<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Andrea Dworkin</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>22320587</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519492577</id>
      <parentid>518168983</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-24T01:32:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Matthew Fennell</username>
        <id>1761615</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Return to New York and contact with the feminist movement */ Cleanup</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="77672">{{pp-move-indef}}
{{good article}}
{{Infobox person
|name          = Andrea Dworkin
|image         = Dworkin on After Dark.JPG
|image_size    =
|alt           =
|caption       = Dworkin appearing on British television discussion programme ''[[After Dark (TV series)|After Dark]]'' in May 1988
|birth_name    =Andrea Rita Dworkin
|birth_date    = {{birth date|mf=yes|1946|9|26|mf=y}}
|birth_place   = [[Camden, New Jersey]], U.S.
|death_date    = {{death date and age|mf=yes|2005|4|9|1946|9|26}}
|death_place   = [[Washington, D.C.]], U.S.
|body_discovered =
|death_cause   = [[Myocarditis]]
|resting_place =
|resting_place_coordinates = &lt;!-- {{coord|LAT|LONG|display=inline,title}} --&gt;
|residence     =
|nationality   = 
|ethnicity     =
|citizenship   =
|other_names   =
|known_for     = [[Radical feminism]], [[Anti-pornography movement|anti-pornography activism]]
|education     = B.A. in literature
|alma_mater    = [[Bennington College]]
|employer      =
|occupation    = Writer
|years_active  = 1966–2005
|home_town     =
|religion      =
|spouse        = Cornelius (Iwan) Dirk de Bruin (1969–1972)&lt;br&gt;[[John Stoltenberg]]
|partner       =
|children      =
|parents       = Harry Dworkin and Sylvia Spiegel
|relations     = Mark Spiegel (brother)
|callsign      =
|awards        =
|signature     =
|signature_alt =
|website       = [http://www.andreadworkin.com/ Portal for Andrea Dworkin's websites]
|footnotes     =
|box_width     = 300px
}}
'''Andrea Rita Dworkin''' (September 26, 1946&amp;nbsp;– April 9, 2005) was an American [[Radical feminism|radical feminist]] and writer best known for her [[Feminist views on pornography#Anti-pornography feminism|criticism of pornography]], which she argued was linked to [[rape]] and other forms of [[violence against women]].

An anti-war activist and anarchist in the late 1960s, Dworkin wrote 10 books on radical feminist theory and practice. During the late 1970s and the 1980s, she gained national fame as a spokeswoman for the feminist [[anti-pornography movement]], and for her writing on pornography and sexuality, particularly in ''[[Pornography: Men Possessing Women]]'' (1979) and ''[[Intercourse (book)|Intercourse]]'' (1987), which remain her two most widely known books.

==Early life and education==
Dworkin was born in [[Camden, New Jersey]], to Harry Dworkin and Sylvia Spiegel. She had one younger brother, Mark. Her father was a schoolteacher and dedicated [[socialist]], whom she credited with inspiring her passion for [[social justice]]. Her relationship with her mother was strained, but Dworkin later wrote about how her mother's belief in legal [[birth control]] and legal [[abortion]], &quot;long before these were respectable beliefs,&quot; inspired her later activism.&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Heartbreak'', p. 23.&lt;/ref&gt;

Though she described her [[Jew]]ish household as being in many ways dominated by the memory of the [[Holocaust]], it nonetheless provided a happy childhood until the age of nine when an unknown man [[child sexual abuse|molested]] her in a movie theater. When Dworkin was 10, her family moved from the city to the suburbs of [[Cherry Hill, New Jersey]] (then known as Delaware Township), which she later wrote she &quot;experienced as being [[kidnapping|kidnapped]] by aliens and taken to a penal colony&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Life and Death'', p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt; In sixth grade, the administration at her new school punished her for refusing to sing &quot;[[Silent Night]]&quot; (as a Jew, she objected to being forced to sing [[Christian]] religious songs at school).&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Heartbreak'', pp. 21–22.&lt;/ref&gt;

Dworkin began writing poetry and fiction in the sixth grade. Throughout high school, she read avidly, with encouragement from her parents. She was particularly influenced by [[Arthur Rimbaud]], [[Charles Baudelaire]], [[Henry Miller]], [[Fyodor Dostoevsky]], [[Che Guevara]], and the [[Beat generation|Beat poets]], especially [[Allen Ginsberg]].&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Life and Death'', pp. 23–24, 28; Dworkin, ''Heartbreak'', pp. 37–40.&lt;/ref&gt;

===College and early activism===
In 1965, while a student at [[Bennington College]], Dworkin was arrested during an anti-[[Vietnam War]] protest at the United States Mission to the [[United Nations]] and sent to the [[New York Women's House of Detention]]. Dworkin testified that the doctors in the House of Detention gave her an [[internal examination]] which was so rough that she bled for days afterwards. She spoke in public and testified before a [[grand jury]] about her experience, and the media coverage of her testimony made national and international news.&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Heartbreak'', pp. 77–81.&lt;/ref&gt; The grand jury declined to make an indictment in the case,&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Heartbreak'', p. 80.&lt;/ref&gt; but Dworkin's testimony contributed to public outrage over the mistreatment of inmates.  The prison was closed seven years later.

Soon after testifying before the grand jury, Dworkin left Bennington to live in [[Greece]] and to pursue her writing.&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Heartbreak'', pp. 80, 83.&lt;/ref&gt; She traveled from [[Paris]] to [[Athens]] on the [[Orient Express]], and went to live and write in [[Crete]].&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Heartbreak'', pp. 83–85, 87.&lt;/ref&gt; While in Crete, she wrote a series of poems titled ''(Vietnam) Variations'', a collection of poems and [[prose poetry|prose poem]]s that she printed on the island in a book called ''Child'', and a novel in a style resembling [[magical realism]] called ''Notes on Burning Boyfriend'' – a reference to the [[pacifist]] [[Norman Morrison]], who had [[Self-immolation|burned himself to death]] in protest of the Vietnam War. She also wrote several poems and dialogues  which she hand-printed after returning to the United States in a book called ''Morning Hair''.&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Heartbreak'', p. 98.&lt;/ref&gt;

After living in Crete, Dworkin returned to Bennington for two years, where she continued to study literature and participated in campaigns against the college's student conduct code, for [[contraception]] on campus, for the legalization of [[abortion]], and against the Vietnam War.&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Heartbreak'', pp. 107–112.&lt;/ref&gt; She graduated with a degree in literature in 1968.

==Life in the Netherlands==
After graduation, she moved to [[Amsterdam]] to interview Dutch [[anarchism|anarchists]] in the [[Provo (movement)|Provo]] countercultural movement.&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Life and Death'', pp. 24–25; Dworkin, ''Heartbreak'', p. 117.&lt;/ref&gt; While there, she became involved with, then married, one of the anarchists she met: Cornelius (Iwan) Dirk de Bruin.&lt;ref&gt;[http://oasis.lib.harvard.edu/oasis/deliver/~sch01210 ''Dworkin, Andrea. Videotape Collection of Andrea Dworkin, 1981–1998 (Inclusive): A Finding Aid'' (Cambridge, Mass.: Arthur and Elizabeth Schlesinger Library on the History of Women in America, Radcliffe Institute for Advanced Study, Harvard Univ. (Vt-136), Feb., 2009)], as accessed Jul. 31, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;. Soon after they were married, she said, de Bruin began to [[domestic violence|abuse her]] severely, punching and kicking her, burning her with cigarettes, beating her on her legs with a wooden beam, and banging her head against the floor until he knocked her unconscious.&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Heartbreak'', p. 119; Dworkin, ''Letters from a War Zone'', pp. 103, 332.&lt;/ref&gt;

After she left de Bruin late in 1971, Dworkin said, her ex-husband attacked, persecuted, and harassed her, beating her and threatening her whenever he found where she was hiding. She found herself desperate for money, often homeless, thousands of miles from her family, later remarking that, &quot;I often lived the life of a fugitive, except that it was the more desperate life of a [[battered woman]] who had run away for the last time, whatever the outcome&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Life and Death'', p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt; For a while, she was a [[prostitution|prostitute]]. [[Ricki Abrams]], a feminist and fellow [[expatriate]], sheltered Dworkin in her home, and helped her find places to stay on houseboats, a communal farm, and deserted buildings.&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Life and Death'', 18–19&lt;/ref&gt; Dworkin tried to work up the money to return to the United States.

Abrams introduced Dworkin to early radical feminist writing from the United States, and Dworkin was especially inspired by [[Kate Millett]]'s ''[[Sexual Politics]]'', [[Shulamith Firestone]]'s ''[[The Dialectic of Sex]]'', and [[Robin Morgan]]'s ''[[Sisterhood is Powerful]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Life and Death'', p. 19; Dworkin, ''Heartbreak'', p. 118.&lt;/ref&gt; She and Abrams began to work together on &quot;early pieces and fragments&quot; of a radical feminist text on the hatred of women in culture and history,&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''[[Woman Hating]]'', Acknowledgment, p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt; including a completed draft of a chapter on the pornographic [[counterculture]] magazine ''Suck'', which was published by a group of fellow expatriates in the Netherlands.&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Life and Death'', p. 21; Dworkin, ''Heartbreak'', p. 122.&lt;/ref&gt;

Dworkin later wrote that she eventually agreed to help smuggle a briefcase of heroin through customs in return for $1,000 and an airplane ticket, thinking that if she was successful she could return home with the ticket and the money, and if caught she would at least escape her ex-husband's abuse by going to prison. The deal for the briefcase fell through, but the man who had promised Dworkin the money gave her the airline ticket anyway, and she returned to the United States in 1972.&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Letters from a War Zone'', pp. 332–333; Dworkin, ''Life and Death'', p. 22.&lt;/ref&gt;

Before she left Amsterdam, Dworkin spoke with Abrams about her experiences in the Netherlands, the emerging feminist movement, and the book they had begun to write together. Dworkin agreed to complete the book — which she eventually titled ''[[Woman Hating]]'' — and publish it when she reached the United States.&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Life and Death'', p. 22.&lt;/ref&gt; In her memoirs, Dworkin relates that during that conversation she vowed to dedicate her life to the feminist movement:

{{quotation|Sitting with Ricki, talking with Ricki, I made a vow to her: that I would use everything I knew, including from prostitution, to make the women's movement stronger and better; that I'd give my life to the movement and for the movement. I promised to be honor-bound to the well-being of women, to do anything necessary for that well-being. I promised to live and to die if need be for women. I made that vow some thirty years ago, and I have not betrayed it yet.|Andrea Dworkin|Heartbreak: The Political Memoir of a Feminist Militant, 122.}}

==Return to New York and contact with the feminist movement==
&lt;!-- When she returned to [[New York City]], Dworkin brought back the &quot;early pieces and fragments&quot; of ''[[Woman Hating]]'', and took odd jobs to support herself while she expanded and finished the book. ''[[Woman Hating]]'' became Dworkin's first published book in 1974. It offered radical feminist analyses of [[fairy tale]]s and literary pornography, which Dworkin argued presented women as passive, dependent, and defined by a [[male sexuality]] that eroticized women's humiliation and submission. It then discussed &quot;gynocidal&quot; expressions of that view of femininity, in the form of European [[witch-hunt]]s and Chinese [[foot binding]]. Dworkin argued that binary [[gender role]]s were a myth, expressed in the stories and enforced by the violence, that could and should be overcome, in favor of an &quot;[[androgynous]] society,&quot; for the sake of women's freedom and human flourishing. --&gt;

In [[New York]], Dworkin worked again as an anti-war organizer, participated in demonstrations for [[lesbian rights]] and against [[apartheid]] in South Africa.&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Heartbreak'', p. 123.&lt;/ref&gt; The feminist poet [[Muriel Rukeyser]] hired her as an assistant (Dworkin later said &quot;I was the worst assistant in the history of the world. But Muriel kept me on because she believed in me as a writer.&quot;)&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Letters from a War Zone'', p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt; Dworkin also joined a feminist [[consciousness raising]] group,&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Heartbreak'', p. 124.&lt;/ref&gt; and soon became involved in radical feminist organizing, focusing on campaigns against violence against women. In addition to her writing and activism, Dworkin gained notoriety as a speaker, mostly for events organized by local feminist groups.&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Heartbreak'', pp. 139–143.&lt;/ref&gt; She became well known for passionate, uncompromising speeches that aroused strong feelings in both supporters and critics, and inspired her audience to action, such as her speech at the first [[Take Back the Night]] march in November 1978, and her 1983 speech at the Midwest Regional Conference of the National Organization for Changing Men (now the [[National Organization for Men Against Sexism]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=A Brief History of NOMAS|url=http://www.nomas.org/history|publisher=National Organization for Men Against Sexism|accessdate=July 5, 2009| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20090603053848/http://nomas.org/history| archivedate= 3 June 2009 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;) entitled &quot;I Want a Twenty-Four Hour Truce During Which There Is No Rape.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Dworkin|chapter=I Want a Twenty-Four Hour Truce During Which There Is No Rape|chapterurl=http://www.nostatusquo.com/ACLU/dworkin/WarZoneChaptIIIE.html|date=Fall 1983|title=Letters from a War Zone|pages=162–171|accessdate=July 5, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Relationship with John Stoltenberg==
In 1974, she met feminist writer and activist [[John Stoltenberg]] when they both walked out on a poetry reading in [[Greenwich Village]] over [[misogyny|misogynist]] material. They became close friends and eventually came to live together.&lt;ref name=Living&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nostatusquo.com/ACLU/dworkin/LivingWithAndrea.html|title=Living with Andrea Dworkin|author=[[John Stoltenberg]]|work=Lambda Book Report|date=May/June 1994|accessdate=July 5, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stoltenberg wrote a series of radical feminist books and articles on [[masculinity]]. Although Dworkin publicly wrote &quot;I love John with my heart and soul&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last=Dworkin| chapter=Andrea Dworkin |chapterurl=http://www.nostatusquo.com/ACLU/dworkin/AutobiographyIII.html |title=Contemporary Authors Autobiography Series, Vol. 21 |year=1994 |publisher=Thomson Gale |location=Farmington Hills, Mich. |isbn=0-8103-4518-8 |accessdate=July 5, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Stoltenberg described Dworkin as &quot;the love of my life&quot;,&lt;ref name=Imagining&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.feminist.com/resources/artspeech/genwom/andreadworkin.html|title=Imagining Life Without Andrea|author=[[John Stoltenberg]]|date=April 30, 2005|publisher=Feminist.com|accessdate=July 5, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; she continued to publicly identify herself as [[lesbian]], and he as [[gay]]. Stoltenberg, recounting the perplexity that their relationship seemed to cause people in the press, summarized the relationship by saying &quot;So I state only the simplest facts publicly: yes, Andrea and I live together and love each other and we are each other's [[life partner]], and yes we are both [[Coming out|out]].&quot;&lt;ref name=Living/&gt;

Dworkin and Stoltenberg were married in 1998; after her death, Stoltenberg said &quot;It's why we never told anybody really that we married, because people get confused about that. They think, Oh, she's yours. And we just did not want that nonsense.&quot;&lt;ref name=Imagining/&gt;

==Critique of pornography==
Andrea Dworkin is most often remembered for her role as a speaker, writer, and activist in the feminist [[anti-pornography movement]].&lt;ref name=WithoutCompromise/&gt;&lt;ref name=NeverHated/&gt;&lt;ref name=GuardianObit/&gt;
&lt;!-- Her critique of pornography began with ''[[Woman Hating]]'', in which she offered a critical analysis of the contemporary pornography, in the novels ''[[Story of O]]'' and ''[[The Image (novel)|L'Image]]'', and in the counterculture pornographic newspaper ''Suck''. Dworkin argued that pornography presented the adult and explicit development of the [[sexual politics]] expressed implicitly for children in [[fairy tale]]s, and that it portrayed women as passive victims, whose identity was expressed in eroticized degradation, humiliation, or outright violence. --&gt;
In February 1976, Dworkin took a leading role in organizing public pickets of ''[[Snuff (film)|Snuff]]'' in [[New York City]] and, during the fall, joined [[Adrienne Rich]], [[Grace Paley]], [[Gloria Steinem]], [[Shere Hite]], [[Lois Gould]], [[Barbara Deming]], [[Karla Jay]], [[Letty Cottin Pogrebin]], [[Robin Morgan]], and [[Susan Brownmiller]] in attempts to form a radical feminist antipornography group.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Susan Brownmiller|authorlink=Susan Brownmiller|title=In Our Time: Memoir of a Revolution|year=1999|publisher=Dial Press|location=New York|isbn=0-385-31486-8|pages=297–299}}&lt;/ref&gt; Members of this group would go on to found [[Women Against Pornography]] in 1979, but by then Dworkin had begun to distance herself from the group over differences in approach.&lt;ref&gt;Brownmiller, ''In Our Time'', pp. 303, 316.&lt;/ref&gt; Dworkin spoke at the first [[Take Back the Night]] march in November 1978, and joined 3,000 women in a march through the [[red-light district]] of [[San Francisco]].&lt;ref&gt;Brownmiller, ''In Our Time'', pp. 391–392.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1979, Dworkin published ''[[Pornography: Men Possessing Women]]'', which analyzes (and extensively cites examples drawn from) contemporary and historical pornography as an industry of woman-hating dehumanization. Dworkin argues that it is implicated in violence against women, both in its production (through the abuse of the women used to star in it), and in the social consequences of its consumption by encouraging men to eroticize the domination, humiliation, and abuse of women.&lt;ref name=WithoutCompromise/&gt;&lt;ref name=NeverHated/&gt;&lt;ref name=GuardianObit/&gt;

==Antipornography civil rights ordinance==
{{main|Antipornography Civil Rights Ordinance}}
In 1980, [[Linda Boreman]] (who had appeared in the pornographic film ''[[Deep Throat (film)|Deep Throat]]'' as &quot;Linda Lovelace&quot;) made public statements that her ex-husband [[Chuck Traynor]] had beaten and raped her, and violently [[coercion|coerced]] her into making that and other pornographic films. Boreman made her charges public for the press corps at a press conference, with Dworkin, feminist lawyer [[Catharine MacKinnon]], and members of [[Women Against Pornography]]. After the press conference, Dworkin, MacKinnon, [[Gloria Steinem]], and Boreman began discussing the possibility of using federal [[civil rights]] law to seek damages from Traynor and the makers of ''Deep Throat''. Boreman was interested, but backed off after Steinem discovered that the [[statute of limitations]] for a possible suit had passed.&lt;ref&gt;Brownmiller, ''In Our Time'', p. 337.&lt;/ref&gt;

Dworkin and MacKinnon, however, continued to discuss civil rights litigation as a possible approach to combating pornography. In the fall of 1983, MacKinnon secured a one-semester appointment for Dworkin at the [[University of Minnesota]], to teach a course in literature for the [[Women's Studies]] program and co-teach (with MacKinnon) an interdepartmental course on pornography, where they hashed out details of a civil rights approach. With encouragement from community activists in south [[Minneapolis]], the Minneapolis city government hired Dworkin and MacKinnon to draft an antipornography civil rights ordinance as an amendment to the Minneapolis city civil rights ordinance. 

The amendment defined pornography as a civil rights violation against women, and allowed women who claimed harm from pornography to [[lawsuit|sue]] the producers and distributors in [[Civil law (common law)|civil court]] for damages. The law was passed twice by the Minneapolis city council but vetoed by Mayor Don Fraser, who considered the wording of the ordinance to be too vague.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Donald Alexander Downs |title=The New Politics of Pornography |publisher=University of Chicago Press |location=Chicago |year=1989 |pages=34–65 |isbn=0-226-16162-5 |chapter=The Minneapolis Ordinance and the Feminist Theory of Pornography and Sexuality |chapterurl=http://books.google.com/books?id=4h4rpVBqtMgC&amp;pg=PA34 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Another version of the ordinance passed in [[Indianapolis, Indiana]] in 1984, but overturned as [[United States Constitution|unconstitutional]] by the [[United States Court of Appeals for the Seventh Circuit|Seventh Circuit Court of Appeals]] in the case ''[[American Booksellers v. Hudnut]]''. Dworkin continued to support the civil rights approach in her writing and activism, and supported anti-pornography feminists who organized later campaigns in [[Cambridge, Massachusetts]] (1985) and [[Bellingham, Washington]] (1988) to pass versions of the ordinance by voter initiative.&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Life and Death'', pp. 90–95.&lt;/ref&gt;

==''Right-Wing Women''==
In 1983, Dworkin published ''Right-Wing Women: The Politics of Domesticated Females'', an examination of what she claimed were women's reasons for collaborating with men for the limitation of women's freedom.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Dworkin |chapter=Abortion |chapterurl=http://www.nostatusquo.com/ACLU/dworkin/RightWingWomenAbortion.html |title=Right Wing Women |year=1983 |accessdate=July 8, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the Preface to the British edition,&lt;ref&gt;Reprinted in Dworkin, ''Letters from a War Zone'', pp. 185–194.&lt;/ref&gt; Dworkin stated that the [[New Right]] in the United States focused especially on preserving male authority in the family, the promotion of [[fundamentalism|fundamentalist]] versions of orthodox religion, combating abortion, and undermining efforts to combat domestic violence,&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Letters from a War Zone'', pp. 192–193.&lt;/ref&gt; but that it also had, for the first time, &quot;succeeded in getting ''women as women'' (women who claim to be acting in the interests of women as a group) to act effectively on behalf of male authority over women, on behalf of a hierarchy in which women are subservient to men, on behalf of women as the rightful property of men, on behalf of religion as an expression of transcendent male supremacy&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Letters from a War Zone'', p. 193.&lt;/ref&gt; Taking this as her problem, Dworkin asked, &quot;Why do right-wing women agitate for their own subordination? How does the [[right-wing|Right]], controlled by men, enlist their participation and loyalty? And why do right-wing women truly hate the feminist struggle for equality?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Letters from a War Zone'', p. 194.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Testimony before Attorney General's Commission on Pornography==
On January 22, 1986, Dworkin testified for half an hour before the [[Attorney General's Commission on Pornography]] (sometimes referred to as the &quot;Meese Commission&quot;) in [[New York City]], and answered questions from commissioners after completing her testimony.&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin's testimony, &quot;Pornography Is a Civil Rights Issue&quot;,  is reprinted in Dworkin, ''Letters from a War Zone'', pp. 276–307.&lt;/ref&gt; Dworkin's testimony against pornography was praised and reprinted in the Commission's [[Meese Report|final report]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.porn-report.com/401-victimization.htm|title=Victimization|work=Attorney General's Commission on Pornography|year=1986|accessdate=July 8, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Dworkin and MacKinnon marked its release by holding a joint press conference.&lt;ref name=&quot;ObsceneDisgustingVileMeeseRpt&quot;&gt;{{cite book|chapterurl=http://cultronix.eserver.org/califia/meese/|chapter=The Obscene, Disgusting, and Vile Meese Commission Report|title=Public Sex: The Culture of Radical Sex|year=1994|publisher=Cleis Press|location=San Francisco|author=[[Patrick Califia|Pat Califia]]|accessdate=July 8, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Meese Commission subsequently successfully demanded that convenience store chains remove from shelves men's magazines such as ''[[Playboy (magazine)|Playboy]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;ObsceneDisgustingVileMeeseRpt&quot; /&gt; (Dworkin wrote that the magazine &quot;in both text and pictures promotes both rape and child sexual abuse&quot;)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amazoncastle.com/feminism/porn.shtml|title=Pornography and Feminism|author=Colleen McEneany|publisher=FeministUtopia|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20060720195949/http://www.amazoncastle.com/feminism/porn.shtml|archivedate=July 20, 2006|accessdate=July 8, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''[[Penthouse (magazine)|Penthouse]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://home.earthlink.net/~durangodave/html/writing/Censorship.htm|title=Politics and Pornography: A Comparison of the Findings of the President's Commission and the Meese Commission and the Resulting Response|author=David M. Edwards|accessdate=July 9, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The demands spread nationally and intimidated some retailers into withdrawing photography magazines, among others.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mediacoalition.org/reports/wildmon.html|title=The Rev. Donald E. Wildmon's Crusade for Censorship, 1977–1992|author=Christopher M. Finan and Anne F. Castro|publisher=Media Coalition|accessdate=July 9, 2009|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20090506105725/http://www.mediacoalition.org/reports/wildmon.html &lt;!--Added by H3llBot--&gt;|archivedate=May 6, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Meese Commission's campaign was eventually quashed with a [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First Amendment]] admonishment against prior restraint by the D.C. Federal Court in Meese v. Playboy (639 F.Supp. 581).

In her testimony and replies to questions from the commissioners, Dworkin denounced the use of criminal obscenity prosecutions against pornographers, stating, &quot;We are against obscenity laws. We do not want them. I want you to understand why, whether you end up agreeing or not.&quot;&lt;ref name=WarZone285&gt;Dworkin, ''Letters from a War Zone'', p. 285.&lt;/ref&gt; She argued that obscenity laws were largely ineffectual,&lt;ref name=WarZone285/&gt; that when they were effectual they only suppressed pornography from public view while allowing it to flourish out of sight,&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Letters from a War Zone'', pp. 285–286.&lt;/ref&gt; and that they suppressed the wrong material, or the right material for the wrong reasons, arguing that &quot;Obscenity laws are also woman-hating in their very construction. Their basic presumption is that it's women's bodies that are dirty.&quot;&lt;ref name=WarZone286&gt;Dworkin, ''Letters from a War Zone'', p. 286.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Instead she offered five recommendations for the Commission, recommending (1) that &quot;the Justice Department instruct law-enforcement agencies to keep records of the use of pornography in violent crimes&quot;,&lt;ref name=WarZone286/&gt; (2) a ban on the possession and distribution of pornography in prisons,&lt;ref name=WarZone287&gt;Dworkin, ''Letters from a War Zone'', p. 287.&lt;/ref&gt; (3) that prosecutors &quot;enforce laws against pimping and pandering against pornographers&quot;,&lt;ref name=WarZone287/&gt; (4) that the administration &quot;make it a Justice Department priority to enforce RICO (the [[Racketeer Influenced and Corrupt Organizations Act]]) against the pornography industry&quot;,&lt;ref name=WarZone287/&gt; and (5) that Congress adopt federal anti-pornography civil rights legislation which would provide for civil damages for harm inflicted on women. She suggested that the Commission consider &quot;creating a criminal conspiracy provision under the civil rights law, such that conspiring to deprive a person of their civil rights by coercing them into pornography is a crime, and that conspiring to traffic in pornography is conspiring to deprive women of our civil rights&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Letters from a War Zone'', p. 288.&lt;/ref&gt; Dworkin compared her proposal to the [[Southern Poverty Law Center]]'s use of civil rights litigation against the [[Ku Klux Klan]].&lt;ref name=WarZone285/&gt;

Dworkin also submitted into evidence a copy of Boreman's book ''Ordeal'', as an example of the abuses that she hoped to remedy, saying &quot;The only thing atypical about Linda is that she has had the courage to make a public fight against what has happened to her. And whatever you come up with, it has to help her or it's not going to help anyone.&quot; Boreman had testified in person before the Commission, but the Commissioners had not yet seen her book.&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Letters from a War Zone'', p. 289.&lt;/ref&gt;

==''Intercourse''==
{{main|Intercourse (book)}}

In 1987, Dworkin published ''[[Intercourse (book)|Intercourse]]'', in which she extended her analysis from pornography to [[sexual intercourse]] itself, and argued that the sort of sexual subordination depicted in pornography was central to men's and women's experiences of heterosexual intercourse in a male supremacist society. In the book, she argues that all heterosexual sex in our patriarchal society is coercive and degrading to women, and sexual penetration may by its very nature doom women to inferiority and submission, and &quot;may be immune to reform.&quot;&lt;ref name=UCCB&gt;{{cite book |chapterurl=http://faculty.uccb.ns.ca/sstewart/sexlove/dworkin.htm |chapter=Occupation/Collaboration |title=[[Intercourse (book)|Intercourse]] |author=Dworkin |accessdate=July 8, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Citing from both pornography and literature—including ''[[The Kreutzer Sonata]]'', ''[[Madame Bovary]]'', and ''[[Dracula]]''—Dworkin argued that depictions of intercourse in mainstream art and culture consistently emphasized heterosexual intercourse as the only kind of &quot;real&quot; sex, portrayed intercourse in violent or invasive terms, portrayed the violence or invasiveness as central to its eroticism, and often united it with male contempt for, revulsion towards, or even murder of, the &quot;carnal&quot; woman. She argued that this kind of depiction enforced a male-centric and coercive view of sexuality, and that, when the cultural attitudes combine with the material conditions of women's lives in a [[sexist]] society, the experience of heterosexual intercourse itself becomes a central part of men's subordination of women, experienced as a form of &quot;occupation&quot; that is nevertheless expected to be pleasurable for women and to define their very status ''as women''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |chapterurl=http://www.nostatusquo.com/ACLU/dworkin/IntercourseI.html |chapter=Occupation/Collaboration |title=[[Intercourse (book)|Intercourse]] |author=Dworkin |accessdate=July 8, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Such descriptions are often cited by Dworkin's critics, interpreting the book as claiming &quot;all&quot; heterosexual intercourse is rape, or more generally that the anatomical mechanics of sexual intercourse make it intrinsically harmful to women's equality. For instance, [[Cathy Young]]&lt;ref name=YoungObit&gt;{{cite web|url=http://reason.com/archives/2005/04/19/womans-hating|title= Woman's Hating: The Misdirected Passion of Andrea Dworkin|author=[[Cathy Young]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; says that statements such as, &quot;Intercourse is the pure, sterile, formal expression of men's contempt for women,&quot;&lt;ref name=UCCB/&gt; are reasonably summarized as &quot;All sex is rape.&quot;

&lt;!-- A couple quick citations would be helpful here; longer stuff can go in the article on the book itself. --&gt;Dworkin rejected that interpretation of her argument,&lt;ref name=LieDetector&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nostatusquo.com/ACLU/dworkin/LieDetect.html|title=The Andrea Dworkin Lie Detector|author=[[Nikki Craft]]|publisher=Andrea Dworkin Online Library|accessdate=July 8, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; stating in a later interview that &quot;I think both intercourse and sexual pleasure can and will survive equality&quot;&lt;ref name=Moorcock&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nostatusquo.com/ACLU/dworkin/MoorcockInterview.html|title=Fighting Talk|author=[[Michael Moorcock]]|work=[[New Statesman|New Statesman and Society]]|date=April 21, 1995|accessdate=July 8, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and suggesting that the misunderstanding came about because of the very sexual ideology she was criticizing: &quot;Since the paradigm for sex has been one of conquest, possession, and violation, I think many men believe they need an unfair advantage, which at its extreme would be called rape. I do not think they need it.&quot;&lt;ref name=Moorcock/&gt; &lt;!-- Is there a good source to cite here for critics' claims that Dworkin's later statements amounted to &quot;backpedaling&quot; or similar? If so, let's have it. --&gt;

==''Butler'' decision in Canada==
In 1992, the [[Supreme Court of Canada]] made a ruling in ''[[R. v. Butler]]'' which incorporated some elements of Dworkin and MacKinnon's legal work on pornography into the existing Canadian obscenity law. In ''Butler'' the Court held that Canadian obscenity law violated Canadian citizens' rights to free speech under the [[Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms]] if enforced on grounds of morality or community standards of decency; but that obscenity law could be enforced constitutionally against some pornography on the basis of the Charter's guarantees of sex equality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Brenda Cossman|title=Bad Attitude/s on Trial: Pornography, Feminism, and the ''Butler'' Decision |publisher=University of Toronto Press|location=Toronto|year=1997|page=107|isbn=0-8020-7643-2|chapter=Feminist Fashion or Morality in Drag? The Sexual Subtext of the ''Butler'' Decision|chapterurl=http://books.google.com/books?id=KfTtZl-hrBsC&amp;pg=PA107}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Court's decision cited extensively from briefs prepared by the [[Women's Legal Education and Action Fund]] (LEAF), with the support and participation of Catharine MacKinnon.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Christopher Jon Nowlin|title=Judging Obscenity: A Critical History of Expert Evidence |publisher=McGill-Queen's University Press|location=Quebec|year=2003|page=126|isbn=0-7735-2538-6|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=spUwNzRGwLgC&amp;pg=PA126}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Andrea Dworkin opposed LEAF's position, arguing that feminists should not support or attempt to reform criminal obscenity law.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Joan Mason-Grant|title=Pornography Embodied: From Speech to Sexual Practice|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield|location=Lanham, Md.|year=2004|page=176, n. 30|isbn=0-7425-1223-1|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ZlGmGa8LMmgC&amp;pg=PA176}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1993, copies of Dworkin's book ''Pornography'' were held for inspection by Canada Customs agents,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wired.com/wired/archive/3.03/canada.html|title=Canada's Thought Police|author=Zachary Margulis|work=[[Wired (magazine)|Wired]]|year=1995|month=March|accessdate=July 8, 2009| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20090605091158/http://www.wired.com/wired/archive/3.03/canada.html| archivedate= 5 June 2009 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; fostering an urban legend that Dworkin's own books had been banned from Canada under a law that she herself had promoted. However, the ''Butler'' decision did not adopt Dworkin and MacKinnon's ordinance; Dworkin did not support the decision; and her books (which were released shortly after they were inspected) were held temporarily as part of a standard procedural measure, unrelated to the ''Butler'' decision.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nostatusquo.com/ACLU/dworkin/OrdinanceCanada.html|title=Statement by Catharine A. MacKinnon and Andrea Dworkin Regarding Canadian Customs and Legal Approaches to Pornography|author=Catharine A. MacKinnon and Andrea Dworkin|date=August 26, 1994|accessdate=July 8, 2009| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20090626123757/http://www.nostatusquo.com/ACLU/dworkin/OrdinanceCanada.html| archivedate= 26 June 2009 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Fiction==
Dworkin published three fictional works after achieving notability as a feminist author and activist. She published a collection of short stories, ''The New Woman's Broken Heart'' in 1980. Her first published novel, ''Ice and Fire'', was published in the United Kingdom in 1986. It is a [[first-person narrative]], rife with violence and abuse; [[Susie Bright]] has claimed that it amounts to a modern feminist rewriting of one of the [[Marquis de Sade]]'s most famous works, ''[[L'Histoire de Juliette|Juliette]]''.&lt;ref name=BrightObit&gt;{{cite web|url=http://susiebright.blogs.com/susie_brights_journal_/2005/04/andrea_dworkin_.html|title=Andrea Dworkin Has Died|author=[[Susie Bright]]|date=April 11, 2005|accessdate=July 11, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, Dworkin aimed to depict men's harm to women as normalized political harm, not as eccentric eroticism. Dworkin's second novel, ''Mercy'', was published in the United Kingdom in 1990.

Dworkin's short fiction and novels often incorporated elements from her life and themes from her nonfiction writing, sometimes related by a first-person narrator. Critics have sometimes quoted passages spoken by characters in ''Ice and Fire'' as representations of Dworkin's own views.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Gladden Schrock|url=http://www.fatherhoodcoalition.org/cpf/newreadings/2001/feminist_hate_speech.htm|title=Feminist Hate-Speech|publisher=The Fatherhood Coalition|accessdate=July 11, 2009| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20090527153653/http://www.fatherhoodcoalition.org/cpf/newreadings/2001/feminist_hate_speech.htm| archivedate= 27 May 2009 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mensnewsdaily.com/archive/r/ross-eric/2005/ross072205.htm|title=Mind-Programming of the Masses|author=Eric Ross|work=MacDworkinism and VAWA: The Fraud of the Millennia|accessdate=July 11, 2009 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080508232955/http://www.mensnewsdaily.com/archive/r/ross-eric/2005/ross072205.htm |archivedate = May 8, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; cf.&lt;ref name=LieDetector/&gt; Dworkin, however, wrote &quot;My fiction is not autobiography. I am not an exhibitionist. I do not show myself. I am not asking for forgiveness. I do not want to confess. But I have used everything I know – my life – to show what I believe must be shown so that it can be faced. The imperative at the heart of my writing – what must be done – comes directly from my life. But I do not show my life directly, in full view; nor even look at it while others watch.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Life and Death'', p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt;

==''Life and Death''==
In 1997, Dworkin published a collection of her speeches and articles from the 1990s in ''Life and Death: Unapologetic Writings on the Continuing War on Women'', including a long autobiographical essay on her life as a writer, and articles on violence against women, pornography, prostitution, [[Nicole Brown Simpson]], the use of rape during the [[war in Bosnia and Herzegovina]], the [[École Polytechnique massacre|Montreal massacre]], [[Israel]], and the gender politics of the [[United States Holocaust Memorial Museum]].&lt;ref name=TimesObit&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/comment/obituaries/article380289.ece|title=Obituary|work=[[The Times]]|date=April 13, 2005|accessdate=July 18, 2009|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Reviewing ''Life and Death'' in ''[[The New Republic]]'', philosopher [[Martha Nussbaum]] criticizes voices in contemporary feminism for denouncing [[Catharine MacKinnon]] and Dworkin as &quot;man-haters,&quot; and argues that [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First Amendment]] critiques of Dworkin's civil ordinance proposal against pornography &quot;are not saying anything intellectually respectable,&quot; for the First Amendment &quot;has never covered all speech: bribery, threats, extortionate offers, misleading advertising, perjury, and unlicensed medical advice are all unprotected.&quot;  Nussbaum adds that Dworkin has focused attention on the proper moral target by making harm associated with subordination, not obscenity, civilly actionable.  

Nevertheless, Nussbaum opposes the adoption of Dworkin's pornography ordinance because it (1) fails to distinguish between moral and legal violations, (2) fails to demonstrate a causal relationship between pornography and specific harm, (3) holds author of printed images or words responsible for others' behavior, (4) grants censorial power to the judiciary (which may be directed against feminist scholarship), and (5) erases the contextual considerations within which sex takes place.  More broadly, Nussbaum faults for Dworkin for (1) occluding economic injustice through an &quot;obsessive focus on sexual subordination,&quot; (2) reproducing [[objectification]] in reducing her interlocutors to their abuse, and (3) refusing reconciliation in favor of &quot;violent extralegal resistance against male violence.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Nussbaum, Martha C. &quot;Rage and Reason.&quot; ''The New Republic.'' August 11, 1997, pp. 36–42.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Later life==
In the same year, the ''[[New York Times Book Review]]'' published a lengthy letter of hers in which she describes the origins of her deeply felt hatred of prostitution and pornography (&quot;mass-produced, technologized prostitution&quot;) as her history of being violently inspected by prison doctors, battered by her first husband and numerous other men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/books/97/06/15/lifetimes/25885.html|title=Pornography and the New Puritans|author=Dworkin|work=[[The New York Times]]|date=May 3, 1992|accessdate=July 11, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Dworkin was a strong opponent of President [[Bill Clinton]] during the [[Lewinsky scandal]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jamestaranto.com/hypo.htm|title=Who's a Hypocrite—and Who Cares?|author=James Taranto|work=[[The Wall Street Journal]]|date=August 4, 1998|accessdate=March 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; She also expressed support for [[Paula Jones]] and [[Juanita Broaddrick]].&lt;ref&gt;Candice E. Jackson. ''[[Their Lives: The Women Targeted by the Clinton Machine]]''. Torrance, Calif.: World Ahead Publishing. p. 240.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2000, she published ''[[Scapegoat: The Jews, Israel, and Women's Liberation]]'', in which she compared the oppression of women to the persecution of Jews,&lt;ref name=LieDetector/&gt; discussed the sexual politics of Jewish identity and [[anti-Semitism]], and called for the establishment of a women's homeland as a response to the oppression of women.&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, Andrea, ''Scapegoat: The Jews, Israel, and Women's Liberation'' (N.Y.: Free Press, 2000 (ISBN 0-684-83612-2)), pp. 246, 245–246, 336, &amp; 248.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/books/2000/may/13/politics1 ''Take No Prisoners'', in ''The Guardian'', May 13, 2000], as accessed Sep. 6, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://psreview.org/content/view/38/99/ Ouma, Veronica A., ''Dworkin's Scapegoating'', in ''Palestine Solidarity Review'' (''PSR''), Fall 2005], as accessed Oct. 21, 2010 (citing, in part, in ''Scapegoat'', ''id.'', pp. 336 &amp; 337).&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2000, Dworkin published controversial articles in the ''New Statesman''&lt;ref name=Drugged&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newstatesman.com/200006050009|title=The Day I Was Drugged and Raped|author=Dworkin|date=June 5, 2000|work=[[New Statesman]]|accessdate=July 11, 2009| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20090620062055/http://www.newstatesman.com/200006050009| archivedate= 20 June 2009 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in the ''Guardian'',&lt;ref name=TookMyBody&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/books/2000/jun/02/society|title='They took my body from me and used it'|author=Dworkin|work=[[The Guardian]]|date=June 2, 2000|accessdate=July 11, 2009|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; stating that one or more men had raped her in her hotel room in [[Paris]] the previous year, putting [[gamma-Hydroxybutyric acid|GHB]] in her drink to disable her. Her articles ignited public controversy&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ifeminists.net/introduction/editorials/2005/0427droberts.html|title=A Post-Mortem Analysis of Andrea Dworkin|author=David A. Roberts|date=April 27, 2005|publisher=ifeminist.com|accessdate=July 11, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; when writers such as [[Catherine Bennett (journalist)|Catherine Bennett]]&lt;ref name=Doubts&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/books/2000/jun/08/society|title=Doubts about Dworkin|author=Catherine Bennett|work=The Guardian|date=June 8, 2000|accessdate=July 11, 2009|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Julia Gracen&lt;ref name=gracen2&gt;{{cite web|author=Julia Gracen|publisher=[[Salon.com]]|date=September 20, 2000|url=http://archive.salon.com/books/feature/2000/09/20/dworkin/index.html|title=Andrea Dworkin in Agony|accessdate=July 11, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; published doubts about her account, polarizing opinion between skeptics and supporters such as [[Catharine MacKinnon]], [[Katharine Viner]],&lt;ref name=NeverHated&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/books/2005/apr/12/gender.highereducation|title='She never hated men'|author=Katharine Viner|work=The Guardian|date=April 12, 2005|accessdate=July 11, 2009|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Gloria Steinem]]. Her reference to the incident was later described by [[Charlotte Raven]] as a &quot;widely disbelieved claim,&quot; better seen as &quot;a kind of artistic housekeeping.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newstatesman.com/200606190055|title=Body of Evidence|work=New Statesman|date=June 19, 2006|author=[[Charlotte Raven]]|accessdate=July 11, 2009| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20090604225001/http://www.newstatesman.com/200606190055| archivedate= 4 June 2009 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; Emotionally fragile and in failing health, Dworkin mostly withdrew from public life for two years following the articles.&lt;ref name=Living/&gt;&lt;ref name=WithoutCompromise&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/books/2004/sep/30/gender.world|title=A life without compromise|date=September 30, 2004|author=Julie Bindel|work=The Guardian|accessdate=July 11, 2009|location=London| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20090529002022/http://www.guardian.co.uk/books/2004/sep/30/gender.world| archivedate= 29 May 2009 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Drugged/&gt;&lt;ref name=TookMyBody/&gt;&lt;ref name=Doubts/&gt;&lt;ref name=gracen2/&gt;&lt;ref name=Trouble&gt;{{cite news|author=[[Louise Armstrong]]|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2001/jun/25/gender.uk1|title=The Trouble with Andrea|work=The Guardian|date=July 25, 2001|accessdate=July 11, 2009|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Patrick Califia|Pat Califia]], ed. ''Forbidden Passages: Writings Banned in Canada.'' Pittsburgh: Cleis Press, 1995.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Adam Parfrey. &quot;The Devil and Andrea Dworkin,&quot; in ''Cult Rapture''. Portland, OR: Feral House Books,  1995. pp. 53–62.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2002, Dworkin published her autobiography, ''Heartbreak: The Political Memoir of a Feminist Militant''. She soon began to speak and write again, and in interview with [[Julie Bindel]] in 2004 said, &quot;I thought I was finished, but I feel a new vitality. I want to continue to help women.&quot;&lt;ref name=WithoutCompromise/&gt; She published three more articles in the ''Guardian'' and began work on a new book, ''Writing America: How Novelists Invented and Gendered a Nation'', on the role of novelists such as [[Ernest Hemingway]] and [[William Faulkner]] in the development of American political and cultural identity, which was left unfinished when she died.&lt;ref name=TimesObit/&gt;

==Illness and death==
During her final years, Dworkin suffered fragile health, and she revealed in her last column for the ''Guardian'' that she had been weakened and nearly crippled for the past several years by severe [[osteoarthritis]] in the knees.&lt;ref name=ThroughPain&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/books/2005/apr/23/features.weekend|title=Through the pain barrier|accessdate=July 11, 2009|author=Dworkin|date=April 23, 2005|work=[[The Guardian]]|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly after returning from Paris in 1999, she had been hospitalized with a high fever and [[blood clot]]s in her legs. A few months after being released from the hospital, she became increasingly unable to bend her knees, and underwent surgery to replace her knees with [[titanium]] and plastic [[prosthetic]]s. She wrote, &quot;The doctor who knows me best says that osteoarthritis begins long before it cripples—in my case, possibly from homelessness, or sexual abuse, or beatings on my legs, or my weight. John, my partner, blames ''Scapegoat'', a study of Jewish identity and women's liberation that took me nine years to write; it is, he says, the book that stole my health. I blame the drug-rape that I experienced in 1999 in Paris.&quot;&lt;ref name=ThroughPain/&gt;

When a newspaper interviewer asked her how she would like to be remembered, she said &quot;In a museum, when male supremacy is dead. I'd like my work to be an anthropological artifact from an extinct, primitive society.&quot;&lt;ref name=GuardianObit&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/news/2005/apr/12/guardianobituaries.gender|title=Obituary|author=Julie Bindel|work=[[The Guardian]]|date=April 12, 2005|accessdate=July 12, 2009|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; She died in her sleep on the morning of April 9, 2005, at her home in [[Washington, D.C.]]&lt;ref name=PrisonerofSex&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nymag.com/nymetro/news/people/features/11907/|title=The Prisoner of Sex|author=[[Ariel Levy]]|work=[[New York (magazine)|New York]]|date=May 29, 2005|accessdate=July 12, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The cause of death was later determined to be acute [[myocarditis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.andreadworkin.net/memorial/stoltinterview.html|title=First Year: An Interview with John Stoltenberg|date=March 11, 2006|author=Beth Ribet|accessdate=July 12, 2009| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20090615050423/http://www.andreadworkin.net/memorial/stoltinterview.html| archivedate= 15 June 2009 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; She was 58 years old.

==Legacy and controversy==
Dworkin authored ten books of radical feminist theory and numerous speeches and articles, each designed to assert the presence of and denounce institutionalized and normalized harm against women. She became one of the most influential writers and spokeswomen of American [[radical feminism]] during the late 1970s and the 1980s.&lt;ref name=NeverHated/&gt;&lt;ref name=Trouble/&gt; She characterized pornography as an industry of damaging objectification and abuse, not merely a [[fantasy (psychology)|fantasy]] realm. She discussed prostitution as a system of exploitation, and intercourse as a key site of subordination in [[patriarchy]]. Her analysis and writing influenced and inspired the work of contemporary feminists, such as [[Catharine MacKinnon]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2006/apr/12/gender.politicsphilosophyandsociety|title=Are women human?|author=Stuart Jeffries|date=April 12, 2006|work=The Guardian|accessdate=July 18, 2009|location=London| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20090826173650/http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2006/apr/12/gender.politicsphilosophyandsociety| archivedate= 26 August 2009 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Gloria Steinem]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/the-new-eve-these-are-some-common-perceptions-about-andrea-dworkin-that-she-hates-men-that-she-hates-sex-and-has-no-real-understanding-of-either-wrong-on-three-counts-her-crusade-against-pornography-and-the-brutalisation-of-women-derives-much-of-its-emotional-power-from-a-fund-of-bitter-personal-experience-1561920.html|title=The New Eve|author=Zoe Heller|date=December 6, 1992|work=[[The Independent]]|accessdate=July 18, 2009|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[John Stoltenberg]],&lt;ref name=PrisonerofSex/&gt; [[Nikki Craft]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nikkicraft.com/|title=The Nikki Wiki: All About Nikki Craft|author=Nikki Craft|accessdate=July 18, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Susan Cole (feminist)|Susan Cole]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Sex, lies and ideologies|author=Susan G. Cole|date=May 12–19, 2005|work=[[Now (magazine)|NOW]]|accessdate=July 18, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Amy Elman]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cpsa-acsp.ca/papers-2009/Waltman.pdf|title=The Civil Rights and Equality Deficit: Legal Challenges to Pornography and Sex Inequality in Canada, Sweden, and the U.S.|author=Max Waltman|year=2009|month=May|publisher=[[Canadian Political Science Association]]|accessdate=July 18, 2009|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Dworkin's uncompromising positions and forceful style of writing and speaking, described by Robert Campbell as &quot;apocalyptic,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hnn.us/blogs/entries/4351.html|title=Radical Feminism: Some Thoughts on Long’s Defense|author=Robert L. Campbell|publisher=[[History News Network]]|date=March 29, 2004|accessdate=July 12, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; earned her frequent comparisons to other speakers such as [[Malcolm X]] (by [[Robin Morgan]],&lt;ref name=PrisonerofSex/&gt; [[Susie Bright]],&lt;ref name=BrightObit/&gt; and others). [[Gloria Steinem]] repeatedly compared her style to that of the [[Old Testament]] prophets;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2005/apr/12/obituaries.gender|title=Andrea Dworkin, embattled feminist, dies at 58|author=Mark Honigsbaum|work=[[The Guardian]]|date=April 12, 2005|accessdate=July 12, 2009|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.democracynow.org/2005/6/23/gloria_steinem_remembers_feminist_writer_and|title=Gloria Steinem Remembers Feminist Writer and Activist Andrea Dworkin|work=[[Democracy Now!]]|date=March 29, 2004|accessdate=July 12, 2009| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20090715164617/http://www.democracynow.org/2005/6/23/gloria_steinem_remembers_feminist_writer_and| archivedate= 15 July 2009 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Susan Brownmiller]] recalls her [[Take Back the Night]] speech in 1978:

{{quotation|Saturday evening culminated in a candlelit &quot;Take Back the Night&quot; march (the first of its kind) through the porn district, kicked off by an exhortation by Andrea Dworkin. I'd seen Andrea in my living room, but this was the first time I'd seen Andrea in action. On the spot I dubbed her Rolling Thunder. Perspiring in her trademark denim coveralls, she employed the rhetorical cadences that would make her both a cult idol and an object of ridicule a few years later. Dworkin's dramatized martyrdom and revival-tent theatrics never sat well with me, but I retained my respect for her courage long after I absented myself from the pornography wars. Her call to action accomplished, three thousand demonstrators took to the streets ...|Susan Brownmiller|''In Our Time: Memoir of a Revolution'', 302–303}}

Many of Dworkin's early speeches are reprinted in her second book, ''Our Blood'' (1976). Later selections of speeches were reprinted ten and twenty years later, in  ''Letters from a War Zone'' (1988) and ''Life and Death'' (1997).&lt;ref name=TimesObit/&gt;

She maintained some political communication with the [[Right-wing politics|political right wing]]. She authored the book ''[[Andrea Dworkin#Right-Wing Women|Right-Wing Women]]'', reviewed as premised on agreement between feminists and right-wing women on the existence of domination by men in sex and class and disagreement on strategy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.ebscohost.com/ehost/pdfviewer/pdfviewer?vid=5&amp;hid=105&amp;sid=6b125cef-4fd9-4b03-af76-1751a8dbe32b%40sessionmgr114 Apparently untitled review, by Sallie L. Foster, in ''Library Journal'', vol. 108, issue 1 (01/01/83) (ISSN 03630277), p. 59, [§&amp;#93; ''Social Science'' (book review), in ''MasterFile Premier'' (EbscoHost) (database) (PDF Full Text)], as accessed May 21, 2010, reviewing ''Right-Wing Women: The Politics of Domesticated Females'', by Andrea Dworkin, Jan. 1983 (ISBN 0-698-11171-0 or ISBN 0-399-50671-3 (pap.)) ([http://web.ebscohost.com/ehost/detail?vid=4&amp;hid=105&amp;sid=6b125cef-4fd9-4b03-af76-1751a8dbe32b%40sessionmgr114&amp;bdata=JnNpdGU9ZWhvc3QtbGl2ZQ%3d%3d#db=f5h&amp;AN=7544468#db=f5h&amp;AN=7544468#db=f5h&amp;AN=7544468 alternate link], as accessed the same day).&lt;/ref&gt; She [[Andrea Dworkin#Testimony before Attorney General's Commission on Pornography|testified at a Meese Commission hearing on pornography]], while [[United States Attorney General|Attorney General]] [[Edwin Meese]] was serving [[Social conservatism|socially]] [[Right-wing politics#Social stratification and social order|conservative]] [[President of the United States|President]] [[Ronald Reagan|Reagan]]. She had a political discourse with ''[[National Review]]'' writer [[David Frum]] and their spouses arranged by [[Christopher Hitchens]];.&lt;ref&gt;[http://frum.nationalreview.com/post/?q=YjA2MGNlZDc1NmNmYzY2NGQ0NjdkMGIzMWMwZDc1ZjM= ''Andrea Dworkin RIP'', in ''David Frum's Diary'', in ''National Review Online'', § ''NRO Blog Row'', Apr. 12, 2005], as accessed May 9, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E0D6113EF934A25757C0A9639C8B63 ''The Nation: Seeing Eye to Eye; A Radical Feminist Who Could Dine With (Not On) Conservatives'', in ''N.Y. Times'', § ''Week In Review'', Apr. 17, 2005], as accessed May 9, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

Her attitude and language often sharply polarized debate, and made Dworkin herself a figure of intense controversy. After her death, the conservative&lt;ref&gt;Sullivan, Andrew, ''The Conservative Soul: How We Lost It, How to Get It Back'' (HarperCollins (ISBN 0-06-018877-4)).&lt;/ref&gt; gay writer [[Andrew Sullivan]] claimed that &quot;Many on the social right liked Andrea Dworkin. Like Dworkin, their essential impulse when they see human beings living freely is to try and control or stop them — for their own good. Like Dworkin, they are horrified by male sexuality, and see men as such as a problem to be tamed. Like Dworkin, they believe in the power of the state to censor and coerce sexual freedoms. Like Dworkin, they view the enormous new freedom that women and gay people have acquired since the 1960s as a terrible development for human culture.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sullivanarchives.theatlantic.com/index.php.dish_inc-archives.2005_04_01_dish_archive.html#111384129072050618|author=[[Andrew Sullivan]]|title=Daily Dish|work=[[The Atlantic]]|date=April 18, 2005|accessdate=July 5, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Libertarianism|Libertarian]]/conservative&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cathyyoung.net/|title=Welcome to the website of writer and journalist Cathy Young|author=[[Cathy Young]]|accessdate=July 12, 2009| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20090611073525/http://www.cathyyoung.net/| archivedate= 11 June 2009 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; journalist [[Cathy Young]] complained of a &quot;whitewash&quot; in feminist obituaries for Dworkin, argued that Dworkin's positions were manifestly [[misandry|misandrist]], stated that Dworkin was in fact [[insane]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cathyyoung.blogspot.com/2005/11/anti-feminist-moi.html|title=Anti-feminist? ''Moi''?|author=Cathy Young|date=November 24, 2005|accessdate=July 12, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.reason.com/blog/show/109179.html|title=The Dworkin Whitewash|author=Cathy Young|date=April 17, 2005|accessdate=July 12, 2009| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20090715155217/http://reason.com/blog/show/109179.html| archivedate= 15 July 2009 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; criticized what she called Dworkin's &quot;destructive legacy&quot;, and described Dworkin as a &quot;sad ghost&quot; that feminism needs to exorcise.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Cathy Young|title=The Misdirected Passion of Andrea Dworkin|work=[[The Boston Globe]]|url=http://www.boston.com/news/globe/editorial_opinion/oped/articles/2005/04/18/the_misdirected_passion_of_andrea_dworkin/|date=April 18, 2005|accessdate=July 12, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other feminists, however, published sympathetic or celebratory memorials online and in print.&lt;ref name=Afraid&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/16/opinion/16mackinnon.html|title=Who Was Afraid of Andrea Dworkin?|last=MacKinnon|first=Catharine A.|authorlink=Catharine MacKinnon|date=April 16, 2005|work=[[The New York Times]]|accessdate=July 12, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.msmusings.net/archives/2005/04/andrea_dworkin.html|title=Andrea Dworkin Dies|work=[[Ms. (magazine)|Ms.]]|date=April 11, 2005|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20061225074237/http://www.msmusings.net/archives/2005/04/andrea_dworkin.html|archivedate=December 25, 2006|accessdate=July 12, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Catharine MacKinnon]], Dworkin's longtime friend and collaborator, published a column in the ''[[New York Times]]'', celebrating what she described as Dworkin's &quot;incandescent literary and political career,&quot; suggested that Dworkin deserved a nomination for the [[Nobel Prize in Literature]], and complained that &quot;Lies about her views on sexuality (that she believed intercourse was rape) and her political alliances (that she was in bed with the right) were published and republished without attempts at verification, corrective letters almost always refused. Where the physical appearance of male writers is regarded as irrelevant or cherished as a charming eccentricity, Andrea's was reviled and mocked and turned into pornography. When she sued for [[libel]], courts trivialized the pornographic lies as fantasy and dignified them as [[satire]].&quot;&lt;ref name=Afraid/&gt;

Dworkin's reports of violence suffered at the hands of men sometimes aroused skepticism, the most famous example being the public controversy over her allegations of being drugged and raped in Paris. In 1989, Dworkin wrote an article about her life as a battered wife in the Netherlands, &quot;What Battery Really Is,&quot; in response to fellow radical feminist [[Susan Brownmiller]], who had argued that [[Hedda Nussbaum]], a battered woman, should have been indicted for her failure to stop [[Joel Steinberg]] from murdering their adoptive daughter. ''[[Newsweek]]'' initially accepted &quot;What Battery Really Is&quot; for publication, but then declined to publish the account at the request of their attorney, according to Dworkin, arguing that she needed either to publish anonymously &quot;to protect the identity of the batterer&quot; and remove references to specific injuries, or to provide &quot;medical records, police records, a written statement from a doctor who had seen the injuries.&quot; Instead, Dworkin submitted the article to the ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'', which published it on March 12, 1989.&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Letters from a War Zone'', p. 330.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some critics, such as [[Larry Flynt]]'s magazine ''[[Hustler]]''&lt;ref name=Flynt/&gt; and Gene Healy,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=[[Gene Healy]]|title=Andrea Dworkin: I Just Don't Get It|url=http://criterion.uchicago.edu/issues/ii6/healy.html |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20061208203708/http://criterion.uchicago.edu/issues/ii6/healy.html|work=Criterion |date=May/June 1998|archivedate=December 8, 2006|accessdate=July 18, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; allege that Dworkin endorsed [[incest]]. In the closing chapter of ''[[Woman Hating]]'' (1974), Dworkin wrote that &quot;The parent-child relationship is primarily erotic because all human relationships are primarily erotic,&quot; and that &quot;The incest taboo, because it denies us essential fulfillment with the parents whom we love with our primary energy, forces us to internalize those parents and constantly seek them. The incest taboo does the worst work of the culture [[...]] The destruction of the incest taboo is essential to the development of cooperative human community based on the free-flow of natural androgynous eroticism.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Woman Hating'', p. 189.&lt;/ref&gt; Dworkin, however, does not explain if &quot;fulfillment&quot; is supposed to involve actual sexual intimacy, and one page earlier characterized what she meant by &quot;erotic relationships&quot; as relationships whose &quot;substance is nonverbal communication and touch,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Woman Hating'', p. 188.&lt;/ref&gt; which she explicitly distinguished from what she referred to as &quot;fucking.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Woman Hating'', p. 187.&lt;/ref&gt;

Dworkin's work from the early 1980s onward contained frequent condemnations of incest and [[pedophilia]] as one of the chief forms of violence against women, arguing once that &quot;Incest is terrifically important in understanding the condition of women. It is a crime committed against someone, a crime from which many victims never recover.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Letters from a War Zone'', pp. 139–142, 149, 176–180, 308, 314–315; Dworkin, ''Intercourse'', pp. 171, 194; Dworkin, ''Life and Death'', pp. 22–23, 79–80, 86, 123, 143, 173, 188–189.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Letters from a War Zone'', p. 139.&lt;/ref&gt; In the early 1980s she had a public row with her former friend [[Allen Ginsberg]] over his support for [[child pornography]] and pedophilia, in which Ginsberg said &quot;The right wants to put me in jail,&quot; and Dworkin responded &quot;Yes, they're very sentimental; I'd kill you.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, ''Heartbreak'', pp. 43–47.&lt;/ref&gt; When ''Hustler'' published in 1985 the claim that Dworkin advocated incest, Dworkin sued them for defamatory libel; the court dismissed Dworkin's complaint on the grounds that regardless of whether ''Hustler'''s interpretations of her reflections on incest were valid, even a faulty interpretation of a work placed into the &quot;[[marketplace of ideas]]&quot; could not amount to [[defamation]] in the legal sense.&lt;ref name=Flynt&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wyomcases.courts.state.wy.us/applications/oscn/DeliverDocument.asp?citeID=122816|title=''Dworkin v. L.F.P., Inc.'', 1992 WY 120, 839 P.2d 903|accessdate=July 12, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other critics, especially women who identify as feminists but sharply differ with Dworkin's style or positions, have offered nuanced views, suggesting that Dworkin called attention to real and important problems, but that her legacy as a whole had been destructive to the women's movement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2005/apr/15/gender.politicsphilosophyandsociety|title=The Real Legacy of Andrea Dworkin|author=Havana Marking|date=April 15, 2005|accessdate=July 12, 2009 | location=London | work=The Guardian| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20090826060751/http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2005/apr/15/gender.politicsphilosophyandsociety| archivedate= 26 August 2009 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; Her work and activism on pornography—especially in the form of the [[Antipornography Civil Rights Ordinance]]—drew heavy criticism from groups such as the [[Feminist Anti-Censorship Task Force]] (FACT). Dworkin also attracted criticism from [[sex-positive feminism|sex-positive feminists]], who emerged largely in opposition to the feminist [[anti-pornography movement]] during the 1980s, as Dworkin was becoming prominent on the national stage. 

Sex-positive feminist critics criticized her legal activism as censorious, and argued that her work on pornography and sexuality promoted an essentialist, conservative, or repressive view of sexuality, which they often characterized as &quot;anti-sex&quot; or &quot;sex-negative.&quot; Her criticisms of common heterosexual sexual expression, pornography, prostitution, and sexual [[Sadism and Masochism|sadism]] were frequently claimed to disregard women's own agency in sex or to deny women's sexual choices. Dworkin countered that her critics often misrepresented her views,&lt;ref&gt;See, for example, ''Letters from a War Zone'', p. 110: &quot;One of the slurs constantly used against me by women writing in behalf of pornography under the flag of feminism in misogynist media is that I endorse a primitive biological determinism. ''Woman Hating'' (1974) clearly repudiates any biological determinism; so does ''Our Blood'' (1976), especially &quot;The Root Cause.&quot; So does this piece, published twice, in 1978 in ''Heresies'' and in 1979 in ''Broadsheet''. The event described in this piece [&quot;Biological Superiority: The World's Most Dangerous and Deadly Idea&quot;], which occurred in 1977, was fairly notorious, and so my position on biological determinism—I am against it—is generally known in the Women's Movement.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; and that under the heading of &quot;choice&quot; and &quot;sex-positivity&quot; her feminist critics were failing to question the often violent political structures that confined women's choices and shaped the meaning of sex acts.&lt;ref&gt;See, for example, the 1995 Preface to ''Intercourse'', pp. vii–x, and ''Intercourse'', Chapter 7.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- We could also use some material on the conflicts between Dworkin and other anti-pornography feminists, e.g. Susan Brownmiller, Wendy Kaminer, etc. over whether to use legal activism as a means of combating pornography. --&gt;

==Publications==
In addition to books, articles, and speeches listed here, she wrote for anthologies and wrote additional articles, and some of her works were translated into other languages.&lt;ref&gt;[http://h-net.msu.edu/cgi-bin/logbrowse.pl?trx=vx&amp;list=H-Women&amp;month=0504&amp;week=b&amp;msg=4df/tu7bqMFY6gQsMcvpAQ&amp;user=&amp;pw= Richards, Deborah, ''Andrea Dworkin September 26, 1946 – April 9, 2005'', Apr. 12, 2005, in ''H-Women'', on ''Humanities and Social Sciences Net Online'' (discussion list message) (&quot;John Stoltenberg has sent these items this morning; they were prepared by Andrea Dworkin&quot;)], as accessed Oct. 8, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Nonfiction===
* ''Heartbreak: The Political Memoir of a Feminist Militant'' (2002) ISBN 0-465-01754-1
* ''[[Scapegoat: The Jews, Israel, and Women's Liberation]]'' (2000) ISBN 0-684-83612-2
* ''Life and Death: Unapologetic Writings on the Continuing War Against Women'' (1997) ISBN 0-684-83512-6
* ''In Harm’s Way: The Pornography Civil Rights Hearings'' (with Catharine MacKinnon, 1997) ISBN 0-674-44579-1
* ''Letters from a War Zone: Writings'' (1988) ISBN 1-55652-185-5 ISBN 0-525-24824-2 ISBN 0-436-13962-6
* ''Pornography and Civil Rights: A New Day for Women's Equality'' (1988) ISBN 0-9621849-0-X
* ''[[Intercourse (book)|Intercourse]]'' (1987) ISBN 0-684-83239-9
* ''Right-Wing Women: The Politics of Domesticated Females'' (1983) ISBN 0-399-50671-3
* ''[[Pornography: Men Possessing Women|Pornography—Men Possessing Women]]'' (1981) ISBN 0-399-50532-6 — [http://www.porn-library.com/dworkin_pornography_summary.htm Online summary], [http://www.nostatusquo.com/ACLU/dworkin/PornAList.html excerpts]
* ''Our Blood: Prophesies and Discourses on Sexual Politics'' (1976) ISBN 0-399-50575-X ISBN 0-06-011116-X
* ''[[Woman Hating: A Radical Look at Sexuality]]'' (Dutton, 1974) ISBN 0-452-26827-3 ISBN 0-525-48397-7

===Fiction and poetry===
* ''Mercy'' (1990, ISBN 0-941423-88-3)
* ''Ice and Fire'' (1986, ISBN 0-436-13960-X)
* ''The New Woman's Broken Heart: Short Stories'' (1980, ISBN 0-9603628-0-0)
* ''Morning Hair'' (self-published, 1968)
* ''Child'' (1966) (Heraklion, Crete, 1966)

===Articles===
* Marx and Gandhi were Liberals: Feminism and the &quot;Radical&quot; Left (1977 (ASIN B0006XEJCG))
* Why So-called Radical Men Love and Need Pornography (1978 (ASIN B0006XX57G))
* Against the Male Flood: Censorship, Pornography and Equality (1985 (ASIN B00073AVJA))
* The Reasons Why: Essays on the New Civil Rights Law Recognizing Pornography as Sex Discrimination (1985 (ASIN B000711OSO))
* Pornography is a Civil Rights Issue for Women (1986 (ASIN B00071HFYG))
* A Good Rape. (1996 (ASIN B0008DT8DE)) (Book Review)
* Out of the Closet.(Normal: Transsexual CEOs, Cross-Dressing Cops and Hermaphrodites with Attitude) (1996 (ASIN B0008E679Q)) (Book Review)
* The Day I Was Drugged and Raped (1996 (ASIN B0008IYNJS))
* Are You Listening, Hillary? President Rape Is Who He Is (1999) (excerpt)&lt;ref&gt;[http://andreadworkin.com/hillary/index.html  ''Are You Listening, Hillary? President Rape Is Who He Is'', by Andrea Dworkin, with ''Note from John Stoltenberg, May 25, 2007''], as accessed Aug. 3, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Speeches and interviews===
Some were digitalized.
* [http://www.andreadworkin.com/audio/TraffickingConference1989_P1_M.mp3 Why Men Like Pornography &amp; Prostitution So Much] Andrea Dworkin Keynote Speech at International Trafficking Conference, 1989. ''(Audio File: 22 min, 128&amp;nbsp;kbit/s, mp3)''
* [http://andreadworkin.com/audio/attgeneralcommNYC_M.mp3 Andrea Dworkin's Attorney General's Commission Testimony] on Pornography and Prostitution
* [http://www.andreadworkin.com/audio/ViolenceAbuseWomensCitizenshipM.mp3 Violence, Abuse &amp; Women's Citizenship Brighton], UK November 10, 1996
* [http://andreadworkin.com/audio/strikingback/ &quot;Freedom Now: Ending Violence Against Women&quot;]
* [http://www.andreadworkin.com/audio/duke01.85_M.mp3 &quot;Speech from Duke University, January, 1985&quot;]
* [http://www.andreadworkin.com/audio/dworkin_ginsberg_m.mp3 Taped Phone Interview] Andrea Dworkin interviewed by Nikki Craft on Allen Ginsberg, May 9, 1990. (Audio File, 20 min, 128&amp;nbsp;kbit/s, mp3)
* ''Dworkin on Dworkin'', ''ca.'' 1980&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, Andrea, ''Dworkin on Dworkin'', in [[Diane Bell|Bell, Diane]], &amp; Renate Klein, eds., ''Radically Speaking: Feminism Reclaimed'' ([[North Melbourne, Victoria|N. Melbourne, Vic., Australia]]: Spinifex, 1996 (ISBN 1 875559 38 8)), pp. 203–217 (ed. Bell then prof. religion, economic development, &amp; social justice, [[College of the Holy Cross|Coll. of the Holy Cross]], Mass., U.S., &amp; ed. Klein then sr. lecturer &amp; dep. dir., Australian Women's Research Centre, [[Deakin University|Deakin Univ.]], as reprinted from ''Dworkin on Dworkin'', in ''Trouble and Strife'', vol. or no. 19 (Summer, 1990), pp. 2–13 (itself from Braeman, Elizabeth, and Carol Cox, title not stated, in ''Off Our Backs'' (probably ''[[off our backs]]'') (10th birthday issue).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reviews of Dworkin's works===
* [http://www.nytimes.com/1987/05/03/books/male-and-female-men-and-women.html ''Ice and Fire'', by Andrea Dworkin; ''Intercourse'', by Andrea Dworkin. &quot;Male and Female, Men and Women&quot;]. Reviewed by Carol Sternhell for the ''[[New York Times]]'' (May 3, 1987).
* [http://maureenmullarkey.com/essays/porn1.html ''Intercourse'', by Andrea Dworkin; ''Feminism Unmodified'', by Catharine MacKinnon. &quot;Porn in the U.S.A., Part I&quot;]. Reviewed by Maureen Mullarkey for ''[[The Nation]]'' (May 30, 1987):
* [http://web.archive.org/web/20030402193857/http://www.isiswomen.org/wia/wia398/vaw00006.html ''Intercourse'', by Andrea Dworkin (Tenth Anniversary Edition 1997)]. Reviewed by Giney Villar for ''Women in Action'' (3:1998).
* [http://web.archive.org/web/20050306002136/http://nyc.indymedia.org/newswire/display/140928/index.php ''Pornography: Men Possessing Women''. &quot;Unburning a Witch: Re-Reading Andrea Dworkin&quot;]. Reviewed by [[Jed Brandt]] for the ''NYC Indypendent'' (February 7, 2005).

===Related work===
She was a member of The American Heritage Dictionary's Usage Panel.&lt;ref&gt;''The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language'' (Boston, Mass.: Houghton Mifflin, 3d ed. 1992 (ISBN 0-395-44895-6)), p. xii (The Usage Panel); the panel is discussed at ''id.'', p. vi (Introduction).&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Biography|Feminism|United States}}
* [[Anti-pornography movement]]

{{-}}

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=25em}}

==Further reading==
* [[Susan Brownmiller|Brownmiller, Susan]] (1999). ''In Our Time: Memoir of a Revolution'' (ISBN 0-385-31486-8).
* Robinson, Jeremy Mark (2008). ''Andrea Dworkin'' (ISBN 978-1-86171-126-7). Crescent Moon.
* [[Nadine Strossen|Strossen, Nadine]], ''Defending Pornography: Free Speech, Sex, and the Fight for Women's Rights'' (ISBN 0-8147-8149-7). New York University Press, 2000. (First edition New York: Scribner, 1995).

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
* [http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/obituaries/culture-obituaries/1487683/Andrea-Dworkin.html Andrea Dworkin] – Daily Telegraph obituary
* [http://www.andreadworkin.com/ Portal for Andrea Dworkin's Websites] maintained by [[Nikki Craft]]
* [http://www.nostatusquo.com/ACLU/dworkin/OnlineLibrary.html Official Andrea Dworkin Online Library] maintained by [[Nikki Craft]]
* [http://www.andreadworkin.net/ Andrea Dworkin Memorial Page] maintained by [[Nikki Craft]]
* [http://www.brainyquote.com/quotes/authors/a/andrea_dworkin.html Andrea Dworkin Quotes]
* [http://www.britannica.com/women/article-9124959 Encyclopaedia Britannica's 300 Women who changed the world] – Andrea Dworkin entry
* [http://nrs.harvard.edu/urn-3:RAD.SCHL:sch01051 Papers, 1914–2007 (inclusive), 1973–2000 (bulk): A Finding Aid.] [http://www.radcliffe.edu/schles Schlesinger Library], Radcliffe Institute, Harvard University.
*[http://nrs.harvard.edu/urn-3:RAD.SCHL:sch01210 Videotape collection of Andrea Dworkin, 1981–1998 (inclusive): A Finding Aid.][http://www.radcliffe.edu/schles Schlesinger Library], Radcliffe Institute, Harvard University.
*[http://nrs.harvard.edu/urn-3:RAD.SCHL:sch01209 Audiotape collection of Andrea Dworkin, 1975–1997 (inclusive): A Finding Aid.][http://www.radcliffe.edu/schles Schlesinger Library], Radcliffe Institute, Harvard University.
* [[Alice Shalvi]], [http://jwa.org/encyclopedia/article/dworkin-andrea Biography of Andrea Dworkin], Jewish Women Encyclopedia
* [http://www.culturalfarming.com/Porn_Parody/dworkin.html Andrea Dworkin] Media praxis video tribute.

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Dworkin, Andrea
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =September 26, 1946
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =[[Camden, New Jersey]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =April 9, 2005
| PLACE OF DEATH    =[[Washington, D.C.]]
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Dworkin, Andrea}}
[[Category:1946 births]]
[[Category:2005 deaths]]
[[Category:American anarchists]]
[[Category:American feminist writers]]
[[Category:American novelists]]
[[Category:American tax resisters]]
[[Category:Anti-pornography feminists]]
[[Category:Anti-prostitution feminists]]
[[Category:Bennington College alumni]]
[[Category:Cardiovascular disease deaths in Washington, D.C.]]
[[Category:Feminist critics of BDSM]]
[[Category:Feminist studies scholars]]
[[Category:Jewish feminists]]
[[Category:Lesbian writers]]
[[Category:Lesbian prostitutes]]
[[Category:LGBT Jews]]
[[Category:LGBT writers from the United States]]
[[Category:People from Camden, New Jersey]]
[[Category:People from Cherry Hill, New Jersey]]
[[Category:Jewish anarchists]]
[[Category:Jewish American novelists]]
[[Category:Jewish women writers]]
[[Category:Radical lesbian feminists]]

{{Link GA|sv}}
[[bg:Андреа Дуоркин]]
[[de:Andrea Dworkin]]
[[et:Andrea Dworkin]]
[[el:Αντρέα Ντβόρκιν]]
[[fr:Andrea Dworkin]]
[[he:אנדריאה דבורקין]]
[[ja:アンドレア・ドウォーキン]]
[[pl:Andrea Dworkin]]
[[pt:Andrea Dworkin]]
[[ru:Дворкин, Андреа]]
[[sv:Andrea Dworkin]]
[[zh:安德里亞·德沃金]]</text>
      <sha1>j3x3e7dyddvu7c1s79cmlcnyw7f5we3</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
