<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Andrea Yates</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>315087</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519413906</id>
      <parentid>518869776</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-23T16:28:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Spelling Style</username>
        <id>17150052</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="34973">{{Infobox person
|name = Andrea Yates
|image =
|caption = Andrea Yates in court.
|birth_name = Andrea Pia Kennedy&lt;br&gt;[[Houston]], [[Texas]], United States
|birth_date = {{Birth date and age|1964|7|2|}}
|spouse = Russell Yates (1993-2004)(divorced)
|children = Noah, b. February 26, 1994 (aged 7 at death) &lt;br&gt; John, b. December 15, 1995 (aged 5 at death) &lt;br&gt; Paul, b. September 13, 1997 (aged 3 at death) &lt;br&gt; Luke, b. February 15, 1999 (aged 2 at death) &lt;br&gt; Mary, b. November 30, 2000 (aged 6 months at death) &lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; All children deceased June 20, 2001
}}

'''Andrea Yates''' (born '''Andrea Pia Kennedy''' on July 2, 1964) is a former [[Houston]], [[Texas]] resident who killed her five children on June 20, 2001 by drowning them in the [[bathtub]] in her house.&lt;ref name=&quot;Spitz, 2006&quot;&gt;Spitz, D.J. (2006): Investigation of Bodies in Water. In: Spitz, W.U. &amp; Spitz, D.J. (eds): ''Spitz and Fisher’s Medicolegal Investigation of Death. Guideline for the Application of Pathology to Crime Investigations (Fourth edition)'', Charles C. Thomas, pp.: 846-881; Springfield, Illinois.&lt;/ref&gt; She had been suffering for some time with very severe [[postpartum depression]] and  [[postpartum psychosis]]. Her case placed the [[M'Naghten Rules]] with the [[Irresistible Impulse]] Test, a legal test for sanity, under close public scrutiny in the United States. Yates's 2002 conviction of [[capital murder]] and sentence to [[life in prison]] with the possibility of [[parole]] after 40 years was later overturned on [[appeal]]. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/6794098/ns/us_news-crime_and_courts/t/convictions-overturned-mom-who-drowned-kids/ |title=Andrea Yates’ murder convictions overturned - US news - Crime &amp; courts - msnbc.com |publisher=MSNBC |date=2005-01-06 |accessdate=2012-03-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On July 26, 2006, a [[Texas]] jury found that Yates was [[Insanity defense|not guilty by reason of insanity]]. She was consequently committed by the court to the [[North Texas State Hospital]], Vernon Campus,&lt;ref&gt;[http://edition.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/0607/26/ng.01.html Not Guilty Verdict for Andrea Yates; Missing Girl's Body Found in Utah]; Nancy Grace; [[CNN]]; July 26, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; a high-security mental health facility in [[Vernon, Texas]], where she received medical treatment and was a roommate of [[Dena Schlosser]], another woman who committed [[filicide]] by killing her infant daughter. In January 2007, Yates was moved to a low security state mental hospital in [[Kerrville, Texas]].&lt;ref name=&quot;abclocal.go.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; |url=http://abclocal.go.com/ktrk/story?section=local&amp;id=4975397 |title=KTRK-News, Houston, January 26, 2007 |publisher=Abclocal.go.com |date=2007-01-26 |accessdate=2012-03-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Overview==
Andrea Yates was born in [[Houston, Texas]]. She is the youngest of five children to Jutta Karin Koehler, a [[German people|German]] immigrant, and Andrew Emmett Kennedy, whose parents were born in [[Ireland]]. Yates was raised in a [[Catholic]] household.{{fact|date=September 2012}} Andrea was [[bulimic]] during her teenage years. She also suffered from depression and, at the age of seventeen, spoke to a friend about suicide.&lt;ref&gt; O'Malley, p. 78 &lt;/ref&gt;

She graduated from [[Milby High School]], in Houston, Texas, in 1982. She was the [[valedictorian|class valedictorian]], captain of the swim team, and an officer in the [[National Honor Society]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Duke Journal of Gender Law &amp; Policy&quot;&gt;[http://www.law.duke.edu/shell/cite.pl?10+Duke+J.+Gender+L.+&amp;+Pol%27y+1#H2N1], ''Duke Journal of Gender Law &amp; Policy''&lt;/ref&gt; Yates completed a two-year pre-nursing program at the [[University of Houston]] and graduated from the [[University of Texas School of Nursing at Houston|University of Texas School of Nursing]]. From 1986 until 1994, she worked as a [[registered nurse]] at the University of Texas [[M.D. Anderson Cancer Center]]. In the summer of 1989, she met Russell &quot;Rusty&quot; Yates at the Sunscape Apartments in Houston, Texas, two months her junior. They soon moved in together and were married on April 17, 1993,&lt;ref name=&quot;TQ&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://library.thinkquest.org/04oct/00803/Yates_Frameset.htm |title=Andrea Yates |publisher=Library.thinkquest.org |date= |accessdate=2012-03-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; and they announced that they &quot;would seek to have [[Quiverfull|as many babies as nature allowed]]&quot;. Afterwards, they bought a four-bedroom house in the town of [[Friendswood, Texas|Friendswood]]. In February 1994, the couple's first child, a son named Noah, was born. Shortly thereafter, Rusty accepted a job offer in [[Florida]], so the family relocated to a small [[trailer]] in [[Seminole, Florida|Seminole]]. By the birth of their third son, Paul, they settled back to Houston and purchased a GMC motor home.&lt;ref name=&quot;TQ&quot;/&gt;

Following the birth of their fourth son, Luke, Andrea became [[clinical depression|depressed]]. The media alleged that her condition was influenced by the extremist sermons of [[Michael Peter Woroniecki]], the preacher who sold them their bus.{{clarification|date=September 2012}} Her family was concerned by the way that she was so captivated by the minister’s words.&lt;ref name=&quot;TQ&quot;/&gt;

On June 16, 1999, Rusty found Andrea shaking and chewing her fingers. The next day, she attempted to commit [[suicide]] by overdosing on pills. She was admitted to the hospital, and prescribed [[antidepressant]]s. Soon after her release, she begged her husband to let her die as she held a knife up to her neck. Once again hospitalized, she was given a mixture of medications including [[Haldol]], an anti-psychotic drug. Her condition improved immediately, and she was prescribed it on her release. After that, Rusty moved the family into a small house for the sake of her health. Andrea appeared temporarily to stabilise.&lt;ref name=&quot;TQ&quot;/&gt; In July 1999, she succumbed to a [[nervous breakdown]], which culminated in two [[suicide]] attempts and two psychiatric hospitalizations that summer. She was diagnosed with [[postpartum psychosis]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Lancet&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal| last =McLellan | first =Faith | title =Mental health and justice: the case of Andrea Yates | journal =[[The Lancet]]| volume =368 | issue =9551 | pages =1951–1954 | publisher =[[Elsevier]]| location =[[Amsterdam]] | date =2 December 2006|url=http://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140673606697894/fulltext | doi =10.1016/S0140-6736(06)69789-4 | accessdate=2008-04-10 | pmid = 17146865 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Her first [[psychiatrist]], Dr. [[Eileen Starbranch]], testified that she urged the couple not to have more children, as it would &quot;guarantee future psychotic depression&quot;. They conceived their fifth and final child approximately 7 weeks after her discharge.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,202606,00.html Doctor: I Warned Andrea Yates Not to Have Any More Children]. [[Fox News Channel]]. July 7, 2006. Retrieved October 3, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; She stopped taking the Haldol in March 2000 and gave birth to daughter Mary on November 30 of that year. She seemed to be coping well until the death of her father on March 12, 2001.&lt;ref name=&quot;crime.about&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://crime.about.com/od/current/p/andreayates.htm |title=Andrea Yates - Profile of Andrea Yates |publisher=Crime.about.com |date= |accessdate=2012-03-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

She then stopped taking medication, [[self-harm|mutilated herself]], and read the [[Bible]] feverishly. She also stopped feeding her youngest child, Mary.&lt;ref name=&quot;TQ&quot;/&gt; Yates became so incapacitated that she required immediate hospitalization. On April 1, 2001 she came under the care of Dr. [[Mohammed Saeed]]. She was treated and released. On May 3, 2001, she degenerated back into a &quot;near [[catatonia|catatonic]]&quot; state and drew a bath in the middle of the day; she would later confess to police that she had planned to drown the children that day, but had decided against doing it then. She was hospitalized the next day after a scheduled doctor visit; her psychiatrist determined she was probably suicidal and had filled the tub to drown herself.&lt;ref&gt;Suzanne O'Malley, Are You There Alone?, p. 20&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;crime.about&quot; /&gt;

Yates continued under Dr. Saeed's care until June 20, 2001, when Rusty left for work, leaving her alone to watch the children against Dr. Saeed's instructions to supervise her around the clock.&lt;ref name=&quot;chron.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.chron.com/disp/story.mpl/special/drownings/4044790.html Yates not Grossly Psychotic before Drownings Dietz testifies]; Dale Lezon; [[Houston Chronicle]]; July 13, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Rusty's mother, Dora Yates, had been scheduled by him to arrive an hour later to take over for her. In the space of that hour, she drowned all five children.&lt;ref name=&quot;Houston Chon&quot;&gt;[http://www.chron.com/CDA/archives/archive.mpl?id=2001_3319302 Brother: Yates thought drownings `best thing' / He says sister felt she was a bad mom]; RUTH RENDON; [[Houston Chronicle]]; July 14, 2001&lt;/ref&gt; She started with the youngest boys, and after drowning them in her bathtub, laid them in her bed. She then drowned Mary, whom she left floating in the tub. Her oldest son, Noah, came in and asked what was wrong with Mary. He then ran, but she soon caught up with him and drowned him. She then left him floating in the tub and laid Mary in her brothers' arms. Afterwards, she called the police. Then she called Rusty, saying only “It’s time” repeatedly. &lt;ref name=&quot;TQ&quot;/&gt;

==Trials==
Yates confessed to drowning her children. She told Dr. [[Michael Welner]] that she waited for Rusty to leave for work that morning before filling the bathtub because she knew he would have prevented her from harming the children.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://abcnews.go.com/US/LegalCenter/Story?id=2245394&amp;page=2 |title=Dr. Michael Welner, who examined her, lists 68 reasons she knew right from wrong |publisher=Abcnews.go.com |date=2006-07-27 |accessdate=2012-03-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the killings, police found the family dog locked up; Rusty advised Welner that it had normally been allowed to run free, and was so when he had left the house that morning, leading the psychiatrist to conclude that she locked it in a cage to prevent it from interfering with her killing the children one by one.

Although the defense's expert testimony agreed that Yates was psychotic, Texas law requires that, in order to successfully assert the [[insanity defense]], the defendant must prove that he or she could not discern right from wrong at the time of the crime. In March 2002, a jury rejected the insanity defense and found her guilty. Although the prosecution had sought the [[death penalty]], the [[jury]] refused that option. The trial court sentenced her to [[life imprisonment]] in the [[Texas Department of Criminal Justice]] with eligibility for [[parole]] in 40 years.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/nation/article/0,8599,218445,00.html Andrea Yates: More To The Story] ''Time'' By Timothy Roche March 18, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;

On January 6, 2005, a [[Texas Court of Appeals]] reversed the convictions, because California [[psychiatry|psychiatrist]] and prosecution witness Dr. [[Park Dietz]] admitted he had given materially false testimony during the trial. Dietz stated that shortly before the killings, an episode of ''[[Law &amp; Order]]'' had aired featuring a woman who drowned her children and was acquitted of murder by reason of insanity. Author [[Suzanne O'Malley]], who was covering the trial for [[O: The Oprah Magazine|''Oprah'' magazine]] and had previously been a writer for ''Law &amp; Order'', immediately reported that no such episode existed;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;'Law &amp; Order' saved Yates,&quot; ''New York Post'', Friday, March 22, 2002, p10&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Later, in 2004, ''[[Law &amp; Order: Criminal Intent]]'' did air the episode &quot;[[Magnificat (Law &amp; Order: Criminal Intent episode)|Magnificat]]&quot;, based in part on Yates's case.&lt;/ref&gt; the appellate court held that the jury may have been influenced by his false testimony and that thus a new trial would be necessary.

On January 9, 2006, Yates again entered pleas of not guilty by reason of insanity. On February 1, 2006, she was granted release on [[bail]] on the condition that she be admitted to a [[psychiatric hospital|mental health treatment facility]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nbc5.com/money/9546260/detail.html Psychiatrist: Yates Thought Drownings Were Right] July 19, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

On July 26, 2006, after three days of deliberations, Yates was found not guilty by reason of insanity, as defined by the state of Texas. She was thereafter committed to the North Texas State Hospital - Vernon Campus.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
  | last = Brown
  | first = Angela K.
  | title = Jury finds Yates not guilty in drownings
  | publisher = Houston Chronicle
  | date = 2006-07-26
  | url = http://www.chron.com/disp/story.mpl/ap/nation/4074127.html
  | accessdate = 2006-07-26}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In January 2007, Yates was moved to a low security state mental hospital in [[Kerrville, Texas]].&lt;ref name=&quot;abclocal.go.com&quot;/&gt;
Although psychiatrists for both the Texas State prosecutors and Yates' defense lawyers agreed that she was severely mentally ill with one of several psychotic diseases at the time she killed her children,&lt;ref&gt;O'Malley, p. 143-145,175,177,236&lt;/ref&gt; the state of Texas asserted that she was by legal definition aware enough to judge her actions as right or wrong despite her mental defect. The prosecution further implied spousal-revenge as motive for the killings, despite the conclusion of defense experts that there was no evidence to support such a motive.&lt;ref&gt;Anne Belli Gesalman, Psychosis Or Vengeance?  Newsweek, Mar. 7, 2002 [http://www.newsweek.com/id/74967?tid=relatedcl Article]; O'Malley, p. 146&lt;/ref&gt; Although the original jury believed she was legally aware of her actions, they disagreed that her motive was spousal-revenge.&lt;ref&gt;O'Malley, p. 217&lt;/ref&gt; The jury in 2006 completely disagreed with the prosecution's assertions and her earlier conviction from 2002 was overturned.

===Russell Yates===
According to trial testimony in 2006, Dr. Saeed advised Rusty, a former NASA engineer, not to leave his patient unattended. However, he began leaving her alone with the children in the weeks leading up to the drownings for short periods of time hoping to improve her independence.&lt;ref name=&quot;chron.com&quot;/&gt; He had announced at a family gathering the weekend before the drownings that he had decided to leave her home alone for an hour each morning and evening, so that she would not become totally dependent on him and his mother for her maternal responsibilities.&lt;ref&gt;Suzy Spencer, Breaking Point, p. 300&lt;/ref&gt; Her brother, Brian Kennedy, told [[Larry King]] on a broadcast of [[CNN]]'s ''[[Larry King Live]]'' that Rusty expressed to him in 2001 while transporting her to Devereux treatment facility that all depressed people needed was a &quot;swift kick in the pants&quot; to get them motivated.&lt;ref&gt;CNN-Larry King Live, January 16, 2005 [http://transcripts.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/0501/16/lkl.01.html Transcript]&lt;/ref&gt; Her mother, Jutta Karin Kennedy, expressed shock when she heard of Rusty's plan while at the gathering with them, saying that she wasn't stable enough to care for the children. She noted that her daughter demonstrated she wasn't in her right mind when she nearly choked her still-toothless infant daughter Mary by trying to feed her solid food.&lt;ref&gt;Cynthia Hunt, &quot;Andrea Yates' Mother Recalls Conversation Days before Drownings,&quot; KTRK News, Houston, 3/18/2002 [http://members.aol.com/niek02/KTRKArchives/AndreaYatesMotherRecallsConversationDaysBefore_Mar18_2002.htm]&lt;/ref&gt; According to authors [[Suzy Spencer]] and Suzanne O'Malley, who investigated her story in great detail, it was during a phone call Dr. Saeed made to Rusty during the breaking news of the killings that he first learned that she was not being supervised full time.&lt;ref&gt;Spencer, p. 18; O'Malley, p. 23&lt;/ref&gt;

Andrea's first psychiatrist, Dr. Eileen Starbranch, says she was shocked to disbelief when the Yateses expressed a desire to discontinue her medications so that she could become pregnant again during an office visit with them. She warned and counseled them against having more children, and noted in the medical record two days later, '&quot;Apparently patient and husband plan to have as many babies as nature will allow! This will surely guarantee future psychotic depression.&quot;'&lt;ref&gt;O'Malley, p. 41; Yates' husband takes stand, CBS News, Feb. 26, 2002 [http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2002/02/28/national/main502440.shtml Article]&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, she became pregnant with her fifth child, Mary, only 7 weeks after being discharged from Dr. Starbranch's care on January 12, 2000.&lt;ref&gt;Yates Timeline, Houston Chronicle, January 6, 2005 [http://www.chron.com/disp/story.mpl/special/drownings/1274920.html Timeline]&lt;/ref&gt; Despite Rusty's statements to the media that he was never told by psychiatrists that she was psychotic nor that she could harm her children, and that he would have never had more children had he known otherwise,&lt;ref&gt;''&quot;'If I'd known she was psychotic, we'd never have even considered having more kids,' she told the Dallas Observer.&quot;'' Terri Langford, Rusty Yates' actions puzzle acquaintance, Houston Chronicle, June 15, 2006 [http://www.chron.com/disp/story.mpl/special/drownings/3733316.html Article]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Carlton Stowers, Tracks of His Tears,  Dallas Observer, January 23, 2003 [http://www.dallasobserver.com/2003-01-23/news/tracks-of-his-tears/full Article]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Laura Parker, Rusty Yates 'didn't know' wife was psychotic, USA Today, Mar. 18, 2002 [http://www.usatoday.com/news/nation/2002/03/18/usat-yates.htm Article]&lt;/ref&gt; she revealed to her jail psychiatrist, Dr. Melissa Ferguson, that prior to their last child, &quot;she had told Rusty that she did not want to have sex because Dr. Starbranch had said she might hurt her children.&quot; Rusty, she said, simply asserted his procreative religious beliefs, complimented her as a good mother, and persuaded her that she could handle more children.&lt;ref&gt;A few months before 11/6/01, she had recalled that prior to Mary’s birth, she had told him that she did not want to have sex because Dr. Starbranch had said she might hurt her children. He had said, “The Lord tells us to go forth and multiply. You’re a good mother. You can handle more children.” After recounting this, she asked Dr. Ferguson, “Did I do the right thing?” [Interview of Melissa Ferguson, M.D., 11/6/01.] [http://www.parkdietzassociates.com/files/Report_of_Dr._Park_Dietz_re._Andrea_Yates__2002.pdf Forensic Psychiatric Evaluation, Park Dietz, Feb. 25, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;

Author Suzanne O'Malley highlighted Russell Yates's continuing sense of unreality regarding having more children:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
''&quot;During the trial, he'd successfully maintained the position that Andrea would be found innocent. He had fantasies of having more children with her after she was successfully treated in a mental health facility and released on the proper medication. He worked his way through various fixes for their damaged lives, such as a surrogate motherhood and adoption (horrifying Andrea's family, attorneys and Houston psychiatrists) before giving in to reality.&quot;''&lt;ref&gt;O'Malley, p. 246&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Medical community===
Rusty Yates contended that as a psychiatrist, Dr. Saeed was responsible for recognizing and properly treating his wife's psychosis, not a medically untrained person like himself.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;My God, we went -- I couldn't see this. We went to a doctor two days before this happened. I mean, we went -- the children passed away on June 20. We went to a doctor on June 18. He's a trained professional who is supposed to be able to recognize these kinds of things. I'm not. I'm just a guy. So...&quot;; CNN Larry King Live, Interview with Rusty Yates, Aired March 18, 2002 [http://transcripts.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/0203/18/lkl.00.html Transcript]&lt;/ref&gt; He also claimed that, despite his urgings to check her medical records for prior treatment, Dr. Saeed had refused to continue her regimen of the antipsychotic [[Haldol]], the treatment that had worked for her during her first breakdown in 1999.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The real question to me is: How could she have been so ill and the medical community not diagnose her, not treat her, and obviously not protect our family from her.&quot;...&quot;Rusty testified that he never knew that Andrea had visions and voices; he said he never knew she had considered killing the children. Neither did Dr. Saeed, even though the delusions could have been found in medical records from 1999...he reluctantly prescribed Haldol, the same drug that worked in a drug cocktail for her in 1999. But after a few weeks, he took her off the drug, citing his concerns about side effects...though her condition seemed to be worsening two days before the drownings, when Rusty drove her to Dr. Saeed's office, he testified, the doctor refused to try Haldol longer or return her to the hospital.&quot; Andrea Yates, More to the Story, Timothy Roche, Time Magazine, March 18, 2002 [http://www.time.com/time/nation/article/0,8599,218445-1,00.html Article pp.1,3]&lt;/ref&gt; He added that she was too sick to be released from her last stay in the hospital in May, 2001. He said he noticed the staff lower their heads as if in shame and embarrassment, turning away without saying a word. The hospital had no other choice due to the ten-day psychiatric hospitalization insurance constraints of their provider, [[Blue Cross-Blue Shield]], subcontracted by [[Magellan Health Services]].&lt;ref&gt;Spencer, p. 119&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;O'Malley, p. 23&lt;/ref&gt;

===Anti-depressants and homicidal ideation===
Rusty and her birth family came to believe that a combination of antidepressants improperly prescribed by Dr. Saeed in the days before the tragedy was responsible for Andrea's violent, psychotic behavior.&lt;ref name=&quot;Article&quot;&gt;Carol Christian, 'Harmful treatment' Family files complaint against Andrea Yates' psychiatrist, Houston Chronicle, Apr. 11, 2002
 [http://www.chron.com/disp/story.mpl/special/drownings/1360510.html Article]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Andrea was on 450 mg of Effexor, among other medications, and was in Rusty's opinion, severely overmedicated.&quot;...&quot;The psychiatrist said he would reduce the Effexor from 450 mg to 300 mg. He protested and quoted his own extensive research on the antidepressant. He said he read it shouldn't be reduced by more than 75 mg every three or four days, not 150 mg in one day.&quot; Suzy Spencer, Breaking Point, St. Martin's Press, c. 2002, p.119,120&lt;/ref&gt; According to Dr. Moira Dolan, executive director of the Medical Accountability Network, &quot;homicidal ideation&quot; was added to the warning label of the antidepressant drug [[Effexor]] as a rare adverse event, in 2005. Yates, she said, had been taking 450&amp;nbsp;mg, twice the recommended maximum dose, for a month before killing her children. Dr. Dolan reviewed Yates's medical record at the request of Rusty.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Yates had been prescribed Effexor in varying doses since shortly after her first suicide attempt in 1999, said Dolan, who reviewed her medical records after her first trial at the request of Rusty. A month before the killings, her daily dose had increased to 450 milligrams, twice the recommended maximum dose, Dolan said.&quot; Angela K. Brown, Group warns of drug she took before deaths, Houston Chronicle, July 10, 2006 [http://www.chron.com/disp/story.mpl/metropolitan/4035681.html Article]&lt;/ref&gt;

Dr. Lucy Puyear, an expert witness hired by Yates's defense team, countered their contention regarding the administration of her antidepressants, saying the dosages prescribed by Dr. Saeed are not uncommon in practice and had nothing at all to do with her reemergent psychosis. She suggested rather that her psychosis returned as a result of the Haldol having been discontinued by her doctor two weeks earlier.&lt;ref name=&quot;Article&quot;/&gt; The oral form of haloperidol (Haldol) takes 4–6 days after discontinuation to reach a terminal plasma level of under 1.5%—a medical standard for &quot;complete&quot; elimination of a drug from the body.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.medsafe.govt.nz/profs/datasheet/s/Serenacetaboralsolninj.htm Haldol Data Sheet]; [http://gargoyle.arcadia.edu/psychology/blustein/neuro/Lecture_Notes/Psychopharmacology_II_Lecture_Notes.pdf Half life drug standard]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Alleged religious influences===
Media outlets alleged that [[Michael Peter Woroniecki]], a traveling preacher whom Rusty had met while attending [[Auburn University]], bears some responsibility for the deaths due to his “[[fire and brimstone]]” message and certain teachings found in his newsletter ''The Perilous Times'' that they had received on occasion and which was entered into evidence at the trial.&lt;ref name=&quot;ABC20020327&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://abcnews.go.com/GMA/story?id=126222&amp;page=1|title=I Shared Jesus With Them|date=2002-03-27|work=Good Morning America|publisher=ABC News|accessdate=10 March 2010|location=New York}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NW20020318&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|title=Examining a spiritual leader's influence|last=Gesalman|first=Anne Belli|date=2002-03-18|work=Newsweek|page=8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.worldnetdaily.com/news/article.asp?ARTICLE_ID=26949 World Net Daily, Beware of Poisonous Preachers] Mar. 23, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lost in the Message? Lisa Teachy, Houston Chronicle, April 5, 2002 [http://www.chron.com/disp/story.mpl/front/1346952.html  Article] &quot;Shortly after Satan's first appearance at her capital murder trial, many observers began blaming the tragedy on a traveling evangelist they once admired. Television networks flashed images of the proselytizing preacher in a devil costume to accompany their coverage of the trial -- linking Michael Woroniecki to her confession that she killed her children to save their souls.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;In the aftermath of her 2006 retrial and insanity verdict, host Chris Cuomo reported on ABC Primetime that: ''&quot;[Andrea Yates'] delusions were fueled by the extreme religious beliefs of a bizarre, itinerant street preacher named Michael Woroniecki ...&quot;''; Chris Cuomo, &quot;Primetime, Insanity Verdict, Insanity Defense. Secrets and Lies: The American Imposter, The American Imposter Tells All&quot;, ABC Primetime, July 27, 2006 [http://www.transcripts.tv/primetime-live.cfm Order Transcript] See also:[http://a.abcnews.com/Primetime/Story?id=2244865&amp;page=1 ABC Article of Telecast]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Doug Saunders, Globe and Mail, Toronto Canada, Mar. 14, 2002 [http://www.rickross.com/reference/woroniecki/woroniecki4.html Article]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Her life was also distinguished by religious obsession and a steadfast devotion to tales of sin and Scripture, a 'repent-or-burn zeal' that led her to believe she was a bad mother with ruined offspring. According to her, she killed her children to save them from Satan and her own evil maternal influences, delusions that did little to help her defense because they fueled her own desire for punishment.&quot; Deborah W. Denno, WHO IS ANDREA YATES? A SHORT STORY ABOUT INSANITY, Duke Journal of Gender Law &amp; Policy, Vol. 10, Summer, 2003 [http://www.law.duke.edu/shell/cite.pl?10+Duke+J.+Gender+L.+&amp;+Pol'y+1+pdf Article]&lt;/ref&gt; However, both Rusty and Michael Woroniecki reject these accusations.&lt;ref name=&quot;duke&quot;&gt;'''Duke Journal of Gender Law and Policy''', ''Volume 10:1, 2003 Apendix 1'', '''Timeline of Andrea Yates Life and Trial''' [http://www.law.duke.edu/journals/djglp/downloads/gen10p61.pdf &quot;Archive&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;chron&quot;&gt;'''&quot;Lost in the message? Cleric says he’s not to blame for Yates demons&quot;''', ''Lisa Teachy, The Houston Chronicle, April 6, 2002'' [http://www.chron.com/CDA/archives/archive.mpl?id=2002_3533886 &quot;Archive&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;grneeded&quot;&gt;['''&quot;They Needed Jesus&quot;''', ''Steve Grinczel, The Grand Rapids Press, March 9, 2002'' ]&lt;/ref&gt; Rusty said that his family’s relationship with the Woronieckis was not that close and that Woroniecki did not cause her delusions.&lt;ref name=&quot;chron&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TS20020420&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|title=Unrepentant in Yates tragedy|last=Nichols|first=Bruce|date=2002-04-20|publisher=The Toronto Star}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Woroniecki maintained that his correspondence with them was with the intention of helping them strengthen their marriage and find the love that he says his own family had found in Jesus.&lt;ref name=&quot;ABC20020327&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;grneeded&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;grneeded&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;cmu&quot;&gt;'''&quot;Michael Woroniecki preaches Jesus not murder&quot;''', ''Central Michigan Life, Heather Bellife, May 22, 2002'' [http://www.cm-life.com/2002/05/22/michaelworonieckipreachesjesusnotmurder &quot;Archive&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;tamw&quot;&gt;'''The Truth About Michael Woroniecki'''[http://www.michaelworoniecki.blogspot.com &quot;Website&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Peter Jennings]] of '''[[World News with Diane Sawyer|World News Tonight]]''' reported that Rachel Woroniecki, in a letter, had told them that they needed to reconcile their marriage. '''Did the preacher see it coming?''', ''World News Tonight, Peter Jennings, January 21, 2002''&lt;/ref&gt; Both men agreed that the alleged connection between his message and her mental state was “nothing more than media created fiction”.&lt;ref name=&quot;chron&quot;/&gt; The adherence of the Yates family to the principles of the [[Quiverfull]] lifestyle, which encourages couples to have many children, has been posited as a factor contributing to the mental and emotional stress that she experienced. Some sources have suggested the lack of community may have contributed to her isolation.&lt;ref&gt; O'Malley, p. 67 {{cite journal |first1=Christy |last1=Mesaros-Winckles |year=2010 |month=September |title=TLC and the fundamentalist family: a televised Quiverfull of babies |journal=Journal of Religion and Popular Culture |volume=22 |issue=3 |issn=1703-289X |quote=More research is needed to fully understand the stress this lifestyle can have on a woman's physical and psychological health. For instance, Andrea Yates, the Texas mother who received national attention in the United States for drowning her five children in a bathtub in the 2000s, is a perfect example of the mental and emotional strain the [[Quiverfull]] lifestyle can have on a woman. Few people realize she and Rusty subscribed to the movement's beliefs, and this places further emphasis on the need to highlight the ideology of this movement.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While in prison, Andrea stated she had considered killing the children for two years, adding that they thought she was not a good mother and claimed her sons were developing improperly. She told her jail psychiatrist: &quot;It was the seventh deadly sin. My children weren't righteous. They stumbled because I was evil. The way I was raising them, they could never be saved. They were doomed to perish in the fires of hell.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last=Christian |first=Carol |coauthors=Lisa Teachy |title=Yates Believed Children Doomed |publisher=''Houston Chronicle'' |date=2002-03-06 |url=http://www.chron.com/disp/story.mpl/special/drownings/1268306.html |accessdate=2006-07-26}}{{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; She also told her jail psychiatrist that [[Satan]] influenced her children and made them more disobedient.&lt;ref&gt;O'Malley, p. 194&lt;/ref&gt;

==Popular culture==
* The [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC-TV]] show ''[[Desperate Housewives]]'' was partly inspired by the Yates drownings, according to creator [[Marc Cherry]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.hollywood.com/news/ChildKiller_Trial_Inspired_Desperate_Housewives/3545880&lt;/ref&gt;
* The ''[[Law &amp; Order: Criminal Intent]]'' episode &quot;[[Magnificat (Law &amp; Order: Criminal Intent episode)|Magnificat]]&quot; was based on the Yates case.{{fact|date=September 2012}}
* The 2008 film ''[[Baby Blues (2008 film)|Baby Blues]]'' (AKA ''Cradle may Fall'' in U.K.) is based on the killings,{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}} although the story is largely changed from the true events.
* On his song &quot;World Gone Crazy&quot;, rapper [[Aaron Yates]] (AKA &quot;Tech N9ne&quot;) references his last name being the same, and also references a woman drowning her babies in the lyrics: &quot;Sick mothers drowning they babies&quot; &amp; &quot;Why I got the same last name as Andrea?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vPGuLLqPWjI&lt;/ref&gt;
* A song by the band [[Trivium (band)|Trivium]], entitled &quot;[[Entrance of the Conflagration]]&quot;, deals with the drownings, and is mostly based on Andrea Yates' testimony.{{fact|date=September 2012}}
* The TV documentary series, ''[[American Justice]]'', has an episode about the case.{{fact|date=September 2012}}
* In 2009, the Andrea Yates incident and its aftermath was adapted by playwright Douglas M. Parker into the play ''Thicker Than Water''.{{fact|date=September 2012}}
*The TV show &quot;Deadly Women&quot; did a segment on Andrea Yates.{{fact|date=September 2012}}

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
*Bienstock, Sheri L. ''Mothers Who Kill Their Children and Postpartum Psychosis'',  (2003) Vol. 32, No. 3 Southwestern University Law Review, 451.
*Keram, ''The Insanity Defense and Game Theory: Reflections on Texas v.Yates'', (2002) Vol. 30, No. 4 Journal of the American Academy of Psychiatry and the Law, 470.
*O'Malley, Suzanne, ''&quot;Are You There Alone?:&quot; The Unspeakable Crime of Andrea Yates'' ISBN 0-7434-6629-2, See also [http://www.suzanneomalley.com/ author website]
*[[Suzy Spencer|Spencer]], ''Breaking Point'' ISBN 0-312-93871-3, See also [http://www.suzyspencer.com/ author website]
*Vatz,R.E. “Will Justice Be Served on Andrea Yates?” (March, 2005) ''USA Today'' magazine

==External links==
{{Portal box|Biography|Houston}}
*[http://www.law.duke.edu/journals/djglp/downloads/gen10p61.pdf Timeline of Andrea Yates' Life and Trial] ([http://www.webcitation.org/67zO5Xee2 Archive])
*[http://www.law.duke.edu/shell/cite.pl?10+Duke+J.+Gender+L.+&amp;+Pol'y+1#H1N2 Who is Andrea Yates? A Short Story of Insanity, Deborah Denno]
*[http://www.crimelibrary.com/notorious_murders/women/andrea_yates/ CrimeLibrary review]
*[http://crime.about.com/od/current/p/andreayates.htm About.com profile]
*[http://abcnews.go.com/US/LegalCenter/Story?id=2245394&amp;page=2 Despite 'Not Guilty' Verdict, Doctor Who Examined Yates Is Unconvinced].&quot; ''[[ABC News]]''.
*[http://www.forensicpanel.com/yates.ppt PowerPoint evidence presented by Dr. Michael Welner during trial.]

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Yates, Andrea
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = American murderer
| DATE OF BIRTH     =July 2, 1964
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Yates, Andrea}}
[[Category:1964 births]]
[[Category:American mass murderers]]
[[Category:American people of German descent]]
[[Category:American people of Irish descent]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Overturned convictions in the United States]]
[[Category:Filicides]]
[[Category:People acquitted by reason of insanity]]
[[Category:People from Houston, Texas]]
[[Category:University of Houston alumni]]
[[Category:American murderers of children]]

[[fr:Andrea Yates]]
[[pt:Andrea Yates]]
[[ru:Йетс, Андреа]]
[[fi:Andrea Yates]]
[[uk:Андреа Єйтс]]</text>
      <sha1>pjy0dck83skhuawwnczia6p3n7aflx4</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
