<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Andy Kaufman</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>99881</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519677399</id>
      <parentid>518283477</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-25T01:37:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>190.44.158.38</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Illness and death */ removed sentence which makes absolutely no sense at all.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="40845">{{About|the entertainer|the former basketball player|Andy Kaufmann}}
{{Infobox person
| name = Andy Kaufman
| image = Akaufman1.jpg
| alt = 
| caption = Andy Kaufman as [[Latka Gravas]]
| birth_name = Andrew Geoffrey Kaufman
| birth_date = {{Birth date|1949|1|17|mf=y}}
| birth_place = [[New York City]], [[New York]], [[United States|U.S.]]
| death_date = {{Death date and age|1984|5|16|1949|1|17|mf=y}} 
| death_place =  [[West Hollywood]], [[California]], U.S.
| resting_place = Beth David Cemetery, [[Elmont, New York]]&lt;ref name=findagrave&gt;{{findagrave|1789}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| resting_place_coordinates = {{coord|40.6986|-73.7047|type:landmark|display=inline}}
| medium = 
| nationality = 
| occupation = Actor, [[performance art]]ist
| years_active= 1974–1984
| genre = 
| influences = 
| influenced = &quot;[[Man on the Moon (song)|Man on the Moon]]&quot; (1992 song), ''[[Man on the Moon (film)|Man on the Moon]]'' (1999 film)
| subject = 
| spouse = 
| television = As [[Latka Gravas]] in ''[[Taxi (TV series)|Taxi]]'' (1978–1983)
}}
'''Andrew Geoffrey &quot;Andy&quot; Kaufman''' (January 17, 1949&amp;nbsp;– May 16, 1984) was an American entertainer, actor and [[performance art]]ist. While often referred to as a [[comedian]], Kaufman did not consider himself to be one.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://movies.nytimes.com/person/37092/Andy-Kaufman/biography| work=[[All Media Guide]]| first=Sandra |last=Brennan | title= Full Biography |publisher=The New York Times | quote=I am not a comic, I have never told a joke...The comedian's promise is that he will go out there and make you laugh with him...My only promise is that I will try to entertain you as best I can....They say, 'Oh wow, Andy Kaufman, he's a really funny guy.' But I'm not trying to be funny. I just want to play with their heads.| accessdate=2012-04-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; He disdained telling jokes and engaging in [[comedy]] as it was traditionally understood, referring to himself instead as a &quot;song-and-dance man.&quot; Elaborate hoaxes and pranks were major elements of his career. His body of work maintains a cult following and he continues to be respected among comedians for his original material, performance style, and unflinching commitment to character.

==Early life==
Kaufman was born in [[New York City]], on January 17, 1949, the first son of Janice ([[married and maiden names|née]] Bernstein) and Stanley Kaufman. He grew up in a middle-class [[Jewish]] family,&lt;ref&gt;Bill Zehme, ''Lost in the Funhouse: The Life and Mind of Andy Kaufman'' (New York 2001)&lt;/ref&gt; in [[Great Neck, New York|Great Neck]], [[Long Island]], New York, and began performing at age nine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://andykaufman.jvlnet.com/realmotm.htm |title=&quot;The Real Man on the Moon Talks&quot; by Kaufman's father |publisher=Andykaufman.jvlnet.com |date= |accessdate=2010-02-10| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20100111075409/http://andykaufman.jvlnet.com/realmotm.htm| archivedate= 11 January 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; He attended the now defunct two-year [[Grahm Junior College]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.grahmjuniorcollege.org/alumni.htm List of Alumni] at college web page&lt;/ref&gt; in Boston, graduating in 1971. He then began performing stand-up comedy at various small clubs along the [[East coast of the United States|East Coast]].

==Career==
===Foreign Man and Mighty Mouse===
Kaufman first caught major attention with a character known as Foreign Man, who claimed to be from Caspiar (a fictional island in the [[Caspian Sea]]) and would appear on the stage of [[comedy club]]s to play a recording of the theme from the ''[[Mighty Mouse]]'' cartoon show and sing only the chorus.&lt;ref name=&quot;cnn2012&quot;/&gt; He would proceed to tell a few jokes and perform a number of [[impersonator|impersonations]] such as television character [[Archie Bunker]] or President [[Richard Nixon]]. Some variations of this performance were broadcast in the first season of ''[[Saturday Night Live]]''; the Mighty Mouse number was featured in the October 11, 1975 premiere, while the joke-telling and Bunker impression were included in the November 8 broadcast that same fall.&lt;ref name=&quot;snl-s1&quot;&gt;''SNL: The complete first season, 1975-1976.'' DVD recording.&lt;/ref&gt;

Foreign Man would often try to impersonate a whole series of different celebrities, with the comedy arising from Foreign Man's obvious ineptitude at impersonation. For example,{{cn|date=April 2012}} in his fake accent Kaufman would say to the audience, &quot;I would like to imitate [[Jimmy Carter|Meester Carter]], de President of de United States&quot;, and then in the same voice, &quot;Hello, I am Meester Carter, de President of de United States. T'ank you veddy much.&quot; At some point in the performance, usually when the audience were entirely used to Foreign Man's inability to perform a single convincing impression, Foreign Man would announce, &quot;And now I would like to imitate the [[Elvis Presley]],&quot; turn around, take off his jacket, slick his hair back, and launch into an unexpectedly credible [[Elvis Presley]] impersonation which Presley himself described as his favorite.&lt;ref&gt;[http://movies.yahoo.com/movie/contributor/1800018063/bio Andy Kaufman] at [[Yahoo!]] Movies&lt;/ref&gt; Like Presley, he would take off his leather jacket and throw it into the audience, but Kaufman would then immediately ask for it back again. After, he would take a simple bow and say in his Foreign Man voice, &quot;T'ank you veddy much!&quot;

===Latka===
{{Main|Latka Gravas}}

Kaufman first used his Foreign Man character in nightclubs in the early 1970's, often to tell jokes incorrectly and do weak imitations of famous people before bursting into his expert Elvis Presley imitation.  The character was then changed into Latka Gravas for the [[American Broadcasting Company]] (ABC)'s ''[[Taxi (TV series)|Taxi]]'' [[Situation comedy|sitcom]], appearing in 79 of 114 episodes from 1978 to 1983.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0077089/ ''Taxi''] from IMDb&lt;/ref&gt; The producers of ''Taxi'' had seen Andy's Foreign Man act and, according to producer [[Ed Weinberger]], &quot;We weren't considering Andy for the show before we saw him. Then we wrote a part for him.&quot; [[Bob Zmuda]] confirms this: &quot;They basically were buying Andy's Foreign Man character for the ''Taxi'' character Latka.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bluedonut.com/ak.htm &quot;Andy Kaufman Oral History&quot;], interviews with Don Steinberg, originally published in short form in ''GQ Magazine,'' December 1999.&lt;/ref&gt; Andy's long-time manager [[George Shapiro]] encouraged Andy to take the gig. &quot;My feeling was that it would be a nice boost for his career...and he would be playing a character that he knew very well, the Foreign Man—this particular character speaks poor English in ''Taxi'' and his name is Latka Gravas.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in ''Lost in the Funhouse: The Life and Mind of Andy Kaufman'' by Bill Zehme (2001), p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Saturday Night Live]]'' creator [[Lorne Michaels]] said of the announcement: &quot;When he agreed to a situation comedy, we were stunned. We couldn’t understand why in the world. Because he was Andy Kaufman. Going from being that far out of the mainstream to being ground zero of it. Not that ''Taxi'' isn’t a good show. But in the pure world of status, he was regarded as a genius. So for a genius to be the 4th lead in a situation comedy was not, at the time, seen to be an act of genius.&quot;

Kaufman disliked sitcoms and was not thrilled with the idea of being in one.&lt;ref&gt;Lost in the Funhouse: The Life and Mind of Andy Kaufman, Bill Zehme (ISBN 0385333722)&lt;/ref&gt; In order to allow Kaufman to demonstrate some comedic range, his character was given [[multiple personality disorder]], which allowed Kaufman to randomly portray other characters. In one episode of ''Taxi'', Kaufman's character came down with a condition which made him act like Alex Reiger, the main character played by [[Judd Hirsch]]. Another such recurring character played by Kaufman was the womanizing Vic Ferrari. His role led to two [[Golden Globe Award|Golden Globe]] nominations, in 1979 and 1981.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0001412/awards Andy Kaufman awards] from IMDb&lt;/ref&gt;

''Taxi'' was an award-winning show with a large audience and Kaufman was widely recognized as Latka. On some occasions, audiences would show up to one of Kaufman's stage performances expecting to see him perform as Latka, and heckling him with demands when he did not. Kaufman would punish these audiences with the announcement that he was going to read the novel ''[[The Great Gatsby]]'' by [[F. Scott Fitzgerald]] to them. The audience would laugh at this, not realizing that he was serious, and Kaufman would proceed to read the book to them, continuing despite audience members' departure.&lt;ref name=&quot;cnn2012&quot;/&gt; At a certain point, he would ask the audience if they wanted him to keep reading, or play a record. When the audience chose to hear the record, the record he cued up was a recording of him continuing to read ''The Great Gatsby'' from where he had left off.

===Tony Clifton===
{{Main|Tony Clifton}}
{{unreferenced section|date=April 2012}}
Another well-known Kaufman character is Tony Clifton, an audience-abusing [[lounge singer]] who began opening for Kaufman at comedy clubs and eventually even performed concerts on his own around the country. Sometimes it was Kaufman performing as Clifton, sometimes it was his brother Michael or his friend Bob Zmuda. For a brief time, it was unclear to some that Clifton was not a real person. News programs interviewed Clifton as Kaufman's opening act, with the mood turning ugly whenever Kaufman's name came up. Kaufman, Clifton insisted, was attempting to ruin Clifton's &quot;good name&quot; in order to make money and get famous.

As a requirement for Kaufman accepting the offer to star on ''Taxi'', he insisted that Clifton be hired for a guest role on the show as if he were a real person, not a character. After throwing a tantrum on the set, Clifton was fired and escorted off of the studio lot by security guards. Much to Kaufman's delight, this incident was reported in the local newspapers. [[Paramount Television]] and producers [[James L. Brooks]] and [[Stan Daniels]] later released a statement that said that although Clifton was &quot;no longer welcome on the set&quot;, his friend Andy Kaufman would continue in his role as Latka, which he did until the show ended its run in 1983.

===Carnegie Hall show===
At the beginning of an April 1979 performance at New York's [[Carnegie Hall]], Kaufman invited his &quot;grandmother&quot; to watch the show from a chair he had placed at the side of the stage. At the end of the show, she stood up, took her mask off and revealed to the audience that she was actually [[comedian]] [[Robin Williams]] in disguise. Kaufman also had an elderly woman (named Eleanor Cody Gould) appear to have a [[heart attack]] and die on stage, at which point he reappeared on stage wearing a [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]] [[headdress]] and performed a dance over her body, seeming to revive her.

The performance is most famous for Kaufman ending the show by actually taking the entire audience, in twenty-four buses, out for milk and cookies. He invited anyone interested to meet him on the [[Staten Island Ferry]] the next morning, where the show continued. This kind of [[performance art]] was a hallmark of Kaufman's career. This was depicted in the biopic ''[[Man on the Moon (film)|Man on the Moon]]''; however, in the movie, it takes place after Kaufman was diagnosed with [[cancer]], when in reality, it took place nearly four years earlier.

===''Andy's Funhouse''===	
The ''Taxi'' deal with [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] included giving Kaufman a television special/pilot. He came up with ''Andy's Funhouse'', based on an old routine he had developed while in junior college. The special was taped in 1977 but did not air until August 1979, on ABC.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0228013/ ''Andy's Funhouse''] from IMDb&lt;/ref&gt; It featured most of Andy's famous gags, including Foreign Man/Latka and his Elvis Presley impersonation, as well as a host of unique segments (including a special appearance by children's television character [[Howdy Doody]] and the &quot;Has-been Corner&quot;). There also was a segment that included fake television screen static as part of the gag, which ABC executives were not comfortable with, fearing that viewers would mistake the static for broadcast problems and would change the channel—which was the comic element Kaufman wanted to present. ''Andy's Funhouse'' was written by Kaufman, Zmuda, and Mel Sherer, with music by Kaufman.

In 1980 a very similar looking show to ''Funhouse ''would be filmed for [[Public Broadcasting Service]] (PBS)'s [[Soundstage (TV series)|SoundStage]] program, called the ''The Andy Kaufman Show''. It would feature a [[peanut gallery]] like Funhouse and is often confused with ''Andy's Funhouse''. The show opens right in the middle of an interview Kaufman is doing in which he is laughing hysterically, and then he proceeds to thank the audience for watching and the credits roll. After this, opening credits do come on and the show has its &quot;proper&quot; beginning. This show is easy to confuse with ''Andy's Funhouse'' as they both feature &quot;The Has-Been Corner&quot; and Kaufman wears his &quot;I Love Grandma&quot; shirt in both shows among other similarities.

===The ''Fridays'' incidents===
In 1981, Kaufman made three appearances on ''[[Fridays (ABC TV series)|Fridays]]'', a [[variety show]] on [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] that was similar to ''[[Saturday Night Live]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0080219/ Kaufman on ''Fridays''] from IMDb&lt;/ref&gt; Kaufman's first appearance on the show proved to be memorable. During a sketch about four people out on a dinner date who excuse themselves to the restroom to smoke [[cannabis (drug)|marijuana]], Kaufman broke character and refused to say his lines.

In response, cast member [[Michael Richards]] walked off camera and returned with a set of cue cards and dumped them on the table in front of Kaufman. Andy responded by splashing Richards with water. Co-producer [[Jack Burns]] stormed onto the stage, leading to a brawl on camera before the show abruptly cut away to commercial.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.funnyordie.com/videos/544255131b |title=Andy Kaufman on Fridays from FridaysFan |publisher=Funnyordie.com |date= |accessdate=2010-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was later revealed that this incident was a practical joke which was known to Richards, associate producer Burns and Kaufman but no one else on the cast or crew.&lt;ref&gt;[http://archive.firstamendmentcenter.org/about.aspx?id=12083 &quot;Michael Richards 'Speaking Freely' transcript&quot;, Recorded Feb. 28, 2002, in Aspen, Colorado]&lt;/ref&gt;

In continuation of the joke, Kaufman appeared the following week in a videotaped apology to the home viewers. Later that year, Kaufman returned to host ''Fridays.'' At one point in the show, he invited a ''[[Lawrence Welk Show]]'' gospel and standards singer, [[Kathie Sullivan]], on stage to sing a few gospel songs with him and announced that the two were engaged to be married, then talked to the audience about his newfound faith in [[Jesus]] (Kaufman was Jewish). That was also a hoax. Later, following a sketch about a drug-abusing pharmacist, Kaufman was supposed to introduce the band [[The Pretenders]]. Instead of introducing the band, he delivered a nervous speech about the harmfulness of drugs while the band stood behind him ready to play. After his speech, he informed the audience that he had talked for too long and had to go to a commercial.

===Professional wrestling===
Kaufman grew up admiring the world of [[professional wrestling]].{{cn|date=April 2012}} Inspired by the theatricality of ''[[kayfabe]]'', the staged nature of the sport, and his own tendency to form elaborate hoaxes, Kaufman began [[Intergender wrestling|wrestling women]] during his act and was the self-proclaimed &quot;Inter-Gender Wrestling Champion of the World&quot;, taking on an aggressive and ridiculous personality based upon the characters invented by professional wrestlers. He offered a $1,000 prize to any woman who could pin him. He employed his friend, the performance artist [[Laurie Anderson]] as a stooge in this act for a while.

Kaufman initially approached the head of the [[World Wrestling Federation]], [[Vince McMahon Sr.]] about bringing his act to the New York wrestling territory.  McMahon dismissed Kaufman's idea as the elder McMahon was not about to bring &quot;show business&quot; into his Pro Wrestling society. Kaufman had by then developed a friendship with Wrestling magazine reporter/photographer Bill Apter.  After many discussions about Andy wanting to be in the Pro Wrestling business, Apter called Memphis' iconic Jerry Lawler and introduced him to Kaufman by telephone from Apter's apartment in Queens, New York. That put the key in the ignition and as they say -- &quot;the rest is history.&quot;{{citation needed|date=June 2012}} The battles between Kaufman and Lawler became legend and was really the first &quot;sports entertainment&quot; angle that became known worldwide and is being seen even today on TV stations such as Comedy Central.

Later, after a challenge from professional wrestler [[Jerry Lawler|Jerry &quot;The King&quot; Lawler]], Kaufman would step into the ring (in the [[Continental Wrestling Association|Memphis wrestling circuit]]) with a man—Lawler himself.&lt;ref name=&quot;cnn2012&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url= http://www.cnn.com/2012/04/07/us/kaufman-lawler-wrestling-match/ | title=The Great Ruse: The comedic genius who rocked wrestling | first=Wayne|last= Drash | publisher=CNN | date=April 7, 2012| accessdate=2012-04-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kaufman taunted the whole city of Memphis, sending &quot;videos showing residents how to use soap&quot; and proclaiming it to be &quot;the nation's [[redneck]] capital.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;cnn2012&quot;/&gt; Their ongoing [[feud (professional wrestling)|feud]], often featuring [[Jimmy Hart]] and other [[heel (professional wrestling)|heels]] in Kaufman's corner, included a broken neck for Kaufman as a result of Lawler's [[piledriver (professional wrestling)|piledriver]] and a famous on-air fight on a 1982 episode of ''[[Late Night with David Letterman]]''. For some time after that, Kaufman appeared wearing a neck brace,&lt;ref name=&quot;cnn2012&quot;/&gt; insisting that his injuries were worse than they were. Kaufman would continue to defend the Inter-Gender Championship in the [[Mid-South Coliseum]] and offered an extra prize, other than the $1,000: that if he were pinned, the woman who pinned him would get to marry him and that Kaufman would also shave his head.&lt;ref name=&quot;klfeud2&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6p5KMZe8n0o | title=The Kaufman Lawler Feud: Chapter 2 - The Fourth One | date=January 13th, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kaufman and Lawler's famous feud and wrestling matches were later revealed to have been staged, or a &quot;[[List of professional wrestling terms#W|work]]&quot;, as the two were actually friends. The truth about it being a &quot;work&quot; was not disclosed until more than 10 years after Kaufman's death, when the Emmy-nominated documentary, ''A Comedy Salute to Andy Kaufman'', aired on [[NBC]] in 1995. Coincidentally, [[Jim Carrey]], the one who revealed the secret, later went on to play Kaufman in the [[1999 in film|1999 film]] ''[[Man on the Moon (film)|Man on the Moon]].'' In a 1997 interview with the ''Memphis Flyer'', Lawler claimed he had improvised during their first match and the ''Letterman'' incident. Although officials at [[St. Francis Hospital]]{{disambiguation needed|date=January 2012}} stated that Kaufman's neck injuries were real, in his 2002 biography ''It's Good to Be the King...Sometimes'', Lawler detailed how they came up with the [[List of professional wrestling terms#A|angle]] and kept it quiet. Even though Kaufman's injury was legitimate, the pair pretended that the injury was more severe than it was. He also said that Kaufman's explosion on ''Letterman'' was Kaufman's own idea, including when Lawler slapped Kaufman out of his chair.

Kaufman also appeared in the [[1983 in film|1983]] film ''[[My Breakfast with Blassie]]'' with professional wrestling personality [[&quot;Classy&quot; Freddie Blassie]], a parody of the art film ''[[My Dinner With Andre]].'' The film was directed by [[Johnny Legend]], who employed his sister Lynne Margulies as one of the girls who appears in the film. Margulies met Kaufman for the first time on camera, and they later became a couple, living together until Kaufman's death.

===Appearances===
Although Kaufman made a name for himself as a guest on [[NBC]]'s ''Saturday Night Live'', his first prime time appearances were several guest spots as the 'Foreign Man' on [[Dick Van Dyke]]'s variety show in 1976. He also appeared four times on ''[[The Tonight Show Starring Johnny Carson|The Tonight Show]]''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0055708/fullcredits ''Tonight Show''] from IMDb&lt;/ref&gt; from 1976–1978, three times on ''[[The Midnight Special (TV series)|The Midnight Special]]'' in 1972, 1977 and 1981.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0229907/fullcredits ''Midnight Special''] from IMDb&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1977 episode, Kaufman performed a song called &quot;I Trusted You&quot; (which features only those three words, repeated over and over, as lyrics), while in 1981 he is shown sitting in the audience during Tony Clifton's act (although it was obvious Kaufman was not in the audience during the sketch).

His ''SNL ''appearances started with the [[Saturday Night Live (season 1)|inaugural October 11, 1975 show]]; he made 16 ''SNL'' appearances in all,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0072562/fullcredits Kaufman on SNL] from IMDb&lt;/ref&gt; although his last two appearances were pre-taped.{{cn|date=April 2012}} He would do routines from his comedy act, such as the ''Mighty Mouse'' sing-along, Foreign Man character, the Elvis impersonation, etc. After he angered the audience with his female wrestling routine, in January 1983 Kaufman did make a pre-taped appearance (his 16th) on the show, where he asked the audience if he should ever appear on the show again, and said that he would honor the audience's decision and stay off the show if the vote was negative. ''[[Saturday Night Live|SNL]]'' ran a phone vote, and close to 195,544 people voted to &quot;Dump Andy&quot; and approximately 169,186 people voted to &quot;Keep Andy&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;passion_tally&quot;&gt;{{cite video |people=Alan Graham (producer)| date=2008-02-21|title=The Passion of Andy Kaufman|url=http://video.google.co.uk/videoplay?docid=-2545402202011032395|format=[[SWF]]|medium=Archive footage|publisher=Subterranean Cinema|accessdate=2008-03-20|time=2:20:00}}&lt;/ref&gt; so Kaufman did not appear &quot;live&quot; but ''Saturday Night Live'' did air a tape of him thanking the 169,186 people who had voted &quot;yes&quot; for him to appear again.

Though it was never made clear whether this was a gag, Kaufman did not appear on the show again. During the ''SNL'' episode with the Keep Andy/Dump Andy phone poll, many of the cast stated their admiration for Andy's work and read the &quot;Keep Andy&quot; number more clearly than the &quot;Dump Andy&quot; number.&lt;ref name=&quot;passion&quot;&gt;{{cite video |people=Alan Graham (producer)|date=2008-02-21|title=The Passion of Andy Kaufman| url= http://video.google.co.uk/videoplay?docid=-2545402202011032395|format=[[SWF]]|medium=Archive footage| publisher=Subterranean Cinema|accessdate=2008-03-20|time=2:10:55–2:20:33}}&lt;/ref&gt; After [[Eddie Murphy]] read both numbers, he said, &quot;Now Andy Kaufman is a friend of mine. Keep that in mind when you call. I don't want to have to punch nobody in America in the face.&quot; [[Mary Gross]] read the &quot;Dump Andy&quot; number at a rate so fast that audiences were unable to catch it.&lt;ref name=&quot;passion&quot; /&gt; The final tally was read by [[Gary Kroeger]] to a cheering audience. As the credits rolled, announcer [[Don Pardo]] said, &quot;This is Don Pardo saying, 'I voted for Andy Kaufman.'&quot;

Kaufman made a number of appearances on the daytime ''[[The David Letterman Show]]'' in 1980, and eleven appearances on ''[[Late Night with David Letterman]]'' in 1982-1983,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0083441/fullcredits ''Late Night with David Letterman''] from IMDb&lt;/ref&gt; including one where he claimed to be homeless and begged the audience for money and one where he talked about his adopted children, who turned out to be three fully-grown black men.{{cn|date=April 2012}}

He appeared twice on ''[[The Merv Griffin Show]]'' (1979–1980),&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0055691/fullcredits ''Merv Griffin Show''] from IMDb&lt;/ref&gt; and once, in 1978 as a participant, on ''[[The Dating Game]]''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0058795/fullcredits ''The Dating Game''] from IMDb&lt;/ref&gt; under an assumed name and as a supposedly real contestant. He also made numerous guest spots on other television programs hosted by or starring celebrities like [[Johnny Cash]] (1979 Christmas special), [[Dick Van Dyke]], [[Dinah Shore]], [[Rodney Dangerfield]], [[Cher]], [[Dean Martin]], [[Redd Foxx]], [[Mike Douglas]], [[Dick Clark]], and [[Joe Franklin]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0001412/ guest appearances] from IMDb&lt;/ref&gt;

He appeared in his first theatrical film ''[[God Told Me To]]'' in 1976, where he portrayed a murderous policeman. He also appeared in several others, including as a [[televangelist]] in the 1980 film ''[[In God We Tru$t]]''.

[[Laurie Anderson]] worked alongside Andy Kaufman for a time in 1970s, acting as a sort of straight woman in a number of his [[Manhattan]] and [[Coney Island]] performances. One of these performances included getting on a ride that people stand in and get spun around. After everyone was strapped in Kaufman would start saying how he did not want to be on the ride in a panicked tone and eventually cry. Anderson later described these performances in her 1995 album ''[[The Ugly One with the Jewels]]''.

At [[Park West (music venue)|Park West Theatre]] in Chicago on March 26, 1982, Kaufman performed [[stage hypnosis]] where he induced local DJ [[Steve Dahl]] to urinate while sitting in a large box. Other staged inductions included Bob Zmuda's childhood friend Joe Troiani mimicking the behavior of a pig and long-time friend Bill Karmia dressed as a police officer arresting Kaufman for inducing public nudity with a woman he had hypnotized.

==Personal life==
Kaufman never married. He was survived by his father&lt;ref name=&quot;TSGDeathCert&quot;/&gt; and daughter, Maria Colonna, who was born in 1969 out of wedlock with a high-school girlfriend of Kaufman's, but later placed for adoption. Colonna learned in 1992 that she was the daughter of Andy Kaufman when she traced her biological roots.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url =http://radio.villagevoice.com/1999-11-09/long-island-voice/waking-andy-kaufman/4 | title = ''Waking Andy Kaufman'' | work = The Village Voice | date = 9 November 1999}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On December 5, 1969, while in college, Kaufman learned [[Transcendental Meditation]].&lt;ref name=aktime/&gt; According to a [[British Broadcasting Company|BBC]] article, Kaufman used Transcendental Meditation to build confidence and take his act to comedy clubs. For the rest of his life Kaufman meditated and performed [[yoga]] three hours a day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/dna/h2g2/A1043173 |title=BBC online, June 25, 2003 |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2010-02-10| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20100126005056/http://www.bbc.co.uk/dna/h2g2/A1043173| archivedate= 26 January 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; He trained as a teacher of Transcendental Meditation in [[Majorca]], Spain from February to June, 1971.&lt;ref name=aktime&gt;{{cite web| url= http://andykaufman.jvlnet.com/aktime.htm |title=The Life and Mind of Andy Kaufman |publisher= Andykaufman.jvlnet.com |date= |accessdate=2010-02-10| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20100110062153/http://andykaufman.jvlnet.com/aktime.htm| archivedate= 10 January 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Illness and death==
At [[Thanksgiving]] dinner with his family on [[Long Island, New York]] in November 1983, several family members grew concerned over Kaufman's persistent [[coughing]] during the dinner and openly expressed worry about it. Kaufman claimed to them that he had had the cough for nearly a month, but also claimed that an initial visit to his doctor told him that nothing was wrong. After returning to [[Los Angeles]], Kaufman consulted a [[physician]], after which he checked himself into [[Cedars-Sinai]] Hospital for a series of medical tests.  A few days later, he was diagnosed with a rare type of [[lung cancer]].

After audiences were shocked by his gaunt appearance during his performances in January 1984, Kaufman acknowledged having an unspecified illness, which he hoped to cure with &quot;[[natural medicine]]&quot; including an all-fruit-and-vegetables diet, among other measures. Kaufman received palliative [[radiotherapy]], but by then the cancer had rapidly spread from his lungs to his brain. His last resort was &quot;[[psychic surgery]]&quot;, a pseudo-procedure performed in [[Baguio]], [[Philippines]], in March 1984. Kaufman died in a hospital in [[West Hollywood]] on May 16, 1984&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://vitals.rootsweb.com/ca/death/search.cgi |title=California Death Index |publisher=Vitals.rootsweb.com |date= |accessdate=2010-02-10| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20100115050039/http://vitals.rootsweb.com/ca/death/search.cgi| archivedate= 15 January 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; of [[renal failure|kidney failure]], caused by [[metastasized]] large cell [[carcinoma]], and was laid to rest in the Beth David Cemetery in [[Elmont, New York]] ([[Long Island]]). He was 35 years old. Because he kept the true nature of his illness a secret — almost until the day he died — fans have, over the years, doubted Kaufman's death, thinking that he staged it as the ultimate Andy Kaufman stunt.

Kaufman allegedly told many people—including Bob Zmuda—that he wished to fake his own death prior to his actual death. This has caused some fans to believe Kaufman is still alive.&lt;ref&gt;Andy Kaufman Revealed! by Bob Zmuda&lt;/ref&gt; Kaufman himself purportedly claimed that if he were to fake his death, he would return 20 years later, which would have been in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url =http://www.times.com/books/99/09/26/bib/990926.rv103930.html | title = ''Andy Kaufman Revealed!'' | work = New York Times Online:book review | date = 26 September 1999}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 1999 Jim Carrey film ''[[Man on the Moon (film)|Man on the Moon]]'' leaves the question [[open-ended question|open-ended]]. &quot;Tony Clifton&quot; performed a year after Kaufman's death at [[The Comedy Store]] benefit in Kaufman's honor, with members of his entourage in attendance. Bob Zmuda has acknowledged &quot;[[death hoax]]&quot; rumors over the years quite [[tongue-in-cheek]], admitting that Kaufman and he had discussed faking his death at times and that he seemed &quot;obsessed with the idea&quot;, but he maintains the opinion that Kaufman truly did die and his death was not faked. Bob Zmuda claims he does not think he would be cruel enough to go this long without making contact with his family if he were still alive. His official website states that his death was not a hoax.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://andykaufman.jvlnet.com/final.htm |title=The Last(?) Days of Andy Kaufman |publisher=Andykaufman.jvlnet.com |date= |accessdate=2011-09-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 1990s, &quot;Tony Clifton&quot; made several appearances at LA nightclubs, prompting speculation that perhaps Kaufman was still alive and working under the makeup. Jim Carrey stated on the NBC special ''Comedy Salute to Andy Kaufman'' that the Clifton character was in fact Bob Zmuda which had been passed onto him by Kaufman while he was still alive. Kaufman's death certificate is on file with the [[Los Angeles County]] Department of Health Services and is also available on the website [[The Smoking Gun]].&lt;ref name=&quot;TSGDeathCert&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thesmokinggun.com/archive/kaufmandeath1.html |title=Kaufman death certificate on |publisher=[[The Smoking Gun]]|date=1984-05-16 |accessdate=2010-02-10| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20100207152440/http://www.thesmokinggun.com/archive/kaufmandeath1.html| archivedate= 7 February 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Filmography==
{{unreferenced section|date=April 2012}}
===Acting===
{{div col}}
*''Van Dyke and Company'' (1975) (TV)
*''Van Dyke and Company'' (1976) TV Series... Regular
*''[[God Told Me To]]'' (1976) .... Police Officer
*''[[Stick Around (TV)|Stick Around]]'' (1977) (TV) .... Andy, the Robot
*''[[Taxi (TV series)|Taxi]]'' (1978) TV Series .... Latka Gravas/Vic Ferrari
*''The Andy Kaufman Special (a.k.a. Andy's Funhouse)'' (1979) (TV) (also as Tony Clifton)...Latka Gravas/Tony Clifton
*''Cher... and Other Fantasies'' (1979) (TV)
*''[[Andy Kaufman Plays Carnegie Hall]]'' (1980) (TV)...Tony Clifton
*''[[In God We Tru$t]]'' (1980) .... Armageddon T. Thunderbird
*''[[The Midnight Special (television)|The Midnight Special]]'' (1981) TV Series... Host
*''[[Heartbeeps]]'' (1981) .... Val
*''Catch a Rising Star's 10th Anniversary'' (1982) (TV)
*''The Fantastic Miss Piggy Show'' (1982) (TV) .... Tony Clifton
*''The Andy Kaufman Show'' (1980) (TV) ... Host/Elvis
*''[[My Breakfast with Blassie]]'' (1983)
*''Elayne Boosler: Party of One'' (1985) (TV) (voice)
*''[[I'm From Hollywood]]'' (1989)
{{div col end}}
===Writing===
*''The Andy Kaufman Special aka Andy's Funhouse'' (Filmed 1977 as Pilot, Aired on ABC in 1979) (TV)
*''The Andy Kaufman Show'' (filmed in 1980 for PBS's Soundstage) (TV)
*''[[Andy Kaufman Plays Carnegie Hall]]'' (1980) (V)
*''[[I'm From Hollywood]]'' (1989) (uncredited)
*''GOD...and other plays'' (1999)
*''The Huey Williams Story'' (1999)
*''Poetry and Stories'' (2000)

===Composing===
*''[[Man on the Moon (soundtrack)|Man on the Moon]]'' (1999) (song &quot;Oh, The Cow Goes Moo&quot;)

===Producing===
*''The Andy Kaufman Special'' (1979) (TV) (producer)

===Notable TV guest appearances===
{{div col}}
*''[[The Dean Martin Comedy World]]'' 6 June 1974
*''[[The Joe Franklin Show]]'' 20 June 1974
*''[[Saturday Night Live]]'' (episode # 1.1) 11 October 1975 .... miming [[Mighty Mouse]] theme
*''[[Saturday Night Live]]'' (episode # 1.3) 25 October 1975 .... miming [[Pop Goes The Weasel]]
*''[[Saturday Night Live]]'' (episode # 1.4) 8 November 1975 .... as Foreign Man
*''[[Saturday Night Live]]'' (episode # 1.15) 28 February 1976 .... miming [[Old MacDonald Had a Farm]] with audience members
*''[[The Tonight Show Starring Johnny Carson]]'' 23 June 1976
*''[[Saturday Night Live]]'' (episode # 2.11) 15 January 1977 .... as Foreign Man/Elvis
*''[[Dinah!]]'' 17 January 1977 .... Foreign Man
*''[[The Tonight Show Starring Johnny Carson]]'' 21 January 1977
*''[[The Tonight Show Starring Johnny Carson]]'' 3 March 1977
*''[[The Hollywood Squares]]'' 15 August 1977
*''[[Redd Foxx]]'' 15 September 1977
*''[[Saturday Night Live]]'' (episode # 3.3) 15 October 1977 .... sings [[Oklahoma (song)|Oklahoma]], &quot;Oh, The Cow Goes Moo&quot;, Elvis
*''[[Saturday Night Live]]'' (episode # 3.7) 10 December 1977
*''[[The Tonight Show Starring Johnny Carson]]'' 20 February 1978
*''[[Saturday Night Live]]'' (episode # 3.13) 11 March 1978 ... reads [[The Great Gatsby]]
*''[[The Mike Douglas Show]]'' 11 April 1978
*''[[The Dating Game]]'' (as Baji Kimran) 21 November 1978 .... - Participant
*''Live Wednesday'' 29 November 1978
*''[[Saturday Night Live]]'' (episode # 4.13) 24 February 1979 .... sings &quot;Yodelling Mad&quot;
*''[[The Tomorrow Show]]'' 20 August 1979
*''[[Saturday Night Live]]'' (episode # 5.2) 20 October 1979
*''[[Saturday Night Live]]'' (uncredited) (episode # 5.5) 17 November 1979
*''The Johnny Cash Christmas Special 1979'' 6 December 1979
*''[[The Merv Griffin Show]]'' 13 December 1979
*''[[Saturday Night Live]]'' (episode # 5.8) 22 December 1979
*''[[The Merv Griffin Show]]'' 25 January 1980
*''The Morning show With David Letterman'' 24 June 1980
*''[[The Midnight Special (television)|The Midnight Special]]'' 23 January 1981
*''Fridays'' (episode # 2.20) 20 February 1981 .... Guest Host
*''Fridays'' playing &quot;Himself&amp;nbsp;– Recorded Apology&quot; (episode # 2.21) 27 February 1981
*''Fridays'' playing &quot;Guest Host&quot; (episode # 3.1) 18 September 1981 .... Guest Host
*''[[Good Morning America]]'' 28 October 1981
*''[[Saturday Night Live]]'' (episode # 7.10) 30 January 1982 .... as Elvis
*''[[Late Night with David Letterman]]'' 17 February 1982
*''[[Late Night with David Letterman]]'' 18 February 1982
*''[[Late Night with David Letterman]]'' 30 March 1982
*''[[Late Night with David Letterman]]'' 1 April 1982
*''[[Good Morning America]]'' 14 April 1982
*''The John Davidson Show'' 15 April 1982
*''Hour Magazine'' 7 May 1982
*''[[Saturday Night Live]]'' (episode # 7.19) 15 May 1982 .... as Himself
*''[[Late Night with David Letterman]]'' 17 May 1982
*''[[Late Night with David Letterman]]'' 28 July 1982
*''[[Saturday Night Live]]'' (episode # 8.5) 30 October 1982
*''[[Late Night with David Letterman]]'' 17 November 1982
*''[[Late Night with David Letterman]]'' 7 January 1983
*''[[Late Night with David Letterman]]'' 23 February 1983
*''[[Late Night with David Letterman]]'' 22 September 1983
*''[[Late Night with David Letterman]]'' 17 November 1983
*''Rodney Dangerfield: I Can't Take It No More'' (As Dr. Vinnie Boombatz) 29 November 1983 .... Guest Appearance
*''The Top'' January 26, 1984 .... Kaufman's last television appearance{{cn|date=April 2012}}
{{div col end}}

==Legacy==
[[Jim Carrey]] portrayed Kaufman in the 1999 biopic film ''[[Man on the Moon (film)|Man on the Moon]]'', directed by [[Miloš Forman]]. The film took its title from the band [[R.E.M.]] [[Man on the Moon (song)|song of the same name]], which also mentions Kaufman's name. Comedian [[Richard Lewis (comedian)|Richard Lewis]] in ''A Comedy Salute to Andy Kaufman'' said of him: &quot;No one has ever done what Andy did, and did it as well, and no one will ever. Because he did it first. So did [[Buster Keaton]], so did Andy.&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite episode|title=A Comedy Salute to Andy Kaufman|airdate= 29 March 1995|network=NBC}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Carl Reiner]] recalled his distinction in the comedy world: &quot;Did Andy influence comedy? No. Because nobody's doing what he did. [[Jim Carrey]] was influenced—not to do what Andy did, but to follow his own drummer. I think Andy did that for a lot of people. Follow your own drumbeat. You didn't have to go up there and say 'take my wife, please.' You could do anything that struck you as entertaining. It gave people freedom to be themselves.&quot;

==References==
{{Film IMDb refimprove|date=April 2012}}
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Further reading==
* Zehme, Bill (2001), ''Lost in the Funhouse: The Life and Mind of Andy Kaufman'', Delta Books. ISBN 0-385-33372-2
* Zmuda, Bob (2001), ''Andy Kaufman Revealed!: Best Friend Tells All'', Back Bay Books. ISBN 0-316-61098-4
* Hecht, Julie (2001), ''Was This Man a Genius? Talks with Andy Kaufman'', Vintage Books. ISBN 0-375-50457-5

==External links==
*{{IMDb name|0001412}}
*[http://cinemavirtualis.com/tony.hmtl The Tony Clifton Story] the &quot;lost&quot; Kaufman screenplay
*{{Find a Grave|1789}}


{{Andy Kaufman}}

{{Authority control|VIAF=29743064}}
{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME = Kaufman, Andy
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES = Kaufman, Andrew Geoffrey
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = American comic actor and performance artist
| DATE OF BIRTH = 17 January 1949
| PLACE OF BIRTH = New York City, New York, [[United States|U.S.]]
| DATE OF DEATH = 16 May 1984
| PLACE OF DEATH = Los Angeles, California, [[United States|U.S.]]
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Kaufman, Andy}}
[[Category:1949 births]]
[[Category:1984 deaths]]
[[Category:American Jews]]
[[Category:American performance artists]]
[[Category:American professional wrestlers]]
[[Category:American stand-up comedians]]
[[Category:American vegetarians]]
[[Category:Cancer deaths in California]]
[[Category:Deaths from lung cancer]]
[[Category:Elvis impersonators]]
[[Category:Jewish actors]]
[[Category:Jewish comedians]]
[[Category:People from Long Island]]
[[Category:Transcendental Meditation practitioners]]
[[Category:American television actors]]
[[Category:The First Family (professional wrestling) members]]
[[Category:Pranksters]]
[[Category:American film actors]]
[[Category:Actors from New York City]]

[[cs:Andy Kaufman]]
[[da:Andy Kaufman]]
[[de:Andy Kaufman]]
[[el:Άντι Κάουφμαν]]
[[es:Andy Kaufman]]
[[fa:اندی کافمن]]
[[fr:Andy Kaufman]]
[[hr:Andy Kaufman]]
[[it:Andy Kaufman]]
[[he:אנדי קאופמן]]
[[lb:Andy Kaufman]]
[[lt:Andy Kaufman]]
[[jbo:andis. kafmen]]
[[hu:Andy Kaufman]]
[[nl:Andy Kaufman]]
[[ja:アンディ・カウフマン]]
[[no:Andy Kaufman]]
[[pl:Andy Kaufman]]
[[pt:Andy Kaufman]]
[[ru:Кауфман, Энди]]
[[sk:Andrew Geoffrey Kaufman]]
[[sh:Andy Kaufman]]
[[fi:Andy Kaufman]]
[[sv:Andy Kaufman]]
[[tr:Andy Kaufman]]</text>
      <sha1>bjbw660llr88uv6h7f9jgz0lqevrjt0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
