<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Augusto Pinochet</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18933396</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521059375</id>
      <parentid>520438986</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T14:52:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Binksternet</username>
        <id>4967956</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted to revision 520275778 by Adville: rv changes by banned editor Zdragon12's sockpuppet Kabulbuddha. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="89808">{{Spanish name|first=Pinochet|second=Ugarte}}
{{Infobox officeholder
|name               = Augusto Pinochet
|image              = Augusto Pinochet - 1995.jpg
|imagesize          = 200px
|smallimage         = 
|alt                = 
|caption            = Pinochet in 1995
|order              = 
|office             = [[President of Chile]]
|term_start         = 17 December 1974
|term_end           = 11 March 1990
|predecessor        = [[Salvador Allende]]
|successor          = [[Patricio Aylwin]]
|order2             = 
|office2            = President of the&lt;br&gt;[[Government Junta of Chile (1973)|Government Junta of Chile]]
|term_start2        = 11 September 1973
|term_end2          = 11 March 1981
|predecessor2       = ''Office established''
|successor2         = [[José Toribio Merino]]
|order3             = 
|office3            = 58th [[List of commanders-in-chief of the Chilean Army|Commander-in-Chief of the Chilean Army]]
|term_start3        = 23 August 1973
|term_end3          = 11 March 1998
|predecessor3       = [[Carlos Prats]]
|successor3         = [[Ricardo Izurieta]]
|birth_date         = {{birth date|1915|11|25|df=y}}
|birth_place        = [[Valparaíso]], [[Chile]]
|death_date         = {{death date and age|2006|12|10|1915|11|25|df=y}}
|death_place        = [[Santiago]], [[Chile]]
|birthname          = Augusto José Ramón Pinochet Ugarte
|nationality        = Chilean
|spouse             = [[Lucía Hiriart]] &lt;small&gt;(1943-2006)&lt;/small&gt;
|children           = [[Lucía Pinochet|Inés Lucía Pinochet]]&lt;br&gt;María Verónica Pinochet&lt;br&gt;Jacqueline Marie Pinochet&lt;br&gt;Augusto Osvaldo Pinochet&lt;br&gt;Marco Antonio Pinochet
|alma_mater         = Chilean War Academy
|occupation         = Military &amp; Politician
|profession         = Soldier
|religion           = [[Catholic Church|Roman Catholic]]
|signature          = Signature of Augusto Pinochet.svg
|signature_alt      = 
|website            = 
|footnotes          = 
|blank1             = 
&lt;!--Military service--&gt;
|nickname           = 
|allegiance         = {{flag|Chile}}
|branch             = [[Chilean Army]]
|serviceyears       = 1931 - 1998
|rank               = Captain General
|unit               = &quot;Chacabuco&quot; Regiment&lt;br&gt;&quot;Maipo&quot; Regiment&lt;br&gt;&quot;Carampangue&quot; Regiment&lt;br&gt;&quot;Rancagua&quot; Regiment&lt;br&gt;1st Army Division
|commands           = &quot;Esmeralda&quot; Regiment&lt;br&gt;2nd Army Division&lt;br&gt;6th Army Division&lt;br&gt;Santiago Army Garrison&lt;br&gt;[[Chilean Army]]
|battles            = none
|awards             = 
|military_blank1    = 
|military_data1     = 
|military_blank2    = 
|military_data2     = 
|military_blank3    = 
|military_data3     = 
|military_blank4    = 
|military_data4     = 
|military_blank5    = 
|military_data5     = 
}}

'''Augusto José Ramón Pinochet Ugarte''', more commonly known as '''Augusto Pinochet''' ({{IPA-es|auˈɣusto pinoˈtʃet}}),{{#tag:ref|Spanish pronunciation: {{IPA|[pinoˈtʃet]}}; [[North American English]]: {{IPA|/piːnoʊˈtʃɛt/}}, [[Commonwealth English]]: {{IPA|/ˈpiːnoʊʃeɪ/}}). Pinochet pronounced his name with a silent ''t'', though it is not uncommon for the {{IPA|/t/}} to be pronounced by Spanish-speaking Chileans.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
|title=Longman pronunciation dictionary
|first=John C.
|last= Wells
|publisher=Longman
|location=Harlow, England
|year=1990
|isbn=0-582-05383-8
|page=537
}} entry &quot;Pinochet&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; |group=note}} (25 November 1915 – 10 December 2006) was an army general and dictator of Chile from 1973 until transferring power to a [[Patricio Aylwin|democratically elected president]] in 1990. He was the [[commander-in-chief]] of the Chilean army from 1973 to 1998 and president of the [[Government Junta of Chile (1973)|Government Junta of Chile]] from 1973 to 1981.&lt;ref name=&quot;return&quot;/&gt; He assumed power in a [[1973 Chilean coup d'état|coup d'état on 11 September 1973]] that overthrew the Government of [[Salvador Allende]].

By early 1972, Pinochet was General Chief of Staff of the Army. In 23 August 1973 he was promoted to Commander-in-Chief of the Chilean Army by president [[Salvador Allende]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CBS&quot; /&gt; On 11 September 1973 Pinochet joined a [[coup d'état]] which overthrew Allende's [[election|elected]] [[socialist]] government. In December 1974 the [[military junta]] appointed Pinochet as President by a joint [[decree]], with which Air Force General [[Gustavo Leigh]] disagreed.&lt;ref&gt;Cavallo, Ascanio et al. ''La Historia Oculta del Régimen Militar'', Grijalbo, Santiago, 1997.&lt;/ref&gt; From the beginning, the government implemented harsh measures against its political opponents.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/1999/jan/15/pinochet.chile1 |title=Chile under Pinochet – a chronology &amp;#124; World news &amp;#124; guardian.co.uk |publisher=Guardian |date= 24 March 1999|accessdate=10 March 2010 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to various reports and investigations 1,200–3,200 people were killed, up to 80,000 were [[List of concentration and internment camps#Chile|interned]], and up to 30,000 were tortured by his regime including women and children.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usip.org/publications/truth-commission-chile-90 English translation] of the [[Rettig Report]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.comisiontortura.cl/inicio/index.php 2004 Commission on Torture] ([[Valech Report]]) {{es icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;latinamericanstudies.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.latinamericanstudies.org/human-rights/false-reports.htm |title=Chile to sue over false reports of Pinochet-era missing. The Age. 30 December 2008 |publisher=Latinamericanstudies.org |date= |accessdate=10 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Under the influence of the free market-oriented [[neoliberalism|neoliberal]] [[Chicago Boys]], the [[military government of Chile (1973&amp;ndash;1990)|new government]] also implemented economic reforms, including currency stabilization, tariff cutting, opening Chile's markets to global trade, restricting labor unions, privatizing social security, and the [[privatization]] of hundreds of state-controlled industries. These policies produced what has been referred to as the &quot;[[miracle of Chile]]&quot;, but critics claim the government policies dramatically increased [[economic inequality]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| last = Angell | first = Alan | authorlink = | coauthors = | title = The Cambridge History of Latin America, Vol. VIII, 1930 to the Present. Ed. Leslie Bethell | publisher = Cambridge University Press | year = 1991 | location = Cambridge; New York | page = 318 | url = http://books.google.com/?id=cbhOISlOv3MC&amp;pg=PA381&amp;lpg=PA381&amp;dq=pinochet+economic+inequality | doi = | id = | isbn = 978-0-521-26652-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt; But the devastating effect of the [[Early 1980s recession|1982 monetary crisis]] in the [[Economy of Chile|Chilean economy]] can be attributed to the Finance Minister Sergio De Castro's decision to [[Fixed_exchange_rate_system|peg]] Chile's currency to the U.S. dollar - to align Chile's high inflation rate with the U.S. inflation rate, but triggered a tremendous devaluation when the U.S. dollar fell, and set off a bank crisis. Economist [[Milton Friedman]], whose ideas influenced the Chicago Boys, criticized De Castro for his decision as it distorted markets.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|  title =Chile: No todo es como parece | publisher =COHA | date =3 January 2005 | url =http://www.coha.org/NEW_PRESS_RELEASES/New_Press_Releases_2004/04.100%20the%20one%20in%20Spanish.htm | accessdate =5 May 2008| archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080224134700/http://www.coha.org/NEW_PRESS_RELEASES/New_Press_Releases_2004/04.100+the+one+in+Spanish.htm| archivedate = 24 February 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Chile has been for most of the nineties the best-performing economy in Latin America, though academics continue to dispute the legacy of Pinochet's reforms.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas M. Leonard p. 322&quot;&gt;Thomas M. Leonard. ''Encyclopedia Of The Developing World.'' Routledge. ISBN 1-57958-388-1 p. 322&lt;/ref&gt;

Pinochet's 17-year regime was given a legal framework through a  controversial [[Chilean constitutional referendum, 1980|1980 plebiscite]], which approved a new Constitution drafted by a government-appointed commission. A [[Chilean national plebiscite, 1988|1988 plebiscite]] (which saw 56% vote against continuing his presidency) led to democratic elections for the Presidency and Parliament. After peacefully stepping down in 1990, Pinochet continued to serve as Commander-in-Chief of the Chilean Army until 10 March 1998, when he retired and became a senator-for-life in accordance with the [[Constitution of Chile|1980 Constitution]]. However, Pinochet was [[Indictment and arrest of Augusto Pinochet|arrested in Britain]] on 10 October 1998 in connection with numerous human rights allegations, but following a legal battle was released and returned to Chile in March 2000. In 2004, Chilean Judge [[Juan Guzmán Tapia]] ruled that Pinochet was medically fit to stand trial and placed him under house arrest.&lt;ref name=&quot;CBS&quot; /&gt; By the time of his death on 10 December 2006, about 300 criminal charges were still pending against him in Chile for numerous [[human rights]] violations, [[tax evasion]], and [[embezzlement]] during his 17-year rule and afterwards.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| last =Chang | first =Jack | coauthors =Yulkowski, Lisa | title =Vocal minority praises Pinochet at his funeral | publisher =Bradenton Herald | date =13 December 2006 | url =http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-28896708_ITM | accessdate =13 April 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pinochet was accused of having corruptly amassed a wealth of US$28 million or more.&lt;ref name=NYT&gt;[[Larry Rohter]], [http://www.nytimes.com/2006/06/19/world/americas/19chile.html?ex=1308369600en=964a159db7c0d614ei=5088partner=rssnytemc=rss Colonel's Death Gives Clues to Pinochet Arms Deals], ''[[The New York Times]]'', 19 June 2006 {{en icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;.


==Early life and military career==
Pinochet was born in [[Valparaíso]]. He was the son of Augusto Pinochet Vera, descendant of a [[Breton people|Breton]] immigrant from [[Lamballe]], and Avelina Ugarte Martínez, a woman of [[Basque Chilean|Basque]] descent.&lt;ref&gt;[http://lahoradelpueblo.blogspot.com/2006/12/augusto-pinochet-el-insulso-hijo-del.html Augusto Pinochet, el insulso hijo del aduanero]&lt;/ref&gt; Pinochet went to primary and secondary school at the San Rafael Seminary of Valparaíso, the Rafael Ariztía Institute ([[Marist Brothers]]) in [[Quillota]], the French Fathers' School of Valparaíso, and then to the Military School in Santiago, which he entered in 1931. In 1935, after four years of study, he graduated with the rank of ''alférez'' ([[Second lieutenant|Second Lieutenant]]) in the [[infantry]]. In September 1937, Pinochet was assigned to the &quot;Chacabuco&quot; Regiment, in [[Concepción, Chile|Concepción]]. Two years later, in 1939, then with the rank of Sub-lieutenant, he moved to the &quot;Maipo&quot; Regiment, garrisoned in Valparaíso. He returned to Infantry School in 1940. On 30 January 1943, Pinochet married [[Lucía Hiriart|Lucía Hiriart Rodríguez]], with whom he has five children: [[Lucía Pinochet|Inés Lucía]], María Verónica, Jacqueline Marie, Augusto Osvaldo, and Marco Antonio.

By late 1945, Pinochet was assigned to the &quot;Carampangue&quot; Regiment in the northern city of [[Iquique]]. Three years later, he entered the War Academy, but he had to postpone his studies because, being the youngest officer, he had to carry out a service mission in the [[coal]] zone of [[Lota, Chile|Lota]]. The following year he returned to his studies in the Academy, and after obtaining the title of Officer Chief of Staff, in 1951, he returned to teach at the Military School. At the same time, he worked as a teachers' aide at the War Academy, giving military geography and geopolitics classes. In addition to this, he was active as editor of the institutional magazine ''Cien Águilas'' (&quot;One Hundred Eagles&quot;). At the beginning of 1953, with the rank of Major, he was sent for two years to the &quot;Rancagua&quot; Regiment in [[Arica]]. While there, he was appointed professor of the Chilean War Academy, and he returned to [[Santiago]] to take up his new position.&lt;ref name=&quot;CBS&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/background/chile/pinochet.html|title=Augusto Pinochet: Timeline|publisher=CBSNews | date=11 December 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1956, Pinochet and a group of young officers were chosen to form a military mission that would collaborate in the organization of the War Academy of [[Ecuador]] in [[Quito]]. He remained with the Quito mission for three-and-a-half years, during which time he dedicated himself to the study of [[geopolitics]], [[military geography]] and intelligence. It's been recently alleged that while in Quito Pinochet had a romance with Piedad Noe, and fathered a boy called Juan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.emol.com/noticias/internacional/detalle/detallenoticias.asp?idnoticia=364860 |title=Supuesto hijo de Pinochet en Ecuador dispuesto a prueba de ADN |publisher=Emol.com |date= |accessdate=10 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the end of 1959, he returned to Chile and was sent to General Headquarters of the 1st Army Division, based in [[Antofagasta]]. The following year, he was appointed Commander of the &quot;Esmeralda&quot; Regiment. Due to his success in this position, he was appointed Sub-director of the War Academy in 1963. In 1968, he was named Chief of Staff of the 2nd Army Division, based in [[Santiago]], and at the end of that year, he was promoted to Brigadier General and Commander in Chief of the 6th Division, garrisoned in Iquique. In his new function, he was also appointed Intendant of the [[Tarapacá Region|Tarapacá]] Province.

In January 1971, Pinochet rose to Division General, and was named General Commander of the Santiago Army Garrison. At the beginning of 1972, he was appointed General Chief of Staff of the Army. With rising domestic strife in Chile, after General Prats resigned his position, Pinochet was appointed [[commander-in-chief]] of the Army on 23 August 1973 by President [[Salvador Allende]] just the day after the [[Chamber of Deputies of Chile]] approved a [[s:Agreement of the Chamber of Deputies of Chile|resolution]] asserting that the government was not respecting the Constitution. Less than a month later, the Chilean military deposed Allende.

==Military coup of 1973==
{{Main|1973 Chilean coup d'état}}

On 11 September 1973, the combined Chilean Armed Forces (the Army, Navy, Air Force and the [[Carabineros de Chile|Carabineros]]) overthrew Allende's government in a coup, during which the presidential palace, [[La Moneda Palace|La Moneda]], was shelled and Allende committed suicide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/jul/20/salvador-allende-committed-suicide-autopsy | location=London | work=The Guardian | title=Chilean president Salvador Allende committed suicide, autopsy confirms | date=20 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In his memoirs Pinochet said that he was the leading plotter of the coup and used his position as commander-in-chief of the Army to coordinate a far-reaching scheme with the other two branches of the military and the national police. In later years, however, high military officials from the time have said that Pinochet reluctantly became involved only a few days before it was scheduled to occur and followed the lead of the other branches (especially the Navy, under Merino) as they executed the coup.{{Citation needed|date=October 2011}}

The new government rounded up thousands of people and held them in the [[Estadio Nacional Julio Martínez Prádanos|national stadium]], where many were killed, setting the stage for decades of brutal repression that followed. As many as 3,000 people died during Pinochet's years in power, and more than 1,000 are still missing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/807599.stm | work=BBC News | title=Soldier confirms Chile stadium killings | date=27 June 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the months that followed the coup, the ''junta'', with authoring work by historian [[Gonzalo Vial Correa|Gonzalo Vial]] and admiral Patricio Carvajal, published a book titled ''El Libro Blanco del cambio de gobierno en Chile'' (commonly known as ''El Libro Blanco'', &quot;[[The White Book of the Change of Government in Chile]]&quot;), where they attempted to justify the coup by claiming that they were in fact anticipating a self-coup (the alleged ''[[Plan Zeta]]'', or Plan Z) that Allende's government or its associates were purportedly preparing. United States intelligence agencies believed the plan to be untrue [[propaganda]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.clarin.com/diario/1999/07/05/i-02501d.htm El fin de un mito en Chile: el Plan Zeta], ''[[Clarín (newspaper)|Clarín]]'', 5 July 1999 {{es icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although later discredited and officially recognized as the product of political propaganda,&lt;ref name=&quot;Valech1&quot;&gt;[http://www.gobiernodechile.cl/comision_valech/pdf/Capitulo3.pdf Comisión Nacional sobre Prisión Política y Tortura CAPÍTULO III Contexto].&lt;/ref&gt; some Chilean historians pointed to the similarities between the alleged Plan Z and other existing paramilitary plans of the Popular Unity parties in support of its legitimacy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| last = Vial Correa | first = Gonzalo | coauthors =| title = Carlos Altamirano, el Plan Z y la &quot;Operación Blanqueo&quot; | work =| pages =| language =| publisher = La Segunda| date = 23 September 2003| url =| accessdate =  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Canadian [[Jean Charpentier]] of [[Télévision de Radio-Canada]] was the first foreign [[journalist]] to interview General Pinochet following the coup.&lt;ref name=gandm&gt;{{Cite news|first=Philip|last=Fine|title=Cool and mannerly, he was Trudeau's press secretary at a difficult time |url=http://v1.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20100123.OBCHARPENTIER23ART2043/BDAStory/BDA/deaths |work=[[Globe and Mail]] |publisher=|date=23 January 2010 |accessdate=7 February 2010 |location=Toronto}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===U.S. backing of the coup===
{{See|United States intervention in Chile}}

The U.S. provided material support to the military regime after the coup, although criticizing it in public. A document released by the U.S. [[Central Intelligence Agency]] (CIA) in 2000, titled &quot;CIA Activities in Chile&quot;, revealed that the CIA actively supported the military junta after the overthrow of Allende, and that it made many of Pinochet's officers into paid contacts of the CIA or U.S. military, even though some were known to be involved in human rights abuses.&lt;ref name=&quot;NSA-2000-9-19&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Peter Kornbluh|url=http://www.gwu.edu/~nsarchiv/news/20000919/|title=CIA Acknowledges Ties to Pinochet’s Repression: Report to Congress Reveals U.S. Accountability in Chile|work=Chile Documentation Project|publisher=National Security Archive|date=19 September 2000|accessdate=26 November 2006| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20061128142216/http://www.gwu.edu/~nsarchiv/news/20000919/| archivedate= 28 November 2006 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; Perhaps most infamously, the CIA maintained contacts among the Chilean [[Dirección de Inteligencia Nacional|DINA]] intelligence service while DINA leaders, under Pinochet's direct command, led the multinational &quot;anti-communism campaign&quot; known as [[Operation Condor]], resulting in assassinations of prominent politicians and activists of the legal left in various Latin American countries, in Washington, D.C., and in Europe (see section below). In particular, CIA contact with the head DINA, [[Manuel Contreras]], was established soon after the coup (in 1974, during the Junta period prior to official transfer of Presidential powers to Pinochet); in 1975, the CIA reviewed a warning that keeping Contreras as an [[Asset (intelligence)|asset]] might threaten human rights in the region.  The CIA chose to keep him as an asset, and at one point even paid him. In addition to the CIA's maintaining of assets in DINA beginning soon after the coup, several CIA assets, such as [[Coordination of United Revolutionary Organizations|CORU]] [[Cuban exile]] militants [[Orlando Bosch]] and Guillermo Novo, collaborated in DINA operations under the Condor Plan in the early years of Pinochet's presidency.

While the U.S. tacitly supported the Pinochet regime after the 1973 coup, there is no evidence that the US was directly involved in the coup.&lt;ref name=&quot;Church Report 1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://foia.state.gov/Reports/ChurchReport.asp#A.%20Overview:%20Cover%20Action%20in%20Chile|title=Covert Action in Chile 1963–1973|publisher=US Government Printing Office|date=18 December 1975|author=Frank Church et al.|quote=Was the United States DIRECTLY involved, covertly, in the 1973 coup in Chile? The Committee has found no evidence that it was.|accessdate=20 July 2010| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20100722060530/http://foia.state.gov/Reports/ChurchReport.asp| archivedate= 22 July 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the [[Church Committee|Church Report]] concluded that, while the US had not directly participated in the 1973 coup, it had supported an attempted coup in 1970,&lt;ref name=&quot;Church Report 2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://foia.state.gov/Reports/ChurchReport.asp#A.%20Overview:%20Cover%20Action%20in%20Chile|title=Covert Action in Chile 1963–1973|publisher=US Government Printing Office|date=18 December 1975|author=Frank Church et al.|quote=The United States sought in 1970 to foment a military coup in Chile; after 1970 it adopted a policy both overt and covert, of opposition to Allende; and it remained in intelligence contact with the Chilean military, including officers who were participating in coup plotting.|accessdate=20 July 2010| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20100722060530/http://foia.state.gov/Reports/ChurchReport.asp| archivedate= 22 July 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; and had directed money to anti-Allende elements, including possibly terrorist groups, during the period 1970–1973.&lt;ref name=&quot;Church Report 3&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://foia.state.gov/Reports/ChurchReport.asp#A.%20Overview:%20Cover%20Action%20in%20Chile|title=Covert Action in Chile 1963–1973|publisher=US Government Printing Office|date=18 December 1975|author=Frank Church et al.|quote=The CIA gave support in 1970 to one group whose tacticts ''[sic]'' became more violent over time. Through 1971 that group received small sums of American money through third parties for specific purpose. And it is possible that money was passed to these groups on the extreme right from CIA-supported opposition political parties. |accessdate=20 July 2010| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20100722060530/http://foia.state.gov/Reports/ChurchReport.asp| archivedate= 22 July 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; The armed forces under Pinochet's command had strong enough coordination and military resources, and sufficient motivation, to undertake the coup on their own, as evidenced by their earlier coup attempt known as the [[Tanquetazo]].

==Military junta==
{{Main|Government Junta of Chile (1973)}}
[[File:Pin8.JPG|thumb|Augusto Pinochet in 1974]]
A [[military junta]] was established immediately following the coup, made up of General Pinochet representing the [[Chilean Army|Army]], Admiral [[José Toribio Merino]] representing the [[Chilean Navy|Navy]], General [[Gustavo Leigh]] representing the [[Chilean Air Force|Air Force]], and General [[César Mendoza]] representing the ''[[Carabineros de Chile|Carabineros]]'' (national police). As established the junta exercised both executive and legislative functions of the government, [[State of emergency|suspended the Constitution]] and the [[National Congress of Chile|Congress]], imposed strict [[censorship]] and [[curfew]], banned all parties and halted all political activities. This military junta held the executive role until 17 December 1974, after which it remained strictly as a legislative body, the executive powers being transferred to Pinochet with the title of President.

==Presidency==
{{Main|Military government of Chile (1973–1990)}}
[[File:Pinochet junta1.gif|thumb|Junta session one week after the 1973 coup]]
[[File:Pinochet 11-09-1982.JPG|thumb|Pinochet in 1982]]
The junta members originally planned for the presidency to rotate among the commanders-in-chief of the four military branches. However, Pinochet soon consolidated his control, first retaining sole chairmanship of the military junta, and then proclaiming himself &quot;Supreme Chief of the Nation&quot; (de facto provisional president) on 27 June 1974. He officially changed his title to &quot;President&quot; on 17 December 1974. General Leigh, head of the Air Force, became increasingly opposed to Pinochet's policies and was forced into retirement on 24 July 1978, after contradicting Pinochet on that year's plebiscite (officially called Consulta Nacional, or National Consultation, in response to a UN resolution condemning Pinochet's government). He would be replaced by General [[Fernando Matthei]].

Pinochet organized a [[Chilean constitutional referendum, 1980|plebiscite on 11 September 1980]]. The Chilean people were asked to ratify a new [[Constitution of Chile|Constitution]], replacing the 1925 Constitution drafted during [[Arturo Alessandri]]'s presidency. The new Constitution, partly drafted by [[Jaime Guzmán]], a close adviser to Pinochet and future founder of the right-wing party [[Independent Democratic Union]] (UDI), gave the position of President of the Republic, held by Pinochet, a large amount of power. It created some new institutions, such as the Constitutional Tribunal and the controversial National Security Council (COSENA). It also prescribed an 8-year presidential period, and a single-candidate presidential [[referendum]] in 1988, where a candidate nominated by the Junta would be approved or rejected for another 8-year period. The 1980 referendum was approved by 67.04% against 30.19%,&lt;ref name=Hudson&gt;Hudson, Rex A., ed. &quot;Chile: A Country Study&quot;. GPO for the Library of Congress. 1995. 20 March 2005 http://lcweb2.loc.gov/frd/cs/cltoc.html&lt;/ref&gt; although the opposition denounced extensive irregularities. Headed by ex-president [[Eduardo Frei Montalva]], they argued that this result did not tally with electoral records. One objection was that voters cast their vote using as identification only their own ID cards, without any official records, and were only marked with ink on the thumb, which came off rapidly, making [[electoral fraud]] easy. These criticisms were rejected by the Scrutiny Association&lt;!--&quot;and international observers&quot; removed until sources are produced... and where are the sources of this rejection by the Scrutiny Association?--&gt;, and the Constitution was promulgated on 21 October 1980, taking effect on 11 March 1981. Pinochet was replaced as President of the Junta that day by Admiral Merino.

In a massive operation spearheaded by Chilean Army Para-Commandos, some 2,000 security forces troops&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=hzrwMb3UppYC&amp;pg=PA146&amp;dq=black+berets+neltume&amp;cd=1#v=onepage&amp;q=black%20berets%20neltume |title=Chile under Pinochet: recovering the truth. By Mark Ensalaco. Page 146. Cloth 1999 |publisher=Books.google.co.nz |date= |accessdate=10 March 2010 | isbn=978-0-8122-3520-3|year=2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; were deployed in the mountains of [[Neltume]] from June to November,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.faqs.org/cia/docs/33/0000451376/LATIN-AMERICA-REVIEW---CHILE:--TERRORISM-STILL-COUNTERPRODUCTIVE.html |title=Chile: Terrorism still counterproductive. CIA document |publisher=Faqs.org |date= |accessdate=10 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; where they destroyed two [[Revolutionary Left Movement (Chile)|MIR]] bases, seizing large caches of munitions and killing a number of guerrillas.

In a 1985 report, the [[Inter-American Commission on Human Rights]] stated that it hoped that &quot;the case now under way will lead to the identification and punishment of the persons responsible for the execution of so culpable an act.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cidh.org/annualrep/85.86eng/chap.4.htm |title=Inter-American Commission on human rights Report 1986 |publisher=Cidh.org |date= |accessdate=10 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eventually, six members of the police secret service were given [[life sentences]].

According to a book by Ozren Agnic Krstulovic, weapons including C-4 [[plastic explosive]]s, [[RPG-7]] and [[M72 LAW]] rocket launchers as well as more than three thousand [[M16 rifle|M-16]] rifles were smuggled into the country by opponents of the government.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.nz/books?id=itzzT3or3noC&amp;pg=PA147&amp;dq=Carrizal+Bajo+m+16+fpmr&amp;as_brr=3&amp;cd=2#v=onepage&amp;q=Carrizal%20Bajo%20m%2016%20fpmr&amp;f=false Pinochet S.A.: la base de la fortuna. Ozren Agnic Krstulovic. Page 147. RiL Editores 2006.]&lt;/ref&gt;

In September, weapons from the same source were used in an unsuccessful [[assassination]] attempt against Pinochet by the [[FPMR]]. Taken by surprise, five of his military bodyguards were killed. Although Pinochet's Mercedes Benz bulletproof vehicle was struck by a rocket, it did not explode, and Pinochet suffered only minor injuries, managing to escape.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.emol.com/especiales/infografias/atentadopinochet/index.htm Emol, website of newspaper El Mercurio: Adobe Flash presentation reconstructing the September 1986 assassination attempt] {{es icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;



===Suppression of opposition===
{{See|Operation Condor|Indictment and arrest of Augusto Pinochet}}
{{rquote|right|He shut down parliament, suffocated political life, banned trade unions, and made Chile his sultanate. His government disappeared 3,000 opponents, arrested 30,000 (torturing thousands of them)&amp;nbsp;... Pinochet's name will forever be linked to the [[Forced disappearance|''Desaparecidos'']], the [[Caravan of Death]], and the institutionalized torture that took place in the [[Villa Grimaldi]] complex.| [[Thor Halvorssen Mendoza|Thor Halvorssen]], president of the [[Human Rights Foundation]], ''[[National Review]]''&lt;ref&gt;[http://article.nationalreview.com/?q=NDQxNTJlM2M4OTRhOGJhNTMzNTkyNDQ2YmYzMTU3ZTU= Pinochet Is History: But how will it remember him?] ''[[National Review]]'' Symposium, 11 December 2006&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Almost immediately after the military's seizure of power, the junta banned all the leftist parties that had constituted Allende's UP coalition.&lt;ref name=Stern&gt;{{Cite book
  | last = Stern
  | first = Steve J.
  | title = Remembering Pinochet's Chile
  | publisher = Duke University Press
  | location = 2004-09-30
  | pages = 32, 90, 101, 180–81
  | isbn = 0-8223-3354-6}}. Retrieved 10-24-2006 through Google Books.&lt;/ref&gt;
All other parties were placed in &quot;indefinite recess,&quot; and were later banned outright. The government's violence was directed not only against dissidents, but also against their families and other civilians.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stern&quot; /&gt;

The [[Rettig Report]] concluded 2,279 persons who disappeared during the military government were killed for political reasons or as a result of political violence, and approximately 31,947 tortured according to the later [[Valech Report]], while 1,312 were exiled. The latter were chased all over the world by the intelligence agencies. In Latin America, this was made in the frame of Operation Condor, a cooperation plan between the various intelligence agencies of South American countries, assisted by a United States CIA communication base in Panama. Pinochet believed these operations were necessary in order to &quot;save the country from communism&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Eduardo Gallardo, [http://abcnews.go.com/International/wireStory?id=2714962 Pinochet Was Unrepentant to the End], [[ABC News]] ([[Associated Press]]), 11 December 2006 {{en icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2011, commission identified an additional 9,800 victims of political repression during the Pinochet regime. This led to the total number of victims being revised to approximately 40,018, including 3,065 killed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-latin-america-14584095 | work=BBC News | title=Chile recognises 9,800 more victims of Pinochet's rule | date=18 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some political scientists have ascribed the relative bloodiness of the coup to the stability of the existing democratic system, which required extreme action to overturn. Some of the most infamous cases of human rights violation occurred during the early period: in October 1973, at least 70 people were killed throughout the country by the [[Caravan of Death]]. [[Charles Horman]], a US journalist, &quot;[[forced disappearance|disappeared]]&quot;, as did [[Víctor Olea Alegría]], a member of the [[Socialist Party of Chile|Socialist Party]], and many others, in 1973.

Furthermore, many other important officials of Allende's government were tracked down by the DINA in the frame of Operation Condor. Thus, General [[Carlos Prats]], Pinochet's predecessor and army commander under Allende, who had resigned rather than support the moves against Allende's government, was assassinated in [[Buenos Aires]], [[Argentina]], in 1974. A year later, the murder of 119 opponents abroad was disguised as an internal conflict, the DINA setting up a propaganda campaign to accredit this thesis ([[Operation Colombo]]), campaign that received diffusion by the leading newspaper in Chile, El Mercurio.

Other victims of Condor included, among hundreds of less famous persons, [[Juan José Torres]], the former President of Bolivia, assassinated in Buenos Aires on 2 June 1976; [[Carmelo Soria]], a UN diplomat working for the [[United Nations Economic Commission for Latin America and the Caribbean|CEPAL]], assassinated in July 1976;
[[Letelier case|Orlando Letelier]], a former Chilean [[ambassador (diplomacy)|ambassador]] to the United States and minister in Allende's cabinet, assassinated after his release from internment and exile in [[Washington, D.C.]] by a car bomb on 21 September 1976. This led to strained relations with the US and to the extradition of [[Michael Townley]], a US citizen who worked for the DINA and had organized Letelier's assassination. Other targeted victims, who escaped assassination, included Christian-Democrat [[Bernardo Leighton]], who escaped an assassination attempt in Rome in 1975 by the Italian terrorist [[Stefano delle Chiaie]]; [[Carlos Altamirano]], the leader of the Chilean Socialist Party, targeted for murder in 1975 by Pinochet, along with [[Volodia Teitelboim]], member of the Communist Party; [[Pascal Allende]], the nephew of Salvador Allende and president of the [[Revolutionary Left Movement (Chile)|MIR]], who escaped an assassination attempt in Costa Rica in March 1976; US Congressman [[Edward Koch]], who became aware in 2001 of relations between death threats and his denunciation of Operation Condor, etc. Furthermore, according to current investigations, [[Eduardo Frei Montalva]], the Christian Democrat President of Chile from 1964 to 1970, may have been poisoned in 1982 by toxin produced by DINA biochemist [[Eugenio Berrios]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/6289209.stm Ex-Chilean leader 'was murdered'], [[BBC]], 23 January 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

Protests continued, however, during the 1980s, leading to several scandals. In March 1985, the savage murder of three [[Communist Party of Chile|Communist Party]] members led to the resignation of [[César Mendoza]], head of the [[Carabineros de Chile|Carabineros]] and member of the ''junta'' since its formation. During a 1986 protest against Pinochet, 21 year old American photographer [[Rodrigo Rojas DeNegri]] and 18 year old student [[Carmen Gloria Quintana]] were [[Burnt Alive case|burnt alive]], with only Carmen surviving.

In August 1989, Marcelo Barrios Andres, a 21 year-old member of the [[FPMR]] (the armed wing of the PCC, created in 1983, which had attempted to assassinate Pinochet on 7 September 1986), was assassinated by a group of military personnel who were supposed to arrest him on orders of Valparaíso's public prosecutor. However, they simply executed him; this case was included in the Rettig Report.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nacion&quot;&gt;[http://www.lanacion.cl/prontus_noticias/site/artic/20050924/pags/20050924155052.html Capítulos desconocidos de los mercenarios chilenos en Honduras camino de Iraq], ''[[La Nación (Chile)|La Nación]]'', 25 September 2005 – URL accessed on 14 February 2007 {{es icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; Among the killed and disappeared during the military regime were 440 MIR guerrillas.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=efkdTQof5z0C&amp;pg=PA179&amp;lpg=PA179&amp;dq=muertos+del+MIR+chile&amp;q=muertos%20del%20MIR%20chile |title=Su revolución contra nuestra revolución: izquierdas y derechas en el Chile, Verónica Valdivia Ortiz de Zárate, p. 179, LOM Ediciones, 2006 |publisher=Books.google.com |date= |accessdate=10 March 2010 | isbn=978-956-282-853-6|year=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Economic policy===
{{economic history of Chile}}
In 1973, the Chilean economy was deeply hurt for several reasons, including the expropriation of 600 businesses by the Marxist Allende government, a tiered exchange rate that distorted markets, protectionism, and the economic sanctions imposed by the [[Richard Nixon|Nixon administration]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Still&quot;&gt;[http://www.hartford-hwp.com/archives/42a/127.html Still Hidden: A Full Record Of What the U.S. Did in Chile], [[Peter Kornbluh]], ''[[The Washington Post]]'', Sunday 24 October 1999; Page B01&lt;/ref&gt; inflation was 1000%, the country had no foreign reserves, and GDP was falling.&lt;ref name=&quot;brauchle&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ecaef.org/klex/user/1/41894820_10_10.ppt|title=Applied Theory: The Reforms in Chile|author=Manfred Bräuchle}}&lt;/ref&gt; By mid 1975, the government set forth an economic policy of [[free-market]] reforms which attempted to stop inflation and collapse. Pinochet declared that he wanted &quot;to make Chile not a nation of [[proletarian]]s, but a nation of [[proprietor]]s.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mundoandino.com/Chile/History-pinochet |title=Augusto Pinochet biography data. Chilean coup d'etat. Pinochet human rights violations |publisher=Mundoandino.com |date= |accessdate=10 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; To formulate the economic rescue, the government relied on the so-called [[Chicago Boys]] and a text called ''[[El ladrillo]]''.

The economic policies espoused by the Chicago Boys and implemented by the junta caused several economic indicators to decline for Chile's lower classes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal
 | author = K. Remmer
 | year = 1998
 | month =
 | title = The Politics of Neoliberal Economic Reform in South America
 | journal =
 | volume = 33
 | issue =
 | pages = 3–29
 | id = Studies in Comparative International Development
 | url =
 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Wages decreased by 8%.&lt;ref name=&quot;Petras and Vieux 1998 57-72&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal
 | author = Petras and Vieux
 | year = 1998 
 | month =
 | title = The Chilean &quot;Economic Miracle&quot;: An Empirical Critique
 | journal =
 | volume =
 | issue =
 | pages = 57–72
 | id = Crit Sociol
 | url =
 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Family allowances in 1989 were 28% of what they had been in 1970 and the budgets for education, health and housing had dropped by over 20% on average&lt;ref name=&quot;Petras and Vieux 1998 57-72&quot; /&gt;
The junta relied on the [[middle class]], the oligarchy, huge foreign corporations, and foreign loans to maintain itself.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=hzrwMb3UppYC&amp;dq=Chile+under+pinochet&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=-66tt8rEmg&amp;sig=nSBX05IdsHb6lVMw141M4G7vYD0&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=he_tSYCpDJCgtgOD4YTjAQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=5] Chile under Pinochet: recovering the truth
&lt;/ref&gt;
Businesses recovered most of their lost industrial and agricultural holdings, for the junta returned properties to original owners who had lost them during expropriations, and sold other industries expropriated by Allende's Popular Unity government to private buyers. This period saw the expansion of business and widespread speculation.

Financial conglomerates became major beneficiaries of the liberalized economy and the flood of foreign bank loans. Large foreign banks reinstated the credit cycle, as the Junta saw that the basic state obligations, such as resuming payment of principal and interest installments, were honored. International lending organizations such as the [[World Bank]], the [[International Monetary Fund]], and the [[Inter-American Development Bank]] lent vast sums anew.&lt;ref name=&quot;Petras and Vieux 1998 57-72&quot; /&gt;
Many foreign multinational corporations such as [[International Telephone and Telegraph]] (ITT), [[Dow Chemical]], and [[Firestone Tire and Rubber Company|Firestone]], all expropriated by Allende, returned to Chile.&lt;ref name=&quot;Petras and Vieux 1998 57-72&quot; /&gt;
Pinochet's policies eventually led to substantial [[Gross Domestic Product|GDP]] growth, in contrast to the negative growth seen in the early years of his administration. Foreign debt also grew substantially under Pinochet, rising 300% between 1974 and 1988.

His government implemented an economic model that had three main objectives: economic liberalization, privatization of state owned companies, and stabilization of inflation. In 1985, the government started with a second round of privatization, it revised previously introduced tariff increases and gave a greater supervisory role for the Central Bank. Pinochet's market liberalizations have continued after his death, led by [[Patricio Aylwin]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas M. Leonard p. 322&quot; /&gt;

===1988 referendum and transition to democracy===
{{See|Chilean transition to democracy}}
According to the transitional provisions of the [[Constitution of Chile|1980 Constitution]], a referendum was scheduled for 5 October 1988, to vote on a new eight-year presidential term for Pinochet. Confronted with increasing opposition, notably at the international level, Pinochet legalized political parties in 1987 and called for a plebiscite to determine whether or not he would remain in power until 1997. If the &quot;YES&quot; won, Pinochet would have to implement the dispositions of the 1980 Constitution, mainly the call for general elections, while he would himself remain in power as President. If the &quot;NO&quot; won, Pinochet would remain President for another year, and a joint Presidential and Parliamentary election would be scheduled.

Another reason of Pinochet's decision to call for elections was the April 1987 visit of [[Pope John Paul II]] to Chile. According to the US Catholic author [[George Weigel]], he held a meeting with Pinochet during which they discussed a return to democracy. John Paul II allegedly pushed Pinochet to accept a democratic opening of the regime, and even called for his resignation.&lt;ref&gt;[[George Weigel]], ''Biografía de Juan Pablo II – Testigo de Esperanza'', Editorial Plaza &amp; Janés (2003), ISBN 84-01-01304-6&lt;/ref&gt;

Political advertising was legalized on 5 September 1987, as a necessary element for the campaign for the &quot;NO&quot; to the referendum, which countered the official campaign which presaged a return to a Popular Unity government in case of a defeat of Pinochet. The Opposition, gathered into the ''[[Coalition of Parties for Democracy|Concertación de Partidos por el NO]]'' (&quot;Coalition of Parties for NO&quot;), organized a colorful and cheerful campaign under the slogan ''La alegría ya viene'' (&quot;Joy is coming&quot;). It was formed by the [[Christian Democrat Party of Chile|Christian Democracy]], the [[Socialist Party of Chile|Socialist Party]] and the [[Social Democrat Radical Party|Radical Party]], gathered in the ''Alianza Democrática'' (Democratic Alliance). In 1988, several more parties, including the [[Humanist Party (Chile)|Humanist Party]], the [[Ecologist Party of Chile|Ecologist Party]], the Social Democrats, and several Socialist Party splinter groups added their support.

On 5 October 1988, the &quot;NO&quot; option won with 55.99%&lt;ref name=&quot;Elections&quot;&gt;[http://www.tribunalcalificador.cl/resultado.php Tribunal Calificador], Chilean governmental website {{es icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; of the votes, against 44.01% of &quot;YES&quot; votes. Pinochet complied, so the ensuing Constitutional process led to presidential and legislative elections the following year.

The Coalition changed its name to ''Concertación de Partidos por la Democracia'' (Coalition of Parties for Democracy) and put forward [[Patricio Aylwin]], a Christian Democrat who had opposed Allende, as presidential candidate, and also proposed a list of candidates for the parliamentary elections. The opposition and the Pinochet government made several negotiations to amend the Constitution and agreed to 54 modifications. These amendments changed the way the Constitution would be modified in the future, added restrictions to [[state of emergency]] dispositions, the affirmation of [[political pluralism]], and enhanced constitutional rights as well as the [[democracy|democratic]] principle and participation to political life. In July 1989, a [[Chilean referendum, 1989|referendum]] on the proposed changes took place, supported by all the parties except the right-wing [[Avanzada Nacional]]. The Constitutional changes were approved by 91.25% of the voters.

Thereafter, Aylwin won the [[Chilean presidential election, 1989|December 1989 presidential election]] with 55% of the votes,&lt;ref name=Elections/&gt; against less than 30% for the right-wing candidate, [[Hernan Buchi]], who had been Pinochet's [[Minister of Finances]] since 1985 (there was also a third-party candidate, [[Francisco Javier Errázuriz Talavera|Francisco Javier Errázuriz]], a wealthy aristocrat that represented the extreme economic right, who garnered the remaining 15%&lt;ref name=Elections/&gt;). Pinochet thus left the presidency on 11 March 1990 and transferred power to the new democratically elected president.

The ''Concertación'' also won the majority of votes for the Parliament. However, due to the &quot;binomial&quot; representation system included in the constitution, the elected senators did not achieve a complete majority in Parliament, a situation that would last for over 15 years. This forced them to negotiate all law projects with the [[Alliance for Chile]] (originally called &quot;Democracy and Progress&quot; and then &quot;Union for Chile&quot;), a center-right coalition involving the ''[[Independent Democratic Union|Unión Demócrata Independiente]]'' (UDI) and ''[[National Renewal (Chile)|Renovación Nacional]]'' (RN), parties composed mainly of Pinochet's supporters.

Due to the transitional provisions of the constitution, Pinochet remained as Commander-in-Chief of the Army until March 1998. He was then sworn in as a [[senator-for-life]], a privilege granted by the 1980 constitution to former presidents with at least six years in office. His senatorship and consequent [[Immunity from prosecution (international law)|immunity from prosecution]] protected him from legal action. These were only possible in Chile after Pinochet was arrested in 1998 in the [[United Kingdom]], on an [[extradition]] request issued by Spanish judge [[Baltasar Garzón]] — allegations of abuses had been made numerous times before his arrest, but never acted upon.&lt;ref&gt;See [[Juan Guzmán Tapia]]'s autobiography&lt;/ref&gt; The extradition attempt was dramatised in the 2006 BBC television docudrama ''[[Pinochet in Suburbia]]'', with Pinochet played by [[Derek Jacobi]].

===Relationship with UK===
Chile was officially neutral during the (Malvinas) [[Falklands War]], but Chile's [[Westinghouse Electronic Systems|Westinghouse]] long range radar that was deployed in the south of the country gave the British task force early warning of Argentinian air attacks. This allowed British ships and troops in the war zone to take defensive action.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.margaretthatcher.org/speeches/displaydocument.asp?docid=108383 |title=Margaret Thatcher Foundation. Speech on Pinochet at the Conservative Party Conference. 6 October 1999 |publisher=Margaretthatcher.org |date=6 October 1999 |accessdate=10 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Margaret Thatcher]], the British prime minister at the time of the war, has said that the day the radar was taken out of service for overdue maintenance was the day Argentinian fighter-bombers bombed the troopships [[Sir Galahad]] and [[Sir Tristram]], leaving 53 dead and many injured. According to Chilean Junta and former Air Force commander Fernando Matthei, Chilean support included military intelligence gathering, radar surveillance, allowing British aircraft to operate with Chilean colours, and facilitating the safe return of British special forces, among other forms of assistance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.mercopress.com/2005/09/03/us-support-to-uk-in-falklands-war-was-decisive |title=Mercopress. September 3rd 2005 |publisher=En.mercopress.com |date=3 September 2005 |accessdate=10 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In April and May 1982, a squadron of mothballed British [[Hawker Hunter]] fighter-bombers departed for Chile, arriving on 22 May and allowing the Chilean Air Force to reform the No. 9 &quot;Las Panteras Negras&quot; Squadron. A further consignment of three frontier surveillance and shipping reconnaissance Canberras left for Chile in October. Some authors have speculated that Argentina might have won the war had the military felt able to employ the elite VIth and VIIIth Mountain Brigades which remained sitting in the [[Andes]] guarding against possible Chilean incursions.&lt;ref&gt;Nicholas van der Bijl and David Aldea, 5th Infantry Brigade in the Falklands, page 28, Leo Cooper 2003&lt;/ref&gt; Pinochet subsequently visited [[Margaret Thatcher]] for tea on more than one occasion.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk_politics/6167351.stm |title=UK &amp;#124; UK Politics &amp;#124; Pinochet death 'saddens' Thatcher |publisher=BBC News |date=11 December 2006 |accessdate=10 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pinochet's controversial relationship with Thatcher led [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour]] Prime Minister [[Tony Blair]] to mock Thatcher's [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservatives]] as &quot;the party of Pinochet&quot; in 1999.

==Ideology and public image==
Pinochet and his regime have been characterised as [[fascism|fascist]].&lt;ref name=&quot;fascist&quot;/&gt; For example, author [[Samuel Chavkin]], in his book ''[[Storm Over Chile: The Junta Under Siege]]'', repeatedly characterizes both Pinochet himself and the military dictatorship as fascist.&lt;ref&gt;Samuel Chavkin, ''Storm Over Chile: The Junta Under Siege''. Laurence Hill Books. ISBN 978-1-55652-067-9&lt;/ref&gt; However, he and his regime are generally excluded from academic typologies of fascism.&lt;ref name=&quot;R. Griffin, 2003, pp. 36-37&quot;&gt;R. Griffin, ''The Nature of Fascism'', London: Routledge, 2003, pp. 36–37&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;R.O. Paxton, 2004, p. 201&quot;&gt;R.O. Paxton, ''The Anatomy of Fascism'', London: Allen Lane 2004, p. 201&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;A. Cento Bull 2009, p. 604&quot;&gt;A. Cento Bull, 'Neo-Fascism', R.J.B. Bosworth, ''The Oxford Handbook of Fascism'', Oxford University Press, 2009, p. 604&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Walter Laqueur]]. ''Fascism: Past, Present, Future''. Oxford University Press. 1997. p. 115&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Roger Griffin]] included Pinochet in a group of pseudo-populist [[Despotism|despot]]s distinct from fascism and including the likes of [[Adolf Hitler|Hitler]], [[Saddam Hussein]], [[Suharto]], and [[Ferdinand Marcos]]. He argues that such regimes may be considered populist [[ultra-nationalism]] but lack the [[palingenesis]] necessary to make them conform to the model of [[palingenetic ultranationalism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;R. Griffin, 2003, pp. 36-37&quot;/&gt; [[Robert Paxton]] meanwhile compared Pinochet's regime to that of [[Mobutu Sese Seko]] in the former [[Zaire]] (now [[Democratic Republic of the Congo]]), arguing that both were merely [[client state]]s that lacked popular acclaim and the ability to expand. He further argued that had Pinochet attempted to build true fascism, the regime would likely have been toppled or at least been forced to alter its relationship to the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;R.O. Paxton, 2004, p. 201&quot;/&gt; Anna Cento Bull also excluded Pinochet from fascism, although she has argued that his regime belongs to a strand of [[Cold War]] [[anti-communism]] that was happy to accommodate [[neo-fascist]] elements within its activity.&lt;ref name=&quot;A. Cento Bull 2009, p. 604&quot;/&gt;
''World Fascism: a Historical encyclopedia'' notes:
&lt;blockquote&gt;Although he was authoritarian and ruled dictatorially, Pinochet's support of neoliberal economic policies and his unwillingness to support national businesses distinguished him from classical fascists.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=nvD2rZSVau4C&amp;pg=PT163&amp;dq=pinochet+fascism&amp;q=pinochet%20fascism |title=World fascism: a historical encyclopedia, Volume 1 By Cyprian Blamires, Paul Jackson |publisher=Books.google.com |date= |accessdate=2010-03-10 | isbn=978-1-57607-940-9|year=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

This view is implicitly rejected by those who have argued that the Chilean economy revived under Pinochet only when the regime adopted corporatist economic policies as opposed to neoliberal ones of the [[Chicago school (economics)|Chicago School]].&lt;ref&gt;Gregory Palast, &quot;Inside corporate America&quot; column, [[The Observer]],22 November 1998&lt;/ref&gt; The notion of Pinochet's &quot;unwillingness to support national businesses&quot; has been challenged by such critics, including [[Noam Chomsky]]; indeed, the copper industry remained nationalized throughout Pinochet's presidency and remains so to this day.

[[Jacobo Timerman]] has called the Chilean army under Pinochet “the last Prussian army in the world&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/1987/11/14/world/buenos-aires-journal-timerman-stranger-in-two-more-strange-lands.html?pagewanted=all | work=The New York Times | first=Shirley | last=Christian | title=Buenos Aires Journal; Timerman, Stranger in Two More Strange Lands | date=14 November 1987}}&lt;/ref&gt; suggesting a pre-Fascist origin to the model of Pinochet's military government.

Historian [[Alfredo Jocelyn-Holt]] has referred to Pinochet's figure as &quot;[[totem]]ic&quot; and added that it is a [[scapegoat]] that attracts &quot;all hate&quot;.&lt;ref name=Salazar/&gt; [[Gabriel Salazar]], also a historian, has lamented the lack of an international condemnation of Pinochet in court, since, according to Salazar, that would have damaged his image &quot;irreparably&quot; and that of the [[Law of Chile|judicial system of Chile]] [for the good] too.&lt;ref name=Salazar&gt;[http://saladehistoria.com/wp/2010/04/04/pinochet-por-salazar-y-jocelyn-holt/ Pinochet por Salazar y Joceyn-Holt].&lt;/ref&gt;     

{{cquote|It's notable that among all declarations of the men of Pinochet nobody has mentioned the craftmen of the new Chilean society and state, I haven't heard anybody mention [[Jaime Guzmán]], [[Carlos Cáceres]], [[Hernán Büchi]], [[Sergio de Castro]]. There is no mention of the true brains nor that the whole armed forces where involved in this, in dirty and symbolic tasks. Everything is embodied in Pinochet, it's very interesting that figures of the size of Büchi are inmolated before the figure of Pinochet, in what is to me a fascist rite, give it everything to the Führer, &quot;I did it, but essentially it was him&quot;.|author=[[Gabriel Salazar]]&lt;ref name=Salazar/&gt;}}

===Nicknames===
Pinochet has different nicknames, some of them given to him by his opponents and some by his supporters. Supporters sometimes refer to him as ''mi general'' (Spanish for &quot;my general&quot;) while opponents call him ''pinocho'' (Spanish for &quot;Pinocchio&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;[http://lasa.international.pitt.edu/members/congress-papers/lasa2009/files/SorensenKristin.pdf Capturing Contested Memories: The Day Pinochet Died], Kristin Sorensen, [[Bentley University]]&lt;/ref&gt; Another common nickname used by both opponents and supporters is ''el tata'' (Spanish equivalent of &quot;the grampa&quot;). After the [[Riggs Bank]] scandal he has been referred sarcastically as ''Daniel Lopez'', one of his fake identities used to deposit money in the bank.

==Arrest and court cases in Britain==
{{Main|Indictment and arrest of Augusto Pinochet}}

The case was a [[wiktionary:watershed|watershed event]] in judicial history, as it was the first time that a former government head was arrested on the principle of [[universal jurisdiction]].&lt;ref&gt;Robertson, Geoffrey, ''Crimes Against Humanity''. Penguin Books, 2006. Ppg. 336-7.&lt;/ref&gt;

After having been placed under [[house arrest]] in Britain and initiating a judicial and public relations battle, the latter run by Thatcherite political operative Patrick Robertson,&lt;ref&gt;Evening Standard 21 June 1995&lt;/ref&gt; he was eventually released in March 2000 on medical grounds by the Home Secretary [[Jack Straw]] without facing trial; Straw had overruled a [[House of Lords]] decision to extradite Pinochet. &lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/663170.stm Pinochet set free], ''[[BBC]]'', 2 March 2000 {{en icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Return to Chile==
Pinochet returned to Chile on 3 March 2000. His first act when landing in [[Comodoro Arturo Merino Benítez International Airport|Santiago's airport]] was to triumphantly get up from his wheelchair to the acclaim of his supporters.&lt;ref name=&quot;Return&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gHReUalWqDw video of Pinochet arriving at Santiago airport], 3 March 2000&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Alex Bellos and Jonathan Franklin, [http://www.guardian.co.uk/pinochet/Story/0,,190560,00.html Pinochet receives a hero's welcome on his return], ''[[The Guardian]]'', 4 March 2000 {{en icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was first greeted by his successor as head of the Chilean armed forces, General [[Ricardo Izurieta]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Return&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/664514.stm Pinochet arrives in Chile], ''[[BBC]]'', 3 March 2000 {{en icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[President-elect]] [[Ricardo Lagos]] said the retired general's televised arrival had damaged the image of Chile, while thousands demonstrated against him.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/665342.stm Thousands march against Pinochet], ''[[BBC]]'', 4 March 2000&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2000 Congress approved a [[Constitution of Chile|constitutional amendment]] creating the status of &quot;ex-president,&quot; which granted its holder immunity from prosecution and a financial allowance; this replaced Pinochet's [[senator-for-life|senatorship-for-life]]. 111 legislators voted for, and 29 (mostly, if not all, from the Left) against.&lt;ref name=&quot;Amendment&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/690817.stm Chile offers Pinochet new immunity], ''[[BBC]]'', 25 March 2000 {{en icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Supreme Court (Chile)|Supreme Court]] ruled in favor of judge Juan Guzmán's request on August 2000, and Pinochet was indicted on 1 December 2000 for the kidnapping of 75 opponents in the [[Caravan of Death]] case.&lt;ref name=&quot;December00&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/1050374.stm Pinochet charged with kidnapping], ''[[BBC]]'', 1 December 2000 {{en icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; Guzmán advanced the charge of kidnapping as the 75 were officially &quot;[[forced disappearance|disappeared]]&quot;: even though they were all most likely dead, the absence of their corpses made any charge of &quot;homicide&quot; difficult.

However, in July 2002, the Supreme Court dismissed Pinochet's indictment in the various human rights abuse cases, for medical reasons (vascular [[dementia]]). The debate concerned Pinochet's mental faculties, his legal team claiming that he was senile and could not remember, while others (including several physicians) claimed that he was only physically affected but retained all control of his faculties. The same year, the [[prosecuting attorney]] Hugo Guttierez, in charge of the Caravan of Death case, declared that &quot;Our country has the degree of justice that the [[Chile's transition to democracy|political transition]] permits us to have.&quot;&lt;ref name=Guttierez&gt;[http://www.memoriayjusticia.cl/english/en_issues-gutierrez.html &quot;The Appeals Court Ruling Is Negotiated Out for Pinochet&quot;], Interview with Attorney Hugo Gutierrez, by ''Memoria y Justicia'',21 February 2002 {{en icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Pinochet resigned from his senatorial seat shortly after the Supreme Court's July 2002 ruling. In May 2004, the Supreme Court overturned its precedent decision, and ruled that he was capable of standing trial. In arguing their case, the prosecution presented a recent TV interview Pinochet had given for a Miami-based television network, which raised doubts about his alleged mental incapacity. He was charged with several crimes in December of that year (including the 1974 assassination of [[Carlos Prats|General Prats]], and the [[Operation Colombo]] case in which 119 died) and was again placed under house arrest. He suffered a stroke on 18 December 2004.&lt;ref&gt; {{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/4108039.stm | work=BBC News | title=Chile's Pinochet 'suffers stroke' | date=18 December 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; Questioned by his judges in order to know if, as President, he was the direct head of [[Dirección de Inteligencia Nacional|DINA]], he answered: &quot;I don't remember, but it's not true. And if it were true, I don't remember.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;16 November 2005. {{lang-es|''&quot;No me acuerdo}}, pero no es cierto. Y si es cierto, no me acuerdo''&quot;. Quoted in [http://www.lanacion.cl/prontus_noticias/site/artic/20061210/pags/20061210221221.html Las frases para el bronce de Pinochet], ''[[La Nacion (Chile)|La Nacion]]'', 11 December 2006 {{es icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2005, the Chilean Army accepted institutional responsibility for past human rights abuses.&lt;ref&gt;General Juan Emilio Cheyre, &quot;Ejército de Chile: el fin de una visión&quot;, La Tercera, 11 May 2004&lt;/ref&gt; In 2006 Pinochet was indicted for kidnappings and torture at the [[Villa Grimaldi]] detention center by the judge Alejandro Madrid (Guzmán's successor),&lt;ref name=&quot;CourtBBC&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/go/pr/fr/-/1/hi/world/americas/5329264.stm Court 'lifts Pinochet immunity'], [[BBC]], 8 September 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; as well as for the 1995 assassination of the DINA biochemist [[Eugenio Berrios]] (himself involved in the [[Letelier case]]).&lt;ref name=LCI&gt;[http://tf1.lci.fr/infos/monde/ameriques/0,,3341806,00-levee-immunite-pinochet-pour-meurtre-chimiste-.html Levée de l'immunité de Pinochet pour le meurtre d'un chimiste], news agency cable, 12 October 2006 {{fr icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; Berrios, who had worked with [[Michael Townley]], had produced [[sarin gas]], [[anthrax]] and [[botulism]] in the Bacteriological War Army Laboratory for Pinochet; these materials were used against political opponents. The DINA biochemist was also alleged of having created [[black cocaine]], which Pinochet then [[illegal drug trade|sold in Europe and the United States]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Franklin&quot;&gt;Jonathan Franklin, [http://www.guardian.co.uk/chile/story/0,,1818137,00.html Pinochet 'sold cocaine to Europe and US'], ''[[The Guardian]]'', 11 July 2006 {{en icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; The money for the drug trade was allegedly put directly into Pinochet's bank accounts.&lt;ref name=&quot;ContrerasBerrios&quot;&gt;[http://www.cooperativa.cl/p4_noticias/antialone.html?page=http://www.cooperativa.cl/p4_noticias/site/artic/20060710/pags/20060710181933.html General (r) Manuel Contreras: Eugenio Berríos está vivo], ''[[Radio Cooperativa]]'', 10 July 2006 {{es icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pinochet's son Marco Antonio, who had been accused of participating in the drug trade, has denied claims of drug trafficking in his father's administration and announced a lawsuit for libel against [[Manuel Contreras]], who had also claimed Pinochet sold cocaine.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lostiempos.com/noticias/10-07-06/10_07_06_ultimas_int8.php Hijo de Pinochet acusa de &quot;mentiroso y canalla&quot; a ex jefe DINA], ''Los Tiempos'', 10 July 2006{{es icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 25 November 2006, Pinochet marked his 91st birthday by having his wife read a statement written by him, and read to his admirers present for his birthday: &quot;I assume the political responsibility of all that has been done.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Quotes&quot;&gt;[http://www.lanacion.cl/prontus_noticias/site/artic/20061210/pags/20061210221221.html Las frases para el bronce de Pinochet], ''[[La Nacion (Chile)|La Nacion]], 11 December 2006 {{es icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two days later, he was again ordered to house arrest for the kidnapping and murder of two bodyguards of Salvador Allende &lt;!-- UNNECESSARY — Wagner Salinas and Francisco Lara — --&gt;who were arrested the day of the 1973 coup and executed by a firing squad during the Caravan of Death episode.&lt;ref&gt;Eduardo Gallardo: &quot;Pinochet indicted for 1973 executions,&quot; [http://www.thestar.com.my/news/story.asp?file=/2006/11/28/apworld/20061128120419&amp;sec=apworld Associated Press], 27 November 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Nov06&gt;[http://www.20minutos.es/noticia/177449/0/pinochet/procesado/homicidios/ Procesan a Pinochet y ordenan su arresto por los secuestros y homicidios de la &quot;Caravana de la Muerte&quot;], ''[[20minutos]]'', 28 November 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

However, Pinochet died a few days later, on 10 December 2006, without having been convicted of any of the crimes of which he was accused.

==Secret bank accounts, tax evasion and arms deal==
In 2004, a [[United States Senate]] [[money laundering]] investigation led by Senators [[Carl Levin]] (D-MI) and [[Norm Coleman]] (R-MN)—ordered in the wake of the [[11 September 2001 attacks]]—uncovered a network of over 125 securities and bank accounts at [[Riggs Bank]] and other U.S. financial institutions used by Pinochet and his associates for twenty-five years to secretly move millions of dollars.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;United States Senate Permanent Subcommittee on Investigations of the Committee on Governmental Affairs: &quot;Levin-Coleman Staff Report Discloses Web of Secret Accounts Used by Pinochet&quot;, Press Release. US Senate Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs, http://www.senate.gov/~levin/newsroom/release.cfm?id=233631 16 March 2005&lt;/ref&gt;
Though the subcommittee was charged only with investigating compliance of financial institutions under the [[USA PATRIOT Act]], and not the Pinochet regime, Senator Coleman noted:
{{quote|This is a sad, sordid tale of money laundering involving Pinochet accounts at multiple financial institutions using alias names, offshore accounts, and close associates. As a former General and President of Chile, Pinochet was a well-known human rights violator and violent dictator.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot; /&gt;}}

Over several months in 2005, Chilean judge [[Sergio Muñoz]] indicted Augusto Pinochet's wife, [[Lucia Hiriart]]; four of his children — Marco Antonio, Jacqueline, Veronica and Lucia Pinochet; his personal secretary, Monica Ananias; and his former aide Oscar Aitken on tax evasion and falsification charges stemming from the Riggs Bank investigation. In January 2006, daughter Lucia Pinochet was detained at Washington DC-Dulles airport and subsequently deported while attempting to evade the tax charges in Chile.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;U.S. Sends Back Pinochet Daughter,&quot; CNN, 28 January 2006&lt;/ref&gt; In January 2007, the Santiago [[Court of Appeal]]s revoked most of the indictment from Judge Carlos Cerda against the Pinochet family.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.emol.com/noticias/nacional/detalle/detallenoticias.asp?idnoticia=240949 Corte revoca mayoría de procesamientos en caso Riggs], ''[[El Mercurio]]'', 3 January 2007 {{es icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; But Pinochet's five children, his wife and 17 other persons (including two generals, one of his former lawyer and former secretary) were arrested in October 2007 on charges of [[embezzlement]] and use of false passports. They are accused of having illegally transferred $27m (£13.2m) to foreign bank accounts during Pinochet's rule.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/7028503.stm Pinochet family arrested in Chile], ''[[BBC]]'', 4 October 2007 {{en icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://docs.latercera.cl/especiales/2007/cobertura_Caso_Riggs/portada2.html Cobertura Especial: Detienen a familia y principales colaboradores de Pinochet], ''[[La Tercera]]'', 4 October 2007 {{es icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2005, a joint investigation by ''[[The Guardian]]'' and ''[[La Tercera]]'' revealed that the British arms firm [[BAE Systems]] had been identified as paying more than £1m to Pinochet, through a front company in the [[British Virgin Islands]], which BAE has used to channel commission on arms deals.&lt;ref name=&quot;BAE&quot;&gt;[[David Leigh (journalist)|David Leigh]] and Rob Evans, [http://www.guardian.co.uk/chile/story/0,13755,1570335,00.html Revealed: BAE's secret £1m to Pinochet], ''[[The Guardian]]'', 15 September 2005 {{en icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; The payments began in 1997 and lasted until 2004.&lt;ref name=&quot;BAE&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Detectivestory&quot;&gt;[[David Leigh (journalist)|David Leigh]], Jonathan Franklin and Rob Evans, [http://www.guardian.co.uk/chile/story/0,13755,1570165,00.html Detective story that linked £1m Pinochet cash to BAE], ''[[The Guardian]]'', 15 September 2005 {{en icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Furthermore, in 2007, fifteen years of investigation led to the conclusion that the 1992 assassination of DINA Colonel [[Gerardo Huber]] was most probably related to various illegal arms traffic carried out, after Pinochet's resignation from power, by military circles very close to himself.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT&quot;&gt;Larry Rohter, [http://www.nytimes.com/2006/06/19/world/americas/19chile.html?ex=1308369600en=964a159db7c0d614ei=5088partner=rssnytemc=rss Colonel's Death Gives Clues to Pinochet Arms Deals], ''[[The New York Times]]'', 19 June 2006 {{en icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; Huber had been assassinated a short time before he was due to [[testify]] in the case concerning the 1991 illegal [[arms deal|export of weapons]] to [[Croatia]]n army. The deal involved 370 tons of weapons, sold to Croatia by Chile on 7 December 1991, when the former country was under a [[United Nations]]' [[embargo]] because of the [[Croatian War of Independence|support for Croatia]] war in [[Yugoslavia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Memoria&quot;&gt;[http://www.memoriaviva.com/culpables/criminales%20h/huber_gerardo.htm Biographical notice] on ''Memoria viva'' NGO website {{es icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; In January 1992, the judge Hernán Correa de la Cerda wanted to hear Gerardo Huber in this case, but the latter may have been silenced to avoid implicating [[Indictment and arrest of Augusto Pinochet|Pinochet in this new case]]&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coronel&quot;&gt;Jorge Molina Sanhueza, [http://www.lanacion.cl/prontus_noticias/site/artic/20050924/pags/20050924223646.html Gerardo Huber sabía demasiado, pero no alcanzó a contarlo. El coronel que le pena al ejército], ''[[La Nación (Chile)|La Nación]]'', 25 September 2005 {{es icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CDE&quot;&gt;Andrea Chaparro, [http://www.lanacion.cl/prontus_noticias/site/artic/20050814/pags/20050814204006.html CDE insiste en unir caso Huber con tráfico de armas a Croacia], ''[[La Nación (Chile)|La Nación]]'', 15 August 2005 {{es icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;—although the latter was not anymore President, he remained at the time Commander-in-Chief of the Army. Pinochet was at the center of this illegal arms trade, receiving money through various [[offshore company|offshores]] and [[front companies]], including the [[Banco Coutts International]] in [[Miami]].&lt;ref&gt;Andrea Chaparro Solís, [http://www.lanacion.cl/prontus_noticias/site/artic/20060613/pags/20060613215629.html Generales (R) y civiles de Famae procesados en caso armas a Croacia], ''[[La Nación (Chile)|La Nación]]'', 13 June 2006 {{es icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Pinochet was stripped of his [[parliamentary immunity]] in August 2000 by the [[Chilean Supreme Court|Supreme Court]], and indicted by judge [[Juan Guzmán Tapia]]. Guzmán had ordered in 1999 the arrest of five militarists, including General [[Pedro Espinoza Bravo]] of the [[Dirección de Inteligencia Nacional|DINA]], for their role in the [[Caravan of Death]] following the 11 September coup. Arguing that the bodies of the &quot;[[Forced disappearance|disappeared]]&quot; were still missing, he made [[jurisprudence]] which had as effect to lift any [[statute of limitation|prescription]] on the crimes committed by the military. Pinochet's trial continued until his death on 10 December 2006, with an alternation of indictments for specific cases, lifting of immunities by the Supreme Court or to the contrary immunity from prosecution, with his health a main argument for, or against, his prosecution. The Supreme Court affirmed in March 2005 Pinochet's immunity concerning the 1974 assassination of General Carlos Prats in Buenos Aires, which had taken place in the frame of Operation Condor. However, he was deemed fit to stand trial for [[Operation Colombo]], during which 119 political opponents were &quot;disappeared&quot; in Argentina. The Chilean justice also lifted his immunity on the [[Villa Grimaldi]] case, a detention and torture center in the outskirts of Santiago. Pinochet, who still benefited from a reputation of righteousness from his supporters, lost legitimacy when he was put under house arrest on tax fraud and passport forgery, following the publication by the US Senate [[Permanent Subcommittee on Investigations]] of a report concerning the [[Riggs Bank]] in July 2004. The report was a consequence of investigations on financial funding of the [[11 September 2001 attacks]] in the US. The bank controlled between USD $4 million and $8 million of Pinochet's assets, who lived in Santiago in a modest house, dissimulating his wealth. According to the report, Riggs participated in [[money laundering]] for Pinochet, setting up offshore [[shell company|shell corporations]] (referring to Pinochet as only &quot;a former public official&quot;), and hiding his accounts from regulatory agencies. Related to Pinochet's and his family secret bank accounts in United States and in Caribbean islands, this tax fraud filing for an amount of 27 million dollars shocked the conservative sectors who still supported him. Ninety percent of these funds would have been raised between 1990 and 1998, when Pinochet was chief of the Chilean armies, and would essentially have come from [[weapons traffic]] (when purchasing Belgian 'Mirage' air-fighters in 1994, Dutch 'Léopard' tanks, Swiss 'Mowag' tanks or by illegal sales of weapons to [[Croatia]], in the middle of the [[Balkans war]].) His wife, [[Lucía Hiriart]], and his son, Marco Antonio Pinochet, were also sued for complicity. For the fourth time in seven years, Pinochet was indicted by the Chilean justice.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cnn.com/2006/US/01/28/chile.pinochet/?section=cnn_topstories U.S. sends back Pinochet daughter], ''[[CNN]]'', 28 January 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

==Human rights violations==
{{Main|Chile under Pinochet#Human rights violations}}
Pinochet's regime was responsible for various human rights abuses during its reign including [[Extrajudicial killing|murder]] and [[torture]] of political opponents. According to a government commission report that included testimony from more than 30,000 people, Pinochet's government killed at least 3,197 people and tortured about 29,000. Two-thirds of the cases listed in the report happened in 1973.&lt;ref name='DarkLegacy'&gt;{{Cite news| first=Monte | last=Reel | coauthors= J.Y. Smith |authorlink= | title=A Chilean Dictator's Dark Legacy | date=11 December 2006 | publisher= | url =http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/12/10/AR2006121000302.html | work =The Washington Post | pages = | accessdate =18 November 2009 | language = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Professor [[Clive Foss]], in ''The Tyrants: 2500 Years of Absolute Power and Corruption'' (Quercus Publishing 2006), estimates that 1,500–2,000 Chileans were killed or [[Forced disappearance|disappeared]] during the Pinochet regime. In October 1979, the ''[[New York Times]]'' reported that [[Amnesty International]] had documented the disappearance of approximately 1,500 Chileans since 1973.&lt;ref&gt;''A Green Light for The Junta?'' New York Times. 28 October 1977&lt;/ref&gt; Among the killed and disappeared during the military regime were at least 663 Marxist [[Revolutionary Left Movement (Chile)|MIR]] guerrillas.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.archivochile.com/Derechos_humanos/doc_gen_ddhh/hhdddocgen0002.pdf CAIDOS DEL MIR EN DIFERENTE PERIODOS. CEME (CENTRO DE ESTUDIOS MIGUEL ENRIQUEZ.]&lt;/ref&gt; The Manuel Rodríguez Patriotic Front, however, has stated that only 49 FPMR guerrillas were killed but hundreds detained and tortured.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20051104044728/fpmr.org/heroes8.html Aquellos que todo lo dieron. El Rodriguista, 11 Años de Lucha y Dignidad, 1994]&lt;/ref&gt; According to a study in [[Latin American Perspectives]],&lt;ref name=&quot;ExileStudy&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Wright |first1=Thomas C. |last2=Oñate Zúñiga |first2=Rody |year=2007 |title=Chilean political exile |journal=[[Latin American Perspectives]] |volume=34 |issue=4 |page=31}}&lt;/ref&gt; at least 200,000 Chileans (about 2% of Chile's 1973 population) were forced to go into [[exile]]. Additionally, hundreds of thousands left the country in the wake of the economic crises that followed the military coup during the 1970s and 1980s.&lt;ref name=&quot;ExileStudy&quot;/&gt; Some of the key individuals who fled because of [[political persecution]] were followed in their exile by the [[Dirección de Inteligencia Nacional|DINA]] secret police, in the framework of [[Operation Condor]], which linked [[South America]]n [[military dictatorship]]s together against political opponents.

==Death==
[[File:Pinochet muerto.jpg|thumb|Augusto Pinochet on the bier on 11 December 2006]]
[[File:Feretro Pinochet.jpg|thumb|Pinochet's funeral]]
Pinochet suffered a [[myocardial infarction|heart attack]] on the morning of 3 December 2006, and subsequently the same day he was given the [[last rites]]. On 4 December 2006, the Chilean Court of Appeals ordered the release of his house arrest. On 10 December 2006 at 13:30 local time (16:30 UTC) he was taken to the intensive care unit.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.elmundo.es/elmundo/2006/12/10/internacional/1165772627.html?a=9226ef1866a7f79b7121e16dc29be1b4&amp;t=1165774791 Muere el ex dictador Chileno Augusto Pinochet] ''[[EFE]]''&lt;/ref&gt; He died of [[congestive heart failure]] and [[pulmonary edema]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.emol.com/noticias/nacional/detalle/detallenoticias.asp?idnoticia=238569 Augusto Pinochet falleció en el Hospital Militar tras sufrir recaída] &quot;; [[El Mercurio]]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; surrounded by family members, at the Military Hospital at 14:15 local time (17:15 UTC).&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/6167237.stm Chile's General Pinochet 'dead'] ''[[BBC News]]''&lt;/ref&gt;

===Demonstrations===
Massive spontaneous street demonstrations broke out throughout the country upon the learning of his death. In Santiago, opponents celebrated at the Alameda avenue, while supporters grieved outside the Military Hospital. Pinochet's remains were publicly exhibited on 11 December 2006 at the Military Academy in [[Las Condes]]. During this ceremony Francisco Cuadrado Prats, the grandson of [[Carlos Prats]], a former Commander in Chief of the Army in Allende's Government, murdered by Pinochet's secret police, spat on the coffin, and was quickly surrounded by supporters of Pinochet, who kicked and insulted him. Pinochet's funeral took place the following day at the same venue before a gathering of 60,000 supporters.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Pinochet's Funeral Draws 360,000&quot;, CBA news, http://www.cbc.ca/world/story/2006/12/12/pinochet-funeral.html&lt;/ref&gt;

===Funeral===
In a government decision, he was not granted a [[state funeral]], an honor bestowed upon constitutionally elected Chilean presidents, but a [[military funeral]] as former [[commander-in-chief]] of the Army appointed by President Salvador Allende. The government also refused to declare an official [[national day of mourning]], but it did authorize flags at military barracks to fly at [[half staff]]. Pinochet's coffin was also allowed to be draped in a Chilean flag. Socialist President [[Michelle Bachelet]], whose father [[Alberto Bachelet|Alberto]] was temporarily imprisoned and tortured after the 1973 coup, dying shortly after from heart complications, said it would be &quot;a violation of [her] conscience&quot; to attend a state funeral for Pinochet.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Clashes Break out after Pinochet's death&quot;, Yahoo!News, 11 December 2006&lt;/ref&gt; The only government authority present at the public funeral was the Defense Minister, [[Vivianne Blanlot]].

===Cremation===
Pinochet's body was [[cremation|cremated]] in &quot;Parque del Mar&quot; [[cemetery]], [[Concón]] on 12 December 2006, on his request to &quot;avoid vandalism of his tomb,&quot; according to his son Marco Antonio.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.plenglish.com/article.asp?ID=%7B1D9E9839-D2D8-4255-8D40-68053E9D60B0%7D)&amp;language=EN Family Wants Pinochet Cremation]{{Dead link|date=October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; His ashes were delivered to his family later that day, and are deposited in one of his personal residences. The armed forces refused to allow his ashes to be deposited on any military grounds.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lanacion.cl/prontus_noticias/site/artic/20061225/pags/20061225180129.html Pedregoso camino para que cenizas de Pinochet llegaran a Los Boldos], La Nación 26 December 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Chilean presidential election, 1970]]
*[[History of Chile]]
*''[[Missing (film)|Missing]]'', a film based on the life of U.S. journalist [[Charles Horman]], who disappeared in the aftermath of the Pinochet coup
*[[United States intervention in Chile]]
*[[David H. Popper]], US ambassador to Chile (1974–77).

==Footnotes and references==
{{Reflist|
refs=
&lt;ref name=&quot;return&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=IxoPAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=jYQDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=6782,3529255&amp;dq=chile+return+to+democracy%20Deseret%20News:%20Bush%20praises%20revival%20of%20democracy%20in%20Chile%20%28Dec%206,%201990%29|title=Bush praises revival of Democracy in Chile|publisher=Google news|accessdate=21 September 2009}}
*{{Cite news|url=http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/latimes/access/60017525.html?dids=60017525:60017525&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;type=current&amp;date=Mar+13%2C+1990&amp;author=JAMES+F.+SMITH&amp;pub=Los+Angeles+Times+%28pre-1997+Fulltext%29&amp;desc=80%2C000+Chileans+Cheer+Return+of+Democracy+in+%60Stadium+of+Pain%27&amp;pqatl=google%20Los%20Angeles%20times:%2080,000%20Chileans%20Cheer%20Return%20of%20Democracy%20in%20%60Stadium%20of%20Pain%27%20%28March%201990%29|title=80,000 Chileans Cheer Return...|publisher=LA Times|accessdate=21 September 2009 | first=James F. | last=Smith | date=13 March 1990}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;fascist&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/pinochet-was-a-vile-fascist-but-allende-was-no-hero-1179768.html|title=Pinochet was a vile Fascist...|publisher=The Independent|accessdate=21 September 2009 | location=London | first=Andrew | last=Neil | date=22 October 1998}}
*{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=WSsGEsBUsVcC&amp;lpg=PA96&amp;dq=pinochet%20fascism&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q=pinochet%20fascism|title=Blackshorts and Reds|publisher=Google Books|accessdate=21 September 2009 | first=Michael | last=Parenti | isbn=978-0-87286-329-3|year=1997}}
*{{cite web|url=http://www.globalresearch.ca/index.php?context=va&amp;aid=4145|title=Mourning for Pinochet...|publisher=GlobalResearch.ca|accessdate=21 September 2009}}
*{{cite web|url=http://www.tni.org/detail_page.phtml?page=letelier-docs_291178|title=Day of Reckoning Near for Pinochet|publisher=Transnational Institute|accessdate=21 September 2009}}
*Alistair Horne, &quot;The case for Henry Kissinger&quot; – The Independent (3587 words, 18 August 2009)
*Alide Dasnois, &quot;Chile and the absurdity of ideological social engineering&quot; – The Cape Times (1226 words, 8 July 2009)
*Michael Posner, &quot;What it's like to arrive at a place called exile; Drawing on personal experience, Carmen Aguirre's play chronicles the plight of Chilean refugees fleeing the Pinochet regime&quot; – The Globe &amp; Mail (829 words, 17 September 2009)
*{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=lIz3ykCJlaMC&amp;lpg=PA302&amp;dq=pinochet%20%22fascist%20policies%22&amp;pg=PA302#v=onepage&amp;q=pinochet%20%22fascist%20policies%22|title=The Identity of Liberation in Latin American Thought...|publisher=Google Books|accessdate=21 September 2009 | first=Mario | last=Sàenz | isbn=978-0-7391-0084-4|date=31 August 1999}}
&lt;/ref&gt;|colwidth=30em}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|group=note}}

==Further reading==
* {{Cite book|last=Muñoz |first=Heraldo |authorlink=Heraldo Muñoz
 |coauthors= |editor= |others=
 |title=The dictator's shadow : life under Augusto Pinochet
 |origdate= |origyear= |origmonth=
 |url=http://lccn.loc.gov/2008015654
 |accessdate=20 January 2008
 |edition= |series= |date=
 |year=2008
 |month=
 |publisher=Basic Books |location=New York
 |language=
 |isbn=978-0-465-00250-4
 |oclc= |doi= |pages= |chapter= |chapterurl= |quote= }} (Reviewed in [[Washington Post]], Book World, p.&amp;nbsp;2, 2009-10-19)

==External links==
{{Sister project links|Augusto Pinochet}}
*[http://www.pinochet-a-biography.org Augusto Pinochet (1915–2006) – A Biography]
*[http://www.france24.com/france24Public/en/special-reports/20061211-dossier-pinochet-dies.html France 24 coverage] – Augusto Pinochet's Necrology on France 24
*[http://news.bbc.co.uk/hi/english/special_report/1998/10/98/the_pinochet_file/newsid_198000/198306.stm BBC coverage] (special report)
*[http://www.chacabuco.org/ Documentary Film on Chilean Concentration Camp from Pinochet's Regime: Chacabuco]
*[http://www.gwu.edu/~nsarchiv/news/20000919/index.html CIA Acknowledges Ties to Pinochet’s Repression] from The National Security Archive
*[http://www.cyberussr.com/hcunn/for/chile-73.html Chile under Allende and Pinochet]
*[http://www.memoriaviva.com/ Human rights violation under Pinochet]
*[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,60-2497858,00.html The Times obituary]
*[http://dollarsandsense.org/archives/2004/0904cypher.html Analysis of economic policy under Pinochet] by economist Jim Cypher in [[Dollars &amp; Sense]] magazine
*[http://www.newenglishreview.org/custpage.cfm?frm=5206&amp;sec_id=5206 Chile: The Price of Democracy] ''New English Review''
*[http://www.hoover.org/publications/digest/6731331.html What Pinochet Did for Chile] ''Hoover Digest (2007 No. 1)''
*[http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/1859843603 Pinochet and Me] by journalist Marc Cooper
*[http://www.democracynow.org/2010/9/15/another_9_11_anniversary_september_11 When US-Backed Pinochet Forces Took Power in Chile] – video report by ''[[Democracy Now!]]''

{{S-start}}
{{S-off}}
{{Succession box
| title=[[President of Chile]]
| before=[[Salvador Allende]]
| after=[[Patricio Aylwin]]
| years='''1974–1990'''}}
{{S-mil}}
{{Succession box
| title=[[Chilean Army|Army Commander-in-chief]]
| before=[[Carlos Prats]]
| after=[[Ricardo Izurieta]]
| years='''1973–1998'''}}
{{end}}
{{Navboxes
|title = History of Chile
|list  =
{{Presidents of Chile}}
{{1973 Chilean coup d'état}}
{{Augusto Pinochet}}
}}
{{Cold War figures}}
&lt;!-- DISPUTED
charged:

probably pov categories:
--&gt;

{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}

{{Authority control|VIAF=27871838}}
{{Persondata
|NAME=Pinochet, Augusto
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=Pinochet Ugarte, Augusto José Ramón (full name)
|SHORT DESCRIPTION=Chilean General and Politician
|DATE OF BIRTH={{Birth date|1915|11|25|df=y}}
|PLACE OF BIRTH=[[Valparaíso]], Chile
|DATE OF DEATH={{Death date|2006|12|10|df=y}}
|PLACE OF DEATH=[[Santiago de Chile]]}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Pinochet, Augusto}}
[[Category:Augusto Pinochet|*]]
[[Category:1915 births]]
[[Category:2006 deaths]]
[[Category:Chilean anti-communists]]
[[Category:Chilean Army generals]]
[[Category:Chilean people of French descent]]
[[Category:Chilean people of Basque descent]]
[[Category:Attempted assassination survivors]]
[[Category:Chilean memoirists]]
[[Category:Chilean Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:Chile under Augusto Pinochet]]
[[Category:Cold War leaders]]
[[Category:Shooting survivors]]
[[Category:Deaths from myocardial infarction]]
[[Category:Heads of state of Chile]]
[[Category:Leaders who took power by coup]]
[[Category:Operation Condor]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of the Liberator General San Martin]]
[[Category:Opposition to Fidel Castro]]
[[Category:People from Valparaíso]]
[[Category:Political corruption]]
[[Category:Presidents of Chile]]
[[Category:Tax evaders]]
[[Category:Legislators with life tenure]]
[[Category:People indicted for crimes against humanity]]
{{Link FA|mk}}

[[ang:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[ar:أوغستو بينوشيه]]
[[an:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[ast:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[az:Auqusto Pinoçet]]
[[bn:আউগুস্তো পিনোচে]]
[[zh-min-nan:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[be:Аўгуста Піначэт]]
[[be-x-old:Аўгуста Піначэт]]
[[bg:Аугусто Пиночет]]
[[bs:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[br:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[ca:Augusto Pinochet Ugarte]]
[[cs:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[cy:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[da:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[de:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[et:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[el:Αουγκούστο Πινοσέτ]]
[[es:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[eo:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[ext:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[eu:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[fa:آگوستو پینوشه]]
[[fr:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[ga:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[gl:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[ko:아우구스토 피노체트]]
[[hsb:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[hr:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[io:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[id:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[is:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[it:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[he:אוגוסטו פינושה]]
[[ka:აუგუსტო პინოჩეტი]]
[[la:Augustus Pinochet]]
[[lv:Augusto Pinočets]]
[[lb:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[lt:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[mk:Аугусто Пиноче]]
[[ml:ആഗസ്റ്റോ പിനോഷെ]]
[[xmf:აუგუსტო პინოჩეტი]]
[[mn:Аугусто Пиночет]]
[[nl:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[ja:アウグスト・ピノチェト]]
[[no:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[nn:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[oc:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[pnb:آگسٹو پنوشے]]
[[pms:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[pl:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[pt:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[ro:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[ru:Пиночет, Аугусто]]
[[se:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[sco:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[sq:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[scn:Augustu Pinochet]]
[[simple:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[sk:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[sl:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[sr:Аугусто Пиноче]]
[[sh:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[fi:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[sv:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[tl:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[tg:Августо Пиночет]]
[[tr:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[uk:Августо Піночет]]
[[ur:آگسٹو پنوشے]]
[[vi:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[wa:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[yo:Augusto Pinochet]]
[[zh:奥古斯托·皮诺切特]]</text>
      <sha1>migdvx5ixmy3v4kwrpy1pnrijueqlxs</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
