<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Comedy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>20914042</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520880579</id>
      <parentid>520867662</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-01T11:12:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>129.175.64.63</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Removed spam</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25783">{{About|a genre of dramatic works|other uses|Comedy (disambiguation)|the popular meaning of the term &quot;comedy&quot;|Humour}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Inadequate lead|date=April 2011}} {{Globalize|date=August 2008}}
[[File:Thalia sarcophagus Louvre Ma475.jpg|thumb|right|[[Thalia (muse)|Thalia]], muse of comedy, holding a comic mask - detail of “Muses Sarcophagus”, the [[nine Muses]] and their attributes; marble, early second century AD, Via Ostiense - ''Louvre'']]
[[Filche:Charlie Chaplin.jpg|thumb|right|[[Charlie Chaplin]]]]

'''Comedy''' (from the {{lang-el|[[wikt:κωμῳδία|κωμῳδία]]}}, ''kōmōidía''), in the contemporary meaning of the term, is any discourse or work generally intended to be [[humor]]ous or to amuse by inducing laughter, especially in [[theatre]], [[television]], [[film]] and [[stand-up comedy]]. This sense of the term must be carefully distinguished from its academic one, namely the comic [[theatre]], whose [[Western culture|Western]] origins are found in [[Ancient Greece]]. In the [[Athenian democracy]], the [[public opinion]] of voters was influenced by the [[political satire]] performed by the [[comic poets]] at the [[Ancient Greek theatre|theaters]].&lt;ref&gt;Henderson, J. (1993) ''Comic Hero versus Political Elite'' pp.307-19 in {{cite book |editor=Sommerstein, A.H.; S. Halliwell, J. Henderson, B. Zimmerman |title=Tragedy, Comedy and the Polis |year=1993 |publisher=Levante Editori |location=Bari}}&lt;/ref&gt; The theatrical genre can be simply described as a dramatic performance which pits two societies against each other in an amusing [[agon]] or conflict. [[Northrop Frye]] famously depicted these two opposing sides as a &quot;Society of Youth&quot; and a &quot;Society of the Old&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;([[Anatomy of Criticism]], 1957)&lt;/ref&gt; but this [[dichotomy]] is seldom described as an entirely satisfactory explanation. A later view characterizes the essential agon of comedy as a struggle between a relatively powerless youth and the societal conventions that pose obstacles to his hopes. In this struggle, the youth is understood to be constrained by his lack of social authority, and is left with little choice but to take recourse in ruses which engender very dramatic [[irony]] which provokes [[laughter]].&lt;ref&gt;(Marteinson, 2006)&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Satire]] and [[political satire]] use ironic comedy to portray persons or social institutions as ridiculous or corrupt, thus alienating their audience from the object of humor. Satire is a type of comedy. [[Parody]] subverts popular genres and forms, using certain [[irony|ironic]] changes to critique those forms from within (though not necessarily in a condemning way). [[Screwball comedy]] derives its humor largely from bizarre, surprising (and improbable) situations or characters. [[Black comedy]] is defined by dark humor that makes light of so-called dark or [[evil]] elements in human nature. Similarly [[Toilet humor|scatological humor]], sexual humor, and [[race humor]] create comedy by violating [[Convention (norm)|social conventions]] or [[taboo]]s in comic ways. A [[comedy of manners]] typically takes as its subject a particular part of society (usually upper class society) and uses humor to parody or satirize the behavior and mannerisms of its members. [[Romantic comedy]] is a popular genre that depicts burgeoning romance in humorous terms and focuses on the foibles of those who are falling in love.

== Etymology ==
[[File:TragicComicMasksHadriansVillamosaic.jpg|thumb|Tragic Comic Masks of &lt;noinclude&gt;[[Theatre of Ancient Greece|Ancient Greek Theatre]]
represented in the  [[Hadrian's Villa]] mosaic.]]

The word &quot;comedy&quot; is derived from the [[Ancient Greek language|Classical Greek]] κωμῳδία ''kōmōidía'', which is a compound either of [[komos|κῶμος]] ''kômos'' (revel) or κώμη ''kṓmē'' (village) and ᾠδή ''ōidḗ'' (singing); it is possible that ''κῶμος'' itself is derived from ''κώμη'', and originally meant a village revel. The adjective &quot;comic&quot; (Greek κωμικός ''kōmikós),'' which strictly means that which relates to comedy is, in modern usage, generally confined to the sense of &quot;laughter-provoking&quot;.&lt;ref name = &quot;Cornford1934pn&quot;&gt;Cornford (1934){{Page needed|date=June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Of this, the word came into modern usage through the Latin ''comoedia'' and Italian ''commedia'' and has, over time, passed through various shades of meaning.&lt;ref name = OED&gt;Oxford English Dictionary&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Ancient Greece|Greeks]] and [[Ancient Rome|Romans]] confined the [[word]] &quot;comedy&quot; to descriptions of stage-plays with happy endings. In the [[Middle Ages]], the term expanded to include narrative poems with happy endings and a lighter tone. In this sense [[Dante]] used the term in the title of his poem, ''[[The Divine Comedy|La Commedia]]''. As time progressed, the word came more and more to be associated with any sort of performance intended to cause laughter.&lt;ref name = OED/&gt; During the Middle Ages, the term &quot;comedy&quot; became synonymous with [[satire]], and later [[humour]] in general, after [[Poetics (Aristotle)|Aristotle's ''Poetics'']] was translated into [[Arabic language|Arabic]] in the [[Islamic Golden Age|medieval Islamic world]], where it was elaborated upon by [[Arabic literature|Arabic writers]] and [[Early Islamic philosophy|Islamic philosophers]], such as Abu Bischr, his pupil [[Al-Farabi]], [[Avicenna]], and [[Averroes]]. Due to cultural differences, they disassociated comedy from [[Greek drama]]tic representation and instead identified it with [[Arabic poetry|Arabic poetic]] themes and forms, such as ''[[hija]]'' (satirical poetry). They viewed comedy as simply the &quot;art of reprehension&quot;, and made no reference to light and cheerful events, or troublous beginnings and happy endings, associated with classical Greek comedy. After the [[Latin translations of the 12th century]], the term &quot;comedy&quot; thus gained a more general semantic meaning in [[medieval literature]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.2307/470561|title=Comedy as Satire in Hispano-Arabic Spain|first=Edwin J.|jstor=470561|last=Webber|journal=Hispanic Review|volume=26|issue=1|month=January |year=1958|publisher=University of Pennsylvania Press|pages=1–11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the late 20th century, emerged among scholars the tendency to pragmatically prefer the term ''[[laughter]]'' to comprehensively refer to the whole [[gamut]] of the comic, to avoid the classification in ambiguous and problematically defined genres and fields like [[humour]], [[grotesque]], [[irony]], and [[satire]].&lt;ref&gt;Herman Braet, Guido Latré, Werner Verbeke (2003) [http://books.google.com/books?id=6mqDEpy0YUsC&amp;pg=PA1 ''Risus mediaevalis: laughter in medieval literature and art''] p.1 quotation: {{quotation|The deliberate use by Menard of the term 'le rire' rather than 'l'humour' reflects accurately the current evidency to incorporate all instances of the comic in the analysis, while the classification in genres and fields such as grotesque, humour and even irony or satire always poses problems. The terms humour and laughter are therefore pragmatically used in recent historiography to cover the entire spectrum.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ménard, Philippe (1988) ''Le rire et le sourire au Moyen Age dans la litterature et les arts. Essai de problématique'' in Bouché, T. and Charpentier, H. (eds., 1988) ''Le rire au Moyen Âge, Actes du colloque international de Bordeaux'', pp.7-30&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==

=== Dionysiac origins and Aristophanes ===
[[File:Crátera ática de columnas (M.A.N. 1999-99-65) 02.jpg|thumb|right|upright|A [[satyr]] masturbating. Detail of side B of a Greek column krater showing two satyrs and a [[maenad]] in a [[Dionysiac]] scene.]]
{{main|Old Comedy}}
Starting from 425 BCE, [[Aristophanes]], a comic playwright and satirical author of the [[Theatre of ancient Greece|Ancient Greek Theater]] wrote 40 comedies, 11 of which survive and are still being performed. Aristophanes developed his type of comedy from the earlier [[satyr plays]], which were shamelessly [[obscene]].&lt;ref&gt;Aristophanes (1996) [http://books.google.com/books?id=YhaawA_m9SEC&amp;pg=PR9 ''Lysistrata''], Introduction, p.ix, published by Nick Hern Books&lt;/ref&gt; Of the satyr plays only survive examples by Euripides which are not representative of the genre.&lt;ref&gt;Reckford, Kenneth J. (1987)[http://books.google.com/books?id=v9MSdTvbOFAC&amp;pg=PA105 ''Aristophanes' Old-and-new Comedy: Six essays in perspective''] p.105&lt;/ref&gt; In ancient [[Greece]], comedy originated in bawdy and [[ribald]] songs or recitations apropos of [[phallic processions]] and fertility festivals or gatherings.&lt;ref name = &quot;Cornford1934p3&quot;&gt;[[Francis MacDonald Cornford|Cornford, F.M.]] (1934) [http://books.google.com/books?id=uhE9AAAAIAAJ ''The Origin of Attic Comedy''] pp.3-4 quotation: {{quotation|That Comedy sprang up and took shape in connection with Dionysiac or Phallic ritual has never been doubted.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Around 335 BCE, philosopher [[Aristotle]], in his work ''[[Poetics (Aristotle)|Poetics]]'', stated that comedy originated in [[Phallic processions]] and the light treatment of the otherwise base and ugly. He also adds that the origins of comedy are obscure because it was not treated seriously from its inception.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?lookup=Aristot.+Poet.+1449a |title=Aristotle, Poetics, lines beginning at 1449a |publisher=Perseus.tufts.edu |date= |accessdate=2012-06-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; That said, comedy had its own [[Muse]]: [[Thalia (muse)|Thalia]].

Also in ''Poetics'', Aristotle defined Comedy as one of the original four genres of [[literature]]. The other three genres are [[tragedy]], [[epic poetry]], and [[lyric poetry]]. Literature in general is defined by Aristotle as a [[mimesis]], or imitation of life. Comedy is the third form of literature, being the most divorced from a true mimesis. Tragedy is the truest mimesis, followed by epic poetry, comedy and lyric poetry. The genre of comedy is defined by a certain pattern according to Aristotle's definition. Comedies begin with low or base characters seeking insignificant aims, and end with some accomplishment of the aims which either lightens the initial baseness or reveals the insignificance of the aims. A modern application of this theory would be the story the &quot;ugly&quot; guy who goes about things the wrong way, but in the end wins the &quot;pretty&quot; girl. Comedies usually also have elements of the supernatural, typically magic and, for the Ancient Greeks, the gods. Comedy includes the unrealistic in order to portray the realistic. For the Greeks, all comedies ended happily which is opposite of tragedy, which ends sadly.

=== In ancient Sanskrit drama ===
After 200 BCE, in ancient [[Sanskrit drama]], [[Bharata Muni]]'s ''[[Natya Shastra]]'' defined humour (''hāsyam'') as one of the nine ''[[nava rasas]]'', or principle ''[[Rasa (aesthetics)|rasas]]'' (emotional responses), which can be inspired in the audience by ''bhavas'', the imitations of emotions that the actors perform. Each ''rasa'' was associated with a specific ''bhavas'' portrayed on stage. In the case of humour, it was associated with mirth (''hasya'').

=== Shakespearean and Elizabethan comedy ===
[[File:MND title page.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Title page of the [[first quarto]] of Shakespeare's [[Midsummer Night's Dream]] (1600)]]
&quot;Comedy&quot;, in its [[Elizabethan]] usage, had a very different meaning from modern comedy. A Shakespearean comedy is one that has a happy ending, usually involving marriages between the unmarried characters, and a tone and style that is more light-hearted than Shakespeare's other plays.&lt;ref&gt;Regan, Richard. &quot;[http://www.faculty.fairfield.edu/rjregan/rrScom.htm Shakespearean comedy]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

=== After the 19th century ===
[[File:Lewis and Martin.jpg|upright|thumb|[[Dean Martin]] and [[Jerry Lewis]] (ca. 1950)]]
[[File:Rowan Atkinson and Manneken Pis.jpg|upright|thumb|[[Rowan Atkinson]] as [[Mr. Bean]]]]
[[File:Jackie Chan Cannes.jpg|thumb|upright|Jackie Chan at the [[2008 Cannes Film Festival]]]]
[[File:Oleg popov2.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Oleg Popov|Popov the Clown]] in 2009]]
[[File:Dame Edna at the royal wedding cropped.jpg|upright|thumb|[[Barry Humphries]] in character in London as &quot;[[Dame Edna Everage]]&quot; on the day of the 2011 [[Wedding of Prince William and Kate Middleton]]]]
The advent of cinema in the late 19th century, and later radio and television in the 20th century broadened the access of comedians to the general public. [[Charlie Chaplin]], through silent film, became one of the best known faces on earth. The silent tradition lived on well in to the 20th century through mime artists like [[Marcel Marceau]], and the physical comedy of artists like [[Rowan Atkinson]] as [[Mr Bean]]. The tradition of the circus clown also continued, with such as [[Bozo the Clown]] in the United States and [[Oleg Popov]] in Russia. Radio provided new possibilities - with Britain producing the influential [[Goon Show]] after the Second World War. [[American cinema]] has produced a great number of globally renowned comedy artists, from [[Laurel and Hardy]], the [[Three Stooges]], [[Abbott and Costello]], [[Martin and Lewis|Dean Martin and Jerry Lewis]], as well as [[Bob Hope]] during the mid-20th century, to performers like [[George Carlin]], [[Robin Williams]], and [[Eddie Murphy]] at the end of the century. [[Hollywood]] attracted many international talents like Canadian comics [[Dan Aykroyd]], [[Jim Carrey]], and [[Mike Myers]]. Among the most successful non-Hollywood comics was [[Australian comedy|Australian comedian]]  [[Paul Hogan]] in character as [[Crocodile Dundee]]. Other centres of creative comic activity have been the [[cinema of Hong Kong]], [[Bollywood]], and French [[farce]].

American television has also been an influential force in world comedy: with American series like ''[[M*A*S*H (TV series)|M*A*S*H]]'', ''[[Seinfeld]]'' and [[The Simpsons]] achieving large followings around the world. British television comedy also remains influential, with quintessential works including ''[[Fawlty Towers]]'', [[Monty Python]], ''[[Dad's Army]]'', ''[[Blackadder]]'', and ''[[The Office (UK TV series)|The Office]]''.
Australian satirist [[Barry Humphries]], whose comic creations include the housewife and &quot;gigastar&quot; Dame [[Edna Everage]], For his delivery of Dadaist and [[Absurdism|absurdist]] humour to millions, was described by biographer Anne Pender in 2010 as not only &quot;the most significant theatrical figure of our time ... [but] the most significant comedian to emerge since [[Charlie Chaplin]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.brisbanetimes.com.au/entertainment/books/absurd-moments-in-the-frocks-of-the-dame-20100914-15ar3.html |title=Absurd moments: in the frocks of the dame |first=Steve |last=Meacham |publisher=Brisbanetimes.com.au |date=2010-09-15 |accessdate=2011-12-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Studies on the theory of the comic ==
The phenomena connected with [[laughter]] and that which provokes it have been carefully investigated by psychologists. They agreed the predominant characteristics are incongruity or contrast in the object and shock or emotional seizure on the part of the subject. It has also been held that the feeling of superiority is an essential factor: thus [[Thomas Hobbes]] speaks of laughter as a &quot;sudden glory&quot;. Modern investigators have paid much attention to the origin both of laughter and of smiling, as well as the development of the &quot;play instinct&quot; and its emotional expression.

[[George Meredith]],
''[[Essay on Comedy]]'', said that &quot;One excellent test of the civilization of a country ... I take to be the flourishing of the Comic idea and Comedy; and the test of true Comedy is that it shall awaken thoughtful laughter.&quot; Laughter is said to be the cure to being sick. Studies show that people who laugh more often get sick less.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://www.ep.tc/realist/15/03.html |title=An impolite interview with Lenny Bruce |journal=The Realist |issue=15 |month=February |year=1960 |page=3 |accessdate=2011-12-30 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://emotional-literacy-education.com/classic-books-online-b/esycm10.htm |title=Essay on Comedy, Comic Spirit |first=George |last=Meredith|publisher=Encyclopedia of the Self, by Mark Zimmerman |year=1987 |accessdate=2011-12-30 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Forms ==
{{Main|Comedic genres}}

Comedy may be divided into multiple [[genre]]s based on the source of humor, the method of delivery, and the context in which it is delivered: for instance, [[standup comedy]], improvisation, [[slapstick]]. The different forms often overlap, and most comedy can fit into multiple genres. Some of the sub-genres of comedy are [[farce]], [[comedy of manners]], [[burlesque]], and [[satire]].

Some comedy apes certain cultural forms: for instance, parody and [[satire]] often rigidly parody the conventions of the genre they are parodying. ''[[The Onion]]'' and ''[[The Colbert Report]]'' parody newspapers and television news shows like ''[[The O'Reilly Factor]]''. Meanwhile, more character-driven comedy can transcend genre and exist in both, say, film, television and books.

== Performing arts ==
{{Performing arts}}
{{Main|Comedy (drama)}}
{{Prose|section|date=April 2008}}

=== Historical forms ===
* [[Ancient Greek comedy]], as practiced by [[Aristophanes]] and [[Menander]]
* [[Ancient Roman comedy]], as practiced by [[Plautus]] and [[Terence]]
* [[Burlesque]], from [[Music hall]] and [[Vaudeville]] to [[Performance art]]
* [[City comedy|Citizen comedy]], as practiced by [[Thomas Dekker (poet)|Thomas Dekker]], [[Thomas Middleton]] and [[Ben Jonson]]
* [[Clown]]s such as [[Richard Tarlton]], [[William Kempe]], and [[Robert Armin]]
* [[Comedy of humours]], as practiced by [[Ben Jonson]] and [[George Chapman]]
* Comedy of intrigue, as practiced by [[Niccolò Machiavelli]] and [[Lope de Vega]]
* [[Comedy of manners]], as practiced by [[Molière]], [[William Wycherley]] and [[William Congreve]]
* [[Comedy of menace]], as practiced by [[David Campton]] and [[Harold Pinter]]
* ''[[comédie larmoyante]]'' or 'tearful comedy', as practiced by [[Pierre-Claude Nivelle de La Chaussée]] and [[Louis-Sébastien Mercier]]
* ''[[Commedia dell'arte]]'', as practiced in the twentieth-century by [[Dario Fo]], [[Vsevolod Meyerhold]], and [[Jacques Copeau]]
* [[Farce]], from [[Georges Feydeau]] to [[Joe Orton]] and [[Alan Ayckbourn]]
* [[Jester]]
* Laughing comedy, as practiced by [[Oliver Goldsmith]] and [[Richard Brinsley Sheridan]]
* [[Restoration comedy]], as practiced by [[George Etherege]], [[Aphra Behn]] and [[John Vanbrugh]]
* Sentimental comedy, as practiced by [[Colley Cibber]] and [[Richard Steele]]
* [[Shakespearean comedy]], as practiced by [[William Shakespeare]]
* [[Stand-up comedy]]
* [[Dada]]ist and [[Surrealism|Surrealist]] performance, usually in [[cabaret]] form
* [[Theatre of the Absurd]], used by some critics to describe [[Samuel Beckett]], [[Harold Pinter]], [[Jean Genet]] and [[Eugène Ionesco]]&lt;ref&gt;This list was compiled with reference to ''The Cambridge Guide to Theatre'' (1998).&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Sketch comedy]]

=== Plays ===
* [[Comedy (drama)|Comic theatre]]
** [[Musical theater#Development of musical comedy|Musical comedy]] and palace

=== Opera ===
* [[Comic opera]]

=== Improvisational comedy ===
* [[Improvisational theatre]]
* [[Bouffon]] comedy
* [[Clowns]]

=== Joke ===
* [[One-liner joke]]
* [[Blonde jokes]]
* [[Shaggy dog story|Shaggy-dog story]]
* [[An Englishman, an Irishman and a Scotsman|Paddy Irishman joke]]

=== Stand-up comedy ===
[[Stand-up comedy]] is a mode of comic performance in which the performer addresses the audience directly, usually speaking in their own person rather than as a dramatic [[Character (arts)|character]].
* [[Impressionist (entertainment)]]
* [[Alternative comedy]]
* [[Comedy club]]
* [[Comedy album]]s

== Events and awards ==
* [[British Comedy Awards]]
* [[Canadian Comedy Awards]]
* [[Cat Laughs|Cat Laughs Comedy Festival]]
* [[The Comedy Festival]], in Aspen, formerly the HBO Comedy Arts Festival
* [http://www.comedywalk.com/ Comedy Walk], monthly comedy festival in Los Angeles
* [[Edinburgh Festival Fringe]]
* [[Edinburgh Comedy Festival]]
* Halifax Comedy Festival
* [[Just for laughs]] festival
* [[Leicester Comedy Festival]]
* [[Melbourne International Comedy Festival]]
* [[New Zealand International Comedy Festival]]
* [[New York Underground Comedy Festival]]
* [[HK International Comedy Festival]]
* Vancouver Comedy Festival

== List of comedians ==
* [[List of stand-up comedians]]
* [[List of musical comedians]]
* [[List of Australian comedians]]
* [[List of British comedians]]
* [[List of Canadian comedians]]
* [[List of Finnish comedians]]
* [[List of German language comedians]]
* [[List of Indian comedians]]
* [[List of Italian comedians]]
* [[List of Mexican comedians]]
* [[List of Puerto Rican comedians]]

== Mass media ==
{{literature}}
{{Prose|section|date=April 2008}}

=== Literature ===
{{expand section|date=April 2010}}
* [[Comic novel]]
* [[Light poetry]]

=== Film ===
* [[Comedy film]]
** [[Anarchic comedy film]]
** [[Gross-out film]]
** [[Parody film]]
** [[Romantic comedy film]]
** [[Screwball comedy film]]
** [[Slapstick film]]

=== Television and radio ===
* [[Television comedy]]
** [[Situation comedy]]
* [[Radio comedy]]

==== Lists of comedy television programs ====
* [[British sitcom]]
* [[British comedy]]
* [[Comedy Central]] - A television channel devoted strictly to comedy.
* [[German television comedy]]
* [[List of British TV shows remade for the American market]]
* [[Paramount Comedy (Spain)]].
* [[Paramount Comedy]] [[Paramount Comedy 1|1]] and [[Paramount Comedy 2|2]].
* [[TBS (TV network)]]
* [[The Comedy Channel]] (Australia)
* [[The Comedy Channel (UK)]]
* [[The Comedy Channel (USA)]] not to be confused with [[Ha! (TV channel)|HA!]] - channels that have merged into [[Comedy Central]].
* [[The Comedy Network]], a Canadian TV channel.
* [[Gold (TV channel)|Gold]]

== See also ==
{{Portal|Comedy}}
* [[List of comedy television series]]
* [[List of genres]]

== References ==

=== Footnotes ===
{{Reflist|30em}}

=== Notations ===
{{Refbegin|30em}}
* {{cite book|author=Aristotle| title=[[Poetics (Aristotle)|Poetics]]}}
* {{cite book|last=Buckham |first=Philip Wentworth | url=http://books.google.com/?id=IjAZAAAAYAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=The+Theatre+of+the+Greeks|title=Theatre of the Greeks| year=1827}}
* {{cite book|last=Marteinson |first=Peter| year=2006| url=http://www.chass.utoronto.ca/french/as-sa/editors/origins.html | title=On the Problem of the Comic: A Philosophical Study on the Origins of Laughter| publisher= Legas Press| location=Ottawa}}
* Pickard-Cambridge, Sir Arthur Wallace
** ''[[Dithyramb]], Tragedy, and Comedy '', 1927.
** ''The Theatre of Dionysus in Athens'', 1946.
** ''The Dramatic Festivals of Athens'', 1953.
* {{cite book|last=Raskin |first=Victor| title=The Semantic Mechanisms of Humor| year=1985 |publisher=Springer |isbn=978-90-277-1821-1 }}
* {{cite book|last=Riu |first=Xavier | title=Dionysism and Comedy| year=1999| url=http://ccat.sas.upenn.edu/bmcr/2000/2000-06-13.html}}
* {{cite book|last=Sourvinou-Inwood |first=Christiane| title=Tragedy and Athenian Religion| publisher=Lexington Books | year=2003 |isbn=978-0-7391-0400-2 }}
* {{cite book|last=Trypanis |first=C.A.|title=Greek Poetry from Homer to Seferis|publisher=University of Chicago Press|year=1981}}
* {{cite book|last=Wiles |first=David| title=The Masked Menander: Sign and Meaning in Greek and Roman Performance| year=1991 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |isbn=978-0-521-40135-7 }}
{{Refend}}

== External links ==
{{Americana Poster}}
*{{Wikiversity-inline|Collaborative_play_writing}}
*{{Commons category-inline}}
&lt;!-- ==============================({{NoMoreLinks}})============================== --&gt;
&lt;!-- DO NOT ADD MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE UNLESS THEY CONFORM TO [[WP:EL]]. WIKIPEDIA IS NOT A COLLECTION OF LINKS --&gt;
&lt;!-- ============================================================================= --&gt;
* {{dmoz|Arts/Performing_Arts/Comedy}}
* [http://www.dbu.edu/mitchell/comedydi.htm A Vocabulary for Comedy] from a professor at [[Dallas Baptist University]]
{{Comedy footer}}
&lt;!-- In the case of having own category with the same name of this article, the only one has to remain itself except the others. Then the other categories are moved into this article-named category, or it will get the complex and superfluity. --&gt;

[[Category:Comedy| ]]

&lt;!-- interwiki --&gt;

[[af:Komedie]]
[[ar:كوميديا]]
[[an:Comedia]]
[[az:Komediya]]
[[ba:Комедия]]
[[be:Камедыя]]
[[be-x-old:Камэдыя]]
[[bg:Комедия]]
[[bs:Komedija]]
[[br:Fentc'hoari]]
[[ca:Comèdia]]
[[cs:Komedie]]
[[cy:Comedi]]
[[da:Komedie]]
[[de:Komödie]]
[[et:Komöödia]]
[[el:Κωμωδία]]
[[es:Comedia]]
[[eo:Komedio]]
[[eu:Komedia]]
[[fa:کمدی]]
[[fr:Comédie]]
[[gag:Komediya]]
[[gl:Comedia]]
[[gan:喜劇]]
[[ko:희극]]
[[hy:Կատակերգություն]]
[[hi:प्रहसन]]
[[hr:Komedija]]
[[io:Komedio]]
[[os:Комеди]]
[[it:Commedia]]
[[he:קומדיה]]
[[ka:კომედია]]
[[kk:Комедия]]
[[la:Comoedia]]
[[lv:Komēdija]]
[[lt:Komedija]]
[[hu:Komédia]]
[[mk:Комедија]]
[[ml:തമാശ]]
[[ms:Komedi]]
[[nl:Komedie]]
[[ja:喜劇]]
[[no:Komedie]]
[[nn:Komedie]]
[[uz:Komediya]]
[[pl:Komedia]]
[[pt:Comédia]]
[[ro:Comedie]]
[[ru:Комедия]]
[[sq:Komedia]]
[[scn:Cummedia]]
[[simple:Comedy]]
[[sk:Komédia]]
[[sl:Komedija]]
[[sr:Комедија]]
[[sh:Komedija]]
[[fi:Komedia]]
[[sv:Komedi]]
[[tl:Komedya]]
[[ta:நகைச்சுவை]]
[[th:ตลก]]
[[tg:Кинокамедия]]
[[tr:Komedi]]
[[uk:Комедія]]
[[vi:Hài kịch]]
[[wa:Comedeye]]
[[yi:קאמעדיע]]
[[diq:Komedi]]
[[bat-smg:Kuomedėjė]]
[[zh:喜劇]]</text>
      <sha1>g4gwn40c6pklca0gndmtewxrgdxs62r</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
