<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Erich Honecker</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>39768</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520889151</id>
      <parentid>520083707</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-01T12:41:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>90.204.112.80</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18451">{{Redirect|Honecker|others so named|Honecker (surname)}}
{{Refimprove|date=June 2007}}
{{Infobox president
| name         = Erich Honecker
| image        = Bundesarchiv Bild 183-R0518-182, Erich Honecker.jpg
| nationality  = German
| order        = [[Leadership of East Germany|General Secretary of the Central Committee of the Socialist Unity Party of Germany]]
| term_start   = May 3, 1971
| term_end     = October 18‚ 1989
| predecessor  = [[Walter Ulbricht]]
| successor    = [[Egon Krenz]]
| birth_date   = {{birth date|mf=yes|1912|8|25}}
| birth_place  = [[Neunkirchen, Saarland|Neunkirchen]], [[German Empire]]
| death_date   = {{death date and age|mf=yes|1994|5|29|1912|8|25}}
| death_place  = [[Santiago, Chile|Santiago]], [[Chile]]
| spouse       = Edith Baumann (1950–1953)&lt;br /&gt;[[Margot Honecker|Margot Feist Honecker]] (b. 1927)
| party        = [[Communist Party of Germany]] (1922–1946)&lt;br&gt;[[Socialist Unity Party of Germany]] (1946–1989)&lt;br&gt; [[Communist Party of Germany (1990)|Communist Party of Germany]] (1990–1994)
| profession   = [[Politician]]
| order2       = [[Leadership of East Germany|Chairman of the State Council of the German Democratic Republic]]
| term_start2  = 29 October 1976
| term_end2    = 18 October 1989
| predecessor2 = [[Willi Stoph]]
| successor2   = [[Egon Krenz]]
| order3       = [[Leadership of East Germany|Chairman of the National Defense Council of East Germany]]
| term_start3  = 1971
| term_end3    = 1989
| predecessor3 = [[Walter Ulbricht]]
| successor3   = [[Egon Krenz]]
| religion     = [[Atheism|None]]
| children     = 2
}}

'''Erich Honecker''' ({{IPA-de|ˈeːʁɪç ˈhɔnɛkɐ|lang}}; 25 August 1912 – 29 May 1994) was a German [[communist]] [[politician]] who led the [[German Democratic Republic]] as General Secretary of the Socialist Unity Party from 1971 until 1989, serving as Head of State as well after [[Willi Stoph]]'s relinquishment of that post in 1976.

Following the definite end of the [[Cold War]], Honecker refused all but cosmetic changes and was ousted by the party in late 1989 and removed from power. Following the [[German reunification]] he successfully evaded prosecution for [[human rights]] abuses committed under his regime, finally settling down with his family in [[Chile]] in 1993, dying the following year from liver cancer.

==Origins and early political career==

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-57000-0512, V. Parteitag der SED, Honecker spricht.jpg|220px|thumb|left|Erich Honecker, watched by his mentor [[Walter Ulbricht]] at the 5th Party Congress, 1958]]

Honecker was born on Max-Braun-Straße in [[Neunkirchen (Saar)|Neunkirchen]], now [[Saarland]], as the son of Wilhelm Honecker, a coal miner and political activist,&lt;ref name=wilsford195&gt;Wilsford (1995) p. 195&lt;/ref&gt; who in 1905 had married Caroline Catharina Weidenhof. There were six children born to the family: Katharina (Käthe), Wilhelm (Willi), Frieda, Erich, Gertrud (b. 1917; m. Hoppstädter), and Karl-Robert.

After [[World War I]], the [[Saar (League of Nations)|Territory of the Saar Basin]] was handed over to [[France]]. This change from the strict rule of Baron von Stumm to French military occupation provided the backdrop for what Wilhelm Honecker understood as proletarian exploitation, and introduced young Erich to communism.&lt;ref name=wilsford195&gt;Wilsford (1995) p. 195&lt;/ref&gt; In 1922 at 10 years old, he joined the [[Spartacus League]], then the [[Young Communist League of Germany]] (KJVD), the youth section of the [[Communist Party of Germany]] (KPD), in 1926&lt;ref name=wilsford195&gt;Wilsford (1995) p. 195&lt;/ref&gt; and joined the KPD itself in 1929. Between 1928 and 1930 he worked as a [[roofer]], but did not finish his apprenticeship. Thereafter he was sent to Moscow to study at the [[International Lenin School]] and for the rest of his life remained a full-time politician.

He returned to Germany in 1931 and was arrested in 1935, two years after the [[Nazism|Nazis]] had come to power. In 1937, he was sentenced to ten years for Communist activities and remained a prisoner until the end of [[World War II]]. At the end of the war, Honecker resumed activity in the party under leader [[Walter Ulbricht]], and, in 1946, became one of the first members of the [[Socialist Unity Party of Germany]] (''Sozialistische Einheitspartei Deutschlands'', SED), which was formed by the merger of the KPD and the [[Social Democratic Party of Germany|Social Democratic Party]] (SPD) in the [[Soviet occupation zone]] of Germany.

Following the SED victory in the October 1946 elections, Honecker took his place amongst the SED leadership in the first postwar East German parliament, the [[German People's Congress]] ''(Deutscher Volkskongress)''. The German Democratic Republic was proclaimed on 7 October 1949  with the adoption of a new [[Constitution of East Germany|constitution]], establishing a political system similar to that of the [[Soviet Union]]. Honecker was a candidate member for the secretariat of the [[Central Committee]] in 1950; by 1958, he had become a full member of the ''[[Politbüro]]''.

==Leadership of East Germany==

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild Y 10-0334-85, NVA-Übung, Ehrengäste.jpg|thumb|left|During a [[National People's Army]] exercise in southern East Germany, 1960: [[Ivan Yakubovsky]], [[Otto Grotewohl]], Erich Honecker, [[Heinz Hoffmann]]]]

In 1961, Honecker, as the Central Committee secretary for security matters, was in charge of the building of the [[Berlin Wall]]. In 1971, he initiated a political power struggle that led, with Soviet support, to his replacing Ulbricht as First Secretary of the SED Central Committee and as chairman of the [[National Defense Council of the GDR|National Defense Council]]. In 1976, he also became Chairman of the [[State Council of the German Democratic Republic|Council of State]] (''Vorsitzender des Staatsrats der DDR''), thus becoming ''[[de jure]]'' [[head of state]] (he was already ''[[de facto]]'' head of state by virtue of his party post).
[[File:Erich Honecker DDR.JPG|thumb|upright|Erich Honecker, 1974]]
Under Honecker's leadership, the GDR adopted a programme of &quot;consumer socialism&quot;, which resulted in a marked improvement in living standards already the highest among the [[Eastern bloc]] countries. More attention was placed on the availability of consumer goods, and the construction of new housing was accelerated, with Honecker promising to &quot;settle the housing problem as an issue of social relevance&quot;.&lt;ref name=speech&gt;Honecker, Erich. 1984. ''The GDR: A State of Peace and Socialism'' [http://www.calvin.edu/academic/cas/gpa/erich1.htm http://www.calvin.edu/academic/cas/gpa/erich1.htm].&lt;/ref&gt; Yet, despite improved living conditions, internal dissent was not tolerated. Around 125 East German citizens &lt;ref&gt;List of Berlin Wall victims http://www.chronik-der-mauer.de/index.php/de/Start/Index/id/593792&lt;/ref&gt; were killed during this period while trying  to cross the border into West Germany or West Berlin.

In foreign relations, Honecker renounced the objective of a unified Germany and adopted the &quot;defensive&quot; position of ideological ''Abgrenzung'' (demarcation). He combined loyalty to the [[USSR]] with flexibility toward [[détente]], especially in relation to rapprochement with West Germany. In September 1987, he became the first East German head of state to visit West Germany. He was received with full state honours by West Germany's [[Helmut Kohl]]—an act that seemed to confirm West Germany's acceptance of East Germany's existence.

In the late 1980s, Soviet leader [[Mikhail Gorbachev]] introduced [[glasnost]] and [[perestroika]], reforms to liberalise communism. Honecker and the East German government refused to implement similar reforms in the GDR, with Honecker reportedly telling Gorbachev: &quot;We have done our perestroika, we have nothing to restructure&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cnn.com/SPECIALS/cold.war/episodes/23/interviews/gorbachev/ }} {{Dead link|date=April 2011|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gorbachev grew to dislike Honecker, and by 1988 was lumping Honecker, along with [[Bulgaria]]'s [[Todor Zhivkov]], [[Czechoslovakia]]'s [[Gustáv Husák]] and [[Romania]]'s [[Nicolae Ceaușescu]] as a &quot;Gang of Four&quot;—a group of inflexible hardliners unwilling to make necessary reforms.&lt;ref name=Revolution1989&gt;{{cite book|last=Sebetsyen|first=Victor|title=Revolution 1989: The Fall of the Soviet Empire|publisher=[[Pantheon Books]]|location=New York City|year=2009|isbn=0-375-42532-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Nonetheless, Honecker appeared to be on solid footing.  However, trouble appeared on the horizon in August 1989, when [[Hungary]] dismantled its section of the [[Iron Curtain]], and opened its border with [[Austria]].  Several thousand East Germans fled to Hungary, in hopes of going to West Germany by way of Austria.  Per a 1969 treaty, the Hungarian government should have forced the East Germans back home.  However, after a week, the Hungarians relented and let the refugees pass into Austria, telling their outraged East German counterparts that international treaties on refugees took precedence. Honecker was recovering from bladder cancer, leaving his colleagues unable to act decisively.&lt;ref name=Revolution1989/&gt;

Honecker was back in charge by September, and immediately had to deal with a new refugee problem.  Several thousand East Germans tried to go to West Germany by way of [[Czechoslovakia]], only to have that government bar them from passing.  Several thousand of them headed straight for the West German embassy in [[Prague]] and demanded safe passage to West Germany.  With some reluctance, Honecker allowed them to go—but forced them to go back through East Germany on [[sealed train]]s and stripped them of their East German citizenship.  Several members of the SED ''Politbüro'' realized this was a serious blunder and made plans to get rid of him.  Honecker got another rude shock at the GDR's 40th anniversary gala in September, when several hundred members of the [[Free German Youth]]—the SED's supposed future vanguard—began chanting, &quot;Gorby, help us! Gorby, save us!&quot;&lt;ref name=Revolution1989/&gt;

As the reform movement spread throughout Central and Eastern Europe, mass demonstrations against the East German government erupted, most prominently in [[Leipzig]]—the first of several [[Monday demonstrations in East Germany|demonstrations which took place on Monday night]] across the country.  In response, an elite paratroop unit was dispatched to Leipzig—almost certainly on Honecker's orders, since he was commander-in-chief of the army.  A bloodbath was only averted when local party officials themselves ordered the troops to pull back.  In the following week, Honecker faced a torrent of criticism.  This gave his ''Politburo'' comrades the impulse they needed to replace him, with Gorbachev's tacit approval. On 18 October 1989, they voted to oust Honecker and replace him with [[Egon Krenz]].

==Post-1989==
After the GDR was dissolved in October 1990, the Honeckers stayed with the family of the Lutheran pastor Uwe Holmer. Honecker then stayed in a Soviet military hospital near Berlin before later fleeing Germany with Margot Honecker via the Soviet-controlled [[Sperenberg Airfield]] to Moscow, to avoid prosecution over charges of [[Cold War]] crimes. He was accused by the German government of involvement in the deaths of 192 East Germans who tried to leave the GDR in violation of anti-[[Republikflucht]] laws. Following the [[dissolution of the Soviet Union]] in December 1991, Honecker took refuge in the [[Chile]]an embassy in Moscow, but was extradited by the [[Boris Yeltsin|Yeltsin]] administration to Germany in 1992. He was officially expelled from the reformed SED-PDS before the trial opened. He then joined the very small [[Communist Party of Germany (1990)|new Communist Party]].&lt;ref&gt;Staatschef a.D.: die letzten Jahre des Erich Honecker. Thomas Kunze. Links-Verlag (2001), S. 159&lt;/ref&gt; When the trial formally opened in early 1993, Honecker was released due to ill health and on 13 January of that year moved to Chile to live with his daughter Sonja, her Chilean husband Leo Yáñez, and their son Roberto. He died of [[Hepatocellular carcinoma|liver cancer]] in [[Santiago de Chile|Santiago]].

==Personal==
Honecker married [[Edith Baumann]] in 1950 and divorced her in 1953. They had a daughter, Erika (b. 1950). In 1953 he married [[Margot Honecker|Margot Feist]] and they remained married until his death. They had a daughter, Sonja, born in 1952. Margot Honecker served for more than 20 years as the [[Ministerrat|GDR Minister for People's Education]].

It is claimed that Honecker was addicted to [[game (food)|game hunting]] and was directly involved in the over-hunting of a number of native game species. Such was his passion that animals bred and reared in neighbouring communist countries had to be supplied for his regular hunting parties.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b00jc6kg &quot;The Lost World of Communism&quot;, Episode 2 – A Socialist Paradise: East Germany, BBC 1, broadcast 14 March 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Famous quotes==
* &quot;The Wall will be standing in 50 and even in 100 years, if the reasons for it are not yet removed.&quot; (Berlin, 19 January 1989) (Original: &quot;''Die Mauer wird in 50 und auch in 100 Jahren noch bestehen bleiben, wenn die dazu vorhandenen Gründe noch nicht beseitigt sind''&quot;)
* &quot;Neither an ox nor a donkey is able to stop the progress of socialism.&quot;  (A rhyming couplet in the original German: &quot;''Den Sozialismus in seinem Lauf hält weder Ochs noch Esel auf''&quot;, Berlin, 7 October 1989), one of Honecker's favourite adages, originally coined by [[August Bebel]].  (The ox and the donkey are symbolic of stubborn stupidity in German culture.)
* &quot;The future belongs to socialism&quot; (Original: ''Die Zukunft gehört dem Sozialismus'') (early 1980s)
* &quot;Always forwards, never backwards.&quot; (Original: ''Vorwärts immer, rückwärts nimmer'') (early 1980s)

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== Bibliography ==
* Wilsford, David. (1995) ''Political leaders of contemporary Western Europe: a biographical dictionary''. Greenwood Publishing Group.

==Further reading==
* Fulbrook, Mary. (2008)  ''The people's state: East German society from Hitler to Honecker''. [[Yale University Press]].
* Honecker, Erich. (1981) ''Aus meinem Leben''. New York : Pergamon, 1981. ISBN 0-08-024532-3.

==External links==
{{Portal|Germany|Biography}}
{{Commons category|Erich Honecker}}
{{wikiquote}}
*[http://web.archive.org/web/*/http://www.cnn.com/SPECIALS/cold.war/kbank/profiles/honecker/ CNN Cold War – Profile: Erich Honecker]
*[http://www.honecker-im-internet.de/ Honecker im Internet] (in German)
*[http://www.warheroes.ru/hero/hero.asp?Hero_id=2158 www.warheroes.ru – Erich Honecker] (in Russian)
*[http://www.archive.org/details/WelcomingAddressto1979SessionoftheWorldPeaceCouncil ''Welcoming Address to 1979 Session of the World Peace Council'' Erich Honecker's speech to the WPC]
*[http://www.archive.org/details/ASuccessfulPolicySearedtotheNeedsofthePeople ''A Successful Policy Seared to the Needs of the People'' Volkskammer pamphlet including material by Honecker]

{{s-start}}
{{s-off}}
{{s-bef| before = [[Walter Ulbricht]] }}
{{s-ttl| title  = [[Leadership of East Germany|General Secretary of the Central Committee &lt;br/&gt;of the Socialist Unity Party of Germany]]
| years = 1971–1989 }}
{{s-aft| rows   = 2 | after  = [[Egon Krenz]] }}
{{s-bef| before = [[Willi Stoph]] }}
{{s-ttl| title  = [[Leadership of East Germany|Chairman of the Council of State &lt;br/&gt;of the German Democratic Republic]]
| years = 1976–1989 }}
{{s-end}}

{{SEDGenSecs}}
{{Head of State of the German Democratic Republic}}
{{Cold War}}
{{Cold War figures}}
{{Fall of Communism}}

{{Authority control|PND=118553399|LCCN=n/50/28179|VIAF=34468994|TSURL=viaf/34468994}}

{{Persondata
| NAME              = Honecker, Erich
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = East German politician
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 25 August 1912
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = ''[[Neunkirchen (Saar)]]'', Germany
| DATE OF DEATH     = 29 May 1994
| PLACE OF DEATH    = [[Santiago de Chile|Santiago]], [[Chile]]
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Honecker, Erich}}
[[Category:1912 births]]
[[Category:1994 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Neunkirchen, Saarland]]
[[Category:People from the Rhine Province]]
[[Category:Communist Party of Germany politicians]]
[[Category:Socialist Unity Party of Germany politicians]]
[[Category:Members of the People's Chamber of the German Democratic Republic]]
[[Category:Cancer deaths in Chile]]
[[Category:Communist rulers]]
[[Category:Anti-Revisionists]]
[[Category:International opponents of apartheid in South Africa]]
[[Category:Deaths from liver cancer]]
[[Category:German atheists]]
[[Category:German expatriates in Chile]]
[[Category:Foreign Heroes of the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:People condemned by Nazi courts]]
[[Category:Communists in the German Resistance]]
[[Category:Expatriates in the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Lenin]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Karl Marx]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Patriotic Order of Merit]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Banner of Labor]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of José Marti]]

[[af:Erich Honecker]]
[[ar:إريش هونيكر]]
[[az:Erik Xonekker]]
[[be:Эрых Хонекер]]
[[be-x-old:Эрых Хонэкер]]
[[bg:Ерих Хонекер]]
[[br:Erich Honecker]]
[[ca:Erich Honecker]]
[[cs:Erich Honecker]]
[[cy:Erich Honecker]]
[[da:Erich Honecker]]
[[de:Erich Honecker]]
[[el:Έριχ Χόνεκερ]]
[[es:Erich Honecker]]
[[eo:Erich Honecker]]
[[eu:Erich Honecker]]
[[fa:اریش هونکر]]
[[fr:Erich Honecker]]
[[ko:에리히 호네커]]
[[hr:Erich Honecker]]
[[io:Erich Honecker]]
[[id:Erich Honecker]]
[[it:Erich Honecker]]
[[he:אריך הונקר]]
[[jv:Erich Honecker]]
[[ka:ერიხ ჰონეკერი]]
[[la:Ericus Honecker]]
[[lb:Erich Honecker]]
[[lt:Erich Honecker]]
[[hu:Erich Honecker]]
[[mr:एरिक होनेकर]]
[[nl:Erich Honecker]]
[[ja:エーリッヒ・ホーネッカー]]
[[no:Erich Honecker]]
[[pl:Erich Honecker]]
[[pt:Erich Honecker]]
[[ro:Erich Honecker]]
[[ru:Хонеккер, Эрих]]
[[simple:Erich Honecker]]
[[sk:Erich Honecker]]
[[sl:Erich Honecker]]
[[sr:Ерих Хонекер]]
[[fi:Erich Honecker]]
[[sv:Erich Honecker]]
[[tr:Erich Honecker]]
[[uk:Еріх Гонеккер]]
[[vi:Erich Honecker]]
[[zh:埃里希·昂纳克]]</text>
      <sha1>tuq3bqv39jsh8yykcar8z8fruq39yi0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
