<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Ferenc Gyurcsány</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>945404</id>
    <revision>
      <id>517420069</id>
      <parentid>513377265</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-12T15:59:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yobot</username>
        <id>7328338</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[WP:CHECKWIKI]] error 61 fix, References after punctuation per [[WP:REFPUNC]] and [[WP:PAIC]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (8459)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="35512">{{eastern name order|Gyurcsány Ferenc}}
{{Infobox Prime Minister
| name        = Ferenc Gyurcsány
| image       = Gyurcsany Ferenc 2010.jpg|150px
| order1       = [[Prime Minister of Hungary]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;6th [[Third Hungarian Republic|Prime Minister of the Third Republic of Hungary]]&lt;/small&gt;
| president1   = [[Ferenc Mádl]]&lt;br&gt;[[László Sólyom]]
| deputy1      =  
| term_start1  = 29 September 2004
| term_end1    = 14 April 2009
| predecessor1 = [[Péter Medgyessy]]
| successor1   = [[Gordon Bajnai]]
| order2       = [[Government of Hungary|Minister of Youth Affairs and Sports]]
| primeminister2 = [[Péter Medgyessy]]&lt;br&gt;Himself 
| deputy2      =  
| term_start2  = 18 May 2003
| term_end2    = 3 October 2004
| predecessor2 = [[György Jánosi]]
| successor2   = post abolished
| birth_date  = {{birth date and age|1961|06|04|df=y}}
| birth_place = [[Pápa]], [[People's Republic of Hungary|Hungary]]
| death_date  =
| death_place = 
| spouse      = [[Klára Dobrev]]
| party       = [[Democratic Coalition|DK]] (2011–present)
| otherparty   = [[Hungarian Young Communist League|KISZ]] (1980–1990)&lt;br&gt;[[Hungarian Socialist Party|MSZP]] (2000–2011)
| profession  = [[Entrepreneur]]
| religion    = [[Atheism]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7HsnMWdAQFM&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
'''Ferenc Gyurcsány''' ({{IPA-hu|ˈfɛrɛnts ˈɟurtʃaːɲ|-|Hu-Ferenc_Gyurcsány.ogg}}; born 4 June 1961) is a [[Hungary|Hungarian]] [[politician]]. He was the [[List of Prime Ministers of Hungary#Republic of Hungary (1989–Present)|sixth Prime Minister]] of [[Hungary]] from 2004 to 2009.

He was nominated to take that position on 25 August 2004 by the [[Hungarian Socialist Party]] (MSZP), after [[Péter Medgyessy]] resigned due to a conflict with the Socialist Party's coalition partner. Gyurcsány was elected Prime Minister on 29 September 2004 in a parliamentary vote (197 ''yes'' votes, 12 ''no'' votes, with most of the opposition in [[National Assembly of Hungary|Parliament]] not voting). He led his coalition to victory in the [[Hungarian parliamentary election, 2006|parliamentary elections in 2006]], securing another term as Prime Minister. His first rise to power was the result of a coalition conflict. His legitimacy was permanently questioned by opposition parties based on the fact that he withheld information about the actual budget deficit in his 2006 re-election campaign.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mr1-kossuth.hu/hirek/itthon/a-ksh-adatszolgaltatasarol-targyal-a-koltsegvetesi-bizottsag.html Jury says statistics should have been published]&lt;/ref&gt; He is also criticised for using derogatory terms for his own country.&lt;ref&gt;[[Ferenc Gyurcsány's speech in Balaton%C5%91szöd in 2006 May#Obscene and offensive excerpts|Offensive expressions of Gyurcsány's speech]]&lt;/ref&gt; He subsequently continued to attempt to make this topic seem relatively insignificant.&lt;ref&gt;[http://hirtv.net/filmek/gyu10319.wmv Gyurcsány relativising his obscenity.]&lt;/ref&gt;

On 24 February 2007, he was elected as the leader of the MSZP, taking 89% of the vote. On 21 March 2009 Gyurcsány announced his intention to resign as Prime Minister.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hungary’s Premier Offers to Resign&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.nytimes.com/2009/03/22/world/22hungary.html?hp | work=The New York Times | title=Hungary's Premier Offers to Resign | first=Nicholas | last=Kulish | date=22 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hungarian PM offers to step down&quot;&gt;[http://edition.cnn.com/2009/WORLD/europe/03/21/hungary.pm/index.html Hungarian PM offers to step down]&lt;/ref&gt; He stated that he is a hindrance to further economic and social reforms.&lt;ref name=&quot;'Obstacle' Hungary PM to resign&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/7956610.stm | work=BBC News | title='Obstacle' Hungary PM to resign | date=21 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; President [[László Sólyom]] stated that instead of a short term transational government ruling only until the 2010 elections, early elections should be held.&lt;ref name=&quot;pr&quot;&gt;[http://www.pr-inside.com/hungary-s-president-favors-early-elections-r1141169.htm Hungary's president favors early elections]&lt;/ref&gt; On 28 March Gyurcsány resigned from his position as party chairman, he was the leader of MSZP between 2007–2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;budapesttimes&quot;&gt;[http://www.budapesttimes.hu/content/view/11530/219/ PM Gyurcsany resigns post as Socialist Party chairman]&lt;/ref&gt; A minister under Gyurcsány, [[Gordon Bajnai]] became the nominee of MSZP for the post of prime minister in March 2009&lt;ref&gt;[http://online.wsj.com/article/SB123840402537769209.html Hungary Picks New Candidate for Premier]&lt;/ref&gt; and he became Prime Minister on 14 April.

==Early years==
Ferenc Gyurcsány was born in Pápa, Hungary. He attended the Apáczai Csere János High School in Budapest for two years, then he left to his hometown Pápa to graduate. Ferenc Gyurcsány studied as a teacher and obtained his B.Sc. in 1984 from the [[University of Pécs]]. Then he studied [[economics]] at the same institution, getting his degree in 1990.

In 1981 he assumed function in the KISZ, the [[Organisation of Young Communists]], where he mostly handled organizing student programs at the beginning. Between 1984 and 1988 he was the vice president of the organisation's committee in [[Pécs]]. Then between 1988 and 1989 he was the president of the central KISZ committee of universities and colleges. After the political change in 1989 he became vice-president of the organisation's short-lived quasi successor, the [[Hungarian Democratic Youth Association]] (DEMISZ).

From 1990 onwards, he transferred from the public to the private sector, working for CREDITUM Financial Consultant Ltd. until 1992, serving as director of EUROCORP International Finance Inc. in 1992. Gyurcsany then took the position of CEO at Altus Ltd., a holding company of which he was owner, from 1992–2002 and thereafter as Chairman of the Board.&lt;ref name=JOBS&gt;[http://www.hungria.org.br/CV_Gyurcsany.htm Ferenc Gyurcsány] Hungarian Embassy, Brasília&lt;/ref&gt; By 2002, he was listed as the 50th richest person in Hungary.&lt;ref name=RICH&gt;[http://www.origo.hu/uzletinegyed/hirek/2002111541tol.html 41-től 60-ig] Origo&lt;/ref&gt;

==Return to politics==
Ferenc Gyurcsány returned to politics in 2002 as the head strategic advisor of [[Péter Medgyessy]], the previous [[Prime Minister of Hungary]]. From May 2003 until September 2004 Gyurcsány was a [[Political minister|minister]] responsible for sports, youth and children. 

He became the president of the MSZP in [[Győr-Moson-Sopron]] [[Counties of Hungary|county]] in January 2004, serving until September 2004. In the summer of that same year it seemed that there were larger problems in his relationship with then current Prime Minister Péter Medgyessy, so he resigned as [[Political minister|minister]]. In a week, problems in the coalition led to the resignation of Medgyessy, and MSZP voted Gyurcsány to become Prime Minister as he was acceptable for the coalition partner, [[Alliance of Free Democrats]] (SZDSZ).

==Prime Minister==
Gyurcsány was reappointed Prime Minister after the [[Hungarian parliamentary election, 2006|2006 parliamentary elections]], with his coalition taking 210 of the available 386 parliamentary seats, and making him the first Prime Minister to keep the office after a general election since 1990.

On 24 February 2007 he became the leader of his party (being the only candidate for the post) gaining 89% of the vote.

Since his 2006 election victory he has introduced austerity measures to tackle Hungary's budget deficit that had grown to become 10% of the GDP by the end of 2006. These austerity measures have been criticized by the main opposition party [[Fidesz – Hungarian Civic Union|Fidesz]] on the one hand as being too harsh on the people, on the other hand by conservative economists for not reducing spending enough on social benefits, including pensions.
Ferenc Gyurcsány has been the first [[prime minister]] since the fall of communism to try to introduce a health care reform in order to rationalize and modernize the national health care system. His efforts for a renewed and more efficient health care however, have been undermined mainly by his own party, as many Socialist Party members regard this reform as a threat to the communist era achievement of free and equal health care service to all.

===Audio recording resulting in riots===
{{Main|Ferenc Gyurcsány's speech in Balatonőszöd in May 2006|2006 protests in Hungary}}
On 17 September 2006, an audio recording surfaced, allegedly from a closed-door meeting of the Prime Minister's party MSZP, held on 26 May 2006, shortly after MSZP won the election. On the [[Ferenc Gyurcsány's speech in Balatonőszöd in 2006 May|recording]], Gyurcsány admitted &quot;we have obviously been lying for the last one and a half to two years.&quot;  (&quot;''Nyilvánvalóan végig hazudtuk az utolsó másfél, két évet''.&quot;). Despite public outrage, the Prime Minister refused to resign, and a series of demonstrations started near the [[Hungarian Parliament]], swelling from 2,000 to about 8,000 demonstrators calling for the resignation of Gyurcsány and his government for several weeks. The Prime Minister admitted the authenticity of the recording.&lt;ref name=UNREST&gt;[http://www.hirtv.hu/?tPath=/belfold/&amp;article_hid=115874 Ha kell, a Magyar Rádió elé vonulnak a tüntetők] HírTV&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Gyurcsany Ferenc-mszp-2.jpg|thumb|left|Gyurcsány at the Socialist Party's congress]]
On 1 October, the governing party suffered a landslide defeat in the local municipal elections.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.valasztas.hu/outroot/onkdina/g12.htm&lt;/ref&gt; On the eve of the elections, before the results were known, President [[László Sólyom]] gave a speech in which he said that the solution to the situation is in the hands of the majority in Parliament.&lt;ref&gt;[http://index.hu/politika/belfold/soly1001/ Sólyom: Most az Országgyűlésnek van cselekvési lehetősége], Index, 2006-10-01&lt;/ref&gt;

===Vote of confidence===
As Prime Minister, Gyurcsány was a strong advocate of the [[South Stream|South Stream pipeline project]], which aimed to supply Russian gas directly to the [[European Union]] (EU); bypassing transit countries such as Ukraine. He signed the contract in Moscow just a week before popularal election at Hungary, which showed around 80% of the votes were against the government reforms.

On 6 October, Gyurcsány won a vote of confidence in Parliament, 207-165, with no coalition MP voting against him. The vote was public.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ft.com/cms/s/853cdd38-55a0-11db-acba-0000779e2340.html Gyurcsany wins vote of confidence], ''[[Financial Times]]'', 6 October 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Gyurcsány has been called to step down several times after this incident.{{Citation needed|date=July 2008}}

===Resignation===
On 21 March 2009 Gyurcsány announced his intention to resign as Prime Minister.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hungary’s Premier Offers to Resign&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hungarian PM offers to step down&quot;/&gt; He stated that he is a hindrance to further economic and social reforms.&lt;ref name=&quot;'Obstacle' Hungary PM to resign&quot;/&gt; Gyurcsány asked his party to find a new candidate for prime minister in two weeks.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/hostednews/ap/article/ALeqM5ia84yEP9jDmntQwdHNNV7NnsG9KwD972C81G0 Hungary's PM to quit amid tumbling popularity]&lt;/ref&gt; President [[László Sólyom]] stated that instead of a short term transational government ruling only until the 2010 elections, early elections should be held.&lt;ref name=&quot;pr&quot;/&gt; In the search for PM [[György Surányi]] became the frontrunner candidate for the post however on the 26th of March he pulled out of the race saying he would not take the job.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.reuters.com/article/rbssFinancialServicesAndRealEstateNews/idUSLQ97333420090326 | work=Reuters | title=SCENARIOS-What next as Hungary seeks new prime minister? | date=26 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 28 March Gyurcsány resigned from his position as party chairman, he was the leader of MSZP between 2007–2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;budapesttimes&quot;/&gt;

==Post-Prime Ministerial career==
He became a member of the [[National Assembly of Hungary]] again in 2010 when he won a seat from the Socialist Party's national list in the [[Hungarian parliamentary election, 2010|elections.]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nol.hu/belfold/20091207-maradt_gyurcsany__nincs_szili_katalin__-_kesz_az_mszp_orszagos_listaja Kész az MSZP országos listája.]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Conflicts with the Socialists===
On 5 October 2010 Gyurcsány announced to the party executive that he is founding a platform named the Democratic Coalition within the party. He said he will organise ''“a broad, open social community for 1989 democrats”'', and a political representation for them. The mood at the meeting was calm, but several party officials expressed disagreement with him.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.politics.hu/20101007/gyurcsany-to-form-socialist-faction/ Gyurcsány to form Socialist faction]&lt;/ref&gt; The Democratic Coalition held its inaugural meeting at 2 p.m. in the Szent István Park in the 13th District on 22 October 2010. Meanwhile, Socialist deputy chairman [[András Balogh]] told [[Népszava]] in an interview that the party performed poorly at the elections because Gyurcsány's cabinet made mistakes while in government, abandoned left-wing values and became complacent, and because of corruption.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.politics.hu/20101022/gyurcsanys-new-faction-forms-today/ Gyurcsány’s new faction forms today]&lt;/ref&gt; The former Prime Minister's group became the Hungarian Socialist party's seventh platform.

Balogh in occasion of an interview in November said socialists must reclaim the vote of the worker from the far right, and to the extent that Gyurcsány wants to build a liberal-centrist wing. he also stated the Democratic Coalition, sought to open a “big front” embracing liberal and certain conservative forces. He added that Gyurcsány would have to accept the party’s concept of renewal, which revolves around emphasising its left-wing credentials, if he wanted the party’s leadership to cooperate with him. Ominously, he called on party members who were directly responsible for the difficult situation of the Socialist party, and society in general, to quit the party.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.politics.hu/20101115/senior-socialist-sends-guarded-signals-about-expm-gyurcsany/ Senior Socialist sends guarded signals about ex-PM Gyurcsány]&lt;/ref&gt; In January 2011 unnamed sources close to the party reported the [[Magyar Hírlap]] that [[Attila Mesterházy]] and the current Socialist leadership does not want Gyurcsány to get too strong within the party but neither do they want him to leave as a martyr.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.politics.hu/20110112/socialists-reportedly-to-assess-former-pms-party-wing-in-february/ Socialists reportedly to assess former PM’s party wing in February]&lt;/ref&gt;

László Puch, one one of the most influential Socialist politicians, said that Gyucsány should found his own liberal party instead of breaking up his party.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.politics.hu/20110218/top-socialist-says-former-pm-gyurcsany-should-leave-party-rather-than-ruining-mszp/ Top Socialist says former PM Gyurcsány should leave party rather than “ruining” MSZP]&lt;/ref&gt; Platforms within the Socialist Party in May 2011 held a debate on whether the party should be developed as a cooperation between left-wing groups or a collective party welcoming non-leftist groups or politicians – a broader alternative to ruling Fidesz. The latter idea was only supported by the Democratic Coalition Platform. All seven platforms of the party agreed that the Socialists do not need a &quot;chieftain&quot;, an “Orbán of the Left” but a team leader, [[István Hiller]], the head of the Social Democratic Platform, told reporters during a break of the meeting. He dismissed Gyurcsány’s idea of embracing liberal and conservative trends. Gyurcsány’s model would make the party dysfunctional, he said.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.politics.hu/20110519/socialist-platforms-discuss-future-strategy/ Socialist platforms discuss future strategy]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Foundation of a new party====
On 22 October 2011 Gyurcsány has announced he is leaving the Socialist Party and will set up a new parliamentary group after succeeding in persuading the necessary number of lawmakers to join him. The new [[Democratic Coalition]] party is to be a ''“Western, civic centre-left”'' formation with ten lawmakers, Gyurcsány announced on the first anniversary that its forerunner, the Democratic Coalition Platform, was set up. He said the reason why he had decided to leave the Socialists was because the party had failed in its efforts to transform itself. Socialist representatives strongly condemned Gyurcsány, who had only last week signed a pledge to stay on in the party. Gyurcsány in his speech branded the new constitution as “illegitimate”, and insisted that members and heads of the independent branches of state such as the constitutional court and the public prosecutor “exclusively serve Viktor Orbán”.

Mesterházy, the chairman of the MSZP responded that the Socialists would emerge stronger after Gyurcsány forms his own party and parliamentary group, because the opposition force’s lawmakers would no longer be engrossed in an internal struggle. Radical nationalist party [[Jobbik]] lawmaker [[Előd Novák]] told [[Magyar Távirati Iroda|MTI]] that Gyurcsány’s new party was “anti-Hungarian”. He also said that Jobbik would now be in a position to provide the stable alternative to Fidesz. Parliamentary group leader of green party [[Politics Can Be Different|LMP]], [[András Schiffer]], told MTI his party had a policy of keeping its distance from the internal affairs of other parties. He added that LMP’s main enemy was the “Fidesz two-thirds [majority]“.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.politics.hu/20111022/gyurcsany-announces-departure-from-socialists-formation-of-new-western-civic-center-left-party/ Gyurcsány announces departure from Socialists, formation of new “Western, civic center-left” party]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hunger strike===
Gyurcsány started a [[hunger strike]] and three other members of the Democratic Coalition ([[Csaba Molnár]], Péter Niedermüller and István Kolber) started on a week-long hunger strike in [[Kossuth tér]] on 9 September 2012. The demonstration, called Seven Days for Free Elections, was to protest the proposed [[voter registration]] plan. The former PM said that &quot;''Dramatic situations call for dramatic reactions, and strong political gestures are needed for apathetic voters to mobilise.''&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.politics.hu/20120910/former-pm-gyurcsany-on-week-long-hunger-strike-over-fidesz-voter-registration-plan/ Former PM Gyurcsány on week-long hunger strike over Fidesz voter registration plan]&lt;/ref&gt; The Parliament’s Office ordered hunger strikers to pay [[Forint|Ft]] 132,000 in usage fees for occupying the area outside [[Hungarian Parliament Building|Parliament]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.politics.hu/20120911/gyurcsany-hunger-strike-party-ordered-to-pay-huf-132000-for-occupying-area-outside-parliament/ Gyurcsány hunger strike party ordered to pay HUF 132,000 for occupying area outside Parliament]&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:DK 2012-09-11 14.44.56.jpg|thumb|right|Gyurcsány during the hunger strike in 2012]]
Gabriella Selmeczi, spokesperson of Fidesz, commented the strike as ''&quot;four middle-aged men bunking together in a tent in downtown Budapest – that doesn’t sound very exciting.&quot;''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.politics.hu/20120911/quotable-gabriella-selmeczi-on-gyurcsanys-hunger-strike/ Quotable: Gabriella Selmeczi on Gyurcsány’s hunger strike]&lt;/ref&gt; [[László Botka]], member of the MSZP and mayor of [[Szeged]], said he was unwilling to comment the strike of Gyurcsány but added that the cause he is protesting against, namely the introduction of voter registration, was outrageous and strongly opposed by the Socialists, too.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.politics.hu/20120913/mszp-must-nominate-pm-name-allies-by-late-2013-says-socialist-board-chairman/ MSZP must nominate PM, name allies by late 2013, says Socialist board chairman]&lt;/ref&gt; Jobbik MP Gergely Farkas said Ferenc Gyurcsány’s hunger strike outside Parliament is ''&quot;phoney and hypocritical&quot;''. He criticised Gyurcsány’s act because as a former prime minister ''&quot;he is one of those responsible for the fact that a large number of people are hungry nowadays not only for a week but from week to week.&quot;'' Jobbik activists handed out hot soup in the same vicinity on 13 September 2012.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.politics.hu/20120914/jobbik-dubs-gyurcsany-hunger-strike-phoney-and-hypocritical-trumps-it-with-hot-meal-handouts/ Jobbik dubs Gyurcsány hunger strike “phoney” and “hypocritical”; trumps it with hot meal handouts]&lt;/ref&gt;

Gyurcsány said he had no plans to run for prime minister in 2014, [[Slovakia|Slovak]] news agency [[News Agency of the Slovak Republic|TASR]] reported on 16 September 2012. He also told ''&quot;we have best chances to win if we manage to join forces with a wide circle of opposition forces. This joining of forces needs to be spearheaded by a person who is acceptable to all without serious compromises. It is common knowledge that there are differences in opinion between me and some opposition leaders.&quot;'' He added: ''&quot;if there is a joint candidate, I will support him or her.&quot;''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.politics.hu/20120917/gyurcsany-says-no-plans-to-run-for-pm-in-2014/ Gyurcsány says “no plans” to run for PM in 2014]&lt;/ref&gt;

On 17 September 2012, during a mass protest after finishing hunger strike, Gyurcsány called on the Socialists and LMP to boycott the parliamentary debate of the election procedures bill and he asked his supporters to submit a petition against the pre-registration requirement. He reiterated that the requirement of pre-registration will exclude hundreds of thousands from the election. Most of those who only decide in the last few weeks that they would cast a vote generally support the opposition, he added. He also told that ''&quot;if the government of Prime Minister Viktor Orbán wants to stay in power with the help of “legal tricks and machinations,” then &quot;Hungary will lose its calm and the people will simply rebel&quot;.'' He invited democratic opposition parties and organisations to hold a joint event marking the anniversary of Hungary’s anti-Soviet 1956 revolution on October 23.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.politics.hu/20120917/former-pm-urges-opposition-to-step-up-protest-against-voter-registration/ Former PM urges opposition to step up protest against voter registration as Socialists plan to boycott debate]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal life==
[[File:Ferenc Gyurcsany cc.jpg|200px|thumb|Gyurcsány at a music festival in Q&amp;A.]]
Ferenc Gyurcsány lives in his third marriage. He has two sons (Péter and Bálint) from his second marriage with Edina Bognár, and two children (Anna and Tamás) from his third marriage. His spouse is [[Klára Dobrev]], whose maternal grandfather [[Antal Apró]] was Hungary's Minister of Industry in the 1950s–60s.

He got his nickname &quot;Fletó&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;i&quot;&gt;Not to be confused with the [http://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/fleto Spanish word fleto]&lt;/ref&gt; from one of his teachers. While Prime Minister of Hungary, he did not pick up his paycheck, but instead, he donated it to varying organizations.

==Criticism==

===Wealth===
The origin of his wealth is regularly questioned by the media and political opposition. The weekly paper ''[[Heti Világgazdaság|HVG]]'' writes about a biography of Gyurcsány: &quot;[it] concludes that talent played a greater role than corruption in Gyurcsány's success. We have to question this claim. Not just because former functionaries are massively overrepresented among Gyurcsány's business partners, but also because, despite his enormous talent for business, Gyurcsány would never have got where he is today without making use of the contacts and support base of the former state party.&quot;&lt;ref name=CORRUPT&gt;[http://hvg.hu/english/20060619gyurcsanybioeng.aspx Not as good as the Lakatos], 19 June 2006, ''Heti Világgazdaság''&lt;/ref&gt; József Debreczeni, the biographer in question, originally reached the conclusion &quot;regarding party connections and performance, the latter has been more important&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Debreczeni |first=József |title= Az új miniszterelnök (The New Prime Minister) {{hu icon}} |publisher= Osiris Kiadó |year= 2006 |isbn= 963-389-844-7 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Opposition MP [[Péter Szijjártó]], as the head of a committee set up to investigate the origins of Gyurcsány's wealth, stated in his report that one of Gyurcsány's companies leased the former vacation site of the Hungarian government in Balatonőszöd and rented the site back to a state-owned company so that the rent paid by the government covered exactly the leasing fee during the first two and a half years of the ten-year lease term (1994–2004).&lt;ref name=CORRUPT2&gt;[http://index.hu/politika/belfold/gya6967/ Szijjártó tíz tétele Gyurcsány gazdagodásáról], 8 November 2005, ''Index.hu''&lt;/ref&gt;

A person named &quot;Gyurcsányi&quot; was mentioned by [[Attila Kulcsár]], the main defendant in the high-profile &quot;K&amp;H Equities&quot; money laundering scandal in Hungary.&lt;ref name=SCANDAL&gt;[http://www.pestiside.hu/archives/nerves_shredded_over_scandal_evidence_shredding000808.php Nerves Shredded Over Scandal Evidence Shredding] Pestiside.hu&lt;/ref&gt; The prime minister denied he had any connections with the case.

===Plagiarism controversy===
{{Main|Ferenc Gyurcsány plagiarism controversy}}

In an article published on 2 April 2012, ''Pécsi Újság'' called into question whether Gyurcsány submitted a diploma thesis.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.pecsiujsag.hu/pecs/hir/helyi-hireink/terjed-hogy-gyurcsany-pecsi-szakdolgozata-sincs-rendben-de-a-pte-nem-adhat-ki-adatot---video&lt;/ref&gt; István Geresdi, [[Dean (education)|Dean]] of the Faculty of Sciences at the [[University of Pécs]] told ''Pécsi Újság'' that they were unable to find Gyurcsány's diploma thesis. He further added that that Gyurcsány's thesis was the only missing work from that time period. On 3 April Gyurcsány published a page from his course record book that stated that he submitted and defended a college thesis.&lt;ref&gt;^ http://www.facebook.com/photo.php?fbid=379552925410509&lt;/ref&gt; He also stated that he did not know where his own copy of his thesis was, but he would make efforts to locate and publish it. After two weeks, on 13 April he announced that he failed to find his copy of the thesis.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.facebook.com/note.php?note_id=385994531433015&lt;/ref&gt; On 27 April ''[[Hír TV]]'', a government-leaning television channel announced that they have found evidence that Szabolcs Rozs, who was Gyurcsány's brother-in-law in 1984, submitted a college thesis at the same college and department as Gyurcsány, with a title identical to Gyurcsány's work, in 1980.&lt;ref&gt;http://mno.hu/belfold/plagium-gyanujaban-gyurcsany-1071944&lt;/ref&gt; Three days later, on 30 April ''Hír Tv'' announced that they have located and compared the reviews of both Rozs's and Gyurcsány's work, and found that based on the common errors and omissions, the two texts are likely to be identical, supporting the allegations of plagiarism.&lt;ref&gt;http://mno.hu/belfold/bebukta-gyurcsany-ferenc-plagizalt-video-1072270&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other===
He often displays himself in the role of an [[anti-fascist]] politician, who is strongly against the Hungarian [[Political radicalism|radicalism]] and [[Antisemitism|anti-semitism]]. However, he is the subject of criticism by his political opponents for the luxury villa of [[Rózsadomb]] in which he lives and is now the property of his recent wife, having been taken away from a [[jews|Jewish]] family twice;
first it was misappropriated when [[Hungary during World War II#The war comes to Hungary|Hungary]] was under the rule of [[Arrow Cross Party]], and then again during the time of the [[History of Hungary#Stalinist era (1949–1956)|communist dictatorship]] of [[Mátyás Rákosi]].

On 2 September 2004, he said in the [[m1 (TV channel)|Hungarian national television]]: &quot;Who has a two-room-apartment, would in general deserve three; who has three, four; who has four, a house. Who has an eld..., olderly, elderly?... olderly ''[struggling with an unintended [[portmanteau]]]'' wife, a younger one; who has a badly behaved kid, a well-behaved. Of course, he would deserve.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Original Hungarian text: ''Akinek kétszobás lakása van, az általában megérdemelne hármat, akinek három, az négyet, akinek négy, az egy családi házat. Akinek öreged..., öregecskedő, öregeskedő?... öregecskedő felesége, az fiatalabbat, akinek rendetlen gyereke, az rendesebbet. Persze, hogy megérdemelné.'' See video at [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OKM0DmfbAgk YouTube]&lt;/ref&gt; This triggerd outrage from feminist organisations, women in general, and the opposition.&lt;ref&gt;[http://index.hu/belfold/noi1014r/ Index.hu] – ''Felháborodtak az asszonyok Gyurcsány kijelentésén'' (Women outrage at Gyurcsány's statement) ''14 September 2004''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://index.hu/belfold/hirek/193249/ Index.hu] – ''Áder bocsánatkérésre szólítja fel Gyurcsányt'' ([[János Áder|Áder]] calls on Gyurcsány to apologize) ''11 September 2004''&lt;/ref&gt;

On 2 February 2005, at the birthday party of the [[Hungarian Socialist Party]], for the sake of a joke, Gyurcsány referred to the players of the [[Saudi Arabia national football team|Saudi national football team]] as terrorists. Later he apologized, but the kingdom recalled its ambassador from Hungary for a time.&lt;ref name=&quot;szaudi&quot;&gt;[http://index.hu/politika/belfold/szaud0211/ Jegyzékben tiltakoznak 'a szaúdi terroristák' Gyurcsánynál] – [[index.hu]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=JOKE&gt;[http://www.magyarhirlap.hu/Archivum_cikk.php?cikk=92593&amp;archiv=1&amp;next=0 Nyúlik a vita az &quot;arab terroristákról&quot;] Magyar Hírlap&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 2006 general election campaign, a video appeared where Gyurcsány danced as [[Hugh Grant]] in ''[[Love Actually]]''.&lt;ref name=DANCE&gt;[http://home.eircom.net/content/reuters/uNews/7379070?view=Standard  Hungarian PM appears on Internet as Hugh Grant], eircom.net&lt;/ref&gt; According to government officials, the spokesperson of the government asked Gyurcsány to dance, as they re-made most parts of the film as a special gift for the wedding of spokesman András Batiz. Opposition claimed that the video was made public on purpose, as part of the election campaign, to gain popularity for the PM among young adults.

After his return to politics, Gyurcsány was at first tight-lipped on his religious affiliation, leading many to assume that he is an [[atheist]] . In an interview aired on TV2 during the 2006 parliamentary election campaign, Gyurcsány said that as a teenager, he &quot;took part in [[confirmation]] for about two years&quot; and even considered becoming a [[priest]].&lt;ref name=&quot;mokka&quot;&gt;&quot;Mokka&quot;, TV2, 2006-03-26&lt;/ref&gt; Since confirmation can only be taken once, some regarded this claim as a giveaway that he was not telling the truth, while others such as Catholic bishop Endre Gyulai supposed he meant he took part in preparations for a confirmation.&lt;ref name=&quot;kurir&quot;&gt;[http://www.magyarkurir.hu/?m_op=view&amp;id=9533&amp;rovat=4 Napi sajtószemle], Magyar Kurír, 2006-03-28 {{hu icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In connection with the unrest fuelled by his speech, he has been criticised in ''[[The Economist]]'' for &quot;turning a blind eye to police brutality&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.economist.com/daily/columns/europeview/displaystory.cfm?story_id=8491837 Europe.view], ''[[The Economist]]'', 4 January 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

On 2009 January 13, [[Dominique Strauss-Kahn]], the Managing Director of the [[International Monetary Fund]], travelled to Budapest to ask Gyurcsány about their agreement made in October, regarding the stabilization of Hungarian government spending.

===Gazprom===
As a Prime Minister, Ferenc Gyurcsány was said to be an advocate of the South Stream pipeline project, which is aimed to supply Russian gas directly to EU, bypassing transit countries such as Ukraine. He signed the contract in Moscow just week before a referendum at Hungary, which showed around 80% of the votes were against the government reforms.&lt;ref name=schroder&gt;[http://www.mn.mno.hu/portal/549993 Magyar Nemzet: &quot;Gyurcsány elindult a schröderi úton?&quot;], 21 March 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

== Notes ==
&lt;references group=&quot;i&quot; /&gt;

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
*[http://www.miniszterelnok.hu The Official Website of the Prime Minister of Hungary] (only a few facts in English yet)
*[http://home.eircom.net/content/reuters/uNews/7379070?view=Standard Hungarian PM appears on Internet as Hugh Grant]
*[http://blog.amoba.hu The blog of Ferenc Gyurcsány] {{hu icon}}
*[http://www.mszp.hu/index.php?gcPage=public/portretar/mutatPortre&amp;fnId=13425 His biography] {{hu icon}}
*[http://web.archive.org/web/20050309142525/www.origo.hu/uzletinegyed/hirek/2002111541tol.html The 100 richest people in Hungary], 2002., origo.hu. ([http://www.origo.hu/uzletinegyed/hirek/20021115elso.html Original URL]) {{hu icon}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-off}}
{{succession box
| title  = [[Government of Hungary|Minister of Youth Affairs and Sports]]
| before = [[György Jánosi]]
| years = 2003–2004
| after = Position abolished
}}
{{succession box
| title  = [[Prime Minister of Hungary]]
| before = [[Péter Medgyessy]]
| years = 2004–2009
| after = [[Gordon Bajnai]]
}}
{{s-ppo}}
{{Succession box
| before = [[István Hiller]]
| title  = [[Hungarian Socialist Party|Chairman of the Hungarian Socialist Party]]
| years = 2007–2009
| after  = [[Ildikó Lendvai]]
}}
{{Succession box
| before = Party established
| title  = [[Democratic Coalition|Chairman of the Democratic Coalition]]
| years = 2011–
| after  = Incumbent
}}
{{s-end}}
{{HungarianPrimeMinisters}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Gyucsany, Ferenc
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =Hungarian politician
| DATE OF BIRTH     =4 June 1961
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =[[Pápa]], [[People's Republic of Hungary|Hungary]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Gyucsany, Ferenc}}
[[Category:1961 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:People from Pápa]]
[[Category:Hungarian atheists]]
[[Category:Hungarian businesspeople]]
[[Category:Hungarian politicians]]
[[Category:Hungarian Socialist Party politicians]]
[[Category:Democratic Coalition politicians]]
[[Category:Prime Ministers of Hungary]]

[[bg:Ференц Дюрчан]]
[[bs:Ferenc Gyurcsány]]
[[ca:Ferenc Gyurcsány]]
[[cs:Ferenc Gyurcsány]]
[[da:Ferenc Gyurcsány]]
[[de:Ferenc Gyurcsány]]
[[et:Ferenc Gyurcsány]]
[[el:Φέρεντς Γκιουρτσάνι]]
[[es:Ferenc Gyurcsány]]
[[eo:Ferenc Gyurcsány]]
[[eu:Ferenc Gyurcsany]]
[[fr:Ferenc Gyurcsány]]
[[gl:Ferenc Gyurcsány]]
[[ko:주르차니 페렌츠]]
[[hr:Ferenc Gyurcsány]]
[[io:Ferenc Gyurcsány]]
[[id:Ferenc Gyurcsány]]
[[it:Ferenc Gyurcsány]]
[[la:Franciscus Gyurcsány]]
[[hu:Gyurcsány Ferenc]]
[[nl:Ferenc Gyurcsány]]
[[ja:ジュルチャーニ・フェレンツ]]
[[no:Ferenc Gyurcsány]]
[[nn:Ferenc Gyurcsány]]
[[oc:Ferenc Gyurcsány]]
[[pl:Ferenc Gyurcsány]]
[[pt:Ferenc Gyurcsány]]
[[ro:Ferenc Gyurcsány]]
[[ru:Дьюрчань, Ференц]]
[[sk:Ferenc Gyurcsány]]
[[sr:Ференц Ђурчањ]]
[[sh:Ferenc Gyurcsany]]
[[fi:Ferenc Gyurcsány]]
[[sv:Ferenc Gyurcsány]]
[[tr:Ferenc Gyurcsány]]
[[uk:Дюрчань Ференц]]
[[zh:久尔恰尼·费伦茨]]</text>
      <sha1>ry88w55tpmjy433swwjesuwlizuy4c8</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
