<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Fidel Castro</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>38301</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521145629</id>
      <parentid>521102461</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-03T02:15:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GFHandel</username>
        <id>5918812</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Politics */ &quot;that that&quot; -&gt; &quot;that&quot;.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="229894">{{bots|deny=Citation bot}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=September 2011}}
{{pp-semi-blp|small=yes}}{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Spanish name|Castro|Ruz}}
{{Infobox officeholder
|birth_name         = Fidel Alejandro Castro Ruz
|colorcode    = Red
|image        = Cuba.FidelCastro.02.jpg
|imagesize    = 250px
|caption      = Castro in front of a Havana statue of Cuban national hero, [[José Martí]], in 2003.
|office       = [[First Secretary of the Communist Party of Cuba|First Secretary]] of the &lt;br&gt; [[Communist Party of Cuba]]
|deputy       = [[Raúl Castro]]
|term_start   = July 1961
|term_end     = April 19, 2011
|predecessor  = [[Blas Roca Calderio]]
|successor    = [[Raúl Castro]]
|office2      = 15th [[President of Cuba]]
|primeminister2 = Himself
|term_start2  = December 2, 1976
|term_end2    = February 24, 2008*
|vicepresident2 = [[Raúl Castro]]
|predecessor2 = [[Osvaldo Dorticós Torrado]]
|successor2   = [[Raúl Castro]]
|office3      = 16th [[Prime Minister of Cuba]]
|president3   = [[Manuel Urrutia Lleó]]&lt;br&gt;[[Osvaldo Dorticós Torrado]]&lt;br&gt;Himself
|term_start3  = February 16, 1959
|term_end3    = February 24, 2008
|predecessor3 = [[José Miró Cardona]]
|successor3   = [[Raúl Castro]]
|office5      = 7th and 23rd [[Non-Aligned Movement|Secretary-General of the Non-Aligned Movement]]
|term_start5  = September 16, 2006
|term_end5    = February 24, 2008
|predecessor5 = [[Abdullah Ahmad Badawi]]
|successor5   = [[Raúl Castro]]
|term_start6  = September 10, 1979
|term_end6    = March 6, 1983
|predecessor6 = [[Junius Richard Jayawardene]]
|successor6   = [[Neelam Sanjiva Reddy]]
|birth_date   = {{birth date and age|1926|8|13}}
|birth_place  = [[Birán]], Cuba
|death_date   =
|death_place  =
|party        = [[Communist Party of Cuba]]
|relations    = (siblings)&lt;br&gt;[[Raúl Castro]]&lt;br&gt;Enma Castro&lt;br&gt;Agustina Castro&lt;br&gt;[[Ramon Castro Ruz]]&lt;br&gt;Angelita Castro
|spouse       = [[Mirta Diaz-Balart]] &lt;small&gt;(1948–1955)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;Dalia Soto del Valle &lt;small&gt;(1980–present)&lt;/small&gt;
|children     = Fidel Ángel Castro Diaz-Balart&lt;br&gt;[[Alina Fernández|Alina Fernández-Revuelta]]&lt;br&gt;Alexis Castro-Soto&lt;br&gt;Alejandro Castro-Soto&lt;br&gt;Antonio Castro-Soto&lt;br&gt;Angel Castro-Soto&lt;br&gt;Alex Castro-Soto&lt;br&gt;Jorge Angel Castro&lt;br&gt;Francisca Pupo
|alma_mater   = [[University of Havana]]
|profession   = Lawyer
|religion     = None
|signature    = Fidel Castro Signature.svg
|footnotes    = *Acting presidential powers were [[2006–2008 Cuban transfer of presidential duties|transferred]] to Raúl Castro from July 31, 2006.
}}

'''Fidel Alejandro Castro Ruz''' ({{IPA-es|fiˈðel ˈkastro|lang}}; born August 13, 1926) is a [[Cuban people|Cuban]] [[communism|communist]] revolutionary and politician, having held the position of [[Prime Minister of Cuba]] from 1959 to 1976, and then [[President of Cuba|President]] from 1976 to 2008. He also served as the [[Secretary of the Communist Party of Cuba|First Secretary]] of the [[Communist Party of Cuba]] from the party's foundation in 1961 until 2011. Politically a [[Marxism-Leninism|Marxist-Leninist]], under his administration the [[Cuba|Republic of Cuba]] was converted into a one-party [[socialist state]], with industry and business being nationalized under state ownership and [[socialism|socialist]] reforms implemented in all areas of society. On the international stage, he also served as the Secretary-General of the [[Non-Aligned Movement]] from 1979 to 1983 and 2006 to 2008.

Born the illegitimate son of a wealthy farmer, Castro became involved in leftist [[Anti-imperialism|anti-imperialist]] politics while studying law at the [[University of Havana]]. Involving himself in armed rebellions against right-wing governments in the Dominican Republic and Colombia, he concluded that the U.S.-backed Cuban President [[Fulgencio Batista]], who was widely seen as a dictator, had to be overthrown; to this end he led a failed armed attack on the [[Moncada Barracks]] in 1953. Imprisoned for a year, he traveled to Mexico, and with the aid of his brother [[Raúl Castro]] and friend [[Che Guevara]], assembled a group of revolutionaries, the [[26th of July Movement]]. Returning with them to Cuba, he took a key role in the [[Cuban Revolution]], leading a successful [[guerrilla warfare|guerrilla war]] against Batista's forces, overthrowing him in 1959. Castro subsequently became [[Rank and Insignia of the Cuban Revolutionary Armed Forces|Commander in Chief]] of the [[Cuban Revolutionary Armed Forces|armed forces]] and shortly thereafter became Prime Minister. The United States was alarmed by his involvement in the overthrow of Batista and relationship with Soviet Premier [[Nikita Khrushchev]], implementing an economic blockade of the island. U.S. President [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]] also ordered the [[Central Intelligence Agency]] (CIA) to overthrow him, which they unsuccessfully tried through multiple assassination attempts and the failed [[Bay of Pigs invasion]] of 1961. To counter this threat, Castro forged an economic and military alliance with the Soviet Union and allowed them to place nuclear weapons on the island, leading to the events of the [[Cuban Missile Crisis]] in 1962.

Adopting Marxism-Leninism as his guiding ideology, in 1961 Castro proclaimed the socialist nature of the Cuban revolution, and in 1965 became First Secretary of the newly founded Communist Party. He then led the transformation of Cuba into a one-party socialist republic, nationalizing industry, embarking on the large-scale construction of housing and infrastructure and introducing free healthcare and education; the administration also halted the [[freedom of the press]] and suppressed internal dissidents considered to be counter-revolutionaries. A keen internationalist, Castro introduced Cuban medical brigades who worked throughout the developing world, and aided foreign revolutionary socialist groups in the hope of toppling world [[capitalism]], thereby involving Cuba in the [[Yom Kippur War]], [[Angolan Civil War]] and the [[Ogaden War]]. In 1976 he stepped down as Prime Minister to become President of both the [[Council of State of Cuba|Council of State]] and [[Council of Ministers of Cuba|Council of Ministers]]. Following the collapse of the Soviet Union in 1991, Castro led Cuba into its economic &quot;[[Special Period]]&quot;, before taking the country into the [[Bolivarian Alliance for the Americas]] in 2006 and forging alliances with other nations in the Latin American &quot;[[Pink tide|Pink Tide]]&quot;. Amidst failing health, in 2006 Castro [[2006 Cuban transfer of presidential duties|transferred his responsibilities]] to Vice-President Raúl Castro, who then became President when Fidel stepped down in 2008.

Castro is a controversial and highly divisive world figure, being lauded as a champion of anti-imperialism, humanitarianism, socialism and environmentalism by his supporters, but his critics have accused him of being a dictator whose authoritarian administration has overseen [[Human rights in Cuba|multiple human rights abuses]] both at home and abroad. A prolific author on various topics, he has had a significant influence on the politics of various individuals and groups across the world, including senior leaders like [[Nelson Mandela]], [[Hugo Chávez]] and [[Evo Morales]].

==Early life==
===Childhood and education: 1926&amp;ndash;1945===
[[File:FCR to FDR letter complete.jpg|thumb|left|A letter written by the 14-year-old Castro, learning English, to U.S. President [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]]{{mdash}}&quot;My good friend Roosevelt.&quot; In the letter Castro expresses his joy at Roosevelt's re-election, states his age as &quot;twelve years old&quot; and writes, &quot;If you like, give me a ten dollar bill green American, because never, I have not seen a ten dollar bill&quot;, signing the letter, &quot;Thank you very much. Good by {{sic}}. Your friend, Fidel Castro.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Quirk 1993. p. 14&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt;]]

Fidel's father, [[Ángel Castro y Argiz]] (1875&amp;ndash;1956) was a Spaniard born to a poor peasant family in rural [[Galicia (Spain)|Galicia]], Northwest Spain. Working as a manual laborer on local farms, in 1895 he was conscripted into the Spanish Army to fight in the [[Cuban War of Independence]] against the Cuban revolutionaries who wished to secede from the [[Spanish Empire]]. The United States declared war on Spain, leading to the [[Spanish-American War]] of 1898, in which the U.S. seized control of Cuba, setting up their own government on the island. In 1902, the [[Republic of Cuba]] was proclaimed, however it remained only partially independent of the U.S., which retained economic and political dominance over it. For a time, Cuba enjoyed economic growth, and Ángel Castro decided to migrate there permanently in search of employment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986. p. 14-15&quot;&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 14&amp;ndash;15.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 7&amp;ndash;8.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 1&amp;ndash;2.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Castro Ramonet. p. 24-29&quot;&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. pp. 24&amp;ndash;29.&lt;/ref&gt; Doing so, he undertook various jobs, eventually earning enough money to set up his own business growing sugar cane on a farm named Las Manacas in [[Birán]], near [[Mayarí]] in [[Oriente Province]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986. p. 14-15&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 2&amp;ndash;3.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Castro Ramonet. p. 24-29&quot;/&gt;

Ángel took a wife, María Luisa Argota, with whom he had two daughters, but they separated after several years and he began a relationship with a household servant who was thirty years his junior.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986. p. 16&quot;&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 03&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt; This woman, Lina Ruz González (September 23, 1903 – August 6, 1963),&lt;ref name=&quot;Parents&quot; &gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.wargs.com/other/castro.html |title=Ancestry of Fidel Castro |work=wargs.com |accessdate=December 25, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; came from an impoverished Cuban family of [[Canarian people|Canarian]] descent, but became Ángel's domestic partner, bearing him three sons and four daughters.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 16&amp;ndash;17.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 03&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. pp. 31&amp;ndash;32.&lt;/ref&gt;

Fidel was Lina's third child, being born at his father's farm on August 13, 1926,&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 03&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. pp. 23&amp;ndash;24.&lt;/ref&gt; and was given his mother's surname of Ruz rather than his father's because he had been born out of [[Marriage|wedlock]], something that carried a particular social stigma at the time. Although he was from a prosperous background, with his father's business proving ever more profitable, his father ensured that he grew up alongside the children of the farm's workforce, many of whom were Haitian economic migrants of African descent,&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986. p. 16&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 3&amp;ndash;4.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 4&amp;ndash;5.&lt;/ref&gt; something that Fidel would later relate prevented him from absorbing &quot;bourgeois culture&quot; at an early age.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. pp. 42–43.&lt;/ref&gt; Aged six, Fidel, along with his elder siblings Ramón and Angela, was sent to live with their teacher in [[Santiago de Cuba]], and it was here that the children dwelt in cramped conditions and in relative poverty, often failing to have enough to eat because of their tutor's poor economic situation.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 05-06&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 5&amp;ndash;6.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. pp. 45&amp;ndash;48, 52&amp;ndash;57.&lt;/ref&gt; Aged eight, Fidel was then [[baptism|baptized]] into the Roman Catholic Church, although later gave up his faith in Christianity, becoming an atheist.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 29&amp;ndash;30.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 05-06&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. pp. 59&amp;ndash;60.&lt;/ref&gt; Being baptized enabled Fidel to begin attending the La Salle boarding school in Santiago, but here he often got into trouble with the school authorities for misbehavior, and so he was instead sent to the privately funded, [[Jesuit]]-run Dolores School in Santiago.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 6&amp;ndash;7.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. pp. 64–67.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1945 he transferred to the more prestigious Jesuit-run [[Belen Jesuit Preparatory School|El Colegio de Belén]] in [[Havana]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Quirk 1993. p. 14&quot;&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 8&amp;ndash;9.&lt;/ref&gt; Although Fidel took an interest in history, geography and debating at Belén, he did not excel academically, instead devoting much of his time to playing sport, including swimming, mountain climbing, table tennis, athletics, basketball and baseball.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 12&amp;ndash;13, 16&amp;ndash;19.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. p. 68.&lt;/ref&gt;

===University and early political activism: 1945&amp;ndash;1947===

{{double image|right|Grau.jpg|165|Carlos Prio Socarras of Cuba.jpg|160|Cuban Presidents Grau and Prío, whose administrations faced student protests that Castro took part in.}}

In late 1945, Castro began studying law at the [[University of Havana]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 16&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. pp. 91&amp;ndash;92.&lt;/ref&gt; Admitting that he was &quot;politically illiterate&quot;, here he became immediately embroiled in the student protest movement, which in Cuba at that time was particularly volatile: under the regimes of Cuban Presidents [[Gerardo Machado]] (1925–1933), [[Fulgencio Batista]] (1933–1944) and [[Ramón Grau]] (1944–1948) there had been a government crackdown on student protesters, with student leaders being killed or terrorized by violent gangs.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 9–10.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 20, 22.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. pp. 16-17&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 16–17.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. pp. 91–93.&lt;/ref&gt; This led to a form of ''gangsterismo'' culture within the university that was dominated by a variety of violent and often armed student groups who spent much of their time fighting one another and running criminal enterprises rather than opposing the government.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 34–35.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Quirk 1993. p. 23&quot;&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 23.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt; Becoming surrounded by this gang culture, Castro focused on political objectives, unsuccessfully campaigning for the position of President of the Federation of University Students (''Federación Estudiantíl Universitaria'' - FEU). To do so he put forward a platform of &quot;honesty, decency and justice&quot; and emphasized his opposition to political corruption, something that he increasingly associated with the involvement of the U.S. government in Cuban politics.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 32–33.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 18&amp;ndash;19.&lt;/ref&gt; He became passionate about [[anti-imperialism]] and opposing U.S. intervention in the Caribbean, joining the University Committee for the [[Puerto Rican independence movement|Independence of Puerto Rico]] and the Committee for Democracy in the Dominican Republic.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 20.&lt;/ref&gt;

He was in contact with members of several student leftist groups at the time, including the [[Popular Socialist Party (Cuba)|Popular Socialist Party]] (''Partido Socialista Popular'' – PSP), the Socialist Revolutionary Movement (''Movimiento Socialista Revolucionaria'' – MSR) and the Insurrectional Revolutionary Union (''Unión Insurrecional Revolucionaria'' – UIR), although did not adopt the [[Marxism|Marxist]] ideas of the former and mistrusted some of MSR's connections to the Grau government. Castro had become critical of the corruption and violence of Grau's regime, delivering a public speech on the subject in November 1946 that earned him a place on the front page of several newspapers. Instead, it was to the UIR that he grew closest to, although whether he ever became a member or not has remained unknown.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 34–37, 63.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 21&amp;ndash;24.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1947, Castro joined a newly founded socialist group, the Party of the Cuban People (''[[Partido Ortodoxo]]''), which had been formed by veteran politician [[Eduardo Chibás]] (1907–1951). A charismatic figure, Chibás attracted many Cubans with his message of social justice, honest government, and political freedom. The ''Partido Ortodoxo'' publicly exposed corruption and demanded governmental and social reform. Though Chibás lost the election, Castro, considering Chibás his mentor, remained committed to his cause, working fervently on his behalf.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 39&amp;ndash;40.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ben92|Benjamin 1992]]. p. 131.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 28&amp;ndash;29.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 23–27.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. pp. 83–85.&lt;/ref&gt;

Meanwhile, the student gang violence had escalated after Grau employed several prominent gang leaders, including members of the MSR, as officers in the police force, and Castro soon received a threat urging him to either leave the university and its political arena or be killed. He did not give in to the threat, instead carrying a gun and surrounding himself with friends who were similarly armed.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 27–28.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. pp. 95–97.&lt;/ref&gt; Various accusations would arise in later years alleging that Castro carried out gang-related assassination attempts at this time, including of prominent UIR member Lionel Gómez, MSR leader Manolo Castro and university policeman Oscar Fernandez, but these are supported by &quot;scant evidence&quot; and remain unproven.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;[[#Von11|Von Tunzelmann 2011]]. p. 39.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 35–36, 54.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 25, 27.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 23–24, 37–38, 46.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Latin American rebellions: 1947–1948===

In June 1947, Castro learned of a planned international expedition to invade the Dominican Republic and overthrow its right-wing president, [[Rafael Trujillo]], a military general widely seen as a dictator who had overseen a system of &quot;repressive brutality&quot; through the use of a violent secret police which routinely murdered and tortured opponents.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 30.&lt;/ref&gt; An ally of the United States, Trujillo angered many across the world when he ordered the [[Parsley Massacre]] that killed 20,000–30,000 impoverished Haitian migrants.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Von11|Von Tunzelmann 2011]]. pp. 30–33.&lt;/ref&gt; Castro had become a heavy critic of Trujillo's regime, rising to the presidency of the University Committee for Democracy in the Dominican Republic, and decided to join the military expedition, which was led by General [[Juan Rodríguez (Dominican general)|Juan Rodríguez]], a Dominican exile, and supported by Grau's Cuban government which feared Trujillo's militaristic behavior.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 40–41.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Quirk 1993. p. 23&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; The invasion was carried out on July 29, 1947, by around 1,200 men, most of whom were exiled Dominicans or Cubans, although other volunteers came from across Latin America. However, both Dominican and U.S. intelligence had gained foreknowledge of the event, and it was soon quashed by the Dominican army and the Cuban government, who had been pressured by the U.S. to cease their support for it. Whilst Grau's government immediately arrested many of those involved, Castro managed to escape the police by jumping off of the naval frigate he was aboard and swimming to shore in the dark of night.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 41–42.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 24.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 32–34.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote box|width=25em|align=left|bgcolor=#ACE1AF|quote=&quot;I joined the people; I grabbed a rifle in a police station that collapsed when it was rushed by a crowd. I witnessed the spectacle of a totally spontaneous revolution... [T]hat experience led me to identify myself even more with the cause of the people. My still incipient Marxist ideas had nothing to do with our conduct – it was a spontaneous reaction on our part, as young people with [[José Martí|Martí-an]], anti-imperialist, anti-colonialist and pro-democratic ideas.&quot;|source=— Fidel Castro on the Bogotazo, 2009 &lt;ref&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. p. 98.&lt;/ref&gt; }}

The botched mission only served to further Castro's opposition to the Grau administration, and returning to Havana, he took a leading role in the student protests that were centered against the killing of a high school pupil by government bodyguards.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 34–35.&lt;/ref&gt; The protests, accompanied by a U.S.-imposed crackdown on those considered to be communists, led to violent clashes between protesters and police in February 1948, in which Castro was badly beaten.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 36–37.&lt;/ref&gt; It was at this point that his public speeches took on a distinctively leftist slant, condemning the social and economic inequalities of Cuba under the Grau government, something that was in contrast to his former public criticisms, which had centered around condemning corruption and U.S. imperialism. Castro's biographer [[Arthur Leycester Scott Coltman|Leycester Coltman]] would later remark that &quot;Castro was not yet expressing a Marxist viewpoint, but he was moving in that direction.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 36.&lt;/ref&gt;

After a quick visit to Venezuela and Panama, in April 1948 Castro traveled to the city of [[Bogotá]] in Colombia with a number of other Cuban students on a trip sponsored by the government of Argentine President [[Juan Perón]], whose anti-imperialist politics impressed Castro. Once there, the assassination of popular leftist leader [[Jorge Eliécer Gaitán Ayala]] led to widespread rioting that came to be known as the [[Bogotazo]]. Leaving three thousand dead, the riots revolved around clashes between rightist [[Colombian Conservative Party|Conservatives]], who then controlled the country's government and who were backed by the army, and leftist [[Colombian Liberal Party|Liberals]] who were supported by a number of Colombian socialist groups. Castro, along with his fellow Cuban visitors, joined in in support of the Liberal cause by stealing guns from a police station, but subsequent police investigations came to the conclusion that neither Castro nor any of the other Cubans had been involved in the killings.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 46&amp;ndash;52.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 25&amp;ndash;26.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 40&amp;ndash;45.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. pp. 98&amp;ndash;99.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Von11|Von Tunzelmann 2011]]. p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Marriage and Marxism: 1948–1950===
Returning to Cuba, Castro became a prominent figure in the widespread protests against the government's attempts to raise bus fares, with buses being the only form of transport available to most students and workers.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 54, 56.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 46–49.&lt;/ref&gt; It was also in 1948 that Castro married [[Mirta Diaz-Balart|Mirta Díaz Balart]], a student from a wealthy Cuban family through whom he was exposed to the lifestyle of the Cuban elite. The relationship was a love match and was disapproved of by both of their families. Mirta's father gave them tens of thousands of dollars to spend in a three-month honeymoon in New York City, and the couple also received a U.S. $1,000 wedding gift from the military general and former president [[Fulgencio Batista]], a friend of Mirta's family.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 55.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 27.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 47–48.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Von11|Von Tunzelmann 2011]]. p. 41.&lt;/ref&gt; That same year, Grau decided not to stand for re-election, and his ''[[Partido Auténtico]]'' instead nominated [[Carlos Prío Socarrás]] as their presidential candidate. Prío would go on to win the election, becoming President of Cuba.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 54–55.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 46.&lt;/ref&gt; However, he faced widespread protests when members of the MSR, which by this time was allied to the police force, assassinated Justo Fuentes, a &quot;self-taught black man&quot; and prominent member of the UIR who was a friend and ally of Castro's. In response, Prío agreed to try to quell the gangs, but found them to be too powerful to control.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote box|width=25em|align=right|bgcolor=#ACE1AF|quote=&quot;Marxism taught me what society was. I was like a blindfolded man in a forest, who doesn't even know where north or south is. If you don't eventually come to truly understand the history of the [[class struggle]], or at least have a clear idea that society is divided between the rich and the poor, and that some people subjugate and exploit other people, you're lost in a forest, not knowing anything.&quot;|source=— Fidel Castro on discovering Marxism, 2009 &lt;ref&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. p. 100.&lt;/ref&gt; }}

Castro had begun to move further to the left in his political views, being influenced by the writings of prominent [[Marxism|Marxists]] like [[Karl Marx]], [[Friedrich Engels]] and [[Vladimir Lenin]]. He came to interpret the problems facing Cuba as being an integral part of capitalist society, or the &quot;dictatorship of the bourgeoisie&quot;, rather than the failings of corrupt politicians. Coming to believe the Marxist idea that meaningful political change could only be brought about by a revolution led by the working class, Castro set about visiting Havana's poorest neighborhoods, witnessing the nation's huge social and racial inequalities, and became active in the University Committee for the Struggle against Racial Discrimination.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986. p. 57&quot;&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 57.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 50&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 50.&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 1949, Mirta gave birth to a son, Fidelito, and so the couple moved to a larger flat in Havana.&lt;ref name=&quot;Quirk 1993. p. 29&quot;&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 29.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 50&quot;/&gt; Despite the need to care for his family, Castro continued to put himself at risk, staying active in the city's political arena and joining a new organization, the September 30 Movement, which contained within it both communists and members of the ''Partido Ortodoxo''. The group's purpose was to oppose the influence of the violent gangs within the university; despite his promises, President Prío had failed to control the situation, instead offering many of their senior members jobs in government ministries.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 39.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 51&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 51.&lt;/ref&gt; Castro volunteered to deliver a speech for the Movement on November 13, in which he exposed the government's secret deals with the gangs and identified many of their key members. Attracting the attention of the national press, the speech angered the gangs, and Castro was forced to go into hiding, first in various rural areas and then in the U.S.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 51&quot;/&gt; Returning to Havana several weeks later, Castro lay low and focused on his university studies, graduating from university as a Doctor of Law in September 1950.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986. p. 57&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 51&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. p. 89.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Career in law and politics: 1950–1952===

Now a Doctor of Law, Castro became a professional lawyer, founding his own legal partnership with two fellow leftist students, Jorge Azpiazu and Rafael Resende, whose intention was to focus on helping poor Cubans in asserting their rights. It was a financial failure, with its main client being a timber merchant who paid them in timber to furnish their office.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 57–58.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Quirk 1993 31&quot;&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 51–52.&lt;/ref&gt; Castro cared little for money or material goods, something his wife found difficult, particularly when their furniture was reposessed and their electricity cut off, in both instances because Castro had failed to pay his bills.&lt;ref name=&quot;Quirk 1993 31&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 52–53.&lt;/ref&gt; Castro remained active in politics, taking part in a high-school protest in [[Cienfuegos]] in November 1950 that involved students fighting a four-hour battle with police in protest at the Education Ministry's ban on the founding of student associations in schools. He was arrested and charged with using violence against police officers, but the magistrate later dismissed the charges.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 53&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 53.&lt;/ref&gt; He also became an active member of the Cuban Peace Committee, a part of the international campaign led by British intellectual [[Betrand Russell]] to oppose western involvement in the [[Korean War]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 53&quot;/&gt; His hopes for Cuba still largely centered around [[Eduardo Chibás]] and his left wing ''[[Partido Ortodoxo]]''; however Chibás had made a mistake when he accused Education Minister Aureliano Sánchez of purchasing a Guatemalan ranch with misappropriated funds, but was unable to substantiate his allegations. The government used this as an opportunity to go on the offensive against Chibás, accusing him of being a liar and a troublemaker. In 1951, while running for president again, Chibás shot himself in the stomach during a radio broadcast in an attempt to issue a &quot;last wake-up call&quot; to the Cuban people. Castro was present and accompanied him to the hospital where he died of his injuries.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 46, 53–55.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 58–59.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. pp. 85–87.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Von Tunzelmann. p. 44&quot;&gt;[[#Von11|Von Tunzelmann 2011]]. p. 44.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:BatistaDC1938.jpg|280px|thumb|left|Castro intended to overthrow the presidency of General Fulgencio Batista (left, with [[Chief of Staff of the United States Army|U.S. Army Chief of staff]] [[Malin Craig]]).]]

Although his political views were further left than the ''Partido Ortodoxo'', Castro believed that those parties on the far left, namely the PSP, were too unpopular to achieve a revolutionary leftist movement in Cuba, and for this reason remained in the ''Ortodoxo''. Seeing himself as the heir to Chibás, Castro wanted to run for Congress in the June 1952 elections, but senior party members feared his radical reputation and refused to nominate him. Instead he gained the support of enough ''Ortodoxo'' members in Havana's poorest districts to be nominated as a candidate for the House of Representatives, and put all his energies into campaigning.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 56–57, 62–63.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 36.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 55–56.&lt;/ref&gt; It was at the time that Castro held a meeting with General [[Fulgencio Batista]], the former president who had recently returned to politics by winning a seat in the Senate and founding the Unitary Action Party; although they both opposed the Prío administration, their meeting never got beyond &quot;polite generalities&quot; with no indication that they would later become bitter enemies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Quirk 1993. p. 29&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt;

The ''Ortodoxo'' had gained a considerable level of support, and there was a &quot;fair chance that the ''Ortodoxos'' and Castro would both have succeeded in the election.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 57.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 33&amp;ndash;34.&lt;/ref&gt; However, this was quashed in March 1952 when General Batista seized power in a military coup, removing the widely discredited President Prío from office, who then fled to Mexico. Subsequently declaring himself president, Batista cancelled the planned presidential elections, describing his new system as &quot;disciplined democracy&quot;: Castro, like many others, instead saw it as the establishment of a one-man dictatorship with no benefit to the Cuban populace.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 64–65.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 37&amp;ndash;39.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 57–62.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Got04|Gott 2004]]. p. 146.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Von Tunzelmann. p. 44&quot;/&gt; Although in his earlier elected term as president Batista had taken a center-left stance, he now moved to the right and went on to solidify his ties with both the wealthy elite and the United States, severing diplomatic relations with the Soviet Union, suppressing trade unions and persecuting socialist groups in Cuba.&lt;ref name=&quot;Von Tunzelmann. p. 44&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 64.&lt;/ref&gt; Intent on opposing the Batista administration, Castro brought several legal cases against them, arguing that Batista had committed sufficient criminal acts to warrant at least 100 years imprisonment and accusing various ministers of breaching labor laws. These came to nothing, leading Castro to begin thinking of alternative ways to oust the new government.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 41, 45.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 63.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Cuban Revolution==
{{Main|Cuban Revolution}}

===The Movement and the Moncada Barracks attack: 1952–1953===
{{Quote box|width=25em|bgcolor=#ACE1AF|align=right|quote=&quot;In a few hours you will be victorious or defeated, but regardless of the outcome – listen well, friends – this Movement will triumph. If you win tomorrow, the aspirations of Martí will be fulfilled sooner. If we fail, our action will nevertheless set an example for the Cuban people, and from the people will arise fresh new men willing to die for Cuba. They will pick up our banner and move forward... The people will back us in Oriente and in the whole island. As in '68 and '92, here in Oriente we will give the first cry of Liberty or Death!&quot;|source=— Fidel Castro's speech to the Movement just before the Moncada Attack, 1953 &lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 79.&lt;/ref&gt; }}
Dissatisfied with the ''Ortodoxo'''s policy of non-violent opposition to Batista's regime, Castro formed a group known simply as &quot;The Movement.&quot; Consisting of both a civil and a military committee, the former conducted political agitation through an underground newspaper, ''El Acusador'' (''The Accuser''), while the latter armed and trained recruits to take violent action against Batista. With Castro as the Movement's head, the organization was based upon a [[clandestine cell system]], with each cell containing ten members, none of whom knew the whereabouts or activities of the other cells.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 68–69.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 50&amp;ndash;52.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 65.&lt;/ref&gt; A dozen individuals formed the nucleus of the movement, many of whom were also dissatisfied ''Ortodoxo'' members, although from July 1952 the Movement went on a recruitment drive, and within a year it had around 1,200 members, organized into over a hundred cells, with the majority of members coming from the poorer districts of Havana.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 69.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 66.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;castro107&quot;&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. p. 107.&lt;/ref&gt; Although Castro's political ideology was that of [[revolutionary socialism]], he avoided an alliance with the communist PSP, fearing that this would frighten away the political moderates who were members of the Movement,&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 66–67.&lt;/ref&gt; but did keep in contact with some of the PSP's members, who included his brother and fellow conspirator Raúl.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 73.&lt;/ref&gt; He would later relate that the members of the Movement were on the whole simply anti-Batista, and few had strong socialist or anti-imperialist views, something which Castro attributed to &quot;the overwhelming weight of the [[Yankee|Yankees']] ideological and advertising machinery&quot; which he felt had suppressed [[class consciousness]] amongst Cuba's working class.&lt;ref name=&quot;castro107&quot;/&gt;

Castro's Movement was not the only militant group that wanted to oust Batista. One of the ''Ortodoxo'''s founding members, the Professor of Philosophy [[Rafael García Bárcena]], had founded the National Revolutionary Movement (''Movimiento Nacional Revolucionaria'' – MNR). Consisting largely of middle-class members, it contrasted with Castro's predominantly working class support base. In March 1953, the MNR had planned to attack and seize control of the barracks at Camp Colombia, but police had been alerted to the plot, with the conspirators being rounded up and tortured. In all, fourteen people were sentenced to imprisonment for the attack.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 71–72.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 45.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 72.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. pp. 104–106.&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, Castro had been having similar ideas, stockpiling weapons in order to lead the armed wing of the Movement in an attack on the [[Moncada Barracks]], a military garrison just outside [[Santiago de Cuba]] in [[Oriente Province|Oriente]]. The plan was for Castro's members to dress in army uniforms and arrive at the base in cars on July 25, the festival of St James, when many of the officers would be on leave or celebrating in the nearby town. The rebels would then seize control of the barracks before the alarm could be raised, raid the armory and then escape before the army could bring in reinforcements.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 69–70, 73.&lt;/ref&gt; Supplied with a wealth of new weaponry, Castro believed that the Movement could arm local supporters and spark a revolution in Oriente, which was dominated by a population of impoverished cane-cutters. The plan was to then seize control of a radio station in Santiago, from which the Movement could broadcast their manifesto and promote widespread uprisings against Batista.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 74.&lt;/ref&gt; In doing so, Castro's plan was directly emulating those of the 19th century Cuban independence fighters who had raided Spanish barracks, and in keeping with this Castro saw himself as the heir to independence leader and national hero [[José Martí]], both leading national liberation struggles against foreign dominance.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 71, 74.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 76.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Moncada.jpg|thumb|230px|left|Fidel Castro under arrest in July 1953 after the Moncada attack.]]

Castro had gathered together 165 members of the Movement to take part in the mission, 138 of which were stationed in Santiago, with the other 27 instead positioned in [[Bayamo]]. The majority of them were young men from Havana and [[Pinar del Río]], and Castro ensured that, with the exception of himself, none of the volunteers had children.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 75–76.&lt;/ref&gt; The plan had been carefully orchestrated, and Castro ordered his troops not to cause bloodshed unless they met armed resistance.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 78.&lt;/ref&gt; The attack took place on July 26, 1953, but before it had even begun it ran into trouble; of the sixteen cars that had set out from Santiago, one broke down on the way and two others got separated from the main convoy. When they eventually reached the barracks, further problems arose and soon the alarm was raised by the guards, with most of the rebels being pinned down outside of the base by machine gun fire. Those that managed to get inside faced heavy resistance, and four of them were killed by gunfire before Castro, realizing that he was heavily outnumbered, ordered his men to retreat.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 80–84.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 52&amp;ndash;55.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 80–81.&lt;/ref&gt; In the attack, the rebels had suffered 6 fatalities and 15 other casualties, whilst the government forces had faced a heavier toll, with 19 dead and 27 wounded.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 82&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 82.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Meanwhile, some of the other rebels had taken over a civilian hospital, but as the main attack on the barracks failed, government soldiers stormed the hospital, rounding up the rebels, before torturing them for information and finally summarily executing 22 of them without trial.&lt;ref name=&quot;Quirk 1993 55&quot;&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 55.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 82&quot;/&gt; Those rebels that had been able to escape, and who included both Fidel and his brother Raúl, had assembled at their base, the Siboney Farm, where some debated surrender, while others wished to flee to Havana. Accompanied by 19 comrades, Castro however decided to set out for Gran Piedra in the rugged [[Sierra Maestra]] mountains several miles to the north, where they could establish a guerrilla base and continue their revolutionary activities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Quirk 1993 55&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 83.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 83.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. pp. 133–134.&lt;/ref&gt; In response to the Moncada attack, Batista's government proclaimed [[martial law]], ordering a violent crackdown on all dissent and imposing strict censorship on the media. Government propaganda began broadcasting misinformation about the event, claiming that the rebels had murdered patients in the civilian hospital and asserting that the Movement was a communist group financed by the exiled President Prío, ignoring the fact that the latter was a fierce anti-communist. Despite this censorship, news and photographs soon spread of the army's use of torture and summary executions in Oriente, causing widespread public and even some governmental disapproval.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 87–88.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 55&amp;ndash;56.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 84.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Arrest and trial: 1953===
{{Quote box|width=25em|bgcolor=#ACE1AF|align=left|quote=&quot;I warn you, I am just beginning! If there is in your hearts a vestige of love for your country, love for humanity, love for justice, listen carefully... I know that the regime will try to suppress the truth by all possible means; I know that there will be a conspiracy to bury me in oblivion. But my voice will not be stifled – it will rise from my breast even when I feel most alone, and my heart will give it all the fire that callous cowards deny it... Condemn me. It does not matter. History will absolve me.&quot;|source=— Fidel Castro in &quot;History Will Absolve Me&quot;, 1953 &lt;ref name=&quot;History Will Absolve Me&quot;&gt;An English language translation of &quot;History Will Absolve Me&quot; can be found at {{cite web|last =Castro |first =Fidel |url = http://www.marxists.org/history/cuba/archive/castro/1953/10/16.htm|title = History Will Absolve Me|publisher=Editorial de Ciencias Sociales, La Habana, Cuba|accessdate =09 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; }}
Over the next few days all of the rebels hiding in the mountains were rounded up by government forces and transported to a prison north of Santiago, although Castro was not executed on the spot as many of his comrades had been.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 86.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 55&amp;ndash;56.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 86.&lt;/ref&gt; Believing that Castro had been incapable of planning the attack by himself, the government accused politicians from the ''Ortodoxo'' and communist PSP of being involved in masterminding the attack, and in all 122 defendants, amongst them Castro, were put on trial on September 21 at the Palace of Justice in Santiago.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 91.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 57.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 87.&lt;/ref&gt; Although censored from reporting on it, journalists were permitted to attend the proceedings, which proved an embarrassment for the Batista administration. Acting as his own defense council, Castro convinced the three presiding judges to overrule the army's decision to keep all defendants handcuffed in court, before proceeding to argue that the charge with which they were all accused – of 'organizing an uprising of armed persons against the Constitutional Powers of the State' – was incorrect, for they had risen up not against the Constitutional Powers of the State but against Batista, who had seized power in an unconstitutional manner. When asked who was the intellectual author of the attack, Castro claimed that it was the long deceased national icon José Martí, before quoting some of Martí's works that justified uprisings against tyrannical regimes.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 91–92.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 57&amp;ndash;59.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 88.&lt;/ref&gt;

As the trial went on, knowledge of the torture that army officers inflicted on their captives emerged. These included castration using a razor and the gouging out of eyes with bayonets; the judges agreed that full investigations into these crimes would have to be undertaken. These revelations proved to be a great embarrassment to the army, which tried unsuccessfully to prevent Castro from testifying any further by claiming that he was too ill to leave his cell.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 58.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 88–89.&lt;/ref&gt; The trial came to an end on October 5, with all of the politicians and many of the rebels being acquitted, although 55 were sentenced to prison terms of between 7 months and 13 years. Castro was sentenced separately, on October 16, during which he proceeded to deliver a speech that would later be printed under the title of ''[[History Will Absolve Me]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986. p. 93&quot;&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 93.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 59.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 90.&lt;/ref&gt; Although the maximum penalty for leading an uprising was a 20 year prison sentence, Castro was sentenced to 15 years, being imprisoned in the hospital wing of the Model Prison (''Presidio Modelo''), a relatively comfortable and modern institution on the [[Isla de la Juventud|Isla de Pinos]], sixty miles off of Cuba's southwest coast.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986. p. 93&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 58&amp;ndash;60.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 91–92.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Imprisonment and the 26th of July Movement: 1953–1955===

{{Quote box|width=25em|align=right|bgcolor=#ACE1AF|quote=&quot;I would honestly love to revolutionize this country from one end to the other! I am sure this would bring happiness to the Cuban people. I would not be stopped by the hatred and ill will of a few thousand people, including some of my relatives, half the people I know, two-thirds of my fellow professionals, and four-fifths of my ex-schoolmates.&quot;|source=— Fidel Castro, 1954 &lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 66.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 97.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Von11|Von Tunzelmann 2011]] pp. 12–13.&lt;/ref&gt; }}

Imprisoned in the ''Presidio Modelo'' with 25 of his fellow conspirators, Castro devoted himself to politics once more, changing the name of &quot;The Movement&quot; to the &quot;[[26th of July Movement]]&quot;, in memory of the date of the failed Moncada attack. Forming a school for prisoners, the Abel Santamaría Ideological Academy, Castro organized five hours a day of teaching, with himself and other Movement members lecturing on such subjects as ancient and modern history, philosophy and the English language.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 94–95.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 61.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 93.&lt;/ref&gt; Making use of the prison library and gifts from friends outside of prison, he continued reading widely, enjoying the works of Marx, Lenin, and Martí but also reading books by [[Sigmund Freud]], [[Immanuel Kant]], [[William Shakespeare]], [[Axel Munthe]], [[Somerset Maugham]] and [[Fyodor Dostoyevsky]], analyzing most of them within a Marxist framework. He also began reading about the [[New Deal]] implemented by U.S. President [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]], believing that something similar should be enacted in Cuba.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 95–96.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 63&amp;ndash;65.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 93–94.&lt;/ref&gt; He corresponded with those outside of prison, trying to maintain control over his Movement without giving too much away to the prison censors, who read all of his letters, and also organized the publication of his ''History Will Absolve Me'' speech, with an initial print run of 27,500 copies.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 98–100.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 71.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 94–95.&lt;/ref&gt; Although at first having a fair amount of freedom within the prison, this came to an end after prison inmates embarrassed the guards by singing anti-Batista songs on a visit by the President in February 1954. In retaliation, the prison authorities removed most of the privileges that Castro and other prisoners were allowed, locking Castro up in [[solitary confinement]] indefinitely.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 97–98.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 67&amp;ndash;71.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 95–96.&lt;/ref&gt;

Meanwhile, Castro's wife Mirta, who did not share his obsession with political activism, had gained employment in the Ministry of the Interior, thereby working for Batista's government. She had been encouraged to do so by her brother, who had been a friend and ally of Batista for many years. This was kept a secret from Castro, who eventually found out through a radio announcement. Appalled, he raged that he would rather die &quot;a thousand times&quot; than &quot;suffer impotently from such an insult&quot;. Both Fidel and Mirta initiated divorce proceedings, with Mirta taking custody of their son Fidelito; this angered Castro, who did not want his son growing up in a bourgeois environment.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 102–103.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 76&amp;ndash;79.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 97–99.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1954, Batista's government went ahead with their earlier promises and held presidential elections, but no politician had risked standing against Batista lest they face violent reprisals. Batista won comfortably, but the election was widely recognized as fraudulent. It had however allowed some political opposition to be openly voiced, and supporters of Castro and his Movement had begun agitating for an amnesty for all those imprisoned over the Moncada incident. Some government politicians suggested that such an amnesty would provide good publicity, and the Congress and Batista eventually agreed. Backed by the U.S. government and major corporations, Batista believed that Castro would be no political threat to his regime, and on May 15, 1955 the prisoners were released.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 103–105.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 80&amp;ndash;82.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 99–100.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Got04|Gott 2004]]. p. 151.&lt;/ref&gt; Returning to Havana, Castro was met by his supporters, being carried along on the shoulders of students, and set about giving various radio interviews and press conferences; the government however kept him closely monitored, and curtailed his activities.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 105.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 83&amp;ndash;85.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. pp. 100&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 100.&lt;/ref&gt; Now divorced, Castro had sexual affairs with two of his female supporters, Naty Revuelta and Maria Laborde, who each conceived him a child.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 110.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. pp. 100&quot;/&gt; He also set about to strengthen his anti-Batista revolutionary Movement, welcoming members of the now defunct MNR into it, and establishing an eleven-person National Directorate of the 26th of July Revolutionary Movement (or MR-26-7). Despite these structural changes, there was still dissent within the group, with some members questioning Castro's autocratic leadership. Castro dismissed their proposals for the leadership to be transferred to a democratic board, arguing that a successful revolution could not be run by a committee. Some of them subsequently abandoned the MR-26-7, labeling Castro a ''[[caudillo]]'' (dictator), although the majority accepted his reasoning and remained loyal.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 106–107.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 100–101.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mexico and guerrilla training: 1955–1956===
[[File:Raulche2.jpg|right|thumb|250px|Fidel's brother Raúl Castro (left) and Argentine friend Che Guevara (right). As Castro would later relate: &quot;[Che] distinguished himself in so many ways, through so many fine qualities... As a man, as an extraordinary human being. He was also a person of great culture, a person of great intelligence. And with military qualities as well. Che was a doctor who became a soldier without ceasing for a single minute to be a doctor.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. p. 177.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
In 1955, a series of bomb attacks and violent demonstrations against Batista's administration led to a crackdown on dissent in Cuba, with Castro being placed under armed guard by his supporters as protection from possible assassination attempts. His brother Raúl was accused of one bomb attack and fled the county, with Fidel deciding to follow on July 7. Those members of the MR-26-7 that remained in Cuba were left with orders to prepare cells for revolutionary action in all of the country's main towns and cities, and await Castro's return, when he would bring with him an army to topple Batista.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 109 and 111.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 85.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 101.&lt;/ref&gt; He sent a letter to the country's political leaders and the press, declaring that he was &quot;leaving Cuba because all doors of peaceful struggle have been closed to me. Six weeks after being released from prison I am convinced more than ever of the dictatorship's intention, masked in many ways, to remain in power for twenty years, ruling as now by the use of terror and crime and ignoring the patience of the Cuban people, which has its limits. As a follower of Martí, I believe the hour has come to take our rights and not beg for them, to fight instead of pleading for them.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 111.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 86.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Castro brothers and a number of other MR-26-7 members traveled to Mexico, a country with a long history of offering asylum to left-wing exiles.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 112.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 88.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 102.&lt;/ref&gt; Raúl had befriended one such exile, an Argentine doctor and Marxist-Leninist named [[Che Guevara|Ernesto &quot;Che&quot; Guevara]] (1928&amp;ndash;1967), who was a proponent of [[guerrilla warfare]] and who was keen to join the Cuban Revolution as a part of his deeply held belief in overthrowing U.S. imperialism in Latin America. Upon meeting Guevara, Fidel took a liking to him, later describing him as being &quot;a more advanced revolutionary than I was.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 115–117.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 96&amp;ndash;98.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 102&amp;ndash;103.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. pp. 172-173.&lt;/ref&gt; Another socialist revolutionary whom Castro began associating with was the Cuban-born Spaniard Colonel [[Alberto Bayo]] (1892&amp;ndash;1967), who had fought for the leftist [[Second Spanish Republic|Republican side]] in the [[Spanish Civil War]] during the 1930s, before being exiled upon the victory of the fascist General [[Francisco Franco]] and his [[Falange]]. Bayo agreed to teach Fidel's rebels the skills in guerrilla warfare that they would need if they were to return to Cuba to battle Batista, clandestinely meeting them at various premises, including [[Chapultepec]] and a rural ranch.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 114.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 105&amp;ndash;106.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;coltman104&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 104&amp;ndash;105.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Got04|Gott 2004]]. p. 154.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. p. 174.&lt;/ref&gt;

In desperate need of money to finance his activities, Castro went on a tour of the United States in search of wealthy sympathizers, including the exiled former President Prío (who contributed the considerable sum of $100,000), during which time he was monitored by agents of Batista's government who at one point allegedly orchestrated a failed plot to kill him. These agents also bribed Mexican police to arrest Castro and other MR-26-7 members in the country, but ultimately the revolutionaries were all released, particularly as several members of the Mexican government sympathized with their cause.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 117&amp;ndash;118, 124.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 101&amp;ndash;102, 108&amp;ndash;114.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 105&amp;ndash;110.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Got04|Gott 2004]]. p. 153.&lt;/ref&gt; Castro had also kept in contact with the MR-26-7 agents who had remained in Cuba, where they had succeeded in getting a large clandestine support base in several towns in Oriente.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 121–124.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;coltman104&quot;/&gt; Other militant groups had also sprung up to oppose Batista within the country, primarily from the ranks of the student movement; most notable of these was the Revolutionary Directorate (DR), which had been founded by the Federation of University Students (FEU) President [[José Antonio Echevarría]] (1932&amp;ndash;1957). Antonio traveled to Mexico City to meet with Castro, but while they agreed to support one another, the two disagreed widely on tactics, with Castro opposing with the young student's policy of supporting indiscriminate assassinations of anyone in the government.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 122, 129&amp;ndash;130.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 102&amp;ndash;104, 114, 116.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 109.&lt;/ref&gt;

Purchasing a decrepit old yacht, the ''[[Granma (yacht)|Granma]]'', it was on the 25 November 1956 that Castro set sail from [[Tuxpan, Veracruz|Tuxpan]] in [[Veracruz]], Mexico with a group of 81 revolutionaries, armed with 90 rifles, 3 machine guns, around 40 pistols and 2 hand-held anti-tank guns.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 132&amp;ndash;133.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 115.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 110-112.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. p. 182.&lt;/ref&gt; The 1,200 mile crossing to Cuba was harsh, and in the overcrowded conditions of the ship (which was designed to hold around 20 passengers), many of the men suffered from [[seasickness]], and food supplies began to run low. At some points they had to bail water caused by a leak, and at another a man fell overboard, delaying their journey.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 134.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 113&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 113.&lt;/ref&gt; The plan had been for the journey to take five days, and on the ''Granma'''s scheduled day of arrival, 30 November, members of the MR-26-7 in Cuba under the leadership of [[Frank Pais]] led an armed uprising against government buildings in Santiago, Manzanillo and several other towns.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 134&amp;ndash;135.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 119&amp;ndash;1216.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 113&quot;/&gt; However, the crossing in the ''Granma'' ultimately lasted for seven days, and with Castro and his men unable to provide immediate back-up, Pais and those MR-26-7 members under his leadership dispersed to their homes after two days of intermittent attacks, having &quot;suffered very few casualties and arrests&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 113&quot;/&gt;

===Guerrilla war in the Sierra Maestra: 1956–1958===
[[File:Pico Torquino in the Sierra Maestra, Cuba's highest mountain, 1974 meters.jpg|thumb|left|250px|The thickly forested mountain range of the Sierra Maestra, from where Castro and his revolutionaries led guerrilla attacks against Batista's forces for two years. Castro biographer [[Robert E. Quirk]] noted that there was &quot;no better place to hide&quot; in all the island.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 126.&lt;/ref&gt;]]

The ''Granma'' landed in Cuba on 2 December 1956, crashing in a [[mangrove swamp]] at Playa Las Coloradas, close to [[Los Cayuelos]]. Batista's forces had been expecting them, and within several hours of their arrival they were bombarded from a naval vessel. Fleeing inland, they headed for the [[Sierra Maestra]] in Oriente, a large forested mountain range from where they could lead a guerrilla war against Batista.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 135.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 122&amp;ndash;125.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 114.&lt;/ref&gt; At daybreak on 5 December they were unexpectedly attacked by a detachment of Batista's Rural Guard; in the confusion, the rebels scattering into different groups which continued making their journey to the Sierra Maestra independently.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 136.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 114-115.&lt;/ref&gt; With only two comrades, Castro made it to the mountains, along the way meeting up with others who had survived the attack; ultimately it was discovered that of the 82 rebels who had arrived on the ''Granma'', only 19 had made it to the Sierra Maestra, the rest being killed or captured by Batista's forces.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 125&amp;ndash;126.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 114-117.&lt;/ref&gt;

Setting up an [[military camp|encampment]] in the thick jungle of the Sierra Maestra, the survivors, who included Fidel Castro, Che Guevara, Raúl Castro and [[Camilo Cienfuegos]],&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 137.&lt;/ref&gt; began launching attacks on small army posts in the region in order to steal weaponry. In January 1957 they attacked the outpost near to the beach at La Plata, defeating the soldiers stationed there. Being a doctor, Guevara treated the soldiers for any injuries, but the revolutionaries executed the local ''mayoral'' (land company overseer) Chicho Osorio, who was despised by the local peasants and who had boasted of killing one of the MR-26-7 rebels several weeks previously.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 116-117.&lt;/ref&gt; The execution of Osorio aided the rebels in gaining the trust of local people, who typically hated the ''mayorals'' as enforcers of the much-despised wealthy landowners. Nonetheless, the locals were initially unenthusiastic in their support for the guerrillas, viewing them with suspicion as outsiders.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 139.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 127.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 118-119.&lt;/ref&gt; As trust grew between the two communities, some locals joined the rebels, although the majority of new recruits came from urban areas, traveling to the Sierra Maestra in order to aid the revolutionary effort.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 144.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 129.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 119&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 119.&lt;/ref&gt; With rising levels of support and increasing number of volunteers joining the rebel army, which now numbered over 200, in July 1957 Castro eventually divided his men into three columns, keeping charge of one and giving control of the others to his brother and Che Guevara.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 122&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 122.&lt;/ref&gt; The MR-26-7 members operating in urban areas continued agitating against the government, sending supplies to the Sierra Maestra rebels and on 16 February 1957 Castro met with other leading members of the group to discuss tactics; it was here that he met [[Celia Sánchez]], who would become a close friend.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 138.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 130.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 119&quot;/&gt;

{{Quote box|width=25em|bgcolor=#ACE1AF|align=right|quote=&quot;The story of our beards is very simple: it arose out of the difficult conditions we were living and fighting under as guerrillas. We didn't have any razor blades... everybody just let their beards and hair grow, and that turned into a kind of badge of identity. For the ''campesinos'' and everybody else, for the press, for the reporters we were &quot;''los barbudos''&quot; - the bearded ones. It had its positive side: in order for a spy to infiltrate us, he had to start preparing months ahead of time - he'd have had to have six-months' growth of beard, you see... Later, with the triumph of the Revolution, we kept our beards to preserve the symbolism.&quot;|source=— Fidel Castro on his iconic beard, 2009 &lt;ref&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. p. 195.&lt;/ref&gt; }}

The Cuban Revolution was not contained to the MR-26-7, and across Cuba militant groups were beginning to rise up against Batista. Most notably, Antonio and his DR had been carrying out bombings and acts of sabotage, leading the police to respond with mass arrests, the torture of suspects and extra-judicial killings; the corpses were often hung on trees to intimidate those with revolutionary sympathies. In March 1957 the DR launched an attack on the presidential palace, with Batista himself narrowly surviving. The rebels were eventually defeated, and Antonio was shot dead by police in the street as he attempted to issue a radio broadcast. His death would prove beneficial for Castro, removing a charismatic rival to his leadership of the anti-Batista movement.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 142-143.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 128, 134&amp;ndash;136.&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 121-122.&lt;/ref&gt; Another prominent revolutionary leader, Frank Pais, was also killed by the army, leaving Castro as the unchallenged leader of the MR-26-7.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 145, 148.&lt;/ref&gt; According to his later claims, Castro kept his Marxist-Leninist beliefs a secret from many of the MR-26-7, something in contrast to Guevara and Raúl, whose beliefs were well known. In this way he hoped to gain a wider support base amongst those of other political persuasions, and in 1957 he met with leading members of the ''Partido Ortodoxo''. Castro and the ''Ortodoxo'' leaders [[Raúl Chibás]] and [[Felipe Pazos]] drafted and signed a document called the Sierra Maestra Manifesto in which they laid out their plans for a post-Batista Cuba. Rejecting the idea that Cuba should be run by a provisional military junta following Batista's demise, it demanded that a provisional civilian government be set up that was &quot;supported by all&quot; and which would implement moderate agrarian reform, industrialization and a campaign to wipe out illiteracy before introducing &quot;truly fair, democratic, impartial, elections&quot;. It also insisted on both [[press freedom]] and free elections within Cuba's trade unions.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 148&amp;ndash;150.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 141&amp;ndash;143.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 122-123.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The text of the Sierra Maestra Manifesto can be found online at {{cite web|url=http://www.chibas.org/raul_chibas_manifiesto.php |title=Raul Antonio Chibás: Manifiesto Sierra Maestra |publisher=Chibas.org |accessdate=09 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Batista's government censored the Cuban media, and so Castro felt it would be beneficial to reach out and contact foreign media sources in order to spread his message. A U.S. journalist from the ''[[The New York Times]]'' named [[Herbert Matthews]] came to interview Castro, attracting international interest to the rebel's cause and turning him into a [[celebrity]]. ''The New York Times'' front page story presented Castro as a romantic and appealing revolutionary, and exaggerated the number of troops and resources that he had at his command, with Matthews declaring that &quot;Batista cannot possibly hope to suppress the Castro revolt&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 140-142.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 131&amp;ndash;134.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 120.&lt;/ref&gt; Soon, other reporters followed in Matthews' footsteps by traveling to the Sierra Maestra to interview Castro, sent by such news agencies as [[CBS]],&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 143.&lt;/ref&gt; while a reporter from ''[[Paris Match]]'' stayed with the rebels for around 4 months, documenting their daily routine.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 159.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 127&amp;ndash;128.&lt;/ref&gt; The number of attacks that Castro's guerrilla's undertook against military outposts in and around the mountains increased, forcing the government to withdraw from all its posts in the region.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986. p. 155&quot;&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 155.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 122&quot;/&gt; By the spring of 1958 the rebels controlled all of the mountainous areas in Oriente province, controlling a hospital, schools, a printing press, slaughterhouse, land-mine factory and a cigar-making factory.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 129.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Countering Operation Verano: 1958 ===

President Batista was coming under increasing pressure by 1958. His army's military failures in Oriente, coupled with his censorship of the media and the repressive techniques of torture and extra-judicial killings employed by the police and armed forces were being increasingly criticized both at home and abroad. Influenced by a wave of anti-Batista sentiment amongst their citizens, the U.S. government made the decision to stop supplying him with weaponry, which he had been using against the rebels, leading him to instead begin buying arms from the United Kingdom.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 129-130, 134.&lt;/ref&gt; The opposition used this as an opportunity to rise up across the country, proposing a [[general strike]] which would be accompanied by armed attacks from the MR-26-7. The strike began on 9 April, and while receiving strong support in the center and east of Cuba, in Havana and other urbanized western parts of the country most workers continued working as usual.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 152&amp;ndash;154.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 130-131.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote box|width=25em|bgcolor=#ACE1AF|align=left|quote=&quot;When I saw the [U.S. supplied] rockets being fired at Mario's house, I swore to myself that the Americans would pay dearly for what they are doing. When this war is over a much wider and bigger war will begin for me: the war that I am going to wage against them. I know that this is my real destiny.&quot;|source=— Fidel Castro in a letter to [[Celia Sánchez]], 1958 &lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986. p. 155&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 133.&lt;/ref&gt; }}

Batista's response was to launch an all-out-attack on Castro's guerrilla forces, known as ''[[Operation Verano]]''. The army began aerial bombardment of forested areas and villages that were suspected of aiding and hiding the militants, whilst 10,000 soldiers under the command of General [[Eulogio Cantillo]] surrounded the Sierra Maestra, driving north to the areas where the rebels were camped. Despite their massive superiority of numbers and weaponry, the army were at a disadvantage, having no experience with guerrilla warfare or the mountainous region. Castro, who by this time had around 300 men at his command, avoided open confrontation, instead using land mines and ambushes to halt the enemy offensive.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 181&amp;ndash;183.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 131-133.&lt;/ref&gt;  The army suffered heavy losses and a number of embarrassments; in June 1958 a battalion was trapped in a valley by the rebels and forced to surrender. Their weapons were confiscated, and they were handed over to the [[Red Cross]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 189&amp;ndash;191.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 132.&lt;/ref&gt; Many of Batista's soldiers, appalled at the human rights abuses that they were being ordered to carry out, defected to Castro's rebel force, who also benefited from &quot;overwhelming&quot; popular support in those areas that they captured.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986. p. 158&quot;&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 158.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the summer, the MR-26-7 went on the offensive, pushing the government forces back, out of the mountain range and into the lowlands, with Castro using his columns in a pincer movement to surround the main army concentration in Santiago. By November, Castro's forces had most of Oriente and Las Villas under his control, and although the capitals of Santiago and Santa Clara remained in government hands, their grip on them was slipping. Through control of Las Villas, the rebels had been able to divide the country in two by closing the major roads and rail lines, severely disadvantaging Batista's forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986. p. 158&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 194&amp;ndash;196.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 135.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Batista's fall and Cantillo's military junta: 1958–1959 ===
[[File:Luis Korda 02.jpg|thumb|Castro (right) with fellow revolutionary [[Camilo Cienfuegos]] entering Havana on January 8, 1959. Castro would later describe Cienfuegos as having &quot;distinguished himself&quot; amongst his men, relating that &quot;He wasn't as intellectual as Che, but he was very, very brave, an eminent leader, very daring, very humane.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. p. 192.&lt;/ref&gt;]]

The U.S. government had come to realize that Batista would probably lose the war, and fearing that Castro, under the influence of known Marxist-Leninists like Che Guevara, would displace U.S. interests with socialist reforms, they decided to support Batista's removal in support of a military junta led by centrist or right wing officers, believing that General Cantillo, who then commanded most of the country's armed forces, would be best placed to lead it. After being approached with this proposal, Cantillo decided to secretly meet with Castro to see if they could bring an end to the fighting, and ultimately it was agreed that the two would call a ceasefire, following which Batista would be apprehended and tried as a [[war criminal]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986 158-159&quot;&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 158&amp;ndash;159.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 196, 202&amp;ndash;207.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 136&amp;ndash;137.&lt;/ref&gt; Double crossing Castro, Cantillo warned Batista of the revolutionary's intentions. Wishing to avoid a war crimes tribunal, Batista resigned on 31 December 1958, informing the armed forces that they were now under Cantillo's control. With his family and closest advisers, Batista then fled into exile, taking with him an amassed fortune of more than US$ 300,000,000.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986 158-159&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. pp. 203, 207&amp;ndash;208.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 137&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 137.&lt;/ref&gt; The following morning Cantillo entered the [[Museum of the Revolution (Cuba)|Presidential Palace]] in Havana, proclaimed the [[Supreme Court of Cuba|Supreme Court]] judge [[Carlos Piedra]] to be the new President, and began appointing new members of the government.&lt;ref name=&quot;Quirk 1993. p. 212&quot;&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 212.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 137&quot;/&gt;

Still in Oriente, Castro was furious at Cantillo's actions, recognizing it as the establishment of a military junta. He told his troops to end the ceasefire and continue on the offensive against government forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986 160&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 211.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 137&quot;/&gt; The MR-26-7 put together a plan to oust the Cantillo-Piedra junta, freeing the high-ranking military officer Colonel Ramón Barquín from the Isle of Pines prison (where he had been held captive for plotting to overthrow Batista), and commanding him to fly to Havana to place Cantillo under house arrest where he would await trial.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986 160&quot;&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 160.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Quirk 1993. p. 212&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 137&quot;/&gt; While there was widespread celebrations as news of Batista's downfall spread across Cuba on 1 January 1959, Castro gave an order to MR-26-7 members to take on the responsibility of policing the country, in order to prevent the widespread looting and vandalism that he had witnessed in the Bogotazo.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 161&amp;ndash;162.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 211.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 137-138.&lt;/ref&gt;

Whilst Cienfuegos and Guevara led their columns of soldiers into Havana onto 2 January, Castro entered Santiago, where he accepted the surrender of the Moncada Barracks, before giving a speech to the assembled crowds in which he invoked the 19th century wars of independence against the Spanish Empire. He proceeded to speak out against the Cantillo-Piedra junta but highlighted that the majority of soldiers in the armed forces were honorable, and that only the few who had committed human rights abuses would be brought to justice. He also praised the role that women had played in the MR-26-7, and proclaimed that they would have equal rights in the new Cuba.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 214.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 138-139.&lt;/ref&gt; Along the way he also met with the mother of the dead revolutionary, José Antonio Echevarría.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 163.&lt;/ref&gt; Castro immediately became a heroic figure to the Cuban people, striking a &quot;Christ-like figure&quot; and wearing a medallion of the [[Virgin Mary]], with cheering crowds meeting him at every town on his way to Havana. Along the way he gave speeches, press conferences and interviews, with U.S. and other foreign reporters noting that the public adulation of Castro was on an unprecedented scale.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 162.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 219.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 140-141.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Provisional government: 1959===

In the Sierra Maestra, Castro had made his opinion clear that the lawyer [[Manuel Urrutia Lleó]] (1901–1981) should become the new Cuban president and leader of a provisional civilian government following Batista's fall. A political moderate, Urrutia had defended several MR-26-7 revolutionaries in court during the Batista administration, and had argued that the attack on the Moncada Barracks was legal according to the Cuban constitution. For this reason Castro believed that Urrutia would make a good leader, being both established yet sympathetic to the revolutionary cause. Following the house arrest of Cantillo and the ensuing collapse of the junta, Urrutia was proclaimed to be Cuba's provisional president, with Castro erroneously announcing that he had been selected for the position by &quot;popular election&quot;. Most of Urrutia's cabinet consisted of MR-26-7 members.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 153, 161.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 216.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 126, 141&amp;ndash;142.&lt;/ref&gt; On January 8, 1959, Castro's army rolled victoriously into Havana, and he would shortly thereafter declare that &quot;power does not interest me, and I will not take it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/printout/0,8816,937070,00.html Cuba: End of a War], ''[[TIME Magazine]]'', January 12, 1959.&lt;/ref&gt; Proclaiming himself to be the Representative of the Rebel Armed Forces of the Presidency,&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986 164&quot;/&gt; Castro, along with a number of close aides and family members, set up both home and office in the penthouse of the [[Hotel Tryp Habana Libre|Havana Hilton Hotel]], there meeting with journalists, foreign visitors and government ministers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986 164&quot;&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 164.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 144.&lt;/ref&gt; 

While he officially had no role within the provisional civilian government, in reality Castro exercised a great deal of influence, largely because of his overwhelming popularity with the Cuban populace and his control of the rebel armed forces. He ensured that the government implemented a number of policies designed to cut corruption and fight illiteracy, but did not initially force through any radical proposals. Attempting to rid Cuba's government of Batistanos and their corruption, the Congress that had been elected under Batista was abolished, and all those elected in the rigged elections of 1954 and 1958 were banned from political life. With the government now [[rule by decree|ruling by decree]], Castro pushed the president to issue a temporary ban on all political parties, but repeatedly claimed that the government would get around to organizing multiparty elections, which ultimately it never did.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 171&amp;ndash;172.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 217.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 150&amp;ndash;154.&lt;/ref&gt; He began secretly meeting with leading members of the banned communist [[Popular Socialist Party (Cuba)|Popular Socialist Party]], believing that they had the intellectual capacity to form a socialist government where the MR-26-7 did not.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 166.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 145.&lt;/ref&gt; He nonetheless kept his true political persuasions a secret from the public eye, and repeatedly denied being a communist.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 170.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote box|width=25em|bgcolor=#ACE1AF|align=left|quote=&quot;We are not executing innocent people or political opponents. We are executing murderers and they deserve it.&quot;|source=— Castro's response to his critics regarding the mass executions, 1959 &lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 168.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 149.&lt;/ref&gt; }}
In trying to suppress the revolution, Batista's government had orchestrated mass human rights abuses, with academic estimates for the death toll ranging between 1,000 and 20,000.&lt;ref&gt;Exploring revolution by Timothy P. Wickham-Crowley, page 63&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gurr, Ted Robert. &quot;Political protest and rebellion in the 1960s: the United States in World Perspective.&quot; In VIOLENCE IN AMERICA: HISTORICAL &amp; COMPARATIVE PERSPECTIVES page 47&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Conflict, Order, and Peace in the Americas'', by the Lyndon B. Johnson School of Public Affairs, 1978, pg 121 ~ &quot;The US-supported Batista regime killed 20,000 Cubans&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Now, popular uproar across Cuba demanded that those figures who had been complicit in the widespread torture and killing of civilians be brought to justice. Although he remained a moderating force and tried to prevent the mass reprisal killings of Batistanos advocated by many Cubans, Castro helped to set-up trials of many figures involved in the old regime across the country, resulting in hundreds of executions. Critics, in particular from the U.S. press, argued that many of these did not meet the standards of a [[fair trial]], and condemned Cuba's new government as being more interested in vengeance than justice. Castro retaliated strongly against such accusations, proclaiming that &quot;revolutionary justice is not based on legal precepts, but on moral conviction&quot;. In a show of support for this &quot;revolutionary justice&quot;, he organized the first Havana trial to take place before a mass audience of 17,000 at the [[Estadio Latinoamericano|Sports Palace stadium]]; when a group of aviators accused of bombing a village were found not guilty, he ordered a retrial in which they were instead found guilty and sentenced to life imprisonment.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 163, 167&amp;ndash;169.&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 147&amp;ndash;149.&lt;/ref&gt;

Widely acclaimed as a hero by many across Latin America, he soon traveled to [[Venezuela]] to attend the first anniversary celebrations of the overthrow of the former right wing president, [[Marcos Pérez Jiménez]]. Meeting President-elect [[Rómulo Betancourt]], Castro proposed greater relations between the two nations, unsuccessfully requesting a loan of $300,000,000 and a new deal to obtain Venezuelan oil.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 169&amp;ndash;170.&lt;/ref&gt; Returning home, an argument between Castro and senior government figures broke out when the government banned the National Lottery and closed down the casinos and brothels that had flourished under Batista's regime. While agreeing that gambling and prostitution should be eradicated, Castro was furious with the manner in which this law had been passed, leaving thousands of Cuban waiters, croupiers and prostitutes unemployed, usually with no other skills to fall back on. As a result of the argument, Prime Minister [[José Miró Cardona]] resigned, going into exile in the U.S. and eventually involving himself in the militant anti-Castro movement.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 173.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 154.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Premiership==

===Consolidating leadership: 1959===
{{double image|right|Fidel Castro - MATS Terminal Washington 1959.jpg|200|Fidel Castro at the Lincoln Memorial.jpg|150|Castro in Washington, D.C., arriving at the MATS Terminal (left) and visiting the [[Lincoln Memorial]] (right).}}
On February 16, 1959, Castro took the vacancy left by Miró, being sworn in as [[Prime Minister of Cuba]]. Initially proclaiming his reluctance in taking the role, he agreed to accept it on the condition that the Prime Minister's powers be increased, in part to the detriment of the President.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 173.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Castro sworn in as Cuban PM&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/february/16/newsid_2544000/2544431.stm | title=1959: Castro sworn in as Cuban PM |publisher=BBC News | accessdate=June 6, 2006 |date=February 16, 1959}}&lt;/ref&gt; One of his first acts as Prime Minister was to travel to the United States between 15 and 26 April, accompanied by a delegation of industrial and diplomatic representatives. Castro hired one of the country's best [[public relations]] firms for a [[charm offensive]], appearing as a &quot;man of the people&quot; by answering impertinent questions jokingly and eating hot dogs and hamburgers. The U.S. President, [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]] of the [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party]], avoided meeting with Castro, who instead met with Vice President [[Richard Nixon]], a man Castro took an instant dislike to.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 174&amp;ndash;177.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 155&amp;ndash;157.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last = Franqui|first = Carlos|url = http://www.historyofcuba.com/history/franqui3.htm|title = Fidel Castro's Trip to the United States|publisher=historyofCuba.com|accessdate =May 16, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rather than returning straight to Cuba, Castro traveled to Canada, Trinidad, Brazil, Uruguay and Argentina, attending an economic conference in [[Buenos Aires]], where he unsuccessfully proposed that the U.S. fund a &quot;[[Marshall Plan]]&quot; for Latin America.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 177.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 158.&lt;/ref&gt;

Castro took a great interest in rural life, and appointed himself to the presidency of the newly created [[National Institute of Agrarian Reform]] (INRA). On 17 May 1959, Castro signed into law the [[Agrarian Reform Laws of Cuba|First Agrarian Reform]], which limited landholdings to {{convert|993|acre|km2}} per owner and forbade further foreign land ownership. As a result, all of the large land-holdings were broken up, and the land redistributed to the peasants who worked it; an estimated 200,000 peasants received title deeds as a result of its implementation. To Castro, this was an important progressive step, breaking the control of the wealthy landowning class over Cuba's agriculture; it proved popular among the working class, but also alienated many in the middle classes who had previously supported Castro.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 177&amp;ndash;178.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 159&amp;ndash;160.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://revolutions.truman.edu/cuba/aboutme.htm|title=First Agrarian Reform Law (1959)|accessdate=August 29, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; In March 1959, Castro ordered that rents for those who paid less than $100 a month should be cut in half, with measures implemented to increase the Cuban people's purchasing powers, although productivity decreased and the country's financial reserves were drained within two years.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 186.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although at the time he refused to categorize his regime as socialist, Castro appointed known Marxists to senior positions throughout Cuban society. He controversially appointed Che Guevara, an Argentinian with no training in economics, to the position of Governor of the Central Bank and then Minister of Industries, while Marxists took control of most of the country's trade unions. Castro appointed Marxists to senior positions in the armed forces, leading to a backlash from various high-ranking anti-communist officers; the commander of the Air Force, Díaz Lanz, soon defected to the United States, calling for the U.S. government to do something before a Marxist regime took over in Cuba.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 176&amp;ndash;177.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 161&amp;ndash;166.&lt;/ref&gt; These defections were denounced by President Manuel Urrutia Lleó, but he too publicly expressed concern with the rising influence of Marxism. This angered Castro, who publicly announced that he was resigning from his position as Prime Minister because Urrutia &quot;complicated&quot; government, arguing that the president's &quot;fevered anti-Communism&quot; was having a detrimental effect. Castro's sentiments received widespread support as organized crowds of over half a million Castro-supporters surrounded the Presidential Palace demanding Urrutia's resignation, which was duly received. On July 23, Castro resumed his position as Prime Minister and appointed the Marxist [[Osvaldo Dorticós Torrado|Osvaldo Dorticós]] to be the new President.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 181&amp;ndash;183.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 162.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote box|width=25em|align=left|bgcolor=#ACE1AF|quote=&quot;Until Castro, the U.S. was so overwhelmingly influential in Cuba that the American ambassador was the second most important man, sometimes even more important than the Cuban president.&quot;|source=— [[Earl T. Smith]], former American Ambassador to Cuba, during 1960 testimony to the U.S. Senate &lt;ref&gt;''Ernesto &quot;Che&quot; Guevara (World Leaders Past &amp; Present)'', by Douglas Kellner, 1989, Chelsea House Publishers, ISBN 1-55546-835-7, pg 66&lt;/ref&gt; }}

Castro made use of radio and the newly developed technology of television to communicate with the Cuban populace, developing what he called a &quot;dialogue with the people&quot;, during which he would pose questions and make intentionally provocative statements.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 179.&lt;/ref&gt; Such tactics proved successful, and Castro's regime remained highly popular with workers, peasants and students, all of whom had benefited from its policies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 168&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 168.&lt;/ref&gt; Nonetheless, opposition continued to grow, particularly within the Cuban middle classes, with thousands of educated doctors, engineers and other professionals emigrating to [[Florida]] in the U.S., causing a [[brain drain]] on the island's economy.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 195&amp;ndash;197.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 167&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 167.&lt;/ref&gt; Militant anti-Castro groups sprung up, undertaking armed attacks against government forces, with some setting up guerrilla bases in Cuba's mountainous regions, leading to the six-year [[War against the Bandits]]. They were funded and armed by various foreign sources, including the exiled Cuban community, the U.S. [[Central Intelligence Agency]] (CIA), and the Dominican government of General [[Rafael Trujillo]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 167&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Ros&quot;&gt;[[#Ros06|Ros 2006]]. pp. 159&amp;ndash;201.&lt;/ref&gt; Castro's government began a crackdown on this opposition movement, labeling it [[counter-revolution]]ary, and arresting hundreds of dissidents.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986. p. 197&quot;&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 197.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 168&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 181.&lt;/ref&gt; Although it rejected the methods of physical torture which had been employed by Batista's regime, Castro's government sanctioned the use of psychological torture, subjecting some prisoners to solitary confinement, rough treatment, hunger and threatening behavior.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 176&amp;ndash;177.&lt;/ref&gt; After conservative editors and journalists began expressing hostility towards the government following its leftward turn, the pro-Castro printers' trade union began to harass and disrupt editorial staff. In January 1960 the government proclaimed that each newspaper would be obliged to publish a &quot;clarification&quot; written by the printers' union to the end of any articles which were critical of the government. This would prove to be the start of press censorship in Castro's Cuba.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986. p. 197&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 165&amp;ndash;166.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Soviet support and U.S. opposition: 1960===
[[File:CheLaCoubreMarch.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Castro (far left), [[Che Guevara]] (center), and other leading revolutionaries, marching through the streets in protest of the [[La Coubre explosion]], 5 March 1960.]]

At the start of the 1960s, the [[Cold War]] was raging between the Earth's two great superpowers, the United States, a [[liberal democracy]] with a [[capitalism|capitalist]] economy, and the Soviet Union (USSR), a Marxist-Leninist one-party state with a socialist economy. Castro had long expressed contempt for the U.S. government and their support of Batista's regime, as well as their imperialist and exploitative attitude towards Cuba, while he shared the ideological views of the Soviet government. Wanting to open a relationship with the Soviets, Castro met with a Soviet [[KGB]] agent operating in Havana, and discussed the possibility of initiating a trading relationship with the Soviet Union. Meeting with Soviet [[First Deputy Premier of the Soviet Union|First Deputy Premier]] [[Anastas Mikoyan]], Castro agreed to provide the USSR with sugar in return for crude oil, fertilizers and industrial goods.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 189&amp;ndash;190, 198&amp;ndash;199.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 170&amp;ndash;172.&lt;/ref&gt; Relations were also established with other Marxist-Leninist governments, such as the [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia]], the [[People's Republic of Poland]] and the [[People's Republic of China]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986. p. 202&quot;&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 202.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Cuban government ordered the country's refineries &amp;ndash; then controlled by the U.S. corporations [[Shell Oil Company|Shell]], [[Esso]] and [[Standard Oil]] &amp;ndash; to process this Soviet oil, but under pressure from the U.S. government, these companies refused. Castro responded by expropriating the refineries and [[nationalization|nationalizing]] them under state control. In retaliation, the U.S. cancelled its import of Cuban sugar, provoking Castro to nationalize most U.S.-owned assets on the island, including banks and sugar mills.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 205&amp;ndash;206.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 173.&lt;/ref&gt; Relations between Cuba and the U.S. were further strained following the explosion and sinking of a French vessel, the ''[[Le Coubre]]'', in Havana harbor in March 1960. Carrying weapons purchased from Belgium, the cause of the explosion was never determined, but Castro publicly accused the U.S. government of sabotage.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 201&amp;ndash;202.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 172.&lt;/ref&gt; Inspired by their earlier success in orchestrating the [[1954 Guatemalan coup d'état]], on 17 March 1960, U.S. President Eisenhower secretly authorized the [[Central Intelligence Agency]] (CIA) to covertly overthrow Castro's government, providing them with a budget of $13 million in order to do so. He permitted them to ally with the [[Mafia]] criminal organization, knowing that they were aggrieved after Castro's government closed down their casinos and other businesses in Cuba.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986. p. 202, 211-213&quot;&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 202, 211&amp;ndash;213.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 172&amp;ndash;173.&lt;/ref&gt; On 13 October 1960, the U.S. government then prohibited the majority of exports to Cuba &amp;ndash; the exceptions being medicines and certain foodstuffs &amp;ndash; marking the start of [[United States embargo against Cuba|an economic embargo]]. In retaliation, the Cuban National Institute for Agrarian Reform took control of 383 private-run businesses on 14 October, and on 25 October a further 166 U.S. companies operating in Cuba had their premises seized and nationalized, including [[Coca-Cola]] and [[Sears Roebuck]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986. p. 214&quot;&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 214.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 177.&lt;/ref&gt; On 16 December, the U.S. then ended its import quota of Cuban sugar, the country's primary export.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986. p. 215&quot;&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 215.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Fidel Castro - UN General Assembly 1960.jpg|thumb|left|150px|Castro at the United Nations General Assembly in 1960.]]

In September 1960, Castro flew to New York City for the [[General Assembly of the United Nations]]. Taking offense at the attitude of the elite Shelburne Hotel, he and his entourage instead stayed at the cheap, run-down [[Hotel Theresa]] in the impoverished area of [[Harlem]]. Here, he met with a number of journalists as well as anti-establishment figures like the African-American leader [[Malcolm X]]. At the hotel he was also visited by the Soviet Premier, [[Nikita Khruschev]], and the two leaders used the occasion as a press opportunity to highlight the poverty faced by many U.S. citizens in areas like Harlem; Castro would later describe New York as a &quot;city of persecution&quot; in reference to the treatment of working class and African-Americans by the establishment. Relations between Castro and Khrushchev were warm, with the two leading the applause to one another's speeches at the General Assembly. Although Castro still publicly denied being a Marxist or even a socialist, Khrushchev would privately inform his entourage that the Cuban would become &quot;a beacon of Socialism in Latin America.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 206&amp;ndash;209.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 174&amp;ndash;176.&lt;/ref&gt; During the trip, Castro was also visited by two other senior world leaders, Egyptian President [[Gamal Abdel Nasser]] and Indian Prime Minister [[Jawaharlal Nehru]], both of whom were also socialists.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 209&amp;ndash;210.&lt;/ref&gt;

Returning to Cuba on 28 September, Castro feared that the U.S. would attempt to overthrow his government, and so purchased tanks and other weaponry from the Soviet Union.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 176&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 176.&lt;/ref&gt; Fearing that many in the armed forces might prove a threat to the new administration, he created a People's Militia through which to arm citizens favourable to his revolutionary cause.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 215.&lt;/ref&gt; In September 1960, he created the [[Committees for the Defense of the Revolution]], a nationwide organization of civilian groups who implemented neighborhood spying in an effort to weed out &quot;counter-revolutionary&quot; activities and who could back up the regular army in the case of invasion. Eventually, 80% of the Cuban population would be involved in these Committees.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986. p. 233&quot;&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 233.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 176&quot;/&gt; Castro's government also placed a great emphasis on social projects to improve the standard of living in Cuba, often to the detriment of economic development. A major emphasis was placed on education, and under the first 30 months of Castro's government, more classrooms were opened than in the previous 30 years of government. The Cuban primary education system offered a work-study program, with half of the time being spent in the classroom, and the other half taking part in a productive activity. Health care was also nationalized and expanded, with rural health centers and urban polyclinics opening up across the island, offering free medical aid. Universal vaccination against childhood diseases was implemented, and infant mortality rates were reduced dramatically. A third aspect of the social programs was the construction of infrastucture; within the first 6 months of Castro's government, 600 miles of road had been built across the island, while $300 million was spent on water and sanitation schemes. Over 800 houses were constructed every month in the early years of the administration in a measure to cut homelessness, while nurseries and day-care centres were opened for children and other centres opened for the disabled and the elderly.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 275&amp;ndash;276.&lt;/ref&gt;

===The Bay of Pigs Invasion: 1961===
[[File:CheyFidel.jpg|thumb|170px|right|[[Che Guevara]] (left) and Castro, photographed by Alberto Korda in 1961.]]
By January 1961, the U.S. Embassy in Havana had 300 staff, of whom 80% were believed by Castro to be spies. He ordered the Embassy to reduce its size to match that of the Cuban Embassy in Washington D.C. The U.S. response was to cut off all diplomatic relations with Cuba, with the CIA increasing its support for militant dissidents in exile. Such dissident groups began attacking ships trading with Cuba, and organized raiding parties to destroy Cuban factories and sugar mills in an attempt to disrupt the island's economy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986. pp. 215-216&quot;&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 215&amp;ndash;216.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 178.&lt;/ref&gt; Under the Eisenhower administration, the CIA had organized a plan to invade Cuba using exiled Cuban dissidents &amp;ndash; unified as the &quot;Democratic Revolutionary Front&quot; &amp;ndash; as soldiers, thereby avoiding an international condemnation that would have arisen if they used U.S. troops. Following the election of Democratic Party nominee [[John F. Kennedy]] as U.S. President in 1961, the CIA gained his support for continuing with the plan, which would result in the [[Bay of Pigs Invasion]] of April 1961. Brigade 2506, made up of around 1,400 Cuban dissidents, divided into five infantry and one paratrooper battalions, had assembled in [[Guatemala]], a U.S. ally, before being transported to another pro-U.S. state, [[Nicaragua]], from which they set off aboard seven ships toward Cuba on 13 April. On 15 April, eight CIA-supplied [[Douglas A-26 Invader|B-26]] bombers took off from Nicaragua and bombed three Cuban military airfields, damaging runways and fighter planes, as well as killing 7 and injuring 52. The U.S. government immediately proclaimed that the bombers had belonged to Cuba's air force and had been commandeered by dissidents who wanted to defect to the U.S.; in retaliation, Castro publicly went on state television to denounce their claims, providing evidence to expose their misinformation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986. p. 217-220&quot;&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 217&amp;ndash;220.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 178&amp;ndash;179.&lt;/ref&gt;

Castro feared that the bombing was a prelude to an invasion, putting the armed forces on maximum alert and ordering the arrest of anyone suspected of having counter-revolutionary sympathies. This constituted at least 20,000 people, who were detained in prisons, theaters and sport centres.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986. p. 221-222&quot;/&gt; At the funerals of the dead airmen on 16 April, he publicly proclaimed that &quot;What the imperialists cannot forgive us, is that we have made a Socialist revolution under their noses.&quot; This was his first ever declaration that the Cuban revolutionary movement was socialist in character, and he proceeded to declare that his movement was &quot;a revolution of the humble, with the humble, for the humble, democratic and Socialist.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986. p. 221-222&quot;&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 221&amp;ndash;222.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 180 and 186.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote box|width=25em|align=left|bgcolor=#ACE1AF|quote=&quot;There was... no doubts about who the victors were. Cuba's stature in the world soared to new heights, and Fidel's role as the adored and revered leader among ordinary Cuban people received a renewed boost. His popularity was greater than ever. In his own mind he had done what generations of Cubans had only fantacized about: he had taken on the United States and won.&quot;|source=— [[Peter Bourne]], Castro biographer, 1986 &lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 226.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

At night, the invasion fleet landed in Cuba largely undetected along the narrow inlet known as the [[Bay of Pigs]]. A local revolutionary militia opened fire on the invaders, but was forced back by heavy fire from the landing craft. Castro had not expected this to be their landing site, and as a result it was a poorly defended stretch of coast. He ordered Captain José Ramón Fernández to launch an immediate counter-offensive, and ordered the country's small air force to destroy the Brigade 2506's ships which contained weapons, food and medical supplies for the dissidents. Eventually taking direct command of the operation, Castro oversaw the counter-offensive, bringing in reinforcements and tanks to use against the rebel army. President Kennedy was unwilling to directly intervene with U.S. military support, and so on 20 April, 1189 men of the Brigade 2506 surrendered to the Cuban army.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986. p. 222-225&quot;&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 222&amp;ndash;225.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceC&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 180&amp;ndash;184.&lt;/ref&gt;

Celebrating his victory, Castro ordered that the rebels be interrogated on live television by a panel of journalists. He himself took over the questioning on 25 April, walking in among them with a microphone and asking them why they had taken part in the invasion. 14 of them were then put on trial for crimes that they allegedly committed before the revolution, while all of the others were returned to the U.S. in exchange for medicine and food valued at around U.S. $25 million.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986. p. 226-227&quot;&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 226&amp;ndash;227.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceC&quot;/&gt; Castro's victory was a powerful symbol for his supporters, both at home and across Latin America, but also served to increase some internal opposition, particularly among the thousands of primarily middle-class Cubans who had been detained in the run-up to the invasion. Although most were freed within a few days, many decided to flee Castro's Cuba for Florida.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 185&amp;ndash;186.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Embracing socialism: 1961&amp;ndash;1962===
With Castro having officially announced the creation of &quot;Socialist Cuba&quot;, he founded a new governing party, the [[Communist Party of Cuba|Integrated Revolutionary Organizations]] (''Organizaciones Revolucionarias Integradas'' - ORI), under which he united the MR-26-7, the Popular Socialist Party and the Revolutionary Directorate.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 230&quot;&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 230.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 188&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 188.&lt;/ref&gt; The Soviet government were hesitant over Cuba's open embrace of socialism, fearing U.S. retaliation, but relations between the two nations deepened, with Castro sending his son Fidelito to be schooled in [[Moscow]]. In turn, the first Soviet technicians arrived on the island on 7 June.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 231&quot;&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 231.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 188&quot;/&gt; In December 1961, Castro officially proclaimed himself to be a [[Marxism-Leninism|Marxist-Leninist]], and in his subsequent Second Declaration of Havana called on the peoples of Latin America to rise up in revolution against their governments.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 230&amp;ndash;234.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 190&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 190.&lt;/ref&gt; In response, the U.S.-dominated [[Organization of American States]] expelled Cuba, although Latin America's largest nations, Argentina, Brazil, Chile and Mexico, all abstained from the vote. The Soviet government privately reprimanded Castro for being reckless, believing that other Latin American governments would now crack down on communists, ultimately hindering the cause of socialism, although he was instead praised by the Chinese government for his cause in advocating Third World revolution.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 232&amp;ndash;234.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 190&quot;/&gt; As the [[Sino-Soviet Split]] began to emerge between the Marxist-Leninist governments of the Soviet Union and the People's Republic of China, Castro's government officially allied itself with the former, recognising that the Soviets had the economic and military ability to aid Cuba, despite the fact that ideologically they remained closer to China.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 232.&lt;/ref&gt;

Castro's government brought in measures to shape society using the Soviet model, persecuting both political opponents and perceived [[deviancy|social deviants]] such as prostitutes and homosexuals. Castro expressed the opinion that homosexuality was a bourgeois decadence absent from working class rural areas, proclaiming that &quot;in the country, there are no homosexuals&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tatchell&quot;&gt;[http://www.galha.org/glh/213/cuba.html ''Gay Rights and Wrongs in Cuba,''], Peter Tatchell (2002), published in the &quot;Gay and Lesbian Humanist&quot;, Spring 2002. An earlier version was published in a slightly edited form as [http://www.guardian.co.uk/cuba/story/0,11983,712621,00.html The Defiant One], in [[The Guardian]], Friday Review, June 8, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 233.&lt;/ref&gt; Members of his government spoke out against the treatment of gay people, noting the support of homosexual intellectuals in the Cuban Revolution, and ultimately Castro agreed that while they would be prevented from involvement in education, they would not be punished.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 188&amp;ndash;189.&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, many homosexuals were rounded up by police and forced into a manual labor organization for criminals, the Military Units for the Support of Production (UMAP).&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 189&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 189.&lt;/ref&gt; Decades later, Castro expressed deep regret for these actions, taking full responsibility and calling them  &quot;moments of great injustice, great injustice!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cnn.com/2010/WORLD/americas/08/31/cuba.castro.gays/index.html?hpt=T2 &quot;Castro admits 'injustice' for gays and lesbians during revolution&quot;], [[CNN]], Shasta Darlington, August 31, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote box|width=25em|align=right|bgcolor=#ACE1AF|quote=&quot;The revolution has no time for elections. There is no more democratic government in Latin America than the revolutionary government. ... If Mr. Kennedy does not like Socialism, we do not like imperialism. We do not like capitalism&quot;|source=— Fidel Castro, 1961 &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |year = 1961|month = May 1|url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/may/1/newsid_2479000/2479867.stm|title = Victorious Castro bans elections|publisher=BBC News |accessdate =May 19, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; }}

By 1962, the Cuban economy was in steep decline, a result of poor economic management coupled with the interference and trade embargo of the U.S. government. There were major food shortages, and the government introduced rationing of both food and consumer goods, with a riot breaking out in [[Cárdenas, Cuba|Cárdenas]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 233.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 189&quot;/&gt; Security reports indicated that the Cuban people were increasingly associating the governing communists with austerity, shortages and persecution, and Castro himself was having difficulties with many of the members of the defunct Popular Socialist Party, in particular Aníbal Escalante and [[Blas Roca]], believing them to be unduly loyal to Moscow over his government in Havana. In March 1962 Castro removed the most prominent of these &quot;Old Communists&quot; from office, labeling them too &quot;sectarian&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 234&amp;ndash;236.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 192.&lt;/ref&gt; On a personal level, Castro was feeling increasingly lonely and isolated in his position as Prime Minister, and relations with his old friend Che Guevara became strained as the latter became increasingly anti-Soviet, instead favoring the Chinese Marxist-Leninist government of [[Mao Zedong]] in the Sino-Soviet Split.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 258&amp;ndash;259.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 191&amp;ndash;192.&lt;/ref&gt;

===The Cuban Missile Crisis: 1962===
{{Main|Cuban Missile Crisis}}
Soviet Premier Khrushchev believed that the USSR was vulnerable to attack from the U.S. and its [[NATO]] allies, who were both militarily superior and who had nuclear weapons in Western Europe and Turkey, within striking distance of the USSR. He developed a plan to alter the balance of power by placing Soviet nuclear missiles on Cuba, from where they could target the U.S.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 192&amp;ndash;194.&lt;/ref&gt; Khrushchev approached Castro with this idea, and while the Cuban leader felt conflicted, he ultimately agreed, believing that it would guarantee Soviet protection of Cuba and enhance the power of the socialist camp.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 194.&lt;/ref&gt; In July 1962, Raúl Castro traveled to Moscow to work out the specifics.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 195&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 195.&lt;/ref&gt; The operation was undertaken in strict secrecy, with only the Castro brothers, Guevara, President Dorticós and security chief [[Ramiro Valdés]] knowing the full picture.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 195&quot;/&gt; It was agreed to deploy Soviet [[R-12 (missile)|R-12]] [[MRBM]]s on Cuban soil, all of which had the capacity to fire nuclear warheads at all of the U.S.' major cities. However, American [[Lockheed U-2]] reconnaissance discovered the construction of the missile installations on October 15, 1962 before the weapons had actually been deployed. The U.S. government viewed the installation of Soviet nuclear weapons {{convert|90|mi|km|0}} south of [[Key West]] as an aggressive act and a threat to U.S. security. As a result, the U.S. publicly announced its discovery on October 22, 1962, and implemented a [[quarantine]] around Cuba that would actively intercept and search any vessels heading for the island. Castro hit back at Kennedy, insisting that Cuba had a right to defend itself from foreign aggression.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986. pp. 238-239&quot;&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 238&amp;ndash;239.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 196&amp;ndash;197.&lt;/ref&gt;

Castro privately urged Khrushchev to heighten tensions by threatening a nuclear strike on the U.S. should Cuba be attacked, but Khrushchev was desperate to avoid [[nuclear war]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 197.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last = Khrushchev|first = Nikita Sergeyevich |date= October 27, 1962|url = http://www.gwu.edu/~nsarchiv/nsa/cuba_mis_cri/621030%20Letter%20to%20Castro.pdf|title = Letter to Castro|format = PDF|publisher=The George Washington University|accessdate =May 11, 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Negotiations took place between Kennedy and Khrushchev, with Castro having no involvement. Ultimately, Khrushchev agreed to remove the missiles in exchange for a U.S. commitment not to invade Cuba and an understanding that the US would secretly remove American MRBMs targeting the Soviet Union from Turkey and Italy, a measure that the U.S. implemented a few months later.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 198&amp;ndash;199.&lt;/ref&gt; After learning of the deal, Castro was furious, believing that Khrushchev had betrayed him and given in to U.S. demands.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 239.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 199&amp;ndash;200.&lt;/ref&gt; Depressed, he lost his appetite and became ill.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 203.&lt;/ref&gt; Proposing a five-point plan, Castro demanded that the U.S. end its embargo, put a stop to its support for dissidents, cease its support for militant attacks on Cuba, stop violating Cuban air space and territorial waters and withdrawing from the [[Guantanamo Bay Naval Base]]. Putting forward these demands to the visiting [[Secretary-General of the United Nations]], the Burmese [[U Thant]], the U.S. ignored his demands, and in turn Castro refused to allow a U.N. inspection team onto Cuba.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 241&amp;ndash;242.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Furthering Socialism: 1963&amp;ndash;1970===
[[File:Фидель Кастро в УДН.JPG|thumb|Castro on his visit to Russia.]]
In February 1963, Castro received a personal letter from Khrushchev, in which the Soviet Premier had emotionally set out his reasons for coming to an agreement with the U.S. government and in which he invited Castro to come and visit the USSR. Deeply touched by the letter, Castro set aside his resentment and traveled to the country in April, ultimately staying for five weeks. Visiting 14 cities, he gave speeches and met with locals, addressing a rally in [[Red Square]] and watching the May Day parade from the wall of the [[Kremlin]]. During his visit, he was also awarded both an honourary doctorate from [[Moscow State University]] as well as the [[Order of Lenin]], becoming the first foreigner to receive the latter.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 245&amp;ndash;248.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 204&amp;ndash;205.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Castro returned from the Soviet Union with new ideas for furthering socialism in Cuba. Inspired by the Soviet daily newspaper, ''[[Pravda]]'', Castro oversaw the amalgamation of Cuba's two authorized newspapers, ''Hoy'' and ''Revolución'', into a new publication, ''[[Granma (newspaper)|Granma]]'', named after the boat upon which Castro had arrived in Cuba with his revolutionaries in 1956.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 249.&lt;/ref&gt; He also oversaw largescale investment in Cuban sports programmes, allowing the country to become one of Latin America's most successful sporting nations.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 249&amp;ndash;250.&lt;/ref&gt; On the 10th anniversary of Castro's attack on the Moncada Barracks, held in 1963, the Cuban leader gave a speech in the Plaza  de la Revolución attended by his mother, who would die 11 days later. Her death was reported on in the Cuban press, but it would prove the last time that they were permitted to mention Castro's private life, who began to increasingly value his privacy.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 250&amp;ndash;251.&lt;/ref&gt; Domestically, Castro agreed to allow anyone wishing to leave Cuba &amp;ndash; with the exception of males aged between 15 and 26 &amp;ndash; to do so. This helped rid the government of many of its opponents, but thousands took up the government's offer, many more than Castro had wanted.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 213&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 213.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1964, Castro undertook a second, shorter trip to Moscow, officially to sign a new five-year sugar trade agreement, but also to discuss the ramifications of the [[assassination of John F. Kennedy]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 263.&lt;/ref&gt; In October 1965, the governing Integrated Revolutionary Organizations officially changed its name to the Cuban Communist Party, and published the membership of its Central Committee.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 213&quot;/&gt;

{{Quote box|width=25em|align=left|bgcolor=#ACE1AF|quote=&quot;The greatest threat presented by Castro's Cuba is as an example to other Latin American states which are beset by poverty, corruption, feudalism, and plutocratic exploitation ... his influence in Latin America might be overwhelming and irresistible if, with Soviet help, he could establish in Cuba a Communist utopia.&quot;|source=— [[Walter Lippmann]], ''[[Newsweek]]'', April 27, 1964 &lt;ref&gt;&quot;Cuba Once More&quot;, by [[Walter Lippmann]], ''[[Newsweek]]'', April 27, 1964, p. 23.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Despite the Soviet government's misgivings, Castro continued to call for armed revolution across the capitalist world, providing funding and support for various militant leftist groups. He supported Che Guevara's plan for the &quot;Andean project&quot;, an unsuccessful plan to set up a guerrilla movement in the highlands of Bolivia, Peru and Argentina, and allowed revolutionary groups from across the world, from the [[Viet Cong]] of Vietnam to the [[Black Panther Party|Black Panthers]] of the U.S., to train in Cuba.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 255.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 211.&lt;/ref&gt; In particular, he thought that Africa, much of which was dominated by western colonial and neo-colonial powers, was rife for revolutionary change, and sent soldiers and medics to aid the socialist government of [[Ahmed Ben Bella]] in Algeria, supporting them during the [[Sand war]] against Morocco; in turn, the Algerian government awarded Castro its Medal of Honour. Also allying itself with the socialist government of [[Alphonse Massemba-Débat]] in [[Republic of the Congo|Congo-Brazzaville]], in 1965 Castro authorized Guevara to travel to the neighbouring [[Congo Kinshasa]] in order to train militant revolutionaries against the western-backed government.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 255&amp;ndash;256, 260.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 211&amp;ndash;212.&lt;/ref&gt; Castro was personally devastated when Guevara was subsequently killed by CIA-backed troops in Bolivia in October 1967, publicly attributing it to Che's disregard for his own safety in the revolutionary cause.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 267&amp;ndash;268.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 216.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1966 Castro staged the first [[Organization of Solidarity with the People of Asia, Africa and Latin America|Tri-Continental Conference of Africa, Asia and Latin America]] in Havana, further establishing himself as a significant player on the world stage despite the small and dependent nature of Cuba's economy.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 265.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 214.&lt;/ref&gt; From this conference, Castro oversaw the creation of the Latin American Solidarity Organization (OLAS), a vehicle through which he could support the cause of socialist revolution. Holding its first meeting in Havana in August 1967, it adopted the slogan of &quot;The duty of a revolution is to make revolution&quot;, with Castro signifying that Havana, and not Moscow, was now the leader of the Marxist-Leninist movement in Latin America.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 267.&lt;/ref&gt;

Castro's increasing role on the world stage led to a strained relationship with the Soviet government, now under the leadership of [[Leonid Brezhnev]]. Attempting to reassert Cuba's independence, Castro refused to sign the [[Treaty on the Non-Proliferation of Nuclear Weapons]] in May 1976, declaring that it represented a Soviet and U.S. attempt to dominate the Third World.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 269.&lt;/ref&gt; In turn, the Soviet-loyalist Aníbal Escalante, then Cuban ambassador to Czechoslovakia, returned to Cuba where he began organizing a network of opposition to Castro's leadership within the government, publicly criticising his advocacy of armed revolution. In January 1968, Escalante and his supporters were then arrested for passing Cuban state secrets on to the Soviet Union.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 269&amp;ndash;270.&lt;/ref&gt; However, Brezhnev exerted pressure on Castro's government to be more obediant, something they ultimately accepted. On August 23, 1968, Castro made a public gesture to the USSR that caused the Soviet leadership to reaffirm their support for him. Two days after [[Warsaw Pact invasion of Czechoslovakia|the Soviet invasion of]] [[Czechoslovakia]] to repress the [[Prague Spring]], Castro took to the airwaves and publicly denounced the Czech rebellion. Castro warned the Cuban people about the Czechoslovakian &quot;counterrevolutionaries&quot;, who &quot;were moving Czechoslovakia towards capitalism and into the arms of [[imperialism|imperialists]]&quot;. He called the leaders of the rebellion &quot;the agents of [[West Germany]] and fascist reactionary rabble.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 270&amp;ndash;271.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 216&amp;ndash;217.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last = Castro|first = Fidel|year = 1968|month = August|url = http://lanic.utexas.edu/project/castro/db/1968/19680824.html|title = Castro comments on Czechoslovakia crisis|publisher=FBIS}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1968, Castro proclaimed a Great Revolutionary Offensive in Cuba, influenced by the [[Great Leap Forward]] in China. As a part of this, any remaining privately owned shops and businesses were shut down, with Castro denouncing their owners as capitalist counter-revolutionaries.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 227&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 227.&lt;/ref&gt; In January 1969, Castro publicly celebrated the tenth anniversary of his administration in Revolution Square, but used the occasion to ask the assembled crowds if they would tolerate greater sugar rations, reflecting the economic problems facing the country.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 227&quot;/&gt; The majority of the country's sugar crop was being sent to the Soviet Union to maintain Cuba's trade quota, but the 1969 crop was heavily damaged by a hurricane. As a result, the government postponed the Christmas and New Year holidays of 1969/1970 so that the harvest could continue with detailed monthly targets being set for every mill, while the military were drafted in to aid in the agricultural effort. Castro and other Cabinet ministers joined in with the harvest, as did several foreign diplomats from friendly nations.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 273.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 229.&lt;/ref&gt; Ultimately, the country failed to achieve that year's production quota for sugar. Castro publicly proclaimed it to be a worse set-back for the Revolution than the failed Moncada Barracks Attack, and offered to resign, but assembled crowds denounced the idea, cheering their support for Castro.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 274.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 230&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 230.&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the country's economic problems, many of Castro's social reforms remained popular in Cuba, whose population were largely supportive of the &quot;Achievements of the Revolution&quot; in education, medical care and road construction, as well as the government's policy of &quot;[[direct democracy]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 275&amp;ndash;276.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 230&quot;/&gt;

===Economic stagnation and Third World politics: 1970–1974===
In a dire economic situation, the Cuban government turned to the Soviets for help. From 1970 through to 1972, Soviet economists re-planned and organized the Cuban economy, founding the Cuban-Soviet Commission of Economic, Scientific and Technical Collaboration, while Soviet Premier [[Aleksey Kosygin]] (1904&amp;ndash;1980) visited Cuba in late 1971.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 276&amp;ndash;277.&lt;/ref&gt; In July 1972, Cuba would successfully apply for membership of the [[Comecon|Council for Mutual Economic Assistance]] (Comecon), an economic organization of socialist states, although this move only served to further limit Cuba's economy to agricultural production.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 277.&lt;/ref&gt; Aside from the economy, Castro's Cuba also faced other problems in the early 1970s: in May 1970, [[Alpha 66]], a militant Cuban dissident group based in Florida, sank two Cuban fishing boats and captured their crews, demanding the release of Alpha 66 members imprisoned in Cuba. Under U.S. government pressure, the hostages were released, with Castro welcoming them back as heroes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 230&quot;/&gt; In April 1971, Castro gained international condemnation after ordering the arrest of [[Herberto Padilla]], a Cuban poet who had won an international prize but whose views were critical of the government. Padilla fell ill, with Castro visiting him in hospital; soon after, the poet publicly confessed his guilt and was released. Soon, the government formed the National Cultural Council through which it ensured that intellectuals and artists produced work that supported their administration.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 232&amp;ndash;233.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1971, Castro made his first foreign visit since 1964, this time to [[Chile]], where the Marxist President [[Salvador Allende]] (1908&amp;ndash;1973) had just been elected as the head of [[Unidad Popular|a left-wing coalition]]. Implementing socialist reforms by nationalizing industry, Allende gained Castro's support, and Castro spent 23 days touring the country, giving speeches and press conferences, talking to both admiring socialists and right wing opponents. Cautious of the staunchly right-wing Chilean military, Castro advised Allende to purge such opponents from the armed forces before they led a coup. Castro was proven right; in 1973, the Chilean military, backed by the U.S. government, [[1973 Chilean coup d'état|led a coup d'etat]] against Allende's government, banning elections, executing thousands of opponents and establishing a military junta led by Commander-in-Chief [[Augusto Pinochet]]. Castro considered it a tragedy, but was unsurprised.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 278&amp;ndash;280.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 233&amp;ndash;236, 240.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-L0614-040, Berlin, Fidel Castro an der Grenze.jpg|thumb|left|Fidel Castro and members of the [[East Germany|East German]] [[Politburo]] on his visit to the country in 1972.]]

Following his trip to Chile, Castro traveled to West Africa to meet with [[Sékou Touré]] (1922–1984), the President of [[Guinea]]. A socialist and nationalist, Touré had much in common with Castro, and they forged an alliance; the Cuban even told a crowd of Guineans that theirs was the greatest leader in Africa.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 237&amp;ndash;238.&lt;/ref&gt; From Guinea he went on a seven-week tour visiting various other leftist allies in Africa and Eurasia: Algeria, Bulgaria, Hungary, Poland, East Germany, Czechoslovakia and the then Soviet Union. On every trip he seemed eager to travel among the people by visiting factories and farms, and chatted and joked with those whom he met. Although publicly highly supportive of these governments, in private he urged them to do more to aid revolutionary socialist movements in other parts of the world, and in particular in Vietnam, where the [[Vietnam War]] was then raging between the Soviet-backed communists and U.S.-backed capitalists.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 238.&lt;/ref&gt; In September 1973 he returned to [[Algiers]] to attend the Fourth Summit of the [[Non-Aligned Movement]] (NAM). Various members of the NAM were critical of Castro's attendance, claiming that Cuba was aligned to the USSR and the [[Eastern Bloc]] and therefore should not be at the conference, particularly as he praised the Soviet Union in his speech and asserted that it was not imperialistic in nature.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 283&amp;ndash;284.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 239.&lt;/ref&gt; 

As the [[Yom Kippur War]] broke out in 1973 between [[Israel]] and a coalition of Arab states led by [[Egypt]] and [[Syria]], Castro's government sent 4000 troops to Syria in order to prevent the Israeli forces entering Syrian territory.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 284.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1974, Castro broke off relations with the Israeli government over both their treatment of Palestinian civilians during the [[Israel-Palestine conflict]] and their increasingly close relationship with the United States. This earned him respect from leaders throughout the Arab world. In particular he was praised by [[Muammar Gaddafi]] (1942&amp;ndash;2011), the socialist president of the [[Libyan Arab Republic]], with Castro and Gaddafi becoming friends and allies.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 239&amp;ndash;240.&lt;/ref&gt; That year, Cuba also experienced an economic boost, due primarily to the high international price of sugar, but also influenced by new trade credits with Canada, Argentina, and various countries in Western Europe.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 283&amp;ndash;284.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 240.&lt;/ref&gt; A number of Latin American states began calling for Cuba's re-admittance into the [[Organization of American States]] (OAM), with the United States finally conceding in 1975 at the advice of [[Henry Kissinger]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 282.&lt;/ref&gt; The Cuban government decided to call the first National Congress of the Cuban Communist Party, thereby officially announcing Cuba's status as a [[socialist state]]. It adopted a new constitution based upon the Soviet model, which abolished both the position of President and Prime Minister, leaving Castro without any official position in government. Instead he took up the role as President of both the newly created [[Council of State of Cuba|Council of State]] and the [[Council of Ministers of Cuba|Council of Ministers]], meaning that he was now both [[head of state]] and head of government.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 283.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 240&amp;ndash;241.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Presidency==

===Foreign wars and NAM Presidency: 1975–1979===
[[File:Lobito Lighthouse 1995.jpg|thumb|right|Castro's image painted onto a now-destroyed lighthouse in Lobito, Angola, 1995.]]
On November 4, 1975, President Castro ordered the deployment of Cuban troops to the southern African state of [[Angola]], in order to aid the Marxist [[MPLA]] government in the [[Angolan Civil War]]. The two opposition forces, the [[National Liberation Front of Angola|FLNA]] and [[National Union for Total Independence of Angola|UNITA]], had the backing of the United States and [[South Africa]], the latter of whom feared that a Marxist-governed Angola would threaten their rule in neighboring Namibia. Initially providing the MPLA with 230 military advisers, South Africa subsequently sent between 5,000 and 10,000 troops into Angola, causing Castro to respond with 18,000 Cuban troops. The Cubans played a major role in forcing the South Africans into retreat.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 281, 284&amp;ndash;287.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 242&amp;ndash;243.&lt;/ref&gt; Considering Africa to be &quot;the weakest link in the imperialist chain&quot;, Castro celebrated the Angolan victory with Angolan President [[Agostinho Neto]], Guinean President [[Sékou Touré]] and Guinea-Bissaun President [[Luís Cabral]], together agreeing to support the communist government of Mozambique from the threat of the rebel army [[RENAMO]] in the [[Mozambique Civil War]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 243.&lt;/ref&gt; Heading north in February, Castro visited his allies in Algeria and then Libya, where he spent ten days in the company of friend and ally Muammar Gadaffi. Moving on to talks with [[Yemeni Socialist Party|the Marxist government]] of [[South Yemen]], he then traveled to Somalia, Tanzania, Mozambique and Angolan, being greeted by crowds as a hero for Cuba's role in opposing the apartheid government of South Africa.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 243&amp;ndash;244.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Fidelcastro1978.jpg|thumb|left|Fidel Castro speaking in Havana, 1978.]]
In 1977, the [[Ogaden War]] broke out between Somalia and Ethiopia as the government of the former, headed by pro-Soviet President [[Siad Barre]], decided to annex the Ethiopian region of [[Ogaden]] to create Greater Somalia. In his earlier talks with Barre, Castro had advised him not to take such action, and as war broke out, Castro sided with the Ethiopians, whose Marxist President [[Mengistu Haile Mariam]] of the [[Workers' Party of Ethiopia]] appealed to fellow Marxist governments for help. Like the Soviet Union, Castro complied, sending troops under the command of General [[Arnaldo Ochoa]] to aid the overwhelmed Ethiopian army. Forcing back the Somali army, Mengistu then ordered the Ethiopians to suppress the [[Eritrean People's Liberation Front]], a measure that Castro refused to support.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 291&amp;ndash;292.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 245&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 245.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, Castro extended support to Marxist revolutionary movements throughout Latin America, namely in [[Nicaragua]], where he aided the [[Sandinista National Liberation Front]] in overthrowing the government of right-wing president [[Anastasio Somoza Debayle]] in July 1979.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 249.&lt;/ref&gt; Castro's critics accused the government of wasting Cuban lives in these military endeavors; it has been claimed by the anti-Castro [[Carthage Foundation]]-funded [[Center for a Free Cuba]] that an estimated 14,000 Cubans were killed in Cuban military actions abroad.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |date=August 25, 2006|url = http://www.mediatransparency.org/recipientgrants.php?recipientID=1892|title = Recipient Grants: Center for a Free Cuba|accessdate =August 25, 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=O'Grady |first=Mary Anastasia |date=October 30, 2005 |url=http://www.cubacenter.org/media/news_articles/countingcastrosvictims.php |title=Counting Castro's Victims |publisher=Wall Street Journal, Center for a Free Cuba |accessdate=May 11, 2006|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20061008182246/http%3A//www.cubacenter.org/media/news_articles/countingcastrosvictims.php |archivedate = October 8, 2006|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote box|width=25em|align=right|bgcolor=#ACE1AF|quote=&quot;There is often talk of human rights, but it is also necessary to talk of the rights of humanity. Why should some people walk barefoot, so that others can travel in luxurious cars? Why should some live for thirty-five years, so that others can live for seventy years? Why should some be miserably poor, so that others can be hugely rich? I speak on behalf of the children in the world who do not have a piece of bread. I speak on the behalf of the sick who have no medicine, of those whose rights to life and human dignity have been denied.&quot;|source=— Fidel Castro's message to the UN General Assembly, 1979 &lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 245&quot;/&gt;}}

In 1979, the Conference of the Non-Aligned Movement (NAM) was held in Havana, while that year Castro was selected as the president of the NAM, a position that he would hold till 1982. In his capacity as both President of the NAM and of Cuba he appeared at the United Nations General Assembly in October 1979, giving a speech on the disparity between the world's rich and poor. His speech was greeted with much applause from other world leaders, although American anti-communist protesters demonstrated against him outside the building.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne. p. 294&quot;&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 294.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 245&quot;/&gt; However, his standing among the Non-Aligned Movement was damaged due to Cuba abstaining from the U.N. General Assembly condemnation of the [[Soviet war in Afghanistan]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne. p. 294&quot;/&gt;

Relations between Cuba and other North American states improved, with the Mexican President [[Luis Echeverría]] reiterating ties between the two countries in the face of U.S. domination and the Canadian Prime Minister [[Pierre Trudeau]] even proclaiming &quot;Viva Castro!&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 244&amp;ndash;245.&lt;/ref&gt; Relations with the U.S. also improved following the election of Democratic Party candidate [[Jimmy Carter]] in 1977. Carter continued to criticize the human rights abuses of Castro's government, but took a more respectful approach which gained Castro's attention. Believing Carter to be well-meaning and sincere, Castro freed certain political prisoners and allowed some Cuban exiles to visit relatives on the island, hoping that in turn Carter would abolish the U.S. economic embargo and halt the CIA's support for militant dissident groups.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 289.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 247&amp;ndash;248.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reagan and Gorbachev: 1980&amp;ndash;1989===

By the start of the 1980s, the Cuban economy was again in trouble, following a decline in the price of sugar on the open market and a decimated harvest following 1979's bad weather and plant infestations.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 250.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Got04|Gott 2004]]. p. 288.&lt;/ref&gt; Increasing numbers of Cubans began hijacking boats and fleeing toward Florida, enticed by the wealth and consumer goods of the U.S.; Castro labelled such individuals traitorous &quot;scum&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 250&amp;ndash;251.&lt;/ref&gt; In one incident, 10,000 Cubans eager to leave had stormed the Peruvian Embassy requesting asylum, embarrassing both the Peruvian and Cuban authorities. The U.S. agreed that it would accept 3,500 Cuban refugees, with Castro conceding that those who wanted to leave could do so from the port of Mariel. Hundreds of boats arrived from the U.S., leading to a mass exodus of 120,000; Castro's government took advantage of the situation by unloading criminals and the mentally ill onto the boats destined for Florida.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 295.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 251&amp;ndash;252.&lt;/ref&gt; The Cuban government were desperate for money to boost the economy and fund its internationalist ambitions, in doing so turning to almost any economic transaction, however un-socialist. They began secretly selling off paintings from the national collections on the international market and illicitly traded to obtain U.S. electronic goods through Panama.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 255&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 255.&lt;/ref&gt; Castro became passionate in his denunciation of the Third World debt problem, arguing that the Third World would never escape the debt that the First World banks and governments had imposed upon it. In 1985 alone Havana hosted five international conferences on the world debt problem.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 255&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Reagan and Gorbachev hold discussions.jpg|thumb|left|250px|U.S. President Reagan and Soviet Premier Gorbachev were the two major players on the world stage in the 1980s, and would heavily affect Castro's governance of Cuba.]]
In 1980, the Republican Party nominee [[Ronald Reagan]] was elected to the U.S. Presidency, pursuing a hard line approach against Castro,&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 296.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 252&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 252.&lt;/ref&gt; and by 1981, Castro was accusing the U.S. of undertaking biological warfare against Cuba.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 252&quot;/&gt; Although he despised the [[National Reorganization Process|right wing military junta]] in Argentina, Castro supported them in the 1982 [[Falklands War]] against the British, whom he viewed as an imperialist aggressor, even offering military aid to the Argentinians, although British forces had won the war before this ever materialized.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 253.&lt;/ref&gt; Castro had also been supportive of the leftist [[New Jewel Movement]] that had seized power in [[Grenada]] in 1979, sending in doctors, teachers, and technicians to aid the country's development, and befriending the Grenadine Marxist president, [[Maurice Bishop]]. When Bishop was murdered in a Soviet-backed coup by hardline Marxist [[Bernard Coard]] in October 1983, Castro cautiously continued supporting the Grenadine government, which remained Marxist. However, the U.S. and six Caribbean nations opposed the coup as a basis for [[Invasion of Grenada (1983)|invading the island and overthrowing the government]]; those Cuban soldiers who fought alongside their Grenadian comrades were killed. Castro denounced the invasion and compared the U.S. to [[Nazi Germany]], with condemnation also coming from the Soviet Union and the U.N. General Assembly.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 297.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 253&amp;ndash;254.&lt;/ref&gt; Subsequently fearing a U.S. invasion of Nicaragua, Castro sent General Ochoa to help train the governing Sandinistas in the tactics of guerrilla warfare, but received little support from the Soviet Union.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 254&amp;ndash;255.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1985, [[Mikhail Gorbachev]] became Secretary-General of the Soviet Communist Party. A reformer, he implemented measures to increase freedom of the press (''[[glasnost]]'') and economic decentralisation (''[[perestroika]]'') in an attempt to strengthen socialism, but like many more-orthodox Marxist critics, Castro feared that they would actually weaken the socialist state and allow capitalist elements to regain control.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 256&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 256.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Got04|Gott 2004]]. p. 273.&lt;/ref&gt; Hoping to strengthen relations with the western powers, Gorbachev entered into further talks with the U.S. government, who demanded that the USSR reduce its support for Castro's Cuba, something Gorbachev conceded to.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 256&quot;/&gt; Relations between the two nations deteriorated, and Castro ordered the security services to begin surveillance of Soviet diplomats in the country.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 257.&lt;/ref&gt; When Gorbachev visited Cuba in April 1989, he was greeted with a banner proclaiming &quot;Long live Marxism-Leninism!&quot;, a reproach for his reforms, and while his meetings with Castro were friendly, Gorbachev informed the Cuban leader that the ''perestroika'' reforms meant an end to subsidies and special favours for Cuba.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 260&amp;ndash;261.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Got04|Gott 2004]]. p. 276.&lt;/ref&gt; Ignoring calls to liberalise his regime in accordance with the policies implemented in the Soviet Union, Castro continued to clamp down on internal dissidents, in particular keeping tabs on the military, whom he saw as the primary threat to his government. A number of senior military officers, including Ochoa and [[Tony de la Guardia]], were subsequently investigated for a variety of crimes, including corruption and complicity in cocaine smuggling, put on trial, and executed in 1989, despite international calls for leniency.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 258&amp;ndash;266.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Got04|Gott 2004]]. pp. 279&amp;ndash;286.&lt;/ref&gt; In October 1985, Castro gave up regularly smoking [[Cuban cigars]] on medical advice, helping to set an example for the rest of the populace.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 224&quot;/&gt;

By November 1987, Castro began spending more time focusing on the ongoing Angolan Civil War, in which UNITA and South Africa had achieved great strides, forcing the Marxist forces into a retreat. Angolan President [[José Eduardo dos Santos]] appealed to Castro to send more troops, which he duly did, on the condition that the Cuban military would have overall command under the leadership of General Ochoa. Castro spent a great deal of his time monitoring the war effort, later admitting that he devoted more time to Angola that to Cuba's domestic situation; he believed that a successful victory would lead to the collapse of the apartheid regime in South Africa. However, relations between long-term friends Castro and Ochoa became strained, with the latter proclaiming the Cuban leader to be &quot;crazy.&quot; Castro wanted to continue for an all-out leftist victory, but Gorbachev was calling for a peaceful end to the conflict, organising quadripartite talks between the USSR, USA, Cuba and South Africa in 1988; the result was an agreement that all foreign troops would be pulled out of Angola. Castro was angered by Gorbachev's approach, believing that he was abandoning the plight of the world's poor in favour of detente.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 257&amp;ndash;258.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Got04|Gott 2004]]. pp. 276&amp;ndash;279.&lt;/ref&gt;

In Eastern Europe, socialism was collapsing as capitalist governments swept to power across the region between 1989 and 1991. Many western observers speculated that the same would happen in Cuba, although it was debated as to whether the transition to capitalism would be peaceful and gradual, as in Czechoslovakia, or violent and sudden, as in Romania.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 277.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Gott 286&quot;&gt;[[#Got04|Gott 2004]]. p. 286.&lt;/ref&gt; Increasingly isolated, Castro's only allies in the Americas were the Sandinista government of [[Daniel Ortega]] in Nicaragua and the military administration of General [[Manuel Noriega]] in Panama. Although Castro personally despised Noriega, a former CIA agent, he agreed to an alliance with him after the U.S. made attempts to depose his regime. Sending military advisers and military equipment to Panama, he advised Noriega to form a popular militia to combat U.S. aggression, but ultimately both the Panamanian military and militias fell before the invading U.S. marines in December 1989.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 267&amp;ndash;268.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Gott 286&quot;/&gt; In February 1990, the Sandinista government in Nicaragua was then defeated by the U.S.-funded [[National Opposition Union]] in an election, further isolating Castro's government.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 268&amp;ndash;270.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Gott 286&quot;/&gt; At the [[United Nations Human Rights Commission]] in [[Geneva]], Switzerland, the U.S. secured a majority vote for a resolution condemning the human rights violations of Castro's regime. Castro was particularly incensed that four of Cuba's former allies in Eastern Europe, Poland, Czechoslovakia, Hungary and Bulgaria, had supported the U.S. resolution, and in turn proclaimed that Cuba would cease to purchase goods from those countries. Rejecting the UN resolution, which the Cuban government asserted was simply a manifestation of increasing U.S. power, they refused to allow a six-nation investigative delegation to enter the country.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 270&amp;ndash;271.&lt;/ref&gt;

===The Special Period: 1990&amp;ndash;2000===

[[File:1 peso cubano 40 aniversario moncada reverso.jpg|thumb|upright|right|Cuban coin minted in 1993 to commemorate the fortieth anniversary of Castro's attack on the Moncada Barracks.]]
With favourable trade from the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe coming to an end, Castro recognised that Cuba was facing an economic crisis, publicly declaring that the country was entering a &quot;[[Special Period|Special Period in Time of Peace]].&quot; Petrol rations were dramatically reduced, Chinese bicycles were imported to replace cars, and factories performing non-essential tasks were shut down. Oxen began to replace tractors, firewood began being used for cooking and electricity cuts were introduced, lasting 16 hours a day. Castro informed the populace that they were facing the worst situation short of open war, and that there may come a time when no oil would reach the island, forcing the urban population to migrate to the countryside and adopt a life of [[subsistence farming]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 271.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Got04|Gott 2004]]. pp. 287&amp;ndash;289.&lt;/ref&gt; By 1992, the Cuban economy had declined by over 40% in under two years, with major food shortages, widespread malnutrition and a lack of basic goods.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 282.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Got04|Gott 2004]]. p. 288.&lt;/ref&gt;

Castro continued to hope for a restoration of orthodox Marxism-Leninism in the Soviet Union, but cautiously refrained from backing the [[1991 Soviet coup d'état attempt|1991 coup in the country]], which saw hardliners oust Gorbachev.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 274&amp;ndash;275.&lt;/ref&gt; When the coup was suppressed and Gorbachev regained control, relations between the two nations deteriorated further, with the Soviets withdrawing their troops stationed in Cuba in September 1991 in order to please the U.S.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 275.&lt;/ref&gt; In December, the [[Dissolution of the Soviet Union|Soviet Union was officially dismantled]], with the capitalist reformer [[Boris Yeltsin]], President of the [[Russian Federation]], overseeing the abolition of the [[Communist Party of the Soviet Union]] and the introduction of a [[multiparty democracy]] with a capitalist economy. A staunch anti-socialist, Yeltsin despised Castro, and developed links with the anti-Castro [[Cuban American National Foundation]], based in Miami.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 274&amp;ndash;275.&lt;/ref&gt; Now without his former Marxist-Leninist allies, Castro began trying to secure good relations with capitalist nations that he had formerly shunned. He welcomed western politicians and investors to Cuba, whatever their motives, and took a particular interest in the policies of the right wing [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative Party]] government of [[Margaret Thatcher]] in the United Kingdom, believing that Cuban socialism could learn from her emphasis on low taxation and personal initiative. He even became a close friend of [[Manuel Fraga]], the rightist Spanish politician then serving as President of the regional government of Galicia, Castro's ancestral homeland.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 290&amp;ndash;291.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1994, he visited Colombia, then in a state of ''de facto'' civil war, to attend the inauguration of President [[Ernesto Samper]] of the [[Colombian Liberal Party]]. He told journalists about his role in the Bogotazo fifty years before, but refrained from praising the socialist [[FARC]] guerillas whom Cuba had formerly funded. Similarly, he refrained from openly praising the [[Zapatista Army of National Liberation|Zapatista Uprising]] in Mexico in 1995, instead calling for a negotiated settlement; publicly, he proclaimed that the era of armed rebellions had come to an end, trying to present himself as a moderate figure on the world stage.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 305&amp;ndash;306.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote box|width=25em|align=left|bgcolor=#ACE1AF|quote=&quot;We do not have a smidgen of capitalism or neo-liberalism. We are facing a world completely ruled by neo-liberalism and capitalism. This does not mean that we are going to surrender. It means that we have to adopt to the reality of that world. That is what we are doing, with great equanimity, without giving up our ideals, our goals. I ask you to have trust in what the government and party are doing. They are defending, to the last atom, socialist ideas, principles and goals.&quot;|source=— Fidel Castro explaining the reforms of the Special Period &lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 291&amp;ndash;292.&lt;/ref&gt; }}

In 1991, Havana [[1991 Pan American Games|hosted]] the [[Pan-American Games]], which involved the construction of [[Estadio Panamericano, Havana|a stadium]] and accommodation for the athletes; Castro would admit that it was an expensive error, but it proved to be a success both for Cuba and Castro. Crowds regularly shouted &quot;Fidel! Fidel!&quot; in front of foreign journalists, proclaiming popular support for his government, while Cuba reached the top of the gold-medal table, the first time a Latin American nation had ever beaten the United States to that title.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 272&amp;ndash;273.&lt;/ref&gt; Support for Castro within Cuba remained strong, and although there were a few minor demonstrations against the government, the opposition movement stationed within the country largely rejected the exile community's calls for an armed uprising, instead hoping for a gradual transition to a multiparty democracy.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 275&amp;ndash;276.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Got04|Gott 2004]]. p. 314.&lt;/ref&gt; On 5 August 1994, the most serious anti-government demonstration since Castro took power occurred in Havana, as 200 to 300 young men began throwing stones at police, demanding that they be given a boat and allowed to travel to Miami. Soon, a much larger pro-Castro crowd emerged to confront them, being joined by Castro himself, who told state media that the men were anti-socials who had been misled by U.S. media. The protests soon dispersed with no recorded injuries.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 297&amp;ndash;299.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Got04|Gott 2004]]. pp. 298&amp;ndash;299.&lt;/ref&gt; Fearing that the U.S. or Florida-based dissident groups would take the opportunity to invade, Fidel, Raul and his military commanders organised a defense strategy known as the &quot;War of All the People.&quot; This involved planning a widespread guerilla warfare campaign, and the unemployed were given jobs in building a network of bunkers and tunnels across the island.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 287.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Got04|Gott 2004]]. pp. 273&amp;ndash;274.&lt;/ref&gt;

Castro recognised the need for reform if Cuban socialism was to survive in a world now dominated by capitalist free markets. In October 1991, the Fourth Congress of the Cuban Communist Party was held in Santiago, at which a number of important changes to the government were announced. Castro would step down as head of government, to be replaced by the much younger [[Carlos Lage]], although would remain the head of the Communist Party and Commander-in-Chief of the armed forces. Many older members of government were to be retired and replaced by younger counterparts. A number of economic changes were proposed, and subsequently put to a national referendum. Free farmers' markets and small-scale private enterprises would be legalised in an attempt to stimulate economic growth, while U.S. dollars were also made legal tender. Certain restrictions on emigration were eased, allowing more discontented Cuban citizens to move to the United States. Further democratisation was to be brought in by having the National Assembly's members elected directly by the people, rather than through municipal and provincial assemblies. Castro welcomed debate between proponents and opponents of the reforms, although over time began to increasingly sympathise with the opponent's positions, arguing that such reforms must be delayed.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 276&amp;ndash;281, 284, 287.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Got04|Gott 2004]]. pp. 291&amp;ndash;294.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Nelson Mandela-2008 (edit).jpg|thumb|right|South African president Nelson Mandela was highly supportive of Cuba's military and humanitarian work in Africa, personally thanking Castro for his role in helping to topple apartheid.]]

Castro's government decided to diversify its economy from sugar production, focusing on the development of [[biotechnology]] and also on tourism, the latter of which overtook the island's sugar industry as its primary source of revenue in 1995.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 288.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Got04|Gott 2004]]. pp. 290, 322.&lt;/ref&gt; The arrival of thousands of tourists from Mexico and Spain led to an increasing number of young Cubans turning to prostitution; although officially illegal, Castro refrained from bringing a full crack down on these prostitutes, fearing a political backlash.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 294.&lt;/ref&gt; Economic hardship led many Cubans to turn towards religion, both in the forms of [[Roman Catholicism]] and the syncretic faith of [[Santeria]]. Although he had long considered religious belief to be backward, Castro softened his approach to the Church and religious institutions, recognising the psychological comfort it could bring, and religious people were permitted for the first time to join the Communist Party.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 278, 294&amp;ndash;295.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Got04|Gott 2004]]. p. 309.&lt;/ref&gt; Although viewing the [[Roman Catholic Church]] as a reactionary, pro-capitalist institution, Castro decided to organise a visit to Cuba by [[Pope John Paul II]], which took place in January 1998; ultimately, it strengthened the position of both the Church in Cuba, and Castro's government.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 309&amp;ndash;311.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Got04|Gott 2004]]. pp. 306&amp;ndash;310.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the early 1990s, Castro embraced [[environmentalism]], campaigning against the waste of natural resources and [[global warming]], accusing the U.S. of being the world's primary polluter.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 312&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 312.&lt;/ref&gt; His government's environmentalist policies would prove highly effective; by 2006, Cuba was the only nation in the world which met the [[World Wide Fund for Nature|WWF]]'s definition of sustainable development, having an [[ecological footprint]] of less than 1.8 hectares per capita and a [[Human Development Index]] of over 0.8 for 2007.&lt;ref&gt;[http://assets.panda.org/downloads/living_planet_report.pdf untitled&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, Castro also became a proponent of the [[anti-globalisation]] movement, criticizing U.S. global hegemony and the control exerted by [[multinational corporation|multinationals]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 312&quot;/&gt; Castro also maintained his devout anti-apatheid beliefs, and at the July 26 celebrations in 1991, Castro was joined onstage by the South African political activist [[Nelson Mandela]], recently released from prison. Mandela would praise Cuba's involvement in battling South Africa in Angola and thanked Castro personally.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 283.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Got04|Gott 2004]]. p. 279.&lt;/ref&gt; He would later attend Mandela's inauguration as President of South Africa in 1994.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 304.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2001 he attended the Conference Against Racism in South Africa at which he lectured on the global spread of racial stereotypes through U.S. film.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 312&quot;/&gt;

===The Pink Tide: 2000&amp;ndash;2006===
{{Expand section|date=October 2012|Information on Cuba's increasingly good relationship with the Pink Tide and its co-founding of ALBA}}
{{Quote box|width=25em|align=right|bgcolor=#ACE1AF|quote=&quot;As I have said before, the ever more sophisticated weapons piling up in the arsenals of the wealthiest and the mightiest can kill the illiterate, the ill, the poor and the hungry but they cannot kill ignorance, illnesses, poverty or hunger.&quot;|source=— Fidel Castro's speech at the International Conference on Financing for Development, 2002 &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cuba.cu/gobierno/discursos/2002/ing/f210302i.html Speech by Fidel Castro to the International Conference on Financing and Development, Monterrey, March 21, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;}}
[[File:Lula anda Castro9822.jpeg|thumb|right|Castro meeting with center-left Brazilian President [[Lula da Silva]], a significant &quot;Pink Tide&quot; leader.]]
At the start of the 21st century, Castro's Cuba was still mired in the economic problems of its &quot;Special Period&quot;. However, Castro would be offered a &quot;political godsend&quot; in the form of Venezuelan President [[Hugo Chávez]] (1954&amp;ndash;). A former army general who represented the [[Fifth Republic Movement]], Chávez was elected to the Presidency of Venezuela in 1999. A [[democratic socialism|democratic socialist]], Chavez began a program of nationalizing much of the country's lucrative oil industry and made use of fiercely anti-U.S. rhetoric.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kozloff 2008. p. 24&quot;&gt;[[#Koz08|Kozloff 2008]]. p. 24.&lt;/ref&gt; First having met in 1994, Castro would later attend Chávez's presidential inauguration,  before they began discussing greater economic links between the two nations. In 2000, Castro and Chávez signed an agreement through which Cuba would send 20,000 medics to Venezuela, in return receiving 53,000 barrels of oil per day at preferential rates; in 2004, this trade was stepped up, with Cuba sending 40,000 medics and Venezuela providing 90,000 barrels a day.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Mar07|Marcano and Tyszka 2007]]. pp. 213&amp;ndash;215.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Koz08|Kozloff 2008]]. pp. 23&amp;ndash;24.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last = Morris
|first = Ruth
|year = 2005
|month = December 18
|url = http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/sun_sentinel/access/943180711.html?dids=943180711:943180711&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;date=Dec+18%2C+2005&amp;author=Ruth+Morris+Havana+Bureau&amp;pub=South+Florida+Sun+-+Sentinel&amp;edition=&amp;startpage=1.A&amp;desc=CUBA%27S+DOCTORS+RESUSCITATE+ECONOMY+AID+MISSIONS+MAKE+MONEY%2C+NOT+JUST+ALLIES
|title = Cuba's Doctors Resuscitate Economy Aid Missions Make Money, Not Just Allies
|publisher=Sun-Sentinel.com
 |accessdate=December 28, 2006
}}&lt;/ref&gt; That same year, Castro initiated Mision Milagro, a joint medical project between Cuba and Venezuela which aimed to provide free eye operations on 300,000 individuals from each nation.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Koz08|Kozloff 2008]]. p. 21.&lt;/ref&gt; The alliance provided a great boost to the Cuban economy, and in May 2005, Castro doubled the minimum wage for 1.6 million workers, raised pensions and delivered new kitchen appliances to the island's poorest residents.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kozloff 2008. p. 24&quot;/&gt; Some economic problems did however remain; during 2004, Castro shut down 118 factories, including steel plants, sugar mills and paper processors to compensate for the crisis due to fuel shortages.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |date=September 30, 2004 |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/3702784.stm |title=Cuba to shut plants to save power |publisher=BBC News  |accessdate=May 20, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Evo Morales]] of [[Bolivia]] has described him as &quot;the grandfather of all Latin American revolutionaries&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|work=Der Spiegel|url=http://www.spiegel.de/international/spiegel/0,1518,434272,00.html|title=Spiegel interview with Bolivia's Evo Morales|date=August 28, 2006|accessdate=August 12, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast to the improved relations between Cuba and a number of leftist Latin American states, in 2004 it broke off diplomatic ties with Panama after centrist President [[Mireya Moscoso]] pardoned four Cuban exiles accused of attempting to assassinate Cuban President Fidel Castro in 2000; diplomatic ties were reinstalled in 2005 following the election of leftist President [[Martín Torrijos]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Cuba and Panama restore relations&quot;&gt;{{cite news |date=August 21, 2005 |url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/4170374.stm|title = Cuba and Panama restore relations|publisher=BBC News |accessdate =May 21, 2006 | first=Stephen | last=Gibbs}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Castro's increasingly good relationship with his Latin American neighbours was accompanied by continuing animosity towards the U.S. government. However, after massive damage caused by [[Hurricane Michelle]] in 2001, Castro successfully proposed a one-time cash purchase of food from the U.S. while declining their government's offer of humanitarian aid.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |date=November 17, 2001 |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/1662346.stm|title = Castro welcomes one-off US trade|publisher=BBC News |accessdate =May 19, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |date=December 16, 2001|url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/1714776.stm|title = US food arrives in Cuba |publisher=BBC News |accessdate =May 19, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; In reaction to the [[September 11 attacks]] in 2001, in which [[Islamism|Islamist]] militants belonging to [[Al Qaeda]] attacked New York City and Washington D.C., Castro expressed solidarity with the United States, condemning the attacks and offering Cuban airports for the emergency diversion of any U.S. planes. He recognized that the attacks would make the U.S. government more aggressive in its foreign policy, which he believed was counter-productive.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 320.&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[File:Fidel Castro 1. Mai 2005 bei Kundgebung.jpg|250px|thumb|left|Castro amid cheering crowds supporting his presidency in 2005.]]

At a summit meeting of sixteen Caribbean countries in 1998, Castro called for regional unity, saying that only strengthened cooperation between Caribbean countries would prevent their domination by rich nations in a global economy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |date=August 21, 1998|url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/156312.stm|title = Castro calls for Caribbean unity|publisher=BBC News |accessdate =May 21, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Caribbean nations have embraced Cuba's Fidel Castro while accusing the US of breaking trade promises. Castro, until recently a regional outcast, has been increasing grants and scholarships to the Caribbean countries, while US aid has dropped 25% over the past five years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |year = 1998|month = August 25|url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/156756.stm|title = Castro finds new friends|publisher=BBC News |accessdate =May 21, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cuba has opened four additional embassies in the [[Caribbean Community]] including: [[Antigua and Barbuda]], Dominica, [[Suriname]], Saint Vincent and the Grenadines. This development makes Cuba the only country to have embassies in all independent countries of the Caribbean Community.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date= March 13, 2006|url = http://www.caribbeannewsnow.com/caribnet/cgi-script/csArticles/articles/000008/000823.htm|title = Cuba opens more Caribbean embassies|publisher=Caribbean Net News|accessdate =May 11, 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Castro was known to be a friend of former Canadian Prime Minister [[Pierre Trudeau]] and was an honorary pall bearer at Trudeau's funeral in October 2000. They had continued their friendship after Trudeau left office until his death. Canada became one of the first [[Americas|American]] allies openly to trade with Cuba. Cuba still has a good relationship with Canada. In 1998, Canadian Prime Minister [[Jean Chrétien]] arrived in Cuba to meet President Castro and highlight their close ties. He is the first Canadian government leader to visit the island since Pierre Trudeau was in Havana in 1976.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|year = 1998|month = April 20|url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/80546.stm|title = Canadian PM visits Fidel in April|publisher=BBC News |accessdate =May 21, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Stepping down: 2006&amp;ndash;2008===
{{Expand section|date=October 2012|Information on Castro's second presidency of the NAM.}}
{{See also|2006 Cuban transfer of presidential duties}}
On July 31, 2006, Castro delegated his duties as President of the [[Council of State of Cuba|Council of State]], President of the [[Council of Ministers of Cuba|Council of Ministers]], First Secretary of the [[Cuban Communist Party]] and the post of [[commander in chief]] of the armed forces to his brother [[Raúl Castro]]. This transfer of duties was described at the time as temporary while Fidel recovered from surgery he underwent due to an &quot;acute intestinal crisis with sustained bleeding&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pbs.org/newshour/bb/latin_america/july-dec06/castro_08-01.html Reaction Mixed to Castro's Turnover of Power]. PBS. August 1, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.juventudrebelde.co.cu/cuba/2011-03-22/my-shoes-are-too-tight/ |title=My Shoes Are Too Tight |author=Castro, Fidel |publisher=Juventud Rebelde |date=March 22, 2011 |accessdate=April 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.cnn.com/2011-03-22/world/cuba.castro.party_1_raul-castro-cuban-people-cuba-plans?_s=PM:WORLD |title=Castro says he resigned as Communist Party chief 5 years ago |publisher=CNN |date=March 22, 2011 |accessdate=April 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of his sickness, Castro was too ill to attend the nationwide commemoration of the 50th anniversary of the ''[[Granma (yacht)|Granma]]'' boat landing on December 2, 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.sky.com/skynews/article/0,,30200-1243432,00.html|title=Casto in Cancer Battle|publisher=Sky News|date=December 8, 2006}}{{dead link|date=September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[File:20070129-Fidelcastro-massforhealthatbogota.jpg|thumb|right|Poster advertising a mass to pray for Castro's health that was posted on a wall in Bogotá, Colombia, in 2007.]]

In February 2007, Raúl announced that Fidel's health was improving and that he was taking part in all important issues facing the government.&lt;ref name=&quot;NewsMax&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://newsmax.com/archives/articles/2007/2/9/220202.shtml Raul Castro Thinks Fidel Improving]&quot;. [[Associated Press]], February 10, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Later that month, Fidel called into ''[[Aló Presidente]]'', a live Venezuelan radio talk show hosted by Hugo Chávez, telling the Venezuelan president that &quot;I am gaining ground. I feel I have more energy, more strength, more time to study&quot;, adding with a chuckle, &quot;I have become a student again.&quot; Later in the conversation, he made reference to the fall of the world stock markets that had occurred earlier in the day and remarked that it was proof of his contention that the world capitalist system was in crisis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| last =Pretel | first =Enrique Andres | date =February 28, 2007 | url =http://www.reuters.com/article/2007/02/28/idUSN27428997 | title =Cuba's Castro says recovering, sounds stronger | publisher=Reuters | accessdate =April 28, 2012
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.granma.cu/espanol/2007/febrero/mier28/conversa.html Transcript in Spanish]; [http://www.juventudrebelde.cu/cuba/2007-02-27/conversacion-telefonica-entre-fidel-castro-y-hugo-chavez-audio/ audio].&lt;/ref&gt; In April, Chávez told the press that Castro was &quot;almost totally recovered&quot; from his illness, and the government announced that he had returned to some of his leadership responsibilities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| last =Pearson| first =Natalie Obiko| year =2007
| month =April 13 | url =http://www.breitbart.com/article.php?id=D8OFU0O80&amp;show_article=1 | title =Venezuela: Ally Castro Recovering | agency=Associated Press | accessdate =April 13, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; On April 21, Castro met with [[Wu Guanzheng]], a member of the [[Politburo Standing Committee of the Communist Party of China|Politburo]] of the [[Chinese Communist Party]] who was visiting Havana, and photographs of the meeting appeared in the Cuban press, illustrating the president's recovery and dispelling rumours of his death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url =http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/6578539.stm| title =Castro resumes official business |publisher=BBC News| accessdate =April 21, 2007 |date=April 21, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; In August, Chávez came to Havana, spending Castro's  birthday with him,&lt;ref&gt;[[#Mar07|Marcano and Tyszka 2007]]. p. 287.&lt;/ref&gt; while another key ally, Evo Morales, came for a visit in September.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Siv08|Sivak 2008]]. p. 52.&lt;/ref&gt;  As a comment on Castro's recovery, U.S. President [[George W. Bush]] said: &quot;One day the good Lord will take Fidel Castro away&quot;. Hearing about this, the atheist Castro ironically replied: &quot;Now I understand why I survived Bush's plans and the plans of other presidents who ordered my assassination: the good Lord protected me.&quot; The quote would subsequently be picked up on by the world's media.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | year =2007 | month =June 28
| url =http://www.reuters.com/article/topNews/idUSN2834938420070629 | title =Bush wishes Cuba's Castro would disappear
| publisher=Reuters | accessdate =July 1, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a letter dated February 18, 2008, Castro announced that he would not accept the positions of President of the Council of State and Commander in Chief at the February 24, 2008 National Assembly meetings,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Castro, Fidel|title=Message from the Commander in Chief|url=http://www.cuba.cu/gobierno/discursos/2008/esp/f180208e.html|work=Diario Granma|publisher=Comité Central del Partido Comunista de Cuba|date=February 18, 2008|accessdate=May 20, 2011}}{{es icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; effectively announcing his retirement from official public life.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date= February 18, 2008|url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/7252109.stm|title = Fidel Castro announces retirement|publisher=BBC News |accessdate =February 18, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date= February 18, 2008|url = http://africa.reuters.com/top/news/usnBAN929511.html|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20090103110711/http://africa.reuters.com/top/news/usnBAN929511.html|archivedate = January 3, 2009|title = Fidel Castro stepping down as Cuba's leader|publisher=Reuters|accessdate =February 18, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |date =February 19, 2008 |url= http://www.miamiherald.com/news/americas/story/424291.html|title = Fidel Castro will step down after 50 years at Cuba's helm |publisher=miamiherald.com|accessdate=February 19, 2008}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Published online by the government, in his letter Castro stated that his health was a primary reason for his decision, remarking that &quot;It would betray my conscience to take up a responsibility that requires mobility and total devotion, that I am not in a physical condition to offer&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |date =February 19, 2008 |url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/7252109.stm|title = Fidel Castro announces retirement |publisher=BBC News |accessdate=February 19, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; On February 24, 2008, the [[National Assembly of People's Power]] unanimously chose his brother Raúl to be Fidel's successor as [[President of Cuba]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC&quot;&gt;{{cite news
| title = Raul Castro named Cuban president
| url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/7261204.stm
|work=BBC
| date = February 24, 2008
| accessdate =February 24, 2008
| quote = Raul, 76, has in effect been president since and the National Assembly vote was seen as formalizing his position.
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Describing his brother as &quot;not substitutable&quot;, Raúl proposed that Fidel continue to be consulted on matters of great importance, such as defense, foreign policy and &quot;the socioeconomic development of the country&quot; during his first presidential speech, a motion that was immediately and unanimously approved by the 597 members of the National Assembly.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ipsnews.net/news.asp?idnews=41321 |title=CUBA: Raúl Shares His Seat with Fidel |publisher=Ipsnews.net |accessdate=March 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Later years and retirement: 2008–present==
Following his retirement from the presidency, Castro's health began to deteriorate, with the octogenarian suffering with an ailment that was widely reported to be [[diverticulitis]] in the international press, an assertion that the Cuban government refused to corroborate.&lt;ref name=&quot;Franks 2012&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://uk.reuters.com/article/2012/08/12/uk-cuba-castro-birthday-idUKBRE87B0HO20120812  |title=Fidel Castro to turn 86, but out of view since June |author=Franks, Jeff |work=Reuters |date=12 August 2012 |accessdate=13 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, he continued to interact with the Cuban people, publishing an opinion column, &quot;Reflections&quot;, in the state newspaper ''Granma'', and making use of a [[Twitter]] account. He also gave the occasional public discussion or lecture, particularly in times of national uncertainty.&lt;ref name=&quot;Franks 2012&quot;/&gt; In January 2009 Castro asked Cubans not to worry about his lack of recent news columns and his failing health, and not to be disturbed by his future death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/centralamericaandthecaribbean/cuba/4324128/Fidel-Castro-sends-farewell-message-to-his-people.html|title=Fidel Castro sends farewell message to his people |last=Govan|first=Fiona|date=January 23, 2009|work=The Daily Telegraph |location=London |accessdate=January 28, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; He still continued to meet with foreign leaders and dignitaries, and that month photographs were released of Castro's meeting with Argentine president [[Cristina Fernández]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC 23Jan9&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/7846670.stm|title=Fidel contemplates his mortality |date=January 23, 2009|publisher=BBC |accessdate=January 28, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Castro in Brasilia, 2003.jpeg|thumb|left|In old age, Castro continued his involvement with politics and international affairs.]]

In July 2010, he made his first public appearance since falling ill, greeting workers at a science center and giving a television interview to the Cuban program ''[[Mesa Redonda Internacional|Mesa Redonda]]'' in which he discussed tensions between the United States, [[Iran]] and [[North Korea]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/world/americas/fidel-castro-makes-rare-tv-appearance/article1637774/ &quot;Fidel Castro makes rare TV appearance&quot;], ''Globe and Mail'', July 12, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;
On August 7, 2010, Castro gave his first speech to the [[National Assembly of People's Power|Cuban National Assembly]] in four years. He addressed the body for ten minutes on international affairs and then remained to listen and respond to questions for a further 70 minutes. In his comments he urged the United States not to go to war with Iran or North Korea and warning about the dangers of a [[nuclear holocaust]]. When asked whether Castro may be re-entering government, Culture minister [[Abel Prieto]] told the [[BBC]], &quot;I think that he has always been in Cuba's political life but he is not in the government...He has been very careful about that. His big battle is international affairs.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/mobile/world-latin-america-10903048 &quot;Fidel Castro addresses parliament after four-year gap&quot;], BBC News, August 7, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usatoday.com/news/world/2010-08-06-castro-parliament_N.htm &quot;Fidel Castro to attend session of Cuba parliament&quot;]. The Associated Press. 8/7/2010&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/08/07/AR2010080702549.html |title=Fidel Castro warns of nuclear risk in 1st speech to Cuban parliament in 4 years |work=The Washington Post  |date=August 8, 2010 |accessdate=March 16, 2011 |first=Will |last=Weissert}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2010/08/08/world/americas/08cuba.html &quot;Fidel Castro Addresses Parliament on Iran Issue&quot;]. Nytimes.com (2010-08-07). Retrieved on September 25, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

On April 19, 2011, Castro resigned from the [[Communist Party of Cuba|Communist Party]] central committee,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.euronews.net/2011/04/19/fidel-quits-communist-party-leadership-as-cuba-looks-to-reform/|title=Fidel quits Communist Party leadership as Cuba looks to reform|publisher=Euronews.net |date=April 19, 2011 |accessdate=April 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; thus stepping down as leader of the party. Raúl Castro was selected as his successor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://uk.reuters.com/article/2011/04/19/uk-cuba-congress-idUKTRE73I3GQ20110419|title=Cuban communists opt for old guard to lead reforms|agency=Reuters  |date=April 19, 2011 |accessdate=April 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Now without any official role in the country's government, he took on the role of an [[elder statesman]]. In March 2012, [[Pope Benedict XVI]] visited Cuba for three days, during which time he briefly met with Castro at Havana's Vatican embassy despite the Pope's vocal opposition to the Cuban government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://uk.reuters.com/article/2012/03/28/uk-pope-cuba-fidel-idUKBRE82R14Q20120328 |title=Pope meets Cuba's Fidel Castro, slams US embargo |author=Pullella, Philip and Franks, Jeff |work=Reuters |date=29 March 2012 |accessdate=13 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Franks 2012&quot;/&gt; Later that year it was revealed that along with his friend Hugo Chávez, Castro had played a significant behind-the-scenes role in orchestrating peace talks between the Colombian government and the far left [[Revolutionary Armed Forces of Columbia|FARC]] guerilla movement that took place in October 2012 in [[Oslo]], [[Norway]], in the hope of putting a stop to the conflict that had raged in the country since 1964.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2012/oct/13/fidel-castro-hugo-chavez-colombia-farc-talks |title=Fidel Castro and Hugo Chávez played role in Colombia's peace talks with Farc |author=Beaumont, Peter |work=The Observer |date=13 October 2012 |accessdate=13 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Politics==
{{Main|Politics of Fidel Castro|Castroism}}
[[File:Marx Engels Lenin.svg|thumb|200px|Castro is a Marxist-Leninist, following the theories about the nature of society put forward by Marx, Engels and Lenin (left to right).]]
Castro has proclaimed himself to be &quot;a Socialist, a [[Marxism|Marxist]], and a [[Leninism|Leninist]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. p. 157.&lt;/ref&gt; As a socialist, Castro believes in converting Cuba, and the wider world, from a [[capitalism|capitalist system]] in which business and industry is owned by private individuals and organizations, into a [[Socialism (Marxism)|socialist system]] in which all business and industry are owned by the state on behalf of the populace. In the former, there is a class divide between the wealthy classes who control the [[means of production]] (i.e. the factories, farms, media etc) and the poorer working classes who labor on them, whilst in the latter, socialists argue, this class divide would be obliterated as society becomes more egalitarian.

Marxism is the sociopolitical theory developed by German sociologists [[Karl Marx]] and [[Friedrich Engels]] in the mid-19th century. It holds as its foundation the idea of class struggle; that society mainly changes and progresses as one socioeconomic class takes power from another. Thus Marxists believe that capitalism replaced [[feudalism]] in the Early Modern period as the wealthy industrial class, or [[bourgeoisie]], took political and economic power from the traditional land-owning class, the aristocracy and monarchy. In the same process, Marxists predict that socialism will replace capitalism as the industrial working class, or [[proletariat]], seize power from the bourgeoisie through revolutionary action. In this way, Marxism is believed by its supporters to provide a scientific explanation for why socialism should, and will, replace capitalism in human society.

Leninism refers to the theories put forward by Russian revolutionary, political theorist and politician [[Vladimir Lenin]], the leader of the [[Bolshevik Party]] who was a leading figure in the [[October Revolution]] that overthrew the Russian capitalist government and replaced it with a socialist alternative in 1917. Taking Marxism as its basis, Leninism revolves around putting forward ideas for how to convert a capitalist state into a socialist one. Castro used Leninist thought as a model upon which to convert the Cuban state and society into a socialist form.

Castro is also a keen proponent of Cuban nationalism, with historian [[Richard Gott]] remarking that one of the keys to Castro's success was in his ability to utilize the &quot;twin themes of socialism and nationalism&quot; and keep them &quot;endlessly in play.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Got04|Gott 2004]]. p. 149.&lt;/ref&gt; Castro describes Marx and the Cuban nationalist [[José Martí]] (1853–1895) as his most significant political influences,&lt;ref&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. pp. 101&amp;ndash;102.&lt;/ref&gt; although Gott believed that ultimately Martí remained more important than Marx in Castro's politics.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Got04|Gott 2004]]. p. 149.&lt;/ref&gt; Castro described Martí's political ideas as &quot;a philosophy of independence and an exceptional humanistic philosophy&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. p. 147.&lt;/ref&gt; Castro has taken a relatively [[social conservatism|socially conservative]] stance on many issues, opposing alcohol, drugs, gambling and prostitution, which he viewed as [[moral evil]]s. Instead he has advocated hard work, family values, integrity and self-discipline.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 200.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal and public life==
In his biography of the Cuban leader, entitled ''[[The Real Fidel Castro]]'' (2003), the Briton Leycester Coltman described the Cuban as being &quot;fiercely hard-working, dedicated[,] loyal... generous and magnanimous&quot; but also noted that he could be &quot;vindictive and unforgiving&quot; at times. He went on to note that Castro &quot;always had a keen sense of humor and could laugh at himself&quot; but could equally be &quot;a bad loser&quot; who would act with &quot;ferocious rage if he thought that he was being humiliated.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, another of Castro's biographers, [[Peter Bourne]], noted that Castro &quot;suffers fools poorly&quot; and that in his younger years he was &quot;intolerant&quot; of those who did not share his views for Cuba's future.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 178.&lt;/ref&gt; He also noted that Castro liked to socialize and meet with ordinary citizens, both in Cuba and abroad, but took a particularly paternal attitude toward his own people, treating them as if &quot;they were a part of his own giant family.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 273.&lt;/ref&gt; In her book, ''[[Red Heat: Conspiracy, Murder and the Cold War in the Caribbean]]'' (2011), the British historian Alex Von Tunzelmann commented that &quot;though ruthless, [Castro] was a patriot, a man with a profound sense that it was his mission to save the Cuban people&quot;, contrasting him strongly to his Haitian contemporary [[François Duvalier]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Von11|Von Tunzelmann 2011]]. p. 94.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Castro was known for his busy working hours, often only going to bed at 3 am or 4 am in the morning.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 1997 219&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 219.&lt;/ref&gt; When meeting with foreign diplomats, he liked to meet them in these early hours, a time when they would be tired and he could gain the upper hand.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt; He described [[Ernest Hemingway]] as his favorite writer,&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 204.&lt;/ref&gt; and enjoyed reading but was uninterested in music. A sports fan, he also spent much of his time trying to keep fit, undertaking regular exercise.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 224&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 224.&lt;/ref&gt; He took a great interest in [[gastronomy]], as well as wine and whisky, and as Cuban leader was known to wander into his kitchen to discuss ingredients and cookery with his chefs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 224&quot;/&gt; Ever since childhood, Castro had a love of weapons, in particular guns, and would carry a pistol with him much of the time, even as President.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt; He also expressed his preference for life in the countryside rather than in the city.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 5.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Fidel Castro's religious beliefs]] have been a matter of some debate. Castro was [[baptized]] and raised a Roman Catholic as a child but did not practice as one. He has publicly stated that &quot;I have never been a believer&quot;, and has total conviction that there is only one life.&lt;ref&gt;{{YouTube|WLUcOqeoKck|Comandante – Fidel Castro &amp; Oliver Stone}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Pope John XXIII]] [[excommunication|excommunicated]] Castro in 1962 after Castro suppressed Catholic institutions in Cuba.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pope Excommunicates Castro&quot;&gt;{{cite news|date= January 3, 1962|title= Pope Excommunicates Castro|publisher=Chronicle Telegram|url = http://www.nytimes.com/library/world/012698pope-cuba-rdp.html|id= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Castro has publicly criticized what he sees as elements of the [[Bible]] that have been used to justify the oppression of both women and people of African descent throughout history.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. pp. 40–41.&lt;/ref&gt; In his 2009 spoken autobiography, Castro said that Christianity exhibited &quot;a group of very humane precepts&quot; which gave the world &quot;ethical values&quot; and a &quot;sense of social justice&quot;, before relating that &quot;If people call me Christian, not from the standpoint of religion but from the standpoint of social vision, I declare that I am a Christian.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Cas09|Castro and Ramonet 2009]]. p. 156.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Family and friends===
Castro's biographer [[Robert E. Quirk]] noted that throughout his life, the Cuban leader had been &quot;unable to form a lasting sexual relationship with any female.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Qui93|Quirk 1993]]. p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt;
By his first wife [[Mirta Díaz-Balart]], whom he married on October 11, 1948, Castro has a son named Fidel Ángel &quot;Fidelito&quot; Castro Díaz-Balart, born on September 1, 1949. Díaz-Balart and Castro were divorced in 1955, and she remarried Emilio Núñez Blanco. After a spell in [[Madrid]], Díaz-Balart reportedly returned to Havana to live with Fidelito and his family.&lt;ref&gt;Ann Louise Bardach: ''Cuba Confidential''. p. 67. &quot;One knowledgeable source claims that Mirta returned to Cuba in early 2002 and is now living with Fidelito and his family.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Fidelito grew up in Cuba; for a time, he ran Cuba's atomic-energy commission before being removed from the post by his father.&lt;ref name=&quot;anderson&quot;&gt;Jon Lee Anderson, &quot;Castro's Last Battle: Can the revolution outlive its leader?&quot; The New Yorker, July 31, 2006. 51.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Fidel has five other sons by his second wife, Dalia Soto del Valle: Antonio, Alejandro, Alexis, Alexander &quot;Alex&quot; and Ángel Castro Soto del Valle.&lt;ref name=&quot;anderson&quot;/&gt; While Fidel was married to Mirta, he had an affair with Natalia &quot;Naty&quot; Revuelta Clews, born in Havana in 1925 and married to Orlando Fernández, resulting in a daughter named [[Alina Fernández|Alina Fernández-Revuelta]].&lt;ref name=&quot;anderson&quot;/&gt; Alina left Cuba in 1993, disguised as a Spanish tourist,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.canada.com/topics/news/world/story.html?id=2ef037b4-5f82-4283-b1fb-2cc9e2442977 |title=Cuba's first family not immune to political rift |accessdate=August 10, 2006 |last=Boadle |first=Anthony |date=August 8, 2006 |publisher=Reuters}}&lt;/ref&gt; and sought asylum in the United States. She has been critical of her father's policies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Fernandez |first=Alina |title=Castro's Daughter, An Exile's Memoir of Cuba |publisher=St. Martin's Press |year=1997 |isbn=031219308}}&lt;/ref&gt; By an unnamed woman he had another son, Jorge Ángel Castro. Fidel has another daughter, Francisca Pupo (born 1953) the result of a one night affair. Pupo and her husband now live in Miami.&lt;ref name=&quot;canf.org&quot;&gt;Roberto Duarte [http://web.archive.org/web/20061210012059/http://www.canf.org/es/ENSAYOS/2003-dic-09-vida_secreta_del_tirano_castro.htm VIDA SECRETA DEL TIRANO CASTRO]. CANF.org. October 29, 2003
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cuba confidential: Love and Vengeance in Miami and Havana By Ann Louise Bardach; Random House, Inc., 2002; ISBN 978-0-375-50489-1&lt;/ref&gt;

His sister [[Juanita Castro]] has been living in the United States since the early 1960s. When she went into exile, she said &quot;I cannot longer remain indifferent to what is happening in my country. My brothers Fidel and Raúl have made it an enormous prison surrounded by water. The people are nailed to a cross of torment imposed by international Communism.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,871241-1,00.html| title=The Bitter Family (page 1 of 2)|work=Time| date=July 10, 1964| accessdate=February 19, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While in power, Castro's two closest male friends were the former Mayor of Havana Pepin Naranjo and his own personal physician, René Vallejo.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986. p. 201&quot;/&gt; From 1980 until his death in 1995, Naranjo headed Castro's team of advisors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.spokesman.com/stories/1995/dec/26/castro-adviser-66-dies-of-heart-attack/| title=Castro Adviser, 66, Dies Of Heart Attack| work=The Spokesman Review| date=December 26, 1995| accessdate=May 31, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also had a deep friendship with fellow revolutionary [[Celia Sanchez]], who accompanied him almost everywhere during the 1960s, and controlled almost all access to the leader.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. pp. 200&amp;ndash;201.&lt;/ref&gt;  During the mid to late 1960s, Vallejo and Sanchez became his two closest companions.&lt;ref name=vallechez&gt;The Socialist Register 1989, NOTES ON THE CUBAN REVOLUTION, Saul Landau, pg. 296&lt;/ref&gt; Vallejo, who served as his personal physician since 1958,&lt;ref name=vallechez /&gt; died in 1969.&lt;ref name=vallechez /&gt; Sanchez died in 1982.&lt;ref name=vallechez /&gt; Castro was also good friends with the Colombian poet [[Gabriel García Márquez]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 299.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Public image===
[[File:Castro sign.jpg|thumb|Cuban propaganda poster proclaiming a quote from Castro: &quot;Luchar contra lo imposible y vencer&quot; (&quot;Fight against the impossible and win&quot;)]]
For 37 years, Castro publicly wore nothing but olive-green military fatigues, emphasizing his role as the perpetual revolutionary, but in a 1994 visit to the [[Ibero-American Conference]] in [[Cartagena, Spain|Cartagena]], surprised assembled dignitaries by appearing in a ''[[guayabera]]''. Several months later he appeared in [[Paris]] wearing a dark civilian suit.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. pp. 303&amp;ndash;304.&lt;/ref&gt; Although mostly seen in military attire, since then his personal tailor, Merel [[Van 't Wout]], convinced him to occasionally change to a business suit.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://secure-wildcat.arizona.edu//papers/old-wildcats/spring95/February/February10, 1995/01_5_m.html |title=In brief |accessdate=August 12, 2006 |date=February 10, 1995 |publisher=Arizona Daily Wildcat}} {{Dead link|date=November 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Within Cuba, Castro is often nicknamed  &quot;''El Caballo''&quot;, meaning &quot;The Horse&quot;, a label that was first attributed to Cuban entertainer [[Benny Moré]], who on hearing Castro passing in the Havana night with his entourage, shouted out &quot;Here comes the horse!&quot; The name itself is an allusion to Castro's well known womanizing during the 1950s and early 1960s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 1997 219&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Got04|Gott 2004]]. p. 175.&lt;/ref&gt; During this period, Castro himself was widely recognized as a [[sex symbol]] within Cuba, and a minor sensation was caused when footage was publicly broadcast showing that he had skinny legs, something widely considered an unattractive trait in Cuba.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bourne 1986. p. 201&quot;&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 201.&lt;/ref&gt;

Large throngs of people gathered to cheer at Castro's fiery speeches, which typically lasted for hours. Many details of Castro's private life, particularly involving his family members, are scarce as the media is forbidden to mention them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Admservice |url=http://www.latinamericanstudies.org/fidel/castro-family.htm |title=Fidel Castro's Family |publisher=Latinamericanstudies.org |date=October 8, 2000 |accessdate=January 13, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike a number of other Soviet-era communist leaders, Castro's government did not construct a [[cult of personality]] around him.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Got04|Gott 2004]]. p. 325.&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, the [[BBC]] reported that by 2006, Castro's image could frequently be found in Cuban stores, classrooms, taxicabs, and on national television.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/4779529.stm |title=Americas &amp;#124; Ailing Castro still dominates Cuba |publisher=BBC News  |date=August 11, 2006 |accessdate=January 13, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Historian and journalist [[Richard Gott]] considered Castro to be &quot;one of the most extraordinary political figures of the twentieth century&quot;, noting that he had become a &quot;world hero in the mould of [[Giuseppe Garibaldi|Garibaldi]]&quot; to people throughout the developing world.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Got04|Gott 2004]]. p. 148.&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, Bourne noted that Castro had established himself as &quot;an influential world leader who is listened to with great respect&quot;, having grown into a &quot;statesmanlike role&quot; that has earned him respect from people of all political persuasions across the developing world. &lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 302.&lt;/ref&gt; Views of Castro differed in other parts of the world; in the United States, particularly in Florida, Castro was viewed with &quot;passion and hatred&quot;, and politicians hoping to get elected in that state would regularly criticise him in order to win votes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 290&quot;&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 290.&lt;/ref&gt; In Canada and Western Europe, Castro was viewed no differently to other Marxist-Leninist leaders.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coltman 2003. p. 290&quot;/&gt;

==Recognition and legacy==
{{Main|List of awards and honours bestowed upon Fidel Castro}}
Various leftist governments across the world have granted Castro awards for his work in promoting socialism and providing international humanitarian aid. The [[Juche]] government of [[North Korea]] for instance awarded him &quot;the Golden Medal (Hammer and Sickle) and the First Class Order of the National Flag&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://granmai.co.cu/ingles/2006/diciembre/mar12/51conde.html|title=Democratic Korea decorates President Fidel Castro|publisher=[[Granma (newspaper)|Granma]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; whilst [[Muammar Gaddafi]]'s [[Arab socialism|Arab socialist]] government of Libya bestowed upon him a &quot;Libyan human rights award&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url =http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/149414.stm|title =Libyan human rights prize awarded to Fidel Castro of Cuba|publisher=BBC News |accessdate =June 13, 2006|date=August 11, 1998}}&lt;/ref&gt; On a visit to South Africa in 1998 he was warmly received by President Nelson Mandela.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |year = 1998|month = September 4|url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/164687.stm|title = Castro's state visit to South Africa|publisher=BBC News |accessdate =May 21, 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; President Mandela gave Castro South Africa's highest civilian award for foreigners, the Order of Good Hope.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |year = 1998|month = September 6|url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/165566.stm|title = Castro ends state-visit to South Africa|publisher=BBC News |accessdate =May 21, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In [[Harlem]], Castro is seen by many as an icon because of his historic visit with [[Malcolm X]] in 1960 at the [[Hotel Theresa]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.columbia.edu/cu/ccbh/mxp/ministermalcolm.html|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070716112121/http://www.columbia.edu/cu/ccbh/mxp/ministermalcolm.html|archivedate = September 16, 2007|title = Malcolm X Chronology|publisher=Columbia University}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After the fall of [[apartheid]] and the independence of [[Namibia]], the country's capital, the city of [[Windhoek]], renamed many streets, including one that now bears the name of Fidel Castro Street.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.map-of-namibia.com/windhoek-streetrenames.html Windhoek Streets Renamed]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tripwolf.com/en/guide/show/687895/Namibia/Windhoek-and-Central-Namibia/Windhoek/Fidel-Castro-Street ''Fidel Castro Street'' travel guide]&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote|What will be his legacy? ... The answers to those questions are mixed. Castro first and foremost is and always has been a committed [[egalitarianism|egalitarian]]. He despises any system in which one class or group of people lives much better than another. He wanted a system that provided the basic needs to all—enough to eat, health care, adequate housing and education. The [[authoritarianism|authoritarian]] nature of the Cuban Revolution stems largely from his commitment to that goal. Castro was convinced that he was right, and that his system was for the good of the people. Thus, anyone who stood against the revolution stood also against the Cuban people and that, in Castro’s eyes, was simply unacceptable. There is, then, very little in the way of individual freedoms – especially freedom of expression and assembly. And there are [[political prisoners]] ... (However) before 1959, Cuba was considered as something of a [[banana republic]]. It played virtually no role in the international arena. But under Castro, it has played a prominent role, indeed at times a role that often resembled that of a world power. Wherever Castro has gone in the [[Western Hemisphere|hemisphere]] over the past few years, he has been received with warm applause. Why? Because he stood up to the United States, has defied Washington and gone his own way. That is something virtually all [[Latin Americans]] respect and admire.| [[Wayne S. Smith]], [[US Interests Section in Havana]] Chief from 1979 to 1982, in 2007&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tompaine.com/articles/2007/02/02/castros_legacy.php Castro's Legacy] by [[Wayne S. Smith]], [[US Interests Section in Havana]] Chief from 1979 to 1982, February 02, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Controversy and criticism==
{{See also|Human rights in Cuba|Censorship in Cuba}}
===Description as a dictator===
{{Quote box|width=25em|align=right|bgcolor=#ACE1AF|quote=&quot;Within Cuba, Fidel's domination of every aspect of the government and the society remains total. His personal needs for absolute control seems to have changed little over the years. He remains committed to a disciplined society in which he is still determined to remake the Cuban national character, creating work-orientated, socially concerned individuals... He wants to increase people's standard of living, the availability of material goods, and to import the latest technology. But the economic realities, despite rapid dramatic growth in the gross national product, severely limit what Cuba can buy on the world market.&quot;|source=— [[Peter Bourne]], Castro Biographer, 1986 &lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 302.&lt;/ref&gt; }}
Many observers refer to Castro as a [[dictator]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Sondrol&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1017/S0022216X00015868|title=Totalitarian and Authoritarian Dictators: A Comparison of Fidel Castro and Alfredo Stroessner |author=Paul C. Sondrol|journal=Journal of Latin American Studies|volume=23|issue=03|pages=599–620|year=1991|ref=harv|jstor=157386}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mallin&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Covering Castro: rise and decline of Cuba's communist dictator|author=Jay Mallin|publisher=Transaction Publishers|isbn=978-1-56000-156-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;idiotsguide&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=The complete idiot's guide to Latino history and culture|author=D. H. Figueredo|isbn=0-02-864360-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CBS Tampa CW44 1010 SPORTS&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://tampa.cbslocal.com/2012/04/07/miami-marlins-manager-apologizes-for-saying-he-loves-fidel-castro|title=Miami Marlins Manager Apologizes For Saying He ‘Loves’ Fidel Castro|work=CW44 1010 SPORTS-CBS Tampa/AP|location=Tampa, FL|date=April 7, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;dailymail&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-516539/Farewell-Fidel-The-man-nearly-started-World-War-III.html|title=Farewell Fidel: The man who nearly started World War III|work=Daily Mail |location=London  | date=February 20, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;timesonline&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/us_and_americas/article3399819.ece|title=Fidel Castro bows to illness and age as he quits centre stage after 50 years – Times Online|work=The Times |location=London |accessdate=April 22, 2009|last=Catan|first=Thomas| date=February 20, 2008}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;fade-out&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2008/feb/24/fidels-fade-out/|title=Fidel's fade-out}}&lt;/ref&gt; and to his regime as the longest to-date in modern Latin American history.&lt;ref name=&quot;idiotsguide&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;dailymail&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;timesonline&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;fade-out&quot;/&gt; Although considering Castro to be genuinely well-intentioned, biographer [[Peter Bourne]] noted that in Cuba, political power was &quot;completely invested&quot; in Castro.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 263.&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, he remarked that &quot;[r]arely if ever have a country and a people been so totally under the domination of the personality of one man.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bou86|Bourne 1986]]. p. 295.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Castro publicly refuted allegations that he was a dictator and repeatedly told foreign journalists that under his government, Cuba was more democratic than the [[liberal democracy|liberal democracies]] in the West, with greater consultation of the populace. He repeatedly emphasized that constitutionally, he held less political power than most heads of state, including that of the U.S. president, although critics nonetheless argued that he held an enormous amount of unofficial influence over the country.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 292.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Allegations of human rights abuses===
The [[Human Rights Watch]] organization has suggested that Castro constructed a &quot;repressive machinery&quot; which &quot;continues to deprive Cubans of their basic rights&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;HRW-Castro&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Cuba: Fidel Castro's Abusive Machinery Remains Intact|publisher=Human Rights Watch|url=http://www.hrw.org/en/news/2008/02/18/cuba-fidel-castro-s-abusive-machinery-remains-intact|date=February 18, 2008|accessdate=October 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Castro has publicly defended his government from such accusations, using the &quot;standard Marxist answers&quot; to such criticisms; that the state must limit the freedoms of individuals in order to protect the rights of the collective populace, such as the right to employment, education and health care.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Col03|Coltman 2003]]. p. 247.&lt;/ref&gt;

Castro has also been criticized for allegedly ordering the execution of political prisoners.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amnesty.org/en/region/cuba Amnesty International reports regarding Cuba]&lt;/ref&gt; Various estimates have been made to ascertain the number of political executions carried out on behalf of the Cuban government in Cuba since the revolution.  According to Amnesty International, official death sentences from 1959 to 1987 numbered 237, of which all but 21 were actually carried out.&lt;ref&gt;''When the State Kills: the death penalty v. human rights'', Amnesty International Publications, 1989&lt;/ref&gt; Estimates for the total number political executions range from 4,000 to 33,000.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.longitudebooks.com/find/p/7230/mcms.html Cuba or the Pursuit of Freedom Hugh Thomas]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hawaii.edu/powerkills/SOD.TAB15.1B.GIF Power Kills] R.J. Rummel&lt;/ref&gt;

The Cuban Government justified such measures on the grounds that the application of the death penalty in Cuba against war criminals and others followed the same procedure as that seen in the trials by the Allies in the Nuremberg trials.&lt;ref&gt;Raul Gomez Treto, &quot;Thirty Years of Cuban Revolutionary Penal Law&quot;, ''Latin American Perspectives'', Vol. 18, No. 2, Spring, 1991, pp. 114-125&lt;/ref&gt;

===Allegations of corruption===
In their book, ''Corruption in Cuba'', Sergio Diaz-Briquets and Jorge F. Pérez-López Servando state that Castro &quot;institutionalized&quot; corruption and that &quot;Castro's [[state corporatism|state-run monopolies]], [[cronyism]], and lack of accountability have made Cuba one of the world's most corrupt states&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;corruption&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Corruption in Cuba|author=Sergio Diaz-Briquets, Jorge F. Pérez-López}}&lt;/ref&gt; Servando Gonzalez, in ''The Secret Fidel Castro'', calls Castro a &quot;corrupt tyrant&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;secretlife&quot;/&gt;

In 1959, according to Gonzalez, Castro established &quot;Fidel's checking account&quot;, from which he could draw funds as he pleased. The &quot;Comandante's reserves&quot; were created in 1970, from which Castro allegedly &quot;provided gifts to many of his cronies, both home and abroad&quot;. Gonzalez asserts that Comandante's reserves have been linked to [[counterfeit]]ing business empires and [[money laundering]].&lt;ref name=&quot;secretlife&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=The Secret Fidel Castro|author=Servando Gonzalez|isbn=0-9711391-0-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Gonzalez wrote that Cuba's paucity of trade with Switzerland contrasts oddly with the National Office of Cuba's relatively large office in Zurich.&lt;ref name=&quot;secretlife&quot;/&gt; Castro has denied having a bank account abroad with even a dollar in it.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC wealth&quot;/&gt;
[[File:6.6.10CubanParadeUCByLuigiNovi7.jpg|thumb|Signs of protest in the 2010 Cuban Day Parade in [[Union City, New Jersey]], a heavily [[Cuban-American]] community.]]

===Allegations of wealth===
A [[KGB]] officer, Alexei Novikov, stated that Castro's personal life, like the lives of the rest of the Communist elite, is &quot;shrouded under an impenetrable veil of secrecy&quot;. Among other things, he asserted that Castro has a personal guard of more than 9,700 men and three luxurious yachts.&lt;ref name=&quot;secretlife&quot;/&gt;

In 2005, American business and financial magazine ''[[Forbes]]'' listed Castro among the world's richest people, with an estimated net worth of US$550&amp;nbsp;million. The estimates, which the magazine admitted were &quot;more art than science&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;CBS wealth&quot;&gt;[http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2006/05/16/world/main1622957.shtml Castro: I am not rich.] CBS News. Assessed April 24, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; claimed that the Cuban leader's personal wealth was nearly double that of Britain's Queen [[Elizabeth II]], despite anecdotal evidence from diplomats and businessmen that the Cuban leader's personal life was notably austere.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC wealth&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/4985510.stm Castro denies huge fortune claim]. BBC News.&lt;/ref&gt; This assessment was drawn by making economic estimates of the net worth of Cuba's [[state-owned company|state-owned companies]], and used the assumption that Castro had personal economic control.&lt;ref name=&quot;wealth&quot;&gt;[http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/12807201/ Castro blasts Forbes over wealth report.], [[Associated Press]]. Retrieved December 13. 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Forbes'' later increased the estimates to US$900&amp;nbsp;million, adding rumors of large cash stashes in Switzerland.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC wealth&quot;/&gt; The magazine offered no proof of this information,&lt;ref name=&quot;CBS wealth&quot;/&gt; and according to [[CBS News]], Castro's entry on the rich list was notably brief compared to the amount of information provided on other figures.&lt;ref name=&quot;CBS wealth&quot;/&gt; Castro, who had considered suing the magazine, responded that the claims were &quot;lies and [[slander]]&quot;, and that they were part of a US campaign to discredit him.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC wealth&quot;/&gt; He declared: &quot;If they can prove that I have a bank account abroad, with US$900m, with US$1m, US$500,000, US$100,000 or US$1 in it, I will resign.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC wealth&quot;/&gt; President of Cuba's Central Bank, Francisco Soberón, called the claims a &quot;grotesque slander&quot;, asserting that money made from various state owned companies is pumped back into the island's economy, &quot;in sectors including health, education, science, internal security, national defense and solidarity projects with other countries.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;wealth&quot;/&gt;

==Authored works==
&lt;small&gt;'''Fully or partially by Fidel Castro'''&lt;/small&gt;
*''Capitalism in Crisis: Globalization and World Politics Today'', Ocean Press, 2000, ISBN 1-876175-18-4
*''Che: A Memoir'', Ocean Press, 2005, ISBN 1-920888-25-X
*''Cuba at the Crossroads'', Ocean Press, 1997, ISBN 1-875284-94-X
*''[[My Life (Fidel Castro autobiography)|My Life: A Spoken Autobiography]]'', Scribner, 2008, ISBN 1-4165-5328-2
*''Fidel Castro Reader'', Ocean Press, 2007, ISBN 1-920888-88-8
*''Fidel My Early Years'', Ocean Press, 2004, ISBN 1-920888-09-8
*''Fidel &amp; Religion: Conversations with Frei Betto on Marxism &amp; Liberation Theology'', Ocean Press, 2006, ISBN 1-920888-45-4
*''How Far We Slaves Have Come! South Africa and Cuba in Today's World'', by [[Nelson Mandela]] &amp; Fidel Castro, Pathfinder Press, 1991, ISBN 0-87348-729-X
*''Playa Giron: Bay of Pigs: Washington's First Military Defeat in the Americas'', Pathfinder Press, 2001, ISBN 0-87348-925-X
*''Political Portraits: Fidel Castro reflects on famous figures in history'', Ocean Press, 2008, ISBN 1-920888-94-2
*''The Declarations of Havana'', Verso, 2008, ISBN 1-84467-156-9
*''The Prison Letters of Fidel Castro'', Nation Books, 2007, ISBN 1-56025-983-3
*''The Strategic Victory: The War Against Batista in the Sierra Maestra'' ''[La contraofensiva estratégica: De la Sierra Maestra a Santiago de Cuba]'', Ocean Press, 2012 [2011], ISBN 0-9870779-0-2
*''Time Warrior'' ''[Guerrillero del Tiempo]'', by Fidel Castro Ruz and Katiuska Blanco, Abril, 2012
*''War, Racism and Economic Justice: The Global Ravages of Capitalism'', Ocean Press, 2002, ISBN 1-876175-47-8

==See also==
{{Portal|Cuba|Biography|Communism|Politics}}
*[[2006–2008 Cuban transfer of presidential duties]]
*[[Cuban dissident movement]]
*[[Politics of Cuba]]
*''[[638 Ways to Kill Castro]]''
*''[[Fidel (film)]]''
{{clear}}

==References==

===Footnotes===
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

===Bibliography===
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book |title=The United States and the Origins of the Cuban Revolution: An Empire of Liberty in an Age of National Liberation |last=Benjamin |first=Jules R. |year=1992 |publisher=Princeton University Press |location=Princeton, New Jersey |isbn=978-0691025360 |ref=Ben92}}
* {{cite book |title=The Castro Obsession: U.S. Covert Operations Against Cuba, 1959–1965 |last= Bohning |first= Don |year=2005 |publisher=Potomac Books, Inc |location=Washington, D.C. |isbn=978-1574886764 |ref=Boh05}}
* {{cite book |title=Fidel: A Biography of Fidel Castro |last=Bourne |first= Peter G. |authorlink=Peter Bourne |year= 1986 |publisher=Dodd, Mead &amp; Company |location=New York City |isbn=978-0396085188 |ref=Bou86}}
* {{cite book |title=Nothing Can Stop the Course of History |last= Castro |first= Fidel |coauthors=Elliot, Jeffrey M. and [[Mervyn M. Dymally|Dymally, Mervyn M.]] (interviewers) |year=1986 |publisher=Pathfinder Press |location=New York |isbn=0-873486617 |ref=Cas86}}
* {{cite book |title=My Life: A Spoken Autobiography |last= Castro |first= Fidel |coauthors=Ramonet, Ignacio (interviewer) |year=2009 |publisher=Scribner |location=New York |isbn=978-1416562337 |ref=Cas09}}
* {{cite book |title=The Real Fidel Castro |last=Coltman |first= Leycester |authorlink=Arthur Leycester Scott Coltman |year= 2003 |publisher=Yale University Press |location=New Haven and London |isbn=978-0300107609 |ref=Col03}}
* {{cite book |title=Guerrilla Prince: The Untold Story of Fidel Castro |last=Geyer |first=Georgie Anne |year=1991 |publisher=Little, Brown and Company |location=New York City |isbn=978-0316308939 |ref=Gey91}}
* {{cite book |title=Cuba: A New History |last=Gott |first=Richard |authorlink=Richard Gott |year=2004 |publisher=Yale University Press |location=New Haven and London |isbn=978-0300104110 |ref=Got04}}
* {{cite book |title= Hugo Chávez: The Definitive Biography of Venezuela's Controversial President |last1=Marcano |first1=Christina |last2=Barrera Tyszka |first2=Alberto |year= 2007 |publisher= Random House |location=New York |isbn=978-0-679-45666-7 |ref=Mar07}}
* {{cite book |title=Fidel Castro |last=Quirk |first=Robert E. |authorlink=Robert E. Quirk |year=1993 |publisher=W.W. Norton &amp; Company |location=New York and London |isbn=978-0393034851 |ref=Qui93}}
* {{cite book |title=Fidel Castro: A Biography |last=Skierka |first=Volka |year=2006 |publisher=Polity |location=Cambridge |isbn=978-0745640815 |ref=Ski06}}
* {{cite book |title=Red Heat: Conspiracy, Murder, and the Cold War in the Caribbean |last= Von Tunzelmann |first= Alex |year= 2011 |publisher=Henry Holt and Company |location=New York City |isbn=978-0805090673 |ref=Von11}}
* {{cite book |title= Changing Venezuela by Taking Power: The History and Policies of the Chávez Government |last=Wilpert |first=Gregory |year=2007 |publisher=Verso |location=London and New York |isbn=978-1-84467-552-4 |ref=Wil07}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
* {{Cite book |last =Castro |first = Fidel |coauthor= Deborah Shnookal, Pedro Alvarez Tabío|year =2005 |title = Fidel: my early years|url = http://books.google.ca/books?id=8RVaBPGRcUcC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;dq=Fidel%20Castro&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=true|publisher=Ocean Press |isbn= 1-920888-09-8|ref =harv}}
* {{Cite book |last =Castro |first = Fidel |coauthor=Ignacio Ramonet |year =2008 |title =Fidel Castro: my life: a spoken autobiography |url =http://books.google.ca/books?id=Z4H45OczqPYC&amp;lpg=PP1|publisher=Scribner Book Company |isbn=1-4165-5328-2|ref =harv }}
* {{Cite book |last = Fuentes  |first =Norberto|coauthor=  Anna Kushner|year =2010 |title =The Autobiography of Fidel Castro|url =http://books.google.ca/books?id=Fazd9dOLUmUC&amp;lpg=PP1|publisher=Norton &amp; Co |isbn=978-0-393-06899-3 |ref = harv}}
* {{Cite book |last = Geyer |first =Georgie Anne |year =2001 |title = Guerrilla Prince: The Untold Story of Fidel Castro
 |url =http://books.google.ca/books?id=dRhJGLnJjugC&amp;lpg=PP1|publisher=Andrews McMeel |isbn=0-7407-2064-3 |ref = harv}}
* {{Cite book |last =  Halperin|first =Maurice |year =1972 |title =The rise and decline of Fidel Castro: an essay in contemporary history |url =http://books.google.ca/books?id=_B9LOCZuDnQC&amp;lpg=PP1|publisher=University of California Press |isbn=0-520-02182-7 |ref =  harv}}
* {{Cite book |last = Leonard |first = Thomas M|year = 2004|title =Fidel Castro: a biography
  |url =http://books.google.ca/books?id=63sFubdrEVcC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;dq=Fidel%20Castro&amp;pg=PP1|publisher=Greenwood Press |isbn=0-313-32301-1 |ref = harv }}
* {{Cite book |last = Marsico |first =Katie |year =2009 |title = Fidel Castro: Cuban President &amp; Revolutionary
 |url =http://books.google.ca/books?id=XgP9n-E7oTwC&amp;lpg=PP1|publisher=ABDO Pub. Co |isbn=978-1-60453-522-8  |ref = harv}}
* {{Cite book |last = Skierka|first =Volker |year = 2006|title =Fidel Castro: a biography
  |url =http://books.google.ca/books?id=x9-U3FWiW_UC&amp;lpg=PP1 |publisher=Polity |isbn=0-7456-3006-5  |ref = harv }}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Sister project links|author=yes|commons=Fidel Castro|wikt=no|b=no|v=no}}
;By Fidel Castro
*[http://www.cuba.cu/gobierno/discursos/ Archive of Fidel Castro's speeches in 6 languages]
*[http://www.marxists.org/history/cuba/archive/castro/ Fidel Castro History Archive] at [[Marxists Internet Archive]].
*[http://lanic.utexas.edu/la/cb/cuba/castro.html Collection of Castro's speeches]
*[http://www.counterpunch.org/castro09042007.html &quot;We Don't Hope for Favors from the Worst of Empires&quot;]
*[http://www.counterpunch.org/castro04072007.html &quot;Where Have All the Bees Gone?&quot;]
*[http://www.counterpunch.org/castro07312007.html &quot;In Spite of Everything: Reflections on the Pan-American Games&quot;]
*[http://www.counterpunch.org/castro08062007.html &quot;Time for an Alliance of {{sic|Civ|lizations|nolink=1}} Against Empire&quot;]
*[http://www.framingbusiness.net/archives/1107 Fidel Castro in His Own Words]

;Images
*[http://www.life.com/image/first/in-gallery/22998/castro-early-years-19531961 Castro: Early Years (1953–1961)] – slideshow by ''[[Life magazine]]''
*[http://www.life.com/timeline/152/fidel-castro-a-revolutionary-life#index/0 Fidel Castro: A Revolutionary Life] – slideshow by ''[[Life magazine]]''
*[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/in_pictures/4392634.stm Fidel Castro: A Life in Pictures] – slideshow by ''[[BBC News]]''
*[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/gallery/2006/08/01/GA2006080101121.html Fidel Castro's Five Decades in Power] – slideshow by ''[[The Washington Post]]''
*[http://www.nytimes.com/slideshow/2008/02/19/world/0219-CASTRO_index.html Fidel Castro Resigns as President] – slideshow by ''[[New York Times]]''

;About Fidel Castro
*[http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=5598311 Fidel Castro: From Rebel to El Presidente] – timeline by ''[[NPR]]''
*[[Arthur Miller]]: [http://www.thenation.com/doc/20040112/miller A Visit With Castro] by ''[[The Nation (U.S. periodical)|The Nation]]'', December 24, 2003
*BBC Video: [http://news.bbc.co.uk/player/nol/newsid_5200000/newsid_5207200/5207264.stm?bw=nb&amp;mp=rm&amp;news=1&amp;nol_storyid=5207264&amp;bbcws=1 Fidel Castro Visits Boyhood Home of Che Guevara]
*''New York Times'' –- Interactive Feature: [http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2008/02/24/weekinreview/20080224_CASTRO_FEATURE.html#section1 Three Days With Fidel]
*[http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/amex/castro/ PBS American Experience] Interactive site on Fidel Castro with a teacher's guide
*[http://mssa.library.yale.edu/findaids/eadHTML/mssa.ms.0650.html Guide to the Cuban Revolution Collection, Manuscripts and Archives], [[Yale University Library]]
*[http://library.duke.edu/digitalcollections/stryker/ Deena Stryker Photographs of Cuba, 1963–1964, Duke University Libraries Digital Collections]
* NPR Audio: [http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=6083227 Cuba's Castro an Inspiration, Not a Role Model] by Tom Gjelten, September 15, 2006
*''The Guardian:'' [http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2006/aug/12/comment.cuba &quot;The Fidel I Think I Know&quot;] by [[Gabriel García Márquez]], August 12, 2006
*''Washington Post:'' [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/02/21/AR2008022102788.html Fidel Castro Will Always Lead Cuba, Locals Say] February 22, 2008
*[http://www.tompaine.com/articles/2007/02/02/castros_legacy.php Castro's Legacy] by [[Wayne S. Smith]], [[US Interests Section in Havana]] Chief from 1979 to 1982

{{s-start}}
{{s-ppo}}
{{s-new|office}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[First Secretary of the Communist Party of Cuba]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;Incapacitated in 2006&lt;/small&gt;|years=1961–2011}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Raúl Castro]]}}
|-
{{s-off}}
{{s-bef|before=[[José Miró Cardona]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Prime Minister of Cuba]]|years=1959–1976}}
{{s-non|reason=Position abolished}}
|-
{{s-bef|before=[[Osvaldo Dorticós Torrado]]|as=[[President of Cuba]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[President of the Council of State of Cuba]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;Incapacitated in 2006&lt;/small&gt;|years=1976–2008}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Raúl Castro]]|rows=2}}
|-
{{s-bef|before=Himself|as=Prime Minister}}
{{s-ttl|title=President of the [[Council of Ministers of Cuba]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;Incapacitated in 2006&lt;/small&gt;|years=1976–2008}}
|-
{{s-mil}}
{{s-new|office}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Military of Cuba|Commander-in-Chief of the Revolutionary Armed Forces]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;Incapacitated in 2006&lt;/small&gt;|years=1959–2008}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Raúl Castro]]}}
|-
{{s-dip}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Junius Richard Jayewardene]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Non-Aligned Movement|Secretary-General of the Non-Aligned Movement]]|years=1979–1983}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Abdullah Ahmad Badawi]]}}
|-
{{s-bef|before=[[Neelam Sanjiva Reddy]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Non-Aligned Movement|Secretary-General of the Non-Aligned Movement]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;Incapacitated in 2006&lt;/small&gt;|years=2005–2008}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Raúl Castro]]}}
{{s-end}}

{{PCCFirstSecs}}
{{CubanPres}}
{{CubanPMs}}
{{Cuba topics}}
{{NAMSecretary-General}}
{{Fall of Communism}}
{{Cold War}}
{{Cold War figures}}

{{Authority control|PND=118519654|LCCN=n/80/39693|VIAF=102325430|TSURL=viaf/102325430}}

{{Persondata
|NAME=Castro, Fidel
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=Fidel Alejandro Castro Ruz
|SHORT DESCRIPTION=[[President of Cuba|President]] of [[Cuba]]
|DATE OF BIRTH=August 13, 1926
|PLACE OF BIRTH=[[Birán]], [[Holguín Province]], Cuba
|DATE OF DEATH=
|PLACE OF DEATH=
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Castro, Fidel}}
[[Category:1926 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Anti-fascists]]
[[Category:Attempted assassination survivors]]
[[Category:Chevaliers of the Order of Merit]]
[[Category:Cold War leaders]]
[[Category:Collars of the Order of the Aztec Eagle]]
[[Category:Communist rulers]]
[[Category:Cuban communists]]
[[Category:Anti-Revisionists]]
[[Category:Communist Party of Cuba politicians]]
[[Category:Cuba–United States relations]]
[[Category:Cuban guerrillas]]
[[Category:Cuban lawyers]]
[[Category:Cuban people of Canarian descent]]
[[Category:Cuban people of Galician descent]]
[[Category:Cuban revolutionaries]]
[[Category:Cuban soldiers]]
[[Category:Fidel Castro|*]]
[[Category:Fidel Castro family]]
[[Category:First Secretaries of the Communist Party of Cuba]]
[[Category:Foreign Heroes of the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:Government ministers of Cuba]]
[[Category:Grand Crosses of the Order of Good Hope]]
[[Category:Grand Crosses of the Order of Polonia Restituta]]
[[Category:Grand Crosses of the Order of the Star of Romania]]
[[Category:Grand Crosses of the Order of the White Lion]]
[[Category:International opponents of apartheid in South Africa]]
[[Category:Leaders who took power by coup]]
[[Category:Lenin Peace Prize recipients]]
[[Category:Marxist writers]]
[[Category:People excommunicated by the Roman Catholic Church]]
[[Category:People from Holguín Province]]
[[Category:Presidents of Cuba]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Karl Marx]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Klement Gottwald]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Lenin, three times]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Prince Yaroslav the Wise]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of the Crown of the Realm]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of the October Revolution]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Merit (Jamaica)]]
[[Category:Order of the Quetzal]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order Of The National Flag 1st Class (North Korea)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Courage (Libya)]]

[[af:Fidel Castro]]
[[ang:Fidel Castro]]
[[ar:فيدل كاسترو]]
[[an:Fidel Castro]]
[[ast:Fidel Castro]]
[[az:Fidel Kastro]]
[[bn:ফিদেল কাস্ত্রো]]
[[zh-min-nan:Fidel Castro]]
[[be:Фідэль Кастра]]
[[be-x-old:Фідэль Кастра]]
[[bcl:Fidel Castro]]
[[bg:Фидел Кастро]]
[[bar:Fidel Castro]]
[[bs:Fidel Castro]]
[[br:Fidel Castro]]
[[ca:Fidel Castro Ruz]]
[[cv:Кастро Фидель]]
[[cs:Fidel Castro]]
[[cy:Fidel Castro]]
[[da:Fidel Castro]]
[[de:Fidel Castro]]
[[dv:ފިޑެލް ކާސްޓްރޯ]]
[[et:Fidel Castro]]
[[el:Φιδέλ Κάστρο]]
[[es:Fidel Castro]]
[[eo:Fidel Castro]]
[[eu:Fidel Castro]]
[[fa:فیدل کاسترو]]
[[fo:Fidel Castro]]
[[fr:Fidel Castro]]
[[fy:Fidel Castro]]
[[ga:Fidel Castro]]
[[gv:Fidel Castro]]
[[gl:Fidel Castro]]
[[gu:ફિડલ કાસ્ટ્રો]]
[[ko:피델 카스트로]]
[[hy:Ֆիդել Կաստրո]]
[[hi:फिदेल कास्ट्रो]]
[[hsb:Fidel Castro]]
[[hr:Fidel Castro]]
[[io:Fidel Castro]]
[[id:Fidel Castro]]
[[is:Fidel Castro]]
[[it:Fidel Castro]]
[[he:פידל קסטרו]]
[[jv:Fidel Castro]]
[[kn:ಫಿಡೆಲ್ ಕ್ಯಾಸ್ಟ್ರೊ]]
[[ka:ფიდელ კასტრო]]
[[kk:Фидел Кастро]]
[[sw:Fidel Castro]]
[[ht:Fidel Castro]]
[[ku:Fidel Castro]]
[[la:Fidelis Castro]]
[[lv:Fidels Kastro]]
[[lb:Fidel Castro]]
[[lt:Fidelis Kastro]]
[[li:Fidel Castro]]
[[ln:Fidel Castro]]
[[hu:Fidel Castro]]
[[mk:Фидел Кастро]]
[[ml:ഫിദൽ കാസ്ട്രോ]]
[[mr:फिडेल कॅस्ट्रो]]
[[xmf:ფიდელ კასტრო]]
[[arz:فيدل كاسترو]]
[[mzn:فیدل کاسترو]]
[[ms:Fidel Castro]]
[[mwl:Fidel Castro Ruz]]
[[mn:Фидель Кастро]]
[[my:ဖီဒယ်လ် ကက်စထရို]]
[[nah:Fidel Castro]]
[[nl:Fidel Castro]]
[[ne:फिडेल कास्ट्रो]]
[[ja:フィデル・カストロ]]
[[no:Fidel Castro]]
[[nn:Fidel Castro]]
[[oc:Fidel Castro]]
[[uz:Fidel Castro]]
[[pl:Fidel Castro]]
[[pt:Fidel Castro]]
[[ro:Fidel Castro]]
[[qu:Fidel Castro]]
[[ru:Кастро, Фидель]]
[[sa:फिदेल कास्ट्रो]]
[[sq:Fidel Castro]]
[[scn:Fidel Castru]]
[[simple:Fidel Castro]]
[[sk:Fidel Castro]]
[[sl:Fidel Castro]]
[[so:Fidel Castaro]]
[[ckb:فیدێل کاسترۆ]]
[[sr:Фидел Кастро]]
[[sh:Fidel Castro]]
[[su:Fidel Castro]]
[[fi:Fidel Castro]]
[[sv:Fidel Castro]]
[[tl:Fidel Castro]]
[[ta:பிடல் காஸ்ட்ரோ]]
[[tt:Фидель Кастро]]
[[te:ఫిడెల్ కాస్ట్రో]]
[[th:ฟีเดล กัสโตร]]
[[tg:Фидел Кастро]]
[[tr:Fidel Castro]]
[[uk:Фідель Кастро]]
[[vec:Fidel Castro]]
[[vi:Fidel Castro]]
[[fiu-vro:Castro Fidel]]
[[war:Fidel Castro]]
[[wuu:非台勒 加斯托洛]]
[[yi:פידעל קאסטרא]]
[[yo:Fidel Castro]]
[[zh-yue:卡斯特羅]]
[[bat-smg:Fidel Castro]]
[[zh:菲德尔·卡斯特罗]]</text>
      <sha1>q9hagwkyjiabn6rxefa6r7ndptqr9bb</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
