<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Habeas corpus</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>14091</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521162323</id>
      <parentid>520786421</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-03T05:15:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Captain Quirk</username>
        <id>7694181</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="37728">{{About|the legal term}}
{{Italic title}}
{{Prerogative writs}}
'''''{{lang|la|Habeas corpus}}''''' ({{IPAc-en|lang|pron|ˌ|h|eɪ|b|ɪ|ə|s|_|ˈ|k|ɔr|p|ə|s}}; [[Latin]]: &quot;you have the body&quot;)&lt;ref&gt;Literally: &quot;you shall/should have the body [in court]&quot;)&lt;/ref&gt; is a [[writ]] (legal action) which requires a person under arrest to be brought before a judge or into court.&lt;ref&gt;[http://oxforddictionaries.com/definition/habeas%2Bcorpus?q=habeas+corpus]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/habeas+corpus]&lt;/ref&gt; This ensures that a prisoner can be released from unlawful [[imprisonment|detention]], in other words, detention lacking sufficient cause or evidence. The remedy can be sought by the prisoner or by another person coming to the prisoner's aid. The legal right to apply for a habeas corpus is also called by the same name.

This right originated in the [[English legal system]], and is now available in many nations. It has historically been an important legal instrument safeguarding [[individual freedom]] against [[Arbitrary power|arbitrary state action]]. 

A writ of ''Habeas corpus'', also known as the '''Great Writ''', is a summons with the force of a [[court order]]; it is addressed to the custodian (a prison official for example) and demands that a prisoner be taken before the court, and that the custodian present proof of authority, allowing the court to determine whether the custodian has lawful authority to detain the person. If the custodian does not have authority to detain the prisoner, then the prisoner must be released from custody. The prisoner, or another person acting on his or her behalf, may petition the court, or a judge, for a writ of ''habeas corpus''. One reason for the writ to be sought by a person other than the prisoner is that the detainee might be held [[Solitary confinement|incommunicado]]. Most [[civil law (legal system)|civil law]] jurisdictions provide a similar remedy for those unlawfully detained, but this is not always called &quot;habeas corpus&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Google books scan of book Introduction to the Study of the Law of the Constitution by Albert Venn Dicey, [http://books.google.com/books?pg=PR3&amp;dq=INTRODUCTION+TO+THE+STUDY+OF+THE+LAW+OF+THE+CONSTITUTION+A.+V.+Dicey&amp;ei=Y2YfR-rMApGepgKuqZWzBg&amp;id=kz40AAAAIAAJ&amp;output=text books.google.com]&lt;/ref&gt; For example, in some Spanish-speaking nations, the equivalent remedy for unlawful imprisonment is the ''[[amparo de libertad]]'' ('protection of freedom').

''Habeas corpus'' has certain limitations. It is technically only a procedural remedy; it is a guarantee against any detention that is forbidden by law, but it does not necessarily protect other rights, such as the entitlement to a fair trial. So if an imposition such as internment without trial is permitted by the law then ''habeas corpus'' may not be a useful remedy. Furthermore, in many countries, the process may be suspended because of a national emergency.

The right to petition for a writ of ''habeas corpus'' has nonetheless long been celebrated as the most efficient safeguard of the liberty of the subject. The jurist [[Albert Venn Dicey]] wrote that the British Habeas Corpus Acts &quot;declare no principle and define no rights, but they are for practical purposes worth a hundred constitutional articles guaranteeing individual liberty&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Anthony Wright (1994) [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=I7oOAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=PA16&amp;dq=declare+no+principle+and+define+no+rights,+but+they+are+for+practical+purposes+worth+a+hundred+constitutional+articles+guaranteeing+individual+liberty&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=Z04mTJuMA9KUOOSj3bMC&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=10&amp;ved=0CFQQ6AEwCQ#v=onepage&amp;q=declare%20no%20principle%20and%20define%20no%20rights%2C%20but%20they%20are%20for%20practical%20purposes%20worth%20a%20hundred%20constitutional%20articles%20guaranteeing%20individual%20liberty&amp;f=false Citizens and subjects: an essay on British politics] Routledge, 1994&lt;/ref&gt;

The writ of ''habeas corpus'' is one of what are called the &quot;extraordinary&quot;, &quot;common law&quot;, or &quot;[[prerogative writ]]s&quot;, which were historically issued by the [[English courts]] in the name of the monarch to control inferior courts and public authorities within the kingdom. The most common of the other such prerogative writs are ''[[quo warranto]]'', ''[[prohibito]]'', ''[[mandamus]]'', ''[[procedendo]]'', and ''[[certiorari]]''. The due process for such petitions is not simply civil or criminal, because they incorporate the presumption of non-authority. The official who is the respondent has the burden to prove his authority to do or not do something. Failing this, the court must decide for the petitioner, who may be any person, not just an interested party. This differs from a motion in a civil process in which the movant must have standing, and bears the burden of proof.

==Derivation and form==
''Habeas corpus'' is a [[Latin]] phrase, which can be literally translated as “(we command) that you have the body”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Oxford English Dictionary|publisher=Oxford University Press|volume=4|page=849}}&lt;/ref&gt; or &quot;you should arrest&quot; the conventional [[incipit]] of medieval [[arrest warrant]]s in England. The writ is referred to in full in legal texts as '''''habeas corpus ad subjiciendum''''' or more rarely '''''ad subjiciendum et recipiendum'''''. It is sometimes described as the “'''great writ'''”. Its name derives from the operative words of the writ in Medieval Latin:

{{quotation|''Praecipimus tibi quod '''corpus''' A.B. in prisona nostra sub custodia tua detentum, ut dicitur, una cum die et causa captionis et detentionis suae, quocumque nomine praedictus A.B. censeatur in eadem, '''habeas''' coram nobis ... ad subjiciendum et recipiendum ea quae curia nostra de eo adtunc et ibidem ordinare contigerit in hac parte. Et hoc nullatenus omittatis periculo incumbente. Et habeas ibi hoc breve.''}}

{{quotation|We command you, that the '''body''' of A.B. in Our prison under your custody detained, as it is said, together with the day and cause of his taking and detention, by whatever name the said A.B. may be known therein, '''you have''' at our Court ... to undergo and to receive that which our Court shall then and there consider and order in that behalf. Hereof in no way fail, at your peril. And have you then there this writ.}}

The word ''habeas'' in the writ is  in the [[subjunctive]] (specifically the volitive subjunctive): &quot;We command ''that you have'' ...&quot;. That the basic form of the writs of habeas corpus, now written in English, has changed little over the centuries can be seen from the following examples.

===Examples===
{{quotation|[[Victoria of the United Kingdom|VICTORIA]] [[by the Grace of God]], of the [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland]] Queen, [[Fidei defensor|Defender of the Faith]], to J.K., Keeper of our Gaol of [[Jersey]], in the Island of Jersey, and to J.C. Viscount of said Island, Greeting.

We command you that you have the body of C.C.W. detained in our prison under your custody, as it is said, together with the day and cause of his being taken and detained, by whatsoever name he may be called or known, in our Court before us, at [[Palace of Westminster|Westminster]], on the 18th day of January next, to undergo and receive all and singular such matters and things which our said Court shall then and there consider of him in this behalf; and have there then this Writ.}}

{{quotation|
 [[United States of America]], [[United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit|Second Judicial Circuit]], [[United States District Court for the Southern District of New York|Southern District of New York]], ss.:

We command you that the body of Charles L. Craig, in your custody detained, as it is said, together with the day and cause of his caption and detention, you safely have before Honorable [[Martin Manton|Martin T. Manton]], United States Circuit Judge for the Second Judicial Circuit, within the circuit and district aforesaid, to do and receive all and singular those things which the said judge shall then and there consider of him in this behalf; and have you then and there this writ.}}

{{anchor|habeas corpus cum causa|Habeas corpus ad deliberandum et recipiendum|Habeas corpus ad faciendum et recipiendum|Habeas corpus ad prosequendum|Habeas corpus ad respondendum|Habeas corpus ad testificandum}}

===Similarly named writs===
The full name of the writ is often used to distinguish it from similar ancient writs, also named ''habeas corpus''. These include
* ''Habeas corpus ad deliberandum et recipiendum'': a writ for bringing an accused from a different county into a court in the place where a crime had been committed for purposes of trial, or more literally to return holding the body for purposes of “deliberation and receipt” of a decision.  (&quot;[[Extradition]]&quot;)
* ''Habeas corpus ad faciendum et recipiendum'' (also called ''habeas corpus cum causa''): a writ of a superior court to a custodian to return with the body being held by the order of a lower court &quot;with reasons&quot;, for the purpose of “receiving” the decision of the superior court and of “doing” what it ordered.
* ''Habeas corpus ad prosequendum'': a writ ordering return with a prisoner for the purpose of “prosecuting” him before the court.
* ''Habeas corpus ad respondendum'': a writ ordering return to allow the prisoner to “answer” to new proceedings before the court.
* ''Habeas corpus ad testificandum'': a writ ordering return with the body of a prisoner for the purposes of “testifying&quot;.

==Origins in England==
{{see|English law}}
In the 17th century the foundations for ''habeas corpus'' were &quot;wrongly thought&quot; to have originated in [[Magna Carta]].&lt;ref&gt;Turner, Ralph V. ''Magna Carta'' Pearson (2003) p162 and p219&lt;/ref&gt; This charter declared that

{{quote|No Freeman shall be taken or imprisoned, or be disseized of his Freehold, or Liberties, or free Customs, or be outlawed, or exiled, or any other wise destroyed; nor will We not pass upon him, nor condemn him, but by lawful judgment of his Peers, or by the Law of the land.}}

[[William Blackstone|Blackstone]] cites the first recorded usage of ''habeas corpus ad subjiciendum'' in 1305, during the reign of [[Edward I of England|King Edward I]]. However, other [[writ]]s were issued with the same effect as early as the reign of [[Henry II of England|Henry II]] in the 12th century. Blackstone explained the basis of the writ, saying &quot;The King is at all times entitled to have an account, why the liberty of any of his subjects is restrained, wherever that restraint may be inflicted.&quot; The procedure for issuing a writ of ''habeas corpus'' was first codified by the [[Habeas Corpus Act 1679]], following judicial rulings which had restricted the effectiveness of the writ. A previous law (the [[Habeas Corpus Act 1640]]) had been passed forty years earlier to overturn a ruling that the command of the King was a sufficient answer to a petition of ''habeas corpus''.

Then, as now, the writ of ''habeas corpus'' was issued by a superior court in the name of the Sovereign, and commanded the addressee (a lower court, sheriff, or private subject) to produce the prisoner before the royal courts of law. A ''habeas corpus'' petition could be made by the prisoner himself or by a third party on his behalf and, as a result of the Habeas Corpus Acts, could be made regardless of whether the court was in session, by presenting the petition to a judge. Since the 18th century the writ has also been used in cases of unlawful detention by private individuals, most famously in ''[[Somersett's Case]]'' (1772), where the black slave Somersett was ordered to be freed.&lt;ref&gt;Frederick Charles Moncreiff (2006). &quot;The Wit and Wisdom of the Bench and Bar&quot;, pp.85–86. The Lawbook Exchange, Ltd.&lt;/ref&gt; In that case these famous words are said to have been uttered &quot;The air of England has long been too pure for a slave, and every man is free who breathes it&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;George Birkbeck Hil (2004) [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=2EQCXQ0IbUkC&amp;pg=PA364&amp;dq=The+air+of+England+has+long+been+too+pure+for+a+slave,+and+every+man+is+free+who+breathes+it.&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=qEkmTPatLoesOPHBiM0F&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CCwQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=The%20air%20of%20England%20has%20long%20been%20too%20pure%20for%20a%20slave%2C%20and%20every%20man%20is%20free%20who%20breathes%20it.&amp;f=false Life of Johnson, Volume 3] Kessinger Publishing, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

The privilege of ''habeas corpus'' has been suspended or restricted several times during [[English history]], most recently during the 18th and 19th centuries. Although internment without trial has been authorised by statute since that time, for example during the two [[World War]]s and the [[The Troubles|Troubles]] in [[Northern Ireland]], the ''habeas corpus'' procedure has in modern times always technically remained available to such internees. However, as ''habeas corpus'' is only a procedural device to examine the lawfulness of a prisoner's detention, so long as the detention is in accordance with an [[Act of Parliament]], the petition for ''habeas corpus'' is unsuccessful. Since the passage of the [[Human Rights Act 1998]], the courts have been able to declare an Act of Parliament to be incompatible with the [[European Convention on Human Rights]], but such a declaration of incompatibility has no legal effect unless and until it is acted upon by the government.

The wording of the writ of ''habeas corpus'' implies that the prisoner is brought to the court for the legality of the imprisonment to be examined. However, rather than issuing the writ immediately and waiting for the return of the writ by the custodian, modern practice in England is for the original application to be followed by a hearing with both parties present to decide the legality of the detention, without any writ being issued. If the detention is held to be unlawful, the prisoner can usually then be released or [[bail]]ed by order of the court without having to be produced before it. It is also possible for individuals held by the state to petition for [[judicial review]], and individuals held by non-state entities to apply for an [[injunction]].

==Other jurisdictions==

===Australia===
The writ of ''habeas corpus'' as a procedural remedy is part of [[Australia]]'s English law inheritance.&lt;ref&gt;Clark, David and Gerard McCoy (1998), &quot;Habeas Corpus&quot; (Federation Press)&lt;/ref&gt; In 2005, the [[Australian parliament]] passed the [[Australian Anti-Terrorism Act 2005]]. Some legal experts questioned the constitutionality of the act, due in part to limitations it placed on ''habeas corpus''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aph.gov.au/senate/committee/legcon_ctte/completed_inquiries/2004-07/terrorism/submissions/sub41.pdf|title=Submission to the Australian Senate|format=PDF|accessdate=2010-08-30}}{{dead link|date=June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{Verify credibility|date=May 2011}}

===Canada===
''Habeas corpus'' rights are part of the British legal tradition inherited by Canada. The rights exist in the common law but have been enshrined in the [[Constitution Act 1982]], under [[Section Ten of the Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms|Section Ten]] of the [[Charter of Rights and Freedoms]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://laws.justice.gc.ca/en/const/annex_e.html#legal
|title=The Constitution Act, 1982; Part I, Section 7: Legal Rights
|publisher=Canadian Department of Justice
|accessdate=2008-06-29
}}{{dead link|date=June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; This states that &quot;Everyone has the right on arrest or detention... (c) to have the validity of the detention determined by way of ''habeas corpus'' and to be released if the detention is not lawful.&quot;

Suspension of the writ in Canadian history occurred famously during the [[October Crisis]], during which the [[War Measures Act]] was invoked by the [[Governor General of Canada]] on the [[Advice (constitutional)|constitutional advice]] of Prime Minister [[Pierre Trudeau]], who had received a request from the [[Quebec]] Cabinet. The Act was also used to justify German, Slavic, and [[Ukrainian Canadian internment]] during the [[First World War]], and the internment of German-Canadians, Italian Canadians and [[Japanese Canadian internment|of Japanese Canadian]]s during the [[Second World War]].

The writ is available where there is no other adequate remedy. However, a superior court always has the discretion to grant the writ even in the face of an alternative remedy (see [[May v. Ferndale Institution]]). Under the [[Criminal Code of Canada]] the writ is largely unavailable if a statutory right of appeal exists, whether or not this right has been exercised.

===Germany===
Germany has constitutional guarantees against improper detention and have been implemented in statutory law in a manner that can be considered as equivalent to writs of habeas corpus.

Article 104, paragraph 1 of the German Constitution provides that deprivations of liberty may be imposed only on the basis of a specific enabling statute that also must include procedural rules. Article 104, paragraph 2 requires that any arrested individual be brought before a judge by the end of the day following the day of the arrest. For those detained as criminal suspects, article 104, paragraph 3 specifically requires that the judge must grant a hearing to the suspect in order to rule on the detention.

Restrictions on the power of the authorities to arrest and detain individuals also emanate from article 2 paragraph 2 of the Constitution which guarantees liberty and requires a statutory authorization for any deprivation of liberty. In addition, several other articles of the Constitution have a bearing on the issue. The most important of these are article 19, which generally requires a statutory basis for any infringements of the fundamental rights guaranteed by the Constitution while also guaranteeing judicial review; article 20, paragraph 3, which guarantees the rule of law; and article 3 which guarantees equality.

In particular, a constitutional obligation to grant remedies for improper detention is required by article 19, paragraph 4 of the Constitution which provides as follows: &quot;Should any person’s right be violated by public authority, he may have recourse to the courts. If no other jurisdiction has been established, recourse shall be to the ordinary courts.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.loc.gov/law/help/habeas-corpus/germany.php Habeas Corpus Rights: Germany|Law Library of Congress&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===India===
The Indian judiciary, in a catena of cases has effectively resorted to the writ of ''habeas corpus'' to secure release of a person from illegal detention. The Indian judiciary has dispensed with the traditional doctrine of ''[[locus standi]]'', so that if a detained person is not in a position to file a petition, it can be moved on his behalf by any other person. The scope of ''habeas'' relief has expanded in recent times by actions of the Indian judiciary.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.legalserviceindia.com/articles/wha.htm|title=Writ Of Habeas Corpus For Securing Liberty - Author - ABS-CBN News|publisher=Legalserviceindia.com|date=|accessdate=2010-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; The habeas writ was used in the [[Rajan case]]. It was also filed by Panthers Party to protest the imprisonment of [[Anna Hazare]], a social activist.

===Ireland===

In the [[Republic of Ireland]] access to the remedy of ''habeas corpus'' is guaranteed by Article 40.4 of the [[Constitution of Ireland|1937 constitution]]. This guarantees &quot;personal liberty&quot; to each individual and outlines a detailed ''habeas corpus'' procedure. It does not mention the Latin term but includes the English phrase &quot;produce the body&quot;. The constitution provides that the ''habeas'' procedure is not binding on the [[Irish Defence Forces|Defence Forces]] during a state of war or armed rebellion.

Article 40.4.2° states that a prisoner, or anyone acting on his behalf, may make a complaint to the High Court (or to any High Court judge) of unlawful detention. The court must then investigate the matter &quot;forthwith&quot; and may order that the defendant bring the prisoner before the court and give reasons for his detention. The court must immediately release the detainee unless it is satisfied that he is being held lawfully. The full text of the provision is as follows:

{{quote|Upon complaint being made by or on behalf of any person to the High Court or any judge thereof alleging that such person is being unlawfully detained, the High Court and any and every judge thereof to whom such complaint is made shall forthwith enquire into the said complaint and may order the person in whose custody such person is detained to ''produce the body'' of such person before the High Court on a named day and to certify in writing the grounds of his detention, and the High Court shall, upon the body of such person being produced before that Court and after giving the person in whose custody he is detained an opportunity of justifying the detention, order the release of such person from such detention unless satisfied that he is being detained in accordance with the law. [''Italics'' added]}}

The state inherited ''habeas corpus'' as part of the common law when it seceded from the [[United Kingdom]] in 1922, but the remedy was also guaranteed by Article 6 of the [[Constitution of the Irish Free State]] in force from 1922 to 1937. A similar provision was included when the current constitution was adopted in 1937. Since that date ''habeas corpus'' has been restricted by two [[constitutional amendment]]s, the [[Second Amendment of the Constitution of Ireland|Second Amendment]] in 1941 and the [[Sixteenth Amendment of the Constitution of Ireland|Sixteenth Amendment]] in 1996.

Before the Second Amendment, an individual detained had the constitutional right to apply to any [[High Court of the Republic of Ireland|High Court]] judge for a writ of ''habeas corpus'' and to as many High Court judges as he wished. Since the Second Amendment, a prisoner has had only the right to apply to one judge, and, once a writ has been issued, the President of the High Court has authority to choose the judge or panel of three judges who will decide the case. The amendment also added a requirement that if the High Court believes someone's detention to be invalid due to the unconstitutionality of a law, it must refer the matter to the [[Irish Supreme Court]] and may only release the individual on bail in the interim.

In 1965, the Supreme Court ruled in the ''O'Callaghan'' case that the provisions of the constitution meant that an individual charged with a crime could be refused bail only if she was likely to flee or to interfere with witnesses or evidence. Since the Sixteenth Amendment, it has been possible for a court to take into account whether a person has committed serious crimes while on bail in the past.

===Malaysia===
In [[Malaysia]], the remedy of ''habeas corpus'' is guaranteed by the federal constitution, although not by name. Article 5(2) of the [[Constitution of Malaysia]] provides that &quot;Where complaint is made to a High Court or any judge thereof that a person is being unlawfully detained the court shall inquire into the complaint and, unless satisfied that the detention is lawful, shall order him to be produced before the court and release him.&quot;

As there are several statutes, for example, the [[Internal Security Act (Malaysia)|Internal Security Act 1960]], that still permit detention without trial, the procedure is usually effective in such cases only if it can be shown that there was a procedural error in the way that the detention was ordered.

===New Zealand===
In [[New Zealand]] ''habeas corpus'' may be invoked against the government or private individuals. In 2006, a child was allegedly kidnapped by his maternal grandfather after a custody dispute. The father began ''habeas corpus'' proceedings against the mother, the grandfather, the grandmother, the great grandmother, and another person alleged to have assisted in the kidnap of the child. The mother did not present the child to the court and so was imprisoned for [[contempt of court]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nzherald.co.nz/section/1/story.cfm?c_id=1&amp;ObjectID=10407667|title=New Zealand Herald newspaper|publisher=Nzherald.co.nz|date=2006-10-26|accessdate=2010-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; She was released when the grandfather came forward with the child in late January 2007.

===The Philippines===
In the Bill of Rights of the Philippine constitution, ''habeas corpus'' is guaranteed in terms almost identically to those used in the U.S. Constitution. in Article 3, Section 15 of the [[Constitution of the Philippines]] states that &quot;The privilege of the writ of ''habeas corpus'' shall not be suspended except in cases of invasion or rebellion when the public safety requires it.&quot;

In 1971, after the [[Plaza Miranda bombing]], the Marcos administration, under [[Ferdinand Marcos]], suspended ''habeas corpus'' in an effort to stifle the oncoming insurgency, having blamed the [[Communist Party of the Philippines|Filipino Communist Party]] for the events of August 21. Many considered this to be a prelude to [[Martial Law]]. After widespread protests, however, the Marcos administration decided to reintroduce the writ. In December 2009, ''habeas corpus'' was suspended in Maguindanao as the province was placed under martial law. This occurred in response to the [[Maguindanao massacre]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=by andoybarrios on Sat, 12/05/2009 - 23:08|url=http://www.abs-cbnnews.com/nation/12/04/09/arroyo-orders-martial-law-maguindanao|title=Arroyo proclaims martial law in Maguindanao - ABS-CBN News Online|publisher=Abs-cbnnews.com|date=2009-12-05|accessdate=2010-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Scotland===

The [[Parliament of Scotland]] passed a law to have the same effect as ''habeas corpus'' in the 18th century. This now known as the Criminal Procedure Act 1701 c.6.&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.statutelaw.gov.uk/content.aspx?ActiveTextDocId=1519689 Full text of the Act]. This law was given its current short title by the [[Statute Law Revision (Scotland) Act 1964]]&lt;/ref&gt; It was originally called &quot;the Act for preventing wrongful imprisonment and against undue delays in trials&quot;. It is still in force although certain parts have been repealed.

===Spain===
In 1526 the ''[[Fuero Nuevo of the Señorío de Vizcaya|Fuero Nuevo]]'' established a form of ''habeas corpus'' in the territory of the ''[[Señorío de Vizcaya]]''. The present [[Constitution of Spain]] states that &quot;A ''habeas corpus'' procedure shall be provided for by law to ensure the immediate handing over to the judicial authorities of any person illegally arrested&quot;. The statute which regulates the procedure is the [[Law of Habeas Corpus of 24 May 1984]] which provides that a person imprisoned may, on his own or through a third person, allege he is imprisoned unlawfully and request to appear before a judge. The request must specify the grounds on which the detention is considered to be unlawful which can be, for example, that the custodian holding the prisoner does not have the legal authority, that the prisoner's constitutional rights have been violated, or that he has been subjected to mistreatment. The judge may then request additional information if needed and may issue a ''habeas corpus'' order at which point the custodian has 24 hours to bring the prisoner before the judge.

===United States===
{{Main|Habeas corpus in the United States}}
&lt;!-- This section is only a BRIEF SUMMARY. Please consider adding extra material to the main article instead! --&gt;

The [[United States]] inherited ''habeas corpus'' from the [[English common law]]. In England the writ was issued in the name of the monarch. When the original [[Thirteen Colonies|thirteen American colonies]] declared independence, and became a republic based on popular sovereignty, any person, in the name of the people, acquired authority to initiate such writs. The [[United States Constitution|U.S. Constitution]] specifically includes the ''habeas'' procedure in the [[Suspension Clause]] (Clause 2), located in [[Article One of the United States Constitution|Article One]], Section 9. This states that &quot;The privilege of the writ of ''habeas corpus'' shall not be suspended, unless when in cases of rebellion or invasion, the public safety may require it.&quot;

The writ of ''habeas corpus ad subjiciendum'' is a civil, not criminal, ''[[ex parte]]'' proceeding in which a court inquires as to the legitimacy of a prisoner's custody. Typically, ''habeas corpus'' proceedings are to determine whether the court which imposed sentence on the defendant had jurisdiction and authority to do so, or whether the defendant's sentence has expired. ''Habeas corpus'' is also used as a legal avenue to challenge other types of custody such as pretrial detention or detention by the [[U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement|United States Bureau of Immigration and Customs Enforcement]] pursuant to a deportation proceeding.

The suspension of Habeas Corpus has occurred in United States history; former presidents Abraham Lincoln, Ulysses Grant, George W. Bush, and Barack Obama have all signed the suspension of Habeas Corpus.&lt;ref&gt;http://usgovinfo.about.com/od/historicdocuments/a/lincolnhabeas.htm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.presidency.ucsb.edu/ws/index.php?pid=70261&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://harvardmagazine.com/2009/01/the-war-the-writ&lt;/ref&gt;

==Equivalent remedies==

===Poland===

In 1433 King [[Jagiełło]] granted the Privilege of Jedlna, which proclaimed, ''Neminem captivabimus nisi iure victum'' (“We will not imprison anyone except if convicted by law”). This revolutionary innovation in civil [[libertarianism]] gave Polish citizens due process-style rights that did not exist in any other European country for another 250 years. Originally, the Privilege of Jedlna was restricted to the nobility (the [[szlachta]]), but it was extended to cover townsmen in the [[Constitution of 3rd May|1791 Constitution]]. Importantly, social classifications in the [[Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth]] were not as rigid as in other European countries; townspeople and Jews were sometimes ennobled. The Privilege of Jedlna provided broader coverage than many subsequently enacted habeas corpus laws because Poland’s nobility constituted an unusually large percentage of the country's total population, which was Europe’s largest. As a result, by the 16th century, it was protecting the liberty of between 500 thousand and a million Poles.&lt;ref&gt;[[Poland’s 1997 Constitution in Its Historical Context http://indylaw.indiana.edu/instructors/cole/web%20page/polconst.pdf]]; Daniel H. Cole, Indiana University School of Law, September 22, 1998&lt;/ref&gt;

==World ''habeas corpus''==

In the 1950s, American lawyer [[Luis Kutner]] began advocating an international writ of ''habeas corpus'' to protect individual human rights. In 1952 he filed a petition for a &quot;United Nations Writ of Habeas Corpus&quot; on behalf of [[William N. Oatis]], an American journalist jailed the previous year by the Communist government of [[Czechoslovakia]].&lt;ref&gt;The petition was titled &quot;United Nations Ex Rel., Luis Kutner, For and on Behalf of William N. Oatis, Petitioner, v. Czechoslovakia, Respondent - Petition of Luis Kutner For and on Behalf of William N. Oatis, For a United Nations Writ of Habeas Corpus.&quot; See [http://www.lawschool.cornell.edu/research/cornell-law-review/upload/Jackson.pdf Vicki C. Jackson, &quot;World Habeas Corpus,&quot; 91 Cornell Law Review 303, 309 (January 2006)]{{dead link|date=June 2012}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Alleging that Czechoslovakia had violated Oatis's rights under the [[United Nations Charter]] and the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]] and that the [[United Nations General Assembly]] had &quot;inherent power&quot; to fashion remedies for human rights violations, the petition was filed with the [[United Nations Commission on Human Rights]].&lt;ref name=Jackson&gt;[http://www.lawschool.cornell.edu/research/cornell-law-review/upload/Jackson.pdf Vicki C. Jackson, &quot;World Habeas Corpus,&quot; 91 Cornell Law Review 303, 309-314 (January 2006)]{{dead link|date=June 2012}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The Commission forwarded the petition to Czechoslovakia, but no other United Nations action was taken.&lt;ref name=Jackson/&gt; Oatis was released in 1953. Kutner went on to publish numerous articles and books advocating the creation of an &quot;International Court of Habeas Corpus.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;His first article was &quot;A Proposal for a United Nations Writ of Habeas Corpus and International Court of Human Rights,&quot; Tulane Law Review, 28 (June 1954): 417-441. See also, Luis Kutner, ''World Habeas Corpus'', Dobbs Ferry, NY: Oceana, 1962, p. 266, for his draft of a &quot;Treaty-Statute of the International Court of Habeas Corpus.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Arbitrary arrest and detention]]
* ''[[corpus delicti]]'' – other Latin legal term using ''corpus,'' here meaning the fact of a crime having been committed, not the body of the person being detained nor (as sometimes inaccurately used) to the body of the victim
* [[Edward Hyde, 1st Earl of Clarendon]]
* [[Habeas Corpus (play)|''Habeas Corpus'' (play)]], by the English writer and playwright Alan Bennett.
* [[Habeas Corpus Restoration Act of 2007]]
* [[Habeas Data]]
* [[List of legal Latin terms]]
* [[Military Commissions Act of 2006]]
* [[Murder conviction without a body]]
* [[Philippine Habeas Corpus Cases]]
* ''[[Recurso de amparo]]'' (Writ of ''amparo'')
* ''[[Subpoena ad testificandum]]''
* ''[[Subpoena duces tecum]]''

==Notes and references==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Further reading==
* [[Asha Bandele]] &quot;Habeas Corpus is a legal Entitlement&quot;, a poem in ''Absence in the Palms of My Hands &amp; Other Poems''. New York: [[Harlem River Press]]. 1996.
* A.H. Carpenter. &quot;Habeas Corpus in the Colonies.&quot; ''[[The American Historical Review]]''. Vol. 8., No. 1 (October 1902), pages 18–27.
* Louis Fisher. 2003. ''Nazi Saboteurs on Trial: A Military Tribunal and American Law.'' University Press of Kansas. ISBN 0-7006-1238-6.
* Michael Dobbs. 2004. ''Saboteurs: The Nazi Raid on America''. Vintage. ISBN 1-4000-3042-0.
* Charles Doyle. 2006. ''Federal Habeas Copus: A Brief Legal Overview.'' Congressional Research Service.
* Peter Irons. 1999. ''A People's History of the Supreme Court''. Viking. ISBN 0-670-87006-4. Political context for ''Ex Parte Milligan'' explained on Pp.&amp;nbsp;186–189.
* Helen A. Nutting. &quot;The Most Wholesome Law—The Habeas Corpus Act of 1679.&quot; ''[[The American Historical Review]]''. Vol. 65., No. 3 (April 1960), pages 527–543.
* Geoffrey R. Stone. 2004. ''Perilous Times, Free Speech in Wartime From the Sedition Act to the War on Terrorism''. Norton. ISBN 0-393-05880-8.
* Cary Federman. 2006. ''The Body and the State: Habeas Corpus and American Jurisprudence''. SUNY. ISBN 0-7914-6703-1.
* Eric M. Freedman. 2001. ''Habeas Corpus: Rethinking the Great Writ of Liberty'' (NYU Press) ISBN 0-8147-2717-4
* Lisa M. Seghetti and Nathan James. 2006. ''Federal Habeas Corpus Relief: Background, Legislation, and Issues.'' Congressional Research Service.
* [[Donald E. Wilkes Jr]], [http://digitalcommons.law.uga.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1223&amp;context=fac_artchop The Georgia Death Penalty Habeas Corpus Reform Act of 1995] (1995) &amp; [http://digitalcommons.law.uga.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1052&amp;context=fac_pm Habeas Corpus: The Great Writ Hit] (2006) &amp; [http://www.law.uga.edu/dwilkes_more/62uncorpsed.pdf Habeas Corpus Uncorpsed] (2008) &amp; [http://digitalcommons.law.uga.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1224&amp;context=fac_artchop Habeas Corpus and Baseball] (2006) &amp; [http://digitalcommons.law.uga.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1064&amp;context=fac_pm The Writ of Habeas Corpus in Georgia] (2007) &amp; [http://www.georgiaencyclopedia.org/nge/Article.jsp?path=/GovernmentPolitics/Government/StateGovernment/ConstitutionalHistory&amp;id=h-3741 Writ of Habeas Corpus], from [http://www.georgiaencyclopedia.org/nge/Home.jsp The New Georgia Encyclopedia] (2009).

==External links==
* [http://denouncetorture.amnestyusa.org/site/c.huITL9MVJxE/b.2607193/k.BDCC/Habeas_corpus_Restoration_Act_of_2007__Background.htm Amnesty International page on Habeas Corpus Restoration Act of 2007]
* [http://www.barristermagazine.com/ Barristermagazine.com]
* [http://www.inmatelaw.org/ Inmatelaw.org]
* [http://www.lectlaw.com/def/h001.htm LectLaw.com]
* [http://tides.sfasu.edu/AN18/SHHIV_40.php?culture=2&amp;chrono=5&amp;index=0 Petition for Habeas Corpus April 16, 1843] From [http://tides.sfasu.edu/ Texas Tides]
* [http://www.thislife.org/Radio_Episode.aspx?episode=331 This American Life: 331: Habeas Schmabeas 2007]
* [http://www.findhabeas.com/ Find Habeas]

{{Criminal procedure (investigation)}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Habeas Corpus}}
[[Category:Constitutional law]]
[[Category:Emergency laws]]
[[Category:Habeas corpus| ]]
[[Category:Human rights]]
[[Category:Latin legal terms]]
[[Category:Liberalism]]
[[Category:Philosophy of law]]
[[Category:Prerogative writs]]

[[af:Habeas corpus]]
[[ca:Habeas Corpus]]
[[cs:Habeas corpus]]
[[da:Habeas corpus]]
[[de:Habeas Corpus]]
[[et:Habeas corpus]]
[[es:Hábeas corpus]]
[[eo:Habeas corpus]]
[[eu:Habeas corpus]]
[[fa:هی‌بی‌اس کورپس]]
[[fr:Habeas corpus]]
[[ko:인신보호영장]]
[[hi:बन्दी प्रत्यक्षीकरण]]
[[hr:Habeas corpus]]
[[it:Habeas corpus]]
[[he:הביאס קורפוס]]
[[kn:ಹೇಬಿಯಸ್ ಕಾರ್ಪಸ್]]
[[la:Habeas corpus]]
[[hu:Habeas Corpus]]
[[ja:ヘイビアス・コーパス]]
[[no:Habeas corpus]]
[[oc:Habeas corpus]]
[[pt:Habeas corpus]]
[[ru:Хабеас корпус]]
[[sl:Habeas corpus]]
[[fi:Habeas corpus]]
[[sv:Habeas corpus]]
[[tl:Habeas corpus]]
[[tr:Habeas corpus]]
[[zh:人身保護令]]</text>
      <sha1>kewswjzkm09l31sq0f6c3nk5u37q7bb</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
