<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Jacques Chirac</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>39764</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520929677</id>
      <parentid>519606029</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-01T18:06:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>193.251.65.8</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Foreign policy */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="77306">{{Redirect|Chirac}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2012}}
{{Infobox officeholder
|name           = Jacques Chirac
|image          = ChiracUSA.jpg
|office         = [[President of France]]
|primeminister  = [[Alain Juppé]]&lt;br&gt;[[Lionel Jospin]]&lt;br&gt;[[Jean-Pierre Raffarin]]&lt;br&gt;[[Dominique de Villepin]]
|term_start     = 17 May 1995
|term_end       = 16 May 2007
|predecessor    = [[François Mitterrand]]
|successor      = [[Nicolas Sarkozy]]
|office1        = [[Co-Princes of Andorra|Co-Prince of Andorra]]
|primeminister1 = [[Marc Forné Molné]]&lt;br&gt;[[Albert Pintat]]
|term_start1    = 17 May 1995
|term_end1      = 16 May 2007
|predecessor1   = [[François Mitterrand]]
|successor1     = [[Nicolas Sarkozy]]
|office2        = [[Prime Minister of France]]
|president2     = [[François Mitterrand]]
|term_start2    = 20 March 1986
|term_end2      = 10 May 1988
|predecessor2   = [[Laurent Fabius]]
|successor2     = [[Michel Rocard]]
|president3     = [[Valéry Giscard d'Estaing]]
|term_start3    = 27 May 1974
|term_end3      = 26 August 1976
|predecessor3   = [[Pierre Messmer]]
|successor3     = [[Raymond Barre]]
|office4        = [[List of mayors of Paris|Mayor of Paris]]
|term_start4    = 20 March 1977
|term_end4      = 16 May 1995
|predecessor4   = Position established
|successor4     = [[Jean Tiberi]]
|office5        = [[Minister of the Interior (France)|Minister of the Interior]]
|primeminister5 = [[Pierre Messmer]]
|term_start5    = 27 February 1974
|term_end5      = 28 May 1974
|predecessor5   = [[Raymond Marcellin]]
|successor5     = [[Michel Poniatowski]]
|office6        = [[Ministry of Agriculture (France)|Minister of Agriculture]]
|primeminister6 = [[Pierre Messmer]]
|term_start6    = 7 July 1972
|term_end6      = 27 February 1974
|predecessor6   = [[Michel Cointat]]
|successor6     = [[Raymond Marcellin]]
|birth_date     = {{birth date and age|1932|11|29|df=y}}
|birth_place    = Paris, [[French Third Republic|France]]
|death_date     = 
|death_place    = 
|party          = [[French Communist Party|Communist Party]] &lt;small&gt;(Before 1962)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Union for the New Republic]] &lt;small&gt;(1962–1968)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Union of Democrats for the Republic]] &lt;small&gt;(1968–1971)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Rally for the Republic]] &lt;small&gt;(1971–2002)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Union for a Popular Movement]] &lt;small&gt;(2002–present)&lt;/small&gt;
|spouse         = [[Bernadette Chirac|Bernadette de Courcel]] &lt;small&gt;(1956–present)&lt;/small&gt;
|children       = 2 daughters
|alma_mater     = [[Institut d'Études Politiques de Paris|Institute of Political Studies, Paris]]&lt;br&gt;[[École nationale d'administration|National School of Administration]]
|religion    = Roman Catholic
|signature      = Jacques Chirac Signature.svg
}}
'''Jacques René Chirac''' ({{IPAc-en|icon|ʒ|ɑː|k|_|ʃ|ɨ|ˈ|r|æ|k}}; {{IPA-fr|ʒak ʃi.ʁak}}; born 29 November 1932) is a French politician who served as [[President of France]] from 1995 to 2007. He previously served as [[Prime Minister of France]] from 1974 to 1976 and from 1986 to 1988 (making him the only person to hold the position of Prime Minister twice under the [[French Fifth Republic|Fifth Republic]]), and as [[List of mayors of Paris|Mayor of Paris]] from 1977 to 1995.

After completing his studies of the [[DEA (former French degree)|DEA]]'s degree at the [[Institut d'études politiques de Paris]], a term at [[Harvard University]] and the [[École nationale d'administration]] (ENA), Chirac began his career as a high-level civil servant, and soon entered politics. He subsequently occupied various senior positions, including [[Minister of Agriculture (France)|Minister of Agriculture]], [[Minister of the Interior (France)|Minister of the Interior]], Prime Minister, [[Mayor of Paris]], and finally [[President of the French Republic]].

Chirac's internal policies included lower tax rates, the removal of [[price controls]], strong punishment for crime and terrorism, and business [[privatisation]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iht.com/articles/1997/07/15/chirac.t.php Privatization Is Essential, Chirac Warns Socialists: Resisting Global Currents, France Sticks to Being French], ''International Herald Tribune''&lt;/ref&gt; He also argued for more socially responsible [[economic policies]], and was elected in 1995 after campaigning on a platform of healing the &quot;social rift&quot; (''fracture sociale'').&lt;ref name=Bonjour&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bonjourlafrance.net/france-history/jacques-chirac.htm |title=Jacques Chirac President of France from 1995–2007 |publisher=Bonjourlafrance.net |accessdate=20 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; After less statist policy when he was Prime Minister (1986–1988), he changed his method. Then, his economic policies, based on ''[[dirigisme]]'', state-directed ideals, stood in opposition to the ''[[laissez-faire]]'' policies of the United Kingdom, which Chirac famously described as &quot;[[Anglosphere|Anglo-Saxon]] [[neoliberalism|ultraliberalism]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=a&gt;{{cite book|last=Giavazzi|first=Francesco|coauthors=Alberto Alesina|year=2006|title=The Future of Europe: Reform Or Decline|page=125}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Chirac is the second-longest serving President of France (two full terms, the first of seven years and the second of five years), after [[François Mitterrand]]. As President, he also served as an ''[[ex officio]]'' [[Co-Prince of Andorra]] and Grand Master of the French [[Légion d'honneur]].

On 15 December 2011, the Paris court declared him guilty of diverting public funds and abusing public confidence, and gave Chirac a two-year suspended prison sentence.

==Family, early life, education, and early career==
Chirac, born in the Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire clinic ([[5th arrondissement of Paris|Paris V&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt;]]), is the son of Abel François Chirac (1893–1968), a successful executive for an aircraft company,&lt;ref name=Bonjour /&gt; and Marie-Louise Valette (1902–1973), a housewife. His great grandparents on both sides were [[peasant]]s, but his two grandfathers were teachers from [[Sainte-Féréole]] in Corrèze. According to Chirac, his name &quot;originates from the [[langue d'oc]], that of the troubadours, therefore that of poetry&quot;. He is a Roman Catholic.

Chirac was an only child (his elder sister, Jacqueline, died in infancy before his birth), and was educated in Paris at the [[Lycée Carnot]] and at the [[Lycée Louis-le-Grand]]. After his [[baccalauréat]], he served for three months as a sailor on a coal-transporter.{{citation needed|date=September 2011}}

Chirac played [[rugby union]] for [[CA Brive|Brive]]'s youth team, and also played at university level. He played [[Number 8 (rugby union)|no. 8]] and [[Second Row (rugby union)|second row]].&lt;ref name=Famous&gt;[http://wesclark.com/rrr/famous.html Famous Ruggers by Wes Clark and others]. Retrieved 19 August 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1956, he married [[Bernadette Chirac|Bernadette Chodron de Courcel]], with whom he had two daughters: Laurence (born 4 March 1958) and Claude (14 January 1962). Claude has long worked as a [[public relations]] assistant and personal adviser,&lt;ref name=b&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/worldservice/europe/europetoday/letters/020321_jlaurenson.shtml |title=BBC World Service: &quot;Letter from Paris – John Laurenson on Claude Chirac's crucial but understated electoral role&quot;. |publisher=BBC News |date=21 March 2002 |accessdate=20 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; while Laurence, who suffered from [[anorexia nervosa]] in her youth, does not participate in the political activities of her father.&lt;ref name=c&gt;Colin Randall, [http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2004/12/07/wchir07.xml&amp;sSheet=/news/2004/12/07/ixworld.html &quot;Chirac's wife tells of anorexic daughter's death wish&quot;]. ''[[Daily Telegraph]]''. 12 July 2004&lt;/ref&gt; Chirac is the grandfather of Martin Rey-Chirac by the relationship of Claude with French [[judoka]] [[Thierry Rey]]. Jacques and Bernadette Chirac also have a foster daughter, [[Anh Dao Traxel]].

[[File:Jacques chirac corrèze 2.jpg|thumb|left|Chirac (right) in the 1960s]]
Inspired by General [[Charles de Gaulle]], Chirac started to pursue a civil service career in the 1950s. During this period, he joined the [[French Communist Party]], sold copies of ''[[L'Humanité]]'', and took part in meetings of a communist cell.&lt;ref name=d&gt;''[[France 3]]'', 12 November 1993&lt;/ref&gt; In 1950, he signed the [[Soviet Union|Soviet]]-inspired [[Stockholm Appeal]] for the abolition of [[nuclear weapons]] – which led him to be questioned when he applied for his first visa to the United States.&lt;ref name=e&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20080608185416/http://www.humanite.fr/1995-05-08_Articles_-Jacques-Chirac-sabre-au-clair Jacques Chirac, sabre au clair]. ''L'Humanité'' 8 May 1995 (in French)&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1953, after graduating from &quot;[[Sciences Po]]&quot; (more formally known as the [[Paris Institute of Political Studies]]), he attended [[Harvard University]]'s summer school, before entering the ENA, the [[Grandes écoles|Grande école]] [[École nationale d'administration|National School of Administration]], which trains France's top civil servants, in 1957.

Chirac trained as a reserve military officer in [[armoured warfare|armoured cavalry]] at [[Saumur]], where he was ranked first in his year.&lt;ref name=f&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20061123131215/http://gouvernement.fr/acteurs/premier_ministre/histoire_chefs_gouvernement_28/jacques_chirac_55/ La biographie de Jacques Chirac]. Portail du Gouvernement – site du Premier ministre. 27 July 2004&lt;/ref&gt; He then volunteered to fight in the [[Algerian War]], using personal connections to be sent despite the reservations of his superiors. His superiors did not want to make him an officer because they suspected he had communist leanings.&lt;ref name=g&gt;Emmanuel Hecht and François Vey ''Chirac de A à Z, dictionnaire critique et impertinent'', A. Michel, 1995, ISBN 2-226-07664-6&lt;/ref&gt; After leaving the ENA in 1959, he became a civil servant in the Court of Auditors.

==Early political career, Cabinet Minister==
In April 1962, Chirac was appointed head of the personal staff of Prime Minister [[Georges Pompidou]]. This appointment launched Chirac's political career. Pompidou considered Chirac his [[protégé]], and referred to him as &quot;my bulldozer&quot; for his skill at getting things done. The nickname &quot;Le Bulldozer&quot; caught on in French political circles. Chirac still maintains this reputation. In 1995 an anonymous British diplomat said Chirac &quot;cuts through the crap and comes straight to the point...It's refreshing, although you have to put your seat belt on when you work with him&quot;.{{Citation needed|date=September 2008}}

At Pompidou's suggestion, Chirac ran as a [[Gaullist]] for a seat in the [[French National Assembly|National Assembly]] in 1967. He was elected deputy for his home [[Corrèze]] ''département'', a stronghold of the left. This surprising victory in the context of a Gaullist ebb permitted him to enter the government as [[Minister of Social Affairs (France)|Minister of Social Affairs]]. Although Chirac was well-situated in de Gaulle's entourage, being related by marriage to the general's sole companion at the time of the [[Appeal of 18 June]] 1940, he was more of a &quot;Pompidolian&quot; than a &quot;Gaullist&quot;. When student and worker unrest rocked France in [[May 1968 in France|May 1968]], Chirac played a central role in negotiating a truce. Then, as state secretary of economy (1968–1971), he worked closely with [[Valéry Giscard d'Estaing]], who headed the ministry of economy and finance.

After some months in the ministry of relations with Parliament, Chirac's first high-level post came in 1972 when he became [[Minister of Agriculture (France)|Minister of Agriculture]] and Rural Development under Pompidou, who had been elected president in 1969, after de Gaulle retired. Chirac quickly earned a reputation as a champion of French farmers' interests, and first attracted international attention when he assailed U.S., [[West German]], and [[European Commission]] agricultural policies which conflicted with French interests.

On 27 February 1974, after the resignation of [[Raymond Marcellin]], Chirac was appointed [[Minister of the Interior (France)|Minister of the Interior]]. On 21 March 1974, he cancelled the [[SAFARI]] project due to privacy concerns after its existence was revealed by ''[[Le Monde]]''. From March 1974, he was entrusted by President Pompidou with preparations for the presidential election then scheduled for 1976. These elections were moved forward because of Pompidou's sudden death on 2 April 1974.

Chirac vainly attempted to rally Gaullists behind Prime minister [[Pierre Messmer]]. [[Jacques Chaban-Delmas]] announced his candidacy in spite of the disapproval of the &quot;Pompidolians&quot;. Chirac and others published the ''call of the 43'' in favour of Giscard d'Estaing, the leader of the non-Gaullist part of the parliamentary majority. Giscard d'Estaing was elected as Pompidou's successor after France's most competitive election campaign in years. In return, the new president chose Chirac to lead the cabinet.

==Prime Minister (1974–1976)==
When [[Valéry Giscard d'Estaing|Giscard]] became president, he nominated Chirac as [[Prime Minister of France|prime minister]] on 27 May 1974, in order to reconcile the &quot;Giscardian&quot; and &quot;non-Giscardian&quot; factions of the parliamentary majority. At the age of 41, Chirac stood out as the very model of the ''jeunes loups'' (&quot;young wolves&quot;) of French politics, but he was faced with the hostility of the &quot;Barons of Gaullism&quot; who considered him a traitor for his role during the previous presidential campaign. In December 1974, he took the lead of the [[Gaullist Party|Union of Democrats for the Republic]] (UDR) against the will of its more senior personalities.

As prime minister, Chirac quickly set about persuading the Gaullists that, despite the social reforms proposed by President Giscard, the basic tenets of Gaullism, such as national and European independence, would be retained. Chirac was advised by Pierre Juillet and [[Marie-France Garaud]], two former advisers of Pompidou. These two organised the campaign against Chaban-Delmas in 1974. They advocated a clash with Giscard d'Estaing because they thought his policy bewildered the conservative electorate. Citing Giscard's unwillingness to give him authority, Chirac resigned as Prime Minister in 1976. He proceeded to build up his political base among France's several conservative parties, with a goal of reconstituting the Gaullist UDR into a neo-Gaullist group, the Rally for the Republic (RPR). Chirac's first tenure as prime minister was also an arguably progressive one, with improvements in both the minimum wage and the social welfare system carried out during the course of his premiership.&lt;ref&gt;https://docs.google.com/viewer?a=v&amp;q=cache:isseic7swS4J:www.ces.fas.harvard.edu/conferences/nordic/papers/France.pdf+http://www.ces.fas.harvard.edu/conferences/nordic/papers/France&amp;hl=en&amp;gl=uk&amp;pid=bl&amp;srcid=ADGEESjE-cEiAnEerRgsYBdxf20ohHeI39Wp8BVMJ8V9Yeq6jmyEXJ92RcPX44AQBfAfN_CVop5BahHR9viWYDmhLJcs7pjiQO14BVJWZUrEM-cOeV15NRVfONmI4z5TfkwgBcP2SFhI&amp;sig=AHIEtbQXdDjodm_gae-WIu0h41nNJE_KkQ&lt;/ref&gt;

==Osirak controversy==
At the invitation of [[Saddam Hussein]] (then vice-president of [[Iraq]], but ''de facto'' dictator), Chirac made an official visit to [[Baghdad]] in 1975. Saddam approved a deal granting French oil companies a number of privileges plus a 23 per cent share of Iraqi oil.&lt;ref name=h&gt;Taheri, Amir, [http://www.nationalreview.com/comment/comment-taheri110402.asp &quot;The Chirac Doctrine: France’s Iraq-war plan&quot;], ''National Review Online'', 4 November 2002&lt;/ref&gt; As part of this deal, France sold Iraq the [[Osirak]] MTR [[nuclear reactor]], a type designed to test nuclear materials.

The [[Israeli Air Force]] alleged that the reactor's imminent commissioning was a threat to its security, and pre-emptively bombed the Osirak reactor on 7 June 1981, provoking considerable anger from French officials and the United Nations Security Council.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/june/7/newsid_3014000/3014623.stm &quot;1981: Israel bombs Baghdad nuclear reactor&quot;], ''On this day – 7 June'', BBC News. Retrieved 5 September 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

The Osirak deal became a controversy again in 2002–2003, when an international [[Multi-National Force – Iraq|military coalition]] led by the United States [[rationale for the Iraq War|invaded Iraq]] and forcibly removed Hussein's government from power. France led several other European countries in an effort to prevent the invasion. The Osirak deal was then used by parts of the American media to criticise the Chirac-led [[opposition to the Iraq War|opposition to starting a war in Iraq]],&lt;ref&gt;Joshua Glenn, [http://www.boston.com/news/packages/iraq/globe_stories/030203_chirac.htm Rebuilding Iraq], ''[[Boston Globe]]'', 2 March 2003&lt;/ref&gt; despite French involvement in the [[Gulf War]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rand.org/pubs/monograph_reports/2007/MR629.pdf |title=Out of Area or Out of Reach? European Military Support for Operations in Southwest Asia |format=PDF |accessdate=13 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Mayor of Paris (1977–1995)==
After his departure from the cabinet, Chirac wanted to gain the leadership of the political right, in order to gain the French presidency in the future. The RPR was conceived as an electoral machine against President Giscard d'Estaing. Paradoxically, Chirac benefited from Giscard's decision to create the office of mayor in Paris, which had been in abeyance since the 1871 [[Paris Commune|Commune]], because the leaders of the [[French Third Republic|Third Republic]] (1871–1940) feared that having municipal control of the capital would give the mayor too much power. In 1977, Chirac stood as a candidate against [[Michel d'Ornano]], a close friend of the president, and he won. As mayor of Paris, Chirac's political influence grew. He held this post until 1995.

Chirac supporters point out that, as mayor, he provided programs to help the elderly, people with disabilities, and single mothers, and introduced the street-cleaning [[Motocrotte]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2002/apr/12/worlddispatch.jonhenley|title=Merde most foul|work=The Guardian |location=UK |date=12 April 2002|accessdate=29 July 2010 | first=Jon | last=Henley}}&lt;/ref&gt; while providing incentives for businesses to stay in Paris. His opponents contend that he installed &quot;clientelist&quot; policies.

===Accused of corruption, convicted===
Chirac has been named in several cases of alleged corruption that occurred during his term as mayor, some of which have led to [[felony]] convictions of some politicians and aides. However, a controversial judicial decision in 1999 granted Chirac immunity while he was president of France. He refused to testify on these matters, arguing that it would be incompatible with his presidential functions. Investigations concerning the running of Paris's city hall, the number of whose municipal employees jumped by 25% from 1977 to 1995 (with 2,000 out of approximately 35,000 coming from the Corrèze region where Chirac had held his seat as deputy), as well as a lack of financial transparency (''marchés publics'') and the communal debt, were thwarted by the legal impossibility of questioning him as president. The conditions of the [[privatisation]] of the Parisian water network, acquired very cheaply by the [[Compagnie Générale des Eaux|Générale]] and the [[Suez Environnement|Lyonnaise des Eaux]], then directed by [[Jérôme Monod]], a close friend of Chirac, were also criticised. Furthermore, the satirical newspaper ''[[Le Canard enchaîné]]'' revealed the astronomical &quot;food expenses&quot; paid by the Parisian municipality (€15 million a year according to the ''Canard''), expenses managed by [[Roger Romani]] (who allegedly destroyed all archives of the period 1978–1993 during night raids in 1999–2000). Thousands of people were invited each year to receptions in the Paris city hall, while many political, media and artistic personalities were hosted in private flats owned by the city.&lt;ref&gt;Jean Guarrigues, professor at the University of [[Orléans]] (and author of ''Les Scandales de la République. De Panama à l'Affaire Elf'', Robert Laffon, 2004), &quot;La dérive des affaires&quot; in ''[[L'Histoire]]'' n° 313, October 2006, pp. 66–71 {{fr icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Chirac's immunity from prosecution ended in May 2007, when he left office as president. In November 2007 a preliminary charge of misuse of public funds was filed against him.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/chirac-faces-investigation-into-misuse-of-public-cash-759026.html|title=Chirac faces investigation into 'misuse of public cash'|date=22 November 2007|work=The Independent |location=London  |accessdate=6 July 2008  | first=John | last=Lichfield}}&lt;/ref&gt; Chirac is said to be the first former French head of state to be formally placed under investigation for a crime.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.capital.fr/Actualite/Default.asp?source=RE&amp;numero=270226&amp;Cat=GEN|title=Le dossier judiciaire de Jacques Chirac s'alourdit|date=22 February 2008|work=Capital.fr|accessdate=6 July 2008|language=fr}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 30 October 2009, a judge ordered Chirac to stand trial on [[embezzlement]] charges, dating back to his time as mayor of Paris.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/10/31/world/europe/31chirac.html|title=Frances Chirac Ordered to Face Trial|date=30 October 2009|author=Alan Cowell|work=The New York Times|accessdate=30 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 15 December 2011, Chirac was found guilty in two related cases, involving 19 totally or partially fake jobs created for his benefit by the RPR Party, which he led as Paris mayor from 1977 to 1995. He was convicted of embezzling public funds, abuse of trust, and illegal [[conflict of interest]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/french-ex-president-chirac-convicted-of-corruption/2011/12/15/gIQAfp97vO_story.html|author=Edward Cody|title=Former French leader Jacques Chirac convicted of corruption for his Paris mayor days|date=16 December 2011|work=The Washington Post|accessdate=16 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{See also|Corruption scandals in the Paris region}}

==Struggle for the right-wing leadership==
In 1978, he attacked the [[pro-European]] policy of [[Valéry Giscard d'Estaing]] (VGE), and made a nationalist turn with the December 1978 [[Call of Cochin]], initiated by his counsellors [[Marie-France Garaud]] and [[Pierre Juillet]], which had first been called by Pompidou. Hospitalised in Cochin hospital after a crash, he declared that &quot;as always about the drooping of France, the pro-foreign party acts with its peaceable and reassuring voice&quot;. He appointed [[Ivan Blot]], an intellectual who would later join the [[National Front (France)|National Front]], as director of his campaigns for the [[European Parliament elections, 1979|1979 European election]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Slama&quot;&gt;[[:fr:Alain-Gérard Slama|Alain-Gérard Slama]], &quot;Vous avez dit bonapartiste?&quot; in ''L'Histoire'' n°313, October 2006, pp.60–63 {{fr icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the poor results of the election, Chirac broke with Garaud and Juillet. His rivalry with Giscard d'Estaing intensified. Although it has been often interpreted by historians as the struggle between two rival French right-wing families (the [[Bonapartist]]s, represented by Chirac, and the [[Orleanist]]s, represented by VGE), both figures in fact were members of the Liberal, Orleanist tradition, according to historian Alain-Gérard Slama.&lt;ref name=&quot;Slama&quot;/&gt; But the eviction of the Gaullist Barons and of President VGE convinced Chirac to assume a strong neo-Gaullist stance.

Chirac made his first run for president against Giscard d'Estaing in the [[French presidential election, 1981|1981 election]], thus splitting the centre-right vote. He was eliminated in the first round with 18% of the vote. He reluctantly supported Giscard in the second round. He refused to give instructions to the RPR voters but said that he supported the incumbent president &quot;in a private capacity&quot;, which was almost like a ''de facto'' support of the [[French Socialist Party|Socialist Party]]'s (PS) candidate, [[François Mitterrand]], who was elected by a broad majority.

Giscard has always blamed Chirac for his defeat. He was told by Mitterrand, before his death, that the latter had dined with Chirac before the election. Chirac told the Socialist candidate that he wanted to &quot;get rid of Giscard&quot;. In his memoirs, Giscard wrote that between the two rounds, he phoned the RPR headquarters. He passed himself off as a right-wing voter by changing his voice. The RPR employee advised him &quot;certainly do not vote Giscard!&quot;. After 1981, the relationship between the two men became tense, with Giscard, even though he was in the same government coalition as Chirac, criticising Chirac's actions openly.

After the May 1981 presidential election, the right also lost the subsequent [[French legislative election, 1981|legislative election]] that year. However, as Giscard had been knocked out, Chirac appeared as the principal leader of the right-wing opposition. Due to his attacks against the economic policy of the Socialist government, he gradually aligned himself with prevailing economic liberal opinion, even though it did not correspond with Gaullist doctrine. While the far-right National Front grew, taking advantage of a [[proportional representation]] electoral law, he signed an electoral platform with the Giscardian (and more or less Christian Democrat) party [[Union for French Democracy]] (UDF).

==First &quot;cohabitation&quot; (1986–1988) and &quot;desert crossing&quot;==
[[File:Jacques Chirac mid-eighties.jpg|thumb|Chirac during his second term as Prime Minister]]
When the RPR/UDF right-wing coalition won a slight majority in the National Assembly in the [[French legislative election, 1986|1986 election]], Mitterrand (PS) appointed Chirac prime minister (though many in Mitterrand's inner circle lobbied him to choose [[Jacques Chaban-Delmas]] instead). This unprecedented power-sharing arrangement, known as [[cohabitation (government)|cohabitation]], gave Chirac the lead in domestic affairs. However, it is generally conceded that Mitterrand used the areas granted to the President of the Republic, or &quot;reserved domains&quot; of the Presidency, Defense and Foreign Affairs, to belittle his Prime Minister.

===Chirac's second ministry===
(20 March 1986 – 12 May 1988)
*'''Jacques Chirac''' – Prime Minister
*[[Jean-Bernard Raimond]] – Minister of Foreign Affairs
*[[André Giraud]] – Minister of Defence
*[[Charles Pasqua]] – Minister of the Interior
*[[Édouard Balladur]] – Minister of Economy, Finance, and Privatisation
*[[Alain Madelin]] – Minister of Industry, Tourism, Posts, and Telecommunications
*[[Philippe Séguin]] – Minister of Employment and Social Affairs
*[[Albin Chalandon]] – Minister of Justice
*[[René Monory]] – Minister of National Education
*[[François Léotard]] – Minister of Culture and Communications
*[[François Guillaume]] – Minister of Agriculture
*[[Bernard Pons]] – Minister of Overseas Departments and Territories
*[[Pierre Méhaignerie]] – Minister of Housing, Equipment, Regional Planning, and Transport
*[[André Rossinot]] – Minister of Relations with Parliament
*[[Michel Aurillac]] – Minister of Cooperation

Chirac's cabinet [[Privatization|sold many public companies]], renewing with the [[liberalisation]] initiated under [[Laurent Fabius]]'s Socialist government (1984–86 – in particular with Fabius' privatisation of the audiovisual sector, leading to the creation of [[Canal +]]), and abolished the [[solidarity tax on wealth]] (ISF), a symbolic tax on very high resources championed by Mitterrand's government. Elsewhere, the plan for university reform (plan Devaquet) caused a crisis in 1986 when a young man named [[Malik Oussekine]] (1964–1986) was killed by the police, leading to massive demonstrations and the proposal's withdrawal. It has been said during other student crises that this event strongly affected Jacques Chirac, who was hereafter careful about possible [[police violence]] during such demonstrations (i.e. maybe explaining part of the decision to &quot;promulgate without applying&quot; the [[First Employment Contract]] (CPE) after [[2006 labor protests in France|large student demonstrations against it]]).

One of his first acts concerning foreign policy was to call back [[Jacques Foccart]] (1913–1997), who had been de Gaulle's and his successors' leading counsellor for African matters, called by journalist [[Stephen Smith (journalist)|Stephen Smith]] the &quot;father of all &quot;networks&quot; on the continent, at the time [in 1986] aged 72.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith&quot;&gt;&quot;Naufrage de la [[Françafrique]] – Le président a poursuivi une politique privilégiant les hommes forts au pouvoir.&quot;, [[Stephen Smith (journalist)|Stephen Smith]] in ''L'Histoire'' n°313, October 2006 (special issue on Chirac), p.70 {{fr icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jacques Foccart, who had also co-founded the Gaullist ''[[Service d'Action Civique]]'' (SAC, dissolved by Mitterrand in 1982) along with Charles Pasqua, and who was a key component of the &quot;[[Françafrique]]&quot; system, was again called to the [[Elysée Palace]] when Chirac won the 1995 presidential election. Furthermore, confronted by [[anti-colonialism|anti-colonialist movements]] in [[New Caledonia]], Prime Minister Chirac ordered a military intervention against the separatists in the Ouvéa cave, leading to several tragic deaths. He allegedly refused any alliance with [[Jean-Marie Le Pen]]'s ''Front National''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.theage.com.au/articles/2002/04/24/1019441263037.html |title=Chirac labels 'racist' Le Pen as threat to nation's soul |work=The Age |location=Australia |date=25 April 2002 |accessdate=20 April 2010 | first=Harry | last=de Quetteville}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1988 presidential elections and afterwards===
Chirac ran against Mitterrand for a second time in the [[French presidential election, 1988|1988 election]]. He obtained 20 percent of the vote in the first round, but lost the second with only 46 percent. He resigned from the cabinet and the right lost the [[French legislative election, 1988|next legislative election]].

For the first time, his leadership over the RPR was challenged. [[Charles Pasqua]] and [[Philippe Séguin]] criticised his abandonment of Gaullist doctrines. On the right, a new generation of politicians, the &quot;renovation men&quot;, accused Chirac and Giscard of being responsible for the electoral defeats. In 1992, convinced a man could not become President whilst advocating anti-European policies, he called for a &quot;yes&quot; vote in the referendum on the [[Maastricht Treaty]], against the opinion of Pasqua, Séguin and a majority of the RPR voters, who chose to vote &quot;no&quot;.

While he still was mayor of Paris (since 1977), Chirac went to [[Abidjan]] (Côte d'Ivoire) where he supported [[Félix Houphouët-Boigny|President Houphouët-Boigny]] (1960–1993), although the latter was being called a &quot;thief&quot; by the local population. Chirac then declared that [[multiparty democracy|multipartism]] was a &quot;kind of luxury.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith&quot;&gt;&quot;Naufrage de la Françafrique – Le président a poursuivi une politique privilégiant les hommes forts au pouvoir.&quot;, Stephen Smith in ''L'Histoire'' n°313, October 2006 (special issue on Chirac), p.70 {{fr icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Nevertheless, the right won the [[French legislative election, 1993|1993 legislative election]]. Chirac announced that he did not want to come back as prime minister, suggesting the appointment of [[Edouard Balladur]], who had promised that he would not run for the presidency against Chirac in 1995. However, benefiting from positive polls, Balladur decided to be a presidential candidate, with the support of a majority of right-wing politicians. Chirac broke at that time with a number of friends and allies, including Charles Pasqua, [[Nicolas Sarkozy]], etc., who supported Balladur's candidacy. A small group of &quot;fidels&quot; would remain with him, including [[Alain Juppé]] and [[Jean-Louis Debré]]. When Nicolas Sarkozy became President in 2007, Juppé was one of the few &quot;chiraquiens&quot; to serve in François Fillon's government.

==First term as President (1995–2002)==
[[File:Clintonchirac.jpg|thumb|left|Chirac with [[Bill Clinton]] outside the [[Élysée Palace]] in Paris, June 1999]]

During the [[French presidential election, 1995|1995 presidential campaign]], Chirac criticised the &quot;sole thought&quot; (''[[pensée unique]]'') of [[neoliberalism]] represented by his challenger on the right and promised to reduce the &quot;social fracture&quot;, placing himself more to the center and thus forcing Balladur to [[Political radicalism|radicalise]] himself. Ultimately, he obtained more votes than Balladur in the first round (20.8 percent), and then defeated the [[Socialist Party (France)|Socialist]] candidate [[Lionel Jospin]] in the second round (52.6 percent).

Chirac was elected on a platform of tax cuts and job programs, but his policies did little to ease the labor strikes during his first months in office. On the domestic front, neo-liberal economic austerity measures introduced by Chirac and his conservative prime minister [[Alain Juppé]], including budgetary cutbacks, proved highly unpopular. At about the same time, it became apparent that Juppé and others had obtained preferential conditions for public housing, as well as other perks. At the year's end Chirac faced [[1995 strikes in France|major workers' strikes]] which turned itself, in November–December 1995, into a [[general strike]], one of the largest since May 1968. The demonstrations were largely pitted against Juppé's plan on the reform of pensions, and led to the dismissal of the latter.

Shortly after taking office, Chirac{{spaced ndash}}undaunted by international protests by environmental groups{{spaced ndash}}insisted upon the resumption of [[nuclear weapons and France|nuclear tests at Mururoa Atoll]] in [[French Polynesia]] in 1995, a few months before signing the [[Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.acronym.org.uk/a09comp.htm |title=Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty |publisher=Acronym.org.uk |accessdate=20 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reacting to criticism, Chirac said, &quot;You only have to look back at 1935...There were people then who were against France arming itself, and look what happened.&quot; On 1 February 1996, Chirac announced that France had ended &quot;once and for all&quot; its nuclear testing, intending to accede to the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty.

Elected as President of the Republic, he refused to discuss the existence of French military bases in Africa, despite requests by the Ministry of Defence and the ''[[Quai d'Orsay]]'' (Ministry of Foreign Affairs).&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith&quot; /&gt; The French Army thus remained in Côte d'Ivoire as well as in [[Omar Bongo]]'s [[Gabon]].
[[File:Chirac and Schroeder on the Neva.jpg|thumb|Chirac with German Federal Chancellor [[Gerhard Schröder]].]]
[[File:Vladimir Putin 2 July 2001-5.jpg|thumb|right|Chirac with then-Russian President [[Vladimir Putin]] in 2001]]
[[File:Bush and Chirac.jpg|thumb|Chirac and [[George W. Bush]] during the [[27th G8 summit]], 21 July 2001.]]

In 1997, Chirac dissolved parliament for early legislative elections in a gamble designed to bolster support for his conservative economic program. But instead, it created an uproar, and his power was weakened by the subsequent backlash. The Socialist Party (PS), joined by other parties on the left, soundly defeated Chirac's conservative allies, forcing Chirac into a new period of cohabitation with Jospin as prime minister (1997–2002), which lasted five years.

Cohabitation significantly weakened the power of Chirac's presidency. The French president, by a [[constitutional convention (political custom)|constitutional convention]], only controls foreign and military policy— and even then, allocation of funding is under the control of Parliament and under the significant influence of the prime minister. Short of dissolving parliament and calling for new elections, the president was left with little power to influence public policy regarding crime, the economy, and public services. Chirac seized the occasion to periodically criticise Jospin's government.

Nevertheless, his position was weakened by [[Corruption scandals in the Paris region|scandals about the financing of RPR by Paris municipality]]. In 2001, the left, represented by [[Bertrand Delanoë]] (PS), won over the majority in the town council of the capital. [[Jean Tiberi]], Chirac's successor at the Paris townhall, was forced to resign after having been put under investigations in June 1999 on charges of ''[[influence peddling|trafic d'influences]]'' in the [[HLM]]s of Paris affairs (related to the illegal financing of the RPR). Tiberi was finally expelled from the [[Rally for the Republic|RPR]], Chirac's party, on 12 October 2000, declaring to the ''[[Le Figaro|Figaro magazine]]'' on 18 November 2000: &quot;Jacques Chirac is not my friend anymore&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Rien ne va plus entre Chirac et Tiberi&quot;, ''[[Le Figaro]]'', 18 November 2000 {{fr icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the publication of the [[Jean-Claude Méry|Méry video-tape]] by ''[[Le Monde]]'' on 22 September 2000, in which Jean-Claude Méry, in charge of the RPR's financing, directly accused Chirac of organizing the network, and of having been physically present on 5 October 1986, when Méry gave in cash 5 millions [[Franc]]s, which came from companies who had benefited from state deals, to [[Michel Roussin]], personal secretary (''directeur de cabinet'') of Chirac,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lemonde.fr/cgi-bin/ACHATS/acheter.cgi?offre=ARCHIVES&amp;type_item=ART_ARCH_30J&amp;objet_id=101715 &quot;Un témoignage pour l'histoire&quot;], ''Le Monde'', 22 September 2000 {{fr icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lemonde.fr/web/recherche_breve/1,13-0,37-101887,0.html La suite du testament de Jean-Claude Méry], ''Le Monde'', 23 September 2000 {{fr icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; Chirac refused to follow up his summons by judge [[Eric Halphen]], and the highest echelons of the French justice declared that he could not been inculpated while in functions.

During his two terms, he increased the Elysee Palace's total budget by 105 percent (currently €90&amp;nbsp;million, whereas 20 years ago it was the equivalent of €43.7&amp;nbsp;million). He doubled the number of presidential cars – nowadays there are 61 cars and seven scooters in the Palace's garage. He has hired 145 extra employees – the total number of the people he employed simultaneously was 963.

===Defence policy===
As the Supreme Commander of the French armed forces, he has reduced the French military budget, as did his predecessor. It now accounts for three percent of GDP.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/rankorder/2034rank.html CIA – The World Factbook – Rank Order – Military expenditures – percent of GDP]. Cia.gov. Retrieved 17 December 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1998 the [[French aircraft carrier Clemenceau (R98)]] was decommissioned after 37 years of service, and another aircraft carrier was decommissioned two years later after 37 years of service, leaving the French Navy with no aircraft carrier until 2001, when [[Charles de Gaulle (R 91)|Charles de Gaulle aircraft carrier]] was commissioned.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.netmarine.net/bat/porteavi/cdg/index.htm |title=Porte-avions Charles de Gaulle |publisher=Netmarine.net |accessdate=20 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; He has also reduced expenditures on nuclear weapons&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=John Pike |url=http://www.globalsecurity.org/wmd/world/france/nuke.htm |title=Nuclear Weapons – France Nuclear Forces |publisher=[[GlobalSecurity.org]] |accessdate=20 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the French nuclear arsenal now includes 350 warheads, which can be compared to the Russian nuclear arsenal that consists of 16,000 warheads.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=John Pike |url=http://www.globalsecurity.org/wmd/world/summary.htm |title=Worldwide Nuclear Forces |publisher=Globalsecurity.org |accessdate=20 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; He has also published a plan which assumes reducing the number of fighters the French military has by 30.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.defense.gouv.fr/air/contents_in_english/french_air_force/the_future/the_future ]{{Dead link|date=April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Second term as president (2002–2007)==
{{Main|Jacques Chirac's second term as President of France}}

At the age of 69, Chirac faced his fourth presidential campaign in 2002. He received just 20% of the vote in the first ballot of the [[French presidential elections, 2002|presidential elections]] in April 2002. It had been expected that he would face incumbent prime minister [[Lionel Jospin]] (PS) in the second round of elections; instead, Chirac faced controversial far right politician [[Jean-Marie Le Pen]] of [[National Front (France)|National Front]] (FN) who came in 200,000 votes ahead of Jospin. All parties outside the National Front (except for ''[[Lutte ouvrière]]'') called for opposing Le Pen, even if it meant voting for Chirac. The 14-day period between the two rounds of voting was marked by demonstrations against Le Pen and slogans such as &quot;Vote for the crook, not for the fascist&quot; or &quot;Vote with a clothespin on your nose&quot;. Chirac won re-election by a landslide, with 82 percent of the vote on the second ballot. However, Chirac became increasingly unpopular during his second term. According to a July 2005 poll,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=10000085&amp;sid=aXp5XEjdZ3_k&amp;refer=europe |title=Europe |publisher=Bloomberg  |date=2 June 2005 |accessdate=20 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; 32 percent judged Chirac favorably and 63 percent unfavorably. In 2006, ''[[The Economist]]'' wrote that Chirac &quot;is the most unpopular occupant of the Elysée Palace in the fifth republic's history.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;economistneeds&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.economist.com/opinion/displaystory.cfm?story_id=8080753|title=What France needs|accessdate=5 August 2007|date=26 October 2006|work=The Economist}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Early term===
As the left-wing Socialist Party was in thorough disarray following Jospin's defeat, Chirac reorganised politics on the [[right-wing|right]], establishing a new party – initially called the Union of the Presidential Majority, then the [[Union for a Popular Movement]] (UMP). The RPR had broken down; A number of members had formed [[Eurosceptic]] breakaways. While the Giscardian liberals of the Union of French Democracy ([[Union for French Democracy|UDF]]) had moved to the right.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20080512001044/http://www.turkishdailynews.com.tr/archives.php?id=8465 More conservative infighting over links to French far right] [[Associated Press]] via ''Turkish Daily News''. 15 August 1998&lt;/ref&gt; The UMP won the [[French legislative election, 2002|parliamentary elections]] that followed the presidential poll with ease.

During an official visit to [[Madagascar]] on 21 July 2005, Chirac described the repression of the 1947 [[Malagasy uprising]], which left between 80,000 and 90,000 dead, as &quot;unacceptable&quot;.

Despite past opposition to state intervention the Chirac government approved a 2.8&amp;nbsp;billion euro aid package to troubled manufacturing giant [[Alstom]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.archive.org/web/20080509043726/http://www.iht.com/articles/2003/08/08/alstom_1.php|author=Eric Pfanner |title=France's §2.8&amp;nbsp;billion aid package unlikely to bring quick fix : Alstom bailout may be long haul |work=International Herald Tribune |date=8 August 2003 |accessdate=20 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In October 2004, Chirac signed a [[trade agreement]] with PRC President [[Hu Jintao]] where Alstom was given one billion euro in contracts and promises of future investment in China.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.people.com.cn/200410/10/eng20041010_159619.html |title=People's Daily Online – France's Alstom, China ink $1.3b contracts |work=People's Daily  |date=10 October 2004 |accessdate=20 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Assassination attempt===
On 14 July 2002, during [[Bastille Day]] celebrations, Chirac survived an assassination attempt by a lone gunman with a rifle hidden in a guitar case. The would-be assassin fired a shot toward the presidential [[motorcade]], before being overpowered by bystanders.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/hi/english/world/europe/newsid_2127000/2127946.stm Chirac escapes lone gunman's bullet], ''BBC'', 15 July 2002&lt;/ref&gt; The gunman, [[Maxime Brunerie]], underwent psychiatric testing; the violent far-right group with which he was associated, [[Unité Radicale]], was then administratively dissolved.

===Stroke===
In early September 2005, he suffered an event that his doctors described as a 'vascular incident'. It was reported as a 'minor stroke'&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Willsher |first=Kim |url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/france/1497612/Minor-stroke-puts-Chirac-in-hospital-but-he-hangs-on-to-reins-of-government.html |title=Minor stroke puts Chirac in hospital but he hangs on to reins of government |work=The Daily Telegraph |location=London   |date=4 September 2005 |accessdate=20 April 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; or a mini-stroke (also known as a [[transient ischemic attack]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-10722229.html |title=Belfast Telegraph |publisher=Highbeam.com |date=6 September 2005 |accessdate=20 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; He recovered and returned to his duties soon after.

===2005 referendum on the TCE===
{{Further|Treaty establishing a Constitution for Europe}}

On 29 May 2005, a [[referendum]] was held in France to decide whether the country should ratify the proposed treaty for a [[Constitution of the European Union]] (TCE). The result was a victory for the No campaign, with 55 percent of voters rejecting the treaty on a turnout of 69 percent, dealing a devastating blow to Chirac and the [[Union for a Popular Movement|UMP]] party, as well as to part of the center-left which had supported the TCE.
&lt;!-- In an address to the nation, Chirac has declared that the new cabinet's top priority would be to curb the unemployment level, which consistently hovers above 10 percent, calling for a &quot;national mobilisation&quot; to that effect. WHICH ADRESS? No sources, and that is a rather usual statement for politicians --&gt;

===Foreign policy===
Along with [[Vladimir Putin]] (Chirac called Vladimir Putin &quot;a personal friend&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.economist.com/node/15578042 |title=Europe's bear problem |date=25 February 2010 |work=The Economist }}&lt;/ref&gt;), [[Hu Jintao]], and [[Gerhard Schröder]], Chirac emerged as a leading voice against [[George W. Bush]] in 2003 during the organization and deployment of the United States led [[Coalition of the willing|military coalition]] to [[Deposition (politics)|forcibly remove]] the then current government of [[Iraq]] controlled by the [[Ba'ath Party]] under the leadership of [[Saddam Hussein]] and resulted in the 2003–2011 [[Iraq War]]. Despite intense US pressure, Chirac threatened to veto, at that given point, a resolution in the [[UN Security Council]] that would authorise the use of military force to rid [[Iraq and weapons of mass destruction|Iraq of alleged weapons of mass destruction]], and rallied other governments to his position. &quot;Iraq today does not represent an immediate threat that justifies an immediate war&quot;, Chirac said on 18 March 2003. Chirac was then the target of various American and British commentators supporting the decisions of Bush and [[Tony Blair]]. Future Prime Minister [[Dominique de Villepin]] acquired much of his popularity for his speech against the war at the United Nations (UN).
After [[Togo]]'s leader [[Gnassingbé Eyadéma]]'s death on 5 February 2005, Chirac gave him tribute and supported his son, [[Faure Gnassingbé]], who has since succeeded to his father.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith&quot; /&gt;

On 19 January 2006, Chirac said that France was prepared to launch a [[nuclear warfare|nuclear strike]] against any country that sponsors a [[List of terrorist incidents|terrorist attack]] against French interests. He said his country's [[Force de frappe|nuclear arsenal]] had been reconfigured to include the ability to make a tactical strike in retaliation for terrorism.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/01/19/AR2006011903311.html Chirac: Nuclear Response to Terrorism Is Possible], ''[[The Washington Post]]'', 20 January 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 2006, the [[G8]] met to discuss international energy concerns. Despite the rising awareness of [[global warming]] issues, the G8 focuses on &quot;[[energy security]]&quot; issues. Chirac continues to be the voice within the G8 summit meetings to support international action to curb global warming and [[climate change]] concerns. Chirac warns that &quot;humanity is dancing on a [[volcano]]&quot; and calls for serious action by the world's leading industrialised nations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cutco2.org/2006/07/chirac-is-not-in-favor-of-dancing-on.html Chirac is Not in Favor of Dancing on Volcanoes], on &quot;CutC02&quot;'s website, 17 July 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

===2005 civil unrest and CPE protests===
{{Further|2005 civil unrest in France |2006 labour protests in France}}

Following major [[2006 labour protests in France|student protests in spring 2006]], which followed [[2005 civil unrest in France|civil unrest]] in autumn 2005 after the death of two young boys in [[Clichy-sous-Bois]], one of the poorest French commune located in Paris' suburbs, Chirac retracted the proposed [[First Employment Contract]] (CPE) by &quot;promulgating [it] without applying it&quot;, an unheard-of – and, some claim, illegal – move destined to appease the protests while giving the appearance not to retract himself, and therefore to continue his support towards his Prime Minister [[Dominique de Villepin]].

===Flight tax===

Chirac requested the ''[http://www.diplomatie.gouv.fr/en/IMG/pdf/LandauENG1.pdf Landau-report]'' (published in September 2004) and combined with the ''[http://www.diplomatie.gouv.fr/en/IMG/pdf/rapportdugroupequadripartite.pdf Report of the Technical Group on Innovative Financing Mechanisms]'' formulated upon request by the Heads of State of Brazil, Chile, France and Spain (issued in December 2004), these documents present various opportunities for innovative financing mechanisms while equally stressing the advantages (stability and predictability) of tax-based models. [[UNITAID]] project was born. Today the organisation executive board is chaired by [[Philippe Douste-Blazy]].

===The Clearstream affair===
{{Further|Clearstream}}

During April and May 2006, Chirac's administration was beset by a crisis as his chosen Prime Minister, Dominique de Villepin, was accused of asking [[Philippe Rondot]], a top level French [[espionage|spy]], for a secret investigation into Villepin's chief political rival, [[Nicolas Sarkozy]], in 2004. This matter has been called the second [[Clearstream Affair]]. On 10 May 2006, following a Cabinet meeting, Chirac made a rare television appearance to try to protect Villepin from the scandal and to debunk allegations that Chirac himself had set up a Japanese bank account containing 300&amp;nbsp;million francs in 1992 as Mayor of Paris.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,542-2174662,00.html French farce], ''[[The Times]]'', 11 May 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Chirac said that &quot;The Republic is not a dictatorship of rumors, a dictatorship of calumny.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,3-2174839,00.html Caught in deep water: Chirac swims against a tide of scandal], ''The Times'', 11 May 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

===Announcement of intention not to seek a third term===
In a pre-recorded television broadcast aired on 11 March 2007, Jacques Chirac announced, in a widely predicted move, that he would not choose to seek a third term as France's President. &quot;My whole life has been committed to serving France, and serving peace&quot;, Chirac said, adding that he would find new ways to serve France after leaving office. He did not explain the reasons for his decision.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iht.com/articles/ap/2007/03/12/europe/EU-POL-France-Chiracs-Future.php France's Chirac says he will not run for re-election] Associated Press, 11 March 2007. Retrieved 11 March 2007&lt;/ref&gt; Chirac did not, during the broadcast, endorse any of the candidates running for election, but did devote several minutes of his talk to a plea against extremist politics that was considered a thinly disguised invocation to voters not to vote for [[Jean-Marie Le Pen]] and a recommendation to [[Nicolas Sarkozy]] not to orient his campaign so as to include themes traditionally associated with Le Pen.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/03/11/AR2007031101091.html Chirac Leaving Stage Admired and Scorned] by John Leicester, Associated Press, 11 March 2007. Retrieved 11 March 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Opinion on hijab==

French President Jacques Chirac declared his complete rejection of the wearing of the Islamic headscarf, or [[hijab]], by female Muslims in French schools and public corporations. He adds that he perceives a kind of hostility in the wearing of the hijab. Chirac stated that with banning the hijab, there will be more integration in French society. He has contributed in establishing a law that prohibits wearing the hijab and other religious symbols and manifestations in schools and public corporations. {{dubious|This has created small controversy in France as some Muslims believe they are being discriminated against.|date=May 2012}}{{Verify credibility|date=May 2012}}&lt;ref&gt;http://www.arabwestreport.info/?q=node/12158 (Arab West Report: Art. 28, Week 50/2003, 10–15 December)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Life after presidency==
Shortly after leaving office, he launched the [[Fondation Chirac]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://afp.google.com/article/ALeqM5jyHbiQwT8A2VnasPh30A3G8kbt3w |title=Chirac launches foundation 'to awaken consciences' |agency=AFP   |date=8 June 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; in June 2008. Since then it has been striving for peace through five advocacy programmes:
conflict prevention, access to water and sanitation, access to quality medicines and healthcare, access to land resources, and preservation of cultural diversity. It supports field projects that involve local people and provide concrete and innovative solutions. Chirac chairs the jury for the [[Fondation Chirac Prize for Conflict Prevention|Prize for Conflict Prevention]] awarded every year by his foundation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fondationchirac.eu/en/the-fondation-chirac-prize-for-conflict-prevention/ The Fondation Chirac Prize for Conflict Prevention]&lt;/ref&gt;

He also became a lifetime member of the [[Constitutional Council of France]]. He sat for the first time in the Council on 15 November 2007, six months after leaving the French Presidency. Immediately after Sarkozy's victory, Chirac moved into a 180 square meters duplex on the Quai Voltaire in Paris lent to him by the family of former [[Lebanon|Lebanese]] Prime Minister [[Rafik Hariri]]. During the [[Didier Schuller]] affair, the latter accused Hariri of having participated to the illegal funding of the [[Rally for the Republic|RPR]]'s political campaigns, but the justice closed the case without further investigations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.liberation.fr/actualite/politiques/250314.FR.php Chirac trouve un point de chute à Paris chez la famille Hariri], ''[[Libération]]'', 27 April 2007 {{fr icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 11 April 2008, Chirac's office announced that he had undergone successful surgery to fit a [[pacemaker]]. In January 2009, it was reported that Chirac had been hospitalised after being attacked by his pet [[Maltese (dog)|Maltese]] poodle. According to Chirac's wife Bernadette, the dog, named Sumo, had a history of unpredictable and vicious behavior, and had previously been medicated with antidepressants in an attempt to control it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=President Chirac hospitalised after mauling by his clinically depressed poodle |publisher=[[Daily Mail]]'' (London) |date=21 January 2009 |url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/worldnews/article-1126136/Former-French-President-Chirac-hospitalised-mauling-clinically-depressed-poodle.html?ITO=1490 |first=Ian |last=Sparks}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Embezzlement trial===
On 7 March 2011, he went on trial for charges of corruption (the first former French head of state to stand trial since [[Philippe Pétain]], who surrendered and collaborated with Nazi Germany) involving the misuse of public money during his time as [[mayor of Paris]] (1977–1995).&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc trial opens&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-12661446 | title=France: Jacques Chirac corruption trial opens | accessdate=8 March 2011 | date=7 March 2011 |publisher=BBC News   | archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5x1Fr7GjO | archivedate=8 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was accused of paying cronies and political allies for 28 jobs that did not exist.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc trial opens&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;tele&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/france/8366721/Jacques-Chirac-trial-faces-further-delays.html | title=Jacques Chirac trial faces further delays | accessdate=8 March 2011 | date=7 March 2011 | publisher=The Telegraph | archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5x1FyQ5W1 | archivedate=8 March 2011 | first=Henry | last=Samuel}}&lt;/ref&gt; Along with Chirac, nine others stood trial in two separate cases, one dealing with fictional jobs for 21 people and the other with jobs for the remaining seven.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc trial opens&quot; /&gt; France's current Minister of Foreign Affairs, [[Alain Juppé]], was sentenced to a 14-month suspended prison sentence for the same case in 2004.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC guilty 15 December&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=French ex-President Jacques Chirac guilty of corruption|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-16194089|publisher=BBC  |accessdate=15 December 2011|date=15 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 15 December 2011, Chirac was found guilty and given a suspended sentence of two years.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC guilty 15 December&quot; /&gt; He was convicted of embezzling public funds, abuse of trust and illegal conflict of interest. The suspended sentence means he does not have to go to prison, and took into account his age, health, and status as a former head of state when determining the sentence.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/dec/15/jacques-chirac-guilty-corruption &quot;Jacques Chirac found guilty of corruption&quot;], ''Guardian'', 15 December 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; He did not attend his trial, since medical doctors deemed that his neurological problems damaged his memory.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC guilty 15 December&quot; /&gt; His defense team decided not to appeal.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC guilty 15 December&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/12/16/world/europe/chirac-found-guilty-in-political-funding-case.html|title=Chirac Found Guilty in Political Funding Case|date=15 December 2011|work=The New York Times|accessdate=15 December 2011|first=Steven|last=Erlanger}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As a former President, he is entitled to a lifetime pension&lt;!-- Of how much? --&gt; and personal security protection, and is ex-officio a member for life of France's constitutional council.&lt;ref name=&quot;CNN Chirac found guilty&quot;&gt;[http://articles.cnn.com/2011-12-15/world/world_europe_france-chirac_1_chirac-francois-hollande-corruption-charges?_s=PM:EUROPE &quot;Chirac found guilty on corruption charges&quot;], CNN.com, 15 December 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Memoirs and popularity===
In Volume 2 of his memoirs published in June 2011, Chirac mocked his successor [[Nicolas Sarkozy]] as &quot;irritable, rash, impetuous, disloyal, ungrateful, and un-French&quot;.&lt;ref name=FE&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-13710626 &quot;France election 2012: Chirac mocks Sarkozy in memoirs&quot;], BBC. 9 June 2011. Retrieved 9 June 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/impetuous-disloyal-and-unfrench-chirac-attempts-coup-de-grace-on-sarkozy-2294940.html &quot;'Impetuous, disloyal, and un-French': Chirac attempts coup de grace on Sarkozy&quot;], John Lichfield. 9 June 2011. Retrieved 9 June 2011&lt;/ref&gt; Chirac wrote he considered firing Sarkozy before, and conceded responsibility in allowing [[Jean Marie Le Pen]] to advance in 2002.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/france/8564184/Jacques-Chirac-breaks-four-year-silence-on-Nicolas-Sarkozy-to-criticise-French-president.html &quot;Jacques Chirac breaks four-year silence on Nicolas Sarkozy to criticise French president&quot;], Henry Samuel. The Telegraph. 9 June 2011. Retrieved 9 June 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

A poll conducted in 2010 suggested he was the most admired political figure in France, while Sarkozy was 32nd.&lt;ref name=FE /&gt;

==In culture==

===Impact on French popular culture===
Because of Jacques Chirac's long career in visible government positions, he has often been parodied or caricatured: Young Jacques Chirac is the basis of a young, dashing bureaucrat character in the 1976 [[Asterix]] comic strip album ''[[Obelix and Co.]]'', proposing methods to quell Gallic unrest to elderly, old-style Roman politicians. Chirac was also featured in ''[[Le Bêbête Show]]'' as an overexcited, jumpy character.

Jacques Chirac is a favorite character of ''[[Les Guignols de l'Info]]'', a satiric latex [[puppet show]]. He was once portrayed as a rather likable, though overexcited, character; however, following the corruption allegations, he has been shown as a kind of dilettante and incompetent who pilfers public money and lies through his teeth. His character for a while developed a [[superhero]] alter ego, ''Super Menteur'' (&quot;Super Liar&quot;) in order to get him out of embarrassing situations. Because of his alleged improprieties, he was lambasted in a song ''Chirac en prison'' (&quot;Chirac in jail&quot;) by French punk band [[Les Wampas]], with a video clip made by the ''Guignols''.

===Portrayals in film===
His role is played by [[Charles Fathy]] in the [[Oliver Stone]] film ''[[W. (film)|W.]]'' and in ''La conquête'' by Bernard Le Coq.

Marc Rioufol plays Chirac in [[Richard Loncraine]]'s 2010 film ''[[The Special Relationship (film)|The Special Relationship]]''.

==Political career==
President of the French Republic: 1995–2007. Reelected in 2002.

Member of the [[Constitutional Council of France]]: Since 2007.

'''Governmental functions'''

Prime minister: 1974–1976 (Resignation) / 1986–1988.

Minister of Interior: March–May 1974.

Minister of Agriculture and Rural Development: 1972–1974.

Minister of Relation with Parliament: 1971–1972.

Secretary of State for Economy and Finance: 1968–1971.

Secretary of State for Social Affairs: 1967–1968.

'''Electoral mandates'''

'''''European Parliament'''''

Member of [[European Parliament]]: 1979–1980 (Resignation). Elected in 1979.

'''''National Assembly of France'''''

Member of the [[National Assembly of France]] for [[Corrèze]]: March–April 1967 (Became Secretary of State in April 1967) Reelected in 1968, 1973, but he stays minister / 1976–1986 (Became Prime minister in 1986) / 1988–1995 (Resignation, became President of the French Republic in 1995). Elected in 1967, reelected in 1968, 1973, 1976, 1981, 1986, 1988, 1993.

'''''General Council'''''

President of the General Council of Corrèze: 1970–1979. Reelected in 1973, 1976.

General councillor of Corrèze: 1968–1988. Reelected in 1970, 1976, 1982.

'''''Municipal Council'''''

Mayor of Paris: 1977–1995 (Resignation, became President of the French Republic in 1995). Reelected in 1983, 1989.

Councillor of Paris: 1977–1995 (Resignation). Reelected in 1983, 1989.

Municipal councillor of [[Sainte-Féréole]]: 1965–1977. Reelected in 1971.

'''Political function'''

President of the [[Rally for the Republic]]: 1976–1994 (Resignation).

==Honours==
*Grand Cross of the [[Legion of Honour]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.elysee.fr/elysee/elysee.fr/anglais_archives/jacques_chirac/biography/biography.39706.html |title=Biography – Website of the Office of the French President |publisher=Elysee.fr |accessdate=20 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Grand Cross of the [[National Order of Merit (France)|French National Order of Merit]]
*[[Croix de la Valeur Militaire]]
*[[Médaille de l'Aéronautique]]
*Knight of the [[Mérite agricole]]
*Knight of the [[Order of Arts and Letters]]
*Knight of the [[Order of the Black Star]] ([[Bénin]]) (French Colonial Order)
*Knight of the [[Mérite Sportif]]
*Grand Cross of the [[Order pro merito Melitensi]]
*Honorary Officer of the [[National Order of Quebec]]
*[[Cóndor de oro]]
* Grand Cross of the [[Order of Good Hope]] (1996)&lt;ref name=&quot;Nat1996&quot;&gt;[http://www.info.gov.za/aboutgovt/orders/recipients/1996.htm 1996 National Orders awards]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Grand Cross of the [[Order of St. Olav]] (2000)&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20080706054452/http://www.saintolav.com/grandcrossawards/headsofstateroyals.html Den Kongelige Norske St. Olavs Orden – www.StOlav.com]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Member 1st class of the [[Order of Merit for the Fatherland]] (Russia, 23 September 1997) – for his great personal contribution to the development of cooperation and friendship between the peoples of Russia and France
*[[Medal &quot;In Commemoration of the 300th Anniversary of Saint Petersburg&quot;]]
*[[State Prize of the Russian Federation]] (2007) – for outstanding achievements in the humanitarian field&lt;ref name=Kommersant&gt;[http://www.kommersant.ru/doc.aspx?DocsID=894018&amp;NodesID=7 Названы лауреаты Государственной премии РФ] [[Kommersant]] 20 May 2008 {{ru icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Knight Grand Cross with Collar of the [[Order of Merit of the Italian Republic]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.quirinale.it/elementi/Onorificenze.aspx?pag=0&amp;qIdOnorificenza=&amp;cognome=chirac&amp;nome=&amp;daAnno=1800&amp;aAnno=2010&amp;luogoNascita=&amp;testo=&amp;ordinamento=OCO_ANNO_DECRETO%20DESC,OCO_MESE_DECRETO%20DESC,OCO_GIORNO_DECRETO%20DESC Jacques Chirac]. Italian presidency website. Quirinale.it (21 October 1999). Retrieved 17 December 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
*Knight of the [[Order of the White Eagle]] (Poland, 1996)
*Grand Collar of the [[Order of Prince Henry]] (Portugal, 1999)
*Grand Star of the [[Decoration for Services to the Republic of Austria]]
*Collar of the [[Order of the White Lion]] (Czech Republic, 1997)
*Grand Cross with Collar of the [[Order of the Star of Romania]] (1998)
*Grand Cross of the [[Order of Vytautas the Great]] (Lithuania, 1997)&lt;ref name=&quot;Lith&quot;&gt;[http://www.lrp.lt/lt/prezidento_veikla/apdovanojimai/apdovanojimai_256/p40.html Lithuanian Presidency], Lithuanian Orders searching form&lt;/ref&gt;
*Honorary Knight Commander of the [[Order of the Bath]] (UK)
*[[Heydar Aliyev Order]] (Azerbaijan)
*Grand Cross of the [[Order of the Lithuanian Grand Duke Gediminas]] (Lithuania, 24 July 2001)&lt;ref name=&quot;Lith&quot; /&gt;
*Commander Grand Cross of the [[Order of the Three Stars]] (Latvia)
*[[Ig Nobel prize]] for peace, for commemorating the fiftieth anniversary of Hiroshima with atomic bomb tests in the Pacific (1996)

==Titles from birth to currently==
*Monsieur le ''Président de la République française'' (1995–2007)
*''His Excellency The Sovereign Co-Prince of Andorra'' (1995–2007)

==See also==
{{Portal|France|Biography|Politics}}
*[[Anh Dao Traxel]]
*[[List of national leaders]]
*[[Politics of France]]
*[[French presidential election, 1981]]
*[[French presidential election, 1988]]
*[[French presidential election, 1995]]
*[[French presidential election, 2002]]
*[[French presidential election, 2007]]
* [[Musée du Président Jacques Chirac]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Bibliography==
*Emmanuel Hecht, Thierry Vey, ''Chirac de A à Z, dictionnaire critique et impertinent'', [[Éditions Albin Michel]], ISBN 2-226-07664-6
*Valéry Giscard d'Estaing, ''Le pouvoir et la vie, tome 3''
*[[Frederic Lepage]], ''A Table avec Chirac''
*Jacques Chirac, ''[[The development of the port of New-Orleans|La Nouvelle-Orléans et son port en 1954]]'', [Presses Universitaires du Nouveau Monde], ISBN 1-931948-68-2

==External links==
{{Wikinews category}}
{{Wikiquote}}
{{commons|Jacques Chirac}}
*[http://www.angus-reid.com/polls/index.cfm/fuseaction/searchSimpleResults/iw/1/keyword/Jacques%20Chirac%20not%20sarkozy Public opinion polls on Jacques Chirac]
*[http://www.elysee.fr/president/la-presidence/les-presidents-depuis-1848/histoire-des-presidents-de-la-republique/jacques-chirac-1932.5308.html Biography at the Official Website of the Office of the French President]
*{{fr icon}} [http://news.tf1.fr/news/france/0,,3232946,00.html TF1]
*{{fr icon}} [http://www.lexpress.fr/info/france/dossier/chirac/dossier.asp?ida=434072 l'Express]
*{{fr icon}} [http://www.paris.fr/portail/accueil/Portal.lut?page_id=96&amp;document_type_id=5&amp;document_id=7999&amp;portlet_id=10575 Mairie de Paris]
*{{fr icon}} [http://www.ldainfos.com/politique/presidentielle_2002/chirac.htm Biography and his election (2002)]
*{{fr icon}} [http://www.lescitations.net/citations/auteurs/Jacques_Chirac.html Some Jacques Chirac's quotations]
*[http://www.thefirstpost.co.uk/index.php?menuID=2&amp;subID=1509&amp;p=2 Jacques Chirac – A life in pictures photo essay]
*[[Anne Applebaum]], [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/05/07/AR2007050701239.html Farewell, Jacques Chirac], ''The Washington Post'', 8 May 2007
*[http://news.pdousteblazy.com Latest news of UNITAID (initiated by Jacques Chirac) and today chaired Philippe Douste-Blazy]
*[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/jacques-chirac Articles at ''The Guardian'']

{{s-start}}
{{s-off}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Michel Cointat]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Ministry of Agriculture (France)|Minister of Agriculture]]|years=1972–1974}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Raymond Marcellin]]}}
|-
{{s-bef|before=[[Raymond Marcellin]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Minister of the Interior (France)|Minister of the Interior]]|years=1974}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Michel Poniatowski]]}}
|-
{{s-bef|before=[[Pierre Messmer]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Prime Minister of France]]|years=1974–1976}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Raymond Barre]]}}
|-
{{s-new|office}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[List of mayors of Paris|Mayor of Paris]]|years=1977–1995}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Jean Tiberi]]}}
|-
{{s-bef|before=[[Laurent Fabius]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Prime Minister of France]]|years=1986–1988}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Michel Rocard]]}}
|-
{{s-bef|before=[[François Mitterrand]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[President of France]]|years=1995–2007}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Nicolas Sarkozy]]}}
|-
{{s-ppo}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Alexandre Sanguinetti]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=Leader of the [[Union of Democrats for the Republic]]|years=1974–1975}}
{{s-aft|after=[[André Bord]]}}
|-
{{s-new|party}}
{{s-ttl|title=Leader of [[Rally for the Republic]]|years=1976–1994}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Alain Juppé]]}}
|-
{{s-bef|before=[[Jacques Chaban-Delmas]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Rally for the Republic]] nominee for [[President of France]]|years=[[French presidential election, 1981|1981]], [[French presidential election, 1988|1988]], [[French presidential election, 1995|1995]], [[French presidential election, 2002|2002]]}}
{{s-non|reason=Party merged}}
|-
{{s-reg}}
{{s-bef|before=[[François Mitterrand]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Co-Princes of Andorra|Co-Prince of Andorra]]|alongside=[[Joan Martí Alanis]], [[Joan Enric Vives Sicília]]|years=1995–2007}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Nicolas Sarkozy]]}}
|-
{{s-rel|ca}}
{{s-bef|before=[[François Mitterrand]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Canon (priest)#Honorary canons|Honorary Canon]] of the [[Basilica of St. John Lateran]]|years=1995–2007}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Nicolas Sarkozy]]}}
|-
{{s-dip}}
{{s-bef|rows=2|before=[[Jean Chrétien]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=Chairperson of the [[G8|Group of 7]]|years=1996}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Bill Clinton]]}}
|-
{{s-ttl|title=Chairperson of the [[G8|Group of 8]]|years=2003}}
{{s-aft|after=[[George W. Bush]]}}
|-
{{s-prec}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Valéry Giscard d'Estaing]]|as=Former President}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[French order of precedence|Order of Precedence of France]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;''Former President''&lt;/small&gt;|years=}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Nicolas Sarkozy]]|as=Former President}}
{{s-end}}

{{Heads of state of France}}
{{Heads of government of France}}
{{Candidates in the French presidential election, 1988}}
{{Presidents of the European Council}}
{{UDRLeaders}}
{{Member Constitutional Council of France}}
{{Authority control|LCCN=n/50/038160}}

{{Persondata
|NAME= Chirac, Jacques
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=Chirac, Jacques René
|SHORT DESCRIPTION=[[President of the French Republic|President of France]]
|DATE OF BIRTH=29 November 1932
|PLACE OF BIRTH=Paris, France
|DATE OF DEATH=
|PLACE OF DEATH=
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Chirac, Jacques}}
[[Category:1932 births]]
[[Category:Alumni of Sciences Po]]
[[Category:École nationale d'administration alumni]]
[[Category:Attempted assassination survivors]]
[[Category:French anti-communists]]
[[Category:French Army officers]]
[[Category:French fraudsters]]
[[Category:French interior ministers]]
[[Category:French military personnel of the Algerian War]]
[[Category:French politicians convicted of crimes]]
[[Category:French Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:Government of Andorra]]
[[Category:Chevaliers of the Ordre des Arts et des Lettres]]
[[Category:Collars of the Order of the White Lion]]
[[Category:Grand Collars of the Order of Prince Henry]]
[[Category:Grand Croix of the Légion d'honneur]]
[[Category:Grand Croix of the Ordre national du Mérite]]
[[Category:Grand Crosses of the Order of Good Hope]]
[[Category:Grand Crosses of the Order of the Lithuanian Grand Duke Gediminas]]
[[Category:Grand Crosses of the Order of Vytautas the Great]]
[[Category:Honorary Knights Grand Cross of the Order of the Bath]]
[[Category:Knights Grand Cross with Collar of the Order of Merit of the Italian Republic]]
[[Category:Knights Grand Cross of the Order of St. Olav]]
[[Category:Knights of the Order of the Black Star]]
[[Category:Officers of the National Order of Quebec]]
[[Category:Knights of the Ordre National du Mérite Agricole (France)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Collar of the Order of the Cross of Terra Mariana]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Croix de la Valeur Militaire]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Heydar Aliyev Order]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Grand Star of the Decoration for Services to the Republic of Austria]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Médaille de l'Aéronautique]]
[[Category:Recipients of the National Order of Merit (Malta)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Merit for the Fatherland, 1st class]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of the Three Stars, 1st Class]]
[[Category:Sashes of the Order of the Star of Romania]]
[[Category:State Prize of the Russian Federation laureates]]
[[Category:Grand Crosses of the Order pro merito Melitensi]]
[[Category:Ig Nobel Prize winners]]
[[Category:Jacques Chirac|Jacques Chirac]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Harvard University alumni]]
[[Category:Lycée Carnot alumni]]
[[Category:Lycée Louis-le-Grand alumni]]
[[Category:Mayors of Paris]]
[[Category:People from Paris]]
[[Category:Politicians of the French Fifth Republic]]
[[Category:Presidents of France]]
[[Category:Prime Ministers of France]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic monarchs]]
[[Category:Stroke survivors]]

[[af:Jacques Chirac]]
[[am:ዣክ ሺራክ]]
[[ar:جاك شيراك]]
[[an:Jacques Chirac]]
[[frp:Jacques Chirac]]
[[ast:Jacques Chirac]]
[[az:Jak Şirak]]
[[bn:জাক শিরাক]]
[[zh-min-nan:Jacques Chirac]]
[[be:Жак Шырак]]
[[be-x-old:Жак Шырак]]
[[bg:Жак Ширак]]
[[bs:Jacques Chirac]]
[[br:Jacques Chirac]]
[[ca:Jacques Chirac]]
[[cv:Жак Ширак]]
[[cs:Jacques Chirac]]
[[co:Jacques Chirac]]
[[cy:Jacques Chirac]]
[[da:Jacques Chirac]]
[[de:Jacques Chirac]]
[[et:Jacques Chirac]]
[[el:Ζακ Σιράκ]]
[[es:Jacques Chirac]]
[[eo:Jacques Chirac]]
[[eu:Jacques Chirac]]
[[fa:ژاک شیراک]]
[[fr:Jacques Chirac]]
[[fy:Jacques Chirac]]
[[ga:Jacques Chirac]]
[[gv:Jacques Chirac]]
[[gl:Jacques Chirac]]
[[ko:자크 시라크]]
[[hy:Ժակ Շիրակ]]
[[hi:ज़्याक शिराक]]
[[hsb:Jacques Chirac]]
[[hr:Jacques Chirac]]
[[io:Jacques Chirac]]
[[id:Jacques Chirac]]
[[ia:Jacques Chirac]]
[[is:Jacques Chirac]]
[[it:Jacques Chirac]]
[[he:ז'אק שיראק]]
[[jv:Jacques Chirac]]
[[ka:ჟაკ შირაკი]]
[[ku:Jacques Chirac]]
[[la:Iacobus Chirac]]
[[lv:Žaks Širaks]]
[[lt:Jacques Chirac]]
[[li:Jacques Chirac]]
[[hu:Jacques Chirac]]
[[mk:Жак Ширак]]
[[mr:जाक शिराक]]
[[xmf:ჟაკ შირაკი]]
[[arz:جاك شيراك]]
[[ms:Jacques Chirac]]
[[nl:Jacques Chirac]]
[[ja:ジャック・シラク]]
[[no:Jacques Chirac]]
[[nn:Jacques Chirac]]
[[nrm:Jacques Chirac]]
[[oc:Jacques Chirac]]
[[nds:Jacques Chirac]]
[[pl:Jacques Chirac]]
[[pt:Jacques Chirac]]
[[ty:Jacques Chirac]]
[[ro:Jacques Chirac]]
[[rm:Jacques Chirac]]
[[ru:Ширак, Жак]]
[[sa:ज्याक शिराक]]
[[sco:Jacques Chirac]]
[[sq:Jacques Chirac]]
[[scn:Jacques Chirac]]
[[simple:Jacques Chirac]]
[[sk:Jacques Chirac]]
[[sl:Jacques Chirac]]
[[sr:Жак Ширак]]
[[sh:Jacques Chirac]]
[[fi:Jacques Chirac]]
[[sv:Jacques Chirac]]
[[tl:Jacques Chirac]]
[[ta:ஜாக் சிராக்]]
[[tt:Жак Ширак]]
[[th:ฌัก ชีรัก]]
[[tg:Жак Ширак]]
[[tr:Jacques Chirac]]
[[uk:Жак Ширак]]
[[vi:Jacques Chirac]]
[[fiu-vro:Chiraci Jacques]]
[[war:Jacques Chirac]]
[[yi:זשאק שיראק]]
[[yo:Jacques Chirac]]
[[zh-yue:希拉克]]
[[bat-smg:Žāks Širāks]]
[[zh:雅克·希拉克]]</text>
      <sha1>2n40vlad280o0ulmmr92myc7wpbn7xb</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
