<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Jeb Bush</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>189322</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521002963</id>
      <parentid>520845913</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T04:03:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>75.27.253.165</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Family */ There are only two sons, so it's &quot;elder&quot; and &quot;younger&quot;</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="47513">{{Infobox Governor
|name= Jeb Bush
|image=&lt;!-- // DO NOT CHANGE THE PHOTO --&gt;Gov Jeb Bush.jpg
|caption=
|order= [[List of Governors of Florida|43rd]]
|office= Governor of Florida
|term_start= January 5, 1999
|term_end= January 2, 2007
|lieutenant= [[Frank Brogan]]&lt;br&gt;[[Toni Jennings]]
|predecessor= [[Buddy MacKay]]
|successor=[[Charlie Crist]]
|birth_name=John Ellis Bush
|birth_date= {{Birth date and age|mf=yes|1953|02|11}}
|birth_place= [[Midland, Texas]]
|death_date=
|residence= [[Coral Gables, Florida]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://lowellinternationalrealty.com/2012/06/08/just-sold-former-florida-governor%E2%80%99s-home/ Former Governor's Home], Lowell International Realty, Retrieved June 10, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
|spouse= [[Columba Bush]]
|children= [[George P. Bush]]&lt;br&gt;Noelle Bush&lt;br&gt;John Ellis Bush, Jr.
|relations= [[George H. W. Bush]] (father)&lt;br&gt;[[Barbara Bush]] (mother)&lt;br&gt;[[George W. Bush]] (brother)&lt;br&gt;[[Prescott Bush]] (grandfather)
|signature=Jeb Bush Signature.svg
|religion= [[Episcopal Church (United States)|Episcopalian]] (before 1995)&lt;br&gt;[[Catholic Church|Catholic]] (after 1995)&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sptimes.com/2005/04/23/Worldandnation/Jeb_Bush_sent_to_Mass.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;
|alma_mater= [[University of Texas]] &lt;small&gt;([[Bachelor of Arts]])&lt;/small&gt;
|profession= [[Banker]]&lt;br&gt;[[Real Estate Developer]]
|party= [[United States Republican Party|Republican]]
|
|footnotes=
}}

'''John Ellis &quot;Jeb&quot; Bush''' (born February 11, 1953) is an [[United States|American]] [[politician]] who served as the [[List of Governors of Florida|43rd Governor]] of [[Florida]] from 1999 to 2007. He is a prominent member of the [[Bush family]]: the second son of former [[President of the United States of America|President]] [[George H. W. Bush]] and former [[First Lady]] [[Barbara Bush]]; the younger brother of former President [[George W. Bush]]; and the older brother of [[Neil Bush]], [[Marvin Bush]], and [[Dorothy Bush Koch]].

==Early years==
Jeb Bush was born in [[Midland, Texas]]. When he was six years old, the family relocated to [[Houston, Texas]].

Jeb initially attended Grady Elementary School in Houston.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://nl.newsbank.com/nl-search/we/Archives?p_product=MH&amp;s_site=miami&amp;p_multi=MH&amp;p_theme=realcities&amp;p_action=search&amp;p_maxdocs=200&amp;p_topdoc=1&amp;p_text_direct-0=0F640A5D0899F681&amp;p_field_direct-0=document_id&amp;p_perpage=10&amp;p_sort=YMD_date:D&amp;s_trackval=GooglePM LONG-HELD VALUES SHAPE PUBLIC LIFE OF JEB BUSH].&quot; ''[[The Miami Herald]]''. September 22, 2002. Retrieved on October 15, 2012. &quot;Bush attended public Grady Elementary School in Houston for several years[...]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Following in the footsteps of older brother, George, Jeb Bush attended high school at the private [[Massachusetts]] [[boarding school]], [[Phillips Academy Andover]]. At the age of 17, he taught [[English as a foreign or second language|English as a second language]] in [[León, Guanajuato]], [[Mexico]], as part of Phillips Academy's [[student exchange program]]. While in Mexico, he met his wife, [[Columba Bush|Columba Garnica Gallo]].

In 1973, Bush graduated [[Phi Beta Kappa]] from the [[University of Texas at Austin]] with a [[Bachelor of Arts|BA]] in [[Latin American Studies]]. He completed his coursework in two and a half years with generally excellent grades.

==Family==
After graduating from UT at Austin, married [[Columba Bush|Columba Garnica Gallo]], on February 23, 1974. Their three children are [[George P. Bush]], Noelle Bush, and John Ellis Bush, Jr. Their elder son, George Prescott Bush (born April 24, 1976, in [[Texas]]), went to [[Gulliver Preparatory School]], studied at [[Rice University]], and earned a [[Juris Doctor]] degree from the [[University of Texas School of Law]]. Noelle Lucila Bush (born July 26, 1977, in Texas) graduated from [[Tallahassee Community College]] in 2000 and enrolled in [[Florida State University]] in 2001.

John Ellis Bush, Jr., Bush's younger son (born December 13, 1983, in Miami), works for a [[Miami, Florida]] commercial real estate firm. In October 2007, he endorsed [[Rudy Giuliani]] for the 2008 Republican Presidential nomination, and supported the effort as chairman of &quot;Florida Young Professionals for Rudy&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://blogs.wsj.com/washwire/2007/10/18/giuliani-picks-up-jeb-bush-jr-endorsement/ &quot;Giuliani Picks Up (Jeb) Bush (Jr.) Endorsement&quot;], ''[[Wall Street Journal]]'' Washington Wire, October 18, 2007. Retrieved November 19, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; In the 2012 GOP Primary, Jeb Bush, Jr. endorsed former Utah governor and former ambassador to China Jon Huntsman.

==Early career==

===Business experience in Texas and abroad===
Bush went to work in an entry level position in the international division of [[Texas Commerce Bank]], a job he received through [[James Baker]], a longtime family friend and chairman of the board of Texas Commerce Bank. Bush assisted in drafting communications for the company's chairman, Ben Love.

In November 1977, he was sent to the [[Venezuela]]n capital of [[Caracas]] to open a new operation for the bank. Bush spent about two years there, working in international finance. He eventually worked for the bank's executive program.

Bush returned to the United States to work without salary on his father's campaign for the Republican [[United States presidential election, 1980|presidential nomination in 1980]], explaining:

:&quot;I wasn't motivated for politics, I wasn't motivated because of [[ideology]] or anything. My dad's the greatest man I've ever met or will meet; I can predict that fairly confidently. It was payback time, simple as that.&quot;

His father ultimately lost the Republican nomination for President that year, but was chosen to be [[Ronald Reagan]]'s running mate. That fall, [[George H.W. Bush]] was elected [[Vice President of the United States]], and won reelection in 1984. In 1988, the elder Bush won both the Republican Party's presidential nomination and the election, becoming the nation's 41st president. In 1992 Bush's father was defeated for re-election by then-[[Arkansas]] Governor [[Bill Clinton]].

===Business and lobbying experience in Miami===
Following the 1980 presidential election, Bush and his family moved to [[Miami-Dade County, Florida]]. He took a job in real estate with [[Armando Codina]], a 32-year-old [[Cuba]]n immigrant and self-made American millionaire. Codina had made a fortune in a computer business, and then formed a new company, IntrAmerica Investments Inc., to pursue opportunities in [[real estate]].

During Bush's years in Miami, he was involved in many different [[entrepreneur]]ial pursuits, including working for a mobile phone company, serving on the board of a [[Norway|Norwegian]]-owned company that sold fire equipment to the [[Trans-Alaska Pipeline System|Alaska oil pipeline]], becoming a minority owner of the [[Jacksonville Jaguars]], buying a shoe company that sold footwear in [[Panama]], and getting involved in a project selling water pumps in [[Nigeria]].

Codina eventually made Bush his partner in a new development business, which quickly became one of South Florida's leading real estate development firms. As a partner, Bush received 40% of the firm's profits.

In 1990, Bush interceded with his father, the president, to pardon [[Orlando Bosch]], a Cuban exile whom Attorney General [[Dick Thornburgh]] called an &quot;unrepentant terrorist.&quot; Bosch was released from prison and granted residency in the U.S.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, Duncan (2 December 2002) [http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2002/dec/02/usa.books &quot;The Bush dynasty and the Cuban criminals.&quot;] ''[The Guardian]''. (Retrieved September 9, 2010.)&lt;/ref&gt;

Recarey, who ran International Medical Centres (IMC), employed Bush as a real estate consultant and paid him a $75,000 fee for finding the company a new location, although the move never took place. Bush did, however, [[lobbying|lobby]] the Reagan/Bush administration vigorously and successfully on behalf of Recarey and IMC. &quot;I want to be very wealthy,&quot; Jeb Bush told the ''Miami News'' when questioned during that period.&lt;ref name=&quot;Guardian dynasty&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/usa/story/0,12271,851913,00.html|title=The Bush dynasty and the Cuban Criminals|accessdate=2007-04-17|publisher=The Guardian|author=Duncan Campbell | location=London | date=December 2, 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Civic and charitable activities===
After narrowly losing a 1994 election for Governor of Florida against [[Lawton Chiles]], Bush pursued policy and charitable interests. He started a [[non-profit organization]] called The Foundation For Florida's Future, a [[think tank]] that stated as its mission influencing [[Public policy (law)|public policy]] at the [[grassroots]] level. Jeb met with Noel Serrano, a member of the Latin Chamber of Commerce in 1991. Noel states, &quot;Jeb was always a dedicated Public Servant long before he became Governor&quot; He also &quot;volunteered time to assist the Miami Children's Hospital, the [[United Way of America|United Way]] of Dade County and the Dade County Homeless Trust&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oneflorida.org/myflorida/government/go%5Bhttp://www.barbarabushfoundation.com/site/c.jhLSK2PALmF/b.4344531/k.BD31/Home.htm Barbara Bush Foundation for Family Literacy%5D, vernorinitiatives/one_florida/bushmore.html]{{Dead link|date=March 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Jeb Bush currently serves as co-chair of the [http://www.barbarabushfoundation.com/site/c.jhLSK2PALmF/b.4344531/k.BD31/Home.htm Barbara Bush Foundation for Family Literacy], along  with his sister [[Doro Bush Koch]]. Jeb Bush has also worked with The [[James Madison Institute]], a [[free market]] public policy [[think tank]] based in [[Tallahassee, FL]]. He helped the institute in numerous ways and still has his think tank working in conjunction with it. In June 2008, Jeb's institute, the [[Foundation for Excellence in Education]],partnered with JMI to hold a summit called [http://www.excelined.org/Program/ViewPage.aspx?pr=4&amp;pc=21 ''' &quot;Excellence in Action: A National Summit on Education Reform&quot;'''].&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web|url=http://www.excelined.org/Program/ViewPage.aspx?pr=4&amp;pc=21
|title=Cato on &quot;Excellence in Action: A National Summit on Education Reform&quot;
|accessdate=2008-08-23
|work=Foundation for Excellence in Education
|publisher=Foundation for Excellence in Education}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1996, The Foundation For Florida's Future published a book that Bush had co-written, ''Profiles in Character'' (ISBN 0-9650912-0-1), a clear parallel to [[John F. Kennedy]]'s 1955 book ''[[Profiles in Courage]]''. The foundation also published and distributed policy papers, such as &quot;A New Lease on Learning: Florida's First Charter School&quot;, which Bush co-wrote.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.heartland.org/pdf/21111f.pdf (PDF)]{{Dead link|date=April 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bush subsequently wrote the foreword to another book, published by the [[Conservatism|conservative]] [[Heritage Foundation]] and written by Nina Shokraii Rees, ''School Choice 2000: What's Happening in the States'' (ISBN 0-89195-089-3).

Bush co-founded the first [[charter school]] in the State of Florida: Liberty City Charter School, a grades K-6 elementary school.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dadeschools.net/schools/liberty_charter.htm Liberty City Charter School&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The school is situated in Liberty City, a Miami neighborhood that was the site, in 1980, of the first major [[race riot]] since the [[Civil Rights]] era.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aaregistry.com/african_american_history/895/Riot_erupts_in_Liberty_City |title=African American Registry: Riot erupts in Liberty City! |publisher=Aaregistry.com |date= |accessdate=2009-04-03 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080611153658/http://www.aaregistry.com/african_american_history/895/Riot_erupts_in_Liberty_City |archivedate = June 11, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The school's co-founder, working alongside Bush, was T. Willard Fair, a well-known local black activist and head of the Greater Miami Urban League. The Liberty City Charter School still operates today as a charter school.

In 2000, Bush established the Points of Light program to recognize an &quot;exemplary volunteer, organization, or person&quot; such as Jimmy Rotonno of [[Our Father's House Soup Kitchen]] who won the award in 2003.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last =Berrios | first =Jerry | title =Hero in the Spotlight | work =The Miami Herald | pages =1B | date =20 August 2003 | accessdate =23 October 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Religious affiliation===
In 1995, Bush converted from [[Episcopal Church in the United States of America|Episcopalianism]] to [[Catholicism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Jeb Bush, Catholic Convert. Will His Brother Convert?|url=http://www.catholic.org/national/national_story.php?id=34357|publisher=Catholic.org|accessdate=8 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; For many years, he and his wife have attended the Church of the Epiphany, a Catholic [[parish (Catholic Church)|parish]] located in Miami. Bush is a Third Degree [[Knights of Columbus|Knight of Columbus]] according to an August 3, 2004 speech his brother, George W. Bush, made at the 122nd Knights of Columbus Convention in [[Dallas, Texas]]. The following is an excerpt from the speech:

:&quot;I'm proud to say that my family has contributed to your ranks. A few years ago, Governor Jeb became a Knight. And he—yes—and he recently took his Third Degree. I'll see him this weekend. His son is getting married. I'll pass on the word, aim for the Fourth.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=President Discusses Compassionate Conservative Agenda in Dallas|url=http://faq.acf.hhs.gov/app/answers/detail/a_id/1556/~/acf-messenger-archive%3A-president-discusses-compassionate-conservative-agenda-in|accessdate=8 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2004, Jeb Bush (while still governor) was inducted into the Fourth Degree by Gary L. McLain at a ceremony held Nov. 1. Bush, a member of Father Hugon Council 3521 in Tallahassee, joined Father Hugon Assembly.{{citation needed|date=March 2012}}

==Political career==

===Early campaigns===
Bush got his start in Florida politics as the Chairman of the Dade County Republican Party. Dade County played an important role in the 1986 election of [[Bob Martinez]] to the Governor's office. In return, Martinez appointed Bush as Florida's Secretary of Commerce. He served in that role in 1987 and 1988, before resigning once again to work on his father's presidential campaign. In 1989 he served as the campaign manager of [[Ileana Ros-Lehtinen]], the first Cuban-American to serve in Congress. He launched an unsuccessful bid for the Governor's office in 1994 against incumbent [[Florida Democratic Party|Democratic]] Governor [[Lawton Chiles]]. Bush lost the election by only 63,940 votes out of 4,206,076 that were cast for the major party candidates (2,135,008; 50.8% to 2,071,068; 49.2%). In the same election year, his older brother, [[George W. Bush|George]], was elected [[Governor of Texas]].

===Governor of Florida===
In 1998, Bush defeated the Democratic opponent Lt. Governor [[Buddy MacKay]] by over 418,000 votes (2,191,105; 55.3% to 1,773,054; 44.7%) to become [[Governor of Florida]], after courting the state's moderate voters and [[Hispanic]]s. Simultaneously, his brother, George W. Bush won a re-election victory for a second term as [[Governor of Texas]], and the Bush brothers became the first siblings to govern two states at the same time since [[Nelson Rockefeller|Nelson]] and [[Winthrop Rockefeller]] governed [[New York]] and [[Arkansas]] from 1967 to 1971. Bush is the first Republican governor of Florida to have served two full four-year terms.

===Education===
Bush's administration was marked by a focus on public education reform. His &quot;A+ Plan&quot; mandated standardized testing in Florida's public schools, eliminated social promotion and established a system of funding public schools based on a statewide grading system using the [[Florida Comprehensive Assessment Test|FCAT]] test. Bush has been a proponent of [[school voucher]]s and [[charter school]]s, especially in areas of the state with failing public schools, although to date very few schools have received failing grades from the state. One program that has seen fruition is the [[Florida Virtual School]], a [[distance-learning]] program that allows students in rural areas of the state to take [[Advanced Placement]] classes for college credit. However, his policies have also been driven by a firm refusal to raise taxes for education, which led Bush to oppose a ballot initiative to amend the Florida Constitution to cap growing school class sizes. Bush said he had &quot;a couple of devious plans if this thing passes&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.floridacapitalnews.com/campaign/stories/1003classsize.htm ]{{Dead link|date=April 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.floridacapitalnews.com/campaign/sound/classsize2.mp3 ]{{Dead link|date=April 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite his opposition, the amendment passed;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.leg.state.fl.us/Statutes/index.cfm?Mode=Constitution&amp;Submenu=3&amp;Tab=statutes#A09S01 |title=Statutes &amp; Constitution :Constitution : Online Sunshine |publisher=Leg.state.fl.us |date= |accessdate=2009-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bush's subsequent suggestions that the amendment be repealed&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flablog.net/2005/02/devious-plan-ver-40.htm |title=Devious Plan Ver. 4.0 |publisher=Flablog |date=2005-02-15 |accessdate=2009-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; have contributed to criticisms that he has failed to implement it in good faith. A similar concern about new expenditures has led to controversy over whether Florida has provided adequate resources to implement a subsequent voter-approved state constitutional amendment that requires a universal state-financed pre-Kindergarten program.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iamforkids.org/campaign/policybriefs/Universal_Pre_Kindergarten.pdf ]{{Dead link|date=April 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In higher education, Bush approved three new medical schools during his tenure and also put forth the &quot;One Florida&quot; proposal, an initiative that effectively ended [[affirmative action]] admissions programs at state universities.&lt;ref&gt;James, Joni. [http://www.sptimes.com/2007/03/18/Business/Jeb_Bush_on_One_Flori.shtml Jeb Bush on One Florida], ''St. Petersburg Times'', March 18, 2007. Retrieved June 14, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; These moves were among the influencing concerns that led to the faculty of the [[University of Florida]] to deny Bush an [[honorary degree]], while the University of Florida Alumni Association made him an [[alumni|honorary alumnus]]. North Miami Beach Attorney Larry R. Fleurantin, then a UF law student, on April 1, 2001, wrote an article in the Gainesville Sun challenging Florida Governor Jeb Bush's Talented 20 Plan, the educational component of &quot;One Florida.&quot; In response to Attorney Fleurantin's article, on April 7, 2001, Gov. Jeb Bush wrote a column in the Gainesville Sun defending his &quot;One Florida&quot; policy.&lt;ref&gt;. {{cite web|author=8:35 p.m. ET |url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/17768626/ |title=Jeb Bush denied one honor, wins another - Politics - MSNBC.com |publisher=MSNBC |date=2007-03-24 |accessdate=2009-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Libraries===
In May 2006, as part of an unprecedented $448.7-million [[line-item veto]] of state funding, Bush slashed a total of $5.8 million in grants to [[public libraries]], pilot projects for library homework help and web-based high-school texts, and funding for a joint-use library in Tampa.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ala.org/ala/alonline/currentnews/newsarchive/2006abc/may2006ab/bushveto.cfm |title=American Libraries - Gov. Jeb Bush Vetoes Florida Library Appropriations |publisher=ALA |date=2006-05-26 |accessdate=2009-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After months of controversy that included thousands of e-mails, petition signatures and hundreds of picketers at the State Capitol, the Florida House voted to ditch Bush's plan to give the biggest collection at the century-old State Library to [[Nova Southeastern University]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://listsmart.osl.state.or.us/pipermail/libs-or/2003-April/000893.html |title=[Libs-Or&amp;#93; Florida library beats bush |publisher=Listsmart.osl.state.or.us |date=2003-04-05 |accessdate=2009-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Environment===
[[File:Jeb Bush Earth Day Rookery Bay 2004.jpg|thumb|240px|Bush at Rookery Bay participating in Earth Day activities in 2004]]
Bush signed legislation to protect the [[Everglades]] and opposed federal plans to drill for [[oil]] off the coast of Florida. In early October 2005, Bush attempted to strike a compromise with fellow Republicans that would allow [[offshore drilling]] in an area that stretches {{convert|125|mi|km}} off Florida's coastline and give the state legislature the power to permit drilling closer to the state's coastlines. The compromise was warmly received by some Florida Republicans and U.S. Congressmen, such as bill sponsor [[Richard Pombo]], but has yet to be agreed upon; others including Republican U.S. Senator [[Mel Martinez]], objected to any backtracking on the drilling moratorium.

===Health policy issues===
Bush was involved in the [[Terri Schiavo case]], involving a woman with massive [[brain damage]], who was on a feeding tube for over 15 years, and whose husband and legal guardian, [[Michael Schiavo]], wished to remove the tube. This move was opposed by Terry Schiavo's parents in the courts. Bush signed &quot;[[Government involvement in the Terri Schiavo case|Terri's Law]],&quot; legislation passed by the Florida legislature that permitted the Governor to keep Schiavo on [[life support]]. The law was ruled unconstitutional by the [[Florida Supreme Court]] on September 23, 2004. That decision was [[appeal]]ed to the federal courts. On January 24, 2005, the [[Supreme Court of the United States|U.S. Supreme Court]] declined to hear the case, thus allowing the Florida court's ruling to stand.

After being vetoed by previous Governor [[Lawton Chiles]], ''[[Choose Life (organization)|Choose Life]]'', a [[pro-life]] [[advocacy group]] based in [[Ocala, Florida]], submitted a specialty license plate application, which passed both houses and Governor Bush signed it into law on June 8, 1999.&lt;ref&gt;[http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4196/is_19991124/ai_n10558203 &quot;Florida approves 'Choose Life' license plate&quot;]) Milwaukee Journal Sentinel, November 24, 1999&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Olszonowicz, Deborah: [http://www.ncsl.org/programs/transportation/tranrm_p.htm &quot;Motor Vehicle Registration and License Plates&quot;] x, September 1999&lt;/ref&gt;

Bush [[List of individuals executed in Florida|oversaw 21 executions as Governor]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dc.state.fl.us/oth/deathrow/execlist.html |title=Execution List - Florida Department of Corrections |publisher=Dc.state.fl.us |date= |accessdate=2009-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; (more than [[Bob Graham|Graham]], [[Bob Martinez|Martinez]] and [[Lawton Chiles|Chiles]] while they were in office). Bush never agreed to commute any sentence.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/article.php?did=126&amp;scid=13 Clemency - Death Penalty Information Center].&lt;/ref&gt;

Bush also presided over switching from [[electric chair]] (the only method of executions until 2000, now optional) to [[lethal injection]], after a botched electrocution of [[Allen Lee Davis]] (first inmate executed under his administration and last, to date, electrocuted in Florida). After two previous botched executions ([[Jesse Tafero]] in 1990 and [[Pedro Medina]] in 1997) Governors Martinez and Chiles along with legislature declined to change methods.&lt;ref&gt;Freedberg, Sydney P. [http://www.sptimes.com/News/92599/news_pf/State/The_story_of_Old_Spar.shtml The story of Old Sparky], ''St. Petersburg Times'', September 25, 1999. Retrieved June 14, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

While he is an advocate of capital punishment, Bush suspended all executions in Florida on December 15, 2006, after the execution of [[Ángel Nieves Díaz]] was seemingly botched. The execution took 37 minutes to complete, and required a second injection of the lethal chemicals.

As Governor, Jeb Bush proposed and passed into law major reform to the medical liability system.  The Florida Senate, a majority of which were Republican, sided with the trial lawyers against caps on non-economic damages.  Bush insisted, and called the legislature into five special sessions.  The contentious debate even included a senior Bush staffer calling for primary opposition to Republicans who disagreed with the Governor on the reforms.  Eventually, the legislature agreed to the caps and Bush's reforms passed.  Bush also passed a massive reform to Florida's Medicaid system.  At the time, this reform was referred to as the most sweeping reform to Medicaid in its 45 year history.  Also, Florida was the first state in the nation to publish hospital outcomes on the Internet, including cost and information on quality, infections and complications.

===International trade===
Bush said one of the most important goals of his final two years as Governor was to secure the [[Free Trade Area of the Americas]] (FTAA) Secretariat for Miami.

===Vetoes===
There has been a 2004 veto on bill about court-appointed the [[parental coordinator]]s because of the concern that the bill does not adequately protect families as they try to resolve their conflicts.&lt;ref name=bush&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thelizlibrary.org/parenting-coordination/bush-veto.pdf|title=Bush veto}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Lieutenant Governors===
&lt;!-- Should this section be here? Seems there's too much material for a Bush article here, none of it more than marginally relevant to Bush--&gt;
Lt. Gov. [[Frank Brogan]], a former fifth-grade teacher, principal, and superintendent, served only one term with Bush. After Brogan remarried, he opted not to serve a second term. Brogan was reelected to a second term in 2002 with Bush and then resigned in March 2003. He and his new wife moved to [[Boca Raton, Florida|Boca Raton]], where he served as president of [[Florida Atlantic University]]. In Tallahassee, a museum was named in honor of Brogan's late wife, Mary, who died on June 27, 1999, of [[breast cancer]] and, like her husband, was a Florida school teacher.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thebrogan.org |title=The Mary Brogan Museum of Art and Science |publisher=Thebrogan.org |date=2009-01-17 |accessdate=2009-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following Brogan's resignation, Bush appointed former [[Florida Senate]] President [[Toni Jennings]], with whom he had occasionally disagreed in regards to public policy, as Lieutenant Governor.

===Florida Cabinet===
As Governor, Bush served as the chairman of the [[Florida Cabinet]], which provides collective governance over part of state government.

===Other organizations===
Bush was a member of the [[National Governors Association]] and the [[Republican Governors Association]].

==2002 gubernatorial election==
{{Main|Florida gubernatorial election, 2002}}
Before Bush's re-election, no Republican in Florida had ever been re-elected to serve a second term as the state's Governor. In addition, there was likely no precedent for any Governor to be branded by the opposition as its &quot;Number One Target&quot; for removal from office, as Bush was ranked in 2002. This was not merely a statewide effort to oust the Republican Governor, but a much-publicized goal of the [[Democratic National Committee]] (DNC) and its highest leadership during the 2002 election cycle.

===The Democratic primary race===
Bush almost faced [[Janet Reno]] in the 2002 Florida Governor's race. However, a number of other Democratic candidates also wanted to become Florida's next Governor, including [[Bill McBride (candidate)|Bill McBride]]. A prominent litigator with [[Holland &amp; Knight]] and a novice candidate, McBride was favored by national Democratic Party leaders in part because of his military background and perceived ability to attract Florida's more conservative voters.

In the ensuing Democratic primary contest (where only Democratic voters could vote, pursuant to state primary laws), circumstances surrounding McBride's victory outraged many voters in South Florida. Some voting venues—located in Reno's urban strongholds of Broward County and Dade County, and operated by Democrats elected as county election officials—reportedly opened hours late, and then [http://www.miami.com/mld/miami/4043757.htm ignored] Bush's Executive Order, issued at Reno's request, to stay open later to accommodate all voters.

===The 2002 election results===
In the closely watched Florida Governor's race that attracted national attention, Bush was re-elected in November 2002, becoming the first Republican in the state's history to be re-elected as Governor. Bush defeated Democratic challenger Bill McBride with 56% to 43%, a greater margin of victory than in Bush's 1998 campaign for the Governor's office. Bush also increased the number of counties in his victory column, winning several Florida counties for the very first time. He campaigned all throughout North West Florida in Pensacola and Milton.

In January 2007, Bush became only the second Florida Governor to complete two full four-year terms in office, the first being Democrat [[Reubin O'Donovan Askew]]. (Bush was prevented from seeking a third term in the 2006 election, due to term limits under state law.)

Bush made Florida political history not only by becoming the first Republican Governor to ever win re-election in Florida, but also by being the first Florida Governor to select a woman, [[Toni Jennings]], to serve as Florida's Lieutenant Governor. No woman had ever been appointed or elected to that high office in Florida's executive branch.

Bush is also the first Governor to hold office while having a brother simultaneously serve as President.

==Political future==
Due to [[term limit]]s under state law, Bush was unable to seek a third term as Governor.
Some speculated that Bush would run against Florida's current Democratic senator, [[Bill Nelson (politician)|Bill Nelson]], in the [[United States Senate election in Florida, 2006|2006 U.S. Senate election]], but he did not; the Republican candidate was [[Katherine Harris]], who lost to Nelson.

Notwithstanding rumors, he did not run for president in the [[United States presidential election, 2008|2008 election]].

===Political bases===
Bush is popular among [[Cuba]]ns in Florida (winning 80 percent of the Cuban vote in 2002) and popular among non-Cuban [[Hispanics]] (56 percent in 2002, equaling the 56 percent he won statewide). As a longtime supporter of [[Israel]],&lt;ref&gt;Associated Press. [http://www.sptimes.com/2004/04/27/State/Gov_Bush_declares_sup.shtml State: Gov. Bush declares support for Israel's fight], ''St. Petersburg Times'', April 27, 2004. Retrieved June 14, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Bush also maintains a significant connection to Florida's [[Jew]]ish voters. He was endorsed in his two winning Governor races by a national Jewish publication, and won 44 percent of the state's Jewish vote in the 2002 Governor's race.&lt;ref&gt;Stewart, Russ. [http://www.russstewart.com/4-16-03.htm WILL IRAQI VICTORY CONVERT JEWS TO GOP?], ''Russ Stewart'', April 16, 2003. Retrieved June 14, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Many black voters support his focus on public education and parental choice in education, and a number of [[Black Republican]] clubs have risen in Florida.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rpos.org/ffbr]{{Dead link|date=March 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; In his re-election in 2002, Bush surprised critics by winning the white female vote in the swing-voting battleground of Central Florida's I-4 corridor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.weeklystandard.com/Content/Public/Articles/000/000/003/259yvdec.asp?pg=2 |title=The (Finally) Emerging Republican Majority |publisher=Weeklystandard.com |date= |accessdate=2009-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most recently{{When|date=July 2011}}, he has reached out extensively to Florida's [[Haiti]]an community.

===Bush's impact on his political party===
Bush's appeal to Florida's highly diverse group of voters, along with his success in expanding the &quot;big tent&quot; of the [[Florida Republican Party]] (GOP), appear to have propelled him into a commanding political position. Nationwide, American [[conservative]]s appear to be positive about Bush, seeing him as committed to upholding core conservative principles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cato.org/pubs/pas/pa-454es.html |title=Fiscal Policy Report Card on America's Governors: 2002 |publisher=Cato.org |date=2002-09-20 |accessdate=2009-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Throughout his two administrations, Bush's office touted his record of non-discrimination and rewarding merit, claiming he employed highly qualified women, blacks and other minorities more often in top-level government positions than any previous Florida Governor.

Outside of Florida, fellow Republican leaders throughout the country have sought Bush's aid both on and off the campaign trail. Bush's out-of-state campaign visits include [[Kentucky]], where Republican challenger [[Ernie Fletcher]] appeared with Bush and won that state's governorship in 2003,&lt;ref&gt;Wolfe, Charles. [http://www.enquirer.com/editions/2003/11/05/loc_kygovernor05k.html As Ky. governor, Fletcher vows to 'clean up mess'], ''The Enquirer'', November 5, 2003. Retrieved June 14, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; ending a 32-year streak of Democratic governors. In [[California]], after Democratic Governor [[Gray Davis]] was ousted in a [[California recall election, 2003|recall vote]], Bush dispatched Florida's budget director&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spokesmanreview.com/local/story_txt.asp?date=101003&amp;ID=s1422739 Schwarzenegger building team], October 10, 2003. Retrieved June 14, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; to that state to lead an independent [[audit]] of California's budget, at the request of the state's newly elected Republican Governor, [[Arnold Schwarzenegger]].

Bush publicly critiqued the national Republican party for its adherence to ideology and partisanship on June 11, 2012.  In provocative comments shared with [[Bloomberg View]], Bush suggested that former Republican Presidents [[Ronald Reagan]] and [[George H. W. Bush]] would &quot;have had a hard time&quot; finding support in the contemporary GOP.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2012/06/12/us/politics/jeb-bush-takes-aim-at-fellow-republicans.html | work=The New York Times | first=Jim | last=Rutenberg | title=Jeb Bush Takes Aim at Fellow Republicans | date=June 11, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Political interests and business activities===
Bush has been active in the [[neoconservative]] think tank [[Project for the New American Century]], whose stated goal is to promote [[United States|American]] global leadership.

Since 2004, he has been serving a four-year term as a Board Member for the National Assessment Governing Board (NAGB).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nagb.org/about/nagb.html What is NAGB?&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]{{Dead link|date=April 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Created by Congress, this board's purpose is to establish policy on reports examining K-12 students' academic progress in America's public and private schools. In 2008, Bush will be serving on the NAGB educational committee focused on Standards, Design and Methodology.

In April 2007, Jeb Bush joined [[Tenet Healthcare]]'s board of directors.&lt;ref&gt;Koenig, David. [http://www.usatoday.com/money/economy/2007-05-10-3254091799_x.htm Jeb Bush joins Tenet Healthcare's board], ''USA Today'', May 10, 2007. Retrieved June 14, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; The following August, Bush joined investment bank, [[Lehman Brothers]], as an adviser in its [[private equity]] group.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/fundsFundsNews/idUSN3046902620070830 |title=Lehman hires Jeb Bush as private equity advisor |publisher=Reuters.com |date=2007-08-30 |accessdate=2009-04-03 | first=Dan | last=Wilchins}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Bush as NFL commissioner===
In May 2006, [[Associated Press|AP]] reported that Bush was privately approached to become the next commissioner of the [[National Football League]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20060524/ap_on_sp_fo_ne/fbn_jeb_bush_nfl_commissioner]{{Dead link|date=March 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is said to be an interest of his, but it was unknown whether he would take the position. The former commissioner, [[Paul Tagliabue]], announced that his tenure would soon be over and he is searching for replacements. &quot;I'm flattered,&quot; Jeb Bush said May 24, 2006, of the NFL's interest, &quot;but I'm Governor of the state of Florida and I intend to be Governor until I leave—which is January 2007. And I'm not going to consider any other options other than being Governor until I finish&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.usatoday.com/news/washington/2006-05-24-bush-tagliabue_x.htm |title=Jeb Bush quashes NFL speculation |publisher=Usatoday.Com |date=2006-05-25 |accessdate=2009-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Roger Goodell]] eventually became the new NFL commissioner.

===Speech at D.C. Summit===
On January 27, 2007, Bush spoke as the keynote speaker at the [[National Review|National Review Institute]]'s Conservative Summit in Washington, D.C. speaking about the Democratic take over in Congress. He told [[political conservative]]s &quot;we lost, and there are significant reasons that happened, but it isn't because conservatives were rejected. It's because we rejected the conservative philosophy in this country.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;DC speech WP&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Jeb Bush preaches to conservative choir at summit |author=Zachary A. Goldfarb|publisher=Washington Post|date=January 29, 2007|url=http://www.knoxnews.com/kns/politics/article/0,1406,KNS_356_5312155,00.html |accessdate=February 2, 2007 }} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; He told them “don't…abandon conservative principles…we don't need to be the end all and be all for every [[special interest group]], for every constituent that you like, for every person that's given a fundraising check to your campaign, for everything that is just wrong about public policy and politics”.&lt;ref name=&quot;CNS DC&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Jeb Bush Calls for Reforms, Return to Civility|author=Nathan Burchfiel|publisher=CNSNews|date=January 29, 2007|url=http://www.cnsnews.com/news/viewstory.asp?Page=/Politics/archive/200701/POL20070129b.html |accessdate=February 2, 2007 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070509024548/http://www.cnsnews.com/news/viewstory.asp?Page=/Politics/archive/200701/POL20070129b.html |archivedate = May 9, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; In attendance at the summit was former chairman of the [[Republican National Committee]] [[Ed Gillespie]] who said if he, like Bush, “left office with approval ratings above 60 percent…he might be in [[Des Moines]] today [preparing for the presidential primary]”.&lt;ref name=&quot;DC speech WP&quot;/&gt; Bush denied rumors that he would run for President in 2008, but “when questioned did not rule out running as a [[U.S. Vice President|vice presidential]] candidate.” He joked about being out of work for the first time in his life but said he is happy for the opportunity to “take a pause.”&lt;ref name=&quot;CNS DC&quot;/&gt;

===Possible run for U.S. Senate===
In 2008, Bush indicated that he was considering running in the [[United States Senate election in Florida, 2010|2010 U.S. Senate race]] for the seat being vacated by [[Mel Martinez]], who announced that he would retire at the end of his term.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.politico.com/news/stories/1208/16155.html |title=Jeb: I am considering Senate run - Carol E. Lee and Jonathan Martin |publisher=Politico.com |date= |accessdate=2009-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newsweek.com/id/172341 |title=Jeb Bush's Prospects in a Florida Senate Race &amp;#124; Newsweek Politics |publisher=Newsweek.com |date= |accessdate=2009-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/hostednews/ap/article/ALeqM5g1g_1QTpZ5s4yTVGnK_iHsVxZK_wD94RFC9G0 ]{{Dead link|date=April 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/12/04/us/04brfs-JEBBUSHSHOWS_BRF.html?ref=us | work=The New York Times | title=Florida: Jeb Bush Shows Interest In Senate Seat | date=December 4, 2008 | accessdate=April 2, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://marcambinder.theatlantic.com/archives/2008/12/jeb_bush_ponders_florida_senat.php |title=Jeb Bush Ponders Florida Senate Run - Marc Ambinder |publisher=Marcambinder.theatlantic.com |date= |accessdate=2009-04-03}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; But in January 2009, he announced that he would not run for the Senate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://politicalticker.blogs.cnn.com/2009/01/06/jeb-bush-not-running-for-senate/ |title=CNN.com: Jeb Bush not running for Senate |publisher=Politicalticker.blogs.cnn.com |date= January 6, 2009|accessdate=2009-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Instead, he supported [[Marco Rubio]] for the position.

===2012 Presidential election===
Throughout 2009 and 2010, rumors abounded that Bush would attempt to win the Republican nomination for the [[United States presidential election, 2012|2012 presidential election]]; rumors that he strongly denied from the beginning.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://blogs.wsj.com/washwire/2010/07/27/jeb-bush-says-no-to-2012-run/ | work=The Wall Street Journal | title=Jeb Bush Says No to 2012 Run | first=Peter | last=Wallsten | date=July 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In February 2011, after renewed calls were made for him to run for president,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nationalreview.com/articles/259099/bush-2012-rich-lowry | work=The National Review | title=Bush 2012 | first=Rich | last=Lowry | date=February 7, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bush was asked whether the door remained closed on a Presidential run. &quot;Yes&quot;, was his reply.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.politico.com/news/stories/0211/49078.html | work=The Politico | title=Jeb emails: National Review or not, it's still no | first=Jonathan | last=Martin | date=February 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2011, he reiterated his position that he was not running, although he was heavily critical of the Obama administration.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.myfoxtampabay.com/dpp/entertainment/television/jeb-bush-gives-obama-'f'-grade-on-economy-07222011 &quot;Jeb Bush gives Obama 'F' grade on economy&quot;], FOX Tampa Bay. 22 july 2011. Retrieved 7 aug 2011&lt;/ref&gt; That month his son [[George P. Bush|George]] urged him to join the 2012 primary.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2017548/George-P-Bush-wants-father-Jeb-White-House--2013.html?ito=feeds-newsxml &quot;George P Bush wants father Jeb in the White House... by 2013&quot;], Daily Mail. 22 july 2011. Retrieved 7 aug 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

== Electoral history ==
{{Election box begin | title=Florida Gubernatorial Election 1994}}
{{Election box candidate with party link|
  |party      = Democratic Party (United States)
  |candidate  = [[Lawton Chiles]] (incumbent)
  |votes      = 2,135,008
  |percentage = 50.75
  |change     =
}}
{{Election box candidate with party link
|party        = Republican Party (United States)
  |candidate  = Jeb Bush
  |votes      = 2,071,068
  |percentage = 49.23
  |change     =
}}
{{Election box end}}

{{Election box begin | title=Florida Gubernatorial Election 1998}}
{{Election box candidate with party link|
  |party      = Republican Party (United States)
  |candidate  = Jeb Bush
  |votes      = 2,191,105
  |percentage = 55.27
  |change     =
}}
{{Election box candidate with party link|
  |party      = Democratic Party (United States)
  |candidate  = [[Buddy MacKay]]
  |votes      = 1,773,054
  |percentage = 44.72
  |change     =
}}
{{Election box end}}

{{Election box begin | title=Florida Gubernatorial Election 2002}}
{{Election box candidate with party link|
  |party      = Republican Party (United States)
  |candidate  = Jeb Bush
  |votes      = 2,856,845
  |percentage = 56.01
  |change     =
}}
{{Election box candidate with party link|
  |party      = Democratic Party (United States)
  |candidate  = [[Bill McBride (candidate)|Bill McBride]]
  |votes      = 2,201,427
  |percentage = 43.16
  |change     =
}}
{{Election box end}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Florida|Biography|Politics}}

*[[Bush family]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
*Freedberg, Sydney P. &quot;Jeb Bush: The Son Rises Away from Dad's Shadow.&quot; ''[[The Miami Herald]]'', August 15, 1994.
*[[Arianna Huffington|Huffington, Arianna]]. [http://www.salon.com/news/col/huff/2002/09/16/war_on_drugs/ &quot;The latest Bush hypocrisy&quot;]. [[Salon.com]], September 16, 2002.
*Viglucci, Andres and Alfonso Chardy. [http://www.miami.com/mld/miami/4221945.htm &quot;Bush and business: Fast success, brushes with mystery&quot;]. ''The Miami Herald'', October 5, 2002.
*Yardley, William. [http://www.miami.com/mld/miamiherald/news/state/4124298.htm &quot;Jeb Bush: His early values shape his politics.&quot;] ''The Miami Herald'', September 22, 2002.
*[[Fred Barnes (journalist)|Barnes, Fred]]. [http://www.weeklystandard.com/Content/Public/Articles/000/000/012/293ppytu.asp &quot;Governor in Chief: Jeb Bush's remarkable eight years of achievement in Florida.&quot;] ''The Weekly Standard'', June 12, 2006.

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Commons|Jeb Bush}}
* [http://www.museumoffloridahistory.com/resources/collections/governors/about.cfm?id=50 Official Governor's portrait and biography from the State of Florida]
*{{GovLinks | nga = past-governors-bios/page_florida/col2-content/main-content-list/title_bush_jeb.html | votesmart = | washpo = Jeb_Bush | ontheissues = Jeb_Bush.htm | followmoney = 3310 | c-span = jebbush | rose = | imdb = nm1654623 | nyt = b/jeb_bush | wsj = | guardian = | worldcat = lccn-n96-73715 | nndb = 646/000022580 | findagrave = }}

{{s-start}}
{{s-off}}
{{succession box
|title=[[Governor of Florida]]
|before=[[Buddy MacKay]]
|years=1999-2007
|after=[[Charlie Crist]]
}}
{{s-ppo}}
{{succession box
|title=[[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]] nominee for [[Governor of Florida]]
|before=[[Bob Martinez]]
|years=[[Florida gubernatorial election, 1994|1994]], [[Florida gubernatorial election, 1998|1998]], [[Florida gubernatorial election, 2002|2002]]
|after=[[Charlie Crist]]}}

{{s-end}}
{{Bush family}}
{{Governors of Florida}}
{{RepNomFlGov}}
{{United states presidential election and recount, 2000}}

&lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
{{Persondata
|NAME= Bush, Jeb
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=
|SHORT DESCRIPTION= Governor of Florida
|DATE OF BIRTH= February 11, 1953
|PLACE OF BIRTH= [[Midland, Texas]]
|DATE OF DEATH=
|PLACE OF DEATH=
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Bush, Jeb}}
[[Category:1953 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:20th-century Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:21st-century Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:American expatriates in Venezuela]]
[[Category:American real estate businesspeople]]
[[Category:American Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:Bush family]]
[[Category:Businesspeople from Texas]]
[[Category:Children of Presidents of the United States]]
[[Category:Converts to Roman Catholicism from Anglicanism]]
[[Category:Florida Republicans]]
[[Category:Governors of Florida]]
[[Category:Great Floridians]]
[[Category:Lehman Brothers people‎]]
[[Category:People from Coral Gables, Florida]]
[[Category:People from Houston, Texas]]
[[Category:People from Midland, Texas]]
[[Category:Phillips Academy alumni]]
[[Category:Republican Party state governors of the United States]]
[[Category:Siblings of Presidents of the United States]]
[[Category:State cabinet secretaries of Florida]]
[[Category:University of Texas at Austin alumni]]



[[ar:جب بوش]]
[[ast:Jeb Bush]]
[[bg:Джеб Буш]]
[[cs:Jeb Bush]]
[[da:Jeb Bush]]
[[de:Jeb Bush]]
[[el:Τζεμπ Μπους]]
[[es:Jeb Bush]]
[[fr:Jeb Bush]]
[[ga:Jeb Bush]]
[[ko:젭 부시]]
[[id:Jeb Bush]]
[[it:Jeb Bush]]
[[he:ג'ב בוש]]
[[ka:ჯებ ბუში]]
[[nl:Jeb Bush]]
[[ja:ジェブ・ブッシュ]]
[[no:Jeb Bush]]
[[pl:Jeb Bush]]
[[pt:Jeb Bush]]
[[ru:Буш, Джеб]]
[[sq:Jeb Bush]]
[[simple:Jeb Bush]]
[[sk:Jeb Bush]]
[[sh:Jeb Bush]]
[[fi:Jeb Bush]]
[[sv:Jeb Bush]]
[[tr:Jeb Bush]]
[[vi:Jeb Bush]]
[[zh:傑布·布希]]</text>
      <sha1>osodzot2p6hmyd0b6g89zuqj0ob280w</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
