<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Jeffrey Dahmer</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>16218</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520687404</id>
      <parentid>520191673</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-31T02:26:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mayumashu</username>
        <id>203494</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Murders */ typo</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="33602">{{Redirect|Dahmer}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=May 2012}}
{{pp-semi-protected|small=yes}}
{{Infobox murderer
| name        = Jeffrey Dahmer
| image       = Jeffrey-dahmer.jpg
| caption     = Dahmer's mugshot, taken in 1982 by the Milwaukee County Sheriff's Department
| birthname   = Jeffrey Lionel Dahmer
| alias       = The Milwaukee Cannibal,&lt;br&gt;The Milwaukee Monster
| birth_date  = {{Birth date|1960|5|21}}
| birth_place = [[West Allis, Wisconsin]], U.S.
| death_date  = {{Death date and age|1994|11|28|1960|5|21}}
| death_place = [[Portage, Wisconsin]], U.S.
| cause       = Severe head [[Physical trauma|trauma]]
| victims     = 17 
| country     = United States
| states      = [[Ohio]], [[Wisconsin]]
| beginyear   = June 6, 1978
| endyear     = July 19, 1991
| apprehended = July 22, 1991
| conviction  = [[Child molestation]],&lt;br&gt;[[Disorderly conduct]],&lt;br&gt;[[Indecent exposure]],&lt;br&gt;Murder,&lt;br&gt;[[Public intoxication]]
| sentence    = [[Life imprisonment]] (15 life terms)
}}
'''Jeffrey Lionel Dahmer''' (May 21, 1960 – November 28, 1994) was an American [[serial killer]] and [[sex offender]]. Dahmer murdered 17 men and boys between 1978 and 1991, with the majority of the murders occurring between 1987 and 1991. His murders involved [[rape]], [[dismemberment]], [[necrophilia]] and [[cannibalism]]. On November 28, 1994, he was beaten to death by an inmate at the [[Columbia Correctional Institution]], where he had been incarcerated.

== Early life ==
[[File:Jeffrey Dahmer HS Yearbook.jpg|thumb|left|Dahmer as a senior in high school, 1978.]]
Dahmer was born in [[West Allis, Wisconsin]], the son of Joyce Annette (née Flint) and Lionel Herbert Dahmer, an [[analytical chemistry|analytical chemist]].&lt;ref name=&quot;beaconj&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=JEFFREY DAHMER|publisher=Beacon Journal|date=November 29, 1994|url=http://nl.newsbank.com/nl-search/we/Archives?p_product=AK&amp;s_site=ohio&amp;p_multi=AK&amp;p_theme=realcities&amp;p_action=search&amp;p_maxdocs=200&amp;p_topdoc=1&amp;p_text_direct-0=0EB63121D18F8CA5&amp;p_field_direct-0=document_id&amp;p_perpage=10&amp;p_sort=YMD_date:D&amp;s_trackval=GooglePM|accessdate=May 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Seven years later, his brother David was born.{{sfn|Dahmer|1994|p=61}} Joyce Dahmer reportedly had a difficult pregnancy with her elder son. When Jeffrey was eight years old, he moved with his family to [[Bath Township, Summit County, Ohio|Bath, Ohio]].  Dahmer grew increasingly withdrawn and uncommunicative between the ages of 10 and 15, showing little interest in any hobbies or social interactions.{{sfn|Dahmer|1994|pp=76–79}} He biked around his neighborhood looking for dead animals, which he dissected at home (or in the woods near his home). In one instance, he put a dog's head on a stake.{{sfn|Dahmer|1994|p=80}} Though fundamentally an outcast at [[Revere High School (Ohio)|Revere High School]], Dahmer nonetheless became something of a [[cult following|cult figure]] among some students due to his impressions of his mother's interior decorator, who suffered from [[cerebral palsy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Backderf|first=Derf|title=My Friend Dahmer|year=2012|publisher=Abrams ComicArts|isbn=1419702173}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Dahmer began drinking in his teens and was an alcoholic by the time of his high school graduation.{{sfn|Dahmer|1994|p=82}}

In 1977, Lionel and Joyce Dahmer divorced.{{sfn|Dahmer|1994|p=90}} Dahmer attended [[The Ohio State University]], but dropped out after one quarter, having failed to attend most of his classes.{{sfn|Dahmer|1994|pp=103–104}} He was drunk for the majority of the term.{{sfn|Dahmer|1994|p=105}} Dahmer's father then forced him to enlist in the [[United States Army|Army]].{{sfn|Dahmer|1994|p=107}} Dahmer did well at first,{{sfn|Dahmer|1994|pp=108–109}} but he was discharged after two years because of his alcoholism.{{sfn|Dahmer|1994|pp=110–111}} When the Army discharged Dahmer in 1981, he was provided with a plane ticket to anywhere in the country. Dahmer later told police he could not go home to face his father, so he headed to [[Miami Beach, Florida]], because he was &quot;tired of the cold.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;adamWalsh&quot; /&gt; He spent most of his time there at a hospital, but was soon kicked out for drinking.&lt;ref name=&quot;adamWalsh&quot; /&gt; After coming home, he continued to drink heavily, and he was arrested for drunk and disorderly conduct later in 1981.{{sfn|Dahmer|1994|p=114}}

In 1982, Dahmer moved in with his grandmother in West Allis,{{sfn|Dahmer|1994|p=115}} where he lived for six years.{{sfn|Dahmer|1994|p=117}} During this time, his behavior grew increasingly strange. His grandmother once found a fully dressed male mannequin in his closet; Dahmer had stolen it from a store.{{sfn|Dahmer|1994|pp=119–120}} On another occasion, she found a [[.357 Magnum]] under his bed.{{sfn|Dahmer|1994|pp=122–123}} Terrible smells came from the basement; Dahmer told his father that he had brought home a dead [[squirrel]] and dissolved it with chemicals.{{sfn|Dahmer|1994|pp=124–126}} He was arrested twice for [[indecent exposure]], in 1982 and 1986;{{sfn|Dahmer|1994|p=131}} in his second offense, he [[masturbation|masturbated]] in front of two boys.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bardsley-7&quot; /&gt;

In summer 1988, Dahmer's grandmother asked him to move out because of his late nights, his strange behavior, and the foul smells from the basement. He then found an apartment on [[Milwaukee]]'s West side, closer to his job at the Ambrosia Chocolate Factory.{{sfn|Dahmer|1994|p=132}} On September 26, 1988, one day after moving into his apartment, he was arrested for drugging and [[Child sexual abuse|sexually fondling]] a 13-year-old boy in Milwaukee.{{sfn|Dahmer|1994|pp=133–135}} He was sentenced to five years' [[probation]] and one year in a [[work release]] camp. He was required to register as a [[sex offense|sex offender]].{{sfn|Dahmer|1994|p=138}} Dahmer was paroled from the work release camp two months early, and he soon moved into a new apartment.{{sfn|Dahmer|1994|pp=143–144}} Shortly thereafter, he began a string of murders that ended with his arrest in 1991.

== Murders ==

Dahmer committed his first murder in the summer of 1978, at the age of 18. His father was away on business and his mother had moved out, taking his brother with her; Dahmer was left behind, alone. That June, Dahmer picked up a hitchhiker named Stephen Hicks and offered to drink beer with him back at his father's house, planning to eventually have sex with him. When Hicks tried to leave, Dahmer bludgeoned Hicks to death with a 10&amp;nbsp;lb. [[dumbbell]], striking the back of his head, later saying he had committed the crime because &quot;the guy wanted to leave and [he] didn't want him to.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;PurcellArrigo2006&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Purcell|first=Catherine E.|coauthors=A. Arrigo, Bruce|title=The Psychology of Lust Murder: Paraphilia, Sexual Killing, and Serial Homicide|publisher=Academic Press|year=2006|page=77|chapter=5|isbn=0-12-370510-X|url=http://books.google.ca/books?id=agmkfIgbQxUC&amp;pg=PA77&amp;lpg=PA77&amp;dq=Jeffery+Dahmer%2Bhicks&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=ymRSt4IgrO&amp;sig=Ii6-iUCiSsMv8xSyTk3xhNY2Jg8&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=_yI5SoOuLo7qsQPc6aX-Bg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dahmer buried the body in the backyard.&lt;ref&gt;Roy, Jody M. ''Love to Hate'' NY: Columbia Univ. Press, 2002; pp. 102 ''et seq.''&lt;/ref&gt; Nine years passed before he killed again; in September 1987, Dahmer picked up 26-year-old Steven Tuomi at a bar and killed him on impulse; he later said he had no memory of committing the crime.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bardsley-7&quot; /&gt; After the Tuomi murder, Dahmer continued to kill sporadically: two more murders in 1988, and another in early 1989, usually picking up his victims in [[gay bar]]s and having sex with them before killing them.&lt;ref&gt;Roy, Jody M. ''Love to Hate'' NY: Columbia Univ. Press, 2002; pp. 103 ''et seq.''&lt;/ref&gt; He kept the skull of one of his victims, Anthony Sears, until he was caught.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bardsley-8&quot; /&gt;

In May 1990, he moved out of his grandmother's house for the last time and into an apartment that later became infamous: Apartment 213, 924 North 25th Street, Milwaukee. Dahmer picked up the pace of his killing: four more murders before the end of 1990, two more in February and April 1991, and another in May 1991.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bardsley-10&quot; /&gt;

In the early morning hours of May 27, 1991, 14-year-old Konerak Sinthasomphone (the younger brother of the boy whom Dahmer had molested in 1988) was discovered on the street, wandering naked, heavily under the influence of drugs and bleeding from his [[rectum]]. Two young women from the neighborhood found the dazed boy and called [[9-1-1|911]]. Dahmer chased his victim down and tried to take him away, but the women stopped him.{{sfn|Davis|1991|p=7}} Dahmer told [[John Balcerzak]] and Joseph Gabrish, police officers dispatched to the scene, that Sinthasomphone was his 19-year-old boyfriend, and that they had an argument while drinking. Against the protests of the two women who had called 911, who recognized him from the neighborhood and insisted that he was a child and could not speak English, the officers turned him over to Dahmer. They later reported smelling a strange scent while inside Dahmer's apartment, but did not investigate it. The smell was the body of Tony Hughes, Dahmer's previous victim, decomposing in the bedroom. The officers did not make any attempt to verify Sinthasomphone's age or identity, nor locate someone who could communicate with him, and failed to run a background check that would have revealed Dahmer being a convicted [[child molestation|child molester]] still under probation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bardsley-3&quot; /&gt; Later that night, Dahmer killed and dismembered Sinthasomphone, keeping his skull as a souvenir.

By summer 1991, Dahmer was murdering approximately one person each week. He killed Matt Turner on June 30, Jeremiah Weinberger on July 5, Oliver Lacy on July 12, and finally Joseph Brandehoft on July 19. Dahmer got the idea that he could turn his victims into &quot;[[zombie]]s&quot; — completely submissive, eternally youthful sexual partners – and attempted to do so by drilling holes into their skulls and injecting [[hydrochloric acid]] or boiling water into the frontal lobe area of their brains with a large syringe, usually while the victim was still alive.{{sfn|Dahmer|1994|p=211}} Other residents of the Oxford Apartments complex noticed terrible smells coming from Apartment 213, as well as the thumps of falling objects and the occasional buzzing of a power saw.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Follow TIME Facebook Twitter Google + Tumblr |url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,973550-1,00.html |title=The Little Flat of Horrors|work=TIME Magazine|date=1991-08-05 |accessdate=2012-08-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike many serial killers, Dahmer killed victims from a variety of racial backgrounds.

== Arrest ==

On July 22, 1991, Dahmer lured another man, Tracy Edwards, into his home. According to the would-be victim, Dahmer struggled with Edwards in order to handcuff him, but ultimately failed to cuff his wrists together.{{sfn|Davis|1991|p=151}} Wielding a large butcher knife, Dahmer forced Edwards into the bedroom, where Edwards saw pictures of mangled bodies on the wall and noticed the terrible smell coming from a large blue barrel; the barrel was filled with potent acid which dissolved human bodies to [[sludge]] for disposal via the apartment toilet.{{sfn|Davis|1991|p=152}} Edwards punched Dahmer in the face, kicked him in the stomach, ran for the door and escaped.{{sfn|Davis|1991|pp=153–154}} Running through the streets with handcuffs still hanging from one hand, Edwards waved for help to a police car driven by Robert Rauth and Rolf Mueller of the Milwaukee police department.{{sfn|Davis|1991|p=154}} Edwards led police back to Dahmer's apartment, where Dahmer at first acted friendly to the officers. However, Edwards remembered that the knife Dahmer had threatened him with was in the bedroom. When one of the officers checked the bedroom, he saw the photographs of mangled bodies and called for his partner to arrest Dahmer.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bardsley-4&quot; /&gt; As one officer subdued Dahmer, the other opened the refrigerator and found a human head. Further searching of the apartment revealed three more severed heads, multiple photographs of murdered victims and human remains, severed hands and penises, and photographs of dismembered victims and human remains in his refrigerator.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bardsley-5&quot; /&gt;

The story of Dahmer's arrest and the inventory in his apartment quickly gained notoriety: several corpses were stored in acid-filled vats, and implements for the construction of an [[altar]] of candles and human skulls were found in his closet. Accusations soon surfaced that Dahmer had practiced necrophilia and cannibalism. Seven skulls were found in the apartment.{{sfn|Davis|1991|p=157}} A human heart was found in the freezer.{{sfn|Davis|1991|p=158}}

== Trial ==

[[File:JeffreyDahmer-StonePhillips.jpg|thumb|Dahmer during an interview for ''[[Dateline NBC]]'' with [[Stone Phillips]], 1994.]]

Dahmer was indicted on 17 murder charges, later reduced to 15. Dahmer was not charged in the [[attempted murder]] of Edwards.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thebiographychannel.co.uk/biographies/jeffrey-dahmer.html |title=Jeffrey Dahmer - Biography on Bio |publisher=Thebiographychannel.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2012-08-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; His trial began on January 30, 1992.{{sfn|Dahmer|1994|p=207}} With evidence overwhelmingly against him, Dahmer pleaded [[Insanity defense|not guilty by reason of insanity]].{{sfn|Dahmer|1994|pp=209–210}} The trial lasted two weeks.{{sfn|Dahmer|1994|p=211}} The court found Dahmer sane and guilty on 15 counts of murder and sentenced him to 15 [[life term]]s,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,975527,00.html &quot;Guilty!&quot;], ''TIME Magazine, May 18, 1992&lt;/ref&gt; totaling 957 years in prison, which was the maximum penalty available as Wisconsin abolished [[capital punishment]] in 1853.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bardsley-21&quot; /&gt; At his sentencing hearing, Dahmer expressed remorse for his actions, and said that he wished for his own death. In May of that year, Dahmer was [[extradition|extradited]] to Ohio, where he entered a plea of guilty for the murder of his first victim, Stephen Hicks.{{sfn|Dahmer|1994|p=241}}

== Imprisonment and death ==

Dahmer served his time at the [[Columbia Correctional Institution]] in [[Portage, Wisconsin]], where he ultimately declared himself a [[Born again Christianity|born-again Christian]]. [[Roy Ratcliff]], a local preacher from the [[Churches of Christ]], met with Dahmer and agreed to [[baptism|baptize]] him.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bardsley-22&quot; /&gt;

Dahmer was attacked twice in prison, the first time in July 1994. An inmate attempted to slash Dahmer's throat with a razor blade while Dahmer was returning to his cell from a church service in the prison chapel. Dahmer escaped the incident with superficial wounds.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.deseretnews.com/article/390410/ Wisconsin Inmate help in Slaying of Dahmer.&quot;] ''Deseret News''. November 29, 1994.&lt;/ref&gt; While doing janitorial work in the prison gym, Dahmer and another inmate, [[Jesse Anderson]], were severely beaten by fellow inmate [[Christopher Scarver]] with a broomstick handle on November 28, 1994.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/1994/11/29/us/jeffrey-dahmer-multiple-killer-is-bludgeoned-to-death-in-prison.html &quot;Jeffrey Dahmer, Multiple Killer, Is Bludgeoned to Death in Prison.&quot;] ''The New York Times. November ''&lt;/ref&gt; Dahmer died of severe head [[Physical trauma|trauma]] while on his way to the hospital in an ambulance. Anderson died two days later from his wounds.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/nation/article/0,8599,2606,00.html &quot;Dahmer Killer Charged&quot;], ''TIME Magazine'', December 15, 1994&lt;/ref&gt;

== Aftermath ==

Upon learning of his death, Dahmer's mother, Joyce Flint, responded angrily to the media, &quot;Now is everybody happy? Now that he's bludgeoned to death, is that good enough for everyone?&quot; The response of the families of Dahmer's victims was mixed, although it appears most were pleased with his death. The district attorney who prosecuted Dahmer cautioned against turning Scarver into a folk hero, noting that Dahmer's death was still murder.&lt;ref name=&quot;peoplemag1994&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.people.com/people/archive/article/0,,20104660,00.html|title=The Final Victim|last=Gleick|first=Elizabeth|date=December 12, 1994|work=Vol. 42 No. 24|publisher=People Magazine|accessdate=June 17, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Oxford Apartments at 924 North 25th Street were demolished in 1992; the site is now a vacant lot. Plans to convert the site into a memorial garden failed to materialize.

In 1994, Lionel Dahmer published a book, ''A Father's Story,'' and donated a portion of the proceeds from his book to the victims' families. Most of the families showed support for Lionel Dahmer and his wife, Shari. He has retired from his career as an [[analytical chemistry|analytical chemist]] and resides with his wife in [[Medina County, Ohio]]. Lionel Dahmer is an advocate for [[creationism]], and his wife was a member of the board of the Medina County Ohio Horseman's Council.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.answersingenesis.org/home/area/bios/ |title=Some modern scientists who have accepted the biblical account of creation |work=Answers in Genesis}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both continue to carry the name Dahmer and say they love Jeffrey despite his crimes. Jeffrey's mother and Lionel Dahmer's first wife, Joyce (Flint), died of cancer in 2000. Jeffrey's younger brother, David, changed his last name and lives in anonymity.

Dahmer's estate was awarded to the families of 11 of his victims who had sued for damages. In 1996, Thomas Jacobson, a lawyer representing eight of the families, announced a planned auction of Dahmer's estate to raise up to $1 million, sparking controversy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://edition.cnn.com/US/9605/08/dahmer.auction/index.html Serial killer's property set to go on the auction block.&quot;] ''CNN.com''. May 8, 1996.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Johnson, Dirk. [http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E4DE1039F933A15756C0A960958260 &quot;Bid to Auction Killer's Tools Provokes Disgust.&quot;] ''The New York Times''. May 20, 1996.&lt;/ref&gt; A civic group, Milwaukee Civic Pride, was quickly established in an effort to raise the funds to purchase and destroy Dahmer's possessions. The group pledged $407,225, including a $100,000 gift by Milwaukee real estate developer Joseph Zilber, for purchase of Dahmer's estate; five of the eight families represented by Jacobson agreed to the terms, and Dahmer's possessions were destroyed and buried in an undisclosed Illinois landfill.&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EEDF1E39F93AA15756C0A960958260 &quot;Auction of Dahmer Items Is Apparently Off.&quot;] ''The New York Times''. May 29, 1996.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;O'Flaherty, Sean. [http://www.todaystmj4.com/features/positivelymilwaukee/12527956.html &quot;Joseph Zilber&amp;nbsp;– A Gift To Milwaukee.&quot;] ''Today's TMJ4''. December 15, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.todaystmj4.com/news/local/dahmer/125984428.html &quot;Dahmer's Possessions Destroyed.&quot;] &quot;Today's TMJ4.&quot; July 21, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2007, evidence surfaced potentially linking Dahmer to [[Murder of Adam Walsh|Adam Walsh's 1981 abduction and murder]] in Florida.&lt;ref name=&quot;adamWalsh&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| url = http://www.wisn.com/news/10903529/detail.html |title=Did Dahmer Have One More Victim? |work=The Milwaukee Channel |accessdate =February 5, 2007|date=February 1, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, Adam's father, [[John Walsh]], believed that another serial killer, [[Ottis Toole]], committed the crime.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,250856,00.html &quot;'America's Most Wanted' Host Believes Dahmer is Not Son's Killer.&quot;] ''FoxNews.com''. February 7, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; When interviewed about Adam Walsh in the early 1990s, Dahmer repeatedly denied involvement in the crime.&lt;ref name=&quot;adamWalsh&quot; /&gt; In 2008, Florida police declared the Walsh case closed, naming Toole, who died in prison in 1996, as the killer.&lt;ref&gt;Almanzar, Yolanne. [http://www.nytimes.com/2008/12/17/us/17adam.html &quot;Police Expected to Close Adam Walsh Case.&quot;] ''The New York Times''. December 17, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Known murder victims ==

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
! Name
! Age&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC&quot;&gt;[http://www.bbc.net.uk/crime/caseclosed/dahmer1.shtml BBC&amp;nbsp;– Jeffrey Dahmer, the Milwaukee Cannibal]{{Dead link|date=July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
! Date of death
|-
| {{sortname|Stephen|Hicks|nolink=1}}
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 19
| align=right | {{dts|Jun 6, 1978}}
|-
| {{sortname|Steven|Tuomi|nolink=1}}
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 26
| align=right | {{dts|Sep 15, 1987}}
|-
| {{sortname|James &quot;Jamie&quot;|Doxtator|nolink=1}}
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 14
| align=right | {{dts|Jan 1988}}
|-
| {{sortname|Richard|Guerrero|nolink=1}}
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 25
| align=right | {{dts|Mar 24, 1988}}
|-
| {{sortname|Anthony|Sears|nolink=1}}
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 26
| align=right | {{dts|Mar 25, 1989}}
|-
| {{sortname|Eddie|Smith|nolink=1}}
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 36
| align=right | {{dts|Jun 1990}}
|-
| {{sortname|Ricky|Beeks|nolink=1}}
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 27
| align=right | {{dts|Jul 1990}}
|-
| {{sortname|Ernest|Miller|nolink=1}}
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 22
| align=right | {{dts|Sep 1990}}
|-
| {{sortname|David|Thomas|nolink=1}}
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 23
| align=right | {{dts|Sep 1990}}
|-
| {{sortname|Curtis|Straughter|nolink=1}}
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 19
| align=right | {{dts|Feb 1991}}
|-
| {{sortname|Errol|Lindsey|nolink=1}}
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 19
| align=right | {{dts|Apr 1991}}
|-
| {{sortname|Tony|Hughes|nolink=1}}
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 31
| align=right | {{dts|May 24, 1991}}
|-
| {{sortname|Konerak|Sinthasomphone|nolink=1}}
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 14
| align=right | {{dts|May 27, 1991}}
|-
| {{sortname|Matt|Turner|nolink=1}}
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 20
| align=right | {{dts|Jun 30, 1991}}
|-
| {{sortname|Jeremiah|Weinberger|nolink=1}}
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 23
| align=right | {{dts|Jul 5, 1991}}
|-
| {{sortname|Oliver|Lacy|nolink=1}}
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 23
| align=right | {{dts|Jul 12, 1991}}
|-
| {{sortname|Joseph|Bradehoft|nolink=1}}
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 25
| align=right | {{dts|Jul 19, 1991}}
|}

==Media portrayals==
* In 1992, [[Hart Fisher]] published a comic book titled ''Jeffery [''[{{sic}}]''] Dahmer: An Unauthorized Biography Of A Serial Killer. Collector's Item Issue'', which the ''[[Milwaukee Sentinel]]'' described as &quot;lurid and error-ridden.&quot; The publication sparked protests both in Milwaukee&lt;ref&gt;Johnson-Elie, Tannette. &quot;Dahmer comic book in demand in city&quot; ''Milwaukee Sentinel'' May 14, 1992; pp. 1, 13A.&lt;/ref&gt; and in Fisher's home town of [[Champaign, Illinois]].&lt;ref&gt;Williams, Celeste. &quot;Comic book on Dahmer sparks protests&quot; ''Milwaukee Journal'' June 14, 1992.&lt;/ref&gt; Dahmer's victims' relatives filed a lawsuit against Fisher (sometimes called &quot;Fischer&quot; in press reports) and his Boneyard Press for exploiting their loved ones' [[Privacy laws of the United States#Appropriation of name or likeness|names and likenesses]] for profit without compensation,&lt;ref&gt;Read, Ben. &quot;Victim's kin file suit over Dahmer's comic.&quot; ''Milwaukee Sentinel'' August 6, 1992.&lt;/ref&gt; but a court eventually ruled that since the victims were dead at the time of publication, &quot;name or likeness&quot; laws were not applicable.&lt;ref&gt;Sheard, Chester and Cole, Jeff. &quot;Comic book lawsuit dismissed: Court rules Dahmer-based cartoon won't infringe on victims'rights&quot; ''Milwaukee Journal'' August 20, 1994.&lt;/ref&gt; In the wake of the lawsuit, Fisher eventually published sequels ''The Further Adventures of Young Jeffy Dahmer'', ''Dahmer's Zombie Squad'' and ''Jeffrey Dahmer vs. Jesus Christ.''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.boneyardpress.net/news/news.html Boneyard Press newspage].&lt;/ref&gt; Hart later discussed the controversy and confronted several family members of Dahmer's victims during two lively appearances on both ''[[The Jerry Springer Show]]'' &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?feature=player_detailpage&amp;v=RJhwFNdWpsY |title=Hart Fisher on Jerry Springer pt. 2 |publisher=YouTube |date=2007-12-21 |accessdate=2012-08-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''[[Sally Jesse Raphael]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=p2WEDhNvZy4 |title=Sally Jesse Raphael with Hart D. Fisher |publisher=YouTube |date= |accessdate=2012-08-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The film ''[[Jeffrey Dahmer: The Secret Life]]'' was released in 1993, starring Carl Crew as Dahmer.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0244782/ &quot;Jeffrey Dahmer: The Secret Life'' at imdb.com]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Joyce Carol Oates]]' novel ''[[Zombie (novel)|Zombie]]'' (1995) was based on Dahmer's life.&lt;ref&gt;Johnson, Greg. ''Invisible Writer: A Biography of Joyce Carol Oates''. New York: Dutton, 1998, p. Ύ201.&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 2002, the biographical film ''[[Dahmer (film)|Dahmer]]'', starring [[Jeremy Renner]] in the title role and [[Bruce Davison]] as his father, premiered in Dahmer's hometown. The film quickly went to video.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Dahmer (film)|Dahmer]]'' opened in theaters on June 21, 2002.[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0285728/releaseinfo] The DVD was released October 27.[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0285728/dvd]&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 2002, cartoonist [[John Backderf]] (known as ''Derf''), who attended middle school and high school with Dahmer, produced a comic book entitled ''My Friend Dahmer'' which presents his recollections about the killer's adolescence.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/columnist/arnold/article/0,9565,230442,00.html] &quot;Hauling Garbage and Knowing Jeffrey Dahmer,&quot; Andrew D. Arnold, ''Time'' magazine, Apr. 16, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 2003, Raw Dog Screaming Press released [[Harold Jaffe]]'s ''15 Serial Killers: Docufiction'', which included a section on Dahmer; racism is implied as a factor in Konerak Sinthasomphone's death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www-rohan.sdsu.edu/~hjaffe/dahmer.html |title=Dahmer by Harold Jaffe from 15 Serial Killers |date= |accessdate=2012-10-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jaffe, Harold. ''15 Serial Killers: Docufiction''.Hyattsville MD:Raw Dog Screaming Press, 2003&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 2006, another film, ''[[Raising Jeffrey Dahmer]]'', was released; the film stars Rusty Sneary as Dahmer and Scott Cordes as Lionel; the film revolves around the reactions of Dahmer's parents after his arrest in 1991.
* Dahmer was featured in the 6th episode of Discovery Channel's documentary series ''[[Most Evil]].''
* In 2012, a documentary called ''[[Jeff (2012 film)|Jeff]]'' premiered, which featured interviews with Dahmer's next door neighbor, Dahmer's [[interrogator]], and the city [[medical examiner]], as well as fictionalized scenarios of Dahmer living in Milwaukee.&lt;ref&gt;[http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/movies/2012/03/sxsw2012-lives-touched-by-dahmer-in-jeff.html &quot;'Jeff' explores Dahmer's effect on Milwaukee&quot;] ''Los Angeles Times''. March 10, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==

* {{cite book
  | last = Dahmer
  | first = Lionel
  | title = A Father's Story
  | publisher = William Morrow and Co
  | year = 1994
  | isbn = 978-0-688-12156-3
  | url = http://books.google.com/?id=Ivp2QgAACAAJ&amp;dq=isbn=9780688121563
  | accessdate =July 26, 2010
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Davis
  | first = Donald
  | title = The Jeffrey Dahmer Story: An American Nightmare (previously published as: The Milwaukee Murders, Nightmare in Apartment 213: The True Story)
  | publisher = Macmillan
  | year = 1991
  | isbn = 978-0-312-92840-7
  | url = http://books.google.com/?id=F6tMtnYYXbEC&amp;dq=isbn=9780312928407
  | accessdate =July 26, 2010
  | ref = harv
  }}

{{Reflist
| colwidth = 30em
| refs =
&lt;ref name=&quot;Bardsley-3&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| url = http://www.trutv.com/library/crime/serial_killers/notorious/dahmer/3.html
| title = Jeffrey Dahmer&amp;nbsp;— Serial Killer and Cannibal&amp;nbsp;— The Body in the Bedroom
| last = Bardsley
| first = Marilyn
| work = TruTV.com
| publisher = TruTV Crime Library
| accessdate =July 26, 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Bardsley-4&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| url = http://www.trutv.com/library/crime/serial_killers/notorious/dahmer/4.html
| title = Jeffrey Dahmer&amp;nbsp;— Serial Killer and Cannibal&amp;nbsp;— Exposed!
| last = Bardsley
| first = Marilyn
| work = TruTV.com
| publisher = TruTV Crime Library
| accessdate =July 26, 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Bardsley-5&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| url = http://www.trutv.com/library/crime/serial_killers/notorious/dahmer/5.html
| title = Jeffrey Dahmer&amp;nbsp;— Serial Killer and Cannibal&amp;nbsp;— The Head in the Fridge
| last = Bardsley
| first = Marilyn
| work = TruTV.com
| publisher = TruTV Crime Library
| accessdate =July 26, 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Bardsley-7&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| url = http://www.trutv.com/library/crime/serial_killers/notorious/dahmer/7.html
| title = Jeffrey Dahmer&amp;nbsp;— Serial Killer and Cannibal&amp;nbsp;— Lust, Booze &amp; Murder
| last = Bardsley
| first = Marilyn
| work = TruTV.com
| publisher = TruTV Crime Library
| accessdate =July 26, 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Bardsley-8&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| url = http://www.trutv.com/library/crime/serial_killers/notorious/dahmer/8.html
| title = Jeffrey Dahmer&amp;nbsp;— Serial Killer and Cannibal&amp;nbsp;— More Murders, More Arrests
| last = Bardsley
| first = Marilyn
| work = TruTV.com
| publisher = TruTV Crime Library
| accessdate =July 26, 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Bardsley-10&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| url = http://www.trutv.com/library/crime/serial_killers/notorious/dahmer/10.html
| title = Jeffrey Dahmer&amp;nbsp;— Serial Killer and Cannibal&amp;nbsp;— The Killing Binge
| last = Bardsley
| first = Marilyn
| work = TruTV.com
| publisher = TruTV Crime Library
| accessdate =July 26, 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Bardsley-21&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| url = http://www.trutv.com/library/crime/serial_killers/notorious/dahmer/21.html
| title = Jeffrey Dahmer&amp;nbsp;— Serial Killer and Cannibal&amp;nbsp;— End of the Road
| last = Bardsley
| first = Marilyn
| work = TruTV.com
| publisher = TruTV Crime Library
| accessdate =July 26, 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Bardsley-22&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| url = http://www.trutv.com/library/crime/serial_killers/notorious/dahmer/22.html
| title = Jeffrey Dahmer&amp;nbsp;— Serial Killer and Cannibal&amp;nbsp;— Did Dahmer Find God?
| last = Bardsley
| first = Marilyn
| work = TruTV.com
| publisher = TruTV Crime Library
| accessdate =July 26, 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/ref name=&quot;JEFFREY DAHMER: A SERIAL KILLERS FINAL INTERVIEW&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| url = http://www.saferschools.org/pdfs/Odahmer.PDF
| title = Jeffrey dahmer: a serial killers final interview 
| work = saferschools.org
| accessdate =11-29-94
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

== Further reading ==

* Mann, Robert &amp; Williamson, Miryam. ''Forensic Detective&amp;nbsp;— How I Cracked The World's Toughest Cases''. Ballantine Books (March 28, 2006)
* Masters, Brian. ''The Shrine of Jeffrey Dahmer''. Hodder and Stoughton Limited, London 1993 (Paperback Coronet 1993)
* Pincus, Jonathan H. ''Base Instincts&amp;nbsp;— What Makes Killers kill?''. W.W. Norton &amp; Company, New York 2001 (Paperback 2002)
* Ratcliff, Roy with Lindy Adams. ''Dark Journey, Deep Grace: The Story Behind a Serial Killer's Journey to Faith''. Leafwood Publishers, (2006).

== External links ==

{{Wikiquote}}
* [http://www.trutv.com/library/crime/serial_killers/notorious/dahmer/2.html Crime Library article on Dahmer]
* {{iMDb name|0197213|Jeffrey Dahmer}}

{{Authority control|VIAF=6584207|LCCN=n/92/014113|GND=119123045}}

{{Persondata
|NAME = Dahmer, Jeffrey Lionel
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
|SHORT DESCRIPTION = serial killer
|DATE OF BIRTH = {{Birth date|1960|5|21|mf=y}}
|PLACE OF BIRTH = [[Milwaukee]], [[Wisconsin]], United States
|DATE OF DEATH = {{Death date|1994|11|28|mf=y}}
|PLACE OF DEATH = [[Portage, Wisconsin]], United States
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Dahmer, Jeffrey}}
[[Category:1960 births]]
[[Category:1994 deaths]]
[[Category:1978 murders in the United States]]
[[Category:1991 murders in the United States]]
[[Category:1994 murders in the United States]]
[[Category:American cannibals]]
[[Category:American members of the Churches of Christ]]
[[Category:American murderers of children]]
[[Category:American people convicted of murder]]
[[Category:American people who died in prison custody]]
[[Category:American prisoners sentenced to life imprisonment]]
[[Category:American rapists]]
[[Category:American serial killers]]
[[Category:American sex offenders]]
[[Category:Converts to Christianity]]
[[Category:Crime in Milwaukee, Wisconsin]]
[[Category:Criminals from Wisconsin]]
[[Category:Deaths by beating]]
[[Category:Human trophy collecting]]
[[Category:LGBT people from the United States]]
[[Category:American necrophiles]]
[[Category:Ohio State University alumni]]
[[Category:People convicted of murder by Wisconsin]]
[[Category:People from Milwaukee County, Wisconsin]]
[[Category:People from Summit County, Ohio]]
[[Category:Prisoners sentenced to life imprisonment by Wisconsin]]
[[Category:Prisoners who died in Wisconsin detention]]
[[Category:Serial killers murdered in prison custody]]
[[Category:United States Army soldiers]]

{{Link GA|ru}}

[[ar:جيفري دامر]]
[[bn:জেফ্রি ডাহ্‌মার]]
[[cs:Jeffrey Dahmer]]
[[da:Jeffrey Dahmer]]
[[de:Jeffrey Dahmer]]
[[es:Jeffrey Dahmer]]
[[fa:جفری دامر]]
[[fr:Jeffrey Dahmer]]
[[ko:제프리 다머]]
[[id:Jeffrey Dahmer]]
[[is:Jeffrey Dahmer]]
[[it:Jeffrey Dahmer]]
[[he:ג'פרי דאהמר]]
[[hu:Jeffrey Dahmer]]
[[nl:Jeffrey Dahmer]]
[[ja:ジェフリー・ダーマー]]
[[no:Jeffrey Dahmer]]
[[pl:Jeffrey Dahmer]]
[[pt:Jeffrey Dahmer]]
[[ru:Дамер, Джеффри]]
[[sco:Jeffrey Dahmer]]
[[simple:Jeffrey Dahmer]]
[[fi:Jeffrey Dahmer]]
[[sv:Jeffrey Dahmer]]
[[tr:Jeffrey Dahmer]]
[[uk:Джеффрі Дамер]]</text>
      <sha1>bzc38ld7r6sctkdtg186wr6040dqsj8</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
