<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Jersey Shore</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>442163</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521194096</id>
      <parentid>521194059</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-03T12:22:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Skamecrazy123</username>
        <id>11225276</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/125.174.204.90|125.174.204.90]] ([[User talk:125.174.204.90|talk]]) to last revision by ClueBot NG ([[WP:HG|HG]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="29300">{{about|the region|the MTV reality show|Jersey Shore (TV series)|the town in Pennsylvania|Jersey Shore, Pennsylvania}}
[[File:Wildwood night view from Mariner's Landing ferris wheel.JPG|right|thumb|270px|[[Wildwood, New Jersey]] at night, 2008.]]

The term '''Jersey Shore''' is used to refer to both the [[Atlantic|Atlantic coast]] of the [[U.S. state]] of [[New Jersey]] and the adjacent resort and residential communities. The New Jersey State Department of Tourism considers the [[Shore Region]], [[Atlantic City, New Jersey|Greater Atlantic City]], and the [[Southern Shore Region|Southern Shore]] to be distinct, each having a different character. The other three tourism marketing areas are the [[Gateway Region|Gateway]], the [[Delaware River Region|Delaware Valley]], and the [[Skylands Region|Skylands]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Visitor Information - Regional Tourism|url=http://www.state.nj.us/travel/regional.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Geographically, the term encompasses about 217 miles of the New Jersey coastal area from [[Sandy Hook (New Jersey)|Sandy Hook]] in the north to [[Cape May]] in the south. The Jersey Shore area includes the easternmost portions of [[Monmouth County, New Jersey|Monmouth]], [[Atlantic County, New Jersey|Atlantic]], [[Cape May County, New Jersey|Cape May]] and [[Ocean County, New Jersey|Ocean]] counties. While there is no defined border between [[North Jersey]] and [[South Jersey]], the [[Manasquan River]] or [[Interstate 195 (New Jersey)|Interstate 195]] are often mentioned as the border.&lt;ref&gt;Galant, Debra. [http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E6DD133FF93AA35757C0A9669C8B63 &quot;JERSEY; South Jersey Is Friendlier? Oh, Shut Up And Drive&quot;], ''[[The New York Times]]'', April 9, 2000, accessed April 11, 2008. &quot;For the purposes of dividing North Jersey from South Jersey, Gannett drew a line between Monmouth County and Ocean County. I decided that it would be amusing to drive down to this dividing line — which turned out to be the Manasquan River — and test the hypothesis.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

The coast is lined with over 40 communities, including [[Long Branch, New Jersey|Long Branch]], [[Asbury Park]], [[Ocean Grove, New Jersey|Ocean Grove]], [[Belmar, New Jersey|Belmar]], [[Spring Lake, New Jersey|Spring Lake]], [[Manasquan, New Jersey|Manasquan]], [[Point Pleasant Beach]], [[Seaside Heights]], [[Long Beach Island]], [[Brigantine]], [[Atlantic City]], [[Ocean City, New Jersey|Ocean City]], [[Sea Isle City]], [[Wildwood, New Jersey|Wildwood]], [[Wildwood Crest]], [[Chadwick Beach Island]], [[Cape May]], and [[Stone Harbor]]. Long Branch and Cape May both claim to be the country's original seashore resort; Ocean Grove and Cape May are world-renowned for their collections of [[Victorian era|Victorian]] residential architecture.

The Jersey Shore is a popular vacation spot for both [[New York]]ers and [[Pennsylvania]]ns. During the [[Pennsylvania gubernatorial election, 1994|1994 Pennsylvania gubernatorial election]], the [[Tom Ridge]] campaign used [[aerial advertising]] along the Jersey Shore.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | title = PoliticsPA's Top Summer Vacation Spots | newspaper = [[PoliticsPA]]| publisher = | date = | url = http://www.politicspa.com/features/top_vacation_spots.htm| archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20030202110025/www.politicspa.com/features/top_vacation_spots.htm|archivedate=2003-02-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[2010 United States Census|Census 2010]] showed that year-round populations along the Shore had significantly decreased.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nj.com/news/index.ssf/2011/05/census_results_show_nj_shore_to.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable shore towns==
===Monmouth County===
====[[Sandy Hook, New Jersey|Sandy Hook]]====
[[File:SH Light crop.jpg|thumb|[[Sandy Hook Light]] ]]
Sandy Hook is a [[barrier island]] owned by the federal government. Most of it is managed by the [[National Park Service]] as the Sandy Hook Unit of [[Gateway National Recreation Area]]. The eastern shoreline consists of public beaches: North Beach, Gunnison Beach, and South Beach. The southern part of the spit consists of public beaches, fishing areas, and the SeaGull's Nest, a seafood restaurant operated by a [[concession stand|concessionaire]]. The peninsula's ocean-facing beaches are considered among the finest in New Jersey and are a popular destination for recreation in summer when seasonal ferries&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.seastreak.com/sandyhook.aspx Sea Streak]&lt;/ref&gt; bring beachgoers.  [[Gunnison Beach, Sandy Hook|Gunnison Beach]] is one of the largest [[clothing optional]] beaches on the [[East Coast of the United States|East Coast]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first= Guy|last= Trebay|authorlink= |coauthors= |title= All Undressed and So Many Places to Go |url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE6D91030F931A3575AC0A9679C8B63 |quote=Crowds are also increasing these final summer days at [[Blacks Beach]] near [[San Diego]], at [[Mazo Beach]] on the lower Wisconsin River and at [[Gunnison Beach]] in Sandy Hook, New Jersey, a ''dress optional'' sand strip run by the [[National Park Service]] that was recently deemed by the Clean Beaches Council, an environmental group, one of the top 10 beaches in the United States. |publisher=New York Times |date=September 2, 2001 |accessdate=2007-08-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Flam, Faye. [http://nl.newsbank.com/nl-search/we/Archives?p_product=PI&amp;s_site=philly&amp;p_multi=PI&amp;p_theme=realcities&amp;p_action=search&amp;p_maxdocs=200&amp;p_topdoc=1&amp;p_text_direct-0=112F14F51E4A74A0&amp;p_field_direct-0=document_id&amp;p_perpage=10&amp;p_sort=YMD_date:D&amp;s_trackval=GooglePM &quot;Clothing optional may not be way of historical human&quot;], [[The Philadelphia Inquirer]], July 17, 2006. Accessed June 17, 2007. &quot;Sandy Hook boasts the biggest nude beach along the Atlantic. The clothing-optional part is called Gunnison Beach and there's even a picture showing people of varying shapes and sizes frolicking in their birthday suits.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The northern end of the island is home to the [[Sandy Hook Lighthouse]].

====[[Asbury Park, New Jersey|Asbury Park]]====
Asbury Park is known for its rich musical history, perhaps most notably for its association with [[Bruce Springsteen]] and [[The Stone Pony]]. The resort town fell on hard times throughout much of the late 20th century, but has rebounded in the 2000s. With attractions such as the [[The Empress Hotel (New Jersey)|Empress Hotel]], Asbury Park has emerged as a popular [[LGBT]] destination. Asbury Park is also home to the [[Garden State Film Festival]].

====[[Ocean Grove, New Jersey|Ocean Grove]]====
Ocean Grove was originally developed as a summer [[camp meeting]] site,&lt;ref name=arcadia&gt;{{cite book |author=Wayne T. Bell |title=Images of America: Ocean Grove |year=2000 |publisher=Arcadia Publishing |location=Charleston, S.C. |isbn=0-7385-0425-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is referred to as  &quot;God's Square Mile at the Jersey Shore&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''2009 Summer Events'', Ocean Grove Camp Meeting Association, p. 1.&lt;/ref&gt; Listed on the [[National Register of Historic Places]], Ocean Grove is noted for its abundant examples of [[Victorian architecture]]. Ocean Grove is home to The Great Auditorium, a 5,500-seat indoor arena constructed in 1894 on bridge-like iron trusses laid on stone foundations. The Auditorium contains a [[pipe organ]] that is one of the 25 largest in the world.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theatreorgans.com/laird/top.pipe.organs.html Largest organs in the world]&lt;/ref&gt; Surrounding the Auditorium are 114&amp;nbsp;tents, which are occupied from May to September, just as they have been since 1869. These rustic throwbacks adjoin to rear sheds containing a kitchen and bathroom. The tents are stored in the sheds during the winter. They are in such demand that there is a waiting list of some ten years for summer rentals.&lt;ref name=arcadia /&gt;

====[[Belmar, New Jersey|Belmar]]====
Belmar is a popular vacation destination due to its [[natural resource|natural]] and recreational resources. Its boardwalk and town offer shops, restaurants, an active arts scene, sporting events, festivals, and a variety of family-oriented activities. Belmar is among the most popular surf spots on the East Coast. Belmar frequently hosts surfing events and competitions.  Along with surfing, Belmar also has an active skate community and skatepark constructed by [[American Ramp Company]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://belmar.com/tag/american-ramp-company/ NJ, Belmar Online]&lt;/ref&gt; 
[[Image:belmar-panorama.jpg|center||thumb|688px|[[Belmar, New Jersey|Belmar]], [[Monmouth County, New Jersey|Monmouth County]], on the Jersey Shore.]]

===Ocean County===
====[[Point Pleasant Beach, New Jersey|Point Pleasant Beach]]====
The Point Pleasant Beach [[boardwalk]] is approximately one mile long, spanning the coastline from the [[Manasquan Inlet]] at the north to New Jersey Avenue in the south. The central third of the boardwalk contains amusement rides, arcades, pizza joints, ice cream parlors, games-of-chance and miniature golf courses. Point Pleasant Beach is also the northern terminus of the [[East Coast of the United States|East Coast's]] [[Intracoastal Waterway]]. Point Pleasant is also home to Jenkinson's Aquarium as well as an annual Seafood festival every September.&lt;ref name=OfficialHistory&gt;[http://www.pointpleasantbeach.org/aboutpointpleasant.shtml History], Borough of Point Pleasant Beach. Accessed April 29, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

====[[Seaside Heights, New Jersey|Seaside Heights]]====
[[File:Seaside Heights boardwalk looking toward Funtown Pier.JPG|thumb|right|[[Seaside Heights, New Jersey|Seaside Heights]] boardwalk looking towards the Funtown Pier]]
Seaside Heights attracts a large crowd due to its amusement-oriented boardwalk and numerous clubs and bars.&lt;ref name=NYT1999&gt;Mansnerus, Laura. [http://www.nytimes.com/1999/06/06/nyregion/so-just-who-goes-where-when-going-to-the-shore.html &quot;So, Just Who Goes Where When Going to the Shore?&quot;], ''[[The New York Times]]'', June 6, 1999. Accessed July 13, 2011. &quot;Seaside Heights, with a summer population of about 65,000, is packed, one of the few shore towns with larger apartment buildings. The boardwalk has almost a mile of skeeball and video arcades and enough fast food and bars to amuse the young into the early-morning hours. 'I don't think they let you into Seaside Heights if you're over 21,' said Kristin Farfalla, a sales representative at Midway Beach Real Estate in South Seaside Park.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; [[Casino Pier]] and Funtown Pier are [[amusement park]]s, each situated on a [[pier]] extending approximately 300 feet (100 m) into the [[Atlantic Ocean]]. Each of the two piers is part of a boardwalk that stretches for {{convert|2|miles}}, which offers many family-friendly attractions from arcades, to games of chance, to beaches, to the wide variety of foods and desserts, all within walking distance. Breakwater Beach (formerly known as Water Works) is a [[water park]] situated across the street from Casino Pier. Seaside Heights hosted the AVP volleyball tournament for two years during the Summers of 2006 and 2007, with volleyball greats such as [[Karch Kiraly]] competing for the $200,000 purse.&lt;ref&gt;Ryan, Joe. [http://blog.nj.com/ledgerupdates/2007/07/down_the_shore.html &quot;Setting and spiking at Seaside Heights&quot;], ''[[The Star-Ledger]]'', July 7, 2007. Accessed July 13, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; South of Seaside Heights is the [[Island Beach State Park]], which is operated and maintained by the [[New Jersey Division of Parks and Forestry]].

====[[Long Beach Island, New Jersey|Long Beach Island]]====
Long Beach Island is a [[barrier island]] and collection of several shore communities. Long Beach Island is approximately {{convert|18|mi}} in length, which includes three miles (5&amp;nbsp;km) of [[nature reserve]] located on the southern tip.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oceancountyhistory.org/OCHistory/long_beach_island.htm Long beach island], Ocean County Historical Society. Accessed July 20, 2007.  &quot;Long Beach Island lies off the New Jersey Coast about {{convert|65|mi|km}} south of Manhattan and {{convert|57|mi|km}} east and slightly south of Philadelphia. The island follows the coast for a distance of {{convert|18|mi|km}} in a roughly northeast-to-southwest direction. Barnegat Bay, which separates it from the mainland, is approximately two to six miles (10 km) wide. The width of the island ranges from more than a mile to less than {{convert|200|yd|m}}.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Bisecting the middle of the island is the sole access point for road vehicles, via [[New Jersey Route 72|State Route 72]], which consists of the [[Manahawkin Bay Bridge|Dorland J. Henderson Memorial Bridge]] (locally known as &quot;The [[Causeway]]&quot;). The bridge is known for its &quot;String of Pearls&quot;, a row of lights mounted on the railings lining the length of the bridge. This beach is popular spot for people who want to relax in the sun all day and don't particularly like the boardwalk. Most places are in walking distance and there is a downtown area with stores and restaurants. 

[[Image:Beach Haven NJ from Engleside Ave toward the bay 2007-07-29.jpg|thumb|left|A street in [[Beach Haven, New Jersey|Beach Haven]] on Long Beach Island]]
The presence of the bisecting roadway, located in Ship Bottom, results in the division of the island into a northern portion and a southern portion. In Beach Haven is The Chicken or The Egg restaurant, that has been serving up delicious meals and debate since 1991. From the bridge northward, the island includes the communities of [[Surf City, New Jersey|Surf City]], North Beach (a section of Long Beach Township), [[Harvey Cedars, New Jersey|Harvey Cedars]], [[Loveladies, New Jersey|Loveladies]] (the northernmost section of Long Beach Township), [[High Bar Harbor, New Jersey|High Bar Harbor]], and [[Barnegat Light, New Jersey|Barnegat Light]].  From the bridge southward, the island includes the communities of [[Long Beach Township, New Jersey|Long Beach Township]] (including the census-designated place of [[North Beach Haven, New Jersey|North Beach Haven]]) and [[Beach Haven, New Jersey|Beach Haven]], with the Holgate section of Long Beach Township at the southernmost tip of the island. The island is home to attractions such as [[Barnegat Lighthouse|Barnegat Light]], the Fantasy Island amusement park, as well as the original [[Ron Jon Surf Shop]] location.

===Atlantic County===
====[[Atlantic City, New Jersey|Atlantic City]]====
[[Image:Atlantic City, aerial view.jpg|right|thumb|[[Atlantic City, New Jersey|Atlantic City]], aerial view.]]
Atlantic City is a nationally renowned resort city for gambling, shopping and fine dining. The city also served as the inspiration for the board game [[Monopoly (game)|Monopoly]]. Atlantic City is considered the &quot;Gambling Capital of the East Coast&quot; and is second to [[Las Vegas Valley|Las Vegas]] in number of casinos, yearly gaming revenue, and number of rooms. The [[List of tallest buildings in Atlantic City|Atlantic City Skyline]] has been transformed by construction of new casino hotels and condominia. Atlantic City is also home to numerous shopping malls and districts.

The Atlantic City Boardwalk was one of the first boardwalks of its type in the United States, having opened on June 26, 1870.&lt;ref&gt;[http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/today/jun26.html Today in History: June 26 at the Library of Congress]&lt;/ref&gt; The Boardwalk starts at Absecon Inlet and runs along the beach for four miles (six kilometers) to the city limit.  An additional one and one half miles (two kilometers) of the Boardwalk extend into [[Ventnor City, New Jersey|Ventnor City]]. Casino/hotels front the boardwalk, as well as retail stores, restaurants, and amusements. Notable attractions include the [[Boardwalk Hall]], [[House of Blues]], the [[Steel Pier]], and the [[Ripley's Believe It or Not!]] museum. 
Formerly home of the [[Miss America]] pageant, Atlantic City has been featured in numerous films and television series, most notably the setting of the HBO series ''[[Boardwalk Empire]]''.

===Cape May County===
====[[Ocean City, New Jersey|Ocean City]]====
[[File:Ocean City NJ boardwalk looking south from 12th Street.JPG|thumb|left|[[Ocean City, New Jersey|Ocean City]] boardwalk]]
Ocean City is home to a boardwalk with several shops and amusement areas. Known as a family-oriented seaside resort, Ocean City has prohibited the sale of alcoholic beverages within its limits since its founding in 1879. Ocean City has miles of guarded beaches, a 2.5-mile [[boardwalk]], and a downtown shopping and dining district. The [[Travel Channel]] rated Ocean City as the ''Best Family Beach of 2005''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://travel.discovery.com/convergence/beachweek/guide/beaches/oceancity.html Best Family Beach of 2005], [[Travel Channel]], March 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; It was ranked the third best beach in New Jersey in the 2008 Top 10 Beaches Contest sponsored by the New Jersey Marine Sciences Consortium.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Urgo |first=Jacqueline L. |title=Triumph for South Jersey |publisher=[[The Philadelphia Inquirer]] |date=May 23, 2008 |url=http://www.philly.com/philly/hp/entertainment/19204259.html |accessdate=2008-05-30 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080605225601/http://www.philly.com/philly/hp/entertainment/19204259.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2008-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In the 2009 Top 10 Beaches Contest, Ocean City ranked first.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nj.com/news/index.ssf/2009/05/top_beach_goes_here.html Ocean City wins No. 1 beach in New Jersey for '09], ''[[The Star-Ledger]]'', May 19, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

====[[The Wildwoods]]====
[[Image:Wildwoods boardwalk sign.JPG|thumb|right|Wildwoods sign on boardwalk in [[Wildwood, New Jersey|Wildwood]]]]
The Wildwoods is used as a collective term for the four communities that have &quot;Wildwood&quot; as part of the municipality name — the Borough of [[Wildwood Crest, New Jersey|Wildwood Crest]], City of Wildwood, Borough of [[West Wildwood, New Jersey|West Wildwood]] and the City of [[North Wildwood, New Jersey|North Wildwood]] — together with [[Diamond Beach, New Jersey|Diamond Beach]], a portion of [[Lower Township, New Jersey|Lower Township]] situated on the island. Its most notable features are its beach and {{convert|1.8|mi|km}} [[boardwalk]], home to the [[Morey's Piers]] amusement complex and Raging Waters and Ocean Oasis [[waterparks]] owned by Morey's Piers. The boardwalk features a trolley called the &quot;[[Tramcar (Wildwood)|Tramcar]]&quot;, which runs from end to end.

[[File:Chateau Bleu.JPG|thumb|left|The [[Chateau Bleu Motel]], a typical [[doo-wop]]-style motel]]
The Wildwoods is home to over 200 motels, built during the [[Googie architecture|Doo-Wop]] era of the 1950s and 1960s,&lt;ref name=&quot;Washington Post&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=The '50s and '60s Thrive In Retro Doo-Wop Motels |curly=y |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/06/22/AR2007062200682.html |work=[[Washington Post]] |date=24 June 2007 |accessdate=2008-12-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt; in an area recognized by the state of New Jersey, known as the [[Wildwoods Shore Resort Historic District]]'&lt;ref name=&quot;league&quot;&gt;[http://www.doowopusa.org/district/index.html Doo Wop Preservation League Web site]&lt;/ref&gt; The term doo-wop was coined by [[Cape May]]'s Mid-Atlantic Center For The Arts in the early 1990s to describe the unique, space-age architectural style, which is also referred to as the [[Googie]] or populuxe style.&lt;ref name=&quot;Crest History Society&quot;&gt;[http://www.cresthistory.org/doowop.php Wildwood Crest Historical Society Web site]&lt;/ref&gt; The motels are unique in appearance, with Vegas-like neon signs and [[fantastic architecture]].&lt;ref&gt;Fancher, Emily. [http://www.jrn.columbia.edu/studentwork/cns/2002-06-10/34.asp &quot;Doo Wop&quot; architecture lures tourists back to seaside town], Columbia News Service, June 10, 2002. Accessed June 17, 2007. &quot;Just about everything in Wildwood, N.J. has been touched by 'Doo Wop'. The term describes the distinctively kitschy flair of the town's 200 motels, which were built in the 1950s and '60s. Reflecting the popular cultural themes of the era, the motels have Hawaiian and Polynesian designs, Space Age accents or rock 'n' roll details.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

====[[Cape May, New Jersey|Cape May]]====
[[Image:Cape may.jpg|thumb|[[Sunset]] at [[Cape May]].]]
Cape May is at the southern tip of [[Cape May Peninsula]] where the [[Delaware Bay]] meets the [[Atlantic Ocean]] and is one of the country's oldest vacation resort destinations.&lt;ref&gt;Johnson, Charles P. [http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=lyEbAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=RksEAAAAIBAJ&amp;dq=southernmost%20cape-may-city&amp;pg=2248%2C799191 &quot;Many Drive To Resorts On Atlantic: Coast Places Draw Drivers From Pittsburgh District&quot;], ''[[The Pittsburgh Press]]'', June 22, 1930, p. 3 of the Automobile section. Accessed July 4, 2011. &quot;The southern part of New Jersey largely in Cape May County contains other popular resorts. Cape May City, the southernmost part of New Jersey, is said to be the oldest vacation resort in the United States.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; With a rich history, award-winning beaches, designation as a top [[birding]] location, and many Victorian structures, Cape May is a seaside resort drawing visitors from around the world. The [[Cape May – Lewes Ferry]] connects the town to [[Lewes, Delaware]]. One of Cape May's &quot;hot spots&quot; is the zoo where children can pet and feed the animals and the whole family can have a good time.

==Beaches==
The following is a list of all the beaches located within the state of New Jersey, listed north to south

{|
|- valign=top
|
'''[[Monmouth County, New Jersey|Monmouth County]]'''
*[[Sandy Hook]]
*[[Highlands, New Jersey|Highlands]]
*[[Sea Bright, New Jersey|Sea Bright]]
*[[Monmouth Beach, New Jersey|Monmouth Beach]]
*[[Long Branch, New Jersey|Long Branch]]
*[[Deal, New Jersey|Deal]]
*[[Allenhurst, New Jersey|Allenhurst]]
*[[Loch Arbour, New Jersey|Loch Arbour]]
*[[Asbury Park, New Jersey|Asbury Park]]
*[[Ocean Grove, New Jersey|Ocean Grove]]
*[[Bradley Beach, New Jersey|Bradley Beach]]
*[[Avon-by-the-Sea, New Jersey|Avon-by-the-Sea]]
*[[Belmar, New Jersey|Belmar]]
*[[Spring Lake, New Jersey|Spring Lake]]
*[[Sea Girt, New Jersey|Sea Girt]]
*[[Manasquan, New Jersey|Manasquan]]
|
|
'''[[Ocean County, New Jersey|Ocean County]]
*[[Point Pleasant Beach, New Jersey|Point Pleasant Beach]]
*[[Bay Head, New Jersey|Bay Head]]
*[[Mantoloking, New Jersey|Mantoloking]]
*[[Brick, New Jersey|Brick]]
*[[Dover Beaches North, New Jersey|Dover Beaches North]]
*[[Lavallette, New Jersey|Lavallette]]
*[[Dover Beaches South, New Jersey|Dover Beaches South]]
*[[Seaside Heights, New Jersey|Seaside Heights]]
*[[Seaside Park, New Jersey|Seaside Park]]
*[[Island Beach State Park]]
*[[Barnegat Light, New Jersey|Barnegat Light]]
*[[Loveladies, New Jersey|Loveladies]]
*[[Harvey Cedars, New Jersey|Harvey Cedars]]
*[[North Beach, New Jersey|North Beach]]
*[[Surf City, New Jersey|Surf City]]
*[[Ship Bottom, New Jersey|Ship Bottom]]
*[[North Beach Haven, New Jersey|North Beach Haven]]
*[[Beach Haven, New Jersey|Beach Haven]]
|
|
'''[[Atlantic County, New Jersey|Atlantic County]]'''
*[[Brigantine, New Jersey|Brigantine]]
*[[Atlantic City, New Jersey|Atlantic City]]
*[[Ventnor City, New Jersey|Ventnor City]]
*[[Margate City, New Jersey|Margate City]]
*[[Longport, New Jersey|Longport]]
|
|
'''[[Cape May County, New Jersey|Cape May County]]'''
*[[Ocean City, New Jersey|Ocean City]]
*[[Strathmere, New Jersey|Strathmere]]
*[[Sea Isle City, New Jersey|Sea Isle City]]
*[[Avalon, New Jersey|Avalon]]
*[[Stone Harbor, New Jersey|Stone Harbor]]
*[[North Wildwood, New Jersey|North Wildwood]]
*[[Wildwood, New Jersey|Wildwood]]
*[[Wildwood Crest, New Jersey|Wildwood Crest]]
*[[Diamond Beach, New Jersey|Diamond Beach]]
*[[Cape May, New Jersey|Cape May]]
|}

==Sound and culture==
The Jersey Shore is home to numerous rock and roll clubs, most famously in [[Asbury Park, New Jersey|Asbury Park]], where [[Bruce Springsteen]] honed his skills at now defunct clubs like The Upstage and the Student Prince. He still makes periodic live appearances at [[The Stone Pony]] bar or at [[Asbury Park Convention Hall|Convention Hall]] as either a solo act, with the [[E Street Band]], or with other artists. Furthermore, [[Bill Haley and the Comets]] performed &quot;[[Rock Around the Clock]]&quot; for the first time live at the Hoff Brau in Wildwood.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

A style of music known as the [[Jersey Shore sound]] evolved from this scene. The [[Springsteen]] song &quot;[[4th of July, Asbury Park (Sandy)]]&quot; is one of several Springsteen songs that contains references to the Jersey shore scene of the early 1970s.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

MTV also used Seaside Heights as the location of their ''Summer Beach House'' in 1998 and again in 2002, and for two episodes of ''[[True Life]]'' about adults in there 20's and 30's living &quot;down the shore&quot; for the summer.{{cn|date=October 2012}}  In 1999, the music video &quot;Summer Girls&quot; by LFO was filmed in Seaside Heights.{{cn|date=October 2012}}

The Jersey Shore area rose to international fame in 2009 after [[MTV]] started airing the reality series ''[[Jersey Shore (TV series)|Jersey Shore]]''. The popular show, filmed mostly in Seaside Heights, debuted amid large amounts of controversy regarding the use of the words &quot;[[Guido (slang)|Guido]]/Guidette&quot;, portrayals of [[Italian-American]] stereotypes, and scrutiny from locals because the cast members, with the exception of three, are not New Jersey residents.&lt;ref name=ppc&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.pointpleasantchamber.com/index.php/local-ocean-and-monmouth-county-news/76-shore-residents-express-anger-with-mtv-qjersey-shoreq-shows-premise|title=Shore Residents Express Anger with MTV|publisher = PointPleasantChamber.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=app1&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.app.com/article/20091129/NEWS/91129051/1004/NEWS01/Shore+residents+express+anger+with+MTV+s++Jersey+Shore++premise+|title = Shore residents express anger with MTV's ''Jersey Shore'' premise|publisher = app.com|date = November 29, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=abcnews&gt;{{cite web|url = http://abcnews.go.com/Entertainment/mtv-show-jersey-shore-angers-italian-american-groups/story?id=9292815|title = MTV's ''Jersey Shore'' Garners Critics Over Use of Term 'Guido'|publisher = abcnews.com|date = December 11, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 2011 film ''[[New Year's Eve (film)|New Year's Eve]]'' was filmed in Seaside Heights.{{cn|date=October 2012}}

Some episodes of ''[[The Real Housewives of New Jersey]]'', season four, took place at the Jersey Shore. As discussed on the show, the families of cast members [[Teresa Giudice]] and [[Melissa Gorga]] have houses in [[Toms River, New Jersey|Toms River]], and [[Kathy Wakile]]'s family also rented a house at the shore.

==Retail businesses==
[[Image:Wawa in Wildwood, New Jersey.jpg|thumb|right|A retro-styled [[Wawa Food Market]] in [[Wildwood, New Jersey]].]]
Unlike areas in the interior of the state, which has many [[big box stores]], small businesses make a significant portion of the economy of barrier island Jersey Shore towns. This is because small businesses can more easily adapt to the seasonal nature of business in shore towns. Stores that are located at the shore are all unique ranging from psychics and accessories at Ocean City to home-made chocolates in Long Beach Island. In addition many shore towns deliberately stymie the entry of big box towns because they want to reduce traffic. In addition, many tourists visit shore towns in order to be in an environment without big box stores. In some shore towns [[Wawa Inc.]] designs its stores to match the aesthetic and changes its operating procedures to adapt to the shore culture. It is the only retailer on the island of [[Cape May]] to have a significant number of stores.&lt;ref name=&quot;Warner1&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Warner|first=Susan|title=Mom and Pop Hold Sway At the Shore|work=[[The New York Times]]|date=August 14, 2005|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2005/08/14/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/14njCHAINS.html?pagewanted=all|accessdate=December 24, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{-}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.visitnjshore.com New Jersey Shore Events, History Hotels, Dining and Articles]
* [http://www.shorefun.com/ Jersey Shore’s activities and events]
* [http://www.app.com/special/boardwalks/intro.html Jersey Shore Boardwalks, a multimedia site with information and history on the Jersey Shore]
* [http://www.ShoreRegion.com Shore Region Tourism Council (covering Ocean and Monmouth Counties)]
* [http://www.shorenewstoday.com 17 New Jersey Shore Newspapers serving Atlantic and Cape May Counties]
* [http://www.butkus.org/postcards/jersey_shore.htm Historical Postcards - Jersey Shore]

{{New Jersey}}

{{Coord|40.048|-74.052|display=title}}

[[Category:Culture of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Seaside resorts in the United States]]
[[Category:Geography of Atlantic County, New Jersey]]
[[Category:Geography of Cape May County, New Jersey]]
[[Category:Geography of Monmouth County, New Jersey]]
[[Category:Geography of Ocean County, New Jersey]]
[[Category:Tourism in New Jersey]]
[[Category:Tourism regions of New Jersey]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Atlantic County, New Jersey]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Cape May County, New Jersey]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Monmouth County, New Jersey]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Ocean County, New Jersey]]

[[da:Jersey Shore]]
[[simple:Jersey Shore]]
[[sv:Jersey Shore]]</text>
      <sha1>qbl4k6r3ytiz5483pv9npemlhput0d4</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
