<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Junichiro Koizumi</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>49544</id>
    <revision>
      <id>516929468</id>
      <parentid>516926775</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-10T01:52:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Dating maintenance tags: {{Unreferenced section}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="32280">{{Japanese name|Koizumi}}
{{Infobox Officeholder
|name             = Junichiro Koizumi
|native_name = 小泉 純一郎
|image            = Koizumi 2010 cropped.png
|office           = [[Prime Minister of Japan]]
|monarch          = [[Akihito]]
|term_start       = 26 April 2001
|term_end         = 26 September 2006
|predecessor      = [[Yoshirō Mori]]
|successor        = [[Shinzō Abe]]
|office2          = [[Minister for Foreign Affairs (Japan)|Minister for Foreign Affairs]]
|term_start2      = 26 January 2002
|term_end2        = 16 February 2002
|predecessor2     = [[Makiko Tanaka]]
|successor2       = [[Yoriko Kawaguchi]]
|office3          = [[Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare (Japan)|Minister of Health and Welfare]]
|term_start3      = 7 November 1996
|term_end3        = 29 July 1998
|primeminister3   = [[Ryutaro Hashimoto]]
|predecessor3     = [[Naoto Kan]]
|successor3       = [[Sohei Miyashita]]
|term_start4      = 27 December 1988
|term_end4        = 10 August 1989
|primeminister4   = [[Noboru Takeshita]]&lt;br&gt;[[Sōsuke Uno]]
|predecessor4     = [[Takao Fujimoto]]
|successor4       = [[Saburo Toida]]
|office5          = [[Ministry of Internal Affairs and Communications|Minister of Post and Telecommunications]]
|term_start5      = 12 December 1992
|term_end5        = 20 July 1993
|primeminister5   = [[Kiichi Miyazawa]]
|predecessor5     = [[Hideo Watanabe]]
|successor5       = [[Kiichi Miyazawa]]
|constituency_MP6 = [[Kanagawa 11th district]]
|parliament6      = Japanese
|term_start6      = 1996
|term_end6        = 2009
|predecessor6     = New constituency
|successor6       = [[Shinjirō Koizumi]]
|majority6        = 197,037 (73.16%)
|birth_date       = {{Birth date and age|1942|1|8|df=y}}
|birth_place      = [[Yokosuka, Kanagawa]], [[Japan]]
|death_date       = 
|death_place      = 
|spouse           = Kayoko Miyamoto &lt;small&gt;(1978–1982)&lt;/small&gt;
|children         = [[Kotaro Koizumi|Kōtarō Koizumi]]&lt;br&gt;[[Shinjirō Koizumi]]&lt;br&gt;Yoshinaga Miyamoto
|party            = [[Liberal Democratic Party (Japan)|Liberal Democratic Party]]
|alma_mater       = [[Keio University]]&lt;br&gt;[[University College London]]
}}
{{nihongo|'''Junichiro Koizumi'''|小泉 純一郎|Koizumi Jun'ichirō|extra=born 8 January 1942}} is a Japanese politician who served as [[Prime Minister of Japan]] from 2001 to 2006. He retired from politics when his term in parliament ended in 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;quit&quot; /&gt;

Widely seen as a [[wikt:maverick|maverick]] leader of the [[Liberal Democratic Party (Japan)|Liberal Democratic Party (LDP)]], he became known as an economic reformer, focusing on Japan's government debt and the privatization of its [[Japan Post|postal service]]. In 2005, Koizumi led the LDP to win one of the largest parliamentary majorities in modern [[Japanese history]].

Koizumi also attracted international attention through his deployment of the [[Japan Self-Defense Forces]] to [[Iraq]]. His visits to [[Yasukuni Shrine]] led to diplomatic tensions with neighboring [[People's Republic of China|China]] and [[South Korea]].

Since 1972, Koizumi is the only Prime Minister to have served more than five years in office. None of his successors have been able to keep the office for more than fifteen months.

==Early life==
Koizumi is a third-generation politician. His father, Junya Koizumi, was director general of the Japan Defense Agency and a member of the [[Diet of Japan|Diet]]. His grandfather, [[Koizumi Matajirō]], was Minister of Posts and Telecommunications under Prime Ministers Hamaguchi and Wakatsuki and an early advocate of postal privatization. See [[Koizumi family]].

Born in [[Yokosuka]], [[Kanagawa prefecture]] on 8 January 1942, Koizumi was educated at [[Kanagawa Prefectural Yokosuka High School|Yokosuka High School]] and [[Keio University]], where he studied economics.  He attended [[University College London]] before returning to Japan in August 1969 upon the death of his father. 

He stood for election to the lower house in December; however, he did not earn enough votes to win election as a Liberal Democratic Party (LDP) representative. In 1970, he was hired as a secretary to [[Takeo Fukuda]], who was Minister of Finance at the time and was elected as Prime Minister in 1976.

In the general elections of December 1972, Koizumi was elected as a member of the Lower House for the [[Kanagawa 11th district]]. He joined Fukuda's faction within the LDP. Since then, he has been re-elected ten times.

==Member of House of Representatives==
Koizumi gained his first senior post in 1979 as Parliamentary Vice Minister of Finance, and his first ministerial post in 1988 as Minister of Health and Welfare under Prime Minister [[Noboru Takeshita]].  He held cabinet posts again in 1992 (Minister of Posts and Telecommunications in the [[Kiichi Miyazawa|Miyazawa]] cabinet) and 1996–1998 (Minister of Health and Welfare in the [[Sōsuke Uno|Uno]] and [[Ryutaro Hashimoto|Hashimoto]] cabinets).

In 1994, with the LDP in opposition, Koizumi became part of a new LDP faction, [[Shinseiki]], made up of younger and more motivated parliamentarians led by [[Taku Yamasaki]], [[Koichi Kato (LDP)|Koichi Kato]] and Koizumi, a group popularly dubbed &quot;YKK&quot; (after the [[YKK Group]] well known for manufacturing [[zipper]]s). He competed for the presidency of the LDP in September 1995 and July 1998, but he gained little support losing decisively to [[Ryutaro Hashimoto]] and then [[Keizō Obuchi]], both of whom had broader bases of support within the party. However, after Yamasaki and Kato were humiliated in a disastrous attempt to force a [[Motion of no confidence|vote of no confidence]] against Prime Minister [[Yoshirō Mori]] in 2000, Koizumi became the last remaining credible member of the YKK trio, which gave him leverage over the reform-minded wing of the party.

On 24 April 2001, Koizumi was elected president of the LDP. He was initially considered an outside candidate against Hashimoto, who was running for his second term as Prime Minister. However, in the first poll of prefectural party organizations, Koizumi won 87 to 11 percent; in the second vote of Diet members, Koizumi won 51 to 40 percent. He defeated Hashimoto by a final tally of 298 to 155 votes.&lt;ref name=&quot;anderson&quot;&gt;Anderson, Gregory E., &quot;[http://www.asianperspective.org/articles/v28n1-g.pdf Lionheart or Paper Tiger? A First-term Koizumi Retrospective],&quot; ''Asian Perspective'' 28:149–182, March 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; He was made Prime Minister of Japan on 26 April, and his coalition secured 78 of 121 seats in the Upper House elections in July.

==Prime minister==
===Domestic policy===
{{Unreferenced section|date=October 2012}}
Within Japan, Koizumi pushed for new ways to revitalise the moribund economy, aiming to act against bad debts with commercial banks, privatize the postal savings system, and reorganize the factional structure of the LDP. He spoke of the need for a period of painful restructuring in order to improve the future.

In the fall of 2002, Koizumi appointed Keio University economist and frequent television commentator [[Heizō Takenaka]] as Minister of State for Financial Services and head of the [[Financial Services Agency|Financial Services Agency (FSA)]] to fix the country's banking crisis. Bad debts of banks were dramatically cut with the NPL ratio of major banks approaching half the level of 2001. The Japanese economy has been through a slow but steady recovery, and the stock market has dramatically rebounded. The [[gross domestic product|GDP]] growth for 2004 was one of the highest among [[G7]] nations, according to the [[International Monetary Fund]] and [[Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development]].{{Citation needed|date=September 2007}} Takenaka was appointed as a Postal Reform Minister in 2004 for the privatization of [[Japan Post]], operator of the country's Postal Savings system.

Koizumi moved the LDP away from its traditional rural agrarian base toward a more urban, [[neoliberal]] core, as Japan's population grew in major cities and declined in less populated areas, although under current purely geographical districting, rural votes in Japan are still many times more powerful than urban ones. In addition to the privatization of Japan Post (which many rural residents fear will reduce their access to basic services such as banking), Koizumi also slowed down the LDP's heavy subsidies for infrastructure and industrial development in rural areas. These tensions made Koizumi a controversial but popular figure within his own party and among the Japanese electorate.

===Foreign policy===
[[File:koizumi with bush.jpg|thumb|Japanese Prime Minister Koizumi and [[President of the United States|U.S. President]] [[George W. Bush]] meet at the White House on 25 September 2001]]

Although Koizumi's foreign policy was focused on closer relations with the United States and UN-centered diplomacy, which were adopted by all of his predecessors, he went further to pursue supporting the US policies in the [[War on Terrorism]]. He decided to deploy the [[Japan Self-Defense Forces]] to [[Iraq]], which was the first military mission in active foreign war zones since the end of the [[World War II]]. Many Japanese commentators indicated that the favorable US-Japan relation was based on the Koizumi's personal friendship with the US President [[George W. Bush]]. In the [[North Korean abductions of Japanese|North Korean abductions]] and nuclear development issues, he took more assertive attitudes than his predecessors.&lt;ref&gt;http://www8.cao.go.jp/survey/tokubetu/h18/h18-jieitai.pdf '「自衛隊のイラク人道復興支援活動に関する特別世論調査」の概要', Cabinet Office of Japan&lt;/ref&gt;

====Self-Defense Forces policy====
Although Koizumi did not initially campaign on the issue of defense reform,&lt;ref name=&quot;anderson&quot; /&gt; he approved the expansion of the [[Japan Self-Defense Forces]] (JSDF) and in October 2001 they were given greater scope to operate outside of the country. Some of these troops were [[Japanese Iraq Reconstruction and Support Group|dispatched to Iraq]]. Koizumi's government also introduced a bill to upgrade the [[Japan Defense Agency]] to ministry status; finally, the Defense Agency became the Japanese [[Ministry of Defense (Japan)|Ministry of Defense]] on 9 January 2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;june06&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://search.japantimes.co.jp/cgi-bin/nn20060617a7.html Diet closes for summer, puts lid on Koizumi legacy],&quot; ''Japan Times'' (registration required), 17 June 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:21apec5.jpg|thumbnail|right| Koizumi meeting with Chinese President [[Hu Jintao]] in 2004]] --&gt;

====Visits to Yasukuni Shrine====
Koizumi has often been noted for his controversial visits to the [[Yasukuni Shrine]], starting on 13 August 2001. He visited the shrine six times as prime minister. Because the shrine honors many convicted [[Japanese war criminals]], including 14 executed Class A [[war criminals]], these visits drew strong condemnation and protests from both Japan's neighbours, mainly [[People's Republic of China|China]] and [[South Korea]], and many Japanese citizens.  China and South Korea's people hold bitter memories of Japanese invasion and occupation during the first half of the 20th century.  China and South Korea refused to have their representatives meet Koizumi in Japan and their countries.  There were no mutual visits between Chinese and Japanese leaders from October 2001, and between South Korean and Japanese leaders from June 2005. The standstill ended when the next prime minister Abe visited China and South Korea in October 2006.

In China, the visits led to massive anti-Japanese riots. The president, ruling and opposition parties, and much of the media of South Korea openly condemned Koizumi's pilgrimages.&lt;ref&gt;
&quot;[http://news.naver.com/news/read.php?mode=LSD&amp;office_id=044&amp;article_id=0000023828&amp;section_id=108&amp;menu_id=108 Lawmakers visit Japanese Embassy to protest Koizumi's planned Seoul trip],&quot; ''The Korea Herald'', 12 October 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;  Many Koreans applauded the president's speeches criticizing Japan, despite the [[Roh Moo-hyun|South Korean President's]] low popularity.  When  asked about the reaction, Koizumi said the speeches were &quot;for the domestic (audience)&quot;. 

Although Koizumi signed the shrine's visitor book as &quot;Junichiro Koizumi, the Prime Minister of Japan&quot;, he claimed that his visits were as a private citizen and not an endorsement of any political stance.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.japantimes.co.jp/cgi-bin/getarticle.pl5?nn20060126a1.htm Koizumi not backing down on Yasukuni],&quot; ''The Japan Times'' (registration required), 26 January 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;  China and Korea found the claims weak as excuses.  Several journals and news reports in Japan, such as one published by Kyodo News Agency on 15 August 2006, questioned Koizumi's statement of private purpose, as he recorded his position on the shrine's guestbook as prime minister.  He visited the shrine annually in fulfillment of a campaign pledge.  Koizumi's last visit as prime minister was on 15 August 2006, fulfilling a campaign pledge to visit on the anniversary of Japan's surrender in World War II.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/4789905.stm | work=BBC News | title=Koizumi shrine visit stokes anger | date=15 August 2006 | accessdate=3 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Eleven months after his resignation as prime minister, Koizumi revisited the shrine on 15 August 2007, to mark the 62nd anniversary of Japan's surrender in [[World War II]].  His 2007 visit attracted less attention from the media than his prior visits while he was in office.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.yahoo.com/photo/070815/ids_photos_wl/r1219897673.jpg Yahoo news]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=20601080&amp;sid=aobKKW2KinWU Former Japanese PM Koizumi Visits War Shrine in Tokyo (Update4)]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Statements on World War II====
On 15 August 2005, the sixtieth anniversary of the end of [[World War II]], Koizumi publicly stated that Japan was deeply saddened by the suffering it caused during World War II and vowed Japan would never again take &quot;the path to war&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://edition.cnn.com/2005/WORLD/asiapcf/08/15/pacific.victoryday/ | work=CNN}} {{Dead link|date=August 2010|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, Koizumi was criticized for actions which allegedly ran contrary to this expression of remorse (e.g. the Yasukuni visits), which resulted in worsening relations with [[China]] and [[South Korea]].

===Popularity===
[[File:Junichiro Koizumi.jpg|thumb|Koizumi meets children in [[Sea Island, Georgia]], shortly before the [[30th G8 summit|2004 G8 summit]].]]
Koizumi was at certain points in his tenure an extremely popular leader.  Most people know him very well due to his trademark wavy grey hair. His outspoken nature and colourful past contributed to that; his nicknames included &quot;Lionheart&quot;, due to his hair style and fierce spirit, and &quot;Maverick&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;anderson&quot; /&gt; During his tenure in office, the Japanese public referred to him as ''Jun-chan'' (the suffix &quot;chan&quot; in the Japanese language is used as a term of familiarity, typically between children, &quot;Jun&quot; is a contraction of Junichiro). In June 2001, he enjoyed an approval rating of 85 percent.&lt;ref&gt;[http://archives.cnn.com/2001/BUSINESS/asia/06/11/japan.popularity/index.html Koizumi's popularity hits fresh peak], CNN.com, 12 June 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2002, Koizumi sacked his popular Foreign Minister [[Makiko Tanaka]], replacing her with [[Yoriko Kawaguchi]].  Following an economic slump and a series of LDP scandals that claimed the career of YKK member [[Koichi Kato (LDP)|Koichi Kato]], by April Koizumi's popularity rating had fallen 40 percentage points since his nomination as prime minister.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/1916438.stm Koizumi ally quits politics over scandal],&quot; BBC News, 8 April 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;

Koizumi was re-elected in 2003 and his popularity surged as the economy recovered. His proposal to cut pension benefits as a move to fiscal reform turned out to be highly unpopular. Two visits to [[North Korea]] to solve the issue of abducted Japanese nationals only somewhat raised his popularity, as he could not secure several abductee's returns to Japan.  In the [[Japan upper house election, 2004|House of Councilors elections in 2004]], the LDP performed only marginally better than the opposition [[Democratic Party of Japan]] (DPJ).

In 2005, the House of Councilors rejected the contentious [[Japan Post|postal privatization bills]]. Koizumi previously made it clear that he would dissolve the lower house if the bill failed to pass. The Democratic Party, while expressing support for the privatization, made a tactical vote against the bill. Fifty-one LDP members also either voted against the bills or abstained.

On 8 August 2005, Koizumi, as promised, dissolved the House of Representatives and called for [[snap election]]s.  He expelled rebel LDP members for not supporting the bill.  The LDP's chances for success were initially uncertain; the secretary general of [[New Komeito Party|New Komeito]] (a junior coalition partner with Koizumi's Liberal Democratic Party) said that his party would entertain forming a coalition government with the Democratic Party of Japan if the DPJ took a majority in the House of Representatives.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.japantimes.co.jp/cgi-bin/getarticle.pl5?nn20050728a2.htm New Komeito exec signals willingness to jump LDP ship],&quot; ''The Japan Times'' (registration required), 28 July 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

Koizumi's popularity rose almost twenty points after he dissolved the House and expelled rebel LDP members.  Opinion polls ranked the government's approval ratings between 51 and 59 percent. The electorate saw the election in terms of a vote for or against the reform (privatisation), which the Democratic Party and rebel LDP members were seen as being against.

The [[Japan general election, 2005|September 2005 elections]] were the LDP's largest victory since 1986, giving the party a large majority in the House of Representatives and nullifying opposing voices in the House of Councilors. In the following Diet session, the last to be held under Koizumi's government, the LDP passed 82 of its 91 proposed bills, including postal privatization.&lt;ref name=&quot;june06&quot; /&gt;

''[[Mudazumo Naki Kaikaku]]'' (''The Legend of Koizumi'') features a caricature of Koizumi as the main character.

===Resignation===
Koizumi announced that he would step down from office in 2006, per LDP rules, and would not personally choose a successor as many LDP prime ministers have in the past. On 20 September 2006, [[Shinzo Abe]] was elected to succeed Koizumi as president of the LDP. Abe succeeded Koizumi as prime minister on 26 September 2006.

Koizumi remained in the Diet through the administrations of Abe and [[Yasuo Fukuda]]. He announced his retirement from politics on 25 September 2008, shortly following the election of [[Taro Aso]] as Prime Minister. Koizumi retained his Diet seat until the [[Japanese general election, 2009|next general election]]. His son [[Shinjiro Koizumi|Shinjiro]] was elected into his father's seat representing the [[Kanagawa's 11th district|Kanagawa 11th district]] in 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;quit&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://search.japantimes.co.jp/cgi-bin/nn20080926a1.html Koizumi to exit political stage]&quot;, ''The Japan Times'', 26 September 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Koizumi supported [[Yuriko Koike]] in the [[Liberal Democratic Party (Japan) leadership election, 2008|LDP leadership election]] held earlier in September 2008, but Koike placed a distant third.&lt;ref&gt;Sachiko Sakamaki and Takahiko Hyuga, [http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=20601101&amp;sid=aZ01YlW1zurQ&amp;refer=japan &quot;Koizumi, Former Japan Premier, to Quit Parliament After Aso Win&quot;], Bloomberg.com, 26 September 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal life==
Koizumi married 21-year-old university student Kayoko Miyamoto in 1978. The couple had been formally introduced to each other as potential spouses, a common practice known as ''[[omiai]]''. The wedding ceremony at the Tokyo Prince Hotel was attended by about 2,500 people, including [[Takeo Fukuda]] (then Prime Minister), and featured a [[wedding cake]] shaped like the [[National Diet Building]].&lt;ref name=time&gt;&quot;[http://www.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,174303-1,00.html Japan's Destroyer],&quot; ''TIME'', 10 September 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;

The marriage ended in [[divorce]] in 1982, as Kayoko was reportedly unhappy with her married life for several reasons.&lt;ref name=time /&gt; After this divorce, Koizumi never married again, saying that divorce consumed ten times more energy than marriage.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[Koizumi's ex-wife ready to lend a hand, has 'nothing to lose'],&quot; Kyodo News, 9 May 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;

Koizumi had custody of two of his three sons: [[Kotaro Koizumi|Kōtarō Koizumi]] and [[Shinjirō Koizumi]], who were reared by one of his sisters. Shinjiro is the representative for [[Kanagawa's 11th district]], a position his father has also filled.  The youngest son, Yoshinaga Miyamoto, now a graduate of Keio University, was born following the divorce&lt;ref name=washpost&gt;&quot;[For Japanese, a Typical Tale of Divorce],&quot; ''Washington Post'', 19 May 2001.&lt;/ref&gt; and has never met Koizumi. The third son is known to have attended one of Koizumi's rallies, but was turned away from trying to meet his father.  He was also turned away from attending his paternal grandmother's funeral.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/newspaper/0,,176-1763663,00.html Japanese PM keeps lost son at bay],&quot; '&quot;The Times'', 4 September 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Koizumi in Graceland 2006.jpg|thumb|Koizumi, hosted by U.S. President George W. Bush, at [[Graceland]] in 2006]]
Koizumi is a fan of [[Richard Wagner]], the heavy metal band [[X Japan]] &lt;ref&gt;[http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0XPQ/is_2001_May_21/ai_74937979 LDP unveils new TV commercials, poster featuring Koizumi]&lt;/ref&gt; and has released a CD of his favorite pieces by contemporary Italian composer [[Ennio Morricone]].&lt;ref&gt;''Watashi no daisuki na morrikone myujikku'', ASIN B000ALJ04G. [http://www.amazon.co.jp/exec/obidos/ASIN/B000ALJ04G/ Amazon link]&lt;/ref&gt; 

Koizumi is also a noted fan of [[Elvis Presley]], with whom he shares a birthday (8 January). In 2001 he released a collection of his favorite Elvis songs on CD, with his comments about each song. His brother is Senior Advisor of the Tokyo Elvis Fan Club. Koizumi and his brother helped finance a statue of Elvis in Tokyo's [[Harajuku]] district. On 30 June 2006, Koizumi visited Presley's estate, [[Graceland]], accompanied by U.S. President George W. Bush, and First Lady Laura Bush.  After arriving in [[Memphis, Tennessee|Memphis]] aboard [[Air Force One]], they headed to Graceland. While there, Koizumi briefly sang a few bars of his favourite Elvis tunes, whilst warmly impersonating Presley, and wearing Presley's trademark oversized golden sunglasses.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/5132376.stm?ls Singing Japan PM tours Graceland], BBC News, 30 June 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

Koizumi also appreciates [[Finland|Finnish]] composer [[Jean Sibelius]]. He and Finnish Prime Minister [[Matti Vanhanen]] visited the [[Ainola|Sibelius' home]] on 8 September 2006. There Koizumi showed respect to the late composer with a moment of silence.  He owns reproductions of the manuscripts of all seven symphonies by Sibelius.

In 2009, Koizumi made a [[voice acting]] appearance in an [[Ultraman]] feature film, ''[[Mega Monster Battle: Ultra Galaxy Legend The Movie]]'', playing the voice of [[Ultraman King]]. Koizumi said he took on the role at the urging of his son Shinjiro.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.reuters.com/article/lifestyleMolt/idUSTRE59C0QH20091013 | title=After quitting politics, Japan's Koizumi turns superhero | first=Yoko | last=Kubota | date=13 October 2009 | work=Reuters}}&lt;/ref&gt; His political career is parodied in the [[seinen manga]], ''[[Mudazumo Naki Kaikaku]]'', which re-interprets his life as a [[mahjong]] master.

He has been compared many times to American actor [[Richard Gere]], because of their similar hair style.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.ctv.ca/CTVNews/Entertainment/20050329/gere_koizumi_050329/ | title=Richard Gere, Japan's PM share a dance  | date=29 March 2005 | work=CTV}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2005, he used the latter as a boost for his falling popularity, by staging an &quot;impromptu ballroom dance performance.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/asia-pacific/4390753.stm | title=Koizumi takes a turn with Gere  | date=29 March 2005 | work=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Koizumi cabinets==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;font-size: 90%;&quot;
|-
! !! First&lt;br /&gt;(26 April 2001) !! First, Realigned&lt;br /&gt;(30 September 2002) !! Second&lt;br /&gt;(19 November 2003) !! Second, Realigned&lt;br /&gt;(22 September 2004) !! Third, Realigned&lt;br /&gt;(31 October 2005)
|-
! [[Chief Cabinet Secretary|Secretary]] 
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; | [[Yasuo Fukuda]] &lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt; || [[Hiroyuki Hosoda]] || [[Shinzō Abe]]
|-
! [[Minister of Public Management, Internal Affairs, Posts and Telecommunications|Internal Affairs]] 
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; | [[Toranosuke Katayama]] 
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; | [[Taro Aso]] || [[Heizō Takenaka]] &lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;
|-
! [[Minister of Justice|Justice]] 
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; | [[Mayumi Moriyama]] || [[Daizō Nozawa]] || [[Chieko Nohno]] || [[Seiken Sugiura]]
|-
! [[Minister of Foreign Affairs|Foreign Affairs]]
| [[Makiko Tanaka]] &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; | [[Yoriko Kawaguchi]] || [[Nobutaka Machimura]] || [[Taro Aso]]
|-
! [[Minister of Finance|Finance]] 
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; | [[Masajuro Shiokawa]] 
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; | [[Sadakazu Tanigaki]]
|-
! [[Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology (Japan)|Education]] 
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; | [[Atsuko Toyama]] || [[Takeo Kawamura (politician)|Takeo Kawamura]] || [[Nariaki Nakayama]] || [[Kenji Kosaka]]
|-
! [[Minister of Health, Labour and Welfare (Japan)|Health]] 
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; | [[Chikara Sakaguchi]] || [[Hidehisa Otsuji]] || [[Jirō Kawasaki]]
|-
! [[Minister of Agriculture, Forestry and Fisheries|Agriculture]]
| [[Tsutomu Takebe]] || [[Tadamori Oshima]] &lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; || [[Yoshiyuki Kamei]] || [[Yoshinobu Shimamura]] || [[Shoichi Nakagawa]]
|-
! [[Minister of Economy, Trade and Industry (Japan)|Economy]] 
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; | [[Takeo Hiranuma]] 
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; | [[Shōichi Nakagawa]] || [[Toshihiro Nikai]]
|-
! [[Minister of Land, Infrastructure and Transport|Land]] 
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; | [[Chikage Oogi]] || [[Nobuteru Ishihara]] 
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; | [[Kazuo Kitagawa]]
|-
! [[Minister of the Environment|Environment]]
| [[Hiroshi Oki]] &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; || [[Shunichi Suzuki (politician)|Shunichi Suzuki]] 
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; | [[Yuriko Koike]]
|-
! [[National Public Safety Commission (Japan)|Public Safety]]
| rowspan=2 | [[Jin Murai]] || [[Sadakazu Tanigaki]] || [[Kiyoko Ono]] || rowspan=2 | [[Yoshitaka Murata]] || rowspan=2 | [[Tetsuo Kutsukake]]
|-
! Disaster Prevention
| [[Yoshitada Konoike]] || [[Kiichi Inoue]]
|-
! [[Japan Defense Agency|Defense]]
| [[Gen Nakatani]] 
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; | [[Shigeru Ishiba]] || [[Yoshinori Ohno]] || [[Fukushiro Nukaga]]
|-
! Economic Policy
| [[Heizō Takenaka]] &lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | [[Heizō Takenaka]] || [[Heizō Takenaka]] || rowspan=2 | [[Kaoru Yosano]]
|-
! Financial Affairs
| [[Hakuo Yanagisawa]] || [[Tatsuya Ito]] 
|-
! Admin. and Reg. Reform 
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; | [[Nobuteru Ishihara]] || [[Kazuyoshi Kaneko]] || [[Seiichiro Murakami]] || [[Kōki Chūma]]
|-
! Technology
| [[Koji Omi]] || [[Hiroyuki Hosoda]] || [[Toshimitsu Motegi]] || [[Yasufumi Tanahashi]] || [[Iwao Matsuda]]
|-
! Youth and Gender
| colspan=4 | || [[Kuniko Inoguchi]]
|}

Notes:
#[[Makiko Tanaka]] was fired on 29 January 2002. Koizumi served as interim foreign minister until 1 February, when he appointed then-environment minister [[Yoriko Kawaguchi]] to the post. Koizumi appointed Hiroshi Oki to replace Kawaguchi.
#Oshima resigned on 31 March 2003 due to a farm-subsidy scandal. He was replaced by Kamei, who was kept in the next reshuffle.
#Takenaka has also held the portfolio of Minister of State for Postal Privatization since the first Koizumi cabinet. He is the only person to serve on Koizumi's cabinet through all five reshuffles.
#Fukuda resigned on 7 May 2004 and was replaced by Hosoda.

==See also==
{{Portal box|Japan|Biography}}
*[[List of Prime Ministers of Japan]]
{{-}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Commons|Junichiro Koizumi}}
*[http://www.mofa.go.jp/announce/pm/koizumi/ Speeches and Statements by Junichiro Koizumi]
*[http://www.kantei.go.jp/foreign/koizumiprofile/index_e.html Profile of Prime Minister Koizumi]
*[http://www.yasukuni.or.jp/english/ Yasukuni Shrine official website]

{{s-start}}
{{s-par|jp-lwr}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Seiichi Tagawa]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Eki Sone]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Shōkichi Matsuo]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Hideo Nakajima]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=Representative for [[Kanagawa's 2nd district (1947-1993)|Kanagawa's 2nd district]] (multi-member)|years=1972–1996}}
{{s-non|reason=Constituency abolished}}
|-
{{s-new|constituency}}
{{s-ttl|title=Representative for [[Kanagawa's 11th district]]|years=1996–2009}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Shinjirō Koizumi]]}}
|-
{{s-off}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Yoshirō Mori]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Prime Minister of Japan]]|years=2001–2006}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Shinzō Abe]]}}
|-
{{s-bef|before=[[Makiko Tanaka]]}}
{{s-ttl|title={{nowrap|[[Minister for Foreign Affairs (Japan)|Minister of Foreign Affairs]]}}|years=2002}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Yoriko Kawaguchi]]}}
{{s-end}}

{{Prime Ministers of Japan}}
{{Japanese foreign ministers}}

{{Authority control|PND=133169367|LCCN=nr/95/19656|VIAF=45483372}}
&lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
{{Persondata
|NAME              = Koizumi, Junichiro
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES = 小泉 純一郎 (Japanese)
|SHORT DESCRIPTION = Japanese Prime Minister
|DATE OF BIRTH     = 8 January 1942
|PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Yokosuka]], [[Kanagawa Prefecture|Kanagawa]], [[Japan]]
|DATE OF DEATH     = 
|PLACE OF DEATH    = 
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Koizumi, Junichiro}}
[[Category:1942 births]]
[[Category:Alumni of University College London]]
[[Category:Foreign ministers of Japan]]
[[Category:Ministers of Agriculture, Forestry and Fisheries of Japan]]
[[Category:Japanese Buddhists]]
[[Category:Japanese expatriates in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Keio University alumni]]
[[Category:Koizumi family|Junichiro]]
[[Category:Liberal Democratic Party (Japan) politicians]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Members of the House of Representatives of Japan]]
[[Category:People from Yokosuka, Kanagawa]]
[[Category:Prime Ministers of Japan]]
[[Category:Japanese Shintoists]]

[[ar:جونيتشيرو كويزومي]]
[[bn:জুনিচিরো কোইযুমি]]
[[zh-min-nan:Koizumi Zyun'itirô]]
[[br:Junichiro Koizumi]]
[[ca:Junichiro Koizumi]]
[[cs:Džuničiró Koizumi]]
[[da:Junichiro Koizumi]]
[[de:Jun’ichirō Koizumi]]
[[et:Jun'ichirō Koizumi]]
[[es:Jun'ichirō Koizumi]]
[[eo:Koizumi Ĝuniĉiro]]
[[fr:Jun'ichirō Koizumi]]
[[ga:Junichiro Koizumi]]
[[gl:Junichiro Koizumi]]
[[ko:고이즈미 준이치로]]
[[hi:जूनीचीरो कोईजूमी]]
[[hr:Junichiro Koizumi]]
[[io:Junichiro Koizumi]]
[[id:Junichiro Koizumi]]
[[is:Junichiro Koizumi]]
[[it:Junichiro Koizumi]]
[[he:ג'וניצ'ירו קואיזומי]]
[[ka:ძიუნიტირო კოიძუმი]]
[[la:Junichiro Koizumi]]
[[lt:Junichiro Koizumi]]
[[hu:Koizumi Dzsunicsiró]]
[[mk:Џуничиро Коизуми]]
[[mi:Junichiro Koizumi]]
[[mr:जुनिचिरो कोइझुमी]]
[[ms:Junichiro Koizumi]]
[[mn:Коизүми Жүн-Ичироо]]
[[nl:Junichiro Koizumi]]
[[ja:小泉純一郎]]
[[no:Junichiro Koizumi]]
[[nn:Junichiro Koizumi]]
[[oc:Junichiro Koizumi]]
[[pl:Jun'ichirō Koizumi]]
[[pt:Junichiro Koizumi]]
[[ro:Junichiro Koizumi]]
[[qu:Junichiro Koizumi]]
[[ru:Коидзуми, Дзюнъитиро]]
[[simple:Junichiro Koizumi]]
[[sr:Џуничиро Коизуми]]
[[sh:Junichiro Koizumi]]
[[su:Junichiro Koizumi]]
[[fi:Jun'ichirō Koizumi]]
[[sv:Junichiro Koizumi]]
[[ta:ஜூனிசிரோ கொய்சுமி]]
[[th:จุนอิชิโร โคะอิซุมิ]]
[[tr:Junichirō Koizumi]]
[[uk:Коїдзумі Дзюнітіро]]
[[vi:Koizumi Junichirō]]
[[yo:Junichiro Koizumi]]
[[zh-yue:小泉純一郎]]
[[zh:小泉纯一郎]]</text>
      <sha1>mvj6tskb7hu237iy8rh4um5wb5tmnc2</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
