<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Karl Marx</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>16743</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521196058</id>
      <parentid>519045137</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-03T12:43:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>EmausBot</username>
        <id>11292982</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>r2.7.2+) (Robot: Adding [[nds-nl:Karl Marx]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="122055">{{pp-semi-indef}}{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Redirect|Marx}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2012}}
{{Infobox philosopher
|region = [[Western Philosophy]], [[German philosophy]]
|era = [[19th-century philosophy]]
|color = #B0C4DE
|image = Karl Marx_001.jpg
|caption = Marx in 1875
|birth_name = Karl Heinrich Marx
|birth_date = 5 May 1818
|birth_place = [[Trier]], [[Kingdom of Prussia]]
|death_date = {{Death date and age|df=yes|1883|03|14|1818|05|05}}
|death_place = [[London]], [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|United Kingdom]]
|residence = Germany, United Kingdom 
|nationality = [[Kingdom of Prussia|Prussian]], [[Germans|German]]
|religion = [[Protestantism]]; later, none ([[atheism|atheist]])
|school_tradition = [[Marxism]], [[Communism]], [[Socialism]], [[Materialism]]
|signature =Karl Marx Signature.svg
|main_interests = Politics, economics, [[philosophy]], [[sociology]], [[Labour relations|labour]], history, [[class struggle]],
|influences = [[Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel|Hegel]], [[Ludwig Feuerbach|Feuerbach]], [[Baruch Spinoza|Spinoza]], [[Pierre-Joseph Proudhon|Proudhon]], [[Max Stirner|Stirner]], [[Adam Smith|Smith]], [[Voltaire]], [[David Ricardo|Ricardo]], [[Giambattista Vico|Vico]], [[Jean-Jacques Rousseau|Rousseau]], [[William Shakespeare|Shakespeare]], [[Johann Wolfgang von Goethe|Goethe]], [[Claude Adrien Helvétius|Helvetius]], [[Baron d'Holbach|d'Holbach]],&lt;ref&gt;Mehring, Franz, ''Karl Marx: The Story of His Life'' (Routledge, 2003) pg. 75&lt;/ref&gt; [[Justus von Liebig|Liebig]],&lt;ref&gt;John Bellamy Foster. &quot;Marx's Theory of Metabolic Rift: Classical Foundations for Environmental Sociology&quot;, ''American Journal of Sociology'', Vol. 105, No. 2 (September 1999), pp. 366-405.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Charles Darwin|Darwin]], [[Charles Fourier|Fourier]], [[Robert Owen]], [[Nicolae Bălcescu|Bălcescu]], [[Moses Hess|Hess]], [[Victor d'Hupay|Hupay]], [[François Guizot|Guizot]], [[Constantin Pecqueur|Pecqueur]],&lt;ref&gt;Allen Oakley, [http://books.google.gr/books?id=L949AAAAIAAJ&amp;dq ''Marx's Critique of Political Economy: 1844 to 1860''], Routledge, 1984, p. 51.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Aristotle]], [[Epicurus]]
|influenced = [[Vladimir Lenin|Lenin]], [[Joseph Stalin|Stalin]], [[Leon Trotsky|Trotsky]], [[Mao Zedong|Mao]], [[Josip Broz Tito|Tito]], [[Enver Hoxha|Hoxha]], [[Fidel Castro|Castro]], [[Che Guevara|Guevara]], [[Ho Chi Minh|Ho]], [[Jean-Paul Sartre|Sartre]], [[Simone de Beauvoir]], [[Rosa Luxemburg|Luxemburg]], [[György Lukács|Lukács]], [[Antonio Gramsci|Gramsci]], [[Karl Korsch|Korsch]], [[Ernst Bloch|Bloch]], [[Peter Kropotkin|Kropotkin]], [[Mikhail Bakunin|Bakunin]], [[Herbert Marcuse|Marcuse]], [[Gilles Deleuze|Deleuze]], [[Guy Debord|Debord]], [[Antonio Negri|Negri]], [[Michael Taussig|Taussig]], [[Manabendra Nath Roy|Roy]], [[Ernesto Laclau|Laclau]], [[Pierre Bourdieu|Bourdieu]], [[Joseph Schumpeter|Schumpeter]], [[George Habash|Habash]], [[Michel Aflaq|Aflaq]] and [[List of Marxists|many others]]
|notable_ideas = Co-founder of [[Marxism]] (with [[Friedrich Engels|Engels]]), [[surplus value]], contributions to the [[labor theory of value]], [[class struggle]], [[Marx's theory of alienation|alienation]] and exploitation of the worker, ''[[The Communist Manifesto]],'' ''[[Das Kapital]],'' [[historical materialism|materialist conception of history]] |}}

'''Karl Heinrich Marx''' (&lt;small&gt;Berlin &lt;/small&gt;{{IPA-de|kaːɐ̯l ˈhaɪnʀɪç ˈmaːɐ̯ks}}, 5 May 1818 – 14 March 1883) was a [[Germans|German]] [[Philosophy|philosopher]], [[economics|economist]], [[sociology|sociologist]], [[historian]], [[journalism|journalist]], and [[Revolutionary socialism|revolutionary socialist]]. His ideas played a significant role in the development of [[social science]] and the [[socialism|socialist movement]]. He published various books during his lifetime, with the most notable being ''[[The Communist Manifesto]]'' (1848) and ''[[Das Kapital|Capital]]'' (1867–1894); some of his works were co-written with his friend and fellow German revolutionary socialist, [[Friedrich Engels]].&lt;ref name=&quot;sep&quot;/&gt;

Born into a wealthy middle-class family in [[Trier]] (formerly in Prussian Rhineland, now called Rhineland-Palatinate), Marx studied at both the [[University of Bonn]] and the [[University of Berlin]], where he became interested in the philosophical ideas of the [[Young Hegelians]]. In 1836 he became engaged to [[Jenny von Westphalen]], marrying her in 1843. After his studies, he wrote for a radical newspaper in [[Cologne]], and began to work out his theory of [[dialectical materialism]]. Moving to Paris in 1843, he began writing for other radical newspapers. He met Engels in Paris, and the two men worked together on a series of books. Exiled to [[Brussels]], he became a leading figure of the [[Communist League]], before moving back to Cologne, where he founded his own newspaper. In 1849 he was exiled again and moved to London together with his wife and children. In London, where the family was reduced to poverty, Marx continued writing and formulating his theories about the nature of society and how he believed it could be improved, and also campaigned for socialism—he became a significant figure in the [[International Workingmen's Association]].

Marx's theories about society, economics and politics—collectively known as [[Marxism]]—hold that all societies progress through the [[dialectic]] of [[class struggle]]: a conflict between an ownership class which controls production and a lower class which produces the labour for goods. Heavily critical of the current socio-economic form of society, [[capitalism]], he called it the &quot;dictatorship of the [[bourgeoisie]]&quot;, believing it to be run by the wealthy classes purely for their own benefit, and predicted that, like previous socioeconomic systems, it would inevitably produce internal tensions which would lead to its self-destruction and replacement by a new system, [[socialism (Marxism)|socialism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;wk&quot;/&gt; He argued that under socialism society would be governed by the working class in what he called the &quot;[[dictatorship of the proletariat]]&quot;, the &quot;workers state&quot; or &quot;workers' democracy&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Karl Marx: [http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1875/gotha/index.htm ''Critique of the Gotha Program''] (Marx/Engels Selected Works, Volume Three, pp. 13–30;)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;In [http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1852/letters/52_03_05.htm Letter from Karl Marx to Joseph Weydemeyer] (MECW Volume 39, p. 58; )&lt;/ref&gt; He believed that socialism would, in its turn, eventually be replaced by a [[stateless society|stateless]], [[classless society]] called [[pure communism|communism]]. Along with believing in the inevitability of socialism and communism, Marx actively fought for the former's implementation, arguing that both social theorists and underprivileged people should carry out organised revolutionary action to topple capitalism and bring about socio-economic change.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-23-24&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;wh1&quot; /&gt;

Revolutionary socialist governments espousing Marxist concepts took power in a variety of countries in the 20th century, leading to the formation of such socialist states as the [[Soviet Union]] in 1922 and the [[People's Republic of China]] in 1949.  Many labor unions and workers' parties worldwide were also influenced by Marxist ideas, while various theoretical variants, such as [[Leninism]], [[Stalinism]], [[Trotskyism]], and [[Maoism]], were developed from them. Marx is typically cited, with [[Émile Durkheim]] and [[Max Weber]], as one of the three principal architects of modern [[social science]].&lt;ref name=&quot;plato.stanford.edu&quot;/&gt; Marx has been described as one of the most influential figures in human history.&lt;ref name=&quot;Manchester&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The 100: A Ranking of the Most Influential Persons in History&quot;/&gt;

==Biography==
===Early life: 1818–1835===
[[File:Marx birthplace Trier.jpg|thumb|Marx's birthplace in Trier, Rhineland-Palatinate, which is now a museum devoted to him.]]
Karl Heinrich Marx was born on 5 May 1818 at 664 Brückergasse in [[Trier]], a town located in the [[Kingdom of Prussia]]'s [[Grand Duchy of the Lower Rhine|Province of the Lower Rhine]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]] [http://books.google.com/books?id=3KOyuSakn80C&amp;pg=PA8 p. 8] and [http://books.google.com/books?id=3KOyuSakn80C&amp;pg=PA12 p. 12]&lt;/ref&gt; His ancestry was [[Ashkenazi Jewish]], with his paternal line having supplied the [[rabbi]]s of Trier since 1723, a role that had been taken up by his own grandfather, Meier Halevi Marx; Meier's son and Karl's father would be the first in the line to receive a secular education.&lt;ref name=&quot;AllanAllan2005-68&quot;/&gt; His maternal grandfather was a Dutch rabbi.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. pp. 07–09, 12.&lt;/ref&gt; Karl's father, [[Heinrich Marx|Herschel Marx]], was middle-class and relatively wealthy: the family owned a number of [[Moselle]] vineyards; he converted from Judaism to the [[Protestantism|Protestant Christian]] denomination of [[Lutheranism]] prior to his son's birth, taking on the German forename of Heinrich over Herschel.&lt;ref name=sep/&gt; In 1815 he began working as an attorney and in 1819 moved his family from a five-room rented apartment into a ten-room property near the [[Porta Nigra]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. [http://books.google.com/books?id=3KOyuSakn80C&amp;pg=PA10 p. 10].&lt;/ref&gt; A man of the [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]], Heinrich Marx was interested in the ideas of the philosophers [[Immanuel Kant]] and [[Voltaire]], and took part in agitation for a constitution and reforms in Prussia, which was then governed by an [[absolute monarchy]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. [http://books.google.com/books?id=3KOyuSakn80C&amp;pg=PA11 p. 11].&lt;/ref&gt; Karl's mother, born Henrietta Pressburg (20 July 1788 – 30 November 1863), was a Dutch Jew who, unlike her husband, was only semi-literate. She claimed to suffer from &quot;excessive mother love&quot;, devoting much time to her family, and insisting on cleanliness within her home.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. [http://books.google.com/books?id=3KOyuSakn80C&amp;pg=PA12 p. 12].&lt;/ref&gt; She was from a prosperous business family that later founded the company [[Philips Electronics]]: she was great-aunt to [[Anton Philips|Anton]] and [[Gerard Philips]], and great-great-aunt to [[Frits Philips]]. Her brother, Marx's uncle Benjamin  Philips (1830-1900), was a wealthy banker and industrialist, upon whom Karl and Jenny Marx would later often come to rely for loans while they were exiled in London.&lt;ref&gt;''Francis Wheen, Karl Marx: A Life'', (Fourth Estate, 1999), ISBN 1-85702-637-3&lt;/ref&gt;

Heinrich Marx converted to Lutheran Protestantism in 1816 or 1817 in order to continue practicing law after the Prussian edict denying Jews to the bar. Karl was born in 1818 and baptized in 1824, but his mother, Henriette, did not convert until 1825, when Karl was seven. There is no evidence that the Marx family actually embraced Lutheranism, although there is no evidence that they were practicing Jews.  Marx identified himself as an atheist.&lt;ref&gt;Enzo Traverso, ''The Marxists and the Jewish Question'', (Humanities Press, 1994): &quot;Born into a Jewish family that had converted to Lutheranism, Marx received no religious education and grew up, under the influence of his father, in a liberal and ''aufklärerisch'' environment. He considered himself a German, an atheist and a Communist and recognized himself as neither a Jew nor a converted Jew&quot; (p14)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The famous Marxist historian and historiographer [[Eric Hobsbawm]] views Marx simply as a Jew, for example, in [http://www.lrb.co.uk/v27/n20/eric-hobsbawm/benefits-of-diaspora this October 2005 essay on the &quot;Benefits of Diaspora&quot;] in the ''[[London Review of Books]]'', in which he states &quot;issues to do with the nature, structure and possible transformations of society in an era of radical historical change both in practice and in theory have attracted emancipated Jews disproportionately almost from the beginning, starting with the Saint Simonians and Marx&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Julius Carlbach's ''Karl Marx and the Jewish Question'' has an interesting discussion of &quot;The Jewishness of Marx&quot; staring on [http://books.google.com/books?id=95c9AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA310 page 310], in which he describes the views of a large number of sources. See also Dennis K. Fischman's 1991 work ''Political Discourse in Exile: Karl Marx and the Jewish Question''.&lt;/ref&gt;

Little is known about Karl Marx's childhood.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. [http://books.google.com/books?id=3KOyuSakn80C&amp;pg=PA13 p. 13].&lt;/ref&gt; He was privately educated until 1830, when he entered Trier High School, whose headmaster [[Hugo Wyttenbach]] was a friend of his father. Wyttenbach had employed many [[Liberal humanism|liberal humanists]] as teachers. This angered the government, causing the police to raid the school in 1832, when they discovered what they labelled seditious literature that espoused political liberalism being distributed amongst the students.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1835 Karl, then seventeen, began attending the [[University of Bonn]], where he wished to study philosophy and literature, but his father insisted on law as a more practical field.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. [http://books.google.com/books?id=3KOyuSakn80C&amp;pg=PA14 p. 14].&lt;/ref&gt; He was able to avoid military service when he turned eighteen because he suffered from a weak chest.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt; Being fond of [[alcohol]]ic beverages, he joined the Trier Tavern Club drinking society (''Landsmannschaft der Treveraner'') and at one point served as its co-president.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt; Marx was more interested in drinking and socialising than studying law. Because of his poor grades, his father forced him to transfer to the far more serious and academically oriented [[Humboldt University of Berlin|University of Berlin]],&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. pp. 16–17.&lt;/ref&gt; where his legal studies became less significant to him than excursions into philosophy and history.&lt;ref name=&quot;AS&quot;/&gt;

===Hegelianism and early activism: 1836–1843===
Marx became interested in, but critical of, the work of the German philosopher [[G.W.F Hegel]] (1770–1831), whose ideas were widely debated amongst European philosophical circles at the time.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. pp. 21–22.&lt;/ref&gt; Marx wrote about falling ill &quot;from intense vexation at having to make an idol of a view I detested.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;FeuerHorowitz2010&quot;/&gt; He became involved with a group of [[Political radicalism|radical thinkers]] known as the [[Young Hegelians]], who gathered around [[Ludwig Andreas Feuerbach|Ludwig Feuerbach]] and [[Bruno Bauer]].&lt;ref name=&quot;AS&quot;/&gt; Like Marx, the Young Hegelians were critical of Hegel's [[metaphysics|metaphysical]] assumptions, but still adopted his [[dialectical method]] in order to criticise established society, politics, and religion. Marx befriended Bauer, and in July 1841 the two scandalised their class in [[Bonn]] by getting drunk, laughing in church, and galloping through the streets on donkeys.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. p. 34.&lt;/ref&gt; During that period Marx concentrated on his criticism of Hegel and certain other Young Hegelians.&lt;ref name=sep/&gt;

[[File:Marx2.jpg|thumb|A contemporary drawing of Karl Marx as a young man.]]

Marx also wrote for his own enjoyment, writing both non-fiction and fiction.  In 1837 he completed a short novel, ''[[Scorpion and Felix]]'', a drama, ''Oulanem'', and some poems, none of which was published.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hyman1974&quot;/&gt; In 1971 Marx's one act play ''Oulanem'' was made available in English by author Robert Payne.  According to Payne, the title ''Oulanem'' is an anagram for &quot;Manuelo&quot; which is a variant of &quot;Emmanuel&quot; meaning &quot;God is with us&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''Robert Payne, The Unknown Karl Marx'', (University Press, 1971)&lt;/ref&gt; He soon gave up writing fiction for other pursuits, including learning English and Italian.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. pp. 25–26.&lt;/ref&gt;

He was deeply engaged in writing his doctoral thesis, ''[[The Difference Between the Democritean and Epicurean Philosophy of Nature]]'', which he finished in 1841. The essay has been described as &quot;a daring and original piece of work in which he set out to show that [[theology]] must yield to the superior wisdom of [[philosophy]]&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. p. 32.&lt;/ref&gt; and as such was controversial, particularly among the conservative professors at the University of Berlin. Marx decided to submit it instead to the more liberal [[University of Jena]], whose faculty awarded him his PhD based on it.&lt;ref name=&quot;AS&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. p. 33.&lt;/ref&gt;

From considering an academic career, Marx turned to journalism.&lt;ref name=sep/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-19&quot;/&gt; He moved to the city of [[Cologne]] in 1842, where he began writing for the radical newspaper ''[[Rheinische Zeitung]]'', where he expressed his increasingly [[socialist]] views on politics.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. pp. 34–36.&lt;/ref&gt; He criticised the governments of Europe and their policies, but also liberals and other members of the socialist movement whose ideas he thought were ineffective or outright anti-socialist.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. pp. 42–44.&lt;/ref&gt; The paper eventually attracted the attention of the Prussian [[censorship|government censors]], who checked every issue for potentially seditious material before it could be printed.  Marx said, &quot;Our newspaper has to be presented to the police to be sniffed at, and if the police nose smells anything un-Christian or un-Prussian, the newspaper is not allowed to appear.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. p. 47.&lt;/ref&gt; After the paper published an article strongly criticising the monarchy in Russia, the Russian Tsar [[Nicholas I of Russia|Nicholas I]], an ally of the Prussian monarchy, requested that the ''Rheinische Zeitung'' be banned.  The Prussian government shut down the paper in 1843.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. pp. 47–48.&lt;/ref&gt; Marx wrote for the Young Hegelian journal, the ''Deutsche-Französische Jahrbücher'', in which he criticised the censorship instructions issued by Prussian King [[Friedrich Wilhelm IV]].  His article was censored and the newspaper closed down by the authorities shortly after.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. p. 36.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1843 Marx published ''[[On the Jewish Question]]'', in which he distinguished between political and human [[emancipation]]. He also examined the role of religious practice in society.&lt;ref name=sep/&gt; That same year he wrote notes on a ''[[Critique of Hegel's Philosophy of Right]]''.&lt;ref name=sep/&gt; He completed both works shortly before leaving Cologne.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morrison2006&quot;/&gt;

===Paris: 1843–1845===
Following the government-imposed shutdown of the ''Rheinische Zeitung'', Marx got involved with a new radical newspaper, the ''[[Deutsch-Französische Jahrbücher]]'' (''German-French Annals''), which was then being set up by [[Arnold Ruge]], another German socialist revolutionary.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. p. 48.&lt;/ref&gt; The paper was based not in Germany, but in the city of Paris in neighbouring France, and it was here that both Marx and his wife moved in October 1843. They initially lived with Ruge and his wife communally at 23 [[Rue Vaneau]], but finding these living conditions difficult, the Marxes moved out following the birth of their daughter Jenny in 1844.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. pp. 62–66.&lt;/ref&gt; Although it was intended to attract writers from both France and the German states, the ''Deutsch-Französische Jahrbücher'' was dominated by the latter, with the only non-German writer being the exiled Russian [[anarcho-communism|anarcho-communist]] [[Michael Bakunin]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. pp. 64–65.&lt;/ref&gt; Only one issue was ever published, but it was relatively successful, largely owing to the inclusion of [[Heinrich Heine]]'s satirical odes on King [[Ludwig I of Bavaria|Ludwig of Bavaria]], which led to those copies sent to Germany being confiscated by the state's police force.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. p. 65.&lt;/ref&gt; Marx's contributions to the ''Jahrbücher'' include the ''Introduction to a Contribution to the Critique of Hegel's Philosophy of Right'', which includes his famous description of religion as  &quot;the [[opiate of the people]].&quot;

It was in Paris that, on 28 August 1844, Marx met German socialist [[Friedrich Engels]] at the [[Café de la Régence]] after becoming interested in the ideas that the latter had expressed in articles written for the ''Rheinische Zeitung'' and the ''Deutsch-Französische Jahrbücher''. Although they had briefly met each other at the offices of the ''Rheinische Zeitung'' in 1842, it was here in Paris that they began their friendship that would last for the rest of their lives.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. p. 75.&lt;/ref&gt; Engels showed Marx his recently published book, ''[[The Condition of the Working Class in England in 1844]]'',&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, Philip: ''Paris Between Empires'', p.390 (St. Martin Press, NY) 2001&lt;/ref&gt; which convinced Marx that the working class would be the agent and instrument of the final revolution in history.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bottomore1991&quot;/&gt; Engels and Marx soon set about writing a criticism of the philosophical ideas of Marx's former friend, the Young Hegelian [[Bruno Bauer]], which would be published in 1845 as ''[[The Holy Family (book)|The Holy Family]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. pp. 85–86.&lt;/ref&gt; Although critical of Bauer, Marx was increasingly influenced by the ideas of the other Young Hegelians [[Max Stirner]] and [[Ludwig Feuerbach]], but eventually also abandoned Feuerbachian materialism as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;et&quot;/&gt;

In 1844 Marx wrote ''[[Economic and Philosophical Manuscripts of 1844|The Economic and Philosophical Manuscripts]]'', a work which covered numerous topics, and went into detail to explain Marx's concept of [[alienated labour]].&lt;ref name=sep/&gt; A year later Marx would write ''[[Theses on Feuerbach]]'', best known for the statement that &quot;the philosophers have only interpreted the world, the point is to change it&quot;.&lt;ref name=sep/&gt; This work contains Marx's criticism of [[materialism]] (for being contemplative), [[idealism]] (for reducing practice to theory) and overall, criticising philosophy for putting abstract reality above the physical world.&lt;ref name=sep/&gt; It thus introduced the first glimpse at Marx's [[historical materialism]], an argument that the world is changed not by ideas but by actual, physical, material activity and practice.&lt;ref name=sep/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Engels1999&quot;/&gt;

After the collapse of the ''Deutsch-Französische Jahrbücher'', Marx, still living on the Rue Vaneau, began writing for what was then the only uncensored German-language radical newspaper in Europe, ''[[Vorwärts!]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. pp. 66–67.&lt;/ref&gt; Based in Paris, the paper had been established and was run by many activists connected to the [[revolutionary socialism|revolutionary socialist]] League of the Just, which would come to be better known as the [[Communist League]] within a few years.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. p. 112.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CapperGiorcelli2007&quot;/&gt; In ''Vorwärts!'', Marx continued to refine his views on socialism based upon the Hegelian and Feuerbachian ideas of dialectical materialism, whilst at the same time criticising various liberals and other socialists operating in Europe at the time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wheen 2001. p. 90&quot;/&gt; However in 1845, after receiving a request from the Prussian king, the French government agreed to shut down ''Vorwärts!'', and furthermore, Marx himself was expelled from France by the interior minister [[François Guizot]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Wheen 2001. p. 90&quot;/&gt;

===Brussels: 1845–1847===
[[File:Communist-manifesto.png|thumb|The first edition of ''The Manifesto of the Communist Party'', published in German in 1848]]

Unable either to stay in France or to move to Germany, Marx decided to emigrate to Brussels in Belgium, but had to pledge not to publish anything on the subject of contemporary politics in order to enter.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wheen 2001. p. 90&quot;/&gt; In Brussels, he associated with other exiled socialists from across Europe, including [[Moses Hess]], [[Karl Heinzen]] and [[Joseph Weydemeyer]], and soon Engels moved to the city in order to join them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wheen 2001. p. 90&quot;/&gt; In 1845 Marx and Engels visited the leaders of the [[Chartism|Chartists]], a socialist movement in Britain, using the trip as an opportunity to study in various libraries in London and Manchester.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. p. 92.&lt;/ref&gt; In collaboration with Engels he also set about writing a book which is often seen as his best treatment of the concept of [[historical materialism]], ''[[The German Ideology]]''; the work, like many others, would not see publication in Marx's lifetime, being published only in 1932.&lt;ref name=sep/&gt;&lt;ref name=wk/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. p. 93.&lt;/ref&gt; He followed this with ''[[The Poverty of Philosophy]]'' (1847), a response to the French anarcho-socialist [[Pierre-Joseph Proudhon]]'s ''[[The Philosophy of Poverty]]'' and a critique of French socialist thought in general.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. p. 107.&lt;/ref&gt;

These books laid the foundation for Marx and Engels's most famous work, a political pamphlet that has since come to be commonly known as ''[[The Communist Manifesto]]''. First published on 21 February 1848, it laid out the beliefs of the Communist League, a group who had come increasingly under the influence of Marx and Engels, who argued that the League must make their aims and intentions clear to the general public rather than hiding them as they had formerly been doing.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. p. 115.&lt;/ref&gt; The opening lines of the pamphlet set forth the principal basis of Marxism, that &quot;The history of all hitherto existing society is the history of class struggles.&quot;{{fact|date=September 2012}} It goes on to look at the antagonisms that Marx claimed were arising between the clashes of interest between the [[bourgeoisie]] (the wealthy middle class) and the [[proletariat]] (the industrial working class). Proceeding on from this, the ''Manifesto'' presents the argument for why the Communist League, as opposed to other socialist and liberal political parties and groups at the time, was truly acting in the interests of the proletariat to overthrow capitalist society and replace it with socialism.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Mar48|Marx and Engels 1848]].&lt;/ref&gt;

Later that year, Europe experienced a series of protests, rebellions, and often violent upheavals, the [[Revolutions of 1848]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Wheen 2001. p. 125&quot;/&gt; In France, [[French Revolution of 1848|a revolution]] led to the overthrow of the monarchy and the establishment of the [[French Second Republic]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Wheen 2001. p. 125&quot;/&gt; Marx was supportive of such activity, and having recently received a substantial inheritance from his father of either 6000&lt;ref name=&quot;MaltsevN.-93&quot;/&gt; or 5000 francs,&lt;ref&gt;Saul Kussiel Padover, ''Karl Marx, an intimate biography'', McGraw-Hill, 1978, page 205&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; allegedly used a third of it to arm Belgian workers who were planning revolutionary action.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. pp. 126–127.&lt;/ref&gt; Although the veracity of these allegations is disputed,&lt;ref name=&quot;MaltsevN.-93&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;David McLellan 1973 ''Karl Marx: His life and Thought''. New York: Harper and Row. pp. 189–190&lt;/ref&gt; the Belgian Ministry of Justice accused him of it, subsequently arresting him, and he was forced to flee back to France, where, with a new republican government in power, he believed that he would be safe.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Felix |first1=David |last2= |first2= |year=1982 |title=Heute Deutschland! Marx as Provincial Politician |journal=Central European History |publisher=Cambridge University Press |volume= 15 |issue= 4 |pages=332–350 |doi=10.1017/S0008938900010621 |jstor=4545968 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cologne: 1848–1849===
Temporarily settling down in Paris, Marx transferred the Communist League executive headquarters to the city and also set up a German Workers' Club with various German socialists living there.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. p. 128.&lt;/ref&gt; Hoping to see the revolution spread to Germany, in 1848 Marx moved back to Cologne (Köln) where he began issuing a handbill entitled the ''Demands of the Communist Party in Germany'', in which he argued for only four of the ten points of the ''Communist Manifesto'', believing that in Germany at that time, the bourgeoisie must overthrow the [[feudalism|feudal]] monarchy and aristocracy before the proletariat could overthrow the bourgeoisie.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. p. 129.&lt;/ref&gt; On 1 June, Marx started publication of the daily ''[[Neue Rheinische Zeitung]]'' (&quot;New Rhenish Newspaper&quot;), which he helped to finance through his recent inheritance from his father. Designed to put forward news from across Europe with his own Marxist interpretation of events, Marx remained one of its primary writers, accompanied by other fellow members of the Communist League who wrote for the paper, although despite their input it remained, according to Friedrich Engels, &quot;a simple dictatorship by Marx&quot;, who dominated the choice of content.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. pp. 130–132.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Seigel, p. 50&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DL-Marx&quot;/&gt;

Whilst editor of the paper, Marx and the other revolutionary socialists were regularly harassed by the police, and Marx was brought to trial on several occasions, facing various allegations including insulting the Chief Public Prosecutor, committing a press misdemeanor, and inciting armed rebellion through tax boycotting,&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Nicolaievsky2007&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Nicolaievsky2007&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Splichal2002&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mehring2003&quot;/&gt; although each time he was acquitted.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nicolaievsky2007&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mehring2003&quot;/&gt; Meanwhile, the democratic parliament in Prussia collapsed, and the king, [[Frederick William IV]], introduced a new cabinet of his reactionary supporters, who implemented counter-revolutionary measures to expunge leftist and other revolutionary elements from the country.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt; Consequently, the ''Neue Rheinische Zeitung'' was soon suppressed and Marx was ordered to leave the country on 16 May.&lt;ref name=&quot;DL-Marx&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. pp. 137–146.&lt;/ref&gt; Marx returned to Paris, which was then under the grip of both a reactionary counter-revolution and a [[cholera]] epidemic, and was soon expelled by the city authorities who considered him a political threat. With his wife Jenny expecting their fourth child, and not able to move back to Germany or Belgium, in August 1849 he sought refuge in London.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. pp. 147–148.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Watson2010&quot;/&gt;

===London: 1849–1883===
[[File:Karl and jenny marx 1866.jpg|thumb|Karl Marx and his daughter Jenny (before May 1864)]]
Marx moved to London in May 1849 and would remain based in the city for the rest of his life. It was here that he founded the new headquarters of the Communist League, and got heavily involved with the socialist [[German Workers' Educational Society]], who held their meetings in [[Great Windmill Street]], [[Soho]], central London's entertainment district.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. pp. 151–155.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Harriss2006&quot;/&gt; Marx devoted himself to two activities: revolutionary organising, and an attempt to understand [[political economy]] and capitalism. For the first few years he and his family lived in extreme poverty.&lt;ref name=&quot;DusselMoseley2001&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;egsbio&quot;/&gt; His main source of income was his colleague, Engels, who derived much of his income from his family's business.&lt;ref name=egsbio/&gt; Marx also briefly worked as correspondent for the ''[[New York Tribune]]'' in 1851.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dispatches for the New York Tribune: Selected Journalism of Karl Marx&quot;/&gt;

From December 1851 to March 1852 Marx wrote ''[[The Eighteenth Brumaire of Louis Napoleon]]'', a work on the [[French Revolution of 1848]], in which he expanded upon his concepts of historical materialism, [[class struggle]] and the [[dictatorship of the proletariat]], advancing the argument that victorious proletariat has to smash the [[bourgeois]] state.&lt;ref name=&quot;Marx2008&quot;/&gt;

The 1850s and 1860s also mark the line between what some scholars see as [[idealistic]], Hegelian [[young Marx]] from the more scientifically-minded [[mature Marx]] writings of the later period.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wood&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wood1993&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hook1994&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Johnston2000&quot;/&gt; This distinction is usually associated with the [[structural Marxism]] school,&lt;ref name=&quot;Johnston2000&quot;/&gt; and not all scholars agree that it exists.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hook1994&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;GeorgeScanlan1975&quot;/&gt;

In 1864 Marx became involved in the [[International Workingmen's Association]] (also known as ''First International'').&lt;ref name=&quot;Nicolaievsky2007&quot;/&gt;, to whose General Council he was elected at its inception in 1864.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nicolaievsky2007-267&quot;/&gt; In that organisation Marx was involved in the struggle against the [[anarchist]] wing centred around [[Mikhail Bakunin]] (1814–1876).&lt;ref name=egsbio/&gt; Although Marx won this contest, the transfer of the seat of the General Council from London to New York in 1872, which Marx supported, led to the decline of the International.&lt;ref name=&quot;JessopWheatley1999-526&quot;/&gt; The most important political event during the existence of the International was the ''[[Paris Commune]] of 1871'' when the citizens of Paris rebelled against their government and held the city for two months. In response to the bloody suppression of this rebellion Marx wrote one of his most famous pamphlets, ''[[The Civil War in France]]'', a defense of the Commune.&lt;ref name=&quot;Curtis1997&quot;/&gt;

Given the repeated failures and frustrations of workers' revolutions and movements, Marx also sought to understand capitalism, and spent a great deal of time in the reading room of the [[British Museum]] studying and reflecting on the works of [[political economy|political economists]] and on economic data.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-20&quot;/&gt; By 1857 he had accumulated over 800 pages of notes and short essays on capital, [[landed property]], wage labour, the state, and foreign trade and the world market; this work did not appear in print until 1941, under the title ''[[Grundrisse]]''.&lt;ref name=egsbio/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Segrest2002&quot;/&gt; In 1859 Marx published ''[[Contribution to the Critique of Political Economy]]'', his first serious economic work. In the early 1860s he worked on composing three large volumes, the ''[[Theories of Surplus Value]]'', which discussed the theoreticians of political economy, particularly [[Adam Smith]] and [[David Ricardo]].&lt;ref name=egsbio/&gt; This work is often seen as the fourth book of ''[[Das Kapital|Capital]]'' and constitutes one of the first comprehensive treatises on the [[history of economic thought]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Rockmore2002&quot;/&gt; In 1867 the first volume of ''[[Das Kapital|Capital]]'' was published, a work which analyzed the capitalist process of production.&lt;ref name=&quot;BrewerMarx1984-15&quot;/&gt; Here Marx elaborated his [[labour theory of value]] (influenced by [[Thomas Hodgskin]]{{citation needed|date=May 2012}}) and his conception of [[surplus value]] and [[exploitation]], which he argued would ultimately lead to a falling rate of profit and the collapse of industrial capitalism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-23&quot;/&gt; Volumes&amp;nbsp;II and III remained mere manuscripts upon which Marx continued to work for the rest of his life and were published posthumously by Engels.&lt;ref name=egsbio/&gt;

[[File:Marx old.jpg|thumb|Marx in 1882]]
During the last decade of his life Marx's health declined and he became incapable of the sustained effort that had characterised his previous work.&lt;ref name=egsbio/&gt; He did manage to comment substantially on contemporary politics, particularly in Germany and Russia. His ''[[Critique of the Gotha Programme]]'' opposed the tendency of his followers [[Wilhelm Liebknecht]] and [[August Bebel]] to compromise with the [[state socialism]] of [[Ferdinand Lassalle]] in the interests of a united socialist party.&lt;ref name=egsbio/&gt; This work is also notable for another famous Marx's quote: &quot;[[From each according to his ability, to each according to his need]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;CGP P1&quot;/&gt;

In a letter to [[Vera Zasulich]] dated 8 March 1881, Marx contemplated the possibility of Russia's bypassing the capitalist stage of development and building communism on the basis of the common ownership of land characteristic of the village [[mir (social)|''mir'']].&lt;ref name=egsbio/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Karl Marx and Frederick Engels, ''Collected Works Volume 46'' (International Publishers: New York, 1992) p. 71.&lt;/ref&gt; While admitting that Russia's rural &quot;commune is the fulcrum of social regeneration in Russia&quot;, Marx also warned that, in order for the mir to operate as a means for moving straight to the socialist stage without a preceding capitalist stage, it &quot;would first be necessary to eliminate the deleterious influences which are assailing it (the rural commune) from all sides.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;k72&quot;/&gt; Given the elimination of these pernicious influences, Marx allowed that &quot;normal conditions of spontaneous development&quot; of the rural commune could exist.&lt;ref name=k72/&gt; However, in the same letter to Vera Zasulich, Marx points out that &quot;at the core of the capitalist system&amp;nbsp;... lies the complete separation of the producer from the means of production.&quot;&lt;ref name=k72/&gt; In one of the drafts of this letter, Marx reveals his growing passion for anthropology, motivated by his belief that future communism would be a return on a higher level to the communism of our prehistoric past. He wrote that &quot;the historical trend of our age is the fatal crisis which capitalist production has undergone in the European and American countries where it has reached its highest peak, a crisis that will end in its destruction, in the return of modern society to a higher form of the most archaic type — collective production and appropriation&quot;. He added that &quot;the vitality of primitive communities was incomparably greater than that of Semitic, Greek, Roman, etc. societies, and, a fortiori, that of modern capitalist societies&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;K. Marx, First draft of letter to Vera Zasulich [1881]. In Marx-Engels 'Collected Works', Volume 24, p. 346.&lt;/ref&gt; Before he died, Marx asked Engels to write up these ideas, which were published in 1884 under the title ''[[The Origin of the Family, Private Property and the State]]''.

===Personal life===
[[File:Jenny laura marx.jpg|thumb|Jenny Carolina and Jenny Laura Marx (1869). All the Marx daughters were named in honour of their mother, [[Jenny von Westphalen]]]]
In 1836, Marx became engaged to [[Jenny von Westphalen]], a beautiful baroness of the Prussian ruling class—&quot;the most desirable young woman in Trier&quot; &lt;ref name=Montefiore /&gt; —who broke off her engagement with a young aristocratic second lieutenant to be with him.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hunt2010&quot;/&gt; Their eventual marriage was controversial for breaking two social taboos of the period: it was a marriage between a woman of a noble background and a man of Jewish origin, as well as being between a member of the upper class (aristocracy) and a member of the middle class, respectively. Such issues were lessened by Marx's friendship with Jenny's father, Baron [[Ludwig von Westphalen]], a liberal thinking aristocrat. Marx dedicated his doctoral thesis to him.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. pp. 17–21, 33.&lt;/ref&gt; The couple married seven years later, on 19 June 1843, at the ''Wilhelmskirche'' in [[Bad Kreuznach|Kreuznach]].&lt;ref&gt;According to a local historiography (Rosenkranz, A. (1951): ''Geschichte der evangelischen Gemeinde Kreuznach'', p. 166), the ''Pauluskirche'', stated by several biographers to have been the place of marriage (cf. [[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. pp. 52–53.), underwent a major renovation until &quot;around New Year's Day of 1844&quot;, leaving the town's other Evangelical church, the ''Wilhelmskirche'', as the most probable place of marriage.&lt;/ref&gt;

Marx and von Westphalen had seven children together, but partly owing to the poor living conditions they were forced to live in whilst in London, only three survived to adulthood.&lt;ref&gt;Peter Singer (2000). Marx a very short introduction. pp. 5. ISBN 0-19-285405-4&lt;/ref&gt; The children were: [[Jenny Longuet|Jenny Caroline]] (m. Longuet; 1844–83); [[Laura Marx|Jenny Laura]] (m. Lafargue; 1845–1911); Edgar (1847–1855); Henry Edward Guy (&quot;Guido&quot;; 1849–1850); Jenny Eveline Frances (&quot;Franziska&quot;; 1851–52); [[Eleanor Marx|Jenny Julia Eleanor]] (1855–98) and one more who died before being named (July 1857). There are allegations that Marx also fathered a son, Freddy,&lt;ref name=Montefiore&gt;{{cite news|last=Montefiore|first=Simon Sebag|title=The Means of Reproduction|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/09/25/books/review/love-and-capital-by-mary-gabriel-book-review.html|publisher=The New York Times|accessdate=25 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  out of wedlock by his housekeeper, [[Helene Demuth]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Karl Marx&quot;/&gt;

Marx frequently used pseudonyms, often when renting a house or flat, apparently to make it harder for the authorities to track him down. While in Paris, he used that of 'Monsieur Ramboz', whilst in London he signed off his letters as 'A. Williams'. His friends referred to him as 'Moor', owing to his dark complexion and black curly hair, something which they believed made him resemble the historical [[Moors]] of North Africa, whilst he encouraged his children to call him 'Old Nick' and 'Charley'.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wheen 2001. p. 152&quot;/&gt; He also bestowed nicknames and pseudonyms on his friends and family as well, referring to Friedrich Engels as 'General', his housekeeper Helene as 'Lenchen' or 'Nym', while one of his daughters, Jennychen, was referred to as 'Qui Qui, Emperor of China' and another, Laura, was known as 'Kakadou' or 'the [[Khoikhoi|Hottentot]]'.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wheen 2001. p. 152&quot;/&gt;

===Death===
[[File:KarlMarx Tomb.JPG|thumb|The tomb of Karl Marx, Highgate Cemetery, London]]
Following the death of his wife Jenny in December 1881, Marx developed a [[catarrh]] that kept him in ill health for the last 15 months of his life. It eventually brought on the [[bronchitis]] and [[pleurisy]] that killed him in London on 14 March 1883. He died a [[Statelessness|stateless person]];&lt;ref name=&quot;stateless&quot;/&gt; family and friends in London buried his body in [[Highgate Cemetery]], London, on 17 March 1883. There were between nine and eleven mourners at his funeral.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. [http://books.google.com/books?id=3KOyuSakn80C&amp;pg=PA382 p. 382].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;GouldMcGarr2007&quot;/&gt;

Several of his closest friends spoke at his funeral, including [[Wilhelm Liebknecht]] and Friedrich Engels. Engels's speech included the passage:
{{quote|On the 14th&amp;nbsp;of March, at a quarter to three in the afternoon, the greatest living thinker ceased to think. He had been left alone for scarcely two minutes, and when we came back we found him in his armchair, peacefully gone to sleep—but forever.&lt;ref name=&quot;1883: The death of Karl Marx&quot;/&gt;}}
Marx's daughter [[Eleanor Marx|Eleanor]] and [[Charles Longuet]] and [[Paul Lafargue]], Marx's two French socialist sons-in-law, were also in attendance.&lt;ref name=&quot;GouldMcGarr2007&quot;/&gt; Liebknecht, a founder and leader of the German Social-Democratic Party, gave a speech in German, and Longuet, a prominent figure in the French working-class movement, made a short statement in French.&lt;ref name=&quot;GouldMcGarr2007&quot;/&gt; Two [[telegram]]s from workers' parties in France and Spain were also read out.&lt;ref name=&quot;GouldMcGarr2007&quot;/&gt; Together with Engels's speech, this constituted the entire programme of the funeral.&lt;ref name=&quot;GouldMcGarr2007&quot;/&gt; Non-relatives attending the funeral included three communist associates of Marx: Friedrich Lessner, imprisoned for three years after the Cologne communist trial of 1852; G. Lochner, whom Engels described as &quot;an old member of the Communist League&quot;; and [[Carl Schorlemmer]], a professor of chemistry in Manchester, a member of the [[Royal Society]], and a communist activist involved in the 1848 [[Revolution in Baden|Baden revolution]].&lt;ref name=&quot;GouldMcGarr2007&quot;/&gt; Another attendee of the funeral was [[Ray Lankester]], a British zoologist who would later become a prominent academic.&lt;ref name=&quot;GouldMcGarr2007&quot;/&gt;

Upon his own death, Engels left Marx's two surviving daughters a &quot;significant portion&quot; of his $4.8 million estate.&lt;ref name=Montefiore /&gt;

Marx's [[tombstone]] bears the carved message: &quot;[[Workers of the world, unite!|WORKERS OF ALL LANDS UNITE]]&quot;, the final line of ''The Communist Manifesto,'' and from the 11th ''[[Theses on Feuerbach|Thesis on Feuerbach]]'' (edited by Engels): &quot;The philosophers have only interpreted the world in various ways—the point however is to change it&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;wh1&quot; /&gt; The [[Communist Party of Great Britain]] had the monumental tombstone built in 1954 with a portrait bust by [[Laurence Bradshaw]]; Marx's original tomb had had only humble adornment.&lt;ref name=&quot;wh1&quot;/&gt; In 1970 there was an unsuccessful attempt to destroy the monument using a homemade bomb.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.camdennewjournal.co.uk/111705/cn111705_11.htm &quot;Tomb raiders' failed attack on Marx grave&quot;], ''Camden New Journal''&lt;/ref&gt;

The later Marxist historian [[Eric Hobsbawm]] remarked that &quot;One cannot say Marx died a failure&quot; because, although he had not achieved a large following of disciples in Britain, his writings had already begun to make an impact on the leftist movements in Germany and Russia. Within 25 years of his death, the continental European socialist parties that acknowledged Marx's influence on their politics were each gaining between 15 and 47% in those countries with [[representative democracy|representative democratic]] elections.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Hob11|Hobsbawm 2011]]. pp. 03–04.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Thought==
===Influences===
{{double image|right|Hegel.jpg|140|Feuerbach Ludwig.jpg|120|The philosophers [[Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel|G.W.F. Hegel]] and [[Ludwig Feuerbach]], whose ideas on dialectics heavily influenced Marx}}

[[File:Engels 1856.jpg|thumb|[[Friedrich Engels]]]]
{{Main|Influences on Karl Marx}}

Marx's thought demonstrates influences from many thinkers, including but not limited to:
* [[Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel]]'s philosophy;&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-20-23&quot;/&gt;
* the classical [[political economy]] (economics) of [[Adam Smith]] and [[David Ricardo]];&lt;ref name=&quot;Sherman1995&quot;/&gt;
* [[History of the Left in France|French socialist thought]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Sherman1995&quot;/&gt; in particular the thought of [[Jean-Jacques Rousseau]], [[Henri de Saint-Simon]], [[Pierre-Joseph Proudhon]], and [[Charles Fourier]];&lt;ref name=&quot;Beilharz1992&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Clark1998&quot;/&gt;
* earlier German philosophical materialism, particularly that of [[Ludwig Feuerbach]];&lt;ref name=et/&gt;
* the working class analysis by [[Friedrich Engels]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bottomore1991&quot;/&gt;

Marx's view of history, which came to be called [[historical materialism]] (controversially adapted as the philosophy of [[dialectical materialism]] by Engels and Lenin) certainly shows the influence of Hegel's claim that one should view reality (and history) [[dialectic]]ally.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-20-23&quot;/&gt; However, Hegel had thought in [[idealist]] terms, putting ideas in the forefront, whereas Marx sought to rewrite dialectics in [[materialist]] terms, arguing for the primacy of matter over idea.&lt;ref name=sep/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-20-23&quot;/&gt; Where Hegel saw the &quot;spirit&quot; as driving history, Marx saw this as an unnecessary mystification, obscuring the reality of humanity and its physical actions shaping the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-20-23&quot;/&gt; He wrote that Hegelianism stood the movement of reality on its head, and that one needed to set it upon its feet.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-20-23&quot;/&gt;

Though inspired by French socialist and sociological thought,&lt;ref name=&quot;Sherman1995&quot;/&gt; Marx criticised [[utopian socialists]], arguing that their favoured small scale socialistic communities would be bound to marginalisation and poverty, and that only a large scale change in the [[economic system]] can bring about real change.&lt;ref name=&quot;Clark1998&quot;/&gt;

The other important contribution to Marx's revision of Hegelianism came from Engels's book, ''[[The Condition of the Working Class in England in 1844]]'', which led Marx to conceive of the historical dialectic in terms of [[class conflict]] and to see the modern working class as the most progressive force for revolution.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bottomore1991&quot;/&gt;

Marx believed that he could study history and society scientifically and discern tendencies of history and the resulting outcome of social conflicts. Some followers of Marx concluded, therefore, that a communist revolution would inevitably occur. However, Marx famously asserted in the eleventh of his ''[[Theses on Feuerbach]]'' that &quot;philosophers have only interpreted the world, in various ways; the point however is to change it&quot;, and he clearly dedicated himself to trying to alter the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-23-24&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;wh1&quot; /&gt;

===Philosophy and social thought===
Marx polemic with other thinkers often occurred through [[critique]], and thus he has been called &quot;the first great user of [[critical method]] in social sciences.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-20-23&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Sherman1995&quot;/&gt; He criticised speculative [[philosophy]], equating [[metaphysics]] with [[ideology]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bannerji2001&quot;/&gt; By adopting this approach, Marx attempted to separate key findings from ideological biases.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sherman1995&quot;/&gt; This set him apart from many contemporary philosophers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-23-24&quot;/&gt;

====Human nature====
{{see|Marx's theory of human nature}}
Fundamentally, Marx assumed that [[human history]] involves transforming [[human nature]], which encompasses both human beings and material objects.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ollman1973&quot;/&gt; Humans recognise that they possess both actual and potential selves.&lt;ref name = &quot;Marx_labour&quot;&gt;Marx K (1999). [http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1867-c1/ch07.htm &quot;The labour-process and the process of producing surplus-value&quot;.] In K Marx, ''Capital'' (Vol. 1, Ch. 7). Marxists.org. Retrieved 20 October 2010. Original work published 1867.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Marx_critique&quot;&gt;See Marx K (1997). &quot;Critique of Hegel's dialectic and philosophy in general&quot;. In K Marx, ''Writings of the Young Marx on Philosophy and Society'' (LD Easton &amp; KH Guddat, Trans.), pp. 314–347. Indianapolis: Hackett Publishing Company, Inc. Original work published 1844.&lt;/ref&gt; For both Marx and Hegel, self-development begins with an experience of internal [[Marx's theory of alienation|alienation]] stemming from this recognition, followed by a realisation that the actual self, as a [[Subject (philosophy)|subjective]] agent, renders its potential counterpart an [[Object (philosophy)|object]] to be apprehended.&lt;ref name = &quot;Marx_critique&quot;/&gt; Marx further argues that, by molding nature&lt;ref name = &quot;Lefever&quot;&gt;See also Lefever DM; Lefever JT (1977). &quot;Marxian alienation and economic organisation: An alternate view&quot;. ''The American Economist(21)''2, pp. 40–48.&lt;/ref&gt; in desired ways,&lt;ref name = &quot;Holland_desire&quot;&gt;See also Holland EW (2005). &quot;Desire&quot;. In CJ Stivale (Ed.), ''Gilles Deleuze: Key Concepts'', pp. 53–62. Montreal &amp; Kingston: McGill-Queens University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; the subject takes the object as its own, and thus permits the individual to be actualised as fully human. For Marx, then, [[Marx's theory of human nature|human nature]]—''Gattungswesen'', or [[species-being]]—exists as a function of human labour.&lt;ref name = &quot;Marx_labour&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Marx_critique&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Holland_desire&quot;/&gt; Fundamental to Marx's idea of meaningful labour is the proposition that, in order for a subject to come to terms with its alienated object, it must first exert influence upon literal, material objects in the subject's world.&lt;ref name = &quot;Marx_objects&quot;/&gt; Marx acknowledges that Hegel &quot;grasps the nature of ''work'' and comprehends objective man, authentic because actual, as the result of his ''own work''&quot;,&lt;ref name = &quot;Marx_work&quot;&gt;Marx (1997), p. 321, emphasis in original.&lt;/ref&gt; but characterises Hegelian self-development as unduly &quot;spiritual&quot; and abstract.&lt;ref name = &quot;Marx_spiritual&quot;&gt;Marx (1997), p. 324.&lt;/ref&gt; Marx thus departs from Hegel by insisting that &quot;the fact that man is a ''corporeal'', actual, sentient, objective being with natural capacities means that he has ''actual, sensuous objects'' for his nature as objects of his life-expression, or that he can only ''express'' his life in actual sensuous objects.&quot;&lt;ref name = &quot;Marx_objects&quot;&gt;Marx (1997), p. 325, emphasis in original.&lt;/ref&gt; Consequently, Marx revises Hegelian &quot;work&quot; into material &quot;[[labour (economics)|labour]]&quot;, and in the context of human capacity to transform nature the term &quot;[[labour power]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=sep/&gt;

====Labour, class struggle, and false consciousness====
{{see|Labour theory of value}}
{{quote|The history of all hitherto existing society is the history of class struggles. | Karl Marx, ''[[The Communist Manifesto]]''{{fact|date=September 2012}}}}
Marx had a special concern with how people relate to that most fundamental resource of all, their own labour power.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-22&quot;/&gt; He wrote extensively about this in terms of the problem of [[Marx's theory of alienation|alienation]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Mészáros2006&quot;/&gt; As with the dialectic, Marx began with a Hegelian notion of alienation but developed a more materialist conception.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-22&quot;/&gt; Capitalism mediates social relationships of production (such as among workers or between workers and capitalists) through commodities, including labour, that are bought and sold on the market.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-22&quot;/&gt; For Marx, the possibility that one may give up ownership of one's own labour—one's capacity to transform the world—is tantamount to being alienated from one's own nature; it is a spiritual loss.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-22&quot;/&gt; Marx described this loss as [[commodity fetishism]], in which the things that people produce, commodities, appear to have a life and movement of their own to which humans and their behavior merely adapt.&lt;ref name=&quot;Balibar1995&quot;/&gt;

Commodity fetishism provides an example of what Engels called &quot;[[false consciousness]]&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;KołakowskiFalla2005&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author1=Leszek Kołakowski|author2=Paul Stephen Falla|title=Main currents of Marxism: the founders, the golden age, the breakdown|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=qUCxpznbkaoC&amp;pg=PA226|accessdate=8 March 2011|date=29 October 2005|publisher=W. W. Norton &amp; Company|isbn=978-0-393-06054-6|page=226}}&lt;/ref&gt; which relates closely to the understanding of [[ideology]]. By &quot;ideology&quot;, Marx and Engels meant ideas that reflect the interests of a particular class at a particular time in history, but which contemporaries see as universal and eternal.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hernadi1989&quot;/&gt; Marx and Engels's point was not only that such beliefs are at best half-truths; they serve an important political function. Put another way, the control that one class exercises over the means of production includes not only the production of food or manufactured goods; it includes the production of ideas as well (this provides one possible explanation for why members of a subordinate class may hold ideas contrary to their own interests).&lt;ref name=sep/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson1990&quot;/&gt; An example of this sort of analysis is Marx's understanding of religion, summed up in a passage from the preface&lt;ref&gt;Karl Marx: [http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1843/critique-hpr/intro.htm Introduction] to A Contribution to the Critique of Hegel's Philosophy of Right, in: ''[[Deutsch-Französische Jahrbücher]]'', February 1844&lt;/ref&gt; to his 1843 ''Contribution to the [[Critique of Hegel's Philosophy of Right]]'':

{{quote|''Religious'' suffering is, at one and the same time, the ''expression'' of real suffering and a ''protest'' against real suffering. Religion is the sigh of the oppressed creature, the heart of a heartless world, and the soul of soulless conditions. It is the [[Opium of the People|''opium'' of the people]]. The abolition of religion as the illusory happiness of the people is the demand for their real happiness. To call on them to give up their illusions about their condition is to call on them to give up a condition that requires illusions.&lt;ref name=&quot;MarxO'Malley1977&quot;/&gt;}}

Whereas his [[Gymnasium (school)|Gymnasium]] senior thesis argued that religion had as its primary social aim the promotion of [[solidarity (sociology)|solidarity]], here Marx sees the social function of religion in terms of highlighting/preserving political and economic [[status quo]] and [[Economic inequality|inequality]].&lt;ref name=&quot;SwatosKivisto1998&quot;/&gt;

====Economy, history and society====
{{see|Marxian economics}}
Marx's thoughts on labour were related to the primacy he gave to the economic relation in determining the society's past, present and future (see also [[economic determinism]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-20-23&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Clark1998&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Turner2005&quot;/&gt; [[Accumulation of capital]] shapes the [[social system]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Clark1998&quot;/&gt; [[Social change]], for Marx, was about conflict between opposing interests, driven, in the background, by economic forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-20-23&quot;/&gt; This became the inspiration for the body of works known as the [[conflict theory]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Turner2005&quot;/&gt; In his [[sociocultural evolution|evolutionary]] model of history, he argued that [[human history]] began with free, productive and creative work that was over time coerced and dehumanised, a trend most apparent under capitalism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-20-23&quot;/&gt; Marx noted that this was not an intentional process; rather, no individual or even state can go against the forces of economy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Clark1998&quot;/&gt;

The organisation of society depends on [[means of production]]. Literally those things, like land, natural resources, and technology, necessary for the production of material goods and the [[relations of production]], in other words, the social relationships people enter into as they acquire and use the means of production.&lt;ref name=&quot;Turner2005&quot;/&gt; Together these compose the [[mode of production]], and Marx distinguished historical eras in terms of distinct modes of production. Marx differentiated between [[base and superstructure]], with the base (or substructure) referring to the economic system, and superstructure, to the cultural and political system.&lt;ref name=&quot;Turner2005&quot;/&gt; Marx regarded this mismatch between (economic) base and (social) [[base and superstructure|superstructure]] as a major source of social disruption and conflict.&lt;ref name=&quot;Turner2005&quot;/&gt;

Despite Marx's stress on critique of capitalism and discussion of the new [[communist society]] that should replace it, his explicit critique of capitalism is guarded, as he saw it as an improved society compared to the past ones ([[slavery]] and [[feudal]]).&lt;ref name=sep/&gt; Marx also never clearly discusses issues of [[morality]] and [[justice]], although scholars agree that his work contained [[Logical implication|implicit]] discussion of those concepts.&lt;ref name=sep/&gt;

[[File:Marx Moscow.jpg|thumb|Memorial to Karl Marx in Moscow. The inscription reads &quot;[[Workers of the world, unite!|Proletarians of all countries, unite!]]&quot;]]
Marx's view of capitalism was two-sided.&lt;ref name=sep/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wood1993&quot;/&gt;
On one hand, Marx, in the 19th century's deepest critique of the dehumanising aspects of this system, noted that defining features of capitalism include alienation, exploitation, and recurring, cyclical [[economic depressions|depressions]] leading to mass unemployment; on the other hand capitalism is also characterised by &quot;revolutionizing, industrializing and universalizing qualities of development, growth and progressivity&quot; (by which Marx meant [[industrialization|industrialisation]], urbanisation, [[technological progress]], increased [[productivity]] and [[economic growth|growth]], [[rationality]] and [[scientific revolution]]), that are responsible for progress.&lt;ref name=sep/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wood1993&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-20-23&quot;/&gt; Marx considered the capitalist class to be one of the most revolutionary in history, because it constantly improved the means of production, more so than any other class in history, and was responsible for the overthrow of [[feudalism]] and its transition to capitalism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Clark1998&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Gilbert2010&quot;/&gt; Capitalism can stimulate considerable growth because the capitalist can, and has an incentive to, reinvest profits in new technologies and [[capital equipment]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-22&quot;/&gt;

According to Marx capitalists take advantage of the difference between the labour market and the market for whatever commodity the capitalist can produce. Marx observed that in practically every successful industry input unit-costs are lower than output unit-prices. Marx called the difference &quot;[[surplus value]]&quot; and argued that this surplus value had its source in [[surplus labour]], the difference between what it costs to keep workers alive and what they can produce.&lt;ref name=sep/&gt; Marx's dual view of capitalism can be seen in his description of the capitalists: he refers to them as to [[vampire]]s sucking worker's blood, but at the same time,&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-20-23&quot;/&gt; he notes that drawing profit is &quot;by no means an injustice&quot;&lt;ref name=sep/&gt; and that capitalists simply cannot go against the system.&lt;ref name=&quot;Clark1998&quot;/&gt; The true problem lies with the &quot;cancerous cell&quot; of [[Capital (economics)|capital]], understood not as property or equipment, but the relations between workers and owners – the economic system in general.&lt;ref name=&quot;Clark1998&quot;/&gt;

At the same time, Marx stressed that capitalism was unstable, and prone to [[crisis theory|periodic crises]].&lt;ref name=wk/&gt; He suggested that over time, capitalists would invest more and more in new technologies, and less and less in labour.&lt;ref name=sep/&gt; Since Marx believed that surplus value appropriated from labour is the source of profits, he concluded that the rate of profit would fall even as the economy grew.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-23&quot;/&gt; Marx believed that increasingly severe crises would punctuate this [[business cycles|cycle]] of growth, collapse, and more growth.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-23&quot;/&gt; Moreover, he believed that in the long-term this process would necessarily enrich and [[empowerment|empower]] the capitalist class and impoverish the proletariat.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-23&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Clark1998&quot;/&gt; In section one of ''The Communist Manifesto'' Marx describes [[feudalism]], capitalism, and the role internal social contradictions play in the historical process:
{{quote|We see then: the means of production and of exchange, on whose foundation the [[bourgeoisie]] built itself up, were generated in feudal society. At a certain stage in the development of these means of production and of exchange, the conditions under which feudal society produced and exchanged&amp;nbsp;... the feudal relations of property became no longer compatible with the already developed productive forces; they became so many fetters. They had to be burst asunder; they were burst asunder. Into their place stepped free competition, accompanied by a social and political constitution adapted in it, and the economic and political sway of the bourgeois class. A similar movement is going on before our own eyes&amp;nbsp;... The productive forces at the disposal of society no longer tend to further the development of the conditions of bourgeois property; on the contrary, they have become too powerful for these conditions, by which they are fettered, and so soon as they overcome these fetters, they bring order into the whole of bourgeois society, endanger the existence of bourgeois property.&lt;ref name=manifesto/&gt;}}

Marx believed that those structural contradictions within capitalism necessitate its end, giving way to socialism, or a post-capitalistic, communist society:
{{quote|The development of Modern Industry, therefore, cuts from under its feet the very foundation on which the bourgeoisie produces and appropriates products. What the bourgeoisie, therefore, produces, above all, are its own grave-diggers. Its fall and the victory of the proletariat are equally inevitable.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;manifesto&quot;/&gt;}}

Thanks to various processes overseen by capitalism, such as urbanisation, the working class, the proletariat, should grow in numbers and develop [[class consciousness]], in time realising that they have to and can change the system.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-20-23&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Clark1998&quot;/&gt; Marx believed that if the proletariat were to seize the means of production, they would encourage social relations that would benefit everyone equally, abolishing exploiting class, and introduce a system of production less vulnerable to cyclical crises.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-20-23&quot;/&gt; Marx argued in ''[[The German Ideology]]'' that capitalism will end through the organised actions of an international working class:

{{quote|Communism is for us not a state of affairs which is to be established, an ideal to which reality will have to adjust itself. We call communism the real movement which abolishes the present state of things. The conditions of this movement result from the premises now in existence.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Elster1985&quot;/&gt;}}

In this new society the self-alienation would end, and humans would be free to act without being bound by the labour market.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-23&quot;/&gt; It would be a [[democratic]] society, enfranchising the entire population.&lt;ref name=&quot;Clark1998&quot;/&gt; In such a [[utopia]]n world there would also be little if any need for a state, which goal was to enforce the alienation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-23&quot;/&gt; He theorised that between capitalism and the establishment of a socialist/communist system, a [[dictatorship of the proletariat]]—a period where the working class holds political power and forcibly socialises the means of production—would exist.&lt;ref name=&quot;Clark1998&quot;/&gt; As he wrote in his &quot;[[Critique of the Gotha Program]]&quot;, &quot;between capitalist and [[communist society]] there lies the period of the revolutionary transformation of the one into the other. Corresponding to this is also a political transition period in which the state can be nothing but the revolutionary [[dictatorship of the proletariat]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Karl Marx:Critique of the Gotha Programme&quot;/&gt; While he allowed for the possibility of peaceful transition in some countries with strong [[democratic]] institutional structures (such as Britain, the US and the Netherlands), he suggested that in other countries with strong centralised state-oriented traditions, like France and Germany, the &quot;lever of our revolution must be force.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;You know that the institutions, mores, and traditions of various countries must be taken into consideration, and we do not deny that there are countries – such as America, England, and if I were more familiar with your institutions, I would perhaps also add Holland – where the workers can attain their goal by peaceful means. This being the case, we must also recognise the fact that in most countries on the Continent the lever of our revolution must be force; it is force to which we must some day appeal to erect the rule of labour.&quot; [http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1872/09/08.htm La Liberté Speech] delivered by Karl Marx on 8 September 1872, in Amsterdam&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
===Influence===
[[File:Marx-Engels-Forum01.jpg|thumb|Karl Marx and Friedrich Engels monument in [[Marx-Engels-Forum]], [[Berlin-Mitte]]]]
Marx is widely considered one of the most influential thinkers in history, who has had a significant influence on both world politics and intellectual thought.&lt;ref name=&quot;The 100: A Ranking of the Most Influential Persons in History&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-23-24&quot;/&gt; [[BBC]] polls have consistently found Marx considered as the top &quot;thinker of the millennium.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Manchester&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wheen, Francis (17 July 2005). [http://observer.guardian.co.uk/comment/story/0,6903,1530250,00.html &quot;Why Marx is man of the moment&quot;]. ''[[The Observer]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Robert C. Tucker]] credits Marx with profoundly affecting ideas about history, society, economics, culture, politics, and the nature of social inquiry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Allan2010&quot;/&gt; Marx's biographer [[Francis Wheen]] considers the &quot;history of the twentieth century&quot; to be &quot;Marx's legacy&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. p. 01.&lt;/ref&gt; whilst philosopher [[Peter Singer]] believes that Marx's impact can be compared with that of [[Jesus Christ]] and [[Muhammad]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Singer 1980. p. 01&quot;/&gt; Singer notes that &quot;Marx's ideas brought about modern sociology, transformed the study of history, and profoundly affected philosophy, literature and the arts.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Singer 1980. p. 01&quot;/&gt; [[Paul Ricœur]] calls Marx one of the masters of the &quot;school of suspicion&quot;, alongside [[Friedrich Nietzsche]] and [[Sigmund Freud]].&lt;ref&gt;Ricoeur, Paul. ''Freud and Philosophy: An Essay on Interpretation''. New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1970, p. 32&lt;/ref&gt; [[Karl Löwith]] considered Marx and [[Søren Kierkegaard]] to be the two greatest Hegelian philosophical successors.&lt;ref&gt;Löwith, Karl. ''From Hegel to Nietzsche''. New York: Columbia University Press, 1991, p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Erich Fromm]] identifies Marx, together with Freud and [[Albert Einstein]], as the &quot;architects of the modern age&quot;, but rejects the idea that Marx and Freud were equally significant, emphasizing that he sees Marx as both far more historically important than Freud and a finer thinker.&lt;ref&gt;Fromm, Erich. ''Beyond the Chains of Illusion: My Encounter with Marx &amp; Freud''. London: Sphere Books, 1980, p. 11&lt;/ref&gt; Philip Stokes says that Marx's ideas led to him becoming &quot;the darling of both European and American intellectuals up until the 1960s&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Sto04|Stokes 2004]]. p. 133.&lt;/ref&gt; Marx has influenced disciplines such as [[Marxist archaeology|archaeology]], [[anthropology]],&lt;ref&gt;Bridget O'Laughlin (1975) ''Marxist Approaches in Anthropology'', ''Annual Review of Anthropology'' Vol. 4: pp. 341–70 (October 1975) {{doi|10.1146/annurev.an.04.100175.002013}}.&lt;br /&gt;William Roseberry (1997) ''Marx and Anthropology'' Annual Review of Anthropology, Vol. 26: pp. 25–46 (October 1997) {{doi|10.1146/annurev.anthro.26.1.25}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[media studies]],&lt;ref&gt;S. L. Becker (1984) &quot;Marxist Approaches to Media Studies: The British Experience&quot;, ''Critical Studies in Mass Communication'', 1(1): pp. 66–80.&lt;/ref&gt; [[political science]], theater, history, [[sociological theory]], [[cultural studies]], education, [[Marxian economics|economics]], [[Marxist geography|geography]], [[literary criticism]], [[aesthetics]], [[critical psychology]], and [[philosophy]].&lt;ref&gt;See [[Manuel Alvarado]], Robin Gutch, and Tana Wollen (1987) ''Learning the Media: Introduction to Media Teaching'', Palgrave Macmillan.&lt;/ref&gt;

The reasons for Marx's widespread influence revolve around his [[ethics|ethical]] message: with its &quot;morally empowering language of critique&quot; against the dominant capitalist society, no other body of work was so relevant to modern times and simultaneously so outspoken about the need for change.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-23-24&quot;/&gt;

===Marxism===
{{main|Marxism}}
[[File:Karl-Marx-Monument in Chemnitz.jpg|thumb|A Karl Marx monument in the German city [[Chemnitz]], formerly the [[East Germany|East German]] city ''Karl-Marx-Stadt'' (Karl Marx City)]]

Followers of Marx have drawn on his work to propose grand, cohesive theoretical outlooks dubbed &quot;[[Marxism]]&quot;. This body of works has had significant influence on both politics and science.&lt;ref name=&quot;AndersenKaspersen2000&quot;/&gt; Nevertheless, Marxists have frequently debated amongst themselves over how to interpret Marx's writings and apply his concepts to the modern world.&lt;ref name=&quot;AndersenKaspersen2000&quot;/&gt; The legacy of Marx's thought has become contested between numerous tendencies, each of which sees itself as Marx's most accurate interpreter. These tendencies include [[Leninism]], [[Stalinism]], [[Trotskyism]], [[Maoism]], [[Luxemburgism]], and [[libertarian Marxism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;AndersenKaspersen2000&quot;/&gt; Various currents have also developed in [[academic Marxism]], often under influence of other views, resulting in [[structuralist Marxism]], historical Marxism, phenomenological Marxism, [[Analytical Marxism]] and Hegelian Marxism.&lt;ref name=&quot;AndersenKaspersen2000&quot;/&gt; The Marxist revolutionary [[Che Guevara]] summed up his own appeal to Marxism by stating that Marx produced &quot;a qualitative change in the history of social thought. He interprets history, understands its dynamic, predicts the future, but in addition to predicting it, he expresses a revolutionary concept: the world must not only be interpreted, it must be transformed.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marxists.org/archive/guevara/1960/10/08.htm &quot;Notes for the Study of the Ideology of the Cuban Revolution&quot;] by Che Guevara, 8 October 1960&lt;/ref&gt;

The German philosopher [[Ernst Bloch]] attempted to reveal what he considered the hidden metaphysical meaning of Marx's thought, which [[Leszek Kołakowski]] summarizes as, &quot;a picture of the world tending towards a universal synthesis of all forces and factors, not only social phenomena but the cosmos as a whole.&quot; Kołakowski credits Bloch with helping to reveal the neo-Platonic roots of Marxism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kołakowski&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Kołakowski, Leszek |title=Main Currents of Marxism Volume 3: The Breakdown |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Oxford |year=1985 |pages=420, 448 |isbn=0-19-285109-8 |oclc= |doi= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There is a distinction between &quot;Marxism&quot; and &quot;what Marx believed&quot;; for example, shortly before he died in 1883, Marx wrote a letter to the French workers' leader [[Jules Guesde]], and to his own son-in-law [[Paul Lafargue]], accusing them of &quot;revolutionary phrase-mongering&quot; and of lack of faith in the working class. After the French party split into a reformist and revolutionary party, some accused Guesde (leader of the latter) of taking orders from Marx; Marx remarked to Lafargue, &quot;What is certain to me is [that, if this is Marxism, then] I myself am not [a] Marxist&quot; (in a letter to Engels, Marx later accused Guesde of being a &quot;Bakuninist&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;McLellan 1973, p. 443&lt;/ref&gt;

===Founder of social science===
Marx is typically cited, along with [[Émile Durkheim]] and [[Max Weber]], as one of the three principal architects of modern [[social science]].&lt;ref name=&quot;plato.stanford.edu&quot;/&gt; In contrast to [[philosopher]]s, Marx offered theories that could often be tested with the [[scientific method]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-23-24&quot;/&gt; Both Marx and [[Auguste Comte]] set out to develop scientifically justified ideologies in the wake of European [[secularisation]] and new developments in the [[philosophy of history|philosophies of history]] and science. Whilst Marx, working in the Hegelian tradition, rejected Comtean [[sociological positivism]], in attempting to develop a ''science of society'' he nevertheless came to be recognised as a founder of [[sociology]] as the word gained wider meaning.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-19&quot;/&gt; In modern [[sociological theory]], [[Marxist sociology]] is recognised as one of the main classical perspectives. [[Isaiah Berlin]] considers Marx the true founder of modern sociology, &quot;in so far as anyone can claim the title.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Berlin, Isaiah. 1967. ''Karl Marx: His Life and Environment''. Time Inc Book Division, New York. pp130&lt;/ref&gt;

===Debate over predictions and theories===
Marx is often criticised for expecting a wave of socialist revolutions, originating in the most highly industrialised countries,&lt;ref name=&quot;LaFleur2003&quot;/&gt; to overturn capitalism. However others, pointing to Marx's encounter with late 19th-century Russian populism and Marx and Engels's preface to the second Russian edition of the ''Manifesto of the Communist Party'' (1882), have argued that Marx evinced a growing conviction in his late writings that revolution might emerge first in Russia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Marx's Ecology: Materialism and Nature&quot;/&gt; Marx predicted socialism would eventually replace capitalism. It has been argued that this was incorrect, as since the late 20th century state socialism (which some historians link to Marx) is in retreat, after the [[Dissolution of the Soviet Union|collapse of the Soviet Union]] and the shift towards a [[socialist market economy|market economy]] by the [[People's Republic of China]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Rondinelli1995&quot;/&gt; Marx actually wrote, however, that socialist revolutions held in countries that were not yet capitalist would only act to bring capitalism to the country: not socialism.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.marxists.org/archive/martov/1918/xx/marxdp.htm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1847/10/31.htm&lt;/ref&gt; China and Russia were both feudal (and hence pre-capitalist) at the time of their revolution, so this prediction has actually so far been accurate. Marx's argument that profits are generated only through [[surplus labour]] has been challenged by the counterclaim that profits also come from investments in [[human capital]] and technology.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-23-24&quot;/&gt; Marx correctly predicted that over time, inequality would grow&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.economist.com/node/17957381 Unbottled Gini: Inequality is rising. Does it matter—and if so why?], [[The Economist]], 20 January 2001&lt;/ref&gt; but he also believed that this would mean growing impoverishment of the growing worker class, increasingly exploited by the capitalists.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-23-24&quot;/&gt; The latter has also come true; as in the developed world, through liberal reforms, [[trade unions]] won many concessions, improving the situation of the workers (something that Marx considered very unlikely); in the more populated parts of the world such as Africa, India, and China the populations continue to grow and all the industry is moving there if it has not already established itself in the last two decades. Worldwide poverty has increased since the end of the 19th century especially considering that the richest are richer than ever but the poor have remained at the same level and the percentage has risen in the last 30 years.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-23-24&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Chen, Shaohua; Ravallion, Martin, [http://econ.worldbank.org/external/default/main?pagePK=64165259&amp;theSitePK=469372&amp;piPK=64165421&amp;menuPK=64166093&amp;entityID=000158349_20100121133109 The developing world is poor and unsuccessful in the fight against poverty], Policy Research working paper, World Bank, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MooreSimon2000&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Whitman2008&quot;/&gt; (Scholars have debated whether Marx's comments about the [[proletariat]] can be analyzed in the context of the working class).&lt;ref&gt;Hugo Radice, The Prospects for Socialism: A Question of Capital and Class. CSGP 11/1 2011, [http://www.trentu.ca/globalpolitics/documents/Radice111.pdf p.7]&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to specific predictions, certain of Marx's theories, such as his [[labour theory of value]], have also been criticised.&lt;ref name=sep/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Sherman1995&quot;/&gt;
However, in the wake of the [[economic crisis of 2008]], [[Greek government debt crisis]], [[2008–2012 Spanish financial crisis]] and [[European sovereign debt crisis]], thinkers such as [[Terry Eagleton]], [[David Harvey (geographer)|David Harvey]], and [[David McNally (professor)|David McNally]] have given renewed impetus to the debate on whether Marx was right that capitalism inherently tends towards crisis (which Marx discussed as the &quot;contradictions of capital&quot;).&lt;ref name=&quot;Was Marx Right?&quot;/&gt;

===Totalitarianism===
[[File:100-Mark-1971.jpg|thumb|100 [[East German Mark|Mark der DDR]] note used in the [[German Democratic Republic]]. 100-Mark banknotes with Marx's portrait circulated from 1964 until [[monetary union]] with West Germany in July 1990.]]

While Marxist thought may be used to empower marginalised and dispossessed people, it has also been used to prop up governments who have utilised violence to remove those seen as impeding the revolution.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-23-24&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Sherman1995&quot;/&gt; In some instances, his ultimate goals have been used as justification for the [[end justifies the means]] logic.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-23-24&quot;/&gt; Moreover, contrary to his goal, his ideas have been used to promote [[dogmatism]] and [[Toleration|intolerance]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-23-24&quot;/&gt; Polish historian [[Andrzej Walicki]] noted that Marx's and Engels's theory was the &quot;theory of freedom&quot;, but a theory that, at the height of its influence, was used to legitimise the [[totalitarian]] socialist state of the [[Soviet Union]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Walicki1997-1&quot;/&gt; This abuse of Marx's thought is perhaps most clearly exemplified in [[Stalinist]] Marxism, described by critics as the &quot;most widespread and successful form of mass indoctrination... a masterly achievement in transforming Marxism into the official ideology of a consistently totalitarian state.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Walicki1997-426&quot;/&gt; Some left-wing theorists have tried to shield Marxism from any connection to the Soviet regime.&lt;ref name=&quot;Walicki1997&quot;/&gt; Lastly, the undue focus on the Marxist thought in the former [[Eastern Bloc]], often forbidding social science arguments from outside the Marxist perspective,&lt;ref name=&quot;Topolski1994&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ferro&quot;/&gt; led to a backlash against Marxism after the [[revolutions of 1989]]. In one example, references to Marx drastically decreased in [[Polish sociology]] after the fall of the revolutionary socialist governments, and two major research institutions which advocated the Marxist approach to sociology were closed.&lt;ref name=&quot;MuchaZałecki&quot;&gt;Janusz Mucha and Paweł Załęcki, [http://replay.waybackmachine.org/20081204114441/http://www.cee-socialscience.net/archive/sociology/poland/report1.html Sociology – Poland], Social Science Knowledge Base, Country Reports, [http://replay.waybackmachine.org/20081204112106/http://www.cee-socialscience.net/archive/sociology/poland/report1_review1.html commentary]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Selected bibliography==

* ''[[The Philosophical Manifesto of the Historical School of Law]]'' (1842)
* ''[[Critique of Hegel's Philosophy of Right]]'', 1843
* ''[[On the Jewish Question]]'', 1843
* ''[[Notes on James Mill]]'', 1844
* ''[[Economic and Philosophic Manuscripts of 1844]]'', 1844
* ''[[The Holy Family (book)|The Holy Family]]'', 1845
* ''[[Theses on Feuerbach]]'', 1845
* ''[[The German Ideology]]'', 1845
* ''[[The Poverty of Philosophy]]'', 1847
* ''[[Wage Labour and Capital]]'', 1847
* ''[[The Communist Manifesto|Manifesto of the Communist Party]]'', 1848
* ''[[The Class Struggles in France]]'', 1850
* ''[[The Eighteenth Brumaire of Louis Napoleon]]'', 1852
* ''[[Grundrisse]]'', 1857
* ''[[A Contribution to the Critique of Political Economy]]'', 1859
* ''[[Writings on the U.S. Civil War]]'', 1861
* ''[[Theories of Surplus Value]]'', 3 volumes, 1862
* ''[[Value, Price and Profit]]'', 1865
* [[Capital, Volume I|''Capital'', Volume&amp;nbsp;I]] (''Das Kapital''), 1867
* ''[[The Civil War in France]]'', 1871
* ''[[Critique of the Gotha Program]]'', 1875
* ''Notes on Wagner'', 1883
* [[Capital, Volume II|''Capital'', Volume&amp;nbsp;II]] (posthumously published by Engels), 1885
* [[Capital, Volume III|''Capital'', Volume&amp;nbsp;III]] (posthumously published by Engels), 1894

==See also==
* [[Karl Marx House]]
* [[Marx Memorial Library]]
* [[Marx’s method]]
* [[Marx's notebooks on the history of technology]]
* [[Marxian Class Theory]]
* [[Mathematical manuscripts of Karl Marx]]
* [[Pre-Marx socialists]]
* [[Karl Marx in film]]
* ''[[Marx Reloaded]]''

==References==
===Footnotes===
{{reflist|30em|refs=

&lt;ref name=&quot;1883: The death of Karl Marx&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1883/death/dersoz1.htm |title=1883: The death of Karl Marx |publisher=Marxists.org |date= |accessdate=21 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;AS&quot;&gt;{{Cite book | last = Appelrouth | first = Scott | coauthor = Laura Desfor Edles | title = Classical and Contemporary Sociological Theory: Text and Readings | page = 23 | publisher=Pine Forge Press | year = 2007 | isbn = 978-0-7619-2793-8 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Allan2010&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Kenneth Allan|title=The Social Lens: An Invitation to Social and Sociological Theory|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=KEgg5g0d-fgC&amp;pg=PA68|accessdate=25 March 2011|date=11 May 2010|publisher=Pine Forge Press|isbn=978-1-4129-7834-7|page=68}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;AllanAllan2005-68&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author1=Kenneth Allan|author2=Kenneth D. Allan|title=Explorations in Classical Sociological Theory: Seeing the Social World|date=2 November 2005|publisher=Pine Forge Press|isbn=978-1-4129-0572-5|page=68}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;AndersenKaspersen2000&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author1=Heine Andersen|author2=Lars Bo Kaspersen|title=Classical and modern social theory|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=_PeGtsC2Hp4C&amp;pg=PA123|accessdate=9 March 2011|year=2000|publisher=Wiley-Blackwell|isbn=978-0-631-21288-1|pages=123–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Balibar1995&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Étienne Balibar|title=The philosophy of Marx|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=HBw-U1tSZoMC&amp;pg=PA56|accessdate=8 March 2011|year=1995|publisher=Verso|isbn=978-1-85984-951-4|page=56}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Bannerji2001&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Himani Bannerji|title=Inventing subjects: studies in hegemony, patriarchy and colonialism|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=rQqos58kEPwC&amp;pg=PA27|accessdate=2 May 2011|year=2001|publisher=Anthem Press|isbn=978-1-84331-072-3|page=27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Beilharz1992&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Peter Beilharz|title=Labour's Utopias: Bolshevism, Fabianism and Social Democracy|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=dJc9AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA4|accessdate=7 March 2011|year=1992|publisher=CUP Archive|isbn=978-0-415-09680-5|page=4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Bottomore1991&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=T. B. Bottomore|title=A Dictionary of Marxist thought|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=q4QwNP_K1pYC&amp;pg=PA108|accessdate=5 March 2011|year=1991|publisher=Wiley-Blackwell|isbn=978-0-631-18082-1|pages=108–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;BrewerMarx1984-15&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author1=Anthony Brewer|author2=Karl Marx|title=A guide to Marx's Capital|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=RyQ4AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA15|accessdate=9 March 2011|year=1984|publisher=CUP Archive|isbn=978-0-521-25730-5|page=15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;CGP P1&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |last=Marx |first=Karl |authorlink=Karl Marx |title=[[Critique of the Gotha Program]] |year=1875 |accessdate=15 July 2008 |chapter=Part I |chapterurl=http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1875/gotha/ch01.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-19&quot;&gt;[[#Cal02|Calhoun 2002]]. [http://books.google.com/books?id=6mq-H3EcUx8C&amp;pg=PA19 p. 19].&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-20&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Craig J. Calhoun|title=Classical sociological theory|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=6mq-H3EcUx8C&amp;pg=PA20|accessdate=5 March 2011|year=2002|publisher=Wiley-Blackwell|isbn=978-0-631-21348-2|page=20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-20-23&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Craig J. Calhoun|title=Classical sociological theory|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=6mq-H3EcUx8C&amp;pg=PA20|accessdate=5 March 2011|year=2002|publisher=Wiley-Blackwell|isbn=978-0-631-21348-2|pages=20–23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-22&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Craig J. Calhoun|title=Classical sociological theory|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=6mq-H3EcUx8C&amp;pg=PA22|accessdate=5 March 2011|year=2002|publisher=Wiley-Blackwell|isbn=978-0-631-21348-2|page=22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-23&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Craig J. Calhoun|title=Classical sociological theory|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=6mq-H3EcUx8C&amp;pg=PA23|accessdate=5 March 2011|year=2002|publisher=Wiley-Blackwell|isbn=978-0-631-21348-2|page=23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Calhoun2002-23-24&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Craig J. Calhoun|title=Classical sociological theory|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=6mq-H3EcUx8C&amp;pg=PA23|accessdate=5 March 2011|year=2002|publisher=Wiley-Blackwell|isbn=978-0-631-21348-2|pages=23–24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;CapperGiorcelli2007&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author1=Charles Capper|author2=Cristina Giorcelli|author3=Lester K. Little|title=Margaret Fuller: transatlantic crossings in a revolutionary age|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=LehjT5N5yQwC&amp;pg=PA18|accessdate=5 March 2011|date=9 November 2007|publisher=Univ of Wisconsin Press|isbn=978-0-299-22340-3|page=18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Clark1998&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Barry Stewart Clark|title=Political economy: a comparative approach|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=3bJHvA1H-2kC&amp;pg=PA57|accessdate=7 March 2011|year=1998|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=978-0-275-96370-5|pages=57–59}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Curtis1997&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Michael Curtis|title=Marxism: the inner dialogues|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=hRdyY2f8UcUC&amp;pg=PA291|accessdate=9 March 2011|year=1997|publisher=Transaction Publishers|isbn=978-1-56000-945-0|page=291}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;DL-Marx&quot;&gt;Doug Lorimer. Introduction. In {{Cite book|author=Karl Marx|title=The Class Struggles in France: From the February Revolution to the Paris Commune|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=xlYfFDJDXewC&amp;pg=PA6|accessdate=9 March 2011|publisher=Resistance Books|isbn=978-1-876646-19-6|page=6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Dispatches for the New York Tribune: Selected Journalism of Karl Marx&quot;&gt;{{Cite book  | last = Karl  | first = Marx  | editor = James Ledbetter  | title = Dispatches for the New York Tribune: Selected Journalism of Karl Marx  | publisher=[[Penguin Books]]  | year = 2007  | isbn = 978-0-14-144192-4}} &lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;DusselMoseley2001&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author1=Enrique D. Dussel|author2=Fred Moseley|title=Towards an unknown Marx: a commentary on the manuscripts of 1861–63|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=-Ld9fM0DOYQC&amp;pg=PR33|accessdate=9 March 2011|year=2001|publisher=Psychology Press|isbn=978-0-415-21545-9|pages=33–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Elster1985&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Jon Elster|title=Making sense of Marx|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=I14p3dFLerYC&amp;pg=PA217|accessdate=23 April 2011|date=31 May 1985|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-0-521-29705-9|page=217}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Engels1999&quot;&gt;Doug Lorimer, in {{Cite book|author=Friedrich Engels|title=Socialism: utopian and scientific|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=_A7P0fL_kYsC&amp;pg=PA34|accessdate=7 March 2011|year=1999|publisher=Resistance Books|isbn=978-0-909196-86-8|pages=34–36}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Ferro&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Marc Ferro|title=The use and abuse of history, or, How the past is taught to children|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=XS1hcDeSne0C&amp;pg|accessdate=5 March 2011|year=2003|publisher=Psychology Press|isbn=978-0-415-28592-6|pages=}} See [http://books.google.com/books?id=XS1hcDeSne0C&amp;pg=PA157 Chapter 8 ''Aspects and variations of Soviet history''] and [http://books.google.com/books?id=XS1hcDeSne0C&amp;pg=PA235 Chapter 10 ''History in profile: Poland''].&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;FeuerHorowitz2010&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author1=Lewis S. Feuer|author2=Irving Horowitz|title=Ideology and the Ideologists|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=8TwfWRr21zEC&amp;pg=PA76|accessdate=5 March 2011|date=1 June 2010|publisher=Transaction Publishers|isbn=978-1-4128-1442-3|page=76}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;GeorgeScanlan1975&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author1=Richard T. De George|author2=James Patrick Scanlan|title=Marxism and religion in Eastern Europe: papers presented at the Banff International Slavic Conference, September&amp;nbsp;4–7, 1974|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=gO_mQQU8-GIC&amp;pg=PA20|accessdate=16 March 2011|date=31 December 1975|publisher=Springer|isbn=978-90-277-0636-2|page=20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Gilbert2010&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Dennis Gilbert|title=The American Class Structure in an Age of Growing Inequality|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=4JyQus8r9JYC&amp;pg=PA6|accessdate=8 March 2011|date=13 May 2010|publisher=Pine Forge Press|isbn=978-1-4129-7965-8|pages=6–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;GouldMcGarr2007&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author1=Stephen Jay Gould|author2=Paul McGarr|author3=Steven Peter Russell Rose|title=The richness of life: the essential Stephen Jay Gould|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=yfXJhKmp1wUC&amp;pg=PA167|accessdate=9 March 2011|date=24 April 2007|publisher=W. W. Norton &amp; Company|isbn=978-0-393-06498-8|pages=167–168}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Harriss2006&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Phil Harriss|title=London Markets, 4th|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=zv6GxJzhrbgC&amp;pg=PA20|accessdate=23 April 2011|date=1 September 2006|publisher=New Holland Publishers|isbn=978-1-86011-306-2|page=20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Hernadi1989&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Paul Hernadi|title=The Rhetoric of interpretation and the interpretation of rhetoric|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=yNGAg_yK6R4C&amp;pg=PA137|accessdate=8 March 2011|year=1989|publisher=Duke University Press|isbn=978-0-8223-0934-5|page=137}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Hook1994&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Sidney Hook|title=From Hegel to Marx: studies in the intellectual development of Karl Marx|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=JXQ_cwiMhAUC&amp;pg=PR24|accessdate=16 March 2011|date=February 1994|publisher=Columbia University Press|isbn=978-0-231-09665-2|pages=24–25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Hunt2010&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Tristram Hunt|title=Marx's General: The Revolutionary Life of Friedrich Engels|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Mdj3AXU2YEEC&amp;pg=PA59|accessdate=9 March 2011|date=3 August 2010|publisher=Macmillan|isbn=978-0-8050-9248-6|pages=59–61}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Hyman1974&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Stanley Edgar Hyman|title=The tangled bank: Darwin, Marx, Frazer and Freud as imaginative writers|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=f0pmAAAAMAAJ|accessdate=6 March 2011|date=March 1974|publisher=Atheneum|page=86}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;JessopWheatley1999-526&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author1=Bob Jessop|author2=Russell Wheatley|title=Karl Marx's social and political thought|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=vz-4LDWCnlAC&amp;pg=PA526|accessdate=9 March 2011|year=1999|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis US|isbn=978-0-415-19327-6|page=526}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Johnston2000&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Ronald John Johnston|title=The dictionary of human geography|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=0-GxowMfwlkC&amp;pg=PA795%7Caccessdate%3D16+March+2011%7Cyear%3D2000%7Cpublisher%3DWiley-Blackwell%7Cisbn%3D978-0-631-20561-6%7Cpages%3D795%E2%80%93%7D%7D%3C%2Fref%3E|accessdate=16 March 2011|year=2000|publisher=Wiley-Blackwell|isbn=978-0-631-20561-6|page=795}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Karl Marx&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Francis Wheen|title=Karl Marx|publisher=W. W. Norton and Company|year=2000|page=173}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Karl Marx:Critique of the Gotha Programme&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1875/gotha/ch04.htm|title=Karl Marx:Critique of the Gotha Programme}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;LaFleur2003&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Robert André LaFleur|title=China: a global studies handbook|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=RKwqnbWf3u0C&amp;pg=PT137|accessdate=5 March 2011|year=2003|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=978-1-57607-284-4|pages=137–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;MaltsevN.-93&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author1=Maltsev|author2=Yuri N.|title=Requiem for Marx|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=gx0X4NvNE_gC&amp;pg=PA93|accessdate=9 March 2011|publisher=Ludwig von Mises Institute|isbn=978-1-61016-116-9|pages=93–94}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Manchester&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/461545.stm|title=Marx the millennium's 'greatest thinker' |publisher=BBC News World Online |date=1 October 1999 | accessdate=23 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Marx's Ecology: Materialism and Nature&quot;&gt; *{{cite book|last=Foster|first=John|title=Marx's Ecology: Materialism and Nature|year=2000|publisher=Monthly Review Press|location=New York|pages=165, 221}} *{{cite book|title=Late Marx and the Russian road : Marx and &quot;the peripheries of capitalism&quot; : a case|year=1983|publisher=Monthly Review Press|location=New York|editor=Shanin, Teodor}} *{{cite web|last=Rosemont|first=Franklin|title=Karl Marx and the Iroquois|url=http://libcom.org/library/karl-marx-iroquois-franklin-rosemont|accessdate=13 June 2011}} *{{cite book|last=Marx|first=Karl|title=The Marx-Engels Reader|year=1978|publisher=W.W. Norton &amp; Company|location=New York|pages=471–2|coauthors=Engels, Friedrich|editor=Tucker, Robert C.}} &lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Marx2008&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Karl Marx|title=The 18th Brumaire of Louis Bonaparte|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ryOVzGSq0zYC&amp;pg=PA141|accessdate=9 March 2011|date=30 March 2008|publisher=Wildside Press LLC|isbn=978-1-4344-6374-6|page=141}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;MarxO'Malley1977&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=Karl Marx|author2=Joseph O'Malley|title=Critique of Hegel's 'Philosophy of right'|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=uxg4AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA131|accessdate=23 April 2011|date=26 August 1977|publisher=CUP Archive|isbn=978-0-521-29211-5|page=131}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Mehring2003&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Franz Mehring|title=Karl Marx: The Story of His Life|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=486z9lE-jdsC&amp;pg=PR19|accessdate=9 March 2011|date=24 September 2003|publisher=Psychology Press|isbn=978-0-415-31333-9|pages=19–20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;MooreSimon2000&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author1=Stephen Moore|author2=Julian Lincoln Simon|title=It's getting better all the time: 100 greatest trends of the last 100 years|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=1ixRxAsdLKwC&amp;pg=PA8|accessdate=5 March 2011|year=2000|publisher=Cato Institute|isbn=978-1-882577-96-5|page=8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Morrison2006&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Kenneth L. Morrison|title=Marx, Durkheim, Weber: formations of modern social thought|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=-sya6fxO6zgC&amp;pg=PA35|accessdate=5 March 2011|date=21 July 2006|publisher=SAGE|isbn=978-0-7619-7056-9|page=35}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Mészáros2006&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=István Mészáros|title=Marx's Theory of Alienation|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=5lckAQAAIAAJ|accessdate=8 March 2011|date=1 March 2006|publisher=Merlin Press|isbn=978-0-85036-554-2|page=96}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Nicolaievsky2007&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Boris Nicolaievsky|title=Karl Marx – Man and Fighter|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=4rbH49xtcpkC&amp;pg=PA192|accessdate=9 March 2011|date=15 March 2007|publisher=READ BOOKS|isbn=978-1-4067-2703-6|pages=192–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Nicolaievsky2007&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Boris Nicolaievsky|title=Karl Marx – Man and Fighter|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=4rbH49xtcpkC&amp;pg=PA261|accessdate=9 March 2011|date=15 March 2007|publisher=READ BOOKS|isbn=978-1-4067-2703-6|pages=261–266}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Nicolaievsky2007-267&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Boris Nicolaievsky|title=Karl Marx – Man and Fighter|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=4rbH49xtcpkC&amp;pg=PA269|accessdate=9 March 2011|date=15 March 2007|publisher=READ BOOKS|isbn=978-1-4067-2703-6|pages=269–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Ollman1973&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Bertell Ollman|title=Alienation: Marx's conception of man in capitalist society|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=8Ac4AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA81|accessdate=8 March 2011|year=1973|publisher=CUP Archive|isbn=978-1-00-133135-5|page=81}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. pp. 126–127.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. pp. 136–137.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Rockmore2002&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Tom Rockmore|title=Marx after Marxism: the philosophy of Karl Marx|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=FkMgeGZuCOwC&amp;pg=PA128|accessdate=9 March 2011|year=2002|publisher=John Wiley and Sons|isbn=978-0-631-23189-9|page=128}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Rondinelli1995&quot;&gt;Shang-Jin Wei. From Marx to Markets: China's Economic Reforms as a Megapolicy. In {{Cite book|author=Dennis A. Rondinelli|title=Great policies: strategic innovations in Asia and the Pacific Basin|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=31HHS8S6svkC&amp;pg=PA151|accessdate=5 March 2011|year=1995|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|isbn=978-0-275-95050-7|page=151}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Segrest2002&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Mab Segrest|title=Born to belonging: writings on spirit and justice|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=gOmpSMh3y3YC&amp;pg=PA232|accessdate=9 March 2011|date=27 June 2002|publisher=Rutgers University Press|isbn=978-0-8135-3101-4|page=232}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Sherman1995&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Howard J. Sherman|title=Reinventing marxism|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=TTZf31HIJKsC&amp;pg=PA5|accessdate=7 March 2011|year=1995|publisher=JHU Press|isbn=978-0-8018-5077-6|page=5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Singer 1980. p. 01&quot;&gt;[[#Sin80|Singer 1980]]. p. 01.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Splichal2002&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Slavko Splichal|title=Principles of publicity and press freedom|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=u8fO_b0lxDAC&amp;pg=PA115|accessdate=9 March 2011|year=2002|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield|isbn=978-0-7425-1615-1|page=115}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;SwatosKivisto1998&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author1=William H. Swatos|author2=Peter Kivisto|title=Encyclopedia of religion and society|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=6TMFoMFe-D8C&amp;pg=PA499|accessdate=8 March 2011|date=28 February 1998|publisher=Rowman Altamira|isbn=978-0-7619-8956-1|pages=499–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;The 100: A Ranking of the Most Influential Persons in History&quot;&gt;{{cite book| last = Hart| first = Michael H.| author-link = Michael H. Hart| year = 2000| title = The 100: A Ranking of the Most Influential Persons in History| publication-place = New York| publisher = Citadel|ref=harv| isbn = 0-89104-175-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson1990&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=John B. Thompson|title=Ideology and modern culture: critical social theory in the era of mass communication|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ql5Ab8OXiPMC&amp;pg=PA37|accessdate=8 March 2011|year=1990|publisher=Stanford University Press|isbn=978-0-8047-1846-2|pages=37–38}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Topolski1994&quot;&gt;Gwidon Zalejko, Soviet Historiography as a &quot;Normal Science&quot; in {{Cite book|author=Jerzy Topolski|title=Historiography between modernism and postmodernism|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=oblFZ28X6oIC&amp;pg=PA179|accessdate=5 March 2011|date=December 1994|publisher=Rodopi|isbn=978-90-5183-744-5|page=179}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Turner2005&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Jonathan H. Turner|title=Sociology|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=90vMAAAACAAJ|accessdate=9 March 2011|date=2 September 2005|publisher=Pearson Prentice Hall|isbn=978-0-13-113496-6|pages=17–18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Walicki1997&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Andrzej Walicki|title=Marxism and the Leap to the Kingdom of Freedom: The Rise and Fall of the Communist Utopia|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=NgZ6vitEjq4C&amp;pg=PA4|accessdate=5 March 2011|date=1 September 1997|publisher=Stanford University Press|isbn=978-0-8047-3164-5|page=4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Walicki1997-1&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Andrzej Walicki|title=Marxism and the Leap to the Kingdom of Freedom: The Rise and Fall of the Communist Utopia|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=NgZ6vitEjq4C&amp;pg=PA1|accessdate=5 March 2011|date=1 September 1997|publisher=Stanford University Press|isbn=978-0-8047-3164-5|page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Walicki1997-426&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Andrzej Walicki|title=Marxism and the Leap to the Kingdom of Freedom: The Rise and Fall of the Communist Utopia|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=NgZ6vitEjq4C&amp;pg=PA426|accessdate=5 March 2011|date=1 September 1997|publisher=Stanford University Press|isbn=978-0-8047-3164-5|page=426}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Was Marx Right?&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Eagleton|first=Terry|title=Was Marx Right?|url=http://commonwealmagazine.org/was-marx-right|work=Commonweal|accessdate=14 July 2011}}; {{cite book|last=Harvey|first=David|title=A Companion to Marx's Capital|year=2010|publisher=Verso|location=London and New York}}; {{cite journal|last=McNally|first=David|title=From Financial Crisis to World-Slump: Accumulation, Financialisation, and the Global Slowdown|journal=Historical Materialism|year=2009|volume=17|pages=35–83|doi=10.1163/156920609X436117|issue=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Watson2010&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Peter Watson|title=The German Genius: Europe's Third Renaissance, the Second Scientific Revolution, and the Twentieth Century|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=lktG_12nBXEC&amp;pg=PA250|accessdate=9 March 2011|date=22 June 2010|publisher=HarperCollins|isbn=978-0-06-076022-9|pages=250–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Wheen 2001. p. 125&quot;&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. p. 125.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Wheen 2001. p. 152&quot;&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. p. 152.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Wheen 2001. p. 90&quot;&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. [http://books.google.com/books?id=3KOyuSakn80C&amp;pg=PA90 p. 90].&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Wheen 2001. p. 90&quot;&gt;[[#Whe00|Wheen 2001]]. p. 90.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Whitman2008&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Sylvia Whitman|title=World poverty|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=fk4QHyTMhQkC&amp;pg=PA3|accessdate=5 March 2011|date=June 2008|publisher=Infobase Publishing|isbn=978-0-8160-6807-4|page=3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Wood&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=John Cunningham Wood|title=Karl Marx's economics : critical assessments|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=0Pr97rppN2EC&amp;pg=PA346|accessdate=16 March 2011|publisher=Psychology Press|isbn=978-0-415-06558-0|page=346}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Wood1993&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=John Cunningham Wood|title=Karl Marx's economics: critical assessments : second series|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=zoNIh_NYeRwC&amp;pg=PA232|accessdate=16 March 2011|year=1993|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|isbn=978-0-415-08711-7|page=232}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Wood1993&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=John Cunningham Wood|title=Karl Marx's economics: critical assessments : second series|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=zoNIh_NYeRwC&amp;pg=PA398%7Caccessdate%3D8+March+2011%7Cyear%3D1993%7Cpublisher%3DTaylor+|accessdate=8 March 2011|year=1993|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|isbn=978-0-415-08711-7|pages=398–400}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;egsbio&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.egs.edu/library/karl-marx/biography/ |title=Karl Heinrich Marx – Biography |publisher=Egs.edu |date= |accessdate=9 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;et&quot;&gt;Several authors elucidated this for long neglected crucial turn in Marx's theoretical development, such as Ernie Thomson in ''The Discovery of the Materialist Conception of History in the Writings of the Young Karl Marx'', New York, The Edwin Mellen Press, 2004; for a short account see [http://www.lsr-projekt.de/poly/eninnuce.html Max Stirner, a durable dissident]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;k72&quot;&gt;Karl Marx and Frederick Engels, ''Collected Works Volume 46'' (International Publishers: New York, 1992) p. 72.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;manifesto&quot;&gt;Marx, K. and Engels, F. (1848).[http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1848/communist-manifesto/index.htm ''The Communist Manifesto'']&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;plato.stanford.edu&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/weber/|title=Max Weber – Stanford Encyclopaedia of Philosophy}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;sep&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/marx/|title=Karl Marx – Stanford Encyclopaedia of Philosophy}}. First published Tue 26 August 2003; substantive revision Mon 14 June 2010. Retrieved 4 March 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;stateless&quot;&gt;McLellan 1973, p.541&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;wh1&quot;&gt;{{Cite book | last = Wheen | first = Francis | authorlink = Francis Wheen | title = Karl Marx: A Life | publisher=New York: Norton |year=2002 | pages = Introduction | nopp = true }} &lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;wk&quot;&gt;{{Cite book | last = Baird | first = Forrest E. | authorlink = | coauthors = Walter Kaufmann | title = From Plato to Derrida | publisher=Pearson Prentice Hall | year = 2008 | location = Upper Saddle River, New Jersey| url = | isbn = 0-13-158591-6 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

===Bibliography===
;Academic and Popular Books
{{refbegin}}
* {{Cite book |title= Classical Sociological Theory |last= {{aut|[[Craig Calhoun|Calhoun, Craig J.]]}} |year= 2002 |publisher=Wiley-Blackwell |location= Oxford |isbn=978-0-631-21347-5 |nopp=|ref=Cal02}}
* {{Cite book |title= The Revolutionary Ideas of Karl Marx |last= {{aut|[[Alex Callinicos|Callinicos, Alex]]}} |year= 2010 [1983] |publisher=Bookmarks |location= Bloomsbury, London |isbn=978-1-905192-68-7 |nopp=|ref=Cal10}}
* {{Cite book |title= How to Change the World: Tales of Marx and Marxism |last= {{aut|[[Eric Hobsbawm|Hobsbawm, Eric]]}} |year= 2011 |publisher=Little, Brown |location= London |isbn=978-1-4087-0287-1 |ref=Hob11}}
* {{Cite book |title= Karl Marx: A Brief Biographical Sketch with an Exposition of Marxism|last= {{aut|[[Vladimir Lenin|Lenin, Vladimir]]}} |year= 1967| origyear=1913|publisher=Foreign Languages Press |location= Peking |ref=Len67|url=http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1914/granat/index.htm}}
* {{Cite book |title= Marx |last= {{aut|[[Peter Singer|Singer, Peter]]}} |year= 1980 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location= Oxford |isbn=978-0-19-287510-5 |nopp=|ref=Sin80}}
* {{Cite book |title= Philosophy: 100 Essential Thinkers |last= {{aut|Stokes, Philip}} |year= 2004 |publisher=Index Books |location= Kettering |isbn=978-0-572-02935-7 |nopp=|ref=Sto04}}
* {{Cite book |title= The Story of a Great Discovery: How Karl Marx wrote &quot;Capital&quot; |last= {{aut|Vygodsky, Vitaly}} |year= 1973 |publisher=Verlag Die Wirtschaft |location= |isbn= |nopp=|ref=Vyg73|url=http://www.marxists.org/archive/vygodsky/1965/discovery.htm}}
* {{Cite book |title= Karl Marx |last= {{aut|[[Francis Wheen|Wheen, Francis]]}} |year= 2001 |publisher=Fourth Estate |location= London |isbn=978-1-85702-637-5 |nopp=|ref=Whe00}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin|30em}}
* [[Althusser, Louis]]. ''For Marx''. London: Verso, 2005.
* Althusser, Louis and [[Balibar, Étienne]]. ''Reading Capital''. London: Verso, 2009.
* [[Shlomo Avineri|Avineri, Shlomo]]. ''The Social and Political Thought of Karl Marx'' (Cambridge University Press, 1968) ISBN 0-521-09619-7
* [[Kostas Axelos|Axelos, Kostas]]. ''Alienation, Praxis, and Techne in the Thought of Karl Marx'' (translated by Ronald Bruzina, University of Texas Press, 1976).
* [[Vincent Barnett|Barnett, Vincent]]. ''Marx'' (Routledge, 2009)
* [[Isaiah Berlin|Berlin, Isaiah]]. ''Karl Marx: His Life and Environment'' (Oxford University Press, 1963) ISBN 0-19-520052-7
* Blackledge, Paul. ''Reflections on the Marxist Theory of History'' (Manchester University Press, 2006)
* Bottomore, Tom, ed. ''A Dictionary of Marxist Thought''. Oxford: Blackwell, 1998.
* [[Alex Callinicos|Callinicos, Alex]]. ''The Revolutionary Ideas of Karl Marx'' (Bookmarks, 1983)
* [[Harry Cleaver|Cleaver, Harry]]. ''Reading Capital Politically'' (AK Press, 2000)
* [[Gerald Cohen|G. A. Cohen]]. ''Karl Marx's Theory of History: A Defence'' (Princeton University Press, 1978) ISBN 0-691-07068-7
* Collier, Andrew. ''Marx'' (Oneworld, 2004)
* [[Hal Draper|Draper, Hal]], ''Karl Marx's Theory of Revolution'' (4 volumes) [[Monthly Review|Monthly Review Press]]
* Duncan, Ronald and [[Colin Wilson|Wilson, Colin]]. (editors) ''Marx Refuted'', (Bath, UK, 1987) ISBN 0-906798-71-X
* [[Ben Fine|Fine, Ben]]. ''Marx's Capital.'' 5th ed. London: Pluto, 2010.
* [[John Bellamy Foster|Foster, John Bellamy]]. ''Marx's Ecology: Materialism and Nature''. New York: Monthly Review Press, 2000.
* [[Stephen Jay Gould|Gould, Stephen Jay]]. ''[http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1134/is_7_108/ai_55698600/pg_1 A Darwinian Gentleman at Marx's Funeral – E. Ray Lankester]'', Page 1, [http://www.findarticles.com/ Find Articles.com] (1999)
* [[David Harvey (geographer)|Harvey, David]]. ''A Companion to Marx's Capital.'' London: Verso, 2010.
* Harvey, David. ''The Limits of Capital''. London: Verso, 2006.
* Iggers, Georg G. &quot;Historiography: From Scientific Objectivity to the Postmodern Challenge.&quot;(Wesleyan University Press, 1997, 2005)
* [[Leszek Kołakowski|Kołakowski, Leszek]]. ''Main Currents of Marxism'' Oxford: Clarendon Press, OUP, 1978
* Little, Daniel. ''The Scientific Marx'', (University of Minnesota Press, 1986) ISBN 0-8166-1505-5
* [[Ernest Mandel|Mandel, Ernest]]. ''Marxist Economic Theory''. New York: Monthly Review Press, 1970.
* Mandel, Ernest. ''The Formation of the Economic Thought of Karl Marx''. New York: Monthly Review Press, 1977.
* [[David McLellan (academic)|McLellan, David]]. ''Marx before Marxism'' (1980), Macmillan, ISBN 978-0-333-27882-6
* McLellan, David. ''Karl Marx: his Life and Thought'' Harper &amp; Row, 1973 ISBN 978-0-06-012829-6
* [[Franz Mehring|Mehring, Franz]]. ''Karl Marx: The Story of His Life'' (Routledge, 2003)
* Miller, Richard W. ''Analyzing Marx: Morality, Power, and History''. Princeton, N.J: Princeton University Press, 1984.
* [[Boris Nicolaevsky|Nicolaevsky, Boris]] and [[Otto Maenchen-Helfen|Maenchen-Helfen, Otto]] (translator). ''Karl Marx: Man and Fighter'' (Penguin Books, 1976) ISBN 0-14-021594-8
* [[Postone, Moishe]]. ''Time, Labour, and Social Domination: A Reinterpretation of Marx's Critical Theory.'' Cambridge [England]: Cambridge University Press, 1993.
* [[Murray Rothbard|Rothbard, Murray]]. ''An Austrian Perspective on the History of Economic Thought Volume&amp;nbsp;II: Classical Economics'' (Edward Elgar Publishing Ltd., 1995) ISBN 0-945466-48-X
* [[Maximilien Rubel|Rubel, Maximilien]]. ''Marx Without Myth: A Chronological Study of his Life and Work'' (Blackwell, 1975) ISBN 0-631-15780-8
* [[Alfredo Saad-Filho|Saad-Filho, Alfredo]]. ''The Value of Marx: Political Economy for Contemporary Capitalism''. London: Routledge, 2002.
* [[Alfred Schmidt (philosopher)|Schmidt, Alfred]]. ''The Concept of Nature in Marx''. London: NLB, 1971.
* Seigel, Jerrold. ''Marx's fate: the shape of a life'' (Princeton University Press, 1978) ISBN 0-271-00935-7
* [[Thomas T. Sekine|Sekinel, Thomas T.]] ''The Dialectic of Capital. A Study of the Inner Logic of Capitalism'', 2 volumes (preliminary edition), Tokyo 1986; ISBN 978-4-924750-44-9 (vol. 1), ISBN 4-924750-34-4 (vol. 2)
* [[Paul Strathern|Strathern, Paul]]. &quot;Marx in 90 Minutes&quot;, (Ivan R. Dee, 2001)
* Thomas, Paul. ''Karl Marx and the Anarchists''. London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, 1980.
* Walker, Frank Thomas. 'Karl Marx: a Bibliographic and Political Biography''. (bj.publications), 2009.
* Wendling, Amy. ''Karl Marx on Technology and Alienation'' (Palgrave Macmillan, 2009)
* [[Francis Wheen|Wheen, Francis]]. ''[http://pubs.socialistreviewindex.org.uk/isj85/morgan.htm Karl Marx: A Life]'', (Fourth Estate, 1999), ISBN 1-85702-637-3
* Wheen, Francis. ''Marx's Das Kapital'', (Atlantic Books, 2006) ISBN 1-84354-400-8
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Sister project links|author=yes|Karl Marx}}

===Bibliography and online texts===
{{Marxism}}
* {{de-icon}} [http://www.zeno.org/Philosophie/M/Marx,%20Karl Works by Karl Marx] at [[Zeno.org]]
* [http://libcom.org/tags/karl-marx Karl Marx] at Libcom.org
* {{SEP|marx}}
* {{In Our Time|Karl Marx|p003k9jg|Karl_Marx}}
* [http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/ Marxists.org], homepage of the [[Marxists Internet Archive]]
* {{worldcat id|id=lccn-n79-6935}}
* [http://librivox.org/newcatalog/search.php?title=&amp;author=Karl+Marx&amp;action=Search Works by Karl Marx in audio format] from [[LibriVox]]
* {{gutenberg author|id=Karl_Marx|name=Karl Marx}}
===Articles and entries===
* [http://www.counterpunch.org/roberts10072009.html Dead Labour: Marx and Lenin Reconsidered] by [[Paul Craig Roberts]]
* [http://www.wsws.org/articles/2006/may2006/rock-m02.shtml Hegel, Marx, Engels, and the Origins of Marxism], by David North
* [http://chronicle.com/article/In-Praise-of-Marx/127027 ''In Praise of Marx''] [[Terry Eagleton]] synopsising his ''Why Marx was right'' chronicle.com 10 April 2011.
* [http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/politics/article4981065.ece Karl Marx: Did he get it all Right?] by Philip Collins, ''[[The Times]]'', 21 October 2008
* [http://www.marxists.org/archive/mandel/19xx/marx/ ''Karl Marx'', Ernest Mandel ]
* [http://libcom.org/library/karl-marx-iroquois-franklin-rosemont ''Karl Marx and the Iroquois''] by [[Franklin Rosemont]]
* [http://www.cato.org/pubs/journal/cj11n3/cj11n3-6.pdf Liberalism, Marxism and The State], by Ralph Raico
* [http://www.emis.ams.org/journals/DMJDMV/xvol-icm/19/Dauben.MAN.html Marx, Mao and mathematics: the politics of infinitesimals], by Joseph Dauben
* [http://www.socialistalternative.com/publications/s21/ch3.html Marx Was Right]
* [http://www.isj.org.uk/index.php4?id=486&amp;issue=120 Marxism and Ethics] from ''[[International Socialism (journal)|International Socialism]]'' Paul Blackledge (2008)
* [http://marxmyths.org/ Marxmyths.org Various essays on misinterpretations of Marx]
* [http://www.iisg.nl/collections/marx/ Portraits of Karl Marx] ([[International Institute of Social History]])
* [http://www.runmuki.com/paul/writing/marx.html Paul Dorn, The Paris Commune and Marx' Theory of Revolution]
* [http://www.greenleft.org.au/1999/346/19592 The Top Seven Reasons why Marx was Right] by ''[[Green Left Weekly]]''
* [http://www.commondreams.org/views05/0717-28.htm Why Marx is the Man of the Moment]
{{Marx/Engels}}
{{History of economic thought}}
{{Social and political philosophy}}
{{jurisprudence}}
{{Communism}}
{{Good article}}
{{Authority control|PND=118578537|LCCN=n/79/6935|VIAF=49228757}}
{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
|NAME              = Marx, Karl
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES = Marx, Karl Heinrich
|SHORT DESCRIPTION = German philosopher, political economist and revolutionary
|DATE OF BIRTH     = 1818-5-5
|PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Trier]], [[Prussia]]
|DATE OF DEATH     = 1883-3-14
|PLACE OF DEATH    = [[London]], [[United Kingdom]]
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Marx, Karl}}
[[Category:Karl Marx| ]]
[[Category:1818 births]]
[[Category:1883 deaths]]
[[Category:19th-century philosophers]]
[[Category:19th-century Prussian people]]
[[Category:19th-century journalists]]
[[Category:Ashkenazi Jews]]
[[Category:Atheist philosophers]]
[[Category:Burials at Highgate Cemetery]]
[[Category:German communists]]
[[Category:Economic historians]]
[[Category:German economists]]
[[Category:German atheists]]
[[Category:German emigrants to the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:German historians]]
[[Category:German Jews]]
[[Category:German philosophers]]
[[Category:German revolutionaries]]
[[Category:German socialists]]
[[Category:German tax resisters]]
[[Category:Historians of economic thought]]
[[Category:Marxian economists|*]]
[[Category:Marxist historians|*]]
[[Category:Marxist journalists|*]]
[[Category:Marxist theorists| ]]
[[Category:Marxists| ]]
[[Category:Materialists]]
[[Category:Members of the International Workingmen's Association]]
[[Category:People from the Rhine Province]]
[[Category:People from Trier]]
[[Category:People associated with the Royal Society of Arts]]
[[Category:Political economy]]
[[Category:Political philosophers]]
[[Category:Social philosophers]]
[[Category:German sociologists]]
[[Category:Stateless persons]]
[[Category:University of Bonn alumni]]
[[Category:Writers about globalization]]
[[Category:19th-century economists]]

{{Link GA|ar}}
{{Link GA|cs}}
{{Link GA|de}}
{{Link GA|no}}
{{Link FA|it}}
{{Link FA|la}}

[[af:Karl Marx]]
[[am:ካርል ማርክስ]]
[[ar:كارل ماركس]]
[[an:Karl Marx]]
[[as:কাৰ্ল মাৰ্ক্স]]
[[ast:Karl Marx]]
[[ay:Karl Marx]]
[[az:Karl Marks]]
[[bn:কার্ল মার্ক্স]]
[[zh-min-nan:Karl Marx]]
[[be:Карл Маркс]]
[[be-x-old:Карл Маркс]]
[[bcl:Karl Marx]]
[[bg:Карл Маркс]]
[[bo:ཁཱར​་ལ་མར་ཁེ་སི།]]
[[bs:Karl Marx]]
[[br:Karl Marx]]
[[ca:Karl Marx]]
[[cv:Карл Маркс]]
[[cs:Karl Marx]]
[[co:Karl Marx]]
[[cy:Karl Marx]]
[[da:Karl Marx]]
[[de:Karl Marx]]
[[dsb:Karl Marx]]
[[et:Karl Marx]]
[[el:Καρλ Μαρξ]]
[[es:Karl Marx]]
[[eo:Karl Marx]]
[[ext:Karl Marx]]
[[eu:Karl Marx]]
[[fa:کارل مارکس]]
[[hif:Karl Marx]]
[[fr:Karl Marx]]
[[fy:Karl Marx]]
[[ga:Karl Marx]]
[[gd:Karl Marx]]
[[gl:Karl Marx]]
[[gan:馬克思]]
[[glk:کارل مارکس]]
[[ko:카를 마르크스]]
[[hy:Կարլ Մարքս]]
[[hi:कार्ल मार्क्स]]
[[hsb:Karl Marx]]
[[hr:Karl Marx]]
[[io:Karl Marx]]
[[ilo:Karl Marx]]
[[bpy:কার্ল মার্ক্স্]]
[[id:Karl Marx]]
[[ia:Karl Marx]]
[[is:Karl Marx]]
[[it:Karl Marx]]
[[he:קרל מרקס]]
[[jv:Karl Marx]]
[[kn:ಕಾರ್ಲ್ ಮಾರ್ಕ್ಸ್]]
[[ka:კარლ მარქსი]]
[[kk:Карл Маркс Генрих]]
[[sw:Karl Marx]]
[[ku:Karl Marx]]
[[ky:Маркс, Карл]]
[[lad:Karl Marx]]
[[lez:Карл Маркс]]
[[la:Carolus Marx]]
[[lv:Kārlis Markss]]
[[lb:Karl Marx]]
[[lt:Karl Marx]]
[[li:Karl Marx]]
[[jbo:karl. marks]]
[[lmo:Karl Marx]]
[[hu:Karl Marx]]
[[mk:Карл Маркс]]
[[ml:കാൾ മാക്സ്]]
[[mt:Karl Marx]]
[[mr:कार्ल मार्क्स]]
[[xmf:კარლ მარქსი]]
[[arz:كارل ماركس]]
[[mzn:کارل مارکس]]
[[ms:Karl Marx]]
[[mwl:Karl Marx]]
[[mn:Карл Маркс]]
[[my:ကားလ်မာ့ခ်]]
[[nah:Karl Marx]]
[[nl:Karl Marx]]
[[nds-nl:Karl Marx]]
[[ne:कार्ल मार्क्स]]
[[ja:カール・マルクス]]
[[no:Karl Marx]]
[[nn:Karl Marx]]
[[nov:Karl Marx]]
[[oc:Karl Marx]]
[[uz:Karl Marx]]
[[pa:ਕਾਰਲ ਮਾਰਕਸ]]
[[pnb:کارل مارکس]]
[[ps:کارل مارکس]]
[[pms:Karl Marx]]
[[nds:Karl Marx]]
[[pl:Karol Marks]]
[[pnt:Καρλ Μαρξ]]
[[pt:Karl Marx]]
[[kaa:Karl Marx]]
[[ro:Karl Marx]]
[[rm:Karl Marx]]
[[qu:Karl Marx]]
[[rue:Карл Маркс]]
[[ru:Маркс, Карл]]
[[sah:Карл Маркс]]
[[sa:कार्ल मार्क्स]]
[[sc:Karl Marx]]
[[sco:Karl Marx]]
[[st:Karl Marx]]
[[sq:Karl Marx]]
[[scn:Karl Marx]]
[[si:කාල් මාක්ස්]]
[[simple:Karl Marx]]
[[sk:Karl Marx]]
[[sl:Karl Marx]]
[[so:Karl Marx]]
[[ckb:کارڵ مارکس]]
[[sr:Карл Маркс]]
[[sh:Karl Marx]]
[[su:Karl Marx]]
[[fi:Karl Marx]]
[[sv:Karl Marx]]
[[tl:Karl Marx]]
[[ta:கார்ல் மார்க்சு]]
[[kab:Karl Marx]]
[[tt:Карл Маркс]]
[[te:కార్ల్ మార్క్స్]]
[[th:คาร์ล มาร์กซ์]]
[[tg:Карл Маркс]]
[[tr:Karl Marx]]
[[uk:Карл Маркс]]
[[ur:کارل مارکس]]
[[ug:كارل ماركىس]]
[[za:Karl Marx]]
[[vi:Karl Marx]]
[[fiu-vro:Marxi Karl]]
[[wa:Karl Marx]]
[[war:Karl Marx]]
[[yi:קארל מארקס]]
[[yo:Karl Marx]]
[[zh-yue:馬克思]]
[[diq:Karl Marx]]
[[bat-smg:Karls Marksos]]
[[zh:卡尔·马克思]]</text>
      <sha1>pnqapp3cd73259kfz1aa2p3lq0y0e59</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
