<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Kurt Cobain</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>16707</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520344472</id>
      <parentid>519024786</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-28T23:56:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Kellygirlaj</username>
        <id>6960535</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Frances Bean Cobain */ sentence restructure</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="72027">{{cite check|article|date=August 2011|talk=Dead links}} 
{{pp-semi-indef}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=April 2011}}
{{Infobox musical artist
| name                = Kurt Cobain
| image               = Kurtcobain1993.jpg
| caption             = Kurt Cobain performing in 1993
| birth_name          = Kurt Donald Cobain
| alias               = Kurdt Kobain 
| birth_date          = {{birth date|1967|2|20|mf=y}}
| birth_place         = [[Aberdeen, Washington]], U.S.
| death_date          = {{death date and age|mf=yes|1994|4|5|1967|2|20}}&lt;!--His body was FOUND on the 8th - the Seattle Coroner's Office ruled that he probably died on the 5th, please do not change this.--&gt;
| death_place         = [[Seattle, Washington|Seattle]], [[Washington (state)|Washington]], U.S.
| instrument          = Vocals, guitar&lt;!--He was primarily notable as a guitarist and vocalist. This has been discussed on the article's talk page numerous times. Please address the topic there if you believe it should be changed.--&gt;, drums
| background          = solo_singer
| occupation          = Musician, songwriter, artist
| years_active        = 1982–1994
| genre               = [[Alternative rock]], [[grunge]]
| label               = [[Sub Pop]], [[DGC Records|DGC]]/[[Geffen Records|Geffen]]
| associated_acts     = [[Nirvana (band)|Nirvana]], [[Fecal Matter (band)|Fecal Matter]]
| spouse              = [[Courtney Love]] (1992-1994, his death) 
| notable_instruments = [[Fender Jag-Stang]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Fender Jaguar]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Fender Mustang]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Fender Stratocaster]]&lt;br/&gt;[[C. F. Martin &amp; Company|Martin D-18E]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Univox Hi-Flier]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.kurtsequipment.com/|title=The Kurt Cobain Equipment F.A.Q.|work=kurtsequipment.com|accessdate=April 6, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br/&gt;[[Mosrite| Mosrite &quot;The Ventures&quot; Guitar]]
}}
[[File:Firma de Kurt Cobain.svg|thumb|Kurt's signature]]
'''Kurt Donald Cobain''' (February 20, 1967&amp;nbsp;– April 5, 1994)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://findadeath.com/Deceased/c/Kurt%20Cobain/DC.JPG |title=Kurt Cobain's death certificate |work=findadeath.com |deadurl=no |accessdate=April 6, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/april/8/newsid_3522000/3522702.stm |title=1994: Rock musician Kurt Cobain 'shoots himself' |work=[[BBC]] |deadurl=no |accessdate=April 6, 2012 |date=April 8, 1994}}&lt;/ref&gt; was an American [[musician]] and [[artist]], best known as the [[lead singer]], [[guitarist]] and primary [[songwriter]] of the [[grunge]] band [[Nirvana (band)|Nirvana]]. Cobain formed Nirvana with [[Krist Novoselic]] in [[Aberdeen, Washington]] in 1985 and established it as part of the Seattle music scene, having its debut album ''[[Bleach (album)|Bleach]]'' released on the independent record label [[Sub Pop]] in 1989.

After signing with major label [[DGC Records]], the band found breakthrough success with &quot;[[Smells Like Teen Spirit]]&quot; from its second album ''[[Nevermind]]'' (1991). Following the success of ''Nevermind'', Nirvana was labeled &quot;the flagship band&quot; of [[Generation X]], and Cobain hailed as &quot;the spokesman of a generation&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Inside the Heart and Mind of Nirvana&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.rollingstone.com/artists/nirvana/articles/story/5937982/inside_the_heart_and_mind_of_nirvana |title=Inside the Heart and Mind of Nirvana |work=[[Rolling Stone]] |author=Michael Azerrad |date=April 16, 1992 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20071002082643/http://www.rollingstone.com/artists/nirvana/articles/story/5937982inside_the_heart_and_mind_of_nirvana |archivedate=2007-10-02 |accessdate=April 5, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cobain, however, was often uncomfortable and frustrated, believing his message and artistic vision to have been misinterpreted by the public, with his personal issues often subject to media attention. He challenged Nirvana's audience with its final studio album ''[[In Utero (album)|In Utero]]'' (1993).

During the last years of his life, Cobain struggled with [[heroin addiction]], illness and depression. He also had difficulty coping with his fame and public image, and the professional and lifelong personal pressures surrounding himself and his wife, musician [[Courtney Love]]. On April 8, 1994, Cobain was found dead at his home in [[Seattle]], the victim of what was officially ruled a [[suicide]] by a self-inflicted shotgun wound to the head. The circumstances of [[Death of Kurt Cobain|his death]] [[27 Club|at age 27]] have become a topic of public fascination and debate. Since their debut, Nirvana, with Cobain as a songwriter, has sold over 25&amp;nbsp;million albums in the U.S., and over 50&amp;nbsp;million worldwide.&lt;ref name=&quot;yahoo2002&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://music.yahoo.com/nirvana/news/nirvana-tops-50-million-mark-in-worldwide-sales-journals-number-one--12064388 |title=Nirvana Tops 50 Million Mark In Worldwide Sales, 'Journals' Number One |work=Yahoo! Music |date=November 17, 2002 |deadurl=no |accessdate=April 6, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Selling Artists&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.riaa.com/goldandplatinumdata.php?table=tblTopArtTop |title=Selling Artists |work=RIAA.com |deadurl=yes |accessdate=September 22, 2008}}{{dead link|date=April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Early life ==
Kurt Donald Cobain was born on February 20, 1967, at Grays Harbor Hospital in [[Aberdeen, Washington]],&lt;ref name=&quot;unseen&quot;&gt;''Cobain Unseen'', by Charles R. Cross&lt;/ref&gt; to a waitress, Wendy Elizabeth (née Fradenburg) (born 1948),&lt;ref name=&quot;Halperin&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=DsDU2DsewtYC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Who+Killed+Kurt+Cobain?&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=YC2CT6KbO8Gl2AWS3aD0Bg&amp;ved=0CDYQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=Who%20Killed%20Kurt%20Cobain%3F&amp;f=false |author=Halperin, Ian &amp; Wallace, Max |title=Who Killed Kurt Cobain? |publisher=Birch Lane Press |year=1998 |isbn=1-55972-446-3 |deadurl=no |accessdate=April 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and an automotive mechanic, Donald Leland Cobain (born 1946). His parents were married on July 31, 1965 in [[Coeur d'Alene, Idaho]]. His ancestry included [[Irish people|Irish]], English, Scottish, and [[German people|German]].&lt;ref&gt;Azerrad, p. 13&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ancestry&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.wargs.com/other/cobain.html |title=Ancestry of Frances Bean Cobain |publisher=Wargs.com |author=William Addams Reitwiesner |deadurl=no |accessdate=April 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cross7&quot;&gt;Cross, p. 7&lt;/ref&gt; Cobain's Irish ancestors migrated from [[County Tyrone]] of Northern Ireland in 1875.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cross7&quot;/&gt; Researchers have found them to have been shoemakers, originally named Cobane, who came from the village of Inishatieve near [[Pomeroy, County Tyrone|Pomeroy]], settling in [[Cornwall, Ontario]], Canada, and then in Washington.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nirvanalegend2010&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.belfasttelegraph.co.uk/news/local-national/nirvana-legend-kurt-cobains-roots-traced-to-co-tyrone-14737909.html |title=Nirvana legend Kurt Cobain's roots traced to Co Tyrone |publisher=BelfastTelegraph.co.uk |date=March 24, 2010 |deadurl=no |accessdate=April 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cobain had one younger sister named Kimberly, born on April 24, 1970.&lt;ref name=&quot;Halperin&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ancestry&quot;/&gt;

Cobain's family had a musical background. His maternal uncle Chuck Fradenburg starred in a band called The Beachcombers, his Aunt Mari Earle played guitar and performed in bands throughout [[Grays Harbor County]], and his great-uncle Delbert had a career as an Irish tenor; making an appearance in the 1930 film ''[[King of Jazz]]''. Cobain was described as being a happy and excitable, while sensitive and caring child. His talent as an artist was evident from an early age. His bedroom was described as having taken on the appearance of an art studio,&lt;ref name=&quot;unseen&quot;/&gt; where he would accurately draw his favorite characters from films and cartoons such as [[Aquaman]], the [[Creature from the Black Lagoon]], and [[The Walt Disney Company|Disney]] characters like [[Donald Duck]], [[Mickey Mouse]] and [[Pluto (Disney)|Pluto]].&lt;ref&gt;Cross, p. 11&lt;/ref&gt; This enthusiasm was encouraged by his grandmother Iris Cobain, who was a professional artist herself. Cobain began developing an interest in music early in his life. According to his Aunt Mari, he began singing at two years old. At age four, Cobain started playing the piano and singing, writing a song about their trip to a local park. He listened to artists like the [[Ramones]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.rocksbackpages.com/article.html?ArticleID=15160 |title=Verse Chorus Verse: The Recording History of Nirvana |work=[[Goldmine (magazine)|Goldmine Magazine]] |author=Gillian G. Gaar |date=February 14, 1997 |deadurl=no |accessdate=April 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and would sing songs like [[Arlo Guthrie]]'s &quot;Motorcycle Song,&quot; [[The Beatles]]' &quot;[[Hey Jude]]&quot;, [[Terry Jacks]]' &quot;[[Seasons in the Sun]]&quot; and the theme song to [[The Monkees]] [[The Monkees (TV series)|television show]] at a young age.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cross, p. 9&quot;&gt;Cross, p. 9&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Young cobain.jpg|thumb|right|A photograph of Cobain from his second grade school yearbook; the picture was handed out at his memorial service.]] --&gt;
When Cobain was seven years old, his parents divorced.&lt;ref&gt;Cross, p. 20&lt;/ref&gt; Later in his life, he said the divorce had a profound effect on his life. His mother noted that his personality changed dramatically; Cobain became defiant and withdrawn.&lt;ref&gt;Azerrad, p. 17&lt;/ref&gt; In a 1993 interview, he elaborated:
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;I remember feeling ashamed, for some reason. I was ashamed of my parents. I couldn't face some of my friends at school anymore, because I desperately wanted to have the classic, you know, typical family. Mother, father. I wanted that security, so I resented my parents for quite a few years because of that.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Savage, Jon 1997&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nirvanafreak.net/art/art8a.shtml |title=Kurt Cobain: The Lost Interview |work=NirvanaFreak.net |author=Jon Savage |deadurl=no |accessdate=April 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Cobain's parents both found new partners after the divorce. His father had promised not to remarry; however, after meeting Jenny Westeby, he did, to Kurt's dismay.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cross, p. 24&quot;&gt;Cross, p. 24&lt;/ref&gt; Kurt, his father, Westeby, and her two children Mindy and James, moved into a new household together. Cobain liked Westeby at first, who gave him the maternal attention he desired.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cross, p. 24&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cross, p. 25&quot;&gt;Cross, p. 25&lt;/ref&gt; In January 1979, Westeby gave birth to a boy, Chad Cobain.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cross, p. 24&quot;/&gt; This new family, which Cobain insisted was not his real one, was in stark contrast to the attention Cobain was used to receiving as an only boy; he soon began to express resentment toward his stepmother.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cross, p. 24&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cross, p. 25&quot;/&gt; Kurt's mother began dating a man who was abusive. Cobain witnessed the [[domestic violence]] inflicted upon her, with one incident resulting in her being hospitalized with a broken arm.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cross, p. 25&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cross, p. 26&quot;&gt;Cross, p. 26&lt;/ref&gt; Wendy steadfastly refused to press charges, remaining completely committed to the relationship.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cross, p. 26&quot;/&gt;

Kurt behaved insolently toward adults. He began bullying another boy at school. These behaviours eventually caused his father and Westeby to take him to a therapist, who concluded that Kurt would benefit in a single family environment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cross, p. 26&quot;/&gt; Both sides of the family attempted to bring his parents back together, but to no avail. On June 28, 1979, Cobain's mother granted full custody of Kurt to his father.&lt;ref&gt;Cross, p. 27&lt;/ref&gt;

Cobain's teenage rebellion quickly became overwhelming for his father, who placed Kurt in the care of family and friends. While living with the [[born-again Christian]] family of his friend Jesse Reed, Cobain became a devout Christian and regularly attended church services. Cobain later renounced Christianity, engaging in what would be described as &quot;anti-God&quot; rants. The song &quot;[[Lithium (Nirvana song)|Lithium]]&quot; is about his experience while living with the Reed family. Religion would remain an important part in Cobain's personal life and beliefs, as he often used Christian imagery in his work and maintained a constant interest in [[Jainism]] and [[Buddhism|Buddhist]] philosophy. The band name [[Nirvana (band)|Nirvana]] was taken from the [[Nirvana|Buddhist concept]], which Cobain described as &quot;freedom from pain, suffering and the external world,&quot; which paralleled with the [[punk rock]] ethic and [[Punk ideologies|ideology]]. Cobain would regard himself as both a Buddhist and a Jain during different points of his life, educating himself about the philosophies through various sources, including through watching late night television documentaries on both subjects.&lt;ref&gt;Cross, p. 196&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cross, p. 69&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Azerrad-p22&quot;&gt;Azerrad, p. 22&lt;/ref&gt;

Although not interested in sports, Kurt was enrolled in a junior high school [[wrestling]] team at the insistence of his father. Kurt was a skilled wrestler, yet despised the experience. Because of the ridicule he endured from his teammates and coach, he allowed himself to be pinned, in an attempt to sadden his father. Later, his father enlisted him in a [[little league baseball]] team, where Cobain would intentionally strike out to avoid playing on the team.&lt;ref&gt;Azerrad, pp. 20–25&lt;/ref&gt;

Cobain befriended a homosexual student at school, and suffered bullying from heterosexual students who concluded that Cobain was gay. In an interview he said that he liked having the identity of being gay because he did not like people and when they thought he was gay they left him alone. Kurt stated, &quot;I started being really proud of the fact that I was gay even though I wasn't&quot;. His friend tried to kiss him and Kurt backed away and told his friend he was not gay but would still be friends with him. In a 1993 interview with ''[[The Advocate]]'', Cobain claimed that he was &quot;gay in spirit&quot; and &quot;probably could be [[Bisexuality|bisexual]].&quot; He also stated that he used to spray paint &quot;God Is Gay&quot; on pickup trucks in the Aberdeen area. However, Aberdeen police records show that the phrase for which he was arrested was actually &quot;Ain't got no how watchamacallit&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Cross, p. 68&lt;/ref&gt; One of his personal journals states, &quot;I am not gay, although I wish I were, just to piss off homophobes.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cobain, Kurt 2002&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |author=Cobain, Kurt |title=Journals |publisher=Riverhead Hardcover |year=2002 |isbn=978-1-57322-232-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cobain enjoyed creating works of art. He would often draw during school classes, including objects associated with [[human anatomy]]. When given a caricature assignment for an art course, Cobain drew a posing [[Michael Jackson]]. When his art teacher told him the caricature would be inappropriate to be displayed in a school hallway, Cobain drew an unflattering sketch of then-President [[Ronald Reagan]].&lt;ref&gt;Cross, p. 41&lt;/ref&gt;

As attested to by numerous of Cobain's classmates and family members, the first concert he attended was [[Sammy Hagar]] and [[Quarterflash]] at the [[KeyArena|Seattle Center Coliseum]] in 1983.&lt;ref name=&quot;unseen&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cross, p. 44&lt;/ref&gt; Cobain, however, claimed that the first concert he attended was the [[Melvins]]; he wrote prolifically in his ''Journals'' of the experience.&lt;ref&gt;Cross, p. 45&lt;/ref&gt; As a teenager living in [[Montesano, Washington | Montesano]], Cobain eventually found escape through the thriving [[Pacific Northwest]] punk scene, going to punk rock shows in Seattle. Cobain soon began frequenting the practice space of fellow Montesano musicians the [[Melvins]].

During his sophomore year in high school, Cobain began living with his mother in Aberdeen. Two weeks prior to graduation, he dropped out of [[Aberdeen High School (Aberdeen, Washington)|Aberdeen High School]] upon realizing he did not have enough credits to graduate. His mother gave him a choice: find employment or leave. After one week, Cobain found his clothes and other belongings packed away in boxes.&lt;ref&gt;Azerrad, p. 35&lt;/ref&gt; Feeling banished from his own mother's home, Cobain stayed with friends, occasionally sneaking back into his mother's basement.&lt;ref name=&quot;Azerrad37&quot;&gt;Azerrad, p. 37&lt;/ref&gt; Cobain also claimed during periods of homelessness to have lived under a bridge over the [[Wishkah River]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Azerrad37&quot;/&gt; an experience that inspired the ''Nevermind'' track &quot;[[Something in the Way]]&quot;. However, Nirvana bassist [[Krist Novoselic]] said, &quot;He hung out there, but you couldn't live on those muddy banks, with the tides coming up and down. That was his own revisionism.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;requiem&quot;&gt;Cross, Charles R. &quot;Requiem for a Dream.&quot; ''Guitar World.'' October 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;

In late 1986 Cobain moved into an apartment, paying his rent by working at a [[Polynesian culture|Polynesian]] coastal resort approximately {{convert|20|mi|km}} north of Aberdeen.&lt;ref&gt;Azerrad, p. 43&lt;/ref&gt; During this period, he was traveling frequently to [[Olympia, Washington]] to go to rock concerts.&lt;ref&gt;Azerrad, p. 46&lt;/ref&gt; During his visits to Olympia, Cobain formed a relationship with Tracy Marander. The couple had a close relationship, but one that was often strained with financial difficulties and Cobain's absence when touring. Marander supported the couple by working at the cafeteria of the [[Seattle–Tacoma International Airport]], often stealing food. Cobain spent most his time sleeping into the late evening, watching television and concentrating on art projects. Marander's insistence that he get a job caused arguments that influenced Cobain to write &quot;[[About a Girl (Nirvana song)|About a Girl]]&quot;, which was featured on the Nirvana album ''[[Bleach (album)|Bleach]]''. Marander is credited with having taken the cover photo for the album.  Marander was not aware that &quot;About a Girl&quot; was written about her until years after Cobain's death.&lt;ref&gt;Cross, pp. 88–93&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cross, pp. 116–17&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cross, p. 122&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cross, pp. 134–36&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cross, p. 143&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cross, p. 153&lt;/ref&gt;

Soon after Marander separated from him, Cobain began dating [[Tobi Vail]], an influential [[DIY]] [[punk zine]]ster of the [[riot grrrl]] band [[Bikini Kill]]. After meeting Vail, Cobain vomited as he was so completely overwhelmed with anxiety regarding his infatuation with her. This event would inspire the lyric: &quot;Love you so much it makes me sick,&quot; which would appear in the song &quot;[[Aneurysm (song)|Aneurysm]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Cross, p. 152&lt;/ref&gt; While Cobain would regard Vail as his female counterpart, his relationship with her waned. Cobain desired the maternal comfort of a traditional relationship, which Vail regarded as sexist within a [[countercultural]] punk rock community. Those who dated Vail would be described by her friend Alice Wheeler as &quot;fashion accessories.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Cross, p. 153&lt;/ref&gt; Kurt and Tobi spent most of their time together as a couple discussing political and philosophical issues. Cobain's relationship with Vail would inspire the lyrical content of many of the songs on ''Nevermind''. Once, while discussing [[anarchism]] and punk rock with friend [[Kathleen Hanna]], Hanna spray-painted &quot;Kurt Smells Like Teen Spirit&quot; on Kurt's apartment wall. [[Teen Spirit (deodorant)|Teen Spirit]] was the name of a deodorant Vail wore; Hanna joked that Cobain smelled like it. Cobain, unaware of this, initially interpreted the slogan as having a revolutionary meaning. The slogan inspired the title to the song &quot;[[Smells Like Teen Spirit]]&quot;.

== Nirvana ==
{{Main|Nirvana (band)}}
{{Refimprove section|date=January 2011}}

&lt;!--Please do not significantly expand this section. This section is intended to simply cover the basics of Cobain's involvement in Nirvana. The details about Nirvana's career are already more extensively discussed in [[Nirvana (band)]].--&gt;

Cobain had his 14th birthday on February 20, 1981. His uncle offered him either a bike or a used guitar. He chose the guitar. Soon, he was mastering [[Stairway to Heaven]]. Cobain began learning guitar with a few covers, including &quot;[[Louie Louie]]&quot;, [[The Cars]]' &quot;[[My Best Friend's Girl (song)|My Best Friend's Girl]]&quot;, and &quot;[[Jesus Wants Me for a Sunbeam|Jesus Doesn't Want Me for a Sunbeam]]&quot; and soon began working on his own songs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Azerrad-p22&quot;/&gt;{{failed verification|date=September 2012}} During high school, Cobain rarely found anyone with whom he could play music. While hanging out at the Melvins' practice space, he met [[Krist Novoselic]], a fellow devotee of punk rock. Novoselic's mother owned a hair salon. Cobain and Novoselic would occasionally practice in the upstairs room of the salon. A few years later, Cobain tried to convince Novoselic to form a band with him by lending him a copy of a [[Illiteracy Will Prevail|home demo]] recorded by Cobain's earlier band, [[Fecal Matter (band)|Fecal Matter]]. After months of asking, Novoselic finally agreed to join Cobain, forming the beginnings of Nirvana.&lt;ref&gt;Azerrad, p. 45&lt;/ref&gt;

Cobain was disenchanted after early touring, due to the band's inability to draw substantial crowds and the apparent difficulty in sustaining themselves. During their first few years playing together, Novoselic and Cobain were hosts to a rotating list of drummers. Eventually, the band settled on [[Chad Channing]], with whom Nirvana recorded the album ''[[Bleach (album)|Bleach]]'', released on [[Sub Pop|Sub Pop Records]] in 1989. Cobain, however, became dissatisfied with Channing's style, leading the band to find a new drummer, eventually settling on [[Dave Grohl]]. With Grohl, the band found their greatest success via their 1991 major-label debut, ''[[Nevermind]]''.

With the lead single &quot;[[Smells Like Teen Spirit]]&quot; from Nirvana's second album ''[[Nevermind]]'' (1991), Nirvana entered the mainstream, popularizing a subgenre of [[alternative rock]] called [[grunge]]. Since their debut, Nirvana, with Cobain as a songwriter, have sold over 25&amp;nbsp;million albums in the United States alone, and over 50&amp;nbsp;million worldwide.&lt;ref name=&quot;yahoo2002&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Selling Artists&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Nirvana around 1992.jpg|thumb|Cobain ''(right)'' with Nirvana in 1992]]
The success of ''[[Nevermind]]'' provided numerous Seattle bands such as [[Alice in Chains]], [[Pearl Jam]], and [[Soundgarden]] to wider audiences, and as a result, alternative rock became a dominant genre on radio and music television in the United States during the early-to-middle 1990s. Nirvana was considered the &quot;flagship band of [[Generation X]]&quot;, and frontman Cobain found himself reluctantly anointed by the media as the generation's &quot;spokesman.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Inside the Heart and Mind of Nirvana&quot;/&gt; Cobain's discomfort with the media attention prompted him to focus on the band's music and, believing their message and artistic vision to have been misinterpreted by the public, challenged the band's audience with its third studio album ''[[In Utero (album)|In Utero]]'' (1993).

Cobain struggled to reconcile the massive success of Nirvana to his [[underground rock|underground]] roots. He also felt persecuted by the media, comparing himself to [[Frances Farmer]]. He began to harbour resentments for people who claimed to be fans of the band yet refused to acknowledge, or misinterpreted, the band's social and political views. A vocal opponent of sexism, racism and homophobia, he was publicly proud that Nirvana had played at a [[gay rights]] benefit supporting No-on-Nine in Oregon in 1992, in opposition to [[Oregon Ballot Measure 9 (1992)|Ballot Measure Nine]], a ballot measure, that if passed, would have prohibited schools in the state from acknowledging or positively accepting LGBT rights and welfare.

Cobain was a vocal supporter of the [[pro-choice]] movement, and had been involved in [[Rock for Choice]] from the campaign inception by [[L7 (band)|L7]]. He received [[death threat]]s from a small number of [[Pro-life movement|anti-abortion]] activists for doing so, with one activist threatening Cobain that he would be shot as soon as he stepped on stage.&lt;ref&gt;Cross, p. 253&lt;/ref&gt; The liner notes from ''[[Incesticide]]'' declared &quot;if any of you in any way hate homosexuals, people of different color, or women, please do this one favor for us-leave us the fuck alone! Don't come to our shows and don't buy our records&quot;. An article from his posthumously released ''[[Journals (Cobain)|Journals]]'' declares that social liberation could be made possible only through the eradication of sexism.

== Musical influences ==
[[The Beatles]] were an early and lasting influence on Cobain; his aunt Mari remembers him singing &quot;[[Hey Jude]]&quot; at the age of two.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cross, p. 9&quot;/&gt; &quot;My aunts would give me Beatles records,&quot; Cobain told [[Jon Savage]] in 1993, &quot;so for the most part [I listened to] the Beatles [as a child], and if I was lucky, I'd be able to buy a single.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Savage, Jon 1997&quot;/&gt; Cobain expressed a particular fondness for [[John Lennon]], whom he called his &quot;idol&quot; in his posthumously-released [[Journals (Cobain)|journals]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Cobain, Kurt 2002&quot;/&gt; and he admitted that he wrote the song &quot;[[About a Girl (Nirvana song)|About a Girl]],&quot; from Nirvana 1989 debut album ''[[Bleach (album)|Bleach]]'', after spending three hours listening to ''[[Meet The Beatles!]].&lt;ref&gt;Cross, p. 121&lt;/ref&gt;

Cobain was also a fan of [[classic rock]] bands, including [[Led Zeppelin]], [[AC/DC]], [[Black Sabbath]], [[Aerosmith]], [[Queen (band)|Queen]], and [[Kiss (band)|Kiss]]. Nirvana occasionally played cover songs by these bands, including Led Zeppelin's &quot;[[Immigrant Song]]&quot;, &quot;[[Dazed and Confused (song)|Dazed and Confused]]&quot; and &quot;[[Heartbreaker (Led Zeppelin song)|Heartbreaker]]&quot;, Black Sabbath's &quot;[[Hand of Doom (song)|Hand of Doom]],&quot; and Kiss' &quot;Do You Love Me?&quot;, and wrote the ''[[Incesticide]]'' song &quot;Aero Zeppelin&quot; as a tribute to Led Zeppelin and Aerosmith.

[[Punk rock]] proved to be a profound influence on a teenaged Cobain's attitude and artistic style. His first punk rock album was ''[[Sandinista!]]'' by [[The Clash]],&lt;ref&gt;Cross, p. 169&lt;/ref&gt; but he became a bigger fan of a fellow 1970s British punk band the [[Sex Pistols]], describing them as &quot;one million times more important than the Clash&quot; in his journals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cobain, Kurt 2002&quot;/&gt; He was introduced to 1980s American hardcore bands like [[Black Flag (band)|Black Flag]], [[Bad Brains]], [[Millions of Dead Cops]] and [[Flipper (band)|Flipper]] by [[Buzz Osbourne]], lead singer and guitarist of [[the Melvins]] and fellow [[Aberdeen, Washington]] native. The Melvins themselves were an important early musical influence on Cobain, with their  heavy, [[grunge music|grungy]] sound mimicked by Nirvana on many songs from ''Bleach''.

Cobain was also a fan of [[protopunk]] acts like [[the Stooges]], whose 1973 album ''[[Raw Power]]'' he listed as his favorite of all time in his journals,&lt;ref name=&quot;Cobain, Kurt 2002&quot;/&gt; and [[The Velvet Underground]], whose 1968 song &quot;[[Here She Comes Now]]&quot; the band covered both live and in the studio.

The 1980s American [[alternative rock]] band [[the Pixies|Pixies]] were instrumental in helping an adult Cobain develop his own songwriting style. In a 1992 interview with ''[[Melody Maker]]'', Cobain said that hearing their 1988 debut album, ''[[Surfer Rosa]]'', &quot;convinced him to abandon his more Black Flag-influenced songwriting in favor of the [[Iggy Pop]]/Aerosmith–type songwriting that appeared on ''[[Nevermind]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Cobain, Kurt. &quot;Kurt Cobain of Nirvana Talks About the Records That Changed His Life. ''[[Melody Maker]]''. August 29, 1992.&lt;/ref&gt; In a 1993 interview with ''[[Rolling Stone]]'', he said that &quot;[[Smells Like Teen Spirit]]&quot; was his attempt at &quot;trying to rip off the Pixies. I have to admit it. When I heard the Pixies for the first time, I connected with that band so heavily that I should have been in that band—or at least a Pixies cover band. We used their sense of dynamics, being soft and quiet and then loud and hard.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;pixies&quot;&gt;Fricke, David. &quot;Kurt Cobain: The Rolling Stone Interview.&quot; ''Rolling Stone''. January 27, 1994&lt;/ref&gt;

Cobain's appreciation of early alternative rock bands also extended to [[Sonic Youth]] and [[R.E.M.]], both of which the members of Nirvana befriended and looked up to for advice. It was under recommendation from Sonic Youth's [[Kim Gordon]] that Nirvana signed to [[DGC Records|DGC]] in 1990,&lt;ref&gt;Azerrad, 1994. p. 162&lt;/ref&gt; and both bands did a two week tour of Europe in the summer of 1991, as documented in the 1992 documentary, ''[[1991: The Year Punk Broke]].'' In 1993, Cobain said of R.E.M.: &quot;If I could write just a couple of songs as good as what they’ve written … I don’t know how that band does what they do. God, they’re the greatest. They’ve dealt with their success like saints, and they keep delivering great music.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;pixies&quot;/&gt;

After attaining mainstream success, Cobain became a devoted champion of lesser known [[indie rock|indie]] bands, covering songs by the [[Vaselines]],  [[Meat Puppets]], [[Wipers]] and [[Fang (band)|Fang]] onstage and/ or in the studio, wearing [[Daniel Johnston]] [[T-shirts]] during photo shoots, having the [[K Records]] logo tattooed on his forearm, and enlisting bands like [[Butthole Surfers]], [[Shonen Knife]], [[Chokebore]] and [[Half Japanese]] along for the ''[[In Utero]]'' tour in late 1993 and early 1994. Cobain even invited his favorite musicians to perform with him: ex-[[Germs (band)|Germs]] guitarist [[Pat Smear]] joined the band in 1993, and the Meat Puppets appeared onstage during Nirvana's 1993 ''[[MTV Unplugged]]'' appearance to perform three songs from their second album, ''[[Meat Puppets II]]''.

Nirvana's ''Unplugged'' set also included renditions of &quot;[[The Man Who Sold the World (song)|The Man Who Sold the World]],&quot; by British rock musician [[David Bowie]], and the American folk song, &quot;[[In the Pines|Where Did You Sleep Last Night]],&quot; as adapted by the American folk musician, [[Lead Belly]]. Cobain introduced the latter by calling Lead Belly his favorite performer, and in a 1993 interview revealed he had been introduced to him from reading the American author, [[William S. Burroughs]]. &quot;I remember [Burroughs] saying in an interview, “These new rock’n'roll kids should just throw away their guitars and listen to something with real soul, like Leadbelly,'&quot; Cobain said. &quot;I’d never heard about Leadbelly before so I bought a couple of records, and now he turns out to be my absolute favorite of all time in music. I absolutely love it more than any rock’n'roll I ever heard.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Laurence&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |author=Laurence Romance |url=http://romanceisdead.net/spip.php?article30 |title=Kurt Cobain interview Date : 08/10/1993 Location : Seattle Ze Full Version Uncut !!! |publisher=Romance Is Dead |author=Laurence Romance |date=April 21, 2010 |deadurl=no |accessdate=April 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Nirvana's acoustic ''Unplugged'' set, which was released posthumously as [[MTV Unplugged in New York|an album]] in 1994, may have provided a hint of Cobain's future musical direction. The record has drawn comparisons to R.E.M.'s 1992 release, ''[[Automatic for the People]]'',&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |last=Thomas |first=Stephen |url={{Allmusic|class=album|id=r206714|pure_url=yes}} |title=MTV Unplugged in New York – Nirvana |publisher=AllMusic |deadurl=no |accessdate=April 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in 1993, Cobain himself predicted that the next Nirvana album would be &quot;pretty ethereal, acoustic, like R.E.M.'s last album.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;pixies&quot;/&gt;

&quot;Yeah, he talked a lot about what direction he was heading in,&quot; Cobain's friend, R.E.M.'s lead singer [[Michael Stipe]], told ''[[Newsweek]]'' in 1994. &quot;I mean, I know what the next Nirvana recording was going to sound like. It was going to be very quiet and acoustic, with lots of stringed instruments. It was going to be an amazing fucking record, and I’m a little bit angry at him for killing himself. He and I were going to record a trial run of the album, a demo tape. It was all set up. He had a plane ticket. He had a car picking him up. And at the last minute he called and said, 'I can't come.' Stipe was chosen as the godfather of Cobain and [[Courtney Love]]'s daughter, [[Frances Bean Cobain]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;September1994&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |author= |url=http://www.newsweek.com/1994/09/25/everybody-hurts-sometime.html |title=Everybody Hurts Sometime |work=Newsweek |date=September 26, 1994 |deadurl=no |accessdate=April 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Artistry ==

Dave Grohl stated that Cobain believed that music comes first and lyrics, second. Cobain focused, foremost, on the melodies of his songs.&lt;ref name=classicalbums&gt;{{cite video |title=Classic Albums—Nirvana: Nevermind |format=DVD |publisher=Isis Productions |date=2004 |quote=Kurt used to say that music comes first and lyrics comes second, and I think Kurt's main focus was melody}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cobain complained when fans and rock journalists attempted to decipher his singing and extract meaning from his lyrics, writing &quot;Why in the hell do journalists insist on coming up with a second-rate [[Sigmund Freud|Freudian]] evaluation of my lyrics, when 90 percent of the time they've transcribed them incorrectly?&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cross, p. 182&quot;&gt;Cross 2001, p. 182&lt;/ref&gt; While Cobain would insist on the subjectivity and unimportance of his lyrics, he was known to labor and procrastinate in writing them, often changing the content and order of lyrics during performances.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cross 2001, p. 177&quot;&gt;Cross 2001, p. 177&lt;/ref&gt; Cobain would describe his lyrics himself as &quot;a big pile of contradictions. They're split down the middle between very sincere opinions that I have and sarcastic opinions and feelings that I have and sarcastic and hopeful, humorous rebuttals toward cliché [[Bohemianism|bohemian]] ideals that have been exhausted for years.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Sliver: The Best of the Box'' album booklet.&lt;/ref&gt;

Cobain originally wanted ''Nevermind'' to be divided into two sides: a &quot;Boy&quot; side, for the songs written about the experiences of his early life and childhood, and a &quot;Girl&quot; side, for the songs written about his dysfunctional relationship with Tobi Vail.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cross 2001, p. 177&quot;/&gt; Charles R. Cross would write &quot;In the four months following their break-up, Kurt would write a half dozen of his most memorable songs, all of them about Tobi Vail&quot;. Though &quot;Lithium&quot; had been written before Cobain knew Vail, the lyrics of the song were changed to reference her.&lt;ref&gt;Cross 2001, pp. 168–69&lt;/ref&gt; Cobain would say in an interview with ''[[Musician (magazine)|Musician]]'' that &quot;some of my very personal experiences, like breaking up with girlfriends and having bad relationships, feeling that death void that the person in the song is feeling. Very lonely, sick.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Morris, Chris. &quot;The Year's Hottest Band Can't Stand Still&quot;. ''Musician'', January 1992.&lt;/ref&gt; While Cobain would regard ''In Utero'' &quot;for the most part very impersonal&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Savage, Jon. &quot;Sounds Dirty: The Truth About Nirvana&quot;. ''The Observer''. August 15, 1993.&lt;/ref&gt; on the album he dealt with the childhood divorce of his parents, his newfound fame and the public image and perception of himself and [[Courtney Love]] on &quot;Serve the Servants&quot;, with his enamored relationship with Love conveyed through lyrical themes of pregnancy and the female anatomy on &quot;[[Heart-Shaped Box]]&quot;. Cobain wrote &quot;[[Rape Me]]&quot; not only as an objective discussion of rape, but a metaphorical protest against his treatment by the media. He wrote about fame, drug addiction and abortion on &quot;[[Pennyroyal Tea]]&quot;, as well as women's rights and the life of Seattle-born [[Frances Farmer]] on &quot;Frances Farmer Will Have Her Revenge on Seattle&quot;.

Cobain was affected enough to write the song &quot;[[Polly (song)|Polly]]&quot; from ''Nevermind'', after reading a newspaper story of an incident in 1987, where a young girl was kidnapped after attending a punk rock show{{who|date=November 2011}}, then raped and tortured with a [[blow torch|blowtorch]]. She managed to escape after gaining the trust of her captor through flirting with him.&lt;ref&gt;Cross, p. 136&lt;/ref&gt; After seeing Nirvana perform, [[Bob Dylan]] would cite &quot;Polly&quot; as the best of Nirvana's songs, and was quoted as saying about Cobain, &quot;the kid has heart&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Cross 2001, p. 137&lt;/ref&gt; [[Patrick Süskind]], whose novel ''[[Perfume (novel)|Perfume: The Story of a Murderer]]'' inspired Cobain to write the song &quot;Scentless Apprentice&quot; from ''In Utero''. The book is an historical horror novel about a [[perfumer]]'s apprentice born with no body odor of his own but with a highly developed sense of smell, and who attempts to create the &quot;ultimate perfume&quot; by killing virginal women and taking their scent.&lt;ref&gt;Gaar 2006, pp. 42–43&lt;/ref&gt;

Cobain immersed himself in artistic projects throughout his life, as much so as he did in songwriting. The sentiments of his art work followed the same subjects of his lyrics, often expressed through a dark and macabre sense of humor. Noted was his fascination with [[physiology]], his own rare medical conditions, and the human anatomy. Often unable to afford artistic resources, Cobain would improvise with materials, painting on board games and album sleeves, and painting with an array of substances, including his own bodily fluids. The artwork seen in his ''Journals'' would later draw acclaim as being of a high artistic standard. Many of Cobain's paintings, collages, and sculptures would appear in the artwork of Nirvana's albums. His artistic concepts would feature notably in Nirvana's music videos; the production and direction of which were acrimonious due to the artistic perfectionism of his visions.

Cobain would contribute backing guitar for a [[spoken word]] recording of beat poet [[William S. Burroughs]]' entitled &quot;[[the &quot;Priest&quot; they called him]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Cross, p. 301&lt;/ref&gt; Cobain regarded Burroughs as a hero. During Nirvana's European tour Cobain kept a copy of Burroughs' ''[[Naked Lunch]]'', purchased in a London bookstall.&lt;ref&gt;Cross, pp. 189-190&lt;/ref&gt;

==Relationships and family==
===Courtney Love===
[[Courtney Love]] and Cobain met on January 12, 1990, in Portland's [[Satyricon nightclub]],&lt;ref&gt;“Heavier Than Heaven,” page 201, biography by Charles R. Cross&lt;/ref&gt; when they both still led ardent underground rock bands.&lt;ref&gt;Barton, Laura. [http://music.guardian.co.uk/rock/story/0,,1969245,00.html &quot;Love me do&quot;], Guardian Unlimited, December 11, 2006: &quot;They met in 1989 at an L7 concert, when they were both fledgling musicians with burgeoning drug addictions...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Love made advances, but Cobain was evasive. Early in their interactions, Cobain broke off dates and ignored Love’s advances because he was unsure if he wanted a relationship. Cobain noted, &quot;I was determined to be a bachelor for a few months [...] But I knew that I liked Courtney so much right away that it was a really hard struggle to stay away from her for so many months.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Azerrad, pp. 172–173&lt;/ref&gt;
Courtney Love first saw Cobain perform in 1989 at a show in [[Portland, Oregon]]; they talked briefly after the show and Love developed a crush on him.&lt;ref&gt;Azerrad, p. 169&lt;/ref&gt;

Cobain was already aware of Love through her role in the 1987 film ''[[Straight to Hell (film)|Straight to Hell]]''. According to journalist [[Everett True]], the pair were formally introduced at an [[L7 (band)|L7]] and [[Butthole Surfers]] concert in Los Angeles in May 1991.&lt;ref name=&quot;WednesdayMarch&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://planbmag.com/blogs/staff/2006/03/01/wednesday-1-march/ |title=Wednesday 1&amp;nbsp;March |author=Everett True |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080206065138/http://planbmag.com/blogs/staff/2006/03/01/wednesday-1-march/ |archivedate=2008-02-06 |deadurl=yes |accessdate=April 6, 2012}} Plan B Magazine Blogs. March 1, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; In the weeks that followed, after learning from Dave Grohl that Cobain shared mutual interests with her, Love began pursuing Cobain. In late 1991 the two were often together and bonded through drug use.&lt;ref name=&quot;Azerrad172&quot;&gt;Azerrad, p. 172. Courtney Love: &quot;We bonded over pharmaceuticals.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

Around the time of Nirvana's 1992 performance on ''[[Saturday Night Live]]'', Love discovered that she was pregnant with Cobain's child. On February 24, 1992, a few days after the conclusion of Nirvana's [[Pacific Rim]] tour, Cobain and Love were married on [[Waikiki Beach]] in Hawaii. Love wore a satin and lace dress once owned by the actress [[Frances Farmer]], and Cobain wore green pajamas, because he had been &quot;too lazy to put on a tux&quot;. In an interview with ''[[The Guardian]]'', Love revealed the opposition to their marriage from various people: &quot;[[Kim Gordon]] [of [[Sonic Youth]]] sits me down and says, 'If you marry him your life is not going to happen, it will destroy your life.' But I said, 'Whatever! I love him, and I want to be with him!'... It wasn't his fault. He wasn't trying to do that.&quot;

=== Frances Bean Cobain ===
On August 18, 1992, the couple's daughter [[Frances Bean Cobain]] was born.

In a 1992 article in ''[[Vanity Fair (magazine)|Vanity Fair]]'', Love admitted to using heroin, not knowing that she was pregnant. Love claimed that ''Vanity Fair'' had misquoted her,&lt;ref&gt;Azerrad, p. 266&lt;/ref&gt; but the event created a media controversy for the couple. While Cobain and Love's romance had always been a media attraction, they found themselves hounded by tabloid reporters after the article was published, many wanting to know if Frances was addicted to drugs at birth. The Los Angeles County Department of Children's Services took the Cobains to court, claiming that the couple's drug usage made them unfit parents.&lt;ref name=&quot;Azerrad270&quot;&gt;Azerrad, p. 270&lt;/ref&gt; Two-week-old Frances was ordered by the judge to be taken from their custody and placed with Courtney's sister Jamie for several weeks, after which the couple obtained custody in an exchange agreement to submit to urine tests and regular visits from a social worker. After months of legal wrangling, the couple were eventually granted full custody of their daughter.

== Health history ==
Throughout most of his life, Cobain suffered from chronic [[bronchitis]] and intense physical pain due to an undiagnosed chronic stomach condition.&lt;ref&gt;Azerrad, p. 66&lt;/ref&gt; His first drug experience was with [[cannabis (drug)|marijuana]] in 1980, at age 13. He regularly used the drug during adulthood.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cross, p. 76&quot;&gt;Cross, p. 76&lt;/ref&gt; Cobain also had a period of consuming &quot;notable&quot; amounts of [[LSD]], as observed by Tracy Marander,&lt;ref&gt;Cross, p. 75&lt;/ref&gt; and was &quot;really into getting fucked up: drugs, acid, any kind of drug&quot;, observed Krist Novoselic; Cobain was also prone to alcoholism and [[solvent abuse]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Cross, p. 76&quot;/&gt; Cobain's cousin Beverly, a nurse, claimed Cobain was diagnosed with [[attention-deficit hyperactivity disorder]] as a child, and [[bipolar disorder]] as an adult. She also brought attention to the history of suicide, [[mental illness]] and alcoholism in the Cobain family, noting two of her uncles who had committed suicide with guns.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ahealthyme.com/topic/cobainqa |title=Even in His Youth |work=AHealthyMe.com |author=Brian Libby |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20070202043704/http://www.ahealthyme.com/topic/cobainqa |archivedate=2007-02-02 |accessdate=April 5, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cobain's stomach condition was emotionally debilitating to him, and he intermittently tried to find its cause, usually at the insistence of Love. None of the many doctors he consulted were able to pinpoint the specific cause though some suggested he was suffering from a rare form of cancer. He suffered from an acute self-consciousness and developed a poor body image, due to his low body weight; which was primarily due to malnourishment caused by his stomach condition, medicines taken as part of treatment for cancer and poor diet (attested to by numerous doctors), or a combination of all three.

Cobain's first experience with heroin occurred sometime in 1986, administered to him by a local drug dealer in [[Tacoma, Washington]] who had previously supplied him with [[Percodan]].&lt;ref&gt;Azerrad, p. 41&lt;/ref&gt; He used heroin sporadically for several years, but, by the end of 1990, his use developed into a full-fledged [[Substance use disorder|addiction]]. Cobain claimed that he was &quot;determined to get a habit&quot; as a way to self-medicate his stomach condition. &quot;It started with three days in a row of doing heroin and I don't have a stomach pain. That was such a relief,&quot; he related.&lt;ref&gt;Azerrad, p. 236&lt;/ref&gt;

His heroin use began to affect the band's ''Nevermind'' supporting tour. One memorable example came the day of the band's 1992 performance on ''Saturday Night Live'', where Nirvana had a photographic session with photographer Michael Levine. Having taken heroin beforehand, Cobain fell asleep several times during the shoot. Cobain divulged to biographer [[Michael Azerrad]], &quot;I mean, what are they supposed to do? They're not going to be able to tell me to stop. So I really didn't care. Obviously to them it was like practicing [[witchcraft]] or something. They didn't know anything about it so they thought that any second, I was going to die.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Azerrad, p. 241&lt;/ref&gt;

Slowly, Cobain's heroin addiction worsened. His first attempt at [[Drug rehabilitation|rehab]] was made in early 1992, not long after he and Love discovered they were going to become parents. Immediately after leaving rehab, Nirvana embarked on their Australian tour, with Cobain appearing pale and gaunt while suffering through [[withdrawal]]s. Not long after returning home, Cobain's heroin use resumed.

Prior to a performance at the New Music Seminar in New York City in July 1993, Cobain suffered a heroin overdose. Rather than calling for an ambulance, Love injected Cobain with [[naloxone|Narcan]] to bring him out of his unconscious state. Cobain proceeded to perform with Nirvana, giving the public no indication that anything out of the ordinary had taken place.&lt;ref&gt;Cross, pp. 296–297&lt;/ref&gt;

== Death ==
{{Main|Death of Kurt Cobain}}
Following a tour stop at [[Munich-Riem airport|Terminal Eins]] in Munich, Germany, on March 1, 1994, Cobain was diagnosed with [[bronchitis]] and severe [[laryngitis]]. He flew to Rome the next day for medical treatment, and was joined there by his wife, Courtney Love, on March 3, 1994. The next morning, Love awoke to find that Cobain had overdosed on a combination of champagne and [[flunitrazepam|Rohypnol]]. Cobain was immediately rushed to the hospital, and spent the rest of the day unconscious. After five days in the hospital, Cobain was released and returned to Seattle.&lt;ref name=&quot;Halperin&quot;/&gt; Love later stated that the incident was Cobain's first [[suicide attempt]].&lt;ref name=&quot;life after death&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.rollingstone.com/artists/courtneylove/articles/story/5937442/life_after_death |title=Courtney Love: Life After Death |work=Rolling Stone |author=David Fricke |date=December 15, 1994 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20090413090248/http://www.rollingstone.com/artists/courtneylove/articles/story/5937442/life_after_death |archivedate=2009-04-13 |accessdate=April 5, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On March 18, 1994, Love phoned Seattle police informing them that Cobain was suicidal and had locked himself in a room with a gun. Police arrived and confiscated several guns and a bottle of pills from Cobain, who insisted that he was not suicidal and had locked himself in the room to hide from Love. When questioned by police, Love said that Cobain had never mentioned that he was suicidal and that she had not seen him with a gun.&lt;ref name=&quot;Seattle1994&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |author=[[Seattle Police Department]] |year=1994 |title=Incident Report&amp;nbsp;— March&amp;nbsp;18|url=http://www.justiceforkurt.com/investigation/documents/march_18_report.shtml |accessdate=March 13, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Love arranged an [[Intervention (counseling)|intervention]] regarding Cobain's drug use on March 25, 1994. The ten people involved included musician friends, record company executives, and one of Cobain's closest friends, [[Dylan Carlson]]. The intervention was initially unsuccessful, with an angry Cobain insulting and heaping scorn on its participants and eventually locking himself in the upstairs bedroom. However, by the end of the day, Cobain had agreed to undergo a [[detoxification|detox]] program.&lt;ref name=&quot;The1994&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |work=[[The Seattle Times]] |year=1994| title=Questions Linger After Cobain Suicide |url=http://www.justiceforkurt.com/coverage/newspapers/seattle_times.shtml |accessdate=March 13, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cobain arrived at the Exodus Recovery Center in Los Angeles, California on March 30, 1994. The staff at the facility were unaware of Cobain's history of depression and prior attempts at suicide. When visited by friends, there was no indication to them that Cobain was in any negative or suicidal state of mind. He spent the day talking to counselors about his drug abuse and personal problems, happily playing with his daughter Frances. These interactions were the last time Cobain saw his daughter. The following night, Cobain walked outside to have a cigarette, and climbed over a six-foot-high fence to leave the facility (which he had joked earlier in the day would be a stupid feat to attempt). He took a taxi to Los Angeles Airport and flew back to Seattle. On the flight, he sat next to [[Duff McKagan]] of [[Guns N' Roses]]. Despite Cobain's own personal animosity towards [[Guns N' Roses]] and specifically [[Axl Rose]], Cobain &quot;seemed happy&quot; to see McKagan. McKagan later stated he knew from &quot;all of my instincts that something was wrong.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Cross, p. 331&lt;/ref&gt; On April 2 and April 3, 1994, Cobain was spotted in various locations around Seattle, although most of his close friends and family were unaware of his whereabouts. He was not seen on April 4, 1994. On April 3, 1994, Love contacted a private investigator, [[Tom Grant (private investigator)|Tom Grant]], and hired him to find Cobain. On April 7, 1994, amid rumors of Nirvana breaking up, the band pulled out of that year's [[Lollapalooza]] music festival.

On April 8, 1994, Cobain's body was discovered at his [[Denny-Blaine, Seattle, Washington|Lake Washington]] home by an electrician who had arrived to install a security system. Apart from a minor amount of blood coming out of Cobain's ear, the electrician reported seeing no visible signs of [[Physical trauma|trauma]], and initially believed that Cobain was asleep until he saw the shotgun pointing at his chin. A note was found, addressed to Cobain's childhood [[imaginary friend]] &quot;Boddah&quot;, that stated that Cobain hadn't &quot;felt the excitement of listening to as well as creating music, along with really writing . . . for too many years now&quot;. A high concentration of heroin and traces of [[diazepam]] were also found in his body. Cobain's body had been lying there for days; the coroner's report estimated Cobain to have died on April 5, 1994.&lt;ref name=&quot;Liu2009&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |author=Liu, Marian |date=April 6, 2009 |title=Kurt Cobain's death, 15 years later, being marked with Friday tribute |url=http://seattletimes.nwsource.com/html/musicnightlife/2008993909_zmus06dispatchcobain.html |publisher=Seattle Times |deadurl=no |accessdate=April 6, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A public vigil was held for Cobain on April 10, 1994, at a park at [[Seattle Center]] drawing approximately seven thousand mourners.&lt;ref&gt;Azerrad, p. 346&lt;/ref&gt; Prerecorded messages by Krist Novoselic and Courtney Love were played at the memorial. Love read portions of Cobain's suicide note to the crowd, crying and chastising Cobain. Near the end of the vigil, Love arrived at the park and distributed some of Cobain's clothing to those who still remained.&lt;ref&gt;Azerrad, p. 350&lt;/ref&gt; Dave Grohl would say that the news of Cobain's death was &quot;probably the worst thing that has happened to me in my life. I remember the day after that I woke up and I was heartbroken that he was gone. I just felt like, 'Okay, so I get to wake up today and have another day and he doesn't.'&quot; He also believed that he knew Cobain would die at an early age, saying that &quot;sometimes you just can't save someone from themselves,&quot; and &quot;in some ways, you kind of prepare yourself emotionally for that to be a reality.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;DaveGrohl&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.nme.com/news/nirvana/48303 |title=Dave Grohl: 'I knew Kurt Cobain was destined to die early' |work=NME |location=UK  |date= |accessdate=August 14, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dave Reed, who for a short time was Cobain's foster father, said that &quot;he had the desperation, not the courage, to be himself. Once you do that, you can't go wrong, because you can't make any mistakes when people love you for being yourself. But for Kurt, it didn't matter that other people loved him; he simply didn't love himself enough.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cross, p. 351&quot;&gt;Cross, p. 351&lt;/ref&gt;

A final ceremony was arranged for Cobain by his mother on May 31, 1999, attended by both Courtney Love and Tracy Marander. As a Buddhist monk chanted, his daughter Frances Bean scattered his ashes into McLane Creek in Olympia, the city where he &quot;had found his true artistic muse.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cross, p. 351&quot;/&gt;

Cobain's artistic endeavors and struggles with [[heroin addiction]], illness and depression, as well as the circumstances of [[Death of Kurt Cobain|his death]] have become a frequent topic of fascination, debate, and controversy throughout the world.  He is one of the well known members of the [[27 Club]].

== Legacy ==
[[File:Viretta Park bench 04.jpg|thumb|A bench in Viretta Park has become a notable memorial to Cobain.]] [[File:Welcome to Aberdeen cropped.jpg|thumb|In 2005, a sign was put up in [[Aberdeen, Washington]], that reads &quot;Welcome to Aberdeen – Come As You Are&quot; as a tribute to Cobain.]]
Cobain has been remembered as one of the most iconic rock musicians in the history of alternative music. He was ranked by ''Rolling Stone'' as the 73rd greatest guitarist and 45th greatest singer of all time,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.rollingstone.com/music/lists/100-greatest-guitarists-20111123/kurt-cobain-19691231 |title= 100 Greatest Guitarists of All Time 12: Kurt Cobain |work=[[Rolling Stone]] |deadurl=no |accessdate=April 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.rollingstone.com/music/lists/100-greatest-singers-of-all-time-19691231/kurt-cobain-19691231 |title= 100 Greatest Singers of All Time 45: Kurt Cobain |work= Rolling Stone |deadurl=no |accessdate=April 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and by MTV as 7th in the &quot;22 Greatest Voices in Music&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Enigmazach2009&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |author=enigmazach |url=http://www.listology.com/list/mtvs-22-greatest-voices-music |title=MTV's 22 Greatest Voices in Music |publisher=Listology |date=June 30, 2009 |deadurl=no |accessdate=April 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2006, he was placed at number twenty by ''[[Hit Parader]]'' on their list of the &quot;100 Greatest Metal Singers of All Time&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oz&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |author=oz |url=http://www.hearya.com/2006/12/04/hit-paraders-top-100-metal-vocalists-of-all-time/ |title=Hit Parader’s Top 100 Metal Vocalists of All Time – HearYa – Indie Music Blog |publisher=Hearya.com |date=December 4, 2006 |deadurl=no |accessdate=April 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reflecting on Cobain's death over ten years later, [[MSNBC]]'s Eric Olsen wrote, &quot;In the intervening decade, Cobain, a small, frail but handsome man in life, has become an abstract Generation X icon, viewed by many as the 'last real rock star' [. . .] a messiah and martyr whose every utterance has been plundered and parsed&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;10 years later&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://today.msnbc.msn.com/id/4652653 |title=10 years later, Cobain lives on in his music |work=[[MSNBC|MSNBC.com]] |author=Eric Olsen |date=April 9, 2004 |deadurl=no |accessdate=April 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005, a sign was put up in [[Aberdeen, Washington]], that read &quot;Welcome to Aberdeen&amp;nbsp;– Come As You Are&quot; as a tribute to Cobain. The sign was paid for and created by the Kurt Cobain Memorial Committee, a non-profit organization created in May 2004 to honour Cobain. The Committee planned to create a Kurt Cobain Memorial Park and a youth center in Aberdeen. Because Cobain was cremated and his remains scattered into the [[Wishkah River]] in Washington,&lt;ref name=&quot;KurtCobain&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.findagrave.com/cgi-bin/fg.cgi?page=gr&amp;GRid=1488 |title=Kurt Cobain (1967–1994) – Find A Grave Memorial |publisher=Findagrave.com |date= |accessdate=August 14, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; many Nirvana fans visit [[Viretta Park]], near Cobain's former [[Lake Washington]] home, to pay tribute. On the anniversary of his death, fans gather in the park to celebrate his life and memory.

In 2006, Cobain took the place of [[Elvis Presley]] as the top-earning deceased celebrity, after the sale of the Nirvana song catalogue. Presley reclaimed the spot in 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.forbes.com/business/2007/10/29/dead-celebrity-earning-biz-media-deadcelebs07_cz_lg_1029celeb_land.html |title=Courtney Love: Life After Death |work=[[Forbes]] |author=Lea Goldman and David M. Ewalt, eds |date=October 29, 2007 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20071101050914/http://www.forbes.com/business/2007/10/29/dead-celebrity-earning-biz-media-deadcelebs07_cz_lg_1029celeb_land.html |archivedate=2007-11-01 |accessdate=April 5, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Controversy erupted in July 2009 when a monument to Cobain in Aberdeen along the [[Wishkah River]] included the quote &quot;...Drugs are bad for you. They will fuck you up.&quot; The city ultimately decided to sandblast the monument to replace the expletive with &quot;f---&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=The Daily World: Park’s four-letter controversy erased |url=http://tdw.thedailyworld.com/content/park%E2%80%99s_four_letter_controversy_erased_0 |work=TheDailyWorld.com |deadurl=no |date=August 7, 2009 |accessdate=April 5, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; but fans immediately drew the letters back in.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Seattle Weekly: You Can Sandblast All You Want, But Drugs Will Still Fuck You Up |url=http://blogs.seattleweekly.com/reverb/2009/08/you_can_sandblast_all_you_want.php |author=Chris Kornelis |date=August 17, 2009 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20110721193533/http://blogs.seattleweekly.com/reverb/2009/08/you_can_sandblast_all_you_want.php |archivedate=2011-07-21 |accessdate=April 6, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The monument and bridge have become popular places for fans to leave tributes.

[[Gus Van Sant]] loosely based his 2005 movie ''[[Last Days (film)|Last Days]]'' on the events in the final days of Cobain's life. In January 2007, Courtney Love began to shop the biography ''Heavier Than Heaven'' to various movie studios in Hollywood to turn the book into an [[A-list]] feature film about Cobain and Nirvana. The video game ''[[Guitar Hero 5]]'' features Cobain as a playable character.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.independent.co.uk/opinion/columnists/tim-walker/tim-walker-in-guitar-hero-a-virtual-kurt-cobain-can-appear-on-stage-with-bon-jovi-1782715.html |title=Tim Walker: 'In Guitar Hero, a virtual Kurt Cobain can appear on stage with Bon Jovi' |work=[[The Independent]] |date=September 7, 2009 |deadurl=no |accessdate=April 6, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the inclusion of Cobain incensed surviving bandmates Krist Novoselic and Dave Grohl and wife Courtney Love, expressing their dismay at the ability to use Cobain with any song, including those sung by female vocalists.&lt;ref name=&quot;Swash2009&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |author=Swash, Rosie |title=Kurt Cobain video game Guitar Hero gives Love a bad name |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/music/2009/sep/11/guitar-hero-upsets-nirvana-fans |work=The Guardian |location=London |date=September 11, 2009 |deadurl=no |accessdate=April 6, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Books and films on Cobain ===
Prior to Cobain's death, writer Michael Azerrad published ''[[Come as You Are: The Story of Nirvana]]'', a book chronicling Nirvana's career from its beginning, as well as the personal histories of the band members. The book explored Cobain's drug addiction, as well as the countless controversies surrounding the band. After Cobain's death, Azerrad re-published the book to include a final chapter discussing the last year of Cobain's life. The book is notable, as it involved the band members themselves, who provided interviews and personal information to Azerrad specifically for the book. In 2006, Azerrad's taped conversations with Cobain were transformed into a documentary about Cobain, titled ''[[Kurt Cobain: About a Son]]''. Though this film does not feature any music by Nirvana, it has songs by the artists that inspired Cobain.

In the 1998 documentary ''[[Kurt &amp; Courtney]]'', filmmaker [[Nick Broomfield]] investigated Tom Grant's claim that Cobain was actually murdered. He took a film crew to visit a number of people associated with Cobain and Love; Love's father, Cobain's aunt, and one of the couple's former nannies. Broomfield also spoke to [[The Mentors|Mentors]] bandleader [[Eldon Hoke|Eldon &quot;El Duce&quot; Hoke]], who claimed Love offered him $50,000 to kill Cobain. Although Hoke claimed he knew who killed Cobain, he failed to mention a name, and offered no evidence to support his assertion. Broomfield inadvertently captured Hoke's last interview, as he died days later, reportedly hit by a train. However, Broomfield felt he hadn't uncovered enough evidence to conclude the existence of a conspiracy. In a 1998 interview, Broomfield summed it up by saying, &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;I think that he committed suicide. I don't think there's a smoking gun. And I think there's only one way you can explain a lot of things around his death. Not that he was murdered, but that there was just a lack of caring for him. I just think that Courtney had moved on, and he was expendable.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.minireviews.com/interviews/broomfield.htm |title=Kurt and Courtney: Interview with Nick Broomfield |work=Minireviews.com |author=Prairie Miller |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20010301212925/http://www.minireviews.com/interviews/broomfield.htm |archivedate=2001-03-01 |accessdate=April 5, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Journalists [[Ian Halperin]] and [[Max Wallace]] took a similar path and attempted to investigate any possible conspiracy for themselves. Their initial work, the 1999 book ''Who Killed Kurt Cobain?'' argued that, while there wasn't enough evidence to prove a conspiracy, there was more than enough to demand that the case be reopened.&lt;ref&gt;Halperin &amp; Wallace, p. 202&lt;/ref&gt; A notable element of the book included their discussions with Grant, who had taped nearly every conversation that he had undertaken while he was in Love's employ. Over the next several years, Halperin and Wallace collaborated with Grant to write a second book, 2004's ''[[Love and Death: The Murder of Kurt Cobain]]''.

In 2001, writer [[Charles R. Cross]] published a biography of Cobain titled ''[[Heavier Than Heaven]]''. For the book, Cross conducted over 400 interviews, and was given access by Courtney Love to Cobain's journals, lyrics, and diaries.&lt;ref name=&quot;Heavierthan&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.hyperionbooks.com/book/heavier-than-heaven-a-biography-of-kurt-cobain/ |title=Heavier than Heaven: A Biography of Kurt Cobain| publisher=HyperionBooks.com |accessdate=July 26, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cross' biography was met with criticism, including allegations of Cross accepting secondhand (and incorrect) information as fact.&lt;ref&gt;''Nirvana: the True Story'' by [[Everett True]]&lt;/ref&gt; Friend [[Everett True]], who derided the book as being inaccurate, omissive, and highly biased; he said ''Heavier than Heaven'' was &quot;the Courtney-sanctioned version of history&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;SmellsLike2007&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.thestranger.com/seattle/Content?oid=184892 |title=Smells Like Everett True – Books – The Stranger, Seattle's Only Newspaper |publisher=Thestranger.com |date=March 27, 2007 |deadurl=no |accessdate=April 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; or, alternatively, Cross's “Oh, I think I need to find the new [[Bruce Springsteen]] now” Kurt Cobain book.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.magnetmagazine.com/interviews/true.html |title=MAGNET Interview: Everett True |work=magnetmagazine.com |author=Matthew Fritch |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20030617162627/http://magnetmagazine.com/interviews/true.html |archivedate=2003-06-17 |accessdate=April 5, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, beyond the criticism, the book contained many details about Cobain and Nirvana's career that would have otherwise been unnoted. Additionally, in 2008 Cross published ''Cobain Unseen: Mosaic of an Artist'', a compilation of annotated photographs and creations and writings by Cobain throughout his life and career.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.rollingstone.com/photos/gallery/23454963/cobain_unseen_rare_photos_artw/photo/17 |title=Cobain Unseen: Rare Photos, Artwork and Journal Entries |work=Rolling Stone |author=Charles M. Cross |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20081020044620/http://www.rollingstone.com/photos/gallery/23454963/cobain_unseen_rare_photos_artw/photo/17 |archivedate=2008-10-20 |accessdate=April 5, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2002, a sampling of Cobain's writings was published as ''[[Journals (Cobain)|Journals]]''. The book fills 280 pages with a simple black cover; the pages are arranged somewhat chronologically (although Cobain generally did not date them). The journal pages are reproduced in color, and there is a section added at the back with explanations and transcripts of some of the less legible pages. The writings begin in the late 1980s and were continued until his death. A paperback version of the book, released in 2003, included a handful of writings that were not offered in the initial release. In the journals, Cobain talked about the ups and downs of life on the road, made lists of what music he was enjoying, and often scribbled down lyric ideas for future reference. Upon its release, reviewers and fans were conflicted about the collection. Many were elated to be able to learn more about Cobain and read his inner thoughts in his own words, but were disturbed by what was viewed as an [[invasion of privacy|invasion of his privacy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nd.edu/~observer/11192002/Scene/0.html |title=Nirvana releases a hit and miss |work=Notre Dame Observer |date=November 19, 2002 |author=David Hartwig |deadurl=no |accessdate=April 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009, [[ECW Press]] released a book titled ''Grunge is Dead: The Oral History of Seattle Rock Music''. It was written by Greg Prato, featuring portions about Nirvana and Kurt Cobain's life and death (including new interviews with bandmates and friends), as well as exploring the history of grunge in great detail. A picture of Cobain from the ''Bleach'' era is used for the book's front cover, and its title comes from a shirt that Cobain was once photographed wearing.&lt;ref name=&quot;GrungeIs&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ecwpress.com/book/grunge-dead |title=Grunge Is Dead: The Oral History of Seattle Rock Music |work=ECW Press |author=Greg Prato |deadurl=no |accessdate=April 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[List of best-selling music artists]]
* [[List of musicians from Seattle]]
{{Portal bar|Alternative music|Biography|Guitar|LGBT|Seattle|Washington|United States}}

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

== References ==
* Azerrad, Michael. ''Come as You Are: The Story of Nirvana''. Doubleday, 1994. ISBN 0-385-47199-8.
* Burlingame, Jeff. ''Kurt Cobain: Oh Well, Whatever, Nevermind''. Enslow, 2006. ISBN 0-7660-2426-1
* Cross, Charles. ''Heavier Than Heaven: A Biography of Kurt Cobain''. Hyperion, 2001. ISBN 0-7868-8402-9.
* Kitts, Jeff, et al. ''Guitar World Presents Nirvana and the Grunge Revolution''. Hal Leonard, 1998. ISBN 0-7935-9006-X.
* Summers, Kim. {{Allmusic|id=p65214/biography|label=''Kurt Cobain''|accessdate=May 9, 2005}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category}}
{{Wikiquote}}
*{{Allmusic|class=artist|id=p65214}}
*{{IMDb name|1052}}
* [http://www.kurtsequipment.com/ The Kurt Cobain Equipment FAQ] – Detailed information on Cobain's guitars, amplifiers, and effects.
* [http://www.thesmokinggun.com/kurt/kurt.html Official police reports into Cobain's death] at [[The Smoking Gun]]
* [http://kurtcobainssuicidenote.com/kurt_cobains_suicide_note_scan.html Kurt Cobain's suicide note]

{{Nirvana (band)}}
{{Courtney Love}}
&lt;!--NOTE: DO ''not'' ADD BISEXUAL CATEGORIES, THEY WILL BE REMOVED AS UNSOURCED. Cobain never went on record as being bisexual&amp;nbsp;— the only primary source quotes him as saying he ''considered'' it.--&gt;
&lt;!--MURDER CATEGORIES SHOULD ''not'' BE INCLUDED. This was a consensus to keep the article NPOV, See Talk Page--&gt;

{{Authority control|VIAF=66668107|LCCN=n/94/074027|GND=119167735|SELIBR=299339}}

{{Persondata
|NAME= Cobain, Kurt Donald
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=
|SHORT DESCRIPTION= American singer, guitarist in Nirvana
|DATE OF BIRTH= February 20, 1967
|PLACE OF BIRTH=[[Aberdeen, Washington]]
|DATE OF DEATH= [[circa|c.]] April 5, 1994
|PLACE OF DEATH=Seattle
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Cobain, Kurt}}
[[Category:Kurt Cobain| ]]
[[Category:1967 births]]
[[Category:1994 deaths]]
[[Category:Alternative rock guitarists]]
[[Category:Alternative rock singers]]
[[Category:American alternative rock musicians]]
[[Category:American diarists]]
[[Category:American feminists]]
[[Category:American male singer-songwriters]]
[[Category:American musicians of French descent]]
[[Category:American musicians of German descent]]
[[Category:American musicians of Irish descent]]
[[Category:American people of Canadian descent]]
[[Category:American people of English descent]]
[[Category:American people of Scottish descent]]
[[Category:American rock singer-songwriters]]
[[Category:Courtney Love]]
[[Category:Feminist musicians]]
[[Category:Grunge musicians]]
[[Category:Homeless people]]
[[Category:LGBT rights activists from the United States]]
[[Category:Male feminists]]
[[Category:Musicians from Washington (state)]]
[[Category:Musicians who committed suicide]]
[[Category:Nirvana (band) members]]
[[Category:People self-identifying as substance abusers]]
[[Category:People with bipolar disorder]]
[[Category:Songwriters from Washington (state)]]
[[Category:Suicides by firearm in Washington (state)]]
[[Category:Writers from Aberdeen, Washington]]
[[Category:Writers from Olympia, Washington]]
[[Category:Writers from Seattle, Washington]]

{{link FA|mk}}

[[ar:كيرت كوباين]]
[[az:Kurt Kobeyn]]
[[be:Курт Кабейн]]
[[be-x-old:Курт Кабэйн]]
[[bg:Кърт Кобейн]]
[[bar:Kurt Cobain]]
[[bs:Kurt Cobain]]
[[ca:Kurt Cobain]]
[[cs:Kurt Cobain]]
[[cy:Kurt Cobain]]
[[da:Kurt Cobain]]
[[pdc:Kurt Cobain]]
[[de:Kurt Cobain]]
[[et:Kurt Cobain]]
[[el:Κερτ Κομπέιν]]
[[es:Kurt Cobain]]
[[eo:Kurt Cobain]]
[[eu:Kurt Cobain]]
[[fa:کرت کوبین]]
[[fr:Kurt Cobain]]
[[ga:Kurt Cobain]]
[[gl:Kurt Cobain]]
[[ko:커트 코베인]]
[[hi:कर्ट कोबेन]]
[[hr:Kurt Cobain]]
[[io:Kurt Cobain]]
[[id:Kurt Cobain]]
[[is:Kurt Cobain]]
[[it:Kurt Cobain]]
[[he:קורט קוביין]]
[[kn:ಕರ್ಟ್ ಕೊಬೈನ್]]
[[ka:კურტ კობეინი]]
[[la:Curtius Cobain]]
[[lv:Kurts Kobeins]]
[[lt:Kurt Cobain]]
[[hu:Kurt Cobain]]
[[mk:Курт Кобејн]]
[[ms:Kurt Cobain]]
[[mn:Курт Кобэйн]]
[[nl:Kurt Cobain]]
[[ja:カート・コバーン]]
[[no:Kurt Cobain]]
[[nn:Kurt Cobain]]
[[oc:Kurt Cobain]]
[[uz:Kurt Cobain]]
[[pl:Kurt Cobain]]
[[pt:Kurt Cobain]]
[[ro:Kurt Cobain]]
[[qu:Kurt Cobain]]
[[ru:Кобейн, Курт]]
[[stq:Kurt Cobain]]
[[sq:Kurt Cobain]]
[[simple:Kurt Cobain]]
[[sk:Kurt Cobain]]
[[sl:Kurt Cobain]]
[[sr:Курт Кобејн]]
[[sh:Kurt Cobain]]
[[su:Kurt Cobain]]
[[fi:Kurt Cobain]]
[[sv:Kurt Cobain]]
[[ta:கர்ட் கோபேன்]]
[[te:కర్ట్ కోబెన్]]
[[th:เคิร์ต โคเบน]]
[[tr:Kurt Cobain]]
[[uk:Курт Кобейн]]
[[vi:Kurt Cobain]]
[[zh:科特·柯本]]</text>
      <sha1>d93a68fmj6z8p44f6wt9eqbjoskhugi</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
