<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Marie Osmond</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>728775</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519842489</id>
      <parentid>519841617</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-25T22:42:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>TV</username>
        <id>16071927</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Other work */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22295">{{Use mdy dates|date=May 2011}}
{{Infobox musical artist  &lt;!-- See Wikipedia:WikiProject Musicians --&gt;
| name                = Marie Osmond
| image                 = Marie_osmond_with_guitar.jpg
| caption            = Osmond with a custom guitar covered in Swarovski Crystals built by Ed Roman Guitars.
| background          = solo_singer
| birth_name          = Olive Marie Osmond
| alias               = Marie Osmond
| birth_date                = {{birth date and age|1959|10|13}}
| origin              = [[Ogden, Utah]], United States
| genre               = [[Country music|Country]], pop
| occupation          = Singer, actress
| years_active        = 1962–{{As of|2010|alt=present}}
| label               = [[MGM Records|MGM]]&lt;br&gt;[[Curb Records|Curb]]&lt;br&gt;[[Polydor Records|Polydor]]
| website                 = {{Official website|http://www.marieosmond.com}}
|spouse                   =  Stephen Craig (2011-)
}}
'''Olive Marie Osmond''' (born October 13, 1959) is an American singer, actress, [[doll]] designer, and a member of the show business family [[The Osmonds]]. Although she was never part of her family's singing group, she gained success as a solo [[country music]] artist in the 1970s and 1980s. Her best known song is a cover of the [[country pop]] ballad &quot;[[Paper Roses]].&quot; In 1976, she and her singer brother [[Donny Osmond]] began hosting the TV variety show ''[[Donny &amp; Marie (1976 TV series)|Donny &amp; Marie]]''.

==Early life==
Born Olive Marie Osmond in [[Ogden, Utah]] to [[Olive Osmond|Olive]] and [[George Osmond]], Marie Osmond was raised as a member of [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]]. The only daughter of nine children, her brothers are Virl, [[Tom Osmond|Tom]], [[Alan Osmond|Alan]], [[Wayne Osmond|Wayne]], [[Merrill Osmond|Merrill]], Jay, [[Donny Osmond|Donny]], and [[Jimmy Osmond]]. From an early age, her brothers maintained a career in show business, singing and performing on national television. Osmond debuted as part of her brothers' act [[The Osmonds|The Osmond Brothers]]&lt;!-- do not change to redlinked &quot;Osmond Brothers&quot; the article The Osmonds is about the brothers --&gt; on the ''[[The Andy Williams Show]]'' when she was three, but generally did not perform with her brothers in the group's television performances through the 1960s.

==Music career==
===1970s===
Aside from her two older brothers (who are deaf), Marie was soon the only family member not involved in the music business. After the initial success of [[The Osmonds]] in 1970, Marie's older brother Donny was gaining success as a solo artist on the Pop Music charts and was becoming a [[teen idol]]. [[The Osmonds]]' management convinced Marie to try her hand as well. She signed with the family's record label, [[MGM Records]] and began making concert appearances with [[The Osmonds]]. Her style was more directed towards [[country music]], in contrast with her brothers' pop music.

In 1973, Osmond cut her first single as a [[solo (music)|solo artist]], &quot;[[Paper Roses]]&quot;. The recording became a No.&amp;nbsp;1 country hit, reached the Top 5 on the ''Billboard'' magazine pop chart, and achieved [[Crossover (music)|crossover]] success. The song earned a [[gold record]] as did the album of the same name. Osmond released another single, &quot;[[My Little Corner of the World|In My Little Corner of the World]]&quot;, and a [[In My Little Corner of the World|same-name album]] in 1974, with both entering the ''Billboard'' Top 40 in 1974.
The title song on her next album ''[[Who's Sorry Now]]'', released in 1975, went to No.&amp;nbsp;20 the month after its release. The title song from Osmond's final solo album of the seventies, ''This Is The Way That I Feel'', reached No.&amp;nbsp;39 within two months of its 1977 release.

In 1974, Osmond had two pop music [[duet]] hits with brother Donny: &quot;[[I'm Leaving It All Up to You]]&quot; and &quot;Morning Side of the Mountain.&quot; The former song was a Top 20 country hit.

===1980s===
In the early 1980s, Osmond's music career went into a brief hiatus while she pursued a career in acting. She turned down the lead role as Sandy in ''[[Grease (film)|Grease]]'' because she didn't approve of the script's moral content,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Huey |first=Steve |url=http://ca.music.yahoo.com/ar-259897-bio--Marie-Osmond |title=Marie Osmond Biography – Yahoo! Music |publisher=Ca.music.yahoo.com |accessdate=May 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the role went to [[Olivia Newton-John]]. She appeared in some [[television|TV movies]] and did voice-over work for children's [[cartoon]]s. Prior to the comeback success of her brother Donny in the late 1980s, Marie made a comeback in country music as a solo artist by signing a deal with [[Curb Records]] in [[Nashville, Tennessee|Nashville]]. In 1985, Marie and [[Dan Seals]] sang a [[duet]] called &quot;[[Meet Me in Montana]]&quot; which became a No.&amp;nbsp;1 country hit that year.

Her follow-up to &quot;Meet Me in Montana&quot; was a solo hit called &quot;[[There's No Stopping Your Heart (song)|There's No Stopping Your Heart]],&quot; which reached No.&amp;nbsp;1 in early 1986 for Marie. Her singles mainly focused on the more-popular [[Countrypolitan]] style. In late 1985, she released the &quot;There's No Stopping Your Heart&quot; album of the same name. In 1986, the single &quot;Read My Lips&quot; became a Top-20 country hit. She hit No.&amp;nbsp;1 again with a [[duet]] with [[Paul Davis (singer)|Paul Davis]] with the song &quot;You're Still New to Me.&quot; The Top-10 hit &quot;I Only Wanted You,&quot; became her last major hit on the Country charts, to date. Osmond continued to release singles throughout much of the '80s, including &quot;I'm In Love And He's In Dallas&quot;.
In 1984, Marie had a single on RCA Records called, &quot;Whos Counting.&quot;  The single charted to only No.&amp;nbsp;82 on Billboard's Hot Country Singles. The single did receive a significant amount of airplay for a couple of weeks.

===1990s===
The last charting single came in 1995 with &quot;What Kind of Man (Walks On a Woman)&quot;.

==Acting career==
In 1976, Osmond and brother Donny began to host their variety show ''[[Donny &amp; Marie (1976 TV series)|Donny &amp; Marie]]'', which ran on [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] until 1979. Osmond's first &quot;made for TV&quot; movie was ''The Gift of Love'' which originally aired on [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] December 5, 1978. The movie was loosely based on the [[O. Henry]] story &quot;[[The Gift of the Magi]].&quot;  Her co-star in the movie was [[Timothy Bottoms]] and she received her first on-screen kiss in this movie. In 1978, she and Donny released their film ''Goin' Coconuts,'' which was not a financial success. The following year, Marie starred in a sitcom pilot titled &quot;Marie.&quot; which did not make the new season schedule and in 1980 she had her own variety show on NBC, also titled ''Marie,'' which only ran for half a season.

Osmond had a recurring role as co-host with [[Jack Palance]] on ABC's documentary series ''[[Ripley's Believe It or Not! (TV series)|Ripley's Believe It or Not!]]'' for two seasons (1985–86), replacing Jack's daughter [[Holly Palance]]. She introduced and narrated segments based on the travels and discoveries of oddity-hunter [[Robert Ripley]]. Following, the singer played her mother, Olive, in the TV movie ''Side By Side: The True Story Of The Osmond Family''. She also starred in the TV movie ''I Married [[Wyatt Earp]]''.

She returned to television first in the short-lived 1995 [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] sitcom ''[[Maybe This Time]]'' and then with brother Donny in 1998 to co-host ''Donny And Marie'', a talk/entertainment show that lasted two seasons. Osmond reappeared as herself in the 2001 TV movie ''Inside The Osmonds'', which showed how the brothers' egos, their father's fiscal mismanagement, and the family's quest to build a multimedia empire led to their downfall. The film was produced by her younger brother, [[Jimmy Osmond]].

In 2004, Osmond had a radio show syndicated to [[adult contemporary]] radio stations, ''Marie And Friends'' that was canceled after 10 months.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=About this ad Marie making airwaves as radio talk-show host|url=http://www.deseretnews.com/article/595074867/Marie-making-airwaves-as-radio-talk-show-host.html?pg=all|publisher=deseretnews.com|accessdate=25 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two years later, she was a judge on the short-lived [[Fox Broadcasting Company|Fox]] celeb reality show competition ''[[Celebrity Duets]]''. It was reported by Entertainment Tonight that Marie will join the daytime cast of [[The Bold and the Beautiful]], a long running CBS soap opera.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.etonline.com/tv/111711_Exclusive_Marie_Osmond_to_Join_The_Bold_and_The_Beautiful/index.html ET Website] ET Website&lt;/ref&gt; but Osmond never appeared.

===Broadway===
She appeared in the [[Broadway theatre|Broadway musical]]s ''[[The King and I]]'' (as Anna) and ''[[The Sound of Music]]'' (as Maria) in the mid-1990s. Marie and her brother [[Donny Osmond|Donny]] recently starred in a new holiday production called ''Donny &amp; Marie – A Broadway Christmas'', which was originally scheduled to play on [[Broadway Theatre|Broadway]] at the [[Marquis Theatre]] from December 9– 19, 2010. The show was then extended till December 30, 2010 and again till January 2, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.broadwayworld.com/article/DONNY_MARIE_A_BROADWAY_CHRISTMAS_to_play_Broadways_Marriott_Marquis_Theatre_this_December_20010101 |title=DONNY &amp; MARIE – A BROADWAY CHRISTMAS to play Broadway's Marriott Marquis Theatre this December |publisher=Broadwayworld.com |accessdate=May 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.playbill.com/news/article/144787-Donny-Maries-A-Broadway-Christmas-Will-Get-Extra-Performances |title=Donny &amp; Marie's A Broadway Christmas Will Get Extra Performances |work=Playbill  |accessdate=May 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.playbill.com/news/article/145810-Donny-Maries-A-Broadway-Christmas-Gets-One-Extra-Performance-on-Jan-2 |title=Donny &amp; Marie's A Broadway Christmas Gets One Extra Performance on Jan.&amp;nbsp;2 |work=Playbill  |accessdate=May 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Other work==
===Talk shows and ''Donny &amp; Marie'' in Las Vegas===
{{Main|Marie (TV series)}}

In 2008, the 750-seat showroom at the Flamingo Hotel in Las Vegas, Nevada, is currently home to ''Donny &amp; Marie'', a 90-minute variety show. The singing siblings are backed by eight dancers and a nine piece band. Both Osmond's sing together at the beginning and end of the show, and have solo segments in between. They recently extended their contract until October 2012. Also in 2008, Osmond had a new talk show in the works that was to have been taped in [[Las Vegas, Nevada|Las Vegas]], Nevada. However, this project was canceled before airing. In 2012, she debuted her new variety show ''Marie'' on October 1, 2012, to 320,000 viewers on [[Hallmark Channel]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.tvmediainsights.com/2012/10/positive-opening-levels-for-new-hallmark-channel-talkers/|accessdate=10-3-12|newspaper=TV Media Insights}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Dancing with the Stars''===
{{Main|Dancing with the Stars (US season 5)}}
On August 29, 2007, it was announced that Osmond would appear as a celebrity contestant on the fifth season of the ABC show, paired with [[Jonathan Roberts (dancer)|Jonathan Roberts]], 2004 US Rising Star Latin Champion. On November 27, 2007, Osmond came in third place on the fifth season of Dancing with the Stars.

===Dolls and embroidery===
In 1991, Osmond debuted her doll line on [[QVC]]. While QVC continues to be a primary source of distribution for her dolls, Osmond also carries her line in retail stores, through internet sales in the USA and worldwide, and direct response. Her first sculpture, a toddler doll she created and named after her mother, &quot;Olive May,&quot; set a collectible record on QVC. Since then, Osmond has sculpted several dolls, including &quot;Remember Me,&quot; &quot;Baby Adora Belle,&quot; &quot;Kissy and Huggs&quot; and her hallmark doll, &quot;Adora Belle.&quot; In 2009, Osmond also debuted her dolls on The Shopping Channel in Canada. In 2009, a 16&quot; vinyl Fashion Doll of Marie Osmond &quot;Grand Finale Fashion&quot; was debuted at Osmond's 50th Birthday party in Las Vegas in celebration of her 50th birthday. Osmond's doll collection has garnered numerous award nominations, including &quot;Trendsetter of the Year&quot; and Dolls magazine's &quot;Awards of Excellence.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marieosmond.com/Bio/tabid/83/Default.aspx Marie Osmond biography] from her website&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2006, Osmond launched an [[embroidery]] machine line, a [[sewing machine]] line, and embroidery designs through [[Bernina Sewing Machine|Bernina]]. She has been featured on the cover of ''[[Designs in Machine Embroidery]]''.

===Crafting===
In 2010, Osmond published a book of handcrafted project designs, ''Marie Osmond’s Heartfelt Giving: Sew and Quilt for Family and Friends''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.martingale-pub.com/store/product_info.php?cPath=_&amp;products_id=1009 Marie Osmond's Heartfelt Giving] at the publisher's website&lt;/ref&gt; (Martingale &amp; Company,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.martingale-pub.com Martingale &amp; Company website] www.martingale-pub.com&lt;/ref&gt;). The book contains step-by-step instructions for more than 20 projects, all designed by Osmond. Projects include her “Paper Roses” quilt, bags, aprons, and gifts for babies, teens, friends, and pets. The book also features several childhood photos.

Osmond has a line of sewing machines with [[Janome]] and a fabric line with Quilting Treasures.

===Children's Miracle Network===
Along with actor [[John Schneider (television actor)|John Schneider]], Osmond co-founded the non-profit organization [[Children's Miracle Network]] in 1983. The CMN is dedicated to saving and improving the lives of children by raising funds for children's hospitals around the world.

===Nutrisystem spokesperson===
As part of the ''Slimsational Stars'', Osmond is currently promoting the [[Nutrisystem]] brand of weight loss meals. She has starred in a number of commercials over the past five years.

==Personal life==
Osmond has been married three times, to two different men. She remarried her first husband, Stephen Lyle Craig, in 2011, after splitting from her second husband.

Osmond first married Craig, a [[Brigham Young University]] basketball player, in 1982. Their only child, Stephen James Craig, was born on April 20, 1983, and they divorced in 1985. On September 24, 2011 Marie's son Stephen James married Claire Olds.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://onebadappledish.blogspot.com/2011/09/congratulations.html |title=Congratulations |publisher=http://onebadappledish.blogspot.com |accessdate=September 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On October 28, 1986, Osmond married Brian Blosil. Osmond and Blosil had two biological children, Rachael Lauren (b. August 1989) and Matthew Richard (b. July 1999), and also adopted five children: Jessica Marie (b. December 1987), Michael Bryan (May 4, 1991– February 26, 2010), Brandon Warren (b. November 1996), Brianna Patricia (b. November 1997), and Abigail Michelle (b. September 2002). On March 30, 2007, Osmond and Blosil announced they were divorcing.&lt;ref name=&quot;div&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/6513213.stm Singer Marie Osmond to divorce] from the [[BBC]]&lt;/ref&gt;

On May 4, 2011, Osmond remarried Craig in a small ceremony in the [[Las Vegas Nevada Temple]] wearing her dress from the 1982 wedding.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tmz.com/2011/05/04/marie-osmond-re-marrying-her-ex-steve-craig-wedding-marriage-las-vegas-love-mormon-temple-son-michael-death-anniversarylas-vegas/ |title=Marie Osmond RE-MARRIES 1st Husband |publisher=TMZ.com |accessdate=May 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 1999, Osmond revealed that she had suffered from severe [[postpartum depression]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/5241178.stm |title=Entertainment , Marie Osmond suicide bid denied |publisher=BBC News  |date=August 3, 2006 |accessdate=May 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; She co-authored a book called ''Behind the Smile'' with Marcia Wilkie and Dr. Judith Moore which chronicles her experiences with the illness. In August 2006, it was suggested by several U.S. [[Tabloid (newspaper format)|tabloid]]s that she had attempted suicide. These reports were denied by her publicity team, which claimed she had suffered an adverse reaction to a medication she was taking.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/5241178.stm Marie Osmond suicide bid denied] from the [[BBC]]&lt;/ref&gt;

On April 29, 2009, Osmond revealed that her oldest daughter, Jessica, is a lesbian and had been living in Los Angeles with her girlfriend for the past three years. In interviews Osmond has expressed support for her daughter and for [[same sex marriage]] rights.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.advocate.com/News/Daily_News/2009/05/05/Marie_Osmond_Loves,_Supports_Lesbian_Daughter/ Marie Osmond Loves Her Gay Daughter]&lt;/ref&gt;

On February 26, 2010, Osmond's son Michael committed suicide by jumping from the eighth floor of his apartment building in Los Angeles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Silverman |first=Stephen M. |url=http://www.people.com/people/article/0,,20347551,00.html |title=Marie Osmond's Son Commits Suicide |work=People  |date=February 27, 2010 |accessdate=May 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He had reportedly battled depression for most of his life and had been in rehabilitation at the age of 12.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wonderwall.msn.com/tv/marie-osmonds-son-commits-suicide-1540395.story?GT1=28135 |title=Marie Osmond's son commits suicide |publisher=Wonderwall.msn.com |date=February 27, 2010 |accessdate=May 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The autopsy released on April 21, 2010 revealed that no drugs were found in his system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cnn.com/2010/SHOWBIZ/04/21/osmond.son.autopsy/index.html?hpt=T2 |title=Osmond son's autopsy finds no drugs before suicide |publisher=CNN |date=April 21, 2010 |accessdate=May 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Marie Osmond is a [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.zimbio.com/Famous+Republicans/articles/4dKcAWkHdi2/Marie+Osmond Osmond in Zimbio's list of &quot;Famous Republicans&quot;] (accessed 2012-05-08).&lt;/ref&gt;

==Discography==
{{Main|Marie Osmond discography}}

*1973: ''[[Paper Roses (album)|Paper Roses]]''
*1974: ''[[In My Little Corner of the World]]''
*1975: ''[[Who's Sorry Now (album)|Who's Sorry Now]]''
*1977: ''[[This is the Way That I Feel]]''
*1985: ''[[There's No Stopping Your Heart]]''
*1986: ''[[I Only Wanted You]]''
*1988: ''[[All in Love]]''
*1989: ''[[Steppin' Stone (album)|Steppin' Stone]]''
*2010: ''I Can Do This''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Osmond |first=Marie |url=http://www.amazon.com/dp/B004AOE0ZI |title=I Can Do This: Marie Osmond: Music |publisher=Amazon.com |accessdate=May 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Filmography==
* ''[[Perry Como television and radio shows|Perry Como Sunshine Show]]'' (1974) – Guest
* ''[[Hugo the Hippo]]'' (1975) – Vocalist
* ''[[Donny &amp; Marie (1976 TV series)|Donny and Marie]]'' (1976) – Herself
* ''[[Goin' Coconuts]]'' (1978) – Marie
* ''The Gift of Love'' (1978) – Beth Atherton
* &quot;[[The Big Show (TV series)|The Big Show]]&quot; (1980) – Host
* &quot;Marie&quot; (1980) TV Series – Herself
* ''The Osmond Family Christmas Special'' (1980) – Herself
* ''Side by Side: The True Story of the Osmond Family'' (1982) – Olive Osmond
* ''[[Rooster (TV film)|Rooster]]'' (1982) – Sister Mae Davis
* &quot;[[The Love Boat]]&quot; (1982) – Maria Rosselli (2 episodes)
* ''[[I Married Wyatt Earp]]'' (1983) – Josephine 'Josie' Marcus
* ''[[Rose Petal Place]]'' (1984) – Rose Petal
* ''[[The Velveteen Rabbit]]'' (1984) – Fairy Princess and Velveteen Rabbit
* ''[[Ripley's Believe It or Not!]]'' (1985–86) – Co-Host
* ''Rose Petal Place: Real Friends'' (1985) – Rose Petal
* ''Marie Osmond's Merry Christmas'' (1986) – Herself
* ''Television's Christmas Classics'' (1994) – Host
* &quot;[[Maybe This Time]]&quot; (1995–96) – Julia Wallace
* ''[[Buster &amp; Chauncey's Silent Night]]'' (1998) – Queen (voice)
*''O' Christmas Tree'' (1999) – Star (voice)
* &quot;[[Donny &amp; Marie (1998 TV series)|Donny &amp; Marie]]&quot; (1998) – Host
* &quot;[[Dancing With The Stars]]&quot; (2007) – Third Place
* &quot;[[Dr. Phil (TV series)|Dr.Phil]]&quot; (2007) – Guest
* &quot;[[The Paul O'Grady Show]]&quot; (2009) – Guest
* &quot;[[The Oprah Winfrey Show]]&quot; (2010) – Guest
* &quot;[[The Rosie Show]]&quot; (2011) – Guest
* &quot;Ladies and Gentlemen... Marie Osmond&quot; (2012) – Herself
* &quot;[[Marie]]&quot; (2012) – Host

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{commons category}}
* {{IMDb name|0005288}} &lt;!-- internet movie data base --&gt;
* {{IBDB name|82878}}
* [http://www.marieosmond.com/ Marie Osmond] – Official Website
* [http://osmond.com/about-us/marie-osmond/ Marie Osmond] - Osmond Family Official Website
* [http://www.countyourbeans.com/osmondresource.htm Marie Osmond Dolls] – Marie Osmond Dolls News
* [http://www.people.com/people/article/0,,20033248,00.html Marie Osmond Getting Divorced] – People Magazine, March 30, 2007

{{s-start}}
{{s-ach}}
{{succession box | title=[[Dancing with the Stars (US TV series)|''Dancing with the Stars'' (US)]] third place contestant| before=[[Laila Ali]] &amp; [[Maksim Chmerkovskiy]]| years=Season 5 (Fall 2007 with [[Jonathan Roberts (dancer)|Jonathan Roberts]]) |after=[[Cristian de la Fuente]] &amp; [[Cheryl Burke]]}}
{{S-end}}

{{Dancing with the Stars Season 5}}

&lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
{{Persondata
|NAME              = Osmond, Marie
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
|SHORT DESCRIPTION = American actress and singer
|DATE OF BIRTH     = October 13, 1959
|PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Ogden, Utah]], US
|DATE OF DEATH     =
|PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Osmond, Marie}}
[[Category:1959 births]]
[[Category:20th-century actors]]
[[Category:Actors from Utah]]
[[Category:American country singers]]
[[Category:American female singers]]
[[Category:American Latter Day Saints]]
[[Category:American musical theatre actors]]
[[Category:American people of English descent]]
[[Category:American people of Welsh descent]]
[[Category:American pop singers]]
[[Category:American television actors]]
[[Category:American television personalities]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Musicians from Utah]]
[[Category:Participants in American reality television series]]
[[Category:People from Ogden, Utah]]
[[Category:The Osmonds members]]
[[Category:Utah Republicans]]

[[de:Marie Osmond]]
[[es:Marie Osmond]]
[[fr:Marie Osmond]]
[[pl:Marie Osmond]]
[[simple:Marie Osmond]]</text>
      <sha1>72ey7tvkkeh7vty2dnjanca1539tqhd</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
