<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Marital rape</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>875547</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521004018</id>
      <parentid>519528296</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T04:15:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>18.250.6.142</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Marriage after rape */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="59146">{{About|marital rape|a related article|Sexual violence by intimate partners|violence between partners|Outline of domestic violence}}
{{Sex and the law}}
{{Violence against women}}
'''Marital [[rape]]''', also known as '''spousal rape''', is non-[[Rape#Consent|consensual]] sex in which the perpetrator is the victim's spouse. As such, it is a form of partner rape, of [[domestic violence]], and of [[sexual abuse]]. Once widely condoned or ignored by law, spousal rape is now repudiated by international conventions and increasingly criminalized. Still, in many countries, spousal rape either remains legal, or is illegal but widely tolerated and accepted as a husband's prerogative. 

In 2006, it was estimated that marital rape could be prosecuted in at least 104 countries (in four of these countries, marital rape could be prosecuted only when the spouses were judicially separated),&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cities-localgovernments.org/uclg/upload/docs/notaminutemore-endingviolenceagainstwomen.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; and since 2006 several other countries have outlawed spousal rape. In many countries it is not clear if marital rape may or may not be prosecuted under ordinary rape laws. Several countries in [[Eastern Europe]] and [[Scandinavia]] made spousal rape illegal before 1970, but other countries in Western Europe and the English-speaking [[Western World]] outlawed it much later, mostly in the 1980s and 1990s. Most [[developing countries]] outlawed it in the 1990s and 2000s.

Research literature, particularly in the areas of incidence and effects, may extend the use of the term spousal/marital rape to include divorced/legally separated ex-spouses or unmarried cohabiting partners. Current state laws, however, often treat rape by ex-spouses or intimate partners as different than marital rape, and therefore, legally equivalent to rape by a stranger.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www3.interscience.wiley.com/journal/119250895/abstract?CRETRY=1&amp;SRETRY=0 |title=The Sex Right: A Legal History of the Marital Rape Exemption - Ryan - 2006 - Law &amp; Social Inquiry - Wiley Online Library |publisher=.interscience.wiley.com |date=2006-07-28 |accessdate=2012-05-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Physical and psychological damage==
{{Main|Effects and aftermath of rape}}

Rape by a spouse, partner or ex-partner is more often associated with physical violence. A nine-nation study within the European Union found that current or ex-partners were the perpetrators of around 25% of all sexual assaults, and that violence was more common in assaults by ex-partners (50% of the time) and partners (40%) than in assaults by strangers or recent acquaintances (25%).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | publisher = Child and Woman Abuse Studies Unit, London Metropolitan University | last = Burman | first = M. | coauthors = J. Lovett, L. Kelly | title = Different systems, similar outcomes? Tracking attrition in reported rape cases in eleven countries | location = London | year = 2009 | page = 106 }}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;!-- goes to prevalence (among ex-partners/partners) and not physical/psychological damage--&gt; 

Attributing the effects of marital rape in research is problematic as it is nearly impossible to find a large enough sample of spouses to study who have experienced sexual violence but have not also been physically assaulted by their spouse.&lt;ref&gt;Bernice, et. al., The Relative Effects of Intimate Partner Physical and Sexual Violence on Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder Symptomatology, Violence and Victims, 2003 February; 18 vol 1, p. 87&lt;/ref&gt;  

While rape by a stranger is highly [[psychological trauma|traumatic]], it is typically a one-time event and is clearly understood as rape. In the case of rape by a spouse or long term sexual partner, the history of the relationship affects the victim’s reactions. Marital rape may occur as part of an [[Domestic violence|abusive relationship]]. Trauma from the rape adds to the effect of other abusive acts or abusive and demeaning talk. Furthermore, marital rape is rarely a one-time event, but a repeated if not frequent occurrence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hiddenhurt.co.uk/marital_rape.html |title=Marital Rape |publisher=Hiddenhurt.co.uk |date=2007-06-17 |accessdate=2012-05-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Whether it takes place once or is part of an established pattern of domestic violence, trauma from rape has serious long term consequences for victims regardless of whether the assault is prosecuted or not.

== Legal aspect ==
Historically, many cultures have had a concept of spouses' [[Marriage#Rights and obligations|conjugal rights]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.malaysiakini.com/letters/29772] {{Dead link|date=January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; to [[sexual intercourse]] with each other. This can be seen in [[Common law]], in force in [[North America]] and the [[Commonwealth of Nations|British Commonwealth]], where the very concept of marital rape was treated as an impossibility. This was illustrated most vividly by [[Sir Matthew Hale]], in his 1736 legal treatise, [[Historia Placitorum Coronæ]] or ''History of the Pleas of the Crown'', where he wrote that such a rape could not be recognized since the wife &quot;hath given up herself in this kind unto her husband, which she cannot retract.&quot;

===Formalization of the marital rape exemption in law===

====Common law and the United Kingdom====
{{See also|Rape in English law}} 

Hale's statement in ''History of the Pleas of the Crown'' was not supported by any [[case law|judicial authority]] but was believed to be a [[Entailment|logical consequence]] of the laws of marriage and rape as understood at the time. Marriage gave conjugal rights to a spouse, and marriage could not be revoked except by private Act of Parliament—it therefore seemed to follow that a spouse could not legally revoke consent to sexual intercourse, and if there was consent there was no rape.

The principle was repeated in East's ''Treatise of the Pleas of the Crown'' in 1803 and in Archbold’s ''Pleading and Evidence in Criminal Cases'' in 1822, but it was not until ''R v Clarence'' (1888) 22 QBD 23 that the question of the exemption first arose in an English courtroom. ''Clarence'' was determined on a different point, and there was no clear agreement between the nine judges regarding the status of the rule.

===Feminist critique in the 19th century===
From the beginnings of the 19th century women's movement, activists challenged the presumed right of men to engage in forced or coerced sex with their wives. In the [[United States]], &quot;the nineteenth-century woman's rights movement fought against a husband's right to control marital intercourse in a campaign that was remarkably developed, prolific, and insistent, given nineteenth-century taboos against the public mention of sex or sexuality.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | volume = 88 | last = Hasday | first = Jill Elaine | title = Contest and Consent: A Legal History of Marital Rape | journal = California Law Review | year = 2000 | page = 1412 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Suffragists]] including [[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]] and [[Lucy Stone]] &quot;singled out a woman's right to control marital intercourse as the core component of equality.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Stanton: &quot;'Woman's degradation is in man's idea of his sexual rights,' Stanton wrote to Anthony. 'How this marriage question grows on me. It lies at the very foundation of all progress.'&quot; Stone: &quot;It is clear to me, that [the marriage] question underlies, this whole movement and all our little skirmishing for better laws, and the right to vote, will yet be swallowed up, in the real question, viz, has woman, as wife, a right to herself? It is very little to me to have the right to vote, to own property &amp;c. if I may not keep my body, and its uses, in my absolute right. Not one wife in a thousand can do that now, &amp; so long as she suffers this bondage, all other rights will not help her to her true position.&quot; {{Cite journal | volume = 88 | last = Hasday | first = Jill Elaine | title = Contest and Consent: A Legal History of Marital Rape | journal = California Law Review | year = 2000 | page = 1425 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Nineteenth century feminist demands centered on the right of women to control their bodies and fertility, positioned consent in marital sexual relations as an alternative to contraception and abortion (which many opposed), and also embraced [[eugenics|eugenic]] concerns about excessive procreation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | volume = 88 | last = Hasday | first = Jill Elaine | title = Contest and Consent: A Legal History of Marital Rape | journal = California Law Review | year = 2000 | pages = 1435–43 }}&lt;/ref&gt; British [[liberalism|liberal]] feminists [[John Stuart Mill]] and [[Hariett Taylor Mill|Harriet Taylor]] attacked marital rape as a gross double-standard in law and as central to the subordination of women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | publisher = Cambridge University Press | isbn = 978-0-521-86020-8 0521860202 9780521677561 0521677564 | editors = Nadia Urbinati (ed.) | last = Zakaras | first = Alex | coauthors = Maria Morales | title = J.S. Mill's political thought: A bicentennial reassessment | chapter = Rational freedom in John Stuart Mill's feminism | location = Cambridge | year = 2007 | page = 52 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Advocates of [[free love]], including early [[Anarcha-feminism|anarcha-feminists]] such as [[Voltairine de Cleyre]] and Emma Goldman, as well as [[Victoria Woodhull]], Thomas Low Nichols, and Mary S. Gove Nichols, joined a critique of marital rape to advocacy of women's autonomy and [[sexual pleasure]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | volume = 88 | last = Hasday | first = Jill Elaine | title = Contest and Consent: A Legal History of Marital Rape | journal = California Law Review | year = 2000 | pages = 1444–51 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Moses Harman]], a Kansas-based publisher and advocate for women's rights, was jailed twice under the [[Comstock laws]] for publishing articles (by a woman who was victimized and a doctor who treated marital rape survivors) decrying marital rape. [[De Cleyre]] defended Harman in a well-known article, &quot;Sexual Slavery.&quot; She refused to draw any distinction between rape outside of, and within marriage: &quot;And that is rape, where a man forces himself sexually upon a woman whether he is licensed by the marriage law to do it or not.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | issn = 1040-0656 | volume = 7 | issue = 3 | pages = 54–68 | last = Palczewski | first = Catherine Helen | title = Voltairine de Cleyre: Sexual Slavery and Sexual Pleasure in the Nineteenth Century | journal = NWSA Journal | accessdate = 2011-03-08 | date = 1995-10-01 | url = http://www.jstor.org.ezproxy.gc.cuny.edu/stable/4316402 | page = 60 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===20th and 21st century criminalization===
[[Image:MaritalRapeCriminalizedMap.svg|thumb|300px|{{legend|#BB3333|Marital rape is criminalized}}{{legend|#FF8888|Marital rape is criminalized only if the couple is legally separated}}{{legend|#F8A20C|Marital rape is a form of non-criminal domestic violence}}{{legend|#000000|Marital rape is known not to be criminalized}}]]
As the concept of human rights has developed, the belief of a marital right to sexual intercourse has become less widely held. Feminists worked systematically since the 1960s to overturn the marital rape exemption and criminalize marital rape.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | volume = 88 | last = Hasday | first = Jill Elaine | title = Contest and Consent: A Legal History of Marital Rape | journal = California Law Review | year = 2000 | pages = 1482–1505 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Increasing criminalization of spousal rape is part of a worldwide reclassification of sexual crimes &quot;from offenses against morality, the family, good customs, honor, or chastity ... to offenses against liberty, self-determination, or physical integrity.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | doi = 10.1177/0003122410388493 | volume = 75 | issue = 6 | pages = 867–893 | last = Frank | first = David John | coauthors = Bayliss J. Camp, Steven A. Boutcher | title = Worldwide Trends in the Criminal Regulation of Sex, 1945 to 2005 | journal = American Sociological Review | accessdate = 2011-03-07 | date = 2010-12-01 | url = http://asr.sagepub.com.ezproxy.gc.cuny.edu/content/75/6/867.abstract | page = 871 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In December 1993, the [[United Nations]] [[High Commissioner for Human Rights]] published the ''[[Declaration on the Elimination of Violence Against Women]]''. This establishes marital rape as a [[human rights]] violation. 

Despite these trends and international moves, criminalization has not occurred in all [[United Nations member states|UN member States]]. In 1997, [[United Nations Children's Fund|UNICEF]] reported that just 17 States criminalized marital rape.&lt;ref name=&quot;UNIFEM-1997&quot;&gt;UNICEF, [http://unicef.org/publications/pub_pon97_en.pdf The Progress of Nations], 1997, 48.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2003, [[UNIFEM]] reported that more than 50 States did so.&lt;ref name=&quot;UNIFEM-2003&quot;/&gt; In 2006, the UN Secretary General found &quot;Marital rape may be prosecuted in at least 104 States. Of these, 32 have made marital rape a specific criminal offence, while the remaining 74 {{sic}} do not exempt marital rape from general rape provisions. Four States criminalize marital rape only when the spouses are judicially separated.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;UNIFEM-2003&quot;&gt;Report of the Secretary-General, [http://daccess-dds-ny.un.org/doc/UNDOC/GEN/N06/419/74/PDF/N0641974.pdf?OpenElement In-depth study on all forms of violence against women], United Nations, UN Doc A/61/122/Add.1, 6 July 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

Countries which were early to criminalize marital rape include the [[Soviet Union]] (1922/1960),&lt;ref&gt;The first criminal law code in Soviet Russia differed from Tsarist law on rape: &quot;although the Tsarist law explicitly excluded marital rape, the Soviet law code of 1922 did not.&quot; {{Cite book | publisher = Greenwood Publishing Group | isbn = 978-0-313-29363-4 | last = Rule | first = Wilma | title = Russian women in politics and society | year = 1996 | page=160 }} Marital rape was explicitly included in the 1960 code.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Poland]] (1932), [[Czechoslovakia]] (1950), some other members of the [[Communist Bloc]], [[Denmark]] (1960), [[Sweden]] (1965),&lt;ref name=&quot;Elman 1996 90&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Sexual subordination and state intervention: comparing Sweden and the United States |first=R Amy |last=Elman |publisher=Berghahn Books |year=1996 |page=90 |isbn=1-57181-071-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Norway]] (1971).&lt;ref name=&quot;Elman 1996 90&quot;/&gt; [[Slovenia]], then a republic within federal [[Yugoslavia]], criminalized marital rape in 1977.&lt;ref name=Slovenia&gt;With the new [[1974 Yugoslav Constitution]] each republic adopted their own Criminal Act, but [[Socialist Republic of Slovenia]] was the only one to introduce rape of wife in its [http://www.dnevnik.si/tiskane_izdaje/dnevnik/1042227600 1977 Criminal Act]; (any) rape is not gender specific since [http://www.uradni-list.si/1/objava.jsp?urlid=199463&amp;stevilka=2167 1995 Criminal Code] (Art. 180), [http://www.uradni-list.si/1/objava.jsp?urlurid=20082296 current Criminal Code] is from 2008 (Art. 170)&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Israel]]i Supreme Court affirmed that marital rape is a crime in a 1980 decision, citing law based on the [[Talmud]].&lt;ref name=RiM284&gt;{{Cite journal| volume = 6 | page = 284 | last = Geis | first = Gilbert | title = Rape-in-marriage: Law and law reform in England, the United States, and Sweden | journal = Adelaide Law Review | year = 1977}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=IntroCrim79&gt;David Kauzlarich, Introduction to Criminology, 2008, p. 79.&lt;/ref&gt; Criminalization in [[Australia]] began with the state of [[New South Wales]] in 1981, followed by all other states from 1985 to 1992.&lt;ref name=&quot;Temkin86&quot;&gt;Jennifer Temkin, Rape and the legal process, p. 86.&lt;/ref&gt; Several formerly British-ruled countries followed suit: Canada (1983),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.statcan.gc.ca/imdb-bmdi/document/3306_D6_T9_V5-eng.htm |title=Legislative Influences |publisher=Statcan.gc.ca |date=2010-08-18 |accessdate=2012-05-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.statcan.gc.ca/kits-trousses/justice/8104299-eng.pdf ]{{dead link|date=May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; New Zealand (1985), and Ireland (1990).&lt;ref name=&quot;Temkin86&quot;/&gt;

Many [[United States]] rape statutes formerly precluded the prosecution of spouses, including estranged or even [[Legal separation|legally separated]] couples. In 1975, [[South Dakota]] removed this exception.&lt;ref&gt;The New York Times, [http://www.nytimes.com/1987/05/13/us/marital-rape-drive-for-tougher-laws-is-pressed.html Marital rape: Drive for tougher laws is pressed], 13 May 1987&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1993, [[North Carolina]] became the last state to remove the spousal exemption.&lt;ref name=&quot;ncvc.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncvc.org/ncvc/main.aspx?dbName=DocumentViewer&amp;DocumentID=32701 |title=The National Center for Victims of Crime - Library/Document Viewer |publisher=Ncvc.org |date= |accessdate=2012-05-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, as of 1999, 33 of 50 [[U.S. states]] regarded spousal rape as a lesser crime [Bergen, 1999]. The perpetrator may be charged with related crimes such as [[assault]], [[battery (crime)|battery]], or [[spousal abuse]]. There are other criminal charges that may be inapplicable to married couples. For example, in the U.S., there is a marriage exemption to the charge of [[statutory rape]] even if one of the spouses is under the [[age of consent]] in the jurisdiction where the [[Human sexual behavior|sexual act]] takes place.

[[France]]'s ''[[Court of Cassation (France)|Cour de Cassation]]'' authorized prosecution of spouses for rape or sexual assault in 1990, but ruled in 1992 that a presumption of consent exists from the time of marriage until it is revoked by either party.&lt;ref name=RJSimon20&gt;{{Cite book | publisher = Lexington Books | isbn = 978-0-7391-0248-0 | last = Simon | first = Rita James | title = A comparative perspective on major social problems | date = 2001-05 | page = 20 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1994, Law 94-89 criminalized marital rape;&lt;ref name=RJSimon20 /&gt; a second law, passed 4 April 2006, makes rape by a partner (including in unmarried couples, married couples, and in civil unions) an aggravating circumstance in prosecuting rape.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | doi = 10.1016/j.sexol.2009.04.001 | issn = 1158-1360 | volume = 18 | issue = 3 | pages = 182–185 | last = Bensussan | first = P. | title = Marital rape according to French law: Desire, need and consent | journal = Sexologies | accessdate = 2011-03-09 | url = http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/B82YG-4WD116V-4/2/e9bef47b8067dd8a064441e205f26248 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Germany]] outlawed spousal rape only in 1997, which is later than other developed countries. Female ministers and women's rights activists lobbied for this law for over 25 years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.msmagazine.com/news/uswirestory.asp?id=4131 |title=Feminist Wire Daily Newsbriefs: U.S. and Global News Coverage |publisher=Msmagazine.com |date=1997-06-16 |accessdate=2012-05-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[India]], the [[Protection of Women from Domestic Violence Act 2005]] (passed August 2005; entered into force October 2006) created a civil remedy for victims, but it did not criminalize marital rape,&lt;ref name=&quot;news.independent.co.uk&quot;&gt;Justin Huggler, &quot;[http://news.independent.co.uk/world/asia/article1932745.ece India abolishes husbands' 'right' to rape wife],&quot; ''Independent'' (London), October 27, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sarid.net&quot;&gt;South Asia Research Institute for Policy and Development, [http://www.sarid.net/governance/102606-india.html India’s landmark domestic abuse law takes effect], October 26, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; and jail time is only considered if a court order has been violated.

[[Thailand|Thai]] legal scholar [[Taweekiet Meenakanit]] voiced his opposition to legal reforms to make spousal rape in Thailand a crime. A non-gender specific amendment to the rape laws appeared to exempt husband and wives from criminal prosecution, and opponents of the amendemnt argued for specfic language criminalizing rape of a wife by her husband.  Mr. Meenakanit argued that allowing a husband to file a rape charge against his wife is &quot;abnormal logic&quot; and that wives would refuse to divorce or put their husband in jail since many Thai wives are dependent on their husbands.&lt;ref&gt;The Nation,[http://nationmultimedia.com/2007/02/14/national/national_30026800.php Anger over proposed change to rape laws], 14 February 2007&lt;/ref&gt; 

Recent countries to criminalize marital rape include [[Turkey]] (2005),&lt;ref name=UNTurkey&gt;[http://www.unis.unvienna.org/unis/pressrels/2005/wom1480.html Anti-Discrimination Committee Takes Up Situation of Women in Turkey], UN Information Service, 21 January 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cambodia]] (2005),&lt;ref name=CAT-Cambodia&gt;{{cite web|title=Concluding observations of the Committee against Torture: Cambodia|url=http://www.unhcr.org/refworld/docid/4d6ccc7a2.html|accessdate=8 March 2011|author=UN Committee Against Torture (CAT)|location=CAT/C/KHM/CO/2|date=20 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nepal (2006),&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | last = Bhattarai | first = Tara | title = Taboos Undercut Nepal's Marital Rape Law | Womens eNews | work = Womens eNews | accessdate = 2012-01-31 | date = 2012-01-18 | url = http://www.womensenews.org/story/rape/120117/taboos-undercut-nepals-marital-rape-law }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Mauritius]] (2007),&lt;ref name=ExpressMauritius&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lexpress.mu/archive_semaine/display_article.php?news_id=85151 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20070927215929/http://www.lexpress.mu/archive_semaine/display_article.php?news_id=85151 |archivedate=27 September 2007 |title= Rape and the Sexual Offences Bill: Beyond the illogical, punitive attitude... |work=l'express |date=23 April 2007 |first1=Lindsey |last1=Collen |first2=Kisna |last2=Kistnasamy |first3=Rajni |last3=Lallah}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ghana (1998/2007),&lt;ref name=UNSRGhana&gt;[http://www.unhcr.org/cgi-bin/texis/vtx/refworld/rwmain?docid=47ce68652 Report of the Special Rapporteur on Violence against Women, Its Causes and Consequences, Yakin Ertürk : addendum: mission to Ghana], 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Malaysia]] (2007),&lt;ref name=SassyMPMalaysia&gt;MP Teresa Kok, [http://teresakok.com/2007/09/15/mixed-reaction-to-marital-rape-reform/ Mixed reaction to marital rape reform], ''Sassy MP'', September 15, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=SMHMalaysia&gt;AP, &quot;[http://news.smh.com.au/breaking-news-world/malaysian-jailed-for-marital-rape-20090806-eb1q.html Malaysian jailed for marital rape],&quot; ''Sydney Morning Herald'', August 6, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Thailand]] (2007),&lt;ref name=AFPThailand&gt;&quot;[http://www.chinapost.com.tw/asia/2007/06/22/113083/Thailand-outlaws.htm Thailand outlaws marital rape],&quot; AFP, June 22, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Tunisia]] (2008),&lt;ref&gt;&quot;In its response to questions posed by the United Nations (UN) Committee on Human Rights, the government of Tunisia declared that, under Articles 227 and 227 bis of the penal code, marital rape, like all other forms of rape, is a crime under Tunisian law (Tunisia 25 Feb. 2008; ibid. 1 Oct. 1913, Art. 227). Under Article 227 of the Tunisian penal code, sexual assault accompanied by acts of violence or threats with a weapon is punishable by death, while, for other cases of rape, the prescribed punishment is life imprisonment (Tunisia 1 Oct. 1913). [US State Department] Country Reports for 2008 indicates that 'the government enforced the laws vigorously ... however, there were no reports of prosecution for spousal rape' in 2008 (US 25 Feb. 2009, Sec. 5).&quot; Immigration and Refugee Board of Canada, ''Tunisia: Domestic violence, legislation and protection available to victims (2007-2009)'', 24 November 2009, TUN103273.FE, available at: http://www.unhcr.org/refworld/docid/4b20f04a3c.html [accessed 3 August 2010]&lt;/ref&gt;  Rwanda (2009),&lt;ref name=AFWRRwanda&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.africa4womensrights.org/post/2009/02/13/Rwanda:-Gender-Violence-Law-to-Be-Passed-in-Two-Weeks |title=Rwanda: Final steps towards the adoption of a law to combat gender violence |publisher=Africa4womensrights.org |date= |accessdate=2012-05-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; South Korea (2009),&lt;ref name=WSKorea&gt;{{cite web|url=http://womensphere.wordpress.com/2009/02/24/marital-rape-ruling-seen-as-move-to-protect-spousal-right-to-sex-korea/ |title=Marital Rape – Ruling Seen as Move to Protect Spousal Right to Sex – Korea « womensphere |publisher=Womensphere.wordpress.com |date=2009-02-24 |accessdate=2012-05-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Jamaica (2009).&lt;ref name=WSJamaica&gt;[http://womensphere.wordpress.com/2009/07/28/in-jamaica-womens-groups-react-to-senate-passing-sexual-offences-bill/ In Jamaica women’s groups react to Senate passing Sexual Offences Bill], July 28, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Human rights observers have criticized a variety of countries—including [[Japan]],&lt;ref&gt;Sumie Asatori and Fumi Suzuki, [http://www2.ohchr.org/english/bodies/cedaw/docs/ngos/Reproductive_Sexual_Rights_08_japan_cedaw44.pdf Discrimination in the field of Reproductive and Sexual Rights in Japan], Space Allies (Women's Rights NGO), July 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Poland]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stopvaw.org/80533bf2-2799-456b-8419-6b44638c1049.html |title=Sexual Assault Laws in the CEE/FSU Region |publisher=Stopvaw.org |date= |accessdate=2012-05-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Kazakhstan]]&lt;ref&gt;International Helsinki Federation for Human Rights, &quot;[http://www.ihf-hr.org/viewbinary/viewdocument.php?download=1&amp;doc_id=2061 Kazakhstan],&quot; in ''Women 2000: An Investigation into the Status of Women's Rights in Central and South-Eastern Europe and the Newly Independent States'' (9 November 2000).&lt;/ref&gt;—for failing to effectively prosecute marital rape once it has been criminalized. South Africa, which criminalized in 1996, saw its first conviction for marital rape in 2012.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Krugersdorp Magistrate's Court sentenced her 48-year-old former husband [Frederik Christiaan Bossert] to an effective 12 years in jail last week for physically abusing and repeatedly raping [Annelise] Kriek during their marriage.  Kriek's court action became the first reported case of rape in a marriage since the Domestic Violence Act was introduced in 1996.&quot; {{Cite news | last = Chelemu | first = Khethiwe | title = Wife's seven-year wait for justice | work = Times | location = Johannesburg | accessdate = 2012-01-29 | url = http://www.timeslive.co.za/local/2012/01/19/wife-s-seven-year-wait-for-justice }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Ending the exemption in England and Wales====
{{Main|Rape in English law}}

The marital rape exemption was abolished in [[England and Wales]] in 1991 by the [[Appellate Committee of the House of Lords]], in the case of ''R v R''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bailii.org/uk/cases/UKHL/1991/12.html |title=&lt;nowiki&gt;[1991] UKHL 12&lt;/nowiki&gt; |author= |date= |work= |publisher=[[BAILII]] |accessdate=19 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[1992] 1 AC 599, [1991] 3 [[Weekly Law Reports|WLR]] 767, [1991] 4 [[All England Law Reports|All ER]] 481, (1991) 135 SJLB 181,  [1992] 1 FZR 217, (1991) 155 JP 989, (1992) 94 [[Criminal Appeal Reports|Cr App R]] 216, [1992] Fam Law 108, [1992] [[Criminal Law Review|Crim LR]] 207, (1991) 155 JPN 752, (1991) 141 NLJ 1481, [1991] UKHL 12, (1991) The Times, 24 October 1991, (1991) The Independent, 24 October 1991, (1991) The Guardian, 30 October 1991, [[House of Lords|HL]], affirming [1991] 2 WLR 1065, [1991] 2 All ER 257, (1991) 135 [[Solicitors Journal|SJ]] 384, (1991) 93 Cr App R 1, (1991) 155 JP 373, [1991] Crim LR 475, (1991) 155 JPN 236, (1991) 141 NLJ 383, (1991) The Times, 15 March 1991, (1991) The Independent, 15 March 1991, (1991) The Guardian, 15 March 1991, [[Court of Appeal|CA]], affirming [1991] 1 All ER 747&lt;/ref&gt; been promulgated in 1736 in [[Matthew Hale (jurist)|Matthew Hale’s]] ''History of the Pleas of the Crown'' (see above).

The first attempted [[prosecution]] of a husband for the rape of his wife was ''R v Clarke'' [1949] 2 All ER 448. Rather than try to argue directly against Hale’s logic, the court held that consent in this instance had been revoked by an [[court order|order of the court]] for non-cohabitation. It was the first of a number of cases in which the courts found reasons not to apply the exemption, notably ''R v O’Brien'' [1974] 3 All ER 663 (the obtaining of [[decree nisi]]), ''R v Steele'' (1976) 65 Cr.App.R. 22 (an undertaking by the husband to the court not to molest the wife) and ''R v Roberts'' [1986] Crim LR 188 (the existence of a formal separation agreement).

There are at least four recorded instances of a husband successfully relying on the exemption in England and Wales. The first was ''R v Miller'' [1954] 2 QB 282, where it was held that the wife had not legally revoked her consent despite having presented a divorce petition. ''R v Kowalski'' (1988) 86 Cr. App. R. 339 was followed by ''R v Sharples'' [1990] Crim LR 198, and the fourth occurred in 1991 in the case of ''R v J'', a [[Judgment (law)|judgment]] made after the [[first instance]] decision of the [[Crown Court]] in ''R v R'' but before the decision of the House of Lords that was to abolish the exemption. In ''Miller'', ''Kowalski'' and ''R v J'' the husbands were instead convicted of [[assault]] or [[indecent assault]].

''R v R'' in 1991 was the first occasion where the marital rights exemption had been [[appeal]]ed as far as the House of Lords, and it followed the trio of cases since 1988 where the marital rights exemption was upheld. The leading judgment, unanimously approved, was given by [[Lord Keith of Kinkel]]. He stated that the contortions being performed in the lower courts in order to avoid applying the marital rights exemption were indicative of the absurdity of the rule, and held, agreeing with earlier judgments in [[Scotland]] and in the [[Court of Appeal]] in ''R v R'', that “the fiction of [[implied consent]] has no useful purpose to serve today in the law of rape” and that the marital rights exemption was a “common law fiction” which had never been a true rule of [[English law]]. R’s appeal was accordingly dismissed, and he was convicted of the rape of his wife.

===Marriage after rape===
In a variety of cultures, marriage after the fact has been treated historically as a &quot;resolution&quot; to the rape of an unmarried woman. Citing [[Bible|Biblical]] injunctions (particularly [[Book of Exodus|Exodus]] 22:16–17 and [[Deuteronomy]] 22:25–30), Calvinist Geneva permitted a single woman's father to consent to her marriage to her rapist, after which the husband would have no right to divorce; the woman had no explicitly stated separate right to refuse. Among ancient cultures virginity was highly prized, and a woman who had been raped had little chance of marrying. These laws forced the rapist to provide for their victim. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | publisher = W.B. Eerdmans Pub. Co. | isbn = 0-8028-4803-6 9780802848031 | last = Witte | first = John | coauthors = Robert M. Kingdon | title = Sex, marriage, and family life in John Calvin's Geneva | location = Grand Rapids, Mich. | year = 2005 | pages = 120–22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Criminal prosecution for rape ends in the event of marriage in [[Morocco]] (by Penal Code Article 475 {{As of|2012|lc=y}}),&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | last = Schuetz | first = Kristen | title = We Are All Amina Filali | work = Ms. Magazine Blog | accessdate = 2012-03-21 | date = 2012-03-16 | url = http://msmagazine.com/blog/blog/2012/03/16/we-are-all-amina-filali/ }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Algeria]], [[Lebanon]] (both {{As of|2010|lc=y}}),&lt;ref name=FH2010&gt;{{Citation| last = Freedom House | title = Women’s Rights in the Middle East and North Africa 2010|url=http://freedomhouse.org/template.cfm?page=383&amp;key=24&amp;parent=23&amp;report=86|date = 2010-03 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jordan]] ({{As of|2009|lc=y}}),&lt;ref name=Warrick66&gt;{{Cite book | publisher = Ashgate Pub. | isbn = 978-0-7546-7587-7 0754675874 | last = Warrick | first = Catherine. | title = Law in the service of legitimacy: Gender and politics in Jordan | location = Farnham, Surrey, England; Burlington, Vt. | year = 2009 | page = 66 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cameroon]] ({{as of|2007|lc=y}}),&lt;ref name=NYCBar30&gt;{{Cite journal | last = Barad | first = E. | coauthors = E. Slattery, and the following: Enikő Horváth, Monwabisi Zukani, Desmond Eppel, Monica Kays, Abdoul Konare, Yeora S. Park, Ekaterina Y. Pischalnikova, Nathaniel Stankard and Tally Zingher With the assistance of: Alana F. Montas and Nicole Manara | title = Gender-Based Violence Laws in Sub-Saharan Africa | journal = Report prepared for the Committee on African Affairs of the New York City Bar | year = 2007 | page =  30 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Brazil]] ({{as of|2003|lc=y}}),&lt;ref name=Warrick66 /&gt; [[Guatemala]] ({{as of|2001|lc=y}}),&lt;ref name=Warrick66 /&gt; and [[Bolivia]] ({{As of|1999|lc=y}}).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oas.org/juridico/spanish/gapeca_sp_docs_bol1.pdf Código Penal] of Bolivia, Art. 317.&lt;/ref&gt; Such laws were ended in [[Mexico]] in 1991, [[Colombia]] in 1997, [[Peru]] in 1999,&lt;ref name=Warrick66 /&gt; and [[Ethiopia]] in 2005.&lt;ref name=NYCBar30 /&gt;

== Prevalence ==
In 1982 [[Diana E. H. Russell]], a radical feminist writer and activist, published a landmark study on marital rape.  Her study surveyed in the summer of 1978 a total of 930 women from San Francisco, California (50% non-response rate, Asian women were specifically excluded as non-reliable respondents) of whom 644 had husbands to whom they were married, or were divorced from them (ex-husbands), or whom they self-identified as a husband although not legally married. 6 of these women (1%) responded that they had been raped by their husbands. The survey interviewers, however, classified 74 (12%) of the women as having been raped. Of the 286 non-married women in the sample, 228 (80%) were classified by the interviewers as having been raped. Russell found that when repeated instances of rape by husbands and ex-husbands are included, these account for 38% of all rape instances, making it one of the most prevalent types of rape.&lt;ref&gt;Russell, Diana E. H., Rape in Marriage. Indiana University Press, New edition, 1990, pp. 57-58, 65-67&lt;/ref&gt;  

[[David Finkelhor]] and Kersti Yllo published a study in 1985 on martial rape that drew on a scientifically-selected area probability sample from the metropolitan Boston area of 323 women who were married or previously married who had a child living with them between the ages of six and fourteen.  The study found that of the women who were married the instance of sexual relations through physical force or the threat of physical force was 3%.&lt;ref&gt;Finkelhor, David, and Yllo, Kersti, License to Rape. New York.  Holt, Rinehart and Winston, 1985, p. 204, p. 205, Table A-2.&lt;/ref&gt; 

A 1992 survey by the National Victim Center in [[Arlington, Virginia]] states that 10% of all sexual assault cases reported by women involved a husband or ex-husband.  

In 1994, Patricia Easteal, then Senior Criminologist at the Australian Institute of Criminology, published the results of survey on sexual assault in many settings. The respondents had been victims of numerous forms of sexual assault. Of these, 10.4% had been raped by husbands or ''de facto'' spouses, with a further 2.3% raped by estranged husbands/''de factos''. &lt;!-- irrelevant statistic: 5.5 percent were raped by non-cohabiting boyfriends. (Easteal, 1994)--&gt; &lt;!-- page number would be a help --&gt;

A 1997 study led by Kathleen C. Basile found that 13% of US married women had experienced rape (defined as unwanted sex obtained through the use or threat of force) by their current husband.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | issn = 0886-6708 | volume = 17 | issue = 5 | page = 511 | last = Basile | first = Kathleen C. | title = Prevalence of Wife Rape and Other Intimate Partner Sexual Coercion in a Nationally Representative Sample of Women | journal = Violence and Victims | date = 2002-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the UK, statistics disseminated by the Rape Crisis Federation yield the information that the most common rapists are husbands, ex-husbands, or partners.&lt;ref&gt;Myhill and Allen, Rape and Sexual Assault of Women: Findings from the  [http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/rds/pdfs2/r159.pdf British Crime Survey]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- irrelevant statistic: Other figures {{Citation needed|date=February 2007}} estimate that one in seven women is raped by a sexual intimate.--&gt; 
&lt;!-- irrelevant fact: Rape also occurs in lesbian and gay relationships. It is not known to what extent women rape male partners.--&gt;

The prevalence of marital rape depends on the particularly legal, national and cultural context. In 1999, the [[World Health Organization]] conducted a study on violence against women in [[Tajikistan]], surveying 900 women above the age of 14 in three districts of the country and found that 47% of married women reported having been forced to have sex by their husband.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eurasianet.org/policy_forum/vand022001.shtml ]{{dead link|date=May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Turkey]] 35.6% of women have experienced marital rape sometimes and 16.3% often.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.religiousconsultation.org/Special_Features/Amnesty_International_violence_vs_women.htm |title=Amnesty International: Report on Violence Against Women |publisher=Religiousconsultation.org |date= |accessdate=2012-05-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Sustaining factors ==
Young women from various settings in [[South Asia]] explained in surveys that even if they felt discomfort and didn't want to have sex, they accepted their husbands' wishes and submitted, fearing that otherwise they would be beaten.&lt;ref name=&quot;popcouncil.org&quot;&gt;http://www.popcouncil.org/pdfs/popsyn/PopulationSynthesis1.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; In many [[developing countries]] it is believed—by both men and women—that a husband is entitled to sex any time he demands it, and that if his wife refuses him, he has the right to use force.&lt;ref name=&quot;popcouncil.org&quot;/&gt; These women, most of them either [[illiterate]] or very poorly educated, are married at very young ages (in [[Bangladesh]], for example, according to statistics from 2005, 45% of women then aged between 25–29 had been married by the age of 15&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unfpa.org/swp/2005/presskit/factsheets/facts_child_marriage.htm |title=Child Marriage Factsheet: State of World Population 2005 |publisher=UNFPA |date= |accessdate=2012-05-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;), and depend on their husbands for their entire life. This situation leaves women with very little sexual autonomy. Often, when asked by their husbands to have sex, they are not in a position to refuse: they have to choose between unwanted sex and being subjected to violence; or between unwanted sex and being abandoned by their husbands and ending up living in abject poverty.

==Problems in prosecuting spousal rape==
There have been many problems with prosecuting the perpetrators of spousal rape, chief amongst them has been the reluctance of the various legal systems to recognize it as a crime at all. However, criminalization has opened a new set of problems. To take an example in the [[United Kingdom]], such a category of rape was only recognized by a 1991 [[House of Lords]] decision known simply as ''R v R (1991 All ER 481)''. While most parties agreed with the House of Lords' motive in making the decision, there were many who were of the opinion that the decision involved ''post facto'' criminalization, since the House of Lords were imprisoning spouses for doing what was once, according to the law, their right.

The second problem arises on what can be called a procedural level. While the law in theory may hold no distinction between a spouse or any other person, in practice when the case comes to court there will be difficulties in proving that rape in fact took place. This is because in marriage, sexual relations are to be expected, and if the defense claims consent, then the evidential burden is a very difficult burden for the prosecution to discharge.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.enterstageright.com/archive/articles/0205/0205sprape.htm |title=ESR &amp;#124; February 21, 2005 &amp;#124; Spousal rape case sparks old debate |publisher=Enterstageright.com |date=2005-02-21 |accessdate=2012-05-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The very definition of consent can also lead to problems and deadlock, since [[Norm (sociology)|social norms]] permit a varying level of [[physical intimacy]] (and freedom) depending on the relationship between the parties.

== Countries that have made spousal rape a criminal offence ==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-break}}
* [[Albania]]
* [[Andorra]]
* [[Angola]]
* [[Antigua and Barbuda]]
* [[Argentina]]
* [[Australia]]
* [[Austria]]
* [[Barbados]]
* [[Belgium]]
* [[Belize]]
* [[Bhutan]]
* [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]]
* [[Brazil]]
* [[Bulgaria]]
* [[Canada]]
* [[Cape Verde]]
* [[Chile]]
* [[Colombia]]
* [[Costa Rica]]
{{col-break}}
* [[Croatia]]
* [[Cuba]]
* [[Cyprus]]
* [[Czech Republic]]
* [[Denmark]]
* [[Dominica]]
* [[Dominican Republic]]
* [[Ecuador]]
* [[El Salvador]]
* [[Estonia]]
* [[Fiji]]
* [[Finland]]
* [[France]]
* [[Germany]]
* [[Greece]]
* [[Grenada]]
* [[Guatemala]]
* [[Guinea-Bissau]]
* [[Hong Kong]]
{{col-break}}
* [[Hungary]]
* [[Iceland]]
* [[Ireland]]
* [[Israel]]
* [[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]]
* [[Mauritania]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/hrrpt/2009/af/135965.htm |title=2009 Human Rights Report: Mauritania |publisher=State.gov |date=2010-03-11 |accessdate=2012-05-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Latvia]]
* [[Lithuania]]
* [[Malaysia]]
* [[Malta]]
* [[Mexico]]
* [[Monaco]]
* [[Montenegro]]
* [[Namibia]]
* [[Nepal]]
* [[Netherlands]]
* [[New Zealand]]
* [[Norway]]
{{col-break}}
* [[Philippines]]
* [[Poland]]
* [[Peru]]
* [[Republic of the Congo]]
* [[Romania]]
* [[Russia]]
* [[Serbia]]
* [[Slovenia]]&lt;ref name=Slovenia /&gt;
* [[South Africa]]
* [[Spain]]
* [[Sweden]]
* [[Republic of China|Taiwan]]
* [[Trinidad and Tobago]]
* [[Turkey]]
* [[Ukraine]]
* [[United Kingdom]]
* [[United States]]
* [[Uzbekistan]]
* [[Zimbabwe]]&lt;ref&gt;U.S. State Department [http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/hrrpt/2008/index.htm 2008 Country Reports on Human Rights Practices]&lt;/ref&gt;{{Failed verification|date=July 2010}}
{{col-end}}

===Only criminalized when couple is legally separated===
* [[Bahamas]] (Termed &quot;spousal sexual assault&quot; eligible for less jail time than charges of rape; requires permission of Attorney General to prosecute)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Sexual Offences Act of the Bahamas|url=http://www.oas.org/dil/Sexual_Offences_and_Domestic_Violence_Act_Bahamas.pdf|publisher=Government of the Bahamas}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Japan]] &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Research Foundation for Safe Society|url=http://www.syaanken.or.jp/wp-content/uploads/2012/05/sh1831shounen1803.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Singapore]] (legal separation, divorce, restraining order, or attempt by the assaulted party to receive such legal status)&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last = Equality Now | title = Words and Deeds: Holding Governments Accountable in the Beijing +15 Review Process | accessdate = 2011-03-07 | year = 2010 | url = http://equalitynow.org/english/campaigns/beijing15/report_en.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Sri Lanka]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
| publisher = SAGE
| isbn = 978-0-7619-9796-2
| last = Goonesekere
| first = Savitri
| title = Violence, law and women's rights in South Asia
| year = 2004
| pages = 60–61
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| last = Fernando
| first = Vijita
| title = Sri Lanka: Island Dilemma: Is It Marital Rape or Domestic Violence?
| work = News Blaze
| accessdate = 2010-07-21
| date = 2008-10-14
| url = http://newsblaze.com/story/20081014080156zzzz.nb/topstory.html
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Tanzania]]&lt;ref name=Stefiszyn&gt;Karen Stefiszyn, &quot;[http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/egm/vaw_legislation_2008/expertpapers/EGMGPLVAW%20Paper%20(Karen%20Stefiszyn).pdf A Brief Overview of Recent Developments in Sexual Offences Legislation in Southern Africa],&quot; United Nations, EGM/GPLVAW/2008/EP.04, 12 May 2008&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[India]] (according to Indian Penal Code section 376(A) Intercourse by a man with his wife during separation.—Whoever has sexual intercourse with his wife, who is living separately from him under a decree of separation or under any custom or usage without her consent shall be punished with imprisonment of either description for a term which may extend to two years and shall also be liable to fine.)

===Treated as a form of noncriminal domestic violence===
* [[India]]&lt;ref name=&quot;news.independent.co.uk&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sarid.net&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vakilno1.com/bareacts/indianpenalcode/s375.htm |title=Indian Penal Code 375 |publisher=Vakilno1.com |date= |accessdate=2012-05-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=ARROW2011 /&gt;
* [[Indonesia]]&lt;ref name=ARROW2011 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Our breakthrough finally came in September 2004. After years of effort, the parliament passed the law on violence against women in the home (Law No. 23/2004). The new law outlaws four forms of violence – physical, psychological, sexual (including marital rape), and economic neglect. Significantly the law makes ‘criminal’ violence against all members of the household, including husbands, wives, children and extended family members.&quot; Ratna Bataramunti &quot;[http://www.insideindonesia.org/edition-87/justice-for-women Justice for women? New anti-domestic violence law brings hope for women],&quot; ''Inside Indonesia'', July–September 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Vietnam]]&lt;ref name=ARROW2011&gt;{{cite book|title=Reclaiming &amp; Redefining Rights: Thematic Studies Series 1: Sexuality &amp; Rights in Asia|year=2011|publisher=ARROW|location=Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia|url=http://www.arrow.org.my/publications/ICPD+15Country&amp;ThematicCaseStudies/ThematicCaseStudies/Sexuality&amp;Rights.pdf|author=Asian-Pacific Resource &amp; Research Centre for Women (ARROW)| pages = 22–23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Countries that have not made marital rape a criminal offence ==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-break}}
* [[Afghanistan]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Rape is not a crime in the Afghan Penal Code. Under the code, rapists can only be charged with “forced” zina, or adultery, which sometimes results in women also being prosecuted for zina.&quot; {{Cite book
| publisher = Human Rights Watch
| author = Human Rights Watch
| title = &quot;We Have the Promises of the World&quot;: Women’s Rights in Afghanistan
| year = 2009
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Algeria]]&lt;ref name=FH2010 /&gt;
* [[Bahrain]]&lt;ref name=FH2010 /&gt;
* [[Bangladesh]]&lt;ref name=ARROW2011 /&gt;
* [[Bolivia]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Bolivia|url=http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/hrrpt/2009/wha/136102.htm|work=2009 Country Reports on Human Rights Practices|accessdate=8 March 2011|author=US State Department|date=March 11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Botswana]]&lt;ref name=Stefiszyn /&gt;
* [[Brunei Darussalam]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The 'Explanation' which forms part of Article 375 of Brunei’s Penal Code (rape) stipulates that 'Sexual intercourse by a man with his own wife, the wife not being under thirteen (13) years of age, is not rape.' This amounts to legalisation and legitimization of marital rape, including the rape of children, in flagrant violation of international human rights law.&quot; Amnesty International, &quot;[http://www.amnesty.org/en/library/asset/ASA15/001/2009/en/34c4959d-8833-4c3e-8b3b-34dfe99c9593/asa150012009en.html Brunei Darussalam: Amnesty International submission to the UN Universal Periodic Review],&quot; Sixth session of the UPR Working Group, November–December 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Cameroon]] (for adult victims who consented to marriage)&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Marital rape is not illegal as long as the marriage was freely consented to between the rapist and the victim and the victim was of age [(16 or over)] at the time of the rape.&quot; {{Cite news | title = Allegedly false rape reports make authorities skeptical, discourage victims in Cameroon | work = TrustLaw | accessdate = 2012-01-29 | date = 2012-01-28 | url = http://www.trust.org/trustlaw/news/allegedly-false-rape-reports-make-authorities-skeptical-discourage-victims-in-cameroon }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[People's Republic of China|China]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=China: MDG 3: Promote Gender Equality and Empower Woman|url=http://www.mdg5watch.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=93&amp;Itemid=155#_edn21|accessdate=8 March 2011|author=Asian-Pacific Resource and Research Centre (ARROW)|quote=China has no legal provisions for marital rape and the main reason for this is in deference to a prevailing cultural perception that wives are supposed to submit to their husband’s wishes in matters of sexual relations and hence, there is no such concept of ‘rape’ within marriage or ‘rape’ being considered a form of violence within the marriage.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Democratic Republic of Congo]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal| doi = 10.2105/AJPH.2010.300070| issn = 00900036| volume = 101| issue = 6| pages = 1060–1067| last = Peterman| first = Amber| coauthors = Tia Palermo, Caryn Bredenkamp| title = Estimates and Determinants of Sexual Violence Against Women in the Democratic Republic of Congo| journal = American Journal of Public Health| date = 2011-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Egypt]]&lt;ref name=Warrick&gt;{{Cite book | publisher = Ashgate Pub. | isbn = 978-0-7546-7587-7 0754675874 | last = Warrick | first = Catherine. | title = Law in the service of legitimacy: Gender and politics in Jordan | location = Farnham, Surrey, England; Burlington, Vt. | year = 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Ethiopia]]&lt;ref name=FBanda&gt;Fareda Banda, [http://www.ohchr.org/Documents/Publications/laws_that_discriminate_against_women.pdf Project on a Mechanism to Address Laws that Discriminate Against Women], Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights – Women’s Rights and Gender Unit, 6 March 2008, pp. 85-87.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Haiti]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Klasing|first=Amanda|title=A chance for Congress to help Haitian women|url=http://www.hrw.org/news/2012/01/24/chance-congress-help-haitian-women|work=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=10 May 2012|date=24 January 2012|quote=The penal code includes penalties for rape but does not address marital rape.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{col-break}}
* [[Honduras]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Honduras: Domestic violence; legislation and protection available to victims (2007-2009)|url=http://www.unhcr.org/refworld/topic,4565c22547,4565c25f569,4b7cee7c26,0.html|accessdate=29 January 2012|author=Immigration and Refugee Board of Canada|date=13 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Iran]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | publisher = The Policy Press | isbn = 978-1-84742-620-8 | last = Westmarland | first = Nicole | coauthors = Geetanjali Gangoli | title = International Approaches to Rape | date = 2011-04-06 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Jordan]]&lt;ref name=Warrick /&gt;
* [[Kenya]]&lt;ref name=FBanda /&gt;
* [[Kuwait]]&lt;ref name=MusawahKO&gt;{{cite book|title=Musawah Thematic Report on Article 16: Kuwait and Oman (50th CEDAW Session)|year=October 2011|location=Selangor, Malaysia|url=http://www.musawah.org/musawah-thematic-report-article-16-kuwait-and-oman|author=Musawah}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Laos]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Lao People’s Democratic Republic boasts new legislation, machinery to improve women’s lot, but expert committee faults rape, domestic violence policies|url=http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs/2009/wom1743.doc.htm|accessdate=8 March 2011|author=UN Committee on Elimination of Discrimination against Women|location=WOM/1743|date=24 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Lebanon]]&lt;ref name=FH2010 /&gt;
* [[Liberia]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://stanford.edu/group/womenscourage/cgi-bin/blogs/sextraffickingandprostitution/2010/05/13/liberias-struggle-against-sexual-violence-in-the-wake-of-conflict/ Liberia's struggle against sexual violence in the wake of conflict],&quot; ''Sex Trafficking and Prostitution'', Stanford University.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Libya]]&lt;ref&gt;Amnesty International, &quot;[http://www.amnesty.org.uk/content.asp?CategoryID=12055 Libya],&quot; 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Malawi]]&lt;ref name=Stefiszyn /&gt;
* [[Mali]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.map-srhr.org/chapters/ch-3-overview-of-sexual-and-reproductive-health-and-rights-in-africa/mali#instruments-and-policies MALI: Sexual and Reproductive Health and Rights] (Instruments and Policies tab), in Women's Network for a Better World, ''[http://www.map-srhr.org/chapters/ch-3-overview-of-sexual-and-reproductive-health-and-rights-in-africa/niger Map of sexual and reproductive health and rights in Africa and Spain]''.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Mongolia]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://stopvaw.org/sites/3f6d15f4-c12d-4515-8544-26b7a3a5a41e/uploads/Sexualabusefacteng.pdf |title=The situation of sexual violence and rape and relevant legislation in Mongolia |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2012-05-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Morocco]]&lt;ref name=FH2010 /&gt;
{{col-break}}
* [[Myanmar]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Concluding observations of the Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women: Myanmar|accessdate=8 March 2011|author=Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women|url=http://www.burmalibrary.org/docs5/CEDAW-C-MMR-CO-3.pdf|location=CEDAW/C/MMR/CO/3|date=7 November 2008|page=para. 46}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Nigeria]]&lt;ref name=FBanda /&gt;
* [[Oman]]&lt;ref name=FH2010 /&gt;&lt;ref name=MusawahKO /&gt;
* [[Pakistan]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | publisher = Seven Stories Press | isbn = 978-1-58322-740-4 | last = Human Rights Watch | title = Human Rights Watch World Report 2007 | date = 2007-04-10 | pages = 300–301 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Saudi Arabia]]&lt;ref name=&quot;usgov2009SA&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=2009 Human Rights Report: Saudi Arabia|url=http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/hrrpt/2009/nea/136079.htm|publisher=U.S. State Department|accessdate=21 September 2010|date=11 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Singapore]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Sexual offences|work=statutes.agc.gov.sg|url=http://statutes.agc.gov.sg/aol/search/display/view.w3p;ident=c834c73a-3531-48b0-8040-4450d41d1351;page=0;query=Status%3Ainforce%20CapAct%3A224%20Depth%3A0;rec=0;resUrl=http%3A%2F%2Fstatutes.agc.gov.sg%2Faol%2Fsearch%2Fsummary%2Fresults.w3p%3Bquery%3DStatus%253Ainforce%2520CapAct%253A224%2520Depth%253A0#pr375-he-.|accessdate=12 July 2012|publisher=[[Attorney-General of Singapore|Attorney-General's Chambers]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[South Sudan]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.goss-online.org/magnoliaPublic/en/Laws--Legislation--Policies/mainColumnParagraphs/0/content_files/file12/15.pdf Penal Code Act, 2008 of South Sudan (Page 129)]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Sudan]]&lt;ref name=FBanda /&gt;
* [[Syria]]&lt;ref name=FH2010 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last = UK Home Office | title = Country of Origin Information Report - The Syrian Arab Republic | accessdate = 2011-03-08 | date = 2010-09-03 | url = http://www.unhcr.org/cgi-bin/texis/vtx/refworld/rwmain?page=search&amp;amp;docid=4c84c0fb2&amp;amp;skip=0&amp;amp;query=syria%20marital%20rape }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Tonga]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Section 118(2) of the Criminal Offences Act | work = The Secretary Generals database on violence against women | accessdate = 2011-03-07 | url = http://webapps01.un.org/vawdatabase/searchDetail.action?measureId=10689&amp;baseHREF=country&amp;baseHREFId=1305 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = Women &amp; Children Crisis Centre | title = Gaps in Tongan Rape Law need to be addressed:: | accessdate = 2011-03-07 | url = http://www.wccc.tbu.to/news/gaps-in-tongan-rape-law-need-to-be-addressed/ }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Uganda]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |work=The Observer |url=http://www.observer.ug/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=8645%3Athe-phenomenon-of-marital-rape&amp;catid=73%3Ahighlights&amp;Itemid=70 |first=Patience |date=May 26, 2010 |title=The phenomenon of marital rape |last=Akumu}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Yemen]]&lt;ref name=FBanda /&gt;
* [[Zambia]]&lt;ref name=Stefiszyn /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;A clause outlawing marital rape has been dropped because of cultural considerations.&quot;
{{Cite news
| last = Fidgen
| first = Jo
| title = Zambia's celebrity couple reveal wife-beating past
| work = BBC
| accessdate = 2010-07-22
| date = 2009-11-30
| url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/8375291.stm
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;But Zambia does not have a comprehensive law on sexual violence or a provision for marital rape or psychological abuse in its penal code.&quot; {{Cite conference
| last = Human Rights Watch
| title = Zambia: Curbing Sexual and Gender-Based Violence
| accessdate = 2010-07-22
| date = 2008-12-16
| url = http://www.unhcr.org/refworld/publisher,HRW,,ZMB,494b62e917,0.html
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{col-end}}

==See also==
* [[Implied consent]]
* ''[[Maouloud Baby v. State of Maryland]]'', court case having to do with the withdrawing of sexual consent
* [[National Clearinghouse on Marital and Date Rape]]
* [[Recognition of marital rape in Pakistani Law]]
* [[Types of rape]]
* [[Victimology]]

== References ==
* Bergen, Raquel Kennedy, [http://www.taasa.org/library/pdfs/TAASALibrary104.pdf &quot;Marital Rape&quot;] on the site of the Applied Research Forum, National Electronic Network on [[Violence against women|Violence Against Women]]. Article dated March 1999. (Retrieved February 8, 2005.)
* {{Cite journal | doi = 10.1177/1524838003004003003 | volume = 4 | issue = 3 | pages = 228–246 | last = Bennice | first = Jennifer A. | coauthors = Patricia A. Resick | title = Marital Rape | journal = Trauma, Violence, &amp; Abuse | accessdate = 2011-03-10 | date = 2003-07-01 | url = http://tva.sagepub.com.ezproxy.gc.cuny.edu/content/4/3/228.abstract }}
* Easteal, P. ''Voices of the Survivors'', Spinifex Press, North Melbourne, 1994.
* Finkelhor, D. and Yllo, K., ''License to Rape'', [[Free Press (publisher)|The Free Press]], New York 1985.
* Gan, K., [http://web.archive.org/web/20041012182003/http://www2.malaysiakini.com/letters/29772 Sex a conjugal right], on the site of [http://www.malaysiakini.com/ Malaysiakini]. Article dated September 2004. (Retrieved April 20, 2005. Original link is dead, substitute link is to the [[Internet Archive]], and is dated October 12, 2004.)
* Russell, Diana E.H., ''Rape in Marriage'' Macmillan Publishing Company, USA, 1990.
* The [http://www.abanet.org American Bar Association], [http://www.abanet.org/media/factbooks/womenlaw.pdf Facts about Women and the Law]. (Retrieved April 20, 2005.)
* [[United Nations General Assembly|General Assembly]] resolution 48/104 of 20, [http://www.unhchr.ch/huridocda/huridoca.nsf/(Symbol)/A.RES.48.104.En?Opendocument Declaration on the Elimination of Violence against Women], on the site of the [[Office of the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights]], December 1993.  (Retrieved April 20, 2005.)
*&amp;mdash;, [http://www.actabuse.com/maritalrape.html Marital Rape], on the site of [http://www.actabuse.com/ Abuse Counseling and Treatment, Inc.] (Retrieved February 8, 2005.)
* [http://www.hiddenhurt.co.uk/marital_rape.html Hidden Hurt]

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
* For a brief overview view of partner rape, see [http://www.star.ak.org/Library/files/maritalrape.htm STAR Library - Marital Rape]
* Minnesota Advocates for Human Rights, [http://www.stopvaw.org/Marital_and_Intimate_Partner_Sexual_Assault.html Marital and Intimate Partner Sexual Assault], ''Stop Violence Against Women''.
* [http://www.aphroditewounded.org Aphrodite Wounded]: Partner Rape Facts, Survivor Support and Educational Resources
* [http://www.theawarenesscenter.org/domesticviolence.html Domestic Violence / Marital Rape in Jewish Families]
* Global AIDS Programme [http://www.panosaids.org/aidsday04/toolkit_policy.htm World AIDS Day 2004]. (Retrieved April 20, 2005).
* [http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1699482 Real Rape, Real Pain: Help for Women Sexually Assaulted by Male Partners] Patricia L. Easteal, Louise McOrmond-Plummer
* [http://www.whealth.com.au/work_raped_by_partner.html] Raped by a Partner Research Report 2008 and [http://www.whealth.com.au/work_partner_rape.html] Partner Rape Educational DVD 2009 produced by Women's Health Goulburn North East.
{{Domestic violence}}
{{Sexual abuse}}
{{abuse}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Spousal Rape}}
[[Category:Sex crimes]]
[[Category:Rape]]
[[Category:Marriage]]
[[Category:Article Feedback 5]]

[[ru:Изнасилование в браке]]</text>
      <sha1>0q85e8695sbjbbnsn28yf6l5yg9qsk0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
