<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Nancy Grace</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>11481790</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520548701</id>
      <parentid>520531765</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-30T05:43:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>EmausBot</username>
        <id>11292982</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>r2.7.3) (Robot: Adding [[tl:Nancy Grace]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="43425">{{For|her current affairs program of the same name|Nancy Grace (TV series)}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=August 2011}}
{{Infobox person
| name=Nancy Grace
| image=Nancy Grace.PNG
| birthname=Nancy Ann Grace
| birth_date={{birth date and age|mf=yes|1959|10|23}}
| birth_place=[[Macon, Georgia|Macon]], Georgia, United States
| salary:=
| death_place=
| education={{nowrap|[[Valdosta State University]]}}&lt;br&gt;{{nowrap|[[Mercer University]] &lt;small&gt;([[Bachelor of Arts|BA]], [[Juris Doctor|JD]])&lt;/small&gt;}}&lt;br&gt;{{nowrap|[[New York University]] &lt;small&gt;([[Master of Law|LLM]])&lt;/small&gt;}}
| occupation=Political commentator, television personality, former prosecutor
| title=
| family=
| years_active=1996–present
| spouse=David Linch (2007–present)
| religion=Christian
| children=Lucy Elizabeth, John David
| credits=''[[Court TV|Closing Arguments]]'' anchor (1996–2007) &lt;br /&gt; ''[[Nancy Grace (TV series)|Nancy Grace]]'' anchor (2005–present)
| URL=
| agent=
}}

'''Nancy Ann Grace''' (born October 23, 1959&lt;ref&gt;http://www.imdb.com/name/nm1456912/&lt;/ref&gt;) is an American legal [[Political commentator|commentator]], television host, television journalist, and former [[prosecutor]]. She frequently discusses issues from what she describes as a [[victims' rights]] standpoint, with an outspoken style that has won her both praise and condemnation. She is the host of ''[[Nancy Grace (TV series)|Nancy Grace]]'', a nightly celebrity news and [[current affairs (news format)|current affairs show]] on [[HLN (TV channel)|HLN]], and she was the host of [[TruTV|Court TV's]] ''Closing Arguments''. She also co-wrote the book ''Objection! — How High-Priced Defense Attorneys, Celebrity Defendants, and a 24/7 Media Have Hijacked Our Criminal Justice System.'' She was also the host of ''[[Swift Justice with Jackie Glass|Swift Justice with Nancy Grace]]'', a syndicated courtroom reality show on which her replacement, former [[Clark County, Nevada|Clark County]] District Court Judge Jackie Glass, was announced May 24, 2011, effective at the end of its first season.

==Early life==
Nancy Grace was born in [[Macon, Georgia]], the youngest of three children, to Mac Grace, a freight agent for [[Southern Railway (U.S.)|Southern Railway]], and Elizabeth Grace, a factory worker. &lt;ref name=&quot;jobs&quot;&gt;[http://www.guideposts.org/celebrities/nancy-graces-inspiring-story-overcoming-grief-through-her-mission-god Nancy Grace's Inspiring Story]&lt;/ref&gt; Grace has two older siblings: a brother, Mac Jr., and a sister, Ginny.&lt;ref name=&quot;park&quot;&gt;[http://www.macon.com/2011/04/17/1528639_grace-park-finds-a-rainbow.html Grace Park finds a rainbow]{{dead link|date=June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The members of the Grace family have been longtime members of Macon's Liberty United Methodist Church, where Nancy's mother Elizabeth plays the church organ and her father Mac was once a Sunday School teacher.&lt;ref name=&quot;park&quot; /&gt;

Grace attended high school at Macon's [[Windsor Academy]], graduating in 1977.&lt;ref name=&quot;windsor&quot;&gt;[http://www.windsoracademyknights.com/alumniNews.asp?id=1 NANCY GRACE PROMOTES MYSTERY NOVEL]&lt;/ref&gt; She attended [[Valdosta State University]], and later received a B.A. from [[Mercer University]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NNDB&quot;&gt;http://www.nndb.com/people/122/000104807/ Retrieved December 15, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; As a student, Grace was a [[fan (aficionado)|fan]] of [[William Shakespeare|Shakespearean]] literature, and intended to become an English professor after graduating from college.&lt;ref name=&quot;jobs&quot; /&gt; However, after the murder of her fiancé, Keith Griffin, when she was 19, Grace decided to enroll in law school and went on to become a felony [[prosecutor]] and a supporter of [[victim's rights group|victims' rights]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CNN Profile&quot;&gt;[http://www.cnn.com/CNN/anchors_reporters/grace.nancy.html CNN &quot;Anchors &amp; Reporters&quot; profile] CNN.com&lt;/ref&gt;

Grace was a member of the [[law review]] at and received her [[Juris Doctor]] from the [[Walter F. George School of Law]] at Mercer. She went on to earn a [[Master of Laws]] in constitutional and criminal law from [[New York University]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CNN Profile&quot;/&gt; She has written articles and opinion pieces for legal periodicals, including the ''[[American Bar Association Journal]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;CNN Profile&quot;/&gt; Grace worked as a clerk for a federal court judge and practiced [[antitrust]] and [[consumer protection]] law with the [[Federal Trade Commission]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CNN Profile&quot;/&gt; She taught litigation at the [[Georgia State University College of Law]] and business law at GSU's School of Business.&lt;ref name=&quot;CNN Profile&quot;/&gt; As of 2006, she is part of Mercer University's board of trustees and adopted a section of the street surrounding the law school.

==Career as prosecutor==
Grace worked for nearly a decade in the [[Atlanta]]-[[Fulton County, Georgia]] [[District Attorney]]'s office as Special Prosecutor. Her work focused on felony cases involving serial murder, serial rape, serial child molestation, and arson.&lt;ref name=&quot;CourtTV bio&quot;&gt;{{wayback|http://web.archive.org/web/20070406181716/www.courttv.com/anchors/nancy_grace.html Court TV Anchor biography}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Grace left the prosecutors' office after the [[District Attorney]] she had been working under decided not to run for reelection.&lt;ref name=&quot;Larry05&quot;&gt;[http://transcripts.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/0502/20/lkl.01.html ''Larry King Live; Interview with Nancy Grace''] CNN transcript. Aired February 20, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

===Prosecutorial misconduct===
The [[Supreme Court of Georgia (U.S. state)|Supreme Court of Georgia]] has twice commented on Grace's conduct as a prosecutor. First, in a 1994 heroin drug trafficking case,
''Bell v. State'', the Court declared a mistrial, saying that Grace had &quot;exceeded the wide latitude of closing argument&quot; by drawing comparisons to unrelated murder and rape cases.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite court|litigants=Bell v. State|vol=263|reporter=Ga. |opinion=776|year=1994|url=http://www.lawskills.com/case/ga/id/3143/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1997, the court was more severe, overturning the murder-arson conviction of businessman W. W. Carr in the death of his wife.  While the court said its reversal was not due to these transgressions, since the case had turned primarily on [[circumstantial evidence]], it nevertheless concluded &quot;the conduct of the prosecuting attorney in this case demonstrated her disregard of the notions of due process and fairness, and was inexcusable.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.law.com/jsp/article.jsp?id=1115111123854 11th Circuit Court: 'Nancy Grace 'Played Fast and Loose' With Ethics'] May 4, 2005{{Dead link|date=July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Carr was freed in 2004 when the Georgia Supreme Court ruled unanimously that Fulton County had waited too long to retry him, thereby unfairly prejudicing his right to a fair trial.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Rankin|first=Bill|title=Weldon Carr will not be retried; he's a free man|url=http://www.truthinjustice.org/carr.htm|work=Atlanta Journal-Constitution|accessdate=July 5, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite upholding the conviction she sought, a panel of the [[11th Circuit Court of Appeals]] wrote in a 2005 opinion that Grace &quot;played fast and loose&quot; with her ethical duties and failed to &quot;fulfill her responsibilities&quot; as a prosecutor in the 1990 triple murder trial of Herbert Connell Stephens.&lt;ref name=&quot;200315251.pdf&quot;&gt;[http://www.ca11.uscourts.gov/opinions/ops/200315251.pdf 11th Circuit Court: Opinion on Grace's misconduct] May 2, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;  The court agreed that it was &quot;difficult to conclude that Grace did not knowingly use ... [apparently false] testimony&quot; from a [[detective]] that there were no other suspects, despite the existence of outstanding [[arrest warrants]] for other men.&lt;ref name=&quot;200315251.pdf&quot;/&gt;

==Career as broadcaster==
After leaving the Fulton County prosecutors' office, Grace was approached by and accepted an offer from [[TruTV|Court TV]] founder [[Steven Brill (law writer)|Steven Brill]] to do a legal commentary show alongside [[Johnnie Cochran]]. When Cochran left the show, Grace was moved to a solo trial coverage show on Court TV.&lt;ref name=&quot;Larry05&quot; /&gt;

In 2005, she began hosting a regular primetime legal analysis show called [[Nancy Grace (TV series)|''Nancy Grace'']] on CNN Headline News (now HLN) in addition to her CourtTV show.&lt;ref name=&quot;CourtTV bio&quot;/&gt; On May 9, 2007, Grace announced that she would be leaving Court TV to focus more on her CNN Headline News Program and charity work.&lt;ref&gt;Associated Press (via Yahoo News), [http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20070509/ap_en_ot/people_nancy_grace;_ylt=Am1_JVjuruaoAyWTeISg5HFxFb8C Nancy Grace to end show on Court TV'']{{dead link|date=June 2012}}, May 9, 2007. Retrieved May 12, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;  She did her last show on Court TV on June 19, 2007.

Nancy Grace has a distinctive interviewing style mixing vocal questions with multimedia stats displays.  The Foundation of American Women in Radio &amp; Television has presented Nancy Grace with two [[Gracie Allen#Gracie Allen Award|Gracie Awards]] for her Court TV show.&lt;ref name=&quot;CourtTV bio&quot;/&gt;

Nancy Grace had been covering the [[Casey Anthony]] story for years. After the controversial verdict finding Casey Anthony not guilty, her show on HLN had its highest ratings ever in the 8 p.m. and 9 p.m. hour slots on Tuesday, July 5, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://khitschicago.radio.com/2011/07/07/nancy-grace-has-best-ratings-ever-after-casey-anthony-verdict/|title=Nancy Grace Has Best Ratings Ever After Casey Anthony Verdict|date=July 7, 2011|publisher=KHITS Chicago}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Grace also hosted Swift Justice with Nancy Grace premiering September 13, 2010 and running until May 2011. Grace left the show due to productions moving from Atlanta to Los Angeles. In September 2011, Judge [[Jackie Glass]], who is known for presiding over the [[O. J. Simpson robbery case]], took over Grace's place. The show is now called Swift Justice with Jackie Glass.

===Controversies===
In 2011 a New York Times article [[David Carr (journalist)|David Carr]] wrote “Since her show began in 2005, the presumption of innocence has found a willful enemy in the former prosecutor turned broadcast judge-and-jury.&quot; He criticized her handling of the kidnapping of [[Elizabeth Smart]], the [[Duke lacrosse]] team rape case, the [[Melinda Duckett]] interview and [[suicide]] and the [[Caylee Anthony]] case. [[George Washington University]] law professor [[Jonathan Turley]] told Carr that Grace, as an attorney and reporter, “has managed to demean both professions with her hype, rabid persona, and sensational analysis. Some part of the public takes her seriously, and her show erodes the respect for basic rights.”&lt;ref name=Carr-NYTimes&gt;David Carr,  [http://www.nytimes.com/2011/05/23/business/media/23carr.html?_r=1 TV Justice Thrives on Fear], [[New York Times]], May 22, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Elizabeth Smart kidnapping====
During the 2002 [[Elizabeth Smart (activist)|Elizabeth Smart]] kidnapping case, when suspect Richard Ricci was arrested by police on the basis that he had a criminal record and had worked on the Smarts' home, Grace immediately and repeatedly proclaimed on CourtTV and CNN's [[Larry King]] that Ricci &quot;was guilty,&quot; although there was little evidence to support this claim. She also suggested publicly that Ricci's girlfriend was involved in the cover-up of his alleged crime. Grace continued to accuse Ricci, though he died while in custody.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www-cgi.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/0306/23/lkl.00.html cnn transcript Larry kKing.]&lt;/ref&gt;

It was later revealed that Smart was kidnapped by Brian David Mitchell and Wanda Barzee, two individuals with whom Richard Ricci had no connection.&lt;ref&gt;[http://crime.about.com/od/current/a/elizabeth_smart.htm about: The Elizabeth Smart Case]&lt;/ref&gt;

When CourtTV confronted Grace seven months later to ask whether she was incorrect in her assertion that Ricci was guilty, and whether or not she felt bad about it in any way, she stated that Ricci was &quot;a known ex-con, a known felon, and brought suspicion on himself, so who could blame anyone for claiming he was the perpetrator?&quot; When Larry King asked her about the matter, she equated criticism of herself with criticism of the police in the case. She said: &quot;I'm not letting you take the police with me on a guilt trip.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;fury&quot;&gt;[http://www.tnr.com/article/politics/trial-fury Presumed Guilty: Trial by Fury] March 8, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 2006, Grace interviewed Smart, who was promoting a legislative bill. Grace repeatedly asked her for information regarding her abduction. Smart told her she didn't feel comfortable discussing it, despite Grace's persistence in the matter. Finally, Grace stopped when Smart said she &quot;didn't appreciate you [Grace] bringing all this up.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5x8ARIxg51I Insane Nancy Grace gets owned by Elizabeth Smart - YouTube&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Danielle van Dam case ====

During the trial of [[David Westerfield]] in 2002 for the [[kidnap]] and murder of Danielle van Dam, Nancy Grace made it clear on CNN's [[Larry King Live]] that she thought him guilty, but she got many facts wrong, and she also made some statements pointing to his possible innocence.

She accused him of [[steam-cleaning]] his [[RV]], but [[Henry Lee (forensic scientist)|Dr. Henry Lee]] pointed out that, had he done so, they wouldn’t have found the [[fingerprint|fingerprints]] and the [[blood residue | bloodstain]] on the [[carpet]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www-cgi.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/0207/15/lkl.00.html Interview With Nancy Grace, Marc Klaas, Jan Ronis], CNN Larry King Live, Aired July 15, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www-cgi.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/0208/05/lkl.00.html Expert Panel Discusses Kidnapping Trials], CNN Larry King Live, Aired August 5, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; In fact, very little cleaning had been done, as evidenced by the absence of the smell of cleaning products, and the fine layer of [[dust]] throughout the interior of the vehicle, and it was the van Dams, not Westerfield, who had a steam-cleaner.&lt;ref&gt;Stevenson, C. [http://www.amazon.com/Rush-Judgement-examination-Westerfield-kidnapping/dp/1460956974/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1310482728&amp;sr=1-1 “Rush to Judgement,”] CreateSpace, June 22, 2011, pages 241 and 258.&lt;/ref&gt;

Grace argued that Westerfield’s black jacket was [[leather jacket | leather]], so van Dam [[hairs]] and [[fibers]] would not have been [[Locard's exchange principle|transferred]] onto it by “[[dirty dancing]]” at the [[bar (establishment)|bar]] on Friday night.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www-cgi.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/0208/20/lkl.00.html Westerfield Jury Completes Ninth Day of Deliberations], CNN Larry King Live, Aired August 20, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; But the jacket was open and his [[shirt]] wasn’t [[leather]], so there could have been transfer. She also thought he kept his jacket on while taking a [[shower]]: “that must be some mighty tough [[DNA]] to stick to a leather jacket and live through a shower”. That statement shows she made another mistake: Danielle’s blood was not on the jacket he was wearing Friday night - no evidence was found on any of his Friday night clothing.&lt;ref&gt;Stevenson, C. [http://www.amazon.com/Rush-Judgement-examination-Westerfield-kidnapping/dp/1460956974/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1310482728&amp;sr=1-1 “Rush to Judgement,”] CreateSpace, June 22, 2011, page 257.&lt;/ref&gt;

The strongest evidence against Westerfield was in his RV, particularly a drop of Danielle’s blood and her handprint. All that small amount of evidence could be innocently explained if, at some previous time while it was parked unlocked in the streets outside her home, Danielle had entered that vehicle, perhaps to explore it out of curiosity. There was no testimony she had done so, but to her credit, Grace said she &quot;can imagine a little girl wandering into a RV and playing in it, much as if they saw a [[swimming pool]], they might jump in, or a [[playground]], they might play on it&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www-cgi.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/0207/15/lkl.00.html Interview With Nancy Grace, Marc Klaas, Jan Ronis], CNN Larry King Live, Aired July 15, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;

She also thought that the parents’ friend Barbara Easton (the one who “[[let the cat out of the bag]]” over the parents’ sexual activities), wasn’t called to testify because she “could go into further evidence of wife-swapping and [[swinging]] on the part of the victims' family”. So Grace didn’t think the whole truth had been revealed.&lt;ref&gt;Stevenson, C. [http://www.amazon.com/Rush-Judgement-examination-Westerfield-kidnapping/dp/1460956974/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1310482728&amp;sr=1-1 “Rush to Judgement,”] CreateSpace, June 22, 2011, pages 19 to 20.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Duke lacrosse allegations====
Grace took a vehemently pro-prosecution position throughout the [[Duke lacrosse case|2006 Duke University lacrosse case]], in which [[Crystal Gail Mangum]], a stripper and [[North Carolina Central University]] student, falsely accused three members of [[Duke University]]'s men's lacrosse team of raping her at a party. Prior to Duke suspending its men's lacrosse team's season, she sarcastically noted on the air, &quot;I'm so glad they didn't miss a lacrosse game over a little thing like gang rape!&quot; and &quot;Why would you go to a cop in an alleged gang rape case, say, and lie and give misleading information?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://transcripts.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/0603/31/ng.01.html Nancy Grace transcript March 31, 2006], CNN, March 31, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;  After the disbarment of District Attorney [[Mike Nifong]], Attorney General Roy Cooper pronounced all three players innocent of the rape charges made by Mangum and Nifong.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dukenews.duke.edu/lacrosseincident/ looking back at the duke lacrosse case]&lt;/ref&gt;  On the following broadcast of her show, Grace did not appear and a substitute reporter, [[Jane Velez-Mitchell]], announced the removal of all charges.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://transcripts.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/0704/11/ng.01.html|work=CNN|title=CNN Transcript April 11, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Suicide of interviewee Melinda Duckett====
In September 2006, 21-year-old Melinda Duckett committed suicide following an interview conducted by Grace concerning the disappearance of Duckett's 2-year-old son Trenton.&lt;ref name=&quot;Multi1&quot;&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,11069-2357726,00.html CNN guest kills herself after gruelling questions] – [[The Times]]. September 14, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

Grace interviewed Duckett less than two weeks after the child went missing, questioning her for her alleged lack of openness regarding her son's disappearance, asking Duckett &quot;Where were you? Why aren't you telling us where you were that day?&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;multi2&quot;&gt;[http://transcripts.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/0609/08/ng.01.html Transcript of Nancy Grace show] – [[CNN]]. September 8, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Duckett appeared confused and was unable to answer whether or not she had taken a [[polygraph test]]. When Grace asked her why she could not account for specific details, Duckett began to reply, &quot;Because I was told not to,&quot; to which Grace responded, &quot;Ms. Duckett, you are not telling us for a reason. What is the reason? You refuse to give even the simplest facts of where you were with your son before he went missing. It is day twelve.&quot; According to the CNN transcript, Duckett replied, &quot;(INAUDIBLE) with all media. It's not just there, just all media. Period.&quot; Grace then moved on to a media psychologist who asserted that Duckett was &quot;skirting around the issue.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Multi1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt;[http://transcripts.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/0609/08/ng.01.html Transcript of show] – [[CNN]]. September 8, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

The next day, before the airing of the show, Duckett shot herself, a death that relatives claim was influenced by media scrutiny, particularly from Grace.&lt;ref name=&quot;Multi1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2006/09/13/ap/national/mainD8K44UI00.shtml Mother of Missing Boy Commits Suicide]{{dead link|date=June 2012}} September 13, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Speaking to ''[[The Orlando Sentinel]]'', Duckett's grandfather Bill Eubank said, &quot;Nancy Grace and the others, they just bashed her to the end. She was not one anyone ever would have thought of to do something like this.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Multi1&quot;/&gt; CNN has also been criticized for allowing the show to air in the wake of Duckett's suicide.&lt;ref name=longshot/&gt; Police investigating the case had not named Melinda Duckett as a suspect in the case at the time, but after her suicide the police did say that, as nearly all parents are in missing-child cases, she was a suspect from the beginning.&lt;ref name=&quot;Multi1&quot; /&gt;

In an interview on ''[[Good Morning America]]'', Nancy Grace said in reaction to events that &quot;If anything, I would suggest that guilt made her commit suicide. To suggest that a 15- or 20-minute interview can cause someone to commit suicide is focusing on the wrong thing.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WpzqVlJJFIg&amp;|title=Nancy Grace CNN Defends Self On GMA Over Duckett Interview|work=[[Google|Google, Inc]]|publisher=YouTube|date=September 3, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; She then said that, while she sympathized with the family, she knew from her own experience as a victim of crime that such people look for somebody else to blame.&lt;ref&gt;[http://abcnews.go.com/GMA/story?id=2448050 Nancy Grace Says 'Guilt' Likely Made Mother Commit Suicide] September 15, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

While describing it as an &quot;extremely sad development,&quot; Janine Iamunno, a spokeswoman for Grace,&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,11069-2357726,00.html CNN guest kills herself after grueling questions] – [[The Times]]. September 14, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; said that her program would continue to follow the case as they had a &quot;responsibility to bring attention to this case in the hopes of helping find Trenton Duckett.&quot; Grace commented that &quot;I do not feel that our show is to blame for what happened to Melinda Duckett. The truth is not always nice or polite or easy to go down. Sometimes it's harsh, and it hurts.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Multi1&quot; /&gt;

On November 21, 2006, [[The Smoking Gun|thesmokinggun.com]] exposed pending litigation on behalf of the estate of Melinda Duckett, asserting a [[wrongful death]] claim against CNN and Grace. The attorney for the estate alleges that, even if Duckett did kill her own son, Grace's aggressive questioning traumatized Duckett so much that she committed suicide. She also argues that CNN's decision to air the interview after Duckett's suicide traumatized her family. Trenton has never been found.&lt;ref name=longshot&gt;Susan Filan, [[MSNBC]], [http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/15841161/ ''Lawsuit against Nancy Grace a long shot''], November 21, 2006. Retrieved May 28, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thesmokinggun.com/archive/1121061grace1.html Nancy Grace Sued For Wrongful Death] November 21, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

On November 8, 2010, Grace reached a settlement with the estate of Melinda Duckett to create a $200,000 trust fund dedicated to locating Trenton. This settlement was reached a month before a jury trial was scheduled to start. According to the agreement, if the young boy is found alive before he turns 13, the remaining proceeds in the trust will be administered by a trustee – Trenton's great-aunt Kathleen Calvert – until he turns 18 and the funds are transferred for his use.  If Trenton is not found by his 13th birthday, or if he is found but is not alive, the funds will be transferred immediately to the [[National Center for Missing and Exploited Children]]. &quot;We are pleased the lawsuit has been dismissed. The statement speaks for itself,&quot; a spokeswoman for [[CNN]] said.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Suevon Lee |url=http://www.ocala.com/article/20101108/articles/101109699?p=1&amp;tc=pg |title=Nancy Grace settles lawsuit with Duckett estate|publisher=Ocala.com|date=November 8, 2010 |accessdate=August 27, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Caylee Anthony case====
From 2008 to 2011 the [[Death of Caylee Anthony|Caylee Anthony]] disappearance and the prosecution, trial and acquittal of her mother Casey Anthony on charges of murder of the child were a regular feature of the Nancy Grace show. She would reveal every new detail of the story.&lt;ref&gt;Jeffrey C. Billman, [http://www2.orlandoweekly.com/news/story.asp?id=12610 Our Dumb State: The Casey Anthony Edition], [[Orlando Weekly]], September 11, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Her program is cited as having &quot;almost single-handedly inflated the Anthony case from a routine local murder into a national obsession&quot;.&lt;ref name=APMedia&gt;Glenn Garvin, [http://www.vancouversun.com/entertainment/Casey+Anthony+verdict+outrage+critics+blame+Nancy+Grace+Geraldo+Rivera+other+media+figures/5062174/story.html Casey Anthony verdict outrage: critics blame Nancy Grace, Geraldo Rivera and other media figures], [[Associated Press]], July 7, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Nancy Grace referred to Casey Anthony as the &quot;tot mom,&quot; a phrase Elizabeth Flock in the [[Washington Post]] described as “almost derisive-sounding.”&lt;ref name=&quot;Flock&quot;&gt;{{cite news|first=Elizabeth|last=Flock|title=Casey Anthony not guilty verdict shocks media; attorneys blast ‘talking heads'|publisher=''[[Washington Post]]''|date=July 6, 2011|accessdate=July 6, 2011|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/blogpost/post/casey-anthony-not-guilty-verdict-shocks-media-attorneys-blast-talking-heads/2011/07/05/gHQAHhIXzH_blog.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The Nancy Grace audience more than doubled in the weeks after the start of the Anthony trial.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/13/business/media/13hln.html?_r=2&amp;ref=media|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|title=Casey Anthony Coverage Gives HLN an Identity|first=Brian|last=Stelter|date=June 12, 2011|accessdate=July 7, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  David Carr wrote that Grace took her show to the trial scene in [[Clearwater, Florida]] in order to “hurl invective from a close, intimate distance.”&lt;ref name=Carr-NYTimes/&gt; Grace expressed rage at Anthony's acquittal right after announcement of the verdict, saying: &quot;Tot Mom's lies seem to have worked.&quot;&lt;ref name=APMedia/&gt;

In a press conference after the verdicts were read, [[Cheney Mason]], one of Casey Anthony's defense attorneys, blamed the media for a &quot;media assassination&quot; which led to public hatred toward Casey Anthony.  He also said: &quot;I can tell you that my colleagues from coast to coast and border to border have condemned this whole process of lawyers getting on television and talking about cases that they don't know a damn thing about, and don't have the experience to back up their words or the law to do it.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;yahoo.com&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Anthony lawyers blast cable news after acquittal|work=[[Yahoo.com]]|date=July 6, 2011|accessdate=July 6, 2011|url=http://news.yahoo.com/anthony-lawyers-blast-cable-news-acquittal-232233047.html|last=Bauder|first=David}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Grace took it personally and responded, &quot;What does he care about what pundits are saying?&quot; Stating she had as much legal experience as Mason, she criticized the defense attorneys for taking on the media before mentioning Caylee's name in their news conference and stated that &quot;[T]here is no way that this is a verdict that speaks the truth.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;yahoo.com&quot;/&gt;  

Michelle Zierler, director of the Project in Law and Journalism at [[New York Law School]] said Grace &quot;is always certain that the defendant is guilty and needs instant punishment&quot; and this had affected her analysis of the case.&lt;ref name=&quot;yahoo.com&quot;/&gt; [[Howard Finkelstein]], the [[Broward County]], Florida public defender said &quot;Nancy Grace should offend every journalist out there. These lawyers on TV during the Anthony trial only offered one side, everybody believed them, and now you've got a big chunk of the population that thinks the legal system let them down. Every time that happens, you lose part of the national community.&quot;&lt;ref name=APMedia/&gt;

On the day Casey Anthony was sentenced on misdemeanor counts of lying to investigators, a supporter held a sign reading: &quot;Nancy Grace, stop trying to ruin innocent lives. The jury has spoken. P.S. Our legal system still works!&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Marry me&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Casey Anthony Supporter: Will You Marry Me? Man Holds Sign Outside Orange County Courthouse|publisher=clickorlando.com|date=July 8, 2011|accessdate=July 9, 2011|url=http://www.clickorlando.com/news/28471012/detail.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a televised appearance with media expert [[Dan Abrams]], Grace stated about Anthony’s being freed from jail that “No one wishes for vigilante justice; nobody advocates that. People who are opposed to the jury verdict, that think it was wrong, are really seeking justice, and I do not believe those people are interested in harming Tot Mom Casey Anthony.” Abrams commented that “There are too many people out there who love Nancy Grace, who watch Nancy Grace on a regular basis, who are going to see her (C.Anthony) out there somewhere and are going to give her a very, very hard time wherever she goes.”&lt;ref&gt;Alex Alvarez,  [http://www.mediaite.com/tv/dan-abrams-on-casey-anthonys-future-nancy-grace-fans-are-going-to-give-her-a-hard-time-wherever-she-goes/ Dan Abrams: Nancy Grace Fans Are Going To Give Casey Anthony A Hard Time Wherever She Goes], [[Mediaite]], plus link to [[ABC News]] video of discussion, July 18, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Whitney Houston death====
Mainstream media have suggested that Grace made &quot;wildly speculative&quot; allegations on her program that the investigation into [[Whitney Houston|Whitney Houston's]] death should include the possibility that someone may have been responsible for drowning Houston. Some reporters have pointed out that Grace should have waited for the coroner's report before making this allegation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/02/16/nancy-grace-whitney-houston-comments_n_1282410.html|work=Huffington Post|first=Rebecca|last=Shapiro|title=Nancy Grace Defends Her Controversial Comments About Whitney Houston, 'View' Hosts Question Grace's Motivations|date=February 16, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Toni Annette Medrano Suicide====
Toni Annette Medrano committed suicide by setting herself on fire, after being condemned by Grace.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2171103/Vodka-mom-Toni-Medrano-burns-death-suffocating-newborn-son-slept.html|work=Daily Mail|title='Vodka mom' who suffocated three-week-old baby after rolling onto him as they slept burns herself to death after weeks of condemnation|date=July 9, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Following Melinda Duckett's suicide, this is the second suicide to which Grace has been linked.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Olson|first=Rochelle|title=Scorned Cottage Grove mom sets self ablaze|url=http://www.startribune.com/local/east/161793165.html|publisher=Minneapolis Star Tribune|accessdate=10 July 2012}} &lt;/ref&gt;

==Other work==
[[File:Nancy Grace Book Cover.jpg|upright|thumb|Nancy Grace's ''Objection! — How High-Priced Defense Attorneys, Celebrity Defendants, and a 24/7 Media Have Hijacked Our Criminal Justice System'']]
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:11thVictim.jpg|upright|thumb|Nancy Grace's ''The Eleventh Victim'']] --&gt;
Grace co-wrote the book ''Objection! — How High-Priced Defense Attorneys, Celebrity Defendants, and a 24/7 Media Have Hijacked Our Criminal Justice System'', which was published by [[Hyperion (publisher)|Hyperion]] on June 8, 2005. The book caused notable controversy{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}} because Grace referred to defense lawyers as &quot;pigs&quot; and compared them to Nazi concentration camp guards.{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}}{{specify|date=December 2010}}

According to an article first published by the ''[[New York Daily News]]'' in September 2006, Grace plagiarized 359 words spread sequentially across pages 204–5 of the book, lifted without indication from an August 5, 2002, article in ''[[The New York Times]]'' written by Sabra Chartrand. Hyperion accepted Grace's claim that the plagiarism was an &quot;inadvertent error&quot; but insisted that Grace send a letter to the ''Times'' promising that the content would be corrected in future printings. Hyperion explained that under contract, Grace must hold the publisher harmless in the event that the ''Times'' filed a lawsuit against her.{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}}

Nancy Grace's first work of fiction, ''The Eleventh Victim'', also published by Hyperion, was released on August 11, 2009. The mystery thriller follows a young psychology student, Hailey Dean, whose fiancé is murdered just weeks before their wedding. She goes on to prosecute violent crime and is forced to reckon with what she left behind.&lt;ref&gt;[http://hyperionbooks.com/titlepage.asp?ISBN=1401303455&amp;SUBJECT=THRILLER]{{dead link|date=June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Publishers Weekly]]'' described it as &quot;less than compelling.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.publishersweekly.com/article/ca6665994.html?q=nancy+Grace+the+eleventh+victim Publishers Weekly fiction reviews June 22, 2009]{{dead link|date=August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; A second novel, ''Death on the D-List'', was published on August 10, 2010.

Nancy Grace has also helped staff a hotline at an Atlanta battered women’s center for 10 years.&lt;ref name=&quot;CNN Profile&quot;/&gt;

Recently, she was featured as a spoof of herself on the [[Fox Broadcasting Company|Fox]] TV series, ''[[Raising Hope]]''.

==Personal life==

===Marriage and motherhood===
In April 2007, Grace married David Linch, an Atlanta investment banker, in a small private ceremony. The two had met while she was studying at Mercer University in the 1970s. Grace, who had given up on marriage after the death of her fiancé, said, &quot;We've been in touch all these years, and a lot of time, we were separated by geography and time. It was a spur-of-the-moment decision to get married. I told my family only two days before the wedding.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nypost.com/p/entertainment/tv/item_ylZK3xpNXrFWmr7Zret74H &quot;NANCY'S SECRET WEDDING&quot;], David Starr. New York Post. June 27, 2007. Retrieved January 15, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

On June 26, 2007, an emotional Grace announced on her HLN talk show that her life had &quot;taken a U-turn&quot; in that she was pregnant and expecting twins due in January 2008.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.people.com/people/article/0,,20043792,00.html Nancy Grace: Married and Expecting Twins] June 26, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://usmagazine.com/cnn_s_nancy_grace_pregnant_with_twins First Photo: CNN’s Nancy Grace Pregnant With Twins!]{{dead link|date=June 2012}} June 26, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; Lucy Elizabeth and John David were born on November 4, 2007.

===Allegations regarding fiancé's murder===
In March 2006, an article in the ''[[New York Observer]]'' suggested that in her book ''Objection!'', Grace had embellished the story of her college [[fiancé]]'s 1979 murder and the ensuing trial to make it better support her image. Grace has described the tragedy as the impetus for her career as a prosecutor and victims' rights advocate, and has often publicly referred to the incident.&lt;ref name=&quot;Muddy&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.observer.com/2006/03/did-nancy-grace-tv-crimebuster-muddy-her-myth/ |title=Did Nancy Grace, TV Crimebuster, Muddy Her Myth? |accessdate=July 6, 2011 |publisher=[[The New York Observer]] |date=March 5, 2006 |last=Dana |first=Rebecca }}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Observer'' researched the murder and found several apparent contradictions between the events and Grace's subsequent statements, including the following:
*Her fiancé, Keith Griffin, was shot not at random by a stranger, but by a former coworker, Tommy McCoy.
*McCoy did not have a prior criminal record and, rather than denying the crime, confessed on the night of the murder.
*The jury deliberated for a few hours, not days.
*There was no ongoing string of appeals (McCoy's family did not want any). McCoy has only once filed a [[habeas corpus|habeas]] petition, which was rejected.

Grace told the ''Observer'' she had not looked into the case in many years and &quot;tried not to think about it.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Muddy&quot; /&gt; She said she made her previous statements about the case &quot;with the knowledge I had.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Muddy&quot; /&gt;

In response to [[Keith Olbermann]]'s claims in a March 2007 ''[[Rolling Stone]]'' interview in which he was quoted as saying, &quot;Anybody who would embellish the story of their own fiancé's murder should spend that hour a day not on television but in a psychiatrist's chair,&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;delawareonline.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.delawareonline.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20070409/LIFE/704090308/1005/LIFE |title=Nancy Grace set to speak her mind in Del. |accessdate=July 1, 2007 |date=April 9, 2007 |work=|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20070930184747/http://www.delawareonline.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20070409/LIFE/704090308/1005/LIFE &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt;|archivedate=September 30, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Grace stated, &quot;I did not put myself through law school and fight for all those years for victims of crime to waste one minute of my time, my energy, and my education in a war of words with Keith Olbermann, whom I've never met nor had any disagreement. I feel we have X amount of time on Earth, and that when we give in to our detractors or spend needless time on silly fights, I think that's abusing the chance we have to do something good.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;delawareonline.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.myqaeda.com/?p=1271 |title=Nancy Grace’s Time on Earth too Precious to Respond to Keith Olbermann’s Attack On Her Exaggerating Her Late Husband’s Time on Earth|accessdate=July 1, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Keith Griffin's murderer, Tommy McCoy, was released on parole from the [[Georgia Department of Corrections]] on December 5, 2006.&lt;!-- He was convicted of [[Assault#Aggravated_assault|aggravated assault]], for which he received ten years, and for murder, for which he received [[life sentence|life]]. --&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Find an offender|url=http://www.dcor.state.ga.us/GDC/OffenderQuery/jsp/OffQryRedirector.jsp|work=Georgia department of corrections|publisher=georgia.gov|accessdate=July 5, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Grace in popular culture==


===''Dancing With the Stars''===
Grace was a contestant on the [[Dancing with the Stars (U.S. season 13)|thirteenth season]] of the popular [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] [[Reality Television]] Show ''[[Dancing with the Stars (U.S. TV series)|Dancing with the Stars]],'' which began airing September 19th, 2011. She was partnered with pro-dancer [[Tristan MacManus]]. The couple lasted for 8 weeks and placed 5th overall in the competition before being eliminated on November 8th, 2011, just one week shy of the semi-finals.

===''Raising Hope''===
In early April 2012, Grace appeared on the 2 last episodes of the second season of the TV show ''[[Raising Hope]]'' playing herself. It was the first time Nancy Grace was seen playing a comic character on television.

===''Law and Order'' connection===
The ''[[Law &amp; Order]]'' programs often base their fictional stories on real-life events and have featured stories based on Grace on several occasions.&lt;ref&gt;5th paragraph {{cite news|last=Farhi|first=Paul|title=Ripped From the Headlines – and From the Heart|publisher=The Washington Post|date=March 8, 2009|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/03/05/AR2009030504029.html|accessdate=September 12, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the episode ''&quot;Haystack&quot;'' of ''[[Law &amp; Order: Special Victims Unit]]'', an overzealous reporter named Cindy Marino (played by [[Kali Rocha]]) causes the mother of a kidnapped son to commit suicide, echoing the Melinda Duckett incident.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://imdb.com/title/tt0946364/|title=Haystack|year=Haystack}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Grace has also been parodied repeatedly on ''[[Law &amp; Order: Criminal Intent]]'' by a character named [[Faith Yancy]] ([[Geneva Carr]]) who hosts a similar talk show (''Inside American Justice'') that sensationalizes whatever case the main characters are working on and makes it difficult for them to gain access to key witnesses. The character has appeared on the episodes &quot;[[In the Wee Small Hours (Law &amp; Order: Criminal Intent)|In the Wee Small Hours]]&quot; (original air date November 6, 2005), &quot;[[Masquerade (Law &amp; Order: Criminal Intent)|Masquerade]]&quot; (original air date October 31, 2006), &quot;[[Albatross (Law &amp; Order: Criminal Intent)|Albatross]]&quot; (original air date February 6, 2007), &quot;[[Neighborhood Watch (Law &amp; Order: Criminal Intent)|Neighborhood Watch]]&quot; (original air date August 10, 2008), and 
&quot;[[Lady's Man (Law &amp; Order: Criminal Intent)|Lady's Man]]&quot; (original air date June 28, 2009).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/name/nm1417931/filmoseries#tt0275140 imdb.com profile - Geneva Carr]&lt;/ref&gt;

On May 22, 2007, Grace appeared in the ''Law &amp; Order: Special Victims Unit'' episode &quot;Screwed&quot; the season 8 finale, playing herself opposite [[Star Jones]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iht.com/articles/ap/2007/03/07/arts/NA-A-E-TV-US-Nancy-Grace-Acting.php Nancy Grace takes first acting role] March 6, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Hancock''===
Grace has a cameo appearance in the film, ''[[Hancock]]'', starring [[Will Smith]], criticising the title character.

===''Gone Girl''===
In [[Gillian Flynn]]'s 2012 book ''Gone Girl'', the character of Ellen Abbott, a 'former prosecutor and victims’ rights advocate', is speculated to be closely based on Nancy Grace&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kansascity.com/2012/06/08/3648791/gone-girls-gillian-flynn-peers.html] June 8, 2012&lt;/ref&gt;, in an unflattering portrayal.

===Boston Legal===
Grace is parodied on ''[[Boston Legal]]'', as Gracie Jane. She has relations with Denny Crane.

==Bibliography==
* {{cite book|title=Objection! — How High-Priced Defense Attorneys, Celebrity Defendants, and a 24/7 Media Have Hijacked Our Criminal Justice System|year=2005|publisher=Hyperion|isbn=978-1-4013-0180-4|page=336}}
* {{cite book|title=The Eleventh Victim|year=2009|publisher=Hyperion|isbn=978-1-4013-0345-7|page=368}}
* {{cite book|title=Death on the D-List|year=2010|publisher=Hyperion|isbn=978-1-4013-2313-4|page=281}}

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
*[http://cnn.com/CNN/Programs/nancy.grace CNN's Nancy Grace Show]
*[http://cnn.com/CNN/anchors_reporters/grace.nancy.html CNN's Bio of Nancy Grace]
*[http://transcripts.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/0502/20/lkl.01.html CNN Transcript: Interview with Larry King]
*[http://transcripts.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/ng.html CNN Transcript: &quot;Nancy Grace&quot; Show]

{{s-start}}
{{s-ach}}
{{succession box | title=[[Dancing with the Stars (US TV series)|''Dancing with the Stars'' (US)]] quarter-finalist | before=[[Romeo Miller|Romeo]] &amp; [[Chelsie Hightower]]| years=Season 13 (Fall 2011 with [[Tristan MacManus]])|after=[[Melissa Gilbert]] &amp; [[Maksim Chmerkovskiy]]}} 
{{s-end}}

{{Dancing with the Stars Season 13}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME=Grace, Nancy
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES=
| SHORT DESCRIPTION=
| DATE OF BIRTH=October 23, 1958
| PLACE OF BIRTH=[[Macon, Georgia|Macon]], Georgia, United States
| DATE OF DEATH=
| PLACE OF DEATH=
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Grace, Nancy}}
[[Category:1958 births]]
[[Category:American prosecutors]]
[[Category:American television personalities]]
[[Category:CNN people]]
[[Category:Georgia (U.S. state) lawyers]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Mercer University alumni]]
[[Category:Participants in American reality television series]]
[[Category:People from Atlanta, Georgia]]
[[Category:People from Macon, Georgia]]
[[Category:American women journalists]]
[[Category:New York University alumni]]
[[Category:Georgia State University faculty]]

[[de:Nancy Grace]]
[[fr:Nancy Grace]]
[[oc:Nancy Grace]]
[[ru:Грэйс, Нэнси]]
[[simple:Nancy Grace]]
[[tl:Nancy Grace]]</text>
      <sha1>my8xlrv0voxjh278bru75wk0jltnpi9</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
