<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Phil Hendrie</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>416366</id>
    <restrictions>move=:edit=</restrictions>
    <revision>
      <id>521105478</id>
      <parentid>521105176</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T20:31:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Amir Tamara</username>
        <id>17079429</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* The Phil Hendrie Show */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11784">{{Refimprove|date=March 2012}}
'''Philip Stephen Hendrie''' (born September 1, 1952) is an [[United States|American]] radio personality, actor and voice over artist.

==''The Phil Hendrie Show''==
He is best known as a radio satirist and the host of ''[[The Phil Hendrie Show]]'', nationally syndicated radio show, heard on about 100 stations, that is driven by his cast of fictional characters, all of whom he created and plays on air.  As host, Hendrie sets up a topic and discusses it with one of his characters who seamlessly takes the discussion beyond obvious social parameters.  Feeding the circle of social satire are the callers who are real and genuinely passionate about what Hendrie’s “guest” is saying.  Loyal fans enjoy being in on the ruse as Hendrie orchestrates a parody of his own profession – talk radio.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.trncorporate.com/ |title=TalkRadioNetwork.com: Welcome To TRN |deadurl=no |accessdate=10 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Hendrie was born in Pasadena, California and grew up in Arcadia, California.  He was a disc jockey for 15 years before transitioning into talk radio.  His first job as a disc jockey was at WBJW 1440 AM in Winter Park, Fla., a suburb of Orlando from 1973–1975.  From 1976 to 1988, Hendrie was a DJ at various music stations in cities such as New Orleans, La., Utica, NY, Miami, Fl., and San Diego, CA.

In 1989, he moved to Los Angeles to make his debut in Talk radio as a weekend host at KFI-AM 640.

In 1990 he made the move to KVEN in Ventura, Calif., where he introduced his first fictional character on air – an Iraqi, Raj Feenan. The Gulf War was happening and Feenan vociferously defended Saddam Hussein.  Thinking he was a real person, listeners went ballistic and the phones lit up. An entire cast of characters would evolve from that moment on, marking Hendrie’s place in radio history.

In October 1996 Hendrie went back to KFI AM 640 to host his new and innovative “The Phil Hendrie Show” daily. 

Hendrie’s popularity resulted in the radio show going national in 1999 via Premiere Radio Networks, a subsidiary of Clear Channel Communications.  In February 2005, Hendrie’s flag ship station, KFI AM 640, moved him to sister station XTRA Sports 570 AM, a sports talk radio station also based in Los Angeles. The show remained nationally syndicated on 100 radio stations until 2006.

On April 27, 2006, Hendrie announced he was leaving radio to pursue his acting career on a full-time basis. At the time, he was working as an actor on NBC’s sitcom “Teachers.” His acting resume already included film and television roles in Trey Parker’s and Matt Stone’s motion picture, Team America:  World Police, Andy Richter Controls the Universe, Richard Appel’s A.U.S.A., and Judd Apatow’s North Hollywood.   He also starred in Steve Levitan’s Phil Hendrie and wrote, executive produced and starred in Phil at the Gate, as well as performing a myriad of character voices on several episodes of the animated television shows “King of the Hill” and “Futurama.”&lt;ref name=&quot;IMDB&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.imdb.com/ |title=The Internet Movie Database (IMDb) |deadurl=no |accessdate=10 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The last live broadcast of “The Phil Hendrie Show” was June 23, 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.premierenetworks.com/ |title=PremiereNetworks.com |deadurl=no |accessdate=10 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Hendrie continues to act and has since had roles on several television shows such as Giants of Radio, The Replacements, Three Strikes, Mike Birbiglia’s Secret Public Journal, David Mamet’s The Unit, Fox’s Napoleon Dynamite, ABC’s Modern Family and Fox’s New Girl. His recent motion picture work includes roles in Semi-pro and Last Call.&lt;ref name=&quot;IMDB&quot;/&gt;

On June 4, 2007, it was announced that Phil Hendrie would return to radio June 25, 2007 from 10 PM to 1 AM PST via national syndicator, Talk Radio Network (TRN) with shows airing nationally Monday through Friday on 100 radio stations.  It was a straight talk show he did until September 14, 2009, when he welcomed back his cast of characters, bringing back his original brand of radio theater that’s unmatched in the industry.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=Orange County Register}}&lt;/ref&gt; “Radio needs alternative programming, like my show, now more than ever,” said Hendrie. “Having the advantage of communicating compelling and outrageous points of view through these characters is an opportunity no other host has.”

On Saturday, November 20, 2010, KFI AM 640 in Los Angeles announced that Phil Hendrie and his cast of voices were joining the station’s weekend line up. &lt;ref name=&quot;New online station reflects the culture of Venice&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Lycan|first=Gary|url=http://www.ocregister.com/articles/radio-277233-station-sunday.html|newspaper=Orange County Register|date=11-22-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; Heard Saturdays from 7-1pm, Hendrie did a local show for the station, while doing his national show Monday through Friday.  His national show airs on KFI’s sister station, KTLK AM.&lt;ref name=&quot;Weekday Program Schedule&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Talk|first=News|url=www.ktlkam1150.com/pages/On_Air_Hosts.html?feed=119597&amp;article=9672048|newspaper=KTLK AM 1150|date=11-2-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
On February 23, 2012, Hendrie announced to his fans via Twitter and www.PhilHendrieShow.com that February 25, 2012 would be his last KFI/640 Los Angeles show.  &lt;ref name=&quot;Phil Hendrie Ends KFI Show&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Saxe|first=Frank|url=http://www.insideradio.com/article.asp?id=2401636&amp;spid=32061|newspaper=Inside Radio|date=2-23-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; He continues his national show on more than 100 stations, including KTLK AM 1150 Los Angeles, via Talk Radio Network.&lt;ref name=&quot;Weekday Program Schedule&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ktlkam1150.com/pages/On_Air_Hosts.html?feed=119597&amp;article=9672048|publisher=KTLK AM 1150|accessdate=2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Hendrie said, “This was not an easy decision because I’m going to miss everyone at KFI big time.  However, doing a show like mine six days a week is murder.  With the acting work cranking up and my obligation to TRN, something had to give.”&lt;ref name=&quot;Phil Hendrie to End His Saturday Night KFI Show&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Fleischer|first=Matthew|url=http://www.mediabistro.com/fishbowlla/phil-hendrie-to-end-his-saturday-night-kfi-show_b54324|newspaper=Fishbowl LA|date=2-24-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Hendrie also runs a successful website business, featuring exclusive webisodes, character archives, members-only pre-shows, online store, and much more at www.philhendrieshow.com. ===Views and Blogs===

Hendrie’s political views are unconventional in the realm of talk radio.  He’s a registered Democrat who supported George W. Bush and the War on Terror, but voted for Barack Obama in 2008. He’s pro-choice, pro-gay marriage, and pro-amnesty for illegal immigrants.

Currently, Hendrie actively maintains blogs for two of his most popular characters – Bobbie Dooley and Ted Bell.

==Acting career==

For the last 13 years, Hendrie has worked as an actor and voice over artist.

In the summer of 2011, Hendrie filmed a part for [[Judd Apatow]]’s motion picture, This is 40, due in theaters December 2012.  In 2012, he played the recurring character Joe Napoli on three episodes of New Girl, 20th Century Fox’s hit sit-com starring Zooey Deschanel. &lt;ref name=&quot;&quot;TRN's Phil Hendrie a Busy Man&quot;&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Ryan|first=Ed|url=http://www.radioink.com/article.asp?id=2530218&amp;spid=24698|newspaper=Radio Ink Magazine|date=10 September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other television work in 2012 included recurring parts on six episodes of [[Napoleon Dynamite]], and a role in an episode of ABC-TV’s Emmy Award winning series [[Modern Family]]. &lt;ref name='&quot;Phil Hendrie Shoots Role for Modern Family&quot;'&gt;{{cite news|last=Simon|first=Perry|url=http://www.allaccess.com/net-news/archive/story/99949/phil-hendrie-shoots-role-on-modern-family|newspaper=All Access|date=12-7-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Also out in 2012 was the film Last Call, in which Hendrie was cast as the liquor company representative, Mulvahill. 

In 2008, Hendrie played the [[New Jersey Nets]] Coach in the comedy film Semi-Pro, starring Will Ferrell.  Also that year, Hendrie had parts in the TV movies Mike Birbiglia’s Secret Public Journal and Giants of Radio.

From 2006 to 2007, Hendrie had a recurring role in David Mamet’s The Unit and appeared in five episodes.  Other TV series included NBC’s sitcom Teachers, where he was part of an ensemble cast, playing the part of school teacher Dick Green for the full season &lt;ref name='&quot;Teachers - Kali Rocha, Phil Hendrie, Justin Bartha and Deon Richmond:'&gt;{{cite news|last=Haston|first=Chris|url=http://www.tvguide.com/celebrities/phil-hendrie/photos/263525|newspaper=TV Guide|date=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; ; and The Replacements, where he appeared in two episodes as the Mayor.  He was also in the 2006 TV movie, Three Strikes.

In 2004, Hendrie voiced the computer I.N.T.E.L.L.I.G.E.N.C.E. and the Chechen terrorist in Trey Parker’s and Matt Stone’s motion picture Team America: World Police and starred in Steve Levitan’s animated TV pilot Phil Hendrie.  &lt;ref name=&quot;Radio legend and icon, the famous Phil Hendrie, talks about Team America: World Police, Futurama, and much more for an exclusive interview.&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Harris|first=Jeffrey|url=http://www.411mania.com/wrestling/columns/230803|newspaper=411mania.com|date=3-25-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

He played Judge McCarthy on Richard Appel’s A.U.S.A. in 2003. &lt;ref name=&quot;Radio legend and icon, the famous Phil Hendrie, talks about Team America: World Police, Futurama, and much more for an exclusive interview.&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Harris|first=Jeffrey|url=http://www.411mania.com/wrestling/columns/230803|newspaper=411mania.com|date=3-25-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also starred in a TV pilot he wrote and executive produced called Phil at the Gate the same year.

From 1999 to 2009, Hendrie voiced characters on 24 episodes of the hit animated TV series King of the Hill.  He also voiced characters for three episodes of Futurama from 2000-2002 and played three characters on the 2009 feature length video, Futurama: Into the Wild Green Yonder.

From 2001-2002, Hendrie appeared on the TV series Andy Richter Controls the Universe and Judd Apatow’s TV movie North Hollywood.

==Personal life==
In July 1997, Hendrie married radio talk show host Maria Sanchez. The wedding was held at the Queen Mary and was broadcast live on KFI. He and Sanchez divorced in 2007.  Living the life of a bachelor ever since, Hendrie is a reader of world history, astronomy, archeology and anthropology and spends time with close friends watching horse racing and playing poker.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* {{IMDb name|id=1042825|name=Phil Hendrie}}
* [http://www.philhendrieshow.com/ Official website]
* {{myspace|philhendrie|Phil Hendrie}}
* [http://web.archive.org/web/19990209124845/kfi640.com/usguys/phil.html Phil Hendrie's page on AM-KFI Los Angeles – Archived December 1998]
* [http://www.radiotapes.com/ Radiotapes.com: featuring an aircheck of Phil Hendrie’s final show on WCCO/Minneapolis–St. Paul]

{{Persondata
| NAME              = Hendrie, Phil
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = September 1, 1952
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Hendrie, Phil}}
[[Category:American comedians]]
[[Category:American talk radio hosts]]
[[Category:American voice actors]]
[[Category:Radio personalities from Los Angeles, California]]
[[Category:Radio personalities from Miami, Florida]]
[[Category:Radio personalities from Minneapolis, Minnesota]]
[[Category:People from the San Gabriel Valley]]
[[Category:1952 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:American television actors]]</text>
      <sha1>oysvlw05lgg4zor5wsueagz2nn13dxg</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
