<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Pol Pot</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>24326</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520574137</id>
      <parentid>520573525</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-30T11:11:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>TheTimesAreAChanging</username>
        <id>13216755</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Restoring sourced material removed without discussion</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="60019">{{Refimprove|date=June 2012}}
{{original research|date=June 2012}}
{{Infobox prime minister
|name = Pol Pot
|image = PolPot.jpg
|imagesize =
|caption = Pol Pot in 1978
|order = [[General Secretary of the Communist Party of Kampuchea]]
|deputy = [[Nuon Chea]] (as vice-secretary)
|term_start =February 1963
|term_end =1981 (party dissolved)
|predecessor =[[Tou Samouth]]
|successor =''None (party dissolved)''
|order2 =[[Prime Minister of Cambodia|Prime Minister of Democratic Kampuchea]]
|president2 = [[Khieu Samphan]]
|religion = Atheism&lt;ref&gt;Kristof, Nicholas, [http://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/03/opinion/03kristof.html A Modest Proposal for a Truce on Religion], ''The New York Times,'' December 3, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
|term_start2 =14 April 1976
|term_end2 =27 September 1976
|predecessor2 =[[Khieu Samphan]]
|successor2 =[[Nuon Chea]]
|president3 = [[Khieu Samphan]]
|term_start3 =25 October 1976
|term_end3 =January 7, 1979
|predecessor3 =[[Nuon Chea]]
|successor3 =[[Pen Sovan]]
|birth_date ={{Birth date|1925|5|19|df=y}}&lt;ref name = BBC&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/historic_figures/pot_pol.shtml |title=BBC – History – Historic Figures: Pol Pot (1925–1998) |publisher=BBC   |accessdate=January 25, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=TIME&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.time.com/time/asia/asia/magazine/1999/990823/pol_pot1.html|work=Time Magazine|title=Pol Pot|last=Chandler |first=David |date=23 August 1999 |accessdate=February 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|birth_place =[[Kampong Thom Province]], [[French Indochina]]
|death_date ={{Death date and age|1998|4|15|1925|5|19|df=y}}
|death_place =[[Anlong Veng District|Anlong Veng]], [[Cambodia|Kingdom of Cambodia]]
|spouse =1) [[Khieu Ponnary]] (div.)&lt;br&gt;2) Mea Son
|constituency =
|party =[[Communist Party of Kampuchea]]
|signature =
}}
{{Contains Khmer text}}
'''Pol Pot''' (19 May 1925 – 15 April 1998),&lt;ref name=BBC/&gt;&lt;ref name=TIME/&gt; born '''Saloth Sar Pol Pot''' ({{lang-km|ប៉ុល ពត}}), was a [[Cambodia]]n [[Maoist]] [[revolutionary]] who led the [[Khmer Rouge]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Red Khmer,&quot; from the French ''rouge'' &quot;red&quot; (longtime symbol of Communism) and ''Khmer,'' the term for [[Khmer people|ethnic Cambodian]]s&lt;/ref&gt; from 1963 until his death in 1998. From 1963 to 1981, he served as the [[General Secretary of the Communist Party of Kampuchea|General Secretary]] of the [[Communist Party of Kampuchea]]. From 1976 to 1979, he also served as the [[Prime Minister of Cambodia|prime minister]] of [[Democratic Kampuchea]]. Pol Pot became leader of [[Cambodia]] on April 17, 1975, and his rule has been described as being a [[dictatorship]].&lt;ref name=&quot;university1975&quot;&gt;Kiernan, Ben. The Pol Pot Regime: Race, Power, and Genocide in Cambodia under the Khmer Rouge, 1975–79. New Haven, CT: Yale University Press, 1996.&lt;/ref&gt; During his time in power he imposed [[agrarian socialism]], forcing urban dwellers to relocate to the countryside to work in collective farms and forced labor projects. The combined effects of forced labor, malnutrition, poor medical care, and executions resulted in the deaths of approximately 21 percent of the Cambodian population.&lt;ref name = yale&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.yale.edu/cgp/ |title=The Cambodian Genocide Program |accessdate=May 12, 2008 |date= 1994-2008 |work=Genocide Studies Program |publisher=[[Yale University]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; In all, an estimated 1 to 3 million people (out of a population of slightly over 8 million) died as a result of the policies of his three-year premiership.&lt;ref name=&quot;Heuveline, Patrick 2001&quot;&gt;Heuveline, Patrick (2001). &quot;The Demographic Analysis of Mortality in Cambodia.&quot; In Forced Migration and Mortality, eds. Holly E. Reed and Charles B. Keely. Washington, D.C.: National Academy Press.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Marek Sliwinski 1995&quot;&gt;Marek Sliwinski, Le Génocide Khmer Rouge: Une Analyse Démographique (L'Harmattan, 1995).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Banister, Judith 1993&quot;&gt;Banister, Judith, and Paige Johnson (1993). &quot;After the Nightmare: The Population of Cambodia.&quot; In Genocide and Democracy in Cambodia: The Khmer Rouge, the United Nations and the International Community, ed. Ben Kiernan. New Haven, Conn.: Yale University Southeast Asia Studies.&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 1979, after the [[Cambodian–Vietnamese War]], Pol Pot fled to the jungles of southwest Cambodia, and the Khmer Rouge government collapsed.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.time.com/time/asia/asia/magazine/1999/990823/pol_pot1.html |title=Time necropsy |newspaper=Time Magazine |date= August 23, 1999|accessdate=February 27, 2009 |first=David |last=Chandler}}&lt;/ref&gt; From 1979 to 1997, he and a remnant of the old Khmer Rouge operated near the border of Cambodia and [[Thailand]], where they clung to power, with nominal United Nations recognition as the rightful government of Cambodia. Pol Pot died in 1998 while under house arrest by the [[Ta Mok]] faction of the Khmer Rouge. Since his death, rumours that he was poisoned have persisted.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| newspaper=Time Magazine | title=Putting a Permanent Lid on Pol Pot|last=Horn | first=Robert | date=March 25, 2002 | url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,219924,00.html | accessdate=September 3, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Biography==
===Early life (1925–61)===
[[Image:Prek Sbauv.JPG|thumb|right|[[Prek Sbauv]], birthplace of Pol Pot.]]
Saloth Sar was born on May 19, 1925—the eighth of nine children and the second of three sons to Pen Saloth and Sok Nem. His older brother, [[Saloth Chhay]] was born 3 years earlier. The family was living in the small fishing village of [[Prek Sbauv]], [[Kampong Thom Province]] during the [[French Indochina|French colonialism]] of the area.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nytimes.com/1997/08/06/world/pol-pot-s-siblings-remember-the-polite-boy-and-the-killer.html?pagewanted=2&amp;src=pm
|title=Pol Pot's Siblings Remember The Polite Boy and the Killer – Page 2|newspaper=New York Times|date= August 6, 1997|last=Seth|first=Mydans|accessdate=April 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pen Saloth was a rice farmer who owned 12 hectares of land and several buffaloes and the family was considered to be moderately wealthy by the day's standards. Although Pen Saloth's family was of [[Chinese Cambodian|Sino]]-[[Khmer people|Khmer]] descent and Saloth Sar was named accordingly due to his fair complexion (&quot;Sar&quot; means white in Khmer),&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Short|2005|p=18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://web.archive.org/web/*/http://www.phnompenhpost.com/TXT/letters/l1402-2.htm |title=Debating Genocide |publisher=Web.archive.org |accessdate=February 27, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; the family had already assimilated themselves with mainstream Khmer society by the time Sar was born.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/27/books/chapters/0227-1st-short.html?pagewanted=print&amp;position= First Chapter &amp;ndash;Pol Pot], February 27, 2005, Philip Short, [[The New York Times]]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1935, Sar left Prek Sbauv to attend the École Miche, a Catholic school in [[Phnom Penh]]. He lived with his cousin, a woman called Meak, a member of the [[Royal Ballet of Cambodia|Royal Ballet]].&lt;ref&gt;Chandler, David P., 1992, ''Brother Number One: A political biography of Pol Pot'', Silkworm Books, Thailand: 8&lt;/ref&gt; In 1926 she bore King [[Sisowath Monivong|Monivong's]] son, HRH Prince Sisowath Kusarak.&lt;ref&gt;Jeldres, Julio A., 2003, ''The Royal House of Cambodia'', Monument Books, Phnom Penh&lt;/ref&gt; She was given the official title ''Khun Preah Moneang Bopha Norleak Meak''. Sar stayed with Meak's household until 1942. His sister Roeung was a [[Concubinage|concubine]] of King Monivong, so through the two women, he often had cause to visit the [[Royal Palace, Phnom Penh|royal palace]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newint.org/issue242/original.htm Ben Kiernan – New Internationalist, 242 – April 1993]&lt;/ref&gt; In 1947, he gained admission to the exclusive [[Lycée Sisowath]], but was unsuccessful in his studies.

====Paris====
{{Unreferenced section|date=June 2012}}
After switching to a technical school at [[Russey Keo]], north of Phnom Penh, Saloth Sar qualified for a scholarship for technical studies in France. He studied radio electronics at the [[EFREI|EFR]] in Paris from 1949 to 1953. He also participated in an international labour brigade building roads in [[Zagreb]] in the [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|Federal Republic of Yugoslavia]] in 1950. After the [[Soviet Union]] recognized the [[Viet Minh]] as the government of Vietnam in 1950, [[French Communist Party|French Communists]] (PCF) took up the cause of Vietnam's independence. The PCF's [[Anti-imperialism|anti-colonialism]] views attracted many young Cambodians, including Sar.

In 1951, he joined a communist cell in a secret organization known as the ''Cercle Marxiste'' (''&quot;[[Marxist]] circle&quot;'') which had taken control of the Khmer Student's Association (AER) that same year. Within a few months, Saloth joined the PCF. His poor academic record was a considerable advantage within the anti-intellectual PCF who saw uneducated peasants as the true [[proletariat]].{{citation needed|date=February 2012}}&lt;!--From historian Philip Short--&gt;

====Return====
{{Refimprove section|date=June 2012}}
As a result of failing his exams in three successive years, Sar was forced to return to Cambodia in January 1953. He was the first member of the ''Cercle Marxiste'' to return to Cambodia. He was given the task of evaluating the various groups rebelling against the government. He recommended the Khmer Viet Minh,{{clarify|date=February 2012}} and in August 1954, Sar, along with Rath Samoeun, travelled to the Viet Minh Eastern Zone headquarters in the village of Krabao in the [[Kampong Cham Province]]/[[Prey Veng Province]] near the border of Cambodia.

Sar learned that the [[Communist Party of Kampuchea|Khmer People's Revolutionary Party]] (KPRP) was little more than a Vietnamese front organization. Due to the 1954 Geneva peace accord, requiring all Viet Minh forces and insurgents be expelled, a group of Cambodians followed the Vietnamese back to Vietnam (as cadres Vietnam would use in a future war to liberate Cambodia). The rest, including Sar, returned to Cambodia.

After [[History of Cambodia|Cambodian independence]] following the 1954 [[Geneva Conference (1954)|Geneva Conference]], [[left-right politics|both left and right wing]] parties struggled for power in the new government. Khmer King [[Norodom Sihanouk]] pitted the parties against each other while using the police and army to suppress extreme political groups. Corrupt elections in 1955 led many leftists in Cambodia to abandon hope of taking power by legal means. The communist movement, while ideologically committed to [[guerrilla warfare]] in such circumstances, did not launch a rebellion due to the party's weakness.

After his return to Phnom Penh, Sar became the liaison between the above-ground leftist parties (Democrats and Pracheachon) and the underground communist movement. He married [[Khieu Ponnary]] on July 14, 1956. She returned to Lycée Sisowath, becoming a teacher, while Sar taught French literature and history at Chamraon Vichea, a newly established private college.&lt;ref name=camnet&gt;{{Cite news
|url=http://www.camnet.com.kh/cambodia.daily/selected_features/khiev.htm
|title=Sister No. 1 The Story of Khieu Ponnary, Revolutionary and First Wife of Pol Pot |author=Thet Sambath |date=October 20, 2001 |publisher=The Cambodia Daily, WEEKEND |accessdate=November 15, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===The path to rebellion (1962–68)===
{{Unreferenced section|date=June 2012}}
In January 1962, the Cambodian government arrested most of the leadership of the far-left [[Pracheachon]] party before parliamentary elections, which were to take place that June. Their newspapers and other publications were closed. Such measures effectively ended any legitimate political role of the communist movement in Cambodia. In July 1962, the underground communist party secretary Tou Samouth was arrested and later killed while in custody, allowing Sar to become the acting leader. At a 1963 party meeting, attended by at most 18 people, Sar was elected secretary of the party's central committee. That March, Saloth went into hiding after his name was published in a list of leftist suspects put together by the police for [[Norodom Sihanouk]]. He fled to the Vietnamese border region and made contact with Vietnamese units fighting against [[South Vietnam]].

In early 1964, Sar convinced the Vietnamese to help the Cambodian communists set up their own base camp. The party's central committee met later that year and issued a declaration calling for armed struggle, emphasizing &quot;self-reliance&quot; in accordance with extreme Cambodians. In the border camps, the ideology of the Khmer Rouge was gradually developed. The party, breaking with [[Marxism]], declared that rural peasant farmers were the true working class proletarian and lifeblood of the revolution, the central committee members having grown up in a [[feudalism|feudal]] peasant society.

After another wave of repression by Sihanouk in 1965, the Khmer Rouge movement under Saloth grew at a rapid rate. Many teachers and students left the cities for the countryside to join the movement.

In April 1965, Sar went to North Vietnam to gain approval for an uprising in Cambodia against the government. [[North Vietnam]] refused to support any uprising due to ongoing negotiation with the Cambodian government. Sihanouk promised to allow the Vietnamese to use Cambodian territory and Cambodian ports in their war against South Vietnam.

After returning to Cambodia in 1966, Sar organized a party meeting where a number of important decisions were made. The party was officially, but secretly, renamed the [[Communist Party of Kampuchea]] (CPK). Lower ranks of the party were not informed of the decision. It was also decided to establish command zones and prepare each region for an uprising against the government.

In early 1966, fighting broke out in the countryside between peasants and the government over the price paid for rice. Sar's Khmer Rouge was caught by surprise by the uprisings and was unable to take any real advantage of them. But the government's refusal to find a peaceful solution to the problem created rural unrest that played into the hands of the Communist movement.

It was not until early 1967 that Sar decided to launch a national uprising, even though North Vietnam refused to assist in any meaningful way. The uprising was launched on January 18, 1968 with a raid on an army base south of [[Battambang]]. The Battambang area had already seen two years of great peasant unrest. The attack was driven off by the army, but the Khmer Rouge had captured a number of weapons, which were then used to drive police forces out of Cambodian villages.

By the summer of 1968, Sar began transitioning from a party leader working with a collective leadership, into the absolutist leader of the Khmer Rouge movement. Where before he had shared communal quarters with other leaders, he now had his own compound with a personal staff and guards. Outsiders were no longer allowed to approach him. Rather, people were summoned into his presence by his staff.

===The path to power (1969–75)===
{{Refimprove section|date=June 2012}}
The movement was estimated to consist of no more than 200 regular members, but the core of the movement was supported by a number of villagers many times that size. While weapons were in short supply, the insurgency was still able to operate in twelve of nineteen districts of Cambodia. In 1969 Sar called a party conference and decided on a change in the propaganda strategy. Prior to 1969, opposition to [[Norodom Sihanouk|Sihanouk]] was the main focus of their propaganda. The party decided to shift the propaganda to oppose the right-wing parties of Cambodia and their alleged pro-American attitudes. While the party ceased making anti-Sihanouk public statements, in private the party had not changed its view of him.

The road to power for Sar and the Khmer Rouge was opened by the events of January 1970 in Cambodia. Sihanouk, while out of the country, ordered the government to stage anti-Vietnamese protests in the capital. The protesters quickly spilled out of control and wrecked the embassies of both North and South Vietnam. Sihanouk, who had ordered the protests, then denounced them from Paris and blamed unnamed individuals in Cambodia for them. These actions, along with clandestine operations by Sihanouk's followers in Cambodia, convinced the government that he should be removed as [[head of state]]. The National Assembly voted to remove Sihanouk from office and closed Cambodia's ports to Vietnamese weapons traffic, demanding that the Vietnamese leave Cambodia.

The North Vietnamese reacted to the political changes in Cambodia by sending Premier [[Phạm Văn Đồng]] to meet Sihanouk in China and recruit him into an alliance with the Khmer Rouge. Sar was also contacted by the Vietnamese who reversed their position, offering him whatever resources he wanted for his [[insurgency]] against the Cambodian government. Sar and Sihanouk were actually in Beijing at the same time, but the Vietnamese and Chinese leaders never informed Sihanouk of the presence of Saloth or allowed the two men to meet. Shortly after, Sihanouk issued an appeal by radio to the people of Cambodia to rise up against the government and support the Khmer Rouge. In May 1970, Saloth finally returned to Cambodia and the insurgency gained traction.

Earlier, on March 29, 1970, the Vietnamese had taken matters into their own hands and launched an offensive against the Cambodian army. A force of 50 Vietnamese quickly overran large parts of eastern Cambodia reaching to within {{convert|15|mi|km}} of [[Phnom Penh]] before being pushed back. In these battles the Khmer Rouge and Sar played a very small role.

In October 1970, Sar issued a resolution in the name of the Central Committee. The resolution stated the principle of independence-mastery (aekdreach machaskar)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Hinton|first=Alexander Laban|title=Why Did They Kill: Cambodia in the Shadow of Genocide|year=2005|publisher=University of California Press|pages=382|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=3fTpplDUlA4C&amp;dq=independence+mastery+cambodia&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Lahneman|first=William J.|title=Military Intervention: Cases in Context for the Twenty-First Century|year=2004|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield|pages=97|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=7MEDymP3JNkC&amp;dq=independence+mastery+cambodia&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s}}&lt;/ref&gt;  which was a call for Cambodia to decide its own future independent of the influence of any other country. The resolution also included statements describing the betrayal of the Cambodian Communist movement in the 1950s by the Viet Minh. This was the first statement of the anti-Vietnamese/self-sufficiency-at-all-costs ideology that would be a major part of the Pol Pot regime when it took power years later.

[[Kaing Guek Eav]] has claimed that US support for the [[Lon Nol]] coup contributed to the Khmer Rouge's rise to power.&lt;ref name=&quot;huffingtonpost.com&quot;&gt;{{Cite news| work=[[The Huffington Post]] | title = Khmer Rouge Defendent: US Policies Enabled Cambodian Genocide| date = April 6, 2009 | url = http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2009/04/06/khmer-rouge-defendent-us_n_183660.html | accessdate =March 5, 2010 | first=Stuart | last=Whatley}}&lt;/ref&gt; However diplomat [[Timothy M. Carney]] disagreed, asserting that Pol Pot won the war due to support from [[Sihanouk]], massive supplies of military aid from North Vietnam, government corruption, the cut-off of U.S. air support after [[Watergate]], and the determination of the Cambodian Communists.&lt;ref&gt;http://shodhganga.inflibnet.ac.in/bitstream/10603/461/8/09_chapter3.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; Although it remains a popular belief in Cambodia, there is no evidence of direct American involvement in the coup.&lt;ref&gt;Clymer, K. J. The United States and Cambodia, Routledge, 2004, p.22&lt;/ref&gt;

Through 1971, the Vietnamese (North Vietnamese and Viet Cong) did most of the fighting against the Cambodian government while Sar and the Khmer Rouge functioned almost as auxiliaries to their forces. Sar took advantage of the situation to gather in new recruits and to train them to a higher standard than previously possible. Sar also put resources of Khmer Rouge organizations into political education and indoctrination. While accepting anyone regardless of background into the Khmer Rouge army at this time, Saloth greatly increased the requirements for membership in the party. Students and so-called &quot;middle peasants&quot; were now rejected by the party. Those with clear peasant backgrounds were the preferred recruits for party membership. These restrictions were ironic in that most of the senior party leadership including Saloth came from student and middle peasant backgrounds. They also created an intellectual split between the educated old guard party members and the uneducated peasant new party members.

In early 1972, Sar toured the insurgent/Vietnamese controlled areas in Cambodia. He saw a regular Khmer Rouge army of 35,000 men taking shape supported by around 100,000 [[Irregular military|irregulars]]. China was supplying five million dollars a year in weapons and Sar had organized an independent revenue source for the party in the form of [[rubber]] plantations in eastern Cambodia using forced labour.

After a central committee meeting in May 1972, the party under the direction of Sar began to enforce new levels of discipline and conformity in areas under their control. Minorities such as the [[Cham (Asia)|Chams]] were forced to conform to Cambodian styles of dress and appearance. These policies, such as forbidding the Chams from wearing jewelry, were soon extended to the whole population. A haphazard version of [[land reform]] was undertaken by Saloth. Its basis was that all land holdings should be of uniform size. The party also confiscated all private means of transportation. The 1972 policies were aimed at reducing the peoples of the liberated areas to a sort of feudal peasant equality. These policies were generally favourable at the time to poor peasants and extremely unfavourable to refugees from towns who had fled to the countryside.

In 1972, the Vietnamese army forces began to withdraw from the fighting against the Cambodian government. Sar issued a new set of decrees in May 1973 which started the process of reorganizing peasant villages into [[cooperative]]s where property was jointly owned and individual possessions banned.

====Control of the countryside====
{{Unreferenced section|date=June 2012}}
The Khmer Rouge advanced during 1973. After they reached the edges of Phnom Penh, Sar issued orders during the peak of the rainy season that the city be taken. The orders led to futile attacks and wasted lives among the Khmer Rouge army. By the middle of 1973, the Khmer Rouge under Sar controlled almost two-thirds of the country and half the population. Vietnam realized that it no longer controlled the situation and began to treat Saloth as more of an equal leader than a junior partner.

In late 1973, Sar made strategic decisions about the future of the war. His first decision was to cut the capital off from contact from outside supply, putting the city under siege. The second decision was to enforce tight command on people trying to leave the city through the [[Khmer Rouge]] lines. He also ordered a series of general [[purge]]s of former government officials and anyone with an education. A set of new prisons was also constructed in Khmer Rouge run areas. The Cham minority attempted an uprising to stop the destruction of their culture. The uprising was quickly crushed, Saloth ordered that harsh physical torture be used against most of those involved in the revolt. As previously, Saloth tested out harsh new policies against the Cham minority, before extending them to the general population of the country.

The Khmer Rouge also had a policy of evacuating urban areas to the countryside. When the Khmer Rouge took the town of [[Kratié (city)|Kratie]] in 1971, Saloth and other members of the party were shocked at how fast the liberated urban areas shook off socialism and went back to the old ways. Various ideas were tried to re-create the town in the image of the party, but nothing worked. In 1973, out of total frustration, Saloth decided that the only solution was to send the entire population of the town to the fields in the countryside. He wrote at the time &quot;if the result of so many sacrifices was that the capitalists remain in control, what was the point of the revolution?&quot;. Shortly after, Sar ordered the evacuation of the {{formatnum:15000}} people of Kompong Cham for the same reasons. The Khmer Rouge then moved on in 1974 to evacuate the larger city of [[Oudong]].

Internationally, Sar and the Khmer Rouge were able to gain the recognition of 63 countries as the true government of Cambodia. A move was made at the UN to give the seat for Cambodia to the Khmer Rouge; they prevailed by three votes.

In September 1974, Sar gathered the central committee of the party together. As the military campaign was moving toward a conclusion, Saloth decided to move the party toward implementing a socialist transformation of the country in the form of a series of decisions. The first being to evacuate the main cities, moving the population to the countryside. The second dictated they would cease to put money in circulation and quickly phase it out. The final decision was that the party would accept Sar's first major purge. In 1974, Saloth had purged a top party official named Prasith. Prasith was taken out into a forest and shot without any chance to defend himself. His death was followed by a purge of cadres who, like Prasith, were ethnically [[Thai people|Thai]]. Sar's explanation was that the [[class struggle]] had become acute, requiring a strong stand against party enemies.

The Khmer Rouge were positioned for a final offensive against the government in January 1975. Simultaneously, at a press event in Beijing, Sihanouk proudly announced Sar's &quot;death list&quot; of enemies to kill after victory. The list, which originally contained seven names expanded to 23, including all the senior government leaders along with the military and police leadership. The rivalry between Vietnam and Cambodia also came out into the open. [[North Vietnam]], as the rival socialist country in [[Indochina]], was determined to take [[Saigon]] before the Khmer Rouge took Phnom Penh. Shipments of weapons from China were delayed, in one instance the Cambodians were forced to sign a humiliating document thanking Vietnam for shipments of Chinese weapons.

In September 1975, the government formed a Supreme National Council with new leadership, with the aim of negotiating a surrender to the Khmer Rouge. It was headed by [[Sak Sutsakhan]] who had studied in France with Saloth, and was cousin to the Khmer Rouge Deputy Secretary [[Nuon Chea]]. Saloth reacted to this by adding the names of everyone involved to his post-victory death list. Government resistance finally collapsed on September 17, 1975.

===Leader of Kampuchea (1975–79)===
{{Main|Khmer Rouge period (1975–1979)}}

[[Image:Choeungek2.JPG|thumb|250px|right|Skulls of Khmer Rouge victims]]
[[File:ChoeungEk-Darter-8.jpg|thumb|250px|right|Mass grave in [[Choeung Ek]]]]

The Khmer Rouge took [[Phnom Penh]] on April 17, 1975. As the leader of the Communist Party, Saloth Sar was the designated leader of the new regime. He took the name &quot;brother number one&quot; and declared his [[Pseudonym#Noms de guerre|''nom de guerre'']] Pol Pot. This derives from '''''Pol'''itique '''pot'''entielle,'' the French equivalent of a phrase supposedly coined for him by the Chinese leadership. An alternative version of the origin of Pol Pot's name is from Philip Short, who states that Saloth Sar announced that he was adopting the name in July 1970 and suspects that it is derived from pol: “the Pols were royal slaves, an aboriginal people,” and that “Pot” was simply a “euphonic monosyllable” that he liked.&lt;ref&gt;See ''Pol Pot: Anatomy of a Nightmare,'' p. 212.&lt;/ref&gt;

A new constitution was adopted on January 5, 1976, officially altering the country's name to &quot;Democratic Kampuchea.&quot; The newly established Representative Assembly held its first plenary meeting on April 11 – 13, electing a new government with Pol Pot as prime minister. His predecessor, [[Khieu Samphan]] was instead given the position of [[head of state]] as ''President of the State Presidium.'' Prince [[Sihanouk]] was given no role in the government and was placed under detention.

Immediately after the fall of Phnom Penh, the Khmer Rouge began to implement their concept of [[Year Zero (political notion)|Year Zero]] and ordered the complete evacuation of Phnom Penh and all other recently captured major towns and cities. Those leaving were told that the evacuation was due to the threat of severe American bombing and it would last for no more than a few days.

Pol Pot and the Khmer Rouge had been evacuating captured urban areas for many years, but the evacuation of Phnom Penh was unique due to its scale. The first operations to evacuate urban areas occurred in 1968 in the Ratanakiri area and were aimed at moving people deeper into Khmer Rouge territory to better control them. From 1971–1973, the motivation changed. Pol Pot and the other senior leaders were frustrated that urban Cambodians were retaining old capitalist habits of trade and business. When all other methods had failed, evacuation to the countryside was adopted to solve the problem.

In 1976, people were reclassified as full-rights (base) people, candidates and depositees – so called because they included most of the new people who had been deposited from the cities into the communes. Depositees were marked for destruction. Their rations were reduced to two bowls of rice soup, or &quot;[[Rice congee|p'baw]]&quot; per day. This led to widespread starvation. &quot;New people&quot; were allegedly given no place in the elections taking place on March 20, 1976, despite the fact the constitution supposedly established [[universal suffrage]] for all Cambodians over age 18.

The Khmer Rouge leadership boasted over the state-controlled radio that only one or two million people were needed to build the new [[Agrarian socialism|agrarian communist]] [[utopia]]. As for the others, as their proverb put it, &quot;To keep you is no benefit, to destroy you is no loss.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;children_of_cambodias_killing_fields&quot;&gt;Children of Cambodia's Killing Fields, ''Worms from Our Skin.'' Teeda Butt Mam. Memoirs compiled by Dith Pran. 1997, [[Yale University]]. ISBN 978-0-300-07873-2. [http://books.google.com/books?id=FjEpaj1F9VoC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_summary_r&amp;cad=0#PPA13,M1 Excerpts available from Google Books].&lt;/ref&gt;

Hundreds of thousands of the new people, and later the depositees, were taken out in shackles to dig their own [[mass grave]]s. Then the Khmer Rouge soldiers buried them alive. A Khmer Rouge extermination prison directive ordered, &quot;Bullets are not to be wasted.&quot; These mass graves are often referred to as [[The Killing Fields]].
[[File:Tuolsleng2.JPG|thumb|Photos of the victims of the Khmer Rouge, [[Tuol Sleng Genocide Museum|Tuol Sleng]]]]
The Khmer Rouge also classified people by religion and ethnic group. They banned all religion and dispersed minority groups, forbidding them to speak their languages or to practice their customs. They especially targeted [[Buddhism|Buddhist]] monks, Muslims, Christians, Western-educated intellectuals, educated people in general, people who had contact with Western countries or with Vietnam, disabled people, and the ethnic Chinese, [[Laos|Laotians]] and [[Vietnamese people|Vietnamese]]. Some were put in the [[Tuol Sleng Genocide Museum|S-21]] camp for interrogation involving torture in cases where a confession was useful to the government. Many others were summarily executed.{{citation needed|date=June 2012}}

According to François Ponchaud's book ''Cambodia: Year Zero,'' &quot;Ever since 1972, the guerrilla fighters had been sending all the inhabitants of the villages and towns they occupied into the forest to live and often burning their homes, so that they would have nothing to come back to.&quot; The Khmer Rouge refused offers of [[humanitarian aid]], a decision that caused a humanitarian catastrophe: millions died of starvation and brutal government-inflicted overwork in the countryside. To the Khmer Rouge, outside aid went against their principle of national [[autarky|self-reliance]].

Property became collective, and education was dispensed at communal schools. Children were raised on a communal basis. Even meals were prepared and eaten communally. Pol Pot's regime was extremely paranoid. [[Political dissent]] and opposition was not permitted. People were treated as opponents based on their appearance or background. [[Torture]] was widespread, thousands of politicians and [[bureaucrat]]s accused of association with previous governments were executed. Phnom Penh was turned into a ghost city, while people in the countryside were dying of [[starvation]], illnesses, or simply killed.

U.S. officials had predicted that more than one million people would be killed by the Khmer Rouge if they took power,&lt;ref&gt;Washington Post, June 4, 23, 1975.&lt;/ref&gt; and President [[Gerald Ford]] had warned of &quot;an unbelievable horror story.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.paulbogdanor.com/left/cambodia/bloodbath1.pdf 1975 interview with President Ford]&lt;/ref&gt;  Different estimates as to the number killed by the Khmer Rouge regime vary from 750,000 to over three million. Analysis of 20,000 mass grave sites by the DC-Cam Mapping Program and [[Yale University]] indicate at least 1,386,734 victims.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dccam.org/Projects/Maps/Mapping.htm Documentation Center of Cambodia]&lt;/ref&gt; Estimates of the total number of deaths resulting from Khmer Rouge policies, including disease and starvation, range from 1.7 to 2.5 million out of a population of around 8 million.&lt;ref&gt;Peace Pledge Union Information – Talking about genocides – Cambodia 1975 – [http://www.ppu.org.uk/genocide/g_cambodia1.html the genocide.]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title=Twentieth Century Atlas – Death Tolls | url=http://users.erols.com/mwhite28/warstat2.htm#Cambodia | accessdate=November 19, 2005 }}&lt;/ref&gt; A figure of 3 million deaths between 1975 and 1979 was given by the People's Republic of Kampuchea. François Ponchaud suggested 2.3&amp;nbsp;million, R.J. Rummel 2.4&amp;nbsp;million (counting [[democide]] in the civil wars), the Yale Cambodian Genocide Project 1.7&amp;nbsp;million, and [[Amnesty International]] 1.4&amp;nbsp;million. Demographer Marek Sliwinski concluded that at least 1.8&amp;nbsp;million were killed from 1975–9 on the basis of the total population decline, compared to roughly 40,000 killed by the U.S. bombing.&lt;ref&gt;Marek Sliwinski, Le Génocide Khmer Rouge: Une Analyse Démographique (L’Harmattan, 1995).&lt;/ref&gt;  Researcher Craig Etcheson of the Documentation Center of Cambodia suggests that the death toll was between 2 and 2.5 million, with a &quot;most likely&quot; figure of 2.2 million. After five years of researching some 20,000 grave sites, he concludes that, &quot;these mass graves contain the remains of 1,386,734 victims of execution.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;CountingHell&quot;&gt;[http://www.mekong.net/cambodia/deaths.htm Counting Hell], discusses the various estimates.&lt;/ref&gt;  Execution is believed to have accounted for about 30–50 percent of the death toll. This would indicate 2.5 to 3 million deaths, but normal mortality over this period would have accounted for about 500,000 deaths — subtracting this from the total sum, we arrive at Etcheson's range for the number of &quot;excess&quot; deaths attributable to the Khmer Rouge regime.&lt;ref name=&quot;CountingHell&quot;/&gt;  A U.N. investigation reported 2–3 million dead, while UNICEF estimated 3 million had been killed.&lt;ref&gt;William Shawcross, The Quality of Mercy: Cambodia, Holocaust, and Modern Conscience (Touchstone, 1985), p115-6&lt;/ref&gt;  Even the Khmer Rouge acknowledged that 2 million had been killed—though they attributed those deaths to a subsequent Vietnamese invasion.&lt;ref&gt;Khieu Samphan, Interview, Time, March 10, 1980.&lt;/ref&gt;  By late 1979, U.N. and Red Cross officials were warning that another 2.25 million Cambodians faced death by starvation due to “the near destruction of Cambodian society under the regime of ousted Prime Minister Pol Pot,”&lt;ref&gt;New York Times, August 8, 1979.&lt;/ref&gt; who were saved by American and international aid after the Vietnamese invasion. It is estimated that at least half a million more were starved to death or slaughtered after the invasion from Vietnam.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hawaii.edu/powerkills/SOD.TAB4.1A.GIF Statistics of Cambodian Democide], Rummel estimates over one million from all causes; Etcheson 500,000 by 1981 from famine alone.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mekong.net/cambodia/demcat.htm Kampuchea: A Demographic Catastrophe], CIA estimates 350,000 in first few months.&lt;/ref&gt;

Pol Pot aligned the country politically with the People's Republic of China and adopted an anti-Soviet line. This alignment was more political and practical than ideological. Vietnam was aligned with the Soviet Union, so Cambodia aligned with the rival of the Soviet Union and Vietnam in Southeast Asia. China had been supplying the Khmer Rouge with weapons for years before they took power.

In December 1976, Pol Pot issued directives to the senior leadership to the effect that Vietnam was now an enemy. Defenses along the border were strengthened and unreliable deportees were moved deeper into Cambodia. Pol Pot's actions were in response to the Vietnamese Communist Party's fourth Congress, which approved a resolution describing Vietnam's special relationship with Laos and Cambodia. It also talked of how Vietnam would forever be associated with the building and defense of the other two countries.

===Conflict with Vietnam===
{{Main|Cambodian-Vietnamese War}}
{{Refimprove section|date=April 2009}}

In May 1975 a squad of Khmer Rouge soldiers raided and took [[Phu Quoc Island]]. By 1977, relations with Vietnam began to fall apart. There were small border clashes in January. Pol Pot tried to prevent border disputes by sending a team to Vietnam. The negotiations failed which resulted in even more border disputes. On April 30, the Cambodian army, backed by artillery, crossed over into Vietnam. In attempting to explain Pol Pot's behavior, one region-watcher{{Specify|date=October 2007}}&lt;!--and source, of course--&gt; suggested that Cambodia was attempting to intimidate Vietnam, by irrational acts, into respecting or at least fearing Cambodia to the point they would leave the country alone. However, these actions only served to anger the Vietnamese people and government against the Khmer Rouge.

In May 1976, Vietnam sent its air force into Cambodia in a series of raids. In July, Vietnam forced a Treaty of Friendship on Laos which gave Vietnam almost total control over the country. In Cambodia, Khmer Rouge commanders in the Eastern Zone began to tell their men that war with Vietnam was inevitable and that once the war started their goal would be to recover parts of Vietnam (Khmer Krom) that were once part of Cambodia, whose people, they alleged, were struggling for independence from Vietnam. It is not clear whether these statements were the official policy of Pol Pot.

In September 1977, Cambodia launched [[Division (military)|division]]-scale raids over the border which once again left a trail of murder and destruction in villages. The Vietnamese claimed that around 1,000 people had been killed or injured. Three days after the raid, Pol Pot officially announced the existence of the formerly secret Communist Party of Kampuchea (CPK) and finally announced to the world that the country was a Communist state. In December, after having exhausted all other options, Vietnam sent 50,000 troops into Cambodia in what amounted to a short raid. The raid was meant to be secret. The Vietnamese withdrew after declaring they had achieved their goals, and the invasion was just a warning. Upon being threatened, the Vietnamese army promised to return with support from the Soviet Union. Pol Pot's actions made the operation much more visible than the Vietnamese had intended and created a situation in which Vietnam appeared weak.

After making one final attempt to negotiate a settlement with Cambodia, Vietnam decided that it had to prepare for a full war. Vietnam also tried to pressure Cambodia through China. However, China's refusal to pressure Cambodia and the flow of weapons from China into Cambodia were both signs that China also intended to act against Vietnam.

When Cambodian communists rebelled in the eastern zone in May 1978 Pol Pot’s armies were unable to crush them quickly. On May 10 his radio broadcast a call not only to ‘exterminate the 50&amp;nbsp;million Vietnamese’ but also to ‘purify the masses of the people’ of Cambodia. Of 1.5&amp;nbsp;million easterners, branded as ‘Khmer bodies with Vietnamese minds’, at least 100,000 were exterminated in six months. Later that year, in response to threats to its borders and the Vietnamese people, Vietnam attacked Cambodia to overthrow the Khmer Rouge, which Vietnam could justify on the basis of self-defense.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.newint.org/features/1993/04/05/original/
|title=The Original Cambodian
|publisher=New Internationalist
|year=1993 |month=April
|work=242
|first=Ben |last=Kiernan
|accessdate=April 16, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
The Cambodian army was defeated, the regime was toppled and Pol Pot fled to the [[Thailand|Thai]] border area. In January 1979, Vietnam installed a new government under [[Heng Samrin]], composed of Khmer Rouge who had fled to Vietnam to avoid the purges. Pol Pot eventually regrouped with his core supporters in the Thai border area where he received shelter and assistance. At different times during this period, he was located on both sides of the border. The military government of Thailand used the Khmer Rouge as a buffer force to keep the Vietnamese away from the border. The Thai military also made money from the shipment of weapons from China to the Khmer Rouge. Eventually Pol Pot was able to rebuild a small military force in the west of the country with the help of the People's Republic of China. The PRC also initiated the [[Sino-Vietnamese War]] around this time.

After the Khmer Rouge were driven from power by the Vietnamese in 1979, the United States and other powers{{Specify|date=October 2007}} refused to allow the Vietnamese-backed Cambodian government to take the seat of Cambodia at the United Nations. The seat, by default, remained in the hands of the Khmer Rouge. These countries justified that decision on the ground that recognising Vietnam's occupation of Cambodia was worse than allowing the Khmer Rouge to hold on to the seat. Also, representatives of these countries argued{{Citation needed|date=October 2007}} that both claimants to the seat were Khmer Rouge governments, because Vietnam's Cambodian government was formed from ex-Khmer Rouge cadres.
[[File:Nicolae Ceauşescu with Pol Pot.jpg|thumb|250px|left|[[Nicolae Ceauşescu]] with Pol Pot (1978)]]

Pol Pot lived in the [[Phnom Malai]] area, giving interviews in the early 1980s accusing all those who opposed him of being traitors and &quot;puppets&quot; of the [[Vietnam]]ese until he disappeared from public view. In 1985, his &quot;retirement&quot; was announced, but he retained influence over the party.&lt;ref&gt;[http://opus.macmillan.yale.edu/workpaper/pdfs/GS24.pdf Kelvin Rowley, ''Second Life, Second Death: The Khmer Rouge After 1978'']&lt;/ref&gt; A cadre interviewed during this period described Pol Pot's views on the death toll under his government:

::''He said that he knows that many people in the country hate him and think he’s responsible for the killings. He said that he knows many people died. When he said this he nearly broke down and cried. He said he must accept responsibility because the line was too far to the left, and because he didn’t keep proper track of what was going on. He said he was like the master in a house he didn’t know what the kids were up to, and that he trusted people too much. For example, he allowed [one person] to take care of central committee business for him, [another person] to take care of intellectuals, and [a third person] to take care of political education.... These were the people to whom he felt very close, and he trusted them completely. Then in the end ... they made a mess of everything.... They would tell him things that were not true, that everything was fine, that this person or that was a traitor. In the end they were the real traitors. The major problem had been cadres formed by the Vietnamese.''&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in David P. Chandler, ''Brother Number One: A Political Biography of Pol Pot,'' Silkworm Books, Chiang Mai, 2000&lt;/ref&gt;

In December 1985, the Vietnamese launched a major offensive and overran most of the Khmer Rouge and other insurgent positions. The Khmer Rouge headquarters at Phnom Malai and its base near [[Pailin]] were completely destroyed; the Vietnamese attackers suffered substantial losses during the attack.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dtic.mil/cgi-bin/GetTRDoc?AD=ADA318310&amp;Location=U2&amp;doc=GetTRDoc.pdf R.R.Ross, ''Current Indochinese Issues'']&lt;/ref&gt;

Pol Pot fled to Thailand where he lived for the next six years. His headquarters were a plantation villa near [[Trat]]. He was guarded by Thai Special Unit 838.

Pol Pot officially resigned from the party in 1985 citing asthma as a contributing factor, but continued as the de facto Khmer Rouge leader and a dominant force within the anti-Vietnam alliance. He handed day to day power to [[Son Sen]], his hand-picked successor. 

In 1986, his new wife Mea Son gave birth to a daughter, Sitha, named after the heroine of the Khmer religious epic, the [[Reamker]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Short|2005|p=423}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly after, Pol Pot moved to China for medical treatment for cancer. He remained there until 1988.

In 1989, Vietnam withdrew from Cambodia. The Khmer Rouge established a new stronghold area in the west near the Thai border and Pol Pot relocated back into Cambodia from Thailand. Pol Pot refused to cooperate with the peace process, and kept fighting the new coalition government. The Khmer Rouge kept the government forces at bay until 1996, when troops started deserting. Several important Khmer Rouge leaders also defected. The government had a policy of making peace with Khmer Rouge individuals and groups after negotiations with the organization as a whole failed. In 1995 Pol Pot experienced a stroke that paralyzed the left side of his body.

Pol Pot ordered the execution of his lifelong right-hand man Son Sen on June 10, 1997 for attempting to make a settlement with the government. Eleven members of his family were killed also, although Pol Pot later denied that he had ordered this. He then fled his northern stronghold, but was later arrested by Khmer Rouge military Chief [[Ta Mok]] on June 19, 1997. Pol Pot had not been seen in public since 1980, two years after his overthrow at the hands of an invading Vietnamese army. He was sentenced to death in absentia by a Phnom Penh court soon afterward.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://articles.cnn.com/1997-06-21/world/9706_21_pol.pot_1_khieu-samphan-anlong-veng-fields-reign?_s=PM:WORLD | work=CNN | title=Pol Pots Khmer Rouge denounces him | date=June 17, 1997}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In July he was subjected to a [[show trial]] for the death of Son Sen and sentenced to lifelong [[house arrest]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cybercambodia.com/dachs/killing/polpot.html Nate Thayer, &quot;Dying Breath The inside story of Pol Pot's last days and the disintegration of the movement he created,&quot; ''Far Eastern Economic Review'', April 30, 1998]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Death===
On the night of April 15, 1998, the [[Voice of America]], to which Pol Pot was a devoted listener, announced that the Khmer Rouge had agreed to turn him over to an international tribunal. According to his wife, he died in his bed later in the night while waiting to be moved to another location. Ta Mok claimed that his death was due to heart failure.&lt;ref&gt;[[Nate Thayer]]. &quot;[http://www.cybercambodia.com/dachs/killing/polpot.html Dying Breath]&quot; ''Far Eastern Economic Review''. April 30, 1998.&lt;/ref&gt; Despite government requests to inspect the body, it was [[cremated]] a few days later at [[Anlong Veng]] in the Khmer Rouge zone,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kZgk_dI4JFo Footage] of the body of Pol Pot (15 april 1988)&lt;/ref&gt; raising suspicions that he committed suicide.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/1999/jan/21/cambodia John Gittings and Mark Tran, &quot;Pol Pot 'killed himself with drugs',&quot; ''The Guardian'', Thursday January 21, 1999.]&lt;/ref&gt;

==International support==
===Support from China===
The [[China|People's Republic of China]] was regarded as the main international support for the Khmer Rouge and its leader Pol Pot. The Chinese provided financial and military support to the party;&lt;ref&gt;[[Andy Carvin|Carvin, Andy]] &quot;[http://www.edwebproject.org/sideshow/khmeryears/fall.html KR Years: The fall of the Khmer Rouge]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; their motivation being its intense rivalry with Vietnam at the time, which coincided with Pol Pot's plans to regain the ancient lands of the kingdom, which were and remain within neighboring countries such as Vietnam. Beijing communist government did not condemn the persecution of the ethnic Chinese within Cambodia's borders.

===Support from UN===
During the Khmer Rouge regime and a period of time directly after, the Khmer Rouge was recognised by UN as a legitimate government, therefore retaining a seat at the UN.&lt;ref&gt;&quot; [[Kiernan, Ben]] &quot;[http://www.historyplace.com/pointsofview/kiernan.htm Cambodia's Twisted Path to Justice]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
While many leaders at the UN attempted to appeal this,{{citation needed|date=June 2012}} the majority allowed the Khmer Rouge (later titled &quot;Democratic Republic of Kampuchea&quot;) to keep their seat for 15 years{{citation needed|date=June 2012}} following the genocide.

==See also==
* [[Khmer Rouge]]
* [[Cambodian Civil War]]
* [[First Indochina War]]
* [[Vietnam War]] (Second Indochina War)
* [[Tuol Sleng Genocide Museum]]
* [[Enemies of the People (film)]]

== References ==

{{Reflist|2}}

== Works ==
*''[http://www.archive.org/details/LongLiveThe17thAnniversaryOfTheCommunistPartyOfKampucheaSpeech Long live the 17th anniversary of the Communist Party of Kampuchea : speech]'' New York : Group of Kampuchean Residents in America, 1977
*''[http://www.archive.org/details/SpeechMadeByComradePolPotSecretaryOfTheCentralCommitteeOfThe Speech made by comrade Pol Pot, Secretary of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of Kampuchea &quot;At the banquet given in honour of the delegation of the Communist party of China and the government of the People's Republic of China. Phnom Penh, November 5, 1978.&quot; ]'' [Phnom Penh]: Dept. of Press and Information, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Democratic Kampuchea, 1978
*''[http://www.archive.org/details/InterviewToTheRepresentativesOfTheHongKongsNewspapersWenWeiPoAnd Interview to the representatives of the Hong Kong's newspapers Wen wei po and Ta kun pao, Phnom Penh, September 21, 1978]'' [Phnom Penh]: Dept. of Press and Information, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Democratic Kampuchea, 1978
*''[http://www.archive.org/details/InterviewOfComradePolPotSecretaryOfTheCentralCommitteeOfThe Interview of Comrade Pol Pot, Secretary of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of Kampuchea, Prime Minister of the Government of Democratic Kampuchea to the delegation of Yugoslav journalists in visit to Democratic Kampuchea, March 17, 1978]'' [Phnom Penh]: Dept. of Press and Information, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Democratic Kampuchea, 1978
*''[http://www.archive.org/details/TalksWithTheDelegationOfTheSweden-kampucheaFriendshipAssociation Talks with the delegation of the Sweden-Kampuchea Friendship Association [August 1978&lt;nowiki&gt;]&lt;/nowiki&gt; ]'' [Phnom Penh]: Dept. of Press and Information, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Democratic Kampuchea, 1978
*''Let us continue to firmly hold aloft the banner of the victory of the glorious Communist Party of Kampuchea in order to defend Democratic Kampuchea, carry on socialist revolution and build up socialism: speech made by Comrade Pol Pot on the occasion of the 18th anniversary of the founding of the Communist Party of Kampuchea, Phnom Penh, September 27, 1978'' [Phnom Penh]: Dept. of Press and Information, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Democratic Kampuchea, 1978
*''[http://www.archive.org/details/TalksWithTheDelegationOfTheAssociationBelgium-kampucheaPhnomPenh Talks with the delegation of the Association Belgium-Kampuchea, Phnom Penh, August 5, 1978]'' [Phnom Penh]: Dept. of Press and Information, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Democratic Kampuchea, 1978

==Further reading==
{{Contains Khmer text}}
*[[Denise Affonço]]: ''To The End Of Hell: One Woman's Struggle to Survive Cambodia's Khmer Rouge.'' (With Introductions by [[Jon Swain]] and [[David P. Chandler|David Chandler]].) ISBN 978-0-9555729-5-1
*{{Cite book|title= Pol Pot: Anatomy of a Nightmare |last= Short |first= Philip |authorlink= Philip Short |edition= 1st American |year= 2005 |publisher=[[Henry Holt and Company]] |location= New York |isbn= 0-8050-6662-4 |ref= CITEREFShort2005 }}
* [[David P. Chandler]]/Ben Kiernan/Chanthou Boua: ''Pol Pot plans the future: Confidential leadership documents from Democratic Kampuchea, 1976–1977''. Yale University Press, New Haven, Conn. 1988. ISBN 0-938692-35-6
* David P. Chandler: ''Brother Number One: A political biography of Pol Pot''. Westview Press, Boulder, Col. 1992. ISBN 0-8133-3510-8
* Stephen Heder: ''Pol Pot and Khieu Samphan''. Clayton, Victoria: Centre of Southeast Asian Studies, 1991. ISBN 0-7326-0272-6
* Ben Kiernan: &quot;Social Cohesion in Revolutionary Cambodia,&quot; Australian Outlook, December 1976
* Ben Kiernan: &quot;Vietnam and the Governments and People of Kampuchea&quot;, Bulletin of Concerned Asian Scholars (October–December 1979)
* Ben Kiernan: ''The Pol Pot regime: Race, power and genocide in Cambodia under the Khmer Rouge'', 1975–79. New Haven, Conn: Yale University Press 1997. ISBN 0-300-06113-7
* Ben Kiernan: ''How Pol Pot came to power: A history of Cambodian communism, 1930–1975''. New Haven, Conn.: Yale University Press 2004. ISBN 0-300-10262-3
* Ponchaud, François. Cambodia: Year Zero. New York: Holt, Rinehart and Winston, 1978
* Vickery, Michael. Cambodia: 1975–1982. Boston: South End Press, 1984
* Pescali, Piergiorgio. Indocina. Bologna: Emil, 2010

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Commons category|Pol Pot}}
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/programmes/from_our_own_correspondent/81048.stm A meeting with Pol Pot] Elizabeth Becker of ''[[The New York Times]]''
*[http://repository.library.georgetown.edu/handle/10822/552628 Pol Pot and the Cambodian Genocide] from the [http://repository.library.georgetown.edu/handle/10822/552494 Dean Peter Krogh Foreign Affairs Digital Archives]
* [http://www.international.ucla.edu/article.asp?parentid=21630 Interview with P. Short], [[UCLA]] International Institute
* ''[http://www.archive.org/details/BiographyOfComradePolPotSecretaryOfTheCentralCommitteeOfThe Biography of comrade Pol Pot, secretary of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of Kampuchea.]'' A pamphlet published by Democratic Kampucheas foreign ministry
*[http://www.ess.uwe.ac.uk/genocide/cambodia.htm Cambodian Genocide]: material compiled by Dr Stuart D Stein
*[http://www.yale.edu/cgp/ Cambodian Genocide Program, 1994–2008]
*[http://www.cambodiatribunal.org/ Cambodia Tribunal Monitor]
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BQMyX80jCF8&amp;feature=related Nate Thayer's Interview with Pol Pot on YouTube, Part 1]
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BQMyX80jCF8&amp;feature=related Nate Thayer's Interview with Pol Pot on YouTube, Part 2]
*[http://www.paulbogdanor.com/left/cambodia/locard.pdf State Violence in Democratic Kampuchea (1975–1979) and Retribution (1979–2004)]
*[http://www.paulbogdanor.com/left/cambodia/diary.pdf Diary From Darkness]
*[http://padevat.info/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/PolPotYugoslav.pdf Pol Pot's Interview with Yugoslav Journalists (1978)]
*[http://docsonline.tv/?search=Pol%20Pot%and%20the%20Khmer%Rouge&amp;type=title&amp;docinfo=397 'Pol Pot and the Khmer Rouge'] a 3 part documentary by Adrian Maben (2001)
{{S-start}}
{{S-off}}
{{S-bef|before = [[Khieu Samphan]]}}
{{S-ttl|title = [[Prime Minister of Cambodia|Prime Minister of Democratic Kampuchea]]
 |years = 1976–1980}}
{{S-aft|after = [[Khieu Samphan]]}}
|-
{{S-bef|before = None}}
{{S-ttl|title = Director of the [[Higher Institute of National Defence]]
 |years = 1985–1997}}
{{S-aft|after = None}}
|-
{{S-ppo}}
{{S-bef|before = [[Tou Samouth]]}}
{{S-ttl|title = [[General Secretary of the Communist Party of Kampuchea]]
 |years = 1963–1981}}
{{S-aft|after = Himself&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;Party of Democratic Kampuchea&lt;/small&gt;}}
|-
{{S-bef|before = Himself&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;Kampuchean Communist Party&lt;/small&gt;}}
{{S-ttl|title = [[Party of Democratic Kampuchea|General Secretary of the Party of Democratic Kampuchea]]
 |years = 1981–1985}}
{{S-aft|after = [[Khieu Samphan]]}}
|-
{{S-mil}}
{{S-bef|before = ?}}
{{S-ttl|title = [[National Army of Democratic Kampuchea|Supreme Commander of the National Army of Democratic Kampuchea]]
 |years = 1980–1985}}
{{S-aft|after = [[Son Sen]]}}
|-
{{S-end}}

{{CambodianLeaders}}
{{Khmer Rouge}}
{{Cold War}}
{{Fall of Communism}}

&lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
{{Persondata
|NAME              = Pot, Pol
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES = Sar, Saloth
|SHORT DESCRIPTION = Prime Minister of Democratic Kampuchea from 1976–1979
|DATE OF BIRTH     = May 19, 1925
|PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Kampong Thum Province]], Cambodia
|DATE OF DEATH     = April 15, 1998
|PLACE OF DEATH    = Cambodia
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Pot, Pol}}
[[Category:1925 births]]
[[Category:1998 deaths]]
[[Category:Anti-intellectualists]]
[[Category:Cambodian communists]]
[[Category:Cambodian people of Chinese descent]]
[[Category:Cancer survivors]]
[[Category:Cold War leaders]]
[[Category:Communist Party of Kampuchea politicians]]
[[Category:Communist rulers]]
[[Category:Former Buddhists]]
[[Category:Guerrillas]]
[[Category:Khmer Rouge]]
[[Category:Leaders who took power by coup]]
[[Category:Maoist theorists]]
[[Category:People from Kampong Thom Province]]
[[Category:People of the Vietnam War]]
[[Category:Prime Ministers of Cambodia]]
[[Category:Rebels]]
[[Category:Atheists]]
[[Category:Revolutionaries]]

{{Link FA|es}}

[[af:Pol Pot]]
[[ar:بول بوت]]
[[an:Pol Pot]]
[[ast:Pol Pot]]
[[be:Пол Пот]]
[[be-x-old:Пол Пот]]
[[bg:Пол Пот]]
[[bs:Pol Pot]]
[[br:Pol Pot]]
[[ca:Pol Pot]]
[[cs:Pol Pot]]
[[cy:Pol Pot]]
[[da:Pol Pot]]
[[de:Pol Pot]]
[[et:Pol Poth]]
[[el:Πολ Ποτ]]
[[es:Pol Pot]]
[[eo:Pol Pot]]
[[eu:Pol Pot]]
[[fa:پل پوت]]
[[fo:Pol Pot]]
[[fr:Pol Pot]]
[[ga:Pol Pot]]
[[gl:Pol Pot]]
[[ko:폴 포트]]
[[hi:पोल पॉट]]
[[hr:Pol Pot]]
[[id:Pol Pot]]
[[is:Pol Pot]]
[[it:Pol Pot]]
[[he:פול פוט]]
[[jv:Pol Pot]]
[[ka:პოლ პოტი]]
[[ku:Pol Pot]]
[[lad:Pol Pot]]
[[lv:Pols Pots]]
[[lt:Pol Potas]]
[[hu:Pol Pot]]
[[mk:Пол Пот]]
[[ml:പോൾ പോട്ട്]]
[[ms:Pol Pot]]
[[mwl:Pol Pot]]
[[mn:Пол Пот]]
[[my:ပိုပေါ့]]
[[nl:Pol Pot]]
[[ja:ポル・ポト]]
[[no:Pol Pot]]
[[nn:Pol Pot]]
[[km:ប៉ុល​ពត]]
[[nds:Pol Pot]]
[[pl:Pol Pot]]
[[pt:Pol Pot]]
[[ro:Pol Pot]]
[[ru:Пол Пот]]
[[sa:पोल पॉट]]
[[sco:Pol Pot]]
[[sq:Pol Pot]]
[[scn:Pol Pot]]
[[simple:Pol Pot]]
[[sk:Pol Pot]]
[[sl:Pol Pot]]
[[sr:Пол Пот]]
[[sh:Pol Pot]]
[[fi:Pol Pot]]
[[sv:Pol Pot]]
[[tl:Pol Pot]]
[[ta:போல் போட்]]
[[te:పాల్ పాట్]]
[[th:พล พต]]
[[tr:Pol Pot]]
[[uk:Пол Пот]]
[[vi:Pol Pot]]
[[fiu-vro:Pol Pot]]
[[war:Pol Pot]]
[[zh:波尔布特]]</text>
      <sha1>e9mt7w8utu360nhdav1c5xozj5tbcma</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
