<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Rock Hudson</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>161466</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520798194</id>
      <parentid>520627506</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-31T20:30:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>LittleWink</username>
        <id>9748448</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Disambiguated: [[Tobruk (film)]] → [[Tobruk (1967 film)]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="35836">{{Infobox person
|name = Rock Hudson
|image = Rock Hudson in Giant trailer cropped.jpg
|caption = An image from the trailer for ''[[Giant (1956 film)|Giant]]'' (1956)
|birth_name = Roy Harold Scherer, Jr.
|birth_date = {{Birth date|mf=yes|1925|11|17}}
|birth_place = [[Winnetka, Illinois]], U.S.
|death_date = {{Death date and age|mf=yes|1985|10|2|1925|11|17}}&lt;ref name=CS17404227 &gt;{{cite news |title=Aids victim Rock Hudson dies in his sleep aged 59 |author=Michael Binyon |date=1985-10-03 |page=1 |newspaper=[http://archive.timesonline.co.uk/tol/keywordsearch.arc?queryKeywords=Aids+victim+Rock+Hudson+dies+in+his+sleep+aged+59 The Times]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|death_place = [[Beverly Hills, California]], U.S.
|death_cause = [[AIDS]]
|othername = Roy Harold Fitzgerald
|occupation = Actor
|years_active = 1948–1985
|spouse = [[Phyllis Gates]] (1925–2006), married 1955–1958, divorced

}}
'''Rock Hudson''' (born '''Roy Harold Scherer, Jr.''', November 17, 1925{{spaced ndash}}October 2, 1985), was an American film and television actor. Though widely known as a [[leading man]] in the 1950s &amp; 60s (often starring in romantic comedies opposite [[Doris Day]]), Hudson is also recognized for dramatic roles in films such as ''[[Giant (1956 film)|Giant]]'' and ''[[Magnificent Obsession (1954 film)|Magnificent Obsession]]''. In later years, Hudson found success in television, starring in the popular [[Mystery fiction|mystery]] series ''[[McMillan &amp; Wife]]'' and landing a recurring role on the prime time [[soap opera]] ''[[Dynasty (TV series)|Dynasty]]''.

Hudson was voted &quot;Star of the Year&quot;, &quot;Favorite Leading Man&quot;, and similar titles by numerous movie magazines. The {{height|ft=6|in=5}} tall actor was one of the most popular and well-known movie stars of the time. He completed nearly 70 motion pictures and starred in several television productions during a career that spanned over four decades.

Hudson died in 1985, being the first major celebrity to die from an [[AIDS]]-related illness.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.tcmdb.com/participant.jsp?participantId=90260|133734&amp;afiPersonalNameId=null&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life==
Hudson was born '''Roy Harold Scherer, Jr.''', in [[Winnetka, Illinois]], the only child of Katherine Wood (of [[English people|English]] and [[Irish people|Irish]] descent), a telephone operator, and Roy Harold Scherer, Sr., (of [[Germans|German]] and [[Swiss]] descent) an auto mechanic who abandoned the family during the depths of the [[Great Depression]]. His mother remarried and his stepfather Wallace &quot;Wally&quot; Fitzgerald adopted him, changing his last name to Fitzgerald. Hudson's years at [[New Trier High School]] were unremarkable. He sang in the school's [[glee club]] and was remembered as a shy boy who delivered newspapers, ran errands and worked as a golf caddy.

After graduating from high school, he served in the [[Philippines]] as an aircraft mechanic for the [[United States Navy]] during [[World War II]].&lt;ref name=autogenerated4&gt;Berger, Joseph, [http://partners.nytimes.com/library/national/science/aids/100385sci-aids.html &quot;Rock Hudson, Screen Idol, Dies at 59&quot;], [[The New York Times]], Oct. 3, 1985. Retrieved 2011-02-12.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1946, Hudson moved to the [[Los Angeles]] area to pursue an acting career and applied to the [[University of Southern California]]'s dramatics program, but he was rejected owing to poor grades. Hudson worked for a time as a truck driver, longing to be an actor but with no success in breaking into the movies. A fortunate meeting with Hollywood talent scout [[Henry Willson]] in 1948 got Hudson his start in the business.

==Career==
===Early career===
Hudson made his debut with a small part in the 1948 [[Warner Bros.]]' ''Fighter Squadron''. Hudson needed no fewer than 38 takes before successfully delivering his only line in the film.&lt;ref&gt;''The Man Who Invented Rock Hudson: The Pretty Boys and Dirty Deals of Henry Willson'' by Robert Hofler, Carroll &amp; Graf, 2005, pp. 163-164 ISBN 0-7867-1607-X&lt;/ref&gt;

Hudson was further coached in [[acting]], [[singing]], [[dancing]], [[fencing (sport)|fencing]], and [[horseback riding]] at Universal International, and he began to be featured in film [[magazine]]s where he was promoted, possibly on the basis of his good looks. Success and recognition came in 1954 with ''[[Magnificent Obsession (1954 film)|Magnificent Obsession]]'' in which Hudson plays a bad boy who is redeemed opposite the popular star [[Jane Wyman]].&lt;ref name=autogenerated4 /&gt; The film received rave reviews, with ''Modern Screen Magazine'' citing Hudson as the most popular actor of the year. Hudson's popularity soared with [[George Stevens]]' ''[[Giant (1956 film)|Giant]]'', based on [[Edna Ferber]]'s novel and co-starring [[Elizabeth Taylor]] and [[James Dean]]. Hudson and Dean both were nominated for [[Academy Award|Oscars]] in the [[Academy Award for Best Actor|Best Actor]] category. In the 1950s Hudson made nine films with acclaimed director and father-figure [[Douglas Sirk]], Sirk's own favorite being ''[[The Tarnished Angels]]'' (1958). 

Following [[Richard Brooks]]' notable ''Something of Value'' (1957) was a moving performance in [[Charles Vidor]]'s box office failure ''[[A Farewell to Arms (1957 film)|A Farewell to Arms]]'', based on [[Ernest Hemingway]]'s novel. In order to make ''A Farewell to Arms'', he had reportedly turned down [[Marlon Brando]]'s role in ''[[Sayonara]]'', [[William Holden]]'s role in ''[[The Bridge on the River Kwai]]'', and [[Charlton Heston]]'s role in ''[[Ben-Hur (1959 film)|Ben-Hur]]''. Those films went on to become hugely successful and critically acclaimed, while ''A Farewell to Arms'' proved to be one of the biggest flops in cinema history.{{Citation needed|date=April 2011}}

Hudson sailed through the 1960s on a wave of romantic comedies. He portrayed humorous characters in ''[[Pillow Talk (film)|Pillow Talk]]'', the first of three profitable co-starring performances with [[Doris Day]]. This was followed by ''[[Lover Come Back (1961 film)|Lover Come Back]]'', ''[[Come September]]'', ''[[Send Me No Flowers]]'', ''[[Man's Favorite Sport?]]'', ''[[The Spiral Road]]'', and ''[[Strange Bedfellows (1965 film)|Strange Bedfellows]]''. Along with [[Cary Grant]], Hudson was regarded as one of the best-dressed male stars in Hollywood, and received &quot;Top 10 Stars of the Year&quot; a record eight times from 1957 to 1964. He worked outside his usual range on the science-fiction thriller ''[[Seconds (film)|Seconds]]'' (1966). The film flopped but it later gained cult status, and Hudson's performance is often regarded as one of his best.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QVKXXDPg2kA&amp;feature=related YouTube – Rock Hudson in ''Seconds''&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.apolloguide.com/mov_fullrev.asp?CID=3835 Apollo Movie Guide's Review of Seconds&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; He also tried his hand in the action genre with ''[[Tobruk (1967 film)|Tobruk]]'' (1967), the lead in 1968's spy thriller ''[[Ice Station Zebra]]'', a role which he had actively sought and remained his personal favorite, and westerns with ''[[The Undefeated (1969 film)|The Undefeated]]'' (1969) opposite [[John Wayne]].

===Later career===
Hudson's popularity on the big screen diminished after the 1960s. He starred in a number of made-for-TV movies and series. His most successful TV series was ''[[McMillan &amp; Wife]]'' opposite [[Susan Saint James]] which ran from 1971 to 1977. In it, Hudson played [[police commissioner]] Stewart &quot;Mac&quot; McMillan with Saint James as his wife Sally. Their on-screen chemistry helped make the show a hit. Hudson took a risk and surprised many by making a successful foray into live theatre late in his career, the most acclaimed of his efforts being [[I Do! I Do!]] with [[Carol Burnett]] in 1974.

In the early 1980s, following years of heavy drinking and smoking, Hudson began having health problems which resulted in a heart attack in November 1981. Emergency quintuple heart bypass surgery sidelined Hudson and his new TV show ''The Devlin Connection'' for a year; the show was canceled in December 1982 not long after it first aired. Hudson recovered from the heart surgery but continued to smoke. He nevertheless continued to work with appearances in several TV movies. He was in ill health while filming the action-drama film ''The Ambassador'' in Israel during the winter months of 1983-84 with [[Robert Mitchum]]. The two stars reportedly did not get along with each other, with Mitchum himself having a serious drinking problem.&lt;ref&gt;Server, Lee ''Baby, I Don't Care'' (2001)&lt;/ref&gt; During 1984, while filming the TV drama ''The Vegas Strip Wars'', Hudson's health grew worse, prompting different rumors that he was suffering from liver cancer, among other ailments, because of his increasingly gaunt face and build.

From December 1984 to April 1985, Hudson landed a recurring role on the [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] prime time [[soap opera]] ''[[Dynasty (TV series)|Dynasty]]'' as Daniel Reece, the love interest for Krystle Carrington (played by [[Linda Evans]]) and biological father of the character Sammy Jo Carrington ([[Heather Locklear]]). While he had long been known to have difficulty memorizing lines, which resulted in his use of [[cue cards]], on ''Dynasty'' it was Hudson's speech itself that began to deteriorate. Hudson was originally slated to appear for the duration of the show's 5th season, however, because of his progressing ill health, his character was abruptly written out of the show and died offscreen.

==Personal life==
While Hudson's career was developing, he and his agent [[Henry Willson]] kept his personal life out of the headlines. In 1955, ''[[Confidential (magazine)|Confidential]]'' magazine threatened to publish an exposé about Hudson's secret [[Homosexuality|homosexual]] life. Willson forestalled this by disclosing information about two of his other clients.&lt;ref&gt;Willson provided information about [[Rory Calhoun]]'s years in prison and the arrest of [[Tab Hunter]] at a party in 1950. See: Hofler, Robert. ''The Man Who Invented Rock Hudson: The Pretty Boys and Dirty Deals of Henry Willson.'' New York: Carroll &amp; Graf, 2005, p. 248–250; Oppenheimer, Jerry and Vitek, Jack. ''Idol Rock Hudson: The True Story of an American Film Hero.'' New York: Villard Books, 1986, p. 55.&lt;/ref&gt; According to some colleagues, Hudson's homosexuality was well known in Hollywood throughout his career;&lt;ref name=autogenerated3&gt;Yarbrough, Jeff. [http://www.people.com/people/archive/article/0,,20091477,00.html &quot;Rock Hudson: On Camera and Off, The Tragic News That He Is the Most Famous Victim of An Infamous Disease, AIDS, Unveils the Hidden Life of a Longtime Hollywood Hero&quot;], [[People Magazine]], Vol. 24, No. 7, August 12, 1985. Retrieved 2011-02-12.&lt;/ref&gt; former costars [[Elizabeth Taylor]] and [[Susan Saint James]] claimed they knew of his homosexual activity, as did both [[Doris Day]] and [[Carol Burnett]].

Soon after the ''Confidential'' incident, Hudson married Willson's secretary [[Phyllis Gates]]. Gates later wrote that she dated Hudson for several months, lived with him for two months before his surprise marriage proposal, and married Hudson out of love and not, as it was later purported, to prevent an exposé of Hudson's [[sexual orientation]].&lt;ref&gt;Phyllis Gates, ''My Husband, Rock Hudson'' (1987), written with [[Bob Thomas (reporter)|Bob Thomas]], pp. ??&lt;/ref&gt; Press coverage of the wedding quoted Hudson as saying, &quot;When I count my blessings, my marriage tops the list.&quot; Gates filed for divorce after three years in April 1958, charging mental cruelty. Hudson did not contest the divorce, and Gates received [[alimony]] of US$250 a week for 10 years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=Dennis Mclellan |title=Phyllis Gates: Her marriage to Hudson had fan magazines raving |url=http://www.dallasnews.com/sharedcontent/dws/dn/obituaries/stories/011706dnmetgatesobit.ce8c30d.html |work=Los Angeles Times |date=January 16, 2006 |accessdate=2007-09-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; After her death from [[lung cancer]] in January 2006, some informants reportedly stated that she was actually a [[lesbian]] who married Hudson for his money, knowing from the beginning of their relationship that he was gay.&lt;ref name=&quot;fa1&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url= http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1589/is_2006_Feb_28/ai_n16107748 |title=Outing Mrs. Rock Hudson: the obits after Phyllis Gates died in January omitted some important facts: Those who knew her say she was a lesbian who tried to blackmail her movie star husband|accessdate=December 20, 2007 |publisher=CNET Networks, Inc|year=2006|author=Robert Hofler |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071219153858/http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1589/is_2006_Feb_28/ai_n16107748 |archivedate = December 19, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; She never remarried.

According to the 1986 biography ''Rock Hudson: His Story'' by Hudson and [[Sara Davidson]], Hudson was good friends with American novelist [[Armistead Maupin]], and Hudson's lovers included: Jack Coates (born 1944); Hollywood publicist Tom Clark (1933–1995), who also later published a memoir about Hudson, ''Rock Hudson: Friend of Mine''; and Marc Christian, who later won a suit against the Hudson estate.

An [[urban legend]] states that Hudson married [[Jim Nabors]] in the 1970s. In fact the two were never more than friends. According to Hudson, the legend originated with a group of &quot;middle-aged homosexuals who live in Huntington Beach&quot; who sent out joke invitations for their annual get-together. One year, the group invited its members to witness &quot;the marriage of Rock Hudson and Jim Nabors&quot;, at which Hudson would take the surname of Nabors' most famous character, [[Gomer Pyle]], becoming &quot;Rock Pyle&quot;. Those who failed to get the joke spread the rumor. As a result, Nabors and Hudson never spoke to each other again.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Barbara Mikkelson |title=Good Nabors Policy |url=http://www.snopes.com/movies/actors/nabors.htm |publisher=Snopes |date=August 10, 2007 |accessdate=2007-09-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==AIDS and death==
[[File:Reagans with Rock Hudson.jpg|thumb|Hudson (left) with President [[Ronald Reagan]] and first lady [[Nancy Reagan]] at a White House state dinner, May 1984]]
In July 1985, Hudson joined his old friend [[Doris Day]] for the launch of her new TV cable show, ''Doris Day's Best Friends'' where he videotaped a live guest appearance at her southern California ranch. His gaunt appearance and nearly incoherent speech were so shocking that it was broadcast again all over the national news shows that night and for weeks to come.

Earlier, Hudson had been diagnosed with [[HIV]] on June 5, 1984, but when the signs of illness became apparent a few months later, his publicity staff and doctors told the public he had inoperable [[Hepatocellular carcinoma|liver cancer]]. During most of 1984 and 1985, Hudson kept his illness a secret while continuing to work and at the same time travel to France and other countries seeking a cure, or at least treatment to slow the progress of the disease.

It was not until July 25, 1985, while in Paris for treatment and just over one week following his appearance on Doris Day's TV cable show, that Hudson issued a press release announcing that he was dying of [[AIDS]]. In another press release a month later, Hudson speculated he might have contracted HIV through transfused blood from an infected donor during the multiple blood transfusions he received during his heart bypass procedure in November 1981. He flew back to Los Angeles on July 31, where he was so physically weak that he was taken off by stretcher from the Air France Boeing 747 he had chartered and upon which he and his medical attendants were the only passengers.&lt;ref&gt;Shilts, Randy. ''And the Band Played On: Politics, People, and the AIDS Epidemic''. New York: St. Martin's Press. 1987. p. 580. ISBN 0-312-00994-1&lt;/ref&gt; He was flown by helicopter to [[Cedars Sinai Hospital]], where he spent nearly a month undergoing further treatment. When the doctors told him there was no hope of saving his life, since the disease had progressed into the advanced stages, Hudson returned to his house, &quot;The Castle&quot;, in [[Beverly Hills]], where he remained in seclusion until his death on October 2, 1985 at 8:37&amp;nbsp;a.m. [[Pacific Standard Time|PDT]]. He was a month and a half away from his 60th birthday.

The disclosure of Hudson's HIV status provoked widespread public discussion of his homosexuality. In its August 15, 1985 issue, [[People (magazine)|''People'']] published a story that discussed his disease in the context of his sexuality. The largely sympathetic article featured comments from famous show business colleagues such as [[Angie Dickinson]], [[Robert Stack]], and [[Mamie Van Doren]], who claimed they knew about Hudson's homosexuality and expressed their support for him.&lt;ref name=autogenerated3 /&gt; At that time ''People'' had a circulation of more than 2.8 million,&lt;ref&gt;Diamond, Edwin. ''Celebrating Celebrity: The New Gossips''. [[New York Magazine]], Vol. 18, No. 19. May 13, 1985.&lt;/ref&gt; and, as a result of this and other stories, theories about Hudson's homosexuality became fully public.

Hudson's revelation had an immediate impact on visibility of AIDS, and on funding of medical research related to the disease. Among activists who were seeking to de-stigmatize AIDS and its victims, Hudson's revelation of his own infection with the disease was viewed as an event that could transform the public's perception of AIDS. Shortly after Hudson's press release disclosing his infection, [[William M. Hoffman]], the author of ''[[As Is (play)|As Is]]'', a play about AIDS that appeared on Broadway in 1985, stated: &quot;If Rock Hudson can have it, nice people can have it. It's just a disease, not a moral affliction.&quot;&lt;ref name=autogenerated3 /&gt; At the same time, [[Joan Rivers]] was quoted as saying: &quot;Two years ago, when I hosted a benefit for AIDS, I couldn't get one major star to turn out. ... Rock's admission is a horrendous way to bring AIDS to the attention of the American public, but by doing so, Rock, in his life, has helped millions in the process. What Rock has done takes true courage.&quot;&lt;ref name=autogenerated3 /&gt; [[Morgan Fairchild]] said that &quot;Rock Hudson's death gave AIDS a face&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/3281609.stm
|title=BBC NEWS – Entertainment – The show goes on in Aids battle |publisher=news.bbc.co.uk |accessdate=2008-07-27 | date=November 24, 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a telegram Hudson sent to a September 1985 Hollywood AIDS benefit, Commitment to Life, which he was too ill to attend in person, Hudson said: &quot;I am not happy that I am sick. I am not happy that I have AIDS. But if that is helping others, I can at least know that my own misfortune has had some positive worth.&quot;&lt;ref name=autogenerated4 /&gt;

Shortly after his death, ''People'' reported: &quot;Since Hudson made his announcement, more than $1.8 million in private contributions (more than double the amount collected in 1984) has been raised to support AIDS research and to care for AIDS victims (5,523 reported in 1985 alone). A few days after Hudson died, Congress set aside $221 million to develop a cure for AIDS.&quot;&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt;[http://www.people.com/people/archive/article/0,,20092645,00.html &quot;Rock Hudson: His Name Stood for Hollywood's Golden Age of Wholesome Heroics and Lighthearted Romance—Until He Became the Most Famous Person to Die of Aids&quot;], [[People Magazine]], Vol. 24 No. 26, Dec. 23, 1985. Retrieved 2011-02-11&lt;/ref&gt; Organizers of the Hollywood AIDS benefit, Commitment to Life, reported after Hudson's announcement he was suffering from the disease, it was necessary to move the event to a larger venue to accommodate the increased attendance.&lt;ref name=autogenerated5&gt;Harmetz, Aljean. [http://www.nytimes.com/1985/09/20/us/hollywood-turns-out-for-aids-benefit.html &quot;Hollywood Turns Out for AIDS Benefit&quot;], [[The New York Times]], Sept. 20, 1985. Retrieved 2011-02-11&lt;/ref&gt;

However, Hudson's revelation did not immediately dispel the stigma of AIDS. Although then-president [[Ronald Reagan]] and his wife [[Nancy Reagan]] were friends of Hudson, Reagan, who was viewed by some as indifferent to the disease and its sufferers, made no public statement concerning Hudson's condition.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;Boffey, Philip M. [http://www.nytimes.com/1985/09/18/us/reagan-defends-financing-for-aids.html &quot;Reagan Defends Financing for AIDS&quot;], [[The New York Times]], Sept. 17, 1985. Retrieved 2001-02-11.&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, privately, Reagan called Hudson in his Paris hospital room where he was being treated in July 1985, and Nancy Reagan telephoned French President [[François Mitterrand]] to ensure that Hudson would receive the best possible care.&lt;ref name=autogenerated3 /&gt; Reagan's first public mention of the disease came in response to questions at a September 15, 1985 press conference, nearly two months after Hudson's announcement. In those remarks, Reagan called medical research on AIDS a &quot;top priority&quot;. However, when asked, &quot;If you had younger children, would you send them to a school with a child who had AIDS?,&quot; Reagan responded equivocally: &quot;[G]lad I'm not faced with that problem today. ...&amp;nbsp;I can understand both sides of it.&quot;&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; Several days later, Reagan sent a telegram to the Commitment to Life AIDS benefit, in which he reiterated his position that his administration would make stopping the spread of AIDS a top priority.&lt;ref name=autogenerated5 /&gt; Nevertheless, Reagan did not publicly address AIDS at length for another two years.&lt;ref&gt;Boffey, Philip M. [http://www.nytimes.com/1987/06/01/us/reagan-urges-wide-aids-testing-but-does-not-call-for-compulsion.html? &quot;Reagan Urges Wide AIDS Testing But Does Not Call for Compulsion&quot;], [[The New York Times]], June 1, 1987. Retrieved 2011-02-11&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition, a controversy arose concerning Hudson's participation in a scene in the television drama ''Dynasty'' in which he shared a kiss with actress [[Linda Evans]] in one episode. When filming the scene Hudson was aware that he had AIDS, but did not inform her. Some felt that he should have disclosed his condition to her beforehand.&lt;ref&gt;Haller, Scot. [http://www.people.com/people/archive/article/0,,20091775,00.html “Rock Hudson's Startling Admission That He Has AIDS Prompts An Urgent Call for Action&amp;nbsp;— And Some Extreme Reactions”], [[People Magazine]], Vol. 23, No. 13, Sept. 23, 1985. Retrieved 2011-02-11.; ''Should Actors Take AIDS Test Before Filming a Kiss?''[[Jet magazine]], Vol. 68, No. 26, Sept. 9, 1985.&lt;/ref&gt; At the time, it was known that the virus was present in low quantities in saliva and tears, but there had been no reported cases of transmission by kissing.&lt;ref&gt;''Should Actors Take AIDS Test Before Filming a Kiss?''[[Jet magazine]], Vol. 68, No. 26, Sept. 9, 1985.&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, the [[Centers for Disease Control and Prevention]] had warned against exchanging saliva with members of groups perceived to be at high risk for AIDS.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt; According to comments given in August 1985 by [[Ed Asner]], then president of the [[Screen Actors Guild]], Hudson's revelation caused incipient &quot;panic&quot; within the film and television industry. Asner said that he was aware of scripts being rewritten to eliminate kissing scenes.&lt;ref&gt;Harmetz, Aljean. [http://www.nytimes.com/1985/08/08/movies/old-and-new-hollywood-seen-in-attitude-to-aids.html &quot;Old and New Hollywood Seen in Attitude to AIDS&quot;], [[The New York Times]], Aug. 8, 1985. Retrieved 2011-02-11.&lt;/ref&gt; Later in the same year, the Guild issued rules requiring that actors be notified in advance of any &quot;open-mouth&quot; kissing scenes, and providing that they could refuse to participate in such scenes without penalty.&lt;ref&gt;Harmetz, Aljean. [http://www.nytimes.com/1985/10/31/movies/a-rule-on-kissing-scenes-and-aids.html &quot;A Rule on Kissing Scenes and AIDS&quot;], [[The New York Times]], Oct. 31, 1985. Retrieved 2011-02-11.&lt;/ref&gt; Linda Evans herself appears not to have been angry at Hudson: she asked to introduce the segment of the 1985 Commitment to Life benefit that was dedicated to Hudson.&lt;ref name=autogenerated5 /&gt;

Hudson was [[cremation|cremated]] and his ashes scattered at sea.

==Post burial, debate and legacy==
Following Hudson's funeral, Marc Christian sued Hudson's estate on grounds of &quot;intentional infliction of emotional distress&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=Willard Manus |title=The Cleaning Man Airs Rock Hudson's Dirty Laundry in L.A. |url=http://www.playbill.com/news/article/57447.html |work=Playbill |date=18 December 2000 |accessdate=2007-09-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; Christian tested negative for HIV but claimed Hudson continued having sex with him until February 1985, more than eight months after Hudson knew he had HIV. Hudson biographer [[Sara Davidson]] later stated that, by the time she had met Hudson, Christian was living in the guest house, and Tom Clark, who had allegedly been Hudson's partner for many years before, was living in the house.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite interview |subject=Marc Christian |interviewer=Larry King |title=Rock Hudson's Ex-Lover Speaks Out |url=http://transcripts.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/0103/29/lkl.00.html |program=Larry King Live |callsign=CNN |date=March 29, 2001 |accessdate=2007-09-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following his death, [[Elizabeth Taylor]], his co-star in the film ''Giant'', purchased a bronze plaque for Hudson on the [[West Hollywood Memorial Walk]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://lisaburks.typepad.com/gravehunting/celebrity_memorials/ Adventures in Grave Hunting by Lisa Burks: Celebrity Memorials&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Hudson has been the subject of three plays: ''Hollywood Valhalla'' by [[Aidan Harney]], starring Patrick Byrnes as Rock and Stewart Roche as his personal trainer, Toby, which was staged at Bewley's Cafe Theatre, Dublin, Ireland, in 2011; &quot;For Roy&quot;, by Nambi E. Kelley, starring [[Richard Henzel]] as Roy and Hannah Gomez as Caregiver, which was staged at American Theatre Company in Chicago in 2010 and ''Rock'', by [[Tim Fountain]], starring Michael Xavier as Rock and Bette Bourne as his agent Henry Willson, which was staged at London's Oval House Theatre in 2008.

In 2010, with the gag orders finally lifted from the 1985 lawsuit trial of Marc Christian versus the estate of Hudson, Robert Park Mills, the attorney who represented the Hudson estate against Christian in court, released a new 492 page book entitled ''Between Rock and a Hard Place-In Defense of Rock Hudson''. In the book, Mills argues that the public was blinded from the real truth, the gross injustice done to the late actor by Christian and by Rock’s alleged friend, Mark Miller, as was the court, the jury, and the press. Mills argues that the jury overlooked the possibility Christian may have been AIDS-free simply because Hudson never had the relationship with Christian which Christian claimed to have had with him. According to this argument, if Hudson had had such a relationship, Christian would have had to have acquired HIV and AIDS if the repeated unprotected sexual activity claimed had taken place. Christian, who died in 2009 at age 56, never had HIV or AIDS.

Mills argues that Christian did not tell the truth to his attorney Harold Rhoden or in court, and that  Hudson could not defend himself before the jurors because Christian waited until Rock died. Only when Christian found out he was not in the late actor's will did he bring his lawsuit, which won $5.5 million dollars from Hudson's estate (minus attorney's fees).&lt;ref&gt;http://www.authorhouse.com/Bookstore/BookDetail.aspx?BookId=SKU-000420092&lt;/ref&gt;

In the book ''Rock Hudson, Friend of Mine'' by his live-in Hollywood publicist Tom Clark, Clark said he would go to his grave believing Hudson acquired HIV from blood transfusions during his emergency quintuple bypass open heart surgery in 1981. Clark's book characterized Christian as &quot;a criminal, a thief, an unclean person, a blackmailer, a psychotic, an extortionist, a forger, a perjurer, a liar, a whore, an arsonist and a squatter.&quot; Christian then sued Clark. Christian was living in the guest house after Clark, who had left in 1983, had returned to Hudson's home in 1985 to take care of him at assistant Mark Miller's request.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://articles.latimes.com/1990-04-05/local/me-1051_1_rock-hudson | work=Los Angeles Times | first=Carol | last=McGraw | title=Rock Hudson Ex-Lover Files Libel Suit | date=April 5, 1990}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Filmography==
{{Multicol}}
* ''[[Fighter Squadron]]'' (1948)
* ''[[Undertow (1949 film)|Undertow]]'' (1949)
* ''[[One Way Street]]'' (1950)
* ''[[I Was a Shoplifter]]'' (1950)
* ''[[Peggy (film)|Peggy]]'' (1950)
* ''[[Winchester '73 (1950 film)|Winchester '73]]'' (1950)
* ''[[The Desert Hawk (1950 film)|The Desert Hawk]]'' (1950)
* ''[[Shakedown (1950 film)|Shakedown]]'' (1950)
* ''[[Tomahawk (film)|Tomahawk]]'' (1951)
* ''[[Air Cadet (film)|Air Cadet]]'' (1951)
* ''[[The Fat Man (radio)|The Fat Man]]'' (1951) (radio show)
* ''[[The Fat Man (film)|The Fat Man]]'' (1951) (film)
* ''[[Bright Victory]]'' (1951)
* ''[[Iron Man (1951 film)|Iron Man]]'' (1951)
* ''[[Bend of the River]]'' (1952)
* ''[[Here Come the Nelsons]]'' (1952)
* ''[[Scarlet Angel]]'' (1952)
* ''[[Has Anybody Seen My Gal? (film)|Has Anybody Seen My Gal?]]'' (1952)
* ''[[Horizons West]]'' (1952)
* ''[[The Lawless Breed]]'' (1953)
* ''[[Seminole (film)|Seminole]]'' (1953)
* ''[[Back to God's Country (1953 film)|Back to God's Country]]'' (1953)
* ''[[Gun Fury]]'' (1953)
* ''[[The Golden Blade]]'' (1953)
* ''[[Sea Devils]]'' (1953)
* ''[[Bengal Brigade]]'' (1954)
* ''[[Magnificent Obsession (1954 film)|Magnificent Obsession]]'' (1954)
* ''[[Taza, Son of Cochise]]'' (1954)
* ''[[Lucy Thinks Ricky Is Trying to Murder Her|I Love Lucy (1 episode, guest star)]]'' (1955)
* ''[[All That Heaven Allows]]'' (1955)
* ''[[One Desire]]'' (1955) .... Clint Saunders
* ''[[Captain Lightfoot]]'' (1955)
* ''[[Never Say Goodbye (1956 film)|Never Say Goodbye]]'' (1956)
* ''[[Giant (1956 film)|Giant]]'' (1956)
* ''[[Written on the Wind]]'' (1956)
* ''[[Battle Hymn (film)|Battle Hymn]]'' (1957)
* ''[[Something of Value]]'' (1957)
* ''[[A Farewell to Arms (1957 film)|A Farewell to Arms]]'' (1957)
{{Multicol-break}}
* ''[[Twilight for the Gods]]'' (1958)
* ''[[The Tarnished Angels]]'' (1958)
* ''[[Pillow Talk (film)|Pillow Talk]]'' (1959)
* ''[[This Earth Is Mine]]'' (1959)
* ''[[Lover Come Back (1961 film)|Lover Come Back]]'' (1961)
* ''[[Come September]]'' (1961)
* ''[[The Last Sunset (film)|The Last Sunset]]'' (1961)
* ''[[The Spiral Road]]'' (1962)
* ''[[Marilyn (1963 film)|Marilyn]]'' (1963)
* ''[[A Gathering of Eagles]]'' (1963)
* ''[[Send Me No Flowers]]'' (1964)
* ''[[Man's Favorite Sport?]]'' (1964)
* ''[[Blindfold (film)|Blindfold]]'' (1965)
* ''[[A Very Special Favor]]'' (1965)
* ''[[Strange Bedfellows (1965 film)|Strange Bedfellows]]'' (1965)
* ''[[Seconds (film)|Seconds]]'' (1966)
* ''[[Tobruk (1967 film)|Tobruk]]'' (1967)
* ''[[Ice Station Zebra]]'' (1968)
* ''[[The Undefeated (1969 film)|The Undefeated]]'' (1969)
* ''[[Ruba al prossimo tuo]]'' (1969)
* ''[[Hornets' Nest]]'' (1970)
* ''[[Darling Lili]]'' (1970)
* ''[[Once Upon a Dead Man]]'' (1971) (TV)
* ''[[Pretty Maids All in a Row]]'' (1971)
* ''[[Showdown (1973 film)|Showdown]]'' (1973)
* ''[[Embryo (1976 film)|Embryo]]'' (1976)
* ''[[McMillan &amp; Wife]]'' (40 episodes, 1971–1977)
* ''[[Avalanche (1978 film)|Avalanche]]'' (1978)
* ''[[Wheels (TV miniseries)|Wheels]]'' (1978) TV mini-series
* ''[[The Martian Chronicles (TV miniseries)|The Martian Chronicles]]'' (1979) TV mini-series
* ''[[The Mirror Crack'd]]'' (1980)
* ''[[Superstunt II]]'' (1980)
* ''[[NBC Family Christmas]]'' (1981)
* ''[[The Star Maker (1981 film)|The Star Maker]]'' (1981)
* ''[[The Devlin Connection]]'' (13 episodes, 1982)
* ''[[World War III (TV miniseries)|World War III]]'' (1982) TV mini-series
* ''[[The Vegas Strip War]]'' (1984)
* ''[[The Ambassador (1984 American film)|The Ambassador]]'' (1984)
* ''[[Dynasty (TV series)|Dynasty]]'' (14 episodes, 1984–1985)
{{Multicol-end}}

==Awards==
* Academy Award: Nominated 1956 Best Actor for ''Giant''
* Golden Globe: Winner 1959 World Film Favorite: Male actor
* Golden Globe: Winner 1960 World Film Favorite: Male actor
* Golden Globe: co-Winner with [[Tony Curtis]] 1961 World Film Favorite: Male actor
* Golden Globe: Winner 1963 World Film Favorite: Male actor
* Hudson received a star on the [[Hollywood Walk of Fame]] at [[Hollywood Boulevard|6104 Hollywood Boulevard]].
* In 2002, a Golden Palm Star on the [[Palm Springs, California]], [[Palm Springs Walk of Stars|Walk of Stars]] was dedicated to him.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.palmspringswalkofstars.com/web-storage/Stars/Stars%20dedicated%20by%20date.pdf Palm Springs Walk of Stars by date dedicated]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* ''[[Rock Hudson's Home Movies]]''
{{Portal bar|Biography|Television in the United States|Film|LGBT|Chicago|Illinois}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
* {{cite book |last=Clark |first=Tom |coauthors=Kleiner, Richard |title=Rock Hudson, Friend of Mine |location=New York, NY|publisher=Pharos Books |year=1990 |isbn=0-88687-562-5}}
* {{cite book |last=Gates |first=Phyllis |coauthors=Thomas, Bob |title=My Husband, Rock Hudson |location=Garden City, NY|publisher=Doubleday |year=1987 |isbn=0-385-24071-6}}
* {{cite book |last=Hudson |first=Rock |coauthors=Davidson, Sara |title=Rock Hudson: His Story |location=New York |publisher=Morrow |year=1986 |isbn=0-688-06472-8}}
* {{cite book |last=Ragland |first=Shannon P. |title=The Thin Thirty |location=Louisville, KY |publisher=Set Shot Press |year=2007 |isbn=0-9791222-1-X}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
* {{IMDb name|1369}}
* {{Tcmdb name|90260}}
* [http://transcripts.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/0106/07/lkl.00.html Transcript of CNN Larry King 7. June 2001, Special on Rock Hudson offscreen with Dale Olson]
* [http://transcripts.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/0310/01/lkl.00.html Transcript of CNN Larry King 1. October 2003, 18th anniversary of Hudson's death]

{{Oscars hosts 1961-1980}}

{{Authority control|VIAF=52486041}}
{{Persondata
|NAME= Hudson, Rock
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES= Scherer, Roy Harold, Jr.
|SHORT DESCRIPTION= Actor
|DATE OF BIRTH= November 17, 1925
|PLACE OF BIRTH= Winnetka, Illinois, U.S.
|DATE OF DEATH= October 2, 1985
|PLACE OF DEATH= Beverly Hills, California, U.S.
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Hudson, Rock}}
[[Category:1925 births]]
[[Category:1985 deaths]]
[[Category:Actors from Illinois]]
[[Category:AIDS-related deaths in California]]
[[Category:American film actors]]
[[Category:American military personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:American television actors]]
[[Category:gay actors]]
[[Category:LGBT people from the United States]]
[[Category:New Trier High School alumni]]
[[Category:People from Winnetka, Illinois]]
[[Category:People self-identifying as alcoholics]]
[[Category:United States Navy sailors]]

[[an:Rock Hudson]]
[[bcl:Rock Hudson]]
[[bs:Rock Hudson]]
[[br:Rock Hudson]]
[[bg:Рок Хъдзън]]
[[ca:Rock Hudson]]
[[co:Rock Hudson]]
[[cy:Rock Hudson]]
[[da:Rock Hudson]]
[[de:Rock Hudson]]
[[es:Rock Hudson]]
[[eo:Rock Hudson]]
[[eu:Rock Hudson]]
[[fa:راک هادسن]]
[[fr:Rock Hudson]]
[[gl:Rock Hudson]]
[[hr:Rock Hudson]]
[[io:Rock Hudson]]
[[id:Rock Hudson]]
[[it:Rock Hudson]]
[[he:רוק הדסון]]
[[la:Rock Hudson]]
[[hu:Rock Hudson]]
[[mk:Рок Хадсон]]
[[nl:Rock Hudson]]
[[ja:ロック・ハドソン]]
[[no:Rock Hudson]]
[[nn:Rock Hudson]]
[[pl:Rock Hudson]]
[[pt:Rock Hudson]]
[[ro:Rock Hudson]]
[[ru:Рок Хадсон]]
[[sq:Rock Hudson]]
[[simple:Rock Hudson]]
[[sr:Рок Хадсон]]
[[sh:Rock Hudson]]
[[fi:Rock Hudson]]
[[sv:Rock Hudson]]
[[tl:Rock Hudson]]
[[th:ร็อค ฮัดสัน]]
[[tr:Rock Hudson]]
[[zh:洛克·哈德森]]</text>
      <sha1>bydq5b74iiolkbj9bvwjifxlzky5t6r</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
