<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Rodney King</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>168601</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520933405</id>
      <parentid>520933309</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-01T18:35:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>NawlinWiki</username>
        <id>301395</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[Help:Reverting|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/75.133.70.222|75.133.70.222]] ([[User talk:75.133.70.222|talk]]) to last version by ClueBot NG</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="35221">{{Use mdy dates|date=June 2012}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Infobox person
| name = Rodney King
| image = RodneyKingApr2012.jpg
| caption = King in April 2012
| alt =
| birth_name = Rodney Glen King
| birth_date = {{birth date|1965|4|2}}
| birth_place = {{nowrap|[[Sacramento, California]], U.S.}}
| death_date = {{death date and age|2012|6|17|1965|4|2}}&lt;ref name=CNN&gt;{{cite news|title=Rodney King dead at 47|url=http://www.cnn.com/2012/06/17/us/obit-rodney-king/index.html|accessdate=June 17, 2012 |publisher=CNN|date=June 17, 2012|author=CNN Wire Staff}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| death_place = {{nowrap|[[Rialto, California]], U.S.}}
| death_cause = Drowning
| known_for = Victim of [[civil rights]] violation involving [[police brutality]]
| occupation =
| nationality = American
| ethnicity = [[African American]]
| spouse = Crystal Waters (divorced)&lt;br /&gt;Danetta Lyles (divorced)
| partner = Cynthia Kelly (fiancée)&lt;ref name=bbct&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-11245542 | publisher=[[BBC News]] | title=Rodney King to marry juror from LA police beating case | date=September 9, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| children = 3 daughters
| height = {{Convert|6|ft|3|in|abbr=on}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Rodney King Height|url=http://www.talltask.com/Rodney-King-height-8525.html|publisher=Talltask.com|accessdate=June 17, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| criminal_charge = Robbery
| criminal_penalty = 2 years imprisonment
}}
'''Rodney Glen King''' (April 2, 1965&amp;nbsp;– June 17, 2012) was an African-American construction worker who became well known after being brutally beaten with excessive force by [[Los Angeles]] [[Los Angeles Police Department|police officers]] following a high-speed car chase on March 3, 1991. George Holliday, a resident in the nearby area, witnessed the [[police brutality]] and videotaped much of it from the balcony of his nearby apartment.  

The videotaped footage shows seven Los Angeles area officers surrounding King, with several of them striking him repeatedly. Whether or not King was resisting is a contentious point, as police safety guidelines regarding offender resistance may differ from what the public might consider them to be. During the struggle to subdue King, other officers stood by, without seeming to take action to stop King from being struck. A portion of the footage was aired around the world, inflaming public outrage in Los Angeles and other American cities where racial tension was often high. The videotape also increased public sensitivity to, and anger about [[police brutality]], [[racism]], and other [[social inequalities]] throughout the United States.

Nine police officers from the LAPD who took part in the incident were tried in the [[Los Angeles County Superior Court]] for their conduct during the incident, and the case was given a change of venue to [[Simi Valley]], in [[Ventura County]]. Three of the police officers were acquitted, and the jury failed to reach a verdict regarding the fourth police officer. The acquittals are generally considered to have triggered the [[1992 Los Angeles riots]], in which 53 people were killed, and over two thousand were injured. The riots ended after soldiers from the [[United States Army]] [[Army National Guard|National Guard]], along with [[United States Marine Corps|United States Marines]] from nearby [[Camp Pendleton, California]], were called in to assist local authorities and quell the riots.

The [[United States federal government]], through the [[United States District Court for the Central District of California]], stepped in and held a federal trial for [[civil right]]s violations, ending with two of the police officers found guilty, and subsequently imprisoned. The other two officers were acquitted.

During the riots, King appeared on television and offered what would later be his famous plea, &quot;Can we all get along?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1sONfxPCTU0 Video of Rodney King's Plea during the 1992 Los Angeles Riots] From [[YouTube]]. Retrieved June 18, 2012. The line has been often misquoted as, &quot;Can we all ''just'' get along?&quot; King did not use the word &quot;just&quot; in his original statement.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life==
'''Rodney Glen King''' was born in [[Sacramento, California]], on April 2, 1965, the son of Ronald King and Odessa King. King grew up in [[Altadena, California]], one of five children.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Rodney King, L.A. police beating victim, dies|url=http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2012/06/17/MN9T1P3FSA.DTL|accessdate=June 18, 2012|newspaper=San Francisco Chronicle|date=June 18, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Indy&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Profile: An icon, anxious and shy: Rodney King - As he awaits a new trial of the police who beat him, Rodney King has become a hero, a demon, and a gold mine. |author=Phil Reeves |url=http://www.independent.co.uk/opinion/profile-an-icon-anxious-and-shy-rodney-king--as-he-awaits-a-new-trial-of-the-police-who-beat-him-rodney-king-has-become-a-hero-a-demon-and-a-gold-mine-phil-reeves-reports-1474406.html |newspaper=The Independent |date=February 21, 1993 |accessdate=July 1, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; King's father, Ronald King, died in 1984&lt;ref name=&quot;Tel o&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/obituaries/9337577/Rodney-King.html|title=Obits, Rodney King|newspaper=The Telegraph|location=United Kingdom|date=June 17, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; at the age of 42.&lt;ref name=&quot;Indy&quot;/&gt;

In November 1989, King robbed a store in [[Monterey Park, California]]. He threatened to hit the Korean store owner with an iron bar he was carrying, then hit him with a pole. King stole two hundred dollars in cash during the robbery, and was caught, convicted, and sentenced to two years of imprisonment and released after serving one-year of the sentence.&lt;ref name=&quot;Indy&quot;/&gt;

King had three daughters, one by Carmen Simpson when he was a teenager and one by each wife. Both King's marriages, to Crystal Waters and Danetta, ended in divorce.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tel o&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Rodney King|url=http://www.buddytv.com/info/rodney-king-info.aspx|publisher=BuddyTV.com|accessdate=June 17, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Incident==
{{POV-check|section|date=June 2012}}

===High-speed chase===
On the night of March 2, 1991, King and two passengers, Bryant Allen and Freddie Helms, were driving west on the [[Foothill Freeway]] (Interstate 210) in the San Fernando Valley area of Los Angeles. Prior to driving on the Foothill Freeway, the three men had spent the night watching a basketball game and drinking at a friend's house in Los Angeles.&lt;ref name=&quot;jurist.law.pitt.edu&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|author=Linder, Douglas|url=http://jurist.law.pitt.edu/trials24.htm |title=The Rodney King Beating Trials|publisher=[[JURIST]]|date=December 2001|accessdate=December 1, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Five hours after the incident, King's blood-alcohol level was found to be slightly under the legal limit, indicating his [[blood alcohol level]] was at 0.19 while he was driving, which is more than twice the legal driving limit in California.&lt;ref&gt;Cannon. ''Official Negligence'': p. 39.&lt;/ref&gt; At 12:30 am, Officers Tim and Melanie Singer, who were husband-and-wife members of the [[California Highway Patrol]], noticed King's car speeding on the freeway. The officers pursued King, and the pursuit attained high speeds, while King refused to pull over.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.law.umkc.edu/faculty/projects/ftrials/lapd/lapdaccount.html An Account of the Los Angeles Police Officers' Trials(The Rodney King Beating Case)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;law.umkc.edu&quot;&gt;[http://www.law.umkc.edu/faculty/projects/ftrials/lapd/koonvunitedstates.html Koon v. United States 518 U.S. 81 (1996)]&lt;/ref&gt; King would later admit he attempted to outrun the police at dangerously high speeds because a charge of [[driving under the influence]] would violate his parole for a previous robbery conviction.&lt;ref&gt;Cannon. ''Official Negligence'': p. 43.&lt;/ref&gt;

King exited the freeway and the pursuit continued through residential surface streets, at speeds ranging from 55 to 80 miles per hour. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1991/03/18/us/seven-minutes-los-angeles-special-report-videotaped-beating-officers-puts-full.html |title=Seven Minutes in Los Angeles&amp;nbsp;– A special report.; Videotaped Beating by Officers Puts Full Glare on Brutality Issue|work=[[The New York Times]]|date=March 18, 1991|accessdate=March 10, 2009 | first1=Richard W. | last1=Stevenson | first2=Timothy | last2=Egan}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;usnews.com&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|author=Whitman, David|url=http://www.usnews.com/usnews/news/articles/930531/archive_015229.htm|title=The Untold Story of the LA Riot|work=[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]|date=May 23, 1993|accessdate=December 1, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; By this point, several police cars and a police helicopter had joined the pursuit. After approximately eight miles, officers cornered King in his car. The first five LAPD officers to arrive at the scene were [[Stacey Koon]], [[Laurence Powell]], Timothy Wind, Theodore Briseno, and Rolando Solano.

===Confrontation===
[[File:Kingbeating.jpg|thumb|right|Screenshots of King lying down and being approached by [[Los Angeles Police Department|LAPD]] officers]]
Officer Tim Singer ordered King and his two passengers to exit the vehicle and lie face down on the ground. King's two passengers complied and were taken into custody without incident.&lt;ref name=&quot;jurist.law.pitt.edu&quot;/&gt; King remained in the car. When he finally did emerge, he acted bizarrely, giggling, patting the ground, and waving to the police helicopter overhead.&lt;ref name=&quot;usnews.com&quot;/&gt; King then grabbed his buttocks which Officer Melanie Singer took to mean King reaching for a weapon.&lt;ref&gt;Cannon. ''Official Negligence'': p. 27.&lt;/ref&gt; She drew her pistol and pointed it at King, ordering him to lie on the ground. King eventually complied, and Singer approached, gun drawn, preparing to effect an arrest.

{{weasel|date=October 2012}}
Sergeant Stacey Koon cautioned Officer Singer to holster her weapon.{{citation needed|date=October 2012}} LAPD officers are taught not to approach a suspect with a drawn gun, as there is a risk that a suspect may gain control of it if an officer gets too close.&lt;ref&gt;Cannon. ''Official Negligence'': p. 28.&lt;/ref&gt; Koon then ordered the four other LAPD officers at the scene, Briseno, Powell, Solano, and Wind, to subdue and handcuff King using a technique called a &quot;swarm.&quot; This involves multiple officers grabbing a suspect with empty hands, in order to quickly overcome potential resistance. As the officers attempted to restrain King, King resisted, standing to remove Officers Powell and Briseno from his back.  Koon ordered the officers to fall back.{{citation needed|date=October 2012}} The officers later testified that they believed King was under the influence of the dissociative drug [[phencyclidine]] (PCP),&lt;ref&gt;Cannon. ''Official Negligence'': {{Page needed|date=September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; although King's toxicology tested negative for the drug.&lt;ref&gt;Cannon, Lou (March 16, 1993). &quot;[http://tech.mit.edu/V113/N14/king.14w.html Prosecution Rests Case in Rodney King Beating]&quot;. ''[[The Washington Post]]''. Retrieved 2009-12-01.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Use of the taser===
After Koon  ordered officers to stand clear of King, King stood, unresponsive to Koon's commands to cease resisting. Koon discharged a [[Taser]] into King's back, and King momentarily fell to his knees. King then stood again, and yelled for approximately five seconds.&lt;ref name=&quot;report 91, p6&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.parc.info/client_files/Special%20Reports/1%20-%20Chistopher%20Commision.pdf Chapter 1: The Rodney King Beating]&quot;. ''Report of the Independent Commission on the Los Angeles Police Department'': p. 6. 1991.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Beating with batons: events on the Holliday video===
[[Image:R King beating.png|thumb|Screenshot of King being beaten by [[Los Angeles Police Department|LAPD]] officers]]
The point at which Rodney King was struck by Koon's Taser is the approximate start of the George Holliday videotape of the incident. In the tape, King is seen on the ground. He rises and moves toward Powell.&lt;ref name=&quot;report 91, p6&quot;/&gt; Taser wire can be seen in King's body. As King moves forward, Officer Powell strikes King with his [[baton (law enforcement)|baton]]. The blow strikes King in the head, and King is knocked to the ground.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.parc.info/client_files/Special%20Reports/1%20-%20Chistopher%20Commision.pdf Chapter 1: The Rodney King Beating]&quot;. ''Report of the Independent Commission on the Los Angeles Police Department'': p. 7. 1991. &quot;The blow hit King's head, and he went down immediately.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Powell strikes King several more times with his baton. Briseno moves in, attempting to stop Powell from striking again, and Powell stands back. Koon reportedly said, &quot;That's enough.&quot; Rodney King then rises again, to his knees, Powell and Wind are then seen hitting King with their batons.&lt;ref name=&quot;report 91, p7&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.parc.info/client_files/Special%20Reports/1%20-%20Chistopher%20Commision.pdf Chapter 1: The Rodney King Beating]&quot;. ''Report of the Independent Commission on the Los Angeles Police Department'': p. 7. 1991.&lt;/ref&gt;

Koon acknowledged ordering the continued use of batons, directing Powell and Wind to strike King with &quot;power strokes.&quot; According to Koon, Powell and Wind used &quot;bursts of power strokes, then backed off.&quot; In the videotape, King continues to try and stand again. Koon orders the officers to &quot;hit his joints, hit the wrists, hit his elbows, hit his knees, hit his ankles.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;report 91, p7&quot;/&gt; After a recorded 56 baton blows and six kicks, several officers again &quot;swarm&quot; King, and place him in handcuffs and cordcuffs, restraining his arms and legs. King is dragged on his abdomen to the side of the road to await the arrival of emergency medical rescue.&lt;ref name=&quot;report 91, p7&quot;/&gt;

George Holliday's videotape of the incident was shot from his apartment near the intersection of Foothill Blvd and Osborne St. in [[Lake View Terrace]]. He contacted the police about his videotape of the incident but was ignored.{{citation needed|date=October 2012}} He then went to [[KTLA]] television with his videotape, which broadcast it in its entirety.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=The Other Beating: Fifteen years after his video of Rodney King reached the world, George Holliday looks back on how that night has hurt him |author=Michael Goldstein |url=http://articles.latimes.com/2006/feb/19/magazine/tm-holiday8 |newspaper=Los Angeles Times |date=February 19, 2006 |accessdate=July 1, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The footage became an instant media sensation. Portions of it were aired numerous times, and it &quot;turned what would otherwise have been a violent, but soon forgotten, encounter between the Los Angeles police and an uncooperative suspect into one of the most widely watched and discussed incidents of its kind.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://law2.umkc.edu/faculty/projects/ftrials/lapd/kingvideo.html|title=The Holliday Videotape, George Holliday Video of King Beating}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Holliday video of the Rodney King arrest is a fairly early example of modern [[sousveillance]], where private citizens, assisted by increasingly sophisticated, affordable video equipment, record significant, sometimes historical events. Several &quot;[[copwatch]]&quot; organizations subsequently appeared throughout the United States, purportedly to safeguard against police abuse, including an umbrella group, October 22 Coalition to Stop Police Brutality.&lt;ref&gt;&lt;!--{{cite web |url=http://www.pbs.org/speaktruthtopower/issue_police.html |title=Police Brutality |work=Speak Truth to Power |publisher=pbs.org |accessdate=July 1, 2012}}--&gt;[http://www.pbs.org/speaktruthtopower/issue_police.html PBS.org] and the ACLU [http://www.aclu.org/police/gen/14614pub19971201.html#credits] draw connections between the event and the subsequent activities of many organizations.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Post-arrest events==
King was taken to Pacifica Hospital immediately after his arrest, where he was shown to have suffered a fractured [[zygomatic arch|facial bone]], a broken right ankle, and numerous bruises and lacerations.&lt;ref&gt;Cannon. ''Official Negligence'': p. 205.&lt;/ref&gt; In a negligence claim filed with the city, King alleged he had suffered &quot;11 skull fractures, permanent brain damage, broken [bones and teeth], kidney damage [and] emotional and physical trauma&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;report 91, p8&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.parc.info/client_files/Special%20Reports/1%20-%20Chistopher%20Commision.pdf Chapter 1: The Rodney King Beating]&quot;. ''Report of the Independent Commission on the Los Angeles Police Department'': p. 8. 1991.&lt;/ref&gt; Blood and urine samples taken from King five hours after his arrest showed that he would be intoxicated under California law. The tests also showed traces of marijuana (26&amp;nbsp;ng/ml), but no indication of any other illegal drug.&lt;ref name=&quot;report 91, p8&quot;/&gt; Pacifica Hospital nurses reported that the officers who accompanied King (including Wind) openly joked and bragged about the number of times King had been hit.&lt;ref name=&quot;report 91, p15&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.parc.info/client_files/Special%20Reports/1%20-%20Chistopher%20Commision.pdf Chapter 1: The Rodney King Beating]&quot;. ''Report of the Independent Commission on the Los Angeles Police Department'': p. 15. 1991.&lt;/ref&gt; King sued the city, settling for $3.8 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Rodney King Is Arrested After a Fight at His Home |agency=Associated Press |url=http://articles.latimes.com/2005/sep/30/local/me-king30 |newspaper=Los Angeles Times |date=September 30, 2005 |accessdate=July 1, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==The Officers==
The Los Angeles district attorney charged officers Koon, Powell, Briseno and Wind with use of excessive force. Sergeant Koon, while he did not strike King, only having deployed the Taser, was, as the supervisory officer at the scene, charged with, &quot;willfully permitting and failing to take action to stop the unlawful assault.&quot;

The [[California Court of Appeals]] removed the initial judge, Bernard Kamins, after it was proved Kamins told prosecutors, &quot;You can trust me.&quot; The Court also granted a [[change of venue]] to [[Simi Valley, California|Simi Valley]] in neighboring [[Ventura County, California|Ventura County]], citing potential contamination due to saturated media coverage.

Though few people at first considered race an important factor in the case, including Rodney King's attorney, Steven Lerman, the sensitizing effect of the Holliday videotape was at the time stirring deep resentment in Los Angeles, as well as other major cities in the United States. The officers' jury consisted of Ventura County residents: ten [[White American|white]]; one [[Hispanic and Latino Americans|Latino]]; one [[Asian American|Asian]]. Prosecutor Terry White was [[African American]]. On April 29, 1992, the jury acquitted three of the officers, but [[hung jury|could not agree]] on one of the charges against Powell.&lt;ref name=&quot;jurist.law.pitt.edu&quot;/&gt;

[[Mayor of Los Angeles|Los Angeles Mayor]] [[Tom Bradley (American politician)|Tom Bradley]] said, &quot;The jury's verdict will not blind us to what we saw on that videotape. The men who beat Rodney King do not deserve to wear the uniform of the L.A.P.D.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Mydans, Seth (April 30, 1992). &quot;[http://www.nytimes.com/books/98/02/08/home/rodney-verdict.html The Police Verdict; Los Angeles Policemen Acquitted in Taped Beating]&quot;. ''[[The New York Times]]''. Retrieved 2009-12-01.&lt;/ref&gt; [[President of the United States|President]] [[George H. W. Bush]] said, &quot;Viewed from outside the trial, it was hard to understand how the verdict could possibly square with the video. Those civil rights leaders with whom I met were stunned. And so was I and so was Barbara and so were my kids.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://www.amazon.com/Media-Matters-Race-Gender-Politics/dp/0816624631|last=Fiske|first=John|title=Media Matters: Race and Gender in U.S. Politics (paperback)|page=188|publisher=Univ Of Minnesota Press; Revised edition |quote=Bush on LA, extracts from his speech to the nation|date=March 1, 1996| ISBN=9780816624638|format=Paperback}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Los Angeles riots and the aftermath==
{{Main|1992 Los Angeles riots}}
The acquittals are considered to have triggered the [[Los Angeles riots of 1992]]. By the time the police, the [[United States Army|U.S. Army]], [[United States Marine Corps|Marines]] and [[National Guard of the United States|National Guard]] restored order, the riots had caused 53 deaths, 2,383 injuries, more than 7,000 fires, damage to 3,100 businesses, and nearly $1 billion in financial losses. Smaller riots occurred in other cities such as [[San Francisco]], [[Las Vegas, Nevada|Las Vegas]] in neighboring [[Nevada]] and as far east as [[Atlanta]], [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]]. A minor riot erupted on Yonge St., in [[Toronto]], [[Ontario]], [[Canada]], as a result of the acquittals.

==Federal trial of officers==
After the riots, the [[United States Department of Justice]] reinstated the investigation and obtained an indictment of violations of federal civil rights against the four officers in the United States District Court for the Central District of California. The federal trial focused more on the evidence as to the training of officers instead of just relying on the videotape of the incident. On March 9 of the 1993 trial, King took the witness stand and described to the jury the events as he remembered them.&lt;ref name=March9&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1993/03/10/us/rodney-king-testifies-on-beating-i-was-just-trying-to-stay-alive.html | title=Rodney King Testifies on Beating: 'I Was Just Trying to Stay Alive' | work=[[The New York Times]] | date=March 10, 2003 | last=Mydans | first=Seth | accessdate=March 5, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The jury found Officer [[Laurence Powell]] and Sergeant [[Stacey Koon]] guilty, and they were subsequently sentenced to 32 months in prison, while Timothy Wind and Theodore Briseno were acquitted of all charges.&lt;ref name=&quot;jurist.law.pitt.edu&quot;/&gt;

==Later life==
[[File:CynthiaKelleyRodneyKingApr2012.jpg|thumb|right|King with fiancée Cynthia Kelly in April 2012. Kelly was one of the jurors in King's civil suit against the city of Los Angeles when he was awarded $3.8 million.]]

King successfully sued the city of Los Angeles in a federal civil rights case. The court jury awarded King $3.8 million and awarded King's attorneys $1.7 million in statutory attorney’s fees, which were in addition to the $3.8 million. King's lawyer, Stephen Lerman, distributed the attorney’s fees to the lawyers who worked on King's behalf. King then sued Lerman for legal malpractice claiming King was entitled to those attorney’s fees instead of his lawyers. Lerman successfully defended himself in the action by having the case dismissed on summary judgment, which was affirmed on appeal.

King continued to get into trouble after the 1991 incident. On August 21, 1993, he crashed his car into a block wall in [[downtown Los Angeles]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Rodney King's Wife Files Petition for Divorce |url=http://articles.latimes.com/1995-11-29/local/me-8370_1_crystal-king |newspaper=Los Angeles Times|date=November 29, 1995 |accessdate=July 1, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was convicted of driving under the influence of alcohol, fined, entered an alcohol rehabilitation program and was placed on probation. In July 1995, he was arrested by [[Alhambra, California|Alhambra]] police, after hitting his wife with his car, knocking her to the ground. He was sentenced to 90 days in jail after being convicted of hit and run.&lt;ref name=&quot;me-king30&quot;/&gt; King invested a portion of his settlement in a record label, Straight Alta-Pazz Records, which went under.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.time.com/time/specials/2007/la_riot/article/0,28804,1614117_1614084_1614831,00.html|title=The L.A. Riots: 15 Years After Rodney King|author=Madison Gray|year=2007|month=May|work=Time}}&lt;/ref&gt; On August 27, 2003, King was arrested again for speeding and running a red light while under the influence of alcohol. He failed to yield to police officers and slammed his vehicle into a house, breaking his pelvis.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.cnn.com/2003/US/West/04/15/rodney.king.ap/|title=Rodney King slams SUV into house, breaks pelvis|date=April 16, 2003 |publisher=[[CNN]] |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20071211205000/http://www.cnn.com/2003/US/West/04/15/rodney.king.ap/|archivedate=December 11, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; On November 29, 2007, while riding home on his bicycle, King was shot in the face, arms, and back with pellets from a shotgun. He reported that it was done by a man and a woman who demanded his bicycle and shot him when he rode away.&lt;ref name=&quot;me-king30&quot;&gt;Reston, Maeve (November 30, 2007). &quot;[http://articles.latimes.com/2007/nov/30/local/me-king30 Rodney King shot while riding bike]&quot;. ''[[Los Angeles Times]]''. Retrieved 2009-12-01.&lt;/ref&gt; Police described the wounds as looking like they came from birdshot, but said King offered few details about the suspects.

In May 2008, King checked into the Pasadena Recovery Center in [[Pasadena, California]], where he filmed as a cast member of the second season of ''[[Celebrity Rehab with Dr. Drew]]'', which premiered in October 2008. Dr. [[Drew Pinsky]], who runs the facility, showed concern for King's lifestyle and said that King would die unless his addiction were treated.&lt;ref&gt;''[[TV Guide]]'': page 8. June 23, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; He also appeared on ''[[Sober House]]'', a ''Celebrity Rehab'' spin-off focusing on a [[sober living environment]], which aired in early 2009. Both shows filmed King's quest not only to achieve sobriety, but to reestablish a relationship with his family, which had been severely damaged due to his drinking and law-breaking.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.realityblurred.com/realitytv/archives/celebrity_rehab/2008_Dec_19_sober_house_cast Sober House Will Follow Celebrity Rehab Cast, Andy Dick in Sober Living]&quot;. RealityBlurred.com. December 19, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

During his time on ''Celebrity Rehab'' and ''Sober House'', King worked on his addiction and on the lingering trauma of the beating. He and Pinsky retraced his path from the night of his beating, eventually reaching the spot where it happened, the site of the [[Children's Museum of Los Angeles]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Thompson |first=Elise |title=Rodney King Forgives Officers Who Beat Him&amp;nbsp;— LAist |url=http://laist.com/2009/02/22/rodney_king_forgives.php |accessdate=December 30, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

King won&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.bittenandbound.com/2009/09/12/rodney-king-fight-results/ Rodney King Fight Results]&quot;. BittenAndBound.com. September 12, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; a celebrity boxing match against ex-[[Chester, Pennsylvania|Chester City]] ([[Delaware County, Pennsylvania|Delaware County]], [[Pennsylvania]]) police officer Simon Aouad on Friday, September 11, 2009, at the Ramada Philadelphia Airport in [[Tinicum Township, Delaware County, Pennsylvania|Essington, Pennsylvania]].&lt;ref&gt;Stamm, Dan (August 19, 2009). &quot;[http://www.nbcphiladelphia.com/news/sports/Rodney-King-Takes-on-Former-Cop-53728342.html No Plan to 'Get Along' When Rodney King Takes on Former Cop]&quot;. NBC Philadelphia. Retrieved 2009-12-01.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009, King and other ''Celebrity Rehab'' alumni appeared as panel speakers to a new group of addicts at the Pasadena Recovery Center, marking 11 months of sobriety for him. His appearance was aired in the third season episode &quot;Triggers&quot;.&lt;ref name=Triggers&gt;[http://www.vh1.com/video/celebrity-rehab-3/full-episodes/triggers/1631736/playlist.jhtml ''[[Celebrity Rehab with Dr. Drew]]'' Episode 3.6 (&quot;Triggers&quot;) [[VH1]]; February 11, 2010]&lt;/ref&gt;

In surprising news on September 9, 2010, it was confirmed that King was going to marry Cynthia Kelley, who had been a juror in the civil suit King brought against the [[Los Angeles|City of Los Angeles]] when he was awarded $3.8 million.&lt;ref name=bbct /&gt;

On March 3, 2011, the 20th anniversary of the beating, King was stopped by LAPD for driving erratically. He was issued a citation for driving with an expired license.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/lanow/2011/03/rodney-king-stopped.html | work=[[Los Angeles Times]] | title=Rodney King stopped after traffic violation, police say | date=March 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pasadenastarnews.com/news/ci_17540843 Rodney King once again runs afoul of the law, cited for expired license in Arcadia - Pasadena Star-News]{{Dead link|date=June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-1362952/Rodney-King-arrested-skipping-red-light-20-years-LA-riots.html | location=London | work=Daily Mail | first=Richard | last=Hartley-Parkinson | title=Rodney King pulled over by police almost 20 years to the day since his arrest and /CRIME/07/12/california.rodney.king.arrest/index.html | publisher=CNN | date=July 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; This arrest led to his February 2012 misdemeanor conviction for reckless driving.&lt;ref name=stanwilson&gt;{{cite news |title=Rodney King pleads for calm in Trayvon Martin case |first=Stan |last=Wilson |work=CNN |date=April 12, 2012 |url=http://www.cnn.com/2012/04/12/us/trayvon-case-rodney-king/?hpt=hp_t1 |accessdate=April 12, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On April 12, 2012, King released a statement to the media regarding the [[Trayvon Martin]] shooting. King said he was &quot;grieving for Trayvon Martin&quot; and stated how the scream on the audio of [[George Zimmerman]]'s 911 call reminded him of his own screaming during his beating by the LAPD.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/lanow/2012/04/rodney-king-speaks-out-on-trayvon-martin.html | work=[[Los Angeles Times]] | title=Rodney King: &quot;I'm grieving for Trayvon Martin&quot; | date=April 12, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The BBC quoted King commenting on his legacy. &quot;Some people feel like I'm some kind of hero,&quot;.
&quot;Others hate me. They say I deserved it. Other people, I can hear them mocking me for when I called for an end to the destruction, like I'm a fool for believing in peace.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-18662564 | work=BBC News | title=Los Angeles riots: Rodney King funeral held | date=July 1, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Death ==
On June 17, 2012, King's fiancée Cynthia Kelly found him lying at the bottom of his [[swimming pool]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url= http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-201_162-57454782/rodney-king-found-dead/| title= Rodney King found dead | date=June 17, 2012|work=CBS News}}&lt;/ref&gt; Police in [[Rialto, California|Rialto]] received a [[9-1-1|911]] call from Kelly at about 5:25 a.m. [[Pacific Time Zone|(PT)]].&lt;ref name=&quot;911 call&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=911 call reveals frantic moments, fiancee’s pleas after finding Rodney King submerged in pool |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/national/rodney-king-autopsy-completed-as-death-investigation-continues-results-to-take-weeks/2012/06/18/gJQAce7UmV_story.html |accessdate=June 20, 2012|newspaper=[[The Washington Post]] |date=June 18, 2012|agency=AP |deadurl=yes}} {{Dead link|date=August 2012|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=June 17, 2012|title=Police Beating Victim Who Asked 'Can We All Get Along?'|author=Jennifer Medina | work = [[The New York Times]] |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2012/06/18/us/rodney-king-whose-beating-led-to-la-riots-dead-at-47.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; Responding officers found King at the bottom of the pool, removed him, and attempted to revive him. He was transferred by ambulance to [[Arrowhead Regional Medical Center]] in [[Colton, California]]. King was pronounced dead at the hospital at 6:11 a.m. The Rialto Police Department began a standard drowning investigation and stated that there did not appear to be any foul play. 
On August 23, 2012, King's autopsy results were released. It stated he died of accidental drowning, although alcohol, cocaine, and marijuana were found in his blood and were contributing factors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Wilson|first=Stan|title=Autopsy attributes Rodney King's death to drowning|url=http://www.cnn.com/2012/08/23/us/rodney-king-autopsy/index.html|publisher=CNN|accessdate=23 August 2012|date=August 23, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Los Angeles|African American}}
*[[List of cases of police brutality in the United States]]
*[[Death of Kelly Thomas]]
{{clear}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
* The &quot;Rodney King Beating video&quot; is under copyright. For authorization contact www.rodneykingvideo.com.ar
*{{Cite book|author=Cannon, Lou |title=Official Negligence: How Rodney King and the riots changed Los Angeles and the LAPD |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=C0tWztU6f0sC |publisher=Westview Press |location=Boulder, Colo. |year=1999 |isbn=9780813337258 |oclc=42852365}}

== Further reading ==
* {{cite book |title=The Riot Within: My Journey from Rebellion to Redemption |last=King |first=Rodney |coauthors=with Lawrence J. Spagnola |year=2012 |publisher=HarperOne |location=New York |isbn=9780062194435 |oclc=761856270}} King's autobiography.
* {{cite book |title=Presumed Guilty: The Tragedy of the Rodney King Affair |last=Koon |first=Stacey C. |authorlink=Stacey Koon |coauthors=with Robert Deitz |year=1992 |publisher=Regnery Gateway |location=Washington, D.C. |isbn=9780895265074 |oclc=26553041}}

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
*{{IMDb name|0455219}}
* {{NYTtopic|people/k/rodney_glen_king|Rodney King}}
* {{Guardiantopic|world/rodney-king|Rodney King}}
* [http://law2.umkc.edu/faculty/projects/ftrials/lapd/kingarrests.html Rodney King's Arrest Record]
* [http://topics.cnn.com/topics/rodney_king Rodney King] news and commentary at [[CNN]]
* [http://laist.com/2009/04/29/meet_rodney_king.php Rodney King: 17 Years After The Riots&quot;], Laist.com
* Kavanagh, Jim. &quot;[http://www.cnn.com/2011/US/03/03/rodney.king.20.years.later/index.html Rodney King, 20 years later].&quot; [[CNN]]. March 3, 2011.
* {{Find a Grave|92047665}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
| NAME              = King, Rodney Glen
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES = King, Rodney
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = Victim of police brutality
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1965-04-02
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = Sacramento, California, United States
| DATE OF DEATH     = 2012-06-17
| PLACE OF DEATH    = Rialto, California, United States
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:King, Rodney}}
[[Category:1965 births]]
[[Category:2012 deaths]]
[[Category:Accidental deaths in California]]
[[Category:African-American people]]
[[Category:American people convicted of robbery]]
[[Category:Citizen journalism]]
[[Category:Deaths by drowning]]
[[Category:Drug-related deaths in California]]
[[Category:History of Los Angeles, California]]
[[Category:Los Angeles Police Department]]
[[Category:Participants in American reality television series]]
[[Category:People from Rialto, California]]
[[Category:People from Sacramento, California]]
[[Category:People self-identifying as alcoholics]]
[[Category:Victims of police brutality]]
[[Category:American construction businesspeople]]
[[Category:People from Altadena, California]]

[[ar:رودني كينغ]]
[[de:Rodney King]]
[[es:Rodney King]]
[[eo:Rodney King]]
[[fr:Rodney King]]
[[is:Rodney King]]
[[it:Rodney King]]
[[nl:Rodney King]]
[[no:Rodney King]]
[[pl:Rodney King]]
[[pt:Rodney King]]
[[ro:Rodney King]]
[[ru:Кинг, Родни]]
[[simple:Rodney King]]
[[fi:Rodney King]]
[[sv:Rodney King]]
[[tr:Rodney King]]
[[yi:ראדני קינג]]
[[zh:罗德尼·金]]</text>
      <sha1>0xo26st19zyuuy3wzko4a9i85yn77ua</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
