<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Salvador Dalí</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>40112</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521089796</id>
      <parentid>521062697</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T18:37:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Elen of the Roads</username>
        <id>7084983</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/216.73.65.68|216.73.65.68]] ([[User talk:216.73.65.68|talk]]): Unexplained deletion. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="83853">{{Use mdy dates|date=October 2011}}
{{Spanish name|Dalí|Domènech}}
{{Infobox artist
| name        = Salvador Dalí
| image       = Salvador Dalí 1939.jpg
| caption     = Salvador Dalí photographed by [[Carl Van Vechten]] on November 29, 1939
| birth_name  = Salvador Domingo Felipe Jacinto Dalí i Domènech
| birth_date  = {{birth date|1904|5|11|mf=y}}
| birth_place = [[Figueres]], Catalonia
| death_date  = {{death date and age|1989|01|23|1904|05|11}}
| death_place = [[Figueres]], Catalonia
| nationality = Spanish
| religion    = Roman Catholic
| field       = Painting, Drawing, Photography, Sculpture, Writing, Film
| training    = [[Real Academia de Bellas Artes de San Fernando|San Fernando School of Fine Arts]], Madrid
| movement    = [[Cubism]], [[Dada]], [[Surrealism]]
| works       = ''[[The Persistence of Memory]]'' (1931)&lt;br /&gt;''Face of Mae West Which May Be Used as an Apartment'', (1935)&lt;br /&gt;''[[Soft Construction with Boiled Beans (Premonition of Civil War)]]'' (1936)&lt;br /&gt;''[[Swans Reflecting Elephants]]'' (1937)&lt;br /&gt;''Ballerina in a Death's Head'' (1939)&lt;br /&gt;''[[Dream Caused by the Flight of a Bee Around a Pomegranate a Second Before Awakening]]'' (1944) &lt;br /&gt;''The Temptation of St. Anthony'' (1946)&lt;br /&gt;''[[Galatea of the Spheres]]'' (1952)&lt;br /&gt;''[[Crucifixion (Corpus Hypercubus)]]'' (1954)
| spouse      = [[Gala Dalí]] (Elena Ivanovna Diakonova)
| patrons     =
| awards      =
}}
'''Salvador Domingo Felipe Jacinto Dalí i Domènech, 1st Marqués de Dalí de Pubol''' (May 11, 1904{{spaced ndash}}January 23, 1989), known as '''Salvador Dalí''' ({{IPA-ca|səɫβəˈðo ðəˈɫi}}), was a prominent [[Spain|Spanish]] [[surrealist]] painter born in [[Figueres]], [[Spain]].

Dalí was a skilled [[Technical drawing|draftsman]], best known for the striking and bizarre images in his [[surrealism|surrealist]] work. His [[painterly]] skills are often attributed to the influence of [[Renaissance]] masters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.artcyclopedia.com/feature-2005-03.html |title=Phelan, Joseph, ',The Salvador Dalí Show |publisher=Artcyclopedia.com |accessdate=August 22, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Dali&gt;Dalí, Salvador. (2000) ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=on_YUj9IP8UC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_ge_summary_r&amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Dalí: 16 Art Stickers]'', Courier Dover Publications. ISBN 0-486-41074-9.&lt;/ref&gt; His best-known work, ''[[The Persistence of Memory]]'', was completed in 1931. Dalí's expansive artistic repertoire included film, sculpture, and photography, in collaboration with a range of artists in a variety of media.

Dalí attributed his &quot;love of everything that is gilded and excessive, my passion for luxury and my love of oriental clothes&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Ian Gibson | title=The Shameful Life of Salvador Dalí | year=1997 | publisher=W. W. Norton &amp; Company | url=http://www.nytimes.com/books/first/g/gibson-dali.html }} Gibson found out that &quot;Dalí&quot; (and its many variants) is an extremely common surname in Arab countries like [[Morocco]], Tunisia, [[Algeria]] or [[Egypt]]. On the other hand, also according to Gibson, Dalí's mother family, the Domènech of Barcelona, had Jewish roots.&lt;/ref&gt; to a self-styled &quot;Arab lineage&quot;, claiming that his ancestors were descended from the [[Moors]].

Dalí was highly imaginative, and also enjoyed indulging in unusual and grandiose behavior. His eccentric manner and attention-grabbing public actions sometimes drew more attention than his artwork, to the dismay of those who held his work in high esteem, and to the irritation of his critics.&lt;ref&gt;Saladyga, Stephen Francis. [http://purple.niagara.edu/jlittle/lamplighter/saladyga.htm &quot;The Mindset of Salvador Dalí&quot;]. ''lamplighter (Niagara University)''. Vol. 1 No. 3, Summer 2006. Retrieved July 22, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Biography==
===Early life===
Salvador Domingo Felipe Jacinto Dalí i Domènech was born on May 11, 1904, at 8:45&amp;nbsp;am GMT&lt;ref&gt;Birth certificate and {{cite web | url=http://www.salvadordalimuseum.org/history/biography.html | title=Dalí Biography | publisher=Dalí Museum | work=Dalí Museum | accessdate=August 24, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; in the town of [[Figueres]], in the [[Empordà]] [[Comarques of Catalonia|region]], close to the French border in [[Catalonia]], Spain.&lt;ref&gt;Dalí, ''[[The Secret Life of Salvador Dalí]]'', 1948, London: Vision Press, p.33&lt;/ref&gt; Dalí's [[Necronym|older brother, also named Salvador]] (born October 12, 1901), [[Necronym|had died]] of [[gastroenteritis]] nine months earlier, on August 1, 1903. His father, Salvador Dalí i Cusí, was a middle-class lawyer and notary&lt;ref name=Llongueras&gt;Llongueras, Lluís. (2004) ''Dalí'', Ediciones B – Mexico. ISBN 84-666-1343-9.&lt;/ref&gt; whose strict disciplinary approach was tempered by his wife, Felipa Domenech Ferrés, who encouraged her son's artistic endeavors.&lt;ref name=Rojas&gt;Rojas, Carlos. ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=MWF5s2yfFqwC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_ge_summary_r&amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Salvador Dalí, Or the Art of Spitting on Your Mother's Portrait]'', Penn State Press (1993). ISBN 0-271-00842-3.&lt;/ref&gt; When he was five, Dalí was taken to his brother's grave and told by his parents that he was his brother's reincarnation,&lt;ref name=sina&gt;[http://edu.sina.com.cn/en/2004-06-17/22707.html Salvador Dalí]. ''[[SINA.com]]''. Retrieved on July 31, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; a concept which he came to believe.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.astrodatabank.com/NM/DaliSalvador.htm Salvador Dalí biography] on astrodatabank.com. Retrieved September 30, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Of his brother, Dalí said, ''&quot;...[we] resembled each other like two drops of water, but we had different reflections.&quot;''&lt;ref name=&quot;Dalí, Secret Life, p.2&quot;&gt;Dalí, Secret Life, p.2&lt;/ref&gt; He ''&quot;was probably a first version of myself but conceived too much in the absolute.&quot;''&lt;ref name=&quot;Dalí, Secret Life, p.2&quot;/&gt; Images of his long-dead brother would reappear embedded in his later works, including ''Portrait of My Dead Brother'' (1963).

Dalí also had a sister, Ana María, who was three years younger.&lt;ref name=Llongueras /&gt; In 1949, she published a book about her brother, ''Dalí As Seen By His Sister''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.artelino.com/articles/dali.asp|title=Dalí Biography 1904–1989 – Part Two|publisher=artelino.com|accessdate =September 30, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; His childhood friends included future [[FC Barcelona]] footballers [[Emilio Sagi Liñán|Sagibarba]] and [[Josep Samitier]]. During holidays at the Catalan resort of [[Cadaqués]], the trio played  [[Association football|football]] together.

Dalí attended [[art school|drawing school]]. In 1916, Dalí also discovered modern painting on a summer vacation trip to [[Cadaqués]] with the family of [[Ramon Pichot]], a local artist who made regular trips to Paris.&lt;ref name=Llongueras /&gt; The next year, Dalí's father organized an exhibition of his charcoal drawings in their family home. He had his first public exhibition at the Municipal Theater in Figueres in 1919.

In February 1921, Dalí's mother died of [[breast cancer]]. Dalí was 16 years old; he later said his mother's death ''&quot;was the greatest blow I had experienced in my life. I worshipped her... I could not resign myself to the loss of a being on whom I counted to make invisible the unavoidable blemishes of my soul.&quot;''&lt;ref&gt;Dalí, Secret Life, pp.152–153&lt;/ref&gt; After her death, Dalí's father married his deceased wife's sister. Dalí did not resent this marriage, because he had a great love and respect for his aunt.&lt;ref name=Llongueras /&gt;

===Madrid and Paris===
[[Image:Man Ray Salvador Dali.jpg|thumb|left|Wild-eyed antics of Dalí (left) and fellow [[surrealism|surrealist]] artist [[Man Ray]] in Paris on June 16, 1934.]]
In 1922, Dalí moved into the [[Residencia de Estudiantes]] (Students' Residence) in [[Madrid]]&lt;ref name=Llongueras /&gt; and studied at the Academia de San Fernando (School of Fine Arts). A lean 1.72 m (5&amp;nbsp;ft. 7¾ in.) tall,&lt;ref&gt;As listed in [http://www.gaudiclub.com/esp/e_links/dali/2004mar18_1.asp his prison record of 1924], aged 20. However, his hairdresser and biographer, Luis Llongueras, states Dalí was {{height|m=1.74|precision=4}} tall.&lt;/ref&gt; Dalí already drew attention as an eccentric and [[dandy]]. He had long hair and [[sideburn]]s, coat, stockings, and [[knee-breeches]] in the style of English [[artistic dress movement|aesthetes]] of the late 19th century.

At the Residencia, he became close friends with (among others) [[Pepín Bello]], [[Luis Buñuel]], and [[Federico García Lorca]]. The friendship with Lorca had a strong element of mutual passion,&lt;ref&gt;For more in-depth information about the Lorca-Dalí connection see ''Lorca-Dalí: el amor que no pudo ser'' and ''The Shameful Life of Salvador Dalí'', both by [[Ian Gibson (author)|Ian Gibson]].&lt;/ref&gt; but Dalí rejected the poet's sexual advances.&lt;ref name=&quot;conversations&quot;&gt;Bosquet, Alain, ''[http://www.ubu.com/historical/dali/dali_conversations.pdf Conversations with Dalí]'', 1969. p. 19–20. (PDF format) (of García Lorca) 'S.D.:He was homosexual, as everyone knows, and madly in love with me. He tried to screw me twice .... I was extremely annoyed, because I wasn’t homosexual, and I wasn’t interested in giving in. Besides, it hurts. So nothing came of it. But I felt awfully flattered vis-à-vis the prestige. Deep down I felt that he was a great poet and that I owe him a tiny bit of the Divine Dalí's asshole. He eventually bagged a young girl, and she replaced me in the sacrifice. Failing to get me to put my ass at his disposal, he swore that the girl's sacrifice was matched by his own: it was the first time he had ever slept with a woman.'&lt;/ref&gt;

However it was his paintings, in which he experimented with [[Cubism]], that earned him the most attention from his fellow students. At the time of these early works, Dalí probably did not completely understand the Cubist movement{{whom?|date=July 2012}}. His only information on Cubist art came from magazine articles and a catalog given to him by Pichot, since there were no Cubist artists in Madrid at the time. In 1924, the still-unknown Salvador Dalí illustrated a book for the first time. It was a publication of the [[Catalan language|Catalan]] poem ''Les bruixes de [[Llers]]'' (&quot;The Witches of Llers&quot;) by his friend and schoolmate, poet [[Carles Fages de Climent]]. Dalí also experimented with [[Dada]], which influenced his work throughout his life.

Dalí was expelled from the Academia in 1926, shortly before his final exams when he was accused of starting an unrest.&lt;ref name=olga&gt;[http://www.abcgallery.com/D/dali/dalibio.html Salvador Dalí: Olga's Gallery]. Retrieved on July 22, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; His mastery of painting skills was evidenced by his realistic ''[[The Basket of Bread]]'', painted in 1926.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dali-gallery.com/html/galleries/painting05.htm |title=Paintings Gallery No.&amp;nbsp;5 |publisher=Dali-gallery.com |accessdate=August 22, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; That same year, he made his first visit to Paris, where he met [[Pablo Picasso]], whom the young Dalí revered. Picasso had already heard favorable reports about Dalí from [[Joan Miró]]. As he developed his own style over the next few years, Dalí made a number of works heavily influenced by Picasso and Miró.

Some trends in Dalí's work that would continue throughout his life were already evident in the 1920s. Dalí devoured influences from many styles of art, ranging from the most academically classic, to the most cutting-edge [[avant garde]].&lt;ref&gt;Hodge, Nicola, and Libby Anson. ''The A–Z of Art: The World's Greatest and Most Popular Artists and Their Works''. California: Thunder Bay Press, 1996. [https://ucmshare.ucmerced.edu/docushare/dsweb/Get/Document-94961/Dali+Salvador.doc Online citation].&lt;/ref&gt; His classical influences included [[Raphael]], [[Bronzino]], [[Francisco de Zurbarán]], [[Vermeer]], and [[Diego Velázquez|Velázquez]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.artcyclopedia.com/feature-2005-03.html |title=Phelan, Joseph |publisher=Artcyclopedia.com |accessdate=August 22, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; He used both classical and modernist techniques, sometimes in separate works, and sometimes combined. Exhibitions of his works in [[Barcelona]] attracted much attention along with mixtures of praise and puzzled debate from critics.

Dalí grew a flamboyant [[moustache]], influenced by 17th-century Spanish master painter [[Diego Velázquez]]. The moustache became an iconic trademark of his appearance for the rest of his life.

===1929 to World War II===
In 1929, Dalí collaborated with surrealist film director [[Luis Buñuel]] on the short film {{lang|fr|''[[Un Chien Andalou]]''}} (''An Andalusian Dog''). His main contribution was to help Buñuel write the script for the film. Dalí later claimed to have also played a significant role in the filming of the project, but this is not substantiated by contemporary accounts.&lt;ref&gt;Koller, Michael. [http://archive.sensesofcinema.com/contents/cteq/01/12/chien.html {{lang|fr|''Un Chien Andalou''}}]. ''senses of cinema'' January 2001. Retrieved on July 26, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Also, in August 1929, Dalí met his lifelong and primary [[muse]], inspiration, and future wife [[Gala Dalí|Gala]],&lt;ref name=unbound&gt;Shelley, Landry. [http://www.tcnj.edu/~unbound/spring2005/articles/a2 &quot;Dalí Wows Crowd in Philadelphia&quot;]. ''Unbound'' ([[The College of New Jersey]]) Spring 2005. Retrieved on July 22, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; born Elena Ivanovna Diakonova. She was a Russian immigrant ten years his senior, who at that time was married to [[Surrealism|surrealist]] poet [[Paul Éluard]]. In the same year, Dalí had important professional exhibitions and officially joined the Surrealist group in the [[Montparnasse]] quarter of Paris. His work had already been heavily influenced by surrealism for two years. The Surrealists hailed what Dalí called his [[paranoiac-critical method]] of accessing the [[subconscious]] for greater artistic creativity.&lt;ref name=Llongueras /&gt;&lt;ref name=Rojas /&gt;

Meanwhile, Dalí's relationship with his father was close to rupture. Don Salvador Dalí y Cusi strongly disapproved of his son's romance with Gala, and saw his connection to the Surrealists as a bad influence on his morals. The last straw was when Don Salvador read in a Barcelona newspaper that his son had recently exhibited in Paris a drawing of the ''Sacred Heart of Jesus Christ'', with a provocative inscription: &quot;Sometimes, I spit for fun on my mother's portrait&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;isbn0-571-19380-3&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Gibson, Ian |title=The Shameful Life of Salvador Dalí |publisher=Faber and Faber |location=London |year=1997 |pages=238–9|isbn=0-571-19380-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Outraged, Don Salvador demanded that his son recant publicly. Dalí refused, perhaps out of fear of expulsion from the Surrealist group, and was violently thrown out of his paternal home on December 28, 1929. His father told him that he would be [[disinherit]]ed, and that he should never set foot in Cadaqués again. The following summer, Dalí and Gala rented a small fisherman's cabin in a nearby bay at Port Lligat. He bought the place, and over the years enlarged it, gradually building his much beloved [[villa]] by the sea. Dalí's father would eventually relent and come to accept his son's companion.&lt;ref name=GalaGSDF&gt;{{cite web|title=Gala Biography|url=http://www.salvador-dali.org/dali/en_biografia-gala.html|work=Dalí|publisher=Gala-Salvador Dalí Foundation|accessdate=27 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Image:The Persistence of Memory.jpg|thumb|right|''[[The Persistence of Memory]]'']]
In 1931, Dalí painted one of his most famous works, ''[[The Persistence of Memory]]'',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.salvadordalimuseum.org/education/documents/clocking_in.pdf Clocking in with Salvador Dalí: Salvador Dalí's Melting Watches] (PDF) from the Salvador Dalí Museum. Retrieved on August 19, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; which introduced a surrealistic image of soft, melting [[pocket watch]]es. The general interpretation of the work is that the soft watches are a rejection of the assumption that time is rigid or [[determinism|deterministic]]. This idea is supported by other images in the work, such as the wide expanding landscape, and other limp watches shown being devoured by ants.&lt;ref name=Conquete&gt;Salvador Dalí, {{lang|fr|''La Conquête de l'irrationnel''}} (Paris: Éditions surréalistes, 1935), p. 25.&lt;/ref&gt;

Dalí and Gala, having lived together since 1929, were married in 1934 in a semi-secret civil ceremony. They later remarried in a Catholic ceremony in 1958&lt;ref&gt;''Carré d'Art'', [[Jean-Pierre Thiollet]], Paris, Anagramme, 2008, p. 212&lt;/ref&gt;. In addition to inspiring many artworks throughout her life, Gala would act as Dalí's [[business manager]], supporting their extravagant lifestyle while adeptly steering clear of insolvency.  Gala seemed to tolerate Dalí's dalliances with younger muses, secure in her own position as his primary relationship. Dali continued to paint her as they both aged, producing sympathetic and adoring images of his muse. The &quot;tense, complex and ambiguous relationship&quot; lasting over 50 years would later become the subject of an opera ''Jo, Dalí'' (I, Dalí) by [[Catalan people|Catalan]] composer [[Xavier Benguerel]].&lt;ref name=Opera&gt;{{cite web|last=Amengual|first=Margalida|title=An opera on the relationship between Salvador Dalí and Gala arrives at Barcelona’s Liceu|url=http://www.catalannewsagency.com/news/culture/opera-relationship-between-salvador-dal%C3%AD-and-gala-arrives-barcelona’s-liceu|work=Catalan News Agency (CNA)|publisher=Intracatalònia, SA|accessdate=27 May 2012|date=17 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Dalí was introduced to America by art dealer [[Julien Levy]] in 1934. The exhibition in New York of Dalí's works, including ''Persistence of Memory'', created an immediate sensation. [[Social Register]] listees feted him at a specially organized &quot;Dalí Ball&quot;.  He showed up wearing a glass case on his chest, which contained a brassiere.&lt;ref&gt;Current Biography 1940, pp219–220&lt;/ref&gt;
In that year, Dalí and Gala also attended a masquerade party in New York, hosted for them by heiress [[Caresse Crosby]]. For their costumes, they dressed as the [[Lindbergh baby]] and his [[Bruno Hauptmann|kidnapper]]. The resulting uproar in the press was so great that Dalí apologized. When he returned to Paris, the Surrealists confronted him about his apology for a surrealist act.&lt;ref&gt;Luis Buñuel, ''My Last Sigh: The Autobiography of Luis Buñuel'', Vintage 1984. ISBN 0-8166-4387-3&lt;/ref&gt;

While the majority of the Surrealist artists had become increasingly associated with [[leftist]] politics, Dalí maintained an ambiguous position on the subject of the proper relationship between politics and art. Leading surrealist [[André Breton]] accused Dalí of defending the &quot;new&quot; and &quot;irrational&quot; in &quot;the Hitler phenomenon&quot;, but Dalí quickly rejected this claim, saying, &quot;I am Hitlerian neither in fact nor intention&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Greeley, Robin Adèle (2006). ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=2w1QddhP56wC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_ge_summary_r&amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Surrealism and the Spanish Civil War]'', Yale University Press. p. 81. ISBN 0-300-11295-5.&lt;/ref&gt; Dalí insisted that surrealism could exist in an apolitical context and refused to explicitly denounce [[fascism]].{{Citation needed|date=April 2009}} Among other factors, this had landed him in trouble with his colleagues. Later in 1934, Dalí was subjected to a &quot;trial&quot;, in which he was formally expelled from the Surrealist group.&lt;ref name=unbound /&gt; To this, Dalí retorted, &quot;I myself am surrealism&quot;.&lt;ref name=olga /&gt;

In 1936, Dalí took part in the [[London International Surrealist Exhibition]]. His lecture, titled {{lang|fr|''Fantômes paranoiaques authentiques''}}, was delivered while wearing a deep-sea [[diving suit]] and helmet.&lt;ref&gt;Jackaman, Rob. (1989) ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=DV9_6DAOSscC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_ge_summary_r&amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false The Course of English Surrealist Poetry Since the 1930s]'', Edwin Mellen Press. ISBN 0-88946-932-6.&lt;/ref&gt; He had arrived carrying a [[billiard cue]] and leading a pair of [[Russian wolfhound]]s, and had to have the helmet unscrewed as he gasped for breath. He commented that &quot;I just wanted to show that I was 'plunging deeply' into the human mind.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Current Biography 1940, p219&lt;/ref&gt;

Also in 1936, at the premiere screening of [[Joseph Cornell]]'s film ''[[Rose Hobart (film)|Rose Hobart]]'' at Julien Levy's gallery in New York City, Dalí became famous for another incident. Levy's program of short surrealist films was timed to take place at the same time as the first surrealism exhibition at the [[Museum of Modern Art]], featuring Dalí's work. Dalí was in the audience at the screening, but halfway through the film, he knocked over the projector in a rage. &quot;My idea for a film is exactly that, and I was going to propose it to someone who would pay to have it made,&quot; he said. &quot;I never wrote it down or told anyone, but it is as if he had stolen it&quot;. Other versions of Dalí's accusation tend to the more poetic: &quot;He stole it from my subconscious!&quot; or even &quot;He stole my dreams!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://andel.home.mindspring.com/cornell_notes.htm |title=Program Notes by Andy Ditzler (2005) and Deborah Solomon, ',Utopia Parkway:The Life of Joseph Cornell (New York: Farrar, Straus, and Giroux, 2003) |publisher=Andel.home.mindspring.com |accessdate=August 22, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In this period, Dalí's main patron in London was the very wealthy [[Edward James]]. He had helped Dalí emerge into the art world by purchasing many works and by supporting him financially for two years. They also collaborated on two of the most enduring icons of the [[Surrealist]] movement: the ''[[Lobster Telephone]]'' and the ''[[Mae West Lips Sofa]]''.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}

In 1938, Dalí met [[Sigmund Freud]] thanks to [[Stefan Zweig]]. Later, in September 1938, Salvador Dalí was invited by Gabrielle [[Coco Chanel]] to her house &quot;La Pausa&quot; in [[Roquebrune-Cap-Martin|Roquebrune]] on the [[French Riviera]]. There he painted numerous paintings he later exhibited at Julien Levy Gallery in New York.&lt;ref&gt;''Salvador Dalí Exhibition'', Exhibition Catalogue – February 16 through May 15, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://philadelphia.about.com/od/salvador_dali/a/salvador_dali_a.htm&lt;/ref&gt; At the end of the 20th century, &quot;La Pausa&quot; was partially replicated at the [[Dallas Museum of Art]] to welcome the Reeves collection and part of Chanel's original furniture for the house.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| title=Impressionist paintings, drawings, and sculpture from the Wendy and Emery Reeves Collection |first=Richard R. |last=Bretell |year=1995 |publisher=Dallas Museum of Art |isbn= 978-0-936227-15-3 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Also in 1938, Dali unveiled ''[[Rainy Taxi]]'', a three-dimensional artwork, consisting of an actual automobile with two [[mannequin]] occupants. The piece was first displayed at the Galerie Beaux-Arts in Paris at the [[Exposition Internationale du Surréalisme]], organised by [[André Breton]] and [[Paul Eluard]]. The Exposition was designed by artist [[Marcel Duchamp]], who also served as host.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.salvador-dali.org/dali/en_biografia.html ''Salvador Dalí''. Gala-Salvador Dalí Foundation. Retrieved 2011-06-07]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=lPN0xxpA6OsC&amp;pg=RA1-PA27 J. Herbert, ''Paris 1937: Worlds on Exhibition'' (Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 1998) ISBN 0-8014-3494-7]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=nDJL4MwVK10C&amp;pg=PA130  A. Cohen-Solal, ''Leo and His Circle: The Life of Leo Castelli'' (New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 2010) ISBN 978-1-4000-4427-6]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1939, André Breton coined the derogatory nickname &quot;Avida Dollars&quot;, an [[anagram]] for &quot;Salvador Dalí&quot;, and a phonetic rendering of the French ''avide à dollars'', which may be translated as &quot;eager for dollars&quot;.&lt;ref name=artcyclopedia&gt;[http://www.artcyclopedia.com/artists/dali_salvador.html Artcyclopedia: Salvador Dalí]. Retrieved September 4, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; This was a derisive reference to the increasing commercialization of Dalí's work, and the perception that Dalí sought self-aggrandizement through fame and fortune. Some surrealists henceforth spoke of Dalí in the past tense, as if he were dead.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}} The Surrealist movement and various members thereof (such as [[Ted Joans]]) would continue to issue extremely harsh [[polemics]] against Dalí until the time of his death, and beyond.

===World War II===
In 1940, as World War II tore through Europe, Dalí and Gala retreated to the United States, where they lived for eight years. They were able to escape because on June 20, 1940, they were issued visas by [[Aristides de Sousa Mendes]], Portuguese consul in Bordeaux, France.  Salvador and Gala Dalí crossed into Portugal and subsequently sailed on the Excambion from Lisbon to New York in August 1940. Dali’s arrival in New York was one of the catalysts in the development of that city as a world art center in the post-War years.After the move, Dalí returned to the practice of [[Catholicism]]. &quot;During this period, Dalí never stopped writing&quot;, wrote Robert and Nicolas Descharnes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Descharnes (1993) p. 35.&quot;&gt;Descharnes, Robert and Nicolas. ''Salvador Dalí''. New York: Konecky &amp; Konecky, 1993. p. 35.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1941, Dalí drafted a film scenario for [[Jean Gabin]] called ''Moontide''. In 1942, he published his autobiography, ''[[The Secret Life of Salvador Dalí]]''. He wrote catalogs for his exhibitions, such as that at the Knoedler Gallery in New York in 1943. Therein he attacked some often-used surrealist techniques by proclaiming, &quot;Surrealism will at least have served to give experimental proof that total sterility and attempts at automatizations have gone too far and have led to a totalitarian system. ... Today's laziness and the total lack of technique have reached their paroxysm in the psychological signification of the current use of the college&quot; ([[collage]]). He also wrote a novel, published in 1944, about a fashion salon for automobiles. This resulted in a drawing by Edwin Cox in ''[[The Miami Herald]]'', depicting Dalí dressing an automobile in an evening gown.&lt;ref name=&quot;Descharnes (1993) p. 35.&quot;/&gt; 

Also, in ''[[The Secret Life of Salvador Dalí|The Secret Life]]'' Dalí suggested that he had split with [[Luis Buñuel]] because the latter was a [[Communist]] and an [[atheist]]. Buñuel was fired (or resigned) from his position at the [[Museum of Modern Art]] (MOMA), supposedly after [[Cardinal Spellman]] of New York went to see [[Iris Barry]], head of the film department at MOMA. Buñuel then went back to Hollywood where he worked in the dubbing department of [[Warner Brothers]] from 1942 to 1946. In his 1982 autobiography ''Mon Dernier soupir'' (''My Last Sigh'', 1983), Buñuel wrote that, over the years, he had rejected Dalí's attempts at reconciliation.&lt;ref&gt;Luis Buñuel, ''My Last Sigh: The Autobiography of Luis Buñuel'' (Vintage, 1984) ISBN 0-8166-4387-3&lt;/ref&gt;

An Italian [[friar]], Gabriele Maria Berardi, claimed to have performed an [[exorcism]] on Dalí while he was in France in 1947.&lt;ref name=&quot;exorcist-gift&quot;&gt;[http://www.cathnews.com/news/510/72.php Dalí's gift to exorcist uncovered] ''Catholic News'', October 14, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2005, a sculpture of Christ on the Cross was discovered in the friar's estate. It had been claimed that Dalí gave this work to his exorcist out of gratitude,&lt;ref name=&quot;exorcist-gift&quot;/&gt; and two Spanish art experts confirmed that there were adequate stylistic reasons to believe the sculpture was made by Dalí.&lt;ref name=&quot;exorcist-gift&quot;/&gt;

===Later years in Catalonia===
[[File:Dali Allan Warren.jpg|thumb|175px|left|Dalí in 1972.]]
From 1949 onwards, Dalí spent his remaining years back in Catalonia. In 1959, [[André Breton]] organized an exhibit called ''Homage to Surrealism'', celebrating the fortieth anniversary of Surrealism, which contained works by Dalí, [[Joan Miró]], [[Enrique Tábara]], and [[Eugenio Granell]]. Breton vehemently fought against the inclusion of Dalí's ''Sistine Madonna'' in the International Surrealism Exhibition in New York the following year.&lt;ref name=lopez&gt;López, Ignacio Javier. ''The Old Age of William Tell (A study of Buñuel's ''Tristana'')''. ''[[MLN]]'' 116 (2001): 295–314.&lt;/ref&gt;

Late in his career, Dalí did not confine himself to painting, but experimented with many unusual or novel media and processes: he made [[bulletism|bulletist]] works.&lt;ref name=bp&gt;[http://www.bonjourparis.com/Articles/Museums_and_Sights/The_Phantasmagoric_Universe_%E2%80%94_Espace_Dal%C3%AD_%C3%80_Montmartre/ The Phantasmagoric Universe—Espace Dalí À Montmartre]. {{lang|fr|''Bonjour Paris''}}. Retrieved on August 22, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Many of his works incorporated [[optical illusion]]s, [[negative space]], [[visual pun]]s, and [[trompe l'oeil]] visual effects. He also experimented with [[pointillism]], enlarged [[half-tone]] dot grids (which [[Roy Lichtenstein]] would later use),  and [[stereoscopic]] images.&lt;ref name=Optical&gt;{{cite book|last=Ades|first=ed. by Dawn|title=Dalí's optical illusions : [Wadsworth Atheneum Museum of Art, January 21 - March 26, 2000 : Hirshhorn Museum and Sculpture Garden, April 19 - June 18, 2000 ; Scottish National Gallery of Modern Art, July 25 - October 1, 2000]|year=2000|publisher=Yale Univ. Press|location=New Haven CT|isbn=978-0300081770}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was among the first artists to employ [[holography]] in an artistic manner.&lt;ref name=holo&gt;[http://www.holophile.com/history.htm The History and Development of Holography]. ''Holophile''. Retrieved on August 22, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; In his later years, young artists such as [[Andy Warhol]] proclaimed Dalí an important influence on [[pop art]].&lt;ref name=warhol&gt;[http://www.carnegiemuseums.org/cmag/bk_issue/1998/mayjun/feat2.htm Hello, Dalí]. ''Carnegie Magazine''. Retrieved on August 22, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Dalí also had a keen interest in natural science and mathematics. This is manifested in several of his paintings, notably from the 1950s, in which he painted his subjects as composed of [[rhinoceros horn]] shapes. According to Dalí, the rhinoceros horn signifies divine geometry because it grows in a [[logarithmic spiral]]. He also linked the rhinoceros to themes of [[chastity]] and to the [[Virgin Mary]].&lt;ref&gt;Elliott H. King in Dawn Ades (ed.), ''Dalí'', Bompiani Arte, Milan, 2004, p. 456.&lt;/ref&gt; Dalí was also fascinated by [[DNA]] and the [[tesseract]] (a 4-dimensional cube); an unfolding of a hypercube is featured in the painting ''[[Crucifixion (Corpus Hypercubus)]]''.

At some point, Dalí had a [[glass floor]] installed in a room near his studio.  He made extensive use of it to study [[foreshortening]], both from above and from below, incorporating dramatic perspectives of figures and objects into his paintings.&lt;ref name=GlassFloor&gt;{{cite book|last=Ades|first=ed. by Dawn|title=Dalí's optical illusions : [Wadsworth Atheneum Museum of Art, January 21 - March 26, 2000 : Hirshhorn Museum and Sculpture Garden, April 19 - June 18, 2000 ; Scottish National Gallery of Modern Art, July 25 - October 1, 2000]|year=2000|publisher=Yale Univ. Press|location=New Haven CT|isbn=978-0300081770|pages=17-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also delighted in using the room for entertaining guests and visitors to his house and studio.

Dalí's post–World War II period bore the hallmarks of technical virtuosity and an intensifying interest in optical effects, science, and religion. He became an increasingly devout Catholic, while at the same time he had been inspired by the shock of [[Hiroshima]] and the dawning of the &quot;[[atomic age]]&quot;. Therefore Dalí labeled this period &quot;Nuclear [[Christian mysticism|Mysticism]].&quot; In paintings such as &quot;[[The Madonna of Port Lligat]]&quot; (first version) (1949) and &quot;Corpus Hypercubus&quot; (1954), Dalí sought to synthesize Christian [[iconography]] with images of material disintegration inspired by [[nuclear physics]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.arton5th.com/Dali/bio.html Salvador Dalí Bio, Art on 5th]. Retrieved July 22, 2006. {{Wayback | url=http://www.arton5th.com/Dali/bio.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; | date=20060504050531 }}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Nuclear Mysticism&quot; included such notable pieces as ''[[La Gare de Perpignan]]'' (1965) and ''[[The Hallucinogenic Toreador]]'' (1968–70). In 1960, Dalí began work on his Teatro Museo ([[Dalí Theatre and Museum]]) in his home town of [[Figueres]]; it was his largest single project and the main focus of his energy through 1974. He continued to make additions through the mid-1980s.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}

In 1968, Dalí filmed a humorous television advertisement for Lanvin chocolates.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ehotelier.com/browse/news_item.php?id=P12135 Salvador Dalí at Le Meurice Paris and St Regis in New York] Andreas Augustin, ehotelier.com, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; In this, he proclaims in French &quot;Je suis fou du chocolat Lanvin!&quot; (I'm crazy about Lanvin chocolate) while biting a morsel causing him to become crosseyed and his moustache to swivel upwards. In 1969, he designed the [[Chupa Chups]] logo in addition to facilitating the design of the advertising campaign for the [[1969 Eurovision Song Contest]] and creating a large on-stage metal sculpture that stood at the Teatro Real in Madrid.

In the television programme ''Dirty Dalí: A Private View'' broadcast on [[Channel 4]] on June 3, 2007, art critic [[Brian Sewell]] described his acquaintance with Dalí in the late 1960s, which included lying down in the fetal position without trousers in the armpit of a figure of Christ and masturbating for Dalí, who pretended to take photos while fumbling in his own trousers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://living.scotsman.com/index.cfm?id=869862007 |title=Scotsman review of Dirty Dalí |work=The Scotsman |location=UK  |accessdate=August 22, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thisislondon.co.uk/arts/article-23398918-details/The+Dali+I+knew/article.do The Dali I knew] By Brian Sewell, thisislondon.co.uk&lt;/ref&gt;

===Final years===
[[Image:20061227-Figueres Sant Pere MQ.jpg|thumb|Sant Pere in [[Figueres]], scene of Dalí's [[Baptism]], [[First Communion]], and funeral]]
[[File:Salvador Dali Crypt in Figueres.jpg|thumb|Dalí's crypt at the [[Dalí Theatre and Museum]] in [[Figueres]], stating his title]]
In 1980, Dalí's health took a catastrophic turn. His near-[[senile]] wife, Gala, allegedly had been dosing him with a dangerous cocktail of unprescribed medicine that damaged his nervous system, thus causing an untimely end to his artistic capacity. At 76 years old, Dalí was a wreck, and his right hand trembled terribly, with [[Parkinson's disease|Parkinson-like]] symptoms.&lt;ref&gt;Ian Gibson (1997). ''The Shameful Life of Salvador Dalí''. W. W. Norton &amp; Company.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1982, [[Juan Carlos of Spain|King Juan Carlos]] bestowed on Dalí the title of ''Marqués de Dalí de Púbol''&lt;ref name=&quot;Marquis title&quot;&gt;[http://www.heraldaria.com/phorum/read.php?f=1&amp;i=25695&amp;t=25695 Excerpts from the BOE] – Website Heráldica y Genealogía Hispana&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.boe.es/aeboe/consultas/bases_datos/doc.php?id=BOE-A-1989-4234 Dalí as &quot;Marqués de Dalí de Púbol&quot;] – Boletín Oficial del Estado, the official gazette of the Spanish government&lt;/ref&gt; (''Marquis of Dalí de Púbol'') in the [[Spanish nobility|nobility of Spain]], hereby referring to [[Púbol]], the place where he lived. The title was in first instance hereditary, but on request of Dalí changed for life only in 1983.&lt;ref name=&quot;Marquis title&quot; /&gt; To show his gratitude for this, Dalí later gave the king a drawing (''Head of Europa'', which would turn out to be Dalí's final drawing) after the king visited him on his deathbed.

Gala died on June 10, 1982, at the age of 87. After Gala's death, Dalí lost much of his will to live. He deliberately [[dehydration|dehydrated]] himself, possibly as a [[suicide]] attempt, or perhaps in an attempt to put himself into a state of [[suspended animation]] as he had read that some [[microorganism]]s could do. He moved from Figueres to the [[Castle of Púbol|castle in Púbol]], which he had bought for Gala and was the site of her death. 

In 1984, a fire broke out in his bedroom&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E1DB1038F932A3575AC0A962948260  &quot;Dalí Resting at Castle After Injury in Fire&quot;]. ''[[The New York Times]]''. September 1, 1984. Retrieved July 22, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; under unclear circumstances. It was possibly a suicide attempt by Dalí, or possibly simple negligence by his staff.&lt;ref name=olga /&gt; In any case, Dalí was rescued and returned to Figueres, where a group of his friends, patrons, and fellow artists saw to it that he was comfortable living in his [[Dalí Theatre and Museum|Theater-Museum]] in his final years.

There have been allegations that Dalí was forced by his guardians to sign blank canvases that would later, even after his death, be used in forgeries and sold as originals.&lt;ref name=&quot;scandal&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title=The Dalí Scandal: An Investigation | author=Mark Rogerson | isbn=0-575-03786-5 | publisher=Victor Gollancz | year=1989}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, art dealers tend to be wary of late works attributed to Dalí.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}

In November 1988, Dalí entered the hospital with [[heart failure]]; a [[pacemaker]] had already been implanted previously.  On December 5, 1988, he was visited by King [[Juan Carlos]], who confessed that he had always been a serious devotee of Dalí.&lt;ref&gt;Etherington
-Smith, Meredith [http://books.google.com/books?id=soncxLrkYX0C&amp;dq The Persistence of Memory: A Biography of Dalí] p. 411, 1995 Da Capo Press, ISBN 0-306-80662-2&lt;/ref&gt;

On January 23, 1989, while his favorite record of ''[[Tristan und Isolde|Tristan and Isolde]]'' played, he died of heart failure at Figueres at the age of 84. Coming full circle, he is buried in the [[crypt]] of his [[Teatro Museo]] in Figueres. The location is across the street from the church of Sant Pere, where he had his baptism, first communion, and funeral, and is three blocks from the house where he was born.&lt;ref&gt;Etherington
-Smith, Meredith [http://books.google.com/books?id=soncxLrkYX0C&amp;dq The Persistence of Memory: A Biography of Dalí] pp. xxiv, 411–412, 1995 Da Capo Press, ISBN 0-306-80662-2&lt;/ref&gt;

The Gala-Salvador Dalí Foundation currently serves as his official estate.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.salvador-dali.org/en_index.html | The Gala-Salvador Dalí Foundation website&lt;/ref&gt; The US copyright representative for the Gala-Salvador Dalí Foundation is the [[Artists Rights Society]].&lt;ref&gt;http://arsny.com/requested.html | Most frequently requested artists list of the Artists Rights Society&lt;/ref&gt; In 2002, the Society made the news when they asked [[Google]] to remove a customized version of its logo put up to commemorate Dalí, alleging that portions of specific artworks under their protection had been used without permission. Google complied with the request, but denied that there was any copyright violation.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}

==Symbolism==
Dalí employed extensive symbolism in his work. For instance, the hallmark &quot;soft watches&quot; that first appear in ''The Persistence of Memory'' suggest [[Albert Einstein|Einstein]]'s theory that [[Special Relativity|time is relative]] and not fixed.&lt;ref name=Conquete /&gt; The idea for clocks functioning symbolically in this way came to Dalí when he was staring at a runny piece of [[Camembert (cheese)|Camembert cheese]] on a hot August day.&lt;ref&gt;Salvador Dalí, ''The Secret Life of Salvador Dalí'' (New York: Dial Press, 1942), p. 317.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[elephant]] is also a recurring image in Dalí's works. It first appeared in his 1944 work ''[[Dream Caused by the Flight of a Bee Around a Pomegranate a Second Before Awakening]]''. The elephants, inspired by [[Gian Lorenzo Bernini]]'s sculpture [[Obelisks in Rome#6|base]] in Rome of an [[Santa Maria sopra Minerva#Minerva's Pulcino|elephant carrying an ancient obelisk]],&lt;ref&gt;Michael Taylor in Dawn Ades (ed.), ''Dalí'' (Milan: Bompiani, 2004), p. 342&lt;/ref&gt; are portrayed &quot;with long, multijointed, almost invisible legs of desire&quot;&lt;ref name=countycollection&gt;[http://www.countyhallgallery.com/education/dali_collection.htm Dalí Universe Collection]. ''County Hall Gallery''. Retrieved on July 28, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; along with obelisks on their backs. Coupled with the image of their brittle legs, these encumbrances, noted for their phallic overtones, create a sense of phantom reality. &quot;The elephant is a distortion in space&quot;, one analysis explains, &quot;its spindly legs contrasting the idea of weightlessness with structure.&quot;&lt;ref name=countycollection /&gt; &quot;I am painting pictures which make me die for joy, I am creating with an absolute naturalness, without the slightest aesthetic concern, I am making things that inspire me with a profound emotion and I am trying to paint them honestly.&quot; —Salvador Dalí, in Dawn Ades, ''Dalí and Surrealism''.

The egg is another common Dalíesque image. He connects the egg to the prenatal and intrauterine, thus using it to symbolize hope and love;&lt;ref name=symb&gt;[http://www.countyhallgallery.com/education/dali_symbols.htm &quot;Salvador Dalí's symbolism&quot;]. ''County Hall Gallery''. Retrieved on July 28, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; it appears in ''[[The Great Masturbator]]'' and ''[[Metamorphosis of Narcissus|The Metamorphosis of Narcissus]]''.  ''The Metamorphosis of Narcissus'' also symbolized death and [[petrification]]. 

Various other animals appear throughout his work as well: [[ant]]s point to death, decay, and immense sexual desire; the [[snail]] is connected to the human head (he saw a snail on a bicycle outside Freud's house when he first met [[Sigmund Freud]]); and [[locust]]s are a symbol of waste and fear.&lt;ref name=symb /&gt;

===Science===
References to Dalí in the context of science are made in terms of his fascination with the paradigm shift that accompanied the birth of [[quantum mechanics]] in the twentieth century. Inspired by [[Werner Heisenberg]]'s [[Uncertainty Principle]], in 1958 he wrote in his &quot;Anti-Matter Manifesto&quot;: &quot;In the Surrealist period, I wanted to create the iconography of the interior world and the world of the marvelous, of my father [[Sigmund Freud|Freud]]. Today, the exterior world and that of physics has transcended the one of psychology. My father today is Dr. Heisenberg.&quot;&lt;ref name=triangle&gt;[http://www.thetriangle.org/media/storage/paper689/news/2005/04/29/Entertainment/Dali-Explorations.Into.The.Domain.Of.Science-944328.shtml?norewrite200608080502&amp;sourcedomain=www.thetriangle.org Dalí: Explorations into the domain of science]. ''The Triangle Online''. Retrieved August 8, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

In this respect, ''[[The Disintegration of the Persistence of Memory]]'', which appeared in 1954, in hearkening back to ''The Persistence of Memory'', and in portraying that painting in fragmentation and disintegration summarizes Dalí's acknowledgment of the new science.&lt;ref name=triangle /&gt;

==Endeavors outside painting==
Dalí was a versatile artist. Some of his more popular works are sculptures and other objects, and he is also noted for his contributions to theatre, fashion, and photography, among other areas.

===Sculptures and other objects===
[[File:Hommage à Newton.jpg|thumb|''Homage to Newton'' (1985). Signed and numbered cast no. 5/8. Bronze with dark patina. Size: 388 x 210 x 133cm. [[UOB Plaza]], [[Singapore]]. Dalí's homage to [[Isaac Newton]], with an open torso and suspended heart to indicate &quot;open-heartedness,&quot; and an open head indicating &quot;open-mindedness&quot;—the two very qualities important for science discovery and successful human endeavors.]]
Two of the most popular objects of the surrealist movement were ''[[Lobster Telephone]]'' and ''[[Mae West Lips Sofa]]'', completed by Dalí in 1936 and 1937, respectively. Surrealist artist and patron [[Edward James]] commissioned both of these pieces from Dalí; James inherited a large English estate in [[West Dean, West Sussex|West Dean]], West Sussex when he was five and was one of the foremost supporters of the surrealists in the 1930s.&lt;ref name=natgalaust&gt;[http://www.nga.gov.au/International/Catalogue/Detail.cfm?IRN=2607 Lobster telephone]. ''National Gallery of Australia''. Retrieved on August 4, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Lobsters and telephones had strong sexual connotations for [Dalí]&quot;, according to the display caption for the ''Lobster Telephone'' at the [[Tate Gallery]], &quot;and he drew a close analogy between food and sex.&quot;&lt;ref name=tate&gt;[http://www.tate.org.uk/servlet/ViewWork?workid=2988 Tate Collection | Lobster Telephone by Salvador Dalí]. ''Tate Online''. Retrieved on August 4, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; The telephone was functional, and James purchased four of them from Dalí to replace the phones in his retreat home. One now appears at the Tate Gallery; the second can be found at the German Telephone Museum in [[Frankfurt]]; the third belongs to the Edward James Foundation; and the fourth is at the [[National Gallery of Australia]].&lt;ref name=natgalaust /&gt;

The wood and satin ''Mae West Lips Sofa'' was shaped after the lips of actress [[Mae West]], whom Dalí apparently found fascinating.&lt;ref name=unbound /&gt; West was previously the subject of Dalí's 1935 painting ''The Face of Mae West''. ''Mae West Lips Sofa'' currently resides at the Brighton and Hove Museum in England.

Between 1941 and 1970, Dalí created an ensemble of 39 jewels. The jewels are intricate, and some contain moving parts. The most famous jewel, &quot;The Royal Heart&quot;, is made of gold and is encrusted with 46 rubies, 42 diamonds, and four emeralds and is created in such a way that the center &quot;beats&quot; much like a real heart. Dalí himself commented that &quot;Without an audience, without the presence of spectators, these jewels would not fulfill the function for which they came into being. The viewer, then, is the ultimate artist.&quot; (Dalí, 1959.) The &quot;Dalí – Joies&quot; (&quot;The Jewels of Dalí&quot;) collection can be seen at the Dalí Theater Museum in Figueres, Catalonia, Spain, where it is on permanent exhibition.

Dalí took a stab at [[industrial design]] in the 1970s with a 500-piece run of the upscale ''Suomi'' tableware by [[Timo Sarpaneva]] that Dalí decorated for the German Rosenthal [[porcelain]] maker's ''Studio Linie''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | title = Faenza-Goldmedaille für SUOMI | journal=Artis | year = 1976 | last = [Anon.] | volume = 29 | pages = 8| issn = 0004-3842}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Theatre and film===
In theatre, Dalí constructed the scenery for [[Federico García Lorca]]'s 1927 romantic play ''[[Mariana Pineda]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kirjasto.sci.fi/fglorca.htm Federico García Lorca]. ''Pegásos''. Retrieved on August 8, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; For ''[[Bacchanale]]'' (1939), a ballet based on and set to the music of [[Richard Wagner]]'s 1845 opera ''[[Tannhäuser (opera)|Tannhäuser]]'', Dalí provided both the set design and the [[libretto]].&lt;ref name=designws&gt;[http://www.designws.com/pagina/1dalieng.htm Dalí Rotterdam Museum Boijmans]. ''Paris Contemporary Designs''. Retrieved on August 8, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Bacchanale'' was followed by set designs for ''Labyrinth'' in 1941 and ''[[The Three-Cornered Hat]]'' in 1949.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marquette.edu/haggerty/exhibitions/past/dalihat.html Past Exhibitions]. ''Haggerty Museum of Art''. Retrieved August 8, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

Dalí became intensely interested in film when he was young, going to the theatre most Sundays. He was part of the era where silent films were being viewed and drawing on the medium of film became popular. He believed there were two dimensions to the theories of film and cinema: &quot;things themselves&quot;, the facts that are presented in the world of the camera; and &quot;photographic imagination&quot;, the way the camera shows the picture and how creative or imaginative it looks.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Dali &amp; Film&quot;  Edt. Gale, Matthew. Salvador Dalí Museum Inc. St Petersburg, Florida. 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Dalí was active in front of and behind the scenes in the film world. 

He is credited as co-creator of [[Luis Buñuel]]'s surrealist film ''[[Un Chien Andalou]]'', a 17-minute French art film co-written with Luis Buñuel that is widely remembered for its graphic opening scene simulating the slashing of a human eyeball with a razor. This film is what Dalí is known for in the independent film world. ''Un Chien Andalou'' was Dalí's way of creating his dreamlike qualities in the real world. Images would change and scenes would switch, leading the viewer in a completely different direction from the one they were previously viewing. The second film he produced with Buñuel was entitled ''[[L'Age d'Or]]'', and it was performed at Studio 28 in Paris in 1930. ''L'Age d'Or'' was &quot;banned for years after fascist and anti-Semitic groups staged a stink bomb and ink-throwing riot in the Paris theater where it was shown&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://hcl.harvard.edu/hfa/films/2000novdec/bunuel.html &quot;L'Âge d'Or (The Golden Age)&quot;] Harvard Film Archive. 2006. April 10, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Although negative aspects of society were being thrown into the life of Dalí which affected the commercial success of his artwork, it did not hold him back from expressing his own ideas and beliefs in his art. Both of these films, ''Un Chien Andalou'' and ''L'Age d'Or'', have had a tremendous impact on the independent surrealist film movement. &quot;If ''Un Chien Andalou'' stands as the supreme record of Surrealism's adventures into the realm of the unconscious, then ''L'Âge d'Or'' is perhaps the most trenchant and implacable expression of its revolutionary intent&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Short, Robert.  &quot;The Age of Gold: Surrealist Cinema, Persistence of Vision&quot; Vol. 3, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;

Dalí worked with other famous filmmakers, such as [[Alfred Hitchcock]]. The most well-known of his film projects is probably the [[dream sequence]] in Hitchcock's ''[[Spellbound (1945 film)|Spellbound]]'', which heavily delves into themes of [[psychoanalysis]]. Hitchcock needed a dreamlike quality to his film, which dealt with the idea that a repressed experience can directly trigger a [[neurosis]], and he knew that Dalí's work would help create the atmosphere he wanted in his film. He also worked on a documentary called ''Chaos and Creation'', which has a lot of artistic references thrown into it to help one see what Dalí's vision of art really is.

Dalí also worked with [[Walt Disney]] on the short film production ''[[Destino]]''. Completed in 2003 by Baker Bloodworth and Walt's nephew [[Roy E. Disney]], it contains dreamlike images of strange figures flying and walking about. It is based on Mexican songwriter Armando Dominguez' song &quot;Destino&quot;. When Disney hired Dalí to help produce the film in 1946, they were not prepared for the quantity of work that lay ahead. For eight months, they worked on it continuously, until their efforts had to stop when they realized they were in financial trouble. However, it was eventually finished 48 years later, and shown in various film festivals. The film consists of Dalí's artwork interacting with Disney's character animation.

Dalí completed only one other film in his lifetime, ''Impressions of Upper Mongolia'' (1975), in which he narrated a story about an expedition in search of giant [[hallucinogenic mushrooms]]. The imagery was based on microscopic [[uric acid]] stains on the brass band of a ballpoint pen on which Dalí had been urinating for several weeks.&lt;ref&gt;Elliott H. King, [http://www.kamera.co.uk/article.php/895 ''Dalí, Surrealism and Cinema''], Kamera Books 2007, p. 169.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fashion and photography===
[[Image:Salvador Dali A (Dali Atomicus) 09633u.jpg|thumb|250px|The Dali Atomicus, photo by [[Philippe Halsman]] (1948), shown before its supporting wires were removed from the image.]]
Dalí built a repertoire in the [[fashion]] and [[photography]] businesses as well. His cooperation with Italian fashion designer [[Elsa Schiaparelli]] was well-known, when Dalí was commissioned to produce a white dress with a lobster print. Other designs Dalí made for her include a shoe-shaped hat, and a pink belt with lips for a buckle. He was also involved in creating textile designs and perfume bottles. In 1950, Dalí created a special &quot;costume for the year 2045&quot; with [[Christian Dior]].&lt;ref name=designws /&gt; 

Photographers with whom he collaborated include [[Man Ray]], [[Brassaï]], [[Cecil Beaton]], and [[Philippe Halsman]]. With Man Ray and Brassaï, Dalí photographed nature; with the others, he explored a range of obscure topics, including (with Halsman) the ''Dalí Atomica'' series (1948) — inspired by his painting ''Leda Atomica''&amp;nbsp;— which in one photograph depicts &quot;a painter's easel, three cats, a bucket of water, and Dalí himself floating in the air.&quot;&lt;ref name=designws /&gt;

One of Dalí's most unorthodox artistic creations may have been an entire [[persona]], in addition to his own. At a French [[nightclub]] in 1965, Dalí met [[Amanda Lear]], a [[fashion model]] then known as Peki D'Oslo.&lt;ref name=Prose&gt;Prose, Francine. (2000) ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=0rJ2EPVYbFUC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_ge_summary_r&amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false The Lives of the Muses: Nine Women and the Artists they Inspired]''. Harper Perennial. ISBN 0-06-055525-4.&lt;/ref&gt; Lear became his protégée and muse,&lt;ref name = Prose/&gt; later writing about their affair in her authorized biography ''My Life With Dalí'' (1986).&lt;ref name=Lear&gt;Lear, Amanda. (1986) ''My Life with Dalí''. Beaufort Books. ISBN 0-8253-0373-7.&lt;/ref&gt; Transfixed by the mannish, larger-than-life Lear, Dalí masterminded her successful transition from modeling to the music world, advising her on self-presentation and helping spin mysterious stories about her origin as she took the [[disco]]-art scene by storm. According to Lear, she and Dalí were united in a &quot;spiritual marriage&quot; on a deserted mountaintop.&lt;ref name=Prose&gt;Prose, ''The Lives of the Muses''.&lt;/ref&gt; She was referred to as Dalí's &quot;Frankenstein,&quot;&lt;ref name=Lozano&gt;Lozano, Carlos. (2000) ''Sex, Surrealism, Dalí, and Me''. Razor Books Ltd. ISBN 0-9538205-0-5.&lt;/ref&gt; and some observers believed Lear's assumed name was a [[pun]] on the French phrase &quot;L'Amant Dalí&quot;, or &quot;Lover of Dalí&quot;. Lear took the place of an earlier muse, [[Ultra Violet (Isabelle Collin Dufresne)]], who had left Dalí's side to join [[The Factory]] of [[Andy Warhol]].&lt;ref name=Etherington-Smith&gt;Etherington-Smith, Meredith. (1995) ''The Persistence of Memory: A Biography of Dalí''. Da Capo Press. ISBN 0-306-80662-2.&lt;/ref&gt;

Both former apprentices would go on to successfully promote their own careers in the arts. On April 10, 2005, they joined a panel discussion &quot;Reminiscences of Dalí: A Conversation with Friends of the Artist&quot; as part of a symposium &quot;The Dalí Renaissance&quot; for a major retrospective Dalí show at the [[Philadelphia Museum of Art]].&lt;ref name=PMADali&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.philamuseum.org/micro_sites/exhibitions/dali/downloads/symposium.pdf|title=(Symposium announcement)|work=The Dalí Renaissance: An international symposium|publisher=Philadelphia Museum of Art|accessdate=24 May 2012|date=April 10–11, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; Their conversation is recorded in the 236-page exhibition catalog ''The Dalí Renaissance: New Perspectives on His Life and Art after 1940''.&lt;ref name=Taylor&gt;{{cite book|last=Taylor|first=edited by Michael R.|title=The Dalí renaissance : new perspectives on his life and art after 1940 : an international symposium|year=2008|publisher=Philadelphia Museum of Art, distributed by Yale University Press|location=New Haven, Conn.|isbn=9780300136470|url=http://www.philamuseum.org/publications/377-1-31012.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Architecture ===
[[Image:Dali museum.jpg|thumb|[[Dalí Theatre and Museum]] in [[Figueres]], also where Dalí is buried]]
Architectural achievements include his [[Port Lligat]] house near [[Cadaqués]], as well as his [[Teatro Museo]] in [[Figueres]].  A major work outside of Spain was the temporary ''Dream of Venus'' surrealist pavilion at the [[1939 New York World's Fair]], which contained within it a number of unusual sculptures and statues, including live performers posing as statues.&lt;ref name=DrmVns&gt;{{cite book|last=Schaffner|first=Ingrid, Photogr. by Eric Schaal|title=Salvador Dalí's &quot;Dream of Venus&quot; : the surrealist funhouse from the 1939 World's Fair|year=2002|publisher=Princeton Architectural Press|location=New York, NY|isbn=978-1568983592|edition=1. }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Literary works===
Under the encouragement of poet [[Federico García Lorca]], Dalí attempted an approach to a literary career through the means of the &quot;pure novel&quot;. In his literary production ''Hidden Faces'' (1944), Dalí describes, in vividly visual terms, the intrigues and love affairs of a group of dazzling, eccentric aristocrats who, with their luxurious and extravagant lifestyle, symbolize the decadence of the 1930s.  The Comte de Grainsalles and Solange de Cladel pursue an awkward love affair, but property transactions, interwar political turmoil, the [[French Resistance]], his marriage to another woman and her responsibilities as a landowner and businesswoman drive them apart. It is variously set in [[Paris]], rural France, [[Casablanca]] in North Africa and [[Palm Springs]] in the United States. Secondary characters include ageing widow Barbara Rogers, her bisexual daughter Veronica, Veronica's sometime female lover Betka, and Baba, a disfigured US fighter pilot. The novel concludes at the end of the [[Second World War]], with Solange dying before Grainsalles can return to his former property and reunite with her &lt;ref&gt; Salvador Dali: ''Hidden faces'': London: Owen: 1973&lt;/ref&gt;


His other, nonfictional literary works include ''[[The Secret Life of Salvador Dalí]]'' (1942), ''Diary of a Genius'' (1952–63), and ''Oui: The Paranoid-Critical Revolution '' (1927–33).

===Graphic arts===
{{Expand section|date=May 2012}}
The artist worked extensively in the [[graphic arts]], producing many etchings and [[lithograph]]s.  While his early work in printmaking is equal in quality to his important paintings, as he grew older he would sell the rights to images but not be involved in the print production itself. In addition, a large number of unauthorized fakes were produced in the 1980s and 1990s, thus further confusing the Dalí print market.

==Politics and personality==
[[Image:Salvador Dali NYWTS.jpg|thumb|right|Dalí in the 1960s wearing the flamboyant mustache style he popularized. Photographed holding his pet [[ocelot]].]]
Salvador Dalí's politics played a significant role in his emergence as an artist. In his youth, he embraced both [[anarchism]] and [[Communism]], though his writings tell anecdotes of making radical political statements more to shock listeners than from any deep conviction. This was in keeping with Dalí's allegiance to the [[Dada]] movement.

As he grew older his political allegiances changed, especially as the Surrealist movement went through transformations under the leadership of the [[Trotsky]]ist writer [[André Breton]], who is said to have called Dalí in for questioning on his politics. In his 1970 book ''Dalí by Dalí'', Dalí declared himself to be both an anarchist and [[monarchist]].

With the outbreak of the [[Spanish Civil War]] (1936–1939), Dalí fled from the fighting and refused to align himself with any group. He did the same during World War II (1939–1945), for which he was heavily criticized; [[George Orwell]] accused him of &quot;scuttling off like a rat as soon as France is in danger&quot; after Dalí had prospered in France during the pre-war years. &quot;When the European War approaches he has one preoccupation only: how to find a place which has good cookery and from which he can make a quick bolt if danger comes too near&quot;, Orwell observed.&lt;ref name=orwell&gt;Orwell, George [http://theorwellprize.co.uk/george-orwell/by-orwell/essays-and-other-works/benefit-of-clergy-some-notes-on-salvador-dali/ &quot;Benefit of Clergy: Some Notes on Salvador Dalí&quot;]. theorwellprize.co.uk. Retrieved February 24, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; In a notable 1944 review of Dalí's autobiography, Orwell wrote, &quot;One ought to be able to hold in one's head simultaneously the two facts that Dalí is a good draughtsman and a disgusting human being&quot;.&lt;ref name=orwell&gt;Orwell, George [http://theorwellprize.co.uk/george-orwell/by-orwell/essays-and-other-works/benefit-of-clergy-some-notes-on-salvador-dali/ &quot;Benefit of Clergy: Some Notes on Salvador Dalí&quot;]. theorwellprize.co.uk. Retrieved February 24, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

After his return to [[Catalonia]] post World War II, Dalí moved closer to the [[authoritarian]] regime of [[Francisco Franco]]. Some of Dalí's statements were supportive, congratulating Franco for his actions aimed &quot;at clearing Spain of destructive forces&quot;.&lt;ref name=navarro&gt;Navarro, Vicente, PhD [http://www.counterpunch.org/navarro12062003.html &quot;The Jackboot of Dada: Salvador Dalí, Fascist&quot;]. ''Counterpunch''. December 6, 2003. Retrieved July 22, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Dalí, having returned to the Catholic faith and becoming increasingly religious as time went on, may have been referring to the [[Second Spanish Republic|Republican]] [[Spanish_Civil_War#Atrocities|atrocities during the Spanish Civil War]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://libro.uca.edu/payne2/payne26.htm |title=Payne, Stanley G. THE A History of Spain and Portugal, Vol. 2, Ch. 26, p. 648–651 (Print Edition: University of Wisconsin Press, 1973) (LIBRARY OF IBERIAN RESOURCES ONLINE Accessed May 15, 2007) |publisher=Libro.uca.edu |accessdate=August 22, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;De la Cueva, Julio, &quot;Religious Persecution, Anticlerical Tradition and Revolution: On Atrocities against the Clergy during the Spanish Civil War&quot;, ''Journal of Contemporary History'', Vol XXXIII – 3, 1998.&lt;/ref&gt; Dalí sent telegrams to Franco, praising him for signing [[death warrant]]s for prisoners.&lt;ref name=navarro /&gt; He even met Franco personally,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.andrewcusack.com/blog/2005/07/franco_jokes.php Salvador Dalí pictured with Francisco Franco]{{dead link|date=August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and painted a portrait of Franco's granddaughter.

He also once sent a telegram praising the ''Conducător'', [[Romania]]n [[Communist]] leader [[Nicolae Ceauşescu]], for his adoption of a [[scepter]] as part of his regalia. The Romanian daily newspaper ''[[Scînteia]]'' published it, without suspecting its mocking aspect. One of Dalí's few possible bits of open disobedience was his continued praise of [[Federico García Lorca]] even in the years when Lorca's works were banned.&lt;ref name=&quot;conversations&quot;/&gt;{{Failed verification|date=August 2009}}

Dalí, a colorful and imposing presence with his ever–present long cape, walking stick, haughty expression, and upturned waxed mustache, was famous for having said that &quot;every morning upon awakening, I experience a supreme pleasure: that of being Salvador Dalí&quot;.&lt;ref name=smithsonian&gt;[http://www.smithsonianmagazine.com/issues/2005/april/dali.php?page=3 The Surreal World of Salvador Dalí]. ''Smithsonian Magazine.'' 2005. Retrieved August 31, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; The entertainer [[Cher]] and her husband [[Sonny Bono]], when young, came to a party at Dalí's expensive residence in New York's [[Plaza Hotel]] and were startled when Cher sat down on an oddly shaped sexual vibrator left in an easy chair.{{citation needed|date=May 2012}} In the 1960s, he gave the actress [[Mia Farrow]] a dead mouse in a bottle, hand-painted, which her mother, actress [[Maureen O'Sullivan]], demanded be removed from her house.&lt;ref&gt;[http://lidogallery.wordpress.com/2012/03/23/salvador-dali-mia-farrow-a-surreal-friendship/ Dali and Mia Farrow a Surreal Fiendship]&lt;/ref&gt;

In his later years, while still remaining a Roman Catholic, Dalí also claimed to be an agnostic as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Salvador Dalí, 1904-1989|year=1994|publisher=Benedikt Taschen|isbn=9783822802984|coauthors=Robert Descharnes, Gilles Néret|accessdate=11 August 2012|page=166|quote=Dali, dualist as ever in his approach, was now claiming to be both an agnostic and a Roman Catholic.}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

When signing autographs for fans, Dalí would always keep their pens.{{citation needed|date=May 2012}} Salvador Dalí frequently traveled with his pet [[ocelot]] Babou, even bringing it aboard the luxury ocean liner ''[[SS France]]''.{{citation needed|date=May 2012}}

Besides visual puns, Dalí shared in the surrealist delight in verbal puns, obscure allusions, and word games.  He often spoke in a bizarre combination of French, Spanish, [[Catalan language|Catalan]], and English which was sometimes amusing as well as arcane.  His copious writings freely mixed words from different languages with terms entirely of his own devising.{{citation needed|date=May 2012}}

When interviewed by [[Mike Wallace (journalist)|Mike Wallace]] on his ''[[60 Minutes]]'' television show, Dalí kept referring to himself in the [[illeism|third person]], and told the startled Mr. Wallace matter-of-factly that &quot;Dalí is immortal and will not die&quot;. During another television appearance, on ''[[The Tonight Show]]'', Dalí carried with him a leather [[rhinoceros]] and refused to sit upon anything else.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}} In a late 1950s appearance on the panel show ''[[What's My Line?]]'', he was a mystery guest, and signed the chalkboard with thick white paint.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.retronaut.co/2011/07/whats-my-line-featuring-salvador-dali/ Dali on Whats my Line]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
Salvador Dalí has been cited as major inspiration from many modern artists, such as [[Damien Hirst]], [[Noel Fielding]], [[Jeff Koons]] and most other modern surrealists. Salvador Dalí's manic expression and famous moustache have made him something of a [[cultural icon]] for the bizarre and surreal.  He has been portrayed on film by [[Robert Pattinson]] in ''[[Little Ashes]]'', and [[Adrien Brody]] in ''[[Midnight in Paris]]''. He was also parodied in a series of painting skits on ''[[Captain Kangaroo]]'' as &quot;Salvador Silly&quot; (played by Cosmo Allegretti) and in a ''[[Sesame Street]]'' muppet skit as &quot;Salvador Dada&quot; (an orange gold AM performed by [[Jim Henson]]).

==Listing of selected works==
{{Main|List of works by Salvador Dalí}}
Dalí produced over 1,500 paintings in his career&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=The Salvador Dalí Online Exhibit | work=MicroVision | url=http://www.daliweb.tampa.fl.us/collection.htm | accessdate =June 13, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; in addition to producing illustrations for books, lithographs, designs for theatre sets and costumes, a great number of drawings, dozens of sculptures, and various other projects, including an animated short film for [[The Walt Disney Company|Disney]]. He also collaborated with director Jack Bond in 1965, creating a movie titled ''Dalí in New York''. Below is a chronological sample of important and representative work, as well as some notes on what Dalí did in particular years.&lt;ref name=Dali /&gt;

In Carlos Lozano's biography, ''Sex, Surrealism, Dalí, and Me'', produced with the collaboration of [[Clifford Thurlow]], Lozano makes it clear that Dalí never stopped being a surrealist. As Dalí said of himself: &quot;the only difference between me and the surrealists is that I am a surrealist.&quot;&lt;ref name=artcyclopedia /&gt;
*1910 ''[[Landscape Near Figueras]]''
*1913 ''[[Vilabertran (Dalí)|Vilabertin]]''
*1916 ''Fiesta in Figueras'' (begun 1914)
*1917 ''View of Cadaqués with Shadow of Mount Pani''
*1918 ''Crepuscular Old Man'' (begun 1917)
*1919 ''Port of Cadaqués (Night)'' (begun 1918) and ''Self-portrait in the Studio''
*1920 ''The Artist's Father at Llane Beach'' and ''View of Portdogué (Port Aluger)''
*1921 ''The Garden of Llaner (Cadaqués)'' (begun 1920) and ''Self-portrait''
*1922 ''[[Cabaret Scene]]'' and ''Night Walking Dreams''
*1923 ''Self Portrait with L'Humanite'' and ''Cubist Self Portrait with La Publicitat''
*1924 ''Still Life (Syphon and Bottle of Rum)'' (for [[García Lorca]]) and ''Portrait of [[Luis Buñuel]]''
*1925 ''Large Harlequin and Small Bottle of Rum'' and a series of fine portraits of his sister Anna Maria, most notably ''Figure at a Window''
*1926 ''[[The Basket of Bread]]'' and ''Girl from Figueres''
*1927 ''Composition with Three Figures (Neo-Cubist Academy)'' and ''Honey is Sweeter than Blood'' (his first important surrealist work)
*1929 {{lang|fr|''[[Un Chien Andalou]]''}} (''An Andalusian Dog'') film in collaboration with [[Luis Buñuel]], ''[[The Lugubrious Game]]'', ''[[The Great Masturbator]]'', ''[[The First Days of Spring]]'', and ''The Profanation of the Host''
*1930 {{lang|fr|''[[L'Age d'Or]]''}} (''The Golden Age'') film in collaboration with [[Luis Buñuel]]
*1931 ''[[The Persistence of Memory]]'' (his most famous work, featuring the &quot;melting clocks&quot;), ''The Old Age of William Tell'', and ''William Tell and [[Gradiva]]''
*1932 ''The Spectre of Sex Appeal'', ''The Birth of Liquid Desires'', ''Anthropomorphic Bread'', and ''Fried Eggs on the Plate without the Plate''. ''The Invisible Man'' (begun 1929) completed (although not to Dalí's own satisfaction)
*1933 ''Retrospective Bust of a Woman'' (mixed media sculpture [[collage]]) and ''Portrait of Gala With Two Lamb Chops Balanced on Her Shoulder'', ''Gala in the Window''
*1934 ''[[The Ghost of Vermeer of Delft Which Can Be Used As a Table]]'' and ''A Sense of Speed''
*1935 ''Archaeological Reminiscence of Millet's Angelus'' and ''The Face of [[Mae West]]''
*1936 ''Autumn Cannibalism'', ''[[Lobster Telephone]]'', ''[[Soft Construction with Boiled Beans (Premonition of Civil War)]]'' and two works titled ''[[Morphological Echo]]'' (the first of which began in 1934)
*1937 ''[[Metamorphosis of Narcissus]]'', ''[[Swans Reflecting Elephants]]'', ''[[The Burning Giraffe]]'', ''Sleep'', ''The Enigma of Hitler'', ''[[Mae West Lips Sofa]]'' and ''Cannibalism in Autumn''
*1938 ''The Sublime Moment'' and ''[[Apparition of Face and Fruit Dish on a Beach]]''
*1939 ''[[Shirley Temple, The Youngest, Most Sacred Monster of the Cinema in Her Time]]''
*1940 ''[[Slave Market with the Disappearing Bust of Voltaire]]'', ''[[The Face of War]]''
*1941 ''Honey is Sweeter than Blood''
*1943 ''The Poetry of America'' and ''[[Geopoliticus Child Watching the Birth of the New Man]]''
*1944 ''Galarina'' and ''[[Dream Caused by the Flight of a Bee around a Pomegranate a Second Before Awakening]]''
*1944–48 ''Hidden Faces'', a novel
*1945, ''[[Basket of Bread|Basket of Bread—Rather Death than Shame]]'' and ''Fountain of Milk Flowing Uselessly on Three Shoes''; also this year, Dalí collaborated with [[Alfred Hitchcock]] on a dream sequence to the film ''[[Spellbound (1945 film)|Spellbound]]'', to mutual dissatisfaction
*1946 ''The Temptation of St. Anthony''
*1948 ''Les Elephants''
*1949 ''[[Leda Atomica]]'' and ''[[The Madonna of Port Lligat]]''. Dalí returned to Catalonia this year
*1951 ''[[Christ of Saint John of the Cross]]'' and ''Exploding Raphaelesque Head''
*1951 [[Katharine Cornell]], a portrait of the famed actress
*1952 ''[[Galatea of the Spheres]]''
*1954 ''[[The Disintegration of the Persistence of Memory]]'' (begun in 1952), ''[[Crucifixion (Corpus Hypercubus)]]'' and ''[[Young Virgin Auto-Sodomized by the Horns of Her Own Chastity]]''
*1955 ''[[The Sacrament of the Last Supper]]'', ''Lonesome Echo'', record album cover for [[Jackie Gleason]]
*1956 ''[[Still Life Moving Fast]]'', ''Rinoceronte vestido con puntillas''
*1957 ''[[Santiago el Grande]]'' oil on canvas on permanent display at Beaverbrook Art Gallery in Fredericton, NB, Canada
*1958 ''The Meditative Rose''
*1959 ''[[The Discovery of America by Christopher Columbus]]''
*1960 ''Composición Numérica (de fond préparatoire inachevé)]''
*1960 Dalí began work on the [[Dalí Theatre and Museum|Teatro-Museo Gala Salvador Dalí]] and ''Portrait of [[Juan de Pareja]], the Assistant to Velázquez''
*1963–1964 ''They Will All Come from Saba'' a work in water color depicting the Magi at St. Petersburg's Dali Museum
*1965 Dalí donates a [[gouache]], ink and pencil drawing of the Crucifixion to the [[Rikers Island]] jail in New York City. The drawing hung in the inmate dining room from 1965 to 1981&lt;ref name=&quot;jail&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/2812683.stm | title=Dalí picture sprung from jail |publisher=BBC   | date=March 2, 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*1965 ''Dalí in New York''
*1967 ''[[Tuna Fishing]]''
*1969 [[Chupa Chups]] logo
*1969 ''Improvisation on a Sunday Afternoon'', television collaboration with the rock group [[Nirvana (UK band)|Nirvana]]
*1970 ''[[The Hallucinogenic Toreador]]'', acquired in 1969 by [[A. Reynolds Morse &amp; Eleanor R. Morse]] before it was completed
*1972 ''[[La Toile Daligram]]'', ''[[Helena Devlin Diakonoff - dit., GALA|Helena Devulina Diakanoff – dit., GALA]]''
*1973 &quot;Le Diners De Gala&quot;, an ornately illustrated cook book
*1976 ''[[Gala Contemplating the Mediterranean Sea]]''
*1977 ''Dalí's Hand Drawing Back the Golden Fleece in the Form of a Cloud to Show Gala Completely Nude, Very Far Away Behind the Sun'' ([[Stereoscopy|stereoscopical]] pair of paintings)
*1983 Dalí completes his final painting, ''[[The Swallow's Tail]]''
*2003 {{lang|es|''[[Destino]]''}}, an animated short film originally a collaboration between Dalí and [[Walt Disney]], is released. Production on {{lang|es|''Destino''}} began in 1945

The largest collections of Dalí's work are at the [[Dalí Theatre and Museum]] in Figueres, Catalonia, Spain, followed by the [[Salvador Dalí Museum]] in [[St. Petersburg, Florida|St. Petersburg]], Florida, which contains the collection of [[A. Reynolds Morse &amp; Eleanor R. Morse]]. It holds over 1,500 works from Dalí. Other particularly significant collections include the [[Museo Nacional Centro de Arte Reina Sofia|Reina Sofia Museum]] in Madrid and the Salvador Dalí Gallery in [[Pacific Palisades, California|Pacific Palisades]], California. [[Espace Dalí]] in [[Montmartre]], Paris, France, as well as the [[Dalí Universe]] in London, England, contain a large collection of his drawings and sculptures.

The unlikeliest venue for Dalí's work was the [[Rikers Island]] jail in New York City; a sketch of the [[Crucifixion]] he donated to the jail hung in the inmate dining room for 16 years before it was moved to the prison lobby for safekeeping. Ironically, the drawing was stolen from that location in March 2003 and has not been recovered.&lt;ref name=&quot;jail&quot; /&gt;

==Dalí museums and permanent exhbitions==
*[[Dalí Theatre and Museum]] – in [[Figueres]], [[Catalonia]]
*[[Dalí Universe]] (closed in 2010) – in [[London]], England
*[[Salvador Dali Museum]] – in [[St Petersburg, Florida]], [[USA]]
*[[Espace Dalí]] – in [[Paris]], France
*[http://www.daliberlin.de/en Dalí], a permanent exhibition - in [[Berlin]], Germany

==Major temporary exhibitions==
&lt;!-- Reference exhibition catalog and/or exhibition website, if possible --&gt;
*''The Dalí Renaissance: New Perspectives on His Life and Art after 1940'' (2005) [[Philadelphia Museum of Art]]&lt;ref name=Taylor&gt;{{cite book|last=Taylor|first=edited by Michael R.|title=The Dalí renaissance : new perspectives on his life and art after 1940 : an international symposium|year=2008|publisher=Philadelphia Museum of Art, distributed by Yale University Press|location=New Haven, Conn.|isbn=9780300136470|url=http://www.philamuseum.org/publications/377-1-31012.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Dalí. Gala.JPG|''Gala in the Window'' (1933)&lt;br /&gt;[[Marbella]].
Image:Dalí.Rinoceronte.JPG|''Rinoceronte vestido con puntillas'' (1956)&lt;br /&gt;[[Puerto José Banús]].
File:Plaza de Dalí (Madrid) 08.jpg|''Plaza de Dalí'' (''Dalí Square''), [[Madrid]]
File:Dalí.Perseo.JPG|''Perseo'' (''[[Perseus]]'') &lt;br /&gt;[[Marbella]].
File:Children-at-Dali-exibition.jpg|Children at Dalí exhibition in [[Sakıp Sabancı Museum]], [[Istanbul]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
*''[[Little Ashes]]''
*[http://www.artchive.com/artchive/D/dali.html#images A list of Salvador Dali Images on the Web]

==Notes==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
*Linde Sabler. &quot;Dalí&quot;. London: Haus Publishing, 2004 (paperback, ISBN 978-1-904341-75-8).
*[http://www.hrc.utexas.edu/multimedia/video/2008/wallace/dali_salvador.html Salvador Dali] interviewed by [[Mike Wallace (journalist)|Mike Wallace]] on ''The Mike Wallace Interview'' April 19, 1985

==External links==
{{Commons}}
{{Wikiquote}}

;Biographies and news
*[http://www.smh.com.au/articles/2003/07/04/1057179156682.html Dalí's surreal wind-powered organ lacks only a rhinoceros]
*[http://www.ubu.com/sound/dali.html UbuWeb: Salvador Dalí]—Interview and bank advertisement.
*[http://www.ina.fr/recherche/recherche?search=dali&amp;vue=Video Salvador Dalí in the INA Archives] – A collection of interviews and footage of Dalí in the French television

;Other links
* [http://www.lletra.net/en/author/salvador-dali Literary news about Salvador Dalí in Lletra, Catalan literature online at the Open University of Catalonia.]
* [http://www.doubletakeart.com/cgi-bin/dtg/dtg.psearch?name=Salvador+Dali&amp;a1=00133 The Image Library of prints by Salvador Dali]
*[http://www.robertwhitakerphotography.com Robert Whitaker, Photographer, took many great images of Dali]
*{{MoMA artist|1364}}
*[http://www.firstthings.com/onthesquare/?p=922 Article on Dalí's religious faith]
*[http://www.daliphoto.com The Salvador Dalí photo library 60.000 photos]
*[http://www.overgrownpath.com/2010/10/salvador-dalis-lost-opera.html Article on Dalí's opera poem ''Être Dieu: opéra-poème, audiovisuel et cathare en six parties'' (Being God: a Cathar Audiovisual Opera-Poem in Six Parts)]
*[http://tesla.liketelevision.com/liketelevision/tuner.php?channel=1099&amp;format=movie&amp;theme=guide Watch Un Chien Andalou] at LikeTelevision
*[http://www.salvador-dali.org/en_index.html Gala-Salvador Dalí Foundation English language site]
*[http://www.thedali.org St. Petersburg Dalí Museum]
*Kurutz, Steven, [http://blogs.wsj.com/speakeasy/2011/01/11/hello-dali-surrealist-museum-becomes-a-reality/ &quot;Hello, Dali: Surrealist Museum Becomes a Reality&quot;], ''The Wall Street Journal'' Speakeasy blog, January 11, 2011, 4:46&amp;nbsp;pm ET. Interview with [[St. Petersburg]] ([[Florida|FL]]) museum director Dr. Hank Hine about new building.
*[http://sapiens.ya.com/fagesdecliment/subpages/gibson1.htm &quot;The shameful life of Salvador Dalí&quot; (the witches of Llers)&quot;].
*[http://www.salvador-dali.org/serveis/ced/articles/en_article6.html Dalí and Fages: &quot;that intelligent and most cordial of collaborations&quot;]
*[http://www.salvadorbrand.com/Salvador-Brand/the-lithograph.html &quot;El Triomf I el Rodoli de la Gala I en Dali&quot; ]
*[http://www.bernardewell.com/2012/04/not-by-dali/ &quot;Not by Dali -- blog post by art appraiser and Dali expert Bernard Ewell&quot;]

;Exhibitions
*[http://www.daliparis.com [[Espace Dalí]]]—The unique permanent exhibition in France (Museum &amp; Dalí Fine Art Galleries)
*[http://www.tate.org.uk/modern/exhibitions/daliandfilm/default.shtm Dalí &amp; Film – Tate Modern, London]
*[http://www.dali-interart.be/ Museum-Gallery Xpo: Salvador Dalí, Marquis de Púbol] in [[Bruges]]
*[http://www.moma.org/calendar/events.php?id=9709&amp;ref=calendar Museum of Modern Art]
*[http://www.getty.edu/vow/ULANFullDisplay?find=salvador+dali&amp;role=&amp;nation=&amp;prev_page=1&amp;subjectid=500009365 Union List of Artist Names, Getty Vocabularies.] ULAN Full Record Display for Salvador Dalí. Getty Vocabulary Program, Getty Research Institute. Los Angeles, California.

{{Normdaten|LCCN=n/79/21554|VIAF=64004109}}
{{Salvador Dalí}}

{{Persondata
|NAME=Dalí, Salvador
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=Dalí, Salvador Felip Jacint, Domènech; Dalí, Salvador Felipe Jacinto, Domènech
|SHORT DESCRIPTION=20th century Catalan surrealist artist
|DATE OF BIRTH=May 11, 1904
|PLACE OF BIRTH=Figueres, Catalonia, Spain
|DATE OF DEATH=January 23, 1989
|PLACE OF DEATH=Figueres, Catalonia, Spain
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Dali, Salvador}}
[[Category:1904 births]]
[[Category:1989 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Figueres]]
[[Category:Salvador Dalí| ]]
[[Category:Catalan artists]]
[[Category:Catalan painters]]
[[Category:Légion d'honneur recipients]]
[[Category:Marquesses of Spain]]
[[Category:Modern artists]]
[[Category:Modern painters]]
[[Category:People with Parkinson's disease]]
[[Category:Spanish agnostics]]
[[Category:Spanish printmakers]]
[[Category:Spanish Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:Surrealist artists]]
[[Category:20th-century painters]]

{{Link FA|af}}
{{Link FA|de}}
{{Link FA|hr}}
{{Link FA|sl}}
{{Link GA|es}}

[[kbd:Салвадор Дали]]
[[af:Salvador Dalí]]
[[als:Salvador Dalí]]
[[ab:Салвадор Дали]]
[[ar:سلفادور دالي]]
[[an:Salvador Dalí]]
[[arc:ܣܠܒܐܕܘܪ ܕܐܠܝ]]
[[as:চালভাদ'ৰ দালি]]
[[az:Salvador Dali]]
[[bn:সালভাদোর দালি]]
[[zh-min-nan:Salvador Dalí]]
[[be:Сальвадор Далі]]
[[be-x-old:Сальвадор Далі]]
[[bg:Салвадор Дали]]
[[bo:སལ་ཝ་ཌོར་དཱ་ལི།]]
[[bs:Salvador Dali]]
[[br:Salvador Dalí]]
[[ca:Salvador Dalí i Domènech]]
[[cs:Salvador Dalí]]
[[cy:Salvador Dalí]]
[[da:Salvador Dali]]
[[de:Salvador Dalí]]
[[et:Salvador Dalí]]
[[el:Σαλβαδόρ Νταλί]]
[[es:Salvador Dalí]]
[[eo:Salvador Dalí]]
[[eu:Salvador Dalí]]
[[fa:سالوادور دالی]]
[[hif:Salvador Dalí]]
[[fr:Salvador Dalí]]
[[fy:Salvador Dalí]]
[[ga:Salvador Dalí]]
[[gl:Salvador Dalí]]
[[gan:答利]]
[[got:𐍃𐌰𐌻𐍅𐌰𐌳𐌰𐌿𐍂 𐌳𐌰𐌻𐌹]]
[[ko:살바도르 달리]]
[[hy:Սալվադոր Դալի]]
[[hi:सेल्वाडोर दाली]]
[[hr:Salvador Dalí]]
[[io:Salvador Dalí]]
[[ilo:Salvador Dali]]
[[bpy:সালভাদর দালি]]
[[id:Salvador Dalí]]
[[ia:Salvador Dalí]]
[[is:Salvador Dalí]]
[[it:Salvador Dalí]]
[[he:סלבדור דאלי]]
[[jv:Salvador Dalí]]
[[kl:Salvador Dalí]]
[[kn:ಸಾಲ್ವಡರ್ ಡಾಲಿ]]
[[pam:Salvador Dali]]
[[ka:სალვადორ დალი]]
[[kw:Salvador Dalí]]
[[sw:Salvador Dali]]
[[ku:Salvador Dalí]]
[[lez:Салвадор Дали]]
[[la:Salvator Dalí]]
[[lv:Salvadors Dalī]]
[[lb:Salvador Dalí]]
[[lt:Salvadoras Dali]]
[[li:Salvador Dalí]]
[[lmo:Salvador Dalí]]
[[hu:Salvador Dalí]]
[[mk:Салвадор Дали]]
[[ml:സാൽവദോർ ദാലി]]
[[mr:साल्व्हादोर दाली]]
[[xmf:სალვადორ დალი]]
[[arz:سالفادور دالى]]
[[ms:Salvador Dalí]]
[[mn:Сальвадор Дали]]
[[nah:Salvador Dalí]]
[[nl:Salvador Dalí]]
[[new:साल्भाडोर् डाली]]
[[ja:サルバドール・ダリ]]
[[no:Salvador Dalí]]
[[nn:Salvador Dalí]]
[[oc:Salvador Dalí]]
[[mhr:Сальвадор Дали]]
[[uz:Salvador Dalí]]
[[pag:Salvador Dalí]]
[[pnb:سیلوادور ڈالی]]
[[pms:Salvador Dalí]]
[[nds:Salvador Dalí]]
[[pl:Salvador Dalí]]
[[pt:Salvador Dalí]]
[[kaa:Salvador Dalí]]
[[ro:Salvador Dalí]]
[[qu:Salvador Dalí]]
[[rue:Салвадор Далі]]
[[ru:Дали, Сальвадор]]
[[sah:Салвадор Дали]]
[[sq:Salvador Dalí]]
[[scn:Salvador Dalí]]
[[simple:Salvador Dalí]]
[[sk:Salvador Dalí]]
[[sl:Salvador Dalí]]
[[so:Salvador Dalí]]
[[ckb:سەلڤادۆر دالی]]
[[srn:Salvador Dalí]]
[[sr:Салвадор Дали]]
[[sh:Salvador Dalí]]
[[fi:Salvador Dalí]]
[[sv:Salvador Dalí]]
[[ta:சல்வடோர் டாலி]]
[[te:సాల్వడార్ డాలీ]]
[[th:ซัลบาดอร์ ดาลี]]
[[tr:Salvador Dalí]]
[[uk:Сальвадор Далі]]
[[ur:سیلواڈور ڈالی]]
[[za:Salvador Dalí]]
[[vec:Salvador Dalí]]
[[vi:Salvador Dalí]]
[[vo:Salvador Dalí]]
[[war:Salvador Dalí]]
[[yi:סאלוואדאר דאלי]]
[[yo:Salvador Dalí]]
[[zh-yue:達利]]
[[bat-smg:Salvaduors Dali]]
[[zh:萨尔瓦多·达利]]</text>
      <sha1>icsxs0fha3vhrqxfkng4kb2pn9yyuwf</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
