<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Scott Peterson</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1163228</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521002107</id>
      <parentid>519237575</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T03:53:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>68.55.123.86</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Sentencing */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26247">{{distinguish2|[[Drew Peterson]], an individual with a similar case}} 
{{other persons}}

{{Infobox criminal
|image_name = Spetersonmug1.1.jpg
| name = Scott Lee Peterson
| image_size = 150px
| image_caption =
| birth_date = {{Birth date and age|1972|10|24}}
| birth_place = [[San Diego]], [[California]]
| death_date =
| death_place =
| alias =
| conviction = First degree [[murder]] in the death of Laci; second degree murder in the death of Conner 
| conviction_penalty = [[Capital punishment|Death sentence]]
| conviction_status = [[Incarceration|Incarcerated]] in [[San Quentin State Prison]]
| occupation =
| spouse = {{marriage|Laci Peterson|1997|2002}}
| parents =Jacqueline Helen Latham and Lee Arthur Peterson
}}

'''Scott Lee Peterson''' (born October 24, 1972) is an American convicted of murdering his wife, [[Murder of Laci Peterson|Laci Peterson]], and their unborn son in [[Modesto, California]], in 2002. Peterson's arrest and subsequent trial received significant American [[news media]] coverage until 2005, when he was [[capital punishment|sentenced to death]] by [[lethal injection]]. He remains on [[death row]] in [[San Quentin State Prison]] while his case is on appeal to the [[Supreme Court of California]]. He maintains his innocence.

==Early life==
Peterson was born in [[San Diego]], [[California]], to Lee Arthur Peterson (born May 9, 1939) and his wife, the former Jacqueline Helen Latham (born September 16, 1943).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wargs.com/other/peterson.html |title=Ancestry of Conner Peterson |publisher=Wargs.com |date= |accessdate= November 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Peterson's father worked for a trucking company, and later owned a crate-packaging business. His mother owned a boutique in the community of [[La Jolla, California|La Jolla]], called The Put On.

Peterson attended the [[University of San Diego High School]] (now Cathedral Catholic High School) and studied briefly at [[Arizona State University]] and [[Cuesta College]] before transferring to [[California Polytechnic State University]] at [[San Luis Obispo]], where he graduated with a [[Bachelor of Arts|B.A.]] in [[agribusiness|agricultural business]] in 1997. He worked in a cafe as a waiter while attending Cal Poly, when he met Laci Denise Rocha. The couple married in August 1997.

==Disappearance of Laci Peterson==
{{Main|Murder of Laci Peterson}}
On December 24, 2002, Laci Peterson was [[missing person|reported missing]] from their [[Modesto, California]], home. She was eight months pregnant&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn/A10074-2004Dec18?language=printer |title=8 months pregnant |work= Washington Post |date= |accessdate= June 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; with a due date of February 10, 2003, and the couple had planned to name the baby, a boy, Conner Peterson. The exact date and cause of Laci's death was never determined. Peterson initially reported his wife missing on Christmas Eve, and the story quickly attracted nationwide media interest.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nndb.com/people/468/000026390/ |title= Scott Peterson |publisher=Notable Names Database}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/4008491.stm |title=US beach bodies killer convicted |publisher=BBC News |date= November 12, 2004 |accessdate= June 21, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Modesto police did not immediately identify Peterson as a suspect, largely because Laci's family and friends maintained their faith in his innocence during the month following Laci's disappearance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.trutv.com/library/crime/notorious_murders/family/laci_peterson/11.html |title=The Murder of Laci Peterson |publisher=Trutv.com |date= |accessdate= June 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eventually, police grew more suspicious due to inconsistencies in his story. On January 17, it became known that Peterson had had numerous extramarital affairs,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.courttv.com/trials/peterson/092704-pm_ctv.html |title=Before Frey, two other affairs for Peterson, detective says |publisher=Courttv.com |date= |accessdate= November 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; most recently with a massage therapist named Amber Frey. Frey approached police about Peterson, whom she had just begun to date, after discovering he was actually married to a missing woman. At this point, Laci's family announced that they had withdrawn their support of Peterson. They later said that they were angered not by the affair, but that Peterson had told Frey that he'd &quot;lost&quot; his wife and that he would be spending his first Christmas without his wife — 14 days before Laci disappeared. To the Rochas, this meant that Peterson had already planned to kill Laci long before her disappearance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=For Laci |last=Rocha |first=Sharon  |year=2006|publisher=[[Crown Publishers]] |location= New York |isbn=0-307-33828-2 |pages= }}{{page needed|date=July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Frey became a key witness in the case against Peterson when she agreed to let the police tape their subsequent phone conversations in hopes of getting him to [[confession (law)|confess]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.courttv.com/trials/peterson/111203-pm_ctv.html |title=Detective: Peterson's mistress agreed to tape phone calls |publisher=Courttv.Com |date= |accessdate= November 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite this, Peterson was not recorded making any confession to Frey.

Frey told the police that two weeks before Laci's disappearance, Peterson had implied to her that he was a widower by saying that he had &quot;lost his wife.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.courttv.com/trials/peterson/110603_ctv.html |title=Detective: Peterson told lover he was a widower weeks before wife disappeared |publisher=Courttv.Com |date= |accessdate= November 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the trial, the audio recordings of Peterson and Frey's telephone conversations were played, and the transcripts were publicized. Their contents proved to be both revealing and, ultimately, damning to Peterson's character. For example, they revealed that in the days after Laci went missing, Peterson claimed to Amber that he had traveled to Paris to celebrate the holidays, in part with his new companions Pasqual and François. In reality, Peterson made one of these phone calls while attending the New Year's Eve candlelight vigil in Modesto for his missing wife.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Laci Peterson Case: Scott Peterson's Ex-Mistress Testifies |publisher=CNN  |url=http://www.cnn.com/2007/US/law/12/11/court.archive.peterson5/index.html |accessdate=June 11, 2008 |date= December 31, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Recovery of body===
On April 14, 2003, the remains of a fetus washed ashore from [[San Francisco Bay]] in [[Richmond, California|Richmond's]] [[Point Isabel Regional Shoreline]],&lt;ref name=&quot;ptisabel&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.cnn.com/2003/US/West/04/18/remains.found/ |title= Laci Peterson's remains identified; husband arrested |publisher= CNN |date= April 18, 2003 |accessdate= September 23, 2007 |deadurl=yes}}{{dead link|date=June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; north of the [[Berkeley Marina]], where Peterson had been boating the day of Laci's disappearance. The next day, a partial female torso missing its hands, feet, and head washed ashore in the same area. The body was identified as Laci Peterson, the fetus as Laci's unborn child. [[Autopsy|Autopsies]] were performed, but due to decomposition the specific cause of death could not be determined. The medical examiner did note that Laci had suffered some broken ribs (the 5th, 6th, and 9th ribs) prior to her death; these injuries were not caused by the body's dragging along the rocks in the bay. Prosecutors theorized that Laci may have been suffocated or strangled in the couple's home.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.courttv.com/trials/peterson/110104_closings_ctv.html |title=In closing, prosecutor says parenthood pushed Peterson to kill  |publisher=Courttv.com |date= |accessdate= November 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Federal Bureau of Investigation|FBI]] and Modesto Police Department performed forensic searches of the couple's home, Peterson's truck, the tool box in the back of his truck, his warehouse, and his boat.

==Arrest==
Peterson was arrested on April 18, 2003, in [[La Jolla]], California, in the parking lot of the [[Torrey Pines Golf Course]], where he said he was meeting his father and brother for a game of golf. At the time of his arrest, Peterson was in possession of the following non-golf specific items:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://crime.about.com/od/news/a/peterson_car.htm |title=Items Found in Peterson's Car |publisher=Crime.about.com |date= April 18, 2003 |accessdate= November 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Div col|cols=2}}
* approximately $10,000 in cash
* Four cell phones
* multiple credit cards belonging to various members of his family
* an array of camping equipment, including knives, implements for warming food, tents and tarpaulins and a water purifier
* a dozen pairs of shoes
* several changes of clothing
* a T-handled double-edged dagger
* a [[MapQuest]] map to Frey's workplace (printed the previous day)
* a shovel
* 2 ropes
* 200 blister packs of sleeping pills
* [[Sildenafil|Viagra]]
* his brother's driver license and a picture of his wife
{{Div col end}}
His hair and goatee had been dyed blond, although he claimed the lighter hair color was the result of chlorine from swimming in a friend's pool. The pool's owner later testified that, to his knowledge, Peterson had never swum in his pool nor made use of his hot tub.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Ryan |first=Harriet |title=Expert Connects Scott Peterson's Fishing Route to Unborn Son's Remains |date=October 5, 2004
 |url=http://www.courttv.com/trials/peterson/100404_ctv.html |accessdate=June 11, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Trial==
Peterson had been represented before his arraignment by Kirk McAllister, a veteran criminal defense attorney from Modesto, California. Peterson told Judge Nancy Ashley at arraignment that he could not afford a private attorney.

Chief Deputy Public Defender Kent Faulkner was also assigned to the case.&lt;ref name=Finz&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/c/a/2003/05/03/MN122043.DTL |title= L.A. attorney says client wants to vindicate himself by finding killer |last= Finz |first= Stacy |date= May 3, 2003 |work= San Francisco Chronicle |accessdate= May 1, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Peterson later indicated that he could afford a private attorney [[Mark Geragos]], who had done other high-profile criminal defense work.&lt;ref name=Finz /&gt;
A judge moved Peterson's trial from Modesto to [[Redwood City, California]] on January 20, 2004, due to increasing hostility toward Peterson in the Modesto area.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,108939,00.html |title= Judge Moves Peterson Trial to San Mateo County |agency= Associated Press |date= January 20, 2004 |publisher= [[Fox News]] |accessdate= May 1, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The trial, ''the People of the State of California v. Scott Peterson'', began in June 2004 and was followed closely by the media. The lead prosecutor was [[Rick Distaso]]. Geragos led Peterson's defense.

Prosecution witness Amber Frey engaged her own attorney, [[Gloria Allred]], to represent her interests. Allred was not bound by the [[gag order]] imposed on those involved in the trial. Although she maintained that her client had no opinion about whether Peterson was guilty, Allred was openly sympathetic to the prosecution. She appeared frequently on television news programs during the trial.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.courttv.com/talk/chat_transcripts/2004/0924peterson-allred.html |title= The Scott Peterson Murder Trial |publisher= Courttv.com |date= |accessdate= November 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Allred played a key role in keeping many facts about her client's past from the public eye.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://transcripts.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/0311/13/lkl.00.html |title= Transcripts |publisher= CNN |date= November 13, 2003 |accessdate= November 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Peterson's defense lawyers based their case on the lack of [[direct evidence]] and played down the significance of [[circumstantial evidence]].&lt;ref name = &quot;courttv-060204&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.courttv.com/trials/peterson/060204_ctv.html |title=TRIALS - Two-timer, yes, but no double murderer: Peterson's defense lays out its case |publisher=Courttv.Com |date= |accessdate=2010-11-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; They suggested that the fetal remains were of a full-term infant and theorized that someone kidnapped Laci, held her until she gave birth, and then dumped both bodies in the bay. The prosecution's medical experts proved that the baby was not full term and died at the same time as his mother.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.courttv.com/trials/peterson/092204_ctv.html |title=Peterson's unborn son died at time of his wife's disappearance, expert says  |publisher=Courttv.com |date= |accessdate= November 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Geragos suggested that a Satanic cult kidnapped the pregnant woman.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first= C. Spencer |last= Beggs |url= http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,89038,00.html |title= Experts: No Proof of Satanic Cults |publisher=Fox News |date= June 10, 2003 |accessdate= November 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also claimed that Peterson was &quot;a [[Rake (character)|cad]]&quot;&lt;ref name = &quot;courttv-060204&quot;/&gt; for cheating on his pregnant wife but not a [[murderer]].

One juror was removed early in the trial due to [[misconduct]] and was replaced, this on a complaint by [[truTV|CourtTV]]. A videotape showed the juror and Brent Rocha, Laci Peterson's older brother, speaking as they passed one another in the courthouse.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.people.com/people/article/0,,656971,00.html |title= Juror Removed from Scott Peterson Trial |last1= Dodd |first1= Johnny |first1= Serena |last2= Kappes |date= June 23, 2004 |work= [[People (magazine)|People]] |accessdate= May 1, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jury foreman and attorney Gregory Jackson later requested his own removal during jury deliberations, most likely because his fellow jurors wanted to replace him as foreman.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.cnn.com/2004/LAW/11/10/peterson.trial |title= Source: Jury foreman dismissed in Peterson case |publisher= CNN |date= November 11, 2004 |accessdate= November 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Geragos told reporters that Jackson had mentioned threats he received when he requested to be removed from the jury.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.courttv.com/trials/peterson/112204_ctv.html |title= Peterson penalty phase postponed until after Thanksgiving |publisher=Courttv.com |date= |accessdate= November 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jackson was also replaced by an alternate. On November 12 the reconstituted jury convicted Peterson of [[murder#The United States|first-degree murder]] with special circumstances for killing Laci and second-degree murder for killing the fetus she carried. The [[Bifurcation (law)|penalty phase]] of the trial began on November 30 and concluded December 13 when, at 1:50 P.M. PST, the twelve-person jury recommended a [[Capital punishment|death sentence]] for Peterson.

Members of the jury stated in later press appearances that they felt that Peterson's demeanor{{spaced ndash}}specifically, his lack of emotion and the phone calls to Amber Frey in the days following Laci's disappearance{{spaced ndash}}indicated he was guilty. They based their verdict on &quot;hundreds of small 'puzzle pieces' of circumstantial evidence that came out during the trial, from the location of Laci Peterson's body to the myriad lies her husband told after her disappearance.&quot; They also decided on the death penalty because they felt Peterson betrayed his responsibility to protect his wife and son.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.courttv.com/trials/peterson/121304_jurors_ctv.html |title= Peterson jurors speak about guilty verdict, death sentence |publisher= Courttv.com |date= |accessdate= November 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Evidence===
The only piece of forensic evidence identified was a single hair, thought to have been Laci's, found in a pair of pliers from Peterson's boat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://writ.news.findlaw.com/hilden/20040720.html  |title=The Scott Peterson Trial  |publisher=Writ.news.findlaw.com |date= July 20, 2004 |accessdate= June 21, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Peterson changed his appearance and purchased a vehicle using his mother's name in order to avoid recognition by the press. He added two [[pornographic]] television channels to his cable service only days after his wife's disappearance;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.courttv.com/trials/peterson/080304_ctv.html |title= Prosecutors: Peterson signed up for porn channels after wife vanished |publisher= Courttv.com |date= |accessdate= November 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; the prosecution suggested that this meant Peterson knew his wife would not be returning home. He expressed interest in selling the house he had shared with his wife,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.courttv.com/trials/peterson/082504_ctv.html |title= Taped phone calls catch Scott Peterson in numerous lies to family, friends |publisher= Courttv.com |date= |accessdate= November 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and he sold Laci's [[Land Rover]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,84562,00.html |title= Body Identified as Laci Peterson; Scott Peterson Arrested in San Diego |last= Cosby |first= Rita |agency=Associated Press |date= April 19, 2003 |publisher=Fox News |accessdate= May 1, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Testimony for the prosecution included Rick Cheng, a [[Hydrology|hydrologist]] with the [[United States Geological Survey]], and an [[expert witness]] on tides, particularly of the [[San Francisco Bay]]. Cheng admitted during his cross-examination that his findings were &quot;probable, not precise&quot;;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2004/10/05/national/main647611.shtml |title= Laci Dumped At Scott Fishing Spot?: But Prosecution Expert Can't Be Certain About The Location |last= de Vries |first= Lloyd |date=October 4, 2004|publisher=[[CBS News]] |accessdate= May 1, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; tidal systems are sufficiently chaotic, and he was unable to develop an exact [[scientific modelling|model]] of the bodies' disposal and travel. The prosecution explored an affair by the defendant with Amber Frey, and the contents of their taped telephone calls.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.smh.com.au/articles/2004/08/23/1093113128828.html?from=storylhs |title= 'Love triangle' murder trial captivates US |date= August 23, 2004 |work= [[Sydney Morning Herald]] |accessdate= May 1, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The defense suggested a prostitute accused of stealing checks from Peterson's mailbox may have murdered Laci, but Modesto police Detective Mike Hermosa did not indicate the prostitute was ever a suspect in Laci Peterson's disappearance. Prosecutor Dave Harris noted that the checks were stolen after Laci vanished, meaning the woman was not involved in her disappearance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2004/07/22/national/main631386.shtml |title= Concrete Found In Peterson Home |accessdate= Aubust 20, 2011 |publisher= CBS News}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Geragos seemed quite confident that Dr. Charles March could single-handedly [[exoneration|exonerate]] Peterson by showing that the fetus Laci carried died a week after prosecutors claimed. Under cross-examination, March admitted basing his findings on an anecdote from one of Laci's friends that she had taken a home pregnancy test on June 9, 2002. &quot;Prosecutors pointed out that no medical records relied on the June 9 date and March became flustered and confused on the stand{{spaced ndash}}and even asked a prosecutor to cut him 'some slack'{{spaced ndash}}undermining his credibility.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4176/is_20041027/ai_n14587325 |title= 'Weak' Peterson defense rests |work= Oakland Tribune }} {{dead link|date=November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Summing up this key defense witness, Stan Goldman, a criminal law professor at [[Loyola Law School]] in [[Los Angeles]] said, &quot;There were moments today that reminded me of [[Chernobyl disaster|Chernobyl]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4176/is_20041022/ai_n14586674 |title= Fetus age debated in Peterson trial |work= Oakland Tribune}} {{dead link|date=November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  According to one newspaper account about Dr. March's testimony, &quot;But by the end of his testimony Thursday, legal analysts and jurors closed their notebooks, rolled their eyes, and snickered when they thought no one was looking.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= Defense witness asks D.A. to cut him slack: Expert says fetus died days after mother disappeared |first1=Stacy |last1= Finz |first2= Diana |last2= Walsh |date= October 22, 2004 |url= http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2004/10/22/BAGNB9E4PG37.DTL |accessdate= July 6, 2012 |work=The San Francisco Chronicle}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Motives===
The prosecution presented Scott Peterson's affair with Amber Frey and money as a motive for the murder. Prosecutors surmised that Peterson killed his pregnant wife due to increasing debt and a desire to be single again.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.foxreno.com/news/3430205/detail.html |title= June 17: Was Money The Motive For Murder? |date= June 24, 2010 |location= Reno, NV |publisher= [[KRXI-TV]] |accessdate= May 1, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sentencing===
[[File:SanQuentinSP.jpg|thumb|[[San Quentin State Prison]], where Peterson is incarcerated]]
On March 16, 2005, Judge Alfred A. Delucchi formally [[sentence (law)|sentenced]] Peterson to death, calling the murder of his wife &quot;cruel, uncaring, heartless, and callous&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.courttv.com/trials/peterson/031605_ctv.html |title=Judge sentences Scott Peterson to death for killing his wife and unborn son |publisher=Courttv.com |date= |accessdate= November 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The prescribed method of execution was [[lethal injection]]. He also denied the defense's request (which was based on evidence of juror misconduct and media influence) for a new trial and ordered Peterson to pay $10,000 toward the cost of Laci Peterson's funeral.

In the early morning hours of March 17, 2005, Peterson arrived at [[San Quentin State Prison]]. Peterson was reported not to have slept the night before, being too &quot;jazzed&quot; to sleep, calling some to question his state of mind.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.cnn.com/2005/LAW/03/17/peterson.prison/index.html | publisher= CNN | title=Prison: Two women want to marry Peterson | date=March 18, 2005 | accessdate=May 23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/7217582/ |title= Scott Peterson sent to San Quentin |publisher=MSNBC |date= March 18, 2005 |accessdate= June 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Peterson joined other inmates in California's sole [[death row]] facility while his case is on automatic appeal to the [[Supreme Court of California]] in [[San Francisco, California|San Francisco]]. ''[[National Geographic Channel|National Geographic]]'' made a documentary on San Quentin prison, with Scott Peterson's admission to the prison covered in its Part Two.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=k5fbslBqVts ]{{dead link|date=June 2011}}, National Geographic San Quentin part 2 of 6&lt;/ref&gt;

After eight years, on July 6, 2012, Peterson's lawyer, Cliff Gardner, filed a 423-page appeal of his sentence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.foxnews.com/us/2012/07/06/scott-peterson-appeals-death-sentence-to-california-supreme-court |title= Scott Peterson appeals death sentence to California Supreme Court |publisher=Fox News |date= July 6, 2012|accessdate= July 6, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Media portrayals ==

In 2004, Peterson was played by [[Dean Cain]] in ''[[The Perfect Husband: The Laci Peterson Story]]''. 

In 2005, he was portrayed by Nathan Anderson in another TV movie, ''Amber Frey: Witness for the Prosecution''.

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite book |title= We, the Jury: Deciding the Scott Peterson Case |first1= Greg |last1= Beratlis |first2= Tom |last2= Marino |first3= Mike |last3= Belmessieri |first4= Dennis |last4= Lear |first5= Richelle |last5= Nice |first6= John |last6= Guinasso |first7= Julie |last7= Zanartu |first8= Frank |last8= Swertlow |first9= Lyndon |last9= Stambler |year= 2007 |location= Beverly Hills, CA |publisher= Phoenix Books |isbn= 1-59777-536-3}}
*{{cite book |title= Blood Brother: 33 Reasons My Brother Scott Peterson Is Guilty |first= Anne |last= Bird |year= 2005 |location= New York |publisher= Regan Books |isbn= 9780060838577}}
*{{cite book |title= A Deadly Game: The Untold Story of the Scott Peterson Investigation |first1= Catherine |last1= Crier |first2= Cole |last2= Thompson |year=2005 |location= New York |publisher= ReganBooks |isbn= 0-06-076612-3}}
*{{cite book |title= Presumed Guilty: What the Jury Never Knew About Laci Peterson's Murder and Why Scott Peterson Should Not Be on Death Row |first1= Matt |last1= Dalton |first2= Bonnie Hearn |last2= Hill  |location= New York |publisher= Atria |year= 2005|isbn= 978-0743286954}}
*{{cite book |title= Dr. Henry Lee's Forensic Files: Five Famous Cases Scott Peterson, Elizabeth Smart, and more... |first1= Henry C. |last1= Lee |first2= Jerry |last2= Labriola |year= 2006 |location= Amherst, NY |publisher= Prometheus Books |isbn= 1-59102-409-9}}
*{{cite book |title= I'm Sorry I Lied To You: The Confession of Scott Peterson |first= Donna |last= Thomas |edition= 3rd |publisher= Duj Pepperman Enterprises |isbn= 1-59453-969-3}}
{{refend}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

{{Portal|California}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Peterson, Scott
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES = 
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = 
| DATE OF BIRTH     = October 24, 1972
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = San Diego, California
| DATE OF DEATH     = 
| PLACE OF DEATH    = 
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Peterson, Scott}}
[[Category:1972 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:American people convicted of murder]]
[[Category:American prisoners sentenced to death]]
[[Category:American Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:Filicides]]
[[Category:California Polytechnic State University, San Luis Obispo alumni]]
[[Category:People convicted of murder by California]]
[[Category:People from San Diego, California]]
[[Category:Prisoners sentenced to death by California]]

[[es:Scott Peterson]]
[[fr:Scott Peterson]]
[[nl:Scott Peterson]]</text>
      <sha1>191vo3k448s3sybyxkv89jf2f7xz204</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
