<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Shock jock</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>189909</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520669753</id>
      <parentid>520669577</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-30T23:58:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cleanupbabe</username>
        <id>11323378</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* See also */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12119">{{About|the type of radio broadcaster|the [[Australia]]n television series|Shock Jock}}
{{Multiple issues
 | refimprove=September 2010
 | weasel=September 2010
 | no footnotes=September 2010
}}

A '''shock jock''' is a type of [[radio]] broadcaster or [[disc jockey]] who entertains listeners or attracts attention using [[humor]] and/or melodramatic exaggeration that a notable portion of the listening audience may find offensive. The term is usually used pejoratively to describe provocative or irreverent [[Presenter|broadcasters]] whose mannerisms, statements and actions are typically offensive to many members of the community. It is a popular term, generally not used within the radio industry. A shock jock is considered to be the radio equivalent of the tabloid newspaper, for which entertaining readers is as important as, or more important than, providing factual information. 

Confusingly, the term has been used in two broad (but sometimes overlapping) contexts:
 
(1) The radio announcer who deliberately does something outrageous and shocking (e.g., to improve ratings).

(2) The political radio announcer who has an emotional outburst in response to a controversial government policy decision.

==Background==
The idea of an [[entertainer]] who breaks [[taboo]]s or adopts a career role in the realm of the frequently offensive is not a new one. Despite the claims of [[decency]] [[activist]]s, there are few eras of history in which there have not existed [[Blue comedy|blue comedians]]; notoriously offensive performers ([[Petronius]], [[Benny Bell]], [[Le Pétomane]], [[Redd Foxx]] and [[Lenny Bruce]] for example). African-American Ralph Waldo [[Petey Greene]] (1931-1984), who started broadcasting in 1966, is considered to be the original radio shock jock in the modern era.&lt;ref&gt;Petey Greene - Radio's first shock jock: The Legacy Continues. http://www.wdkkradio.com/the-legacy/petey-greene/&lt;/ref&gt; Petey gave a start to, and influenced, the alleged king of shock jocks [[Howard Stern]].

Shock jocks also tend to push the envelope of decency in their market, and may appear to show a lack of regard for communications regulations (e.g. [[Federal Communications Commission|FCC]] rules in the U.S.) regarding content. But nearly all American broadcasters have strict policies against content that is likely to draw indecency forfeitures, and air personalities are often contractually obligated to avoid broadcasting such content. Indecency [[fine (penalty)|fine]]s are, in fact, rarely issued  by U.S. regulators—no broadcaster has been issued a forfeiture for indecent content since 2003, although several earlier cases are in appeals court.

Popular envelope-pushing areas for shock jocks include sexual (especially [[kink (sexual)|kink]]y) and/or [[scatological]] ([[toilet humour]]) topics, or just unabashed [[innuendo]].

Many shock jocks have been fired as a result of such punishments as regulatory fines, loss of [[advertising|advertisers]], or simply social and political outrage.  On the other hand, it is also not uncommon for such broadcasters to be quickly rehired by another station or network.

Shock jocks in the United States have been [[Censorship|censored]] under additional pressure from the United States government since the introduction of the [[Broadcast Decency Enforcement Act of 2005]], which increased the fines on radio stations for violating decency guidelines by nearly 20 times.&lt;ref&gt;http://thomas.loc.gov/cgi-bin/bdquery/z?d109:SN00193:@@@D&amp;summ2=1&amp;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable incidents: United States==
{{globalize/US|date=March 2011}}
{{Peacock|date=September 2010}}

* July 12, 1979: [[WLUP-FM|WLUP]] Chicago disc jockeys [[Steve Dahl]] and [[Garry Meier]] staged &quot;[[Disco Demolition Night]]&quot; at [[Comiskey Park]] between games of a scheduled [[Chicago White Sox]]-[[Detroit Tigers]] double-header. Fans were granted admittance to the games for 98 cents if they also donated unwanted disco records to be blown up at Comiskey's second base during the event. After the records were blown up, fans spilled onto the playing field and rioted, causing the White Sox to forfeit the scheduled second game.

* October 1993: Matthew &quot;[[Mancow]]&quot; Muller made national headlines while working for radio station [[KYLD]] in San Francisco, California. At the time, a story had been circulated that President Clinton had tied up traffic on an LAX runway for over an hour because of a haircut on Air Force One. Mancow staged a parody of this incident on the San Francisco-Oakland Bay Bridge during rush hour, using vans to block the westbound lanes of the bridge, while his sidekick Jesus &quot;Chuy&quot; Gomez got a haircut. Muller was convicted of a felony by a San Francisco Municipal Court and sentenced to three years probation, ordered to perform 100 hours of community service and fined $500, while KYLD settled a lawsuit filed by a bridge commuter for $1.5 million. Mancow later had his felony conviction expunged.

* April 1995: On the [[Don Imus]] radio show, [[United States Senate|US Senator]] [[Al D'Amato]] put on a comical [[Asian people|Asian]] accent and criticized judge [[Lance Ito]] for personal interest in allowing [[television]] cameras in the [[O. J. Simpson]] [[O.J. Simpson#Criminal trial|murder trial]]. Imus was criticized for keeping D'Amato on air because of the shock value of the senator's comments.

* February 27, 2001: [[Bubba the Love Sponge]] had a [[pig]] [[castration|castrated]] and killed on the air. Bubba was charged with [[animal cruelty]], but was [[acquittal|acquitted]].

* June 12, 2001: A rumour that Britney Spears was dead was scotched by her publicists after the story was spread by two US radio DJs and a hoax website using the BBC logo. Dallas shock jocks Kramer and Twitch told listeners to their KEGL-FM evening show that pop singer Spears and her then boyfriend Justin Timberlake had been involved in a car accident in Los Angeles. The hoax sparked panic among fans, who called police and fire departments in their hundreds. The story was then turned into a spoof version of a BBC News Online web page, and the link was sent around the world by e-mail. The BBC lodged a strong protest, and the spoof page was removed.&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/1388131.stm 'Britney Death Hoax Fools Fans' June 12, 2001&lt;/ref&gt;

* August 16, 2002: [[Opie and Anthony]] sponsored a contest where the goal was to have sex in notable public places, called ''Sex For Sam''. The contest went without a major outcry until ''Sex for Sam 3'' after a couple had sex in a [[Vestibule (architecture)|vestibule]] at [[St. Patrick's Cathedral, New York|St. Patrick's Cathedral]]. The resulting controversy led to [[Infinity Broadcasting]] cancelling the ''Opie and Anthony Show''. Infinity was fined $357,500 USD for the incident.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2002/08/21/entertainment/main519365.shtml Shock Jocks Fired For Sex In St. Pats Stunt&lt;/ref&gt;

* April 8, 2004: [[Howard Stern]]'s show was cancelled by [[Clear Channel Communications]] after they were fined $495,000 USD for a number of statements made during a Stern show.{{citation needed|date=October 2011}} Stern later used his remaining [[market share]] to criticize [[Clear Channel Communications|Clear Channel]] and the [[George W. Bush administration|Bush Administration]], and left the public airwaves to move to [[satellite radio]], which is not subject to the same FCC decency regulations.

* April 9, 2004: The [[Regular Guys]] of [[WWPW|WKLS]] 96 Rock in [[Atlanta, Georgia]] were fired after a graphic interview with porn movie actress Devin Lane was accidentally aired over a Honda commercial. That interview was intended to be played backwards when they returned from the break, mocking the FCC indecency crackdown at the time.

* May 12, 2004: [[Portland, Oregon]] disk jockeys Marconi and Tiny played the audio portion of the video of [[Nick Berg]]'s murder on their morning program several times, accompanied by music, jokes, and laughter over the scenes. The pair were fired on the same day.

* May 15, 2007:  XM suspended [[Opie and Anthony]] for 30 days after a homeless man making a guest appearance described how he would like to have a threesome with the United States Secretary of State Condoleezza Rice and First Lady Laura Bush, and abused Queen Elizabeth II.

* March 2, 2012: [[Rush Limbaugh]], is criticized and faced with an advertiser exodus after making [[Rush Limbaugh&amp;ndash;Sandra Fluke controversy|misogynist comments]] toward activist [[Sandra Fluke]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Zielenziger|first=David|title=Limbaugh Boycott Draws Blood: Cumulus Media Cites ‘Drag’ In 2Q Revenue|url=http://www.ibtimes.com/articles/374036/20120815/rush-limbaugh-boycott-romney-ryan-cumulus-premiere.htm|newspaper=International Business Times|date=August 15, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Limbaugh was not disciplined for the remarks.

==Notable incidents: Great Britain==
*June 2005, radio DJ [[Tim Shaw]] propositioned glamour model [[Jodie Marsh]] live on-air on his [[Kerrang Radio|Kerrang! FM]] show by announcing he would leave his family for her. This enraged Shaw's wife, who promptly sold his [[Lotus Espirit]] on [[ebay]] for [[Fifty pence (British coin)|50p]]. Earlier that year he had been suspended for staging a mock burglary at the home of former programme director Andrew Jeffries, &lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/west_midlands/4122842.stm Scorned wife sells Lotus for 50p]&lt;/ref&gt; and in 2004,  after he was challenged by listeners, he phoned his [[sister-in-law]] live on-air to boast that he fantasized about her during sex with his wife.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thefreelibrary.com/DJ'S+RADIO+GA-GA+FOR+HIS+WIFE'S+SISTER%3B+Tim+in+fantasy+prank+on+live...-a0119175676 DJ'S RADIO GA-GA FOR HIS WIFE'S SISTER; Tim in fantasy prank on live show]&lt;/ref&gt;

* October 18, 2008: (UK) BBC Radio 2 host [[Russell Brand]] resigned after calling Fawlty Towers' Andrew Sachs and leaving an answering machine message claiming that he had had sex with his granddaughter.

==Notable incidents: Australia==
* July 29, 2009: On his morning breakfast radio show, Australian DJ [[Kyle Sandilands]] provoked outrage when his &quot;[[Lie Detector]]&quot; segment featured a 14 year old girl who, when quizzed on her sexual history by her mother, broke down, revealing she had been raped at the age of 12. Kyle then said her mother meant any intercourse other than rape. The show was suspended for one week.&lt;ref&gt;http://theglobalherald.com/australia-shock-as-kyle-sandilands-quizzes-14-year-old-rape-victim-on-air/597/&lt;/ref&gt; Sandilands provoked further outrage three days after his suspension expired when he made a slur about [[Jenny Craig]] ambassador [[Magda Szubanski]], saying she could have lost more weight in a [[concentration camp]]. Sandilands was suspended for ten days without pay, and after a review on September 18, had his suspension extended by three weeks. Sandilands returned to air on October 8, apologized for the incident, and was blessed by a priest at the start of the show.

==See also==
* [[Low culture]]
* [[Censorship in the United States]]
* [[Shock humour]]
* [[Shock value]]
* [[Alan Jones (radio broadcaster)]]
* [[Bubba the Love Sponge]]
* [[Petey Greene]]
* [[Opie and Anthony]]
* [[Rush Limbaugh]]
* [[Kyle Sandilands]]
* [[Tim Shaw (presenter)|Tim Shaw]]
* [[Howard Stern]]
* [[Stan Zemanek]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://theglobalherald.com/australia-shock-as-kyle-sandilands-quizzes-14-year-old-rape-victim-on-air/597/ Australia Shock as Kyle Sandilands Quizzes 14-year-old Rape Victim On Air] July 29, 2009
* [http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2002/08/21/entertainment/main519365.shtml Shock Jocks Fired For Sex In St. Pats Stunt]
* [http://www.voanews.com/english/AmericanLife/2006-07-24-voa47.cfm 'Shock Jocks' Have a Problem], &quot;[[Voice Of America]]&quot;, July 24, 2006
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/1388131.stm 'Britney Death Hoax Fools Fans'] June 12, 2001
* [http://music.yahoo.com/read/news/12051329 'DJs Fired in Wake of Britney Spears Hoax'] June 20, 2001

{{DEFAULTSORT:Shock Jock}}
[[Category:Radio personalities]]</text>
      <sha1>7w8z7p6igkr31fs6a8be7lkbfjbajgr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
