<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Sweatshop</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>102075</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521189705</id>
      <parentid>521084088</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-03T11:38:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Legobot</username>
        <id>7304691</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Bot: Tagging ap.google.* links with {{dead link}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="35441">{{about}}
{{mergefrom|Sweating system|date=September 2012}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=June 2012}}

[[Image:Sweatshop in Ludlow Street Tenement, New York cph.3a24271.jpg|thumb|right|A sweatshop in New York City, 1889]]
{{Slavery}}

'''Sweatshop''' (or '''sweat factory''') is a [[connotation|negatively connoted]] term for any [[workplace|working environment]] considered to be unacceptably difficult or dangerous. Sweatshop workers often work long hours for very low pay, regardless of laws mandating overtime pay or a [[minimum wage]]. [[Child labor]] laws may be violated. Sweatshops may have hazardous materials and situations. Employees may be subject to employer abuse without an easy way, if any way, to protect themselves.

==History==
{{Section OR|date=September 2011}}

[[Image:sweatshop-1890.jpg|thumb|right|A sweatshop c.1890]]
While many workplaces through history have been crowded, dangerous, low-paying and without job security, the concept of a sweatshop has its origins between 1830 and 1850 as a specific type of workshop in which a certain type of middleman, the ''sweater'', directed others in ''garment making'' (the process of producing clothing), under arduous conditions. The terms ''sweater'' for the middleman and ''sweating system'' for the process of subcontracting piecework were used in early critiques like [[Charles Kingsley]]'s [http://www.historyhome.co.uk/peel/economic/sweat.htm ''Cheap Clothes and Nasty''], written in 1850, which described conditions in London, England. The workplaces created for the [[sweating system]] were called ''sweatshops'' and comprised workplaces ranging from only a few workers to as many as one-hundred or more.

Between 1850 and 1900, sweatshops attracted the rural poor to rapidly-growing cities, and attracted immigrants to places like London, England and New York City's garment district, located near the [[tenement]]s of New York's [[Lower East Side]]. Wherever they were located, sweatshops also attracted critics and labour leaders who cited them as crowded, poorly ventilated, and prone to fires and [[rat]] infestations, since much of the work was done by many people crowded into small tenement rooms.

In the 1890s a group calling itself the [[National Anti-Sweating League]] was formed in [[Melbourne, Australia]] and campaigned successfully for a [[minimum wage]] via trade boards.  A group with the same name campaigned from 1906 in the UK, resulting in the [[Trade Boards Act 1909]].&lt;ref name=Blackburn&gt;Sheila Blackburn (1991) ''The Historical Journal'' '''34''' (1) 43–64 &quot;Ideology and Social Policy: The Origins of the Trade Boards Act&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1910, the [[International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union]] was founded in an effort to improve the condition of these workers.

Criticism of garment sweatshops became a major force behind workplace safety regulation and [[labor laws]]. As some journalists strove to change working conditions, the term ''sweatshop'' came to describe a broader set of workplaces whose conditions were considered inferior. In the United States, [[investigative journalism|investigative journalists]], known as [[Muckraker]]s, wrote exposés of business practices, and [[Progressivism in the United States|progressive]] politicians campaigned for new laws. Notable exposés of sweatshop conditions include [[Jacob Riis]]' [[photo journalism|photo documentary]] ''[[How the Other Half Lives]]'' and [[Upton Sinclair]]'s book, ''[[The Jungle]]'' about the [[meat packing industry]].

In 1911, negative public perceptions of sweatshops were galvanized by the [[Triangle Shirtwaist Factory Fire]] in New York City. The pivotal role of this time and place is chronicled at the [http://www.tenement.org/ Lower East Side Tenement Museum], part of the [[Lower East Side Tenement National Historic Site]]. While trade unions, [[minimum wage]] laws, [[fire safety]] codes, and labour laws have made sweatshops (in the original sense) rarer in the [[developed world]], they did not eliminate them, and the term came to be increasingly associated with factories in the [[developing world]].

In a report issued in 1994, the United States [[Government Accountability Office]] found that there were still thousands of sweatshops in the United States, using a definition of a ''sweatshop'' as any &quot;employer that violates more than one federal or state labour law governing minimum wage and overtime, child labour, industrial [[homeworker|homework]], occupational safety and health, workers' compensation, or industry registration&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gao.gov/archive/1995/he95029.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; This recent definition eliminates any historical distinction about the role of a middleman or the items produced, and focuses on the legal standards of developed country workplaces. An area of controversy between supporters of outsourcing production to the [[Third World]] and the anti-sweatshop movement is whether such standards can or should be applied to the workplaces of the developing world.{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}}

Sweatshops are also sometimes implicated in [[human trafficking]] when workers have been tricked into starting work without [[informed consent]], or when workers are kept at work through [[debt bondage]] or mental duress, all of which are more likely in cases where the workforce is drawn from children or the uneducated rural poor.{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}} Because they often exist in places without effective workplace safety or environmental laws, sweatshops sometimes injure their workers or the environment at greater rates than would be acceptable in developed countries.{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}} Sometimes [[penal labor]] facilities (employing prisoners) are grouped under the sweatshop label.{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}}

Sweatshops have proved a difficult issue to resolve because their roots lie in the conceptual foundations of the world economy.{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}} Developing countries like India, China, Vietnam, Bangladesh and Honduras encourage the outsourcing of work from the developed world to factories within their borders in order to provide employment for their people and profits to their employers.{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}} The shift of production to developing countries is part of the process known as [[globalization]], but may also be described as [[neoliberalism|neoliberal]] globalization to emphasize the role that [[free market]] economics plays in outsourcing.{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}}

==Positions on sweatshops==

===Anti-sweatshop movement===
Some of the earliest sweatshop critics were found in the 19th century [[abolitionist]] movement that had originally coalesced in opposition to chattel [[slavery]], and many abolitionists saw similarities between slavery and sweatshop work. As slavery was successively outlawed in industrial countries between 1794 (in France) and 1865 (in the United States), some abolitionists sought to broaden the anti-slavery consensus to include other forms of harsh labor, including sweatshops. As it happened, the first significant law to address sweatshops (the [[Factory Act|Factory Act of 1833]]) was passed in the United Kingdom at the same time that the slave trade (1807) and ownership of slaves (1833) were made illegal.

Ultimately, the abolitionist movement split apart. Some advocates focused on working conditions and found common cause with trade unions and [[Marxists]] and socialist political groups, or [[progressive movement]] and the [[muckraker]]s. Others focused on the continued slave trade and [[involuntary servitude]] in the colonial world. For those groups that remained focused on slavery, sweatshops became one of the primary objects of controversy. Workplaces across multiple sectors of the economy were categorized as sweatshops. However, there were fundamental philosophical disagreements about what constituted slavery. Unable to agree on the status of sweatshops, the abolitionists working with the [[League of Nations]] and the United Nations ultimately backed away from efforts to define slavery, and focused instead on a common precursor of slavery – [[human trafficking]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Miers|first=Suzanne|year=2003|title=Slavery in the Twentieth Century: The Evolution of a Global Problem|publisher=Alta Mira Press, Walnut Creek, California}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Those focused on working conditions included [[Friedrich Engels]], whose book ''[[The Condition of the Working Class in England in 1844]]'' would inspire the Marxist movement named for his collaborator, [[Karl Marx]]. In the United Kingdom the Factory Act was revised six further times between 1844 and 1878 to help improve the condition of workers by limiting work hours and the use of child labor. The formation of the [[International Labour Organization]] in 1919 under the League of Nations and then the United Nations sought to address the plight of workers the world over. Concern over working conditions as described by muckraker journalists during the [[Progressive Era]] in the United States saw the passage of new workers rights laws and ultimately resulted in the [[Fair Labor Standards Act]] of 1938, passed during the [[New Deal]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.finduslaw.com/fair_labor_standards_act_flsa_29_u_s_code_chapter_8 Fair Labor Standards Act – FLSA – 29 U.S. Code Chapter 8 | finduslaw]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:StudentsMarchOnRussellHQ.jpg‎|frame|Members of United Students Against Sweatshops marching in protest.]]

More recently, the [[anti-globalization movement]] has arisen in opposition to corporate [[globalization]], a process by which [[multinational corporation]]s move their operations [[overseas]] in order to lower their costs and increase profits. The anti-sweatshop movement has much in common with the [[anti-globalization movement]]. Both consider sweatshops harmful, and both have accused many companies (such as the [[Walt Disney Company]], [[The Gap (clothing retailer)|The Gap]], and [[Nike, Inc.|Nike]]) of using sweatshops. Some in these movements charge that [[neoliberalism|neoliberal]] globalization is similar to the [[sweating system]], arguing that there tends to be a &quot;[[race to the bottom]]&quot;, as multinationals leap from one low-wage country to another searching for lower production costs, in the same way that ''sweaters'' would have steered production to the lowest cost sub-contractor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairworkplace.org/articles/the-problem/the-race-to-the-bottom-insights-on-how-it-affects-corporate-executives.html |title=Fair Workplace Council Sweatshop Free Electronics – The Race to the Bottom |publisher=Fairworkplace.org |date=April 25, 2007 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Various groups support or embody the anti-sweatshop movement today. The [[National Labor Committee]] brought sweatshops into the mainstream media in the 1990s when it exposed the use of sweatshop and child labor to sew Kathie Lee Gifford's Wal-Mart label. United Students Against Sweatshops is active on college campuses. The [[International Labor Rights Fund]] filed a lawsuit&lt;ref&gt;''[http://laborrights.org/projects/corporate/walmart/WalMartComplaint091305.pdf Jane Doe et all v. Wal-Mart Stores]'', International Labor Rights Fund. ''Retrieved December 30, 2006.''&lt;/ref&gt; on behalf of workers in China, Nicaragua, Swaziland, Indonesia, and Bangladesh against Wal-Mart charging the company with knowingly developing purchasing policies particularly relating to price and delivery time that are impossible to meet while following the Wal-Mart code of conduct. Labor unions, such as the [[AFL-CIO]], have helped support the anti-sweatshop movement out of concern both for the welfare of workers in the developing world and those in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aflcio.org/corporatewatch/stop/ |title=&amp;#124; Stop Sweatshops |publisher=Aflcio.org |date=June 25, 2007 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Critics point out that sweatshop workers often do not earn enough money to buy the products that they make, even though such items are often commonplace goods such as t-shirts, shoes, and toys. In 2003, Honduran garment factory workers were paid US$0.24 for each $50 [[Sean John]] sweatshirt, $0.15 for each long-sleeved t-shirt, and only five cents for each short-sleeved shirt – less than one-half of one percent of the retail price.&lt;ref name=&quot;seanjohn&quot;&gt;{{cite web| title =Sean John Setisa Report| publisher =[[National Labor Committee]]| year =2003| month=October| url =http://www.nlcnet.org/article.php?id=103| accessdate =May 31, 2007 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070522173501/http://www.nlcnet.org/article.php?id=103 &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = May 22, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Even comparing international costs of living, the $0.15 that a Honduran worker earned for the long-sleeved t-shirt was equal in [[purchasing power]] to $0.50 in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/weo/2008/02/weodata/weorept.aspx?sy=2004&amp;ey=2008&amp;scsm=1&amp;ssd=1&amp;sort=country&amp;ds=.&amp;br=1&amp;c=268&amp;s=NGDPD%2CNGDPDPC%2CPPPGDP%2CPPPPC%2CLP&amp;grp=0&amp;a=&amp;pr.x=39&amp;pr.y=9 |title=Honduras|publisher=International Monetary Fund|accessdate=October 9, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Critics of sweatshops cite high savings, increased capital investment in developing nations, diversification of their exports and their status as trade ports as the reason for their economic success rather than sweatshops&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.galbithink.org/topics/ea/save.htm |title=Economic Growth in East Asia High Savings and Investment |publisher=Galbithink.org |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.treasury.gov.au/documents/1396/HTML/docshell.asp?URL=02_East_Asia_investment.htm |title=Investment in East Asia since the Asian financial crisis. by Elisha Houston, Julia Minty and Nathan Dal Bon |publisher=Treasury.gov.au |date=April 9, 2007 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=East Asian economy growing |newspaper=BBC News   |date=June 2, 2000, |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/business/774876.stm |accessdate=December 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and cite the numerous cases in the East Asian &quot;Tiger Economies&quot; where sweatshops have reduced living standards and wages.&lt;ref name=&quot;Businessweek&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Secrets, Lies, And Sweatshops |first=Dexter |last=Roberts |first2=Pete |last2=Engardio |newspaper=[[Bloomberg Businessweek]] |date=November 6, 2006 |url=http://www.businessweek.com/magazine/content/06_48/b4011001.htm |accessdate=December 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; They believe that better-paying jobs, increased capital investment and domestic ownership of resources will improve the economies of sub-Saharan Africa rather than sweatshops. They point to good labor standards developing strong manufacturing export sectors in wealthier sub-Saharan countries such as Mauritius&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://goliath.ecnext.com/coms2/gi_0199-5923802/Nike-to-the-rescue-Africa.html |title=Nike to the rescue? Africa needs better jobs, not sweatshops. – Dollars and Sense |publisher=Goliath.ecnext.com |date=September 1, 2006 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and believe measures like these will improve economic conditions in developing nations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.organicconsumers.org/clothes/sweatshops_poverty.cfm |title=&quot;There's Only So Much That Foreign Trade Can Do&quot; – Washington Post Sunday, June 2, 2002 By Alan Tonelson |publisher=Organicconsumers.org |date=June 2, 2002 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Critics of sweatshops argue that the minor gains made by employees of some of these institutions are outweighed by the negative costs such as lowered wages to increase profit margins and that the institutions pay less than the daily expenses of their workers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.coopamerica.org/programs/sweatshops/whattoknow.cfm |title=Green America's Ending Sweatshops Program |publisher=Coopamerica.org |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.globalexchange.org/campaigns/sweatshops/sweatshopsfaq.html |title=Sweatshops FAQ |publisher=Globalexchange.org |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nlcnet.org/campaigns/archive/chinareport/costoflivingdoc.shtml |title=Trying to Live on 25 Cents an Hour |publisher=Nlcnet.org |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; They also point to the fact that sometimes local jobs offered higher wages before trade liberalization provided tax incentives to allow sweatshops to replace former local unionized jobs.&lt;ref&gt;Kwong, Peter and Joann Lum. &quot;How the Other Half Lives Now.&quot; The Nation. June 18, 1988, Vol. 246: 858–60.&lt;/ref&gt; They further contend that sweatshop jobs are not necessarily inevitable.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Dreier |first=Peter |url=http://www.commondreams.org/archive/2007/12/07/5693 |title=NPR Debate Moderators All Wet on Sweatshop Labor by Peter Dreier |publisher=Commondreams.org |date=December 7, 2007 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.mit.edu/utr/www/consensus.doc A Consensus Statement on Sweatshop Abuse and MIT’s Prospective Actions in Pursuit of International Labor Justice – Signed by Individual Faculty Members and Students of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eric Toussaint claims that quality of life in developing countries was actually higher between 1945–1980 before the international debt crisis of 1982 harmed economies in developing countries causing them to turn to IMF and World Bank-organized &quot;structural adjustments&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://books.google.com/books?id=or5NcgF3Ac0C&amp;dq=Eric+Toussaint,+your+money+your+life&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=bn&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=E4WYSdL5Gc3dtge_6c2pCw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ct=result#PPA12,M1&lt;/ref&gt; and that unionized jobs pay more than sweatshop ones overall – &quot;several studies of workers producing for US firms in Mexico are instructive: workers at the Aluminum Company of America’s Ciudad Acuna plant earn between $21.44 and $24.60 per week, but a weekly basket of basic food items costs $26.87. Mexican GM workers earn enough to buy a pound of apples in 30 minutes of work, while GM workers in the US earn as much in 5 minutes.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unc.edu/~andrewsr/ints092/sweat.html |title=Historical Development of the Sweatshop – Todd Pugatch; INTS 92: The Nike Seminar. April 30, 1998 |publisher=Unc.edu |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; People critical of sweatshops believe that &quot;free trade agreements&quot; do not truly promote free trade at all but instead seek to protect multinational corporations from competition by local industries (which are sometimes unionized).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.henrygeorge.org/miktrade.htm |title=Protection and International Trade by Mike Curtis. Arden, Delaware, July 13, 1999 |publisher=Henrygeorge.org |date=July 13, 1999 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; They believe free trade should only involve reducing tariffs and barriers to entry and that multinational businesses should operate within the laws in the countries they want to do business in rather than seeking immunity from obeying local environmental and labor laws. They believe these conditions are what give rise to sweatshops rather than natural industrialization or economic progression.

Critics also point to the fact that sweatshops often do not pay taxes and thus don't pay for the public services they use for production and distribution and don't contribute to the country's tax revenue.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://academic.brooklyn.cuny.edu/core9/phalsall/studpages/chan/sweat.htm |title=The Sweatshop |publisher=Academic.brooklyn.cuny.edu |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In some countries, such as China, it is not uncommon for these institutions to withhold workers' pay.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.china-labour.org.hk/en/node/46878 |title=Child workers' wages withheld for up to a year |publisher=China-labour.org.hk |date=July 9, 2007 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{cquote|&quot;According to labor organizations in Hong Kong, up to $365 million is withheld by managers who restrict pay in exchange for some service, or don't pay at all.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=China's peasants opt for urban grindstone |first=Robert |last=Marquand |newspaper=[[Christian Science Monitor]] |date=23 January 2004 |url=http://www.csmonitor.com/2004/0123/p08s01-woap.html |accessdate=6 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Furthermore, critics of sweatshops point to the fact that those in the West who defend sweatshops show double standards by complaining about sweatshop labor conditions in countries considered enemies or hostile by Western governments, while still gladly consuming their exports but complaining about the quality.&lt;ref name=&quot;Businessweek&quot; /&gt; They contend that multinational jobs should be expected to operate according to international labor and environmental laws and minimum wage standards like businesses in the West do.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Overseas Sweatshops Are a U.S. Responsibility |first=Daniel |last=Viederman |newspaper=[[Bloomberg Businessweek]] |date=June 2007 |url=http://www.businessweek.com/debateroom/archives/2007/06/overseas_sweats.html |accessdate=December 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Pro-sweatshop arguments===
[[Image:Percentage living on less than $1 per day 1981-2001.png|thumb|right|250px|While East Asia has embraced large numbers of sweatshops, sub-Saharan Africa has not. This graph shows that the percentage of the population living on less than $1 per day (adjusted for inflation) has fallen substantially in East Asia, while remaining relatively unchanged in sub-Saharan Africa. The graph shows the 1981–2001 period. Data source: &quot;How Have the World's Poorest Fared Since the Early 1980s?&quot; by Shaohua Chen and Martin Ravallion. [http://econ.worldbank.org/external/default/main?ImgPagePK=64202990&amp;entityID=000112742_20040722172047&amp;menuPK=64168175&amp;pagePK=64210502&amp;theSitePK=477894&amp;piPK=64210520] Table 3, p. 28.]]

In 1997, economist [[Jeffrey Sachs]] said, &quot;My concern is not that there are too many sweatshops, but that there are too few.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;meyerson&quot;&gt;{{cite news| last =Meyerson| first =Allen| title =In Principle, A Case for More 'Sweatshops'|work=The New York Times| date =June 22, 1997| url =http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E6D8103EF931A15755C0A961958260| accessdate =April 4, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sachs and other proponents of sweatshops cite the economic theory of [[comparative advantage]], which states that [[international trade]] will, in the long run, make all parties better off. The theory holds that developing countries improve their condition by doing something that they do &quot;better&quot; than industrialized nations (in this case, they charge less but do the same work). Developed countries will also be better off because their workers can shift to jobs that they do better. These are jobs that some economists say usually entail a level of education and training that is exceptionally difficult to obtain in the developing world. Thus, economists like Sachs say, developing countries get factories and jobs that they would not otherwise. Some{{Who|date=September 2011}} would say with this situation occurs when developing countries try to increase wages because sweatshops tend to just get moved on to a new state that is more welcoming. This leads to a situation where states often will not try to get increased wages for sweatshop workers for fear of losing investment and boosted GDP. However, this only means average wages around the world will increase at a steady rate. A nation only gets left behind if it demands wages higher than the current market price for that labor.

When asked about the working condition in sweatshops, proponents say that although wages and working conditions may appear inferior by the standards of developed nations, they are actually improvements over what the people in developing countries had before. It is said that if jobs in such factories did not improve their workers' [[standard of living]], those workers would not have taken the jobs when they appeared. It is also often pointed out that, unlike in the industrialized world, the sweatshops are not replacing high-paying jobs. Rather, sweatshops offer an improvement over [[subsistence farming]] and other back-breaking tasks, or even prostitution, trash picking, or [[starvation]] by unemployment.&lt;ref name=&quot;meyerson&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last =Kristof| first =Nicholas| authorlink =Nicholas Kristof| title =Inviting All Democrats|work=The New York Times| date =January 14, 2004| url =http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0DD1330F937A25752C0A9629C8B63| accessdate =April 4, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The absence of the work opportunities provided by sweatshops can quickly lead to malnourishment or starvation. After the [[Child Labor Deterrence Act]] was introduced in the US, an estimated 50,000 children were dismissed from their garment industry jobs in Asia, leaving many to resort to jobs such as &quot;stone-crushing, street hustling, and prostitution.&quot; [[UNICEF]]'s 1997 ''State of the World's Children'' study found these alternative jobs &quot;more hazardous and exploitative than garment production.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;unicef&quot;&gt;{{cite conference| first =Carol| last =Bellamy| authorlink =Carol Bellamy| title =An Agreement in Bangladesh| booktitle =The State of the World's Children 1997| pages =66| publisher =[[United Nations Children's Fund]]| year =1997| url =http://www.unicef.org/sowc97/download/sow2of2.pdf| accessdate =May 31, 2007| id = ISBN 0-19-262871-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Writer [[Johan Norberg]], a proponent of [[market economics]], points out an irony:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| last =Gillespie| first =Nick| authorlink =Nick Gillespie| title =Poor Man's Hero| work =[[Reason magazine]]| publisher =[[Reason Foundation]]| year =2003| month=December| url =http://www.reason.com/0312/fe.ng.poor.shtml| accessdate =May 31, 2007 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070509042824/http://reason.com/0312/fe.ng.poor.shtml &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = May 9, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{cquote|[Sweatshop critics] say that we shouldn't buy from countries like Vietnam because of its labor standards, they've got it all wrong. They're saying: &quot;Look, you are too poor to trade with us. And that means that we won't trade with you. We won't buy your goods until you're as rich as we are.&quot; That's totally backwards. These countries won't get rich without being able to export goods.}}

In the [[Wal-Mart]] episode of [[Penn &amp; Teller: Bullshit!]], Professor of Economics Benjamin Powell from [[San Jose State University]] is interviewed. Professor Powell argues that sweatshop-type jobs in a [[developing country]] are often a significant improvement over other employment options (for example, [[subsistence farming]]). He further notes that the United States went through its own period of sweatshop labor during its development.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hjsshqyAFh8 |title=YouTube |publisher=YouTube |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
According to an article in Gale Opposing Viewpoints in Context, sweatshops became prevalent in the United States during the Industrial Revolution. As new jobs in factories began to appear, people left the hard life of farming to work in these factories. Although the working conditions and wages in these factories were very poor, the agricultural nature of the economy shifted into a manufacturing one because of this industrialization. Through this new industrialized economy, sufficient wealth was created and a large middle class began to emerge.
The labor movement came about with this rise in the average level of income and factory workers began to demand better wages and working conditions. Through much struggle, workers and advocates were able to achieve basic rights for workers, which included the right to form unions, and negotiate terms such as wages, overtime pay, health insurance, and retirement pensions; and eventually they were also able to attain legal protections such as minimum wage standards, and discrimination and sexual abuse protections. Furthermore, Congress set forth to ensure a minimum set of safety standards were followed in workplaces by passing the Occupational Safety and Health Act (OSHA) in 1970. These developments were able to improve working environments for Americans but it was through sweatshops that the economy grew and people were able to accumulate wealth and move out of poverty. As Nobel prize-winning economist [[Paul Krugman]] states in a 1997 article for Slate, “as manufacturing grows in poor countries, it creates a ripple effect that benefits ordinary people: ‘The pressure on the land becomes less intense, so rural wages rise; the pool of unemployed urban dwellers always anxious for work shrinks, so factories start to compete with each other for workers, and urban wages also begin to rise.’ In time average wages creep up to a level comparable to minimum-wage jobs in the United States.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Manjoo |first=Farhad |url=http://www.slate.com/articles/business/the_dismal_science/1997/03/in_praise_of_cheap_labor.html |title=In Praise of Cheap Labor – Slate Magazine |publisher=Slate.com |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In an article about a Nike sweatshop in Vietnam, Johan Norberg wrote, &quot;But when I talk to a young Vietnamese woman, Tsi-Chi, at the factory, it is not the wages she is most happy about. Sure, she makes five times more than she did, she earns more than her husband, and she can now afford to build an extension to her house. But the most important thing, she says, is that she doesn't have to work outdoors on a farm any more... Farming means 10 to 14 hours a day in the burning sun or the intensive rain... The most persistent demand Nike hears from the workers is for an expansion of the factories so that their relatives can be offered a job as well.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;norberg&quot;&gt;[http://www.johannorberg.net/?page=articles&amp;articleid=53 The Noble Feat of Nike] by Johan Norberg&lt;/ref&gt;

According to a November 2001 [[BBC]] article, in the previous two months, 100,000 sweatshop workers in Bangladesh had lost their sweatshop jobs. The sweatshop workers wanted their jobs back, and the Bangladeshi government was planning to lobby the U.S. government to repeal its trade barriers so the sweatshop workers could have their jobs back.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Bangladesh wants textiles curbs lifted |newspaper=BBC News   |date=November 12, 2001 |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/south_asia/1650952.stm |accessdate=December 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2005 article in the ''[[Christian Science Monitor]]'' states, &quot;For example, in Honduras, the site of the infamous [[Kathy Lee Gifford]] sweatshop scandal, the average apparel worker earns $13.10 per day, yet 44 percent of the country's population lives on less than $2 per day... In Cambodia, Haiti, Nicaragua, and Honduras, the average wage paid by a firm accused of being a sweatshop is more than double the average income in that country's economy.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Don't get into a lather over sweatshops |first=Benjamin |last=Powell |first2=David |last2=Skarbek |newspaper=[[Christian Science Monitor]] |date=August 2, 2005 |url=http://www.csmonitor.com/2005/0802/p09s02-coop.html |accessdate=December 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On three documented occasions during the 1990s, anti-sweatshop activists in rich countries have apparently caused increases in [[child prostitution]] in poor countries. In Bangladesh, there was a closure of several sweatshops which had been run by a German company, and as a result, thousands of Bangladeshi children who had been working in those sweatshops ended up working as prostitutes, turning to crime, or starving to death. In Pakistan, several sweatshops, including ones run by [[Nike, Inc.|Nike]], [[Reebok]], and other corporations, were closed, which caused those Pakistani children to turn to prostitution. In Nepal, a carpet manufacturing company closed several sweatshops, resulting in thousands of Nepalese girls turning to prostitution.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,119125,00.html Third World Workers Need Western Jobs], Fox News,
by Radley Balko, May 6, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

An October 19, 2008 [[Associated Press]] article reported about the Chinese citizens complaining about how the current U.S. economic crises had caused them to lose their sweatshop jobs. The article quoted Wang Wenming, who had lost his job at a [[Dongguan]] sweatshop, as saying, &quot;This financial crisis in America is going to kill us. It's already taking food out of our mouths.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://ap.google.com/article/ALeqM5hkboG00r1GaStjjPcd6fXGEJV-tQD93TLTB80 Factory closure in China a sign of deeper pain], Associated Press, October 19, 2008{{dead link|date=November 2012|bot=Legobot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Defenders of sweatshops cite Hong Kong, Singapore, South Korea, and Taiwan as recent examples of countries that benefited from having sweatshops.&lt;ref&gt;[http://tqe.quaker.org/2003/TQE087-EN-ProductCycle.html The Product Cycle and Globalization], The Quaker Economist, November 1, 2003&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hoover.org/pubaffairs/dailyreport/archive/2864991.html The Case for Sweatshops], Hoover Institution, Stanford University, February 7, 2000&lt;/ref&gt;

== Anti-Sweatshop Organizations ==
* [[Clean Clothes Campaign]] international alliance of labor unions and non-governmental organizations
* [[International Labor Rights Fund]]
* [[International Labour Organization]] a specialized agency of the United Nations
* [[National Labor Committee]]  founded to combat sweatshop labor and US government policy in El Salvador and Central America.
* [[Green America]] membership organization based in the United States
* United Students Against Sweatshops a student organization in the United States and Canada
* [[Free the Children]] A Canadian organization that helps raise awareness and put a stop to Child Labour – Also helps other children in need.
* [[Not for Sale Campaign]]

== See also ==
{{multicol|60%}}
* [[Amazon.com_controversies#Treatment_of_workers|Amazon.com treatment of workers]]
* [[Anti-sweatshop]]
* [[Assembly line]]
* [[Comparative advantage]]
* [[Contingent work]]
* [[Child labour]]
* [[Economic development]]
* [[Emerging markets]]
* [[Exploitation]]
* [[Export processing zone]]
{{multicol-break}}
* [[Game sweatshop]]
* [[Maquiladora]]
* [[National Anti-Sweating League]]
* [[Nike sweatshops]]
* [[Precarious work]]
* [[Protectionism]]
* [[Race to the bottom]]
* [[Sweating system]]
* [[Union organizer]]
{{multicol-end}}

==External links==
* [http://americanhistory.si.edu/sweatshops/index.htm Between a Rock and a Hard Place: A History of American Sweatshops, 1820 – present] An online exhibition from the National Museum of American History, Smithsonian Institution

== References ==

=== Notes ===
{{reflist|2}}

{{Fair trade}}

[[Category:Manufacturing]]
[[Category:Labor]]
[[Category:Garment industry]]
[[Category:Business ethics]]
[[Category:Clothing controversies]]
[[Category:Anti-corporate activism]]
[[Category:Economic growth]]
[[Category:Economic development]]

[[ca:Taller de treball esclau]]
[[de:Sweatshop]]
[[es:Taller de trabajo esclavo]]
[[fr:Atelier de misère]]
[[id:Sweatshop]]
[[he:סדנת יזע]]
[[ms:Kilang peras tenaga]]
[[nl:Sweatshop]]
[[ja:ブラック企業]]
[[simple:Sweatshop]]
[[fi:Hikipaja]]
[[sv:Låglönefabrik]]
[[zh-yue:血汗工廠]]
[[zh:血汗工廠]]</text>
      <sha1>laf1g1rs0uui0llews23xzku59yzobd</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
