<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Varg Vikernes</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>305561</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520402395</id>
      <parentid>518854871</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-29T09:42:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>213.131.238.28</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Biography */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="55861">{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2012}}
{{Overly detailed|date=January 2012}}
{{Infobox musical artist
| name            = Varg Vikernes
| image           = Varg Vikernes.jpg
| caption         = Vikernes during his final year in prison (2009).
| image_size      =
| background      = solo_singer
| birth_name      = Kristian Vikernes
| alias           = Count Grishnackh, Greifi Grishnackh, Varg Kvísling Larsson Víkarnes, colloquially known as Greven
| birth_date      = {{birth date and age|df=y|1973|2|11}}
|birth_place      = [[Bergen]], Norway 
| instrument      = Guitar, bass, drums, synthesizer, keyboards, vocals
| genre           = [[Black metal]], [[death metal]], [[thrash metal]], [[dark ambient]]
| occupation      = Musician, songwriter, writer
| years_active    = 1988&lt;ref&gt;http://www.burzum.org/eng/library/a_burzum_story01.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://filosofem.altervista.org/bio.htm&lt;/ref&gt;–1999, 2009–present
| label           =
| associated_acts = [[Burzum]], [[Mayhem (band)|Mayhem]], [[Old Funeral]], [[Darkthrone]], Uruk-Hai, Satanel, Kalashnikov
| website         = {{URL|http://www.burzum.org}}
}}
'''Varg Vikernes'''&lt;!-- not Varg Qisling Larssøn Vikernes, according to Norwegian Tax Registry --&gt; ({{IPA-sv|ˈʋɑrɡ ˈʋiːkəɳeːs|no}}; born 11 February 1973) is a Norwegian musician and writer. In ''[[Metal: A Headbanger's Journey]]'', director [[Sam Dunn]] described Vikernes as &quot;the most notorious black metal musician of all time&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video |people=Dunn, Sam (Director) |date=5 August 2005 |url=http://imdb.com/title/tt0478209/ |title=Metal: A Headbanger's Journey |medium=motion picture |location=Canada |publisher=Dunn, Sam}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Vikernes was born in [[Bergen]], Norway. In 1991, he founded the one-man music project [[Burzum]], which quickly became popular within the [[early Norwegian black metal scene]]. In 1992, he joined the band [[Mayhem (band)|Mayhem]] and adopted the stage name Count Grishnackh. Around this time he became affiliated with the [[Heathen Front]] and had several writings on [[Germanic neopaganism]] published.&lt;ref name=&quot;GC204&quot;&gt;Goodrick-Clarke 2003: 204&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1994, Vikernes was convicted of the murder of his Mayhem bandmate [[Euronymous|Øystein Aarseth]], known by his stage name Euronymous. Vikernes was further convicted of four counts of arson involving the burnings of historic churches, and was sentenced to 21 years in prison. Having served almost 16 years of his sentence, Vikernes was released on parole in early 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| title= Varg Vikernes ute på prøve | curly=y | url= http://www.vg.no/nyheter/innenriks/artikkel.php?artid=557287 | work= [[Verdens Gang]] | location= Oslo, Norway | agency= [[Norsk Telegrambyrå|NTB]] | date= 10 March 2009 | accessdate= 10 March 2009 | language= Norwegian | archiveurl= http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.vg.no%2Fnyheter%2Finnenriks%2Fartikkel.php%3Fartid%3D557287&amp;date=2009-03-10 | archivedate= 10 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| title= Ute av fengsel | url= http://www.dagbladet.no/2009/05/22/nyheter/black_metal/varg_vikernes/6354526/ | work= Dagbladet.no | date= 22 May 2009 | accessdate= 23 May 2009 | language= Norwegian}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009, Varg Vikernes changed his name to a French name that is currently unknown to anyone outside his family.{{citation needed|date=September 2012}}

==Biography==
Vikernes was sentenced to 21 years in prison for the August 1993 murder of [[Euronymous|Øystein Aarseth]] (aka 'Euronymous') of [[Mayhem (band)|Mayhem]] and for the burning of three Christian churches in Norway (he was also suspected of burning the fourth.) He was eligible for parole in spring 2008, after serving 15 years in prison, but his application was denied.&lt;ref name=&quot;Too dangerous for parole&quot;&gt;[[Aftenposten]], English edition, 11 June 2008:[http://www.aftenposten.no/english/local/article2477398.ece Too dangerous for parole]&lt;/ref&gt; A June 2008 newspaper article mentions that Vikernes is married and has a daughter, born in 1993, and a son, born 2007.&lt;ref&gt;[[Verdens Gang|VG Nett]], 11 June 2008: [http://www.vg.no/nyheter/innenriks/artikkel.php?artid=513005 Varg Vikernes for farlig for friheten] {{no icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a 2004 interview, Vikernes said that he has a daughter whom he had seen only twice since 1993 (the year he was incarcerated).&lt;ref name=&quot;BZINT&quot;&gt;www.burzum.org: [http://www.burzum.org/eng/library/interview01.shtml 12 August 2004 interview]&lt;/ref&gt; In a 2008 interview, he referred to his two children, as well as an expected third child.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;[http://www.dagbladet.no/nyheter/2008/07/06/540102.html Rune Midtskogen, &quot;Jeg er klar for samfunnet&quot;] ''Dagbladet'' June 6, 2008. Retrieved 21 January 2009&lt;/ref&gt; In connection with his parole in March 2009, Vikernes stated in an interview that he would be settling on a small farm in [[Telemark]] with his family.&lt;ref name=&quot;TV2-nyhetene&quot;&gt;{{Cite news | author= Berg, Morten Michelsen | title= Nå slipper &quot;Greven&quot; ut | curly=y | url= http://www.tv2nyhetene.no/innenriks/krim/article2614786.ece | work= [[TV 2 Nyhetene]] | language= Norwegian | date= 10 March 2009 | accessdate= 10 March 2009 | archiveurl= http://www.webcitation.org/5fAUhHYIr | archivedate=10 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Background, childhood and adolescence===
Vikernes does not have a published biography (authorized or unauthorized), but some information can be gathered from interviews he has given and from articles on the web page [http://www.burzum.org www.burzum.org]. [[Michael Moynihan (journalist)|Michael Moynihan]], one of the authors of ''Lords of Chaos'', has been described as &quot;quite active in the propaganda support network for Vikernes&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coogan&quot;&gt;Coogan 1999&lt;/ref&gt;

In the interviews printed in ''Lords of Chaos'', Vikernes discusses his background and childhood. ''Lords of Chaos'' also includes an interview with his mother, Helene Bore (the book incorrectly refers to her with the given name 'Lene',&lt;ref&gt;Michael Moynihan, Didrik Søderlind: ''Lords of Chaos'', First Edition, Feral House 1998, p. 142.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Michael Moynihan, Didrik Søderlind: ''Lords of Chaos'', First Edition, Feral House 1998, p. 316.&lt;/ref&gt; whereas Norwegian newspapers{{citation needed|date=July 2012}}&lt;!-- A newspaper on page 316 of ''Lords of Chaos'', first edition, also refers to her als Lene Bore, not Helene.--&gt; and even Vikernes' own website {{URL|http://www.burzum.org}} all use her correct name 'Helene'). In the 2004 interview, Vikernes mentions that &quot;she is working in a large oil company&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;BZINT&quot;/&gt; He also claims his father is an &quot;electronics engineer&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;BZINT&quot;/&gt; whereas his brother, who (according to the ''Lords of Chaos'' interview) is &quot;one and a half years older&quot;,&lt;ref name=LoC148/&gt; is a &quot;graduate civil engineer&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;BZINT&quot;/&gt;

In the ''Lords of Chaos'' interview, Vikernes recalls an incident from his childhood: When he was about 6 years old, the family moved for about a year to [[Baghdad]], Iraq, because Vikernes' &quot;father was working for [[Saddam Hussein]]&quot;,&lt;ref name=LoC147&gt;LoC 1998: 147&lt;/ref&gt; developing a computer program. Since there were no places available in the English school in Baghdad, the young Vikernes went to an Iraqi elementary school during this time. According to his interview, Vikernes here became &quot;aware of racial matters&quot;.&lt;ref name=LoC148&gt;LoC 1998: 148&lt;/ref&gt; [[Corporal punishment]] was not uncommon in the school, and on one occasion Vikernes had a &quot;quarrel&quot; with a teacher and called him &quot;a monkey&quot;. But as Vikernes perceived it the teachers &quot;didn't dare to hit me because I was white&quot;.&lt;ref name=LoC148 /&gt; Vikernes' mother also recalls how they &quot;spent a year in Iraq&quot;, and that &quot;the other children in his class would get slapped by their teachers; he would not&quot;.&lt;ref name=LoC142&gt;LoC 1998: 142&lt;/ref&gt; She mentions that this created problems, but generally she &quot;has no good explanation&quot; of how Varg developed his views.&lt;ref name=LoC144&gt;LoC 1998: 144&lt;/ref&gt; Vikernes reveals slightly more in his interview. When asked about his father, he says that he &quot;had a [[swastika]] flag at home&quot;&lt;ref name=LoC147 /&gt; and that his father was hysterical about it. However, Vikernes feels that his father was a hypocrite, because he was worried about Vikernes &quot;being a Nazi&quot;, whereas he too was &quot;pissed about all the colored people he saw in town&quot;.&lt;ref name=LoC147 /&gt; About his mother, Vikernes says that she was &quot;very race conscious&quot;, in the sense that she was afraid that Vikernes &quot;was going to come home with a black girl!&quot;&lt;ref name=LoC146&gt;LoC 1998: 146&lt;/ref&gt; At the time of the interview (1995), Vikernes still had a positive relationship with his mother, but &quot;very little contact&quot; with his father.&lt;ref name=LoC147 /&gt; His parents are divorced. Vikernes' father is said to have &quot;left about 10 years ago&quot;,&lt;ref name=LoC147 /&gt; which would have been 1985, when Vikernes was 12.

There is some evidence that Vikernes was involved with the skinhead scene in Bergen before he became a part of the black metal scene. Goodrick-Clarke introduces [[Burzum]] as the &quot;musical vehicle&quot; of the &quot;ex-skinhead&quot; Vikernes.&lt;ref name=&quot;GC204&quot;/&gt; According to the ''[[Encyclopedia of White Power]]'', &quot;Vikernes first became involved with the extreme right as a National Socialist skinhead while he was an adolescent.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kapl-319&quot;&gt;Kaplan 2000: 319.&lt;/ref&gt; When he is asked in the interview in ''Lords of Chaos'' whether he hung out with skinheads in Bergen, Vikernes boldly replies: &quot;There were no skinheads in Bergen.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;LoC149&quot;/&gt; He mentions, though, that he had short hair at that time and that he was into weapons, that he liked the Germans and hated the British and Americans.&lt;ref name=&quot;LoC149&quot;/&gt;

===Early musical career===
{{Further|Burzum}}
Vikernes had been learning the guitar since he was 14.&lt;ref name=&quot;LoC149&quot;&gt;LoC 1998: 149&lt;/ref&gt; When he was about seventeen, Vikernes came into contact with the members of the Bergen [[death metal]] band [[Old Funeral]]. He played guitar with them during 1990–1991 and performed on their ''Devoured Carcass'' EP.

In 1991, Vikernes began a solo musical project named [[Burzum]], and quickly became involved with the [[early Norwegian black metal scene]]. During 1992–1993, he recorded four albums as Burzum.

Vikernes has stated that for the recording of these early albums he used an old Westone guitar, bought in 1987 from an acquaintance.&lt;ref name = &quot;burzummusic&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.burzum.org/eng/library/a_burzum_story06.shtml |title=A Burzum Story: Part VI – The Music |publisher=Burzum.org |accessdate=2011-08-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; He used the cheapest bass guitar there was in the shop and he borrowed drumsets from Old Funeral, Immortal and &quot;another musician living nearby&quot;.&lt;ref name = &quot;burzummusic&quot;/&gt; On ''[[Hvis lyset tar oss]]'', he borrowed [[Hellhammer (musician)|Hellhammer]]'s drumset, the same one Hellhammer used to record ''[[De Mysteriis Dom Sathanas]]'' by [[Mayhem (band)|Mayhem]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Teufel |url=http://www.teufelstomb.com/interviews/mayhem-1999/ |title=Interview with Hellhammer |publisher=Teufels Tomb |accessdate=2011-08-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; He used a [[Marshall Amplification|Marshall]] amplifier, but for the recording of ''[[Filosofem]]'' he used the amplifier on his brother's stereo and some old fuzz pedals.&lt;ref name = &quot;burzummusic&quot;/&gt; For vocals, he would use whatever microphone the sound tech handed him, but during the recording of ''Filosofem'' he intentionally used the worst mic they had, a headset mic.&lt;ref name = &quot;burzummusic&quot;/&gt; On the track &quot;Dungeons of Darkness&quot; he used the large gong at [[Grieghallen]] for background noise ([[Euronymous]] assisted him by beating his fists on it).&lt;ref name = &quot;burzummusic&quot;/&gt;

In 1992, Vikernes and Dimitrios Faust joined the black metal band [[Mayhem (band)|Mayhem]].

===Arson of churches===
On 6 June 1992, the [[Fantoft stave church]], dating from the 12th century and considered architecturally significant, was burned to the ground by arson. By January 1993, arson attacks had occurred on at least seven other major [[stave churches]], including one on Christmas Eve of 1992.&lt;ref name=&quot;GC204&quot;/&gt; Vikernes was found guilty of several of these cases: the arson and attempted arson of Åsane Church and Storetveit Church, respectively, in [[Bergen]], the arson of Skjold Church in [[Vindafjord]], and the arson of Holmenkollen Chapel in [[Oslo]]. He was also charged with the arson of Fantoft stave church, although the jurors voted not guilty. The judges called this an error but did not overthrow the whole case.&lt;ref name=&quot;nuokon&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Burzum aske.jpg|thumb|right|The charred ruins of the Fantoft stave church as seen on Burzum's 1992 EP, ''[[Aske (album)|Aske]]''.]]
Vikernes was rumored to have been motivated both by [[paganism]] and [[theistic Satanism]], but has denied he was ever a Satanist.&lt;ref&gt;See 1995 [[Morgenbladet]] article &quot;Satanism in Norway&quot;, English translation Michael Moynihan, ''Lords of Chaos'', pp. 344–45.&lt;/ref&gt;

In an interview with [[Michael Moynihan (journalist)|Michael Moynihan]], Vikernes made a statement about the church burnings that hints at a [[Germanic paganism|heathen]] rather than a Satanist motivation:

&lt;blockquote&gt;I am not going to say that I burnt any churches. But let me put it this way: There was one person who started it. I was not found guilty of burning the Fantoft stave church, but anyway, that was what triggered the whole thing. That was the 6th of June and everyone linked it to Satanism ... What everyone overlooked was that on the 6th June, 793, in [[Lindesfarne]] in [[Great Britain|Britain]] was the site of the first known [[Viking]] raid in history, with Vikings from [[Hordaland]], which is my county ... They [the Christians] desecrated our graves, our burial mounds, so it's revenge.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Moynihan, ''Lords of Chaos'', p. 88; quoted in: M. Gardell, ''Gods of the Blood'', p.306;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Echoing this sentiment, he writes in ''Vargsmål'': &quot;For each devastated graveyard, one heathen grave is avenged, for each ten churches burnt to ashes, one [[Heathen hofs|heathen hof]] is avenged, for each ten priests or [[freemason]]s assassinated, one heathen is avenged.&quot;''&lt;ref&gt;quoted after M. Gardell, ''Gods of the Blood'', p.306, 307. Translation by M. Gardell&lt;/ref&gt;

When asked whether the church burnings were linked to [[Odinism]] or [[Ásatrú]] he replied: &quot;The point is that all these churches [i.e. church burnings] are linked to one person ... who was not [[Øystein Aarseth|Øystein]] obviously. All the church burnings, with the exception of Stavanger, because that was another group (who, by the way, have also turned into nationalistic pagans).&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Lords of Chaos'', p. 89&lt;/ref&gt;

===Murder of Øystein Aarseth===
In late January 1993, Vikernes was interviewed by a journalist from ''[[Bergens Tidende]]''. Vikernes had requested the interview in order to gain publicity for the black metal scene and for Aarseth's record store ''Helvete''. However, the interview led to a police investigation and Vikernes was put under arrest for a week. Aarseth decided to close his record store due to this negative attention.

On 10 August 1993, Vikernes and [[Thorns (band)|Snorre Ruch]] traveled from Bergen to Aarseth's apartment in [[Oslo]]. Upon their arrival a confrontation began, which ended when Vikernes fatally stabbed Aarseth. His body was found outside the apartment with twenty-three cut wounds&amp;nbsp;– two to the head, five to the neck, and sixteen to the back.&lt;ref&gt;Steinke, Darcey. &quot;Satan's Cheerleaders&quot; ''SPIN Magazine'', February 1996.&lt;/ref&gt;

The entry on Varg Vikernes in the specialized ''[[Encyclopedia of White Power]]'' mentions that the murder has been &quot;variously described as a power struggle between rival leaders of a satanic circle, a conflict over a girl's affection, or a dispute over a record contract&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kapl-319&quot;&gt;Kaplan 2000: 319&lt;/ref&gt; Vikernes himself contends &quot;that Aarseth planned to kill him and that he was striking first in self-defense&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kapl-319&quot;/&gt; On his website, Vikernes elaborates that Aarseth had plotted to [[torture]] him to death and videotape the event&amp;nbsp;– using a meeting about an unsigned contract as a pretext.&lt;ref name = &quot;nuokon&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.burzum.org/eng/library/a_burzum_story02.shtml |title=Varg Vikernes – A Burzum Story: Part II – Euronymous |publisher=Burzum.org |accessdate=2011-08-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the night of the murder, Vikernes claims he intended to hand Aarseth the signed contract and &quot;tell him to fuck off&quot;, but that Aarseth attacked him first.&lt;ref name = &quot;nuokon&quot;/&gt; Additionally, Vikernes contends that most of Aarseth's cut wounds were caused by broken glass he had fallen on during the struggle.&lt;ref name = &quot;nuokon&quot;/&gt; After the slaying, Vikernes drove to a nearby lake to dispose of his bloodied clothes before he returned to Bergen.&lt;ref name = &quot;Young-p203&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title=Metal: The Definitive Guide | year=2007 | author=Garry Sharpe-Young | page=203}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At the arrest of Vikernes, the police found 150&amp;nbsp;kg of explosives and 3,000 rounds of ammunition in Vikernes' home.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dagbladet.no&quot;&gt;{{cite web |author=Midtskogen, Rune |title=&quot;Greven&quot; angrer ingenting |date=4 July 2009 |url=http://www.dagbladet.no/2009/07/04/magasinet/innenriks/kriminalomsorg/kirkebrann/drapsdom/7051663/ |accessdate=25 August 2009 |language=Norwegian |trans_title=&quot;The Count&quot; regrets nothing}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to ''Encyclopedia of White Power'', Vikernes has stated that these explosives were &quot;intended to blow up [[Blitz (movement)|Blitz House]], the radical leftist and anarchist enclave in Oslo&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Kapl-319&quot;/&gt; a plan which &quot;was reportedly on the verge of execution&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kapl-319&quot;/&gt; and only prevented by Vikernes' arrest. In an article originally published in 1999, [[Kevin Coogan]] points to Vikernes' planned attack in the Blitz House as a possible motive for the murder of Aarseth. Referring to the passages of ''[[Lords of Chaos (book)|Lords of Chaos]]'' quoted above, Coogan writes: &quot;LOC offers strong evidence that Vikernes, who came from a divorced family and was raised by his mother Helene Bore, was a fascist well before he became a metalhead.&quot; Then he, too, mentions Vikernes' intent to &quot;destroy an Oslo-based punk anti-fascist squat called Blitz House&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Coogan&quot;&gt;Coogan 1999&lt;/ref&gt; and concludes: &quot;Vikernes may have felt that he had no choice but to kill Euronymous before bombing Blitz House because 'the Communist' would almost certainly have opposed such an act&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coogan&quot;/&gt; Though on Vikernes' website, he refers to the creators of &quot;Lords of Chaos&quot; as being unreliable sources.

The media speculated that Euronymous and Vikernes had conspired to blow up [[Nidaros Cathedral]], which appears on the cover of ''[[De Mysteriis Dom Sathanas]]''. Vikernes denied this allegation in a 2009 interview, stating &quot;I was getting [the explosives and ammunition] in order to defend Norway if we were attacked any time. During the Cold War, the United States and the Soviet Union could have decided to attack us. We have no reason to trust neither the government, the royal family or the military because of what happened last time we were attacked. We are left to ourselves&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dagbladet.no&quot;/&gt;

===Trial===
Vikernes' trial began on 2 May 1994. During the court case, the 22-year-old Snorre Ruch, who drove Vikernes to and from Øystein's apartment and stood outside during the incident, was put on trial together with Vikernes and sentenced to 8 years imprisonment. Vikernes was sentenced to 21 years imprisonment, the maximum sentence in Norway. He was found guilty of murdering Øystein Aarseth and the arson of four churches, one of which involved [[Jørn Inge Tunsberg|Jørn Tunsberg]] of black metal band [[Hades Almighty]]. In a controversial display, Vikernes smiled at the moment his verdict was read, an image that was widely reprinted in the news media.&lt;ref name = &quot;nuokon&quot;/&gt;

===Time in prison===
During his time in prison, Vikernes recorded two albums (''[[Dauði Baldrs]]'' and ''[[Hliðskjálf (album)|Hliðskjálf]]''), which are composed of [[dark ambient]] songs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.intro.de/kuenstler/interviews/23043719/norwegischer-black-metal-als-die-kirchen-brannten |title=Norwegischer Black Metal |language={{de icon}} |publisher=Intro.de |accessdate=2011-08-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Vikernes was denied access to an electric guitar, bass guitar or drums, and instead used a synthesizer. In 2000, Vikernes terminated his musical project because of what he perceived to be negative notoriety. He believed that his philosophy was constantly misinterpreted by an ignorant fan base that was too closely related to black metal and [[Satanism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.burzum.org/eng/library/lords_of_chaos_review.shtml |title=Varg Vikernes – A review of M. Moynihan &amp; D. Søderlind's &quot;Lords of Chaos: The Bloody Rise of The Satanic Metal Underground&quot; (new edition) |publisher=Burzum.org |accessdate=2011-08-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Through his website, he indicated that he intended to continue Burzum after his release from prison, stating: &quot;I will publish a few books, possibly using a pseudonym in order to stay anonymous, and perhaps a Burzum album or two, but that's it&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.burzum.org/eng/library/a_burzum_story09.shtml |title=A Burzum Story: Part IX – The Tomorrow |publisher=Burzum.org |date=24 February 2006 |accessdate=2011-08-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Regarding the style of his next album, Vikernes stated on his website: &quot;[A future album] will, as far as I can tell, sound much like the old albums, whether I like it or not, because I'm incapable of making music that doesn't sound rather 'Burzumic'.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.burzum.org/eng/library/interview02.shtml Interview with Chris Mitchell] (10 May 2005)&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2003, Vikernes failed to return to his low-security prison in [[Tønsberg]], Norway after having been granted a short leave. He was found riding in a stolen Volvo car, which, according to the media, contained an unloaded [[Heckler &amp; Koch G3|AG3]] automatic rifle, a handgun, numerous large knives, a gas mask, camouflage clothing, a laptop, a compass, a [[GPS navigation device|GPS device]], various maps and a fake passport (it is thought that Vikernes came to be in possession of this equipment by means of a military barracks). For this thirteen months were added to his sentence, and he was then moved to a maximum-security prison in [[Trondheim]]. He was subsequently moved again, this time to [[Tromsø]] Prison.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aftenposten.no/english/local/article655724.ece |title=Berglund, Nina. &quot;Police nab 'The Count' after he fled jail&quot; ''Aftenposten'' (English) 27 October 2003 |publisher=Aftenposten.no |accessdate=2011-08-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;aft001&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aftenposten.no/english/local/article656646.ece |title=Berglund, Nina. &quot;Arrested 'Count' was heavily armed&quot; ''Aftenposten'' (English edition) October 28, 2003 |publisher=Aftenposten.no |accessdate=2011-08-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

When Vikernes was convicted, it was possible to be released on parole after serving 12 years of a 21-year sentence, but in 2002, before he became eligible, the [[Storting|Norwegian Parliament]] extended this to 14 years. In June 2006, after serving 12 years, Vikernes was denied parole by the Department of Criminal Justice for this reason.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; His lawyer, John Christian Elden, has complained that the policy change is a form of [[Ex post facto law|retroactive legislation]]. Article 97 of the Norwegian constitution prohibits any law being given retroactive force.

Varg Vikernes was denied parole again in June 2008, although he was allowed to leave Tromsø Prison for short periods to visit his family. His full sentence would run for another seven years.&lt;ref name=&quot;Too dangerous for parole&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.burzum.org/eng/news.shtml |title=Burzum and Varg Vikernes news and updates |publisher=Burzum.org |accessdate=2011-08-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; In March 2009, however, Vikernes' parole was announced. He had then served 15 years of his 21-year sentence.&lt;ref name=&quot;TV2-nyhetene&quot;/&gt;

On 24 May 2009, Vikernes was released from prison on probation.

==Beliefs==
According to Goodrick-Clarke, &quot;while in jail, Vikernes began to formulate his nationalist heathen ideology using material from Norse mythology combined with racism and occult National Socialism.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;GC204&quot;/&gt; Goodrick-Clarke bases this account of Vikernes' beliefs on some articles that Vikernes had written for the short-lived &quot;neo-Nazi magazine&quot; ''Filosofem'', published by
Vidar von Herske. Goodrick-Clarke also uses the book ''[[Lords of Chaos (book)|Lords of Chaos]]'', and a manifesto called ''Vargsmål'' ('Speech of the Wolf'), which Vikernes began to write after his imprisonment. According to ''Lords of Chaos'', ''Vargsmål'' became available on the internet for some time in 1996, but not in a printed form.&lt;ref&gt;''Lords of Chaos'' (1998):159&lt;/ref&gt; In 1997, a Norwegian publisher released a paperback edition of the book; its publication was financed by Vikernes' mother, Helene Bore.&lt;ref name = &quot;hist&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Christe |first=Ian |title=Sound of the Beast: the Complete Headbanging History of Heavy Metal |publisher=HarperCollins Publishers Inc. |year=2003 |location=New York, New York |page=279 |url= |id= |isbn=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Vikernes has denounced the English translation of his book in an article on his website. He has also stated on the website that &quot;''Vargsmål'' was written in anger, while I was young and in isolation, and the book is marked by this&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.burzum.org/eng/library/a_comment_to_vargsmal_and_other_books_by_varg_vikernes.shtml |title=Varg Vikernes – A Comment to &quot;Vargsmål&quot; and other books by Varg Vikernes |publisher=Burzum.org |accessdate=2011-08-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Political affiliation===
After his conviction, Vikernes began identifying himself as a [[neo-Nazi]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Coogan&quot;/&gt; The ''[[Encyclopedia of White Power]]'' describes him as &quot;busy promoting his [[Odinist]] and [[National Socialist]] philosophy from behind bars.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kapl-319&quot;/&gt;

In a July 2005 statement on his website entitled &quot;The Nazi Ghost&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Ghost&quot;&gt;[http://www.burzum.org/eng/library/a_burzum_story07.shtml Part VII] of the autobiographical series: &quot;[http://www.burzum.org/eng/biography.shtml A Burzum Story]&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; Vikernes states that although he &quot;occasionally used the term 'nazism' to describe [his] ideological foundation&quot;, he no longer describes himself as a 'Nazi'.

&lt;blockquote&gt;The reason I have been drawn to and occasionally have expressed support for 'nazism' is mainly because many of the Norwegian (and German) 'Nazis' embraced our Pagan religion as our blood-religion and they rejected [[Judeo-Christianity]] as Jewish [[heresy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Ghost&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Vikernes expresses a desire to not be associated with [[Anti-Slavism|anti-Slavic]] sentiments. He identifies three things which distinguish him from the &quot;Nazis&quot;: &quot;unlike them I am not socialistic (not even on a [[national socialism|national]] level), I am not [[materialistic]] and I believe in (the ancient [[Scandinavia]]n) democracy.&quot;

In the late 90s, &quot;to avoid confusion&quot; and &quot;to find a term more suitable and accurate&quot;, Vikernes coined the term &quot;odalism&quot; based on the [[Odal (rune)|Odal]] rune. &quot;[F]rom Norse ''óðal'' ([[homeland]], [[allodium]], [[allodial law]], [[nobility]], [[Nobility|noble]], [[inherited goods]], [[fatherland]], [[land property]], [[distinguished family]], [[distinguished]], splendid, [[Kinship|kin]] and the nation).&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.burzum.org/eng/library/a_burzum_story07.shtml A Burzum Story: Part VII – The Nazi Ghost]&lt;/ref&gt; He explains, &quot;In it lies [[Paganism]], [[traditional]] nationalism, [[Racism|racialism]] and environmentalism.&quot; Vikernes contrasts it with &quot;modern 'civilization'&quot; which he equates with &quot;capitalism, [[materialism]], [[Judeo-Christianity]], pollution, urbanization, [[race-mixing]], [[Americanization]], socialism, [[globalization]], ''[[et cetera]]''&quot;. He places importance on the fact that odalism &quot;is not a term tainted by history&quot;; in contrast with nazism:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The 'nazi ghost' has scared millions of Europeans from caring about their blood and homeland for sixty years now, and it is about time we banish this ghost and again start to think and care about the things that (whether we like it or not) are important to us.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ghost&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In other texts on his website, he embraces [[Nordicism]], racism&lt;ref&gt;With respect to what appears to be his interpretation of the [[Edda]], though there could be another source, Vikernes writes: &quot;This is the mythology, a pretty unmistakably racist statement left to us from our forefathers.&quot;[http://www.burzum.org/eng/library/paganism01.shtml Paganism: Part I – The Ancient Religion]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[eugenics]] (''&quot;race hygiene&quot;'').&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The mental hygiene and race hygiene practiced by the ancient Europeans also was disrupted by the introduction of Christianity.&quot; [http://www.burzum.org/eng/library/paganism06.shtml Paganism: Part VI – Hygiene In The Pagan Era]&lt;/ref&gt; However, he makes the point that following one's own culture is an equally valid and beneficial choice for all peoples.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[Odalism] is not only a more accurate but also a more inclusive term that can be used by all Europeans (and others too for that sake)&quot;. [http://www.burzum.org/eng/library/a_burzum_story07.shtml A Burzum Story: Part VII – The Nazi Ghost]&lt;/ref&gt; Vikernes states that although he is a racist, he hates no one and that &quot;hatred is irrational&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dagbladet.no&quot;/&gt;

In a response to a question from a fan, Vikernes expressed his contempt for the [[European Union]], describing it as being &quot;thoroughly corrupt, extremely bureaucratic, predominately catholic and utterly chaotic&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.burzum.org/eng/library/2004_interview_bg.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;

====Involvement in the Heathen Front====
According to several sources{{Who|date=December 2009}}, during his time in prison, Vikernes became a central figure in the [[Neo-völkisch movements|Neo-völkisch]] [[Heathen Front]]. The Heathen Front started as a group in Norway, ''Norsk Hedensk Front'' (Norwegian Heathen Front) or NHF, and grew into the international ''Allgermanische Heidnische Front'' (Pan-Germanic&lt;!--This is the correct translation: Germanisch=Germanic, referring to the historic Germanic tribes, not to inhabitants of contemporary Germany--&gt; Heathen Front) or AHF. At the time of their publication, the article on Vikernes in the ''Encyclopedia of White Power''&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Vikernes is also the self-proclaimed leader of the Norsk Hedensk Front (Norwegian Heathen Front) and of an international heathen brotherhood he calls Cymophane.&quot; Article by Xavier Cattarinich, Kaplan 2000: 319.&lt;/ref&gt; and ''[[Gods of the Blood]]'' by the Swedish scholar [[Matthias Gardell]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Advocating national socialism, anti-Semitism, eugenics, and racist paganism, Vikernes launched Norsk Hedensk Front in 1993, which soon evolved into a network of independent tribes called the Allgermanische Heidnische Front (AHF).&quot;'' Gardell 2003: 307.&lt;/ref&gt; considered Vikernes to be the leader (and the founder) of the Norwegian Heathen Front. Goodrick-Clarke mentions that Vikernes underlined &quot;his role as chieftain of his Norwegian Heathen Front&quot; with the writing of ''Vargsmål''.&lt;ref&gt;Goodrick-Clarke 2003: 205.&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 2009 interview with Vikernes, the Norwegian newspaper ''[[Dagbladet]]'' pointed out that he has been linked to neo-Nazi and racist groups during his time in prison.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dagbladet.no&quot;/&gt; Vikernes replied: &quot;I have never formed or been a member of such organizations. The only organization I am a member of is [[Riksmålsforbundet]]&quot; (''The Society for the Preservation of Traditional Standard Norwegian'').&lt;ref name=&quot;Dagbladet.no&quot;/&gt;

When he was asked about his involvement in the AHF in a 2004 interview published on burzum.org, Vikernes pointed out that it was [[Antifa]] groups who &quot;repeatedly wrote&quot; that the NHF was a Neo-Nazi group and that he was their leader, claims which he describes as &quot;persecution&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;BZINT&quot;/&gt; He also said that &quot;the [Norwegian] secret police claimed adamantly&quot; that he was the leader of the Heathen Front.&lt;ref name=&quot;BZINT&quot;/&gt; Vikernes then continued by stating that, as a result of these claims, he left the Heathen Front, to see what &quot;the Antifa/Monitor morons and the secret police would do&quot;. In practice, Vikernes stated, he never was a member of the group, since, being in prison, he could not participate in their activities and he had not ever &quot;met half of them&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;BZINT&quot;/&gt; If he would want to write articles for their magazine, he could do that, regardless of whether he was a member or not.&lt;ref name=&quot;BZINT&quot;/&gt;

===Religion===
In a 2010 interview with &quot;Vampiria&quot; Magazine Spain (18-03-2010) Vikernes was asked about Odinism playing a major role in his life, to which he responded:

&quot;Well, I am not religious in any way, but I have a Pagan ideology and Pagan values. I believe in blood, soil and honour; family, homeland and [[hamingja]]; strength, traditions and courage. And I believe in a Europe waking up.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.burzum.org/eng/library/2010_interview_vampiria.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Burzum-Flyer-92.jpg|thumb|right|Pro-Burzum Flyer with a list of church fires]] --&gt;
Vikernes has written lyrics for several songs by [[Darkthrone]] that make use of themes from old [[German folklore|Germanic folklore]]. In these, [[Satan]] is referenced as an aspect of the Germanic god [[Odin]] in the context of an 'eye' that is a source of light (i.e. the sun), there are also mentions of a 'spear' and a 'hall of battle', which are also masked references to [[Odin]]. This was done with the double meaning of Odin as the 'adversary' of Jewish and Christian tradition. Many have thus inferred that Vikernes is or was a [[Satanism|Satanist]], though he has stated many times that he is opposed to Satanism as he considers it to be a reactionary form of Christianity.

According to Vikernes:
&lt;blockquote&gt;Christianity was created by some decadent and degenerated Romans as a tool of oppression, in the late Roman era, and it should be treated accordingly. It is like &quot;handcuff's&quot; to the mind and spirit and is nothing but destructive to mankind. In fact I don't really see Christianity as a religion. It is more like a spiritual plague, a mass psychosis, and it should first and foremost be treated as a problem to be solved by the medical science. Christianity is a diagnosis. It's like Islam and the other Asian &quot;religions&quot; a [[HIV/AIDS]] of the spirit and mind.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.archive.org/web/20090606001302/http://www.metalcrypt.com/pages/interviewsframe.php?intid=170 |title=Varg Vikernes |publisher=The Metal Crypt |accessdate=2011-08-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Vikernes now embraces a &quot;modern scientific worldview resting on a foundation made up of the Pagan values and ideals: loyalty, wisdom, courage, love, discipline, honesty, intelligence, beauty, responsibility, health and strength.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;bards8&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.burzum.org/eng/library/a_bards_tale08.shtml |title=Bard's Tale: part VIII: Religion or Reason |publisher=Burzum.org |accessdate=2011-08-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; He draws a direct connection between both [[race and intelligence]] and [[intelligence and religion]], denouncing [[theism]] as &quot;mental enslavement&quot; fit only for &quot;inferior races&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;bards8&quot; /&gt; Vikernes goes on to say &quot;If it is supposed to serve a purpose Paganism needs to be an ideology, not a religion&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;bards8&quot; /&gt; Despite accusing mainstream theists of holding onto &quot;[[Stone Age]] misconceptions&quot;, Vikernes still holds that religious myths should be turned to in areas where science has not yet achieved a complete understanding of the natural world—such as the origin of life and where we go after death, if anywhere at all.&lt;ref name=&quot;bards8&quot; /&gt;

Later in 2009, he posted an article on his website, writing &quot;I obviously live in a different world, where one can discuss ones perception of reality without any fear of harassment; a world of tolerance and respect, a world of intellectual debate and honesty. Some of You apparently don't, so when I speak I must be careful.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Varg Vikernes&quot; group=Burzum.org&gt;{{cite web|last=Vikernes|first=Varg|title=A Burzum Story: Part XI – Birds Of A Feather Flock Together|url=http://www.burzum.org/eng/library/a_burzum_story11.shtml|work=A Burzum Story|publisher=Majordomo|accessdate=24 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In addition to ''Vargsmål'', works by Vikernes on his personal [[world view]] include ''Irminsûl'' and ''Germansk Mytologi og Verdensanskuelse'' ('Germanic Mythology and Worldview').&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.arktos.com/germansk-mytologi-verdensanskuelse.html?___store=gbz|title=Germansk Mytologi &amp; Verdensanskuelse|publisher=Arktos|accessdate=15 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2011, Vikernes published his first book in English, ''Sorcery and Religion in Ancient Scandinavia'', a revised version of ''Germansk Mytologi'' about the religious practices of Scandinavian peoples, particularly during the [[Stone Age]] and [[Bronze Age]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = Vikernes| first = Varg| title = Varg Vikernes &quot;Sorcery And Religion In Ancient Scandinavia&quot;| date = 27 August 2011| url = http://www.burzum.org/eng/library/sorcery_and_religion_in_ancient_scandinavia.shtml | accessdate = 15 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rejecting most contemporary academic theories, he takes inspiration from [[Sir James Frazer]]'s work ''[[The Golden Bough]]'' in interpreting the myths as representing aspects of yearly rituals related to death, burial and ruling.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last = Vikernes| first = Varg| title = Sorcery and Religion in Ancient Scandinavia| publisher = Abstract Sounds Books Ltd| edition = 1st| date = 5 December 2012| page = 6| isbn = 978-0-9566959-3-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; It includes a new translation of the [[Völuspá]] with notes about what each stanza means according to Vikernes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = Pomo| first = Brian| title = &quot;Sorcery and Religion in Ancient Scandinavia&quot; by Varg Vikernes| publisher = Heathen Harvest| date = 17 May 2012| url = http://heathenharvest.org/2012/05/17/sorcery-and-religion-in-ancient-scandinavia-by-varg-vikernes-3/| accessdate = 15 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Influence of Vidkun Quisling===
[[Vidkun Quisling]], Nazi [[Collaborationism|collaborator]] [[minister-president]] of occupied Norway between 1942 and 1945 and involuntary originator of the term [[quisling]]-regime, had developed an extremely obscure [[Esotericism|esoteric]] doctrine labeled 'Universism'. An online article&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bitsofnews.com/content/view/3965/2/ &quot;The World According to Quisling&quot;] by Gisle Tangenes, BitsofNews.com, 19 September 2006&lt;/ref&gt; about him mentions that the only &quot;modest intellectual influence&quot; he ever had with this doctrine was &quot;on certain extreme strains of Norwegian black metal music&quot;. This impression is indeed given in ''Lords of Chaos''. In the interview there, Varg Vikernes is faced with the question whether Quisling's religion was pagan or Christian.&lt;ref&gt;Lords of Chaos (First Edition), 163&lt;/ref&gt; Moynihan &amp; Søderlind write: &quot;Vikernes has discovered his predecessor in Vidkun Quisling.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Lords of Chaos (First Edition), 162&lt;/ref&gt; At one point, he temporarily took the artist name 'Kvisling',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.burzum.org/eng/discography/official/1997_daudi_baldrs.shtml |title=Discography – Official Releases – &quot;Daudi Baldrs&quot; (&quot;Balder's Dod&quot;) 1997 |publisher=Burzum |accessdate=2011-08-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; but he explained this choice in ''Vargsmål'':
&lt;blockquote&gt;One of my foremothers was called Susanne Malene Qisling. She was born 06-02-1811 and dies {{sic}} 10-05-1891. Qisling means &quot;that which stems from a division of kingly descendants&quot; [...]&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Vikernes stated in an interview, &quot;They [the Norwegian government at the beginning of World War II] ran like chickens, leaving Norway, with absolutely NO authorities, and when Vidkun Quisling tried to bring order back, he was thanked with a bullet in his heart after the war.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.burzum.com/burzum/library/interviews/heresy/ |title=The Music of Burzum and the Writings of Varg Vikernes (with 1993 interview) |publisher=Burzum.com |accessdate=2011-08-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is the only known instance of Vikernes mentioning Vidkun Quisling, besides ''Lords of Chaos''; on www.burzum.org Vikernes does not mention Vidkun Quisling at all.&lt;ref&gt;other than the above-referenced mention of his great-great-grandmother's name: [http://www.burzum.org/eng/library/a_burzum_story05.shtml A Burzum Story: Part V – Satanism]&lt;/ref&gt;

===''The Lord of the Rings''===
From an early age, Vikernes was fascinated with the fictional realm of [[Middle-earth]] created by [[J. R. R. Tolkien]]. His stage name ''[[Grishnakh#Grishnákh|Grishnackh]]'' is taken from that of an orc in ''[[The Two Towers]]''. The name ''Burzum'', meaning ''darkness'', was taken from the [[Black Speech]] inscribed on the [[One Ring]] in ''[[The Lord of the Rings]]''. The inscription read &quot;Ash nazg durbatulûk, ash nazg gimbatul, ash nazg thrakatulûk agh ''burzum''-ishi krimpatul&quot; or in English &quot;One Ring to rule them all, One Ring to find them, One Ring to bring them all and in the ''darkness'' bind them.&quot; Additionally, before joining Old Funeral, he was in a band called Uruk-Hai, also derived from ''The Lord of the Rings'' text.

Vikernes interpreted ''The Lord of the Rings'' on his website, pointing out the connections to paganism in the books, but also recognizing the Judeo-Christian context of Tolkien's Catholic beliefs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.burzum.org/eng/library/paganism03.shtml |title=Paganism: Part III – The One Ring |publisher=Burzum.org |accessdate=2011-08-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Publicity==

===''Lords of Chaos''===
American journalist [[Michael Moynihan (journalist)|Michael Moynihan]] wrote a book entitled ''[[Lords of Chaos (book)|Lords of Chaos: The Bloody Rise of the Satanic Metal Underground]]'' with co-author Didrik Søderlind that is concerned with the events of the early black metal scene in Norway, a book many of the participants of the Norwegian black metal scene{{Who|date=April 2009}}{{Citation needed|date=April 2009}} have accused of misquotation and distortion of facts. One extensive review has been written by [[Kevin Coogan]], author of a biography of the neo-fascist writer and activist [[Francis Parker Yockey]]. In ''Lords of Chaos'', as Coogan writes, &quot;Moynihan suggests that Vikernes is an avatar of a long-repressed Odinist archetype analogous to what Jung claimed for Nazi Germany in his famous 1936 essay on Wotan.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coogan&quot;/&gt; The book's thesis about black metal as a &quot;rise&quot; of this Odinist archetype is factually problematic: &quot;LOC's musings about fascism and black metal largely hang on a thin evidential thread, Varg Vikemes.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coogan&quot;/&gt;

There is also a review of this book available on Burzum's official website, www.burzum.org, that is allegedly written by Varg Vikernes:
&lt;blockquote&gt;I dare say the vast majority of all the statements made in this book are either misinterpretations; taken out of context; misunderstandings; malicious lies made by enemies; a result of ignorance; extreme exaggerations; and/or third-hand information at best. This includes the statements attributed to me!... [The authors] have no insight into or even good knowledge about the subjects discussed and ... don't understand one bit what black metal was about in 1991 and 1992... [They] have managed to fill the heads of a generation of metal fans with lies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.burzum.org/eng/library/lords_of_chaos_review.shtml |title=&quot;Lords of Chaos: The Bloody Rise of The Satanic Metal Underground&quot; review |publisher=Burzum.org |accessdate=2011-08-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===''Satan rir media''===
Torstein Grude created a Norwegian documentary entitled ''[[Satan rir media]]'' (''Satan Rides the Media''), to which Vikernes has given a more positive review. As its title implies, the movie focuses on the often hysterical media coverage of the church-burning cases and the black metal scene in general. In the film, Vikernes accuses a journalist who writes for ''[[Bergens Tidende]]'' of deliberately informing the police about his identity after he had completed an anonymous interview. Vikernes was arrested only hours after the interview, one day before it was published, and was released after a week in prison due to lack of proof. In the film, the head of criminal investigations, Bergen Police District evades the question whether the journalist preserved Vikernes' anonymity by stating &quot;It was all OK and legal&quot;.

According to ''Satan rir media'', it was also the BT who gave Vikernes the name &quot;Greven&quot; (The Count). However, Vikernes has said in ''Vargsmål'' that &quot;the reason I chose this name was not to have a tough name. The word 'count (greven)' comes from the Latin word 'comites', that means partner or companion. I am the true Germanic folk's 'partner' and 'companion' and with that I chose this title&quot;.

''Satan rir media'' claims that by emphasizing the Satanist angle, the Norwegian news media unwittingly created a mass following for Burzum and Vikernes, both in Norway and internationally.

===''Until the Light Takes Us''===
Vikernes is one of the central figures in the 2009 documentary film ''[[Until The Light Takes Us]]''. Interviewed in prison by American directors Aaron Aites and Audrey Ewell, Vikernes explains, in great detail, the circumstances surrounding both the creation of black metal and the murder of Euronymous.

===Influence on other church arsons===
[[File:Church.20060530 PM.porvoo of finland.ojp.jpg|thumb|right|Vikernes's actions allegedly inspired Kalle Holm to burn Porvoo Cathedral in Finland.]]
* Novak Majstorovic, then 19-year-old guitarist of the metal band Schwarzreich, was charged with arson and burglary in relation to the burning of a 100+-year-old [[United and uniting churches|Uniting Church]] in [[Ascot Vale, Victoria|Ascot Vale]], Australia in August 2004. He was convicted and sentenced to three years in Youth Detention. In all media depictions of the event, he is said to have been heavily influenced by Burzum. However, he has stated on several message boards across the internet that the influence does not stretch beyond the superficial, and that the media has overblown his statements to the police to suit their own ends. He claims that the arson had very little in common with Vikernes' attacks. Majstorovic was released in August 2006. His current whereabouts are unknown.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.theage.com.au/news/opinion/dont-simply-demonise-death-metal/2005/09/28/1127804542833.html/ |title=Johnston, Chris. &quot;Don't simply demonise death metal&quot; ''The Age'' 28 September 2005 |work=The Age |location=Australia |date= 29 September 2005|accessdate=2011-08-20 |location=Melbourne}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Kalle Holm, an 18-year-old [[Finland|Finn]] known to have played drums in several Finnish metal bands, has stated on his website that he was influenced by Burzum. He set fire to the [[Porvoo Cathedral]] in Finland in May 2006: the roof of the church burned, but the ceiling, vaults and interiors survived undamaged. The attorney's claims that the motives behind the arson were related to a &quot;hatred towards Christianity&quot; were overruled in court. He was sentenced to three years and two months of imprisonment without parole.&lt;ref&gt;Helsingin Sanomat: [http://www.hs.fi/kotimaa/artikkeli/Porvoon+tuomiokirkon+tulipalosta+yli+kolmen+vuoden+vankeustuomio/1135221308860 Porvoon tuomiokirkon tulipalosta yli kolmen vuoden vankeustuomio] {{fi icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; The sentence was later doubled to six years and six months by the Court of Appeal.&lt;ref&gt;Helsingin Sanomat: [http://www.hs.fi/kotimaa/artikkeli/Hovioikeus+kovensi+Porvoon+kirkon+sytytt%C3%A4j%C3%A4n+tuomiota/1135227276873 Hovioikeus kovensi Porvoon kirkon sytyttäjän tuomiota] {{fi icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The ''[[Winnipeg Sun]]'' reported that three people were convicted on 27 June 2006 of arson in a fire that destroyed the Minnedosa [[United Church of Canada|United Church]] in [[Minnedosa, Manitoba]], Canada on 12 February 2006. One was sentenced to three years in prison, the second to two years and the third to two years less a day. All three were ordered to pay CAD $1.2 million in restitution. Justice officials said the church was set on fire on 11 February, Vikernes' birthday.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.roadrunnerrecords.com/blabbermouth.net/news.aspx?mode=Article&amp;newsitemID=54325 |title=Canadian Black Metal Arsonists Receive Jail Time – 28 June 2006 |publisher=Roadrunnerrecords.com |accessdate=2011-08-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Works==
&lt;!--this section is only for the lists--&gt;

===Discography===
'''''As Burzum:'''''
*1992&amp;nbsp;– ''[[Burzum (album)|Burzum]]'' (recorded January 1992)
*1993&amp;nbsp;– ''[[Aske (album)|Aske]]'' (recorded August 1992)
*1993&amp;nbsp;– ''[[Det som engang var]]'' (recorded April 1992)
*1994&amp;nbsp;– ''[[Hvis lyset tar oss]]'' (recorded September 1992)
*1996&amp;nbsp;– ''[[Filosofem]]'' (recorded March 1993)
*1997&amp;nbsp;– ''[[Dauði Baldrs]]'' (recorded in prison 1994–1995)
*1999&amp;nbsp;– ''[[Hliðskjálf (album)|Hliðskjálf]]'' (recorded in prison 1998)
*2010&amp;nbsp;– ''[[Belus (album)|Belus]]'' (recorded in 2009)
*2011&amp;nbsp;– ''[[Fallen (Burzum album)|Fallen]]'' (recorded November 2010)
*2011&amp;nbsp;– ''[[From the Depths of Darkness]]'' (recorded March 2010)
*2012&amp;nbsp;– ''[[Umskiptar]]'' (recorded September 2011)

'''''Other appearances:'''''
*1994&amp;nbsp;– [[Darkthrone]]&amp;nbsp;– ''[[Transilvanian Hunger]]'' (wrote lyrics for four songs)
*1995&amp;nbsp;– Darkthrone&amp;nbsp;– ''[[Panzerfaust (album)|Panzerfaust]]'' (wrote lyrics for one song)
*1994&amp;nbsp;– [[Mayhem (band)|Mayhem]]&amp;nbsp;– ''[[De Mysteriis Dom Sathanas]]'' (performed bass guitar)
*2009&amp;nbsp;– Mayhem&amp;nbsp;– ''[[Life Eternal (EP)|Life Eternal]]'' (EP, performed bass guitar)
*1991&amp;nbsp;– [[Old Funeral]]&amp;nbsp;– ''[[Devoured Carcass]]'' (EP, performed electric guitar)
*1999&amp;nbsp;– Old Funeral&amp;nbsp;– ''[[Join the Funeral Procession]]'' (compilation album, performed electric guitar)
*1999&amp;nbsp;– Old Funeral&amp;nbsp;– ''[[The Older Ones]]'' (compilation album, performed electric guitar)
*2002&amp;nbsp;– Old Funeral&amp;nbsp;– ''[[Grim Reaping Norway]]'' (live album, performed electric guitar)

===Bibliography===
* 1997&amp;nbsp;– ''Vargsmål''
* 2000&amp;nbsp;– ''Germansk Mytologi og Verdensanskuelse''
* 2001&amp;nbsp;– ''Guide to the Norse Gods and Their Names''
* 2002&amp;nbsp;– ''Irminsûl''
* 2006&amp;nbsp;– ''Речи Варга II'' (Russian language-only compilation of articles, the title means &quot;Vargsmål II&quot;)
* 2011&amp;nbsp;– ''Sorcery And Religion In Ancient Scandinavia''

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
* [http://www.antirasistisk-senter.no/infobank/hoyre_nor/nazirapp2001.PDF Right wing extremism in Norway – 2001], page 8, paragraph title ''Norsk Hedensk Front'', published by [[Antirasistisk senter]] and Monitor {{no icon}}
* [http://www.antirasistisk-senter.no/infobanken/dokumenter/artikler/xt99.html The extreme right 1999], a report from Antirasistisk senter {{no icon}}
* [http://www.aftenposten.no/nyheter/iriks/article656500.ece The Count caught with an AG-3 automatic rifle], news coverage in ''[[Aftenposten]]'' {{no icon}}
* [http://www.aftenposten.no/english/local/article655724.ece Police nab ''The Count'' after he fled jail], news coverage in ''Aftenposten''
* [http://www.aftenposten.no/english/local/article656646.ece Arrested ''Count'' was heavily armed], news coverage in ''Aftenposten''
* [http://www.metalcrypt.com/pages/interviewsframe.php?intid=170 Interview on a metal site] (old photo before new political affiliations)
* [http://www.theage.com.au/news/opinion/dont-simply-demonise-death-metal/2005/09/28/1127804542833.html/ Editorial] in ''[[The Age]]'' on Novak and his actions
* [http://www.dagbladet.no/nyheter/2000/07/25/212726.html The nun-murders inspired by ''The count''], news coverage in ''[[Dagbladet]]'' {{no icon}}
* [http://www.vg.no/pub/vgart.hbs?artid=6897182 ''The Count'' could have inspired the nun-killing], news coverage in ''[[Verdens Gang]]'' {{no icon}}
* {{Reflist|group=Burzum.org}}

==Documentation==
* [[Kevin Coogan]]. 1999. [http://oraclesyndicate.twoday.net/stories/605560/ How Black is Black Metal?] ''Hit List'' 1:1 (February/March), 33–59. Retrieved 23 July 2009.
*[[Mattias Gardell]]. 2003. ''[[Gods of the Blood]]: The Pagan Revival and White Separatism''. Duke University Press. ISBN 978-0-8223-3071-4
*[[Nicholas Goodrick-Clarke]]. 2003. ''[[Black Sun (Goodrick-Clarke book)|Black Sun]]: Aryan Cults, Esoteric Nazism and the Politics of Identity''. New York University Press. ISBN 0-8147-3155-4
*Jeffrey Kaplan (Ed.). 2000. ''[[Encyclopedia of White Power]]: A Sourcebook on the Radical Racist Right''. AltaMira Press. ISBN 978-0-7425-0340-3
*[[Michael Moynihan (journalist)|Michael Moynihan]] &amp; Didrik Søderlind. 1998. ''[[Lords of Chaos (book)|Lords of Chaos]]: The Bloody Rise of the Satanic Metal Underground.'' Feral House. ISBN 0-922915-48-2
*Torstein Grude. 1998. ''[[Satan rir media]]'' (''Satan Rides the Media''). (film)

==External links==
; Official sites
* [http://www.burzum.org/ Official Burzum and Varg Vikernes home site]

; Unofficial sites
* [http://www.burzum.com/ Burzum.com]
* [http://www.vg.no/pub/vgart.hbs?artid=82235 Article and picture from the 2003 arrest]
* [http://www.ethniko.net/blog/varg-vikernes-vidkun-quisling Article about Varg Vikernes' relationship with Vidkun Quisling]

{{Burzum}}
{{Mayhem (band)}}
{{White nationalism}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Vikernes, Varg
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = Norwegian musciian
| DATE OF BIRTH     =11 February 1973
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = near [[Bergen]], Norway (age )
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Vikernes, Varg}}
[[Category:1973 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:1993 crimes]]
[[Category:Adherents of Germanic neopaganism]]
[[Category:Dark ambient musicians]]
[[Category:Anti-Christianity]]
[[Category:Anti-Judaism]]
[[Category:Black metal singers]]
[[Category:Norwegian activists]]
[[Category:Norwegian fascists]]
[[Category:Mayhem (band) members]]
[[Category:Norwegian anti-communists]]
[[Category:Norwegian arsonists]]
[[Category:Norwegian black metal musicians]]
[[Category:Norwegian bloggers]]
[[Category:Norwegian neopagans]]
[[Category:Norwegian non-fiction writers]]
[[Category:Norwegian people convicted of murder]]
[[Category:Norwegian rock bass guitarists]]
[[Category:Norwegian rock keyboardists]]
[[Category:People convicted of murder by Norway]]
[[Category:Musicians from Bergen]]
[[Category:Norwegian multi-instrumentalists]]
[[Category:White nationalists]]
[[Category:Norwegian rock drummers]]
[[Category:Norwegian rock guitarists]]
[[Category:Norwegian rock singers]]

{{Link GA|ru}}
[[be:Варг Вікернес]]
[[bg:Варг Викернес]]
[[br:Varg Vikernes]]
[[cs:Varg Vikernes]]
[[da:Varg Vikernes]]
[[de:Varg Vikernes]]
[[es:Varg Vikernes]]
[[fa:ورگ ویکرنس]]
[[fr:Varg Vikernes]]
[[hr:Varg Vikernes]]
[[id:Varg Vikernes]]
[[is:Varg Vikernes]]
[[it:Varg Vikernes]]
[[lv:Vargs Vikerness]]
[[lt:Varg Vikernes]]
[[nl:Varg Vikernes]]
[[ja:ヴァルグ・ヴィーケネス]]
[[no:Varg Vikernes]]
[[nn:Varg Vikernes]]
[[nrm:Varg Vikernes]]
[[oc:Varg Vikernes]]
[[pl:Varg Vikernes]]
[[pt:Varg Vikernes]]
[[ro:Varg Vikernes]]
[[ru:Викернес, Варг]]
[[simple:Varg Vikernes]]
[[sk:Varg Vikernes]]
[[fi:Varg Vikernes]]
[[sv:Varg Vikernes]]
[[tr:Varg Vikernes]]
[[uk:Варґ Вікернес]]
[[vi:Varg Vikernes]]</text>
      <sha1>2dfrkwicvwubflezj41huwt0vt8uk6q</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
