<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Antisemitism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1078</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521030856</id>
      <parentid>520828967</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T10:21:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Magioladitis</username>
        <id>1862829</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Malaysia */Remove unicode control characters (CHECKWIKI error 16) using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (8514)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="146128">{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2012}}
{{pp-semi|small=yes}}
{{Antisemitism}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
'''Antisemitism''' (also spelled '''anti-semitism''' or '''anti-Semitism''') is suspicion of, hatred toward, or [[discrimination]] against [[Jews]] for reasons connected to their [[Judaism|Jewish]] heritage. Social scientists consider it a form of racism. In a 2005 U.S. governmental report, antisemitism is defined as &quot;hatred toward Jews—individually and as a group—that can be attributed to the Jewish religion and/or ethnicity.&quot;&lt;ref name=USDS&gt;[http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/40258.htm &quot;Report on Global Anti-Semitism&quot;], [[United States Department of State|U.S. State Department]], 5 January 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; A person who holds such views is called an &quot;antisemite&quot;.
Antisemitism may be manifested in many ways, ranging from expressions of hatred of or [[discrimination]] against individual Jews to organized [[pogroms|violent attacks]] by mobs, state police, or even military attacks on entire Jewish communities. Extreme instances of [[Persecution of Jews|persecution]] include the [[pogroms]] which preceded the [[Persecution of Jews in the First Crusade|First Crusade]] in 1096, the [[Edict of Expulsion|expulsion from England]] in 1290, the [[History of the Jews in Spain#Massacre of 1391|massacres of Spanish Jews]] in 1391, the persecutions of the [[Spanish Inquisition]], the [[Alhambra Decree|expulsion from Spain]] in 1492, [[Khmelnytsky Uprising#Jews|Cossack massacres in Ukraine]], various [[Anti-Jewish pogroms in the Russian Empire|pogroms]] in Russia, the [[Dreyfus affair]], the [[Holocaust]], official [[Antisemitism in the Soviet Union|Soviet anti-Jewish policies]] and the [[Jewish exodus from Arab and Muslim countries]].

While the term's [[etymology]] might suggest that antisemitism is directed against all [[Semitic peoples]], the term was coined in the late 19th century in Germany as a more scientific-sounding term for ''Judenhass'' (&quot;Jew-hatred&quot;),&lt;ref name=Judenhass&gt;
*Jerome A. Chanes. ''Antisemitism: A Reference Handbook'', ABC-CLIO, 2004, p. 150.
*Rattansi, Ali. [http://books.google.com/books?id=YVOb3MDBmBEC&amp;pg=PA4 ''Racism: A Very Short Introduction''], [[Oxford University Press]], 2007, pp. 4–5.
*Rubenstein, Richard L.; Roth, John K. [http://books.google.com/books?id=IfoBx6skMCkC&amp;pg=PA30 ''Approaches to Auschwitz: the Holocaust and its legacy''], [[Westminster John Knox Press]], 2003, p.&amp;nbsp;30.
*Johnston, William M. [http://books.google.com/books?id=-dmH7FjxassC&amp;pg=PA27 ''The Austrian Mind: An Intellectual and Social History, 1848–1938''], [[University of California Press]], 1983, p. 27.&lt;/ref&gt;
and that has been its normal use since then.&lt;ref name=JustJews&gt;
*[[Bernard Lewis|Lewis, Bernard]]. [http://middleeastinfo.org/library/lewis_antisemitism.html &quot;Semites and Antisemites&quot;]. Extract from ''Islam in History: Ideas, Men and Events in the Middle East'', The Library Press, 1973.
*&quot;Anti-Semitism&quot;, ''Encyclopædia Britannica'', 2006.
*[[Paul Johnson (writer)|Johnson, Paul]]. ''A History of the Jews'', HarperPerennial 1988, pp. 133 ff.
*[[Bernard Lewis|Lewis, Bernard]]. [http://hnn.us/blogs/entries/21832.html &quot;The New Anti-Semitism&quot;], ''The American Scholar'', Volume 75 No. 1, Winter 2006, pp. 25–36. The paper is based on a lecture delivered at [[Brandeis University]] on 24 March 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Etymology and usage==

===Usage===
Despite the use of the prefix ''anti-'', the terms ''Semitic'' and ''anti-Semitic'' are not directly opposed to each other. ''Antisemitism'' refers specifically to prejudice against [[Jew]]s alone and in general,&lt;ref name=JustJews/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/antisemitism Antisemitism – Definition and More from the Merriam-Webster Dictionary]. Retrieved on 2 June 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; despite the fact that there are other speakers of [[Semitic language]]s (e.g. [[Arab people|Arab]]s, [[People of Ethiopia|Ethiopians]], or [[Assyrian people|Assyrians]]) and that not all Jews speak a Semitic language.

The term ''anti-Semitic'' has been used on occasion to include [[bigotry]] against other Semitic-language peoples such as Arabs, but such usage is not widely accepted.&lt;ref&gt;[[David Matas|Matas, David]]. [http://books.google.com/books?id=DYR7SqcMe9gC&amp;pg=PA34 ''Aftershock: Anti-Zionism and Antisemitism''], Dundurn Press, 2005, p. 34.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|title=Semites and Anti-Semites: An Inquiry Into conflict and Prejudice
|first=Bernard
|last=Lewis
|authorlink=Bernard Lewis
|page=117
|year=1999}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Both terms ''anti-Semitism'' and ''antisemitism'' are in common use. Some scholars favor the unhyphenated form ''antisemitism'' to avoid possible confusion involving whether the term refers specifically to Jews, or to [[Semitic]]-language speakers as a whole.&lt;ref&gt;{{PDFlink|[http://www.facinghistory.org/campus/reslib.nsf/99ca830bb4f483948525717f005abfc7/2820f36c177cc758852571860065e8c2/$FILE/complete_antisemitism.pdf Antisemitism. The Power of Myth] (Facing History).|184&amp;nbsp;KB}} Retrieved 21 August 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Bauer&gt;[[Yehuda Bauer|Bauer, Yehuda]]. {{PDFlink|[http://humwww.ucsc.edu/jewishstudies/docs/YBauerLecture.pdf &quot;Problems of Contemporary Antisemitism&quot;]|196&amp;nbsp;KB}}. Retrieved 12 March 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Bauer2&gt;Bauer, Yehuda. ''A History of the Holocaust'', Franklin Watts, 1982, p. 52. ISBN 0-531-05641-4&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Almog&gt;Almog, Shmuel. [http://sicsa.huji.ac.il/hyphen.htm &quot;What's in a Hyphen?&quot;], SICSA Report: Newsletter of the [[Vidal Sassoon International Center for the Study of Antisemitism]] (Summer 1989).&lt;/ref&gt; For example, [[Emil Fackenheim]] supported the unhyphenated spelling, in order to &quot;dispel[] the notion that there is an entity 'Semitism' which 'anti-Semitism' opposes.&quot;&lt;ref name=Fackenheim&gt;[[Dennis Prager|Prager, Dennis]]; [[Joseph Telushkin|Telushkin, Joseph]]. [http://books.google.com/books?id=VK0llzUqQ2YC&amp;pg=PA199 ''Why the Jews?: The Reason for Antisemitism''], [[Simon and Schuster]], 1983, p. 199.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Etymology===
[[File:Bookcover-1880-Marr-German uber Juden.jpg|thumb|Cover page of Marr's ''The Way to Victory of Germanicism over Judaism'', 1880 edition]]
Although [[Wilhelm Marr]] is generally credited with coining the word ''anti-Semitism'' (see below), [[Alex Bein]] writes that the word was first used in 1860 by the Austrian Jewish scholar [[Moritz Steinschneider]] in the phrase &quot;anti-Semitic prejudices&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[Alex Bein|Bein, Alex]]. [http://books.google.com/books?id=cQOn0y8ENg4C&amp;pg=PA594 ''The Jewish Question: Biography of a World Problem'']. Fairleigh Dickinson University Press, 1990, p.&amp;nbsp;594. ISBN 0-8386-3252-1.&lt;/ref&gt; Steinschneider used this phrase to characterize [[Ernest Renan]]'s ideas about how &quot;[[Semitic]] races&quot; were inferior to &quot;[[Aryan]] races.&quot; These [[Pseudoscience|pseudo-scientific]] theories concerning race, civilization, and &quot;progress&quot; had become quite widespread in Europe in the second half of the 19th century, especially as [[Prussia]]n nationalistic historian [[Heinrich von Treitschke]] did much to promote this form of racism. He coined the term &quot;the Jews are our misfortune&quot; which would later be widely used by [[Nazism|Nazis]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Leon Poliakov|Poliakov, Leon]] ''The History of Anti-Semitism, Vol. 3: From Voltaire to Wagner'', University of Pennsylvania Press: 2003, p. 404 ISBN 978-0-8122-1865-7&lt;/ref&gt; In Treitschke's writings ''Semitic'' was synonymous with ''Jewish'', in contrast to its use by Renan and others.

In 1873 German journalist [[Wilhelm Marr]] published a pamphlet ''&quot;The Victory of the Jewish Spirit over the Germanic Spirit. Observed from a non-religious perspective.&quot;'' (''&quot;Der Sieg des Judenthums über das Germanenthum. Vom nicht confessionellen Standpunkt aus betrachtet.&quot;'')&lt;ref&gt;[[Wilhelm Marr|Marr, Wilhelm]]. [http://www.archive.org/details/DerSiegdesJudenthumsueberdasGermanenthum|Der Sieg des Judenthums über das Germanenthum. Vom nicht confessionellen Standpunkt aus betrachtet.] Rudolph Costenoble. 1879, 8th edition. Archive.org.&lt;/ref&gt; in which he used the word ''&quot;Semitismus&quot;'' interchangeably with the word &quot;Judentum&quot; to denote both &quot;Jewry&quot; (the Jews as a collective) and &quot;jewishness&quot; (the quality of being Jewish, or the Jewish spirit). Although he did not use the word &quot;Antisemitismus&quot; in the pamphlet, the coining of the latter word followed naturally from the word &quot;Semitismus&quot;, and indicated either opposition to the Jews as a people, or else opposition to Jewishness or the Jewish spirit, which he saw as infiltrating German culture. In his next pamphlet, ''&quot;The Way to Victory of the Germanic Spirit over the Jewish Spirit&quot;'', published in 1880, Marr developed his ideas further and coined the related German word ''Antisemitismus'' – ''antisemitism'', derived from the word &quot;Semitismus&quot; that he had earlier used.

The pamphlet became very popular, and in the same year he founded the ''&quot;League of Antisemites&quot;'' (&quot;''Antisemiten-Liga''&quot;), the first German organization committed specifically to combatting the alleged threat to Germany and German culture posed by the Jews and their influence, and advocating their [[population transfer|forced removal]] from the country.

So far as can be ascertained, the word was first widely printed in 1881, when Marr published ''&quot;Zwanglose Antisemitische Hefte,&quot;'' and [[Wilhelm Scherer]] used the term &quot;''Antisemiten''&quot; in the January issue of ''&quot;Neue Freie Presse&quot;''. The related word ''[[Philo-Semitism|semitism]]'' was coined around 1885.

===Definition===
Though the general definition of antisemitism is hostility or prejudice against Jews, and, according to Olaf Blaschke, become an 'umbrella term for negative stereotypes about Jews,'&lt;ref&gt;cited in Sonja Weinberg, [http://books.google.com.au/books?id=0HDeEPouQm0C&amp;pg=PA18 ''Pogroms and Riots: German Press Responses to Anti-Jewish Violence in Germany and Russia, (1881–1882),''] Peter Lang, 2010 p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt; a number of authorities have developed more formal definitions. 

Holocaust scholar and [[City University of New York]] professor [[Helen Fein]] defines it as &quot;a persisting latent structure of hostile beliefs towards Jews as a collective manifested in individuals as attitudes, and in culture as myth, ideology, folklore and imagery, and in actions – social or legal discrimination, political mobilization against the Jews, and collective or state violence – which results in and/or is designed to distance, displace, or destroy Jews as Jews.&quot; 

Elaborating on Fein's definition, Dietz Bering of the [[University of Cologne]] writes that, to antisemites, &quot;Jews are not only partially but totally bad by nature, that is, their bad traits are incorrigible. Because of this bad nature: (1) Jews have to be seen not as individuals but as a collective. (2) Jews remain essentially alien in the surrounding societies. (3) Jews bring disaster on their 'host societies' or on the whole world, they are doing it secretly, therefore the antisemites feel obliged to unmask the conspiratorial, bad Jewish character.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Avner, Falk. [http://books.google.com/books?id=zL_0WOiZj0oC&amp;pg=PA5 ''Anti-semitism: a history and psychoanalysis of contemporary hatred''], [[Greenwood Publishing Group]], 2008, p.&amp;nbsp;5.&lt;/ref&gt;

For Sonja Weinberg, as distinct from economic and religious [[anti-Judaism]], antisemitism in its modern form shows conceptual innovation, a resort to 'science' to defend itself, new functional forms and organisational differences. It was anti-liberal, racialist and nationalist. It promoted the myth that [[The Protocols of the Elders of Zion|Jews conspired to 'judaise' the world]]; it served to consolidate social identity; it channeled dissatisfactions among victims of the capitalist system; and it was used as a conservative cultural code to fight emancipation and liberalism.&lt;ref&gt;Sonja Weinberg, [http://books.google.com.au/books?id=0HDeEPouQm0C&amp;pg=PA18 ''Pogroms and Riots: German Press Responses to Anti-Jewish Violence in Germany and Russia, (1881–1882),''] pp. 18–19.&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[File:Antisemiticroths.jpg|thumb|Antisemitic caricature by C.Léandre (France, 1898) showing [[Rothschild family|Rothschild]] with the world in his hands]]
[[Bernard Lewis]] defines antisemitism as a special case of prejudice, hatred, or persecution directed against people who are in some way different from the rest. According to Lewis, antisemitism is marked by two distinct features: Jews are judged according to a standard different from that applied to others, and they are accused of &quot;cosmic evil.&quot; Thus, &quot;it is perfectly possible to hate and even to persecute Jews without necessarily being anti-Semitic&quot; unless this hatred or persecution displays one of the two features specific to antisemitism.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;[[Bernard Lewis|Lewis, Bernard]]. [http://hnn.us/blogs/entries/21832.html &quot;The New Anti-Semitism&quot;], ''The American Scholar'', Volume 75 No. 1, Winter 2006, pp. 25–36. The paper is based on a lecture delivered at [[Brandeis University]] on 24 March 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

There have been a number of efforts by international and governmental bodies to define antisemitism formally. The U.S. Department of State defines antisemitism in its 2005 Report on Global Anti-Semitism as &quot;hatred toward Jews—individually and as a group—that can be attributed to the Jewish religion and/or ethnicity.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;USDS&quot;/&gt;

In 2005, the European Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia (now [[Fundamental Rights Agency]]), then an agency of the [[European Union]], developed a more detailed [[EUMC Working Definition of Antisemitism|working definition]], which states: &quot;Antisemitism is a certain perception of Jews, which may be expressed as hatred toward Jews. Rhetorical and physical manifestations of antisemitism are directed toward Jewish or non-Jewish individuals and/or their property, toward Jewish community institutions and religious facilities.&quot; It adds &quot;such manifestations could also target the state of Israel, conceived as a Jewish collectivity.&quot; It provides contemporary examples of antisemitism, which include: promoting the harming of Jews in the name of an ideology or religion; promoting negative stereotypes of Jews; holding Jews collectively responsible for the actions of an individual Jewish person or group; [[Holocaust denial|denying the Holocaust]] or accusing Jews or Israel of exaggerating it; and accusing Jews of [[dual loyalty]] or a greater allegiance to Israel than their own country. It also lists ways in which attacking Israel could be antisemitic, and that denying the Jews their right to self-determination is antisemitic, e.g. by claiming that the existence of a state of Israel is a racist endeavor, or applying double standards by requiring of Israel a behavior not expected or demanded of any other democratic nation, or holding Jews collectively responsible for actions of the State of Israel.&lt;ref name=workingdef&gt;{{PDFlink|[http://fra.europa.eu/fraWebsite/material/pub/AS/AS-WorkingDefinition-draft.pdf &quot;Working definition of antisemitism&quot;]|33.8&amp;nbsp;KB}}, EUMC.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:1889 French election poster for antisemitic candidate Adolphe Willette.jpg|thumb|1889 Paris, France elections poster for self-described &quot;candidat antisémite&quot; [[Adolphe Willette]]: &quot;The Jews are a different race, hostile to our own... Judaism, there is the enemy!&quot; (see file for complete translation)]]

===Evolution of usage===
In 1879, [[Wilhelm Marr]] founded the ''Antisemiten-Liga'' (Antisemitic League). Identification with antisemitism and as an antisemite was politically advantageous in Europe in the latter 19th century. For example, [[Karl Lueger]], the popular mayor of [[fin de siècle]] [[Vienna]], skillfully exploited antisemitism as a way of channeling public discontent to his political advantage.&lt;ref&gt;Richard S. Geehr. ''Karl Lueger, Mayor of Fin-de-Siècle Vienna'', Wayne State University Press, Detroit, 1989. ISBN 0-8143-2055-4&lt;/ref&gt; In its 1910 obituary of Lueger, ''The New York Times'' notes that Lueger was &quot;Chairman of the Christian Social Union of the Parliament and of the Anti-Semitic Union of the Diet of Lower Austria.&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9404E7D91E30E333A25752C1A9659C946196D6CF Dr. Karl Lueger Dead; Anti-Semitic Leader and Mayor of Vienna Was 66 Years Old.] ''The New York Times'', 11 March 1910.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1895 [[A. C. Cuza]] organized the ''Alliance Anti-semitique Universelle'' in Bucharest. In the period before [[World War II]], when animosity towards Jews was far more commonplace, it was not uncommon for a person, organization, or political party to self-identify as an antisemite or antisemitic.

In 1882, the early Zionist pioneer [[Judah Leib Pinsker]] wrote that antisemitism was an inherited predisposition:{{quote|Judeophobia is a psychic aberration. As a psychic aberration it is hereditary, and as a disease transmitted for two thousand years it is incurable.' ... 'In this way have Judaism and Anti-Semitism passed for centuries through history as inseparable companions.'... ...'Having analyzed Judeophobia as an hereditary form of demonopathy, peculiar to the human race, and having represented Anti-Semitism as proceeding from an inherited aberration of the human mind, we must draw the important conclusion that we must give' up contending against these hostile impulses as we must against every other inherited predisposition.&lt;ref&gt;[[Wikisource:Auto-Emancipation|''Auto-Emancipation'' by Judah Leib Pinsker]]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In the aftermath of the  [[Kristallnacht]] pogrom in 1938, German propaganda minister [[Josef Goebbels|Goebbels]] announced: &quot;The German people is anti-Semitic. It has no desire to have its rights restricted or to be provoked in the future by parasites of the Jewish race.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Daily Telegraph'', 12 November 1938. Cited in [[Martin Gilbert|Gilbert, Martin]]. ''Kristallnacht: Prelude to Destruction.'' Harper Collins, 2006, p. 142.&lt;/ref&gt;

After the 1945 [[End of World War II in Europe|victory of the Allies over Nazi Germany]], and particularly after the extent of the [[The Holocaust|Nazi genocide of Jews]] became known, the term &quot;antisemitism&quot; acquired [[pejorative]] connotations. This marked a full circle shift in usage, from an era just decades earlier when &quot;Jew&quot; was used as a pejorative term.&lt;ref&gt;Jacob Rader Marcus. ''United States Jewry, 1776–1985.'' Wayne State University Press, 1989, p. 286. ISBN 0-8143-2186-0&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Alex Bein. ''The Jewish Question: Biography of a World Problem''. Fairleigh Dickinson University Press, 1990, p. 580. ISBN 0-8386-3252-1&lt;/ref&gt; Yehuda Bauer wrote in 1984: &quot;There are no antisemites in the world... Nobody says, 'I am antisemitic.'&quot; You cannot, after Hitler. The word has gone out of fashion.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Yehuda Bauer]]: ''The Most Ancient Group Prejudice'' in Leo Eitinger (1984): ''The Anti-Semitism of Our Time''. Oslo. Nansen Committee. p. 14. citing from: Jocelyn Hellig (2003): ''The Holocaust and Antisemitism: A Short History.'' Oneworld Publications. p.&amp;nbsp;73. ISBN 1-85168-313-5.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Forms==
[[File:Medieval manuscript-Jews identified by rouelle are being burned at stake.jpg|thumb|Jews (identified by the mandatory [[Jewish badge]] and [[Jewish hat]]) being burned during the [[Black Death]] in 1348.]]
It is often emphasized that there are different forms of antisemitism. René König mentions social antisemitism, economic antisemitism, religious antisemitism, and political antisemitism as examples. König points out that these different forms demonstrate that the &quot;origins of antisemitic prejudices are rooted in different historical periods.&quot; König asserts that differences in the chronology of different antisemitic prejudices and the irregular distribution of such prejudices over different segments of the population create &quot;serious difficulties in the definition of the different kinds of antisemitism.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Materialien zur Kriminalsoziologie |first=René |last= König |publisher=VS Verlag |year=2004 |page=231 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=N9oL2cljv8QC&amp;pg=PA231|isbn=978-3-8100-3306-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; These difficulties may contribute to the existence of different taxonomies that have been developed to categorize the forms of antisemitism. The forms identified are substantially the same; it is primarily the number of forms and their definitions that differ. Bernard Lazare identifies three forms of antisemitism: [[Christianity and antisemitism|Christian antisemitism]], economic antisemitism, and ethnologic antisemitism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Anti-Semitism: Its History and Causes |first=Bernard |last=Lazare |publisher=Cosimo, Inc. |year=2006 |page=224|url=http://books.google.com/?id=VP81v2Y24HUC&amp;pg=PA224|isbn=978-1-59605-601-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;
William Brustein names four categories: religious, racial, economic and political.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Roots of hate: anti-semitism in Europe before the Holocaust |first=William |last=Brustein |publisher=Cambridge University Press |year=2003 |page=46 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=Hc3HabBQsdsC&amp;pg=PA46 |isbn=978-0-521-77478-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Roman Catholic]] historian [[Edward Flannery]] distinguished four varieties of antisemitism:&lt;ref&gt;Flannery, Edward H. ''The Anguish of the Jews: Twenty-Three Centuries of Antisemitism'', Stimulus Books, first published 1965, this edition 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;{{page needed|date=November 2010}}
*political and economic antisemitism, giving as examples [[Cicero]] and [[Charles Lindbergh]];
*[[Religious antisemitism|theological or religious antisemitism]], sometimes known as [[anti-Judaism]];
*nationalistic antisemitism, citing [[Voltaire]] and other [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]] thinkers, who attacked Jews for supposedly having certain characteristics, such as greed and arrogance, and for observing customs such as [[kashrut]] and [[Shabbat]];
*and [[racial antisemitism]], with its extreme form resulting in the [[The Holocaust|Holocaust]] by the [[Nazi]]s.

Louis Harap separates &quot;economic antisemitism&quot; and merges &quot;political&quot; and &quot;nationalistic&quot; antisemitism into &quot;ideological antisemitism&quot;. Harap also adds a category of &quot;social antisemitism&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Creative awakening: the Jewish presence in twentieth-century American literature, 1900-1940s |first=Louis |last=Harap |publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group |year=1987 |page=24|url=http://books.google.com/?id=mAPvam-n_DYC&amp;pg=PA24|isbn=978-0-313-25386-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* religious (Jew as Christ-killer),
* economic (Jew as banker, usurer, money-obsessed),
* social (Jew as social inferior, &quot;pushy,&quot; vulgar, therefore excluded from personal contact),
* racist (Jews as an inferior &quot;race&quot;),
* ideological (Jews regarded as subversive or revolutionary),
* cultural (Jews regarded as undermining the moral and structural fiber of civilization).

===Cultural antisemitism===

Louis Harap defines cultural antisemitism as &quot;that species of anti-Semitism that charges the Jews with corrupting a given culture and attempting to supplant or succeeding in supplanting the preferred culture with a uniform, crude, &quot;Jewish&quot; culture.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Creative awakening: the Jewish presence in twentieth-century American literature |first=Louis |last=Harap |publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group |year=1987 |page=76 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=mAPvam-n_DYC&amp;pg=PA76 |isbn=978-0-313-25386-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, Eric Kandel characterizes cultural antisemitism as being based on the idea of “Jewishness” as a &quot;religious or cultural tradition that is acquired through learning, through distinctive traditions and education.&quot; According to Kandel, this form of antisemitism views Jews as possessing &quot;unattractive psychological and social characteristics that are acquired through acculturation.&quot;&lt;ref name=Kandel30&gt;{{cite book |title=In search of memory: the emergence of a new science of mind |first=Eric R. |last=Kandel |publisher=W. W. Norton &amp; Company |year=2007 |page=30 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=PFnRwWXzypgC&amp;pg=PA30 |isbn=978-0-393-32937-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; Niewyk and Nicosia characterize cultural antisemitism as focusing on and condemning &quot;the Jews' aloofness from the societies in which they live.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Columbia Guide to the Holocaust |first1=Donald L. |last1=Niewyk|first2=Francis R. |last2=Nicosia |publisher=Columbia University Press |year=2003|page=215|url=http://books.google.com/?id=z-6vKBHggVwC&amp;pg=PA215|isbn=978-0-231-11201-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;
An important feature of cultural antisemitism is that it considers the negative attributes of Judaism to be redeemable by education or religious conversion.&lt;ref name=Kandel3031&gt;{{cite book |title=In search of memory: the emergence of a new science of mind |first=Eric R. |last=Kandel |publisher=W. W. Norton &amp; Company |year=2007 |pages=30–31 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=PFnRwWXzypgC&amp;pg=PA30|isbn=978-0-393-32937-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Religious antisemitism===
{{See also|Anti-Judaism|Christianity and antisemitism|Islam and antisemitism}}

[[Religious antisemitism]] is also known as anti-Judaism. Under this version of antisemitism, attacks would often stop if Jews stopped practicing or changed their public faith, especially by [[Religious conversion|conversion]] to the official or right religion, and sometimes, liturgical exclusion of Jewish converts (the case of Christianized ''[[Marranos]]'' or Iberian Jews in the late 15th century and 16th century convicted of secretly practising Judaism or Jewish customs).&lt;ref name=Flannery&gt;Flannery, Edward H. ''The Anguish of the Jews: Twenty-Three Centuries of Antisemitism'', Stimulus Books, first published 1985, this edition 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the origins of antisemitism are rooted in the Judeo-Christian conflict, religious antisemitism, other forms of antisemitism have developed in modern times. Frederick Schweitzer asserts that, &quot;most scholars ignore the Christian foundation on which the modern antisemitic edifice rests and invoke political antisemitism, cultural antisemitism, racism or racial antisemitism, economic antisemitism and the like.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=A concise history of American antisemitism |first=Robert |last=Michael |publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield |year=2005|page=vii |url=http://books.google.com/?id=5G3feplFBYUC&amp;pg=PR7|isbn=978-0-7425-4313-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; William Nichols draws a distinction between religious antisemitism and modern antisemitism based on racial or ethnic grounds: &quot;The dividing line was the possibility of effective conversion . . . a Jew ceased to be a Jew upon baptism.&quot; From the perspective of racial antisemitism, however, &quot;... the assimilated Jew was still a Jew, even after baptism ... . From the Enlightenment onward, it is no longer possible to draw clear lines of distinction between religious and racial forms of hostility towards Jews... Once Jews have been emancipated and secular thinking makes its appearance, without leaving behind the old Christian hostility towards Jews, the new term antisemitism becomes almost unavoidable, even before explicitly racist doctrines appear.&quot;

===Economic antisemitism===
The underlying premise of [[economic antisemitism]] is that Jews perform harmful economic activities or that economic activities become harmful when they are performed by Jews.&lt;ref name=MeyerBrenner220&gt;{{cite book |title=German-Jewish History in Modern Times: Integration in dispute, 1871–1918 |publisher=Columbia University Press|year=1998 |page=220 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=HFFoSglsovoC&amp;pg=PA220|isbn=978-0-231-07476-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Linking Jews and money underpins the most damaging and lasting [[Antisemitic canard]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Jews &amp; Money – The story of a stereotype|url=http://www.adl.org/Anti_semitism/jewsandmoney/default.asp|accessdate=18 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Antisemites claim that Jews control the world finances, a theory promoted in the fraudulent [[Protocols of the Elders of Zion]], and later repeated by [[Henry Ford]] and his [[The Dearborn Independent|Dearborn Independent]]. In the modern era, such myths continue to be spread in books such as [[The Secret Relationship Between Blacks and Jews]] published by the [[Nation of Islam]], and on the internet.
[[File:Der Stürmer Christmas 1929.jpg|thumb|A caricature from the German antisemitic ''[[Der Stürmer]]'', around Christmas 1929. It urged Germans to avoid buying from Jewish shops.]]
[[Derek Penslar]] writes that there are two components to the financial [[Antisemitic canard|canards]]:&lt;ref&gt;Penslar, p. 5&lt;/ref&gt; 
:a) Jews are savages that &quot;are temperamentally incapable of performing honest labor&quot;
:b) Jews are &quot;leaders of a financial cabal seeking world domination&quot;

[[Abraham Foxman]] describes six facets of the financial canards:
#All Jews are wealthy&lt;ref&gt;Foxman, p. 84&lt;/ref&gt;
#Jews are stingy and greedy&lt;ref&gt;Foxman, p. 89&lt;/ref&gt;
#Powerful Jews control the business world&lt;ref&gt;Foxman, p. 93&lt;/ref&gt;
#Jewish religion emphasizes profit and materialism&lt;ref&gt;Foxman, p. 98&lt;/ref&gt;
#It is okay for Jews to cheat non-Jews&lt;ref&gt;Foxman, p. 102&lt;/ref&gt;
#Jews use their power to benefit &quot;their own kind&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Foxman, p. 105&lt;/ref&gt;

Gerald Krefetz summarizes the myth as &quot;[Jews] control the banks, the money supply, the economy, and businesses – of the community, of the country, of the world&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Krefetz, p. 45&lt;/ref&gt; Krefetz gives, as illustrations, many slurs and proverbs (in several different languages) which suggest that Jews are stingy, or greedy, or miserly, or aggressive bargainers.&lt;ref&gt;Krefetz, pp. 6–7&lt;/ref&gt; During the nineteenth century, Jews were described as &quot;scurrilous, stupid, and tight-fisted&quot;, but after the [[Jewish Emancipation]] and the rise of Jews to the middle- or upper-class in Europe were portrayed as &quot;clever, devious, and manipulative financiers out to dominate [world finances]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Krefetz, p. 47&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Leon Poliakov]] asserts that economic antisemitism is not a distinct form of antisemitism, but merely a manifestation of theologic antisemitism (because, without the theological causes of the economic antisemitism, there would be no economic antisemitism). In opposition to this view, Derek Penslar contends that in the modern era, the economic antisemitism is &quot;distinct and nearly constant&quot; but theological antisemitism is &quot;often subdued&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Penslar, p. 12&lt;/ref&gt;

===Racial antisemitism===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-267-0111-36, Russland, russische Kriegsgefangene (Juden).jpg|thumb|Soviet prisoner of war, August 1941. At least 50,000 Jewish soldiers were shot after selection.]]
[[Racial antisemitism]] is prejudice against [[Jew]]s as a racial/ethnic group, rather than [[Judaism]] as a religion.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=1603&amp;letter=A&amp;search=Anti-semitism &quot;Anti-Semitism&quot;], [[Jewish Encyclopedia]].&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Racial antisemitism]] is the idea that the Jews are a distinct and inferior race compared to their host nations. In the late 19th century and early 20th century, it gained mainstream acceptance as part of the [[eugenics]] movement, which categorized non-&quot;Europeans&quot; as inferior. It more specifically claimed that the &quot;Nordic&quot; Europeans were superior. Racial antisemites saw the Jews as part of a Semitic race and emphasized their &quot;alien&quot; extra-European origins and culture. They saw Jews as beyond redemption even if they converted to the majority religion. Anthropologists discussed whether the Jews possessed any Arabic-[[Armenoid race|Armenoid]], African-[[Nubian people|Nubian]] or Asian-[[Turkic peoples|Turkic]] ancestries.

Racial antisemitism replaced the hatred of Judaism with the hatred of Jews as a group. In the context of the [[Industrial Revolution]], following the [[Jewish Emancipation|emancipation of the Jews]], Jews rapidly urbanized and experienced a period of greater social mobility. With the decreasing role of religion in public life tempering religious antisemitism, a combination of growing [[nationalism]], the rise of [[eugenics]], and resentment at the socio-economic success of the Jews led to the newer, and more virulent, racist antisemitism.

According to William Nichols, religious antisemitism may be distinguished from modern antisemitism based on [[Race (classification of human beings)|racial]] or [[ethnicity|ethnic]] grounds. &quot;The dividing line was the possibility of effective conversion . . . a Jew ceased to be a Jew upon baptism.&quot; However, with racial antisemitism, &quot;Now the assimilated Jew was still a Jew, even after baptism ... . From the [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]] onward, it is no longer possible to draw clear lines of distinction between religious and racial forms of hostility towards Jews... Once Jews have been emancipated and secular thinking makes its appearance, without leaving behind the old Christian hostility towards Jews, the new term antisemitism becomes almost unavoidable, even before explicitly racist doctrines appear.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Nichols, William: ''Christian Antisemitism, A History of Hate'' (1993) p. 314.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the early 19th century, a number of laws enabling [[Jewish emancipation|emancipation of the Jews]] were enacted in Western European countries.&lt;ref&gt;Paul Webster (2001)''Petain's Crime''. London, Pan Books: 13, 15&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dan Cohn-Sherbok (2006) ''The Paradox of Anti-Semitism''. Continuum: 44–46&lt;/ref&gt; The old laws restricting them to [[ghetto]]s, as well as the many laws that limited their property rights, rights of worship and occupation, were rescinded. Despite this, traditional discrimination and hostility to Jews on religious grounds persisted and was supplemented by [[racial antisemitism]], encouraged by the work of racial theorists such as [[Joseph Arthur de Gobineau]] and particularly his ''Essay on the Inequality of the Human Race'' of 1853–5.[[Nationalist]] agendas based on [[ethnicity]], known as [[ethnonationalism]], usually excluded the Jews from the national community as an alien race.&lt;ref&gt;Steven Beller (2007)''Antisemitism: A Very Short Introduction'': 64&lt;/ref&gt; Allied to this were theories of [[Social Darwinism]], which stressed a putative conflict between higher and lower races of human beings. Such theories, usually posited by white Europeans, advocated the superiority of white [[Aryan]]s to [[Semitic]] Jews.&lt;ref&gt;Steven Beller (2007) ''Antisemitism: A Very Short Introduction'': pp. 57–9&lt;/ref&gt;

===Political antisemitism===
{{Expand section|date=June 2011}}
William Brustein defines [[political antisemitism]] as hostility toward Jews based on the belief that Jews seek national and/or world power.&quot; Yisrael Gutman characterizes political antisemitism as tending to &quot;lay responsibility on the Jews for defeats and political economic crises&quot; while seeking to &quot;exploit opposition and resistance to Jewish influence as elements in political party platforms.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Genocide, critical issues of the Holocaust: a companion to the film, Genocide |publisher=Behrman House, Inc |year=1983 |page=100 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=DcdiVs9lwvcC&amp;pg=PA100|isbn=978-0-940646-04-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Viktor Karády, political antisemitism became widespread after the legal [[Jewish emancipation|emancipation of the Jews]] and sought to reverse some of the consequences of that emancipation.
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Jews of Europe in the modern era: a socio-historical outline |first=Viktor |last=Karády |publisher=Central European University Press |year=2004 |page=348 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=4hGg9rMQpEEC&amp;pg=PA351|isbn=978-963-9241-52-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Apocalyptic antisemitism===
{{Expand section|date=July 2011}}

[[Adolf Hitler]]'s millennial and messianic vision which culminated in the [[Holocaust]] is sometimes referred to as an &quot;apocalyptic antisemitism&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Charles B. |last1=Strozier |first2=David M. |last2=Terman |first3=James William |last3=Jones |first4=Katharine |last4=Boyd |publisher=Oxford University Press US |year=2010 |page=168 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=mWqLrJpSA4oC&amp;pg=PA168 |isbn=978-0-19-537965-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The color of words: an encyclopaedic dictionary of ethnic bias in the United States |first=Philip |last=Herbst |publisher=Intercultural Press |year=1997 |page=13 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=UiZQH5gHuggC&amp;pg=PA13|isbn=978-1-877864-97-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Conspiracy theories===
&lt;!-- refs need sorting out --&gt;
[[Holocaust denial]] and [[Jewish conspiracy]] theories are also considered a form of antisemitism.&lt;ref name=&quot;hoax&quot;&gt;Mathis, Andrew E. [http://www.holocaust-history.org/denial/abc-clio/ Holocaust Denial, a Definition], [[The Holocaust History Project]], 2 July 2004. Retrieved 16 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Michael Shermer &amp; Alex Grobman. ''Denying History: : who Says the Holocaust Never Happened and why Do They Say It?'', University of California Press, 2000, ISBN 0-520-23469-3, p. 106.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tau.ac.il/Anti-Semitism/asw2000-1/usa.htm Antisemitism and Racism Country Reports: United States], [[Stephen Roth Institute]], 2000. Retrieved 17 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Deborah Lipstadt]]. ''Denying the Holocaust – The Growing Assault on Truth and Memory'', Penguin, 1993, ISBN 0-452-27274-2, p. 27.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;adl.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.adl.org/holocaust/theory.asp Introduction: Denial as Anti-Semitism], &quot;Holocaust Denial: An Online Guide to Exposing and Combating Anti-Semitic Propaganda&quot;, [[Anti-Defamation League]], 2001. Retrieved 12 June 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;adl.org&quot;/&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;Lawrence N. Powell, ''Troubled Memory: Anne Levy, the Holocaust, and David Duke's Louisiana'', University of North Carolina Press, 2000, ISBN 0-8078-5374-7, p. 445.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;antisemitic&quot;&gt;[http://fra.europa.eu/fraWebsite/material/pub/AS/AS-WorkingDefinition-draft.pdf ''Working Definition of Antisemitism'']|33.8&amp;nbsp;KB, [[European Fundamental Rights Agency]]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Zoological conspiracy theories]] have been propagated by the Arab media and Arabic language websites, alleging a &quot;Zionist plot&quot; behind the use of animals to attack civilians or to conduct espionage.

===New antisemitism===
{{Main|New antisemitism}}
Starting in the 1990s, some scholars have advanced the concept of [[New antisemitism]], coming simultaneously from the [[Left-wing politics|left]], the [[Right-wing politics|right]], and [[Islamism|radical Islam]], which tends to focus on opposition to the creation of a Jewish homeland in the [[State of Israel]],&lt;ref name=&quot;New-AS-List&quot;&gt;
*[[Phyllis Chesler|Chesler, Phyllis]]. ''The New Antisemitism: The Current Crisis and What We Must Do About It'', Jossey-Bass, 2003, pp. 158–159, 181
*[[Warren Kinsella|Kinsella, Warren]]. [http://warrenkinsella.com/oldsite/old/words_extremism_nas.htm The New antisemitism], accessed 5 March 2006
*[http://observer.guardian.co.uk/uk_news/story/0,6903,1278580,00.html &quot;Jews predict record level of hate attacks: Militant Islamic media accused of stirring up new wave of antisemitism&quot;], ''[[The Guardian]]'', 8 August 2004.
*Endelman, Todd M. [http://books.google.com/books?id=Lmym8zUBCKcC&amp;pg=PA65 &quot;Antisemitism in Western Europe Today&quot;] in ''Contemporary Antisemitism: Canada and the World''. University of Toronto Press, 2005, pp. 65–79.
*[[David Matas|Matas, David]]. [http://books.google.com/books?id=DYR7SqcMe9gC&amp;pg=PA30 ''Aftershock: Anti-Zionism and Antisemitism''], Dundurn Press, 2005, pp. 30–31.
*Wistrich, Robert S. &quot;From Ambivalence to Betrayal: The Left, the Jews, and Israel (Studies in Antisemitism)&quot;, University of Nebraska Press, 2012
&lt;/ref&gt; and argue that the language of [[anti-Zionism]] and [[criticism of Israel]] are used to attack the Jews more broadly. In this view, the proponents of the new concept believe that [[criticism of Israel|criticisms of Israel]] and [[Zionism]] are often disproportionate in degree and unique in kind, and attribute this to antisemitism.&lt;ref&gt;
Sources for the following are:
*[[Yehuda Bauer|Bauer, Yehuda]]. [http://web.archive.org/web/20030705131522/http://humanities.ucsc.edu/JewishStudies/docs/YBauerLecture.pdf &quot;Problems of Contemporary Anti-Semitism&quot;], 2003, Retrieved 22 April 2006.
*[[Phyllis Chesler|Chesler, Phyllis]]. ''The New Anti-Semitism: The Current Crisis and What We Must Do About It'', Jossey-Bass, 2003, pp. 158–159, 181.
*Doward, Jamie. [http://observer.guardian.co.uk/uk_news/story/0,6903,1278580,00.html Jews predict record level of hate attacks: Militant Islamic media accused of stirring up new wave of anti-semitism], ''[[The Guardian]]'', 8 August 2004.
*[[Warren Kinsella|Kinsella, Warren]]. [http://www.warrenkinsella.com/words_extremism_nas.htm The New anti-Semitism], accessed 5 March 2006.
*[[Jonathan Sacks|Sacks, Jonathan]]. [http://israel.jcca.org/articles.htm?y=620051118152416 &quot;The New Antisemitism&quot;], Ha'aretz, 6 September 2002, Retrieved 10 January 2007.
*Strauss, Mark. [http://yaleglobal.yale.edu/display.article?id=2791 &quot;Antiglobalism's Jewish Problem&quot;] in Rosenbaum, Ron (ed). ''Those who forget the past: The Question of Anti-Semitism'', Random House 2004, p. 272.&lt;/ref&gt; It is asserted that the new antisemitism deploys traditional antisemitic motifs, including older motifs such as the [[blood libel]].&lt;ref name=&quot;New-AS-List&quot;/&gt;

Critics of the concept view it as trivializing the meaning of antisemitism, and as exploiting antisemitism in order to silence debate and deflect attention from legitimate [[criticism of Israel|criticism of the State of Israel]], and, by associating anti-Zionism with antisemitism, misused to taint anyone opposed to Israeli actions and policies.&lt;ref&gt;[[Brian Klug|Klug, Brian]]. [http://www.thenation.com/doc.mhtml?i=20040202&amp;s=klug The Myth of the New Anti-Semitism]. ''[[The Nation (U.S. periodical)|The Nation]]'', posted 15 January 2004 (2 February 2004 issue), accessed 9 January 2006; and [[Michael Lerner (rabbi)|Lerner, Michael]]. [http://baltimorechronicle.com/2007/020207LERNER.shtml There Is No New Anti-Semitism], posted 5 February 2007. Retrieved 6 February 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{{Main|History of antisemitism}}

Many authors see the roots of economic antisemitism in both pagan antiquity and early Christianity. Jerome Chanes identifies six stages in the historical development of antisemitism:
#Pre-Christian anti-Judaism in ancient Greece and Rome which was primarily ethnic in nature
#Christian antisemitism in antiquity and the Middle Ages which was religious in nature and has extended into modern times
#Traditional Muslim antisemitism which was – at least in its classical form – nuanced in that Jews were a protected class
#Political, social and economic antisemitism of Enlightenment and post-Enlightenment Europe which laid the groundwork for racial antisemitism
#Racial antisemitism that arose in the 19th century and culminated in Nazism
#Contemporary antisemitism which has been labeled by some as the [[New Antisemitism]]

Chanes suggests that these six stages could be merged into three categories: &quot;ancient antisemitism, which was primarily ethnic in nature; [[Christian antisemitism]], which was religious; and the racial antisemitism of the nineteenth and twentieth centuries.&quot;&lt;ref name=Chanes5&gt;{{cite book |title=Antisemitism: a reference handbook |first=Jerome A. |last=Chanes|publisher=ABC-CLIO |year=2004 |pages=5–6 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=ju7U83nRDt8C&amp;pg=PA5 |isbn=978-1-57607-209-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ancient world===

The first clear examples of anti-Jewish sentiment can be traced back to [[Alexandria]] in the 3rd century BCE.&lt;ref name=Flannery&gt;Flannery, Edward H. ''The Anguish of the Jews: Twenty-Three Centuries of Antisemitism''. Paulist Press, first published in 1985; this edition 2004, pp. 11–2. ISBN 0-8091-2702-4. [[Edward Flannery]]&lt;/ref&gt; Alexandria was home to the largest Jewish community in the world and the [[Septuagint]], a Greek translation of the [[Hebrew Bible]], was produced there. [[Manetho]], an Egyptian priest and historian of that time, wrote scathingly of the Jews and his themes are repeated in the works of [[Chaeremon]], [[Lysimachus]], [[Poseidonius]], [[Apollonius Molon]], and in [[Apion]] and [[Tacitus]].&lt;ref name=Flannery /&gt; [[Agatharchides of Cnidus]] ridiculed the practices of the Jews and the &quot;absurdity of [[Torah|their Law]]&quot;, making a mocking reference to how [[Ptolemy Lagus]] was able to invade [[Jerusalem]] in 320 BCE because its inhabitants were observing the ''[[Shabbat]]''.&lt;ref name=Flannery /&gt; One of the earliest anti-Jewish [[edict]]s, promulgated by [[Antiochus IV Epiphanes]] in about 170–167 BCE, sparked a revolt of the [[Maccabees]] in [[Judea]].

In view of Manetho's anti-Jewish writings, antisemitism may have originated in Egypt and been spread by &quot;the [[Greeks|Greek]] retelling of [[Ancient Egypt]]ian prejudices&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schäfer&quot;&gt;Schäfer, Peter. ''Judeophobia'', Harvard University Press, 1997, p. 208.[[Peter Schaefer (author)|Peter Schäfer]]&lt;/ref&gt; The ancient Jewish philosopher [[Philo of Alexandria]] describes an attack on Jews in Alexandria in 38 CE in which thousands of Jews died.&lt;ref name=Barclay&gt;Barclay, John M G, 1999. ''Jews in the Mediterranean Diaspora: From Alexander to Trajan (323 BCE–117 CE)'', University of California. John M. G. Barclay of the [[Durham University|University of Durham]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Philo of Alexandria, [http://www.earlychristianwritings.com/yonge/book36.html ''Flaccus'']&lt;/ref&gt; The violence in Alexandria may have been caused by the Jews being portrayed as [[misanthropy|misanthropes]].&lt;ref name=vanderhorst&gt;Van Der Horst, Pieter Willem, 2003. ''Philo's Flaccus: the First Pogrom'', Philo of Alexandria Commentary Series, Brill. [[Pieter Willem van der Horst]]&lt;/ref&gt; Tcherikover argues that the reason for hatred of Jews in the Hellenistic period was their separateness in the Greek cities, the ''[[polis|poleis]]''.&lt;ref name=tcherikover&gt;Tcherikover, Victor, ''Hellenistic Civilization and the Jews'', New York: Atheneum, 1975&lt;/ref&gt; Bohak has argued, however, that early animosity against the Jews cannot be regarded as being anti-Judaic or antisemitic unless it arose from attitudes that were held against the Jews alone, and that many Greeks showed animosity toward any group they regarded as barbarians.&lt;ref name=Bohak&gt;Bohak, Gideon. &quot;The Ibis and the Jewish Question: Ancient 'Antisemitism' in Historical Context&quot; in Menachem Mor et al., ''Jews and Gentiles in the Holy Land in the Days of the Second Temple, the Mishna and the Talmud'', Yad Ben-Zvi Press, 2003, pp. 27–43 ISBN 9652172057.&lt;/ref&gt;
Statements exhibiting prejudice against Jews and their religion can be found in the works of many [[pagan]] [[ancient Greece|Greek]] and [[ancient Rome|Roman]] writers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|jstor=3265911|author=Daniels J.L.|title=Anti-Semitism in the Hellenistic-Roman Period|journal=Journal of Biblical Literature|volume=98 |year=1979|pages=45–65|doi=10.2307/3265911}}&lt;/ref&gt; Edward Flannery writes that it was the Jews' refusal to accept Greek religious and social standards that marked them out. Hecataetus of Abdera, a Greek historian of the early third century BCE, wrote that Moses &quot;in remembrance of the exile of his people, instituted for them a misanthropic and inhospitable way of life.&quot; [[Manetho]], an Egyptian historian, wrote that the Jews were expelled Egyptian [[Leprosy|lepers]] who had been taught by [[Moses]] &quot;not to adore the gods.&quot; Edward Flannery describes antisemitism in ancient times as essentially &quot;cultural, taking the shape of a national xenophobia played out in political settings.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The anguish of the Jews: twenty-three centuries of antisemitism |first=Edward H. |last=Flannery |publisher=Paulist Press |year=1985 |page=25 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=J40gNC7cxfYC&amp;pg=PA25 |isbn=978-0-8091-4324-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are examples of [[Hellenistic]] rulers desecrating the [[Temple in Jerusalem|Temple]] and banning Jewish religious practices, such as [[circumcision]], Shabbat observance, study of Jewish religious books, etc. Examples may also be found in anti-Jewish riots in [[Alexandria]] in the 3rd century BCE. [[Philo of Alexandria]] described an attack on Jews in Alexandria in 38 CE in which thousands of Jews died.

The Jewish diaspora on the [[Nile River|Nile]] island [[Elephantine]], which was founded by mercenaries, experienced the destruction of its temple in 410 BCE.&lt;ref&gt;Colpe, Carsten (Berlin). &quot;Anti-Semitism.&quot; Brill's New Pauly. Antiquity volumes edited by: Hubert Cancik and Helmuth Schneider. Brill, 2008. Brill Online. 28 April 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

Relationships between the Jewish people and the occupying [[Roman Empire]] were at times antagonistic and resulted in [[Jewish-Roman wars|several rebellions]]. According to [[Suetonius]], the emperor [[Tiberius]] expelled from Rome Jews who had gone to live there. The 18th century English historian [[Edward Gibbon]] identified a more tolerant period in Roman-Jewish relations beginning in about 160 CE {{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}. However, when Christianity became the state religion of the Roman Empire, the state's attitude towards the Jews [[History of antisemitism#Late Roman Empire|gradually worsened]].

[[James Carroll (novelist)|James Carroll]] asserted: &quot;Jews accounted for 10% of the total population of the [[Roman Empire]]. By that ratio, if other factors such as [[pogrom]]s and [[forced conversion|conversion]]s had not intervened, there would be 200 million Jews in the world today, instead of something like 13 million.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Carroll, James. ''[[Constantine's Sword]]'' (Houghton Mifflin, 2001) ISBN 0-395-77927-8 p. 26&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.townhall.com/columnists/DennisPrager/2006/02/21/explaining_jews,_part_iii_a_very_insecure_people Explaining Jews, Part III: A very insecure people::By Dennis Prager]. Townhall.com (2006-02-21). Retrieved on 2 June 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Persecutions in the Middle Ages===
{{Main|Jews in the Middle Ages}}{{Jews and Judaism sidebar|history}}
From the 9th century CE, the [[Islamic Golden Age|medieval Islamic world]] classified Jews (and Christians) as ''[[dhimmi]]'', and allowed them to practice their religion more freely than they could do in [[Middle Ages|medieval Christian Europe]]. Under [[Al-Andalus|Islamic rule]], there was a [[Golden age of Jewish culture in Spain]] that lasted until at least the 11th century,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|first=María Rosa|last=Menocal|author-link=María Rosa Menocal|title=The Ornament of the World: How Muslims, Jews and Christians Created a Culture of Tolerance in Medieval Spain|date=April 2003|publisher=Back Bay Books|isbn=0-316-16871-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; when several Muslim [[pogrom]]s against Jews took place in the [[Iberian Peninsula]]; those that occurred in [[Córdoba, Spain|Córdoba]] in 1011 and in [[1066 Granada massacre|Granada in 1066]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Schweitzer267-268&quot;&gt;Schweitzer, Perry (2002) pp. 267–268.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=412&amp;letter=G&amp;search=Granada Granada] by Richard Gottheil, Meyer Kayserling, ''[[Jewish Encyclopedia]]''. 1906 ed.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Harzig, Hoerder &amp; Shubert, 2003, p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt; Several decrees ordering the destruction of [[synagogue]]s were also enacted in [[Egypt]], [[Syria]], [[Iraq]] and [[Yemen]] from the 11th century. Jews were also forced to convert to Islam or face death in some parts of Yemen, [[Morocco]] and [[Baghdad]] several times between the 12th and 18th centuries.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/anti-semitism/Jews_in_Arab_lands_(gen).html The Treatment of Jews in Arab/Islamic Countries]. Jewishvirtuallibrary.org (1947-02-19). Retrieved on 2 June 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Almohad Caliphate|Almohads]], who had taken control of the [[Almoravid dynasty|Almoravids]]' [[Maghreb|Maghribi]] and Andalusian territories by 1147,&lt;ref name=islamicworldeb&gt;Islamic world. (2007). In Encyclopædia Britannica. Retrieved 2 September 2007, from [http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-26925 Encyclopædia Britannica Online].&lt;/ref&gt; were far more fundamentalist in outlook, and they treated the ''dhimmis'' harshly. Faced with the choice of either death or conversion, many Jews and Christians emigrated.&lt;ref name=frank&gt;Frank and Leaman, 2003, p. 137-138.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.myjewishlearning.com/history_community/Medieval/IntergroupTO/JewishMuslim/Almohads.htm The Almohads]. Myjewishlearning.com. Retrieved on 2 June 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20080117215705/http://www.theforgottenrefugees.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=66&amp;Itemid=39 Historical Timeline]. The Forgotten Refugees&lt;/ref&gt; Some, such as the family of [[Maimonides]], fled east to more tolerant Muslim lands,&lt;ref name=frank/&gt; while some others went northward to settle in the growing Christian kingdoms.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/Judaism/Sephardim.html Sephardim]. Jewishvirtuallibrary.org. Retrieved on 2 June 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[Middle Ages]] in Europe there was persecution against Jews in many places, with [[blood libel]]s, expulsions, [[forced conversion]]s and [[massacre]]s. A main justification of prejudice against Jews in Europe was religious. The persecution hit its first peak during the [[Crusades]]. In the [[First Crusade]] (1096) flourishing communities on the [[Rhine]] and the [[Danube]] [[German Crusade, 1096|were destroyed]]. In the [[Second Crusade]] (1147) the Jews in Germany were subject to several massacres. The Jews were also subjected to attacks by the [[Shepherds' Crusade]]s of 1251 and 1320. The Crusades were followed by expulsions, including, in 1290, the banishing of all [[English people|English]] Jews; in 1396, the expulsion of 100,000 Jews in France; and in 1421, the expulsion of thousands from Austria. Many of the expelled Jews fled to Poland.&lt;ref&gt;{{Wayback |df=yes|url=http://www.holocaustcenterpgh.net/2-3.html |date=20031211173212 |title=Why the Jews? – Black Death}}&lt;/ref&gt; In medieval and Renaissance Europe, a major contributor to the deepening of antisemitic sentiment and legal action among the Christian populations was the popular preaching of the zealous reform religious orders, the Franciscans (especially Bernardino of Feltre) and Dominicans (especially Vincent Ferrer), who combed Europe and promoted antisemitism through their often fiery, emotional appeals.&lt;ref&gt;Franco Mormando, ''The Preacher's Demons: Bernardino of Siena and the Social Underworld of Early Renaissance Italy'', Chicago, University of Chicago Press, 1999, Ch. 2.&lt;/ref&gt;

As the [[Black Death]] epidemics devastated Europe in the mid-14th century, annihilating more than half of the population, Jews were used as [[scapegoating#Psychology and sociology|scapegoats]]. Rumors spread that they caused the disease by deliberately poisoning wells. Hundreds of Jewish communities were destroyed. Although [[Pope Clement VI]] tried to protect them by issuing the 6 July 1348, [[papal bull]] and an additional bull in 1348, several months later, 900 Jews were burned alive in [[Strasbourg]], where the plague had not yet affected the city.&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;&gt;See Stéphane Barry and Norbert Gualde, ''La plus grande épidémie de l'histoire'' (&quot;The greatest epidemics in history&quot;), in ''[[L'Histoire]]'' magazine, n°310, June 2006, p. 47 {{fr icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Seventeenth century===
During the mid-to-late 17th century the [[Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth]] was devastated by several conflicts, in which the Commonwealth lost over a third of its population (over 3 million people), and Jewish losses were counted in hundreds of thousands. First, the [[Khmelnytsky Uprising]] when [[Bohdan Khmelnytsky]]'s [[Cossacks]] massacred tens of thousands of [[History of Jews in Poland|Jews]] in the eastern and southern areas he controlled (today's [[Ukraine]]). The precise number of dead may never be known, but the decrease of the Jewish population during that period is estimated at 100,000 to 200,000, which also includes emigration, deaths from diseases and [[Slavery (Ottoman Empire)|captivity in the Ottoman Empire]], called ''jasyr''.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Bogdan Chmelnitzki leads Cossack uprising against Polish rule; 100,000 Jews are killed and hundreds of Jewish communities are destroyed.&quot; [http://www.cbsnews.com/htdocs/religion/judaism/timeline.html Judaism Timeline 1618–1770], ''[[CBS News]]''. Retrieved 13 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;... as many as 100,000 Jews were murdered throughout the Ukraine by Bogdan Chmielnicki's Cossack soldiers on the rampage.&quot; [[Martin Gilbert]]. ''Holocaust Journey: Traveling in Search of the Past'', Columbia University Press, 1999, ISBN 0-231-10965-2, p. 219.&lt;/ref&gt;

European immigrants to the United States brought antisemitism to the country as early as the 17th century. [[Peter Stuyvesant]], the Dutch governor of [[New Amsterdam]], implemented plans to prevent Jews from settling in the city. During the Colonial Era, the American government limited the political and economic rights of Jews. It was not until the [[Revolutionary War]] that Jews gained legal rights, including the right to vote. However, even at their peak, the restrictions on Jews in the United States were never as stringent as they had been in Europe.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Boyer|first=Ed. by Paul S.|title=The Oxford companion to United States history|year=2006|publisher=Oxford Univ. Press|location=Oxford|isbn=978-0-19-508209-8|page=42}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Enlightenment===
In 1744, [[Frederick II of Prussia]] limited the number of Jews allowed to live in [[Breslau]] to only ten so-called &quot;protected&quot; Jewish families and encouraged a similar practice in other [[Prussia]]n cities. In 1750 he issued the ''Revidiertes General Privilegium und Reglement vor die Judenschaft'': the &quot;protected&quot; Jews had an alternative to &quot;either abstain from marriage or leave [[Berlin]]&quot; (quoting [[Simon Dubnow]]). In the same year, Archduchess of Austria [[Maria Theresa of Austria|Maria Theresa]] ordered Jews out of [[Bohemia]] but soon reversed her position, on the condition that Jews pay for their readmission every ten years. This [[extortion]] was known as ''malke-geld'' (queen's money). In 1752 she introduced the law limiting each Jewish family to one son. In 1782, [[Joseph II, Holy Roman Emperor|Joseph II]] abolished most of these persecution practices in his ''[[Toleranzpatent]]'', on the condition that [[Yiddish language|Yiddish]] and [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] were eliminated from public records and that judicial autonomy was annulled. [[Moses Mendelssohn]] wrote that &quot;Such a tolerance... is even more dangerous play in tolerance than open persecution.&quot;

In 1772, the empress of Russia [[Catherine the Great|Catherine II]] forced the Jews of the [[Pale of Settlement]] to stay in their [[shtetls]] and forbade them from returning to the towns that they occupied before the [[partition of Poland]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/vjw/Poland.html The Virtual Jewish History Tour By Rebecca Weiner]. Jewishvirtuallibrary.org. Retrieved on 2 June 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Islamic antisemitism in the nineteenth century===
Historian [[Martin Gilbert]] writes that it was in the 19th century that the position of Jews worsened in Muslim countries. [[Benny Morris]] writes that one symbol of Jewish degradation was the phenomenon of stone-throwing at Jews by Muslim children. Morris quotes a 19th century traveler: &quot;I have seen a little fellow of six years old, with a troop of fat toddlers of only three and four, teaching [them] to throw stones at a Jew, and one little urchin would, with the greatest coolness, waddle up to the man and literally spit upon his Jewish [[gaberdine]]. To all this the Jew is obliged to submit; it would be more than his life was worth to offer to strike a Mahommedan.&quot;&lt;ref name=Morris10&gt;[[Benny Morris|Morris, Benny]]. ''Righteous Victims: A History of the Zionist-Arab Conflict, 1881–2001''. Vintage Books, 2001, pp. 10–11.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Secular or racial antisemitism===

In 1850 the German composer [[Richard Wagner]] published ''[[Das Judenthum in der Musik]]'' (&quot;Jewishness in Music&quot;) under a [[pseudonym]] in the ''[[Neue Zeitschrift für Musik]]''. The essay began as an attack on Jewish composers, particularly Wagner's contemporaries (and rivals) [[Felix Mendelssohn]] and [[Giacomo Meyerbeer]], but expanded to accuse Jews of being a harmful and alien element in [[Culture of Germany|German culture]]. Antisemitism can also be found in many of the [[Grimms' Fairy Tales]] by [[Jacob Grimm|Jacob]] and [[Wilhelm Grimm]], published from 1812 to 1857. It is mainly characterized by Jews being the [[villain]] of a story, such as in &quot;The Good Bargain (Der gute Handel)&quot; and &quot;The Jew Among Thorns (Der Jude im Dorn).&quot;

The [[Dreyfus Affair]] was an infamous antisemitic event of the late 19th century and early 20th century. [[Alfred Dreyfus]], a Jewish artillery captain in the French army, was accused in 1894 of passing secrets to the Germans. As a result of these charges, Dreyfus was convicted and sentenced to [[life imprisonment]] on [[Devil's Island]]. The actual spy, Marie Charles Esterhazy, was acquitted. The event caused great uproar among the French, with the public choosing sides regarding whether Dreyfus was actually guilty or not. [[Émile Zola]] accused the army of polluting the French justice system. However, general consensus held that Dreyfus was guilty: 80% of the press in France condemned him. This attitude among the majority of the French population reveals the underlying antisemitism of the time period.&lt;ref&gt;Rapport, Michael. (2005) Nineteenth Century Europe. New York: Palgrave MacMillan ISBN 0333652460.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Adolf Stoecker]] (1835–1909), the [[Lutheran]] court chaplain to [[Kaiser Wilhelm I]], founded in 1878 an antisemitic, [[Liberalism|antiliberal]] political party called The [[Christian Social Party (Germany)]]. However, this party did not attract as many votes as the Nazi party, which flourished in part because of [[The Great Depression]], which hit Germany especially hard during the early 1930s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Harold M. Green|year=2003|title=Adolf Stoecker:Portrait of a Demagogue|journal=Politics and Policy|volume=31|doi=10.1111/j.1747-1346.2003.tb00889.x|issue=1|pages=106–129}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=D. A. Jeremy Telman|year=1995|title=Adolf Stoecker: Anti-Semite with a Christian Mission|jstor=20101235|journal=Jewish History|volume=9|issue=2|pages=93–112|doi=10.1007/BF01668991}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some scholars view [[Karl Marx|Karl Marx's]] essay ''[[On The Jewish Question]]'' as antisemitic, and he often used antisemitic epithets in his published and private writings.&lt;ref name=&quot;Flannery2004&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=The Anguish of the Jews: Twenty-Three Centuries of Antisemitism |last=Flannery |first=Edward H. |authorlink=Edward H. Flannery |year=2004 |publisher=Paulist Press |location=Mahwah, NY |isbn=0-8091-2702-4 |page=168}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jacobs2005&quot;&gt;{{cite book |chapter=Marx, Karl (1818–1883) |title=Antisemitism: A Historical Encyclopedia of Prejudice and Persecution |last=Jacobs |first=Jack |editor=Levy, Richard S. |year=2005 |publisher=ABC-CLIO |location=Santa Barbara, CA |isbn=1-85109-439-3 |pages=446–447 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewis1999&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Semites and Anti-Semites: An Inquiry into Conflict and Prejudice |last=Lewis |first=Bernard |year=1999 |publisher=W. W. Norton &amp; Company |location=New York |isbn=0-393-31839-7 |page=112}}&lt;/ref&gt; Marx's equation of Judaism with capitalism, together with his pronouncements on Jews, strongly influenced socialist movements and shaped their attitudes and policies toward the Jews. Marx's ''On the Jewish Question'' influenced [[Nazism|National Socialist]], as well as Soviet and Arab antisemites.&lt;ref name=&quot;Perry2005&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Antisemitism: Myth and Hate from Antiquity to the Present |last=Perry |first=Marvin |coauthors=Schweitzer, Frederick M. |year=2005 |publisher=Palgrave |location=New York |isbn=0-312-16561-7 |pages=154–157}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stav2003&quot;&gt;{{cite book |chapter=Israeli Anti-Semitism |title=Israel and the Post-Zionists: A Nation at Risk |last=Stav |first=Arieh |editor=Sharan, Shlomo |year=2003 |publisher=Sussex Academic Press |location=Brighton |isbn=1-903900-52-2 |page=171 |quote=Hitler simply copied Marx's own anti-Semitism. }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Muravchik2003&quot;&gt;According to Joshua Muravchik Marx's aspiration for &quot;the emancipation of society from Judaism&quot; because &quot;the practical Jewish spirit&quot; of &quot;huckstering&quot; had taken over the Christian nations is not that far from the Nazi program's twenty-four point: &quot;combat[ing] the Jewish-materialist spirit within us and without us&quot; in order &quot;that our nation can […] achieve permanent health.&quot; See {{cite book |title=Heaven on Earth: The Rise and Fall of Socialism |last=Muravchik |first=Joshua |authorlink=Joshua Muravchik |year=2003 |publisher=Encounter Books |location=San Francisco |isbn=1-893554-45-7 |page=164}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Albert Lindemann]] and [[Hyam Maccoby]] have suggested that Marx was [[Self-hating Jew|embarrassed by his Jewish background]].&lt;ref&gt;Lindemann, Albert S. ''Modern Anti-Semitism and the Rise of the Jews''. Cambridge University Press, 2000. ISBN 0-521-79538-9, ISBN 978-0-521-79538-8. p. 166.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Antisemitism and Modernity: Innovation and Continuity |last=Maccoby |first=Hyam |year=2006 |publisher=Routledge |location=London |isbn=0-415-31173-X |pages=64–66}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Others argue that Marx consistently supported Prussian Jewish communities' struggles to achieve equal political rights. These scholars argue that &quot;On the Jewish Question&quot; is a critique of Bruno Bauer's arguments that Jews must convert to Christianity before being emancipated, and is more generally a critique of liberal rights discourses and capitalism.&lt;ref&gt;David McLellan: ''Marx before Marxism'' (1970), pp. 141–142&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Y. Peled|title= From theology to sociology: Bruno Bauer and Karl Marx on the question of Jewish emancipation|journal=History of Political Thought|volume =13|issue= 3|year= 1992|pages=463–485|url=http://telaviv.academia.edu/YoavPeled/Papers/228344/From_Theology_to_Sociology_Bruno_Bauer_and_Karl_Marx_on_the_Question_of_Jewish_Emancipation}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
 | last=Brown
 | first=Wendy
 | author-link=Wendy Brown (political scientist)
 | year=1995
 | contribution=Rights and Identity in Late Modernity: Revisiting the 'Jewish Question'
 | editor-last=Sarat
 | editor-first=Austin
 | editor2-last=Kearns
 | editor2-first=Thomas
 | title=Identities, Politics, and Rights
 | publisher=University of Michigan Press
 | pages=85–130}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Robert Fine|url=http://www.engageonline.org.uk/journal/index.php?journal_id=10&amp;article_id=33 |title=Karl Marx and the Radical Critique of Anti-Semitism|journal=Engage| issue=2|date= May 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; David McLellan and [[Francis Wheen]] argue that readers should interpret ''On the Jewish Question'' in the deeper context of Marx's debates with [[Bruno Bauer]], author of ''[[The Jewish Question]]'', about [[Jewish emancipation]] in Germany. According to McLellan, Marx used the word ''Judentum'' colloquially, as meaning ''commerce'', arguing that Germans must be emancipated from the capitalist mode of production not Judaism or Jews in particular.&lt;ref&gt;McLellan 1980, p. 142&lt;/ref&gt;

===Twentieth century===
[[File:Ekaterinoslav1905.jpg|thumb|left|The victims of a 1905 [[pogrom]] in [[Dnipropetrovsk|Yekaterinoslav]]]] 

Between 1900 and 1924, approximately 1.75 million Jews migrated to America, the bulk from Eastern Europe. Before 1900 American Jews had always amounted to less than 1% of America's total population, but by 1930 Jews formed about 3.5%. This increase, combined with the upward social mobility of some Jews, contributed to a resurgence of antisemitism. In the first half of the 20th century, in the USA, Jews were discriminated against in employment, access to residential and resort areas, membership in clubs and organizations, and in tightened quotas on Jewish enrolment and teaching positions in colleges and universities. The lynching of [[Leo Frank]] by a mob of prominent citizens in [[Marietta, Georgia|Marietta]], [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]] in 1915 turned the spotlight on antisemitism in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;
[http://books.google.com/books?id=ju7U83nRDt8C&amp;pg=PA72 Chanes, p.&amp;nbsp;72].&lt;/ref&gt; The case was also used{{by whom|date=November 2011}} to build support for the renewal of the [[Ku Klux Klan]] which had been inactive since 1870.&lt;ref&gt;Levy, Richard S. [http://books.google.com/books?id=Tdn6FFZklkcC&amp;pg=PA243 ''Antisemitism: A Historical Encyclopedia of Prejudice and Persecution'' (Volume 1)], [[ABC-CLIO]], p.&amp;nbsp;72.&lt;/ref&gt;

At the beginning of the 20th century, the [[Menahem Mendel Beilis|Beilis Trial]] in Russia represented incidents of blood-libel in Europe. Christians{{which|date=November 2011}} used allegations of Jews killing Christians as a justification for the killing of Jews.

Antisemitism in America reached its peak during the interwar period. The pioneer automobile manufacturer [[Henry Ford]] propagated antisemitic ideas in his newspaper ''[[The Dearborn Independent]]'' (published by Ford from 1919 to 1927). The radio speeches of [[Father Coughlin]] in the late 1930s attacked [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]]'s [[New Deal]] and promoted the notion of a Jewish financial conspiracy. Some prominent politicians shared such views: [[Louis T. McFadden]], Chairman of the [[United States House Committee on Banking and Currency]], blamed Jews for Roosevelt's decision to abandon the [[gold standard]], and claimed that &quot;in the United States today, the Gentiles have the slips of paper while the Jews have the lawful money&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Arad |first=Gulie Ne'eman |title=America, Its Jews, and the Rise of Nazism |year=2000 |publisher=Indiana University Press |location=Indianapolis |isbn=0-253-33809-3 |page=174}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Einsatzgruppe A.jpg|thumb|left|''[[Einsatzgruppen|Einsatzgruppe A]]'' members shoot Jews on the outskirts of [[Kaunas]], 1941–1942]] 

In the early 1940s the [[aviator]] [[Charles Lindbergh]] and many prominent Americans led The [[America First Committee]] in opposing any involvement in the war against [[Fascism]]. During his July 1936 visit to Germany, Lindbergh wrote letters saying that there was &quot;more intelligent leadership in Germany than is generally recognized&quot;.

The [[German American Bund]] held parades in New York City during the late 1930s, where members wore [[Nazi]] uniforms and raised flags featuring [[swastika]]s alongside American flags. With the start of U.S. involvement in [[World War II]] most of the Bund's members were placed{{by whom|date=November 2011}} in [[internment camp]]s, and some were deported{{by whom|date=November 2011}} at the end of the war.

Sometimes race riots, as in [[Detroit]] in 1943, targeted Jewish businesses for looting and burning.&lt;ref&gt;Capeci Jr., Dominic J. [http://books.google.com/books?id=BBzbA3HwmbkC&amp;pg=PA384 &quot;Black–Jewish Relations in Wartime Detroit&quot;], in Maurianne Adams, John H. Bracey. ''Strangers &amp; neighbors: relations between Blacks &amp; Jews in the United States'', [[University of Massachusetts Press]], 1999, p. 384.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Buchenwald Corpses 60623.jpg|A wagon piled high with corpses outside the crematorium in the newly liberated [[Buchenwald concentration camp]]|thumb]]
&lt;!-- [[File:Selection Birkenau ramp.jpg|thumb|&quot;Selection&quot; on the ''Judenrampe'', [[Auschwitz concentration camp|Auschwitz]], May/June 1944. To be sent to the right meant slave labor; to the left, the [[gas chamber]]s. This image shows the arrival of [[Hungarian people|Hungarian]] Jews from [[Carpathian Ruthenia|Carpatho-Ruthenia]], many of them from the [[Berehove|Berehov]] ghetto. It was taken by Ernst Hofmann or Bernhard Walter of the [[SS]]. Courtesy of [[Yad Vashem]].&lt;ref name=AuschwitzAlbum&gt;[http://www1.yadvashem.org/exhibitions/album_auschwitz/home_auschwitz_album.html &quot;The Auschwitz Album&quot;], [[Yad Vashem]].&lt;/ref&gt; {{FFDC|1=Selection Birkenau ramp.jpg|log=2009 April 6|date=May 2012}}]] --&gt;

In Germany the [[Nazism|National Socialist]] regime of [[Adolf Hitler]], which came to power on 30 January 1933, instituted repressive legislation denying the Jews basic civil rights. It instituted a pogrom on the night of 9–10 November 1938, dubbed ''[[Kristallnacht]]'', in which Jews were killed, their property destroyed and their synagogues torched.&lt;ref&gt;Ian Kershaw (2008) ''Fateful Choices'': 441-44
&lt;/ref&gt; Antisemitic laws, agitation and propaganda were extended to Nazi-occupied Europe in the wake of conquest, often building on local antisemitic traditions. In the east the Third Reich forced Jews into ghettos in [[Warsaw]], [[Krakow]], [[Lvov]], [[Lublin]] and [[Radom]].&lt;ref&gt;Martin Kitchen (2007) ''The Third Reich: A Concise History''. Tempus.&lt;/ref&gt; After the invasion of Russia in 1941 a campaign of mass murder, conducted by the [[Einsatzgruppen]], culminated between 1942 to 1945 in systematic [[genocide]]: [[the Holocaust]].&lt;ref name=&quot;saul1&quot;&gt;Saul Friedlander (2008) The Years of Extermination: Nazi Germany and the Jews. London, Phoenix&lt;/ref&gt; Eleven million Jews were targeted for extermination by the Nazis, and some six million were eventually killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;saul1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wolfgang Benz in Dimension des Volksmords: Die Zahl der Jüdischen Opfer des Nationalsozialismus (Munich: Deutscher Taschebuch Verlag, 1991). Israel Gutman, ''Encyclopedia of the Holocaust,'' Macmillan Reference Books; Reference edition (1 October 1995)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Lucy Dawidowicz|Dawidowicz, Lucy]]. ''The War Against The Jews, 1933–1945''. New York : Holt, Rinehart and Winston, 1975.&lt;/ref&gt;

Antisemitism was commonly used as an instrument for personal conflicts in [[USSR|Soviet Russia]], starting from conflict between [[Joseph Stalin]] and [[Leon Trotsky]] and continuing through numerous conspiracy-theories spread by official propaganda. Antisemitism in the USSR reached new heights after 1948 during the campaign against the [[Rootless cosmopolitan|&quot;rootless cosmopolitan&quot;]] (euphemism for &quot;Jew&quot;) in which numerous Yiddish-language poets, writers, painters and sculptors were killed or arrested.&lt;ref name=&quot;jcws&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|author=Konstantin Azadovskii and Boris Egorov| title=From Anti-Westernism to Anti-Semitism| journal=Journal of Cold War Studies| year=2002| volume=4:1| issue=Winter| pages=66–80| url=http://www.fas.harvard.edu/~hpcws/egorov.htm#REF31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Myth&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=The Myth of the Jewish Race| coauthors=Raphael and Jennifer Patai| year=1989| page=178| publisher=Wayne State University Press| isbn=0-8143-1948-3, 9780814319482}}&lt;/ref&gt; This culminated in the so-called [[Doctors' Plot]] (1952–1953). Similar antisemitic propaganda in Poland resulted in the flight of Polish Jewish survivors from the country.&lt;ref name=&quot;Myth&quot; /&gt;

After the war, the [[Kielce pogrom]] and &quot;[[March 1968 events]]&quot; in communist Poland represented further incidents of antisemitism in Europe. The [[Anti-Jewish violence in Poland, 1944–1946|anti-Jewish violence in postwar Poland]] has a common theme of [[blood libel|blood-libel]] rumours.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | url = http://books.google.com/?id=4Iiw0KB31rgC&amp;pg=PA233&amp;dq=Cracow+Kupa+synagogue+ritual+murder | title = Contested memories: Poles and Jews during the Holocaust and its aftermath | isbn = 978-0-8135-3158-8 | author1 = Zimmerman | first1 = Joshua D | year = 2003}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | url = http://books.google.com/?id=xZ5Ceq6l0M0C&amp;pg=PA74&amp;dq=blood+libel+kielce | title = World without civilization: Mass murder and the Holocaust, history and analysis | isbn = 978-0-7618-2963-8 | author1 = Spector | first1 = Robert Melvin | year = 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1965 [[Pope Paul VI]] disbanded the cult of [[Simon of Trent]], and the shrine erected to him was dismantled{{by whom|date=November 2011}}. He was removed from the [[General Roman Calendar|Roman Catholic calendar of saints]], and his future veneration was forbidden{{by whom|date=November 2011}}, though a handful of extremists{{citation needed|date=November 2011}} still promote the Simon of Trent narrative as fact.

==Current situation==
A March 2008 report by the [[United States Department of State|U.S. State Department]] found that there was an increase in antisemitism across the world, and that both old and new expressions of antisemitism persist.&lt;ref&gt;[http://edition.cnn.com/2008/US/03/14/anti-semitism/index.html &quot;Report: Anti-Semitism on the rise globally&quot;], [[CNN]], 14 March 2008, Retrieved 24 November 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Causes===

{{Expand section|date=July 2011}}
Dean Phillip Bell documents and enumerates a number of categories of causes for anti-Jewish sentiment and behavior. Socio-psychological explanations focus on scapegoating via projection of guilt and displaced aggression. Ethnic explanations associate marginalization of Jews with perceived ethnic and cultural differences.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Jews in the early modern world |first=Dean Phillip |last=Bell |publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield |year=2008 |page=212 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=5rJ85OyVWV0C&amp;pg=PA212 |isbn=978-0-7425-4518-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===
{{Main|Antisemitism in the United States}}
{{see also|History of antisemitism in the United States}}

A 2007 survey by the [[Anti-Defamation League]] (ADL) concluded that 15% of Americans hold antisemitic views, which was in-line with the average of the previous ten years, but a decline from the 29% of the early sixties. The survey concluded that education was a strong predictor, “with most educated Americans being remarkably free of prejudicial views.” The belief that Jews have too much power was considered a common antisemitic view by the ADL. Other views indicating antisemitism, according to the survey, include the view that Jews are more loyal to Israel than America, and that they are responsible for the death of Christ. The survey found that antisemitic Americans are likely to be intolerant generally, e.g. regarding immigration and free-speech. The 2007 survey also found that 29% of foreign-born [[Hispanic and Latino Americans|Hispanics]] and 32% of [[African American|African-Americans]] hold strong antisemitic beliefs, three times more than the 10% for whites.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adl.org/Anti_semitism/poll_2007/ ADL Survey: American Attitudes Towards Jews in America]. Adl.org. Retrieved on 2 June 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; 

In November 2005, the [[U.S. Commission on Civil Rights]] examined antisemitism on college campuses. It reported that &quot;incidents of threatened bodily injury, physical intimidation or property damage are now rare&quot;, but antisemitism still occurs on many campuses and is a &quot;serious problem.&quot; The Commission recommended that the [[U.S. Department of Education]]'s [[Office for Civil Rights]] protect college students from antisemitism through vigorous enforcement of ''Title VI'' of the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]] and further recommended that [[United States Congress|Congress]] clarify that Title VI applies to discrimination against Jewish students.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eusccr.com/Ending%20Campus%20Ant-Semitism1.htm Ending Campus Anti-Semitism]. Eusccr.com. Retrieved on 2 June 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 19 September 2006, [[Yale University]] founded the [[Yale Initiative for the Interdisciplinary Study of Anti-Semitism]] (YIISA), the first North American university-based center for study of the subject, as part of its Institution for Social and Policy Studies. Director [[Charles A. Small|Charles Small]] of the Center cited the increase in antisemitism worldwide in recent years as generating a &quot;need to understand the current manifestation of this disease&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iht.com/articles/ap/2006/09/19/america/NA_GEN_US_Yale_Anti_Semitism.php Yale creates center to study antisemitism] Associated Press, 19 September 2006&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2011, Yale voted to close this initiative. After carrying out a routine review, the faculty review committee said that the initiative had not met its research and teaching standards. Donald Green, who heads Yale’s Institution for Social and Policy Studies, the body under whose aegis the antisemitism initiative was run, said that it had not had many papers published in the relevant leading journals or attracted many students. As with other programs that had been in a similar situation, the initiative had therefore been cancelled.&lt;ref name=nhregister201106&gt;{{Cite news | author = Mary E. O'Leary | title = Yale cancels interdisciplinary course on anti-Semitism | newspaper = New Haven Register | date = 7 June 2011 | url = http://nhregister.com/articles/2011/06/07/news/new_haven/doc4deebfb3198cb509290513.txt}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kampeas, Ron. (2011-06-10) [http://www.jewishjournal.com/education/article/shuttering_of_yale_program_on_anti-semitism_raises_hackles_20110610/ Shuttering of Yale program on anti-Semitism raises hackles]. Jewishjournal.com. Retrieved on 2 June 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; This decision has been criticized by figures such as former U.S. Commission on Civil Rights Staff Director [[Kenneth L. Marcus]], who is now the director of the Initiative to Combat Anti-Semitism and Anti-Israelism in America’s Educational Systems at the Institute for Jewish and Community Research, and [[Deborah Lipstadt]], who described the decision as &quot;weird&quot; and &quot;strange.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nbcconnecticut.com/news/local/Yale-C-123455979.html Yale Pulls the Plug on Anti-Semitism Institute]. nbcconnecticut.com (9 June 2011)&lt;/ref&gt; [[Antony Lerman]] has supported Yale's decision, describing the YIISA as a politicized initiative that was devoted to the promotion of Israel rather than to serious research on antisemitism.&lt;ref&gt;[http://antonylerman.com/2011/06/10/antisemitism-research-just-improved-yale%E2%80%99s-initiative-for-studying-antisemitism-is-axed/ Antony Lerman, &quot;Antisemitism Research Just Improved: Yale’s ‘Initiative’ for Studying Antisemitism is Axed&quot;], Antony Lerman: Context Is Everything, 10 June 2011, Retrieved 13 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2009 study published in ''[[Boston Review]]'' found that nearly 25% of non-Jewish Americans blamed Jews for the [[financial crisis of 2008–2009]], with a higher percentage among Democrats than Republicans.&lt;ref&gt;Neil Malhotra and Yotam Margalit. [http://bostonreview.net/BR34.3/malhotra_margalit.php State of the Nation: Anti-Semitism and the economic crisis]. Boston Review. Retrieved on 2 June 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2012, the [[California state assembly]] approved a [[non-binding resolution]] that &quot;encourages university leaders to combat a wide array of anti-Jewish and anti-Israel actions,&quot; although the resolution &quot;is purely symbolic and does not carry policy implications.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/national/on-faith/calif-resolution-denouncing-anti-semitism-on-college-campuses-targets-anti-israel-protests/2012/08/29/17a0188a-f1b2-11e1-b74c-84ed55e0300b_story.html Calif. resolution denouncing anti-Semitism on college campuses targets anti-Israel protests]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Latin America===

====Venezuela====
{{Further|History of the Jews in Venezuela}}
In a 2009 news story, Michael Rowan and Douglas E. Schoen wrote, &quot;In an infamous Christmas Eve speech several years ago, Chávez said the Jews killed Christ and have been gobbling up wealth and causing poverty and injustice worldwide ever since.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.forbes.com/2009/02/13/chavez-jews-referendum-opinions-contributors_0215_rowan_schoen.html Hugo Chavez And Anti-Semitism\]&quot;. Forbes.com. 15 February 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Hugo Chávez]] stated that &quot;[t]he world is for all of us, then, but it so happens that a minority, the descendants of the same ones that crucified Christ, the descendants of the same ones that kicked [[Simón Bolívar|Bolívar]] out of here and also crucified him in their own way over there in Santa Marta, in Colombia. A minority has taken possession of all of the wealth of the world.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.weeklystandard.com/Content/Public/Articles/000/000/006/572vteaf.asp Blast From the Past]&quot;. ''The Weekly Standard''. 11 January 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2012, opposition candidate for the [[Venezuelan presidential election, 2012|2012 Venezuelan presidential election]] [[Henrique Capriles]] was subject to what foreign journalists characterized as vicious&lt;ref name=ChavezRival&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/02/17/jewish-group-chavez-foe-a_n_1285507.html|title=Henrique Capriles Radonski: Hugo Chavez Foe A Target Of Anti-Semitism|work=[[The Huffington Post]]|date=17 February 2012|accessdate=22 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; attacks by state-run media sources.&lt;ref name=ChavezMedia&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2012-02-21/chavez-media-say-rival-capriles-backs-plots-ranging-from-nazis-to-zionists.html |title= Chavez media say rival Capriles backs plots ranging from Nazis to Zionists |author= Devereux, Charlie |publisher= Bloomberg |date= 20 February 2012 |accessdate= 21 February 2012}} Also available from [http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/g/a/2012/02/21/bloomberg_articlesLZJTP51A74E901-LZP8I.DTL sfgate.com]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name= TheMan&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.reuters.com/article/2012/04/01/us-venezuela-election-capriles-idUSBRE83008Y20120401 |title= Insight: The man who would beat Hugo Chavez |publisher= Reuters |author= Cawthorne, Andrew |date= 1 April 2012 |accessdate= 10 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''[[Wall Street Journal]]'' said that Capriles &quot;was vilified in a campaign in Venezuela's state-run media, which insinuated he was, among other things, a homosexual and a Zionist agent&quot;.&lt;ref name=ChavezRival/&gt; A 13 February 2012 opinion article in the state-owned [[Radio Nacional de Venezuela]], titled &quot;The Enemy is Zionism&quot;&lt;ref name=ADL17022012&gt;{{cite web |publisher= [[Anti-Defamation League]] |date= 17 February 2012 |url= http://www.adl.org/main_Anti_Semitism_International/AntiSemitic-Article-Venezuela-021712.htm |title= Anti-Semitic article appears in Venezuela |accessdate= 7 May 2012}} Includes English translation of Venezuelan National Radio article.&lt;/ref&gt; attacked Capriles' Jewish ancestry and linked him with Jewish national groups because of a meeting he had held with local Jewish leaders,&lt;ref name=ChavezRival/&gt;&lt;ref name=ChavezMedia/&gt;&lt;ref name=JewishGay&gt;{{cite news |url= http://worldnews.msnbc.msn.com/_news/2012/02/15/10411964-chavez-allies-attack-new-opponent-capriles-as-jewish-gay?lite |title= Chavez allies attack new opponent Capriles as Jewish, gay |publisher= MSNBC |date= 15 February 2012 |accessdate= 10 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; saying, &quot;This is our enemy, the Zionism that Capriles today represents ... Zionism, along with capitalism, are responsible for 90% of world poverty and imperialist wars.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ChavezRival&quot;/&gt;

===Europe===
{{Further|Antisemitism in Europe|New antisemitism}}
According to a 2004 report from the [[Jerusalem Center for Public Affairs]], antisemitism had increased significantly in Europe since 2000, with significant increases in verbal attacks against Jews and vandalism such as graffiti, fire bombings of Jewish schools, desecration of synagogues and cemeteries. Germany, France, [[United Kingdom|Britain]] and Russia are the countries with the highest rate of antisemitic incidents in Europe.&lt;ref name = &quot;mgjmsp&quot;&gt;[http://www.jcpa.org/phas/phas-urban-f04.htm Anti-Semitism In Germany Today: Its Roots And Tendencies – Susanne Urban]. Jcpa.org. Retrieved on 2 June 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; The Netherlands and Sweden have also consistently had high rates of antisemitic attacks since 2000.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;The 2005 U.S. State Department Report on Global Antisemitism.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some claim that recent European antisemitic violence can actually be seen as a spill over from the long running [[Arab–Israeli conflict|Arab-Israeli conflict]] since the majority of the perpetrators are from the [[Islam in Europe|large Muslim immigrant communities in European cities]]. However, compared to France, the United Kingdom and much of the rest of Europe, in Germany Arab and pro-Palestinian groups are involved in only a small percentage of antisemitic incidents.&lt;ref name = &quot;mgjmsp&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tau.ac.il/Anti-Semitism/ Stephen Roth Institute, Tel Aviv University].&lt;/ref&gt; According to ''The Stephen Roth Institute for the Study of Contemporary Antisemitism and Racism'', most of the more extreme attacks on Jewish sites and physical attacks on Jews in Europe come from militant Islamic and Muslim groups, and most Jews tend to be assaulted in countries where groups of young Muslim immigrants reside.&lt;ref name=roth&gt;[http://www.tau.ac.il/Anti-Semitism/asw2004/general-analysis.htm GENERAL ANALYSIS 2004], The Stephen Roth Institute for the Study of Contemporary Antisemitism and Racism, Tel Aviv University. Retrieved 29 March 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 1 January 2006, Britain's chief [[rabbi]], Lord [[Jonathan Sacks]], warned that what he called a &quot;tsunami of antisemitism&quot; was spreading globally. In an interview with [[BBC Radio 4]], Sacks said: &quot;A number of my rabbinical colleagues throughout Europe have been assaulted and attacked on the streets. We've had synagogues desecrated. We've had Jewish schools burnt to the ground – not here but in France. People are attempting to silence and even ban Jewish societies on campuses on the grounds that Jews must support the state of Israel, therefore they should be banned, which is quite extraordinary because ... British Jews see themselves as British citizens. So it's that kind of feeling that you don't know what's going to happen next that's making ... some European Jewish communities uncomfortable.&quot;&lt;ref name=Gillan&gt;Gillan, Audrey. [http://www.guardian.co.uk/religion/Story/0,2763,1676509,00.html &quot;Chief rabbi fears 'tsunami' of hatred&quot;], ''The Guardian'', 2 January 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

Following an escalation in antisemitism in 2012, which included the [[Toulouse and Montauban shootings|deadly shooting of three children]] at a Jewish school in France, the [[European Jewish Congress]] demanded in July a more proactive response.  EJC President Moshe Kantor explained, &quot;We call on authorities to take a more proactive approach so there would be no reason for statements of regret and denunciation. All these smaller attacks remind me of smaller tremors before a massive earthquake. The Jewish community cannot afford to be subject to an earthquake and the authorities cannot say that the writing was not on the wall.&quot;  He added that European countries should take legislative efforts to ban any form of [[incitement]], as well as to equip the authorities with the necessary tools to confront any attempt to expand [[terrorist]] and violent activities against Jewish communities in Europe.&lt;ref name=EJP&gt;{{cite news|last=Shamee|first=Maureen|title='Proactive' response needed to escalation of anti-Semitic attacks across Europe, says European Jewish Congress|url=http://www.ejpress.org/article/news/uk/59964|accessdate=13 July 2012|newspaper=European Jewish Press|date=6 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Germany====
{{Further|History of the Jews in Germany}}
The Interior Minister of Germany, [[Wolfgang Schäuble]], points out the official policy of Germany: &quot;We will not tolerate any form of extremism, xenophobia or anti-Semitism.&quot;&lt;ref name=bbcwolfgang&gt;{{cite news
|title=Germans warned of neo-Nazi surge
|accessdate=6 June 2007
|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/5005472.stm
|date=22 May 2006
| work=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the number of extreme right-wing groups and organisations grew from 141 (2001)&lt;ref name=bundesamt1&gt;Bundesamt für Verfassungsschutz. Federal Office for the Protection of the Constitution. {{PDFlink|[http://www.verfassungsschutz.de/download/SHOW/vsbericht_2003.pdf Verfassungsschutzbericht 2003]}}. Annual Report. 2003, p. 29&lt;/ref&gt; to 182 (2006),&lt;ref name=bundesamt2&gt;[[Bundesamt für Verfassungsschutz]]. Federal Office for the Protection of the Constitution. {{PDFlink|[http://www.verfassungsschutz.de/download/de/publikationen/verfassungsschutzbericht/vsbericht_2006/vsbericht_2006.pdf ''Verfassungsschutzbericht 2006''. Annual Report]}}. 2006, p. 51&lt;/ref&gt; especially in the formerly communist East Germany,&lt;ref name=bbcwolfgang/&gt; [[Fight Against The Right|Germany's measures against right-wing groups]] and antisemitism are effective, despite Germany having the highest rates of antisemitic acts in Europe. According to the annual reports of the [[Bundesamt für Verfassungsschutz|Federal Office for the Protection of the Constitution]] the overall number of far-right extremists in Germany dropped during the last years from 49,700 (2001),&lt;ref name=bundesamt1/&gt; 45,000 (2002),&lt;ref name=bundesamt1/&gt; 41,500 (2003),&lt;ref name=bundesamt1/&gt; 40,700 (2004),&lt;ref name=bundesamt2/&gt; 39,000 (2005),&lt;ref name=bundesamt2/&gt; to 38,600 in 2006.&lt;ref name=bundesamt2/&gt; Germany provided several million Euros to fund &quot;nationwide programs aimed at fighting far-right extremism, including teams of traveling consultants, and victims' groups.&quot;&lt;ref name=ihtassociated&gt;
[[The Associated Press]]. [http://www.iht.com/articles/ap/2006/10/22/europe/EU_GEN_Germany_Neo_Nazis.php &quot;Berlin police say 16 arrested during neo-Nazi demonstration&quot;.] ''[[International Herald Tribune]]''. 22 October 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 2012, two women were assaulted in Germany, sprayed with tear gas, and were shown a &quot;Hitler salute,&quot; apparently because of a [[Star of David]] necklace that they wore.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frauen im&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.nordbayern.de/region/fuerth/frauen-im-freizeitbad-beleidigt-und-mit-reizgas-bespruht-1.2227517 | title=Frauen im Freizeitbad beleidigt und mit Reizgas besprüht | publisher=Nordbayern | date=3 August 2012 | accessdate=3 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In late August 2012, [[Berlin]] police investigated an attack on a 53-year-old rabbi and his 6-year-old daughter, allegedly by four Arab teens, after which the rabbi needed treatment for head wounds at a hospital. The police classified the attack as a hate crime. ''Jüdische Allgemeine'' reported that the rabbi was wearing a [[kippah]] and was approached by one of the teens, who asked the rabbi if he was Jewish.  The teen then attacked the rabbi while yelling antisemitic comments, and threatened to kill the rabbi's daughter. Berlin’s mayor condemned the attack, saying that “Berlin is an international city in which intolerance, xenophobia and anti-Semitism are not being tolerated. Police will undertake all efforts to find and arrest the perpetrators.”&lt;ref name=&quot;VoNG&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.vosizneias.com/112634/2012/08/29/germany-berlin-rabbi-and-his-six-year-old-daughter-become-victims-of-a-hate-crime/ | title=Germany – Berlin Rabbi And His Six-Year-Old Daughter Become Victims Of A Hate Crime | publisher=Vos Iz Neias | date=29 August 2012 | accessdate=29 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2012, varius historians, including Dr. Julius H. Schoeps, a prominent German-Jewish historian and a member of the German Interior Ministry’s commission to combat antisemitism, charged the majority of [[Bundestag]] deputies with failing to understand antisemitism and the imperativeness of periodic legislative reports on German antisemitism.  Schoeps cited various anti-Semitic statements by German parliament members as well.  The report in question determined that 15% of Germans are anti-Semitic while over 20% espouse &quot;latent anti-Semitism,&quot; but the report has been criticized for downplaying the sharpness of antisemitism in Germany, as well as for failing to examine anti-Israel media coverage in Germany.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.jpost.com/International/Article.aspx?id=289609 | title=Historian slams Germany for ignoring anti-semitism | publisher=The Jerusalem Post | date=October 28, 2012 | accessdate=October 29, 2012 | author=Weinthal, Benjamin}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====The Netherlands====
{{Further|History of the Jews in the Netherlands}}
Antisemitic incidents, from verbal abuse to violence, are reported, allegedly connected with Islamic youth, mostly boys of [[Morocco|Moroccan]] descent. According to the Centre for Information and Documentation on Israel, a pro-Israel lobby group in the Netherlands, in 2009, the number of antisemitic incidents in [[Amsterdam]], the city that is home to most of the approximately 40,000 [[History of the Jews in the Netherlands|Dutch Jews]], was said to be doubled compared to 2008.&lt;ref&gt;Berkhout, Karel. (2010-01-26) [http://www.nrc.nl/international/article2468489.ece/Anti-Semitism_on_the_rise_in_Amsterdam &quot;Anti-Semitism on the rise in Amsterdam&quot;]. Nrc.nl. Retrieved on 2 June 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, Raphaël Evers, an [[Orthodox judaism|orthodox]] rabbi in [[Amsterdam]], told the Norwegian newspaper [[aftenposten]] that Jews can no longer be safe in the city anymore due to the risk of violent assaults. &quot;Jews no longer feel at home in the city. Many are considering [[aliyah]] to [[Israel]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;aftenposten.no&quot;&gt;[http://www.aftenposten.no/nyheter/uriks/article3584266.ece Hets av jøder er økende i Europa – Aftenposten]. Aftenposten.no. Retrieved on 2 June 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

====United Kingdom====
{{Further|British Jews}}
In 2005, a group of British [[Parliament of the United Kingdom|Members of Parliament]] set up an inquiry into antisemitism, which published its findings in 2006. Its report stated that &quot;until recently, the prevailing opinion both within the Jewish community and beyond [had been] that antisemitism had receded to the point that it existed only on the margins of society.&quot; It found a reversal of this progress since 2000. In his oral evidence, the Chief Rabbi stated: “If you were to ask me is Britain an antisemitic society, the answer is manifestly and obviously no. It is one of the least antisemitic societies in the world.” The inquiry set out to investigate the problem, identify the sources of contemporary antisemitism and make recommendations to improve the situation. It discussed the influence of the Israel-Palestine conflict and issues of anti-Israel sentiment versus antisemitism at length and noted &quot;most of those who gave evidence were at pains to explain that [[criticism of Israel]] is not to be regarded in itself as antisemitic ... The Israeli government itself may, at times, have mistakenly perceived criticism of its policies and actions to be motivated by antisemitism.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{PDFlink|[http://www.antisemitism.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/All-Party-Parliamentary-Inquiry-into-Antisemitism-REPORT.pdf Report of the All-Party Parliamentary Inquiry into Antisemitism]|430&amp;nbsp;KB}}, All-Party Parliamentary Group against Antisemitism, September 2006, Retrieved 24 November 2010. For the first and second quote, see summary; for the third quote, see p. 17. [http://www.webcitation.org/5uUETyGni Archived] 24 November 2010.
*See [http://www.thepcaa.org/ inquiry website].&lt;/ref&gt; In November 2010, the [[BBC]]'s investigative program ''Panorama'' reported that Saudi national textbooks advocating antisemitism were being used in Islamic religious programs attended by 5,000 British schoolchildren in the United Kingdom. In the textbooks, Jews were described as looking like monkeys and pigs, and said to be condemned to hellfire.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2010/11/23/world/europe/23britain.html Lessons of Hate at Islamic Schools in Britain]. New York Times (23 November 2010)&lt;/ref&gt;

A report released in 2012 by the [[Community Security Trust]], documenting antisemitic incidents from January–June 2012, revealed that the number of incidents rose in these months compared to incidents in 2011, with 299 cases deemed antisemitic.  There was a significant rise in the number of antisemitic incidents in March 2012, apparently influenced by the [[Toulouse and Montauban shootings|antisemitic terrorist attack in Toulouse, France]] during that month by Mohammed Merah.&lt;ref name=&quot;THECST&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.thecst.org.uk/docs/CST%20Incidents%20Report_Jan-June%202012.pdf | title=Anti-Semitic incidents report: January–June 2012 | publisher=Community Security Trust | accessdate=October 3, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Commentator Anti&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.thecommentator.com/article/1722/anti_semitism_on_the_rise_in_the_uk | title=Anti-Semitism on the rise in the UK | publisher=The Commentator | date=29 September 2012 | accessdate=October 3, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====France====
{{Further|History of the Jews in France}}
France is home to the continent's largest Jewish community (about 600,000). Jewish leaders decry an intensifying antisemitism in France, mainly among Muslims of [[Arab]] or African heritage, but also growing among [[Caribbean]] islanders from former French colonies.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/841445.html Jews for Le Pen] by Daniel Ben-Simon. Haaretz. 25 March 2007&lt;/ref&gt;
Former Interior Minister [[Nicolas Sarkozy]] denounced the killing of [[Ilan Halimi]] on 13 February 2006 as an antisemitic crime.

Jewish philanthropist Baron Eric de Rothschild suggests that the extent of antisemitism in France has been exaggerated. In an interview with ''[[The Jerusalem Post]]'' he says that &quot;the one thing you can't say is that France is an anti-Semitic country.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Krieger, Leila Hilary. [http://fr.jpost.com/servlet/Satellite?pagename=JPost/JPArticle/ShowFull&amp;cid=1150191582833 &quot;Rothschild: France not anti-Semitic&quot;]. ''[[The Jerusalem Post]]'', 15 June 2006/ [http://web.archive.org/web/20080605002628/http://www.jpost.com/servlet/Satellite?pagename=JPost/JPArticle/ShowFull&amp;cid=1150191582833 Archived] 24 November 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2012, Mohammed Merah [[Toulouse and Montauban shootings|opened fire at a Jewish school]] in Toulouse, killing a teacher and three children. A 8 year old girl was shot in the head at point blank range. President [[Nicolas Sarkozy]] said that it was &quot;obvious&quot; it was an antisemitic attack&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=School Shooting Gun Same As Other Attacks|url=http://news.sky.com/home/world-news/article/16191704|newspaper=Sky News|date=19 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that, &quot;I want to say to all the leaders of the Jewish community, how close we feel to them. All of France is by their side.&quot; The Israeli Prime Minister condemned the &quot;despicable anti-Semitic&quot; murders.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Netanyahu: Murder in French Jewish school a 'despicable anti-Semitic' attack|url=http://www.haaretz.com/news/diplomacy-defense/netanyahu-murder-in-french-jewish-school-a-despicable-anti-semitic-attack-1.419570|publisher=Haaretz|accessdate=19 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Toulouse shooting: Same gun and motorbike used in Jewish and soldier attacks|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/france/9152469/France-school-shooting-Four-dead-at-Ozar-Hatorah-school-in-Toulouse.html|newspaper=The Telegraph|date=19 Mar 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; After a 32 hour siege and standoff with the police outside his house, and a French raid, Merah jumped off a balcony and was shot in the head and killed.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2012/03/22/mohamed-merah-dies-in-french-standoff-s-gory-end.html&lt;/ref&gt; Merah told police during the standoff that he intended to keep on attacking, and he loved death the way the police loved life.  He also claimed connections with al-Qaeda.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.jpost.com/International/Article.aspx?id=276728&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-4252861,00.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.theaustralian.com.au/news/world/france-probes-gunman-siege-tapes/story-e6frg6so-1226420833585&lt;/ref&gt;

4 months later, in July 2012, a French Jewish teenager wearing a &quot;distinctive religious symbol&quot; was the victim of a violent antisemitic attack on a train travelling between Toulouse and Lyon.  The teen was first verbally harassed and later beaten up by two assailants.  The French Jewish umbrella group, [[Conseil Représentatif des Institutions juives de France|CRIF]], called the attack “another development in the worrying trend of anti-Semitism in our country.”&lt;ref&gt;http://www.timesofisrael.com/yeshiva-student-attacked-on-french-train/&lt;/ref&gt;

Another incident in July 2012 dealt with the vandalism of the synagogue of [[Noisy-le-Grand]] of the [[Seine-Saint-Denis]] district in [[Paris]].  The synagogue was vandalized three times in a ten day period.  Prayer books and shawls were thrown on the floor, windows were shattered, drawers were ransacked, and vandalized the walls, tables, clocks, and floors.  The authorities were alerted of the incidents by the Bureau National de Vigilance Contr L’Antisemtisme (BNVCA), a French antisemitism watchdog group, which called for more measures to be taken to prevent future hate crimes. BNVCA President Sammy Ghozlan stated that, &quot;Despite the measures taken, things persist, and I think that we need additional legislation, because the Jewish community is annoyed.&quot;&lt;ref name=Algemeiner1&gt;{{cite news|title=French Synagogue Vandalized For Third Time in Ten Days|url=http://www.algemeiner.com/2012/07/12/french-synagogue-vandalized-for-third-time-in-ten-days/|accessdate=13 July 2012|newspaper=Algemeiner|date=12 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2012, [[Abraham Cooper]], the dean of the [[Simon Wiesenthal Center]], met French Interior Minister [[Manuel Valls]] and reported that antisemitic attacks against French Jews increased by 40% since [[Toulouse and Montauban shootings|Merah's shooting spree]] in [[Toulouse]].  Cooper pressed Valls to take extra measures to secure the safety of French Jews, as well as to discuss strategies to foil an increasing trend of lone-wolf terrorists on the Internet.&lt;ref name=&quot;IHA&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.israelhayom.com/site/newsletter_article.php?id=5606 | title=Anti-Semitic attacks in France surge by 40% since March | publisher=Israel Hayom | work=Reuters; Israel Hayom | date=29 August 2012 | accessdate=29 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Norway====
{{Main|Antisemitism in Norway}}
In 2010, the [[Norwegian Broadcasting Corporation]] after one year of research, revealed that antisemitism was common among some 8th, 9th, and 10th graders in Oslo's schools. Teachers at schools with large numbers of [[Muslim]]s revealed that Muslim students often &quot;praise or admire [[Adolf Hitler]] for his killing of [[Jew]]s&quot;, that &quot;Jew-hate is legitimate within vast groups of Muslim students&quot; and that &quot;Muslims laugh or command [teachers] to stop when trying to educate about the [[Holocaust]]&quot;. Additionally, &quot;while some students might protest when some express support for [[terrorism]], none object when students express hate of Jews&quot;, saying that it says in &quot;the [[Quran]] that you shall kill Jews, all true Muslims hate Jews&quot;. Most of these students were said to be born and raised in Norway. One [[Jew]]ish father also stated that his child had been taken by a Muslim mob after school (though the child managed to escape), reportedly &quot;to be taken out to the forest and [[lynching|hung]] because he was a Jew&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www1.nrk.no/nett-tv/indeks/205057|work=NRK Lørdagsrevyen|title=Jødiske blir hetset|date=13 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://theforeigner.no/pages/columns/what-about-norwegian-anti-semitism/&lt;/ref&gt;

Norwegian Education Minister Kristin Halvorsen referred to the antisemitism reported in this study as being “completely unacceptable.” The head of a local Islamic council joined Jewish leaders and Halvorsen in denouncing such antisemitism.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.newsinenglish.no/2010/03/16/anti-semitism-report-shocks-officials/&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2012, the [[Organization for Security and Co-Operation in Europe]] issued a report regarding antisemitism in Norway, criticizing Norway for an increase in antisemitism in the country and blaming Norwegian officials for failing to address antisemitism.  The OSCE also appealed to Norway to abolish a ban on [[Jewish ritual slaughter]], which was in place since 1929, as an &quot;important symbolic gesture.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.algemeiner.com/2012/10/26/report-criticizes-norway-for-rise-in-anti-semitism/ | title=Report Criticizes Norway for Rise in Anti-Semitism | publisher=The Algemeiner | date=26 October 2012 | accessdate=October 28, 2012 | author=Pontz, Zach}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Sweden====
{{Main|Antisemitism in Sweden}}
After Germany and Austria, Sweden has the highest rate of antisemitic incidents in Europe, though the Netherlands has reported a higher rate of antisemitism in some years.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; A government study in 2006 estimated that 15% of Swedes agree with the statement: &quot;The Jews have too much influence in the world today&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Henrik Bachner and Jonas Ring. [http://web.archive.org/web/20071201103823/http://intolerans.levandehistoria.se/article/article_docs/antisemitism_english.pdf Antisemitic images and attitudes in Sweden]. levandehistoria.se&lt;/ref&gt; 5% of the entire adult population, and 39% of the [[Muslims|Muslim]] population, harbor strong and consistent antisemitic views. Former Prime Minister [[Göran Persson]] described these results as &quot;surprising and terrifying&quot;. However, the Rabbi of Stockholm's Orthodox Jewish community, Meir Horden claimed that &quot;It's not true to say that the Swedes are anti-Semitic. Some of them are hostile to Israel because they support the weak side, which they perceive the [[Palestinians]] to be.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/922248.html Anti-Semitism, in Sweden? Depends who you're asking], Haaretz, 9 November 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009, a synagoguage that served the Jewish community in Malmö was set ablaze. Jewish cemeteries were repeatedly desecrated, worshippers were abused while returning home from prayer, and masked men mockingly chanted &quot;Hitler&quot; in the streets.  As a result of security concerns, Malmö's synagogue has guards and rocket-proof glass in the windows, and the Jewish kindergarten can only be reached through thick steel security doors.&lt;ref name=&quot;Malmo Jews leaving Telegraph&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/sweden/7278532/Jews-leave-Swedish-city-after-sharp-rise-in-anti-Semitic-hate-crimes.html | title=Jews leave Swedish city after sharp rise in anti-Semitic hate crimes | work=The Telegraph | date=21 February 2012 | accessdate=24 July 2012 | author=Meo, Nick | location=Malmo, Sweden}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In early 2010, the Swedish publication ''The Local'' published series of articles about the growing antisemitism in [[Malmö, Sweden]]. In an interview in January 2010, Fredrik Sieradzki of the Jewish Community of Malmö stated that &quot;Threats against Jews have increased steadily in Malmö in recent years and many young Jewish families are choosing to leave the city. Many feel that the community and local politicians have shown a lack of understanding for how the city's Jewish residents have been marginalized.&quot; He also added that &quot;right now many Jews in Malmö are really concerned about the situation here and don't believe they have a future here.&quot; The Local also reported that Jewish cemeteries and synagogues have repeatedly been defaced with antisemitic graffiti, and a chapel at another Jewish burial site in Malmö was firebombed in 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thelocal.se/24632/20100127/ Jews flee Malmö as anti-Semitism grows] by David Landes, The Local, 27 January 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009 the Malmö police received reports of 79 antisemitic incidents, which was twice the number of the previous year (2008).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/sweden/7278532/Jews-leave-Swedish-city-after-sharp-rise-in-anti-Semitic-hate-crimes.html Jews leave Swedish city after sharp rise in anti-Semitic hate crimes] Sunday Telegraph. 21 February 2010&lt;/ref&gt; Fredrik Sieradzki, spokesman for the Malmö Jewish community, estimated that the already small Jewish population is shrinking by 5% a year. &quot;Malmö is a place to move away from,&quot; he said, citing antisemitism as the primary reason.&lt;ref name=&quot;forward.com&quot;&gt;Donald Snyder. [http://www.forward.com/articles/129233/ For Jews, Swedish City Is a ‘Place To Move Away From’]. Forward.com (2010-07-07). Retrieved on 2 June 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2010, Fredrik Sieradzk told ''Die Presse'', an Austrian Internet publication, that Jews are being &quot;harassed and physically attacked&quot; by &quot;people from the Middle East,&quot; although he added that only a small number of Malmö's 40,000 Muslims &quot;exhibit hatred of Jews.&quot; Sieradzk also stated that approximately 30 Jewish families have emigrated from Malmö to Israel in the past year, specifically to escape from harassment. Also in March, the Swedish newspaper ''Skånska Dagbladet'' reported that attacks on Jews in Malmö totaled 79 in 2009, about twice as many as the previous year, according to police statistics.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jta.org/news/article/2010/03/22/1011279/report-anti-semitic-attacks-in-rise-in-scandanavia Report: Anti-Semitic attacks rising in Scandinavia], Jewish Telegraphic Agency (JTA), 22 March 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2010, ''The Forward'' reported on the current state of Jews and the level of antisemitism in Sweden. Henrik Bachner, a writer and professor of history at the University of Lund, claimed that members of the Swedish Parliament have attended anti-Israel rallies where the Israeli flag was burned while the flags of Hamas and Hezbollah were waved, and the rhetoric was often antisemitic—not just anti-Israel. But such public rhetoric is not branded hateful and denounced. Charles Small, director of the [[Yale Initiative for the Interdisciplinary Study of Antisemitism]], stated that &quot;Sweden is a microcosm of contemporary anti-Semitism. It's a form of acquiescence to radical Islam, which is diametrically opposed to everything Sweden stands for.&quot; Per Gudmundson, chief editorial writer for ''Svenska Dagbladet'', has sharply criticized politicians who offer &quot;weak excuses&quot; for Muslims accused of anti-Semitic crimes. &quot;Politicians say these kids are poor and oppressed, and we have made them hate. They are, in effect, saying the behavior of these kids is in some way our fault.&quot;&lt;ref name=moveaway&gt;[http://www.forward.com/articles/129233/ For Jews, Swedish City Is a ‘Place To Move Away From’] by Donald Snyder, The Forward, Published 7 July 2010, issue of 16 July 2010.).&lt;/ref&gt; Judith Popinski, an 86-year-old Holocaust survivor, stated that she is no longer invited to schools that have a large Muslim presence to tell her story of surviving the Holocaust. Popinski, who found refuge in Malmö in 1945, stated that, until recently, she told her story in Malmö schools as part of their Holocaust studies program, but that now, many schools no longer ask Holocaust survivors to tell their stories, because Muslim students treat them with such disrespect, either ignoring the speakers or walking out of the class. She further stated that &quot;Malmö reminds me of the anti-Semitism I felt as a child in Poland before the war. I am not safe as a Jew in Sweden anymore.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;forward.com&quot;/&gt;

In December 2010, the [[Jews|Jewish]] [[human rights]] organization [[Simon Wiesenthal Center]] issued a travel advisory concerning Sweden, advising Jews to express &quot;extreme caution&quot; when visiting the southern parts of the country due to an alleged increase in verbal and physical harassment of Jewish citizens in the city of [[Malmö]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wiesenthal.com/site/apps/nlnet/content2.aspx?c=lsKWLbPJLnF&amp;b=4441467&amp;ct=8971903 Simon Wiesenthal Center to Issue Travel Advisory for Sweden – Officials Confer With Swedish Justice Minister Beatrice Ask | Simon Wiesenthal Center]. Wiesenthal.com (2010-12-14). Retrieved on 2 June 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
 
[[Ilmar Reepalu]], the mayor of Malmö for over 15 years, has been accused of failing to protect the Jewish community in Malmö, causing 30 Jewish families to leave the city in 2010, and more preparing to leave, which has left the possibility that Malmö's Jewish community will disappear soon.  Critics of Reepalu say that his statements, such as antisemitism in Malmö actually being an &quot;understandable&quot; consequence of Israeli policy in the Middle East, have encouraged young Muslims to abuse and harass the Jewish community.&lt;ref name=&quot;Malmo Jews leaving Telegraph&quot; /&gt; In an interview with ''the Sunday Telegraph'' in February 2010, Reepalu said, &quot;There haven't been any attacks on Jewish people, and if Jews from the city want to move to Israel that is not a matter for Malmö,&quot; which renewed concerns about Reepalu.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thelocal.se/25210/20100225/ Sahlin raps Malmö mayor over Jew comments], ''The Local'', 25 February 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

===Middle East===
{{Further|Arabs and antisemitism}}

[[Robert L. Bernstein|Robert Bernstein]], founder of [[Human Rights Watch]], says that antisemitism is &quot;deeply ingrained and institutionalized&quot; in &quot;Arab nations in modern times.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/why-do-human-rights-groups-ignore-palestinians-war-of-words/2011/09/26/gIQAWU5y2K_story.html Why do human rights groups ignore Palestinians’ war of words?]. Washingtonpost.com (2011-09-26). Retrieved on 2 June 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 2011 survey by the [[Pew Research Center]], all of the Muslim-majority Middle Eastern countries polled held strongly negative views of Jews. In the questionnaire, only 2% of [[Egypt]]ians, 3% of [[Lebanon|Lebanese]] Muslims, and 2% of [[Jordan]]ians reported having a positive view of Jews. Muslim-majority countries outside the Middle East held similarly negative views, with 4% of [[Turkey|Turks]] and 9% of [[Indonesia]]ns viewing Jews favorably.&lt;ref&gt;Pew Research Center. [http://pewglobal.org/2011/07/21/muslim-western-tensions-persist/3/ &quot;Views of Jews Positive in the West, Dismal in Muslim World&quot;, PEW Global Attitudes Report, July 21, 2011, retrieved August 21, 2011.]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Edward Rothstein]], cultural critic of ''[[The New York Times]]'', writes that some of the dialogue from Middle East media and commentators about Jews bear a striking resemblance to [[Nazi propaganda]].&lt;ref&gt;Rothstein, Edward. [http://www.nytimes.com/2009/02/24/arts/design/24muse.html?ref=design&amp;pagewanted=all &quot;Nazis’ ‘Terrible Weapon,’ Aimed at Minds and Hearts&quot;], ''[[The New York Times]]'', 23 February 2009, Retrieved 24 November 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; According to Josef Joffe of ''[[Newsweek]]'', &quot;anti-Semitism—the real stuff, not just bad-mouthing particular Israeli policies—is as much part of Arab life today as the hijab or the hookah. Whereas this darkest of creeds is no longer tolerated in polite society in the West, in the Arab world, Jew hatred remains culturally endemic.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Joffe, Josef. [http://www.newsweek.com/id/186974 &quot;Anti-Semitism In Araby&quot;], ''[[Newsweek]]'', 28 February 2009, Retrieved 24 November 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the Middle East, anti-Zionist propaganda frequently adopts the terminology and symbols of the Holocaust to demonize Israel and its leaders.

Muslim clerics in the Middle East have frequently referred to Jews as descendants of apes and pigs, which are conventional epithets for Jews and Christians.&lt;ref&gt;[[Bernard Lewis|Lewis, Bernard]] (1984). ''The Jews of Islam''. Princeton: Princeton University Press. ISBN 0-691-00807-8 p. 33&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Aluma Solnick. [http://memri.org/bin/articles.cgi?Area=sr&amp;ID=SR01102 ''Based on Koranic Verses, Interpretations, and Traditions, Muslim Clerics State: The Jews Are the Descendants of Apes, Pigs, And Other Animals''.] MEMRI Special Report – No. 11, 1 November 2002&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
*Neil J. Kressel. [http://chronicle.com/free/v50/i27/27b01401.htm &quot;The Urgent Need to Study Islamic Anti-Semitism&quot;], ''The Chronicle of Higher Education'', ''The Chronicle Review'', 12 March 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Egypt====

In [[Egypt]], Dar al-Fadhilah published a translation of [[Henry Ford]]'s antisemitic treatise, ''[[The International Jew]]'', complete with distinctly antisemitic imagery on the cover.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.intelligence.org.il/eng/sib/4_04/as_egypt.htm Examples of anti-Semitism in the Arab and Muslim world] on intelligence.org.il, site of the Intelligence and Terrorism Information Center
at the Center for Special Studies (C.S.S), Israel. Retrieved 24 September 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 5 May 2001, after [[Shimon Peres]] visited [[Egypt]], the Egyptian ''[[Al Akhbar (Egypt)|al-Akhbar]]'' internet paper said that &quot;lies and deceit are not foreign to Jews[...]. For this reason, Allah changed their shape and made them into monkeys and pigs.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adl.org/egyptian_media/media_2002/stereotypes.asp Anti-Semitism in the Egyptian Media: February 2001 – February 2002], &quot;Classic Anti-Semitic Stereotypes&quot;, [[Anti-Defamation League]]. Retrieved 4 March 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 2012, Egypt's Al Nahar channel fooled actors into thinking they were on an Israeli television show and filmed their reactions to being told it was an Israeli television show.  In response, some of the actors launched into antisemitic rants or dialogue, and many became violent. Actress Mayer El Beblawi said that &quot;Allah did not curse the worm and moth as much as he cursed the Jews while actor Mahmoud Abdel Ghaffar launched into a violent rage and said, &quot;You brought me someone who looks like a Jew... I hate the Jews to death&quot; after finding out it was a prank.&lt;ref name=&quot;Anti-semitism candid camera Egypt&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.jpost.com/MiddleEast/Article.aspx?id=278645 | title=Violent anti-Semitism applauded on Egypt TV | publisher=The Jerusalem Post | date=24 July 2012 | accessdate=24 July 2012 | author=Lappin, Yaakov}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Candid camera egypt Times&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.timesofisrael.com/egyptian-actor-slaps-and-fells-female-host-denounces-israelis-in-egyptian-tv-prank-gone-wrong/ | title=Egyptian actor slaps and fells female host, denounces Israelis, in Egyptian TV ‘prank’ gone wrong | work=The Times of Israel | date=24 July 2012 | accessdate=24 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Gaza &amp; Palestinian Territories====
Mudar Zahran, a Palestinian, writing for the [[Hudson Institute]] says that &quot;the Palestinians have been used as fuel for the new form of anti-Semitism; this has hurt the Palestinians and exposed them to unprecedented and purposely media-ignored abuse by Arab governments, including some of those who claim love for the Palestinians, yet in fact only bear hatred to Jews. This has resulted in Palestinian cries for justice, equality, freedom and even basic human rights being ignored while the world getting consumed with delegitimizing Israel from either ignorance or malice.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hudson-ny.org/1979/anti-semitism-20 Anti-semitism 2.0]. Hudson-ny.org (2011-03-21). Retrieved on 2 June 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1987-004-09A, Amin al Husseini und Adolf Hitler.jpg|thumb|[[Haj Amin al-Husseini]] meeting with [[Adolf Hitler]], December 1941. The Grand Mufti of Jerusalem helped recruit Muslims for the [[Waffen-SS]].]]

====Iran====
President Mahmoud Ahmadinejad of Iran has frequently denied the Holocaust.  For more information, please see this [[Holocaust_denial#Iranian_President_Ahmadinejad|page]].

In July, the winner of Iran's first annual International [[Wall Street]] Downfall Cartoon Festival, jointly sponsored by the semi-state-run Iranian media outlet [[Fars News]], was an antisemitic cartoon depicting Jews praying before the [[New York Stock Exchange]], which is made to look like the [[Western Wall]].  Other cartoons in the contest were antisemitic as well. The national director of the Anti-Defamation League, Abraham Foxman, condemned the cartoon, stating that &quot;Here's the anti-Semitic notion of Jews and their love for money, the canard that Jews 'control' Wall Street, and a cynical perversion of the Western Wall, the holiest site in Judaism,&quot; and &quot;Once again Iran takes the prize for promoting antisemitism.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Algemeiner&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Anti-Semitic Cartoon Wins Iranian Festival Prize|url=http://www.algemeiner.com/2012/07/11/anti-semitic-cartoon-wins-iranian-festival-prize/|accessdate=11 July 2012|newspaper=The Algemeiner|date=11 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Jewish Chronicle&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Rocker|first=Simon|title=Iran gives antisemitic cartoon top prize|url=http://www.thejc.com/news/world-news/69827/iran-gives-antisemitic-cartoon-top-prize?utm_source=twitterfeed&amp;utm_medium=twitter|accessdate=11 July 2012|newspaper=The Jewish Chronicle|date=11 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=ADL&gt;{{cite web|title=Anti-Semitic Cartoon Declared Winner Of Iranian 'Wall Street Downfall' Festival|url=Anti-Semitic Cartoon Declared Winner Of Iranian 'Wall Street Downfall' Festival|work=The Anti-Defamation League|accessdate=11 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Lebanon====
In 2004, [[Al-Manar]] aired a drama series, ''The Diaspora'', which observers allege is based on historical antisemitic allegations. [[BBC]] correspondents who have watched the program says it quotes extensively from the ''Protocols of the Elders of Zion''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/3581514.stm &quot;France offers 'hate TV' reprieve&quot;], [[BBC News]], 20 August 2004, Retrieved 24 November 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Saudi Arabia====

The website of the [[Saudi Arabia]]n [[Saudi Commission for Tourism &amp; Antiquities|Supreme Commission for Tourism]] initially stated that Jews would not be granted tourist visas to enter the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.sauditourism.gov.sa/sct/indexlist.php?catid=39&amp;maincat=Travel_Tips |title=Visa requirements |publisher=[[Saudi Commission for Tourism &amp; Antiquities|Supreme Commission for Tourism]] |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20040206173019/http://www.sauditourism.gov.sa/sct/indexlist.php?catid=39&amp;maincat=Travel_Tips |archivedate=6 February 2004 |quote=Visas will not be issued for the following groups of people: * An Israeli passport holder or a passport that has an Israeli arrival/departure stamp. * Those who don't abide by the Saudi traditions concerning appearance and behaviors. Those under the influence of alcohol will not be permitted into the Kingdom. * There are certain regulations for pilgrims and you should contact the consulate for more information. * Jewish People}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/3493448.stm &quot;Jews barred in Saudi tourist drive&quot;], [[BBC News]], 27 February 2004, Retrieved 25 November 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
The Saudi embassy in the U.S. distanced itself from the statement, which was later removed.&lt;ref&gt;Morrison, JAmes. [http://goliath.ecnext.com/coms2/gi_0199-739782/Saudis-invite-Jews-WORLD-EMBASSY.html &quot;Saudis invite Jews.&quot;], ''[[The Washington Times]]'', 1 March 2004, Retrieved 25 November 2010.
*Whitaker, Brian. [http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2004/mar/01/saudiarabia.brianwhitaker &quot;Saudis deny anti-Jewish visa policy&quot;], ''[[The Guardian]]'', 1 March 2004, Retrieved 25 November 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Members of religions other than Islam, including Jews, are not permitted to practice their religion publicly in Saudi Arabia.

In 2001, Arab Radio and Television of Saudi Arabia produced a 30-part television miniseries entitled &quot;Horseman Without a Horse&quot;, a dramatization of ''[[The Protocols of the Elders of Zion]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adl.org/presrele/islme_62/4013_62.asp &quot;ADL Calls on Arab Leaders to Denounce Anti-Semitic Television Series&quot;], [[Anti-Defamation League]], 10 December 2001, Retrieved 24 November 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; One Saudi Arabian government newspaper suggested that hatred of all Jews is justifiable.&lt;ref&gt;''Al-Riyadh'', Saudi government daily, 15 April 2002, Turki 'Abdallah as-Sudayri, ''All of History is against Them''&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Saudi-Arabian textbook controversy|Saudi textbooks]] vilify Jews (and Christians and non-[[Wahabi]] Muslims): according to the 21 May 2006 issue of ''[[The Washington Post]]'', Saudi textbooks claimed by them to have been sanitized of antisemitism still call Jews apes (and Christians swine); demand that students avoid and not befriend Jews; claim that Jews worship the devil; and encourage Muslims to engage in Jihad to vanquish Jews.&lt;ref&gt;Shea, Nina. [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/05/19/AR2006051901769.html &quot;This is a Saudi textbook. (After the intolerance was removed.)&quot;], ''[[The Washington Post]]'', 21 May 2006, p. B01.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Center for Religious Freedom of [[Freedom House]] analyzed a set of Saudi Ministry of Education textbooks in Islamic studies courses for elementary and secondary school students. The researchers found statements promoting hate of Christians, Jews, &quot;polytheists&quot; and other &quot;unbelievers,&quot; including non-Wahhabi Muslims. [[The Protocols of the Elders of Zion]] was taught as historical fact. The texts described Jews and Christians as enemies of Muslim believers and the clash between them as an ongoing fight that will end in victory over the Jews. Jews were blamed for virtually all the &quot;subversion&quot; and wars of the modern world.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.freedomhouse.org/template.cfm?page=70&amp;release=379 Press Release]. freedomhouse.org. Retrieved on 2 June 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; A {{PDFlink|[http://www.hudson.org/files/publications/CRF_SaudiReport_2006.pdf 38-page overview]|371&amp;nbsp;KB}} of Saudi Arabia's curriculum has been released to the press by the [[Hudson Institute]].

The [[BBC]] aired a [[Panorama (TV series)|Panorama]] episode, entitled ''A Question of Leadership'', which reported that al-Sudais referred to Jews as &quot;the scum of the human race&quot; and &quot;offspring of apes and pigs&quot;, and stated, &quot;the worst [...] of the enemies of Islam are those [...] whom he [...] made monkeys and pigs, the aggressive Jews and oppressive [[Zionists]] and those that follow them [...] Monkeys and pigs and worshippers of false Gods who are the Jews and the Zionists.&quot; [[Abdul Rahman Al-Sudais]] is the leading [[Imam (Sunni Islam)|imam]] of the [[Masjid al-Haram|Grand mosque]] located in the Islamic holy city of [[Mecca]], [[Saudi Arabia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;panorama&quot;&gt;{{cite interview
 |last=Sacranie
 |first=Iqbal
|subjectlink = Iqbal Sacranie
|last2 = Abdul Bari
|first2 = Muhammad
|subjectlink2 = Muhammad Abdul Bari
|last3 = Kantharia
|first3 = Mehboob
|last4 = Siddiqui
|first4 = Ghayasuddin
|interviewer = John Ware
 |title=A Question of Leadership
 |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/programmes/panorama/4171950.stm
|program = ''[[Panorama (TV series)|Panorama]]''
|callsign = [[BBC]]
|city = [[London, England]]
 |date=21 August 2005
 |accessdate=30 March 2007
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Tom Gross, [http://www.nationalreview.com/comment/gross200406181018.asp &quot;Living in a Bubble: The BBC’s very own Mideast foreign policy&quot;.], ''[[National Review]]'', 18 June 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; In another sermon, on 19 April 2002, he declared that Jews are &quot;evil offspring, infidels, distorters of [others'] words, calf-worshippers, prophet-murderers, prophecy-deniers [...] the scum of the human race whom Allah cursed and turned into apes and pigs [...]&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{PDFlink|[http://arts.monash.edu.au/jewish-civilisation/visiting/kinberg-jews-koran.pdf &quot;Jews In The Koran And Early Islamic Traditions&quot;]}} by Dr. Leah Kinberg. Lecture delivered in May 2003, Monash University, Melbourne, quoting [http://www.alminbar.cc/alkhutab/khutbaa.asp?mediaURL=5544]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Asia===

====Malaysia====
{{See also|History of the Jews in Malaysia}}

Although [[Malaysia]] presently has no Jewish population, the country has reportedly become an example of a phenomenon called “Anti-Semitism without Jews.&quot; 

In his treatise on Malay identity, &quot;The Malay Dilemma,&quot; which was published in 1970, former Malaysian Prime Minister [[Mahathir Mohamad]] wrote: &quot;The Jews are not only hooked-nosed ... but understand money instinctively. ... Jewish stinginess and financial wizardry gained them the economic control of Europe and provoked antisemitism which waxed and waned throughout Europe through the ages.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.huffingtonpost.com/rabbi-abraham-cooper/malaysia-anti-semitism_b_903767.html In Malaysia, When in Doubt, Blame the Jews] by Rabbi Abraham Cooper, ''[[Huffington Post]]'', July 22, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Malay-language [[Utusan Malaysia]] daily stated in an editorial that Malaysians &quot;cannot allow anyone, especially the Jews, to interfere secretly in this country's business... When the drums are pounded hard in the name of human rights, the pro-Jewish people will have their best opportunity to interfere in any Islamic country,&quot; the newspaper said. &quot;We might not realize that the enthusiasm to support actions such as demonstrations will cause us to help foreign groups succeed in their mission of controlling this country.&quot; Prime Minister [[Najib Razak]]'s office susbsequently issued a statement late Monday saying Utusan's claim did &quot;not reflect the views of the government.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.yahoo.com/malaysia-media-claims-jewish-plot-rally-062311621.html Malaysia media claims Jewish plot after rally] by Sean Yoong, ''[[Associated Press]]'' (republished in Yahoo.news), July 18, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.themalaysianinsider.com/malaysia/article/bersih-an-opportunity-for-jews-to-infiltrate-country-says-utusan/ Bersih an opportunity for Jews to infiltrate country, says Utusan] by Shannon Teoh, ''[[Malaysia Insider]]'', July 18, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jta.org/news/article/2011/07/18/3088591/jews-trying-to-interfere-malaysian-newspaper-warns Jews trying to interfere, Malaysian newspaper warns], ''[[Jewish Telegraphic Agency]]'', July 18, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Turkey====
{{Further|History of the Jews in Turkey}}
In recent decades, synagogues have been targeted in a number of terrorist attacks. In 2003, the [[Neve Shalom Synagogue]] was targeted in a car bombing, killing 21 Turkish Muslims and 6 Jews.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/3276549.stm | work=BBC News | title=Film clue to Turkey Jewish attack | date=17 November 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2011, the ''Economist'' suggested that &quot;The best way for Turks to promote democracy would be to vote against the ruling party&quot;. Not long after, the Turkish Prime Minister, [[Recep Tayyip Erdoğan]], said that &quot;The International media, as they are supported by Israel, would not be happy with the continuation of the AKP government&quot;.&lt;ref name=cm&gt;[http://www.commentarymagazine.com/2011/06/07/turkey%E2%80%99s-prime-minister-the-jews-are-out-to-get-me/ Turkey's Prime Minister: The Jews Are Out to Get Me!], Commentary Magazine, 6 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Hurriyet Daily News'' quoted Erdoğan at the time as claiming &quot;The Economist is part of an Israeli conspiracy that aims to topple the Turkish government&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hurriyetdailynews.com/n.php?n=the-economist-faces-barrage-of-accusations-from-turkish-govt-2011-06-05 The Economist faces barrage of accusations from the Turkish gov't], The Hurriyet Daily News (English language edition), 12 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
Moreover, during Erdogan's tenure, Hitler's ''Mein Kampf'' has once again become a best selling book in Turkey.&lt;ref name=cm/&gt; Prime Minister Erdogan called antisemitism a &quot;crime against humanity.&quot; He also said that &quot;as a minority, they're our citizens. Both their security and the right to observe their faith are under our guarantee.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.jpost.com/JewishWorld/JewishNews/Article.aspx?id=131576 |work=[[The Jerusalem Post]] | title=Erdogan vows to fight anti-Semitism in Turkey |date=2 March 2009 |accessdate=12 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Judaism}}
{{Colbegin|2}}
*[[1968 Polish political crisis]]
*[[Antisemitism in the anti-globalization movement]]
*[[Anti-Jewish violence in Poland, 1944–1946]]
*[[Anti-Judaism]]
*''[[Anti-Semite and Jew]]''
*[[Anti-Zionism]]
*[[Antisemitic canard]]
*[[Antisemitism around the world]]
*[[The Legacy of Islamic Antisemitism]]
*[[Blood libel]]
*[[Criticism of Israel]]
*[[Criticism of Judaism]]
*[[Dreyfus affair]]
*[[Farhud]]
*[[General Order No. 11 (1862)]]
*[[History of antisemitism]]
*[[Holocaust denial]]
*[[Host desecration]]
*[[Jacob Barnet affair]]
*[[Judeo-Masonic conspiracy theory]]
*[[May Laws]]
*[[Nazi propaganda]]
*[[Persecution of Jews]]
*[[Racial policy of Nazi Germany]]
*[[Secondary antisemitism]]
*[[Semiticization]]
*[[Stab-in-the-back legend]]
*[[Timeline of antisemitism]]
*[[Three Whom God Should Not Have Created: Persians, Jews, and Flies]]
{{Colend}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
{{Refbegin|colwidth=60em}}
*[[Yosef Bodansky|Bodansky, Yossef]]. ''Islamic Anti-Semitism as a Political Instrument'', Freeman Center For Strategic Studies, 1999.
*Carr, Steven Alan. ''Hollywood and anti-Semitism: A cultural history up to World War II'', Cambridge University Press 2001.
*Chanes, Jerome A. ''Antisemitism: A Reference Handbook'', ABC-CLIO, 2004.
*Cohn, Norman. ''Warrant for Genocide'', Eyre &amp; Spottiswoode 1967; Serif, 1996.
*{{Cite book |title=The Anguish of the Jews: Twenty-Three Centuries of Antisemitism |last=Flannery |first=Edward H. |year=2004 |publisher=Paulist Press |isbn=0-8091-4324-0}}
*[[Avner Falk|Falk, Avner]]. ''Anti-Semitism: The History and Psychoanalysis of Contemporary Hatred''. Wesport, Connecticut, Praeger, 2008. ISBN 978-0-313-35384-0.
*Freudmann, Lillian C. ''Antisemitism in the New Testament'', University Press of America, 1994.
*[[Jane Gerber|Gerber, Jane S.]] (1986). &quot;Anti-Semitism and the Muslim World&quot;. In ''History and Hate: The Dimensions of Anti-Semitism'', ed. David Berger. Jewish Publications Society. ISBN 0-8276-0267-7
*[[Raul Hilberg|Hilberg, Raul]]. ''[[The Destruction of the European Jews]]''. Holmes &amp; Meier, 1985. 3 volumes.
*[[Paul Johnson (writer)|Johnson, Paul]]: ''A History of the Jews'' (New York: HarperCollins Publishers, 1987) ISBN 0-06-091533-1
*[[Walter Laqueur|Laqueur, Walter]]. ''The Changing Face of Antisemitism: From Ancient Times To The Present Day''. Oxford University Press. 2006. ISBN 0-19-530429-2
*Lewis, Bernard (1999). ''Semites and Anti-Semites: An Inquiry into Conflict and Prejudice''. W. W. Norton &amp; Co. ISBN 0-393-31839-7
*[[Deborah Lipstadt|Lipstadt, Deborah]]. ''Denying the Holocaust: The Growing Assault on Truth and Memory'', Penguin, 1994.
*McKain, Mark. ''Anti-Semitism: At Issue'', Greenhaven Press, 2005.
*Michael, Robert and Philip Rosen. [http://www.scarecrowpress.com/ISBN/0810858622 Dictionary of Antisemitism], The Scarecrow Press, Inc., 2007
*Perry, Marvin and Frederick Schweitzer. ''Anti-Semitism: Myth and Hate from Antiquity to the Present.'' Palgrave Macmillan. 2002.
*[[Leon Poliakov|Poliakov, Leon]]. ''The History of Anti-Semitism, Volume 1: From the Time of Christ to the Court Jews'', University of Pennsylvania Press: 2003
*[[Leon Poliakov|Poliakov, Leon]]. ''The History of Anti-Semitism, Volume 2: From Mohammad to the Marranos'', University of Pennsylvania Press: 2003
*[[Leon Poliakov|Poliakov, Leon]]. ''The History of Anti-Semitism, Volume 3: From Voltaire to Wagner'', University of Pennsylvania Press: 2003
*[[Leon Poliakov|Poliakov, Leon]]. ''The History of Anti-Semitism, Volume 4: Suicidal Europe 1870–1933'', University of Pennsylvania Press: 2003
*[[Leon Poliakov|Poliakov, Leon]] (1997). &quot;Anti-Semitism&quot;. ''[[Encyclopedia Judaica]]'' (CD-ROM Edition Version 1.0). Ed. [[Cecil Roth]]. Keter Publishing House. ISBN 965-07-0665-8
*Prager, Dennis, Telushkin, Joseph. ''Why the Jews? The Reason for Antisemitism''. Touchstone (reprint), 1985.
*{{Cite book |title=Anti-Judaism in Early Christianity |last=Richardson |first=Peter |year=1986 |publisher=Wilfrid Laurier University Press |isbn=0-88920-167-6}}
*Roth, Philip. [[The Plot Against America]], 2004
*Schweitzer, Frederick M. &amp; Perry, Marvin. ''Anti-Semitism: myth and hate from antiquity to the present'', Palgrave Macmillan, 2002, ISBN 0-312-16561-7
*Selzer, Michael (ed). ''&quot;Kike!&quot; : A Documentary History of Anti-Semitism in America'', New York 1972.
*Steinweis, Alan E. ''Studying the Jew: Scholarly Antisemitism in Nazi Germany''. Harvard University Press, 2006. ISBN 0-674-02205-X.
*[[Norman Stillman|Stillman, Norman]] (1979). ''The Jews of Arab Lands: A History and Source Book''. Philadelphia: Jewish Publication Society of America. ISBN 0-8276-0198-0
*Stillman, N.A. (2006). &quot;Yahud&quot;. ''[[Encyclopaedia of Islam]]''. Eds.: P.J. Bearman, Th. Bianquis, C.E. Bosworth, E. van Donzel and W.P. Heinrichs. Brill. Brill Online
*[http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=1603&amp;letter=A&amp;search=anti-semitism Anti-semitism] entry by Gotthard Deutsch in the [[Jewish Encyclopedia]], 1901–1906 ed.
*{{PDFlink|[http://www.state.gov/documents/organization/102301.pdf &quot;Contemporary Global Anti-Semitism: A Report Provided to the United States Congress&quot;]|7.4&amp;nbsp;MB}}, [[United States Department of State]], 2008, Retrieved 25 November 2010. See [http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/102406.htm html version].
{{Refend}}

==Further reading==
{{Refbegin|colwidth=60em}}
*[http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/jewish/lazare-anti.html ''Antisemitism: Its History and Causes''] by [[Bernard Lazare]].
*[http://www.jewishjournal.com/home/searchview.php?id=17335/ &quot;Experts explore effects of Ahmadinejad anti-Semitism&quot;], ''Jewish Journal of Greater Los Angeles'', 9 March 2007
*[[Anti-Defamation League]] [http://www.adl.org/main_Arab_World/default.htm Arab Antisemitism]
*[http://www.aish.com/seminars/whythejews/ Why the Jews? A perspective on causes of anti-Semitism]
*Stav, Arieh (1999). ''Peace: The Arabian Caricature – A Study of Anti-semitic Imagery''. Gefen Publishing House. ISBN 965-229-215-X
*Falk, Avner. (2008). ''Anti-Semitism: The History and Psychoanalysis of Contemporary Hatred''. Wesport, Connecticut, Praeger, ISBN 978-0-313-35384-0
*[http://www.antisemitism.org.il/ Coordination Forum for Countering Antisemitism] (with up to date calendar of antisemitism today)
*[http://har2.huji.ac.il:83/ALEPH/ENG/SAS/BAS/BAS/START Annotated bibliography of anti-Semitism] hosted by the Hebrew University of Jerusalem's Center for the Study of Antisemitism (SICSA)
*[http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/antisem.html Anti-Semitism and responses] at [[Jewish Virtual Library]]
*[http://www.coe.int/t/E/human_rights/ecri/1-ECRI/2-Country-by-country_approach/ Council of Europe, ECRI Country-by-Country Reports]
*[http://www.zionism-israel.com/his/judeophobia.htm Judeophobia: A short course on the history of anti-Semitism] at [http://www.zionism-israel.com] Zionism and Israel Information Center.
*Porat, Dina. [http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/818365.html &quot;What makes an anti-Semite?&quot;], ''[[Haaretz]]'', 27 January 2007, Retrieved 24 November 2010.
*[http://www.azure.org.il/article.php?id=18&amp;page=all An Attempt to Identify the Root Cause of Antisemitism] by [[A. B. Yehoshua]], [http://www.azure.org.il Azure], Spring 2008.
*[http://www.analitik.org.ua/author/46076f2011c07/ Antisemitism in modern Ukraine]
* Robert Michael ''Holy Hatred: Christianity, Antisemitism, and the Holocaust''
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Sister project links}}
*''[http://jsantisemitism.org/ The Journal for the Study of Antisemitism]
*[[Aish HaTorah|Aish]] ''[http://www.aish.com/seminars/whythejews/ Why the Jews? Real Causes or mere excuses?]''
* [[Yad Vashem]] [http://www1.yadvashem.org/yv/en/holocaust/about/01/antisemitism.asp?WT.mc_id=wiki Antisemitism: About the Holocaust]
*[[Anti-Defamation League]] [http://www.adl.org/main_Anti_Semitism_International/Default.htm Report on International Anti-Semitism]
*[[United States Holocaust Memorial Museum]]: [http://www.ushmm.org/museum/exhibit/focus/antisemitism/ Special Focus: Antisemitism]; Encyclopedia [http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/article.php?lang=en&amp;ModuleId=10007170 1], [http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/article.php?lang=en&amp;ModuleId=10007167 2], [http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/article.php?lang=en&amp;ModuleId=10007171 3], [http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/article.php?lang=en&amp;ModuleId=10007173 4], [http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/article.php?lang=en&amp;ModuleId=10007166 5], [http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/article.php?lang=en&amp;ModuleId=10005175 6]; [http://www.ushmm.org/museum/exhibit/focus/antisemitism/voices/ ''Voices on Antisemitism Podcast Series'']
*[http://www.jewishaffairs.org Antisemitism and anti-Israelism]
*The Coordination Forum for Countering Antisemitism [http://www.antisemitism.org.il/eng/search/?country=63&amp;id_category=&amp;region= Antisemitism measuring]
*Simpletoremember.com [http://www.simpletoremember.com/vitals/HistoryJewishPersecution.htm 2,000 Year Timeline of Jewish Persecution]
*[http://www.tau.ac.il/Anti-Semitism Stephen Roth Institute for the Study of Contemporary Antisemitism and Racism at Tel Aviv University]
*[http://www.yale.edu/yiisa/ Yale Initiative for the Interdisciplinary Study of Antisemitism]
*[http://iibsa.org/cms/index.php?id=83&amp;L=1 International Institute for Education and Research on Antisemitism (Berlin/London)]
*[http://www.h-net.org/~antis/ H-Antisemitism, H-Net Humanities &amp; Social Sciences OnLine]
*[http://www.archive.org/details/EuropeanAnti-semitismReinventsItself Robert Wistrich ''European Anti-Semitism Reinvents Itself.'']

{{Navboxes
|list =
{{Antisemitism topics|state=collapsed}}
{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}
{{Jews and Judaism}}
{{Discrimination}}
}}

[[Category:Antisemitism| ]]
[[Category:Jewish political status]]
[[Category:Political terms]]

[[als:Antisemitismus]]
[[ar:معاداة السامية]]
[[az:Antisemitizm]]
[[bn:ইহুদি-বিদ্বেষ]]
[[be:Антысемітызм]]
[[bg:Антисемитизъм]]
[[bs:Antisemitizam]]
[[br:Enepyuzevegezh]]
[[ca:Antisemitisme]]
[[ceb:Antisemitismo]]
[[cs:Antisemitismus]]
[[cy:Gwrth-Semitiaeth]]
[[da:Antisemitisme]]
[[de:Judenfeindlichkeit]]
[[et:Antisemitism]]
[[el:Αντισημιτισμός]]
[[es:Antisemitismo]]
[[eo:Kontraŭjudismo]]
[[eu:Antisemitismo]]
[[fa:یهودستیزی]]
[[fr:Antisémitisme]]
[[fy:Antisemitisme]]
[[gl:Antisemitismo]]
[[ko:반유대주의]]
[[hi:यहूदी विरोधवाद]]
[[hr:Antisemitizam]]
[[id:Antisemitisme]]
[[it:Antisemitismo]]
[[he:אנטישמיות]]
[[ka:ანტისემიტიზმი]]
[[ky:Антисемитизм]]
[[lad:Antisemitizmo]]
[[la:Antisemitismus]]
[[lv:Antisemītisms]]
[[lb:Antisemitismus]]
[[lt:Antisemitizmas]]
[[hu:Antiszemitizmus]]
[[mk:Антисемитизам]]
[[ml:ജൂതവിരോധം]]
[[mr:ज्यूविरोध]]
[[arz:معاداة الساميه]]
[[ms:Antisemitisme]]
[[nl:Antisemitisme]]
[[ja:反ユダヤ主義]]
[[no:Antisemittisme]]
[[nn:Antisemittisme]]
[[pfl:Andisemidismus]]
[[pl:Antysemityzm]]
[[pt:Antissemitismo]]
[[ro:Antisemitism]]
[[ru:Антисемитизм]]
[[sq:Antisemitizmi]]
[[scn:Antisimitismu]]
[[simple:Antisemitism]]
[[sk:Antisemitizmus]]
[[sl:Antisemitizem]]
[[sr:Антисемитизам]]
[[sh:Antisemitizam]]
[[fi:Antisemitismi]]
[[sv:Antisemitism]]
[[tl:Antisemitismo]]
[[ta:யூத எதிர்ப்புக் கொள்கை]]
[[th:การต่อต้านยิว]]
[[tr:Antisemitizm]]
[[uk:Антисемітизм]]
[[ur:ضد سامیت]]
[[vi:Chủ nghĩa bài Do Thái]]
[[yi:אנטיסעמיטיזם]]
[[zh:反犹太主义]]</text>
      <sha1>5g560venryjt1ybm692bg076si2fax8</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
