<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Aryan race</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>42277</id>
    <revision>
      <id>517273231</id>
      <parentid>516464374</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-11T21:32:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Niceguyedc</username>
        <id>5288432</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[:en:WP:CLEANER|WPCleaner]] v1.18 - Repaired 7 links to disambiguation page - [[WP:DPL|(You can help)]] - [[Aryans]], [[FOTW]], [[Guilt]], [[Indo-Europeans]], [[Indo-Iranian]], [[The Races of Europe]], [[World domination]] / Fixed using [[WP:WCW]] - I...</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="43871">{{About|the racial theory|the full range of meanings of &quot;Aryan&quot;|Aryan|other uses|Aryan (disambiguation)}}
{{Redirect|Aryanism|the Christian theology|Arianism}}
{{pp-semi|small=yes}}
{{race}}

The '''Aryan race''' is a concept historically influential in [[Western culture]] in the period of the late 19th century and early 20th century. It derives from the idea that the original speakers of the [[Indo-European languages]] and their descendants up to the present day constitute a distinctive [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]] or subrace of the larger [[Caucasian race]].&lt;ref&gt;Mish, Frederic C., Editor in Chief ''Webster's Tenth New Collegiate Dictionary'' Springfield, Massachusetts, U.S.A.:1994--Merriam-Webster See original definition (definition #1) of &quot;Aryan&quot; in English--Page 66&lt;/ref&gt; Belief in the existence of an Aryan race is sometimes referred to as &quot;Aryanism&quot;.

While originally meant simply as a neutral ethno-linguistic classification, it was later used for ideologically motivated [[racism]] in [[Nazi]] and [[neo-Nazi]] doctrine, as well as in [[occultism]] and [[white supremacism]] in particular.

== Origin of the term ==
{{Main|Aryan}}
[[Image:Darius I the Great's inscription.jpg|thumb|The earliest epigraphically-attested reference to the word ''arya'' occurs in the 6th century B.C. [[Behistun inscription]], which describes itself to have been composed &quot;in ''arya'' [language or script]&quot; (§ 70). As is also the case for all other &lt;!--[[Old Iranian|--&gt;Old Iranian language&lt;!--]]--&gt; usage, the ''arya'' of the inscription does not signify anything but &quot;[[Etymology of Iran|Iranian]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''cf.'' {{Cite book|last=Gershevitch|first=Ilya|chapter=Old Iranian Literature|title=Handbuch der Orientalistik, Literatur I|year=1968|location=Leiden|publisher=Brill|pages=1–31|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}, p. 2.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
[[File:Aria Waldseemuller 1507.png|right|200px|thumb|The region ''[[Aria (satrapy)|Aria]]'' as depicted by [[Waldseemuller]] in 1507]]

The term ''Aryan'' originates from the [[Sanskrit]] word ''[[ārya]]'', in origin an ethnic self-designation, in Classical Sanskrit meaning &quot;honourable, respectable, noble&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[Monier-Williams]] (1899).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Monier Williams Sanskrit-English Dictionary (2008 revision)|publisher=UNIVERSITÄT ZU KÖLN |url=http://www.sanskrit-lexicon.uni-koeln.de/monier/|accessdate=July 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 18th century, the most ancient known [[Indo-European languages]] were those of the [[Indo-Iranian peoples|Indo-Iranians]]' ancestors. The word ''Aryan'' was therefore adopted to refer not only to the Indo-Iranian people, but also to native Indo-European speakers as a whole, including the [[Greek language|Greeks]], [[Latin Europe|Latins]], and [[Germanic people|Germans]]. It was soon recognised that [[Armenians]], [[Baltic people|Balts]], [[Celtic people|Celts]], [[Albanians]] and [[Slavic people|Slavs]] also belonged to the same group. It was argued that all of these languages originated from a common root—now known as [[Proto-Indo-European language|Proto-Indo-European]]—spoken by an ancient people. The ethnic group composed of the [[Proto-Indo-Europeans]] and their modern descendants was termed the &quot;[[Aryan]]s&quot;.

This usage was common in the late 19th and early 20th century.  An example of an influential best-selling book that reflects this usage is the 1920 book ''[[The Outline of History]]'' by [[H. G. Wells]].&lt;ref&gt;Wells, H.G. ''[[The Outline of History]]'' New York:1920 Doubleday &amp; Co. Chapter 19 The Aryan Speaking Peoples in Pre-Historic Times Pages 271-285&lt;/ref&gt; Wells  wrote about the accomplishments of the Aryan people, stating how they &quot;learned methods of civilization&quot; while &quot;Sargon II and Sardanapalus were ruling in Assyria and fighting with Babylonia and Syria and Egypt&quot;. As such, Wells suggested that the Aryans had eventually &quot;subjugated the whole ancient world, Semitic, Aegean and Egyptian alike&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bartleby.com/86/19.html H.G. Wells describes the origin of the Aryans (Proto-Indo Europeans):]&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1944 edition of [[Rand McNally]]’s World Atlas, the Aryan race is depicted as being one of the ten major racial groupings of mankind.&lt;ref&gt;''Rand McNally’s World Atlas International Edition'' Chicago:1944 Rand McNally  Map: &quot;Races of Mankind&quot; Pages 278–279--In the explanatory section below the map, the Aryan race (the word “Aryan” being defined in the description below the map as a synonym for “Indo-Europeans”) is described as being one of the ten major racial groupings of mankind.  Each of the ten racial groupings is depicted in a different [[color]] on the map and the estimated populations in 1944 of the larger racial groups except the Dravidians are given (the Dravidian population in 1944 would have been about 70,000,000).  The other nine groups are depicted as being the [[Semitic|Semitic race]] (the Aryans (850,000,000) and the Semites (70,000,000) are described as being the two main branches of the [[Caucasian race]]), the [[Dravidian race]], the [[Mongoloid race|Mongolian race]] (700,000,000), the [[Malayan race]] (Correct population given on page 413--64,000,000 including besides the populations of the Dutch East Indies, the Philippines, and Madagascar also half of the Malay States, Micronesia, and Polynesia), the [[Indigenous people of the Americas|American Indian race]] (10,000,000), the [[Black people|Negro race]] (140,000,000), the [[Australoid race|Native Australians]], the [[Australoid race|Papuans]], and the [[Capoid race|Hottentots and Bushmen]].&lt;/ref&gt; The [[science fiction]] [[author]] [[Poul Anderson]] (1926–2001), an [[Anti-racism|anti-racist]] [[Libertarianism|libertarian]] of [[Scandinavia]]n ancestry, in his many [[novel]]s, [[novella]]s, and [[Short story|short stories]], consistently used the term ''Aryan'' as a synonym  for ''Indo-Europeans''. He spoke of the ''Aryan bird of prey'' which impelled those of the Aryan race to take the lead in developing [[interstellar travel]], [[Colonization of space#Outside the Solar System|colonize]] [[habitable planet]]s in other [[planetary systems]] and become leading business [[entrepreneur]]s on the newly colonized [[planet]]s.&lt;ref&gt;See, for example, the Poul Anderson short stories in the 1964 collection [[Time and Stars]] and the ''Polesotechnic League'' stories featuring [[Nicholas van Rijn]]&lt;/ref&gt;

The use of &quot;Aryan&quot; as a synonym for &quot;Indo-European&quot; or to a lesser extent for &quot;Indo-Iranian&quot;, is regarded today by many{{who|date=September 2012}} as obsolete and [[political correctness|politically incorrect]], but may still occasionally appear in material based on older scholarship, or written by persons accustomed to older usage, such as in a 1989 article in ''[[Scientific American]]'' by [[Colin Renfrew]] in which he uses the word &quot;Aryan&quot; in its traditional meaning as a synonym for &quot;Indo-European&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Renfrew, Colin. (1989). The Origins of Indo-European Languages. /Scientific American/, 261(4), 82-90.&lt;/ref&gt; However, the term [[Indo-Aryan languages|Indo-Aryan]] is still commonly used to describe the Indic half of the [[Indo-Iranian languages]], i.e. the family that includes Sanskrit and modern languages such as [[Hindi]], [[Urdu]] and [[Bengali language|Bengali]].

== 19th-century physical anthropology ==
{{Main|Caucasian race}}
{{See also|Scientific racism}}

[[File:Meyers b11 s0476a.jpg|thumb|450px|The 4th edition of [[Meyers Konversationslexikon]] ([[German Empire|Leipzig, 1885-1890]]) shows the ''[[Caucasian race]]'' (in various shades of grayish blue-green) as comprising ''Aryans'','' [[Semitic race|Semites]]'', and ''[[Hamitic|Hamites]]''. ''Aryans'' are further subdivided into ''European Aryans'' and ''Indo-Aryans'' (the term &quot;Indo-Aryans&quot; was then used to describe those now called [[Indo-Iranians]]).]]

In 19th century [[physical anthropology]], represented by some as being [[scientific racism]], the &quot;Aryan race&quot; was defined as the subgroup of the [[Caucasian race|Caucasian]] (or Europid) race consisting of the native speakers of [[Indo-European languages]] descended from the original [[Proto-Indo-Europeans]], that in [[Modern history|modern times]] reside in [[Northern India]], [[Sri Lanka]], [[Maldives]], [[Pakistan]], [[Gujarat]], [[Maharashtra]], [[Eastern India]], [[Bangladesh]], [[Nepal]], [[Northeast India]], [[Europe]], [[Asian Russia]], [[Anglo-America]], [[Quebec]], [[Southern South America]], [[South Africa]], [[Australia]] and [[New Zealand]], [[Armenia]], [[Iran]], and in [[Afghanistan]] and [[Tadzhikistan]],   .&lt;ref&gt;''Rand McNally’s World Atlas International Edition'' Chicago:1944 Rand McNally  Map: &quot;Races of Mankind&quot; Pages 278–279 The domain of the Aryan race is shown as extending throughout the regions mentioned above.&lt;/ref&gt;

The original 19th-century and early 20th-century use of the term ''Aryan'' referred to &quot;the early speakers of Proto-Indo European and their descendents&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Mish, Frederic C., Editor in Chief ''Webster's Tenth New Collegiate Dictionary'' Springfield, Massachuetts, U.S.A.:1994--Merriam-Webster Page 66&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Joseph Pomeroy Widney|Widney, Joseph P]] ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=s9UKAAAAIAAJ&amp;printsec=titlepage Race Life of the Aryan Peoples]'' New York: Funk &amp; Wagnalls. 1907 In Two Volumes: Volume One--''The Old World'' Volume Two--''The New World'' ISBN B000859S6O&lt;/ref&gt; [[Max Müller]] is often identified as the first writer to speak of an Aryan &quot;[[:wikt:race|race]]&quot; in English. In his ''Lectures on the Science of Language'' in 1861&lt;ref name=Orsucci/&gt; he referred to Aryans as a &quot;race of people&quot;. At the time, the term ''race'' had the meaning of &quot;a group of tribes or peoples, an ethnic group&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[OED]] under
race, ''n.''&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt; I.1.c has &quot;A group of several tribes or peoples, regarded as forming a distinct ethnic set. Esp. used in 19th-cent. anthropological classification, sometimes in conjunction with linguistic groupings.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

When Müller's statement was interpreted to imply a biologically distinct sub-group of humanity, he soon clarified that he simply meant a line of descent, insisting that it was very dangerous to mix linguistics and anthropology. &quot;The Science of Language and the [[Science]] of Man cannot be kept too much asunder&amp;nbsp;... I must repeat what I have said many times before, it would be wrong to speak of Aryan blood as of [[Cephalic index|dolichocephalic]] grammar&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Speech before the University of Stassbourg, 1872, Chaudhuri, Nirad, ''Scholar Extraordinary: The Life of Professor the Rt. Hon. Freidrich Max Muller'', Chatto and Windus, 1974, p.313&lt;/ref&gt; He restated his opposition to this method in 1888 in his essay ''Biographies of words and the home of the Aryas''.&lt;ref name=Orsucci&gt;Andrea Orsucci, &quot;[http://www.unifi.it/riviste/cromohs/3_98/orsucci.html Ariani, indogermani, stirpi mediterranee: aspetti del dibattito sulle razze europee (1870-1914)]&quot;, in ''[[Cromohs]]'', 1998 {{it icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Arthur de Gobineau.jpg|thumb|left|[[Arthur de Gobineau]], one of the key formulators of the theory of the &quot;Aryan race&quot;]]

Müller was responding to the development of racial anthropology, and the influence of the work of [[Arthur de Gobineau]] who argued that the Indo-Europeans represented a superior branch of humanity. A number of later writers, such as the French anthropologist [[Vacher de Lapouge]] in his book ''L'Aryen'', argued that this superior branch could be identified biologically by using the cephalic index (a measure of head shape) and other indicators. He argued that the long-headed &quot;dolichocephalic-blond&quot; Europeans, characteristically found in northern Europe, were natural leaders, destined to rule over more &quot;brachiocephalic&quot; (short headed) peoples.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1086/210895|last=Vacher de Lapouge (trans Clossen, C)|first=Georges |title=Old and New Aspects of the Aryan Question|journal=The American Journal of Sociology|volume= 5| issue = 3|pages=329–346|year=1899}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The division of the Caucasian race into Aryans, Semites and Hamites is in origin linguistic, not based on physical anthropology, the division in physical anthropology being that into [[Nordic race|Nordic]], [[Alpine race|Alpine]] and [[Mediterranean race|Mediterranean]]. However, the linguistic classification of &quot;Aryan&quot; later became closely associated, and conflated, with the classification of &quot;Nordic&quot; among some archaeologists and anthropologists.

This claim became increasingly important during the 19th century. In the mid-19th century, it was commonly believed that the Aryans originated in the southwestern [[steppe]]s of present-day [[Russia]]. However, by the late 19th century the steppe theory of Aryan origins was challenged by the view that the Aryans originated in ancient Germany or [[Scandinavia]], or at least that in those countries the original Aryan ethnicity had been preserved. The German origin of the Aryans was especially promoted by the archaeologist [[Gustaf Kossinna]], who claimed that the Proto-Indo-European peoples were identical to the [[Corded Ware culture]] of Neolithic Germany. This idea was widely circulated in both intellectual and popular culture by the early twentieth century,&lt;ref&gt;Arvidsson, Stefan (2006). Aryan Idols. USA: University of Chicago Press, 143. ISBN 0-226-02860-7.&lt;/ref&gt; and is reflected in the concept of &quot;[[Corded-Nordics]]&quot; in [[Carleton S. Coon]]'s 1939 ''[[The Races of Europe (1939 book)|The Races of Europe]]''.

Other anthropologists contested such claims. In Germany, [[Rudolf Virchow]] launched a study of [[craniometry]], which prompted him to denounce &quot;Nordic mysticism&quot; in the 1885 Anthropology Congress in [[Karlsruhe]], while [[Josef Kollmann]]&lt;!-- see [[:de:Josef Kollmann]] --&gt;, a collaborator of Virchow, stated in the same congress that the people of Europe, be they English, German, French, and Spaniard belonged to a &quot;mixture of various races,&quot; furthermore declaring that the &quot;results of craniology...[are] against any theory concerning the superiority of this or that European race&quot; to others.&lt;ref name=Orsucci&gt;Andrea Orsucci, &quot;[http://www.unifi.it/riviste/cromohs/3_98/orsucci.html Ariani, indogermani, stirpi mediterranee: aspetti del dibattito sulle razze europee (1870-1914)], ''[[Cromohs]]'', 1998 {{it icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Virchow's contribution to the debate sparked a controversy. [[Houston Stewart Chamberlain]], a strong supporter of the theory of a superior Aryan race, attacked Josef Kollmann arguments in detail. While the &quot;Aryan race&quot; theory remained popular, particularly in Germany, some authors defended Virchow's perspective, in particular [[Otto Schrader (philologist)|Otto Schrader]], [[Rudolph von Jhering]] and the ethnologist [[Robert Hartmann]] (1831–1893), who proposed to ban the notion of &quot;Aryan&quot; from anthropology.&lt;ref name=Orsucci/&gt;

== Indo-Aryan migration ==
{{Main|Indo-Aryan migration}}
{{See also|Out of India theory}}

Models of the Indo-Aryan migration discuss scenarios of [[prehistoric migrations]] of the early [[Indo-Aryans]] to their historically attested areas of settlement in the northwest of the [[Indian subcontinent]] and from there further across all of [[North India]]. Claims of [[Indo-Aryan peoples|Indo-Aryan]] migration are primarily drawn from [[natural language|linguistic]]&lt;ref&gt;The Quest for the Origins of Vedic Culture: The Indo-Aryan Migration Debate, Edwin Bryant, 2001&lt;/ref&gt; evidence but also from a multitude of data stemming from genetics,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Bijal P|last=Trivedi|title=Genetic evidence suggests European migrants may have influenced the origins of India's caste system|url=http://www.genomenewsnetwork.org/articles/05_01/Indo-European.shtml|work=Genome News Network|publisher=J. Craig Venter Institute|date=2001-05-14|accessdate=2005-01-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;(although more recent genetic studies cast doubt on the certitude of earlier claims),&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dnaindia.com/scitech/report_indians-are-one-people-descended-from-two-tribes_1292864 Indians are one people descended from two tribes]
[http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/news/india/Aryan-Dravidian-divide-a-myth-Study/articleshow/5053274.cms Aryan-Dravidian divide a myth: Study], [[Times of India]]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Vedic period|Vedic]] [[Historical Vedic religion|religion]], rituals, [[Vedas|poetics]] as well as some aspects of social organization and [[chariot]] technology.

All discussion of historical Indo-Aryan migrations or Aryan and [[Dravidian people|Dravidian]] races remains highly controversial in India to this day, and continues to affect political and religious debate. Some Dravidians, and supporters of the [[Dalitstan|Dalit movement]], most commonly [[Tamil people|Tamil]]s, claim that the worship of [[Shiva]] is a distinct Dravidian religion going back to the [[Indus Valley Civilization|Indus Civilization]],&lt;ref&gt;It is claimed that the Pashupati seal represents Shiva. J. Marshall 1931: Vol. 1, 52-55. Mohenjo-Daro and the IVC. London: Arthur Probsthain.&lt;/ref&gt; to be distinguished from [[Brahmin]]ical &quot;Aryan&quot; Hinduism. In contrast, the Indian nationalist [[Hindutva]] movement argues that no Aryan invasion or migration ever occurred, asserting that Vedic beliefs emerged from the [[Indus Valley Civilisation]],&lt;ref&gt;Although most pro-Aryan migration theory scholars also agree that a part of the IVC culture has influenced Hinduism. Renfrew says: &quot;it is difficult to see what is particularly non-Aryan about the Indus Valley Civilization. Renfrew 1988:188-190. Archaeology and Language. New York: Cambridge University Press&lt;/ref&gt; which pre-dated the supposed advent of the Indo-Aryans in India, and is identified as a likely candidate for a [[Proto-Dravidian]] culture.

Some Indians were also influenced by the debate about the Aryan race during the [[British Raj]]. The Indian nationalist [[V. D. Savarkar]] believed in the theory that an &quot;Aryan race&quot; migrated to India,&lt;ref&gt;Bryant 2001:271, Talageri 2000. The Rigveda.&lt;/ref&gt; but he didn't find much value in a [[racialized]] interpretation of the &quot;Aryan race&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;After all there is throughout this world so far as man is concerned but a single race - the human race, kept alive by one common blood, the human blood. All other talk is at best provisional, a makeshift and only relatively true. (...) Even as it is, not even the aborigines of the Andamans are without some sprinkling of the so-called Aryan blood in their veins and vice-versa. Truly speaking all that one can claim is that one has the blood of all mankind in one’s veins. The fundamental unity of man from pole to pole is true, all else only relatively so. Savarkar: &quot;Hindutva&quot;. Vinayak Damodar Savarkar, Savarkar Samagra: Complete Works of Vinayak Damodar Savarkar in 10 volumes, ISBN 81-7315-331-0&lt;/ref&gt; Some Indian nationalists supported the British version of the theory because it gave them the prestige of common descent with the ruling British class.&lt;ref&gt;Erdosy 1995:21, The Indo-Aryans of ancient South Asia.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Genetic anthropology of Indo-Aryan Migration ===

In a major study (2009) using over 500,000 biallelic autosomal markers, Reich hypothesized that the modern Indian population was the result of admixture between two genetically divergent ancestral populations dating from the post-Holocene era. These two &quot;reconstructed&quot; ancient populations he termed &quot;Ancestral South Indians&quot; (ASI) and &quot;Ancestral North Indians&quot; (ANI). According to Reich: &quot;ANI ancestry is significantly higher in Indo-European than Dravidian speakers, suggesting that the ancestral ASI may have spoken a Dravidian language before mixing with the ANI.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;nature.com&quot;&gt;[[Colin Humphreys]] and W. G. Waddington, &quot;Dating the Crucifixion ,&quot; Nature 306 (December 22/29, 1983), pp. 743-46.[http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v306/n5945/abs/306743a0.html]&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, Reich observes: &quot;It is tempting to assume that the population ancestral to ANI and CEU spoke 'Proto-Indo-European', which has been reconstructed as ancestral to both Sanskrit and European languages, although we cannot be certain without a date for ANI–ASI mixture.&quot; 

Similarly, an earlier study conducted by Watkins et al. (2008) states:&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;The historical record documents an influx of Vedic Indo-European-speaking immigrants into northwest India starting at least 3500 years ago. These immigrants spread southward and eastward into an existing agrarian society dominated by Dravidian speakers. With time, a more highly-structured patriarchal caste system developed. India is now broadly characterized by Indo-European (e.g. Hindi, Urdu, and Punjabi) speaking populations found in the central and northern regions and by Dravidian (e.g. Tamil, Telugu, and Kannada) speaking populations in the southern and southeastern regions. ... Although other interpretations may be possible, our data are consistent with a model in which nomadic populations from northwest and central Eurasia intercalated over millennia into an already complex, genetically diverse set of subcontinental populations. As these populations grew, mixed, and expanded, a system of social stratification likely developed in situ, spreading to the Indo-Gangetic plain, and then southward over the Deccan plateau. A strong patrilineal social structure, accompanied by a developing practice of caste endogamy, may have contributed to an asymmetric apportioning of Y-chromosome, autosomal, and to a lesser extent, mtDNA lineages.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2156/9/86/ABSTRACT%20/COMMENTS/ABSTRACT/ABSTRACT/ADDITIONAL/ Genetic variation in South Indian castes: evidence from Y-chromosome, mitochondrial, and autosomal polymorphisms]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

== Occultism ==
=== Theosophy ===
[[Image:Blavatsky and Olcott.jpg|thumb|280px|Mme. [[Helena Blavatsky|Blavatsky]] and [[Henry Steel Olcott]], a lawyer, agricultural expert, and journalist who covered the [[Spiritualist]] phenomena.]]
{{Main|Root race}}

The [[Theosophy|Theosophical]] movement founded by [[Madame Blavatsky|Helena Blavatsky]] and [[Henry Steel Olcott|Henry Olcott]] at the end of the nineteenth century took inspiration from Indian culture, in this case, perhaps, from the Hindu reform movement the [[Arya Samaj]] founded by [[Swami Dayananda]].
Blavatsky argued that humanity had descended from a series of &quot;[[Root Race]]s&quot;, naming the fifth root race (out of seven) the Aryan Race. She thought that the [[Aryan]]s originally [[The Secret Doctrine#Volume two|came from]] [[Atlantis]] and described the Aryan races with the following words:

:&quot;The Aryan races, for instance, now varying from dark brown, almost black, red-brown-yellow, down to the whitest creamy colour, are yet all of one and the same stock -- the Fifth [[Root-Race]] -- and spring from one single progenitor, (...) who is said to have lived over 18,000,000 years ago, and also 850,000 years ago -- at the time of the sinking of the last remnants of the great continent of [[Atlantis]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Blavatsky, [[The Secret Doctrine|The Secret Doctrine, the Synthesis of Science, Religion and Philosophy]], Vol.II, p.249&lt;/ref&gt;

Blavatsky used &quot;[[Root Race]]&quot; as a technical term to describe human evolution over the large [[time]] periods in her [[cosmology]]. However, she also claimed that there were modern non-Aryan peoples who were inferior to Aryans. She regularly contrasts &quot;Aryan&quot; with &quot;[[Semitic]]&quot; culture, to the detriment of the latter, asserting that Semitic peoples are an offshoot of Aryans who have become &quot;degenerate in spirituality and perfected in materiality.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Blavatsky, ''The Secret Doctrine'', Vol II, p. 200&lt;/ref&gt; She also states that some peoples are &quot;semi-animal creatures&quot;. These latter include &quot;the Tasmanians, a portion of the Australians and a mountain tribe in China.&quot; There are also &quot;considerable numbers of the mixed Lemuro-Atlantean peoples produced by various crossings with such semi-human stocks -- e.g., the wild men of Borneo, the Veddhas of Ceylon, most of the remaining Australians, Bushmen, Negritos, Andaman Islanders, etc.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Blavatsky, ''The Secret Doctrine'', Vol II, pp. 195-6&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite this, Blavatsky's admirers claim that her thinking was not connected to fascist or racialist ideas, asserting that she believed in a [[Universal Brotherhood]] of humanity and wrote that &quot;all men have spiritually and physically the same origin&quot; and that &quot;mankind is essentially of one and the same essence&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''The Key to Theosophy'', Section 3&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, in ''The Secret Doctrine'', Blavatsky states: &quot;Verily mankind is 'of one blood,' but not of the same essence.&quot;

Blavatsky connects physical race with spiritual attributes constantly throughout her works:
:&quot;Esoteric history teaches that idols and their worship died out with the Fourth Race, until the survivors of the hybrid races of the latter (Chinamen, African Negroes, &amp;c.) gradually brought the worship back. The Vedas countenance no idols; all the modern Hindu writings do&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Blavatsky, ''The Secret Doctrine'', Vol. II, p.723&lt;/ref&gt;

:&quot;The intellectual difference between the Aryan and other civilized nations and such savages as the [[South Sea Islanders]], is inexplicable on any other grounds. No amount of culture, nor generations of training amid civilization, could raise such human specimens as the [[Bushmen]], the [[Veddhas]] of [[Ceylon]], and some [[African Tribes|African tribes]], to the same intellectual level as the Aryans, the [[Semites]], and the [[Turanian]]s so called. The 'sacred spark' is missing in them and it is they who are the only inferior races on the globe, now happily -- owing to the wise adjustment of nature which ever works in that direction -- fast dying out. Verily mankind is 'of one blood,' but not of the same essence. We are the hot-house, artificially quickened plants in nature, having in us a spark, which in them is latent&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Blavatsky, ''The Secret Doctrine'', Vol II, p 421&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Blavatsky, &quot;the MONADS of the lowest specimens of humanity (the &quot;narrow-brained&quot; savage South-Sea Islander, the African, the Australian) had no Karma to work out when first born as men, as their more favoured brethren in intelligence had&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Blavatsky, ''The Secret Doctrine'', Vol II, p.168&lt;/ref&gt;

She also prophecies of the destruction of the racial &quot;failures of nature&quot; as the future &quot;higher race&quot; ascends:
:&quot;Thus will mankind, race after race, perform its appointed cycle-pilgrimage. Climates will, and have already begun, to change, each tropical year after the other dropping one sub-race, but only to beget another higher race on the ascending cycle; while a series of other less favoured groups -- the failures of nature -- will, like some individual men, vanish from the human family without even leaving a trace behind&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Blavatsky, ''The Secret Doctrine'', Vol II, p.446&lt;/ref&gt;

The second subrace of the Fifth or Aryan root race, the Arabian, is regarded by Theosophists as one of the Aryan subraces. It is believed by Theosophists that the Arabians, although asserted in traditional Theosophy to be of Aryan (i.e., Indo-European) ancestry, adopted the [[Semitic language]] of the people around them who had migrated earlier from Atlantis (the fifth or (original) Semite subrace of the Atlantean [[root race]]). Theosophists assert that the [[Jews]] originated as an offshoot of the Arabian subrace in what is now [[Yemen]] about 30,000 BC.  They migrated first to [[Somalia]] and then later to [[Egypt]] where they lived until the time of [[Moses]]. Thus, according to the teachings of Theosophy, the Jews are part of the Aryan race.&lt;ref&gt;Powell, A.E. ''The Solar System: A Complete Outline of the Theosophical Scheme of Evolution'' London:1930 The Theosophical Publishing House  Pages 298-299&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Samael Aun Weor]] published a book in 1967 retitled in 2008 ''The Doomed Aryan Race'' in which he asserted that the Aryan &quot;Root Race&quot; is doomed to be destroyed by [[hydrogen bomb]]s unless the people of the Aryan race learn [[tantric yoga]].&lt;ref&gt;1967 - Christmas Message 1967-1968: ''The Solar Bodies and Gnostic Wisdom'' (in Spanish), published in English as ''The Doomed Aryan Race'' in 2008 ISBN 1-934206-30-X&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Ariosophy ===
{{Main|Ariosophy}}
[[Image:Swastika solarsymbol.svg|thumb|The [[swastika]] is a version of the [[sun cross]] that was adopted as a symbol of the Aryan race in the early 20th century in [[Esotericism in Germany and Austria|German occultism]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The first time the swastika was used with an &quot;Aryan&quot; meaning was on December 25, 1907, when the self-named [[Order of the New Templars]], a secret society founded by [Adolf Joseph] Lanz von Liebenfels, hoisted at Werfenstein Castle ([[Austria]]) a yellow flag with a swastika and four [[Fleur-de-lys|fleurs-de-lys]].&quot; José Manuel Erbez. &quot;[http://flagspot.net/flags/de%7Dns_or.html#ont Order of the New Templars 1907]&quot;. ''[[Flags of the World]]''. January 21, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt; and after the end of World War I it became a &quot;symbol of Aryan conquest and mastery&quot; in the ''[[völkisch]]'' movement.&lt;ref&gt;Robert Lavenda, [http://www.stcloudstate.edu/affirmativeaction/resources/insights/pdf/Insights-Vol2-Issue4.pdf &quot;A History of Swastikas&quot;], Insights For A Diverse Campus Community, St. Cloud State University, Volume II, Issue 4, Spring 2005, page 3 .&lt;/ref&gt;]]
[[Guido von List]] (and his followers such as [[Lanz von Liebenfels]]) later took up some of Blavatsky's ideas, mixing her ideology with nationalistic and fascist ideas; this system of thought became known as [[Ariosophy]]. It was believed in Ariosophy that the [[Germanic languages|Teutonic]]s were superior to all other peoples because according to Theosophy the Teutonics or Nordics were the most recent subrace of the Aryan root race to have evolved.&lt;ref&gt;Goodrick-Clarke, Nicholas ''The Occult Roots of Nazism: Secret Aryan Cults and Their Influence on Nazi Ideology'' New York:1992 New York University Press Chapter 13 &quot;Herbert Reichstein and Ariosophy&quot; Pages 164-176&lt;/ref&gt; Such views also fed into the development of Nazi ideology.  Theosophical publications such as ''[[The Aryan Path]]'' were strongly opposed to the Nazi usage, attacking [[Racism|racialism]].

== Nazism and Neo-Nazism ==
=== Nazism ===
{{Further|Nazism and race}}
[[File:ArnoBrekerDiePartei.jpg|thumb|250px|right|[[Arno Breker]]'s 1939 neoclassical sculpture ''Die Partei'' (The Party) encapsulated [[National Socialist]] ideals of Aryanism, with ''Die Partei'' as the physical embodiment of the spirit of the [[Nazi Party]].]]
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1979-105-02, Berlin, Ehrenhof der Neuen Reichskanzlei.jpg|thumb|250px|right|[[Arno Breker]]'s 1939 twin symbolic Aryan statues at the entrance to the [[Reich Chancellery]], ''Partei'' (Party) and ''Wehrmacht'' (Army).]]

The idea of the Northern origins of the Aryans was particularly influential in [[Germany]]. It was widely believed that the &quot;Vedic Aryans&quot; were ethnically identical to the [[Goths]], [[Vandals]] and other ancient Germanic peoples of the ''[[Völkerwanderung]]''. This idea was often intertwined with [[antisemitic]] ideas. The distinctions between the &quot;Aryan&quot; and &quot;[[Semitic]]&quot; peoples were based on the aforementioned linguistic and ethnic history.

Semitic peoples came to be seen as a foreign presence within Aryan societies, and the Semitic peoples were often pointed to as the cause of conversion and destruction of social order and values leading to culture and civilization's downfall by proto-Nazi and Nazi theorists such as [[Houston Stewart Chamberlain]] and [[Alfred Rosenberg]].

According to the adherents to [[Ariosophy]], the Aryan was a &quot;[[master race]]&quot; that built a civilization that dominated the world from [[Atlantis]] about 10,000 years ago. This alleged civilization declined when other parts of the world were colonized after the 8000 BC destruction of [[Atlantis]] because the inferior races mixed with the Aryans but it left traces of their civilization in [[Tibet]] (via [[Buddhism]]), and even in [[Central America]], [[South America]], and [[Ancient Egypt]]. (The date of 8000 BC for the destruction of [[Atlantis]] in [[Ariosophy]] is 2,000 years later than the date of 10,000 BC given for this event in [[Theosophy]].) These theories affected the more esotericist strand of Nazism.

A complete, highly speculative theory of Aryan and anti-Semitic history can be found in [[Alfred Rosenberg]]'s major work, ''[[The Myth of the Twentieth Century]]''. Rosenberg's well-researched account of ancient history, melded with his racial speculations, proved to be very effective in spreading racialism among German intellectuals in the early twentieth century, especially after the [[World War I|First World War]].

These and other ideas evolved into the [[Nazism|Nazi]] use of the term &quot;Aryan race&quot; to refer to what they saw as being a [[master race]], which was narrowly defined by the Nazis as being identical with the [[Nordic race]], followed by other sub-races of the Aryan race. They worked to maintain the purity of this race through [[Nazi eugenics|eugenics]] programs (including [[Miscegenation|anti-miscegenation]] legislation, [[compulsory sterilization]] of the mentally ill and the mentally deficient, the execution of the institutionalized mentally ill as part of a [[T-4 Euthanasia Program|euthanasia program]]).

[[Heinrich Himmler]] (the ''[[Reichsführer]]'' of the [[SS]]), the person ordered by [[Adolf Hitler]] to implement the [[Final Solution]], or [[The Holocaust]],&lt;ref&gt;Himmler noted on 26 July 1942 in response to Rosenberg’s attempt to influence Jewish policy that &quot;The occupied territories will be [[Judenfrei|Jew-free]].  The [[Fuhrer]] has laid the implementation of this very difficult order on my shoulders.&quot; [[Richard J. Evans|Evans, Richard J.]] ''The Third Reich at War'' New York:2008 Penguin Page 271; Himmler had begun the initial pre-[[Wansee Conference]] implementation of the [[final solution]] by July and August of 1941. [[Richard J. Evans|Evans, Richard J.]] ''The Third Reich at War'' New York:2008 Penguin Page 240.&lt;/ref&gt; told his personal masseur [[Felix Kersten]] that he always carried with him a copy of the ancient [[Aryan]] scripture, the [[Bhagavad Gita]] because it relieved him of [[guilt (emotion)|guilt]] about what he was doing – he felt that like the warrior [[Arjuna]], he was simply doing his duty without attachment to his actions.&lt;ref&gt;Padfield, Peter ''Himmler'' New York:1990--Henry Holt Page 402&lt;/ref&gt;

Himmler was also interested in Buddhism and his institute ''[[Ahnenerbe]]'' sought to mix some traditions from Hinduism and Buddhism&lt;ref&gt;P.7, ''New Religions and the Nazis'', By Karla Powne&lt;/ref&gt; – [[Gautama Buddha]]'s original name for the religion we now call ''[[Buddhism]]'' was ''The Aryan Path''.&lt;ref&gt;Wells, H.G. ''[[The Outline of History]]'' New York:1920 Doubleday &amp; Co. See chapter on Gautama Buddha&lt;/ref&gt; Himmler sent a [[1939 German Expedition to Tibet|1939 German expedition to Tibet]] as part of his research into Aryan origins.

In 1936 biologists [[Julian Huxley]] and [[Alfred Court Haddon]] famously ridiculed the Nazi idea of the superior Aryan race, writing: 
{{quote|&quot;Thus our German neighbors have ascribed to themselves a Teutonic type that is fair, long-headed, tall, slender, unemotional, brave straightforward, gentle, and virile. Let us make a composite picture of a typical Teuton from the most prominent of the exponents of this view. Let him be physically as blond and mentally as unemotional as Hitler, physically as long-headed and mentally as direct as Rosenberg, as tall and truthful as Goebbels, as slender and gentle as Goering, and as manly and straightforward as Streicher.&quot;|&quot;We Europeanse&quot; p. 171}}

=== Neo-Nazism ===
[[Image:Crossed circle.svg|thumb|right|The [[Sun cross|sun wheel]] is used as the symbol of the Aryan race.]]

Since the military defeat of [[Nazi Germany]] by the [[Allies]] in 1945, most [[Neo-Nazism|neo-Nazis]] have expanded their concept of the Aryan race, moving from the Nazi concept that the purest Aryans were the Teutonics or [[Nordic race|Nordics]] of Northern Europe to the idea that the true Aryans are everyone descended from the Western or [[Europe]]an branch of the [[Proto-Indo-Europeans|Indo-European peoples]] because it is believed that they most closely resemble the original racial stock of the [[Proto-Indo-Europeans]].  Although admitting that those of the Eastern or [[Indo-Iranians|Indo-Iranian]] branch of the Indo-European peoples are &quot;Aryans&quot; in name, it is felt that they are not really true Aryans because it is believed that the [[Iranian peoples]] are mostly too intermixed with the [[Arabs]] and  [[Mongols]], and the [[Indo-Aryans]] are mostly too intermixed with the [[Dravidians]], to still be pure Aryans.&lt;ref&gt;Goodrick-Clarke, Nicholas ''[[Black Sun (Goodrick-Clarke book)|Black Sun]]: Aryan Cults, Esoteric Nazism, and The Politics of Identity'' New York: 2002--N.Y. University Press, See Chapter 15 for a discussion of ''Aryan [[identity politics]]''&lt;/ref&gt;

Moderate [[white nationalists]] who embrace  what is called ''Pan-Aryanism'' want to establish a [[Democracy|democratically governed]] ''Aryan Federation.''&lt;ref&gt;[http://forums.skadi.net/showthread.php?p=940600 Fundamentals of Pan-Aryanism:]&lt;/ref&gt; It is envisioned that the [[North America]]n part of the &quot;Aryan Federation&quot; would be a new nation for [[Anglo-America#Anglo-American ethnic group|Euro-Anglo Americans]] ([[European Americans]] and [[English Canadians]]) called ''Vinland'' which would include what is now the northern [[United States]] and all of [[Canada]] except [[Quebec]], and which would use the [[Vinland flag]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vinlandfolkresistance.com/ Vinland Folk Resistance website:]&lt;/ref&gt;

On the other hand, according to [[Nicholas Goodrick-Clarke]], many neo-Nazis want to establish an [[Autocracy|autocratic state]] modeled after [[Nazi Germany]] to be called the ''Western Imperium''. It is believed this proposed state would be able to attain [[Hyperpower|world domination]] by combining the [[nuclear arsenal]]s of the four major Aryan [[world power]]s, the [[United States]], the [[United Kingdom]], [[France]], and [[Russia]] under a single [[military command]].&lt;ref name=&quot;GC&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Goodrick-Clarke, Nicholas|title=Black Sun: Aryan Cults, Esoteric Nazism and the Politics of Identity|publisher=New York University Press|location=New York|year=2003|pages=221|isbn=0-8147-3155-4|oclc = |doi=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This proposed state would be led by a ''[[Führer]]''-like figure called the ''Vindex'', and would include all areas inhabited by the &quot;Aryan race&quot;, as conceived by Neo-Nazis. Only those of the Aryan race would be full citizens of the state. The &quot;Western Imperium&quot; would embark on a vigorous and dynamic program of [[space exploration]], followed by the creation by [[genetic engineering]] of a  [[super race]] called [[Super race#Homo Galactica|Homo Galactica]]. The concept of the &quot;Western Imperium&quot; as outlined in the previous three sentences is based on the original concept of the ''Imperium'' as outlined in the 1947 book ''Imperium: The Philosophy of History and Politics'' by [[Francis Parker Yockey]] as further updated, extended and refined in the early 1990s in pamphlets published by [[David Myatt]].&lt;ref&gt;Goodrick-Clarke, Nicholas ''[[Black Sun (Goodrick-Clarke book)|Black Sun]]: Aryan Cults, Esoteric Nazism, and The Politics of Identity'' New York: 2002--N.Y. University Press, See Chapters 4 and 11 for extensive information about the proposed &quot;Western Imperium&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://blogs.myspace.com/index.cfm?fuseaction=blog.view&amp;friendId=423609919&amp;blogId=497426085 “Vindex—The Destiny of the West—Imperium of the West” by David Myatt:]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.natvan.com/national-vanguard/130/index.html &quot;Space Exploration: An Expression of the Aryan Soul&quot; by John Clarke [[National Vanguard (publication)|National Vanguard]] magazine Issue 130, January–February 2006:]&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Tempelhofgesellschaft ====
A [[neo-Nazi]] [[Esoteric Nazism|esoteric Nazi]] [[Gnostic]] sect headquartered in [[Vienna, Austria]] called the ''[[Neo-volkisch movements#Tempelhofgesellschaft|Tempelhofgesellschaft]]'', founded in the early 1990s, teaches a form of what it calls [[Marcionism]]. They distribute pamphlets claiming that the Aryan race originally came to [[The Secret Doctrine#Volume two|Atlantis]] from the star [[Aldebaran]].

== See also ==
*[[Anatolian hypothesis]]
*[[Aryan]]
*[[Germanic peoples]]
*[[Indo-Aryan migrations]]
*[[Indo-Iranians]]
*[[Iranian peoples]]
*[[Nordic theory]]
*[[Nordic race]]
*[[Proto-Indo-Europeans]]
*[[Indo-European language family]]
*[[Kurgan hypothesis]]
*[[R1a1a]]
*[[Race Life of the Aryan Peoples]]
*[[SLC24A5]]
*[[Scandinavism]]
*[[White nationalism]]
*[[White supremacy]]

===Philosophical===
*[[Esotericism in Germany and Austria]]
*[[Thule Society]]
*[[Germanic Neopaganism]]
*[[Neo-völkisch movements]]
As opposed to:
*[[Soviet people]]
*[[Zhonghua minzu]]

===Third Reich specific===
*[[Aryanization]]
*[[Aryan paragraph]]
*[[Honorary Aryan]]
*[[Ahnenpass]]
*[[Aryan Games]]

===Contemporaneous concepts of race===
*[[Alpine race]]
*[[Armenoid race]]
*[[Dinaric race]]
*[[East Baltic race]]
*[[Iranid race]]
*[[Mediterranean race]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== Further reading ==
*[[The Arctic Home in the Vedas]] by [[Bal Gangadhar Tilak]]
*[[Stefan Arvidsson|Arvidsson, Stefan]]. ''Aryan Idols. The Indo-European Mythology as Science and Ideology.'' Chicago: University of Chicago Press. 2006 ISBN 0-226-02860-7
*[[Leon Poliakov|Poliakov, Leon]]. ''The Aryan Myth: A History of Racist and Nationalistic Ideas In Europe'' New York: Barnes &amp; Noble Books. 1996 ISBN 0-7607-0034-6
*{{Cite book |title=Defending the Master Race: Conservation, Eugenics, and the Legacy of [[Madison Grant]] |last=Spiro |first=Jonathan P. |publisher=Univ. of Vermont Press |year=2009 |isbn=978-1-58465-715-6 |laysummary=http://www.upne.com/1-58465-715-4.html |laydate=29 September 2010 |ref=harv }}
*[[Joseph Pomeroy Widney|Widney, Joseph P]] ''[[Race Life of the Aryan Peoples]]'' New York: Funk &amp; Wagnalls. 1907 In Two Volumes: Volume One--''The Old World''  Volume Two--''The New World'' ISBN B000859S6O:
**[http://books.google.com/books?id=okNDAAAAIAAJ&amp;oe=UTF-8 Race Life of the Aryan Peoples Vol.1--&quot;The Old World&quot;:]
**[http://books.google.com/books?id=s9UKAAAAIAAJ&amp;printsec=titlepage Race Life of the Aryan Peoples Vol.2--&quot;The New World&quot;:]

== External links ==
*[http://www.wisdomworld.org/additional/ListOfCollatedArticles/TheAryanRace.html The Aryan race]
*[http://www.bookrags.com/Indo-European_languages Indo-European Languages]
*[http://kpearson.faculty.tcnj.edu/Dictionary/aryan.htm Aryan by Kim Pearson]
*[http://www.nvtc.gov/lotw/months/february/IranianBranch.html Iranian Branch of the Indo-European Family]
*[http://www.farhangsara.com/races.htm Races and Ethnic Groups of Iran]
*[http://www.port.ac.uk/departments/academic/biology/research/forensicanthropology/ Forensic Anthropology]

{{Historical definitions of race}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Aryan Race}}
[[Category:Esoteric anthropogenesis]]
[[Category:Indo-European]]
[[Category:Historical definitions of race]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Nazism]]
[[Category:Nazi terminology]]
[[Category:Neo-Nazism]]
[[Category:Race (human classification)]]
[[Category:White supremacy]]
[[Category:Nazi propaganda]]

[[ar:جنس آري]]
[[az:Ariçilik]]
[[bg:Арийска раса]]
[[ca:Raça ària]]
[[cs:Árijská rasa]]
[[et:Aarja rass]]
[[es:Raza aria]]
[[fr:Race aryenne]]
[[gl:Raza aria]]
[[hi:आर्य वंश]]
[[hr:Arijska rasa]]
[[it:Razza ariana]]
[[he:הגזע הארי]]
[[hu:Árja fajelmélet]]
[[mk:Ариевска раса]]
[[nl:Arische ras]]
[[ja:アーリアン学説]]
[[pt:Raça ariana]]
[[ru:Арийская раса]]
[[simple:Aryan race]]
[[sr:Аријевска раса]]
[[tr:Ari ırk]]
[[uk:Арійська раса]]
[[zh:雅利安人]]</text>
      <sha1>5807uy5tvediou6e68idunico0l62re</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
