<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of the Alamo</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>501984</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520471057</id>
      <parentid>520470413</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-29T19:10:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sriharsh1234</username>
        <id>17348405</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edit(s) by [[Special:Contributions/206.77.0.158|206.77.0.158]] identified as test/vandalism using [[WP:STiki|STiki]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="69807">{{Redirect|Remember the Alamo|the song|Remember the Alamo (song)}}
{{Redirect6|Alamo|the site of this battle|Alamo Mission in San Antonio}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Battle of the Alamo
|partof=the [[Texas Revolution]]
|image=[[File:1854 Alamo.jpg|300px|alt=The crumbling facade of a stone building is missing its roof and part of its second floor. A pile of stone rubble sits in the courtyard. In front of the building are a horse-drawn carriage and several people in 1850s-style clothing: women in long dresses with full skirts and men in fancy suits with top hats.]]
|caption=The Alamo, as drawn in 1854.
|date=February 23 &amp;nbsp;– March 6, 1836
|place=modern-day [[San Antonio]], [[Texas]], USA
|result=Mexican victory
|combatant1={{flag|Mexico|1823}}
|combatant2={{flag|Republic of Texas}}
|commander1={{flagicon|Mexico|1823}}[[Antonio López de Santa Anna]]
|commander2={{flagicon|Republic of Texas}}[[William B. Travis|William Travis]]{{KIA}}&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Republic of Texas}}[[James Bowie]]{{KIA}}
|strength1=approx. 1,800&lt;ref name=&quot;tsha&quot;&gt;[http://www.tshaonline.org/handbook/online/articles/qea02 Texas State Historical Association]&lt;/ref&gt;
|strength2=189-257&lt;ref name=&quot;tsha&quot;/&gt;
|casualties1=approx. 600&lt;ref name=&quot;tsha&quot;/&gt;
|casualties2=189-257&lt;ref name=&quot;tsha&quot;/&gt;}}
{{Campaignbox Texas Revolution}}
The '''Battle of the Alamo''' (February 23&amp;nbsp;– March 6, 1836) was a pivotal event in the [[Texas Revolution]]. Following a [[siege of the Alamo|13-day siege]], Mexican troops under [[president of Mexico|President]] [[Antonio López de Santa Anna|General Antonio López de Santa Anna]] launched an assault on the [[Alamo Mission in San Antonio|Alamo Mission]] near [[San Antonio de Béxar]] (modern-day San Antonio, Texas, USA). All but two of the [[Texian]] defenders were killed. Santa Anna's perceived cruelty during the battle inspired many Texians—both Texas settlers and adventurers from the United States—to join the Texian Army. Buoyed by a desire for revenge, the Texians defeated the Mexican Army at the [[Battle of San Jacinto]], on April 21, 1836, ending the revolution.

Several months previously, Texians had driven all Mexican troops out of [[Mexican Texas]]. Approximately 100&amp;nbsp;Texians were then garrisoned at the [[Legacy of the Battle of the Alamo|Alamo]]. The Texian force grew slightly with the arrival of reinforcements led by eventual Alamo co-commanders [[James Bowie]] and [[William B. Travis]]. On February 23, approximately 1,500 Mexican troops marched into San Antonio de Béxar as the first step in a campaign to re-take Texas. For the next 12 days the two armies engaged in several skirmishes with minimal casualties. Aware that his garrison could not withstand an attack by such a large force, Travis wrote multiple letters pleading for more men and supplies, but fewer than 100 reinforcements arrived.

In the early morning hours of March 6, the Mexican Army advanced on the Alamo. After repulsing two attacks, Texians were unable to fend off a third attack. As Mexican soldiers scaled the walls, most of the Texian soldiers withdrew into interior buildings. Defenders unable to reach these points were slain by the Mexican cavalry as they attempted to escape. Between five and seven Texians may have surrendered; if so, they were quickly executed. Most eyewitness accounts reported between 182 and 257 Texians dead, while most historians of the Alamo agree that 400–600 Mexicans were killed or wounded. Several noncombatants were sent to [[Gonzales, Texas|Gonzales]] to spread word of the Texian defeat. The news sparked a panic, known as &quot;The Runaway Scrape&quot;, in which the Texian army, most settlers, and the new [[Republic of Texas]] government fled from the advancing Mexican Army.

Within Mexico, the battle has often been overshadowed by events from the [[Mexican–American War]] of 1846–48. In 19th-century Texas, the Alamo complex gradually became known as a battle site rather than a former mission. The Texas Legislature purchased the land and buildings in the early part of the 20th century and designated the Alamo chapel as an official Texas State Shrine. The [[Legacy of the Battle of the Alamo|Alamo]] is now &quot;the most popular tourist site in Texas&quot;.&lt;ref name=gronemanbattle52&gt;Groneman (1998), p. 52.&lt;/ref&gt; The Alamo has been the subject of numerous non-fiction works beginning in 1843. Most Americans, however, are more familiar with the myths spread by many of the movie and television adaptations,&lt;ref name=nofi213&gt;Nofi (1992), p. 213.&lt;/ref&gt; including the 1950s [[The Walt Disney Company|Disney]] miniseries ''[[Davy Crockett (TV miniseries)|Davy Crockett]]'' and [[John Wayne]]'s 1960 film ''[[The Alamo (1960 film)|The Alamo]]''.

==Background==
{{Further|Mexican Texas|Texas Revolution}}

Under President [[Antonio López de Santa Anna]], the Mexican government began to shift away from a [[federalism|federalist]] model. The increasingly dictatorial policies, including the revocation of the [[Constitution of 1824]] in early 1835, incited many federalists to revolt.&lt;ref name=todish6&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt; The Mexican border region of [[Mexican Texas|Texas]] was largely populated by immigrants from the United States. These were accustomed to a federalist government and to extensive individual rights, and they were quite vocal in their displeasure at Mexico's shift towards centralism.&lt;ref&gt;Henson (1982), p. 96.&lt;/ref&gt; Already leery of previous American attempts to purchase Texas,&lt;ref name=edmondson78&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 78.&lt;/ref&gt; Mexican authorities blamed much of the Texian unrest on American immigrants, most of whom had made little effort to adapt to the Mexican culture.&lt;ref name=barr4&gt;Barr (1990), p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt;

In October, Texians engaged Mexican troops in the first official battle of the [[Texas Revolution]].&lt;ref name=barr56/&gt; Determined to quash the rebellion, Santa Anna began assembling a large force, the Army of Operations in Texas, to restore order.&lt;ref name=hardin98&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 98.&lt;/ref&gt; Most of his soldiers were raw recruits,&lt;ref name=hardin99&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 99.&lt;/ref&gt; and a large number had been forcibly [[conscript]]ed.&lt;ref name=todish20&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 20.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Fall-of-the-alamo-gentilz 1844.jpg|right|thumb|The ''Fall of the Alamo'', painted by Theodore Gentilz in 1844, depicts the Alamo complex from the south. The Low Barracks, the chapel, and the wooden palisade connecting them are in the foreground.|alt=A sprawling complex of buildings with low walls sits in a shallow valley overlooked by rolling hills.|300px]]
The [[Texian]]s systematically defeated the Mexican troops already stationed in Texas. The last group of Mexican soldiers in the region—commanded by Santa Anna's brother-in-law, General [[Martín Perfecto de Cos]]—surrendered on December 9 following the [[siege of Béxar]].&lt;ref name=barr56&gt;Barr (1990), p. 56.&lt;/ref&gt; By this point, the [[Texian Army]] was dominated by very recent arrivals to the region, primarily adventurers from the United States. Many Texas settlers, unprepared for a long campaign, had returned home.&lt;ref name=barr63/&gt; Angered by what he perceived to be American interference in Mexican affairs, Santa Anna [[wikt:spearhead|spearheaded]] a resolution classifying foreigners found fighting in Texas as [[pirate]]s. The resolution effectively banned the taking of prisoners of war: in this period of time, captured pirates were executed immediately.&lt;ref name=barr63&gt;Barr (1990), p. 63.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=scott71&gt;Scott (2000), p. 71.&lt;/ref&gt; Santa Anna reiterated this message in a strongly worded letter to United States President [[Andrew Jackson]]. This letter was not widely distributed, and it is unlikely that most of the American recruits serving in the Texian Army were aware that there would be no prisoners of war.&lt;ref name=scott74and75&gt;Scott (2000), pp. 74–75.&lt;/ref&gt;

When Mexican troops departed San Antonio de Béxar (now [[San Antonio|San Antonio, Texas, USA]]) Texian soldiers established a garrison at the [[Alamo Mission in San Antonio|Alamo Mission]], a former [[Spanish missions in Texas|Spanish religious outpost]] which had been converted to a makeshift fort.&lt;ref name=edmondson129/&gt; Described by Santa Anna as an &quot;irregular fortification hardly worthy of the name&quot;,&lt;ref name=edmondson129&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 129.&lt;/ref&gt; the Alamo had been designed to withstand an attack by native tribes, not an artillery-equipped army.&lt;ref name=edmondson128&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 128.&lt;/ref&gt; The complex sprawled across {{convert|3|acre|ha}}, providing almost {{convert|1320|ft|m}} of perimeter to defend.&lt;ref name=edmondson131/&gt; An interior plaza was bordered on the east by the chapel and to the south by a one-story building known as the Low Barracks.&lt;ref name=myers181/&gt; A wooden palisade stretched between these two buildings.&lt;ref name=todish10&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt; The two-story Long Barracks extended north from the chapel.&lt;ref name=myers181&gt;Myers (1948), p. 181.&lt;/ref&gt; At the northern corner of the east wall stood a cattle pen and horse corral.&lt;ref name=edmondson364&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 364.&lt;/ref&gt; The walls surrounding the complex were at least {{convert|2.75|ft|m}} thick and ranged from {{convert|9|-|12|ft|m|abbr=on}} high.&lt;ref name=myers180&gt;Myers (1948), p. 180.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=Note&gt;The plaza covered an area {{convert|75|ft|m}} long and {{convert|62|ft|m}} wide. The Low Barracks was {{convert|114|ft|m}} long, and the Long Barracks was {{convert|186|ft|m}} long and {{convert|18|ft|m}} wide. (Myers (1948), pp. 180–81.)&lt;/ref&gt;

To compensate for the lack of firing ports, Texian engineer Green B. Jameson constructed catwalks to allow defenders to fire over the walls; this method, however, left the rifleman's upper body exposed.&lt;ref name=edmondson131&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 131.&lt;/ref&gt; Mexican forces had left behind 19&amp;nbsp;cannons, which Jameson installed along the walls. A large 18-pounder had arrived in Texas with the New Orleans Greys. Jameson positioned this cannon in the southwest corner of the compound. He boasted to Texian Army commander [[Sam Houston]] that the Texians could &quot;whip 10 to 1 with our artillery&quot;.&lt;ref name=hardin111&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 111.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Texian garrison was woefully under-manned and under-provisioned, with fewer than 100&amp;nbsp;soldiers remaining by January 6, 1836.&lt;ref name=todish29&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 29.&lt;/ref&gt; Colonel [[James C. Neill]], the acting Alamo commander, wrote to the [[Consultation (Texas)|provisional government]]: &quot;If there has ever been a dollar here I have no knowledge of it&quot;.&lt;ref name=todish29/&gt; Neill requested additional troops and supplies, stressing that the garrison was likely to be unable to withstand a siege lasting longer than four days.&lt;ref name=todish29/&gt;&lt;ref name=todish30&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 30.&lt;/ref&gt; The Texian government was in turmoil and unable to provide much assistance.&lt;ref name=todish31&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=Note&gt;A week after Neill sent his letter, the Texian provisional legislature impeached [[Henry Smith (Texas Governor)|the governor]], who in turn disbanded the legislature. The interim constitution had given neither party the authority to take these actions, and no one in Texas was entirely sure who was in charge. (Todish ''et al.'' (1998), pp. 30–31.)&lt;/ref&gt; Four different men claimed to have been given command over the entire army:&lt;ref group=Note&gt;Houston, [[James Fannin]], [[Frank W. Johnson]], and Dr. James Grant. (Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 30.)&lt;/ref&gt; on January 14, Neill approached one of them, [[Sam Houston]], for assistance in gathering supplies, clothing, and ammunition.&lt;ref name=todish31/&gt;

==Prelude to battle==
[[File:Jimbowie.jpg|thumb|left|150px|upright|[[James Bowie]] arrived at the [[Alamo Mission]] on January 19 with orders to destroy the complex. He instead became the garrison's co-commander.|alt=Three-quarter portrait of a young clean-shaven man with long sideburns and a widow's peak hairline. His arms are crossed.]]
Houston could not spare the number of men necessary to mount a successful defense.&lt;ref name=edmondson252&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 252.&lt;/ref&gt; Instead, he sent Colonel [[James Bowie]] with 30 men to remove the artillery from the Alamo and destroy the complex.&lt;ref name=todish31/&gt;&lt;ref group=Note&gt;Houston's orders to Bowie were vague, and historians disagree on their intent. One interpretation is that Bowie's orders were to destroy only the barricades that the Mexican Army had erected around San Antonio de Béxar, and that he should then wait in the Alamo until Governor Henry Smith decided whether the mission should be demolished and the artillery removed. Smith never gave orders on this issue. (Edmondson (2000), p. 252.)&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie was unable to transport the artillery since the Alamo garrison lacked the necessary draft animals. Neill soon persuaded Bowie that the location held strategic importance.&lt;ref name=hopewell114&gt;Hopewell (1994), p. 114.&lt;/ref&gt; In a letter to Governor [[Henry Smith (Texas Governor)|Henry Smith]], Bowie argued that &quot;the salvation of Texas depends in great measure on keeping Béxar out of the hands of the enemy. It serves as the frontier picquet guard, and if it were in the possession of Santa Anna, there is no stronghold from which to repel him in his march toward the Sabine.&quot;&lt;ref name=hopewell115/&gt;&lt;ref group=Note&gt;The [[Sabine River (Texas-Louisiana)|Sabine River]] marked the eastern border of Mexican Texas.&lt;/ref&gt; The letter to Smith ended, &quot;Colonel Neill and myself have come to the solemn resolution that we will rather die in these ditches than give it up to the enemy.&quot;&lt;ref name=hopewell115&gt;Hopewell (1994), p. 115.&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie also wrote to the provisional government, asking for &quot;men, money, rifles, and cannon powder&quot;.&lt;ref name=hopewell115/&gt; Few reinforcements were authorized; cavalry officer [[William B. Travis]] arrived in Béxar with 30&amp;nbsp;men on February 3. Five days later, a small group of volunteers arrived, including the famous frontiersman and former U.S. Congressman [[Davy Crockett]] of Tennessee.&lt;ref name=hardin117&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 117.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna 1852.jpg|right|thumb|upright|General [[Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna]] led Mexican troops into Texas in 1836.|alt=Lithograph depicting head and shoulders of a middle-aged, clean-shaven man wearing an ostentatious military uniform.]]
On February 11, Neill left the Alamo, likely to recruit additional reinforcements and gather supplies.&lt;ref name=todish32&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 32.&lt;/ref&gt; He transferred command to Travis, the highest-ranking regular army officer in the garrison.&lt;ref name=hopewell115/&gt; Volunteers comprised much of the garrison, and they were unwilling to accept Travis as their leader.&lt;ref group=Note&gt;Volunteers in the Texian Army asserted the right to choose their own leaders, and most of them were unwilling to serve under officers of the regular army.&lt;/ref&gt; The men instead elected Bowie, who had a reputation as a fierce fighter, as their commander. Bowie celebrated by getting very intoxicated and creating havoc in Béxar. To mitigate the resulting ill feelings, Bowie agreed to share command with Travis.&lt;ref name=todish32/&gt;&lt;ref name=hopewell116&gt;Hopewell (1994), p. 116.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=hardin120&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 120.&lt;/ref&gt;

As the Texians struggled to find men and supplies, Santa Anna continued to gather men at [[San Luis Potosi]]; by the end of 1835 his army numbered 6,019 soldiers.&lt;ref name=hardin102/&gt; Rather than advance along the coast, where supplies and reinforcements could be easily delivered by sea, Santa Anna ordered his army inland to Béxar, the political center of Texas and the site of Cos's defeat.&lt;ref name=hardin102/&gt; The army began its march north in late December.&lt;ref name=hardin102&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 102.&lt;/ref&gt;  Officers used the long journey to train the men. Many of the new recruits did not know how to use the sights of their guns, and many refused to fire from the shoulder because of the large recoil.&lt;ref name=lord67&gt;Lord (1961), p. 67.&lt;/ref&gt;

Progress was slow. There were not enough mules to transport all of the supplies, and many of the teamsters, all civilians, quit when their pay was delayed. The large number of ''[[soldaderas]]''–women and children who followed the army–consumed the already scarce supplies. The soldiers were soon reduced to partial rations.&lt;ref name=hardin103&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 103.&lt;/ref&gt; On February 12 they crossed the [[Rio Grande]].&lt;ref name=lord73&gt;Lord (1961), p. 73.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=Note&gt;Although the Rio Grande now marks the border between Texas and Mexico, in this era the [[Nueces River]], several hundred miles north, was considered the southern boundary of Mexican Texas.&lt;/ref&gt; Temperatures in Texas reached record lows, and by February 13 an estimated {{convert|15|-|16|in|cm}} of snow had fallen. Hypothermia, dysentery, and [[Comanche]] raiding parties took a heavy toll on the Mexican soldiers.&lt;ref name=hardin105&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 105.&lt;/ref&gt;

On February 21, Santa Anna and his vanguard reached the banks of the [[Medina River]], {{convert|25|mi|km}} from Béxar.&lt;ref name=lord89&gt;Lord (1961), p. 89.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=todish36/&gt; Unaware of the Mexican Army's proximity, the majority of the Alamo garrison joined Béxar residents at a [[wikt:fiesta|fiesta]].&lt;ref name=nofi76&gt;Nofi (1992), p. 76.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=Note&gt;The fiesta was in celebration of the birthday of [[George Washington]], the first president of the United States.&lt;/ref&gt; After learning of the planned celebration, Santa Anna ordered General [[Joaquín Ramírez y Sesma]] to immediately seize the unprotected Alamo, but sudden rains halted that raid.&lt;ref name=todish36&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 36.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Siege==
{{Main|Siege of the Alamo}}

===Investment===
[[File:Texas Alamo Flag.svg|thumb|180px||right|The Alamo Flag]]
In the early hours of February 23, residents began fleeing Béxar, fearing the Mexican army's imminent arrival. Although unconvinced by the reports, Travis stationed a soldier in the [[San Fernando Cathedral|San Fernando church]] bell tower—the highest location in town—to watch for signs of an approaching force. Several hours later, Texian scouts reported seeing Mexican troops {{convert|1.5|mi|km}} outside the town.&lt;ref name=nofi76/&gt; Few arrangements had been made for a potential siege. One group of Texians scrambled to herd cattle into the Alamo, while others scrounged for food in the recently abandoned houses.&lt;ref name=edmondson299&gt;Edmondson (2000), pp. 299–301.&lt;/ref&gt; Several members of the garrison who had been living in town brought their families with them when they reported to the Alamo. Among these were [[Almaron Dickinson]], who brought his wife [[Susanna Dickinson|Susanna]] and their infant daughter Angelina; Bowie, who was accompanied by his deceased wife's cousins, Gertrudis Navarro and [[Juana Navarro Alsbury]], and Alsbury's young son;&lt;ref name=lord95&gt;Lord (1961), p. 95.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Gregorio Esparza]], whose family climbed through the window of the Alamo chapel after the Mexican army arrived.&lt;ref name=lord105&gt;Lord (1961), p. 105.&lt;/ref&gt; Other members of the garrison failed to report for duty; most of the men working outside Béxar did not try to sneak past Mexican lines.&lt;ref name=lindley89&gt;Lindley (2003), p. 89.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote box |width=30em |quote = I reply to you, according to the order of His Excellency, that the Mexican army cannot come to terms under any conditions with rebellious foreigners to whom there is no recourse left, if they wish to save their lives, than to place themselves immediately at the disposal of the Supreme Government from whom alone they may expect clemency after some considerations. |source =response of José Bartres to Texian requests for an honorable surrender, as quoted in the journal of [[Juan Almonte]]&lt;ref name=todish40and41&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), pp. 40–41.&lt;/ref&gt; |quoted = 1}}

By late afternoon Béxar was occupied by about 1,500 Mexican troops.&lt;ref name=todish40&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt; When the Mexican troops raised a blood-red flag signifying [[no quarter]], Travis responded with a blast from the Alamo's largest cannon.&lt;ref name=nofi78/&gt; Believing that Travis had acted hastily, Bowie sent Jameson to meet with Santa Anna.&lt;ref name=todish40and41/&gt; Travis was angered that Bowie had acted unilaterally and sent his own representative, Captain [[Albert Martin (soldier)|Albert Martin]].&lt;ref name=edmondson308&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 308.&lt;/ref&gt; Both emissaries met with Colonel [[Juan Almonte]] and José Bartres. According to Almonte, the Texians asked for an honorable surrender but were informed that any surrender must be unconditional.&lt;ref name=todish40and41/&gt; On learning this, Bowie and Travis mutually agreed to fire the cannon again.&lt;ref name=edmondson308/&gt;&lt;ref group=Note name=santaannafatality&gt;Although Santa Anna later reported that Texian cannon fire on February 23 killed two Mexican soldiers and wounded eight others, no other Mexican officer reported fatalities from that day. (Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 40., Edmondson (2000), p. 304.)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Skirmishes===
The first night of the siege was relatively quiet.&lt;ref name=edmondson310&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 310.&lt;/ref&gt; Over the next few days, Mexican soldiers established artillery batteries, initially about {{convert|1000|ft|m}} from the south and east walls of the [[Legacy of the Battle of the Alamo|Alamo]].&lt;ref name=nofi81&gt;Nofi (1992), p. 81.&lt;/ref&gt; A third battery was positioned southeast of the fort. Each night the batteries inched closer to the Alamo walls.&lt;ref name=todish43/&gt; During the first week of the siege more than 200 cannonballs landed in the Alamo plaza. At first the Texians matched Mexican artillery fire, often reusing the Mexican cannonballs.&lt;ref name=hardin132/&gt;&lt;ref name=petite34&gt;Petite (1999), p. 34.&lt;/ref&gt; On February 26 Travis ordered the artillery to conserve powder and shot.&lt;ref name=hardin132&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 132.&lt;/ref&gt;

Two notable events occurred on Wednesday, February 24. At some point that day, Bowie collapsed from illness,&lt;ref name=nofi80&gt;Nofi (1992), p. 80.&lt;/ref&gt; leaving Travis in sole command of the garrison.&lt;ref name=nofi80/&gt; Late that afternoon, a Mexican scout became the first fatality of the siege.&lt;ref name=todish42&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=Note name=santaannafatality/&gt; The following morning, 200–300 Mexican soldiers crossed the [[San Antonio River]] and took cover in abandoned shacks near the Alamo walls.&lt;ref name=todish43&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 43.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=todish42/&gt;&lt;ref name=tinkle118&gt;Tinkle (1985), p. 118.&lt;/ref&gt; Several Texians ventured out to burn the huts&lt;ref name=tinkle118/&gt; while Texians within the Alamo provided cover fire.&lt;ref name=lord109&gt;Lord (1961), p. 109.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=tinkle119/&gt; After a two-hour skirmish the Mexican troops retreated to Béxar.&lt;ref name=todish43/&gt;&lt;ref name=tinkle119&gt;Tinkle (1985), p. 119.&lt;/ref&gt; Two Mexican soldiers were killed and four wounded.&lt;ref name=todish43/&gt; No Texians were injured.&lt;ref name=tinkle120&gt;Tinkle (1985), p. 120.&lt;/ref&gt;

A [[cold wave|blue norther]] blew in on February 25, dropping the temperature to {{convert|39|F}}.&lt;ref name=hardin132/&gt; Neither army was prepared for the cold temperatures.&lt;ref name=nofi83&gt;Nofi (1992), p. 83.&lt;/ref&gt; Texian attempts to gather firewood were thwarted by Mexican troops.&lt;ref name=hardin132/&gt; On the evening of February 26 Colonel Juan Bringas engaged several Texians who were burning more huts.&lt;ref name=todish44&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 44.&lt;/ref&gt; According to historian J.R. Edmondson, one Texian was killed.&lt;ref name=edmondson325&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 325.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reinforcements===
{{Quote box |width=30em |quote = I am determined to sustain myself as long as possible &amp; die like a soldier who never forgets what is due to his own honor &amp; that of his country. VICTORY OR DEATH. |source =excerpt from [[William B. Travis]]'s letter [[To the People of Texas &amp; All Americans in the World]].&lt;ref&gt;Lord (1961), p. 14&lt;/ref&gt; |quoted = 1 }}

Santa Anna posted one company east of the Alamo, on the road to [[Gonzales, TX|Gonzales]].&lt;ref name=todish43/&gt;&lt;ref name=lord107&gt;Lord (1961), p. 107.&lt;/ref&gt; Almonte and 800&amp;nbsp;[[dragoon]]s were stationed along the road to [[Goliad, TX|Goliad]].&lt;ref name=scott102&gt;Scott (2000), p. 102.&lt;/ref&gt; Throughout the siege these towns had received multiple couriers, dispatched by Travis to plead for reinforcements and supplies.&lt;ref name=nofi78&gt;Nofi (1992), p. 78.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=myers200&gt;Myers (1948), p. 200.&lt;/ref&gt; The most famous of his missives, written February 24, was addressed [[To the People of Texas &amp; All Americans in the World]]. According to historian Mary Deborah Petite, the letter is &quot;considered by many as one of the masterpieces of American patriotism&quot;.&lt;ref name=petite88&gt;Petite (1998), p. 88.&lt;/ref&gt; Copies of the letter were distributed across Texas,&lt;ref name=petite90&gt;Petite (1998), p. 90.&lt;/ref&gt; and eventually reprinted throughout the United States and much of Europe.&lt;ref name=todish42/&gt; At the end of the first day of the siege, Santa Anna's troops were reinforced by 600 men under General [[Joaquin Ramirez y Sesma]], bringing the Mexican army up to more than 2,000 men.

As news of the siege spread throughout Texas, potential reinforcements gathered in Gonzales. They hoped to rendezvous with Colonel [[James Fannin]], who was expected to arrive from Goliad with his garrison.&lt;ref name=tinkle162&gt;Tinkle (1985), p. 162.&lt;/ref&gt; On February 26, after days of indecision, Fannin ordered 320&amp;nbsp;men, four&amp;nbsp;cannon, and several supply wagons to march toward the Alamo, {{convert|90|mi|km}} away. This group traveled less than {{convert|1.0|mi|km}} before turning back.&lt;ref name=edmondson324&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 324.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=nofi95&gt;Nofi (1992), p. 95.&lt;/ref&gt; Fannin blamed the retreat on his officers; the officers and enlisted men accused Fannin of aborting the mission.&lt;ref name=scott100and101&gt;Scott (2000), pp. 100–101.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:William b travis.JPG|upright|thumb|left|[[William B. Travis]] became sole Texian commander at the Alamo on February 24.|alt=Head and shoulders of a clean-shaven man with wavy hair. He wears a simple miiltary jacket, unbuttoned, with a star on the collar.]]
Texians gathered in Gonzales were unaware of Fannin's return to Goliad, and most continued to wait. Impatient with the delay, on February 27 Travis ordered Samuel G. Bastian to go to Gonzales &quot;to hurry up reinforcements&quot;.&lt;ref name=lindley130&gt;Lindley (2003), p. 130.&lt;/ref&gt; According to historian Thomas Ricks Lindley, Bastian encountered the [[Gonzales Ranging Company]] led by Lieutenant [[George C. Kimble]] and Travis' courier to Gonzales, Albert Martin, who had tired of waiting for Fannin. A Mexican patrol attacked, driving off four of the men, including Bastian.&lt;ref group=Note&gt;Colonel Juan Almonte's journal did not mention any skirmishes that evening. In 1837, Santa Anna's secretary Roman Martinez Caro did report &quot;two small reinforcements from Gonzales that succeeded in breaking through our lines and entering the fort. The first consisted of four men who gained the fort one night, and the second was a party of twenty-five.&quot; (Lindley (2003), p. 131.)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=lindley131&gt;Lindley (2003), p. 131.&lt;/ref&gt; In the darkness, the Texians fired on the remaining 32&amp;nbsp;men, whom they assumed were Mexican soldiers. One man was wounded, and his English curses convinced the defenders to open the gates.&lt;ref group=Note&gt;These Texian reinforcements were later dubbed the Immortal 32.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=edmondson340&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 340.&lt;/ref&gt;

On March 3, the Texians watched from the walls as approximately 1,000 Mexican troops marched into Béxar. The Mexican army celebrated loudly throughout the afternoon, both in honor of their reinforcements and at the news that troops under General [[José de Urrea]] had soundly defeated Texian Colonel [[Frank W. Johnson]] at the [[Battle of San Patricio]] on February 27.&lt;ref name=todish47&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 47.&lt;/ref&gt; Most of the Texians in the Alamo believed that Sesma had been leading the Mexican forces during the siege, and they mistakenly attributed the celebration to the arrival of Santa Anna. The reinforcements brought the number of Mexican soldiers in Béxar to almost 3,100.&lt;ref&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 349.&lt;/ref&gt;

The arrival of the Mexican reinforcements prompted Travis to send three men, including Davy Crockett, to find Fannin's force, which he still believed to be en route.&lt;ref name=lindley140&gt;Lindley (2003), p. 140.&lt;/ref&gt; The scouts discovered a large group of Texians camped {{convert|20|mi|km}} from the Alamo.&lt;ref name=lindley142/&gt; Lindley's research indicates that up to 50 of these men had come from Goliad after Fannin's aborted rescue mission. The others had left Gonzales several days earlier.&lt;ref name=lindley137and8&gt;Lindley (2003), pp. 137–38.&lt;/ref&gt; Just before daylight on March 4, part of the Texian force broke through Mexican lines and entered the Alamo. Mexican soldiers drove a second group across the prairie.&lt;ref name=lindley142&gt;Lindley (2003), p. 142.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=Note&gt;Almonte's journal reported that there was an engagement that night, but that the Mexican troops had repulsed the assault. (Lindley (2003), p. 143.)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Assault preparations===
On March 4, the day after his reinforcements arrived, Santa Anna proposed an assault on the Alamo. Many of his senior officers recommended that they wait for two 12-pounder cannons anticipated to arrive on March 7.&lt;ref name=todish48&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 48.&lt;/ref&gt; That evening, a local woman, likely Bowie's cousin-in-law [[Juana Navarro Alsbury]], approached Santa Anna to negotiate a surrender for the Alamo defenders.&lt;ref name=edmondson355&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 355.&lt;/ref&gt; According to many historians, this visit probably increased Santa Anna's impatience; as historian Timothy Todish noted, &quot;there would have been little glory in a bloodless victory&quot;.&lt;ref name=todish49&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt; The following morning, Santa Anna announced to his staff that the assault would take place early on March 6.  Santa Anna arranged for troops from Béxar to be excused from the front lines, so that they would not be forced to fight their own families.&lt;ref name=todish49/&gt;

Legend holds that at some point on March 5, Travis gathered his men and explained that an attack was imminent, and that the Mexican Army would prevail. He supposedly drew a [[line in the sand (phrase)|line in the ground]] and asked those willing to die for the Texian cause to cross and stand alongside him; only one man ([[Moses Rose]]) was said to have declined.&lt;ref name=hopewell126&gt;Hopewell (1994), p.&amp;nbsp;126.&lt;/ref&gt; Most scholars disregard this tale as there is no primary source evidence to support it (the story only surfaced decades after the battle in a third-hand account).&lt;ref name=chariton195&gt;Chariton (1992), p.&amp;nbsp;195.&lt;/ref&gt;  However, Travis apparently did, at some point prior to the final assault, assemble the men for a conference to inform them of the dire situation and giving them the chance to either escape or stay and die for the cause.  Susannah Dickinson recalled Travis announcing that any men who wished to escape should let it be known and step out of ranks.&lt;ref name=hardin985&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 124.&lt;/ref&gt;

The last Texian verified to have left the Alamo was James Allen, a courier who carried personal messages from Travis and several of the other men on March 5.&lt;ref&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 360.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Final assault==
===Exterior fighting===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center; margin:0 0 0.5em 1em; float:right&quot;
|+Initial Mexican troop deployment&lt;ref name=edmondson356&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 356.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=edmondson357&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 357.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
!Commander!!Troops!!Equipment
|-
|[[Martin Perfecto de Cos|Cos]]
|350
|10&amp;nbsp;ladders
2&amp;nbsp;crowbars
&lt;br /&gt;2&amp;nbsp;axes
|-
|Duque/[[Manuel Fernández Castrillón|Castrillón]]
|400
|10&amp;nbsp;ladders
|-
|Romero
|400
|6&amp;nbsp;ladders
|-
|Morales
|125
|2&amp;nbsp;ladders
|-
|[[Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna|Santa Anna]]
|400 reserves
|
|}
At 10&amp;nbsp;p.m. on March 5, the Mexican artillery ceased their bombardment. As Santa Anna had anticipated, the exhausted Texians soon fell into the first uninterrupted sleep many had gotten since the siege began.&lt;ref name=todish51&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 51.&lt;/ref&gt; Just after midnight Mexican troops began preparing for the final assault.&lt;ref name=edmondson362&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 362.&lt;/ref&gt; The troops were divided into four [[Column (formation)|columns]], commanded by Cos, Colonel Francisco Duque, Colonel José María Romero and Colonel Juan Morales.&lt;ref name=edmondson356/&gt;&lt;ref name=edmondson357/&gt; Veterans were positioned on the outside of the columns to better control the new recruits and conscripts in the middle.&lt;ref name=hardin138&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 138.&lt;/ref&gt; As a precaution, 500 Mexican cavalry were positioned around the Alamo to prevent escape of either Texian or Mexican soldiers. Santa Anna remained in camp with the 400 reserves.&lt;ref name=edmondson357/&gt;&lt;ref name=todish50&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 50.&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the bitter cold, the soldiers were ordered not to wear overcoats, which could impede their movements.&lt;ref name=edmondson357/&gt; Clouds concealed the moon, and thus the movements of the soldiers.&lt;ref name=lord160&gt;Lord (1961), p. 160.&lt;/ref&gt;

At 5:30&amp;nbsp;a.m. troops silently advanced. Cos and his men approached the northwest corner of the Alamo,&lt;ref name=&quot;hardin138&quot; /&gt; while Duque led his men from the northwest toward a repaired breach in the Alamo's north wall.&lt;ref name=hardin139&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 138-139.&lt;/ref&gt; The column commanded by Romero marched towards the east wall, and Morales's column aimed for the low parapet by the chapel.&lt;ref name=hardin139/&gt;

The three Texian sentinels stationed outside the walls were killed in their sleep,&lt;ref name=hardin139/&gt;&lt;ref name=tinkle196&gt;Tinkle (1985), p. 196.&lt;/ref&gt; allowing Mexican soldiers to approach undetected within musket range of the walls.&lt;ref name=hardin139/&gt; At this point, the silence was broken by shouts of ''&quot;¡Viva Santa Anna!&quot;'' and music from the buglers.&lt;ref name=edmondson362/&gt; The noise woke the Texians.&lt;ref name=tinkle196/&gt; Most of the noncombatants gathered in the church [[sacristy]] for safety.&lt;ref&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 363.&lt;/ref&gt; Travis rushed to his post yelling, &quot;Come on boys, the Mexicans are upon us and we'll give them hell!&quot;&lt;ref name=hardin139/&gt; and, as he passed a group of Tejanos, ''&quot;¡No rendirse, muchachos!&quot;'' (&quot;No surrender, boys&quot;).&lt;ref name=todish51/&gt;
[[File:AlamoplanF0385.jpg|thumb|right|250px|alt=A manuscript map with a diagram of the Alamo complex. Mexican artillery are shown positioned at the northwest, southwest, and south, with their projected trajectory reaching all of the north, west, and south walls.|This plan of the [[Alamo Mission in San Antonio|Alamo]] was created by José Juan Sánchez-Navarro in 1836. Places marked R and V denote Mexican cannon; position S indicates Cos's forces.]]

In the initial moments of the assault Mexican troops were at a disadvantage. Their column formation allowed only the front rows of soldiers to fire safely.&lt;ref name=todish52&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 52.&lt;/ref&gt; Unaware of the dangers, the untrained recruits in the ranks &quot;blindly fir[ed] their guns&quot;, injuring or killing the troops in front of them.&lt;ref name=petite113&gt;Petite (1998), p. 113.&lt;/ref&gt; The tight concentration of troops also offered an excellent target for the Texian artillery.&lt;ref name=todish52/&gt; Lacking [[canister shot]], Texians filled their cannon with any metal they could find, including door hinges, nails, and chopped-up horseshoes, essentially turning the cannon into giant shotguns.&lt;ref name=hardin139/&gt; According to the diary of [[José Enrique de la Peña]], &quot;a single cannon volley did away with half the company of chasseurs from [[Toluca]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=hardin146&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 146.&lt;/ref&gt; Duque fell from his horse after suffering a wound in his thigh and was almost trampled by his own men. General [[Manuel Fernández Castrillón|Manuel Castrillón]] quickly assumed command of Duque's column.&lt;ref name=edmondson364/&gt;

Although some in the front of the Mexican ranks wavered, soldiers in the rear pushed them on.&lt;ref name=todish52/&gt; As the troops massed against the walls, Texians were forced to lean over the walls to shoot, leaving them exposed to Mexican fire. Travis became one of the first defenders to die, shot while firing his shotgun into the soldiers below him.&lt;ref name=todish52/&gt; Few of the Mexican ladders reached the walls.&lt;ref name=hardin147&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 147.&lt;/ref&gt; The few soldiers who were able to climb the ladders were quickly killed or beaten back. As the Texians discharged their previously loaded rifles, however, they found it increasingly difficult to reload while attempting to keep Mexican soldiers from scaling the walls.&lt;ref name=edmondson364/&gt;

Mexican soldiers withdrew and regrouped, but their second attack was repulsed. Fifteen minutes into the battle, they attacked a third time.&lt;ref name=edmondson364/&gt;&lt;ref name=todish52/&gt; During the third strike, Romero's column, aiming for the east wall, was exposed to cannon fire and shifted to the north, mingling with the second column.&lt;ref name=edmondson364/&gt; Cos's column, under fire from Texians on the west wall, also veered north.&lt;ref name=todish53&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 53.&lt;/ref&gt; When Santa Anna saw that the bulk of his army was massed against the north wall, he feared a rout; &quot;panicked&quot;, he sent the reserves into the same area.&lt;ref name=petite112&gt;Petite (1998), p. 112.&lt;/ref&gt; The Mexican soldiers closest to the north wall realized that the makeshift wall contained many gaps and toeholds. One of the first to scale the 12-foot (3.7 m) wall was General [[Juan Valentín Amador|Juan Amador]]; at his challenge, his men began swarming up the wall. Amador opened the [[postern]] in the north wall, allowing Mexican soldiers to pour into the complex.&lt;ref name=&quot;hardin147&quot; /&gt; Others climbed through gun ports in the west wall, which had few defenders.&lt;ref name=edmondson366&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 366.&lt;/ref&gt; As the Texian defenders abandoned the north wall and the northern end of the west wall,&lt;ref name=&quot;hardin147&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=edmondson366/&gt; Texian gunners at the south end of the mission turned their cannon toward the north and fired into the advancing Mexican soldiers. This left the south end of the mission unprotected; within minutes Mexican soldiers had climbed the walls and killed the gunners, gaining control of the Alamo's 18-pounder cannon.&lt;ref name=&quot;lord160&quot; /&gt; By this time Romero's men had taken the east wall of the compound and were pouring in through the cattle pen.&lt;ref name=edmondson366/&gt;

===Interior fighting===
{{Quote box |width=30em |quote = Great God, Sue, the Mexicans are inside our walls! If they spare you, save my child |source =Last words of Texian defender [[Almaron Dickinson]] to his wife [[Susanna Dickinson|Susanna]] as he prepared to defend the chapel.&lt;ref name=todish53/&gt; |quoted = 1 }}

As previously planned, most of the Texians fell back to the barracks and the chapel. Holes had been carved in the walls to allow the Texians to fire.&lt;ref name=todish53/&gt; Unable to reach the barracks, Texians stationed along the west wall headed west for the San Antonio River. When the cavalry charged, the Texians took cover and began firing from a ditch. Sesma was forced to send reinforcements, and the Texians were eventually killed. Sesma reported that this skirmish involved 50&amp;nbsp;Texians, but Edmondson believes that number was inflated.&lt;ref name=edmondson368&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 368.&lt;/ref&gt;

The defenders in the cattle pen retreated into the horse corral. After discharging their weapons, the small band of Texians scrambled over the low wall, circled behind the church and raced on foot for the east prairie, which appeared empty.&lt;ref name=todish53/&gt;&lt;ref name=edmondson366/&gt;&lt;ref name=edmondson367/&gt; As the Mexican cavalry advanced on the group, Almaron Dickinson and his artillery crew turned a cannon around and fired into the cavalry, probably inflicting casualties. Nevertheless, all of the escaping Texians were killed.&lt;ref name=edmondson367&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 367.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:FalloftheAlamo.jpg|thumb|left|250px|''The Fall of the Alamo'' (1903) by Robert Jenkins Onderdonk, depicts [[Davy Crockett]] wielding his rifle as a club against Mexican troops who have breached the walls of the mission.|alt=A man in buckskin clothes holds a rifle over his head. He is surrounded by dead soldiers.]]
The last Texian group to remain in the open were Crockett and his men, defending the low wall in front of the church. Unable to reload, they used their rifles as clubs and fought with knives. After a volley of fire and a wave of Mexican [[bayonet]]s, the few remaining Texians in this group fell back toward the church.&lt;ref name=edmondson368/&gt; The Mexican army now controlled all of the outer walls and the interior of the Alamo compound except for the church and rooms along the east and west walls.&lt;ref name=edmondson369&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 369.&lt;/ref&gt; Mexican soldiers turned their attention to a Texian flag waving from the roof of one building. Four Mexicans were killed before the [[flag of Mexico]] was raised in that location.&lt;ref group=Note&gt;Lieutenant José Maria Torres is credited with successfully raising the Mexican flag; he was mortally wounded in the process. (Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 54.)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=todish54&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 54.&lt;/ref&gt;

For the next hour, the Mexican army worked to secure complete control of the Alamo.&lt;ref name=petite114&gt;Petite (1998), p. 114.&lt;/ref&gt; Many of the remaining defenders were ensconced in the fortified barracks rooms.&lt;ref name=edmondson370&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 370.&lt;/ref&gt; In the confusion, the Texians had neglected to [[wikt:spike#Verb|spike]] their cannon before retreating. Mexican soldiers turned the cannon toward the barracks.&lt;ref name=&quot;hardin147&quot;/&gt; As each door was blown off Mexican soldiers would fire a volley of muskets into the dark room, then charge in for [[hand-to-hand combat]].&lt;ref name=edmondson370/&gt;

Too sick to participate in the battle, Bowie likely died in bed. Eyewitnesses to the battle gave conflicting accounts of his death. Some witnesses maintained that they saw several Mexican soldiers enter Bowie's room, bayonet him, and carry him alive from the room.&lt;ref&gt;Groneman (1996), p.&amp;nbsp;214.&lt;/ref&gt; Others claimed that Bowie shot himself or was killed by soldiers while too weak to lift his head.&lt;ref name=hopewell127&gt;Hopewell (1994), p.&amp;nbsp;127.&lt;/ref&gt; According to historian Wallace Chariton, the &quot;most popular, and probably the most accurate&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Chariton (1992), p.&amp;nbsp;74.&lt;/ref&gt; version is that Bowie died on his cot, &quot;back braced against the wall, and using his pistols and his [[Bowie knife|famous knife]].&quot;&lt;ref name=hopewell127/&gt;

The last of the Texians to die were the 11 men manning the two 12-pounder cannon in the chapel.&lt;ref name=todish54/&gt;&lt;ref name=petite115&gt;Petite (1998), p. 115.&lt;/ref&gt; A shot from the 18-pounder cannon destroyed the barricades at the front of the church, and Mexican soldiers entered the building after firing an initial musket volley. Dickinson's crew fired their cannon from the [[apse]] into the Mexican soldiers at the door. With no time to reload, the Texians, including Dickinson, [[Gregorio Esparza]] and [[James Bonham]], grabbed rifles and fired before being bayoneted to death.&lt;ref name=edmondson371&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 371.&lt;/ref&gt; Texian Robert Evans, the master of ordnance, had been tasked with keeping the gunpowder from falling into Mexican hands. Wounded, he crawled toward the powder magazine but was killed by a musket ball with his torch only inches from the powder.&lt;ref name=edmondson371/&gt; Had he succeeded, the blast would have destroyed the church and killed the women and children hiding in the sacristy.&lt;ref name=tinkle216&gt;Tinkle (1985), p. 216.&lt;/ref&gt;

As soldiers approached the sacristy, one of the young sons of defender Anthony Wolf stood to pull a blanket over his shoulders.&lt;ref name=edmondson371/&gt; In the dark, Mexican soldiers mistook him for an adult and killed him.&lt;ref group=Note&gt;According to Edmondson, Wolf then ran into the room, grabbed his remaining son, and leaped with the child from the cannon ramp at the rear of the church; both were killed by musket shots before hitting the ground. (Edmondson (2000), p. 372.)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=edmondson372/&gt; Possibly the last Texian to die in battle was Jacob Walker,&lt;ref name=tinkle218&gt;Tinkle (1985), p. 218.&lt;/ref&gt; who attempted to hide behind [[Susannah Dickinson]] and was bayoneted in front of the women.&lt;ref name=lord166&gt;Lord (1961), p. 166.&lt;/ref&gt; Another Texian, Brigido Guerrero, also sought refuge in the sacristy.&lt;ref name=edmondson371/&gt; Guerrero, who had deserted from the Mexican Army in December 1835, was spared after convincing the soldiers he was a Texian prisoner.&lt;ref name=edmondson372&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 372.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=groneman55and56&gt;Groneman (1990), pp. 55–56.&lt;/ref&gt;

By 6:30&amp;nbsp;a.m. the battle for the Alamo was over.&lt;ref name=lord166/&gt; Mexican soldiers inspected each corpse, bayoneting any body that moved.&lt;ref name=edmondson372/&gt; Even with all of the Texians dead, Mexican soldiers continued to shoot, some killing each other in the confusion. Mexican generals were unable to stop the bloodlust and appealed to Santa Anna for help. Although the general showed himself, the violence continued and the buglers were finally ordered to sound a retreat. For 15&amp;nbsp;minutes after that, soldiers continued to fire into dead bodies.&lt;ref name=tinkle220&gt;Tinkle (1985), p. 220.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
===Casualties===
[[File:San Antonio 067.JPG|thumb|left|A [[Burial vault (tomb)|crypt]] in the [[San Fernando Cathedral]] purports to hold the ashes of the Alamo defenders. Historians believe it more likely that the ashes were buried near the Alamo.|alt=A white marble coffin sits on a ledge in front of stained glass windows. On the front of the coffin is a large 5-pointed star. Engraved within the star are the words &quot;Texas Heroes&quot; and small images of three men.]]
According to many accounts of the battle, between five and seven Texians surrendered.&lt;ref group=Note&gt;Edmondson speculates that these men might have been sick or wounded and were therefore unable to fight. (Edmondson (2000), p. 373)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=edmondson373&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 373.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=petite123&gt;Petite (1998), p. 123.&lt;/ref&gt; Incensed that his orders had been ignored, Santa Anna demanded the immediate execution of the survivors.&lt;ref name=hardin148&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 148.&lt;/ref&gt; Weeks after the battle, stories circulated that Crockett was among those who surrendered.&lt;ref name=petite123/&gt; However, Ben, a former American slave who cooked for one of Santa Anna's officers, maintained that Crockett's body was found surrounded by &quot;no less than sixteen Mexican corpses&quot;.&lt;ref name=tinkle214&gt;Tinkle (1985), p. 214.&lt;/ref&gt; Historians disagree on which version of Crockett's death is accurate.&lt;ref group=Note&gt;According to Petite (1998), p. 124, &quot;Every account of the Crockett surrender-execution story comes from an avowed antagonist (either on political or military grounds) of Santa Anna's. It is believed that many stories, such as the surrender and execution of Crockett, were created and spread in order to discredit Santa Anna and add to his role as villain.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=petite124&gt;Petite (1998), p. 124.&lt;/ref&gt;

Santa Anna reportedly told Captain Fernando Urizza that the battle &quot;was but a small affair&quot;.&lt;ref name=lord167&gt;Lord (1961), p. 167.&lt;/ref&gt; Another officer then remarked that &quot;with another such victory as this, we'll go to the devil&quot;.&lt;ref group=Note&gt;The identity of this officer is disputed. Edmondson (2000), p. 374 claims that this remark was made by Colonel Juan Almonte, and overheard by Almonte's cook, Ben. Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 55. attributes the remark to Lieutenant Colonel José Juan Sanchez Navarro.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=todish55/&gt; In his initial report Santa Anna claimed that 600&amp;nbsp;Texians had been killed, with only 70&amp;nbsp;Mexican soldiers killed and 300&amp;nbsp;wounded.&lt;ref name=edmondson374&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 374.&lt;/ref&gt; His secretary, Ramón Martínez Caro, later repudiated the report.&lt;ref name=hardin156&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 156.&lt;/ref&gt; Other estimates of the number of Mexican soldiers killed ranged from 60–200, with an additional 250–300&amp;nbsp;wounded.&lt;ref name=todish55/&gt; Most Alamo historians place the number of Mexican casualties at 400–600&amp;nbsp;Mexicans.&lt;ref name=todish55/&gt;&lt;ref name=hardin155&gt;Hardin (1961), p. 155.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=nofi136&gt;Nofi (1992), p. 136.&lt;/ref&gt; This would represent about one-third of the Mexican soldiers involved in the final assault, which Todish remarks is &quot;a tremendous casualty rate by any standards&quot;.&lt;ref name=todish55/&gt; Most eyewitnesses counted between 182–257&amp;nbsp;Texians killed.&lt;ref name=nofi133&gt;Nofi (1992), p. 133.&lt;/ref&gt; Some historians believe that at least one Texian, Henry Warnell, successfully escaped from the battle. Warnell died several months later of wounds incurred either during the final battle or during his escape as a courier.&lt;ref name=edmondson407&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 407.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Groneman (1990), p. 119.&lt;/ref&gt;

Mexican soldiers were buried in the local cemetery, Campo Santo.&lt;ref group=Note&gt;According to Francisco Ruiz, possibly the ''[[alcalde]]'' of Béxar, the graveyard was near full and that he instead threw some of the corpses in the river. (Edmondson (2000), p. 374.) However, Sam Houston reported on March 13 that all Mexicans were buried. (Lindley (2003), p. 277.)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=edmondson374/&gt;  Shortly after the battle, Colonel José Juan Sanchez Navarro proposed that a monument should be erected to the fallen Mexican soldiers.  Cos rejected the idea.&lt;ref name=petite134&gt;Petite (1998), p. 134.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Texian bodies were stacked and burned.&lt;ref group=Note&gt;Cremating bodies was anathema at the time, as most Christians believed that a body could not be resurrected unless it were whole. (Petite (1998), p. 139.)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=edmondson374/&gt; The only exception was the body of Gregorio Esparza. His brother Francisco, an officer in Santa Anna's army, received permission to give Gregorio a proper burial.&lt;ref name=edmondson374/&gt; The ashes were left where they fell until February 1837, when [[Juan Seguín]] returned to Béxar to examine the remains. A simple coffin inscribed with the names Travis, Crockett, and Bowie was filled with ashes from the funeral pyres.&lt;ref name=petite131&gt;Petite (1998), p. 131.&lt;/ref&gt; According to a March 28, 1837, article in the ''[[Telegraph and Texas Register]]'',&lt;ref name=chariton78&gt;Chariton (1990), p. 78.&lt;/ref&gt; Seguín buried the coffin under a peach tree grove. The spot was not marked and cannot now be identified.&lt;ref name=petite132&gt;Petite (1998), p. 132.&lt;/ref&gt; Seguín later claimed that he had placed the coffin in front of the altar at the [[San Fernando Cathedral]]. In July 1936 a coffin was discovered buried in that location, but according to historian Wallace Chariton it is unlikely to actually contain the remains of the Alamo defenders. Fragments of uniforms were found in the coffin, and it is known that the Alamo defenders did not wear uniforms.&lt;ref name=chariton78/&gt;

===Texian survivors===
{{Main|List of Texan survivors of the Battle of the Alamo}}
[[File:alamo77dickinson.jpg|thumb|right|upright|[[Susanna Dickinson]] survived the Battle of the Alamo. Santa Anna sent her to spread word of the Texian defeat to the Texas colonists.|alt=Portrait of an unsmiling, middle-aged woman in a voluminous dress. Her hair is piled on the back of her head, with ringlets near her ears. She holds a fan in her hands.]]
In an attempt to convince other slaves in Texas to support the Mexican government over the Texian rebellion, Santa Anna spared Travis's slave, Joe.&lt;ref name=petite128&gt;Petite (1998), p. 128.&lt;/ref&gt; The day after the battle, he interviewed each noncombatant individually. Impressed with Susanna Dickinson, Santa Anna offered to adopt her infant daughter Angelina and have the child educated in Mexico City. Dickinson refused the offer, which was not extended to Juana Navarro Alsbury for her son who was of similar age.&lt;ref name=todish55&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 55.&lt;/ref&gt; Each woman was given a blanket and two silver [[peso]]s.&lt;ref name=petite127&gt;Petite (1998), p. 127.&lt;/ref&gt; Alsbury and the other ''Tejano'' women were allowed to return to their homes in Béxar; Dickinson, her daughter and Joe were sent to Gonzales, escorted by Ben. They were encouraged to relate the events of the battle, and to inform the remainder of the Texian forces that Santa Anna's army was unbeatable.&lt;ref name=todish55/&gt;

===Impact on revolution===
During the siege, newly elected delegates from across Texas met at the [[Convention of 1836]]. On March 2, the delegates [[Texas Declaration of Independence|declared independence]], forming the [[Republic of Texas]]. Four days later, the delegates at the convention received a dispatch Travis had written March 3 warning of his dire situation. Unaware that the Alamo had fallen, Robert Potter called for the convention to adjourn and march immediately to relieve the Alamo. Sam Houston convinced the delegates to remain in [[Washington-on-the-Brazos]] to develop a constitution. After being appointed sole commander of all Texian troops, Houston journeyed to Gonzales to take command of the 400&amp;nbsp;volunteers who were still waiting for Fannin to lead them to the Alamo.&lt;ref name=edmondson375&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 375.&lt;/ref&gt;

Within hours of Houston's arrival on March 11, Andres Barcenas and Anselmo Bergaras arrived with news that the Alamo had fallen and all Texians were slain.&lt;ref name=nofi138&gt;Nofi (1992), p. 138.&lt;/ref&gt; Hoping to halt a panic, Houston arrested the men as enemy spies. They were released hours later when Susannah Dickinson and Joe reached Gonzales and confirmed the report.&lt;ref name=edmondson376&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 376.&lt;/ref&gt; Realizing that the Mexican army would soon advance toward the Texian settlements, Houston advised all civilians in the area to evacuate and ordered his new army to retreat.&lt;ref name=todish67&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 67.&lt;/ref&gt; This sparked a mass exodus, known as the [[Runaway Scrape]], and most Texians, including members of the new government, fled east.&lt;ref name=todish68&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 68.&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite their losses at the Alamo, the Mexican army in Texas outnumbered the Texian army by almost six to one.&lt;ref name=lord190&gt;Lord (1961), p. 190.&lt;/ref&gt; Santa Anna assumed that knowledge of the disparity in troop numbers and the fate of the Texian soldiers at the Alamo would quell the resistance,&lt;ref name=edmondson378/&gt; and that Texian soldiers would quickly leave the territory.&lt;ref name=hardin158&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 158.&lt;/ref&gt; News of the Alamo's fall had the opposite effect, and men flocked to Houston's army.&lt;ref name=edmondson378&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 378.&lt;/ref&gt; The ''[[New York Post]]'' editorialized that &quot;had [Santa Anna] treated the vanquished with moderation and generosity, it would have been difficult if not impossible to awaken that general sympathy for the people of Texas which now impels so many adventurous and ardent spirits to throng to the aid of their brethren&quot;.&lt;ref name=lord169&gt;Lord (1961), p. 169.&lt;/ref&gt;

On the afternoon of April 21 the Texian army attacked Santa Anna's camp near [[Lynchburg Ferry]]. The Mexican army was taken by surprise, and the [[Battle of San Jacinto]] was essentially over after 18&amp;nbsp;minutes. During the fighting, many of the Texian soldiers repeatedly cried &quot;Remember the Alamo!&quot;&lt;ref name=todish69&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 69.&lt;/ref&gt; Santa Anna was captured the following day, and reportedly told Houston: &quot;That man may consider himself born to no common destiny who has conquered the Napoleon of the West. And now it remains for him to be generous to the vanquished.&quot;&lt;ref name=todish70&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 70.&lt;/ref&gt; Houston replied, &quot;You should have remembered that at the Alamo&quot;.&lt;ref name=todish70/&gt; Santa Anna was forced to order his troops out of Texas, ending Mexican control of the province and giving some legitimacy to the new republic.&lt;ref name=todish70/&gt;

==Legacy==
{{Main|Legacy of the Battle of the Alamo}}
[[File:Alamo Village.jpg|left|thumb|Cenotaph of the Alamo defenders|Alamo Village, an active movie set and tourist attraction north of Brackettville, Texas.]]
Following the battle, Santa Anna was alternately viewed as a national hero or a pariah. Mexican perceptions of the battle often mirrored the prevailing viewpoint.&lt;ref name=glaser98&gt;Glaser (1985), p. 98.&lt;/ref&gt; Santa Anna had been disgraced following his capture at the Battle of San Jacinto, and many Mexican accounts of the battle were written by men who had been, or had become, his outspoken critics. Petite and many other historians believe that some of the stories, such as the execution of Crockett, may have been invented to further discredit Santa Anna.&lt;ref name=&quot;petite124&quot; /&gt; In Mexican history, the Texas campaign, including the Battle of the Alamo, was soon overshadowed by the [[Mexican–American War]] of 1846–48.&lt;ref name=glaser98/&gt;

[[File:AlamoMemorial-5478.jpg|right|thumb|Cenotaph of the Alamo defenders|alt=The rectangular base of a cenotaph. An angel is carved on one end. On the side are carvings of several men, shown wearing bucksin or 19th-century suits. Many hold guns or knives; at the far end, one operates a cannon.]]
In San Antonio de Béxar, the largely ''Tejano'' population viewed the Alamo complex as more than just a battlesite; it represented decades of assistance—as a mission, a hospital, or a military post.&lt;ref name=schoelwer18&gt;Schoelwer (1985), p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt; As the English-speaking population increased, the complex became best known for the battle. Focus has centered primarily on the Texian defenders, with little emphasis given to the role of the ''Tejano'' soldiers who served in the Texian army or the actions of the Mexican army.&lt;ref name=schoelwer52and56&gt;Schoelwer (1985), pp. 52, 56.&lt;/ref&gt; In the early 20th century the Texas Legislature purchased the property and appointed the [[Daughters of the Republic of Texas]] as permanent caretakers&lt;ref name=todish199&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 199.&lt;/ref&gt; of what is now an official state shrine.&lt;ref name=&quot;gronemanbattle52&quot;/&gt; In front of the church, in the center of Alamo Plaza, stands a [[cenotaph]], designed by [[Pompeo Coppini]], which commemorates the Texians and ''Tejanos'' who died during the battle.&lt;ref name=gronemanbattle56&gt;Groneman (1998), p. 56.&lt;/ref&gt; According to Bill Groneman's ''Battlefields of Texas'', the Alamo has become &quot;the most popular tourist site in Texas&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;gronemanbattle52&quot; /&gt;

[[File:Texas centennial half dollar commemorative reverse.jpg|thumb|left|This commemorative coin, marking 100 years since Texas declared independence from Mexico, includes the phrase &quot;Remember the Alamo&quot;.|alt=In the center of a circular coin is a kneeling angel with her arm draped over the Alamo chapel. Under each of her wings is a circular portrait with the head and shoulders of a man; on the left the portrait is labelled Houston, on the right it is labelled Austin. Along the edges of the coin are the words &quot;The Texas Independence Centennial&amp;nbsp;– Remember the Alamo&quot;.]]
The first English-language histories of the battle were written and published by [[Texas Ranger Division|Texas Ranger]] and amateur historian [[John Henry Brown]].&lt;ref name=lindley106&gt;Lindley (2003), p. 106.&lt;/ref&gt; The next major treatment of the battle was Reuben Potter's ''The Fall of the Alamo'', published in ''The Magazine of American History'' in 1878. Potter based his work on interviews with many of the Mexican survivors of the battle.&lt;ref name=lindley106/&gt;&lt;ref name=nofi211&gt;Nofi (1992), p. 211.&lt;/ref&gt; The first full-length, non-fiction book covering the battle, [[John Myers Myers]]' ''The Alamo'', was published in 1948.&lt;ref name=cox&gt;{{citation|last=Cox|first=Mike|title=Last of the Alamo big books rests with 'A Time to Stand'|newspaper=The Austin-American Statesman|date=March 6, 1998}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the decades since, the battle has featured prominently in many non-fiction works.

According to Todish ''et al.'', &quot;there can be little doubt that most Americans have probably formed many of their opinions on what occurred at the Alamo not from books, but from the various movies made about the battle.&quot;&lt;ref name=todish187&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 187.&lt;/ref&gt; The first film version of the battle appeared in 1911, when [[Gaston Méliès]] directed ''[[The Immortal Alamo]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;nofi213&quot;/&gt; The battle became more widely known after it was featured in the 1950s [[The Walt Disney Company|Disney]] miniseries ''[[Davy Crockett (TV miniseries)|Davy Crockett]]'', which was largely based on myth.&lt;ref name=&quot;nofi213&quot; /&gt; Within several years, [[John Wayne]] directed and starred in one of the best-known, but questionably accurate, film versions, 1960's ''[[The Alamo (1960 film)|The Alamo]]''.&lt;ref name=todish188&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 188.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=Note&gt;Historians [[James Frank Dobie|J. Frank Dobie]] and [[Lon Tinkle]] requested that they not be listed as historical advisers in the credits of ''The Alamo'' because of its disjunction from recognized history.(Todish ''et al.'', p. 188.)&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004 another film, also called ''[[The Alamo (2004 film)|The Alamo]]'', was released. [[CNN]] described it as possibly &quot;the most character-driven of all the movies made on the subject&quot;. It is also considered more faithful to the actual events than other movies.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Culpepper|first=Andy|title=A different take on 'The Alamo'|publisher=CNN|url=http://www.cnn.com/2004/SHOWBIZ/Movies/04/08/the.alamo/|date=April 8, 2004|accessdate=2008-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Modern popular culture===
A number of songwriters have been inspired by the Battle of the Alamo. [[Tennessee Ernie Ford]]'s &quot;[[The Ballad of Davy Crockett]]&quot; spent 16&amp;nbsp;weeks on the [[country music]] charts, peaking at No. 4 in 1955.&lt;ref name=todish194&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 194.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Marty Robbins]] recorded a version of the song &quot;The Ballad of the Alamo&quot; in 1960 which spent 13&amp;nbsp;weeks on the pop charts, peaking at No. 34.&lt;ref name=todish196&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 196.&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Jane Bowers]]' song &quot;[[Remember the Alamo (song)|Remember the Alamo]]&quot; has been recorded by artists including [[Johnny Cash]]&lt;ref name=Edwards148&gt;Edwards (2009), p. 148&lt;/ref&gt;  and [[Donovan]].&lt;ref name=Chemerka157&gt;Chemerka (2009), p. 157&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Texas}}
* [[List of Alamo defenders]]
* [[List of Texan survivors of the Battle of the Alamo]]
* [[List of Texas Revolution battles]]
* [[Last stand]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|group=Note|colwidth=40em}}

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=20em}}

==Bibliography==
* {{citation|last=Barr|first=Alwyn|title=Black Texans: A history of African Americans in Texas, 1528–1995|edition=2nd|publisher=[[University of Oklahoma Press]]|location=Norman, OK|year=1996|isbn=0-8061-2878-X}}
* {{citation|last=Barr|first=Alwyn|title=Texans in Revolt: the Battle for San Antonio, 1835|publisher=University of Texas Press|location=Austin, TX|year=1990|isbn=0-292-77042-1|oclc=20354408}}
* {{citation|last=Chariton|first=Wallace O.|title=Exploring the Alamo Legends|publisher=Republic of Texas Press|location=Dallas, TX|year=1990|isbn=978-1-55622-255-9}}
*{{citation|last=Chemerka|first=William H.|title=Music of the Alamo|year=2009|publisher=Bright Sky Press|isbn=978-1-933979-31-1|url=http://books.google.com/?id=orMAAQAAMAAJ&amp;dq=donovan+%22remember+the+alamo%22+bowers&amp;q=donovan++#search_anchor|coauthors=Allen J. Wiener | accessdate=2012-02-18}}
* {{citation|last=Edmondson|first=J.R.|title=The Alamo Story-From History to Current Conflicts|publisher=Republic of Texas Press|place=Plano, TX|isbn=1-55622-678-0|year=2000}}
*{{citation|last=Edwards|first=Leigh H.|title=Johnny Cash and the paradox of American identity|year=2009|publisher=Indiana UP|isbn=978-0-253-35292-7|url=http://books.google.com/?id=DOIecLTkHaIC&amp;pg=PA148&amp;dq=johnny+cash+%22remember+the+alamo%22#v=onepage&amp;q=johnny%20cash%20%22remember%20the%20alamo%22&amp;f=false| accessdate=2012-02-18}}
* {{citation|last=Glaser|first=Tom W.|title=Alamo Images: Changing Perceptions of a Texas Experience|publisher=The DeGlolyer Library and Southern Methodist University Press|year=1985|location=Dallas, TX|isbn=0-87074-213-2|editor-last=Schoelwer|editor-first=Susan Prendergast}}
* {{citation|last=Groneman|first=Bill|title=Alamo Defenders, A Genealogy: The People and Their Words|publisher=Eakin Press|place=Austin, TX|year=1990|isbn=0-89015-757-X}}
* {{Citation|last=Groneman|first=Bill|title=Eyewitness to the Alamo|publisher=Republic of Texas Press|year=1996|isbn=1-55622-502-4|location=Plano, TX}}
* {{citation|last=Groneman|first=Bill|title=Battlefields of Texas|publisher=Republic of Texas Press|location=Plano, TX|year=1998|isbn=978-1-55622-571-0}}
* {{citation|last=Hardin|first=Stephen L.|title=Texian Iliad|location=Austin, TX|publisher=[[University of Texas Press]]|year=1994|isbn=0-292-73086-1}}
* {{citation|last=Henson|first=Margaret Swett|title=Juan Davis Bradburn: A Reappraisal of the Mexican Commander of Anahuac|publisher=Texas A&amp;M University Press|location=College Station, TX|year=1982|isbn=978-0-89096-135-3}}
* {{citation|last=Hopewell|first=Clifford|title=James Bowie Texas Fighting Man: A Biography|publisher=Eakin Press|location=Austin, TX|year=1994|isbn=0-89015-881-9}}
* {{citation|last=Lindley|first=Thomas Ricks|title=Alamo Traces: New Evidence and New Conclusions|publisher=Republic of Texas Press|location=Lanham, MD|year=2003|isbn=1-55622-983-6}}
* {{citation|last=Lord|first=Walter|author-link=Walter Lord|title=A Time to Stand|publisher=[[University of Nebraska Press]]|year=1961|location=Lincoln, NE|isbn=0-8032-7902-7}}
* {{citation|last=Manchaca|first=Martha|title=Recovering History, Constructing Race: The Indian, Black, and White Roots of Mexican Americans|series=The Joe R. and Teresa Lozano Long Series in Latin American and Latino Art and Culture|publisher=University of Texas Press|location=Austin, TX|year=2001|isbn=0-292-75253-9}}
* {{citation|last=Myers|first=John Myers|title=The Alamo|publisher=University of Nebraska Press|location=Lincoln, NE|year=1948|isbn=0-8032-5779-1}}
* {{citation|last=Nofi|first=Albert A.|author-link=Albert Nofi|title=The Alamo and the Texas War of Independence, September 30, 1835 to April 21, 1836: Heroes, Myths, and History|publisher=Combined Books, Inc.|year=1992|place=Conshohocken, PA|isbn=0-938289-10-1}}
* {{citation|last=Petite|first=Mary Deborah|title=1836 Facts about the Alamo and the Texas War for Independence|year=1999|isbn=1-882810-35-X|publisher=Savas Publishing Company|location=Mason City, IA}}
* {{citation|last=Schoelwer|first=Susan Prendergast|title=Alamo Images: Changing Perceptions of a Texas Experience|publisher=The DeGlolyer Library and Southern Methodist University Press|year=1985|location=Dallas, TX|isbn=0-87074-213-2}}
* {{citation|last=Scott|first=Robert|title=After the Alamo|publisher=Republic of Texas Press|year=2000|location=Plano, TX|isbn=978-1-55622-691-5}}
* {{citation|last=Tinkle|first=Lon|author-link=Lon Tinkle|title=13 Days to Glory: The Siege of the Alamo|publisher=Texas A&amp;M University Press|location=College Station, TX|year=1985|isbn=0-89096-238-3}}. Reprint. Originally published: New York: McGraw-Hill, 1958
* {{citation|last=Todish|first=Timothy J.|last2=Todish|first2=Terry|last3=Spring|first3=Ted|title=Alamo Sourcebook, 1836: A Comprehensive Guide to the Battle of the Alamo and the Texas Revolution|publisher=Eakin Press|year=1998|location=Austin, TX|isbn=978-1-57168-152-2}}

==Further reading==
* {{citation|last=Crisp|first=James E.|title=Sleuthing the Alamo|year=2005|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|isbn=0-19-516349-4}}
* {{citation|last=Hardin|first=Stephen L.|title=The Alamo 1836: Santa Anna's Texas Campaign|series=Osprey Campaign Series #89|publisher=[[Osprey Publishing]]|year=2001|isbn=1-84176-090-0}}
* {{citation|last=Dole|first=Gerard|title=Texas 1836 – Musical Echoes from the Alamo|publisher=[[Terre de Brume]]|year=2011|isbn=978-2-84362-474-2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.thealamo.org/ Official website for the Alamo]

{{Battle of the Alamo}}
{{Texas History Navbox}}

{{Coord|29|25|32|N|98|29|10|W|region:US_type:event|display=title}}

{{featured article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Alamo, Battle Of The}}
[[Category:Battles of the Texas Revolution]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1836|Battle of the Alamo]]
[[Category:History of San Antonio, Texas]]
[[Category:Sieges]]
[[Category:Battles involving the Republic of Texas]]
[[Category:1836 in Texas]]

{{Link GA|ru}}

[[ar:معركة إل ألامو]]
[[bg:Битка при Аламо]]
[[ca:Setge d'El Álamo]]
[[cs:Bitva u Alama]]
[[de:Schlacht von Alamo]]
[[et:Alamo lahing]]
[[el:Μάχη του Άλαμο]]
[[es:Batalla de El Álamo]]
[[eo:Batalo de la Alamo]]
[[fa:نبرد آلامو]]
[[fr:Siège de Fort Alamo]]
[[ko:알라모 전투]]
[[id:Pertempuran Alamo]]
[[it:Battaglia di Alamo]]
[[he:קרב אלמו]]
[[ka:ალამოს ბრძოლა]]
[[mk:Битка кај Аламо]]
[[nl:Slag om de Alamo]]
[[ja:アラモの戦い]]
[[no:Slaget ved Alamo]]
[[oc:Sètge de l'Alamo]]
[[pl:Bitwa o Alamo]]
[[pt:Batalha do Álamo]]
[[ro:Bătălia de la Alamo]]
[[ru:Защита миссии Аламо]]
[[simple:Battle of the Alamo]]
[[sl:Bitka za Alamo]]
[[fi:Alamon taistelu]]
[[sv:Slaget vid Alamo]]
[[tr:Alamo Muharebesi]]
[[zh:阿拉摩之戰]]</text>
      <sha1>mq1b1nqhqapjsusqdkypabxwdjcayl1</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
