<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Crusades</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4412145</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519250553</id>
      <parentid>518676147</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-22T18:56:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Womprat99</username>
        <id>1493792</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Spelling error correction</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="100195">{{About|the 11th, 12th and 13th century religious military campaigns|other uses|Crusade (disambiguation)|and|Crusader (disambiguation)}}
[[File:Battle-of-Ager-Sanguinis.jpg|thumb|right|The [[Battle of Ager Sanguinis]], 1337 miniature]]

{{sprotect|small=yes}}

The '''Crusades''' were a series of [[Religious war|religious]] [[expeditionary war]]s blessed by [[Pope Urban II]] and the [[Catholic Church]], with the stated goal of restoring Christian access to the [[List of Christian holy sites in the Holy Land|holy places]] in and near [[Jerusalem]]. Jerusalem was and is a sacred city and symbol of all three major Abrahamic faiths ([[Judaism]], [[Christianity]] and [[Islam]]).&lt;ref name=Esposito&gt;Esposito ''What Everyone Needs to Know about Islam''&lt;/ref&gt; The background to the Crusades was set when the [[Seljuk Turk]]s decisively defeated the [[Byzantine]] army in 1071 and cut off Christian access to Jerusalem. The Byzantine emperor, [[Alexios I Komnenos|Alexis I]] feared that all Asia Minor would be overrun. He called on western Christian leaders and the papacy to come to the aid of Constantinople by undertaking a pilgrimage or a crusade that would free Jerusalem from Muslim rule.&lt;ref name=Esposito87&gt;Esposito ''What Everyone Needs to Know About Islam'' p. 87&lt;/ref&gt; Another cause was the destruction of many Christian [[List of religious sites|sacred sites]] and the [[persecution of Christians]] under the [[Fatimid]] [[caliph]] [[Al-Hakim bi-Amr Allah|Al-Hakim]].

The crusaders comprised military units of Roman Catholics from all over western Europe, and were not under unified command. The main series of Crusades, primarily against [[Muslim]]s in the [[Levant]], occurred between 1095 and 1291. Historians have given many of the earlier crusades numbers. After some early successes, the later crusades failed and the crusaders were defeated and forced to return home. Several hundred thousand soldiers became Crusaders by taking vows;&lt;ref name=Asbridge1&gt;Asbridge ''Crusades'' p. 1&lt;/ref&gt; the Pope granted them [[plenary indulgence]].  Their emblem was the cross — the term &quot;crusade&quot; is derived from the French term for taking up the cross. Many were from France and called themselves &quot;Franks,&quot; which became the common term used by Muslims.&lt;ref name=Asbridge6&gt;Asbridge ''Crusades'' p. 6&lt;/ref&gt;

The term &quot;crusade&quot; is also used to describe religiously motivated campaigns conducted between 1100 and 1600 in territories outside the [[Levant]]{{efn|Such as Muslim territories in [[Al-Andalus]], [[Ifriqiya]], and [[Egypt]], as well as in [[Eastern Europe]]}} usually against pagans, heretics, and peoples under the ban of [[excommunication]] for a mixture of religious, economic, and political reasons.{{efn|Such as the [[Albigensian Crusade]], the [[Aragonese Crusade]], the [[Reconquista]], and the [[Northern Crusades]].}} Rivalries among both Christian and Muslim powers led also to alliances between religious factions against their opponents, such as the Christian alliance with the Islamic [[Sultanate of Rûm]] during the [[Fifth Crusade]].

The Crusades had major political, economic, and social impact on western Europe. It resulted in a substantial weakening of the Christian [[Byzantine Empire]], which fell several centuries later to the Muslim [[Turkish people|Turks]]. The [[Reconquista]], a long period of wars in Spain and Portugal ([[Iberia]]), where Christian forces reconquered the peninsula from Muslims, is closely tied to the Crusades.

== Background ==

===Middle Eastern situation===
{{main|Muslim conquests}}
In 636 CE, Muslim forces led by the Arab Rashidun [[Caliph]]s defeated the Eastern Roman/Byzantines at the [[Battle of Yarmouk]], conquering Palestine.&lt;ref name=Lock4&gt;Lock ''Routledge Companion'' p. 4&lt;/ref&gt; Jerusalem fell to Caliph [[Umar|Omar]]'s forces in February 638.&lt;ref name=Hindley12&gt;Hindley ''Crusades'' p. 12&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Umayyad Dynasty]] was inaugurated by [[Muawiyah I]], sole caliph from 661,&lt;ref name=Wickham280&gt;Wickham ''Inheritance of Rome'' p. 280&lt;/ref&gt; who made his capital in [[Damascus]].&lt;ref name=Wickham287&gt;Wickham ''Inheritance of Rome'' p. 287&lt;/ref&gt; In 750 the Umayyads were overthrown by the [[Abbasid Dynasty]] of [[Baghdad]]&lt;ref name=Lock4/&gt; and from 878 Palestine was ruled by semi-autonomous governors in Egypt{{citation needed|date=August 2012}} until the [[Fatimids]] conquered it in 969.&lt;ref name=Hindley14&gt;Hindley ''Crusades'' p. 14&lt;/ref&gt; The Fatimids, whose empire stretched to Morocco and centered on Egypt, were tolerant for the times and had many trade and political relationships with the Christian states of Europe.  In 1072 the Fatimids lost control of Palestine to the rapidly expanding [[Great Seljuq Empire]].&lt;ref name=Hindley15/&gt; They regained control of it in 1098, but their control was shaky, with the countryside subject to raids by Bedouin nomads and Turkish mercenaries.&lt;ref name=Hindley16/&gt;

One factor that may have contributed to Western interest in Palestine came during the reign of the [[Fatimid Caliphate|Fatimid]] Caliph [[al-Hakim bi-Amr Allah]] who ordered the destruction of the [[Church of the Holy Sepulchre]]. In 1039 his successor permitted the Byzantine Empire to rebuild it.&lt;ref name=Pringle157&gt;Pringle &quot;Architecture in Latin East&quot; ''Oxford History of the Crusades'' p. 157&lt;/ref&gt; Pilgrimages had been allowed by Christians to the holy sites in Palestine from soon after their conquest by the Muslims.&lt;ref name=Hindley15&gt;Hindley ''Crusades'' p. 15&lt;/ref&gt; However, under the Seljuqs pilgrimage routes were disrupted and the unsettled conditions in Palestine were not conducive to either pilgrims or merchants.&lt;ref name=Hindley16&gt;Hindley ''Crusades'' pp. 15-16&lt;/ref&gt; The Muslims realized that much of the wealth of Jerusalem came from the pilgrims; for this reason and others, the persecution of pilgrims eventually stopped. However, the damage was already done, and the violence of the conquering Seljuk Turks became part of the concern that spread support for the Crusades across the Christian world.&lt;ref name=Madden8&gt;Madden ''New Concise History of the Crusades'' p. 8&lt;/ref&gt;

===Western European situation===
The western European idea of the Crusades came in response to the deterioration of the [[Byzantine Empire]] caused by a new wave of [[Byzantine–Seljuk Wars|Turkish Muslim attacks]].&lt;ref name=Smith1&gt;Riley-Smith ''Crusades'' pp. 1-2&lt;/ref&gt; The Byzantine emperors in the east, now threatened by the [[Seljuks]], sent emissaries to the papacy asking for aid in their struggles with the Seljuk Turks. In 1074, Emperor [[Michael VII]] sent a request for aid to [[Pope Gregory VII]], but although Gregory appears to have considered leading an expedition to aid Michael, nothing reached the planning stage.&lt;ref name=Lock306/&gt; In 1095 Emperor [[Alexios I Komnenos]] asked [[Pope Urban II]] for help against the Turks.&lt;ref name=Smith1/&gt; 

The Crusades were, in part, an outlet for an intense religious piety which rose up in the late 11th century among the lay public. This was an outgrowth of the [[Investiture Controversy]], which had started around 1075 and was still on-going during the First Crusade. The papacy began to assert its independence of secular rulers and marshalled arguments for the proper use of armed force by Christians. As both sides of the Investiture Controversy tried to marshal public opinion in their favor, people became personally engaged in a dramatic religious controversy. The result was an awakening of intense Christian piety and public interest in religious affairs, and was further strengthened by religious propaganda, which advocated &quot;[[Just War]]&quot; in order to retake Palestine from the Muslims. Taking part in such a justified war was seen as a form of [[penance]], which could remit sins.&lt;ref name=Smith8&gt;Riley-Smith ''Crusades'' pp. 8-10&lt;/ref&gt;

It was a hotly debated issue throughout the Crusades as what exactly &quot;remission of sin&quot; meant. Most believed that by retaking Jerusalem they would go straight to heaven after death. However, much controversy surrounds exactly what was promised by the popes of the time. One theory was that one had to die fighting for Jerusalem for the remission to apply, which would hew more closely to what [[Pope Urban II]] said in his speeches. This meant that if the crusaders were successful, and retook Jerusalem, the survivors would not be given remission.

====Precursors====
[[File:Almoravid map reconquest loc.jpg|thumb|Map of the [[Iberian Peninsula]] at the time of the [[Almoravid dynasty|Almoravid]] arrival in the 11th century&amp;ndash; Christian Kingdoms included '''A'''ragón, '''C'''astile, '''L'''eon, '''N'''avarre, and '''P'''ortugal]]

When the First Crusade was preached in 1095, the Christian princes of northern Iberia had been fighting their way out of the mountains of [[Kingdom of Galicia|Galicia]] and [[Asturias]], the [[Basque Country (greater region)|Basque Country]] and [[Kingdom of Navarre|Navarre]], with increasing success, for about a hundred years.&lt;ref name=Barber341&gt;Barber ''Two Cities'' pp. 341-345&lt;/ref&gt; The fall of Moorish [[Toledo, Spain|Toledo]] to the [[Kingdom of León]] in 1085 was a major victory,&lt;ref name=Bull18&gt;Bull &quot;Origins&quot; ''Oxford History of the Crusades'' pp. 18-19&lt;/ref&gt; but the turning points of the ''[[Reconquista]]'' still lay in the future. The disunity of Muslim emirs was an essential factor.&lt;ref name=Barber341/&gt; Other areas were also undergoing Christian expansion against the Muslims. In Sicily, the [[Normans|Norman]] adventurer [[Robert Guiscard]] had conquered northern Sicily by 1072.&lt;ref name=Mayer17&gt;Mayer ''Crusades'' pp. 17-18&lt;/ref&gt; The maritime state of [[Pisa]] funded its new cathedral from two raids on the Muslims - Palermo in 1063 and Mahdia in 1087.&lt;ref name=Lock306/&gt; Not all these precursor conflicts were against the Muslims, as the Germans were expanding at the expense of the [[Slavs]] in Northern Europe.&lt;ref name=Contest31&gt;Housley ''Contesting the Crusades'' p. 31&lt;/ref&gt; All of these expeditions, along with a few others, are considered precursors to the Crusades, and are often given the name of &quot;proto-crusades&quot;.&lt;ref name=Lock306&gt;Lock ''Routledge Companion'' pp. 306-308&lt;/ref&gt;

====Just war doctrine====
The papacy of [[Pope Gregory VII]] had struggled with reservations about the doctrinal validity of a holy war and the shedding of blood for the Lord and had, with difficulty, resolved the question in favour of justified violence. More importantly to the Pope, the Christians who made pilgrimages to the Holy Land were being persecuted. Saint [[Augustine of Hippo]], Gregory's intellectual model, had justified the use of force in the service of Christ in ''[[City of God (book)|The City of God]]'', and a Christian &quot;[[Just War]]&quot; might enhance the wider standing of an aggressively ambitious leader of Europe, as Gregory saw himself.{{citation needed|date=August 2012}}

The northerners would be cemented to Rome, and their troublesome knights could see the only kind of action that suited them. Previous attempts by the church to stem such violence, such as the concept of the &quot;Peace of God&quot;, were not as successful as hoped. To the south of Rome, Normans were showing how such energies might be unleashed against both Arabs (in Sicily) and Byzantines (on the mainland). A Latin hegemony in the [[Levant]] would provide leverage in resolving the Papacy's claims of supremacy over the [[Patriarch of Constantinople]], which had resulted in the [[East–West Schism|Great Schism]] of 1054, a rift that might yet be resolved through the force of Frankish arms.{{citation needed|date=August 2012}}

====Byzantine weakness====
[[File:Seljuk Empire locator map.svg|thumb|The [[Seljuq dynasty]] at its greatest extent, in 1092.]]
The Eastern Empire and its church were officially divided from the Western church and society in 1054, with the [[East-West Schism]], but cultural differences had long divided the two before the official break in 1054.&lt;ref name=Mayer2&gt;Mayer ''Crusades'' pp. 2-3&lt;/ref&gt; In the Byzantine Empire, the Eastern emperor's weakness was revealed by the defeat at the [[Battle of Manzikert]] in 1071, which opened Asia Minor to the control of the Turks.&lt;ref name=Smith1/&gt; The Empire was on the verge of collapse, with its treasury bankrupt, its armies poorly deployed, and its aged emperor ineffective.&lt;ref name=Asbridge97&gt;Asbridge, ''First Crusade'' p. 97&lt;/ref&gt; Although an appeal was made in 1074 to the papacy, no aid was forthcoming from Pope Gregory VII.&lt;ref name=Lock306/&gt; The Eastern Empire also faced difficulties in the Danube river area, as the [[Petchenegs]] had allied with the Seljuks and threatened the Empire until 1091 when they were defeated by Emperor Alexius. Alexius still needed to rebuild his armies, and sought to increase his military forces by hiring mercenaries. The Byzantine envoys to Piacenza in March 1095 likely were more concerned to secure mercenaries for Alexius' armies and may have exaggerated the dangers facing the Eastern Empire in order to secure the needed troops.&lt;ref name=Mayer6&gt;Mayer ''Crusades'' pp. 6-7&lt;/ref&gt;

===Pope Urban II===
[[File:CouncilofClermont.jpg|thumb|left|15th century [[Illuminated manuscript|illumination]] of [[Pope Urban II]] at the [[Council of Clermont]], where he preached an impassioned sermon to take back the Holy Land.]]

The immediate cause of the First Crusade was the Byzantine emperor [[Alexios I Komnenos|Alexios I]]'s appeal to [[Pope Urban II]] for mercenaries to help him resist Muslim advances into territory of the Byzantine Empire.&lt;ref name=Mayer6/&gt; Although attempts at reconciliation after the [[East–West Schism]] between the [[Catholic Church]] in western Europe and the [[Eastern Orthodox Church]] had failed, Alexius I hoped for a positive response from Urban II.&lt;ref name=Mayer2/&gt;

Pope Urban II defined and launched the crusades at the [[Council of Clermont]] in 1095. He was a reformer worried about the evils which had hindered the spiritual success of the church and its clergy and the need for a revival of religiosity.&lt;ref name=Smith2&gt;Riley-Smith ''Crusades'' pp. 2-3&lt;/ref&gt; He was moved by the urgent appeal for help from Byzantine Emperor Alexius I.  Urban's solution was announced on the last day of the council when the pope suddenly proclaimed the Crusade against the infidel Muslims. He called for Christian princes across Europe to launch a holy war in the Holy Land. He contrasted the sanctity of Jerusalem and the holy places with the plunder and desecration by the infidel Turks. He caused outrage by vividly describing attacks upon the Christian pilgrims. He also noted the military threat to the fellow Christians of Byzantium.&lt;ref name=Mayer8&gt;Mayer ''Crusades'' pp. 8-9&lt;/ref&gt; He charged Christians to take up the holy cause, promising to all those who went remission of sins and to all who died in the expedition immediate entry into heaven.&lt;ref name=Bull32&gt;Bull &quot;Origins&quot; ''Oxford History of the Crusades'' pp. 32-34&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|Early crusading popes used gendered language that excluded women's military participation, but after the loss of Jerusalem, popes used neutral and even inclusive language, thus inviting women's participation. In any case women &quot;camp followers&quot; accompanied the armies, usually to handle cooking and cleaning chores.&lt;ref&gt;Susan B. Edgington and Sarah Lambert, eds. ''Gendering the Crusades.'' (2002)&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Then Urban raised secular motives, talking of the feudal love of tournaments and warfare. He urged the barons to give up their fratricidal and unrighteous wars in the West for the holy war in the East. He also suggested material rewards, regarding feudal fiefdoms, land ownership, wealth, power, and prestige, all at the expense of the Arabs and Turks. He said they could be defeated very easily by the Christian forces.  When he finished, his listeners chanted &quot;Deus vult&quot; (God wills it). This became the battle cry of the crusaders.  Urban put the bishop of Le Puy in charge of encouraging prelates and priests to join the cause.{{efn|Spanish Christians were exempt because they were busy expelling the Moors from Spain.}}  Word spread rapidly that war against unbelief would be fused with the practice of pilgrimage to holy sites, and the pilgrims' reward would be great on earth, as in heaven.  Immediately thousands pledged themselves to go on the first crusade. Pope Urban's speech ranks as one of the most influential speeches ever made: it launched the holy wars which occupied the minds and forces of western Europe for two hundred years.&lt;ref name=Munro&gt;Munro &quot;Speech of Pope Urban II&quot; ''American Historical Review''&lt;/ref&gt;

===Preaching and preparation before the First Crusade===
{{main| Persecution of Jews in the First Crusade}}

Urban's sermon at Clermont was the start of an eight month preaching tour that the pope undertook throughout France, urging the holy war and exhorting people to help defend the Byzantine church against the Muslims. He also sent other preachers throughout Western Europe to spread the word of the Crusade. Urban fixed a date of August 1096 for the crusaders to depart for Palestine. Urban's example inspired the preaching of [[Peter the Hermit]], who eventually led a &quot;[[People's Crusade]]&quot; of perhaps as many as 20,000 people, mostly lower class, towards the Holy Land just after Easter 1096.&lt;ref name=Hindley20&gt;Hindley ''Crusades'' pp. 20-21&lt;/ref&gt; When they reached the Byzantine Empire, Alexius urged them to wait for the western nobles, but the &quot;army&quot; insisted on proceeding and was ambushed outside Nicaea by the Turks, with only about 3000 people escaping the ambush.&lt;ref name=Hindley23&gt;Hindley ''Crusades'' p. 23&lt;/ref&gt;  

On a popular level, the preaching of the First Crusade unleashed a wave of impassioned, personally felt pious Christian fury that was expressed in the massacres of [[Jews]] that accompanied and preceded the movement of the crusaders through Europe,&lt;ref name=Smith23&gt;Riley-Smith ''Crusades'' pp. 23-24&lt;/ref&gt; as well as the violent treatment of &quot;[[schism (religion)|schism]]atic&quot; Orthodox Christians of the east.

Besides the People's Crusade, Urban's appeal gathered a large number of noblemen and other soldiers together. Among the leaders of the First Crusade were [[Godfrey of Bouillon]], [[Robert Curthose]] - son of [[William the Conqueror]] and eldest brother of the then King of England, [[William II of England]], [[Hugh of Vermandois]] - brother of King [[Philip I of France]], and [[Stephen, Count of Blois]] - brother-in-law of Robert Curthose. The French king was excommunicated and thus unable to go. The German Emperor, [[Henry IV, Holy Roman Emperor|Henry IV]], was still embroiled in the Investiture Crisis and would not have supported papal initiatives.&lt;ref name=Hindley25&gt;Hindley ''Crusades'' pp. 25-26&lt;/ref&gt; The various leaders left at different times, with Hugh of Vermandois departing first and the bulk of the army dividing into four parts which travelled separately to Constantinople.&lt;ref name=Hindley27&gt;Hindley ''Crusades'' pp. 27-30&lt;/ref&gt; In all, the western forces may have totaled as much as 100,000 persons counting both combatants and non-combatants.&lt;ref name=Hindley31&gt;Hindley ''Crusades'' pp. 30-31&lt;/ref&gt;

==List==
A traditional numbering scheme for the crusades totals nine during the 11th to 13th centuries. This division is arbitrary and excludes many important expeditions, among them those of the 14th, 15th, and 16th centuries.  The [[Knights Hospitaller]] continued to crusade in the [[Mediterranean Sea]] around [[Malta]] until their defeat by [[Napoleon]] in 1798. There were frequent &quot;minor&quot; Crusades throughout this period, not only in the area the crusaders called [[Outremer]] but also in the Iberian Peninsula and central Europe, against Muslims and also Christian heretics and personal enemies of the Papacy or other powerful monarchs.

===First Crusade 1095–1099===
{{Main|First Crusade}}
[[File:Byzantium after the First crusade.PNG|thumb|left|Route of the First Crusade through Asia]]

The official crusader armies set off from France and Italy on the papally ordained date of 15 August 1096. The armies journeyed eastward by land toward Constantinople, where they received a wary welcome from the Byzantine Emperor. Pledging to restore lost territories to the empire, the main army, mostly French and Norman knights under baronial leadership—[[Godfrey of Bouillon]] (1060–1100), Baldwin of Flanders, Raymond of Toulouse, [[Robert Curthose|Robert of Normandy]], [[Bohemond I of Antioch|Bohemond of Taranto]], marched south through Anatolia.&lt;ref name=GodsWar106&gt;Tyerman ''God's War'' pp. 106–124&lt;/ref&gt;

====Campaigns====
The Crusader armies fought the Turks, at first at the lengthy [[Siege of Antioch]] that began in October 1097 and lasted until June 1098. Once inside the city, as was standard military practice when an enemy had refused to surrender,&lt;ref name=Tuchman279&gt;Tuchman  ''A Distant Mirror'' p. 279&lt;/ref&gt; the Crusaders massacred the Muslim inhabitants and pillaged the city.&lt;ref name=Nicholle56&gt;Nicholle ''First Crusade'' p. 56&lt;/ref&gt; However, a large Muslim relief army under [[Kerbogha]] immediately besieged the victorious Crusaders within Antioch. [[Bohemund of Taranto]] led a successful break-out and defeat of Kerbogha's army on 28 June.&lt;ref name=Tyerman143&gt;Tyerman ''God's War'' pp. 143-146&lt;/ref&gt; While Bohemond and his men retained control of Antioch,&lt;ref name=Tyerman146/&gt; in spite of his pledge to the Byzantine emperor,&lt;ref name=Mayer60&gt;Mayer ''Crusades'' pp. 60-61&lt;/ref&gt; most of the surviving crusader army marched south, moving from town to town along the coast, finally reaching the walls of Jerusalem on 7 June 1099 with only a fraction of their original forces.&lt;ref name=Tyerman146&gt;Tyerman ''God's War'' pp. 146–153&lt;/ref&gt;

====Siege of Jerusalem====
{{Main|Siege of Jerusalem (1099)}}
[[File:Godefroi1099.jpg|thumb|left|After the successful siege of Jerusalem in 1099, [[Godfrey of Bouillon]], leader of the First Crusade, became the first ruler of the Kingdom of Jerusalem.]]
The Jews and Muslims fought together to defend Jerusalem against the invading Franks. They were unsuccessful though and on 15 July 1099 the crusaders entered the city. They proceeded to massacre the remaining Jewish and Muslim civilians and pillaged or destroyed mosques and the city itself.&lt;ref name=&quot;accessed February 17, 2008&quot;&gt;Trumpbour, John. &quot;Crusades.&quot; In The Oxford Encyclopedia of the Islamic World., edited by John L. Esposito. Oxford Islamic Studies Online, http://www.oxfordislamicstudies.com/article (accessed February 17, 2008).&lt;/ref&gt; One historian has written that the &quot;isolation, alienation and fear&quot;  felt by the Franks so far from home helps to explain the atrocities they committed, including the cannibalism which was recorded after the [[Siege of Ma'arra]] in 1098.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Les Croisades, origines et consequences&quot;, p.62, Claude Lebedel, ISBN 2-7373-4136-1&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of the First Crusade, several small [[Crusader states]] were created, notably the [[Kingdom of Jerusalem]]. In the Kingdom of Jerusalem at most 120,000 Franks (predominantly [[French language|French]]-speaking Western Christians) ruled over 350,000 Muslims, Jews, and native Eastern Christians who had remained since the Arab occupation began in 638 AD.&lt;ref&gt;Benjamin Z. Kedar, &quot;The Subjected Muslims of the Frankish Levant&quot;, in ''The Crusades: The Essential Readings'', ed. [[Thomas Madden|Thomas F. Madden]], Blackwell, 2002, pg. 244. Originally published in ''Muslims Under Latin Rule, 1100–1300'', ed. James M. Powell, Princeton University Press, 1990. Kedar quotes his numbers from [[Joshua Prawer]], ''Histoire du royaume latin de Jérusalem'', tr. G. Nahon, Paris, 1969, vol. 1, pp. 498, 568–72.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Crusaders also tried to gain control of the city of [[Tyre, Lebanon|Tyre]], but were defeated by the Muslims. The people of Tyre asked [[Toghtekin|Zahir al-Din Atabek]], the leader of [[Damascus]], for help defending their city from the Franks with the promise to surrender Tyre to him. When the Franks were defeated the people of Tyre did not surrender the city but Zahir al-Din simply said, &quot;What I have done I have done only for the sake of God and the Muslims, not out of desire for wealth and kingdom.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;The Damascus Chronicle of the Crusades, Extracted and translated from the chronicle of Ibn Al-Qalanisi, translated by H.A.R. Gibb (London: Luzac &amp; Co., 1932).&lt;/ref&gt;

After gaining control of Jerusalem the Crusaders created four Crusader states: the [[Kingdom of Jerusalem]], the [[County of Edessa]], the [[Principality of Antioch]] and the [[County of Tripoli]].&lt;ref name=&quot;accessed February 17, 2008&quot;/&gt; Initially, Muslims did very little about the Crusader states due to internal conflicts.&lt;ref name=&quot;oxfordislamicstudies.com&quot;&gt;&quot;Crusades&quot; In The Islamic World: past and Present., edited by John L. Esposito. Oxford Islamic Studies Online, http://www.oxfordislamicstudies.com/article (accessed February 17, 2008).&lt;/ref&gt;
Eventually, the Muslims began to reunite under the leadership of [[Zengi|Imad ad-Din Zengi]]. He began by re-taking Edessa in 1144. It was the first city to fall to the Crusaders, and became the first to be recaptured by the Muslims. This led the Pope to call for a second Crusade.

====Crusaders' perspectives====
[[File:Near East 1135.svg|thumb|The [[crusader states]] after the First Crusade]]
The story of the first crusade from the crusaders' perspective recounts the struggles of the first wave of crusaders to reach the hinterlands of Byzantium, of Islamic Syria, and then of Jerusalem; of the terrible slaughters of Jewish populations committed by a second wave as it marched through the Rhineland;&lt;ref&gt;Jeremy Cohen, ''Sanctifying the Name of God: Jewish Martyrs and Jewish Memories of the First Crusade.'' (2004) examines Hebrew accounts of how crusader bands in 1096 forced Jews in Mainz, Speyer, and other towns to convert and murdered or drive to suicide many who refused summary baptism, and how some Jewish leaders killed their followers and mothers killed their children.&lt;/ref&gt; of finding food and facing starvation; of the &quot;miracles&quot; associated with the alleged finding of the Holy Lance in Antioch; of the competition between European princes for leadership; and of the eventual taking of Jerusalem itself. It was an achievement to coordinate crusaders with sharply different languages, styles of leadership, and modes of fighting. That such a band even made it to Jerusalem is remarkable, and was possible, first, because of divisions within the realm of Islam, and second, because Muslims in the various provinces misinterpreted the presence of the crusading army. They seem to have regarded the Christian forces as renegades, escapees from the poverty and oppression of the &quot;territory of war.&quot; This interpretation led to a low estimate of the threat posed to Muslim security by an army that, despite weaknesses, was motivated by a profound religious fervor.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas Asbridge, ''First Crusade: A New History'' (2004)&lt;/ref&gt;

====Scholarly debates====
According to the interpretation of historian [[Steven Runciman]] (1951), the First Crusade was like a barbarian invasion of the civilized and sophisticated Byzantine empire and ultimately brought about the ruin of Byzantine civilization.&lt;ref&gt;John M. Riddle, ''A history of the Middle Ages, 300-1500'' (2008) p. 315&lt;/ref&gt;  The crusade was unwittingly triggered by the Byzantine emperor, Alexius I Comnenus, when he had sent ambassadors to the pope in 1095 to ask for mercenary soldiers to enroll in his armies. The emotive appeal made in response by Pope Urban II, however, had the effect of sending thousands of Frankish knights to Constantinople under their own leaders, quite a different outcome from what Alexius had expected.  There had been long-distance intellectual disputes between Byzantium and the West in the past, but since contact between the two societies was sporadic, there was little open hostility. Now that the westerners arrived in the center of the empire in large numbers, those differences became a serious matter. Especially important, Runciman argues, was tension between the Byzantine patriarch and the pope, and the more tolerant attitude of the Byzantines towards Muslim powers. Although Runciman lays some of the blame at the door of the Byzantine emperors who reigned after 1143, the sack of Constantinople by the Fourth Crusade in April 1204 was the culmination of the mounting dislike and suspicion that all western Christendom now felt towards the Byzantines.
[[File:Baldwin 1 of Jerusalem.jpg|thumb|left|[[Baldwin I of Jerusalem]]]]
Ever since Runciman published his interpretation in 1951, it has been under challenge by scholars. They say he was too uncritical in accepting the main Byzantine source, the narrative by [[Anna Comnena]] (the daughter of Emperor Alexius I), which presents Alexius I's actions as motivated solely by superhuman charity and places the blame entirely on the crusaders, particularly on the Norman, Bohemond of Taranto. Critics say Runciman takes at face value Anna Comnena's descriptions of some of the crusaders as uncouth louts and this is largely the basis for belief that the two peoples were mutually estranged from the start. Scholars argue that the classicising literary genre in which Comnena wrote dictated that foreign peoples be presented as 'barbarians' and that this did not necessarily mean that the entire populations of the two halves of Christendom were in a constantly increasing state of mutual antipathy.&lt;ref&gt;Steven Runciman, ''A history of the Crusades'' (Volume 1, 1951)&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Peter the Hermit.jpg|thumb|A medieval image of [[Peter the Hermit]], leading knights, soldiers and women toward Jerusalem during the First Crusade]]
Among recent scholars, Paul Magdalino's and Ralph-Johannes Lilie's close studies of Byzantine policies towards the crusader states of Syria show not steadily mounting tension, but periods of animosity interspersed with co-operation and alliance.&lt;ref&gt;R-J. Lilie, ''Byzantium and the Crusader States 1095-1204'' (1993); Paul Magdalino, ''The Empire of Manuel I Komnenos 1143-1180'' (1993), pp. 66-108.&lt;/ref&gt; Jonathan Shepard re-examines the whole question of Byzantine involvement with the genesis of the First Crusade in two influential articles. Adopting a more critical stance towards Anna Comnena, Shepard argues that there was far more to the episode than an innocent Byzantine emperor taken aback by the turn of events and that Alexius was cleverly exploiting the situation for his own ends. While Runciman denounces Bohemond, the Norman leader, as a &quot;villain&quot; whose greed soured relations with the Byzantines, Shepard argues that this picture depends on an uncritical reading of Anna Comnena, who glorified her own family and vilified Bohemond mercilessly. In reality in 1096-7, Alexius viewed Bohemond as a potential tool, ally and recruit, a kind of imperial agent to oversee the re-conquest of Asia Minor.&lt;ref&gt;Jonathan Shepard, &quot;Cross-purposes: Alexius Comnenus and the First Crusade,&quot; in ''The First Crusade Origins and Impact,'' ed. Jonathan Phillips (1997), pp. 107–29, and Shepard, &quot;When Greek meets Greek: Alexius Comnenus and Bohemond in 1097-98&quot;, ''Byzantine and Modern Greek Studies,'' 12 (1988), pp. 185–277.&lt;/ref&gt;

Harris (2003) rejects the &quot;clash of civilizations&quot; model. He argues that trouble arose because the West misunderstood Byzantine foreign policy. That policy was narrowly focused on three goals which the West did not accept: acceptance of the theory  that the Roman inheritance had shifted from Rome to Constantinople (called ''translatio imperii''), that the suzerainty of Byzantine emperors ought to be recognized by the West, and commitment to the security of the ''Oikumene'' (that is, the civilized, Christian world centered around Constantinople).  Although the Byzantines employed many high-ranking Latins in their government, Harris finds repeated instances of Byzantine hostility toward Latins, based on deep-rooted and long-standing antipathy that was rooted in a conviction of Byzantine cultural and religious superiority, and perhaps heightened by a growing fear of Byzantium's military inferiority and political weakness.&lt;ref&gt;Jonathan, Harris, ''Byzantium and the Crusades.'' (2003)&lt;/ref&gt;

====Crusade of 1101====
{{Main|Crusade of 1101}}
Following this crusade there was a second, less successful wave of crusaders, in which Turks led by [[Kilij Arslan I|Kilij Arslan]] defeated the Crusaders in three separate battles in a well-managed response to the [[First Crusade]].&lt;ref&gt;Contesting the Crusades
 By Norman Housley, pg. 42&lt;/ref&gt; This is known as the [[Crusade of 1101]] and may be considered an adjunct of the First Crusade.

====Norwegian Crusade 1107–1110====
{{Main|Norwegian Crusade}}

[[Sigurd I of Norway]] was the first European king who went on a crusade and his crusader armies defeated Muslims in [[Al-Andalus]], the [[Balearic Islands]], and in The Holy Land where they joined the king of Jerusalem in the [[Siege of Sidon (1110)|Siege of Sidon]].

===Second Crusade 1147–1149===
{{Main|Second Crusade}}
[[File:Europe 1142.jpg|thumb|Europe and the Christian States in the East in 1142]]
After a period of relative peace in which Christians and Muslims co-existed in the Holy Land, Muslims conquered the town of [[County of Edessa|Edessa]]. A new crusade was called for by various preachers, most notably by [[Bernard of Clairvaux]]. French and South German armies, under the Kings [[Louis VII of France|Louis VII]] and [[Conrad III of Germany|Conrad III]] respectively, marched to Jerusalem in 1147 but failed to win any major victories, launching a failed pre-emptive siege of Damascus, an independent city that would soon fall into the hands of [[Nur ad-Din Zangi]], the main enemy of the Crusaders.&lt;ref name=&quot;lewis&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Archibald Ross Lewis|title=Nomads and Crusaders: AD 1000–1368.|month=January | year=1988|publisher=Indiana University Press|isbn=978-0-253-20652-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the other side of the Mediterranean, however, the Second Crusade met with great success as a group of Northern European Crusaders stopped in [[Portugal]], allied with the [[List of Portuguese monarchs|Portuguese King]], [[Afonso I of Portugal]], and [[Siege of Lisbon|retook Lisbon]] from the Muslims in 1147.&lt;ref name=&quot;lewis&quot;/&gt; A detachment from this group of crusaders helped [[Ramon Berenguer IV, Count of Barcelona|Count Raymond Berenguer IV of Barcelona]] conquer the city of [[Tortosa]] the following year.&lt;ref&gt;Villegas-Aristizábal, L. (2009), &quot;Anglo-Norman involvement in the conquest of Tortosa and Settlement of Tortosa, 1148–1180&quot;, ''Crusades'' 8, pp. 63–129&lt;/ref&gt; In the Holy Land by 1150, both the kings of France and Germany had returned to their countries without any result. St. Bernard of Clairvaux, who in his preachings had encouraged the Second Crusade, was upset with the amount of misdirected violence and slaughter of the Jewish population of the Rhineland. North Germans and Danes attacked the [[Wends]] during the 1147 [[Wendish Crusade]], which was unsuccessful as well.

===Third Crusade 1187–1192===
{{Main|Third Crusade}}
[[File:Richard I of England - Palace of Westminster - 24042004.jpg|thumb|left|A statue of king [[Richard I of England]] (Richard the Lionheart), outside the [[Palace of Westminster]] in London.]]

The Muslims had long fought among themselves, but they were finally united by [[Saladin]], who created a single powerful state.&lt;ref&gt;P. M. Holt, &quot;Saladin and His Admirers: A Biographical Reassessment,&quot; ''Bulletin of the School of Oriental and African Studies, University of London,''  Vol. 46, No. 2 (1983), pp. 235-239 [http://www.jstor.org/pss/615389 in JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt;  Following his victory at the [[Battle of Hattin]] he easily overwhelmed the disunited crusaders in 1187 and all of the crusader holdings except a few coastal cities. The Byzantines, fearful of the crusaders, made an alliance with Saladin.

Saladin's victories shocked Europe. On hearing news of the [[Siege of Jerusalem (1187)]], [[Urban III|Pope Urban III]] died of a heart attack on 19 October 1187. On 29 October [[Pope Gregory VIII]] issued a [[papal bull|bull]] ''[[Audita tremendi]]'', proposing the [[Third Crusade]]. To reverse this disaster Emperor [[Frederick I, Holy Roman Emperor|Frederick I Barbarossa]] (r. 1152-1190) of Germany, King [[Philip II of France|Philip II Augustus]] of France, (r. 1180-1223), and King [[Richard I of England|Richard the Lion-Hearted]] (r. 1189-1199) of England established a crusade; the pope's role was minor. Frederick died en route and few of his men reached the Holy Land. The other two armies arrived but were beset by political quarrels. King Philip feigned illness and returned to France, there scheming to win back the duchy of Normandy from Richard's control.  Richard captured the island of [[Cyprus]] from the Byzantines in 1191.&lt;ref name=lewis/&gt;  Cyprus served as a Crusader base for centuries to come, and remained in European hands until 1571.&lt;ref name=lewis/&gt; After [[Siege of Acre (1189–1191)|a long siege]], Richard the Lionheart recaptured the city of [[Acre, Israel|Acre]] and placed the entire Muslim garrison under captivity (they were executed after a series of failed negotiations).  The Crusader army headed south along the Mediterranean coast. They defeated the Muslims near [[Arsuf]], recaptured the port city of [[Jaffa]], and were in sight of Jerusalem.&lt;ref name=lewis/&gt;  However, Richard did not believe he would be able to hold Jerusalem once it was captured, as the majority of Crusaders would then return to Europe, and the crusade ended without the taking of Jerusalem.&lt;ref name=lewis/&gt; Richard left the following year after negotiating a treaty with Saladin. The treaty allowed trade for merchants and unarmed Christian pilgrims to make pilgrimages to the Holy Land (Jerusalem), while it remained under Muslim control.

Richard the Lion-Hearted's exploits gave rise to the legends of the Lion-Hearted, and, through them, Richard acquired a greatly exaggerated posthumous prestige. More showman than statesman, a brave knight but a bad king, his stature was measured by [[Winston Churchill]]: &quot;His life was one magnificent parade which, when ended, left only an empty plain.&quot; Richard did regain Acre and Jaffa for the Christians, but that was all. The agreement he finally reached with Saladin gave pilgrims free access to Jerusalem and little else. The city itself and the adjoining kingdom, except for some coastal cities, were still subject to the same law—that of the Koran, not the Bible.&lt;ref&gt;Charles M. Brand, &quot;The Byzantines and Saladin, 1185-1192: Opponents of the Third Crusade,&quot; ''Speculum,'' Vol. 37, No. 2 (Apr., 1962), pp. 167-181 [http://www.jstor.org/pss/2849946 in JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;A recent popular account is James Reston, Jr., ''Warriors of God: Richard the Lionheart and Saladin in the Third Crusade'' (2005)&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:LatinEmpire2.png|thumb|The Latin Empire and the Partition of the Byzantine Empire after the [[Fourth Crusade]]. (c. 1204)]]

===Fourth Crusade 1202–1204===
{{Main|Fourth Crusade}}

The Fourth Crusade was initiated in 1202 by [[Pope Innocent III]], with the intention of invading the Holy Land through Egypt. Because the Crusaders lacked the funds to pay for the fleet and provisions that they had contracted from the [[Republic of Venice|Venetians]], [[Doge of Venice|Doge]] [[Enrico Dandolo]] enlisted the crusaders to restore the Christian city of Zara ([[Zadar]]) to obedience. At this point, they lost the support of the pope who considered them excommunicated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://boisestate.edu/courses/crusades/4th/08.shtml |title=The Crusades - home page |publisher=Boisestate.edu |date= |accessdate=2012-08-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because they subsequently lacked provisions and time on their vessel lease, the leaders decided to go to [[Constantinople]], where they attempted to place a Byzantine exile on the throne. After a series of misunderstandings and outbreaks of violence, the Crusaders [[Siege of Constantinople (1204)|sacked the city]] in 1204, and established the so-called [[Latin Empire]] and a series of other [[Frankokratia|Crusader states]] throughout the territories of the Greek Byzantine Empire. While deploring the means, the pope finally supported this apparent forced reunion between the Eastern and Western churches. This is often seen as the final breaking point of the [[East–West Schism|Great Schism]] between the [[Eastern Orthodox Church]] and (Western) [[Roman Catholic Church]].

===Albigensian Crusade===
{{Main|Albigensian Crusade}}
[[File:Albigensian Crusade 01.jpg|thumb|[[Pope Innocent III]] excommunicating the Albigensians (left), Massacre against the Albigensians by the crusaders (right)]]

The [[Albigensian Crusade]] was launched in 1209 to eliminate the [[heresy|heretical]] [[Cathars]] of [[Occitania]] (the south of modern-day [[France]]).&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,897752-1,00.html Massacre of the Pure].&quot; ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]''. 28 April 1961.&lt;/ref&gt; It was a decades-long struggle that had as much to do with the concerns of northern France to extend its control southwards as it did with heresy. In the end, both the Cathars and the independence of southern France were exterminated.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/144695/Crusades/235534/Crusades-of-the-13th-century Crusades of the 13th century]. Britannica Onlince Encyclopedia.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Children's Crusade===
{{Main|Children's Crusade}}
The chronicles report a spontaneous youth movement in France and Germany in 1212 attracting large numbers of peasant teenagers and young people (few were under age 15){{citation needed|date=July 2012}}. They were convinced they could succeed where older and more sinful crusaders had failed: the miraculous power of their faith would triumph where the force of arms had not. Many parish priests and parents encouraged such religious fervour and urged them on. The pope and bishops opposed the attempt but failed to stop it entirely. The French movement was led by Stephen, a shepherd-boy of about twelve years old from the small town of Cloyes in the Orléannais. Stephen, as befitted the leader, insisted on having a gaily decorated cart for himself, with a canopy to shade him from the sun. At his side rode boys of noble birth, each rich enough to possess a horse. No one resented the inspired prophet travelling in comfort. On the contrary, he was treated as a saint, and locks of his hair and pieces of his garments were collected as precious relics. They took the road past Tours and Lyons, making for Marseilles. It was a painful journey. The summer was unusually hot. They depended on charity for their food, and the drought left little to spare in the country, and water was scarce. Many of the children died by the wayside. Others dropped out and tried to wander home. But at last the little Crusade reached Marseilles. After a few days two merchants of Marseilles, called, according to tradition, Hugh the Iron and William the Pig, offered to put ships at their disposal and to carry them free of charge, for the glory of God, to Palestine. Stephen eagerly accepted the kindly offer. Seven vessels were hired by the merchants, and the children were taken aboard and set out to sea. Eighteen years passed before there was any further news of them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Steven Kreis&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Steven Kreis |url=http://www.historyguide.org/ancient/children.html |title=The Children's Crusades (1212) |publisher=Historyguide.org |date=2006-02-28 |accessdate=2012-08-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A band of several thousand youths and young men led by a German boy called Nicholas, from a Rhineland village had gathered at [[Cologne]] and set out for Italy. About a third survived the march over the Alps and got as far as [[Genoa]]; Stephen's group from France came to [[Marseilles]]. The luckier ones eventually managed to get safely home, but many others were sold as slaves in Marseilles.  Little is known of the return journey of Stephen from France or Nicolas from Germany. Many of the children, especially the girls, could not face again the ardours of the road and stayed behind in some Italian town or village. Only a few stragglers found their way back next spring to the Rhineland. Nicholas was probably not amongst them. But the angry parents whose children had perished insisted on the arrest of his father, who had, it seems, encouraged the boy out of vainglory. He was taken and hanged.&lt;ref name=&quot;Steven Kreis&quot;/&gt; The sources are scattered and unclear and historians are still not sure exactly what happened to many of the thousands of children.&lt;ref&gt;Dana C. Munro, &quot;The Children's Crusade,&quot; ''The American Historical Review,'' Vol. 19, No. 3 (Apr., 1914), pp. 516-524 [http://www.jstor.org/pss/1835076 in JSTOR]; and Norman P. Zacour, &quot;The Children's Crusade,&quot; in R. L.  Wolff, and H. W. Hazard, eds., ''The later Crusades, 1189-1311'' (1969) pp. 325-342, esp. 330-37 [http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/History/History-idx?type=article&amp;did=HISTORY.CRUSTWO.I0023&amp;isize=M online edition]&lt;/ref&gt; In more recent times it is considered doubtful that there was any such expedition.&lt;!--see main article for much detail--&gt;

===Fifth Crusade 1217–1221===
{{Main|Fifth Crusade}}

By processions, prayers, and preaching, the Church attempted to set another crusade afoot, and the [[Fourth Council of the Lateran]] (1215) formulated a plan for the recovery of the Holy Land. In the first phase, a crusading force from [[Austria]] and [[Hungary]] joined the forces of the king of Jerusalem and the [[Principality of Antioch|prince of Antioch]] to take back Jerusalem. In the second phase, crusader forces achieved a remarkable feat in the capture of [[Damietta]] in Egypt in 1219, but under the urgent insistence of the [[papal legate]], [[Pelagio Galvani|Pelagius]], they then launched a foolhardy attack on [[Cairo]] in July 1221. The crusaders were turned back after their dwindling supplies led to a forced retreat. A night-time attack by the ruler of Egypt, the powerful [[Ayyubid]] [[Sultan]] [[Al-Kamil]], resulted in a great number of crusader losses and eventually in the surrender of the army. Al-Kamil agreed to an eight-year peace agreement with Europe.

Al-Kamil had put a bounty of a Byzantine gold piece for every Christian head brought to him during the war. During 1219, [[St. Francis of Assisi]] crossed the battle lines at Damietta in order to speak with Al-Kamil. He and his companion Illuminatus were captured and beaten and brought before the Sultan. St. Bonaventure, in his Major Life of St. Francis, says that the Sultan was impressed by Francis and spent some time with him. Francis was given safe passage and although he was offered many gifts, all he accepted was a horn for calling the faithful to prayer. This act eventually led to the establishment of the [[Franciscan#Franciscan Custody of the Holy Land|Franciscan Custody of the Holy Land]].

===Sixth Crusade 1228–1229===
{{Main|Sixth Crusade}}
[[File:Dirham struck in Acre by Christians 1216-1241.jpg|thumb|left|[[Dirham]] struk by Christians between 1216-1241 with Arabic inscriptions.]]
[[File:Fridrich2 Al-Kamil.jpg|thumb|[[Emperor Frederick II]] (left) meets [[al-Kamil]] (right), from a manuscript of the ''[[Nuova Cronica]]'' by [[Giovanni Villani]]]]
[[Emperor Frederick II]] had repeatedly vowed a crusade but failed to live up to his words, for which he was excommunicated by [[Pope Gregory IX]] in 1228. He nonetheless set sail from [[Brindisi]], landed in [[Acre, Israel|Saint-Jean d'Acre]]. There were no battles as Frederick made a peace treaty with [[Al-Kamil]], the ruler of Egypt. This treaty allowed Christians to rule over most of Jerusalem and a strip of territory from Acre to Jerusalem, while the Muslims were given control of the [[Dome of the Rock]] and the [[Al-Aqsa Mosque]]. Thus he achieved unexpected success. In 1225 he married Yolanda, the young heiress to the kingdom of Jerusalem; upon her death in 1228, Frederick crowned himself king of Jerusalem.&lt;ref&gt;Ernest Kantorowicz, ''Frederick the 2nd: 1194-1250'' (1957)&lt;/ref&gt; The peace lasted for about ten years. Many of the Muslims though were not happy with Al-Kamil for giving up control of Jerusalem. In 1244, following the [[Siege of Jerusalem (1244)|siege of Jerusalem]], the Muslims regained control of the city.&lt;ref name=&quot;oxfordislamicstudies.com&quot;/&gt;

===Seventh Crusade 1248–1254===
{{Main|Seventh Crusade}}

The papal interests represented by the [[Knights Templar|Templars]] brought on a conflict with Egypt in 1243, and in the following year a [[Khwārazm-Shāh dynasty|Khwarezmian]] force summoned by the latter stormed Jerusalem. The crusaders were drawn into battle at [[Battle of La Forbie|La Forbie]] in [[Gaza]]. The crusader army and its Bedouin mercenaries were completely defeated within forty-eight hours by [[Baibars]]' force of [[Khwārazm-Shāh dynasty|Khwarezmian]] tribesmen. This battle is considered by many historians to have been the death knell to the [[Outremer|Kingdom of Outremer.]]

[[Louis IX of France]] organized a crusade against Egypt from 1248 to 1254, leaving from the newly constructed port of [[Aigues-Mortes]] in southern France.  The crusaders were decisively defeated en-route to Cairo and King Louis was captured; the Arabs demanded and received a huge ransom for the release of the hapless king.&lt;ref&gt;Joseph R. Strayer, &quot;The Crusades of Louis IX,&quot; in R. L.  Wolff and H. W. Hazard, eds., ''The later Crusades, 1189-1311'' (1969) pp. 487-521 [http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/History/History-idx?type=goto&amp;id=History.CrusTwo&amp;isize=M&amp;submit=Go+to+page&amp;page=487 online edition];  Peter Jackson, ''The Seventh Crusade, 1244-1254'' (2007) [http://www.amazon.com/Seventh-Crusade-12441254-Texts-Translation/dp/0754657221/ref=sr_1_5?ie=UTF8&amp;s=books&amp;qid=1205399558&amp;sr=8-5 excerpt and text search]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Eighth Crusade 1270===
{{Main|Eighth Crusade}}
Ignoring his advisers, in 1270 [[Louis IX of France|King Louis IX]] again attacked the Arabs in Tunis in North Africa. He picked the hottest season of the year for campaigning and his army was devastated by disease. The king himself died, ending the last major attempt to take the Holy Land.&lt;ref&gt;Joseph R. Strayer, &quot;The Crusades of Louis IX,&quot; in R. L.  Wolff and H. W. Hazard, eds., ''The later Crusades, 1189-1311'' (1969) pp. 487-521 [http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/History/History-idx?type=goto&amp;id=History.CrusTwo&amp;isize=M&amp;submit=Go+to+page&amp;page=487 online edition]&lt;/ref&gt;  The numbering of crusades is problematical. The Eighth Crusade is sometimes counted as the Seventh, if the Fifth and Sixth Crusades are counted as a single crusade. The Ninth Crusade is sometimes also counted as part of the Eighth.

===Ninth Crusade 1271–1272===
{{Main|Ninth Crusade}}
[[File:ChristianStatesInTheLevant.jpg|thumb|Christian states in the [[Levant]]]]

The future [[Edward I of England]] undertook another expedition against [[Baibars]] in 1271, after having accompanied Louis on the Eighth Crusade. Louis died in Tunisia. The Ninth Crusade was deemed a failure and ended the Crusades in the Middle East.&lt;ref&gt;Dore's Illustrations of the Crusades By Gustave Dore, Dore&lt;/ref&gt;

In their later years, faced with the threat of the Egyptian [[Mamluk]]s, the Crusaders' hopes rested with a [[Franco-Mongol alliance]]. The [[Ilkhanate]]'s [[Mongols]] were thought to be sympathetic to Christianity, and the Frankish princes were most effective in gathering their help, engineering their invasions of the Middle East on several occasions.&lt;ref&gt;David Nicolle, ''Crusader Warfare Volume II: Muslims, Mongols and the Struggle against the Crusades'' (2007)&lt;/ref&gt;  Although the Mongols successfully attacked as far south as Damascus on these campaigns, the ability to effectively coordinate with Crusades from the west was repeatedly frustrated most notably at the [[Battle of Ain Jalut]] in 1260. The Mamluks, led by Baibars, eventually made good their pledge to cleanse the entire Middle East of the Franks. With the fall of [[Principality of Antioch|Antioch]] (1268), [[County of Tripoli|Tripoli]] (1289), and [[Siege of Acre (1291)|Acre]] (1291), those Christians unable to leave the cities were massacred or [[History of slavery|enslaved]] and the last traces of Christian rule in the [[Levant]] disappeared.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Gazetteer/Places/Asia/Armenia/_Texts/KURARM/30*.html |title=Hetoum II (1289‑1297) |publisher=Penelope.uchicago.edu |date= |accessdate=2012-08-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.historynet.com/wars_conflicts/ancient_medieval_wars/3028006.html?showAll=y&amp;c=y |title=Third Crusade: Siege of Acre |publisher=Historynet.com |date= |accessdate=2010-04-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Aftermath====
The island of [[Arwad|Ruad]], three kilometers from the Syrian shore, was occupied for several years by the [[Knights Templar]] but was ultimately lost to the [[Mamluk]]s in the [[Siege of Ruad]] on September 26, 1302. The [[Armenian Kingdom of Cilicia]], which was not itself a crusader state, and was not Latin Christian, but was closely associated with the crusader states and was ruled by the Latin Christian Lusignan dynasty for its last 34 years, survived until 1375. Other echoes of the crusader states survived for longer, but well away from the Holy Land itself. The Knights of St John carved out a new territory based on the Aegean island of Rhodes, which they ruled until [[Siege of Rhodes (1522)|1522]]. Cyprus remained under the rule of the House of Lusignan until 1474/89 (the precise date depends on how Venice's highly unusual takeover is interpreted – see [[Caterina Cornaro]]) and subsequently that of Venice until 1570. By this time the Knights of St John had moved to Malta – even further from the Holy Land – which they ruled until 1798.&lt;ref&gt;William Lannin, ''Historic review of the order of the knights hospitallers of St. John of Jerusalem, of Rhodes, and Malta'' (1922) [http://books.google.com/books?id=3w4MAAAAYAAJ  online edition]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Northern Crusades===
{{Main|Northern Crusades}}

====Crusades of the Teutonic Order====
[[File:Knight livonia.png|thumb|The knight of The [[Livonian Brothers of the Sword]].]]
A German religious and military order originally founded during the siege of Acre in the Third Crusade and modeled after the Knights Templar and Hospitalers, the Teutonic Knights moved to eastern Europe early in the 13th century.&lt;ref&gt;Charles Moeller, &quot;Teutonic Order,&quot; [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/14541b.htm ''Catholic Encyclopedia'' (1912) vol 14 online]&lt;/ref&gt; There, under their grand master, Hermann von Salza, they became powerful and prominent. 
In 1198, the Teutonic Order started the [[Livonian Crusade]]. Despite numerous setbacks and rebellions, by 1290, [[Livonians]], [[Latgalians]], [[Selonians]], [[Estonians]] (including [[Oeselians]]), [[Curonians]] and [[Semigallians]] had been all gradually subjugated. [[Denmark]] and [[Sweden]] also participated in fight against Estonians.

In 1229, responding to an appeal from [[Konrad of Masovia|the Duke of Poland]], they began a crusade against the pagan Slavs of Prussia. They became sovereigns over lands they conquered over the next century. In a series of campaigns, the Teutonic Knights gained control over the whole Baltic coast, founding numerous towns and fortresses and establishing Christianity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Edgar N.|last=Johnson|title=The German Crusade on the Baltic,|url=http://digital.library.wisc.edu/1711.dl/History.CrusThree|editor=H. W. Hazard|work=A History of the Crusades, Volume III: The fourteenth and fifteenth centuries|year=1975|pages=545–585}}&lt;/ref&gt; A later conflict between Teutonic Knights and Christian Poland resulted in the [[Battle of Grunwald]]. 

The Teutonic Order's attempts to conquer [[Eastern Orthodox Church|Orthodox]] [[Russia]] (particularly the Republics of [[Pskov Republic|Pskov]] and [[Novgorod Republic|Novgorod]]), an enterprise endorsed by [[Pope Gregory IX]], can also be considered as a part of the Northern Crusades. One of the major blows for the idea of the conquest of Russia was the [[Battle of the Ice]] in 1242. With or without the Pope's blessing, Sweden also undertook several [[Swedish–Novgorodian Wars|crusades against Orthodox Novgorod]]. A later conflict between Teutonic Knights and Christian Poland resulting in the [[Battle of Grunwald]].

====Swedish Crusades====
{{Unreferenced section|date=December 2007|reason=article had several cn tags dated December 2007 and no references; this &quot;unreferenced&quot; added January 2012 with date of the replaced cns}}
[[File:Swedish crusaders in Finland.gif|thumb|left|Swedish crusaders in Finland]]
National-romanticist Swedish and Finnish historians in the nineteenth century gave the name &quot;crusades&quot; to military expeditions which resulted in the [[Sweden|Swedish]] conquest of [[Finland]] in the [[Middle Ages]].

The [[First Swedish Crusade]], considered mythical by some historians, may have taken place around 1155 AD.

There is no surviving historical record for the [[Second Swedish Crusade]] in about 1249 AD, but it is believed to have taken place, and resulted in the known conquest of southwestern Finland. The [[Third Swedish Crusade]], against [[Novgorod]], is documented by both parties to the conflict.

According to archaeological finds, Finland was largely Christian before these crusades; they can be seen as military expeditions for territorial gain, rather than religious reasons.

===Other===

====Wendish Crusade====
Contemporaneous with the Second Crusade, [[Saxons]] and [[Danes (Germanic tribe)|Danes]] fought against [[Polabian Slavs]] in the 1147 [[Wendish Crusade]].

====Stedinger Crusade====
Between 1232 and 1234, there was a crusade against the [[Stedingen|Stedingers]]. This crusade was special, because the Stedingers were not heathens or heretics, but fellow Roman Catholics. They were free [[Frisians|Frisian]] farmers who resented attempts of the count of [[Duchy of Oldenburg|Oldenburg]] and the archbishop [[Archbishopric of Bremen|Bremen-Hamburg]] to make an end to their freedoms. The archbishop excommunicated them, and [[Pope Gregory IX]] declared a crusade in 1232. The Stedingers were defeated in 1234.

====Aragonese Crusade====
The '''[[Aragonese Crusade]]''', or Crusade of Aragón, was declared by [[Pope Martin IV]] against the [[Peter III of Aragon|King of Aragón, Peter III the Great]], in 1284 and 1285.

====Alexandrian Crusade====
The '''[[Alexandrian Crusade]]''' of October 1365 was a minor seaborne crusade against Muslim [[Alexandria]] led by [[Peter I of Cyprus]]. His motivation was at least as commercial as religious.

====Norwich Crusade====
See [[Norwich Crusade]].

====Mahdian Crusade====
The [[Mahdian Crusade]] of Summer 1390 was a French-Genoese enterprise against Muslim [[pirate]]s in North Africa and their main base at [[Mahdia]] led by [[Louis II, Duke of Bourbon]].
[[File:Siege of Nándorfehérvár.jpg|thumb|The [[Siege of Belgrade (1456)|Siege of Belgrade]] in 1456]]

====Crusades in the Balkans====
To counter the expanding [[Ottoman Empire]], several crusades were launched in the 15th century.
The most notable are:
* the '''[[Crusade of Nicopolis]]''' (1396) organized by [[Sigismund of Luxemburg]], king of Hungary, culminated in the [[Battle of Nicopolis]]
* the '''[[Crusade of Varna]]''' (1444) led by the Polish-Hungarian king, [[Władysław III of Poland|Władysław Warneńczyk]], ended in the [[Battle of Varna]]
* and the '''[[Crusade of 1456]]''' organized to lift the [[Siege of Belgrade (1456)|Siege of Belgrade]] led by [[John Hunyadi]] and [[Giovanni da Capistrano]]

====Crusade against the Tatars====
In 1259, Mongols led by [[Burundai]] and [[Nogai Khan]] ravaged the principality of [[Halych-Volynia]], [[Lithuania]] and [[Poland]]. After that [[Pope Alexander IV]] tried without success to create a crusade against the [[Blue Horde]] (see [[Mongol invasion of Poland]]).

In the 14th century, Khan [[Tokhtamysh]] combined the Blue and White Hordes forming the [[Golden Horde]]. It seemed that the power of the Golden Horde had begun to rise, but in 1389, Tokhtamysh made the disastrous decision of waging war on his former master, the great [[Tamerlane]]. Tamerlane's hordes rampaged through southern [[Russia]], crippling the Golden Horde's economy and practically wiping out its defenses in those lands.

After losing the war, Tokhtamysh was then dethroned by the party of Khan Temur Kutlugh and Emir Edigu, supported by Tamerlane. When Tokhtamysh asked [[Vytautas the Great]] for assistance in retaking the Horde, the latter readily gathered a huge army which included Lithuanians, Ruthenians, Russians, [[Mongols]], [[Moldavia]]ns, Poles, Romanians and [[Teutonic Knights]].

In 1398, the huge army moved from Moldavia and conquered the southern steppe all the way to the [[Dnieper River]] and northern [[Crimea]]. Inspired by their great successes, Vytautas declared a 'Crusade against the Tatars' with [[Pope Boniface IX|Papal]] backing. Thus, in 1399, the army of Vytautas once again moved on the Horde. His army met the Horde's at the [[Vorskla River]], slightly inside Lithuanian territory.

Although the Lithuanian army was well equipped with [[cannon]], it could not resist a rear attack from Edigu's reserve units. Vytautas hardly escaped alive. Many princes of his kin—possibly as many as 20—were killed (for example, [[Stefan Musat]], [[Prince of Moldavia]] and two of his brothers, while a fourth was badly injured {{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}), and the victorious Tatars besieged [[Kiev]]. &quot;And the Christian blood flowed like water, up to the Kievan walls,&quot; as one chronicler put it. Meanwhile, Temur Kutlugh died from the wounds received in the battle, and Tokhtamysh was killed by one of his own men.

====Hussite Crusade====
[[File:Husité - Jenský kodex.jpg|thumb|170px|The battle between the Hussite warriors and the Crusaders, Jena Codex, 15th century]]
The Hussite Crusade(s), also known as the &quot;[[Hussite Wars]],&quot; or the &quot;Bohemian Wars,&quot; involved the military actions against and amongst the followers of [[Jan Hus]] in [[Bohemia#Hussite Bohemia|Bohemia]] in the period 1420 to circa 1434. The Hussite Wars were arguably the first European war in which hand-held gunpowder weapons such as [[musket]]s made a decisive contribution. The [[Taborite]] faction of the [[Hussite]] warriors were basically infantry, and their many defeats of larger armies with heavily armoured knights helped affect the infantry revolution. In the end, it was an inconclusive war.

==Role of women==
Most writings stress the crusades as a masculine movement symbolic of honour and male courage. But women were also involved behind the scenes, and as direct victims.&lt;ref&gt;See Natasha Hodgson, ''Women, Crusading and the Holy Land in Historical Narrative'' (Boydell, 2007)&lt;/ref&gt;

Women at home were intricately connected with the crusade movement by aiding the recruitment of crusading men, taking on extra duties in their absence, and supporting them financially and with prayer.  Their encouragement and familial ties created kinship connections which made the prospect of taking the cross more appealing for those risking their lives.&lt;ref&gt;Natasha Hodgson, ''Women, Crusading and the Holy Land in Historical Narrative'' (Boydell, 2007) 39-44&lt;/ref&gt; Arguably the most significant role that women played in the West during the crusades was their preservation of the home. The best known example is of [[Adela of Normandy|Adela of Blois]], wife of [[Stephen II, Count of Blois|Stephen of Blois]] whose correspondence with her husband while he was on Crusade and she was at home managing his fief has survived in part.  It appears she was rather more keen on his crusading than he was.  Men could journey to [[The Holy Land]] without having to worry about their home because regents, often wives or mothers, were in charge of their estates and families.&lt;ref&gt;Jonathan Riley-Smith. The First Crusaders 1096–1131, New York, NY: Cambridge University Press 1997, 99.&lt;/ref&gt; The Church recognised that concern about their families and estates might discourage crusaders, however, so they instituted special papal protections for them as part of the crusading privilege.&lt;ref&gt;The earliest reference comes from Guibert of Nogent c1108. See Natasha Hodgson, ''Women, Crusading and the Holy Land in Historical Narrative'' (Boydell, 2007), 110-112&lt;/ref&gt;

Even though most women showed their support for the crusades at home, some women took the cross themselves to go on the crusade. Aristocratic women who joined the movement often found that they had new positions of authority they did not have in the West. [[Eleanor of Aquitaine]], the wealthy queen of France and the wife of king [[Louis VII of France|Louis VII]], took the cross from [[St. Bernard of Clairvaux]] on Easter Sunday 1145 to join her husband.&lt;ref&gt;Roy Douglas Davis Owen. Eleanor of Aquitaine : queen and legend, Oxford, UK; Cambridge, Mass: Blackwell Publishing 1993, 22.&lt;/ref&gt; Another woman who had ultimate political power in the East was [[Melisende of Jerusalem]], who under law gained hereditary rights to the crown upon her husband's death. Like Eleanor, Melisende never led troops into battle, but she did participate in acts of political diplomacy. Less successful was her granddaughter [[Sibylla of Jerusalem]], whose choice of husband had been a crucial political issue since her childhood.  Her second marriage to [[Guy of Lusignan]] made him the [[king-consort]] on the death of [[Baldwin IV]], with disastrous results. While most women were there to help and care for the crusading men by bringing them water or raising their spirits by offering emotional support, there were women who had specific tasks which defined their feminine characteristics like the washerwoman.&lt;ref&gt;Susan B. Edington and Sarah Lambert ed. Gendering the Crusades, New York: Columbia University Press 2002, 98.&lt;/ref&gt;

The permanent residents of the Crusader kingdoms, if born in Europe, had usually come unmarried.  Very many married women from [[Apulia]] in Southern Italy, where living conditions were often harsh, encouraged young women to take ship for Palestine in the knowledge that many men there were looking for wives.

The most controversial role that women had in the crusades was of course taking an active part, which threatened their femininity. Accounts are contradictory. The accounts of women fighting come mostly from Muslim historians whose aim was to portray Christian women as barbaric and ungodly because of their acts of killing.  The contrasting view from Christian accounts portray women fighting only in emergency situations for the preservation of the camps and their own lives. In these cases women are seen as more feminine while behaving like 'proper women'.&lt;ref&gt;Helen Nicholson. &quot;Women on the Third Crusade. ''Journal of Medieval History'' (23) no.4 (1997) p. 337.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Virtually all crusade writings came from men, and women would have been interpreted subjectively no matter what roles they played.

==Criticism==
Elements of the Crusades were criticized by some from the time of their inception in 1095. For example, [[Roger Bacon]] felt the Crusades were not effective because, &quot;those who survive, together with their children, are more and more embittered against the Christian faith.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;AC&quot;&gt;Riley-Smith, Jonathan. ''The Atlas of the Crusades'' New York: Facts on File, 1990. ISBN 0-8160-2186-4.&lt;/ref&gt; In spite of such criticism, the movement was widely supported in Europe long after the fall of Acre in 1291.{{citation needed|date=October 2011}}

[[Francis of Assisi|St. Francis of Assisi]] crossed enemy lines to meet the Sultan of Egypt. Hoeberichts cast doubt on the intentions most Christian historians assign to Francis.{{clarify|not one assigned in this subsection|date=October 2011}}

From the fall of Acre forward, the Crusades to recover [[Kingdom of Jerusalem|Jerusalem]] and the Christian East were largely lost. Later, [[Age of Enlightenment|18th century Enlightenment thinkers]] judged the Crusaders harshly. Likewise, some modern historians in the West expressed moral outrage. In the 1950s, Sir [[Steven Runciman]] wrote a resounding condemnation:

:&quot;High ideals were besmirched by cruelty and greed ... the Holy War was nothing more than a long act of intolerance in the name of God&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;AC&quot;/&gt;

[[Ibn Jubayr]]'s described the Muslims living under the Christian crusaders' [[Kingdom of Jerusalem]]:
{{bquote|We left [[Toron|Tibnin]] by a road running past farms where Muslims live who do very well under the Franks-may Allah preserve us from such a temptation! The regulations imposed on them are the handing over of half of the grain crop at the time of harvest and the payment of a poll tax of one dinar and seven qirats, together with a light duty on their fruit trees. The Muslims own their own houses and rule themselves in their own way. This is the way the farms and big villages are organized in Frankish territory. Many Muslims are sorely tempted to settle here when they see the far from comfortable conditions in which their brethren live in the districts under Muslim rule. Unfortunately for the Muslims, they have always reason for complaint about the injustices of their chiefs in the lands governed by their coreligionists, whereas they can have nothing but praise for the conduct of the Franks, whose justice they can always rely on.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;''[http://books.google.com/books?id=YdzpSO1_Pm8C&amp;pg=PA172&amp;dq&amp;hl=en#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false The crusaders]''&quot;. Régine Pernoud (2003). p.172. ISBN 0-89870-949-0.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

One aspect of the crusades that shocked some easterners was the formation in the west of military religious orders.&lt;ref&gt;Kolbaba, T. M., (2000), '' The Byzantine lists: errors of the Latins'' (University of Illinois) -Bishops and priests in battle p49ff.&lt;/ref&gt; This went against canon law.&lt;ref&gt;Canon VII - The Fourth Ecumenical Council. The Council of Chalcedon.&lt;/ref&gt;

Another criticism was raised that the crusaders had sworn to uphold the [[Alexios I Komnenos|emperor's]] claims to the holy land, but upon taking Jerusalem the crusaders established &quot;Latin&quot; states there.

{{quote|&quot;After several confrontations and some stand offs Godfrey agreed to swear fealty and recognition of Alexius over all the lands that he conquered.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.angevin.org/first_crusade.htm/ First crusade]{{dead link|date=August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Further criticisms have been leveled; the misdirection of the crusading movement being one. This is especially evident in the Fourth Crusade which instead of attacking Islam attacked another Christian power - the (Eastern) Roman Empire, viewed as a ''change in direction,''&lt;ref&gt;Vasiliev, A. A., (1952) ''History of the Byzantine Empire. 2, Volume 2,''(University of Wisconsin Press), p457&lt;/ref&gt; not just literally, but in the ethos behind the movement where material considerations became more pronounced.&lt;ref&gt;''Ibid.'', p450&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==

===Historiography===
{{Main|Historiography of the Crusades}}
Historians are largely agreed on the facts of the crusades and their long-term impact, but differ sharply regarding their moral interpretation and their wisdom.

===Politics and culture===
The Crusades had an enormous influence on the European [[Middle Ages]]. At times, much of the continent was united under a powerful [[Papacy]], but by the 14th century, the development of centralized bureaucracies (the foundation of the modern [[nation state]]) was well on its way in France, England, Spain, [[Burgundy (region)|Burgundy]], and [[Portugal]], and partly because of the dominance of the church at the beginning of the crusading era.

[[File:Saladin and Guy.jpg|thumb|20th century depiction of a victorious [[Saladin]]]]
Although Europe had been exposed to [[Islamic culture]] for centuries through contacts in Iberian Peninsula and [[Sicily]], much knowledge in areas such as science, medicine, and architecture was transferred from the Islamic to the western world during the crusade era.

The military experiences of the crusades also had a limited degree of influence on European castle design; for example, [[Caernarfon Castle]], in [[Wales]], begun in 1283, directly reflects the style of fortresses Edward I had observed while fighting in the Crusades.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://uktv.co.uk/blighty/listing/aid/582330 |title=Caernarfon Castle |publisher=Uktv.co.uk |date=2007-03-12 |accessdate=2010-04-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Crusader society in the Kingdom of Jerusalem was also characterized by a culture of innovation, including in economic and social structures, governance and taxation, social mobility, and agricultural technology.

Catholic historians have long argued that the Crusades opened up European culture to the world, especially Asia, and gave Christian Europe a more cosmopolitan world view that led to its world-wide empires. The ''Catholic Encyclopedia'' of 1911 stated:

{{cquote|The Crusades brought about results of which the popes had never dreamed, and which were perhaps the most, important of all. They re-established traffic between the East and West, which, after having been suspended for several centuries, was then resumed with even greater energy; they were the means of bringing from the depths of their respective provinces and introducing into the most civilized Asiatic countries Western knights, to whom a new world was thus revealed, and who returned to their native land filled with novel ideas... If, indeed, the Christian civilization of Europe has become universal culture, in the highest sense, the glory redounds, in no small measure, to the Crusades.&quot;&lt;ref name=CathEnc&gt;''Crusades'' in ''The New Catholic Encyclopedia'', New York: McGraw-Hill Book Company, 1966, Vol. IV, p. 508.[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/04543c.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Along with trade, new scientific discoveries and inventions made their way east or west. Arab and classical Greek advances (including the development of [[algebra]], optics, and refinement of engineering) made their way west and sped the course of advancement in European universities that led to the Renaissance in later centuries

The invasions of German crusaders prevented formation of the large Lithuanian state incorporating all Baltic nations and tribes. Lithuania was destined to become a small country and forced to expand to the East looking for resources to combat the crusaders.&lt;ref&gt;{{lt icon}} [http://www.omni.lt/?i$9359_70693$z_373522 Tomas Baranauskas. ''Prūsų sukilimas—prarasta galimybė sukurti kitokią Lietuvą'' (Prussian rebellion—the lost chance of creating different Lithuania). 20 September 2006]&lt;/ref&gt; The Northern Crusades caused great loss of life among the pagan [[Polabian Slavs]], and they consequently offered little opposition to German colonization (known as [[Ostsiedlung]]) of the Elbe-Oder region and were gradually assimilated by the [[Germans]], with the exception of [[Sorbs]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/639735/Wend Wend (people)]. Britannica Online Encyclopedia.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:KnightsTemplarPlayingChess1283.jpg|thumb|[[Knights Templar]] playing chess, ''Libro de los juegos'', 1283]]
The [[Persecution of Jews in the First Crusade|First Crusade]] ignited a long tradition of organized violence against [[Jews]] in European culture.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/History/crusadetime.html Crusades (Christian Warfare with Islam in Palestine)]. Jewishvirtuallibrary.org.&lt;/ref&gt;{{Citation needed|reason=loaded statement not completely supported by citation|date=July 2009}}

The Albigensian Crusade was initiated by the Catholic Church to eliminate the [[Catharism|Cathar heresy]] in [[Languedoc]]. The violence led to France's acquisition of lands with closer cultural and linguistic ties to [[Principality of Catalonia|Catalonia]]. The Albigensian Crusade also had a role in the creation and institutionalization of both the [[Dominican Order]] and the [[Medieval Inquisition]].&lt;ref&gt;Joseph Reese Strayer (1992). &quot;''[http://books.google.com/books?id=lskGFVtySXsC&amp;pg=PA143&amp;dq&amp;hl=en#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false The Albigensian Crusades]''&quot;. [[University of Michigan Press]]. p.143. ISBN 0-472-06476-2&lt;/ref&gt;

===Trade===
The need to raise, transport and supply large armies led to a flourishing of [[Trade route|trade throughout Europe]]. Roads largely unused since the days of [[Roman Empire|Rome]] saw significant increases in traffic as local merchants began to expand their horizons. This was not only because the Crusades ''prepared'' Europe for travel, but also because many ''wanted'' to travel after being reacquainted with the products of the Middle East. This also aided in the beginning of the [[Renaissance]] in Italy, as various Italian [[city-state]]s from the very beginning had important and profitable trading colonies in the crusader states, both in the [[Holy Land]] and later in captured [[Byzantine]] territory.

Increased trade brought many things to Europeans that were once unknown or extremely rare and costly. These goods included a variety of spices, ivory, jade, diamonds, improved glass-manufacturing techniques, early forms of gun powder, oranges, apples, and other Asian crops, and many other products.
&lt;!--UNCITED====Wider geo-political effects====
{{Original research|date=January 2008}}
Despite the ultimate defeat in the [[Middle East]], the Crusaders were successful in regaining the [[Iberian Peninsula]] permanently and slowed down the military expansion of [[Islam]].

The successful international coordination of Crusading forces from different countries, and the reduction (not cessation) in fighting between Christian monarchs that the crusading ideal encouraged, allowed Christian Europe to remain strong in the face of Muslim military expansionism. It is therefore likely that a considerable part of modern Christian Europe (particularly [[Spain]], [[Portugal]], and the [[Balkans]]) would be Muslim today had the Crusades not occurred, and it is furthermore possible that Christianity might have been largely replaced by Islam throughout Europe. &lt;!--improper citation-nor does it work... (This is one traditional Roman Catholic perspective:  [[#Catholic Encyclopedia perspective|See below]].)--&gt;

From a larger perspective, and certainly from that of noted naval/maritime historian [[Archibald Ross Lewis]], the Crusades must be viewed as part of a massive macrohistorical event during which Western Europe, primarily by its ability in naval warfare, amphibious siege, and maritime trade, was able to advance in all spheres of civilization.&lt;ref name=lewis/&gt; Recovering from the [[Dark Ages (historiography)|Dark Ages]] of AD 700–1000, throughout the 11th century Western Europe began to push the boundaries of its civilization.&lt;ref name=lewis/&gt; Prior to the [[First Crusade]] the Italian city-state of [[Venice]], along with the [[Byzantine Empire]], had cleared the [[Adriatic Sea]] of Islamic pirates, and loosened the Islamic hold on the [[Mediterranean Sea]] (Byzantine-Muslim War of 1030–1035).&lt;ref name=lewis/&gt; The [[Normans]], with the assistance of the Italian city-states of [[Genoa]] and [[Pisa]], had retaken [[Sicily]] from the Muslims from 1061–1091.&lt;ref name=lewis/&gt; These conflicts prior to the [[First Crusade]] had both retaken Western European territory and weakened the Islamic hold on the Mediterranean, allowing for the rise of Western European Mediterranean trading and naval powers such as the Sicilian Normans and the Italian city-states of Venice, Genoa, and Pisa.&lt;ref name=lewis/&gt;
[[File:Crusade market.jpg|thumb|Model of a Crusader market in [[David's Citadel]] museum, Jerusalem]]
During the Middle Ages, the key trading region of Western Europe was the [[Black Sea]]-[[Mediterranean Sea]]-[[Red Sea]].&lt;ref name=lewis/&gt; It was the aforementioned pre-First Crusade actions, along with the Crusades themselves, which allowed Western Europe to contest the trade of the Mediterranean Sea and Black Sea, for a period which began in the 11th century and would only be ended by the Turkish Ottoman Empire beginning in the mid-to-late 15th century.&lt;ref name=lewis/&gt; This Western European contestation of vital sea lanes allowed the economy of Western Europe to advance to previously unknown degrees, most obviously as regards the Maritime Republics of Venice, Genoa, and Pisa.&lt;ref name=lewis/&gt; Indeed, it is no coincidence that the Renaissance began in Italy, as the Maritime Republics, through their control of the Eastern Mediterranean and Black Seas, were able to return to Italy the ancient knowledge of the Greeks and Romans, as well as the products of distant East Asia.&lt;ref name=lewis/&gt;

Combined with the Mongol Empire, Western Europe traded extensively with East Asia, the security of the Mongol Empire allowing the products of Asia to be brought to such Western European controlled ports as [[Acre, Israel|Acre]], [[Antioch]], [[Caffa|Kaffa]] (on the Black Sea) and even, for a time, Constantinople itself.&lt;ref name=lewis/&gt; The [[Fifth Crusade]] of 1217–1221 and the [[Seventh Crusade]] of 1248–1254 were largely attempts to secure Western European control of the Red Sea trade region, as both Crusades were directed against Egypt, the power base of the [[Ayyubid]], and then [[Mameluke]], [[Sultan]]ates.&lt;ref name=lewis/&gt; It was only in the 14th century, as the stability of trade with Asia collapsed with the Mongol Empire, the [[Mamelukes]] destroyed the Middle Eastern Crusader States, and the rising Ottoman Empire impeded further Western European trade with Asia, that Western Europeans sought alternate trade routes to Asia, ultimately leading to [[Christopher Columbus|Columbus]]'s voyage of 1492.&lt;ref name=lewis/&gt;

===Caucasus===
In the [[Caucasus Mountains]] of [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]], in the remote highland region of [[Khevsureti]], a tribe called the [[Khevsurs]] are thought to possibly be direct descendants of a party of crusaders who got separated from a larger army and have remained in isolation with some of the crusader culture intact. Into the 20th century, relics of armor, weaponry and chain mail were still being used and passed down in such communities. Russian serviceman and ethnographer [[Arnold Zisserman]] who spent 25 years (1842–1867) in the Caucasus, believed the exotic group of Georgian highlanders were descendants of the last Crusaders based on their customs, language, art and other evidence.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://hearstmuseum.berkeley.edu/exhibitions/photo2/photo2_intro.html Images from the Georgia–Chechnya Border, 1970–1980]'', Phoebe A. Hearst Museum of Anthropology.&lt;/ref&gt; American traveler [[Richard Halliburton]] saw and recorded the customs of the tribe in 1935.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.swordhistory.com/excerpts/crusaders.html Sword and Buckler Fighting among the Lost Crusaders]. Excerpts of Halliburton's observations&lt;/ref&gt;

==Etymology and usage==
The crusades were never referred to as such by their participants. The original crusaders were known by various terms, including ''fideles Sancti Petri'' (the faithful of [[Saint Peter]]) or ''{{lang|la|milites Christi}}'' (knights of Christ). They saw themselves as undertaking an ''iter'', a journey, or a ''peregrinatio'', a [[pilgrimage]], though pilgrims were usually forbidden from carrying arms.{{Citation needed|reason=seems highly unlikely given the era, unsupported at pilgrimage pages; also general point needs citation|date=April 2009}}

Like pilgrims, each crusader swore a vow (a ''votus''), to be fulfilled on successfully reaching Jerusalem, and they were granted a cloth cross (''crux'') to be sewn into their clothes. This &quot;taking of the cross&quot;, the ''crux'', eventually became associated with the entire journey; the word &quot;crusade&quot; (coming into English from the Medieval [[French language|French]] ''croisade'' and [[Spanish language|Spanish]] ''cruzada'')&lt;ref&gt;''American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language'', Fourth Edition, Houghton Mifflin Company, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; developed from this.

==Crusades in popular culture==
''[[Kingdom of Heaven (film)|Kingdom of Heaven]]'' (2005) - film directed by [[Ridley Scott]]—a fictionalized account of [[Balian of Ibelin]], a nobleman in the 13th&amp;#8209;century [[Kingdom of Jerusalem]]

==See also==
{{Wikipedia books|The Crusades}}
*[[Bull of the Crusade]]
*[[Byzantine–Ottoman Wars]]
*[[History of the Jews and the Crusades]]
*[[Islamic Golden Age]]
*[[Medieval demography]]
*[[Mongol conquests]]
*[[Ottoman wars in Europe]]
*[[Persecution of Jews in the First Crusade]]
*[[Siege of Antioch (1268)]]
;Some results of the crusades
* [[Crusader states]]
* [[Letter of the Karaite elders of Ascalon]]
* [[List of Crusader castles]]
;Background to crusades
* [[Byzantine–Arab Wars]]
* [[Byzantine–Seljuk Wars]]
* [[Great German Pilgrimage of 1064–1065]]
* [[History of Islam in southern Italy|Islamic conquest of southern Italy]]
* [[Umayyad conquest of Hispania]]
* [[War of Barbastro]]
;Events named &quot;crusade&quot; but not included in historical crusades
* [[Hussite Wars]]
* [[Shepherds' Crusade]]
* [[Tenth Crusade]]
;Media and culture
* [[Art of the Crusades]]
* ''[[Assassin's Creed]]''
* [[Crusade cycle]]
* ''[[Kingdom of Heaven (film)|Kingdom of Heaven]]'' (film)
* [[List of operas set in the Crusades]]
;Knightly Orders:
* [[Knights Hospitaller|Knights of Malta]]
* [[Military order]]s
;Participants
* [[Frisian participation in the Crusades]]
* [[Hashshashin]]
* [[List of principal Crusaders]]
;Famous Opponents:
* [[al-Ashraf Khalil]]
* [[Zengi]]

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

==Citations==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
* {{cite book |author=Asbridge, Thomas |title=The Crusades: The Authoritative History of the War for the Holy Land |year=2011 |publisher=Ecco |isbn= 978-0060787295 }}
* {{cite book |author=Asbridge, Thomas |title=The First Crusade: A New History: The Roots of Conflict between Christianity and Islam |year=2005 |publisher=Oxford University Press |isbn= 978-0195189056}}
* {{cite book |author=Barber, Malcolm |authorlink=Malcolm Barber |title=The Two Cities: Medieval Europe 1050-1320 |publisher=Routledge |location=London |year=1992 |isbn=0-415-09682-0}}
* {{cite encyclopedia |author=Bréhier, Louis |title=Crusades |url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/04543c.htm |encyclopedia=Catholic Encyclopedia'' |year=1908 |volume=4}}
* {{cite encyclopedia|author=Bull, Marcus |title=Origins |encyclopedia= The Oxford History of the Crusades |editor= Riley-Smith, Jonathan |location=New York |publisher=Oxford University Press |year=1999 |pages=15–34|isbn=0-19-280312-3}}
* {{cite book |first=John L. |last=Esposito |url= http://www.amazon.ca/What-Everyone-Needs-about-Islam/dp/0195157133 |title=What Everyone Needs to Know about Islam  }}
* {{cite book |author=Hindley, Geoffrey |title=The Crusades: Islam and Christianity in the Struggle for World Supremacy |publisher=Carrol &amp; Graf |isbn=0-7867-1344-5|location=New York}}
* {{cite book |author=Housley, Norman |authorlink= Norman Housley |title=Contesting the Crusades  |publisher=Blackwell Publishing |location=Malden, MA |year=2006  |isbn=1-4051-1189-5 }}
* {{cite book |author=Lock, Peter |title=Routledge Companion to the Crusades |publisher=Routledge |location=New York |year=2006  |isbn=0-415-39312-4 }}
* {{cite book |author=Madden, Thomas F. |title=The New Concise History of the Crusades |year=2005 |publisher= Rowman &amp; Littlefield |location= Lanham, MD |isbn= 9780742538221}}
* {{cite book |author=Mayer, Hans Eberhard |title=The Crusades |edition=Second|publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Oxford  |year=1988|isbn=0-19-873097-7 }}
* {{cite journal |author=Munro,Dana Carleton |title=The Speech of Pope Urban II at Clermont, 1095 |journal = American Historical Review |volume= 11 |issue= 2 |month=January |year=1906 |pages= 231–242 |jstor=1834642 }}
* {{cite book |author=Nicholle, David |title=The First Crusade 1066-99: Conquest of the Holy Land |series=Campaign |publisher=Osprey |location=Wellingborough, UK |year=2003|isbn=1-84176-515-5}}
* {{cite encyclopedia|author=Pringle, Denys |title=Architecture in Latin East|encyclopedia= The Oxford History of the Crusades |editor= Riley-Smith, Jonathan |location=New York |publisher=Oxford University Press |year=1999 |pages=155–175|isbn=0-19-280312-3}}
* {{cite book |author=Riley-Smith, Jonathan |author-link=Jonathan Riley-Smith |title=The Crusades: A Short History|edition=Second |publisher=Yale University Press |location=New Haven, CT |year=2005  |isbn=0-300-10128-7}}
* {{cite book |author=Wickham, Chris |authorlink= Christopher Wickham |title=The Inheritance of Rome: Illuminating the Dark Ages 400–1000 |publisher=Penguin Books |location=New York |year=2009 |isbn=978-0-14-311742-1}}

==Further reading==

===Introductions===
{{refbegin}}
* Andrea, Alfred J. ''Encyclopedia of the Crusades''. (2003).
* Asbridge, Thomas. ''The First Crusade: A New History: The Roots of Conflict between Christianity and Islam'' (2005) [http://www.amazon.com/First-Crusade-History-Conflict-Christianity/dp/0195189051/ref=pd_bbs_9/103-4827826-5463040?ie=UTF8&amp;s=books&amp;qid=1192595071&amp;sr=8-9 excerpt and text search]
* France, John. ''Western Warfare in the Age of the Crusades, 1000-1300'' (1999) [http://www.questia.com/read/109099963 online edition]
* Hillenbrand, Carole. ''The Crusades, Islamic Perspectives''. (2000). [http://www.amazon.com/Crusades-Islamic-Perspectives-Car-Hillenbrand/dp/1579582109/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;s=books&amp;qid=1205278657&amp;sr=8-1 excerpt and text search]
* Holt, P.M. ''The Age of the Crusades: The Near East from the Eleventh Century to 1517''. (1986).
* Phillips, Jonathan. ''Holy Warriors: A Modern History of the Crusades'' (2010)
* Riley-Smith, Jonathan, ed. ''The Atlas of the Crusades'' (1991)
* Runciman, Steven. ''A History of the Crusades, Volume I: The First Crusade and the Foundations of the Kingdom of Jerusalem.''; ''Volume II: The Kingdom of Jerusalem and the Frankish East 1100-1187.'' and ''Volume III: The Kingdom of Acre and the Later Crusades'' (1951–53), the classic narrative history; hostile toward the crusaders
* Tyerman, Christopher. ''God's War: A New History of the Crusades'' (2006)
{{refend}}

===Specialized studies===
{{refbegin}}
* Abulafia, David. ''Frederick II: A Medieval Emperor'' (1988)
* Baldin, M. W., ed. ''The first hundred years'' (A History of the Crusades, volume, I) [http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/History/History-idx?id=History.CrusOne 1969 online]
* Boas, Adrian J. ''Jerusalem in the Time of the Crusades: Society, Landscape, and Art in the Holy City under Frankish Rule'' (2001) [http://www.questia.com/read/107613849 online edition]
* Bull, Marcus, and Norman Housley, eds. ''The Experience of Crusading Volume 1, Western Approaches.'' (2003) 323 pp.
* Constable, Giles. &quot;The Historiography of the Crusades&quot;  in Angeliki E.  Laiou, ed. ''The Crusades from the Perspective of Byzantium and the Muslim World'' (2001); major overview of scholarship [http://www.doaks.org/Crusades/CR01.pdf online]
* Edbury, Peter, and Jonathan Phillips, eds. ''The Experience of Crusading Volume 2, Defining the Crusader Kingdom.'' (2003) 326pp; specialized articles by scholars
* Edgington, Susan B., and Sarah Lambert, eds. ''Gendering the Crusades.'' (2002) 232pp. essays by scholars.
* Florean, Dana. &quot;East Meets West: Cultural Confrontation and Exchange after the First Crusade.&quot; ''Language &amp; Intercultural Communication,'' 2007, Vol. 7 Issue 2, pp.&amp;nbsp;144–151 in [[EBSCO]]
* Folda, Jaroslav. ''Crusader Art in the Holy Land, From the Third Crusade to the Fall of Acre'' (2005) [http://www.amazon.com/Crusader-Holy-Land-Third-Crusade/dp/0521835836/ref=sr_1_3?ie=UTF8&amp;s=books&amp;qid=1205436596&amp;sr=8-3 excerpt and text search]
* France, John. ''Victory in the East: A Military History of the First Crusade'' (1996)
* Harris, Jonathan. ''Byzantium and the Crusades.'' (2003). 276 pp.
* Hillenbrand, Car. ''The Crusades: Islamic Perspectives'' (1999) [http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/1579582109 excerpt and text search]
* Hodgson, Natasha ''Women, Crusading and the Holy Land in Historical Narrative'' (Boydell, 2007) [http://www.amazon.co.uk/Crusading-Historical-Narrative-Warfare-History/dp/1843833328/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1333555697&amp;sr=8-1 excerpt and text search]
* Housley, Norman. ''The Later Crusades, 1274-1580: From Lyons to Alcazar'' (1992) [http://www.questia.com/read/65567896 online edition]
* James, Douglas. &quot;Christians and the First Crusade.&quot; ''History Review'' (Dec 2005), Issue 53; online at [[EBSCO]]
* Kagay, Donald J., and L. J. Andrew Villalon, eds. ''Crusaders, Condottieri, and Cannon: Medieval Warfare in Societies around the Mediterranean.'' (2003) [http://www.questia.com/read/109303998 online edition]
* Maalouf, Amin. ''Crusades Through Arab Eyes'' (1989) [http://www.amazon.com/Crusades-Through-Arab-Eyes-Maalouf/dp/0805208984/ excerpt and text search]
* Madden, Thomas F. ed. ''The Crusades: The Essential Readings'' (2002) ISBN 0-631-23023-8. 284 pp, articles by scholars
* Madden, Thomas F. ''et al.'', eds. ''Crusades Medieval Worlds in Conflict'' (2010), essays by specialists
* Peters, Edward. ''Christian Society and the Crusades, 1198-1229'' (1971) [http://www.questia.com/read/14405191 online edition]
* Powell, James M. ''Anatomy of a Crusade, 1213-1221,'' (1986) [http://www.questia.com/read/3123539 online edition]
* Queller, Donald E., and Thomas F. Madden. ''The Fourth Crusade: The Conquest of Constantinople'' (2nd ed. 1999) [http://www.amazon.com/Fourth-Crusade-Conquest-Constantinople-Middle/dp/0812217136/  excerpt and text search]
* Richard, Jean. ''Saint Louis: Crusader King of France'' (1992)
* Riley-Smith, Jonathan.''The First Crusade and the Idea of Crusading''. (1986).
* Runciman, Steven. ''A History of the Crusades, Volume I: The First Crusade and the Foundations of the Kingdom of Jerusalem.''; ''Volume II: The Kingdom of Jerusalem and the Frankish East 1100-1187.'' and ''Volume III: The Kingdom of Acre and the Later Crusades'' (1951–53), the classic history; very hostile toward the crusaders
* Setton, Kenneth ed., ''A History of the Crusades''. (1969-1989), the standard scholarly history in six volumes, published by the University of Wisconsin Press  [http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/History/History-idx?type=browse&amp;scope=History.HistCrusades complete text online].
* Smail, R. C. &quot;Crusaders' Castles of the Twelfth Century&quot;   ''Cambridge Historical Journal'' Vol. 10, No. 2. (1951), pp.&amp;nbsp;133–149. [http://www.jstor.org/pss/3021083 in JSTOR]
* Stark, Rodney. ''God's Battalions: The Case for the Crusades'' (2010) [http://www.amazon.com/Gods-Battalions-Crusades-Rodney-Stark/dp/0061582603/ excerpt and text search]
* Tyerman, Christopher.  ''England and the Crusades, 1095-1588.'' (1988). 492 pp.
{{refend}}

===Primary sources===
{{refbegin}}
* [[Malcolm Barber|Barber, Malcolm]], Bate, Keith (2010). ''Letters from the East: Crusaders, Pilgrims and Settlers in the 12th-13th Centuries'' (Crusade Texts in Translation Volume 18, Ashgate Publishing Ltd). ISBN 978-0-7546-6356-0
* Housley, Norman, ed. ''Documents on the Later Crusades, 1274-1580'' (1996)
* Krey, August C. ''The First Crusade: The Accounts of Eye-Witnesses and Participants'' (1958).
* Shaw, M. R. B. ed.''Chronicles of the Crusades'' (1963) [http://www.questia.com/read/58956484 online edition]
* Villehardouin, Geoffrey, and Jean de Joinville. ''Chronicles of the Crusades'' ed. by Sir Frank Marzials (2007) [http://www.amazon.com/Chronicles-Crusades-Dover-Value-Editions/dp/0486454363/ref=pd_bbs_sr_8?ie=UTF8&amp;s=books&amp;qid=1205270195&amp;sr=8-8 excerpt and text search]
:Villehardouin's ''Conquest of Constantinople'' is a standard reference work on the Fourth Crusade; it is the first work in medieval French prose. Joinville's life of St. Louis is a classic description of the life and times of King Louis IX; it is written in Old French and is considered perhaps the best biography written in the Middle Ages.
{{refend}}

==External links==

{{Wiktionary|Crusade}}
{{Commons category|Crusades}}
{{Wikisource1911Enc}}
*[http://crusades.boisestate.edu/ The Crusades], a virtual college course through [[Boise State University]] ed. by E. L. Knox.
*[http://www.the-orb.net/encyclop/religion/crusades/crusade.html Crusades: A Guide to Online Resources], Paul Crawford, 1999.
*[http://www.staff.u-szeged.hu/~capitul/sscle/ The Society for the Study of the Crusades and the Latin East]—an international organization of professional Crusade scholars
*[http://www.deremilitari.org De Re Militari: The Society for Medieval Military History]—contains articles and primary sources related to the Crusades
*[http://www.dinur.org/resources/resourceCategoryDisplay.aspx?categoryid=453&amp;rsid=478 Resources &amp;gt; Medieval Jewish History &amp;gt; The Crusades] The Jewish History Resource Center – Project of the Dinur Center for Research in Jewish History, The [[Hebrew University of Jerusalem]]

{{Crusader States}}
{{Middle Ages}}
{{Christian History}}
{{Christianityfooter}}
{{History of Europe}}
{{History of the Roman Catholic Church}}

{{Portal bar|Crusades|Middle Ages|History}}

[[Category:Crusades| ]]

{{Link GA|lt}}
{{Link GA|no}}
{{Link FA|af}}
{{Link FA|cs}}
{{Link FA|eo}}
{{Link FA|mk}}
{{Link FA|ur}}
[[af:Kruistog]]
[[als:Kreuzzug]]
[[ar:حملات صليبية]]
[[an:Cruzatas]]
[[ast:Cruzaes]]
[[az:Səlib yürüşləri]]
[[bn:ক্রুসেড]]
[[zh-min-nan:Si̍p-jī-kun]]
[[be:Крыжовыя паходы]]
[[be-x-old:Крыжовыя паходы]]
[[bg:Кръстоносен поход]]
[[bs:Krstaški ratovi]]
[[br:Kroaziadegoù]]
[[ca:Croades]]
[[ceb:Mga Krusada]]
[[cs:Křížové výpravy]]
[[cy:Y Croesgadau]]
[[da:Korstog]]
[[de:Kreuzzug]]
[[et:Ristisõjad]]
[[el:Σταυροφορίες]]
[[es:Cruzadas]]
[[eo:Krucmilitoj]]
[[eu:Gurutzadak]]
[[fa:جنگ‌های صلیبی]]
[[fr:Croisades]]
[[fy:Krústocht]]
[[fur:Crosadis]]
[[ga:Crosáidí]]
[[gl:Cruzadas]]
[[ko:십자군]]
[[hy:Խաչակրաց արշավանքներ]]
[[hi:सलीबी युद्ध]]
[[hr:Križarski ratovi]]
[[io:Kruco-milito]]
[[ig:Njè Ághá Jésu]]
[[ilo:Dagiti Krusada]]
[[id:Perang Salib]]
[[ia:Cruciadas]]
[[is:Krossferðir]]
[[it:Crociata]]
[[he:מסעי הצלב]]
[[jv:Perang Salib]]
[[ka:ჯვაროსნული ლაშქრობები]]
[[kk:Крест жорықтары]]
[[sw:Vita za Misalaba]]
[[ku:Seferên Xaçperestan]]
[[lad:Krusatas]]
[[la:Expeditio sacra]]
[[lv:Krusta kari]]
[[lt:Kryžiaus žygiai]]
[[hu:Keresztes háborúk]]
[[mk:Крстоносни војни]]
[[ml:കുരിശുയുദ്ധങ്ങൾ]]
[[mt:Kruċjata]]
[[mr:क्रुसेड]]
[[arz:حملات صليبيه]]
[[ms:Perang Salib]]
[[mwl:Cruzada]]
[[mn:Загалмайтны аян дайн]]
[[my:ခရူးဆိတ် စစ်ပွဲများ]]
[[nl:Kruistocht]]
[[new:क्रुसेड्स्]]
[[ja:十字軍]]
[[no:Korstog]]
[[nn:Krosstog]]
[[nrm:Crouésade]]
[[oc:Crosada]]
[[uz:Salib yurishi]]
[[pa:ਸਲੀਬੀ ਜੰਗਾਂ]]
[[pnb:صلیبی جنگاں]]
[[ps:صليبي جګړې]]
[[pms:Crosià]]
[[nds:Krüüztog]]
[[pl:Krucjata]]
[[pt:Cruzada]]
[[ro:Cruciadă]]
[[rue:Хрестовы походы]]
[[ru:Крестовые походы]]
[[sq:Kryqëzatat]]
[[scn:Cruciati]]
[[si:කුරුස යුද්ධ]]
[[simple:Crusades]]
[[sk:Križiacka výprava]]
[[sl:Križarske vojne]]
[[ckb:شەڕەکانی خاچپەرستی]]
[[sr:Крсташки ратови]]
[[sh:Križarski ratovi]]
[[fi:Ristiretket]]
[[sv:Korståg]]
[[tl:Krusada]]
[[ta:சிலுவைப் போர்கள்]]
[[te:క్రూసేడులు]]
[[th:สงครามครูเสด]]
[[tr:Haçlı Seferleri]]
[[tk:Haçly ýörişler]]
[[uk:Хрестові походи]]
[[ur:صلیبی جنگیں]]
[[ug:سەلىپنىڭ شەرققە يۈرۈش قىلىشى]]
[[za:Cibcihginh doengcwngh]]
[[vec:Crociade]]
[[vi:Thập tự chinh]]
[[fiu-vro:Ristisõda]]
[[wa:Croejhåde (guere)]]
[[war:Krusada]]
[[wo:Xarey jóoñe]]
[[yi:קרייצצוג]]
[[zh-yue:十字軍東征]]
[[bat-smg:Krīžiaus žīgē]]
[[zh:十字軍東征]]</text>
      <sha1>bi2jdeytcqd258zfrp08pi4nv26ujih</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
