<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Genocide</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>12441</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520534756</id>
      <parentid>520073498</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-30T03:18:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>187.191.13.14</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="81948">{{About|the crime}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2012}}
[[File:Buchenwald Slave Laborers Liberation.jpg|thumb|250px|[[Buchenwald concentration camp]] was not an extermination camp, though it was responsible for a vast number of deaths]]
{{Discrimination sidebar}}

'''Genocide''' is &quot;the deliberate and systematic destruction, in whole or [[Local extinction | in part]], of an [[ethnic group|ethnic]], [[Race (classification of humans)|racial]], [[Religious denomination|religious]], or national group&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;See generally {{cite book |author=Funk, T. Marcus |title=Victims' Rights and Advocacy at the International Criminal Court |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Oxford, England |year=2010 |isbn=0-19-973747-9 |page=[http://www.oup.com/us/catalog/general/subject/Law/PublicInternationalLaw/InternationalCriminalandHumanita/?view=usa&amp;ci=9780199737475]}}&lt;/ref&gt; though what constitutes enough of a &quot;part&quot; to qualify as genocide has been subject to much debate by legal scholars.&lt;ref name=&quot;What is Genocide&quot;&gt;[http://efchr.mcgill.ca/WhatIsGenocide_en.php?menu=2 What is Genocide?] McGill Faculty of Law ([[McGill University]])&lt;/ref&gt; While a precise [[genocide definitions|definition varies among genocide scholars]], a legal definition is found in the 1948 United Nations [[Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide]] (CPPCG). Article 2 of this convention defines genocide as &quot;any of the following acts committed with intent to destroy, in whole or in part, a  national, [[ethnicity|ethnical]]&lt;!-- This is a quote. The original is 'ethnical'. See www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/p_genoci.htm--&gt;, [[Race (classification of human beings)|racial]] or religious group, as such: killing members of the group; causing serious bodily or mental harm to members of the group; deliberately inflicting on the group conditions of life, calculated to bring about its physical destruction in whole or in part; imposing measures intended to prevent births within the group; [and] forcibly transferring children of the group to another group.&quot;&lt;ref  name=CPPCG&gt;Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights. ''[http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/p_genoci.htm Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide]'' &lt;!--Retrieved 2008-10-22--&gt; {{Wayback|df=yes|url=http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/p_genoci.htm|date =20080502140534|bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Raphael Lemkin in his masterpiece &quot;Axis Rule in Occupied Europe&quot; (1943) invented the term &quot;genocide,&quot;by combining &quot;genos&quot; (race, people) and &quot;cide&quot; (to kill).

Lemkin defined genocide as follows:
&quot;Generally speaking, genocide does not necessarily mean the immediate destruction of a nation, except when accomplished by mass killings of all members of a nation. It is intended rather to signify a coordinated plan of different actions aiming at the destruction of essential foundations of the life of national groups, with the aim of annihilating the groups themselves. The objectives of such a plan would be the disintegration of the political and social institutions, of culture, language, national feelings, religion, and the economic existence of national groups, and the destruction of the personal security, liberty, health, dignity, and even the lives of the individuals belonging to such groups.&quot;
The preamble to the CPPCG states that instances of genocide have taken place throughout history,&lt;ref  name=CPPCG/&gt; but it was not until [[Raphael Lemkin]] coined the term and the prosecution of perpetrators of the [[Holocaust]] at the [[Nuremberg trials]] that the United Nations agreed to the CPPCG which defined the crime of genocide under international law.

During a video interview with Raphael Lemkin, the interviewer asked him about how he came to be interested in this genocide. He replied; &quot;I became interested in genocide because it happened so many times. [[Armenian Genocide|First to the Armenians]], then after the Armenians, [[Hitler]] took action.&quot;&lt;ref name=RaphaelLemkininterview&gt;Video interview with Raphael Lemkin CBS news. &quot;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uCebMq-GmH4]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=nytimes&gt;New York Times &quot;[http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/17/arts/television/17stan.html?pagewanted=print]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

There was a gap of more than forty years between the CPPCG coming into force and the first prosecution under the provisions of the treaty. To date all international prosecutions of genocide, the [[Rwandan Genocide]] and the [[Srebrenica Genocide]], have been  by ''ad hoc'' international [[tribunals]].&lt;ref&gt;Verdirame, Guglielmo &quot;The Genocide Definition in the Jurisprudence of the ''Ad Hoc'' Tribunals&quot;, ''International &amp; Comparative Law Quarterly''  (2000), 49 : 578–598 Cambridge University Press, {{doi|10.1017/S002058930006437X}}. [http://journals.cambridge.org/action/displayAbstract;jsessionid=07E462EEFA2A366C7A6476B30AC9CB06.tomcat1?fromPage=online&amp;aid=1531072 Abstract]&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[International Criminal Court]] came into existence in 2002 and it has the authority to try people from the states that have signed the treaty, but to date it has not tried anyone.

Since the CPPCG came into effect in January 1951 about 80 member states of the United Nations have passed legislation that incorporates the provisions of the CPPCG into their domestic law, and some perpetrators of genocide have been found guilty under such municipal laws, such as [[Nikola Jorgic]], who was found guilty of genocide in Bosnia by a German court (''Jorgic v. Germany'').

Critics of the CPPCG point to the narrow definition of the groups that are protected under the treaty, particularly the lack of protection for political groups for what has been termed [[politicide]] (politicide is included as genocide under some municipal jurisdictions).&lt;ref&gt;Naomi Klein. ''The Shock Doctrine: The Rise of Disaster Capitalism'', Macmillan, 2007 ISBN 0-8050-7983-1, ISBN 978-0-8050-7983-8. [http://books.google.com/books?id=b1uQNYbE8DkC&amp;pg=PA101&amp;lpg=PA101 p. 101], see footnote&lt;/ref&gt; One of the problems was that until there was a body of case law from prosecutions, the precise definition of what the treaty meant had not been tested in court, for example, what precisely does the term ''&quot;in part&quot;'' mean? As more perpetrators are tried under international tribunals and municipal court cases, a body of legal arguments and legal interpretations are helping to address these issues.

The exclusion of political groups and politically motivated violence from the international definition of genocide is particularly controversial. The reason for this exclusion is because a number of UN member nations insisted on it when the Genocide Convention was being drafted in 1948. They argued that political groups are too vaguely defined, as well as temporary and unstable. They further held that international law should not seek to regulate or limit political conflicts, since that would give the UN too much power to interfere in the internal affairs of sovereign nations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Staub, Ervin |title=The Roots of Evil: The Origins of Genocide and Other Group Violence |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Cambridge, UK |isbn=0-521-42214-0 |page=[http://books.google.com/books?id=29u-vt_KgGEC&amp;pg=PA8&amp;lpg=PA8&amp;dq=genocide+political+economic+groups#PPA8,M1 8]}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the years since then, critics have argued that the exclusion of political groups from the definition, as well as the lack of a specific reference to the destruction of a social group through the forcible removal of a population, was designed to protect the [[Soviet Union]] and the [[Allies of World War II|Western Allies]] from possible accusations of genocide in the wake of World War II.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Robert Gellately &amp; Ben Kiernan |title=The Specter of Genocide: Mass Murder in Historical Perspective |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Cambridge, UK |year=2003|isbn=0-521-52750-3 | page= [http://books.google.com/books?id=Ay76mYBLU3sC&amp;pg=PA267&amp; dq=where+Stalin+was+presumably+anxious+to+avoid+his+purges+being+subjected+to+genocidal+scrutiny&amp;ie=ISO-8859-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Adam Jones (Canadian scholar)|Adam Jones]]. ''Genocide: A Comprehensive Introduction.'' [[Routledge]]; 2 edition (1 August 2010). ISBN 0-415-48619-X p. 137&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;William Schabas, Genocide in International Law, Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2000, p. 198.&lt;/ref&gt;

Another criticism of the CPPCG is that when its provisions have been invoked by the [[United Nations Security Council]], they have only been invoked to punish those who have already committed genocide and have left a paper trail. It was this criticism that led to the adoption of [[UN Security Council Resolution 1674]] by the [[United Nations Security Council]] on 28 April 2006 which commits the Council to action to protect civilians in armed conflict and to protect populations from genocide, [[war crimes]], [[ethnic cleansing]] and [[crimes against humanity]].

Genocide scholars such as [[Gregory Stanton]] have postulated that conditions and acts that often occur before, during, and after genocide—such as [[dehumanization]] of victim groups, strong organization of genocidal groups, and [[denial]] of genocide by its perpetrators—can be identified and actions taken to stop genocides before they happen. Critics of this approach such as [[Dirk Moses]] assert that this is unrealistic and that, for example, ''&quot;[[War in Darfur|Darfur]] will end when it suits the [[great powers]] that have a stake in the region&quot;''.

==Genocide as a crime==

===International law===
After the Holocaust, Lemkin successfully campaigned for the universal acceptance of [[international law]]s defining and forbidding genocide. In 1946, the first session of the [[United Nations General Assembly]] adopted a [[United Nations General Assembly Resolution 96|resolution]] that &quot;affirmed&quot; that genocide was a crime under international law, but did not provide a legal definition of the crime. In 1948, the UN General Assembly adopted the ''[[Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide]]'' which legally defined the crime of genocide for the first time.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Rubinstein |first=W. D. |url=http://books.google.com/?id=nMMAk4VwLLwC&amp;pg=PA308&amp;dq#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false |title=Genocide: a history |publisher=Pearson Education |year=2004 |page=308 |isbn=0-582-50601-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''CPPCG'' was adopted by the UN General Assembly on 9 December 1948 and came into effect on 12 January 1951 (Resolution 260 (III)). It contains an internationally-recognized definition of genocide which was incorporated into the national criminal legislation of many countries, and was also adopted by the [[Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court]], the treaty that established the [[International Criminal Court]] (ICC). The Convention (in article 2) defines genocide:

{{quotation|...any of the following acts committed with [[#Intent to destroy|intent to destroy]], [[Genocide#In part|in whole or in part]], a national, ethnical, racial or religious group, as such:
:(a) Killing members of the group;
:(b) Causing serious bodily or mental harm to members of the group;
:(c) Deliberately inflicting on the group conditions of life calculated to bring about its physical destruction in whole or in part;
:(d) Imposing measures intended to prevent births within the group;
:(e) Forcibly transferring children of the group to another group.|Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide, Article II}}

The first draft of the Convention included political killings, but the [[Soviet Union|USSR]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Robert Gellately &amp; Ben Kiernan |title=The Specter of Genocide: Mass Murder in Historical Perspective |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Cambridge, UK |year=2003|isbn=0-521-52750-3 | pages= 267 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=Ay76mYBLU3sC&amp;pg=PA267&amp;dq=where+Stalin+was+presumably+anxious+to+avoid+his+purges+being+subjected+to+genocidal+scrutiny}}&lt;/ref&gt; along with some other nations would not accept that actions against groups identified as holding similar political opinions or social status would constitute genocide,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Staub, Ervin |title=The Roots of Evil: The Origins of Genocide and Other Group Violence |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Cambridge, UK |pages= 8|isbn=0-521-42214-0 |url= http://books.google.com/?id=29u-vt_KgGEC&amp;pg=PA8&amp;lpg=PA8&amp;dq=genocide+political+economic+groups+soviet+union |date=31 July 1992}}&lt;/ref&gt; so these stipulations were subsequently removed in a political and diplomatic compromise.

{{quotation|
The Convention was manifestly adopted for humanitarian and civilizing purposes. Its objectives are to safeguard the very existence of certain human groups and to affirm and emphasize the most elementary principles of humanity and morality. In view of the rights involved, the legal obligations to refrain from genocide are recognized as ''[[erga omnes]]''.
&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/br&gt;
When the Convention was drafted, it was already envisaged that it would apply not only to then existing forms of genocide, but also &quot;to any method that might be evolved in the future with a view to destroying the physical existence of a group&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;From a statement made by Mr. Morozov, representative of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, on 19 April 1948 during the debate in the Ad Hoc Committee on Genocide (E/AC.25/SR.12).&lt;/ref&gt; As emphasized in the preamble to the Convention, genocide has marred all periods of history, and it is this very tragic recognition that gives the concept its historical evolutionary nature.
&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/br&gt;
The Convention must be interpreted in good faith, in accordance with the ordinary meaning of its terms, in their context, and in the light of its object and purpose. Moreover, the text of the Convention should be interpreted in such a way that a reason and a meaning can be attributed to every word. No word or provision may be disregarded or treated as superfluous, unless this is absolutely necessary to give effect to the terms read as a whole.&lt;ref&gt;See Vienna Convention on the Law of Treaties, opened for signature on 23 May 1969, United Nations Treaty Series, vol. 1155, No. I-18232.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/br&gt;
Genocide is a crime under international law regardless of &quot;whether committed in time of peace or in time of war&quot; (art. I). Thus, irrespective of the context in which it occurs (for example, peace time, internal strife, international armed conflict or whatever the general overall situation) genocide is a punishable international crime.
|UN Commission of Experts that examined violations of international humanitarian law committed in the territory of the former Yugoslavia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ess.uwe.ac.uk/comexpert/I-II.htm#I Mandate, structure and methods of work: Genocide I] of the [http://www.ess.uwe.ac.uk/comexpert/Intr.htm UN Commission of Experts] to examine violations of international humanitarian law committed in the territory of the former Yugoslavia, created by [[United Nations Security Council Resolution 780|Security Council resolution 780]] (1992) of 6 October 1992.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

====Intent to destroy====

In 2007 the [[European Court of Human Rights]] (ECHR), noted in its judgement on ''Jorgic v. Germany'' case that in 1992 the majority of legal scholars took the narrow view that &quot;intent to destroy&quot; in the CPPCG meant the intended physical-biological destruction of the protected group and that this was still the majority opinion. But the ECHR also noted that a minority took a broader view and did not consider biological-physical destruction was necessary as the intent to destroy a national, racial, religious or ethnical group was enough to qualify as genocide.&lt;ref&gt;European Court of Human Rights [http://cmiskp.echr.coe.int/tkp197/viewhbkm.asp?sessionId=1448788&amp;skin=hudoc-en&amp;action=html&amp;table=F69A27FD8FB86142BF01C1166DEA398649&amp;key=63590&amp;highlight= Judgement in Jorgic v. Germany (Application no. 74613/01)] paragraphs 18, 36,74&lt;/ref&gt;

In the same judgement the ECHR reviewed the judgements of several international and municipal courts judgements. It noted that [[International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia]] and the [[International Court of Justice]] had agreed with the narrow interpretation, that biological-physical destruction was necessary for an act to qualify as genocide. The ECHR also noted that at the time of its judgement, apart from courts in Germany which had taken a broad view, that there had been few cases of genocide under other Convention States [[municipal law]]s and that &quot;There are no reported cases in which the courts of these States have defined the type of group destruction the perpetrator must have intended in order to be found guilty of genocide&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;European Court of Human Rights [http://cmiskp.echr.coe.int/tkp197/viewhbkm.asp?sessionId=1448788&amp;skin=hudoc-en&amp;action=html&amp;table=F69A27FD8FB86142BF01C1166DEA398649&amp;key=63590&amp;highlight= Judgement in Jorgic v. Germany (Application no. 74613/01)] paragraphs 43–46&lt;/ref&gt;

====In part====

The phrase &quot;in whole or in part&quot; has been subject to much discussion by scholars of international humanitarian law.&lt;ref name=&quot;What is Genocide&quot;/&gt; The [[International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia]] found in ''Prosecutor v. Radislav Krstic – Trial Chamber I – Judgment – IT-98-33 (2001) ICTY8 (2 August 2001)''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.worldlii.org/int/cases/ICTY/2001/8.html Prosecutor v. Radislav Krstic – Trial Chamber I – Judgment – IT-98-33 (2001) ICTY8 (2 August 2001)]&lt;/ref&gt; that Genocide had been committed. In ''Prosecutor v. Radislav Krstic – Appeals Chamber – Judgment – IT-98-33 (2004) ICTY 7 (19 April 2004)''&lt;ref name=PvRKappel&gt;[http://www.worldlii.org/int/cases/ICTY/2004/7.html Prosecutor v. Radislav Krstic – Appeals Chamber – Judgment – IT-98-33 (2004) ICTY 7 (19 April 2004)]&lt;/ref&gt; paragraphs 8, 9, 10, and 11 addressed the issue of ''in part'' and found that &quot;the part must be a substantial part of that group. The aim of the Genocide Convention is to prevent the intentional destruction of entire human groups, and the part targeted must be significant enough to have an impact on the group as a whole.&quot; The Appeals Chamber goes into details of other cases and the opinions of respected commentators on the Genocide Convention to explain how they came to this conclusion.

The judges continue in paragraph 12, &quot;The determination of when the targeted part is substantial enough to meet this requirement may involve a number of considerations. The numeric size of the targeted part of the group is the necessary and important starting point, though not in all cases the ending point of the inquiry. The number of individuals targeted should be evaluated not only in absolute terms, but also in relation to the overall size of the entire group. In addition to the numeric size of the targeted portion, its prominence within the group can be a useful consideration. If a specific part of the group is emblematic of the overall group, or is essential to its survival, that may support a finding that the part qualifies as substantial within the meaning of Article 4 [of the Tribunal's Statute].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.worldlii.org/int/cases/ICTY/2004/7.html Prosecutor v. Radislav Krstic – Appeals Chamber – Judgment – IT-98-33 (2004) ICTY 7 (19 April 2004)] See Paragraph 6: &quot;Article 4 of the Tribunal's Statute, like the Genocide Convention, covers certain acts done with &quot;intent to destroy, in whole or in part, a national, ethnical, racial or religious group, as such.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www1.umn.edu/humanrts/icty/statute.html Statute of the International Tribunal for the Prosecution of Persons Responsible for Serious Violations of International Humanitarian Law Committed in the Territory of the Former Yugoslavia since 1991], U.N. Doc. S/25704 at 36, annex (1993) and S/25704/Add.1 (1993), adopted by Security Council on 25 May 1993, [[United Nations Security Council Resolution 827|Resolution 827]] (1993).&lt;/ref&gt;

In paragraph 13 the judges raise the issue of the perpetrators' access to the victims: &quot;The historical examples of genocide also suggest that the area of the perpetrators’ activity and control, as well as the possible extent of their reach, should be considered. ... The intent to destroy formed by a perpetrator of genocide will always be limited by the opportunity presented to him. While this factor alone will not indicate whether the targeted group is substantial, it can—in combination with other factors—inform the analysis.&quot;&lt;ref name=PvRKappel /&gt;

====CPPCG coming into force====
After the minimum 20 countries became parties to the Convention, it came into force as international law on 12 January 1951. At that time however, only two of the five permanent members of the [[UN Security Council]] (UNSC) were parties to the treaty: France and the [[Republic of China]]. Eventually the [[Soviet Union]] ratified in 1954, the United Kingdom in 1970, the People's Republic of China in 1983 (having replaced the Taiwan-based Republic of China on the UNSC in 1971), and the United States in 1988. This long delay in support for the Genocide Convention by the world's most powerful nations caused the Convention to languish for over four decades. Only in the 1990s did the international law on the crime of genocide begin to be enforced.

====UN Security Council on genocide====
[[UN Security Council Resolution 1674]], adopted by the [[United Nations Security Council]] on 28 April 2006,  &quot;reaffirms the provisions of paragraphs 138 and 139 of the 2005 [[World Summit Outcome Document]] regarding the responsibility to protect populations from genocide, war crimes, ethnic cleansing and crimes against humanity&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://daccess-dds-ny.un.org/doc/UNDOC/GEN/N06/331/99/PDF/N0633199.pdf?OpenElement Resolution Resolution 1674 (2006)]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[United Nations Security Council Resolution|resolution]] committed the Council to action to protect civilians in armed conflict.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oxfam.org/en/news/pressreleases2006/pr060428_un Security Council passes landmark resolution – world has responsibility to protect people from genocide] [[Oxfam]] Press Release – 28 April 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008 the [[U.N. Security Council]] adopted [[United Nations Security Council Resolution 1820|resolution 1820]], which noted that “rape and other forms of sexual violence can constitute war crimes, crimes against humanity or a constitutive act with respect to genocide”.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs/2008/sc9364.doc.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

===Municipal law===
{{Main|Genocide under municipal laws}}

Since the Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide (CPPCG) came into effect in January 1951 about 80 member states of the United Nations have passed legislation that incorporates the provisions of the CPPCG into their [[municipal law]].

==Criticisms of the CPPCG and other definitions of genocide==
{{See also|Genocide definitions}}

William Schabas has suggested that a permanent body as recommended by the [[Whitaker Report (United Nations)|Whitaker Report]] to monitor the implementation of the Genocide Convention, and require States to issue reports on their compliance with the convention (such as were incorporated into the United Nations [[Optional Protocol to the Convention against Torture]]), would make the convention more effective.&lt;ref&gt;William Schabas ''War crimes and human rights: essays on the death penalty, justice and accountability'', Cameron May 2008 ISBN 1-905017-63-4, ISBN 978-1-905017-63-8. [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=SPhGSg_5Go0C&amp;pg=PA791&amp;dq=Whitaker+Report+Sub+commision&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3#PPA791,M1 p. 791]&lt;/ref&gt;

Writing in 1998 Kurt Jonassohn and Karin Björnson stated that the CPPCG was a legal instrument resulting from a diplomatic compromise. As such the wording of the treaty is not intended to be a definition suitable as a research tool, and although it is used for this purpose, as it has an international legal credibility that others lack, [[Genocide definitions|other definitions]] have also been postulated. Jonassohn and Björnson go on to say that none of these alternative definitions have gained widespread support for various reasons.&lt;ref name=Jonassohn-133-135&gt;Kurt Jonassohn &amp; Karin Solveig Björnson, ''Genocide and Gross Human Rights Violations in Comparative Perspective: In Comparative Perspective'', Transaction Publishers, 1998, ISBN 0-7658-0417-4, ISBN 978-0-7658-0417-4. [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=jIxCUXI38zcC&amp;pg=PA133&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3&amp;as_pt=ALLTYPES pp. 133–135]&lt;/ref&gt;

Jonassohn and Björnson postulate that the major reason why no single generally accepted genocide definition has emerged is because academics have adjusted their focus to emphasise different periods and have found it expedient to use slightly different definitions to help them interpret events. For example Frank Chalk and Kurt Jonassohn studied the whole of human history, while [[Leo Kuper]] and [[R. J. Rummel]] in their more recent works concentrated on the 20th century, and [[Helen Fein]], Barbara Harff and Ted Gurr have looked at post World War II events. Jonassohn and Björnson are critical of some of these studies arguing that they are too expansive and concludes that the academic discipline of genocide studies is too young to have a canon of work on which to build an academic [[paradigm]].&lt;ref name=Jonassohn-133-135/&gt;

The exclusion of social and political groups as targets of genocide in the CPPCG legal definition has been criticized by some historians and sociologists, for example M. Hassan Kakar in his book ''The Soviet Invasion and the Afghan Response, 1979–1982''&lt;ref&gt;M. Hassan Kakar ''[http://www.escholarship.org/editions/view?docId=ft7b69p12h&amp;brand=eschol Afghanistan: The Soviet Invasion and the Afghan Response, 1979–1982] [[University of California]] press  1995 The Regents of the University of California.&lt;/ref&gt; argues that the international definition of genocide is too restricted,&lt;ref&gt;M. Hassan Kakar [http://www.escholarship.org/editions/view?docId=ft7b69p12h&amp;chunk.id=d0e5195&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;toc.id=d0e5195&amp;brand=eschol 4. The Story of Genocide in Afghanistan: 13. Genocide Throughout the Country]&lt;/ref&gt; and that it should include political groups or any group so defined by the perpetrator and quotes Chalk and Jonassohn: &quot;Genocide is a form of one-sided mass killing in which a state or other authority intends to destroy a group, as that group and membership in it are defined by the perpetrator.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Frank Chalk, Kurt Jonassohn ''The History and Sociology of Genocide: Analyses and Case Studies'', Yale University Press, 1990, ISBN 0-300-04446-1&lt;/ref&gt; While there are various definitions of the term, Adam Jones states that the majority of genocide scholars consider that &quot;intent to destroy&quot; is a requirement for any act to be labelled genocide, and that there is growing agreement on the inclusion of the physical destruction criterion.&lt;ref&gt;Jones, Adam. ''[http://www.genocidetext.net/gaci_excerpts.htm Genocide: A Comprehensive Introduction]'', Routledge/Taylor &amp; Francis Publishers, 2006. ISBN 0-415-35385-8. [http://www.genocidetext.net/gaci_origins.pdf Chapter 1: The Origins of Genocide] pp.20–21&lt;/ref&gt;

Barbara Harff and Ted Gurr defined genocide as &quot;the promotion and execution of policies by a state or its agents which result in the deaths of a substantial portion of a group ...[when] the victimized groups are defined primarily in terms of their communal characteristics, i.e., ethnicity, religion or nationality.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://efchr.mcgill.ca/WhatIsGenocide_en.php?menu=2 What is Genocide?] McGill Faculty of Law ([[McGill University]]) source cites Barbara Harff and Ted Gurr ''Toward empirical theory of genocides and politicides,'' International Studies Quarterly, 37:3, 1988&lt;/ref&gt; Harff and Gurr also differentiate between genocides and [[politicide]]s by the characteristics by which members of a group are identified by the state. In genocides, the victimized groups are defined primarily in terms of their communal characteristics, i.e., ethnicity, religion or nationality. In politicides the victim groups are defined primarily in terms of their hierarchical position or political opposition to the regime and dominant groups.&lt;ref name=HG-2&gt;[http://science.jrank.org/pages/9496/Genocide-Origins-Evolution-Concept.html Origins and Evolution of the Concept] in the Science Encyclopedia by Net Industries. states &quot;Politicide, as [Barbara] Harff and [Ted R.] Gurr define it, refers to the killing of groups of people who are targeted not because of shared ethnic or communal traits, but because of 'their hierarchical position or political opposition to the regime and dominant groups' (p. 360)&quot;. But does not give the book title to go with the page number.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Staff. ''[http://www.apfn.org/apfn/genocide.htm There are NO Statutes of Limitations on the Crimes of Genocide!]'' On the website of the American Patriot Friends Network. Cites Barbara Harff and Ted Gurr &quot;Toward empirical theory of genocides and politicides,&quot; International Studies Quarterly 37, 3 [1988].&lt;/ref&gt; Daniel D. Polsby and Don B. Kates, Jr. state that &quot;... we follow Harff's distinction between genocides and '[[pogrom]]s,' which she describes as 'short-lived outbursts by mobs, which, although often condoned by authorities, rarely persist.' If the violence persists for long enough, however, Harff argues, the distinction between condonation and complicity collapses.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Polsby |first=Daniel D. |last2=Kates |first2=Don B., Jr. |title=OF HOLOCAUSTS AND GUN CONTROL |journal=Washington University Law Quarterly |year=1997 |month=3 November |volume=75 |issue=Fall |pages=1237 |url=http://lawreview.wustl.edu/inprint/75-3/753-4.html}} (cites Harff 1992, see other note)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;harff&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |first=Barbara |last= Harff |title=Recognizing Genocides and Politicides |journal= Genocide Watch |volume= 27 |editor-first=Helen| editor-last= Fein |year=1992 |pages=37, 38 |location=New Haven, CT |publisher= Yale University Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to R. J. Rummel, genocide has 3 different meanings. The ordinary meaning is murder by government of people due to their national, ethnic, racial, or religious group membership. The legal meaning of genocide refers to the international treaty, the ''Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide''. This also includes non-killings that in the end eliminate the group, such as preventing births or forcibly transferring children out of the group to another group. A generalized meaning of genocide is similar to the ordinary meaning but also includes government killings of political opponents or otherwise intentional murder. It is to avoid confusion regarding what meaning is intended that Rummel created the term [[democide]] for the third meaning.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hawaii.edu/powerkills/GENOCIDE.HTM Domocide versus genocide; which is what?]&lt;/ref&gt;

A major criticism of the international community's response to the Rwandan Genocide was that it was reactive, not proactive. The international community has developed a mechanism for prosecuting the perpetrators of genocide but has not developed the will or the mechanisms for intervening in a genocide as it happens. Critics point to the [[Darfur conflict]] and suggest that if anyone is found guilty of genocide after the conflict either by prosecutions brought in the International Criminal Court or in an ''ad hoc'' International Criminal Tribunal, this will confirm this perception.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}

==International prosecution of genocide==

===By ad hoc tribunals===
[[File:Nuon Chea - 5 December 2011.jpg|thumb|[[Nuon Chea]], the Khmer Rouge's chief ideologist, before the [[Cambodian Genocide Tribunal]] on 5 December 2011.]]
All signatories to the CPPCG are required to prevent and punish acts of genocide, both in peace and wartime, though some barriers make this enforcement difficult. In particular, some of the signatories—namely, [[Bahrain]], Bangladesh, [[India]], Malaysia, the [[Philippines]], Singapore, the United States, Vietnam, [[Yemen]], and [[Yugoslavia]]—signed with the proviso that no claim of genocide could be brought against them at the [[International Court of Justice]] without their consent.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/treaty1gen.htm United Nations Treaty Collection (As of 9 October 2001): Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide] on the web site of the [http://www.ohchr.org/english/ Office of the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights]&lt;/ref&gt; Despite official protests from other signatories (notably [[Cyprus]] and [[Norway]]) on the ethics and legal standing of these reservations, the [[Immunity from prosecution (international law)|immunity]] from prosecution they grant has been invoked from time to time, as when the United States refused to allow a charge of genocide brought against it by [[Yugoslavia]] following the 1999 [[Kosovo War]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ess.uwe.ac.uk/Kosovo/Kosovo-International_Law10.htm (See for example the submission by Agent of the United States, Mr. David Andrews to the ICJ Public  Sitting, 11 May 1999])&lt;/ref&gt;

It is commonly accepted{{citation needed|date=July 2012}} that, at least since [[World War II]], genocide has been illegal under [[custom (law)|customary international law]] as a [[peremptory norm]], as well as under [[treaty|conventional international law]]. Acts of genocide are generally difficult to establish for prosecution, because a chain of accountability must be established. International criminal courts and tribunals function primarily because the states involved are incapable or unwilling to prosecute crimes of this magnitude themselves.

====Nuremberg Tribunal (1945–1946)====
{{Main|Nuremberg Trials}}

Because the universal acceptance of [[international law]]s, defining and forbidding genocide was achieved in 1948, with the promulgation of the ''Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide'' (CPPCG), those criminals who were prosecuted after the war in international courts, for taking part in the Holocaust were found guilty of [[crimes against humanity]] and other more specific crimes like murder. Nevertheless the Holocaust is universally recognized to have been a genocide and the term, that had been coined the year before by [[Raphael Lemkin]],&lt;ref&gt;[[Oxford English Dictionary]]: 1944 R. Lemkin ''Axis Rule in Occupied Europe'' ix. 79 &quot;By 'genocide' we mean the destruction of a nation or of an ethnic group.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; appeared in the [[Nuremberg Trials#Trial|indictment of the 24 Nazi leaders]], Count 3, stated that all the defendants had &quot;conducted deliberate and systematic genocide—namely, the extermination of racial and national groups...&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Oxford English Dictionary]] &quot;Genocide&quot; citing Sunday Times 21 October 1945&lt;/ref&gt;

====International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia (1993 to present (2014 is the scheduled end date))====
{{see also|Bosnian Genocide|List of Bosnian genocide prosecutions}}
[[File:Srebrenica massacre memorial gravestones 2009 1.jpg|thumb|200px|right|The cemetery at the [[Srebrenica Genocide memorial|Srebrenica-Potočari Memorial and Cemetery to Genocide Victims]]]]
The term ''Bosnian Genocide'' is used to refer either to [[Srebrenica massacre|the genocide]] committed by Serb forces in [[Srebrenica]] in 1995,&lt;ref&gt;Staff. ''[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/1907122.stm Bosnian genocide suspect extradited]'', [[BBC]], 2 April 2002&lt;/ref&gt; or to ethnic cleansing that took place during the 1992–1995 [[war in Bosnia and Herzegovina|Bosnian War]] (an interpretation rejected by a majority of scholars).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.echr.coe.int/echr/ European Court of Human Rights]. [http://cmiskp.echr.coe.int/tkp197/viewhbkm.asp?sessionId=1448788&amp;skin=hudoc-en&amp;action=html&amp;table=F69A27FD8FB86142BF01C1166DEA398649&amp;key=63590&amp;highlight= Jorgic v. Germany Judgment], 12 July 2007. § 47&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2001 the [[International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia]] (ICTY) judged that the 1995 [[Srebrenica massacre]] was an act of genocide.&lt;ref&gt;The [[International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia]] found in [http://www.worldlii.org/int/cases/ICTY/2001/8.html Prosecutor v. Radislav Krstic – Trial Chamber I – Judgment – IT-98-33 (2001) ICTY8 (2 August 2001)] that genocide had been committed. (see paragraph 560 for name of group in English on whom the genocide was committed). It was upheld in  ''[http://www.worldlii.org/int/cases/ICTY/2004/7.html Prosecutor v. Radislav Krstic – Appeals Chamber – Judgment – IT-98-33 (2004) ICTY 7 (19 April 2004)]''&lt;/ref&gt;

On 26 February 2007 the [[International Court of Justice]] (ICJ), in the ''[[Bosnian Genocide Case]]'' upheld the ICTY's earlier finding that the Srebrenica massacre constituted genocide, but found that the Serbian government had not participated in a wider genocide on the territory of Bosnia and Herzegovina during the war, as the Bosnian government had claimed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/n/a/2007/02/26/international/i033600S38.DTL&amp;type=politics|title=Courte: Serbia failed to prevent genocide, UN court rules|date=26 February 2007|agency=Associated Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 12 July 2007, [[European Court of Human Rights]] when dismissing the appeal by [[Nikola Jorgic]] against his conviction for genocide by a German court ([[Jorgic v. Germany]]) noted that the German courts wider interpretation of genocide has since been rejected by international courts considering similar cases.&lt;ref&gt;ECHR Jorgic v. Germany. § 42 citing Prosecutor v. Krstic, IT-98-33-T, judgment of 2 August 2001, §§ 580&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;ECHR ''Jorgic v. Germany Judgment'', 12 July 2007. § 44 citing Prosecutor v. Kupreskic and Others  (IT-95-16-T, judgment of 14 January 2000), § 751. In 14 January 2000 the ICTY ruled in the [[Prosecutor v. Kupreskic and Others]] case that the killing of 116 Muslims in order to expel the Muslim population from a village, was persecution, not of genocide.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.icj-cij.org/presscom/index.php?pr=1897&amp;pt=1&amp;p1=6&amp;p2=1 ICJ press release 2007/8] 26 February 2007&lt;/ref&gt; The ECHR also noted that in the 21st century  &quot;Amongst scholars, the majority have taken the view that [[ethnic cleansing]], in the way in which it was carried out by the Serb forces in Bosnia and Herzegovina in order to expel Muslims and Croats from their homes, did not constitute genocide. However, there are also a considerable number of scholars who have suggested that these acts did amount to genocide&quot;&lt;ref&gt;ECHR ''Jorgic v. Germany Judgment'', 12 July 2007. § 47&lt;/ref&gt;

About 30 people have been indicted for participating in genocide or complicity in genocide during the early 1990s in [[Bosnia and Herzegovina|Bosnia]]. To date after several [[plea bargain]]s and some convictions that were successfully challenged on appeal two men, [[Vujadin Popović]] and [[Ljubiša Beara]], have been found guilty of genocide, and two others, [[Radislav Krstic]] and Drago Nikolic, have been found guilty of aiding and abetting genocide. Three others have been found guilty of participating in genocides in Bosnia by German courts, one of whom [[Nikola Jorgic]] lost an appeal against his conviction in the [[European Court of Human Rights]]. A further eight men, former members of the Bosnian Serb security forces were found guilty of genocide by the [[State Court of Bosnia and Herzegovina]] (See [[List of Bosnian genocide prosecutions]]).

[[Slobodan Milosevic]], as the former President of Serbia and of Yugoslavia was the most senior political figure to stand trial at the ICTY. He died on 11 March 2006 during his trial where he was accused of genocide or complicity in genocide in territories within Bosnia and Herzegovina, so no verdict was returned. In 1995 the ICTY issued a warrant for the arrest of Bosnian Serbs [[Radovan Karadzic]] and [[Ratko Mladic]] on several charges including genocide. On 21 July 2008, Karadzic was arrested in Belgrade, and he is currently in The Hague on trial accused of genocide among other crimes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Staff |date=5 November 2009 |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/7521347.stm |title=Q&amp;A: Karadzic on trial |publisher=BBC News |accessdate=28 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ratko Mladic was arrested on 26 May 2011 by Serbian special police in Lazarevo, Serbia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Staff |date=26 May 2011 |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-13561407 |title=Q&amp;A: Ratko Mladic arrested: Bosnia war crimes suspect held |publisher=BBC News |accessdate=28 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====International Criminal Tribunal for Rwanda (1994 to present (2012 is the scheduled end date))====
{{See also|Rwandan Genocide}}
[[File:Genocide Victims Rwanda Photo by Sascha Grabow.jpg|thumb|Rwandan Genocide Victims]]
The [[International Criminal Tribunal for Rwanda]] (ICTR) is a court under the auspices of the United Nations for the prosecution of offenses committed in [[Rwanda]] during the [[Rwandan genocide|genocide which occurred there]] during April 1994, commencing on 6 April. The ICTR was created on 8 November 1994 by the Security Council of the United Nations in order to judge those people responsible for the acts of genocide and other serious violations of the international law performed in the territory of Rwanda, or by Rwandan citizens in nearby states, between 1 January and 31 December 1994.

So far, the ICTR has finished nineteen trials and convicted twenty seven accused persons. On 14 December 2009 two more men were accused and convicted for their crimes. Another twenty five persons are still on trial. Twenty-one are awaiting trial in detention, two more added on 14 December 2009. Ten are still at large.&lt;ref&gt;These figures need revising they are from the [[ICTR]] page which says see [http://www.ictr.org/ www.ictr.org]&lt;/ref&gt; The first trial, of [[Jean Akayesu|Jean-Paul Akayesu]], began in 1997. In October 1998, Akayesu was sentenced to life imprisonment. [[Jean Kambanda]], interim Prime Minister, pled guilty.

====Extraordinary Chambers in the Courts of Cambodia (2003 to present)====
{{Main|Killing Fields|Khmer Rouge Tribunal}}
[[File:Skulls from the killing fields.jpg|right|thumb|Skulls in the [[Choeung Ek]].]]

The [[Khmer Rouge]], led by [[Pol Pot]], [[Ta Mok]] and other leaders, organized the mass killing of ideologically suspect groups. The total number of victims is estimated at approximately 1.7 million [[Cambodia]]ns between 1975–1979, including deaths from slave labour.&lt;ref name=Yale-CGP&gt;[http://www.yale.edu/cgp/index.html Cambodian Genocide Program], [[Yale University]]'s MacMillan Center for International and Area Studies&lt;/ref&gt;

On 6 June 2003 the Cambodian government and the United Nations reached an agreement to set up the [[Extraordinary Chambers in the Courts of Cambodia]] (ECCC) which would focus exclusively on crimes committed by the most senior [[Khmer Rouge]] officials during the period of Khmer Rouge rule of 1975–1979.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://unakrt-online.org/Docs/GA%20Documents/A-Res-57-228B.pdf |title=A/RES/57/228B |date=2003-05-022 |accessdate=11 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The judges were sworn in early July 2006.&lt;ref name=KD-Time&gt;Doyle, Kevin. [http://www.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,1647257,00.html &quot;Putting the Khmer Rouge on Trial&quot;], ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'', 26 July 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;MacKinnon, Ian [http://www.guardian.co.uk/international/story/0,,2028421,00.html &quot;Crisis talks to save Khmer Rouge trial&quot;], ''[[The Guardian]]'', 7 March 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cambodia.gov.kh/krt/english/ The Khmer Rouge Trial Task Force], Royal Cambodian Government&lt;/ref&gt;

The investigating judges were presented with the names of five possible suspects by the prosecution on 18 July 2007.&lt;ref name=KD-Time/&gt;&lt;ref name=Buncombe&gt;{{cite news|first=Andrew |last=Buncombe |title=Judge quits Cambodia genocide tribunal |newspaper=[[The Independent]] |url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/asia/judge-quits-cambodia-genocide-tribunal-2368644.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Kang Kek Iew]] was formally charged with war crime and [[crimes against humanity]] and detained by the Tribunal on 31 July 2007. He was indicted on charges of war crimes and crimes against humanity on 12 August 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;ap-munthit-2008-08-12&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.usatoday.com/news/world/2008-08-12-1013612312_x.htm |title=Cambodian tribunal indicts Khmer Rouge jailer  |author=Ker Munthit |newspaper=[[USA Today]]|agency=Associated Press |date=12 August 2008 |accessdate=April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; His appeal against his conviction for war crimes and crimes against humanity was rejected on 3 February 2012, and he is serving a sentence of life imprisonment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.eccc.gov.kh/en/articles/kaing-guek-eav-alias-duch-sentenced-life-imprisonment-supreme-court-chamber-0 |title=Kaing Guek Eav alias Duch Sentenced to Life Imprisonment by the Supreme Court Chamber |publisher=Extraordinary Chambers in the Courts of Cambodia |date=3 February 2012 |accessdate=April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Nuon Chea]], a former prime minister, who was indicted on charges of genocide, war crimes, crimes against humanity and several other crimes under Cambodian law on 15 September 2010. He was transferred into the custody of the ECCC on 19 September 2007. His trial, which is ongoing, started on 27 June 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;Case-002&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.eccc.gov.kh/en/case/topic/2 |title=Case 002 |publisher=Extraordinary Chambers in the Courts of Cambodia |accessdate=April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Case-002 closing-order&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.eccc.gov.kh/sites/default/files/documents/courtdoc/D427Eng.pdf |title=002/19-09-2007: Closing Order |format=PDF |publisher=Extraordinary Chambers in the Courts of Cambodia |date=15 September 2010 |accessdate=April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Khieu Samphan]], a former head of state, who was indicted on charges of genocide, war crimes, crimes against humanity and several other crimes under Cambodian law on 15 September 2010. He was transferred into the custody of the ECCC on 19 September 2007. His trial, which is ongoing, started on 27 June 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;Case-002&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Case-002 closing-order&quot;/&gt;
*[[Ieng Sary]], a former foreign minister, who was indicted on charges of genocide, war crimes, crimes against humanity and several other crimes under Cambodian law on 15 September 2010. He was transferred into the custody of the ECCC on 12 November 2007. His trial, which is ongoing, started on 27 June 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;Case-002&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Case-002 closing-order&quot;/&gt;
*[[Ieng Thirith]], wife of Ieng Sary and a former minister for social affairs, who was indicted on charges of genocide, war crimes, crimes against humanity and several other crimes under Cambodian law on 15 September 2010. She was transferred into the custody of the ECCC on 12 November 2007. Proceedings against her have been suspended pending a health evaluation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Case-002 closing-order&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.eccc.gov.kh/sites/default/files/documents/courtdoc/E138_1_7_EN-1.PDF |title=002/19-09-2007: Decision on immediate appeal against Trial Chamber's order to release the accused Ieng Thirith |format=PDF |publisher=Extraordinary Chambers in the Courts of Cambodia |date=13 December 2011 |accessdate=April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There has been disagreement between some of the international jurists and the Cambodian government over whether any other people should be tried by the Tribunal.&lt;ref name=Buncombe/&gt;

===By the International Criminal Court===

To date all international prosecutions for genocide have been brought in specially convened international tribunals. Since 2002, the International Criminal Court can exercise its jurisdiction if national courts are unwilling or unable to investigate or prosecute genocide, thus being a &quot;court of last resort,&quot; leaving the primary responsibility to exercise jurisdiction over alleged criminals to individual states. Due to the [[United States and the International Criminal Court|United States concerns over the ICC]], the United States prefers to continue to use specially convened international tribunals for such investigations and potential prosecutions.&lt;ref&gt;{{PDFlink|[http://www.amicc.org/docs/U.S.%20statement%20on%20ICC%20draft%20resolution_23Nov051.pdf Statement by  Carolyn Willson, Minister Counselor for International Legal Affairs, on the Report of the ICC, in the UN General Assembly]|123&amp;nbsp;KB}} 23 November 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

====Darfur, Sudan====
{{Main|War in Darfur}}
[[Image:Darfur report - Page 6 Image 1.jpg|thumb|upright|A mother with her sick baby at Abu Shouk IDP camp in [[North Darfur]]]]
There has been much debate over categorizing the situation in Darfur as genocide.&lt;ref&gt;Jafari, Jamal and [[Paul Williams (professor)|Paul Williams]] (2005) [http://jurist.law.pitt.edu/forumy/2005/03/word-games-un-and-genocide-in-darfur.php &quot;Word Games: The UN and Genocide in Darfur&quot;] ''JURIST''&lt;/ref&gt; The on-going conflict in [[Darfur]], Sudan, which started in 2003, was declared a &quot;genocide&quot; by [[United States Secretary of State]] [[Colin Powell]] on 9 September 2004 in testimony before the [[United States Senate Committee on Foreign Relations|Senate Foreign Relations Committee]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pbs.org/newshour/updates/sudan_09-09-04.html POWELL DECLARES KILLING IN DARFUR 'GENOCIDE'], [[The NewsHour with Jim Lehrer]], 9 September 2004&lt;/ref&gt; Since that time however, no other permanent member of the UN Security Council followed suit. In fact, in January 2005, an International Commission of Inquiry on Darfur, authorized by [[UN Security Council Resolution 1564]] of 2004, issued a report to the Secretary-General stating that &quot;the Government of the Sudan has not pursued a policy of genocide.&quot;&lt;ref name=un-org-January-25-2005&gt;{{PDFlink|[http://www.un.org/News/dh/sudan/com_inq_darfur.pdf Report of the International Commission of Inquiry on Darfur to the United Nations Secretary-General]|1.14&amp;nbsp;MB}}, 25 January 2005, at 4&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, the Commission cautioned that &quot;The conclusion that no genocidal policy has been pursued and implemented in Darfur by the Government authorities, directly or through the militias under their control, should not be taken in any way as detracting from the gravity of the crimes perpetrated in that region. International offences such as the crimes against humanity and war crimes that have been committed in Darfur may be no less serious and heinous than genocide.&quot;&lt;ref name=un-org-January-25-2005/&gt;

In March 2005, the Security Council formally referred the situation in Darfur to the Prosecutor of the International Criminal Court, taking into account the Commission report but without mentioning any specific crimes.&lt;ref&gt;{{PDFlink|[http://www.icc-cpi.int/library/cases/N0529273.darfureferral.eng.pdf Security Council Resolution 1593 (2005)]|24.8&amp;nbsp;KB}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two permanent members of the Security Council, the United States and [[People's Republic of China|China]], abstained from the vote on the referral resolution.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs/2005/sc8351.doc.htm SECURITY COUNCIL REFERS SITUATION IN DARFUR, SUDAN, TO PROSECUTOR OF INTERNATIONAL CRIMINAL COURT], UN Press Release SC/8351, 31 March 2005&lt;/ref&gt; As of his fourth report to the Security Council, the Prosecutor has found &quot;reasonable grounds to believe that the individuals identified [in the [[UN Security Council Resolution 1593]]] have committed crimes against humanity and war crimes,&quot; but did not find sufficient evidence to prosecute for genocide.&lt;ref&gt;{{PDFlink|[http://www.icc-cpi.int/library/organs/otp/OTP_ReportUNSC4-Darfur_English.pdf Fourth Report of the Prosecutor of the International Criminal Court, to the Security Council pursuant to UNSC 1593 (2005)]|597&amp;nbsp;KB}}, Office of the Prosecutor of the International Criminal Court, 14 December 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

In April 2007, the Judges of the ICC issued arrest warrants against the former Minister of State for the Interior, [[Ahmad Harun]], and a Militia
[[Janjaweed]] leader, [[Ali Kushayb]], for crimes against humanity and war crimes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.icc-cpi.int/library/organs/otp/ICC-OTP-ST20080605-ENG.pdf Statement by Mr. Luis Moreno Ocampo, Prosecutor of the International Criminal Court, to the United Nations Security Council pursuant to UNSCR 1593 (2005)], [http://www.icc-cpi.int/ International Criminal Court], 5 June 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

On 14 July 2008, prosecutors at the [[International Criminal Court]] (ICC), filed ten charges of [[war crimes]] against Sudan's President [[Omar al-Bashir]]: three counts of genocide, five of [[crimes against humanity]] and two of murder. The ICC's prosecutors claimed that al-Bashir &quot;masterminded and implemented a plan to destroy in substantial part&quot; three tribal groups in Darfur because of their ethnicity.

On 4 March 2009, the ICC issued a warrant of arrest for Omar Al Bashir, President of Sudan as the ICC Pre-Trial Chamber I concluded that his position as head of state does not grant him immunity against prosecution before the ICC. The warrant was for war crimes and crimes against humanity. It did not include the crime of genocide because the majority of the Chamber did not find that the prosecutors had provided enough evidence to include such a charge.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.icc-cpi.int/NR/exeres/0EF62173-05ED-403A-80C8-F15EE1D25BB3.htm ICC issues a warrant of arrest for Omar Al Bashir, President of Sudan] (ICC-CPI-20090304-PR394), ICC press release,  4 March 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

==Genocide in history==
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 192-208, KZ Mauthausen, Sowjetische Kriegsgefangene.jpg|thumb|Naked [[Nazi crimes against Soviet POWs|Soviet POWs]] in Mauthausen concentration camp. &quot;... the murder of at least 3.3 million Soviet POWs is one of the least-known of modern genocides; there is still no full-length book on the subject in English.&quot; —Adam Jones&lt;ref&gt;[[Adam Jones (Canadian scholar)|Adam Jones]] (2010), ''Genocide: A Comprehensive Introduction'' (2nd ed.), p.271. – {{&quot; ' &quot;}} Next to the Jews in Europe,&quot; wrote [[Alexander Werth]]', &quot;the biggest single German crime was undoubtedly the extermination by hunger, exposure and in other ways of . . . Russian war prisoners.&quot; Yet the murder of at least 3.3 million Soviet POWs is one of the least-known of modern genocides; there is still no full-length book on the subject in English. It also stands as one of the most intensive genocides of all time: &quot;a holocaust that devoured millions,&quot; as Catherine Merridale acknowledges. The large majority of POWs, some 2.8 million, were killed in just eight months of 1941–42, a rate of slaughter matched (to my knowledge) only by the 1994 Rwanda genocide.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;]]
{{Main|Genocides in history}}

The preamble to the [[CPPCG]] states that &quot;genocide is a crime under international law, contrary to the spirit and aims of the United Nations and condemned by the civilized world,&quot; and that &quot;at all periods of history genocide has inflicted great losses on humanity.&quot;

In many cases where accusations of genocide have circulated, partisans have fiercely disputed such an interpretation and the details of the event. This often leads to the promotion of vastly different versions of the event in question.

[[Historical revisionism (negationism)|Revisionist attempts]] to deny or challenge claims of genocides are illegal in some countries. For example, several European countries ban denying the [[Holocaust]], whilst in Turkey it is illegal to refer to mass killings of [[Armenian Genocide|Armenians]], [[Greek genocide|Greeks]] and [[Assyrian Genocide|Assyrians]] by the Ottoman Empire towards the end of the First World War as a genocide.

{{quotation|The 'Age of Totalitarianism' included nearly all of the infamous examples of genocide in modern history, headed by the Jewish Holocaust, but also comprising the mass murders and purges of the Communist world, other mass killings carried out by Nazi Germany and its allies, and also the Armenian genocide of 1915. All these slaughters, it is argued here, had a common origin, the collapse of the elite structure and normal modes of government of much of central, eastern and southern Europe as a result of the First World War, without which surely neither Communism nor Fascism would have existed except in the minds of unknown agitators and crackpots.|William Rubinstein, ''Genocide: a history''&lt;ref&gt;[[William Rubinstein|Rubinstein, W. D.]] (2004). ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=nMMAk4VwLLwC&amp;pg&amp;dq&amp;hl=en#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f Genocide: a history]''. Pearson Education. p.7. ISBN 0-582-50601-8&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Stages of genocide, influences leading to genocide, and efforts to prevent it==

{{quotation|For genocide to happen, there must be certain preconditions. Foremost among them is a national culture that does not place a high value on human life. A totalitarian society, with its assumed superior ideology, is also a precondition for genocidal acts.&lt;ref name=Kakar&gt;M. Hassan Kakar [http://www.escholarship.org/editions/view?docId=ft7b69p12h&amp;chunk.id=d0e5195&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;toc.id=d0e5195&amp;brand=eschol Chapter 4. The Story of Genocide in Afghanistan] Footnote 9. Citing Horowitz, quoted in Chalk and Jonassohn, Genocide, 14.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, members of the dominant society must perceive their potential victims as less than fully human: as &quot;pagans,&quot; &quot;savages,&quot; &quot;uncouth barbarians,&quot; &quot;unbelievers,&quot; &quot;effete degenerates,&quot; &quot;ritual outlaws,&quot; &quot;racial inferiors,&quot; &quot;class antagonists,&quot; &quot;counterrevolutionaries,&quot; and so on.&lt;ref&gt;M. Hassan Kakar [http://www.escholarship.org/editions/view?docId=ft7b69p12h&amp;chunk.id=d0e5195&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;toc.id=d0e5195&amp;brand=eschol Chapter 4. The Story of Genocide in Afghanistan] Footnote 10. Citing For details, see Carlton, ''War and Ideology.''&lt;/ref&gt;  In themselves, these conditions are not enough for the perpetrators to commit genocide. To do that—that is, to commit genocide—the perpetrators need a strong, centralized authority and bureaucratic organization as well as pathological individuals and criminals. Also required is a campaign of vilification and dehumanization of the victims by the perpetrators, who are usually new states or new regimes attempting to impose conformity to a new ideology and its model of society.&lt;ref name=Kakar/&gt;|M. Hassan Kakar&lt;ref&gt;M. Hassan Kakar ,''[http://www.escholarship.org/editions/view?docId=ft7b69p12h&amp;brand=eschol Afghanistan: The Soviet Invasion and the Afghan Response, 1979–1982]'', [[University of California]] Press, 1995.&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

In 1996 [[Gregory Stanton]], the president of [[Genocide Watch]], presented a briefing paper called &quot;The 8 Stages of Genocide&quot; at the [[United States Department of State]].&lt;ref name=GSGW-1996&gt;[[Gregory Stanton]]. [http://www.genocidewatch.org/aboutgenocide/8stagesofgenocide.html The 8 Stages of Genocide], [[Genocide Watch]], 1996&lt;/ref&gt; In it he suggested that genocide develops in eight stages that are &quot;predictable but not inexorable&quot;.&lt;ref name=GSGW-1996/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The [[FBI]] has found somewhat similar stages for [[Hate groups#Psychopathology of hate groups|hate groups]].&lt;/ref&gt;

The Stanton paper was presented at the State Department, shortly after the Rwanda genocide and much of the analysis is based on why that genocide occurred. The preventative measures suggested, given the original target audience, were those that the United States could implement directly or use their influence on other governments to have implemented.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! Stage
! Characteristics
! Preventive measures
|-
! 1.&lt;br /&gt;Classification
| People are divided into &quot;us and them&quot;.
| &quot;The main preventive measure at this early stage is to develop universalistic institutions that [[Racial integration|transcend]]... divisions.&quot;
|-
! 2.&lt;br /&gt;Symbolization
| &quot;When combined with hatred, symbols may be forced upon unwilling members of pariah groups...&quot;
| &quot;To combat symbolization, hate symbols can be legally forbidden as can [[hate speech]]&quot;.
|-
! 3.&lt;br /&gt;Dehumanization
| &quot;One group denies the humanity of the other group. Members of it are equated with animals, vermin, insects,  or diseases.&quot;
| &quot;Local and international leaders should condemn the use of hate speech and make it culturally unacceptable. Leaders who incite genocide should be banned from international travel and have their foreign finances frozen.&quot;
|-
! 4.&lt;br /&gt;Organization
| &quot;Genocide is always organized... Special army units or [[militia]]s are often trained and armed...&quot;
| &quot;The U.N. should impose arms embargoes on governments and citizens of countries involved in genocidal massacres, and create commissions to investigate violations&quot;
|-
! 5.&lt;br /&gt;Polarization
| &quot;Hate groups broadcast polarizing propaganda...&quot;
| &quot;Prevention may mean security protection for moderate leaders or assistance to human rights groups...Coups d’état by extremists should be opposed by international sanctions.&quot;
|-
! 6.&lt;br /&gt;Preparation
| &quot;Victims are identified and separated out because of their ethnic or religious identity...&quot;
| &quot;At this stage, a Genocide Emergency must be declared. ...&quot;
|-
! 7.&lt;br /&gt;Extermination
| &quot;It is 'extermination' to the killers because they do not believe their victims to be fully human&quot;.
| &quot;At this stage, only rapid and overwhelming armed intervention can stop genocide. Real safe areas or refugee escape corridors should be established with heavily armed international protection.&quot;
|-
! 8.&lt;br /&gt;[[Genocide denial|Denial]]
| &quot;The perpetrators... deny that they committed any crimes...&quot;
| &quot;The response to denial is punishment by an international tribunal or national courts&quot;
|}

In April 2012, it was reported that Stanton would soon be officially adding two new stages, Discrimination and Persecution, to his original theory, which would make for a 10-stage theory of genocide.&lt;ref&gt;http://aipr.wordpress.com/2012/04/19/genprev-in-the-news-19-april-2012/&lt;/ref&gt;

In a paper for the [[Social Science Research Council]] Dirk Moses criticises the Stanton approach concluding:

{{quotation|In view of this rather poor record of ending genocide, the question needs to be asked why the &quot;genocide studies&quot; paradigm cannot predict and prevent genocides with any accuracy and reliability. The paradigm of &quot;genocide studies,&quot; as currently constituted in North America in particular, has both strengths and limitations. While the moral fervor and public activism is admirable and salutary, the paradigm appears blind to its own implication in imperial projects that are themselves as much part of the problem as they are part of the solution. The US government called Darfur a genocide to appease domestic lobbies, and because the statement cost it nothing. Darfur will end when it suits the great powers that have a stake in the region.|Dirk Moses&lt;ref&gt;Dirk Moses [http://howgenocidesend.ssrc.org/Moses/ Why the Discipline of &quot;Genocide Studies&quot; Has Trouble Explaining How Genocides End?], [[Social Science Research Council]], 22 December 2006&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Other authors have focused on the structural conditions leading up to genocide and the psychological and social processes that create an evolution toward genocide. Helen Fein&lt;ref&gt;Fein, H. (1979). Accounting for genocide: Victims and survivors of the Holocaust. New York: Fre Press {{Page needed|date=April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; showed that pre-existing anti-Semitism and systems that maintained anti-Semitic policies was related to the number of Jews killed in different European countries during the Holocaust. Ervin Staub showed that economic deterioration and political confusion and disorganization were starting points of increasing discrimination and violence in many instances of genocides and mass killing. They lead to scapegoating a group and ideologies that identified that group as an enemy. A history of devaluation of the group that becomes the victim, past violence against the group that becomes the perpetrator leading to psychological wounds, authoritarian cultures and political systems, and the passivity of internal and external witnesses (bystanders) all contribute to the probability that the violence develops into genocide.&lt;ref&gt;Staub, E (1989). The roots of evil: The origins of genocide and other group violence. New York: Cambridge University Press.{{page needed|date=April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Intense conflict between groups that is unresolved, becomes intractable and violent can also lead to genocide. The conditions that lead to genocide provide guidance to early prevention, such as humanizing a devalued group,creating ideologies that embrace all groups, and activating bystander responses. There is substantial research to indicate how this can be done, but information is only slowly transformed into action.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ervinstaub.com Staub, E. (2011) ''Overcoming evil: Genocide, violent conflict and terrorism'' New York: Oxford University Press.{{page needed|date=April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Cultural genocide==
{{main|Cultural genocide}}

The precise definition of &quot;cultural genocide&quot; remains unclear. The term was proposed by lawyer [[Raphael Lemkin]] in 1933 as a component to genocide, which he called &quot;[[vandalism]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.preventgenocide.org/lemkin/madrid1933-english.htm Raphael Lemkin, ''Acts Constituting a General (Transnational) Danger Considered as Offences Against the Law of Nations'' (J. Fussell trans., 2000) (1933)]; [http://www.preventgenocide.org/lemkin/AxisRule1944-3.htm Raphael Lemkin, ''Axis Rule in Occupied Europe'', p. 91 (1944)].&lt;/ref&gt; The drafters of the 1948 [[Genocide Convention]] considered the use of the term,&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.un.org/icty/krstic/TrialC1/judgement/krs-tj010802e-3.htm#IIIG2bi Prosecutor v. Krstic, Case No. IT-98-33-T (Int'l Crim. Trib. Yugo. Trial Chamber 2001), at para. 576].&lt;/ref&gt; but dropped it under strong opposition from [[Western world|western countries]], especially the United Kingdom, who feared that too broad a definition of genocide could implicate its activity in [[British Empire|its colonies]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Genocide and the Europeans|author=Smith, Karen E.|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|year=2010|isbn=978-0-521-13329-6|pages=34–36}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Genocide}}
* [[Autogenocide]]
* [[Countervalue]]
* [[Crimes against humanity]]
* [[Cultural genocide]]
* [[Democide]]
* [[Eugenics]]
* [[Ethnic cleansing]]
* [[Feticide]]
* [[Forensic osteology]]
* [[Gendercide]]
* [[Genocides in history]]
* [[Infanticide]]
* [[Local extinction]]
* [[Mass murder]]
* [[Mutual assured destruction]]
* [[Policide]]
* [[War crime|War crimes]]

=== Research ===
* [[The Center for the Study of Genocide, Conflict Resolution, and Human Rights]]
* [[International Association of Genocide Scholars]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
* Kakar, M. Hassan. ''[http://www.escholarship.org/editions/view?docId=ft7b69p12h&amp;brand=eschol Afghanistan: The Soviet Invasion and the Afghan Response, 1979–1982]''. Berkeley: [[University of California]] Press, 1995. ISBN 0-520-08591-4.
* {{cite book|last=Lemkin|first=Raphael|title=Axis Rule in Occupied Europe: Laws of Occupation – Analysis of Government – Proposals for Redress|year=1944|publisher=[[Carnegie Endowment for International Peace]]|location=Washington, D.C}}

==Further reading==

===Articles===
* [http://www.csmonitor.com/Commentary/Opinion/2009/0819/p09s02-coop.html The Genocide in Darfur is Not What It Seems] Christian Science Monitor
* (in Spanish) Aizenstatd, Najman Alexander. &quot;Origen y Evolución del Concepto de Genocidio&quot;. Vol. 25 Revista de Derecho de la Universidad Francisco Marroquín 11 (2007). ISSN 1562-2576 [http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1728522]
* [http://www.brynmawr.edu/socialwork/GSSW/schram/harff.pdf No Lessons Learned from the Holocaust? Assessing Risks of Genocide and Political Mass Murder since 1955] American Political Science Review. Vol. 97, No. 1. February 2003.
* Harff, B. and T. R. Gurr (1988). &quot;Toward Empirical Theory of Genocides and Politicides: Identification and Measurement of Cases since 1945.&quot; International Studies Quarterly 32: 359–371.
* (in Spanish) Marco, Jorge. &quot;Genocidio y Genocide Studies: Definiciones y debates&quot;, en: Aróstegui, Julio, Marco, Jorge y Gómez Bravo, Gutmaro (coord.): &quot;De Genocidios, Holocaustos, Exterminios...&quot;, ''Hispania Nova'', 10 (2012). Véase [http://hispanianova.rediris.es/10/dossier/10d002.pdf]
* [http://www.miller-mccune.com/politics/what-really-happened-in-rwanda-3432/ What Really Happened in Rwanda?] Christian Davenport and Allan C. Stam.
* Reyntjens, F. (2004). &quot;Rwanda, Ten Years On: From Genocide to Dictatorship.&quot; African Affairs 103(411): 177–210.
* Brysk, Alison.  1994.  &quot;The Politics of Measurement: The Contested Count of the Disappeared in Argentina.&quot;  Human Rights Quarterly 16: 676–92.
* Davenport, C. and P. Ball (2002). &quot;Views to a Kill: Exploring the Implications of Source Selection in the Case of Guatemalan State Terror, 1977–1996.&quot; Journal of Conflict Resolution 46(3): 427–450.
* Krain, M. (1997). &quot;State-Sponsored Mass Murder: A Study of the Onset and Severity of Genocides and Politicides.&quot; Journal of Conflict Resolution 41(3): 331–360.

===Books===
* {{cite book |last=Andreopoulos |first=George J., ed. |title=Genocide: Conceptual and Historical Dimensions |year=1994 |publisher=University of Pennsylvania Press |isbn=0-8122-3249-6 }}
* Ball, P., P. Kobrak, and H. Spirer (1999).  State Violence in Guatemala, 1960–1996: A Quantitative Reflection.  Washington, D.C.: American Association for the Advancement of Science.
* {{cite book |last=Chalk |first=Frank |title=The History and Sociology of Genocide: Analyses and Case Studies |coauthors=Kurt Jonassohn |year=1990 |publisher=Yale University Press |isbn=0-300-04446-1 }}
* {{cite book |last=Charny |first=Israel W. |title=Encyclopedia of Genocide |authorlink=Israel Charny |date=1 December 1999|publisher=ABC-Clio Inc |isbn=0-87436-928-2 }}
* {{cite book |last=Conversi |first= Daniele |title=Handbook of Nations and Nationalism |chapter=Genocide, ethnic cleansing, and nationalism |editor=Gerard Delanty, Krishan Kumar (eds) |volume=vol. 1 |year=2005 |publisher=Sage Publications |location=London |isbn= 1-4129-0101-4 |pages=319–333}}
* Corradi, Juan, Patricia Weiss Fagen, and Manuel Antonio Garreton, eds.  1992.  Fear at the Edge: State Terror and Resistance in Latin America.  Berkeley: University of California Press.
* Elliot, G. (1972). Twentieth Century Book of the Dead. New York, C. Scribner.
* {{cite book |last=Goldhagen |first=Daniel |title=Worse Than War: Genocide, Eliminationism, and the Ongoing Assault on Humanity |authorlink=Daniel Goldhagen |year=2009 |publisher=[[PublicAffairs]] |isbn=1-58648-769-8 |pages=672}}
* {{cite book |last=Harff |first=Barbara |title=Early Warning of Communal Conflict and Genocide: Linking Empirical Research to International Responses |date=August 2003 |publisher=Westview Press |isbn=0-8133-9840-1 }}
* {{cite book |last= Hochschild |first=Adam |title=King Leopold's Ghost: A Story of Greed, Terror, and Heroism in Colonial Africa |authorlink=Adam Hochschild |year=1998 |publisher=Houghton Mifflin Harcourt |isbn=0-395-75924-2 }}
* {{cite book |last= Horowitz |first=Irving |title=Taking Lives: Genocide and State Power |authorlink=Irving Louis Horowitz |year=2001 |publisher=Transaction Publishers |isbn=0-7658-0094-2 |edition=5th}}
* {{cite book |last=Jonassohn |first=Kurt |title=Genocide and Gross Human Rights Violations |coauthors=Karin Björnson |year=1998 |publisher=Transaction Publishers |isbn=1-56000-314-6 }}
* {{cite book |last=Jones |first=Adam |title=Genocide: A Comprehensive Introduction |authorlink=Adam Jones (Canadian scholar) |year=2010 |publisher=[[Routledge]] |isbn=0-415-48619-X}}
* {{cite book |last=Kelly |first=Michael J. |title=Nowhere to Hide: Defeat of the Sovereign Immunity Defense for Crimes of Genocide &amp; the Trials of Slobodan Milosevic and Saddam Hussein |year=2005 |publisher=Peter Lang |isbn=0-8204-7835-0 }}
* {{cite book |last= Kiernan |first=Ben |title=Blood and Soil: A World History of Genocide and Extermination from Sparta to Darfur |authorlink=Ben Kiernan |year=2007 |publisher=Yale University Press |isbn=0-300-10098-1 }}
* {{cite book |last=Laban |first=Alexander |title=Genocide: An Anthropological Reader |year=2002 |publisher=Blackwell Publishing |isbn=0-631-22355-X }}
* {{cite book |last= Lemarchand  |first=René |title=Burundi: Ethnic Conflict and Genocide |authorlink=René Lemarchand |year=1996 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |isbn=0-521-56623-1 }}
* Levene, M. (2005). Genocide in the Age of the Nation State. New York, Palgrave Macmillan.
* {{cite book |last=MacKinnon |first=Catharine A. |title=Are Women Human?: And Other International Dialogues |authorlink=Catharine MacKinnon |year=2006 |publisher=The Belknap Press of Harvard University Press |isbn=0-674-02555-5 }}
*Lewy, Guenter (2012). ''Essays on Genocide and Humanitarian Intervention''. University of Utah Press. ISBN 978-1-60781-168-8.
* Mamdani, M. (2001). When Victims Become Killers: Colonialism, Nativism, and the Genocide in Rwanda. Princeton, N.J., Princeton University Press.
* {{cite book |last=Power |first=Samantha |title=[[A Problem from Hell|&quot;A Problem from Hell&quot;: America and the Age of Genocide]] |authorlink=Samantha Power |year=2003 |publisher=Harper Perennial |isbn=0-06-054164-4 }}
* {{cite journal |last=Rosenfeld |first=Gavriel D. |authorlink=Gavriel David Rosenfeld |year=1999  |title=The Politics of Uniqueness: Reflections on the Recent Polemical Turn in Holocaust and Genocide Scholarship |journal=[[Holocaust and Genocide Studies]] |volume=13 |issue=1 |pages=28–61  |url=| doi= 10.1093/hgs/13.1.28 }}
* {{cite book |last= Rotberg |first=Robert I. |title=From Massacres to Genocide: The Media, Public Policy, and Humanitarian Crises |coauthors= Thomas G. Weiss |year=1996 |publisher=Brookings Institution Press |isbn=0-8157-7590-3 }}
* {{cite book |last= Rummel |first=R.J. |title=Death by Government |authorlink=R.J. Rummel |date=March 1997 |publisher=[[Transaction Publishers]] |isbn=1-56000-927-6 |url=http://www.hawaii.edu/powerkills/NOTE1.HTM }}
* {{cite book |last=Shaw |first=Martin |title=What is Genocide? |year=2007 |publisher=Polity Press |location=Cambridge |isbn=0-7456-3182-7 }}
* {{cite book |last=Sunga |first=Lyal S. |title=The Emerging System of International Criminal Law: Developments in Codification and Implementation |authorlink=Lyal S. Sunga |year=1997 |publisher= Kluwer |isbn=90-411-0472-0 }}
* {{cite book |last=Sunga |first=Lyal S. |title=Individual Responsibility in International Law for Serious Human Rights Violations |year=1992 |publisher=Springer |isbn=0-7923-1453-0 }}
* {{cite book |last=Totten |first= Samuel |title=Century of Genocide: Critical Essays and Eyewitness Accounts |coauthors=William S. Parsons, and [[Israel W. Charny]] |year=2008 |publisher=Routledge |isbn=0-415-99085-8 |edition=3rd}}
* [http://www.ervinstaub.com Staub, Ervin (1989). ''The roots of evil: The origins of genocide and other group violence''. New York: Cambridge University Press. 978-0521-42214-7]
* [http://www.ervinstaub.com Staub, Ervin (2011). ''Overcoming Evil: Genocide, violent conflict and terrorism''. New York: Oxford University Press. 978-0-19-538204-4]
* {{cite book |last=Valentino |first=Benjamin A. |title=Final Solutions: Mass Killing and Genocide in the 20th Century |year=2004 |publisher=[[Cornell University Press]] |isbn=0-8014-3965-5 }}
* {{cite book |last=Weitz |first=Eric D. |title =A Century of Genocide: Utopias of Race and Nation |publisher=[[Princeton University Press]] |year=2003  |pages=360 |isbn=0-691-12271-7}}
* {{PDFlink|{{cite web |url=http://www.minorityrights.org/admin/Download/pdf/MRGGenocideReport.pdf |format=PDF|title= Preventing Genocide and Mass Killing: The Challenge for the United Nations |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20070703100816/http://www.minorityrights.org/admin/Download/pdf/MRGGenocideReport.pdf |archivedate=3 July 2007}}|366&amp;nbsp;KB}}, report by Minority Rights Group International, 2006
&lt;!-- *{{cite book |title= |isbn= }} --&gt;
* Rummel, R. J.  (1990) Lethal Politics: Soviet Genocides and Mass Murders 1917–1987, Rutgers, New Jersey: Transaction Publishers.
* Rummel, R. J.(1991) China's Bloody Century: Genocide and Mass Murder Since 1900. Rutgers, New Jersey: Transaction Publishers.
* Rummel, R. J.(1992) Democide: Nazi Genocide and Mass Murder. Rutgers, New Jersey: Transaction Publishers.
* Rummel, R. J.(1994) Death by Government: Genocide and Mass Murder in the Twentieth Century, New Jersey: Transaction Publishers.
* Rummel, R. J.(1997) Statistics of Democide. Center on National Security and Law, University of Virginia, 1997: entire. Republished by Lit Verlag, MŸster, Germany in 1998 and distributed in North America by Transaction Publishers.
* Rummel, R. J.(1997).  Power Kills. New Brunswick, Transaction Publishers.
* Schmid, A. P. (1991). Repression, State Terrorism, and Genocide: Conceptual Clarifications. State Organized Terror: The Case of Violent Internal Repression. P. T. Bushnell. Boulder, Colo., Westview Press: x, 312 p.
* Van den Berghe, P. L. (1990). State Violence and Ethnicity. Niwot, Colo., University of Colorado Press.

===Overviews===
* [http://www.isg-iags.org/ Institute for the Study of Genocide/International Association of Genocide Scholars]
* [http://www.genocideintervention.net/ Genocide Intervention Network]
* [http://us.oneworld.net/section/us/perspectives/8/genocide OneWorld Perspectives Magazine: Preventing Genocide (April/May 2006)]- global human rights and development network looks at genocide from a variety of perspectives
* [http://www.ushmm.org/conscience/ Committee on Conscience of the United States Holocaust Memorial Museum]; Responding to Threats of Genocide
* Staff, ''[http://www.preventgenocide.org/law/domestic/ The Crime of Genocide in Domestic Laws and Penal Codes]'', [http://www.preventgenocide.org/aboutus/ Prevent Genocide International]
* [http://www.bl.uk/learning/histcitizen/voices/holocaust.html Voices of the Holocaust]—a learning resource at the British Library
* [http://www.law-ref.org/GENOCIDE/index.html Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide at Law-Ref.org]—fully indexed and crosslinked with other documents
* [http://www.warcrimes.info/ Documents and Resources on War, War Crimes and Genocide]
* [http://www.inogs.com International Network of Genocide Scholars (INoGS)]
* [http://www.genocidewatch.org/eightstages.htm Genocide Watch] stages of genocide
* [http://netnebraska.org/extras/humanrights/02gen/0200/0200_01.htm Genocide &amp; Crimes Against Humanity]—a learning resource, highlighting the cases of Myanmar, Bosnia, the DRC, and Darfur
* [http://www.preventgenocide.org/prevent/UNdocs/whitaker/ Whitaker Report]

===Resources===
* [http://www.auschwitzinstitute.org/ Auschwitz Institute for Peace and Reconciliation]
* [http://www.unrefugees.org/ USA for UNHCR Web site]

===Research Programs===
* [http://www.genocidecentre.dept.shef.ac.uk/ Centre for the Study of Genocide and Mass Violence, Sheffield, United Kingdom]
* [http://www.chgs.nl/ Center for Holocaust and Genocide Studies, Amsterdam, the Netherlands]
* [http://www.chgs.umn.edu/ Center for Holocaust and Genocide Studies, University of Minnesota]
* [http://www.yale.edu/gsp/ Genocide Studies Program, Yale University]
* [http://www.genodynamics.com GenoDynamics: Understanding Genocide Through Time and Space] by Christian Davenport (Kroc Institute – University of Notre Dame) and Allan Stam (University of Michigan)
* [http://migs.concordia.ca/ Montreal Institute for Genocide Studies, Concordia University]
* [http://www.cidcm.umd.edu/mar/ Minorities at Risk project at the University of Maryland]
* [http://www.inforce.org.uk/ The Inforce Foundation (International Forensic Centre of Excellence), UK]
* [http://www.genocideprevention.eu/ Foundation for the International Prevention of Genocide and Mass Atrocities, Hungary]

==External links==
{{Wiktionary}}
{{commons category|Genocide}}
* [http://www.ess.uwe.ac.uk/genocide/ethnocide.htm Ethnocide]
* [http://www.massviolence.org/ethnocide Ethnocide by Barbara Lukunka in the encyclopedia of mass violence]

{{International Criminal Law}}
{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}
{{Genocide topics}}
{{Ethnicity}}

[[Category:Crimes]]
[[Category:Murder]]
[[Category:Genocide|*]]
[[Category:International criminal law]]
[[Category:Population]]
[[Category:United Nations General Assembly resolutions]]

[[af:Volksmoord]]
[[als:Völkermord]]
[[ang:Folcmorðor]]
[[ar:إبادة جماعية]]
[[az:Soyqırım]]
[[be:Генацыд]]
[[be-x-old:Генацыд]]
[[bg:Геноцид]]
[[bs:Genocid]]
[[br:Gouennlazh]]
[[ca:Genocidi]]
[[cv:Геноцид]]
[[cs:Genocida]]
[[cy:Hil-laddiad]]
[[da:Folkedrab]]
[[de:Völkermord]]
[[et:Genotsiid]]
[[el:Γενοκτονία]]
[[es:Genocidio]]
[[eo:Genocido]]
[[eu:Genozidio]]
[[fa:نسل‌کشی]]
[[fr:Génocide]]
[[ga:Cinedhíothú]]
[[gl:Xenocidio]]
[[ko:집단 학살]]
[[hy:Ցեղասպանություն]]
[[hr:Genocid]]
[[id:Genosida]]
[[it:Genocidio]]
[[he:רצח עם]]
[[jv:Genosida]]
[[ka:გენოციდი]]
[[kk:Геноцид]]
[[sw:Mauaji ya kimbari]]
[[ku:Jenosîd]]
[[ky:Геноцид]]
[[la:Generis occidio]]
[[lv:Genocīds]]
[[lt:Genocidas]]
[[hu:Népirtás]]
[[ms:Pembasmian kaum]]
[[nl:Genocide]]
[[ja:ジェノサイド]]
[[no:Folkemord]]
[[nn:Folkemord]]
[[oc:Genocidi]]
[[pl:Ludobójstwo]]
[[pt:Genocídio]]
[[ro:Genocid]]
[[rue:Ґеноцід]]
[[ru:Геноцид]]
[[sq:Gjenocidi]]
[[si:වර්ග සංහාරය]]
[[simple:Genocide]]
[[sk:Genocída (právo)]]
[[sl:Genocid]]
[[ckb:جینۆساید]]
[[sr:Геноцид]]
[[sh:Genocid]]
[[fi:Kansanmurha]]
[[sv:Folkmord]]
[[tl:Pagpatay ng lahi]]
[[ta:இனப்படுகொலை]]
[[th:พันธุฆาต]]
[[tr:Soykırım]]
[[uk:Геноцид]]
[[vi:Diệt chủng]]
[[wa:Djenocide]]
[[yi:פעלקער מארד]]
[[zh:种族灭绝]]</text>
      <sha1>klq4k6t13iy9xq2o3sdfj7wl8kucm2n</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
