<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Green Revolution</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>72727</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520569630</id>
      <parentid>520564083</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-30T10:22:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sriharsh1234</username>
        <id>17348405</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edit(s) by [[Special:Contributions/120.62.19.55|120.62.19.55]] identified as test/vandalism using [[WP:STiki|STiki]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="49477">{{Other uses}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2011}}
[[File:Cropduster spraying pesticides.jpg|thumb|right|Increased use of various technologies such as pesticides, herbicides, and fertilizers as well as new breeds of high yield crops were employed in the decades after the Second World War to greatly increase global food production.]]
{{Agriculture}}
'''Green Revolution''' refers to a series of research, development, and [[technology transfer]] initiatives, occurring between the 1940s and the late 1970s, that increased agriculture production around the world, beginning most markedly in the late 1960s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Peter B.R. |last=Hazell |title=The Asian Green Revolution |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=frNfVx-KZOcC&amp;pg=PA1 |year=2009 |work=IFPRI Discussion Paper |publisher=Intl Food Policy Res Inst |id=GGKEY:HS2UT4LADZD}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The initiatives, led by [[Norman Borlaug]], the &quot;Father of the Green Revolution&quot; credited with saving over a billion people from starvation, involved the development of [[high-yielding varieties]] of cereal grains, expansion of irrigation infrastructure, modernization of management techniques, distribution of hybridized seeds, synthetic [[fertilizer]]s, and [[pesticide]]s to farmers.

The term &quot;Green Revolution&quot; was first used in 1968 by former [[United States Agency for International Development]] (USAID) director [[William Gaud]], who noted the spread of the new technologies and said,

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;These and other developments in the field of agriculture contain the makings of a new revolution. It is not a violent [[October Revolution|Red Revolution]] like that of the Soviets, nor is it a [[White Revolution]] like that of the [[Mohammad Reza Pahlavi|Shah of Iran]]. I call it the Green Revolution.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;agbio&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.agbioworld.org/biotech-info/topics/borlaug/borlaug-green.html |title=The Green Revolution: Accomplishments and Apprehensions |last1= Gaud |first1=William S. |date=8 March 1968 |publisher=AgBioWorld |accessdate=8 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==History==
The agricultural development that began in [[Mexico]] by [[Norman Borlaug]] in 1943 (based on [[Nazareno Strampelli]]'s studies) had been judged as a success and the [[Rockefeller Foundation]] sought to spread it to other nations. The Office of Special Studies in Mexico became an informal international research institution in 1959, and in 1963 it formally became [[CIMMYT]], The International Maize and Wheat Improvement Center.

In 1961 India was on the brink of mass famine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2001/06/0621_bamboo.html |title=India Girds for Famine Linked With Flowering of Bamboo |publisher=News.nationalgeographic.com |accessdate=13 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Borlaug was invited to India by the adviser to the Indian minister of agriculture [[M. S. Swaminathan]]. Despite bureaucratic hurdles imposed by India's grain monopolies, the [[Ford Foundation]] and Indian government collaborated to import wheat seed from CIMMYT. [[Punjab (India)|Punjab]] was selected by the Indian government to be the first site to try the new crops because of its reliable water supply and a history of agricultural success. India began its own Green Revolution program of plant breeding, irrigation development, and financing of agrochemicals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cgiar.org/newsroom/releases/news.asp?idnews=532 |title=Newsroom: News Releases |publisher=CGIAR |accessdate=13 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

India soon adopted [[IR8 (rice)|IR8]] – a semi-dwarf rice variety developed by the [[International Rice Research Institute]] (IRRI) that could produce more grains of rice per plant when grown with certain fertilizers and irrigation. In 1968, Indian agronomist S.K. De Datta published his findings that IR8 rice yielded about 5 tons per hectare with no fertilizer, and almost 10 tons per hectare under optimal conditions. This was 10 times the yield of traditional rice.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.2134/agronj1968.00021962006000060017x |author=De Datta SK, Tauro AC, Balaoing SN |title=Effect of plant type and nitrogen level on growth characteristics and grain yield of indica rice in the tropics |journal=Agron. J. |volume=60 |issue= 6|pages=643–7 |date=1 November 1968|url=http://agron.scijournals.org/cgi/content/abstract/60/6/643 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  IR8 was a success throughout Asia, and dubbed the &quot;Miracle Rice&quot;. IR8 was also developed into [[Semi-dwarf IR36]].
[[File:Wheat yields in developing countries 1951-2004.png|thumb|right|300px|Wheat yields in developing countries, 1950 to 2004, kg/HA baseline 500.  The steep rise in crop yields in the  U.S. began in the 1940s.  The percentage of growth was fastest in the early rapid growth stage. In developing countries maize yields are still rapidly rising.&lt;ref&gt;{{ Cite journal
| last1 = Fischer
| first1 =R. A.
| last2 =Byerlee
| first2 =Eric
| last3 =Edmeades
| first3 =E.  O.
| author1-link =
| title = Can Technology Deliver on the Yield Challenge to 2050
| year = 
|journal=Expert Meeting on How to Feed the World
|issue=
|pages=
|publisher= Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations
| url = ftp://ftp.fao.org/docrep/fao/012/ak977e/ak977e00.pdf
}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
In the 1960s, rice yields in India were about two tons per hectare; by the mid-1990s, they had risen to six tons per hectare. In the 1970s, rice cost about $550 a ton; in 2001, it cost under $200 a ton.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| last = Barta| first = Patrick |title = Feeding Billions, A Grain at a Time| newspaper=The Wall Street Journal| pages = A1| date = 28 July 2007| url = http://online.wsj.com/article/SB118556810848880619.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; India became one of the world's most successful rice producers, and is now a major rice exporter, shipping nearly 4.5&amp;nbsp;million tons in 2006.

===IR8 and the Philippines===
In 1960, the Government of the Republic of the [[Philippines]] with Ford and Rockefeller Foundations established IRRI (International Rice Research Institute). A rice crossing between Dee-Geo-woo-gen and Peta was done at IRRI in 1962. In 1966, one of the breeding lines became a new [[cultivar]], IR8.&lt;ref name=ir8 &gt;IRRI [http://www.irri.org/publications/chandler/pdfs/chap4a.pdf Early research and training results] (pdf)pp.106–109.&lt;/ref&gt;  IR8 required the use of fertilizers and pesticides, but produced substantially higher yields than the traditional cultivars. Annual rice production in the Philippines increased from 3.7 to 7.7&amp;nbsp;million tons in two decades.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fao.org/fishery/topic/13472/en |title=Rice paddies |publisher=FAO Fisheries &amp; Aquaculture |accessdate=20 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The switch to IR8 rice made the Philippines a rice exporter for the first time in the 20th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Friday, 14 Jun. 1968 |url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,900147,00.html |title=Rice of the Gods |work=TIME |date=14 June 1968 |accessdate=20 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  But the heavy pesticide use reduced the number of fish and frog species found in rice paddies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blog.baliwww.com/environment-nature/1421 |title=Bali Hotel Villa Blog Culture Travel Guide Indonesia – BALIwww.COM » Through the Eyes of Researcher: “Miracle Rice” Unwittingly Destroys Bali’s Coral Reefs |publisher=Blog.baliwww.com |date=14 May 2008 |accessdate=13 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===CGIAR===
In 1970, foundation officials proposed a worldwide network of agricultural research centers under a permanent secretariat. This was further supported and developed by the [[World Bank]]; on 19 May 1971, the [[Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research]] was established, co-sponsored by the FAO, IFAD and UNDP. CGIAR, has added many research centers throughout the world.

CGIAR has responded, at least in part, to criticisms of Green Revolution methodologies. This began in the 1980s, and mainly was a result of pressure from donor organizations.&lt;ref name=oasa&gt;{{harvnb|Oasa|1987}}&lt;/ref&gt; Methods like Agroecosystem Analysis and Farming System Research have been adopted to gain a more holistic view of agriculture. Methods like Rapid Rural Appraisal and Participatory Rural Appraisal have been adopted to help scientists understand the problems faced by farmers and even give farmers a role in the development process.

===Problems in Africa===
There have been numerous attempts to introduce the successful concepts from the Mexican and Indian projects into Africa.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite thesis |degree=Master |title=Debating Development – A historical analysis of the Sasakawa Global 2000 project in Ghana and indigenous knowledge as an alternative approach to agricultural development |url=http://igitur-archive.library.uu.nl/student-theses/2009-0910-200159/UUindex.html |last=Gröniger |first=Wout  |year=2009 |publisher=Universiteit Utrecht }}&lt;/ref&gt; These programs have generally been less successful. Reasons cited include widespread corruption, insecurity, a lack of infrastructure, and a general lack of will on the part of the governments. Yet environmental factors, such as the availability of water for irrigation, the high diversity in slope and soil types in one given area are also reasons why the Green Revolution is not so successful in Africa.&lt;ref name=&quot;inwent.org&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Emile Frison |title=Biodiversity: Indispensable resources  |journal=D+C |volume=49 |issue=5 |pages=190–3 |date=May 2008 |url=http://www.inwent.org/ez/articles/070224/index.en.shtml |quote=If there is to be a Green Revolution for Africa, it will be necessary to breed improved varieties and, indeed, livestock. That task will depend on access to the genetic resources inherent in agricultural biodiversity. However, biodiversity is also important for tackling malnutrition as well as food security. }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A recent program in western Africa is attempting to introduce a new high-yield variety of rice known as &quot;[[New Rice for Africa]]&quot; (NERICA). NERICAs yield about 30% more rice under normal conditions, and can double yields with small amounts of fertilizer and very basic irrigation. However the program has been beset by problems getting the rice into the hands of farmers, and to date the only success has been in [[Guinea]] where it currently accounts for 16% of rice cultivation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2007/10/10/world/africa/10rice.html |title=In Africa, Prosperity From Seeds Falls Short |work=[[The New York Times]]  |date= 10 October 2007|accessdate=20 March 2011 |first=Celia W. |last=Dugger}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After a famine in 2001 and years of chronic hunger and poverty, in 2005 the small African country of [[Malawi]] launched the &quot;Agricultural Input Subsidy Program&quot; by which vouchers are given to smallholder farmers to buy subsidized nitrogen fertilizer and maize seeds. Within its first year, the program was reported with extreme success, producing the largest maize harvest of the country's history; enough to feed the country with tons of maize left over. The program has advanced yearly ever since. Various sources claim that the program has been an unusual success, hailing it as a &quot;miracle&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/business/8363914.stm Malawi Miracle] article on the [[BBC]] website. According to the [http://www.wfp.org/countries/Malawi/News/Malawi--P4P-raising-income-for-women-farmers UN website on Malawi] the program was highly effective. This website highlights the women farmers program. The claims of success are substantiated by Malawi government claims at [http://www.nso.malawi.net/data_on_line/economics/Trade%20on%20NSO%20website/Malawi%202005%20Trade%20Statistics%20Brief_Release.pdf Malawi National Statistics Organization site]. The international [[WaterAid]] organisation seems to contradict these facts with its [http://www.wateraid.org/international/what_we_do/where_we_work/malawi/3117.asp report on plans from 2005–2010]. Similarly, the [[World Trade Organization]] reported that [http://www.wto.org/english/tratop_e/tpr_e/tp331_e.htm Malawi had noted problems] including lack of transparency and administrative difficulties. This follows with a recent (2010 [http://www.nyasatimes.com/national/malawi-ranks-153-on-un-human-development-index.html Malawi newspaper tells of UN report] with Malawi one of the lowest on the UN list of developing states, confirmed by this [http://www.wfp.org/content/malawi-20052006-biennial-report UN World Food Program report]. Another [http://www.iss.co.za/pubs/ASR/14No4/EHussein.htm report from the Institute for Security Studies] from 2005, showed corruption still prevailing in Malawi at that time.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Agricultural production and food security==
===Technologies===
[[File:Wheat-haHula-ISRAEL2.JPG|thumb|New varieties of wheat and other grains were instrumental to the green revolution.]]
The Green Revolution spread technologies that had already existed before, but had not been widely used outside industrialized nations. These technologies included modern [[irrigation]] projects, [[pesticide]]s, [[synthetic nitrogen fertilizer]] and improved crop varieties developed through the conventional, science-based methods available at the time.

The novel technological development of the Green Revolution was the production of novel wheat [[cultivars]]. [[Agronomist]]s [[Plant breeding|bred]] cultivars of maize, wheat, and rice that are generally referred to as HYVs or “high-yielding varieties”. HYVs have higher nitrogen-absorbing potential than other varieties. Since cereals that absorbed extra nitrogen would typically lodge, or fall over before harvest, semi-dwarfing [[gene]]s were bred into their [[genome]]s. A Japanese dwarf wheat cultivar ([[Norin 10 wheat]]), which was sent to Washington, D.C. by [[Cecil Salmon]], was instrumental in developing Green Revolution wheat cultivars. IR8, the first widely implemented HYV rice to be developed by IRRI, was created through a cross between an Indonesian variety named “Peta” and a Chinese variety named “Dee-geo-woo-gen.”

With advances in [[molecular genetics]], the [[mutant]] [[genes]] responsible for ''[[Arabidopsis thaliana]]'' genes (GA 20-oxidase,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Xu YL, Li L, Wu K, Peeters AJ, Gage DA, Zeevaart JA |title=The GA5 locus of ''Arabidopsis thaliana'' encodes a multifunctional gibberellin 20-oxidase: molecular cloning and functional expression |journal=Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. |volume=92 |issue=14 |pages=6640–4 |year=1995 |month=July |pmid=7604047 |pmc=41574 |url=http://www.pnas.org/content/92/14/6640.abstract |doi=10.1073/pnas.92.14.6640|bibcode = 1995PNAS...92.6640X }}&lt;/ref&gt; ''ga1'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Silverstone AL, Chang C, Krol E, Sun TP |title=Developmental regulation of the gibberellin biosynthetic gene GA1 in Arabidopsis thaliana |journal=Plant J. |volume=12 |issue=1 |pages=9–19 |year=1997 |month=July |pmid=9263448 |url=http://www3.interscience.wiley.com/resolve/openurl?genre=article&amp;sid=nlm:pubmed&amp;issn=0960-7412&amp;date=1997&amp;volume=12&amp;issue=1&amp;spage=9 |doi=10.1046/j.1365-313X.1997.12010009.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''ga1-3''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Silverstone AL, Ciampaglio CN, Sun T |title=The Arabidopsis RGA gene encodes a transcriptional regulator repressing the gibberellin signal transduction pathway |journal=Plant Cell |volume=10 |issue=2 |pages=155–69 |year=1998 |month=February |pmid=9490740 |pmc=143987 |url=http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&amp;pmid=9490740 |doi=10.1105/tpc.10.2.155}}&lt;/ref&gt;), wheat reduced-height genes (''Rht'')&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Appleford NE |title=Decreased shoot stature and grain alpha-amylase activity following ectopic expression of a gibberellin 2-oxidase gene in transgenic wheat |journal=J. Exp. Bot. |volume=58 |issue=12 |pages=3213–26 |year=2007 |pmid=17916639 |doi=10.1093/jxb/erm166 |url=http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/erm166v1 |author-separator=, |author2=Wilkinson MD |author3=Ma Q |display-authors=3 |last4=Evans |first4=D. J. |last5=Stone |first5=M. C. |last6=Pearce |first6=S. P. |last7=Powers |first7=S. J. |last8=Thomas |first8=S. G. |last9=Jones |first9=H. D.}}&lt;/ref&gt;  and &lt;!--''slender rice (slr1)'' This gene makes rice's height taller. --&gt; a rice semidwarf gene (''sd1'')&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Monna L |title=Positional cloning of rice semidwarfing gene, sd-1: rice &quot;green revolution gene&quot; encodes a mutant enzyme involved in gibberellin synthesis |journal=DNA Res. |volume=9 |issue=1 |pages=11–7 |year=2002 |month=February |pmid=11939564 |url=http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&amp;pmid=11939564 |doi=10.1093/dnares/9.1.11 |author-separator=, |author2=Kitazawa N |author3=Yoshino R |display-authors=3 |last4=Suzuki |first4=J |last5=Masuda |first5=H |last6=Maehara |first6=Y |last7=Tanji |first7=M |last8=Sato |first8=M |last9=Nasu |first9=S}}&lt;/ref&gt; were [[cloned]]. These were identified as [[gibberellin]] [[biosynthesis]] genes or [[Cell signaling|cellular signaling]] component genes. [[Plant stem|Stem]] growth in the mutant background is significantly reduced leading to the [[Dwarf plant|dwarf]] [[phenotype]]. [[Photosynthetic]] investment in the stem is reduced dramatically as the shorter plants are inherently more stable mechanically. Assimilates become redirected to grain production, amplifying in particular the effect of chemical fertilizers on commercial yield.

HYVs significantly outperform traditional varieties in the presence of adequate irrigation, pesticides, and fertilizers. In the absence of these inputs, traditional varieties may outperform HYVs. Therefore, several authors have challenged the apparent superiority of HYVs not only compared to the traditional varieties alone, but by contrasting the monocultural system associated with HYVs with the polycultural system associated with traditional ones.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Igbozurike, U.M. |title=Polyculture and Monoculture: Contrast and Analysis |journal=GeoJournal |volume=2 |issue=5 |pages=443–49 |year=1978}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Production increases===
Cereal production more than doubled in developing nations between the years 1961–1985.&lt;ref name=conway1&gt;{{harvnb|Conway|1997|loc=Ch. 4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Yields of rice, maize, and wheat increased steadily during that period.&lt;ref name=conway1/&gt; The production increases can be attributed roughly equally to irrigation, fertilizer, and seed development, at least in the case of Asian rice.&lt;ref name=conway1/&gt;

While agricultural output increased as a result of the Green Revolution, the energy input to produce a crop has increased faster,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |archiveurl=http://www.energybulletin.net/node/5045 |archivedate=1 April 2005 |url=http://www.powerswitch.org.uk/portal/index.php?option=content&amp;task=view&amp;id=563|title=Why Our Food is So Dependent on Oil |last1= Church |first1=Norman |date=1 April 2005 |publisher=PowerSwitch |accessdate=8 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  so that the ratio of crops produced to energy input has decreased over time. Green Revolution techniques also heavily rely on chemical [[fertilizer]]s, [[pesticide]]s and [[herbicide]]s, some of which must be developed from fossil fuels, making agriculture increasingly reliant on petroleum products.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.timesdaily.com/article/20070914/NEWS/709140329/1011/RSS&amp;source=RSS |title=Fuel costs, drought influence price increase |publisher=Timesdaily.com |accessdate=20 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Proponents of the [[Peak Oil]] theory fear that a future decline in oil and gas production would lead to a decline in food production or even a [[Malthusian catastrophe]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.csmonitor.com/2007/0724/p01s01-wogi.html |title=Rising food prices curb aid to global poor |publisher=Csmonitor.com |date=24 July 2007 |accessdate=20 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:World population history.svg|thumb|280px|World population 1950–2010]]
===Effects on food security===
{{Main|Food security}}
The effects of the Green Revolution on global [[food security]] are difficult to assess because of the complexities involved in food systems.

The [[world population]] has grown by about four billion since the beginning of the Green Revolution and many believe that, without the Revolution, there would have been greater [[famine]] and [[malnutrition]]. [[India]] saw annual wheat production rise from 10 million tons in the 1960s to 73&amp;nbsp;million in 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/south_asia/4994590.stm |title=The end of India's green revolution? |publisher=BBC News  |date=29 May 2006 |accessdate=20 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The average person in the developing world consumes roughly 25% more &lt;!-- calorie source? from sugar, or rice, or ? --&gt;calories per day now than before the Green Revolution.&lt;ref name=conway1/&gt;  Between 1950 and 1984, as the Green Revolution transformed agriculture around the globe, world grain production increased by over 250%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Kindall, Henery W &amp; Pimentel, David|title=Constraints on the Expansion of the Global Food Supply |journal=Ambio. |volume=23 |issue=3 |year=1994 |month=May |url= http://dieoff.org/page36.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The production increases fostered by the Green Revolution are often credited with having helped to avoid widespread [[famine]], and for feeding billions of people.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.fao.org/news/story/en/item/80096/icode/ Save and Grow farming model launched by FAO]&quot;. [[Food and Agriculture Organization]].&lt;/ref&gt;

There are also claims that the Green Revolution has decreased food security for a large number of people. One claim involves the shift of subsistence-oriented cropland to cropland oriented towards production of grain for export or animal feed. For example, the Green Revolution replaced much of the land used for [[Pulse (legume)|pulses]] that fed Indian peasants for wheat, which did not make up a large portion of the peasant diet.&lt;ref name=spitz&gt;{{harvnb|Spitz|1987}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticism==
===Food security===
====Malthusian criticism====
Some criticisms generally involve some variation of the [[Malthusian]] principle of population. Such concerns often revolve around the idea that the Green Revolution is unsustainable,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dieoff.com/page55.htm |title=Food, Land, Population and the U.S. Economy |publisher=Dieoff.com |accessdate=20 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and argue that humanity is now in a state of [[overpopulation]] with regards to the sustainable [[Carrying capacity#Humans|carrying capacity]] and [[ecological footprint|ecological demands]] on the Earth.

Although 36 million people die each year as a direct or indirect result of hunger and poor nutrition,&lt;ref&gt;[[Hunger#Malnutrition mortality statistics|Mortality statistics w/references in Wikipedia article on hunger.]]&lt;/ref&gt; Malthus' more extreme predictions have frequently failed to materialize. In 1798 Thomas Malthus made his prediction of impending famine.&lt;ref name = &quot;Green Revolutionary&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.technologyreview.com/Biotech/19871/ |title=Green Revolutionary |publisher=Technology Review |accessdate=20 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The world's population had doubled by 1923 and doubled again by 1973 without fulfilling Malthus' prediction. Malthusian [[Paul R. Ehrlich]], in his 1968 book ''[[The Population Bomb]]'', said that &quot;India couldn't possibly feed two hundred million more people by 1980&quot; and &quot;Hundreds of millions of people will starve to death in spite of any crash programs.&quot;&lt;ref name = &quot;Green Revolutionary&quot;/&gt;  Ehrlich's warnings failed to materialize when India became self-sustaining in cereal production in 1974 (six years later) as a result of the introduction of [[Norman Borlaug]]'s dwarf wheat varieties.&lt;ref name = &quot;Green Revolutionary&quot;/&gt;
[[File:Hubbert peak oil plot.svg|right|thumb|250px|[[M. King Hubbert]]'s prediction of world petroleum production rates. Modern agriculture is totally reliant on petroleum energy.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.independent.co.uk/news/science/world-oil-supplies-are-set-to-run-out-faster-than-expected-warn-scientists-6262621.html World oil supplies are set to run out faster than expected, warn scientists]&quot;. ''The Independent''. June 14, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Since supplies of oil and gas are essential to [[Intensive agriculture|modern agriculture]] techniques,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Oil shock could push world food prices higher |newspaper=CNNMoney |date=March 3, 2011 |url=http://money.cnn.com/2011/03/03/news/economy/food_prices/index.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; a fall in [[Peak oil|global oil supplies]] could cause spiking food prices in the coming decades.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Does a surge in food and oil prices mean that it's now time to panic? |newspaper=Daily Telegraph |date=February 5, 2011 |url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/finance/comment/liamhalligan/8306004/Does-a-surge-in-food-and-oil-prices-mean-that-its-now-time-to-panic.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Famine====
To some modern Western sociologists and writers, increasing food production is not synonymous with increasing food security, and is only part of a larger equation. For example, Harvard professor [[Amartya Sen]] claimed large [[List of famines|historic famines]] were not caused by decreases in food supply, but by socioeconomic dynamics and a failure of public action.&lt;ref name=sen&gt;Drezé and Sen 1991&lt;/ref&gt; However, economist Peter Bowbrick disputes Sen's theory, arguing that Sen relies on inconsistent arguments and contradicts available information, including sources that Sen himself cited.&lt;ref name=Bowbrick1986&gt;{{cite journal| last = Bowbrick| first = Peter| title = A Refutation of Professor Sen's Theory of Famine| journal=Food Policy| volume = 11| issue = 2| pages = 105–124|date=May 1986| doi = 10.1016/0306-9192(86)90059-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bowbrick further argues that Sen's views coincide with that of the [[Bengal]] government at the time of the [[Bengal famine of 1943]], and the policies Sen advocates failed to relieve the famine.&lt;ref name=Bowbrick1986/&gt;

====Quality of diet====
Some have challenged the value of the increased food production of Green Revolution agriculture. [[Miguel Altieri|Miguel A. Altieri]], (a pioneer of agroecology and peasant-advocate), writes that the comparison between traditional systems of agriculture and Green Revolution agriculture has been unfair, because Green Revolution agriculture produces [[monocultures]] of cereal grains, while traditional agriculture usually incorporates [[polyculture]]s.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

These monoculture crops are often used for export, feed for animals, or conversion into biofuel. According to Emile Frison of [[Bioversity International]], the Green Revolution has also led to a change in dietary habits, as fewer people are affected by hunger and die from starvation, but many are affected by [[malnutrition]] such as [[iron deficiency|iron]] or [[vitamin A deficiency|vitamin-A deficiencies]].&lt;ref name=&quot;inwent.org&quot;/&gt; Frison further asserts that almost 60% of yearly deaths of children under age five in developing countries are related to malnutrition.&lt;ref name=&quot;inwent.org&quot;/&gt;

High-yield rice (HYR), introduced since 1964 to poverty-ridden Asian countries, such as the [[Philippines]], was found to have inferior flavor and be more glutinous and less savory than their native varieties.{{Citation needed|date=April 2009}} This caused its price to be lower than the average market value.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Chapman, Graham P. |chapter=The Green Revolution |title=The Companion to Development Studies |publisher=Arnold |location=London |year=2002 |pages=155–9 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the Philippines the introduction of heavy pesticides to rice production, in the early part of the Green Revolution, poisoned and killed off fish and weedy green vegetables that traditionally coexisted in [[rice paddy|rice paddies]]. These were nutritious food sources for many poor Filipino farmers prior to the introduction of pesticides, further impacting the diets of locals.&lt;ref name=rice-robbery&gt;{{cite book |url=http://www.collectivetech.org/apc/sites/default/files/IRRI_Resource%20Kit_Final_SIBAT_0.pdf#page=21 |title=The Great Riice Robbery: A Handbook on the Impact of IRRI in Asia |author=Kilusang Magbubukid ng Pilipinas |editor=Victoria M. Lopez, et al |year=2007 |isbn=978-983-9381-35-1 |location=Penang, Malaysia |publisher=[[Pesticide Action Network Asia and the Pacific]]  |accessdate=8 August 2011 |author-separator=, |display-authors=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Political impact====
A major critic{{Citation needed|date=April 2009}} of the Green Revolution, U.S. investigative journalist [[Mark Dowie]], writes:{{Citation needed|date=April 2009}}&lt;blockquote&gt;
The primary objective of the program was geopolitical: to provide food for the populace in undeveloped countries and so bring social stability and weaken the fomenting of communist insurgency.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Citing internal Foundation documents, Dowie states that the Ford Foundation had a greater concern than Rockefeller in this area.&lt;ref&gt;Primary objective was geopolitical – see {{cite book |first=Mark |last=Dowie |title=American Foundations: An Investigative History |publisher=MIT Press |location=Cambridge MA |year=2001 |pages=109–114 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

There is significant evidence that the Green Revolution weakened socialist movements in many nations. In countries such as India, Mexico, and the Philippines, ''technological solutions'' were sought as an alternative to expanding ''[[agrarian reform]]'' initiatives, the latter of which were often linked to socialist politics.&lt;ref name=&quot;ross1&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Ross|1998|loc=Ch. 5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Socioeconomic impacts====
The transition from traditional agriculture, in which inputs were generated on-farm, to Green Revolution agriculture, which required the purchase of inputs, led to the widespread establishment of rural credit institutions. Smaller farmers often went into [[debt]], which in many cases results in a loss of their farmland.&lt;ref name=oasa/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ponting&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Ponting |first=Clive |year=2007 |title=A New Green History of the World: The Environment and the Collapse of Great Civilizations |location=New York |publisher=[[Penguin Books]] |isbn=978-0-14-303898-6 |page=244}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The increased level of mechanization on larger farms made possible by the Green Revolution removed a large source of employment from the rural economy.&lt;ref name=oasa/&gt;  Because wealthier farmers had better access to credit and land, the Green Revolution increased class disparities, with the rich–poor gap widening as a result. Because some regions were able to adopt Green Revolution agriculture more readily than others (for political or geographical reasons), interregional economic disparities increased as well. Many small farmers are hurt by the dropping prices resulting from increased production overall.{{Citation needed|date=February 2008}} However, large-scale farming companies only account for less than 10% of the total farming capacity.

The new economic difficulties of small holder farmers and landless farm workers led to increased [[Urbanization|rural-urban migration]]. The increase in food production led to a cheaper food for urban dwellers, and the increase in urban population increased the potential for industrialization.{{Citation needed|reason=I've heard this before, so I know reliable sources should be available; UN stats?|date=December 2008}}

====Globalization====
In the most basic sense, the Green Revolution was a product of [[globalization]] as evidenced in the creation of international agricultural research centers that shared information, and with transnational funding from groups like the Rockefeller Foundation, Ford Foundation, and [[United States Agency for International Development]] (USAID). Additionally, the inputs required in Green Revolution agriculture created new markets for seed and chemical corporations, many of which were based in the United States. For example, [[Exxon|Standard Oil of New Jersey]] established hundreds of distributors in the Philippines to sell agricultural packages composed of HYV seed, fertilizer, and pesticides.{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}

===Environmental impact===
[[File:Irrigation1.jpg|350px|thumb|Increased use of irrigation played a major role in the green revolution.]]

====Pesticides====
Green Revolution agriculture relies on extensive use of [[pesticides]], which are necessary to limit the high levels of [[pest (organism)|pest]] damage that inevitably occur in [[monocropping]] – the practice of producing or growing one single crop over a wide area.

====Biodiversity====
The spread of Green Revolution agriculture affected both agricultural [[biodiversity]] and wild biodiversity.&lt;ref name=rice-robbery/&gt; There is little disagreement that the Green Revolution acted to reduce agricultural biodiversity, as it relied on just a few high-yield varieties of each crop.

This has led to concerns about the susceptibility of a food supply to pathogens that cannot be controlled by agrochemicals, as well as the permanent loss of many valuable genetic traits bred into traditional varieties over thousands of years. To address these concerns, massive seed banks such as [[Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research]]’s (CGIAR) International Plant Genetic Resources Institute (now [[Bioversity International]]) have been established (see [[Svalbard Global Seed Vault]]).

There are varying opinions about the effect of the Green Revolution on wild biodiversity. One hypothesis speculates that by increasing production per unit of land area, agriculture will not need to expand into new, uncultivated areas to feed a growing human population.&lt;ref name=Davies2003&gt;{{cite journal| last = Davies| first = Paul| title = An Historical Perspective from the Green Revolution to the Gene Revolution| journal=Nutrition Reviews| volume = 61| issue = 6| pages = S124–34|date=June 2003| doi = 10.1301/nr.2003.jun.S124-S134| pmid = 12908744}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, land degradation and soil nutrients depletion have forced farmers to clear up formerly forested areas in order to keep up with production.&lt;ref name=Shiva1991&gt;{{cite journal| last = Shiva| first = Vandana| title = The Green Revolution in the Punjab| journal=The Ecologist| volume = 21| issue = 2| pages = 57–60|date=March–April 1991}}&lt;/ref&gt; A counter-hypothesis speculates that biodiversity was sacrificed because traditional systems of agriculture that were displaced sometimes incorporated practices to preserve wild biodiversity, and because the Green Revolution expanded agricultural development into new areas where it was once unprofitable or too arid. For example, the development of wheat varieties tolerant to acid soil conditions with high aluminium content, permitted the introduction of agriculture in sensitive [[Wildlife of Brazil|Brazilian ecosystems]] as [[Cerrado]] [[tropical savanna climate|semi-humid]] [[tropical savanna]] and [[Amazon rainforest]] in the geoeconomic macroregions of [[Brazil socio-geographic division|Centro-Sul and Amazônia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Davies2003&quot;/&gt; Before the Green Revolution, other Brazilian ecosystems were also significantly damaged by human activity, such as the once 1st or 2nd main contributor to Brazilian megadiversity [[Mata Atlântica|Atlantic Rainforest]] (above 85% of deforestation in the 1980s, about 95% after 2010s) and the important [[xeric shrubland]]s called [[Caatinga]] mainly in the [[Northeast Region, Brazil|Northeastern Brazil]] (about 40% in the 1980s, about 50% after 2010s — deforestation of the Caatinga biome is generally associated with greater risks of [[desertification]]).

Nevertheless, the world community has clearly acknowledged the negative aspects of agricultural expansion as the 1992 [[Rio Treaty]], signed by 189 nations, has generated numerous national [[Biodiversity Action Plans]] which assign significant biodiversity loss to agriculture's expansion into new domains.

===Health impact===

The consumption of the [[pesticide]]s used to kill [[Pest (organism)|pest]]s by humans in some cases may be increasing the likelihood of cancer in some of the rural villages using them. Poor farming practices including non-compliance to usage of masks and over-usage of the chemicals compound this situation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Loyn |first=David |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/programmes/from_our_own_correspondent/7366899.stm |title=Punjab suffers from adverse effect of Green revolution |publisher=BBC News  |date=26 April 2008 |accessdate=20 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1989, WHO and UNEP estimated that there were around 1 million human pesticide poisonings annually. Some 20,000 (mostly in developing countries) ended in death, as a result of poor labeling, loose safety standards etc.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Pimentel, D. |title=Green revolution agriculture and chemical hazards |journal=The Science of the Total Environment |volume=188 |issue=Suppl |pages=S86–S98 |year=1996 |doi=10.1016/0048-9697(96)05280-1 |url=http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/0048969796052801}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Pesticides and cancer====
Long term exposure to pesticides such as [[organochlorines]], [[creosote]], and [[sulfate]] have been correlated with higher cancer rates and organochlorines [[DDT]], [[chlordane]], and [[lindane]] as tumor promoters in animals.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}} Contradictory epidemiologic studies in humans have linked phenoxy acid herbicides or contaminants in them with [[soft tissue sarcoma]] (STS) and malignant [[lymphoma]], organochlorine insecticides with STS, [[non-Hodgkin's lymphoma]] (NHL), [[leukemia]], and, less consistently, with cancers of the [[Lung cancer|lung]] and [[Breast cancer|breast]], [[organophosphorous]] compounds with NHL and leukemia, and triazine herbicides with [[ovarian cancer]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Dich J, Zahm SH, Hanberg A, Adami HO |title=Pesticides and cancer |journal=Cancer Causes Control |volume=8 |issue=3 |pages=420–43 |year=1997 |month=May |pmid=9498903 |doi=10.1023/A:1018413522959 |url=http://www.springerlink.com/content/p43860605x4h5v63/}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |pmid=9646054 |title=Pesticides and childhood cancer |date=21 January 2011 |last2=Ward |first2=MH |volume=106 |pages=893–908 |pmc=1533072 |journal=Environmental health perspectives |issue=Suppl 3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Punjab case====
{{See also|Green Revolution in India}}
The Indian state of [[Punjab (India)|Punjab]] pioneered green revolution among the other states transforming India into a food-surplus country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite report |url=http://planningcommission.nic.in/plans/stateplan/sdr_pdf/shdr_pun04.pdf |title=Human Development Report 2004, Punjab |date=2004 |author=[[Government of Punjab, India|The Government of Punjab]] |accessdate=9 August 2011}}  Section: &quot;The Green Revolution&quot;, pp. 17–20.&lt;/ref&gt; The state is witnessing serious consequences of intensive farming using chemicals and pesticide. A comprehensive study conducted by [[Post Graduate Institute of Medical Education and Research]] ([[PGIMER]]) has underlined the direct relationship between indiscriminate use of these chemicals and increased incidence of cancer in this region.&lt;ref name=cancer&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hardnewsmedia.com/2006/11/648 |title=Green revolution’s cancer train |author=Sandeep Yadav Faridkot |date=November 2006 |publisher=Hardnews |accessdate=8 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; An increase in the number of cancer cases has been reported in several villages including Jhariwala, Koharwala, Puckka, Bhimawali, and Khara.&lt;ref name=cancer/&gt;

Environmental activist [[Vandana Shiva]] has written extensively about the social, political and economic impacts of the Green Revolution in Punjab. She claims that the Green Revolution's reliance on heavy use of chemical inputs and monocultures has resulted in water scarcity, vulnerability to pests, and incidents of violent conflict and social marginalization.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://livingheritage.org/green-revolution.htm |title=Green revolution in Punjab, by Vandana Shiva |publisher=Livingheritage.org |date=15 October 1988 |accessdate=20 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009, under a [[Greenpeace]] Research Laboratories investigation, Dr Reyes Tirado, from the [[University of Exeter]], UK conducted the study in 50 villages in [[Muktsar]], [[Bathinda]] and [[Ludhiana district]]s revealed chemical, radiation and biological toxicity rampant in Punjab. Twenty percent of the sampled wells showed nitrate levels above the safety limit of 50&amp;nbsp;mg/l, established by WHO, the study connected it with high use of synthetic nitrogen [[fertilizer]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/india/Uranium-metals-make-Punjab-toxic-hotspot/articleshow/6048431.cms |title=Uranium, metals make Punjab toxic hotspot |newspaper=The Times of India |date=15 June 2010|first1=Balwant|last1=Garg}}&lt;/ref&gt; With increasing poisoning of the soil, the region once hailed as the home to the [[Green Revolution in India|Green Revolution]], now due to excessive use of chemical fertilizer, is being termed by one columnist as the &quot;Other [[Bhopal tragedy|Bhopal]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.livemint.com/2010/06/09212410/LAWS-TO-TACKLE-OTHER-8216BH.html?atype=tp |title=Laws To Tackle Other ‘Bhopals’ |date=10 June 2010 |work=[[Mint (newspaper)|Mint]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Organic farming====
About four decades after the Green Revolution widely helped the world to be able to produce food in sufficient levels, a small percentage of farmers in [[India]] have chosen to employ [[organic farming]] methods in response to side effects from their adoption of [[Industrial agriculture|modern agriculture]] techniques.&lt;ref name=&quot;usnews.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usnews.com/articles/news/world/2008/07/07/the-toxic-consequences-of-the-green-revolution.html |title=The Toxic Consequences of the Green Revolution |publisher=Usnews.com |date=7 July 2008 |accessdate=20 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Norman Borlaug's response to criticism==
He dismissed certain claims of critics, but did take other concerns seriously and stated that his work has been:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;a change in the right direction, but it has not transformed the world into a Utopia&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.agbioworld.org/biotech-info/topics/borlaug/iowans.html |title=Iowans Who Fed The World - Norman Borlaug: Geneticist |date= 26 October 2002 |publisher=AgBioWorld |accessdate=8 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Of environmental lobbyists he said:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;some of the environmental lobbyists of the Western nations are the [[Salt and Light#Cultural references|salt of the earth]], but many of them are [[elitist]]s. They've never experienced the physical sensation of hunger. They do their lobbying from comfortable office suites in Washington or [[Brussels]]...If they lived just one month amid the misery of the developing world, as I have for fifty years, they'd be crying out for tractors and fertilizer and irrigation canals and be outraged that fashionable elitists back home were trying to deny them these things&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Tierney |first=John |url=http://tierneylab.blogs.nytimes.com/2008/05/19/greens-and-hunger/ |title=Greens and Hunger |work=TierneyLab – Putting Ideas in Science to the Test |publisher=''[[The New York Times]]'' |accessdate=13 February 2009 | date=19 May 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==See also==
{{refbegin|2}}
&lt;!-- Please keep entries in alphabetical order --&gt;
* [[British Agricultural Revolution]]
* [[Environmental issues with agriculture]]
* [[Food security]]
* [[Genetic pollution]]
* [[Industrial agriculture]]
* [[Arab Agricultural Revolution]]
* [[Neolithic Revolution]]
* [[Plant breeding]]
&lt;!-- Please keep entries in alphabetical order --&gt;
{{refend}}

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
{{refbegin|colwidth=30em}}
* {{cite journal |author=Cleaver, Harry |title=The Contradictions of the Green Revolution |journal=[[American Economic Review]] |volume=62 |issue=2 |pages=177–86 |month=May |year=1972 |url=http://utexas.academia.edu/HarryMCleaverJr/Papers/27744/-The-Contradictions-of-the-Green-Revolution---1972}}
* {{cite book |last=Conway |first=Gordon |title=The doubly green revolution: food for all in the twenty-first century |publisher=Comstock Pub |location=Ithaca, N.Y |year=1998 |isbn=0-8014-8610-6 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |author=Dowie, Mark |title=American foundations: an investigative history |publisher=MIT |location=Cambridge, Mass |year=2001 |isbn=0-262-04189-8 }}
* {{cite book |author=Farrell, John Joseph; Altieri, Miguel A. |title=Agroecology: the science of sustainable agriculture |publisher=[[Westview Press|Westview]] |location=Boulder, CO |year=1995 |isbn=0-8133-1718-5 |edition=2nd}}
* {{cite journal |author=Frison, Emile |title=Green Revolution in Africa will depend on biodiversity  |journal=Development and Cooperation |volume=49 |issue=5 |pages=190–3 |year=2008 |url=http://www.inwent.org/ez/articles/070224/index.en.shtml}}
* {{cite book |author=Jain, H.K. |title=The Green Revolution: History, Impact and Future |publisher=Studium Press |location=Houston, TX |year=2010 |isbn=1-933699-63-9 |edition=1st}}
* {{cite book |last=Oasa |first=Edmud K |chapter=The Political Economy of International Agricultural Research in Glass |editor=Glaeser, Bernhard |title=The Green Revolution revisited: critique and alternatives |publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin |year=1987 |pages=13–55 |isbn=0-04-630014-7 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Ross |first=Eric |title=The Malthus Factor: Poverty, Politics and Population in Capitalist Development |publisher=Zed Books |location=London |year=1998 |isbn=1-85649-564-7 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal |author=[[Vernon Ruttan|Ruttan, Vernon]] |title=The Green Revolution: Seven Generalizations |journal=International Development Review|volume=19|pages=16–23|year=1977 }}
* {{cite book |author=Sen, Amartya Kumar; Drèze, Jean |title=Hunger and public action |publisher=Clarendon Press |location=Oxford |year=1989 |isbn=0-19-828365-2 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |author=[[Vandana Shiva|Shiva, Vandana]] |title=The violence of the green revolution: Ecological degradation and political conflict in Punjab  |year=1989 |isbn=81-85019-19-3 |publisher=Research Foundation for Science and Ecology |location=Dehra Dun }}
* {{cite book |title= Enriching the Earth: Fritz Haber, Carl Bosch, and the Transformation of World Food Production|last=Smil|first=Vaclav |year=2004 |publisher= MIT Press |isbn= 0-262-69313-5 }}
* {{cite book |last=Spitz |first=Pierre |chapter=The Green Revolution Re-Examined in India in Glass |editor=Glaeser, Bernhard |title=The Green Revolution revisited: critique and alternatives |publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin |year=1987 |pages=57–75 |isbn=0-04-630014-7 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |author=[[Angus Wright (academic)|Wright, Angus]] |chapter=Innocence Abroad: American Agricultural Research in Mexico |editor=Bruce Colman; Jackson, Wes; Berry, Wendell |title=Meeting the expectations of the land: essays in sustainable agriculture and stewardship |publisher=North Point Press |location=San Francisco |year=1984 |pages=124–38 |isbn=0-86547-171-1 }}
* {{cite book |author=Wright, Angus Lindsay |title=The death of Ramón González: the modern agricultural dilemma |publisher=University of Texas Press |location=Austin |year=2005 |isbn=0-292-71268-5 }}
{{refend}}

==External links==
* [http://www.archive.org/details/BorlaugIARI Norman Borlaug talk transcript, 1996]
* [http://livingheritage.org/green-revolution.htm The Green Revolution in the Punjab, by Vandana Shiva]
*{{cite web |title=Accelerating the Green Revolution in Africa |publisher=Rockefeller Foundation |url=http://www.rockefellerfoundation.org/what-we-do/where-we-work/africa/accelerating-green-revolution-africa}}
*{{cite news |author=Moseley, W.G. |title=In search of a better revolution |newspaper=Minneapolis StarTribune |date=May 14 2008 |url=http://www.startribune.com/opinion/18908939.html?page=1&amp;c=y}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book | title=Green revolution : history, impact and future | publisher=Studium Press | author=Jain, H.K. | year=2010 | location=Houston | isbn=978-1-933699-63-9, 9781441674487}} A brief history, for general readers.

{{Agriculture footer}}
{{Population}}

[[Category:Industrial agriculture]]
[[Category:International development]]
[[Category:Revolutions by type]]
[[Category:Rockefeller Foundation]]

{{Link GA|ja}}
[[af:Groen rewolusie]]
[[ar:الثورة الخضراء]]
[[ca:Revolució Verda]]
[[cs:Zelená revoluce (zemědělství)]]
[[de:Grüne Revolution]]
[[et:Roheline revolutsioon]]
[[el:Πράσινη επανάσταση]]
[[es:Revolución verde]]
[[eo:Verda revolucio]]
[[fr:Révolution verte]]
[[gl:Revolución verde]]
[[ko:녹색 혁명]]
[[hi:हरित क्रांति]]
[[id:Revolusi Hijau]]
[[it:Rivoluzione verde]]
[[he:המהפכה הירוקה]]
[[ka:მწვანე რევოლუცია]]
[[kk:Жасыл революция]]
[[lt:Žalioji revoliucija]]
[[ml:ഹരിതവിപ്ലവം]]
[[mr:हरितक्रांती]]
[[mn:Ногоон хувьсгал]]
[[nl:Groene revolutie]]
[[ja:緑の革命]]
[[no:Den grønne revolusjonen]]
[[pl:Zielona rewolucja]]
[[pt:Revolução verde]]
[[ro:Revoluția verde]]
[[ru:Зелёная революция]]
[[si:හරිත විප්ලවය]]
[[simple:Green Revolution]]
[[fi:Vihreä vallankumous]]
[[sv:Den gröna revolutionen]]
[[ta:பசுமைப் புரட்சி]]
[[te:హరిత విప్లవం]]
[[uk:Зелена революція]]
[[vi:Cách mạng xanh]]
[[zh:绿色革命]]</text>
      <sha1>6ctvebgx0epnxg3w1kys1bnewly2okc</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
