<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Heimatvertriebene</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>402030</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521090473</id>
      <parentid>521053311</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T18:42:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sparafucil</username>
        <id>2846386</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>context better served by German name</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6782">{{Merge|German exodus from Eastern Europe|date=July 2011}}
{{Unreferenced|date=July 2007}}
[[Image:GuentherZ 2005-06-25 2116 Unterretzbach Heimatdenkmal.jpg|thumb|Memorial near the former [[Znojmo|Znaim an der Thaya]] to the ''[[Sudetenland|Sudeten]]'' expellees of [[South Moravian Region|South]]{{Citation needed|date=July 2009}}&lt;!-- Cant read inscription; is the monument indeed only for southern Moravians? --&gt; Moravia.]]
[[Image:Bundesarchiv Bild 175-13223, Berlin, Flüchtlinge aus dem Osten.jpg|thumb|Refugees from the East 1945 in [[Berlin]]]]

'''''Heimatvertriebene''''' ([[German language|German]] for &quot;expellees&quot;, literally &quot;homeland displaced person&quot;) are those around 12 million [[German citizen]]s (no matter of which ethnicity) and [[ethnic Germans]] (no matter of which citizenship) [[Expulsion of Germans after World War II|who fled or were expelled after World War II]] from parts of Germany annexed by Poland and the Soviet Union (today Russia), and from other countries (the so-called einheitliches Vertreibungsgebiet; i.e. uniform territory of expulsion&lt;ref&gt;The uniform territory of expulsion was legally defined as the [[Former eastern territories of Germany]] (lost by the First or Second World War), the former Austria-Hungary, Estonia, Latvia, Lithuania, and Poland. Cf. Federal Expellee Law, § 2 (1).&lt;/ref&gt;), who found refuge in both [[West Germany|West]] and [[East Germany]], and [[Austria]]. Refugees who had fled voluntarily but were later refused permission to return are often not distinguished from those who were forcibly deported. By the definition of the West German [[Federal Expellee Law]], enacted on 19 May 1953, refugees of German citizenship or German ethnicity, whose return to their home places was denied, were treated like expellees, thus the frequent general usage of the term expellees for refugees alike.  

Distinguished are refugees and expellees who had neither German citizenship nor German ethnicity but as a matter of fact had fled or been expelled from their former domiciles and stranded in West Germany or West Berlin before 1951. They were taken care of – as part of the [[displaced persons]] – by international refugee organisations until 1951 and then by West German authorities granting them the extra status of [[heimatloser Ausländer]] with preferential naturalisation rules, distinct from other legal aliens or stateless people.&lt;ref&gt;Cf. the [http://www.gesetze-im-internet.de/hauslg/index.html ''Gesetz über die Rechtsstellung heimatloser Ausländer im Bundesgebiet''] (shorthand: HAuslG; literally: law on the legal status of homeless foreigners in the federal territory).&lt;/ref&gt; Occupational functionaries and other German expatriates, who had moved to German-annexed or German-occupied foreign territory only due to the war were not considered expellees by law unless they showed circumstances (such as marrying a resident of the respective area) providing for the intention to settle abroad also for the time after the war.&lt;ref&gt;Cf. Federal Expellee Law, § 1 (4).&lt;/ref&gt; Besides the narrow legal definition for the Heimatvertriebene, there were also other groups accepted as Vertriebene (expellees) such as the [[Aussiedler]]. These comprised refugees and emigrants either originally of foreign citizenship but of German ethnicity, or who themselves or whose ancestors had involuntarily lost German citizenship, coming from the above-mentioned uniform territory of expulsion or from Albania, Bulgaria, China, Romania, the Soviet Union, or Yugoslavia, and arriving only after the end of general expulsions but not later as 31 December 1992.&lt;ref&gt;Cf. Federal Expellee Law, § 1 (2) No. 3.&lt;/ref&gt; 

In a document signed in 1950 the ''Heimatvertriebene'' organisations recognised the plight of the different groups of people living in today's Poland who were resettled there by force. The Heimatvertriebene are just one (but by far the largest) of the groups of millions of other people, from many different countries, who all found refuge in today's Germany.

Some of the expellees are active in politics and belong to the political right wing. Many others do not belong to any organizations, but they continue to maintain what they call a lawful right to their homeland.  The vast majority pledged to work peacefully towards that goal while rebuilding post-war Germany and Europe.

The expellees are still highly active in German politics, and are one of the major social groups of the nation, with around 2 million members. The president of the [[Federation of Expellees]] is {{As of|2004|lc=on}} a member of the [[Bundestag]].

Although expellees and their descendants were active in West German politics, the prevailing political climate within West Germany was that of atonement for [[Nazism|Nazi]] actions. However the [[Christian Democratic Union (Germany)|CDU]] governments have shown considerable support for the expellees and German civilian victims.

==Expellee towns==
As a result of the huge influx of expellees, there was a massive increase of population in some areas such as [[Mecklenburg]] (where population numbers doubled), and in some places the previous homogeneity of the population was broken by Protestant expellees moving to a purely Catholic area or conversely. The population numbers of a number of small settlements in West Germany exploded permanently due to a refugee camp on their territory or nearby. Examples of this phenomenon include ''Neugablonz'', a quarter of [[Kaufbeuren]] in [[Bavaria]], founded by the expellees and named after [[Jablonec nad Nisou|Gablonz (Jablonec nad Nisou)]]. Neugablonz nowadays makes up a third of the town's population. An extreme example of the population explosion is [[Neutraubling]] (also in Bavaria), which had 53 inhabitants in 1947, 1300 in 1951, and 3800 in 1960. Since the refugee camps were mostly located on the sites of former hidden ammunition factories, most of these ''Vertriebenenstädte'' are located in a (former) forest. See also [[Espelkamp]]. 

== See also ==
*[[Aussiedler]] ([[:de:Aussiedler]]&lt;!-- article necessary--&gt;)
*[[Expulsion of Germans after World War II]]
*[[Federation of Expellees]]
*[[Glossary of the Third Reich]]

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Ostlandkreuz Schorndorf.jpg|[[Ostlandkreuz]] between [[Schorndorf]] and [[Winterbach]]
File:Oberursel, Vertriebenendenkmal.JPG|Memorial in [[Oberursel (Taunus)|Oberursel]]
File:Bad Homburg Denkmal Egerland.jpg|Memorial in [[Bad Homburg vor der Höhe]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Notes==
&lt;references/&gt;

[[Category:Aftermath of World War II]]
[[Category:20th century in Germany]]
[[Category:German refugees| ]]

[[de:Heimatvertriebene]]
[[nl:Verdrijving van Duitsers na de Tweede Wereldoorlog]]
[[pl:Wypędzony (prawo niemieckie)]]
[[pt:Heimatvertriebener]]
[[sv:Heimatvertriebener]]</text>
      <sha1>izxjh1zgr88thzoh4qmu2ul02cspr6q</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
