<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Irredentism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>15226</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520943901</id>
      <parentid>519035340</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-01T19:52:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>24.22.217.162</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* United States */ vague, oblique</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="30518">[[Image:BoliviaChile.jpg|thumb|300px|right|Example of recent expressions of Bolivian irredentism over territorial losses in the [[War of the Pacific]] (1879–1884). In the mural it is written; &quot;What once was ours, will be ours once again&quot;, and &quot;Hold fast ''[[roto]]s'' (Chileans), for here come the ''Colorados'' of Bolivia&quot;. [[Eduardo Avaroa]]'s statue on top points toward the sea.]]

'''Irredentism''' (from [[Italian language|Italian]] ''irredento'', &quot;unredeemed&quot;) is any position advocating [[annexation]] of territories administered by another [[State (polity)|state]] on the grounds of common [[ethnicity]] or prior historical possession, actual or alleged. It is often advocated by [[pan-nationalism|pan-nationalist]] movements and is a feature of [[identity politics]], [[cultural geography|cultural]] and [[political geography]]. Because most [[border]]s have been moved and redrawn over time, a great many countries could theoretically present irredentist claims to their neighbors. [[Germany]]'s [[Anschluss]] of [[Austria]] and annexation of German-speaking Sudetenland from Czechoslovakia in 1938 and a return of territory from Czechoslovakia to [[Hungary]] as a result of the [[First Vienna Award]] are perhaps historical examples of this idea in practice.

However, some states are the subject of potential irredentism from their inception. Post–World War I  [[Eastern Europe]], the [[Balkans]], and the [[Near East]] had borders carved out by the [[Allies of World War I|Allies]] that left many of the new states in that region unsatisfied due to minority populations and conflicting historical claims. Many of Africa's borders were artificially imposed by European colonial powers. The result split ethnic groups between different countries, such as the [[Yoruba people|Yoruba]] who are divided between [[Nigeria]] and [[Benin]]. In some cases, the irredentist argumentation continued well past the Second World War and on to the present day.

An area that may be subjected to a potential claim is therefore sometimes called an '''''irredenta'''''. Not all irredentas are involved in actual irredentism.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thefreedictionary.com/irredenta]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origins==
{{Main|Italia irredenta}}
The word was coined in [[Italy]] from the phrase ''Italia irredenta'' (&quot;unredeemed Italy&quot;). This originally referred to [[Austria-Hungary|Austro-Hungarian]] rule over mostly or partly Italian-inhabited territories such as [[Trentino]], [[Trieste]], [[Istria]] and [[Dalmatia]] during the 19th and early 20th century.

A common way to express a claim to adjacent territories on the grounds of historical or ethnic association is by using the epithet &quot;Greater&quot; before the country name. This conveys the image of national territory at its maximum conceivable extent with the country &quot;proper&quot; at its core. The use of &quot;Greater&quot; does not always convey an irredentistic meaning.

During the [[unification of Germany]], the term ''[[German question#Later influence|Großdeutschland]]'' (or greater Germany) referred to a possible German nation consisting of the states that later comprised the Second German Empire ''and'' Austria; the term ''lesser'' Germany, or small Germany, or ''[[Kleindeutschland]]'', referred to a possible German state without Austria. The term was also used by Germans referring to Greater Germany, a state consisting of pre World War I Germany, actual Austria and the Sudetenland.

==Constitutional irredentism==
Some states formalize their irredentist claims by including them in their constitutional documents.

=== Afghanistan ===
The [[Afghanistan|Afghan]] border with [[Pakistan]], known as the [[Durand Line]], was arbitrarily drawn by colonial officials of the British Empire in 1893 following the [[Second Afghan War]].  Accordingly, the [[Pashtun people|Pashtun]] tribes inhabiting the border areas were arbitrarily divided; the tribes have never accepted the still-porous border.  The Durand Line was not intended as a permanent border, and clashes broke out in the 1950s and 1960s between Afghanistan and Pakistan over the issue.  All Afghan governments of the past century have declared, with varying intensity, a long-term goal of re-uniting all Pashtun-dominated areas under Afghan rule.&lt;ref name=&quot;Roashan&quot;&gt;[http://www.institute-for-afghan-studies.org/Contributions/Commentaries/DRRoashanArch/2001_08_11_unholy_durand_line.htm The Unholy Durand Line, Buffering the Buffer] by Dr. G. Rauf Roashan. August 11, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/05/10/AR2009051001959.html ''Pakistan's Ethnic Fault Line''] by Selig S. Harrison, [[The Washington Post]]. May 11, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Argentina ===
{{see also|Falkland Islands sovereignty dispute}}
[[Image:Malvinas-cartel.JPG|thumb|A sign at the Argentine-Brazilian border, translated into English, proclaims &quot;The [[Falkland Islands|Falklands]] are Argentine&quot; to visitors entering the country from Brazil.]]
The Argentine government has maintained a claim over the Falkland Islands since 1833, and renewed it as recently as June 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lanacion.com.ar/nota.asp?nota_id=1140883 |title=Malvinas: la ONU hará más gestiones para abrir el diálogo |publisher=Lanacion.com.ar |date= |accessdate=2010-03-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; It considers the archipelago part of the [[Tierra del Fuego Province (Argentina)|Tierra del Fuego Province]], along with [[South Georgia]] and the [[South Sandwich Islands]].

The Argentine claim is included in the transitional provisions of the [[Constitution of Argentina]] as [[1994 amendment of the Argentine Constitution|amended in 1994]]:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
url = http://www.senado.gov.ar/web/interes/constitucion/cuerpo1.php
title = Constitución Nacional
lang = Spanish
date =  22 August 1994
accessdate = 17 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
url = http://www.senado.gov.ar/web/interes/constitucion/english.php
title = Constitution of the Argentine Nation
date =  22 August 1994
accessdate = 17 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|The Argentine Nation ratifies its legitimate and non-prescribing sovereignty over the Malvinas, Georgias del Sur and Sandwich del Sur Islands and over the corresponding maritime and insular zones, as they are an integral part of the National territory.

The recovery of these territories and the full exercise of sovereignty, respecting the way of life for its inhabitants and according to the principles of international law, constitute a permanent and unwavering goal of the Argentine people.}}

=== Bolivia ===
The 2009 constitution of [[Bolivia]] states that the country has an unrenounceable right over the territory that gives it access to the [[Pacific Ocean]] and its maritime space.&lt;ref&gt;CAPÍTULO CUARTO, REIVINDICACIÓN MARÍTIMA. Artículo 267. I. El Estado boliviano declara su derecho irrenunciable e imprescriptible sobre el territorio que le dé acceso al océano Pacífico y su espacio marítimo. II. La solución efectiva al diferendo marítimo a través de medios pacíficos y el ejercicio pleno de la soberanía sobre dicho territorio constituyen objetivos permanentes e irrenunciables del Estado boliviano.[http://www.presidencia.gob.bo/download/constitucion.pdf Constitution of Bolivia]&lt;/ref&gt; This is understood as Chilean territory that Bolivia and Peru ceded after the [[War of the Pacific]] which left Bolivia a [[landlocked]] country.

=== People's Republic of China ===
[[File:ROC Administrative and Claims.svg|thumb|right|Official territorial claims according to the Constitution of the [[Republic of China]] (Taiwan).]]
The preamble to the [[Constitution of the People's Republic of China]] states &quot;[[Taiwan]] is part of the sacred territory of the [[People's Republic of China]]. It is the lofty duty of the entire [[Chinese people]], including our compatriots in Taiwan, to accomplish the great task of [[Chinese reunification|reunifying the motherland]].&quot;  The PRC claim to sovereignty over Taiwan is generally based on the [[Succession of states|successor state]] theory, with the PRC claiming that it is the successor state to the Republic of China.&lt;ref name = prc_wp&gt;{{cite web | year=2005| title=The One-China Principle and the Taiwan Issue | work=PRC Taiwan Affairs Office and the Information Office of the State Council | url=http://www.gwytb.gov.cn:8088/detail.asp?table=WhitePaper&amp;title=White%20Papers%20On%20Taiwan%20Issue&amp;m_id=4 | accessdate=2006-03-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Republic of China (Taiwan) ===
Article 4 of the [[Constitution of the Republic of China]] originally stated that &quot;[t]he territory of the Republic of China within its existing national boundaries shall not be altered except by a resolution of the [[National Assembly of the Republic of China|National Assembly]]&quot;, although recent constitutional changes have moved this power to that of a national referendum.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}} The PRC's influence in international organizations prevents Taiwan from participating in many such organizations. In some organizations the [[Republic of China]] is able to participate as [[Chinese Taipei]]. The PRC has an extensive missile build-up near Taiwan{{cn|date=August 2012}} and passed an [[Anti-Secession Law]] in 2005 threatening to use force.

Throughout the 1950s and 1960s, the ROC government on Taiwan maintained itself to be the legitimate ruler of Mainland China. As part of its current policy of 'status quo', the ROC has not renounced claims over the territories currently controlled by the People's Republic of China, [[Mongolia]], and [[Tuvan Republic]] in [[Russia]], Northern Burma and some [[Central Asia]]n states bordering areas. However, the ROC does not actively pursue these claims in practice; the remaining claims that the ROC are actively seeking are the [[Diaoyu Islands]], whose sovereignty is also asserted by [[Japan]] and the PRC; and the [[Spratly Islands]] in [[South China Sea]], with multiple claimants.

=== Comoros ===
Article 1 of the Constitution of the Union of the [[Comoros]] begins: &quot;The Union of the Comoros is a republic, composed of the autonomous islands of [[Mohéli]], [[Mayotte]], [[Anjouan]], and [[Grande Comore]].&quot; Mayotte, geographically a part of the Comoro Islands, was the only island of the four to vote against independence from France (independence losing 37%-63%) in the referendum held December 22, 1974. The total vote was 94%-5% in favor of independence. Mayotte is currently a &quot;departmental collectivity&quot; of the French Republic.&lt;ref&gt;UN General Assembly, [http://un.cti.depaul.edu/Countries/Comoros/1156245840.pdf Forty-ninth session: Agenda item 36]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Security Council S/PV. 1888 para 247 S/11967 [http://www.globalpolicy.org/security/membship/veto/vetosubj.htm] [http://untreaty.un.org/cod/repertory/art33/english/rep_supp5_vol2-art33_e.pdf] {{Wayback|url=http://www.globalpolicy.org/security/membship/veto/vetosubj.htm|date =20080317010910|bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== India ===
All of the European colonies on the Indian subcontinent which were not part of the [[British Raj]] have been annexed by the [[Republic of India]] since it gained its independence from the [[British Empire]]. An example of such territories was the [[1961 Indian annexation of Goa]] and [[Indian integration of Junagadh]].

[[Akhand Bharat]] is another irridentist call for &quot;undivided India&quot; to include [[Pakistan]] and [[Bangladesh]] into [[India]] to form a [[Hindu Rashtra]] raised by  mainstream Indian political organization [[Vishva Hindu Parishad]] (VHP), [[Rashtriya Swayamsevak Sangh]] (RSS) and [[Bharatiya Janata Party]] (BJP).&lt;ref name=Ferguson&gt;Yale H. Ferguson and R. J. Barry Jones, ''Political space: frontiers of change and governance in a globalizing world'', page 155, SUNY Press, 2002, ISBN 978-0-7914-5460-2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Majumder&gt;Sucheta Majumder, &quot;Right Wing Mobilization in India&quot;, ''Feminist Review'', issue 49, page 17, Routledge, 1995, ISBN 978-0-415-12375-4&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Martensson&gt;Ulrika Mårtensson and Jennifer Bailey, ''Fundamentalism in the Modern World'' (Volume 1), page 97, I.B.Tauris, 2011, ISBN 978-1-84885-330-0&lt;/ref&gt;

From 1956 after King of Kashmir ceded to India entirely resulting from a Pakistani invasion of Kashmir earlier, [[India]] has claimed the entire area of [[Kashmir]] as part of their state's &quot;national territory.&quot; Meanwhile [[Pakistan]] has claimed almost all of the state except for the portion of the state Pakistan ceded to China. Both currently administer large sections of the area, and the two countries have fought multiple wars over the area. India and Pakistan aspire to take [[Pakistan-administered Kashmir]], and [[Indian-administered Kashmir]], respectively, so that Kashmir may be re-united under their respective rule.

=== Indonesia ===
Indonesia claimed all territories of the former [[Dutch East Indies]], and previously viewed British plans to group the [[Straits Settlements]], the [[Federated Malay States]], the [[Unfederated Malay States]], [[Sarawak]] and [[Sabah|British North Borneo]] into a new independent federation of [[Malaysia]] as a threat to its objective to create a united state called [[Greater Indonesia]]. The Indonesian opposition of Malaysian formation has led to [[Indonesia-Malaysia confrontation]] in early 1960s. It had also held [[History of Timor Leste|Portuguese Timor]] from 1975 to 2002, based on irredentist claims.

The idea of uniting former British and Dutch colonial possessions in Southeast Asia actually have its roots in early 20th century, as the concept of Greater Malay (''Melayu Raya'') was coined in [[British Malaya]] espoused by students and graduates of  [[Universiti Pendidikan Sultan Idris|Sultan Idris Training College for Malay Teachers]] in the late 1920s.&lt;ref name=&quot;McIntyre&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=McIntyre |first=Angus |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=1973 |month= |title=The 'Greater Indonesia' Idea of Nationalism in Malaysia and Indonesia. |journal=Modern Asian Studies |volume=7 |issue=1 |pages=75–83 |id= |url= |accessdate= 2008-02-16 |doi=10.1017/S0026749X0000439X}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some of political figures in Indonesia including [[Muhammad Yamin]] and [[Sukarno]] revived the idea in the 1950s and named the political union concept as Greater Indonesia.

=== Ireland ===
From 1937 until 1998, [[Articles 2 and 3 of the Constitution of Ireland|Articles 2 and 3]] of the [[Constitution of Ireland]] provided that &quot;[t]he national territory consists of the whole island of Ireland&quot;. However, &quot;[p]ending the re-integration of the national territory&quot;, the powers of the state were restricted to legislate only for the area that had ceded from the [[United Kingdom]]. Arising from the [[Northern Ireland peace process]], the matter was mutually resolved in 1998. The [[Republic of Ireland]]'s constitution was altered by [[referendum]] and its territorial claim to [[Northern Ireland]] was dropped. The amended constitution asserts that while it is the entitlement of &quot;every person born in the island of Ireland … to be part of the Irish Nation&quot; and to hold Irish citizenship, &quot;a united Ireland shall be brought about only by peaceful means with the consent of a majority of the people, democratically expressed, in both jurisdictions in the island.&quot; Certain [[North/South Ministerial Council|joint policy and executive bodies]] were created between Northern Ireland, the part of the island that remained in the United Kingdom, and the Republic of Ireland, and these were given executive authority. The advisory and consultative role of the government of Ireland in the government of Northern Ireland granted by the United Kingdom, that had begun with the 1985 [[Anglo-Irish Agreement]], was maintained. The two states also settled the long-running [[Names of the Irish state|dispute concerning their respective names]]: ''Ireland'' and the ''United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland'', with both governments agreeing to use those names.

=== Israel ===
The entire area of the West Bank and Gaza, previously annexed by Jordan and occupied by Egypt respectively,  was controlled by Israel from the 1967 war until August 2005, when Israel withdrew from Gaza.  Israel never explicitly claimed any of the West Bank for its own state except the city of Jerusalem, which it unilaterally annexed in 1980.  However, Israel has settled hundreds of thousands of its citizens in various Israeli controlled settlements in the West Bank.

Article 3 of the Basic Law of the [[Palestinian Authority]], which was ratified in 2002 by the [[Palestinian National Authority]] and serves as an interim constitution, states that &quot;[[Jerusalem]] is the capital of Palestine.&quot; The Israeli annexing instrument, the [[Jerusalem Law]]&amp;mdash;one of the [[Basic Laws of Israel]] that &quot;serve in the place of a constitution&quot;&amp;mdash;declares Jerusalem, &quot;complete and united&quot;, to be the capital of Israel, creating a conflict with Palestinian claims. ''De facto'', the Palestinian government administers the parts of the [[West Bank]] that Israel has granted it authority over from [[Ramallah]], while the [[Gaza Strip]] is administered from [[Gaza]].

According to United Nations Resolutions 242 and 338, East Jerusalem is part of the occupied territories. The United States does not recognize Israeli sovereignty over East Jerusalem and maintains its embassy in Tel Aviv. In Jerusalem, the United States maintains a Consulate General as a diplomatic representation to the city of Jerusalem alone, separate from the US's representation to the state of Israel.  The Consulate General maintains two buildings in the city as they were established before the 1967 war, one building on what was the Israeli side and one on what was the Jordanian-annexed side of Jerusalem.

===Korea===
Since their founding, both Korean states have disputed the legitimacy of the other. [[South Korea]]'s constitution claims jurisdiction over the entire Korean peninsula. It acknowledges the [[division of Korea]] only indirectly by requiring the president to work for reunification. [[North Korea]]'s constitution also stresses the importance of reunification, but makes no similar claim to the entire peninsula.

===United States===
The first constitution of the United States, the [[Articles of Confederation]], included a provision in Article XI to allow the admission of [[Canada]] as a state.

==Other irredentism==
Until the [[Nineteenth Amendment of the Constitution of Ireland]] in 1998 the Irish Republic claimed the territory of six counties that form Northern Ireland. 
[[Spain]] claims the [[British Overseas Territories|British overseas territory]] of [[Gibraltar]], ceded to Britain in perpetuity in 1713 under the [[Treaty of Utrecht]], and argues its case at the [[United Nations]] claiming its territorial integrity is affected. During World War II, the Spanish Falangist media agitated for irredentism claiming for Spain the French Navarre, French Basque Country and Roussillon (French Catalonia) as well. [[Morocco]] makes similar claims against Spain over the [[North Africa]]n enclaves of [[Ceuta]] and [[Melilla]]. [[Portugal]] does not recognize as Spanish the territory of [[Olivenza]] conquered by Spain during the [[Napoleonic Wars]]. [http://www.elpais.com/articulo/espana/eterna/disputa/Olivenza-Olivenca/elpepunac/20061204elpepinac_13/Tes]

Some of the most violent irredentist conflicts of recent times in [[Europe]] flared up as a consequence of the break-up of the former [[Yugoslavia]] in the early 1990s. The wars in [[Croatia]] and [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]] were largely about creating a new political framework of states, each of which would be ethnically and politically homogeneous{{dubious|date=October 2011}}{{clarify|date=October 2011}}. The conflict erupted further south with the ethnic Albanian majority in [[Kosovo]] seeking to switch allegiance to the adjoining state of [[Albania]].&lt;ref&gt;See [[Naomi Chazan]] 1991, ''Irredentism and international politics''&lt;/ref&gt; [[Greece]] claims that the use of the name [[Republic of Macedonia]] by its northern neighbor signifies an irredentist claim on the northern province of [[Macedonia (Greece)|Macedonia]] in Greece. 

[[South Asia]] too is another region in which armed irredentist movements have been active for almost a century, due to the [[Balkanization]] of [[North-East India]], Burma and [[Bangladesh]] under [[British colonialism]]. {{dubious|date=January 2012}}{{clarify|date=January 2012}} Most prominent amongst them are the [[Naga (clan)|Naga]] fight for Greater [[Nagaland]], the [[Chin people|Chin]] struggle for a unified [[Chinland]] and other self-determinist movements by the [[ethnic]] [[indigenous peoples]] of the erstwhile [[Assam]] both under the British and post-British Assam under India.{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}}

Irredentism is acute in the Caucasus region, too.  The [[Nagorno-Karabakh]] movement’s original slogan of miatsum (‘union’) was explicitly oriented towards unification with Armenia, feeding an Azerbaijani understanding of the conflict as a bilateral one between itself and an irredentist Armenia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.c-r.org/resources/occasional-papers/resources-for-peace.php Dr Laurence Broers, The resources for peace: comparing the Karabakh, Abkhazia and South Ossetia peace processes, Conciliation Resources, 2006]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://cria-online.org/5_4.html Fareed Shafee, Inspired from Abroad: The External Sources of Separatism in Azerbaijan, Caucasian Review of International Affairs, Vol. 2 (4) - Autumn 2008, pp. 200-211]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.semp.us/publications/biot_reader.php?BiotID=224 What is Irredentism? SEMP, Biot Report #224, USA, June 21, 2005]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sneps.net/NNE/09NNNSaidemanAyres.pdf Saideman, Stephen M. and R. William Ayres, For Kin and Country: Xenophobia, Nationalism and War, New York, N.Y.: Columbia University Press, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jamestown.org/single/?no_cache=1&amp;tx_ttnews%5Btt_news%5D=17598&amp;tx_ttnews%5BbackPid%5D=212 IRREDENTISM ENTERS ARMENIA'S FOREIGN POLICY, Jamestown Foundation Monitor Volume: 4 Issue: 77, Washington DC, April 22, 1998]&lt;/ref&gt; According to Prof. Thomas Ambrosio, &quot;Armenia's successful irredentist project in the Nagorno-Karabakh region of Azerbaijan&quot; and &quot;From 1992 to the cease-fire in 1994, Armenia encountered a highly permissive or tolerant international environment that allowed its annexation of some 15 percent of Azerbaijani territory&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=0hLzXEO-fAQC&amp;pg=PA146 Prof. Thomas Ambrosio, Irredentism: ethnic conflict and international politics, Greenwood Publishing Group, 2001]&lt;/ref&gt;
In the view of Nadia Milanova, Nagorno-Karabakh represents a combination of separatism and irredentism.&lt;ref&gt;Nadia Milanova. The Territory-Identity Nexus in the Conflict over Nagorno Karabakh: Implications for OSCE Peace Efforts, Human Rights Without Frontiers International, 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Syrian Social Nationalist Party]], which operates in [[Lebanon]] and [[Syria]], works for the unification of most modern states of the [[Levant]] and beyond in a single state referred to as [[Greater Syria]].{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}} The proposed Syrian country includes [[Israel]], [[Jordan]], [[Iraq]], [[Kuwait]]; and southern [[Turkey]], northern [[Egypt]], and southwestern [[Iran]].

Japan claims the Russian-administered [[Kuril Islands]], the four southernmost isles of the island chain north of [[Hokkaido]], annexed by the [[Soviet Union]] following World War II.{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}}

The 1909 [[Gando Convention]] addressed a territory dispute between China and [[Joseon Korea]] in China's favor. Both Korean states now accept the convention border as an administrative boundary. However, because the convention was made by the occupying [[Empire of Japan]], [[South Korea]] has disputed its legality and some Koreans claim that Korea extends into ''de facto'' PRC territory. The most ambitious claims include all parts of [[Manchuria]] that the [[Goguryeo]] kingdom controlled. Both Korean states [[Liancourt Rocks dispute|claim the Liancourt Rocks]], which Japan annexed while Korea was a Japanese protectorate.

Irredentism is commonplace in [[Africa]] due to the political boundaries of former European colonial nation-states passing through tribal boundaries, and recent declarations of independence after civil war. For example, some Ethiopian nationalist circles still claim the former Ethiopian province of [[Eritrea]] (internationally recognized as the independent State of Eritrea in 1993 after a 30 year civil war).  [[Ogaden]] in eastern Ethiopia has seen a movement seeking to make it part of [[Somalia]].

==North American==
{{See also|Reconquista (Mexico)}}
Irredentism is also expressed by some [[Chicano]] &quot;nationalists&quot; and [[Mexican-American]] activists in the [[Aztlán]] movement. They call for the return of formerly Mexican-dominated lands in the [[American Southwest|Southwestern United States]] back to [[Mexico]] after the [[United States of America|US]] annexed lands in the [[Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo]] to become the present-day states of [[California]], [[Texas]], [[Nevada]] and [[Utah]]; and parts of [[Colorado]], [[Arizona]], and [[New Mexico]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Mexicano political experience in occupied Aztlán: struggles and change |last=Navarro |first=Armando |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=2005 |publisher=AltaMira Press |location=[[Walnut Creek, California]] |isbn=978-0-7591-0567-6 |page= |pages=753 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=on1DZMLNcZIC&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s |accessdate=28 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Congressional Record, V. 149, Pt. 9, May 14, 2003 to May 21, 2003 |last= |first= |authorlink= |coauthors= |year= |publisher=[[Government Printing Office]] |location= |isbn= |page=11990 |pages= |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=k7dKHW9trqIC&amp;lpg=PA11990&amp;dq=Aztlan%20return%20of%20Southwest%20United%20States&amp;pg=PA11990#v=onepage&amp;q=Aztlan%20return%20of%20Southwest%20United%20States&amp;f=false |accessdate=28 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://isanet.ccit.arizona.edu/noarchive/price.html |title=Chapter Two:Border Clashes in Aztlán |author= |date= |work=International Studies Association |publisher=[[University of Arizona]] |accessdate=28 February 2012 |quote=Some leaders, particularly during the early years of El Movimiento, were political nationalists who advocated the secession of the Southwest from the Anglo-republic of the United States of America, if not fully, at least locally with regard to Chicano self-determination in local governance, education, and means of production. }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.fairus.org/site/News2?page=NewsArticle&amp;id=16971&amp;security=1601&amp;news_iv_ctrl=1821 |title=
Chicano Nationalism, Revanchism and the Aztlan Myth |author= |date=January 2005 |work= |publisher=[[Federation for American Immigration Reform]] |accessdate=28 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.humanevents.com/article.php?id=16245 |title=The Reconquista Movement: Mexico's Plan for the American Southwest |last1=Gilchrist |first1=Jim |last2=Corsi |first2=Jerome R. |date=27 July 2006 |work=[[Human Events]] |publisher=Eagle Publishing, Inc. |accessdate=28 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.adl.org/learn/aztlan/atzlan_printable.html |title=Backgrounder: Nation of Aztlan |author= |date=2001 |work= |publisher=[[Anti-Defamation League]] |accessdate=28 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==UK issues==
A unique situation exists with that of [[Berwick-upon-Tweed|Berwick]]. Part of the citizenry of the town support the transfer of Berwick to Scotland, although others would prefer it to remain as part of the English county of Northumberland.&lt;ref&gt;Katie Dawson, [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/politics/election_2010/england/8640148.stm Berwick-upon-Tweed: English or Scottish?], BBC, 1 May 2010&lt;/ref&gt; However, due to the nature of the political union between [[Scotland]] and [[England]] forming the [[UK]] the reunification of Berwick goes largely unpursued. Various debates have arisen surrounding the constitutional future of Berwick, or [[Berwick-upon-Tweed]] as it is known in England, but have been largely academic. 

Irredentism was also one of main reasons for the People's Republic of China to assume sovereignty over [[Hong Kong]]. The territory had been leased by the British for 99 years. In 1997, when the lease ran out, the United Kingdom relenquished control of Hong Kong. However, in the case of Hong Kong, irredentism was incidental as the he [[New Territories]] part of the British colony were only on a lease expiring in 1997 anyway and, with their surrender, it was thought the Crown territory of Hong Kong itself would be nonviable as an entity independent of mainland China. Of course, irredentism could be considered to have played a role in that the People's Republic of China had no intention of renewing the lease on the New Territories.

==See also==
*[[List of irredentist claims or disputes]]
*[[Annexationism]]
*[[Ethnic nationalism]]
*[[Expansionism]]
*[[Lebensraum]]
*[[Manifest Destiny]]
*[[Reconquista (Mexico)]]
*[[Revanchism]]
*[[Status quo ante bellum]]
*[[Territorial dispute]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
* Willard, CA 1996 — Liberalism and the Problem of Knowledge: A New Rhetoric for Modern Democracy, Chicago: University of Chicago Press. 10-ISBN 0226898458/13-ISBN 9780226898452; OCLC 260223405

== External links ==
{{Wiktionary}}
{{commons category|Irredentism}}

{{Irredentism}}
{{Nationalism}}

[[Category:Divided regions]]
[[Category:International relations theory]]
[[Category:Irredentism| ]]
[[Category:Pan-nationalism| ]]

[[bg:Иредентизъм]]
[[bs:Iredentizam]]
[[ca:Irredemptisme]]
[[cs:Iredentismus]]
[[cy:Iredentiaeth]]
[[da:Irredentisme]]
[[de:Irredentismus]]
[[el:Αλυτρωτισμός]]
[[es:Irredentismo]]
[[eo:Iredentismo]]
[[eu:Irredentismo]]
[[fr:Irrédentisme]]
[[fur:Iredentisim]]
[[gl:Irredentismo]]
[[hy:Իրրեդենտիզմ]]
[[hr:Iredentizam]]
[[it:Irredentismo]]
[[he:אירידנטה]]
[[ka:ირედენტიზმი]]
[[kk:Ирредентизм]]
[[hu:Irredentizmus]]
[[mk:Иредентизам]]
[[nl:Irredentisme]]
[[ja:民族統一主義]]
[[no:Irredentisme]]
[[pl:Irredenta]]
[[pt:Irredentismo]]
[[ro:Iredentism]]
[[rm:Irredentissem (sursilvan)]]
[[ru:Ирредентизм]]
[[simple:Irredentism]]
[[sk:Iredentizmus]]
[[sl:Iredentizem]]
[[sr:Иредентизам]]
[[sh:Iredentizam]]
[[fi:Irredentismi]]
[[sv:Irredentism]]
[[tr:İrredantizm]]
[[uk:Іредентизм]]
[[zh:民族统一主义]]</text>
      <sha1>hgdrv6dxkcjx5hg69ams45v81s90gve</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
