<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Japanese American internment</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>46884</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520652168</id>
      <parentid>519787189</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-30T21:40:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>TheRedPenOfDoom</username>
        <id>5745932</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Notable internees */ dont inter wiki link that way</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="103670">{{Use mdy dates|date=April 2012}}
{{Infobox historical event
  |Event_Name     = Japanese American internment
  |Image_Name     = Map of World War II Japanese American internment camps.png
  |Imagesize      = 400
  |Image_Alt      = 
  |Image_Caption  = Internment camps and further institutions of the War Relocation Authority in the western United States.
  |Thumb_Time     = 
  |AKA            = 
  |Participants   =
  |Location       = [[United States]]
  |Date           = 1942 - 1946&lt;ref name=&quot;arizona.edu&quot;&gt;{{Web reference | title=War Relocation Camps in Arizona 1942-1946| work=| url=http://parentseyes.arizona.edu/wracamps/| date=| year=| accessdate=October 2, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
  |nongregorian   = 
  |Deaths        = 
  |Result         = 
  |URL            = 
}}

'''Japanese-American internment''' was the relocation and [[internment]] by the [[Federal government of the United States|United States government]] in 1942 of about 110,000 [[Japanese American]]s and Japanese who lived along the Pacific coast of the United States to camps called &quot;War Relocation Camps,&quot; in the wake of [[Empire of Japan|Imperial Japan]]'s [[attack on Pearl Harbor]].&lt;ref&gt;National Park Service. [http://www.nps.gov/manz/ Manzanar National Historic Site]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=howmany&gt;Various primary and secondary sources list counts between persons.&lt;/ref&gt; The internment of Japanese Americans was applied unequally throughout the United States. All who lived on the [[West Coast of the United States]] were interned, while in [[Territory of Hawaii|Hawaii]], where the 150,000-plus Japanese Americans composed over one-third of the population, an estimated 1,200&lt;ref&gt;Ogawa, Dennis M. and Fox, Jr., Evarts C. ''Japanese Americans, from Relocation to Redress''. 1991, page 135.&lt;/ref&gt; to 1,800 were interned.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hawaiischoolreports.com/history/internment.htm Internment – WWII Hawaii&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]{{Dead link|date=April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Of those interned, 62% were [[Citizenship in the United States|American citizens]].&lt;ref&gt;Semiannual Report of the War Relocation Authority, for the period January 1 to June 30, 1946, not dated. Papers of Dillon S. Myer. [http://www.trumanlibrary.org/whistlestop/study_collections/japanese_internment/documents/index.php?pagenumber=4&amp;documentid=62&amp;documentdate=1946-00-00&amp;collectionid=JI&amp;nav=ok Scanned image at] trumanlibrary.org. Retrieved September 18, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=trumanlib_1948&gt;&quot;The War Relocation Authority and The Incarceration of Japanese Americans During World War II: 1948 Chronology,&quot; [http://www.trumanlibrary.org/whistlestop/study_collections/japanese_internment/1948.htm Web page] at www.trumanlibrary.org. Retrieved September 11, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

President [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]] authorized the internment with [[Executive Order 9066]], issued February 19, 1942, which allowed local military commanders to designate &quot;military areas&quot; as &quot;exclusion zones,&quot; from which &quot;any or all persons may be excluded.&quot; This power was used to declare that all people of Japanese ancestry were excluded from the entire Pacific coast, including all of California and much of Oregon, Washington and Arizona, except for those in internment camps.&lt;ref name=korematsu_roberts&gt;[http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?navby=CASE&amp;court=US&amp;vol=323&amp;page=214 ''Korematsu v. United States''] dissent by Justice [[Owen Josephus Roberts]], reproduced at findlaw.com. Retrieved September 12, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1944, the [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]] [[Korematsu v. United States|upheld]] the constitutionality of the exclusion orders,&lt;ref name=korematsu_majority&gt;[http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?court=US&amp;vol=323&amp;invol=214 ''Korematsu v. United States''] majority opinion by Justice [[Hugo Black]], reproduced at findlaw.com. Retrieved September 11, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; while noting that the provisions that singled out people of Japanese ancestry were a separate issue outside the scope of the proceedings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Hakim | first = Joy | title = A History of Us: War, Peace and all that Jazz | publisher=Oxford University Press | year = 1995 | location = New York | pages = 100–104 | isbn = 0-19-509514-6 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[United States Census Bureau]] assisted the internment efforts by providing confidential neighborhood information on Japanese Americans. The Bureau's role was denied for decades, but was finally proven in 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite document|title=Confirmed: The U.S. Census Bureau Gave Up Names of Japanese-Americans in WW II|url=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=confirmed-the-us-census-b&amp;sc=I100322|publisher=Scientific American|author=JR Minkel|date=March 30, 2007|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite document|url=http://www.usatoday.com/news/nation/2007-03-30-census-role_N.htm|title=Papers show Census role in WWII camps|work=USA Today |author=Haya El Nasser|date=March 30, 2007|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1988, [[United States Congress|Congress]] passed and [[President of the United States|President]] [[Ronald Reagan]] signed legislation which apologized for the internment on behalf of the [[Federal government of the United States|U.S. government]]. The legislation said that government actions were based on &quot;race prejudice, war hysteria, and a failure of political leadership&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;100th Congress, S. 1009, [http://www.internmentarchives.com/showdoc.php?docid=00055&amp;search_id=19269&amp;pagenum=2 reproduced at] internmentarchives.com. Retrieved September 19, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;  The U.S. government eventually disbursed more than $1.6&amp;nbsp;billion in [[reparation (legal)|reparations]] to Japanese Americans who had been interned and their heirs.&lt;ref name=&quot;democracynow&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.democracynow.org/1999/2/18/wwii_reparations_japanese_american_internees |title=Wwii Reparations: Japanese-American Internees |publisher=Democracy Now! |accessdate=January 24, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Historical context==
{{See also|Anti-Japanese sentiment in the United States}}
In the first half of the 20th century, California experienced a wave of anti-Japanese prejudice, in part because of the concentration of new immigrants. This was distinct from the [[Japanese American]] experience in the broader United States. Over 90% of Japanese immigrants to the USA settled in California, where labor and farm competition fed into general anti-Japanese sentiment.&lt;ref name=leupp&gt;Leupp, Gary P. ''Interracial Intimacy in Japan: Western Men and Japanese Women, 1543–1900''. 2003, page 216-7&lt;/ref&gt; In 1905, California's anti-[[miscegenation]] law outlawed marriages between Caucasians and &quot;[[Mongoloid race|Mongolians]]&quot;, an umbrella term that was used to refer to the Japanese and other ethnicities of East Asian ancestry.&lt;ref name=leupp/&gt; In October 1906, the San Francisco Board of Education separated Japanese students from Caucasian students. It ordered 93 Japanese students in the district to attend a segregated school in Chinatown.&lt;ref&gt;Nakanishi, Don T. and Nishida, Tina Yamano. ''The Asian American Educational Experience''. 1995, page 15-6&lt;/ref&gt; Twenty-five of the students were American citizens. In 1924, the &quot;[[1924 Immigration Act|Oriental Exclusion Law]]&quot; eliminated all Japanese immigration. Japanese immigrants had already been unable to attain citizenship by naturalization.&lt;ref name=leupp/&gt;

In 1939 through 1941, the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation]] (FBI) compiled the [[Custodial Detention Index]] (CDI) on citizens, enemy aliens and foreign nationals, citing national security. On June 28, 1940, the [[Smith Act|Alien Registration Act]] was passed. Among many other loyalty regulations, Section 31 required the registration and fingerprinting of all aliens older than 14, and Section 35 required aliens to report any change of address within five days. In the subsequent months, nearly five million foreign nationals registered at post offices around the country.&lt;ref&gt;John J. Culley, &quot;World War II and a Western Town: The Internment of Japanese Railroad Workers of Clovis, New Mexico.&quot; ''[[Western Historical Quarterly]]'' 13 (January 1982): 43–61.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.spartacus.schoolnet.co.uk/USAmccarthyism.htm|title=US McCarthyism}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Of 127,000 Japanese Americans living in the continental United States at the time of the Pearl Harbor attack, 112,000 resided on the West Coast.&lt;ref&gt;Okihiro, Gary Y. ''The Columbia Guide to Asian American History''. 2005, page 104&lt;/ref&gt; About 80,000 were ''nisei'' (literal translation: &quot;second generation&quot;; Japanese people born in the United States and holding American citizenship) and ''[[sansei]]'' (literal translation: &quot;third generation&quot;; the sons or daughters of ''[[nisei]]''). The rest were ''[[issei]]'' (literal translation: &quot;first generation&quot;; immigrants born in Japan who were ineligible for U.S. citizenship).&lt;ref&gt;Nash, Gary B., Julie Roy Jeffrey, John R. Howe, Peter J. Frederick, Allen F. Davis, Allan M. Winkler, Charlene Mires, and Carla Gardina Pestana. ''The American People, Concise Edition Creating a Nation and a Society'', Combined Volume (6th Edition). New York: Longman, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

==After Pearl Harbor==
[[Image:JapaneseRelocationNewspapers1942.gif|thumb|San Francisco Examiner, February 1942.]] [[Image:JapaneseAmericanGrocer1942.jpg|thumb|A Japanese American unfurled this banner the day after the Pearl Harbor attack. This [[Dorothea Lange]] photograph was taken in March 1942, just prior to the man's internment.]]
[[File:JapaneseAmericansChildrenPledgingAllegiance1942-2.jpg|thumb|Children at the Weill public school in San Francisco [[pledge of allegiance|pledge allegiance]] to the [[American flag]] in April 1942, prior to the internment of Japanese Americans.]]
[[File:Russell Lee, Tagged for evacuation, Salinas, California, May 1942.jpg|thumb|Taken by [[Russell Lee (photographer)|Russell Lee]], this photograph is labeled &quot;Tagged for evacuation, [[Salinas, California]], May 1942&quot;.]]
The [[attack on Pearl Harbor]] on December 7, 1941 led military and political leaders to suspect that [[Imperial Japan]] was preparing a full-scale attack on the West Coast of the United States. Japan's [[Pacific War#Japanese Blitzkrieg|rapid military conquest]] of a large portion of Asia and the Pacific between 1936 and 1942 made its military forces seem unstoppable to some Americans. Civilian and military officials had serious concerns about the loyalty of the ethnic Japanese after the [[Niihau Incident]] which immediately followed the attack on Pearl Harbor, when a civilian Japanese national and two Hawaiian-born ethnic Japanese on the island of Ni'ihau violently freed a downed and captured Japanese naval airman, attacking their fellow Ni'ihau islanders in the process.

Several concerns over the loyalty of ethnic Japanese seemed to stem from [[racial prejudice]] rather than evidence of actual malfeasance. Major [[Karl Bendetsen]] and Lieutenant General [[John L. DeWitt]], head of the Western Command, each questioned Japanese American loyalty. DeWitt, who administered the internment program, repeatedly told newspapers that &quot;A Jap's a Jap&quot; and testified to Congress,

{{quotation|I don't want any of them [persons of Japanese ancestry] here. They are a dangerous element. There is no way to determine their loyalty... It makes no difference whether he is an American citizen, he is still a Japanese. American citizenship does not necessarily determine loyalty... But we must worry about the Japanese all the time until he is wiped off the map.&lt;ref&gt;Fred Mullen, &quot;DeWitt Attitude on Japs Upsets Plans,&quot; ''Watsonville Register-Pajaronian'', April&amp;nbsp;16,&amp;nbsp;1943. p.1, reproduced by [http://web.archive.org/web/20070928001103/http://www.santacruzpl.org/history/ww2/9066/articles/rp/43/4-16.shtml Santa Cruz Public Library]. Retrieved September 11, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Testimony of John L. DeWitt, April 13, 1943, House Naval Affairs Subcommittee to Investigate Congested Areas, Part 3, pp. 739–40 (78th Cong ., 1st Sess.), cited in [http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?court=US&amp;vol=323&amp;invol=214#fff1 ''Korematsu v. United States (Murphy, J., dissenting)'', footnote 2], reproduced at findlaw.com. Retrieved September 11, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

DeWitt also sought approval to conduct search and seizure operations aimed at preventing alien Japanese from making radio transmissions to Japanese ships.&lt;ref name=&quot;Taslitz&quot;&gt;Andrew E. Taslitz, Stories of Fourth Amendment Disrespect: From Elian to the Internment, 70 ''Fordham Law Review''. 2257, 2306–07 (2002).&lt;/ref&gt; The Justice Department declined, stating that there was no [[probable cause]] to support DeWitt's assertion, as the FBI concluded that there was no security threat.&lt;ref name=&quot;Taslitz&quot;/&gt; On January 2, the Joint Immigration Committee of the California Legislature sent a manifesto to California newspapers which attacked &quot;the ethnic Japanese,&quot; who it alleged were &quot;totally unassimilable.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Taslitz&quot;/&gt; This manifesto further argued that all people of Japanese heritage were loyal subjects of the [[Emperor of Japan]]; Japanese language schools, furthermore, according to the manifesto, were bastions of racism which advanced doctrines of Japanese racial superiority.&lt;ref name=&quot;Taslitz&quot;/&gt;

The manifesto was backed by the [[Native Sons and Daughters of the Golden West]] and the California Department of the [[American Legion]], which in January demanded that all Japanese with [[dual citizenship]] be placed in concentration camps.&lt;ref name=&quot;Taslitz&quot;/&gt; Internment was not limited to those who had been to Japan, but included a small number of German and Italian enemy aliens.&lt;ref name=&quot;Taslitz&quot;/&gt; By February, [[Earl Warren]], the [[Attorney General of California]], had begun his efforts to persuade the federal government to remove all people of Japanese heritage from the West Coast.&lt;ref name=&quot;Taslitz&quot;/&gt;

Those that were as little as 1/16 Japanese could be placed in internment camps.&lt;ref name=&quot;Short History of Amache Japanese Internment Camp&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.colorado.gov/dpa/doit/archives/wwcod/granada3.htm|title=''Short History of Amache Japanese Internment''|accessdate=April 21, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is evidence supporting the argument that the measures were racially motivated, rather than a military necessity. For example, orphaned infants with &quot;one drop of Japanese blood&quot; (as explained in a letter by one official) were included in the program.

Upon the bombing of Pearl Harbor and pursuant to the [[Alien and Sedition Acts|Alien Enemies Act]], Presidential Proclamations 2525, 2526 and 2527 were issued designating Japanese, German and Italian nationals as enemy aliens.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=In Defense of Internment: The World War II Round-Up and What It Means For America's War on Terror |last=Malkin |first=Michelle |authorlink=Michelle Malkin |year=2004 |publisher=Regnery Publishing |isbn=0-89526-051-4 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=nvsIQNwYvSwC&amp;pg=PA56 |accessdate=April 3, 2010 |page=56 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Information from the CDI was used to locate and incarcerate foreign nationals from Japan, Germany and Italy (although Germany and Italy did not declare war on the U.S. until December 11).

Presidential Proclamation 2537 was issued on January 14, 1942, requiring aliens to report any change of address, employment or name to the FBI. Enemy aliens were not allowed to enter restricted areas. Violators of these regulations were subject to &quot;arrest, detention and internment for the duration of the war.&quot;

===Executive Order 9066 and related actions===
Executive Order 9066, signed by Franklin D. Roosevelt on February 19, 1942, allowed authorized military commanders to designate &quot;military areas&quot; at their discretion, &quot;from which any or all persons may be excluded.&quot; These &quot;exclusion zones,&quot; unlike the &quot;alien enemy&quot; roundups, were applicable to anyone that an authorized military commander might choose, whether citizen or non-citizen. Eventually such zones would include parts of both the East and West Coasts, totaling about 1/3 of the country by area. Unlike the subsequent detainment and internment programs that would come to be applied to large numbers of Japanese Americans, detentions and restrictions directly under this Individual Exclusion Program were placed primarily on individuals of German or Italian ancestry, including American citizens.&lt;ref name=archives_aliens&gt;[http://www.archives.gov/genealogy/immigration/enemy-aliens-overview.html ''WWII Enemy Alien Control Overview''] from archives.gov Retrieved January 8, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
*March 2, 1942: General [[John L. DeWitt]] issued Public Proclamation No. 1, declaring that &quot;such person or classes of persons as the situation may require&quot; would, at some later point, be subject to exclusion orders from &quot;Military Area No. 1&quot; (essentially, the entire Pacific coast to about {{convert|100|mi|km|1}} inland), and requiring anyone who had &quot;enemy&quot; ancestry to file a Change of Residence Notice if they planned to move.&lt;ref name=korematsu_roberts/&gt; A second exclusion zone was designated several months later, which included the areas chosen by most of the Japanese Americans who had managed to leave the first zone.
*March 11, 1942: Executive Order 9095 created the Office of the Alien Property Custodian, and gave it discretionary, plenary authority over all alien property interests. Many assets were frozen, creating immediate financial difficulty for the affected aliens, preventing most from moving out of the exclusion zones.&lt;ref name=korematsu_roberts/&gt;
*March 24, 1942: Public Proclamation No. 3 declares an 8:00&amp;nbsp;pm to 6:00&amp;nbsp;am curfew for &quot;all enemy aliens and all persons of Japanese ancestry&quot; within the military areas.&lt;ref name=hirabayashi&gt;[http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?navby=CASE&amp;court=US&amp;vol=320&amp;page=81 ''Hirabayashi v. United States''], reproduced at findlaw.com. Retrieved September 15, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
*March 24, 1942: General DeWitt began to issue Civilian Exclusion Orders for specific areas within &quot;Military Area No. 1.&quot;&lt;ref name=hirabayashi/&gt; Japanese Americans on [[Bainbridge Island]], Washington were the first in the country to be subject to such an order, due to the island's proximity to naval bases; they were given until March 30 to prepare themselves for removal from the island, an event commemorated by the [[Bainbridge Island Japanese American Exclusion Memorial]].&lt;ref name=&quot;SeattlePI20099330&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.seattlepi.com/local/article/Bainbridge-Island-breaks-ground-for-1302905.php|last=Ho|first=Vanessa|date=March 29, 2009|title=Bainbridge Island breaks ground for Japanese-American internment memorial|periodical=Seattle Post-Intelligencer|accessdate=September 1, 2011|postscript=&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NYTimes20110805&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/08/06/us/06internment.html?pagewanted=all|last=Seelye|first=Katharine Q.|date=August 5, 2011|title=A Wall to Remember an Era's First Exiles|periodical=The New York Times|accessdate=September 1, 2011|postscript=&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*March 27, 1942: General DeWitt's Proclamation No. 4 prohibited all those of Japanese ancestry from leaving &quot;Military Area No. 1&quot; for &quot;any purpose until and to the extent that a future proclamation or order of this headquarters shall so permit or direct.&quot;&lt;ref name=korematsu_roberts/&gt;
*May 3, 1942: General DeWitt issued Civilian Exclusion Order No. 34, ordering all people of Japanese ancestry, whether citizens or non-citizens, who were still living in &quot;Military Area No. 1&quot; to report to assembly centers, where they would live until being moved to permanent &quot;Relocation Centers.&quot;&lt;ref name=korematsu_roberts/&gt;

These edicts included persons of part-Japanese ancestry as well. Anyone with at least one-sixteenth Japanese ancestry was eligible.&lt;ref name='JPRI WP110'&gt;{{cite web| first=Ellen Clare| last=Kennedy |url=http://www.jpri.org/publications/workingpapers/wp110.html |title=The Japanese-American Renunciants: Due Process and the Danger of Making Laws During Times of Fear|publisher=[[Japan Policy Research Institute]]|month=October
|year=2006|accessdate=March 3, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Korean-Americans and Taiwanese, {{Citation needed|date=April 2008}} considered to have Japanese nationality (since Korea and Taiwan were both Japanese colonies), were also included.

===Non-military advocates for exclusion, removal, and detention===
Internment was popular among many white farmers who resented the Japanese-American farmers. &quot;White American farmers admitted that their self-interest required removal of the Japanese.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Taslitz&quot;/&gt; These individuals saw internment as a convenient means of uprooting their Japanese-American competitors. Austin E. Anson, managing secretary of the Salinas Vegetable Grower-Shipper Association, told the ''Saturday Evening Post'' in 1942:

{{quotation|
&quot;We're charged with wanting to get rid of the Japs for selfish reasons. We do. It's a question of whether the white man lives on the Pacific Coast or the brown men. They came into this valley to work, and they stayed to take over... If all the Japs were removed tomorrow, we'd never miss them in two weeks, because the white farmers can take over and produce everything the Jap grows. And we do not want them back when the war ends, either.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?court=US&amp;vol=323&amp;invol=214 ''Korematsu v. United States''] dissent by Justice [[Frank Murphy]], footnote 12, reproduced at findlaw.com. Retrieved September&amp;nbsp;11,&amp;nbsp;2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

The Roberts Commission Report, prepared at President Franklin D. Roosevelt's request, has been cited as an example of the fear and prejudice informing the thinking behind the internment program.&lt;ref name=&quot;Taslitz&quot;/&gt; The Report sought to link Japanese Americans with espionage activity, and to associate them with the bombing of Pearl Harbor.&lt;ref name=&quot;Taslitz&quot;/&gt; Columnist Henry McLemore reflected growing public sentiment fueled by this report:

{{quotation|
&quot;I am for the immediate removal of every Japanese on the West Coast to a point deep in the interior. I don't mean a nice part of the interior either. Herd 'em up, pack 'em off and give 'em the inside room in the badlands... Personally, I hate the Japanese. And that goes for all of them.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Neiwert, David. ''The Eliminationists: How Hate Talk Radicalized the American Right''. 2009, page 195&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

Other California newspapers also embraced this view. According to a ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'' editorial,

{{quotation|
&quot;A viper is nonetheless a viper wherever the egg is hatched.... So, a Japanese American born of Japanese parents, nurtured upon Japanese traditions, living in a transplanted Japanese atmosphere... notwithstanding his nominal brand of accidental citizenship almost inevitably and with the rarest exceptions grows up to be a Japanese, and not an American.... Thus, while it might cause injustice to a few to treat them all as potential enemies, I cannot escape the conclusion... that such treatment... should be accorded to each and all of them while we are at war with their race.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Niiya, Brian. ''Japanese American History''. 1993, page 54&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
State politicians joined the bandwagon that was embraced by Leland Ford of Los Angeles, who demanded that &quot;all Japanese, whether citizens or not, be placed in [inland] concentration camps.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Taslitz&quot;/&gt; Internment of Japanese Americans, who provided critical agricultural labor on the West Coast, created a labor shortage, which was exacerbated by the induction of many American laborers into the Armed Forces. This vacuum precipitated a mass immigration of Mexican workers into the United States to fill these jobs,&lt;ref&gt;Berberoglu, Berch. ''Labor and Capital in the Age of Globalization''. 2002, page 90&lt;/ref&gt; largely under the banner of what became known as the [[Bracero Program]]. Many Japanese internees were even temporarily released from their camps – for instance, to harvest Western beet crops – to address this wartime labor shortage.&lt;ref&gt;Hanel, Rachael. ''The Japanese American Internment''. 2008, page 20&lt;/ref&gt;

==Statement of military necessity as justification for internment==
[[File:A Challenge to Democracy (1944).ogv|thumb|320px|[[A Challenge to Democracy]] was a twenty-minute film produced in 1944 by the [[War Relocation Authority]] ]]

===Niihau Incident===
The [[Niihau Incident]] occurred in December 1941, just after the Japanese attack on Pearl Harbor. It involved three Japanese Americans on the Hawaiian island of [[Niihau]] assisting a Japanese pilot who crashed there. Despite the incident, the Territorial Governor of Hawaii rejected calls for mass internment of the Japanese Americans living there.

===Cryptography===
{{Main|Magic (cryptography)}}
In ''Magic: The Untold Story of US Intelligence and the Evacuation of Japanese Residents From the West Coast During World War II'', [[David Lowman]], a former [[National Security Agency]] (NSA) operative, argues that [[Magic (cryptography)|Magic intercepts]] (&quot;Magic&quot; was the code-name for American code-breaking efforts) posed &quot;the frightening specter of massive espionage nets,&quot; thus justifying internment.&lt;ref&gt;Maki, Mitchell Takeshi and Kitano, Harry H. L. and Berthold, Sarah Megan. ''Achieving the Impossible Dream''. 1999, page 143&lt;/ref&gt; Lowman contended that internment served to ensure the secrecy of US code-breaking efforts, because effective prosecution of Japanese Americans might necessitate disclosure of secret information. If US code-breaking technology was revealed in the context of trials of individual spies, the Japanese Imperial Navy would change its codes, thus undermining US strategic wartime advantage.

Some scholars have criticized or dismissed Lowman's reasoning that &quot;disloyalty&quot; among some individual Japanese Americans could legitimize &quot;incarcerating 120,000 people, including infants, the elderly, and the mentally ill&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Leslie T. Hatamiya. ''Righting a Wrong''. 1994, page 106&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hayashi, Brian Masaru. ''Democratizing the enemy: the Japanese American internment''. 2004, page 6&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Irons, Peter. | title=Justice At War: The Story of the Japanese American Internment Cases | publisher=University of Washington Press | year=1993 page 374-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lowman's reading of the contents of the ''Magic'' cables has also been challenged, as some scholars contend that the cables demonstrate the opposite of what Lowman claims:  that Japanese Americans were not heeding the overtures of Imperial Japan to spy against the United States.&lt;ref&gt;Brian Niiya. ''Japanese American history''. 1993, page 222&lt;/ref&gt; According to one critic, Lowman's book has long since been &quot;refuted and discredited&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.seattlepi.com/local/185162_vcenter06.html |title=Book defends WWII internment of Japanese Americans, racial profiling |publisher=Seattlepi.com |accessdate=January 24, 2010 |deadurl=yes}} {{Dead link|date=January 2012|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The controversial conclusions drawn by Lowman were defended by pundit [[Michelle Malkin]] in her book ''[[In Defense of Internment]]; The Case for 'Racial Profiling' in World War II and the War on Terror''.&lt;ref&gt;Malkin, Michelle. ''In Defense of Internment''. 2004, pages 128; 135; 275.&lt;/ref&gt; Malkin's defense of Japanese internment was in part the result of what she describes as the &quot;constant alarmism from Bush-bashers who argue that every counter-terror measure in America is tantamount to the internment&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Malkin |first=Michelle |url=http://michellemalkin.com/2004/08/03/in-defense-of-internment-2/ |title=In Defense Of Internment |publisher=Michelle Malkin |date=August 3, 2004 |accessdate=December 5, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The text was critical of academia's treatment of the subject, and suggested that academics critical of Japanese internment had ulterior motives. She received much criticism for her text, particularly in regards to her reading of the &quot;Magic&quot; cables.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Eric Muller |url=http://hnn.us/articles/7094.html |title=So Let Me Get This Straight: Michelle Malkin Claims to Have Rewritten the History of Japanese Internment in Just 16 Months? |publisher=Hnn.us |accessdate=December 5, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://hnn.us/articles/7092.html Why the Media Should Stop Paying Attention to the New Book that Defends Japanese Internment&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Khawaja |first=Irfan |url=http://hnn.us/articles/9512.html |title=Japanese Internment: Why Daniel Pipes Is Wrong |publisher=Hnn.us |accessdate=January 24, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Daniel Pipes]], also drawing on Lowman, has defended Malkin's stance, and asserted that Japanese American internment was &quot;a good idea&quot; which offers &quot;lessons for today&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Daniel Pipes |url=http://hnn.us/articles/9289.html |title=Japanese Internment: Why It Was a Good Idea-And the Lessons It Offers Today |publisher=Hnn.us |accessdate=December 5, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States District Court opinions===
[[Image:Posted Japanese American Exclusion Order.jpg|thumb|Official notice of exclusion and removal]]
A report by [[John L. DeWitt|General DeWitt]] and [[Karl Bendetsen|Colonel Bendetsen]] depicting racist bias against Japanese Americans was circulated and then hastily redacted in 1943–1944. The report stated flatly that, because of their race, it was impossible to determine the loyalty of Japanese Americans, thus necessitating internment.&lt;ref name='Final Report'&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sfmuseum.org/war/dewitt0.html|author=Lt. Gen. J.L. DeWitt |title=Final Report; Japanese Evacuation from the West Coast 1942 |publisher=U.S. Army |date=June 5, 1943 |accessdate=March 3, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The original version was so offensive – even in the atmosphere of the wartime 1940s – that Bendetsen ordered all copies to be destroyed. {{Citation needed|date=June 2010}}

In 1980, a copy of the original ''Final Report: Japanese Evacuation from the West Coast – 1942'' was found in the [[United States National Archives|National Archives]], along with notes showing the numerous differences between the original and redacted versions.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}} This earlier, racist and inflammatory version, as well as the FBI and [[Office of Naval Intelligence]] (ONI) reports, led to the ''[[coram nobis]]'' retrials which overturned the convictions of [[Fred Korematsu]], [[Gordon Hirabayashi]] and [[Minoru Yasui]] on all charges related to their refusal to submit to exclusion and internment.&lt;ref name='Bad landmark'&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,926338,00.html| title = Bad landmark; righting a racial wrong| accessdate =March 3, 2011| date = November 21, 1983|work=Time Magazine }}&lt;/ref&gt; The courts found that the government had intentionally withheld these reports and other critical evidence, at trials all the way up to the [[United Nations Supreme Court|Supreme Court]], which would have proved that there was no military necessity for the exclusion and internment of Japanese Americans. In the words of [[United States Department of Justice|Department of Justice]] officials writing during the war, the justifications were based on &quot;willful historical inaccuracies and intentional falsehoods.&quot;

===The Ringle Report===
In May 2011, U.S. Solicitor General [[Neal Katyal]], after a year of investigation, found [[Charles Fahy]] intentionally withheld ''The Ringle Report'', drafted by the Office of Naval Intelligence, in order to justify the Roosevelt administration in the cases of [[Hirabayashi v. United States]] and [[Korematsu v. United States]]. The report would have undermined the administration's position of the military necessity for such action, finding most Japanese-Americans were not a national security threat, along with allegations of communication espionage being unfounded by the FBI and [[Federal Communications Commission]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thenewamerican.com/history/american/7762-fdrs-solicitor-general-withheld-evidence-in-japanese-internment-cases &quot;FDR’s Solicitor General Withheld Evidence in Japanese Internment Cases&quot;], Michael Tennant. New American. June 7, 2011. Accessed June 7, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.latimes.com/2011/may/27/opinion/la-ed-internment-20110527 &quot;The truth about WWII internment&quot;], Los Angeles Times. May 27, 2011. Accessed June 7, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

==Facilities==
[[File:Photograph of Members of the Mochida Family Awaiting Evacuation - NARA - 537505.tif|thumb|left|&quot;Members of the Mochida family awaiting evacuation bus. Identification tags are used to aid in keeping the family unit intact during all phases of evacuation. Mochida operated a nursery and five greenhouses on a two-acre site in Eden Township. He raised snapdragons and sweet peas.&quot;]]

While this event is most commonly called the ''internment'' of Japanese Americans, in fact there were several different types of camps involved. The best known facilities were the ''Assembly Centers'' run by the Wartime Civil Control Administration (WCCA), and the ''Relocation Centers'' run by the [[War Relocation Authority]] (WRA), which are generally (but unofficially) referred to as &quot;internment camps.&quot; The [[United States Department of Justice|Department of Justice]] (DOJ) operated camps officially called ''Internment Camps'', which were used to detain those suspected of actual crimes or &quot;enemy sympathies.&quot; [[German American internment]] and [[Italian American internment]] camps also existed, sometimes sharing facilities with the Japanese Americans. The WCCA and WRA facilities were the largest and the most public. The WCCA Assembly Centers were temporary facilities that were first set up in horse racing tracks, fairgrounds and other large public meeting places to assemble and organize internees before they were transported to WRA Relocation Centers by truck, bus or train. The WRA Relocation Centers were camps that housed persons removed from the exclusion zone after March 1942, or until they were able to relocate elsewhere in America outside the exclusion zone.

===DOJ Internment Camps===
&lt;!-- Some of the following taken from http://www.nps.gov/manz/ccdoj.htm which is a US government source and public domain --&gt;
During World War II, over 7,000 Japanese Americans and Japanese from Latin America were held in internment camps run by the [[Immigration and Naturalization Service]], part of the Department of Justice. In this period, Latin Americans of Japanese ancestry were rounded up and transported to American internment camps run by the U.S. Justice Department.&lt;ref&gt;Robinson, Greg. (2001). [http://books.google.com/books?id=GCFT3SXwsWQC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Gregg+Robinson&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;source=gbs_summary_r&amp;cad=0#PPA14,M1 ''By Order of the President:FDR and the Internment of Japanese Americans,'' p. 264n2] citing C. Harvey Gardiner, ''Pawns in a Triangle of Hate'' (Seattle: University of Washington Press, 1981).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=niiya&gt;Niiya, Brian. ''Japanese American History''. 1993, page 191&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;search.japantimes.co.jp&quot;&gt;Nanami, Masaharu ([[Kyodo News]]), &quot;[http://search.japantimes.co.jp/cgi-bin/nn20090916f2.html Japanese-Peruvians still angry over wartime internment in U.S. camps],&quot; ''[[Japan Times]]'', Sep 16, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; These Latin American internees were eventually, through the efforts of civil rights attorney [[Wayne M. Collins]],&lt;ref name=jla&gt;{{cite web | title=Japanese Latin Americans |url=http://www.densho.org/learning/spice/lesson4/4activity4-7handouts.pdf| accessdate=April 12, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=sfjhw&gt;{{cite web | title=Japanese Americans, the Civil Rights Movement and Beyond|url=http://www.nddcreative.com/sfjhw/sfjhw_pdf/sfjhw_sign2.pdf| accessdate=April 10, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; offered &quot;[[parole]]&quot; relocation to the labor-starved farming community in [[Seabrook, New Jersey]].&lt;ref&gt;Higashide, , Seiichi. (2000).[http://books.google.com/books?id=ORE5wfUNdccC&amp;pg=PA193&amp;dq=Adios+to+Tears:+The+Memoirs+of+a+Japanese-Peruvian+Internee+in+U.S.+Concentration+Camps&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;source=gbs_toc_r&amp;cad=0_0#PPA179,M1 ''Adios to Tears,'' p. 179.]&lt;/ref&gt; Many became naturalized American citizens or Japanese Americans after the war.
[[File:Hayward, California. Friends say good-bye as family of Japanese ancestry await evacuation bus. Bag . . . - NARA - 537514.jpg|thumb|200px|Friends say good-bye as family of Japanese ancestry await evacuation bus. Hayward, California, 8 May 1942]]
There were twenty-seven U.S. Department of Justice Camps, eight of which (in Texas, [[Idaho]], [[North Dakota]], [[New Mexico]], and [[Montana]]) held Japanese Americans. The camps were guarded by [[United States Border Patrol|Border Patrol]] agents rather than military police and were intended for non-citizens including [[Buddhist]] ministers, Japanese language instructors, newspaper workers, and other community leaders.

In addition 2,264 persons of Japanese ancestry&lt;ref name=niiya /&gt; taken from 12 Latin American countries by the U.S. State and Justice Departments were held at the Department of Justice Camps.&lt;ref&gt;Connel, Thomas. ''America's Japanese Hostages''. 2002, page 145-8&lt;/ref&gt; About two-thirds of these persons were Japanese Peruvians.&lt;ref name=niiya /&gt; There has been some speculation that the United States intended to use them in hostage exchanges with Japan,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nps.gov/manz/ccdoj.htm &quot;Department of Justice and U.S. Army Facilities&quot;], [[U.S. National Park Service]]. Retrieved August 31, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; a plot in part facilitated by local prejudice against Japanese communities in various South American countries.&lt;ref name=niiya /&gt; After the war, Peru refused to accept the return of the Japanese Peruvians they had acquiesced to interning in American camps; of this group, some were transferred to Japan, some were granted American citizenship, and a small minority of about 100 managed to achieve repatriation into Peru by asserting special circumstances, such as marriage to a non-Japanese Peruvian.&lt;ref name=niiya /&gt; Three hundred of the Japanese Peruvians who fought deportation in the courts were allowed to settle in the United States, and were granted American citizenship in 1953.&lt;ref name=niiya /&gt;
&lt;!-- Some of the preceding taken from http://www.nps.gov/manz/ccdoj.htm which is a US government source and public domain --&gt;

===WCCA Civilian Assembly Centers===
&lt;!--The following paragraph was copied from http://www.nps.gov/history/history/online_books/anthropology74/ce16.htm and is a place holder until better copy can be drafted.--&gt;Executive Order 9066 authorized the evacuation of all persons of Japanese ancestry from the West Coast; it was signed when there was no place for the Japanese Americans to go. When voluntary evacuation proved impractical, the military took over full responsibility for the evacuation; on April 9, 1942, the Wartime Civilian Control Agency (WCCA) was established by the military to coordinate the evacuation to inland relocation centers. The relocation centers were far from ready for large influxes of people. For some, there was still contention over the location, but for most, their placement in &quot;isolated&quot; undeveloped areas of the country exacerbated problems of building infrastructure and housing. Since the Japanese Americans living in the restricted zone were considered too dangerous to freely conduct their daily business, the military decided it was necessary to find temporary &quot;assembly centers&quot; to house the evacuees until the relocation centers were completed.&lt;ref&gt;''Confinement and Ethnicity: An Overview of World War II Japanese American Relocation Sites'', Jeffery F. Burton, Mary M. Farrell, Florence B. Lord, and Richard W. Lord, [http://www.nps.gov/history/history/online_books/anthropology74/ce16.htm Chapter 16], [http://www.nps.gov/ NPS]. Retrieved August 31, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;float:right; font-size:85%; margin-left:10px;&quot;
|+'''WRA Relocation Centers'''&lt;ref&gt;Confinement and Ethnicity: An Overview of World War II Japanese American Relocation Sites, Jeffery F. Burton, Mary M. Farrell, Florence B. Lord, and Richard W. Lord, [http://www.nps.gov/history/history/online_books/anthropology74/ce3g.htm Chapter 3], [http://www.nps.gov/ NPS]. Retrieved August 31, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
!Name
!State
!Opened
!Max. Pop'n
|- Ft missoula relocation center|missoula|Montana|?|?
|-
|[[Manzanar]]
|California
|March 1942
|10,046
|-
|[[Tule Lake War Relocation Center|Tule Lake]]
|California
|May 1942
|18,789
|-
|[[Poston War Relocation Center|Poston]]
|Arizona
|May 1942
|17,814
|-
|[[Gila River War Relocation Center|Gila River]]
|Arizona
|July 1942
|13,348
|-
|[[Granada War Relocation Center|Granada]]
|Colorado
|August 1942
|7,318
|-
|[[Heart Mountain War Relocation Center|Heart Mountain]]
| Wyoming
|August 1942
|10,767
|-
|[[Minidoka War Relocation Center|Minidoka]]
|Idaho
|August 1942
|9,397
|-
|[[Topaz War Relocation Center|Topaz]]
| Utah
|September 1942
|8,130
|-
|[[Rohwer War Relocation Center|Rohwer]]
|Arkansas
|September 1942
|8,475
|-
|[[Jerome War Relocation Center|Jerome]]
|Arkansas
|October 1942
|8,497
|}

===WRA Relocation Centers===
The [[War Relocation Authority]] (WRA) was the U.S. civilian agency responsible for the relocation and detention. The WRA was created by President Roosevelt on March 18, 1942 with [[Executive Order 9102]] and officially ceased to exist June 30, 1946. [[Milton S. Eisenhower]], then an official of the Department of Agriculture, was chosen to head the WRA. Dillon S. Myer replaced Milton Eisenhower on June 17, 1942, three months after Milton took control. Myer served as Director of the WRA until the centers were closed.&lt;ref&gt;''Japanese Americans From Relocation to Redress.'' Daniels, Roger, Sandra Taylor, Harry Kitano. Seattle Washington. University of Washington Press, 1991.&lt;/ref&gt; Within nine months, the WRA had opened ten facilities in seven states, and transferred over 100,000 people from the WCCA facilities.

The WRA camp at [[Tule Lake War Relocation Center|Tule Lake]], though initially like the other camps, eventually became a detention center for people believed to pose a security risk. Tule Lake also served as a &quot;segregation center&quot; for individuals and families who were deemed &quot;disloyal&quot; and for those who were to be deported to Japan.

===List of camps===
There were three types of camps. ''Civilian Assembly Centers'' were temporary camps, frequently located at horse tracks, where the Nisei were sent as they were removed from their communities. Eventually, most were sent to ''Relocation Centers,'' also known as ''internment camps.'' ''Detention camps'' housed Nikkei considered to be disruptive or of special interest to the government.

====Civilian Assembly Centers====
*[[Arcadia, California]] ([[Santa Anita Racetrack]], stables)
*[[Fresno, California]] ([[Big Fresno Fairgrounds]], racetrack, stables)
*[[Marysville, California|Marysville]] / [[Arboga, California]] (migrant workers' camp)
*[[Mayer, Arizona]] ([[Civilian Conservation Corps]] camp)
*[[Merced, California]] (county fairgrounds)[[File:Eleanor Roosevelt at Gila River, Arizona at Japanese,American Internment Center - NARA - 197094.jpg|thumb|[[Eleanor Roosevelt]] at the Gila River Relocation Center, April 23, 1943]]
*[[Owens Valley, California]]
*[[Parker Dam, Arizona]]
*[[Pinedale, California]] ([[Pinedale, California|Pinedale Assembly Center]], warehouses)
*[[Pomona, California]] ([[Fairplex|Los Angeles County Fairgrounds]], racetrack, stables)
*[[Portland, Oregon]] ([[Portland Metropolitan Exposition Center|Pacific International Livestock Exposition]], including 3,800 housed in the main pavilion building)
*[[Puyallup, Washington]] (fairgrounds racetrack stables, Informally known as &quot;[[Camp Harmony]]&quot;)
*[[Sacramento, California]] / (Site of Present-Day Walerga Park) (migrant workers' camp)
*[[Salinas, California]] ([[California Rodeo Salinas|fairgrounds]], racetrack, stables)
*[[San Bruno, California]] ([[Tanforan]] racetrack, stables)
*[[Stockton, California]] (San Joaquin County Fairgrounds, racetrack, stables)
*[[Tulare, California]] (fairgrounds, racetrack, stables)
*[[Turlock, California]] (Stanislaus County Fairgrounds)
*[[Woodland, California]]
[[File:Heart Mountain Relocation Center, Heart Mountain, Wyoming. Residents of Japanese ancestry, at the H . . . - NARA - 539235.jpg|thumb|Heart Mountain Relocation Center, January 10, 1943]]
====Relocation Centers====
*[[Gila River War Relocation Center]], Arizona
*[[Granada War Relocation Center]], Colorado (AKA &quot;Amache&quot;)
*[[Heart Mountain War Relocation Center]], Wyoming
*[[Jerome War Relocation Center]], Arkansas
*[[Manzanar War Relocation Center]], California
*[[Minidoka War Relocation Center]], Idaho
*[[Poston War Relocation Center]], Arizona
*[[Rohwer War Relocation Center]], Arkansas
*[[Topaz War Relocation Center]], Utah
*[[Tule Lake War Relocation Center]], California

====Justice Department detention camps====
These camps often held German and Italian detainees in addition to Japanese Americans:&lt;ref name=&quot;fulllist&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=Japanese American Internment Camps | url=http://www.bookmice.net/darkchilde/japan/camp.html | accessdate=October 2, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Crystal City, Texas]]&lt;ref name=texasarchive&gt;{{cite web|title=Alien Enemy Detention Facility, Crystal City, Texas|url=http://www.texasarchive.org/library/index.php?title=Alien_Enemy_Detention_Facility%2C_Crystal_City%2C_Texas&amp;gsearch=alien%20enemy|work=[[The Texas Archive of the Moving Image]]|accessdate=August 5, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Fort Lincoln Internment Camp]]
*[[Fort Missoula Internment Camp|Fort Missoula]], [[Montana]]
*[[Fort Stanton, New Mexico]][[File:Tule Lake Relocation Center, Newell, California. Harvesting spinach. - NARA - 538316.jpg|thumb|Harvesting spinach. Tule Lake Relocation Center, September 8, 1942]]
*[[Kenedy, Texas]]
*[[Kooskia, Idaho]]
*[[Santa Fe, New Mexico]]
*[[Seagoville, Texas]]

====Citizen Isolation Centers====
The Citizen Isolation Centers were for those considered to be problem inmates.&lt;ref name=&quot;fulllist&quot;/&gt;
*[[Leupp, Arizona]]
*[[Moab, Utah]] (AKA Dalton Wells)
*[[Fort Stanton, New Mexico]] (AKA Old Raton Ranch)

====Federal Bureau of Prisons====
Detainees convicted of crimes, usually draft resistance, were sent to these camps:&lt;ref name=&quot;fulllist&quot;/&gt;
*[[Catalina, Arizona]]
*[[Fort Leavenworth, Kansas]]
*[[McNeill Island, Washington]]

====US Army facilities====
These camps often held German and Italian detainees in addition to Japanese Americans:&lt;ref name=&quot;fulllist&quot;/&gt;
*[[Angel Island, California]]/[[Angel Island (California)#History|Fort McDowell]]
*[[Camp Blanding, Florida]]
*[[Camp Forrest]]
*[[Camp Livingston]], Louisiana
*[[Camp Lordsburg, New Mexico]]
*[[Camp McCoy, Wisconsin]]
*[[Florence, Arizona]]
*[[Fort Bliss]]
*[[Fort Howard (Maryland)|Fort Howard]]
*[[Fort Lewis]]
*[[Fort Meade, Maryland]]
*[[Fort Richardson]]
*[[Fort Sam Houston]]
*[[Fort Sill, Oklahoma]]
*[[Griffith Park]]
*[[Honolulu, Hawaii]]
*[[Sand Island, Hawaii]]
*[[Stringtown, Oklahoma]]

==Exclusion, removal, and detention==
[[File:Byron, California. Field laborers of Japanese ancestry in front of Wartime Civil Control Administra . . . - NARA - 537774.tif|thumb|left|Field laborers of Japanese ancestry stand in front of a Wartime Civil Control Administration site, where they are seeking instruction in regards to their &quot;evacuation&quot;.]]

Somewhere between 110,000 and 120,000 people of Japanese ancestry were subject to this mass exclusion program, of whom about two-thirds were U.S. citizens.&lt;ref name=howmany/&gt; The remaining one-third were non-citizens subject to internment under the [[Alien Enemies Act]]; many of these &quot;resident aliens&quot; had long been inhabitants of the United States, but had been deprived the opportunity to attain citizenship by laws that blocked Asian-born nationals from ever achieving citizenship.

Internees of Japanese descent were first sent to one of 17 temporary &quot;Civilian Assembly Centers,&quot; where most awaited transfer to more permanent relocation centers being constructed by the newly formed [[War Relocation Authority]] (WRA). Some of those who did report to the civilian assembly centers were not sent to relocation centers, but were released under the condition that they remain outside the prohibited zone until the military orders were modified or lifted. Almost 120,000&lt;ref name=howmany/&gt; Japanese Americans and resident Japanese aliens would eventually be removed from their homes in California, the western halves of [[Oregon]] and [[Washington (U.S. state)|Washington]] and southern [[Arizona]] as part of the single largest forced relocation in [[History of the United States|U.S. history]].

Most of these camps/residences, gardens, and stock areas were placed on Native American reservations, for which the Native Americans were formally compensated. The Native American councils disputed the amounts negotiated in absentia by US government authorities and later sued finding relief and additional compensation for some items of dispute.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
 |title=Docket No. 236-A, 236-B, Gila River Indian Community v. The United States of America
 |url=http://digital.library.okstate.edu/icc/v25/iccv25p250.pdf
 |date=April 28, 1971
 |work=Indian Claims Commission Decisions
 |volume=25
 |page=250}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Under the National Student Council Relocation Program (supported primarily by the [[American Friends Service Committee]]), students of college age were permitted to leave the camps to attend institutions willing to accept students of Japanese ancestry. Although the program initially granted leave permits to only a very small number of students, this eventually grew to 2,263 students by December 31, 1943.&lt;ref&gt;Source: War Relocation Authority annual reports&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Luggage - Japanese American internment.jpg|thumb|right|The baggage of Japanese Americans from the west coast, at a makeshift reception center located at a racetrack.]]
[[File:A young evacuee of Japanese ancestry waits with the family baggage before leaving by bus for an assembly center... - NARA - 539959.tif|thumb|An evacuee with family belongings en route to an &quot;assembly center&quot;, Spring 1942]]

===Curfew and exclusion===
&lt;!-- This section should address the initial stages, including the curfew imposed after the military areas were defined; the exclusion zone definitions, and the steps toward removal. The voluntary resettlement policy and its response should be discussed here. --&gt;
The exclusion from Military Area No. 1 initially occurred through a voluntary relocation policy. Under the voluntary relocation policy, the Japanese Americans were free to go anywhere outside of the exclusion zone; the arrangements and costs of relocation were borne by the individuals. The night-time curfew, initiated on March 27, 1942, was the first mass-action restricting the Japanese Americans.{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}

===Conditions in the camps===
According to a 1943 [[War Relocation Authority]] report, internees were housed in &quot;tar paper-covered barracks of simple frame construction without plumbing or cooking facilities of any kind.&quot; The spartan facilities met international laws, but still left much to be desired. Many camps were built quickly by civilian contractors during the summer of 1942 based on designs for military barracks, making the buildings poorly equipped for cramped family living.
[[File:&quot;Persons of Japanese ancestry arrive at the Santa Anita Assembly Center from San Pedro. Evacuees lived at this center at - NARA - 539960.tif|thumb|Dust storm at [[Manzanar]] War Relocation Center.]]
[[Image:Ansel Adams, Baseball game at Manzanar, 1943.jpg|thumb|A baseball game at Manzanar. Picture by [[Ansel Adams]] c. 1943.]]

To describe the conditions in more detail, the [[Heart Mountain War Relocation Center]] in northwestern [[Wyoming]] was a barbed-wire-surrounded enclave with unpartitioned toilets, cots for beds, and a budget of 45 cents daily per capita for food rations.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
 |url=http://www.trumanlibrary.org/whistlestop/study_collections/japanese_internment/documents/index.php?documentdate=1943-03-00&amp;documentid=16&amp;studycollectionid=JI&amp;pagenumber=1
 |title=Work of the War Relocation Authority, An Anniversary Statement
 |first=Dillon S.
 |last=Myer
 |date=March 1943
 |publisher=The Harry S. Truman Library &amp; Museum
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because most internees were evacuated from their West Coast homes on short notice and not told of their assigned destinations, many failed to pack appropriate clothing for Wyoming winters which often reached temperatures below zero Fahrenheit. Many families were forced to simply take the &quot;clothes on their backs.&quot;{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}

Armed guards were posted at the camps, which were all in remote, desolate areas far from population centers. Internees were typically allowed to stay with their families, and were treated well unless they violated the rules. There are documented instances of guards shooting internees who reportedly attempted to walk outside the fences. One such shooting, that of James Wakasa at Topaz, led to a re-evaluation of the security measures in the camps. Some camp administrations eventually allowed relatively free movement outside the marked boundaries of the camps. Nearly a quarter of the internees left the camps to live and work elsewhere in the United States, outside the exclusion zone. Eventually, some were authorized to return to their hometowns in the exclusion zone under supervision of a sponsoring American family or agency whose loyalty had been assured.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
 |title=Wartime Internment
 |first= Mikiso
 |last=Hane
 |date=September 1990
 |publisher=Organizer of American Historians}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The phrase &quot;[[shikata ga nai]]&quot; (loosely translated as &quot;it cannot be helped&quot;) was commonly used to summarize the interned families' resignation to their helplessness throughout these conditions. This was even noticed by the children, as mentioned in the well-known memoir ''[[Farewell to Manzanar]].''

===Loyalty questions and segregation===
Some Japanese Americans did question the American government, after finding themselves in internment camps. Several pro-Japan groups formed inside the camps, particularly at the Tule Lake location.&lt;ref name=tulelake&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tulelake.org/2004-pilgrimage/ |title=Tule Lake Committee - tulelake.org |publisher=tulelake.org |accessdate=January 24, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; When the government passed a law that made it possible for an internee to [[Renunciation of citizenship|renounce American citizenship]], 5,589 internees opted to do so; 5,461 of these were at Tule Lake.&lt;ref name=tulelake/&gt; Of those who renounced their citizenship, 1,327 were repatriated to Japan.&lt;ref name=tulelake/&gt; Many of these individuals would later face stigmatization in the Japanese-American community, after the war, for having made that choice, although even at the time they were not certain what their futures held were they to remain American, and remain interned.&lt;ref name=tulelake/&gt;

These renunciations of American citizenship have been highly controversial, for a number of reasons. Some apologists for internment have cited the renunciations as evidence that &quot;disloyalty&quot; or [[anti-Americanism]] was well represented among the interned peoples, thereby justifying the internment.&lt;ref&gt;Malkin, Michelle. ''In Defense of Internment''. 2004, pages 111.&lt;/ref&gt; Many historians have dismissed the latter argument, for its failure to consider that the small number of individuals in question were in the midst of persecution by their own government at the time of the &quot;renunciation&quot;:&lt;ref&gt;Ng, Wendy L. ''Japanese American Internment During World War II''. 2002, page 61&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=niiya293&gt;Niiya, Brian. ''Japanese American History''. 1993, page 293&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;[T]he renunciations had little to do with &quot;loyalty&quot; or &quot;disloyalty&quot; to the United States, but were instead the result of a series of complex conditions and factors that were beyond the control of those involved. Prior to discarding citizenship, most or all of the renunciants had experienced the following misfortunes: forced removal from homes; loss of jobs; government and public assumption of disloyalty to the land of their birth based on race alone; and incarceration in a &quot;segregation center&quot; for &quot;disloyal&quot; ISSEI or NISEI...&lt;ref name=niiya293 /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Minoru Kiyota, who was among those who renounced his citizenship and swiftly came to regret the decision, has stated that he wanted only &quot;to express my fury toward the government of the United States,&quot; for his internment and for the mental and physical duress, as well as the intimidation, he was made to face.&lt;ref name=ngai&gt;Ngai, Mae M. ''Impossible Subjects''. 2004, page 192&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;[M]y renunciation had been an expression of momentary emotional defiance in reaction to years of persecution suffered by myself and other Japanese Americans and, in particular, to the degrading interrogation by the FBI agent at [[Topaz War Relocation Center|Topaz]] and being terrorized by the guards and gangs at [[Tule Lake War Relocation Center|Tule Lake]].&lt;ref&gt;Kiyota, Minoru and Keenan, Linda Klepinger. ''Beyond Loyalty''. 1997, page 129&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Civil rights attorney [[Wayne M. Collins]] successfully challenged most of these renunciations as invalid, owing to the conditions of duress and intimidation under which the government obtained them.&lt;ref name=ngai /&gt;&lt;ref name=christgau&gt;{{cite journal | last = Christgau | first = John | title = Collins versus the World: The Fight to Restore Citizenship to Japanese American Renunciants of World War II | journal=Pacific Historical Review | volume = 54 | issue = 1 | pages = 1–31 | publisher=University of California Press | date = February 1985 | jstor=3638863}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many of the deportees were ''[[Issei]]'' (first generation Japanese immigrants) who often had difficulty with English and often did not understand the questions they were asked.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}} Even among those ''Issei'' who had a clear understanding, Question 28 posed an awkward dilemma: Japanese immigrants were denied US citizenship at the time, so when asked to renounce their Japanese citizenship, answering &quot;Yes&quot; would have made them [[Statelessness|stateless persons]].&lt;ref&gt;Yamamoto, Traise. ''Masking Selves, Making Subjects''. 1999, page 284&lt;/ref&gt;

When the government circulated a questionnaire seeking army volunteers from among the internees, 6% of military-aged male respondents volunteered to serve in the U.S. Armed Forces.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}} Most of those who refused tempered that refusal with statements of willingness to fight if they were restored their rights as American citizens. 20,000 Japanese American men and many Japanese American women served in the U.S. Army during World War II.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.javadc.org/AJA%20women_in_wwII.htm|title=Japanese American women in World World II}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:442nd US Army RCT squad leader in france.jpg|thumb|left|The [[442nd Infantry Regiment (United States)|442nd Regimental Combat Team]], which was composed primarily of [[Japanese American]]s, served with uncommon distinction in the [[European Theatre of World War II]]. Many of the US soldiers serving in the unit had their families interned at home while they fought abroad.]]
The famed [[442nd Infantry Regiment (United States)|442nd Regimental Combat Team]], which [[European Theatre of World War II|fought in Europe]], was formed from those Japanese Americans who did agree to serve. This unit was the most highly decorated US military unit of its size and duration.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www4.army.mil/ocpa/read.php?story_id_key=1813|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20071104172145/http://www4.army.mil/ocpa/read.php?story_id_key=1813|archivedate=November 4, 2007 |title=President Clinton Approves Medal of Honor for Asian Pacific American World War II Heroes |publisher=US Army |date=May 12, 2000 |accessdate=October 20, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most notably, the 442nd was known for saving the [[Lost Battalion (World War II)|141st (or the &quot;lost battalion&quot;)]] from the Germans. The 1951 film ''[[Go for Broke! (1951 film)|Go For Broke!]]'' was a fairly accurate portrayal of the 442nd, and starred several of the RCT's veterans.

===Other detention camps===
As early as 1939, when war broke out in Europe and while armed conflict began to rage in East Asia, the FBI and branches of the Department of Justice and the armed forces began to collect information and surveillance on influential members of the Japanese community in the United States. These data were included in the [[Custodial Detention index]] (CDI). Agents in the Department of Justice's Special Defense Unit classified the subjects into three groups: A, B and C, with A being &quot;most dangerous,&quot; and C being &quot;possibly dangerous.&quot;

After the Pearl Harbor attacks, Roosevelt authorized his attorney general to put into motion a plan for the arrest of individuals on the potential enemy alien lists. Armed with a blanket arrest warrant, the FBI seized these men on the eve of December 8, 1941. These men were held in municipal jails and prisons until they were moved to Department of Justice detention camps, separate from those of the Wartime Relocation Authority (WRA). These camps operated under far more stringent conditions and were subject to heightened criminal-style guard, despite the absence of criminal proceedings.

[[Crystal City, Texas]], was one such camp where Japanese Americans, German Americans, Italian Americans, and a large number of US-seized, Axis-descended nationals from several Latin-American countries were interned.&lt;ref name=jla/&gt;&lt;ref name=texasarchive /&gt;

[[Japanese Canadian|Canadian citizens with Japanese ancestry]] were also interned by the Canadian government during World War II (see [[Japanese Canadian internment]]). Japanese people from various parts of Latin America, including Peru, were brought to the United States for internment or interned in their countries of residence,&lt;ref name=jla/&gt; and there were [[Japanese Brazilian#Prejudice and forced assimilation|varied restrictions]] placed on [[Japanese Brazilian]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;[[Agence France-Presse]]/[[Jiji Press]], &quot;Peru sorry for WWII internments&quot;, ''[[Japan Times]]'', June 16, 2011, p. 2.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hawaii===
Although there was a strong push from mainland Congressmen (Hawaii was only a US territory at the time, and did not have a voting representative or senator in Congress) to remove and intern all [[Japanese Americans]] and Japanese immigrants in Hawaii, it never happened. 1,200 to 1,800 Japanese nationals and Japanese Americans from Hawaii were interned, either in five camps on the islands or in one of the mainland internment camps.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hawaii.gov/dlnr/reports-to-the-legislature/2008/2008/shpd/HP08-Japanese-Internment-Camp%20-Act163SLH07.pdf |title=Japanese Internment Camps In Hawaii |format=PDF |accessdate=December 5, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The vast majority of Japanese Americans and their immigrant parents in Hawaii were not interned because the government had already declared [[martial law]] in Hawaii and this allowed it to significantly reduce the supposed risk of espionage and sabotage by residents of Japanese ancestry. Also, Japanese Americans comprised over 35% of the territory's population, with about 150,000 inhabitants; detaining so many people would have been enormously challenging in terms of logistics. Also, the whole of Hawaiian society was dependent on their productivity. Lieutenant General [[Delos C. Emmons]], commander of the Hawaii Department, promised the local Japanese-American community that they would be treated fairly so long as they remained loyal to the United States, and he succeeded in blocking efforts to relocate them to the outer islands or mainland by pointing out the logistical difficulties.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Guarding the United States and Its Outposts|url=http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/USA/USA-WH-Guard/USA-WH-Guard-8.html|work=United States Army in Word War II|publisher=United States Army Center of Military History|accessdate=November 7, 2011|author=Stetson Conn|coauthors=Rose C. Engelman and Byron Fairchild|month=May|year=1961}}&lt;/ref&gt; Among the small number interned were a number of community leaders and prominent politicians, including territorial legislators [[Thomas Sakakihara]] and [[Sanji Abe]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://the.honoluluadvertiser.com/article/2001/Sep/16/op/op06a.html|periodical=The Honolulu Advertiser|last=Dye|first=Bob|date=September 16, 2001|accessdate=December 23, 2009|title=How bigots 'cleansed' Legislature in 1942}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There were five internment camps in Hawaii, referred to as &quot;Hawaiian Island Detention Camps&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;HA20051127&quot;/&gt; One camp was located at [[Sand Island (Hawaii)|Sand Island]] at the mouth of [[Honolulu]] Harbor. This camp was prepared in advance of the war's outbreak. All prisoners held here were &quot;detained under military custody... because of the imposition of martial law throughout the Islands&quot;. Another Hawaiian camp was the [[Honouliuli Internment Camp]], near Ewa, on the southwestern shore of Oahu; it was opened in 1943 to replace the Sand Island camp. One was also located on the island of [[Maui]] in the town of [[Haiku-Pauwela, Hawaii|Haiku]].&lt;ref name=&quot;MT8207&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.mauitime.com/Articles-i-2007-08-02-174168.112113-The-Camp.html|periodical=Maui time|title=The Camp|last=Greg Mebel|first=Anthony Pignataro|date=August 20, 2007|accessdate=April 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In total, five internment camps operated in Hawaii.&lt;ref name=&quot;HA20051127&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://the.honoluluadvertiser.com/article/2005/Nov/27/ln/FP511270347.html|periodical=The Honolulu Advertiser|title=Wartime stain in history retraced in O'ahu's brush|last=Gordon|first=Mike|date=November 27, 2005|accessdate=December 10, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;HA20060205&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://the.honoluluadvertiser.com/article/2006/Feb/05/ln/FP602050354.html|periodical=The Honolulu Advertiser|date=February 5, 2006|accessdate=December 10, 2009|last=Gordon|first=Mike|title=Under Honouliuli brush, dark history}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Internment ends===
On December 18, 1944, the [[Supreme Court of the United States]] clarified the legality of the exclusion process under Order 9066 by handing down two decisions. ''[[Korematsu v. United States]]'', a 6–3 decision, stated that the exclusion process in general was constitutional. ''[[Ex parte Endo]]'' unanimously declared that loyal citizens of the United States, regardless of cultural descent, could not be detained without cause.

On January 2, 1945, the exclusion order was rescinded entirely. The internees then began to leave the camps to rebuild their lives at home, although the relocation camps remained open for residents who were not ready to make the move back. The freed internees were given $25 and a train ticket to their former homes. While the majority returned to their former lives, some of the Japanese Americans emigrated to Japan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pbs.org/opb/historydetectives/investigations/202_tulelakefeature.html|title=PBS Investigations of the Tule Lake Camp. Retrieved August&amp;nbsp;24, 2007.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The last internment camp was not closed until 1946;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Japanese Americans Internment Camps During World War II,&quot; [http://web.archive.org/web/20070619073757/http://www.lib.utah.edu/spc/photo/9066/9066.htm Library web page at Utah.edu]. Retrieved October 1, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Japanese taken by the U.S. from Peru that were still being held in the camp in Santa Fe took legal action in April 1946 in an attempt to avoid deportation to Japan.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
 |first=Thomas
 |last=Connell
 |title=America's Japanese Hostages: The World War II Plan for a Japanese Free Latin America
 |publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group
 |year=2002
 |isbn=0-275-97535-5
 |page=223}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One of the WRA camps, [[Manzanar Japanese internment camp|Manzanar]], was designated a [[National Historic Sites (United States)|National Historic Site]] in 1992 to &quot;provide for the protection and interpretation of historic, cultural, and natural resources associated with the relocation of Japanese Americans during World War II&quot; (Public Law 102-248). In 2001, the site of the Minidoka War Relocation Center in Idaho was designated the [[Minidoka National Historic Site]].

==Hardship and material loss==
[[File:Granada Relocation Center, Amache, Colorado. Not all the center residents will return to their form . . . - NARA - 539932.tif|thumb|Graveyard at Granada Relocation Center, in Amache, Colorado.]]
[[Image:Manzanar shrine.jpg|thumb|A monument at Manzanar, &quot;to console the souls of the dead.&quot;]]
Many internees lost irreplaceable personal property due to the restrictions on what could be taken into the camps. These losses were compounded by theft and destruction of items placed in governmental storage. A number of persons died or suffered for lack of medical care, and several were killed by sentries; James Wakasa, for instance, was killed at [[Topaz War Relocation Center]], near the perimeter wire. [[Japanese diaspora|Nikkei]] were prohibited from leaving the Military Zones during the last few weeks before internment, and only able to leave the camps by permission of the camp administrators.

Psychological injury was observed by Dillon S. Myer, director of the WRA camps. In June 1945, Myer described how the Japanese Americans had grown increasingly depressed, and overcome with feelings of helplessness and personal insecurity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Myer&quot;&gt;''The WRA says Thirty,'' New Republic 112, pp. 867–68.&lt;/ref&gt; Author Betty Furuta insists that the Japanese used [[Gaman (term)|gaman]], loosely meaning &quot;perseverance&quot;, to overcome hardships which was mistaken by non-Japanese as being introverted and lacking initiative.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Niiya|first=Brian|url=http://books.google.com/?id=QZg6Ft_jvJ0C&amp;pg=PA143&amp;dq=gaman+japan#v=onepage&amp;q=gaman%20japan&amp;f=false|title=Japanese American history : an A-to-Z reference from 1868 to the present|year=1993|publisher=Facts On File|location=New York, NY|isbn=0-8160-2680-7|page=143}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some Japanese-American farmers were able to find families willing to tend their farms for the duration of their internment. In other cases Japanese-American farmers had to sell their property in a matter of days, usually at great financial loss. In these cases, the land speculators who bought the land made huge profits. California's [[California Alien Land Law of 1913|Alien Land Laws]] of the 1910s, which prohibited most non-citizens from owning property in that state, contributed to Japanese-American property losses. Because they were barred from owning land, many older Japanese-American farmers were [[tenant farmer]]s and therefore lost their rights to those farm lands.

To compensate former internees for their property losses, the [[US Congress]], on July 2, 1948, passed the &quot;American Japanese Claims Act,&quot; allowing Japanese Americans to apply for compensation for property losses which occurred as &quot;a reasonable and natural consequence of the evacuation or exclusion.&quot; By the time the Act was passed, the [[Internal Revenue Service|IRS]] had already destroyed most of the 1939–42 tax records of the internees, and, due to the time pressure and the strict limits on how much they could take to the assembly centers and then the internment camps, few of the internees themselves had been able to preserve detailed tax and financial records during the evacuation process. Thus, it was extremely difficult for claimants to establish that their claims were valid. Under the Act, Japanese-American families filed 26,568 claims totaling $148&amp;nbsp;million in requests; about $37&amp;nbsp;million was approved and disbursed.&lt;ref&gt;Commission on Wartime Relocation and Internment, ''[http://www.nps.gov/history/history/online_books/personal_justice_denied/chap4.htm Personal Justice Denied]'', Chapter 4&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reparations and redress==
{{See also|Japanese American redress and court cases}}

During World War II, [[Colorado]] governor [[Ralph Lawrence Carr]] was the only elected official to publicly apologize for the internment of American citizens. The act cost him reelection, but gained him the gratitude of the Japanese American community, such that a statue of him was erected in Sakura Square in Denver's Japantown.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.coloradohistory.org/RIPsigns/show_markertext.asp?id=811 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20061002001303/http://www.coloradohistory.org/RIPsigns/show_markertext.asp?id=811 |archivedate=October 2, 2006 |title=The Colorado History Organization |publisher=Web.archive.org |accessdate=January 24, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Largely through the efforts of college President William Dennis, [[Earlham College]] instituted a program beginning in 1942 that enrolled several dozen Japanese-American students, in order to spare them from internment. While this action was controversial in [[Richmond, IN|Richmond, Indiana]], it helped strengthen the college's ties to Japan and the Japanese-American community.&lt;ref&gt;http://legacy.earlham.edu/~jpnstudies/documents/pdf/historical_brochure.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

Beginning in the 1960s, a younger generation of Japanese Americans who were inspired by the [[Civil Rights movement]] began what is known as the &quot;Redress Movement,&quot; an effort to obtain an official apology and reparations from the federal government for interning their parents and grandparents during the war, focusing not on documented property losses but on the broader injustice of the internment. The movement's first success was in 1976, when President [[Gerald Ford]] proclaimed that the internment was &quot;wrong,&quot; and a &quot;national mistake&quot; which &quot;shall never again be repeated&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Stone, Geoffrey R. ''Perilous Times''. 2004, page 305&lt;/ref&gt;

The campaign for redress was launched by Japanese Americans in 1978. The [[Japanese American Citizens League]] (JACL) asked for three measures to be taken as redress: $25,000 to be awarded to each person who was detained, an apology from Congress acknowledging publicly that the U.S. government had been wrong, and the release of funds to set up an educational foundation for the children of Japanese American families.

In 1980, Congress established the [[Commission on Wartime Relocation and Internment of Civilians]] (CWRIC) to study the matter. On February 24, 1983, the commission issued a report entitled ''Personal Justice Denied'', condemning the internment as &quot;unjust and motivated by racism rather than real military necessity&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nps.gov/history/history/online_books/personal_justice_denied/intro.htm |title=Personal Justice Denied, www.nps.gov |publisher=Nps.gov |date=January 8, 2007 |accessdate=January 24, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Commission recommended that $20,000 in reparations be paid to those Japanese Americans who had been victims of internment.

[[File:Ronald Reagan signing Japanese reparations bill.jpg|thumb|left|U.S. President Ronald Reagan signs the [[Civil Liberties Act of 1988]], which granted reparations for the internment of Japanese Americans.]]
In 1988, U.S. President [[Ronald Reagan]] signed the [[Civil Liberties Act of 1988]], which had been sponsored by Representative [[Norman Mineta]] and Senator [[Alan K. Simpson]] – the two had met while Mineta was interned at a camp in [[Wyoming]] – which provided redress of $20,000 for each surviving detainee, totaling $1.2&amp;nbsp;billion dollars. The question of to whom reparations should be given, how much, and even whether monetary reparations were appropriate were subjects of sometimes contentious debate.&lt;ref&gt;Hatamiya, Leslie T. ''Righting a Wrong''. 1994, page 108-9&lt;/ref&gt;

On September 27, 1992, the Civil Liberties Act Amendments of 1992, appropriating an additional $400&amp;nbsp;million to ensure all remaining internees received their $20,000 redress payments, was signed into law by President [[George H. W. Bush]], who also issued another formal apology from the U.S. government on December 7, 1991, on the very day of the 50th-Anniversary of the [[Attack on Pearl Harbor|Pearl Harbor Attack]]:
&lt;blockquote&gt;''&quot;In remembering, it is important to come to grips with the past. No nation can fully understand itself or find its place in the world if it does not look with clear eyes at all the glories and disgraces of its past. We in the United States acknowledge such an injustice in our history. The internment of Americans of Japanese ancestry was a great injustice, and it will never be repeated.&quot;''&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Some Japanese and Japanese Americans who were relocated during World War II received compensation for property losses, according to a 1948 law. Congress appropriated $38&amp;nbsp;million to meet $131&amp;nbsp;million of claims from among 23,000 claimants.&lt;ref name=dans&gt;Daniels, Roger. ''Prisoners Without Trial''. 2004, page 89&lt;/ref&gt; These payments were disbursed very slowly, the final disbursal occurring in 1965.&lt;ref name=dans /&gt; In 1988, following lobbying efforts by Japanese Americans, $20,000 per internee was paid out to individuals who had been interned or relocated, including those who chose to return to Japan. These payments were awarded to 82,210 Japanese Americans or their heirs at a cost of $1.6&amp;nbsp;billion; the program's final disbursement occurred in 1999.&lt;ref name=&quot;democracynow&quot;/&gt;

Under the 2001 budget of the United States, it was also decreed that the ten sites on which the detainee camps were set up are to be preserved as historical landmarks: “places like Manzanar, Tule Lake, Heart Mountain, Topaz, Amache, Jerome, and Rohwer will forever stand as reminders that this nation failed in its most sacred duty to protect its citizens against prejudice, greed, and political expediency”.&lt;ref&gt;Tateishi and Yoshino 2000&lt;/ref&gt;

On January 30, 2011, California first observed an annual &quot;[[Fred Korematsu]] Day of Civil Liberties and the Constitution&quot;, the first such commemoration for an [[Asian American]] in the U.S.&lt;ref name=&quot;ti&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.time.com/time/nation/article/0,8599,2045111,00.html|title=California Marks the First Fred Korematsu Day|last=Liu|first=Ling Woo|date=January 29, 2011|work=TIME|accessdate=January 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  On June 14, 2011, Peruvian president [[Alan García]] apologized for his country's internment of Japanese immigrants during World War II, most of whom were transferred to the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

==Legal legacy==
[[File:Manzanar Relocation Center, Manzanar, California. Grandfather and grandson of Japanese ancestry at . . . - NARA - 537992.tif|thumb|Grandfather and grandson at Manzanar, July 2, 1942.]]

Several significant legal decisions arose out of Japanese-American internment, relating to the powers of the government to detain citizens in wartime. Among the cases which reached the Supreme Court were ''[[Yasui v. United States]]'' (1943), ''[[Hirabayashi v. United States]]'' (1943), ''[[ex parte Endo]]'' (1944), and ''[[Korematsu v. United States]]'' (1944). In ''Yasui'' and ''Hirabayashi'' the court upheld the constitutionality of curfews based on Japanese ancestry; in ''Korematsu'' the court upheld the constitutionality of the exclusion order. In ''Endo'', the court accepted a petition for a [[writ of habeas corpus]] and ruled that the WRA had no authority to subject a citizen whose loyalty was acknowledged to its procedures.

Korematsu's and Hirabayashi's convictions were vacated in a series of ''[[coram nobis]]'' cases in the early 1980s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Irons&quot;&gt;{{cite book | author=Irons, Peter. | title=Justice At War: The Story of the Japanese American Internment Cases | publisher=University of Washington Press | year=1976, 1996 | isbn=0-520-08312-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the ''coram nobis'' cases, federal district and appellate courts ruled that newly uncovered evidence revealed an unfairness which, had it been known at the time, would likely have changed the [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court's]] decisions in the Yasui, Hirabayashi, and Korematsu cases.&lt;ref name=korematsu_majority/&gt;&lt;ref name=hirabayashi/&gt; These new court decisions rested on a series of documents recovered from the [[National Archives and Records Administration|National Archives]] showing that the government had altered, suppressed and withheld important and relevant information from the Supreme Court, including the Final Report by General DeWitt justifying the internment program.&lt;ref name=&quot;Irons&quot;/&gt; The Army had destroyed documents in an effort to hide the fact that alterations had been made to the report.&lt;ref name=hirabayashi/&gt; The ''coram nobis'' cases vacated the convictions of Korematsu and Hirabayashi (Yasui died before his case was heard, rendering it moot), and are regarded as one of the impetuses for the [[Civil Liberties Act of 1988]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Irons&quot;/&gt;

The rulings of the US Supreme Court in the Korematsu and Hirabayashi cases, specifically in its expansive interpretation of government powers in wartime, have yet to be overturned. They are still the law of the land because a lower court cannot overturn a ruling by the US Supreme Court. The ''coram nobis'' cases totally undermined the ''factual'' underpinnings of the 1944 cases, leaving the original decisions without much logical basis.&lt;ref name=&quot;Irons&quot;/&gt; Nonetheless, in light of the fact that these 1944 decisions are still on the books, a number of legal scholars have expressed the opinion that the original Korematsu and Hirabayashi decisions have taken on renewed relevance in the context of the [[War on Terror]].

Former [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]] Justice [[Tom C. Clark]], who represented the US Department of Justice in the &quot;relocation,&quot; writes in the epilogue to the 1992 book ''Executive Order 9066: The Internment of 110,000 Japanese Americans'':&lt;ref&gt;Conrat, Maisie and Conrat, Richard. ''Executive Order 9066: The Internment of 110,000 Japanese Americans''.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quotation|
The truth is—as this deplorable experience proves—that constitutions and laws are not sufficient of themselves...Despite the unequivocal language of the [[United States Constitution|Constitution of the United States]] that the [[writ of habeas corpus]] shall not be suspended, and despite the Fifth Amendment's command that no person shall be deprived of life, liberty or property without due process of law, both of these constitutional safeguards were denied by military action under Executive Order 9066.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://asianamericanbooks.com/books/1990.htm |title=Asian American Books.com, quote from back cover |publisher=Asianamericanbooks.com |accessdate=January&amp;nbsp;24,&amp;nbsp;2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==Terminology debate==
There has been much discussion over what to call the locations in which internees were held.&lt;ref name=&quot;ManzanarControversy&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=The Manzanar Controversy | url=http://www.pbs.org/weekendexplorer/california/mammoth/manzanar.htm |date = not available | accessdate=July 18, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; The WRA officially called them &quot;War Relocation Centers.&quot; Manzanar, for instance, was officially known as the Manzanar War Relocation Center. Because of this, the National Park Service has chosen to use &quot;relocation center&quot; in referring to the camps.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reflectionsiii-iv&quot;&gt;{{cite book | author=Manzanar Committee | title=Reflections: Three Self-Guided Tours Of Manzanar | year = 1998 | publisher=Manzanar Committee | pages = iii–iv | nopp=true}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some historians and scholars, as well as former internees, object to this wording, noting that the internees were literally imprisoned, such that &quot;relocation&quot; becomes a euphemism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reflectionsiii-iv&quot;/&gt;

Another widely used name for the American camps is &quot;internment camp&quot;. This phrase is also potentially misleading, as the [[United States Department of Justice]] operated separate camps that were officially called &quot;internment camps&quot; in which some Japanese Americans were imprisoned during World War II.&lt;ref name=&quot;Weglyn&quot;&gt;{{cite book | author=Weglyn, Michi | title=Years Of Infamy: The Untold Story Of America's Concentration Camps | publisher=University of Washington Press | year=1976, 1996 | isbn=0-295-97484-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CAE17&quot;&gt;{{cite book | author=Jeffery F. Burton, Mary M. Farrell, Florence B. Lord, Richard W. Lord | title=Confinement and Ethnicity: An Overview of World War II Japanese American Relocation Sites | publisher=Western Archaeological and Conservation Center, National Park Service, US Department of the Interior | year=1999 | id=Publications in Anthropology 74 |pages = 379–406}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;Concentration camp&quot; is the most controversial descriptor of the camps. This term is criticized for suggesting that the Japanese American experience was analogous to the [[Holocaust]] and the [[Nazi concentration camps]].&lt;ref name=&quot;InsideNazi-Glossary&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=Auschwitz: Inside the Nazi State: Glossary | url=http://www.pbs.org/auschwitz/learning/glossary/
 | date=2004-2005 | accessdate=July 18, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; For this reason, [[National Park Service]] officials have attempted to avoid the term.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reflectionsiii-iv&quot;/&gt; [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]], [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]] and Secretary of the Interior [[Harold L. Ickes]] each referred to the American camps as &quot;concentration camps,&quot; at the time.&lt;ref name=&quot;SmithsonianIckes&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=Smithsonian Institution: A More Perfect Union: Japanese Americans &amp; the U.S. Constitution: Internment: Permanent Camps | url=http://americanhistory.si.edu/perfectunion/non-flash/internment_permanent.html | date=1990-2001 | accessdate=July 18, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; When the nature of the Nazi concentration camps became clear to the world, and the phrase &quot;concentration camp&quot; came to signify a Nazi death camp, most historians turned to other terms to describe Japanese internment.

Recognizing the controversy over the terminology, in 1971, when the [http://www.manzanarcommittee.org/ Manzanar Committee] applied to the [[California Department of Parks and Recreation]] to have Manzanar designated as a California State Historical Landmark, it was proposed that both &quot;relocation center&quot; and &quot;concentration camp&quot; be used in the wording of the plaque for the landmark.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reflectionsiv&quot;&gt;{{cite book | author=Manzanar Committee | title=Reflections: Three Self-Guided Tours Of Manzanar | pages = iv}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some Owens Valley residents vehemently opposed the use of &quot;concentration camp,&quot; and it took a year of discussion and negotiation before both terms were accepted and included on the plaque.&lt;ref name=&quot;ManzanarControversy&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Reflectionsiv&quot;/&gt;

==Notable internees==
*[[Richard Aoki]] (1938–2009), Black Panther Party, as a child at [[Topaz War Relocation Center|Topaz]]
*[[Violet Kazue de Cristoforo]] (1917–2007), poet ([[Tule Lake War Relocation Center|Tule Lake]] and [[Jerome War Relocation Center|Jerome]])
*[[Takayo Fischer]], actress ([[Jerome War Relocation Center|Jerome]] and [[Rohwer War Relocation Center|Rohwer]])
*[[Bill Hosokawa]] (1915–2007), journalist ([[Heart Mountain War Relocation Center|Heart Mountain]])
*[[Jeanne Wakatsuki Houston]], author (Manzanar)
*[[Lawson Fusao Inada]], poet (multiple camps)
*[[Robert Ito]], actor (Japanese-Canadian Internee)
*[[Hiroshi Kashiwagi]], actor, poet, playwright ([[Tule Lake War Relocation Center|Tule Lake]])
*[[Kenwood_Corporation#History_of_Kenwood_Corporation|Bill Kasuga]], co-founder of [[Kenwood Corporation]]
*[[Kichimatsu Kishi]] (?-1956), founder of an agricultural colony and a small oil company
*[[Yuri Kochiyama]], activist ([[Jerome War Relocation Center|Jerome]])
*[[Stand Up for Justice: The Ralph Lazo Story|Ralph Lazo]] (Manzanar)
*[[Bob Matsui]] (1941–2005), U.S. Congressman ([[Tule Lake War Relocation Center|Tule Lake]])
*[[Doris Matsui]] (1944– ), U.S. Congresswoman (born in [[Poston War Relocation Center|Poston]])
*[[Pat Morita]] (1932–2005), actor, comedian ([[Gila River]])
*[[Norman Mineta]] (1931– ), former Mayor of [[San Jose, California]], U.S. Congressman, Sec. of Commerce, Sec. of Transportation ([[Heart Mountain War Relocation Center|Heart Mountain]])
*[[Tōyō Miyatake]] (1896–1979), photographer (Manzanar)
*[[Robert A. Nakamura]] (1937– ), Filmmaker, Founder of [[Visual Communications (VC)]] (Manzanar)
*[[George Nakashima]] (1905–1990), woodworker, furniture designer, architect ([[Minidoka National Historic Site|Minidoka]])
*[[Arthur Okamura]] (1932–2009), screen print artist ([[Granada War Relocation Center|Granada]])
*[[Miné Okubo]] (1912–2001), artist, author ''Citizen 13660'' ([[Tanforan]] and [[Topaz War Relocation Center|Topaz]])
*[[Tura Satana]] (1938–2011), actress, burlesque star ([[Manzanar]])
*[[Yuki Shimoda]] (1921–1981), actor ([[Tule Lake War Relocation Center|Tule Lake]])
*[[Larry Shinoda]] (1930–1997), automotive designer
*[[Monica Sone]] (1919–2011) autobiographer (''Nisei Daughter'', 1953) ([[Camp Harmony]] and Minidoka)
*[[Jack Soo]] (1917–1979), actor, comedian ([[Topaz War Relocation Center|Topaz]])
*[[Pat Suzuki]], singer, actress, entertainer
*[[Shinkichi Tajiri]] (1923–2009), soldier, 442nd. [[Documenta]] artist, sculptor, photographer, lived in the Netherlands. With the family at [[Poston War Relocation Center|Poston]]. 
*[[Iwao Takamoto]] (1925–2007), animator, TV producer (Manzanar)
*[[George Takei]], (1937– ), actor ([[Rohwer War Relocation Center|Rohwer]] and [[Tule Lake War Relocation Center|Tule Lake]])
*[[A. Wallace Tashima]], Ninth Circuit judge ([[Poston War Relocation Center|Poston]])
*[[Dave Tatsuno]] (1913–2006), (Topaz), who filmed scenes of the camp with an illegal camera, later compiled as ''[[Topaz (1945 film)|Topaz]]'', and placed in the [[National Film Registry]]
*[[Yoshiko Uchida]] (1921–1992), author (&quot;Journey to Topaz&quot; for children and &quot;Desert Exile&quot; for adults) ([[Tanforan]] and [[Topaz War Relocation Center|Topaz]])
*[[Michi Weglyn|Michi Nishiura Weglyn]] (1926–1999), author of ''Years Of Infamy''
*[[Hisaye Yamamoto]] (1921–2011), author ([[Poston War Relocation Center|Poston]])
*[[Wakako Yamauchi]], author, playwright ([[Poston War Relocation Center|Poston]])

==Expulsions and population transfers of WWII==
{{Main|World War II evacuation and expulsion|Population transfers in the Soviet Union}}
The internment of Japanese Americans has sometimes been compared to the persecutions, expulsions, and dislocations of other ethnic minorities in the context of World War II, in Europe and Asia.&lt;ref name=ms /&gt;&lt;ref name=mr /&gt;&lt;ref name=mkr /&gt;&lt;ref name=mm /&gt; An estimated 500,000 [[Volga Germans]] were rounded up and deported to Siberia and Kazakhstan when Germany invaded the Soviet Union, with many of them dying en route.&lt;ref name=ms&gt;Maxim Shrayer (2007). &quot;''[http://books.google.com/books?id=TSXYMF3RNEYC&amp;pg=PA30&amp;dq&amp;hl=en#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Waiting for America: a story of emigration]''&quot;. Syracuse University Press. p.30. ISBN 0-8156-0893-4&lt;/ref&gt; The Volga Germans were deported prior to the [[Battle of Stalingrad]], as they were regarded, in the &quot;war hysteria of the moment&quot;, as a potential &quot;[[Fifth Column]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=mr&gt;Michael Rywkin (1994). &quot;''[http://books.google.com/books?id=dufZDXtYaV4C&amp;pg=PA66&amp;dq&amp;hl=en#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Moscow's lost empire]''&quot;. M.E. Sharpe. p.66. ISBN 1-56324-237-0.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1944, the Red Army rounded up about 500,000 [[Chechens]] and [[Ingushes]] for relocation; a third of this population perished in the first year, from starvation, cold, and disease.&lt;ref name=mkr&gt;Mohit Kumar Ray, Rama Kundu, Pradip Kumar Dey (2005). &quot;''[http://books.google.com/books?id=wIC9cdVrAnwC&amp;pg=PA150&amp;dq&amp;hl=en#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Widening horizons: essays in honour of Professor Mohit K. Ray]''&quot;. Sarup &amp; Sons. p.150. ISBN 81-7625-598-X&lt;/ref&gt; Other nationalities which faced ethnic cleansing for having been identified as potential collaborators with the Germans were the [[Balkars]], [[Crimean Tartars]], [[Karachays|Karachi]], [[Kalmyks]], and [[Meskheti]]ans.&lt;ref name=mm&gt;Michael Mann (2005). &quot;''[http://books.google.com/books?id=cGHGPgj1_tIC&amp;pg=PA328&amp;dq&amp;hl=en#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false The dark side of democracy: explaining ethnic cleansing]''&quot;. Cambridge University Press. p.328.
ISBN 0-521-53854-8&lt;/ref&gt;

==Exhibitions and Collections==
The [[Smithsonian Institution]]’s [[National Museum of American History]] has more than 800 artifacts from its A More Perfect Union collection available online. Archival photography, publications, original manuscripts, artworks, and handmade objects comprise the collection of items related to the [[Japanese American]] experience.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://americanhistory.si.edu/perfectunion/collection/index.html |title=A More Perfect Union Collection Search |publisher=National Museum of American History, Smithsonian Institution |accessdate=April 24, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On October 1, 1987, the [[Smithsonian Institution]] [[National Museum of American History]] opened an exhibition called, &quot;A More Perfect Union: [[Japanese Americans]] and the [[U.S. Constitution]].&quot; The exhibition examined the Constitutional process by considering the experiences of Americans of Japanese ancestry before, during, and after World War II. On view were more than 1,000 artifacts and photographs relating to the experiences of [[Japanese Americans]] during [[World War II]]. The exhibition closed on January 11, 2004. On November 8, 2011, the [[National Museum of American History]] launched an online exhibition of the same name with shared content.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian Online&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://americanhistory.si.edu/perfectunion/experience/index.html |title=A More Perfect Union Online Exhibition |publisher=National Museum of American History, Smithsonian Institution |accessdate=April 24, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References In Music==
[[Fort Minor]]'s release [[The Rising Tied]] contains a track entitled [[Kenji (song)|Kenji]], which relates the tale of a Japanese-American family's experience during the internment period. Lead singer [[Mike Shinoda]]'s paternal grandparents were interned during World War II, along with his father (as an infant). Shinoda is a third generation Japanese American, and his father is [[Nisei]].

Folk/country musician [[Tom Russell]] wrote &quot;Manzanar&quot;, a song about the Japanese American internment, that was released on his album ''Box of Visions'' (1993).&lt;ref name = &quot;Billboard.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title = Box of Visions – Tom Russell (1993) | url = http://www.billboard.com/song/tom-russell/manzanar/11908130#/album/tom-russell/box-of-visions/144904 | publisher = Billboard | date = April 10, 2003 | accessdate = May 2, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Discrimination|World War II|Asian Americans|Japan}}
* [[American propaganda during World War II]]
* [[Arizona during World War II]]
* [[List of documentary films about the Japanese American internment]]
* [[Population transfer]]
* [[Propaganda for Japanese-American internment]]
{{-}}

==References and notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
*{{Cite book| title = Command Decisions| editor = Kent Roberts Greenfield| url = http://www.history.army.mil/books/70-7_0.htm| publisher=[[United States Army Center of Military History]]| year = 2000 (reissue from 1960)| id = CMH Pub 70-7| chapter = 5. The Decision to Evacuate the Japanese from the Pacific Coast| first = Stetson| last = Conn| chapterurl =http://www.history.army.mil/books/70-7_05.htm }}
*De Nevers, Klancy Clark. ''The Colonel and the Pacifist: Karl Bendetsen, Perry Saito, and the Incarceration of Japanese Americans during World War II''. Salt Lake City: University of Utah Press, 2004. ISBN 978-0-87480-789-9
* Drinnon, Richard. ''Keeper of Concentration Camps: Dillon S. Meyer and American Racism.'' Berkeley: University of California Press, 1989.
* Gardiner, Clinton Harvey. (1981). [http://books.google.com/books?id=9zp1AAAACAAJ&amp;dq=Pawns+in+a+Triangle+of+Hate&amp;client=firefox-a ''Pawns in a Triangle of Hate: The Peruvian Japanese and the United States.''] Seattle: [[University of Washington Press]]. 10-ISBN 0-295-95855-3; ISBN 978-0-295-95855-2
*{{Cite book | author=Harth, Erica. | title=Last Witnesses: Reflections on the Wartime Internment of Japanese Americans | publisher=Palgrave, New York | year=2001 | isbn=0-312-22199-1}}
* Higashide, Seiichi. (2000). [http://books.google.com/books?id=ORE5wfUNdccC&amp;dq=Adios+to+Tears:+The+Memoirs+of+a+Japanese-Peruvian+Internee+in+U.S.+Concentration+Camps&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;source=gbs_summary_s&amp;cad=0 ''Adios to Tears: The Memoirs of a Japanese-Peruvian Internee in U.S. Concentration Camps.''] Seattle: University of Washington Press. 10-ISBN 0-295-97914-3; 13-ISBN 978-0-295-97914-4
* Hirabayashi, Lane Ryo. ''The Politics of Fieldwork: Research in an American Concentration Camp.'' Tucson: The University of Arizona Press, 1999.
*{{Cite book
 | editor-first = Linda
 | editor-last = Gordon
 | editor2-first = Gary Y.
 | editor2-last = Okihiro
 | year = 2006
 | title = Impounded: Dorothea Lange and the Censored Images of Japanese American Internment
 | publisher=W. W. Norton and Company
 | location = New York
 | isbn = 0-393-33090-7
}}
* Mackey, Mackey, ed. ''Remembering Heart Mountain: Essays on Japanese American Internment in Wyoming.'' Wyoming: Western History Publications, 1998.
* Miyakawa, Edward T. ''Tule Lake.'' Trafford Publishing, 2006. ISBN 1-55369-844-4
* Robinson, Greg. ''By Order of the President: FDR and the Internment of Japanese Americans.'' Cambridge and others: Harvard University Press, 2001.
*{{Cite book | author=Robinson, Greg | title=A Tragedy of Democracy: Japanese Confinement in North America | publisher=Columbia University Press | year=2009 | isbn=978-0-231-12922-0}}
*{{Cite book | author=Weglyn, Michi. | title=Years Of Infamy: The Untold Story Of America's Concentration Camps | publisher=University of Washington Press | year=1976, 1996 | isbn=0-295-97484-2}}
*{{Cite book | author=Civil Liberties Public Education Fund. | title=Personal Justice Denied: Report of the Commission on Wartime Relocation and Internment of Civilians | publisher=Civil Liberties Public Education Fund and University of Washington Press | year=1997 | isbn=0-295-97558-X}}
*{{Cite book |title=Japanese-American civilian prisoner exchanges and detention camps, 1941–45 |last=Elleman |first=Bruce |year=2006 |publisher=Routledge |isbn=978-0-415-33188-3 |oclc=  |page=179 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=zTsAj1cfYKUC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA31#v=onepage&amp;q= |accessdate=14 September2009}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
===Archival sources of documents, photos, and other materials===
{{Commons category}}
*[http://memory.loc.gov/learn/lessons/99/fear/gallery.html Nothing to Fear but Fear Itself] – Photo gallery at U.S. Library of Congress.
*[http://www.archives.gov/research/arc/topics/japanese-americans/ Japanese American Internment Records] available in the [http://www.archives.gov/research/arc/ Archival Research Catalog] of the [[National Archives and Records Administration]]
*[http://www.densho.org/ Densho: The Japanese American Legacy Project], Free digital archive containing hundreds of video oral histories and 10,000 historical photographs and documents
*[http://www.statesmanjournal.com/japanese_internment/intro.html &quot;Beyond Barbed Wire: Japanese Internment through Salem Eyes&quot;], ''Statesman Journal'', videos, stories, photographs and documents.
*[http://jarda.cdlib.org/ &quot;Japanese American Relocation Digital Archives&quot;], University of California, contains personal &amp; official photographs, letters, diaries, transcribed oral histories, etc.
*[http://bss.sfsu.edu/internment/documents.html Large number of documents] – Official documents, including official court opinions on the Yasui, Hirabayashi, and Korematsu Supreme Court cases
*[http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/aamhtml/aamhome.html Ansel Adams, &quot;Photographs of Japanese American Internment at Manzanar&quot;], ''American Memory Collection'', Library of Congress
*[http://www.smithsonianeducation.org/educators/lesson_plans/japanese_internment/index.html &quot;Letters from the Japanese American Internment&quot;], Correspondence between librarian Clara Breed and young internees, Smithsonian Institution
*[http://www.texasarchive.org/library/index.php?title=Alien_Enemy_Detention_Facility%2C_Crystal_City%2C_Texas&amp;gsearch=alien%20enemy &quot;Alien Enemy Detention Facility, Crystal City, Texas&quot;], film produced by the INS about Crystal City Alien Enemy Detention Facility, c. 1943
*[http://www.japaneserelocation.org/ JapaneseRelocation.org] – WW2 Japanese Relocation Camp Internee Records index
*[http://www.oac.cdlib.org/findaid/ark:/13030/tf596nb4h0/?query=Japanese%2520American%2520 Evacuation War Relocation Authority Photographs of Japanese-American Evacuation and Resettlement, 1942-1945], [http://www.oac.cdlib.org/findaid/ark:/13030/kt638nc9ww/?query=Japanese%2520American%2520Evacuation Japanese American Relocation Collection], and [http://www.oac.cdlib.org/findaid/ark:/13030/tf5j49n8kh/?query=Japanese%2520American%2520Evacuation Inventory of the Japanese American Evacuation and Resettlement Records, 1930-1974 (bulk 1942-1946)] at [[The Bancroft Library]]

===Other sources===
*{{Handbook of Texas|id=WW/quwby|name=World War II Internment Camps}}
*[http://www.campaignforjusticejla.org/ &quot;Campaign For Justice: Redress Now For Japanese American Internees!&quot;. A website with information about the lesser known internment of Japanese Latin Americans]
*[http://americanhistory.si.edu/exhibitions/exhibition.cfm?key=38&amp;exkey=78 A More Perfect Union: Japanese Americans and the U.S. Constitution] Online exhibition from the National Museum of American History, Smithsonian Institution
*[http://www.nps.gov/history/history/online_books/anthropology74/index.htm National Park Service; Confinement and Ethnicity: An Overview of World War II Japanese American Relocation Sites.]
*[http://www.minidoka.org/ Friends of Minidoka]
*[http://reclaimdemocracy.org/articles_2004/fred_korematsu_racial_profiling.html 60 years after his landmark Supreme Court battle, Fred Korematsu is fighting racial profiling of Arabs]
*[http://www.colostate.edu/Orgs/TuleLake/Tule%20Lake%20Menu.html Tule Lake Relocation Center by I. Fujimoto and D. Sunada]
* {{Internet Archive short film|id=gov.fdr.144|name=&quot;Japanese Relocation with Milton Eisenhower&quot;}}
* {{Internet Archive short film|id=gov.fdr.21|name=&quot;Challenge to Democracy (Japanese Internment) (1942)&quot;}}
* {{Internet Archive short film|id=gov.archives.arc.39227|name=&quot;Barriers And Passes, ca. 1939 – ca. 1945&quot;}}

{{NARA}}
{{Japanese American internment camps}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Japanese American Internment}}
[[Category:Japanese-American internment|*]]

{{Link GA|simple}}

[[cs:Americké internační tábory pro Japonce]]
[[de:Internierung japanischstämmiger Amerikaner]]
[[es:Campos de concentración para japoneses en los Estados Unidos]]
[[fa:بازداشت دسته‌جمعی ژاپنی‌ها در آمریکا]]
[[fr:Internement des Japonais-américains]]
[[id:Penginterniran orang Jepang-Amerika]]
[[he:כליאת היפנים בארצות הברית]]
[[nl:Internering van Japanse Amerikanen]]
[[ja:日系人の強制収容]]
[[pl:Internowanie Amerykanów japońskiego pochodzenia w czasie II wojny światowej]]
[[pt:Campos de concentração nos Estados Unidos]]
[[ru:Интернирование японцев в США]]
[[simple:Japanese American internment]]
[[sv:Internering av japaner i USA under andra världskriget]]
[[zh:日裔美國人囚禁]]</text>
      <sha1>8ywiw0evhlbvvwcuvqb6u4ny5cox2qr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
