<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Maoism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>46636</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520404020</id>
      <parentid>520380958</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-29T10:04:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>117.239.101.130</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Origins */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="52332">{{multiple issues|cleanup=December 2010|npov=December 2010|essay=June 2011}}
{{Maoism sidebar |expanded=all}}
{{Communism sidebar |expanded=Ideologies}}
{{Marxism–Leninism sidebar}}

'''Maoism''', formally known as '''Mao Zedong Thought ''' ({{zh|t=毛澤東思想|s=毛泽东思想|p=Máozédōng sīxiǎng}}), is a [[political]] theory derived from the teachings of the [[People's Republic of China|Chinese]] political leader [[Mao Zedong]] (1893–1976). Its followers, known as '''Maoists''', consider it as an [[anti-Revisionist]] form of [[Marxism-Leninism]].{{citation needed|date=August 2012}} Developed during the 1950s and 1960s, it was widely applied as the political and military guiding ideology of the [[Communist Party of China]] (CPC).

Maoism sees the [[agrarian]] [[peasantry]], rather than the [[working class]], as the key revolutionary force which can fundamentally transform [[capitalist]] society towards [[socialism]]. Holding that &quot;all political power proceeds from the barrel of a gun,&quot;{{citation needed|date=August 2012}} Maoist organizations mainly draw upon Mao's ideology of the [[People's War]], mobilizing large parts of rural populations to revolt against established institutions by engaging in [[guerrilla warfare]]. 

Maoism can also refer to the [[egalitarianism]] that was seen during Mao's era as opposed to the free-market ideology of [[Deng Xiaoping]]; some scholars additionally define [[personality cult]]s and political sloganeering as &quot;Maoist&quot; practices.{{Citation needed|date=August 2012}} Contemporary Maoists in China criticize the social inequalities created by a capitalist and &quot;revisionist&quot; Communist party. Maoism fell into disfavour in China in 1978,{{Citation needed|date=August 2012}} when [[Deng Xiaoping]] started the ''[[Reform and Opening]]'' economic policies that introduced capitalist market principles.

Notable Maoist organizations and armed groups currently exist in several countries, particularly in the most impoverished sections of the [[third world]].{{Citation needed|date=August 2012}} Examples of contemporary Maoist movements most notably include the [[Shining Path]] in [[Peru]], the [[Naxalite insurgency]] in [[India]], and the [[Communist Party of Nepal (Maoist)]]; the latter of which is the only current Maoist party [[Nepalese Constituent Assembly election, 2008|holding power]] through a democratic process.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.india-defence.com/reports-2361 |title=Maoist groups split in Nepal, violence feared |publisher=India Defence |date= |accessdate=2011年11月10日}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origins==

Although often described as an evolution of Marxism/Leninism, Maoism is defined more by its theoretical and ideological departures from orthodox Marxism or Leninism than by its similarities to the Western versions of modern socialism. The origins of Maoism stem not from Marxist writings alone, but also from the modern Chinese intellectual tradition in which Mao was raised.still on going.

===The modern Chinese intellectual tradition===

The modern Chinese intellectual tradition of the turn of the twentieth century is defined by two central concepts, [[iconoclasm]] and [[nationalism]].&lt;ref&gt;Meisner, Maurice. Mao’s China and After. New York: Free Press, 1999. Pages 12-16.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Iconoclastic revolution/anti-Confucianism====
By the turn of the twentieth century, a proportionately small yet socially significant cross-section of China's traditional elite (i.e. landlords and bureaucrats), found themselves increasingly skeptical of the efficacy and even the moral validity of Confucianism.&lt;ref&gt;Meisner, Maurice. Mao’s China and After. New York: Free Press, 1999. Page 10.&lt;/ref&gt; These skeptical iconoclasts formed a new segment of Chinese society, a modern intelligentsia, whose arrival, or as lauded historian of China [[Maurice Meisner]] would label it, their defection, heralded the beginning of the destruction of the gentry as a social class in China.&lt;ref&gt;Meisner, Maurice. Mao’s China and After. New York: Free Press, 1999. Page 11.&lt;/ref&gt; The fall of the last Chinese imperial dynasty in 1911 marked the final failure of the Confucian moral order, and did much to make Confucianism synonymous with political and [[social conservatism]] in the minds of Chinese intellectuals. It was this association of conservatism and Confucianism which lent to the iconoclastic nature of Chinese intellectual thought during the first decades of the Twentieth century.&lt;ref&gt;Meisner, Maurice. Mao’s China and After. New York: Free Press, 1999. Page 14.&lt;/ref&gt;

Chinese iconoclasm was expressed most clearly and vociferously by Chen Duxiu during the New Culture Movement which occurred between 1915 and 1919.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meisner, Maurice 1999. Pages 14&quot;&gt;Meisner, Maurice. Mao’s China and After. New York: Free Press, 1999. Pages 14.&lt;/ref&gt; Proposing the, &quot;total destruction of the traditions and values of the past,&quot; the New Culture Movement was spearheaded by the ''New Youth'', a periodical which was published by Chen Duxiu and which was profoundly influential on a young Mao Zedong whose first published work appeared on the magazine's pages.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meisner, Maurice 1999. Pages 14&quot;/&gt;

====Nationalism and the appeal of Marxism====
Along with iconoclasm, radical anti-imperialism dominated the Chinese intellectual tradition and slowly evolved into a fierce nationalist fervor which influenced Mao's philosophy immensely and was crucial in adapting Marxism to the Chinese model.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meisner, Maurice 1999. Page 44&quot;&gt;Meisner, Maurice. Mao’s China and After. New York: Free Press, 1999. Page 44.&lt;/ref&gt; Vital to understanding Chinese nationalist sentiments of the time is the Treaty of Versailles which was signed in 1919. The Treaty aroused a wave of bitter nationalist resentment in Chinese intellectuals as lands formerly ceded to Germany in Shandong were, without consultation with the Chinese, transferred to Japanese control rather than returned to Chinese sovereignty.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meisner, Maurice 1999. Page 17&quot;&gt;Meisner, Maurice. Mao’s China and After. New York: Free Press, 1999. Page 17.&lt;/ref&gt; The negative reaction culminated in the May 4th Incident which occurred on that day in 1919. The protest began with 3,000 students in Beijing displaying their anger at the announcement of the Versailles Treaty's concessions to Japan yet rapidly took a violent turn as protesters began attacking the homes and offices of ministers who were seen as cooperating with, or in the direct pay of the Japanese.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meisner, Maurice 1999. Page 17&quot;/&gt; The May 4th Incident and Movement which followed, &quot;catalyzed the political awakening of a society which had long seemed inert and dormant&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Meisner, Maurice 1999. Page 17&quot;/&gt;

Yet another international event would have a large impact on not only Mao but also the Chinese intelligensia was the Bolshevik Revolution of 1917. Although the revolution did elicit interest among Chinese intellectuals, socialist revolution in China was not considered a viable option until after the May 4th Incident.&lt;ref&gt;Meisner, Maurice. Mao’s China and After. New York: Free Press, 1999. Pages 18.&lt;/ref&gt; Afterwards, &quot;To become a Marxist was one way for a Chinese intellectual to reject both the traditions of the Chinese past and Western domination of the Chinese present&quot; Maurice Meisner, ''Mao's China and After'', page 18.

===Mao's personal philosophy===

Along with the Chinese intellectual tradition which was prevalent during his youth, it is clear that Mao's personal philosophy, his idealism and populist leanings, were foundational to the formation and profile of Maoism. Mao's political ideas emerge from his personal ethics. One source is commentaries to &quot;A System of Ethics&quot; by Friederich Paulsen (1917-1918) where he expressed: &quot;I do not agree with the view that to be moral, the motive of one action has to be benefiting others...Morality does not have to be defined in relation to others...People like me want to ...satisfy our hearts to the full, and in doing so we automatically have the most valuable moral codes. Of course there are people and objects in the world, but they are only for me&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chang, Jung; Halliday Jon, 2005. Page 15&quot;&gt;Chang, Jung; Halliday Jon. Mao: The Unknown Story. London: Vintage Books, 2005. Page 15.&lt;/ref&gt; His politics were consistent with these personal values and views.

====Idealism====
Mao believed that human consciousness is the principal factor in human history. In other words, he may be viewed as an idealist and, as such, directly contradicted the [[dialectical materialism|materialistic determinist]] tenets of orthodox Marxism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meisner, Maurice 1999. Page 41&quot;&gt;Meisner, Maurice. Mao’s China and After. New York: Free Press, 1999. Page 41.&lt;/ref&gt; Mao had the utmost faith that, through the actions of &quot;dedicated revolutionaries,&quot; a new social reality could be formed which would be in harmony with his ideals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meisner, Maurice 1999. Page 41&quot;/&gt;

====Populism====
Mao also believed strongly in the concept of a unified &quot;people&quot;. These notions were what prompted him to investigate the peasant uprisings in Hunan while the rest of the China's communists were in the cities and focused on the orthodox Marxist proletariat.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meisner, Maurice 1999. Page 43&quot;&gt;Meisner, Maurice. Mao’s China and After. New York: Free Press, 1999. Page 43.&lt;/ref&gt; Many of the pillars of Maoism such as the distrust of intellectuals and the abhorrence of occupational specialty are typical populist ideas.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meisner, Maurice 1999. Page 44&quot;/&gt; The concept of &quot;People's War&quot; which is so central to Maoist thought is directly populist in its origins. Mao believed that intellectuals and party cadres had to become first students of the masses to become teachers of the masses later. This concept was vital to the strategy of the &quot;People's War.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Meisner, Maurice 1999. Page 44&quot;/&gt;

====Nationalism====
Mao's nationalist impulses also played a crucially important role in the adaption of Marxism to the Chinese model and in the formation of Maoism.&lt;ref&gt;Meisner, Maurice. Mao’s China and After. New York: Free Press, 1999. Page 42.&lt;/ref&gt; Mao truly believed that China was to play a crucial preliminary role in the socialist revolution internationally. This belief, or the fervor with which Mao held it, separated Mao from the other Chinese Communists and led Mao onto the path of what Leon Trotsky called, &quot;Messianic Revolutionary Nationalism&quot; which was central to his personal philosophy and is demonstrated in his long-standing hostile relationship with ComIntern.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meisner, Maurice 1999. Page 43&quot;/&gt;

=== The Yan'an period ===

During the period immediately following the [[Long March]], Mao and the Chinese Communist Party were headquartered in Yan'an, which is a prefecture-level city in the Shaanxi province. During this period Mao clearly established himself as a Marxist theoretician and produced the bulk of the works which would later be canonized into the &quot;thought of Mao Zedong&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meisner, Maurice 1999. Page 45&quot;&gt;Meisner, Maurice. Mao’s China and After. New York: Free Press, 1999. Page 45.&lt;/ref&gt; The rudimentary philosophical base of Chinese Communist ideology is laid down in Mao's numerous dialectical treatises and was conveyed to newly recruited party members. This period truly established ideological independence from Moscow for Mao and the CCP.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meisner, Maurice 1999. Page 45&quot;/&gt; Although the Yan'an period did answer some of the questions, both ideological and theoretical, which were raised by the Chinese Communist Revolution, it left many of the crucial questions unresolved; including how the Chinese Communist Party was supposed to launch a socialist revolution while completely separated from the urban sphere.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meisner, Maurice 1999. Page 45&quot;/&gt;

==Components==

===Basic components===

#[[People's war]] and the mass line: The party must not be separate from the popular masses, either in policy or in revolutionary struggle. To conduct a successful revolution the needs and demands of the masses must be the most important issues.
#[[New Democracy]]: In so called backward countries, socialism cannot be introduced before the country has gone through a period in which the material conditions improve. This cannot be done by the [[bourgeoisie]], as its progressive character is long since replaced by a regressive character.
#Contradictions as the most important feature of society: Society is dominated by a wide range of contradictions that call for varying strategies. Revolution is necessary to resolve fully antagonistic contradictions such as those between labour and capital. Contradictions arising within the revolutionary movement call for ideological correction to prevent them from becoming antagonistic.
#[[Cultural revolution]]: The revolution does not wipe out bourgeois ideology; the class-struggle continues, and even intensifies, during socialism. Therefore a constant struggle against these ideologies and their social roots must be conducted. Cultural Revolution is directed also against traditionalism.
#[[Three Worlds Theory]]: During the [[Cold War]], two imperialist states formed the &quot;first world&quot;; the [[United States]] and the [[Soviet Union]]. The second world consisted of the other imperialist states in their spheres of influence. The third world consisted of the non-imperialist countries. Both the first and the second world exploit the third world, but the first world is the most aggressive part. The workers in the first and second world are &quot;bought up&quot; by imperialism, preventing socialist revolution. The people of the third world, on the other hand, have not even a short-sighted interest in the prevailing circumstances. Hence revolution is most likely to appear in third world countries, which again will weaken imperialism opening up for revolutions in other countries too.&lt;ref name=&quot;emg&quot;&gt;[http://www.marxists.org/glossary/terms/m/a.htm#maoism Maoism] Glossary of Terms, Encyclopedia of Marxism&lt;/ref&gt;

===Contradiction===
Mao Zedong drew from the writings of [[Karl Marx]], [[Friedrich Engels]] and [[Vladimir Lenin]] in elaborating his theory. Philosophically, his most important reflections emerge on the concept of &quot;contradiction&quot; (''maodun''). In two major essays, [[On contradiction]] and &quot;On the correct handling of contradictions among the people&quot;, he adopts the [[positivist]]-[[empiricist]] idea (shared by Engels) that contradiction is present in matter itself (and thus, also in the ideas of the brain). Matter always develops through a dialectical contradiction:

{{quote|&quot;The interdependence of the contradictory aspects present in all things and the struggle between these aspects determine the life of things and push their development forward. There is nothing that does not contain contradiction; without contradiction nothing would exist&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Mao Tse Tung, &quot;On contradiction&quot;, Selected Readings from the Works of Mao Tse-Tung, Foreign Language Press, Peking, 1967, p. 75, or http://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/mao/selected-works/volume-1/mswv1_17.htm.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Furthermore, each contradiction (including [[class struggle]], the contradiction holding between relations of production and the concrete development of forces of production) expresses itself in a series of other contradictions, some dominant, others not.

{{quote|&quot;There are many contradictions in the process of development of a complex thing, and one of them is necessarily the principal contradiction whose existence and development determine or influence the existence and development of the other contradictions&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Mao Tse-Tung, &quot;On contradiction&quot;, Selected Readings from the Works of Mao Tse-Tung, op. cit., p. 89, or http://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/mao/selected-works/volume-1/mswv1_17.htm.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Thus, the principal contradiction should be tackled with priority when trying to make the basic contradiction &quot;solidify&quot;. Mao elaborates further on this theme in the essay [[On Practice]]. On the relation between knowledge and practice, between knowing and doing&quot;. Here, &quot;Practice&quot; connects &quot;contradiction&quot; with &quot;class struggle&quot; in the following way: Inside a mode of production, there are three realms where practice functions: economic production, scientific experimentation (which also takes place in economic production and should not be radically disconnected from the former) and finally, class struggle. These may be considered the proper objects of economy, scientific knowledge, and politics.&lt;ref&gt;Cfr. Mao Tse-Tung, &quot;On practice. On the relation between knowledge and practice, between knowing and doing&quot;, Selected Readings from the Works of Mao Tse-Tung, op.cit., p. 55: &quot;Man's social practice is not confined to activity in production, but takes many forms&amp;mdash;class struggle, political life, scientific and artistic pursuits; in short, as a social being, man participates in all spheres of the practical life of society. Thus man, in varying degrees, comes to know the different relations  between man and man, not only through his material life but also though his political and cultural life (both of which are intimately bound up with material life)&quot;, or http://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/mao/selected-works/volume-1/mswv1_16.htm.&lt;/ref&gt;

These three spheres deal with matter in its various forms, socially mediated. As a result, they are the only realms where knowledge may arise (since truth and knowledge only make sense in relation to matter, according to Marxist epistemology). Mao emphasizes&amp;mdash;like Marx in trying to confront the &quot;bourgeoisie idealism&quot; of his time&amp;mdash;that knowledge must be based on [[empirical evidence]].

Knowledge results from hypotheses verified in the contrast with a real object; this real object, despite being mediated by the subject’s theoretical frame, retains its materiality and will offer resistance to those ideas that do not conform to its truth. Thus, in each of these realms (economic, scientific and political practice), contradictions (principle and secondary) must be identified, explored and put to function to achieve the communist goal. This involves the need to know, &quot;scientifically&quot;, how the masses produce (how they live, think, and work), to obtain knowledge of how class struggle (the main contradiction that articulates a mode of production, in its various realms) expresses itself.

===People's war and mass line===
Maoism's political orientation emphasizes the &quot;revolutionary struggle of the vast majority of people against the exploiting classes and their state structures&quot;, which Mao termed a &quot;[[People's War]]&quot;. Usually involving peasants, its military strategies have involved [[guerrilla war]] tactics focused on surrounding the cities from the countryside, with a heavy emphasis on political transformation through mass involvement of the lower classes of society.

===Agrarian socialism===
Maoism departs from conventional European-inspired Marxism in that its focus is on the agrarian countryside, rather than the industrial urban forces. This is known as [[Agrarian socialism]]. Notably, Maoist parties in Peru, Nepal and Philippines have adopted equal stresses on urban and rural areas, depending on the country's focus of economic activity. Maoism broke with the [[state capitalist]] framework of the [[Soviet Union]] under [[Nikita Khrushchev]] and dismisses it as modern [[Marxist revisionism|revisionism]], a traditional pejorative term among communists referring to those who fight for capitalism in the name of socialism.

===New Democratic revolution===

The theory of the [[New Democracy]] was known to the Chinese revolutionaries from the late 40’s. This thesis held that for the majority of the peoples of the planet, the long road to [[socialism]] could only be opened by a ‘national, popular, democratic, anti-feudal and anti-imperialist revolution [the language of the day], run by the communists.'&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
| last = Amin
| first = Samir
| title = The Countries of the South Must Take Their Own Independent Initiatives
| newspaper =
| publisher = The Third World Forum
| date = October 2009
| url = http://www.forumtiersmonde.net/fren/index.php/activitesactions/249-the-countries-of-the-south-must-take-their-own-independent-initiatives

 | accessdate = 2011年02月22日}}

&lt;/ref&gt;

And in the context of New Democratic revolution, the rationality of such economic policies as to destroy feudalism on the basis of land to the tiller, to confiscate all foreign and domestic economic establishments with a monopolistic character and to limit, control and guide private capital that do not control public life, have been proved in practice.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
| last = Dahal
| first = Pushpa Kamal(Prachanda)
| title = On Maoism
| newspaper =PROBLEMS &amp; PROSPECTS OF REVOLUTION IN NEPAL
| publisher = Published by (Printed Version): Janadisha Publications, Nepal, 2004
| date =
| url = http://web.archive.org/web/20041021024225/www.insof.org/collected/p_onmaoism.html

 | accessdate = 2011年02月22日}}

&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mao's intellectual Marxist development===
Mao’s &quot;Intellectual&quot; Marxist development can be divided into five major periods:  (1) The Initial Marxist Period from 1920–1926; (2) the formative Maoist period from 1927–1935; (3) the mature Maoism period from 1935–1940; (4) the civil war period from 1940–1949; and (5) the post-1949 period, following the revolutionary victory.
#	The Initial Marxist Period from 1920–1926: Marxist thinking employs imminent socioeconomic explanations; Mao’s reasons were declarations of his enthusiasm.    Mao did not believe education alone would bring about the transition from capitalism to communism because of three main reasons.  (1) Psychologically: the capitalists would not repent and turn towards communist on their own; (2) the rulers must be overthrown by the people; (3) &quot;the proletarians are discontented, and a demand for communism has arisen and had already become a fact.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Lowe, Donald M. The Function of &quot;China&quot; in Marx, Lenin, and Mao. Berkeley: University of California Press, 1966. Page 109&lt;/ref&gt; These reasons do not provide socioeconomic explanations, which usually forms the core of Marxist ideology.
#	The Formative Maoist Period from 1927–1935: In this period, Mao avoided all theoretical implications in his literature and employed a minimum of Marxist category thought.  His writings in this period failed to elaborate what he meant by the &quot;Marxist method of political and class analysis&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Lowe, Donald M. The Function of &quot;China&quot; in Marx, Lenin, and Mao. Berkeley: University of California Press, 1966. Page 111&lt;/ref&gt;  Prior to this period, Mao was concerned with the dichotomy between knowledge and action.  Now, he was more concerned with the dichotomy between revolutionary ideology and counter-revolutionary objective conditions.  There was more correlation drawn between China and the Soviet model.
#       The Mature Maoist Period from 1935–1940: Intellectually, this was Mao’s most fruitful time.  The shift of orientation was apparent in his pamphlet &quot;Strategic Problems of China’s Revolutionary War&quot; (Dec, 1936).  &quot;This pamphlet tried to provide a theoretical veneer for his concern with revolutionary practice.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Lowe, Donald M. The Function of &quot;China&quot; in Marx, Lenin, and Mao. Berkeley: University of California Press, 1966. Page 113&lt;/ref&gt;  Mao started to separate from the Soviet Model since it was not automatically applicable to China.    China’s historical particularism viewed through Marxist eyes served as the link between the Marxist process and China.
#	The Civil-War Period from 1940-1949: Unlike the Mature period, this period was intellectually barren.  Mao focused more on revolutionary practice and paid less attention to Marxist theory.  &quot;He continued to emphasize theory as practice-oriented knowledge.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lowe, Donald M 1966. Page 117&quot;&gt;Lowe, Donald M. The Function of &quot;China&quot; in Marx, Lenin, and Mao. Berkeley: University of California Press, 1966. Page 117&lt;/ref&gt;  The biggest topic of theory he delved into was in connection with the cheng-feng movement of 1942.  It was here that Mao summarized the correlation between Marxist theory and Chinese practice; &quot;The target is the Chinese revolution, the arrow is Marxism-Leninism.  We Chinese communists seek this arrow for no other purpose than to hit the target of the Chinese revolution and the revolution of the east.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lowe, Donald M 1966. Page 117&quot;/&gt;  The only new emphasis was Mao’s concern with two types of subjectivist deviation:  1) Dogmatism, the excessive reliance upon abstract theory; 2) Empiricism, excessive dependence on experience.
#       The post-1949 period, following the revolutionary victory: The victory of 1949 was a conformation of theory and practice.  &quot;Optimism is the keynote to Mao’s intellectual orientation in the post-1949 period.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Lowe, Donald M. The Function of &quot;China&quot; in Marx, Lenin, and Mao. Berkeley: University of California Press, 1966. Page 118&lt;/ref&gt;  Mao assertively revised theory to relate it to the new practice of socialist construction.  These revisions are apparent in the 1951 version of &quot;On Contradiction&quot;.    &quot;In the 1930’s, when Mao talked about contradiction, he meant the contradiction between subjective thought and objective reality.  In &quot;Dialectal Materialism&quot; of 1940, he saw idealism and materialism as two possible correlations between subjective thought and objective reality.  In the 1940s he introduced no new elements into his understanding of the subject-object contradiction.  Now, in the 1951 version of &quot;On Contradiction&quot;, he saw contradiction as a universal principle underlying all processes of development, yet with each contradiction possessed of its own particularity.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Lowe, Donald M. The Function of &quot;China&quot; in Marx, Lenin, and Mao. Berkeley: University of California Press, 1966. Page 119&lt;/ref&gt;

===Departure from Leninism===
Mao departed from Leninism not only in his near-total lack of interest in the urban working class but also in his concept of the nature and role of the Party. For Lenin, the Party was sacrosanct because it was the incarnation of the &quot;proletarian consciousness,&quot; and there was no question about who were the teachers and who were the pupils. For Mao, on the other hand, this question would always be virtually impossible to answer.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Meisner, Maurice. Mao’s China and After. New York: Free Press, 1999. Page 44.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Post-revolution==
In its post-revolutionary period, Mao Zedong's thought is defined in the CPC's Constitution as &quot;[[Marxism-Leninism]] applied in a Chinese context&quot;, synthesized by Mao Zedong and China's &quot;[[Generations of Chinese leadership|first-generation leaders]]&quot;. It asserts that [[class struggle]] continues even if the [[proletariat]] has already overthrown the [[bourgeoisie]], and there are capitalist restorationist elements within the Communist Party itself. Maoism provided the CPC's first comprehensive theoretical guideline with regards to how to continue socialist revolution, the creation of a socialist society, socialist military construction, and highlights various contradictions in society to be addressed by what is termed &quot;socialist construction&quot;. While it continues to be lauded to be the major force that defeated &quot;imperialism and feudalism&quot; and created a &quot;New China&quot; by the Communist Party of China, the ideology survives only in name on the Communist Party's Constitution; [[Deng Xiaoping]] abolished most Maoist practices in 1978, advancing a guiding ideology called &quot;[[Socialism with Chinese characteristics]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.xinhuanet.com/ziliao/2002-11/18/content_633225_1.htm |title=Xinhua: Constitution of the Communist Party of China |publisher=News.xinhuanet.com |date= |accessdate=2011年11月10日}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Medical staff of [[China PLA 165 Hospital]] and mental hospitals in [[Chenzhou]], [[Hunan]] claims that mental diseases should be defeated in a mental way, and [[mental disorder]]s can be cured using &quot;invincible&quot; Maoism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=|title=靠毛泽东思想治好精神病|url=http://cul.cn.yahoo.com/ypen/20110720/479631.html|newspaper=人民日報|date=1971年8月10日|agency=人民日報社|location=北京}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Maoism after Mao ==

{{Politics of the People's Republic of China}}
Shortly after Mao's death in 1976, [[Deng Xiaoping]] started the capitalist reforms of the People's Republic of China (PRC) in 1978 beginning the radical change of Mao's ideology in the PRC.&lt;ref&gt;[http://journalism.berkeley.edu/faculty/schell/schelldeng.html UC Berkeley Journalism -Faculty - Deng's Revolution]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although Mao Zedong Thought nominally remains the state ideology, Deng's admonition to [[seek truth from facts]] means that state policies are judged on their practical consequences; the role of ideology in determining policy, in many areas, has thus been considerably reduced. Deng also separated Mao from Maoism, making it clear that Mao was fallible and hence that the truth of Maoism comes from observing social consequences rather than by using Mao's quotations as [[Holy Writ|holy writ]], as was done in Mao's lifetime.&lt;ref name=&quot;citizendia.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://citizendia.org/Maoism#Maoism_in_China |title=Maoism |publisher=Citizendia |date= |accessdate=2011年11月10日}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition, the party constitution has been rewritten to give the capitalist ideas of Deng Xiaoping prominence over those of Mao. One consequence of this is that groups outside China which describe themselves as Maoist generally regard China as having repudiated Maoism and restored [[capitalism]], and there is a wide perception both in and out of China that China has abandoned Maoism. However, while it is now permissible to question particular actions of Mao and to talk about excesses taken in the name of Maoism, there is a prohibition in China on either publicly questioning the validity of Maoism or questioning whether the current actions of the CPC are &quot;Maoist.&quot;

Although Mao Zedong Thought is still listed as one of the [[four cardinal principles]] of the People's Republic of China, its historical role has been re-assessed. The Communist Party now says that Maoism was necessary to break China free from its feudal past, but that the actions of Mao are seen to have led to excesses during the [[Cultural Revolution]].&lt;ref name=&quot;citizendia.org&quot;/&gt;

The official view is that China has now reached an economic and political stage, known as the [[Socialism with Chinese characteristics|primary stage of socialism]], in which China faces new and different problems completely unforeseen by Mao, and as such the solutions that Mao advocated are no longer relevant to China's current conditions. The official proclamation of the new CPC stand came in June 1981, when the Sixth Plenum of the Eleventh National Party Congress Central Committee took place. The 35,000-word &quot;Resolution on Certain Questions in the History of Our Party Since the Founding of the People's Republic of China&quot; reads:

[[Image:LonggangZhen-NanyangShidi-0026.jpg|thumb|&quot;Mao Zedong is the Chinese people's savior!&quot;, an old slogan painted on the brick wall of a [[Chinese Buddhist]] [[Temple]]]]
&quot;Chief responsibility for the grave 'Left' error of the 'cultural revolution,' an error comprehensive in magnitude and protracted in duration, does indeed lie with Comrade Mao Zedong . . . . [and] far from making a correct analysis of many problems, he confused right and wrong and the people with the enemy. . . . Herein lies his tragedy.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.country-studies.com/china/the-four-modernizations,-1979-82.html |title=China the Four Modernizations, 1979-82 |publisher=Country-studies.com |date= |accessdate=2011年11月10日}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Scholars outside China see this re-working of the definition of Maoism as providing an ideological justification for what they see as the restoration of the essentials of capitalism in China by Deng and his successors, who sought to &quot;eradicate all ideological and physiological obstacles to economic reform&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;S. Zhao, &quot;A State-Led Nationalism: The Patriotic Education Campaign in Post-Tiananmen China&quot;, Communist and Post-Communist Studies, 1998, 31(3): pp. 288&lt;/ref&gt; In 1978 this led to the [[Sino-Albanian Split]] when Albanian leader [[Enver Hoxha]] denounced Deng as a revisionist and formed [[Hoxhaism]] as an anti-revisionist form of Marxism.

Mao himself is officially regarded by the CPC as a &quot;great revolutionary leader&quot; for his role in fighting the [[Japanese people|Japanese]] and creating the People's Republic of China, but Maoism as implemented between 1959 and 1976 is regarded by today's CPC as an economic and political disaster. In Deng's day, support of radical Maoism was regarded as a form of &quot;left deviationism&quot; and being based on a [[cult of personality]], although these 'errors' are officially attributed to the [[Gang of Four (China)|Gang of Four]] rather than to Mao himself.&lt;ref&gt;For a newest expression of the official judgment, see 中国共产党历史第二卷下册，中共中央党史研究室著，中共党史出版社，第二八章对&quot;文化大革命&quot;十年的基本分析(History of China Communist Party, Vol. 2, Party History Research Centre (Nov. 2010), Chap 28 Analysis on Cultural Revolution)&lt;/ref&gt; Thousands of Maoists were arrested in the Hua Guofeng period after 1976. The prominent Maoists, [[Zhang Chunqiao]] and [[Jiang Qing]] were sentenced to death with two-year-reprieve while some others were sentenced to life imprisonment or imprisonment over 15 years.

== Maoism internationally ==

=== Maoism outside China ===
From 1962 onwards, the challenge to the Soviet [[hegemony]] in the [[World Communist Movement]] made by the CPC resulted in various divisions in communist parties around the world. At an early stage,{{Citation needed|date=May 2012}} the [[Albanian Party of Labour]] sided with the CPC. So did many of the [[mainstream]] (non-splinter group) communist parties in South-East Asia, like the [[Burmese Communist Party]], [[Communist Party of Thailand]], and [[Communist Party of Indonesia]]. Some Asian parties, like the [[Workers Party of Vietnam]] and the [[Workers Party of Korea]] attempted to take a middle-ground position.

The Khmer Rouge of Cambodia is said to have been a replica of the Maoist regime. According to BBC  The Communist Party of Kampuchea (Cambodia), better known as the &quot;[[Khmer Rouge]]&quot;, identified strongly with Maoism, and is generally labeled a &quot;Maoist&quot; movement today.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/8373556.stm | work=BBC News | title=Khmer Rouge Duch trial nears end | date=2009年11月23日 | accessdate=2010年05月12日}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.straitstimes.com/BreakingNews/SEAsia/Story/STIStory_459313.html ]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Maoists, however, are quick to point out that the CPK strongly deviated from Marxist doctrine, and that the few references to Maoist China in CPK propaganda were critical of the Chinese.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aworldtowin.org/back_issues/1999-25/PolPot_eng25.htm |title=What Went Wrong with the Pol Pot Regime |publisher=Aworldtowin.org |date= |accessdate=2011年11月10日}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the west and south, a plethora of parties and organizations were formed that upheld links to the CPC. Often they took names such as ''Communist Party (Marxist-Leninist)'' or ''Revolutionary Communist Party'' to distinguish themselves from the traditional pro-Soviet communist parties. The pro-CPC movements were, in many cases, based among the wave of student radicalism that engulfed the world in the 1960s and 1970s.

Only one [[Western world|Western]] classic communist party sided with CPC, the [[Communist Party of New Zealand]]. Under the leadership of CPC and Mao Zedong, a parallel international communist movement emerged to rival that of the [[Soviets]], although it was never as formalized and homogeneous as the pro-Soviet tendency.

After the death of Mao in 1976 and the resulting power-struggles in China that followed, the international Maoist movement was divided into three camps. One group, composed of various ideologically nonaligned groups, gave weak support to the new Chinese leadership under Deng Xiaoping.  Another camp denounced the new leadership as traitors to the cause of Marxism-Leninism-Mao Zedong Thought. The third camp sided with the Albanians in denouncing the [[Three Worlds Theory]] of the CPC (see [[Sino-Albanian Split]].)

[[Che Guevara]], though initially praising the [[Soviet Union]] prior to, during and shortly after the [[Cuban Revolution]], later came out in support of Maoism, and advocated the adoption of the ideology throughout [[Latin America]]. The pro-Albanian camp would start to function as an international group as well,&lt;ref&gt;''ROMA OF THE FORMER YUGOSLAVIA'' Author: Judith Latham {{doi|10.1080/009059999109037}}. Published in: journal Nationalities Papers, Volume 27, Issue 2 June 1999 , pages 205 - 226&lt;/ref&gt; led by [[Enver Hoxha]] and the [[Albanian Party of Labour|APL]], and was also able to amalgamate many of the communist groups in Latin America, including  the [[Communist Party of Brazil]] and [[Marxist-Leninist Communist Party of Ecuador|Marxist-Leninist Communist Party]] in [[Ecuador]]. Later Latin American Communists such as [[Peru|Peru's]] [[Shining Path]] also embraced the tenets of Maoism.

The new Chinese leadership showed little interest in the various foreign groups supporting Mao's China. Many of the foreign parties that were [[fraternal party|fraternal parties]] aligned with the Chinese government before 1975 either disbanded, abandoned the new Chinese government entirely, or even renounced [[Marxism-Leninism]] and developed into non-communist, [[social democratic]] parties. What is today called the &quot;international Maoist movement&quot;  evolved out of the second camp{{spaced ndash}}the parties that opposed Deng and claimed to uphold the legacy of Mao.

==== India ====
*[[Maoism in India]]

The [[Communist Party of India (Maoist)]] is a [[Maoist]] [[political party]] in [[India]] which aims to overthrow the government of India.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
  | last = Ridge
  | first = Mian
  | title = Maoists' hijacking of Indian train reveals new audacity
  | newspaper = The Christian Science Monitor
  | publisher = The Christian Science Monitor
  | date = 2009年10月29日
  | url = http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/india/Maoists-looking-at-armed-overthrow-of-state-by-2050/articleshow/5648742.cms
  | accessdate = 2009年12月14日}}
&lt;/ref&gt; It was founded on September 21, 2004, through the merger of the [[Communist Party of India (Marxist–Leninist) People's War]] and the [[Maoist Communist Centre|Maoist Communist Centre of India]] (MCC). The merger was announced to the public on October 14 the same year. In the merger a provisional central committee was constituted, with the erstwhile People's War Group leader [[Muppala Lakshmana Rao]] alias Ganapathi as General Secretary. It is currently proscribed as a [[terrorist]] organization by the Indian government for organizing mass killings in furtherance of their ideology.

==== Nepal====
The [[Unified Communist Party of Nepal (Maoist)]], a national communist party with a revolutionary background, is a follower of Maoism, although it is believed that the party has developed its own ideology, [[Prachanda Path]], which was developed taking Nepal's political, sociological and geographical constraints into consideration.  Still, this party is believed to have taken Maoism as its doctrine as its name suggests.

==== Norway====
In Norway, the maoism of the ml-movement (''ml-bevegelsen'') was described in the 2012 movie by Wong Men Hoi, ''The East is Red''.&lt;ref&gt;http://klassekampen.no/60203/article/item/null/kinesisk-blikk-pa-akp&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Philippines====
In the [[Philippines]], the [[Communist Party of the Philippines]] (CPP) and its [[New People's Army]] (NPA) has been waging a revolutionary war since 1968. Its strength peaked during the dictatorial rule of [[Ferdinand Marcos]] and was the main bulk of the opposition against the dictatorship. However due to controversies regarding massive purges of its members in the mid-1980s and political miscalculations, it suffered several splits within its ranks in 1992 and 1997 forming several separate communist parties. It maintains active guerrilla fronts throughout the Philippines until today and is still considered by the military as the main threat to national security. The CPP, according to the military also allegedly has been leading and influencing legal left-wing political organizations and engages in elections.

The Marxist-Leninist Party of the Philippines (MLPP), formed by former [[Central Luzon]] Regional Committee members of the CPP after the split in 1997 maintained much of the Maoist orientation from the CPP most especially on the concept of People's War. However it has put equal emphasis on legal political struggles along with armed revolution and it sees the proletariat as the leader of the Philippine revolution in union with the peasantry. The Rebolusyonaryong Hukbo ng Bayan (People's Revolutionary Army, RHB) is the armed wing of the MLPP and according to military intelligence sources, the most active and fastest growing insurgent force in the Philippines recently next to the CPP. Like its estranged political sibling the MLPP is said to be organizing legal organizations but does not engage in electoral processes.

==== United States====
In the United States, the [[Black Panther Party]], especially [[Huey Newton]], was influenced by Maoist thought.

In the USA the [[Kasama Project]] (KP), was initiated by former [[Revolutionary Communist Party, USA]] members critical of what they viewed as the dogmatism and cult of personality of RCP USA. KP describes itself as seeking to radically re-imagine contemporary revolutionary politics. It is deeply influenced by Maoist thought, in particular as developed by the RCP USA, but claims members who arrive from other traditions, such as anarchism.

==== Spain====
The [[Communist Unification of Spain]] is an independent party that follows Marxist-Leninism and Maoism.

==== Somalia====
In Africa, [[Siad Barre|Siad Barre's]] regime in [[Somalia]] is often cited as being pro-Maoist, as it sided with the [[People's Republic of China]] during the [[Sino-Soviet split]] and, as such, China provided support to the regime during [[Ogaden War|its war]] with the pro-Soviet nations of [[Derg|Ethiopia]], [[Cuba]] and [[South Yemen]].

=== Maoist organizations ===
Today, there is no consensus on who does and who does not represent Maoism. Various efforts have sought to regroup the international communist movement under Maoism since the time of Mao's death in 1976.

One notable organization was the [[Revolutionary Internationalist Movement]] (RIM). RIM was founded in 1984 and included such notable organizations as the [[Shining Path|Communist Party of Peru]] (PCP), also known as &quot;Sendero Luminoso&quot; or &quot;Shining Path,&quot; the then [[Communist Party of Nepal (Maoist)]], now known as the [[Unified Communist Party of Nepal (Maoist)]] UCPN(M), and the [[Revolutionary Communist Party USA]] (RCP(USA)). Today, the RIM appears to be defunct or near defunct. The magazine associated with the RIM, A World To Win, has not published an issue since 2006, though A World To Win News Service still publishes regularly on the internet.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aworldtowin.org/wordpress/ |title=AWorld To Win News Service |publisher=Aworldtowin.org |date=2006年04月03日 |accessdate=2011年11月10日}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition, many of the one-time RIM organizations have become increasingly critical of each other. This has resulted in many public splits. For example, recently the RCP USA has criticized the UCPN(M) as revisionist after the UCPN(M) abandoned its people's war for the parliamentary road. In addition, Red Sun, a web page that claims to be affiliated with some faction the Communist Party of Peru, has criticized both the UCPN(M) and RCP USA. Another movement that has criticized the UCPN(M) is the Communist Party of India (Maoist) -- although they were never formally a RIM member, the CPI(Maoist) was formed out of three organizations, some of which were RIM members, at conferences organized by RIM.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://revcom.us/a/1200/awtwindia.htm |title=RW ONLINE: Maoist Organizations Unite in India |publisher=Revcom.us |date= |accessdate=2011年11月10日}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Scott H. |url=http://www.massline.info/India/Indian_Groups.htm#CPI%28Maoist%29 |title=Maoist Revolutionary parties and organizations in India |publisher=Massline.info |date= |accessdate=2011年11月10日}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another effort at regrouping the international communist movement is the [[International Conference of Marxist-Leninist Parties and Organizations]] (ICMLPO). Two notable parties that participate in the ICMLPO are the [[Marxist Leninist Party of Germany]] (MLPD) and the [[Communist Party of the Philippines]] (CPP). The ICMLPO seeks to unity around Marxism-Leninism, not Maoism. However, some of the parties and organizations within the ICMLPO identify as Mao Zedong Thought or Maoist.

== Criticisms and interpretations ==
Maoism has fallen out of favour within the Communist Party of China, beginning with Deng Xiaoping's reforms in 1978. Deng believed that Maoism showed the dangers of &quot;ultra-leftism&quot;, manifested in the harm perpetrated by the various mass movements that  characterized the Maoist era. In Chinese Communism, the term &quot;left&quot; can be taken as a euphemism for Maoist policies. However, Deng stated that the revolutionary side of Maoism should be considered separate from the governance side, leading to his famous epithet that Mao was &quot;70% good, 30% bad&quot;. China scholars generally agree that Deng's interpretation of Maoism preserves the legitimacy of Communist rule in China but at the same time criticizes Mao's brand of economic and political governance.

Critic Graham Young claims that Maoists see [[Joseph Stalin]] as the last true socialist leader of the Soviet Union, but allows that the Maoist assessments of Stalin vary between the extremely positive and the more ambivalent.&lt;ref&gt;Graham Young, ''On Socialist Development and the Two Roads'', The Australian Journal of Chinese Affairs, No. 8 (Jul., 1982), pp. 75-84, {{doi|10.2307/2158927}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some political philosophers, such as Martin Cohen, have seen in Maoism an attempt to combine [[Confucianism]] and [[Socialism]] - what one such called 'a third way between communism and capitalism'.&lt;ref&gt;Political Philosophy from Plato to Mao, by Martin Cohen, page 206, published 2001 by Pluto Press, London and Sterling VA ISBN 0-7453-1603-4&lt;/ref&gt;

Enver Hoxha critiqued Maoism from a Marxist-Leninist perspective, arguing that ''new democracy'' halts class struggle, the theory of the three worlds is &quot;counter-revolutionary&quot; and questioned Mao's guerilla warfare methods.

== See also ==
* [[Chinese New Left]]
* [[Cult of Personality]]
* [[Deng Xiaoping Theory]]
* [[History of the People's Republic of China]]
* [[New Democracy]]
* [[Three Represents]]
* ''[[Quotations from Chairman Mao]]''

'''External to China:'''
* [[Communist Party of India (Maoist)]]
* [[Guevarism]]
* [[Naxalite]]
* [[Naxalite-Maoist insurgency]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
*''Marxism in the Chinese Revolution'' by Arif Dirlik
*''Rethinking Mao: Explorations in Mao Zedong's Thought'' by Nick Knight
*''The Function of &quot;China&quot; in Marx, Lenin, and Mao'' by Donald Lowe
*''Li Ta-chao and the Origins of Chinese Marxism'' by Maurice Meisner
*''Mao’s China and After'' by Maurice Mesiner
*''The Political Thought of Mao Tse-Tung'' by [[Stuart Schram]]
*''Mao Tse-Tung, The Marxist Lord of Misrule. On Practice and Contradiction'' by Slavoj Zizek
*Gregor, A. James and Maria Hsia Chang. &quot;Maoism and Marxism in Comparative Perspective.&quot; ''[[The Review of Politics]]''. [[Cambridge University Press]] for the [[University of Notre Dame du Lac]] on behalf of ''[[Review of Politics]]''. Vol. 40, No. 3, July 1978. 307-327. [http://www.jstor.org/stable/1407255 Available at Jstor].
*[[Maurice Meisner|Meisner, Maurice]]. &quot;Leninism and Maoism: Some Populist Perspectives on Marxism-Leninism in China.&quot; ''[[The China Quarterly]]''. [[Cambridge University Press]] on behalf of the [[School of Oriental and African Studies]]. No. 45, January - March 1971. p.&amp;nbsp;2-36. [http://www.jstor.org/stable/651881 Available at Jstor].
*Steiner, H. Arthur. &quot;Maoism or Stalinism for Asia?&quot; ''[[Far Eastern Survey]]''. [[Institute of Pacific Relations]]. Vol. 22, No. 1, January 14, 1953. P. 1-5. [http://www.jstor.org/stable/3024690 Available at Jstor].

== External links ==
{{External links|date=August 2011}}

=== General ===
&lt;div class=&quot;references-small&quot;&gt;
*[http://www.marx2mao.com/Mao/Index.html Marx2Mao.org] Mao Internet Library
*[http://marxists.org/glossary/terms/m/a.htm#maoism The Encyclopedia of Marxism]  Mao Zedong Thought.
*[http://www.marxists.org/glossary/people/m/a.htm#mao-tse-tung The Encyclopedia of Marxism]  Mao's life.
*[http://www.monthlyreview.org/0105commentary.htm ''Monthly Review'' January 2005] Text of the leaflets distributed by the Zhengzhou Four.
*[http://revmedia.net World Revolution Media] Maoist revolutionary film, music, and art archive
* Batchelor, J. [http://cliojournal.wikispaces.com/Maoism+and+Classical+Marxism Maoism and Classical Marxism], Clio History Journal, 2009.
&lt;/div&gt;

=== Selected organizations ===
&lt;div class=&quot;references-small&quot;&gt;
*[http://pcpargentina.es.tl Communist Party of Argentina People]
*[http://slmarxist.yolasite.com  Maoist Group of Sri Lanka.]
*[http://llco.org Leading Light Communist Organization -- for Global People's War]
*[http://www.kasamaproject.org  The Kasama Project]
*[http://english.cpc.people.com.cn/ Chinese Communist Party]
*[http://www.freedomroad.org/ Freedom Road Socialist Organization]
*[http://www.aworldtowin.org Revolutionary Internationalist Movement]
Committee of Marxist-Leninist-Maoist parties from around the world
*[http://revcom.us/ Revolutionary Communist Party, USA] ''Revolution'' newspaper online
*[http://www.ucpnm.org/english/index.php www.ucpnm.org] Unified Communist Party of Nepal (Maoist)
*[http://www.sarbedaran.org www.sarbedaran.org] Communist Party of Iran (MLM) *in [[Persian language|Persian]]*
*[http://www.philippinerevolution.net/ Communist Party of the Philippines (CPP)]
*[http://www.redsun.org/ Communist Party of Peru Shining Path ]
*[http://www.risparty.org/ Revolutionary Internationalist Socialist Party, USA (RISP) ]
*[http://www.ip.org.tr/ Workers' Party (Turkey)]
*[http://www.pcr-rcpcanada.org/ Revolutionary Communist Party of Canada (PCR-RCP)]
*[http://www.pctpmrpp.org Communist Party of the Portuguese Workers] PCTP/MRPP (Portugal)
*[http://trzeciswiat.wordpress.com Third World] Polish Journal of Maoism-Third Worldism
&lt;/div&gt;

===Revolutions===
&lt;div class=&quot;references-small&quot;&gt;
* [http://news.google.com/news?q=Maoists&amp;hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;oe=UTF-8&amp;safe=off&amp;sa=N&amp;tab=wn Search for Maoists] on [[Google News]]
&lt;/div&gt;

{{Maoism}}
{{BlackPanther}}
{{Cultural Revolution}}

[[Category:Maoism| ]]
[[Category:Chinese philosophy]]
[[Category:Communism]]
[[Category:Far-left politics]]
[[Category:Political philosophy by politician]]
[[Category:Stalinism]]
[[Category:Totalitarianism]]

[[ar:ماوية]]
[[ast:Maoísmu]]
[[az:Maoizm]]
[[bg:Маоизъм]]
[[br:Maoouriezh]]
[[ca:Maoisme]]
[[cs:Maoismus]]
[[cy:Maoaeth]]
[[da:Maoisme]]
[[de:Maoismus]]
[[et:Maoism]]
[[el:Μαοϊσμός]]
[[es:Maoísmo]]
[[eo:Maoismo]]
[[eu:Maoismo]]
[[fa:مائوئیسم]]
[[fr:Maoïsme]]
[[gl:Maoísmo]]
[[ko:마오쩌둥주의]]
[[id:Maoisme]]
[[is:Maóismi]]
[[it:Maoismo]]
[[he:מאואיזם]]
[[kk:Маоизм]]
[[lv:Maoisms]]
[[lt:Maoizmas]]
[[hu:Maoizmus]]
[[ms:Maoisme]]
[[nl:Maoïsme]]
[[ne:माओवाद]]
[[ja:毛沢東思想]]
[[no:Maoisme]]
[[nn:Maoisme]]
[[pl:Maoizm]]
[[pt:Maoísmo]]
[[ro:Maoism]]
[[ru:Маоизм]]
[[scn:Maoismu]]
[[simple:Maoism]]
[[sk:Maoizmus]]
[[sl:Maoizem]]
[[sr:Маоизам]]
[[fi:Maolaisuus]]
[[sv:Maoism]]
[[tl:Maoismo]]
[[tr:Maoculuk]]
[[uk:Маоїзм]]
[[zh:毛泽东思想]]</text>
      <sha1>2qse8jc1jwpuni6ujts3fw0wxskwxwr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
