<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Nazism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>31045316</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520066903</id>
      <parentid>520066747</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-27T04:21:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dolescum</username>
        <id>11312068</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Notes */ Snip surplus entry</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="92796">{{Redirect|National Socialism|other ideologies and groups called National Socialism|National Socialism (disambiguation)}}
{{Redirect|Nazi|the Sumerian deity|Nazi (god)}}
{{Pp-semi-indef}}{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Nazism sidebar}}
'''Nazism''' ([[German language|German]]: '''''Nationalsozialismus'''''; English long form '''''National Socialism''''') was the [[ideology]] of the [[Nazi Party]] and [[Nazi Germany]].&lt;ref name=&quot;dictionary&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;university&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;university1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;payne1995a&quot;/&gt; It is a variety of [[fascism]] that incorporates [[Scientific racism|biological racism]] and [[antisemitism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;minneapolis&quot;/&gt; Nazism used elements of the [[Far-right politics|far-right]] [[Racism|racist]] ''[[Völkisch movement|Völkisch]]'' [[German nationalism|German nationalist]] movement and the [[Anti-communism|anti-communist]] ''[[Freikorps#Post-World War I|Freikorps]]'' [[paramilitary]] culture which fought against the [[Communism|communists]] in post-[[World War I]] Germany.&lt;ref name=&quot;stormtroopers&quot;/&gt; It was designed to draw workers away from communism and into ''Völkisch'' nationalism.&lt;ref name=&quot;stormtroopers2&quot;/&gt; Major elements of Nazism have been described as [[Far-right politics|far-right]], such as allowing domination of society by people deemed racially superior, while purging society of people declared inferior which were said to be a threat to national survival.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oliver H. Woshinsky 2008. p. 156&quot;/&gt;{{sfn|McNab|2009|p=11}}

Nazi philosophy claimed that an [[Aryan race|Aryan]] [[master race]] was superior to all other [[Race (classification of humans)|races]].&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt; To maintain what it regarded as the purity and strength of the Aryan race, the Nazis sought to [[Genocide|exterminate]] [[Jews]] and [[Romani people|Romani]], and the [[Physical disability|physically]] and [[Developmental disability|mentally disabled]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Simone Gigliotti 2005. p. 14&quot;/&gt; Other groups deemed &quot;[[Degeneration|degenerate]]&quot; or &quot;[[Asociality|asocial]]&quot; received [[Social exclusion|exclusionary treatment]] by the Nazi state and included [[Homosexuality|homosexuals]], [[Black people|blacks]], [[Jehovah's Witnesses]] and political opponents.&lt;ref name=&quot;Simone Gigliotti 2005. p. 14&quot;/&gt; The Nazis promoted German territorial [[expansionism]] to gain ''[[Lebensraum]]'' (&quot;living space&quot;) for German settlers and to bring labor, food and materials into the nation for growth.&lt;ref name=&quot;education&quot;/&gt;{{sfn|McNab|2009|p=13}}

Nazi ''[[Führer]]'' [[Adolf Hitler]] had objected to the party's previous leader's decision to use the word &quot;[[Socialism|Socialist]]&quot; in its name as Hitler at the time instead preferred to use &quot;Social Revolutionary&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Konrad Heiden 2010. p. 85&quot;/&gt; Upon taking over the leadership, Hitler kept the term but defined socialism as meaning a commitment of an individual to a community.&lt;ref name=&quot;Konrad Heiden 2010. p. 85&quot;/&gt; Hitler claimed that true socialism does not repudiate [[private property]] unlike the claims of [[Marxism]], and claimed that the &quot;Marxians have stolen the term and confused its meaning&quot; and said that &quot;Communism is not socialism. Marxism is not socialism.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;guardian&quot;/&gt; Nazism favoured private property, freedom of contract, and promoted the creation of national [[Social solidarity|solidarity]] that would transcend class differences.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated11&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;political&quot;/&gt; The Nazis outlawed [[Strike action|strikes]] by [[employee]]s and [[Lockout (industry)|lockouts]] by [[employer]]s, because these were regarded a threat to national unity.&lt;ref name=&quot;university3&quot;/&gt; Instead, the state controlled and approved wage and salary levels.&lt;ref name=&quot;davidson&quot;/&gt;

==Etymology==
The full name of Adolf Hitler's party was ''Nationalsozialistische Deutsche Arbeiterpartei'' (National Socialist German Workers' Party). The acronym ''Nazi'' was formed from the first syllable of ''NAtional'' and the second syllable of ''SoZIalist''. Such acronyms, usually formed from the initial letters or syllables of successive parts of compound names, were popular in the [[Nazi Germany|Third Reich]]. Another such example was [[Gestapo]] for ''GEheime STAatsPOlizei'' (Secret State Police).&lt;ref name=&quot;encyclopedia&quot;/&gt;

==Position in the political spectrum==
[[File:WWII, Europe, Germany, &quot;Nazi Hierarchy, Hitler, Goering, Goebbels, Hess&quot;, The Desperate Years p143 - NARA - 196509.tif|thumb|300px|''Führer'' [[Adolf Hitler]] (first from left side), [[Hermann Göring]] (second from left side), Minister of Propaganda [[Joseph Goebbels]] (third from left side), [[Rudolf Hess]] (fourth from left side).]]
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 102-02134, Bad Harzburg, Gründung der Harzburger Front.jpg|thumb|300px|Nazis alongside members of the far-right [[reactionary]] and [[Monarchism|monarchist]] [[German National People's Party]] (DNVP), during the brief Nazi-DNVP alliance in the [[Harzburg Front]] from 1931 to 1932.]]

A majority of scholars identify Nazism in practice as a form of [[far-right politics]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Fritzsche, Peter 1998&quot;/&gt; Far right themes in Nazism include the argument that superior people have a right to dominate over others and purge society of supposed inferior elements.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oliver H. Woshinsky 2008. p. 156&quot;/&gt; Adolf Hitler and other proponents officially portrayed Nazism as being neither left- nor right-wing, but syncretic.&lt;ref name=&quot;Adolf Hitler p. 170&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Rudy Koshar 1986. p. 190&quot;/&gt; Hitler in ''Mein Kampf'' directly attacked both left-wing and right-wing politics in Germany, saying: &lt;blockquote&gt;
Today our left-wing politicians in particular are constantly insisting that their craven-hearted and obsequious foreign policy necessarily results from the disarmament of Germany, whereas the truth is that this is the policy of traitors [...] But the politicians of the Right deserve exactly the same reproach. It was through their miserable cowardice that those ruffians of Jews who came into power in 1918 were able to rob the nation of its arms.&lt;ref name=&quot;Adolf Hitler 2010. p. 287&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Hitler, when asked whether he supported the &quot;bourgeois right-wing&quot;, claimed that Nazism was not exclusively for any class, and indicated that it favoured neither the left nor the right, but preserved &quot;pure&quot; elements from both &quot;camps&quot;, stating: &quot;From the camp of bourgeois [[tradition]], it takes national resolve, and from the [[Dialectical materialism|materialism]] of the [[Marxism|Marxist]] dogma, living, creative Socialism&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;commentary&quot;/&gt;

The Nazis were strongly influenced by the post-[[World War I]] far-right in Germany, which held common beliefs such as anti-Marxism, anti-liberalism, and anti-Semitism, along with nationalism, contempt towards the Treaty of Versailles, and condemnnation of the Weimar Republic for signing the armistice in November 1918 that later led to their signing of the Treaty of Versailles.&lt;ref name=&quot;Peukert, Detlev 1993 pp. 73-74&quot;/&gt; A major inspiration for the Nazis were the far-right nationalist ''[[Freikorps#Post-World War I|Freikorps]]'', paramilitary organizations that engaged in political violence after World War I.&lt;ref name=&quot;Peukert, Detlev 1993 pp. 73-74&quot;/&gt; Initially, the post-World War I German far right was dominated by [[Monarchism|monarchists]], but the younger generation, who were associated with ''Völkisch'' nationalism, were more radical and did not express any emphasis on the restoration of the German monarchy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Peukert, Detlev 1993 p. 74&quot;/&gt; This younger generation desired to dismantle the Weimar Republic and create a new radical and strong state based upon a martial ruling ethic that could revive the &quot;Spirit of 1914&quot; that was associated with German national unity (''[[Volksgemeinschaft]]'').&lt;ref name=&quot;Peukert, Detlev 1993 p. 74&quot;/&gt;

The Nazis, the far-right monarchist and [[reactionary]] [[German National People's Party]] (DNVP), and others, such as monarchist officers of the German army and several prominent industrialists, formed an alliance in opposition to the Weimar Republic on 11 October 1931 in [[Bad Harzburg]]; officially known as the &quot;National Front&quot;, but commonly referred to as the [[Harzburg Front]].&lt;ref name=&quot;machtergreifung&quot;/&gt; The Nazis stated the alliance was purely tactical and there remained substantial differences with the DNVP. The Nazis described the DNVP as a bourgeois party and called themselves an anti-bourgeois party.&lt;ref name=&quot;machtergreifung4&quot;/&gt; After the elections in 1932, the alliance broke after the DNVP lost many of its seats in the Reichstag. The Nazis denounced them as &quot;an insignificant heap of reactionaries&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;machtergreifung5&quot;/&gt; The DNVP responded by denouncing the Nazis for their socialism, their street violence, and the &quot;economic experiments&quot; that would take place if the Nazis rose to power.&lt;ref name=&quot;machtergreifung6&quot;/&gt;

Te exiled Kaiser Wilhelm II, who fled Germany into exile amidst an attempted communist revolution in Germany, initially supported the Nazi Party, and his four sons of the exiled German royal family, including Prince [[Prince Eitel Friedrich of Prussia|Eitel Friedrich]] and Prince [[Prince Oskar of Prussia|Oskar]], became members of the Nazi Party, in hopes that in exchange for their support, the Nazis would permit the restoration of the monarchy.&lt;ref name=&quot;nicholas&quot;/&gt;

There were factions in the Nazi Party, both conservative and radical.&lt;ref name=&quot;Michael Mann 2004. p. 183&quot;/&gt; The conservative Nazi [[Hermann Göring]] urged Hitler to conciliate with [[Capitalism|capitalists]] and [[Reactionary|reactionaries]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Michael Mann 2004. p. 183&quot;/&gt; Other prominent conservative Nazis included [[Heinrich Himmler]] and [[Reinhard Heydrich]].&lt;ref name=&quot;foundations&quot;/&gt;

The radical Nazi [[Joseph Goebbels]], hated capitalism, viewing it as having Jews at its core, and he stressed the need for the party to emphasize both a [[Proletariat|proletarian]] and national character. Those views were shared by [[Otto Strasser]], who later left the Nazi Party in the belief that Hitler had betrayed the party's socialist goals by allegedly endorsing capitalism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Michael Mann 2004. p. 183&quot;/&gt; Large segments of the Nazi Party staunchly supported its official socialist, revolutionary, and anti-capitalist positions and expected both a social and economic revolution upon the party gaining power in 1933.&lt;ref name=&quot;Joseph W. Bendersky 2007. p. 96&quot;/&gt; Many of the million members of the [[Sturmabteilung]] (SA) were committed to the party's official socialist program.&lt;ref name=&quot;Joseph W. Bendersky 2007. p. 96&quot;/&gt; The leader of the SA, [[Ernst Röhm]], pushed for a &quot;second revolution&quot; (the &quot;first revolution&quot; being the Nazis' seizure of power) that would entrench the party's official socialist program. Further, Röhm desired that the SA absorb the much smaller German Army into its ranks under his leadership.&lt;ref name=&quot;Joseph W. Bendersky 2007. p. 96&quot;/&gt;

Prior to becoming an anti-Semite and a Nazi, Hitler had lived a [[Bohemianism|Bohemian]] lifestyle as a wandering watercolour artist in [[Austria]] and southern Germany, though he maintained elements of it later in life.&lt;ref name=&quot;publishers&quot;/&gt; Hitler served in World War I and after the war his battalion was absorbed by the [[Bavarian Soviet Republic]] from 1918 to 1919, where he was elected Deputy Battalion Representative. According to historian Thomas Weber, he attended the funeral of communist [[Kurt Eisner]] (a German Jew), wearing a black mourning armband on one arm and a red communist armband on the other.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas Weber 2011. p. 251&quot;/&gt; Further that Hitler's political beliefs had not yet solidified, and at that time he supported the idea of a [[classless society]] and was an [[Anti-monarchism|anti-monarchist]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas Weber 2011. p. 251&quot;/&gt; In ''Mein Kampf'', Hitler never mentioned any service with the Bavarian Soviet Republic, and he stated that he became an anti-Semite in 1913 in Vienna. This statement has been disputed with the contention he in fact was not an anti-Semite at that time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jeffrey S. Gaab 2008. p. 61&quot;/&gt; Hitler altered his political views in response to the [[Treaty of Versailles]] of June 1919, and it was then that he became an anti-Semitic, German nationalist.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jeffrey S. Gaab 2008. p. 61&quot;/&gt; As a Nazi, Hitler had expressed opposition to capitalism; he regarded capitalism as having Jewish origins, and accused capitalism of holding nations ransom in the interests of a parasitic [[Cosmopolitanism|cosmopolitan]] [[rentier]] class.&lt;ref name=&quot;R.J. Overy 2004. pp. 399-403&quot;/&gt;

Hitler took a pragmatic position between the conservative and radical factions of the Nazi Party, in that he accepted private property and allowed capitalist private enterprises to exist as long as they adhered to the goals of the Nazi state. However, if a capitalist private enterprise resisted Nazi goals, he sought to destroy it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Michael Mann 2004. p. 183&quot;/&gt; Upon the Nazis achieving power, Röhm's SA began attacks against individuals deemed to be associated with conservative reaction, without Hitler's authorization to do so.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nyomarkay, Joseph 1967 p. 130&quot;/&gt; Hitler considered Röhm's independent actions to be violating and possibly threatening his leadership, as well as jeopardizing the regime by alienating the conservative President [[Paul von Hindenburg]] and the conservative-oriented German Army.&lt;ref name=&quot;Joseph Nyomarkay 1967. p. 133&quot;/&gt; This resulted in Hitler purging Röhm and other radical members of the SA in what came to be known as the [[Night of the Long Knives]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Joseph Nyomarkay 1967. p. 133&quot;/&gt;

Although he opposed communist ideology, Hitler on numerous occasions publicly praised the [[Soviet Union]]'s leader [[Joseph Stalin]] and [[Stalinism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;François Furet 1999. pp. 191-192&quot;/&gt; Hitler commended Stalin for seeking to purify the [[Communist Party of the Soviet Union]] of Jewish influences, noting Stalin's purging of Jewish communists such as [[Leon Trotsky]], [[Grigory Zinoviev]], [[Lev Kamenev]] and [[Karl Radek]].&lt;ref name=&quot;communism&quot;/&gt; While Hitler always intended to bring Germany into conflict against the Soviet Union to gain ''[[Lebensraum]]'' (&quot;living space&quot;), he supported a temporary strategic alliance between Nazi Germany and the Soviet Union to form a common anti-liberal front to crush liberal democracies, particularly [[France]].&lt;ref name=&quot;François Furet 1999. pp. 191-192&quot;/&gt;

==Origins==
{{See also|Early timeline of Nazism}}

===Nationalism, antisemitism and racism===
[[File:Johann Gottlieb Fichte.jpg|thumb|[[Johann Gottlieb Fichte]], considered one of the fathers of German nationalism.]]

One of the most significant ideological influences on the Nazis was the German nationalist [[Johann Gottlieb Fichte]], whose works had served as inspiration to Hitler and other Nazi members, including [[Dietrich Eckart]] and [[Arnold Fanck]].&lt;ref name=&quot;timothy&quot;/&gt; In ''Speeches to the German Nation'' (1808), written amid [[Napoleon]]ic France's occupation of Berlin, Fichte called for a German national revolution against the French occupiers, making passionate public speeches, arming his students for battle against the French, and stressing the need for action by the German nation to free itself.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated18&quot;/&gt; Fichte's nationalism was populist and opposed to traditional elites, spoke of the need of a &quot;People's War&quot; (''Volkskrieg''), and put forth concepts similar to those the Nazis adopted.&lt;ref name=autogenerated18 /&gt; Fichte promoted German [[exceptionalism]] and stressed the need for the German nation to be purified (including purging the German language of French words, a policy that the Nazis undertook upon rising to power).&lt;ref name=autogenerated18 /&gt;

''Völkisch'' nationalism denounced soulless [[materialism]], [[individualism]], and [[secular]]ized [[Urban area|urban]] industrial society, while advocating a &quot;superior&quot; society based on ethnic German &quot;folk&quot; culture and German &quot;blood&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;encyclopedia7&quot;/&gt; It denounced foreigners, foreign ideas and declared that Jews, national minorities, [[Catholic Church|Catholics]], and [[Freemasonry|Freemasons]] were &quot;traitors to the nation&quot; and unworthy of inclusion.&lt;ref name=&quot;constructing&quot;/&gt; ''Völkisch'' nationalism saw the world in terms of [[natural law]] and [[romanticism]], viewed societies as organic, extolling the virtues of [[rural]] life, condemning the neglect of tradition and decay of morals, denounced the destruction of the natural environment, and condemned &quot;cosmopolitan&quot; cultures such as Jews and Romani.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jonathan Olsen 1999. p. 62&quot;/&gt;

During the era of Imperial Germany, ''Völkisch'' nationalism was overshadowed by both Prussian patriotism and the federalist tradition of various states therein.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nina Witoszek 2002. pp. 89-90&quot;/&gt; The events of World War I including the end of the Prussian monarchy in Germany, resulted in a surge of revolutionary ''Völkisch'' nationalism.&lt;ref name=&quot;witoszek&quot;/&gt; The Nazis supported such revolutionary ''Völkisch'' nationalist policies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nina Witoszek 2002. pp. 89-90&quot;/&gt; The Nazis claimed that their ideology was influenced by the leadership and policies of [[Chancellor of Germany|German Chancellor]] [[Otto von Bismarck]], the founder of the [[German Empire]].&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated14&quot;/&gt; The Nazis declared that they were dedicated to continuing the process of creating a unified German [[nation state]] that Bismarck had begun and desired to achieve.&lt;ref name=&quot;chancellor&quot;/&gt; While Hitler was supportive of Bismarck's creation of the German Empire, he was critical of Bismarck's moderate domestic policies.&lt;ref name=&quot;chancellor8&quot;/&gt; On the issue of Bismarck's support of a ''[[Kleindeutschland]]'' (&quot;Lesser Germany&quot;, excluding Austria) versus the pan-German ''[[German question#Later influence|Großdeutschland]]'' (&quot;Greater Germany&quot;) of the Nazis, Hitler stated that Bismarck's attainment of ''Kleindeutschland'' was the &quot;highest achievement&quot; Bismarck could have achieved &quot;within the limits possible of that time&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated12&quot;/&gt; In ''[[Mein Kampf]]'' (''My Struggle''), Hitler presented himself as a &quot;second Bismarck&quot;.&lt;ref name=autogenerated12 /&gt;

The concept of the [[Aryan race]] which the Nazis promoted stems from racial theories asserting that Europeans are the descendants of Indo-Iranian settlers, people of ancient India and ancient Persia.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated6&quot;/&gt; Proponents of this theory based their assertion on the similarity of European words and their meaning to those of Indo-Iranian languages.&lt;ref name=autogenerated6 /&gt; [[Johann Gottfried Herder]] argued that the Germanic peoples held close racial connections with the ancient Indians and ancient Persians, who he claimed were advanced peoples possessing a great capacity for wisdom, nobility, restraint, and science.&lt;ref name=autogenerated6 /&gt; Contemporaries of Herder utilized the concept of the Aryan race to draw a distinction between what they deemed &quot;high and noble&quot; Aryan culture versus that of &quot;parasitic&quot; Semitic culture.&lt;ref name=autogenerated6 /&gt;

Notions of [[white supremacy]] and Aryan racial superiority combined in the nineteenth century, with white supremacists maintaining that [[white people]] were members of an Aryan &quot;master race&quot; which is superior to other races, and particularly the Semitic race, which they associated with &quot;cultural sterility&quot;.&lt;ref name=autogenerated6 /&gt; [[Arthur de Gobineau]], a French racial theorist and aristocrat, blamed the fall of the ''ancien régime'' in France on racial degeneracy caused by racial intermixing, which he argued destroyed the purity of the Aryan race.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated8&quot;/&gt; Gobineau's theories, which attracted a strong following in Germany,&lt;ref name=autogenerated8 /&gt; emphasized the existence of an irreconcilable [[polarity in international relations|polarity]] between Aryan and Jewish cultures.&lt;ref name=autogenerated6 /&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 119-1600-06, Houston Stewart Chamberlain.jpg|170px|left|[[Houston Stewart Chamberlain]]]]
Aryan [[mysticism]] claimed that [[Christianity]] originated in Aryan religious tradition and that Jews had usurped the legend from Aryans.&lt;ref name=autogenerated6 /&gt; [[Houston Stewart Chamberlain]], an English proponent of racial theory, supported notions of Germanic supremacy and anti-Semitism in Germany.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated4&quot;/&gt; Chamberlain's work, ''[[Foundations of the Nineteenth Century]]'' (1899) praised Germanic peoples for their creativity and idealism while asserting that the Germanic spirit was threatened by a &quot;Jewish&quot; spirit of selfishness and [[materialism]].&lt;ref name=autogenerated4 /&gt; Chamberlain used his thesis to promote [[Monarchism|monarchical]] [[conservatism]] while denouncing [[democracy]], [[liberalism]], and [[socialism]].&lt;ref name=autogenerated8 /&gt; The book became popular, especially in Germany.&lt;ref name=autogenerated8 /&gt; Chamberlain stressed the need of a nation to maintain racial purity in order to prevent degeneration, and argued that racial intermingling with Jews should never be permitted.&lt;ref name=autogenerated8 /&gt; In 1923, Chamberlain met Hitler, whom he admired as a leader of the rebirth of the free spirit.&lt;ref name=&quot;encyclopedia9&quot;/&gt;

Beginning in the 1870s, German [[Völkisch movement|''Völkisch'' nationalism]] began to adopt anti-Semitic and racist themes and was adopted by a number of radical right political movements.&lt;ref name=&quot;witoszek10&quot;/&gt;

''[[The Protocols of the Elders of Zion]]'' (1912) was an anti-Semitic forgery created by the police of the Russian Empire.  Anti-Semites believed it was real and the Protocol surged in popularity after World War I.&lt;ref name=&quot;stackelberg&quot;/&gt; ''The Protocols'' claimed that there was a secret international Jewish conspiracy to take over the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;kershaw&quot;/&gt; Hitler had been introduced to ''The Protocols'' by [[Alfred Rosenberg]], and from 1920 onward Hitler focused his attacks on claiming that Judaism and Marxism were directly connected; that Jews and [[Bolshevik]]s were one and the same and that Marxism was a Jewish ideology.&lt;ref name=&quot;dictator&quot;/&gt; Hitler believed that ''The Protocols'' were authentic.&lt;ref name=&quot;dictator11&quot;/&gt;

Radical anti-Semitism was promoted by prominent advocates of ''Völkisch'' nationalism including [[Eugen Diederichs]], [[Paul de Lagarde]], and [[Julius Langbehn]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Jonathan Olsen 1999. p. 62&quot;/&gt; De Lagarde called the Jews a &quot;[[bacillus]], the carrier of decay...who pollute every national culture...and destroy all faith with their materialistic liberalism&quot; and he called for the extermination of the Jews.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jack Fischel 1998. p. 5&quot;/&gt; Langbehn called for a war of annihilation of the Jews and Langbehn's genocidal policies were published by the Nazis and given to soldiers on the front during [[World War II]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Jack Fischel 1998. p. 5&quot;/&gt;

[[Johann Gottlieb Fichte]] accused [[Jews]] in Germany of having been, and inevitably continuing to be, a &quot;state within a state&quot; in Germany that was a threat to German national unity.&lt;ref name=autogenerated18 /&gt; Fichte promoted two options to address this: the first was the creation of a Jewish state in [[Palestine]] to impel the Jews to leave Europe.&lt;ref name=&quot;timothy12&quot;/&gt; The other option was violence against Jews, saying that the goal would be &quot;...to cut off all their heads in one night, and set new ones on their shoulders, which should not contain a single Jewish idea&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;timothy13&quot;/&gt;

The Nazis claimed that Bismarck was unable to complete German national unification because of Jewish infiltration of the German parliament, and that their abolition of parliament ended the obstacle to unification.&lt;ref name=autogenerated14 /&gt; Using the &quot;stab in the back&quot; legend, the Nazis accused Jews, and other populaces it considered non-German, of possessing extra-national loyalties, thereby exacerbating German [[Antisemitism|anti-semitism]] about the ''[[Jewish question|Judenfrage]]'' (the Jewish Question), the perennial [[far right]] political canard popular when the ethnic [[Völkisch movement]] and their politics of [[Romantic nationalism]] for establishing a ''[[German question#Later influence|Großdeutschland]]'' were strong.&lt;ref name=&quot;PostWWIAntisemitism&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JFrage&quot;/&gt; 

Nazism's racial policy positions may have developed from the views of important biologists of the 19th century, including French [[biologist]] [[Jean-Baptiste Lamarck]], through [[Ernst Haeckel]]'s idealist version of [[Lamarckism]] and the father of [[genetics]], German [[botanist]] [[Gregor Mendel]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Peter J. Bowler 1989. pp. 304-305&quot;/&gt; However Haeckel's works were later condemned and banned from bookshops and libraries by the Nazis as inappropriate for “National-Socialist formation and education in the Third Reich.” This may have been because of his &quot;monist&quot; atheistic, materialist philosophy which the Nazis disliked.&lt;ref name=&quot;Robert J. Richards 2008. pp. 7-8&quot;/&gt; Unlike Darwinian theory, Lamarckian theory officially ranked races in a hierarchy of evolution from [[ape]]s while Darwinian theory did not grade races in a hierarchy of higher or lower evolution from apes, simply categorizing humans as a whole of all as having progressed in evolution from apes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Peter J. Bowler 1989. pp. 304-305&quot;/&gt; Many Lamarckians viewed &quot;lower&quot; races as having been exposed to debilitating conditions for too long for any significant &quot;improvement&quot; of their condition in the near future.&lt;ref name=&quot;evolution&quot;/&gt; Haeckel utilized Lamarckian theory to describe the existence of interracial struggle and put races on a hierarchy of evolution, ranging from being wholly human to [[subhuman]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Peter J. Bowler 1989. pp. 304-305&quot;/&gt;
[[File:VonSchoenerer.jpg|170px|thumb|[[Georg Ritter von Schönerer]]]]
[[Mendelian inheritance|Mendelian inheritance or Mendelism]] was supported by the Nazis and also mainstream eugenics proponents at the time. The Mendelian theory of inheritance declared that genetic traits and attributes were passed from one generation to another.&lt;ref name=&quot;university14&quot;/&gt; Proponents of eugenics used Mendelian inheritance theory to demonstrate the transfer of biological illness and impairments from parents to children, including mental disability; others also utilized Mendelian theory to demonstrate the inheritance of social traits, with racialists claiming a racial nature of certain general traits such as inventiveness or criminal behaviour.&lt;ref name=&quot;friedlander&quot;/&gt;

During his youth in Austria, Hitler was politically influenced by Austrian pan-Germanist proponent [[Georg Ritter von Schönerer]], who advocated radical [[German nationalism in Austria|German nationalism]], anti-Semitism, anti-Catholicism, anti-Slavism and anti-Habsburg views.&lt;ref name=&quot;nicholls236237&quot;/&gt; From von Schönerer and his followers, Hitler adopted for the Nazi movement the ''Heil'' greeting, the ''Führer'' title, and the model of absolute party leadership.&lt;ref name=&quot;nicholls236237&quot;/&gt; Hitler was also impressed with the [[Populism|populist]] anti-Semitism and anti-liberal bourgeois agitation of [[Karl Lueger]], who as the mayor of Vienna during Hitler's time in the city used a rabble-rousing oratory style that appealed to the wider masses.&lt;ref name=&quot;nicholls159160&quot;/&gt; Unlike von Schönerer, however, Lueger was not a German nationalist, but a pro-Catholic Habsburg supporter.&lt;ref name=&quot;nicholls159160&quot;/&gt;

===Response to World War I and fascism===
During World War I, German sociologist [[Johann Plenge]] spoke of the rise of a &quot;National Socialism&quot; in Germany within what he termed the &quot;[[Spirit of 1914|ideas of 1914]]&quot; that were a declaration of war against the &quot;ideas of 1789&quot; (the [[French Revolution]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Martin Kitchen 2006. p. 205&quot;/&gt; According to Plenge, the &quot;ideas of 1789&quot; that included rights of man, democracy, individualism and liberalism were being rejected in favour of &quot;the ideas of 1914&quot; that included &quot;German values&quot; of duty, discipline, law, and order.&lt;ref name=&quot;Martin Kitchen 2006. p. 205&quot;/&gt; Plenge believed that ethnic solidarity (''[[Volksgemeinschaft]]'') would replace class division and that &quot;racial comrades&quot; would unite to create a socialist society in the struggle of &quot;proletarian&quot; Germany against &quot;capitalist&quot; Britain.&lt;ref name=&quot;Martin Kitchen 2006. p. 205&quot;/&gt; He believed that the &quot;Spirit of 1914&quot; manifested itself in the concept of the &quot;People's League of National Socialism&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bernd-Rüdiger Hüppauf 1997. p. 92&quot;/&gt; This National Socialism was a form of state socialism that rejected the &quot;idea of boundless freedom&quot; and promoted an economy that would serve the whole of Germany under the leadership of the state.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bernd-Rüdiger Hüppauf 1997. p. 92&quot;/&gt; This National Socialism was opposed to capitalism due to the components that were against &quot;the national interest&quot; of Germany, but insisted that National Socialism would strive for greater efficiency in the economy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bernd-Rüdiger Hüppauf 1997. p. 92&quot;/&gt; Plenge advocated an authoritarian rational ruling elite to develop National Socialism through a hierarchical [[Technocracy|technocratic]] state.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas Rohkrämer 2007. p. 130&quot;/&gt; Plenge's ideas formed the basis of Nazism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Martin Kitchen 2006. p. 205&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-R06610, Oswald Spengler.jpg|170px|left|[[Oswald Spengler]]]]
[[Oswald Spengler]], a German cultural philosopher, was a major influence on Nazism; although after 1933 Spengler became alienated from Nazism and was later condemned by the Nazis for criticizing Adolf Hitler.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated16&quot;/&gt; Spengler's conception of national socialism along with a number of his political views were shared by the Nazis and the [[Conservative Revolutionary movement]].&lt;ref name=autogenerated7 /&gt; Spengler's views were also popular amongst [[Italian fascism|Italian Fascists]], including [[Benito Mussolini]].&lt;ref name=&quot;encyclopedia15&quot;/&gt; 

Spengler's book ''[[The Decline of the West]]'' (1918) written during the final months of [[World War I]], addressed the claim of [[decadence]] of modern European civilization, whicht he claimed was caused by atomizing and irreligious individualization and [[cosmopolitanism]].&lt;ref name=autogenerated16 /&gt; Spengler's major thesis was that a law of historical development of cultures existed involving a cycle of birth, maturity, aging, and death when it reaches its final form of civilization.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated16&quot;/&gt; Upon reaching the point of civilization, a culture will lose its creative capacity and succumb to [[decadence]] until the emergence of &quot;[[barbarian]]s&quot; create a new epoch.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated16&quot;/&gt; Spengler considered the [[Western world]] as having succumbed to decadence of intellect, money, [[cosmopolitanism|cosmopolitan]] urban life, irreligious life, [[wiktionary:Atomization|atomized]] [[individualism|individualization]], and the end of biological fertility as well as &quot;spiritual&quot; fertility.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated16&quot;/&gt; He believed that the &quot;young&quot; German nation as an imperial power would inherit the legacy of [[Ancient Rome]], lead a restoration of value in &quot;[[Bloodline|blood]]&quot; and instinct, while the ideals of rationalism would be revealed as absurd.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated16&quot;/&gt;

Spengler's notions of &quot;Prussian socialism&quot; as described in his book ''[[Preussentum und Sozialismus]]'' (&quot;Prussiandom and Socialism&quot;, 1919), influenced Nazism and the [[Conservative Revolutionary movement]].&lt;ref name=autogenerated7/&gt; Spengler wrote: &quot;The meaning of socialism is that life is controlled not by the opposition between rich and poor, but by the rank that achievement and talent bestow. That is ''our'' freedom, freedom from the economic despotism of the individual.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated7&quot;/&gt; Spengler adopted the anti-English ideas addressed by Plenge and Sombart during World War I that condemned English liberalism and English parliamentarianism while advocating a national socialism that was free from [[Marxism]] and that would connect the individual to the state through [[Corporatism|corporatist]] organization.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated16&quot;/&gt; Spengler claimed that socialistic Prussian characteristics existed across Germany, including creativity, discipline, concern for the greater good, productivity and self-sacrifice.&lt;ref name=&quot;university17&quot;/&gt; He prescribed war as a necessity, saying &quot;War is the eternal form of higher human existence and states exist for war: they are the expression of the will to war.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;university18&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Dasdrittereich.jpg|140px|thumb|The book ''[[Das Dritte Reich]]'' (1923) translated as &quot;The Third Reich&quot;, by [[Arthur Moeller van den Bruck]].]]
Spengler's definition of socialism did not advocate a change to property relations.&lt;ref name=autogenerated7 /&gt; He denounced [[Marxism]] for seeking to train the proletariat to &quot;expropriate the expropriator&quot;, the capitalist, and then to let them live a life of leisure on this expropriation.&lt;ref name=&quot;H. Stuart Hughes 1992. p. 108&quot;/&gt; He claimed that &quot;Marxism is the capitalism of the working class&quot; and not true socialism.&lt;ref name=&quot;H. Stuart Hughes 1992. p. 108&quot;/&gt; True socialism, according to Spengler, would be in the form of corporatism, stating that &quot;local corporate bodies organized according to the importance of each occupation to the people as a whole; higher representation in stages up to a supreme council of the state; mandates revocable at any time; no organized parties, no professional politicians, no periodic elections.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;transaction&quot;/&gt;

[[Arthur Moeller van den Bruck]] who initially was the dominant figure of the Conservative Revolutionaries influenced Nazism.&lt;ref name=&quot;university19&quot;/&gt; He rejected [[reactionary]] conservatism, while proposing a new state, that he coined the &quot;Third Reich&quot;, which would unite all classes under [[authoritarian]] rule.&lt;ref name=&quot;macmillan&quot;/&gt; Van den Bruck advocated a combination of the nationalism of the right and the socialism of the left.&lt;ref name=&quot;millennial&quot;/&gt;

[[Fascism]] was a major influence on Nazism. The seizure of power by Italian Fascist leader Benito Mussolini in the [[March on Rome]] in 1922 drew admiration by Hitler who less than a month later had begun to model himself and the [[Nazi Party]] upon Mussolini and the Fascists.&lt;ref name=&quot;kershaw20&quot;/&gt; Hitler presented the Nazis as a German fascism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fulda, Bernhard 2009. p. 65&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Carlsten, F. L. 1982. p. 80&quot;/&gt; 
[[File:March on Rome.jpg|thumb|left|250px|[[Benito Mussolini]] (centre in suit with fists against body) along with other Fascist leader figures and [[Blackshirts]] during the [[March on Rome]].]]

In November 1923, the Nazis attempted a &quot;March on Berlin&quot; modelled upon the March on Rome that resulted in the failed [[Beer Hall Putsch]] in [[Munich]].&lt;ref name=&quot;dissolution&quot;/&gt; Other Nazis — especially more radical ones such as [[Gregor Strasser]], Joseph Goebbels and [[Heinrich Himmler]] — rejected Italian Fascism, accusing it of being too conservative or capitalist.&lt;ref name=&quot;university21&quot;/&gt; [[Alfred Rosenberg]] condemned Italian Fascism for being racially confused and having influences from philo-Semitism.&lt;ref name=&quot;stanley&quot;/&gt; Strasser criticized the policy of ''[[Führerprinzip]]'' as being created by Mussolini, and considered its presence in Nazism as a foreign imported idea.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stanley G. Payne 1995. p. 464&quot;/&gt; Throughout the relationship between Nazi Germany and Fascist Italy, a number of lower-ranking Nazis scornfully viewed fascism as a conservative movement that lacked a full revolutionary potential.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stanley G. Payne 1995. p. 464&quot;/&gt;

==Ideology==

From 1920 to 1923, Hitler formulated his ideology, then published it in 1925–26, as ''[[Mein Kampf]]'', a two-volume, biography and political manifesto.&lt;ref name=&quot;kershaw22&quot;/&gt;

Though Hitler for &quot;tactical&quot; reasons had rhetorically declared a 1920 party platform with [[Socialism|socialist]] platitudes &quot;unshakable,&quot; actually &quot;many paragraphs of the party program were obviously merely a demagogic appeal to the mood of the lower classes at a time when they were in bad straits and were sympathetic to radical and even socialist slogans...Point 11, for example...Point 12...nationalization...Point 16...communalization.... put in at the insistence of Drexler and Feder, who apparently really believed in the 'socialism' of National Socialism.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;William L. Shirer 1990 41&quot;/&gt;  In actual practice, such points were mere slogans, &quot;most of them forgotten by the time the party came to power.... the Nazi leader himself was later to be embarrassed when reminded of some of them.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;William L. Shirer 1990 41&quot;/&gt; Historian Conan Fischer argues that the Nazis were sincere in their use of the adjective ''socialist'', which they saw as inseparable from the adjective ''national'', and meant it as a socialism of the [[master race]], rather than the socialism of the &quot;underprivileged and oppressed seeking justice and equal rights.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;manchester&quot;/&gt;

===Social class===
In 1922, Adolf Hitler discredited other nationalist and racialist political parties as disconnected from the mass populace, especially lower and [[working class|working-class]] young people:

{{quote|The racialists were not capable of drawing the practical conclusions from correct theoretical judgements, especially in the Jewish Question. In this way, the German racialist movement developed a similar pattern to that of the 1880s and 1890s. As in those days, its leadership gradually fell into the hands of highly honourable, but fantastically naïve men of learning, professors, district counsellors, schoolmasters, and lawyers&amp;nbsp;— in short a bourgeois, idealistic, and refined class. It lacked the warm breath of the nation's youthful vigour.&lt;ref name=&quot;burleigh&quot;/&gt;}}

Despite many working-class supporters and members, the appeal of the [[Nazi Party]] was arguably more effective with the [[middle class]]. Moreover, the financial collapse of the [[White-collar worker|white collar]] middle-class of the 1920s figures much in their strong support of Nazism, thus the great percentage of declared middle-class support for the Nazis.&lt;ref name=&quot;Burleigh, 2000. p. 77&quot;/&gt; In the poor country that was the [[Weimar Republic]] of the early 1930s, the Nazi Party realised their socialist policies with food and shelter for the unemployed and the homeless — later recruited to the Brownshirt ''[[Sturmabteilung]]'' (SA — Storm Detachment).&lt;ref name=&quot;Burleigh, 2000. p. 77&quot;/&gt;

===Sex and gender===
{{Further2|[[Women in the Third Reich]]}}
[[File:Berlin Pink Triangle.JPG|thumb|125px|''Homophobia:'' Berlin Memorial to Homosexual Victims of the Holocaust; ''Totgeschlagen—Totgeschwiegen'' (Struck Dead—Hushed Up)]]
Nazi ideology advocated excluding women from political involvement and confining them to the spheres of &quot;[[Kinder, Küche, Kirche]]&quot; (Children, Kitchen, Church).{{citation needed|date=May 2012}}

====Opposition to homosexuality====
{{further2|[[Persecution of homosexuals in Nazi Germany and the Holocaust]]}}

After the Night of the Long Knives, Hitler promoted Himmler and the [[SS]], who then zealously suppressed homosexuality, saying: &quot;We must exterminate these people root and branch ... the homosexual must be eliminated.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;plant&quot;/&gt; In 1936, Himmler established the &quot;Reichszentrale zur Bekämpfung der Homosexualität und Abtreibung&quot; (&quot;Reich Central Office for the Combating of Homosexuality and Abortion&quot;).&lt;ref name=&quot;Homosexualität und Staatsräson. Männlichkeit, Homophobie und Politik in Deutschland 1900-1945&quot;/&gt; The Nazi régime incarcerated some 100,000 homosexuals during the 1930s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Holocaust: Gay activists press for German apology&quot;/&gt; As concentration camp prisoners, homosexual men were forced to wear [[pink triangle]] badges.&lt;ref name=&quot;international&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;homosexuals&quot;/&gt;

===Racial policy===
{{further2|[[Nazism and race]]|[[Racial policy of Nazi Germany]]}}
[[File:NordischNordic.JPG|thumb|150px|left|The Master Race: the ''Meyers Blitz-Lexikon'' ([[Weimar Republic|Leipzig, 1932]]) depicts German war hero [[Karl von Müller]] as an exemplar Nordic type of the [[Herrenvolk]].]]
[[File:Generalplan Ost map.tiff|thumb|Europe, with pre-WW2 borders, showing the extension of ''[[Generalplan Ost]]'', i.e., the massive depopulation and ethnic cleansing within German ''Lebensraum''.]]
Several of the founders and leaders of the Nazi Party were members of the ''[[Thule-Gesellschaft]]'' (Thule Society), who romanticized Aryan race superstitions with ritual and theology.&lt;ref name=&quot;goodrick&quot;/&gt; Originally, derived from the ''[[Germanenorden]]'', the Thule Society shared the racist superstitions of [[Ariosophy]] and the society's activities consisted of [[anti-Semitism]] lectures and excursions of Germanic antiquity.&lt;ref name=&quot;goodrick23&quot;/&gt; The Thule Society member, [[Dietrich Eckart]], coached Adolf Hitler in public speaking, and Hitler later dedicated ''Mein Kampf'' to Eckart.&lt;ref name=&quot;goodrick24&quot;/&gt; The DAP had initial support from the Thule Society — but after Hitler had taken over the Party, by denigrating their superstitious approach to politics, the society's members were quickly marginalised to allow the party to become a mass movement.&lt;ref name=&quot;goodrick25&quot;/&gt; 

Hitler viewed individual races as being part of a hierarchy, and he espoused the &quot;aristocratic idea of nature&quot;. This view led to his assertion of superior and higher qualities of the Aryan race.&lt;ref name=&quot;Joseph W. Bendersky 2007. p. 32&quot;/&gt; Hitler claimed to have first developed his worldview while in Vienna from 1907 to 1913, concluding that the [[Austria-Hungary|Austro–Hungarian Empire]] comprised racial, religious, and cultural hierarchies; he viewed &quot;Aryans&quot; as the ultimate master race inhabiting the top, whilst Jews and [[Romani people|Gypsies]] were at bottom.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kershaw&quot;/&gt; Other research suggests that Hitler's virulent antisemitism was a post-war development, influenced from the [[Russian civil war]].&lt;ref name=&quot;apprenticeship&quot;/&gt; The idea of the Russian roots of Nazism has been explored by [[Walter Laqueur]]&lt;ref name=&quot;weidenfeld&quot;/&gt; and Michael Kellogg.&lt;ref name=&quot;socialism&quot;/&gt;

The racist subject of Nazism was ''[[Volk|Das Volk]]'', the German people living under continual cultural attack by [[Judeo-Bolshevism]]. Nazi Party leadership sought to unify the ''Volk'', and strongly encouraged [[stoicism]], self-discipline and self-sacrifice to achieve final victory.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated17&quot;/&gt; Nazi propagandist [[Joseph Goebbels]] frequently employed antisemitic rhetoric to underline this view: &quot;The Jew is the enemy and destroyer of the purity of blood, the conscious destroyer of our race ... As socialists, we are opponents of the Jews, because we see, in the Hebrews, the incarnation of [[capitalism]], of the misuse of the nation's goods.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;thosedamnednazis&quot;/&gt; {{-}}

In the [[Pseudoscience|pseudoscientific]] treatise, ''[[The Myth of the Twentieth Century]]'' — according to Terrence Ball and Richard Bellamy, the second-most important book to Nazism, after ''Mein Kampf''&lt;ref name=&quot;university26&quot;/&gt; — [[Reichstag]] Secretary, [[Alfred Rosenberg]] proposed that, &quot;[F]rom a northern centre of creation which, without postulating an actual submerged Atlantic continent, we may call [[Atlantis]], swarms of warriors once fanned out, in obedience to the ever-renewed and incarnate [[Nordic race|Nordic]] longing for distance to conquer and space to shape&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;jahrhunderts&quot;/&gt; 

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-F0918-0201-001, KZ Treblinka, Lageplan (Zeichnung) II.jpg|thumb|left|220px|Sketch plan of [[Treblinka extermination camp]]. Between the years 1942 and 1943, more than 850,000 Jews were murdered there and only 54 survived.]]

According to Nazism, through struggle and proper &quot;breeding&quot;, the &quot;strong&quot; would subdue the &quot;weak&quot; and rise to dominance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Joseph W. Bendersky 2007. p. 32&quot;/&gt; For example, Nazi policy since 1920 emphasized that only people of &quot;German blood&quot; could be considered German citizens thus excluding people of Jewish descent,&lt;ref name=&quot;bendersky&quot;/&gt; a view that ultimately resulted in the killing of millions of people in the [[Holocaust]]. 

[[File:Buchenwald Corpses 60623.jpg|thumb|220px|A wagon piled high with corpses outside the crematorium in [[Buchenwald concentration camp]]]]

To maintain the &quot;purity and strength&quot; of the Aryan race, the Nazis sought to [[Genocide|exterminate]] Jews, [[Romani people|Romani]], and the [[Physical disability|physically]] and [[Developmental disability|mentally disabled]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Simone Gigliotti 2005. p. 14&quot;/&gt; Other groups deemed &quot;[[Degeneration|degenerate]]&quot; and &quot;[[Asociality|asocial]]&quot; who were not targeted for extermination, but received [[Social exclusion|exclusionary treatment]] by the Nazi state, included [[Homosexuality|homosexuals]], [[Black people in Nazi Germany|blacks]], [[Jehovah's Witnesses]] and political opponents.&lt;ref name=&quot;Simone Gigliotti 2005. p. 14&quot;/&gt; One of Hitler's ambitions at the start of the war was to [[Generalplan Ost|exterminate]], expel, or enslave most or all [[Slav]]s from central and eastern Europe (i.e., [[Nazi crimes against ethnic Poles|Poles]], Russians, Ukrainians, etc.) so as to make [[Lebensraum|living space]] for German settlers.&lt;ref name=&quot;google&quot;/&gt;

Hitler declared that racial conflict against Jews was necessary to save Germany from suffering under them and dismissed concerns about such conflict being inhumane or an injustice:

&lt;blockquote&gt;We may be inhumane, but if we rescue Germany we have achieved the greatest deed in the world. We may work injustice, but if we rescue Germany then we have removed the greatest injustice in the world. We may be immoral, but if our people is rescued we have opened the way for morality.&lt;ref name=&quot;koenigsberg&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In Germany, the idea of creating a master-race resulted in efforts to &quot;purify' the ''Deutsche Volk'' through [[Nazi eugenics|eugenics]]; its culmination was [[compulsory sterilization]] or [[involuntary euthanasia]] of physically or mentally disabled people. The ideological justification was [[Adolf Hitler]]'s view of [[Sparta]] (11th c.–195 BC) as the original ''Völkisch'' state; he praised their dispassionate destruction of congenitally deformed infants in maintaining racial purity:&lt;ref name=&quot;pathological&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Social Darwinism in European and American Thought, 1860–1945: nature as model and nature as threat&quot;/&gt;

The number of Germans of African descent was low; however, some of them were enlisted into Nazi organisations like the [[Hitler Youth]] and the ''Wehrmacht''.&lt;ref name=&quot;experiences&quot;/&gt;

===Religion===
{{Further|Religious aspects of Nazism|Religion in Nazi Germany|Positive Christianity|German Christians|Kreuz und Adler}}
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 102-15234, Berlin, Luthertag.jpg|thumb|Members of the [[German Christians]] organization celebrating ''Luther-Day'' in Berlin in 1933, speech by bishop Hossenfelder]]
[[File:Orsen.jpg|thumb|Hitler with [[Cesare Orsenigo]], the [[Catholic Church]]'s [[nuncio to Germany]], in 1935.]]

The [[National Socialist Program|Nazi Party Programme]] of 1920 guaranteed freedom for all religious denominations not hostile to the State and endorsed [[Positive Christianity]] to combat “the Jewish-materialist spirit”.&lt;ref name=&quot;documents&quot;/&gt; It was a modified version of Christianity which emphasized racial purity and nationalism.{{sfn|McNab|2009|p=182}} The Nazis were aided by theologians, such as, Dr. [[Ernst Bergmann (philosopher)]]. Bergmann, in his work, ''Die 25 Thesen der Deutschreligion'' (Twenty-five Points of the German Religion), held that the Old Testament and portions of the New Testament of the Bible were inaccurate. He claimed that Jesus was not a Jew and of Aryan origin, and that Adolf Hitler was the new messiah.{{sfn|McNab|2009|p=182}} At the same time the Nazis utilized Protestant [[Martin Luther]] in their propaganda. Nazis publicly displayed an original of Luther's ''On the Jews and their Lies'' during the annual Nuremberg rallies.&lt;ref name=&quot;understandably&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;baylor&quot;/&gt; The Nazis endorsed the pro-Nazi Protestant [[German Christians]] organization.

The Nazis were initially highly hostile to Catholics because most Catholics supported the [[German Centre Party]]. Catholics opposed the Nazis' promotion of sterilization of those deemed inferior, and the Catholic Church forbid its members to vote for the Nazis. In 1933, extensive Nazi violence occurred against Catholics due to the their association with the Centre Party and their opposition to the Nazi regime's sterilization laws.&lt;ref name=&quot;international27&quot;/&gt; The Nazis demanded that Catholics declare their loyalty to the German state.&lt;ref name=&quot;Robert Anthony Krieg 2004. p. 4&quot;/&gt; In propaganda, the Nazis used elements of Germany's Catholic history, in particular the German Catholic [[Teutonic Knights]] and their campaigns in Eastern Europe. The Nazis identified them as &quot;sentinels&quot; in the East against &quot;Slavic chaos&quot;, though beyond that symbolism the influence of the Teutonic Knights on Nazism was limited.&lt;ref name=&quot;interaction&quot;/&gt; Hitler also admitted that the model of the Nazis' night rallies was inspired by the Catholic rituals he witnessed during his Catholic upbringing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Roger Griffin 2005. p. 85&quot;/&gt; The Nazis did seek official reconciliation with the Catholic Church and endorsed the creation of the pro-Nazi Catholic ''[[Kreuz und Adler]]'' organization that supported a [[national Catholicism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Robert Anthony Krieg 2004. p. 4&quot;/&gt; On 20 July 1933, a successful concordat (''[[Reichskonkordat]]'') was signed between Nazi Germany and the Catholic Church which demanded loyalty of German Catholics to the German state in exchange for acceptance of the Catholic Church in Germany. The Catholic Church then ended its ban on members supporting the Nazi Party.&lt;ref name=&quot;Robert Anthony Krieg 2004. p. 4&quot;/&gt;

Historian [[Michael Burleigh]] claims that Nazism used Christianity for political purposes, but such use required that &quot;fundamental tenets were stripped out, but the remaining diffuse religious emotionality had its uses&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Roger Griffin 2005. p. 85&quot;/&gt; Burleigh claims that Nazism's conception of spirituality was &quot;self-conciously pagan and primitive&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Roger Griffin 2005. p. 85&quot;/&gt; However, historian [[Roger Griffin]] rejects the claim that Nazism was primarily pagan, noting that although there were some influential neo-paganists in the Nazi Party, such as [[Heinrich Himmler]] and [[Alfred Rosenberg]], they represented a minority and their views did not influence Nazi ideology beyond its use for symbolism; its noted that Hitler denounced Germanic paganism in ''Mein Kampf'' and condemned Rosenburg's and Himmler's paganism as &quot;nonsense&quot;.{{sfn|Speer|1971|p=141, 212}}&lt;ref name=&quot;totalitarianism&quot;/&gt;

===Economics===
{{Further|Economy of Nazi Germany}}
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 102-15750, Ausstellung &quot;Deutsches Volk-Deutsche Arbeit&quot;.jpg|thumb|''Deutsches Volk–Deutsche Arbeit:'' German People, German Work, the alliance of worker and work. (1934)]]

Hitler believed that private ownership was useful in that it encouraged creative competition and technical innovation, but insisted that it had to conform to national interests and be &quot;productive&quot; rather than &quot;parasitical&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;R.J. Overy 2004. p. 403&quot;/&gt; Private property rights were conditional upon the economic mode of use, if it did not advance Nazi economic goals then the state could nationalize it.&lt;ref name=&quot;economic573&quot;/&gt; Although the Nazis [[Privatisation|privatised]] public properties and public services, they also increased economic state control.&lt;ref name=&quot;guillebaud&quot;/&gt; Under Nazi economics, free competition and self-regulating markets diminished; nevertheless, Hitler's [[Social Darwinism|social Darwinist]] beliefs made him reluctant to entirely disregard business competition and private property as economic engines.&lt;ref name=&quot;economics&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;university28&quot;/&gt;

To tie farmers to their land, selling agricultural land was prohibited.{{citation needed|date=May 2012}} Farm ownership was nominally private, but discretion over operations and residual income were proscribed.{{citation needed|date=May 2012}} That was achieved by granting business monopoly rights to marketing boards, to control production and prices with a quota system.{{citation needed|date=May 2012}}

====Anti-communism====
Historians [[Ian Kershaw]] and [[Joachim Fest]] argue that in post-[[World War I]] Germany, the Nazis were one of many nationalist and fascist political parties contending for the leadership of Germany's [[anti-communism|anti-communist]] movement. The Nazis claimed that communism was dangerous to the well-being of nations because of its intention to dissolve [[private property]], its support of [[class conflict]], its aggression against the [[Middle-class|middle class]], its hostility to small businessmen, and its [[atheism]].&lt;ref name=autogenerated20 /&gt; Nazism rejected [[class conflict]]-based [[socialism]] and economic [[egalitarianism]], favouring instead a [[Social stratification|stratified]] economy with [[social class]]es based on merit and talent, retaining [[private property]], and the creation of national solidarity that transcends class distinction.&lt;ref name=autogenerated11 /&gt;

During the 1920s, Hitler urged disparate Nazi factions to unite in opposition to &quot;[[Jewish Bolshevism|Jewish Marxism]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Adolf Hitler&quot;/&gt; Hitler asserted that the &quot;three vices&quot; of &quot;Jewish [[Marxism]]&quot; were [[democracy]], [[pacifism]] and [[internationalism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Hitler, the Germans, and the Final Solution&quot;/&gt;

In 1930, Hitler said: &quot;Our adopted term ‘Socialist' has nothing to do with Marxian Socialism. Marxism is anti-property; true Socialism is not.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;university29&quot;/&gt; In 1942, Hitler privately said: &quot;I absolutely insist on protecting private property ... we must encourage private initiative&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hitler's Table Talk, 1941–1944: His Private Conversations&quot;/&gt;

During the late 1930s and the 1940s, anti-communist regimes and groups that supported Nazism included the [[Falange]] in [[Spain]]; the [[Vichy France|Vichy regime]] and the [[33rd Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS Charlemagne (1st French)]] in France; and the [[Cliveden Set]], [[Lord Halifax]], and associates of [[Neville Chamberlain]] in Britain.&lt;ref name=&quot;carroll&quot;/&gt;

====Anti-capitalism====
[[File:Der Stürmer Christmas 1929.jpg|thumb|Nazi anti-Semitic and anti-capitalist theme in a cartoon telling Germans not to buy from Jewish shops. It portrays a stereotypical depiction of Jews as affluent capitalists.]]

The Nazis argued that capitalism damages nations due to [[international finance]], the economic dominance of [[big business]], and Jewish influences.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated20&quot;/&gt; Nazi propaganda posters in [[working-class]] districts emphasized anti-capitalism, such as one that said: &quot;The maintenance of a rotten industrial system has nothing to do with nationalism. I can love Germany and hate capitalism.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;publishers30&quot;/&gt;

Hitler, both in public and in private, expressed strong disdain for capitalism, accusing modern capitalism of holding nations ransom in the interests of a parasitic [[Cosmopolitanism|cosmopolitan]] [[rentier]] class.&lt;ref name=&quot;R.J. Overy 2004. p. 399&quot;/&gt; He opposed free-market capitalism's profit-seeking impulses and desired an economy in which community interests would be upheld.&lt;ref name=&quot;R.J. Overy 2004. p. 403&quot;/&gt; He distrusted capitalism for being unreliable, due to its [[Egotism|egotistic]] nature, and he preferred a state-directed economy that is subordinated to the interests of the [[Volk]].&lt;ref name=&quot;R.J. Overy 2004. p. 399&quot;/&gt; Hitler told a party leader in 1934, &quot;The economic system of our day is the creation of the Jews.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;R.J. Overy 2004. p. 399&quot; /&gt; Hitler said to [[Benito Mussolini]] that &quot;Capitalism had run its course&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;R.J. Overy 2004. p. 399&quot;/&gt; Hitler also said that the business bourgeoisie &quot;know nothing except their profit. 'Fatherland' is only a word for them.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;dictators&quot;/&gt; Hitler admired [[Napoleon]] as a role model for his anti-conservative, anti-capitalist and anti-bourgeois attitudes.&lt;ref name=&quot;hanfstaengl&quot;/&gt;

In ''Mein Kampf'', Hitler effectively supported [[mercantilism]], in the belief that economic resources from their respective territories should be seized by force; he believed that the policy of ''[[Lebensraum]]'' would provide Germany with such economically valuable territories.&lt;ref name=&quot;R.J. Overy 2004. p. 402&quot;/&gt; He believed that the only means to maintain economic security was to have direct control over resources rather than being forced to rely on world trade.&lt;ref name=&quot;dictators31&quot;/&gt; He claimed that war to gain such resources was the only means to surpass the failing capitalist economic system.&lt;ref name=&quot;R.J. Overy 2004. p. 402&quot;/&gt;

A number of other Nazis held strong revolutionary socialist and anti-capitalist beliefs, most prominently [[Ernst Röhm]], the leader of the [[Sturmabteilung]] (SA).&lt;ref name=&quot;factionalism&quot;/&gt; Röhm claimed that the Nazis' rise to power constituted a national revolution, but insisted that a socialist &quot;second revolution&quot; was required for Nazi ideology to be fulfilled.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nyomarkay, Joseph 1967 p. 130&quot;/&gt; Röhm's SA began attacks against individuals deemed to be associated with conservative reaction.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nyomarkay, Joseph 1967 p. 130&quot;/&gt; Hitler saw Röhm's independent actions as violating and possibly threatening his leadership, as well as jeopardizing the regime by alienating conservative President [[Paul von Hindenburg]] and the conservative-oriented German Army.&lt;ref name=&quot;Joseph Nyomarkay 1967. p. 133&quot;/&gt; This resulted in Hitler purging Röhm and other radical members of the SA.&lt;ref name=&quot;Joseph Nyomarkay 1967. p. 133&quot;/&gt; Another radical Nazi, Propaganda Minister [[Joseph Goebbels]] adamantly stressed the socialist character of Nazism, and claimed in his diary that if he were to pick between [[Bolshevism]] and capitalism, he said &quot;in final analysis&quot;, &quot;it would be better for us to go down with Bolshevism than live in eternal slavery under capitalism.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;disciples&quot;/&gt;

==See also==
{{div col}}
* [[Antisemitism]]
* [[Consequences of German Nazism]]
* [[Denazification]]
* [[Fascism]]
* [[Fascism and ideology]]
* [[Final Solution]]
* [[Functionalism versus intentionalism]]
* [[German nationalism]]
* [[Holocaust]]
* [[Nationalism]]
* [[Nazi occultism]]
* [[Neo-Nazism]]
* [[New Order (Nazism)]]
* [[Racism]]
* [[Women in the Third Reich]]
{{div col end}}

==References==

===Notes===
{{reflist|2|refs=

&lt;ref name=&quot;Adolf Hitler 2010. p. 287&quot;&gt;Hitler, Adolf, ''Mein Kampf'', Bottom of the Hill Publishing, 2010. p. 287.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Adolf Hitler p. 170&quot;&gt;Hitler, Adolf in Domarus, Max and Patrick Romane, eds. ''The Essential Hitler: Speeches and Commentary'', Waulconda, Illinois: Bolchazi-Carducci Publishers, Inc., 2007, p. 170.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Adolf Hitler&quot;&gt;&quot;They must unite, [Hitler] said, to defeat the common enemy, Jewish Marxism.&quot; ''A New Beginning,'' Adolf Hitler, ''Völkischer Beobachter.'' February 1925. Cited in: {{Cite book|last=Toland |first=John |year=1992 |title=Adolf Hitler |publisher=Anchor Books |page=207 |isbn=0-385-03724-4 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;apprenticeship&quot;&gt;Brigitte Hamann, ''Hitler's Vienna: A Dictator's Apprenticeship'', New York: Oxford University Press, 1999. pp. 347-359.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;Blamires, Cyprian; Jackson, Paul. ''World Fascism: A Historical Encyclopedia: Volume 1''. Santa Barbara, California, USA: ABC-CLIO, Inc, 2006. p. 61.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated11&quot;&gt;Bendersky, Joseph W. ''A History of Nazi Germany: 1919-1945''. 2nd ed. Burnham Publishers, 2000. p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated12&quot;&gt;Gerwarth, Robert, ''The Bismarck Myth: Weimar Germany and the Legacy of the Iron Chancellor'', p. 131.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated14&quot;&gt;Gerwarth, Robert, ''The Bismarck Myth: Weimar Germany and the Legacy of the Iron Chancellor'', Oxford, England; New York, New York: Oxford University Press, p. 150.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated16&quot;&gt;Blamires, Cyprian; Jackson, Paul. ''World Fascism: A Historical Encyclopedia: Volume 1''. Santa Barbara, California, USA: ABC-CLIO, Inc, 2006. p. 628.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated17&quot;&gt;[[Ian Kershaw]], ''Hitler: A Profile in Power'', first chapter &quot;The Power of the Idea&quot;, London, (2001) [1991].&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated18&quot;&gt;Ryback, Timothy W. ''Hitler's Private Library: The Books That Shaped His Life'', New York; Toronto: Vintage Books, 2010. p. 129&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated20&quot;&gt;Bendersky, Joseph W. ''A History of Nazi Germany: 1919-1945''. 2nd ed. Burnham Publishers, 2000. p. 72.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated4&quot;&gt;Stackelberg, Roderick; Winkle, Sally Anne, ''The Nazi Germany Sourcebook: An Anthology of Texts'', London: Routledge, 2002. p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated6&quot;&gt;Blamires, Cyprian; Jackson, Paul. ''World Fascism: A Historical Encyclopedia: Volume 1''. Santa Barbara, California, USA: ABC-CLIO, Inc, 2006. p. 62.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated7&quot;&gt;Winkler, Heinrich August and Alexander Sager, ''Germany: The Long Road West'', English ed. 2006, p. 414.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated8&quot;&gt;Stackelberg, Roderick; Winkle, Sally Anne. ''The Nazi Germany Sourcebook: An Anthology of Texts'', London: Routledge, 2002. p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;baylor&quot;&gt;[[Marc H. Ellis|Ellis, Marc H]]. [http://www3.baylor.edu/American_Jewish/everythingthatusedtobehere/resources/PowerPoints/Christian%20Anti-Semitism%20(part%202).ppt &quot;Hitler and the Holocaust, Christian Anti-Semitism&quot;], Baylor University Center for American and Jewish Studies, Spring 2004, slide 14. Also see [http://elsinore.cis.yale.edu/lawweb/avalon/imt/proc/04-29-46.htm#herrwerth Nuremberg Trial Proceedings], Vol. 12, p. 318, Avalon Project, Yale Law School, April 19, 1946.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;bendersky&quot;&gt;Joseph W. Bendersky. ''A Concise History of Nazi Germany'', 2007. p. 33.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Bernd-Rüdiger Hüppauf 1997. p. 92&quot;&gt;Hüppauf, Bernd-Rüdiger ''War, Violence, and the Modern Condition'', Berlin: Walter de Gruyter &amp; Co., 1997. p. 92.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Burleigh, 2000. p. 77&quot;&gt;Burleigh, Michael. ''The Third Reich: A New History'', New York, USA: Hill and Wang, 2000. p. 77.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;burleigh&quot;&gt;Burleigh, Michael. ''The Third Reich: A New History'', New York, USA: Hill and Wang, 2000. pp. 76-77.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Carlsten, F. L. 1982. p. 80&quot;&gt;Carlsten, F. L. ''The Rise of Fascism''. 2nd ed. University of California Press, 1982. p. 80.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;carroll&quot;&gt;Carroll Quigley, ''Tragedy and Hope'', 1966. p. 619.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;chancellor&quot;&gt;Gerwarth, Robert, ''The Bismarck Myth: Weimar Germany and the Legacy of the Iron Chancellor'', p. 149.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;chancellor8&quot;&gt;Gerwarth, Robert, ''The Bismarck Myth: Weimar Germany and the Legacy of the Iron Chancellor'', p. 54.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;commentary&quot;&gt;Adolf Hitler, Max Domarus. ''The Essential Hitler: Speeches and Commentary''. pp. 171, 172-173.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;communism&quot;&gt;Furet, François, ''Passing of an Illusion: The Idea of Communism in the Twentieth Century'', 1999. p. 191.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;constructing&quot;&gt;Keith H. Pickus. ''Constructing Modern Identities: Jewish University Students in Germany, 1815-1914''. Detroit, Michigan, USA: Wayne State University Press, 1999. p. 86.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;davidson&quot;&gt;Eugene Davidson. ''The Unmaking of Adolf Hitler'', 2004. p. 117.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;dictator&quot;&gt;David Welch. ''Hitler: Profile of a Dictator''. 2nd edition. New York, New York, USA: UCL Press, 2001. pp. 13-14.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;dictator11&quot;&gt;David Welch. ''Hitler: Profile of a Dictator'', 2001. p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;dictators&quot;&gt;Overy, R.J., ''The Dictators: Hitler's Germany and Stalin's Russia'', W. W. Norton &amp; Company, Inc., 2004. p. 230.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;dictators31&quot;&gt;Overy, R.J., ''The Dictators: Hitler's Germany and Stalin's Russia'', W. W. Norton &amp; Company, Inc., 2004. p. 402&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- &lt;ref name=&quot;dictatorship&quot;&gt;MacGregor Knox. ''Common Destiny: Dictatorship, Foreign Policy, and War in Fascist Italy and Nazi Germany''. Cambridge, England, UK: Cambridge University Press, 2000. p. 208.&lt;/ref&gt; --&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;dictionary&quot;&gt;[[Walter John Raymond]]. ''Dictionary of Politics'', 1992. p. 327.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;disciples&quot;&gt;Read, Anthony, ''The Devil's Disciples: Hitler's Inner Circle'', 1st American ed. New York, New York: W. W. Norton &amp; Company, 2004. p. 142&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;dissolution&quot;&gt;David Jablonsky. ''The Nazi Party in Dissolution: Hitler and the Verbotzeit, 1923–1925''. London, England, UK; Totowa, New Jersey, USA: Frank Cass and Company Ltd., 1989. pp. 20–26, 30&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;documents&quot;&gt;J Noakes and G Pridham, ''Documents on Nazism, 1919-1945'', London 1974&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;economic573&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal | author=Peter Temin | title= | journal=Economic History Review, New Series | volume=44| issue=4 | pages=573–593 | date=November 1991&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;economics&quot;&gt;Barkai, Avaraham 1990. ''Nazi Economics: Ideology, Theory and Policy.'' Oxford Berg Publisher.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;education&quot;&gt;Lisa Pine. ''Education in Nazi Germany''. Oxford, England, UK; New York, New York, USA: Berg, 2011. p. 5.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;encyclopedia&quot;&gt;L. L. Snyder, ''Encyclopedia Of The Third Reich'', Wordsworth Editions Ltd, 1998. p. 245&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;encyclopedia15&quot;&gt;Blamires, Cyprian; Jackson, Paul. ''World Fascism: A Historical Encyclopedia: Volume 1'', 2006. p. 629.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;encyclopedia7&quot;&gt;Cyprian Blamires. ''World Fascism: A Historical Encyclopedia, Volume 1''. Santa Barbara, California, USA: ABC-CLIO, Inc., 2006. p. 542.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;encyclopedia9&quot;&gt;Blamires, Cyprian and Paul Jackson, ''World Fascism: A Historical Encyclopedia: Volume 1'', 2006. p. 126.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;evolution&quot;&gt;Peter J. Bowler. ''Evolution: The History of an Idea'', 1989. p. 305.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;experiences&quot;&gt;Clarence Lusane. ''Hitler's Black Victims: The Historical Experiences of Afro-Germans, European Blacks, Africans, and African Americans in the Nazi Era''. Routledge, 2002. pp. 112, 113, 189.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;factionalism&quot;&gt;Nyomarkay, Joseph, ''Charisma and Factionalism in the Nazi Party'', Minnesota University Press, 1967. p. 132&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;foundations&quot;&gt;Browder, George C., ''Foundations of the Nazi Police State: The Formation of Sipo and SD'', paperback, Lexington, Kentucky, USA: Kentucky University Press, 2004. p. 202.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;François Furet 1999. pp. 191-192&quot;&gt;Furet, François, ''Passing of an Illusion: The Idea of Communism in the Twentieth Century'', Chicago, Illinois' London, England: University of Chicago Press, 1999. ISBN 0-226-27340-7, pp. 191-192.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- &lt;ref name=&quot;Frank McDonough 2003. p. 64&quot;&gt;Frank McDonough. ''Hitler and the Rise of the Nazi Party''. Pearson/Longman, 2003. p. 64.&lt;/ref&gt; --&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;friedlander&quot;&gt;Henry Friedlander. ''The Origins of Nazi Genocide: From Euthanasia to the Final Solution''. Chapel Hill, North Carolina, USA: University of North Carolina Press, 1995. p. 5.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Fritzsche, Peter 1998&quot;&gt;Fritzsche, Peter. ''Germans into Nazis'', Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press, 1998; Eatwell, Roger, ''Fascism, A History'', Viking-Penguin, 1996. pp. xvii-xxiv, 21, 26–31, 114–140, 352. [[Roger Griffin|Griffin, Roger]],  &quot;Revolution from the Right: Fascism,&quot; in David Parker, ed., ''Revolutions and the Revolutionary Tradition in the West 1560-1991'', London: Routledge, 2000&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Fulda, Bernhard 2009. p. 65&quot;&gt;Fulda, Bernhard. ''Press and Politics in the Weimar Republic''. Oxford University Press, 2009. p. 65.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;goodrick&quot;&gt;Goodrick-Clarke 1985, p. 149 and 2003. p. 114.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;goodrick23&quot;&gt;Goodrick-Clarke (2002). pp. 114-117.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;goodrick24&quot;&gt;Goodrick-Clarke 2002. p. 117.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;goodrick25&quot;&gt;Goodrick-Clarke (1985). pp. 150, 51.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;google&quot;&gt;[[William W. Hagen]] (2012). &quot;''[http://books.google.cz/books?id=zBgr3kL-PP4C&amp;pg=&amp;dq&amp;hl=en#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false German History in Modern Times: Four Lives of the Nation]''&quot;. Cambridge University Press. p. 313. ISBN 0-521-19190-4&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;guardian&quot;&gt;George Sylvester Viereck. ''The Guardian''. 1923. http://www.guardian.co.uk/theguardian/2007/sep/17/greatinterviews1&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;guillebaud&quot;&gt;Guillebaud, Claude W. 1939. ''The Economic Recovery of Germany 1933-1938''. London: MacMillan and Co. Limited.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;H. Stuart Hughes 1992. p. 108&quot;&gt;Hughes, H. Stuart, ''Oswald Spengler'', New Brunswick, New Jersey: Transaction Publishers, 1992. p. 108.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;hanfstaengl&quot;&gt;''Hitler's Piano Player: The Rise and Fall of Ernst Hanfstaengl: Confidant of Hitler'', Ally of FDR, New York, New York: Carroll and Graf Publishers, 2004. p. 284.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Hitler, the Germans, and the Final Solution&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|last=Kershaw |first=Ian |year=2008 |title=Hitler, the Germans, and the Final Solution |publisher=Yale University Press |page=53 |isbn=0-300-12427-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Hitler's Table Talk, 1941–1944: His Private Conversations&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|last=Hitler |first=A. |coauthors=transl. Norman Cameron, R. H. Stevens; intro. H. R. Trevor-Roper |title=Hitler's Table Talk, 1941–1944: His Private Conversations |publisher=Enigma Books |year=2000 |isbn=1-929631-05-7 |pages=162–163 |chapter=March 24, 1942 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Holocaust: Gay activists press for German apology&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4158/is_/ai_n14142669|title=Holocaust: Gay activists press for German apology|last=Bennetto|first=Jason|date=1997-11-01|work=[[The Independent]]|accessdate=2008-12-26}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Homosexualität und Staatsräson. Männlichkeit, Homophobie und Politik in Deutschland 1900-1945&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|last=Pretzel|first=Andreas|chapter=Vom Staatsfeind zum Volksfeind. Zur Radikalisierung der Homosexuellenverfolgung im Zusammenwirken von Polizei und Justiz|editor-last=Zur Nieden|editor-first=Susanne|publisher=Campus Verlag|location=Frankfurt/M.|title=Homosexualität und Staatsräson. Männlichkeit, Homophobie und Politik in Deutschland 1900-1945|year=2005|page=236|url=http://books.google.de/books?id=HaZwHeBm2lkC&amp;pg=PA236&amp;lpg=PA236#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false|isbn=978-3-593-37749-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;homosexuals&quot;&gt;Plant, Richard, ''The Pink Triangle: The Nazi War Against Homosexuals'', Owl Books, 1988. ISBN 0-8050-0600-1.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;interaction&quot;&gt;Ausma Cimdiņa, Jonathan Osmond. ''Power and Culture: Hegemony, Interaction and Dissent''. PLUS-Pisa University Press, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;international&quot;&gt;''The Holocaust Chronicle'', Publications International Ltd. p. 108.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;international27&quot;&gt;Robert Anthony Krieg. ''Catholic Theologians in Nazi Germany''. London, England, UK: Continuum International Publishing Group, 2004. pp. 4-8.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Jack Fischel 1998. p. 5&quot;&gt;Jack Fischel. ''The Holocaust''. Westport, Connecticut, USA: Greenwood Press, 1998. p. 5.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;jahrhunderts&quot;&gt;Alfred Rosenberg: Der Mythus des 20. Jahrhunderts. Eine Wertung der seelisch-geistigen Gestaltenkämpfe unserer Zeit, 1-34. Aufl., München 1934&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Jeffrey S. Gaab 2008. p. 61&quot;&gt;Gaab, Jeffrey S., ''Munich: Hofbräuhaus &amp; History: Beer, Culture, &amp; Politics'', 2nd ed. New York City: Peter Lang Publishing, Inc, 2008. p. 61.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;JFrage&quot;&gt;&quot;THHP Short Essay: What Was the Final Solution?&quot;. Holocaust-History.org, July 2004, webpage: [http://www.holocaust-history.org/short-essays/final-solution.shtml HoloHist-Final]: notes that [[Hermann Göring]] used the term in his order of July 31, 1941 to [[Reinhard Heydrich]], chief of the [[Reich Main Security Office]] (RSHA).&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Jonathan Olsen 1999. p. 62&quot;&gt;Jonathan Olsen. ''Nature and Nationalism: Right-wing Ecology and the Politics of Identity in Contemporary Germany''. New York, New York, USA: Palgrave Macmillan, 1999. p. 62.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Joseph Nyomarkay 1967. p. 133&quot;&gt;Nyomarkay, Joseph, ''Charisma and Factionalism in the Nazi Party'', Minnesota University Press, 1967. p. 133&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Joseph W. Bendersky 2007. p. 32&quot;&gt;Joseph W. Bendersky. ''A Concise History of Nazi Germany''. Plymouth, England, UK: Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers, 2007. p. 32.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Joseph W. Bendersky 2007. p. 96&quot;&gt;Bendersky, Joseph W., ''A Concise History of Nazi Germany'', Lanham, Maryland, USA; Plymouth, England, UK: Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers, Inc., 2007. p. 96.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Kershaw&quot;&gt;[[Ian Kershaw]], ''Hitler: A Profile in Power'', London, (2001) [1991], first chapter.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;kershaw&quot;&gt;Ian Kershaw. ''Hitler, 1936-45: Nemesis''. New York, New York: USA: W. W. Norton &amp; Company Inc., 2001. p. 588.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;kershaw20&quot;&gt;Ian Kershaw. ''Hitler, 1889–1936: Hubris'', 2000. p. 182.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;kershaw22&quot;&gt;Ian Kershaw, 1991. chapter I.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;koenigsberg&quot;&gt;Richard A. Koenigsberg. ''Nations have the Right to Kill: Hitler, the Holocaust, and War''. New York, New York, USA: Library of Social Science, 2009. p. 2.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Konrad Heiden 2010. p. 85&quot;&gt;Konrad Heiden. ''A History of National Socialism''. Oxon, England, UK; New York, New York, USA: Routledge, 2010. p. 85.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;machtergreifung&quot;&gt;Beck, Hermann ''The Fateful Alliance: German Conservatives and Nazis in 1933: The Machtergreifung in a New Light'', Berghahn Books, 2008. ISBN 9781845456801, p. 72.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;machtergreifung4&quot;&gt;Beck, Hermann ''The Fateful Alliance: German Conservatives and Nazis in 1933: The Machtergreifung in a New Light'', 2008. p. 72.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;machtergreifung5&quot;&gt;Beck, Hermann ''The Fateful Alliance: German Conservatives and Nazis in 1933: The Machtergreifung in a New Light'', 2008. pp. 72-75.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;machtergreifung6&quot;&gt;Beck, Hermann ''The Fateful Alliance: German Conservatives and Nazis in 1933: The Machtergreifung in a New Light'', 2008. p. 84.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;macmillan&quot;&gt;Burleigh, Michael ''The Third Reich: a new history'' Pan MacMillan (2001) p75&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;manchester&quot;&gt;Conan Fischer, ''The Rise of the Nazis'', Manchester University Press, 2002. ISBN 0-7190-6067-2. p. 53&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Martin Kitchen 2006. p. 205&quot;&gt;Kitchen, Martin, ''A History of Modern Germany, 1800-2000'', Malden, Massaschussetts, USA; Oxford, England, UK; Carlton, Victoria, Australia: Blackwell Publishing, Inc., 2006. p. 205.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Michael Mann 2004. p. 183&quot;&gt;Mann, Michael, ''Fascists'', New York City: Cambridge University Press, 2004. p. 183.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;millennial&quot;&gt;Redles, David ''Nazi End Times; The Third Reich as a Millennial Reich'' in Kinane, Karolyn &amp; Ryan, Michael A. (eds)  ''End of days: essays on the apocalypse from antiquity to modernity'' McFarland and Co (2009) p176.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;minneapolis&quot;&gt;Neocleous, Mark. ''Fascism''. Minneapolis, Minnesota, USA: University of Minnesota Press, 1997. p. 23.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;nicholas&quot;&gt;Miranda Carter. George, Nicholas and Wilhelm: Three Royal Cousins and the Road to World War I. Borzoi Book, 2009. Pp. 420.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;nicholls159160&quot;&gt;David Nicholls. ''Adolf Hitler: A Biographical Companion''. Chapel Hill, North Carolina, USA: University of North Carolina Press, 2000. pp. 159-160.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;nicholls236237&quot;&gt;David Nicholls. ''Adolf Hitler: A Biographical Companion''. Chapel Hill, North Carolina, USA: University of North Carolina Press, 2000. pp. 236-237.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Nina Witoszek 2002. pp. 89-90&quot;&gt;Nina Witoszek, Lars Trägårdh. ''Culture and Crisis: The Case of Germany and Sweden''. Berghahn Books, 2002. pp. 89-90.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Nyomarkay, Joseph 1967 p. 130&quot;&gt;Nyomarkay, Joseph, ''Charisma and Factionalism in the Nazi Party'', Minnesota University Press, 1967. p. 130&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Oliver H. Woshinsky 2008. p. 156&quot;&gt;Oliver H. Woshinsky. ''Explaining Politics: Culture, Institutions, and Political Behavior''. Oxon, England, UK; New York, New York, USA: Routledge, 2008. p. 156.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pathological&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=[[Adolf Hitler|Hitler, Adolf]]|title=[[Hitler's Secret Book]] | year=1961 | publisher=Grove Press | location=New York | isbn=0-394-62003-8 | oclc=9830111| pages=8–9, 17–18 | quote=Sparta must be regarded as the first Völkisch State. The exposure of the sick, weak, deformed children, in short, their destruction, was more decent and in truth a thousand times more humane than the wretched insanity of our day which preserves the most pathological subject.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;payne1995a&quot;&gt;Payne, Stanley G. ''A History of Fascism, 1914–45''. Madison, WI: University of Wisconsin Press, 1995.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Peter J. Bowler 1989. pp. 304-305&quot;&gt;Peter J. Bowler. ''Evolution: The History of an Idea''. 2nd edition. Berkeley and Los Angeles, California, USA: University of California Press, 1989. pp. 304-305.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Peukert, Detlev 1993 p. 74&quot;&gt;Peukert, Detlev, ''The Weimar Republic''. 1st paperback ed. Macmillan, 1993. ISBN 9780809015566, p. 74.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Peukert, Detlev 1993 pp. 73-74&quot;&gt;Peukert, Detlev, ''The Weimar Republic''. 1st paperback ed. Macmillan, 1993. ISBN 9780809015566, pp. 73-74.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;plant&quot;&gt;Plant, 1986. p. 99.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;political&quot;&gt;''European Journal of Political Economy'', Vol. 21, Issue 4, p. 1015.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;PostWWIAntisemitism&quot;&gt;&quot;Florida Holocaust Museum - Antisemitism - Post World War 1&quot; (history), www.flholocaustmuseum.org, 2003, webpage: [http://www.flholocaustmuseum.org/history_wing/antisemitism/post_ww1.cfm Post-WWI Antisemitism].&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;publishers&quot;&gt;Glenn D. Walters. ''Lifestyle Theory: Past, Present, and Future''. Nova Publishers, 2006. p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;publishers30&quot;&gt;Bendersky, Joseph W. ''A History of Nazi Germany: 1919-1945''. 2nd ed. Burnham Publishers, 2000. pp. 58-59.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;R.J. Overy 2004. p. 399&quot;&gt;Overy, R.J., ''The Dictators: Hitler's Germany and Stalin's Russia'', W. W. Norton &amp; Company, Inc., 2004. p. 399&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;R.J. Overy 2004. p. 402&quot;&gt;ROvery, R.J., ''The Dictators: Hitler's Germany and Stalin's Russia'', W. W. Norton &amp; Company, Inc., 2004. p. 402.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;R.J. Overy 2004. p. 403&quot;&gt;Overy, R.J., ''The Dictators: Hitler's Germany and Stalin's Russia'', W. W. Norton &amp; Company, Inc., 2004. p. 403.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;R.J. Overy 2004. pp. 399-403&quot;&gt;Overy, R.J., ''The Dictators: Hitler's Germany and Stalin's Russia'', W. W. Norton &amp; Company, Inc., 2004. pp. 399-403.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Robert Anthony Krieg 2004. p. 4&quot;&gt;Robert Anthony Krieg. ''Catholic Theologians in Nazi Germany'', 2004. p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Robert J. Richards 2008. pp. 7-8&quot;&gt;Robert J. Richards. ''Myth 19 That Darwin and Haeckel were Complicit in Nazi Biology''. The University of Chicago, Illinois, USA. http://home.uchicago.edu/~rjr6/articles/Myth.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Roger Griffin 2005. p. 85&quot;&gt;Roger Griffin. ''Fascism, Totalitarianism and Political Religion''. Oxon, England, UK; New York, New York, USA: Routledge, 2005. p. 85.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Rudy Koshar 1986. p. 190&quot;&gt;Koshar, Rudy. ''Social Life, Local Politics, and Nazism: Marburg, 1880-1935'', University of North Carolina Press, 1986. p. 190.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Simone Gigliotti 2005. p. 14&quot;&gt;Simone Gigliotti, Berel Lang. ''The Holocaust: A Reader''. Malden, Massachusetts, USA; Oxford, England, UK; Carlton, Victoria, Australia: Blackwell Publishing, 2005. p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Social Darwinism in European and American Thought, 1860–1945: nature as model and nature as threat&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |author=Mike Hawkins |title=Social Darwinism in European and American Thought, 1860–1945: nature as model and nature as threat | year=1997 | publisher=Cambridge University Press | isbn=0-521-57434-X | oclc = 34705047 | page=276 | url=http://books.google.com/?id=SszNCxSKmgkC&amp;pg=PA276&amp;dq=Hitler%27s+Secret+Book+sparta | quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;socialism&quot;&gt;Michael Kellogg, ''The Russian Roots of Nazism White Émigrés and the Making of National Socialism, 1917–1945'', Cambridge, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;stackelberg&quot;&gt;Roderick Stackelberg, Sally Anne Winkle. ''The Nazi Germany Sourcebook: An Anthology of Texts'', 2002. p. 45.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Stanley G. Payne 1995. p. 464&quot;&gt;Stanley G. Payne. ''A History of Fascism, 1914-1945'', 1995. p. 464.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;stanley&quot;&gt;Stanley G. Payne. ''A History of Fascism, 1914-1945'', 1995. p. 463.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;stormtroopers&quot;&gt;Thomas D. Grant. ''Stormtroopers and Crisis in the Nazi Movement: Activism, Ideology and Dissolution''. London, England, UK; New York, New York, USA: Routledge, 2004. pp. 30-34, 44.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;stormtroopers2&quot;&gt;Otis C. Mitchell. ''Hitler's Stormtroopers and the attack on the German Republic, 1919-1933''. Jefferson, North Carolina, USA: McFarland &amp; Company, Inc., 2008. p. 47.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas Rohkrämer 2007. p. 130&quot;&gt;Rohkrämer, Thomas, &quot;A Single Communal Faith?: The German Right from Conservatism to National Socialism&quot;, ''Monographs in German History''. Volume 20, Berghahn Books, 2007. p. 130&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas Weber 2011. p. 251&quot;&gt;Weber, Thomas, ''Hitler's First War: Adolf Hitler, the Men of the List Regiment, and the First World War'', Oxford, England, UK: Oxford University Press, 2011. p. 251.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;thosedamnednazis&quot;&gt;Goebbels, Joseph; Mjölnir (1932). ''Die verfluchten Hakenkreuzler. Etwas zum Nachdenken''. Munich: Franz Eher Nachfolger. English translation: ''[http://www.calvin.edu/academic/cas/gpa/haken32.htm Those Damned Nazis]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;timothy&quot;&gt;Ryback, Timothy W. ''Hitler's Private Library: The Books That Shaped His Life'', New York; Toronto: Vintage Books, 2010. pp. 129-130.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;timothy12&quot;&gt;Ryback, Timothy W. ''Hitler's Private Library: The Books That Shaped His Life''. New York, Toronto: Vintage Books, 2010. p. 130.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;timothy13&quot;&gt;Ryback, Timothy W., ''Hitler's Private Library: The Books That Shaped His Life'', 2010. p. 130&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;totalitarianism&quot;&gt;Roger Griffin. ''Fascism, Totalitarianism and Political Religion'', 2005. p. 93.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;transaction&quot;&gt;Hughes, H. Stuart, ''Oswald Spengler'', New Brunswick, New Jersey: Transaction Publishers, 1992. p. 109.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;understandably&quot;&gt;Scholarship for [[Martin Luther|Martin Luther's]] 1543 treatise, ''[[On the Jews and their Lies]]'', exercising influence on Germany's attitude: * Wallmann, Johannes. &quot;The Reception of Luther's Writings on the Jews from the Reformation to the End of the 19th Century&quot;, ''Lutheran Quarterly'', n.s. 1 (Spring 1987) 1:72–97. Wallmann writes: &quot;The assertion that Luther's expressions of anti-Jewish sentiment have been of major and persistent influence in the centuries after the Reformation, and that there exists a continuity between Protestant anti-Judaism and modern racially oriented anti-Semitism, is at present wide-spread in the literature; since the Second World War it has understandably become the prevailing opinion.&quot; * Michael, Robert. ''Holy Hatred: Christianity, Antisemitism, and the Holocaust''. New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2006; see chapter 4 &quot;The Germanies from Luther to Hitler&quot;, pp. 105–151. * Hillerbrand, Hans J. &quot;Martin Luther,&quot; ''Encyclopædia Britannica'', 2007. Hillerbrand writes: &quot;[H]is strident pronouncements against the Jews, especially toward the end of his life, have raised the question of whether Luther significantly encouraged the development of German anti-Semitism. Although many scholars have taken this view, this perspective puts far too much emphasis on Luther and not enough on the larger peculiarities of German history.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;university&quot;&gt;Fritzsche, Peter. ''Germans into Nazis''. Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press, 1998.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;university1&quot;&gt;Kele, Max H. ''Nazis and Workers: National Socialist Appeals to German Labor, 1919–1933''. Chapel Hill: The University of North Carolina Press, 1972.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;university14&quot;&gt;Denis R. Alexander, Ronald L. Numbers. ''Biology and Ideology from Descartes to Dawkins''. Chicago, Illinois, USA; London, England, UK: University of Chicago Press, 2010. p. 209.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;university17&quot;&gt;Weitz, Eric D., ''Weimar Germany: Promise and Tragedy'', Princeton, New Jersey: Princeton University Press, 2007. pp. 336-337.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;university18&quot;&gt;Weitz, Eric D., ''Weimar Germany: Promise and Tragedy'', Princeton, New Jersey: Princeton University Press, 2007. p. 336.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;university19&quot;&gt;Stern,Fritz Richard  ''The politics of cultural despair: a study in the rise of the Germanic ideology'' University of California Press reprint edition (1974) p 296&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;university21&quot;&gt;Stanley G. Payne. ''A History of Fascism, 1914-1945''. Madison, Wisconsin, USA: Wisconsin University Press, 1995. pp. 463-464.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;university26&quot;&gt;Ball, Terence and Bellamy, Richard (2003). ''The Cambridge History of Twentieth-Century Political Thought'', Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. ISBN 0-521-56354-2&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;university28&quot;&gt;Hayes, Peter. 1987 ''Industry and Ideology IG Farben in the Nazi Era.'' Cambridge University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;university29&quot;&gt;Carsten, Francis Ludwig ''The Rise of Fascism'', 2nd ed. University of California Press, 1982. p. 137. Quoting: Hitler, A., ''Sunday Express'', September 28, 1930.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;university3&quot;&gt;Eugene Davidson. ''The Unmaking of Adolf Hitler''. First paperback edition. Columbia, Missouri, USA: Missouri University Press, 2004. p. 117.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;weidenfeld&quot;&gt;Walter Laqueur, ''Russia and Germany: A Century of Conflict'', London, Weidenfeld and Nicolson 1965. p. 76.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;William L. Shirer 1990 41&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=sY8svb-MNUwC&amp;pg=PA41&amp;dq=socialist+AND+communalization+AND+embarrassing+AND+%22These+demands+had+been+put+in+at+the+insistence+of+Drexler+and+Feder,+who+apparently+really+believed+in+the+socialism%22+AND+%22rise+and+fall+of+the+third+reich%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=HvVcTrXxKIaCgAfVoPT2AQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCoQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|title=The Rise and Fall of the Third Reich: A History of Nazi Germany (3 ed.,1960)|author=William L. Shirer|year=1990|publisher=Simon and Schuster|page=41|isbn=0-671-72868-7|accessdate=August 30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;witoszek&quot;&gt;Witoszek, Nina and Lars Trägårdh, ''Culture and Crisis: The Case of Germany and Sweden'', Berghahn Books, 2002, p. 90.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;witoszek10&quot;&gt;Nina Witoszek, Lars Trägårdh. ''Culture and Crisis: The Case of Germany and Sweden''. Berghahn Books, 2002. p. 89.&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

===Bibliography===
* {{cite book | last = Allen | first = William | title = The Nazi Seizure of Power: The Experience of a Single German Town 1922–1945 | publisher = Penguin | year = 1995 | origyear = 1965 | isbn=0-14-023968-5}}
* {{cite book | last = Fritzsche | first = Peter | title = Rehearsals for Fascism: Populism and Political Mobilization in Weimar Germany | location = New York | publisher = Oxford University Press | year = 1990 | isbn=0-19-505780-5}}
* [[Nicholas Goodrick-Clarke|Goodrick-Clarke, Nicholas]] (2004) [1985]. ''[[The Occult Roots of Nazism]]: Secret Aryan Cults and Their Influence on Nazi Ideology: The Ariosophists of Austria and Germany, 1890–1935''. Wellingborough, England: The Aquarian Press. ISBN 0-85030-402-4 and ISBN 1-86064-973-4.
* {{cite book | last= Goodrick-Clarke | first = Nicholas | title = [[Black Sun (Goodrick-Clarke book)|''Black Sun: Aryan Cults, Esoteric Nazism and the Politics of Identity'']] | publisher = New York University Press | year = 2003 | origyear = 2002 | isbn=0-8147-3155-4}}
* [[Victor Klemperer|Klemperer, Victor]] (1947). [[LTI - Lingua Tertii Imperii]].
* {{cite book | last = McNab | first = Chris | title = The Third Reich | publisher = Amber Books Ltd | year = 2009 | isbn = 978-1-906626-51-8 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last = von Mises | first = Ludwig | authorlink = Ludwig von Mises | title = [[Omnipotent Government: The Rise of the Total State and Total War]] | publisher = Libertarian Press | year = 1985 | origyear = 1944 | isbn=0-910884-15-3}}
* {{cite book | last = Paxton | first = Robert | authorlink = Robert O. Paxton | title = The Anatomy of Fascism | publisher = London: Penguin Books Ltd | year = 2005 | isbn=0-14-101432-6}}
* {{cite book | last = Peukert | first = Detlev | authorlink = Detlev Peukert | title = Inside Nazi Germany: Conformity, Opposition, and Racism in Everyday Life | year = 1989 | publisher = Yale University Press | location = New Haven | isbn=978-0-300-04480-5}}
* Redles, David (2005). ''Hitler's Millennial Reich: Apocalyptic Belief and the Search for Salvation''. New York: University Press. ISBN 0-8147-7524-1.
* Sauer, Wolfgang. &quot;National Socialism: Totalitarianism or Fascism?&quot; pp.&amp;nbsp;404–424 from ''The American Historical Review'', Volume 73, Issue #2, December 1967.
* {{cite book | last = Sohn-Rethel | first = Alfred | authorlink = Alfred Sohn-Rethel | title = Economy and Class Structure of German Fascism | publisher = London: CSE Bks | year = 1978 | isbn=0-906336-00-7}}
* {{cite book | last = Speer | first = Albert | authorlink = Albert Speer | origyear = 1969 | year = 1971 | title = [[Inside the Third Reich]] | publisher = Avon | location = New York | isbn = 978-0-380-00071-5 | ref = harv }}
* [[Richard Steigmann-Gall|Steigmann-Gall, Richard]] (2003). ''The Holy Reich: Nazi Conceptions of Christianity, 1919–1945''. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|Nazism|Nazi}}
{{Commons category|National Socialism}}
* [http://avalon.law.yale.edu/subject_menus/nca_v4menu.asp Hitler's National Socialist Party platform]
* [http://www.ns-archiv.de/index.php NS-Archiv], a large collection of scanned original Nazi documents.
* [http://www.life.com/image/first/in-gallery/23127/wwii-nazi-thugs-and-thinkers WWII: Nazi Thugs and Thinkers] - slideshow by ''[[Life magazine]]''
* [http://www.nytimes.com/slideshow/2010/10/16/world/20101016_HITLER.html Exhibit on Hitler and the Germans] - slideshow by ''[[The New York Times]]''
* Jonathan Meades (1994): [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jagoBzZT1q8 Jerry Building - Unholy Relics of Nazi Germany ] (in 4 parts)
&lt;!--spacing, please do not remove--&gt;
{{Navboxes
|list =
{{Nazism}}
{{Adolf Hitler}}
{{Fascism movement}}
{{Antisemitism topics|state=collapsed}}
{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}
{{Authoritarian types of rule}}
}}

[[Category:Adolf Hitler]]
[[Category:Anti-communism]]
[[Category:Antisemitism]]
[[Category:Fascism]]
[[Category:Far-right politics]]
[[Category:History of Germany]]
[[Category:Ideologies]]
[[Category:Jewish German history]]
[[Category:Nationalism]]
[[Category:Nazi Germany]]
[[Category:Nazism| ]]
[[Category:Persecution of homosexuals in Nazi Germany and the Holocaust]]
[[Category:Politics of Germany]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:The Holocaust]]
[[Category:Totalitarianism]]
[[Category:Weimar Republic]]

{{Link GA|no}}
[[als:Nationalsozialismus]]
[[ar:نازية]]
[[an:Nazismo]]
[[ast:Nacionalsocialismu]]
[[be:Нацыянал-сацыялізм]]
[[be-x-old:Нацыянал-сацыялізм]]
[[bg:Националсоциализъм]]
[[bar:Nationalsozialismus]]
[[bs:Nacizam]]
[[br:Naziegezh]]
[[ca:Nazisme]]
[[cs:Nacismus]]
[[cy:Natsïaeth]]
[[da:Nazisme]]
[[de:Nationalsozialismus]]
[[et:Natsionaalsotsialism]]
[[el:Εθνικοσοσιαλισμός]]
[[es:Nazismo]]
[[eo:Naziismo]]
[[eu:Nazionalsozialismo]]
[[fa:نازیسم]]
[[fr:Nazisme]]
[[fy:Nasjonaalsosjalisme]]
[[ga:Naitsíochas]]
[[gl:Nazismo]]
[[gu:નાઝીવાદ]]
[[ko:나치즘]]
[[hi:नात्सीवाद]]
[[hsb:Nacionalsocializm]]
[[hr:Nacionalsocijalizam]]
[[id:Nazisme]]
[[ia:Nazismo]]
[[is:Nasismi]]
[[it:Nazionalsocialismo]]
[[he:נאציזם]]
[[kn:ನಾಜಿಸಮ್]]
[[ka:ნაციონალ-სოციალიზმი]]
[[kk:Нацизм]]
[[ku:Nazî]]
[[la:Nazismus]]
[[lv:Nacionālsociālisms]]
[[lt:Nacizmas]]
[[hu:Nemzetiszocializmus]]
[[mk:Нацизам]]
[[mr:नाझीवाद]]
[[arz:نازيه]]
[[nl:Nationaalsocialisme]]
[[ne:नाजीवाद]]
[[ja:ナチズム]]
[[nap:Nazzismo]]
[[no:Nasjonalsosialisme]]
[[nn:Nazisme]]
[[oc:Nazisme]]
[[pl:Narodowy socjalizm]]
[[pt:Nazismo]]
[[ro:Nazism]]
[[rue:Націзм]]
[[ru:Национал-социализм]]
[[sco:Nazism]]
[[scn:Nazzismu]]
[[simple:Nazism]]
[[sk:Nacizmus]]
[[sl:Nacionalsocializem]]
[[sr:Нацизам]]
[[sh:Nacionalsocijalizam]]
[[fi:Kansallissosialismi]]
[[sv:Nazism]]
[[ta:நாசிசம்]]
[[te:నాజీయిజం]]
[[th:นาซี]]
[[tg:Нозисм]]
[[tr:Nasyonal sosyalizm]]
[[uk:Націонал-соціалізм]]
[[vi:Chủ nghĩa Quốc xã]]
[[vo:Netasogädim]]
[[war:Nazismo]]
[[yi:נאציזם]]
[[bat-smg:Nacėzmos]]
[[zh:纳粹主义]]</text>
      <sha1>3rxke0k0tnjqngwvmzxup0eq03j8hf0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
