<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Prohibition</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>24856</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520472822</id>
      <parentid>520472807</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-29T19:22:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contributions/86.168.33.161|86.168.33.161]] to version by Illegitimate Barrister. False positive? [[User:ClueBot NG/FalsePositives|Report it]]. Thanks, [[User:ClueBot NG|ClueBot NG]]. (1302462) (Bot)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="30363">{{About||prohibition of certain other drugs|Prohibition of drugs|the general concept of legal prohibition|Prohibitionism|other uses|Prohibition (disambiguation)}}
[[Image:Raid at elk lake.jpg|thumb|A police raid confiscating illegal alcohol, in [[James, Ontario|Elk Lake, Canada]], in 1925.]] 

'''Prohibition of alcohol''', often referred to simply as '''prohibition''', is the legal act of prohibiting the manufacture, transportation and sale of [[alcohol]] and [[alcoholic beverage]]s. The term can also apply to the periods in the histories of the countries during which the prohibition of alcohol was enforced. Use of the term as applicable to a historical period is typically applied to countries of European culture. 

==History==
[[image:The Drunkard's Progress - Color.jpg|thumb|250px|The Drunkard's Progress: A lithograph by [[Nathaniel Currier]] supporting the temperance movement, January 1846]]

The earliest records of prohibition of alcohol date back to the [[Xia Dynasty]] (ca. 2070 BC–ca. 1600 BC) in China. [[Yu the Great]], the first ruler of the Xia Dynasty, prohibited alcohol throughout the kingdom.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sytu.edu.cn/zhgjiu/u9-1.htm Chinese Administration of Alcoholic Beverages]&lt;/ref&gt; It was legalized again after his death, during the reign of his son [[Qi of Xia|Qi]].

In the early twentieth century, much of the impetus for the prohibition movement in the Nordic countries and North America came from moralistic convictions of pietistic Protestants.&lt;ref&gt; Richard J. Jensen, ''The winning of the Midwest: social and political conflict, 1888-1896'' (1971) [http://books.google.com/books?id=XpCgCNZwpvoC&amp;pg=PA89&amp;dq=%22Iowa+wet+or+dry%22+intitle:winning+intitle:midwest+inauthor:jensen&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=HeNKT5_RKYKtsAK409nqCA&amp;ved=0CDIQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false pp 89-121 online]&lt;/ref&gt; Prohibition movements in the West coincided with the advent of [[women's suffrage]], with newly empowered women as part of the political process strongly supporting policies that curbed alcohol consumption.&lt;ref&gt;Aileen Kraditor, ''The Ideas of the Woman Suffrage Movement, 1890–1920'' (1965) pp 12–37.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Anne Myra Goodman Benjamin, ''A history of the anti-suffrage movement in the United States from 1895 to 1920: women against equality'' (1991)&lt;/ref&gt;

The first half of the 20th century saw periods of prohibition of alcoholic beverages in several countries:
* 1907 to 1948 in [[Prohibition in Canada|Prince Edward Island]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.ca/books?id=k9lWztgWymgC&amp;lpg=PA21&amp;dq=prohibition%20%22prince%20edward%20island%22%2C%20alcohol&amp;pg=PA21#v=onepage&amp;q=prohibition%20%22prince%20edward%20island%22,%20alcohol&amp;f=false Heath, Dwight B. (1995). International handbook on alcohol and culture. Westport, CT. Greenwood Publishing Group, p. 21] There seems to be agreement in the literature for 1948 but various dates are given for the initiation of PEI's prohibition legislation. 1907 is the latest. 1900, 1901 and 1902 are given by others.&lt;/ref&gt; and for shorter periods in other provinces [[Prohibition in Canada|in Canada]]
* 1907 to 1992 in [[Faroe Islands]]; limited private imports from Denmark were allowed from 1928
* 1914 to 1925 in [[Prohibition in Russian Empire and Soviet Union|Russia and the Soviet Union]]
* 1915 to 1922 in [[Prohibition in Finland|Iceland]] (beer was still prohibited until 1989)&lt;ref&gt;Associated Press, [http://www.nytimes.com/1988/05/11/world/beer-soon-for-icelanders.html Beer (Soon) for Icelanders], ''New York Times'', May 11, 1988&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1916 to 1927 in [[Prohibition in Finland|Norway]] (fortified wine and beer also prohibited from 1917 to 1923)
* 1919 in [[Prohibition#Europa|Hungary]] (in the [[Hungarian Soviet Republic]], March 21 to August 1; called ''szesztilalom'')
* 1919 to 1932 in [[Prohibition in Finland|Finland]] (called ''kieltolaki'', &quot;ban law&quot;)
* 1920 to 1933 in [[Prohibition in the United States|the United States]]

After several years, prohibition became a failure in North America and elsewhere, as [[Rum-running|bootlegging (rum-running)]] became widespread and [[organized crime]] took control of the distribution of alcohol. Distilleries and breweries in [[Canada]], [[Mexico]] and the [[Caribbean]] flourished as their products were either consumed by visiting Americans or illegally exported to the United States. [[Chicago]] became notorious as a haven for prohibition dodgers during the time known as the [[Roaring Twenties]]. Prohibition generally came to an end in the late 1920s or early 1930s in most of North America and Europe, although a few locations continued prohibition for many more years.

==Australasia==
===Australia===
[[Image:Prohibition lifted in Canberra 1928.jpg|thumb|250px|The first consignment of liquor [[Canberra]], [[Australian Capital Territory]], following the repeal of prohibition laws in 1928.]]
The [[Australian Capital Territory]] was the first jurisdiction in [[Australia]] to enable prohibition laws. In 1910 [[King O'Malley]], the then Minister of Home Affairs, shepherded the laws through parliament to address unruly behaviour. Seventeen years later the Federal Parliament repealed the laws.

In [[Melbourne]], [[Victoria, Australia|Victoria]] in the late 1920s, the [[temperance movement]] drove suburban councils to hold polls and the residents of some of these municipalities voted for the creation of a dry area. This prohibited the granting of a liquor license without a formal vote of approval by local residents. These areas continue to this day in the suburbs of [[Camberwell, Victoria|Camberwell]] and [[Box Hill, Victoria|Box Hill]]. Polls have been held since, however the majority of voters continue to support the restrictions on liquor licenses.

More recently alcohol has been prohibited in many remote [[Indigenous Australians|indigenous]] communities. Penalties for transporting alcohol into these &quot;dry&quot; communities are severe and can result in confiscation of any vehicles involved; in dry areas within the [[Northern Territory]], all vehicles used to transport alcohol are seized.

Because alcohol consumption has been linked to violent behaviour in some individuals, some communities sought a safer alternative in substances such as [[kava]], especially in the Northern Territory. Over-indulgence in kava causes sleepiness, rather than the violence that can result from over-indulgence in alcohol. These and other measures to counter alcohol abuse met with variable success. Some communities saw decreased social problems and others did not. The ANCD study notes that, to be effective, programs must address &quot;...the underlying structural determinants that have a significant impact on alcohol and drug misuse.&quot; (''Op. cit.'', p.&amp;nbsp;26) The Federal government banned kava imports into the Northern Territory in 2007.&lt;ref&gt;Australian Broadcasting Commission (2007) &quot;Kava Ban 'Sparks Black Market Boom'&quot;, ''ABC Darwin'' 23 August 2007 http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2007/08/23/2012707.htm?site=darwin Accessed 18 October 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

===New Zealand===
In [[History of New Zealand|New Zealand]], prohibition was a moralistic reform movement begun in the mid-1880s by the Protestant evangelical and Nonconformist churches and the [[Woman's Christian Temperance Union]] and after 1890 by the Prohibition League. It never achieved its goal of national prohibition. It was a middle-class movement which accepted the existing economic and social order; the effort to legislate morality assumed that individual redemption was all that was needed to carry the colony forward from a pioneering society to a more mature one. However, both the Church of England and the largely Irish Catholic Church rejected prohibition as an intrusion of government into the church's domain, while the growing labor movement saw capitalism rather than alcohol as the enemy.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1914&quot;&gt;Greg Ryan, &quot;Drink and the Historians: Sober Reflections on Alcohol in New Zealand 1840–1914,&quot; ''New Zealand Journal of History'' (April 2010) Vol.44, No.1&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated52&quot;&gt;Richard Newman, &quot;New Zealand'S Vote For Prohibition In 1911,&quot; ''New Zealand Journal of History,'' April 1975, Vol. 9 Issue 1, pp 52-71&lt;/ref&gt;

Reformers hoped that the women's vote, in which New Zealand was a pioneer, would swing the balance, but the women were not as well organized as in other countries. Prohibition had a majority in a national referendum in 1911, but needed a 60% vote to pass. The movement kept trying in the 1920s, losing three more referenda by close votes; it managed to keep in place a [[Six o'clock swill|6pm closing hour]] for pubs and Sunday closing. The Depression and war years effectively ended the movement.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1914&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated52&quot;/&gt;

==North America==
===Canada===
{{Main|Prohibition in Canada}}

===United States===
{{Main|Prohibition in the United States}}

[[File:Woman's Christian Temperance Union Cartoon.jpg|thumb|250px|This illustration from the Hawaiian Gazette newspaper humorously illustrates the [[Anti-Saloon League]] and the [[Women's Christian Temperance Union]]'s campaign against the producers and sellers of beers in Hawaii.]]
Prohibition in the United States focused on the manufacture and sale of alcohol. Drinking itself was never illegal, and there were exceptions for medicinal and religious uses.
 
Prohibition was a major reform movement from the 1840s into the 1920s, and was sponsored by evangelical Protestant churches, especially the Methodists, Baptists, Presbyterians, Disciples and Congregationalists. Kansas and Maine were early adopters. The [[Women's Christian Temperance Union]], founded in 1874, and the [[Prohibition Party]] were major players until the early 20th century, when the movement was taken over by the [[Anti-Saloon League]]. By using pressure politics on legislators, the Anti-Saloon League achieved the goal of nationwide prohibition during World War I, emphasizing the need to destroy the political corruption of the saloons, the political power of the German-based brewing industry, and the need to reduce domestic violence in the home.

Prohibition was instituted with ratification of the [[Eighteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution]] on January 16, 1919, which prohibited the &quot;...manufacture, sale, or transportation of intoxicating liquors within, the importation thereof into, or the exportation thereof from the United States...&quot; Congress passed the &quot;[[Volstead Act]]&quot; on October 28, 1919, to enforce the law, but most large cities were uninterested in enforcing the legislation, leaving an understaffed federal service to go after bootleggers. Although alcohol consumption did decline as a whole, there was a rise in alcohol consumption in many cities along with significant increases in organized crime related to its production and distribution.

The sale of alcohol was illegal, but alcoholic drinks were still widely available. People also kept private bars to serve their guests. Large quantities of alcohol were smuggled in from Canada, overland, by sea along both ocean coasts, and via the Great Lakes. The government cracked down on alcohol consumption on land within the U.S. It was a different story on the water where vessels outside the 3 mile limit were exempt. Legal and illegal home brewing was popular during Prohibition. &quot;Malt and hop&quot; stores popped up across the country and some former breweries turned to selling malt extract syrup, ostensibly for baking and &quot;beverage&quot; purposes.

Prohibition became increasingly unpopular during the [[Great Depression in the United States|Great Depression]]. The repeal movement was started by a wealthy Republican, [[Pauline Sabin]], who said that prohibition should be repealed because it made the US a nation of hypocrites and undermined its respect for the rule of law. Her fellow Republicans were put in office by the &quot;drys&quot; and, even though they eagerly partook in consumption of alcoholic beverages at her parties, in public they presented themselves as opposing the repeal of prohibition, lest they be thrown out of office by the dry voting blocks. This hypocrisy and the fact that women led the prohibition movement convinced her to start the organization that eventually led to the repeal of prohibition.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1933&quot;&gt;Thomas R. Pegram, ''Battling Demon Rum: The Struggle for a Dry America, 1800-1933'' (1998)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2005&quot;&gt;Jeffrey A. Miron, &quot;Alcohol Prohibition&quot; ''Eh.Net Encyclopedia'' (2005) [http://eh.net/encyclopedia/article/miron.prohibition.alcohol online]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Prohibition prescription front.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Prescription form for medicinal liquor]]
When her fellow Republicans would not support her efforts, she went to the Democrats, who changed from drys led by conservative Democrats and Catholics to supporting repeal led by liberal politicians such as [[Fiorello La Guardia|La Guardia]] and [[Franklin D. Roosevelt|Franklin Roosevelt]]. She, and they, emphasized that repeal would generate enormous sums of much needed tax revenue, and weaken the base of organized crime. The [[Repeal of Prohibition]] in the United States was accomplished with the passage of the [[Twenty-first Amendment to the United States Constitution|Twenty-first Amendment]] to the United States Constitution on December 5, 1933. By its terms, states were allowed to set their own laws for the control of alcohol. The organized Prohibition movement was dead nationwide, but survived for a while in a few southern and border states.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1933&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2005&quot;/&gt;

====Al Capone====
Al Capone was the most notorious gangster of his generation. Born in 1899, Capone settled in Chicago to take over Johnny Torrio’s business dealing with outlawed liquor. Within 3 years, Capone had nearly 700 men at his disposal. As the profits came in, Capone acquired finesse- particularly finesse in the management of politics and politicians.  By the middle of the decade, he had gained complete control of the suburb Cicero, and had installed his own Mayor in office.  Capone’s rise to fame did not come without bloodshed.  Rival gangs, such as the Gennas and the Aiellos, started wars with Capone, eventually leading to an epidemic of killings of epic proportions.  In 1927, Capone and his gang were pulling in approximately $60 million per year- most of it from beer. Capone did not only control the sale of liquor to over 10,000 speakeasies, but he also controlled the supply: from Canada to Florida.  Capone was imprisoned for tax violations and eventually died on January 25, 1947, due to a heart attack and pneumonia.  &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=America's Longest War|year=1974|publisher=Praeger}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Latin America==
===Mexico===
[[List of anarchist communities#Zapatista Autonomous Municipalities|Zapatista Communities]] will often ban alcohol as part of a collective decision. This has been used by many villages as a way to decrease domestic violence and has generally been favored by women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.narconews.com/Issue33/article971.html |title=The Zapatistas Reject the War on Drugs |publisher=Narco News |date= |accessdate=2010-04-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, this is not recognized by federal Mexican law as the [[Zapatista Army of National Liberation|Zapatista]] movement is strongly opposed by the federal government.

The sale and purchase of alcohol is prohibited on and the night before certain national holidays, such as ''[[Fiestas Patrias (Mexico)|Natalicio de Benito Juárez]]'' (birthdate of [[Benito Juárez]]) and ''[[Fiestas Patrias (Mexico)|Día de la Revolución]]'', which are meant to be dry nationally. The same &quot;dry law&quot; applies to the days before presidential elections every six years.

==Europe==
===Czech Republic===
On 14 September, 2012, the government of the [[Czech Republic]] banned all sales of liquor with more than 20% alcohol. From this date on it is illegal to sell (and/or offer for sale) such alcoholic beverages in shops, supermarkets, bars, restaurants, gas stations, e-shops etc. This measure was taken in response to the wave of [[methanol poisoning]] cases resulting in the deaths of 18 people in the Czech Republic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Nečas: Liquor needs new stamps before hitting the shelves|url=http://praguemonitor.com/2012/09/20/ne%C4%8D-liquor-needs-new-stamps-hitting-shelves|accessdate=20-0902012|newspaper=Prague Daily Monitor (ČTK)|date=2012-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since the beginning of the &quot;methanol affair&quot; the total number of deaths has increased to 25.  The ban remains until further notice,&lt;ref&gt;[http://uk.reuters.com/article/2012/09/14/uk-czech-alcohol-idUKBRE88D1GA20120914 Reuters -Czechs ban sale of spirits after bootleg booze kills 19]&lt;/ref&gt; though restrictions were eased towards the end of September.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Czechs partially lift spirits ban after mass poisoning|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-19738765|accessdate=27 September 2012|newspaper=BBC News|date=26 September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Nordic countries===&lt;!-- This section is linked from many places --&gt;
The [[Nordic countries]], with the exception of [[Denmark]], have had a strong [[temperance movement]] since the late 1800s, closely linked to the [[Christian revival]] movement of the late 19th century, but also to several worker organisations. As an example, in 1910 the temperance organisations in Sweden had some 330,000 members,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iogt.info/106_Historia-2.html IOGT history] (in Swedish) Retrieved 2011-12-08&lt;/ref&gt; which was 6% of a population of 5.5 million.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scb.se/Grupp/Hitta_statistik/Historisk_statistik/_Dokument/BISOS_A/1910/Befolkning%20A%20Historisk%20statistik%201900-talet%201910.pdf SCB Population statistics for 1910] (in Swedish) Retrieved 2011-12-08&lt;/ref&gt; Naturally, this heavily influenced the decisions of Nordic politicians in the early 20th century.

Already in 1907, the [[Faroe Islands]] passed a law prohibiting all sale of alcohol, which was in force until 1992. However, very restricted private importation from Denmark was allowed from 1928.

In 1914, [[Sweden]] put in place a rationing system, the [[Bratt System]], in force until 1955. However a [[Swedish prohibition referendum, 1922|referendum in 1922]] rejected an attempt to enforce total prohibition. 

In 1915, [[Iceland]] instituted total prohibition. The ban for wine and spirits was lifted in 1935, but beer remained prohibited until 1989.

In 1916, [[Norway]] prohibited [[distilled beverage]]s, and in 1917 the prohibition was extended to also include [[fortified wine]] and beer. The wine and beer ban was lifted in 1923, and in 1927 the ban of distilled beverages was also lifted.

In 1919, [[Finland]] enacted prohibition, as one of the first acts after independence from the [[Russian Empire]]. Four previous attempts to institute prohibition in the early 20th century had failed due to opposition from the [[Nicholas II of Russia|tsar]]. After a development similar to the one in the United States during its prohibition, with large-scale [[smuggling]] and increasing violence and crime rates, public opinion turned against the prohibition, and after a national [[referendum]] where 70% voted for a repeal of the law, prohibition was ended in early 1932.&lt;ref&gt;John H. Wuorinen, &quot;Finland's Prohibition Experiment,&quot; ''Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science'' vol. 163, (Sep., 1932), pp. 216-226 [http://www.jstor.org/stable/1017701 in JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;S. Sariola, &quot;Prohibition in Finland, 1919-1932; its background and consequences,&quot; ''Quarterly Journal of Studies in Alcohol'' (Sept 1954) 15(3) pp 477-90&lt;/ref&gt;

Today, all Nordic countries (with the exception of Denmark) continue to have strict controls on the sale of alcohol which is highly taxed (dutied) to the public. There are [[alcohol monopoly|government monopolies]] in place for selling spirits, wine and stronger beers in [[Norway]] ([[Vinmonopolet]]), [[Sweden]] ([[Systembolaget]]), [[Iceland]] ([[Vínbúð]]in), the [[Faroe Islands]] ([[Rúsdrekkasøla landsins]]) and [[Finland]] ([[Alko]]). Bars and restaurants may, however, import alcoholic beverages directly or through other companies.
{{See also|Alcoholic beverages in Sweden|Algoth Niska}}

===Soviet Union===
{{Main|Prohibition in Russian Empire and Soviet Union}}
In the [[Russian Empire]], a limited version of a Dry Law was introduced in 1914.&lt;ref&gt;I.N. Vvedensky, [http://www.tvereza.info/downloads/literature/forcedabstinenceexperience_ru.html#fae-results An Experience in Enforced Abstinence] (1915), Moscow (Введенский И. Н. Опыт принудительной трезвости. М.: Издание Московского Столичного Попечительства о Народной Трезвости, 1915.) {{ru icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; It continued through the turmoil of the [[Russian Revolution (1917)|Russian Revolution of 1917]] and the [[Russian Civil War]] into the period of [[Russian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic|Soviet Russia]] and the [[Soviet Union]] until 1925.

===United Kingdom===
Although the sale or consumption of commercial alcohol has never been prohibited by law, historically various groups in the UK have campaigned for the prohibition of alcohol, including the [[Society of Friends]] (Quakers), [[Methodist Church of Great Britain|The Methodist Church]] and other [[non-conformist]] Christians, as well as temperance movements such as [[Hope UK|Band of Hope]] and [[Chartism|temperance Chartist]] movements of the 19th century. 

In 1853, inspired by the [[Maine law]] in the USA, the [[United Kingdom Alliance]] led by [[John Bartholomew Gough]] was formed aimed at promoting a similar law prohibiting the sale of alcohol in the UK. This hard-line group of prohibitionists was opposed by other temperance organisations who preferred moral persuasion to a legal ban. This division in the ranks limited the effectiveness of the temperance movement as a whole. The impotence of legislation in this field was demonstrated when the [[List of Acts of the Parliament of the United Kingdom, 1840-1859|Sale of Beer Act 1854]] which restricted Sunday opening hours had to be repealed, following widespread rioting. In 1859 a prototype prohibition bill was overwhelmingly defeated in the House of Commons.&lt;ref&gt;Nick Brownlee (2002) ''This is Alcohol'': 99-100&lt;/ref&gt;

==Asia==
===Bangladesh===
In [[Bangladesh]], foreign passport holders of non-Muslim nations can drink in some licenced restaurants and bars (and expatriate clubs) and can purchase imported alcohol from 'diplomatic bonded warehouses' at a hefty rate of sales duty (Approx 300%). Holders of diplomatic passports and some other specially privileged persons (such as U.N. employees) have 'passbooks' which entitle them to buy imported alcohol from the same 'bonded warehouses' duty free. Often duty free and duty paid prices are shown alongside one another. Bangladesh nationals of any religion may purchase alcohol from special outlets with a medical certificate. Illegal homemade liquor (known as 'Mod' or 'Bangla') is widely consumed in rural areas. The (mostly Christian) Garo tribal folk also brew a strong rice beer called 'Choo'. Christians are permitted to use wine for Holy Communion.

===Brunei===
In [[Brunei]], alcohol consumption in public is banned and there is no sale of alcohol. Non-Muslims are allowed to purchase a limited amount of alcohol from their point of embarkation overseas for their own private consumption. Non-Muslims over 17 years of age may be allowed to bring in not more than two bottles of liquor (about two quarts) and twelve cans of beer per person into the country.{{Citation needed|date=January 2009}}

===India===
{{main|Prohibition in India}}
In some states of [[India]] alcoholic drinks are banned, for example the states of [[Gujarat]], [[Nagaland]] and [[Mizoram]]. Certain national holidays such as Independence Day and ''[[Gandhi Jayanti]]'' (birthdate of [[Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi|Mahatma Gandhi]]) are meant to be ''dry days'' nationally. The state of [[Andhra Pradesh]] had imposed Prohibition under the Chief Ministership of [[N. T. Rama Rao]] but this was thereafter lifted. Dry days are also observed on voting days. Prohibition was also observed from 1996 to 1998 in [[Haryana]]. Prohibition has become controversial in Gujarat following a [[2009 Gujarat hooch tragedy|July 2009 episode]] in which widespread poisoning resulted from alcohol that had been sold illegally.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ibnlive.in.com/news/ftn-in-right-spirit-gujarat-must-end-prohibition/97059-3.html In right spirit, Gujarat must end prohibition], IBN Live, 14 July 2009&lt;/ref&gt; All of the Indian states observe dry days on major religious festivals/occasions depending on the popularity of the festival in that region. These dry days are observed to maintain peace and order during the festival days.

===Maldives===
The [[Maldives]] ban the import of alcohol, x-raying all baggage on arrival. Alcoholic beverages are available only to foreign tourists on resort islands and may not be taken off the resort.

===Pakistan===
[[Pakistan]] allowed the free sale and consumption of alcohol for three decades from 1947, but restrictions were introduced by [[Zulfikar Ali Bhutto]] just weeks before he was removed as prime minister in 1977. Since then, only members of non-Muslim minorities such as [[Hinduism|Hindus]], [[Christian]]s and [[Zoroastrianism|Zoroastrians]] are allowed to apply for permits for alcohol. The monthly quota depends on their income but is usually about five bottles of liquor or 100 bottles of beer. In a country of 180 million, only about 60 outlets are allowed to sell alcohol and there used to be only one legal brewery, [[Murree Brewery]] in [[Rawalpindi]], Now there are more. Enforced by the country's Islamic Ideology Council, the ban is strictly policed. However, members of religious minorities often sell their liquor permits to Muslims and a black market trade in alcohol continues.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theage.com.au/articles/2003/03/10/1047144915849.html?from=moreStories |title=Lone brewer small beer in Pakistan |publisher=theage.com.au |date=2003-03-11 |accessdate=2010-04-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Middle East==
Numerous countries in the Middle East including Iran, Yemen, Libya, Saudi Arabia&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://travel.state.gov/travel/cis_pa_tw/cis/cis_1012.html |title=Saudi Arabia |publisher=Travel.state.gov |date= |accessdate=2012-10-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Kuwait ban alcohol.

==Elections==
In many countries in [[Latin America]], the [[Philippines]], and several US states, the sale but not the consumption of alcohol is prohibited before and during [[election]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Massachusetts General Laws 138 33.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.history.com/topics/prohibition Prohibition]--View Videos&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Baptists and Bootleggers]]
* [[Iron Law of Prohibition]]
* [[Legal drinking age]]
* [[Prohibition of drugs]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
* Susanna Barrows, Robin Room, and Jeffrey Verhey (eds.), ''The Social History of Alcohol: Drinking and Culture in Modern Society'' (Berkeley, Calif: Alcohol Research Group, 1987)
* Susanna Barrows and Robin Room (eds.), ''Drinking: Behavior and Belief in Modern History'' University of California Press, (1991)
* Jack S. Blocker, David M. Fahey, and Ian R. Tyrrell eds. ''Alcohol and Temperance in Modern History: An International Encyclopedia'' 2 Vol. (2003)
* JS Blocker, Jr. &quot;Did prohibition really work? Alcohol prohibition as a public health innovation.&quot; Am J Public Health. 2006 Feb;96(2):233-43. Epub 2005 27 December.
* Ernest Cherrington, ed., ''Standard Encyclopaedia of the Alcohol Problem'' 6 volumes (1925–1930), comprehensive international coverage to late 1920s
* Jessie Forsyth ''Collected Writings of Jessie Forsyth 1847-1937: The Good Templars and Temperance Reform on Three Continents'' ed by David M. Fahey (1988)
* Gefou-Madianou. ''Alcohol, Gender and Culture'' (European Association of Social Anthropologists) (1992)
* Dwight B. Heath, ed; ''International Handbook on Alcohol and Culture'' Greenwood Press, (1995)
*[[Max Henius]]   ''Modern liquor legislation and systems in Finland, Norway, Denmark and Sweden'' (1931)
*[[Max Henius]] ''The error in the National prohibition act''  (1931)
* Patricia Herlihy; ''The Alcoholic Empire: Vodka &amp; Politics in Late Imperial Russia'' Oxford University Press, (2002)
* Daniel Okrent. ''Last Call; The Rise and Fall of Prohibition''. New York: Scribner, 2010. 
* Sulkunen, Irma. ''History of the Finnish Temperance Movement: Temperance As a Civic Religion'' (1991)
*  Tyrrell, Ian; ''Woman's World/Woman's Empire: The Woman's Christian Temperance Union in International Perspective, 1880-1930'' U of North Carolina Press, (1991)
* Mark Thornton, ''[http://www.cato.org/publications/policy-analysis/alcohol-prohibition-was-failure &quot;Alcohol Prohibition was a Failure,&quot;]'' Policy Analysis, Washington DC: Cato Institute, 1991.
* Mark Thornton, ''[http://mises.org/books/prohibition.pdf The Economics of Prohibition]'', Salt Lake City, UT: [[University of Utah Press]], 1991.
* White, Helene R. (ed.), ''Society, Culture and Drinking Patterns Reexamined'' (New Brunswick, N.J.: Rutgers Center of Alcohol Studies, 1991).
* White, Stephen.''Russia Goes Dry: Alcohol, State and Society'' (1995)
* Robert S. Walker and Samuel C. Patterson, OKLAHOMA GOES WET: THE REPEAL OF PROHIBITION (McGraw-Hill Book Co. Eagleton Institute Rutgers University 1960).
* Samuel C. Patterson and Robert S. Walker, &quot;The Political Attitudes of Oklahoma Newspapers Editors: The Prohibition Issue,&quot; The Southwestern Social Science Quarterly (1961)
* Farness, Kate, &quot;One Half So Precious&quot;, Dodd, Mead, and Company, (1995)


{{Prohibition}}
{{Alcohol and health}}

[[Category:Prohibition| ]]

[[ar:منع الكحول]]
[[ca:Llei seca]]
[[cs:Prohibice]]
[[de:Prohibition#Alkoholprohibition]]
[[es:Ley seca]]
[[eu:Lege lehor]]
[[fr:Prohibition]]
[[ko:금주법]]
[[hr:Prohibicija]]
[[is:Bannár]]
[[it:Proibizionismo]]
[[ka:მშრალი კანონი]]
[[hu:Szesztilalom]]
[[ja:禁酒令]]
[[no:Forbudstiden]]
[[pl:Prohibicja]]
[[pt:Lei seca]]
[[ru:Сухой закон]]
[[sk:Prohibícia]]
[[sl:Prohibicija]]
[[sr:Прохибиција]]
[[fi:Kieltolaki]]
[[sv:Alkoholförbud]]
[[ta:மதுவிலக்கு]]
[[tr:İçki yasağı]]
[[zh:禁酒令]]</text>
      <sha1>8ouydp2flsjl3axukc8y1d2qpr0i6ek</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
