<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Roswell UFO incident</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>376985</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520326273</id>
      <parentid>520296225</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-28T21:32:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>David J Johnson</username>
        <id>12472594</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Undid revision 520296225 by [[Special:Contributions/81.156.40.93|81.156.40.93]] ([[User talk:81.156.40.93|talk]]) Un-necessary.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="85963">{{Infobox historical event
  |Event_Name     = Roswell UFO incident
  |Image_Name    = RoswellDailyRecordJuly8,1947.jpg
  |Imagesize      = 300px
  |Image_Alt      = 
  |Image_Caption  = ''[[Roswell Daily Record]]'', July 8, 1947, announcing the &quot;capture&quot; of a &quot;flying saucer.&quot;
  |Thumb_Time     = 
  |AKA            = 
  |Participants   =
  |Location       = [[Chaves County, New Mexico]], United States
  |Date           = 1947
  |nongregorian   = 
  |Deaths        = 
  |Result         = 
  |URL            = 
}}

The '''Roswell UFO Incident''', also known simply as '''Roswell''', was a report of an object that crashed near [[Roswell, New Mexico]], in June or July 1947, allegedly an extra-terrestrial spacecraft and its alien occupants. Since the late 1970s the incident has been the subject of intense controversy and several [[conspiracy theory|conspiracy theories]] as to the true nature of the object that crashed. The [[United States Armed Forces]] maintains that what was recovered was debris from an experimental high-altitude surveillance balloon belonging to a classified program named &quot;[[Project Mogul|Mogul]]&quot;;&lt;ref&gt;United States Air Force (Col. Richard L. Weaver, USAF; 1st LT. James MacAndrew, USAFR), ''The Roswell Report: Fact versus Fiction in the New Mexico Desert'' (1995)&lt;/ref&gt; many [[Unidentified flying object|UFO]] proponents maintain that an  [[Extraterrestrial life|alien]] craft was found and its occupants were captured, and that the military then engaged in a cover-up. The incident has turned into a widely known [[popular culture|pop culture]] phenomenon, making the name Roswell synonymous with UFOs. It is the most publicized and controversial of alleged UFO incidents.&lt;ref name=&quot;ARoswellRequiem&quot;/&gt;

On July 8, 1947, the [[Walker Air Force Base|Roswell Army Air Field]] (RAAF) [[public information officer]] [[Walter Haut]] in Roswell, New Mexico, issued a [[press release]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ufologie.net/rw/p/rdr8jul1947.htm |title=ufo - UFOS at close sight: Roswell 1947, article, Roswell Daily Record, July 8, 1947 |date= |accessdate=2011-09-15 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20050512051045/http://ufologie.net/rw/p/rdr8jul1947.htm |archivedate=2005-05-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; stating that personnel from the field's [[509th Operations Group|509th Bomb Group]] had recovered a crashed &quot;flying disk&quot; from a ranch near Roswell, sparking intense media interest. The next day, the press reported that [[Commanding General]] of the [[Eighth Air Force]] [[Roger M. Ramey]] stated that, in fact, a [[weather balloon|radar-tracking balloon]] had been recovered by the RAAF personnel, not a &quot;flying disc.&quot;&lt;ref name=fas&gt;{{cite web | title = Results of a Search for Records Concerning the 1947 Crash Near Roswell, New Mexico (Letter Report, 07/28/95, GAO/NSIAD-95-187) | work = General Accounting Office Government Records | publisher = Federation of American Scientists (Republished by) | url = http://www.fas.org/sgp/othergov/roswell.html | accessdate = 2006-10-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt; A subsequent [[News conference|press conference]] was called, featuring debris said to be from the crashed object, which seemed to confirm the weather balloon description.

The incident was forgotten and almost completely ignored, even by UFO researchers, for more than 30 years. Then, in 1978, physicist and [[ufologist]] [[Stanton T. Friedman]] interviewed Major [[Witness accounts of the Roswell UFO incident#Jesse Marcel's testimony|Jesse Marcel]] who was involved with the original recovery of the debris in 1947. Marcel expressed his belief that the military had covered up the recovery of an alien spacecraft. His story spread through UFO circles, being featured in some UFO documentaries at the time.&lt;ref name=&quot;ARoswellRequiem&quot;&gt;B.D. Gildenberg. &quot;A Roswell Requiem&quot;. ''Skeptic'' 10-1 (2003).&lt;/ref&gt; In February 1980, ''[[The National Enquirer]]'' ran its own interview with Marcel, garnering national and worldwide attention for the Roswell incident.&lt;ref name=&quot;ARoswellRequiem&quot;/&gt;

Additional witnesses added significant new details, including claims of a huge [[military operation]] dedicated to recovering alien craft and aliens themselves, at as many as 11 crash sites,&lt;ref name=&quot;ARoswellRequiem&quot;/&gt; and alleged witness intimidation. In 1989, former [[funeral director|mortician]] [[Glenn Dennis]] put forth a detailed personal account, wherein he claimed that [[Alien autopsy|alien autopsies]] were carried out at the Roswell base.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Roswell Report: Case Closed&quot;&gt;“The Roswell Report: Case Closed,” Appendix C, &quot;Transcript of interview with W. Glenn Dennis&quot;, interview with Karl T. Pflock, November 2, 1992, p. 211-226, James McAndrews, Headquarters United States Air Force, 1997 http://web.archive.org/web/20080413203804/http://www.gl.iit.edu/wadc/history/Roswell/roswell.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

In response to these reports, and after [[United States Congress|congressional]] inquiries, the [[Government Accountability Office|General Accounting Office]] launched an inquiry and directed the Office of the [[United States Secretary of the Air Force|Secretary of the Air Force]] to conduct an internal investigation. The result was summarized in two reports. The first, released in 1995, concluded that the reported recovered material in 1947 was likely debris from a secret government program called [[Project Mogul]], which involved high altitude balloons meant to detect sound waves generated by Soviet atomic bomb tests and ballistic missiles.&lt;ref&gt;[http://video.google.com/videoplay?docid=-2334857802602777622 Physics lecture in which Prof. Richard A. Muller gives a detailed explanation of the science behind the 1947 event] (Google Video)&lt;/ref&gt; The second report, released in 1997, concluded that reports of recovered alien bodies were likely a combination of innocently transformed memories of military accidents involving injured or killed personnel, innocently transformed memories of the recovery of [[anthropomorphism|anthropomorphic]] dummies in military programs like [[Operation High Dive|Project High Dive]] conducted in the 1950s, and hoaxes perpetrated by various witnesses and UFO proponents. The psychological effects of time compression and confusion about when events occurred explained the discrepancy with the years in question. These reports were dismissed by UFO proponents as being either [[disinformation]] or simply implausible. However, numerous high-profile UFO researchers discount the possibility that the incident had anything to do with aliens.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Pflock now believes that no flying saucer crashed in New Mexico in 1947&quot; (article), &quot;The Klass Files&quot;, from &quot;The Sceptics UFO Newsletter&quot; (SUN) #43, January 1997, http://web.archive.org/web/20110604124016/http://www.csicop.org/klassfiles/SUN-43.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Another Major Roswell Crashed-Saucer Proponent 'Abandons Ship'&quot; (article), &quot;The Klass Files&quot;, from &quot;The Skeptics UFO Newsletter&quot; (SUN) #44,March 1997, http://web.archive.org/web/20110604124029/http://www.csicop.org/klassfiles/SUN-44.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;STOP THE PRESSES!&quot; (article), &quot;The Klass Files&quot;, from &quot;The Sceptics UFO Newsletter&quot; (SUN) #47, September 1997, http://web.archive.org/web/20110604124049/http://www.csicop.org/klassfiles/SUN-47.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Contemporary accounts of materials found==
[[File:SacramentoBeeArticleJuly8,1947.jpg|thumb|right|''[[The Sacramento Bee]]'' article detailing the [[Roswell Army Air Field|RAAF]] statements]]
On June 14, 1947, William Ware &quot;Mack&quot; or &quot;Mac&quot; Brazel noticed some strange clusters of debris while working on the Foster homestead, where he was foreman, some {{convert|30|mi|-1}} north of Roswell. This date (or &quot;about three weeks&quot; before July 8) appeared in later stories featuring Brazel, but the initial press release from the Roswell Army Air Field said the find was &quot;sometime last week,&quot; suggesting Brazel found the debris in early July.&lt;ref name=telex1&gt;{{cite web | title = United Press Teletype Messages | publisher = Roswell Proof (republished by) | url = http://roswellproof.homestead.com/United_Press_Telexes.html | accessdate = 2006-10-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Brazel told the Roswell Daily Record that he and his son saw a &quot;large area of bright wreckage made up of rubber strips, tinfoil, a rather tough paper and sticks.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.archive.org/web/20070108010347/http://ufologie.net/rw/p/roswelldailyrecord9jul1947.htm |title=ufo - UFOS at close sight: Roswell 1947, the Press, Roswell Daily Record, July 9 |publisher=Web.archive.org |date= |accessdate=2011-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; He paid little attention to it but returned on July 4 with his son, wife and daughter to gather up the material.&lt;ref name=tpretty&gt;{{cite web | last = Printy | first = Timothy | title = A mystery on a ranch | year= 1999 | url = http://home.comcast.net/~tprinty/UFO/discover.htm | accessdate = 2009-07-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Some accounts have described Brazel as having gathered some of the material earlier, rolling it together and stashing it under some brush.&lt;ref name=ap3jnine&gt;{{cite web | title = Associated Press Main Roswell Story | publisher = Roswell Proof (Republished by) | date= 1947-06-09 | url = http://roswellproof.com/AP3_Main_July9.html | accessdate = 2006-10-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The next day, Brazel heard reports about &quot;flying discs&quot; and wondered if that was what he had picked up.&lt;ref name=tpretty/&gt; On July 7, Brazel saw Sheriff Wilcox and &quot;whispered kinda confidential like&quot; that he may have found a flying disc.&lt;ref name=tpretty/&gt; Another account quotes Wilcox as saying that Brazel reported the object on July 6.&lt;ref name=telex1/&gt;

Sheriff Wilcox called Roswell Army Air Field. Major [[Jesse Marcel]] and a &quot;man in plainclothes&quot; accompanied Brazel back to the ranch where more pieces were picked up. &quot;[We] spent a couple of hours Monday afternoon [July 7] looking for any more parts of the weather device&quot;, said Marcel. &quot;We found a few more patches of tinfoil and rubber.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Fort Worth Star-Telegram | publisher = Roswell Proof (Republished by) | date= 1947-06-09 | url = http://roswellproof.homestead.com/FortWorthST_July9.html | accessdate = 2006-10-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

As described in the July 9, 1947, edition of the ''[[Roswell Daily Record]]'',

{{Quote|The balloon which held it up, if that was how it worked, must have been 12&amp;nbsp;feet long, [Brazel] felt, measuring the distance by the size of the room in which he sat. The rubber was smoky gray in color and scattered over an area about 200 yards in diameter. When the debris was gathered up, the tinfoil, paper, tape, and sticks made a bundle about three feet long and 7 or 8 inches thick, while the rubber made a bundle about 18 or 20 inches long and about 8 inches thick. In all, he estimated, the entire lot would have weighed maybe five pounds. There was no sign of any metal in the area which might have been used for an engine, and no sign of any propellers of any kind, although at least one paper fin had been glued onto some of the tinfoil. There were no words to be found anywhere on the instrument, although there were letters on some of the parts. Considerable Scotch tape and some tape with flowers printed upon it had been used in the construction. No strings or wires were to be found but there were some eyelets in the paper to indicate that some sort of attachment may have been used.&lt;ref name=rswdr&gt;{{cite news | title = Harassed Rancher who Located Saucer Sorry He Told About It | work = Roswell Daily Record | date= 1947-07-09 | url = http://www.angelfire.com/indie/anna_jones1/daily_record02.html | accessdate = 2006-10-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

A telex sent to an [[Federal Bureau of Investigation|FBI]] office from their office in [[Dallas, Texas]], quoted a major from the Eighth Air Force on July 8:

{{Quote|THE DISC IS HEXAGONAL IN SHAPE AND WAS SUSPENDED FROM A {{Sic|BALLON}} BY CABLE, WHICH BALLON WAS APPROXIMATELY TWENTY FEET IN DIAMETER. MAJOR CURTAN FURTHER ADVISED THAT THE OBJECT FOUND RESEMBLES A HIGH ALTITUDE WEATHER BALLOON WITH A RADAR REFLECTOR, BUT THAT TELEPHONIC CONVERSATION BETWEEN THEIR OFFICE AND WRIGHT FIELD HAD NOT [unintelligible] BORNE OUT THIS BELIEF.&lt;ref name=tprettydefla&gt;{{cite web | last = Printy | first = Timothy | title = A Deflating Experience | year= 1999 | url = http://home.comcast.net/~tprinty/UFO/FtWorth.htm | accessdate = 2009-07-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

[[File:Nssl0020.jpg|upright|right|thumb|A NOAA [[weather balloon]] just after launch]]
Early on Tuesday, July 8, the Roswell Army Air Field issued a press release, which was immediately picked up by numerous news outlets:

{{Quote|The many rumors regarding the flying disc became a reality yesterday when the intelligence office of the [[509th Operations Group|509th Bomb group]] of the Eighth Air Force, Roswell Army Air Field, was fortunate enough to gain possession of a disc through the cooperation of one of the local ranchers and the sheriff's office of [[Chaves County, New Mexico|Chaves County]]. The flying object landed on a ranch near Roswell sometime last week. Not having phone facilities, the rancher stored the disc until such time as he was able to contact the sheriff's office, who in turn notified Maj. Jesse A. Marcel of the 509th Bomb Group Intelligence Office. Action was immediately taken and the disc was picked up at the rancher's home. It was inspected at the Roswell Army Air Field and subsequently loaned by Major Marcel to higher headquarters.&lt;ref name=raff1&gt;{{cite web | last = Printy | first = Timothy | title = Exciting Times for Roswell | year= 1999 | url = http://home.comcast.net/~tprinty/UFO/RAAF.htm | accessdate = 2006-07-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Colonel [[William H. Blanchard]], commanding officer of the 509th, contacted General Roger M. Ramey of the Eighth Air Force in [[Fort Worth, Texas]], and Ramey ordered the object be flown to [[Carswell Air Force Base|Fort Worth Army Air Field]]. At the base, [[Warrant Officer (United States)#Air Force|Warrant Officer]] Irving Newton confirmed Ramey’s preliminary opinion, identifying the object as being a weather balloon and its &quot;kite,&quot;&lt;ref name=ap3jnine/&gt; a nickname for a radar reflector used to track the balloons from the ground. Another news release was issued, this time from the Fort Worth base, describing the object as being a &quot;weather balloon&quot;.

In Fort Worth, several news photographs were taken that day of debris said to be from the object.

==Witness accounts emerge==

===New witness accounts and the emergence of alien narratives===
{{See also|Witness accounts of the Roswell UFO incident}}

In 1978, nuclear physicist and author [[Stanton T. Friedman]] interviewed Jesse Marcel, the only person known to have accompanied the Roswell debris from where it was recovered to Fort Worth where reporters saw material said to be part of the recovered object. Over the next few years, the accounts he and others gave elevated Roswell from a forgotten incident to perhaps the most famous UFO case of all time.&lt;ref name=&quot;ARoswellRequiem&quot;/&gt;

By the early 1990s, UFO researchers such as Friedman, [[Bill Moore (ufologist)|William Moore]], [[Karl T. Pflock]], and the team of [[Kevin D. Randle]] and Donald R. Schmitt had interviewed several hundred people who had, or claimed to have had, a connection with the events at Roswell in 1947.&lt;ref name=korff-csi&gt;Kal K. Korff, &quot;[http://www.csicop.org/si/show/what_really_happened_at_roswell What Really Happened at Roswell]&quot;, ''Skeptical Inquirer (July 1997).&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, hundreds of documents were obtained via Freedom of Information Act requests, as were some apparently leaked by insiders, such as the disputed &quot;[[Majestic 12]]&quot; documents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.roswellfiles.com/FOIA/majestic12.htm |title=Majestic 12 and the Roswell UFO Incident Story |publisher=Roswellfiles.com |date= |accessdate=2011-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Their conclusions were that at least one alien craft had crashed in the Roswell vicinity, that aliens, some possibly still alive, were recovered, and that a massive cover-up of any knowledge of the incident was put in place.

Numerous books, articles, television specials and even a made-for-TV movie brought the 1947 incident fame and notoriety so that by the mid-1990s, strong majorities in polls, such as a 1997 [[CNN]]/''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'' poll, believed that aliens had visited earth and specifically that aliens had landed at Roswell and the government was covering up the fact.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ufoevidence.org/documents/doc830.htm Poll: U.S. hiding knowledge of aliens - UFO Evidence&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

A new narrative emerged, which was at strong odds with what was reported in 1947. This narrative evolved over the years from the time the first book on Roswell was published in 1980 as many new witnesses and accounts emerged, drawn out in part by publicity on the incident. Though skeptics had many objections to the plausibility of these accounts, it was not until 1994 and the publication of the first Air Force report on the incident that a strong counter-argument to the presence of aliens was widely publicized.

Numerous scenarios emerged from these authors as to what they felt were the true sequence of events, depending on which witness accounts were embraced or dismissed, and what the documentary evidence suggested. This was especially true in regards to the various claimed crash and recovery sites of alien craft, as various authors had different witnesses and different locations for these events.&lt;ref name=&quot;ARoswellRequiem&quot;/&gt;

The following general outline from ''UFO Crash at Roswell'' (1991) by Kevin D. Randle and Donald R. Schmitt is common to most of these accounts:

{{quote|A UFO crashed northwest of Roswell, New Mexico, in the summer of 1947. The military acted quickly and efficiently to recover the debris after its existence was reported by a ranch hand. The debris, unlike anything these highly trained men had ever seen, was flown without delay to at least three government installations. A cover story was concocted to explain away the debris and the flurry of activity. It was explained that a weather balloon, one with a new radiosonde target device, had been found and temporarily confused the personnel of the 509th Bomb Group. Government officials took reporters' notes from their desks and warned a radio reporter not to play a recorded interview with the ranch hand. The men who took part in the recovery were told never to talk about the incident. And with a whimper, not a bang, the Roswell event faded quickly from public view and press scrutiny.&lt;ref&gt;Randle and Schmitt 1991, p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

What follows is accounts of the sequence of events according to some of the major books published on the subject.

===''The Roswell Incident'' (1980)===

The first book on the subject, ''The Roswell Incident'' by [[Charles Berlitz]] and William L. Moore, was published in 1980.&lt;ref name=berlitz-general&gt;Charles Berlitz/William L. Moore. ''The Roswell Incident''. New York: Grosset &amp; Dunlap (1980). ISBN 0-448-21199-8.&lt;/ref&gt; The authors at the time said they had interviewed more than ninety witnesses. Though uncredited, Stanton Friedman did substantial research for the book.&lt;ref name=korff-general&gt;Kal K. Korff. ''The Roswell UFO Crash: What They Don't Want You to Know''. Prometheus Books (1997). ISBN 1-57392-127-0.&lt;/ref&gt; The book featured accounts of debris described by Jesse Marcel as &quot;nothing made on this earth.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Berlitz28&quot;&gt;Berlitz/Moore. ''The Roswell Incident'', p. 28.&lt;/ref&gt; Additional accounts suggested that the material Marcel recovered had super-strength and other attributes not associated with anything known of terrestrial origin, and certainly not anything associated with a &quot;weather balloon&quot; which was the official description of the object. The book also introduced the contention that debris recovered by Marcel  at the Foster ranch (visible in photographs showing Marcel posing with the debris) was substituted for debris from a weather device (visible in pictures with Gen. Ramey, Marcel and others) as part of a cover-up.&lt;ref name=&quot;Berlitz33&quot;&gt;Berlitz/Moore. ''The Roswell Incident'', p. 33, 67-69.&lt;/ref&gt; The actual debris recovered from the ranch—which, the authors claimed, was from a crashed UFO—was not permitted a close inspection by the press. Also described were efforts by the military to discredit and &quot;counteract the growing hysteria towards flying saucers&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Berlitz42&quot;&gt;Berlitz/Moore. ''The Roswell Incident'', p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, various accounts of witness intimidation were included, in particular reports of the incarceration of Mac Brazel, who reported the debris in the first place. (These reports came from relatives and others as Brazel had died years earlier.)

A report of Roswell residents Dan Wilmot and his wife seeing an object &quot;like two inverted saucers faced mouth to mouth&quot; passing overhead on the evening of July 2 was included,&lt;ref name=&quot;Berlitz21&quot;&gt;Berlitz/Moore. ''The Roswell Incident'', p. 21-22.&lt;/ref&gt; as were other reports of mysterious objects seen flying overhead.&lt;ref name=&quot;Berlitz25&quot;&gt;Berlitz/Moore. ''The Roswell Incident'', pp. 25-27.&lt;/ref&gt; The book also introduced an alien account by Barney Barnett who had died years earlier. Friends said he had on numerous occasions described the crash of a flying saucer and the recovery of alien corpses in the [[Socorro, New Mexico|Socorro]] area, about {{convert|150|mi}} west of the Foster ranch. He and a group of [[archaeology|archaeologists]] who happened to be in the vicinity had stumbled upon an alien craft and its occupants on the morning of July 3, only to be led away by military personnel.&lt;ref name=&quot;Berlitz53&quot;&gt;Berlitz/Moore. ''The Roswell Incident'', p. 53-62.&lt;/ref&gt; Further accounts suggested that these aliens and their craft were shipped to [[Edwards Air Force Base]] (known then as Muroc Army Air Field) in [[California]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BerlitzCh5&quot;&gt;Berlitz/Moore. ''The Roswell Incident'', pp 92-103.&lt;/ref&gt; The book suggested that either there were two crafts that crashed, or debris from the vehicle Barnett had described had landed on the Foster ranch after an explosion.&lt;ref name=&quot;Berlitz53&quot;/&gt;

Marcel said he &quot;heard about it on July 7&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Berlitz63&quot;&gt;Berlitz/Moore ''The Roswell Incident'', p. 63.&lt;/ref&gt; when the sheriff whom Brazel had called him, but also said that &quot;[on] Sunday, July 6, Brazel decided he had better go into town and report this to someone,&quot; who in turn called Marcel, suggesting, though not stating, that he was contacted July 6.&lt;ref name=&quot;Berlitz65&quot;&gt;Berlitz/Moore. ''The Roswell Incident'', p. 65.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1947, Marcel was quoted as saying he visited the ranch on Monday, July 7.

Marcel described returning to Roswell the evening of July 7 to find that news of the discovery of a flying disc had leaked out. Calls were made to his house, including a visit from a reporter, but he would not confirm the reports for the press. &quot;The next morning, that written press release went out, and after that things really hit the fan.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Berlitz67&quot;&gt;Berlitz/Moore. ''The Roswell Incident'', p. 67.&lt;/ref&gt;

The book suggested that the military orchestrated Brazel's testimony to make it appear a mundane object had landed on the ranch, though the book did not explicitly say that the military instructed Brazel to give a mid-June date for his discovery. &quot;Brazel... [went] to great pains to tell the newspaper people exactly what the Air Force had instructed him to say regarding how he had come to discover the wreckage and what it looked like ...&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Berlitz40&quot;&gt;Berlitz/Moore. ''The Roswell Incident'', p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt;

===''UFO Crash at Roswell'' (1991)===

In 1991, with the benefit of a decade of publicity on the incident and numerous new witness interviews, Kevin D. Randle and Donald R. Schmitt published ''UFO Crash at Roswell''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Randle-general&quot;&gt;Kevin D. Randle, Donald R. Schmitt. ''UFO Crash at Roswell''. Avon Books (1991). ISBN 0-380-76196-3.&lt;/ref&gt;

Timelines were slightly altered. The date that Brazel reported the debris and Marcel went to the ranch was said to be Sunday, July 6, not the next day as some of the original accounts suggested, and ''The Roswell Incident'' had left unclear. Additionally, Marcel and an unidentified counter-intelligence agent spent the night at the ranch, something not mentioned previously. They gathered material on Monday, then Marcel dropped by his house on the way to the Roswell base in the early hours of Tuesday, July 8.

Significant new details emerged, including accounts of a &quot;gouge... that extended four or five hundred feet&quot; at the ranch&lt;ref name=&quot;Randle200&quot;&gt;Randle/Schmitt. ''UFO Crash at Roswell'', p. 200.&lt;/ref&gt; and descriptions of an elaborate cordon and recovery operation. (Several witnesses in ''The Roswell Incident'' described being turned back from the Foster ranch by armed military police, but more extensive descriptions were lacking.)

The Barnett accounts were mentioned, though the dates and locations were changed from the accounts found in ''The Roswell Incident''. In this new account, Brazel is described as leading the Army to a second crash site on the ranch, where the Army was &quot;horrified to find civilians [including Barnett] there already.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Randle206&quot;&gt;Randle/Schmitt. ''UFO Crash at Roswell'', p. 206.&lt;/ref&gt;

New witness accounts added substantially to the reports of aliens and their recovery. Glenn Dennis had emerged as an important witness after calling the hotline when an episode of “Unsolved Mysteries” featured the Roswell incident in 1989. His descriptions of [[Alien autopsy|Roswell alien autopsies]] were the first to place alien corpses at the Roswell Army Air Base.&lt;ref name=&quot;ARoswellRequiem&quot;/&gt;

No mention, except in passing, was made of the claim found in ''The Roswell Incident'' that the Roswell aliens and their craft were shipped to Edwards Air Force Base. The book established a chain of events with alien corpses seen at a crash site, their bodies shipped to the Roswell base as witnessed by Dennis, and then flown to Fort Worth and finally to [[Wright Field]] in [[Dayton, Ohio]], the last known location of the bodies (accounts assembled in part from the testimony of Frank Kaufmann and Capt. O. W. Henderson).

The book also introduced an account from General Arthur E. Exon, an officer stationed at the alleged final resting place of the recovered material. He stated there was a shadowy group, which he called the Unholy Thirteen, who controlled and had access to whatever was recovered.&lt;ref name=&quot;Randle231&quot;&gt;Randle/Schmitt. ''UFO Crash at Roswell'', p. 231-234.&lt;/ref&gt; He later stated:

{{quote|In the '55 time period [when Exon was at [[the Pentagon]]], there was also the story that whatever happened, whatever was found at Roswell was still closely held and probably would be held until these fellows I mentioned had died so they wouldn't be embarrassed or they wouldn't have to explain why they covered it up. ... until the original thirteen died off and I don't think anyone is going to release anything [until] the last one's gone.&lt;ref&gt;Kevin Randle. ''Roswell UFO Crash Update. Roswell UFO Crash Update, Exploring the Military Cover-Up of the Century''. New York, Global Communications (1995).{{Clarify|date=December 2009}}, see also http://www.roswellproof.com/exon.html&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===''Crash at Corona'' (1992)===

In 1992, ''Crash at Corona'', written by Stanton Friedman and Don Berliner, suggested a high-level cover-up of a UFO recovery, based on documents they obtained such as the [[Majestic 12]] archive.&lt;ref name=Friedman-general&gt;Stanton T. Friedman, Don Berliner. ''Crash at Corona: The U.S. Military Retrieval and Cover-up of a UFO''. Paragon House (1992). ISBN 1-55778-449-3.&lt;/ref&gt; These documents were anonymously dropped off at a UFO researcher’s house in 1984 and purported to be 1952 briefing papers for incoming President [[Dwight Eisenhower]] describing a high-level government agency whose purpose was to investigate aliens recovered at Roswell and to keep such information hidden from public view. Friedman had done much of the research for ''The Roswell Incident'' with William Moore, and ''Crash at Corona'' built on that research. The title contains [[Corona, New Mexico|Corona]] instead of Roswell as Corona is geographically closer to the Foster ranch crash site.&lt;ref name=FriedmanIX&gt;Friedman/Berliner. ''Crash at Corona'', p. ix.&lt;/ref&gt;

The time-line is largely the same as previously, with Marcel and Sheridan Cavitt, a counter-intelligence agent who was likely the &quot;man in plainclothes&quot; described by Brazel in 1947, visiting the ranch on Sunday, July 6. But the book says that Brazel was &quot;taken into custody for about a week&quot; and escorted into the offices of the Roswell Daily Record on July 10 where he gave an account he was told to give by the government.&lt;ref name=Friedman79&gt;Friedman/Berliner. ''Crash at Corona'', p. 79-90.&lt;/ref&gt;

A sign of the disputes between various researchers is on display as Friedman and Berliner move the Barnett account back to near Socorro and introduce a new eyewitness account of the site from Gerald Anderson who provided vivid descriptions of both a downed alien craft and four aliens, of which at least one was alive.&lt;ref name=Friedman90&gt;Friedman/Berliner. ''Crash at Corona'', p. 90-97.&lt;/ref&gt; The authors note that much of their evidence had been dismissed by ''UFO Crash at Roswell'' &quot;without a solid basis&quot;&lt;ref name=Friedman206&gt;Friedman/Berliner. ''Crash at Corona'', p. 206.&lt;/ref&gt; and that &quot;a personality conflict between Anderson and Randle&quot; meant that Friedman was the author who investigated his claim.&lt;ref name=Friedman89&gt;Friedman/Berliner. ''Crash at Corona'', p. 89.&lt;/ref&gt; The book, however, largely embraces the sequence of events from ''UFO Crash at Roswell'', where aliens are seen at the Roswell Army Air Field, based on the Dennis account, and then shipped off to Fort Worth and then Wright Field.

The book suggests as many as eight alien corpses were recovered from two crash sites: three dead and perhaps one alive from the Foster ranch, and three dead and one living from the Socorro site.&lt;ref name=Friedman129&gt;Friedman/Berliner. ''Crash at Corona'', p. 129.&lt;/ref&gt;

===''The Truth about the UFO Crash at Roswell'' (1994)===

In 1994, Randle and Schmitt published a second book, ''The Truth about the UFO Crash at Roswell''.&lt;ref name=&quot;RandleTruth-general&quot;&gt;Kevin D. Randle, Donald R. Schmitt. ''The Truth About the UFO Crash at Roswell''. M Evans &amp; Co. ISBN 0-87131-761-3.&lt;/ref&gt;  while restating much of the case as laid out in their earlier book, new and expanded accounts of aliens were included, and a new location for the recovery of aliens was detailed. Additionally, an almost completely new scenario as to the sequence of events was laid out.

For the first time, the object was said to have crashed on the evening of Friday, July 4 instead of Wednesday July 2, the date in all the previous books. Another important difference was the assertion that the alien recovery was well under way before Brazel went into Roswell with his news about debris on the Foster ranch. Indeed, several objects had been tracked by radar for a few days in the vicinity before one crashed. In all previous accounts, the military was made aware of the alleged alien crash only when Brazel came forward. Additionally, Brazel was said to have given his news conference on July 9, and his press conference and the initial news release announcing the discovery of a &quot;flying disc&quot; were all part of an elaborate ruse to shift attention away from the &quot;true&quot; crash site.

The book featured a new witness account describing an alien craft and aliens from Jim Ragsdale, at a new location just north of Roswell, instead of closer to Corona on the Foster ranch. Corroboration was given by accounts from a group of archaeologists. Five alien corpses were seen.&lt;ref name=&quot;RandleTruth3&quot;&gt;Randle/Schmitt. ''The Truth About the UFO Crash at Roswell'', p. 3-11.&lt;/ref&gt; While the Foster ranch was a source of debris as well, no bodies were recovered there.

Expanded accounts came from Dennis and Kaufmann. And a new account from Ruben Anaya described New Mexico Lieutenant Governor [[Joseph Montoya]]'s claim that he saw alien corpses at the Roswell base.

More disagreement between Roswell researchers is on display in the book. A full chapter is devoted to dismissing the Barnett and Anderson accounts from Socorro, a central part of ''Crash at Corona'' and ''The Roswell Incident''. &quot;...Barnett's story, and in fact, the Plains [of San Augustin, near Soccoro] scenario, must be discarded&quot;, say the authors.&lt;ref name=&quot;RandleTruth155&quot;&gt;Randle/Schmitt. ''The Truth About the UFO Crash at Roswell'', p. 155.&lt;/ref&gt; An appendix is devoted to describing the Majestic 12 documents, another central part of ''Crash at Corona'', as a hoax.&lt;ref name=&quot;RandleTruth187&quot;&gt;Randle/Schmitt. ''The Truth About the UFO Crash at Roswell'', p. 187.&lt;/ref&gt;

The two Randle and Schmitt books remain highly influential in the UFO community, their interviews and conclusions widely reproduced on websites.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.roswellfiles.com/storytellers/RandleSchmitt.htm |title=The Roswell UFO Incident Storytellers Kevin Randle and Donald Schmitt |publisher=Roswellfiles.com |date= |accessdate=2011-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; Randle and Schmitt claimed to have &quot;conducted more than two thousand interviews with more than five hundred people&quot; during their Roswell investigations.&lt;ref&gt;Kevin Randle. ''Roswell UFO Crash Update. Roswell UFO Crash Update, Exploring the Military Cover-Up of the Century''. New York, Global Communications (1995).{{Clarify|date=December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===UFO community schism===

By the publication of ''The Truth About the UFO Crash at Roswell'' in 1994, a serious split had emerged within the UFO community as to the true sequence of the events and the locations of the alleged alien crash sites.&lt;ref name=&quot;Saler24&quot;&gt;Benson Saler, Charles A. Ziegler, Charles B. Moore. ''UFO Crash at Roswell: The Genesis of a Modern Myth''. Smithsonian Institution (1997), p. 24-25. ISBN 1-58834-063-5.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[CUFOS|Center for UFO Studies]] (CUFOS) and the [[MUFON|Mutual UFO Network]] (MUFON), two leading UFO societies, were at odds over the various scenarios presented by Randle/Schmitt and Friedman/Berliner, so much so that several conferences were held to try to resolve the differences. One of the issues under discussion was where, precisely, Barnett was when he saw the alien craft he was said to have encountered. A 1992 conference tried to achieve a consensus among the various scenarios as portrayed in ''Crash at Corona'' and ''UFO Crash at Roswell'', but the publication of ''The Truth About the UFO Crash at Roswell'' in 1994 &quot;resolved&quot; the Barnett problem by simply ignoring him and citing a new location for the alien craft recovery, including a new group of archaeologists not connected to the ones the Barnett story cited.&lt;ref name=&quot;Saler24&quot;/&gt;

===&quot;Alien autopsy&quot; footage===
{{Main|Alien autopsy}}

Film footage claimed to have been taken by a U.S. military official shortly after the Roswell incident, and purportedly showing an [[alien autopsy]], was released in 1995 by [[Ray Santilli]], a London-based video entrepreneur. The footage caused an international sensation when it aired on television networks around the world.  In 2006, Santilli admitted that the film was mostly a reconstruction but continued to claim that it was based on genuine footage now lost, and that some frames from the original remained. The story was retold in the comedy film ''[[Alien Autopsy (film)|Alien Autopsy]]'', released in 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/4873284.stm | work=BBC News | first=Michael | last=Osborn | title=Ant and Dec leap into the unknown | date=April 5, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/uk/article706122.ece | location=London | work=The Times | first=Marc | last=Horne | title=Max Headroom creator made Roswell alien | date=April 16, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Air Force and skeptics respond to alien reports==

===Air Force reports on the Roswell UFO incident===
{{Main|Air Force reports on the Roswell UFO incident}}

In the mid-1990s, the [[United States Air Force]] issued two reports that, they said, accounted for the debris found and reported on in 1947, and that also accounted for the later reports of alien recoveries. The reports identified the debris as coming from a top secret government experiment called [[Project Mogul]], which tested the feasibility of detecting [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] [[Nuclear weapon|nuclear]] tests and [[ballistic missiles]] with equipment on high-altitude balloons. Accounts of aliens were explained as resulting from misidentified military experiments that used anthropomorphic dummies, accidents involving injured or killed military personnel, and hoaxes perpetrated by various witnesses and UFO proponents.

The Air Force report formed a basis for a skeptical response to the claims many authors were making about the recovery of aliens, though skeptical researchers such as [[Philip J. Klass]] and Robert Todd had already been publishing articles for several years raising doubts about alien accounts before the Air Force issued its conclusions.

While books published into the 1990s suggested there was much more to the Roswell incident than the mere recovery of a weather balloon, [[Skepticism|skeptics]], and even some [[social anthropology|social anthropologists]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Saler2&quot;&gt;Saler/Ziegler/Moore. ''UFO Crash at Roswell: The Genesis of a Modern Myth''.&lt;/ref&gt; instead saw the increasingly elaborate accounts as evidence of a myth being constructed. After the release of the Air Force reports in the mid-1990s, several books, such as Kal K. Korff's ''The Roswell UFO Crash: What They Don't Want You To Know'', published in 1997, built on the evidence presented in the reports to conclude &quot;there is no credible evidence that the remains of an extraterrestrial spacecraft was involved.&quot;&lt;ref name=korff-csi/&gt;

Critics identified several reasons for their contention that the Roswell incident had nothing to do with aliens:

===Problems with witness accounts===
{{Main|Witness accounts of the Roswell UFO incident}}
Hundreds of witnesses were interviewed by the various researchers, a seemingly impressive figure, but a comparable few were true &quot;witnesses&quot; who claimed to have actually seen debris or aliens, critics point out. Most &quot;witnesses&quot; were in fact repeating the claims of others, and their testimony would be inadmissible hearsay in an American court, says Korff. Of the 90 witnesses claimed to have been interviewed for ''The Roswell Incident'', says Korff, the testimony of only 25 appear in the book, and only seven actually saw the debris. Of these, five handled the debris.&lt;ref name=korff29&gt;Korff. ''The Roswell UFO Crash'', p. 29.&lt;/ref&gt;

Karl T. Pflock, in his 2001 book ''Roswell: Inconvenient Facts and the Will to Believe'', makes a similar point about Randle and Schmitt's ''UFO Crash at Roswell.'' Some 271 people are listed in the book who were &quot;contacted and interviewed&quot; for the book, and this number does not include those who chose to remain anonymous, etc., meaning more than 300 &quot;witnesses&quot; were interviewed, a figure Pflock said the authors frequently cited.&lt;ref name=PflockInconv176&gt;Karl T. Pflock. ''Roswell: Inconvenient Facts and the Will to Believe''. Prometheus Books, Amherst, New York (2001), p. 176-177. ISBN 1-57392-894-1.&lt;/ref&gt; Of these 300-plus individuals, said Pflock, only 41 can be &quot;considered genuine first- or second-hand witnesses to the events in and around Roswell or at the Fort Worth Army Air Field,&quot; and only 23 can be &quot;reasonably thought to have seen physical evidence, debris recovered from the Foster Ranch.&quot; Of these, said Pflock, only seven have asserted anything suggestive of otherworldly origins for the debris.&lt;ref name=PflockInconv176/&gt;

As for the several accounts from those who claimed to have seen aliens, critics identified problems with these accounts ranging from the reliability of second-hand accounts (Pappy Henderson, General Exon, etc.), to serious credibility problems with witnesses making demonstrably false claims or multiple, contradictory accounts (Gerald Anderson, Glenn Dennis, Frank Kaufmann, Jim Ragsdale), to dubious death-bed &quot;confessions&quot; or accounts from elderly and easily confused witnesses (Maj. Edwin Easley, Lewis Rickett).&lt;ref name=korff-ch3&gt;Korff. ''The Roswell UFO Crash'', pp. 77-81; pp. 86-104; pp. 107-108.&lt;/ref&gt;

Pflock, writing in 2001, noted that only four people with firsthand knowledge of alien bodies were interviewed and identified by Roswell authors: Frank Kaufmann; Jim Ragsdale; Lt. Col. Albert Lovejoy Duran; Gerald Anderson.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt;Pflock. ''Roswell: Inconvenient Facts and the Will to Believe''. p. 118.&lt;/ref&gt; Duran is mentioned in a brief footnote in ''The Truth About the UFO Crash at Roswell'' and never again, while the other three all have serious credibility problems, said Pflock.

A basic problem with all the witness accounts, charge critics, is that they all came a minimum of 31 years after the events in question, and in many cases were recounted more than 40 years after the fact. Not only are memories this old of dubious reliability, say the critics, they were also subject to contamination from other accounts they may have heard.&lt;ref name=&quot;ARoswellRequiem&quot;/&gt;

Finally, the shifting claims of Jesse Marcel, whose suspicions that what he recovered in 1947 was &quot;not of this world&quot; sparked interest in the incident in the first place, cast serious doubt on the reliability of what he claimed, critics charge.

In ''The Roswell Incident'', Marcel stated: &quot;Actually, this material may have ''looked'' like tinfoil and balsa wood, but the resemblance ended there.&quot; And, &quot;They took one picture of me on the floor holding up some of the less-interesting metallic debris...The stuff in that one photo was pieces of the actual stuff we found. It was not a staged photo.&quot;&lt;ref name=berlitz-general/&gt; Timothy Printy points out that the material Marcel positively identified as being part of what he recovered is material that skeptics and UFO advocates agree is debris from a balloon device.&lt;ref name=tprettydefla/&gt;

After that fact was pointed out to him, Marcel changed his story to say that that material was not what he recovered.&lt;ref name=tprettydefla/&gt; Skeptics like Robert G. Todd argue that Marcel had a history of embellishment and exaggeration, such as claiming to have been a pilot and having received five Air Medals for shooting down enemy planes, claims that were found to be false, and his evolving Roswell story was another instance of this.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.roswellfiles.com/pdf/KowPflop120895.pdf |title=The Cowflop Quarterly, Vol.1 No. 3, Fri. December 8, 1995, Robert G. Todd |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2011-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Contradictory conclusions, questionable research, Roswell as a myth===

Critics point out that the large variety of claimed crash flights suggest events spanning many years have been incorporated into a single event&lt;ref name=&quot;ARoswellRequiem66&quot;&gt;Gildenberg. &quot;A Roswell Requiem&quot;, p. 66.&lt;/ref&gt; and that many authors uncritically embrace anything that suggests aliens, even when accounts contradict each other. Said Karl Pflock, a one-time advocate of an alien incident at Roswell: &quot;[T]he case for Roswell is a classic example of the triumph of quantity over quality. The advocates of the crashed-saucer tale... simply shovel everything that seems to support their view into the box marked 'Evidence' and say, 'See? Look at all this stuff. We ''must'' be right.' [emphasis in original] Never mind the contradictions. Never mind the lack of independent supporting fact. Never mind the blatant absurdities.&quot;&lt;ref name=PflockInconv223&gt;Pflock. ''Roswell: Inconvenient Facts and the Will to Believe''. p. 223.&lt;/ref&gt;

Kal Korff suggests there are clear incentives for some to promote the idea of aliens at Roswell, while many researchers are not doing competent work: &quot;[The] UFO field is {{sic|hide=y|comprised |of}} people who are willing to take advantage of the gullibility of others, especially the paying public. Let's not pull any punches here: The Roswell UFO myth has been very good business for UFO groups, publishers, for Hollywood, the town of Roswell, the media, and UFOlogy ... [The] number of researchers who employ science and its disciplined methodology is appallingly small.&quot;&lt;ref name=korff248&gt;Korff. ''The Roswell UFO Crash'', p. 248.&lt;/ref&gt;

Gildenberg and others said that, when added up, there were as many as 11 reported alien recovery sites&lt;ref name=&quot;ARoswellRequiem&quot;/&gt; and these recoveries bore only a marginal resemblance to the event as initially reported in 1947 or recounted later by the initial witnesses. Some of these new accounts could have been confused accounts of the several known recoveries of injured and dead from four military plane crashes that occurred in the vicinity from 1948–50.&lt;ref name=creatures1&gt;{{cite web | last = Printy | first = Timothy | title = The Creatures | year= 1999 | url = http://home.comcast.net/~tprinty/UFO/Easley.htm | accessdate = 2009-07-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Others could have been recoveries of [[Crash test dummy|test dummies]], as suggested by the Air Force in their reports.

Charles Ziegler argued that the Roswell story has all the hallmarks of a traditional folk narrative. He identified six distinct narratives, starting with ''The Roswell Incident'' (1980) and a process of transmission via storytellers with a core story that was created from various witness accounts, and was shaped and molded by those who carry on the group's (the UFO community) tradition. Others were sought out to expand the core narrative, with those who give accounts not in line with the core beliefs repudiated or omitted by the &quot;gatekeepers.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Saler34&quot;&gt;Saler/Ziegler/Moore. ''UFO Crash at Roswell'', p. 1, 34-37.&lt;/ref&gt; Others retold the narratives in new forms, and the process would repeat.

===Roswellian Syndrome===
Prominent skeptics [[Joe Nickell]] and co-author James McGaha identified the mythmaking process which they called the ‘Roswellian Syndrome’,&lt;ref name=syndrome&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Nickell|first1=Joe|last2=McGaha|first2=James|title=The Roswellian Syndrome: How Some UFO Myths Develop|journal=Skeptical Inquirer|volume=36|issue=3 May/June|pages=30–36|year=2012|publisher=Committee for Skeptical Inquiry}}&lt;/ref&gt; using the Roswell event as an example but the syndrome is readily observed in other [[UFO]] incidents.  They dissected the process and identified five distinguished stages of development of the myth:

''Incident''
The initial incident and reporting on July 8, 1947 

''Debunking''
Soon after the initial reports, the mysterious object was identified as a weather balloon, later confirmed to be a balloon array from [[Project Mogul]] which had gone missing in flight.

''Submergence''
The news story ended with the identification of the weather balloon.  However, the event lingered on in the ‘fading and recreative memories of some of those involved’.  Rumor and speculation simmered just below the surface in Roswell and became part of the culture at large.  In time, [[UFOlogists]] arrived, asked leading questions and helped to spin a tale of crashed flying saucers and government conspiracy of cover-up.

''Mythologizing''
The most complex part of the syndrome.  After the story submerged and over time, reemerged, it developed into an ever expanding and elaborate myth.  The mythologizing process included exaggeration, faulty memory, folklore and deliberate hoaxing.   The deliberate hoaxing, usually self-serving for personal gain or promotion (for example, promotion of the 1950 sci-fi movie [[The Flying Saucer]]) in turn fed the folklore.  

''Reemergence and Media Bandwagon Effect''
Publication of books such as ‘The Roswell Incident’ by [[Charles Berlitz|Berlitz]] and Moore in 1980, television shows and other venues perpetuate the UFO crash and cover-up conspiracy beliefs that typically mirror and oscillate with public sentiment toward the US government.

The authors predicted that the Roswellian Syndrome would &quot;play out again and again&quot;,&lt;ref name=syndrome/&gt; not only in the Roswell story, but also in other UFO and conspiracy-theorized stories.

==Developments since 1990s==

===Pro-UFO advocates dismiss Roswell incident===

One of the immediate outcomes of the Air Force reports on the Roswell UFO incident was the decision by some prominent UFO researchers to view the Roswell incident as not involving any alien craft.

While the initial Air Force report was a chief reason for this, another was the release of secret documents from 1948 that showed that top Air Force officials did not know what the UFO objects being reported in the media were and their suspicion they might be Soviet spy vehicles.

In January 1997, Karl T. Pflock, one of the more prominent pro-UFO researchers, said “Based on my research and that of others, I'm as certain as it's possible to be without absolute proof that no flying saucer or saucers crashed in the general vicinity of Roswell or on the Plains of San Agustin in 1947. The debris found by Mac Brazel...was the remains of something very earthly, all but certainly something from the Top Secret Project Mogul....The formerly highly classified record of correspondence and discussions among top Air Force officials who were responsible for cracking the flying saucer mystery from the mid-1940s through the early 1950s makes it crystal clear that they didn't have any crashed saucer wreckage or bodies of saucer crews, but they were desperate to have such evidence ...&quot;&lt;ref name=autogenerated3&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.archive.org/web/20110604124016/http://www.csicop.org/klassfiles/SUN-43.html |title=The Klass Files #43, JANUARY 1997 |publisher=Web.archive.org |date=2011-06-04 |accessdate=2011-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kent Jeffrey, who organized petitions to ask President [[Bill Clinton]] to issue an [[Executive order (United States)|Executive Order]] to declassify any government information on the Roswell incident, similarly concluded that no such aliens were likely involved.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.archive.org/web/20110604124029/http://www.csicop.org/klassfiles/SUN-44.html |title=The Klass Files #44, MARCH 1997 |publisher=Web.archive.org |date=2011-06-04 |accessdate=2011-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.roswellfiles.com/storytellers/KentJeffrey1.htm |title=Kent Jeffrey Anatomy of a Myth |publisher=Roswellfiles.com |date= |accessdate=2011-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

William L. Moore, one of the earliest proponents of the Roswell incident, said this in 1997: &quot;After deep and careful consideration of recent developments concerning Roswell...I am no longer of the opinion that the extraterrestrial explanation is the best explanation for this event.&quot; Moore was co-author of the first book on Roswell, ''The Roswell Incident''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.archive.org/web/20110604124049/http://www.csicop.org/klassfiles/SUN-47.html |title=The Klass Files #47 SEPTEMBER 1997 |publisher=Web.archive.org |date=2011-06-04 |accessdate=2011-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Shoddy research revealed; witnesses suspected of hoaxes===

Around the same time, a serious rift between two prominent Roswell authors emerged. [[Kevin D. Randle]] and Donald R. Schmitt had co-authored several books on the subject and were generally acknowledged, along with [[Stanton Friedman]], as the leading researchers into the Roswell incident.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.roswellfiles.com/storytellers/RandleSchmitt.htm |title=Kevin Randle and Donald Schmitt |publisher=Roswellfiles.com |date= |accessdate=2011-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Air Force reports on the Roswell UFO incident|Air Force reports]] on the incident suggested that basic research claimed to have been carried out was not carried out,&lt;ref name=&quot;The Roswell Report: Fact verses Fiction in the New Mexico Desert&quot;&gt;”The Roswell Report: Fact verses Fiction in the New Mexico Desert,” Col. Richard Weaver and 1st Lt. James McAndrew, Headquarters United States Air Force, 1995, https://www.airforcehistory.hq.af.mil/Publications/fulltext/roswell.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; a fact verified in a 1995 [[Omni (magazine)|''Omni'']] magazine article.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.roswellfiles.com/Articles/MissingNurses.htm |title=The Missing Nurses of Roswell |publisher=Roswellfiles.com |date=1947-07-05 |accessdate=2011-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, Schmitt claimed he had a [[bachelor’s degree]], a [[master’s degree]] and was in the midst of pursuing a [[doctorate]] in [[criminology]]. He also claimed to be a [[medical illustrator]]. When checked, it was revealed he was in fact a [[mail carrier|letter carrier]] in [[Hartford, Wisconsin]], and had no known academic credentials. At the same time, Randle publicly distanced himself from Schmitt and his research. Referring to Schmitt’s investigation of witness Dennis’s accounts of a missing nurse at the Roswell base, he said: &quot;The search for the nurses proves that he [Schmitt] will lie about anything. He will lie to anyone ... He has revealed himself as a [[Pseudologia fantastica|pathological liar]] ... I will have nothing more to do with him.&quot;&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;

Additionally, several prominent witnesses were shown to be perpetrating hoaxes, or suspected of doing so. Frank Kaufmann, a major source of alien reports in the 1994 Randle and Schmitt book ''The Truth About the UFO Crash at Roswell'' and a witness whose testimony it was charged was “ignored” by the Air Force when compiling their reports,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=CUFOS |url=http://www.cufos.org/airforce.htm |title=Center for UFO Studies |publisher=Cufos.org |date= |accessdate=2011-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; was shown, after his 2001 death, to have been forging documents and inflating his role at Roswell. Randle and Mark Rodeigher repudiated Kaufmann’s credibility in two 2002 articles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cufos.org/Roswell_fs1.html |title=Frank Kaufmann Roswell Witness |publisher=Cufos.org |date= |accessdate=2011-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Glenn Dennis, who testified that Roswell alien autopsies were carried out at the Roswell base and that he and others were the subjects of threats, was deemed one of the “least credible” Roswell witnesses by Randle in 1998. In Randle and Schmitt’s 1991 book ''UFO Crash at Roswell'', Dennis’s story was featured prominently. Randle said Dennis was not credible “for changing the name of the nurse once we had proved she didn't exist.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.roswellfiles.com/storytellers/KevinRandleOnIRC.htm |title=Kevin Randle on the UK-UFO-NW IRC #UFO Channel |publisher=Roswellfiles.com |date=1998-04-11 |accessdate=2011-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dennis’s accounts were also doubted by researcher Pflock.&lt;ref name=autogenerated3 /&gt;

===Photo analysis; documentaries; new claims===

UFO researcher David Rudiak, and others before him, claimed that a telegram that appears in one of the 1947 photos of balloon debris in Ramey's office contains text that confirms that aliens and a &quot;disk&quot; were found. Rudiak and some other examiners claim that when enlarged, the text on the paper General Ramey is holding in his hand includes key phrases &quot;the victims of the wreck&quot; and &quot;in/on the 'disc'&quot; plus other phrases seemingly in the context of a crashed vehicle recovery.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Roswell Proof: What really happened | publisher = Roswell Proof | url = http://www.roswellproof.com/reconstruct.html | accessdate = 2006-10-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, pro-UFO interpretations of this document are disputed by other photoanalyses, such as one facilitated by researcher James Houran, Ph.D.,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = Houran | first = James | title = A Message in a Bottle: Confounds in Deciphering the Ramey Memo from the Roswell UFO Case | year= 2002 | url = http://www.scientificexploration.org/journal/jse_16_1_houran.pdf | accessdate = 2009-07-14 }}&lt;/ref&gt; that suggest the letters and words are indistinct. Other objections question the plausibility of a general allowing himself to be photographed holding such a document, raise issues with the format of the memo, and ponder the logic of Ramey having in his possession a document he, as Rudiak argued, has sent, which says &quot;...the wreck you forwarded...&quot; yet is supposedly addressed to the Headquarters of the Army Air Force in Washington, not the Roswell Army Air Field.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = Printy | first = Timothy | title = The Ramey Document: Smoking gun or empty water pistol? | year= 1999 | url = http://home.comcast.net/~tprinty/UFO/Ramey.htm | accessdate = 2009-07-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Gen Ramey balloon 7-8-47.jpg|thumb|right|Gen. Roger Ramey (left) and chief of staff Col. Thomas Dubose posed with weather balloon and radar reflector, July 8, 1947, Fort Worth, Texas. Some claim text contained on the paper in Ramey's hand (boxed) confirms an alien recovery. Enlarged to the left.]] --&gt;
[[File:Gen Ramey Roswell memo 1947.jpg|300px|thumb|left|Enlargement of Gen. Ramey's held message in the original photo.]]

In 2002, the [[Syfy|Sci-Fi Channel]] sponsored an excavation at the Brazel site in the hopes of uncovering any missed debris that the military failed to collect. Although these results have so far turned out to be negative, the [[University of New Mexico]] archaeological team did verify recent soil disruption at the exact location that some witnesses said they saw a long, linear impact groove. Gov. [[Bill Richardson (politician)|Bill Richardson]] of New Mexico, who headed the [[United States Department of Energy]] under President Clinton, apparently found the results provocative. In 2004, he wrote in a foreword to ''The Roswell Dig Diaries'', that &quot;the mystery surrounding this crash has never been adequately explained—not by independent investigators, and not by the U.S. government.&quot;

On October 26, 2007, Richardson (at the time a candidate for the [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic Party]] nomination for U.S. President) elaborated when he was asked about releasing government files on Roswell. Richardson responded that when he was a Congressman, he attempted to get information on behalf of his New Mexico constituents, but was told by both the Department of Defense and Los Alamos Labs that the information was classified. &quot;That ticked me off,&quot; he said &quot;The government doesn't tell the truth as much as it should on a lot of issues.&quot; He promised to work on opening the files if he were elected as President.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.archive.org/web/20090122111528/http://www.dallasnews.com/sharedcontent/dws/news/texassouthwest/stories/102707dntexrichardson.3164110.html |title=Dallas Morning News |publisher=Web.archive.org |date=2009-01-22 |accessdate=2011-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dentonrc.com/sharedcontent/dws/news/texassouthwest/stories/102707dntexrichardson.3164110.html |title=Denton (Texas) Record-Chronicle |publisher=Dentonrc.com |date=2007-10-27 |accessdate=2011-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.archive.org/web/20080309074311/http://www.wfaa.com/sharedcontent/dws/news/texassouthwest/stories/102707dntexrichardson.3164110.html |title=On Texas stop, Democratic candidate Richardson criticizes government secrecy &amp;#124; WFAA.com &amp;#124; Texas Southwest |publisher=Web.archive.org |date=2008-03-09 |accessdate=2011-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2002 before airing its Roswell documentary, the Sci-Fi Channel also hosted a Washington UFO news conference. [[John Podesta]], President Clinton's chief of staff, appeared as a member of the public relations firm hired by Sci-Fi to help get the government to open up documents on the subject. Podesta stated, &quot;It is time for the government to declassify records that are more than 25 years old and to provide scientists with data that will assist in determining the true nature of the phenomena.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stenger&quot;&gt;Richard Stenger. &quot;[http://cnn.space.printthis.clickability.com/pt/cpt?action=cpt&amp;title=CNN.com+-+Clinton+aide+slams+Pentagon%27s+UFO+secrecy+-+Oct.+22%2C+2002&amp;expire=-1&amp;urlID=11951646&amp;fb=Y&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Farchives.cnn.com%2F2002%2FTECH%2Fspace%2F10%2F22%2Fufo.records%2Findex.html&amp;partnerID=2018 Clinton aide slams Pentagon's UFO secrecy]&quot;, ''CNN'' October 22, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2005, the [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC TV]] network aired a UFO special hosted by news anchor [[Peter Jennings]]. Jennings lambasted the Roswell case as a &quot;myth ... without a shred of evidence.&quot; ABC endorsed the Air Force's explanation that the incident resulted solely from the crash of a Project Mogul balloon.

===''Top Secret/Majic'' (2005 edition)===

[[Stanton T. Friedman]] continues to defend his view that the [[Majestic 12]] documents, which describe a secret government agency hiding information on recovered aliens, are authentic. In an afterword dated April 2005 to a new edition of his book ''Top Secret/Majic'' (first published in 1996), he responds to more recent questions on their validity and concludes &quot;I am still convinced Roswell really happened, [and] that the Eisenhower Briefing Document [i.e., Majestic 12] ... [and others] are the most important classified documents ever leaked to the public.&quot; &lt;ref name=FriedmanTSM-general&gt;Stanton T. Friedman. ''Top Secret/Majic: Operation Majestic-12 and the United States Government's UFO Cover-up''. New York, Marlowe &amp; Company (2005). ISBN 1-56924-741-2.&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Witness to Roswell'' (2007)===

In June 2007, Donald Schmitt and his investigation partner Tom Carey published their first book together, ''Witness to Roswell''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carey-general&quot;&gt;Thomas J. Carey, Donald R. Schmitt. ''Witness to Roswell''. The Career Press Inc. (2007). ISBN 978-1-56414-943-5.&lt;/ref&gt; In this book, they claim a &quot;continuously growing roster of more than 600 people directly or indirectly associated with the events at Roswell who support the first account - that initial claim of the flying saucer recovery.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Carey38&quot;&gt;Carey/Schmitt. ''Witness to Roswell'', p. 38.&lt;/ref&gt; New accounts of aliens or alien recoveries were described, including from [[Walter Haut]] who wrote the initial press release in 1947.

A new date was suggested for a crash of a mysterious object—the evening of Thursday, July 3, 1947.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carey21&quot;&gt;Carey/Schmitt. ''Witness to Roswell'', p. 21,127.&lt;/ref&gt; Also, unlike previous accounts, Brazel took debris to Corona, where he showed fragments to local residents in the local bar, hardware store and elsewhere, and to Capitan to the south, while portions of the object ended up at a 4 July rodeo.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carey48&quot;&gt;Carey/Schmitt. ''Witness to Roswell'', p. 48-49.&lt;/ref&gt; Numerous people are described as visiting the debris field and taking souvenirs before Brazel finally went to Roswell to report the find on July 6. Once the military was alerted to the debris, extensive efforts were undertaken to retrieve those souvenirs: &quot;Ranch houses were and [sic] ransacked. The wooden floors of livestock sheds were pried loose plank by plank and underground cold storage fruit cellars were emptied of all their contents.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Carey51&quot;&gt;Carey/Schmitt. ''Witness to Roswell'', p. 51.&lt;/ref&gt;

The subsequent events are related as per the sequence in previous books, except for a second recovery site of an alien body at the Foster ranch. This recovery near the debris field is the same site mentioned in 1991's ''UFO Crash at Roswell''. The authors suggest that Brazel discovered the second site some days after finding the debris field, and this prompted him to travel to Roswell and report his find to the authorities.

Neither Barnett nor the archaeologists are present at this body site. While noting the earlier &quot;major problems&quot; with Barnett's account, which caused Schmitt and previous partner Randle to omit Barnett's claim in 1994's ''The Truth about the UFO Crash at Roswell'', the new book further notes another site mentioned in the 1994 publication. This site closer to Roswell &quot;turned out to be bogus, as it was based upon the testimony of a single, alleged eyewitness [Frank Kaufmann] who himself was later discovered to have been a purveyor of false information.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Carey126&quot;&gt;Carey/Schmitt. ''Witness to Roswell'', p. 126-127.&lt;/ref&gt; Jim Ragsdale, whose alien account opened that book and who was claimed to have been present along with some archaeologists, is not mentioned in the new book.

The book includes claims that Major Marcel saw alien bodies, a claim not present in the previous books mentioned. Two witnesses are cited who say Marcel briefly mentioned seeing bodies, one a relative and another a tech sergeant who worked with Marcel's intelligence team.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carey79&quot;&gt;Carey/Schmitt. ''Witness to Roswell'', p. 79-80.&lt;/ref&gt;

Much additional new testimony is presented to support notions that alien bodies were found at the Foster ranch and at another main crash site along with a craft, then processed at the base in a hangar and at the hospital, and finally flown out in containers, all under very tight security. The book suggests Brazel found &quot;two or three alien bodies&quot; about two miles east of the debris field and describes the rest of a stricken alien craft along with the remainder of the crew remaining airborne for some 30 more miles before crashing at another site about 40 miles north/northwest of Roswell (but not the same site described by Kaufmann). The authors claim to have located this final crash site in 2005 where &quot;an additional two or three dead aliens and one live one were discovered by civilian archaeologists,&quot; but offer no more information about the new site.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carey127&quot;&gt;Carey/Schmitt. ''Witness to Roswell'', p. 127-128.&lt;/ref&gt;

Walter Haut, as the Roswell Army Air Field public affairs officer, had drafted the initial press release that went out over the news wires on the afternoon of July 8, 1947, announcing a &quot;flying disc&quot;. This was the only direct involvement Haut had previously described in public statements and signed affidavits. The book presents a new affidavit that Haut signed in 2002 in which he claims much greater personal knowledge and involvement, including seeing alien corpses and craft, and involvement in a cover-up. Haut died in 2005.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carey215&quot;&gt;Carey/Schmitt. ''Witness to Roswell'', pp. 215-217.&lt;/ref&gt;

Another new first-hand account from MP Elias Benjamin describes how he guarded aliens on [[gurney]]s taken to the Roswell base hospital from the same hangar.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carey136&quot;&gt;Carey/Schmitt. ''Witness to Roswell'', pp. 136-140.&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, family members of Miriam Bush, secretary to the chief medical officer at Roswell base, told of having been led into an examination room where alien corpses were laid out on gurneys.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carey-ch12&quot;&gt;Carey/Schmitt. ''Witness to Roswell'', pp. 119-123.&lt;/ref&gt; In both accounts, one of the aliens was said to be still alive. The book also recounted earlier testimony of the Anaya family about picking up New Mexico Lt. Governor [[Joseph Montoya]] at the base, and a badly shaken Montoya relating that he saw four alien bodies at the base hangar, one of them alive.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carey-ch8&quot;&gt;Carey/Schmitt. ''Witness to Roswell'', pp. 83-92.&lt;/ref&gt; Benjamin's and Bush's accounts, as do a few lesser ones, again place aliens at the Roswell base hospital, as had the Glenn Dennis story from almost 20 years before. The book notes that Dennis had been found to have told lies, and therefore is a supplier of unreliable testimony, but had nevertheless told others of incidents at the Roswell base long before it became associated with aliens in the late 1970s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carey135&quot;&gt;Carey/Schmitt. ''Witness to Roswell'', p. 135.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Walter Haut controversy===
The publishing of the Walter Haut affidavit&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.news.com.au/story/0,23599,21994224-2,00.html | title=Roswell theory revived by deathbed confession | date=July 1, 2007 | work=The Sunday Telegraph}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Dirk Vander Ploeg, Wainfleet, Ontario, Canada. Telephone 905 834-2177, fax 905 312-9312 e-mail publisher@ufodigest.com |url=http://www.ufodigest.com/news/0707/haut.html |title=2002 SEALED AFFIDAVIT OF WALTER G. HAUT |publisher=Ufodigest.com |date= |accessdate=2011-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; in ''Witness to Roswell'', wherein Haut described a cover-up and seeing alien corpses, ignited a controversy in UFO circles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://frankwarren.blogspot.com/2007/07/new-revelations-on-haut-affidavit.html |title=UFO Breaking News! UFO Articles UFO Opinion Editorial UFO Flying Saucers Flying Disks Aerial Phenomenon Alien Abduction FOIA Requests Declassified Documents UFO History UFO Si |publisher=Frankwarren.blogspot.com |date=2007-07-24 |accessdate=2011-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; While many embraced his accounts as confirmation of the presence of aliens from a person who was known to have been on the base in 1947, others raised questions about the credibility of the accounts.

UFO researcher Dennis G. Balthaser, who along with fellow researcher Wendy Connors interviewed Haut on-camera in 2000, doubted that the same man he interviewed could have written the affidavit he signed. &quot;[The 2000 video] shows a man that couldn't remember where he took basic training, names, dates, etc., while the 2002 affidavit is very detailed and precise with information Haut couldn't accurately remember 2 years after he was video taped.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Dirk Vander Ploeg, Hamilton, Ontario, Canada. Telephone 905 834-2177, fax 905 312-9312 e-mail publisher@ufodigest.com.com |url=http://www.ufodigest.com/news/1007/walterhaut.html |title=Walter Haut, Roswell and a whole Lotta Questions |publisher=Ufodigest.com |date= |accessdate=2011-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Witness to Roswell'' co-author Donald R. Schmitt, he notes, admitted that the affidavit was not written by Haut, but prepared for him to sign, based on statements Haut had made privately to Schmitt and co-author Tom Carey over a period of years.&lt;ref&gt;[http://theparacast.com/ the Paracast interview with Schmitt and Carey on July 22, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt; And further, notes Balthaser, neither he nor Carey were there when Haut signed the affidavit and the witness' name has not been revealed, casting doubt on the circumstances of the signing.

He had further questions about what he saw as problems with the 2002 account. If the cover-up was decided at a meeting at Roswell, he asked, &quot;why was it necessary for Major Marcel to fly debris from Roswell to General Ramey’s office in Ft Worth, since they had all handled the debris in the meeting and apparently set up the cover-up operation?&quot; He also wondered which Haut statements were true: a 1993 affidavit he signed, the 2000 video interview, or the 2002 affidavit.

Bill Birnes, writing for UFO Magazine, summarizes that whatever disagreements there are about the 2000 video and the 2002 affidavit, &quot;I think Walter Haut's 2002 affidavit really says it all and agrees, on its material facts, with Walter's 2000 interview with Dennis Balthaser and Wendy Connors. Dennis said he agrees with me, too, on this point.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://web.archive.org/web/20081219004840/http://www.ufomag.com/archive/archive07/08.07/08.14.07.html Dennis, Tom, and Jesse ...]&quot; ''UFO Magazine Daily Edition'', August 14, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

A comparison of the affidavit and interview shows that in both Haut said he saw a craft and at least one body in a base hangar and also attended a Roswell staff meeting where General Ramey was present and where Ramey put a cover-up into place.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.roswellproof.com/Haut_2000_interview.html Walter Haut's 2000 Interview] and [http://www.roswellproof.com/Haut.html Lt. Walter G. Haut - Roswell base public information officer &quot;deathbed&quot; affidavit to seeing spacecraft &amp; bodies] at roswellproof.com].&lt;/ref&gt;

Birnes also says that Carey told that while Haut may not have written the affidavit, &quot;his statements were typed, shown to him for his review and agreement, and then affirmed by him in the presence of a witness... The fact that a notary was present and sealed the document should end any doubt as to the reality of its existence.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Bill Birnes. &quot;[http://web.archive.org/web/20081219004513/http://www.ufomag.com/archive/archive07/08.07/08.13.07.html The affidavit, the interview, and the affidavit ...]&quot;, ''UFO Magazine - Daily Edition'', August 13, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

Julie Shuster, Haut's daughter and Director of the International UFO Museum in Roswell, said that Schmitt had written the affidavit based on years of conversations he and Carey had had with him. Writing in the September 2007 MUFON newsletter, she said she and Haut reviewed the document, that &quot;he did not want to make any changes,&quot; and in the presence of two witnesses, a notary public from the museum and a visitor, both unidentified, he signed the affidavit.&lt;ref&gt;Julie Schuster, &quot;Haut's Daughter tells how affidavit came to be&quot;, ''[http://www.theblackvault.com/encyclopedia/documents/MUFON/Journals/2007/September_2007.pdf MUFON UFO Journal'' No. 473 (September 2007)], p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt;

====UFO FBI document release, 2011====
[[File:FlyingSaucersMemorandumMarch22-1950.jpg|thumb|165px|Flying saucer memorandum.]]
In April 2011, the [[FBI]] posted a document from 1950 &lt;ref&gt;[http://vault.fbi.gov/hottel_guy/Guy%20Hottel%20Part%201%20of%201/view FBI — Guy Hottel Part 1 of 1&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; on their website written by agent Guy Hottel which discussed a report forwarded by an investigator from the Air Force of three alien craft and their occupants having been recovered in New Mexico. The memo stated that &quot;three so-called flying saucers&quot; were recovered, each circular in shape with raised centers, each about 50 feet in diameter. Three occupants of &quot;human shape,&quot; each about three feet tall, were found in each craft, and all were dressed &quot;in metallic cloth of a very fine texture.&quot; The memo said that reports were &quot;high-powered radar&quot; had affected the alien crafts' control systems, causing them to crash. No date was mentioned, though the memo was date-stamped March 22, 1950, and no location more specific than &quot;New Mexico&quot; was mentioned. The memo stated that &quot;no further evaluation was attempted&quot; by the person who supplied the information.

Numerous sources connected the memo &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/world/uk/Aliens-landed-in-Roswell/articleshow/7940717.cms | work=The Times Of India | title=Aliens landed in Roswell | date=2011-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/newstopics/howaboutthat/ufo/8442464/Exploding-UFOs-and-alien-landings-in-secret-FBI-files.html | location=London | work=The Daily Telegraph | first=Bonnie | last=Malkin | title='Exploding UFOs and alien landings' in secret FBI files | date=2011-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; to the Roswell UFO incident of 1947.

Other sources said the memo had been in the public domain for years and was revealed as a hoax as far back as 1952 in an article in [[True (magazine)|True]] magazine.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.realityuncovered.net/blog/2009/02/play-it-again-scam/&lt;/ref&gt; They said the hoax was perpetrated by several men who were peddling a device purported to be able to locate [[gold]], [[oil]], gas or anything their victims sought, based on supposed alien technology. The two men, Silas Newton and Leo A. Gebauer, were convicted of [[fraud]] in 1953.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ibtimes.com/articles/132868/20110411/fbi-hottel-memo-reveals-ufo-hoax.htm FBI &quot;Hottel Memo&quot; Reveals UFO Hoax - International Business Times&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Area 51'' (2011)===
{{Quote box|
&quot;[They] were not aliens. Nor were they consenting&lt;br&gt;
airmen. They were human guinea pigs.&quot;&lt;br&gt;
— [[Annie Jacobsen]], author of ''Area 51''}}

The book ''[[Area 51: An Uncensored History of America's Top Secret Military Base]]'' by [[Annie Jacobsen]], based on interviews with scientists and engineers who worked in [[Area 51]], dismisses the alien story. Instead, it suggests that [[Josef Mengele]] was recruited by the Soviet leader [[Joseph Stalin]] to produce &quot;grotesque, child-size aviators&quot; to be remotely piloted and landed in America to cause hysteria in the likeness of [[Orson Welles]]' 1938 radio drama ''[[The War of the Worlds (radio drama)|War of the Worlds]]'', but that the aircraft crashed and the incident was hushed up by the Americans.

Jacobsen writes that the bodies found at the crash site were children. Grotesquely but similarly deformed, aged around 12, each under five feet tall, with large heads and abnormally shaped oversize eyes. They were neither aliens nor consenting airmen, but human guinea pigs.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas Harding. &quot;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/newstopics/howaboutthat/ufo/8512408/Roswell-was-Soviet-plot-to-create-US-panic.html Roswell 'was Soviet plot to create US panic']&quot;, ''[[The Daily Telegraph]]'', 13 May 2011. Retrieved 15 May 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  The book was sharply criticized for extensive errors in an essay by two scientists at the Federation of American Scientists.&lt;ref&gt;Robert S. Norris and Jeffrey T. Richelson, “Dreamland Fantasies,” ''Washington Decoded'', 11 July 2011,  www.washingtondecoded.com/site/2011/07/area51.html (retrieved 9/26/2011)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Cultural influence==
{{Refimprove section|date=July 2010}}
[[File:Alien Encounters.ogv|thumb|'Alien Encounters: The Wright-Patterson Air Force Base Connection', a short documentary about the incident from 1994]]
The Roswell incident has become a popular subject of many science fiction movies, television series, video games, and books.

===Film===
Kevin D. Randle and Donald R. Schmitt's 1991 nonfiction book ''UFO Crash at Roswell'' inspired the 1994 American television film ''[[Roswell (film)|Roswell]]'', which starred [[Martin Sheen]] and [[Kyle MacLachlan]]. The film depicts Major Jesse Marcel trying to discover the truth about strange debris found on a local rancher's field in Roswell in July 1947. The film received a [[Golden Globe Award]] nomination for Best Mini-Series or Motion Picture Made for Television, but did not win.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0111021/awards Awards for Roswell (1994) (TV)], [[IMDB]], Retrieved 20 October 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

The 1996 [[science fiction]] film [[Independence Day (film)|Independence Day]] featured a top secret underground facility at [[Area 51]], which housed a recovered spacecraft and three alien bodies that had been stored there since the Roswell incident.

The 2008 [[science fiction]] film [[Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull]] begin in &quot;Hanger 51&quot; (an allusion to Area 51 and Hangar 18 within the base,) and had Dr. Jones lead Soviet agents to a mummified Alien body from the Roswell Site, contained in a chest labeled &quot;Roswell, New Mexico. July, 1947&quot;, Jones stating that he was one of twenty-one experts taken in secret to the original Roswell crash to examine the unidentified body.

===Literature===
Several novels have been written about the Roswell incident, including [[Whitley Strieber]]'s ''Majestic'' (1989), Kevin D. Randle's ''Operation Roswell'' (2004), and [[Sonny Whitelaw]]'s ''[[Stargate SG-1: Roswell]]'' (2007), ''The True Meaning of Smekday'' by Adam Rex and ''Gotcha Gas: Debacle Near Roswell'' (2011), an historical parody by Banak and Weimer.

And several non Fiction Books as the following:
* &quot;The truth about the UFO crash at Roswell&quot; by Kevin D. Randle &amp; Donald R. Schmitt, ISBN 0-380-77803-3
* &quot;The Roswell Legacy&quot; by Jesse Marcel, Jr. and Linda Marcel, ISBN 978-1-60163-026-1
* ''Alien Interview'' (2008) edited by Lawrence Spencer, 2010, ISBN 978-0-557-60195-0
* ''The Day After Roswell'' (1998) by Col. P. J. Corso,1998, ISBN 978-0-671-01756-9

===Television===
An American television series, ''Roswell High'', later renamed ''[[Roswell (TV series)|Roswell]]'', aired from 1999 to 2002, originally on [[The WB Television Network]] and later on [[UPN]]. Based on [[Melinda Metz]]'s ''[[Roswell High]]'' children's book series, the program followed the lives of four extraterrestrials who had survived the Roswell crash and assumed the form of human teenagers.

An American animation series, ''[[Futurama]]'', has an episode called &quot;[[Roswell That Ends Well]]&quot;. The episode contains jokes implying that Zoidberg was the alien found in Roswell on the famous date.

According to the episode &quot;The Best Christmas Story Never Told&quot; of the American television series ''[[American Dad!]]'', the extraterrestrial character [[Roger (American Dad!)|Roger]] claims he has been on the planet for sixty years (accurate, at the time the episode aired), originally crashing  &quot;in Roswell in '47&quot;. 

The ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]'' episode  &quot;[[Little Green Men (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|Little Green Men]]&quot; reveals that this incident was the unintentional crash of a [[Ferengi]] vessel from the 24th century, owned by main character [[Quark (Star Trek)|Quark]] who was accompanied by his brother Rom, nephew Nog, and nemesis Odo.

The 1996-97 [[NBC]] television series ''[[Dark Skies]]'' featured an interpretation of the Roswell incident as the starting point of the super-secret government agency [[Majestic 12]] which was involved in a covert war between humans and an alien conspiracy.  In ''Dark Skies'', [[President of the United States|President]] [[Harry Truman]] was present at the Roswell site in 1947, when an alien representative demanded humanity's unconditional surrender.  A fictional version of Jesse
Marcel, played by actor [[Richard Gilliland]], appeared in several episodes of the series.

The 1998 - 2001 [[UPN]] television series ''[[Seven Days (TV series)|Seven Days]]'' featured a top-secret government time travel project based on alien technology recovered from the Roswell crash site.  One episode of the series featured an alien survivor of the UFO crash.

===Comics, series and animation===
The comic book series ''[[The Invisibles]]'' (1994–2000), by [[Grant Morrison]], made extensive use of the Roswell incident in its second volume. A humorous [[Bongo Comics]] series, called ''[[Roswell, Little Green Man]]'', ran from 1996 to 1999 and followed the misadventures of an extraterrestrial who survived from the craft. The graphic novel ''[[Roswell, Texas (graphic novel)|Roswell, Texas]]'' features an [[alternate history]] in which the site of the UFO crash was part of the still-independent [[republic of Texas]].
In the anime, webcomic and manga ''[[Hetalia: Axis Powers]]'', the personification of America has an alien friend named Tony, who began living with him after the Roswell incident. In the 2007 American comic book ''Atarian Conquest'', an alien named Irvyll, rescued from Area 51 by his home race, claims to be the descendant of the aliens who &quot;crashed in a nearby Eartian desert in the mid 1900's&quot;.

===Music===
The 2004 album, [[The Crash of '47]] from hard rock band [[Atomship]] is a direct reference to the Roswell incident.

The American band [[Foo Fighters]] takes its name from an old term for UFOs, specific to &quot;[ghosts]&quot; that trailed the wings of fighter planes, and has named its [[record label]] Roswell Records.  The band has performed concerts on the site of the Roswell Air Force Base&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.realnetworks.com/company/press/releases/2005/foofighters_freeconcert.html Close Encounters of the Foo Fighters Kind], [[RealNetworks]], Inc. Press Release, Retrieved 21 October 2006&lt;/ref&gt; and at the site of the crash. Foo Fighters frontman [[Dave Grohl]] is known for having an interest in supernatural phenomena.

Singer/songwriter [[John Stewart]] included a song called &quot;Mac Brasel's (sic) Farm&quot; on his 1997 album &quot;Rough Sketches From Rt. 66.&quot;

Swedish Death Metal-Band [[Hypocrisy]] wrote a song called &quot;Roswell 47&quot;, released on their 1996 album &quot;Abducted&quot;.

===Toys===
Two plastic kits of the Roswell ship were made by [[Testors]], following the forensic reconstructions of Bill McDonald. One shows the crash site, and the other just the intact ship.{{citation needed|date=December 2011}}

==See also==
* [[Area 51]]
* [[List of UFO sightings]]
* [[National Security Act of 1947]]
* [[The Disclosure Project]]
* [[Million Fax on Washington]]
* [[Coyame UFO incident]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Roswell UFO incident}}
* [http://www.babelation.com/content/ufoaliens-smoking-gunsworn-statement-fbi-informant-states-flying-saucers-and-occupants-recov Original Guy Hottel Statement]
* [http://www.UFOfestivalRoswell.com/  The Amazing Roswell UFO Festival]
* [http://www.RoswellMysteries.com/  The City of Roswell, NM.  Visitors welcome!]
* [http://www.wafbmuseum.org/ Walker Air Force Base at Roswell online museum]
* Carey, Tom, and Schmitt, Don. [http://web.archive.org/web/20040413230419/http://www.scifi.com/ufo/roswell/ UFOlogy Resource Center: ''The Roswell Report''], via [[Syfy|SciFi.com]]. Archived from [http://www.scifi.com/ufo/roswell/ the original] on April 13, 2004.
{{UFOs}}
{{Conspiracy theories}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Roswell Ufo Incident}}
[[Category:Conspiracy theories]]
[[Category:Roswell UFO incident| ]]

{{Link FA|he}}
[[bn:রজওয়েলের ঘটনা]]
[[ca:Incident OVNI de Roswell]]
[[cs:Roswellský incident]]
[[da:Roswell ufo-hændelsen]]
[[de:Roswell-Zwischenfall]]
[[et:Roswelli juhtum]]
[[el:Συμβάν του Ρόσγουελ]]
[[es:Incidente ovni de Roswell]]
[[eo:Roswell-incidento]]
[[fa:حادثه رازول]]
[[fr:Affaire de Roswell]]
[[ko:로스웰 사건]]
[[hr:Slučaj Roswell]]
[[it:Incidente di Roswell]]
[[he:תקרית רוזוול]]
[[mk:Розвелски инцидент]]
[[nl:Roswellincident]]
[[ja:ロズウェル事件]]
[[no:Roswell-saken]]
[[pl:Incydent w Roswell]]
[[pt:Caso Roswell]]
[[ro:Incidentul OZN de la Roswell]]
[[ru:Розуэлльский инцидент]]
[[sk:Roswellský prípad]]
[[sl:Incident v Roswellu]]
[[sh:Roswellski NLO incident]]
[[fi:Roswellin tapaus]]
[[sv:Roswellincidenten]]
[[tr:Roswell UFO vakası]]
[[uk:Розвельський інцидент]]
[[zh:羅斯威爾飛碟墜毀事件]]</text>
      <sha1>8lo9tdrsgh4536bcvid6ff0feajbmuw</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
