<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Silesia</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>28399</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519374397</id>
      <parentid>517954272</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-23T11:56:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>LilHelpa</username>
        <id>8024439</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Etymology */., replaced: prefered → preferred using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="35898">{{Other uses}}
[[File:Silesia (Now).png|thumb|360px|Historic Silesia, superimposed on modern international borders: The mediæval Bohemian crown land (as of 1538) outlined in cyan, Prussian Silesia as of 1815 in yellow]]
[[File:Wappen Schlesiens.png|thumb|Coat of Arms of Silesia]]
'''Silesia''' ({{IPAc-en|icon|s|aɪ|ˈ|l|iː|ʒ|ə}} or {{IPAc-en|s|aɪ|ˈ|l|iː|ʃ|ə}}; {{lang-pl|Śląsk}} {{IPAc-pl|ś|l|ą|s|k}}; {{Audio-de|Schlesien|Schlesien.ogg}}; [[Silesian German]]: ''Schläsing''; {{lang-cs|Slezsko}}; [[Silesian language|Silesian]]: ''Ślůnsk'' {{IPA|[ɕlonsk]}}; {{lang-la|Silesia}}) is a [[historical region]] of [[Central Europe]] located mostly in [[Poland]], with smaller parts also in the [[Czech Republic]], and [[Germany]].

Silesia is rich in mineral and natural resources and includes several important industrial areas. Silesia's largest city and historical capital is [[Wrocław]] . Other large cities are [[Opole]], [[Gliwice]], [[Katowice]] in Poland; [[Ostrava]]; [[Opava]] in the Czech Republic; and [[Görlitz]]  in Germany. Its main river is the [[Oder]].

Silesia's borders and national affiliation have changed radically over time, both when it was a hereditary possession of [[feudalism|noble houses]] and after the rise of modern [[nation-states]]. The first known states to hold power there were those of [[Greater Moravia]]  at end of 9th century and [[Duchy of Bohemia|Bohemia]] early in the 10th century. In the 10th century Silesia was incorporated into the early Polish state, but it later broke into independent duchies, coming under increasing Czech and German influence. It came under the rule of the [[Lands of the Bohemian Crown|Crown of Bohemia]], which passed to the Austrian [[Habsburg Monarchy]] in 1526. Most of Silesia was conquered by [[Kingdom of Prussia|Prussia]] in 1742, later becoming part of the [[German Empire]], the Weimar Republic and Nazi Germany up to 1945. After [[World War I]] the easternmost part of this region was awarded to Poland by the victorious Allies after rebellions by Silesian Polish people and a plebiscite. After [[World War II]]  the bulk of Silesia was transferred to Polish jurisdiction and became part of Poland. The remaining small parts of Silesia mostly went to [[Czechoslovakia]] after World War I, and are part of the Czech Republic.
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Status !! Time
|-
| [[Celts]] || 4th century BC to 1st century AD
|-
| possibly as a lands of [[Silingi|Silings]]—supposedly an [[East Germanic tribes|East]] [[Germanic tribe]] || to 5th century AD.
|-
| as lands of Slavic [[Silesian tribes]] || from 5th century to 9th century
|-
| within [[Great Moravia]] || at the end of 9th century
|-
| within [[Duchy of Bohemia|Bohemia]] || in the 10th century
|-
| within Poland || from the end of the 10th century to 12th century
|-
| as independent [[Silesian Piasts]] [[Duchies of Silesia]] || 12th century to 14th century
|-
| as [[Duchies of Silesia]] within [[Lands of the Bohemian Crown|Bohemian Crown]] || 1335 to 1526
|-
| within Bohemian Crown as part of  Habsburg Monarchy || 1526 to 1742
|-
| within Kingdom of Prussia, German Empire, with a small part in Austria || 1742 to 1918
|-
| within Germany, and part as [[Silesian Voivodeship (1920–1939)|Silesian Voivodeship]] (1922–1939 in Poland), and a small part in [[Czechoslovakia]]|| 1918 to 1945
|-
| within Poland, much smaller parts in Czech Republic and  Germany || from 1945
|}

Most inhabitants of Silesia today speak the national languages of their respective countries ([[Polish language|Polish]], [[Czech language|Czech]], [[German language|German]]). There is an ongoing debate whether a local [[Silesian language|Silesian]] speech should be considered a [[Polish language|Polish]] dialect or a separate language. There also exists a Silesian German or [[Lower Silesian language]], although this form of German is almost extinct.

==Etymology==
The names of Silesia in the different languages most likely share their etymology—[[Latin]] and [[English language|English]]: ''Silesia''; [[Polish language|Polish]]: ''Śląsk''; [[Old Polish]]: ''Ślążsk[o]''; '''Silesian''': ''Ślůnsk''; [[German language|German]]: ''Schlesien''; [[Silesian German]]: ''Schläsing''; [[Czech language|Czech]]: ''Slezsko''; [[Slovak language|Slovak]]: ''Sliezsko''; [[Kashubian language|Kashubian]]: ''Sląsk''; [[Upper Sorbian]]: ''Šleska''; [[Lower Sorbian]]: ''Šlazyńska''. The names all relate to the name of a river (now [[Ślęza]]) and mountain ([[Mount Ślęża]]) in mid-southern Silesia. The mountain served as a holy place in prehistoric times.

''Ślęża'' is listed as one of the numerous [[Pre-Indo-European languages|Pre-Indo-European]] topographic names in the region (see [[old European hydronymy]]).&lt;ref&gt;
Zbigniew Babik, &quot;Najstarsza warstwa nazewnicza na ziemiach polskich w granicach średniowiecznej Słowiańszczyzny&quot;, Uniwersitas, Kraków, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Polish [[Slavist]]s  M. Rudnicki, T. Lehr-Splawinski,  S Rospond  and historian W. Semkowicz, demonstrate the  name ‘Ślęża’ {{IPAc-pl|'|ś|l|ę|ż|a}} or ‘Ślęż’ {{IPAc-pl|'|ś|l|ę|ż}}  (translated in [[Latin]] ''Silesia’’,  in [[Silesian language|Silesian]] ''Ślunsk'', in [[German language|German]] ''Schlesien'') has direct relation with the old–Slavic words &quot;ślęg&quot; {{IPAc-pl|'|ś|l|ę|g}}  or &quot;śląg&quot; {{IPAc-pl|'|ś|l|ą|g}}, what means dampness, moisture or humidity.&lt;ref&gt;Rudolf Fischer. Onomastica slavogermanica. Uniwersytet Wrocławski. 2007. t. XXVI. 2007. str. 83&lt;/ref&gt; The above Polish scientists reject the German hypothesis of ethnic origin of name ''Śląsk'' {{IPAc-pl|'|ś|l|ą|s|k}} from the name of tribe Silings.

According to some etymology the Slavic name derives from the Germanic ethnonym [[Silingi]]. This etymology is preferred by some German authors.&lt;ref name='RGA'&gt;{{cite encyclopedia | editor = Jankuhn, Herbert; Beck, Heinrich et al. | encyclopedia = [[Reallexikon der Germanischen Altertumskunde]] | title = Wandalen | accessdate = 2012-08-04 | language = German | edition = 2nd | year = 2006 | publisher = de Gruyter | volume = 33 | location = Berlin, Germany; New York, New York | quote = Da die Silingen offensichtlich ihren Namen im mittelalterlichen pagus silensis und dem mons slenz - möglicherweise mit dem Zobten gleichzusetzen [...] - hinterließen und damit einer ganzen Landschaft – Schlesien – den Namen gaben [...]}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{{Main|History of Silesia}}
[[File:Silesia 1172-1177.jpg|thumb|Silesia in an early period of [[Piast Poland#Fragmentation and Invasion, (1146-1295)|Poland's fragmentation]], 1172–1177]]
[[File:Provnice of Silesia, Kingdom of Prussia, 1905, Administrative Map.png|thumb|right|280px|1905 administrative map of Province of Silesia showing the historical locations of Upper Silesia (Oppeln) in red, Middle Silesia (Breslau) in yellow, and Lower Silesia (Liegnitz) in green]]

Silesia has historically been an [[ethnically]] diverse region. In the fourth century BC [[Celts]] entered Silesia settling around the [[Mount Ślęża]] near the modern [[Wrocław]], [[Oława]] and [[Strzelin]].&lt;ref&gt;R. Żerelik(in:) M. Czpliński (red.) Historia Śląska, Wrocław 2007, s. 34-35&lt;/ref&gt; [[East Germanic tribes|Germanic tribes]] were first recorded within Silesia in the first century. [[Slavic peoples]] arrived in this territory around the Seventh century.&lt;ref&gt;R. Żerelik(in:) M. Czpliński (red.) Historia Śląska, Wrocław 2007, s. 37-38&lt;/ref&gt; In the early ninth century the Slavic settlement stabilized. Local Slavs started to erect boundary structures like the [[Silesian Przesieka]] and the [[Silesia Walls]]. In those days the eastern border of [[Silesian tribes|Silesian]] settlement was situated to the west of the [[Bytom]], and east from [[Racibórz]] and [[Cieszyn]]. East from this line dwelled a closely related Slav tribe, the [[Vistulans]]. Their northern border was in the valley of the [[Barycz]] river, north of which dwelled [[Polans (western)|Polans]].&lt;ref name=&quot;M. Czpliński 2007&quot;&gt;R. Żerelik(in:) M. Czpliński (red.) Historia Śląska, Wrocław 2007, s. 21-22&lt;/ref&gt;

The first known states in Silesia were [[Greater Moravia]] and [[Bohemia]]. In the tenth century, the Polish ruler [[Mieszko I]] of the [[Piast dynasty]] incorporated Silesia into the Polish state. During the [[History of Poland during the Piast dynasty|Fragmentation of Poland]], Silesia, as well as the rest of the country, was divided among [[Duchies of Silesia|many independent duchies]] ruled by various Silesian [[Dukes of Silesia|dukes]]. During this time, German cultural and ethnic [[Germanization|influence]] increased as a result of [[Ostsiedlung|immigration]] from German-speaking parts of the [[Holy Roman Empire]]. In 1178, parts of the [[Duchy of Kraków]] around Bytom, [[Oświęcim]], [[Chrzanów]] and [[Siewierz]] were transferred to the Silesian Piasts, yet their population was of Vistulan and not of Silesian descent.&lt;ref name=&quot;M. Czpliński 2007&quot;/&gt;

Between 1289 and 1292, Bohemian king [[Wenceslaus II]] became [[suzerain]] of some [[Upper Silesia]]n duchies. It wasn't however until 1335 when Polish kings renounced their hereditary rights to Silesia.&lt;ref&gt;R. Żerelik(in:) M. Czpliński (red.) Historia Śląska, Wrocław 2007, s. 81&lt;/ref&gt; The province became part of the [[Lands of the Bohemian Crown|Bohemian Crown]] under the Holy Roman Empire, and passed with that crown to the [[Habsburg Monarchy]] of Austria in 1526. 

In the 15th century there were several border changes of the province. First of all parts of the territories that were transferred to the Silesian Piasts in 1178, were bought by the [[Monarchs of Poland|Polish kings]] in the second half of the 15th century (the [[Duchy of Oświęcim]] in 1457 and the [[Duchy of Zator]] in 1494). The Bytom area however remained in the possession of the Silesian Piasts, even though it was a part of the [[Diocese of Kraków]].&lt;ref name=&quot;M. Czpliński 2007&quot;/&gt; Secondly the Duchy of [[Krosno Odrzańskie|Crossen]] was inherited by [[Margraviate of Brandenburg]] in 1476 and, with the renunciation by King [[Ferdinand I, Holy Roman Emperor|Ferdinand I]] and estates of Bohemia in 1538, it became an integral part of Brandenburg.

In 1742, most of Silesia was seized by King [[Frederick II of Prussia|Frederick the Great]] of [[Kingdom of Prussia|Prussia]] in the [[War of the Austrian Succession]] and subsequently made the Prussian [[Province of Silesia]]. Consequently, Silesia became part of the [[German Empire]] when it was proclaimed in 1871.

After World War I, [[Upper Silesia]] was contested by Germany and the newly-independent [[Second Polish Republic]]. The [[League of Nations]] organized a [[Upper Silesia plebiscite|plebiscite]] to decide the issue in 1921. It resulted in 60% votes being cast for Germany and 40% for Poland. Following the third [[Silesian Uprising]] (1921), however, the easternmost portion of Upper Silesia (including [[Katowice]]), with a majority ethnic Polish population, was awarded to Poland, where it was formed into the [[Silesian Voivodeship (1920–1939)|Silesian Voivodeship]]. The Prussian Province of Silesia within Germany was then divided into the provinces of [[Province of Lower Silesia|Lower Silesia]] and [[Province of Upper Silesia|Upper Silesia]]. Meanwhile [[Austrian Silesia]], the small portion of Silesia retained by Austria after the [[Silesian Wars]], was mostly awarded to the new [[Czechoslovakia]] (becoming known as [[Czech Silesia]]), although most of [[Cieszyn]] and territory to the east of it went to Poland (see [[Zaolzie]]).

Polish Silesia was among the first regions invaded during [[Germany]]'s 1939 attack on [[Poland]].  One of the goals of [[Nazi]] occupation, particularly the occupation of [[Upper Silesia]], was to expel the Polish Silesian population.  German repatriation of Poles in Upper Silesia was made a priority for two crucial reasons.  First, [[Nazi Germany]] was resentful over the loss of Silesia after the uprisings of the early 1920s and wished to regain the region for its natural resource wealth and strategically important locomotive network.  Second, the [[Nazi]] war machine needed more members.  Those repatriated as German were immediately subject to military service, thus bolstering the German Army's numbers.  As for the non-German speaking Polish population of Silesia, they were reduced to a lower worker class status and were oftentimes severely mistreated by their new German overlords.  This treatment would be addressed by the Poles years later.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Lukowski, Zawadski|first=Jerzy, Hubert|title=A Concise History of Poland|year=2006|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=Cambridge, UK|isbn=978-0-521-61857-1|pages=256–257}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1945, Silesia and its population went through another traumatic change.  The German expulsion of Poles from Silesia was echoed by Polish expulsion of Germans.  The [[Potsdam Conference]] of 1945 concluded that the [[Oder-Neisse]] would be the official border between Germany and Poland.  Millions of German Silesians were evicted from their homes and replaced by Poles from the East.  Furthermore, the newly formed [[Polish United Workers' Party]] created a [[Ministry of the Recovered Territories]] that claimed half of the available arable land for state-run collectivized farms.  Many Silesian residents not only resented the Germans for their invasion in 1939, but now also the newly formed Polish communist government for their population shifting and interference in agricultural, as well as industrial, affairs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Lukowski, Zawadski|first=Jerzy, Hubert|title=A Concise History of Poland|year=2006|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=Cambridge, UK|isbn=978-0-521-61857-1|pages=278–280}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The administrative division of Silesia within Poland has changed several times since 1945. Since 1999 it has been divided between [[Lower Silesian Voivodeship]], [[Opole Voivodeship]], [[Silesian Voivodeship]] and [[Lubusz Voivodeship]]. Czech Silesia is now part of the Czech Republic, forming the [[Moravian-Silesian Region]] and the northern part of the [[Olomouc Region]]. Germany retains the Silesia-Lusatia region (''Niederschlesien-Oberlausitz'' or ''Schlesische Oberlausitz'') west of the [[Lusatian Neisse|Neisse]], which is part of the federal state of Saxony.

==Geography==
[[File:Landkarte von Schlesien.jpg|thumb|left|First map of Silesia by [[Martin Helwig]], 1561; north at the bottom]]

Most of Silesia is relatively flat, although its southern border is generally mountainous. It is primarily located in a swath running along both banks of the upper and middle [[Oder River|Oder (Odra)]] river, but it extends eastwards to the upper [[Vistula]] river. The region also includes many tributaries of the Oder, including the [[Bóbr]] (and its tributary the [[Kwisa]]), the [[Barycz]] and the [[Nysa Kłodzka]]. The [[Sudeten mountains]] run along most of the southern edge of the region, though at its south-eastern extreme it reaches the [[Silesian Beskids]] and [[Moravian-Silesian Beskids]], which belong to the [[Carpathian Mountains|Carpathian]] range.

Historically, Silesia was bounded to the west by the [[Kwisa]] and [[Bóbr]] rivers, while the territory west of the Kwisa was in Upper [[Lusatia]] (earlier ''Milsko''). However, because part of Upper Lusatia was included in the [[Province of Silesia]] in 1815, in Germany [[Görlitz]], [[Niederschlesischer Oberlausitzkreis]] and neighbouring areas are considered parts of historical Silesia. Those districts, along with Poland's [[Lower Silesian Voivodeship]] and parts of [[Lubusz Voivodeship]], make up the geographic region of [[Lower Silesia]].

Silesia has undergone a similar notional extension at its eastern extreme. Historically it extended only as far as the [[Brynica]] river, which separates it from [[Zagłębie Dąbrowskie]] in the [[Lesser Poland]] region. However to many Poles today, Silesia (''Śląsk'') is understood to cover all of the area around Katowice, including Zagłębie. This interpretation is given official sanction in the use of the name [[Silesian Voivodeship]] (''województwo śląskie'') for the province covering this area. In fact the word ''Śląsk'' in Polish (when used without qualification) now commonly refers exclusively to this area (also called ''Górny Śląsk'' or [[Upper Silesia]]).

As well as the Katowice area, historical Upper Silesia also includes the [[Opole]] region (Poland's [[Opole Voivodeship]]) and [[Czech Silesia]]. Czech Silesia consists of a part of the [[Moravian-Silesian Region]] and the [[Jeseník District]] in the [[Olomouc Region]].

==Natural resources==

Silesia is a resource-rich and populous region.

Since the middle of the 18th century, coal has been mined. The industry grew during German rule and peaked in the 1970s under the [[History of Poland (1945–1989)|People's Republic of Poland]]. During this period Silesia became one of the world's largest producers of coal, with a record tonnage in 1979.&lt;ref name=&quot;en.poland.gov.pl&quot;&gt;http://en.poland.gov.pl/Natural,Resources,310.html&lt;/ref&gt; Coal mining declined during the next two decades but has increased again following the end of Communist rule.

There are 41 coal mines in Silesia, most forming part of the Gornoslaskie Zaglebie Weglowe coalfield which lies in the Silesian Upland. The field has an area of about 4,500&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;ref name=&quot;en.poland.gov.pl&quot;/&gt; Deposits in Lower Silesia have proven to be difficult to exploit and the area's unprofitable mines were closed in 2000.&lt;ref name=&quot;en.poland.gov.pl&quot;/&gt; In 2008 an estimated 35 billion tonnes of [[lignite]] reserves was found near Legnica, making them some of the largest in the world.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gazetawyborcza.pl/1,82244,4820533.html Article &quot;We have the largest reserves of lignite in the world&quot;, Gazeta Wyborcza, 2008-01-08 (in Polish)]&lt;/ref&gt;

From the fourth century BC iron ore has been mined in the upland areas of Silesia.&lt;ref name=&quot;en.poland.gov.pl&quot;/&gt; The same period saw lead, copper, silver and gold mining. Zinc, cadmium, arsenic,&lt;ref&gt;S.Z. Mikulski, &quot;Late-Hercynian gold-bearing arsenic-polymetallic mineralization within Saxothuringian zone in the Polish Sudetes, Northeast Bohemian Massif&quot;. In: &quot;Mineral Deposit at the Beginning of the 21st Century&quot;, A. Piestrzyński et al. (eds). Swets &amp; Zeitinger Publishers [http://books.google.com/books?id=DcUk9rlWHuEC&amp;pg=PA787&amp;lpg=PA787 (Google books)]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[uranium]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www10.antenna.nl/wise/index.html?http://www10.antenna.nl/wise/439-440/poland.html WISE - Nuclear issues information service]&lt;/ref&gt; have also been mined in the region. Lower Silesia features large copper mining and processing between the cities of [[Legnica]], [[Głogów]], Lubin and Polkowice.
	
The region is known for stone quarrying specifically in the [[Swietokrzyskie Mountains]] and in the [[Lublin Upland]]&lt;ref name=&quot;en.poland.gov.pl&quot;/&gt; primarily to produce limestone, [[marl]], marble, and basalt.

{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+'''Annual production of minerals in Silesia'''
|-
!Mineral Name
!Production (tonnes)
!Reference
|-
|Bituminous coal
|95,000,000
|
|-
|Copper
|571,000
|&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.indexmundi.com/en/commodities/minerals/copper/copper_t21.html Copper: World Smelter Production, By Country]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|Zinc
|160,000
|&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.indexmundi.com/en/commodities/minerals/zinc/zinc_table18.html Zinc: World Smelter Production, By Country]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|Silver
|1,200
|&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.indexmundi.com/en/commodities/minerals/silver/silver_table08.html Silver: World Mine Production, By Country]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|Cadmium
|500
|&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.indexmundi.com/en/commodities/minerals/cadmium/cadmium_t5.html Cadmium: World Refinery Production, By Country]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|Lead
|70,000
|&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.indexmundi.com/en/commodities/minerals/lead/lead_t16.html Lead: World Refinery Production, By Country]&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

The region also has a thriving [[agriculture|agricultural]] sector, which produces cereals (wheat, rye, barley, oats, corn), potatoes, rapeseed, sugar beets and others. Milk production is well developed. The Opole Silesia has for decades occupied the top spot in Poland for their indices of effectiveness of agricultural land use.&lt;ref&gt;[http://umwo.opole.pl/serwis/index.php?id=2009 Web site of the Opole regional government containing the current statistics (in Polish)]&lt;/ref&gt;

Mountainous parts of southern Silesia feature many significant and attractive tourism destinations (e.g., [[Karpacz]], [[Szczyrk]], [[Wisła]]). Silesia is generally well forested. This is because greenness is generally highly desirable by the local population, particularly in the highly industrialized parts of Silesia.

==Demographics==
[[File:Polskie-nazwy śląskich miejscowosci z patentu Fryderyka II 1750.jpg|thumb|300px|Polish names of Silesian cities in [[Polish language|Polish]], from a 1750 Prussian official document published in [[Berlin]] during the [[Silesian Wars]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sbc.org.pl/dlibra/doccontent?id=26222&amp;from=FBC Prusian document from 1750 in Polish - &quot;Wznowione powszechne taxae-stolae sporządzenie, Dla samowładnego Xięstwa Sląska, Podług ktorego tak Auszpurskiey Konfessyi iak Katoliccy Fararze, Kaznodzieie i Kuratusowie Zachowywać się powinni. Sub Dato z Berlina, d. 8. Augusti 1750&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Modern Silesia is inhabited by [[Poles]], [[ethnic Germans|Germans]], [[Czechs]] and [[Silesians]]. The last Polish census of 2002 showed that the Silesians are the largest national minority in Poland, Germans being the second; both groups are located mostly in [[Upper Silesia]]. The Czech part of Silesia is inhabited by [[Czechs]], [[Moravians (ethnic group)|Moravians]], [[Silesians]] and [[Poles]].

Before the Second World War, Silesia was inhabited mostly by Germans and Poles, with a Czech and Jewish minority. In 1905, a census showed that 75% of the population were Germans and 25% Poles.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} The German population tended to be based in the urban centres and in the rural areas to the north and west, whilst the Polish population was generally rural and in the east.&lt;ref&gt;Hunt Tooley, T (1997). ''National Identity and Weimar Germany: Upper Silesia and the Eastern Border, 1918-1922,'' University of Nebraska Press, p.17.&lt;/ref&gt;

Silesia's Jewish community, who were concentrated around [[Wrocław|Breslau]] and Upper Silesia, numbered 48,003 (1.1% of the population) in 1890, decreasing to 44,985 persons (0.9%) by 1910.&lt;ref&gt;Kamusella, T (2007). ''Silesia and Central European nationalisms: the emergence of national and ethnic groups in Prussian Silesia and Austrian Silesia, 1848-1918,'' Purdue University Press, p.173.&lt;/ref&gt; In Polish East Upper Silesia the number of Jews was around 90,000-100,000.&lt;ref&gt;Christopher R. Browning (2000). ''Nazi Policy, Jewish Workers, German Killers,'' Cambridge University Press, 2000, p.147.&lt;/ref&gt;

After the German invasion of Poland in 1939, the Jewish population of Silesia was either placed in ghettos or expelled to the [[General Government]]. Those sent to ghettos would from 1942 be expelled to concentration and work camps.&lt;ref&gt;Steinbacher, S. &quot;In the Shadow of Auschwitz, The murder of the Jews of East Upper Silesia&quot;, in Cesarani, D. (2004) ''Holocaust: From the persecution of the Jews to mass murder,'' Routledge, pp.110-138.&lt;/ref&gt; In August 1942 10,000 to 13,000 Silesian Jews were killed at Auschwitz.&lt;ref&gt;Christopher R. Browning (2007). ''The Origins of the Final Solution: The Evolution of Nazi Jewish Policy, September 1939-March 1942,'' University of Nebraska Press, p.544.&lt;/ref&gt; There were seventy thousand Jews in Lower Silesia at the end of the war.&lt;ref&gt;Kochavi, AJ (2001). ''Post-Holocaust politics: Britain, the United States &amp; Jewish refugees, 1945-1948,'' University of North Carolina Press, p.176.&lt;/ref&gt;

The majority of Germans fled or were expelled from the present-day Polish and Czech parts of Silesia during and after World War II. From June 1945 to January 1947, 1.77 million Germans were expelled from Lower Silesia, and 310,000 from Upper Silesia.&lt;ref&gt;DB Klusmeyer &amp; DG Papademetriou (2009). ''Immigration policy in the Federal Republic of Germany: negotiating membership and remaking the nation,'' Berghahn, p.70.&lt;/ref&gt; Today, most German Silesians and their descendants live in the territory of the Federal Republic of Germany, many of them in the [[Ruhr area]] working as miners, like their ancestors in Silesia. In order to smooth their integration into West German society after 1945, they were placed into officially recognized organizations, like the [[Landsmannschaft Schlesien]], with financing from the federal Western German budget.{{Citation needed|date=April 2009}} One of its most notable but controversial spokesmen was the [[Christian Democratic Union (Germany)|CDU]] politician [[Herbert Hupka]]. Prevailing public opinion in Germany is that these organisations will achieve reconciliation with the Polish Silesians, which is gradually occurring.{{Citation needed|date=April 2009}}&lt;!-- What does this even mean? --&gt;

The expulsion of Germans led to widespread underpopulation. The population of the town of [[Glogau]] fell from 33,500 to 5,000, and from 1939 to 1966 the population of [[Wrocław]] fell by 25%.&lt;ref&gt;Scholz, A (1964). ''Silesia: yesterday and today,'' Martinus Nijhoff, The Hague, p.69.&lt;/ref&gt; Attempts to repopulate Silesia proved unsuccessful in the 1940s and 1950s,&lt;ref&gt;Mazower, M (1999). ''Dark Continent: Europe's 20th Century,'' Penguin, p.223.&lt;/ref&gt; and it was not until the late 1970s that Silesia's population reached pre-war levels.

==Cities==
The following table lists the cities in Silesia with a population greater than 100,000 (2006) 
{| cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; cellpadding=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 0 1em 1em; text-align:center; width:150px; float:right;&quot;
|-
|[[File:Wroclaw 1.jpg|115px|center]]
|-
|[[Wrocław]]
|-
|[[File:Ostrava, pohled z Nové radnice 2.jpg|115px|center]]
|-
|[[Ostrava]] 
|-
|[[File:K-ce (noc 1).jpg|115px|center]]
|-
|[[Katowice]]
|-
|[[File:PL Bielsko Biala Ratusz.JPG|115px|center]]
|-
|[[Bielsko-Biała]]
|-
|[[File:PL Opole NCentrum.jpg|115px|center]]
|-
|[[Opole]]
|-
|[[File:Goerlitz bruecke waidhaus und st peter u paul.jpg|115px|center]]
|-
|[[Görlitz]]
|}

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;margin:auto;&quot;
|-
!style=&quot;width:1%;&quot;|
!style=&quot;width:1%;&quot;|
!style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Name
!style=&quot;width:8%;&quot;| Population
!style=&quot;width:8%;&quot;| Area
!style=&quot;width:17%;&quot;| Administrative
!style=&quot;width:4%;&quot;| Country
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|| 1 || [[File:Herb wroclaw.svg|center|25px]] || style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;| '''[[Wrocław]]'''|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 632,162 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 293&amp;nbsp;km² || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Lower Silesian Voivodeship|Lower Silesian V.]] || [[File:Flag of Poland.svg|center|33px]]
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|| 2 || [[File:Ostrava CoA CZ.svg|center|25px]] || style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;| '''[[Ostrava]]'''* || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 336,556 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 214&amp;nbsp;km² || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Moravian-Silesian Region|Moravian-Silesian R.]] || [[File:Flag of the Czech Republic.svg|center|33px]]
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|| 3 || [[File:Katowice Herb.svg|center|25px]] || style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;| '''[[Katowice]]'''|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 317,220 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 165&amp;nbsp;km² || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Silesian Voivodeship]] || [[File:Flag of Poland.svg|center|33px]]
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|| 4 || [[File:Gliwice herb.svg|center|25px]] || style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;| '''[[Gliwice]]'''|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 199,451 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 134&amp;nbsp;km² || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Silesian Voivodeship]] || [[File:Flag of Poland.svg|center|33px]]
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|| 5 || [[File:Bytom herb.svg|center|25px]] || style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;| '''[[Bytom]]'''|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 187,943 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 69&amp;nbsp;km² || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Silesian Voivodeship]] || [[File:Flag of Poland.svg|center|33px]]
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|| 6 || [[File:POL Zabrze COA.svg|center|25px]] || style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;| '''[[Zabrze]]'''|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 191,247 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 80&amp;nbsp;km² || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Silesian Voivodeship]] || [[File:Flag of Poland.svg|center|33px]]
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|| 7 || [[File:POL Bielsko-Biała COA.svg|center|48px]] || style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;| '''[[Bielsko-Biała]]'''*|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|176,864 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 125&amp;nbsp;km² || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Silesian Voivodeship]] || [[File:Flag of Poland.svg|center|33px]]
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|| 8 || [[File:POL Ruda Śląska COA.svg|center|25px]] || style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;| '''[[Ruda Śląska]]'''|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 146,658 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 78&amp;nbsp;km² || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Silesian Voivodeship]] || [[File:Flag of Poland.svg|center|33px]]
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|| 9 || [[File:POL Rybnik COA.svg|center|25px]] || style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;| '''[[Rybnik]]''' || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 141,580 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 148&amp;nbsp;km² || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Silesian Voivodeship]] || [[File:Flag of Poland.svg|center|33px]]
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|| 10 || [[File:POL Tychy COA.svg|center|25px]] || style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;| '''[[Tychy]]'''|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 131,153 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 82&amp;nbsp;km² || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Silesian Voivodeship]] || [[File:Flag of Poland.svg|center|33px]]
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|| 11 || [[File:POL Opole COA.svg|center|25px]] || style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;| '''[[Opole]]'''|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 128,268 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 97&amp;nbsp;km² || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Opole Voivodeship]] || [[File:Flag of Poland.svg|center|33px]]
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|| 12 || [[File:POL Wałbrzych COA.svg|center|25px]] || style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;| '''[[Wałbrzych]]''' || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 126,465 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 85&amp;nbsp;km² || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Lower Silesian Voivodeship|Lower Silesian V.]] || [[File:Flag of Poland.svg|center|33px]]
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|| 13 || [[File:POL Zielona Góra COA.svg|center|25px]] || style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;| '''[[Zielona Góra]]'''|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 118,221 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 58&amp;nbsp;km² || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Lubusz Voivodeship]] || [[File:Flag of Poland.svg|center|33px]]
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|| 14 || [[File:Chorzów herb.svg|center|25px]] || style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;| '''[[Chorzów]]'''|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 114,686 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 33&amp;nbsp;km² || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Silesian Voivodeship]] || [[File:Flag of Poland.svg|center|33px]]
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|| 15 || [[File:Legnica herb.svg|center|25px]] || style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;| '''[[Legnica]]'''|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 105,750|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 56&amp;nbsp;km² || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Lower Silesian Voivodeship|Lower Silesian V.]] || [[File:Flag of Poland.svg|center|33px]]
|}* Only part in Silesia

==See also==
* [[Architecture of Silesia]]
* [[Czech Silesia]]
* [[Austrian Silesia]]
* [[Expulsion of Germans after World War II]]
* [[Expulsion of Poles by Germany]]
* [[List of Silesians]]
* [[Silesian cuisine]]
* [[Silesian language]]
* [[Silesian German]]
* [[Silesians]]
* [[Slezak]]

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
* {{Cite book|last=Długajczyk|first=Edward|authorlink=Edward Długajczyk|title=Tajny front na granicy cieszyńskiej. Wywiad i dywersja w latach 1919-1939|publisher=Śląsk|year=1993|location=[[Katowice]]| pages=|doi=|isbn=83-85831-03-7}}
* {{Cite book|last=Zahradnik|first=Stanisław|coauthors=and Marek Ryczkowski|title=Korzenie Zaolzia| publisher=PAI-press|year=1992|location=Warszawa - Praga - Trzyniec|pages=|url=|doi=|oclc=177389723}}
* {{Cite book|last=Weczerka|first=Hugo|authorlink=|title=Handbuch der historischen Stätten: Schlesien|publisher=Alfred Kröner Verlag|year=2003|location=[[Stuttgart]]|page=738|doi=|isbn= 3-520-31602-1}}
*{{1911}}

==Further reading==
* de Zayas, Alfred M.: A terrible Revenge. Palgrave/Macmillan, New York, 1994. ISBN 1-4039-7308-3.
* de Zayas, Alfred M.: Nemesis at Potsdam. London, 1977. ISBN 0-8032-4910-1.
* Douglas, R.M.: Orderly and Humane. The Expulsion of the Germans after the Second World War. Yale University Press, 2012. ISBN 978-0300166606.
*''Documents on British Foreign Policy 1919–1939'', 1st Series, volume XI, ''Upper Silesia, Poland, and the Baltic States, January 1920-March 1921'', edited by Rohan Butler, MA, J.P.T.Bury, MA, &amp; M.E.Lambert, MA, Her Majesty's Stationery Office (HMSO), London, 1961 (amended edition 1974), ISBN 0-11-591511-7
*''Documents on British Foreign Policy 1919–1939'', 1st Series, volume XVI, ''Upper Silesia, March 1921 – November 1922'', edited by W.N. Medlicott, MA, D.Lit., Douglas Dakin, MA, PhD, &amp; M.E.Lambert, MA, HMSO, London, 1968
* Kleineberg A., Marx Ch., Knobloch E., Lelgemann D.: Germania und die Insel Thule. Die Entschlüsselung von Ptolemaios: &quot;Atlas der Oikumene&quot;. Wissenschaftliche Buchgesellschaft, 2010.
*''Microcosm, Portrait of a Central European City'', by [[Norman Davies]] and [[Roger Moorhouse]] ([[Jonathan Cape]], 2002) ISBN 0-224-06243-3
*''Dehio - Handbuch der Kunstdenkmäler in Polen: Schlesien'', Herder-Institut Marburg and Krajowy Osrodek Badan i Dokumentacji Zabytkow Warszawa, Deutscher Kunstverlag 2005, ISBN 3-422-03109-X

==External links==
{{Commons|Silesia}}
*[http://web.archive.org/web/20070727142251/http://brws.silesia-region.pl/indexang.php Silesia in Europe page]
*[http://www.hoeckmann.de/germany/silesia.htm Map of Silesia in 1763]
*[http://www.vogel-soya.de/bilder/Schlesphoto.html Old postcards from Silesian towns]
*[http://www.schlesierland.de/index.html Photos from Silesian towns, villages and communities before 1946]
*[http://www.tr62.de/maps/Silesia-2000.html Map of Silesia as of 2000]
*[http://www.upper-silesia.com/map.html Silesia in maps of Europe]
*[http://google.com/search?q=cache:hpCJqtZMuwoJ:www.dhm.de/ausstellungen/europas-mitte-um-1000/EM_Pressemappe_deutsch.pdf+herstellung+bronze+T%C3%BCren+gnesen&amp;hl=en&amp;gl=us&amp;ct=clnk&amp;cd=2 Combined European History Exhibit by Germans, Poles, Czech, Slovaks and Hungarians]

{{Silesia topics}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2010}}

[[Category:Silesia| ]]
[[Category:Historical regions in the Czech Republic]]
[[Category:Divided regions]]
[[Category:Historical regions in Germany]]
[[Category:Historical regions in Poland]]
[[Category:States of the Holy Roman Empire]]

{{Link GA|eo}}
[[af:Silesië]]
[[ar:سيليزيا]]
[[az:Sileziya]]
[[bg:Силезия]]
[[bs:Šleska]]
[[br:Silezia]]
[[ca:Silèsia]]
[[cs:Slezsko]]
[[cy:Silesia]]
[[da:Schlesien]]
[[de:Schlesien]]
[[et:Sileesia]]
[[el:Σιλεσία]]
[[es:Silesia]]
[[eo:Silezio]]
[[eu:Silesia]]
[[fa:سیلیزیا]]
[[fr:Silésie]]
[[fy:Sileezje]]
[[gl:Silesia]]
[[ko:실롱스크]]
[[hsb:Šleska]]
[[hr:Šleska]]
[[id:Silesia]]
[[os:Силези]]
[[it:Slesia]]
[[he:שלזיה]]
[[jv:Silesia]]
[[ka:სილეზია]]
[[la:Silesia]]
[[lv:Silēzija]]
[[lb:Schlesien]]
[[lt:Silezija]]
[[hu:Szilézia]]
[[mzn:سیلزی]]
[[mdf:Силезие]]
[[nl:Silezië]]
[[ja:シレジア]]
[[no:Schlesien]]
[[nn:Schlesien]]
[[oc:Silèsia]]
[[pl:Śląsk]]
[[pt:Silésia]]
[[ro:Silezia]]
[[ru:Силезия]]
[[simple:Silesia]]
[[sk:Sliezsko]]
[[sl:Šlezija]]
[[szl:Ślůnsk]]
[[sr:Шлеска]]
[[sh:Šleska]]
[[fi:Sleesia]]
[[sv:Schlesien]]
[[tl:Silesya]]
[[th:ไซลีเซีย]]
[[tr:Silezya]]
[[uk:Сілезія]]
[[vi:Silesia]]
[[yi:שלעזיע]]
[[zh:西里西亞]]</text>
      <sha1>60wdkj1boxg2wop310ipyalrm7wq2lm</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
