<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>The Rape of Nanking (book)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>65735</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519756620</id>
      <parentid>519722096</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-25T13:28:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mateinsixtynine</username>
        <id>3065507</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 519722096 by [[Special:Contributions/Agentveritas|Agentveritas]] ([[User talk:Agentveritas|talk]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="45092">&lt;!--This article uses the old spelling of &quot;Nanking&quot; in &quot;Nanking Massacre&quot; but &quot;Nanjing&quot; when referring to the city itself, per article naming for English Wikipedia for both subjects--&gt;
{{Infobox book
| name           = The Rape of Nanking
| title_orig     =
| translator     =
| image          = [[Image:TheRapeOfNanking 1edCover.jpg]]
| image_caption  = First edition cover of ''The Rape of Nanking''
| author         = [[Iris Chang]]
| illustrator    =
| cover_artist   = Rick Pracher
| country        = United States of America
| language       = English
| series         =
| subject        = [[Nanking Massacre]]
| genre          = History/Military/War
| publisher      = [[Basic Books]]
| pub_date       = 1997
| media_type     = Print ([[Hardcover]])
| pages          = 290 pp ''(first edition)''
| isbn           = 0-465-06835-9
| dewey= 951.04/2 21
| congress= DS796.N2 C44 1997
| oclc= 37281852
| preceded_by    =
| followed_by    =
}}
'''''The Rape of Nanking: The Forgotten Holocaust of World War II''''' is a [[Bestseller|bestselling]] 1997 [[non-fiction]] book written by [[Iris Chang]] about the 1937–1938 [[Nanking Massacre]], the massacre and atrocities committed by the [[Imperial Japanese Army]] after it captured [[Nanjing]], then capital of [[Republic of China|China]], during the [[Second Sino-Japanese War]]. It describes the events leading up to the Nanking Massacre and the atrocities that were committed. The book presents the view that the [[Japanese government]] has not done enough to redress the atrocities. It is one of the first major English-language books to introduce the Nanking Massacre to [[Western world|Western]] and [[Eastern world|Eastern]] readers alike, and has been translated into several languages.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.irischangmemorialfund.org/A_Brief_Biography_of_Iris_Chang.pdf|title=A Brief Biography of Iris Chang|publisher=Global Alliance for Preserving the History of WW II in Asia|accessdate=2007-07-27|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The book was a source of fame for Chang but was also controversial; it was received with both acclaim and criticism by the public and by academics. It has been praised as a work that &quot;shows more clearly than any previous account&quot; the extent and brutality of the episode,&lt;ref name=&quot;KirbyForward&quot;&gt;Forward by William C. Kirby, in: {{cite book|author=Iris Chang|title=The Rape of Nanking|publisher=Penguin Books|year=1998|isbn=0-465-06835-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; while at the same time it was criticized as &quot;seriously flawed&quot; and &quot;full of misinformation and harebrained explanations&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fogel&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|journal=The Journal of Asian studies|author=Joshua A. Fogel|title=Reviewed Work|month=August|year=1998|pages=818–820|volume=57|issue=3|jstor=2658758}}&lt;/ref&gt; Chang's research on the book was credited with the finding of the diaries of [[John Rabe]] and [[Minnie Vautrin]], both of whom played important roles in the [[Nanking Safety Zone]], a designated area in Nanjing that protected Chinese civilians during the Nanking Massacre.&lt;ref name=&quot;SFGate2005-04-17&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/c/a/2005/04/17/CMGCNBQRRP1.DTL|title=Historian Iris Chang won many battles/The war she lost raged within|publisher=SFGate|date=2005-04-17|accessdate=2007-07-22 | first=Heidi | last=Benson}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The book prompted [[AOL]] executive [[Ted Leonsis]] to fund and produce ''[[Nanking (film)|Nanking]]'', a 2007 [[documentary film]] about the Nanking Massacre.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/07/30/AR2006073000026.html|title=Ted Leonsis Takes a Sharp Turn|publisher=The Washington Post|date=2006-07-31|accessdate=2007-07-22 | first=Thomas | last=Heath}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Inspiration==
When Iris Chang was a child, she was told by her immigrant parents, who had escaped from China via [[Taiwan]] to the United States during [[World War II]], that during the Nanking Massacre, the Japanese &quot;sliced babies not just in half but in thirds and fourths&quot;. In the introduction of ''The Rape of Nanking'', she wrote that throughout her childhood, the Nanking Massacre &quot;remained buried in the back of [her] mind as a metaphor for unspeakable evil&quot;.  When she searched the local public libraries in her school and found nothing, she wondered why nobody had written a book about it.&lt;ref name=&quot;RapeOfNanking7-8&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Iris Chang|title=The Rape of Nanking|publisher=Penguin Books|year=1998|isbn=0-465-06835-9|pages=7–8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The subject of the Nanking Massacre entered Chang's life again almost two decades later when she learned of producers who had completed documentary films about it. One of the producers was Shao Tzuping, who helped produce ''Magee's Testament'', a film that contains footage of the Nanking Massacre itself, shot by the [[missionary]] [[John Magee (missionary)|John Magee]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Princeton&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.princeton.edu/~nanking/html/proposal.pdf|title=Proposal for The Nanking Conference at Princeton University|publisher=Princeton University|accessdate=2007-07-23|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; The other producer was Nancy Tong, who, together with Christine Choy, produced and co-directed ''In The Name of the Emperor'', a film containing a series of interviews with Chinese, American, and Japanese citizens.&lt;ref name=&quot;Princeton&quot; /&gt;  Chang began talking to Shao and Tong, and soon she was connected to a network of activists who felt the need to document and publicize the Nanking Massacre.&lt;ref name=&quot;RapeOfNanking8-9&quot;&gt;Chang, ''The Rape of Nanking'', pp. 8-9&lt;/ref&gt;  In December 1994, she attended a conference on the Nanking Massacre, held in [[Cupertino, California|Cupertino]], [[California]], and what she saw and heard at the conference motivated her to write ''The Rape of Nanking''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Penguin&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://us.penguingroup.com/static/rguides/us/rape_of_nanking.html|title=The Rape of Nanking|publisher=Penguin Group USA|accessdate=2007-07-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;  As she wrote in the introduction to the book, while she was at the conference, she was &quot;suddenly in a panic that this terrifying disrespect for death and dying, this reversion in human social evolution, would be reduced to a footnote of history, treated like a harmless glitch in a computer program that might or might not again cause a problem, unless someone forced the world to remember it&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;RapeOfNanking10&quot;&gt;Chang, ''The Rape of Nanking'', pp. 10&lt;/ref&gt;

==Research==
Chang spent two years on research for the book.&lt;ref name=&quot;SFGate2005-04-17&quot; /&gt; She found that raw source materials were available in the US, contained in the diaries, films, and photographs of American missionaries, journalists, and military officers who were in [[Nanjing]] at the time of the Nanking Massacre.&lt;ref name=&quot;RapeOfNanking11&quot;&gt;Chang, ''The Rape of Nanking'', pp. 11&lt;/ref&gt;  Additionally, she traveled to Nanjing to interview survivors of the Nanking Massacre and to read Chinese accounts and confessions by Japanese army veterans.&lt;ref name=&quot;SFGate1998&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/chronicle/archive/1998/07/26/SC77214.DTL|title=Wars of Memory|publisher=SFGate|date=1998-07-26|accessdate=2007-07-21 | first=Charles | last=Burress}}&lt;/ref&gt; Chang did not, however, conduct research in Japan, and this left her vulnerable to criticisms on how she portrayed modern Japan in the context of how it deals with its World War II past.&lt;ref name=&quot;SFGate1998&quot; /&gt;

Chang's research led her to make what one ''[[San Francisco Chronicle]]'' article called &quot;significant discoveries&quot; on the subject of the Nanking Massacre, in the forms of the diaries of two Westerners that were in Nanjing leading efforts to save lives during the Japanese invasion.&lt;ref name=&quot;SFGate2005-04-17&quot; /&gt; One diary was that of John Rabe, a [[Germans|German]] [[Nazi Party]] member who was the leader of the Nanking Safety Zone, a [[demilitarized zone]] in Nanjing that Rabe and other Westerners set up to protect Chinese civilians.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://humanum.arts.cuhk.edu.hk/NanjingMassacre/NMNR.html|title=Rabe's Records of &quot;The Rape of Nanjing&quot; Discovered|publisher=The Chinese University of Hong Kong|date=1996-09-26|accessdate=2007-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The other diary belonged to Minnie Vautrin, the American missionary who saved the lives of about 10,000 women and children when she provided them with shelter in [[Ginling College]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Vautrin&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.siu.edu/~siupress/titles/s00_titles/hu_goddess.htm|title=American Goddess at the Rape of Nanking|publisher=Southern Illinois University|accessdate=2007-07-23 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070525134253/http://www.siu.edu/~siupress/titles/s00_titles/hu_goddess.htm |archivedate = May 25, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The diaries documented the events of the Nanking Massacre from the perspectives of their writers, and provided detailed accounts of atrocities that they saw, as well as information surrounding the circumstances of the Nanking Safety Zone. Chang dubbed Rabe the &quot;[[Oskar Schindler]] of Nanking&quot; and Vautrin the &quot;[[Anne Frank]] of Nanking&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;SFGate2005-04-17&quot; /&gt;  Rabe's diary is over 800 pages, and contains one of the most detailed accounts of the Nanking Massacre.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=PrAoHzoP1QkC&amp;pg=RA1-PA121&amp;lpg=RA1-PA121&amp;dq=%22john+rabe%22+diary+%22detailed+accounts%22|author=Malcolm Trevor|title=Japan: Restless Competitor|publisher=Routledge|year=2001|isbn=1-903350-02-6|pages=121}}&lt;/ref&gt; Translated into English, it was published in 1998 by [[Random House]] as ''[[The Good Man of Nanking: The Diaries of John Rabe]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=John Rabe|title=The Good Man of Nanking: The Diaries of John Rabe|publisher=Random House|year=1998|isbn=0-375-40211-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Vautrin's diary recounts her personal experience and feelings on the Nanking Massacre; in it, an entry reads, &quot;There probably is no crime that has not been committed in this city today.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/223038.stm|title=Scarred by history: The Rape of Nanjing|publisher=BBC News|date=2005-04-11|accessdate=2007-07-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It was used as source material by Hua-ling Hu for a biography of Vautrin and her role during the Nanking Massacre, entitled ''[[American Goddess at the Rape of Nanking: The Courage of Minnie Vautrin]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.atimes.com/atimes/China/DH24Ad01.html|title=An American hero in Nanking|publisher=Asia Times|date=2002-08-24|accessdate=2007-07-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==The book==
''The Rape of Nanking'' is structured into three main parts.  The first uses a technique that Chang called &quot;the [[Rashomon (film)|Rashomon perspective]]&quot; to narrate the events of the Nanking Massacre, from three different perspectives:  that of the Japanese military, the Chinese victims, and the Westerners who tried to help Chinese civilians.  The second part concerns the postwar reaction to the massacre, especially that of the American and European governments.  The third part of the book examines the circumstances that, Chang believed, have kept knowledge of the massacre out of public consciousness decades after the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;RapeOfNanking14-15&quot;&gt;Chang, ''The Rape of Nanking'', pp. 14-15&lt;/ref&gt;

===Atrocities===
The book depicted in detail the killing, torture, and rape that occurred during the Nanking Massacre.  Chang listed and described the kinds of torture that were visited upon the residents, including [[live burial]]s, [[mutilation]], &quot;death by fire&quot;, &quot;death by ice&quot;, and &quot;death by dogs&quot;.  Based on the testimony of a survivor of the massacre, Chang also described a killing contest amongst a group of Japanese soldiers to determine who could kill the fastest.&lt;ref name=&quot;RapeOfNanking83-88&quot;&gt;Chang, ''The Rape of Nanking'', pp. 83-88&lt;/ref&gt;  On the rape that occurred during the massacre, Chang wrote that &quot;certainly it was one of the greatest mass rapes in world history.&quot;  She estimated that the number of women raped ranged from 20,000 to as many as 80,000,&lt;ref name=&quot;RapeOfNanking89&quot;&gt;Chang, ''The Rape of Nanking'', p. 89. Chang's sources listed as: Catherine Rosair, ''For One Veteran, Emperor Visit Should Be Atonement''; George Fitch, ''Nanking Outrages''; Li En-han, ''Questions of How Many Chinese Were Killed by the Japanese Army in the Great Nanking Massacre''&lt;/ref&gt; and stated that women from all classes were raped, including [[Buddhist nun]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;RapeOfNanking90&quot;&gt;Chang, ''The Rape of Nanking'', p. 90. Chang's sources listed as: Hu Hua-ling, ''Chinese Women Under the Rape of Nanking''&lt;/ref&gt;  Furthermore, rape occurred in all locations and at all hours,&lt;ref name=&quot;RapeOfNanking90-91&quot;&gt;Chang, ''The Rape of Nanking'', pp. 90-91. Chang's sources listed as: Fitch, ''Nanking Outrages''; Gao Xingzu et al., ''Japanese Imperialism and the Massacre in Nanjing''&lt;/ref&gt; and both very young and very old women were raped.&lt;ref name=&quot;RapeOfNanking91a&quot;&gt;Chang, ''The Rape of Nanking'', p. 91. Chang's sources listed as: Hu Hua-ling, ''Chinese Women Under the Rape of Nanking''; David Nelson Sutton, ''All Military Aggression in China Including Atrocities Against Civilians and Others''; Shuhsi Hsu, ''Documents of the Nanking Safety Zone''&lt;/ref&gt;  Not even pregnant women were spared, Chang wrote, and that after gang rape, Japanese soldiers &quot;sometimes slashed open the bellies of pregnant women and ripped out the [[fetus]]es for amusement&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;RapeOfNanking91b&quot;&gt;Chang, ''The Rape of Nanking'', p. 91. Chang's sources listed as: Dagong Daily (Feb. 7, 1938), ''A Debt of Blood''; Xinhua Daily (Feb. 24, 1951); Hu Hua-ling, ''Chinese Women Under the Rape of Nanking''; Tang Shunsan, interview with Chang; Gao Xingzu et al., ''Japanese Imperialism and the Massacre in Nanjing''&lt;/ref&gt;  Not all rape victims were women, according to the book, Chinese men were sodomized and forced to perform repulsive sexual acts.&lt;ref name=&quot;RapeOfNanking95a&quot;&gt;Chang, ''The Rape of Nanking'', pp. 95. Chang's sources listed as: Shuhsi Hsu, ''Documents of the Nanking Safety Zone''&lt;/ref&gt;  Some were forced to commit incest—fathers to rape their own daughters, brothers their sisters, sons their mothers.&lt;ref name=&quot;RapeOfNanking95b&quot;&gt;Chang, ''The Rape of Nanking'', p. 95. Chang's sources listed as: Guo Qi, ''Shendu xueluilu'', Xijing Pingbao (August 1938).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Death toll===
Chang wrote of the death toll estimates given by different sources; Chinese military specialist Liu Fang-chu proposed a figure of 430,000, officials at the [[Nanjing Massacre Memorial Hall]] and the procurator of the District Court of Nanjing in 1946 stated at least 300,000 were killed, the [[International Military Tribunal for the Far East]] (IMTFE) judges concluded that more than 260,000 people were killed, Japanese historian Fujiwara Akira approximated 200,000, John Rabe, who &quot;never conducted a systematic count and left Nanking in February&quot;, estimated only 50,000 to 60,000, and Japanese author [[Ikuhiko Hata]] argued the number killed was between 38,000 and 42,000.&lt;ref name=&quot;RapeOfNanking100&quot;&gt;Chang, ''The Rape of Nanking'', p. 100.&lt;/ref&gt;

The book discussed the research of historian Sun Zhaiwei of the Jiangsu Academy of Social Sciences.  In his 1990 paper, ''The Nanking Massacre and the Nanking Population'', Sun estimated the total number of people killed at 377,400.  Using Chinese burial records, he calculated that the number of dead exceeded the figure of 227,400.  He then added estimates totaling 150,000 given by Japanese Imperial Army Major Ohta Hisao in a confessional report about the Japanese army's disposal efforts of dead bodies, arriving at the sum of 377,400 dead.&lt;ref name=&quot;RapeOfNanking101&quot;&gt;Chang, ''The Rape of Nanking'', pp. 101&lt;/ref&gt;

Chang wrote that there is &quot;compelling evidence&quot; that the Japanese themselves, at the time, believed that the death toll may have been as high as 300,000. She cited a message that [[Minister for Foreign Affairs (Japan)|Japan's foreign minister]] [[Kōki Hirota]] relayed to his contacts in [[Washington, DC]] in the first month of the massacre on January 17, 1938.  The message acknowledged that &quot;not less than three hundred thousand Chinese civilians [were] slaughtered, many cases in cold blood.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;RapeOfNanking103-104&quot;&gt;Chang, ''The Rape of Nanking'', pp. 103-104&lt;/ref&gt;

==Acclaim==
[[Image:Rape-of-nanking-cover.gif|thumb|right|250px|Second edition (1998) of the book.]]
''The Rape of Nanking'' sold more than half a million copies when it was first published in the U. S., and according to ''[[The New York Times]]'', received general critical acclaim.&lt;ref name=&quot;NewYorkTimes&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.irischang.net/press_article.cfm?n=1|title=History's Shadow Foils Nanking Chronicle|publisher=The New York Times (article hosted by IrisChang.net)|date=1999-05-20|accessdate=2007-07-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Iris Chang became an instant celebrity in the U. S.;&lt;ref name=&quot;TimesOnline&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/life_and_style/article429065.ece|title=One final victim of the Rape of Nanking?|publisher=Times Online|date=2005-03-17|accessdate=2007-07-21 | location=London | first=Oliver | last=August}}&lt;/ref&gt; she was awarded honorary degrees,&lt;ref name=&quot;SFGate2004-11-11&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/c/a/2004/11/11/MNGB59PKL01.DTL|title=Chinese American writer found dead in South Bay|publisher=SFGate|date=2004-11-11|accessdate=2007-07-21 | first=Charles | last=Burress}}&lt;/ref&gt; invited to give lectures and to discuss the Nanking Massacre on shows such as ''[[Good Morning America]]'', ''[[Nightline (US news program)|Nightline]]'', and ''[[The NewsHour with Jim Lehrer]]'', and was profiled by ''The New York Times'' and featured on the cover of ''[[Reader's Digest]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Penguin&quot; /&gt;  The book was on the [[New York Times Best Seller list|''New York Times''' Best Seller list]] for 10 weeks and sold more than 125,000 copies in four months.&lt;ref name=&quot;SFGate1998&quot; /&gt;  [[Hillary Clinton]] invited her to the [[White House]], U. S. historian [[Stephen Ambrose]] described her as &quot;maybe the best young historian we've got&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;TimesOnline&quot; /&gt; and the [[Organization of Chinese Americans]] named her National Woman of the Year.&lt;ref name=&quot;SFGate2004-11-11&quot; /&gt;  The book's popularity prompted a lengthy book tour, with Chang visiting 65 cities in over a year and a half.&lt;ref name=&quot;SFGate2005-04-17&quot; /&gt;

The book received praise from news media. ''[[The Wall Street Journal]]'' wrote that it was the &quot;first comprehensive examination of the destruction of this Chinese imperial city&quot;, and that Chang &quot;skillfully excavated from oblivion the terrible events that took place&quot;. ''[[The Atlantic Monthly]]'' described the book as &quot;a crushing indictment of the Japanese army's behavior&quot;. The ''[[Chicago Tribune]]'' called it &quot;a powerful new work of history and moral inquiry&quot; and stated that &quot;Chang takes great care to establish an accurate accounting of the dimensions of the violence.&quot;  ''[[The Philadelphia Inquirer]]'' wrote that it was a &quot;compelling account of a horrendous episode that, until recently, has been largely forgotten&quot;, and that &quot;animals do not behave the way the Japanese troops of the Imperial Army behaved.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;MediaPraise&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.irischang.net/press_article.cfm?n=14|title=Media Praise For The Rape of Nanking|publisher=IrisChang.net|accessdate=2007-07-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to [[William C. Kirby]], Professor of History at [[Harvard University]], Chang &quot;shows more clearly than any previous account just what [the Japanese] did&quot;, and that she &quot;draws connections between the slaughter in Europe and in Asia of millions of innocents during World War II&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;KirbyForward&quot; /&gt; Ross Terrill, an associate in research at the Fairbank Center for East Asian Research at [[Harvard University]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.perseusbooksgroup.com/basic/author_detail.jsp?id=1000016300|title=Ross Terrill|publisher=Basic Books|accessdate=2007-07-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; wrote that the book is &quot;scholarly, an exciting investigation and a work of passion&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Quotes&quot;&gt;Quotes on the Jacket and Interior of - {{cite book|author=Iris Chang|title=The Rape of Nanking|publisher=Penguin Books|year=1998|isbn=0-465-06835-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; Beatrice S. Bartlett, [[Emeritus Professor]] of History at [[Yale University]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.yale.edu/history/faculty/bartlett.html|title=Beatrice S. Bartlett|publisher=Yale University|accessdate=2007-07-21 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20060920012335/http://www.yale.edu/history/faculty/bartlett.html |archivedate = September 20, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; wrote, &quot;Iris Chang's research on the Nanking holocaust yields a new and expanded telling of this World War II atrocity and reflects thorough research.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Quotes&quot; /&gt;

==Criticism==
Joshua A. Fogel, at [[York University]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://chinajapan.org/fogel|title=Joshua A. Fogel|publisher=Sino-Japanese Studies|accessdate=2007-07-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; argued that the book is &quot;seriously flawed&quot; and &quot;full of misinformation and harebrained explanations.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fogel&quot; /&gt;  He suggested that the book &quot;starts to fall apart&quot; when Chang tries to explain why the massacre took place, as she repeatedly comments on &quot;the Japanese psyche&quot;, which she sees as &quot;the historical product of centuries of conditioning that all boil down to [[mass murder]]&quot; even though in the introduction, she wrote that she would offer no &quot;commentary on the Japanese character or the genetic makeup of a people who could commit such acts&quot;. Fogel asserted that part of the problem was Chang's &quot;lack of training as a historian&quot; and another part was &quot;the book's dual aim as passionate polemic and dispassionate history&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fogel&quot; /&gt; [[David M. Kennedy (historian)|David M. Kennedy]], a Pulitzer Prize-winning professor of history at [[Stanford University]], also pointed out that while Chang noted that &quot;this book is not intended as a commentary on the Japanese character,&quot; she then wrote about the &quot;'Japanese identity'—a bloody business, in her estimation, replete with martial competitions, samurai ethics, and the fearsome warriors' code of [[bushido]]&quot;, making the inference that &quot;'the path to Nanking' runs through the very marrow of Japanese culture.&quot; Kennedy also suggested that &quot;accusation and outrage, rather than analysis and understanding, are this book's dominant motifs, and although outrage is a morally necessary response to Nanjing, it is an intellectually insufficient one.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kennedy&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | author=David M. Kennedy | title=The Horror : Should the Japanese atrocities in Nanking be equated with the Nazi Holocaust? | url=http://www.theatlantic.com/doc/199804/nanking | journal=[[The Atlantic Monthly]] | pages=110–116 | volume=281 | issue=4 |month=April | year=1998 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Roger B. Jeans, professor of history at [[Washington and Lee University]], referred to Chang's book as &quot;half-baked history&quot;, and criticized her lack of experience with the subject matter:

&lt;blockquote&gt;In writing about this horrific event, Chang strives to portray it as an unexamined Asian holocaust. Unfortunately, she undermines her argument—she is not a trained historian—by neglecting the wealth of sources in English and Japanese on this event. This leads her into errors such as greatly inflating the population of Nanjing (Nanking) at that time and uncritically accepting the Tokyo War Crimes Tribunal and contemporary Chinese figures for the numbers of Chinese civilians and soldiers killed. What particularly struck me about her argument was her attempt to charge all Japanese with refusing to accept the fact of the 'Rape of Nanking' and her condemnation of the 'persistent Japanese refusal to come to terms with its past.'
&lt;ref name=Jeans&gt;{{cite journal|last=Jeans|first=Roger B.|date=January 2005|title=Victims or Victimizers? Museums, Textbooks, and the War Debate in Contemporary Japan|journal=The Journal of Military History|publisher=Society for Military History|volume=69|issue=1|pages=149–195|doi=10.1353/jmh.2005.0025}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Jeans continued what he calls &quot;giving the lie to Iris Chang's generalizations about 'the Japanese'&quot; by discussing the clashing interest groups within Japanese society over such things as museums, textbooks, and war memory.&lt;ref name=Jeans/&gt;

Robert Entenmann, professor of history at [[St. Olaf College]], criticized the work on the grounds that the &quot;Japanese historical background Chang presents is clichéd, simplistic, stereotyped, and often inaccurate.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stolaf.edu/depts/history/faculty/entenmann.html|title=Robert Entenmann|publisher=St. Olaf College|accessdate=2007-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; On Chang's treatment of modern Japanese reaction to the massacre, he writes that Chang seemed &quot;unable to differentiate between some members of the ultranationalist fringe and other Japanese&quot;, and that &quot;her own ethnic [[prejudice]] implicitly pervades her book.&quot; Stating that Chang's description of the massacre is &quot;open to criticism&quot;, Entenmann further commented that Chang &quot;does not adequately explain why the massacre occurred&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ess.uwe.ac.uk/genocide/reviewswc3.htm|title=Book review of ''The Rape of Nanking''|publisher=University of the West of England|accessdate=2007-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Timothy M. Kelly, professor at Edogawa University,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uky.edu/CIS/JAT/HallofFame/halloffame/kelly2000.htm|title=Timothy M. Kelly|publisher=University of Kentucky|accessdate=2007-07-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; described Chang's work as exhibiting &quot;simple carelessness, sheer sloppiness, historical inaccuracies, and shameless plagiarism.&quot;  Kelly further criticized Chang for her &quot;lack of attention to detail&quot;.{{#tag:ref|As examples of this lack of attention to detail, Kelly cited a number of errors such as incorrectly referring to Commodore [[Matthew C. Perry|Perry]] as &quot;Commander&quot; and writing [[Itô Nobufumi]]'s name as &quot;Ito Nobufumo&quot;, without a [[circumflex]] on the letter ''o''.  As an example of &quot;sheer sloppiness&quot;, Kelly cited Chang's sentence, &quot;Another rape victim was found with a golf stick rammed into her&quot;, and noted that &quot;(while) golfers do colloquially refer to their clubs as 'sticks'&quot;, the terms &quot;golf club&quot; or &quot;the shaft of a golf club&quot; should have been used.&lt;ref name=Kelly&gt;{{cite journal|author=Timothy M. Kelly|url=http://www.edogawa-u.ac.jp/~tmkelly/research_review_nanking.html|title=Book Review: The Rape of Nanking by Iris Chang|journal=Edogawa Women's Junior College Journal|issue=15|month=March|year=2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;|group=note}} Finally, Kelly charged that Chang had [[Plagiarism|plagiarized]] passages and an illustration from ''Japan's Imperial Conspiracy'' by [[David Bergamini]].&lt;ref name=Kelly /&gt;

Kennedy criticized Chang's accusation of &quot;Western indifference&quot; and &quot;Japanese denial&quot; of the massacre as &quot;exaggerated&quot;, commenting that &quot;the Western world in fact neither then nor later ignored the Rape of Nanking&quot;, &quot;nor is Chang entirely correct that Japan has obstinately refused to acknowledge its wartime crimes, let alone express regret for them.&quot; Chang argues that Japan &quot;remains to this day a renegade nation,&quot; having &quot;managed to avoid the moral judgment of the civilized world that the Germans were made to accept for their actions in this nightmare time.&quot; However, according to Kennedy, this accusation has already become a cliché of Western criticism of Japan, most notably exemplified by [[Ian Buruma]]'s ''The Wages of Guilt'' (1994), whose general thesis might be summarized as &quot;Germany remembers too much, Japan too little.&quot; Kennedy pointed out that a vocal Japanese left has long kept the memory of Nanking alive, noting the [[Resolution to renew the determination for peace on the basis of lessons learned from history|1995 resolution]] of Japan's [[House of Councillors]] that expressed &quot;deep remorse&quot; (''fukai hansei'') for the suffering that Japan inflicted on other peoples during World War II and clear [[List of war apology statements issued by Japan|apologies]] (''owabi'') for Imperial Japan's offenses against other nations from two Japanese Prime Ministers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kennedy&quot; /&gt;

Sonni Efron of the ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'' warned that the bitter row over Iris Chang's book may leave Westerners with the &quot;misimpression&quot; that little has been written in Japan about the Nanjing Massacre, when in fact the [[National Diet Library]] holds at least 42 books about the Nanjing massacre and Japan's wartime misdeeds, 21 of which were written by liberals investigating Japan's wartime atrocities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://japanforum.hp.infoseek.co.jp/zheng/04/1122a.htm 我看张纯如《南京大屠杀》]&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, Efron noted that geriatric Japanese soldiers have published their memoirs and have been giving speeches and interviews in increasing numbers, recounting the atrocities they committed or witnessed. After years of government-enforced denial, Japanese middle school textbooks now carry accounts of the Nanjing massacre as accepted truth.&lt;ref name=once&gt;{{cite news | title=Once Again, Japan is at war over History | author=Sonni Efron | publisher=[[Los Angeles Times]] | date=June 6, 1999 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Fogel also writes: &quot;Dozens of Japanese scholars are now actively engaged in research on every aspect of the war.... Indeed, we know many details of the Nanjing massacre, Japanese sexual exploitation of 'comfort women,' and biological and chemical warfare used in China because of the trailblazing research&quot; of Japanese scholars.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fogel&quot; /&gt;

[[Image:Baoshan1937-Asahi-01.jpg|thumb|right|250px|The original version of a photograph used by Chang—the accuracy of the caption in the book is disputed&lt;ref name=&quot;SFGate1998&quot; /&gt;]]
''[[San Francisco Chronicle]]'' staff writer Charles Burress wrote that Chang's quote of a secret telegram sent by Japan's foreign minister in 1938 was incorrectly cited as &quot;compelling evidence&quot; that Japanese troops killed at least 300,000 Chinese civilians in Nanjing.&lt;ref name=&quot;SFGate1998&quot; /&gt; According to Burress, the figure of 300,000 Chinese civilians killed actually came from a message sent by a British reporter, concerning deaths not only in Nanjing but in other places as well.  Additionally, Burress questioned Chang's motivation for writing the book - whether she wrote it as an activist or as a historian, stating that the book &quot;draws its emotional impetus&quot; from her conviction to not let the Nanking Massacre be forgotten by the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;SFGate1998&quot; /&gt;  Burress also cited [[Ikuhiko Hata]], a Japanese history professor at [[Nihon University]], who argued that 11 photos in the book were misrepresented or fake. One particular photo shows women and children walking across a bridge with Japanese soldiers, and captioned as &quot;The Japanese rounded up thousands of women. Most were gang-raped or forced into military prostitution.&quot; Hata stated that the photo originally appeared in 1937 in a Japanese newspaper as part of a series of photos that showed peaceful scenes of Chinese villagers under Japanese occupation.&lt;ref name=&quot;SFGate1998&quot; /&gt;

Chang responded to Charles Burress's criticism in a letter written to the ''San Francisco Chronicle'', but the letter was not published by the newspaper.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://vikingphoenix.com/public/rongstad/news/bamr/changletter.htm|title=San Francisco Chronicle refused to publish Iris Chang's rebuttal|publisher=VikingPhoenix.com|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20010305234642/http://www.vikingphoenix.com/public/rongstad/news/bamr/changletter.htm|archivedate=2001-03-05|date=1999-06-18|accessdate=2007-07-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In the letter, she offered criticism of her own concerning Burress's article.&lt;ref name=&quot;ChangLetter&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.irischang.net/press_article.cfm?n=9|title=Iris Chang's Letter to the San Francisco Chronicle|publisher=IrisChang.net|accessdate=2007-07-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Chang found a &quot;disturbing tendency&quot; by Burress to quote right-wing Japanese critics &quot;without demanding evidence to back up their allegations&quot;. She argued that Ikuhiko Hata, a source cited by Burress, was not &quot;regarded as a serious scholar&quot; in either Japan or in the U. S., because he was a regular contributor to &quot;ultra right-wing&quot; Japanese publications.  One such publication had published an article from a [[Holocaust denial|Holocaust denier]] that argued that no [[gas chamber]]s were used in [[Germany]] to kill [[Jew]]s. This caused the parent publisher to shut down the publication. On Burress's criticism of her inaccurate photo captioning, Chang disputed the contention that the caption was wrong. She wrote that her book dealt with the &quot;horror of the Japanese invasion of China&quot;, and that the caption reading &quot;The Japanese rounded up thousands of women. Most were gang-raped or forced into military prostitution&quot; contained two statements of indisputable fact.

Chang also issued a rejoinder to Burress's argument that she incorrectly cited a telegram sent by Japan's foreign minister. She wrote that while the original figure of 300,000 Chinese civilian deaths in Nanjing was reported by a British reporter, this figure was cited in a message that Japan's foreign minister sent to his contacts in [[Washington, DC]]. Chang argued that figure's use by a high-ranking Japanese government official was evidence that the Japanese government recognized 300,000 as the number of Chinese civilian deaths. Finally, she criticized Burress for his &quot;nitpick&quot; of small details in order to draw attention away from the scope and magnitude of the Nanking Massacre, writing that such was a &quot;common tactic&quot; of Holocaust deniers.&lt;ref name=&quot;ChangLetter&quot; /&gt;

==Reaction in Japan==
[[Image:Rape-of-nanking-J-cover.png|thumb|right|200px|Japanese translation of the book, published in December 2007]]
''The Rape of Nanking'' has caused controversy in Japan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://search.japantimes.co.jp/cgi-bin/nn20070223a5.html|title=LDP-DPJ group plan to scrutinize 'Rape of Nanking'|publisher=The Japan Times|date=2007-02-23|accessdate=2007-07-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;  ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'' staff writer, Sonni Efron, reported that Chang was also criticized by both Japanese &quot;ultranationalists&quot;, who believe that the massacre in Nanjing never took place, and Japanese liberals, who &quot;insist the massacre happened but allege that Chang's flawed scholarship damages their cause&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;CHGS&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://chgs.umn.edu/news/v3i1.html#nanjingmassacre|journal=CHGS Newsletter|publisher=University of Minnesota Center for Holocaust and Genocide Studies|title=Nanjing Massacre Disputed Again!|year=2000|volume=3|issue=1|accessdate=2007-07-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Associate Professor David Askew of
[[Ritsumeikan Asia Pacific University]] stated that Chang's work dealt a &quot;severe blow&quot; to the &quot;Great Massacre School&quot; of thought, which advocates for the validity of the findings at the [[Tokyo Trials]], the tribunal convened to try the leaders of the [[Empire of Japan]] for crimes committed during World War II. Askew further argued that &quot;the Great Massacre School has thus been forced into the (unusual) position of criticising a work that argues for a larger death toll.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Askew&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.japanesestudies.org.uk/articles/Askew.html|title=The Nanjing Incident|publisher=Electronic journal of contemporary Japanese studies|date=2002-04-04|accessdate=2007-07-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the publication of ''The Rape of Nanking'', Japanese critic [[Masaaki Tanaka]] had his 1987 book on Nanking translated into English. Entitled ''What Really Happened in Nanking: The Refutation of a Common Myth'', Tanaka stated in his introduction &quot;I am convinced that [American researchers] will arrive at the realization that violations of international law of the magnitude alleged by Iris Chang in ''The Rape of Nanking'' (more than 300,000 murders and 80,000 rapes) never took place.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Critic disputes 'Rape of Nanking' in English translation of '87 work What Really Happened in Nanking--The Refutation of Common Myth |last=Anai|first=Ikuo|date=6 May 2001|publisher=''[[The Daily Yomiuri]]'' (Tokyo)|page= 23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Chang's book was not published in a translated Japanese language edition until December 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title=「ザ・レイプ・オブ・南京」の日本語版が出版 | url=http://j.people.com.cn/2007/12/17/jp20071217_81293.html | publisher=[[People's Daily]] | date=2007-12-17|accessdate=2007-12-18 | language=Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;ザ・レイプ・オブ・南京—第二次世界大戦の忘れられたホロコースト. Translated by 巫召鴻. ISBN 4-88683-617-8&lt;/ref&gt; Problems with translation efforts surfaced immediately after a contract was signed for the Japanese publishing of the book. A Japanese literary agency informed Chang that several Japanese historians declined to review the translation, and that one professor backed out because of pressure placed on his family from &quot;an unknown organization&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;NewYorkTimes&quot; /&gt;  According to Japan scholar Ivan P. Hall,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.japanreview.net/interview_ivan_hall.htm|title=Ivan P. Hall|publisher=Japan Review Net|accessdate=2007-07-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; revisionist historians in Japan organized a committee of right-wing scholars to condemn the book with repeated appearances at the [[Foreign Correspondents' Club]] in [[Tokyo]] and throughout Japan.  They prevailed on Kashiwa Shobo, the contracted Japanese publisher of the book, to insist that Chang edit the book for &quot;corrections&quot; they wanted made, to delete photographs and alter maps, and to publish a rebuttal to Chang's book. Chang disagreed with the changes and, as a result, withdrew the Japanese publishing of the book.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hall&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jpri.org/publications/occasionalpapers/op28.html|title=Japan and the U.S.: Sidelining the Heterodox|publisher=Japan Policy Research Institute|year=2002|month=December|accessdate=2007-07-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The rebuttal piece was nonetheless published as a book by [[Nobukatsu Fujioka]] and Shudo Higashinakano entitled ''A Study of 'The Rape of Nanking'''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hall&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Higashinakano&quot; /&gt;

Shudo Higashinakano, a professor of intellectual history at [[Asia University (Japan)|Asia University of Japan]], argued in ''[[Sankei Shimbun]]'' that the book was &quot;pure baloney&quot;, that there was &quot;no witness of illegal executions or murders&quot;, and that &quot;there existed no 'Rape of Nanking' as alleged by the Tokyo Trial.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Higashinakano&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jiyuu-shikan.org/e/nanking4.html|title=California State Assembly Should Indict the Atomic Bomb Droppings on Japan|publisher=Association for Advancement of Unbiased View of History|date=1999-09-05|accessdate=2007-07-22|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20070810191502/http://www.jiyuu-shikan.org/e/nanking4.html &lt;!--Added by H3llBot--&gt;|archivedate=2007-08-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;  He identified 90 historical factual errors in the first 64 pages of the book, some of which were corrected in the 1998 [[Penguin Books]] edition.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mistakes&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jiyuu-shikan.org/nanjing/errors.html|title=Thanks for correcting some mistakes|publisher=Association for Advancement of Unbiased View of History|accessdate=2007-07-22|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20070705013557/http://www.jiyuu-shikan.org/nanjing/errors.html &lt;!--Added by H3llBot--&gt;|archivedate=2007-07-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Chang's death===
[[File:Nanjing massacre footprints of survivors.jpg|thumb|Nanjing massacre [[footprint]]s of survivors]]

The book was the main source of fame for Iris Chang, who was well respected in China for raising awareness of the Nanking Massacre in the Western world.&lt;ref name=&quot;SFGate2004-11-11&quot; /&gt; At the same time, Chang received hate mail, primarily from Japanese [[Nationalism#Ultranationalism|ultranationalists]],&lt;ref name=&quot;SFGate2005-04-17&quot; /&gt; threatening notes on her car and believed her phone was tapped. She responded overwhelmingly{{Clarify|date=January 2012}} to any question of the validity of her work. Her mother said the book &quot;made Iris sad&quot;. Suffering from [[Clinical depression|depression]], Chang was diagnosed with &quot;brief reactive [[psychosis]]&quot; in August 2004. She began taking medications to stabilize her mood.&lt;ref name=&quot;SFGate2005-04-17&quot; /&gt; She wrote: &lt;blockquote&gt;''I can never shake my belief that I was being recruited, and later persecuted, by forces more powerful than I could have imagined. Whether it was the [[Central Intelligence Agency|CIA]] or some other organization I will never know. As long as I am alive, these forces will never stop hounding me.''&lt;ref name=&quot;SFGate2005-04-17&quot; /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; Succumbing to her battle with depression, Chang took her own life November 9, 2004.&lt;ref name=&quot;SFGate2005-04-17&quot; /&gt; A memorial service was held in China by Nanking Massacre survivors coinciding with her funeral in [[Los Altos, California|Los Altos]] [[California]]. The [[Nanjing Massacre Memorial Hall|Memorial Hall of the Victims in the Nanjing Massacre]], a memorial site in Nanjing built to commemorate the victims of the Nanking Massacre,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nj1937.org|title=The memorial hall of the victims in Nanjing massacre by Japanese invaders|accessdate=2007-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; added a wing dedicated to her in 2005.&lt;ref name=&quot;SFGate2004-11-20&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2004/11/20/DDGN29TV0G1.DTL|title=Iris Chang's suicide stunned those she tried so hard to help &amp;mdash; the survivors of Japan's 'Rape of Nanking'|publisher=SFGate|date=2004-11-20|accessdate=2007-07-21 | first=Kathleen E. | last=McLaughlin}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the U. S., a Chinese garden in [[Norfolk, Virginia|Norfolk]], [[Virginia]], which contains a memorial to [[Minnie Vautrin]], added a memorial dedicated to Chang, including her as the latest victim of the Nanking Massacre, and drawing parallels between Chang and Vautrin, who also took her own life.&lt;ref name=&quot;SFGate2004-11-20&quot; /&gt; Vautrin exhausted herself trying to protect women and children during the Nanking Massacre and subsequently during the Japanese occupation of Nanjing, finally suffering a nervous breakdown in 1940. She returned to the US for medical treatment, committing suicide a year later.&lt;ref name=&quot;Vautrin&quot; /&gt;

==See also==
* [[Black Sun: The Nanking Massacre]]
* [[City of Life and Death]]
* [[Don't Cry, Nanking]]
* ''[[Nanking (film)|Nanking]]''
* [[Tokyo Trial (film)]]

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|group=note}}

== Editions ==
* English: {{Cite book|title=The Rape of Nanking: The Forgotten Holocaust of World War II|last=Chang|first=Iris|year=1997|isbn=978-0-465-06835-7|pages=290|publisher=Basic Books}}
** {{Cite book|title=The Rape of Nanking: The Forgotten Holocaust of World War II|last=Chang|first=Iris|year=1998|isbn=978-0-14-027744-9|publisher=Penguin USA (Paper)}} Foreword by Harvard professor [[William C. Kirby]].
* French: {{Cite book|title=Le viol de Nankin: 1937 : un des plus grand massacres du XXe siècle|year=2010|publisher=Payot|last=Chang|first=Iris|isbn=978-2-228-90520-6|pages=367}}
* Chinese: {{Cite book|title=南京大屠杀|publisher=东方出版社|year=2005|pages=382|translator=马志行, 田怀滨, 崔乃颖|last=张|first=纯如|isbn=978-7-5060-1052-8}}
* Japanese: 巫召鴻訳『ザ・レイプ・オブ・南京—第二次世界大戦の忘れられたホロコースト』（同時代社、2007年12月）ISBN 4-88683-617-8
::(Corrected version) 巫召鴻著『「ザ・レイプ・オブ・南京」を読む』（同時代社、2007年12月）ISBN 4886836186

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.irischang.net/ Iris Chang's official site]
* [http://www.metroactive.com/papers/metro/12.12.96/cover/china1-9650.html Interview with Iris Chang on ''The Rape of Nanking''], Metroactive (1996-12-12)
* [http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://www.geocities.com/wallstreet/floor/9597/his.html&amp;date=2009-10-26+00:04:40  Once Again, Japan is at war over History] by Sonni Efron, Time Staff Writer (1999-06-06, hosted by GeoCities.com)
* [http://web.archive.org/web/20070926232658/http://news.asianweek.com/news/view_article.html?article_id=a5c77a51584d1ae3a160ab0a1deff467 Iris’s Spirit is Everywhere], AsianWeek.com (archived version from 2006-12-08)
* [http://homepage3.nifty.com/kadzuwo/fact/ The Nanking Incident Archives] Fact Finders' Forum — includes analysis of photos.
* [http://www.pbs.org/newshour/gergen/february98/chang_2-20.html FORGOTTEN HOLOCAUST] ([[Public Broadcasting Service|PBS]], February 20, 1998)
*[http://www.booknotes.org/Watch/95452-1/Iris+Chang.aspx ''Booknotes'' interview with Chang on ''Rape of Nanking'', January 11, 1998.]

{{good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Rape Of Nanking, The}}
[[Category:1997 books]]
[[Category:Nanking Massacre books]]
[[Category:History books about the Sino-Japanese War]]
[[Category:American non-fiction books]]
[[Category:Asian-American literature]]
[[Category:Literature by Asian-American women]]

[[fr:Le Viol de Nankin]]
[[ko:난징의 강간]]
[[it:Lo stupro di Nanchino]]
[[ja:ザ・レイプ・オブ・南京]]
[[pt:O Estupro de Nanquim (livro)]]
[[zh:南京暴行：被遗忘的大屠杀]]</text>
      <sha1>g0csshql3pbjpigw6d1ccrptc9amzij</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
