<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Accountancy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2593</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521985498</id>
      <parentid>521985193</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-08T11:43:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pinethicket</username>
        <id>9674144</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>rm stray entries</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="32072">{{other uses}}
{{Accounting}}
'''Accountancy''' is the process of communicating financial information about a [[business entity]] to users such as [[shareholders]] and [[managers]].&lt;ref&gt;Elliot, Barry &amp; Elliot, Jamie: ''Financial accounting and reporting'', [[Prentice Hall]], London 2004, ISBN 0-273-70364-1, p. 3, [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=82B1L70-xrsC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;dq=Financial%20accounting%20and%20reporting&amp;pg=PA3#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false Books.Google.co.uk]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[communication]] is generally in the form of [[financial statements]] that show in money terms the [[Factors of production|economic resources]] under the control of management; the art lies in selecting the information that is relevant to the user and is reliable.&lt;ref&gt;Elliot, Barry &amp; Elliot, Jamie: ''Financial accounting and reporting'', Prentice Hall, London 2004, ISBN 0-273-70364-1, p. 3&lt;/ref&gt; The [[principle]]s of accountancy are applied to business entities in three divisions of practical art, named accounting, [[bookkeeping]], and [[auditing]].&lt;ref&gt;Goodyear, Lloyd Earnest: ''Principles of Accountancy'', Goodyear-Marshall Publishing Co., [[Cedar Rapids, Iowa]], 1913, p.7 [http://www.archive.org/download/principlesofacco00goodrich/principlesofacco00goodrich.pdf Archive.org]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[American Institute of Certified Public Accountants]] (AICPA) defines accountancy as &quot;the art of recording, classifying, and summarizing in a significant manner and in terms of money, transactions and events which are, in part at least, of financial character, and interpreting the results thereof.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Singh Wahla | first = Ramnik | title = AICPA committee on Terminology. Accounting Terminology Bulletin No. 1 Review and Résumé}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Accounting is thousands of years old; the earliest accounting records, which date back more than 7,000 years, were found in [[Mesopotamia]] ([[Assyrians]]). The people of that time relied on primitive accounting methods to record the growth of crops and herds. Accounting evolved, improving over the years and advancing as business advanced.&lt;ref name=&quot;Friedlob, G. Thomas 1996, p.1&quot;&gt;Friedlob, G. Thomas &amp; Plewa, Franklin James, ''Understanding balance sheets'', [[John Wiley &amp; Sons]], NYC, 1996, ISBN 0-471-13075-3, p.1&lt;/ref&gt;

Early accounts served mainly to assist the memory of the [[businessperson]] and the audience for the account was the [[Sole proprietorship|proprietor]] or record keeper alone. Cruder forms of accounting were inadequate for the problems created by a business entity involving multiple [[investors]], so [[double-entry bookkeeping]] first emerged in northern Italy in the 14th century, where trading ventures began to require more [[Financial capital|capital]] than a single individual was able to invest. The development of [[joint stock companies]] created wider audiences for accounts, as investors without firsthand knowledge of their [[Business operations|operations]] relied on accounts to provide the requisite information.&lt;ref&gt;Carruthers, Bruce G., &amp; Espeland, Wendy Nelson, ''Accounting for Rationality: Double-Entry Bookkeeping and the Rhetoric of Economic Rationality'', [[American Journal of Sociology]], Vol. 97, No. 1, July 1991, pp. 40-41,44 46,&lt;/ref&gt; This development resulted in a split of accounting systems for internal (i.e. [[management accounting]]) and external (i.e. [[financial accounting]]) purposes, and subsequently also in accounting and disclosure regulations and a growing need for independent attestation of external accounts by [[auditors]].&lt;ref&gt;Lauwers, Luc &amp; Willekens, Marleen: &quot;Five Hundred Years of Bookkeeping: A Portrait of Luca Pacioli&quot; (Tijdschrift voor Economie en Management, [[Katholieke Universiteit Leuven]], 1994, vol:XXXIX issue 3, p.302), [https://lirias.kuleuven.be/bitstream/123456789/119065/1/TEM1994-3_289-304p.pdf KUleuven.be]&lt;/ref&gt;

Today, accounting is called &quot;the language of business&quot; because it is the vehicle for reporting financial information about a business entity to many different groups of people. Accounting that concentrates on reporting to people inside the business entity is called [[management accounting]] and is used to provide information to employees, managers, [[Self-employment|owner-managers]] and [[auditors]]. Management accounting is concerned primarily with providing a basis for making management or operating decisions. Accounting that provides information to people outside the business entity is called [[financial accounting]] and provides information to present and potential shareholders, [[creditors]] such as [[bank]]s or vendors, [[financial analysts]], [[economists]], and [[government agencies]]. Because these users have different needs, the presentation of financial accounts is very structured and subject to many more rules than management accounting. The body of rules that governs financial accounting in a given jurisdiction is called [[Generally Accepted Accounting Principles]], or GAAP. Other rules include [[International Financial Reporting Standards]], or IFRS,&lt;ref&gt;www.ifrs.com&lt;/ref&gt; or US GAAP.

==Theory==
The basic accounting equation is [[assets]] = [[liabilities]] + [[Equity (finance)|equity]]. This is the Statement of Financial Position (It is the new name of Balance Sheet according to IFRS). The foundation for the balance sheet begins with the income statement, which is revenues - expenses = net income or net loss. This is followed by the retained earnings statement, which is beginning retained earnings + net income + additional capital(capital contribution) - dividends/drawings = ending retained earnings.

==Etymology==
The word &quot;[[Accountant]]&quot; is derived from the French word {{lang|fr|''Compter''}}, which took its origin from the [[Latin]] word {{lang|la|''Computare''}}. The word was formerly written in English as &quot;Accomptant&quot;, but in process of time the word, which was always pronounced by dropping the &quot;p&quot;, became gradually changed both in [[pronunciation]] and in [[orthography]] to its present form&lt;ref&gt;Pixley, Francis William: Accountancy — constructive and recording accountancy (Sir Isaac Pitman &amp; Sons, Ltd, London, 1900), p4&lt;/ref&gt; (see also ''[[comptroller]]'').

==History==

===Token accounting in ancient Mesopotamia===
[[File:Map of fertile cresent.svg|thumb|right|180px|Map of the Middle East showing the Fertile Crescent circa [[3rd millennium BC.]]]]
The earliest accounting records were found amongst the ruins of ancient [[Babylon]], [[Assyria]] and [[Sumer]]ia, which date back more than 7,000 years. The people of that time relied on primitive accounting methods to record the growth of crops and herds. Because there is a natural season to farming and herding, it is easy to count and determine if a [[Economic surplus|surplus]] had been gained after the crops had been harvested or the young animals weaned.&lt;ref name=&quot;Friedlob, G. Thomas 1996, p.1&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Clay accounting tokens Susa Louvre n2.jpg|thumb|180px|left|Accounting tokens made of clay, from [[Susa]], [[Uruk period]], circa 3500 BC. Department of Oriental Antiquities, [[Louvre]].]]

The invention of a form of [[bookkeeping]] using clay tokens represented a huge [[cognitive]] leap for mankind.&lt;ref&gt;Oldroyd, David &amp; Dobie, Alisdair: ''Themes in the history of bookkeeping'', The Routledge Companion to Accounting History, London, July 2008, ISBN 978-0-415-41094-6, Chapter 5, p. 96&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Accountancy clay envelope Louvre Sb1932.jpg|thumb|right|180px|Globular token envelope with a cluster of accounting tokens. Clay, [[Susa]], [[Uruk period]] (4000 to 3100 BC). Department of Oriental Antiquities, [[Louvre]].]]
[[File:Economic tablet Susa Louvre Sb3047.jpg|thumb|left|180px|Economic tablet with numeric signs. [[Proto-Elamite]] script in clay, [[Susa]], [[Uruk period]] (3200 BC to 2700 BC). Department of Oriental Antiquities, [[Louvre]].]]

===Accounting in the Roman Empire===
[[Image:Res Gestae.jpg|thumb|left|180px|Part of the ''Res Gestae Divi Augusti'' from the ''[[Monumentum Ancyranum]]'' (Temple of Augustus and Rome) at [[Ancyra]], built between 25 BCE - 20 BCE.]]
The ''[[Res Gestae Divi Augusti]]'' ([[Latin]]: &quot;The Deeds of the Divine Augustus&quot;) is a remarkable account to the Roman people of the Emperor [[Augustus]]' stewardship. It listed and quantified his public expenditure, which encompassed distributions to the people, grants of land or money to army veterans, subsidies to the ''[[aerarium]]'' (treasury), building of temples, religious offerings, and expenditures on theatrical shows and [[gladiatorial]] games. It was not an account of state revenue and expenditure, but was designed to demonstrate Augustus' munificence. The significance of the ''Res Gestae Divi Augusti'' from an accounting perspective lies in the fact that it illustrates that the [[Executive (government)|executive authority]] had access to detailed financial information, covering a period of some forty years, which was still retrievable after the event. The scope of the accounting information at the emperor's disposal suggests that its purpose encompassed planning and decision-making.&lt;ref&gt;Oldroyd, David: ''The role of accounting in public expenditure and monetary policy in the first century AD Roman Empire'', Accounting Historians Journal, Volume 22, Number 2, [[Birmingham, Alabama]], December 1995, p.124, [http://umiss.lib.olemiss.edu:82/articles/1028395.3253/1.PDF Olemiss.edu]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Roman historians [[Suetonius]] and [[Cassius Dio]] record that in 23 BC, [[Augustus]]  prepared a ''rationarium'' (account) which listed public revenues, the amounts of cash in the ''aerarium'' (treasury), in the provincial ''fisci'' (tax officials), and in the hands of the ''[[publicani]]'' (public contractors); and that it included the names of the freedmen and slaves from whom a detailed account could be obtained.  The closeness of this information to the executive authority of the emperor is attested by [[Tacitus]]' statement that it was written out by Augustus himself.&lt;ref&gt;Oldroyd, David: ''The role of accounting in public expenditure and monetary policy in the first century AD Roman Empire'', Accounting Historians Journal, Volume 22, Number 2, Birmingham, Alabama, December 1995, p.123, [http://umiss.lib.olemiss.edu:82/articles/1028395.3253/1.PDF Olemiss.edu]&lt;/ref&gt; [[File:Roman writing tablet 02.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Roman writing tablet from the Vindolanda Roman fort of [[Hadrian's Wall]], in [[Northumberland]] (1st-2nd century AD) requesting money to buy 5,000 measures of cereal used for brewing beer. Department of Prehistory and Europe, [[British Museum]].]]

Records of [[cash]], [[commodities]], and transactions were kept scrupulously by military personnel of the [[Roman army]]. An account of small cash sums received over a few days at the [[fort]] of [[Vindolanda]] circa 110 AD shows that the fort could compute [[revenues]] in cash on a daily basis, perhaps from sales of surplus supplies or goods manufactured in the camp, items dispensed to slaves such as ''cervesa'' ([[beer]]) and ''clavi caligares'' ([[Nail (fastener)|nails]] for boots), as well as commodities bought by individual soldiers. The basic needs of the fort were met by a mixture of direct [[manufacturing|production]], [[purchase]] and [[requisition]]; in one letter, a request for money to buy 5,000 ''modii'' (measures) of ''braces'' (a cereal used in brewing) shows that the fort bought provisions for a considerable number of people.&lt;ref&gt;Bowman, Alan K., ''Life and letters on the Roman frontier: Vindolanda and its people'' [[Routledge]], London, January 1998, ISBN 978-0-415-92024-7, p. 40-41,45&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Heroninos Archive]] is the name given to a huge collection of [[papyrus]] documents, mostly letters, but also including a fair number of accounts, which come from [[Roman Egypt]] in 3rd century AD. The bulk of the documents relate to the running of a large, private [[Estate (house)|estate]]&lt;ref&gt;Farag, Shawki M., ''The accounting profession in Egypt: Its origin and development'', [[University of Illinois]], 2009, p.7 [http://www.aucegypt.edu/academics/facultyresearch/Profiles/Documents/Science%20paper,%20Shawki%20Farag.pdf Aucegypt.edu]&lt;/ref&gt; is named after Heroninos because he was ''phrontistes'' ([[Koine Greek]]: [[Management|manager]]) of the estate which had a complex and standarised system of accounting which was followed by all its local farm managers.&lt;ref&gt;Rathbone, Dominic: ''Economic Rationalism and Rural Society in Third-Century AD Egypt: The Heroninos Archive and the Appianus Estate'', [[Cambridge University Press]], ISBN 0-521-03763-8, 1991, p.4&lt;/ref&gt; Each administrator on each sub-division of the estate drew up his own little accounts, for the day-to-day running of the estate, payment of the workforce, production of crops, the sale of produce, the use of animals, and general expenditure on the staff. This information was then summarized as pieces of papyrus [[scroll]] into one big yearly account for each particular sub—division of the estate. Entries were arranged by sector, with cash expenses and gains extrapolated from all the different sectors. Accounts of this kind gave the owner the opportunity to take better [[economic]] decisions because the information was purposefully selected and arranged.&lt;ref&gt;Cuomo,Serafina: ''Ancient mathematics'', [[Routledge]], London, ISBN 978-0-415-16495-5, July 2001, p.231&lt;/ref&gt;

Simple accounting is mentioned in the [[Christian Bible]] (New Testament) in the [[Book of Matthew]], in the [[Parable of the Talents]].&lt;ref&gt;Matt. 25:19&lt;/ref&gt;

===Islamic accounting and algebra===
{{off-topic|date=January 2012}}

The [[Islamic inheritance jurisprudence|Islamic law of inheritance]] ([[Sura 4]], [[ayah]] [http://www.freemedialibrary.com/index.php/Quran_4:11 11]) defines exactly how the estate is calculated after death of an individual. The power of [[testamentary disposition]] is basically limited to one-third of the net estate (i.e. the assets remaining after the payment of funeral expenses and debts), providing for every member of the family by allotting fixed shares not only to wives and children, but also to fathers and mothers.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis, Mervyn K.: ''Islam and accounting'', Wiley-Blackwell, [[Oxford]], 2001, p. 109,[http://www.acis.pamplin.vt.edu/faculty/tegarden/5034/handouts/Lewis-AcctForum-2001.pdf VT.edu]&lt;/ref&gt; The complexity of this law served as an impetus behind the development of [[algebra]] ([[Arabic language|Arabic]]: ''al-jabr'') by the [[Persian People|Persian]] mathematician [[Muhammad ibn Mūsā al-Khwārizmī]] and other medieval Islamic mathematicians. Khwārizmī's &quot;[[The Compendious Book on Calculation by Completion and Balancing]]&quot; (Arabic: ''Hisab al-jabr w'al-muqabala'', [[Baghdad]], c. 825) devoted a chapter on the solution to the Islamic law of inheritance using [[linear equation]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=The Algebra of Inheritance: A Rehabilitation of Al-Khuwarizmi|first=Solomon|last=Gandz|journal=[[Osiris (journal)|Osiris]]|volume=5|year=1938|publisher=[[University of Chicago Press]]|pages=319–91|doi=10.1086/368492|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 12th century, [[Latin]] translations of al-Khwārizmī's &quot;Book of Addition and Subtraction According to the Hindu Calculation&quot; (Arabic:''Kitāb al-Jamʿ wa-l-tafrīq bi-ḥisāb al-Hind'') on the use of [[Indian numerals]], introduced the [[decimal]] [[Positional notation|positional number system]] to the [[Western world]].&lt;ref&gt;Struik, Dirk Jan (1987), A Concise History of Mathematics (4th ed.), [[Dover Publications]], ISBN 0-486-60255-9&lt;/ref&gt;
The development of [[mathematics]] and accounting was intertwined during the [[Renaissance]]. Mathematics was in the midst of a period of significant development in the late 15th century. [[Hindu-Arabic numeral system|Hindu-Arabic numerals]] and [[algebra]] were introduced to Europe from Arab mathematics at the end of the 10th century by the Benedictine monk [[Gerbert of Aurillac]], but it was only after [[Leonardo Pisano]] (also known as Fibonacci) put commercial [[arithmetic]], Hindu-Arabic numerals, and the rules of algebra together in his [[Liber Abaci]] in 1202 that Hindu-Arabic numerals became widely used in Italy.&lt;ref&gt;Alan Sangster, Greg Stoner &amp; Patricia McCarthy, pp. 1–2&lt;/ref&gt;

===Luca Pacioli and double-entry bookkeeping ===
{{Main|Luca Pacioli|Double-entry bookkeeping system}}
When medieval Europe moved to a [[monetary economy]] in the 13th century, [[Sedentism|sedentary]] merchants depended on bookkeeping to oversee multiple simultaneous transactions financed by [[bank loan]]s. One important breakthrough took place around that time: the introduction of double-entry bookkeeping,&lt;ref name=&quot;logica.ugent.be&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Heeffer |first=Albrecht |title=On the curious historical coincidence of algebra and double-entry bookkeeping |work= Foundations of the Formal Sciences |publisher=[[Ghent University]] |date=November 2009 | page=11 |url=http://logica.ugent.be/albrecht/thesis/FOTFS2008-Heeffer.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt; which is defined as any bookkeeping system in which there was a [[debit and credit]] entry for each transaction, or for which the majority of transactions were intended to be of this form.&lt;ref&gt;Mills, Geofrey T. &quot;Early accounting in Northern Italy: The role of commercial development and the printing press in the expansion of double-entry from Genoa, Florence and Venice&quot; (Critical Perspectives on Accounting, Vol. 4 No. 2, June 1993, pp. 113-140)&lt;/ref&gt; The historical origin of the use of the words 'debit' and 'credit' in accounting goes back to the days of single-entry bookkeeping in which the chief objective was to keep track of amounts owed by customers ([[debtor]]s) and amounts owed to [[creditor]]s. 'Debit,' is [[Latin]] for 'he owes' and 'credit' Latin for 'he trusts'.&lt;ref&gt;Thiéry, Michel: ''Did you say Debit?'', [[Assumption University (Thailand)]], AU-GSB e-Journal,  Vol. 2 No. 1, June 2009, p.35, [http://gsbejournal.au.edu/2V/Journal/DID%20YOU%20SAY%20DEBIT.pdf AU.edu]&lt;/ref&gt;

The earliest extant evidence of full double-entry bookkeeping is the  Farolfi ledger of 1299-1300.&lt;ref name=&quot;logica.ugent.be&quot;/&gt; Giovanno Farolfi &amp; Company were a firm of [[Florentine]] merchants whose head office was in [[Nîmes]] who also acted as [[moneylender]]s to the [[Archbishop of Arles]], their most important customer.&lt;ref&gt;Lee, Geoffrey A., ''The Coming of Age of Double Entry: The Giovanni Farolfi Ledger of 1299-1300'', Accounting Historians Journal, Vol. 4, No. 2, 1977 p.80 [http://130.74.92.202:82/record=b1000778 University of Mississippi]&lt;/ref&gt;  The oldest discovered record of a complete double-entry system is the ''Messari'' ([[Italian language|Italian]]: [[Treasurer]]'s) accounts of the city of [[Genoa]] in 1340. The ''Messari'' accounts contain debits and credits journalised in a [[wikt:bilateral|bilateral]] form, and contain balances carried forward from the preceding year, and therefore enjoy general recognition as a double-entry system.&lt;ref&gt;Lauwers, Luc &amp; Willekens, Marleen: &quot;Five Hundred Years of Bookkeeping: A Portrait of Luca Pacioli&quot; (Tijdschrift voor Economie en Management, Katholieke Universiteit Leuven, 1994, vol:XXXIX issue 3, p.300),  [https://lirias.kuleuven.be/bitstream/123456789/119065/1/TEM1994-3_289-304p.pdf KUleuven.be]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Pacioli.jpg|thumb|right|250px|''[[Portrait of Luca Pacioli]]'', attributed to  [[Jacopo de' Barbari]], 1495, ([[Museo di Capodimonte]]).]]

[[Luca Pacioli]]'s ''&quot;Summa de Arithmetica, Geometria, Proportioni et Proportionalità&quot;'' (early Italian: &quot;Review of [[Arithmetic]], [[Geometry]], [[Ratio]] and Proportion&quot;) was first printed and published in [[Venice]] in 1494. It included a 27-page [[treatise]] on [[bookkeeping]], ''&quot;Particularis de Computis et Scripturis&quot;'' (Latin: &quot;Details of Calculation and Recording&quot;). It was written primarily for, and sold mainly to, merchants who used the book as a reference text, as a source of pleasure from the [[mathematical puzzles]] it contained, and to aid the education of their sons. It represents the first known printed treatise on bookkeeping; and it is widely believed to be the forerunner of modern bookkeeping practice. In ''Summa Arithmetica'', Pacioli introduced symbols for [[plus and minus]] for the first time in a printed book, symbols that became standard notation in Italian Renaissance mathematics. ''Summa Arithmetica'' was also the first known book printed in Italy to contain [[algebra]].&lt;ref&gt;Alan Sangster, Greg Stoner &amp; Patricia McCarthy: &quot;The market for Luca Pacioli's Summa Arithmetica&quot; (Accounting, Business &amp; Financial History Conference, Cardiff, September 2007) p.1–2, [http://www.cardiff.ac.uk/carbs/conferences/abfh07/summa.pdf Cardiff.ac.uk]&lt;/ref&gt;

Although Luca Pacioli did not invent double-entry bookkeeping,&lt;ref&gt;Carruthers, Bruce G., &amp; Espeland, Wendy Nelson, ''Accounting for Rationality: Double-Entry Bookkeeping and the Rhetoric of Economic Rationality'', American Journal of Sociology, Vol. 97, No. 1, July 1991, pp. 37&lt;/ref&gt; his 27-page [[treatise]] on bookkeeping contained the first known published work on that topic, and is said to have laid the foundation for double-entry bookkeeping as it is practiced today.&lt;ref&gt;vSangster, Alan: &quot;The printing of Pacioli's Summa in 1494: how many copies were printed?&quot; (Accounting Historians Journal, John Carroll University, Cleveland, Ohio, June 2007)&lt;/ref&gt; Even though Pacioli's treatise exhibits almost no [[originality]], it is generally considered as an important work, mainly because of its wide circulation, it was written in the [[vernacular]] [[Italian language]], and it was a printed book.&lt;ref&gt;Lauwers, Luc &amp; Willekens, Marleen: &quot;Five Hundred Years of Bookkeeping: A Portrait of Luca Pacioli&quot; (Tijdschrift voor Economie en Management, Katholieke Universiteit Leuven, 1994, vol:XXXIX issue 3, p.292), [https://lirias.kuleuven.be/bitstream/123456789/119065/1/TEM1994-3_289-304p.pdf KUleuven.be]&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Pacioli, accounting is an ad hoc ordering system devised by the merchant. Its regular use provides the merchant with continued information about his business, and allows him to evaluate how things are going and to act accordingly. Pacioli recommends the Venetian method of double-entry bookkeeping above all others. Three major books of account are at the direct basis of this system: the ''memoriale'' (Italian: [[memorandum]]), the ''giornale'' ([[Journal (accounting)|Journal]]), and the ''quaderno'' ([[ledger]]). The ledger is considered as the central one and is accompanied by an alphabetical [[Index (publishing)|index]].&lt;ref&gt;Lauwers, Luc &amp; Willekens, Marleen: &quot;Five Hundred Years of Bookkeeping: A Portrait of Luca Pacioli&quot; (Tijdschrift voor Economie en Management, Katholieke Universiteit Leuven, 1994, vol:XXXIX issue 3, p.296), [https://lirias.kuleuven.be/bitstream/123456789/119065/1/TEM1994-3_289-304p.pdf KUleuven.be]&lt;/ref&gt;

Pacioli's treatise gave instructions in how to record barter transactions and transactions in a variety of currencies – both of which were far more common than they are today. It also enabled merchants to audit their own books and to ensure that the entries in the accounting records made by their bookkeepers complied with the method he described. Without such a system, all merchants who did not maintain their own records were at greater risk of theft by their employees and agents: it is not by accident that the first and last items described in his treatise concern maintenance of an accurate [[inventory]].&lt;ref&gt;Alan Sangster, ''Using accounting history and Luca Pacioli to teach double entry'', [[Middlesex University]] Business School, September 2009, p.9, [http://www.cardiff.ac.uk/carbs/conferences/abfh2008/sangster2.pdf Cardiff.ac.uk]&lt;/ref&gt;

The nature of double-entry can be grasped by recognizing that this system of bookkeeping did not simply record the things merchants traded so that they could keep track of assets or calculate profits and losses; instead as a system of writing, double-entry produced effects that exceeded transcription and calculation. One of its social effects was to proclaim the honesty of [[merchants]] as a group; one of its [[Epistemology|epistemological]] effects was to make its formal [[Arithmetic precision|precision]] based on a [[Rule-based system|rule bound system]] of [[arithmetic]] seem to guarantee the [[Accuracy and precision|accuracy]] of the details it recorded.  Even though the information recorded in the books of account was not necessarily accurate, the combination of the double entry system's precision and the [[Normalization (sociology)|normalizing]] effect that precision tended to create, produced the impression that books of account were not only precise, but accurate as well. Instead of gaining prestige from numbers, double entry bookkeeping helped confer cultural authority on numbers.&lt;ref&gt;Poovey, Mary &quot;A history of the modern fact&quot; (University of Chicago Press, 1998) Ch.2 p.30, 58 &amp; 54&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:William welch deloitte small.jpg|thumb|[[William Welch Deloitte]]]]
Double entry accounting means that each transaction requires the use of at least two accounts.

===Accounting in the internet era===
In the [[IETF]] [[Request for Comments|RFCs]] the act of accounting is usually defined as ''the act of collecting information on resource usage for the purpose of trend analysis, auditing, billing, or cost allocation''.

For example when a user uses a connectivity service paid with a [[pay-per-view]] approach the accounting process is based on a [[metering]] of the resource usage by the user (usually time spent with an active connection or the amount of data transferred using that connection).
The accounting is hence the recording of this connectivity service ''consumption'' for subsequent charging of the service itself.

==Accounting scandals==
{{Main|Accounting scandals}}
The year 2001 witnessed a series of financial information frauds involving [[Enron Corporation]], auditing firm [[Arthur Andersen]], the telecommunications company [[WorldCom]], [[Qwest]] and [[Jarden|Sunbeam]], among other well-known corporations. These problems highlighted the need to review the effectiveness of [[Standard accounting practice|accounting standards]], auditing regulations and [[corporate governance]] principles. In some cases, management manipulated the figures shown in financial reports to indicate a better economic performance. In others, tax and regulatory incentives encouraged over-leveraging of companies and decisions to bear extraordinary and unjustified risk.&lt;ref name=&quot;mba.ufm.edu.gt&quot;&gt;Astrid Ayala and Giancarlo Ibárgüen Snr.: &quot;A Market Proposal for Auditing the Financial Statements of Public Companies&quot; (Journal of Management of Value, [[Universidad Francisco Marroquín]], March 2006) p. 41, [http://www.mba.ufm.edu.gt/journalofmanagement/content/ENG_MarketProposal.pdf UFM.edu.gt]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Enron scandal]] deeply influenced the development of new regulations to improve the reliability of financial reporting, and increased public awareness about the importance of having accounting standards that show the financial reality of companies and the objectivity and independence of auditing firms.&lt;ref name=&quot;mba.ufm.edu.gt&quot;/&gt;

In addition to being the largest bankruptcy reorganization in American history, the [[Enron scandal]] undoubtedly is the biggest audit failure.&lt;ref&gt;Bratton, William W. &quot;Enron and the Dark Side of Shareholder Value&quot; ([[Tulane Law Review]], New Orleans, May 2002) p. 61&lt;/ref&gt; It involved a financial scandal of [[Enron|Enron Corporation]] and their auditors [[Arthur Andersen]], which was revealed in late 2001. The scandal caused the dissolution of [[Arthur Andersen]], which at the time was one of the five largest accounting firms in the world.  After a series of revelations involving irregular accounting procedures conducted throughout the 1990s, Enron filed for [[Chapter 11]] bankruptcy protection in December 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Enron files for bankruptcy | publisher = BBC News | date = 2001-12-03 | url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/business/1688550.stm | accessdate = 2008-03-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One consequence of these events was the passage of [[Sarbanes–Oxley Act]] in 2002, as a result of the first admissions of fraudulent behavior made by Enron. The act significantly raises criminal penalties for [[securities fraud]], for destroying, altering or fabricating records in federal investigations or any scheme or attempt to defraud shareholders.&lt;ref&gt;Aiyesha Dey, and Thomas Z. Lys: &quot;Trends in Earnings Management and Informativeness of Earnings Announcements in the Pre- and Post-Sarbanes Oxley Periods ([[Kellogg School of Management]], Evanston, Illinois, February, 2005) p. 5&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--
N  O  T  I  C  E  : Do not add internal or external links to this article, as an extensive links to other topics are already contained in the body of the article itself. Standalone links are not necessary, as this article forms part of an extensive web of categories (see WP:CATEGORY for more information). Stand alone links are not appropriate in accordance with Wikipedia's policy on internal links (see WP:LINKFARM) and Spam (see WP:SPAM). Such links may be more appropriate in sub-topics of Accountancy. For a list of sub-topics, follow the link to Category:Accountancy at the bottom of this page, or use the search tool by inserting Category:Accountancy. Thank you.
--&gt;

Another example of corporate fraud was the case of Australian telecommunications company One-tel. The financial manager, Jodee Rich, was subsequently charged with fraud and spent several years in jail after fraudulently misrepresenting the company's financial position to encourage investment by some of Australia's richest people, including James Packer and Lachlan Murdoch.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first=Drew |last=Cratchley |date=20 November 2009 |title= One.Tel saga not over for James Packer and Lachlan Murdoch |publisher=[[The Daily Telegraph]] |url=http://www.dailytelegraph.com.au/business/news/onetel-saga-not-over-for-james-packer-and-lachlan-murdoch/story-e6frez80-1225800268330?from=public_rss }}&lt;/ref&gt; When it collapsed in 2001, One-tel lost its shareholders more than 920 million dollars.

==Notes and references==
{{Portal|Business and economics}}
{{Wiktionary|accountancy|accounting}}
{{wikibooks|Accountancy}}

{{Reflist|2}}

[[Category:Accountancy| ]]
[[Category:Finance]]

[[af:Rekeningkunde]]
[[als:Buchhaltung]]
[[ar:محاسبة]]
[[be-x-old:Бухгальтарскі ўлік]]
[[bg:Счетоводство]]
[[bs:Računovodstvo]]
[[ca:Comptabilitat]]
[[cs:Účetnictví]]
[[cbk-zam:Contabilida]]
[[da:Regnskab]]
[[de:Rechnungswesen]]
[[et:Raamatupidamine]]
[[el:Λογιστική]]
[[es:Contabilidad]]
[[eo:Kontado]]
[[eu:Kontabilitate]]
[[fa:حسابداری]]
[[fr:Comptabilité d'entreprise]]
[[ga:Cuntasaíocht]]
[[gd:Cunntasachd]]
[[gl:Contabilidade]]
[[gan:會計學]]
[[ko:회계]]
[[hr:Računovodstvo]]
[[id:Akuntansi]]
[[it:Contabilità]]
[[he:חשבונאות]]
[[ka:ბუხჰალტრული აღრიცხვა]]
[[kk:Бухгалтерлік есеп]]
[[lv:Grāmatvedība]]
[[lt:Apskaita]]
[[ln:Botángi-mbɔ́ngɔ]]
[[lez:Бухгалтердин гьисабун]]
[[hu:Számvitel]]
[[mk:Сметководство]]
[[ml:അക്കൗണ്ടൻസി]]
[[ms:Perakaunan]]
[[my:စာရင်းကိုင်ပညာ]]
[[ja:会計]]
[[no:Regnskap]]
[[nn:Rekneskap]]
[[pl:Rachunkowość]]
[[pt:Contabilidade]]
[[ro:Contabilitate]]
[[ru:Бухгалтерский учёт]]
[[sm:Suegatusi po'o suetusi]]
[[sco:Accoontin]]
[[sq:Kontabiliteti]]
[[si:ගණකාධිකරණය]]
[[simple:Accountancy]]
[[sk:Účtovníctvo]]
[[sr:Рачуноводство]]
[[sh:Računovodstvo]]
[[fi:Laskentatoimi]]
[[sv:Redovisning]]
[[tl:Pagtutuos]]
[[ta:கணக்கியல்]]
[[th:การบัญชี]]
[[tr:Muhasebe ve finans]]
[[uk:Бухгалтерський облік]]
[[ur:حسابداری]]
[[ug:بوغالتىرلىق]]
[[vi:Kế toán]]
[[yi:בוך האלטעריי]]
[[diq:Mıhasebe]]
[[bat-smg:Apskaita]]
[[zh:会计学]]</text>
      <sha1>bkz1dmcsyp0k3akzdag9ojw30vju14u</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
