<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Actuary</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>43405</id>
    <revision>
      <id>516934916</id>
      <parentid>516865505</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-10T02:34:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Malik Shabazz</username>
        <id>3020778</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted [[WP:AGF|good faith]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/86.140.148.33|86.140.148.33]] ([[User talk:86.140.148.33|talk]]): No Wikipedia article. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="43689">{{pp-move-indef}}{{Bots|deny=DASHBot, H3llBot}}
{{Infobox Occupation
 |name=Actuary 
 |image=[[File:Hurricane katrina damage gulfport mississippi.jpg|300px]]
 |caption=Damage from [[Hurricane Katrina]]. Actuaries need to estimate long-term levels of such damage in order to accurately price property insurance and set appropriate [[actuarial reserves|reserves]].
 |official_names=Actuary
&lt;!------------Details-------------------&gt;
 |type=[[Profession]]
 |activity_sector=[[Insurance]], [[Reinsurance]], [[Pension plan]]s, [[Social security|Social welfare programs]]
 |competencies=[[Mathematics]], [[finance]], analytical skills, business knowledge
 |formation=See [[#Credentialing and exams|Credentialing and exams]]
 |employment_field=Insurance companies,Superannuation funds, consulting firms and government
 |related_occupation=[[Insurance underwriter|Underwriter]]
 |average_salary=See [[#Remuneration|Remuneration]]
}}

An '''actuary''' is a business professional who deals with the financial impact of [[risk]] and uncertainty. Actuaries provide expert assessments of financial security systems, with a focus on their complexity, their mathematics, and their mechanisms {{harv|Trowbridge|1989|p=7}}.

Actuaries mathematically evaluate the probability of events and quantify the contingent outcomes in order to minimize financial losses associated with uncertain undesirable events. Since many events, such as death, cannot be avoided, it is helpful to take measures to minimize their financial impact when they occur. These risks can affect both sides of the [[balance sheet]], and require [[investment management|asset management]], [[liability (financial accounting)|liability]] management, and valuation skills. Analytical skills, business knowledge and understanding of human behavior and the vagaries of information systems are required to design and manage programs that control risk {{harv|BeAnActuary|2005a}}.

The profession has consistently ranked as one of the most desirable in various studies over the years. In 2006, a study by ''[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]'' included actuaries among the 25 Best Professions that it expects will be in great demand in the future {{harv|Nemko|2006}}. In 2010, a study published by job search website CareerCast ranked actuary as the #1 job in the United States {{harv|Needleman|2010}}. The study used five key criteria to rank jobs: environment, income, employment outlook, physical demands and stress. In 2012, the same study ranked the profession as the second best job {{harv|Thomas|2012}}.

==Disciplines==
Actuaries' [[insurance]] disciplines include [[Life insurance|life]]; [[Health insurance|health]]; [[Mathematical finance|pensions, annuities, and asset management]]; [[social security|social welfare programs]]; [[Property insurance|property]]; [[Casualty insurance|casualty]]; [[general insurance]]; and [[reinsurance]]. Life, health, and pension actuaries deal with [[Mortality rate|mortality]] risk, [[morbidity]], and consumer choice regarding the ongoing utilization of drugs and medical services risk, and investment risk. Products prominent in their work include [[life insurance]], [[Annuity (financial contracts)|annuities]], [[pension]]s, [[Mortgage insurance|mortgage]] and [[trade credit insurance|credit insurance]], short and long term [[disability]], and [[health insurance|medical, dental]], [[health savings account]]s and [[Long-term care|long term care]] insurance. In addition to these risks, [[Social security|social insurance]] programs are greatly influenced by [[public opinion]], [[politics]], budget constraints, changing [[demographics]] and other factors such as [[medical technology]], [[inflation]] and [[Cost-of-living index|cost of living]] considerations {{harv|Bureau of Labor Statistics|2009}}.

Casualty actuaries, also known as non-life or [[general insurance]] actuaries, deal with risks that can occur to people or property other than risks related to the life or health of a person. Products prominent in their work include [[auto insurance]], [[home insurance|homeowners insurance]], commercial property insurance, [[workers' compensation|workers’ compensation]], [[title insurance]], [[malpractice]] insurance, [[Product liability|products liability insurance]], [[directors and officers liability insurance]], environmental and [[marine insurance]], [[terrorism insurance]] and other types of [[liability insurance]]. [[Reinsurance]] products have to accommodate all of the previously mentioned products, and in addition have to reflect properly the increasing long term risks associated with [[climate change]], cultural litigiousness, [[War|acts of war]], [[terrorism]] and politics {{harv|Bureau of Labor Statistics|2009}}.

Both major classes of actuaries are also called upon for their expertise in [[enterprise risk management]] {{harv|Bureau of Labor Statistics|2009}}. This can involve [[dynamic financial analysis]], [[stress testing#Financial sector|stress testing]], the formulation of corporate risk policy, and the setting up and running of corporate risk departments {{harv|Institute and Faculty of Actuaries|2011b}}. Actuaries are also involved in other areas of the [[financial services]] industry, and can be involved in managing corporate credit, company evaluations, and tool development {{harv|Bureau of Labor Statistics|2009}}.

==History==

===Need for insurance===
The basic requirements of communal interests gave rise to risk sharing since the dawn of [[civilization]]. For example, people who lived their entire lives in a camp had the risk of fire, which would leave their band or family without shelter. After basic [[barter (economics)|exchange]] came into existence, more complex forms developed beyond a basic [[barter (economics)|barter]] economy, and new forms of risk manifested. [[Merchant]]s embarking on trade journeys bore the risk of losing goods entrusted to them, their own possessions, or even their lives. [[Intermediary|Intermediaries]] developed to warehouse and trade goods, and they often suffered from [[financial risk]]. The primary providers in any extended families or household always ran the risk of premature death, disability or infirmity, leaving their dependents to starve. [[Credit (finance)|Credit]] procurement was difficult if the [[lender]] worried about repayment in the event of the borrower's death or infirmity. Alternatively, people sometimes lived too long from a financial perspective, exhausting their savings, if any, or becoming a burden on others in the extended family or society {{harv|Lewin|2007|p=3}}.

===Early attempts===
In the ancient world there was not always room for the sick, suffering, disabled, aged, or the poor—these were often not part of the [[Collective consciousness|cultural consciousness]] of societies {{harv|Perkins|1995}}. Early methods of protection, aside from the normal support of the extended family, involved [[Charitable organization|charity]]; [[Religion-supporting organization|religious organizations]] or neighbors would collect for the destitute and needy. By the middle of the 3rd century, 1,500 suffering people were being supported by charitable operations in [[Ancient Rome|Rome]] {{harv|Perkins|1995}}. Charitable protection is still an active form of support to this very day {{harv|GivingUSA|2009}}. However, receiving charity is uncertain and is often accompanied by [[social stigma]]. Elementary [[mutual aid (organization)|mutual aid]] agreements and pensions did arise in antiquity {{harv|Thucydides}}. Early in the [[Roman Empire|Roman empire]], associations were formed to meet the expenses of burial, cremation, and monuments—precursors to [[Burial society|burial insurance]] and [[Friendly society|friendly societies]]. A small sum was paid into a communal fund on a weekly basis, and upon the death of a member, the fund would cover the expenses of rites and burial. These societies sometimes sold shares in the building of [[Columbarium|columbāria]], or burial vaults, owned by the fund—the precursor to [[Mutual insurance|mutual insurance companies]] {{harv|Johnston|1903|loc=§475–§476}}. Other early examples of mutual [[surety]] and [[Life insurance|assurance]] pacts can be traced back to various forms of fellowship within the Saxon clans of England and their Germanic forbears, and to Celtic society {{harv|Loan|1992}}.

Non-life insurance started as a hedge against loss of cargo during sea travel. Anecdotal reports of such guarantees occur in the writings of [[Demosthenes]], who lived in the 4th century BCE {{harv|Lewin|2007|loc=pp. 3–4}}. The earliest records of an official non-life insurance policy come from [[Sicily]], where there is record of a fourteenth century contract to insure a shipment of wheat {{harv|Sweeting|2011|p=14}}. In 1350, Lenardo Cattaneo assumed &quot;all risks from act of God, or of man, and from perils of the sea&quot; that may occur to a shipment of wheat from Sicily to Tunis up to a maximum of 300 [[Florin (Italian coin)|florin]]s. For this he was paid a premium of eighteen per cent {{harv|Lewin|2007|p=4}}. In current terminology, this would be an ocean marine contract for a rate-on-line of 18%.

===Development of theory===
[[File:Excerpt from CDC 2003 Table 1.pdf|thumb|right|2003 US mortality ([[life table|life]]) table, Table 1, Page 1]]
The 17th century was a period of extraordinary advances in mathematics in Germany, France, and England. At the same time there was a rapidly growing desire and need to place the valuation of personal risk on a more scientific basis. Independently from each other, [[compound interest]] was studied and [[probability theory]] emerged as a well understood mathematical discipline. Another important advance came in 1662 from a [[London]] [[draper]] named [[John Graunt]], who showed that there were predictable patterns of longevity and death in a defined group, or [[Cohort (statistics)|cohort]], of people, despite the uncertainty about the future longevity or mortality of any one individual person. This study became the basis for the original [[life table]]. It was now possible to set up an insurance scheme to provide life insurance or pensions for a group of people, and to calculate with some degree of accuracy how much each person in the group should contribute to a common fund assumed to earn a fixed rate of interest. The first person to demonstrate publicly how this could be done was [[Edmond Halley]]. In addition to constructing his own life table, Halley demonstrated a method of using his life table to calculate the [[Insurance|premium]] someone of a given age should pay to purchase a life-annuity {{harv|Halley|1693}}.

===Early actuaries===
[[James Dodson]]’s pioneering work on the level premium system led to the formation of the Society for Equitable Assurances on Lives and Survivorship (now commonly known as [[The Equitable Life Assurance Society|Equitable Life]]) in London in 1762. This was the first life insurance company to use premium rates which were calculated scientifically for long-term life policies, using Dodson’s work. The company still exists, though it has run into difficulties recently. After Dodson’s death in 1757, [[Edward Rowe Mores]] took over the leadership of the group that eventually became the Society for Equitable Assurances in 1762. It was he who specified that the chief official should be called an ‘actuary’ {{harv|Ogborn|1956|p=235}}. Previously, the use of the term had been restricted to an official who recorded the decisions, or ‘acts’, of ecclesiastical courts, in ancient times originally the secretary of the [[Roman senate]], responsible for compiling the [[Acta Senatus]] {{harv|Ogborn|1956|p=233}}. Other companies which did not originally use such mathematical and scientific methods most often failed or were forced to adopt the methods pioneered by Equitable {{harv|Bühlmann|1997|p=166}}.

===Development of the modern profession===
{{main|Actuarial science}}
In the 18th and 19th centuries, computational complexity was limited to manual calculations. The actual calculations required to compute fair insurance premiums are rather complex. The actuaries of that time developed methods to construct easily used tables, using sophisticated approximations called commutation functions, to facilitate timely, accurate, manual calculations of premiums {{harv|Slud|2006}}. Over time, actuarial organizations were founded to support and further both actuaries and [[actuarial science]], and to protect the public interest by ensuring competency and ethical standards {{harv|Hickman|2004|p=4}}. However, calculations remained cumbersome, and actuarial shortcuts were commonplace. Non-life actuaries followed in the footsteps of their life compatriots in the early 20th century. In the United States, the 1920 revision to workers' compensation rates took over two months of around-the-clock work by day and night teams of actuaries {{harv|Michelbacher|1920|pp=224, 230}}. In the 1930s and 1940s, however, rigorous mathematical foundations for [[stochastic]] processes were developed {{harv|Bühlmann|1997|p=168}}. Actuaries could now begin to forecast losses using models of random events instead of [[deterministic]] methods. Computers further revolutionized the actuarial profession. From pencil-and-paper to punchcards to microcomputers, the modeling and forecasting ability of the actuary has grown exponentially {{harv|MacGinnitie|1980|pp=50–51}}.

Another modern development is the convergence of modern [[finance theory|financial theory]] with actuarial science {{harv|Bühlmann|1997|pp=169–171}}. In the early 20th century, actuaries were developing many techniques that can be found in modern financial theory, but for various historical reasons, these developments did not achieve much recognition {{harv|Whelan|2002}}. However, in the late 1980s and early 1990s, there was a distinct effort for actuaries to combine financial theory and stochastic methods into their established models {{harv|D’arcy|1989}}. Today, the profession, both in practice and in the educational syllabi of many actuarial organizations, combines tables, loss models, stochastic methods, and financial theory {{harv|Feldblum|2001|pp=8–9}}, but is still not completely aligned with modern [[financial economics]] {{harv|Bader|Gold|2003}}.

==Responsibilities==
Actuaries use skills in [[mathematics]], [[economics]], [[computer science]], [[finance]], [[probability]] and [[statistics]], and [[business]] to help businesses assess the risk of certain events occurring and to formulate policies that minimize the cost of that risk. For this reason, actuaries are essential to the insurance and reinsurance industry, either as staff employees or as [[consultants]]; to other businesses, including sponsors of pension plans; and to [[government]] agencies such as the [[Government Actuary's Department|Government Actuary’s Department]] in the UK or the [[Social Security Administration]] in the US. Actuaries assemble and analyze data to estimate the probability and likely cost of the occurrence of an event such as death, sickness, injury, disability, or loss of property. Actuaries also address financial questions, including those involving the level of pension contributions required to produce a certain retirement income and the way in which a company should invest resources to maximize its return on investments in light of potential risk. Using their broad knowledge, actuaries help design and price insurance policies, pension plans, and other financial strategies in a manner which will help ensure that the plans are maintained on a sound financial basis {{harv|Bureau of Labor Statistics|2009}}.

===Traditional employment===
On both the life and casualty sides, the classical function of actuaries is to calculate premiums and reserves for insurance policies covering various risks. Premiums are the amount of money the insurer needs to collect from the policyholder in order to cover the expected losses, expenses, and a provision for profit. Reserves are provisions for future liabilities and indicate how much money should be set aside now to reasonably provide for future payouts. If you inspect the balance sheet of an insurance company, you will find that the liability side consists mainly of reserves.

On the casualty side, this analysis often involves quantifying the probability of a loss event, called the frequency, and the size of that loss event, called the severity. Further, the amount of time that occurs before the loss event is also important, as the insurer will not have to pay anything until after the event has occurred. On the life side, the analysis often involves quantifying how much a potential sum of money or a financial liability will be worth at different points in the future. Since neither of these kinds of analysis are purely [[deterministic]] processes, [[stochastic]] models are often used to determine frequency and severity [[frequency distribution|distributions]] and the [[parameter]]s of these distributions. Forecasting interest yields and currency movements also plays a role in determining future costs, especially on the life side.

Actuaries do not always attempt to predict aggregate future events. Often, their work may relate to determining the cost of financial liabilities that have already occurred, called [[Retrocession (Insurance)|retrospective reinsurance]], or the development or re-pricing of new products.

Actuaries also design and maintain products and systems. They are involved in financial reporting of companies’ assets and liabilities. They must communicate complex concepts to clients who may not share their language or depth of knowledge. Actuaries work under a strict code of ethics that covers their communications and work products, but their clients may not adhere to those same standards when interpreting the data or using it within different kinds of businesses.

===Non-traditional employment===
Many actuaries are general business managers or financial officers. They analyze business prospects with their financial skills in valuing or discounting risky future cash flows, and many apply their pricing expertise from insurance to other lines of business. Some actuaries act as [[expert witness]]es by applying their analysis in court trials to estimate the economic value of losses such as lost profits or lost wages.

There has been a recent widening of the scope of the actuarial field to include [[investment]] advice and [[asset management]]. Further, there has been a convergence from the financial fields of [[risk management]] and [[Quantitative analyst|quantitative analysis]] with [[actuarial science]]. Now, actuaries also work as risk managers, quantitative analysts, or investment specialists. Even actuaries in traditional roles are now studying and using the tools and data previously in the domain of finance {{harv|Feldblum|2001|p=8}}. One of the latest developments in the industry, insurance securitization, requires both the actuarial and finance skills {{harv|Krutov|2006}}.

Another field in which actuaries are becoming more prominent is that of [[Enterprise Risk Management]], for both financial and non-financial corporations {{harv|D’arcy|2005}}. For example, the [[Basel II]] accord for financial institutions, and its analogue, the [[Solvency II]] accord for insurance companies, requires such institutions to account for [[operational risk]] separately and in addition to [[credit risk|credit]], [[Actuarial reserves|reserve]], [[asset]], and [[insolvency]] risk. Actuarial skills are well suited to this environment because of their training in analyzing various forms of risk, and judging the potential for upside gain, as well as downside loss associated with these forms of risk {{harv|D’arcy|2005}}.

===Remuneration===
The credentialing and examination procedure for becoming a fully qualified actuary can be intensely demanding. Consequently, the profession remains very small throughout the world. As a result, actuaries are in high demand, and they are highly paid for the services they render {{harv|Ezra|2011}}. In the UK, where there are approximately 9,000 fully qualified actuaries, typical post-university starting salaries range between [[Pound sterling|GBP]] £25,300 and £35,000 and successful more experienced actuaries can earn well in excess of £100,000 a year {{harv|Lomas|2009}}.

==Credentialing and exams==
{{Main|Actuarial credentialing and exams|:Category:Actuarial associations}}
Becoming a fully credentialed actuary requires passing a rigorous series of professional examinations, usually taking several years in total. In some countries, such as Denmark, most study takes place in a university setting {{harv|Norberg|1990|p=407}}. In others, such as the U.S., most study takes place during employment through a series of examinations ({{harvnb|SOA|2012}}, {{harvnb|CAS|2011}}). In the UK, and countries based on its process, there is a hybrid university-exam structure {{harv|Institute and Faculty of Actuaries|2011a}}.

===Exam support===
As these qualifying exams are rigorous, support is usually available to people progressing through the exams. Often, employers provide paid on-the-job study time and paid attendance at seminars designed for the exams {{harv|BeAnActuary|2005b}}. Also, many companies which employ actuaries have automatic pay raises or promotions when exams are passed. As a result, actuarial students have strong incentives for devoting adequate study time during off-work hours. A common rule of thumb for exam students is that, for the Society of Actuaries examinations, roughly 400 hours of study time are necessary for each four-hour exam {{harv|Sieger|1998}}. Thus, thousands of hours of study time should be anticipated over several years, assuming no failures {{harv|Feldblum|2001|p=6}}. In practice, as the historical passing percentages remain below 50% for these exams, the “travel time” to credentialing is extended and more study time is needed. This process resembles formal schooling, so that actuaries who are sitting for exams are still called “students” or “candidates” despite holding important positions with substantial responsibilities.

==Notable actuaries==
{{Div col|colwidth = 40em}}
;[[Harald Cramér]] :Swedish actuary and probabilist notable for his contributions in the area mathematical statistics, such as the [[Cramér–Rao bound|Cramér–Rao inequality]] {{harv|Cramér|1946}}. Professor Cramér was an Honorary President of the Swedish Actuarial Society {{harv|Kendall|1983}}.

;[[James Dodson]] :Head of the Royal Mathematical School, and Stone's School, Dodson built on the statistical mortality tables developed by Edmund Halley in 1693 {{harv|Lewin|2007|p=38}}.

;[[Edmond Halley]] :While Halley actually predated much of what is now considered the start of the actuarial profession, he was the first to mathematically and statistically rigorously calculate premiums for a life insurance policy {{harv|Halley|1693}}.

;[[James C. Hickman]] :Notable actuarial educator, researcher, and author {{harv|Chaptman|2006}}.

;[[David X. Li]] : a Canadian qualified actuary who in the first decade of the 21st century pioneered the use of [[Gaussian copula]] models for the pricing of [[collateralized debt obligation]]s (CDOs). The Financial Times called him &quot;the world’s most influential actuary,&quot; while in the aftermath of the Global financial crisis of 2008–2009, to which Li's model has been credited partly to blame, his model has been called a &quot;recipe for disaster&quot;.

;[[Edward Rowe Mores]] :First person to use the title ‘actuary’ with respect to a business position {{harv|Ogborn|1956}}.

;[[William Morgan (scientist)|William Morgan]] :Morgan was the appointed Actuary of the Society for Equitable Assurances in 1775. He expanded on Mores's and Dodson's work, and may be rightly considered the father of the actuarial profession in that his title became applied to the field as a whole.{{harv|Ogborn|1973}}.

;[[Anette Norberg]] :[[Skip (curling)|Skip]] for the Swedish Women's [[Curling]] Team at the [[2010 Winter Olympics]]. Norberg has won gold medals at the 2010 Winter Olympics, the [[2006 Winter Olympics]], seven [[European Curling Championships]], and two [[World Curling Championships]].

;[[Maurice Princet]] :French actuary and close associate of artist [[Pablo Picasso]]. Princet is considered &quot;Le Mathématicien du Cubisme&quot; (&quot;The Mathematician of Cubism&quot;) for his &quot;critical influence on Picasso’s development as an artist at the birth of [[cubism]]&quot; {{harv|Boyle|2002}}.

;[[Frank Redington]] :Developed the Redington Immunization Theory

;[[I. M. Rubinow|Isaac M. Rubinow]] :Founder and first president of the [[Casualty Actuarial Society]] {{harv|CASF|2008}}.

;[[Elizur Wright]] :American actuary and abolitionist, professor of mathematics at Western Reserve College (Ohio). He campaigned for laws that required life insurance companies to hold sufficient reserves to guarantee that policies would be paid {{harv|Stearns|1905}}.
{{Div col end}}

==Fictional actuaries==
{{main|Fictional actuaries}}
Due to the low public-profile of the job, some of the most recognizable actuaries to the general public happen to be characters in movies. Many actuaries were unhappy with the stereotypical portrayals of these actuaries as unhappy, math-obsessed and socially inept people; others have claimed that the portrayals are close to home, if a bit exaggerated {{harv|Coleman|2003}}.

==References==
&lt;!-- Note: This article uses author-date citation format, not footnotes. If you have any problems, please ask on the talk page and someone will be happy to help you. Also, please place references in alphabetical order by last name or organizational name. The references have been broken into alphabetical sections to make it easier. Thank you. --&gt;
{{refbegin|2}}
&lt;!-- A --&gt;
&lt;!-- B --&gt;
*{{Cite news
 |last1=Bader
 |first1=Lawrence N.
 |last2=Gold
 |first2=Jeremy
 |year=2003
 |title=Reinventing Pension Actuarial Science
 |periodical=Pension Forum
 |volume=14
 |issue=2
 |pages=1–39
 |url=http://users.erols.com/jeremygold/reinventingpensionactuarialscience.pdf
 |format=PDF
 |accessdate=2008-09-14
 |ref=harv
}}
*{{cite web
 |year=2005a
 |url=http://www.beanactuary.com/about/whatis.cfm
 |title=What is an Actuary?
 |publisher=BeAnActuary
 |accessdate=2006-06-11
 |ref={{harvid|BeAnActuary|2005a}}
}}
*{{cite web
 |year=2005b
 |url=http://www.beanactuary.com/exams/exam_info.cfm
 |title=About Actuarial Examinations
 |publisher=BeAnActuary
 |accessdate=2006-08-21
 |ref={{harvid|BeAnActuary|2005b}}
}}
*{{cite journal
 |last=Boyle
 |first=Phelim
 |year=2002
 |month=September
 |title=The actuary and the artist
 |journal=The Actuary
 |page=32
 |url=http://www.the-actuary.org.uk/pdfs/02_09_09.pdf
 |accessdate=2007-03-15
 |format=PDF
 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite journal
 |last=Bühlmann
 |first=Hans
 |year=1997
 |month=November
 |title=The actuary: The role and limitations of the profession since the mid-19th century
 |journal=ASTIN Bulletin
 |volume=27
 |issue=2
 |pages=165–171
 |url=http://www.casact.org/library/astin/vol27no2/165.pdf
 |format=PDF
 |accessdate=2006-06-28
 |ref=harv
}}
*{{cite web
 |date=December 17, 2009
 |url=http://www.bls.gov/oco/ocos041.htm
 |title=Actuaries
 |work=Occupational Outlook Handbook, 2010-11 Edition
 |publisher=[[Bureau of Labor Statistics]], [[United States Department of Labor|U.S. Department of Labor]]
 |accessdate=February 27, 2012
 |ref={{harvid|Bureau of Labor Statistics|2009}}
}}
&lt;!-- C --&gt;
*{{cite web
 |year=2008
 |url=http://www.casact.org/about/index.cfm?fa=aboutTheCAS
 |title=History
 |work=CAS Overview
 |publisher=[[Casualty Actuarial Society]]
 |accessdate=August 14, 2011
 |ref={{harvid|CASF|2008}}
}}
*{{cite web
 |url=http://www.casact.org/admissions/syllabus/summary.pdf
 |title=2011 CAS Basic Education Summary
 |accessdate=2011-01-19
 |year=2011
 |work=Syllabus of Basic Education
 |publisher=[[Casualty Actuarial Society]]
 |format=PDF
 |ref={{harvid|CAS|2011}}
}}
*{{cite web
 |url=http://www.news.wisc.edu/12874
 |title=James C. Hickman, former business school dean, dies
 |accessdate=2008-01-11
 |last=Chaptman
 |first=Dennis
 |date=2006-09-13
 |work=News
 |publisher=[[University of Wisconsin–Madison]]
 |ref=harv
}}
*{{cite journal
 |last=Coleman
 |first=Lynn G.
 |year=2003
 |month=Spring
 |title=Was &quot;About Schmidt&quot; about actuaries?
 |journal=The Future Actuary
 |volume=12
 |issue=1
 |url=http://www.beanactuary.org/news/futureactuary/2003mar/schmidt.cfm
 |accessdate=2006-08-29
 |ref=harv
}}
*{{cite book
 |last=Cramér
 |first=Harald
 |title=Mathematical Methods of Statistics
 |place=Princeton, NJ
 |publisher=Princeton Univ. Press
 |year=1946
 |isbn=0-691-08004-6
 |oclc=185436716
 |ref=harv
}}
&lt;!-- D --&gt;
*{{cite journal
 |last=D’arcy
 |first=Stephen P.
 |year=1989
 |month=May
 |title=On Becoming An Actuary of the Third Kind
 |journal=Proceedings of the Casualty Actuarial Society
 |volume=LXXVI
 |issue=145
 |pages=45–76
 |url=http://www.casact.org/pubs/proceed/proceed89/89045.pdf
 |format=PDF
 |accessdate=2006-06-28
 |ref=harv
}}
*{{cite journal
 |last=D’arcy
 |first=Stephen P.
 |year=2005
 |month=November
 |title=On Becoming An Actuary of the Fourth Kind
 |journal=Proceedings of the Casualty Actuarial Society
 |volume=XCII
 |issue=177
 |pages=745–754
 |url=http://www.casact.org/pubs/proceed/proceed05/05755.pdf
 |format=PDF
 |accessdate=2007-07-05
 |ref=harv
}}
&lt;!-- E --&gt;
* {{cite web
|year=2011
|url=http://www.ezrapenland.com/salary
|title=Actuarial Salaries
|publisher=Ezra Penland
|accessdate=July 27, 2011
|ref={{harvid|Ezra|2011}}
}}
&lt;!-- F --&gt;
*{{cite book
 |last=Feldblum
 |first=Sholom
 |editor=Robert F. Lowe (ed.)
 |title=Foundations of Casualty Actuarial Science
 |origyear=1990
 |edition=4th
 |year=2001
 |publisher=[[Casualty Actuarial Society]]
 |location=Arlington, Virginia
 |isbn=0-9624762-2-6
 |lccn=2001088378
 |chapter=Introduction
 |ref=harv
}}
&lt;!-- G --&gt;
*{{cite web
 |url=http://www.aafrc.org/press_releases/gusa/GivingReaches300billion.pdf
 |title=U.S. charitable giving estimated to be $307.65 billion in 2008
 |work=Giving USA
 |publisher=Giving USA Foundation
 |format=PDF
 |date=2009-06-10
 |accessdate=2011-08-04
 |ref={{harvid|GivingUSA|2009}}
}}
&lt;!-- H --&gt;
*{{cite journal
 |last=Halley
 |first=Edmond
 |authorlink=Edmond Halley
 |year=1693
 |title=An Estimate of the Degrees of the Mortality of Mankind, Drawn from Curious Tables of the Births and Funerals at the City of Breslaw; With an Attempt to Ascertain the Price of Annuities upon Lives
 |journal=[[Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society|Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London]]
 |volume=17
 |pages=596–610
 |url=http://www.york.ac.uk/depts/maths/histstat/halley.pdf
 |format=PDF
 |accessdate=2006-06-21
 |doi=10.1098/rstl.1693.0007
 |ref=harv
 |issue=192–206
}}
*{{cite web
 |url=http://www.wiley.co.uk/eoas/pdfs/TAH012-.pdf
 |title=History of Actuarial Profession
 |accessdate=2006-06-28
 |last=Hickman
 |first=James
 |year=2004
 |format=PDF
 |work=Encyclopedia of Actuarial Science
 |publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd.
 |page=4
 |ref=harv
 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20040804113004/http://www.wiley.co.uk/eoas/pdfs/TAH012-.pdf
 |archivedate = August 4, 2004
}}
&lt;!-- I --&gt;
*{{cite web
 |year=2011
 |url=http://www.actuaries.org.uk/becoming-actuary/pages/our-qualifications
 |title=Our qualifications
 |work=Student
 |publisher=[[Institute and Faculty of Actuaries]]
 |accessdate=February 27, 2012
 |ref={{harvid|Institute and Faculty of Actuaries|2011a}}
}}
*{{cite journal
| year = 2011
| month = May
| title = Actuaries in Risk Management Actuarial Profession Survey 2010/2011
| publisher = [[Institute and Faculty of Actuaries]]
| format = PDF
| accessdate = February 27, 2012
| url = http://www.actuaries.org.uk/sites/all/files/documents/pdf/acturariesinriskmanagement.pdf
| ref = {{harvid|Institute and Faculty of Actuaries|2011b}}
}}
&lt;!-- J --&gt;
*{{cite book
 |last=Johnston
 |first=Harold Whetstone
 |authorlink=Harold Whetstone Johnston
 |others=Revised by Mary Johnston
 |title=The Private Life of the Romans
 |origyear=1903
 |url=http://www.forumromanum.org/life/johnston.html
 |accessdate=2006-06-26
 |year=1932
 |publisher=Scott, Foresman and Company
 |location=Chicago, Atlanta
 |lccn=32007692
 |pages=§475–§476
 |chapter=Burial places and funeral ceremonies
 |chapterurl=http://www.forumromanum.org/life/johnston_14.html
 |quote=Early in the Empire, associations were formed for the purpose of meeting the funeral expenses of their members, whether the remains were to be buried or cremated, or for the purpose of building columbāria, or for both....If the members had provided places for the disposal of their bodies after death, they now provided for the necessary funeral expenses by paying into the common fund weekly a small fixed sum, easily within the reach of the poorest of them. When a member died, a stated sum was drawn from the treasury for his funeral&amp;nbsp;....&amp;nbsp;If the purpose of the society was the building of a columbārium, the cost was first determined and the sum total divided into what we should call shares (sortēs virīlēs), each member taking as many as he could afford and paying their value into the treasury.
 |ref={{harvid|Johnston|1903|loc=§475–§476}}
 |isbn=0-8154-0453-0
}}
&lt;!-- K --&gt;
*{{cite journal
 |last=Kendall
 |first=David
 |authorlink=David George Kendall
 |year=1983
 |title=A Tribute to Harald Cramer
 |journal=[[Journal of the Royal Statistical Society]]. Series A (General)
 |volume=146
 |issue=3
 |pages=211–212
 |publisher=[[Wiley-Blackwell|Blackwell Publishing]]
 |location=[[Oxford]], [[England]]
 |issn=0035-9238
 |jstor=2981652
 |ref=harv
}}
*{{cite journal
 |last=Krutov
 |first=Alex
 |year=2006
 |title=Insurance Linked Securities
 |journal=Financial Engineering News magazine
 |issue=48
 |url=http://www.fenews.com/fen48/one_time_articles/insurance/insurance.html
 |accessdate=2006-11-30
 |ref=harv
}}
&lt;!-- L --&gt;
*{{cite journal
| last = Lewin
| first = Chris
| date = June 14, 2007
| title = Actuarial History
| publisher = [[Institute and Faculty of Actuaries]]
| accessdate = February 27, 2012
| url = http://www.actuaries.org.uk/research-and-resources/documents/overview-actuarial-history-slides-notes
| ref = {{harvid|Lewin|2007}}
}}
*{{cite journal
 |last=Loan
 |first=Albert
 |year=1991/92
 |month=Winter
 |title=Institutional Bases of the Spontaneous Order: Surety and Assurance
 |journal=Humane Studies Review
 |volume=7
 |issue=1
 |url=http://mason.gmu.edu/~ihs/w91essay.html
 |accessdate=2006-06-26
 |ref={{harvid|Loan|1992}}
}}
*{{cite web
 |last=Lomas
 |first=Anna
 |date=2009-01-23
 |url=http://www.prospects.ac.uk/downloads/occprofiles/profile_pdfs/I1_Actuary,_consultancy.pdf
 |title=Occupational profile: Actuary, consultancy
 |format=PDF
 |page=4
 |publisher=AGCAS
 |accessdate=2009-01-05
 |ref=harv
 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20040728202539/http://www.prospects.ac.uk/downloads/occprofiles/profile_pdfs/I1_Actuary,_consultancy.pdf
 |archivedate = July 28, 2004
}}
&lt;!-- M --&gt;
*{{cite journal
 |last=MacGinnitie
 |first=James
 |year=1980
 |month=November
 |title=The Actuary and his Profession: Growth, Development, Promise
 |journal=Proceedings of the Casualty Actuarial Society
 |volume=LXVII
 |issue=127
 |pages=49–56
 |url=http://www.casact.com/pubs/proceed/proceed80/80049.pdf
 |format=PDF
 |accessdate=2006-06-28
 |ref=harv
}}
*{{cite journal
 |last=Michelbacher
 |first=Gustav F.
 |year=1920
 |title=The Technique of Rate Making as Illustrated by the 1920 National Revision of Workmen's Compensations Insurance Rates
 |journal=Proceedings of the Casualty Actuarial Society
 |volume=VI
 |issue=14
 |pages=201–249
 |url=http://www.casact.org/pubs/proceed/proceed19/19201.pdf
 |format=PDF
 |accessdate=2006-06-28
 |ref=harv
}}
&lt;!-- N --&gt;
*{{cite web
 |last=Needleman
 |first=Sarah E.
 |date=January 5, 2010
 |url=http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748703580904574638321841284190.html
 |title=The Best and Worst Jobs
 |work=[[Wall Street Journal]]
 |accessdate=2010-01-07
 |ref=harv
}}
*{{cite web
 |last=Nemko
 |first=Marty
 |year=2006
 |url=http://www.usnews.com/usnews/biztech/best_careers_2007/
 |title=Best Careers 2007
 |work=[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]
 |accessdate=2008-09-14
 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20071118105300/www.usnews.com/usnews/biztech/best_careers_2007/careertable-njs.htm
 |archivedate=2007-12-26
 |ref=harv
}}
*{{cite conference
 |first=Ragnar
 |last=Norberg
 |year=1990
 |title=Actuarial Statistics&amp;nbsp;— The European Perspective
 |booktitle=International Conference on the Teaching of Statistics 3, Dunedin, New Zealand
 |publisher=International Association for Statistical Education
 |location=Auckland, New Zealand
 |pages=405–410
 |url=http://www.stat.auckland.ac.nz/~iase/publications/18/BOOK2/B7-2.pdf
 |format=PDF
 |accessdate=February 27, 2012
 |ref=harv
}}
&lt;!-- O --&gt;
*{{cite journal
 |last=Ogborn
 |first=M.E.
 |year=1956
 |month=December
 |title=The Professional Name of Actuary
 |journal=Journal of the Institute of Actuaries
 |volume=82
 |pages=233–246
 |url=http://www.actuaries.org.uk/sites/all/files/documents/pdf/0233-0246.pdf
 |format=PDF
 |accessdate=April 27, 2011
 |publisher=Faculty and Institute of Actuaries
 |ref=harv
}}
*{{cite journal
 |last=Ogborn
 |first=M.E.
 |year=1973
 |month=July
 |url=http://www.actuaries.org.uk/sites/all/files/documents/pdf/0005-0014.pdf
 |title=Catalogue of an exhibition illustrating the history of actuarial science in the United Kingdom
 |journal = Journal of the Institute of Actuaries
 |volume=100
 |format=PDF
 |pages=7–8
 |publisher=Faculty and Institute of Actuaries
 |accessdate=April 27, 2011
 |ref=harv
}}
&lt;!-- P --&gt;
*{{cite book
 |last=Perkins
 |first=Judith
 |title=The Suffering Self; Pain and Narrative Representation in the Early Christian Era
 |date=1995-08-25
 |publisher=[[Routledge]]
 |location=London, England
 |isbn=0-415-11363-6
 |lccn=94042650
 |ref=harv
}}
&lt;!-- Q --&gt;
&lt;!-- R --&gt;
&lt;!-- S --&gt;
*{{cite journal
 |last=Sieger
 |first=Richard
 |year=1998
 |month=March
 |title=What is an Actuary?
 |journal=Future Fellows
 |volume=4
 |issue=1
 |url=http://casact.org/admissions/futfell/mar98/whatis.htm
 |accessdate=2006-06-22
 |ref=harv
}}
*{{cite book
 |last=Slud
 |first=Eric V.
 |title=Actuarial Mathematics and Life-Table Statistics
 |origyear=2001
 |url=http://www.math.umd.edu/~evs/s470/BookChaps/01Book.pdf
 |format=PDF
 |accessdate=2006-06-28
 |year=2006
 |pages=149–150
 |chapter=6: Commutation Functions, Reserves &amp; Select Mortality
 |chapterurl=http://www.math.umd.edu/~evs/s470/BookChaps/Chp6.pdf
 |quote=The Commutation Functions are a computational device to ensure that net single premiums&amp;nbsp;...&amp;nbsp;can all be obtained from a single table lookup. Historically, this idea has been very important in saving calculational labor when arriving at premium quotes. Even now...company employees without quantitative training could calculate premiums in a spreadsheet format with the aid of a life table.
 |ref=harv
}}
*{{cite web
 |url=http://www.soa.org/education/exam-req/edu-asa-req.aspx
 |title=Associate of the Society of Actuaries (ASA)–Requirements
 |accessdate=February 27, 2012
 |year=2012
 |work=Education
 |publisher=[[Society of Actuaries]]
 |ref={{harvid|SOA|2012}}
}}
*{{cite book
 |last=Stearns
 |first=Frank Preston
 |title=Cambridge sketches
 |url=http://www.gutenberg.org/dirs/etext05/7camb10.txt
 |format=text
 |accessdate=2007-01-15
 |edition=1st
 |year=1905
 |publisher=[[J. B. Lippincott Company]]
 |location=Philadelphia, Pennsylvania
 |lccn=05011051
 |chapter=Elizur Wright
 |quote=This danger could only be averted by placing their rates of insurance on a scientific basis, which should be the same and unalterable for all companies. ...&amp;nbsp;After two or three interviews with Elizur Wright the presidents of the companies came to the conclusion that he was exactly the man that they wanted, and they commissioned him to draw up a revised set of tables and rates which could serve them for a uniform standard.
 |ref=harv
}}
*{{cite book
| last          = Sweeting
| first         = Paul
| title         = Financial Enterprise Risk Management
| series        = International Series on Actuarial Science
| year          = 2011
| publisher     = [[Cambridge University Press]]
| isbn          = 978-0-521-11164-5
| lccn          = 2011025050
| ref           = harv
}}
&lt;!-- T --&gt;
*{{cite web
 |last=Thomas
 |first=David
 |year=2012
 |url=http://www.efinancialnews.com/story/2012-04-12/the-best-and-worst-jobs-in-finance
 |title=Be happy: Become an actuary
 |accessdate=April 18, 2012
 |ref=harv
}}
*{{cite book
 |last=Thucydides
 |authorlink=Thucydides
 |others=Translated by [[Richard Crawley]]
 |title=[[The History of the Peloponnesian War]]
 |url=http://classics.mit.edu/Thucydides/pelopwar.html
 |accessdate=2006-06-27
 |year=c. 431 [[Common Era|BCE]]
 |location=Greece
 |chapter=VI&amp;nbsp;— Funeral Oration of Pericles
 |chapterurl=http://classics.mit.edu/Thucydides/pelopwar.2.second.html
 |quote=My task is now finished. ...&amp;nbsp;those who are here interred have received part of their honours already, and for the rest, their children will be brought up till manhood at the public expense: the state thus offers a valuable prize, as the garland of victory in this race of valour, for the reward both of those who have fallen and their survivors.
 |ref={{harvid|Thucydides}}
 |isbn=0-525-26035-8
}}
*{{cite journal
 |last=Trowbridge
 |first=Charles L.
 |year=1989
 |url=http://www.actuarialfoundation.org/research_edu/fundamental.pdf
 |format=PDF
 |title=Fundamental Concepts of Actuarial Science
 |publisher=Actuarial Education and Research Fund
 |version=Revised Edition
 |accessdate=2006-06-28
 |ref=harv
}}
&lt;!-- U --&gt;
&lt;!-- V --&gt;
&lt;!-- W --&gt;
*{{cite news
 |first=Shane
 |last=Whelan
 |url=http://www.the-actuary.org.uk/pdfs/02_12_08.pdf
 |title=Actuaries’ contributions to financial economics
 |work=The Actuary
 |publisher=Staple Inn Actuarial Society
 |pages=34–35
 |date=December 2002
 |accessdate=2006-06-28
 |format=PDF
 |ref=harv
}}
{{refend}}
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{See also|Category:Actuarial associations}}
{{Wiktionary}}
* [http://www.beanactuary.com/ Be An Actuary: The SOA and CAS jointly sponsored web site]
* [http://www.actuarialoutpost.com/actuarial_discussion_forum/index.php Global actuarial discussion forum] and [http://www.actuarialoutpost.com/wiki actuarial wiki]

{{Featured article}}

[[Category:Actuarial science]]
[[Category:Insurance]]
[[Category:Mathematical science occupations]]
[[Category:Occupations]]
[[Category:Risk]]

[[af:Aktuaris]]
[[ar:خبير إكتواري]]
[[bg:Актюер]]
[[cs:Aktuár]]
[[cy:Actwari]]
[[da:Aktuar]]
[[de:Aktuar (Versicherungswirtschaft)]]
[[et:Aktuaar]]
[[el:Αναλογιστική]]
[[es:Actuaría]]
[[eo:Aktuario]]
[[fr:Actuaire]]
[[ga:Achtúire]]
[[ko:보험계리인]]
[[hy:Ապահովագրության վիճակագիր]]
[[hi:जीवनांकिक प्रबंधक]]
[[hr:Aktuar]]
[[id:Aktuaris]]
[[it:Attuario]]
[[he:אקטואר]]
[[kk:Актуарий]]
[[lv:Aktuārs]]
[[lb:Versécherungsmathematiker]]
[[hu:Aktuárius]]
[[nl:Actuaris]]
[[ja:アクチュアリー]]
[[no:Aktuar]]
[[nov:Aktuare]]
[[pl:Aktuariusz]]
[[pt:Atuário]]
[[ru:Актуарий]]
[[sq:Aktuari]]
[[simple:Actuary]]
[[sl:Aktuar]]
[[sh:Aktuar]]
[[fi:Aktuaari]]
[[sv:Aktuarie]]
[[th:นักคณิตศาสตร์ประกันภัย]]
[[tr:Aktüerya]]
[[uk:Актуарій]]
[[zh:精算師]]</text>
      <sha1>3tettxwumw0rn8isx0sd4wajak2djrj</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
