<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Auction</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>62912</id>
    <revision>
      <id>518224062</id>
      <parentid>517880349</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-17T00:10:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mdmoss</username>
        <id>17710927</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="46303">{{Redirect|Auctioneer|the DC Comics supervillain|Auctioneer (comics)}}
[[File:Auction.jpg|thumb|400px|An auctioneer and her assistants scan the crowd for bidders.]]
An '''auction''' is a process of [[Trade|buying and selling]] [[Good (economics)|goods]] or [[Service (economics)|services]] by offering them up for bid, taking bids, and then selling the item to the highest bidder. In [[economic theory]], an auction may refer to any mechanism or set of trading rules for exchange.

==History==
[[File:Microcosm of London Plate 006 - Auction Room, Christie's.jpg|thumb|Auction Room, [[Christie's]], circa 1808]]
[[File:East pediment G Parthenon BM.jpg|thumb|[[Artemis]], Ancient Greek marble sculpture. In 2007, a [[Roman art|Roman-era]] [[bronze sculpture]] of &quot;Artemis and the Stag&quot; was sold at [[Sotheby's]] in New York for [[United States dollar|US$]]28.6&amp;nbsp;million, by far exceeding its estimates and at the time setting the new record as [[List of most expensive sculptures|the most expensive sculpture]] as well as work from antiquity ever sold at auction.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
| title = Sotheby's Sets a New World Record for Sculpture at Auction
| last = [[Sotheby's]]
| date = 2007-06-07
| url = http://files.shareholder.com/downloads/BID/340155988x0x110223/36c23cb5-958d-4a86-b517-ea6f9d297127/110223.pdf
|format=PDF| accessdate = 2008-06-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
| last = New York Times
| title = Artemis and Stag at Met Museum
| date = 2008-01-10
| url = http://www.nytimes.com/2008/01/10/arts/10arts-ARTEMISANDST_BRF.html
| accessdate = 2008-06-20
| work=The New York Times}}.&lt;/ref&gt;]]

[[File:Vase meiping Musée Guimet 2418 .jpg|thumb|An 18th century Chinese ''[[meiping]]'' porcelain vase. [[Porcelain]] has long been a staple at [[History of art auction sales|art sales]]. In 2005, a 14th century Chinese porcelain piece was sold by the [[Christie's]] for [[Pound sterling|£]]16&amp;nbsp;million, or US[[United States dollar|$]]28&amp;nbsp;million. It set a world auction record for any ceramic work of art.&lt;ref&gt;*{{citation
|url= http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/13/arts/13iht-web.melik.html
|title= Chinese Jar Sets Record for Asian Art
|accessdate= 2008-06-19
|last= Melikian
|first= Souren
|date= 2005-07-26|publisher= The New York Times
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;]]

The word &quot;auction&quot; is derived from the Latin ''[[wikt:augeo#Latin|augeō]]'' which means &quot;I increase&quot; or &quot;I augment&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;#Krishna2002|Krishna, 2002: p2&quot;&gt;[[#Krishna2002|Krishna, 2002: p2]]&lt;/ref&gt;

For most of history, auctions have been a relatively uncommon way to negotiate the exchange of goods and commodities. In practice, both [[haggling]] and sale by set-price have been significantly more common.&lt;ref name=&quot;Economist99&quot;&gt;{{citation
| title = The Heyday of the Auction
| journal = The Economist
| volume = 352
| issue = 8129
| pages = 67–68
| publisher =
| location =
| date = 1999-07-24
| issn = 0013-0613
 }}
&lt;/ref&gt; Indeed, before the seventeenth century the few auctions that were held were sporadic and infrequent.&lt;ref name=&quot;#Shubik|Shubik, 2004: p214&quot;&gt;[[#Shubik|Shubik, 2004: p214]]&lt;/ref&gt;

Nonetheless, auctions have a long history, having been recorded as early as 500 B.C.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Krishna2002|Krishna, 2002: p1]]&lt;/ref&gt; According to Herodotus, in [[Babylon]] auctions of women for [[marriage]] were held annually. The auctions began with the woman the auctioneer considered to be the most beautiful and progressed to the least. It was considered illegal to allow a daughter to be sold outside of the auction method.&lt;ref name=&quot;#Shubik|Shubik, 2004: p214&quot; /&gt;

During the [[Roman Empire]], following military victory, Roman soldiers would often drive a spear into the ground around which the spoils of war were left, to be auctioned off. Later slaves, often captured as the &quot;spoils of war&quot;, were auctioned in the forum under the sign of the spear, with the proceeds of sale going towards the war effort.&lt;ref name=&quot;#Shubik|Shubik, 2004: p214&quot; /&gt;

The Romans also used auctions to [[liquidate]] the assets of debtors whose property had been confiscated.&lt;ref name=&quot;Shubik, 2004: p215&quot;&gt;[[#Shubik|Shubik, 2004: p215]]&lt;/ref&gt; For example, [[Marcus Aurelius]] sold household furniture to pay off debts, the sales lasting for months.&lt;ref name=&quot;Doyle&quot;&gt;{{Citation
| last = Doyle
| first = Robert A.
| last2 = Baska
| first2 = Steve
| title = History of Auctions: From ancient Rome to todays high-tech auctions
| journal = Auctioneer
| date = November 2002
| accessdate = 2008-06-22
| url = http://www.auctioneersfoundation.org/news_detail.php?id=5094
| format = |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080517071614/http://auctioneersfoundation.org/news_detail.php?id=5094 |archivedate = May 17, 2008}} {{Dead link|date=October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; One of the most significant historical auctions occurred in the year 193 A.D. when the entire Roman Empire was put on the auction block by the [[Praetorian Guard]]. On March 23 The Praetorian Guard first killed emperor [[Pertinax]], then offered the empire to the highest bidder. [[Didius Julianus]] outbid everyone else for the price of 6,250 drachmas per Guard{{Citation needed|date=June 2008}}, an act that initiated a brief civil war. Didius was then [[Decapitation|beheaded]] two months later when [[Septimius Severus]] conquered Rome.&lt;ref name=&quot;Shubik, 2004: p215&quot; /&gt;

From the end of the Roman Empire to the eighteenth century auctions lost favor in Europe,&lt;ref name=&quot;Shubik, 2004: p215&quot; /&gt; while they had never been widespread in Asia.&lt;ref name=&quot;#Shubik|Shubik, 2004: p214&quot; /&gt;

In some parts of England during the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries [[Candle auction|auction by candle]] was used for the sale of goods and leaseholds. This auction began by lighting a candle after which bids were offered in ascending order until the candle spluttered out. The high bid at the time the candle extinguished itself won the auction.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tatworth&quot;&gt;{{citation
| quotes =
| last = Patten
| first = R. W.
| date = Summer, 1970
| title = Tatworth Candle Auction
| journal = Folklore
| volume = 81
| issue = 2
| pages = 132–135
| publisher = Taylor &amp; Francis, Ltd. on behalf of Folklore Enterprises, Ltd.
| location = London, United Kingdom
| issn = 0015-587x
| jstor = 1258945
 
| doi = 
| doi_brokendate = 2009-10-02
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The oldest [[auction house]] in the world is [[Stockholm Auction House]] (''Stockholms Auktionsverk''). It was established in Sweden in 1674.&lt;ref name=&quot;Auktionsverk&quot;&gt;{{citation
| last = Varoli
| first = John
| title = Swedish Auction House to Sell 8 Million Euros of Russian Art
| journal = Bloomberg.com News
| publisher = Bloomberg Finance L.P.
| location = Moscow
| date = 2007-10-02
| url = http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=20601088&amp;sid=aGlwT7.MHwzw&amp;refer=muse
| accessdate = 2008-06-21}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AuktionsverkHistory&quot;&gt;{{citation
| title = About the company
| publisher = Stockholms Auktionsverk
| location = Stockholm, Sweden
| url = http://www.auktionsverket.se/historike.htm
| accessdate = 2008-06-21 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080522014917/http://www.auktionsverket.se/historike.htm |archivedate = May 22, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the end of the 18th century, soon after the [[French Revolution]], auctions came to be held in [[taverns]] and [[coffeehouses]] to sell art. Such auctions were held daily, and catalogs were printed to announce available items. Such [[Auction catalog]]s are frequently printed and distributed before auctions of rare or collectible items. In some cases these catalogs were elaborate works of art themselves, containing considerable detail about the items being auctioned.{{Citation needed|date=June 2008}}
&lt;br&gt;
[[Sotheby's]], now the world's second-largest auction house,&lt;ref name=&quot;Auktionsverk&quot; /&gt; held its first auction in 1744. [[Christie's]], now the world's largest auction house,&lt;ref name=&quot;Auktionsverk&quot; /&gt; was established around 1766. Other early auction houses that are still in operation include
[[Dorotheum]] (1707), [[Mallams]] (1788), [[Bonhams]] (1793), [[Phillips de Pury &amp; Company]] (1796), [[Freeman's]] (1805) and [[Lyon &amp; Turnbull]] (1826).&lt;ref name=&quot;Stoica&quot;&gt;{{citation
| last = Stoica
| first = Michael
| title = The Business of Art
| date = August 2007
| url = http://www.washburn.edu/mabee/crc/courses/auctionhouses.html
| accessdate = 2008-06-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[American civil war]] goods seized by armies were sold at auction by the [[Colonel]] of the division. Thus, some of today's auctioneers in the U.S. carry the unofficial title of &quot;colonel&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Doyle&quot; /&gt;

The development of the internet, however, has led to a significant rise in the use of auctions as auctioneers can solicit bids [[Online auction|via the internet]] from a wide range of buyers in a much wider range of commodities than was previously practical.&lt;ref name=&quot;Economist99&quot; /&gt;

In 2008, the National Auctioneers Association reported that the gross revenue of the auction industry for that year was approximately $268.4&amp;nbsp;billion, with the fastest growing sectors being agricultural, machinery, and equipment auctions and residential real estate auctions.

==Types==
===Primary===
[[Image:Auction Tsukiji fishmarket.jpg|thumb|right|Tuna auction at the [[Tsukiji fish market]] in [[Tokyo]]]]
[[Image:Fish auction Hawaii.jpg|thumb|right|Fish auction in [[Honolulu]], [[Hawaii]]]]
* '''[[English auction]]''', also known as an ''open ascending price auction''. This type of auction is arguably the most common form of auction in use today.&lt;ref name=&quot;#Krishna2002|Krishna, 2002: p2&quot; /&gt; Participants bid openly against one another, with each subsequent bid higher than the previous bid.&lt;ref name=&quot;McAfee&quot;&gt;{{Citation
| last =McAfee
| first =R. Preston
| author-link =
| last2 =McMillan
| first2 =John
| author2-link =
| publication-date =June 1987
| year =1987
| title =Auctions and Bidding
| periodical =Journal of Economic Literature
| publisher =American Economic Association
| volume =25
| issue =2
| pages =699–738
| url =http://vita.mcafee.cc/PDF/JEL.pdf
| accessdate =2008-06-25
| doi =
| doi_brokendate =2009-10-02
| jstor =2726107
}}&lt;/ref&gt; An auctioneer may announce prices, bidders may call out their bids themselves (or have a proxy call out a bid on their behalf), or bids may be submitted electronically with the highest current bid publicly displayed.&lt;ref name=&quot;McAfee&quot; /&gt; In some cases a maximum bid might be left with the auctioneer, who may bid on behalf of the bidder according to the bidder's instructions.&lt;ref name=&quot;McAfee&quot; /&gt; The auction ends when no participant is willing to bid further, at which point the highest bidder pays their bid.&lt;ref name=&quot;McAfee&quot; /&gt; Alternatively, if the seller has set a minimum sale price in advance (the 'reserve' price) and the final bid does not reach that price the item remains unsold.&lt;ref name=&quot;McAfee&quot; /&gt; Sometimes the auctioneer sets a minimum amount by which the next bid must exceed the current highest bid.&lt;ref name=&quot;McAfee&quot; /&gt; The most significant distinguishing factor of this auction type is that the current highest bid is always available to potential bidders.&lt;ref name=&quot;McAfee&quot; /&gt; The English auction is commonly used for selling goods, most prominently antiques and artwork,&lt;ref name=&quot;McAfee&quot; /&gt; but also secondhand goods and [[real estate]]. At least two bidders are required.
* '''[[Dutch auction]]''' also known as an ''open descending price auction''.&lt;ref name=&quot;#Krishna2002|Krishna, 2002: p2&quot; /&gt; In the traditional Dutch auction the auctioneer begins with a high asking price which is lowered until some participant is willing to accept the auctioneer's price.&lt;ref name=&quot;McAfee&quot; /&gt; The winning participant pays the last announced price.&lt;ref name=&quot;#Krishna2002|Krishna, 2002: p2&quot; /&gt; The Dutch auction is named for its best known example, the Dutch [[tulip]] auctions. (&quot;Dutch auction&quot; is also sometimes used to describe online auctions where several identical goods are sold simultaneously to an equal number of high bidders.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|author=eBay|title=Selling Multiple Items in a Listing (Dutch Auction)| url=http://pages.ebay.com/help/sell/multiple.html|accessdate=2009-01-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;) In addition to cut flower sales in the [[Netherlands]], Dutch auctions have also been used for perishable commodities such as fish and tobacco.&lt;ref name=&quot;McAfee&quot; /&gt; In practice, however, the Dutch auction is not widely used.&lt;ref name=&quot;#Krishna2002|Krishna, 2002: p2&quot; /&gt;
* '''[[Sealed first-price auction]]''', also known as a ''first-price sealed-bid auction'' (FPSB). In this type of auction all bidders simultaneously submit sealed bids so that no bidder knows the bid of any other participant. The highest bidder pays the price they submitted.&lt;ref name=&quot;#Krishna2002|Krishna, 2002: p2&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;McAfee&quot; /&gt; This type of auction is distinct from the English auction, in that bidders can only submit one bid each. Furthermore, as bidders cannot see the bids of other participants they cannot adjust their own bids accordingly.&lt;ref name=&quot;McAfee&quot; /&gt; This kind of bid produces the same outcome as [[Dutch auction]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Krishna2002|Krishna, 2002: p13]]&lt;/ref&gt; Sealed first-price auctions are commonly used in tendering, particularly for government contracts and auctions for mining leases.&lt;ref name=&quot;McAfee&quot; /&gt;
* '''[[Vickrey auction]]''', also known as a ''sealed-bid second-price auction''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Krishna, 2002: p9&quot;&gt;[[#Krishna2002|Krishna, 2002: p9]]&lt;/ref&gt; This is identical to the sealed first-price auction except that the winning bidder pays the second highest bid rather than his or her own.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Krishna2002|Krishna, 2002: p3]]&lt;/ref&gt; This is very similar to the [[proxy bid]]ding system used by [[eBay]], where the winner pays the second highest bid plus a bidding increment (e.g., 10%).&lt;ref name=&quot;Krishna, 2002: p9&quot; /&gt; Although extremely important in auction theory, in practice Vickrey auctions are rarely used.&lt;ref name=&quot;McAfee&quot; /&gt;
* '''[[Multi-unit auction]]s''' sell more than one identical item at the same time, rather than having separate auctions for each.  This type can be further classified as a [[uniform price auction]] or a [[discriminatory price auction]].

===Secondary===
* '''[[All-pay auction]]''' is an auction in which all bidders must pay their bids regardless of whether they win. The highest bidder wins the item. All-pay auctions are primarily of academic interest, and may be used to model lobbying/bribery (bids are political contributions) or competitions such as a running race.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Milgrom2004|Milgrom, 2004: p119]]&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''[[Bidding fee auction]]''', also known as a penny auction, requires that each participant must purchase bids prior to placing them. When an auction's time expires, the last bidder wins the item and must pay a final bid price.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/grace-nasri/the-seduction-of-the-penn_b_846221.html|title=The Seduction of the Penny Auction|accessdate=2011-04-27 | work=Huffington Post|first=Grace|last=Nasri|date=2011-04-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; An example of this type of auction is [[Madbid]], [[Quibids]]  or Sweepola.
* '''Buyout auction''' is an auction with a set price (the 'buyout' price) that any bidder can accept at any time during the auction, thereby immediately ending the auction and winning the item.&lt;ref name=&quot;buyout&quot;&gt;{{Citation
| last = Gallien
| first = Jérémie
| last2 = Gupta
| first2 = Shobhit
| title = Temporary and Permanent Buyout Prices in Online Auctions
| journal = Management Science
| volume = 53
| issue = 5
| pages = 814–833
| publisher = INFORMS
| date = May 2007
| doi = 10.1287/mnsc.1060.0650
| url = http://mansci.journal.informs.org/cgi/content/abstract/53/5/814
| issn = 1526-5501 }}&lt;/ref&gt; If no bidder chooses to utilize the buyout option before the end of bidding the highest bidder wins and pays their bid.&lt;ref name=&quot;buyout&quot; /&gt; Buyout options can be either ''temporary'' or ''permanent''.&lt;ref name=&quot;buyout&quot; /&gt; In a temporary-buyout auction the option to buy out the auction is not available after the first bid is placed.&lt;ref name=&quot;buyout&quot; /&gt; In a permanent-buyout auction the buyout option remains available throughout the entire auction until the close of bidding.&lt;ref name=&quot;buyout&quot; /&gt; The buyout price can either remain the same throughout the entire auction, or vary throughout according to rules or simply at the whim of the seller.&lt;ref name=&quot;buyout&quot; /&gt;
* '''[[Combinatorial auction]]''' is any auction for the simultaneous sale of more than one item where bidders can place bids on an &quot;all-or-nothing&quot; basis on &quot;packages&quot; rather than just individual items. That is, a bidder can specify that he or she will pay for items A and B, but only if he or she gets ''both''.&lt;ref name=&quot;combinatorial&quot;&gt;{{Citation
| last = Pekec
| first = Aleksandar
| last2 = Rothkopf
| first2 = Michael H.
| title = Combinatorial auction design.
| journal = Management Science
| volume = 49
| issue = 11
| pages = 1485–1503
| publisher = INFORMS
| date = November 2003
| year = 2007
| doi = 10.1287/mnsc.49.11.1485.20585
| url = http://mansci.journal.informs.org/cgi/content/abstract/53/5/814
| issn = 1526-5501 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In combinatorial auctions, determining the winning bidder(s) can be a complex process where even the bidder with the highest individual bid is not guaranteed to win.&lt;ref name=&quot;combinatorial&quot; /&gt; For example, in an auction with four items (W, X, Y and Z), if Bidder A offers $50 for items W &amp; Y, Bidder B offers $30 for items W &amp; X, Bidder C offers $5 for items X &amp; Z and Bidder D offers $30 for items Y &amp; Z, the winners will be Bidders B &amp; D while Bidder A misses out because the ''combined'' bids of Bidders B &amp; D is higher ($60) than for Bidders A and C ($55).
* [[Generalized second-price auction]]
* '''Japanese auction''' is a variation of the English auction. When the bidding starts no new bidders can join, and each bidder must continue to bid each round or drop out. It has similarities to the [[Betting_(poker)#Ante|ante]] in [[Poker]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.auctusdev.com/auctiontypes.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Lloyd's syndicate auction'''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lloyds.com/Lloyds_Market/Capacity/Capacity_auctions/Auction_process.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''{{visible anchor|Mystery auction}}''' is a type of auction where bidders bid for boxes or envelopes containing various items, usually on the hope that the items will be humorous, interesting, or valuable.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Ralph Brody, Marcie Goodman|title=Fund-raising events: strategies and programs for success|publisher=Human Sciences Press, 1988|isbn=0898853621}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Harold W. Donahue|title=The Toastmaster's Manual|publisher=Kessinger Publishing, 2005|isbn=1419156365}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the early days of [[eBay]]'s popularity, sellers began promoting boxes or packages of random and usually low-value items not worth selling by themselves.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Julia L. Wilkinson|title=The Ebay Price Guide: What Sells for What|publisher=No Starch Press, 2006|isbn=1593270550}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''{{visible anchor|No-reserve auction}}''' (NR), also known as an ''absolute auction'', is an auction in which the item for sale will be sold regardless of price.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fisher&quot;&gt;{{Citation|last1= Fisher |first1= Steven |title= The Real Estate Investor's Handbook: The Complete Guide for the Individual Investor |url= |format= |year= 2006 |publisher= Atlantic Publishing Company |location= [[Ocala, Florida]] |isbn= 0-910627-69-X |oclc= |doi=  |pages= 89–90 |ref= |bibcode= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AuctionBasics&quot;&gt;{{Citation|last= Good |first= Steven L. |coauthors= Lynn, Paul A. |year= 2007 |month= January |title= The eBay Effect |journal= Commercial Investment Real Estate |volume= |issue= |pages= |publisher= [[CCIM|CCIM Institute]]  |url= http://www.ciremagazine.com/article.php?article_id=1036 |accessdate=2009-06-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt; From the seller's perspective, advertising an auction as having no [[Reservation price|reserve price]] can be desirable because it potentially attracts a greater number of bidders due to the possibility of a bargain.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fisher&quot; /&gt; If more bidders attend the auction, a higher price might ultimately be achieved because of heightened competition from bidders.&lt;ref name=&quot;AuctionBasics&quot; /&gt; This contrasts with a ''reserve auction'', where the item for sale may not be sold if the final bid is not high enough to satisfy the seller. In practice, an auction advertised as &quot;absolute&quot; or &quot;no-reserve&quot; may nonetheless still not sell to the highest bidder on the day, for example, if the seller withdraws the item from the auction or extends the auction period indefinitely,&lt;ref name=&quot;Leichman&quot;&gt;{{Citation|title= 90% off! real estate |last= Leichman |first= Laurence |year= 1996 |publisher= Leichman Assoc Pubns |location= [[Ocala, Florida]] |isbn= 0-9636867-7-1 |pages= 78–79 }}&lt;/ref&gt; although these practices may be restricted by law in some jurisdictions or under the terms of sale available from the auctioneer.
* '''Reserve auction''' is an auction where the item for sale may not be sold if the final bid is not high enough to satisfy the seller; that is, the seller ''reserves'' the right to accept or reject the highest bid.&lt;ref name=&quot;AuctionBasics&quot; /&gt; In these cases a set 'reserve' price known to the auctioneer, but not necessarily to the bidders, may have been set, below which the item may not be sold.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fisher&quot; /&gt; The reserve price may be ''fixed'' or ''discretionary''. In the latter case, the decision to accept a bid is deferred to the auctioneer, who may accept a bid that is marginally below it. A reserve auction is safer for the seller than a no-reserve auction as they are not required to accept a low bid, but this could result in a lower final price if less interest is generated in the sale.&lt;ref name=&quot;AuctionBasics&quot; /&gt;
* '''[[Reverse auction]]''' is a type of auction in which the roles of the buyer and the seller are reversed, with the primary objective to drive purchase prices downward.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reverse&quot;&gt;{{citation
| last = Schoenherr
| first = Tobias
| last2 = Mabert
| first2 = Vincent A.
| title = Online reverse auctions: Common myths versus evolving reality
| journal = Business Horizons
| volume = 50
| issue = 5
| pages = 373–384
| publisher = Kelley School of Business, Indiana University
| date = September–October 2007
| doi = 10.1016/j.bushor.2007.03.003
| url =
| issn = }}&lt;/ref&gt; While ordinary auctions provide suppliers the opportunity to find the best price among interested buyers, reverse auctions give buyers a chance to find the lowest-price supplier. During a reverse auction, suppliers may submit multiple offers, usually as a response to competing suppliers’ offers, bidding down the price of a good or service to the lowest price they are willing to receive. By revealing the competing bids in real time to every participating supplier, reverse auctions promote “information transparency”. This, coupled with the dynamic bidding process, improves the chances of reaching the fair market value of the item.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.scribd.com/doc/39032383/Electronic-Reverse-Auction-and-the-Public-Sector-Factors-of-Success-Moshe-E-Shalev-Stee-Asbjorensen. Shalev Moshe and Asbjornsen Stee, &quot;ELECTRONIC REVERSE AUCTIONS AND THE PUBLIC SECTOR – FACTORS OF SUCCESS&quot;, Journal of Public Procurement, 10(3) 428-452.&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Silent auction''' is a variant of the English auction in which bids are written on a sheet of paper. At the predetermined end of the auction, the highest listed bidder wins the item.&lt;ref name=&quot;silent&quot;&gt;{{Citation
| last1 = Isaac | first1 = R. Mark
| last2 = Schnier | first2 = Kurt
| title = Silent auctions in the field and in the laboratory
| journal = Economic Inquiry
| volume = 43
| issue = 4
| pages = 715–733
| publisher = Western Economic Association International
| location = Oxford, United Kingdom
| date = October 2005
| doi = 10.1093/ei/cbi050
| url = http://ideas.repec.org/a/oup/ecinqu/v43y2005i4p715-733.html
| issn = 0095-2583 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This auction is often used in [[Charitable organization|charity]] events, with many items auctioned simultaneously and &quot;closed&quot; at a common finish time.&lt;ref name=&quot;silent&quot; /&gt; The auction is &quot;silent&quot; in that there is no auctioneer selling individual items,&lt;ref name=&quot;silent&quot; /&gt; the bidders writing their bids on a bidding sheet often left on a table near the item.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Milgrom2004|Milgrom, 2004: p268]]&lt;/ref&gt; At charity auctions, bid sheets usually have a fixed starting amount, predetermined bid increments, and a &quot;guaranteed bid&quot; amount which works the same as a &quot;buy now&quot; amount. Other variations of this type of auction may include sealed bids.&lt;ref name=&quot;silent&quot; /&gt; The highest bidder pays the price he or she submitted.&lt;ref name=&quot;silent&quot; /&gt;
* '''Senior auction''' is a variation on the all-pay auction, and has a defined loser in addition to the winner. The top two bidders must pay their full final bid amounts, and only the highest wins the auction. The intent is to make the high bidders bid above their upper limits. In the final rounds of bidding, when the current losing party has hit their maximum bid, they are encouraged to bid over their maximum (seen as a small loss) to avoid losing their maximum bid with no return (a very large loss).&lt;ref&gt;Ab Hugh, Dafydd. ''[[Balance of Power (Star Trek)|A Balance of Power]]''. Star Trek Press, 1995&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Top-Up auction''' is a variation on the all-pay auction, primarily used for charity events. Bidders must pay the difference between their bid and the next lowest bid, whether they win or not. Only the winning bidder does not have to pay the &quot;top-up&quot; fee, but does have to pay for the item.
* '''[[Walrasian auction]]''' or ''Walrasian tâtonnement'' is an auction in which the auctioneer takes bids from both buyers and sellers in a market of multiple goods.&lt;ref name=&quot;Milgrom p267&quot;&gt;[[#Milgrom2004|Milgrom, 2004: p267]]&lt;/ref&gt; The auctioneer progressively either raises or drops the current proposed price depending on the bids of both buyers and sellers, the auction concluding when supply and demand exactly balance.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Milgrom2004|Milgrom, 2004: p267-268]]&lt;/ref&gt; As a high price tends to dampen demand while a low price tends to increase demand, in theory there is a particular price somewhere in the middle where supply and demand will match.&lt;ref name=&quot;Milgrom p267&quot; /&gt;
* '''[[Auction by the candle]]'''. A type of auction, used in England for selling ships, in which the highest bid laid on the table when a guttering candle expires wins.
* '''Other auctions''': Other auction types also exist, such as Simultaneous Ascending Auction

&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
| last = Peter
| first = Cramton
| author-link =
| year = 2006
| contribution = Simultaneous Ascending Auctions
| contribution-url =
| editor-last = Cramton
| editor-first = Peter
| editor-link =
| editor2-last = Shoham
| editor2-first = Yoav
| editor2-link =
| editor3-last = Steinberg
| editor3-first = Richard
| editor3-link =
| title = Combinatorial Auctions
| edition =
| place = Cambridge, MA
| publisher = MIT Press
| pages =
 
| isbn = 978-0-262-03342-8
| doi =
| oclc =
| url =
| accessdate =
| ref =
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Anglo-Dutch auction,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ssc.wisc.edu/~dquint/econ805%202007/econ%20805%20lecture%2012.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; Private value auction,&lt;ref&gt;http://en.wikiversity.org/wiki/Economic_Classroom_Experiments/Private_Value_Auctions&lt;/ref&gt; [[Common value auction]]

==Time requirements==
{{Unreferenced section|date=June 2008}}
Each type of auction has its specific qualities such as pricing accuracy and time required for preparing and conducting the auction. The number of simultaneous bidders is of critical importance. Open bidding during an extended period of time with many bidders will result in a final bid that is very close to the true market value. Where there are few bidders and each bidder is allowed only one bid, time is saved, but the winning bid may not reflect the true market value with any degree of accuracy. Of special interest and importance during the actual auction is the time elapsed from the moment that the first bid is revealed to the moment that the final (winning) bid has become a binding agreement.

==Characteristics==
{{Unreferenced section|date=June 2008}}
Auctions can differ in the number of participants:
* In a ''supply'' (or ''reverse'') auction, ''m'' sellers offer a good that a buyer requests
* In a ''demand'' auction, ''n'' buyers bid for a good being sold
* In a [[double auction|''double'' auction]] ''n'' buyers bid to buy goods from ''m'' sellers

Prices are ''bid'' by buyers and ''asked'' (or ''offered'') by sellers. Auctions may also differ by the procedure for bidding (or asking, as the case may be):
* In an ''open'' auction participants may repeatedly bid and are aware of each other's previous bids.
* In a ''closed'' auction buyers and/or sellers submit sealed bids

Auctions may differ as to the price at which the item is sold, whether the first (best) price, the second price, the first ''unique'' price or some other. Auctions may set a [[reservation price]] which is the least/maximum acceptable price for which a good may be sold/bought.

Without modification, ''auction'' generally refers to an open, demand auction, with or without a ''[[reservation price]]'' (or ''reserve''), with the item sold to the highest bidder.

{|align=center
|[[Image:Supplyauction.svg|thumb|Supply auction]]
|[[Image:Purchaseauction.svg|thumb|Demand auction]]
|[[Image:Doubleauction.svg|thumb|Double auction]]
|}

==Common uses==
Auctions are publicly and privately seen in several contexts and almost anything can be sold at auction. Some typical auction arenas include the following:
[[File:Clearing sale.JPG|thumb|Farm clearing sale, Woolbrook, NSW.]]
[[File:Cattle sale.jpg|thumb|Grass-fed [[cattle]] at auction, [[Walcha]], NSW]]
[[File:Wool auction.JPG|thumb|Wool buyers' room at a wool auction, Newcastle, NSW.]]
* The [[Antiques|antique]] business, where besides being an opportunity for [[trade]] they also serve as social occasions and entertainment
* In the sale of [[collectible]]s such as stamps, coins, classic cars, fine art&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.quadraevents.com/auction.html Canadian Museum of Civilization and Canada Postal Museum - Auction of Fine Art and Stamps]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[luxury real estate]]
* The wine auction business, where serious collectors can gain access to rare bottles and mature vintages, not typically available through retail channels
* In the sale of all types of [[real property]] including residential and commercial [[real estate]], farms, vacant lots and land.
* For the sale of consumer [[second-hand good]]s of all kinds, particularly farm (equipment) and house clearances and online auctions.
* Sale of industrial machinery, both surplus or through insolvency.
* In [[commodity|commodities]] auctions, like the fish wholesale auctions
* In [[livestock]] auctions where sheep, cattle, pigs and other livestock are sold. Sometimes very large numbers of stock are auctioned, such as the regular sales of 50,000 or more sheep during a day in [[New South Wales]].&lt;ref&gt;The Land Newspaper, ''Prime sheep'', Rural Press, 13 August 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;
* In [[wool]] auctions where international agents purchase lots of wool&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/rural/news/stories/s843702.htm Combined factors hit wool auctions hard]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Thoroughbred]] horses, where yearling horses and other bloodstock are auctioned.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.inglis.com.au/about/ William Inglis &amp; Son Limited]&lt;/ref&gt;
* In legal contexts where [[force (law)|forced]] auctions occur, as when one's farm or house is sold at auction on the [[courthouse]] steps.
* Travel tickets. One example is [[SJ AB]] in Sweden auctioning surplus at Tradera (Swedish eBay).
* Holidays. A variety of holidays are available for sale online particularly via eBay. Vacation rentals appear to be most common. Many holiday auction websites have launched but failed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/travel/news/article6998942.ece | location=London | work=The Times | first=Susan | last=d'Arcy | title=Bag a holiday bargain in an online auction | date=2010-01-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Self storage]] units. In certain jurisdictions, if a storage facility's tenant fails to pay his/her rent, the contents of his/her locker(s) may be sold at a public auction. Several television shows focus on such auctions, including ''[[Storage Wars]]'' and ''[[Auction Hunters]]''.

Although less publicly visible, the most economically important auctions are the commodities auctions in which the bidders are [[business]]es even up to [[corporation]] level. Examples of this type of auction include:
* Sales of businesses
* [[Spectrum auction]]s, in which companies purchase licenses to use portions of the [[electromagnetic spectrum]] for communications (e.g., mobile phone networks)
* [[Private electronic market]]s using combinatorial auction techniques to continuously sell commodities (coal, iron ore, grain, water...) to a pre-qualified group of buyers (based on price and non-price factors)
* [[Timber]] auctions, in which companies purchase licenses to log on government land
* Timber allocation auctions, in which companies purchase timber directly from the government [http://www.forestauctions.com Forest Auctions]
* Electricity auctions, in which large-scale generators and consumers of electricity bid on generating contracts
* Environmental auctions, in which companies bid for licenses to avoid being required to decrease their environmental impact. These include auctions in [[emissions trading]] schemes.
* [[Debt]] auctions, in which governments sell [[Financial instruments|debt instruments]], such as [[Bond (finance)|bonds]], to investors. The auction is usually sealed and the uniform price paid by the investors is typically the best non-winning bid. In most cases, investors can also place so called ''non-competitive bids'', which indicates an interest to purchase the [[Financial instruments|debt instrument]] at the resulting price, whatever it may be
* [[Auto auction]]s, in which car dealers purchase used vehicles to retail to the public.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pickles.com.au/cars/about/?contentId=250 Pickles Auctions]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Bidding strategy==
{{Unreferenced section|date=June 2008}}

===Bid shading===
[[Bid shading]] is placing a bid which is below the bidder's actual value for the item. Such a strategy risks losing the auction, but has the possibility of winning at a low price. Bid shading can also be a strategy to avoid the [[Winner's curse]].

===Chandelier or Rafter Bidding===
A practice, especially by high-end art auctioneers, of raising false bids at crucial times in the bidding process in order to create the appearance of greater demand or to extend bidding momentum for a work on offer. To call out these nonexistent bids, auctioneers might fix their gaze at a point in the auction room that is difficult for the audience to pin down.

In the [[United Kingdom]], this practice is legal on property auctions up to but not including the reserve price, and is also known as off-the-wall bidding.&lt;ref&gt;http://ukauctions.org.uk/articles-videos/help-and-advice/what-is-bidding-off-the-wall/&lt;/ref&gt;

===Collusion===
{{Unreferenced section|date=March 2009}}
Whenever bidders at an auction are aware of the identity of the other bidders there is a risk that they will form a &quot;ring&quot; and thus manipulate the auction result, a practice known as [[collusion]]. By agreeing to bid only against outsiders, never against members of the &quot;ring&quot;, competition becomes weaker, which may dramatically affect the final price level. After the end of the official auction an unofficial auction may take place among the &quot;ring&quot; members. The difference in price between the two auctions could then be split among the members.  This form of a ring was used as a central plot device in the opening episode of the 1979 British Television Series The [[House of Caradus]], For Love or Money, uncovered by Helena Caradus on her return from Paris.

A ring can also be used to increase the price of an auction lot, in which the owner of the object being auctioned may increase competition by taking part in the bidding him or herself, but drop out of the bidding just before the final bid.  In Britain and many other countries, rings and other forms of bidding on one's own object are illegal. This form of a ring was used as a central plot device in an episode of the British television series [[Lovejoy]] (series 4, episode 3) in which the price of a watercolour by the (fictional) Jessie Webb is inflated so that others by the same artist could be sold for more than their purchase price.  

In an English auction a dummy bid is a bid made by a dummy bidder acting in collusion with the auctioneer or vendor, designed to deceive genuine bidders into paying more. In a First price auction a dummy bid is an unfavourable bid designed so as not to become the winning bid. (The bidder does not want to win this auction, but he or she wants to make sure to be invited to the next auction).

In Australia a dummy bid ([[shill]], schill) is a criminal offence but a vendor bid or a co-owner bid below the [[reserve price]] is permitted, if clearly declared as such by the auctioneer. These are all official legal terms in Australia, but may have other meanings elsewhere. A co-owner is one of two or several owners (who disagree among themselves).

In Sweden and many other countries there are no legal restrictions, but it will severely hurt the reputation of an auction house that knowingly permits any other bids except genuine bids. If the reserve is not reached this should be clearly declared.

===Suggested opening bid (SOB)===
{{cleanup|section|date=July 2007}}
There will usually be an estimate of what price the lot will fetch. In an ascending open auction it is considered important to get at least a 50-percent increase in the bids from start to finish. To accomplish this, the auctioneer must start the auction by announcing a suggested opening bid (SOB) that is low enough to be immediately accepted by one of the bidders. Once there is an opening bid, there will quickly be several other, higher bids submitted. Experienced auctioneers will often select an SOB that is about 45 percent of the (lowest) estimate. Thus there is a certain margin of safety to ensure that there will indeed be a lively auction with many bids submitted. Several observations indicate that the lower the SOB, the higher the final winning bid. This is due to the increase in the number of bidders attracted by the low SOB.

A [[chi-squared distribution]] shows many low bids but few high bids. Bids &quot;show up together&quot;; without several low bids there will not be any high bids.

Another approach to choosing an SOB: The auctioneer may achieve good success by asking the expected final sales price for the item, as this method suggests to the potential buyers the item's particular value. For instance, say an auctioneer is about to sell a $1,000 car at a sale. Instead of asking $100, hoping to entice wide interest (for who wouldn't want a $1,000 car for $100?), the auctioneer may suggest an opening bid of $1,000; although the first bidder may begin bidding at a mere $100, the final bid may more likely approach $1,000.

==Terminology==
{{Expand section|date=May 2010}}
* [[Appraisal]] - An estimate of an item's worth, usually performed by an expert in that particular field
* Auction block
* [[Bidding]]
* [[Buyer's premium]] - A [[fee]] paid by the buyer to the auction house; typically calculated as a percentage of the winning bid and added on to it.
* Buyout price - A price that, if accepted by a bidder, immediately ends the auction and awards the item to him/her.
* [[Commission (remuneration)|Commission]] - A fee collected by the auction house; typically calculated as a percentage of the winning bid and subtracted from it before the money is released to the seller.
* [[Consignee]]
* [[Consignor]]
* Dummy bid
* CMD (Caution Money Deposit)
* Dynamic closing
* EMD (Earnest Money Deposit) - A payment that must be made by prospective bidders ahead of time to indicate that they are serious about wanting to buy an item. Most often used when high-value goods such as [[real estate]] are up for auction. The winning bidder has his/her earnest money applied toward the final selling price; the non-winners have theirs refunded to them.
* [[Escrow]] - An arrangement in which the winning bidder pays the amount of his/her bid to a third party, who in turn releases the funds to the seller under agreed-upon terms.
* Hammer price - Nominal price at which a lot is sold; the buyer is responsible for paying any additional fees and taxes on top of this amount.
* [[Increment]] - The minimum amount by which a new bid must exceed the previous one.
* Job lot - A large quantity of identical manufactured goods being sold as a single item.
* Knocked down to
* Lot - A single item or group of items that are bid on as one unit.
* Minimum bid - The smallest opening bid that will be accepted.
* No reserve -  An auction in which the seller must honor the winning bid, regardless of its amount.
* Outbid - To bid higher than another person.
* Opening bid - First bid placed on a particular lot.
* Proxy bid (aka absentee bid) - A bid placed by an authorized representative of a bidder who is not physically present at the auction. If the proxy is outbid, he/she may increase the bid in increments up to a pre-arranged maximum.
* Registration deposit
* Relisting
* Reserve price - A minimum acceptable price that is established by the seller prior to the auction; may or may not be disclosed to the bidders. If the winning bid is below the reserve price, the seller has the right to withdraw the lot.
* [[Auction sniping|Sniping]] - Placing a bid just before the end of a timed auction, thus giving other bidders no time to enter new bids.
* [[Vendor]]
* Vendor bid

==JEL classification==
The [[Journal of Economic Literature]] (JEL) [[JEL classification codes|classification code]] for auctions is D44.&lt;ref name=&quot;JEL&quot;&gt;{{Citation
| title = Journal of Economic Literature Classification System
| publisher = American Economic Association
| url = http://aea-web.org/journal/jel_class_system.html
| accessdate = 2008-06-25}} (D: Microeconomics, D4: Market Structure and Pricing, D44: Auctions)&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* Types of auction:
** [[Art sale]]
** [[Auto auctions]]
** [[Car dealer auctions]]
** [[Chinese auction]]
** [[Estate sale]]
** [[Bidding fee auction]]

* Other topics:
** [[Tendering]]
** [[Auction school]]
** [[Auction theory]]
** [[Auction chant]]
** [[Auction Network]]
** [[Auction sniping]]
** [[Dollar auction]]
** [[Foreclosure]]
** [[Game theory]]
** [[Online auction]]
** [[Online auction tools]]
** [[Online auction business model]]
** [[Monopoly (game)]],a game in which auction is sometimes used

&lt;!--===========================({{NoMoreLinks}})===============================
 | DO NOT ADD MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. WIKIPEDIA IS NOT A COLLECTION OF |
 | LINKS. If you think that your link might be useful, do not add it here, |
 | but put it on this article's discussion page first or submit your link |
 | to the appropriate category at the Open Directory Project (www.dmoz.org)|
 | and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template. |
 | |
 | Links that have not been verified WILL BE DELETED. |
 | See [[Wikipedia:External links]] and [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details |
 ===========================({{NoMoreLinks}})===============================--&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
{{Commons category|Auctions}}
* {{Citation
|last=Krishna
|first=Vijay
|title=Auction Theory
|year=2002
|publisher=Academic Press
|location=San Diego, USA
|isbn=0-12-426297-X
|ref=Krishna2002
}}
* {{Citation
|last=Milgrom
|first=Paul
|authorlink=Paul Milgrom
|title=Putting Auction Theory to Work
|year=2004
|publisher=Cambridge University Press
|location=Cambridge, United Kingdom
|isbn=0-521-55184-6
|ref=Milgrom2004
}}
* {{Citation
| last = Shubik
| first = Martin
| title = The Theory of Money and Financial Institutions: Volume 1
| publisher = MIT Press
| month = March | year = 2004
| location = Cambridge , Mass., USA
| pages = 213–219
| isbn = 0-262-69311-9
| ref=Shubik}}

==Further reading==
* {{Citation| last =Klemperer| first = Paul| authorlink = Paul Klemperer|year=2004|title=Auctions: Theory and Practice|isbn=0-691-11925-2| publisher =Princeton University Press| location =Princeton, N.J.}} [http://www.nuff.ox.ac.uk/users/klemperer/VirtualBook/VirtualBookCoverSheet.asp Draft edition available online].
* {{Citation|author=Smith, Charles W.|year=1990|title=Auctions: Social Construction of Value|publisher=University of California Press|isbn=0-520-07201-4}}
* http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1727409

&lt;!--== External links ==--&gt;
&lt;!--== External links ==--&gt;
&lt;!--===========================({{NoMoreLinks}})===============================
 | DO NOT ADD MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. WIKIPEDIA IS NOT A COLLECTION OF |
 | LINKS. If you think that your link might be useful, do not add it here, |
 | but put it on this article's discussion page first or submit your link |
 | to the appropriate category at the Open Directory Project (www.dmoz.org)|
 | and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template. |
 | |
 | Links that have not been verified WILL BE DELETED. |
 | See [[Wikipedia:External links]] and [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details |
 ===========================({{NoMoreLinks}})===============================--&gt;

[[Category:Auctioneering]]
[[Category:Auction theory]]
[[Category:Business models]]

[[ar:مزاد]]
[[az:Auksion]]
[[bn:নিলাম]]
[[be-x-old:Аўкцыён]]
[[bg:Аукцион]]
[[ca:Subhasta]]
[[cs:Dražba]]
[[da:Auktion]]
[[pdc:Vendu]]
[[de:Auktion]]
[[et:Oksjon]]
[[es:Subasta]]
[[eo:Aŭkcio]]
[[fa:مزایده]]
[[fr:Enchère]]
[[gd:Rup]]
[[ko:경매]]
[[id:Lelang]]
[[it:Asta (economia)]]
[[he:מכירה פומבית]]
[[ka:აუქციონი]]
[[kk:Аукцион]]
[[lb:Stee (Handel)]]
[[lt:Aukcionas]]
[[hu:Árverés]]
[[ms:Lelong]]
[[mn:Үнэ хаялцах]]
[[nl:Veiling]]
[[ja:競売]]
[[no:Auksjon]]
[[pl:Aukcja (forma przetargu)]]
[[pt:Leilão]]
[[ru:Аукцион]]
[[simple:Auction]]
[[sk:Dražba (predaj)]]
[[sr:Аукција]]
[[sh:Aukcija]]
[[fi:Huutokauppa]]
[[sv:Auktion]]
[[te:వేలంపాట]]
[[tr:Müzayede]]
[[uk:Аукціон]]
[[vi:Đấu giá]]
[[wa:Håsse (vinte)]]
[[zh:拍卖]]</text>
      <sha1>4028yfvdr8b2dxzrd7fmquqo8awbwrm</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
