<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Big Mac Index</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>220886</id>
    <revision>
      <id>517337278</id>
      <parentid>515222109</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-12T07:07:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Kravietz</username>
        <id>49031</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Big Mac Index not found at this URL</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18390">[[File:BigMacCroatia.jpg|thumb|right|A McDonalds Big Mac.]]
[[File:Big Mac index 50USD 2columns.png|thumb|right|How many burgers you get for $50 USD? (Jan 2012)]]
The '''Big Mac Index''' is published by ''[[The Economist]]'' as an informal way of measuring the [[purchasing power parity]] (PPP) between two [[currency|currencies]] and provides a test of the extent to which market [[exchange rate]]s result in goods costing the same in different countries. It &quot;seeks to make exchange-rate theory a bit more digestible&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last= |first= |authorlink= |coauthors= |title=Big MacCurrencies |work= |publisher=[[The Economist]] |date=1998-04-09 |url=http://www.economist.com/finance/displaystory.cfm?story_id=E1_TVJRVJ |doi= |accessdate=2007-07-24 |quote =&quot;Big Mac Index, which seeks to make exchange-rate theory a bit more digestible,&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Index (economics)|index]] takes its name from the [[Big Mac]], a [[hamburger]] sold at [[McDonald's]] restaurants.

==Overview==
The Big Mac index was introduced in ''[[The Economist]]'' in September 1986 by [[Pam Woodall]] as a semi-humorous illustration and has been published by that paper annually since then. The index also gave rise to the word ''burgernomics''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
  | last1 = Daley | first1 = James
  | title = Burgernomics: Why the price of a Big Mac may hold the key to better investment returns
  | newspaper = [[The Independent]]
  | date = 2008-09-06
  | url = http://www.independent.co.uk/money/invest-save/burgernomics-why-the-price-of-a-big-mac-may-hold-the-key-to-better-investment-returns-920726.html
  | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[UBS Wealth Management]] Research has expanded the idea of the Big Mac index to include the amount of time that an average worker in a given country must work to earn enough to buy a Big Mac.
The working-time based Big Mac index might give a more realistic view of the purchasing power of the average worker, as it takes into account more factors, such as local [[wage]]s.&lt;ref name=ubs&gt;{{Cite journal
  | author =Hoefert, Andreas
  | coauthors = Hofer, Simone
  | title = Prices and Earnings: A Comparison of Purchasing Power Around the Globe
  | version = 2006 Edition
  | page = 11
  | publisher = UBS AG, Wealth Management Research
  | year = 2006
  | url = http://www.ubs.com/1/ShowMedia/ubs_ch/wealth_mgmt_ch?contentId=103982&amp;name=eng.pdf
  | format = [[PDF]]
  | accessdate = 2008-09-24 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

One suggested method of predicting exchange rate movements is that the rate between two currencies should naturally adjust so that a sample [[basket (finance)|basket of goods]] and services should cost the same in both currencies [[Purchasing power parity|(PPP)]].  In the Big Mac index, the basket in question is a single [[Big Mac]] burger as sold by the [[McDonald's]] fast food restaurant chain.  The Big Mac was chosen because it is available to a common specification in many countries around the world as local McDonald's [[franchising|franchisees]] at least in theory have significant responsibility for negotiating input prices. For these reasons, the index enables a comparison between many countries' currencies.

The Big Mac PPP exchange rate between two countries is obtained by dividing the price of a Big Mac in one country (in its currency) by the price of a Big Mac in another country (in its currency). This value is then compared with the actual exchange rate; if it is lower, then the first currency is under-valued (according to PPP theory) compared with the second, and conversely, if it is higher, then the first currency is over-valued.

For example, using figures in July 2008:&lt;ref name = BMIJuly2008&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.economist.com/finance/displaystory.cfm?story_id=11793125|work = The Big Mac Index |title = Sandwiched (Burgernomics says currencies are very dear in Europe but very cheap in Asia)|publisher = The Economist|date = 24 July 2008|accessdate = 2008-11-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;
#the price of a Big Mac was $3.57 in the [[United States]] (varies by store)
#the price of a Big Mac was £2.29 in the United Kingdom (Britain) (varies by region)
#the implied purchasing power parity was $1.56 to £1, that is $3.57/£2.29 = 1.56
#this compares with an actual exchange rate of $2.00 to £1 at the time
#(2.00-1.56)/1.56 = 28%
#the pound was thus overvalued against the dollar by 28%

The [[Eurozone]] is mixed, as prices differ widely in the EU area. As of April 2009, the Big Mac is trading in Germany at {{€|2.99}}, which translates into {{USD|3.96}}, which would imply that the Euro is slightly trading above the PPP, with the difference being 10.9%.

===Variants===
''The Economist'' sometimes produces variants on the theme.  For example in January 2004, it showed a ''Tall Latte index'' with the Big Mac replaced by a cup of [[Starbucks]] [[coffee]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
 | url = http://money.cnn.com/2004/01/16/news/funny/latteindex/
 | title = The price of latte in Lucerne
 | last =  Max
 | first =  Sarah
 | authorlink =
 | coauthors =
 | work =
 | publisher = CNN/Money
 | date = 2004-01-30
 | doi =
 | accessdate = 2008-05-30
 | archiveurl =
 | archivedate =
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, an Australian bank's subsidiary, Commonwealth Securities, adapted the idea behind the Big Mac index to create an &quot;[[iPod]] index.&quot; The bank's theory is that since the iPod is manufactured at a single place, the value of iPods should be more consistent globally. However, this theory can be criticised for ignoring shipping costs, which will vary depending on how far the product is delivered from its &quot;single place&quot; of manufacture in [[China]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
 | url = http://www.smh.com.au/news/technology/ipod-index-trumps-the-bigmac-one/2007/01/18/1169095897045.html
 | title = iPod Index trumps the BigMac one
 | last =
 | first =
 | authorlink =
 | coauthors =
 | work =
 | publisher = Sydney Morning Herald
 | date = 2007-01-18
 | doi =
 | accessdate = 2008-05-19
 | archiveurl = http://www.webcitation.org/5XwRET9sG
 | archivedate = 2008-05-19
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Bloomberg L.P.]] introduced the Billy index where they convert local prices of [[Ikea]]'s Billy bookshelf into US dollars and compare the prices.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.svd.se/naringsliv/nyheter/artikel_3499675.svd SvD: Ikea-Billy utmanar Big Mac][http://translate.google.com/translate?prev=hp&amp;hl=sv&amp;js=y&amp;u=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.svd.se%2Fnaringsliv%2Fnyheter%2Fartikel_3499675.svd&amp;sl=sv&amp;tl=en&amp;history_state0=]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thelocal.se/21998/20090910/ The Local: Billy bookshelf does battle with Big Mac Index]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dagenshandel.se/dh/DagensH.nsf/0/C78C108458A0ED4DC125762D00334236?open Dagens Handel: Billy-index utmanar Big Mac]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=newsarchive&amp;sid=a.K4T4ypP9ko Ikea Billy Bookshelf Index Shows Lowest Price in U.A.E. (Table)]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Limitations===
While economists widely cite the Big Mac index as a reasonable real-world measurement of purchasing power parity,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
  | last1 = McConnell | first1 = Campbell
  | last2 = Brue  | first2 = Stanley
  | title = Microeconomics, 16th ed.
  | url = http://books.google.com/books?id=hObpeG6v1VsC&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | page = 473
  | publisher = [[McGraw Hill]]
  | date =
  | year = 2004
  | isbn = 0-07-287561-5
  | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;}}(Leading American microeconomics college textbook)&lt;/ref&gt;{{r|ec20110127}} the burger methodology has some limitations.&lt;ref&gt;Haidar, Jamal Ibrahim, 2011. “[http://ideas.repec.org/a/wej/wldecn/479.html Currency Valuation and Purchasing Power Parity],” World Economics – The Oxford Institute for Economic Policy, vol. 12(3), pages 1-12, September&lt;/ref&gt; In many countries, eating at international fast-food chain restaurants such as [[McDonald's]] is relatively expensive in comparison to eating at a local restaurant, and the demand for Big Macs is not as large in countries like [[India]] as in the [[United States]]. Social status of eating at fast food restaurants like McDonald's in a local market, what proportion of sales might be to expatriates, local taxes, levels of competition, and import duties on selected items may not be representative of the country's economy as a whole.

In addition, there is no theoretical reason why non-tradable goods and services such as property costs should be equal in different countries: this is the theoretical reason for PPPs being different from market exchange rates over time. The relative cost of high-[[profit margin|margin]] products, such as essential pharmaceutical products, or cellular telephony might compare local capacity and [[willingness to pay]], as much as relative currency values.

Nevertheless, McDonald's is also using different commercial strategies which can result in huge differences for a product. Overall, the price of a Big Mac will be a reflection of its local production and delivery cost, the cost of advertising (considerable in some areas), and most importantly what the local market will bear - quite different from country to country, and not all a reflection of relative currency values.

In some markets, a high-volume and low-margin approach makes most sense to maximize profit, while in others a higher margin will generate more profit. Thus the relative prices reflect more than currency values. For example, a hamburger sandwich costs only {{€|1}} in France, and {{€|1.50}} in Belgium, but overall, McDonald's restaurants are cheaper in Belgium.{{Citation needed|date=September 2010}} Prices of Big Macs can also vary greatly between different areas within a country. For example, a Big Mac sold in New York City will be more expensive than one sold at a McDonald's located in a rural area of a neighboring state.

===Manipulation===
Critics of the [[presidency of Cristina Fernández de Kirchner]] in [[Argentina]] and many economists believe that the government has for years falsified consumer price data to understate the country's true inflation rate.{{r|politi20111124}} ''The Economist'' stated in January 2011 that Big Mac index &quot;does support claims that Argentina’s government is cooking the books. The gap between its average annual rate of burger inflation (19%) and its official rate (10%) is far bigger than in any other country.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ec20110127&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.economist.com/node/18014576?story_id=18014576 | title=Lies, flame-grilled lies and statistics | work=The Economist | date=2011-01-27 | accessdate=June 10, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; That year the press began reporting on unusual behavior by the more than 200 Argentinean McDonald's. The restaurants no longer prominently advertise Big Macs for sale and the sandwich, both individually and as part of [[value meal]]s, is sold for an unusually low price compared to other items. [[Guillermo Moreno]], Secretary of Commerce in the Kirchner government, reportedly forced McDonald's to sell the Big Mac at an artificially low price to manipulate the country's performance on the Big Mac index.{{r|sanguinetti20120608}}&lt;ref name=&quot;politi20111124&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://latitude.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/24/argentinas-big-mac-attack/ | title=Argentina’s Big Mac Attack | work=The New York Times | date=2011-11-24 | accessdate=June 10, 2012 | author=Politi, Daniel}}&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2012 the price of the Big Mac value meal suddenly rose by 26%, closer to that of other meals, after ''The Economist'', ''The New York Times'', and other media reported on the unusual pricing. A Buenos Aires newspaper stated &quot;Moreno loses the battle&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;sanguinetti20120608&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.cronista.com/economiapolitica/Moreno-pierde-la-batalla-el-Big-Mac-sale-del-freezer-y-aumenta-26-su-precio-20120608-0012.html | title=Moreno pierde la batalla: el Big Mac sale del freezer y aumenta 26% su precio | language=Spanish | work=El Cronista | date=2012-06-08 | accessdate=June 15, 2012 | author=Sanguinetti, Andrew | location=Buenos Aires, Argentina}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Comparison issues===
The Big Mac (and virtually all sandwiches) vary from country to country with differing nutritional values, weights and even nominal size differences.

Not all Big Mac burgers offered by the chain are exclusively beef. In India — which is a predominantly [[Hindu]] country — beef burgers are not available at any McDonald's outlets. The chicken Maharaja Mac serves as a substitute for the Big Mac.

There is a lot of variance with the exclusively Beef &quot;Big Mac&quot;: the Australian version of the Big Mac has 22% less energy than the Canadian version, and is 8% lighter than the version sold in Mexico.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last= |first= |authorlink= |coauthors= |title=Big Mac? Not really, as Australian version of burger downsized |work= |publisher=[[The Advertiser (Adelaide)]] |date=2009-06-13 |url=http://www.economist.com/finance/displaystory.cfm?story_id=E1_TVJRVJ |doi= |accessdate=2009-06-18 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2009, it was reported that all three of the McDonald's in [[Iceland]] would be closing primarily due to the chain's high cost of importing most of the chain's meat and vegetables from the Eurozone. At the time, a Big Mac in Iceland cost 650 krona ($5.29), and the 20% price increase that would have been needed to stay in business would have increased that cost to 780 krona ($6.36).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2009/10/26/world/main5422511.shtml Iceland Says Bye to the Big Mac], CBS News, 26 October 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

==Figures==
'''Five most expensive''' (12 January 2012) (not considering the fact that the buyer's equivalent purchasing power is different)&lt;ref name=&quot;2012index&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=The Economist Big Mac index, January 2012|publisher=[[The Economist]]|date=2012-01-12|url=http://www.economist.com/blogs/graphicdetail/2012/01/daily-chart-3|accessdate=2012-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;2012indexdata&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=The Big Mac index|publisher=[[The Economist]]|date=2012-01-12|url=http://www.scribd.com/fullscreen/78055840|accessdate=2012-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;
#{{flag|Venezuela}} - $15.12 (65 [[Bolivares|Bs.]])
#{{flag|Switzerland}} - $6.81 (6.50 [[Swiss franc|CHF]])
#{{flag|Norway}} - $6.79 (41 [[Norwegian krone|kr.]])
#{{flag|Sweden}} - $5.91 (41 [[Swedish krona|Kr.]])
#{{flag|Brazil}} - $5.68 (10.25 [[R$]])

'''Six most affordable''' (12 January 2012) (not considering the fact that the buyer's equivalent purchasing power is different and not including the Indian Big Mac which contains chicken instead of beef)&lt;ref name=&quot;2012index&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;2012indexdata&quot; /&gt;
#{{flag|Ukraine}} - $2.11 (18 [[Ukrainian hryvnia|UAH]])&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mcdonalds.ua/ukr/nashi-stravi-/stravi-na-vibr/big-mak/&lt;/ref&gt;
#{{flag|Hong Kong}} - $2.13 (16.5 [[Hong Kong dollar|HKD]])
#{{flag|Russia}} - $2.15 (70 [[Russian ruble|RUR]])
#{{flag|Malaysia}} - $2.34 (7.35 [[Malaysian ringgit|MYR]])
#{{flag|China}} - $2.44 (15.4 [[Renminbi|CNY]])
#{{flag|South Africa}} - $2.45 (19.95 [[South African rand|ZAR]])

'''Ten fastest earned''' (July 2009)
#{{flagicon|Japan}} [[Tokyo]] - 10 minutes
#{{flagicon|United States}} [[Los Angeles]] - 11 minutes
#{{flagicon|United States}} [[Chicago]] - 12 minutes
#{{flagicon|United States}} [[Miami]] - 12 minutes
#{{flagicon|United States}} [[New York City]] - 13 minutes
#{{flagicon|New Zealand}} [[Auckland]] - 14 minutes
#{{flagicon|Australia}} [[Sydney]] - 14 minutes
#{{flagicon|Canada}} [[Toronto]] - 14 minutes
#{{flagicon|Switzerland}} [[Zürich]] - 15 minutes
#{{flagicon|Ireland}} [[Dublin]] - 15 minutes

'''Ten slowest earned''' (July 2009)
#{{flagicon|Kenya}} [[Nairobi]] - 158 minutes
#{{flagicon|Indonesia}} [[Jakarta]] - 136 minutes
#{{flagicon|Mexico}} [[Mexico City]] - 129 minutes
#{{flagicon|Venezuela}} [[Caracas]] - 126 minutes
#{{flagicon|Philippines}} [[Manila]] - 88 minutes
#{{flagicon|Egypt}} [[Cairo]] - 82 minutes
#{{flagicon|Chile}} [[Santiago de Chile]] - 69 minutes
#{{flagicon|Slovakia}} [[Bratislava]] - 62 minutes
#{{flagicon|India}} [[Mumbai]] - 61 minutes
#{{flagicon|Hungary}} [[Budapest]] - 59 minutes

==See also==
* [[Golden Arches Theory of Conflict Prevention]]
* [[Christmas Price Index]]
* [[Recession index]]
* [[List of unusual units of measurement]]
* [[List of humorous units of measurement]]
* [[Banana equivalent dose]] - a whimsical way of looking at radiation exposure

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.economist.com/markets/Bigmac/Index.cfm The Big Mac Index index page] &amp;mdash; contains Big Mac Index data dating back to 1997 (Economist.com subscription required for detail)
*[http://econblog.aplia.com/2006/06/itunes-index-for-exchange-rates_16.html Big Mac versus iTunes] Aplia
*[http://bigmacindex.org/bmi-data-text-format.html Big Mac Index in text format for analysis]
*[http://www.theglobalguru.com/article.php?id=97&amp;offer=GURU001 Global Investor Article on Big Mac Index] - Discusses origins &amp; significance to international investors - 9 February 2007
* [http://www.ubs.com/1/ShowMedia/wealthmanagement/wealth_management_research?contentId=170298&amp;name=PreiseLoehne_2009_e.pdf &quot;Prices and Earnings: A Comparison of Purchasing Power Around the Globe -2009,&quot; UBS AG, Wealth Management Research] Good report on purchasing power containing a Big Mac index (in minutes) as well as for staples such as bread and rice for 71 world cities.
* [http://www.finfacts.ie/irelandbusinessnews/publish/article_10006889.shtml UBS Prices and Earnings Report 2006: Dublin is 8th most expensive city but 3rd highest for net earnings] Very thorough article on the time-based Big Mac index.
* [http://www.thebigmacindex.com The Big Mac Index Converter] &amp;mdash; Currency conversion calculator that uses the Big Mac Index.

{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2010}}

[[Category:Economic indicators]]
[[Category:McDonald's]]
[[Category:The Economist]]

{{Link GA|de}}
[[az:Biq Mak İndeksi]]
[[be-x-old:Індэкс біг-маку]]
[[ca:Índex Big Mac]]
[[cs:Big Mac Index]]
[[da:Big Mac index]]
[[de:Big-Mac-Index]]
[[es:Índice Big Mac]]
[[fa:شاخص بیگ مک]]
[[fr:Indice Big Mac]]
[[gl:Índice Big Mac]]
[[ko:빅맥 지수]]
[[id:Indeks Big Mac]]
[[it:Indice Big Mac]]
[[he:מדד ביג מק]]
[[lt:Big Mac indeksas]]
[[ms:Indeks Big Mac]]
[[nl:Big Mac-index]]
[[ja:ビッグマック指数]]
[[no:Big Mac-indeks]]
[[pl:Wskaźnik Big Maca]]
[[pt:Índice Big Mac]]
[[ru:Индекс Биг-Мака]]
[[simple:Big Mac Index]]
[[sk:Big Mac index]]
[[fi:Big Mac -indeksi]]
[[sv:Big Mac-index]]
[[uk:Індекс БігМака]]
[[zh:巨無霸指數]]</text>
      <sha1>7pqppajt4kul4m372kv66jacmap4vgo</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
