<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Charity shop</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>535982</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521715572</id>
      <parentid>521609673</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-06T19:45:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>50.78.229.137</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Popularity of charity shops */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14724">{{Multiple issues|disputed=July 2010|neutrality=July 2010|essay=September 2009}}
[[Image:Charity shop in West Street (6) - geograph.org.uk - 1504815.jpg|thumb|right|250px|A charity shop in the UK.]]

A '''charity shop''', '''thrift shop''', '''thrift store''', '''hospice shop''' ([[United States|U.S.]], [[Canada]]), '''resale shop''' (when not meaning [[consignment]] shop U.S.) or '''op shop''' ([[Australia]]/[[New Zealand|N.Z.]]) (from &quot;opportunity shop&quot;) is a [[retail]] establishment run by a [[charitable organization]] to raise money.  

Charity shops are a type of [[social enterprise]]. They usually sell mainly [[used good]]s [[donation|donated]] by members of the public, and are often staffed by [[volunteer]]s. Because the items for sale were obtained for free, and business costs are low, the items can be sold at competitive prices.  After costs are paid, all remaining income from the sales is used in accord with the organization's stated charitable purpose. Costs include purchase and/or depreciation of fixtures (clothing racks, bookshelves, counters, etc.), operating costs (maintenance, municipal service fees, electricity, telephone, limited advertising) and the building lease or mortgage.  It is widely recognized that quality thrift store merchandise is priced 50-75% below the original retail price, offering significant bargains.&lt;ref&gt;First Research 6/2011 Report on SIC CODES: 5932
NAICS CODES: 453310, 522298 (available from www.firstresearch.com)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Popularity of charity shops==
Charity shops are often popular with people who are [[Frugality|frugal]]  . In [[the United States]], shopping at a charity store has become popular enough to earn a slang term: [[thrifting]].

[[Environmentalist]]s may prefer buying [[used good|second-hand good]]s as this uses fewer [[natural resource]]s and would appear do less damage to the [[ecology|environment]] than by buying new goods would, in part because the goods are usually collected locally.  In addition, reusing second-hand items is a form of [[recycling]], and thus reduces the amount of [[waste]] going to [[landfill]] sites.

People who oppose [[sweat shops]] often purchase second-hand clothing as an alternative to supporting clothing companies with dubious [[ethical]] practices. Alot of online E-Commerce thrift stores have been popping up as of late as well. Stores such as [http://www.tntkasik.com TnT Kasik], and many others

Second-hand goods are considered to be quite safe. The [[South Australia]]n Public Health Directorate says that the health risk of buying used clothing is very low. It explains that washing purchased items in hot water is just one of several ways to eliminate the risk of contracting infectious diseases.&lt;ref name=&quot;sa_health&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Second-hand goods: A guide for consumers|url=http://www.health.sa.gov.au/pehs/PDF-files/ph-fs-consumers-secondhand.pdf|work=Public and Environmental Health Service website|publisher=Department of Health, Government of South Australia|accessdate=16 July 2010|format=PDF|month=October|year=2008|quote=As the risk to health associated with second-hand goods is very low, thorough and hygienic cleaning is all that is required to eliminate the risk of contracting infectious diseases. ... Washing second-hand clothing and bedding in hot water (hotter than 60°C) and detergent kills these disease-causing organisms. Items that cannot be washed ...}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==New goods sold at charity shops==
Some charity shops, such as the [[British Heart Foundation]], also sell a range of new goods which may be branded to the charity, or have some connection with the cause the charity supports. [[Oxfam]] stores, for example, sell [[fair trade]] food and crafts. Other stores may sell new [[Halloween]] supplies and decorations where old [[vintage]] clothes are popular for use as [[costume]]s.  Some stores specialise in selling books, music, or bridalwear. Charity shops may receive [[overstock]] or obsolete goods from local for-profit businesses; the for-profit businesses benefit by taking a tax write-off and [[closeout|clearing unwanted goods]] from their store instead of throwing the goods out, which is costly.

== United Kingdom ==
[[Image:Charity-shop-Epping-029.JPG|thumb|right|Window display in a UK charity shop.]]
The first [[Oxfam]] charity shop in the United Kingdom was established in Broad Street, [[Oxford]], and began trading in December 1947 (although the shop itself did not open until February 1948).  Oxfam opened some of the first charity shops.  

However, pre-dating this, one of the first [[Red Cross]] shops was opened at 17 Old Bond Street, [[London]], as early as 1941. In total, over two hundred “permanent” (for the duration of the war) Red Cross gift shops and about 150 temporary Red Cross shops were opened during the war years. A condition of the shop licence issued by the Board of Trade was that all goods offered for sale were gifts. Purchase for re-sale was forbidden. The entire proceeds from sales had to be passed to the Duke of Gloucester’s Red Cross and St John Fund. Most premises were lent free of rent and in some cases owners also met the costs of heating and lighting. 

There is also evidence that the Wolverhampton Society for the Blind (now called the Beacon Centre for the Blind) opened up a shop in Wolverhampton in 1899 to sell goods made by blind people to raise money for the Society.

During [[World War I]], similar fund-raising activities occurred such as a [[bazaar]] in [[Shepherd Market]], London, which made £50,000 for the Red Cross.

Oxfam has the largest number of charity shops in the [[United Kingdom|UK]] with over 700 stores. Many Oxfam shops also sell books, and the organization now operates over 70 specialist [[Oxfam Bookshop]]s, making them the largest retailer of second-hand books in Britain. Other Oxfam affiliates also have stores, such as [[Jersey]], [[Germany]], [[Ireland]] (45 shops in NI/ROI), the [[Netherlands]] and [[Hong Kong]]. 

Other charities with a strong presence on high streets in the UK include [[YMCA]], [[British Heart Foundation]], [[Barnardos]], [[Cancer Research UK]], [[Roy Castle Lung Cancer Foundation]], [[Age UK]] (formerly [[Age Concern]] and [[Help the Aged]]), [[Oxfam]], [[Save the Children]], [[Scope (British charity)|Scope]] and [[Sue Ryder Care]]. Many local [[Hospice care|hospice]]s also operate charity shops to raise funds.

There are over 9,000 charity shops in the UK and Republic of Ireland. Their locations can be found on the Charity Retail Association (CRA) website,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.charityretail.org.uk/locator.php Charity Retail Association FAQ]&lt;/ref&gt; along with information on charity retail, what shops can and can't accept, etc. The CRA is a member organisation for charities which run shops.

British charity shops are mainly staffed by unpaid volunteers, with a paid shop manager. Goods for sale are predominantly from donations - 87% according to the official estimate.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.charityretail.org.uk/faqs_shop.html Charity Retail Association FAQ]&lt;/ref&gt; Donations should be taken directly to a charity shop during opening hours, as goods left on the street may be stolen or damaged by passers-by or inclement weather. In expensive areas, donations include a proportion of good quality designer clothing and charity shops in these areas are sought out for cut-price fashions{{Citation needed|date=November 2008}}.

'Standard' charity shops sell a mix of clothing, books, music and bric-a-brac (like cutlery and ornaments). Some shops specialise in certain areas, like vintage clothing, furniture, electrical items, or records.

Almost all charity shops sell on their unsold textiles (i.e. unfashionable, stained or damaged fabric) to textile processors. Each charity shop saves an average or 40 tonnes of textiles every year, by selling them in the shop, or passing them on to these textile merchants for recycling or reuse. This grosses to around 363,000 tonnes across all charity shops in the UK; based on 2010 landfill tax value at £48 per tonne, the value of textiles reused or passed for recycling by charity shops in terms of savings in landfill tax is £17,424,000 p.a.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.charityretail.org.uk/reuse.html Charity Retail Association Reuse FAQ]&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Gift Aid]] is a UK tax incentive for individual donors where, subject to a signed declaration being held by the charity, income tax paid on donations can be reclaimed by the charity. Although initially intended only for cash donations, the scheme now (since 2006) allows tax on the income earned by charity shops acting as agent for the donor to be reclaimed.&lt;ref name=hmrc&gt;[http://www.hmrc.gov.uk/charities/giftaid-charities/other.htm#gifts_of_goods HMRC Gift Aid]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sue Ryder Care]] was the first to '[[Gift Aid]]' its donations with a pioneering new system developed with Eproductive Ltd.

Charity shops in the UK get mandatory 80% relief on [[Business rates in England and Wales|business rates]] on their premises, which is funded by central government (not by local ratepayers) and is one illustration of their support for the charity sector and the role of charity shops in raising funds for charities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.charityretail.org.uk/howcharityshopswork.html Charity Retail Association FAQ]&lt;/ref&gt; Charities can apply for discretionary relief on the remaining 20%, which is an occasional source of criticism from retailers which have to pay in full.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/cornwall/4612843.stm Call to cut charity shops in town]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Australia==
In Australia, major national opportunity shop chains include the [[St. Vincent de Paul Thrift Store]] ([[trading as]] Vinnies), the [[Salvation Army]] (trading as Salvos), the [[Red Cross]], MS Australia, and the [[Brotherhood of St. Laurence]]. Many local charitable organisations, both religious and secular, run opportunity shops.  Common among these are missions and [[animal shelter]]s.

==United States and Canada==
In the United States, major national thrift shop operators include [http://www.arcthrift.org Arc Thrift Stores], [[Goodwill Industries]], [[Salvation Army]], [[St. Vincent de Paul Thrift Store]]s, ReStore (see [[Habitat for Humanity International]]), [[Deseret Industries]] (in the western U.S.), and Value Village (see [[Savers]]).  Regional operators include [[Deseret Industries]] in the [[western United States]], and those run by the Bethesda [[Lutheran]] Home in the [[Upper Midwest]].  Many local charitable organizations, both religious and secular, operate thrift shops.  Common among these are missions, children's homes, homeless shelters, and animal shelters. In addition, some charity shops are operated by churches, and are fundraising venues that support activities including, in some cases, missionary activities in other countries.  Several U.S. stores are for-profit, with the charity that collected the goods making money from the [[wholesale]] of those items to the store.

In July 2009, a [[U.S. government]] report revealed that several lenders were judging their customers' financial status based on where they shopped, and were assuming that those who shopped at thrift stores and other low-cost retailers were struggling financially. In response, the lender were increasing [[interest rate]]s, lowering their [[credit limit]], or even damaging their overall [[credit score]], which may have caused other [[Credit (finance)|credit]] issuers to further harm the shopper by taking similar actions ([[universal default]]), or denying credit applications altogether. Laws were passed by Congress in 2009 to stop issuers from these practices.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.witn.com/blogs/newsblog/50940922.html &quot;Report: Where You Shop Matters&quot;], [[WITN]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.woai.com/business/story/Credit-card-companies-accused-of-penalizing-the/aQzP6e1kwEOXoI8xihkBzQ.cspx &quot;Credit card companies accused of penalizing the thrifty&quot;], [[WOAI-TV|WOAI]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wmbfnews.com/Global/story.asp?S=10671306 &quot;Store purchases could punish credit holders&quot;], [[WMBF]]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Thrift stores==
Thrift stores are generally owned by a charity but run as an independent business under contract: they are licensed by the charity, which provides the merchandise for sale, and benefits by the sale of these goods directly to the contractor who operates the shop. The shop may then make a profit from this arrangement. In some cases, e.g. 'Savers' and 'Value Village' they pay a small percentage of the profit to the charity. Charities in the US are supported by tax legislation (see [[501(c)(3)]]) but this does not extend to the 'for profit' thrift shop. Unlike directly charity-run shops run by volunteers, thrift shops pay taxes, and must under their contract have employees with proper contracts of employment.{{Citation needed|date=July 2009}}

In many countries around the world, not just exclusively in the Third World, second-hand clothing that is initially donated, are resold and is considered a commodity throughout the world.  Some countries forbid it as it harms the local textile industry, as it is in the case in the Philippines. In other cases countries increase tariffs to reduce imports. Some countries ban the sale of second-hand clothing because unwashed used clothing is seen as a potential threat of spreading disease. The author of an article, Karen Transberg Hansen, suggested that in Zambia, however, ''salaula'', or the selling of second-hand clothing actually helps the local economy in generating income.&lt;ref&gt;Hansen, Karen Tranberg. 2004. Helping or hindering? Controversies around the international
second-hand clothing trade. Anthropology Today 20 (4):3-9.&lt;/ref&gt; Hansen said the trade provided more jobs (handling, cleaning, repairing, and restyling). It has also provided governments with revenue from tariffs.

== See also ==
*[[Consignment]]
*[[Flea market]]
*[[Give-away shop]]
*[[Jumble sale]]
*[[Surplus store]]
*[[Sustainable clothing]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://opshop.org Australian OpShop Listing]
* [http://www.charityretail.org.uk/index.html Charity Retail Association]
* [http://charityshoptourism.wordpress.com Charity Shop Tourism blog]
{{charity}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2010}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Charity Shop}}
[[Category:Retailing]]
[[Category:Charitable organizations]]
[[Category:The Salvation Army]]
[[Category:Waste collection]]
[[Category:Reuse]]

[[da:Genbrugsbutik]]
[[de:Secondhandladen]]
[[ko:자선 가게]]
[[it:Mercatino dell'usato]]
[[hu:Adománybolt]]
[[nl:Kringloopcentrum]]
[[ja:古着]]
[[pt:Brechó]]
[[ksh:Altreusheräj]]
[[ru:Благотворительный магазин]]
[[uk:Благодійний магазин]]
[[zh:古着]]</text>
      <sha1>3ijhho69ahw3z2jy6hhcm17njhup9ik</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
