<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Collusion</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>162557</id>
    <revision>
      <id>510229137</id>
      <parentid>501782955</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-01T05:06:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>183.37.248.153</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Variations */ Clarified sentence regarding price increases in firm collusion</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7902">{{other uses}}
{{More footnotes|date=July 2008}}
{{Competition law}}
'''Collusion''' is an agreement between two or more persons, sometimes illegal and therefore secretive, to limit open [[competition]] by deceiving, misleading, or defrauding others of their legal rights, or to obtain an objective forbidden by law typically by defrauding or gaining an unfair advantage.{{citation needed|date=October 2009}}  It is an agreement among firms to divide the market, set prices, or limit production.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | last = Sullivan
  | first = arthur
  | authorlink = Arthur O' Sullivan
  | coauthors = Steven M. Sheffrin
  | title = Economics: Principles in action
  | publisher = Pearson Prentice Hall
  | year = 2003
  | location = Upper Saddle River, New Jersey 07458
  | pages = 171
  | url = http://www.pearsonschool.com/index.cfm?locator=PSZ3R9&amp;PMDbSiteId=2781&amp;PMDbSolutionId=6724&amp;PMDbCategoryId=&amp;PMDbProgramId=12881&amp;level=4
  | doi =
  | isbn = 0-13-063085-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;
It can involve &quot;wage fixing, kickbacks, or misrepresenting the independence of the relationship between the colluding parties&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://definitions.uslegal.com/c/collusion/ Collusion Law &amp; Legal Definition]&lt;/ref&gt;  In legal terms, all acts affected by collusion are considered [[void (law)|void]].&lt;ref&gt;Collusion [http://encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761571249/Collusion.html]. [http://www.webcitation.org/5kwRA5eiX Archived] 2009-10-31.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Definition ==
In the study of [[economics]] and market [[competition]], collusion takes place within an [[industry]] when rival companies cooperate for their mutual benefit. Collusion most often takes place within the [[market structure]] of [[oligopoly]], where the decision of a few firms to collude can significantly impact the market as a whole. [[Cartel]]s are a special case of explicit collusion. Collusion which is not overt, on the other hand, is known as [[tacit collusion]].

== Variations ==
According to [[Neoclassical economics|neoclassical price-determination theory]] and [[game theory]], the independence of suppliers forces prices to their minimum, increasing [[Economic efficiency|efficiency]] and decreasing the price determining ability of each individual firm. However, if firms collude to all increase prices, loss of sales is minimized, as consumers lack alternative choices at lower prices. This benefits the colluding firms at the cost of [[Economic efficiency|efficiency]] to society.

One variation of this traditional theory is the theory of [[kinked demand]]. Firms face a kinked demand curve if, when one firm decreases its price, other firms will follow suit in order to maintain sales, and when one firm increases its price, its rivals are unlikely to follow, as they would lose the sales' gains that they would otherwise get by holding prices at the previous level.  Kinked demand potentially fosters [[supra-competitive prices]] because any one firm would receive a reduced benefit from cutting price, as opposed to the benefits accruing under neoclassical theory and certain game theoretic models such as [[Bertrand competition]].

== Indicators ==
Practices that suggest collusion include:

* [[Price fixing|Uniform prices]]
* A penalty for price discounts
* Advance notice of price changes
* Information exchange

== Examples ==
Collusion is largely illegal in the [[United States]], [[Canada]] and most of the [[EU]] due to [[competition law|competition/antitrust]] law, but implicit collusion in the form of [[price leadership]] and tacit understandings still takes place. Several examples of collusion in the United States include:

* Market division and price-fixing among manufacturers of heavy [[electricity|electrical]] equipment in the 1960s, including [[General Electric]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
| title = Encyclopedia of white-collar &amp; corporate crime
| url = http://books.google.com/books?id=0f7yTNb_V3QC&amp;pg=PA377&amp;lpg=PA377&amp;dq=market+division+collusion+heavy+electrical+equipment++1960}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* An attempt by [[Major League Baseball]] owners to [[Baseball collusion|restrict players' salaries]] in the mid-1980s.
* The sharing of potential contract terms by NBA free agents in an effort to help a targeted franchise circumvent the salary cap
* Price fixing within [[food]] manufacturers providing cafeteria food to [[school]]s and the [[military]] in 1993.
* Market division and output determination of livestock feed additive, called [[lysine]], by companies in the US, [[Japan]] and [[South Korea]] in 1996, [[Archer Daniels Midland]] being the most notable of these.&lt;ref&gt;Hunter-Gault, Charlayne (October 15, 1996). &quot;ADM: Who's Next?&quot;. MacNeil/Lehrer Newshour (PBS). http://www.pbs.org/newshour/bb/business/october96/adm_10-15.html. Retrieved on 2007-10-17.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Glossary_of_poker_terms#C|Chip dumping]] in [[poker]] or any other high stake card game.

There are many ways that implicit collusion tends to develop:

* The practice of stock analyst conference calls and meetings of industry participants almost necessarily results in tremendous amounts of strategic and price transparency. This allows each firm to see how and why every other firm is pricing their products.
* If the practice of the industry causes more complicated pricing, which is hard for the consumer to understand (such as [[risk-based pricing]], hidden taxes and fees in the wireless industry, negotiable pricing), this can cause competition based on price to be meaningless (because it would be too complicated to explain to the customer in a short advertisement). This causes industries to have essentially the same prices and compete on advertising and image, something theoretically as damaging to consumers as normal price fixing.{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}}

== Barriers ==
There can be significant barriers to collusion. In any given industry, these may include:

* The number of firms: As the number of firms in an [[industry]] increases, it is more difficult to successfully organize, collude and communicate.
* Cost and demand differences between firms: If costs vary significantly between firms, it may be impossible to establish a price at which to fix output.
* Cheating: There is considerable incentive to cheat on collusion agreements; although lowering prices might trigger [[price wars]], in the short term the defecting firm may gain considerably. This phenomenon is frequently referred to as &quot;chiseling&quot;.
* Potential entry: New firms may enter the industry, establishing a new baseline price and eliminating collusion (though anti-dumping laws and tariffs can prevent foreign companies entering the market).
* Economic recession: An increase in average total cost or a decrease in revenue provides incentive to compete with rival firms in order to secure a larger market share and increased demand.

==See also==
* [[Collusive lawsuit]]
* [[Conscious parallelism]]
* [[Corporate crime]]
* [[Baseball collusion]]

== References ==
&lt;references/&gt;

* Vives, X. (1999) ''Oligopoly pricing'', MIT Press, Cambridge MA (readable; suitable for advanced undergraduates.)
*[[Jean Tirole|Tirole, J.]] (1988) ''The Theory of Industrial Organization'', MIT Press, Cambridge MA  (An organized introduction to industrial organization)
*[[Jean Tirole|Tirole, J.]] (1986), &quot;Hierarchies and Bureaucracies&quot;, Journal of Law Economics and Organization, vol. 2, pp.&amp;nbsp;181–214.
*[[Jean Tirole|Tirole, J.]] (1992), &quot;Collusion and the Theory of Organizations&quot;, Advances in Economic Theory: Proceedings of the Sixth World Congress of the Econometric Society, ed by J.-J. Laffont. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, vol.2:151-206.

{{game theory}}

[[Category:Anti-competitive behaviour]]
[[Category:Game theory]]

[[ca:Col·lusió]]
[[de:Kollusion (Recht)]]
[[es:Colusión]]
[[eu:Kolusio]]
[[fa:تبانی]]
[[fr:Entente illicite]]
[[id:Kolusi]]
[[it:Collusione]]
[[nl:Samenspel (economie)]]
[[pt:Conluio]]
[[simple:Collusion]]
[[tr:Muvazaa]]</text>
      <sha1>3i3m7xxcvmtmj3l9pt8ryvv57ybcs3a</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
