<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Competition</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>181592</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522089829</id>
      <parentid>521017129</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T00:04:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Widefox</username>
        <id>1588193</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>fix link away from DAB page</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="33405">{{Other uses}}
{{Globalize|date=August 2008}}
[[File:Athletics competitions.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Competition in sports. A selection of images showing some of the sporting events that are classed as athletics competitions.]]

'''Competition''' in [[biology]], [[ecology]], and [[sociology]], is a [[contest (disambiguation)|contest]] between organisms, animals, individuals, groups, etc., for [[territory (animal)|territory]], a niche, or a location of [[resources]], for resources and goods, for [[:wikt:prestige|prestige]], [[Recognition (sociology)|recognition]], [[award]]s, mates, or group or social status, for leadership; it is the opposite of [[cooperation]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/129779/competition competition], [[Encyclopædia Britannica Online]] edition. Retrieved March 6, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sociologyguide.com/basic-concepts/Competition.php Competition], Sociology guide&lt;/ref&gt; It arises whenever at least two parties strive for a goal which cannot be shared or which is desired individually but not in sharing and cooperation. Competition occurs [[nature|naturally]] between living organisms which co-exist in the same [[Natural environment|environment]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Keddy, P.A 2001&quot;&gt;Keddy, P.A. 2001.

 Competition (2 nd edition) Kluwer, Dordrecht. 552 p.&lt;/ref&gt; For example, animals compete over water supplies, food, mates, and other [[biological resources]]. Humans compete usually for food and mates, though when these needs are met deep rivalries often arise over the pursuit of [[wealth]], prestige, and [[celebrity|fame]]. Competition is also a major tenet in [[market economy]] and business is often associated with competition as most companies are in competition with at least one other firm over the same group of customers, and also competition inside a company is usually stimulated for meeting and reaching higher quality of services or products that the company produce or develop. A competition or trade promotion lottery, is also the equivalent of [[sweepstakes]] in some countries.

== Consequences ==
Competition can have both beneficial and detrimental effects. Many evolutionary biologists view inter-species and intra-species competition as the driving force of [[adaptation]], and ultimately of [[evolution]]. However, some biologists, most famously [[Richard Dawkins]], prefer to think of evolution in terms of competition between single genes, which have the welfare of the organism 'in mind' only insofar as that welfare furthers their own selfish drives for replication. Some [[social darwinist]]s claim that competition also serves as a mechanism for determining the best-suited group; politically, economically and ecologically. Positively, competition may serve as a form of [[recreation]] or a challenge provided that it is non-hostile. On the negative side, competition can cause injury and loss to the organisms involved, and drain valuable resources and energy. In the human species competition can be expensive on many levels, not only in lives lost to war, physical injuries, and damaged psychological well beings, but also in the health effects from everyday civilian life caused by work stress, long work hours, abusive working relationships, and poor working conditions, that detract from the enjoyment of life, even as such competition results in financial gain for the owners.

==Economics and business==
{{Main|Competition (economics)}}

Merriam-Webster defines competition in business as &quot;the effort of two or more parties acting independently to secure the business of a third party by offering the most favorable terms&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://m-w.com/dictionary/competition m-w.com]&lt;/ref&gt;  It was described by [[Adam Smith]] in ''[[The Wealth of Nations]]'' (1776) and later economists as allocating productive [[resources]] to their most highly-valued uses.&lt;ref&gt;[[George J. Stigler]] ([[The New Palgrave: A Dictionary of Economics|[1987]]] 2008). &quot;competition,&quot; ''[[The New Palgrave Dictionary of Economics]]''. [http://www.dictionaryofeconomics.com/article?id=pde2008_C000261&amp;q=competition&amp;topicid=&amp;result_number=6 Abstract.]&lt;/ref&gt; and encouraging [[x-efficiency|efficiency]]. Later [[microeconomic theory]] distinguished between [[perfect competition]] and [[imperfect competition]], concluding that no system of resource allocation is more efficient than [[perfect competition]]. Competition, according to the theory, causes commercial firms to develop new products, services and technologies, which would give consumers greater selection and better products. The greater selection typically causes lower prices for the products, compared to what the price would be if there was no competition ([[monopoly]]) or little competition ([[oligopoly]]).

However, competition may also lead to wasted (duplicated) effort and to increased [[cost]]s (and prices) in some circumstances. For example, the intense competition for the small number of [[Superstar (celebrity)|top jobs in music and movie acting]] leads many aspiring musicians and actors to make substantial investments in training which are not recouped, because only a fraction become successful.  Critics have also argued that competition can be destabilizing, particularly competition between certain financial institutions.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Simkovic, [http://ssrn.com/abstract=1924831 ''Competition and Crisis in Mortgage Securitization'']&lt;/ref&gt; 

Experts have also questioned the constructiveness of competition in profitability. It has been argued that competition-oriented objectives are counterproductive to raising revenues and profitability because they limit the options of strategies for firms as well as their ability to offer innovative responses to changes in the market.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://marketing.wharton.upenn.edu/documents/research/CompOrientPDF%2011-27%20%282%29.pdf | title = The Profitability of Winning | author = J. Scott Armstrong and Fred Collopy | journal = Chief Executive | pages = 61–63 | year = 1994}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, the strong desire to defeat rival firms with competitive prices has the strong possibility of causing price wars.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://qbox.wharton.upenn.edu/documents/mktg/research/Profitability%20of%20winning.pdf | title = Competitor-oriented Objectives: The Myth of Market Share | author = J. Scott Armstrong and Kesten C. Greene | journal = International Journal of Business | volume = 12 | issue = 1 | pages = 116–134 | year = 2007 | ISSN= 1083-4346}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Three levels of economic competition have been classified:

* The most narrow form is '''direct competition''' (also called category competition or brand competition), where [[product (business)|product]]s which perform the same function compete against each other. For example, one brand of pick-up trucks competes with several other brands of pick-up trucks. Sometimes, two companies are rivals and one adds new products to their line, which leads to the other company distributing the same new things, and in this manner they compete.

* The next form is '''substitute''' or '''indirect competition''', where products which are close substitutes for one another compete. For example, butter competes with margarine, mayonnaise and other various sauces and spreads.

* The broadest form of competition is typically called '''budget competition'''. Included in this category is anything on which the [[consumer]] might want to spend their available [[income|money]]. For example, a family which has $20,000 available may choose to spend it on many different items, which can all be seen as competing with each other for the family's expenditure. This form of competition is also sometimes described as a competition of &quot;share of wallet&quot;.

In addition, companies also compete for [[financing]] on the capital markets (equity or debt) in order to generate the necessary cash for their operations. An [[investor]] typically will consider alternative investment opportunities given his risk profile and not only look at companies just competing on product ('''direct competitors'''). Enlarging the investment universe to include '''indirect competitors''' leads to a broader [[peer universe]] of comparable, indirectly competing companies.

Competition does not necessarily have to be between companies. For example, business writers sometimes refer to '''internal competition'''. This is competition within companies. The idea was first introduced by [[Alfred Sloan]] at [[General Motors Corporation|General Motors]] in the 1920s. Sloan deliberately created areas of overlap between divisions of the company so that each division would be competing with the other divisions. For example, the [[Chevy]] division would compete with the [[Pontiac]] division for some [[market segment]]s. The competing brands by the same company allowed partes tobe designed by one division and shared by several divisions, for example parts designed by Chevy would also be used by pontiac. Also, in 1931, [[Procter &amp; Gamble]] initiated a deliberate system of internal brand-versus-brand rivalry. The company was organized around different [[brand]]s, with each brand allocated resources, including a dedicated group of employees willing to champion the brand. Each brand manager was given responsibility for the success or failure of the brand, and compensated accordingly. This is known as '''intra-brand competition'''.

Finally, most businesses also encourage competition between individual employees. An example of this is a contest between sales representatives. The sales representative with the highest sales (or the best improvement in sales) over a period of time would gain benefits from the employer.

Shalev and Asbjornsen also found that success (i.e. the saving resulted) of [[reverse auction]]s correlated most closely with competition. The literature widely supported the importance of competition as the primary driver of reverse auctions success.&lt;ref&gt;[http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1727409 papers.ssrn.com]&lt;/ref&gt; Their findings appear to support that argument, as competition correlated strongly with the reverse auction success, as well as with the number of bidders.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.scribd.com/doc/39032383/Electronic-Reverse-Auction-and-the-Public-Sector-Factors-of-Success-Moshe-E-Shalev-Stee-Asbjorensen |publisher= Shalev Moshe and Asbjornsen Stee |title=Electronic revers auctions and the public sector - Factors of success |work=Journal of Public Procurement |volume10(3) |pages=428–452 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

It should also be noted that business and economic competition in most [[country|countries]] is often limited or restricted. Competition often is subject to legal restrictions. For example, competition may be legally prohibited, as in the case with a [[government monopoly]] or a [[government-granted monopoly]]. [[Tariffs]], [[subsidies]] or other [[protectionist]] measures may also be instituted by government in order to prevent or reduce competition. Depending on the respective economic policy, pure competition is to a greater or lesser extent regulated by [[competition policy]] and [[competition law]].  Another component of these activities is the discovery process, with instances of higher [[government regulation]]s typically leading to less competitive businesses being launched.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cato.org/pub_display.php?pub_id=884&amp;full=1 Competition, Regulation, and the Market Process: An &quot;Austrian&quot; Perspective, Sept. 30, 1982] by [[Israel M. Kirzner]]&lt;/ref&gt;

Competition between countries is quite subtle to detect, but is quite evident in the [[world economy]]. Countries compete to provide the best possible business environment for [[multinational corporations]]. Such competition is evident by the policies undertaken by these countries to educate the future workforce. For example, East Asian economies such as Singapore, Japan and South Korea tend to emphasize education by allocating a large portion of the budget to this sector, and by implementing programmes such as [[gifted education]].

==Law==
{{Main|Competition law}}
[[File:Usdepartmentofjustice.jpg|thumb|right|The [[United States Department of Justice|Department of Justice]] building in [[Washington, D.C.]] is home to the influential [[United States antitrust law|antitrust]] enforcers of U.S. competition laws]]
Competition [[law]], known in the [[United States]] as antitrust law, has three main functions. First it prohibits agreements aimed to restrict free trading between business entities and their customers. For example, a [[cartel]] of sports shops who together fix football jersey prices higher than normal is illegal.&lt;ref&gt;''JJB Sports v OFT [2004] CAT 17''&lt;/ref&gt; Second competition law can ban the existence or abusive behaviour of a firm dominating the market. One case in point could be a software company who through its [[monopoly]] on computer platforms makes consumers use its media player.&lt;ref&gt;in the E.U. side of the saga, see [http://europa.eu.int/jurisp/cgi-bin/gettext.pl?lang=en&amp;num=79958777T1904%20R0201_2&amp;doc=T&amp;ouvert=T&amp;seance=ORD&amp;where=() Case T-201/04] ''Microsoft v. Commission'' Order, 22 December 2004&lt;/ref&gt; Third to preserve competitive markets, the law supervises the [[mergers and acquisitions]] of very large corporations. Competition authorities could for instance require that a large packaging company give plastic bottle [[license]]s to competitors before taking over a major [[Polyethylene terephthalate|PET]] producer.&lt;ref&gt;Case C-12/03 P, Commission v. Tetra Laval&lt;/ref&gt; In this case (as in all three), competition law aims to protect the [[consumer welfare|welfare of consumers]] by ensuring business must compete for its share of the [[market economy]].

In recent decades, competition law has also been sold as good medicine to provide better [[public services]], traditionally funded by [[tax]] payers and administered by [[Democracy|democratically]] accountable [[government]]s. Hence competition law is closely connected with the law on deregulation of access to markets, providing state aids and subsidies, the [[privatisation]] of state-owned assets and the use of independent sector regulators, such as the United Kingdom telecommunications watchdog [[Ofcom]]. Behind the practice lies the theory, which over the last fifty years has been dominated by [[neo-classical economics]]. Markets are seen as the most efficient method of allocating resources, although sometimes [[market failure|they fail]], and regulation becomes necessary to protect the ideal market model. Behind the theory lies the history, reaching back further than the [[Roman Empire]]. The business practices of market traders, [[guilds]] and governments have always been subject to scrutiny and sometimes severe sanctions. Since the twentieth century, competition law has become global. The two largest, most organised and influential systems of competition regulation are [[United States antitrust law]] and [[European Community competition law]]. The respective national authorities, the [[U.S. Department of Justice]] (DOJ) and the [[Federal Trade Commission]] (FTC) in the United States and the [[Directorate-General for Competition (European Commission)|European Commission's Competition Directorate General]] (DGCOMP) have formed international support and enforcement networks. Competition law is growing in importance every day, which warrants for its careful study.

== Politics ==

Competition is also found in [[politics]]. In [[democracy|democracies]], an [[election]] is a competition for an elected office. In other words, two or more candidates strive and compete against one another to attain a position of power. The winner gains the seat of the elected office for a predefined period of time, towards the end of which another election is usually held to determine the next holder of the office.

In addition, there is inevitable competition inside a government. Because several offices are appointed, potential candidates compete against the others in order to gain the particular office. Departments may also compete for a limited amount of resources, such as for [[budget|funding]]. Finally, where there are [[party systems]], elected leaders of different parties will ultimately compete against the other parties for [[law]]s, [[funding]] and [[political power|power]].

Finally, competition also exists between [[government]]s. Each [[country]] or [[nationality]] struggles for world dominance, power, or [[military]] strength. For example, the [[United States]] competed against the [[Soviet Union]] in the [[Cold War]] for world power, and the two also struggled over the different types of government (in these cases [[representative democracy]] and [[communism]]). The result of this type of competition often leads to worldwide tensions, and may sometimes erupt into [[war]]fare.

== Competitive sports ==&lt;!--Important: DO NOT CHANGE. There are redirects that lead to this heading. See [[Help:Link#Section linking (anchors)]].--&gt;
{{Main|Sport}}
[[File:US Olympic Committee Headquarters by David Shankbone.jpg|thumb|The [[USOC]]'s headquarters in [[Colorado Springs, Colorado]].  The [[Olympic Games]] are regarded as the international pinnacle of sports competition.]]
While some sports (such as [[fishing]] or [[hiking]]) have been viewed as primarily recreational, most sports are considered competitive. The majority involve competition between two or more persons (sometimes using [[horse racing|horses]] or [[auto racing|cars]]). For example, in a game of [[basketball]], two teams compete against one another to determine who can score the most points. When there is no set reward for the winning team, many players gain a sense of [[pride]]. In addition, extrinsic rewards may also be given. Athletes, besides competing against other humans, also compete against [[nature]] in sports such as [[whitewater kayaking]] or [[mountaineering]], where the goal is to reach a destination, with only natural barriers impeding the process. A regularly scheduled (for instance annual) competition meant to determine the &quot;best&quot; competitor of that cycle is called a [[championship]].
[[File:Citi Field Day.jpg|thumb|left|[[Baseball]] is a competitive sport.]]
Professional sports, as well as the business of it, are intense and extremely competitive, while recreational sports are often less intense and found enjoyable by many, as well as cathartic. Yet psychological evidence has been found that the more aggressive sports result in increased aggressive behavior when the sport is not being played. For those attaining winning status, endorphins are released, often driving them, and in extreme cases, addicting them to increased levels of competition, dedication, and enjoyment of the sport. In the case of sports viewers, participating artificially, similar evidence was found. Mostly in professional sports rivals, there may be half of the home team's fans and half of the visiting team's fans viceversa during the rivalry games.

Competitive sports are governed by codified rules agreed upon by the participants. Violating these rules is considered to be unfair competition. Thus, sports provide artificial (not natural) competition; for example, competing for control of a ball, or defending territory on a playing field is not an innate biological factor in humans. Athletes in sports such as [[gymnastics]] and competitive [[diving]] compete against each other in order to come closest to a conceptual ideal of a perfect performance, which incorporates measurable criteria and standards which are translated into numerical ratings and scores by appointed judges.

Sports competition is generally broken down into three categories: '''individual''' sports, such as [[archery]]; '''dual''' sports, such as [[tennis|doubles tennis]], and '''team''' sports competition, such as [[cricket]] or [[football]]. While most sports competitions are recreation, there exist several [[major]] and [[minor league|minor]] professional sports leagues throughout the world. The [[Olympic Games]], held every four years, is usually regarded as the international pinnacle of sports competition.

== Education ==
Competition is a major factor in education. On a global scale, national education systems, intending to bring out the best in the next generation, encourage competitiveness among students through [[scholarships]]. Countries such as England and Singapore have [[special education]] programmes which cater for specialist students, prompting charges of [[academic elitism]]. Upon receipt of their academic results, students tend to compare their grades to see who is better. In severe cases, the pressure to perform in some countries is so high that it can result in stigmatization of intellectually deficient students, or even suicide as a consequence of failing the exams; Japan being a prime example (see [[Education in Japan]]). This has resulted in critical re-evaluation of examinations as a whole by educationalists {{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}. Critics of competition (as opposed to [[excellence]]) as a motivating factor in education systems, such as [[Alfie Kohn]], assert that competition actually has a net negative influence on the achievement levels of students, and that it &quot;turns all of us into losers&quot; (Kohn 1986). Economist [[Richard Layard]] has commented on the harmful effects, stating &quot;people feel that they are under a great deal of pressure. They feel that their main objective in life is to do better than other
people. That is certainly what young people are being taught in school every day. And it's not a good basis for a society.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-13052639 ''Group dedicated to happiness launched in UK'', BBC video, April 12, 2011]&lt;/ref&gt;

Competitions also make up a large portion of [[extracurricular]] activities in which students participate. Such competitions include [[TVOntario|TVO]]'s broadcast [[Reach for the Top]] competition, [[FIRST]] Robotics, [[Duke Annual Robo-Climb Competition (DARC)]] and the [[University of Toronto Space Design Contest]]. In Texas, the [[University Interscholastic League]] (UIL) has 22 High School-level contests and 18 elementary and Junior High in subjects ranging from accounting to science to ready writing.

== Literature ==
Literary competitions, such as contests sponsored by [[literary journals]], publishing houses and theaters, have increasingly become a means for aspiring writers to gain recognition.  Prestigious awards for fiction include those sponsored by the [[Missouri Review]], [[Boston Review]], [[Indiana Review]], [[North American Review]] and [[Southwest Review]].  The [[Edward Albee|Albee]] Award, sponsored by the Yale Drama Series, is among the most prestigious playwriting awards.  Some American writers, such as [[Gina Ochsner]] and [[Jacob M. Appel|Jacob Appel]], have gained prominence specifically for their active participation in numerous literary competitions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://literaryrejectionsondisplay.blogspot.com/2009/06/bug-off-gina-oschner-jacob-appel.html  Bug Off], June 16, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

Charging fees for literary competitions is extremely controversial.  Some writers view fees as a form of exploitation that takes advantage of aspiring authors and playwrights.  However, fee-based contests also have strong supporters who argue that these competitions offer rare opportunities for young writers to have their voices heard at a time when access to major agents and editors has grown increasingly limited.&lt;ref&gt;Appel, Jacob.  ''The Case for Contests'' Poets &amp; Writers, Jan/Feb 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Consumer competitions ==
In Australia, New Zealand and the United Kingdom, competitions or lottos are the equivalent of what are commonly known as [[sweepstakes]] in the United States. The correct technical name for Australian consumer competitions is a trade promotion lottery or lottos. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.olgr.nsw.gov.au/promos_trade_promos.asp&lt;/ref&gt;

Competition or trade promotion lottery entrants enter to win a prize or prizes, hence many entrants are all in competition, or competing for a limited number of prizes.

A trade promotion lottery or competition is a free entry lottery run to promote goods or services supplied by a business. An example is where you purchase goods or services and then given the chance to enter into the lottery and possibly win a prize. A trade promotion lottery can be called a lotto, competition, contest, sweepstake, or giveaway.

People that enjoy entering competitions are known as compers. Many compers attend annual national conventions. In 2012 over 100 people from around Australia met on the Gold Coast, Queensland to discuss competitions.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lottos.com.au/competitions/viewthreadlite.php?tid=275933&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://aca.ninemsn.com.au/article.aspx?id=8536705&lt;/ref&gt;

== Biology and ecology ==
&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Natural selection]] --&gt;
{{Main|Competition (biology)}}
Competition within, between, and among species is one of the most important forces in biology, especially in the field of [[ecology]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Keddy, P.A 2001&quot;/&gt; Competition between members of a species (&quot;intraspecific&quot;) for resources such as [[food]], [[water]], [[Territory (animal)|territory]], and [[sunlight]] may result in an increase in the frequency of a variant of the species best suited for survival and reproduction until its fixation within a population. Competition is also present between species (&quot;interspecific&quot;). When resources are limited, several species may depend on these resources. Thus, each of the species competes with the others to gain access to the resources. As a result, species less suited to compete for the resources may [[extinction|die out]] unless they [[adaptation|adapt]] by character dislocation, for instance. According to [[evolutionary theory]], this competition within and between species for resources plays a significant role in [[natural selection]]. At shorter time scales, competition is also one of the most important factors controlling diversity in ecological communities, particularly in plant communities where asymmetric competition and competitive dominance frequently occur.&lt;ref name=&quot;Keddy, P.A 2001&quot;/&gt;

==The study of competition==
Competition has been studied in several fields, including [[psychology]], [[sociology]] and [[anthropology]]. Social [[psychologist]]s, for instance, study the nature of competition. They investigate the natural urge of competition and its circumstances. They also study [[group dynamics]], to detect how competition emerges and what its effects are. [[Sociologist]]s, meanwhile, study the effects of competition on society as a whole. In addition, [[anthropologist]]s study the history and prehistory of competition in various cultures. They also investigate how competition manifested itself in various [[culture|cultural]] settings in the past, and how competition has developed over time.

==Competitiveness==
{{Main|Competitiveness}}
Many [[philosopher]]s and [[psychologist]]s have identified a trait in most living organisms which can drive the particular organism to compete. This trait, unsurprisingly called competitiveness, is viewed as an innate [[biology|biological]] [[Trait (biological)|trait]] which coexists along with the urge for survival. Competitiveness, or the inclination to compete, though, has become synonymous with aggressiveness and ambition in the [[English language]]. More advanced [[civilization]]s integrate aggressiveness and competitiveness into their [[Social interaction|interactions]], as a way to distribute resources and adapt. Most plants compete for higher spots on trees to receive more sunlight.

However, [[Stephen Jay Gould]] and others have argued that as one ascends the evolutionary hierarchy, competitiveness (the survival instinct) becomes less innate, and more a learned behavior.{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}} The same could be said for co-operation: in humans, at least, both co-operation and competition are considered learned behaviors, because the human species learns to adapt to environmental pressures. Consequently, if survival requires competitive behaviors, the individual will compete, and if survival requires co-operative behaviors, the individual will co-operate. In the case of humans, therefore, aggressiveness may be an innate characteristic, but a person need not be competitive at the same time, for instance when scaling a cliff. On the other hand, humans seem also to have a nurturing instinct, to protect newborns and the weak. While that does not necessitate co-operative behavior, it does help.

The term also applies to [[econometrics]]. Here, it is a comparative measure of the ability and performance of a firm or sub-sector to sell and produce/supply goods and/or services in a given market. The two academic bodies of thought on the assessment of competitiveness are the '''Structure Conduct Performance Paradigm''' and the more contemporary '''New Empirical Industrial Organisation''' model. Predicting changes in the competitiveness of business sectors is becoming an integral and explicit step in public policymaking. Within capitalist economic systems, the drive of enterprises is to maintain and improve their own competitiveness.

=== Hypercompetitiveness ===
The tendency toward extreme, unhealthy competition has been termed '''hypercompetitiveness'''. This concept originated in [[Karen Horney]]'s theories on [[neurosis]]; specifically, the highly aggressive personality type which is characterized as &quot;moving against people&quot;. In her view, some people have a need to compete and win at all costs as a means of maintaining their [[self-esteem|self-worth]]. These individuals are likely to turn any activity into a competition, and they will feel threatened if they find themselves losing. Researchers have found that men and women who score high on the trait of hypercompetitiveness are more [[Narcissism|narcissistic]] and less psychologically healthy than those who score low on the trait.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Ryckman, R. M., Thornton, B., Butler, J. C. |year=1994 |title= Personality correlates of the hypercompetitive attitude scale: Validity tests of Horney's theory of neurosis |work=[[Journal of Personality Assessment]] |volume=62 |pages=84–94 |url=http://www.leaonline.com/doi/abs/10.1207/s15327752jpa6201_8?cookieSet=1&amp;journalCode=jpa |doi=10.1207/s15327752jpa6201 8}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Hypercompetitive individuals generally believe that &quot;[[winning isn't everything; it's the only thing]]&quot;.

==Criticisms==

===Marxist ethics ===
Marx insisted that &quot;the capitalist system fosters competition and egoism in all its members and thoroughly undermines all genuine forms of community&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;allenb&quot;&gt;Allen E. Buchanan, ''[http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=j1AOAAAAQAAJ&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;hl=bg&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Marx and justice: the radical critique of liberalism]'', [[Taylor &amp; Francis]], 1982&lt;/ref&gt; It is created such &quot;climate of competitive egoism and individualism&quot; with competition going in the two ways of competition for jobs and competition between employees, Marx even said competition between workers is bigger than of the company owners.&lt;ref name=&quot;allenb&quot;/&gt; He also points out that competition separates individuals from one another and while concentration of workers and development of better communication alleviate this, they are not a decision.&lt;ref name=&quot;allenb&quot;/&gt;

===Gandhi===
Gandhi also speaks of egoistic competition.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gandhi&quot;&gt;Parmeshwari Dayal, [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=FemHmw5fGQUC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;hl=bg&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Gandhian Theory of Social Reconstruction], Atlantic Publishers &amp; Dist, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; For him, when such qualities are glorified and/or left unbridled, it would lead to violence, conflict, discord and destructiveness. For Ghandhi, competition comes from the ego, and therefore society must be based on mutual love, cooperation and sacrifice for the well-being of humanity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gandhi&quot;/&gt; In the society desired by Gandhi, each individual will cooperate and serve for the welfare of others and people will share each other's joys, sorrows and achievements as a norm of a social life. For him, in a non-violent society, competition does not have a place and this should become realized with more people making the personal choice to have less tendencies toward egoism and selfishness.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gandhi&quot;/&gt;

== See also ==
{{Wiktionary|competition|competitor}}
{{Wikiquote}}
* [[Biological interaction]]
* [[Competition regulator]]
* [[Competitor analysis]]
* [[Conflict of interest]]
* [[Cooperation]]
* [[Cooperative]]
* [[Ecological model of competition]]
* [[Monopolistic competition]]
* [[Planned economy]]
* [[Sharing]]
* [[Zero-profit condition]]
* [[Zero-sum]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Competition]]
[[Category:Social events]]

[[ar:منافسة]]
[[az:Rəqabət]]
[[bn:প্রতিযোগিতা]]
[[cs:Soutěž]]
[[de:Wettkampf]]
[[et:Võistlus]]
[[ko:경쟁]]
[[hy:Մրցակցություն]]
[[hi:प्रतियोगिता]]
[[id:Kompetisi]]
[[is:Samkeppni]]
[[it:Competizione]]
[[he:תחרות]]
[[nl:Competitie]]
[[ja:コンクール]]
[[ru:Соревнование]]
[[simple:Competition]]
[[fi:Kilpailu]]
[[sv:Tävling]]
[[tl:Paligsahan]]
[[ta:போட்டி]]
[[th:การแข่งขัน]]
[[tr:Rekabet]]
[[uk:Змагання]]
[[yi:קאנקורענץ]]
[[zh:竞争]]</text>
      <sha1>40qhraaanhovmj7nifw80uve9qucw8o</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
