<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Cooperative</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>89313</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520806830</id>
      <parentid>520650504</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-31T21:40:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>65.207.11.228</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Social economy */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="48541">:''&quot;Coop&quot; redirects here. For other uses, see [[Coop (disambiguation)]].''
A '''cooperative''' (&quot;coop&quot;), '''co-operative''' (&quot;co-op&quot;), or '''coöperative''' (&quot;coöp&quot;) is an autonomous association of persons who [[voluntary association|voluntarily]] cooperate for their mutual social, economic, and cultural benefit.&lt;ref name=&quot;ica-principles&quot;&gt;[http://www.ica.coop/coop/principles.html Statement on the Cooperative Identity.] ''[[International Cooperative Alliance]].''&lt;/ref&gt; Cooperatives include non-profit community organizations and businesses that are owned and managed by the people who use its services (a consumer cooperative) and/or by the people who work there (a worker cooperative) or by the people who live there (a housing cooperative).

[[Image:OSGCo-opAGM20050423 CopyrightKaihsuTai.jpg|thumb|The volunteer board of a retail [[consumers' cooperative]], such as the former [[Oxford, Swindon &amp; Gloucester Co-operative Society|Oxford, Swindon &amp; Gloucester Co-op]], is held to account at an Annual General Meeting of members]]
[[Image:Co-op City Hutch River.jpg|thumb|[[Co-op City, Bronx|Co-op City]] in New York is the largest cooperative housing development in the world with 55,000 people.&lt;ref name=&quot;Urban Mass: A Look at Co-op City&quot;&gt;Whitsett, Ross. [http://cooperator.com/articles/1354/1/Urban-Mass/Page1.html Urban Mass: A Look at Co-op City.] ''[[The Cooperator]]''. December 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;]]

==Origins==
{{Main|History of the cooperative movement}}
Cooperation dates back as far as human beings have been organizing for mutual benefit. Tribes were organized as cooperative structures, allocating jobs and resources among each other, only trading with the external communities. In alpine environments, trade could only be maintained in organized cooperatives to achieve a useful condition of artificial roads such as [[Viamala]] in 1472.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hohenraetien.ch/HR-Web-2008/web-content/HR-08-Materialien/Viamala_Brief_vollstText.pdf |title=1473 letter of intent to build a road, in (old) german |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pre-industrial Europe is home to the first cooperatives from an industrial context.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

[[File:Portrait of Robert Owen (1771 - 1858) by John Cranch, 1845.jpg|thumb|right|[[Robert Owen]] (1771 - 1858) was a social reformer and a pioneer of the cooperative movement.]]
In 1761, the [[Fenwick Weavers' Society]] was formed in [[Fenwick, East Ayrshire|Fenwick]], [[East Ayrshire]], [[Scotland]] to sell [[discounts and allowances|discount]]ed [[oatmeal]] to local workers.&lt;ref&gt;Carrell, Severin. [http://www.guardian.co.uk/business/2007/aug/07/retail.uknews Strike Rochdale from the record books. The Co-op began in Scotland.], ''[[The Guardian]]'', 7 August 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Its services expanded to include assistance with savings and loans, emigration and education. In 1810, [[Welsh people|Welsh]] [[social reform]]er [[Robert Owen]], from Newtown in mid-[[Wales]], and his partners purchased [[New Lanark]] mill from Owen's father-in-law [[David Dale]] and proceeded to introduce better labour standards including discounted retail shops where profits were passed on to his employees. Owen left New Lanark to pursue other forms of cooperative organization and develop co-op ideas through writing and lecture. Cooperative communities were set up in [[Glasgow]], [[Indiana]] and [[Hampshire]], although ultimately unsuccessful. In 1828, [[William King (doctor)|William King]] set up a newspaper, ''The Cooperator'', to promote Owen's thinking, having already set up a co-operative store in Brighton.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

The [[Rochdale Pioneers|Rochdale Society of Equitable Pioneers]], founded in 1844, is usually considered the first successful cooperative enterprise, used as a model for modern co-ops, following the '[[Rochdale Principles]]'. A group of 28 weavers and other artisans in [[Rochdale]], England set up the society to open their own store selling food items they could not otherwise afford. Within ten years there were over 1,000 cooperative societies in the United Kingdom.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

Other events such as the founding of a [[friendly society]] by the [[Tolpuddle Martyrs]] in 1832 were key occasions in the creation of organized labor and consumer movements.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

==Social economy==
In the final year of the 20th century, cooperatives banded together to establish a number of [[social enterprise]] agencies which have moved to adopt the multi-stakeholder cooperative model.&lt;ref name = &quot;RidleyDuff&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Brown, J. (2006), “Designing Equity Finance for Social Enterprises”, ''Social Enterprise Journal'', 2(1): 73 81.&lt;/ref&gt;  Since 1994 the [[EU]] and its member nations, have gradually revised national accounting systems to &quot;make visible&quot; the increasing contribution of [[social economy]] organizations.&lt;ref&gt;Monzon, J. L. &amp; Chaves, R. (2008) “The European Social Economy: Concept and Dimensions of the Third Sector”, ''Annals of Public and Cooperative Economics'', 79(3/4): 549-577.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Organizational and ideological roots==
The roots of the cooperative movement can be traced to multiple influences and extend worldwide. In the [[Anglosphere]], post-[[feudal]] forms of cooperation between workers and owners, that are expressed today as &quot;profit-sharing&quot; and &quot;surplus sharing&quot; arrangements, existed as far back as 1795.&lt;ref&gt;Gates, J. (1998) ''The Ownership Solution'', London: Penguin.&lt;/ref&gt;  The key ideological influence on the Anglosphere branch of the cooperative movement, however, was a ''rejection'' of the [[charity (practice)|charity]] principles that underpinned [[welfare]] reforms when the [[British government]] radically revised its [[Poor Laws]] in 1834. As both state and church institutions began to routinely distinguish between the 'deserving' and 'undeserving' poor, a movement of [[friendly society|friendly societies]] grew throughout the [[British Empire]] based on the principle of mutuality, committed to self-help in the welfare of working people.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

Friendly Societies established forums through which [[one member, one vote]] was practiced in organisation decision-making. The principles challenged the idea that a person should be an owner of [[property]] before being granted a political voice.&lt;ref name=&quot;RidleyDuff&quot;&gt;[http://www3.interscience.wiley.com/journal/117967289/abstract Ridley-Duff, R. J. (2007) “Communitarian Perspectives on Social Enterprise”, ''Corporate Governance: An International Review'', 15(2):382-392].&lt;/ref&gt; Throughout the second half of the nineteenth century (and then repeatedly every 20 years or so) there has been a surge in the number of cooperative organisations, both in commercial practice and civil society, operating to advance [[democracy]] and [[universal suffrage]] as a political principle.&lt;ref&gt;Rothschild, J., Allen-Whitt, J. (1986) ''The Cooperative Workplace'', Cambridge University Press&lt;/ref&gt; Friendly Societies and consumer cooperatives became the dominant form of organization amongst working people in Anglosphere [[industrial societies]] prior to the rise of [[trade unions]] and industrial factories. Weinbren reports that by the end of the 19th century, over 80% of British working age men and 90% of Australian working age men were members of one or more Friendly Society.&lt;ref name=&quot;Weinbren&quot;&gt;[http://www.historycooperative.org/journals/lab/88/weinbren.html Weinbren, D. &amp; James, B. (2005) “Getting a Grip: the Roles of Friendly Societies in Australia and Britain Reappraised”, Labour History, Vol. 88].&lt;/ref&gt;

From the mid-nineteenth century, [[mutual organisation]]s embraced these ideas in economic enterprises, firstly amongst tradespeople, and later in cooperative stores, educational institutes, financial institutions and industrial enterprises. The common thread (enacted in different ways, and subject to the constraints of various systems of national law) is the principle that an enterprise or association should be owned and controlled by the people it serves, and share any surpluses on the basis of each members' cooperative contribution (as a producer, labourer or consumer) rather than their capacity to invest financial capital.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.emeraldinsight.com/Insight/viewContentItem.do;jsessionid=9F0FA205C77BB6EEBEA9AB506E11BEE8?contentType=Article&amp;contentId=1740497 Ridley-Duff, R. J. (2008) “Social Enterprise as a Socially Rational Business”], International Journal of Entrepreneurial Behaviour and Research, 14(5): 291-312.&lt;/ref&gt;

The cooperative movement has been fueled globally by ideas of [[economic democracy]]. Economic democracy is a socioeconomic philosophy that suggests an expansion of decision-making power from a small minority of corporate shareholders to a larger majority of public stakeholders. There are many different approaches to thinking about and building economic democracy. Both [[Marxism]] and [[anarchism]], for example, have been influenced by [[utopian socialism]], which was based on voluntary cooperation, ''without'' recognition of [[class conflict]]. Anarchists are committed to [[libertarian socialism]] and they have focused on local organization, including locally managed cooperatives, linked through confederations of unions, cooperatives and communities. Marxists, who as socialists have likewise held and worked for the goal of democratizing productive and reproductive relationships, often placed a greater strategic emphasis on confronting the larger scales of human organization. As they viewed the capitalist class to be politically, militarily and culturally mobilized for the purpose of maintaining an exploitable [[working class]], they fought in the early 20th century to appropriate from the capitalist class the society's collective political capacity in the form of [[Sovereign state|the state]], either through [[democratic socialism]], or through what came to be known as [[Leninism]]. Though they regard the state as an unnecessarily oppressive institution, Marxists considered appropriating national and international-scale capitalist institutions and resources (such as the state) to be an important first pillar in creating conditions favorable to solidaristic economies.&lt;ref&gt;Rothschild, J., Allen-Whitt, J. (1986) ''The cooperative workplace'', Cambridge University Press, Chapter 1.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cliff, T., Cluckstein, D. (1988) ''The Labour Party: A Marxist History'', London: Bookmarks.&lt;/ref&gt; With the declining influence of the [[USSR]] after the 1960s, socialist strategies pluralized, though economic democratizers have not as yet established a fundamental challenge to the [[hegemony]] of global [[neoliberal]] capitalism.

==Meaning==
===Cooperatives as legal entities===
A cooperative is a [[Legal person|legal entity]] owned and democratically controlled by its members. Members often have a close association with the enterprise as producers or consumers of its products or services, or as its employees.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

In some countries, e.g. [[Finland]] and [[Sweden]], there are specific forms of incorporation for cooperatives.  Cooperatives may take the form of companies limited by shares or by guarantee, partnerships or unincorporated associations. In the UK they may also use the [[industrial and provident society]] structure. In the [[USA]], cooperatives are often organized as non-capital stock corporations under state-specific cooperative laws. However, they may also be unincorporated associations or business [[corporation]]s such as limited liability companies or [[partnership]]s; such forms are useful when the members want to allow{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}:
#some members to have a greater share of the control, or
#some investors to have a return on their [[Capital (economics)|capital]] that exceeds fixed [[interest]],
neither of which may be allowed under local laws for cooperatives. Cooperatives often share their earnings with the membership as [[dividend]]s, which are divided among the members according to their participation in the enterprise, such as patronage, instead of according to the value of their capital shareholdings (as is done by a [[joint stock company]]).

===Identity===
&lt;div id=&quot;Cooperative identity&quot; /&gt;&lt;!-- anchor for incoming links--&gt;
Cooperatives are typically based on the cooperative values of &quot;self-help, self-responsibility, democracy and equality, equity and solidarity&quot; and the seven [[Rochdale Principles|cooperative principles]]:&lt;ref name = Identity&gt;International Cooperative Alliance.[http://www.ica.coop/coop/principles.html Statement on the Cooperative Identity]. Retrieved on: 2011-07-31.&lt;/ref&gt;
#Voluntary and open membership
#Democratic member control
#Economic participation by members
#Autonomy and independence
#Education, training and information
#Cooperation among cooperatives
#Concern for community

Cooperatives are dedicated to the values of openness, social responsibility and caring for others. Such legal entities have a range of social characteristics. Membership is open, meaning that anyone who satisfies certain non-discriminatory conditions may join. Economic benefits are distributed proportionally to each member's level of participation in the cooperative, for instance, by a dividend on sales or purchases, rather than according to [[capital (economics)|capital]] invested.&lt;ref name = Identity/&gt; Cooperatives may be classified as either ''worker'', ''consumer'', ''producer'', ''purchasing'' or ''housing'' cooperatives.&lt;ref&gt;Andrew McLeod (December 2006). [http://www.nwcdc.coop/Resources/CSS/CSS01Types.pdf Types of Cooperatives]. Northwest Cooperative Development Centre. Retrieved on: 2011-07-31.&lt;/ref&gt; They are distinguished from other forms of incorporation in that profit-making or economic stability are balanced by the interests of the community.&lt;ref name = Identity/&gt; Co-ops can sometimes be identified on the Internet through the use of the [[.coop]] [[gTLD|suffix of internet addresses]].  Organizations using .coop domain names must adhere to the basic co-op values.

The [[United Nations]] has declared 2012 to be the International Year of Cooperatives (IYC) &lt;ref name = IYC&gt;The UN's official website is found at http://social.un.org/coopsyear/; retrieved on 25 Feb 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Types of cooperative governance==
===Retailers' cooperative===
{{Main|Retailers' cooperative}}
A  [[retailers' cooperative]] (known as a secondary or marketing cooperative in some countries) is an organization which employs [[economies of scale]] on behalf of its members to receive discounts from manufacturers and to pool marketing. It is common for locally owned  [[supermarket|grocery stores]], [[hardware store]]s  and [[pharmacy|pharmacies]]. In this case the members of the cooperative are businesses rather than individuals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Feder|first=Barnaby J.|title=Independents Have a Weapon Against the 'Big Boxes'|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1997/06/11/business/independents-have-a-weapon-against-the-big-boxes.html?pagewanted=all&amp;src=pm|newspaper=The New York Times|date=11 June 1997|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/64CZUEsQ0|archivedate=25 December 2011|deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Best Western]] international hotel chain is actually a retailers' cooperative, whose members are hotel operators, although it refers to itself as a &quot;nonprofit membership association.&quot;  It gave up on the &quot;cooperative&quot;  label after some courts insisted on enforcing regulatory requirements for [[franchisor]]s despite its member-controlled status.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

===Worker cooperative===
{{Main|Worker cooperative}}
A  [[worker cooperative]] or producer cooperative is a cooperative, that is owned and democratically controlled by its &quot;worker-owners&quot;. There are no outside owners in a &quot;pure&quot; workers' cooperative, only the workers own shares of the business, though hybrid forms exist in which consumers, community members or capitalist investors also own some  shares. In practice, control by worker-owners may be exercised through individual, collective or majority ownership by the workforce, or the retention of individual, collective or majority voting rights (exercised on a one-member one-vote basis).&lt;ref&gt;Ridley-Duff, R. J. (2009) [http://digitalcommons.shu.ac.uk/ciod_papers/57/ &quot;Cooperative Social Enterprises: Company Rules, Access to Finance and Management Practice”], ''Social Enterprise Journal'', 5(1): 50-68&lt;/ref&gt; A worker cooperative, therefore, has the characteristic that the majority of its workforce owns shares, and the majority of shares are owned by the workforce.&lt;ref name=&quot;ICA&quot;&gt;[http://www.cooperatives-uk.coop/live/images/cme_resources/Public/governance/Worker%20co-op%20governance/ICA.pdf ICA (2005) World Declaration on Worker  Cooperatives], Approved by the ICA General Assembly in Cartagena, Columbia, 23rd September 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; Membership is not always compulsory for employees, but generally only employees can become members either directly (as shareholders) or indirectly through membership of a trust that owns the company.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

The impact of political ideology on practice constrains the development of cooperatives in different countries. In India, there is a form of workers' cooperative which insists on compulsory membership for all employees and compulsory employment for all members.  That is the form of the [[Indian Coffee House]]s. This system was advocated by the  Indian communist leader  [[A. K. Gopalan]]. In places like the UK, common ownership (indivisible collective  ownership) was popular in the 1970s. Cooperative Societies only became legal in Britain after the passing of Slaney's Act in 1852. In 1865 there were 651 registered societies with a total membership of well over 200,000.&lt;ref&gt;Slaney's Act and the Christian Sociliasts: A Study of How the Industrial and Provident societies' Act 1852 was passed.&lt;/ref&gt; There are now more than 400 worker cooperatives in the UK,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cooperatives-uk.coop/performancereview The Cooperative Review.]{{Dead link|date=July 2010}} ''[[Co-operatives UK]].''&lt;/ref&gt; Suma Wholefoods being the largest example with a turnover of £24  million.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

Spanish law permits owner-members to register as self-employed  enabling worker-owners  to establish regulatory regimes that support cooperative  working, but which differs considerably from cooperatives that are subject to Anglo-American  systems of law that require the cooperative (employer) to view (and treat) its worker-members as salaried workers (employees).&lt;ref&gt;Oakeshott, R. (1990) ''The Case for Worker Co-ops (2nd Edition)'', Basingstoke:  Macmillan.&lt;/ref&gt;  The implications of this are far-reaching, as this requires cooperatives  to establish authority driven statutory disciplinary and grievance procedures (rather than democratic mediation schemes), impacting on the ability of leaders to enact democratic forms of  management and counter the authority structures embedded in the dominant system of private enterprise centred around the entrepreneur.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.roryridleyduff.com/18%20-%20Mediation%20-%20An%20Introduction.pdf   Ridley-Duff, R. J. (2008) ''Mediation:  Developing a Theoretical Framework for Understanding Alternative Dispute  Resolution'', Centre for  Individual and Organisational Development, Sheffield Hallam University], published at www.roryridleyduff.com/writingacademic.htm.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Volunteer cooperative====
A volunteer cooperative is a cooperative that is run by and for a network of volunteers, for the benefit of a defined membership or the general public, to achieve some goal. Depending on the structure, it may be a [[collective]] or [[mutual organization]], which is operated according to the principles of cooperative governance. The most basic form of volunteer-run cooperative is a [[voluntary association]]. A [[Fraternity|lodge]] or [[social club]] may be organized on this basis. A volunteer-run co-op is distinguished from a [[worker cooperative]] in that the latter is by definition [[Employee-owned corporation|employee-owned]], whereas the volunteer cooperative is typically a [[non-stock corporation]], volunteer-run [[consumer cooperative|consumer co-op]] or [[service organization]], in which workers and beneficiaries jointly participate in management decisions and receive discounts on the basis of [[sweat equity]].{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

===Social cooperative===
{{Main|Social cooperative}}
A  particularly successful form of multi-stakeholder cooperative is the Italian &quot;social cooperative&quot;, of which some 7,000 exist. &quot;Type A&quot; social cooperatives bring together providers and beneficiaries of a social service as members. &quot;Type B&quot; social cooperatives bring together  permanent workers and previously unemployed people who wish to integrate into the labour market. They are legally defined as follows:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://it.wikisource.org/wiki/L._8_novembre_1991,_n.381_-_Disciplina_delle_cooperative_sociali |title=L. 8 novembre 1991, n.381 - Disciplina delle cooperative sociali |language={{it icon}} |publisher=Wikisource |date= |accessdate=25 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*no  more than 80% of profits may be distributed, interest is limited to the bond rate and dissolution is altruistic (assets may not be distributed)
*the  cooperative has legal personality and limited liability
*the objective is the general benefit of the community and the social integration of citizens
*those of type B integrate disadvantaged people into the labour market. The categories of disadvantage they target may include physical and mental disability, drug and alcohol addiction, developmental disorders and problems with the law. They do not include other factors of disadvantage such as unemployment, race, sexual orientation or abuse.
*type A cooperatives provide health, social or educational services
*various categories of stakeholder may become members, including paid employees, beneficiaries, volunteers (up to 50% of members), financial investors and public institutions. In type  B cooperatives at least 30% of the members must be from the disadvantaged target groups
*voting is one person one vote

A good estimate of the current size of the social cooperative sector in Italy is given by updating the official [[Istituto Nazionale di Statistica]] (Istat) figures from the end of 2001 by an annual growth rate of 10% (assumed by the ''Direzione Generale per gli Ente Cooperativi''). This gives totals of 7,100 social cooperatives, with 267,000 members, 223,000 paid employees, 31,000 volunteers and 24,000 disadvantaged people undergoing integration. Combined turnover is around 5 billion euro. The cooperatives break into three types: 59% type A (social and health services), 33% type B (work integration) and 8% mixed. The average size is 30 workers.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

===Consumers' cooperative===
{{Main|Consumers'  cooperative}}
A consumers' cooperative is a  business owned by its customers. Employees can also generally become members. Members vote on major decisions and elect the board of  directors from amongst their own number. The first of these was set up in 1844 in the North-West of England by 28 weavers who wanted to sell food at a lower price than the local shops.
A well known example in the United States is the [[R.E.I.|REI]] (Recreational Equipment Incorporated) co-op, and in Canada: [[Mountain Equipment Co-op]].{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

With its 414,383 employees, 7,736,210 members and a turnover of €50Bn per year growing at a steady rate of 4.41%,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thedti.gov.za/co-operative/presentations/4july/LEGACOOP.pdf Dti Reference]{{dead link|date=December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Legacoop]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aboutus.org/LegaCoop.it |title=Legacoop |publisher=Aboutus.org |date= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; of Italy is arguably the world's biggest federation of cooperatives.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

The world's largest consumers' cooperative is [[the Co-operative Group]] in the [[United Kingdom]], which offers a variety of retail and financial services. The UK also has a number of autonomous consumers' cooperative societies, such as the [[East of England Co-operative Society]] and [[Midcounties Co-operative]]. In fact, the Co-operative Group is something of a hybrid, having both corporate members (mostly other consumers' cooperatives, as a result of its origins as a [[Co-operative wholesale society|wholesale society]]), and individual retail consumer members.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

Japan has a very large and well-developed consumer cooperative movement with over 14 million members; retail co-ops alone had a combined turnover of 2.519&amp;nbsp;trillion&amp;nbsp;Yen (21.184&amp;nbsp;billion&amp;nbsp;US&amp;nbsp;dollars [market exchange rates as of 15 November 2005]) in 2003/4.&lt;ref&gt;Japanese Consumers' Co-operative Union., 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Migros]] is the largest supermarket chain in Switzerland and has around 2 million of the country's 7.2 million population as members.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}} Switzerland's second-biggest supermarket chain, [[Coop (Switzerland)|Coop]] is also a cooperative. In 2001, it merged with 11 cooperative federations which had been its main suppliers for over 100 years.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}} As of 2005, Coop operates 1,437 shops and employs almost 45,000 people. According to Bio Suisse, the Swiss organic producers' association, Coop accounts for half of all the organic food sold in Switzerland.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

[http://www.eurocoop.coop Euro Coop] is the European Community of Consumer Cooperatives.

===Business and employment cooperative===
{{Main|Business and  employment co-operative}}
'''Business and  employment cooperatives''' (BECs) are a subset of worker cooperatives that  represent a new approach to providing support to the creation of new  businesses.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

Like other business creation support schemes, BECs  enable budding entrepreneurs to experiment with their business idea  while benefiting from a secure income.  The innovation BECs introduce is  that once the business is established the entrepreneur is not forced to  leave and set up independently, but can stay and become a full member  of the cooperative.   The micro-enterprises  then combine to form one multi-activity enterprise whose members  provide a mutually supportive environment for each other.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

BECs  thus provide budding business people with an easy transition from  inactivity to self-employment,  but in a collective framework. They open up new horizons for people who  have ambition but who lack the skills or confidence needed to set off  entirely on their own –  or who simply want to carry on an independent economic activity but  within a supportive group context.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

=== New generation cooperative ===
'''New generation cooperatives''' (NGCs) are an adaptation of traditional cooperative structures to modern, capital intensive industries.  They are sometimes described as a hybrid between traditional co-ops and limited liability companies. They were first developed in [[California]] and spread and flourished in the US [[Mid-West]] in the 1990s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www1.agric.gov.ab.ca/$department/deptdocs.nsf/all/bmi6646 |title=New Generation Cooperatives - 10 Things You Need to Know |publisher=Government of Alberta: Agriculture and Rural Development |date= |accessdate=25 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; They are now common in Canada where they operate primarily in agriculture and food services, where their primary purpose is to [[value added|add value]] to [[primary products]].  For example producing [[Ethanol fuel|ethanol]] from [[maize|corn]], [[pasta]] from [[durum wheat]], or [[Goat's milk cheese|gourmet cheese]] from [[Goat's milk|goat’s milk]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.acca.coop/6FAQs.pdf |title=Creating a Co-operative: Frequently Asked Questions about Co-operatives |publisher=Alberta Community and Co-operative Association |date= |accessdate=25 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Types of cooperatives==
===Housing cooperative===
[[Image:Co-op City Hutch River.jpg|thumb|[[Co-op City, Bronx|Co-op City]] in New York is the largest cooperative housing development in the world with 55,000 people.&lt;ref name=&quot;Urban Mass: A Look at Co-op City&quot;/&gt;]]
{{Main|Housing cooperative}}
A [[housing cooperative]] is a legal mechanism for ownership of housing where residents either own [[shares]] (share capital co-op) reflecting their equity in the cooperative's real estate, or have membership and occupancy rights in a [[not-for-profit]] cooperative (non-share capital co-op), and they underwrite their housing through paying subscriptions or rent.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

Housing cooperatives come in three basic equity structures{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}:
*In '''market-rate housing cooperatives''', members may sell their shares in the cooperative whenever they like for whatever price the market will bear, much like any other residential property. Market-rate co-ops are very common in [[New York City]].
*'''Limited equity housing cooperatives''', which are often used by [[affordable housing]] developers, allow members to own some equity in their home, but limit the sale price of their membership share to that which they paid.
*'''Group equity''' or '''zero-equity housing cooperatives''' do not allow members to own equity in their residences and often have rental agreements well below market rates.

{{Main|Building cooperative}}

Members of a building cooperative (in Britain known as a self-build housing cooperative) pool resources to build housing, normally using a high proportion of their own labour. When the building is finished, each member is the sole owner of a homestead, and the cooperative may be dissolved.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

This collective effort was at the origin of many of Britain's [[building societies]], which however, developed into &quot;permanent&quot; [[Mutual organization|mutual]] [[savings and loan]] organisations, a term which persisted in some of their names (such as the former ''Leeds Permanent''). Nowadays such self-building may be financed using a step-by-step [[mortgage loan|mortgage]] which is released in stages as the building is completed.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

The term may also refer to worker cooperatives in the building trade.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

===Utility cooperative===
{{Main|Utility cooperative}}
A utility cooperative is a type of [[consumers' cooperative]] that is tasked with the delivery of a [[public utility]] such as [[electricity]], [[water]] or [[telecommunications]] services to its members. [[Profit (accounting)|Profits]] are either reinvested into [[infrastructure]] or distributed to members in the form of &quot;patronage&quot; or &quot;capital credits&quot;, which are essentially [[dividend]]s paid on a member's [[investment]] into the cooperative. In the United States, many cooperatives were formed to provide rural electrical and telephone service as part of the [[New Deal]].  ''See [[Rural Utilities Service]]''.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

In the case of electricity, cooperatives are generally either generation and transmission (G&amp;T) co-ops that create and send power via the transmission grid or local distribution co-ops that gather electricity from a variety of sources and send it along to homes and businesses.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ncba.coop/ncba/about-co-ops About Cooperatives: Utility Cooperatives.] ''[[National Cooperative Business Association]].''&lt;/ref&gt;

In Tanzania, it has been proven that the cooperative method is helpful in water distribution. When the people are involved with their own water, they care more because the quality of their work has a direct effect on the quality of their water.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Raphael |first=Immaculata |url=http://www.inwent.org/ez/articles/193005/index.en.shtml |title=No more cholera |publisher=Inwent.org |date= |accessdate=25 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Agricultural cooperative===
[[Image:Graincoop.JPG|thumb|250px|right|[[Grain elevator]]s are used by agricultural cooperatives in the storage and shipping of grains.]]
{{Main|Agricultural cooperative}}
Agricultural cooperatives or farmers' cooperatives are cooperatives where [[farmer]]s pool their resources for mutual economic benefit. Agricultural cooperatives are broadly divided into ''agricultural service cooperatives'', which provide various services to their individual farming members, and ''agricultural production cooperatives'', where production resources such as land or machinery are pooled and members farm jointly.&lt;ref name=Cobia&gt;Cobia, David, editor, ''Cooperatives in Agriculture'', Prentice-Hall, Englewood Cliffs, NJ (1989), p. 50.&lt;/ref&gt; Agricultural production cooperatives are relatively rare in the world, and known examples are limited to [[collective farm]]s in [[CIS|former socialist countries]] and the [[kibbutzim]] in Israel.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

Agricultural supply cooperatives aggregate purchases, storage, and distribution of farm inputs for their members. By taking advantage of volume discounts and utilizing other [[economy of scale|economies of scale]], supply cooperatives bring down members' costs. Supply cooperatives may provide seeds, fertilizers, chemicals, fuel, and farm machinery. Some supply cooperatives also operate machinery pools that provide mechanical field services (e.g., plowing, harvesting) to their members.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

Agricultural marketing cooperatives provide the services involved in moving a product from the point of production to the point of consumption. [[Agricultural marketing]] includes a series of inter-connected activities involving planning production, growing and [[harvest]]ing, grading, packing, transport, storage, [[food processing]], distribution and sale. Agricultural marketing cooperatives are often formed to promote specific commodities.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

Commercially successful cooperatives include India's [[Amul]] (dairy products) and Malaysia's [[FELDA]] ([[palm oil]]).

===Credit unions and cooperative banking===
{{Main|Cooperative banking|Credit union}}
[[Image:Co-operativeBankHeadOffice20051019 CopyrightKaihsuTai.jpg|thumb|right|[[The Co-operative Bank]]'s head office in [[Manchester]].  The statue in front is of [[Robert Owen]], a pioneer in the cooperative movement.]]
[[Credit union]]s are cooperative [[financial institution]]s that are owned and controlled by their members. Credit unions provide the same [[financial services]] as banks but are considered [[not-for-profit]] organizations and adhere to [[Rochdale Principles|cooperative principles]].

Credit unions originated in mid-19th century Germany through the efforts of pioneers [[Franz Hermann Schulze-Delitzsch]] and [[Friedrich Wilhelm Raiffeisen]]. The concept of financial cooperatives crossed the Atlantic at the turn of the 20th century, when the ''caisse populaire'' movement was started by [[Alphonse Desjardins (co-operator)|Alphonse Desjardins]] in [[Quebec]], [[Canada]]. In 1900, from his home in [[Lévis, Quebec|Lévis]], he opened North America's first credit union, marking the beginning of the [[Mouvement Desjardins]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.accessmylibrary.com/article-1G1-54036863/desjardins-model-rest-canada.html Desjardins: a model for the rest of Canada?(Quebec's Desjardins caisses populaires).] ''Canadian Banker.'' 1 January 1999.&lt;/ref&gt; Eight years later, Desjardins provided guidance for the first credit union in the [[Credit unions in the United States|United States]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.acumuseum.org/history.html Birthplace of America's Credit Union Movement.] ''[[America's Credit Union Museum]].''&lt;/ref&gt; where there are now about 7,950 active status federally insured credit unions, with almost 90 million members and more than $679 billion on deposit.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.ncua.gov/About/History.aspx| title=History of Credit Unions| publisher=National Credit Union Administration| accessdate=27 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While they have not taken root so deeply as in [[Ireland]], credit unions are also established in the UK. The largest are work-based, but many are now offering services in the wider community. The Association of British Credit Unions Ltd ([[ABCUL]]) represents the majority of British Credit Unions. British [[Building society|Building Societies]] developed into general-purpose savings &amp; banking institutions with &quot;one member, one vote&quot; ownership and can be seen as a form of financial cooperative (although nine '[[Demutualization|de-mutualised]]' into conventionally owned banks in the 1980s &amp; 1990s). The UK Co-operative Group includes both an [[insurance]] provider [[Co-operative Insurance Society|CIS]] and the [[Co-operative Bank]], both noted for promoting [[Ethical investing|ethical investment]].

Other important European banking cooperatives include the [[Crédit Agricole]] in France, [[Migros]] and Coop Bank in Switzerland and the [[Friedrich Wilhelm Raiffeisen|Raiffeisen]] system in many Central and Eastern European countries. The Netherlands, Spain, Italy and various European countries also have strong cooperative banks. They play an important part in mortgage credit and professional (i.e. farming) credit.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

Cooperative banking networks, which were nationalized in Eastern Europe, work now as real cooperative institutions. A remarkable development has taken place in Poland, where the [http://www.skok.pl/ SKOK] (''Spóldzielcze Kasy Oszczednosciowo-Kredytowe'') network has grown to serve over 1 million members via 13,000 branches, and is larger than the country’s largest conventional bank.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

In [[Nordic Countries|Scandinavia]], there is a clear distinction between [[mutual savings bank]]s (Sparbank) and true [[credit unions]] (Andelsbank).{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

The oldest cooperative banks in Europe, based on the ideas of Friedrich Raiffeisen, are joined together in the 'Urgenossen'.

===Federal or secondary cooperatives===
{{Main|Cooperative Federation}}
In some cases, cooperative societies find it advantageous to form [[cooperative federation]]s in which all of the members are themselves cooperatives. Historically, these have predominantly come in the form of cooperative wholesale societies, and cooperative unions.&lt;ref name=&quot;gide&quot;&gt;Gide, Charles; as translated from French by the Cooperative Reference Library, Dublin, &quot;Consumers' Co-Operative Societies&quot;, Manchester: The Co-Operative Union Limited, 1921,  p. 122&lt;/ref&gt; Cooperative federations are a means through which cooperative societies can fulfill the sixth [[Rochdale Principles|Rochdale Principle]], [[cooperation among cooperatives]], with the [[International Cooperative Alliance|ICA]] noting that &quot;Cooperatives serve their members most effectively and strengthen the cooperative movement by working together through local, national, regional and international structures.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ica-statistics&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ica.coop/coop/statistics.html |title=Statistical information on the Co-operative Movement |publisher=International Co-operative Alliance |date= |accessdate=25 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{See also|List of Co-operative Federations}}

====Cooperative wholesale society====
{{Main|Cooperative wholesale society}}
According to cooperative economist [[Charles Gide]], the aim of a cooperative wholesale society is to arrange “bulk purchases, and, if possible, organise production.”&lt;ref name=&quot;gide&quot;/&gt; The best historical example of this were the English CWS and the Scottish CWS, which were the forerunners to the modern [[The Co-operative Group|Co-operative Group]].{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

====Cooperative union====
{{Main|Cooperative union}}
A second common form of cooperative federation is a cooperative union, whose objective (according to Gide) is “to develop the spirit of solidarity among societies and... in a word, to exercise the functions of a government whose authority, it is needless to say, is purely moral.”&lt;ref name=&quot;gide&quot;/&gt; [[Co-operatives UK]] and the [[International Cooperative Alliance]] are examples of such arrangements.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

====Cooperative political movements====
&lt;span id=&quot;Cooperative Party&quot; /&gt;
In some countries with a strong cooperative sector, such as the UK, cooperatives may find it advantageous to form political groupings to represent their interests. The British [[Cooperative Party]], the Canadian [[Cooperative Commonwealth Federation]] and [[United Farmers of Alberta]] are prime examples of such arrangements.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

The [[British cooperative movement]] formed the Cooperative Party in the early 20th century to represent members of [[consumers' cooperative]]s in Parliament, which was the first of its kind.  The [[Cooperative Party]] now has a permanent electoral pact with the [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]] meaning someone cannot be a member if they support a party other than Labour. An alternative grouping, the [[Conservative Co-operative Movement]] is open to people of all parties or none. UK cooperatives retain a significant market share in [[Co-op (supermarket)|food retail]], insurance, banking, funeral services, and the travel industry in many parts of the country.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Cooperatives|Organized labour}}
{{div col|3}}
*[[Cooperative economics]]
*[[Co-operative living arrangements]]
*[[Collective]]
*[[Common ownership]]
*[[Commune (intentional community)]]
*[[Cost the limit of price]]
*[[Danish cooperative movement]]
*[[Democratic socialism]]
*[[Employee-owned corporation]]
*[[Employee Share Ownership Plan]]
*[[FC Barcelona]] (the world's first cooperative-based football club)
*[[Friendly Society]]
*[[History of the cooperative movement]]
*[[Industrial and provident society]]
*[[List of Co-operative Federations]]
*[[List of cooperatives]]
*[[Microfinance]] / [[microcredit]]
*[[Mondragón Cooperative Corporation]]
*[[Mutual aid (politics)|mutual aid]]
*[[Mutual organization]]
*[[Mutual Ownership Defense Housing Division]]
*[[Mutualism (economic theory)]]
*[[Neo-Capitalism]]
*[[Participatory democracy]]
*[[Participatory economics]]
*[[Polytechnic University of the Philippines College of Cooperatives and Social Development]]
*[[Friedrich Wilhelm Raiffeisen]]
*[[Rochdale Principles]]
*[[Social economy]]
*[[Social enterprise]]
*[[Syndicalism]]
*[[Socialism]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
===Notes===
{{refimprove|date=June 2011}}
{{Reflist|colwidth=35em}}

===Bibliography===
{{Refbegin}}
*{{Cite journal|author=Japanese Consumers' Co-operative Union |title=co.op, 2003 Facts and Figures |year=2003 |url=http://www.co-op.or.jp/jccu/English_here/publications/ff/ff2003.pdf}}{{Dead link|date=July 2010}}
*{{Cite journal|author=Isao Takamura |title=Japan: Consumer Co-op Movement in Japan |year=1995 |url=http://uwcc.wisc.edu/icic/today/consumer/move.html}}
{{Refend}}

== Further reading ==
* Llewellyn, D. and Holmes, M. (1991) 'In Defence of Mutuality: A Redress to an Emerging Conventional Wisdom', Annals of Public and Co-operative Economics, Vol.62(3): pp.&amp;nbsp;319–354 (p.&amp;nbsp;327).
* Armitage, S. (1991) 'Consequences of Mutual Ownership for Building Societies', The Service Industries Journal, October, Vol.11(4): pp.&amp;nbsp;458–480 (p.&amp;nbsp;471).
* Rasmusen, E. (1988) 'Mutual banks and stock banks', Journal of Law and Economics, October, Vol.31: pp.&amp;nbsp;395–421 (p.&amp;nbsp;412).
* Masulis, R. (1987) 'Changes in Ownership Structure: Conversions of Mutual Savings and Loans to Stock Charter', Journal of Financial economics, Vol.18: pp.&amp;nbsp;29–59 (p.&amp;nbsp;32).
*[http://backspace.com/notes/2005/09/collectives-for-designers.php &quot;Consider the Collective: More than business as usual&quot;] by John Emerson, 2005. Article on graphic design and printing cooperatives.
*&quot;Consumer Co-operatives in a Changing World&quot; edited by Johann Brazda and Robert Schediwy (ICA), 1989
*[http://fax.libs.uga.edu/HD3271xG453/ ''Consumers' Co-operative Societies''], by [[Charles Gide]], 1922
*[http://fax.libs.uga.edu/HD2951xC776/ ''Co-operation 1921-1947''], published monthly by the [[Cooperative League of America]]
*[http://abob.libs.uga.edu/bobk/coopp.html ''Cooperative Peace''], by [[James Peter Warbasse]], 1950
*[http://www.uwcc.wisc.edu/info/uwcc_pubs/primer.html ''Cooperatives: Principles and practices in the 21st century''], by Kimberly A. Zeuli and Robert Cropp, 2004
*[http://fax.libs.uga.edu/HD2965xW37/ ''Problems Of Cooperation''], by James Peter Warbasse, 1941
*[http://fax.libs.uga.edu/HD3486xH7/ ''The History of Co-operation''], by [[George Jacob Holyoake]], 1908
*&quot;''For All The People: Uncovering the Hidden History of Cooperation, Cooperative Movements, and Communalism in America'',&quot; PM Press, by John Curl, 2009
*&quot;The International Co-operative Movement&quot; by Johnston Birchall, 1997
*[http://digitalcommons.shu.ac.uk/ciod_papers/57/ ''Cooperative Social Enterprises: Company Rules, Access to Finance and Management Practice'' in the ''Social Enterprise Journal'', Vol. 5., Issue, 1] by Rory Ridley-Duff, 2009.
*''Developing Successful Worker Co-ops'', London: Sage Publications by Cornforth, C. J., Thomas, A., Spear, R. G. &amp; Lewis, J. M., 1988.
*''Reluctant Entrepreneurs'', Open University Press by Paton, R., 1989.
*''Making Mondragon'', New York: ILR Press/Itchaca, by Whyte, W. F. &amp; Whyte, K. K., 1991
*[http://cooperativenetwork.coop/wm/education/youthprograms/web/USDACurriculum_MNedition/usdamnedition.html ''Understanding Cooperatives''], a curriculum on cooperative business for secondary school students.
*[http://southasia.oneworld.net/todaysheadlines/india-re-inventing-cooperatives-by-increasing-youth-involvement ''India: Re-inventing cooperatives by increasing youth involvement'']
*[http://journals.sfu.ca/affinities/index.php/affinities/issue/view/4/showToc &quot;The New Cooperativism&quot; in ''Affinities: A Journal of Radical Theory, Culture, and Action'', Vol. 4, Issue 1 (2010)]

==External links==
{{Wikisource1911Enc|co-operation}}
{{Commons category|Cooperatives}}
*[http://www.CoopsCanada.coop/ Canadian Co-operative Association]
*[http://www.uk.coop/ Co-operatives UK]
*[http://www.debut-brussels.com/ DEBUuT, Business Cooperative of the Brussels Region]
*[http://www.ica.coop/ International Co-operative Alliance]
*[http://www.cibp.eu/ International Confederation of Popular Banks]
*[http://www.dollarsandsense.org/archives/2006/0706bowmanstone.html Venezuela's Cooperative Revolution] from [[Dollars &amp; Sense]] magazine
*[http://archive.co-op.ac.uk/ The National Co-operative Archive] – holds records relating to all aspects of the co-operative movement.
*[http://www.credit-coops.ru/ The European Union Project “Credit Cooperatives – Russian Federation”] official web site
*[http://www.communitiesconference.org/ Twin Oaks Communities Conference] Conference focused on education about Cooperative Living
*[http://social.un.org/coopsyear/ United Nations 2012 International Year of Cooperatives (IYC)] official website

{{Co-operatives}}
{{Anarchism}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2010}}

[[Category:Cooperatives| ]]
[[Category:Types of organization]]
[[Category:Types of business entity]]
[[Category:Business models]]
[[Category:Mutualism (movement)]]

[[als:Genossenschaft]]
[[bjn:Kuprasi]]
[[bg:Кооперация]]
[[br:Kevelouri]]
[[ca:Cooperativa]]
[[cs:Družstvo]]
[[cy:Menter gydweithredol]]
[[da:Kooperativ]]
[[de:Genossenschaft]]
[[et:Ühistu]]
[[es:Cooperativa]]
[[eo:Kooperativo]]
[[eu:Kooperatiba]]
[[fa:شرکت تعاونی]]
[[fr:Coopérative]]
[[fy:Koöperaasje]]
[[gl:Cooperativa]]
[[ko:협동조합]]
[[hy:Կոոպերատիվ]]
[[hr:Zadruga]]
[[id:Koperasi]]
[[ia:Cooperativa]]
[[it:Società cooperativa]]
[[he:קואופרטיב]]
[[la:Societas cooperativa]]
[[lt:Kooperatyvas]]
[[hu:Szövetkezet]]
[[ml:സഹകരണസംഘം]]
[[nl:Coöperatie]]
[[ja:協同組合]]
[[no:Samvirke]]
[[nn:Samvirkelag]]
[[pl:Spółdzielnia]]
[[pt:Cooperativismo]]
[[ro:Cooperativă]]
[[ru:Кооператив]]
[[sk:Družstvo (ekonómia)]]
[[fi:Osuuskunta]]
[[sv:Kooperation]]
[[tl:Kooperatiba]]
[[te:సహకార సంఘాలు]]
[[th:สหกรณ์]]
[[tr:Kooperatif]]
[[uk:Кооператив]]
[[vi:Hợp tác xã]]
[[war:Kooperatiba]]
[[zh:合作社]]</text>
      <sha1>5g5kvhqbfqdihvcfwaqgpmga7yk75n8</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
