<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Currency</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5665</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520746133</id>
      <parentid>519110024</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-31T13:47:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Another John S</username>
        <id>17632126</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27441">{{Other uses}}
{{Refimprove|date=October 2011}} 
[[File:Euromoenterogsedler.jpg|thumb|right|[[Coin]]s and [[banknote]]s are the two most common forms of currency. Pictured are several [[Denomination (currency)|denominations]] of the [[euro]].]]
{{Numismatics}}
In [[economics]], '''currency''' is a generally accepted [[medium of exchange]]. These are usually the [[coin]]s and [[banknote]]s of a particular government, which comprise the physical aspects of a nation's [[money supply]]. The other part of a nation's money supply consists of [[Deposit account|bank deposits]] (sometimes called [[deposit money]]), ownership of which can be transferred by means of [[cheque]]s, [[debit card]]s, or other forms of money transfer. Deposit money and currency are [[money]] in the sense that both are acceptable as a means of payment.&lt;ref name=Bernstein&gt;{{cite book |last1=Bernstein |first1=Peter |authorlink1=Peter L. Bernstein |title=A Primer on Money, Banking and Gold |edition=3rd |year=2008 |origyear=1965 |publisher=Wiley |location=Hoboken, NJ  |isbn=978-0-470-28758-3 |oclc=233484849 |chapter=Chapters 4–5 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Direct exchange of [[commodity money|commodities]] such as precious metals, furs, grain, etc. in early human [[society|societies]] led to the first money proper in early civilizations. Until modern times, precious metals such as [[gold]] or [[silver]] typically were used to retain the commodity nature of the store of value function of money. However, nearly all contemporary monetary systems are based on [[fiat money]]. Usually, a government declares its currency (including notes and coins issued by the [[central bank]]) to be [[legal tender]], making it unlawful to not accept it  as a means of repayment for all debts, public and private.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author = Deardorff, Prof. Alan V. |year = 2008 |title = Deardorff's Glossary of International Economics |url = http://www-personal.umich.edu/~alandear/glossary/f.html |publisher = Department of Economics, University of Michigan |accessdate = 2008-07-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Black, Henry Campbell (1910). &quot;A Law Dictionary Containing Definitions Of The Terms And Phrases Of American And English Jurisprudence, Ancient And Modern&quot;, page 494. West Publishing Co. [[Black’s Law Dictionary]] defines the word &quot;fiat&quot; to mean &quot;a short order or warrant of a Judge or magistrate directing some act to be done; an authority issuing from some competent source for the doing of some legal act&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; In major modern economies such as those of the United States or the Euro Zone, most money is electronic, but the &quot;currency&quot; of these polities may, depending on context, include all money or just [[specie]] (i.e., various physical representations of money).

== History ==&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Shekel]] --&gt;

=== Early currency ===
[[File:A print from 1845 shows cowry shells being used as money by an Arab trader.jpg|thumb|left|Cowry shells being used as money by an Arab trader.]]
{{Unreferenced section|date=October 2011}} 
Currency evolved from two basic innovations, both of which had occurred by 2000 BC. Originally money was a form of receipt, representing grain stored in temple granaries in [[Sumer]] in ancient [[Mesopotamia]], then [[Ancient Egypt]].

This first stage of currency, where metals were used to represent stored value, and symbols to represent commodities, formed the basis of trade in the [[Fertile Crescent]] for over 1500 years. However, the collapse of the Near Eastern trading system pointed to a flaw: in an era where there was no place that was safe to store value, the value of a circulating medium could only be as sound as the forces that defended that store. Trade could only reach as far as the credibility of that military. By the late [[Bronze Age]], however, a series of [[Treaty|treaties]] had established safe passage for merchants around the Eastern Mediterranean, spreading from [[Minoan civilization|Minoan]] [[Crete]] and [[Mycenae]] in the northwest to [[Elam]] and [[Bahrain]] in the southeast. Although it is not known what functioned as a currency to facilitate these exchanges, it is thought that ox-hide shaped ingots of copper, produced in [[Cyprus]] may have functioned as a currency.
It is thought that the increase in piracy and raiding associated with the [[Bronze Age collapse]], possibly produced by the [[Peoples of the Sea]], brought this trading system to an end. It was only with the recovery of Phoenician trade in the ninth and tenth centuries BC that saw a return to prosperity, and the appearance of real coinage, possibly first in Anatolia with [[Croesus]] of [[Lydia]] and subsequently with the Greeks and Persians.
In Africa many forms of value store have been used including beads, ingots, [[ivory]], various forms of weapons, livestock, the [[manilla currency]], ochre and other earth oxides, and so on. The manilla rings of [[West Africa]] were one of the currencies used from the 15th century onwards to buy and sell slaves. [[African currency]] is still notable for its variety, and in many places various forms of [[barter]] still apply.

=== Coinage ===
{{main|Coin}}
These factors led to the shift of the store of value being the metal itself: at first silver, then both silver and gold, at one point there was bronze as well. Now we have copper coins and other non-precious metals as coins. Metals were mined, weighed, and stamped into coins. This was to assure the individual taking the coin that he was getting a certain known weight of precious metal. Coins could be counterfeited, but they also created a new [[unit of account]], which helped lead to [[banking]]. [[Archimedes' principle]] provided the next link: coins could now be easily tested for their [[Fineness|fine]] weight of metal, and thus the value of a coin could be determined, even if it had been shaved, debased or otherwise tampered with (see [[Numismatics]]).

In most major economies using coinage, copper, silver and gold formed three tiers of coins. Gold coins were used for large purchases, payment of the military and backing of state activities. Silver coins were used for midsized transactions, and as a unit of account for taxes, dues, contracts and fealty, while copper coins represented the coinage of common transaction. This system had been used in ancient [[Indian coinage|India]] since the time of the [[Mahajanapadas]]. In Europe, this system worked through the [[medieval]] period because there was virtually no new gold, silver or copper introduced through mining or conquest.{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}} Thus the overall ratios of the three coinages remained roughly equivalent.

=== Paper money ===
{{main|Banknote}}
In [[History of China|premodern]] [[China]], the need for credit and for circulating a medium that was less of a burden than exchanging thousands of [[copper]] coins led to the introduction of [[banknote|paper money]], commonly known today as [[banknote]]s. This economic phenomenon was a slow and gradual process that took place from the late [[Tang Dynasty]] (618–907) into the [[Song Dynasty]] (960–1279). It began as a means for merchants to exchange heavy coinage for [[receipt]]s of deposit issued as [[promissory note]]s from shops of [[wholesaler]]s, notes that were valid for temporary use in a small regional territory. In the 10th century, the [[Song Dynasty]] government began circulating these notes amongst the traders in their [[monopoly|monopolized]] salt industry. The Song government granted several shops the sole right to issue banknotes, and in the early 12th century the government finally took over these shops to produce state-issued currency. Yet the banknotes issued were still regionally valid and temporary; it was not until the mid 13th century that a standard and uniform government issue of paper money was made into an acceptable nationwide currency. The already widespread methods of [[woodblock printing]] and then [[Pi Sheng]]'s [[movable type]] [[printing]] by the 11th century was the impetus for the massive production of paper money in premodern China.

[[Image:Jiao zi.jpg|thumb|right|Song Dynasty ''Jiaozi,'' the world's earliest paper money]]

At around the same time in the [[Islamic Golden Age|medieval Islamic world]], a vigorous [[monetary economy]] was created during the 7th–12th centuries on the basis of the expanding levels of circulation of a stable high-value currency (the [[dinar]]). Innovations introduced by Muslim economists, traders and merchants include the earliest uses of [[Credit (finance)|credit]],&lt;ref name=Banaji&gt;{{cite journal |last=Banaji  |first=Jairus |year=2007 |title=Islam, the Mediterranean and the Rise of Capitalism |journal=Historical Materialism |volume=15 |issue=1 |pages=47–74 |publisher=[[Brill Publishers]] |issn=1465-4466 |doi=10.1163/156920607X171591 |bibcode= |oclc=440360743 |url=http://www.scribd.com/doc/14246569/Banaji-Jairus-Islam-The-Mediterranean-and-the-Rise-of-Capitalism |accessdate=August 28, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[cheque]]s, [[promissory note]]s,&lt;ref name=&quot;Medieval Trade in the Mediterranean World: Illustrative Documents&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Lopez |first1=Robert Sabatino |authorlink1=Roberto Sabatino Lopez |last2=Raymond |first2=Irving Woodworth |last3=Constable |first3=Olivia Remie |title=Medieval trade in the Mediterranean world: Illustrative documents |series=Records of Western civilization.; Records of civilization, sources and studies, no. 52 |year=2001  |origyear=1955 |publisher=[[Columbia University Press]] |location=New York |url=http://cup.columbia.edu/bookpreview/978-0-231-12356-3/ |isbn=0-231-12357-4 |oclc=466877309 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[savings account]]s, [[transactional account]]s, [[loan]]ing, [[trusts]], [[exchange rate]]s, the transfer of credit and [[debt]],&lt;ref name=Labib&gt;{{cite journal |last=Labib |first=Subhi Y. |year=1969 |month=March |title=Capitalism in Medieval Islam |journal=The Journal of Economic History |volume=29 |issue=1 |pages=79–86 |publisher=Economic History Association |location=Wilmington, DE |issn=0022-0507 |oclc=478662641 |jstor=2115499 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[banking institution]]s for loans and [[deposit account|deposit]]s.&lt;ref name=Labib /&gt;

In Europe, paper money was first introduced in [[Sweden]] in 1661. Sweden was rich in copper, thus, because of copper's low value, extraordinarily big coins (often weighing several kilograms) had to be made.

The advantages of paper currency were numerous: it reduced transport of gold and silver, and thus lowered the risks; it made loaning gold or silver at interest easier, since the specie (gold or silver) never left the possession of the lender until someone else redeemed the note; and it allowed for a division of currency into credit and specie backed forms. It enabled the sale of [[stock]] in [[joint stock company|joint stock companies]], and the redemption of those [[shares]] in paper.

However, these advantages held within them disadvantages. First, since a note has no intrinsic value, there was nothing to stop issuing authorities from printing more of it than they had specie to back it with. Second, because it increased the money supply, it increased inflationary pressures, a fact observed by [[David Hume]] in the 18th century. The result is that paper money would often lead to an inflationary bubble, which could collapse if people began demanding hard money, causing the demand for paper notes to fall to zero. The printing of paper money was also associated with wars, and financing of wars, and therefore regarded as part of maintaining a [[standing army]]. For these reasons, paper currency was held in suspicion and hostility in Europe and America. It was also addictive, since the speculative profits of trade and capital creation were quite large. Major nations established [[mint (coin)|mints]] to print money and mint coins, and branches of their treasury to collect taxes and hold gold and silver stock.

At this time both silver and gold were considered [[legal tender]], and accepted by governments for taxes. However, the [[Gresham's law|instability in the ratio]] between the two grew over the course of the 19th century, with the increase both in supply of these metals, particularly silver, and of trade. This is called [[bimetallism]] and the attempt to create a [[Bimetallism|bimetallic]] standard where both gold and silver backed currency remained in circulation occupied the efforts of [[inflation]]ists. Governments at this point could use currency as an instrument of policy, printing paper currency such as the United States [[United States Note|Greenback]], to pay for military expenditures. They could also set the terms at which they would redeem notes for specie, by limiting the amount of purchase, or the minimum amount that could be redeemed.

By 1900, most of the industrializing nations were on some form of gold standard, with paper notes and silver coins constituting the circulating medium. Private [[bank]]s and governments across the world followed [[Gresham's Law]]: keeping gold and silver paid, but paying out in notes. This did not happen all around the world at the same time, but occurred sporadically, generally in times of war or financial crisis, beginning in the early part of the 20th century and continuing across the world until the late 20th century, when the regime of floating fiat currencies came into force. One of the last countries to break away from the [[gold standard]] was the United States in 1971.

No country anywhere in the world today has an enforceable [[gold standard]] or [[silver standard]] currency system.

===Banknote era===
{{Main|Banknote|Fiat currency}}
A [[banknote]] (more commonly known as a bill in the United States and Canada) is a type of currency, and commonly used as legal tender in many jurisdictions. With [[coin]]s, banknotes make up the [[cash]] form of all [[money]]. Banknotes are mostly paper, but Australia's [[Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation]] developed the world's first [[Polymer banknote|polymer currency]] in the 1980s that went into circulation on the nation's bicentenary in 1988. Now used in some 22 countries (over 40 if counting commemorative issues), [[Polymer banknote|polymer currency]] dramatically improves the life span of banknotes and prevents counterfeiting.

== Modern currencies ==
{{main|Tables of historical exchange rates to the USD}}
[[File:2002 currency exchange AIGA euro money.png|thumb|Currencies exchange logo]]
To find out which currency is used in a particular country, check [[list of circulating currencies]].

Currency use is based on the concept of [[lex monetae]]; that a sovereign state decides which currency it shall use. Currently, the [[International Organization for Standardization]] has introduced a three-letter system of codes ([[ISO 4217]]) to define currency (as opposed to simple names or [[currency sign]]s), in order to remove the confusion that there are dozens of currencies called the [[dollar]] and many called the [[franc]]. Even the [[List of countries using pound currency|pound]] is used in nearly a dozen different countries, all, of course, with wildly differing values. In general, the three-letter code uses the [[ISO 3166-1]] country code for the first two letters and the first letter of the name of the currency (D for dollar, for instance) as the third letter. United States currency, for instance is globally referred to as [[USD]]. It is also possible for a currency to be internet-based and digital, for instance, a [[Bitcoin]], the Ripple Pay system or Mintchip, and not tied to any specific country.

The [[International Monetary Fund]] uses a variant system when referring to national currencies.

==Control and production==
In most cases, a [[central bank]] has [[monopoly]] control over emission of coins and banknotes ([[fiat money]]) for its own area of circulation (a country or group of countries); it regulates the production of currency by banks ([[credit]]) through [[monetary policy]].

In order to facilitate [[international trade|trade]] between these currency zones, there are different [[exchange rate]]s, which are the prices at which currencies (and the goods and services of individual currency zones) can be exchanged against each other. Currencies can be classified as either [[floating currency|floating currencies]] or [[fixed currency|fixed currencies]] based on their [[exchange rate regime]]. 

In cases where a country does have control of its own currency, that control is exercised either by a [[central bank]] or by a [[Finance minister|Ministry of Finance]]. In either case, the institution that has control of monetary policy is referred to as the monetary authority. Monetary authorities have varying degrees of autonomy from the governments that create them. In the [[United States]], the [[Federal Reserve System]] operates without direct oversight by the legislative or executive branches. A monetary authority is created and supported by its sponsoring government, so independence can be reduced by the legislative or executive authority that creates it. 

Several countries can use the same name for their own distinct currencies (for example, ''dollar'' in [[Australian dollar|Australia]], [[Canadian dollar|Canada]] and the [[United States dollar|United States]]). By contrast, several countries can also use the same currency (for example, the [[euro]]), or one country can declare the currency of another country to be [[legal tender]]. For example, [[Panama]] and [[El Salvador]] have declared U.S. currency to be legal tender, and from 1791–1857, [[Spanish silver coins]] were legal tender in the United States. At various times countries have either re-stamped foreign coins, or used [[currency board]] issuing one note of currency for each note of a foreign government held, as [[Ecuador]] currently does.

Each currency typically has a main currency unit (the [[dollar]], for example, or the [[euro]]) and a fractional currency, often valued at {{Frac|1|100}} of the main currency: 100 [[Cent (currency)|cent]]s = 1 [[dollar]], 100 [[centime]]s = 1 [[franc]], 100 [[British One Penny coin|pence]] = 1 [[Pound sterling|pound]], although units of {{Frac|1|10}} or {{Frac|1|1000}} are also common. Some currencies do not have any smaller units at all, such as the [[Icelandic króna]].

[[Mauritania]] and [[Madagascar]] are the only remaining countries that do not use the decimal system; instead, the Mauritanian [[Mauritanian ouguiya|ouguiya]] is divided into 5 [[khoums]], while the [[Madagascar|Malagasy]] [[Malagasy ariary|ariary]] is divided into 5 [[iraimbilanja]]. In these countries, words like ''dollar'' or ''pound'' &quot;were simply names for given weights of gold.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Collapse of the Dollar&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Turk |first1=James |last2=Rubino |first2=John |title=The collapse of the dollar and how to profit from it: Make a fortune by investing in gold and other hard assets.|edition=Paperback |year=2007 |origyear=2004 |publisher=Doubleday |location=New York |isbn=978-0-385-51224-4 |oclc=192055959 |pages=43 of 252 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Due to [[inflation]] khoums and iraimbilanja have in practice fallen into disuse. (See [[non-decimal currencies]] for other historic currencies with non-decimal divisions).

== Currency convertibility ==
Convertibility of a currency determines the ability of an individual, corporate or government to convert its local currency to another currency or vice versa with or without central bank/government intervention. Based on the above restrictions or free and readily conversion features currencies are classified as:

* Fully Convertible - When there are no restrictions or limitations on the amount of currency that can be traded on the international market, and the government does not artificially impose a fixed value or minimum value on the currency in international trade. The US dollar is an example of a fully convertible currency and for this reason, US dollars are one of the major currencies traded in the FOREX&lt;ref name=InsuranceProducts&gt;{{cite web|title=Top Forex News|url=http://www.topforexnews.com/|publisher=Forex News|accessdate=17 july 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; market.
* Partially Convertible - Central Banks control international investments flowing in and out of the country, while most domestic trade transactions are handled without any special requirements, there are significant restrictions on international investing and special approval is often required in order to convert into other currencies. The Indian Rupee is an example of a partially convertible currency.
* Nonconvertible - Neither participate in the international FOREX market nor allow conversion of these currencies by individuals or companies. As a result, these currencies are known as blocked currencies. e.g.: [[North Korean Won]] and the [[Cuban Peso]]

== Local currencies ==
{{Main|Local currency}}
In economics, a local currency is a currency not backed by a national government, and intended to trade only in a small area. Advocates such as [[Jane Jacobs]] argue that this enables an economically depressed region to pull itself up, by giving the people living there a medium of exchange that they can use to exchange services and locally produced goods (In a broader sense, this is the original purpose of all money.) Opponents of this concept argue that local currency creates a barrier which can interfere with economies of scale and comparative advantage, and that in some cases they can serve as a means of [[tax evasion]].

Local currencies can also come into being when there is economic turmoil involving the national currency. An example of this is the Argentinian economic crisis of 2002 in which IOUs issued by local governments quickly took on some of the characteristics of local currencies.

One of the best examples of a local currency is the original [[LETS]] currency, founded on Vancouver Island in the early 1980s.  In 1982 the Canadian Central Bank’s lending rates ran up to 14% which drove chartered bank lending rates as high as 19%.  The resulting currency and credit scarcity left island residents with few options other than to create a local currency.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite podcast|url=http://media.blubrry.com/extraenvironmentalist/p/extraenvironmentalist.com/audio/low/Ep45_final_lowbitrate.mp3 |title=Opening Money |website=http://www.extraenvironmentalist.com/2012/07/11/episode-45-opening-money/ |host=The Extraenvironmentalist |date=7-11-2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Proposed currencies==
* [[Amero]]: [[American currency union]] (hypothetical)
* [[Asian Currency Unit]]: proposed for the [[ASEAN +3]], or the [[East Asian Community]]
* [[Bancor]]: an international currency proposed by [[John Maynard Keynes]] in the negotiations that established the [[Bretton Woods system]] (never implemented)
* Currency for Caribbean area&lt;ref name=JamaicaGleaner&gt;{{cite news |title=CARICOM Single Market (CSM) ratified! – Caribbean leaders sign formal document |url=http://www.jamaica-gleaner.com/gleaner/20060131/lead/lead1.html |newspaper=[[Jamaica Gleaner]] |publisher=The Gleaner Company Limited |location=Kingston, Jamaica |oclc=50239830 |date=January 31, 2006 |accessdate=August 30, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;—[[CARICOM]] states except the [[Bahamas]].
* [[East African shilling]]: [[East African Community]] ([[Burundi]], [[Kenya]], [[Rwanda]], [[Tanzania]], [[Uganda]])
* [[Eco (currency)|Eco]]: [[West African Monetary Zone]] ([[The Gambia]], [[Ghana]], [[Guinea]], [[Nigeria]], [[Sierra Leone]], possibly [[Liberia]])
*[[Khaleeji (currency)]]: [[Cooperation Council for the Arab States of the Gulf|Gulf Cooperation Council]] ([[Bahrain]], [[Kuwait]], [[Oman]], [[Qatar]], [[Saudi Arabia]], [[United Arab Emirates]])
* [[Mozambican metica|Metica]]: [[Mozambique]] (never implemented)
* [[Montenegrin perun|Perun]]: [[Montenegro]] (never implemented)
* [[Gaucho (currency)]]: Currency for bilateral commerce (never implemented)
* [[Iranian toman|Toman]]: The new currency that is proposed by the [[Central Bank of Iran]] which would replace the [[Iranian Rial]] by slashing four zeros off the country's national currency.
* [[Caribbean guilder]], the new currency for [[Curaçao]] and [[Sint Maarten]] for 2012 replacing the [[Netherlands Antillean guilder]].
* [[Spesmilo]]

== See also ==
{{too many see alsos|date=September 2011}}
{{Portal|Numismatics}}
{{Col-begin}}{{Col-break}}
&lt;center&gt;'''Related concepts'''&lt;/center&gt;
* [[Counterfeit money]]
* [[Currency transaction tax]]
* [[Foreign exchange market]]
* [[Foreign exchange reserves]] {{spaces|10}}
* [[History of banking]]
* [[History of money]]
* [[Mutilated currency]]
* [[Optimum currency area]]
* [[Slang terms for money]]
* [[World currency]]
{{Col-break}}
&lt;center&gt;'''Accounting units'''&lt;/center&gt;
* [[Currency pair]]
* [[Currency sign]]
* [[Currency strength]]
* [[European Currency Unit]] {{spaces|10}}
* [[Fictional currency]]
* [[Franc Poincaré]]
* [[Local currencies]]
* [[Petrocurrency]]
* [[Special drawing rights]]
{{Col-break}}
&lt;center&gt;'''Lists'''&lt;/center&gt;
* [[List of currencies]]
* [[List of circulating currencies]]
* [[List of fictional currencies]]
* [[List of historical currencies]]
* [[List of historical exchange rates]]
* [[List of international trade topics]]
* [[List of motifs on banknotes]]
{{Col-end}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Commons category multi|Banknotes|Coins|Numismatics}}

{{Economics}}

[[Category:Currency| ]]
[[Category:Foreign exchange market]]

{{Link GA|de}}
[[ar:عملة]]
[[an:Divisa]]
[[arc:ܙܘܙܐ]]
[[as:প্ৰচলিত মুদ্ৰা (চলাৰ্থ)]]
[[ast:Divisa]]
[[az:Valyuta]]
[[be:Валюта]]
[[be-x-old:Валюта]]
[[bg:Валута]]
[[bar:Wearung]]
[[bs:Valuta]]
[[br:Moneiz]]
[[ca:Moneda]]
[[cs:Měna]]
[[cy:Arian cyfred]]
[[da:Valuta]]
[[de:Währung]]
[[et:Valuuta]]
[[el:Νομισματική μονάδα]]
[[es:Divisa]]
[[eo:Valuto]]
[[ext:Monea]]
[[eu:Dibisa]]
[[fa:یکای پول]]
[[hif:Mudra]]
[[fo:Gjaldoyra]]
[[fr:Devise (monnaie)]]
[[fy:Munt]]
[[ga:Airgeadra]]
[[gd:Ruith-airgid]]
[[gl:Divisa]]
[[ko:통화]]
[[hy:Տարադրամ]]
[[hi:मुद्रा (करेंसी)]]
[[hr:Valuta]]
[[id:Mata uang]]
[[ia:Numerario]]
[[os:Валютæ]]
[[is:Gjaldmiðill]]
[[it:Valuta]]
[[jv:Valuta]]
[[kn:ನಗದು]]
[[krc:Валюта]]
[[ka:ვალუტა]]
[[kk:Валюта]]
[[lo:ເງິນຕາ]]
[[la:Moneta (pecunia)]]
[[lv:Valūta]]
[[lt:Valiuta]]
[[hu:Valuta (fizetőeszköz)]]
[[mk:Валута]]
[[ml:നാണയം]]
[[mr:चलन]]
[[arz:عمله]]
[[ms:Mata wang]]
[[mwl:Moneda]]
[[mn:Мөнгөн тэмдэгт]]
[[nl:Valuta]]
[[new:दां]]
[[ja:通貨]]
[[pih:Kurencii]]
[[no:Valuta]]
[[nn:Valuta]]
[[nrm:Mounaie]]
[[oc:Devisa (moneda)]]
[[uz:Valyuta]]
[[pnb:کرنسی]]
[[pap:Moneda]]
[[ps:ارز]]
[[nds:Geldsoort]]
[[pl:Waluta]]
[[pt:Moeda]]
[[ro:Valută]]
[[rm:Valuta]]
[[qu:Kañina]]
[[rue:Міна]]
[[ru:Валюта]]
[[sah:Валюта]]
[[se:Ruhta]]
[[nso:Mašeleng]]
[[sq:Deviza]]
[[simple:Currency]]
[[sl:Valuta]]
[[cu:Платьно срѣдьство]]
[[ckb:دراو]]
[[sr:Валута]]
[[sh:Valuta]]
[[su:Mata uang]]
[[fi:Valuutta]]
[[sv:Valuta]]
[[tl:Pananalapi (yunit ng palitan)]]
[[ta:நாணயம்]]
[[te:ద్రవ్యం]]
[[th:เงินตรา]]
[[tr:Döviz]]
[[udm:Валюта]]
[[uk:Валюта]]
[[ur:فلس]]
[[vec:Vałuta]]
[[vi:Tiền tệ]]
[[wa:Manoye]]
[[war:Pananalapi]]
[[yi:וואלוטע]]
[[yo:Owóníná]]
[[bat-smg:Valiota]]
[[zh:通貨]]</text>
      <sha1>204xw343do3h31fb9zdairlg8qwaqtr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
