<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Dynamic stochastic general equilibrium</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>12052214</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520248556</id>
      <parentid>516626217</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-28T11:11:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>82.204.105.103</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="19255">'''Dynamic stochastic general equilibrium''' modeling (abbreviated '''DSGE''' or sometimes '''SDGE''' or '''DGE''') is a branch of applied [[general equilibrium theory]] that is influential in contemporary [[macroeconomics]]. The DSGE methodology attempts to explain aggregate economic phenomena, such as [[economic growth]], [[business cycles]], and the effects of [[monetary policy|monetary]] and [[fiscal policy]], on the basis of [[macroeconomic model]]s derived from [[microfoundations|microeconomic principles]].  One of the main reasons macroeconomists seek to build microfounded models is that, unlike more [[Large-scale macroeconometric model|traditional macroeconometric forecasting models]], microfounded models should not, in principle, be vulnerable to the [[Lucas critique]]. Furthermore, since the [[microfoundations]] are based on the preferences of the decision-makers in the model, DSGE models feature a natural benchmark for evaluating the welfare effects of policy changes (for discussion of both points, see Woodford, 2003, pp.&amp;nbsp;11–12 and Tovar, 2008, pp.&amp;nbsp;15–16).

==Structure of DSGE models==
Like other [[general equilibrium]] models, DSGE models aim to describe the behavior of the economy as a whole by analyzing the interaction of many [[microeconomic]] decisions. The decisions considered in most DSGE models correspond to some of the main quantities studied in [[macroeconomics]], such as [[Consumption (economics)|consumption]], [[saving]], [[Investment#In economics or macroeconomics|investment]], and [[labor supply]] and [[labor demand]]. The decision-makers in the model, often called [[Agent (economics)|'agents']], may include [[household]]s, [[business|business firms]], and possibly others, such as [[government]]s or [[central bank]]s.

Furthermore, as their name indicates, DSGE models are '''dynamic''', studying how the economy evolves over time.  They are also [[stochastic process|'''stochastic''']], taking into account the fact that the economy is affected by random [[Shock (economics)|shocks]] such as technological change, fluctuations in the price of oil, or changes in macroeconomic policy-making. This contrasts with the static models studied in [[Léon Walras|Walrasian]] [[general equilibrium]] theory, [[applied general equilibrium]] models and some [[computable general equilibrium]] models.

For a coherent description of the macroeconomy, DSGE models must spell out the following economic 'ingredients'.

* '''Preferences''': the objectives of the [[Agent (economics)|agents]] in the economy must be specified. For example, households might be assumed to maximize a [[utility]] function over consumption and labor effort. Firms might be assumed to maximize [[profit (economics)|profit]]s.
* '''Technology''': the productive capacity of the agents in the economy must be specified. For example, firms might be assumed to have a [[production function]], specifying the amount of goods produced, depending on the amount of labor, capital and other inputs they employ. Technological constraints on agents' decisions might also include costs of adjusting their capital stocks, their employment relations, or the prices of their products.
* '''Institutional framework''': the institutional constraints governing economic interactions must be specified. In many DSGE models, this might just mean that agents must obey some exogenously imposed [[budget constraint]]s, and that prices are assumed to adjust until [[Market clearing|markets clear]]. It might also mean specifying the rules of monetary and fiscal policy, or even how policy rules and budget constraints change depending on a political process.

[[Macroeconomic model#Empirical forecasting models|Traditional macroeconometric forecasting models]] used by central banks in the 1970s, and even today, estimated the dynamic correlations between prices and quantities in different sectors of the economy, and often included thousands of variables. Since DSGE models start from [[microfoundations|microeconomic principles]] of [[Constraint (mathematics)|constrained]] decision-making, instead of just taking as given observed correlations, they are technically more difficult to solve and analyze. Therefore they usually abstract from so many sectoral details, and include far fewer variables: just a few variables in theoretical DSGE papers, or on the order of a hundred variables in the experimental DSGE forecasting models now being constructed by central banks. What DSGE models give up in sectoral detail, they attempt to make up in logical consistency.

==Advantages and disadvantages of DSGE modeling==

By specifying preferences (what the agents want), technology (what the agents can produce), and institutions (the way they interact), it is possible (in principle, though challenging in practice) to solve the DSGE model to predict what is actually produced, traded, and consumed, and how these variables evolve over time in response to various shocks. In principle, it is also possible to make predictions about the effects of changing the institutional framework. 

In contrast, as [[Lucas critique|Robert Lucas]] pointed out, such a prediction is unlikely to be valid in traditional macroeconometric forecasting models, since those models are based on observed past correlations between macroeconomic variables. These correlations can be expected to change when new policies are introduced, invalidating predictions based on past observations. 

Given the difficulty of constructing accurate DSGE models, most central banks still rely on traditional macroeconometric models for short-term forecasting. However, the effects of alternative policies are increasingly studied using DSGE methods. Since DSGE models are constructed on the basis of assumptions about agents' preferences, it is possible to ask whether the policies considered are [[Pareto optimality|Pareto optimal]], or how well they satisfy some other [[Social welfare function|social welfare]] criterion derived from preferences (Woodford, 2003, p.&amp;nbsp;12).

==Schools of DSGE modeling==

At present two competing schools of thought form the bulk of DSGE modeling.&lt;ref&gt;Cantore et al (2010) have suggested that the difference between RBC and New Keynesian models, when controlling for key supply
channels, can be limited.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Real Business Cycle Theory|Real business cycle]] (RBC) theory builds on the [[Exogenous growth model|neoclassical growth model]], under the assumption of flexible prices, to study how real shocks to the economy might cause business cycle fluctuations. The paper of [[Finn Kydland|Kydland]] and [[Edward C. Prescott|Prescott]] (1982) is often considered the starting point of RBC theory and of DSGE modeling in general.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
 | title = Time to build and aggregate fluctuations
 | url = http://web.mit.edu/dancao/OldFiles/Public/Network%20Idea/Time%20to%20Build%20and%20Aggregate%20Fluctuation.pdf
 | year = 1982
 | journal = Econometrica: Journal of the Econometric Society
 | pages = 1345–1370 | volume = 50 | issue = 6
 | last1 = Kydland	 | first1 =  F.E. | authorlink = Finn Kydland
 | last2 =  Prescott	 | first2 =  E.C. | authorlink = Edward Prescott
 | accessdate = 2010-07-23	}}
&lt;/ref&gt; The RBC point of view is surveyed in Cooley (1995).
* [[New Keynesian economics|New-Keynesian]] DSGE models build on a structure similar to RBC models, but instead assume that prices are set by monopolistically competitive firms, and cannot be instantaneously and costlessly adjusted. The paper that first introduced this framework was Rotemberg and Woodford (1997). Introductory and advanced textbook presentations are given by [[Jordi Galí|Galí]] (2008) and [[Michael Woodford (economist)|Woodford]] (2003).  Monetary policy implications are surveyed by [[Richard Clarida|Clarida]], [[Jordi Galí|Galí]], and [[Mark Gertler (economist)|Gertler]] (1999).

==Example==
The [[European Central Bank]] (ECB) has developed a DSGE model, often called the [http://www.ecb.int/home/html/researcher_swm.en.html  Smets-Wouters model], which it uses to analyze the economy of the [[Eurozone]] as a whole (in other words, the model does not analyze individual European countries separately). The model is intended as an alternative to the ''Area-Wide Model (AWM)'', a [[Model (macroeconomics)#Empirical forecasting models|more traditional empirical forecasting model]] which the ECB has been using for several years. The [http://www.ecb.int/home/html/researcher_swm.en.html  ECB webpage] that describes the Smets-Wouters model also discusses the advantages of building a DSGE model instead of relying on more traditional methods.

The equations in the Smets-Wouters model describe the choices of three types of [[Agent (economics)|decision makers]]: households, who made an optimal trade-off between consumption and worked hours, under a budget contraint; firms, who optimize theirs labor and capital to employ; and the central bank, which controls monetary policy. The [[parameter]]s in the equations were estimated using [[Bayesian statistics|Bayesian]] statistical techniques so that the model approximately describes the dynamics of GDP, consumption, investment, prices, wages, employment, and interest rates in the Eurozone economy. In order to accurately reproduce the sluggish behavior of some of these variables, the model incorporates several types of frictions that slow down adjustment to [[Shock (economics)|shocks]], including [[Sticky (economics)|sticky prices and wages]], and adjustment costs in investment.

==Controversy==
[[Willem Buiter]] of the [[London School of Economics and Political Science|London School of Economics]] has argued that DSGE models rely excessively on an assumption of [[complete market]]s, and are unable to describe the highly [[nonlinear dynamics]] of economic fluctuations, making training in 'state-of-the-art' macroeconomic modeling &quot;a privately and socially costly waste of time and resources&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
  | last = Buiter
  | first = Willem
  | authorlink = Willem Buiter
  | title = The unfortunate uselessness of most 'state of the art’ academic monetary economics
  | work = ft.com/maverecon
  | publisher = Financial Times
  | date = 2009-03-03
  | url = http://blogs.ft.com/maverecon/2009/03/the-unfortunate-uselessness-of-most-state-of-the-art-academic-monetary-economics/
  | doi = 
  | accessdate = 2010-07-23 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

[[N. Gregory Mankiw]], regarded as one of the founders of [[New Keynesian]] DSGE modeling, has also argued that
:'New classical and new Keynesian research has had little impact on practical macroeconomists who are charged with ... policy. ... From the standpoint of macroeconomic engineering, the work of the past several decades looks like an unfortunate wrong turn.'&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
 | title = The Macroeconomist as Scientist and Engineer
 | url = http://www.economics.harvard.edu/files/faculty/40_Macroeconomist_as_Scientist.pdf
 | year = 2006
 | last = Mankiw | first = N. Gregory | authorlink = N. Gregory Mankiw
 | journal = The Journal of Economic Perspectives
 | pages = 29–46 | volume = 20 | issue = 4
 | accessdate = 2010-07-23
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Michael Woodford (economist)|Michael Woodford]], replying to Mankiw, argues that DSGE models are commonly used by [[central bank]]s today, and have strongly influenced policy makers like [[Ben Bernanke]]. However, he argues that what is learned from DSGE models is not so different from traditional Keynesian analysis:
:'It is true that the modeling efforts of many policy institutions can reasonably be seen as an evolutionary development within the macroeconomic modeling program of the postwar Keynesians; thus if one expected, with the early New Classicals, that adoption of the new tools would require building anew from the ground up, one might conclude that the new tools have not been put to use. But in fact they have been put to use, only not with such radical consequences as had once been expected.'&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
  | last = Woodford  | first = Michael | author-link = Michael Woodford (economist)
  | title = Convergence in Macroeconomics: Elements of a New Synthesis
  | journal = annual meeting of the American Economics Association.
  | volume =  | issue =  | pages = 
  | date = 2008-01-04
  | url = http://www.columbia.edu/~mw2230/Convergence_AEJ.pdf 
  | doi = 
  | id = }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Narayana Kocherlakota]], President of the [[Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis]], acknowledges that DSGE models were not very useful for analyzing the [[financial crisis of 2007-2010]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
  | last = Kocherlakota | first = Narayana  | authorlink = Narayana Kocherlakota
  | title = Modern Macroeconomic Models as Tools for Economic Policy
  | work = Banking and Policy Issues Magazine
  | publisher = Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis
  | year = 2010 | month = May
  | url = http://www.minneapolisfed.org/publications_papers/pub_display.cfm?id=4428
  | doi = 
  | accessdate = 2010-07-23 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;
Nonetheless, he argues that the applicability of these models is improving, and that there is growing consensus among macroeconomists that DSGE models need to incorporate both price stickiness and financial market frictions.

The [[United States Congress]] hosted hearings on [[macroeconomic model]]ing methods on July 20, 2010, to investigate why macroeconomists failed to foresee the [[Financial crisis of 2007-2010]]. [[Robert Solow]] blasted DSGE models currently in use:

:'I do not think that the currently popular DSGE models pass the smell test. They take it for granted that the whole economy can be thought about as if it were a single, consistent person or dynasty carrying out a rationally designed, long-term plan, occasionally disturbed by unexpected shocks, but adapting to them in a rational, consistent way... The protagonists of this idea make a claim to respectability by asserting that it is founded on what we know about [[microeconomics|microeconomic]] behavior, but I think that this claim is generally phony. The advocates no doubt believe what they say, but they seem to have stopped sniffing or to have lost their sense of smell altogether.'&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20110204034313/http://democrats.science.house.gov/Media/file/Commdocs/hearings/2010/Oversight/20july/Solow_Testimony.pdf Prepared Statement of Robert Solow, Professor Emeritus, MIT, to the House Committee on Science and Technology, Subcommittee on Investigations and Oversight: “Building a Science of Economics for the Real World,” July 20, 2010]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[V.V. Chari]] pointed out, however, that state-of-the-art DSGE models are more sophisticated than their critics suppose:
:'The models have all kinds of heterogeneity in behavior and decisions... people's objectives differ, they differ by age, by information, by the history of their past experiences. '

Chari also argued that current DSGE models frequently incorporate [[frictional unemployment]], [[Incomplete markets|financial market imperfections]], and [[Sticky (economics)|sticky]] prices and wages, and therefore imply that the macroeconomy behaves in a [[Pareto optimality|suboptimal]] way which [[Monetary policy|monetary]] and [[fiscal policy]] may be able to improve.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20110205174457/http://democrats.science.house.gov/Media/file/Commdocs/hearings/2010/Oversight/20july/Chari_Testimony.pdf Testimony before the Committee on Science and Technology, U.S. House of Representatives, V.V. Chari, Univ. of Minnesota and Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis” July 20, 2010]&lt;/ref&gt;

Commenting on the Congressional session, [[The Economist]] asked whether [[agent-based model]]s might better predict [[Financial crisis|financial crises]] than DSGE models.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.economist.com/node/16636121 Agents of change, ''The Economist'', July 22, 2010.]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==

* [[Lucas critique]]
* [[Real business cycle]]s
* [[New Keynesian economics]]
* [[General equilibrium]]
* [[Applied general equilibrium]] (AGE) models
* [[Computable general equilibrium]] (CGE) models
* [[Macroeconomic model]]
* [[Large-scale macroeconometric model]]
* [[Welfare cost of business cycles]]
* [[New neoclassical synthesis]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;
*Bank of England (2005), 'The Bank of England quarterly model': http://www.bankofengland.co.uk/publications/other/beqm/index.htm (See especially Chapters 1 and 3.)
*Cristiano Cantore, Miguel León-Ledesma, Peter McAdam and Alpo Willman (2011), 'Shocking stuff: technology, hours, and factor substitution', European Central Bank, Working Paper No. 1278: http://www.ecb.europa.eu/pub/pdf/scpwps/ecbwp1278.pdf
*European Central Bank: [http://www.ecb.int/home/html/researcher_swm.en.html The Smets-Wouters (2003) model]
*Fabio Canova (2007), ''Methods for Applied Macroeconomic Research''. Princeton University Press, ISBN 0-691-11504-4.
*Richard Clarida, Jordi Gali, and Mark Gertler (1999), 'The science of monetary policy: a New-Keynesian perspective.' ''Journal of Economic Literature'' 37, pp.&amp;nbsp;1661–707.
*Thomas Cooley, ed., (1995), ''Frontiers of Business Cycle Research''. Princeton University Press, ISBN 0-691-04323-X.
*DeJong, D. N. with C. Dave (2007), ''Structural Macroeconometrics''. Princeton University Press, ISBN 0-691-12648-8.
*Galí, Jordi (2008), ''Monetary Policy, Inflation, and the Business Cycle''. Princeton University Press, ISBN 978-0-691-13316-4.
*Robert E. Lucas, Jr. (1976), 'Econometric policy evaluation: a critique.' ''Carnegie-Rochester Conference Series on Public Policy' 1, pp.&amp;nbsp;19–46.
*Julio Rotemberg and Michael Woodford (1997), 'An optimization-based econometric framework for the evaluation of monetary policy.' NBER Macroeconomics Annual 12, pp.&amp;nbsp;297–346.
*Camilo Tovar (2008), '[http://www.bis.org/publ/work258.htm DSGE models and central banks]', Bank for International Settlements working paper #258.
*Michael Woodford (2003), ''Interest and Prices: Foundations of a Theory of Monetary Policy.'' Princeton University Press, ISBN 0-691-01049-8.
*Narayana Kocherlakota (2010), '[http://www.minneapolisfed.org/publications_papers/pub_display.cfm?id=4428 Modern Macroeconomic Models as Tools for Economic Policy.]' ''The Region'', May 2010.
*Argia Sbordone, Andrea Tambalotti, Krishna Rao, and Kieran Walsh (2010), '[http://www.newyorkfed.org/research/epr/10v16n2/1010sbor.html Policy analysis using DSGE models: an introduction]'. ''Federal Reserve Bank of New York Economic Policy Review'' 16 (2).

==External links==
*[http://www.economicdynamics.org/society.htm Society for Economic Dynamics] - Website of the [[Society for Economic Dynamics]], dedicated to advances in DSGE modeling
*[http://www.dsge.net DSGE-NET] - International Network for DSGE modeling, monetary and fiscal policy
*[http://www.dynare.org DYNARE] - software for DSGE modeling
*[http://code.google.com/p/iris-toolbox-project/ IRIS] - software for DSGE modeling

[[Category:Macroeconomics and monetary economics]]
[[Category:General equilibrium and disequilibrium]]
[[Category:New classical macroeconomics]]
[[Category:New Keynesian economics]]

[[es:Equilibrio general dinámico estocástico]]
[[fr:Modèles stochastiques dynamiques d'équilibre général]]
[[nl:Dynamisch stochastisch algemeen evenwichtsmodel]]</text>
      <sha1>hn040m7efvnnif9m62tl5sjhc3yi1p3</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
