<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Economic growth</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>69415</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522433473</id>
      <parentid>522170026</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-11T04:48:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Collinpark</username>
        <id>2689211</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Data */ intelligentguess.com seems taken over by advertisers</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="66260">{{refimprove|date = April 2011}}

[[File:Gdp accumulated change.png|right|thumb|350px|[[GDP]] real growth rates, 1990–1998 and 1990–2006, in selected countries.]]

[[File:WeltBIPWorldgroupOECDengl.PNG|thumb|350px|Rate of change of [[Gross domestic product]], world and [[OECD]], since 1961]]

[[File:PPF expansion.svg|thumb|250px|right|Economic growth caused the [[production-possibility frontier]] to shift outward.]]

'''Economic growth''' is the increase in the amount of the goods and services produced by an [[economics|economy]] over time. It is conventionally measured as the percent rate of increase in ''real [[gross domestic product]]'', or ''real GDP''. Growth is usually calculated in ''real'' terms, i.e. [[real vs. nominal in economics|inflation-adjusted]] terms, in order to obviate the distorting effect of [[inflation]] on the price of the goods and services produced. In [[economics]], &quot;economic growth&quot; or &quot;economic growth theory&quot; typically refers to growth of [[potential output]], i.e., production at &quot;[[full employment]],&quot; which is caused by growth in [[aggregate demand]] or observed output.

As an area of study, ''economic growth'' is generally distinguished from ''[[development economics]]''. The former is primarily the study of how countries can advance their economies. The latter is the study of the economic aspects of the development process in low-income countries.

As economic growth is measured as the annual percent change of gross domestic product (GDP), it has all the advantages and drawbacks of that measure.

==Definitions and history==

===Economic growth versus the business cycle===
Economists distinguish between short-run economic changes in [[production (economics)|production]] and long-run economic growth. Short-run variation in economic growth is termed the ''[[business cycle]]''. Briefly, the business cycle is made up of booms and busts in production that occur over a period of months or years. The most recent example of a business cycle was the global boom starting in approximately 2002 that ended with the [[Late-2000s recession]]. As discussed in the article on the [[business cycle]], economists attribute the ups and downs in the [[business cycle]] to a number of causes including: overproduction of goods followed by large inventories that cannot be readily sold, overexpansion of credit resulting in piling up of debt that inhibits purchasing; speculative bubbles, and shocks—like wars, political upheavals, and so on.  

In contrast, the topic of '''economic growth''' is concerned with the long-run trend in production due to basic causes such as [[industrialization]]. The business cycle moves up and down, creating fluctuations in the long-run trend in economic growth.

===Historical sources of economic growth===
{{main|Productivity improving technologies (historical)}}

Economic growth has traditionally been attributed to increases in population, accumulation of capital, and increased productivity.&lt;ref name=&quot;www.sciencedirect.com&quot;&gt;Lucas, R. E. 1988. &quot;[http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/0304393288901687# On the mechanics of economic development],&quot; Journal of monetary economics, 22(1), 3-42. &lt;/ref&gt; 

Increases in productivity are a major factor responsible for per capita economic growth, especially since the mid-19th century.  Most of the economic growth in the 20th century was due to reduced inputs of labor, materials, energy, and land per unit of economic output (less input per widget).  The balance of growth has come from using more inputs overall because of the growth in output (more widgets or alternately more value added), including new kinds of goods and services (innovations).&lt;ref name=&quot;nber.org&quot;&gt;Kendrick, J. W. 1961 &quot;[http://www.nber.org/books/kend61-1 Productivity trends in the United States],&quot; Princeton University Press &lt;/ref&gt; 

Opening up new territories was considered a growth factor in the past, not being important since the late 19th century, except in a few areas areas such as Latin America, where forests were cleared in the 20th century for agriculture and in sub-Saharan Africa.&lt;ref&gt;{{ Cite journal
 | last1 = Fischer
| first1 =R. A.
| last2 =Byerlee
| first2 =Eric
| last3 =Edmeades
| first3 =E.  O.
| author1-link =
| title = Can Technology Deliver on the Yield Challenge to 2050
| year = 
|journal=Expert Meeting on How to Feed the World
|issue=
|pages=8
|publisher= Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations
| url = ftp://ftp.fao.org/docrep/fao/012/ak977e/ak977e00.pdf
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During colonial times, what ultimately mattered for economic growth were the institutions and systems of government imported through [[colonization]].  There is a clear reversal of fortune between the poor and wealthy countries, which is evident when comparing the method of [[colonialism]] in a region.  Geography and endowments of natural resources are not the sole determinants of GDP.  In fact, those that were blessed with good factor endowments experienced colonial extraction which only provided limited rapid growth; whereas, countries that were less fortunate in their original endowments experienced European settlement, relative equality, and demand for [[rule of law]].  These initially poor colonies end up developing an open franchise, equality, and broad public education, which helps them experience greater economic growth than the colonies that had exploited their [[economies of scale]].

During the [[Industrial Revolution]], [[mechanization]] began to replace hand methods in manufacturing and new processes were developed to make chemicals, iron, steel and other products.  [[Machine tool]]s made possible the economical production of metal parts to precise tolerances so that parts could be interchangeable.  See: [[Interchangeable parts].

During the [[Second Industrial Revolution]], a major factor of [[productivity]] was the substitution of energy from, human and animal labor, [[water power|water]] and wind power to [[electrification]] and internal combustion. Since that replacement, the great expansion of total power was driven by continuous improvements in energy conversion efficiency.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ayres-Warr2004&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal
| last1 = Ayres
| last2 = Warr
| first1 = Robert U.
| first2 = Benjamin
| author1-link =
| title = Accounting for Growth: The Role of Physical Work
| year = 2004
| url =http://www.abundancedebunked.com/downloads/Ayres-TheRoleOfPhysicalWork.pdf
| postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other major [[Productivity improving technologies (historical)|historical sources of productivity]] were [[automation]], transportation infrastructures (canals, railroads, and highways),&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
| last1 = Grubler
| first1 = Arnulf
| author1-link =
| title = The Rise and Fall of Infrastructures
| year = 1990
| url = http://www.iiasa.ac.at/Admin/PUB/Documents/XB-90-704.pdf
| postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;
}}&lt;/ref&gt; new materials (steel) and power, which includes steam and internal combustion engines and [[electrification|electricity]]. Other [[productivity]] improvements included [[mechanized agriculture]] and scientific agriculture including chemical [[fertilizer]]s and livestock and poultry management, and the [[Green Revolution]]. [[Interchangeable parts]] made with [[machine tools]] powered by [[electric motors]] evolved into [[mass production]], which is universally used today.
[[File:Cost of chicken in time worked.jpg|thumb|320px|right|Productivity lowered the cost of most items in terms of work time required to purchase.  Real food prices fell due to improvements in transportation and trade, [[mechanized agriculture]], [[fertilizers]], scientific farming and the [[Green Revolution]].]]
Great sources of productivity improvement in the late 19th century were the railroads, steam ships, horse-pulled [[reaper]]s and [[combine harvesters]], and [[steam engine|steam]]-powered factories. The invention of processes for making cheap [[steel]] were important for many forms of [[mechanization]] and transportation. By the late 19th century, power and machinery were creating overproduction, which eventually caused a reduction of the hourly work week. Prices fell because less labor, materials, and energy were required to produce and transport goods; however, workers real pay rose, allowing workers to improve their diet and buy consumer goods and better housing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wells1890&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|title=Recent Economic Changes and Their Effect on Production and Distribution of Wealth and Well-Being of Society
|last=Wells
|first=David A.
|authorlink=
|coauthors=
|year=1890 |publisher= D. Appleton and Co.|location= New York|isbn= 0-543-72474-3 |pages= |url= http://books.google.com/books?id=2V3qF4MWh_wC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=RECENT+ECONOMIC+CHANGES+AND+THEIR+EFFECT+ON+DISTRIBUTION+OF+WEALTH+AND+WELL+BEING+OF+SOCIETY+WELLS#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Mass production]] of the 1920s created overproduction, which was arguably one of several [[Causes of the Great Depression|causes]] of the [[Great Depression]] of the 1930s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Mass Production, the Stock Market Crash and the Great Depression |last=Beaudreau |first=Bernard C. |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=1996 |publisher=Authors Choice Press|location=New York, Lincoln, Shanghi |isbn= |pages= |url= }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Following the [[Great Depression]], economic growth resumed, aided in part by demand for entirely new goods and services, such as telephones, radio, television, automobiles, and household appliances, air conditioning, and commercial aviation (after 1950), creating enough new demand to stabilize the work week.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal| last1 = Moore
| first1 = Stephen
| last2 = Simon
| first2 = Julian
| author1-link =
| title = The Greatest Century That Ever Was: 25 Miraculous Trends of the last 100 Years, The Cato Institute: Policy Analysis, No. 364
| date = December  15, 1999
| url = http://www.cato.org/pubs/pas/pa364.pdf
| postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;
}}[[Diffusion curve]]s for various innovations start at Fig. 14&lt;/ref&gt;  Building of highway infrastructures also contributed to post World War II growth, as did capital investments in manufacturing and chemical industries.  The post World War II economy also benefited from the discovery of vast amounts of oil around the world, particularly in the Middle East.

Economic growth in Western nations slowed after 1973, but growth in [[Asia]] has been strong since then, starting with Japan and spreading to Korea, China, the [[Indian subcontinent]] and other parts of Asia. In 1957 [[South Korea]] had a lower per capita [[GDP]] than [[Ghana]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.independent.co.uk/news/education/education-news/leading-article-africa-has-to-spend-carefully-407666.html Leading article: Africa has to spend carefully]. The Independent. July 13, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; and by 2008 it was 17 times as high as Ghana's.&lt;ref&gt;Data refer to the year 2008. $26,341 GDP for Korea, $1513 for Ghana. ''World Economic Outlook Database-October 2008''. [[International Monetary Fund]].&lt;/ref&gt; The Japanese economic growth has slowed down considerably since late 1980s.

===Economic growth per capita===
Often, the concern about economic growth focuses on the desire to improve a country's [[standard of living]]—the level of goods and services that, on average, individuals purchase or otherwise gain access to. It should be noted that if population has grown along with economic production, increases in [[GDP]] do not necessarily result in an improvement in the standard of living. When the focus is on standard of living, economic growth is expressed on a per capita basis.&lt;ref name=&quot;ideas.repec.org&quot;&gt;Haidar, Jamal Ibrahim, 2009. &quot;[http://ideas.repec.org/a/eee/ecolet/v103y2009i1p1-4.html Investor protections and economic growth],&quot; Economics Letters, Elsevier, vol. 103(1), pages 1-4, April&lt;/ref&gt; 

Economic growth per capita is primarily driven by improvements in [[productivity]], also called [[economic efficiency]]. Increased productivity means producing more goods and services with the same inputs of labour, capital, energy, and/or materials. For example, labour and land productivity in agriculture were increased during the [[Green Revolution]]. The Green Revolution of the 1940s to 1970s introduced new grain hybrids, which increased yields around the world. 

However, there is not necessarily a long term one-to-one relationship between improvements in productivity and improvements in average standard of living.&lt;ref&gt;Gregory Clark, ''A Farewell to Alms, a Brief Economic History of the World'', Princeton University Press, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; Among other factors that might prevent a long-term improvement in standard of living despite economic growth is the potential for population growth matching or outstripping productivity improvements. When increased food supplies spur population growth rather than an improvement in the standard of living, people are said to be caught in the &quot;[[Malthusian trap]],&quot; named for [[Thomas Robert Malthus]], the first observer to detail out this dilemma. There is considerable controversy, for example, as to whether the Green Revolution resulted in long-term improvements in the standard of living as it was accompanied by rapid population growth creating population sizes that may be unsustainable.&lt;ref&gt;Spitz, Pierre (1987)&quot;The Green Revolution Re-Examined in India in Glass&quot;. In Glaeser, Bernhard. The Green Revolution revisited: critique and alternatives. Allen &amp; Unwin. pp. 57–75. ISBN 0-04-630014-7&lt;/ref&gt;

A high savings rate is also linked to the standard of living. Higher saving will in the long run lead to a permanently higher output (income) per capita as capital accumulation per individual also increases.{{citation needed|date=July 2012}}

Economic growth can also be of interest without reference to per capita changes in standard of living. An example of this is the economic growth in England during the [[Industrial Revolution]]. Certainly, per capita increases in productivity occurred due to the replacement of hand labour by machines. However, economic growth during this period was in large part so dramatic because England's population simultaneously increased very rapidly (1700 – 1860). The two factors together, more production per worker combined with many more workers, resulted in a sixfold increase in production between 1700 and 1860. Population growth alone accounted for most of this increase.&lt;ref&gt;Gregory Clark, ''A Farewell to Alms, a Brief Economic History of the World'', Princeton University Press, 2007, pages 245–246 and Figure 12.8.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Measuring economic growth===
Economic growth is measured as a percentage change in the [[Gross Domestic Product]] (GDP) or [[Gross National Product]] (GNP). These two measures, which are calculated slightly differently, total the amounts paid for the goods and services that a country produced. As an example of measuring economic growth, a country which creates $9,000,000,000 in goods and services in 2010 and then creates $9,090,000,000 in 2011, has a nominal economic growth rate of 1% for 2011. 

In order to compare per capita economic growth among countries, the total sales of the countries to be compared may be quoted in a single currency. This requires converting the value of currencies of various countries into a selected currency, for example U.S. dollars. One way to do this conversion is to rely on [[exchange rates]] among the currencies, for example how many [[Mexican pesos]] buy a single U.S. dollar? Another approach is to use the [[purchasing power parity]] method. This method is based on how much consumers must pay for the same &quot;basket of goods&quot; in each country.  

[[Inflation]] or [[deflation]] can make it difficult to measure economic growth. If GDP, for example, goes up in a country by 1% in a year, was this due solely to rising prices (inflation) or because more goods and services were produced and saved? To express real growth rather than changes in prices for the same goods, statistics on economic growth are often adjusted for inflation or deflation. 

For example, a table may show changes in GDP in the period 1990 to 2000, as expressed in 1990 U.S. dollars. This means that the single currency being used is the U.S. dollar with the purchasing power it had in the U.S. in 1990. The table might mention that the figures are &quot;inflation-adjusted&quot; or [[real versus nominal value (economics)|real]]. If no adjustment were made for inflation, the table might make no mention of inflation-adjustment or might mention that the prices are [[real versus nominal value (economics)|nominal]].

===The power of annual growth===

Over long periods of time, even small rates of growth, like a 2% annual increase, will have large effects. For example, the United Kingdom experienced a 1.97% average annual increase in inflation-adjusted GDP between 1830 and 2008.&lt;ref&gt;Lawrence H. Officer, &quot;What Was the U.K. GDP Then?&quot; MeasuringWorth, 2011. URL:http://www.measuringworth.com/ukgdp/&lt;/ref&gt; In 1830, the GDP was 41,373 million pounds. It grew to 1,330,088 million pounds by 2008. (Figures are adjusted for inflation and stated in 2005 values for the pound.) A growth rate which averaged 1.97% over 178 years resulted in a 32-fold increase in GDP by 2008. 

The large impact of a relatively small growth rate over a long period of time is due to the power of [[compound interest|compounding]] (also see [[exponential growth]]). A growth rate of 2.5% per annum leads to a doubling of GDP within 29 years, whilst a growth rate of 8% per annum (an average exceeded by [[Historical GDP of the People's Republic of China|China]] between 2000 and 2010) leads to a doubling of GDP within 10 years. Thus, a small difference in economic growth rates between countries can result in very different standards of living for their populations if this small difference continues for many years.

==Theories of economic growth {{anchor|theory}}==

===Classical growth theory===
[[File:Smith.gif|thumb|right|170px|Adam Smith wrote ''[[The Wealth of Nations]]'']]
The modern conception of economic growth began with the critique of [[Mercantilism]], especially by the [[physiocrats]] and with the [[Scottish Enlightenment]] thinkers such as [[David Hume]] and [[Adam Smith]], and the foundation of the discipline of modern [[political economy]]. 

[[David Ricardo]] argued that trade was a benefit to a country, because if one could buy a good more cheaply from abroad, it meant that there was more profitable work to be done here. This theory of &quot;[[comparative advantage]]&quot; would be the central basis for arguments in favor of [[free trade]] as an essential component of growth.&lt;ref&gt;The Theory of Comparative Advantage http://internationalecon.com/Trade/Tch40/T40-0.php&lt;/ref&gt;

===The neoclassical growth model===
The notion of growth as increased stocks of capital goods ([[means of production]]) was codified as the [[Exogenous growth model|Solow-Swan Growth Model]], which involved a series of equations which showed the relationship between labor-time, capital goods, output, and investment. According to this view, the role of [[technological change]] became crucial, even more important than the [[capital accumulation|accumulation of capital]].  This model, developed by [[Robert Solow]]&lt;ref&gt;Robert M. Solow (1956), &quot;A Contribution to the Theory of Economic Growth,&quot; ''Quarterly Journal of Economics'', 70(1), p [http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0033-5533%28195602%2970%3A1%3C65%3AACTTTO%3E2.0.CO%3B2-M&amp;size=LARGE&amp;origin=JSTOR-enlargePage p. 65]-94.&lt;/ref&gt;  and [[Trevor Swan]]&lt;ref&gt;Trevor W. Swan (1956). &quot;Economic Growth and Capital Accumulation', ''Economic Record'', 32, pp. 334–61.&lt;/ref&gt; in the 1950s, was the first attempt to model long-run growth analytically.  This model assumes that countries use their resources [[Efficiency (economics)|efficiently]] and that there are [[diminishing returns]] to capital and labor increases. From these two premises, the neoclassical model makes three important predictions. First, increasing capital relative to labor creates economic growth, since people can be more productive given more capital. Second, poor countries with less capital per person will grow faster because each investment in capital will produce a higher return than rich countries with ample capital. Third, because of diminishing returns to capital, economies will eventually reach a point at which any increase in capital will no longer create economic growth. This point is called a &quot;[[steady state economy|steady state]]&quot;.

The model also notes that countries can overcome this steady state and continue growing by inventing new technology. In the long run, output per capital depends on the rate of saving, but the rate of output growth should be equal for any saving rate. In this model, the process by which countries continue growing despite the diminishing returns is &quot;exogenous&quot; and represents the creation of new technology that allows production with fewer resources. Technology improves, the steady state level of capital increases, and the country invests and grows. The data does not support some of this model's predictions, in particular, that all countries grow at the same rate in the long run, or that poorer countries should grow faster until they reach their steady state. Also, the data suggests the world has slowly increased its rate of growth.

However, modern economic research shows that the baseline version of the neoclassical model of economic growth is not supported by the evidence. {{Citation needed|date=April 2012}}

===Salter cycle===
According to the Salter cycle, economic growth is enabled by increases in [[productivity]], which lowers the inputs (labour, capital, material, energy, etc.) for a given amount of product (output).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book 
|title=Productivity Trends in the United States
|last=Kendrick	
|first=John W.
|authorlink= 
|coauthors= 
|year=1961 |publisher= Princeton University Press for NBER|location= |isbn= |page=111 |url= }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Lowered cost increases [[demand]] for goods and services, which also results in capital investment to increase capacity.  New capacity is more efficient because of new technology, improved methods and economies of scale.  This leads to further price reductions, which further increases demand, until markets become saturated due to diminishing [[marginal utility]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
|title=Turning Point: an End to the Growth Paradigm
 |last=Ayres
 |first= Robert U.
|authorlink= 
|year=1998 |publisher =Earthscan Publications
|location= London
|isbn= |pages= 193–4|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=maHS2Ta_nIUC&amp;pg=PA193&amp;lpg=PA193&amp;dq=salter+cycle+economics&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Ppk_En8KkV&amp;sig=aLsfYP5EvxZT1Ep4ch5hwFeLDHQ&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=U5wwT6yqO5C5twfaru2BBw&amp;ved=0CEgQ6AEwBw#v=onepage&amp;q=salter%20cycle%20economics&amp;f=false}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fraw.org.uk/files/economics/ayres_2001.pdf ''Two Paradigms of Production and Growth'' Robert Ayres &amp; Benjamin Warr]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Endogenous growth theory===
{{Main|Endogenous growth theory}}
[[File:Global Competitiveness Index 2008-2009.svg|thumb|250px|World map of the 2008–2009 [[Global Competitiveness Index]].]]
Growth theory advanced again with  theories of economist [[Paul Romer]] and [[Robert Lucas, Jr.]] in the late 1980s and early 1990s.

Unsatisfied with Solow's explanation, economists worked to &quot;endogenize&quot; technology in the 1980s.  They developed the [[endogenous growth theory]] that includes a mathematical explanation of technological advancement.&lt;ref&gt;Romer, 1986&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lucas, 1988&lt;/ref&gt;  This model also incorporated a new concept of [[human capital]], the skills and knowledge that make workers productive. Unlike [[physical capital]], human capital has increasing rates of return. Therefore, overall there are constant returns to capital, and economies never reach a [[steady state economy|steady state]]. Growth does not slow as capital accumulates, but the rate of growth depends on the types of capital a country invests in.  Research done in this area has focused on what increases [[human capital]] (e.g. [[education]]) or technological change (e.g. [[innovation]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;mystery&quot;&gt;Elhanah Helpman, [http://www.amazon.com/dp/067401572X/ The Mystery of Economic Growth], Havard University Press, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[John Joseph Puthenkalam]]'s research aims at the process of economic growth theories that lead to economic development. After analyzing the existing capitalistic growth-development theoretical apparatus, he introduces the new model which integrates the variables of freedom, democracy and human rights into the existing models and argue that any future economic growth-development of any nation depends on this emerging model as we witness the third wave of unfolding demand for democracy in the Middle East. He develops the knowledge sector in growth theories with two new concepts of 'micro knowledge' and 'macro knowledge'. Micro knowledge is what an individual learns from school or from various existing knowledge and macro knowledge is the core philosophical thinking of a nation that all individuals inherently receive. How to combine both these knowledge would determine further growth that leads to economic development of developing nations. For further reading, please refer to &quot;Integrating Freedom, Democracy and Human Rights into Theories of Economic Growth&quot; (1998,2000&amp;2009).

===Energy and energy efficiency theories===
The importance of energy to economic growth was emphasized by [[William Stanley Jevons]] in ''[[The Coal Question]]''  in which he described the [[Rebound effect (conservation)|rebound effect]] based on the observation that increasing energy efficiency resulted in more use of energy.  (See: [[Jevons paradox]])  In the 1980s, the economists Daniel Khazzoom and Leonard Brookes independently put forward ideas about energy consumption and behavior that argue that increased energy efficiency paradoxically tends to lead to increased energy consumption.  In 1992, the US economist Harry Saunders dubbed this hypothesis the ''[[Khazzoom–Brookes postulate]]'', and showed that it was true under neo-classical growth theory over a wide range of assumptions.&lt;ref&gt;Harry D. Saunders, &quot;The Khazzoom-Brookes postulate and neoclassical growth&quot;, ''The Energy Journal'', October 1, 1992.&lt;/ref&gt;

Ayres and Warr have presented a model that aims to address deficiencies in the neo-classical and endogenous growth models.  It claims that physical and chemical work performed by energy, or more correctly exergy, has historically been a very important driver of economic growth.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ayres-Warr2004&quot; /&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal
| last1 = Ayres
| last2 = Warr
| first1 = Robert U.
| first2 = Benjamin
| author1-link =
| title = Economic growth, technological progress and energy use in the U.S. over the last century: Identifying common trends and structural change in macroeconomic time series, INSEAD
| year = 2006
| url = http://www.helsinki.fi/iehc2006/papers2/Warr.pdf
| postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;
}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Key support for this theory is a mathematical model showing that the efficiency of a composite indicator using electrical generation and other energy efficiencies is a good proxy for the [[Solow residual]], or technological progress, that is, the portion of economic growth that is not attributable to capital or labor.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal
| last1 = Ayres
| last2 = Ayres
| last3 =Warr
| first1 = R. U.
| first2 = L. W.
| first3 =B.
| author1-link =
| title = Exergy, Power and Work in the U. S. Economy 1900-1998, Insead's Center For the Management of Environmental Resources, 2002/52/EPS/CMER
| year = 2002
| url =http://flora.insead.edu/fichiersti_wp/inseadwp2002/2002-52.pdf
| postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|title=The Economic Growth Engine: How Energy and Work Drive Material Prosperity (The International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis)
|last1=Ayres
|first1=Robert
|last2=Warr
|first2= Banjamin
|authorlink=
|coauthors=
|year=|publisher= Edward Elgar Publishing; Reprint edition (October 31, 2010) |location= |isbn= 1-84980-435-4 |pages= |url= }}&lt;/ref&gt;  

Energy growth theory economists have criticized orthodox economics for neglecting the role of energy and natural resources.  Ayres and Warr's model relates the slowing of economic growth to energy conversion efficiencies approaching thermodynamic limits, and cautions that declining resource quality could bring an end to economic growth in a few decades.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ayres-Warr2009&quot;&gt;[[Robert Ayres (scientist)|Robert U. Ayres]] and Benjamin Warr, ''The Economic Growth Engine: How useful work creates material prosperity'', 2009. ISBN 978-1-84844-182-8&lt;/ref&gt; Hall et al. 2001 state: &quot;Although the first and second laws of thermodynamics are the most thoroughly tested and validated laws of nature [..] the basic neoclassical economic model is a perpetual motion machine, with no required inputs or limits.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal  
| last1 = Hall
| last2 = Lindenberger
| last3 = Kümmel
| last4 = Kroeger
| last5 = Eichhorn
| first1 = Charles
| first2 = Dietmar
| first3 = Reiner
| first4 = Timm
| first5 = Wolfgang
| author1-link =
| title = The Need to Reintegrate the Natural Sciences with Economics
| journal = BioScience
| volume = 51
| issue = 8
| pages = 663–673
| year = 2001
| url = http://www.bioone.org/doi/abs/10.1641/0006-3568%282001%29051%5B0663%3ATNTRTN%5D2.0.CO%3B2
| postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Theory of cognitive wealth (cognitive capitalism)===
The theory of &quot;Cognitive capitalism&quot; asserts that cognitive ability is the crucial factor which creates wealth in modern economies, and that the geographical factors which have been necessary in ancient societies are no longer so important. The average cognitive ability of a nation determines its wealth, each IQ point increase boosting a country's average GDP by $229. Of even more significance, the IQ of the brightest 5% of people in the nation (the cognitive elite) boosts GDP by $468 per IQ point. The cognitive elite support general efficiency, technological innovation, efficient administration, independent institutions, and economic freedom. Via these factors intelligence and knowledge stimulate growth leading to national wealth, which in turn may boost cognitive ability in a [[virtuous circle and vicious circle|virtuous circle]].
The theory was developed by the two psychologists Heiner Rindermann and James Thompson.&lt;ref&gt;Rindermann, H. &amp; Thompson, J. (2011). Cognitive capitalism: The effect of cognitive ability on wealth, as mediated through scientific achievement and economic freedom. ''Psychological Science'', ''22'', 754–763.&lt;/ref&gt; The theory is related to human capital theory.

===Unified growth theory===
[[Unified growth theory]] was developed by [[Oded Galor]] and his co-authors to address the inability of endogenous growth theory to explain key empirical regularities in the growth processes of individual economies and the world economy as a whole. Endogenous growth theory was satisfied with accounting for empirical regularities in the growth process of developed economies over the last hundred years. As a consequence, it was not able to explain the qualitatively different empirical regularities that characterized the growth process over longer time horizons in both developed and less developed economies. Unified growth theories are endogenous growth theories that are consistent with the entire process of development, and in particular the transition from the epoch of Malthusian stagnation that had characterized most of the process of development to the contemporary era of sustained economic growth.&lt;ref&gt;Galor O., 2005, From Stagnation to Growth: Unified Growth Theory. Handbook of Economic Growth, Elsevier&lt;/ref&gt;

===The big push===
In theories of economic growth, the mechanisms that let it take place and its main determinants are abundant. One popular theory in the 1940s, for example, was that of the &quot;[[Big Push Model|Big Push]]&quot; which suggested that countries needed to jump from one stage of development to another through a [[virtuous cycle]], in which large investments in infrastructure and education coupled with private investments would move the economy to a more productive stage, breaking free from economic paradigms appropriate to a lower productivity stage.&lt;ref&gt;[[Paul Rosenstein-Rodan]] {{specify|date=November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Schumpeterian Growth===
'''Schumpeterian growth''' is an [[economic theory]] named after the 20th century [[Austrians|Austrian]] [[economist]] [[Joseph Schumpeter]]. Unlike other economic growth theories, his approach explains growth by [[innovation]] as a process of creative destruction, which captures the dual nature of technological progress: in terms of [[creation]], entrepreneurs introduce new products or processes in the hope that they will enjoy temporary monopoly-like profits as they capture markets. In doing so, they make old technologies or products obsolete: this is the [[destruction]]{{disambiguation needed|date=August 2012}} referred to by Schumpeter, that could also be referred to as the annulment of previous technologies which makes them obsolete, and &quot;which destroys the rents generated by previous innovations&quot; (Aghion 855).&lt;ref&gt;• Quote from [[Philippe Aghion]], 2002, [http://dash.harvard.edu/bitstream/handle/1/3350067/aghion_schumpeterian.pdf?sequence=2 ''Schumpeterian Growth Theory and the Dynamics of Income Inequality''], [[Econometrica]], 70(3), 855–882.&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; • Also see Wendy Carlin and David Soskice, 2006, ''Macroeconomics: Imperfections, Institutions &amp; Policies'', specifically chapter 14.&lt;/ref&gt; A major model that illustrates [[Schumpeterian growth]] is the Aghion-Howitt model.&lt;ref&gt;• [[Philippe Aghion]] and Peter Howitt, 1992, [http://www.signallake.com/innovation/CreativeDestructionModelMarch1992.pdf ''A Model of Growth Through Creative Destruction''], [[Econometrica]], 60(2), 323-351.&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; • [[Philippe Aghion]], 2002, [http://dash.harvard.edu/bitstream/handle/1/3350067/aghion_schumpeterian.pdf?sequence=2 ''Schumpeterian Growth Theory and the Dynamics of Income Inequality''], [[Econometrica]], 70(3), 855–882.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Institutions and growth==
According to [[Daron Acemoğlu|Acemoğlu]], [[Simon Johnson (economist)|Simon Johnson]] and [[James Robinson]], the positive correlation between high income and cold climate is a by-product of history. Europeans adopted very different colonization policies in different colonies, with different associated institutions. In places where these colonizers faced high mortality rates (e.g., due to the presence of tropical diseases), they could not settle permanently, and they were thus more likely to establish extractive institutions, which persisted after independence; in places where they could settle permanently (e.g. those with temperate climates), they established institutions with this objective in mind and modeled them after those in their European homelands. In these 'neo-Europes' better institutions in turn produced better development outcomes. Thus, although other economists focus on the identity or type of legal system of the colonizers to explain institutions, these authors look at the environmental conditions in the colonies to explain institutions. For instance, former colonies have inherited corrupt governments and geo-political boundaries (set by the colonizers) that are not properly placed regarding the geographical locations of different ethnic groups, creating internal disputes and conflicts which in turn hinder development. In another example, societies that emerged in colonies without solid native populations established better property rights and incentives for long-term investment than those where native populations were large.&lt;ref name=&quot;ideas.repec.org&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Daron Acemoğlu]], [[Simon Johnson (economist)|Simon Johnson]] and James A. Robinson.[http://www.iser.uaa.alaska.edu/iser/people/colt/econ337_f03/acemoglu_institutions_aer2001.pdf The Colonial Origins of Comparative Development: An Empirical Investigation.] ''[[American Economic Review]]'' 91(5): 1369–401. 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Human capital and growth==
One ubiquitous element of both theoretical and empirical analyses of economic growth is the role of [[human capital]].  The skills of the population enter into both neoclassical and endogenous growth models.&lt;ref&gt;• [[N. Gregory Mankiw|Mankiw, N. Gregory]], [[David Romer]], and David Weil. 1992. &quot;A contribution to the empirics of economic growth.&quot; Quarterly Journal of Economics 107, no. 2 (May): [http://econ.nyu.edu/user/debraj/Courses/Readings/MankiwRomerWeil.pdf 407-437]&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; • Sala-i-Martin, Xavier, Gernot Doppelhofer, and Ronald I. Miller. 2004. &quot;Determinants of long-term growth: A Bayesian Averaging of Classical Estimates (BACE) approach.&quot; American Economic Review 94, no. 4 (September): 813–835.&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; • Lud[[Paul Romer|Romer, Paul.]] 1990. &quot;Human capital and growth: Theory and evidence.&quot; Carnegie-Rochester Conference Series on Public Policy 32: 251–286.&lt;/ref&gt;  The most commonly used measure of human capital is the level of school attainment in a country, building upon the data development of [[Robert Barro]] and Jong-Wha Lee.&lt;ref&gt;[[Robert Barro|Barro, Robert J.]], and Jong-Wha Lee. 2001. &quot;International data on educational attainment: Updates and implications.&quot; Oxford Economic Papers 53, no. 3 (July): 541–563.&lt;/ref&gt;  This measure of human capital, however, requires the strong assumption that what is learned in a year of schooling is the same across all countries.  It also presumes that human capital is only developed in formal schooling, contrary to the extensive evidence that families, neighborhoods, peers, and health also contribute to the development of human capital.  In order to measure human capital more accurately, [[Eric Hanushek]] and Dennis Kimko introduced measures of mathematics and science skills from international assessments into growth analysis.&lt;ref&gt;[[Eric Hanushek|Hanushek, Eric A.]], and Dennis D. Kimko. 2000. &quot;Schooling, labor force quality, and the growth of nations.&quot; American Economic Review 90, no. 5 (December): 1184–1208 [http://hanushek.stanford.edu/publications/schooling-labor-force-quality-and-growth-nations]&lt;/ref&gt;  They found that quality of human capital was very significantly related to economic growth.  This approach has been extended by a variety of authors, and the evidence indicates that economic growth is very closely related to the cognitive skills of the population.&lt;ref&gt;• [[Eric Hanushek|Hanushek, Eric A.]], and Ludger Woessmann. 2008. &quot;The role of cognitive skills in economic development.&quot; Journal of Economic Literature 46, no. 3 (September): 607–668 [http://hanushek.stanford.edu/publications/role-cognitive-skills-economic-development].&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; • [[Eric Hanushek|Hanushek, Eric A.]], and Ludger Woessmann. 2011. &quot;How much do educational outcomes matter in OECD countries?&quot; Economic Policy, 26, no. 67: 427–491.[http://hanushek.stanford.edu/publications/how-much-do-educational-outcomes-matter-oecd-countries]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Inequality and economic growth==

[[File:Berg Ostry 2011 Chart 4.gif|thumb|right|Percentage changes in GDP growth spell length as each factor moves from 50th to 60th percentile and all other factors are held constant. '''Income distribution is measured by the [[Gini coefficient]].''' Political institutions are measured by the Polity IV Project scale. Exchange rate competitiveness is measured by rate deviation from purchasing power parity adjusted for per capita income.&lt;ref name=BergOstryEE /&gt;]]

Initial theories incorrectly stated that inequality had a positive effect on economic development. The marginal propensity to save was thought to increas with wealth and inequality increases savings and capital accumulation.&lt;ref&gt;Kaldor, Nicoals, 1955, Alternative Theories of Distribution,” Review of Economic Studies, 23(2), 83-100.&lt;/ref&gt; However, it was determined much later that the analysis based on comparing yearly equality figures to yearly growth rates was flawed and misleading because it takes several years for the effects of equality changes to manifest in economic growth changes.&lt;ref name=BergOstryEE&gt;{{Cite journal |last= Berg |first= Andrew G. |last2= Ostry |first2= Jonathan D. |year= 2011 |title= Equality and Efficiency |journal= Finance and Development |volume= 48 |issue= 3 |publisher= International Monetary Fund |url= http://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/fandd/2011/09/berg.htm |accessdate= September 10, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The credit market imperfection approach, developed by Galor and Zeira (1993), demonstrates that inequality in the presence of credit market imperfections has a long lasting detrimental effect on human capital formation and economic development.&lt;ref&gt;Galor, Oded and Joseph Zeira, 1993, &quot;Income Distribution and Macroeconomics,&quot; Review of Economic Studies, 60(1), 35-52.&lt;/ref&gt;

The political economy approach, developed by Alesian and Rodrik (1994) and Persson and Tabellini (1994), argues that inequality is harmful for economic development because inequality generates a pressure to adopt redistributive policies that have an adverse effect on investment and economic growth.&lt;ref&gt;Alesina, Alberto and Dani Rodrik, 1994. &quot;Distributive Politics and Economic Growth,&quot; Quarterly Journal of Economics, 109(2), 65-90; Persson, Torsten and Guido Tabellini, 1994, “Is Inequality Harmful for Growth?” American Economic Review 84(3), 600-621.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Evidence===

A study by Perotti (1996) examines of the channels through which inequality may affect economic growth. He shows that in accordance with the credit market imperfection approach, inequality is associated with lower level of human capital formation (education, experience, apprenticeship) and higher level of fertility, while lower level of human capital is associated with lower growth and lower levels of economic growth.  In contrast, his examination of the political economy channel refutes the political economy mechanism. He  demonstrates that inequality is associated with lower levels of taxation, while lower levels of taxation, contrary to the theories, are associated with lower level of economic growth&lt;ref&gt;Perotti, Roberto, 1996, “Growth, Income Distribution, and Democracy: What the Data Say” ''Journal of Economic Growth'', 1(2), 149-187.&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2011 note for the [[International Monetary Fund]] by Andrew G. Berg and Jonathan D. Ostry found a strong association between lower levels of inequality in developing countries and sustained periods of economic growth. Developing countries with high inequality have &quot;succeeded in initiating growth at high rates for a few years&quot; but &quot;longer growth spells are robustly associated with more equality in the income distribution.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/sdn/2011/sdn1108.pdf Inequality and Unsustainable Growth: Two Sides of the Same Coin?] Andrew G. Berg and Jonathan D. Ostry| IMF STAFF DISCUSSION NOTE | April 8, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

Disputing the claim of a [[Washington Post]] editorialist that &quot;Western Europe’s recent history suggests that flat income distribution accompanies flat economic growth,&quot; journalist [[Timothy Noah]], points out that redistribution policies in Europe do not seem to be correlated to economic problems of the late twenty-oughts.  With the exception of Ireland, the countries at risk of default in 2011 (Greece, Italy, Spain, Portugal) were notable for their high Gini-measured levels of income inequality compared to other European countries. As measured by the Gini index, Greece as of 2008 had more income inequality than the economically healthy Germany.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tnr.com/blog/timothy-noah/98781/inequality-necessary &quot;Is Inequality Necessary?&quot;] by Timothy Noah, ''The New Republic'' December 20, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

==Quality of life==
Happiness has been shown to increase with a higher [[GDP per capita]], at least up to a level of $15,000 per person.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cato.org/pub_display.php?pub_id=8179 In Pursuit of Happiness Research. Is It Reliable? What Does It Imply for Policy?] The Cato institute. April 11, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; 

Economic growth has the indirect potential to alleviate poverty, as a result of a simultaneous increase in employment opportunities and increase [[labour productivity]].&lt;ref name=ODI2&gt;Claire Melamed, Renate Hartwig and Ursula Grant 2011. [http://www.odi.org.uk/resources/details.asp?id=5752&amp;title=jobs-growth-poverty-employment Jobs, growth and poverty: what do we know, what don't we know, what should we know?] London: [[Overseas Development Institute]]&lt;/ref&gt; A study by researchers at the [[Overseas Development Institute]] (ODI) of 24 countries that experienced growth found that in 18 cases, poverty was alleviated.&lt;ref name=ODI2/&gt; However, employment is no guarantee of escaping [[poverty]], the [[International Labour Organisation]] (ILO) estimates that as many as 40% of workers as poor, not earning enough to keep their families above the $2 a day [[poverty line]].&lt;ref name=ODI2/&gt; For instance, in [[India]] most of the chronically poor are wage earners in formal employment, because their jobs are insecure and low paid and offer no chance to accumulate wealth to avoid risks.&lt;ref name=ODI2/&gt; This appears to be the result of a negative relationship between employment creation and increased productivity, when a simultaneous positive increase is required to reduced poverty. According to the [[UNRISD]], increasing labour productivity appears to have a negative impact on job creation: in the 1960s, a 1% increase in output per worker was associated with a reduction in employment growth of 0.07%, by the first decade of this century the same productivity increase implies reduced employment growth by 0.54%.&lt;ref name=ODI2/&gt; 

Increases in employment without increases in productivity leads to a rise in the number of &quot;working poor&quot;, which is why some experts are now promoting the creation of &quot;quality&quot; and not &quot;quantity&quot; in labour market policies.&lt;ref name=ODI2/&gt; This approach does highlight how higher productivity has helped reduce poverty in [[East Asia]], but the negative impact is beginning to show.&lt;ref name=ODI2/&gt; In [[Vietnam]], for example, employment growth has slowed while productivity growth has continued.&lt;ref name=ODI2/&gt; Furthermore, productivity increases do not always lead to increased wages, as can be seen in the [[United States]], where the gap between productivity and wages has been rising since the 1980s.&lt;ref name=ODI2/&gt; The ODI study showed that other sectors were just as important in reducing unemployment, as [[manufacturing]].&lt;ref name=ODI2/&gt; The [[services sector]] is most effective at translating productivity growth into employment growth. [[Agriculture]] provides a safety net for jobs and economic buffer when other sectors are struggling.&lt;ref name=ODI2/&gt; This study suggests a more nuanced understanding of economic growth and quality of life and poverty alleviation.

Opportunities, education, health, security and a healthy environment contribute to the quality of life. Public policy plays a great role happiness, as Petra Pinzler points out in [http://www.dandc.eu/articles/220391/index.en.shtml D+C Development and Cooperation].

==Negative effects of economic growth==
A number of critical arguments have been raised against economic growth.&lt;ref name=&quot;PoM&quot;&gt;Case, K.E., and Fair, R.C.  2006. ''Principles of Macroeconomics.''  Prentice Hall. ISBN 0-13-222645-6, ISBN 978-0-13-222645-5.&lt;/ref&gt;

It may be that economic growth improves the quality of life up to a point, after which it doesn't improve the quality of life, but rather obstructs sustainable living.&lt;ref name='http://www.pnas.org/content/106/8/2483.short'&gt;{{cite pmid|19240221}}&lt;/ref&gt; Historically, sustained growth has reached its limits (and turned to catastrophic decline) when perturbations to the environmental system last long enough to destabilise the bases of a culture.&lt;ref name='http://www.pnas.org/content/106/8/2483.short'/&gt;

===Resource depletion===
Many earlier predictions of resource depletion, such as [[Thomas Malthus]]' 1798 predictions about approaching famines in Europe, ''[[The Population Bomb]]'' (1968),&lt;ref name=&quot;oswego.edu&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oswego.edu/~edunne/200ch17.html |title=Chapter 17: Growth and Productivity-The Long-Run Possibilities |publisher=Oswego.edu |date=1999-06-10 |accessdate=2010-12-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;reason.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Ronald Bailey |url=http://www.reason.com/news/show/34758.html |title=Science and Public Policy - Reason Magazine |publisher=Reason.com |date=2004-02-04 |accessdate=2010-12-22|unused_data=February 4, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;aei.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Hayward |first=Steven F. |url=http://www.aei.org/publications/pubID.21588/pub_detail.asp |title=That Old Time Religion |publisher=AEI |date= |accessdate=2010-12-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Limits to Growth]]'' (1972),&lt;ref name=&quot;oswego.edu&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;reason.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;aei.org&quot;/&gt; and the [[Simon–Ehrlich wager]] (1980) &lt;ref name=&quot;wired.com&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.wired.com/wired/archive/5.02/ffsimon_pr.html | work=Wired | first=Ed | last=Regis}}&lt;/ref&gt; did not materialize, nor has diminished production of most resources occurred so far, one reason being that advancements in technology and science have allowed some previously unavailable resources to be produced.&lt;ref name=&quot;wired.com&quot;/&gt;  In some cases, substitution of more abundant materials, such as plastics for cast metals, lowered growth of usage for some metals.  In the case of the limited resource of land, famine was relieved firstly by the revolution in transportation caused by railroads and steam ships, and later by the [[Green Revolution]] and chemical fertilizers, especially the [[Haber process]] for ammonia synthesis.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wells1891&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|title=Recent Economic Changes and Their Effect on Production and Distribution of Wealth and Well-Being of Society
|last=Wells
|first=David A.
|authorlink=
|coauthors=
|year=1891 |publisher= D. Appleton and Co.|location= New York|isbn= 0-543-72474-3 |pages= |url= http://books.google.com/?id=2V3qF4MWh_wC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=RECENT+ECONOMIC+CHANGES+AND+THEIR+EFFECT+ON+DISTRIBUTION+OF+WEALTH+AND+WELL+BEING+OF+SOCIETY+WELLS#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false }}Opening line of the Preface.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= Enriching the Earth: Fritz Haber, Carl Bosch, and the Transformation of World Food Production
|last=Smil
|first=Vaclav |authorlink=
|coauthors=
|year=2004
|publisher= MIT Press|location=
|isbn= 0-262-69313-5
|pages=
|url= }}&lt;/ref&gt;  
[[File:Hubbert peak oil plot.svg|right|thumb|250px|[[M. King Hubbert]]'s prediction of world [[petroleum]] production rates. Virtually all economic sectors rely heavily on petroleum.]]
In the case of minerals, lower grades of mineral resources are being extracted, requiring higher inputs of capital and energy for both extraction and processing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= Energy and Resource Quality: The ecology of the Economic Process |last1=Hall |first1=Charles A.S. |authorlink=
|last2= Cleveland |first2=Cutler J.
|last3=Kaufmann |first3=Robert
|coauthors= |year=1992 |publisher= University Press of Colorado |location= Niwot, Colorado |isbn=  |pages=|url= }}&lt;/ref&gt;  An example is [[natural gas]] from shale and other low permeability rock, which can be developed with much higher inputs of energy, capital, and materials than conventional gas in previous decades.  Another example is offshore oil and gas, which has exponentially increasing cost as water depth increases.

Some &quot;Malthusians&quot;, such as [[William R. Catton, Jr.]], author of the 1980 book &quot;Overshoot,&quot; are skeptical of these various advancements in technology which make available previously inaccessible or lower grade resources. The counter-argument is that such advances as well as increases in efficiency merely accelerate the drawing down of finite resources. Catton has referred to the contemporary increases in rates of resource extraction as &quot;stealing ravenously from the future.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Overshoot&quot; by William Catton, p. 3 [1980]&lt;/ref&gt; The apparent and temporary &quot;increase&quot; of resource extraction with the use of new technology leads to the popular perception that resources are infinite or can be substituted without limit, but this perception fails to consider that ultimately, even lower quality resources are finite and become uneconomic to extract when the ore quality is too low. Because of cultural lag, the perception of infinite resources and substitutes may linger on for generations, and may not change, since the inevitable resource bankruptcy is passed on to posterity. Catton has called the faith in technology a form of &quot;cargoism,&quot; which takes its meaning from various &quot;[[Cargo Cults]]&quot; in Melanesia and Micronesia. Furthermore, [[Joseph Tainter]], anthropologist, historian and author of the book &quot;The Collapse of Complex Societies,&quot; has pointed out that each new addition of complexity to technology can only be sustained if there is a good enough return to justify the technology, and that over time, increases in complexity have improved productivity at an ever decreasing rate. As an example, in the early 20th century when much of the world's oil was untapped, it was sufficient to drill a few metres into the ground and install inexpensive rigs to extract oil at rapid rates. At the beginning of the 21st century, in order to achieve the same flowrates or less, oilfields must be drilled much deeper and managed with sophisticated techniques and equipment costing many hundreds of millions of dollars. If such trends continue, there may arrive a time when it becomes uneconomic to increase complexity in order to access lower grade resources with no net improvement in productivity.

===Environmental impact===
[[File:Forest of Bangka Island.jpg|thumb|Forest in [[Indonesia]] being cut for [[palm oil]] plantation.]]
Some critics{{Who|date=April 2010}} argue that a narrow view of economic growth, combined with globalization, is creating a scenario where we could see a systemic collapse of our planet's natural resources.&lt;ref&gt;• Donella H. Meadows, Jorgen Randers, Dennis L. Meadows. Limits to Growth: The 30-Year Update. White River Junction, Vermont : Chelsea Green, 2004.&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; • Allan Schnaiberg. The Environment: From Surpus to Scarcity. New York: Oxford University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;
Other critics draw on [[archaeology]] to cite examples of cultures they claim have disappeared because they grew beyond the ability of their ecosystems to support them.&lt;ref&gt;Jared Diamond. Collapse: How Societies Choose to Fail or Succeed. Penguin, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
Concerns about possible negative effects of growth on the environment and society led some to advocate lower levels of growth, from which comes the ideas of [[uneconomic growth]] and [[de-growth]], and [[Green parties]] which argue that economies are part of a global society and a global ecology and cannot outstrip their natural growth without damaging them.

Those more optimistic about the environmental impacts of growth believe that, although localized environmental effects may occur, large scale ecological effects are minor. The argument as stated by commentators [[Julian Lincoln Simon]] states that if these global-scale ecological effects exist, human ingenuity will find ways of adapting to them.&lt;ref&gt;The Ultimate Resource, Julian Simon&lt;/ref&gt;

===Equitable growth===
While acknowledging the central role economic growth can potentially play in [[Human development (humanity)|human development]], [[poverty reduction]] and the achievement of the [[Millennium Development Goals]], it is becoming widely understood amongst the development community that special efforts must be made to ensure poorer sections of society are able to participate in economic growth.&lt;ref name=ODI&gt;Claire Melamed, Kate Higgins and Andy Sumner (2010) http://www.odi.org.uk/resources/details.asp?id=4892&amp;title=millennium-development-goals-equitable-growth-policy-brief Economic growth and the MDGs] [[Overseas Development Institute]]&lt;/ref&gt; For instance, with low inequality a country with a growth rate of 2% per head and 40% of its population living in poverty, can halve poverty in ten years, but a country with high inequality would take nearly 60 years to achieve the same reduction.&lt;ref&gt;Ravallion, M. (2007) Inequality is bad for the poor in S. Jenkins and J. Micklewright, (eds.) Inequality and Poverty Re-examined, Oxford University Press, Oxford.&lt;/ref&gt; In the words of the [[Secretary-General of the United Nations|Secretary General]] of the United Nations [[Ban Ki-Moon]]:
:&quot;While economic growth is necessary, it is not sufficient for progress on reducing poverty.&quot;&lt;ref name=ODI/&gt;
Researchers at the [[Overseas Development Institute]] compares situations such as in Uganda, where during a period of annual growth of 2.5% between 2000 and 2003, the percentage of people living in poverty actually increased by 3.8%.&lt;ref name=ODI/&gt; The ODI thus emphasises the need to ensure social protection is extended to allow universal access and that policies are introduced to encourage the private sector to create new jobs as the economy grows (as opposed to [[jobless growth]]) and seek to employ people from disadvantaged groups.&lt;ref name=ODI/&gt;

===Implications of global warming===
:''see [[Economics of global warming]]''

Up to the present there are close correlations of economic growth with [[carbon dioxide]] emissions across nations, although there is also a considerable divergence in carbon intensity (carbon emissions per GDP).&lt;ref&gt;Stern Review, Part III Stabilization. Table 7.1 p. 168&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Stern Review]] notes that the prediction that &quot;under business as usual, global emissions will be sufficient to propel greenhouse gas concentrations to over 550ppm {{CO2}}e by 2050 and over 650–700ppm by the end of this century is robust to a wide range of changes in model assumptions&quot;. The scientific consensus is that planetary ecosystem functioning without incurring dangerous risks requires stabilization at 450–550 ppm.&lt;ref&gt;Stern Review Economics of Climate Change. Part III Stabilization p.183&lt;/ref&gt;

As a consequence, growth-oriented environmental economists propose massive government intervention into switching sources of energy production, favouring wind, solar, hydroelectric, and nuclear. This would largely confine use of fossil fuels to either domestic cooking needs (such as for kerosene burners) or where [[carbon capture and storage]] technology can be cost-effective and reliable.&lt;ref&gt;Jaccard, M. 2005 Sustainable Fossil Fuels. Cambridge University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Stern Review]], published by the United Kingdom Government in 2006, concluded that an investment of 1% of GDP would be sufficient to avoid the worst effects of climate change, and that failure to do so could risk climate-related costs equal to 20% of GDP. Because carbon capture and storage is as yet widely unproven, and its long term effectiveness (such as in containing carbon dioxide 'leaks') unknown, and because of current costs of alternative fuels, these policy responses largely rest on faith of technological change.

On the other hand, [[Nigel Lawson]] claimed that people in a hundred years' time would be &quot;seven times as well off as we are today&quot;, therefore it is not reasonable to impose sacrifices on the &quot;much poorer present generation&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/jt200607/jtselect/jtclimate/170/7051604.htm|title=Examination of Witnesses (Questions 32–39)|date=16 May 2007|accessdate=2007-11-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prominent growth economists==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
* [[Frank P. Ramsey]]
* [[Joseph Schumpeter]]
* [[Roy Harrod]]
* [[Evsey Domar]]
* [[Simon Kuznets]]
* [[Nicholas Kaldor]]
* [[Robert Solow]]
* [[Edward J. Nell]]
{{col-2}}

* [[Arthur Lewis (economist)|Sir Arthur Lewis]]
* [[Paul Romer]]
* [[Robert Lucas, Jr.]]
* [[Robert J. Barro]]
* [[Xavier Sala-i-Martin]]
* [[Oded Galor]]
* [[Trevor Swan]]
* [[Daron Acemoglu]]
{{col-end}}

==See also==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
* [[Capital accumulation]]
* [[Demographic economics]]
* [[Economic development]]
* [[Export-led growth]]
* [[Growth accounting]]

{{col-2}}
* [[Growth elasticity of poverty]]
* [[Human development theory]]
* [[List of countries by GDP (real) growth rate]]
* [[Malthusian trap]]
* [[Steady state economy]]
* [[Unified growth theory]]

{{col-end}}

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Further reading==
* Joseph Halevi, David Laibman and [[Edward J. Nell]] (eds.) (1992) Beyond the Steady State: Essays in the Revival of Growth Theory, edited with, London, UK:
* Barro, Robert J. (1997) ''Determinants of Economic Growth: A Cross-Country Empirical Study.'' MIT Press: Cambridge, MA.
* Argyrous, G., Forstater, M and Mongiovi, G. (eds.) (2004) ''Growth, Distribution, And Effective Demand: Essays in Honor of Edward J. Nell''. New York: M.E. Sharpe.
* Galor, O. (2005) ''From Stagnation to Growth: Unified Growth Theory.'' Handbook of Economic Growth, Elsevier.
* Jones, Charles I. (2002) ''Introduction to Economic Growth'' 2nd ed. W. W. Norton &amp; Company: New York, N.Y.
* Kirzner, Israel. (1973) ''Competition and Entrepreneurship''
* Puthenkalam, John Joseph, &quot;Integrating Freedom, Democracy and Human Rights into Theories of Economic Growth&quot;, Manila, 1998.
* [[Robert Lucas, Jr.|Lucas, Robert E., Jr.]] (2003) ''The Industrial Revolution: Past and Future'', Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis, ''Annual Report'' [http://www.minneapolisfed.org/pubs/region/04-05/essay.cfm  online edition]
* Mises, Ludwig E. (1949) ''Human Action'' 1998 reprint by the Mises Institute
* Schumpeter, Jospeph A. (1912) ''The Theory of Economic Development'' 1982 reprint, Transaction Publishers
* Weil, David N. (2008) ''Economic Growth'' 2nd ed. Addison Wesley.
* Vladimir N. Pokrovskii (2011) [http://www.springer.com/physics/complexity/book/978-94-007-2095-4 ''Econodynamics. The Theory of Social Production''], Springer, Berlin.
*{{cite book
|title=The Evolution of Progress: The End of Economic Growth and the Beginning of Human Transformation
 |last1=Paepke
 |first1= C. Owen
|authorlink= 
|year= |publisher =Random House
|location= New York, Toronto
|isbn= 0-679-41582-3|pages=
| postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;}}

==External links==

===Articles and lectures===
* [http://www.econlib.org/library/Enc/EconomicGrowth.html Economic Growth] by Paul Romer, The Concise Encyclopedia of Economics.
* [http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-9106198/economic-growth &quot;Economic growth.&quot;] Encyclopædia Britannic. 2007. Encyclopædia Britannica Online. 17 November 2007.
* [http://www.gsb.stanford.edu/research/faculty/news_releases/Romer.Paul/London_Speech.html Beyond Classical and Keynesian Macroeconomic Policy]. [[Paul Romer]]'s plain-English explanation of endogenous growth theory.
* [http://www.economicshelp.org/essays/economics-growth-happiness.html Does Economic Growth increase Living Standards?]
* [http://www.spiked-online.com/Articles/0000000CB04D.htm Who's afraid of economic growth?] Essay by Daniel Ben-Ami on the contemporary anxiety about economic growth.
* [http://www.cepr.net/index.php/economics-seminar-series/ CEPR Economics Seminar Series] Two seminars on the importance of growth with economists [[Dean Baker]] and [[Mark Weisbrot]]
* [http://www.iisg.nl/research/jvz-research.pdf On global economic history] by Jan Luiten van Zanden. Explores the idea of the inevitability of the Industrial Revolution.
* [http://www.sciam.com/article.cfm?id=the-economist-has-no-clothes The Economist Has No Clothes] &amp;ndash; essay by [[Robert Nadeau (science historian)|Robert Nadeau]] in [[Scientific American]] on the basic assumptions behind current [[economic theory]]
* [[World Growth Institute]].  An organization dedicated to helping the developing world realize its full potential via economic growth.
* [http://www.indiainfoline.com/Markets/News/Economics-for-Everyone-Evaluating-Economic-Growth/4675439076 Economics for Everyone- Evaluating Economic Growth]
* [http://gsociology.icaap.org/  Understanding the world today] Multiple reports on economic growth

===Data===
* [http://www.intelligentguess.com/blog/2007/03/01/usa-comparism-of-gdp-growth-versus-fed-rate-since-1954/ &lt;s style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;Historical data - since 1954 - comparing the US GDP growth rate versus the US Fed Funds Rate&lt;/s&gt; ] &lt;i style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;link broken&lt;/i&gt;
* [http://www.ggdc.net/maddison/ Angus Maddison's Historical Dataseries] -Series for almost all countries on GDP, Population and GDP per capita from the year 0 up to 2003
* [http://stats.oecd.org/wbos/Index.aspx?QueryId=350 OECD Economic growth statistics]
* [http://gsociology.icaap.org/dataupload.html multinational data sets] easy to use data set showing gdp, per capita and population, by country and region, 1970 to 2008. Updated regularly.

{{DEFAULTSORT:Economic Growth}}
[[Category:Economic growth|*]]
[[Category:Welfare economics]]
[[Category:Macroeconomics]]
[[Category:Economic indicators]]
[[Category:Economics terminology]]

[[ar:تنمية اقتصادية]]
[[bg:Икономически растеж]]
[[ca:Creixement econòmic]]
[[cs:Hospodářský růst]]
[[de:Wirtschaftswachstum]]
[[et:Majanduskasv]]
[[el:Οικονομική ανάπτυξη]]
[[es:Crecimiento económico]]
[[eo:Ekonomia kresko]]
[[eu:Hazkunde ekonomiko]]
[[fa:رشد اقتصادی]]
[[fr:Croissance économique]]
[[ko:경제성장]]
[[hi:आर्थिक वृद्धि]]
[[hr:Ekonomski rast]]
[[id:Pembangunan ekonomi]]
[[it:Crescita economica]]
[[he:צמיחה כלכלית]]
[[lo:ການຂະຫຍາຍໂຕທາງເສດຖະກິດ]]
[[mk:Економски раст]]
[[ms:Pertumbuhan ekonomi]]
[[nl:Economische groei]]
[[ja:経済成長]]
[[km:កំណើនសេដ្ឋកិច្ច]]
[[pl:Wzrost gospodarczy]]
[[pt:Crescimento econômico]]
[[kaa:Ekonomikalıq o'siw]]
[[ru:Экономический рост]]
[[sq:Rritja ekonomike]]
[[sk:Hospodársky rast]]
[[sr:Привредни раст]]
[[sh:Ekonomski rast]]
[[fi:Talouskasvu]]
[[sv:Ekonomisk tillväxt]]
[[th:ความเจริญเติบโตทางเศรษฐกิจ]]
[[tr:Ekonomik büyüme]]
[[uk:Економічне зростання]]
[[vi:Tăng trưởng kinh tế]]
[[zh:经济增长]]</text>
      <sha1>bssp08z9vls51rlupn0833zj09ged5j</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
