<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Economic problem</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2705885</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521221228</id>
      <parentid>521221221</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-03T16:28:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contributions/82.11.4.212|82.11.4.212]] to version by Omnipaedista. False positive? [[User:ClueBot NG/FalsePositives|Report it]]. Thanks, [[User:ClueBot NG|ClueBot NG]]. (1312462) (Bot)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6362">{{Noref|date=October 2012}}
The '''economic problem''', sometimes called the basic, central or fundamental economic problem, is one of the fundamental [[economic theory|economic theories]] in the operation of any [[economy]].  It asserts that there is [[scarcity]], or that the finite resources available are insufficient to satisfy all human [[wants]] and needs. The problem then becomes how to determine what is to be produced and how the [[factors of production]] (such as [[capital (economics)|capital]] and [[Labor (economics)|labor]]) are to be allocated.  [[Economics]] revolves around methods and possibilities of solving the economic problem.

In short, the economic problem is the choice one must make, arising out of '''limited means''' and '''unlimited wants'''.

==Overview==
The economic problem is most simply explained by the question &quot;how do we satisfy unlimited wants with limited resources?&quot;  The premise of the economic problem model is that wants are constant and infinite due to constantly changing demands (often closely related to changing [[demographics]] of the population).  However, resources in the world to satisfy human wants are always limited to the amount of natural or [[human resources]] available.  The economic problem, and methods to curb it, revolve around the idea of choice in prioritizing which wants can be fulfilled..
and how do we know what to produce for the economy.

===Needs===
Needs are material items people need for survival, such as food, clothing, housing and ware. Until the [[Industrial Revolution]], the vast majority of the worlds population struggled for access to basic human needs.

===Wants===
While the basic needs of survival are important in the function of the economy, wants are the driving force which stimulates demand for goods and services. In order to curb the economic problem, economists must classify the nature and different wants of consumers, as well as prioritize wants and organize production to satisfy as many wants as possible.
One assumption often made in mainstream [[neoclassical economics]] (and the methods which attempt to solve the economic problem) is that humans inherently pursue their self-interest and the market mechanism best satisfies the various wants different individuals might have. These wants are often classified into ''individual wants'', which depend on the individual's preferences and [[purchasing power parity]], and ''collective wants'', those of entire groups of people. Things such as food and clothing can be classified as either wants or needs, depending on what type and how often a good is asked for.
Wants are effective desires for a particular product, or something which can only be obtained by working for it.

===Choice===
The economic problem fundamentally revolves around the idea of choice, which ultimately must answer the problem. Due to the limited resources available, businesses must determine what to produce first to satisfy demand. Consumers are considered the biggest influences of this choice, and the goods which they want must also fit within their [[budget]]s and [[purchasing power parity]]. Different economic models place choice in different hands.

*[[Socialism]] asserts that producers (workers) should have some control over the decisions that affect their welfare in the workplace and on the governmental level, which cooperatively formulates economic plans for economic decisions regarding the allocation and use of capital goods. Socialist systems that utilize the market for this role are termed [[market socialism]].

*The idea of [[State socialism]] argues that most or all major economic choices (regarding production, allocation of inputs and distribution of output) should be made through [[central planning]] by the government. Only by constructing a cohesive plan that takes the good of everyone into account, so the idea states, can the best allocation of resources be achieved. (Also see [[Planned economy]].)

*[[Communism]] refers to a stage of development where the productive forces are advanced to such a degree that it solves the economic problem, insofar as needs are concerned. A communist system is a highly developed form of [[Socialist mode of production|socialism]] where productive property is held in common, individual autonomy from coercive social relations is abolished and the state no longer exists. (Also see [[Marxism]].)

*[[Capitalism]] argues for a system where private businesses (and some state-owned enterprises, in the case of [[mixed economies]]) make economic decisions regarding investment decisions, production levels and distribution of output, where in the role of the government is to protect the [[property rights]] of individuals and companies, provide the institutional and infrastructural framework for the development of a market economy and the provision of some government social programs.

*In a [[free-market]] economy, which exists without the constraints of government [[wage and price controls]], proponents of market capitalism argue that resources are automatically allocated toward the things that society collectively values the most. This form of [[capitalism]] argues for a [[laissez-faire]] approach, wherein the role of the government is to protect the [[property rights]] of individuals and companies so that they can have the confidence to undertake the economic activity (and [[risk (economics)|risks]]) that will create the most value.
**If a good or service is overvalued (i.e., the price is too high), the [[economic surplus|surplus]] will force providers of the good or service to lower their prices or to re-allocate their capacity to produce something more worthwhile.
**If the supply of a good or service is [[shortage|inadequate]], rising prices increase the value and so cause more production capacity to be directed toward the item. [[Adam Smith]]'s [[The Wealth of Nations]] has been an extremely influential book for this school of thought.

==See also==
*[[Full employment]]
*[[Post-scarcity]]
*[[Job guarantee]]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Economic Problem}}
[[Category:Economic theories]]

[[ar:المشكلة الاقتصادية]]
[[hi:अर्थशास्त्र]]
[[pt:Problema econômico]]
[[sa:अर्थशास्त्रं]]
[[ta:அடிப்படை பொருளாதாரப் பிரச்சனைகள்]]</text>
      <sha1>4ftg5weylciv81u4ht82gas0ybtly48</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
