<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Ecotax</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>177753</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520920405</id>
      <parentid>508193556</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-01T16:57:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JayJasper</username>
        <id>2643895</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>c/e</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15187">{{Taxation}}
'''Ecotax''' (short for '''Ecological taxation''') refers to [[taxation|taxes]] intended to promote [[Sustainability|ecologically sustainable activities]] via economic incentives. Such a policy can complement or avert the need for regulatory (command and control) approaches. Often, an ecotax policy proposal may attempt to maintain overall tax revenue by proportionately reducing other taxes (e.g. taxes on human labor and renewable resources); such proposals are known as a '''green tax shift''' towards ecological taxation.

Ecotaxes are examples of [[pigovian tax]]es, which are ''taxes that attempt to make the private parties involved feel the social burden of their actions''. An example might be philosopher [[Thomas Pogge]]'s proposed [[Global Resources Dividend]].

==Taxes affected==
{{Green economics sidebar}}
Examples of taxes which could be lowered or eliminated by a green [[tax shift]] are:
* [[Payroll tax|Payroll]], [[income tax|income]], and, to a lesser extent, [[sales tax]]es.
* [[Corporate tax]]es (taxes on investment and entrepreneurship).
* [[Property tax]]es on buildings and other infrastructure.

Examples of ecotaxes which could be implemented or increased are:
* [[Carbon tax]]es on the use of [[fossil fuel]]s by [[greenhouse gas]]es produced. Old [[hydrocarbon tax]]es don't penalize green house gas (GHG) production.
* [[Duty (economics)|Duties]] on imported goods containing significant non-ecological energy input (to a level necessary to treat fairly local manufacturers)
* [[Severance tax]]es on the extraction of [[mineral]], [[energy]], and [[forest]]ry products.
* [[License|License fees]] for [[camping]], hiking, [[fishing]] and [[hunting]] and associated equipment.
* Specific taxes on technologies and products which are associated with substantial negative [[externalities]].
* [[Waste disposal]] taxes and refundable fees.
* Taxes on [[effluent]]s, [[pollution]] and other [[hazardous waste]]s.
* [[Land value tax|Site value taxes]] on the unimproved value of land.

==Economic frameworks and strategies employing tax shifting and ecotaxes==
The object of a green tax shift is often to implement a &quot;[[full cost accounting]]&quot; or &quot;[[true cost accounting]]&quot;, using fiscal policy to internalize market distorting externalities, which leads to [[sustainability|sustainable]] [[wealth]] creation. The broader measures required for this are also sometimes called [[ecological fiscal reform]], especially in [[Canada]], where the government has generally employed this terminology.

Tax shifting usually includes balancing taxation levels to be revenue-neutral for [[government]] and to maintain overall [[progressive tax|progressiveness]]. It also usually includes measures to protect the most vulnerable, such as raising the minimum income to file income tax at all, or an increase to pension and social assistance levels to offset increased costs of fuel consumption.

Basic economic theory recognizes the existence of [[externalities]] and their potential negative effects. To the extent that green taxes correct for externalities such as pollution, they correspond with mainstream economic theory. In practice, however, setting the correct taxation level or the tax collection system needed to do so is difficult, and may lead to further distortions or unintended consequences.

Taxes on consumption may take the &quot;[[feebate]]&quot; approach advocated by [[Amory Lovins]], in which additional fees on less sustainable products &amp;mdash; such as [[sport utility vehicle]]s &amp;mdash; are pooled to fund subsidies on more sustainable alternatives, such as [[hybrid electric vehicle]]s.

However, they may simply act as incentives to change habits and make capital investments in newer more efficient vehicles or appliances or to upgrade buildings. Small changes in corporate tax rates for instance can radically change [[return on investment]] of capital projects, especially if the averted costs of future fossil fuel use are taken into account.

The same logic applies to major consumer purchases. A &quot;[[green mortgage]]&quot; such as a [[Location Efficient Mortgage]], for example, recognizes that persons who do not drive cars and live generally energy-efficient lifestyles pay far less per month than others and accordingly have more to pay a heftier mortgage bill with. This justifies lending them much more money to upgrade a house to use even less energy overall. The result is a bank taking more per month from a consumer's income as utilities and car insurance companies take less, and housing stock upgraded to use the minimum energy feasible with current technology.

Aside from energy, the refits will generally be those required to be maximally accommodating to [[telework]], [[permaculture]] gardens (for example [[green roof]]s), and a lifestyle that is generally localized in the community not based on commuting. The last, especially, raises real state valuations for not only the neighborhood but the entire surrounding region. Consumers living sustainable lifestyles in upgraded housing will generally be unwilling to drive around aimlessly shopping, for instance, to save a few dollars on their purchases. Instead, they'll stay nearer to home and create jobs in grocery delivery and small organic grocers, spending substantially less money on gasoline and car operation costs even if they pay more for food.

==Progressive or regressive?==
Some green tax shift proposals have been criticized as being fiscally [[regressive tax|regressive]] (a tax with an average tax rate that decreases as the taxpayer's income increases). Taxing negative externalities usually entails exerting a burden on consumption, and since the poor consume more and save or invest less as a share of their income, any shift towards [[consumption tax]]es can be regressive. In 2004, research by the [[Policy Studies Institute]] and [[Joseph Rowntree Foundation]] indicated that flat rate taxes on domestic rubbish, energy, water and transport use would have a relatively higher impact on poorer households.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news 
|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/3955285.stm 
|title=Green taxes 'would hit poor most' 
|work=BBC News 
|date=October 26 2004
|archiveurl= http://www.webcitation.org/68sZibSdt
|archivedate= July 3 2012
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, conventional regulatory approaches can affect prices in much the same way, while lacking the revenue-recycling potential of ecotaxes. Moreover, correctly assessing distributive impact of any tax shift requires an analysis of the specific instrument design features. For example, tax revenue could be redistributed on a per capita basis as part of a [[basic income]] scheme; in this case, the poorest would gain what the average citizen pays as ecotaxes, minus their own small contribution (no car, small apartment, ...). This design would be highly progressive. Alternatively, an ecotax can have a &quot;lifeline&quot; design, in which modest consumption levels are priced relatively low (even zero, in the case of water), and higher consumption levels are priced at a higher rate. Furthermore, an ecotax policy package can include revenue recycling to reduce or eliminate any regressivity; an increase in an ecotax could be more than offset by a decrease in a (regressive) payroll or consumption tax. Some proponents claim a second benefit of increased employment or lower health care costs as the market and society adjust to the new fiscal policy (these claims, as with the claim &quot;tax cuts create jobs,&quot; are often difficult to prove or disprove even after the fact).

Furthermore, pollution and other forms of environmental harm are often felt more acutely by the poor, who cannot &quot;buy their way out&quot; of being receptors of air pollution, water pollution, etc. Such losses, although [[externalities]], have real economic welfare impacts. Thus by reducing environmental harm, such instruments have a progressive effect.

==Ecotax policies enacted==
{{Environmental law}}
An ecotax has been enacted in [[Germany]] by means of three laws in 1998, 1999 and 2002. The first introduced a tax on electricity and petroleum, at variable rates based on environmental considerations; renewable sources of electricity were not taxed. The second adjusted the taxes to favor efficient conventional power plants. The third increased the tax on petroleum. At the same time, [[income tax]]es were reduced proportionally so that the total tax burden remained constant.

The regional government of [[Balearic Islands]] (then held by an [[ecosocialist]] coalition) established an ecotax in 1999. The Balearic Island suffer a high human pressure from tourism, that at the same time provides the main source of income. The tax ([[€]]1.00 per person per day) would be paid by visitors staying at tourist resorts. This was criticized by the conservative opposition as contrary to business interests, and they abolished the tax in 2003 after seizing back the government.

A variety of ecotaxes (often called &quot;severance taxes&quot;) have been enacted by various states in the United States. The [[Supreme Court of the United States]] held in ''[[Commonwealth Edison Co. v. Montana]]'', 453 U.S. 609 (1981), that in the absence of federal law to the contrary, states may set ecotaxes as high as they wish without violating the [[Commerce Clause]] or the [[Supremacy Clause]] of the [[United States Constitution]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Elison&quot;&gt;Elison, Larry M. and Snyder, Fritz. ''The Montana State Constitution: A Reference Guide.'' Santa Barbara, Calif.: Greenwood Publishing Group, 2001. ISBN 0-313-27346-4&lt;/ref&gt;

===Registration taxes===
The Netherlands, Portugal, Canada, Spain and Finland have introduced differentiations into their car registration taxes to encourage car buyers to opt for the cleanest car models.

In the Netherlands, the new registration taxes, payable when a car is sold to its first buyer, can earn the owner of a hybrid a discount up to [[€]]6000. Spain reduced taxes for cars that produced less CO2 (some of which will be exempted), while the more consuming, like [[Special purpose vehicle|SPV]] and [[Four-wheel drive|4WD]] saw their taxes increased.

Austria has had a registration tax based on fuel consumption for several years.

==Worldwide implementation==
===United Kingdom===
In 1993, the conservative government introduced the [[Fuel Price Escalator]], featuring a small but steady increase of fuel taxes, as proposed by Weizsäcker and Jesinghaus in 1992.&lt;ref name=&quot;Weizsäcker and Jesinghaus&quot;&gt; Weizsäcker, Ernst Ulrich and Jesinghaus, Jochen. ''Ecological Tax Reform.'' London: ZED Books, 1992. Online [http://esl.jrc.it/dc/etr/ecological_tax_reform.htm]&lt;/ref&gt; The FPE was stopped in 2000, following nationwide protests; while fuel was relatively cheap in 1993, fuel prices were then among the highest in Europe.
Under the [[Blair-Brown government]], despite [[Gordon Brown|Gordon Brown’s]] promise to the contrary, green taxes as a percentage of overall taxes have actually fallen from 9.4% to 7.7%, according to calculations by [[Friends of the Earth]].&lt;ref name='R000084'&gt;{{cite news | first=Peter | last=Madden | coauthors= | title=No excuses for inaction - It is perhaps surprising that business is beginning to make progress on the environment while our elected governments are wasting precious time | url =http://www.guardian.co.uk/environment/2007/nov/05/greenlist.comment | work =[[The Guardian]] | pages = | accessdate = 2008-09-28 | location=London | date=2007-11-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 2006 proposal, the U.K.'s then-[[Secretary of State for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs|Environment Secretary]] [[David Miliband]] had the government in discussions on the use of various green taxes to reduce [[Global warming|climate-changing pollution]]. Of the proposed taxes, which were meant to be revenue-neutral, Miliband stated: ''&quot;They're not fundamentally there to raise revenue.&quot;''&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC&quot; /&gt;

Miliband provided additional comments on their need, saying: ''&quot;Changing people's behaviour is only achieved by &quot;market forces and price signals&quot;'', and ''&quot;As our understanding of climate change increases, it is clear more needs to be done.&quot;''&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://newsvote.bbc.co.uk/mpapps/pagetools/print/news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/6095680.stm|title=Miliband Draws Up Green Tax Plan: Environment Secretary David Miliband Has Confirmed the Government Is Holding Discussions On Tackling Climate Change Using Green Taxes|date=2006/10/30 11:04:01 GMT|publisher=BBC News website|accessdate=2009-06-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ukraine===
Starting in 1999, the Ukrainian government has been collecting an ecological tax, officially known as Environmental Pollution Fee ({{lang-uk|Збір за забруднення навколишнього природного середовища}}), which is collected from all polluting entities, whether it's one-time or ongoing pollution and regardless of whether the polluting act was legal or illegal at the time.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rada.gov.ua/cgi-bin/laws/main.cgi?nreg=303-99-%EF Resolution by the Cabinet of Minister of Ukraine on March 1, 1999 N 303 &quot;On approval of regulations establishing fees for environmental pollution and recovery of this collection» {{lang-uk|}}]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://zakon.rada.gov.ua/cgi-bin/laws/main.cgi?nreg=z0544-99 Joint Order of the Ministry of Environmental Protection and Nuclear Safety of Ukraine and State Tax Administration of Ukraine from 19.07.99 #162/379 &quot;On approval of Instruction on procedure of calculation and payment of the environmental pollution тах&quot;{{lang-uk|}}]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dpa.dp.ua/section.phtml?l1=21&amp;l2=126 Explanation of the Environmental Pollution Fee by the Tax Administration of Ukraine {{lang-uk|}}]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Electronic Waste Recycling Fee]]
* [[Energy Tax Act]]
* [[Environmental crime]]
* [[Feebate]]
* [[Free-market environmentalism]]
* [[Green politics]]
* [[Pigovian tax]]
* [[Environmental Tariff]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.sightline.org/research/taxes [[Sightline Institute]]'s research and resources on green taxes]
* [http://ntj.tax.org/wwtax/ntjrec.nsf/F57602350346C55985256AFC007F1BF7/$FILE/v52n4655.pdf A Distributional Analysis of Green Tax Reforms] - Gilbert E. Metcalf
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/shared/bsp/hi/pdfs/30_10_06_exec_sum.pdf STERN REVIEW: The Economics of Climate Change] - An executive summary of a report by economist [[Nicholas Stern]] (27pg [[Portable Document Format|pdf]] file)
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/business/6096084.stm BBC article on Stern's Report]

{{Electricity generation}}

[[Category:Politics of Germany]]
[[Category:Environmental economics]]
[[Category:Taxation]]
[[Category:Environmental law]]
[[Category:Sustainability]]

[[ar:ضرائب بيئية]]
[[da:Grøn afgift]]
[[de:Ökosteuer (Deutschland)]]
[[et:Keskkonnamaks]]
[[es:Ecotasas]]
[[fr:Écotaxe]]
[[kk:Экологиялық Салық]]
[[ja:環境税]]
[[no:Grønn skattepolitikk]]
[[nn:Grøn skattepolitikk]]
[[pl:Podatek ekologiczny]]
[[pt:Tributo ambiental]]
[[ru:Экологические налоги]]
[[uk:Збір за забруднення навколишнього природного середовища]]</text>
      <sha1>fyg6oxhqfnkv0axtorxixmpziz9t3i0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
