<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Excess burden of taxation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5004491</id>
    <revision>
      <id>502762078</id>
      <parentid>499226769</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-07-17T08:47:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>BattyBot</username>
        <id>15996738</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>changed {{no footnotes}} to {{more footnotes}} &amp; [[WP:AWB/GF|general fixes]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (8097)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7449">{{POV|date=November 2011}}
{{More footnotes|date=April 2009}}
{{Taxation}}
In [[economics]], the '''excess burden''' of [[taxation]], also known as the '''distortionary cost''' or '''deadweight loss''' of taxation, is one of the economic losses that society suffers as the result of a tax.  [[Economics|Economic theory]] posits that [[Distortions (economics)|distortions]] changes the amount and type of economic behavior from that which would occur in a free market without the tax. Excess burdens can be measured using the '''average cost of funds''' or the [[Marginal cost of public funds|marginal cost of funds]] ('''MCF'''). Excess burdens were first discussed by [[Adam Smith]].&lt;ref name=Economicae&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.unc.edu/depts/econ/byrns_web/Economicae/taxburdens.html |title=Adam Smith and Tax Burden Theory | accessdate=06 Jun 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An equivalent kind of inefficiency can also be caused by subsidies (that are actually taxes with negative rates).{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}

Economic losses due to taxes were evaluated to be as low as 2.5 cents per dollar of revenue, and as high as 30 cents per dollar of revenue (on average), and even much higher at the margins. See Martin Feldstein, Tax Avoidance and the Deadweight Loss of the Income Tax, 81(4), Review of Economics and Statistics (1999), at p.&amp;nbsp;674; Charles L. Ballard, John B. Shoven and John Whalley, The Welfare Cost of Distortions in the United States Tax System: A General Equilibrium Approach, National Bureau of Economic Research Working Paper No. 1043. For a review of literature arguing that moving to a uniform taxation of investment will lead to 0.1% to 0.3% increase in GNP, see Lawrence H. Summers, Should Tax Reform Level the Playing Field?, National Bureau of Economic Research Working Paper No. 2132, Cambridge, MA, January 1987.{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}

== Measures of the excess burden ==

The cost of a distortion is usually measured as the amount that would have to be paid to the people affected by its supply, the greater the excess burden. The second is the tax rate: as a general rule, the excess burden of a tax increases with the square of the tax rate.{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}

The average cost of funds is the total cost of distortions divided by the total revenue collected by a government.  In contrast, the ''marginal'' cost of funds (MCF) is the size of the distortion that accompanied the last unit of revenue raised (i.e. the [[derivative|rate of change]] of distortion with respect to revenue).  In most cases, the MCF increases as the amount of tax collected increases.{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}

The standard position in economics is that the costs in a [[cost-benefit analysis]] for any tax-funded project should be increased according to the marginal cost of funds, because that is close to the deadweight loss that will be experienced if the project is added to the budget, or to the deadweight loss removed if the project is removed from the budget.{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}

== Distortion and redistribution ==

In the case of [[progressive taxation|progressive taxes]], the distortionary effects of a tax may be accompanied by other benefits: the redistribution of dollars from wealthier people to poorer people who could possibly obtain more benefit from them.{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}

In fact almost any tax measure will distort the economy from the path or process that would have prevailed in its absence ([[land value tax]]es are a notable exception).  For example a [[sales tax]] applied to all goods will tend to discourage consumption of all the taxed items, and an [[income tax]] will tend to discourage people from earning money in the category of income that is taxed (unless they can manage to avoid being taxed).  Some people may move out of the work force (to avoid income tax); some may move into the cash or [[Black market|black economies]] (where incomes are not revealed to the tax authorities).{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}

For example, in Western nations the incomes of the relatively affluent are taxed partly to provide the money used to assist the relatively poor.  As a result of the taxes (and associated subsidies to the poor), incentives are changed for both groups.  The relatively rich are discouraged from declaring income and from earning marginal (extra) income, because they know that any additional money that they earn and declare will be taxed at their highest marginal tax rates.  At the same time the poor have an incentive to conceal their own taxable income (and usually their assets) so as to increase the likelihood of their receiving state assistance.  It can be argued that the distortion of incentives (the move away from a fiscally neutral stance that does not affect incentives) does more harm than good.{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}

One of the main distortions sometimes said to have arisen in the [[USA]] and the [[United Kingdom|UK]] as a result of tax policy is the creation of a permanent [[underclass]], dependent on welfare and discouraged (by the tax system) from seeking work and betterment.  In some countries the tax system can be badly designed to deal with such issues, e.g. sometimes the [[marginal tax rate]] that applies to earned income (as someone takes work attempting to escape from unemployment and welfare) is so high that the person's take-home income (post-tax and after taking account of any benefits or welfare receipts) does not increase as a result of taking work.  This is known as the [[welfare trap]].{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}

There was an example of distortion of the economy by tax policy some years ago in the UK when cars supplied by employers to their employees were taxed at advantageous rates (e.g. encouraging the growth of company car fleets).  Over several years the distortion grew to the point that the majority of cars used by working families were company cars and the dealership structures, and even the types of cars used, altered to adjust to the tax regime.{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}

== Deliberate distortion ==

{{details|Pigovian tax}}

Not all distortions are bad; [[Pigovian tax]]es create distortions that correct for [[externality|externalities]] and therefore have a negative MCF.{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}

Here, the fiscal distortion is deliberate, so as to compensate for externalities. &quot;[[Sin tax]]es&quot; are levied on products that incur additional costs to society, such as [[alcohol]], [[tobacco]] and [[pollution]]. Ideally, these taxes raise the price to the exact level that the market would bear if the negative externalities were included in the price. [[Pigovian tax]]es are often preferable to outright [[prohibition]], since prohibition incites [[illegal drug trade|trafficking]], often resulting in [[crime]] and other social costs, but no revenue.{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}

==See also==
* [[Deadweight loss]]
* [[Lump-sum tax]]
* [[Land value tax]]
* [[Laffer Curve]]

==References==
* [[T.N. Srinivasan]] (1987). &quot;distortions,&quot; ''[[The New Palgrave: A Dictionary of Economics]]'', v. 1, pp.&amp;nbsp;865–67.
* N.H. Stern (1987). &quot;optimal taxation,&quot; ''[[The New Palgrave: A Dictionary of Economics]]'', v. 1, pp.&amp;nbsp;865–67.
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Welfare economics]]
[[Category:Public finance]]
[[Category:Taxation and efficiency]]
[[Category:Tax incidence]]</text>
      <sha1>3w7leoz83tqgggvgvkr0sg2y3kgngye</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
