<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Geographical pricing</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>256851</id>
    <revision>
      <id>471063394</id>
      <parentid>471061568</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-01-13T01:04:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SwisterTwister</username>
        <id>7505908</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 471061568 by [[Special:Contributions/190.80.17.6|190.80.17.6]] ([[User talk:190.80.17.6|talk]])Unexplained removal</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3405">'''Geographical pricing''', in [[marketing]], is the practice of modifying a basic list price based on the geographical location of the buyer. It is intended to reflect the costs of shipping to different locations.

There are several types of geographic pricing:  
* '''FOB origin''' ([[Free on Board]] origin)  - The shipping cost from the factory or warehouse is paid by the purchaser. Ownership of the goods is transferred to the buyer as soon as it leaves the point of origin. It can be either the buyer or seller that arranges for the transportation.  
* '''Uniform delivery pricing''' - (also called postage stamp pricing) - The same price is charged to all.  
* '''Zone pricing''' - Prices increase as shipping distances increase. This is sometimes done by drawing concentric circles on a map with the plant or warehouse at the center and each circle defining the boundary of a price zone. Instead of using circles, irregularly shaped price boundaries can be drawn that reflect geography, population density, transportation infrastructure, and shipping cost.  (The term &quot;zone pricing&quot; can also refer to the practice of setting prices that reflect local competitive conditions, i.e., the market forces of supply and demand, rather than actual cost of transportation.){{Citation needed|date=December 2007}}

:Zone pricing, as practiced in the [[gasoline]] industry in the United States, is the pricing of gasoline based on a complex and secret weighting of factors, such as the number of competing stations, number of vehicles, average traffic flow, population density, and geographic characteristics.  This can result in two branded gas stations only a few miles apart selling gasoline at a price differential of as much as $0.50 per gallon.{{Dubious|date=March 2008}}

:Many businesspeople and economists state that gasoline zone pricing merely reflects the costs of doing business in a complex and volatile marketplace.  Critics contend that industry [[monopoly]] and the ability to control not only industry-owned &quot;corporate&quot; stations, but locally owned or [[Franchising|franchise]] stations, make zone pricing into an excuse to raise gasoline prices virtually at will.  Oil industry representatives contend that while they set wholesale and ''dealer tank wagon'' prices, individual dealers are free to see whatever prices they wish and that this practice in itself causes widespread price variations outside industry control.  {{Citation needed|date=December 2007}}

* '''Basing point pricing''' - Certain cities are designated as basing points. All goods shipped from a given basis point are charged the same amount.   
* '''Freight-absorption pricing''' - The seller absorbs all or part of the cost of transportation. This amounts to a price [[discounts and allowances|discount]], and is used as a [[promotion (marketing)|promotion]]al tactic.  
     
==See also==
* [[Incoterms]]
* [[Pricing]]
* [[Marketing]]
* [[Geo (marketing)]]
* [[Distribution (business)|Distribution]]

==Links==
*[http://www.latimes.com/news/local/valley/la-fi-calprice19jun19,1,5304103.story?coll=la-editions-valley Zones of Contention in Gasoline Pricing] (LA Times)
*[http://www.illinois.gov/gasprices/zonePricing.htm Zone Pricing] (state of Illinois)
*[http://www.cato.org/dailys/04-04-03.html Balance Sheet of Gouging] (Cato Institute)

[[Category:International trade]]
[[Category:Marketing]]
[[Category:Pricing]]</text>
      <sha1>47qiu5jwo13dcdejht20zf4jy0li74p</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
