<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Homo economicus</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>83042</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519438886</id>
      <parentid>516220020</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-23T19:04:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bluerasberry</username>
        <id>7830073</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* External links */ added navbox...</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21276">{{about|the economic concept|the journal|Homo Oeconomicus}}
{{Italic title}}
In [[economics]], '''''homo economicus''''', or '''economic human''', is the concept in many [[economic theories]] of humans as [[Rationality|rational]] and narrowly [[Rational egoism|self-interested]] actors who have the ability to make judgments toward their subjectively defined ends. Using these rational assessments, '''''homo economicus''''' attempts to maximize utility as a consumer and economic profit as a producer.&lt;ref&gt;Rittenberg and Trigarthen. Principles of Microeconomics: Chapter 6. pp. 2 [http://www.saylor.org/site/wp-content/uploads/2012/06/ECON101-3.1.pdf] Accessed June 20, 2012&lt;/ref&gt; This theory stands in contrast to the concept of ''[[homo reciprocans]]'', which states that human beings are primarily motivated by the desire to be cooperative and to improve their environment.

== History of the term ==
The term &quot;Economic Man&quot; was used for the first time in the late nineteenth century by critics of [[John Stuart Mill]]’s work on political economy.&lt;ref name=persky&gt;Persky, Joseph. &quot;Retrospectives: The Ethology of Homo Economicus.&quot; ''The Journal of Economic Perspectives'', Vol. 9, No. 2 (Spring, 1995), pp. 221-231&lt;/ref&gt; Below is a passage from Mill’s work that those 19th-century critics were referring to:

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;[Political economy] does not treat the whole of man’s nature as modified by the social state, nor of the whole conduct of man in society.  It is concerned with him solely as a being who desires to possess wealth, and who is capable of judging the comparative efficacy of means for obtaining that end.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Mill, John Stuart. &quot;On the Definition of Political Economy, and on the Method of Investigation Proper to It,&quot; London and Westminster Review, October 1836. ''Essays on Some Unsettled Questions of Political Economy'', 2nd ed. London: Longmans, Green, Reader &amp; Dyer, 1874, essay 5, paragraphs 38 and 48.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Later in the same work, Mill goes on to write that he is proposing “an arbitrary definition of man, as a being who inevitably does that by which he may obtain the greatest amount of necessaries, conveniences, and luxuries, with the smallest quantity of labour and physical self-denial with which they can be obtained.”

Although the term did not come into use until the 19th century, it is often associated with the ideas of 18th century thinkers like [[Adam Smith]] and [[David Ricardo]].  In ''[[The Wealth of Nations]]'', Smith wrote:

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;It is not from the benevolence of the butcher, the brewer, or the baker that we expect our dinner, but from their regard to their own interest.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Smith, Adam. “On the Division of Labour,” The Wealth of Nations, Books I-III. New York: Penguin Classics, 1986, page 119&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

This suggests the same sort of rational, self-interested, labor-averse individual that Mill proposes (although Smith did claim that individuals have sympathy for the well-being of others, in ''[[The Theory of Moral Sentiments]]''). Aristotle's ''[[Politics (Aristotle)|Politics]]'' discussed the nature of self-interest in Book II, Part V.&lt;ref&gt;http://classics.mit.edu/Aristotle/politics.html&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Again, how immeasurably greater is the pleasure, when a man feels a thing to be his own; for surely the love of self is a feeling implanted by nature and not given in vain, although selfishness is rightly censured; this, however, is not the mere love of self, but the love of self in excess, like the miser's love of money; for all, or almost all, men love money and other such objects in a measure. And further, there is the greatest pleasure in doing a kindness or service to friends or guests or companions, which can only be rendered when a man has private property.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

A wave of economists in the late 19th century—[[Francis Edgeworth]], [[William Stanley Jevons]], [[Léon Walras]], and [[Vilfredo Pareto]]—built mathematical models on these assumptions.  In the 20th century, [[Lionel Robbins]]’ [[rational choice theory]] came to dominate mainstream economics and the term Economic Man took on a more specific meaning of a person who acted rationally on complete knowledge out of self-interest and the desire for wealth.

==Model==
''Homo economicus'' is a term used for an approximation or [[Economic model|model]] of ''[[Homo sapiens]]'' that acts to obtain the highest possible well-being for him or herself given available information about opportunities and other constraints, both natural and [[institution]]al, on his ability to achieve his predetermined goals. This approach has been formalized in certain [[social sciences]] models, particularly in [[economics]].

''Homo economicus'' is seen as &quot;rational&quot; in the sense that well-being as defined by the [[utility function]] is optimized given perceived opportunities. That is, the individual seeks to attain very specific and predetermined goals to the greatest extent with the least possible cost. Note that this kind of &quot;rationality&quot; does not say that the individual's actual goals are &quot;rational&quot; in some larger ethical, social, or human sense, only that he tries to attain them at minimal cost. Only naïve applications of the ''Homo economicus'' model assume that this hypothetical individual knows what is best for his long-term physical and mental health and can be relied upon to always make the right decision for himself. See [[rational choice theory]] and [[rational expectations]] for further discussion; the article on [[rationality]] widens the discussion.

As in social science in general, these assumptions are at best approximations. The term is often used derogatorily in academic literature, perhaps most commonly by [[sociology|sociologists]], many of whom tend to prefer structural explanations to ones based on rational action by individuals.

The use of the Latin form ''Homo economicus'' is certainly long established; Persky&lt;ref name=persky/&gt; traces it back to [[Vilfredo Pareto|Pareto]] (1906)&lt;ref&gt;Pareto, Vilfredo (1906). &quot;Manual of political economy&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; but notes that it may be older. The English term ''economic man'' can be found even earlier, in [[John Kells Ingram]]'s ''A History of Political Economy'' (1888).&lt;ref&gt;Zabieglik, Stefan (2002). &quot;The Origins of the Term ''Homo Oeconomicus''&quot;, Gdansk, 123-130.&lt;/ref&gt;  The ''[[Oxford English Dictionary]] (O.E.D.)'' cites the use of ''homo oeconomicus'' by [[Charles Stanton Devas|C. S. Devas]] in his 1883 work ''The Groundwork of Economics'' in reference to Mill's writings, as one of a number of phrases that imitate the scientific name for the human species:

{{quote|Mill has only examined the ''homo oeconomicus'', or dollar-hunting animal.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/87988#eid215918154&lt;/ref&gt;
}}.  According to the ''O.E.D.,'' the human genus name ''Homo'' is

{{quote|Used with [[Latin|L.]] or mock-L. adjs. in names imitating ''Homo sapiens,'' ''etc.,'' and intended to personify some aspect of human life or behaviour (indicated by the adj.). ''Homo faber'' (&quot;feIb@(r)) [H. Bergson L'Evolution Créatrice (1907) ii. 151], a term used to designate man as a maker of tools.) Variants are often comic: ''Homo insipiens;'' ''Homo turisticus.''&lt;ref&gt;This is from the CD edition of 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Note that such forms should logically keep the capital for the &quot;genus&quot; name&amp;mdash;''i.e.,'' ''&lt;u&gt;H&lt;/u&gt;omo economicus'' rather than ''&lt;u&gt;h&lt;/u&gt;omo economicus.'' Actual usage is inconsistent.

[[Amartya Sen]] has argued there are grave pitfalls in assuming that rationality is limited to selfish rationality. Economics should build into its assumptions the notion that people can give credible commitments to a course of conduct. He demonstrates the absurdity with the narrowness of the assumptions by some economists with the following example of two strangers meeting on a street.&lt;ref&gt;AK Sen, ‘Rational Fools: A Critique of the Behavioural Foundations of Economic Theory’ (1977) 6 Philosophy and Public Affairs 317, 332&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Cquote|&quot;Where is the railway station?&quot; he asks me. &quot;There,&quot; I say, pointing at the post office, &quot;and would you please post this letter for me on the way?&quot; &quot;Yes,&quot; he says, determined to open the envelope and check whether it contains something valuable.}}

== Criticisms ==
''Homo economicus'' bases his choices on a consideration of his own personal &quot;utility function&quot;. 

Consequently, the ''homo economicus'' assumptions have been criticized not only by economists on the basis of logical arguments, but also on empirical grounds by cross-cultural comparison. Economic anthropologists such as [[Marshall Sahlins]],&lt;ref&gt;Marshall Sahlins: ''[http://www.eco-action.org/dt/affluent.html The Original Affluent Society],'' in: Marshall Sahlins (1972''): Stone Age Economics.'' London: Routledge 2003&lt;/ref&gt; [[Karl Polanyi]],&lt;ref&gt;Karl Polanyi (1944): ''[[The Great Transformation (book)|The Great Transformation]].'' Beacon Press 2001&lt;/ref&gt; [[Marcel Mauss]]&lt;ref&gt;Marcel Mauss (1924): ''[[The Gift (book)|The Gift]]. The Form and Reason for Exchange in Archaic Societies.'' London: Routledge 2006&lt;/ref&gt; or [[Maurice Godelier]]&lt;ref&gt;Maurice Godelier: ''The Enigma of the Gift.'' University Of Chicago Press 1999&lt;/ref&gt; have demonstrated that in traditional societies, choices people make regarding production and exchange of goods follow patterns of [[reciprocity (cultural anthropology)|reciprocity]] which differ sharply from what the ''homo economicus'' model postulates. Such systems have been termed [[gift economy]] rather than market economy. Criticisms of the ''homo economicus'' model put forward from the standpoint of ethics usually refer to thís traditional ethic of kinship-based reciprocity that held together traditional societies. 

Economists [[Thorstein Veblen]], [[John Maynard Keynes]], [[Herbert A. Simon]], and many of the [[Austrian School]] criticise ''Homo economicus'' as an actor with too great of an understanding of macroeconomics and economic forecasting in his decision making. They stress [[uncertainty]] and [[bounded rationality]] in the making of economic decisions, rather than relying on the rational man who is fully informed of all circumstances impinging on his decisions. They argue that perfect knowledge never exists, which means that all economic activity implies risk. Austrian economists rather prefer to use as a model tool the ''[[Homo agens]]''. 

Empirical studies by [[Amos Tversky]] questioned the assumption that investors are rational. In 1995, Tversky demonstrated the tendency of investors to make risk-averse choices in gains, and risk-seeking choices in losses. The investors appeared as very risk-averse for small losses but indifferent for a small chance of a very large loss. This violates economic rationality as usually understood. Further research on this subject, showing other deviations from conventionally-defined economic rationality, is being done in the growing field of experimental or [[behavioral economics]]. Some of the broader issues involved in this criticism are studied in [[Decision Theory]] of which [[Rational Choice Theory]] is only a subset.

Other critics of the ''Homo economicus'' model of humanity, such as [[Bruno Frey]], point to the excessive emphasis on [[extrinsic motivation]] (rewards and punishments from the social environment) as opposed to [[intrinsic motivation]]. For example, it is difficult if not impossible to understand how ''Homo economicus'' would be a hero in war or would get inherent pleasure from [[artisan|craftsmanship]]. Frey and others argue that too much emphasis on rewards and punishments can &quot;crowd out&quot; (discourage) intrinsic motivation: paying a boy for doing household tasks may push him from doing those tasks &quot;to help the family&quot; to doing them simply for the reward. 

Another weakness is highlighted by sociologists, who argue that ''Homo economicus'' ignores an extremely important question, ''i.e.,'' the origins of tastes and the parameters of the utility function by social influences, training, education, and the like. The exogeneity of tastes (preferences) in this model is the major distinction from ''Homo sociologicus,'' in which tastes are taken as partially or even totally determined by the societal environment (see below). 

Further critics, learning from the broadly-defined [[psychoanalysis|psychoanalytic]] tradition, criticize the ''Homo economicus'' model as ignoring the inner conflicts that real-world individuals suffer, as between short-term and long-term goals (''e.g.,'' eating chocolate cake and losing weight) or between individual goals and societal values. Such conflicts may lead to &quot;irrational&quot; behavior involving inconsistency, psychological paralysis, neurosis, and/or psychic pain. Further irrational human behaviour can occur as a result of habit, laziness, mimicry and simple obedience.

== Responses ==

{{Refimprove|date=December 2008}}

Economists tend to disagree with these critiques, arguing that it may be relevant to analyze the consequences of enlightened [[Rational egoism|egoism]] just as it may be worthwhile to consider altruistic or social behavior. Others argue that we need to understand the consequences of such narrow-minded greed even if only a small percentage of the population embraces such motives. [[Free rider problem|Free riders]], for example, would have a major negative impact on the provision of [[public good]]s. However, economists' supply and demand predictions might obtain even if only a significant minority of market participants act like ''Homo economicus''. In this view, the assumption of ''Homo economicus'' can and should be simply a preliminary step on the road to a more sophisticated model. 

Yet others argue that ''Homo economicus'' is a reasonable approximation for behavior within market institutions, since the individualized nature of human action in such social settings encourages individualistic behavior. Not only do market settings encourage the application of a simple cost/benefit calculus by individuals, but they reward and thus attract the more individualistic people. It can be difficult to apply social values (as opposed to following self-interest) in an extremely competitive market; a company that refuses to pollute (for example) may find itself bankrupt. 

Defenders of the ''Homo economicus'' model see many critics of the dominant school as using a [[straw man]] technique. For example, it is common for critics to argue that real people do not have cost-less access to infinite information and an innate ability to instantly process it. However, in advanced-level theoretical economics, scholars have found ways of addressing these problems, modifying models enough to more realistically depict real-life decision-making. For example, models of individual behavior under [[bounded rationality]] and of people suffering from [[envy]] can be found in the literature.''&lt;ref&gt;Geoffrey Brennan: ''[http://search.barnesandnoble.com/Culture-Social-Norms-and-Economics/Mark-Casson/e/9781858986173] Pareto Desirable Redistribution: The case of Malice and Envy,'' in: Culture, Social Norms and Economics(1997'')''&lt;/ref&gt;'' It is primarily when targeting the limiting assumptions made in constructing undergraduate models that the criticisms listed above are valid. These criticisms are especially valid to the extent that the professor asserts that the simplifying assumptions are true and/or uses them in a propagandistic way. 

The more sophisticated economists are quite conscious of the empirical limitations of the ''Homo economicus'' model. In theory, the views of the critics can be combined with the ''Homo economicus'' model to attain a more accurate model.

== Perspectives ==
According to Sergio Caruso, when talking of ''Homo economicus'', one should distinguish between the purely “methodological” versions, aimed at practical use in the economic sphere (e.g. economic calculus), and the” anthropological” versions, more ambitiously aimed at depicting a certain type of man (supposed to be actually existing), or even human nature in general. The former, traditionally founded on a merely speculative psychology, have proved unrealistic and frankly wrong as descriptive models of economic behaviour (therefore not applicable for normative purposes either); however, they are liable to be corrected resorting to the new empirically based economic psychology, which turns quite other than the philosophers’ psychology that economists have used until yesterday. Among the latter (i.e. the anthropological versions), one can make a further distinction between the weak versions, more plausible, and the strong ones, irreparably ideological. Depicting different types of “economic man” (each depending on the social context) is in fact possible with the help of cultural anthropology, and social psychology (a branch of psychology economists have strangely ignored), if only those types are contrived as socially and/or historically determined abstractions (such as [[Max Weber|Weber's]], [[Karl Korsch|Korsch's]], and [[Erich Fromm|Fromm's]] concepts of ''Idealtypus'', “historical specification”, and “social character”). Even a Marxist theoretician such as [[Antonio Gramsci|Gramsci]] – reminds Caruso – admitted of the ''Homo economicus'' as a useful abstraction on the ground of economic theory, provided that we grant there be as many ''homines oeconomici'' as the modes of production. On the contrary, when one concept of ''Homo economicus'' claims to grasp the eternal essence of what is human, at the same time putting aside all other aspects of human nature (such as ''Homo faber'', ''Homo loquens'', ''Homo ludens'', ''Homo reciprocans'', and so on), then the concept leaves the field of good philosophy, not to speak of social science, and is ready to enter a political doctrine as the most dangerous of its ideological ingredients.&lt;ref&gt;Caruso, Sergio: ''Homo oeconomicus. Paradigma, critiche, revisioni'', Florence (Italy): Firenze University Press, 2012 (ISBN 978-88-6655-105-8
)&lt;/ref&gt;

==''Homo sociologicus''==
Comparisons between economics and sociology have resulted in a corresponding term '''''Homo sociologicus''''' (introduced by German Sociologist [[Ralf Dahrendorf]] in 1958), to parody the image of human nature given in some sociological models that attempt to limit the social forces that determine individual tastes and social values. (The alternative or additional source of these would be biology.) Hirsch ''et al.'' say that ''Homo sociologicus'' is largely a ''[[tabula rasa]]'' upon which societies and cultures write values and goals; unlike ''economicus,'' ''sociologicus'' acts not to pursue selfish interests but to fulfill social roles&lt;ref&gt;Hirsch, Paul, Stuart Michaels and Ray Friedman. 1990. &quot;Clean Models vs. Dirty Hands: Why Economics Is Different from Sociology.&quot; In Sharon Zukin and Paul DiMaggio, eds. ''Structures of Capital: The Social Organization of the Economy'': 39-56. Cambridge; New York and Melbourne: Cambridge University Press, 1990 (ISBN 0-521-37523-1)&lt;/ref&gt; (though the fulfillment of social roles may have a selfish rationale—e.g. politicians or [[socialite]]s). This &quot;individual&quot; may appear to be all society and no individual.

== See also ==
* [[Agent (economics)]]
* [[Consumer confusion]]
* [[Dictator game]]
* [[Economic rationalism]]
* [[Economism]]
* ''[[Homo biologicus]]''
* [[List of alternative names for the human species]]
* [[Modern portfolio theory]]
* [[Pirate game]]
* [[Post-autistic economics]]
* [[Profit motive]]
* [[Rational agent]]
* [[Rational choice theory]]
* [[Rational pricing]]
* [[Rationality]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==References==
*[[J.S. Mill]], 'On the Definition of Political Economy, and on the Method of Investigation Proper to It' (1836) London and Westminster Review
*J.S. Mill, ''Essays on Some Unsettled Questions of Political Economy'' (2nd ed. Longmans, Green, Reader &amp; Dyer 1874)
*[[Amartya Sen|A.K. Sen]], ‘Rational Fools: A Critique of the Behavioural Foundations of Economic Theory’ (1977) 6 Philosophy and Public Affairs 317

== External links ==
*[http://william-king.www.drexel.edu/top/prin/txt/Neoch/Eco111t.html Rational self interest], Prof. Roger A. McCain, [[Drexel University]]
*[http://globalwebpost.com/farooqm/writings/islamic/i_econ_fin/homo-islamicus.doc Self-Interest, Homo Islamicus and Some Behavioral Assumptions in Islamic Economics and Finance] (DOC) by Dr. Mohammad Omar Farooq
*[http://www.mayoresearch.org/files/REQUIEM.pdf Requiem for Homo Economicus] Edward J. O’Boyle, Mayo Research Institute, a refutation of reductionism in [[free will]] using tenets of [[natural law]]

{{Consumer behaviour}}

[[Category:Economics models]]
[[Category:Latin philosophical phrases]]
[[Category:Underlying principles of microeconomic behavior]]
[[Category:Rational choice theory]]

[[ca:Homo economicus]]
[[de:Homo oeconomicus]]
[[es:Homo œconomicus]]
[[fr:Homo œconomicus]]
[[it:Homo oeconomicus]]
[[la:Homo oeconomicus]]
[[nl:Homo economicus]]
[[ja:経済人]]
[[pl:Homo oeconomicus]]
[[pt:Homo economicus]]
[[ro:Homo economicus]]
[[sl:Homo economicus]]
[[sr:Хомо економикус]]
[[sv:Homo oeconomicus]]
[[uk:Людина економічна]]
[[zh:经济人]]</text>
      <sha1>j19151wwulxkmuaqsgym72t3jl7kx1h</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
