<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Import</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7515651</id>
    <revision>
      <id>515740659</id>
      <parentid>515728748</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-03T04:31:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Beagel</username>
        <id>2057630</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 515728748 by [[Special:Contributions/70.247.162.84|70.247.162.84]] ([[User talk:70.247.162.84|talk]]) -- rv disambig.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9807">{{Otheruses|Import (disambiguation)}}
{{trade bloc}}

The term '''import''' is derived from the conceptual meaning as to bring in the goods and services  into the port of a country. The buyer of such goods and services is referred to an &quot;importer&quot; who is based in the country of import where the overseas based seller is referred to as an &quot;exporter&quot;. &lt;ref&gt; [[Rakesh Mohan Joshi|Joshi, Rakesh Mohan]], (2009) International Business, Oxford University Press, New Delhi and New York ISBN 0-19-568909-7&lt;/ref&gt; Thus an import is any [[good (economics and accounting)|good]] (e.g. a [[commodity]]) or [[service (economics)|service]] brought in from one country to another country in a legitimate fashion, typically for use in [[trade]]. It is a good that is brought in from another country for sale.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book 
  | last       = Sullivan
  | first      = Arthur
  | authorlink = Arthur O'Sullivan
  | coauthors  = Steven M. Sheffrin
  | title      = Economics: Principles in action
  | publisher  = [[Pearson Prentice Hall]]
  | date       = 2003
  | location   = [[Upper Saddle River, New Jersey]] 07458
  | pages      = 552
  | url        = http://www.pearsonschool.com/index.cfm?locator=PSZ3R9&amp;PMDbSiteId=2781&amp;PMDbSolutionId=6724&amp;PMDbCategoryId=&amp;PMDbProgramId=12881&amp;level=4
  | doi        = 
  | id         = 
  | isbn       = 0-13-063085-3
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Imported goods or services are provided to domestic [[consumer]]s by foreign [[Production, costs, and pricing|producer]]s. An import in the receiving country is an [[export]] to the sending country.

Imports, along with [[exports]], form the basics of [[international trade]]. Import of goods normally requires involvement of the [[customs]] authorities in both the country of import and the country of [[export]] and are often subject to [[import quota]]s, [[tariff]]s and [[trade agreements]]. When the &quot;imports&quot; are the set of goods and services imported, &quot;Imports&quot; also means the [[value (economics)|economic value]] of all goods and services that are imported. The [[macroeconomics|macroeconomic]] variable I usually stands for the value of these imports over a given period of time, usually one year.{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}

==Definition==
&quot;Imports&quot; consist of transactions in goods and services (sales, barter, gifts or grants) from non-residents [http://epp.eurostat.ec.europa.eu/statistics_explained/index.php/Resident_institutional_unit residents] to residents.&lt;ref&gt;Lequiller, F; Blades, D.: Understanding National Accounts, Paris: OECD 2006, pp. 139-143&lt;/ref&gt; The exact definition of imports in [[national accounts]] includes and excludes specific &quot;borderline&quot; cases. &lt;ref&gt;for example, see Eurostat: European System of Accounts - ESA 1995, §§ 3.128-3.146, Office for Official Publications of the European Communities, Luxembourg, 1996&lt;/ref&gt; A general delimitation of imports in national accounts is given below:
* An import of a good occurs when there is a change of ownership from a non-resident to a resident; this does not necessarily imply that the good in question physically crosses the frontier. However, in specific cases national accounts impute changes of ownership even though in legal terms no change of ownership takes place (e.g. ''cross border financial leasing'', ''cross border deliveries between affiliates of the same enterprise'', ''goods crossing the border for significant processing to order or repair''). Also smuggled goods must be included in the import measurement.
* Imports of services consist of all services rendered by non-residents to residents. In national accounts any direct purchases by residents outside the [http://epp.eurostat.ec.europa.eu/statistics_explained/index.php/Economic_territory economic territory] of a country are recorded as imports of services; therefore all expenditure by tourists in the economic territory of another country are considered as part of the imports of services. Also international flows of illegal services must be included.

Basic trade statistics often differ in terms of definition and coverage from the requirements in the national accounts:
* Data on international trade in goods are mostly obtained through declarations to custom services. If a country applies the general trade system, all goods entering the country are recorded as imports. If the special trade system (e.g. extra-EU trade statistics) is applied goods which are received into customs warehouses are not recorded in external trade statistics unless they subsequently go into free circulation of the importing country.
* A special case is the intra-EU trade statistics. Since goods move freely between the member states of the EU without customs controls, statistics on trade in goods between the member states must be obtained through surveys. To reduce the statistical burden on the respondents small scale traders are excluded from the reporting obligation.
* Statistical recording of trade in services is based on declarations by banks to their central banks or by surveys of the main operators. In a globalized economy where services can be rendered via electronic means (''e.g. internet'') the related international flows of services are difficult to identify.
* Basic statistics on international trade normally do not record smuggled goods or international flows of illegal services. A small fraction of the smuggled goods and illegal services may nevertheless be included in official trade statistics through dummy shipments or dummy declarations that serve to conceal the illegal nature of the activities.

==Balance of trade==
Balance of trade represents a difference in value for import and export for a country. A country has [[Demand (economics)|demand]] for an import when domestic quantity demanded exceeds domestic quantity [[supply (economics)|supplied]], or when the [[price]] of the good (or service) on the [[world economy|world market]] is less than the price on the [[domestic market]].

The [[balance of trade]], usually denoted &lt;math&gt;NX&lt;/math&gt;, is the difference between the value of the goods (and services) a country exports and the value of the goods the country imports:

&lt;math&gt;NX = X - I&lt;/math&gt;, or equivalently &lt;math&gt;I = X - NX&lt;/math&gt;

A [[trade deficit]] occurs when imports are large relative to exports. Imports are impacted principally by a country's [[income]] and its productive resources. For example, the [[United States of America|US]] imports [[petroleum|oil]] from [[Canada]] even though the US has oil and Canada uses oil.  However, [[Consumer|consumers]] in the US are [[willingness to pay|willing to pay]] more for the [[marginalism|marginal]] barrel of oil than Canadian consumers are, because there is more oil demanded in the US than there is oil produced.{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}

In [[macroeconomic theory]], the value of imports &lt;math&gt;I&lt;/math&gt; can be modeled as a function of the domestic [[absorption (economics)|absorption]] &lt;math&gt;A&lt;/math&gt; and the [[real exchange rate]] &lt;math&gt;\sigma&lt;/math&gt;.  These are the two largest factors of imports and they both affect imports positively:

&lt;math&gt;I = I(A, \sigma)&lt;/math&gt; &lt;ref&gt;[[Burda, Wyplosz]] (2005): Macroeconomics: A European Text, Fourth Edition, [[Oxford University Press]]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Types of import==
There are two basic types of import:

# Industrial and consumer goods
# Intermediate goods and services

Companies import goods and services to supply to the domestic market at a cheaper price and better quality than competing goods manufactured in the domestic market. Companies import products that are not available in the local market.

There are three broad types of importers:

# Looking for any product around the world to import and sell.
# Looking for foreign sourcing to get their products at the cheapest price.
# Using foreign sourcing as part of their global [[supply chain]].

[[Direct Imports|Direct-import]] refers to a type of business importation involving a major retailer (e.g. [[Wal-Mart]]) and an overseas [[manufacturer]]. A retailer typically purchases products designed by local companies that can be manufactured overseas. In a direct-import program, the retailer bypasses the local supplier (colloquial ''middle-man'') and buys the final product directly from the manufacturer, possibly saving in [[added cost]]s. This type of business is fairly recent and follows the trends of the [[economic globalization|global economy]].

==Statistical data==

Data on the value of imports and their quantities often broken down by detailed lists of products are available in [[International_trade#Data|statistical collections on international trade]] published by the statistical services of intergovernmental organisations (e.g. [http://unstats.un.org/unsd/default.htm UNSTAT], [[FAOSTAT]], [[OECD]]), supranational statistical institutes (e.g. [[Eurostat]]) and national statistical institutes.

== See also ==
*[[List of countries by imports]]
*[[Export function]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.import-export-made-easy.com/glossary-of-trade-terms.html Glossary of Trade Terms]

[[Category:International trade]]

[[ar:استيراد]]
[[az:İmport]]
[[be:Імпарт]]
[[be-x-old:Імпарт]]
[[bg:Внос]]
[[ca:Importació]]
[[cs:Dovoz]]
[[da:Import]]
[[de:Import]]
[[es:Importación]]
[[eo:Importo]]
[[eu:Inportazio]]
[[fa:واردات]]
[[fr:Importation]]
[[gl:Importación]]
[[ko:수입 (무역)]]
[[hr:Uvoz]]
[[id:Impor]]
[[it:Importazione]]
[[kk:Кері импорт]]
[[lv:Imports]]
[[lt:Importas]]
[[hu:Import]]
[[ms:Import]]
[[nl:Invoer (handel)]]
[[new:आयात]]
[[ja:輸入]]
[[uz:Import]]
[[pl:Import]]
[[pt:Importação]]
[[ru:Импорт]]
[[sq:Importi]]
[[sk:Dovoz (obchod)]]
[[fi:Maahantuonti]]
[[sv:Import]]
[[tr:İthalat]]
[[tk:Import]]
[[uk:Імпорт]]
[[vi:Nhập khẩu]]
[[zh:進口]]</text>
      <sha1>swt0f0xnwwnj34k0pxys09rxswjldf5</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
