<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Investment</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>63121</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521600415</id>
      <parentid>520675326</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-06T01:22:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>EmausBot</username>
        <id>11292982</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>r2.7.3) (Robot: Adding [[uz:Investitsiya]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11125">{{Other uses}}
{{redirect|Invest|the term in meteorology|Invest (meteorology)}}
{{multiple issues|lead rewrite=July 2011|npov=July 2011|refimprove=July 2011}}
'''Investment''' has different meanings in finance and economics. Finance investment is putting money into something with the expectation of gain, that upon thorough analysis, has a high degree of security for the principal amount, as well as security of return, within an expected period of time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Graham|first=Benjamin and David Dodd|title=Security Analysis|year=1951|publisher=McGraw–Hill Book Company|isbn=007144829}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In contrast putting money into something with an expectation of gain without thorough analysis, without security of principal, and without security of return is [[gambling]]. Putting money into something with an expectation of gain with thorough analysis, without security of principal, and without security of return is [[speculation]]. As such, those shareholders who fail to thoroughly analyze their stock purchases, such as owners of mutual funds, could well be called gamblers. Indeed, given the efficient market hypothesis, which implies that a thorough analysis of stock data is irrational, most rational shareholders are, by definition, not investors, but speculators.

Investment is related to [[Saving (money)|saving]] or deferring [[Consumption (economics)|consumption]]. Investment is involved in many areas of the [[economy]], such as [[business management]] and [[finance]] whether for households, firms, or governments.

To avoid speculation an investment must be either directly backed by the pledge of sufficient [[collateral (finance)|collateral]] or insured by sufficient assets pledged by a third party.{{Or|date=September 2011}}  A thoroughly analyzed loan of money backed by collateral with greater immediate value than the loan amount may be considered an investment.  A financial instrument that is insured by the pledge of assets from a third party, such as a deposit in a financial institution insured by a government agency  may be considered an investment. Examples of these agencies include, in the United States, the [[Securities Investor Protection Corporation]], [[Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation]], or [[National Credit Union Administration]], or in Canada, the [[Canada Deposit Insurance Corporation]].

==In economics or macroeconomics==
In [[economic theory]] or in [[macroeconomics]], investment is the amount purchased per unit time of [[Good (economics and accounting)|goods]] which are not consumed but are to be used for future production (i.e. [[Capital (economics)|capital]]). Examples include [[railroad]] or [[factory]] construction.  Investment in [[human capital]] includes costs of additional schooling or on-the-job training. [[Inventory investment]] is the accumulation of goods [[inventories]]; it can be positive or negative, and it can be intended or unintended. In [[measures of national income and output]], &quot;gross investment&quot; (represented by the [[Variable (mathematics)|variable]] &lt;var style=&quot;font-family: serif; font-size: 1.1em;&quot;&gt;I&lt;/var&gt;) is also a component of [[gross domestic product]] (&lt;var&gt;GDP&lt;/var&gt;), given in the formula &lt;var&gt;GDP&lt;/var&gt; = &lt;var&gt;C&lt;/var&gt; + &lt;var style=&quot;font-family: serif; font-size: 1.1em;&quot;&gt;I&lt;/var&gt; + &lt;var&gt;G&lt;/var&gt; + &lt;var&gt;NX&lt;/var&gt;, where &lt;var&gt;C&lt;/var&gt; is consumption, &lt;var&gt;G&lt;/var&gt; is government spending, and &lt;var&gt;NX&lt;/var&gt; is net exports. Thus investment is everything that remains of total expenditure after consumption, government spending, and net exports are subtracted (i.e. &lt;var&gt;I&lt;/var&gt; = &lt;var&gt;GDP&lt;/var&gt; &amp;minus; &lt;var style=&quot;font-family: serif; font-size: 1.1em;&quot;&gt;C&lt;/var&gt; &amp;minus; &lt;var&gt;G&lt;/var&gt; &amp;minus; &lt;var&gt;NX&lt;/var&gt;).

Non-residential fixed investment (such as new factories) and residential investment (new houses) combine with inventory investment to make up &lt;var style=&quot;font-family: serif; font-size: 1.1em;&quot;&gt;I&lt;/var&gt;. &quot;Net investment&quot; deducts [[depreciation]] from gross investment. Net fixed investment is the value of the net increase in the capital stock per year.

Fixed investment, as expenditure over a period of time (&quot;per year&quot;), is not [[capital (economics)|capital]]. The time dimension of investment makes it a ''[[Stock and flow|flow]]''. By contrast, capital is a ''stock''&amp;mdash; that is, accumulated net investment ''to a point'' in time (such as December 31).

Investment is often modeled as a function of Income and Interest rates, given by the relation &lt;var style=&quot;font-family: serif; font-size: 1.1em;&quot;&gt;I&lt;/var&gt; = &lt;var&gt;f&lt;/var&gt;(&lt;var&gt;Y&lt;/var&gt;, &lt;var&gt;r&lt;/var&gt;). An increase in income encourages higher investment, whereas a higher interest rate may discourage investment as it becomes more costly to borrow money. Even if a firm chooses to use its own funds in an investment, the interest rate represents an [[opportunity cost]] of investing those funds rather than lending out that amount of money for interest.&lt;ref&gt;[[Kevin A. Hassett]] (2008, 2nd ed.). [http://www.econlib.org/library/Enc/Investment.html &quot;Investment,&quot;] ''The Concise Encyclopedia of Economics''. Library of Economics and Liberty.&lt;/ref&gt;

==In finance==
In [[finance]], investment is the commitment of funds through collateralized lending, or making a deposit into a secured institution.

In contrast to investment; dollar cost averaging, [[market timing]], and diversification are phrases associated with speculation.

Investments are often made indirectly through [[intermediary|intermediaries]], such as [[bank]]s,  [[credit union]]s, [[brokerage firm|broker]]s, [[lender]]s, and [[insurance]] companies. Though their legal and procedural details differ, an intermediary generally makes an investment using money from many individuals, each of whom receives a claim on the intermediary.

== History ==

The [[Code of Hammurabi]] 1700 B.C. provided a legal framework for investment establishing a means for the pledge of collateral by codifying debtor and creditor rights in regard to pledged land.  Punishments for breaking financial obligations were not as severe as those for crimes involving injury or death.

In the early 1900s purchasers of stocks, bonds, and other securities were described in media, academia, and commerce as [[speculation|speculators]]. By the 1950s the term investment had been co-opted by financial brokers and their advertising agencies to promote speculation. By the late 1900s the terms speculation and speculator were somewhat down played by the media, likely due to turmoil in the capital markets ever since the tech boom bubble pop, and the historical fascination with blaming wall street speculators for all the ills of the world, had mysteriously returned to the newspapers. The public is instead fed the word ''investor'' or ''investment'' instead of ''speculator'' or ''speculation'', even though the bulk of the activities are not investment grade.

== Linguistic significance ==

Common usage of ''investment'' to describe ''speculation'' has reduced investor capacity to discern investment from speculation, reduced investor awareness of risk associated with speculation, increased capital available to speculation, and decreased capital available to investment.

==Real estate as the instrument of investment==
&lt;!-- [[Pakeha settlers#Nelson]] links here. Please update that link when changing this section name --&gt;
In [[real estate]], investment money is used to purchase [[property]] for the purpose of holding, reselling or leasing for income and there is an element of capital risk.

===Residential real estate===
Investment in residential real estate is the most common form of real estate investment measured by number of participants because it includes property purchased as a primary residence. In many cases the buyer does not have the full purchase price for a property and must engage a lender such as a bank, finance company or private lender. Different countries have their individual normal lending levels, but usually they will fall into the range of 70–90% of the purchase price. Against other types of real estate, residential real estate is the least risky.{{Citation needed|date=November 2009}}

===Commercial real estate===
Commercial real estate consists of multifamily apartments, office buildings, retail space, hotels and motels, warehouses, and other commercial properties. Due to the higher risk of commercial real estate, [[loan-to-value ratio]]s allowed by banks and other lenders are lower and often fall in the range of 50–70%.{{Citation needed|date=May 2009}}

==See also==
* [[Asset]]
* [[Risk]]
* [[Alternative investments]]
* [[Diversifying investment]]
* [[Foreign direct investment]]
* [[List of countries by gross fixed investment as percentage of GDP]]
* [[List of economics topics]]
* [[Mortgage Investment Corporation]]
* [[Rate of return]] (ROR, a.k.a. ROI)
* [[Socially responsible investing]]
* [[Specialized investment fund]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* {{dmoz|Business/Investing/Stocks_and_Bonds/Equities/Research_and_Analysis/|Investing}}
&lt;!--======================== {{No more links}} ============================
    | PLEASE BE CAUTIOUS IN ADDING MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. Wikipedia  |
    | is not a collection of links nor should it be used for advertising. |
    |                                                                     |
    |           Excessive or inappropriate links WILL BE DELETED.         |
    | See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.  |
    |                                                                     |
    | If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or   |
    | replacements on this article's discussion page, or submit your link |
    | to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org)   |
    | and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.         |
    ======================= {{No more links}} =============================--&gt;

[[Category:Investment| ]]
[[Category:Macroeconomics]]

[[ar:استثمار]]
[[arc:ܫܘܚܡܠܐ]]
[[az:İnvestisiya]]
[[be:Інвестыцыя]]
[[be-x-old:Інвэстыцыя]]
[[bg:Инвестиция]]
[[bs:Investicija]]
[[br:Posterezh]]
[[ca:Inversió econòmica]]
[[cs:Investice]]
[[da:Investering]]
[[de:Investition]]
[[et:Investeering]]
[[el:Επένδυση]]
[[es:Inversión]]
[[eu:Inbertsio]]
[[fa:سرمایه‌گذاری]]
[[fr:Investissement]]
[[ko:투자]]
[[hy:Ներդրում (բանկային)]]
[[hi:विनियोग]]
[[hr:Investicija]]
[[it:Investimento]]
[[he:השקעה]]
[[kn:ಬಂಡವಾಳ]]
[[la:Collocatio pecuniae]]
[[lv:Investīcija]]
[[lt:Investicijos]]
[[ms:Pelaburan]]
[[nl:Investering]]
[[new:लगानी]]
[[ja:投資]]
[[no:Investering]]
[[nn:Investering]]
[[mhr:Инвестиций]]
[[uz:Investitsiya]]
[[pl:Inwestycja]]
[[pt:Investimento]]
[[ru:Инвестиции]]
[[sq:Investimi]]
[[simple:Investing]]
[[sh:Investicija]]
[[fi:Investointi]]
[[sv:Investering]]
[[te:పెట్టుబడి]]
[[th:การลงทุน]]
[[tr:Yatırım]]
[[uk:Інвестиція]]
[[vi:Đầu tư (kinh tế học)]]
[[zh:投资]]</text>
      <sha1>ad94tfgim8r2um6wuaxdqvuz5c4rqli</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
