<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Local purchasing</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>324008</id>
    <revision>
      <id>518557830</id>
      <parentid>518557616</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-18T18:29:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>174.45.108.109</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Alternative Viewpoints */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8869">{{Refimprove|date=September 2007}}
'''Local purchasing''' is a preference to buy locally produced goods and services over those produced more distantly. It is very often abbreviated as a positive goal 'buy local' to parallel the phrase [[think globally, act locally]] common in [[green politics]].

On the national level, the equivalent of local purchasing is [[import substitution]], the deliberate [[industrial policy]] or [[agricultural policy]] of replacing goods or services produced on the far side of a national border with those produced on the near side, i.e. in the same country or [[trade bloc]].

Historically, there have been so many incentives to buy locally that no one had to make any kind of point to do so, but with current market conditions, it is often cheaper to buy distantly-produced goods, despite the added costs in terms of [[packaging]], [[transport]], [[inspection]], [[retail]] facilities, etc.. As such, one must now often take explicit action if one wants to purchase locally produced goods.

These market conditions are based on externalized costs, argues local economy advocates. Examples of externalized costs include the price of war, asthma, or climate change, which are not typically included in the cost of a gallon of fuel, for instance.

Most advocates for local economics address contracting and investment, as well as purchasing. 

Agricultural alternatives are being sought, and have manifested themselves in the form of farmers’ markets, farmed goods sold through the community [[cooperatives]], [[urban (horticulture) gardens|urban gardens]], and even school programs that endorse community agriculture.

==Rationale for local purchasing==
Advocates often suggest local purchasing as a form of [[moral purchasing]]. Local purchasing is often claimed to be better for the environment and better for working conditions.&lt;ref name=&quot;sustainableconnections&quot;&gt;[http://sustainableconnections.org/thinklocal/why/ &quot;Why Buy Locally Owned?&quot;] by Sustainable Connections&lt;/ref&gt; Others contend (with  empirical evidence) that local purchasing and contracting enhances local job creation and wealth while strengthening community cohesiveness.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Benefits of Doing Business Locally&quot;&gt;[http://www.amiba.net/home/benefits-local-business &quot;The Benefits of Doing Business Locally&quot;] by Jeff Milchen&lt;/ref&gt;

The first potential moral benefit is environmental: Bringing goods from afar generally requires using more energy than transporting goods locally, and some environmental advocates (for instance, [[Amory Lovins]]) see this as a serious environmental threat. Transportation contributes to environmental contamination in addition to the pollution caused by chemical inputs in the growing phase. Of course, locally produced goods are not ''always'' more energy-efficient; local [[agriculture]] or [[manufacturing]] may rely on heavy inputs (e.g. [[industrial agriculture]]) or energy-inefficient machinery and/or transportation systems. However, small-scale growers tend to be more environmentally friendly because industrial-sized agriculture uses genetically modified crops, monoculture production, and chemical fertilizer intensive processes to grow crops—practices that local farmers typically avoid.&lt;ref name=&quot;Society 2010&quot;&gt;Environment and Society: A Critical Introduction (Critical Introductions to Geography) by Paul Robbins, John Hintz, and Sarah A. Moore, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

The second potential benefit is creating better working conditions.  Nonetheless, while diverting purchasing from developing countries to local farmers helps build the local economy, it can lead to worse conditions for poor farmers in developing countries because it removes potential buyers from the market.

The goal of localization is not necessarily to eradicate globalization; rather, it is to reduce unnecessary transport and to strengthen and diversify community economies.&lt;ref&gt;Bringing the Food Economy Home: Local Alternatives to Global Agribusiness, by Helena Norberg-Hodge, Todd Merrifield, and Steven Gorelick, 2002, p. 113&lt;/ref&gt; This calls for condensation of agriculture and supports the idea that local farmers are capable of sustaining a community.

The term “Buy Local” has become subject to varying interpretations. While leading advocates of local independent business such as the [[American Independent Business Alliance]] say the term should apply only to locally-owned independent businesses, some campaigns run by governments and Chambers of Commerce consider local to be merely a geographic consideration.&lt;ref name=&quot;amiba&quot;&gt;[http://www.amiba.net/about_ibas &quot;What is a Local Independent Business] by American Independent Business Alliance&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, many corporations have manipulated the term in ways critics call &quot;local-washing.&quot; &lt;ref name=&quot;newrules&quot;&gt;[http://www.newrules.org/retail/article/corporate-coopt-local &quot;The Corporate Co-opt of Local&quot;] article by Stacy Mitchell&lt;/ref&gt;

==Alternative Viewpoints ==

The argument that 'buying local' is good for the economy is questioned by many economic theorists. They argue that transportation costs actually account for a tiny fraction of overall production prices, and that choosing less efficient local products over more efficient nonlocal products is an economic [[deadweight loss]]. Moreover, the community as a whole does not actually save money because consumers have to spend so much more on the more expensive local products.&lt;ref name=&quot;buylocalcanbebadeconomics&quot;&gt;[http://minnesota.publicradio.org/display/web/2009/04/06/buy_local_economics/ &quot;'Buy Local' Can Be Bad Economics&quot;] by Louis Johnston on MPR News&lt;/ref&gt; [http://www.econlib.org/library/Columns/y2008/Selicklocal.html Karen Selick] argues that the buying local trend is just a watered down version of protectionism, and would not benefit communities as proponents envisage.

Additionally, organic local food tends to be more costly so this is not an appealing option to consumers who are shopping on a budget. Small-scale farmers do not receive government subsidies and are not able to support their business on prices comparable to those of industrial-scale food production,&lt;ref name=&quot;Society 2010&quot;/&gt; so they must sell at higher prices to make a living. Therefore, in order for the appeal of the local agriculture movement to overcome the economic cost, people must be willing to invest in it, which is unlikely when apparently similar products are available in grocery stores for a lower cost. Despite this, distribution costs of expansive food trade must also be factored in; with increasing gas prices, it becomes more expensive to ship food from outside sources.

Besides these arguments against purchasing locally, society has now reached a point where globalization is so deeply embedded, it is difficult to turn back, and impossible to remove completely. Globalization has fostered a higher level of dependency, requiring international trade for products that may not be otherwise available, particularly produce that is grown out-of-season. Limited local accessibility is indicative that trade on a global scale is a necessity in the modern economy. This transcontinental sharing of food results in an exchange that continues to be both profitable and sustainable, provided that the government support and consumer demand for these products persists.

==See also==

*[[Fiscal localism]]
*[[Energy economics]]
*[[Community-based economics]]
*[[Eco-communalism]]
*[[Local food]]
*[[Local currency]]
*[[Comparative advantage]]
*[[Small business]]
*[[Civic agriculture]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://amiba.net The American Independent Business Alliance], a non-profit organization devoted to advancing local purchasing by helping North American communities establish [[Independent Business Alliance]]s.
*[http://www.localharvest.org/ Local Harvest], a resource for the buy local, farm product and other 'alternative market' food, activism, news and event
*[http://www.livingeconomies.org/ BALLE - Business Alliance for Local Living Economies], a network of communities supporting their independent businesses
*[http://www.pluggingtheleaks.org/ New Economics Foundation], case studies and information on the economic impacts of local purchasing.
*[http://greenfabric.com/ Green Fabric], a buy-local-what-was-made-local website, trying to fill the need for a listing of local creatives and producers.
*[http://buylocalfood.org/ CISA - Community Involved in Sustaining Agriculture], a community organization of farmers, consumers and professionals working together to sustain agriculture and the unique rural character of western Massachusetts for the past 15 years.
*[http://www.the350project.net/ The 3/50 Project], a &quot;buy local&quot; promotional campaign by marketing consultant Cinda Baxter.

[[Category:Consumer behaviour]]
[[Category:Localism]]

[[cs:Lokální nakupování]]</text>
      <sha1>oi2e04qbk0j9fmc3cn9x7n0525g6lcu</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
