<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Low-carbon economy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8941842</id>
    <revision>
      <id>515419297</id>
      <parentid>515416551</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-01T05:04:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cupco</username>
        <id>17406884</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/59.27.18.40|59.27.18.40]] ([[User talk:59.27.18.40|talk]]): Test edit. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="31583">{{Expand Japanese|低炭素社会|date=January 2012}}
{{Green economics sidebar}}
A '''Low-Carbon Economy''' (LCE), '''Low-Fossil-Fuel Economy''' (LFFE)&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt;[http://nanoparis.blogspot.com/2006/03/dye-sensitized-solar-cells.html Nanomech in Photovoltaics: Dye Sensitized Solar Cells&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; or '''Decarbonised Economy'''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.greenpeace.org/india/en/news/Decarbonised-Economy1/ Greenpeace (2010), Decarbonised Economy - Opportunities and responsibilities of the ICT sector in a changing climate&lt;/ref&gt; is an [[economy]] that has a minimal output of [[greenhouse gas]] (GHG) emissions into the environment [[biosphere]], but specifically refers to the greenhouse gas [[carbon dioxide]]. GHG emissions due to anthropogenic (human) activity are increasingly either causing [[climate change]] ([[global warming]]) or making climate change worse. Scientists are concerned about the negative impacts of climate change on humanity in the foreseeable future.&lt;ref&gt;[[Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change|IPCC]]&lt;/ref&gt;

Globally implemented LCEs, therefore, are proposed, by those having drawn this conclusion, as a means to [[Avoiding dangerous climate change|avoid catastrophic climate change]], and as a precursor to the more advanced, zero-carbon society and [[renewable energy]] economy.

==Rationale and aims==
{{Refimprove section|date=October 2010}}
Nations may seek to become low-carbon or decarbonised economies as a part of a national [[climate change mitigation]] strategy.  A comprehensive strategy to mitigate, if that is possible, [[climate change]] is [[carbon neutrality]] and [[geoengineering]].

The aim of a LCE is to integrate all aspects of itself from its manufacturing, agriculture, transportation, and power-generation, etc. around technologies that produce energy and materials with little GHG emission, and, thus, around populations, buildings, machines, and devices that use those energies and materials efficiently, and, dispose of or recycle its wastes so as to have a minimal output of GHGs. Furthermore, it has been proposed that to make the transition to an LCE economically viable we would have to attribute a cost(per unit output) to GHGs through means such as [[emissions trading]] and/or a [[carbon tax]].

Some nations are presently low carbon: societies that are not heavily industrialised or populated. In order to avoid climate change on a global level, all nations considered [[carbon intensity|carbon intensive]] societies, and societies that are heavily populated might have to become zero-carbon societies and economies. Several of these countries{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}} have pledged to cut their emissions by 100% via [[Carbon offset|offset]]ting emissions rather than ceasing all emissions ([[carbon neutrality]]); in other words, emitting will not cease but will continue and will be ''offset'' to a different geographical area.

===Energy policy===
====Renewable energy and energy efficiency====
{{See also|Renewable energy commercialization}}
[[Image:Total Installed Wind Capacity 1197-2020 -MW-.jpg|thumb|Worldwide installed wind power capacity 1997–2020 [MW], history and predictions. Data source: [http://www.wwindea.org/ WWEA]]]
[[Image:Nellis AFB Solar panels.jpg|thumb|Solar array at [[Nellis Solar Power Plant]]. These panels track the sun in one axis.  Credit: U.S. Air Force photo by Senior Airman Larry E. Reid Jr.]]

Recent advances in technology and policy will allow [[renewable energy]] and [[Efficient energy use|energy efficiency]] to play major roles in displacing fossil fuels, meeting global energy demand while reducing carbon dioxide emissions. Renewable energy technologies are being rapidly commercialized and, in conjunction with efficiency gains, can achieve far greater emissions reductions than either could independently.&lt;ref name=wwinst2009&gt;Janet L. Sawin and William R. Moomaw. [http://www.worldwatch.org/files/pdf/Renewable%20Revolution.pdf Renewable Revolution:Low-Carbon Energy by 2030] Worldwatch Report, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

Renewable energy is [[energy]] that comes from [[natural resource]]s such as [[sunlight]], [[wind]], [[rain]], [[tidal energy|tides]], and [[geothermal energy|geothermal heat]], which are [[Renewable resource|renewable]] (naturally replenished). In 2008, about 19% of global final energy consumption came from renewables.&lt;ref name=r2010&gt;[[REN21]] (2010). [http://www.ren21.net/globalstatusreport/REN21_GSR_2010_full.pdf Renewables 2010 Global Status Report] p. 15-16.&lt;/ref&gt; During the five years from the end of 2004 through 2009, worldwide renewable energy capacity grew at rates of 10–60 percent annually for many technologies. For wind power and many other renewable technologies, growth accelerated in 2009 relative to the previous four years.&lt;ref name=ren15/&gt; More wind power capacity was added during 2009 than any other renewable technology. However, grid-connected [[photovoltaics]] increased the fastest of all renewables technologies, with a 60 percent annual average growth rate for the five-year period.&lt;ref name=ren15&gt;[[REN21]] (2010). [http://www.ren21.net/globalstatusreport/REN21_GSR_2010_full.pdf Renewables 2010 Global Status Report] p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt;

Energy efficiency gains in recent decades have been significant, but there is still much more that can be achieved. With a concerted effort and strong policies in place, future energy efficiency improvements are likely to be very large. Heat is one of many forms of &quot;energy wastage&quot; that could be captured to significantly increase useful energy without burning more fossil fuels.&lt;ref name=wwinst2009/&gt;

====Energy storage====
A criticsm of renewable energy is the difficulty in balancing an electrical energy grid using intermittant and variable energy sources. Storage of energy using for example chemical, mechanical, etc. can help, but at a cost of lowering overall system efficiencies.


====Smart grid====
One proposal from Karlsruhe University&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tR8gEMpzos4 Combined Power Plant video]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.kombikraftwerk.de/index.php?id=27 Combined Power Plant &lt;/ref&gt; developed as a virtual power station is the use of solar and wind energy for base load with hydro and biogas for make up or peak load. Hydro and biogas are used as energy storage. This requires the development of a smart intelligent grid hopefully including local power networks than use energy near the site of production, thereby minimising electrical grid losses.

====Methane cycle====
A further development of this at kassel University&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uni-kassel.de/upress/online/frei/978-3-89958-798-2.volltext.frei.pdf Bioenergy and renewable power methane in integrated 100% renewable energy system]&lt;/ref&gt;, Fraunhofer Institute, Negawatt Institute&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.negawatt.org/scenario-negawatt-2011-p46.html scénario négaWatt 2011 (France)]&lt;/ref&gt;, etc. is the use of the carbon capture, hydrogen and its conversion into methane (SNG synthetic natural gas) to act as a storage for intermittant renewables. 

CO2 + 4H2 → CH4 + 2H2O Sabatier reaction

This involves the use of the existing natural gas (methane) grid as the store. In this case, the carbon dioxide is given economic value as a component of energy carrier.

This &quot;solar fuel&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.solar-fuel.net/en/the-challenge Solar Fuel]&lt;/ref&gt; cycle uses the excess electrical renewable energy that cannot be used instantanously in the grid, which otherwise would be wasted to create hydrogen via electrolysis of water. The hydrogen is then combined with CO2 to create synthetic or substitute natural gas SNG and stored in the natural gas network. 

The natural gas is used to create electrical energy (and the heat used as well in CHP) on demand when there is not enough sun (photovoltaic, CSP...) or wind (turbines) or water (hydro, ocean current, waves,...).  The German natural gas grid, for example, has 2 months of storage, more than enough to see out renewable energy low production points.

====Nuclear power and CCS====
[[Nuclear power]] and/or the proposed strategies of [[carbon capture and storage]] (CCS) have been offered as the primary means to achieve a LCE while continuing to exploit non-renewable resources; there is concern, however, with the matter of spent-nuclear-fuel storage, security, and the uncertainty of costs and time needed to successfully implement CCS worldwide and with guarantees that the stored emissions will not leak into the [[biosphere]]. The [[liquid fluoride thorium reactor]] (LFTR) has been suggested as a solution to the concerns posed by conventional nuclear.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1021/es2021318}} &quot;LFTR can mean a 1000+ year solution or a quality low-carbon bridge to truly [[sustainable energy]] sources solving a huge portion of mankind’s negative [[environmental impact]].&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

====Combined Heat and Power====

[[Combined Heat and Power]] (CHP) is a technology which by allowing the more efficient use of fuel will at least reduce carbon emissions; should the fuel be [[biomass]] or [[biogas]] or hydrogen used as an energy store then in principle it can be a zero carbon option. CHP can also be used with a nuclear reactor as the energy source, there are examples of such installations in the far North of the Russian Federation.

==Primary sector==
{{Refimprove section|date=October 2010}}

===Agriculture===
{{See also|Low carbon diet}}

Most of the agricultural facilities in the developed world are mechanized due to rural electrification.  Rural electrification has produced significant productivity gains, but it also uses a lot of energy.  For this and other reasons (such as transport costs) in a low-carbon society, rural areas would need available supplies of renewably produced electricity.{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}}

Irrigation can be one of the main components of an agricultural facility's energy consumption.  In parts of California, it can be up to 90%.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fypower.org/agri/ Flex Your Power - Agricultural Sector]&lt;/ref&gt;  In the low carbon economy, irrigation equipment will be maintained and continuously updated and farms will use less irrigation water.

====Crops====
Different crops require different amounts of energy input.  For example, glasshouse crops, irrigated crops, and orchards require a lot of energy to maintain, while row crops and field crops do not need as much maintenance.  Those glasshouse and irrigated crops that do exist will incorporate the following improvements:&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;New Zealand Energy Intensive Business Initiative, http://www.mfe.govt.nz/issues/climate/policies-initiatives/energy-pilot-scheme.html&lt;/ref&gt;

Glasshouse crops
*environmental control systems
*heat recovery using condensers
*heat storage using buffer tanks
*heat retention using thermal screens
*alternative fuels (e.g., waste wood)
*cogeneration (heat and power)
Irrigated arable crops
*soil moisture measurement to regulate irrigation
*variable-speed drives on pumps

====Livestock====
Livestock operations can also use a lot of energy depending on how they are run.  Feed lots use animal feed made from corn, soybeans, and other crops.  Energy must be expended to produce these crops, process, and transport them.  Free-range animals find their own vegetation to feed on.  The farmer may expend energy to take care of that vegetation, but not nearly as much as the farmer growing cereal and oil-seed crops.

Many livestock operations currently use a lot of energy to water their livestock.  In the low-carbon economy, such operations will use more water conservation methods such as rainwater collection, water cisterns, etc., and they will also pump/distribute that water with on-site renewable energy sources (most likely wind and solar).

Due to rural electrification, most agricultural facilities in the developed world use a lot of electricity.  In a low-carbon economy, farms will be run and equipped to allow for greater energy efficiency.  The dairy industry, for example, will incorporate the following changes:&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;

Irrigated Dairy
*heat recovery on milk vats
*variable speed drives on motors/pumps
*heat recovery from hot water wash
*soil moisture measurement to regulate irrigation
*biodigester with cogen (heat &amp; power)
*vat wrap
*solar water heating
*ripple control
*ice bank
*chemical substitute for hot-water wash

===Hunting and fishing===
Fishing is quite energy intensive.  Improvements such as heat recovery on refrigeration and trawl net technology will be common in the low-carbon economy.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;{{Dead link|date=May 2010}}

===Forestry===
{{Main|Wood economy}}
In the low-carbon economy, forestry operations will be focused on low-impact practices and regrowth.  Forest managers will make sure that they do not disturb soil-based carbon reserves too much.  Specialized tree farms  will be the main source of material for many products.  Quick maturing tree varieties will be grown on short rotations in order to maximize output.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.woodland-trust.org.uk/campaigns/briefingsmore/carbonmgt.htm Trees and their role in carbon management for land and business], The Woodland Trust.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mining===
{{Main|Gas flare}}
Flaring and venting of [[natural gas]] in oil wells is a significant source of [[greenhouse gas]] emissions. Its contribution to greenhouse gases has declined by three-quarters in absolute terms since a peak in the 1970s of approximately 110 million metric tons/year, and in 2004 accounted for about 1/2 of one percent of all [[human impact on the environment|anthropogenic]] [[carbon dioxide]] emissions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://cdiac.esd.ornl.gov/trends/emis/tre_glob.htm Global, Regional, and National CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; Emissions]. In ''Trends: A Compendium of Data on Global Change'', Marland, G., T.A. Boden, and R. J. Andres, 2005, Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Center, Oak Ridge National Laboratory, U.S. Department of Energy, Oak Ridge, Tennessee.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[World Bank]] estimates that 134 billion cubic meters of natural gas are flared or vented annually (2010 datum), an amount equivalent to the combined annual gas consumption of [[Germany]] and [[France]] or enough to supply the entire world with gas for 16 days.
This flaring is highly concentrated: 10 countries account for 70% of emissions, and twenty for 85%.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.worldbank.org/WBSITE/EXTERNAL/TOPICS/EXTOGMC/EXTGGFR/0,,menuPK:578075~pagePK:64168427~piPK:64168435~theSitePK:578069,00.html The World Bank, ''Global Gas Flaring Reduction&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The top-ten leading contributors to world gas flaring in 2010, were (in declining order): [[Russia]] (26%), [[Nigeria]] (11%), [[Iran]] (8%), [[Iraq]] (7%), [[Algeria]] (4%), [[Angola]] (3%), [[Kazakhstan]] (3%), [[Libya]] (3%), [[Saudi Arabia]] (3%), and [[Venezuela]] (2%).&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.worldbank.org/WBSITE/EXTERNAL/TOPICS/EXTOGMC/EXTGGFR/0,,contentMDK:22137498~pagePK:64168445~piPK:64168309~theSitePK:578069,00.html Globas Gas Flaring Reduction, The World Bank.]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Secondary sector==
===Basic metals processing===
*high efficiency electric motors
*induction furnaces
*[[heat recovery]]

===Nonmetallic product processing===
*variable speed drives
*[[injection molding]] - replace hydraulic with electric servo motors

===Wood processing===
*high efficiency motors
*high efficiency fans
*dehumidifier driers

===Paper and pulp making===
*variable speed drives
*high efficiency motors

===Food processing===
*high efficiency boilers
*heat recovery e.g. refrigeration
*solar hot water for pre-heating
*[[bio fuel]]s e.g. tallow, wood

==Tertiary sector==
===Retail===
Retail operations in the low-carbon economy will have several new features.  One will be high-efficiency lighting such as compact fluorescent, halogen, and eventually LED light sources.  Many retail stores will also feature roof-top solar panel arrays.  These make sense because solar panels produce the most energy during the daytime and during the summer.  These are the same times that electricity is the most expensive and also the same times that stores use the most electricity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.renewableenergyworld.com/rea/news/story?id=35633 Grocery Store Sets California Solar Standard], Renewable Energy World, 22 August 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Transportation services===
Decarbonisation of (urban) mobility by means of:
* More energy efficiency and alternative propulsion:
** Increased focus on fuel efficient vehicle shapes and configurations, with more [[vehicle electrification]], particularly through [[plug-in hybrid]]s.
** More alternative and flex-fuel vehicles (based on local conditions and availability)
** Driver training for more fuel efficiency.
** Low-carbon [[biofuel]]s [[cellulosic ethanol|cellulosic]] ([[biodiesel]], [[bioethanol]], [[biobutanol]])
** Petroleum fuel [[fee|surcharge]]s will be a more significant part of consumer costs.
* Less international trade of physical objects, despite more overall trade (as measure by value of goods)
* Greater use of marine and [[electric rail transport]], less use of air and truck transport.
* Increased non-motorised transport (i.e. walking and cycling) and public transport usage, less reliance on private motor vehicles.
* More [[Pipeline transport|pipeline]] capacity for common fluid commodities such as water, ethanol, butanol, natural gas, petroleum, and hydrogen (in addition to gasoline and diesel).

See&lt;ref&gt;[[Energy Information Administration]] Industry Analysis Briefs, http://www.eia.doe.gov/emeu/mecs/iab/index5e.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Carbon Trust, http://www.carbontrust.com&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dti.gov.uk/files/file10719.pdf BERR - Redirect&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Health services===

There have been some moves to investigate the ways and extent to which health systems contribute to greenhouse gas emissions and how they may need to change to become part of a low-carbon world.  The Sustainable Development Unit&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sdu.nhs.uk/&lt;/ref&gt; of the NHS in the UK is one of the first official bodies to have been set up in this area, whilst organisations such as the Campaign for Greener Healthcare&lt;ref&gt;http://greenerhealthcare.org/&lt;/ref&gt; are also producing influential changes at a clinical level.   This work includes
* Quantification of where the health services emissions stem from.
* Information on the environmental impacts of alternative models of treatment and service provision
Some of the suggested changes needed are:
* Greater efficiency and lower ecological impact of energy, buildings, and procurement choices (e.g., in-patient meals, pharmaceuticals, and medical equipment).
* A shift from focusing solely on cure to prevention, through the promotion of healthier, lower-carbon lifestyles, e.g. diets lower in red meat and dairy products, walking or cycling wherever possible, better town planning to encourage more outdoor lifestyles.
* Improving public transport and liftsharing options for transport to and from hospitals and clinics.

==Initial steps==
A good overview of the history of international efforts towards a low-carbon economy, from its initial seed at the inaugural UN Conference on the Human Environment in Stockholm in 1972, has been given by David Runnals.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sapiens.revues.org/1150 Runnals, D. (2011) “Environment and economy: joined at the hip or just strange bed-fellows?”. ''S.A.P.I.EN.S.'' '''4''' (1) ]&lt;/ref&gt;
On the international scene, the most prominent early step in the direction of a low-carbon economy was the signing of the [[Kyoto Protocol]], which came into force on February 16, 2005, under which most industrialized countries committed to reduce their carbon emissions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://2050.nies.go.jp/ Japan Low Carbon Society Scenarios toward 2050&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite speech
| title = Towards a low carbon economy | author = Margot Wallström | date = 11 March 2004 | location = Brussels | url = http://www.europaworld.org/week168/speechwalstrom12304.htm | accessdate = 2008-08-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; Importantly, all member nations of the [[Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development]] except the [[Energy policy of the United States|United States]] have ratified the protocol.
Europe is the leading geopolitical continent in defining and mobilising decarbonisation policies.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.euractiv.com/climate-change/decarbonisation-challenge-us-european-perspectives/article-162796 The decarbonisation challenge - US and European perspectives, EurActiv, 28 march 2007]&lt;/ref&gt; For instance, the [[International Association of Public Transport|UITP]] - an organisation advocating [[sustainable mobility]] and [[public transport]] - has an EU office, but less well developed contacts with, for example, the US. The European Union Committee of the [[International Association of Public Transport|UITP]] wants to promote decarbonisation of urban mobility in Europe.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uitp.org/news/pics/pdf/PR_Decarbonisation.pdf UITP (2011), More and better public transport is the key to decarbonised mobility in Europe]&lt;/ref&gt; Although Europe is nowadays the leading geopolitical continent with regard to lowering emissions, Europe is quickly losing ground to Asia, with countries such as China and South Korea.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.e3g.org/programmes/europe-articles/financing-the-decarbonisation-of-european-infrastructure Holmes et al (2012), Financing the Decarbonisation of European Infrastructure]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Countries===
====Costa Rica====
[[Costa Rica]] sources much of its energy needs from renewables and is undertaking [[reforestation]] projects. In 2007, the Costa Rican government announced the commitment for Costa Rica to become the first [[carbon neutral]] country by 2021.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title= Costa Rica Aims to Be a Carbon-Neutral Nation | url =http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=19141333 | accessdate = 2008-02-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title= Costa Rica Aims to Become First &quot;Carbon Neutral&quot; Country | url =http://www.worldwatch.org/node/4958 | accessdate = 2008-02-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title= País quiere ser primera nación con balance neutro de carbono | url =http://www.nacion.com/ln_ee/2007/febrero/21/aldea1002694.html | accessdate = 2008-02-18 | language = Spanish}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Iceland====
{{Main|Renewable energy in Iceland}}
Iceland began utilising renewable energy early in the 20th century and so since has been a low-carbon economy. However, since dramatic economic growth, Iceland's emissions have increased significantly per capita. As of 2009, Iceland energy is sourced from mostly [[geothermal energy]] and [[hydropower]], [[renewable energy in Iceland]] and, since 1999, has provided over 70% of the nation's [[primary energy]] and 99.9% of Iceland's [[electricity]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.statice.is/Uploads/files/LH06/L060701.xls |title=Gross energy consumption by source 1987–2005 |publisher=''[http://www.statice.is/?PageID=583 Statistics Iceland]'' |accessdate=2007-05-14 |format=XLS}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of this, Iceland's carbon emissions per capita are 62% lower than those of the [[United States]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://mdgs.un.org/unsd/mdg/Data.aspx |title=United Nations Millennium Development Goals Indicators |publisher=[[United Nations]] |accessdate=2006-08-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; despite using more primary energy per capita,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://eng.idnadarraduneyti.is/Publications/nr/1170 |title=Energy in Iceland |publisher=Icelandic Ministries of Industry and Commerce |accessdate=2007-05-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; due to the fact that it is renewable and thus limitless and costs Icelanders almost nothing. Iceland seeks [[carbon neutrality]] and expects to use 100% renewable energy by 2050 by generating [[hydrogen fuel]] from renewable energy sources.

====Australia====
{{Main|Renewable energy in Australia}}
Australia has implemented schemes to start the transition to a low-carbon economy but [[carbon neutrality]] has not been mentioned and since the introduction of such scheme emissions have increased. The [[Rudd Government|current government]] has mentioned the concept but has done little and has pledged to lower emissions by 5-15%. In 2001, The Howard Government introduced a Mandatory Renewable Energy Target (MRET) scheme. In 2007, the Government revised the MRET - 20 percent of Australia's electricity supply to come from renewable energy sources by 2020. In 2009, the Rudd Government will legislate a short-term emissions reduction target, another revision to the Mandatory Renewable Energy Target as well as an [[emissions trading scheme]]. Renewable energy sources provide 8-10% of the nation's energy, and this figure will increase significantly in the coming years. However coal dependence and exporting conflicts with the concept of Australia as a low-carbon economy. Carbon-neutral businesses have received no incentive; they have voluntarily done so. Carbon-offset companies offer assessments based on lifecycle impacts to businesses that seek carbon neutrality. The Carbon Reduction Institute&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.noco2.com.au Carbon Reduction Institute]&lt;/ref&gt; is one such offset provider, that has produced a [[NoCO2 Certification Program|certification procedure]] to promote a low-carbon economy in Australia.

In 2011 the Gillard Government introduced a tax on carbon dioxide emissions for businesses.

====New Zealand====
====China====
{{Main|Renewable energy in China}}
In [[China]], the city of [[Dongtan]] is to be built to produce zero net greenhouse gas emissions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.arup.com/newsitem.cfm?pageid=7009
|title=Arup unveils plans for world’s first sustainable city in Dongtan, China
|publisher=[[Arup]]
|date=2005-08-24
|accessdate=2007-04-26
|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070407074256/http://www.arup.com/newsitem.cfm?pageid=7009 |archivedate = April 7, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Chinese State Council has announced its aim to cut China's carbon dioxide emission per unit of GDP by 40%-45% in 2020 from 2005 levels.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.chinadaily.com.cn/cndy/2009-11/27/content_9060500.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

====United Kingdom====
In the [[United Kingdom]], the [[Climate Change Act 2008]] outlining a framework for the transition to a low-carbon economy became law on November 26, 2008.  This legislation requires a 80% cut in the UK's [[carbon emissions]] by 2050 (compared to 1990 levels), with an intermediate target of between 26% and 32% by 2020.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.defra.gov.uk/news/2007/070313a.htm|title=New Bill and strategy lay foundations for tackling climate change|publisher=[[Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs]]|date=2007-03-13|accessdate=2007-03-13 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070927000610/http://www.defra.gov.uk/news/2007/070313a.htm |archivedate = September 27, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Thus, the UK became the first country to set such a long-range and significant carbon reduction target into law.

A meeting at the [[Royal Society]] on 17–18 November 2008 concluded that an integrated approach, making best use of all available technologies, is required to move toward a low-carbon future. It was suggested by participants that it would be possible to move to a low-carbon economy within a few decades, but that 'urgent and sustained action is needed on several fronts'.&lt;ref&gt;[http://royalsociety.org/document.asp?tip=0&amp;id=8174 Towards a low carbon future], [[Royal Society]], 29 June 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2012, the UK [[coalition government]] announced the introduction of mandatory carbon reporting, requiring around 1,100 of the UK’s largest listed companies to report their [[greenhouse gas emissions]] every year. [[Deputy Prime Minister]] [[Nick Clegg]] confirmed that emission reporting rules would come into effect from April 2013 in his piece for The Guardian.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2012/jun/19/rio-earth-summit-development-deadlines|title=Rio's reprise must set hard deadlines for development|publisher=[[The Guardian]]|date=2012-06-19|accessdate=2012-07-30 |archiveurl = http://liveweb.archive.org/http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2012/jun/19/rio-earth-summit-development-deadlines |archivedate = July 30, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===India===
[http://indiaenvironmentportal.org.in/content/low-carbon-strategies-inclusive-growth-interim-report Low carbon strategies for inclusive growth - An interim report (India), May 2011]

===Cities===
Companies are planning large scale developments without using fossil fuels. Development plans such as those by [[World Wide Assets LLC]] for entire cities using only [[geothermal energy]] for electricity, [[geothermal desalination]], and employing full recycling systems for water and waste are under development (2006) in Mexico and Australia.

==Education==
The [[University of Edinburgh]] has a [http://www.business-school.ed.ac.uk/msc/carbon-management/ Carbon Management] [[MSc]].  As well as a Carbon Finance MSc.

The [[University of East Anglia]] has a Strategic Carbon Management [[MBA]].

The [[myclimate]] climate education&lt;ref&gt;http://www.myclimate.org/en/climate-education.html , [[Myclimate]] Education&lt;/ref&gt; offers capacity building tools like exhibitions, games, schoolbooks and courses for young people, adults and businesses.

==See also==
{{multicol}}
*[[Alternative propulsion]]
*[[Avoiding dangerous climate change]]
*[[Carbon negative fuel]]
*[[Carbon neutrality]]
*[[Carbon Process Management]]
*[[Coal phase out]]
*[[Comparisons of life-cycle greenhouse gas emissions]]
*[[Electric vehicle]]
*[[Emission standard]]
*[[Emissions trading]]
*[[Energy policy]]
*[[Environmental economics]]
{{multicol-break}}
{{Portal|Global warming|Economics|Renewable energy|Energy|Sustainable development}}
*[[Low-carbon building]]
*[[Low Carbon Communities]]
*[[Low carbon diet]]
*[[Low-carbon emission]]
*[[Low-carbon fuel standard]]
*[[One Watt Initiative]]
*[[Petroleum phase out]]
*[[Sustainable development]]
*[[World energy resources and consumption]]
{{multicol-end}}
{{Renewable energy by country}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://marcchow.com/using-social-media-for-low-carbon-economy-7.html Using Social Media for Low Carbon Economy]
* [http://indiaenvironmentportal.org.in/category/thesaurus/climate-change/climate-economics/low-carbon-economy Resources on Low Carbon Economy]
* [http://energy.senate.gov/public/index.cfm?FuseAction=IssueItems.View&amp;IssueItem_ID=55 Senate.gov: The “Low Carbon Economy Act” of 2007] and [http://www.washingtonwatch.com/bills/show/110_SN_1766.html Status]
* [[British Petroleum]]: [http://www.bp.com/genericarticle.do?categoryId=98&amp;contentId=2004180 Gas and Power in a Low Carbon Economy]
* [[Department of Trade and Industry (United Kingdom)|DTI]] [[United Kingdom|UK]]: [http://www.dti.gov.uk/files/file10719.pdf Creating a low carbon economy]
* [http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/16560106/ Europe eyes 'low-carbon economy'], [[MSNBC.com]]
* [http://www.energyislife.org/?p=35&amp;lang_view=en Hydrogen Economy]
* [http://www.internationalbusinessreport.com/main/report.php?page=137&amp;lang=en&amp;id=122357&amp;country_id=0 Grant Thornton International Business Report Energy &amp; Environment survey]
* [http://www.enn.com/pollution/article/37502 New &quot;carbon revolution&quot; urged to slow warming]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Low-Carbon Economy}}
[[Category:Low-carbon economy| ]]
[[Category:Economics and climate change]]
[[Category:Energy economics]]
[[Category:Sustainable technologies]]
[[Category:Alternative energy economy]]
[[Category:Renewable-energy economy]]

[[es:Economía de bajo carbono]]
[[ja:低炭素社会]]
[[zh-yue:低碳經濟]]
[[zh:低碳經濟]]</text>
      <sha1>6yzkxppqr2qdnnwaokblqnkwvvjafop</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
