<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Market</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3736784</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522216405</id>
      <parentid>522216391</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T18:48:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contributions/Payton.schneider|Payton.schneider]] to version by GrindtXX. False positive? [[User:ClueBot NG/FalsePositives|Report it]]. Thanks, [[User:ClueBot NG|ClueBot NG]]. (1326049) (Bot)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26391">{{redirect|market forces|the novel by Richard Morgan|Market Forces|other meanings of market|market (disambiguation)}}
[[Image:MercadodeSanJuandeDios.jpg|thumb|right|200px|[[San Juan de Dios Market]] in [[Guadalajara]]]]
{{Economics sidebar}}

A '''market''' is one of many varieties of [[system]]s, [[institution]]s, [[Procedure (term)|procedure]]s, [[social relation]]s and [[infrastructure]]s whereby parties engage in exchange. While parties may exchange goods and services by [[barter]], most markets rely on sellers offering their goods or services (including labor) in exchange for [[money]] from buyers. It can be said that a market is the process by which the prices of goods and services are established.

For a market to be competitive, there must be more than a single buyer or seller. It has been suggested that two people may trade, but it takes at least three persons to have a market, so that there is competition on at least one of its two sides.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Sullivan
  | first = arthur
  | authorlink = Arthur O' Sullivan
  | coauthors = Steven M. Sheffrin
  | title = Economics: Principles in action
  | publisher = Pearson Prentice Hall
  | date = 2003
  | location = Upper Saddle River, New Jersey 07458
  | pages = 28
  | url = http://www.pearsonschool.com/index.cfm?locator=PSZ3R9&amp;PMDbSiteId=2781&amp;PMDbSolutionId=6724&amp;PMDbCategoryId=&amp;PMDbProgramId=12881&amp;level=4
  | doi = 
  | id = 
  | isbn = 0-13-063085-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
However, competitive markets rely on much larger numbers of both buyers and sellers. A market with single seller and multiple buyers is a [[monopoly]]. A market with a single buyer and multiple sellers is a [[monopsony]]. These are the extremes of [[imperfect competition]].

Markets vary in form, scale (volume and geographic reach), location, and types of participants, as well as the types of goods and services traded. Examples include:
* Physical retail markets, such as local [[farmers' market]]s (which are usually held in town squares or parking lots on an ongoing or occasional basis), [[shopping center]]s and [[shopping mall]]s
* (Non-physical) internet markets (see [[electronic commerce]])
* Ad hoc [[auction]] markets 
* Markets for [[intermediate good]]s used in production of other goods and services
* Labor markets
* International [[Foreign exchange market|currency]] and [[commodity market]]s
* [[Stock market]]s, for the exchange of shares in [[corporation]]s
* Artificial markets created by regulation to exchange rights for derivatives that have been designed to ameliorate externalities, such as pollution permits (see [[carbon trading]])
* Illegal markets such as the market for [[Illegal drug trade|illicit drugs]], [[arms trafficking|arms]] or [[Copyright infringement|pirated products]]

In [[mainstream economics]], the concept of a '''market''' is any structure that allows buyers and sellers to exchange any type of goods, services and [[information economy|information]]. The exchange of goods or services for [[money]] is a [[Financial transaction|transaction]]. Market participants consist of all the buyers and sellers of a [[Good (economics)|good]] who influence its [[price]]. This influence is a major study of [[economic]]s and has given rise to several theories and [[economic models|models]] concerning the basic market forces of [[supply and demand]]. There are two roles in markets, [[buyer]]s and [[seller]]s. &lt;!--The definition implies that at least three actors are needed for a market to exist; at least one actor, on the one side of the market, who is aware of at least two actors on the other side whose offers can be evaluated in relation to each other.--&gt; The market facilitates [[trade]] and enables the distribution and [[allocation of resources]] in a society. Markets allow any tradable item to be evaluated and [[price]]d. A market emerges more or less spontaneously or is constructed deliberately by human interaction in order to enable the exchange of rights (cf. [[ownership]]) of services and goods. 

Historically, markets originated in physical [[marketplace]]s which would often develop into — or from — small communities, towns and cities.{{Citation needed|date=July 2008}}

[[File:EmpressMarket1995.jpg|thumbnail|right|[[Empress Market]] in [[Karachi]], circa 1995]]
== Types of markets ==
Although many markets exist in the traditional sense &amp;mdash; such as a [[marketplace]] &amp;mdash; there are various other types of markets and various organizational structures to assist their functions. The nature of business transactions could define markets.
[[File:Microcosm of London Plate 033 - Corn Exchange.jpg|right|right|thumb|200px|Corn Exchange in London circa 1809]]
=== Financial markets ===

Financial markets facilitate the exchange of [[liquid asset]]s. Most investors prefer investing in two markets, the [[stock market]]s and the [[bond market]]s. [[NYSE]], [[American Stock Exchange|AMEX]], and the [[NASDAQ]] are the most common stock markets in the US. [[Futures market]]s, where contracts are exchanged regarding the future delivery of goods are often an outgrowth of general [[commodity market]]s.

[[Currency market]]s are used to trade one currency for another, and are often used for speculation on currency exchange rates.

The [[money market]] is the name for the global market for lending and borrowing.

=== Prediction markets ===
[[Prediction market]]s are a type of speculative market in which the goods exchanged are futures on the occurrence of certain events. They apply the market dynamics to facilitate information aggregation.

== Organization of markets ==
A market can be organized as an [[auction]], as a [[private electronic market]], as a commodity wholesale market, as a shopping center, as a complex institution such as a [[stock market]], and as an informal discussion between two individuals.

Markets of varying types can spontaneously arise whenever a party has interest in a good or service that some other party can provide. Hence there can be a market for cigarettes in correctional facilities, another for chewing gum in a playground, and yet another for contracts for the future delivery of a commodity. There can be [[black market]]s, where a good is exchanged illegally and virtual markets, such as [[eBay]], in which buyers and sellers do not physically interact during negotiation. There can also be markets for goods under a command economy despite pressure to repress them.

== Mechanisms of markets ==
In economics, a market that runs under [[laissez-faire]] policies is a [[free market]].  It is &quot;free&quot; in the sense that the government makes no attempt to intervene through [[tax]]es, [[subsidy|subsidies]], [[minimum wage]]s, [[price ceiling]]s, etc. Market prices may be distorted by a seller or sellers with [[monopoly]] power, or a buyer with [[monopsony]] power. Such price distortions can have an adverse effect on market participant's welfare and reduce the efficiency of market outcomes.  Also, the relative level of organization and negotiating power of buyers and sellers markedly affects the functioning of the market. Markets where price negotiations meet equilibrium though still do not arrive at desired outcomes for both sides are said to experience [[market failure]].

Markets are a [[system]], and systems have [[structure]]. The structure of a well-functioning market is defined by the theory of [[perfect competition]]. Well-functioning markets of the real world are never perfect, but basic structural characteristics can be approximated for real world markets, for example:
*many small buyers and sellers
*buyers and sellers have equal access to information
*products are comparable

There exists a popular thought that free markets would have a structure of a [[perfect competition]]. The logic behind the thought is that market failures are thought to be caused by other [[Exogeny|exogenic]] systems, and after removing those exogenic systems (&quot;freeing&quot; the markets) the free markets could run without market failures. 

As an argument against such a logic there is a view that suggests that the source of market failures is inside the market system, so the removal of other interfering systems would not result in markets with a structure of perfect competition: capitalists don't want to enhance the structure of markets, just like a [[coach (sport)|coach]] of a football team would influence the [[referee]]s or would break the [[Regulation of sport|rules]] if he could while he is pursuing his target of winning the game. The capitalists are not enhancing the balance of their team versus the team of [[consumer]]-[[Workforce|workers]], so the market system needs a  &quot;referee&quot; from outside that balances the game. The role of a &quot;referee&quot; of the market system is usually given to a [[democracy|democratic]] government.

[[File:Cokelahore.jpg|thumbnail|left|Liberty Market in [[Lahore]], [[Pakistan]].]]
== Study of markets ==
[[File:Vaclav Maly - Cabbage Market 060.jpg|thumb|200px|Cabbage market by Vaclav Maly]]
[[File:Preziosi - Piaţă la Râmnicu Vâlcea.jpg|thumb|200px|A market in [[Râmnicu Vâlcea]] by Amedeo Preziosi]]
[[File:Afghan market teeming with vendors and shoppers 2-4-09.jpg|thumb|200px|An [[Afghanistan|Afghan]] market teeming with vendors and shoppers]]
[[File:Ul_mercò_dal_lunedi.JPG|thumb|200px|Market in [[Portovenere]], [[Italy]]]]
[[File:Wetherby Market (13th May 2010) 002.jpg|thumb|right|200px|[[Wetherby]] town’s market]]
[[File:MercadodeGomez.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Gómez Palacio]] city's municipal market]]

The study of actual existing markets made up of persons interacting in a place in diverse ways is widely seen{{by whom?|date=October 2012}} as an antidote to abstract and all-encompassing concepts of “the market” and has historical precedent in the works of [[Fernand Braudel]] and [[Karl Polanyi]]. The latter term is now generally used in two ways:

# &quot;the market&quot; denoting the abstract mechanisms whereby supply and demand confront each other and deals are made. In its place, reference to markets reflects ordinary experience and the places, processes and institutions in which exchanges occurs.&lt;ref&gt;Callon, M. (1998) &quot;Introduction: The Embeddedness of Economic Markets in Economics.&quot; In The Laws of the Markets, edited by Michel Callon. Basic Blackwell/The Sociological Review pp 1-57 1998, p.2).&lt;/ref&gt;
# &quot;the market&quot; signifying an integrated, all-encompassing and cohesive capitalist world economy. See Aspers (2011) &lt;ref&gt; (Aspers, Patrik (2011) &quot;Markets&quot; Cambridge Polity Press &lt;/ref&gt; for an overview of the research on markets. 

A widespread trend in [[economic history]] and [[sociology]] is skeptical of the idea that it is possible to develop a theory to capture an essence or unifying thread to markets.&lt;ref&gt;
Swedberg, Richard (1994) “Markets as Social Structures” The Handbook of Economic Sociology. Ed. Neil Smelser and Richard Swedberg. Princeton University Press.  255-2821994, p. 258) &lt;/ref&gt;
For economic geographers, reference to regional, local, or commodity specific markets can serve to undermine assumptions of global integration, and highlight geographic variations in the structures, institutions, histories, path dependencies, forms of interaction and modes of self-understanding of agents in different spheres of market exchange.&lt;ref&gt;
Peck, J. (2005) “Economic Geographies in Space” Economic Geography 81(2) 129-175.&lt;/ref&gt;
Reference to actual markets can show capitalism not as a totalizing force or completely encompassing mode of economic activity, but rather as &quot;a set of economic practices scattered over a landscape, rather than a systemic concentration of power&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;
(Gibson-Graham, J.K. (2006) Postcapitalist Politics.  University of Minnesota Press,. p.2).&lt;/ref&gt;

[[C. B. Macpherson]] identifies an underlying model of the market underlying Anglo-American liberal-democratic political economy and philosophy in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries: Persons are cast as self-interested individuals, who enter into contractual relations with other such individuals, concerning the exchange of goods or personal capacities cast as commodities, with the motive of maximizing pecuniary interest. The state and its governance systems are cast as outside of this framework.&lt;ref&gt; (MacPherson, C.B. (1962) The Political Theory of Possessive Individualism: From Hobbes to Locke. Oxford Clarendon Press. p.3 &lt;/ref&gt; This model came to dominant economic thinking in the later nineteenth century, as economists such as [[David Ricardo|Ricardo]], [[James Mill|Mill]], [[William Stanley Jevons|Jevons]], [[Walras]] and later neo-classical economics shifted from reference to geographically located marketplaces to an abstract &quot;market&quot;.&lt;ref&gt; (Swedberg, 1994, p. 258 &lt;/ref&gt; This tradition is continued in contemporary [[neoliberalism]], where the market is held up as optimal for wealth creation and human freedom, and the states’ role imagined as minimal, reduced to that of upholding and keeping stable property rights, contract, and money supply. This allowed for boilerplate economic and institutional restructuring under [[structural adjustment]] and post-Communist reconstruction.&lt;ref&gt; Harvey, David (2005) A Short History of Neoliberalism Oxford University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;

Similar formalism occurs in a wide variety of social democratic and Marxist discourses that situate political action as antagonistic to the market. In particular, commodification theorists such as [[Georg Lukács]] insist that market relations necessarily lead to undue exploitation of labour and so need to be opposed in toto.&lt;ref&gt; Lukács, Georg. (1971) History and Class Consciousness. Trans. Rodney Livingstone. Merlin Press. London.p. 87&lt;/ref&gt; [[Pierre Bourdieu]] has suggested the market model is becoming self-realizing, in virtue of its wide acceptance in national and international institutions through the 1990s.&lt;ref&gt;Bourdieu, Pierre (1999) Acts of Resistance: Against the Tyranny of the Market. The New Press.p. 95 &lt;/ref&gt; The formalist conception faces a number of insuperable difficulties, concerning the putatively global scope of the market to cover the entire Earth, in terms of penetration of particular economies, and in terms of whether particular claims about the subjects (individuals with pecuniary interest), objects (commodities), and modes of exchange (transactions) apply to any actually existing markets.

A central theme of empirical analyses is the variation and proliferation of types of markets since the rise of capitalism and global scale economies. The [[Regulation school]] stresses the ways in which developed capitalist countries have implemented varying degrees and types of environmental, economic, and social regulation, taxation and public spending, fiscal policy and government provisioning of goods, all of which have transformed markets in uneven and geographical varied ways and created a variety of mixed economies. Drawing on concepts of institutional variance and path dependency, varieties of capitalism theorists (such as Hall and Soskice) identify two dominant modes of economic ordering in the developed capitalist countries, &quot;coordinated market economies&quot; such as Germany and Japan, and an Anglo-American &quot;liberal market economies&quot;. However, such approaches imply that the Anglo-American liberal market economies, in fact, operate in a matter close to the abstract notion of &quot;the market&quot;. While Anglo-American countries have seen increasing introduction of neo-liberal forms of economic ordering, this has not led to simple convergence, but rather a variety of hybrid institutional orderings.&lt;ref&gt;Peck, supra, p. 154) &lt;/ref&gt; Rather, a variety of new markets have emerged, such as for carbon trading or rights to pollute. In some cases, such as emerging markets for water, different forms of privatization of different aspects of previously state run infrastructure have created hybrid private-public formations and graded degrees of commodification, commercialization, and privatization.&lt;ref&gt; Bakker, Karen (2005) “Neoliberalizing Nature?: Market Environmentalism in water supply in England and Wales” Annals of the Association of American Geographers 95 (3), 542-565 &lt;/ref&gt;

Problematic for market formalism is the relationship between formal capitalist economic processes and a variety of alternative forms, ranging from semi-feudal and peasant economies widely operative in many developing economies, to informal markets, barter systems, [[worker cooperative]]s, or illegal trades that occur in most developed countries. Practices of incorporation of non-Western peoples into global markets in the nineteenth and twentieth century did not merely result in the quashing of former social economic institutions.  Rather, various modes of articulation arose between transformed and hybridized local traditions and social practices and the emergence world economy. So called capitalist markets, in fact, include and depend on a wide range of geographically situated economic practices that do not follow the market model. Economies are thus hybrids of market and non-market elements.&lt;ref&gt; (Mitchell, Timothy (2002) Rule of Experts. University of California Pressp. 270; Gibson-Graham 2006, supra pp. 53-78) &lt;/ref&gt;

Helpful here is [[J. K. Gibson-Graham]]’s complex topology of the diversity of contemporary market economies describing different types of transactions, labour, and economic agents. Transactions can occur in underground markets (such as for marijuana) or be artificially protected (such as for patents). They can cover the sale of public goods under privatization schemes to co-operative exchanges and occur under varying degrees of monopoly power and state regulation. Likewise, there are a wide variety of economic agents, which engage in different types of transactions on different terms: One cannot assume the practices of a religious kindergarten, multinational corporation, state enterprise, or community-based cooperative can be subsumed under the same logic of calculability (pp.&amp;nbsp;53–78). This emphasis on proliferation can also be contrasted with continuing scholarly attempts to show underlying cohesive and structural similarities to different markets.&lt;ref name=&quot;Swedberg, 1994, p. 267&quot;&gt;Swedberg, 1994, p. 267 &lt;/ref&gt;

A prominent entry-point for challenging the market model's applicability concerns exchange transactions and the ''[[homo economicus]]'' assumption of self-interest maximization. {{As of | 2012}} a number of streams of [[economic sociology|economic sociological]] analysis of markets focus on the role of the social in transactions, and on the ways transactions involve social networks and relations of trust, cooperation and other bonds.&lt;ref name=&quot;Swedberg, 1994, p. 267&quot;/&gt; Economic geographers in turn draw attention to the ways in exchange transactions occur against the backdrop of institutional, social and geographic processes, including class relations, uneven development, and historically contingent path-dependencies.&lt;ref&gt;
Martin, Ron (2000) &quot;Institutional Approaches in Economic Geography&quot;, ''Handbook of Economic Geography''. Ed. Eric Sheppard and Trevor J. Barnes. Blackwell Publishers.Peck, 2005 &lt;/ref&gt;
[[Michel Callon]]'s concept of framing provides a useful schema: each economic act or transaction occurs against, incorporates and also re-performs a geographically and cultural specific complex of social histories, institutional arrangements, rules and connections. These network relations are simultaneously bracketed, so that persons and transactions may be disentangled from thick social bonds. The character of calculability is imposed upon agents as they come to work in markets and are &quot;formatted&quot; as calculative agencies. Market exchanges contain a history of struggle and contestation that produced actors predisposed to exchange under c{{huh?|date=October 2012}}

An emerging theme worthy of further study is the interrelationship, interpenetrability and variations of concepts of persons, commodities, and modes of exchange under particular market formations. This is most pronounced in recent movement towards post-structuralist theorizing that draws on [[Michel Foucault|Foucault]] and [[Actor-network theory|Actor Network Theory]] and stress relational aspects of personhood, and dependence and integration into networks and practical systems. Commodity network approaches further both deconstruct and show alternatives to the market models concept of commodities. Here, both researchers and market actors are understood as reframing commodities in terms of processes and social and ecological relationships. Rather than a mere objectification of things traded, the complex network relationships of exchange in different markets calls on agents to alternatively deconstruct or “get with” the fetish of commodities.&lt;ref&gt;Hughes, Alex (2005) “Geographies of Exchange and Circulation: alternative trading spaces” Progress in Human Geography &lt;/ref&gt; Gibson-Graham thus read a variety of alternative markets, for fair trade and organic foods, or those using [[Local Exchange Trading Systems]] as not only contributing to proliferation, but also forging new modes of ethical exchange and economic subjectivities.

==Size parameters==
''Market size'' can be given in terms of the number of buyers and sellers in a particular market&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.investorwords.com/6576/market_size.html investorwords.com &gt; market size] Retrieved on April 17, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; or in terms of the total exchange of money in the market, generally annually (per year). When given in terms of money, market size is often termed ''market value'', but in a sense distinct from [[market value]] of individual products. For one and the same goods, there may be different (and generally increasing) market values at the production level, the wholesale level and the retail level. For example, the value of the global illicit drug market for the year 2003 was estimated by the [[United Nations]] to be US$13 billion at the production level, $94 billion at the wholesale level (taking seizures into account), and US$322 billion at the retail level (based on retail prices and taking seizures and other losses into account).&lt;ref&gt;United Nations, “2005 World Drug Report,” Office on Drugs and Crime, June 2005, pg. 16. [http://www.unodc.org/pdf/WDR_2005/volume_1_web.pdf] &lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* [[Agricultural marketing]]
* [[Farmers' market]]
* [[Financial market]]
* [[Grocery store]]
* [[Knowledge market]]
* [[Market economy]]
* [[Market Information Systems]]
* [[Market microstructure]]
* [[Marketplace]]
* [[Market square]]
* [[Market town]]
* [[Media market]]
* [[Mercado Central]]
* [[Stock market]]
* [[Street market]]
* [[Supermarket]]
* [[Wholesale marketing]]
* [[Shopper marketing]]
{{div col end}}

== Notes ==
{{reflist|2}}

== References ==
* Aspers, Patrik (2011) Markets Cambridge: Polity Press.
* Bakker, Karen (2005) “Neoliberalizing Nature?: Market Environmentalism in water supply in England and Wales” Annals of the Association of American Geographers 95 (3), 542-565.
* Bourdieu, Pierre (1999) Acts of Resistance: Against the Tyranny of the Market. The New Press.
* Callon, Michel (1998) &quot;Introduction: The Embeddedness of Economic Markets in Economics.&quot; In The Laws of the Markets, edited by Michel Callon. Basic Blackwell/The Sociological Review pp 1–57
* Gibson-Graham, J.K. (2006) Postcapitalist Politics.  University of Minnesota Press,.
* Harvey, David (2005) A Short History of Neoliberalism Oxford University Press.
* Hughes, Alex (2005) “Geographies of Exchange and Circulation: alternative trading spaces” Progress in Human Geography 
* Lukács, Georg. (1971) History and Class Consciousness. Trans. Rodney Livingstone. Merlin Press. London.
* MacPherson, C.B. (1962) The Political Theory of Possessive Individualism: From Hobbes to Locke. Oxford Clarendon Press.
* Marshall, A. (1961). ''Principles of Economics.'' C. W. Guillebaud, Ed. 2 Vol. London: Macmillan.
* Martin, Ron (2000) “Institutional Approaches in Economic Geography” Handbook of Economic Geography. Ed. Eric Sheppard and Trevor J. Barnes. Blackwell Publishers.
* Mitchell, Timothy (2002) Rule of Experts University of California Press.; 
* Peck, J. (2005) “Economic Geographies in Space” Economic Geography 81(2) 129-175
* Swedberg, Richard (1994) “Markets as Social Structures” The Handbook of Economic Sociology. Ed. Neil Smelser and Richard Swedberg. Princeton University Press.  255-282

== Sources ==
* ''Microeconomics'' by Robert S. Pindyck, Daniel L. Rubinfeld

== External links ==
{{wiktionary}}{{commons}}
* [http://www.qualitionary.eu/index.php?title=Market Qualitionary - Legal Definitions - Market]
*[http://www.swingtradingforecast.com/dow-jones-forecast/ Stock Market Forecast]

[[Category:Economics terminology]]
[[Category:Anthropology]]
[[Category:Retail markets| ]]
[[Category:Financial markets|*Main]]
[[Category:Markets (customer bases)|*Mai]]

.

[[af:Mark (ekonomie)]]
[[ar:سوق]]
[[arc:ܫܘܩܐ (ܬܐܓܪܘܬܐ)]]
[[ay:Rikuwa]]
[[bn:বাজার]]
[[zh-min-nan:Chhī-tiûⁿ]]
[[be:Рынак]]
[[be-x-old:Рынак]]
[[bg:Пазар]]
[[bs:Tržište]]
[[ca:Mercat]]
[[cv:Пасар]]
[[cs:Trh (ekonomie)]]
[[sn:Musika (Kunotengeswa)]]
[[cy:Marchnad]]
[[da:Marked]]
[[de:Markt]]
[[et:Turg]]
[[es:Mercado]]
[[eo:Merkato]]
[[eu:Merkatu]]
[[fa:بازار (اقتصاد)]]
[[fr:Marché]]
[[ga:Margadh]]
[[gl:Mercado]]
[[ko:시장]]
[[hi:बाज़ार]]
[[hr:Tržište]]
[[io:Merkato]]
[[ilo:Tiendáan]]
[[id:Pasar]]
[[it:Mercato]]
[[he:שוק (כלכלה)]]
[[ka:ბაზარი]]
[[kk:Нарық]]
[[kg:Zandu]]
[[ht:Mache]]
[[la:Mercatus (oeconomia)]]
[[lv:Tirgus]]
[[lb:Maart]]
[[lt:Rinka]]
[[hu:Piac]]
[[mk:Пазар]]
[[ml:ചന്ത]]
[[ms:Pasaran]]
[[nl:Markt (economie)]]
[[ne:बजार]]
[[new:बजार]]
[[ja:市場]]
[[no:Marked]]
[[nn:Marknad]]
[[nrm:Marchi]]
[[uz:Bozor]]
[[tpi:Maket]]
[[pl:Rynek (ekonomia)]]
[[pt:Mercado]]
[[ro:Piață]]
[[qu:Qhatu]]
[[ru:Рынок]]
[[sah:Баhаар]]
[[simple:Market]]
[[sk:Trh]]
[[sl:Trg (ekonomija)]]
[[sr:Тржиште]]
[[su:Pasar]]
[[fi:Markkinat (taloustiede)]]
[[sv:Marknad (ekonomi)]]
[[tl:Pamilihan]]
[[th:ตลาด]]
[[tr:Pazar (ekonomi)]]
[[uk:Ринок]]
[[ur:منڈی]]
[[vi:Chợ]]
[[zh-classical:市場]]
[[war:Merkado]]
[[yi:מארק]]
[[zh-yue:市場]]
[[zh:市场]]</text>
      <sha1>jd3s9bppzarbalern04yud88lgv9q4i</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
