<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Microeconomics</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18819</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521832822</id>
      <parentid>520160594</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-07T15:04:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>FrescoBot</username>
        <id>9021902</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Bot: [[User:FrescoBot/Links|link syntax/spacing]] and minor changes</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23440">[[Image:Supply-demand-right-shift-demand.svg|thumb|270px|The [[supply and demand]] model describes how prices vary as a result of a balance between product availability at each price (supply) and the desires of those with purchasing power at each price (demand). The graph depicts a right-shift in demand from D&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; to D&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; along with the consequent increase in price and quantity required to reach a new market-clearing equilibrium point on the supply curve (S).]]
{{Economics sidebar}}
'''Microeconomics''' (from Greek prefix micro- &quot;μικρό&quot; meaning &quot;small&quot; + &quot;economics&quot;- &quot;οικονομια&quot;) is a branch of [[economics]] that studies the behavior of individual households and firms in making decisions on the allocation of limited resources.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ca.uky.edu/agc/pubs/aec/aec75/aec75.pdf |title=Macroeconomic and International Policy Terms |accessdate=2007-05-04 |last=Marchant |first=Mary A. |coauthors= Snell, William M. |publisher=[[University of Kentucky]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; Typically, it applies to markets where goods or services are bought and sold. Microeconomics examines how these decisions and behaviors affect the [[supply and demand]] for goods and services, which determines prices, and how prices, in turn, determine the quantity supplied and quantity demanded of goods and services.&lt;ref name=&quot;glossary&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Economics Glossary|publisher=Monroe County Women's Disability Network|url=http://www.mcwdn.org/ECONOMICS/EcoGlossary.html|accessdate=2008-02-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Social Studies Standards Glossary|url=http://nmlites.org/standards/socialstudies/glossary.html |accessdate=2008-02-22|publisher=New Mexico Public Education Department |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070808200604/http://nmlites.org/standards/socialstudies/glossary.html |archivedate = 2007-08-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This is in contrast to [[macroeconomics]], which involves the &quot;sum total of economic activity, dealing with the issues of [[Economic growth|growth]], [[inflation]], and [[unemployment]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;glossary&quot; /&gt; Microeconomics also deals with the effects of national economic policies (such as changing [[taxation]] levels) on the aforementioned aspects of the economy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.econ100.com/eu5e/open/glossary.html|title=Glossary|accessdate=2008-02-22|publisher=ECON100}}&lt;/ref&gt; Particularly in the wake of the [[Lucas critique]], much of modern macroeconomic theory has been built upon '[[microfoundations]]'—i.e. based upon basic assumptions about micro-level behavior.

One of the goals of microeconomics is to analyze [[market]] mechanisms that establish [[relative price]]s amongst goods and services and allocation of limited resources amongst many alternative uses. Microeconomics analyzes [[market failure]], where markets fail to produce efficient results, and describes the theoretical conditions needed for [[perfect competition]]. Significant fields of study in microeconomics include [[general equilibrium]], markets under [[asymmetric information]], choice under [[uncertainty]] and economic applications of [[game theory]]. Also considered is the [[elasticity (economics)|elasticity]] of products within the market system.

==Assumptions and definitions==
The theory of [[supply and demand]] usually assumes that markets are [[perfect competition|perfectly competitive]]. This implies that there are many buyers and sellers in the market and none of them have the capacity to significantly influence prices of goods and services. In many real-life transactions, the assumption fails because some individual buyers or sellers have the ability to influence prices. Quite often, a sophisticated analysis is required to understand the demand-supply equation of a good model. However, the theory works well in situations meeting these assumptions.

[[Mainstream economics]] does not assume ''[[A priori and a posteriori (philosophy)|a priori]]'' that markets are preferable to other forms of social organization. In fact, much analysis is devoted to cases where so-called [[market failure]]s lead to [[resource allocation]] that is suboptimal by some standard (defense spending is the classic example, profitable to all for use but not directly profitable for anyone to finance). In such cases, [[economist]]s may attempt to find policies that will avoid waste, either directly by government control, indirectly by regulation that induces market participants to act in a manner consistent with optimal welfare, or by creating &quot;[[missing market]]s&quot; to enable efficient trading where none had previously existed.

This is studied in the field of [[collective action]] and [[public choice theory]]. &quot;Optimal welfare&quot; usually takes on a [[Pareto Efficiency|Paretian]] norm, which in its mathematical application of [[Kaldor–Hicks efficiency|Kaldor–Hicks method]].  This can diverge from the [[Utilitarianism|Utilitarian]] goal of maximising [[utility (economics)|utility]] because it does not consider the distribution of goods between people. Market failure in positive economics (microeconomics) is limited in implications without mixing the belief of the economist and their theory.

The demand for various commodities by individuals is generally thought of as the outcome of a utility-maximizing process, with each individual trying to maximise their own utility. The interpretation of this relationship between price and quantity demanded of a given good assumes that, given all the other goods and constraints, the set of choices which emerges is that one which makes the consumer happiest.

==Modes of operation==
It is assumed that all firms are following rational decision-making, and will produce at the profit-maximizing output. Given this assumption, there are four categories in which a firm's profit may be considered to be.

*A firm is said to be making an [[economic profit]] when its average total cost is less than the price of each additional product at the profit-maximizing output. The economic profit is equal to the quantity output multiplied by the difference between the average total cost and the price.
*A firm is said to be making a [[normal profit]] when its economic profit equals zero. This occurs where average total cost equals price at the profit-maximizing output.
*If the price is between average total cost and average variable cost at the profit-maximizing output, then the firm is said to be in a loss-minimizing condition. The firm should still continue to produce, however, since its loss would be larger if it were to stop producing. By continuing [[production (economics)|production]], the firm can offset its variable cost and at least part of its fixed cost, but by stopping completely it would lose the entirety of its [[fixed cost]].
*If the price is below average variable cost at the profit-maximizing output, the firm should go into [[Shutdown (economics)|shutdown]]. Losses are minimized by not producing at all, since any production would not generate returns significant enough to offset any fixed cost and part of the [[variable cost]]. By not producing, the firm loses only its fixed cost. By losing this fixed cost the company faces a challenge. It must either exit the market or remain in the market and risk a complete loss.

==Opportunity cost==
{{Main|Opportunity cost}}
Opportunity cost of an activity (or goods) is equal to the best next alternative foregone.
Although ''opportunity cost'' can be hard to quantify, the effect of opportunity cost is universal and very real on the individual level. In fact, this principle applies to all decisions, not just economic ones.
Since the work of the [[Austrian School|Austrian]] economist [[Friedrich von Wieser]], opportunity cost has been seen as the foundation of the [[marginal theory of value]]{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}.

Opportunity cost is one way to measure the cost of something. Rather than merely identifying and adding the costs of a project, one may also identify the next best alternative way to spend the same amount of money. The forgone profit of this ''next best alternative'' is the opportunity cost of the original choice. A common example is a farmer that chooses to farm their land rather than rent it to neighbors, wherein the opportunity cost is the forgone profit from renting. In this case, the farmer may expect to generate more profit alone. Similarly, the opportunity cost of attending [[university]] is the lost wages a student could have earned in the workforce, rather than the cost of tuition, books, and other requisite items (whose sum makes up the total cost of attendance).

Note that opportunity cost is not the ''sum'' of the available alternatives, but rather the benefit of the single, best alternative.  Possible opportunity costs of a city's decision to build a hospital on its vacant land are the loss of the land for a sporting center, ''or'' the inability to use the land for a parking lot, ''or'' the money that could have been made from selling the land, ''or'' the loss of any of the various other possible uses — but not all of these in aggregate. The true opportunity cost would be the forgone profit of the most lucrative of those listed.

One question that arises here is how to determine a money value for each alternative to facilitate comparison and assess opportunity cost, which may be more or less difficult depending on the things we are trying to compare. For example, many decisions involve environmental impacts whose monetary value is difficult to assess because of scientific uncertainty. Valuing a human life or the economic impact of an Arctic oil spill involves making subjective choices with ethical implications.

It is imperative to understand that no decision on allocating time is free.  No matter what one chooses to do, they are always giving something up in return. An example of opportunity cost is deciding between going to a concert and doing homework.  If one decides to go the concert, then they are giving up valuable time to study, but if they choose to do homework then the cost is giving up the concert.  Any decision in allocating capital is likewise: there is an opportunity cost of capital, or a hurdle rate, defined as the expected rate one could get by investing in similar projects on the open market.  Opportunity cost is vital in understanding microeconomics and decisions that are made.

==Applied microeconomics==
Applied microeconomics includes a range of specialized areas of study, many of which draw on methods from other fields. [[Industrial organization]] examines topics such as the entry and exit of firms, innovation, and the role of trademarks. [[Labor economics]] examines wages, employment, and labor market dynamics. [[Financial economics]] examines topics such as the structure of optimal portfolios, the rate of return to capital, econometric analysis of security returns, and corporate financial behavior. [[Public economics]] examines the design of government tax and expenditure policies and economic effects of these policies (e.g., social insurance programs). [[Political economy]] examines the role of political institutions in determining policy outcomes. [[Health economics]] examines the organization of health care systems, including the role of the health care workforce and health insurance programs. [[Urban economics]], which examines the challenges faced by cities, such as sprawl, air and water pollution, traffic congestion, and poverty, draws on the fields of urban geography and sociology. [[Law and economics]] applies microeconomic principles to the selection and enforcement of competing legal regimes and their relative efficiencies. [[Economic history]] examines the evolution of the economy and economic institutions, using methods and techniques from the fields of economics, history, geography, sociology, psychology, and political science.
{{clear}}

==Development==
The modern field of microeconomics arose as an effort of [[neoclassical economics]] school of thought to put economic ideas into mathematical mode. An early attempt was made by [[Antoine Augustine Cournot]] Researches on the Mathematical Principles of the Theory of Wealth (1838) in describing a spring water duopoly that now bears his name.  Latter [[William Stanley Jevons]]'s Theory of Political Economy (1871), [[Carl Menger]]'s Principles of Economics (1871), and [[Léon Walras]]'s Elements of Pure Economics (1874–1877) gave way to what was called the [[Marginal Revolution]]. Some common ideas behind those works were models or arguments characterized by rational economic agents maximizing utility under a budget constrain. This arose as a necessity of arguing against the [[labour theory of value]] associated with [[classical economists]] such as Adam Smith, David Ricardo and Karl Marx.

Walras also went as far as developing the concept of [[general equilibrium]] of an economy.

[[Alfred Marshall]]'s textbook, Principles of Economics was published in 1890 and became the dominant textbook in England for a generation. His main point was that [[marginalists]] went too far in emphasizing [[utility]] as an attempt to explain prices over costs of production. To correct that he presented the idea that prices were determined by supply and demand curves. The [[demand curve]] could be derived by aggregating individual consumer demand curves, which were themselves based on the consumer problem of maximizing utility. The [[supply curve]] could be derived by aggregating individual producer supply curves, which depended first on constructing [[cost curves]] and then analyzing how much each producer was willing to sell his goods at a given price level. The cost curves depended on solving a producer problem of minimizing costs under a given [[production function]]. He also introduced the notion of different market periods: mainly [[short run]] and [[long run]]. This set of ideas gave way to what was latter called [[perfect competition]].

A new impetus was given to field when around 1933. [[Joan Robinson]] and [[Edward H. Chamberlin]], published respectively, The Economics of Imperfect Competition (1933) and The Theory of Monopolistic Competition (1933), introducing models of imperfect competition. Although Marshall himself had already considered both the [[monopoly]] case and Cournot had built his [[duopoly]] model, a whole new set of models grew out of this new literature. In particular the [[monopolistic competition]] model results in a non efficient equilibrium. Latter on some market models were built using game theory, particularly regarding [[oligopolies]].

In 1937 The Nature of the Firm was published by [[Ronald Coase]] introducing the notion of [[transaction costs]] (the term itself was coined in the fifties), which explained why firms have an advantage over a group of independent contractors working with each other. The idea was that there were transaction costs in the use of the market: search and information costs, bargaining costs, etc. which give an advantage to a firm which can internalize the production process required to deliver a certain good to the market.  A related result was published by Coase in his “The Problem of Social Cost” (1960) which deals with problem of [[externalities]]: the presence of transaction costs prevents agents from bargaining among themselves to arrive at mutually beneficial agreement. This then becomes relevant in context of [[regulations]].

Around the seventies the study of [[market failures]] came again into focus with the study of [[information asymmetry]]. In particular three authors emerged from this period: [[George Akerlof]], [[Michael Spence]] and [[Joseph Stiglitz]]. Akerlof considered the problem of bad quality cars driving good quality cars out of the market in his classic “The Market for Lemons” (1970) because of the presence of asymmetrical information between buyers and sellers. Spence explained that [[signaling]] was fundamental in the [[labour market]], because since employers cant know beforehand which of the candidates are the most productive, a college degree becomes a signaling device which allows a firm to hire new personnel.

More recently [[Kahneman]] and [[Tversky]] published their paper &quot;Prospect Theory: An Analysis of Decision under Risk&quot; in 1979 criticizing the very idea of the rational economic agent. The main point is that there an asymmetry in the psychology of the economic agent which gives a much higher value to losses that to gains. This article is usually regarded as the beginning of [[behavioral economics]] and has consequences particularly regarding the world of [[finance]].

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book|first=Robin|last=Bade|coauthors=Michael Parkin|title=Foundations of Microeconomics|publisher=Addison Wesley Paperback 1st Edition|year=2001}}
* Bouman, John: [http://www.inflateyourmind.com Principles of Microeconomics - free fully comprehensive Principles of Microeconomics and Macroeconomics texts]. Columbia, Maryland, 2011
*Colander, David. ''Microeconomics.'' McGraw-Hill Paperback, 7th Edition: 2008.
*{{cite book |author=Dunne, Timothy, J. Bradford Jensen, and Mark J. Roberts |title=Producer Dynamics: New Evidence from Micro Data |publisher=University of Chicago Press |year=2009 |pages= |isbn=978-0-226-17256-9}}
*Eaton, B. Curtis; Eaton, Diane F.; and Douglas W. Allen. ''Microeconomics''. Prentice Hall, 5th Edition: 2002.
*Frank, Robert A.; ''Microeconomics and Behavior''. McGraw-Hill/Irwin, 6th Edition: 2006.
*Friedman, Milton. ''Price Theory.'' Aldine Transaction: 1976
* Hagendorf, Klaus: [http://ssrn.com/paper=1489383 Labour Values and the Theory of the Firm. Part I: The Competitive Firm. Paris: EURODOS; 2009.]
* [[Arnold Harberger|Harberger, Arnold C.]], 2008.  [http://www.econlib.org/library/Enc/Microeconomics.html &quot;Microeconomics,&quot;]  ''The Concise Encyclopedia of Economics''.
* Hicks, John R. ''[[Value and Capital]]''.  Clarendon Press. [1939] 1946, 2nd ed.
* [[Jack Hirshleifer|Hirshleifer, Jack]]., Glazer, Amihai, and [[David Hirshleifer|Hirshleifer, David]], ''Price theory and applications: Decisions, markets, and information.'' Cambridge University Press, 7th Edition: 2005.
*Jehle, Geoffrey A.; and [[Philip J. Reny]]. ''Advanced Microeconomic Theory.'' Addison Wesley Paperback, 2nd Edition: 2000.
*Katz, Michael L.; and Harvey S. Rosen. ''Microeconomics''. McGraw-Hill/Irwin, 3rd Edition: 1997.
*Kreps, David M. ''A Course in Microeconomic Theory''. Princeton University Press: 1990
*Landsburg, Steven. ''Price Theory and Applications''. South-Western College Pub, 5th Edition: 2001.
*Mankiw, N. Gregory. ''Principles of Microeconomics''. South-Western Pub, 2nd Edition: 2000.
*[[Andreu Mas-Colell|Mas-Colell, Andreu]]; Whinston, Michael D.; and Jerry R. Green. ''Microeconomic Theory''. Oxford University Press, US: 1995.
*McGuigan, James R.; Moyer, R. Charles; and Frederick H. Harris. ''Managerial Economics: Applications, Strategy and Tactics''. South-Western Educational Publishing, 9th Edition: 2001.
*Nicholson, Walter. ''Microeconomic Theory: Basic Principles and Extensions.'' South-Western College Pub, 8th Edition: 2001.
*Perloff, Jeffrey M. ''Microeconomics''. Pearson - Addison Wesley, 4th Edition: 2007.
*Perloff, Jeffrey M. ''Microeconomics: Theory and Applications with Calculus''. Pearson - Addison Wesley, 1st Edition: 2007
*Pindyck, Robert S.; and Daniel L. Rubinfeld.'' Microeconomics.'' Prentice Hall, 7th Edition: 2008.
*Ruffin, Roy J.; and Paul R. Gregory. ''Principles of Microeconomics''. Addison Wesley, 7th Edition: 2000.
*[[Hal Varian|Varian, Hal R.]] (1987). &quot;microeconomics,&quot; ''[[The New Palgrave: A Dictionary of Economics]]'', v. 3, pp.&amp;nbsp;461–63.
*Varian, Hal R. ''Intermediate Microeconomics: A Modern Approach''. W. W. Norton &amp; Company, 7th Edition: 2005.
*Varian, Hal R. ''Intermediate Microeconomics: A Modern Approach''. W. W. Norton &amp; Company, 8th Edition: 2009.
*Varian, Hal R. ''Microeconomic Analysis''. W. W. Norton &amp; Company, 3rd Edition: 1992.

==External links==
{{Wikibooks|Microeconomics}}
*[http://www.introecon.com/ Open Source Introduction to Microeconomics] ([[Introduction to Economic Analysis|see wiki article]]) by R. Preston McAfee – California Institute of Technology
*[http://www.amosweb.com/cgi-bin/awb_nav.pl?s=gls Amosweb.com homepage] – online economics dictionary
* [http://xlab.berkeley.edu X-Lab: A Collaborative Micro-Economics and Social Sciences Research Laboratory]
* [http://www.standardsoflife.com/Micro+Economics Micro Economics] – the role of microeconomics in supporting the social fabric of macro economies
&lt;!--* [http://www.econphd.net/notes.htm: www.econphd.net] - Lecture notes on economics online //site inactive --&gt;
* [http://www.economicsnetwork.ac.uk/teaching/simulations/principlesofmicroeconomics.htm Simulations in Microeconomics]
*http://media.lanecc.edu/users/martinezp/201/MicroHistory.html - a brief history of microeconomics

{{microeconomics-footer}}{{economics}}

[[Category:Microeconomics|*]]

{{Link GA|id}}

[[ar:اقتصاد جزئي]]
[[arc:ܡܡܘܢܐ ܕܡܝܟܪܐ]]
[[ast:Microeconomía]]
[[az:Mikroiqtisadiyyat]]
[[zh-min-nan:Kò-thé-keng-chè-ha̍k]]
[[be:Мікраэканоміка]]
[[be-x-old:Мікраэканоміка]]
[[bg:Микроикономика]]
[[bo:ཕྲ་མཐོང་དཔལ་འབྱོར།]]
[[bs:Mikroekonomija]]
[[ca:Microeconomia]]
[[ceb:Mikroekonomiya]]
[[cs:Mikroekonomie]]
[[da:Mikroøkonomi]]
[[de:Mikroökonomie]]
[[et:Mikroökonoomika]]
[[el:Μικροοικονομία]]
[[es:Microeconomía]]
[[eo:Mikroekonomiko]]
[[eu:Mikroekonomia]]
[[fa:اقتصاد خرد]]
[[fr:Microéconomie]]
[[gu:સૂક્ષ્મ અર્થશાસ્ત્ર]]
[[ko:미시경제학]]
[[hy:Միկրոէկոնոմիկա]]
[[hi:सूक्ष्म अर्थशास्त्र]]
[[hr:Mikroekonomija]]
[[id:Ekonomi mikro]]
[[os:Микроэкономикæ]]
[[is:Rekstrarhagfræði]]
[[it:Microeconomia]]
[[he:מיקרו-כלכלה]]
[[kn:ಸೂಕ್ಷ್ಮ ಅರ್ಥಶಾಸ್ತ್ರ]]
[[ka:მიკროეკონომიკა]]
[[kk:Микроэкономика]]
[[lo:ເສດຖະສາດຈຸນລະພາກ]]
[[la:Micro-oeconomia]]
[[lv:Mikroekonomika]]
[[lt:Mikroekonomika]]
[[li:Mikro-ikkenemie]]
[[hu:Mikroökonómia]]
[[mk:Микроекономија]]
[[arz:اقتصاد جزئى]]
[[mn:Микро эдийн засаг]]
[[nl:Micro-economie]]
[[new:माइक्रोइकोनोमिक्स]]
[[ja:ミクロ経済学]]
[[no:Mikroøkonomi]]
[[nn:Mikroøkonomi]]
[[ps:کوچنی وټه]]
[[pl:Mikroekonomia]]
[[pt:Microeconomia]]
[[ro:Microeconomie]]
[[ru:Микроэкономика]]
[[sah:Микроэкономика]]
[[sq:Mikroekonomia]]
[[scn:Micruecunumìa]]
[[si:ක්ෂුද්‍ර ආර්ථික විද්‍යාව]]
[[simple:Microeconomics]]
[[sk:Mikroekonómia]]
[[sl:Mikroekonomija]]
[[sr:Микроекономија]]
[[sh:Mikroekonomija]]
[[fi:Mikrotaloustiede]]
[[sv:Mikroekonomi]]
[[tl:Mikroekonomiya]]
[[ta:குறும்பொருளியல்]]
[[te:సూక్ష్మ అర్థ శాస్త్రము]]
[[th:เศรษฐศาสตร์จุลภาค]]
[[tr:Mikroekonomi]]
[[uk:Мікроекономіка]]
[[ur:جزیاتی معاشیات]]
[[vi:Kinh tế học vi mô]]
[[war:Maykroekonomiks]]
[[zh:微观经济学]]</text>
      <sha1>9dp8q7y61fyfx3htd7ttnvsokhv118e</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
