<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Microcredit</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>167854</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522040524</id>
      <parentid>519485984</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-08T18:30:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>87.13.57.222</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Bibliography */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="45059">:''This article is specific to small loans. For financial services to the poor, see [[Microfinance]].  For small payments, see [[Micropayment]].''
{{Refimprove|date=May 2011}}

'''Microcredit''' is the extension of very small [[loan]]s ('''microloans''') to impoverished borrowers who typically lack [[collateral (finance)|collateral]], steady employment and a verifiable [[credit history]]. It is designed not only to support entrepreneurship and alleviate poverty, but also in many cases to empower women and uplift entire communities by extension. In many communities worldwide, in developed and developing nations alike, women lack the highly stable employment histories that traditional lenders tend to require. This reality might result from factors such as leaving the paid workforce to care for children and elderly relatives. As of 2009 an estimated 74 million men and women held microloans that totalled US$38 billion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| last = Microfinance Information Exchange, Inc.| title = MicroBanking Bulletin Issue #19, December, 2009, pp. 49| publisher = Microfinance Information Exchange, Inc.| date = 2009-12-01| url = http://www.themix.org/microbanking-bulletin/mbb-issue-no-19-december-2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Grameen Bank reports that repayment success rates are between 95 and 98 per cent.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.grameenfoundation.org/what-we-do/microfinance-basics Grammen Bank report]&lt;/ref&gt;

Microcredit is a division of [[microfinance]], which is the provision of a wider range of financial services, especially savings accounts, to the poor. Modern microcredit is generally considered to have originated with the [[Grameen Bank]] founded in [[Bangladesh]] in 1983. Many traditional banks subsequently introduced microcredit despite initial misgivings. The [[United Nations]] declared 2005 the [[International Year of Microcredit]]. As of 2012, microcredit is widely used in developing countries and is presented as having &quot;enormous potential as a tool for poverty alleviation.&quot;&lt;ref name=Cons-Paprocki /&gt; 

Critics argue, however, that microcredit has not had a positive impact on gender relationships, does not alleviate poverty, has led many borrowers into a debt trap and constitutes a &quot;privatization of welfare&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;gina&quot;&gt;Gina Neff:[http://www.leftbusinessobserver.com/Micro.html Microcredit, microresults] The Left Business Observer #74, October 1996&lt;/ref&gt; 
The first randomized evaluation of microcredit, conducted by [[Esther Duflo]] and others, showed mixed results: there was no effect on household expenditure, gender equity, education or health, but the number of new businesses increased by one third compared to a control group.&lt;ref name=Banerjee/&gt; Professor [[Dean Karlan]] from Yale University says that whilst microcredit generates benefits it isn't the panacea that it has been purported to be. He advocates also giving the poor access to savings accounts.&lt;ref name=Karlan/&gt; 

== History ==
===Early beginnings===
Ideas relating to microcredit can be found at various times in modern history. [[Jonathan Swift]] inspired the [[Irish Loan Funds]] of the 18th and 19th centuries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Complementarity, Competition and Institutional Development: The Irish Loan Funds through Three Centuries|url=http://129.3.20.41/econ-wp/eh/papers/9704/9704003.pdf|accessdate=30 January 2012|author=Aidan Hollis (University of Calgary)|coauthors=Arthur Sweetman (University of Victoria)|date=March 1997}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the mid-19th century, [[Individualist anarchism|Individualist anarchist]] [[Lysander Spooner]] wrote about the benefits of numerous small loans for entrepreneurial activities to the poor as a way to alleviate poverty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Spooner|first=Lysander|title=Poverty: Its illegal causes and legal cure.|url=http://www.lysanderspooner.org/Poverty.htm|accessdate=30 January 2012|location=Boston|year=1846}}&lt;/ref&gt; At about the same time, but independently to Spooner, [[Friedrich Wilhelm Raiffeisen]] founded the first cooperative lending banks to support farmers in rural [[Germany]].&lt;ref&gt;Deutscher Raiffeisenverband:[http://www.raiffeisen.de/genossenschaften/genossenschaften/pdf/Raiffeisen-Organisation-englisch.pdf The Raiffeisen organization: Beginnings, tasks, current developments], March 2011&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1950s, [[Akhtar Hameed Khan]] began distributing group-oriented credit in East Pakistan. Khan used the [[Comilla Model]], in which credit is distributed through community-based initiatives.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bateman 2010&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Bateman|first=Milford|title=Why Doesn't Microfinance Work?|year=2010|publisher=Zed Books}}&lt;/ref&gt; The project failed due to the over-involvement of the Pakistani government, and the hierarchies created within communities as certain members began to exert more control over loans than others.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bateman 2010&quot;/&gt;

===Modern microcredit===
[[Image:Grameen Yunus Dec 04.jpg|thumb|upright|Nobel laureate Muhammad Yunus, the founder of Grameen Bank, which is generally considered the first modern microcredit institution.]]
The origins of microcredit in its current practical incarnation can be linked to several organizations founded in [[Bangladesh]], especially the [[Grameen Bank]]. The Grameen Bank, which is generally considered the first modern microcredit institution, was founded in 1976 by [[Muhammad Yunus]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bateman 2010&quot;/&gt; Yunus began the project in a small town called Jobra, using his own money to deliver small loans at low-interest rates to the rural poor. Grameen Bank was followed by organizations such as [[BRAC (NGO)|BRAC]] in 1972 and [[Association for Social Advancement|ASA]] in 1978.&lt;ref name=&quot;Drake 2002&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Drake|first=Deborah|title=The Commercialization of Microfinance|year=2002|publisher=Kumarian}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Microcredit reached Latin America with the establishment of PRODEM in Bolivia in 1986; a bank that later transformed into the for-profit BancoSol.&lt;ref name=&quot;Armendariz 2005&quot;/&gt; Microcredit quickly became a popular tool for economic development, with hundreds of institutions emerging throughout the third world.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bateman 2010&quot;/&gt; Though the Grameen Bank was formed initially as a non-profit organization dependent upon government subsidies, it later became a corporate entity and was renamed Grameen II in 2002.&lt;ref name=&quot;Drake 2002&quot;/&gt;   [[Muhammad Yunus]] was awarded the [[Nobel Peace Prize]] in 2006 for his work providing microcredit services to the poor.&lt;ref&gt;Nobel Prize.org:[http://www.nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/peace/laureates/2006/ The Nobel Peace Prize 2006:Muhammad Yunus, Grameen Bank], retrieved on 13 February 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

==Principles==
===Economic principles===
Microcredit is ideally based on a unique set of principles that are readily distinguished from trends in the wider credit market.&lt;ref&gt;Vrajlal Sapovadia:[http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=955062 Micro Finance: The Pillars of a Tool to Socio-Economic Development], Development Gateway, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Microcredit organizations were initially created as alternatives to the &quot;loan-sharks&quot; known to take advantage of clients.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bateman 2010&quot;/&gt; Indeed, many microlenders began as non-profit organizations and operated with government funds or private subsidies. By the 1980s, however the &quot;financial systems approach,&quot; influenced by [[neoliberalism]] and propagated by the [[Harvard Institute for International Development]], became the dominant ideology among microcredit organizations. The commercialization of microcredit officially began in 1984 with the formation of Unit Desa (BRI-UD) within the [[Bank Rakyat Indonesia]]. Unit Desa offered ‘kupedes’ microloans based on market interest rates. 

Ironically, many microcredit organizations now function as independent banks. This has led to their charging higher interest rates on loans and placing more emphasis on savings programs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bateman 2010&quot;/&gt; Notably, Unit Desa has charged in excess of 20 per cent on small business loans.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gdrc.org/icm/country/unit-desa.html gdrc.org]&lt;/ref&gt; The application of [[neoliberal economics]] to microcredit has generated much debate among scholars and development practitioners, with some claiming that microcredit bank directors, such as Muhammad Yunus, apply the practices of loan sharks for their personal enrichment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Drake 2002&quot;/&gt; Indeed, the academic debate foreshadowed a Wall-street style scandal involving the Mexican microcredit organization [[Compartamos Banco|Compartamos]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bateman 2010&quot;/&gt; 

Even so, the numbers indicate that ethical microlending and investor profit can go hand-in-hand. In the 1990s a rural finance minister in Indonesia showed how Unit Desa could lower its rates by about 8% while still bringing attractive returns to investors.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gdrc.org/icm/country/unit-desa.html gdrc.org]&lt;/ref&gt; Today, smaller investment firms are adopting the microlending movement's original ideals. For instance, whereas small coffee farmers in Honduras are typically charged an 18% bank rate, a private investment firm in the US has room to offer more ethical loan terms and offer an attractive return to investors.&lt;ref&gt;[http://theodtc.com/coffee-project theodtc.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Group lending===
[[File:Small Enterprise Foundation - microfinance meeting.jpg|thumb|left|Microfinance meeting in Tzaneen, South Africa. Group-lending is a key part of microcredit.]]

Though lending to groups has long been a key part of microcredit{{citation needed|date=April 2012}}, microcredit initially began with the principle of lending to individuals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Drake 2002&quot;/&gt;  Despite the use of solidarity circles in 1970s Jobra, [[Grameen Bank]] and other early microcredit institutions initially focused on individual lending.&lt;ref name=&quot;Armendariz 2005&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Armendariz|first=Beatriz|title=The Economics of Microfinance|year=2005|publisher=The MIT Press|location=Cambridge, Mass}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Indeed, [[Muhammad Yunus]] propagated the notion that every person has the potential to become an entrepreneur. The use of group-lending was motivated by [[economics of scale]], as the costs associated with monitoring loans and enforcing repayment are significantly lower when credit is distributed to groups rather than individuals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Armendariz 2005&quot;/&gt;  Many times the loan to one participant in group-lending depends upon the successful repayment from another member, thus transferring repayment responsibility off of microcredit institutions to loan recipients.&lt;ref name=&quot;Armendariz 2005&quot;/&gt;

===Lending to women===
Lending to women has become an important principle in microcredit, with banks and [[Non-governmental organization|NGO]]s such as BancoSol, [[Women's_World_Banking|WWB]], and [[Pro Mujer]] catering to women exclusively.&lt;ref name=&quot;Armendariz 2005&quot;/&gt; Though [[Grameen Bank]] initially tried to lend to both men and women at equal rates, women presently make up ninety-five percent of the bank’s clients. Women continue to make up seventy-five percent of all microcredit recipients worldwide.&lt;ref name=&quot;Armendariz 2005&quot;/&gt; Exclusive lending to women began in the 1980s when Grameen Bank found that women have higher repayment rates, and tend to accept smaller loans than men. Subsequently, many microcredit institutions have used the goal of empowering women to justify their disproportionate loans to women.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bateman 2010&quot;/&gt;

==Examples==
[[File:NABARD.jpg|thumb|Mumbai Headquarters of the National Bank for Agriculture and Rural Development of India, which on-lends funds to banks providing microcredit.]]
Grameen Bank in Bangladesh is the oldest and probably best-known microfinance institution in the world. In [[India]], the [[National Bank for Agriculture and Rural Development]] ([[NABARD]]) finances more than 500 banks that on-lend funds to [[self-help group (finance)|self-help group]]s (SHGs). SHGs comprise twenty or fewer members, of whom the majority are women from the poorest [[caste]]s and tribes. Members save small amounts of money, as little as a few rupees a month in a group fund. Members may borrow from the group fund for a variety of purposes ranging from household emergencies to school fees. As SHGs prove capable of managing their funds well, they may borrow from a local bank to invest in small business or farm activities. Banks typically lend up to four rupees for every rupee in the group fund. In Asia borrowers generally pay interest rates that range from 30% to 70% without commission and fees.&lt;ref&gt;Nimal A. Fernando:[http://www.adb.org/documents/books/interest-rates-microcredit/microcredit-understanding-dealing.pdf Understanding and Dealing with High Interest Rate on Microcredit], Asian Development Bank, May 2006, p. 1&lt;/ref&gt; Nearly 1.4 million SHGs comprising approximately 20 million women now borrow from banks, which makes the Indian SHG-Bank Linkage model the largest microfinance program in the world. Similar programs are evolving in Africa and Southeast Asia with the assistance of organizations like [[IFAD]], [[Opportunity International]], [[Catholic Relief Services]], [[Compassion International]], [[CARE (relief agency)|CARE]], [[APMAS]], [[Oxfam]], [[Tearfund]] and [[World Vision]].

[[Grameen Bank]] launched their US operations in New York in April 2008.&lt;ref&gt;University of Michigan, Urban and Regional Planning Economic Development Handbook: [http://www.umich.edu/~econdev/microcredit/ Microcredit strategies for assisting neighborhood businesses], 22 March 2005, retrieved on 13 February 2012&lt;/ref&gt; Bank of America has announced plans to award more than $3.7 million in grants to nonprofits to use in backing microloan programs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Bank of America Issues Grants for Microloans|url=http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748703735804575535900346930486.html|publisher=Wall Street Journal|accessdate=30 January 2012|date=October 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Accion USA|ACCION USA]], the US subsidiary of the better-known [[Accion International|ACCION International]], has provided US$117 million in microloans since 1991, with an over 90% repayment rate.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}} One research study of the Grameen model shows that poorer individuals are safer borrowers because they place more value on the relationship with the bank.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kansascityfed.org/PUBLICAT/RESWKPAP/PDF/rwp10-11.pdf Federal Reserve Bank of Kansas City, ''The Creditworthiness of the Poor: A Model of the Grameen Bank'', April 2010]&lt;/ref&gt; Even so, efforts to replicate Grameen-style [[solidarity lending]] in developed countries have generally not succeeded. For example, the [[Calmeadow Foundation]] tested an analogous peer-lending model in three locations in Canada during the 1990s. It concluded that a variety of factors — including difficulties in reaching the target market, the high risk profile of clients, their general distaste for the joint liability requirement, and high overhead costs — made solidarity lending unviable without subsidies.&lt;ref&gt;Cheryl Frankiewicz. &quot;Calmeadow Metrofund: A Canadian Experiment in Sustainable Microfinance&quot;, Calmeadow Foundation, April 2001.&lt;/ref&gt; Microcredits have also been introduced in Israel,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.svivatomehet.org.il Svivatomehet.org.il] {{he icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; Russia, Ukraine and other nations where micro-loans help small business entrepreneurs overcome cultural barriers in the mainstream business society. The [[Israel Free Loan Association (IFLA)]] has lent more than $100 million in the past two decades to Israeli citizens of all backgrounds.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}}

===Peer-to-peer lending over the Web===
The principles of microcredit have also been applied in attempting to address several non-poverty-related issues.  Among these, multiple Internet-based organizations have developed platforms that facilitate a modified form of [[peer-to-peer lending]] where a loan is not made in the form of a single, direct loan, but as the aggregation of a number of smaller loans—often at a negligible interest rate.  There are several ways by which the general public can participate in alleviating poverty using Web platforms.

New platforms that connect lenders to micro-entrepreneurs are emerging on the Web, for example [[Kiva (organization)|Kiva]], [[Zidisha]], [http://www.lendforpeace.org/ Lend for Peace], and the [[Microloan Foundation]]. Another WWW-based microlender [[United Prosperity (organisation)|United Prosperity]] uses a variation on the usual microlending model; with United Prosperity the micro-lender provides a guarantee to a local bank which then lends back double that amount to the micro-entrpreneur. United Prosperity claims this provides both greater leverage and allows the micro-entrepreneur to develop a credit history with their local bank for future loans. In 2009, the US-based nonprofit [[Zidisha]] became the first peer-to-peer microlending platform to link lenders and borrowers directly across international borders without local intermediaries.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.microfinancefocus.com/news/2010/02/07/zidisha-set-to-expand-in-peer-to-peer-microfinance-julia-kurnia/ &quot;Zidisha Set to &quot;Expand&quot; in Peer-to-Peer Microfinance&quot;, Microfinance Focus, Feb 2010]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Vittana]] allows peer-to-peer lending for student loans in developing countries.&lt;ref&gt;Rao. L. (2010). ''Vittana Applies The Kiva Model To Help Finance Education In Developing Countries''. Retrieved March 9, 2011, from http://techcrunch.com/2010/03/15/vittana-applies-the-kiva-model-to-help-finance-education-in-developing-countries/&lt;/ref&gt;

==Impact==
Microcredit is being justified by its positive impact on poverty reduction, income, consumption, the creation of businesses, education and health, the empowerment of women and the empowerment of the poor in general.

Critics argue that microcredit has driven poor households into a debt trap, that the money from loans is used for consumption, that men actually use the money for which their female relatives get into debt and that microcredit does not alleviate poverty or improve health and education.

At the 2008 [[Innovations for Poverty Action]]/[[Financial Access Initiative]] Microfinance Research conference, economist Jonathan Morduch of [[New York University]] noted there are only one or two methodologically sound studies of microfinance's impact.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| last = Morduch | first = Jonathan | title = Comments Made at IPA/FAI Microfinance Conference Oct. 17 2008 | publisher = Philanthropy Action | date = 2008-10-17| url = http://www.philanthropyaction.com/nc/cutting_edge_research_on_microfinance/| accessdate = 2008-10-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Grameen Foundation has released two papers summarizing the state of research on the impact of microfinance on poverty: &quot;Measuring the Impact of Microfinance, Taking Stock of What We Know&quot; by Nathanael Goldberg&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.givewell.org/files/Cause1-2/Independent%20research%20on%20microfinance/GFUSA-MicrofinanceImpactWhitepaper-1.pdf|title=Measuring the Impact of Microfinance, Taking Stock of What We Know|publisher=Grameen Bank|year=2005|accessdate=2011-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; (now with Innovations for Poverty Action) and an update, &quot;Measuring the Impact of Microfinance: Taking Another Look&quot; by Professor Kathleen Odell.  These two papers identify scores of findings indicating positive impact in research conducted over the last twenty years, as well as some findings that suggest limited or negative impact in some cases.

===Income, consumption and the creation of businesses===
[[File:Rwandan farm cooperative goats.jpg|thumb|Microlending aims at increasing income through productive activities such as goat herding, as shown here in Rwanda on a cooperative funded through microlending.]] 
Tazul Islam suggests that microcredit has a &quot;positive impact on enterprise and household income and asset accumulation&quot;.&lt;ref name=Islam&gt;{{cite book|last=Islam|first=Tazul|title=Microcredit and Poverty alleviation|year=2007|publisher=Ashgate Publishing, Ltd.,}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the positive economic impacts associated with microcredit are not as extensive as once thought.&lt;ref name=Karlan&gt;BBC:[http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/p003s71s Business Weekly], 2 August 2009&lt;/ref&gt; A study by [[Dean Karlan]] of [[Yale University]] in the Philippines compared two groups in Manila: a treatment group, financed through microcredit, and a control group that did not receive microcredit. The study showed that in this case many microcredits were loaned to people with existing business, and not to those seeking to establish new businesses. The businesses became more profitable and laid off unproductive employees including friends and relatives that they previously had felt obliged to employ.&lt;ref&gt;Karlan, Dean S., and Jonathan Zinman. 2011. &quot;List Randomization for Sensitive Behavior: An Application for Measuring Use of Loan Proceeds.&quot; Journal of Development Economics 2012. http://www.povertyactionlab.org/evaluation/measuring-impact-microcredit-and-interest-rate-sensitivity-philippines&lt;/ref&gt;

The first randomized evaluation of the impact of introducing microcredit in a new market has been undertaken in slums in Hyderabad, India, in 2008. Half the slums were randomly selected for opening branches of banks that provided microcredits while the remainder were not. The study showed that fifteen to 18 months after lending began, there was no effect on average monthly expenditure per capita, but expenditure on durable goods increased and the number of new businesses increased by
one third.&lt;ref name=Banerjee&gt;{{cite web|last=Banerjee|first=Abhijit|title=The miracle of microfinance? Evidence from a randomized evaluation|url=http://www.povertyactionlab.org/evaluation/measuring-impact-microfinance-hyderabad-india|accessdate=17 April 2012|coauthors=Esther Duflo, Rachel Glennester, Cynthia Kinnan}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Poverty===
Milford Bateman, the author of ''Why Doesn't Microfinance Work?'', argues that microcredit offers only an &quot;illusion of poverty reduction&quot;. &quot;As in any lottery or game of chance, a few in poverty do manage to establish microenterprises that produce a decent living,&quot; he argues, but &quot;these isolated and often temporary positives are swamped by the largely overlooked negatives.&quot; Bateman concludes that &quot;The international development community is now faced with the reality that, overall, microfinance has been a development policy blunder of quite historic proportions.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title = The illusion of poverty reduction | publisher = Red Pepper magazine | date = 2010-09-01| url = http://www.redpepper.org.uk/the-illusion-of-poverty-reduction}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Sociologist]] Jonathan H. Westover, Ph.D. found that much of the evidence on the effectiveness of microfinance for alleviating poverty is based in anecdotal reports or case studies. He initially found over 100 articles on the subject, but included only the 6 which used enough quantitative data to be representative, and none of which employed rigorous methods such as randomized control trials similar to those reported by [[Innovations for Poverty Action]] and the [[M.I.T.]] [[Jameel Poverty Action Lab]]. One of these studies found that microfinance reduced poverty. Two others were unable to conclude that microfinance reduced poverty, although they attributed some positive effects to the program. Other studies concluded similarly, with surveys finding that a majority of participants feel better about finances with some feeling worse.&lt;ref&gt;Westover J. (2008). [http://www.sociology.org/content/2008/_westover_finance.pdf The Record of Microfinance: The Effectiveness/Ineffectiveness of Microfinance Programs as a Means of Alleviating Poverty]. ''[[Electronic Journal of Sociology]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Islam the [[Grameen Bank]] does not reach the poorest, since the clients of the bank tend to be clustered around the poverty line of predominantly moderately poor or vulnerable non-poor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Islam|first=Tazul|title=Microcredit and poverty alleviation|year=2007|pages=3}}&lt;/ref&gt; Of the poor who join Grameen bank’s microcredit program, a high percentage often drop out after only a few loan cycles, while many others eventually drop out in later loan cycles as loan amounts begin to exceed their repayment capacity.&lt;ref name=Sharma&gt;{{cite news|last=Sharma|first=Sudhirendar|title=MFIs lay small-debt trap in Andhra|url=http://infochangeindia.org/micro-credit/news/mfis-lay-small-debt-trap-in-andhra.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some problems with microcredit are mistakenly alleged in The Micro Debt, a film by the Danish journalist Tom Heinemann.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dr.dk/Nyheder/Udland/2010/12/01/170646.htm |title=Tom Heinemann: &quot;Fanget i Mikrogæld&quot; |publisher=Dr.dk |date= |accessdate=2011-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; After a thorough investigation in December 2010 by the Norwegian Foreign Ministry, the alleged problems have been proven to be false and no further actions against the Grameen Bank and its founder, Muhammad Yunnis, have been taken.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Grameen: Norway gives all-clear to Bangladesh bank|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-south-asia-11947902|work=BBC News|publisher=BBC|accessdate=17 September 2011|date=2010-12-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; The documentary by Heinemann also looks at the effectiveness of Grameen Bank and alleges that it has little impact on poverty by highlighting the purported continued poverty of Sufiya Begum, the original loan recipient of Grameen, in Jobra Village. This allegation is disputed, since documentary maker Gayle Ferraro found the woman alive and well, confirming the original Grameen story.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blogs.cgdev.org/open_book/2011/02/being-crossfire.php |title=David Roodman's Microfinance Open Book Blog |publisher=Blogs.cgdev.org |date= |accessdate=2011-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Risks like sickness and natural disasters are a critical dimension of poverty and poor people rely heavily on informal savings to manage these risks. Microfinance institutions could provide savings services to this population to reduce these risks, but not all of them have been successful at doing so. For example, a study of microcredit institutions in Bolivia in 2003, for example, found that they were very slow to deliver quality [[microsavings]] services because of easy access to cheaper forms of external capital.&lt;ref&gt;Hillary Miller.  ''The paradox of savings mobilization in microfinance:  why microfinance institutions in Bolivia have virtually ignored savings''.  Development Alternatives Inc. and USAID, Washington, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;

Microcredit has been blamed for many suicides in India: aggressive lending by microcredit companies in [[Andhra Pradesh]] is said to have resulted in over 80 deaths in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-south-asia-11997571 | work=BBC News | title=India's micro-finance suicide epidemic | date=2010-12-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Interest rates, stock offerings and repayment rates===
There has been much criticism of the high interest rates charged to borrowers. For example, Bangladesh's former Finance and Planning Minister M. Saifur Rahman charged in 2005 that some microfinance institutions use excessive interest rates.&lt;ref name=&quot;Saifur&quot;&gt;Bangladesh Strategic and Development Forum:[http://www.bdsdf.org/forum/index.php?showtopic=3573&amp;st=15 Saifur takes swipe at micro-credit], 21 November 2005, retrieved on 13 February 2012&lt;/ref&gt; Sharma has criticized microfinance institutions for creating small-debt traps for the poor in Andhra Pradesh in India with high interest rates and coercive methods of recovery.&lt;ref name=Sharma/&gt; A 2008 study in Bangladesh showed that some loan recipients sink into a cycle of debt, using a microcredit loan from one organization to meet interest obligations from another. Field officers who are in a position of power locally and are remunerated based on repayment rates sometimes use coercive and even violent tactics to collect installments on the microcredit loans.&lt;ref name=Cons-Paprocki /&gt; The real average portfolio yield cited by the sample of 704 microfinance institutions that voluntarily submitted reports to the MicroBanking Bulletin in 2006 was 22.3% annually.  However, annual rates charged to clients are higher, as they also include local inflation and the bad debt expenses of the microfinance institution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| last = Microfinance Information Exchange, Inc.| title = MicroBanking Bulletin Issue #15, Autumn, 2007, pp. 48| publisher = Microfinance Information Exchange, Inc.| date = 2007-08-01| url = http://www.themix.org/microbanking-bulletin/mbb-issue-no-15-autumn-2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Muhammad Yunus]] has recently made much of this point, and in his latest book&lt;ref&gt;Muhammad Yunus and Karl Weber.  ''Creating a World Without Poverty:  Social Business and the Future of Capitalism''. PublicAffairs, New York, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; argues that microfinance institutions that charge more than 15% above their long-term operating costs should face penalties.

A related issue is interest rate disclosure: Many suppliers of microcredit quote their rates to clients using the [[flat rate (finance)|flat calculation method]], which significantly understates the true [[Annual Percentage Rate]].{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}} In [[Andhra Pradesh]], the villagers who take out the loan often did not know the interest that they were being charged and were not aware of the consequences of taking multiple loans as they take the second loan to clear the first loan.&lt;ref name=Tucker&gt;{{cite journal|last=Tucker|first=Jeffrey|title=The Micro-Credit Cult|url=http://mises.org/freemarket_detail.aspx?control=215|date=November 1995|journal=The Free Market, The Mises Institute Monthly}} retrieved on 13 February 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

The issuing of stocks through IPOs (Initial Public Offerings) by microfinance institutions has also been criticized. In July 2010 India's biggest MFI, [[SKS Microfinance]] also went public. In both instances [[Muhammad Yunus]] publicly stated his disagreement, saying that the poor should be the only beneficiaries of microfinance.&lt;ref&gt;Businessweek, &quot;Online Extra: Yunus Blasts Compartamos&quot; http://www.businessweek.com/magazine/content/07_52/b4064045920958.htm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;ABCNews, SKS Launches India's First Microfinance IPO http://abcnews.go.com/Business/wireStory?id=11270209&lt;/ref&gt;

Tucker argued in 1995 that the 98% repayment rate of Grameen’s loans only refer to first-time loans, that they are often repaid by new loans and that the practice of lending only to groups of women puts lenders under pressure because each member can only obtain a new loan if each member has repaid the previous loan.&lt;ref name=Tucker/&gt;

===Gender===
[[File:An ESAF 'Sangam' Meeting in progress in Kerala.jpg|thumb|left|Meeting of clients of the Indian microlender ESAF in the state of Kerala.]]
A 1996 study in Bangladesh acknowledges the &quot;success&quot; of reaching women with microcredit as &quot;highly impressive&quot;, but also notes that loans are often given over to male relatives or husbands. In a minority of cases there was even an increase in [[domestic violence]] for women who did not get the loan or had to wait a long time to get the loan. The study also showed that women are more likely to retain control over their loans in traditional women’s work like livestock rearing that are considered “women’s work”.&lt;ref name=&quot;GuptaGoetz&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Goetz|coauthors=Gupta|journal=World Development|year=1996|volume=24|series=Who takes the credit?Gender, Power, Control over loan use in Rural credit program in Bangladesh|url=http://www.citt.ufl.edu/portfolio/genders/Readings/ReadingsW10/Whotakesthecredit.pdf|issue=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2008 study of microcredit programs in Bangladesh found that women often act merely as collection agents for their husbands and sons, such that the men spend the money themselves while women are saddled with the credit risk.&lt;ref name=Cons-Paprocki&gt;Jason Cons and Kasia Paprocki of the Goldin Institute, [http://www.foodfirst.org/en/node/2351 &quot;The Limits of Microcredit—A Bangladeshi Case&quot;], ''Food First Backgrounder'' (Institute for Food and Development Policy), Winter 2008, volume 14, number 4.&lt;/ref&gt; The bigger the size of the loan, women lose their control more. For example, a study in Bangladesh showed that women have 100% control over loans that are smaller than 1000 Taka but only 46% of control if the loan is bigger than 4,000 Taka.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Montgomery|first=Bhattacharya|coauthors=Hulme|title=Credit for the poor in Bangladesh: the BRAC Rural Development Programme and the Government Thana Resource Development and Employment Programme,|journal=Finance Against Poverty}}&lt;/ref&gt; A study in India showed that women may be put under pressure by their male relatives to join a credit group and indebt themselves.&lt;ref name=Sharma/&gt; A study in Bangladesh showed that microcredit increases [[dowry|dowries]], with women forced at times to take microcredit loans as the only means to pay these increased dowries for their daughters.&lt;ref name=Cons-Paprocki /&gt; The first randomized evaluation of the introduction of microcredit, carried out in Hyderabad in India, found no impact on women's decision-making.&lt;ref name=Banerjee/&gt;

A large majority of microloans is awarded to women, often under the pretense of ensuring their empowerment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leach 2002 575–588&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Leach|first=Fiona|coauthors=Shashikhala Sitiram|title=Microfinance and Women’s Empowement: A Lesson from India|journal=Development in Practice|year=2002|volume=12|url=http://www.jstor.org/discover/10.2307/4029403?uid=3737864&amp;uid=2&amp;uid=4&amp;sid=21100728509251issue=5|pages=575–588}}&lt;/ref&gt; Parmar takes issue with the idea that empowerment can be given to women by (mostly male) development practitioners in the form of loans, arguing that empowerment is a self-directed process.&lt;ref name=&quot;Parmar 2003 461–476&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Parmar|first=Aradhana|title=Micro-credit, Empowerment, and Agency: re-Evaluating the Discourse|journal=Canadian Journal of Development Studies|year=2003|volume=XXIV|issue=3|pages=461–476}}&lt;/ref&gt; Johnson argues for the inclusion of more female employees in microcredit institutions, and gender awareness training for existing staff.&lt;ref name=&quot;Parmar 2003 461–476&quot;/&gt; Additionally, Leach claims that men must be included in the process of lending to women in order to diminish gender antagonism, as men often feel excluded from microcredit services.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leach 2002 575–588&quot;/&gt;

Some authors argue that microcredit not only empowers women, but men as well. For example, Cheston and Kuhn say that microcredit programs have the &quot;potential&quot; to transform [[power (philosophy)|power]] relations and empower the poor — both men and women.&lt;ref name=Chester&gt;{{cite journal|last=cheston|coauthors=kuhn|journal=empowering women through microfinance}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Education and health===
Tazul Islam asserts a positive influence of microcredit on the level of education, health and nutrition.&lt;ref name=Islam/&gt; However, the first randomized evaluation of microcredit, carried out in Hyderabad in India, did not find any evidence of an impact on education and health.&lt;ref name=Banerjee/&gt;

==Improvement==
[[File:Inside banco palmas woman.JPG|thumb|Many microfinance institutions also offer savings facilities, such as Banco Palma in Brazil shown here.]]
Many scholars and practitioners suggest an integrated package of services ('a credit-plus' approach) rather than just providing credits. When access to credit is combined with savings facilities, non-productive loan facilities, insurance, [[enterprise development]] (production-oriented and management training, marketing support) and welfare-related services (literacy and health services, gender and social awareness training), the adverse effects discussed above can be diminished.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Holvoet|first=Nathalie|title=The Impact of Microfinance on Decision-Making Agency: Evidence from South India}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some argue that more experienced entrepreneurs who are getting loans should be qualified for bigger loans to ensure the success of the program.&lt;ref name=&quot;GuptaGoetz&quot;/&gt;

One of the principal challenges of microcredit is providing small loans at an affordable cost.  The global average interest and fee rate is estimated at 37%, with rates reaching as high as 70% in some markets.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nytimes.com/2010/04/14/world/14microfinance.html?pagewanted=all&lt;/ref&gt;  The reason for the high interest rates is not primarily cost of capital.  Indeed, the local microfinance organizations that receive zero-interest loan capital from the online microlending platform [[Kiva]] charge average interest and fee rates of 35.21%.&lt;ref name=&quot;HighRates&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kiva.org/about/app.php?page=help&amp;action=InterestRateComparison#AverageInterestRateBorrowerPaysToKivaFieldPartner|title=Kiva Help - Interest Rate Comparison|publisher=Kiva.org|accessdate=October 10, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Rather, the principal reason for the high cost of microcredit loans is the high transaction cost of traditional microfinance operations relative to loan size. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.kiva.org/about/microfinance#interestRatesAreHigh&lt;/ref&gt;  Microcredit practitioners have long argued that such high interest rates are simply unavoidable.  The result is that the traditional approach to microcredit has made only limited progress in resolving the problem it purports to address: that the world's poorest people pay the world's highest cost for small business growth capital.  The high costs of traditional microcredit loans limit their effectiveness as a poverty-fighting tool. Borrowers who do not manage to earn a rate of return at least equal to the interest rate may actually end up poorer as a result of accepting the loans.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.quora.com/Microfinance/Do-the-micro-loans-contribute-to-the-well-being-of-the-people-or-do-they-leave-them-even-poorer-due-to-high-interest-rates&lt;/ref&gt;  According to a recent survey of microfinance borrowers in Ghana published by the Center for Financial Inclusion, more than one-third of borrowers surveyed reported struggling to repay their loans.&lt;ref&gt;http://centerforfinancialinclusionblog.files.wordpress.com/2011/11/111108_cfi_over-indebtedness-in-ghana_jessica-schicks_en_final.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;   In recent years, microcredit providers have shifted their focus from the objective of increasing the volume of lending capital available, to address the challenge of providing microfinance loans more affordably.  Analyst David Roodman contends that in mature markets, the average interest and fee rates charged by microfinance institutions tend to fall over time. &lt;ref&gt;Roodman, David. &quot;Due Diligence: An Impertinent Inquiry Into Microfinance.&quot; Center for Global Development, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Cooperative banking]]
* [[Count Me In (charity)]]
* [[Crowdfunding]]
* [[Crowd sourcing]]
* [[Flat rate (finance)]]
* [[Micro credit for water supply and sanitation]]
* [[Microgrant]]
* [[Project Enterprise]]
* [[Solidarity lending]]
* [[Oikocredit]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Bibliography==
Following is a selected bibliography about microcredit.
* Adams, Dale, Doug Graham and J.D. Von Pischke (eds.).  ''Undermining Rural Development with Cheap Credit''.  Westview Press, Boulder, Colorado, 1984.
*Drake, Deborah, and Elizabeth Rhyne (eds.).  ''The Commercialization of Microfinance:  Balancing Business and Development''.  Kumarian Press, 2002.
*Rhyne, Elizabeth.  ''Mainstreaming Microfinance:  How Lending to the Poor Began, Grew and Came of Age in Bolivia''.  Kumarian Press, 2001.
*Fuglesang, Andreas and Dale Chandler. ''Participation as Process – Process as Growth – What We can Learn from the Grameen Bank.''  Grameen Trust, Dhaka, 1993.
*Gibbons, David.  ''The Grameen Reader''.  Grameen Bank, Dhaka, 1992.
*Harper, Malcolm and Shailendra Vyakarnam.  ''Rural Enterprise:  Case Studies from Developing Countries''. ITDG Publishing, 1988.
*Hulme, David and Paul Mosley.  ''Finance Against Poverty''.  Routledge, London, 1996.
*Johnson, Susan and Ben Rogaly.  ''Microfinance and Poverty Reduction''.  Oxfam, Oxford UK, 1997.
*Kadaras, James &amp; Elizabeth Rhyne.  ''Characteristics of equity investment in microfinance''. Accion International, 2004.
*Khandker, Shahidur R. ''Fighting Poverty with Microcredit''. Bangladesh edition, The University Press Ltd, Dhaka, 1999.
*Ledgerwood, Joanna.  ''Microfinance Handbook''.  Washington, D.C., World Bank, 1998.
*Rutherford, Stuart.  ''ASA:  The Biography of an NGO, Empowerment and Credit in Rural Bangladesh''.  ASA, Dhaka, 1995.
*''Small Enterprise Development''. Intermediate Technology Publications, London.
*Todd, Helen ''Women at the Center:  Grameen Borrowers After One Decade''. University Press Ltd, Dhaka, 1996.
*Wood, Geoff D. &amp; I. Sharif (eds.).  ''Who Needs Credit?  Poverty and Finance in Bangladesh''.  University Press Ltd., Dhaka, 1997.
*Yunus, Muhammad.  ''Banker to the Poor:  Micro-Lending and the Battle Against World Poverty''.  Public Affairs, 2003.
*Padmanabahn, K.P., ''Rural Credit'', Intermediate Tech. Publ. Ltd., London 1988.
*Germidis D. et al.,''Financial Systems and Development: what role for the formal and informal financial sectors?'', OECD, Paris 1991.
*Robinson, Marguerite S., ''The microfinance revolution'', The World Bank, Washington D.C., 2001.
*Mauri, Arnaldo, (1995): ''A new approach to institutional lending and loan administration in rural areas of LDCs'', International Review of Economics, ISSN 1865-1704, Vol. 45, no. 4, pp. 707-716.
*Goetz, A.-M., and R. Sengupta. 1996. Who Takes the Credit? Gender, Power and Control over Loan Use in Rural Credit Programmes in Bangladesh. World Development 24:45–63.
*Johnson, S. 1997. Gender and Micro-finance: guidelines for best practice. Action Aid-UK.
*Kabeer, N. 1998. 'Money Can't Buy Me Love'? Re-evaluating Gender, Credit and Empowerment in Rural Bangladesh. IDS Discussion Paper 363.
*Mayoux, L. 1998a. Women's Empowerment and Micro-finance programmes: Approaches, Evidence and Ways Forward. The Open University Working Paper No 41.
*Rahman, A. (1999). “Micro-credit Initiatives for Equitable and Sustainable Development: Who Pays?” World Development 27(1): 67–82.
*CHESTON, S. and KUHN, L. (2002). Empowering Women through Microfinance. Pathways Out of Poverty: Innovations in Microfinance for the Poorest Families.
*Harper, A. ( 1995). Providing women in Baltistan with access to loans – potential and problems. Lahore, AKRSP Pakistan.
*Mutalima, I. K., 2006, [http://www.microcreditsummit.org/papers/Workshops/28_Mutalima.pdf Microfinance and Gender Equality: Are We Getting There?]: Micro Credit Summit, Halifa, Royal Tropical Institute and Oxfam Novib.
*ZAIDI, S AKBAR, HAROON JAMAL, SARAH JAVEED and SARAH ZAKA. (2007). &quot;Social Impact Assessment of Microfinance Programmes.&quot;

==External links==
* [http://www.povertyactionlab.org/publication/latest-findings-randomized-evaluations-microfinance Latest Findings from Randomized Evaluations of Microfinance] Access to Finance Forum by CGAP and Its Partners No. 2, December 2011
* [http://www.usaid.gov/locations/sub-saharan_africa/sudan/ss_microfinance.html Building a Microfinance Institution from Scratch] Institution's objective is to offer financial services on a self-sustaining yet efficient basis to microentrepreneurs.
* [http://www.lib.byu.edu/spc/microfinance/ Journal of Microfinance], a forum for practitioners in microfinance and microenterprise development to exchange information and ideas
* [http://www.tufts.edu/microfinancefund/ Omidyar-Tufts Microfinance Fund], a partnership between [[Pierre Omidyar]] and [[Tufts University]].
*[http://thehague.usembassy.gov/mrs._arnall_microfinance &quot;Microfinance in the U.S.&quot;] Helping ensure egalitarian access to needed financial services.
*[http://www.csa.com/discoveryguides/microfinance/review.php The Promise of Microfinance for Poverty Relief in the Developing World]
*[http://www.mra.gov.bd/ Microcredit Regulatory Authority, MRA] The central body to monitor and supervise microfinance operation of NGOs of Bangladesh
*[http://www.brac.net/ Alleviation and poverty and enpowerment of the poor, BRAC] [[Bangladesh]]
*[http://www.credit-coops.ru The European Union Project &quot;Credit Cooperatives – Russian Federation&quot;] official web site
*[http://www.kbyutv.org/smallfortunes/ Small Fortunes: Microcredit and the Future of Poverty] web site for a [[PBS]] documentary

[[Category:Development]]
[[Category:Microfinance]]
[[Category:United Nations Secretariat]]

[[bn:ক্ষুদ্রঋণ]]
[[ca:Microcrèdit]]
[[cs:Mikroúvěr]]
[[de:Mikrokredit]]
[[es:Microcrédito]]
[[fr:Microcrédit]]
[[ko:마이크로크레딧]]
[[id:Kredit mikro]]
[[it:Microcredito]]
[[he:מיקרו אשראי]]
[[ka:მიკროკრედიტი]]
[[lt:Mikrokreditas]]
[[ml:മൈക്രോക്രെഡിറ്റ്]]
[[nl:Microkrediet]]
[[ja:マイクロクレジット]]
[[no:Mikrokreditt]]
[[nn:Mikrokreditt]]
[[pl:Mikrokredyt]]
[[pt:Microcrédito]]
[[ru:Микрокредитование]]
[[fi:Mikroluotto]]
[[sv:Mikrolån]]
[[ta:குறுங்கடன்]]
[[zh:小额贷款]]</text>
      <sha1>tp18bvq18wo78uef4s790f405slk2td</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
