<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Natural capital</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>45795</id>
    <revision>
      <id>516540012</id>
      <parentid>505104577</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-07T22:23:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DASonnenfeld</username>
        <id>2922608</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>removed [[Category:Environmental economics]]; added [[Category:Ecological economics]] using [[WP:HC|HotCat]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14419">{{Cleanup|date=September 2010}}
{{Refimprove|date=April 2009}}

[[File:Bachalpseeflowers.jpg|thumb|right|275px|[[Bachalpsee]] in the [[Swiss Alps]]; generally mountainous areas are less affected by human activity.]]
[[File:Extemporaneous remarks at Harve, Montana - NARA - 197750.tif|150px|right|thumb|Remarks from 1937 by [[Franklin Delano Roosevelt|FDR]] on &quot;natural capital&quot; and &quot;balancing the budget of our resources&quot;]]

'''Natural capital''' is the extension of the economic notion of [[capital (economics)|capital]] (manufactured means of production) to goods and services relating to the [[natural environment]]. Natural capital is thus the stock of natural [[ecosystems]] that yields a flow of valuable ecosystem goods or services into the future. For example, a stock of [[trees]] or [[fish]] provides a flow of new trees or fish, a flow which can be indefinitely [[sustainability|sustainable]]. Natural capital may also provide services like [[recycling]] wastes or [[water catchment]] and [[erosion]] control. Since the flow of services from ecosystems requires that they function as whole systems, the structure and diversity of the system are important components of natural capital.

==Background==

In ''[[Natural Capitalism: Creating the Next Industrial Revolution]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Hawken|first=Paul |coauthors=Amory Lovins, Hunter Lovins|title=Natural Capitalism: Creating the Next Industrial Revolution|year=1999}}&lt;/ref&gt; the authors see the world's economy as being within the larger economy of natural resources and ecosystem services that sustain us. This implies that we should attribute value to things such as [[Intelligence#Human intelligence|human intelligence]] and [[culture]]s to&lt;!-- what does this &quot;to&quot; mean? --&gt; [[hydrocarbons]], [[minerals]], trees, and microscopic [[fungi]].{{Clarify|date=January 2010}} The authors argue that only through recognizing this essential relationship with the Earth's valuable resources can businesses, and the people they support, continue to exist. The book has many practical suggestions for companies interested in a sustainable future.&lt;ref name=nat&gt;[http://www.socialfunds.com/news/print.cgi?sfArticleId=164 Book Review: Natural Capitalism] from [http://www.socialfunds.com/ Socialfunds.com]. Retrieved April 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the authors, the &quot;next industrial revolution&quot; depends on the espousal of four central strategies: &quot;the conservation of resources through more effective [[manufacturing]] processes, the reuse of materials as found in natural systems, a change in values from quantity to quality, and investing in natural capital, or restoring and sustaining [[natural resources]].&quot;&lt;ref name=nat/&gt;

Natural capital is described in the book Natural Capitalism as a metaphor for the mineral, [[plant]], and [[animal]] formations of the Earth's [[biosphere]] when viewed as a means of production of [[oxygen]], water filter, erosion preventer, or provider of other ecosystem services. It is one approach to ecosystem valuation, an alternative to the traditional view of all non-human life as passive natural resources, and to the idea of [[Ecology|ecological]] health. However, human knowledge and understanding of the [[natural environment]] is never complete, and therefore the boundaries of natural capital expand or contract as knowledge is gained or lost.

In a traditional economic analysis of the factors of production, natural capital would usually be classified as &quot;land&quot; distinct from &quot;capital&quot; in its original sense. The historical distinction between &quot;land&quot; and &quot;capital&quot; was that land is naturally occurring and its supply is assumed to be fixed, whereas capital as originally defined referred only to man-made goods, (e.g., [[Georgism]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.henrygeorge.org/pchp2.htm] - ''[[Progress and Poverty]]'' by [[Henry George]], Chapter 2]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.henrygeorge.org/def2.htm&lt;/ref&gt;). It has been argued that it's useful to view many natural systems as capital because they can be improved or degraded by the actions of man over time (see Tragedy of the commons), so that to view them as if their productive capacity is fixed by nature alone is misleading. Moreover, they yield benefits naturally which are harvested by humans, those being nature's services, 17 of which were closely analyzed by Robert Costanza. These benefits are in some ways similar to those realized by owners of infrastructural capital which yields more goods, e.g. a factory which produces automobiles just as an apple tree produces apples.

The term and metaphor were first used by [[E.F. Schumacher]] in his book ''[[Small Is Beautiful]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Schumacher|first=E.F |title=Small is Beautiful:  A Study of Economics As If People Mattered|year=1973}}&lt;/ref&gt; and are closely identified with [[Herman Daly]], [[Robert Costanza]], the [[Biosphere 2]] project, and the [[Natural Capitalism]] economic model of [[Paul Hawken]], [[Amory Lovins]], and [[Hunter Lovins]] until recently, when it began to be used by politicians, notably [[Ralph Nader]], [[Paul Martin Jr.]], and agencies of the UK government including the [[Public Health Observatory|London Health Observatory]]. Some economists and politicians, including Martin, believe natural capital measures play a key role in money supply and inflation measurements in a modern economy. They point to [[uneconomic growth]] and a lack of any direct connection between measuring well-being and such indicators as GDP.

Indicators adopted by United Nations Environment Programme's World Conservation Monitoring Centre and the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD) to measure natural biodiversity use the term in a slightly more specific way. However, all users of the term differentiate natural from man-made manufactured capital or infrastructural capital in some way. It does not appear that the basic principle is controversial, although there is much controversy on ecological health indicators, value of nature's services and Earth itself, consistent methods of ecosystem valuation, biodiversity metrics and methods of audit that might apply to these services, systems and [[biomes]].

[[Full cost accounting]], triple bottom line, measuring well-being and other proposals for [[accounting reform]] often include proposals to measure an &quot;ecological deficit&quot; or &quot;natural deficit&quot; alongside a social deficit and financial deficit. It is difficult to measure such a deficit without some agreement on methods of valuating and auditing at least the global forms of natural capital (e.g. value of air, water, soil).

The concept of natural capital implies that the savings rate of an [[economics|economy]] is an imperfect measure of what the country is actually saving, because it measures only investment in man-made capital. [[The World Bank]] now calculates the genuine savings rate of a country, taking into account the extraction of natural resources and the ecological damage caused by [[CO2|CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;]] emissions.

Ecologists are teaming up with economists to measure the wealth of ecosystems and to express their value as a way of finding solutions to the biodiversity crisis.&lt;ref name=&quot;Edwards98&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |last = Edwards |first = P. J. |last2 = Abivardi |first2 = C. |title = The value of biodiversity: Where ecology and economy blend |journal = Biological Conservation |volume = 83 |issue = 2 |pages=239–246|year = 1998 |doi = 10.1016/S0006-3207(97)00141-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Naidoo09&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |last = Naidoo |first = R. |last2 = Malcolm|first2 = T. |last3 = Tomasek |first3 = A. |title = Economic benefits of standing forests in highland areas of Borneo: quantification and policy impacts |journal = Conservation Letters |volume = 2 |pages=35–44 |year = 2009 |url = http://www.azoresbioportal.angra.uac.pt/files/publicacoes_Naiddo%20et%20al2009.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Zhoua09&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |last = Zhoua |first = X. |last2 = Al-Kaisib |first2 = M. |last3 = Helmers |first3 = M. J. |title = Cost effectiveness of conservation practices in controlling water erosion in Iowa |journal = Soil and Tillage Research |volume = 106 |issue = 1 |pages=71–8 |year = 2009 |doi = 10.1016/j.still.2009.09.015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some researchers have attempted to place a dollar figure on ecosystem services, such as the value that the [[Boreal forest of Canada|Canadian boreal forest]] is contributing to global ecosystem services. If ecologically intact, the boreal forest has an estimated value of US$3.7 trillion. The [[boreal forest]] ecosystem is one of the planet's great atmospheric regulators and it stores more carbon than any other biome on the planet.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jonsson09&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |last = Jonsson |first = M. |last2 = Wardle |first2 = D. A. |title = Structural equation modelling reveals plant-community drivers of carbon storage in boreal forest ecosystems |journal = Biology Letters |pages=1–4 |year = 2009 |doi = 10.1098/rsbl.2009.0613 |accessdate = Downloaded from rsbl.royalsocietypublishing.org on January 13, 2010 |pmid = 19755530 |volume = 6 |issue = 1 |pmc = 2817262}}&lt;/ref&gt; The annual value for ecological services of the Boreal Forest is estimated at US$93.2 billion, or 2.5 greater than the annual value of resource extraction. The economic value of 17 ecosystem services for the entire biosphere (calculated in 1997) has an estimated average value of US$33 trillion per year.&lt;ref name=&quot;Costanza97&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |author = Costanza, R. et al.|title = The value of the world’s ecosystem services and natural capital. |journal = Nature |volume = 387 |pages=253–260 |year = 1997 |url = http://www.uvm.edu/giee/publications/Nature_Paper.pdf |doi = 10.1038/387253a0 |issue=6630}}&lt;/ref&gt; These ecological economic values are not currently included in calculations of national income accounts, the GDP and they have no price attributes because they exist mostly outside of the global markets.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ferguson06&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |last = Ferguson |first = K.|title = The True Value of Forests |journal = Frontiers in Ecology and the Environment |volume = 4 |issue = 9 |page = 456 |year = 2006 |url = http://www.jstor.org/pss/3868812}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Anielski05&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last = Anielski |first = M.|last2 = Wilson |first2 = S. |title = Counting Canada’s Natural Capital: Assessing the Real value of Canada’s Boreal Ecosystems |year = 2005 |url = http://www.borealcanada.ca/pr_docs/Boreal_Wealth_Report_Nov_2005.pdf |location = Can. Bor. Ini., Pembina Institute, Ottawa}} {{dead link|date=July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The loss of natural capital continues to accelerate and goes undetected by mainstream monetary analysis.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wakernagel97&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |last = Wakernagel |first = M. |last2 = Rees |first2 = W. E. |title = Perceptual and structural barriers to investing in natural capital: Economics from an ecological footprint perspective. |journal = Ecological Economics |volume = 20 |issue = 1 |pages=3–24 |year = 1997 |doi = 10.1016/S0921-8009(96)00077-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;center&gt;{{gallery
|title=Global [[biogeochemical cycles]] critical for life
|width=180
|lines=2
|Image:Nitrogen_Cycle.jpg|alt1=Diagram of the nitrogen cycle|[[Nitrogen cycle]]
|Image:Water cycle.png|alt2=Diagram of the water cycle|[[Water cycle]]
|Image:Carbon cycle-cute diagram.svg|alt3=Diagram of the carbon cycle|[[Carbon cycle]]
|Image:Oxygen Cycle.jpg|alt4=Diagram of the oxygen cycle|[[Oxygen cycle]]
|Image:phoscycle-EPA.jpg|alt5=Diagram of the phosphorus cycle|[[Phosphorus cycle]]}}&lt;/center&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Environment|Ecology|Earth sciences|Sustainable development}}
{{div col|3}}
*[[Bioeconomics (biophysical)]]
*[[Conservation biology]]
*[[Earth economics]] (policy think tank)
*[[Ecodynamics]]
*[[Ecological Economics]]
*[[Ecology]]
*[[Energy and Environment]]
*[[Econophysics]]
*[[Energy Accounting]]
*[[Environmental economics]]
*[[Environmental protection]]
*[[Five Capitals]]
*[[Habitat conservation]]
*[[Natural Capital Initiative]]
*[[Oil depletion]]
*[[Population dynamics]]
*[[Renewable resource]]
*[[Thermoeconomics]]
*[[Sustainable development]]
*[[Sustainability]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* Pearce, D. 1993. Blueprint 3: Measuring Sustainable Development. Earthscan. ISBN 1-85383-183-2
* Jansson, AnnMari; et al. (1994). Investing in Natural Capital : The Ecological Economics Approach to Sustainability. Washington, D.C.: Island Press, 504 pp.&amp;nbsp;ISBN 1-55963-316-6.
* Daily, Gretchen C. (editor) (1997). Nature’s Services: Societal Dependence on Natural Ecosystems. Washington, D.C.: Island Press, 392 pp.&amp;nbsp;ISBN 1-55963-476-6.
* Prugh, Thomas; Robert Costanza et al. (1999). Natural capital and human economic survival. Solomons, Md.: International Society for Ecological Economics, 180 pp.&amp;nbsp;ISBN 1-56670-398-0.

==External links==
{{Commons category|Natural capital}}
* Costanza, Robert (Lead Author); Cutler J. Cleveland (Topic Editor). 2008. [http://www.eoearth.org/article/Natural_capital &quot;Natural capital.&quot;] In: Encyclopedia of Earth. Eds. Cutler J. Cleveland (Washington, D.C.: Environmental Information Coalition, National Council for Science and the Environment). First published in the Encyclopedia of Earth February 26, 2007; Last revised July 31, 2008; Retrieved September 5, 2008.
*[http://www.naturalcapitalproject.org/about.html Natural Capital Project.] A joint venture among The Woods Institute for the Environment at [[Stanford University]], The Nature Conservancy, [[World Wildlife Fund]].
* NOAA Economics [http://www.economics.noaa.gov/?goal=ecosystems US Economic Benefits of Natural Systems to Business and Society.]
* Lacombe Morgane and Aronson James, 2009. [http://www.csf-desertification.org/index.php/bibliotheque/publications-csfd/les-dossiers-du-csfd-english/doc_details/124-lacombe-m-and-aronson-j-2009-restoring-natural-capital Restoring Natural Capital in Arid and Semiarid Regions Combining Ecosystem Health with Human Wellbeing]. Les dossiers thématiques du CSFD. N° 7.
*Earth Economics [http://www.eartheconomics.org]

{{Types of capital}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Natural Capital}}
[[Category:Ecological economics]]
[[Category:Capital]]

[[cs:Přírodní kapitál]]
[[de:Naturkapital]]
[[et:Looduskapital]]
[[fr:Capital naturel]]
[[ja:自然資本]]
[[pl:Kapitał naturalny]]
[[pt:Capital natural]]
[[ru:Естественный капитал]]
[[simple:Natural capital]]
[[sl:Naravne dobrine]]
[[sv:Naturkapital]]</text>
      <sha1>6qyij6gmejrj243lnguljkvdy9lbvtb</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
