<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Neoclassical economics</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>21634</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520922477</id>
      <parentid>520921822</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-01T17:13:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jackftwist</username>
        <id>1567576</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* The Marginal Revolution */ ce: changed “Marshalls” to the possessive form, “Marshal’s”, in the sentence that introduces the bulleted list.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22726">{{refimprove|date=August 2011}}
{{Economics sidebar}}
'''Neoclassical economics''' is a term variously used for approaches to [[economics]] focusing on the determination of prices, outputs, and income [[distribution (economics)|distribution]]s in markets through [[supply and demand]], often mediated through a hypothesized maximization of [[utility]] by income-constrained individuals and of [[Profit (economics)|profit]]s by cost-constrained firms employing available information and factors of production, in accordance with [[rational choice theory]].&lt;ref&gt;Antonietta Campus (1987), &quot;marginal economics&quot;,  ''The [[New Palgrave: A Dictionary of Economics]]'', v. 3, p. 323.&lt;/ref&gt; Neoclassical economics dominates microeconomics, and together with [[Keynesian economics]] forms the [[neoclassical synthesis]] which dominates [[mainstream economics]] today.&lt;ref name=&quot;Clark&quot;&gt;Clark, B. (1998). ''Principles of political economy: A comparative approach''. Westport, Connecticut: Praeger.&lt;/ref&gt; Although neoclassical economics has gained widespread acceptance by contemporary economists, there have been many critiques of neoclassical economics, often incorporated into newer versions of neoclassical theory as awareness of economic criteria changes.

==Overview==
The term was originally introduced by [[Thorstein Veblen]] in 1900, in his article 'Preconceptions of Economic Science', to distinguish [[marginalism|marginalist]]s in the tradition of [[Alfred Marshall]] from those in the [[Austrian School]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Colander&quot; &gt;Colander, David; ''The Death of Neoclassical Economics''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Aspromourgos, T. (1986). On the origins of the term ‘neoclassical’. Cambridge Journal of Economics, 10(3), 265 -270.
[http://cje.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/reprint/10/3/265.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; &quot;No attempt will here be made even to pass a verdict on the relative claims of the recognized two or three main &quot;schools&quot; of theory, beyond the somewhat obvious finding that, for the purpose in hand, the so-called Austrian school is scarcely distinguishable from the neo-classical, unless it be in the different distribution of emphasis. The divergence between the modernized classical views, on the one hand, and the historical and Marxist schools, on the other hand, is wider, so much so, indeed, as to bar out a consideration of the postulates of the latter under the same head of inquiry with the former.&quot; - Veblen&lt;ref&gt;Veblen, T. (1900). 'The Preconceptions of Economic Science - III', ''The Quarterly Journal of Economics'', 14(2), 240-269.  (Term on pg. 261).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
It was later used by [[John Hicks]], [[George Stigler]], and others&lt;ref name=&quot;Stigler&quot;&gt;[[George J. Stigler]] (1941 [1994]). ''Production and Distribution Theories''.  New York: Macmillan. [http://books.google.com/books?id=c4z5t4GTlxwC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_v2_summary_r&amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Preview.]&lt;/ref&gt; to include the work of [[Carl Menger]], [[William Stanley Jevons]], [[John Bates Clark]] and many others.&lt;ref name=&quot;Colander&quot; /&gt; Today it is usually used to refer to [[mainstream economics]], although it has also been used as an [[umbrella term]] encompassing a number of other [[school of thought|schools of thought]],&lt;ref&gt;Fonseca G. L.; [http://cepa.newschool.edu/~het/essays/margrev/ncintro.htm “Introduction to the Neoclassicals”], The New School.&lt;/ref&gt; notably excluding [[institutional economics]], various [[historical school of economics|historical schools of economics]], and [[Marxian economics]], in addition to various other [[heterodox economics|heterodox approaches to economics]].

Neoclassical economics is characterized by several assumptions common to many [[schools of economic thought]]. There is not a complete agreement on what is meant by neoclassical economics, and the result is a wide range of neoclassical approaches to various problem areas and domains—ranging from neoclassical theories of labor to neoclassical theories of demographic changes.
As expressed by [[E. Roy Weintraub]], neoclassical economics rests on three assumptions, although certain branches of neoclassical theory may have different approaches:&lt;ref&gt;E. Roy Weintraub. (2007). Neoclassical Economics. The Concise Encyclopedia Of Economics. Retrieved September 26, 2010, from http://www.econlib.org/library/Enc1/NeoclassicalEconomics.html&lt;/ref&gt;

#People have [[Rational choice theory|rational preferences]] among outcomes that can be identified and associated with a value.
#Individuals [[utility maximization|maximize utility]] and firms [[profit maximization|maximize profits]].
#People act independently on the basis of [[information asymmetry|full and relevant information]].

From these three assumptions, neoclassical economists have built a structure to understand the allocation of scarce resources among alternative ends—in fact understanding such allocation is often considered the definition of economics to neoclassical theorists. Here's how [[William Stanley Jevons]] presented &quot;the problem of Economics&quot;.

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Given, a certain population, with various needs and powers of production, in possession of certain lands and other sources of material: required, the mode of employing their labour which will maximize the utility of their produce.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[William Stanley Jevons]] (1879, 2nd ed., p. 289), [http://books.google.com/books?id=aYcBAAAAQAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_v2_summary_r&amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false''The Theory of Political Economy''.]  Italics in original.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

From the basic assumptions of neoclassical economics comes a wide range of theories about various areas of economic activity.  For example, profit maximization lies behind the neoclassical [[theory of the firm]], while the derivation of [[demand]] curves leads to an understanding of [[consumer good]]s, and the [[Supply (economics)|supply]] curve allows an analysis of the [[factors of production]].  Utility maximization is the source for the neoclassical theory of consumption, the derivation of demand curves for consumer goods, and the derivation of labor supply curves and [[reservation price|reservation demand]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Philip H. Wicksteed]] ''The Common Sense of Political Economy''&lt;/ref&gt; Market supply and demand are aggregated across firms and individuals.   Their interactions determine equilibrium output and price.  The market supply and demand for each factor of production is derived analogously to those for market [http://bea.gov/bea/glossary/glossary.cfm?key_word=Final_use&amp;letter=F#Final_use final output] to determine equilibrium income and the income distribution.  Factor demand incorporates the [[Production, costs, and pricing|marginal-productivity]] relationship of that factor in the output market.
&lt;ref name=&quot;Stigler&quot; /&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;Christopher Bliss (1987),  &quot;distribution theories, neoclassical&quot;, ''The New Palgrave: A Dictionary of Economics'',
v. 1, pp. 883-886.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Robert F. Dorfman (1987), &quot;marginal productivity theory&quot;,  ''The [[New Palgrave: A Dictionary of Economics]]'',
v. 3, pp. 323-25.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;C.E. Ferguson (1969). ''The Neoclassical Theory of Production and Distribution''. Cambridge. [http://www.cambridge.org/catalogue/catalogue.asp?isbn=9780521076296 Description], ch. 1 excerpt, pp. [http://assets.cambridge.org/97805210/76296/excerpt/9780521076296_excerpt.pdf 1-10] (press '''+'''), &amp; review [http://www.jstor.org/pss/2720638 excerpt.]&lt;/ref&gt;

Neoclassical economics emphasizes equilibria, where equilibria are the solutions of [[agent (economics)|agent]] maximization problems. Regularities in economies are explained by [[methodological individualism]], the position that economic phenomena can be explained by aggregating over the behavior of agents. The emphasis is on [[microeconomics]]. Institutions, which might be considered as prior to and conditioning individual behavior, are de-emphasized. [[Economic subjectivism]] accompanies these emphases.  See also [[general equilibrium]].

== Origins ==&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Labor theory of value]] --&gt;
{{Unreferenced section|date=August 2011}}
[[Classical economics]], developed in the 18th and 19th centuries, included a [[value theory]] and [[Distribution (economics)|distribution]] theory. The value of a product was thought to depend on the costs involved in producing that product. The explanation of costs in Classical economics was simultaneously an explanation of distribution. A landlord received rent, workers received wages, and a capitalist tenant farmer received profits on their investment. This classic approach included the work of [[Adam Smith]] and [[David Ricardo]].

However, some economists gradually began emphasizing the perceived value of a good to the consumer. They proposed a theory that the value of a product was to be explained with differences in utility (usefulness) to the consumer. (In England, economists tended  to conceptualize utility in keeping with the [[Utilitarianism]] of [[Jeremy Bentham]] and later of [[John Stuart Mill]].)

The third step from political economy to economics was the introduction of [[marginalism]] and the proposition that economic actors made decisions based on [[Margin (economics)|margin]]s. For example, a person decides to buy a second sandwich based on how full they are after the first one, a firm hires a new employee based on the expected increase in profits the employee will bring. This differs from the aggregate decision making of classical political economy in that it explains how vital goods such as water can be cheap, while luxuries can be expensive.

==The Marginal Revolution==

Neoclassical economics is frequently dated from [[William Stanley Jevons]]'s ''Theory of Political Economy'' (1871), [[Carl Menger]]'s ''Principles of Economics'' (1871), and [[Léon Walras]]'s ''Elements of Pure Economics'' (1874–1877). These three economists have been said to have begun &quot;the Marginal Revolution&quot;. Historians of economics and economists  have debated:

* Whether [[utility]] or marginalism was more essential to this revolution (whether the noun or the adjective in the phrase &quot;marginal utility&quot; is more important)

* Whether there was a revolutionary change of thought or merely a gradual development and change of emphasis from their predecessors

* Whether grouping these economists together disguises differences more important than their similarities.&lt;ref name=&quot;William Jaffé 1976&quot;&gt;William Jaffé (1976) &quot;Menger, Jevons, and Walras De-Homogenized&quot;, ''Economic Inquiry'', V. 14 (December): 511-525&lt;/ref&gt;

In particular, Jevons saw his economics as an application and development of [[Jeremy Bentham]]'s utilitarianism and never had a fully developed [[general equilibrium theory]]. Menger did not embrace this hedonic conception, explained diminishing marginal utility in terms of subjective prioritization of possible uses, and emphasized disequilibrium and the discrete; further Menger had an objection to the use of mathematics in economics, while the other two modeled their theories after 19th century mechanics.&lt;ref&gt;Philip Mirowski (1989) ''More Heat than Light: Economics as Social Physics, Physics as Nature's Economics'', Cambridge University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;  Walras' conception of utility, like that of Menger, was that of ''usefulness'' in general,&lt;ref&gt;Philip Mirowski (1989) ''More Heat than Light: Economics as Social Physics, Physics as Nature's Economics'', Cambridge University Press, p 234-5.&lt;/ref&gt; rather than the hedonic conception of Bentham or of Mill; and Walras was more interested in the interaction of markets than in explaining the individual psyche.&lt;ref name=&quot;William Jaffé 1976&quot;/&gt;

[[Alfred Marshall]]'s textbook, ''Principles of Economics'' (1890), was the dominant textbook in England a generation later. Marshall's influence extended elsewhere; Italians would compliment [[Maffeo Pantaleoni]] by calling him the &quot;Marshall of Italy&quot;. Marshall thought [[classical economics]] attempted to explain prices by the [[cost of production theory of value|cost of production]]. He asserted that earlier marginalists went too far in correcting this imbalance by overemphasizing utility and demand. Marshall thought that &quot;We might as reasonably dispute whether it is the upper
or the under blade of a pair of scissors that cuts a piece of
paper, as whether value is governed by utility or cost of
production&quot;.

Marshall explained price by the intersection of supply and demand curves. The introduction of different market &quot;periods&quot; was an important innovation of Marshall’s:
*Market period. The goods produced for sale on the market are taken as given data, e.g. in a fish market. Prices quickly adjust to clear markets.
*Short period. Industrial capacity is taken as given. The level of output, the level of employment, the inputs of raw materials, and prices fluctuate to equate [[marginal cost]] and [[marginal revenue]], where profits are maximized. [[Economic rent]]s exist in short period equilibrium for fixed factors, and the rate of profit is not equated across sectors.
*Long period. The stock of [[capital (economics)|capital]] goods, such as factories and machines, is not taken as given. Profit-maximizing equilibria determine both industrial capacity and the level at which it is operated.
*Very long period. Technology, population trends, habits and customs are not taken as given, but allowed to vary in very long period models.
Marshall took supply and demand as stable functions and extended supply and demand explanations of prices to all runs. He argued supply was easier to vary in longer runs, and thus became a more important determinant of price in the very long run.

== Further developments ==
An important change in neoclassical economics occurred around 1933. [[Joan Robinson]] and [[Edward H. Chamberlin]], with the near simultaneous publication of their respective books, ''The Economics of Imperfect Competition'' (1933) and ''The Theory of Monopolistic Competition'' (1933), introduced models of [[imperfect competition]]. Theories of [[market form]]s and [[industrial organization]] grew out of this work. They also emphasized certain tools, such as the [[marginal revenue]] curve.

Joan Robinson's work on imperfect competition, at least, was a response to certain problems of Marshallian [[supply and demand|partial equilibrium]] theory highlighted by [[Piero Sraffa]]. Anglo-American economists also responded to these problems by turning towards [[general equilibrium]] theory, developed on the European continent by Walras and [[Vilfredo Pareto]]. [[J. R. Hicks]]'s ''[[Value and Capital]]'' (1939) was influential in introducing his English-speaking colleagues to these traditions. He, in turn, was influenced by the [[Austrian School]] economist [[Friedrich Hayek]]'s move to the [[London School of Economics]], where Hicks then studied.

These developments were accompanied by the introduction of new tools, such as [[indifference curve]]s and the theory of ordinal [[utility]]. The level of mathematical sophistication of neoclassical economics increased. [[Paul Samuelson]]'s ''[[Foundations of Economic Analysis]]'' (1947) contributed to this increase in mathematical modelling.

The interwar period in American economics has been argued to have been pluralistic, with neoclassical economics and [[institutional economics|institutionalism]] competing for allegiance. [[Frank Knight]], an early [[Chicago school (economics)|Chicago school]] economist attempted to combine both schools. But this increase in mathematics was accompanied by greater dominance of neoclassical economics in Anglo-American universities after World War II.

Hicks' book, ''[[Value and Capital]]'' had two main parts. The second, which was arguably not immediately influential, presented a model of temporary equilibrium. Hicks was influenced directly by Hayek's notion of intertemporal coordination and paralleled by earlier work by Lindhal. This was part of an abandonment of disaggregated long run models. This trend probably reached its culmination with the [[Arrow-Debreu model]] of [[intertemporal equilibrium]]. The Arrow-Debreu model has canonical presentations in Gérard Debreu's ''Theory of Value'' (1959) and in Arrow and Hahn's &quot;General Competitive Analysis&quot; (1971).

Many of these developments were against the backdrop of improvements in both [[econometrics]], that is the ability to measure prices and changes in goods and services, as well as their aggregate quantities, and in the creation of [[macroeconomics]], or the study of whole economies. The attempt to combine neo-classical microeconomics and [[Keynesian economics|Keynesian]] macroeconomics would lead to the [[neoclassical synthesis]]&lt;ref&gt;Olivier Jean Blanchard (1987). &quot;neoclassical synthesis&quot;, ''The [[New Palgrave: A Dictionary of Economics]]'', v. 3, pp.  634-36.&lt;/ref&gt; which has been the dominant paradigm of economic reasoning in English-speaking countries since the 1950s. Hicks and Samuelson were for example instrumental in mainstreaming Keynesian economics.

Macroeconomics influenced the neoclassical synthesis from the other direction, undermining foundations of classical economic theory such as [[Say's Law]], and assumptions about [[political economy]] such as the necessity for a hard-money standard. These developments are reflected in neoclassical theory by the search for the occurrence in markets of the equilibrium conditions of [[Pareto optimality]] and self-sustainability.

== Criticisms ==
{{main|Criticisms of neoclassical economics}}

Neoclassical economics is sometimes criticized for having a [[Normative economics|normative]] bias. In this view, it does not focus on explaining actual economies, but instead on describing a &quot;utopia&quot; in which [[Pareto efficiency|Pareto optimality]] applies.

The assumption that individuals act rationally may be viewed as ignoring important aspects of human behavior. Many see the &quot;[[Homo economicus|economic man]]&quot; as being quite different from real people. Many economists, even contemporaries, have criticized this model of economic man. [[Thorstein Veblen]] put it most sardonically. Neoclassical economics assumes a person to be,

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;a lightning calculator of pleasures and pains, who oscillates like a homogeneous globule of desire of happiness under the impulse of stimuli that shift about the area, but leave him intact.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Thorstein Veblen]] (1898) ''Why Is Economics Not an Evolutionary Science?'', reprinted in The Place of Science in Modern Civilization (New York, 1919), p. 73.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Large corporations might perhaps come closer to the neoclassical ideal of profit maximization, but this is not necessarily viewed as desirable if this comes at the expense of neglect of wider social issues. The response to this is that neoclassical economics is descriptive and not normative. It addresses such problems with concepts of private versus social utility.

Problems exist with making the neoclassical [[general equilibrium]] theory compatible with an economy that develops over time and includes capital goods.  This was explored in a major debate in the 1960s—the &quot;[[Cambridge capital controversy]]&quot;—about the validity of neoclassical economics, with an emphasis on the [[economic growth]], [[capital (economics)|capital]], aggregate theory, and the [[marginal productivity theory]] of distribution. There were also internal attempts by neoclassical economists to extend the Arrow-Debreu model to disequilibrium investigations of stability and uniqueness.  However a result known as the [[Sonnenschein-Mantel-Debreu theorem]] suggests that the assumptions that must be made to ensure that the equilibrium is stable and unique are quite restrictive.

Neoclassical economics is also often seen as relying too heavily on complex mathematical models, such as those used in [[general equilibrium]] theory, without enough regard to whether these actually describe the real economy. Many see an attempt to model a system as complex as a modern economy by a mathematical model as unrealistic and doomed to failure. A famous answer to this criticism is [[Milton Friedman]]'s claim that theories should be judged by their ability to predict events rather than by the realism of their assumptions.&lt;ref&gt;Friedman argued for this in essays III, IV and V in &quot;Essays in Positive Economics&quot;. http://www.econ.umn.edu/~schwe227/teaching.s11/files/articles/friedman-1953.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; Mathematical models also include those in [[game theory]], [[linear programming]], and [[econometrics]]. Critics of neoclassical economics are divided into those who think that highly mathematical method is inherently wrong and those who think that mathematical method is potentially good even if contemporary methods have problems.

In general, allegedly overly unrealistic assumptions are one of the most common criticisms towards neoclassical economics. It is fair to say that many (but not all) of these criticisms can only be directed towards a subset of the neoclassical models (for example, there are many neoclassical models where unregulated markets fail to achieve Pareto-optimality and there has recently been an increased interest in modeling non-rational decision making).

== See also ==
*[[Marginalism]]
*[[Microeconomics]]
*[[Neo-classical synthesis]]
*[[Static equilibrium (economics)]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.econlib.org/library/Enc/NeoclassicalEconomics.html Neoclassical economics] from the Concise Library of Economics
*[http://william-king.www.drexel.edu/top/prin/txt/Neoch/Eco111s1.html Introduction to neoclassical economics] at Drexel

{{Neoclassical economists}}

{{ History of economic thought}}

[[Category:Economic theories]]

[[be-x-old:Нэаклясычная школа эканамічнай думкі]]
[[bg:Неокласически икономикс]]
[[ca:Economia neoclàssica]]
[[cs:Neoklasická ekonomie]]
[[de:Neoklassische Theorie]]
[[et:Neoklassikaline koolkond]]
[[es:Economía neoclásica]]
[[eo:Neoklasika ekonomika skolo]]
[[eu:Ekonomia neoklasiko]]
[[fr:École néoclassique]]
[[ko:신고전파 경제학]]
[[id:Ekonomi neo-klasik]]
[[it:Economia neoclassica]]
[[he:כלכלה נאו-קלאסית]]
[[hu:Neoklasszikus közgazdaságtan]]
[[nl:Neoklassieke theorie]]
[[ja:新古典派経済学]]
[[no:Nyklassisk økonomi]]
[[pl:Ekonomia neoklasyczna]]
[[pt:Economia neoclássica]]
[[ru:Неоклассическая экономическая теория]]
[[simple:Neoclassical economics]]
[[sk:Neoklasická ekonómia]]
[[sr:Неокласична политичка економија]]
[[fi:Uusklassinen taloustiede]]
[[sv:Neoklassisk nationalekonomi]]
[[vi:Kinh tế học tân cổ điển]]
[[zh:新古典主義經濟學]]</text>
      <sha1>dy1hw793agr1besmexc0ustjshg1gsw</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
