<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Parable of the broken window</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>157267</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522277936</id>
      <parentid>521036706</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T03:35:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>FrescoBot</username>
        <id>9021902</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Bot: [[User:FrescoBot/Links|link syntax/spacing]] and minor changes</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27803">{{About|the economic parable|the criminological theory|Broken windows theory}}
{{Essay-like|date=July 2011}}

The '''parable of the broken window''' was introduced by [[Frédéric Bastiat]] in his 1850 essay ''{{lang|fr|Ce qu'on voit et ce qu'on ne voit pas}}'' (''[[s:That Which Is Seen, and That Which Is Not Seen|That Which Is Seen and That Which Is Unseen]]'') to illustrate why destruction, and the money spent to recover from destruction, is actually not a net-benefit to society. The [[parable]], also known as the '''broken window fallacy''' or '''glazier's fallacy''', demonstrates how [[opportunity costs]], as well as the [[Unintended consequences|law of unintended consequences]], affect economic activity in ways that are &quot;unseen&quot; or ignored.

==The parable==

Bastiat's original parable of the broken window from ''Ce qu'on voit et ce qu'on ne voit pas'' (1850):

{{quote|
Have you ever witnessed the anger of the good shopkeeper, James Goodfellow, when his careless son has happened to break a pane of glass? If you have been present at such a scene, you will most assuredly bear witness to the fact that every one of the spectators, were there even thirty of them, by common consent apparently, offered the unfortunate owner this invariable consolation—&quot;It is an ill wind that blows nobody good. Everybody must live, and what would become of the glaziers if panes of glass were never broken?&quot;

Now, this form of condolence contains an entire theory, which it will be well to show up in this simple case, seeing that it is precisely the same as that which, unhappily, regulates the greater part of our economical institutions.

Suppose it cost six francs to repair the damage, and you say that the accident brings six francs to the glazier's trade—that it encourages that trade to the amount of six francs—I grant it; I have not a word to say against it; you reason justly. The glazier comes, performs his task, receives his six francs, rubs his hands, and, in his heart, blesses the careless child. All this is that which is seen.

But if, on the other hand, you come to the conclusion, as is too often the case, that it is a good thing to break windows, that it causes money to circulate, and that the encouragement of industry in general will be the result of it, you will oblige me to call out, &quot;Stop there! Your theory is confined to that which is seen; it takes no account of that which is not seen.&quot;

It is not seen that as our shopkeeper has spent six francs upon one thing, he cannot spend them upon another. It is not seen that if he had not had a window to replace, he would, perhaps, have replaced his old shoes, or added another book to his library. In short, he would have employed his six francs in some way, which this accident has prevented.''&lt;ref name=&quot;Bastiat-en&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Bastiat |first1=Frédéric |authorlink1=Frédéric Bastiat |others=translated by Patrick James Stirling |title=That Which Is Seen, and That Which Is Not Seen |url=http://en.wikisource.org/wiki/That_Which_Is_Seen,_and_That_Which_Is_Not_Seen |accessdate=2009-06-07 |year=1850}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bastiat-fr&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Bastiat |first1=Frédéric |authorlink1=Frédéric Bastiat |title=Ce qu'on voit et ce qu'on ne voit pas |url=http://fr.wikisource.org/wiki/Ce_qu'on_voit_et_ce_qu'on_ne_voit_pas |accessdate=2009-06-07 |month= |year=1850 |language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==Differing interpretations==

The implications of the fallacy can also be extended to the glazier. The onlookers assume that this needed window will have a positive effect for the glazier, but in order for this to be true, the glazier must currently have time and supplies available for use. If the glazier has other jobs which demand his time and supplies, this additional job now represents a negative constraint for the glazier in that he may not be able to complete his other jobs on time.

In this case, the broken window (and the boy who broke it) did not provide any net benefit to the town, but rather made the town poorer in future benefits by (at least) the value of one window.

===Bastiat's argument===
[[Austrian School|Austrian theorists]], and Bastiat himself, apply the parable of the broken window in a different way. Suppose it was discovered that the little boy was actually hired by the glazier, and paid a franc for every window he broke. Suddenly the same act would be regarded as theft: the glazier was breaking windows in order to force people to hire his services. Yet the facts observed by the onlookers remain true: the glazier benefits from the business at the expense of the baker, the tailor, and so on.

Bastiat argues that people actually do endorse activities which are morally equivalent to the glazier hiring a boy to break windows for him:
{{quote|Whence we arrive at this unexpected conclusion: &quot;Society loses the value of things which are uselessly destroyed;&quot; and we must assent to a maxim which will make the hair of protectionists stand on end—To break, to spoil, to waste, is not to encourage national labour; or, more briefly, &quot;destruction is not profit.&quot;

What will you say, ''Moniteur Industriel''&lt;ref&gt;''Le Moniteur Industriel'' was a famous protectionist journal.&lt;/ref&gt;—what will you say, disciples of good M. F. Chamans, who has calculated with so much precision how much trade would gain by the burning of Paris, from the number of houses it would be necessary to rebuild?&lt;ref name=&quot;Bastiat-en&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bastiat-fr&quot;/&gt;
}}

Bastiat is not addressing production&amp;nbsp;— he is addressing the stock of wealth. In other words, Bastiat does not merely look at the immediate but at the longer effects of breaking the window. Moreover, Bastiat does not only take into account the consequences of breaking the window for one group but for all groups, for society as a whole.&lt;ref&gt;Chapter two of 'Economics in one lesson' by Henry Hazlitt&lt;/ref&gt;

Theorists of the [[Austrian School]] frequently cite this fallacy and claim that it is a common element of popular thinking (e.g., the [[Car Allowance Rebate System#Economic effects|&quot;Cash for Clunkers&quot;]] program,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=newsarchive&amp;sid=aBHGhk3_aakc &quot;Cash for Clunkers Is Just a Broken Windshield&quot;], Caroline Baum, [[Bloomberg L.P.|Bloomberg.com]], August 4, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; etc.). The 20th century American economist [[Henry Hazlitt]] devoted a chapter to it in his book ''[[Economics in One Lesson]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hazlitt_broken_window&quot;&gt;[[Henry Hazlitt]]. [http://jim.com/econ/preface.html &quot;Preface&quot;], ''[[Economics in One Lesson]]'', online version, referenced 2009-05-15.&lt;/ref&gt;

===The opportunity cost of war===
{{See also|Military Keynesianism}}
{{Unreferenced section|date=March 2008}}
The argument can be made that [[war]] is a benefactor, since historically it often has focused the use of resources and triggered advances in technology and other areas while reducing unemployment. The increased production and employment [[war economy|associated with war]] often leads some to claim that &quot;war is good for the economy.&quot; However, this belief is often given as an example of the broken window fallacy. The money spent on the war effort, for example, is money that cannot be spent on food, clothing, health care, consumer electronics or other areas. The stimulus felt in one sector of the economy comes at a direct—but hidden—cost to other sectors.

Bastiat himself argued against the claim that hiring men to be soldiers was inherently beneficial to the economy in the second chapter of ''That Which is Seen, and That Which is Not Seen'', &quot;The Disbanding of Troops&quot;:

{{quote|
It is the same with a people as it is with a man. If it wishes to give itself some gratification, it naturally considers whether it is worth what it costs. To a nation, security is the greatest of advantages. If, in order to obtain it, it is necessary to have an army of a hundred thousand men, I have nothing to say against it. It is an enjoyment bought by a sacrifice. Let me not be misunderstood upon the extent of my position. A member of the assembly proposes to disband a hundred thousand men, for the sake of relieving the tax-payers of a hundred millions.

If we confine ourselves to this answer - &quot;The hundred thousand men, and these hundred millions of money, are indispensable to the national security: it is a sacrifice; but without this sacrifice, France would be torn by factions, or invaded by some foreign power,&quot; - I have nothing to object to this argument, which may be true or false in fact, but which theoretically contains nothing which militates against economy. The error begins when the sacrifice itself is said to be an advantage because it profits somebody.

Now I am very much mistaken if, the moment the author of the proposal has taken his seat, some orator will not rise and say - &quot;Disband a hundred thousand men! Do you know what you are saying? What will become of them? Where will they get a living? Don't you know that work is scarce everywhere? That every field is overstocked? Would you turn them out of doors to increase competition, and weigh upon the rate of wages? Just now, when it is a hard matter to live at all, it would be a pretty thing if the State must find bread for a hundred thousand individuals? Consider, besides, that the army consumes wine, clothing, arms&amp;nbsp;— that it promotes the activity of manufactures in garrison towns&amp;nbsp;— that it is, in short, the god-send of innumerable purveyors. Why, any one must tremble at the bare idea of doing away with this immense industrial movement.&quot;

This discourse, it is evident, concludes by voting the maintenance of a hundred thousand soldiers, for reasons drawn from the necessity of the service, and from economical considerations. It is these considerations only that I have to refute.

A hundred thousand men, costing the tax-payers a hundred millions of money, live and bring to the purveyors as much as a hundred millions can supply. This is that which is seen.

But, a hundred millions taken from the pockets of the tax-payers, cease to maintain these taxpayers and the purveyors, as far as a hundred millions reach. This is that which is not seen. Now make your calculations. Cast up, and tell me what profit there is for the masses?
}}

In addition, war destroys property and lives. The economic stimulus to one nation's [[defense industry|defense]] sector is offset not only by immediate [[opportunity costs]], but also by the costs of the damage and devastation of war to the country it attacks. This forms the basis of a second application of the broken window fallacy: rebuilding what war destroys stimulates the economy, particularly the construction sector. However, immense resources are spent merely to restore pre-war conditions. After a war, there is only a rebuilt city. Without a war, there are opportunities for the same resources to be applied to more fruitful purposes. Instead of rebuilding a destroyed city, the resources could have been used to improve and enlarge the city or build a second one.

One example of the costs of war sometimes given is the many projects postponed or not started until after the end of [[World War II]] in the [[United States]]. The pent-up demand for roads, bridges, houses, cars, and even radios led to massive inflation in the late 1940s.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}} The war delayed the commercial introduction of [[television]], among other things, and the resources sent overseas to rebuild the rest of the world after the war were not available to the American people for their direct benefit; neither did the war enrich any of these other nations.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

According to Hazlitt: {{quote|&quot;It is never an advantage to have one’s plants destroyed by shells or bombs unless those plants have already become valueless or acquired a negative value by depreciation and obsolescence. ... Plants and equipment cannot be replaced by an individual (or a socialist government) unless he or it has acquired or can acquire the savings, the capital accumulation, to make the replacement. But war destroys accumulated capital. ... Complications should not divert us from recognizing the basic truth that the wanton destruction of anything of real value is always a net loss, a misfortune, or a disaster, and whatever the offsetting considerations in a particular instance, can never be, on net balance, a boon or a blessing.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hazlitt_war&quot;&gt;[[Henry Hazlitt]]. [http://jim.com/econ/chap03p1.html &quot;The Blessings of Destruction&quot;], ''[[Economics in One Lesson]]'', online version, referenced 2009-05-15.&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

===The cost of special interests and government===
Bastiat, Hazlitt, and others equated the glazier with [[special interest]]s, and the little boy with government. Special interests request money from the government (in the form of subsidies, grants, etc.), and the government then forces the taxpayer to provide the funds. The recipients certainly do benefit, so the government action is often regarded by the people as benefiting everyone. But the people are failing to consider the hidden costs: the taxpayers are now poorer by exactly that much money. The food, clothing or other items they might have purchased with that money will now not be purchased—but since there is no way to count &quot;non-purchases,&quot; this is a [[hidden cost]], sometimes called [[opportunity cost]]. Bastiat referred to this in his essay as &quot;what is not seen&quot;. Because the costs are hidden, there is an illusion that the benefits cost nothing. Hazlitt summarized the principle by saying, &quot;Everything we get, outside the free gifts of nature, must in some way be paid for.&quot; [[Robert A. Heinlein]] popularized a summarization/acronym of the concept called &quot;[[TANSTAAFL]]&quot; (''There Ain't No Such Thing As A Free Lunch'').

Common examples of special interest groups practicing the broken window fallacy might be:
* Arguments for [[public works]] projects as a way to reduce unemployment. The hidden cost here is of course the tax payer's money, and the special interests are the jobs created by the public works. This is analogous to the fallacy only if in fact the taxation induces opportunity costs and a net social loss, yet public works are not inherently destructive and need not involve demolition for the sake of superflous rebuilding (i.e., intentionally breaking windows). Public works often are genuinely new and additive to shared societal value, independent of any benefits of maintaining a pool of skilled glaziers or other workers.
* [[Car Allowance Rebate System|Cash for Clunkers]] which was a program in which the U.S. government paid consumers to trade in antiquated low gas mileage cars for newer, more efficient higher gas mileage cars, and the trade-ins were subsequently destroyed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=20601039&amp;sid=aBHGhk3_aakc Cash for Clunkers Is Just a Broken Windshield], [[Caroline Baum]], ''Bloomberg News'', August 4, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;  A similar program allows for trade-ins of old energy inefficient appliances for more energy efficient appliances. Such programs may be viewed as imposing a net cost only if failing to account for the benefits of expending fewer units of fuel per mile, and the potential added value of decreased pollution. However, the pollution from, and the costs of, the yearly manufacturing of a new fleet of vehicles may outweigh any perceived gains from the improvements in gas mileage.
* [[Depreciation (currency)|Depreciation]] as a means to increase exports by making goods less expensive to foreigners, and to decrease the demand for imports—which are made more expensive—in order to stimulate the domestic economy.  What is not seen is the fact that domestic workers must do more work for less pay, and can purchase less with the proceeds.  Essentially, the entire nation takes a pay cut.
* [[Inflation]] as a means to stimulate economic activity by making savings worth less and goods worth more, creating an imperative to purchase sooner rather than waiting.  What is not seen is the increased risk of no cushion of savings, the stimulation of large amounts of [[consumer debt]], and the loss of [[purchasing power]] due to salaries lagging inflation.
* [[Planned obsolescence]], an item designed to break or become undesirable after some period of time.
* Advertisements promoting the replacement of old items with new items; for example, replacing last year's fashions with this year's.

With all of these examples, care must be taken that every factor is taken into account, just as happened in the parable of the broken window: does one know all the costs and benefits? E.g. hiring people to do nothing or to break things and repair them is probably a bad idea. This is the case in the military spending and government employment examples. But if the hired people or the spent money actually result in useful work (however, the term &quot;useful work&quot; is a fallacy in itself&amp;nbsp;— it is not the work that is useful but only the product or result produced by the work), things are less clear. It depends on the amount of useful work delivered compared to the amount of money spent if the spending was a good idea. This is the case in the cash for clunkers, the public works, and the renewable energy examples.  This analysis is only necessary, however, when the accomplished result has a future benefit beyond the simple fact of delivering work.  As Bastiat shows, the simple accomplishment of useful work can never make such projects a net positive; the glazier also performed useful work.  But if a project improves the efficiency of future work, there can be a net benefit.  For example, a public works program to build roads creates no wealth simply by virtue of building the road.  But in the future, that road may increase trade by improving the efficiency of moving goods and reducing future costs.  In such a case, the road may be a net benefit&amp;nbsp;— it is an investment, rather than destruction followed by redistribution.  The point of the broken window parable is to show that one cannot ignore the hidden costs of taking wealth to build the road when totalling up any such &quot;net benefit.&quot;

==Criticisms==
The interpretations assume that the &quot;window&quot; has positive value and {{refnec|text=that replacing it is not a good investment|date=November 2012}}.  In the broader scope, offsetting factors can reduce or even negate the cost of destruction.  For example, new technologies developed during a war and forced modernization during postwar reconstruction can cause old technologies to become valueless. Also, if two shopkeepers keep their &quot;window&quot; beyond the point where it would maximize their profit, the shopkeeper whose window is broken is forced to make a good investment - increasing his comparative profit, or rather, reducing his comparative loss. Regardless, while wanton destruction of real value may not be a net loss, it is of course still a misfortune, not a blessing.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | title = Economics in One Lesson: The Shortest and Surest Way to Understand Basic Economics | isbn = 9780517548233 | last1 = Hazlitt | first1 = Henry | year = 1988 | page = 30}}&lt;/ref&gt; Others argue that the broken window may not lead to reduction in spending by the victim, but rather, a reduction in excessive savings.&lt;ref&gt;[http://seekingalpha.com/article/113821-in-case-of-emergency-break-glass In Case of Emergency, Break Glass], Andy Harless, ''Seeking Alpha''{{self-published inline|date=September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;The logic of limited resources only applies when the economy is using most of those limited resources. If there are slack resources, we need merely mobilize some of the slack resources.&quot; The ''[[reductio ad absurdum]]'' of breaking 100 windows, then, only applies once underutilised resources have run out, and the tailor is forced to divert resources from more productive means.

Another problem with this being a &quot;fallacy&quot; is that the positive and negative results depend on the financial condition and disposition of the victim.  At the low end, the victim simply can't afford to replace the window, or refuses to do so, resulting in almost no economic effect.  In the medium range, it is a fallacy and the standard argument above applies. However, {{refnec|text=at the top end it is an economic benefit|date=November 2012}}, especially if too much capital is trapped in high end savings and investment, because the funds used to replace the window will not change the victim's spending habits, but will simply be a minor reduction of his long term savings or investments, or that of his insurer.

It has been argued that the 'parable', while intuitive, does not correspond to actual evidence. For instance, researchers have found that natural disasters can often lead to improved growth in both the short and long term.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1093/ei/40.4.664 |title=Do Natural Disasters Promote Long-Run Growth? |year=2002 |last1=Skidmore |first1=Mark |last2=Toya |first2=Hideki |journal=Economic Inquiry |volume=40 |issue=4 |pages=664–87}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Defenses===
Bastiat and Austrian theorists hold to a [[subjective theory of value]], which holds that the value of a product is determined by its consumer or owner. Therefore, if the window had a negative value, it is because the owner already wishes it broken. If the proverbial window were old, and the newer proverbial window had a greater value (determined by the shopkeeper's own valuation), then the net increase in value in the economy is the difference between the value of the old and new window. Bastiat and Austrian economists also believe that depreciation and other losses in the value of goods reduces the net value in the economy by the amount of the reduction in value of the goods.{{citation needed|date=September 2012}}

The very concept of excess savings is meaningless without the presumption of an authority which can define the proper amount of savings.   Money saved represents demand for money which is a commodity like windows or suits. The result of spending saved money is to lower the demand for money relative to suits or glass and therefore contributes to general price inflation (or loss of purchasing power).  Such an authority would suggest that by controlling prices (forcing the exchange of savings for consumer goods), that the economy could be better off.  This concept when enforced by governments is known as [[Price control|price controls]] and results in shortages when prices are artificially reduced below market value.   A shortage of savings results in a reduction of capital investment as more resources are diverted from future needs to present needs.   The shop owner was saving so that he could grow his business, but an outside authority has determined that his savings were 'excess' and that by breaking his window the economy will be better off.  Without free exchange there would be no prices, and without prices there can be no economic calculation, and without proper economic calculation there is no means to determine whether or not a particular action will be 'profitable'.  Therefore any authority that suggests that there might be an 'excess of savings' presumes the ability to make economic calculations without prices established by free exchange. This was shown to be impossible in [http://mises.org/econcalc.asp Economic Calculation In The Socialist Commonwealth by Ludwig von Mises].

If there was more profit to be made by destroying buildings, windows or leveling an entire community due to a natural disaster then pursuing other courses of action then participants in the market would pro-actively and voluntarially destroy property.  It is quite clear that far more profit can be earned by recycling, selling, or repurposing an old window pane than could be achieved via random destruction by vandal or nature.  Therefore, arguments that propose that destruction 'might' be good for the economy have to presume that actors in the economy were missing an opportunity to profit in excess of the value of the goods destroyed.  The probability of random destruction being good for the economy is equal to the probability of random destruction being bad for the economy as both are equal to the probability that free exchange has not achieved the best allocation of resources.

==See also==
*[[Cobra effect]]
*[[Creative destruction]]
*[[Disaster capitalism]]
*[[Jevons paradox]]
*[[Spending multiplier]]
*[[Tax choice]]
*[[Uneconomic growth]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite journal |doi=10.2202/1553-3832.1638 |title=Is CARS a Clunker? |year=2009 |last1=Abrams |first1=Burton A |last2=Parsons |first2=George R |journal=The Economists' Voice |volume=6 |issue=8}}
*{{cite journal |first1=Robert W. |last1=McGee |year=2010 |title= Financial Bailouts and the philosophy of Frédéric Bastiat |journal=Aestimatio |issue=1 |pages=88–97 |url=http://dialnet.unirioja.es/servlet/articulo?codigo=3807818}}
*{{cite journal |doi=10.1108/03068290810886885 |title=The broken trailer fallacy: Seeing the unseen effects of government policies in post-Katrina New Orleans |year=2008 |last1=Stringham |first1=Edward P. |last2=Snow |first2=Nicholas A. |journal=International Journal of Social Economics |volume=35 |issue=7 |pages=480–9}}
*{{cite journal |first1=Louis |last1=Carabini |year=2007 |title=Bastiat's 'The Broken Window': A Critique |url=http://mises.org/journals/jls/21_4/21_4_11.pdf |journal=Journal of Libertarian Studies |volume=21 |issue=4 |pages=151–5}}
*{{cite journal |doi=10.2139/ssrn.1670759 |title=The Effects of Fiscal Stimulus: Evidence from the 2009 'Cash for Clunkers' Program |year=2010 |last1=Mian |first1=Atif R. |last2=Sufi |first2=Amir |journal=SSRN Electronic Journal}}
*{{cite journal |doi=10.1080/0953825042000313825 |title=Mises, bastiat, public opinion, and public choice |year=2005 |last1=Caplan |first1=Bryan |last2=Stringham |first2=Edward |journal=Review of Political Economy |volume=17 |pages=79–105}}
*{{cite journal |doi=10.1111/j.1468-0270.2010.02022.x |title=The Broken University: What is Seen and What is Not Seen in the Uk Higher Education Sector |year=2010 |last1=Stanfield |first1=James |journal=Economic Affairs |volume=30 |issue=3 |pages=53–8}}
*{{cite journal |doi=10.1093/ei/40.4.664 |title=Do Natural Disasters Promote Long-Run Growth? |year=2002 |last1=Skidmore |first1=Mark |last2=Toya |first2=Hideki |journal=Economic Inquiry |volume=40 |issue=4 |pages=664–87}}
*{{cite book |first1=Bo |last1=Bennett |year=2012 |chapter=Broken Window Fallacy |chapterurl=http://books.google.com/books?id=WFvhN9lSm5gC&amp;pg=PT83 |pages=83–4 |title=Logically Fallacious: The Ultimate Collection of Over 300 Logical Fallacies |publisher=K. Wills |location=Fishers, Indiana |isbn=978-1-4566-0737-1}}

==External links==
{{wikisource|That Which Is Seen, and That Which Is Not Seen}}
* [http://bastiat.org/fr/cqovecqonvp.html &quot;Ce qu'on voit et ce qu'on ne voit pas&quot;] (original essay)
* [http://bastiat.org/en/twisatwins.html &quot;That Which is Seen and That Which is Not Seen&quot;] (English translation)

{{unintended consequences}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Parable Of The Broken Window}}
[[Category:Classical liberalism]]
[[Category:Economics models]]
[[Category:Libertarian theory]]
[[Category:Parables]]
[[Category:Windows]]

[[ca:Paràbola del vidre trencat]]
[[cs:Klam rozbitého okna]]
[[de:Parabel vom zerbrochenen Fenster]]
[[es:Parábola del cristal roto]]
[[fr:Sophisme de la vitre cassée]]
[[it:Racconto della finestra rotta]]
[[lt:Išmušto stiklo metafora]]
[[nl:Parabel van de gebroken ruit]]
[[pl:Metafora zbitej szyby]]
[[pt:Parable of the broken window]]
[[ru:Метафора о разбитом окне]]
[[sk:Klam rozbitého okna]]
[[fi:Rikotun ikkunan ongelma]]
[[uk:Метафора про розбите вікно]]</text>
      <sha1>8td0sma60xq4h388rvpsfnz4lbl4cij</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
