<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Poverty threshold</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>170584</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521911598</id>
      <parentid>520164965</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-08T00:07:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Professortimithy</username>
        <id>7474607</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18584">{{About||the term as defined in the United States|Poverty thresholds (United States)}}
[[File:Percentage population living on less than $1.25 per day 2009.svg|thumb|right|300px|Percentage of population living on less than $1.25 per day. [[UN]] estimates 2000-2007.]]

The '''poverty threshold''', or '''poverty line''', is the minimum level of [[income]] deemed adequate in a given country.&lt;ref&gt;Ravallion, Martin ''Poverty freak: A Guide to Concepts and Methods''. Living Standards Measurement Papers, The World Bank, 1992, p. 25&lt;/ref&gt; In practice, like the definition of [[poverty]], the official or common understanding of the poverty line is significantly higher in [[developed countries]] than in [[developing countries]].&lt;ref&gt;Hagenaars, Aldi &amp; de Vos, Klaas ''The Definition and Measurement of Poverty''. Journal of Human Resources, 1988&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hagenaars, Aldi &amp; van Praag, Bernard ''A Synthesis of Poverty Line Definitions''. Review of Income and Wealth, 1985&lt;/ref&gt;

The common '''international poverty line''' has in the past been roughly $1 a day.&lt;ref&gt; Sachs, Jeffrey D. ''The End of Poverty'' 2005, p. 20&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, the [[World Bank]] came out with a revised figure of $1.25 at 2005 [[purchasing-power parity]] (PPP).&lt;ref&gt; Ravallion, Martin; Chen Shaohua &amp; Sangraula, Prem ''Dollar a day'' The World Bank Economic Review, 23, 2, 2009, pp. 163-184&lt;/ref&gt;

Determining the poverty line is usually done by finding the total cost of all the essential resources that an average human adult consumes in one year.&lt;ref name=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;{Poverty Lines-Martin Ravallion, in The New Palgrave Dictionary of Economics, 2nd Edition, London: Palgrave Macmillan}&lt;/ref&gt; The largest of these expenses is typically the [[renting|rent]] required to live in an apartment, so historically, economists have paid particular attention to the real estate market and housing prices as a strong poverty line affector.

Individual factors are often used to account for various circumstances, such as whether one is a parent, elderly, a child, married, etc. The poverty threshold may be adjusted annually.

==Absolute poverty==
Absolute poverty is a level of poverty as defined in terms of the minimal requirements necessary to afford minimal standards of food, clothing, health care and shelter.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dictionary.babylon.com/absolute%20poverty/ |title=Absolute poverty definition by Babylon’s free dictionary |publisher=Dictionary.babylon.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; For the measure to be absolute, the line must be the same in different countries, cultures, and technological levels. Such an absolute measure should look only at the individual's power to consume and it should be independent of any changes in income distribution. The intuition behind an absolute measure is that mere survival takes essentially the same amount of resources across the world and that everybody should be subject to the same standards if meaningful comparisons of policies and progress are to be made. Notice that if everyone's real income in an economy increases, and the [[income distribution]] does not change, absolute poverty will decline.

Measuring poverty by an absolute threshold has the advantage of applying the same standard across different locations and time periods, it makes comparisons easier. On the other hand, it suffers from the disadvantage that any absolute poverty threshold is to some extent arbitrary; the amount of wealth required for survival is not the same in all places and time periods. For example, a person living in far northern Scandinavia requires a source of heat during colder months, while a person living on a tropical island does not.

This type of measure is often contrasted with measures of relative poverty (see below), which classify individuals or families as &quot;poor&quot; not by comparing them to a fixed cutoff point, but by comparing them to others in the population under study.

The term ''absolute poverty'' is also sometimes used as a synonym for [[extreme poverty]]. Absolute poverty is the absence of enough resources (such as money) to secure basic life necessities.

According to a UN declaration that resulted from the [[Commission for Social Development|World Summit on Social Development]] in Copenhagen in 1995, absolute poverty is &quot;a condition characterised by severe deprivation of basic human needs, including food, safe drinking water, sanitation facilities, health, shelter, education and information. It depends not only on income but also on access to services.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Indicators of Poverty and Hunger&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.un.org/esa/socdev/unyin/documents/ydiDavidGordon_poverty.pdf |title=Indicators of Poverty and Hunger|accessdate=2008-02-14 |work=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

David Gordon's paper, &quot;Indicators of Poverty &amp; Hunger&quot;, for the United Nations, further defines absolute poverty as the absence of any two of the following eight basic needs:&lt;ref name=&quot;Indicators of Poverty and Hunger&quot;/&gt;

* ''Food:'' [[Body Mass Index]] must be above 16.
* ''Safe drinking water:'' Water must not come solely from rivers and ponds, and must be available nearby (less than 15 minutes' walk each way).
* ''Sanitation facilities:'' Toilets or [[latrine]]s must be accessible in or near the home.
* ''Health:'' Treatment must be received for serious illnesses and pregnancy.
* ''Shelter:'' Homes must have fewer than four people living in each room. Floors must not be made of dirt, mud, or clay.
* ''Education:'' Everyone must attend school or otherwise learn to read.
* ''Information:'' Everyone must have access to newspapers, radios, televisions, computers, or telephones at home.
* ''Access to services:'' This item is undefined by Gordon, but normally is used to indicate the complete panoply of education, health, legal, social, and financial ([[credit (finance)|credit]]) services.

For example, a person who lives in a home with a mud floor is considered severely deprived of shelter. A person who never attended school and cannot read is considered severely deprived of education. A person who has no newspaper, radio, television, or telephone is considered severely deprived of information. All people who meet any two of these conditions&amp;nbsp;— for example, they live in homes with mud floors ''and'' cannot read&amp;nbsp;— are considered to be living in absolute poverty.

==Relative poverty==
{{citations missing|section|date=June 2012}}
:{{See also|Income inequality|Relative deprivation}}
A measure of ''relative poverty'' defines &quot;poverty&quot; as being below some relative poverty threshold. For example, the statement that &quot;households with an accumulated income less than 60% of the median equivalized household disposable income are living in poverty&quot; uses a relative measure to define poverty. In this system, if everyone's real income in an economy increases, but the [[income distribution]] stays the same, then the rate of relative poverty will also stay the same.

This means, by its very nature, that there will always be a family living in (relative) poverty, even if they have a very high living standard, unless everyone has almost exactly the same income.

Relative poverty measurements can sometimes produce odd results, especially in small populations. For example, if the [[median]] household in a wealthy neighborhood earns US$1 million each year, then a family that earns US$100,000 would be considered poor on the relative poverty scale, even though such a family could meet all of its basic needs and much more. At the other end of the scale, if the median household in a very poor neighborhood earned only 50% of what it needs to buy food, then a person who earned the median income would not be considered poor on a relative poverty scale, even though the person is clearly poor on an absolute poverty scale.

Measures of relative poverty are almost the same as measuring [[income inequality]]: If a society gets a more equal income distribution, relative poverty will fall. They point out that if society changed in a way that hurt high earners more than low ones, then relative poverty would decrease, but every citizen of the society would be worse off. Likewise in the reverse direction: it is possible to reduce absolute poverty while increasing relative poverty.

The term ''relative poverty'' can also be used in a different sense to mean &quot;moderate poverty&quot;&amp;nbsp;–- for example, a [[standard of living]] or level of income that is high enough to satisfy basic needs (like [[water]], [[food]], [[clothing]], shelter, and basic [[health care]]), but still significantly lower than that of the majority of the population under consideration.

==Basic needs==
Some measurements combine certain aspects of absolute and relative measures. For example, the [[Fraser Institute]] publishes a [[basic needs]] poverty measure for [[Canada]]. According to the Fraser Institute, &quot;the basic-needs approach is partly absolute (the list [of necessities] is limited to items required for long-term physical well-being) and partly relative, reflecting the standards that apply in the individual's own society at the present time.&quot;&lt;ref name=BasicNeeds&gt;[http://www.fraserinstitute.org/COMMERCE.WEB/product_files/PovertyinCanada2006.pdf Poverty in Canada: 2006 Update], [[Fraser Institute]], November 2006, URL accessed 14 February 2008&lt;/ref&gt; The Fraser Institute's list of necessities for living creditably in Canada includes not only [[food]], shelter, [[clothing]], and [[health care]], but also [[Hygiene|personal care]], [[furniture]], [[transportation]], [[communication]], [[laundry]], and [[home insurance]]. It is criticized for not including any entertainment items like [[cable television]], daily newspapers, and tickets to movies or sporting events.&lt;ref name=BasicNeeds/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ccsd.ca/pubs/2001/povertypp.htm &quot;Defining and Re-Defining Poverty: A CCSD Perspective&quot;], October 2001, Canadian Council On Social Development&lt;/ref&gt;

==National poverty lines==
[[File:Percent poverty world map.png|300px|right|thumb|CIA World Factbook-based map showing the percentage of population by country living below that country's official poverty line.]]
National estimates are based on population-weighted subgroup estimates from household surveys. Definitions of the poverty line may vary considerably among nations. For example, rich nations generally employ more generous standards of poverty than poor nations. Thus, the numbers are not comparable among countries.

In 2010, in the United States, the poverty threshold for one person under 65 was US$11,344 (annual income); the threshold for a family group of four, including two children, was US$22,133.&lt;ref name=&quot;Poverty Thresholds 2010&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.census.gov/hhes/www/poverty/about/overview/measure.html |title=Poverty Thresholds 2010|accessdate=2012-02-05 |work=}} &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=How the Census Bureau Measures Poverty|url=http://www.census.gov/hhes/www/poverty/data/threshld/thresh09.xls|accessdate=22 December 2010|author=US Census Bureau}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the U.S. Census Bureau data released on September 13, 2011, the nation's poverty rate rose to 15.1 percent in 2010.

In the UK, &quot;more than five million people&amp;nbsp;– over a fifth (23 percent) of all employees&amp;nbsp;– were paid less than £6.67 an hour in April 2006. This is based on a low pay rate of 60 percent of full-time median earnings, equivalent to a little over £12,000 a year for a 35-hour working week. In April 2006, a 35-hour week would have earned someone £9,191 a year&amp;nbsp;– before tax or National Insurance&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Working out of Poverty: A study of the low paid and the working poor by Graeme Cooke and Kayte Lawton&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ippr.org.uk/pressreleases/?id=2965 IPPR Article: &quot;Government must rescue ‘forgotten million children’ in poverty&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

India's official poverty level, on the other hand, is split according to rural vs. urban thresholds. For urban dwellers, the poverty line is defined as living on less than 538.60 rupees (approximately USD $12) per month, whereas for rural dwellers, it is defined as living on less than 356.35 rupees per month (approximately USD $7.50).&lt;ref name=&quot;POVERTY ESTIMATES FOR 2004-05&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://planningcommission.gov.in/news/prmar07.pdf |title=POVERTY ESTIMATES FOR 2004-05 |accessdate=2009-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticisms==
Using a poverty threshold is problematic because having an income marginally above it is not substantially different from having an income marginally below it: the negative effects of poverty tend to be continuous rather than discrete, and the same low income affects different people in different ways. To overcome this problem, poverty indices are sometimes used instead; see [[income inequality metrics]].

A poverty threshold relies on a [[Numerical data|quantitative]], or purely numbers-based, measure of income. If other human development-indicators like health and education are used, they must be quantified, which is not a simple (if even achievable) task.

===Overstating poverty===

In-kind gifts, whether from public or private sources, are not counted when calculating a poverty threshold. For example, if a parent pays the rent on an apartment for an adult son directly to the apartment owner, instead of giving the money to
the son to pay the rent, then that money does not count as income to the son. If a church or non-profit organization gives food to an elderly person, the value of the food is not counted as income to the elderly person. Rea Hederman, a senior policy analyst in the Center for Data Analysis at the [[Heritage Foundation]], said
&lt;blockquote&gt;The official poverty measure counts only monetary income. It considers antipoverty programs such as [[food stamps]], [[Section 8 (housing)|housing assistance]], the [[Earned Income Tax Credit]], [[Medicaid]] and [[school lunch]]es, among others, &quot;in-kind benefits&quot;&amp;nbsp;– and hence not income. So, despite everything these programs do to relieve poverty, they aren't counted as income when Washington measures the ''poverty rate.''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.heritage.org/Press/Commentary/ed090806b.cfm &quot;Poor poverty yardsticks&quot;], Rea S. Hederman, Jr., September 8, 2006, The Heritage Foundation&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Studies measuring the difference between income before and after taxes and government transfers, however, have found that without these programs poverty would be roughly 30% to 40% higher than the official poverty line indicates, despite many of their benefits not being counted as income.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kenworthy&quot;&gt;Kenworthy, L. (1999). Do social-welfare policies reduce poverty? A cross-national assessment. ''Social Forces, 77''(3), 1119-1139. {{doi|10.1093/sf/77.3.1119}} &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bradley et al.&quot;&gt;Bradley, D., Huber, E., Moller, S., Nielson, F. &amp; Stephens, J. D. (2003). [http://www.jstor.org/stable/3088901 Determinants of relative poverty in advanced capitalist democracies.] ''American Sociological Review, 68''(3), 22-51.&lt;/ref&gt;{{clarify|date=December 2011|reason=How exactly are transfers not counted as income going to decrease poverty in terms of income? Could someone with access to the sources expand on this?}}

Further, the U.S. Census Bureau calculates the poverty line the same throughout the U.S. regardless of the cost-of-living in a state or urban area. For instance, the cost-of-living in California, the third largest state, was 142% of the U.S. average in 2010 while the cost-of-living in Texas, the second largest state, was 90% of the U.S. average.{{citation needed|date=October 2012}}

==See also==
*[[Asset poverty]]
*[[Income deficit]]
*[[List of countries by percentage of population living in poverty]]
*[[Living wage]]
*[[Minimum wage]]
*[[Measuring poverty]]
*[[UN Millennium Development Goals]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book
  | last = Shweparde
  | first = Jon
  | coauthors = Robert W. Greene
  | title = Sociology and You
  | publisher = Glencoe McGraw-Hill
  | year = 2003
  | location = Ohio
  | pages = A-22
  | url = http://www.glencoe.com/catalog/index.php/program?c=1675&amp;s=21309&amp;p=4213&amp;parent=4526
  | doi =
  | id =
  | isbn = 0-07-828576-3}}
* Alan Gillie, &quot;The Origin of the Poverty Line&quot;, ''Economic History Review,'' XLIX/4 (1996), 726

==External links==
* [http://eesc.orst.edu/agcomwebfile/edmat/html/em/em8743/part1/officialgovt.html History of the U.S. Poverty Line] by Tom Gentle, Oregon State University.
* [http://aspe.hhs.gov/poverty/index.shtml United States Department of Health and Human Services Poverty Guidelines, Research, and Measurement]
* [http://aspe.hhs.gov/poverty/07poverty.shtml 2007 United States Department of Health and Human Services Poverty Guidelines]
* [[Debraj Ray]] 1998, ''Development Economics'', Princeton University Press, ISBN 0-691-01706-9.
* [http://www.un.org/esa/socdev/wssd/agreements/index.html World Summit for Social Development Agreements], United Nations
* [http://www.inclusivedemocracy.org/journal/vol4/vol4_no1_takis_poverty.htm The &quot;elimination&quot; of poverty], Takis Fotopoulos, [http://www.inclusivedemocracy.org/journal/ The International Journal of Inclusive Democracy], vol.4, no.1, (January 2008).
* {{cite web
  | last = Fisher
  | first = Gordon
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = Relative or Absolute&amp;nbsp;— New Light on the Behavior of Poverty Lines Over Time
  | work =
  | publisher = Department of Health and Human Services
  | date = 2005-12-16
  | url = http://aspe.hhs.gov/POVERTY/papers/relabs.htm
  | doi =
  | accessdate = 2008 -01-16}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Poverty Threshold}}
[[Category:Measurements and definitions of poverty]]
[[Category:Socioeconomics]]
[[Category:Welfare economics]]
[[Category:Economic problems]]

[[ar:خط الفقر]]
[[bg:Жизнен минимум]]
[[ca:Llindar de pobresa]]
[[cs:Práh chudoby]]
[[da:Fattigdomsgrænse]]
[[de:Armutsgrenze]]
[[es:Línea de pobreza]]
[[fr:Seuil de pauvreté]]
[[gl:Limiar de pobreza]]
[[ko:빈곤선]]
[[hi:निर्धनता सीमा]]
[[id:Garis kemiskinan]]
[[it:Soglia di povertà]]
[[he:קו העוני]]
[[mr:दारिद्र्यरेषा]]
[[ms:Garis kemiskinan]]
[[nl:Armoedegrens]]
[[ja:貧困線]]
[[no:Fattigdomsgrense]]
[[nn:Fattigdomsgrense]]
[[oc:Lindal de pauretat]]
[[pl:Relatywna granica ubóstwa]]
[[pt:Linha de pobreza]]
[[simple:Poverty line]]
[[sk:Hranica chudoby]]
[[sr:Апсолутно сиромаштво]]
[[fi:Köyhyysraja]]
[[sv:Fattigdomsgräns]]
[[ta:வறுமைக் கோடு]]
[[tr:Yoksulluk sınırı]]
[[ur:عتَبہ غربت]]
[[vi:Ngưỡng nghèo]]
[[zh:貧窮門檻]]</text>
      <sha1>6x66asv4lcxcbgdf3o0dabcf7w9ieqi</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
