<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Public choice theory</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>51256</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521795883</id>
      <parentid>521253208</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-07T08:25:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Omnipaedista</username>
        <id>8524693</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>add template</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="32281">'''Public choice theory''' is the use of modern [[economic]] tools to study problems that traditionally are in the province of [[political science]].  From the perspective of political science, it is the subset of [[positive political theory]] that models voters, politicians, and bureaucrats as mainly self-interested.&lt;ref&gt;Gordon Tullock, [1987] 2008. &quot;public choice,&quot; ''The New Palgrave Dictionary of Economics'', 2nd Edition. [http://www.dictionaryofeconomics.com/article?id=pde2008_P000240&amp;q=rational%20choice&amp;topicid=&amp;result_number=10 Abstract].&lt;/ref&gt; In particular, it studies such [[Agent (economics)|agents]] and their interactions in the social system either as such or under alternative constitutional rules. These can be represented in a number of ways, including standard constrained [[utility]] maximization, [[game theory]], or [[decision theory]]. Public choice analysis has roots in [[positive economics|positive analysis]] (&quot;what is&quot;) but is often used for [[normative economics|normative]] purposes (&quot;what ought to be&quot;), to identify a problem or suggest how a system could be improved by changes in constitutional rules, the subject of [[constitutional economics]].&lt;ref&gt;• Gordon Tullock, 1987, &quot;public choice,&quot; 1987 [[New Palgrave Dictionary of Economics|[2008]]].  ''[[The New Palgrave: A Dictionary of Economics]]''. pp. 1040–41. [http://www.dictionaryofeconomics.com/article?id=pde2008_P000240&amp;q=rational%20choice&amp;topicid=&amp;result_number=10 Abstract].&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; • James M. Buchanan, 1990. &quot;The Domain of Constitutional Economics,&quot; ''Constitutional Political Economy'', 1(1), pp. [http://www.walkerd.people.cofc.edu/400/Sobel/2A-8.%20Buchanan%20-%20Constitutional%20Economics.pdf  1-18].&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; • [[Dennis C. Mueller]], 2008. &quot;constitutions, economic approach to,&quot; ''The New Palgrave Dictionary of Economics'', 2nd Edition. [http://www.dictionaryofeconomics.com/article?id=pde2008_E000212&amp;edition=current&amp;q=Constitutional%20economics&amp;topicid=&amp;result_number=8 Abstract].&lt;/ref&gt; 

Public choice theory is closely related to [[social choice theory]], a mathematical approach to aggregation of individual interests, welfares, or votes.&lt;ref&gt;Found in the [[JEL classification codes|Journal of Economic Literature classification codes]] at JEL: D71 for social choice and, narrowly at [[JEL classification codes#Microeconomics JEL: D Subcategories|JEL: D72 —  Economic Models of Political Processes: Rent-Seeking, Elections, Legislatures, and Voting Behavior ]] for public choice in literature searches.&lt;/ref&gt; Much early work had aspects of both, and both use the tools of economics and [[game theory]]. Since voter behavior influences the behavior of public officials, public choice theory often uses results from social choice theory. General treatments of public choice are classified as a subarea of [[public economics]].&lt;ref&gt;At [[JEL classification codes#Public economics JEL: H Subcategories|JEL: HO — General]] of the [[JEL classification codes]].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
Prior to the emergence of public choice theory, many economists tended to consider the [[State (polity)|state]] as an agent outside the scope of economic theory, whose actions depend on different considerations than those driving economic agents. (The many ''other'' economists who ''did'' place the state and its agents within such theory include [[Vilfredo Pareto]].){{citation needed|date=June 2012}}

Public choice theory attempts to look at governments from the perspective of the bureaucrats and politicians who compose them, and makes the assumption that they act based on a [[budget-maximizing model]] in a self-interested way for the purpose of growing their own power and influence. The theory aims to apply economic analysis (usually [[decision theory]] and [[game theory]]) to the political decision-making process in order to reveal certain systematic trends towards inefficient government policies. There are also Austrian variants of public choice theory (suggested by [[Ludwig von Mises|von Mises]], [[Friedrich Hayek|Hayek]], [[Israel Kirzner|Kirzner]], Lopez, and [[Peter Boettke|Boettke]]) in which it is assumed that bureaucrats and politicians may be benevolent but have access to limited information. The assumption that such benevolent political agents possess limited information for making decisions often results in conclusions similar to those generated separately by means of the rational self-interest assumptions. [[Randall Holcombe]] and [[Richard E. Wagner]] have also developed the notion of &quot;[[Political_entrepreneur|Political Entrepreneurship]]&quot;.{{citation needed|date=June 2012}}

===Special interests===
Public choice theory is often used to explain how political decision-making results in outcomes that conflict with the preferences of the general public. For example, many [[advocacy group]] and [[pork barrel]] projects are not the desire of the overall [[democracy]]. However, it makes sense for politicians to support these projects. It may make them feel powerful and important. It can also benefit them financially by opening the door to future wealth as [[lobbyists]]. The project may be of interest to the politician's local [[constituency]], increasing district votes or [[campaign finance|campaign contributions]]. The politician pays little or no cost to gain these benefits, as he is spending public money. Special-interest lobbyists are also behaving rationally. They can gain government favors worth millions or billions for relatively small investments. They face a risk of losing out to their competitors if they don't seek these favors. The taxpayer is also behaving rationally. The cost of defeating any one government give-away is very high, while the benefits to the individual taxpayer are very small. Each citizen pays only a few pennies or a few dollars for any given government favor, while the costs of ending that favor would be many times higher. Everyone involved has rational incentives to do exactly what they're doing, even though the desire of the general constituency is opposite. Costs are diffused, while benefits are concentrated. The voices of vocal minorities with much to gain are heard over those of indifferent majorities with little to individually lose.&lt;ref name=&quot;Specialinterests&quot;&gt;• William C. Mitchell and Michael C. Munger, 1991. &quot;Economic Models of Interest Groups: An Introductory Survey,&quot; ''American Journal of Political Science'', 35(2), pp. [http://www.jstor.org/pss/2111373 512]-546.&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; • Gordon Tullock, [1987] 2008. &quot;public choice,&quot; ''[[The New Palgrave Dictionary of Economics]]''. 2nd Edition. [http://www.dictionaryofeconomics.com/article?id=pde2008_P000240&amp;q=rational%20choice&amp;topicid=&amp;result_number=10 Abstract].&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; • [[Gary S. Becker]], 1983. &quot;A Theory of Competition Among Pressure Groups for Political Influence,&quot; ''Quarterly Journal of Economics'', 98(3), pp. [http://www2.bren.ucsb.edu/~glibecap/BeckerQJE1983.pdf 371-400].&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; •_____, 1985. &quot;Public Policies, Pressure Groups, and Dead-weight Costs,&quot; ''Journal of Public Economics'', 28(3), pp.&amp;nbsp;329–347. [http://www.sciencedirect.com/science?_ob=ArticleURL&amp;_udi=B6V76-4591172-4N&amp;_user=10&amp;_coverDate=12/31/1985&amp;_rdoc=1&amp;_fmt=high&amp;_orig=search&amp;_sort=d&amp;_docanchor=&amp;view=c&amp;_searchStrId=1346655200&amp;_rerunOrigin=scholar.google&amp;_acct=C000050221&amp;_version=1&amp;_urlVersion=0&amp;_userid=10&amp;md5=1c816a6df7341b704dcd76e7f485ce1b Abstract] and reprinted in George J. Stigler, ed., 1988, ''Chicago Studies in Political Economy'', pp. [http://books.google.com/books?id=8s5C8ffXdjUC&amp;pg=PA85&amp;lpg=PA85&amp;dq=%22Public+policies,+pressure+groups,+and+dead+weight+costs%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Zjt624Mo2-&amp;sig=sZJdmh5HOcP6mWUU3eBysXTP21M&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=e-P6S7zJLcPflgfIycSECw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=5&amp;ved=0CDIQ6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Public%20policies%2C%20pressure%20groups%2C%20and%20dead%20weight%20costs%22&amp;f=false 85-105].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Rentseeking&quot;&gt;• Gordon Tullock, [1987] 2008. &quot;rent seeking,&quot; ''The New Palgrave Dictionary of Economics'', 2nd Edition. [http://www.dictionaryofeconomics.com/article?id=pde2008_R000100&amp;edition=&amp;field=keyword&amp;q=special%20interests&amp;topicid=&amp;result_number=1  Abstract].&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; • _____, 1967. &quot;The Welfare Costs of Tariffs, Monopolies, and Theft,&quot;''Western Economic Journal'', later ''Economic Inquiry'', 5(3), pp. [http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1465-7295.1967.tb01923.x/abstract 224]–232.&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; • [[Anne O. Krueger]], 1974. &quot;The Political Economy of the Rent-Seeking Society,&quot; ''American Economic Review'', 64(3), pp. [http://spot.colorado.edu/~mertens/4221/krueger.pdf 291-303].&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; • Gordon Tullock, 1989. ''The Economics of Special Privilege and Rent Seeking, Springer. [http://books.google.com/books?id=nJHIZl1ewCMC&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s Description] and chapter-preview [http://books.google.com/books?id=nJHIZl1ewCMC&amp;printsec=find&amp;pg=PR5#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false links].&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; • [[Jagdish N. Bhagwati]], 1982. &quot;Directly Unproductive, Profit-Seeking (DUP) Activities,&quot; ''Journal of Political Economy'', 90(5), pp. [http://www.jstor.org/pss/1837129 988]-1002.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Decision making processes and the state===
One way to organize the subject matter studied by public choice theorists is to begin with the foundations of the state itself. According to this procedure, the most fundamental subject is the origin of [[government]]. Although some work has been done on [[anarchy]], [[autocracy]], [[revolution]], and even [[war]], the bulk of the study in this area has concerned the fundamental problem of collectively choosing [[constitution|constitutional rules]]. This work assumes a group of individuals who aim to form a government, then it focuses on the problem of hiring the agents required to carry out government functions agreed upon by the members.{{citation needed|date=June 2012}}

===Bureaucracy===
Another major sub-field is the study of [[bureaucracy]]. The usual model depicts the top bureaucrats as being chosen by the chief executive and legislature, depending on whether the democratic system is [[presidential system|presidential]] or [[parliamentary system|parliamentary]]. The typical image of a bureau chief is a person on a fixed salary who is concerned with pleasing those who appointed him. The latter have the power to hire and fire him more or less at will. The bulk of the [[bureaucrats]], however, are civil servants whose jobs and pay are protected by a civil service system against major changes by their appointed bureau chiefs. This image is often compared with that of a business owner whose profit varies with the success of production and sales, who aims to maximize profit, and who can in an ideal system [[At-will employment|hire and fire employees at will]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Niskanen&quot;&gt;[[William A. Niskanen]] ([1971] 1994). ''Bureaucracy and Public Economics'', Elgar. Expanded ed. Description and review  [http://www.thelockeinstitute.org/books/bureaucracy.html links] and review [http://books.google.com/books/about/Bureaucracy_and_public_economics.html?id=QDB-QgAACAAJ excerpts].&lt;/ref&gt;

===Rent-seeking===
A field that is closely related to public choice is &quot;[[rent-seeking]]&quot;. This field combines the study of a market economy with that of government. Thus, one might regard it as a &quot;new political economy.&quot; Its basic thesis is that when both a market economy and government are present, government agents provide numerous special market privileges. Both the government agents and self-interested market participants seek these privileges in order to partake in the resulting monopoly rent. When such privileges are granted, they reduce the efficiency of the economic system. In addition, the rent-seekers use resources that could otherwise be used to produce goods that are valued by consumers.

Rent-seeking is broader than Public Choice in that it applies to autocracies as well as democracies and, therefore, is not directly concerned with collective decision-making. However, the obvious pressures it exerts on legislators, executives, bureaucrats, and even judges are factors that public choice theory must account for in its analysis of collective decision-making rules and institutions. Moreover, the members of a collective who are planning a government would be wise to take prospective rent-seeking into account.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rentseeking&quot;/&gt;

==Theory==

===Democracy===
One of the basic claims that results from public choice theory is that good government policies in a [[democracy]] are an underprovided [[public good]], because of the [[rational ignorance]] of the voters. Each voter is faced with a tiny probability that his vote will change the result of the elections, while gathering the relevant information necessary for a well-informed voting decision requires substantial time and effort. Therefore, the rational decision for each voter is to be generally ignorant of politics and perhaps even abstain from voting. Rational choice theorists claim that this explains the gross ignorance of most citizens in modern democracies as well as low voter turnout. Rational abstention creates the so-called &quot;[[Paradox of voting]]&quot; in which a strict cost-benefit analysis implies that no one should vote.{{citation needed|date=June 2012}}

===Special interests===
While good government tends to be a pure [[public good]] for the mass of voters, there may be many [[advocacy groups]] that have strong incentives for [[lobbying]] the government to implement specific policies that would benefit them, potentially at the expense of the general public. For example, lobbying by the sugar manufacturers might result in an inefficient [[subsidy]] for the production of sugar, either direct or by [[protectionist]] measures. The costs of such inefficient policies are dispersed over all citizens, and therefore unnoticeable to each individual. On the other hand, the benefits are shared by a small special-interest group with a strong incentive to perpetuate the policy by further lobbying.  Due to [[rational ignorance]], the vast majority of voters will be unaware of the effort; in fact, although voters may be aware of special-interest lobbying efforts, this may merely select for policies which are even harder to evaluate by the general public, rather than improving their overall efficiency.  Even if the public were able to evaluate policy proposals effectively, they would find it infeasible to engage in [[collective action]] in order to defend their diffuse interest.  Therefore, theorists expect that numerous special interests will be able to successfully lobby for various inefficient policies. In public choice theory, such scenarios of inefficient government policies are referred to as ''[[government failure]]'' — a term akin to ''[[market failure]]'' from earlier theoretical [[welfare economics]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Specialinterests&quot;/&gt;

===&quot;Expressive interests&quot; and democratic irrationality===
Geoffrey Brennan and [[Loren Lomasky]] claim that democratic policy is biased to favor &quot;expressive interests&quot; and neglect practical and utilitarian considerations. Brennan and Lomasky differentiate between instrumental interests (any kind of practical benefit, both monetary and non-monetary) and expressive interests (forms of expression like applause). According to Brennan and Lomasky, the voting paradox can be resolved by differentiating between expressive and instrumental interests. While voters have virtually no instrumental incentive to vote, they do have an expressive interest in voting. Since voters vote for expressive reasons, politicians win by targeting the median expressive preferences. Bias in favor of expressive interests means that public policy often ignores important practical considerations. For example, there are instrumental costs to restricting international trade. Yet many people favor protectionism as an expression of nationalism, despite its economic costs.{{citation needed|date=June 2012}}

This argument has led some public choice scholars to claim that politics is plagued by irrationality. In articles published in the Econ Journal Watch, economist [[Bryan Caplan]] contended that voter choices and government economic decisions are inherently irrational.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.econjournalwatch.org/pdf/CaplanCommentApril2005.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.econjournalwatch.org/pdf/CaplanRejoinderAugust2005.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;  Caplan‘s ideas are more fully developed in his book ''[[The Myth of the Rational Voter]]'' (Princeton University Press 2007). In opposition to the arguments put forward by economist [[Donald Wittman]] in his The Myth of Democratic Failure, Caplan claims that politics is biased in favor of irrational beliefs. 

According to Caplan, democracy effectively subsidizes irrational beliefs. Anyone who derives utility from potentially irrational policies (such as protectionism) can receive private benefits while imposing the costs of such beliefs on the general public.  Were people to bear the full costs of their “irrational beliefs”, they would lobby for them optimally, taking into account both their instrumental consequences and their expressive appeal.  Instead, democracy oversupplies policies based on irrational beliefs.  Caplan defines rationality mainly in terms of mainstream price theory, pointing out that mainstream economists tend to oppose protectionism and government regulation more than the general population, and that more educated people are closer to economists on this score, even after controlling for confounding factors such as income, wealth or political affiliation.  One criticism is that many economists do not share Caplan's views on the nature of public choice. However, Caplan does have some data to support his position. Economists have, in fact, often been frustrated by public opposition to economic reasoning. As Sam Peltzman puts it &quot;Economists know what steps would improve the efficiency of HSE [health, safety, and environmental] regulation, and they have not been bashful advocates of them. These steps include substituting markets in property rights, such as emission rights, for command and control. . . . The real problem lies deeper than any lack of reform proposals or failure to press them. It is our inability to understand their lack of political appeal &quot;George Stigler's Contribution to the Economic Analysis of Regulation&quot; 101 J. Pol. Econ. 818, 830 (October 1993).{{citation needed|date=June 2012}}

===Rent-seeking===
Another major claim is that much of political activity is a form of [[rent-seeking]] which wastes resources. [[Gordon Tullock]], [[Jagdish Bhagwati]], and [[Anne Osborn Krueger]] have argued that rent-seeking has caused considerable waste.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rentseeking&quot;/&gt; In a parallel line of research Fred McChesney claims that rent extraction causes considerable waste, especially in the developing world. As the term implies, rent extraction happens when officials use threats to extort payments from private parties.

===Political stance===
From such results it is sometimes asserted that public choice theory has an anti-state tilt. But there is ideological diversity among public choice theorists. [[Mancur Olson]] for example was an advocate of a strong state and instead opposed political [[interest group]] lobbying.&lt;ref name=&quot;Olson&quot;/&gt; More generally, James Buchanan has suggested that public choice theory be interpreted as &quot;politics without romance,&quot; a critical approach to a pervasive earlier notion of idealized politics set against market failure. As such it is more a correction of the earlier scientific record, almost requiring a certain pragmatism in comparing alternative politicized institutional structures.&lt;ref&gt;Buchanan, 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

==Applications==
Public choice's application to government regulation was developed by [[George Stigler]] (1971) and [[Sam Peltzman]] (1976). [[William Niskanen]] is generally considered the founder of Public Choice literature on the [[bureaucracy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Niskanen&quot;/&gt;

==Development==
The modern literature in Public Choice began with [[Duncan Black]], who in 1948 identified the underlying concepts of what would become [[median voter theory]]. He also wrote ''The Theory of Committees and Elections'' in 1958. [[Gordon Tullock]]&lt;ref&gt;1987, p. 1040&lt;/ref&gt; refers to him as the &quot;father of public choice theory&quot;.

[[James M. Buchanan]] and [[Gordon Tullock]] coauthored ''[[The Calculus of Consent: Logical Foundations of Constitutional Democracy]]'' (1962), considered one of the landmark works that founded the discipline of public choice theory. In particular (1962, p. v), the book is about the ''political organization'' of a free society. But its method, conceptual apparatus, and analytics &quot;are derived, essentially, from the discipline that has as its subject the ''economic'' organization of such a society.&quot; The book focuses on [[positive economics|positive-economic]] analysis as to the development of constitutional democracy but in an ethical context of consent. The consent takes the form of a [[compensation principle]] like [[Pareto efficiency]] for making a policy change and unanimity at least no opposition as a point of departure for social choice.

[[Kenneth Arrow]]'s ''[[Social Choice and Individual Values]]'' (1951) influenced formulation of the theory. Among other important works are [[Anthony Downs]]'s ''[[An Economic Theory of Democracy]]'' (1957) and [[Mancur Olson]]'s ''[[The Logic of Collective Action]]'' (1965).&lt;ref name=&quot;Olson&quot;&gt;Mancur Olson, Jr., 1965, 2nd ed., 1971. ''The Logic of Collective Action: Public Goods and the Theory of Groups'', Harvard University Press, [http://www.hup.harvard.edu/catalog.php?isbn=9780674537514 Description], [http://www.hup.harvard.edu/catalog.php?recid=24500&amp;content=toc Table of Contents], and [http://books.google.com/books?id=jzTeOLtf7_wC&amp;printsec=find&amp;pg=PA5=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false preview].&lt;/ref&gt;

During the same decade, the [[probabilistic voting theory]] started to replace the median voter theory, since it clearly showed how it was able to find Nash Equilibria also in multidimensional space. The theory was later completely formalized by Peter Coughlin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Coughlin|first=Peter|year=1991|title=Probabilistic Voting Theory |pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Recognition==
Several notable Public Choice scholars have been awarded the [[Nobel Prize in Economics]], including [[James M. Buchanan]] (1986), [[George Stigler]] (1982), and [[Gary Becker]] (1992). In addition, [[Vernon L. Smith|Vernon Smith]] (2002) and [[Elinor Ostrom]] (2009) were former Presidents of the Public Choice Society.

==Criticisms==
In their 1994 book ''Pathologies of Rational Choice Theory'', political scientists Donald P. Green and Ian Shapiro argue that [[rational choice theory]] (of which public choice theory is a branch) has contributed less to the field than its popularity suggests.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Friedman|first=Jeffrey|year=1996|title=The Rational Choice Controversy: Economic Models of Politics|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt; They write:
:The discrepancy between the faith that practitioners place in rational choice theory and its failure to deliver empirically warrants closer inspection of rational choice theorizing as a scientific enterprise.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Green|first=Donald P.|coauthors=Ian Shapiro|year=1994|title=Pathologies of Rational Choice Theory|pages=6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Linda McQuaig]] writes in ''All You Can Eat'':{{citation needed|date=June 2012}}
:The absurdity of public-choice theory is captured by [[Nobel Prize in Economics|Nobel Prize]]-winning economist [[Amartya Sen]] in the following little scenario: “Can you direct me to the railway station?” asks the stranger. &quot;Certainly,&quot; says the local, pointing in the opposite direction, towards the post office, &quot;and would you post this letter for me on your way?&quot; &quot;Certainly,&quot; says the stranger, resolving to open it to see if it contains anything worth stealing.

It should be noted that scenarios of this type contain an implicit assumption of zero probability of the two strangers ever interacting again.  With a positive probability of future interactions and the propensity of humans to use tit-for-tat type strategies (someone harms or helps you, you return the favor in kind), the optimal totally self-interested decision may be to point to the train station.  Furthermore, as [[David D. Friedman]] observes, the benefit of cheating the stranger ''on one occasion'' may not be worth the mental effort of conceiving a way to do so and weighing the odds of suffering the consequences. Sen, in fact, has participated in the development of public choice theory, in such works as ''Collective Choice and Social Welfare''.{{citation needed|date=June 2012}}

James Buchanan and Gordon Tullock outline the limitations of their methodology in their work ''Calculus of Consent'':
:“even if the model [with its rational self-interest assumptions] proves to be useful in explaining an important element of politics, it does not imply that all individuals act in accordance with the behavioral assumption made or that any one individual acts in this way at all times… the theory of collective choice can explain only some undetermined fraction of collective action. However, so long as some part of all individual behavior… is, in fact, motivated by utility maximization, and so long as the identification of the individual with the group does not extend to the point of making all individual utility functions identical, an economic-individualist model of political activity should be of some positive worth.”{{citation needed|date=June 2012}}

==See also==
{{MultiCol}} 
*[[Choice modelling]]
*[[Economic calculation debate]]
*[[Economic imperialism (economics)]]
*[[Fiscal Illusion]]
{{ColBreak}}
*[[Flipism]]
*[[Flypaper effect]]
*[[Public economics]]
*[[Real politik]]
{{ColBreak}}
*[[Regulatory capture]]
*[[Prisoner's dilemma]]
*[[Sortition]]
*[[Subsidiarity]]
*[[Tax choice]]
{{EndMultiCol}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
*Arrow, Kenneth J. (1951, 2nd ed., 1963). ''[[Social Choice and Individual Values]]''
*Black, Duncan (1958). ''[[The Theory of Committees and Elections]]''. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.
*Buchanan, James M. (1968). ''The Demand and Supply of Public Goods. Rand McNally. [http://www.econlib.org/library/Buchanan/buchCv5.html Chapter links.]
* _____ (2003). [http://sb.cofc.edu/pv_obj_cache/pv_obj_id_C75D512B1781A110978C02C20FADB6A32CE10700/filename/Public%20Choice%20Origins%20Buchanan.pdf &quot;Public Choice: The Origins and Development of a Research Program,&quot;] Center for Study of Public Choice at George Mason University, Fairfax: Virginia, USA.
*Buchanan, James M. and Gordon Tullock (1962). ''[[The Calculus of Consent]]''. Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press.
*Downs, Anthony. (1957). ''[[An Economic Theory of Democracy]]''. Cambridge: York: Cambridge University Press.
*Holcombe, R. G. (1989). &quot;The Median Voter Model in Public Choice Theory&quot;, Public Choice 61, 115-125
*Isani, Muzaffar Ali.  (1982). ''[[An Economic Approach to Politics in Developing Countries]]''. Unpublished Ph.D. Dissertation, Georgetown University, Washington, D.C.
*McKelvey, R.D. (1976). &quot;Intransitivities in Multi Dimensional Voting Models and some Implications for Agenda Control&quot;, Journal of Economic Theory 12(3) 472-482
*MacKenzie, DW. (2008). ''The Use of Knowledge about Society''. Journal of Economic Behavior and Organization.
*MacKenzie, DW. (2008). ''Politics and Knowledge: Expectations formation in Democracy''. Working paper, Presented at the Southern Economics Association Conference in 2005.
*Malik, Muzaffer (2009). ''Hunger, choice and struggle for it''. Unpublished desertation on poverty in India.
*Mueller, Dennis C. (2003). ''Public Choice III''. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. [http://www.cambridge.org/gb/knowledge/isbn/item1175589/?site_locale=en_GB Description] and [http://books.google.com/books?id=CdIOKZWc3oMC&amp;printsec=Find&amp;pg=PR7=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false preview.]
*Niskanen, W. A. (1987). “Bureaucracy.&quot; In Charles K. Rowley, ed. ''Democracy and Public Choice''. Oxford: Basil Blackwell.
*Olson, Mancur, Jr. (1965, 2nd ed., 1971). ''[[The Logic of Collective Action]]''. Cambridge: Harvard University Press. [http://books.google.com/books?id=jzTeOLtf7_wC Description] and chapter-previews links, pp. [http://books.google.com/books?id=jzTeOLtf7_wC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=frontcover#PPR9,M1 ix]-[http://books.google.com/books?id=jzTeOLtf7_wC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=frontcover#PPR10,M1 x.]
*Ostrom, Vincent (1986). ''The Theory of the Compound Republic''. Lincoln, Nebraska: University of Nebraska Press. Second edition.
*[[William H. Riker|Riker, William H.]] (1962). ''[[The Theory of Political Coalitions]]''. New Haven and London: Yale University Press.
*Romer, T. &amp; Rosenthal, H. (1979). &quot;The Elusive Median Voter&quot;, Journal of Public Economics 12(2) 143-170
* Schram, Sanford F., and Brian Caterino, eds. (2006). ''Making Political Science Matter: Debating Knowledge, Research, and Method''. New York and London: New York University Press. [http://books.google.com/books?id=kyJ5GJ7DeMQC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=%22Making+Political+Science+Matter%22&amp;sig=s_bqA18zhy02NKJwsJHJj3vHzKc Preview.]
* Rowley, Charles K., and Friedrich Schneider, ed. (2004). ''The Encyclopedia of Public Choice''. 2 v. Springer.[http://www.springer.com/economics/book/978-0-7923-8607-0 Description] and v. 2  [http://books.google.com/books?id=YUVMr-aFYwYC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_atb#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false preview.]
* Shughart, William F. II. (2008) &quot;[http://www.econlib.org/library/Enc/PublicChoice.html Public Choice,&quot;] ''The Concise Encyclopedia of Economics'', D.R. Henderson, ed. Library Fund.
{{Refend}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite journal |last=Borcherding |first=T. E. |last2=Dillon |first2=P. |lastauthoramp=yes |last3=Willett |first3=T. D. |year=1998 |title=Henry George: Precursor to public choice analysis |journal=[[The American Journal of Economics and Sociology]] |volume=57 |issue=2 |pages=173–182 |doi=10.1111/j.1536-7150.1998.tb03269.x }}

==External links==
*[http://ssrn.com/abstract=1103644 A Comparative Bibliography: Regulatory Competition on Corporate Law]
*[http://www.econlib.org/library/Buchanan/buchCContents.html ''Collected Works of James M. Buchanan''] at the Library of Economics and Liberty.
*[http://www.econlib.org/library/Buchanan/buchCv3Contents.html ''The Calculus of Consent''] by James M. Buchanan and Gordon Tullock
*[http://www.econlib.org/library/Enc/PublicChoiceTheory.html &quot;Public Choice Theory&quot;] at the ''Concise Encyclopedia of Economics''
*[http://www.gmu.edu/departments/economics/bcaplan/e410/econ410.htm Notes for a course in public choice] by Bryan Caplan
*[http://perspicuity.net/sd/pub-choice.html Introduction to Public Choice Theory] by Leon Felkins. Contains numerous links of interest
*[http://www.nomadpress.com/public_choice/34432.html The Field of Public Choice] by Pat Gunning
*[http://www.pubchoicesoc.org/about2.htm &quot;Statement of Purpose,&quot;] Public Choice Society
*[http://www.canaktan.org/ekonomi/anayasal_iktisat/anasayfa-anayasaliktisat.htm Turkish Public Choice Site]
*[http://unjobs.org/tags/public-choice-theory Public choice documents on unjobs.org]

{{Chiconomists}}
{{Schools of economic thought}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Public Choice Theory}}
[[Category:Public choice theory|*]]
[[Category:Public economics]]
[[Category:Political economy]]
[[Category:Political science theories]]

{{Link GA|zh}}

[[ar:نظرية الخيار العام]]
[[be:Тэорыя грамадскага выбару]]
[[ca:Teoria de l'elecció pública]]
[[cs:Teorie veřejné volby]]
[[da:Public choice]]
[[de:Neue Politische Ökonomie]]
[[es:Teoría de la elección pública]]
[[fa:نظریه انتخاب عمومی]]
[[fr:Théorie des choix publics]]
[[is:Almannavalsfræði]]
[[it:Teoria della scelta pubblica]]
[[he:תאוריית הבחירה הציבורית]]
[[lv:Sabiedriskās izvēles teorija]]
[[nl:Publiekekeuzetheorie]]
[[ja:公共選択論]]
[[no:Public choice]]
[[pl:Teoria wyboru publicznego]]
[[pt:Escolha pública]]
[[ru:Теория общественного выбора]]
[[sk:Teória verejnej voľby]]
[[fi:Julkisen valinnan teoria]]
[[sv:Public choice]]
[[zh:公共選擇理論]]</text>
      <sha1>l5xtnli3755u2yc3zsqrooctp2uy78o</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
