<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Remanufacturing</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2101077</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522192758</id>
      <parentid>506671011</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T16:02:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Emkothe</username>
        <id>17857451</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Range of products being remanufactured */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7397">{{refimprove|date=May 2008}}

'''Remanufacturing''' is the process of disassembly and recovery at the module level and, eventually, at the component level. It requires the repair or replacement of worn out or [[Obsolescence|obsolete]] components and modules. Parts subject to [[Elegant degradation|degradation]] affecting the performance or the expected life of the whole are replaced.  See an example of a professional automotive [[electronics remanufacturing]] flow.

Remanufacturing is a form of a product recovery process which differs from other recovery processes in its completeness: a remanufactured machine should match the same customer expectation as new machines.

== Other forms of product recovery ==
#[[Reuse]] implies that items are used by a second customer without prior repair operations or as originally designed.
# [[Repair]]: the process of bringing damaged components back to a functional condition.
# [[Refurbishing]]/Reconditioning is the process of restoring components to a functional and/or satisfactory state to the original speciﬁcation, using methods such as resurfacing, repainting, etc.
# [[Recycling]] is the process of taking a component material and processing it to make the same material or useful degraded material.

Many formal definitions of remanufacturing exist in the literature, but the first published report on remanufacturing, by R. Lund (1998), describes remanufacturing as &quot;… an industrial process in which worn-out products are restored to like-new condition. Through a series of industrial processes in a factory environment, a discarded product is completely disassembled. Useable parts are cleaned, refurbished, and put into inventory. Then the product is reassembled from the old parts (and where necessary, new parts) to produce a unit fully equivalent and sometimes superior in performance and expected lifetime to the original new product&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Remanufacturing&quot;. Lund, Robert T., Technology review, v 87, n 2, p 19-23, 28-29, Feb-Mar 1984&lt;/ref&gt;

== Range of products being remanufactured&lt;ref&gt;http://reman.org&lt;/ref&gt; ==
* Aerospace	
* Air-conditioning units	
* Automatic transmissions	
* Bakery Equipment	
* Car and truck engines	
* Carpet tiles	
* Compressors	
* Computer and telecommunication equipment.	
* Defense equipment	
* Electrical motors and apparatus	
* Excavation equipment	
* Gaming Machines	
* Industrial food processing equipment	
* Machine tools	
* Musical Instruments 	
* Office furniture	
* Office photocopiers (laser toner cartridges)	
* Power bearings	
* Pumps	
* Robots	
* Rolling stock (railway vehicles)	
* Starter motors	
* Vending Machines

== Different types of remanufacturing ==
There are three types of remanufacturing activities, each with different operational challenges.
# ''Remanufacturing without identity loss''; with this method, a current machine is built on yesterday’s base, receiving all of the enhancements, expected life and [[warranty]] of a new machine. The physical structure (the [[chassis]] or frame) is inspected for soundness. The whole product is refurbished and critical modules are overhauled, upgraded or replaced. If there are defects in the original design, they are eliminated. This is the case for customized remanufacturing of machine tools, [[fixed-wing aircraft|airplane]]s, computer [[Mainframe computer|mainframes]], large medical equipment and other capital goods. Because of its uniqueness, this product recovery is characterized as a project.
# ''Remanufacturing by recoating of worn engine parts''; many engine parts, components are large and expensive and after a period of use become worn. An example of such a part is the engine block, in particular the cylinder engine bores, which must withstand explosions during piston firing. Instead of disposing of large engine blocks, remanufacturing has resulted in re-use of the parts by coating them with plasma transferred wire arc spraying ([[PTWA]]) [[Caterpillar]] known for manufacturing very large industrial trucks and machinery has started such remanufacturing programs of equipment parts using PTWA, resulting in a greener environment. Remanufacturing by recoating of parts is also very popular in the aircraft field, the geothermal pipe field and the automotive engine field.
# ''Repetitive remanufacturing without identity loss''; in this method, there is the additional challenge of scheduling the sequence of dependent processes and identifying the location of [[inventory]] buffers. There is a fine line between repetitive remanufacturing without loss of identity and product overhaul. Again, the critical difference is that remanufacturing is a complete process. The final output has a like-new appearance and is covered by a warranty comparable to that of a new product.

===Remanufacturing with loss of original product identity===
With this method, used goods are disassembled into pre-determined [[Manufacturing|component]]s and repaired to stock, ready to be reassembled into a remanufactured product. This is the case when remanufacturing [[automobile]] components, [[photocopier]]s, [[toner]] cartridges, furniture, ready-to-use [[camera]]s and [[personal computer]]s. Once the product is disassembled and the parts are recovered, the process concludes with an operation not too different from original manufacturing. Disassembled parts are inventoried, just like purchased parts and made available for final assembly.

Remanufacturing with loss of original [[brand|product identity]] encompasses some unique challenges in [[inventory management]] and disassembly sequence development. Some of the open questions relate to the commonality of parts in products of different generations, the uncertainty in the supply of used products, and their relationship with [[production planning]]. The [[National Center for Remanufacturing and Resource Recovery]] (NCR3) at [[Rochester Institute of Technology]] ([[New York|NY]]) is researching remanufacturing processes including testing standards for remanufactured products.

==Rebuilding==
'''Rebuilding''' is an old name for remanufacturing. It is still widely used by automotive industry. For example, the [[Automotive Parts Remanufacturers Association]] (APRA),&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.apra.org/ apra.org]&lt;/ref&gt; have the new term in their name, but to be safe on their own website use the combined term as 'rebuild/remanufacture'.

The term 'rebuilding' is also often used by [[railway]] companies; a [[steam locomotive]] may be rebuilt with a new [[boiler]] or a [[diesel locomotive]] may be rebuilt with a new [[Diesel engine|engine]]. This saves money (by re-using the frame, and some other components, which still have years of useful life) and allows the incorporation of improved technology. For example, a new diesel engine may have lower fuel consumption, reduced exhaust emissions and better reliability. Recent examples include [[British Rail Class 57]] and [[British Rail Class 43 (HST)#Life extension of HSTs|British Rail Class 43]].

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;

==External links==
* [http://www.remanufacturing.org.uk http://www.remanufacturing.org.uk]
* [http://www.prcind.com www.prcind.com]
[http://www.ivorsearle.co.uk/what_remanufacturing_entails.htm Ivor Searle's Engine Remanufacturing Process]

[[Category:Production and manufacturing]]
[[Category:Design for X]]
[[Category:Waste management]]

[[de:Remanufacturing]]
[[pt:Remanufatura]]</text>
      <sha1>sae78wg540uop6t54fvdv3k5n62qfj0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
