<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Safe trade</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>45260</id>
    <revision>
      <id>401730650</id>
      <parentid>317978339</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-12-11T05:09:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JaGa</username>
        <id>2092487</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Unlinked: [[Prevention]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6566">{{Unreferenced|date=November 2007}}

'''''Safe trade''''' is a slogan advocated by [[Greenpeace]] in its desire to &quot;[[Green movement|green]]&quot; the [[World Trade Organisation]] and the [[Doha Development Round]].  It is designed to compete with &quot;[[free trade]]&quot; as a concept.

Safe trade is generally seen as a single framework of rules worldwide to drastically inhibit the flow of alien [[organism]]s (e.g. [[Genetically modified organism]]s, [[imported animals]]) across the borders of [[ecoregion]]s, to preserve their natural wild [[biodiversity]].  It seeks to prevent [[ecological]] disasters caused by imported organisms or untested [[genetics|genetic]] [[technologies]], and to augment and increase local [[natural capital]] by encouraging soil remediation, [[precision agriculture]], and [[local consumption]] of the [[Endemic (ecology)|native]] [[species]], rather than imported organisms and heavy use of [[pesticide]]s.

==Proposal==
An important achievement of safe [[trade]] [[advocacy]] is the [[Biosafety Protocol]] agreed in [[Montreal]] in January 2000.  Although it relied on the weaker legal principle of [[Informed Consent]] and not the much stronger [[Precautionary Principle]] language sought by advocates, the [[Protocol (treaty)|protocol]] was considered by most to be a victory that could enhance both [[biosafety]] and [[biosecurity]].

Other safe trade reforms seek to advance [[sustainability]] by reducing reliance on [[energy]] [[subsidies]] and [[Petroleum|oil]]-based [[transport]], and (indirectly) improves [[Equity (economics)|equity]] in [[economic]] affairs - that is, it promotes a safer [[political economy]] which is more respectful of [[life]] in general.

Safe trade is a major goal of systems of [[Bioregional democracy]] and is often advocated alongside it, e.g. by [[Green movement|Greens]].  Both are also implicitly related to [[Community-Based Economics]], as local trade in local goods with no reliance on [[Alien (biology)|alien]] organisms presents no ecological risk to its [[genome]]s, [[soil]], or [[drainage basin]]s.  Accordingly, some advocates argue, local trade in any native species within an ecoregion's borders should not be taxed at all, as it presents little or no ecological risk compared to imported goods, and so requires little or no [[regulation]], labelling, [[inspection]], or other expenses.

The assumption that imports carry [[moral hazard]]s, and that [[tax, trade, tariff]] measures should compensate for harms done, is shared by advocates of [[fair trade]] whose programs address, in addition, more overt [[social justice]] concerns of [[human]] beings, such as the maintenance of the &quot;[[human capital]]&quot; of a region.  Both initiatives are alternatives to [[free trade]], which has no such controls, and generally permits and encourages free [[transport|transit]] in goods (but not, in general, labour) across ecological and social borders.

A broader understanding of [[biosecurity]] that is emerging under threat of [[biological warfare]], and the fear that such economically devastating events as the [[mad cow disease]] epidemic could recur, either deliberately (as an act of [[bioterrorism]]) or by accident due to unrestricted imports, is causing some nations, notably [[New Zealand]], to adopt relatively harsh restrictions against imported organisms.  As one objective of [[asymmetric warfare]] is to cause attacks to appear initially as accidents, or blame slow responses on apparently incompetent governments, there is some concern that spreading a virulent organism among animals would be an effective way to attack humans, damage economies, and discredit governments who are lax on [[biosecurity]].  Technologies for scanning for dangerous organisms at ports and markets are also becoming more reliable and less expensive.  However, no [[bio-defense]] solution seems to be able to compete with a simple reduction of import volumes, and its corresponding reduction in risk of any accidents.

==Reception==
===Opposition===
Critics of safe trade argue that the [[military]] and [[agriculture]] aspects of [[biosecurity]] are dissimilar, unlikely to converge in the form of an attack disguised as an accident, and require such differential prevention and response measures that there is little risk reduced in altering the [[fundamental structure]] of trade relationships to accommodate a robust regime of [[biosecurity]].  Such critics usually argue instead that emergency services' [[biodefense]] measures are sufficient to handle outbreaks of any diseases or alien organisms, and that such outbreaks are unlikely to be long sustained or deliberately masked as agricultural accidents.  This, to the advocates, seems like wishful thinking.

===Support===
Advocates point to the costs of emergency measures such as burning over one million cows suspected of having [[foot-and-mouth disease]] in the UK, smoke from which they calculated (based on [[Polychlorinated dibenzodioxins|dioxin]] levels) was to be expected to kill several hundred Britons from cancers in this generation.  Safe trade, they argue, would have removed the need for any such measures, as [[vaccination]] of British beef cattle would have been possible (the burning was to prevent British exports of beef from being rejected by its trade partners, who would not have been able to tell vaccinated from infected beef), and the foot-and-mouth disease was not so dangerous to humans that it could have justified dooming so many fellow citizens to die of the dioxin-caused cancers.  The burning, they argue, was justified only by bad trade rules that spread infection and advise dangerous cures that are worse than the ailment itself.

Another argument supporting safe trade rules is that there are links between [[primate extinction]] and [[deforestation]] in the regions where primates are abundant, i.e. the [[Amazon rainforest]], [[African rainforest]], and [[Sumatran rainforest]].  Fail to prevent devastating logging in these regions, advocates claim, and a [[Great Ape]] species will likely become extinct, causing a critical link to the human past to be permanently lost.  Accordingly, preventing logs from these forests from reaching foreign markets has been a major focus of [[Greenpeace]] actions, especially in 2002.

==See also==
*[[fair trade]]
*[[biosafety]]
*[[biosecurity]]
*[[biodiversity]]

==External links==

* [http://www.greenpeace.org/politics/wto/ciel.pdf &quot;Safe Trade in the 21st Century&quot;, Greenpeace, Center for Environmental Law]

[[Category:International trade]]
[[Category:Environment]]</text>
      <sha1>grswar8sd9z9uhaep4rhjezn6u5fzme</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
