<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Sales tax</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>296328</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520991333</id>
      <parentid>514554931</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T01:57:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Guest2625</username>
        <id>14410800</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22247">{{Taxation}}
A '''sales tax''' is a [[tax]] paid to a governing body by a seller for the sales of certain goods and services. Usually laws allow (or require) the seller to collect funds for the tax from the consumer at the [[point of purchase]]. 

Laws may allow sellers to itemized the tax separately from the price of the goods or services, or require it to be included in the price ([[tax-inclusive]]). The tax amount is usually calculated by applying a [[percentage]] rate to the taxable price of a sale.

When a tax on goods or services is paid to a governing body directly by a consumer, it is usually called a [[use tax]].

Often laws provide for the [[Tax exemption|exemption]] of certain goods or services from sales and use tax.

==Types==
[[File:The bill.jpg|thumb|upright|Cash register receipt showing sales tax]]
A conventional or retail sales tax is only levied on the sale of a good to its final end user. Sales to businesses who later resell the goods are not charged the tax. A purchaser who is not an end user is usually issued a &quot;resale certificate&quot; by the taxing authority and required to provide the certificate (or its ID number) to a seller at the point of purchase, along with a statement that the item is for resale. The tax is otherwise charged on each item sold to purchasers who do not provide such a certificate and who are under the jurisdiction of the taxing authority.&lt;ref name=&quot;resale&quot;&gt;[http://business.marylandtaxes.com/taxinfo/salesanduse/resold.asp Purchases for Resale] Maryland State Comptroller's website. Retrieved 2010-05-19&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://business.marylandtaxes.com/news/taxtips/business/bustip4.pdf|title=Business tax tip #4: If You Make Purchases for Resale|publisher=Maryland Comptroller of the Treasury|accessdate=April 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other types of sales taxes, or similar taxes, include:

*[[Gross receipts tax]]es, levied on all sales of a business. This tax has been criticized for its &quot;cascading&quot; or &quot;pyramiding&quot; effect, in which an item is taxed more than once as it makes its way from production to final retail sale.&lt;ref name=&quot;tfstudy&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.taxfoundation.org/news/show/2061.html|title=Tax Pyramiding: The Economic Consequences of Gross Receipts Taxes|publisher=Tax Foundation|last=Chamberlain|first=Andrew|coauthors=Fleenor, Patrick|date=2006-12-01|accessdate=2007-02-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Excise tax]]es, applied to a narrow range of products, such as gasoline or alcohol, usually imposed on the producer or wholesaler rather than the retail seller.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ato.gov.au/businesses/pathway.aspx?pc=001/003/095|title=Excise essentials|publisher=Australian Taxation Office|accessdate=April 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Use tax]], imposed directly on the consumer of goods purchased without sales tax, generally items purchased from a vendor who is not under the jurisdiction of the taxing authority (e.g., a vendor in another state). Use taxes are commonly imposed by states with a sales tax, but are usually only enforced for large items such as automobiles and boats.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.house.leg.state.mn.us/hrd/pubs/usetax.pdf|title=Use Tax Collection on Income Tax Returns in Other States|author=Nina Manzi|date=June 2010|work=Policy Brief|publisher=Minnesota House of Representatives Research Department|page=4|accessdate=April 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Securities turnover excise tax]], a tax on the trade of securities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.commondreams.org/view/2008/09/26|title=How Wall Street Can Bail Itself Out Without Destroying The Dollar|publisher=CommonDreams.org|author=Thom Hartmann|date=September 26, 2008|accessdate=April 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Value added tax|Value added taxes]], in which tax is charged on all sales, thus avoiding the need for a system of resale certificates. Tax cascading is avoided by applying the tax only to the difference (&quot;value added&quot;) between the price paid by the first purchaser and the price paid by each subsequent purchaser of the same item.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.liechtenstein.li/en/eliechtenstein_main_sites/portal_fuerstentum_liechtenstein/fl-wuf-wirtschaft_finanzen/fl-wuf-steuern/fl-wuf-steuern-mehrwertsteuer.htm|title=Value added tax|publisher=Government Spokesperson’s Office, Principality of Liechtenstein|accessdate=April 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[FairTax]], a proposed federal sales tax, intended to replace the U.S. federal income tax.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://people.bu.edu/kotlikoff/WSJ%20Op%20Ed%203-7-05.pdf|title=The Case for the 'FairTax'|work=The Wall Street Journal|date=March 7, 2005|author=Laurence J. Kotlikoff|page=A18|accessdate=April 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Turnover tax]], similar to a sales tax, but applied to intermediate and possibly capital goods as an [[indirect tax]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sars.gov.za/home.asp?pid=43122#1|title=What is turnover tax and how does it work?|work=Turnover Tax for Small Business|publisher=South African Revenue Service|accessdate=April 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Most countries in the world have sales taxes or value-added taxes at all or several of the national, state, county or city government levels. Countries in [[Western Europe]], especially in [[Scandinavia]] have some of the world's highest valued-added taxes. [[Norway]], [[Denmark]] and [[Sweden]] have higher VATs at 25%, [[Hungary]] has the highest at 27%,&lt;ref&gt;[http://ec.europa.eu/taxation_customs/resources/documents/taxation/vat/how_vat_works/rates/vat_rates_en.pdf VAT Rates Applied in the Member States of the European Community] European Commission Taxation and Customs Union (2009-7-1), retrieved 2009-12-7&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.skatteetaten.no/no/Bibliotek/Publikasjoner/Brosjyrer-og-boker/Guide-to-Value-Added-Tax-in-Norway/?chapter=7174 Guide to Value Added Tax in Norway] Skatteetaten (2009-4-7), retrieved 2009-12-7&lt;/ref&gt; although reduced rates are used in some cases, as for groceries, art, books and newspapers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.walletpop.co.uk/2010/06/28/how-to-beat-the-vat-hike-on-groceries/|title=How to beat the VAT hike on groceries|author=Julia Kollewe|date=June 28, 2010|work=Wallet Pop UK|accessdate=April 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In some jurisdictions of the United States, there are multiple levels of government which each impose a sales tax. For example, sales tax in [[Chicago]] [[Cook County, Illinois|(Cook County)]], IL is 10.25%—consisting of 6.25% state, 1.25% city, 1.75% county and 1% regional transportation authority. Chicago also has the Metropolitan Pier and Exposition Authority tax on food and beverage of 1% (which means eating out is taxed at 11.25%).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.revenue.state.il.us/Publications/taxratefinder.htm Tax Rate Finder] Illinois Revenue official website, retrieved 2009-12-7&lt;/ref&gt;  

For Baton Rouge, Louisiana, the tax is 9%, consisting of 4% state and 5% local rate.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.laota.com/parish2/East_Baton_Rouge_Parish.html Sales and Use Tax Rates effective 7/1/2009] East Baton Rouge Parish, retrieved 2009-12-7&lt;/ref&gt;

In California, sales taxes are made up of various state, county and city taxes.  The state tax is &quot;imposed upon all retailers&quot; for the &quot;privilege of selling tangible personal property at retail.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boe.ca.gov/lawguides/business/current/btlg/vol1/sutl/6051.html|title=Chapter 2: Imposition and rate of sales tax|work=Sales and Use Tax Law|publisher=California State Board of Equalization|year=2011|accessdate=July 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Strictly speaking, only the retailer is responsible for the payment of the tax; when a retailer adds this tax to the purchase price, the consumer is merely reimbursing the retailer by contractual agreement.  When consumers purchase goods from out-of-state (in which case the seller owes no tax to California) the consumer is required to pay a &quot;use tax&quot; which is identical to the sales tax.  Use tax is levied upon the &quot;storage, use, or other consumption in this state of tangible personal property.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boe.ca.gov/lawguides/business/current/btlg/vol1/sutl/6201.html|title=Chapter 3: Imposition and rate of use tax|work=Sales and Use Tax Law|publisher=California State Board of Equalization|year=2001|accessdate=July 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Consumers are responsible for declaring these purchases in the same filing as their annual state income tax, but it is rare for them to do so.  An exception is out of state purchase of automobiles, in which case use tax is collected by the state as part of registering the vehicle in California.

The trend has been for conventional sales taxes to be replaced by more broadly based value added taxes. Value added taxes provide an estimated 20 percent of worldwide tax revenue and have been adopted by more than 140 countries. The United States is now one of the few countries to retain conventional sales taxes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.taxanalysts.com/www/freefiles.nsf/Files/JAMES-2.pdf/$file/JAMES-2.pdf|title=Exploring the Origins and Global Rise of VAT|author=Kathryn James|publisher=Tax Analysts|work=The VAT Reader|accessdate=April 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Effects==
Sales taxes are often seen as good tax systems for economic growth, savings, and investment.  Economists at the [[Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development]] studied the effects of various types of taxes on the economic growth of developed nations within the OECD and found that sales taxes are one of the least harmful taxes for growth.&lt;ref name=&quot;uncompetitive&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url= http://online.wsj.com/article/SB121875570585042551.html|title=America the Uncompetitive|publisher=Wall Street Journal editorial|date=August 15, 2008|accessdate=2010-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some people{{who|date=July 2012}} consider sales taxes to be [[Regressive tax|regressive]]; that is, they believe that the tax imposes a greater burden on low-income families than wealthy families. However, it has been suggested that any regressive effect of a sales tax could be mitigated, e.g., by excluding rent, or by exempting &quot;necessary&quot; items, such as food, clothing and medicines.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.itepnet.org/whopays3.pdf|title=Who Pays? A distributed analysis of the tax systems in all 50 states, 3rd edition|publisher=The Institute on Taxation &amp; Economic Policy|date=November 2009|author=Carl Davis, Kelly Davis, Matthew Gardner, Robert S. McIntyre, Jeff McLynch, All Sapozhnikov|accessdate=2010-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Enforcement of tax on remote sales===
In the United States, every state with a sales tax law has a use tax component in that law applying to purchases from out-of-state mail order, catalog and e-commerce vendors, a category also known as &quot;remote sales&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Michigan&quot; /&gt; As e-commerce sales have grown in recent years, noncompliance with use tax has had a growing impact on state revenues. The Congressional Budget Office estimated that uncollected use taxes on remote sales in 2003 could be as high as $20.4 billion. Uncollected use tax on remote sales was projected to run as high as $54.8 billion for 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;CBO&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cbo.gov/ftpdocs/46xx/doc4638/10-20-InternetTax.pdf|title=Economic Issues in Taxing Internet and Mail-Order Sales|publisher=Congressional Budget Office|date=October 2003|accessdate=April 15, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Enforcement of the tax on remote sales, however, is difficult. Unless the vendor has a physical location, or ''nexus'', within a state, the vendor cannot be required to collect tax for that state.&lt;ref name=&quot;Michigan&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.michigan.gov/taxes/0,1607,7-238-43529-155531--,00.html|title=Facts on Internet and Mail Order Purchases|publisher=Michigan Department of Treasury|accessdate=April 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; This limitation was defined as part of the [[Dormant Commerce Clause]] by the Supreme Court in the 1967 decision on [[National Bellas Hess v. Illinois]]. An attempt to require a Delaware e-commerce vendor to collect North Dakota tax was overturned by the court in the 1992 decision on [[Quill Corp. v. North Dakota]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CBO&quot; /&gt;

The Internet Tax Freedom Act of 1998 established a commission to study the possibility of internet taxation, but the commission did not make any formal recommendations. In a report in 2003, the Congressional Budget Office warned of the economic burden of a &quot;multiplicity of tax systems, particularly for smaller firms&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;CBO&quot; /&gt;

In an effort to reduce the burden of compliance with the tax laws of multiple jurisdictions, the [[Streamlined Sales Tax Project]] was organized in March 2000. Cooperative efforts in this project by 44 state governments and the District of Columbia eventually produced the Streamlined Sales and Use Tax Agreement in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.streamlinedsalestax.org/index.php?page=modules|title=Streamlined Sales and Use Tax Agreement|date=December 13, 2010|publisher=Streamlined Sales Tax Governing Board, Inc.|accessdate=April 21, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; This agreement establishes standards necessary for simplified and uniform sales tax laws. As of December 2010, 24 states had passed legislation conforming with the agreement. Whether the Streamlined Sales Tax can actually be applied to remote sales ultimately depends upon Congressional support, because the 1992 Quill v. North Dakota decision determined that only the U.S. Congress has the authority to enact interstate taxes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.streamlinedsalestax.org/index.php?page=faqs|title=Frequently Asked Questions|publisher=Streamlined Sales Tax Governing Board, Inc.|accessdate=April 21, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
===Early examples===
A tax imposed on the sale of goods is depicted on the walls of ancient Egyptian tombs, which have been dated as far back as 2000 BC. These paintings describe the collection of tax for specific commodities, such as cooking oil.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fox&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cber.bus.utk.edu/staff/mnmecon338/foxipt.pdf|title=History and Economic Impact: Sales Tax History|author=William F. Fox|date=March 13, 2002|publisher=University of Tennessee Knoxville, Center for Business and Economic Research|accessdate=April 15, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sales tax amounts, measured in drachmas at a rate of one percent, were recorded in a separate column of a record prepared for the auction of 16 slaves in [[Piraeus]], Greece in 415 BC.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=vkguTquQ3igC&amp;pg=PA188&amp;lpg=PA188&amp;dq=Ancient+Greek+sales+tax#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|title=Ancient Greece: Social and Historical Documents from Archaic Times to the Death of Alexander the Great, 3rd Edition|page=188|author=Dillon, Matthew and Garland, Lynda|year=2010|publisher=Routledge, New York|isbn=ISBN 0-203-85455-1|accessdate=April 15, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nearby [[Athens]] collected duties on the import and export of commodities, recorded at a rate of two percent in 399 BC. At that period of time, Athens did not rely on government agencies to collect its taxes; the responsibility was delegated to the highest bidder, a practice known as [[tax farming]].&lt;ref&gt;Dillon and Garland, p. 41&lt;/ref&gt;

The Roman emperor [[Augustus]] collected [[funds]] for his military [[aerarium]] in AD 6 with a one percent general sales tax, known as the ''centesima rerum venalium'' (hundredth of the value of everything sold).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=uBDGAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA193&amp;lpg=PA193&amp;dq=centesima+rerum+venalium#v=onepage&amp;q=centesima%20rerum%20venalium&amp;f=false|title=Some Roman Trade Routes Along the Pathway of the Great War|work=The Historical Outlook: The History Teacher's Magazine|page=193|volume=IX|author=S. Percy R. Chadwick|publisher=McKinley Publishing Company, New York|date=January–December, 1918|accessdate=April 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Roman sales tax was later reduced to a half percent (''ducentesima'') by [[Tiberius]], then abolished completely by [[Caligula]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/secondary/SMIGRA*/Vectigalia.html|title=Vectigalia|work=A Dictionary of Greek and Roman Antiquities|author=Leonhard Schmitz|page=1184|publisher=John Murray, London|year=1875|accessdate=April 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===In the United States===
{{Main|Sales taxes in the United States}}
Although the United States government has never used a general sales tax, an excise tax on whiskey enacted in 1791 was one of its first fund raising efforts. The unpopularity of this tax with farmers on the western frontier led to the [[Whiskey Rebellion]] in 1794. 

Federal and state sales taxes in the United States remained selective, rather than general, through the 19th century. However, excise taxes were applied to so many specific commodities during the [[Civil War (United States)|Civil War]] that they functioned collectively as a general sales tax.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fox&quot; /&gt;

The first broad-based, general sales taxes in the United States were enacted by Kentucky and Mississippi in 1930, although Kentucky repealed its sales tax in 1936. Twenty-two other states began imposing general sales taxes later in the 1930s, followed by six in the 1940s and five in the 1950s. Kentucky re-enacted its sales tax law in 1960. Eleven more states enacted sales tax laws during the 1960s, with Vermont as the last in 1969. Only five states currently do not have general sales taxes: Alaska, Delaware, Montana, New Hampshire, and Oregon.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fox&quot; /&gt;

The 2010 health care reform law imposed a 10 percent federal sales tax on indoor tanning services, effective July 1, 2010. Unlike previous federal excise taxes, this tax is collected directly from the consumer by the seller and based on the sale price rather than a quantity. However, the new tax is ''selective'' rather than general, applying only to a specific service.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.journalofaccountancy.com/Web/20102724.htm Tax Provisions in the Health Care Act] AICPA Journal of Accountancy, retrieved 2010-04-02&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://healthreformstat.com/senate-bill-homepage/h-r-3590-sec-10907/ H.R. 3590 Sec. 10907] HealthReformStat, retrieved 2010-04-02&lt;/ref&gt;

===In Canada===
{{main|Sales taxes in Canada}}
Canada uses a value-added federal [[Goods and Services Tax (Canada)|Goods and Services Tax]] (GST) with a rate of 5 percent, effective since January 1, 2008. Every province in Canada except Alberta has either a [[Provincial Sales Tax]] (PST) or the [[Harmonized Sales Tax]] (HST), which is a single, blended combination of the GST and PST.

==Sales tax avoidance==
Businesses can reduce the impact of sales tax for themselves and their customers by planning for the tax consequences of all activities. Sales tax avoidance often includes the following:
* Designing invoices to reduce the taxable portion of a sale transaction. In Maryland, for example, a delivery charge is exempt from the tax when stated separately from handling and other taxable charges.&lt;ref&gt;[http://business.marylandtaxes.com/faq/faqanssalesuse/q1.asp What is included in the taxable price?] Maryland State Comptroller's website. Retrieved 2010-05-19&lt;/ref&gt;
* New facilities. Jurisdictions with no sales tax or broad exemptions for certain types of business operations would be an obvious consideration in selecting a site for a new manufacturing plant, warehouse or administrative office.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=yy0AVSwido8C&amp;pg=PT389&amp;lpg=PT389&amp;dq=manufacturing+exemption+multistate#v=onepage&amp;q=manufacturing%20exemption%20multistate&amp;f=false|title=Multistate Corporate Tax Guide 2009, Volume II Sales/Use Tax|page=373|author=Healy, John C. and Schadewald, Michael S.|year=2008|isbn=978-0-8080-9229-2|publisher=CCH Group|accessdate=April 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Delivery location. For a businesses operating in several jurisdictions, choosing the best location in which to take delivery can reduce or eliminate the sales tax liability. This is particularly important for an item to be sold or used in another jurisdiction with a lower tax rate or an exemption for that item. Businesses should consider whether a temporary storage exemption applies to merchandise initially accepted in a jurisdiction with a higher tax rate.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=yy0AVSwido8C&amp;pg=PT381&amp;lpg=PT381&amp;dq=temporary+storage+exemption&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=BM79lWwYcV&amp;sig=MYNjZgnGMHesvjFChgsxBpTajCI&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=kgCnTfnfLKWG0QGyyrn5CA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CCkQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=temporary%20storage%20exemption&amp;f=false Healy and Schadewald, p. 365]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Review of company purchases to determine whether tax was paid in error for equipment and supplies qualifying for exemptions, especially in jurisdictions with broad manufacturing exemptions. Some jurisdictions allow refunds as long as three or even four years after the tax was paid.&lt;ref&gt;[http://business.marylandtaxes.com/taxinfo/salesanduse/production/default.asp Production Exemptions.] Maryland State Comptroller's website. Retrieved 2010-05-20&lt;/ref&gt;
* Periodic review of record-keeping procedures related to sales and use tax. Proper supporting detail, including exemption and resale certificates, invoices and other records must be available to defend the company in the event of a sales and use tax audit. Without proper documentation, a seller can be held liable for tax not collected from a buyer.&lt;ref name=&quot;resale&quot; /&gt;

In the United States, online retailers who have no physical presence in a given state can ship goods to customers there without collecting that state's sales tax, because as of 2011, there is no federal sales tax.  [[Amazon.com]] has been criticized for not collecting sales tax, and has intentionally disaffiliated itself from businesses in certain states to continue doing so legally.

{{further2|[[Amazon tax]]}}

==See also==
* [[Consumption tax]]
* [[Excise tax]]
* [[FairTax]]
* [[Goods and Services Tax (Australia)]]
* [[Sales Tax Audit]]
* [[Sales taxes in Canada]]
* [[Sales taxes in the United States]]
* [[Streamlined Sales Tax Project]]
* [[Turnover tax]]
* [[Value added tax]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Sales Tax}}
[[Category:Sales taxes| ]]

[[de:Umsatzsteuer]]
[[fr:Taxe sur la vente]]
[[hi:बिक्री कर]]
[[is:Söluskattur]]
[[he:מס קנייה]]
[[ja:消費税]]
[[ru:Налог с продаж]]
[[sv:Moms]]
[[te:అమ్మకపు పన్ను]]
[[vi:Thuế gián thu]]
[[zh:消费税]]</text>
      <sha1>0zvd1bkx3fhvaxhn1k5onqywinm6anz</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
