<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>The Experience Economy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>191191</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521649155</id>
      <parentid>521641331</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-06T10:13:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>124.181.152.80</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Stages of marketing a product or service */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6871">The term ''Experience Economy'' was first described in an article published in 1998 by [[B. Joseph Pine II]] and [[James H. Gilmore]], titled &quot;The Experience Economy&quot;. In it they described the experience economy as the next economy following the agrarian economy, the industrial economy, and the most recent [[service economy]]. This concept had been previously researched by many other authors (see History of the Concept). 

Pine and Gilmore argue that businesses must orchestrate memorable events for their customers, and that memory itself becomes the product - the &quot;experience&quot;. More advanced experience businesses can begin charging for the value of the &quot;transformation&quot; that an experience offers, e.g., as [[education]] offerings might do if they were able to participate in the value that is created by the educated individual. This, they argue, is a natural progression in the [[value added]] by the business over and above its inputs.&lt;ref&gt;Pine, J. and Gilmore, J. (1999) ''The Experience Economy'', Harvard Business School Press, Boston, 1999.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the concept of the Experience Economy was born in the business field, it has crossed its frontiers to tourism, architecture, nursing, urban planners and other fields. 

The Experience Economy is also considered to be the main underpinning for [[customer experience management]].

Within the hospitality management academic programs in the US and Europe, Experience Economy is often shortened to Exponomy and is of increasing focus.

==History of the concept==

This customer behavior in the society has been acknowledged by various authors. An early example is the book of [[Alvin Toffler]], [[Future Shock]], which Pine and Gilmore quote in their work. In 1971, Toffler criticized how “economists have great difficulty imagining alternatives to communism and capitalism”, and how they could only envision the economy in the terms of scarcity of resources. He talked about the upcoming “experiential industry”, in which people in the “future”, would be willing to allocate high percentages of their salaries to live amazing experiences.
Later in 1982, Holbrook and Hirschman’s pioneering article &quot;The Experiential Aspects of Consumption: Consumer Fantasies, Feelings, and Fun&quot; in the Journal of Consumer Research (Vol. 9, #2), discussed emotional experiences linked to products and services.  
Then in 1992, the German sociologist Gerhard Schulze argued for the idea of the “experience society” in his book &quot;Erlebnisgesellschaft&quot;, which was translated into English as &quot;The Experience Society&quot; in 1995. In 1999, it was published at the same time a twin book of &quot;The Experience Economy&quot;, that is ''The Dream Society'' by [[Rolf Jensen]] of the [[Copenhagen Institute for Futures Studies]], containing many of the same ideas.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.allbusiness.com/specialty-businesses/1144934-1.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Stages of marketing a product or service==

A core argument is that because of technology, increasing competition,and the increasing expectations of consumers, services today are starting to look like [[commodity|commodities]].  Products can be placed on a continuum from undifferentiated (referred to as commodities) to highly [[product differentiation|differentiated]]. Just as service markets build on goods markets which in turn build on [[commodity market]]s, so transformation and experience markets build on these newly commoditized services, e.g. Internet [[Bandwidth (computing)|bandwidth]], [[Consultant|consulting]] help.

The classification for each stage in the evolution of [[product (business)|products]] is:
*A '''commodity business''' charges for undifferentiated products.
*A '''goods business''' charges for distinctive, tangible things.
*A '''service business''' charges for the activities you perform.
*An '''experience business''' charges for the feeling customers get by engaging it.
*A '''transformation business''' charges for the benefit customers (or &quot;guests&quot;) receive by spending time there.

Proceeding to the next stage more or less requires giving away products at the more commodified level.  For instance, to charge for a service such as new car warranties, one must be prepared to give away new cars to replace &quot;[[lemon (automobile)|lemon]]s&quot;.  And to charge for transformations, one must be prepared to risk not being paid for the time one spends working with customers who don't &quot;transform&quot;.

Pine and Gilmore draw on [[The Walt Disney Company|Walt Disney]], [[AOL]], [[Nordstrom]], [[Starbucks]], [[Saturn Corporation|Saturn]], [[Kanye West]], [[IBM]] and many others as examples.

==Criticisms==

Pine and Gilmore's thesis has been criticized as an example of an over-hyped [[business philosophy]] arising from or in the [[dot-com bubble|dot-com boom]] and a rising economy in the [[United States|U.S.]] that was tolerant of high prices, inflated claims, and no limitations of supply or [[investment]].  Detractors contrast it with other service economy theses such as [[Natural Capitalism]], in which there is a clear focus on making measurably better use of scarce resources, usually considered to be the basis of [[economics]]. They claim service management should stress [[economic efficiency|efficiency]] more than effectiveness. 


The thesis has also been criticized from within the fields of tourism, leisure and hospitality studies where theories as to the role of experiences in the economy were already well established prior to the work of Pine and Gilmore but were not acknowledged by Pine and Gilmore in their work. Although continuing to influence business thinking the concept has already been superseded within much service marketing and management literature by the argument that the value of all goods and services are co-created or co-produced through the interaction of consumers and producers. Therefore, at one level of abstraction all consumption can be understood in experiential terms.

== References ==
{{reflist}}
* Pine, J. and Gilmore, J. (1999) ''The Experience Economy'', Harvard Business School Press, Boston, 1999.

* Schmitt, B. (2003) ''Customer Experience Management'', The Free Press, New York, 2003.

* Schmitt, B. and Simonson, A. (1997) In ''Marketing Aesthetics:The strategic management of brands, identity, and image'' The Free Press, New York, 1997.

&lt;!--
     Do not place advertisements here.
     COMMERCIAL LINKS WILL BE REMOVED.
     See Talk, WP:EL, and WP:SPAM for more information.
     Wikipedia is not a link directory.  Consider submitting your link to DMOZ instead.
--&gt;

{{DEFAULTSORT:Experience Economy}}
[[Category:Services management and marketing]]
[[Category:Strategic management]]
[[Category:Marketing books]]
[[Category:Article Feedback 5]]

[[da:Oplevelsesøkonomi]]
[[simple:Experience economy]]
[[sv:Upplevelseindustri]]
[[tr:İş Hayatı Bir Tiyatro ve de Her Şirket Bir Sahne]]</text>
      <sha1>sq6yqgmorub0duo350hqqayjw0lzvi9</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
