<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Transformation problem</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>220751</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519730796</id>
      <parentid>519552054</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-25T09:55:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jack Upland</username>
        <id>399595</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="41539">{{About|the transformation problem in economics|the transformation problem in group theory|Conjugacy problem }}
{{Marxian economics |expanded=Topics}}
In 20th-century discussions of [[Karl Marx]]'s [[Marxian economics|economics]] the '''transformation problem''' is the problem of finding a general rule to transform the &quot;values&quot; of commodities (based on socially necessary labour content according to his [[labour theory of value]]) into the &quot;competitive prices&quot; of the marketplace. This problem was first introduced by Marx in Chapter 9 of ''[[Das Kapital|Capital]]'s'' draft Volume III, where he also sketched a solution. The essential difficulty was this: given that Marx derived profit, in the form of [[surplus value]], from direct labour inputs, and that the ratio of direct labour input to capital input varied widely between commodities, how could he reconcile this with the tendency to an average rate of profit on all capital invested?

==Marx's theory==
Marx defines [[Exchange value|value]] as the number of hours of labor contained in a commodity. This includes two elements: First, it includes the hours that a worker of normal skill and dedication would take to produce a commodity under average conditions and with the usual equipment (Marx terms this living labor). Second, it includes the labor embodied in raw materials, tools and machinery used up or worn away during its production (which Marx terms &quot;dead labor&quot;). Workers work a portion of their day reproducing the value of their means of subsistence (represented as wages), and a portion of their day producing value above and beyond that, referred to as [[surplus value]].

Since according to Marx the source of capitalist profit is this [[surplus labor]] of the workers, and since in this theory only new, living labor produces profit, it would appear to be logical that enterprises with a low [[Organic composition of capital|organic composition]] (a higher proportion of capital spent on new living labor) would have a higher rate of profit than enterprises with a high organic composition (a higher proportion of capital spent on raw materials and means of production). However, higher rates of profit are not generally found in low-organic composition enterprises or vice versa{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}. Instead, there is a tendency toward [[Surplus value#Equalization of rates of surplus value|equalization of the rate of profit]] in industries of different organic compositions. 

Marx outlined the transformation problem as a theoretical solution to this discrepancy. The tendency of the rate of profit toward equalization means that in this theory there is no simple translation from value to money – e.g. ''1 hour of value equals 20 dollars'' – which is the same across every sector of the economy. While such a simple translation may hold approximately true in general, Marx postulated that there is an economy-wide, systematic deviation according to the organic compositions of the different industries in society, such that ''1 hour of value equals 20 dollars times T'', where ''T'' represents a transformation factor which varies according to the organic composition of the industry in consideration. 

In this theory, ''T'' is approximately 1 in industries where the organic composition is close to average, it is less than 1 in industries where the organic composition is lower than average, and greater than 1 in industries where the organic composition is higher than average.

Note: It should be recalled that because Marx is considering only [[Socially necessary labour time|socially necessary, simple labor]], this variation from industry to industry has nothing to do with higher-paid skilled, versus lower-paid unskilled labor. This transformation factor varies only with respect to the organic compositions of different industries.

==British classical labour theory of value==
Marx's value theory was developed from the [[labour theory of value]] discussed by [[Adam Smith]] and used by many British [[classical economists]].  It became central to his economics.

===Simplest case: labour costs only===
Consider the very simple example used by Adam Smith to introduce the subject. Assume a hunters’ economy with free land, no slavery and no significant current production of tools, where beavers &lt;math&gt;(B)&lt;/math&gt; and deer &lt;math&gt;(D)&lt;/math&gt; are hunted. In the language of modern [[linear production models]], call the unit labour-input requirement for the production of each good &lt;math&gt;l_i&lt;/math&gt;, where &lt;math&gt;i&lt;/math&gt; may be &lt;math&gt;B&lt;/math&gt; or &lt;math&gt;D&lt;/math&gt; (i.e., &lt;math&gt;l_i&lt;/math&gt; is the number of hours of uniform labour normally required to catch either a beaver or a deer; notice that we need to assume labour as uniform in order to be able, later on, to use a uniform wage rate).

Then&amp;mdash;Smith noticed&amp;mdash;each hunter will be willing to exchange one deer (which costs him &lt;math&gt;l_D&lt;/math&gt;hours) for &lt;math&gt;{l_D \over l_B}&lt;/math&gt; beavers. The ratio &lt;math&gt;{l_D \over l_B}&lt;/math&gt;&amp;mdash;i.e. the relative amount of labour embodied in (unit) deer production with respect to beaver&amp;mdash;gives thus the exchange ratio between deer and beavers, the &quot;relative price&quot; of deer in units of beavers. Moreover, since the only costs are here labour costs, that ratio is also the &quot;relative unit cost&quot; of deer for any given competitive uniform wage rate &lt;math&gt;w&lt;/math&gt;. Hence the relative amount of labour embodied in deer production coincides with the ''competitive relative price'' of deer in units of beavers, which can be written as &lt;math&gt;{P_D \over P_B}&lt;/math&gt; (where the &lt;math&gt;P&lt;/math&gt; stands for absolute competitive prices in some arbitrary unit of account, and are defined as &lt;math&gt;P_i = wl_i&lt;/math&gt;).

===Capital costs===
Things get less simple if production uses some scarce [[capital good]] as well. Suppose that hunting requires also some arrows &lt;math&gt;(A)&lt;/math&gt;, with input coefficients equal to &lt;math&gt;a_i&lt;/math&gt;, meaning that to catch for instance one beaver you need to use &lt;math&gt;a_B&lt;/math&gt; arrows, besides &lt;math&gt;l_B&lt;/math&gt; hours of labour. Now the unit total cost (or absolute competitive price) of beavers and deer becomes:

:&lt;math&gt;P_i = wl_i + k_A a_i , (i = B, D) &lt;/math&gt;

where &lt;math&gt;k_A&lt;/math&gt; stands for the capital cost incurred in using each arrow.

Now, this capital cost is made up of two parts. First, there is the replacement cost of substituting the arrow when it is lost in production. This is &lt;math&gt;P_A&lt;/math&gt;, or the competitive price of the arrows, times the proportion &lt;math&gt;h \le 1&lt;/math&gt; of arrows lost after each shot. Second, there is the net rental or return required by the arrows' owner (who might or might not be the same person as the hunter using it). This can be expressed as the product &lt;math&gt;r P_A&lt;/math&gt;, where &lt;math&gt;r&lt;/math&gt; is the (uniform) ''net rate of return'' of the system.

Summing up, and assuming a uniform replacement rate &lt;math&gt;h&lt;/math&gt;, the absolute competitive prices of beavers and deer may be written as:

:&lt;math&gt;P_i = wl_i + (h + r) P_A a_i&lt;/math&gt;

Yet, we still have to determine the arrows' competitive price &lt;math&gt;P_A&lt;/math&gt;. Assuming arrows are produced by labour only, with &lt;math&gt;l_A&lt;/math&gt; man-hours per arrow, we have:

:&lt;math&gt;P_A = wl_A&lt;/math&gt;

Assuming further for simplicity &lt;math&gt;h = 1&lt;/math&gt; (all arrows are lost after just one shot, so that they are [[circulating capital]]), the absolute competitive prices of beavers and deer become:

:&lt;math&gt;P_i = wl_i + (1 + r) wl_A a_i&lt;/math&gt;

Here &lt;math&gt;l_i&lt;/math&gt; is the amount of labour directly embodied in beaver and deer unit production, while &lt;math&gt;l_A a_i&lt;/math&gt; is the labour indirectly thus embodied, through previous arrow production. The sum of the two,

:&lt;math&gt;E_i = l_i + l_A a_i&lt;/math&gt;

gives the total amount of labour embodied.

It is now obvious that the relative competitive price of deer &lt;math&gt;{P_D \over P_B}&lt;/math&gt; can no longer be generally expressed as the ratio between total amounts of labour embodied.  With &lt;math&gt;a_i &gt; 0 &lt;/math&gt; the ratio &lt;math&gt;{E_D \over E_B}&lt;/math&gt; will correspond to &lt;math&gt;{P_D \over P_B}&lt;/math&gt; only in two very special cases: if either &lt;math&gt;r = 0&lt;/math&gt;; or, if &lt;math&gt;{l_B \over l_D} = {a_B \over a_D}&lt;/math&gt;. In general the two ratios will not only differ: &lt;math&gt;{P_D \over P_B}&lt;/math&gt; may change for any given &lt;math&gt;{E_D \over E_B}&lt;/math&gt;, if the net rate of return or the wages vary.

As it will now be seen, this general lack of any functional relationship from &lt;math&gt;{E_D \over E_B}&lt;/math&gt; to &lt;math&gt;{P_D \over P_B}&lt;/math&gt; &amp;mdash;of which Ricardo had been particularly well aware&amp;mdash;is at the heart of Marx's transformation problem.  Although Marx was aware that at equilibrium with no monopoly r=0.  For Marx r was a portion of surplus value.

==Marx’s labour theory of value==

===Surplus value and exploitation===
Marx distinguishes between [[labour power]] as the potential to work, and labour, which is its actual use. He describes labour power as a commodity, and like all commodities, Marx assumes that on average it is exchanged at its value. Its value is determined by the value of the quantity goods required for its reproduction. 

Yet, there is a difference between the value of labour power, and the value produced by that labour power in its use. Unlike other commodities, in its use labour power produces new value beyond that used up by its use. This difference is called [[surplus value]] and is for Marx the source of profit for the capitalists. The appropriation of surplus labor is what Marx denoted as exploitation of labour.

===Labour as the &quot;value-creating substance&quot;===
Marx defined the &quot;value&quot; of [[commodities]] as the total amount of socially necessary labour embodied in their production.  He developed this special brand of the labour theory of value in the first Chapter of ''Capital'''s Volume I.  Due to the influence of Marx's particular definition of value on the transformation problem, he is quoted at length where he argues as follows:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;Let us take two commodities, e.g., corn and iron. The proportions in which they are exchangeable, whatever those proportions may be, can always be represented by an equation in which a given quantity of corn is equated to some quantity of iron: e.g., 1 quarter corn = x cwt. iron. What does this equation tell us? It tells us that in two different things&amp;mdash;in 1 quarter of corn and x cwt. of iron, there exists in equal quantities something common to both. The two things must therefore be equal to a third, which in itself is neither the one nor the other. Each of them, so far as it is exchange value, must therefore be reducible to this third.&quot;
[…]
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;This common 'something' cannot be either a geometrical, a chemical, or any other natural property of commodities. Such properties claim our attention only in so far as they affect the utility of those commodities, make them use values. But the exchange of commodities is evidently an act characterised by a total abstraction from use value.&quot;
[…]
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;If then we leave out of consideration the use value of commodities, they have only one common property left, that of being products of labour. […] Along with the useful qualities of the products themselves, we put out of sight both the useful character of the various kinds of labour embodied in them, and the concrete forms of that labour; there is nothing left but what is common to them all; all are reduced to one and the same sort of labour, human labour in the abstract.&quot;
[…]
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;A use value, or useful article, therefore, has value only because human labour in the abstract has been embodied or materialised in it. How, then, is the magnitude of this value to be measured? Plainly, by the quantity of the value-creating substance, the labour, contained in the article.&quot;
:Karl Marx, [http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1867-c1/ch01.htm#35b/ ''Capital'' Volume I, Chapter 1]
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Variable and constant capital===
As labour produces in this sense more than its own value, the direct-labour input is called [[variable capital]] and denoted as &lt;math&gt;v&lt;/math&gt;.  The amount of value which labour transmits to the deer in our previous example, varies according to the intensity of the exploitation.  In our previous example one has &lt;math&gt;v_i  = l_W l_i&lt;/math&gt;.

By contrast, the value of other inputs&amp;mdash;in our example the indirect (or “dead”) past labour embodied in used up arrows&amp;mdash;is transmitted to the product as it stands, without additions. It is hence called [[constant capital]] and denoted as ''c''. The value transmitted by the arrow to the deer can never be greater than the value of the arrow itself.  In our previous example one has &lt;math&gt;c_i = l_A a_i&lt;/math&gt;.

===Value formulas===
The total value of each produced good is obtained as the sum of the above three elements: constant capital plus variable capital plus surplus value. In our previous example:

:&lt;math&gt;p_i = c_i + v_i + s_i = l_A a_i + l_W l_i + s_i &lt;/math&gt;

Where &lt;math&gt;p_i&lt;/math&gt; stands for the (unit) Marxian value of beavers and deer.

However, from the definition of Marxian value as total labour embodied it must also be true that:

:&lt;math&gt;p_i = l_A a_i + l_i = E_i&lt;/math&gt;

Solving for &lt;math&gt;s_i&lt;/math&gt; the above two relationships one has:

:&lt;math&gt;{s_i \over v_i} = {(1- l_W) \over l_W} = \sigma &lt;/math&gt;

for all &lt;math&gt;i&lt;/math&gt;.

This necessarily uniform ratio &lt;math&gt;{s_i \over v_i} = \sigma&lt;/math&gt; is called by Marx the [[rate of surplus value]], and it allows to re-write Marx's value equations as:

:&lt;math&gt;p_i = c_i + v_i (1 + \sigma) = l_A a_i + l_W l_i (1 + \sigma)&lt;/math&gt;

==Transformation of values into prices==
{{Incoherent|date=January 2012}}
Like Ricardo, Marx knew that ''relative'' labour values&amp;mdash; &lt;math&gt;{p_D \over p_B}&lt;/math&gt; in the above example&amp;mdash;do not generally tally with relative competitive prices&amp;mdash; &lt;math&gt;{P_D \over P_B}&lt;/math&gt; in the same example. However, in the third volume of ''Capital'' he argued that competitive prices were obtained from his values through a '''''transformation''''' process, whereby capitalists ''redistributed'' among themselves the given ''aggregate'' surplus value of the system, in such a way as to bring about a tendency toward a more equal rate of profit &lt;math&gt;r&lt;/math&gt; between sectors of the economy. This happened because of the capitalists' tendency to shift their capital towards the sectors where it earned higher returns. As competition become fierce in a given sector, the rate of return comes down, while the opposite will happen in a sector with a low rate of return. Marx describes this process in detail in [http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1894-c3/ch09.htm chapter 9 of Volume III].

===Marx's reasoning===
The two following tables adapt the deer-beaver-arrow example already seen above (which, of course, is ''not'' found in Marx, and is only a useful simplification), to illustrate Marx's approach. In both cases it is assumed that the total quantities of beavers and deer captured are &lt;math&gt;Q_B&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;Q_D&lt;/math&gt; respectively. It is also supposed that the subsistence real wage is one beaver per unit of labour, so that the amount of labour embodied in it is &lt;math&gt;l_W = E_B = l_A a_B + l_B &lt; 1&lt;/math&gt;.

{| border=&quot;2&quot; cellpadding=&quot;4&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;vertical-align:center;text-align:center; border: 1px #aaa solid; border-collapse: collapse;&quot;
|+'''''Table 1&amp;mdash;Composition of Marxian values in the deer-beaver-arrow production model'''''
|-
 ! Sector
 ! Total Constant Capital &lt;br/&gt; &lt;math&gt;Q_i c_i&lt;/math&gt;
 ! Total Variable Capital &lt;br/&gt; &lt;math&gt;Q_i v_i&lt;/math&gt;
 ! Total Surplus Value &lt;br/&gt;&lt;math&gt; \sigma Q_i v_i&lt;/math&gt;
 ! Unit Value &lt;br/&gt;&lt;math&gt;c_i + (1 + \sigma) v_i&lt;/math&gt;
|-
 ! Beavers
 | &lt;math&gt;Q_B l_A a_B&lt;/math&gt;
 | &lt;math&gt;Q_B(l_A a_B + l_B) l_B&lt;/math&gt;
 | &lt;math&gt;\sigma Q_B (l_A a_B + l_B) l_B &lt;/math&gt;
 | &lt;math&gt;l_A a_B + (1 + \sigma) (l_A a_B + l_B) l_B&lt;/math&gt;
|-
 ! Deer
 | &lt;math&gt;Q_D l_A a_D&lt;/math&gt;
 | &lt;math&gt; Q_D (l_A a_B + l_B) l_D &lt;/math&gt;
 | &lt;math&gt; \sigma Q_D (l_A a_B + l_B) l_D &lt;/math&gt;
 | &lt;math&gt; l_A a_D + (1 + \sigma) (l_A a_B + l_B) l_D &lt;/math&gt;
|-
 ! Total
 |
 |
 | &lt;math&gt; \sigma (l_A a_B + l_B) (Q_B l_B + Q_D l_D) &lt;/math&gt;
 |
|}

Table 1 shows how the total amount of surplus value of the system&amp;mdash;in the last row&amp;mdash;is determined.

{| border=&quot;2&quot; cellpadding=&quot;4&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;vertical-align:center;text-align:center; border: 1px #aaa solid; border-collapse: collapse;&quot;
|+'''''Table 2&amp;mdash;Marx's transformation formulas in the deer-beaver-arrow production model'''''
|-
 ! Sector
 ! Total Constant Capital &lt;br/&gt; &lt;math&gt;Q_i c_i&lt;/math&gt;
 ! Total Variable Capital &lt;br/&gt; &lt;math&gt;Q_i v_i&lt;/math&gt;
 ! Redistributed Total &lt;br/&gt;Surplus Value &lt;br/&gt; &lt;math&gt; rQ_i c_i&lt;/math&gt;
 ! Resulting &lt;br/&gt; Competitive &lt;br/&gt;Price &lt;br/&gt; &lt;math&gt; v_i + (1 + r) c_i&lt;/math&gt;
|-
 ! Beavers
 | &lt;math&gt; Q_B l_A a_B &lt;/math&gt;
 | &lt;math&gt; Q_B (l_A a_B + l_B) l_B &lt;/math&gt;
 | &lt;math&gt; rQ_B l_A a_B &lt;/math&gt;
 | &lt;math&gt; (l_A a_B + l_B) l_B + (1 + r) l_A a_B &lt;/math&gt;
|-
 ! Deer
 | &lt;math&gt; Q_D l_A a_D&lt;/math&gt;
 | &lt;math&gt; Q_D (l_A a_B + l_B) l_D &lt;/math&gt;
 | &lt;math&gt; rQ_D l_A a_D &lt;/math&gt;
 | &lt;math&gt; (l_A a_B + l_B) l_D + (1 + r) l_A a_D &lt;/math&gt;
|-
 ! Total
 |
 |
 |&lt;math&gt;r l_A(Q_B A_B + Q_D a_D) = \sigma (l_A a_B + l_B) (Q_B l_B + Q_D l_D)&lt;/math&gt;
 |
|}

Table 2 then illustrates how Marx thought that this total would be redistributed between the two industries, as “profit” at a uniform return rate ''r'' over constant capital. First, the condition that total “profit” must equal total surplus value – in the last row of table 2 – is used to determine ''r''. The result is then multiplied by the value of the constant capital of each industry, to get its “profit”. Finally, each (absolute) competitive price in labour units is obtained, as the sum of constant capital, variable capital and “profit” per unit of output, in the last column of Table 2.

Tables 1 and 2 parallel the tables in which Marx elaborated his numerical example in [http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1894-c3/ch09.htm Chapter 9 of ''Capital's'' Volume III].

===Marx's error and its correction===
Later scholars argued that Marx's formulas for competitive prices were mistaken.

First, [[competitive equilibrium]] requires a uniform rate of return over constant capital valued at its ''price'', not its Marxian value, contrary to what is done in Table 2 above. Secondly, competitive prices result from the sum of costs valued at the ''prices'' of things, not as amounts of embodied labour. Thus, both Marx's calculation of &lt;math&gt;r&lt;/math&gt; and the sums of his price formulas do not add up in all the normal cases, where&amp;mdash;as in the above example&amp;mdash;relative competitive prices differ from relative Marxian values. Marx noted this, but thought that it was not significant, stating in Chapter 9 of Volume 3 of Capital that &quot;Our present analysis does not necessitate a closer examination of this point.&quot;

The [[simultaneous linear equations]] method of computing competitive (relative) prices in an equilibrium economy is today very well known. In the greatly simplified model of Tables 1 and 2, where by assumption the wages rate is given and equal to the price of beavers, the most convenient way is to express such prices in units of beavers, which means normalising &lt;math&gt;w = P_B = 1&lt;/math&gt;. This immediately yields the (relative) price of arrows as

:&lt;math&gt;P_A = l_A&lt;/math&gt; beavers.

Substituting this into the relative-price condition for beavers

:&lt;math&gt; 1 = l_B + (1 + r) l_A a_B&lt;/math&gt;

gives the solution for the rate of return as

:&lt;math&gt;r = {(1 - l_B) \over (l_A a_B)} - 1&lt;/math&gt;

Finally, the price condition for deer can hence be written as

:&lt;math&gt;P_D = l_D + (1 + r) l_A a_D = l_D + {a_D (1 - l_B) \over a_B} &lt;/math&gt;

This latter result, which gives the correct competitive price of deer in units of beavers for the simple model used here, is generally inconsistent with Marx's price formulae of Table 2.

[[Ernest Mandel]], defending Marx, explains this discrepancy in term of the time frame of production rather than as a logical error, i.e. in this simplified model, capital goods are purchased at a labour value price but final products are sold under prices which reflect redistributed surplus value. [http://www.marxists.org/archive/mandel/19xx/marx/ch04.htm]

===Mathematical vs historical transformation===
Frederick Engels – the editor of ''Capital'''s Volume III – hinted since 1894 at a possibly alternative way to look at the whole matter. His view was that the pure Marxian &quot;law of value&quot; of Volume I and the &quot;transformed&quot; prices of Volume III applied to different periods of economic history. In particular, the &quot;law of value&quot; would have prevailed in the pre-capitalist exchange economies – from Babylon to the fifteenth century of the common era – while the &quot;transformed&quot; prices would have materialized under capitalism: see Engels' quotation by Morishima and Catephores (1975) p.&amp;nbsp;310.

Engels' reasoning was later taken up by Meek (1956) and Nell (1973). These authors argued that – whatever one must say of his interpretation of capitalism – Marx's &quot;value&quot; theory keeps its usefulness as a tool to interpret pre-capitalist societies, because – they maintained – in pre-capitalist exchange economies there were no &quot;prices of production&quot; with a uniform rate of return (or &quot;profit&quot;) on capital. It hence follows that Marx's transformation must have had a ''historical'' dimension, given by the actual transition to capitalist production (an no more Marxian &quot;values&quot;) at the beginning of the modern era. Then this true &quot;historical transformation&quot; could and should take the place of the mathematical transformation postulated by Marx in Chapter 9 of Volume III.

As Althusser and Balibar (1970) and others have pointed out, this proposal runs counter to Marx's own ideas, as expressed in Marx (1859), where one reads:

:&quot;''The point at issue is not the role that various economic relations have played in the succession of various social formations'' appearing in the course of history […], but their position within modern society.&quot; (En. trans. p.210, italics in the original.)

Moreover, the available quantitative research by economic historians has ''not'' generally endorsed Engels' view of antiquity and the Middle Ages as a &quot;value epoch&quot; in the Marxian sense: see for instance Hicks (1969) and Godelier (1973).

===Other Marxist views===
There are several schools of thought among those who see themselves as upholding or furthering Marx on the question of transformation from values to prices, or modifying his theory in ways to make it more consistent.

According to the [[Temporal single-system interpretation]] of &quot;Capital&quot; advanced by Alan Freeman, Andrew Kliman and others, Marx's writings on the subject can be interpreted in such a way as to remove any supposed inconsistencies (Choonara, 2007). Modern traditional Marxists argue that not only does the Labour Theory of Value hold up today, but that Marx's understanding of the Transformation Problem was in the main also correct.&lt;ref name=JG&gt;Joseph Green (2010): [http://www.communistvoice.org/45cTransformation1.html On the non-naturalness of value: A defense of Marx and Engels on the transformation problem (part one)]&lt;/ref&gt;

Political-economic readings of ''Capital'', such as [[Harry Cleaver]]'s ''[[Reading Capital Politically]]'' re-define exploitation as a direct control of worked time, unrelated as such to distribution.  These readings are usually associated with the [[Autonomist Marxism|autonomist]] strand of Marxism, which focuses on production as the key economic site within society.  These readings of ''Capital'' are typically hostile to economics as such, and consider the transformation problem unimportant because they see all social arrangements in capitalism (in particular, profit and distribution) as politically determined contests between classes.

The probabilistic interpretation of Marx advanced by Emmanuel Farjoun and Moshe Machover in ''Laws of Chaos'' (see references). They &quot;''dis''solve&quot; the transformation problem by reconceptualising the relevant quantities as random variables. In particular, they consider profit rates to reach an equilibrium ''distribution''. A heuristic analogy with the statistical mechanics of an ideal gas leads them to the hypothesis that this equilibrium distribution should be a gamma distribution.

Finally, there are Marxist scholars (e.g., [[Anwar Shaikh (Economist)|Anwar Shaikh]], Fred Moseley, Alan Freeman, [[Makoto Itoh]], Gerard Dumenil &amp; Dominique Levy, Duncan Foley) who hold that there exists no incontestable logical procedure by which to derive price magnitudes from value magnitudes, but still think that it has no lethal consequences on his system as a whole. In a few very special cases, Marx's idea of labour as the &quot;substance&quot; of (exchangeable) value would not be openly at odds with the facts of market competitive equilibrium. These authors have argued that such cases&amp;mdash;though not generally observed&amp;mdash;throw light on the &quot;hidden&quot; or &quot;pure&quot; nature of capitalist society. Thus Marx's related notions of surplus value and unpaid labour can still be treated as ''basically'' true, although they hold that the practical details of their workings are more complicated than Marx thought.

In particular, some (e.g. [[Anwar Shaikh (Economist)|Anwar Shaikh]]) have suggested that&amp;mdash;since aggregate surplus value will generally differ from aggregate &quot;profit&quot;&amp;mdash;the former should be in fact treated as a mere ''pre-condition'' for the latter, rather than a full explanation of it. Using input-output data and empirical proxies for labour-values, [[Anwar Shaikh (Economist)|Anwar Shaikh]] &amp; Ochoa have provided some statistical evidence to show that, although there may be no incontestable ''logical'' deduction possible of specific price magnitudes from specific value magnitudes even within a complex model (in contrast to a probabilistic ''prediction''), even a &quot;93% Ricardian theory&quot; of labour-value appears to be a better empirical predictor of price than its rivals.

==Critics of the theory==
Many mathematical economists assert that a set of functions in which Marx's equalities hold does ''not'' generally exist at the individual enterprise or aggregate level, so that Chapter 9's transformation problem has no general solution, outside two classes of very special cases. This was first pointed out by, among others, [[Eugen von Böhm-Bawerk|Böhm-Bawerk]] (1896) and [[Ladislaus Bortkiewicz|Bortkiewicz]] (1906). In the second half of the twentieth century, [[Wassily Leontief|Leontief]]’s and [[Piero Sraffa|Sraffa]]’s work on linear production models provided a framework within which to prove this result in a simple and general way.

Although he never actually mentioned the transformation problem, Sraffa’s (1960) Chapter VI on the &quot;reduction&quot; of prices to &quot;dated&quot; amounts of current and past embodied labour gave implicitly the first general proof, showing that the competitive price &lt;math&gt;P_i&lt;/math&gt; of the &lt;math&gt;i^{th}&lt;/math&gt; produced good can be expressed as

:&lt;math&gt;P_i = \sum_{n=0}^\infty l_{in} w {(1+r)^n}&lt;/math&gt;,

where &lt;math&gt;n&lt;/math&gt; is the time lag, &lt;math&gt;l_{in}&lt;/math&gt; is the lagged-labour input coefficient, &lt;math&gt;w&lt;/math&gt; is the wage and &lt;math&gt;r&lt;/math&gt; is the &quot;profit&quot; (or net return) rate. Since total embodied labour is defined as

:&lt;math&gt;E_i = \sum_{n=0}^\infty l_{in}&lt;/math&gt;,

it follows from Sraffa’s result that there is generally no function from &lt;math&gt;E_i&lt;/math&gt; to &lt;math&gt;P_i&lt;/math&gt;, as was made explicit and elaborated upon by later writers, notably [[Neo-Ricardianism|Ian Steedman]] in ''Marx after Sraffa''.

A standard reference – with an extensive survey of the entire literature pre-1971 and a comprehensive bibliography – is [[Paul Samuelson|Samuelson]]'s (1971) &quot;Understanding the Marxian Notion of Exploitation: A Summary of the So-Called Transformation Problem Between Marxian Values and Competitive Prices&quot; ''Journal of Economic Literature'' '''9''' 2 399&amp;ndash;431.

Since the 1970s several major schools of [[Marxian economics]] have arisen in response to the transformation problem-related challenges of the neoclassical and Sraffian schools. [[Analytical Marxists]] held that the transformation problem disproved the [[Labour Theory of Value]] and based their Marxian social theory on a combination of the [[Fundamental Marxian theorem]], [[game theory]], and other neoclassical and mathematical tools. Empirical Marxists, including [[Anwar Shaikh (economist)|Anwar Shaikh]], [[Moshe Machover]], and [[Paul Cockshott]], maintain that since empirical data bears out the correspondence of prices and labour values, the transformation problem is irrelevant. Followers of the [[Temporal Single System Interpretation]] and the New Interpretation argue that critics have misunderstood Marx's definition of value and that, correctly defined, there is no difference between value and price.

The lack of any function to transform Marx's &quot;values&quot; to competitive prices has important implications for Marx's theory of labour [[exploitation]] and [[capital accumulation|economic dynamics]], namely that, some people argue, there is no [[Tendency of the rate of profit to fall]]. This means that it is not pre-ordained that capitalists must exploit labour to compensate for a declining rate of profit. This implies that Marx's prophecy that worsening labour exploitation would result in an eventual revolution against the capitalist system and the establishment of [[communism]] is logically and mathematically false.

The mathematical proof that Marx's transformation problem has no general solution has been formally questioned [http://www.mtholyoke.edu/~fmoseley/CRITIQUE.pdf] by proponents of the [[Temporal Single System Interpretation]], who argue that the determination of prices by simultaneous linear equations (which assumes that prices are the same at the start and end of the production period) is logically inconsistent with the determination of value by labour time. Other Marxian economists accept the proof, but reject its relevance for some key elements of Marxian political economy. Still others reject Marxian economics outright, and emphasise the politics of the assumed [[relations of production]] instead. To this extent, the transformation problem&amp;mdash;or rather its implications&amp;mdash;is still today a controversial question.

===Non-Marxian critiques===
Mainstream scholars such as Samuelson question the assumption that the basic nature of capitalist production and distribution can be gleaned from unrealistic special cases. For example, in special cases where it apply, Marx's reasoning can be easily turned upside down, through an ''inverse'' transformation process, Samuelson argue that Marx's inference:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;Profit is therefore the [bourgeois] disguise of surplus value which must be removed before the real nature of surplus value can be discovered.&quot; (''Capital'' Volume III, Chapter 2)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

could with equal cogency be “transformed” into:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;Surplus value is therefore the [Marxist] disguise of profit which must be removed before the real nature of profit can be discovered.&quot; [Samuelson (1971) p.417]
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

To further clarify this point, it may be noticed that the special cases in question are also precisely those where [[John Bates Clark|J.B. Clark]]’s old model of ''aggregate'' marginal productivity holds strictly true, leading to equality between the equilibrium levels of the real wage rate and labour's aggregate marginal product, a hypothesis regarded as disproved by all sides during the [[Cambridge capital controversy]]. One would thus have a &quot;pure&quot; state of capitalist society where Marx's [[exploitation theory]] and its main supposed confutation were ''both'' true.

This remarkable result, it is maintained, leads straight to the heart of the matter. Like Clark’s contention about the &quot;fairness&quot; of marginal-productivity wages, so Marx's basic argument&amp;mdash;from the &quot;substance&quot; of value to the concept of exploitation&amp;mdash;is claimed to be a set of non-analytical and non-empirical propositions. That is why, being non-falsifiable, both theories may be found to apply to the same formal and/or empirical object, though they are supposed to negate each other, as [[Karl Popper]]{{Citation needed|date=May 2009}} and many others{{Who|date=May 2009}} had argued.

[[Paul Samuelson]] not only dismissed the labour theory of value because of the transformation problem, but provided himself, in cooperation with economists like [[Carl Christian von Weizsäcker]], solutions. Carl Christian von Weizsäcker 1962,&lt;ref name=CW&gt;Weizsäcker, Carl Christian von (2010): A New Technical Progress Function (1962). German Economic Review  11/3 (first publication of an article written in 1962)&lt;/ref&gt; and, together with Paul Samuelson, 1971&lt;ref name=WS&gt;Weizsäcker Carl Christian von, and [[Paul A. Samuelson]] (1971): A new labor theory of value for rational planning through use of the bourgeois profit rate. Proceedings of the National Acadademy of Sciences U S A. [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC389151/ download of facsimile]&lt;/ref&gt; analysed the problem under the assumption that the economy grows at a constant rate following the [[Golden Rule savings rate|Golden Rule of Accumulation]]. Weizsäcker concludes:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;The price of the commodity today is equal to the sum of the 'present' values of the different labour inputs,...&quot; [Weizsäcker (2010 [1962]) p.262]
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Marxian reply to non-Marxian critiques===

The Marxian reply to this mainstream view is as follows:

* It is important to understand that the attempt to discard the theoretical relevance of the necessary preconditions of Marx's value analysis in volume 1 of Capital through a [[reductio ad absurdum]] is superficial. By first identifying that the preconditions which are necessary for [[John Bates Clark|J.B. Clark]]’s old model of ''aggregate'' marginal productivity to hold true are the same as those which are necessary for Marxian values to conform to relative prices we are then, on a leap of faith which is passed as logic, supposedly to conclude that the foundation of Marx's analysis ''as based in these preconditions'' is faulty ''because'' Clark's model had been proven wrong in the [[Cambridge capital controversy]]. The superficiality stems from the fact that those who support this reduction forget that the [[Cambridge capital controversy]] put the entire concept of marginal productivity into question by attacking not the special case assumptions of Clark but the notion that physical capital can be aggregated. Marx simply does not run into this problem because his analysis does not rely on an aggregation of physical quantities which receive a return based on their contribution as 'factors' of production. The fact that marginal productivity in its aggregate form is 'a hypothesis regarded as disproved by all sides during the [[Cambridge capital controversy]]' simply has nothing to do with the validity of the special cases of Marx, and thus we '''WOULD NOT''' &quot;have a &quot;pure&quot; state of capitalist society where Marx's [[exploitation theory]] and its main supposed confutation (Clark) were ''both'' true&quot;, as is concluded from this view,'' because'' the 'correctness' or 'incorrectness' of Clark's aggregate marginal productivity scheme in this case flows not from special case assumptions but from the fact that he is aggregating physical units of capital - i.e., Clark would still not hold true ''even with'' the assumed special cases. Once again, the bourgeois theorists manage to impress us their erudition while completely sidestepping the substance of the debate.

To further clarify this point, it may be noticed that

*it is firstly argued that it is never possible to provide any absolute scientific proof for the truth of ''any'' particular concept of economic value in economics, because the attribution of economic value itself always involves human and moral interpretations which go beyond facts and logic. By nature, the concept of economic value is not itself a scientifically provable concept but an assumption. Marx himself explicitly ridiculed the idea that he should be required to &quot;prove his concept of value&quot;.

*Secondly, however, the validity of any proposed theory of value depends on its explanatory, [[heuristic]] and predictive power, i.e. whether it makes possible a coherent interpretation of the known facts that can at least to some extent predict observable trends. In this sense, Marx evidently felt that he had &quot;proved&quot; the validity of his concept of value by the integrated theory of capitalist development which it made possible (see also [[law of value]]). What mattered was the ''application'' of the concept.

*Thirdly, once a certain concept of economic value is assumed, certain predictions or explanations can be made on the basis of it, and those explanations or predictions can at least in principle be falsified by reference to logic and observables. And that concept of value can be compared with rival concepts and the rival theories they make possible, in order to establish which has more explanatory or predictive capacity.

*Fourthly, modern [[philosophy of science]] rejects Popper's falsification theory as an adequate portrayal of science. Scientific statements are not necessarily ''falsifiable'' statements but instead ''fallible'' statements (they could be wrong) which, in principle, can be tested against observables, even if contingently we do not yet know technically how to do this. Scientists do not aim mainly to falsify theories, but confirm them to provide usable knowledge.

*Finally, as [[Piero Sraffa]] showed clearly, the theory of the production and distribution of a surplus, however it might be devised, is logically independent of any particular theory of labour-exploitation. Labour-exploitation may occur and be conceptualised in various ways, regardless of which theory of value is held to be true. Consequently, if Marx's theory of labour-exploitation is false, this is a quite separate issue.

==See also==

*[[labour theory of value]]
*[[law of value]]
*[[surplus value]]
*[[socially necessary labour time]]
*[[prices of production]]
*[[capital accumulation]]
*[[return of capital]]
*[[Temporal Single System Interpretation]]

==References==

*Marx, K. (1859) ''Zur Kritik der politischen Oeconomie'', Berlin (trans. ''A Contribution to the Critique of Political Economy'' London 1971).
*Marx, K. (1867) ''Das Kapital'' Volume I.
*Marx, K. (1894) ''Das Kapital'' Volume III (ed. by F. Engels).
*Böhm-Bawerk, E., von (1896) &quot;Zum Abschluss des Marxschen Systems&quot; ''Festgabe für Karl Knies'' Berlin [trans. P. Sweezy ed. (1949) ''Karl Marx and the close of his system by Eugen Böhm-Bawerk and Böhm-Bawerk’s criticism of Marx by Rudolf Hilferding with an appendix by L. von Bortkiewicz''].
*Bortkiewicz, L. von (1906) &quot;Wertrechnung und Preisrechnung im Marxschen System&quot; ''Archiv für Sozialwissenschaft und Sozialpolitik'' 3, XXIII and XXV [trans. &quot;Value and Price in the Marxian System&quot; ''International Economic Papers'' 1952 2 5&amp;ndash;60].
* Choonara, J. (2007) [http://www.isj.org.uk/index.php4?id=353&amp;issue=115 &quot;Marx's &quot;transformation&quot; made easy&quot;]
* Alan Freeman: ''Price, value and profit - a continuous, general treatment.'' In: Alan Freeman, Guglielmo Carchedi (editors): ''Marx and non-equilibrium economics.'' Edward Elgar. Cheltenham, UK, Brookfield, US 1996.
*Meek, R. (1956)  'Some Notes on the Transformation Problem' ''Economic Journal'' '''66''' (March) 94-107.
*Sraffa, P. (1960) ''Production of commodities by means of commodities''.
*Hicks, J. (1969) ''A Theory of Economic History'' Oxford.
*Althusser, L. and E. Balibar (1970) ''Reading 'Capital' '' London.
*Samuelson, P.A. (1971) &quot;Understanding the Marxian Notion of Exploitation: A Summary of the So-Called Transformation Problem Between Marxian Values and Competitive Prices&quot; ''Journal of Economic Literature'' '''9''' 2 399&amp;ndash;431.
*Godelier, M. (1973) ''Horizon, trajets marxistes en anthropologie'' Paris.
*Nell, E.J. (1973) 'Marx's Economics. A Dual Theory of Value and Growth: by Micho Morishima' (book review) ''Journal of Economic Literature'' '''XI''' 1369-71.
*Morishima, M. and G. Catephores (1975) 'Is there an &quot;historical transformation problem&quot;?' ''Economic Journal '''85''' (June) 309-28.
*[[Anwar Shaikh (Economist)|Anwar Shaikh]] papers: [http://homepage.newschool.edu/~AShaikh/]
*Alan Freeman papers: [http://www.iwgvt.org/index.php]
*Fred Moseley papers: [http://home.mtholyoke.edu/~fmoseley/]
*Emmanuel Farjoun and Moshe Machover, ''Laws of Chaos; A Probabilistic Approach to Political Economy'', London: Verso, 1983. [http://www.probabilisticpoliticaleconomy.net] [http://www.free-books.us/Others/317475/Laws-of-Chaos-A-Probabilistic-Approach-to-Political-Economy-Farjoun-Machover Free verso books]
*Makoto Itoh, ''The Basic Theory of Capitalism''.
*Gerard Dumenil &amp; Dominique Levy papers [http://www.jourdan.ens.fr/~levy/]
*Duncan Foley papers [http://cepa.newschool.edu/~foleyd/]
* Hagendorf, Klaus: [http://ssrn.com/paper=1489383 Labour Values and the Theory of the Firm. Part I: The Competitive Firm. Paris: EURODOS; 2009.]

==Notes==
&lt;references/&gt;

{{DEFAULTSORT:Transformation Problem}}
[[Category:Marxist theory]]

[[de:Transformationsproblem]]
[[it:Problema della trasformazione dei valori in prezzi di produzione]]</text>
      <sha1>enqcmh3oa4l72xorpalujxv1497xlod</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
