<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Triple bottom line</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>316929</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522139288</id>
      <parentid>522139196</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T07:14:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Zyxzupf</username>
        <id>17847835</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Criticism */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23199">{{Buzzword|date=February 2012}}
The '''triple bottom line''' (abbreviated as '''TBL''' or '''3BL''', and also known as '''people, planet, profit''' or '''the three pillars'''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.goethe.de/ges/umw/dos/nac/den/en3106180.htm Sustainability – From Principle To Practice] ''[[Goethe-Institut]]'', March 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;) captures an expanded spectrum{{Elucidate|date=February 2012|reason=an expanded spectrum compared to what?}} of values and criteria for measuring organizational (and societal) success: economic, ecological, and social.  With the ratification of the [[United Nations]] and [[ICLEI]] TBL standard for urban and community accounting in early 2007,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unep.org/delc/Portals/119/industrryRoleOfIndclean.pdf Enhancing the role of industry through for example, private-public partnerships], May 2011. [[United Nations Environment Programme]]&lt;/ref&gt; this became the dominant approach to [[public sector]] [[full cost accounting]].  Similar UN standards apply to [[natural capital]] and [[human capital]] measurement to assist in measurements required by TBL, e.g. the EcoBudget standard for reporting [[ecological footprint]].

In the [[private sector]], a commitment to [[corporate social responsibility]] (CSR) implies a commitment to some form of TBL reporting.  This is distinct from the more limited changes required to deal only with ecological issues.

==Definition==

For reporting their efforts companies may demonstrate their commitment to CSR through the following:
*Top-level involvement (CEO, Board of Directors)
*Policy Investments
*Programs
*Staffing resources
*Signatories to voluntary standards
*Principles (UN Global Compact-Ceres Principles)
*Reporting (Global Reporting Initiative)

Triple bottom line (TBL) accounting expands the traditional reporting framework to take into account social and environmental performance in addition to financial performance. In 1981 Freer Spreckley first articulated the triple bottom line in a publication called 'Social Audit - A Management Tool for Co-operative Working'.&lt;ref&gt;Freer Spreckley 1981 [http://www.locallivelihoods.com/cmsms/uploads/PDFs/Social%20Audit%20-%20A%20Management%20Tool.pdf Social Audit - A Management Tool for Co-operative Working]&lt;/ref&gt; In this work, he argued that enterprises should measure and report on social, environmental and financial performance. 

The phrase was coined by [[John Elkington]] in his 1997 book ''Cannibals with Forks: the Triple Bottom Line of 21st Century Business.''&lt;ref&gt;Brown, D., J. Dillard and R.S. Marshall. (2006) [http://www.recercat.net/bitstream/2072/2223/1/UABDT06-2.pdf &quot;Triple Bottom Line: A business metaphor for a social construct.&quot;] Portland State University, School of Business Administration. Retrieved on: 2007-07-18.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bsdglobal.com/tools/principles_triple.asp Business and Sustainable Development: A Global Guide]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sustainability]], itself, was first defined by the [[Brundtland Commission]] of the United Nations in 1987.

1988 also marked the foundation of the ''Triple Bottom Line Investing'' group by [[Robert J. Rubinstein]], a group advocating and publicizing these principles.

The concept of TBL demands that a company's responsibility lies with [[stakeholder (corporate)|stakeholders]] rather than [[shareholders]]. In this case, &quot;stakeholders&quot; refers to anyone who is influenced, either directly or indirectly, by the actions of the firm. According to the [[stakeholder theory]], the business entity should be used as a vehicle for coordinating stakeholder interests, instead of maximizing shareholder (owner) profit.

==Bottom lines==
{{Unreferenced section|date=June 2009}}
The triple bottom line is made up of &quot;social, economic and environmental&quot; factors. 

[[File:Triple Bottom Line graphic.jpg|thumb|Graphic describing the bottom lines]]

&quot;People, planet and profit&quot; succinctly describes the triple bottom lines and the goal of [[sustainability]]. The phrase, &quot;people, planet, profit&quot;, was coined by John Elkington in 1995 while at SustainAbility, and was later adopted as the title of the Anglo-Dutch oil company Shell's first sustainability report in 1997.  As a result, one country in which the 3P concept took deep root was The Netherlands.

'''&quot;People&quot;''' pertains to fair and beneficial business practices toward labour and the community and region in which a corporation conducts its business. A TBL company conceives a reciprocal [[social structure]] in which the well-being of corporate, labour and other stakeholder interests are interdependent.

A triple bottom line enterprise seeks to benefit many constituencies, not exploit or endanger any group of them. The &quot;upstreaming&quot; of a portion of profit from the marketing of finished goods back to the original producer of raw materials, for example, a farmer in [[fair trade]] agricultural practice, is a common feature.  In concrete terms, a TBL business would not use child labour and monitor all contracted companies for child labour exploitation, would pay fair salaries to its workers, would maintain a safe work environment and tolerable working hours, and would not otherwise exploit a community or its labour force. A TBL business also typically seeks to &quot;give back&quot; by contributing to the strength and growth of its community with such things as health care and education. Quantifying this bottom line is relatively new, problematic and often subjective.  The [[Global Reporting Initiative]] (GRI) has developed guidelines to enable corporations and [[NGO]]s alike to comparably report on the social impact of a business.

'''&quot;Planet&quot;''' ([[natural capital]]) refers to sustainable environmental practices. A TBL company endeavors to benefit the natural order as much as possible or at the least do no harm and minimise environmental impact.  A TBL endeavour reduces its [[ecological footprint]] by, among other things, carefully managing its consumption of energy and non-renewables and reducing manufacturing waste as well as rendering waste less toxic before disposing of it in a safe and legal manner. &quot;[[Cradle to grave]]&quot; is uppermost in the thoughts of TBL manufacturing businesses, which typically conduct a [[life cycle assessment]] of products to determine what the true environmental cost is from the growth and harvesting of raw materials to manufacture to distribution to eventual disposal by the end user. A triple bottom line company does not produce harmful or destructive products such as weapons, toxic chemicals or batteries containing dangerous heavy metals, for example.

Currently, the cost of disposing of non-degradable or toxic products is borne financially by governments and environmentally by the residents near the disposal site and elsewhere. In TBL thinking, an enterprise which produces and markets a product which will create a waste problem should not be given a free ride by society. It would be more equitable for the business which manufactures and sells a problematic product to bear part of the cost of its ultimate disposal.

Ecologically destructive practices, such as overfishing or other endangering depletions of resources are avoided by TBL companies. Often environmental sustainability is the more profitable course for a business in the long run. Arguments that it costs more to be environmentally sound are often specious when the course of the business is analyzed over a period of time. Generally, sustainability reporting metrics are better quantified and standardized for environmental issues than for social ones. A number of respected reporting institutes and registries exist including the Global Reporting Initiative, CERES, Institute 4 Sustainability and others.

The eco bottom line is akin to the concept of [[Eco-capitalism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Ekins|first=Paul|title=The Gaia Atlas of Green Economics|year=1992|publisher=Anchor Books|isbn=0-385-41914-7|pages=191}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''&quot;Profit&quot;''' is the economic value created by the organization after deducting the cost of all inputs, including the cost of the capital tied up. It therefore differs from traditional accounting definitions of profit. In the original concept, within a sustainability framework, the &quot;profit&quot; aspect needs to be seen as the real economic benefit enjoyed by the host society.  It is the real economic impact the organization has on its economic environment.  This is often confused to be limited to the internal profit made by a company or organization (which nevertheless remains an essential starting point for the computation).  Therefore, an original TBL approach cannot be interpreted as simply traditional corporate accounting profit ''plus'' social and environmental impacts unless the &quot;profits&quot; of other entities are included as a social benefit.

==Supporting arguments==
{{Refimprove section|date=June 2009}}
The following business-based arguments support the concept of TBL:
*Reaching untapped market potential: TBL companies can find financially profitable niches which were missed when money alone was the driving factor. Examples include:
# Adding [[ecotourism]] or [[geotourism]] to an already rich tourism market such as the [[Dominican Republic]]
# Developing profitable methods to assist existing NGOs with their missions such as fundraising, reaching clients, or creating networking opportunities with multiple NGOs
# Providing products or services which benefit underserved populations and/or the environment which are also financially profitable.

*Adapting to new business sectors: Since many business opportunities are developing in the realm of social entrepreneurialism,&lt;ref&gt;http://socialedge.org&lt;/ref&gt; businesses hoping to reach this expanding market must design themselves to be financially profitable, socially beneficial and ecologically sustainable or fail to compete with those companies who do design themselves as such. For example, [[Fair Trade]] and Ethical Trade companies require ethical and sustainable practices from all of their suppliers and service providers. A business which is planning to work with Fair Trade or Ethical Trade companies must design their business model to be TBL.

[[Fiscal policy]] of governments usually claims to be concerned with identifying social and natural deficits on a less formal basis. However, such choices may be guided more by [[ideology]] than by [[economics]]. The primary benefit of embedding one approach to measurement of these deficits would be first to direct [[monetary policy]] to reduce them, and eventually achieve a global [[monetary reform]] by which they could be systematically and globally reduced in some uniform way.

The argument is that the [[Earth]]'s [[carrying capacity]] is itself at risk, and that in order to avoid catastrophic breakdown of [[climate]] or ecosystem, there is a need for a comprehensive reform in global financial institutions similar in scale to that undertaken at [[Bretton Woods, New Hampshire|Bretton Woods]] in 1944. [[Marilyn Waring]] has been a major proponent of this reform.

With the emergence of an externally consistent [[green economics]] and agreement on definitions of potentially contentious terms such as [[full-cost accounting]], [[natural capital]] and [[social capital]], the prospect of formal metrics for ecological and social loss or risk has grown less remote through the 1990s.

In the [[United Kingdom]] in particular, the London Health Observatory has undertaken a formal programme to address social deficits via a fuller understanding of what &quot;social capital&quot; is, how it functions in a real [[community]] (that being the [[City of London]]), and how losses of it tend to require both [[financial capital]] and significant political and social attention from [[volunteer]]s and professionals to help resolve.  The data they rely on is extensive, building on decades of statistics of the [[Greater London Council]] since [[World War II]].  Similar studies have been undertaken in [[North America]].

Studies of the [[value of Earth]] have tried to determine what might constitute an ecological or natural life deficit. The [[Kyoto Protocol]] relies on some measures of this sort, and actually relies on some [[value of life]] calculations that, among other things, are explicit about the ratio of the price of a human life between developed and developing nations (about 15 to 1). While the motive of this number was to simply assign responsibility for a cleanup, such stark honesty opens not just an economic but political door to some kind of negotiation &amp;mdash; presumably to reduce that ratio in time to something seen as more equitable. As it is, people in developed nations can be said to benefit 15 times more from [[ecological devastation]] than in developing nations, in pure financial terms.  According to the [[Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change|IPCC]], they are thus obliged to pay 15 times more per life to avoid a loss of each such life to [[climate change]] &amp;mdash; the [[Kyoto Protocol]] seeks to implement exactly this formula, and is therefore sometimes cited as a first step towards getting nations to accept formal [[legal liability|liability]] for damage inflicted on ecosystems shared globally.

Advocacy for triple bottom line reforms is common in [[Green Parties]]. Some of the measures undertaken in the [[European Union]] towards the [[Euro]] currency integration standardize the reporting of ecological and social losses in such a way as to seem to endorse in principle the notion of unified accounts, or [[unit of account]], for these deficits.

==Criticism==
{{Unreferenced section|date=June 2009}}
While many people agree with the importance of good social conditions and preservation of the environment, there are also many who disagree with the triple bottom line as the way to enhance these conditions.
The main arguments against it are summarised below.

*[[Reductive method]]: In the triple bottom line, a corporate-oriented approach, the social—that is, the way in which humans live and relate to each other and the environment—is secondary. The economic as a domain is given an independent status which is ideologically assumed rather than analytically argued. In the most problematic versions, the economic is elevated to the master category and defined in terms that assume the dominance of a singular, historically specific, economic configuration—modern globalizing capitalism. Concurrently the environment comes to be treated as an externality or background feature, an externality that tends not to have the human dimension build into its definition. Thus, in many writings, even in those critical of the triple-bottom-line approach, the social becomes a congeries of miscellaneous considerations left other from the other two prime categories. Alternative approaches that treat the economic as a social domain, alongside and in relation to the ecological, the political and the cultural are now being considered as more appropriate for understanding institutions, cities and regions.&lt;ref&gt;Andy Scerri and Paul James, ‘Communities of Citizens and “Indicators” of Sustainability’, ''Community Development Journal'', vol. 45, no. 2, 2010, pp. 219–36.
Andy Scerri and Paul James, ‘Accounting for Sustainability: Combining Qualitative and Quantitative Research in Developing ‘Indicators’ of Sustainability’, ''International Journal of Social Research Methodology'', vol. 13, no. 1, 2010, pp. 41–53.
Paul James and Andy Scerri, ‘Auditing Cities through Circles of Sustainability’, Mark Amen, Noah J. Toly, Patricia L. Carney and Klaus Segbers, eds, ''Cities and Global Governance'', Ashgate, Farnham, 2011, pp. 111–36.
Andy Scerri 2012, ‘Ends in View: The capabilities approach in ecological/sustainability economics’, Ecological Economics 77: 7-10; Liam Magee, &amp; Scerri, A. (2012) ‘From Issues to Indicators: A Response to Grosskurth and Rotmans’, Local Environment 17(8): 915-933.&lt;/ref&gt;

*[[Division of labour]] is characteristic of rich societies and a major contributor to their wealth. This leads to the view that organisations contribute most to the welfare of society in all respects when they focus on what they do best: the baker exchanges his loaves with the shoemaker rather than making his own shoes - to the benefit of both and by extension the whole of society. In the case of business the expertise is in satisfying the needs of society and generating a [[value added]] surplus. Thus the triple bottom line is thought to be harmful by diverting business attention away from its core competency. Just as charitable organizations like the [[International Red Cross and Red Crescent Movement|Red Cross]] would not be expected to attend to environmental issues or pay a cash dividend, and [[Greenpeace]] would not be expected to make a profit or succor the [[homeless]], business should not be expected to take on concerns outside its core expertise, provided the business doesn't do obvious harm to people or the planet.

*[[Effectiveness]]: It is observed that concern for social and environmental matters is rare in poor societies (a hungry person would rather eat the [[whale]] than photograph it). As a society becomes richer its citizens develop an increasing desire for a clean environment and protected wildlife, and both the willingness and financial ability to contribute to this and to a compassionate society. Support for the concept of the triple bottom line itself is said to be an example of the choices available to the citizens of a society made wealthy by businesses attending to business. Thus by unencumbered attention to business alone, [[Adam Smith]]'s [[Invisible Hand]] will ensure that business contributes most effectively to the improvement of all areas of society, social and environmental as well as economic.

*[[Nationalism]]: Some countries adopt the view that they must look after their own citizens first. This view is not confined to one sector of society, having support from elements of business, [[labour union]]s, and politicians.

*[[Libertarianism|Libertarian]]: As it is possible for a socially responsible person to sincerely believe that the triple bottom line is harmful to society, the libertarian view is that it would be arrogant to force them to support a mechanism for the improvement of society that may, or may not, be the best available. That is, those who would not force Greenpeace and the Salvation Army to generate a profit should not force businesses to take responsibilities outside their area of expertise. At least in areas where a business doesn't do obvious harm to people or the planet.

*[[Inertia]]: The difficulty of achieving global agreement on [[simultaneous policy]] may render such measures at best advisory, and thus unenforceable. For example, people may be unwilling to undergo a [[Depression (economics)|depression]] or even sustained [[recession]] to replenish lost [[ecosystem]]s.

*Application: According to Fred Robins' ''The Challenge of TBL: A Responsibility to Whom?'' one of the major weaknesses of the TBL framework is its ability to be applied in a monetary-based economic system. Because there is no single way in monetary terms to measure the benefits to the society and environment as there is with profit, it does not allow for businesses to sum across all three bottom lines. In this regard, it makes it difficult for businesses to recognize the benefits of using TBL for the company, itself.

*Criticism from the Left: TBL is viewed as an attempt by otherwise exploitative corporations to avoid legislation and taxation and generate a fictitious people-friendly &amp; eco-friendly image for PR purposes.

==Legislation==
Legislation permitting corporations to adopt a triple bottom line is under consideration in some jurisdictions, including [[Minnesota]] and [[Oregon]].&lt;ref&gt;http://survey.bcorporation.net/become/legal.php&lt;/ref&gt;

Some businesses have voluntarily adopted a triple bottom line as part of their articles of incorporation or bylaws, and some have advocated for state laws creating a &quot;Sustainable Corporation&quot; that would grant triple bottom line businesses benefits such as tax breaks.&lt;ref&gt;http://nylawline.typepad.com/greencounsel/2007/01/nau_a_legally_e.html&lt;/ref&gt;

The triple bottom line was adopted as a part of the State Sustainability Strategy,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sustainability.dpc.wa.gov.au/docs/Strategy.htm&lt;/ref&gt; and accepted by the [[Western Australian Government|Government of Western Australia]] but its status was increasingly marginalised by subsequent premiers [[Alan Carpenter]] and [[Colin Barnett]] and is in doubt.

==See also==
{{Portal|Sustainable development}}
*[[Circles of Sustainability]], an alternative four-domain model
*[[Double bottom line]], a similar concept predating the UN standard
*[[EC3 Global]]
*[[Grassroots Business Fund]]
*[[Institute for Sustainable Communication]]
*[[Integrated bottom line]], an attempt to combine the parameters from the triple bottom line as a single parameter
*[[Not Just For Profit]]
*[[Sustainability]]
*[[Value network]]
*[[Value network analysis]]
*[[Social entrepreneurship]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
*''Social Audit - A Management Tool for Co-operative Working 1981'' by Freer Spreckley [http://www.locallivelihoods.com/cmsms/uploads/PDFs/Social%20Audit%20-%20A%20Management%20Tool.pdf Local Livelihoods Publications]
*''The Gaia Atlas of Green Economics'' (Gaia Future Series) [Paperback], by Paul Ekins, Anchor Books
*''Harvard Business Review on Corporate Responsibility'' by [[Harvard Business School Press]]
*''The Soul of a Business: Managing for Profit and the Common Good'' by Tom Chappell
*''Capitalism at the Crossroads: The Unlimited Business Opportunities in Solving the World's Most Difficult Problems'' by Professor Stuart L. Hart
*''The Triple Bottom Line: How Today's Best-Run Companies Are Achieving Economic, Social and Environmental Success—and How You Can Too'' by Andrew W. Savitz and Karl Weber
*''The Sustainability Advantage: Seven Business Case Benefits of a Triple Bottom Line (Conscientious Commerce)'' by Bob Willard, [[New Society Publishers]] ISBN 978-0-86571-451-9

==External links==
* [http://www.ibrc.indiana.edu/ibr/2011/spring/article2.html The Triple Bottom Line: What Is It and How Does It Work? - Indiana Business Review]
* [http://www.isa.org.usyd.edu.au/publications/balance.shtml Balancing Act - A Triple Bottom Line Analysis of the Australian Economy]
* [http://www.c4cr.org/ Citizens for Corporate Redesign] ([[Minnesota]])
* [http://www.triplepundit.com/ Triple Pundit - Blog on Triple Bottom Line] ([[United States]])
* [http://www.corporate-responsibility.org/ Corporate Responsibility] ([[United Kingdom]])
* [http://www.isa.org.usyd.edu.au/research/tbl.shtml TBL Accounting without boundaries - Australian corporate and government experiences]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Triple Bottom Line}}
[[Category:Welfare economics]]
[[Category:Sustainability]]
[[Category:Business ethics]]

[[cs:Trojí zodpovědnost]]
[[de:Drei-Säulen-Modell (Nachhaltigkeit)]]
[[et:Tulemuste kolmikmõõde]]
[[es:Triple resultado]]
[[fr:Triple bottom line]]
[[nl:People Planet Profit]]
[[pt:Tripé da sustentabilidade]]
[[sv:Triple bottom line reporting]]</text>
      <sha1>c3ojyp2bs3aili0g4zab04w07ao2t8m</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
