<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Unit of account</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>312461</id>
    <revision>
      <id>515461055</id>
      <parentid>515460936</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-01T13:18:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Robbiemorrison</username>
        <id>12615966</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>improved previous hyperlink</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="5447">A '''unit of account''' is a standard monetary unit of measurement of value/cost of goods, services, or assets. It is one of three well-known [[money#Functions|functions of money]].{{Citation Needed|date=August 2012}} It lends meaning to profits, losses, liability, or assets.

The [[accounting]] [[monetary]] unit of account suffers from the pitfall of not being a stable unit of account over time. Inflation destroys the assumption that [[money]] is stable which is the basis of classic accountancy. In such circumstances, historical values registered in accountancy books become heterogeneous amounts measured in different units. The use of such data under traditional accounting methods without previous correction often leads to invalid results.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=WXwfMDDYOdkC&amp;pg=PA259&amp;lpg=PA259&amp;dq=inflation+destroys+historical+cost+values&amp;source=web&amp;ots=YMBICCQr42&amp;sig=lsiPcViCm3RhVQXwrigJK675RC8&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;resnum=9&amp;ct=result] The Taxation of Income from Business and Capital in Colombia: Fiscal Reform in the Developing World
By Charles E. McLure, John Mutti, Victor Thuronyi, George R. Zodrow, Contributor Charles E. McLure, Published by Duke University Press, 1990, ISBN 0-8223-0925-4, ISBN 978-0-8223-0925-3, Page 259 : '''Inflation destroys the assumption that money is stable which is the basis of classic accountancy'''. In such circumstances, historical values registered in accountancy books become heterogeneous amounts measured in different units. The use of such data under traditional accounting methods without previous correction, makes no sense and leads to results that are void of meaning.(Massone, 1981a. p.6)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Uses==

A standard '''unit of account''' allows meaningful interpretation of prices, costs, and profits, so that an entity can monitor its own performance and its shareholders can make sense of its past performance and have an idea of its future profitability. In modern economies, [[money]] in the form of [[currency]] usually serves the role of the standard unit of account.  The use of money, under conditions of price stability, vastly improves the [[Economic efficiency|efficiency]] of [[market economies]].

Historic examples of units of account include the [[livre tournois]], used in France from 1302 to 1794 whether or not livre coins were minted. In the 14th century Naples used the grossi gigliati, and Bohemia used the Prague groschen.

At any one time there might be two or three units of account in one region based on the local base, silver and sometimes gold coins, and each often expressed in [[£sd|L.S.D]] units in ratio 240:12:1. The [[Florin (Italian coin)|Florentine gold florin]], the [[Franc#Origins|French franc]] and the electoral [[rheingulden]] all became pounds (240 denari) of account. Units of account would often survive over 100 years despite the original coins changing composition and availability (e.g. the Castilian maravedi).&lt;ref name=Spufford1986&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.philipresheph.com/a424/study/exchange.doc |title=Handbook of medieval exchange; Introduction |author=Peter Spuffords |year=1986 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A modern unit of account is the [[European Currency Unit]], used in the European Union from 1979 to 1998; its replacement in 1999, the [[euro]], was also just a unit of account until the introduction of notes and coins in 2002.

Unit of account is the main way of calculating a carrier or ship owner’s liability in relation to carriage of goods contracts in which the [[Hague-Visby Rules]] apply.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}

===Modern finance===
The use of a unit of account in [[financial accounting]], according to the American business model, allows investors to invest capital into those companies that provide the highest [[rate of return]]. The use of a unit of account in [[managerial accounting]] enables firms to choose between activities that yield the highest profit.

In [[economics]], a standard unit of account is used for statistical purposes to describe economic activity. Indexes such as GDP and the CPI are so broad in their scope that compiling them would be impossible without a standard unit of account. After being compiled, these figures are often used to guide governmental policy; especially monetary and fiscal policy.

In calculating the [[opportunity cost]] of a policy, a standard unit of account allows for the creation of a [[composite good]]. A composite good is a theoretical abstraction that represents an aggregation of all other opportunities that are not realized by the first good. It allows an economic decision's benefits to be weighed against the costs of all other possible goods in that society, without having to refer to any directly. Often, this is most easily accomplished with [[money]].

==See also==
*[[Medium of exchange]]
*[[Store of value]]
*[[Equivalization]]
*[[Inflation accounting]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.egwald.ca/ubcstudent/aboriginal/exchanges.php Linguistic and Commodity Exchanges] by Elmer G. Wiens.  Examines the structural differences between barter and monetary commodity exchanges and oral and written linguistic exchanges.

[[Category:Currency]]
[[Category:Money]]

[[ca:Unitat de compte]]
[[es:Unidad de cuenta]]
[[eu:Kontu-unitate]]
[[fr:Unité de compte]]
[[it:Unità di conto]]
[[lb:Unité de compte]]
[[nl:Rekeneenheid]]
[[no:Valutakurv]]
[[ru:Счётная денежная единица]]</text>
      <sha1>7w6cg3bg66jimoofb15j82frybrym8m</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
