<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Virtuous circle and vicious circle</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>384239</id>
    <revision>
      <id>516158733</id>
      <parentid>512464990</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-05T15:00:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>99.50.227.21</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9591">{{Redirect|Vicious circle||Vicious Circle (disambiguation)}}
{{Multiple issues |refimprove=March 2012|essay-like=May 2012}}
A '''virtuous circle''' and a '''vicious circle''' (also referred to as  '''virtuous cycle''' and '''vicious cycle''') are economic terms. They refer to  a complex chain of events that reinforces itself through a [[feedback]] loop.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Handbook of Peace and Conflict Studies |date=19 March 2012 |author=Charles Webel, Johan Galtung |publisher=Routledge |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=hULHeXWxLLQC&amp;pg=PA189&amp;lpg=PA189&amp;dq=virtuous+circle+feedback+hyperinflation&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=GXIaOLTAz3&amp;sig=z6n6Li5ejiXL_iMuna4GV3dfhTg&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=peJnT6zaHouGiQKjyPH1Bg&amp;ved=0CD8Q6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q=virtuous%20circle%20feedback%20hyperinflation&amp;f=false/|accessdate=19 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  A ''virtuous'' circle has favorable results, while a ''vicious'' circle has detrimental results.
 
Both circles are complexes of events with no tendency towards  [[Economic equilibrium|equilibrium]]  (at least in the short run).  Both systems of events have feedback loops in which each iteration of the cycle reinforces the previous one ([[positive feedback]]). These cycles will continue in the direction of their momentum until an external factor intervenes and breaks the cycle. The prefix &quot;hyper-&quot; is sometimes used to describe these cycles if they are extreme.  The best-known example of a vicious circle is [[hyperinflation]].

==Example in macroeconomics==
===Virtuous circle===

Economic growth can be seen as a virtuous circle. It might start with an exogenous, or outside factor such as technological innovation. As people get familiar with the new technology, there could be [[learning curve effects]] and [[economies of scale]]. This could lead to reduced costs and improved [[x-efficiency|production efficiencies]]. In a [[market forms|competitive market structure]], this will probably result in lower average prices. As prices decrease, consumption could increase and aggregate output also. Increased levels of output lead to more learning and scale effects and a new cycle starts. 

[[Image:Virtuous circle in macroeconomics.svg|thumb|center|450px|Virtuous circle]]
&lt;div style=&quot;clear:both;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===Vicious circle===

Hyperinflation is a spiral of [[inflation]] which causes even higher inflation. The initial exogenous event might be a sudden large increase in international [[interest rate]]s or a massive increase in government [[debt]] due to excessive spendings. Whatever the cause, the government could pay down some of its debt by printing more money (called monetizing the debt). This increase in the money supply could increase the level of inflation. In an inflationary environment, people tend to spend their money quickly because they expect its value to decrease further in the future. They convert their financial assets into physical assets while their money still has some purchasing power. Often they will purchase on [[credit (finance)|credit]]. Eventually, the currency loses all of its value. Because of this, the level of savings in the country is very low and the government could have problems refinancing its debt. Its solution could be to print still more money starting another iteration of the vicious cycle. 

[[Image:Vicious circle in macroeconomics.svg|thumb|center|450px|Vicious circle]]
&lt;div style=&quot;clear:both;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

==Example in management==
===Virtuous circle===

An employer's investment in his employees’ ability to provide superior service to customers can be seen as a virtuous circle. Effort spent in selecting and training employees and creating a corporate culture in which they are empowered can lead to increased employee satisfaction and employee competence. This can result in superior service delivery and customer satisfaction. This in turn will create customer loyalty, improved sales levels, and higher profit margins. Some of these profits can be reinvested in employee development, thereby initiating another iteration of a virtuous cycle.

[[Image:Virtuous circle in management.svg|thumb|center|450px|Virtuous circle]]
&lt;div style=&quot;clear:both;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===Vicious circle===

A harvesting strategy which can be an example of a vicious circle is rather than reinvesting in [[employee]] development, new [[product development]], and [[market research]], [[management]] could decide to harvest its [[investment]] by reducing [[cost]]s then increasing [[dividend]]s or increasing [[executive compensation]]. The consequence of this could be reduced employee [[wage]]s, minimal [[training]], an outdated product line, and a failure to understand the needs of the [[customer]]. This will probably result in employee dissatisfaction, employee incompetence, and high employee turnover. This could cause poor service delivery, customer dissatisfaction, high customer turnover, and loss of [[market share]]. Reduced [[sales]] and lower [[profit margin]]s may require a further reduction in investment, thereby initiating another iteration of the vicious circle.

==Vicious circles in the subprime mortgage crisis==

[[Image:Subprime crisis - Foreclosures &amp; Bank Instability.png|thumb|Vicious Cycles in the Subprime Mortgage Crisis]]

The contemporary [[Subprime mortgage crisis#Understanding the causes and risks of the subprime crisis|subprime mortgage crisis]] is a complex of vicious circles, both in its genesis and in its manifold outcomes, most notably the [[late 2000s recession]]. A specific example is the circle related to housing. As housing prices decline, more homeowners go &quot;[[negative equity|underwater]]&quot;, when the market value of a home drops below the mortgage on it. This provides an incentive to walk away from the home, increasing defaults and foreclosures. This, in turn, lowers housing values further, reinforcing the cycle.&lt;ref&gt;[http://online.wsj.com/article/SB122697004441035727.html WSJ-Vicious Cycle in Subprime Crisis]&lt;/ref&gt;

The foreclosures reduce the cash flowing into banks and the value of mortgage-backed securities (MBS) widely held by banks. Banks incur losses and require additional funds, also called “recapitalization”. If banks are not capitalized sufficiently to lend, economic activity slows and unemployment increases, which further increase the number of foreclosures.

Economist [[Nouriel Roubini]] described the vicious circles within and across the housing market and financial markets during  interviews with [[Charlie Rose]] in September and October 2008.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.charlierose.com/view/interview/9248 Charlie Rose - Roubini &amp; Panel]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.charlierose.com/view/interview/9310 Rose &amp; Roubini Discussion]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.charlierose.com/view/clip/9416 Rose &amp; Roubini]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Other examples==
Other examples include the [[poverty cycle]], [[sharecropping]], and the intensification of [[drought]]. In [[climate change]] science, [[glossary of climate change#F|feedback loops]] involve [[positive feedback]]s and [[negative feedback]]s that respectively serve to intensify or dampen the [[effects of global warming|effects]] of [[global warming]].

==See also==
* [[Causal loop diagram]]
* [[Closed timelike curve]]
* [[Positive feedback]]
* [[List of economics topics]]
* [[List of finance topics]]
* [[List of management topics]]
* [[List of marketing topics]]
* [[List of production topics]]				
* [[Endogeneity (econometrics)]]
* [[Self-fulfilling prophecy]]
* [[Spiral of silence]]
* [[Subprime mortgage crisis]]

=== Analogous concepts ===
* [[Self-fulfilling prophecy]]
* [[Matthew effect (sociology)]]
* [[Matthew effect (education)]]
* [[Predestination paradox]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External sources==

* Schlesinger, L. and Heskett, J. (1991) Breaking the cycle of failure in services, ''Sloan Management Review'', vol. 31, spring 1991, pp.&amp;nbsp;17 – 28.
*http://william-king.www.drexel.edu/top/prin/txt/gro/gro21b.html - An introduction to 20th century virtuous circle theory.
*[http://216.239.37.104/search?q=cache:TxgNA2SGlWQJ:www.gordon.edu/ace/pdf/Yuengert_Choice.pdf+Virtue+%22economics%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ie=UTF-8 Rational Choice with Passion:Virtue in a Model of Rational Addiction] - In this link the author uses Aristotelian virtue as a mediator between passion and reason in the construction of utility/consumption functions in an esoteric part of consumer behaviour theory related to decision making in addictive situations.
*[http://scid.stanford.edu/publicationsprofile/1255 China: A Stabilizing or Deflationary Influence in East Asia? The Problem of Conflicted Virtue ] - In this link the author is using virtue in the sense of a positive outcome (balance of payments surplus) that conflicts with long term regional growth and stability.
* http://www.bioenergycentres.com/resources.shtml - an essay in 3 parts by Polarity Therapist Andrew Harry, Bath, UK.  Defining The Virtuous Cycle as an integrated healing process.

{{DEFAULTSORT:Virtuous Circle And Vicious Circle}}
[[Category:Economics terminology]]
[[Category:Management]]
[[Category:Macroeconomics]]
[[Category:Microeconomics]]
[[Category:Finance]]
[[Category:Marketing]]
[[Category:Behavioral and social facets of systemic risk]]

[[ca:Cercle viciós]]
[[da:Circulus vitiosus]]
[[de:Teufelskreis]]
[[es:Dialelo]]
[[fr:Cercle vicieux]]
[[hi:दुष्चक्र]]
[[io:Vertuoza cirklo e vicioza cirklo]]
[[it:Circolo virtuoso e circolo vizioso]]
[[he:מעגל קסמים]]
[[nl:Vicieuze cirkel]]
[[ja:循環論法]]
[[pt:Círculo vicioso]]
[[fi:Noidankehä]]
[[sv:Circulus vitiosus]]
[[th:วงจรอุบาทว์]]</text>
      <sha1>awia8vyis64xglhuw65y7wisvozzgfy</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
