<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Black supremacy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>65426</id>
    <revision>
      <id>517685380</id>
      <parentid>516858362</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-14T05:17:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ptbotgourou</username>
        <id>7355879</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>r2.7.2) (Robot: Adding [[pt:Supremacia negra]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21081">{{Discrimination sidebar}}
The term '''black supremacy''' is a blanket term for various racist ideologies which hold that [[black people]] are superior to people of other races.

==Active organizations==
====Nation of Islam====
{{Main|Nation of Islam}}
&lt;!--  Commented out: [[Image:Savioursday041.jpg|right|thumb|Malcolm X with Elijah Muhammad at [[Savior's Day]] {{ifdc|1=Image:Savioursday041.jpg|log=2008 July 24}}]] --&gt;
In the 1930s the [[Nation of Islam]] emerged, coming to prominence during the 1960s, when charismatic minister [[Malcolm X]] became a spokesman for the movement. The group's founders, [[Wallace Fard Muhammad|&quot;Master Fard&quot; Muhammad]] and [[Elijah Muhammad]], preached the Doctrine of [[Yakub (Nation of Islam)|Yakub]], which held that the [[First man|Original Man]] was an &quot;[[Asia]]tic black man&quot;. White people, it contended, were &quot;grafted&quot; from black people 6,000 years ago by an ancient black scientist named Yakub.&lt;ref&gt;Muhammad, Elijah. &quot;[http://www.muhammadspeaks.com/Makingofdevil.html The Making of Devil]&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;

The belief in sacrificial killing and ritualistic murder was part of the early Nation of Islam doctrine. Fard thought explicitly that it was the duty for every Muslim to offer as sacrifice four &quot;Caucasian devils&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Steven|last=Tsoukalas|authorlink=Steven Tsoukalas|year=2001|title=The Nation of Islam - Understanding the &quot;Black Muslims&quot;|pages=23–24|publisher=P&amp;R Publishing}}&lt;/ref&gt; A portion of Fard's lesson reads as follows:

{{bquote|Why does Fard Mohammad and any Moslem murder the devil? What is the duty of each Moslem in regard to four devils? What reward does a Moslem receive by presenting the four devils at one time? — Because he is one hundred percent wicked and will not keep and obey the laws of Islam. His ways and actions are like a snake of the grafted type. So Mohammad learned that he could not reform the devils, so they had to be murdered. All Moslems will murder the devil because they know he is a snake and also if he be allowed to live, he would sting someone else. Each Moslem is required to bring four devils, and by bringing and presenting four at one time his reward is a button to wear on the laple of his coat, also a free transportation to the Holy City of Mecca.|||Master Fard Mohammad, Lesson #1.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Mattias|last=Gardell|authorlink=Mattias Gardell|year=1996|title=In the Name of Elijah Muhammad: Louis Farrakhan and the Nation of Islam|pages=56|location=Durham, N.C. |publisher= Duke University Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Nation of Islam leader [[Louis Farrakhan]] later argued that the lessons about murdering devils was only a metaphor designed to &quot;rally NOI members to 'slay whites' psychological and social grip on them&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Arthur J.|last=Magida|authorlink=Arthur J. Magida|year=1996|title=Prophet of Rage: A Life of Louis Farrakhan and His Nation|pages=52|location=New York|publisher= HarperCollins}}&lt;/ref&gt; but Fard's lessons on the murder of white people in at least one instance were taken literally and verbatim:
&lt;blockquote&gt;One afternoon in the early 1970s, when Ali K. Muslim, then Charles 41x, was guarding the temple, a man carrying a sack asked to meet a temple official. The man, thoroughly confused about Elijah Muhammad's teachings, believed that if he killed four white &quot;devils&quot; he would win a trip to the Holy Land. He had come to redeem his prizes. In the sack, Ali K. Muslim says, were four severed heads.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Steven|last=Barbosa|authorlink=Steven Barbosa|year=1993|title=American Jihad: Islam after Malcolm X|pages=115–116|publisher=New York: Doubleday}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

This teaching also culminated in the creation of the [[Death Angels]], a small splinter group of the Nation of Islam. Between 1972 and 1974, the Death Angels murdered 14 white people in the San Francisco Bay area. These murders later would become known as the [[Zebra murders]] because the police used Radio Z to communicate about the case.&lt;ref&gt;Lubinskas, James. &quot;[http://www.frontpagemag.com/Articles/Printable.asp?ID=3693 Remembering the Zebra Killings]&quot;. ''Front Page Magazine''. 30 August 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hodge, Damon. &quot;[http://www.lasvegasweekly.com/2002/03_21/news_coverstory_1.html Alien Nation: Louis Farrakhan, Phone Home]&quot;. ''Las Vegas Weekly''. undated.&lt;/ref&gt;

Elijah Muhammad also preached black self-reliance, black separatism, cooperative economics, strict moral and physical discipline, and opposition to black-white [[miscegenation]]. Since its founding, the NOI has gone through reorganizations and internal conflicts, but even as it moves closer to the mainstream of Islamic belief and practice, NOI leadership has not rejected formally any of Fard's doctrines. It opposes any changes in the major beliefs and programs that were instituted by Fard Muhammad and Elijah Muhammad, including the annual &quot;[[Savior's Day]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Gudel, Joseph P. and Larry Duckworth. &quot;[http://www.rim.org/muslim/nationofislam.htm Hate Begotten of Hate]&quot;. ''Christian Research Institute'. 1993.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.adl.org/PresRele/NatIsl_81/4878_81.htm Farrakhan Again Spews Hate in Saviours' Day Speech ]&quot; [[Anti-Defamation League]]. 28 February 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?pid=394 Snarling at the White Man]&quot;. [[Southern Poverty Law Center]] ''Intelligence Report''. Fall 2000.&lt;/ref&gt;

Members of the NOI have been publicly criticized by the leadership for making [[anti-Semitic]], anti-[[Catholic]] anti-white and anti-[[Homosexuality|homosexual]] statements,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.adl.org/hate-patrol/noi.asp Nation of Islam ]&quot;. 2001.&lt;/ref&gt; and for urging the murder of such people.  Farrakhan has been banned from entering the UK since 1986 because of his &quot;racist and anti-Semitic views&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/1959105.stm Farrakhan British ban stays ]&quot;. [[British Broadcasting Corporation]]. 30 April 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;

Most historians and social scientists{{Nonspecific|date=December 2007}} classify the Nation of Islam as a [[black nationalism|black nationalist]], or black separatist, organization. Recently, the [[Southern Poverty Law Center]] headed by [[Morris Dees]] placed the Nation of Islam on its list of [[hate groups]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.splcenter.org/intel/map/hate.jsp?T=24&amp;m=4Active U.S. Hate Groups in 2005]. [[Southern Poverty Law Center]]. 2005. Retrieved 25 December 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

====New Black Panther Party====
{{Main|New Black Panther Party}}
The New Black Panther Party (NBPP), whose formal name is the New Black Panther Party for Self-Defense, is a U.S.-based black supremacist organization founded in Dallas, Texas in 1989.

====United Nuwaubian Nation of Moors====
{{Main|United Nuwaubian Nation of Moors}}
The United Nuwaubian Nation of Moors was founded by [[Dwight York]]. The [[Nuwaubianism|Nuwaubians]] believe in black people's superiority to white people, that white people are &quot;devils,&quot; devoid of both [[heart]] and [[Soul (spirit)|soul]], that the color of white people is the result of [[leprosy]] and genetic inferiority, and that the ancestors of white people are the sexual partners of [[dogs]] and [[jackals]].&lt;ref&gt;Moser, Bob. &quot;[http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?aid=41 'Savior' in a Strange Land]&quot;. [[Southern Poverty Law Center]] ''Intelligence Report''. Fall 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2004, York was sentenced to 135 years in prison for child molestation and racketeering-related charges.

{{bquote|Among the different species of Apeman you have the black-haired Lar. This is where you get the word ‘lord,’ or master from. The Lares, plural for Lar, were recognized for their intelligence. These Lares were the head monkeys or spiritual monkeys, well known. This is where the word ‘monks’ comes from. Certain beings used the species known as the Baboon (part hyena, jackal and monkey) together with Orangutans for breeding. This resulted in your Behaymaw (called the beast of the field) type of carnivorous man called Mankind, one of the many species of Caucasians.&lt;ref&gt;York, Malachi Z. [http://factology.com/front2_12_00.htm ''A Wake Up Call'']&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;York, Malachi Z. ''El Ishtakhlaag: The Creation'' Tablet 9 (p. 95-98)&lt;/ref&gt;}}
	 	
[[White people]] are said in one myth to have been originally created as a race of killers to serve black people as a slave army.
	 
{{bquote|The Caucasian has not been chosen to lead the world. They lack true emotions in their creation. We never intended them to be peaceful. They were bred to be killers, with low reproduction levels and a short life span. What you call Negroid was to live 1,000 years each and the other humans 120 years. But the warrior seed of Caucasians only 60 years. They were only created to fight other invading races, to protect the God race Negroids. But they went insane, lost control when they were left unattended. They were never to taste blood. They did, and their true nature came out.… Because their reproduction levels were cut short, their sexual organs were made the smallest so that the female of their race will want to breed with Negroids to breed themselves out of existence after 6,000 years. It took 600 years to breed them, part man and part beast.&lt;ref&gt;York, Malachi Z. &quot;[http://apublicoutcry.com/Letters%20From%20Reverend%20York/CompilationOfPowerfulLetters.pdf This is your message Najwa and Davina, Kirsten]&quot; (letter) 10 November 2004 &lt;br /&gt;See also Amunnubi Raakhptah’s ''9 Principles in the Human Being'' where he writes (p. 33): &quot;The First Thing That All Nubuns Or Their Offspring Nubian Must Know Is That The Caucasoids Did Not And Still Don’t Produce Any Data On Negroids. Nothing You Read About In The Medical Field Applied To Negroids. It All Pertains To The Chemical Make Up Of The Caucasoid Bodies. Nothing In The Mental Field Of The Psychiatrist Pertains To The Negroids. The Caucasoids Cannot Evaluate Our Mental Stability, Or Try To Decipher Why We Do What We Do Because We Do Not Think Or Feel The Way They Do. Nor Do The Caucasoids Know Anything About Us Spiritually. The Caucasoids Are Carnivorous Mammals, Who Are Flesh Eating Killers By Nature. Mongoloids And Others Are Human, Also Mammals Because They Are Mixed. Some Are Carnivores And Some Are Herbivores By Nature. And We Are Deities, Herbivores By Nature Who Are Their Mothers And Fathers. The Caucasoid Were All Grafted From Us, And Mixed With Other Beast To Make Their Beast Like Nature.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;}}

====Tribu Ka====
Tribu Ka was founded in 2004 by [[Stellio Capo Chichi]] (&quot;Kémi Séba&quot;), dubbed as &quot;the [[France|French]] Farrakhan&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jeuneafrique.com/Article/LIN30076quiessianar0/Qui-est-le--Farrakhan-francais---.html ''Qui est le Farrakhan français ?''], [[Jeune Afrique]], 31 July 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; in [[Paris]].&lt;ref name=CONVICTION&gt;[http://www.jta.org/page_view_breaking_story.asp?intid=6945&amp;ref=daily_briefing French gang leader sentenced] {{Dead link|date=August 2008}} [[Jewish Telegraphic Agency]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=VISIT&gt;{{cite news |title=Sarkozy visits Jewish neighborhood after threat from Black extremists |url=http://www.ejpress.org/article/8719 |publisher=European Jewish Press |date=2006-05-31 |accessdate=2008-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=DEMONSTRATION&gt;{{cite news |title=Leader of Black anti-Semitic group arrested in France |url=http://www.ejpress.org/article/13918 |publisher=European Jewish Press |date=2007-02-09 |accessdate=2008-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; The group identified itself as following Louis Farrakhan's ideology&lt;ref name=&quot;independent&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/french-youths-fight-police-and-attack-mayors-house-480432.html | work=The Independent | location=London | title=French youths fight police and attack mayor's house | first=John | last=Lichfield | date=2006-05-31 | accessdate=2010-04-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; but their thinking was also described as a mix of [[antisemitic]] [[Kemetism]] and [[René Guénon|Guénonian]] [[Islam]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://vho.org/aaargh/fran/livres9/Ka.pdf &quot;Le ''Weltanschauung'' de la Tribu Ka], Stéphane François, Damien Guillame, and Emmanuel Kreis&lt;/ref&gt; After an investigation of racist incitement, Interior Minister [[Nicolas Sarkozy]] dissolved Tribu Ka on July 26, 2006 but it reformed under the name Génération Kémi Séba.&lt;ref name=CONVICTION/&gt;&lt;ref name=VISIT/&gt;&lt;ref name=DEMONSTRATION/&gt; In April 2008, a Parisian court verdict judged Génération Kémi Séba was the refoundation of the dissolved group Tribu Ka.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.iquebec.com/actu/france/245279 Tribu Ka: un an de prison avec sursis pour reconstitution de ligue dissoute]&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2009, Interior Minister [[Brice Hortefeux]] ordered the dissolution of the group Jeunesse Kémi Séba, founded to replace Génération Kémi Séba.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.interieur.gouv.fr/misill/sections/a_la_une/toute_l_actualite/securite-interieure/dissolution-jeunesse-kemi-seba/view Dissolution du groupuscule &quot;Jeunesse Kemi Seba&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.antisemitism.org.il/eng/struggle/41606/France-Dissolutionof%22%22Jeunesse%27K%C3%A9miS%C3%A9ba%22%28%22%27K%C3%A9miS%C3%A9baYouth%22%29 France - Dissolution of &quot;&quot;Jeunesse 'Kémi Séba&quot; (&quot;'Kémi Séba Youth&quot;)]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other groups===
====Nation of Yahweh====
{{Main|Nation of Yahweh}}
The Nation of Yahweh is a black supremacist religious group that is an offshoot of the [[Black Hebrew Israelites]] line of thought{{Citation needed|date=October 2007}}, and was founded by [[Yahweh ben Yahweh]], meaning &quot;God the Son of God&quot; in [[Hebrew]], formerly known as [[Hulon Mitchell Jr]]. At its height, the Nation of Yahweh controlled an $8 million empire of properties, including a Miami headquarters known as the ''Temple of Love'' and temples in 22 states.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.apologeticsindex.org/n04.html Nation of Yahweh ]&quot; Apologetics Index. undated.&lt;/ref&gt; Followers of the Nation of Yahweh view black people as the only &quot;true Jews&quot; and believe that White [[Jew]]s are the spawn of [[Satan]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?aid=172 Popularity and Populism ]&quot;. [[Southern Poverty Law Center]] ''Intelligence Report''. Winter 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the [[Crime Library]], followers of the Nation of Yahweh formed a secret group called &quot;The Brotherhood&quot;. To become a member of The Brotherhood, applicants had to kill a &quot;white devil&quot; and bring Mitchell a body part - an ear, nose or finger - as proof of the kill. Several Nation of Yahweh members were convicted of conspiracy in more than a dozen anti-white murders, among them [[Robert Rozier]], a former pro football player and member of the secret Brotherhood, who admitted the killing of seven white people.&lt;ref name=yahweh&gt;Scheeres, Julie. &quot;[http://www.crimelibrary.com/notorious_murders/classics/yahweh_cult/12.html The Yahweh Ben Yahweh Cult ]&quot;. ''The Crime Library''. undated.&lt;/ref&gt; Mitchell started a private school for his followers and held sex classes for boys and men in which he showed them movies of white women having sex with animals to dissuade them from lusting after white females.&lt;ref name=yahweh/&gt;

===Bobo Shanti===
The [[Mansions of Rastafari|Bobo Shanti]] are a mansion within the [[Rastafari movement]] and led by the late [[Charles Edwards (Rastafarian)|Charles Edwards]] preach a form of black supremacy based on the original teachings of [[Leonard Howell]] and on the teachings of [[Marcus Garvey]]. The Bobo say they are not racist, arguing instead that the concepts of &quot;white&quot; and &quot;black&quot; are symbolic, and that a Caucasian could be morally &quot;black&quot;, or righteous, and that a man of African descent could be morally &quot;white&quot;, or wicked.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nalis.gov.tt/Communities/communities_BoboShantis.html HELLO, HELLO AFRICA BOBO SHANTIS LIVE TO FULFIL MARCUS GARVEY'S DREAM]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Black supremacist theories==
Many of these theories espouse an ideology of a past Black Supremacy in the world that has been lost. Some focus on claiming this supremacy by claiming they are the chosen people in one religion or another as seen in the Nation of Islam or the Black Israelites. Others even claim extra terrestrial intervention, such as the Nuwaubians or the Nation of Islam. Two trends have acquired a veneer of respectability in many places of Black Academia and Black Studies departments; the Melanin Theory, and Afrocentrism/Global Pan Africanism.

===Melanin theory===
{{Main|Melanin theory}}

Some black supremacists justify supremacist assertions by assigning dubious properties to [[melanin]] based on pseudo-science and distortions of scientific fact or speculation. This body of belief is known generally as &quot;[[Melanin theory]]&quot;. The central idea of the Melanin theory is that the levels of melanin in dark skin naturally enhance intelligence and emotional, psychic and spiritual sensitivity.&lt;ref&gt;Skeptinq, Ortiz de Montellano, B. R. 1993. &quot;Afrocentricity, Melanin, and Pseudoscience,&quot; Yearbook of Physical Anthropology 36, 33-58
3.^ Ortiz de Montellano, Bernard R. (17 Dec 2006); &quot;Afrocentric Pseudoscience: The Miseducation of African Americans&quot;. Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences (New York Academy of Sciences) 775: 561–572. {{doi|10.1111/j.1749-6632.1996.tb23174.x}}. http://www3.interscience.wiley.com/journal/119242630/abstract?CRETRY=1&amp;SRETRY=0.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=suzar&gt;Suzar.&quot;[http://suzar.com/BOTW/BOTW-ch5b-pages55-56.html Other Astounding Properties of Melanin] undated.&lt;/ref&gt; Such claims have made inroads among some African Americans within academia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ferris.edu/HTMLS/staff/webpages/site.cfm?LinkID=328&amp;eventID=34 Mehler, Barry. &quot;African American Racism in the Academic Community.&quot; First published in ''The Review of Education'' 15 # 3/4 (Fall 1993); revised and republished as &quot;Addressing the Problem of African-American Racism in Academia,&quot; in ''Martyrdom and Resistance'' (Nov.-Dec. 1993); slightly revised for posting (undated)]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Alliances with white supremacist groups==
Due to some commonly held separatist ideologies, some black supremacist organizations have found limited common cause with [[white supremacist]] or extremist organizations.

In 1961 and 1962 [[George Lincoln Rockwell]], the leader of the [[American Nazi Party]], was invited to speak by [[Elijah Muhammad]] at a [[Nation of Islam]] rally.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first= |last= |authorlink= |coauthors= |title=The Messenger Passes |url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,917218,00.html |work= |publisher=[[Time magazine]] |date=March 10, 1975 |accessdate=2007-08-19 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1965, after breaking with the Nation of Islam and denouncing its separatist doctrine, [[Malcolm X]] told his followers that the Nation of Islam under Elijah Muhammad had made agreements with the American Nazi Party and the Ku Klux Klan that &quot;were not in the interests of Negros.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nizkor.org/hweb/orgs/american/adl/uncommon-ground/secret-relationship.html Uncommon Ground: Secret Relationship&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; In 1985 Louis Farrakhan invited white supremacist [[Tom Metzger (white supremacist)|Tom Metzger]], leader of the [[White Aryan Resistance]] (a neo-Nazi white power group), to attend a NOI gathering. The Washington Times reports Metzger's words of praise: &quot;They speak out against the Jews and the oppressors in Washington. ... They are the black counterpart to us.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.answering-islam.org/NoI/noi1.html#fn31 Louis Farrakhan and the Nation of Islam: Part One&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{portal|Discrimination}}
*[[White supremacy]]
*[[Afrocentrism]]
*[[Antisemitism]]
*[[Melanin]]
*[[Melanin theory]]
*[[Race and intelligence]]
*[[Racism]]
*[[Supremacy]]
*[[Hate group]]
*[[Black nationalism]]
*[[Black Power]]
* [[Black Power (New Zealand)]], [[Māori people|Māori]] gang

==References==
{{Reflist|3}}

==External links==
*[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/12/15/AR2005121501728_pf.html ''Scientists Find A DNA Change That Accounts For White Skin'' (Washington Post Staff Writer - Friday, December 16, 2005; A01) Biotechnology]
*[http://www.csicop.org/si/9201/minority.html ''Magic Melanin: Spreading Scientific Illiteracy to Minorities'' (CSICOP article on melanin theory and associated pseudoscience)]
*[http://www.ferris.edu/HTMLS/othersrv/isar/archives2/mehler/academic.htm Institute for the Study of Academic Racism (ISAR): African American Racism in the Academic Community]
*[http://www.ancient-knowledge-breakthrough.net/id5.html Annual World Melanin Conference]
*[http://www.time.com/time/archive/preview/0,10987,980453,00.html TIME Magazine Teaching Reverse Racism]
*[http://www.nizkor.org/hweb/orgs/american/adl/uncommon-ground/ Uncommon Ground: The Black African Holocaust Council and Other Links Between Black and White Extremists]

{{Black supremacist organizations}}
{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Black Supremacy}}
[[Category:Black supremacy| ]]
[[Category:African American]]
[[Category:Black African people]]
[[Category:Racism]]

[[de:Black Supremacy]]
[[fr:Suprémacisme noir]]
[[ko:흑인 우월주의]]
[[pl:Czarna supremacja]]
[[pt:Supremacia negra]]
[[fi:Musta ylivalta]]
[[zh:黑人优越主义]]</text>
      <sha1>cip1uz4wytz5ip4mrz1oxi5wsl9qk0x</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
