<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Catalan nationalism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>425757</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519943065</id>
      <parentid>519275093</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-26T13:20:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Xqbot</username>
        <id>8066546</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>r2.7.3) (Robot: Adding [[io:Kataluniana nacionalismo]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="38949">{{Catalan-speaking world|image=[[File:Estelada blava.svg|250px]]|expanded=Politics}}

'''Catalan [[nationalism]]''' ({{lang-ca|Nacionalisme català}}; {{IPA-ca|nəsiunəˈɫizmə kətəˈɫa|ec}}, {{IPA-ca|nasionaˈlizme kataˈla|wc}}) or '''Catalanism''' ({{lang-ca|Catalanisme}}), is a [[Politics|political]] movement advocating for either further political autonomy or full independence of [[Catalonia]].

Intellectually, Catalanism departs from the unsuccessful attempts to establish a federal state in Spain in the context of the [[First Spanish Republic|First Republic]]. [[Valentí Almirall i Llozer]] and other intellectuals that participated in this process set up a new political ideology in the 19th century, to restore self-government, as well as to obtain recognition for the [[Catalan language]]. These demands were summarized in the so-called ''Bases de Manresa'' in 1892.

It met very little support at first.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.es/books?id=GgGmyZcPSuQC&amp;pg=PA537&amp;lpg=PA537&amp;dq=catalanismo+secta+religiosa&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=lvHh5Zp5dQ&amp;sig=1bzFqtPsou7y7ciasHb-Z2OCUMo&amp;hl=es&amp;ei=sLLoTPXpG4q3hQeF45wP&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CBYQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=catalanismo%20secta%20religiosa&amp;f=false In Spanish, quotes by Francesc Cambó and Josep Pla]&lt;/ref&gt; But after the Spanish-American war in which the United States invaded and annexed the last of the Spanish colonies, these early stages of Catalanism grew in support, mostly because of the weakened Spanish international position after the war and the loss of the two main destinations for Catalan exports ([[Cuba]] and [[Puerto Rico]]).

==Several forms of contemporary Catalanism==
Being a broad movement, it can be found in several presentations in the current political scenario. Most of the main Catalan political parties ([[Convergence and Union]] (CiU), [[Socialists' Party of Catalonia]] (PSC),&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.socialistes.cat/public/PONENCIAXIeCONGRES-English.pdf Declaration in the 11th Congress of PSC]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Republican Left of Catalonia]] (ERC) and [[Initiative for Catalonia Greens]] (ICV)) adhere to Catalanism to some extent, even though some of them (PSC and ICV) reject being labelled as &quot;independentist&quot;.{{Citation needed|date=August 2008}}

The framework for their national demands diverges as well. While some restrict them to Catalonia-proper, others claim to seek for the acknowledgment of the political personality of the so-called ''[[Catalan Countries]]'', the Catalan-speaking territories as a whole. Such claims, which can be seen as a form of [[Pan-nationalism]], can be read in official documents of CiU,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.convergencia.org/media/120.pdf Catalunya a Europa i el món, Ponència de CiU]&lt;/ref&gt; ERC &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.esquerra.cat/documents/arxiu/declaracio.pdf Declaració ideològica d'ERC]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Popular Unity Candidates]] (CUP).&lt;ref&gt;[http://nacional.cup.cat/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=11&amp;Itemid=44 CUP presentation on their web page]&lt;/ref&gt; Besides Catalonia, the main Catalan-speaking regions have their own nationalist parties and coalitions thereof which support, at some degree, the demands for the building of a national personality for the Catalan Countries: [[Valencian Nationalist Bloc]] (BNV)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bloc.ws/index.php/bloc/extended-local/ponncia_destatuts_aprovada_al_iv_congrs_nacional_del_bloc/global/ Ponència del Bloc Nacionalista Valencià]&lt;/ref&gt; in the [[Valencian Community]], Bloc Nacional i d'Esquerres,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.psm-entesa.org/documentos/declaracio_politica_BLOC_20b1.pdf Declaració política del Bloc Nacional i d'Esquerres]&lt;/ref&gt; PSM and [[Majorcan Union]] (UM) in the Balearic Islands. Other nationalist parties existed with additional affiliation such as [[PSC - Reagrupament]] whose leader  [[Josep Pallach i Carolà]] died in 1977. 

The two main Catalan nationalist parties have shown their commitment to the idea of the Catalan Countries in different ways and with different intensities. For CiU, this issue is not among the main items in their agenda. Nevertheless, the federation has enjoyed a long term collaboration with the Valencian party BNV&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ciu.cat/fitxa_noticies.php?news_ID=4051&lt;/ref&gt; and with the Majorcan parties UM&lt;ref&gt;http://uniomallorquina.com/?id_section=197&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Socialist Party of Majorca]] (PSM).&lt;ref&gt;http://www.psm-entesa.org/historia2.php&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast, [[Esquerra Republicana de Catalunya]] (ERC) has taken more substantial steps in that direction by expanding the party to [[Roussillon]], [[Balearic Islands]] and (as [[Republican Left of the Valencian Country]] (ERPV)) the [[Valencian Community]].

==The origins of Catalan national identity==
During the first centuries of the [[Reconquista]], the [[Franks]] drove the Muslims south of the Pyrenees. To prevent future incursions, Holy Roman Emperor [[Charlemagne]] created the [[Marca Hispanica]] in 790 CE, which consisted of a series of [[petty kingdom]]s serving as [[buffer state]]s between the Frankish kingdom and [[Al-Andalus]]. 

Between 878 and 988 CE, the area became a hotbed of Frankish-Muslim conflict. However, as the Frankish monarchy and the [[Caliphate of Córdoba]] weakened during the 11th century, the resulting impasse allowed for a process of consolidation throughout the region's many [[earl]]doms, resulting in their combination into the [[County of Barcelona]], which became the embryo of today's Catalonia. By 1070, [[Ramon Berenguer I]], Count of Barcelona, had subordinated other Catalan Counts and intransigent [[nobility|nobles]] as [[vassal]]s. His action brought peace to a turbulent feudal system and sowed the seeds of Catalan [[cultural identity|identity]].

According to several scholars, the term &quot;Catalan&quot; and &quot;Catalonia&quot; emerged near the end of the 11th century and appeared in the ''[[Usatges]]'' of 1150. Two factors fostered this identity: stable institutions and cultural prosperity. While the temporary lack of foreign invasions contributed to Catalonia's stability, it was not a main cause. Rather, it provided a site for sociopolitical development. For example, after the County of Barcelona merged with the [[Kingdom of Aragon]], to create the [[Crown of Aragon]] in 1137 through a [[dynastic union]], the system was designed to mutually check both the king's and nobility's powers, while the small but growing numbers of free citizens and bourgeoisie would tactically take sides with the king in order to diminish typically feudal institutions. 

By 1150, the king approved a series of pacts, called the Usatges, which &quot;explicitly acknowledged legal equality between burghers…and nobility&quot; (Woolard 17). In addition, the Catalan-Aragonese gentry established the ''[[Cortes Generales|Corts]]'', a representative body of nobles, [[bishop]]s, and [[abbot]]s that counterbalanced the King's authority. By the end of the 13th century, &quot;the monarch needed the consent of the Corts to approve laws or collect revenue&quot; (McRoberts 10). Soon after, the ''Corts'' elected a standing body called the ''Diputació del General'' or the ''[[Generalitat]]'', which included the rising high bourgeoisie. The first [[Catalan constitutions]] were promulgated by the ''Corts of Barcelona'' in 1283, following the Roman tradition of the [[Codex]].

In the 13th century, King [[James I of Aragon]] conquered [[Kingdom of Valencia|Valencia]] and the [[Balearic Islands]]. Subsequent conquests expanded into the Mediterranean, reaching [[Sardinia]], [[Corsica]], [[Sicily]], [[Naples]] and Greece, so by 1350 the [[Crown of Aragon]] &quot;presided over the one of the most extensive and powerful mercantile empires of the Mediterranean during this period&quot; (Woolard 16). Catalonia's economic success formed a powerful [[merchant]] class, which wielded the Corts as its political weapon. It also produced a smaller middle class, or ''menestralia'', that was &quot;composed of artisans, shopkeepers and workshop owners&quot; (McRoberts 11). 

Over the 13th and 14th centuries, these merchants accrued so much wealth and political sway that placed a significant check on the Aragonese crown. By the 15th century the Aragonese monarch &quot;was not considered legitimate until he had sworn to respect the basic law of the land in the presence of the ''Corts''&quot; (Balcells 9). This balance of power is a classic example of ''pactisme'', or contractualism, which seems to be a defining feature of the Catalan [[political culture]].

Along with political and economic success, Catalan culture flourished in the 13th and 14th centuries. During this period, the Catalan vernacular gradually replaced Latin as the language of culture and government. Scholars rewrote everything from ancient [[Visigoths|Visigothic]] law to religious sermons in Catalan (Woolard 14). Wealthy citizens bolstered Catalan's literary appeal through poetry contests and history pageants dubbed the ''[[Jocs Florals]]'', or &quot;Floral Games.&quot; As the kingdom expanded southeast into Valencia and the Mediterranean, Catalan followed.

The [[medieval]] heyday of Catalan culture would not last, however. After a bout of famine and [[Bubonic plague|plague]] hit Catalonia in the mid-14th century, the population dropped from 500,000 to 200,000 (McRoberts 13). This exacerbated feudal tensions, sparking [[serf]] revolts in rural areas and political impasses in Barcelona. Financial issues and the burden of multiple dependencies abroad further strained the region. 

In 1410, the king died without leaving an heir to the throne. Finding no legitimate alternative, leaders of the realms composing the [[Crown of Aragon]] agreed by means of the [[Compromise of Caspe]] that the vacant throne should go to the Castilian [[Ferdinand I of Aragon|Ferdinand I]], as he was among the nearest relatives of the recently extinguished [[House of Barcelona]] through a maternal line. The new dynasty began to assert the authority of the Crown, leading to a perception among the nobility that their traditional privileges associated with their position in society were at risk. From 1458 to 1479, civil wars between King [[John II of Aragon|John II]] and local chieftains engulfed Catalonia. 

During the conflict, John II, in the face of French aggression in the Pyrenees&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/557573/Spain/70383/United-Spain-under-the-Catholic-Monarchs#ref=ref587441&amp;tab=active~checked%2Citems~checked&amp;title=Spain%20%3A%3A%20United%20Spain%20under%20the%20Catholic%20Monarchs%20--%20Britannica%20Online%20Encyclopedia]&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;had his heir Ferdinand married to [[Isabella I of Castile]], the heiress to the Castilian throne, in a bid to find outside allies&quot; (Balcells 11). Their dynastic union, which came to be known as the [[Catholic Monarchs]], marked the ''de facto'' unification of the [[Kingdom of Spain]]. At that point, however, ''de jure'' both the [[Crown of Castile|Castile]] and the Crown of Aragon remained distinct territories, each keeping its own traditional institutions, parliaments and laws.  This was a common practice at this time in Western Europe as the concept of sovereignty lay in the monarch.  

With the dawn of the [[Age of Discovery]], led by the Portuguese, the importance of the Aragonese possessions in the Mediterranean became drastically reduced and, along the rise of [[barbary pirates]] predating commerce in the Mediterranean, the theater of European power shifted from the Mediterranean basin to the Atlantic Ocean. These political and economic restrictions impacted all segments of society. Also, because of the locally bred social conflicts, Catalonia squandered in one century most of what it had gained in political rights between 1070 and 1410.

Nevertheless, early political, economic and cultural advances gave Catalonia &quot;a mode of organization and an awareness of its own identity which might in some ways be described as national, though the idea of popular or national sovereignty did not yet exist&quot; (Balcells 9). Other scholars like Kenneth McRoberts and Katheryn Woolard hold similar views. Both support Pierre Vilar, who contends that in 13th and 14th centuries &quot;the Catalan principality was perhaps the European country to which it would be the least inexact or risky to use such seemingly anachronistic terms as political and economic [[imperialism]] or ‘[[nation-state]]’&quot; (McRoberts 13). In other words, an array of political and cultural forces laid the foundations of Catalan &quot;national&quot; identity. 

Llobera agrees with this opinion, saying, &quot;By the mid-thirteenth century, the first solid manifestations of national consciousness can be observed.&quot; Indeed, 13th and 14th century Catalonia did exhibit features of a nation-state. The role of Catalan Counts, the ''Corts'', Mediterranean rule and economic prosperity support this thesis. But as Vilar points out, these analogies are only true if we acknowledge that a 14th century nation-state is anachronistic. In other words, those living in Catalonia before latter day nationalism possessed something like a collective identity on which this was to be based, but this does not automatically equate to the modern concept of nation, neither in Catalonia nor elsewhere in similar circumstances during the Middle Age.

The ''Corts'' and the rest of the autochthonous legal and political organization was finally terminated in 1716, as a result of the [[War of the Spanish Succession]]. The local population mostly took sides and provided troops and resources for [[Charles VI, Holy Roman Emperor|Archduke Charles]], the pretender, who was arguably to maintain the legal [[status quo]]. His utter defeat meant the legal and political termination of the autonomous parliaments in the Crown of Aragon, as the [[Nueva Planta decrees]] were passed and King [[Philip V of Spain]] of the new [[House of Bourbon]] sealed the transformation of Spain from a ''de facto'' unified realm into a ''de jure'' centralized state.

==The development of modern Catalanism==
The [[Renaixença]] (&quot;rebirth&quot; or &quot;renaissance&quot;) was a cultural, historical and literary movement that pursued in the wake of European [[Romanticism]] the recovery of the own language and literature. As time went by, and particularly immediately after the fiasco of the [[Glorious Revolution (Spain)|Revolution of 1868]] 
(led by the Catalan general Juan Prim), the movement acquired a clear political character, directed to the attainment of self-government for Catalonia within the framework of the Spanish liberal state.

Like most [[Romanticism|Romantic]] currents, the Renaixença gave historical analysis a central role. History, in fact, was an integral part of Catalonia's &quot;rebirth.&quot; Texts on Catalonia's history—inspired by the Romantic philosophy of history—laid the foundations of a Catalanist movement. Works like Valentí Almirall i Llozer's ''Lo Catalanisme'', Victor Balaguer's ''Historia de Cataluña y de la Corona de Aragón'' and Prat de la Riba's ''La nacionalitat catalana'' used history as evidence for Catalonia's nationhood. According to Elie Kedourie, such claims were common in 19th century nationalist discourse because &quot;the ‘past’ is used to explain the ‘present,’ to give it meaning and legitimacy. The ‘past’ reveals one's identity, and history determines one's role in the drama of human development and progress&quot; (36). Publications of histories thus &quot;explained&quot; why the Catalans constituted a nation instead of a Spanish region or coastal province. 

At the heart of many of works of the Renaixença lay a powerful idea: the [[Volk]]. Indeed, the concept of Volk (pl. Völker) played a vital role in mainstream Catalan Romantic nationalism. It has its origins in the writings of German Romantics like [[Friedrich Carl von Savigny]], [[Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel]] and, most notably, [[Johann Gottfried Herder]]. 
	
The concept of Volk entered Catalan intellectual circles in the 1830s, stemming from the emphasis on the region's medieval history and philology. It first appeared in the writings of Joan Cortada, Marti d'Eixalà and his discipline, Francesc-Xavier Llorens i Barba, intellectuals who reinvigorated the literature on the Catalan national character.  Inspired by the ideas of Herder, Savigny and the entire [[Scottish School of Common Sense]], they asked why the Catalans were different from other Spaniards—especially the Castilians (Conversi 1997: 15) For example, Cortada wanted to determine why, despite its poor natural environment, Catalonia was so much more successful than other parts of Spain. In a series of generalizations, he concluded that the &quot;Catalans have succeeded in developing a strong sense of resolution and constancy over the centuries. Another feature of their character was the fact that they were hardworking people&quot; (Llobera 1983: 342). D’Eixalà and Llorens held a similar understanding of the Catalan national character. They held that that two characteristics particular to Catalans were common sense ([[seny]]) and industriousness. To them, &quot;the traditional Catalan seny was a manifestation of the [[Volksgeist]]&quot;, one which made Catalans essentially different from Castilians (Llobera 2004: 75). 

The early works on the Catalan ''Volk'' would remain on paper long before they entered politics. This is because the Catalan [[bourgeoisie]] had not yet abandoned the hope of spearheading the Spanish state (Conversi 1997: 14). Indeed, in the 1830s, the Renaixença was still embryonic and the industrial class still thought that it could at least control the Spanish economy. Notions of Catalonia's uniqueness mattered little to a group that believed it could integrate and lead the entire country. But this all changed around 1880. After decades of discrimination from Spanish elites, Catalan industrialists buried their dream of leading Spain. As Vilar observes: &quot;It is only because, in its acquisition of the Spanish market, the Catalan industrial bourgeoisie did not succeed either in securing the state apparatus or identifying its interests with those of the whole of Spain, in influential opinion, that Catalonia, this little &quot;fatherland&quot;, finally became the 'national' focal point&quot;, (1980: 551)

This switch of allegiance was particularly easy because the idea of a Catalan nation had already matured into a corpus of texts about the region's &quot;uniqueness&quot; and ''Volksgeist''. Inspired by these works of Romantic nationalism, the Catalan economic elite became conscious of &quot;the growing dissimilitude between the Catalonia's social structure and that of the rest of the nation&quot; (Vilar 1963: 101).  Consequently, Romantic nationalism (and the ''Volk'') expanded beyond its philosophical bounds into the political arena.

In the last third of the 19th century, Catalanism was formulating its own doctrinal foundations, not only among the progressive ranks but also in the conservative, and at the same time it started to establish the first political programmes (e.g. ''Bases de Manresa'', 1892), and to generate a wide cultural and association movement of a clearly vindicatory character.

In 1898, Spain lost its last colonial possessions in [[Cuba]] and the [[Philippines]], a fact that not only involved an important crisis of confidence, but also gave an impulse to political Catalanism. The first modern political party in Catalonia and Spain was the [[Regionalist League|Lliga Regionalista]]. Founded in 1901, it formed a coalition in 1907 with other Catalanist forces (from [[Carlism]] to Federalists), grouped in the so-called ''Solidaritat Catalana'', and won the elections with the regionalist programme that [[Enric Prat de la Riba]] had formulated in his manifesto ''La nacionalitat catalana'' (1906).

===Industrialization and Catalanism===
[[Image:Catalonia nation.JPG|thumb|right|Nationalist graffiti in Catalonia]]

The 18th century Spanish economy depended mostly on [[agriculture]]. The social structure stayed hierarchical, if not [[feudal]], while the [[Catholic Church]] and [[House of Bourbon|Bourbon]] [[monarch]]s wrestled for internal supremacy. Into the 19th century, the Napoleonic invasion devastated the country and its early attempts for industrialization and led to political unstability, so Spain remained politically and culturally isolated from the rest of Europe.

Unlike in the rest of Spain, the [[Industrial Revolution]] made some progress in Catalonia, whose pro-industry [[middle class]] strived to mechanize everything, from [[textile]]s and crafts to [[wineries]]. Industrialization and trade went hand in hand with the proto-nationalist ''[[Renaixença]]'' cultural movement, which, annoyed with the shortcomings of the Royal court in Madrid, began to fashion an alternative, and that was Catalan identity.

To finance their cultural project, a locally bred proto-nationalist [[intelligentsia]] sought patronage and protection from Barcelona's industrial barons. This relationship played a decisive role in the development of Catalanism. On the one hand, intellectuals sought to renew Catalan identity as a response to Spain's overall backwardness. They wanted to distance themselves from the Spanish problems by creating a new [[ontology]] rooted in Catalan [[culture]], language and [[world view]]. On the other hand, those same intellectuals avoided demands for separation. They knew that their patrons would want Catalan nationalism to include Spain for two reasons:

* Any secession from Spain would devastate industrial markets and impoverish the region.
* The Catalan [[Industrial society|industrial class]] was &quot;unconditionally pro-Spanish at heart&quot; (Conversi 1997: 18).

As Woolard notes, the economic interests in Madrid and the budding Catalan industrialists converged during the 18th century, resulting in cooperation. For the nationalist [[intellectual|literati]], this meant that Catalanism could promote a national identity, but it had to function within Spain.

Furthermore, Barcelona's industrial [[elite]] wanted Catalonia to stay part of Spain since Catalonia's industrial markets relied on consumption from other Spanish regions which, little by little, started to join some sort of development. In fact, part of the industrialists’ desire to remain part of Spain was their desire for protectionism, hegemony in domestic markets and the push to &quot;influence Madrid's political choices by intervening in central Spanish affairs&quot; (Conversi 1997: 18-20), thus, it made no economic sense to promote any secession from Spain. On the contrary, Catalonia's prominent industrialists acted as the Spanish leading economic heads. As [[Stanley Payne]] observes: &quot;The modern Catalan élite had played a major role in what there was of economic industrialization in the nineteenth century, and had tended to view Catalonia not as the antagonist but to some degree the leader of a freer, more prosperous Spain&quot; (482). Barcelona's [[bourgeois]] industrialists even claimed that protectionism and leadership served the interests of the &quot;‘national market’ or of ‘developing the national economy’ (national meaning Spanish here) &quot; (Balcells 19). The inclusion of Spain was instrumental to Catalonia's success, meaning that industrialists would not tolerate any secessionist movement. Claiming that independence would have assured nothing but weak markets, an internal enemy and strengthened [[anarchist]] movements. And hence, though manufacturers funded the ''Renaixença''— and Catalan nationalism — they demanded that Catalonia stayed part of Spain to ensure economic stability.

This federalist-like lobbying had not worked at first, nor did it succeed until the late 1880s. Finally, in 1889, the pro-industrialist [[Regionalist League|''Lliga Regionalista'']] managed to save the particular Catalan [[Civil Code]], after a [[Classical liberalism|liberal]] attempt to homogenize the Spanish legal structures (Conversi 1997: 20). Two years later, they coaxed Madrid into passing protectionist measures, which reinvigorated pro-Spanish attitudes among manufacturers. Then, they also took great profits from Spain's [[Neutrality (international relations)|neutrality]] in World War I, which allowed them to export to both sides, and the [[Spanish Protectorate of Morocco|Spanish expansion in Morocco]], which Catalan industrialists encouraged, since it was to become a fast growing market for them. Also, by early 20th century, Catalan businessmen had managed to gain control of the most profitable commerce between Spain and its American colonies and ex-colonies, namely Cuba and [[Puerto Rico]]. 

This nationalist-industrialist accord is a classic example of inclusionary Catalanism. Nationalists might have hoped for an independent Catalonia but their patrons needed access to markets and [[protectionism]]. As a result, nationalists could propagate the Catalan identity provided that it coincided with the industrialists’ pro-Spanish stance. Because the ''Lliga Regionalista de Catalunya'' endorsed this compromise, it dominated Catalan politics after the turn of the 19th to 20th century. Payne notes: &quot;The main Catalanist party, the bourgeois Lliga, never sought separatism but rather a more discrete and distinctive place for a self-governing Catalonia within a more reformist and progressive Spain. The ''Lliga'''s leaders ran their 1916 electoral campaign under the slogan ''‘Per l'Espanya Gran’'' (For the Great Spain)&quot; (482). The ''Lliga'' had tempered the nationalist position to one of inclusionary nationalism. It allowed Catalanism to flourish, but demanded that it promote [[federalism]] within Spain, and not separation from it. Any deviation from this delicate balance would have enraged those pro-Catalan and Spanish-identifying industrialists. Ultimately, this prevented any moves towards separation while strengthening Catalonia's &quot;federal&quot; rights after the [[Commonwealth of Catalonia]] took power in 1914.

===Catalanism in the 20th century===
[[Image:060218 ManiSomunaNacio24.jpg|thumb|right|Catalan Nationalist demonstration celebrated in Barcelona on 18 February 2006]]

During the first part of the 20th century, the main nationalist party was the right-wing [[Regionalist League|''Lliga Regionalista'']], headed by [[Francesc Cambó]]. For the nationalists, the main achievement in this period was the [[Commonwealth of Catalonia]] a grouping of the four Catalan provinces, with limited administrative power. This institution was abolished during the dictatorship of [[Miguel Primo de Rivera]].

In 1931, the left-wing ''[[Esquerra Republicana de Catalunya]]'' party won the elections in Catalonia, advocating a [[Catalan Republic]] federated with Spain. Under pressure from the Spanish government, the leader of [[Republican Left of Catalonia|ERC]], [[Francesc Macià i Llussà]], accepted an autonomous Catalan government instead, which recovered the historical name of [[Generalitat de Catalunya]].

A dramatically short period of restoration of democratic and cultural normality was interrupted at its outset by the outbreak of the [[Spanish Civil War]]. The autonomous government was abolished in 1939, after the victory of the [[Francoist]] troops. During the last stages of the war, when the Republican side was on the verge of defeat, Catalan president of the Generalitat, [[Lluís Companys]], rhetorically declared Catalan independence, even though it never materialized due to objections within Catalonia and, eventually, by the defeat of the [[Second Spanish Republic]].

[[Image:Companysmemorial.JPG|thumb|frame|left|Small monument in [[Barcelona]] dedicated to [[Lluís Companys]], the Catalan Nationalist leader executed by Franco's Nationalists in 1940]]

Right after the war, Companys, along with thousands of Spanish Republicans, sought cover in France exiled but because of the, by that time, mutual sympathy between Franco's government and [[Nazi Germany]], he was captured after the [[Fall of France]] in 1940 and handed to Spanish authorities, who tortured him and which sentenced him to death for 'military rebellion'. He was executed at [[Montjuïc]] in Barcelona at 6.30 a.m. on October 15, 1940. Refusing to wear a blindfold, he was taken before a firing squad of Civil Guards and, as they fired, he cried 'Per Catalunya!'.&lt;ref&gt;Preston, Paul. (2012). ''The Spanish Holocaust.'' Harper Press. London p.493&lt;/ref&gt;

Several political or cultural Catalan movements operated underground during the dictatorship of [[Francisco Franco]], which lasted until 1975. A president of the Catalan government was still designated, and operated symbolically in exile.

Companys's successor in exile, [[Josep Tarradellas i Joan]], kept away from Spain until Franco's death in 1975. When he came back in 1977, the government of Catalonia -the ''[[Generalitat of Catalonia|Generalitat]]''- was restored again. Following the approval of the Spanish constitution in 1978, a [[Statute of Autonomy of Catalonia of 1979|Statute of Autonomy]] was promulgated and approved in referendum. Catalonia was organized as an [[Autonomous Community]], and in 1980, [[Jordi Pujol i Soley]], from the conservative nationalist party ''[[Convergència Democràtica de Catalunya]]'', was elected president and ruled the autonomous government for 23 consecutive years. 

[[Image:Manifestació10J-293.JPG|thumb|View of the [[2010 Catalan autonomy protest|demonstration on 10 July 2010]] ([[Barcelona]]) to reject the ruling that the [[Constitutional Court of Spain]] had about [[Statute of Autonomy of Catalonia|Statute of Autonomy (2006)]] and in favor of [[Self-determination|the right to decide]].]]
In contrast, there is no significant political autonomy, nor recognition of the language in the historical [[Northern Catalonia|Catalan territories]] belonging to France ([[Rosselló|Roussillon]], in the [[Departments of France|French département]] of [[Pyrénées-Orientales]]).

Currently, the main political parties which define themselves as being Catalan nationalists are ''[[Convergència Democràtica de Catalunya]]'', ''[[Unió Democràtica de Catalunya]]'' and the ''[[Reagrupament|Independence Rally]]''. The ''[[Esquerra Republicana de Catalunya]]'', although deriving from nationalism, refuses the term &quot;nationalism&quot; and prefers to describe itself as [[Catalan separatism|independentist]]; so does ''[[Catalan Solidarity for Independence|Soldaritat Catalana]]''. These parties obtained 50,03% of the votes in the [[Catalonian parliamentary election, 2010|2010 election]]. Within these parties, there is much divergence of opinion. More radical elements are only content with the establishment of a separate Catalan state. In contrast, more moderate elements do not necessarily identify with the belief that protection of Catalan identity is incompatible within Spain. Others vote for these parties simply as a protest and do not necessarily identify with the overall party platform (for example, some people may vote for ERC because they are simply tired of CiU, even though they do not actually desire a leftist Catalan republic). The other way around also occurs: some voters may vote for non-nationalist parties (especially the [[Initiative for Catalonia Greens]], ICV, and the [[Socialists' Party of Catalonia]], PSC) for reasons of policy, ideology or personal preference, although they share a nationalist viewpoint regarding Catalonia's status within Spain. Some polls, conducted in 2010, show that more than a third of PSC and more than half of ICV voters support Catalonia's independence (in the latter case, the percentage is even higher than among [[Convergence and Union]] voters); according to these polls, even 15% of the pro-Spanish [[People's Party (Spain)|Partido Popular]] voters in Catalonia support the region's independence.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.burbuja.info/inmobiliaria/politica/168925-encuesta-sobre-la-independencia-un-15-de-votantes-del-pp-catalan-son-secesionistas.html&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2006, a [[Catalonian constitutional referendum, 2006|referendum]] was held on amending the [[Statute of Autonomy of Catalonia of 1979]] to further expand the authority of the Catalan government. It was approved by 73.24% of the census, and became effective as of August 9, 2006. However, the turnout of 48.84% represented an unprecedented high [[abstention]] in Catalonia's democratic history. This has been cited both as a symptom of having large sectors in the average populace disengaged or at odds with the politics of identity in Catalonia,&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20080227060215/http://www.ciutadansdecatalunya.com/pdf/eng.pdf Some Catalan intellectuals denounce in a public manifesto what they deem as excesses of Catalan nationalism, 2005 (in English)]&lt;/ref&gt; and, alternatively, as a symptom of fatigue among Catalan nationalists who would like to see bolder steps towards political autonomy or independence. In this regard, both ''[[Esquerra Republicana de Catalunya]]'' (Catalan independentist left wing) and ''[[People's Party (Spain)|Partido Popular]]'' (Spanish right wing) campaigned against having the 2006 Statute of Autonomy passed: the former considered it too little, the latter too much.

== See also ==
* [[Anti-Catalanism]]
* [[Catalan symbols]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

== References ==
* Alland, Alexander. Catalunya, One Nation, Two States: An Ethnographic Study of Nonviolent Resistance to Assimilation. New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2006.
* Balcells, Albert. Catalan Nationalism: Past and Present. New York: St. Martin's Press, Inc., 1996.
* Conversi, Daniele. ''The Basques, the Catalans, and Spain: Alternative Routes to Nationalist Mobilisation''. London: Hurst &amp; Company, 1997. ISBN 1-85065-268-6.
* Conversi, Daniele. &quot;Language or race?: the choice of core values in the development of Catalan and Basque nationalisms.&quot; Ethnic and Racial Studies 13 (1990): 50-70.
* Elliot, J.H. The Revolt of the Catalans. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1963.
* Figueres, Josep M. Valentí Almirall, Forjador del Catalanisme Polític. Barcelona: Generalitat: Entitat Autònoma del Diari Official i de Publicacions, 1990.
* Fradera, Josep M. Cultura Nacional en una Societat Dividida. Barcelona: Curial, 1992.
* ---. &quot;Rural Traditionalism and Conservative Nationalism in Catalonia 1865-1900.&quot; Critique of Anthropology X (1990): 51-72.
* Guibernau, Monserrat. Catalan Nationalism: Francoism, transition and democracy. Routledge: New York, 2004.
* Harvgreaves, John. Freedom for Catalonia? Catalan Nationalism, Spanish Identity and the Barcelona Olympic Games. New York: Cambridge, 2000.
* Herder, Johann Gottfried von. Introduction. Reflections on the Philosophy of the History of Mankind. By Manuel. Ed. Frank E. Manuel. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1968.
* Hooper, John. The Spaniards: a Portrait of the New Spain. Suffolk: Penguin Books, 1986.
* &quot;Jacint Verdaguer i Santaló.&quot; Enciclopèdia Catalana. 2006. S.A. 12 Oct 2006 &lt;http://www.grec.net/cgibin/hecangcl.pgm?&amp;USUARI=&amp;SESSIO=&amp;NDCHEC=0070084&amp;PGMORI=E&gt;.
* Keating, Michael. Nations Against the State: The New Politics of Nationalism in Quebec, Catalonia and Scotland. New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2001.
* Kedourie, Elie. Nationalism in Asia and Africa. London: Frank Cass, 1970.
* Linz, Juan. &quot;Early State-Building and Late Peripheral Nationalisms Against the State: the Case of Spain.&quot; Building States and Nations: Analyses by Region. Eds. S.N. Eisenstadt, and [[Stein Rokkan]]. Beverly Hills: Sage, 1973. 32-116.
* Llobera, Josep R. Foundations of National Identity: from Catalonia to Europe. New York: Berghahn Books, 2004.
* ---. &quot;The idea of Volksgeist in the formation of Catalan nationalist ideology&quot; Ethnic and Racial Studies 6 (1983): 332-350.
* McRoberts, Kenneth. Catalonia: Nation Building Without a State. New York: Oxford, 2001.
* Payne, Stanley G. &quot;Nationalism, Regionalism and Micronationalism in Spain.&quot; Journal of Contemporary History 26.3/4 (1991): 479-491.
* Penrose, Jan, and Joe May. &quot;Herder's Concept of the Nation and Its Relevance to Contemporary Ethnic Nationalism.&quot; Canadian Review of Studies in Nationalism XVIII (1991): 165-177.
* Smith, Angel, and Clare Mar-Molinero. &quot;The Myths and Realities of Nation-Building in the Iberian Peninsula.&quot; Nationalism and the Nation in the Iberian Peninsula: Competing and Conflicting Identities. Eds. Angel Smith, and Clare Mar-Molinero. Washington, D.C.: Berg, 1996. 1-33.
* Vilar, Pierre. La Catalogne dans L’Espagne moderne. Paris: Flammation, 1977 (Spanish Translation: 'Cataluña en la España moderna'. Barcelona: Editorial Crítica Grijalbo, 1978)
* ---. Historia de España. Paris: Librarie Espagnole, 1963.
* ---. &quot;Spain and Catalonia.&quot; Review III (1980): 527-577.
* Vives, Jaime Vicens. Approaches to the History of Spain. 2nd. Berkeley: University of California Press, 1970.
* Woolard, Kathryn A. Double Talk: Bilingualism and the Politics of Ethnicity in Catalonia. Stanford: Stanford University Press, 1989.

== External links ==
{{commons category|Nationalism of Catalonia}}
* [http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=FA0611FD385B0C718CDDA80994DE404482 Party Urging More Autonomy From Spain Seems to Win in Catalonia] Article on New York Times, November 2, 2006
* [http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F60D10FD34550C718EDDAF0894DE404482 Courage in Catalonia] Article on New York Times, June 22, 2006
* [http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F70D11FF35550C7A8DDDAF0894DE404482 Voters in Catalonia Approve A Plan for Greater Autonomy] Article on New York Times, June 19, 2006
* [http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F30C13FF39540C728FDDAA0894DE404482 Spain Moves On Law to Give Broad Powers To Catalonia] Article on New York Times, March 31, 2006
* [http://www.grec.net/cgibin/hecangcl.pgm?&amp;USUARI=&amp;SESSIO=&amp;NDCHEC=0224838&amp;PGMORI=E Catalanism] ''in Catalan Encyclopaedia''
*[http://10anys.vilaweb.com/trueta/index.html The Spirit of Catalonia]. 1946 book by Oxford Professor Dr. [[Josep Trueta]]
* [http://vimeo.com/24052492 Spain's secret conflict (Documentary)]

{{Stateless nationalism in Europe}}
{{Ethnic nationalism}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Catalan Nationalism}}
[[Category:Catalan Countries]]
[[Category:Catalan nationalism| ]]
[[Category:Nationalism by country or region]]
[[Category:Nationalisms of Spain]]
[[Category:Pan-nationalism]]
[[Category:Politics of Catalonia]]

{{Link FA|ca}}
{{Link GA|uk}}

[[an:Nacionalismo catalán]]
[[ast:Nacionalismu catalán]]
[[ca:Catalanisme]]
[[cy:Cenedlaetholdeb Catalanaidd]]
[[de:Katalanismus]]
[[et:Katalaani rahvuslus]]
[[es:Nacionalismo catalán]]
[[eo:Kataluna naciismo]]
[[ext:Nacionalismu catalán]]
[[eu:Katalanismo]]
[[fa:ملی‌گرایی کاتالان]]
[[fr:Catalanisme]]
[[gl:Catalanismo]]
[[ko:카탈루냐 민족주의]]
[[io:Kataluniana nacionalismo]]
[[nl:Catalanisme]]
[[ja:カタルーニャ・ナショナリズム]]
[[no:Katalansk nasjonalisme]]
[[oc:Catalanisme]]
[[pt:Nacionalismo catalão]]
[[ro:Naționalismul catalan]]
[[ru:Каталонизм]]
[[tr:Katalan milliyetçiliği]]
[[uk:Каталонський національний рух]]</text>
      <sha1>6t0zuvjdgrvsy74nddxfl72qgp81ngr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
