<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Cherokee</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>50490</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520898947</id>
      <parentid>520898926</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-01T14:06:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contributions/70.90.36.153|70.90.36.153]] to version by Til Eulenspiegel. False positive? [[User:ClueBot NG/FalsePositives|Report it]]. Thanks, [[User:ClueBot NG|ClueBot NG]]. (1308300) (Bot)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="87632">{{Other uses}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=December 2011}}
{{Infobox ethnic group
|group    = Cherokee&lt;br&gt;ᏣᎳᎩ&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;ᎠᏂᏴᏫᏯᎢ&lt;/small&gt;
|image    = [[File:Cherokees.jpg|none|250px]]
|image_caption=From the top, L-R:
John Ross or Tsanusdi; Colonel E. C. Boudinot Jr.; Samuel Smith; Lilly Smith: Walini;  Marcia Pascal;  Lillian Gross; William Penn; Thomas M. Cook
|poptime  = 316,049+ &lt;br/&gt;(Eastern Band: 13,000+, Cherokee Nation: 288,749, United Keetoowah Band: 14,300)&lt;ref name=oia&gt;[http://www.ok.gov/oiac/Publications/ &quot;Pocket Pictorial.&quot;] ''Oklahoma Indian Affairs Commission.'' 2010: 6 and 37. (retrieved June 11, 2010)&lt;/ref&gt;
|popplace = {{flagicon|United States}} United States&lt;br&gt;({{flagicon|North Carolina}} [[North Carolina]], {{flagicon|Oklahoma}} [[Oklahoma]])
|rels     = Christianity, [[Keetoowah Nighthawk Society|Kituhwa]], [[Four Mothers Society]],&lt;ref&gt;Sturtevant and Fogelson, 613&lt;/ref&gt; [[Native American Church]]&lt;ref&gt;Minges, Patrick, [http://genebrooks.com/cpijournal2.html &quot;Middle and Valley Towns in Western North Carolina.&quot;] ''Cherokee Prayer Initiative Journal.'' 1999 (retrieved June 11, 2010)&lt;/ref&gt;
|langs    = English, [[Cherokee language|Cherokee]]
|related  =
}}
{{Contains Cherokee text}}
The '''Cherokee''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|tʃ|ɛr|ə|k|iː}}; {{lang-chr|ᏣᎳᎩ}} {{lang|chr|''Tsalagi''}}) are a Native American people historically settled in the Southeastern United States (principally [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]], [[the Carolinas]], and [[East Tennessee]]).  Linguistically, they are part of the [[Iroquoian languages|Iroquoian language family]].  In the 19th century, historians and [[ethnographers]] recorded their oral tradition that told of the tribe having migrated south in ancient times from the [[Great Lakes]] region, where other Iroquoian-speaking peoples were located.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mooney 1900 393&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|last= Mooney |first= James |authorlink= James Mooney |title= Myths of the Cherokee and Sacred Formulas of the Cherokees |publisher= Kessinger Publishing |origyear= 1900 |year= 2006 |isbn= 978-1-4286-4864-7 |url= http://books.google.com/?id=9HDbWUX71joC |page= 393}}&lt;/ref&gt; They began to have contact with European traders in the 18th century.

In the 19th century, white settlers in the United States called the Cherokee one of the &quot;[[Five Civilized Tribes]]&quot;, because they had assimilated numerous cultural and technological practices of [[European American]] settlers. The Cherokee were one of the first, if not the first, major non-European ethnic group to become U.S. citizens. Article 8 in the 1817 treaty with the Cherokee stated Cherokees may wish to become citizen of the United States.&lt;ref name=Cherokee_us_citizenship&gt;
{{Cite web
| url        = http://digital.library.okstate.edu/kappler/vol2/treaties/che0140.htm
| title      = INDIAN AFFAIRS: LAWS AND TREATIES Vol. II, Treaties
| accessdate = 2012-05-16
| author     = Charles Kappler
| last       = Kappler
| first      = Charles
| year       = 1904
| publisher  = Government Printing Office
}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the 2000 U.S. Census, the [[Cherokee Nation]] has more than 300,000 members, the largest of the 565 [[Federally recognized tribes|federally recognized Native American tribes]] in the United States.&lt;ref name=Census_2002&gt;{{cite web| title = The American Indian and Alaska Native Population: 2000 | work = Census 2000 Brief| url = http://www.census.gov/prod/2002pubs/c2kbr01-15.pdf |format=PDF| date = February 1, 2002 |accessdate =March 10, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Of the three federally recognized Cherokee tribes, the [[Cherokee Nation]] and the [[United Keetoowah Band of Cherokee Indians]] (UKB) have headquarters in [[Tahlequah, Oklahoma|Tahlequah]], Oklahoma. The UKB are mostly descendants of &quot;Old Settlers&quot;, Cherokee who migrated to Arkansas and Oklahoma about 1817.  The Cherokee Nation are related to the people who were [[Cherokee removal|forcibly relocated]] there in the 1830s under the [[Indian Removal Act]]. The [[Eastern Band of Cherokee Indians]] is located on the [[Qualla Boundary]] in western [[North Carolina]].

In addition, there are Cherokee bands in the [[Southeastern United States|Southeast]] that are recognized as tribes by [[U.S. state|state]] governments, such as the Echota Cherokee Tribe of [[Alabama]], but not the [[U.S. federal government]].

==Name==
The Cherokee refer to themselves as ''Tsalagi'' ({{lang|chr|ᏣᎳᎩ}}) or Aniyvwiyaʔi ({{lang|chr|ᎠᏂᏴᏫᏯᎢ}}), which means &quot;Principal People.&quot; The [[Iroquois]], who were based in New York, called the Cherokee ''Oyata’ge'ronoñ'' (inhabitants of the cave country).

Many theories&amp;nbsp;– though none proven&amp;nbsp;– abound about the [[etymology|origin of the word]] Cherokee. It may have originally been derived from the [[Choctaw]] word ''Cha-la-kee'', which means &quot;those who live in the mountains&quot;, or Choctaw ''Chi-luk-ik-bi,'' meaning &quot;those who live in the cave country&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.accessgenealogy.com/native/tribes/cherokee/cherohist.htm Cherokee Indian Tribe.] ''Access Genealogy.'' (September 21, 2009)&lt;/ref&gt; The earliest Spanish rendering of Cherokee, from 1755, is ''Tchalaquei''.&lt;ref&gt;Charles A. Hanna, ''The Wilderness Trail'', (New York: 1911).&lt;/ref&gt; Another theory is that &quot;Cherokee&quot; derives from a [[Muscogee Creek|Lower Creek]] word, ''Ciló-kki'', meaning someone who speaks another language.&lt;ref&gt;Sturtevant and Fogelson, 349&lt;/ref&gt; The most likely derivation, however, is an [[Anglicisation]] of their [[Endonym|autonym]], or name for themselves: ''Tsalagi'' in their language. {{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

==Origins==
[[File:Smoky Mtn View.jpg|thumb|500px|[[Great Smoky Mountains]]]]
There are two prevailing views about Cherokee origins. One is that the Cherokee, an [[Iroquoian]]-speaking people, are relative latecomers to Southern [[Appalachia]], who may have migrated in late prehistoric times from northern areas, the traditional territory of the later ''[[Haudenosaunee]]'' five nations and other Iroquoian-speaking peoples. Researchers in the 19th century recorded conversations with elders who recounted an oral tradition of the Cherokee people's migrating south from the [[Great Lakes]] region in ancient times.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mooney 1900 393&quot;/&gt; The other theory, which is disputed by academic specialists, is that the Cherokee had been in the Southeast for thousands of years. There is no archeological evidence for this.

Some traditionalists, [[historians]] and [[archaeologists]] believe that the Cherokee did not come to Appalachia until the 15th century or later. They may have migrated from the north and moved south into [[Muscogee Creek]] territory and settled at the sites of [[mound]]s built by the [[Mississippian culture]]. During early research, archeologists had mistakenly attributed several Mississippian culture sites to the Cherokee, including [[Moundville Archaeological Site|Moundville]] and [[Etowah Indian Mounds|Etowah Mounds]]. Late 20th-century studies have shown conclusively instead that the weight of [[archeological]] evidence at the sites shows they are unquestionably related to ancestors of [[Muskogean]] peoples rather than to the Cherokee.

Pre-contact Cherokee are considered to be part of the later [[Pisgah Phase]] of Southern Appalachia, which lasted from circa 1000 to 1500.&lt;ref&gt;Sturtevant and Fogelson, 132&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the consensus among most specialists in Southeast archeology and anthropology, some scholars contend that ancestors of the Cherokee people lived in western North Carolina and eastern Tennessee for a far longer period of time.&lt;ref&gt;Finger, 6–7&lt;/ref&gt; During the late [[Archaic period in the Americas|Archaic]] and [[Woodland Period]], Indians in the region began to cultivate plants such as [[marsh elder]], [[Chenopodium berlandieri|lambsquarters]], [[pigweed]], [[sunflowers]] and some native [[Squash (plant)|squash]]. People created new art forms such as [[shell gorget]]s, adopted new technologies, and followed an elaborate cycle of religious ceremonies. During the [[Mississippian Culture]]-period (800 to 1500 CE), local women developed a new variety of maize (corn) called eastern [[flint corn|flint]].  It closely resembled modern corn and produced larger crops. The successful cultivation of corn surpluses allowed the rise of larger, more complex chiefdoms with several villages and concentrated populations during this period.  Corn became celebrated among numerous peoples in religious ceremonies, especially the [[Green Corn Ceremony]].

==Early cultures==
Much of what is known about pre-18th-century Native American cultures has come from records of Spanish expeditions. The earliest ones of the mid-16th century encountered people of the [[Mississippian culture]], the ancestors to later tribes in the Southeast such as the [[Muscogee (Creek)|Creek]] and [[Catawba (tribe)|Catawba]].  The Cherokee arrived later, descended from a different people, but they occupied some of the ancient Mississippian sites and were observed by the Spanish.{{Citation needed|date=October 2012}} Some of this work was not translated into English and made available to historians until the 20th century. In addition, the dominance of English colonists over the Southeast led to a discounting of Spanish sources for some time.

The American writer [[John Howard Payne]] wrote about pre-19th century Cherokee culture and society.  The Payne papers describe the account by Cherokee elders of a traditional two-part societal structure.  A &quot;white&quot; organization of elders represented the seven clans.  As Payne recounted, this group, which was [[hereditary]] and priestly, was responsible for religious activities, such as healing, purification, and prayer.  A second group of younger men, the &quot;red&quot; organization, was responsible for warfare.  The Cherokee considered warfare a polluting activity, and warriors required the purification by the priestly class before participants could reintegrate into normal village life.  This hierarchy had disappeared long before the 18th century.

Researchers have debated the reasons for the change.  Some historians believe the decline in priestly power originated with a revolt by the Cherokee against the abuses of the priestly class known as the ''[[Ani-kutani]]''.&lt;ref name = &quot;Irwina-1992&quot;&gt;Irwin 1992.&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Ethnographer]] [[James Mooney]], who studied the Cherokee in the late 1880s, was the first to trace the decline of the former hierarchy to this revolt.&lt;ref&gt;Mooney, p. 392.&lt;/ref&gt; By the time of Mooney, the structure of Cherokee religious practitioners was more informal, based more on individual knowledge and ability than upon heredity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Irwina-1992&quot;/&gt;

Another major source of early cultural history comes from materials written in the 19th century by the ''didanvwisgi'' ({{lang|chr|ᏗᏓᏅᏫᏍᎩ}}), Cherokee [[medicine man|medicine men]], after [[Sequoyah]]'s creation of the [[Cherokee syllabary]] in the 1820s.  Initially only the ''didanvwisgi'' adopted and used such materials, which were considered extremely powerful in a spiritual sense.&lt;ref name=&quot;Irwina-1992&quot;/&gt;  Later, the syllabary and writings were widely adopted by the Cherokee people.

Unlike most other Indians in the American Southeast at the start of the historic era, the Cherokee spoke an [[Iroquoian languages|Iroquoian language]].  Since the [[Great Lakes]] region was the core of Iroquoian-language speakers, scholars have theorized that the Cherokee migrated South from that region.  This is supported by the Cherokee [[oral history]] tradition. According to the scholars' theory, the [[Tuscarora people|Tuscarora]], another Iroquoian-speaking people who inhabited the Southeast in historic times, and the Cherokee broke off from the major group during its northern migration.

Other historians hold that, judging from linguistic and cultural data, the Tuscarora people migrated South from other Iroquoian-speaking people in the Great Lakes region in ancient times.  In the 1700s, the Tuscarora left the Southeast and &quot;returned&quot; to the New York area by 1722 because of warfare in the southern region.  The Tuscarora were admitted by the Iroquois as the Sixth Nation of their political confederacy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://college.hmco.com/history/readerscomp/naind/html/na_041100_tuscarora.htm David Landy, &quot;Tuscarora&quot;], ''Encyclopedia of North American Indians'', Cengage Learning Website, Houghton Mifflin Company, accessed January 12, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

Linguistic analysis shows a relatively large difference between Cherokee and the northern Iroquoian languages. Scholars posit a split between the groups in the distant past, perhaps 3500–3800 years ago.&lt;ref name=&quot;mooney&quot;&gt;{{Cite book| last = Mooney | first = James | authorlink = James Mooney | title = Myths of the Cherokee | origyear = 1900 | year = 1995 | publisher = [[Dover Publications]] | isbn = 0-486-28907-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Glottochronology]] studies suggest the split occurred between about 1,500 and 1,800 BCE.&lt;ref&gt;Glottochronology from: Lounsbury, Floyd (1961), and Mithun, Marianne (1981), cited in [http://www.famsi.org/research/hopkins/SouthEastUSLanguages.pdf Nicholas A. Hopkins, ''The Native Languages of the Southeastern United States''].&lt;/ref&gt;  The Cherokee have claimed the ancient settlement of ''[[Kituwa]]'' on the [[Tuckasegee River]], formerly next to and now part of [[Qualla Boundary]] (the reservation of the [[Eastern Band of Cherokee Indians]]), as the original Cherokee settlement in the Southeast.&lt;ref name=&quot;mooney&quot;/&gt;

==History==
{{Main|Cherokee history}}

===17th century: English contact===
In 1657, there was a disturbance in [[Virginia Colony]] as the ''Rechahecrians'' or ''Rickahockans'', as well as the Siouan ''[[Manahoac]]'' and ''[[Nahyssan]]'', broke through the frontier and settled near the Falls of the James, near present-day [[Richmond, Virginia]].  The following year, a combined force of English and [[Pamunkey]] drove the newcomers away.  The identity of the ''Rechahecrians'' has been much debated.  Historians noted the name closely resembled that recorded for the ''Eriechronon'' or ''Erielhonan'', commonly known as the [[Erie tribe]].  The Iroquoian people had been driven away from the southern shore of [[Lake Erie]] by the powerful [[Iroquois]] Five Nations in 1654.  The [[anthropologist]] [[Martin Smith]] theorized some remnants of the tribe migrated to Virginia after the wars ([[#refSmith1987|1986:131–32]]).  Few historians suggest this tribe was Cherokee.&lt;ref&gt;Conley, ''A Cherokee Encyclopedia'', p. 3&lt;/ref&gt;

Virginian traders developed a small-scale trading system with the Cherokee before the end of the 17th century; the earliest recorded Virginia trader to visit the Cherokee was a certain Dority, in 1690.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis Preston Summers, 1903, ''History of Southwest Virginia, 1746–1786'', p. 40&lt;/ref&gt; The Cherokee sold the traders [[Slavery among Native Americans in the United States|Indian slaves]] for use as laborers in Virginia and further north.&lt;ref name=&quot;gallay&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|last= Gallay |first= Alan |title= The Indian Slave Trade: The Rise of the English Empire in the American South 1670–1717 |year= 2002 |publisher= Yale University Press |isbn= 0-300-10193-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===18th century===
{{Further|Cherokee military history}}
The Cherokees gave sanctuary to a band of  [[Shawnee]] in the 1660s, but from 1710 to 1715 the Cherokee and Chickasaw, allied with the British, fought Shawnee, who were allied with the French, and forced them to move northward.&lt;ref&gt;Vicki Rozema, ''Footsteps of the Cherokees'' (1995), p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt; Cherokees fought with the [[Yamasee]], [[Catawba (tribe)|Catawba]], and British in late 1712 and early 1713 against the [[Tuscarora people|Tuscarora]] in the Second [[Tuscarora War]]. The Tuscarora War marked the beginning of an English-Cherokee relationship that, despite breaking down on occasion, remained strong for much of the 18th century. With the growth of the [[deerskin trade]], the Cherokee were valuable trading partners, since deer-skins from the cooler country of their mountain hunting-grounds were of a better quality than those supplied by neighboring tribes.

In January 1716, Cherokee murdered a delegation of [[Muscogee Creek]] leaders at the town of [[Tugaloo (Cherokee town)|Tugaloo]], marking their entry into the [[Yamasee War]].  It ended in 1717 with peace treaties between [[South Carolina]] and the Creek.  Hostility and sporadic raids between the Cherokee and Creek continued for decades.&lt;ref name=&quot;oatis&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Oatis |first=Steven J. |title=A Colonial Complex: South Carolina's Frontiers in the Era of the Yamasee War, 1680–1730 |location=Lincoln |publisher=University of Nebraska Press |year=2004 |isbn=0-8032-3575-5 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  These raids came to a head at the [[Battle of Taliwa]] in 1755, present-day [[Ball Ground, Georgia]], with the defeat of the Muscogee.

In 1721, the Cherokee ceded lands in [[South Carolina]]. In 1730, at [[Nikwasi]], a former Mississippian culture site, a Scots adventurer, Sir Alexander Cumming, crowned [[Moytoy of Tellico]] as &quot;Emperor&quot; of the Cherokee.  Moytoy agreed to recognize King [[George II of Great Britain]] as the Cherokee protector.  Cumming arranged to take seven prominent Cherokee, including ''[[Attakullakulla]]'',  to London, England.  The Cherokee delegation signed the [[Treaty of Whitehall]] with the British.  Moytoy's son, ''Amo-sgasite'' (Dreadful Water) attempted to succeed him as &quot;Emperor&quot; in 1741, but the Cherokees elected their own leader, Cunne Shote ([[Standing Turkey]]) of [[Chota (Cherokee town)|Chota]].&lt;ref name=ecc&gt;Brown, John P. [http://digital.library.okstate.edu/Chronicles/v016/v016p003.html &quot;Eastern Cherokee Chiefs&quot;], ''Chronicles of Oklahoma'', Vol. 16, No. 1, March 1938. Retrieved September 21, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

Political power among the Cherokee remained decentralized and towns acted autonomously.  In 1735 the Cherokee were estimated to have sixty-four towns and villages, and 6,000 fighting men.  In 1738 and 1739 [[smallpox]] epidemics broke out among the Cherokee, who had no natural immunity.  Nearly half their population died within a year.  Hundreds of other Cherokee committed suicide due to their losses and disfigurement from the disease.
[[File:Three Cherokee.jpg|thumb|After the [[Anglo-Cherokee War]], bitterness remained between the two groups. In 1765, [[Henry Timberlake]] took three of the former Cherokee adversaries to London to help cement the newly declared friendship.]]

From 1753 to 1755, battles broke out between the Cherokee and Muscogee over disputed hunting grounds in [[North Georgia]]. The Cherokee were victorious in the Battle of Taliwa.  British soldiers built forts in Cherokee country to defend against the French in the [[Seven Years War]], called the [[French and Indian War]] in North America.  These included [[Fort Loudoun (Tennessee)|Fort Loudoun]] near Chota.  In 1756 the Cherokee were allies of the British in the French and Indian War.  Serious misunderstandings arose quickly between the two allies, resulting in the 1760 [[Anglo-Cherokee War]].  King George III's [[Royal Proclamation of 1763]] forbade British settlements west of the Appalachian crest, as his government tried to afford some protection from colonial encroachment to the Cherokee and other tribes.  The ruling was difficult to enforce.&lt;ref&gt;Rozema, pp. 17–23.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1771–1772, North Carolinian settlers squatted on Cherokee lands in Tennessee, forming the [[Watauga Association]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.northcarolinahistory.org/encyclopedia/98/entry &quot;Watauga Association&quot;], ''North Carolina History Project.'' . Retrieved September 21, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Daniel Boone]] and his party tried to settle in Kentucky, but the Shawnee, [[Lenape|Delaware]], [[Mingo]], and some Cherokee attacked a scouting and forage party that included Boone’s son.  The American Indians used this territory as a hunting ground; it had hardly been inhabited for years.  The conflict sparked the beginning of what was known as [[Dunmore's War]] (1773–1774).

In 1776, allied with the Shawnee led by [[Cornstalk]], Cherokee attacked settlers in South Carolina, Georgia, Virginia, and North Carolina in the [[Chickamauga wars#The Second Cherokee War|Second Cherokee War]]. [[Overhill Cherokee]] [[Nancy Ward]], [[Dragging Canoe]]'s cousin, warned settlers of impending attacks. Provincial militias retaliated, destroying over 50 Cherokee towns. North Carolina militia in 1776 and 1780 invaded and destroyed the [[Overhill Cherokee|Overhill towns]]. In 1777 surviving Cherokee town leaders signed treaties with the states.

[[Dragging Canoe]] and his band moved near present-day [[Chattanooga, Tennessee]], where they established 11 new towns.  Chickamauga was his headquarters and his entire band became known as the Chickamauga. From here he fought a guerrilla war against settlers, the [[Chickamauga Wars (1776–1794)]].  The first Treaty of [[Tellico Blockhouse]], signed November 7, 1794, ended the Chickamauga Wars. In 1805, the Cherokee ceded their lands between the [[Cumberland River|Cumberland]] and [[Duck River (Tennessee)|Duck]] rivers (i.e. the [[Cumberland Plateau]]) to [[Tennessee]].

====Scots (and other Europeans) among the Cherokee in the 18th century====

The traders and British government agents dealing with the Southern tribes in general and the Cherokee in particular were nearly all of Scottish extraction, especially from the [[Scottish Highlands|Highlands]], though a few were Scots-Irish, English, French, even German (see [[Scottish Indian trade]]).  Many of these married women from their host people and remained after the fighting had ended, some fathering children who would later become significant leaders.&lt;ref&gt;Mooney, James. History, Myths, and Scared Formulas of the Cherokee, p. 83. (Washington: Government Printing Office, 1900).&lt;/ref&gt;

Notable traders, agents, and refugee Tories among the Cherokee included [[John Stuart (loyalist)|John Stuart]], Henry Stuart, Alexander Cameron, John McDonald, John Joseph Vann (father of [[James Vann]]), Daniel Ross (father of [[John Ross (Cherokee chief)|John Ross]]), John Walker Sr., John McLemore (father of Bob), William Buchanan, John Watts (father of [[John Watts (Cherokee chief)|John Watts Jr.]]), [[Chisholm Tavern (Knoxville)|John D. Chisholm]], John Benge (father of Bob Benge), Thomas Brown, [[John Rogers (Cherokee chief)|John Rogers]] (Welsh), John Gunter (German, founder of Gunter's Landing), James Adair (Irish), William Thorpe (English), and Peter Hildebrand (German), among many others, several attaining the status of minor chiefs and/or members of significant delegations.

In contrast, a large portion of the settlers encroaching on their territories and against whom the Cherokee (and other Indians) took most of their actions were [[Scotch-Irish American|Scots-Irish]], Irish from [[Ulster]] of Scottish descent, a group which also provided the backbone for the forces of the Revolution (a famous example of a Scots-Irishman doing the reverse is [[Simon Girty]]).  It is a historical irony that those from a group seen as rebels or &quot;Whigs&quot; back home in the Isles became Tories in the Americas while those from a group now considered one of the most &quot;Tory&quot; in regards to the United Kingdom became [[Patriot (American Revolution)|Whigs]] in the Americas.

===19th century===

====Acculturation====
The Cherokee lands between the [[Tennessee River|Tennessee]] and [[Chattahoochee River|Chattahoochee]] rivers were remote enough from white settlers to remain independent after the [[Chickamauga Wars]]. The [[deerskin trade]] was no longer feasible on their greatly reduced lands, and over the next several decades, the people of the fledgling [[Cherokee Nation (19th century)|Cherokee Nation]] began to build a new society modeled on the white Southern United States.
[[File:Major ridge.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Portrait of Major Ridge in 1834, from [[History of the Indian Tribes of North America]].]]

[[George Washington]] sought to 'civilize' Southeastern American Indians, through programs overseen by the [[Indian Agent]] [[Benjamin Hawkins]]. He encouraged the Cherokee to abandon their communal land-tenure and settle on individual farmsteads, facilitated by the destruction of many American Indian towns during the [[American Revolutionary War]]. The [[deerskin trade]] brought [[white-tailed deer]] to the brink of extinction, and as pigs and cattle were introduced, they became the principal sources of meat. The government supplied the tribes with [[spinning wheel]]s and cotton-seed, and men were taught to fence and plow the land, in contrast to their traditional division in which crop cultivation was woman's labor.  Americans instructed the women in weaving.  Eventually Hawkins helped them set up blacksmiths, gristmills and cotton plantations.

The Cherokee organized a national government under Principal Chiefs [[Little Turkey]] (1788–1801), [[Black Fox (Cherokee chief)|Black Fox]] (1801–1811), and [[Pathkiller]] (1811–1827), all former warriors of [[Dragging Canoe]]. The 'Cherokee triumvirate' of [[James Vann]] and his protégés [[Major Ridge|The Ridge]] and [[Charles R. Hicks]] advocated acculturation, formal education, and modern methods of farming. In 1801 they invited [[Moravian Church|Moravian]] missionaries from [[North Carolina]] to teach Christianity and the 'arts of civilized life.' The Moravians and later [[Congregationalist]] missionaries ran boarding schools, and a select few students were educated at the [[American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions]] school in [[Connecticut]].

In 1806 a [[Federal Road (Cherokee lands)|Federal Road]] from [[Savannah, Georgia]] to [[Knoxville, Tennessee]] was built through Cherokee land. Chief [[James Vann]] opened a tavern, inn and ferry across the [[Chattahoochee River|Chattahoochee]] and built a [[Chief Vann House Historic Site|cotton-plantation]] on a spur of the road from [[Athens, Georgia]] to [[Nashville]]. His son [[Joseph Vann|'Rich Joe' Vann]] developed the plantation to {{convert|800|acre|km2}}, cultivated by 150 slaves.  He exported cotton to England, and owned a [[steamboat]] on the [[Tennessee River]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.georgiaencyclopedia.org/nge/Article.jsp?id=h-2726&amp;hl=y |title=New Georgia Encyclopedia: Chief Vann House |publisher=Georgiaencyclopedia.org |date=September 23, 2005 |accessdate=April 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Cherokee allied with the U.S. against the nativist and pro-British [[Red Stick]] faction of the Upper Creek in the [[Creek War]] during the [[War of 1812]], and Cherokee warriors led by [[Major Ridge]] played a major role in General [[Andrew Jackson]]'s victory at the [[Battle of Horseshoe Bend (1814)|Battle of Horseshoe Bend]]. Major Ridge moved his family to Rome, Georgia, where he built a [[Chieftains (Rome, Georgia)|substantial house]], developed a large plantation and ran a ferry on the [[Oostanaula River]].  Although he never learned English, he educated his son and nephews in New England mission schools. His interpreter and protégé Chief [[John Ross (Cherokee chief)|John Ross]], the descendant of several generations of Cherokee women and Scots fur-traders, built a plantation and operated a trading firm and a ferry at Ross' Landing ([[Chattanooga, Tennessee]]). During this period, divisions arose between the acculturated elite and the great majority of Cherokee, who clung to traditional ways of life.

Around 1809 [[Sequoyah]] began developing a written form of the Cherokee language. He spoke no English, but his experiences, as a silversmith dealing regularly with white settlers and as a  warrior at Horseshoe Bend, convinced him the Cherokee needed to develop writing. In 1821, he introduced [[Cherokee syllabary]], the first written syllabic form of an American Indian language outside of [[Mesoamerican scripts|Central America]].  Initially his innovation was opposed by both Cherokee traditionalists and white missionaries who sought to encourage the use of English. When Sequoyah taught children to read and write with the syllabary, he reached the adults and, by the 1820s, the Cherokee had a higher rate of literacy than the whites around them in Georgia.

[[File:New Echota.jpg|thumb|left|Cherokee National Council building, [[New Echota]]]]

In 1819, the Cherokee began holding council meetings at New Town, at the headwaters of the [[Oostanaula River|Oostanaula]] (near present-day [[Calhoun, Georgia]]). In November 1825, New Town became the capital of the Cherokee Nation, and was renamed [[New Echota]], after the [[Overhill Cherokee]] principal town of [[Chota (Cherokee town)|Chota]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ngeorgia.com/ang/New_Echota_Historic_Site |title=New Echota Historic Site |publisher=Ngeorgia.com |date=June 5, 2007 |accessdate=April 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sequoyah's syllabary was adopted. They had developed a police force, a judicial system, and a National Committee.

In 1827, the Cherokee Nation drafted a Constitution modeled on the United States, with executive, legislative and judicial branches and a system of checks and balances. The two-tiered legislature was led by Major Ridge and his son [[John Ridge]]. Convinced the tribe's survival required English-speaking leaders who could negotiate with the U.S., the legislature appointed [[John Ross (Cherokee chief)|John Ross]] as Principal Chief. A printing press was established at New Echota by the [[Vermont]] missionary [[Samuel Worcester]] and Major Ridge's nephew [[Elias Boudinot (Cherokee)|Elias Boudinot]], who had taken the name of his [[Elias Boudinot|white benefactor]], a leader of the [[Continental Congress]] and [[New Jersey]] Congressman. They translated the Bible into [[Cherokee syllabary]].  Boudinot published the first edition of the bilingual '[[Cherokee Phoenix]],' the first American Indian newspaper, in February 1828.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.georgiaencyclopedia.org/nge/Article.jsp?id=h-611&amp;hl=y |title=New Georgia Encyclopedia: Cherokee Phoenix |publisher=Georgiaencyclopedia.org |date=August 28, 2002 |accessdate=April 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Removal era====
{{See also|Thomas Jefferson and Indian Removal}}
[[File:Tahchee.jpg|thumb|Tah-Chee (Dutch), A Cherokee Chief, 1837]]
Before the final removal to present-day Oklahoma, many Cherokees relocated to present-day [[Arkansas]], [[Missouri]] and Texas.&lt;ref&gt;Rollings (1992) pp. 187, 230–255.&lt;/ref&gt;  Between 1775 and 1786 the Cherokee, along with people of other nations such as the [[Choctaw]] and [[Chickasaw]], began voluntarily settling along the [[Arkansas River|Arkansas]] and [[Red River (Mississippi River)|Red River]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Rollings (1992) pp. 187, 236.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1802, the federal government promised to extinguish Indian titles to lands claimed by [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]] in return for Georgia's cession of the western lands that became [[Alabama]] and [[Mississippi]]. To convince the Cherokee to move voluntarily in 1815, the US government established a Cherokee Reservation in Arkansas.&lt;ref&gt;Logan, Charles Russell. [http://www.arkansaspreservation.org/pdf/publications/Cherokee_Removal.pdf &quot;The Promised Land: The Cherokees, Arkansas, and Removal, 1794–1839.&quot;] ''Arkansas Historic Preservation Program.'' 1997 . Retrieved September 21, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The reservation boundaries extended from north of the [[Arkansas River]] to the southern bank of the [[White River (Arkansas)|White River]]. [[The Bowl (Cherokee chief)|Di'wali]] (The Bowl), [[Sequoyah]], Spring Frog and Tatsi (Dutch) and their bands settled there. These Cherokees became known as &quot;Old settlers.&quot;

The Cherokee eventually migrated as far north as the Missouri [[Bootheel]] by 1816.  They lived interspersed among the [[Delaware Nation|Delawares]] and [[Shawnee]]s of that area.&lt;ref&gt;Doublass (1912) pp. 40–2&lt;/ref&gt;  The Cherokee in [[Missouri Territory]] increased rapidly in population, from 1,000 to 6,000 over the next year (1816–1817), according to reports by Governor [[William Clark (explorer)|William Clark]].&lt;ref&gt;Rollings (1992) p. 235.&lt;/ref&gt;  Increased conflicts with the [[Osage Nation]] led to the [[Battle of Claremore Mound]] and the eventual establishment of [[Fort Smith, Arkansas|Fort Smith]] between Cherokee and Osage communities.&lt;ref&gt;Rollings (1992) pp. 239–40.&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[Treaty of St. Louis]] (1825), the Osage were made to &quot;cede and relinquish to the United States, all their right, title, interest, and claim, to lands lying within the State of Missouri and Territory of Arkansas...&quot; to make room for the Cherokee and the ''Mashcoux'', [[Muscogee Creek]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Rollings (1992) pp. 254–5, Doublass (1912) p. 44.&lt;/ref&gt; As late as the winter of 1838, Cherokee and Creek living in the Missouri and Arkansas areas petitioned the War Department to remove the Osage from the area.&lt;ref&gt;Rollings (1992) pp. 280–1&lt;/ref&gt;

A group of Cherokee traditionalists led by [[The Bowl (Cherokee chief)|''Di'wali'']] moved to [[Spanish Texas]] in 1819. Settling near [[Nacogdoches, Texas|Nacogdoches]], they were welcomed by Mexican authorities as potential allies against Anglo-American colonists. The [[Texas Cherokees]] were mostly neutral during the [[Texas War of Independence]].  In 1836, they signed a treaty with Texas President [[Sam Houston]], an adopted member of the Cherokee tribe. His successor [[Mirabeau Lamar]] sent militia to evict them in 1839.

=====Trail of Tears=====
{{Main|Trail of Tears|Cherokee Removal}}
[[File:Chief John Ross.jpg|left|thumb|upright|Chief [[John Ross (Cherokee chief)|John Ross]], ca. 1840]]

During the first decades of the 19th century, Georgia focused on removing the Cherokee's neighbors, the [[Muscogee (Creek)|Lower Creek]]. The Georgia Governor [[George Troup]] and his cousin [[William McIntosh]], chief of the Lower Creek, signed the [[Treaty of Indian Springs]] (1825), ceding the last [[Muscogee (Creek)]] lands claimed by Georgia.  The state's northwestern border reached the [[Chattahoochee River|Chattahoochee]], the border of the Cherokee Nation. In 1829, gold was discovered at [[Dahlonega, Georgia|Dahlonega]], on Cherokee land claimed by Georgia. The [[Georgia Gold Rush]] was the first in U.S. history, and state officials demanded that the federal government expel the Cherokee. When [[Andrew Jackson]] was inaugurated as President in 1829, Georgia gained a strong ally in [[Washington, D.C.|Washington]]. In 1830 Congress passed the [[Indian Removal Act]], authorizing the forcible relocation of American Indians east of the [[Mississippi River|Mississippi]] to a new [[Indian Territory]].

[[Andrew Jackson]] said the removal policy was an effort to prevent the Cherokee from facing extinction as a people, which he considered the fate that &quot;the [[Mohegan]], the [[Narragansett tribe|Narragansett]], and the [[Lenape|Delaware]]&quot; had suffered.&lt;ref&gt;Wishart, p. 120&lt;/ref&gt; But, there is ample evidence that the Cherokee were adapting modern farming techniques.  A modern analysis shows that the area was in general in a state of economic surplus and could have accommodated both the Cherokee and new settlers.&lt;ref&gt;Wishart 1995.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Cherokee brought their grievances to a US judicial review that set a precedent in [[Indian Country]]. John Ross traveled to Washington, D.C., and won support from [[National Republican Party]] leaders [[Henry Clay]] and [[Daniel Webster]]. [[Samuel Worcester]] campaigned on behalf of the Cherokee in New England, where their cause was taken up by [[Ralph Waldo Emerson]] (see [[Emerson's letter to Martin Van Buren|Emerson's 1838 letter to Martin Van Buren]]). In June 1830, a delegation led by Chief Ross defended Cherokee rights before the U.S. Supreme Court in ''[[Cherokee Nation v. Georgia]]''.

In 1831 Georgia militia arrested [[Samuel Worcester]] for residing on Indian lands without a state permit, imprisoning him in [[Milledgeville, Georgia|Milledgeville]].  In ''[[Worcester v. Georgia]]'' (1832), the US [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]] [[Chief Justice]] [[John Marshall]] ruled that American Indian nations were &quot;distinct, independent political communities retaining their original natural rights,&quot; and entitled to federal protection from the actions of state governments that infringed on their [[sovereignty]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.georgiaencyclopedia.org/nge/Article.jsp?id=h-2720 |title=New Georgia Encyclopedia: &quot;Worcester v. Georgia (1832)&quot; |publisher=Georgiaencyclopedia.org |date=April 27, 2004 |accessdate=April 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Worcester v. Georgia'' is considered one of the most important dicta in law dealing with Native Americans.

Jackson ignored the Supreme Court's ruling, as he needed to conciliate Southern sectionalism during the era of the [[Nullification Crisis]]. His landslide reelection in 1832 emboldened calls for Cherokee removal. Georgia sold Cherokee lands to its citizens in a [[Georgia Land Lottery|Land Lottery]], and the state militia occupied [[New Echota]]. The Cherokee National Council, led by John Ross, fled to [[Red Clay State Park|Red Clay]], a remote valley north of Georgia's land claim. Ross had the support of Cherokee traditionalists, who could not imagine removal from their ancestral lands.
[[File:Cherokee beadwork sampler 1840 ohs.jpg|thumb|Cherokee [[beadwork]] sampler, made at [[Dwight Presbyterian Mission|Dwight Mission]], Indian Territory, 19th century, collection of the [[Oklahoma History Center]].]]
A small group known as the &quot;Ridge Party&quot; or the &quot;Treaty Party&quot; saw relocation as inevitable and believed the Cherokee Nation needed to make the best deal to preserve their rights in Indian Territory. Led by [[Major Ridge]], [[John Ridge]] and [[Elias Boudinot (Cherokee)|Elias Boudinot]], they represented the Cherokee elite, whose homes, plantations and businesses were confiscated, or under threat of being taken by white squatters with Georgia land-titles. With capital to acquire new lands, they were more inclined to accept relocation. On December 29, 1835, the &quot;Ridge Party&quot; signed the [[Treaty of New Echota]], stipulating terms and conditions for the removal of the Cherokee Nation. In return for their lands, the Cherokee were promised a large tract in the [[Indian Territory]], $5 million, and $300,000 for improvements on their new lands.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ourgeorgiahistory.com/documents/treaty_of_new_echota.html |title=Treaty of New Echota, Dec. 29, 1835 (Cherokee – United States) |publisher=Ourgeorgiahistory.com |accessdate=April 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

John Ross gathered over 15,000 signatures for a petition to the U.S. Senate, insisting that the treaty was invalid because it did not have the support of the majority of the Cherokee people.  The Senate passed the Treaty of New Echota by a one-vote margin.  It was enacted into law in May 1836.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ngeorgia.com/history/cherokeehistory7.html |title=Cherokee in Georgia: Treaty of New Echota |publisher=Ngeorgia.com |date=June 5, 2007 |accessdate=April 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Two years later President [[Martin Van Buren]] ordered 7,000 Federal troops and state militia under General [[Winfield Scott]] into Cherokee lands to evict the tribe. Over 16,000 Cherokee were forcibly relocated westward to [[Indian Territory]] in 1838–1839, a migration known as the [[Trail of Tears]] or in Cherokee {{lang|chr|ᏅᎾ ᏓᎤᎳ ᏨᏱ}} or {{lang|chr|''Nvna Daula Tsvyi''}} (''The Trail Where They Cried''), although it is described by another word {{lang|chr|''Tlo-va-sa''}} (''The Removal''). Marched over {{convert|800|mi|km}} across [[Tennessee]], [[Kentucky]], [[Illinois]], [[Missouri]] and [[Arkansas]], the people suffered from disease, exposure and starvation, and as many as 4,000 died.&lt;ref&gt;Georgia Historic Marker, New Echota, 1958&lt;/ref&gt; As some Cherokees were slaveholders, they took [[slavery|enslaved]] African Americans with them west of the Mississippi. Intermarried European Americans and [[missionaries]] also walked the Trail of Tears. Ross preserved a vestige of independence by negotiating for the Cherokee to conduct their own removal under U.S. supervision.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.goodreads.com/author/show/225917.Alex_W_Bealer|title=Books by Alex W. Bealer|publisher=goodreads.com, 1972 and 1996|accessdate=March 27, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In keeping with the tribe's &quot;blood law&quot; that prescribed the death penalty for Cherokee who sold lands, Ross's son arranged the murder of the leaders of the &quot;Treaty Party&quot;. On June 22, 1839, a party of twenty-five Ross supporters assassinated Major Ridge, John Ridge and Elias Boudinot.  The party included Daniel Colston, John Vann, Archibald, James and Joseph Spear. Boudinot's brother [[Stand Watie]] fought and survived that day, escaping to [[Arkansas]].

In 1827, [[Sequoyah]] had led a delegation of Old Settlers to Washington, D.C. to negotiate for the exchange of Arkansas land for land in Indian Territory. After the Trail of Tears, he helped mediate divisions between the Old Settlers and the rival factions of the more recent arrivals. In 1839, as President of the Western Cherokee, Sequoyah signed an Act of Union with John Ross that reunited the two groups of the Cherokee Nation.

=====Eastern Band=====
[[File:Cól-lee, a Band Chief.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Cól-lee, a Band Chief, painted by [[George Catlin]], 1834]]

The [[Oconaluftee (Great Smoky Mountains)|Oconaluftee]] Cherokee of the [[Great Smoky Mountains]] were the most conservative and isolated from European-American settlements. They rejected the reforms of the Cherokee Nation.  When the Cherokee government ceded all territory east of the [[Little Tennessee River]] to [[North Carolina]] in 1819, they withdrew from the Nation.&lt;ref&gt;Theda Purdue, ''Native Carolinians: The Indians of North Carolina,'' pg. 40&lt;/ref&gt; [[William Holland Thomas]], a white store owner and state legislator from [[Jackson County, North Carolina]], helped over 600 Cherokee from [[Cherokee, North Carolina|Qualla Town]] obtain North Carolina citizenship, which exempted them from forced removal. Over 400 Cherokee either hid from Federal troops in the remote Snowbird Mountains, under the leadership of [[Tsali]] ({{lang|chr|ᏣᎵ}}),&lt;ref name=Tsali&gt;[http://www.cherokee-nc.com/history.php?Name=Tsali &quot;Tsali.&quot;] ''History and culture of the Cherokee (North Carolina Indians).'' (March 10, 2007)&lt;/ref&gt; or belonged to the former Valley Towns area around the [[Cheoah River]] who negotiated with the state government to stay in North Carolina. An additional 400 Cherokee stayed on reserves in Southeast Tennessee, North Georgia, and Northeast Alabama, as citizens of their respective states.  They were mostly mixed-race and Cherokee women married to white men. Together, these groups were the ancestors of the federally recognized [[Eastern Band of Cherokee Indians]], and some of the state-recognized tribes in surrounding states.

====Civil War====
[[Image:Cherokee Confederates Reunion.gif|right|325px|thumb|Cherokee confederates reunion in [[New Orleans]], 1903.]]

{{Further|Cherokee in the American Civil War|Native Americans in the Civil War}}
The [[American Civil War]] was devastating for both East and Western Cherokee. The Eastern Band, aided by [[William Holland Thomas|William Thomas]], became the Thomas Legion of Cherokee Indians and Highlanders, fighting for the Confederacy in the [[American Civil War]].&lt;ref name=Will_Thomas&gt;[http://www.cherokee-nc.com/history.php?Name=Will%20Thomas &quot;Will Thomas.&quot;] ''History and culture of the Cherokee (North Carolina Indians).'' (March 10, 2007)&lt;/ref&gt; Cherokee in Indian Territory divided into Union and Confederate factions, with most supporting the Confederacy.

[[Stand Watie]], the leader of the Ridge Party, raised a regiment for [[Confederate Army|Confederate]] service in 1861. [[John Ross (Cherokee chief)|John Ross]], who had reluctantly agreed to ally with the Confederacy, was captured by Federal troops in 1862. He lived in self-imposed exile in [[Philadelphia]], supporting the Union. In Indian Territory, the national council of those who supported the Union voted to abolish slavery in the Cherokee Nation in 1863, but they were not the majority slaveholders and the vote had little effect on those supporting the Confederacy.

Watie was elected Principal Chief of the pro-Confederacy majority. A master of hit-and-run cavalry tactics, Watie fought those Cherokee loyal to John Ross and Federal troops in [[Indian Territory]] and [[Arkansas]], capturing Union supply trains and [[steamboats]], and saving a Confederate army by covering their retreat after the [[Battle of Pea Ridge]] in March 1862. He became a Brigadier General of the [[Confederate States]]; the only other American Indian to hold the rank in the American Civil War was [[Ely S. Parker]] with the Union Army.  On June 25, 1865, two months after [[Robert E. Lee]] surrendered at [[Appomattox Court House National Historical Park|Appomattox]], Stand Watie became the last Confederate General to stand down.

====Reconstruction and late 19th century====
[[File:Group of Cherokee, Yankton, and Sisseton 1909.jpg|thumb|left|William Penn (Cherokee), His Shield (Yanktonai), Levi Big Eagle (Yanktonai), Bear Ghost (Yanktonai) and Black Moustache (Sisseton).]]
After the Civil War, the US government required the Cherokee Nation to sign a new treaty, because of its alliance with the Confederacy. The US required the 1866 Treaty to provide for the [[emancipation]] of all Cherokee slaves, and full citizenship to all Cherokee [[freedmen]] and all free African Americans who chose to continue to reside within tribal lands, so that they &quot;shall have all the rights of native Cherokees.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://digital.library.okstate.edu/kappler/VOL2/treaties/che0942.htm &quot;Treaty with the Cherokee, 1866.&quot;] ''Oklahoma Historical Society: Indian Affairs: Laws and Treaties. Vol. 2, Treaties.'' (retrieved January 10, 2010)&lt;/ref&gt; Both before and after the Civil War, some Cherokee intermarried or had relationships with African Americans, just as they had with whites. Many Cherokee Freedmen have been active politically within the tribe.

The US government also acquired [[easement]] rights to the western part of the territory, which became the [[Oklahoma Territory]], for the construction of railroads. Development and settlers followed the railroads. By the late 19th century, the government believed that Native Americans would be better off if each family owned its own land. The [[Dawes Act]] of 1887 provided for the breakup of commonly held tribal land into individual household allotments. Native Americans were registered on the Dawes Rolls and allotted land from the common reserve. The US government counted the remainder of tribal land as &quot;surplus&quot; and sold it to non-Cherokee individuals.

The [[Curtis Act of 1898]] dismantled tribal governments, courts, schools, and other civic institutions. For Indian Territory, this meant abolition of the Cherokee courts and governmental systems. This was seen as necessary before the Oklahoma and Indian territories could be admitted as a combined state. In 1905, the [[Five Civilized Tribes]] of the [[Indian Territory]] proposed the creation of the [[State of Sequoyah]] as one to be exclusively Native American, but failed to gain support in Washington, D.C.. In 1907, the [[Oklahoma Territory|Oklahoma]] and [[Indian Territory|Indian Territories]] entered the union as the state of [[Oklahoma]].
[[File:CherokeeOTSA.PNG|thumb|300px|Map of present-day Cherokee Nation Tribal Jurisdiction Area (dark blue)]]

By the late 19th century, the Eastern Band of Cherokee were laboring under the constraints of a [[Racial segregation|segregated]] society. In the aftermath of [[Reconstruction era of the United States|Reconstruction]], conservative white Democrats regained power in North Carolina and other southern states. They proceeded to effectively [[Disfranchisement after Reconstruction era (United States)|disfranchise]] all blacks and many poor whites by new constitutions and laws related to voter registration and elections. They passed [[Jim Crow laws]] that divided society into &quot;white&quot; and &quot;colored&quot;, mostly to control freedmen. Cherokee and other Native Americans were classified on the colored side and suffered the same racial segregation and disfranchisement as former slaves. They also often lost their historical documentation for identification as Indians, when the Southern states classified them as colored.  Blacks and Native Americans would not have their constitutional rights as US citizens enforced until after the [[Civil Rights Movement]] secured passage of civil rights legislation in the mid-1960s, and the federal government began to monitor voter registration and elections, as well as other programs.

==Culture==

===Marriage===
Before the 19th century, [[polygamy]] was common among the Cherokee, especially by elite men.&lt;ref name=&quot;Perdue 1999, p. 176&quot;&gt;Perdue (1999), p. 176&lt;/ref&gt; The [[matrilineal]] culture meant that women controlled property, such as their dwellings, and their children were considered born into their mother's [[clan]], where they gained hereditary status.  Advancement to leadership positions were generally subject to approval by the women elders.  In addition, the society was [[matrifocal]]; customarily, a married couple lived with or near the woman's family, so she could be aided by her female relatives.  Her oldest brother was a more important mentor to her boys than was their father, who belonged to another clan. Traditionally, couples, particularly women, can divorce freely.&lt;ref&gt;Perdue (1999), pp. 44, 57–8&lt;/ref&gt;

Intermarriage with European Americans had occurred before the 19th century, generally between male [[merchant|traders]] and high-status Cherokee women whose families were seeking joint alliances. Some of the mixed-race sons of such high-status women became leading chiefs among the Cherokee; they gained hereditary leadership from their mothers' clans and used what they learned of American culture to benefit their people.

It was unusual for a Cherokee man to marry a European-American woman.  The children of such a union were disadvantaged, as they would not belong to the nation.  They would be born outside the clans and traditionally were not considered Cherokee citizens. This is because of the matrilineal aspect of Cherokee culture.&lt;ref name=&quot;Perdue 1999, p. 176&quot;/&gt; As the Cherokee began to adopt some elements of European-American culture in the early 19th century, they sent elite young men, such as [[John Ridge]] and [[Elias Boudinot (Cherokee)|Elias Boudinot]] to American schools for education. After Ridge had married a European-American woman from Connecticut and Boudinot was engaged to another, the Cherokee Council in 1825 passed a law making children of such unions full citizens of the tribe, as if their mothers were Cherokee. This was a way to protect the families of men expected to be leaders of the tribe.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Yarbough |first=Fay |title=Legislating Women’s Sexuality: Cherokee Marriage Laws |journal=Journal of Social History |volume=38 |year=2004 |issue=2 |pages=385–406 [p. 388] |doi=10.1353/jsh.2004.0144 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the late nineteenth century, the US government put new restrictions on marriage between a Cherokee and non-Cherokee, although it was still relatively common. A European-American man could legally marry a Cherokee woman by petitioning the federal court, after gaining approval of ten of her blood relatives.  Once married, the man had status as an &quot;Intermarried White,&quot; a member of the Cherokee tribe with restricted rights; for instance, he could not hold any tribal office. He also remained a citizen of and under the laws of the United States. [[Common law marriage]]s were more popular. Such &quot;Intermarried Whites&quot; were listed in a separate category on the registers of the [[Dawes Rolls]], prepared for allotment of plots of land to individual households of members of the tribe, in the early twentieth-century federal policy for [[cultural assimilation|assimilation]] of the Native Americans.

===Cultural institutions===
The Qualla Arts and Crafts Mutual, Inc., of Cherokee, North Carolina is the oldest continuing Native American art co-operative. They were founded in 1940 to provide a venue for traditional Eastern Band Cherokee artists.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.quallaartsandcrafts.org/history.php Qualla History.] . Retrieved September 15, 09.&lt;/ref&gt; The Museum of the Cherokee Indian, also in Cherokee, displays permanent and changing exhibits, houses archives and collections important to Cherokee history, and sponsors cultural groups, such as the Warriors of the AniKituhwa dance group.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cherokeemuseum.org/ The Museum of the Cherokee Indian.] . Retrieved September 15, 09.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, the [[Eastern Band of Cherokee Indians]] entered into a partnership with [[Southwestern Community College (North Carolina)|Southwestern Community College]] and [[Western Carolina University]] to create the [[Oconaluftee Institute for Cultural Arts]] (OICA), to emphasize native art and culture in traditional fine arts education, thus preserving traditional art forms and encouraging exploration of contemporary ideas. Located in Cherokee, OICA currently offers an associate's degree program.&lt;ref name=&quot;SCC&quot;&gt;[http://www.southwesterncc.edu/news/06-jul-dec/EBCI-cultural-arts-inst.htm &quot;Announcement of the founding of the Oconaluftee Institute for Cultural Arts in Cherokee&quot;], Southwestern Community College (retrieved Nov 24, 2010)&lt;/ref&gt; In August 2010, OICA acquired a letterpress and had the [[Cherokee syllabary]] recast to begin printing one-of-a-kind fine art books and prints in the [[Cherokee language]].&lt;ref name=&quot;letterpress&quot;&gt;[http://www.nc-cherokee.com/theonefeather/2010/08/13/new-letterpress-arrives-at-oica/ &quot;New Letterpress Arrives at OICA&quot;], ''The One Feather'' (retrieved Nov 24, 2010)&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Cherokee Heritage Center]], of [[Park Hill, Oklahoma]] hosts a reproduction of an ancient Cherokee Village, Adams Rural Village (including 19th-century buildings), Nofire Farms, and the Cherokee Family Research Center for genealogy.&lt;ref name=CHC&gt;{{cite web| title = Cherokee Heritage Center | url = http://www.cherokeeheritage.org | accessdate =March 10, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Cherokee Heritage Center also houses the Cherokee National Archives. Both the [[Cherokee Nation]] (of Oklahoma) and the [[United Keetoowah Band of Cherokee]], as well as other tribes, contribute funding to the CHC.

==Language and writing system==
{{Further|Cherokee language|Cherokee syllabary}}
[[File:Sequoyah.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Sequoyah]], the inventor of the Cherokee syllabary]]

The Cherokee speak a Southern [[Iroquoian languages|Iroquoian]] language, which is [[polysynthetic language|polysynthetic]] and is written in a [[syllabary]] invented by [[Sequoyah]] ({{lang|chr|ᏍᏏᏉᏯ}}).&lt;ref&gt;Morand, Ann, Kevin Smith, Daniel C. Swan, and Sarah Erwin. ''Treasures of Gilcrease: Selections from the Permanent Collection.'' Tulsa, OK: Gilcrease Museum,2003. ISBN 0-9725657-1-X&lt;/ref&gt; For years, many people wrote transliterated Cherokee or used poorly intercompatible fonts to type out the syllabary. However, since the fairly recent addition of the Cherokee syllables to [[Unicode]], the Cherokee language is experiencing a renaissance in its use on the Internet.

[[File:Sequoyah Arranged Syllabary .png|thumb|left|Sequoyah's syllabary in the order that he originally arranged the characters.]]

Because of the polysynthetic nature of the Cherokee language, new and descriptive words in Cherokee are easily constructed to reflect or express modern concepts. Examples include ''ditiyohihi'' ({{lang|chr|ᏗᏘᏲᎯᎯ}}), which means &quot;he argues repeatedly and on purpose with a purpose,&quot; meaning &quot;attorney.&quot; Another example is ''didaniyisgi'' ({{lang|chr|ᏗᏓᏂᏱᏍᎩ}}) which means &quot;the final catcher&quot; or &quot;he catches them finally and conclusively,&quot; meaning &quot;policeman.&quot;

Many words, however, have been borrowed from the English language, such as ''gasoline'', which in Cherokee is {{lang|chr|''ga-so-li-ne''}} ({{lang|chr|ᎦᏐᎵᏁ}}). Many other words were borrowed from the languages of tribes who settled in Oklahoma in the early 20th century. One example relates to a town in Oklahoma named &quot;Nowata&quot;. The word {{lang|chr|''nowata''}} is a [[Delaware languages|Delaware Indian]] word for &quot;welcome&quot; (more precisely the Delaware word is {{lang|del|''nu-wi-ta''}} which can mean &quot;welcome&quot; or &quot;friend&quot; in the Delaware Language).   The white settlers of the area used the name &quot;nowata&quot; for the township, and local Cherokees, being unaware the word had its origins in the Delaware Language, called the town ''Amadikanigvnagvna'' ({{lang|chr|ᎠᎹᏗᎧᏂᎬᎾᎬᎾ}})  which means &quot;the water is all gone from here&quot;, i.e. &quot;no water&quot;.

Other examples of borrowed words are {{lang|chr|''kawi''}} ({{lang|chr|ᎧᏫ}}) for ''coffee'' and {{lang|chr|''watsi''}} ({{lang|chr|ᏩᏥ}}) for ''watch'' (which led to {{lang|chr|''utana watsi''}} ({{lang|chr|ᎤᏔᎾ ᏩᏥ}}) or &quot;big watch&quot; for ''clock'').

The following table is an example of Cherokee text and its translation:

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
| style=&quot;background:#fff;&quot;| ᏣᎳᎩ: ᏂᎦᏓ ᎠᏂᏴᏫ ᏂᎨᎫᏓᎸᎾ ᎠᎴ ᎤᏂᏠᏱ ᎤᎾᏕᎿ ᏚᏳᎧᏛ ᎨᏒᎢ. ᎨᏥᏁᎳ ᎤᎾᏓᏅᏖᏗ ᎠᎴ ᎤᏃᏟᏍᏗ ᎠᎴ ᏌᏊ ᎨᏒ ᏧᏂᎸᏫᏍᏓᏁᏗ ᎠᎾᏟᏅᏢ ᎠᏓᏅᏙ ᎬᏗ.&lt;ref name=&quot;Omniglot&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.omniglot.com/writing/cherokee.htm |title=Cherokee syllabary |accessdate=May 14, 2009 |date=1998–2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| style=&quot;background:#ddd;&quot; | {{lang|chr|[[Cherokee language|Tsalagi]]: ''Nigada aniyvwi nigeguda'lvna ale unihloyi unadehna duyukdv gesv'i. Gejinela unadanvtehdi ale unohlisdi ale sagwu gesv junilvwisdanedi anahldinvdlv adanvdo gvhdi.''}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Omniglot&quot;/&gt;
|-
| ''All human beings are born free and equal in dignity and rights. They are endowed with reason and conscience and should act towards one another in a spirit of brotherhood.'' ''(Article 1 of the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]])''&lt;ref name=&quot;Omniglot&quot;/&gt;
|}

==Treaties and government==

===Treaties===
{{see also|Historic treaties of the Cherokee}}

The Cherokee have participated in at least thirty-six treaties in the past three hundred years.

===Government===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
| 1794 || Establishment of the Cherokee National Council and officers over the whole nation
|-
| 1808 || Establishment of the Cherokee Lighthorse Guard, a national police force
|-
| 1809 || Establishment of the National Committee
|-
| 1810 || End of separate regional councils and abolition of blood vengeance
|-
| 1820 || Establishment of courts in eight districts to handle civil disputes
|-
| 1822 || Cherokee Supreme Court established
|-
| 1823 || National Committee given power to review acts of the National Council
|-
| 1827 || Constitution of the Cherokee Nation East
|-
| 1828 || Constitution of the Cherokee Nation West
|-
| 1832 || Suspension of elections in the Cherokee Nation East
|-
| 1839 || Constitution of the reunited Cherokee Nation
|-
| 1868 || Constitution of the Eastern Band of Cherokee Indians
|-
| 1888 || Charter of Incorporation issued by the State of North Carolina to the Eastern Band
|-
| 1950 || Constitution and federal charter of the United Keetoowah Band of Cherokee Indians
|-
| 1975 || Constitution of the Cherokee Nation of Oklahoma
|-
| 1999 || Constitution of the Cherokee Nation drafted&lt;ref&gt;This constitution was approved by Cherokee Nation voters in 2003 but was not approved by the BIA. The Cherokee Nation then amended their 1975 constitution to not require BIA approval. The 1999 constitution has been ratified but the Cherokee Nation Supreme Court is currently deciding what year the 1999 constitution officially went into effect. [http://www.cherokee.org/Docs/TribalGovernment/Executive/CCC/2003_CN_CONSTITUTION.pdf Constitution of the Cherokee Nation.] (pdf file). ''Cherokee Nation.'' . Retrieved March 5, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

After being ravaged by smallpox, and pressed by increasingly violent land-hungry settlers, the Cherokee adopted a European-American [[Representative democracy]] form of government in an effort to retain their lands. They established a governmental system modeled on that of the United States, with an elected principal chief, senate, and house of representatives. On April 10, 1810 the seven Cherokee clans met and began the abolition of blood vengeance by giving the sacred duty to the new Cherokee National government. Clans formally relinquished judicial responsibilities by the 1820s when the Cherokee Supreme Court was established. In 1825, the National Council extended citizenship to the children of Cherokee men married to white women. These ideas were largely incorporated into the 1827 Cherokee constitution.&lt;ref&gt;Perdue, p. 564.&lt;/ref&gt; The constitution stated that &quot;No person who is of negro or [[mulatto]] {{sic}} parentage, either by the father or mother side, shall be eligible to hold any office of profit, honor or trust under this Government,&quot; with an exception for, &quot;negroes and descendants of white and Indian men by negro women who may have been set free.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Perdue, pp. 564–565.&lt;/ref&gt; This definition to limit rights of multiracial descendants, may have been more widely held among the elite than the general population.&lt;ref&gt;Perdue, p. 566.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Modern Cherokee tribes==

===Cherokee Nation===
[[File:Cherokeenationalflag.png|left|200px|thumb|Flag of the Cherokee Nation]]
{{Main|Cherokee Nation}}
[[File:Cherokee National Capitol.jpg|thumb|[[Cherokee National Capitol|Cherokee Nation Historic Courthouse]] in Tahlequah, Oklahoma.]]
[[File:Seminary Hall.jpg|thumb|The [[Cherokee Female Seminary]] was built in 1889 by the Oklahoma Cherokees.]]
During 1898–1906 the federal government dissolved the former Cherokee Nation, to make way for the incorporation of [[Indian Territory]] into the new state of [[Oklahoma]]. From 1906 to 1975, structure and function of the tribal government were not clearly defined. In 1975 the tribe drafted a constitution, which they ratified on June 26, 1976,&lt;ref&gt;[http://thorpe.ou.edu/constitution/cherokee/index.html Constitution of the Cherokee Nation of Oklahoma.] ''University of Oklahoma Law Center.'' (retrieved January 16, 2010)&lt;/ref&gt; and the tribe received federal recognition. In 1999, the CNO changed or added several provisions to its constitution, among them the designation of the tribe to be &quot;Cherokee Nation,&quot; dropping &quot;of Oklahoma.&quot; According to a statement by BIA head Larry Echohawk the Cherokee Nation is not the historical Cherokee tribe but instead a &quot;successor in interest.&quot;  The attorney of the Cherokee Nation has stated that they intend to appeal this decision.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Associated |first=The |url=http://www.indiancountrytoday.com/archive/50644002.html |title=Cherokee Nation likely to appeal BIA decision &amp;#124; Indian Country Today &amp;#124; Archive |publisher=Indian Country Today |date=July 13, 2009 |accessdate=April 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The modern Cherokee Nation, in recent times, has experienced an almost unprecedented expansion in economic growth, equality, and prosperity for its citizens. The Cherokee Nation, under the leadership of Principal Chief [[Chad &quot;Corntassel&quot; Smith|Chad Smith]], has significant business, corporate, real estate, and agricultural interests, including numerous highly profitable casino operations. The CN controls Cherokee Nation Entertainment, Cherokee Nation Industries, and Cherokee Nation Businesses. CNI is a very large defense contractor that creates thousands of jobs in eastern Oklahoma for Cherokee citizens.

The CN has constructed health clinics throughout Oklahoma, contributed to community development programs, built roads and bridges, constructed learning facilities and universities for its citizens, instilled the practice of [[Gadugi]] and self-reliance in its citizens, revitalized language immersion programs for its children and youth, and is a powerful and positive economic and political force in Eastern Oklahoma.

The CN hosts the [[Cherokee National Holiday]] on Labor Day weekend each year, and 80,000 to 90,000 Cherokee Citizens travel to [[Tahlequah, Oklahoma]], for the festivities. It also publishes the [[Cherokee Phoenix]], the tribal newspaper, published in both English and the Sequoyah syllabary. The Cherokee Nation council appropriates money for historic foundations concerned with the preservation of Cherokee Culture.

The Cherokee Nation also supports the Cherokee Nation Film Festivals in Tahlequah, Oklahoma and participates in the [[Sundance Film Festival]] in [[Park City, Utah]].

===Eastern Band of Cherokee Indians===
[[File:Eastern Band Cherokee Flag.svg|left|200px|thumb|Flag of the Eastern Band Cherokee]]
{{Main|Eastern Band of Cherokee Indians}}
The Eastern Band of the Cherokee Indians in North Carolina, led by Chief Michell Hicks,
hosts over a million visitors a year to cultural attractions of the {{convert|100|sqmi|km2|sing=on}} sovereign nation. The reservation, the &quot;[[Qualla Boundary]]&quot;, has a population of over 8,000 Cherokee, primarily direct descendants of Indians who managed to avoid “[[The Trail of Tears]]”.

Attractions include the Oconaluftee Indian Village, Museum of the Cherokee Indian, and the country’s oldest and foremost Native American crafts cooperative. The outdoor drama ''[[Unto These Hills]]'', which debuted in 1950, recently broke record attendance sales. Together with Harrah’s Cherokee Casino and Hotel, Cherokee Indian Hospital and Cherokee Boys Club, the tribe generated $78 million dollars in the local economy in 2005.

===United Keetoowah Band of Cherokee Indians===
[[File:UKBflag (bordered).png|left|200px|thumb|Flag of the United Keetoowah Band of Cherokee Indians]]
{{Main|United Keetoowah Band of Cherokee Indians}}
The United Keetoowah Band of Cherokee Indians formed their government under the [[Indian Reorganization Act]] of 1934 and gained federal recognition in 1946. Enrollment into the tribe is limited to people with a quarter or more of Cherokee blood. Many members of the UKB are descended from Old Settlers – Cherokees who moved to Arkansas and Indian Territory before the Trail of Tears.&lt;ref&gt;Leeds, George R. [http://digital.library.okstate.edu/encyclopedia/entries/U/UN006.html United Keetoowah Band.] ''Oklahoma Historical Society's Encyclopedia of Oklahoma History and Culture.'' (retrieved October 5, 2009)&lt;/ref&gt; Of the 12,000 people enrolled in the tribe, 11,000 live in Oklahoma. Their chief is George G. Wickliffe. The UKB operate a tribal casino, bingo hall, smokeshop, fuel outlets, truck stop, and gallery that showcases art and crafts made by tribal members. The tribe also issues their own tribal vehicle tags.&lt;ref&gt;Oklahoma Office of Indian Affairs. [http://www.ok.gov/oiac/Publications/index.html Oklahoma Indian Nations Pocket Pictorial Directory.] 2008:36&lt;/ref&gt;

===Relations among the three federally recognized Cherokee tribes===
The Cherokee Nation participates in numerous joint programs with the Eastern Band of Cherokee Indians. It also participates in cultural exchange programs and joint Tribal Council meetings involving councilors from both Cherokee Tribes. These are held to address issues affecting all of the Cherokee People.

The administrations of the United Keetoowah Band of Cherokee Indians and the Cherokee Nation have a somewhat adversarial relationship. The Eastern Band of Cherokee Indians interacts with the Cherokee Nation in a unified spirit of ''[[Gadugi]]''.{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}}

The United Keetoowah Band tribal council unanimously passed a resolution to approach the Cherokee Nation for a joint council meeting between the two Nations, as a means of &quot;offering the olive branch&quot;, in the words of the UKB Council. While a date was set for the meeting between members of the Cherokee Nation Council and UKB representative, Chief Smith vetoed the meeting.{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}}

==Contemporary settlement==
[[File:Lange-MigrantMother02.jpg|thumb|[[Dorothea Lange]]'s famous photograph, ''Migrant Mother'', that epitomized the [[Great Depression]], features [[Florence Owens Thompson]] (Cherokee)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://archive.newtimesslo.com/archive/2004-01-21/archives/cov_stories_2002/cov_01172002.html |title=New Times - San Luis Obispo - Cover Story - Photographic license |publisher=Archive.newtimesslo.com |date= |accessdate=2012-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; and her three children]]
Cherokees are most concentrated in Oklahoma and North Carolina, but some reside in the [[US West Coast]], due to economic migrations caused by the [[Dust Bowl]] during the Great Depression, job availability during the Second World War, and the [[Indian Relocation Act of 1956|Federal Indian Relocation program]] during the 1950s–1960s. Cherokees constitute over 2% of population of three largely rural communities in California–[[Covelo, California|Covelo]], [[Hayfork, California|Hayfork]] and [[San Miguel, Contra Costa County, California|San Miguel]], one town in [[Oregon]] and one town in [[Arizona]]).{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}} Destinations for Cherokee diaspora included multi-ethnic/racial urban centers of California (i.e. the [[Greater Los Angeles area|Greater Los Angeles]] and [[San Francisco Bay Area|SF Bay area]]s), and they usually lived in farming communities, by military bases and other Indian reservations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.epodunk.com/ancestry/Cherokee.html |title=Cherokee Ancestry Search – Cherokee Genealogy by City |publisher=ePodunk.com |accessdate=April 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''See also the [[Albuquerque Cherokee Nation Township (Cherokee Nation)]]'' about the Cherokee community of [[Albuquerque, NM]].

==Membership controversies==

===Tribal recognition and membership===
{{Main|Cherokee Heritage Groups}}
The three Cherokees tribes have differing requirements for enrollment. The Cherokee Nation determines enrollment by lineal descent from Cherokees listed on the [[Dawes Rolls]] and has no minimum [[blood quantum]] requirement.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cherokee.org/home.aspx?section=services&amp;service=Registration&amp;ID=8sRG9ZCF7PE= Cherokee Nation Registration].&lt;/ref&gt; Currently, descendents of the Dawes Cherokee Freedman rolls are members of the tribe, pending court decisions. CN has numerous members who also have African-American, Latino, Asian, European-American, and other ancestry. The Eastern Band of Cherokee Indians requires a minimum one-sixteenth Cherokee blood quantum (genealogical descent, equivalent to one great-great-grandparent) and an ancestor on the Baker Roll. The United Keetoowah Band of Cherokee Indians requires a minimum one-quarter Keetoowah Cherokee blood quantum (equivalent to one grandparent), and the UKB does not allow members that have relinquished their membership to re-enroll in the UKB.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.keetoowahcherokee.org/enrollment.html Enrollment.] ''United Keetoowah Band of Cherokees.'' (retrieved October 5, 2009)&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2000 the U.S. census reported 875,276 people self-identified as Cherokee Indian;&lt;ref&gt;{{PDFlink|[http://www.census.gov/prod/2006pubs/censr-28.pdf ''We the People: American Indians and Alaska Natives in the United State'']}}, Census 2000 Special Reports, [[United States Census Bureau]]&lt;/ref&gt; however, only approximately 316,049 people are enrolled in the federally recognized Cherokee tribes.

Over 200 groups claim to be Cherokee nations, tribes, or bands.&lt;ref&gt;Glenn, Eddie. [http://www.tahlequahdailypress.com/cnhi/tahlequahdailypress/features/local_story_006134311.html?keyword=secondarystory &quot;A League of Nations?&quot;] ''Tahlequah Daily Press.'' January 6, 2006 (retrieved October 5, 2009)&lt;/ref&gt; Cherokee Nation spokesman Mike Miller has suggested that some groups, which he calls [[Cherokee Heritage Groups]], are encouraged.&lt;ref&gt;Glenn 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Others, however, are controversial for their attempts to gain economically through their claims to be Cherokee. The three federally recognized groups assert themselves as the only groups having the legal right to present themselves as Cherokee Indian Tribes and only their enrolled members as Cherokee.&lt;ref&gt;Official Statement Cherokee Nation 2000, Pierpoint 2000.&lt;/ref&gt;

One exception to this may be the [[Texas Cherokees]]. Prior to 1975, they were considered a part of the Cherokee Nation, as reflected in briefs filed before the Indian Claims Commission. At one time W.W. Keeler served not only as Principal Chief of the Cherokee Nation, but at the same time held the position as Chairman of the Texas Cherokee and Associated Bands (TCAB) Executive Committee.

Following the adoption of the Cherokee constitution in 1976, TCAB descendants whose ancestors had remained a part of the physical Mount Tabor Community in [[Rusk County, Texas]] were excluded from citizenship. Their ancestors did not appear on the Final Rolls of the Five Civilized Tribes, registered under the Dawes Commission. However, most if not all TCAB descendants did have an ancestor listed on the Guion-Miller or [[Old settler (Cherokee)|Old settler]] rolls.

While most Mount Tabor residents returned to the Cherokee Nation following the death of John Ross in 1866, today there is a sizable group that is well documented but outside that body. It is not actively seeking a status clarification. They do have treaty rights going back to the [[Treaty of Bird’s Fort]]. From the end of the Civil War until 1975, they were associated with the Cherokee Nation. The TCAB formed as a political organization in 1871 led by [[William Penn Adair]] and Clement Neely Vann. Descendants of the Texas Cherokees and the Mount Tabor Community joined together to try to gain redress from treaty violations, stemming from the Treaty of Bowles Village in 1836. Today, most Mount Tabor descendants are in fact members of the Cherokee Nation. Only some 800 are stuck in limbo without status as Cherokees. Many of them still reside in Rusk and Smith counties of east Texas.

Other remnant populations continue to exist throughout the Southeast United States and individually in the states surrounding Oklahoma. Many of these people trace descent from persons enumerated on official rolls such as the Guion-Miller, Drennan, Mullay and Henderson Rolls, among others. Other descendants trace their heritage through the treaties of 1817 and 1819 with the federal government which gave individual allotments to Cherokees.  State recognized Tribes require irrefutable genealogical proof that applicants are of Cherokee descent. Current enrollment guidelines of the Cherokee Nation of Oklahoma do not allow these descendants admission despite the fact that many current Cherokee citizens have provable relatives ineligible to enroll. Such facts were pointed out by Cherokee citizens of CNO during the Constitutional Convention held to ratify a new governing document. The document that was eventually ratified by a small portion of the electorate has yet to be approved by the Federalgovernment.&lt;ref&gt;
* [http://www.tngennet.org/cherokee_by_blood/aoc.htm Act of Congress Roll, 1854]
* [http://www.cherokee.org/Government/254/Page/default.aspx (Pre-convention – 1999) Oral and Written Testimonies]
* [http://www.tngennet.org/cherokee_by_blood/census.htm Cherokee Census Rolls, a follow-up]
* [http://www.tngennet.org/cherokee_by_blood/chapman.htm Chapman Roll Eastern Cherokees, 1851]
* [http://digital.library.okstate.edu/kappler/Vol2/treaties/che0140.htm#mn11 Treaty with the Cherokee, 1817]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cherokee Freedmen===
{{Main|Cherokee Freedmen Controversy}}
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:CNSeal.jpg|thumb|upright|left|The seal of the Cherokee Nation.]] --&gt;

The Cherokee freedmen, descendants of African American slaves owned by citizens of the Cherokee Nation during the [[Antebellum Period]], were first guaranteed Cherokee citizenship under a treaty with the United States in 1866. This was in the wake of the [[American Civil War]], when the US emancipated slaves and passed US constitutional amendments granting freedmen citizenship in the United States.

In 1988, the federal court in the Freedmen case of ''[[Nero v. Cherokee Nation]]'' held that Cherokees could decide citizenship requirements and exclude freedmen. On March 7, 2006, the Cherokee Nation Judicial Appeal Tribunal ruled that the Cherokee Freedmen were eligible for Cherokee citizenship. This ruling proved controversial; while the Cherokee Freedman had historically been recorded as &quot;citizens&quot; of the Cherokee Nation at least since 1866 and the later [[Dawes Commission]] Land Rolls, the ruling &quot;did not limit membership to people possessing Cherokee blood&quot;.&lt;ref name=Freedman-Decision&gt;{{cite web |title=Freedman Decision |url=http://www.cherokee.org/docs/news/Freedman-Decision.pdf |format=PDF |accessdate=March 10, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This ruling was consistent with the 1975 Constitution of the Cherokee Nation of Oklahoma, in its acceptance of the Cherokee Freedmen on the basis of historical citizenship, rather than documented blood relation.

On March 3, 2007 a constitutional amendment was passed by a Cherokee vote limiting citizenship to Cherokees on the Dawes Rolls for those listed as Cherokee by blood, Shawnee and Delaware.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cherokeecourts.com/Portals/5/44%20-%20Motion%20for%20Summary%20Judgment%20and%20Brief%20in%20Support.pdf Cherokee Constitutional Amendment March 3, 2007].&lt;/ref&gt; The Cherokee Freedmen had 90 days to appeal this amendment vote which disenfranchised them from Cherokee citizenship and file appeal within the Cherokee Nation Tribal Council, which is currently pending in ''Nash, et al. v. Cherokee Nation Registrar''. On May 14, 2007, the Cherokee Freedmen were reinstated as citizens of the Cherokee Nation by the Cherokee Nation Tribal Courts through a temporary order and temporary injunction until the court reached its final decision.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url= http://www.cherokeecourts.com/Portal/5/44%20-%20Motion%20for%20Summary%20Judgment%20and%20Brief%20in%20Support.pdf | format = PDF | title = Nash, et al v. Cherokee Nation Registrar}}&lt;/ref&gt;  On January 14, 2011, the tribal district court ruled that the 2007 constitutional amendment was invalid because it conflicted with the 1866 treaty guaranteeing the Freedmen's rights.&lt;ref&gt;Gavin Off, [http://www.tulsaworld.com/news/article.aspx?subjectid=14&amp;articleid=20110114_14_0_AChero292984 &quot;Judge grants Cherokee citizenship to non-Indian freedmen&quot;], ''[[Tulsa World]]'', January 14, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Cherokee in history==
This includes only Cherokee documented in history. Contemporary notable Cherokee people are listed in the articles for the appropriate tribe. For self-identified people of Cherokee heritage, see [[List of Self-identified people of Cherokee ancestry]].
&lt;!-- Do not add contemporary people to this list --&gt;
* [[William Penn Adair]] (1830–1880), Cherokee senator and diplomat, Confederate colonel.
* ''[[Attakullakulla]]'' (ca. 1708 – ca. 1777), diplomat to Britain, headman of Chota, chief
* [[Bob Benge]] (ca. 1762–1794), warrior of the Lower Cherokee during the Chickamauga Wars
* [[Elias Boudinot (Cherokee)|Elias Boudinot]] (''Galagina'') (1802–1839), statesman, orator, and editor, founded  first Cherokee newspaper, ''Cherokee Phoenix''
* [[Ned Christie]] (1852–1892), statesman, Cherokee Nation senator, infamous outlaw&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nps.gov/fosm/historyculture/case-of-ned-christie.htm &quot;The Case of Ned Christie&quot;], Fort Smith Historic Site, National Park Service. Retrieved February 3, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Admiral [[Joseph J. Clark]] (1893–1971), United States Navy, highest ranking Native American in the US military, awarded the [[Navy Cross]].
* [[Doublehead]], ''Taltsuska'' (d. 1807), a war leader during the Chicamauga Wars, led the Lower Cherokee, signed land deals with US
* [[Dragging Canoe]], ''Tsiyugunsini'' (1738–1792), general the militant Cherokee during the Chickamauga Wars, principal chief of the Chicamauga or Lower Cherokee
* [[Franklin Gritts]], Cherokee artist taught at [[Haskell Indian Nations University|Haskell Institute]] and served on the USS Franklin
* [[Charles R. Hicks]] (d. 1827), veteran of the [[Red Stick War]], Second Principal Chief to Pathkiller in early 17th century, ''de facto'' Principal Chief from 1813–1827
* ''[[Junaluska]]'' (ca. 1775–1868), veteran of the Creek War, who saved President Andrew Jackson's life
* ''[[Oconostota]]'', ''Aganstata'' (Beloved Man) (ca. 1710–1783), war chief during the Anglo-Cherokee War,
* ''[[Ostenaco]]'', ''Ustanakwa'' (ca. 1703–1780), war chief, diplomat to Britain, founded the town of Ultiwa
* [[Major Ridge]] ''Ganundalegi'' or &quot;Pathkiller&quot; (ca.1771–1839), veteran of the Chickamauga Wars and the Red Stick War, signer of the Treaty of New Echota
* [[John Ridge]], ''Skatlelohski'' (1792–1839), son of Major Ridge, statesman, New Echota Treaty signer
* [[John Rollin Ridge]], ''Cheesquatalawny'', or &quot;Yellow Bird&quot; (1827–1867), grandson of Major Ridge, first Native American novelist
* [[Clem Rogers|Clement V. Rogers]] (1839–1911), US Senator, judge, cattleman, member of the Oklahoma Constitutional Convention
* [[Will Rogers]], entertainer, roper, journalist, and author&lt;ref name=Carter&gt;{{cite web| title = Father and Cherokee Tradition Molded Will Rogers | author = Carter JH | url = http://www.willrogers.com/stories/stories/molded/Molded.html | accessdate =March 10, 2007 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20061110060059/http://www.willrogers.com/stories/stories/molded/Molded.html |archivedate = November 10, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[John Ross (Cherokee chief)|John Ross]], ''Guwisguwi'' (1790–1866), veteran of the Red Stick War, Principal Chief in the east, during Removal, and in the west
* ''[[Sequoyah]]'' (ca. 1767–1843), inventor of the Cherokee syllabary&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.georgiaencyclopedia.org/nge/Article.jsp?id=h-618&amp;sug=y  &quot;Sequoyah&quot;], ''New Georgia Encyclopedia''. Retrieved January 3, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Nimrod Jarrett Smith]], ''Tsaladihi'' (1837–1893), Principal Chief of the Eastern Band, Civil War veteran
* [[Redbird Smith]] (1850–1918), traditionalist, political activist, and chief of the Nighthawk Keetoowah Society
* [[William Holland Thomas]], ''Wil' Usdi ''(1805–1893), non-Native but adopted into tribe, founding Principal Chief of the Eastern Band of Cherokee Indians, commanding officer of Thomas Legion of Cherokee Indians and Highlanders
* [[James Vann]] (ca. 1765–1809), Scottish-Cherokee, highly successful businessman and veteran of the Chickamauga Wars
* [[Nancy Ward]], ''[[Nanye-hi]]'' (ca. 1736–1822/4), (Beloved Woman), diplomat
* [[Stand Watie]], ''Degataga'' (1806–1871), signer of the Treaty of New Echota, last Confederate general to cease hostilities in the American Civil War as commanding officer of the First Indian Brigade of the Army of Trans-Mississippi

==See also==
{{Portal|Indigenous peoples of North America}}
* [[Black drink]]
* [[Black Indians in the United States]]
* [[:chr:wikipedia|Cherokee wikipedia]]
* [[One-drop rule]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
* Doublass, Robert Sydney.  &quot;History of Southeast Missouri&quot;, 1992, pp.&amp;nbsp;32–45
* Evans, E. Raymond.  &quot;Notable Persons in Cherokee History: Dragging Canoe&quot;. ''Journal of Cherokee Studies, Vol. 2, No. 2'', pp.&amp;nbsp;176–189.  (Cherokee: Museum of the Cherokee Indian, 1977).
* Finger, John R. ''Cherokee Americans: The Eastern Band of Cherokees in the 20th century''. Knoxville: University of Tennessee Press, 1991. ISBN 0-8032-6879-3.
* Glenn, Eddie. [http://www.tahlequahdailypress.com/cnhi/tahlequahdailypress/features/local_story_006134311.html?keyword=secondarystory &quot;A league of nations?&quot;] ''Tahlequah Daily Press''. January 6, 2006 (Accessed May 24, 2007)
* Halliburton, R., jr.: ''Red over Black – Black Slavery among the Cherokee Indians'', Greenwood Press, Westport, Connecticut 1977 ISBN 0-8371-9034-7
* Irwin, L, &quot;Cherokee Healing: Myth, Dreams, and Medicine.&quot; ''American Indian Quarterly''. Vol. 16, 2, 1992, p.&amp;nbsp;237.
*[[William G. McLoughlin|McLoughlin, William G.]] ''Cherokee Renascence in the New Republic''. (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1992).
* [[James Mooney|Mooney, James]]. &quot;Myths of the Cherokees.&quot; Bureau of American Ethnology, Nineteenth Annual Report, 1900, Part I. pp.&amp;nbsp;1–576. Washington: Smithsonian Institution.
* Perdue, Theda. &quot;Clan and Court: Another Look at the Early Cherokee Republic.&quot; ''American Indian Quarterly''. Vol. 24, 4, 2000, p.&amp;nbsp;562.
* Perdue, Theda. ''Cherokee women: gender and culture change, 1700–1835.'' Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1999. ISBN 978-0-8032-8760-0.
* Pierpoint, Mary. [http://www.indiancountrytoday.com/archive/28197994.html &quot;Unrecognized Cherokee claims cause problems for nation.&quot;] ''Indian Country Today''. August 16, 2000 (Accessed May 16, 2007).
* Rollings, Willard H. &quot;The Osage: An Ethnohistorical Study of Hegemony on the Prairie-Plains.&quot; (University of Missouri Press, 1992)
* Sturtevant, William C., general editor and Raymond D. Fogelson, volume editor. ''Handbook of North American Indians: Southeast.'' Volume 14. Washington DC: Smithsonian Institution, 2004. ISBN 0-16-072300-0.
* Wishart, David M. &quot;Evidence of Surplus Production in the Cherokee Nation Prior to Removal.&quot; ''Journal of Economic History''. Vol. 55, 1, 1995, p.&amp;nbsp;120.

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
{{InterWiki|code=chr}}
* [http://www.cherokee.org Cherokee Nation], official site
* [http://www.nc-cherokee.com/ Eastern Band of Cherokee Indians], official site
* [http://www.unitedkeetoowahband.org/ United Keetoowah Band of Cherokee Indians], official site
* [http://www.cherokeemuseum.org/ Museum of the Cherokee Indian], Cherokee, NC
* [http://www.cherokeeheritage.org/ Cherokee Heritage Center], Park Hill, OK
* [http://siris-collections.si.edu/search/results.jsp?q=Cherokee Smithsonian Institution – Cherokee photos and documents]
* [http://www.cherokeeregistry/ Historical Sound Files of Cherokee Stomp Dance]
* [http://www.cherokeeregistry.com/ Cherokee Heritage Documentation Center – Genealogy and Culture]
* [http://digital.library.okstate.edu/encyclopedia/entries/C/CH014.html Cherokee article], Oklahoma Historical Society Encyclopedia of Oklahoma History and Culture
* {{1911}}
* [http://wiki.familysearch.org/en/Cherokee_Indians Cherokee Indians] in FamilySearch Research Wiki for genealogists

{{Cherokee}}
{{Five Civilized Tribes}}

[[Category:Cherokee tribe| ]]
[[Category:Native American tribes in North Carolina]]
[[Category:Native American tribes in Tennessee]]
[[Category:Native American tribes in Oklahoma]]
[[Category:Native American tribes in Georgia (U.S. state)]]
[[Category:Cherokee Nation (19th century)]]

[[am:ጻላጊ]]
[[ar:شيروكي (قبيلة)]]
[[ast:Cheroqui]]
[[bg:Чероки]]
[[ca:Cherokees]]
[[cs:Čerokíové]]
[[cy:Cherokee]]
[[da:Cherokee]]
[[de:Cherokee]]
[[nv:Chééwokii dinéʼiʼ]]
[[es:Cheroqui]]
[[eo:Ĉerokoj]]
[[eu:Txeroki]]
[[fa:چروکی]]
[[fo:Cherokee-indiánarnir]]
[[fr:Cherokees]]
[[ko:체로키 족]]
[[hr:Cherokee Indijanci]]
[[it:Cherokee]]
[[he:צ'רוקי]]
[[lt:Čerokiai]]
[[hu:Cserokik]]
[[mk:Чироки]]
[[mr:चेरोकी]]
[[nl:Cherokee (volk)]]
[[ja:チェロキー]]
[[no:Cherokee]]
[[nds:Cherokee (Volk)]]
[[pl:Czirokezi]]
[[pt:Cherokees]]
[[ro:Cherokee]]
[[qu:Chiruki]]
[[ru:Чероки]]
[[simple:Cherokee]]
[[sr:Čiroki indijanci]]
[[sh:Cherokee]]
[[fi:Cherokeet]]
[[sv:Cherokeser]]
[[ta:செரோக்கீ]]
[[th:เชอโรคี]]
[[chr:ᏣᎳᎩ]]
[[chy:Sena'kaneo'o]]
[[tr:Çerokiler]]
[[uk:Черокі]]
[[vi:Cherokee]]
[[zh:切羅基人]]</text>
      <sha1>8tbtnu83uju6dcanwqfanix0vvponf6</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
