<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Communist state</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>215623</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521110683</id>
      <parentid>520698819</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T21:12:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>FriedrickMILBarbarossa</username>
        <id>9758360</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>+ iw sr</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22874">{{pp-semi-vandalism|small=yes}}

{{Communism sidebar |expanded=all}}
[[File:Communist countries 1979-1983.png|300px|thumb|right|Map of countries that declared themselves to be socialist states under the Marxist–Leninist or Maoist definition - that is to say, &quot;Communist states&quot; - between 1979 and 1983. This period marked the greatest territorial extent of Communist states.]]
{{History of Communist Nations}}
{{Forms of government}}
A '''Communist state''', in popular usage, is a [[State (polity)|state]] with a [[form of government]] characterized by [[Single-party state|single-party rule]] or [[Dominant-party system|dominant-party rule]] by a [[communist party]] or [[socialist party]] and a professed allegiance to a [[Leninist]] or [[Marxism–Leninism|Marxist–Leninist]] ideology as the guiding principle of the state. Theoretically, &quot;communist state&quot; is a ''[[contradictio in terminis]]'' as a communist society as defined by both [[Marxism|Marxists]] and [[anarcho-communism|anarcho-communists]] is in principle stateless and would not be bound by a single country.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;N.I. Bukharin and E. Preobrazhensky in ''The ABC of Communism'' write &quot;In a communist society there will be no classes. But if there will be no classes, this implies that in communist society there will likewise be no State.&quot; See also ''State and Revolution'' by Lenin, chapter 5.4 &quot;The Higher Phase of Communist Society&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; From this perspective, '''Marxist–Leninist state''' is more appropriate and applicable. 

However, these states [[Constitution|constitutionally]] designate themselves as [[socialist state]]s. They do this not to disguise the fact that the ruling party is communist, but rather because they do not consider themselves to be a communist society at present. Instead, they constitutionally identify themselves as [[socialist state]]s or workers' states. The primary goal of these states, which also explains their official name, is to guide and lead their respective countries in the process of constructing [[socialism]], ultimately leading to communism.

Historically, a &quot;communist state&quot; referred to a system where public ownership and centralized planning of all or most means of production by the [[Communist party]]-run state is deemed necessary to further the interests of the [[working class]]; today, a communist state can also, for instance, refer to contemporary China and Vietnam, where a Communist Party-run state exists alongside a [[mixed economy]]. According to Marxist–Leninists, the state is a tool in the hands of the [[ruling class]], which in a [[socialism|socialist society]] is the working class. According to Leninists, a workers' state is a [[dictatorship of the proletariat|state of the working class]].

Communist states may have several legal [[Political party|political parties]], but the communist party is usually granted a special or dominant role in government,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The first defining feature of a Communist system is the monopoly of power of the Communist Party&quot; : [[Archie Brown]], ''The Rise and Fall of communism'', Vintage Books, 2009, page 105&lt;/ref&gt; often by statute or under the constitution. Consequently, the institutions of the state and of the communist party become intimately entwined, such as in the development of parallel institutions.

In the 20th century, most communist states adopted [[Planned economy|planned economies]]. However, there were exceptions: The [[Soviet Union]] during the 1920s and late 1980s and [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]] after [[World War II]] allowed limited markets and a degree of worker self-management, while [[China]], [[Vietnam]] and [[Laos]] introduced far-reaching market reforms after the 1980s.  In the 21st century, China and Vietnam have allowed a [[mixed economy]] to develop.

The fundamental concepts of communist states often diverge from the original socio-economic ideologies from which they develop. As a result, many adherents of these ideologies often oppose the political systems commonly associated with these states. For example, dissenting communists such as [[Trotskyist]]s were often opposed to the communist states of the 20th century, claiming either that they had nothing to do with &quot;real&quot; communism or that the ideology of such states had reached a point of irrevocable [[political corruption|corruption]].

== Types of communist states ==
While historically almost all claim lineage to [[Marxism|Marxist]] thought, there are many varieties of communist states, with indigenous adaptions.

These Communist states often do not claim to have achieved socialism or communism in their countries; rather, they claim to be ''building'' and working toward the establishment of socialism in their countries. For example, the preamble to the [[Socialist Republic of Vietnam]]'s constitution states that Vietnam only entered a transition stage between capitalism and socialism after the country was re-unified under the Communist party in 1976,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vietnamembassy-usa.org/learn_about_vietnam/politics/constitution/ VN Embassy - Constitution of 1992] Full Text. From the Preamble: &quot;On 2 July 1976, the National Assembly of reunified Vietnam decided to change the country's name to the Socialist Republic of Vietnam; the country entered a period of transition to socialism, strove for national construction, and unyieldingly defended its frontiers while fulfilling its internationalist duty.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; and the 1992 Constitution of the [[Cuba|Republic of Cuba]] states that the role of the Communist Party is to &quot;guide the common effort toward the goals and construction of socialism&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cubanet.org/ref/dis/const_92_e.htm Cubanet - Constitution of the Republic of Cuba, 1992] Full Text. From Article 5: &quot;The Communist Party of Cuba, a follower of Martí’s ideas and of Marxism-Leninism, and the organized vanguard of the Cuban nation, is the highest leading force of society and of the state, which organizes and guides the common effort toward the goals of the construction of socialism and the progress toward a communist society,&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

Alternative names that states adhering to an officially communist ideology may assign themselves is [[socialist state]] or socialist republic. This is because these nations have not yet transcended [[capitalism]] or [[state capitalism]] and progressed toward [[pure communism]] in the Marxist sense, which can only be achieved once capitalism exhausts itself of its historical role.

== State institutions ==
Marxist-Leninist states share similar institutions, which are organized on the premise that the communist party is a [[Vanguard party|vanguard of the proletariat]] and represents the long-term interests of the people. The doctrine of [[democratic centralism]], which was developed by [[Vladimir Lenin]] as a set of principles to be used in the internal affairs of the communist party, is extended to society at large.&lt;ref name=&quot;Furtak, Robert K. 1986, pp. 8-9&quot;&gt;Furtak, Robert K. ''The political systems of the socialist states'', St. Martin's Press, New York, 1986, pp. 8-9.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to democratic centralism, all leaders must be elected by the people and all proposals must be debated openly, but, once a decision has been reached, all people have a duty to obey that decision and all debate should end. When used within a political party, democratic centralism is meant to prevent factionalism and splits. When applied to an entire state, democratic centralism creates a [[Single-party state|one-party system]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Furtak, Robert K. 1986, pp. 8-9&quot;/&gt;

The constitutions of most socialist states describe their political system as a form of democracy.&lt;ref&gt;Furtak, Robert K. ''The political systems of the socialist states'', St. Martin's Press, New York, 1986, p. 12.&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, they recognize the sovereignty of the people as embodied in a series of [[Representative democracy|representative]] parliamentary institutions. Such states do not have a [[separation of powers]]; instead, they have one national legislative body (such as the [[Supreme Soviet]] in the Soviet Union) which is considered the highest organ of state power and which is legally superior to the executive and judicial branches of government.&lt;ref&gt;Furtak, Robert K. ''The political systems of the socialist states'', St. Martin's Press, New York, 1987, p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt;

Such national legislative politics in communist states often have a similar structure to the parliaments that exist in liberal republics, with two significant differences: first, the deputies elected to these national legislative bodies are not expected to represent the interests of any particular constituency, but the long-term interests of the people as a whole; second, against Marx's advice, the legislative bodies of communist states are not in permanent session. Rather, they convene once or several times per year in sessions which usually last only a few days.&lt;ref&gt;Furtak, Robert K. ''The political systems of the socialist states'', St. Martin's Press, New York, 1986, p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt;

When the national legislative body is not in session, its powers are transferred to a smaller council (often called a [[presidium]]) which combines legislative and executive power, and, in some communist states (such as the [[Soviet Union]] before 1990), acts as a collective [[head of state]]. In some systems, the presidium is composed of important communist party members who vote the resolutions of the communist party into law.

=== State social institutions ===
Another feature of communist states is the existence of numerous state-sponsored social organizations ([[trade union]]s, youth organizations, women's organizations, associations of teachers, writers, journalists and other professionals, consumer cooperatives, sports clubs, etc.) which are integrated into the political system.

In some communist states,{{Which?|date=March 2009}} representatives of these organizations are guaranteed a certain number of seats on the national legislative bodies. In socialist states, the social organizations are expected to promote social unity and cohesion, to serve as a link between the government and society, and to provide a forum for recruitment of new communist party members.&lt;ref&gt;Furtak, Robert K. ''The political systems of the socialist states'', St. Martin's Press, New York, 1986, p. 16-17.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Political power ===
Historically, the political organization of many communist states has been dominated by a single-party monopoly. Some communist regimes, such as [[North Korea]], [[East Germany]] or the [[Czechoslovak Socialist Republic]] have or had more than one political party, but all minor parties are or were required to follow the leadership of the communist party. In socialist states, the government may not tolerate criticism of policies that have already been implemented in the past or are being implemented in the present.&lt;ref&gt;Furtak, Robert K. ''The political systems of the socialist states'', St. Martin's Press, New York, 1986, p. 18-19.&lt;/ref&gt;

Nevertheless, communist parties have won elections and governed in the context of [[Multi-party system|multi-party democracies]], without seeking to establish a one-party state. Examples include [[San Marino]], Republic of [[Nicaragua]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/1987/01/15/world/nicaragua-s-communist-party-shifts-to-opposition.html | work=The New York Times | first=Stephen | last=Kinzer | title=NICARAGUA'S COMMUNIST PARTY SHIFTS TO OPPOSITION | date=15 January 1987}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Moldova]], [[Nepal]] (presently), [[Cyprus]] (presently),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/mobile/europe/country_profiles/1016541.stm | work=BBC News | title=Country profile: Cyprus | date=3 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[India]]n states of [[Kerala]], [[West Bengal]] and [[Tripura]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://cyberjournalist.info/kerala/sumas.php4?year=2006 Kerala Assembly Elections-- 2006]&lt;/ref&gt; However, for the purposes of this article, these entities do not fall under the definition of communist state.

== Objections to use of term ==
No state led by a communist party describes itself as a &quot;communist state.&quot; In [[Marxism]], [[communism]] is the final phase of history at which time the state would have &quot;withered away&quot;&lt;ref&gt;The oft-cited quote is borrowed from a variation of the English translation of [[Anti-Dühring]] 1878 by [[Friedrich Engels]], [http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1877/anti-duhring/ch24.htm Part III: Socialism] - «The proletariat seizes political power and turns the means of production in the first instance into state property. But, in doing this, it abolishes itself as proletariat, abolishes all class distinctions and class antagonisms, abolishes also the state as state. Society thus far, based upon class antagonisms, had need of the state, that is, of an organisation of the particular class, which was pro tempore the exploiting class, for the maintenance of its external conditions of production, and, therefore, especially, for the purpose of forcibly keeping the exploited classes in the condition of oppression corresponding with the given mode of production (slavery, serfdom, wage-labour). The state was the official representative of society as a whole; the gathering of it together into a visible embodiment. But it was this only in so far as it was the state of that class which itself represented, for the time being, society as a whole: in ancient times, the state of slave-owning citizens; in the Middle Ages, the feudal lords; in our own time, the bourgeoisie. When at last it becomes the real representative of the whole of society, it renders itself unnecessary. As soon as there is no longer any social class to be held in subjection; as soon as class rule, and the individual struggle for existence based upon our present anarchy in production, with the collisions and excesses arising from these, are removed, nothing more remains to be repressed, and a special repressive force, a state, is no longer necessary. The first act by virtue of which the state really constitutes itself the representative of the whole of society—the taking possession of the means of production in the name of society—this is, at the same time, its last independent act as a state. State interference in social relations becomes, in one domain after another, superfluous, and then dies out of itself; the government of persons is replaced by the administration of things, and by the conduct of processes of production. The state is not &quot;abolished&quot;. ''It dies out''.»&lt;/ref&gt; and therefore &quot;communist state&quot; is a contradiction in terms under premises of this theory. Current states are either in the capitalist or socialist phase of history{{spaced ndash}}making the term &quot;[[socialist state]]&quot; preferable to many communists and Marxist theorists.&lt;ref&gt;[[Alain Badiou|Badiou, Alain]]. ''The Communist Hypothesis'', transl. by [[David Macey]] and Steve Corcoran; (New York: Verso, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

== Criticism ==
{{Main|Criticisms of communist party rule}}

=== From the liberal or conservative viewpoint ===
Totalitarian communist regimes have been criticized for their [[Single-party state|one-party]] dictatorships, [[totalitarianism|totalitarian]] control of the economy and society and repression of civil liberties by the [[Council of Europe]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://assembly.coe.int/Mainf.asp?link=/Documents/AdoptedText/ta06/Eres1481.htm Council of Europe Parliamentary Assembly, Resolution 1481 (2006) Need for international condemnation of crimes of totalitarian communist regimes]&lt;/ref&gt; economic focus on heavy industry at the expense of consumer goods, sometimes resulting in shortages of vital products or even famine,&lt;ref&gt;''The Economics of Soviet Agriculture'' by Leonard E. Hubbard, p. 117-18&lt;/ref&gt; and militarism and propaganda to cover up the mistakes of the government .&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Birth of the Propaganda State: Soviet Methods of Mass Mobilization, 1917-1929 |last=Kenez |first=Peter |publisher=Cambridge University Press |year=1985 |isbn=0-521-31398-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== From the communist and socialist viewpoints ===
Within the socialist and communist movements themselves, there are a number of criticisms of using the term &quot;communist states&quot;. Left communists,&lt;ref&gt;[http://en.internationalism.org/node/609 STATE CAPITALISM | International Communist Current]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Anarchist]]s and some [[Trotskyists]]&lt;ref&gt;[[Tony Cliff]], for example. See: [http://www.marxists.org/archive/cliff/ Tony Cliff's Internet Archive]&lt;/ref&gt; contend that the so-called &quot;communist&quot; or &quot;socialist&quot; states or &quot;people's states&quot; were actually state capitalist and thus cannot be called &quot;socialist&quot;.

== Modern period ==
[[File:Communist States.svg|thumb|right|300px|A map showing the current states (as of 2012) having a single-party political system and ruled by self-declared Marxist-Leninist governments. They are [[China]], [[Cuba]], [[Laos]],  and [[Vietnam]].]]
===List of current communist states ===

The following countries are one-party states in which the institutions of the ruling communist party and the state have become intertwined; hence they fall under the definition of ''Socialist states'' that officially support ''communism''. They are generally adherents of Marxism-Leninism in particular and as such represent a particular ideology that many communists may not share. They are listed here together with the year of their founding and their respective ruling parties:&lt;ref&gt;[[Central Intelligence Agency]] [[World Factbook]]: ''[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/fields/2128.html?countryName=Korea,%20North&amp;countryCode=kn&amp;regionCode=eas&amp;#kn FIELD LISTING :: GOVERNMENT TYPE]''&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; width=100%
! width = 150px |Country
! width = 125px | Since
! width=100px | Party
! width=95px | Leader
|-
| {{flag|People's Republic of China|name=People's Republic of China}}
| 1 October 1949
| [[Communist Party of China]]
| [[Hu Jintao]]
|-
| {{flag|Cuba|name=Republic of Cuba}}
| 1 May 1961
| [[Communist Party of Cuba]]
| [[Raúl Castro]]
|-
| {{flag|Laos|name=Lao People's Democratic Republic}}
| 2 December 1975
| [[Lao People's Revolutionary Party]]
| [[Choummaly Sayasone]]
|-
| {{flag|Vietnam|name=Socialist Republic of Vietnam}}
| 2 July 1976
| [[Communist Party of Vietnam]]
| Triumvirate:
*[[Nguyen Phu Trong|Nguyễn Phú Trọng]]
*[[Nguyen Tan Dung|Nguyễn Tấn Dũng]]
*[[Truong Tan Sang|Trương Tấn Sang]]
|}

===Disputed or mixed governments ===
* {{flag|North Korea|name=Democratic People's Republic of Korea}} (since 1948); the [[Workers' Party of Korea]] has removed and disavowed all Marxist-Leninist and communist references in the constitution and government, a Party congress has not been held since 1980, hereditary rule has become an institution, and officially follows [[Juche]].

=== Democratic states with current governing communist parties in power ===
These are multi-party states that currently have communist parties leading the government. Such states are not considered to be communist ''states'' as the countries themselves allow for multiple parties, and do not provide a constitutional role for their communist parties.
* {{flag|Cyprus}} (since February 2008); [[Progressive Party of Working People]]
* {{flag|Nepal}} (since April 2008); [[Unified Communist Party of Nepal (Maoist)]]; In [[Nepal]], the ruling Communist parties participate in a multi-party coalition government, an alliance of 22 parties that holds 350 seats in the 601-member constituent assembly.

===Communist parties as part of a ruling coalition===
There are also some parties that participate as junior partners in ruling coalitions, as listed below.

* {{flag|Bangladesh}}{{spaced ndash}}[[Workers Party of Bangladesh]]{{spaced ndash}} participates in the [[Grand Alliance (Bangladesh)|ruling coalition]]
* {{flag|Belarus}}{{spaced ndash}}[[Communist Party of Belarus]]{{spaced ndash}} participates in the [[Government of Belarus]]
* {{flag|Brazil}}{{spaced ndash}}[[Communist Party of Brazil]]{{spaced ndash}}participates in the [[For Brazil to keep on changing|ruling coalition]]
* {{flag|Mali}}{{spaced ndash}}[[Malian Party of Labour]]{{spaced ndash}} involved with the [[Alliance for Democracy in Mali]]
* {{flag|Mongolia}}{{spaced ndash}}[[Mongolian People's Revolutionary Party (2010-)]]{{spaced ndash}} forms a government with the [[Democratic Party (Mongolia)]]
* {{flag|Peru}}{{spaced ndash}}[[Peruvian Communist Party]]{{spaced ndash}}participates in the [[Peru Wins|ruling coalition]]
* {{flag|South Africa}}{{spaced ndash}}[[South African Communist Party]]{{spaced ndash}}participates in the [[Tripartite alliance|ruling coalition]]
* {{flag|Sri Lanka}}{{spaced ndash}}[[Communist Party of Sri Lanka]]{{spaced ndash}}participates in the [[United People's Freedom Alliance|ruling coalition]]
* {{flag|Syria}}{{spaced ndash}}[[Syrian Communist Party (Bakdash)]], [[Syrian Communist Party (Faisal)]]{{spaced ndash}}participates in the [[National Progressive Front (Syria)|ruling coalition]]
*{{flag|Ukraine}}{{spaced ndash}}[[Communist Party of Ukraine]]{{spaced ndash}}participates in the [[Azarov Government|ruling coalition]]
*{{flag|Uruguay}}{{spaced ndash}}[[Communist Party of Uruguay]]{{spaced ndash}}participates in the [[Broad Front (Uruguay)|ruling coalition]]
* {{flag|Venezuela}}{{spaced ndash}}[[Communist Party of Venezuela]]{{spaced ndash}} participates in the [[Great Patriotic Pole|ruling coalition]]

== See also ==
* [[Capitalist state]]
* [[Socialist state]]
* [[Marxism-Leninism]]
* [[Democratic centralism]]
* [[Socialist market economy]]
* [[State capitalism]]
* [[Planned economy]]
* [[List of socialist countries]], which includes a list of current and former communist states.
* [[List of communist parties]]
* [[Criticisms of communist party rule]]
* [[List of communist and anti-capitalist parties with parliamentary representation]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Communist states}}
{{Authoritarian types of rule}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2010}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Communist State}}
[[Category:Lists of countries]]
[[Category:Communist states| ]]
[[Category:Forms of government]]
[[Category:Communism]]

[[ar:دولة شيوعية]]
[[cs:Komunistický režim]]
[[et:Kommunistlik riik]]
[[el:Κομμουνιστικό κράτος]]
[[fr:État communiste]]
[[ko:공산주의 국가]]
[[hr:Komunistička država]]
[[id:Negara komunis]]
[[arz:دولة شيوعيه]]
[[ms:Negara komunis]]
[[no:Liste over kommuniststater]]
[[pt:Anexo:Lista de estados comunistas atuais]]
[[ro:Stat comunist]]
[[simple:Socialist state]]
[[sr:Комунистичка држава]]
[[fi:Luettelo kommunistisista valtioista]]
[[sv:Kommunistiska stater]]
[[th:รัฐคอมมิวนิสต์]]
[[tr:Komünist devlet]]
[[yo:Orílẹ̀-èdè kọ́múnístì]]
[[zh:共产主义国家]]</text>
      <sha1>nu1tlg8ggnismaway1g57cwunmi31n7</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
