<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Domestic violence</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18978563</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520494177</id>
      <parentid>520493997</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-29T21:49:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Materialscientist</username>
        <id>7852030</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[Help:Reverting|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/Enzomey|Enzomey]] ([[User talk:Enzomey|talk]]) to last version by Materialscientist</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="134463">{{Edit semi-protected}}
{{Infobox disease
| Name = Domestic violence
| DiseasesDB =
| Image =
| Caption =
| ICD10 =
| ICD9 =
| ICDO =
| OMIM =
| MedlinePlus =
| eMedicineSubj =
| eMedicineTopic =
| eMedicine_mult = {{eMedicine2|article|805546}}
| MeshID = D017579
}}
{{Family law}}
{{Feminism sidebar |expanded=Waves}}

'''Domestic violence''', also known as '''domestic abuse''', '''spousal abuse''', '''battering''', '''family violence''', and '''intimate partner violence (IPV)''', is defined as a pattern of abusive behaviors by one partner against another in an [[intimate relationship]] such as marriage, dating, family, or cohabitation.&lt;ref name=Shipway&gt;Shipway (2004)&lt;/ref&gt; Domestic violence, so defined, has many forms, including physical aggression or assault (hitting, kicking, biting, shoving, restraining, slapping, throwing objects), or threats thereof; [[sexual abuse]]; [[psychological abuse|emotional abuse]]; controlling or domineering; [[intimidation]]; [[stalking]]; passive/covert abuse (e.g., [[neglect]]); and [[Economic abuse|economic deprivation]].&lt;ref name=Shipway/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Siemieniuk 2010 763–770&quot;&gt;{{cite doi|10.1089/apc.2010.0235}}&lt;/ref&gt; Alcohol consumption&lt;ref name=&quot;Markz&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Markowitz, Sara|title=The Price of Alcohol, Wife Abuse, and Husband Abuse|journal=Southern Economic Journal|volume=67 |issue=2|pages=279–303|year=2000|doi=10.2307/1061471|jstor=1061471}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[mental illness]]&lt;ref name=dutton1994&gt;{{Cite pmid|7696196}}&lt;/ref&gt; can be [[co-morbid]] with [[abuse]], and present additional challenges in eliminating domestic violence.
Awareness, perception, definition and documentation of domestic violence differs widely from country to country, and from era to era.

Domestic violence and abuse is not limited to obvious physical violence. Domestic violence can also mean endangerment, criminal coercion, kidnapping, unlawful imprisonment, trespassing, harassment, and stalking.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Crimes|url=http://womenslaw.org/laws_state_type.php?statelaw_name=Crimes&amp;state_code=GE|publisher=National Network to End Domestic Violence, Inc.|accessdate=2 December 2011|year=2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{TOC limit|3}}

==Definitions==
According to the Merriam-Webster dictionary definition, domestic violence is: &quot;the inflicting of physical injury by one family or household member on another; also: a repeated / habitual pattern of such behavior.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/domestic%20violence ''Domestic Violence.''] Merriam Webster. Retrieved 14 Nov. 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

The term &quot;intimate partner violence&quot; (IPV) is often used synonymously with domestic abuse/domestic violence. Family violence is a broader definition, often used to include [[child abuse]], [[elder abuse]], and other violent acts between family members.&lt;ref&gt;Wallace, p. 2&lt;/ref&gt; Wife abuse, wife beating, and battering are descriptive terms that have lost popularity recently for several reasons:
*There is acknowledgment that many victims are not actually married to the abuser, but rather cohabiting or in other arrangements.&lt;ref name=&quot;waits1985&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Waits, Kathleen |title=The Criminal Justice System's Response to Battering: Understanding the Problem, Forging the Solutions |journal=Washington Law Review |volume=60 |date=1984-1985 |pages=267–330|url=https://www.ncjrs.gov/App/publications/Abstract.aspx?id=108130}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Abuse can take other forms than physical abuse. Other forms of abuse may be constantly occurring, while physical abuse happens occasionally.
*Males as well as females may be victims of domestic violence.
These other forms of abuse have the potential to lead to [[mental illness]], [[self-harm]], and even attempts at [[suicide]].&lt;ref&gt;Shipway (2004), p. 3&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Mayhew, P., Mirlees-Black, C. and Percy, A. |title=The 1996 British Crime Survey England &amp; Wales |publisher=Home Office |year=1996}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Government definitions===
The US [[Office on Violence Against Women]] (OVW) defines domestic violence as a &quot;pattern of abusive behavior in any relationship that is used by one partner to gain or maintain [[Power (communication)|power]] and control over another intimate partner&quot;. The definition adds that domestic violence &quot;can happen to anyone regardless of race, age, sexual orientation, religion, or gender&quot;, and can take many forms, including physical abuse, sexual abuse, emotional, economic, and psychological abuse.&lt;ref name=&quot;ovw-about&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usdoj.gov/ovw/domviolence.htm |title=About Domestic Violence |publisher=Office on Violence Against Women |accessdate=2007-06-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Children and Family Court Advisory and Support Service]] in the [[United Kingdom]] in its &quot;Domestic Violence Policy&quot; uses ''domestic violence'' to refer to a range of violent and abusive behaviours, defining it as:

{{quote|Patterns of behaviour characterised by the misuse of power and control by one person over another who are or have been in an intimate relationship. It can occur in mixed gender relationships and same gender relationships and has profound consequences for the lives of children, individuals, families and communities. It may be physical, sexual, emotional and/or psychological. The latter may include intimidation, harassment, damage to property, threats and [[financial abuse]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cafcass.gov.uk/English/Publications/consultation/04DecDV%20Policy.pdf|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20071130235416/http://www.cafcass.gov.uk/English/Publications/consultation/04DecDV%20Policy.pdf|archivedate=2007-11-30|title=Domestic Violence Assessment Policy |publisher=Children and Family Court Advisory and Support Service |format=PDF |accessdate=2007-06-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Dynamics classification===
Violence by a person against their intimate partner is often done as a way for controlling their partner, even if this kind of violence is not the most frequent.&lt;ref&gt;
LAROCHE Denis, [http://www.stat.gouv.qc.ca/publications/conditions/pdf2008/ViolenceH_F2004_an.pdf Context and Consequences of Domestic Violence Against Men and Women in Canada in 2004] p.35. 2004&lt;/ref&gt; Many types of intimate partner violence occur, including violence between gay and lesbian couples,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Renzetti, C. M. and C. H. Miley |year=1996 |title=Violence in Gay and Lesbian Domestic Partnerships |publisher=Haworth Press |isbn=1-56023-074-6 |oclc=33947252}}&lt;/ref&gt; and by women against their male partners.&lt;ref name=&quot;johnson2000c&quot;&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1111/j.1741-3737.2000.00948.x}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Intimate partner violence types===
Michael P. Johnson argues for four major types of intimate partner violence, which is supported by subsequent research and evaluation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite pmid|17043363}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=jstor353683&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Patriarchal Terrorism and Common Couple Violence: Two Forms of Violence against Women|author=Michael P. Johnson|journal=Journal of Marriage and Family|volume=57|issue=2|year=1995|page=283|doi=10.2307/353683| jstor=353683|pages=283–294}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Johnson, M. P. (2006). [http://books.google.com/books?id=pvafa2zE0R8C&amp;pg=PA557 Violence and abuse in personal relationships: Conflict, terror, and resistance in intimate partnerships]. In A. L. Vangelisti &amp; D. Perlman (Eds.), Cambridge handbook of personal relationships (pp. 557–576). Cambridge: Cambridge University Press ISBN 0-521-82617-9&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1111/j.1741-3737.2004.00032.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as independent researchers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite pmid|12816403}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite pmid|19774764}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite pmid|16180370}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Distinctions are made among the types of violence, motives of perpetrators, and the social and cultural context based upon patterns across numerous incidents and motives of the perpetrator. Types of violence identified by Johnson:&lt;ref name=&quot;johnson2000c&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=jstor353683/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;johnson2000a&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Johnson, M. P. |year=2000 |chapter=Conflict and Control: Images of Symmetry and Asymmetry in Domestic Violence |editor=Booth, A., A. C. Crouter, and M. Clements |title=Couples in Conflict|isbn=0-8058-3545-8 |publisher=Erlbaum}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Tilbrook |first1= E. |last2= Allan |first2= A. |last3= Dear |first3= G.|title= Intimate Partner Abuse of Men|publisher= Edith Cowan University School of Psychology|year= 2010|url=http://www.man.org.au/Portals/0/docs/Intimate%20Partner%20Abuse%20of%20Men%20Report.pdf|format = PDF|work = Men's Advisory Network|location = Perth, Western Australia|accessdate= 21 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''[[Common couple violence]] (CCV)''' is not connected to general control behavior, but arises in a single argument where one or both partners physically lash out at the other.
*'''Intimate terrorism (IT)''' may also involve emotional and psychological abuse. Intimate terrorism is one element in a general pattern of control by one partner over the other. Intimate terrorism is less common than common couple violence, more likely to escalate over time, not as likely to be mutual, and more likely to involve serious injury.&lt;ref name=&quot;johnson2000c&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;johnson2000a&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1007/BF00978514}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Kirkwood, C. |year=1993 |title=Leaving Abusive Partners: From the Scars of Survival to the Wisdom for Change |publisher=Sage |isbn=0-8039-8686-6 |oclc=29049176}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Chang, V. N. |year=1996 |title=I Just Lost Myself: Psychological Abuse of Women in Marriage |publisher=Praeger|isbn=978-0-275-95209-9|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=3S0EAQAAIAAJ}}&lt;/ref&gt; IT batterers include two types: &quot;Generally-violent-antisocial&quot; and &quot;dysphoric-borderline&quot;. The first type includes people with general psychopathic and violent tendencies. The second type are people who are emotionally dependent on the relationship.&lt;ref name=&quot;johnson2000c&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;jacobson1998&quot; /&gt; Support for this typology has been found in subsequent evaluations.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite pmid|9210273}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite pmid|11142534}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''Violent resistance (VR), ''' sometimes thought of as &quot;self-defense&quot;, is violence perpetrated by victims against their abusive partners.&lt;ref name=&quot;johnson2000a&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;jacobson1998&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Jacobson, N. and J. Gottman |year=1998 |title=When Men Batter Women: New Insights into Ending Abusive Relationships |publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster |isbn=0-684-81447-1 |oclc=37748396}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1177/10778019922181284}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1007/BF02336946}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1007/BF01531942}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''Mutual violent control (MVC)''' is rare type of intimate partner violence occurring when both partners act in a violent manner, battling for control.&lt;ref name=&quot;johnson2000c&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Saunders DG |chapter=Wife Abuse, Husband Abuse, or Mutual Combat? A Feminist Perspective on the Empirical Findings |editor=Bograd ML, Yllö K |title=Feminist perspectives on wife abuse |publisher=Sage Publications |location=Thousand Oaks |year=1988 |pages=90–113 |isbn=0-8039-3053-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Types of male batterers identified by Holtzworth-Munroe and Stuart (1994) include &quot;family-only&quot;, which primarily fall into the CCV type, who are generally less violent and less likely to perpetrate psychological and sexual abuse.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite pmid|7809309}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other===
Others, such as the US [[Centers for Disease Control]], divide domestic violence into two types: reciprocal, in which both partners are violent, and non-reciprocal violence, in which one partner is violent; it is possible that the former is more common&lt;ref name=&quot;10.2105/AJPH.2005.079020&quot;&gt;{{cite doi|10.2105/AJPH.2005.079020}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Straus&quot; /&gt;

==Forms==
All forms of domestic abuse have one purpose: to ''gain and maintain control'' over the victim. Abusers use many tactics to exert power over their spouse or partner: dominance, [[humiliation]], [[Solitude|isolation]], [[Coercion|threats]], [[intimidation]], [[denial]] and [[blame]].&lt;ref name=&quot;HelpGuide&quot;&gt;[http://helpguide.org/mental/domestic_violence_abuse_types_signs_causes_effects.htm Domestic Violence and Abuse: Warning Signs and Symptoms of Abusive Relationships]. helpguide.org (2009-09-06).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Physical===
{{Main|Physical abuse}}
[[File:Kalighat Painting Calcutta 19th Century - Woman Strinking Man With Broom.jpg|thumb|right|Kalighat Painting, &quot;Woman Striking Man With Broom,&quot; Calcutta, India, 1875]]
'''Physical abuse''' is abuse involving contact intended to cause feelings of intimidation, pain, injury, or other physical suffering or bodily harm.

Physical abuse includes hitting, slapping, punching, choking, pushing, burning and other types of contact that result in physical injury to the victim. Physical abuse can also include behaviors such as denying the victim of medical care when needed, depriving the victim of sleep or other functions necessary to live, or forcing the victim to engage in drug/alcohol use against his/her will. If a person is suffering from any physical harm then they are experiencing physical abuse. This pain can be experienced on any level.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|last = U.S Department of Justice
| title = About Domestic Violence.
|year = 2007
|url = http://www.usdoj.gov/ovw/domviolence.htm
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; It can also include inflicting physical injury onto other targets, such as children or pets, in order to cause psychological harm to the victim.&lt;ref name=&quot;azcadv.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| title = Arizona Coalition Against Domestic Violence
| year = 2010
|url = http://www.azcadv.org
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sexual===
{{Main|Sexual abuse|Marital rape}}
'''Sexual abuse''' is any situation in which force or threat is used to obtain participation in unwanted sexual activity. Coercing a person to engage in sexual activity against their will, even if that person is a spouse or intimate partner with whom consensual sex has occurred, is an act of aggression and violence.

[[Sexual violence]] is defined by [[World Health Organization]] as:
*any sexual act, attempt to obtain a sexual act, unwanted sexual comments or advances, or acts to [[Human trafficking#Human trafficking and sexual exploitation|traffic]], or otherwise directed, against a person’s sexuality using [[Consent (criminal)|coercion]], ''by any person regardless of their relationship to the victim, in any setting, including but not limited to home'' and work.&lt;ref&gt;World Health Organization., World report on violence and health (Geneva: World Health Organization, 2002), 149.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Marital rape]], also known as '''spousal rape''', is non-[[consent|consensual]] sex in which the perpetrator is the victim's spouse. As such, it is a form of [[partner rape]], of domestic violence, and of [[sexual abuse]]. In the [[United States|US]] spousal rape is illegal in all 50 states.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/1987/05/13/us/marital-rape-drive-for-tougher-laws-is-pressed.html Marital rape: Drive for tougher laws is pressed], 13 May 1987]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ncvc.org/ncvc/main.aspx?dbName=DocumentViewer&amp;DocumentID=32701 Spousal Rape Laws: 20 Years Later] National Center for Victims of Crime. Retrieved 2011-11-18.&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Canada]], spousal rape was outlawed in 1983, when several legal changes were made, including changing the rape statute to ''sexual assault'', and making the laws gender neutral.&lt;ref name=grady/&gt; Criminalization in [[Australia]] began with the state of [[New South Wales]] in 1981, followed by all other states from 1985 to 1992.&lt;ref name=&quot;Temkin86&quot;&gt;Jennifer Temkin, ''Rape and the legal process'', Oxford University Press, 2002 ISBN 0198763549, p. 86.&lt;/ref&gt; [[New Zealand]] outlawed spousal rape in 1985, and [[Ireland]] in 1990.&lt;ref name=&quot;Temkin86&quot;/&gt;
In [[England and Wales]], spousal rape was made illegal in 1991, when the marital rape exemption was abolished by the [[Appellate Committee of the House of Lords]], in the case of ''R v R''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bailii.org/uk/cases/UKHL/1991/12.html |title=&lt;nowiki&gt;[1991] UKHL 12&lt;/nowiki&gt; |publisher=[[BAILII]] |accessdate=21 January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Categories of sexual abuse include:
# Use of physical force to compel a person to engage in a sexual act against his or her will, whether or not the act is completed;
# Attempted or completed sex act involving a person who is unable to understand the nature or condition of the act, unable to decline participation, or unable to communicate unwillingness to engage in the sexual act, e.g., because of underage immaturity, illness, disability, or the influence of alcohol or other drugs, or because of intimidation or pressure.

===Emotional===
{{Main|Emotional abuse}}
'''Emotional abuse''' (also called psychological abuse or mental abuse) can include humiliating the victim privately or publicly, controlling what the victim can and cannot do, withholding information from the victim, deliberately doing something to make the victim feel diminished or [[embarrassed]], isolating the victim from friends and family, implicitly [[blackmail]]ing the victim by harming others when the victim expresses independence or happiness, or denying the victim access to money or other basic resources and necessities. Degradation in any form can be considered psychological abuse.

Emotional abuse can include verbal abuse and is defined as any behavior that threatens, intimidates, undermines the victim’s self-worth or self-esteem, or controls the victim’s freedom.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1177/088626000015009001}}&lt;/ref&gt; This can include threatening the victim with injury or harm, telling the victim that they will be killed if they ever leave the relationship, and public humiliation. Constant criticism, name-calling, and making statements that damage the victim’s self-esteem are also common verbal forms of emotional abuse. Often perpetrators will use children to engage in emotional abuse by teaching them to harshly criticize the victim as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;ncadv.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| title = National Coalition Against Domestic Violence
|year = 2010
|url = http://www.ncadv.org
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Emotional abuse includes conflicting actions or statements which are designed to [[gaslighting|confuse and create insecurity in the victim]]. These behaviors also lead the victims to question themselves, causing them to believe that they are making up the abuse or that the [[victim blaming|abuse is their fault]].&lt;ref name=&quot;azcadv.org&quot;/&gt;

Emotional abuse includes forceful efforts to isolate the victim, keeping them from contacting friends or family. This is intended to eliminate those who might try to help the victim leave the relationship and to create a lack of resources for them to rely on if they were to leave. Isolation results in damaging the victim’s sense of internal strength, leaving them feeling helpless and unable to escape from the situation.&lt;ref name=&quot;ncadv.org&quot;/&gt;

People who are being emotionally abused often feel as if they do not own themselves; rather, they may feel that their significant other has nearly total control over them. Women or men undergoing emotional abuse often suffer from [[major depressive disorder|depression]], which puts them at increased risk for [[suicide]], [[eating disorder]]s, and [[drug abuse|drug]] and [[alcohol abuse]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20060907132522/http://faculty.inverhills.edu/vbutter/domesticviolenceweb.htm The Physical and Psychological Effects of Domestic Violence on Women]. Web.archive.org (2006-09-07). Retrieved on 2012-06-25.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Verbal===
{{Main|Verbal abuse}}

'''Verbal abuse''' is a form of emotionally abusive behavior involving the use of language. Verbal abuse can also be referred to as the act of threatening. Through threatening a person can blatantly say they will harm you in any way and will also be considered as abuse.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Domestic violence|url=http://womensweb.ca/violence/dv/abuse.php|publisher=Women's Web|year=2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; It may include [[profanity]] but can occur with or without the use of [[Expletive attributive|expletives]].{{citation needed|date=November 2011}}

Verbal abuse may include aggressive actions such as name-calling, blaming, ridicule, disrespect, and criticism, but there are also less obviously aggressive forms of verbal abuse. Statements that may seem benign on the surface can be thinly veiled attempts to [[humiliate]]; [[falsely accuse]]; or manipulate others to submit to undesirable behavior, make others feel unwanted and unloved, threaten others economically, or isolate victims from support systems.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign |title=Types of Emotional Abuse|year=2007|url=http://www.counselingcenter.illinois.edu/?page_id=168}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Jekyll and Hyde behaviors, the abuser may fluctuate between sudden [[Rage (emotion)|rages]] and false joviality toward the victim; or may simply show a very different &quot;face&quot; to the outside world than to the victim. While oral communication is the most common form of verbal abuse, it includes abusive communication in written form.{{citation needed|date=November 2011}}

===Economic===
{{main|Economic abuse}}

'''Economic abuse''' is a form of abuse when one intimate partner has control over the other partner's access to economic resources.&lt;ref name=&quot;Adams (2008)&quot;&gt;{{cite pmid|18408173}}&lt;/ref&gt; Economic abuse may involve preventing a spouse from resource acquisition, limiting the amount of resources to use by the victim, or by exploiting economic resources of the victim.&lt;ref name=&quot;Adams (2008)&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Brewster (2003)&quot;&gt;{{cite doi|10.1023/A:1024064214054}}&lt;/ref&gt; The motive behind preventing a spouse from acquiring resources is to diminish victim's capacity to support him/herself, thus forcing him/her to depend on the perpetrator financially, which includes preventing the victim from obtaining education, finding employment, maintaining or advancing their careers, and acquiring assets.&lt;ref name=&quot;Adams (2008)&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Brewster (2003)&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Sanders (2004)&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Sanders|first=Cynthia|title=Organizing for Economic Empowerment of Battered Women: Women’s Savings Accounts|work=Center for Social Development, George Warren Brown School of Social Work, Washington University}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In addition, the abuser may also put the victim on an allowance, closely monitor how the victim spends money, spend victim's money without his/her consent and creating debt, or completely spend victim's savings to limit available resources&lt;ref name=&quot;Adams (2008)&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Brewster (2003)&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Sanders (2004)&quot; /&gt;

==Effects==
===On children===
3.3 million children witness domestic violence each year in the US. There has been an increase in acknowledgment that a child who is exposed to domestic abuse during their upbringing will suffer in their developmental and psychological welfare.&lt;ref name=Dodd2009&gt;{{cite doi|10.1080/02667360802697571}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because of the awareness of domestic violence that some children have to face, it also generally impacts how the child develops emotionally, socially, behaviorally as well as cognitively.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1111/j.1365-2524.2009.00833.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some emotional and behavioral problems that can result due to domestic violence include increased aggressiveness, anxiety, and changes in how a child socializes with friends, family, and authorities.&lt;ref name=Dodd2009/&gt; Depression, as well as self-esteem issues, can follow due to traumatic experiences. Problems with attitude and cognition in schools can start developing, along with a lack of skills such as problem-solving.&lt;ref name=Dodd2009/&gt; Correlation has been found between the experience of abuse and neglect in childhood and perpertrating domestic violence and sexual abuse in adulthood.&lt;ref name=Sadeler&gt;Sadeler, Christiane (1994). ''[http://scholars.wlu.ca/etd/634/ An ounce of prevention: The life stories and perceptions of men who sexually offended against children]'' (M.A. thesis) Wilfrid Laurier University&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, in some cases the abuser will purposely abuse the mother&lt;ref name=Damant&gt;{{cite doi|10.1111/j.1365-2206.2009.00632.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; or father{{citation needed|date=December 2011}} in front of the child to cause a ripple effect, hurting two victims simultaneously.&lt;ref name=Damant/&gt; It has been found that children who witness mother-assault are more likely to exhibit symptoms of [[posttraumatic stress disorder]] (PTSD).&lt;ref name=Lehmann&gt;Lehmann, Peter John (1995). ''[http://scholars.wlu.ca/etd/193/ Children who witness mother-assault: An expander posttraumatic stress disorder conceptualization]'' (M.A. thesis) Wilfrid Laurier University&lt;/ref&gt; Consequences to these children are likely to be more severe if their assaulted mother develops posttruamatic stress disorder (PTSD) and does not seek treatment due to her difficulty in assisting her child with processing his or her own experience of witnessing the domestic violence.&lt;ref&gt;Schechter DS, Willheim E, McCaw J, Turner JB, Myers MM, Zeanah CH (2011). [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22170456 The relationship of violent fathers, posttraumatically stressed mothers, and symptomatic children in a preschool-age inner-city pediatrics clinic sample.] Journal of Interpersonal Violence, 26(18), 3699–3719.&lt;/ref&gt;

Family Violence prevention in Australia and other countries has begun to focus on breaking intergenerational cycles, according to the National (Aust) Standards for Working with Children Exposed to Family Violence it is important to acknowledge that exposing children to Family Violence is child abuse.&lt;ref&gt;National Standards for Working with Children Exposed to Domestic and Family Violence&lt;/ref&gt; Some of the effects of Family Violence on children are highlighted in the Queensland Government and [[Sunnykids|SunnyKids]] awareness raising campaign.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?feature=player_embedded&amp;v=aws4YYC-hOk Act As One]. Youtube.com. Retrieved on 2011-12-23.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Physical===
Bruises, broken bones, head injuries, lacerations, and internal bleeding are some of the acute effects of a domestic violence incident that require medical attention and hospitalization.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones 1997 43–50&quot;&gt;{{Cite pmid|9253665}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Some chronic health conditions that have been linked to victims of domestic violence are arthritis, irritable bowel syndrome, chronic pain, pelvic pain, ulcers, and migraines.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite pmid|1926841}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Victims who are pregnant during a domestic violence relationship experience greater risk of miscarriage, pre-term labor, and injury to or death of the fetus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones 1997 43–50&quot;/&gt;

===Psychological===
Among victims who are still living with their perpetrators high amounts of stress, fear, and anxiety are commonly reported. Depression is also common, as victims are made to feel [[guilty]] for ‘provoking’ the abuse and are frequently subjected to intense [[criticism]]. It is reported that 60% of victims meet the diagnostic criteria for depression, either during or after termination of the relationship, and have a greatly increased risk of suicidality.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1177/1524838001002001001}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to depression, victims of domestic violence also commonly experience long-term [[anxiety]] and [[panic]], and are likely to meet the diagnostic criteria for [[Generalized Anxiety Disorder]] and [[Panic Disorder]]. The most commonly referenced psychological effect of domestic violence is [[Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder]] (PTSD). PTSD (as experienced by victims) is characterized by [[Flashback (psychology)|flashbacks]], intrusive images, exaggerated [[startle response]], [[nightmares]], and avoidance of triggers that are associated with the abuse.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite pmid|8555116}}&lt;/ref&gt; These symptoms are generally experienced for a long span of time after the victim has left the dangerous situation. Many researchers state that PTSD is possibly the best diagnosis for those suffering from psychological effects of domestic violence, as it accounts for the variety of symptoms commonly experienced by victims of trauma.

===Financial===
Once victims leave their perpetrator, they can be stunned with the reality of the extent to which the abuse has taken away their autonomy. Due to economic abuse and isolation, the victim usually has very little money of their own and few people on whom they can rely when seeking help. This has been shown to be one of the greatest obstacles facing victims of DV, and the strongest factor that can discourage them from leaving their perpetrators.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stop Violence Against Women&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| title = Stop Violence Against Women
| year = 2010
|url = http://www.stopvaw.org/Domestic_Violence_and_Housing.html
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In addition to lacking financial resources, victims of DV often lack specialized skills, education, and training that are necessary to find gainful employment, and also may have several children to support. In 2003, thirty-six major US cities cited DV as one of the primary causes of homelessness in their areas.&lt;ref name=&quot;aclu.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| title = American Civil Liberties Union Women's Rights Project
| year = 2007
|url = http://www.aclu.org/FilesPDFs/housing%20paper.4.pdf
}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has also been reported that one out of every three homeless women are homeless due to having left a DV relationship. If a victim is able to secure rental housing, it is likely that her apartment complex will have &quot;zero tolerance&quot; policies for crime; these policies can cause them to face eviction even if they are the victim (not the perpetrator) of violence.&lt;ref name=&quot;aclu.org&quot;/&gt; While the number of shelters and community resources available to DV victims has grown tremendously, these agencies often have few employees and hundreds of victims seeking assistance which causes many victims to remain without the assistance they need.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stop Violence Against Women&quot;/&gt;

===Long-term===
Domestic violence can trigger many different responses in victims, all of which are very relevant for any professional working with a victim. Major consequences of domestic violence victimization include psychological/mental health issues and chronic physical health problems. A victim’s overwhelming lack of resources can lead to homelessness and poverty.

===On responders===
====Vicarious trauma====
{{See also|Vicarious traumatization}}
Due to the gravity and intensity of hearing victims’ stories of abuse, professionals (social workers, police, counselors, therapists, advocates, medical professionals) are at risk themselves for secondary or vicarious trauma (VT), which causes the responder to experience trauma symptoms similar to the original victim after hearing about the victim’s experiences with abuse.&lt;ref name=&quot;Iliffe&quot;&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1177/088626000015004004}}&lt;/ref&gt; Research has demonstrated that professionals who experience vicarious trauma show signs of exaggerated startle response, [[hypervigilance]], nightmares, and [[intrusive thoughts]] although they have not experienced a trauma personally and do not qualify for a clinical diagnosis of PTSD.&lt;ref name=&quot;Iliffe&quot; /&gt; Researchers concluded that although clinicians have professional training and are equipped with the necessary clinical skills to assist victims of domestic violence, they may still be personally affected by the emotional impact of hearing about a victim’s traumatic experiences. Iliffe et al. found that there are several common initial responses that are found in clinicians who work with victims: loss of confidence in their ability to help the client, taking personal responsibility for ensuring the client’s safety, and remaining supportive of the client’s autonomy if they make the decision to return to their perpetrator.&lt;ref name=&quot;Iliffe&quot; /&gt; It has also been shown that clinicians who work with a large number of victims may alter their former perceptions of the world, and begin to doubt the basic goodness of others. Iliffe et al. found that clinicians who work with victims tend to feel less secure in the world, become &quot;acutely aware&quot; of power and control issues both in society and in their own personal relationships, have difficulty trusting others, and experience an increased awareness of gender-based power differences in society.&lt;ref name=&quot;Iliffe&quot; /&gt;

The best way for a clinician to avoid developing VT is to engage in good self-care practices. These can include exercise, relaxation techniques, debriefing with colleagues, and seeking support from supervisors.&lt;ref name=&quot;Iliffe&quot; /&gt; Additionally, it is recommended that clinicians make the positive and rewarding aspects of working with domestic violence victims the primary focus of thought and energy, such as being part of the healing process or helping society as a whole. Clinicians should also continually evaluate their empathic responses to victims, in order to avoid feelings of being drawn in to the trauma that the victim experienced. It is recommended that clinicians practice good [[personal boundaries|boundaries]], and find a balance in expressing empathic responses to the victim while still maintaining personal detachment from their traumatic experiences.&lt;ref name=&quot;Iliffe&quot; /&gt;

====Burnout====
{{See also|Burnout (psychology)}}
Vicarious trauma can lead directly to burnout, which is defined as &quot;emotional exhaustion resulting from excessive demands on energy, strength, and personal resources in the work setting&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Koocher&quot;&gt;{{Cite book
|last = Koocher
|first = G
|coauthors = Keith-Spiegel
|title = Ethics in psychology
|publisher = Oxford University Press
|year = 1998
|location = New York
|isbn = 0-19-509201-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; The physical warning signs of burnout include headaches, fatigue, lowered immune function, and irritability.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite pmid|112612}}&lt;/ref&gt; A clinician experiencing burnout may begin to lose interest in the welfare of clients, be unable to empathize or feel compassion for clients, and may even begin to feel aversion toward the client.&lt;ref name=&quot;Koocher&quot; /&gt; If the clinician experiencing burnout is working with victims of domestic violence, the clinician risks causing further great harm through [[re-victimization]] of the client. It should be noted, however, that vicarious trauma does not always directly lead to burnout and that burnout can occur in clinicians who work with any difficult population&amp;nbsp;– not only those who work with domestic violence victims.

==Cause==
There are many different theories as to the causes of domestic violence. These include psychological theories that consider personality traits and mental characteristics of the perpetrator, as well as social theories which consider external factors in the perpetrator's environment, such as family structure, stress, social learning. As with many phenomena regarding human experience, no single approach appears to cover all cases.

Whilst there are many theories regarding what causes one individual to act violently towards an intimate partner or family member there is also growing concern around apparent intergenerational cycles of domestic violence. In Australia where it has been identified that as many as 75% of all victims of domestic violence are children&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sunnykids.org.au/pdf/publications/2010annual-report.pdf SunnyKids annual report 2010]. sunnykids.org.au&lt;/ref&gt; Domestic violence services such as [[Sunnykids]] are beginning to focus their attention on children who have been exposed to domestic violence.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sunnykids.org.au/index.html SunnyKids Australia].&lt;/ref&gt;

Responses that focus on children suggest that experiences throughout life influence an individuals' propensity to engage in family violence (either as a victim or as a perpetrator). Researchers supporting this theory suggest it is useful to think of three sources of domestic violence: childhood socialization, previous experiences in couple relationships during adolescence, and levels of strain in a person's current life. People who observe their parents abusing each other, or who were themselves abused may incorporate abuse into their behaviour within relationships that they establish as adults. (Kalmuss &amp; Seltzer 1984)

===Psychological===
Psychological theories focus on personality traits and mental characteristics of the offender. Personality traits include sudden bursts of [[anger]], poor [[impulse control]], and poor [[self-esteem]]. Various theories suggest that psychopathology and other personality disorders are factors, and that abuse experienced as a child leads some people to be more violent as adults. Correlation has been found between [[juvenile delinquency]] and domestic violence in adulthood.&lt;ref name=Kalra&gt;Kalra, Michelle (1996). ''[http://scholars.wlu.ca/etd/570/ Juvenile delinquency and adult aggression against women]'' (M.A. thesis) Wilfrid Laurier University&lt;/ref&gt; Studies have found high incidence of [[psychopathy]] among abusers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1007/BF00978276}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1007/BF00978715}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1521/pedi.1993.7.4.329}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For instance, some research suggests that about 80% of both court-referred and self-referred men in these domestic violence studies exhibited diagnosable [[psychopathology]], typically [[personality disorders]]. &quot;The estimate of personality disorders in the general population would be more in the 15–20% range [...] As violence becomes more severe and chronic in the relationship, the likelihood of [[psychopathology]] in these men approaches 100%.&quot;&lt;ref name=dutton1994/&gt;
Dutton has suggested a psychological profile of men who abuse their wives, arguing that they have [[borderline personality disorder|borderline personalities]] that are developed early in life.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Dutton, D. G., S. K. Golant |year=1995 |title=The Batterer: A Psychological Profile |publisher=Basic Books |isbn=0-465-03387-3 |oclc=243827535}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite pmid|8060906}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, these psychological theories are disputed: Gelles suggests that psychological theories are limited, and points out that other researchers have found that only 10% (or less) fit this psychological profile. He argues that social factors are important, while personality traits, mental illness, or psychopathy are lesser factors.&lt;ref&gt;Gelles (1997), pp. 126–127&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Steele BF |year=1974 |chapter=A Psychiatric Study of Parents Who Abuse Infants and Small Children |editor=Kempe CH, Helfer RE |title=The Battered Child |pages=89–134 |publisher=Jossey-Bass |edition=2nd |isbn=0-226-32629-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Straus MA |year=1980 |chapter=A Sociological Perspective on the Causes of Family Violence |title=Violence and the Family |editor=Green MR |publisher=Westview |isbn=0-385-14259-5 |oclc=5725780}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Jealousy===
Many cases of domestic violence against women occur due to [[jealousy]] when one partner is either suspected of being unfaithful or is planning to leave the relationship.&lt;ref name=Jealousy1/&gt;&lt;ref name=Jealousy2/&gt; An [[evolutionary psychology]] explanation of such cases of domestic violence against a woman is that they represent male attempts to control female reproduction and ensure sexual exclusivity through violence or the threat of violence.&lt;ref name=Jealousy1&gt;{{cite doi|10.4236/psych.2011.24062}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Jealousy2&gt;{{cite pmid|20100422}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Behavioral===
Behavioral theories draw on the work of behavior analysts. [[Applied behavior analysis]] uses the basic principles of [[learning theory (education)|learning theory]] to change behavior. Behavioral theories of domestic violence focus on the use of functional assessment with the goal of reducing episodes of violence to zero rates.&lt;ref name=&quot;baojournal.com&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|author=Shorey, R.C., Cornelius, T.L. and Bell, K.M. |year=2008|title= Behavioral Theory and Dating Violence: A Framework for Prevention Programming|journal= Journal of Behavior Analysis of Offender and Victim: Treatment and Prevention|volume= 1|issue=4| pages=298–311}}&lt;/ref&gt; This program leads to [[behavior therapy]]. Often by identifying the antecedents and consequences of violent action, the abusers can be taught [[self control]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Bonem, M., Stanely- Kime, K.L. and Corbin, M. |year=2008|title= A behavioral approach to domestic violence|journal=Journal of Behavior Analysis of Offender and Victim: Treatment and Prevention|issue=4|pages= 210–213|volume=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Recently more focus has been placed on prevention and a behavioral prevention theory.&lt;ref name=&quot;baojournal.com&quot;/&gt;

===Social theories===
Looks at external factors in the offender's environment, such as family structure, stress, social learning, and includes [[rational choice theory (criminology)|rational choice]] theories.&lt;ref&gt;Haugan, Grethemor Skagseth and Nøttestad, Jim Aage [http://www.europrofem.org/contri/2_04_en/en-viol/81en_vio.htm ''Norway : Treatment Program For Men Who Batter'']. Norwegian University of Science and Technology. Trondheim, Norway&lt;/ref&gt;

====Resource theory====
Resource theory was suggested by William Goode (1971).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Goode, William |year=1971 |title=Force and Violence in the Family |journal=Journal of Marriage and the Family |volume=33 |pages=624–36 |doi=10.2307/349435 |issue=4 |publisher=National Council on Family Relations |jstor=349435}}&lt;/ref&gt; Women who are most dependent on the spouse for economic well being (e.g. homemakers/housewives, women with handicaps, the unemployed), and are the primary caregiver to their children, fear the increased financial burden if they leave their marriage. Dependency means that they have fewer options and few resources to help them cope with or change their spouse's behavior.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Kalmuss, D. S. and Straus, M. A.|chapter=Wife's Marital Dependency and Wife Abuse |editor=Straus, M. A., Gelles, R. J. and Smith Ch.|title=Physical Violence in American Families|isbn=1-56000-828-8|publisher=Transaction Publishers|year=1995|url=http://books.google.com/?id=4_3nLMBoiTwC&amp;printsec=frontcover}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Couples that share power equally experience lower incidence of conflict, and when conflict does arise, are less likely to resort to violence. If one spouse desires control and power in the relationship, the spouse may resort to abuse.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Kurz, D. |year=1992 |chapter=Battering and the Criminal Justice System: A Feminist View |editor=Buzawa, E. S., C. G. Buzawa |title=Domestic Violence: The Changing Criminal Justice Response |publisher=Auburn House|isbn=0865690014}}&lt;/ref&gt; This may include coercion and threats, intimidation, emotional abuse, economic abuse, isolation, [[making light of]] the situation and blaming the spouse, using children (threatening to take them away), and behaving as &quot;master of the castle&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Wallace, pp. 184–185&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theduluthmodel.org/documents/PhyVio.pdf|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20100601232757/http://www.theduluthmodel.org/documents/PhyVio.pdf|archivedate=2010-06-01|publisher=Domestic Abuse Intervention Project |title=Power and Control Wheel |accessdate=2007-11-27|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Social stress====
Stress may be increased when a person is living in a family situation, with increased pressures. Social stresses, due to inadequate finances or other such problems in a family may further increase tensions.&lt;ref&gt;Gelles (1997), p. 128&lt;/ref&gt; Violence is not always caused by stress, but may be one way that some people respond to stress.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Seltzer, Judith A., Debra Kalmuss |title=Socialization and Stress Explanations for Spouse Abuse |journal=Social Forces |volume=67 |year=1988 |pages=473–91 |doi=10.2307/2579191 |issue=2 |publisher=University of North Carolina Press |jstor=2579191}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1146/annurev.so.18.080192.000311}}&lt;/ref&gt; Families and couples in poverty may be more likely to experience domestic violence, due to increased stress and conflicts about finances and other aspects.&lt;ref name=&quot;jewkes2002&quot;&gt;{{Cite pmid|11978358}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some speculate that poverty may hinder a man's ability to live up to his idea of &quot;successful manhood&quot;, thus he fears losing honor and respect. Theory suggests that when he is unable to economically support his wife, and maintain control, he may turn to [[misogyny]], [[substance abuse]], and [[crime]] as ways to express masculinity.&lt;ref name=&quot;jewkes2002&quot; /&gt;

====Social learning theory====
[[Social learning theory]] suggests that people learn from observing and modeling after others' behavior. With [[positive reinforcement]], the behavior continues. If one observes violent behavior, one is more likely to imitate it. If there are no negative consequences (e. g. victim accepts the violence, with submission), then the behavior will likely continue. Often, violence is transmitted from generation to generation in a cyclical manner.{{Vague|date=December 2010}}
&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite pmid|3154143}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite pmid|8193057}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1007/bf01531961}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Power and control====
In abusive relationships, violence is posited to arise out of a need for power and control of one partner over the other. An abuser will use various tactics of abuse (e.g., physical, verbal, emotional, sexual or financial) in order to establish and maintain control over the partner.

Abusers' efforts to dominate their partners have been attributed to low self-esteem or feelings of inadequacy, unresolved childhood conflicts, the stress of poverty, hostility and resentment toward women ([[misogyny]]), hostility and resentment toward men ([[misandry]]), personality disorders, genetic tendencies and sociocultural influences, among other possible causative factors. Most authorities seem to agree that abusive personalities result from a combination of several factors, to varying degrees.

A [[causality|causalist]] view of domestic violence is that it is a strategy to gain or maintain power and control over the victim. This view is in alignment with Bancroft's &quot;cost-benefit&quot; theory that abuse rewards the perpetrator in ways other than, or in addition to, simply exercising power over his or her target(s). He cites evidence in support of his argument that, in most cases, abusers are quite capable of exercising control over themselves, but choose not to do so for various reasons.&lt;ref name=Bancroft&gt;{{Cite book|last = Bancroft|first = L|title = Why does he do that? Inside the minds of angry and controlling men|url = http://books.google.com/books?id=xEZIpu3SVvcC&amp;printsec=frontcover|publisher = [[Berkley Books]]|year = 2002|isbn = 0425191656}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An alternative view is that abuse arises from powerlessness and [[Externalization|externalizing]]/[[psychological projection|projecting]] this and attempting to exercise control of the victim. It is an attempt to 'gain or maintain power and control over the victim' but even in achieving this it cannot resolve the powerlessness driving it. Such behaviours have addictive aspects leading to a [[cycle of abuse]] or [[cycle of violence|violence]]. Mutual cycles develop when each party attempts to resolve their own powerlessness in attempting to assert control.

Questions of power and control are integral to the widely utilized [[Duluth Domestic Abuse Intervention Project]]. They developed a &quot;Power and Control Wheel&quot; to illustrate this: it has power and control at the center, surrounded by spokes (techniques used), the titles of which include: coercion and [[threat]]s, [[intimidation]], [[emotional abuse]], [[solitude|isolation]], [[Minimisation (psychology)|minimizing]], [[denial|denying]] and blaming, using children, economic abuse, and male privilege.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ncdsv.org/images/Power_and_Control_wheel_NCDSV.pdf Power and Control Wheel.] National Center on Domestic and Sexual Violence. Retrieved 2011-11-18.&lt;/ref&gt; The model attempts to address abuse by challenging the misuse of power by the perpetrator.

The power wheel model is not intended to assign personal responsibility, enhance respect for mutual purpose or assist victims and perpetrators in resolving their differences. Rather, it is an informational tool designed to help individuals understand the dynamics of power operating in abusive situations and identify various methods of abuse.

Critics of this model argue that it ignores research linking domestic violence to substance abuse and psychological problems.&lt;ref name=Twohey&gt;{{cite news|last=Twohey|first=Megan|title=How can domestic abuse be stopped?|url=http://www.chicagotribune.com/news/local/chi-abusers-02-jan02,0,1147422.story?page=1|accessdate=16 April 2011|newspaper=Chicago Tribune|date=January 2, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some modern research into the patterns in DV has found that women are more likely to be physically abusive towards their partner in relationships in which only one partner is violent,&lt;ref name=&quot;10.2105/AJPH.2005.079020&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Straus&quot;&gt;{{cite conference|url=http://pubpages.unh.edu/~mas2/ID41E2.pdf|format=PDF|first1=Murray A|last1=Straus|title=Dominance and symmetry in partner violence by male and female university students in 32 nations|date=23 May 2006|accessdate=30 April 2012|publisher=New York University|booktitle=Trends In Intimate Violence Intervention}}&lt;/ref&gt; which draws the effectiveness of using concepts like male privilege to treat domestic violence into question; however, it may still be valid in studying severe abuse cases, which are mostly male perpetrated.&lt;ref name=&quot;Straus&quot; /&gt; However, modern research into predictors of injury from domestic violence finds that the strongest predictor of injury by domestic violence is participation in reciprocal domestic violence, and that this pattern of domestic violence is more often initiated by the female in the relationship.&lt;ref name=&quot;aphapublications2005&quot;&gt;{{cite doi|10.2105/AJPH.2005.079020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mental illness===
Many psychiatric disorders are risk factors for domestic violence, including several [[personality disorder]]s: all [[Cluster B]] PDs, (especially [[antisocial personality disorder|antisocial]]), [[paranoid personality disorder|paranoid]] and [[passive-aggressive]]. [[Bipolar disorder]], [[schizophrenia]], [[drug abuse]], [[alcoholism]] and poor [[impulse control]] are also risk factors.&lt;ref name=&quot;Siemieniuk 2010 763–770&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://ajp.psychiatryonline.org/article.aspx?Volume=159&amp;page=1973&amp;journalID=13 Mental disorder and violence]&lt;/ref&gt; It is estimated that at least one-third of all abusers have some type of mental illness.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Worell|first=Judith|title=Encyclopedia of Women and Gender|year=2001|publisher=Academic Press|location=San Diego|isbn=0-12-227245-5|page=183|volume=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Marital conflict disorder===
The [[American Psychiatric Association]] planning and research committees for the forthcoming [[DSM-5]] (2013) have canvassed a series of new [[Relational disorder]]s which include ''Marital Conflict Disorder Without Violence'' or ''Marital Abuse Disorder (Marital Conflict Disorder With Violence)''.&lt;ref&gt;First, pp. 164, 166&lt;/ref&gt; Couples with marital disorders sometimes come to clinical attention because the couple recognize long-standing dissatisfaction with their [[marriage]] and come to the [[clinician]] on their own initiative or are referred by an astute health care professional. Secondly, there is serious [[violence]] in the marriage which is -&quot;usually the husband battering the wife&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;First, p. 163&lt;/ref&gt;

In these cases the emergency room or a legal authority often is the first to notify the [[clinician]]. Most importantly, marital violence &quot;is a major risk factor for serious injury and even death and women in violent marriages are at much greater risk of being seriously injured or killed ([[National Advisory Council on Violence Against Women]] 2000).&quot;&lt;ref name=First166&gt;First, p. 166&lt;/ref&gt; The authors of this study add that &quot;There is current considerable controversy over whether male-to-female marital violence is best regarded as a reflection of male [[psychopathology]] and control or whether there is an empirical base and clinical utility for conceptualizing these patterns as relational.&quot;&lt;ref name=First166 /&gt;

Recommendations for clinicians making a diagnosis of ''Marital Relational Disorder'' should include the assessment of actual or &quot;potential&quot; male violence as regularly as they assess the potential for [[suicide]] in depressed patients. Further, &quot;clinicians should not relax their vigilance after a battered [[wife]] leaves her [[husband]], because some data suggest that the period immediately following a marital separation is the period of greatest risk for the women. Many men will [[stalking|stalk]] and [[battery (crime)|batter]] their wives in an effort to get them to return or punish them for leaving. Initial assessments of the potential for violence in a marriage can be supplemented by standardized interviews and questionnaires, which have been reliable and valid aids in exploring marital violence more systematically.&quot;&lt;ref name=First166 /&gt;

The authors conclude with what they call &quot;very recent information&quot;&lt;ref name=First167&gt;First, pp. 167–168&lt;/ref&gt; on the course of violent marriages which suggests that &quot;over time a husband's battering may abate somewhat, but perhaps because he has successfully [[intimidate]]d his wife. The risk of violence remains strong in a marriage in which it has been a feature in the past. Thus, treatment is essential here; the clinician cannot just wait and watch.&quot;&lt;ref name=First167 /&gt; The most urgent clinical priority is the protection of the wife because she is the one most frequently at risk, and clinicians must be aware that supporting assertiveness by a battered wife may lead to more beatings or even death.&lt;ref name=First167 /&gt;

==Gender aspects of abuse==
The relationship between [[gender]] and domestic violence is a controversial topic. There continues to be debate about the rates at which each gender is subjected to domestic violence and whether abused men should be provided the same resources and shelters that exist for female victims. In particular, some studies suggest that men are less likely to report being victims of domestic violence due to social stigmas.&lt;ref name=dutton1&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1016/j.avb.2005.02.001}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Carney1&quot;&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1016/j.avb.2006.05.002}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other sources, however, argue that the rate of domestic violence against men is often inflated due to the practice of including self-defense as a form of domestic violence.&lt;ref name=Johnson2000&gt;{{cite doi|10.1111/j.1741-3737.2000.00948.x}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Dobash1992&gt;{{cite doi|10.1525/sp.1992.39.1.03x0064l}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Both men and women have been arrested and convicted of assaulting their partners in both heterosexual and homosexual relationships. The majority of these arrests have been men being arrested for assaulting women, though since the early-to-mid 1990s the number of women arrested has increased significantly, which is often attributed to the implementation of &quot;Must Arrest&quot; laws. However, the gender neutrality of the enforcement of domestic violence laws remains questionable.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reason.com/news/show/30529.html Domestic Violations]. Reason Magazine. Retrieved on 2011-12-23.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to a 2004 survey in Canada, the percentages of males being physically or sexually victimized by their partners was 6% versus 7% for women. However, females reported higher levels of repeated violence and were more likely than men to experience serious injuries; 23% of females versus 15% of males were faced with the most serious forms of violence including being beaten, choked, or threatened with or having a gun or knife used against them. Also, 21% of women versus 11% of men were likely to report experiencing more than 10 violent incidents. Women who often experience higher levels of physical or sexual violence from their current partner, were 44% versus only 18% of males to suffer from an injury. Cases in which women are faced with extremely abusive partners, results in the females having to fear for their lives due to the violence they had faced. In addition, statistics show that 34% of women feared for their lives whereas only 10% of males felt this way.&lt;ref name=grady&gt;O'Grady William (2011). Crime in Canadian Context: debates and controversies. Oxford University Press ISBN 0195433785.&lt;/ref&gt;

A problem in conducting studies that seek to describe violence in terms of gender is the amount of silence, fear and shame that results from abuse within families and relationships. Another is that abusive patterns can tend to seem normal to those who have lived in them for a length of time. Similarly, subtle forms of abuse can be quite transparent even as they set the stage for further abuse seeming normal. Finally, inconsistent definition of what constitutes domestic violence makes definite conclusions difficult to reach when compiling the available studies.

===Violence against women===
Although the exact rates are widely disputed, especially within the United States, there is a large body of cross-cultural evidence that women are subjected to domestic violence significantly more often than men.&lt;ref name=Dobash1992/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hamel2007&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Hamel|first=John|coauthors=Tonia L. Nicholls|title=Family Interventions in Domestic Violence: A Handbook of Gender-Inclusive Theory and Treatment|year=2007|publisher=Springer|location=New York|isbn=0-8261-0245-X|quote=...there is ample cross-cultural evidence of much higher rates of physical aggression and somewhat higher rates of verbal aggression by men.|page=6}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Compton2010&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Compton|first=Michael T.|title=Clinical Manual of Prevention in Mental Health|year=2010|publisher=American Psychiatric Publishing|location=Washington, D.C.|isbn=978-1-58562-347-1|page=245|edition=1st|quote=Women are more often the victims of domestic violence than men and are more likely to suffer injuries and health consequences...}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Brinkerhoff2008&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Brinkerhoff|first=David B.|coauthors=Lynn K. White, Suzanne T. Ortega, Rose Weitz|title=Essentials of Sociology|year=2008|publisher=Thomson/Wadsworth|isbn=0-495-09636-9|page=13|edition=7th|quote=A conflict analysis of domestic violence, for example, would begin by noting that women are battered far more often and far more severely than are men...}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, there is broad consensus that women are more often subjected to severe forms of abuse and are more likely to be injured by an abusive partner.&lt;ref name=&quot;Compton2010&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Brinkerhoff2008&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;FeibertLATimes&quot;/&gt;

According to a report by the [[United States Department of Justice]], a survey of 16,000 Americans showed 22.1% of women and 7.4% of men reported being physically assaulted by a current or former spouse, cohabiting partner, boyfriend or girlfriend, or date in their lifetime.&lt;ref name=Tjaden&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nij.gov/pubs-sum/183781.htm|title=Full Report of the Prevalence, Incidence, and Consequences of Violence Against Women|publisher=National Institute of Justice, United States Department of Justice|first1=Patricia|last1=Tjaden|first2=Nancy|last2=Thoennes|date=November 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2010 survey of over 21,000 residents of England and Wales by the UK [[Home Office]] showed that 7% of women and 3% of men were victims of domestic abuse in the last year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110218135832/http://rds.homeoffice.gov.uk/rds/pdfs11/hosb0111.pdf |title=Homicides, Firearm Offences and Intimate Violence 2009/10 |author=Kevin Smith (Ed.), Kathryn Coleman, Simon Eder and Philip Hall |year=2011 |publisher=Home Office |accessdate=December 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; A study in the United States found that women were 13 times more likely than men to seek medical attention due to injuries related to spousal abuse.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schwartz1987&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Schwartz|first=Martin D.|year=1987|title=Gender and injury in spousal assault|journal=Sociological Focus|volume=20|page=67|jstor=20831423}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Women are more likely than men to be murdered by an intimate partner. Of those killed by an intimate partner about three quarters are female and about a quarter are male. In 1999 in the United States 1,218 women and 424 men were killed by an intimate partner,&lt;ref name=&quot;usdoj1993&quot;&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20090414033235/http://www.ojp.usdoj.gov/bjs/pub/pdf/ipv01.pdf Intimate Partner Violence, 1993–2001]. U.S. Department of Justice. Bureau of Justice Statistics. Crime Data Brief. February 2003&lt;/ref&gt; and 1181 females and 329 males were killed by their intimate partners in 2005.&lt;ref name=&quot;cdc.gov&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cdc.gov/violencePrevention/intimatepartnerviolence/consequences.html |title=CDC&amp;nbsp;– Injury&amp;nbsp;– Intimate Partner Violence Consequences |publisher=Cdc.gov |date=2009-12-14 |accessdate=2010-04-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;theduluthmodel.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theduluthmodel.org/wheelgallery.php |title=Domestic Abuse Intervention Programs, Home of the Duluth Model |publisher=Theduluthmodel.org |accessdate=2010-04-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[England and Wales]] about 100 women are killed by partners or former partners each year while 21 men were killed in 2010.&lt;ref name=BBC&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-13058300 |title=All domestic abuse deaths to have multi-agency review |date=13 April 2011 |publisher=BBC |accessdate=14 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, in [[France]], 156 women and 27 men were killed by their intimate partner.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.interieur.gouv.fr/sections/a_votre_service/aide_aux_victimes/violence-couple/downloadFile/attachedFile/morts_violentes_au_sein_couples.pdfEtude Nationale sur les Morts Violentes au sien de Couple.] Ministère de l'Intérieur, Delegation aux Victimes. 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

The UN Declaration on the Elimination of Violence against Women (1993) states that &quot;[[violence against women]] is a manifestation of historically unequal power relations between men and women, which has led to domination over and discrimination against women by men and to the prevention of the full advancement of women, and that violence against women is one of the crucial social mechanisms by which women are forced into a subordinate position compared with men.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/documents/ga/res/48/a48r104.htm |title=A/RES/48/104. Declaration on the Elimination of Violence against Women |publisher=Un.org |accessdate=2010-04-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unfpa.org/rights/violence.htm |title=Addressing Gender-Based Violence: Advancing Human Rights |publisher=UNFPA |accessdate=2010-04-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In their study of severely violent couples, Neil Jacobson and John Gottman conclude that the ''frequency'' of violent acts is not as crucial as the impact of the violence and its function, when trying to understand spousal abuse; specifically, they state that the purpose of domestic violence is typically to control and intimidate, rather than just to injure.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first1=Neil S.|last1=Jacobson|first2=John M.|last2=Gottman|title=When Men Batter Women: New Insights into Ending Abusive Relationships|location=New York|publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster|year=1998|isbn=0-684-81447-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Violence against men===
Determining how many instances of domestic violence actually involve male victims is difficult. Male domestic violence victims may be reluctant to get help for a number of reasons.&lt;ref name=kumar&gt;{{cite doi|10.1080/10911359.2012.655988}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some studies have shown that women who assaulted their male partners were more likely to avoid arrest even when the male victim contacts police.&lt;ref&gt;Felson and Pare, (2007) p. 436&lt;/ref&gt; Another study examined the differences in how male and female batterers were treated by the criminal justice system. The study concluded that female intimate violence perpetrators are frequently viewed by law enforcement and the criminal justice system as victims rather than the actual offenders of violence against men.&lt;ref&gt;Kingsnorth and MacIntosh, (2007) p. 461&lt;/ref&gt; Other studies have also demonstrated a high degree of acceptance of aggression against men by women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first = Murray A.|last = Straus|title = Paper presented at conference on Trends in Intimate Violence Intervention|url = http://pubpages.unh.edu/~mas2/ID41H3a.pdf|year = 2006|place = New York University}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 32-nation study revealed that more than 51% of men and 52% of women felt that there were times when it was appropriate for a wife to slap her husband. By comparison, only 26% of men and 21% of women felt that there were times when it was appropriate for a husband to slap his wife. &lt;ref name=&quot;ASC&quot;&gt;[http://www.example.org Link Violence Socialization and approval of violence], American Society of Criminology, November 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

Studies have shown many police officers do not treat domestic violence against men as a serious crime, and often will view the male victim as a &quot;pathetic figure&quot;. It is for this reason, and also the view among many law enforcement officers that men are inherently &quot;stronger&quot; than women, that male victims are often less likely to report domestic violence than female victims. When and if they do, men are often treated as the aggressor in the situation, and often even placed under arrest.&lt;ref&gt;Hoyle, Carolyn; Young, Richard ''New Visions of Crime Victims'' (2002) pp. 94-96&lt;/ref&gt;

Some researchers have found a relationship between the availability of domestic violence services, improved laws and enforcement regarding domestic violence, increased access to divorce, and higher earnings for women with declines in intimate partner homicide by women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1177/1088767999003003001}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Theories that women are as violent as men have been dubbed &quot;gender symmetry&quot; theories.&lt;ref name=kumar/&gt;&lt;ref name=archer2000&gt;{{Cite pmid|10989615}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite pmid|10989617}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite pmid|10989616}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite pmid|10989618}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Johnson&quot;&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1111/j.1741-3737.2005.00204.x}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Straus and Gelles found that in couples reporting spousal violence, 27% of the time the man struck the first blow; in 24% of cases, the woman initiated the violence. The rest of the time, the violence was mutual, with both partners brawling. The results were the same even when the most severe episodes of violence were analyzed. In order to counteract claims that the reporting data was skewed, female-only surveys were conducted, asking females to self-report, and the data was the same.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Physical Violence in American Families|year=1995| publisher = Transaction Publishers |editor=Straus, M. A., Gelles, R. J. and Smith Ch. |isbn=1-56000-828-8 |page=105|url=http://books.google.com/?id=4_3nLMBoiTwC&amp;printsec=frontcover}}&lt;/ref&gt; The simple tally of physical acts is typically found to be similar in those studies that examine both directions, but some studies show that male violence may be more serious. Male violence may do more damage than female violence;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid|7696192}}&lt;/ref&gt; women are more likely to be injured and/or hospitalized. Wives are more likely to be killed by their husbands than the reverse (59% to 41% per Department of Justice study), and women in general are more likely to be killed by their spouses than by all other types of assailants combined.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Angela Browne and Kirk R. Williams|title=Exploring the Effect of Resource Availability and the Likelihood of Female-perpetrated Homicides|journal=Law and Society Review|volume= 23 |year=1989|pages=75–94|jstor=3053881|doi=10.2307/3053881|issue=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;  From a data set of 6,200 cases of spousal abuse in the Detroit area of USA in 1978-79 found that men used weapons 25% of the time while female assailants used weapons 86% of the time, 74% of men sustained injury and of these 84% required medical care. &lt;ref&gt;Women against men: An examination of domestic violence based on an analysis of official data and national victimization data, McLeod, M., Justice Quarterly, 1, 171-193&lt;/ref&gt;

Martin S. Fiebert of the Department of Psychology at [[California State University, Long Beach]], has compiled an annotated bibliography of research relating to spousal abuse by women on men. This bibliography examines 275 scholarly investigations: 214 empirical studies and 61 reviews and/or analyses that appear to demonstrate that women are as physically aggressive, or more aggressive, than men in their relationships with their spouses or male partners. The aggregate sample size in the reviewed studies exceeds 365,000.&lt;ref&gt;Fiebert, Martin S. [http://www.csulb.edu/~mfiebert/assault.htm ''References examining assaults by women on their spouses or male partners:an annotated bibliography'']&lt;/ref&gt; In a ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'' article about male victims of domestic violence, Fiebert suggests that &quot;...consensus in the field is that women are as likely as men to strike their partner but that—as expected—women are more likely to be injured than men.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;FeibertLATimes&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Parsons|first=Dana|title=Pitcher's Case Throws a Curve at Common Beliefs About Abuse|work=L.A. Times|url=http://www.csulb.edu/~mfiebert/latimes.htm|date=10 April 2002|accessdate=23 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, he noted, men are seriously injured in 38% of the cases in which &quot;extreme aggression&quot; is used. Fiebert additionally noted that his work was not meant to minimize the serious effects of men who abuse women.

In a review of the research however [[Michael Kimmel]] found that violence is instrumental in maintaining control and that more than 90% of &quot;systematic, persistent, and injurious&quot; violence is perpetrated by men. He points out that most of the empirical studies that Fiebert reviewed used the same empirical measure of family conflict, i.e., the [[Conflict Tactics Scale]] (CTS) as the sole measure of domestic violence and that many of the studies noted by Fiebert discussed samples composed entirely of single people younger than 30, not married couples.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ncjrs.gov/App/Publications/abstract.aspx?ID=198004 &quot;Gender Symmetry&quot; in Domestic Violence: A Substantive and Methodological Research Review] NCJRS Abstract.&lt;/ref&gt; Kimmel argues that among various other flaws, the CTS is particularly vulnerable to reporting bias because it depends on asking people to accurately remember and report what happened during the past year. Men tend to underestimate their use of violence, while women tend to overestimate their use of violence. Simultaneously men tend to overestimate their partner's use of violence while women tend to underestimate their partner's use of violence. Thus, men will likely overestimate their victimization, while women tend to underestimate theirs.&lt;ref&gt;Kimmel, Michael S. (2002) [http://www.ncdsv.org/images/male_DV_victims1.pdf Male Victims of Domestic Violence. Published as &quot;Gender Symmetry&quot; in Domestic Violence: A Substantive and Methodological Research Review] in ''Violence Against Women''.&lt;/ref&gt;

Similarly, the [[National Institute of Justice]] states that some studies finding equal or greater frequency of abuse by women against men are based on data compiled through the [[Conflict Tactics Scale]]. This survey tool was developed in the 1970s and may not be appropriate for intimate partner violence research because it does not measure control, coercion, or the motives for conflict tactics; it also leaves out sexual assault and violence by ex-spouses or partners and does not determine who initiated the violence. Furthermore, the [[NIJ]] contends that national surveys supported by NIJ, the [[Centers for Disease Control and Prevention]], and the [[Bureau of Justice Statistics]] that examine more serious assaults do not support the conclusion of similar rates of male and female spousal assaults. These surveys are conducted within a safety or crime context and clearly find more partner abuse by men against women.&lt;ref name=&quot;ojp.usdoj.gov&quot;&gt;[http://www.ojp.usdoj.gov/nij/topics/crime/intimate-partner-violence/measuring.htm ''Measuring Intimate Partner (Domestic) Violence''] National Institute of Justice. Retrieved 2011-11-18.&lt;/ref&gt; However more modern [[Centers for Disease Control and Prevention]] and other research reports that female perpetrated domestic abuse, is more common than male &lt;ref name=&quot;Straus&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;aphapublications2005&quot;/&gt;

In a Meta-analysis, John Archer, Ph. D., from the Department of Psychology, University of Central Lancashire, UK, writes:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The present analyses indicate that men are among those who are likely to be on the receiving end of acts of physical aggression.&lt;ref name=kumar/&gt; The extent to which this involves mutual combat or the male equivalent to &quot;battered women&quot; is at present unresolved. Both situations are causes for concern. Straus (1997) has warned of the dangers involved—especially for women—when physical aggression becomes a routine response to relationship conflict. &quot;Battered men&quot;—those subjected to systematic and prolonged violence—are likely to suffer physical and psychological consequences, together with specific problems associated with a lack of recognition of their plight (George and George, 1998). Seeking to address these problems need not detract from continuing to address the problem of &quot;battered women.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1016/S1359-1789(01)00061-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[Gender roles]] and expectations can and do play a role in abusive situations, and exploring these roles and expectations can be helpful in addressing abusive situations. Likewise, it can be helpful to explore factors such as race, class, religion, sexuality and philosophy. However, studies investigating whether sexist attitudes are correlated with domestic violence have shown conflicting results.&lt;ref&gt;Adkins, Katie S. (2010). [http://etd.ohiolink.edu/view.cgi/Adkins%20Katie%20S.pdf?osu1275494312 ''A Contextual Family Therapy Theory Explanation For Intimate Partner Violence.''] Doctoral Dissertation: Ohio State University.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Eades|first=Rebecca Ann|title=Ambivalent sexism as a predictor of severity of domestic violence by male offenders|year=2003|format=PhD thesis|publisher=University of Memphis|quote=Participants high in hostile sexism, paired with either low or high benevolent sexism, had significantly higher risk for offending against a family member in the upcoming year.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 1997 report says significantly more men than women do not disclose the identity of their attacker.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid|12295375}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2009 study showed that there was greater acceptance for abuse perpetrated by females than by males.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1111/j.1559-1816.2009.00492.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; Several studies have confirmed that women’s physical violence towards intimate male partners is sometimes in self-defense.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1080/02732173.1997.9982160}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid|7696193}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1177/107780120200800302}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid|9754498}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Norway, researcher Anja Bredal's opinion is that non-Norwegian men are being assaulted by their wives who are of the same ethnicity—who are Norwegian citizens.&lt;ref&gt;http://nrk.no/nyheter/distrikt/ostafjells/buskerud/1.8259684&lt;/ref&gt;

===Same-sex relationships===
Domestic violence also occurs in same-sex relationships. Gay and lesbian relationships have been identified as a risk factor for abuse in certain populations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Siemieniuk 2010 763–770&quot;/&gt; In an effort to be more inclusive, many organizations have made an effort to use gender-neutral terms when referring to perpetratorship and victimhood.

Historically, domestic violence has been seen as a family issue and little interest has been directed at violence in same-sex relationships.&lt;ref name=Aguinaldo&gt;Aguinaldo, Jeffrey (2000). [http://scholars.wlu.ca/etd/697/ Partner abuse in gay male relationships: Challenging 'we are family (M.A. thesis) Wilfrid Laurier University]&lt;/ref&gt; It has not been until recently, as the gay rights movement has brought the issues of gay and lesbian people into public attention, when research has been conducted on same-sex relationships. A 1999 analysis of nineteen studies of partner abuse concluded that &quot;[r]esearch suggests that lesbians and gay men are just as likely to abuse their partners as heterosexual men,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite pmid|10467488}}&lt;/ref&gt; although the study also noted the uncertain nature of much of the contemporary research in the area. Gays and lesbians, however, face special obstacles in dealing with the issues that some researchers have labeled &quot;the double closet&quot;. A recent Canadian study by Mark W. Lehman&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| last =Lehman
| first =Mark
| title =At the End of the Rainbow: A Report on Gay Male Domestic Violence and Abuse
| publisher =Minnesota Center Against Violence and Abuse
| year =1997
| url =http://www.mincava.umn.edu/documents/rainbow/At%20The%20End%20Of%20The%20Rainbow.pdf
| accessdate =2007-12-30 |format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; suggests similarities include frequency (approximately one in every four couples); manifestations (emotional, physical, financial, etc.); co-existent situations (unemployment, substance abuse, low self-esteem); victims' reactions (fear, feelings of helplessness, hypervigilance); and reasons for staying (love, can work it out, things will change, denial). At the same time, significant differences, unique issues and deceptive myths are typically present. Lehman points to added discrimination and fear gays and lesbians can face; dismissal by police and some social services; a lack of support from peers who would rather keep quiet about the problem in order not to attract negative attention toward the [[gay community]]; the impacts of HIV status or AIDS in keeping partners together, due to health care insurance/access, or guilt; outing used as a weapon; and encountering supportive services that are targeted and/or structured for the needs of heterosexual women and which may not meet the needs of gay men or lesbians. However Lehman himself noted that &quot;due to the limited number of returned responses and non-random sampling methodology the findings of this work are not generalizable beyond the sample&quot; of 32 initial respondents and final 10 who completed the more in-depth survey.

==Cycle of abuse==
{{Main|Cycle of abuse}}
Frequently, domestic violence is used to describe specific violent and overtly abusive incidents, and legal definitions will tend to take this perspective. However, when violent and abusive behaviours happen within a relationship, the effects of those behaviours continue after these overt incidents are over. Advocates and counsellors will refer to domestic violence as a pattern of behaviours, including those listed above.

[[Lenore Walker]] presented the model of a [[Cycle of abuse]] which consists of three basic phases:

; ''Tension Building Phase'': Characterized by poor communication, tension, fear of causing outbursts. During this stage the victims try to calm the abuser down, to avoid any major violent confrontations.
; ''Violent Episode'': Characterized by outbursts of violent, abusive incidents. During this stage the abuser attempts to dominate his/her partner(victim), with the use of domestic violence.
; ''Honeymoon Phase'': Characterized by affection, apology, and apparent end of violence. During this stage the abuser feels overwhelming feelings of remorse and sadness. Some abusers walk away from the situation, while others shower their victims with love and affection.

Although it is easy to see the outbursts of the Acting-out Phase as abuse, even the more pleasant behaviours of the Honeymoon Phase serve to perpetuate the abuse.

Many domestic violence advocates believe that the cycle of abuse theory is limited and does not reflect the realities of many men and women experiencing domestic violence.

==Management==
The response to domestic violence is typically a combined effort between law enforcement, social services, and health care. The role of each has evolved as domestic violence has been brought more into public view.

Domestic violence historically has been viewed as a private family matter that need not involve the government or [[criminal justice]].&lt;ref name=&quot;fagan1995&quot;&gt;{{cite conference |url=http://www.ncjrs.gov/pdffiles/crimdom.pdf |title=Criminalization of Domestic Violence: Promises and Limits |author=Fagan, Jeffrey |conference=Conference on Criminal Justice Research and Evaluation |year=1995 |booktitle=Research Report |publisher=National Institute of Justice|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Police officer]]s were often reluctant to intervene by making an [[arrest]], and often chose instead to simply counsel the couple and/or ask one of the parties to leave the residence for a period of time. The courts were reluctant to impose any significant sanctions on those convicted of domestic violence, largely because it was viewed as a [[misdemeanor]] offense.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}

Today domestic violence should be viewed as a public matter. All criminal authority should be involved. Now the offender is killing innocent people. Once the violence is reported it should be taken seriously. Domestic violence is never a private family matter any longer. Domestic violence should be viewed as criminal not viewed as a misdemeanor offense.  

===Medical response===
Medical professionals can make a difference in the lives of those who experience abuse. Many cases of spousal abuse are handled solely by physicians and do not involve the police. Sometimes cases of domestic violence are brought into the [[emergency room]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite pmid|14734366}}&lt;/ref&gt; while many other cases are handled by [[General practitioner|family physician]] or other [[primary care]] provider.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite pmid|10523218}}&lt;/ref&gt; Subspecialist physicians are also increasingly playing an important role. For example, HIV physicians are ideally suited to play an important role in managing abuse given the association between abuse and HIV infection as well as their often lifelong relationships with patients.&lt;ref name=&quot;Siemieniuk 2010 763–770&quot;/&gt;

Medical professionals are in position to empower people, give advice, and refer them to appropriate services. The health care professional has not always met this role, with uneven quality of care, and in some cases misunderstandings about domestic violence.&lt;ref name=&quot;Williamson-p83&quot;&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1080/095892399102841}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Washaw (1993) suggests that many doctors prefer not to get involved in people's &quot;private&quot; lives. Clifton, Jacobs, and Tulloch (1996) found that training for general practitioners in the United States about domestic violence was very limited or they had no training. Abbott and Williamson found that knowledge and understanding of domestic violence was very limited among health care professionals in a [[English Midlands|Midlands]], [[United Kingdom]] county, and that they do not see themselves as being able to play a major role in helping women in regards to domestic violence.&lt;ref name=&quot;Williamson-p83&quot; /&gt; Furthermore, in the biomedical model of health care, injuries are often just treated and diagnosed, without regard for the causes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Warshaw, C. |year=1993 |chapter=Limitations of the Medical Model in the Care of Battered Women |editors=Bart, P., E. Moran |title=Violence Against Women: The Bloody Footprints |publisher=Sage}}&lt;/ref&gt; As well, there is substantial reluctance for victims to come forward and broach the issue with their physicians.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite pmid|1593735}}&lt;/ref&gt; On average, women experience 35 incidents of domestic violence before seeking treatment.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1111/1468-2311.00238}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the U. S., the Institute of Medicine recognized the shortcomings of the health care system in its 2002 report entitled Confronting Chronic Neglect and attributed some of the problems cited to a lack of adequate training among health professionals.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|editors=Cohn, F, Salmon, ME, Stobo JD, |title=Confronting Chronic Neglect, the Education and Training of Health Professional on Family Violence |year=2002 |publisher=National Academy Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; Health professionals have an ethical responsibility to recognize and address exposure to abuse in their patients, in the health care setting. For example, the American Medical Association's code of medical ethics states that &quot;Due to the prevalence and medical consequences of family violence, physicians should routinely inquire about physical, sexual, and psychological abuse as part of the medical history. Physicians must also consider abuse in the differential diagnosis for a number of medical complaints, particularly when treating women.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ama-assn.org/ama/pub/physician-resources/medical-ethics/code-medical-ethics/opinion202.shtml |title=AMA&amp;nbsp;– Opinion 2.02&amp;nbsp;– Abuse of Spouses, Children, Elderly Persons}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Duluth model====
{{See also|Duluth model}}
{{unreferenced section|date=November 2011}}
In 1981, the Duluth Domestic Abuse Intervention Project became the first multi-disciplinary program designed to address the issue of domestic violence. This experiment, conducted in [[Duluth, Minnesota]], frequently referred to as the &quot;Duluth Project&quot; because it is constantly evolving through the help of an entire community.&lt;ref name=&quot;Home of the Duluth Model&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Home of the Duluth Model|url=http://www.theduluthmodel.org|accessdate=December 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It coordinated agencies dealing with domestic situations, drawing together diverse elements of the system, from police officers on the street, to shelters for battered women and [[probation officer]]s supervising offenders.

This program has become a model for other jurisdictions seeking to deal more effectively with domestic violence. Corrections/probation agencies in many areas are supervising domestic violence offenders more closely, and are also paying closer attention to the victim's needs and safety issues.

There has been controversy as the Duluth framework depends on a strict &quot;[[patriarchy|patriarchal]] violence&quot; model and presumes that all violence in the home and elsewhere has a male perpetrator and female victim. Also evidence of success of the model is limited, with scholarly analysis and critique.

Many victims leave their abusers, only to return. Research has shown that a major factor in helping a victim to establish lasting independence from the abusive partner is her or his ability to get legal assistance. Economists at the Brennan Center for Justice analyzed Bureau of Justice Statistics data to determine what accounted for the nationwide reduction in reported abuse. Their findings revealed that one significant factor was the availability of legal services to assist abuse victims. Another major study by economists at Colgate University and the University of Arkansas flatly stated that the only public service that reduces domestic violence in the long term is legal aid. Legal assistance can provide essential safety planning, buttress a family’s economic position through child or spousal support, allay fears planted by the batterer about loss of custody, and help victims to secure needed government benefits.

What the community has done using the Duluth approach:&lt;ref name=&quot;Home of the Duluth Model&quot;/&gt;
*Remove the blame from the victim and they have made the offender accountable for the abuse.
*Criminal and civil justice systems have created policies to hold offenders accountable and keep the victims safe.
*Use the experiences and voices from battered women to improve and create policies.
*Court-ordered educational groups are available for the offenders.
*Constantly reviewing and discussing current cases and policies.

The Domestic Abuse Intervention Program has federal, state and local funders who support them. This funding allows DAIP to explore strategies to end violence to communities throughout the United States and around the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;Home of the Duluth Model&quot;/&gt;

===Law enforcement===
In the 1970s, it was widely believed that domestic disturbance calls were the most dangerous type for responding officers, who arrive to a highly emotionally charged situation. This belief was based on FBI statistics which turned out to be flawed, in that they grouped all types of disturbances together with domestic disturbances, such as brawls at a bar. Subsequent statistics and analysis have shown this belief to be false.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Garner, J. and F. Clemmer |title=Danger to Police in Domestic Disturbances—A New Look |year=1986 |publisher=Bureau of Justice Statistics}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Stanford, M. R. and B. I. Mowry |title=Domestic Disturbance Danger Rate |journal=Journal of Police Science and Administration |year=1990 |volume=17 |pages=244–9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Statistics on incidents of domestic violence, published in the late 1970s, helped raise public awareness of the problem and increase [[activism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;fagan1995&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;straus1980&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Straus, M., Gelles, R., &amp; Steinmetz, S. |year=1980 |title=Behind Closed Doors: Violence in the American Family |publisher=Anchor/Doubleday |isbn=0-385-14259-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; A study published in 1976 by the Police Foundation found that the police had intervened at least once in the previous two years in 85% of spouse [[homicide]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Police Foundation|year=1976|title=Domestic Violence and the Police: Studies in Detroit and Kansas City|publisher=The Police Foundation}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the late 1970s and early 1980s, [[feminism|feminists]] and battered women's advocacy groups were calling on police to take domestic violence more seriously and change intervention strategies.&lt;ref name=&quot;gelles1993&quot;&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1177/0002764293036005003}}&lt;/ref&gt; In some instances, these groups took legal action against police departments, including [[Los Angeles]]'s, [[Oakland, California]]'s and [[New York City]]'s, to get them to make arrests in domestic violence cases.&lt;ref name=&quot;sherman1984-pf&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|url= http://www.policefoundation.org/pdf/minneapolisdve.pdf|title=The Minneapolis Domestic Violence Experiment|year=1984 |author=Sherman, Lawrence W. and Richard A. Berk |publisher=Police Foundation |accessdate=2007-06-12|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; They claimed that police assigned low priority to domestic disturbance calls.&lt;ref&gt;Straus (1980), and references below, &quot;Criticism of police response&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Minneapolis Domestic Violence Experiment]] was a study done in 1981–1982, led by [[Lawrence W. Sherman]], to evaluate the effectiveness of various [[police]] responses to domestic violence calls in [[Minneapolis, Minnesota]], including sending the abuser away for eight hours, giving advice and mediation for disputes, and making an arrest. Arrest was found to be the most effective police response. The study found that arrest reduced the rate by half of [[recidivism|re-offending]] against the same victim within the following six months.&lt;ref name=&quot;maxwell-RiB&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Maxwell, Christopher D., Garner, Joel H., Fagan, Jefferey A. |title=The effects of arrest on intimate partner violence: New evidence from the spouse assault replication program (Research in Brief) |publisher=National Institute of Justice|year=2001 |url=http://www.ncjrs.gov/pdffiles1/nij/188199.pdf |format=PDF |id={{NCJ|188199}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; The results of the study received a great deal of attention from the news media, including ''[[The New York Times]]'' and prime-time news coverage on television.&lt;ref name=&quot;buzawa&quot; /&gt;

Many U.S. police departments responded to the study, adopting a mandatory arrest policy for spousal violence cases with [[probable cause]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Elliott, Delbert S. |chapter=Criminal Justice Procedures in Family Violence Crimes |editor=Oblin, Lloyd and Michael Tonry |title=Family Violence. Crime and Justice: A Review of Research |pages=427–80 |publisher=University of Chicago |year=1989}}&lt;/ref&gt; By 2005, 23 states and the District of Columbia had enacted mandatory arrest for domestic assault, without warrant, given that the officer has probable cause and regardless of whether or not the officer witnessed the crime.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Hoctor, M. |title=Domestic Violence as a Crime against the State |journal=California Law Review |volume=85 |year=1997 |page=643 |doi=10.2307/3481154 |issue=3 |publisher=California Law Review, Inc. |jstor=3481154|pages=643–700}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Minneapolis study also influenced policy in other countries, including [[New Zealand]], which adopted a pro-arrest policy for domestic violence cases.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://www.justice.govt.nz/publications/global-publications/f/family-violence-and-the-pro-arrest-policy-a-literature-review-december-2006/2-historical-development-of-the-pro-arrest-policy-in-new-zealand|title=Family violence and the pro-arrest policy: a literature review |chapter=Historical development of the pro-arrest policy|publisher=New Zealand Ministry of Justice |author=Carswell, Sue|year=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, the study was subject of much criticism, with concerns about its methodology, as well as its conclusions.&lt;ref name=&quot;buzawa&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Buzawa, E. S., and C. G. Buzawa|title=Domestic Violence: The Criminal Justice Response|publisher=Sage|year=1990 |pages=94–9 |isbn=0-7619-2448-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Minneapolis study was replicated in several other cities, beginning in 1986, with some of these studies having different results; one of which being the fact that the deterrent effect observed in the Minneapolis experiment was largely localized.&lt;ref name=&quot;schmidt1993&quot; /&gt; In the replication studies which were far more broad and methodologically sound in both size and scope, arrest seemed to help in the short run in certain cases, but those arrested experienced double the rate of violence over the course of one year.&lt;ref name=&quot;schmidt1993&quot;&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1177/0002764293036005005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Criminologist]]s do not fully understand the reasons why deterrent effects do not last over time. But they suggest that abusers who are employed and have ties to the community may initially fear punishment, though many cases do not make it all the way through the criminal justice process. If the victim is uncooperative during investigation, the [[prosecutor]] may choose not to pursue the case.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1080/07418820100095031}}&lt;/ref&gt; If the case is pursued through the criminal justice system, sometimes the resulting [[sentence (law)|sentence]] is minor. Subsequently, any fear that the abuser has of punishment may have diminished.&lt;ref name=&quot;siegel-p126&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Siegel, Larry J. |title=Criminology, 8th edition |year=2003 |publisher=Thomson-Wadsworth |pages=126–7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Each agency and jurisdiction within the United States has its own Standard Operating Procedures (SOP) when it comes to responding and handling domestic calls. Generally, it has been accepted that if the understood victim has visible (and recent) marks of abuse, the suspect is arrested and charged with the appropriate crime. However, that is a guideline and not a rule. Like any other call, domestic abuse lies in a gray area. Law enforcement officers have several things to consider when making a warrantless arrest:
*Are there signs of physical abuse?
*Were there witnesses?
*Is it recent?
*Was the victim assaulted by the alleged suspect?
*Who is the primary aggressor?
*Could the victim be lying?
*Could the suspect be lying?

Along with protecting the victim, law enforcement officers have to ensure that the alleged abusers' rights are not violated. Many times in cases of mutual combatants, it is departmental policy that both parties be arrested and the court system can establish truth at a later date. In some areas of the nation, this mutual combatant philosophy is being replaced by the primary abuser philosophy in which case if both parties have physical injuries, the law enforcement officer determines who the primary aggressor is and only arrests that one. This philosophy started gaining momentum when different government/private agencies started researching the effects. It was found that when both parties are arrested, it had an adverse effect on the victim. The victims were less likely to call or trust law enforcement during the next incident of domestic abuse.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mnadv.org/index.html Maryland Network Against Domestic Violence]. Mnadv.org. Retrieved on 2011-12-23.&lt;/ref&gt;{{Page needed|date=September 2010}}

In Spain, the 2004 &quot;The Organic Act on Integrated Protection Measures against Gender Violence&quot; established Courts of &quot;Violence against Women.&quot; Spanish Courts may allow to hear the case behind closed doors and that proceedings should not be made public, order a person accused of gender violence to leave the abode he shared with his victim, suspend the alleged perpetrator of acts of gender violence from exercising parental authority, custody or guardianship with regard to the minors he or she specifies, and may order the suspension of the right to possess weapons.&lt;ref&gt;[http://noticias.juridicas.com/base_datos/Admin/lo1-2004.t5.html#c4 Ley Orgánica 1/2004, de 28 de diciembre, de Medidas de Protección Integral contra la Violencia de Género]. Noticias.juridicas.com (2011-01-21). Retrieved on 2011-12-23.&lt;/ref&gt;

It was announced on April 13, 2011 that all homicides resulting from domestic abuse in England and Wales will be subject to a multi-agency review involving the police and health services, local authorities, probation, voluntary groups and any other bodies connected to a victim. Director of Public Prosecutions [[Keir Starmer]] pointed out that the survey shows young women between the ages of sixteen and nineteen at highest risk of domestic abuse, saying &quot;What that tends to show is that there may be a next generation of domestic violence waiting in the wings. Domestic violence is serious and pernicious. It ruins lives, breaks up families and has a lasting impact.&quot;&lt;ref name=BBC/&gt; In England and Wales there is no specific offence of domestic violence and incidents are prosecuted under generally applicable legislation. However, when an offence is committed in a domestic context, specific aggravating factors commonly arise.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://sentencingcouncil.judiciary.gov.uk/docs/web_domestic_violence.pdf |title=Overarching Principles: Domestic Violence |publisher=[[Sentencing Guidelines Council]] |accessdate=1 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Counseling for person affected===
Due to the extent and prevalence of violence in relationships, counselors and therapists should assess every client for domestic violence (both experienced and perpetrated). If the clinician is seeing a couple for couple’s counseling, this assessment should be conducted with each individual privately during the initial interview, in order to increase the victim’s sense of safety in disclosing DV in the relationship.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lawson 2003 19–33&quot;&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1002/j.1556-6678.2003.tb00221.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to determining whether DV is present, counselors and therapists should also make the distinction between situations where battering may have been a single, isolated incident or an ongoing pattern of control. The therapist must, however, consider that domestic violence may be present even when there has been only a single physical incident as emotional/verbal, economic, and sexual abuse may be more insidious.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lawson 2003 19–33&quot;/&gt;

Another important issue in assessing clients for DV lies in differing definitions of abuse&amp;nbsp;– the therapist’s definition may differ from that of the client, and paying close attention to the way the client describes their experiences is crucial in developing effective treatment plans. The therapist must determine if it is in the best interest of the client to explain that some behaviors (such as emotional abuse) are considered domestic violence, even if the client did not previously consider them as such.

If it becomes apparent to the therapist that domestic violence is taking place in a client’s relationship, there are several statements the clinician can make that have been shown to be effective in rapport-building and immediate crisis intervention with clients. Firstly, it is essential that the therapist believe the victim’s story and validate their feelings. It is recommended that the therapist acknowledge them for taking a risk in disclosing this information, and assure them that any ambivalent feelings they may be having are normal. The therapist should emphasize that the abuse they have experienced is not their fault, but should keep their feelings of ambivalence in mind and refrain from blaming their partner or telling them what to do. It is unreasonable for the therapist to expect that a victim will leave their perpetrator solely because they disclosed the abuse, and the therapist should respect the victim’s autonomy and allow them to make their own decisions regarding termination of the relationship. Finally, the therapist must explore options with the client (such as emergency housing in shelters, police involvement, etc.) in order to uphold their obligation to protect the welfare of the client.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lawson 2003 19–33&quot;/&gt;

====Lethality assessment====
A lethality assessment is a tool that can assist in determining the best course of treatment for a client, as well as helping the client to recognize dangerous behaviors and more subtle abuse in their relationship.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite pmid|16049107}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a study of victims of attempted domestic violence-related homicide, only about one-half of the participants recognized that their perpetrator was capable of killing them, as many domestic violence victims minimize the true seriousness of their situation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1300/J146v05n02_08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, lethality assessment is an essential first step in assessing the severity of a victim’s situation.

====Safety planning====
Safety planning allows the victim to plan for dangerous situations they may encounter, and is effective regardless of their decision on whether remain with their perpetrator. Safety planning usually begins with determining a course of action if another acute incident occurs in the home. The victim should be given strategies for their own safety, such as avoiding confrontations in rooms where there is only one exit and avoiding certain rooms that contain many potential weapons (such as kitchens, bathrooms, etc.).&lt;ref name=&quot;azcadv.org&quot;/&gt;

===Counseling for offenders===
The main goal for treatment for offenders of domestic violence is to minimize the offender’s risk of future domestic violence, whether within the same relationship or a new one. Treatment for offenders should emphasize minimizing risk to the victim, and should be modified depending on the offender’s history, risk of reoffending, and criminogenic needs.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
|last = Andrews
|first = D
|coauthors = Bonta
|title = The psychology of criminal conduct.
|publisher = Anderson Publishing Co
|year = 1994
|location = Cincinnati, OH
|isbn = 0-87084-712-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; The majority of offender treatment programs are 24–36 weeks in length and are conducted in a group setting with groups not exceeding 12 participants.&lt;ref name=&quot;Colorado Domestic Violence Offender Management Board 2010&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|last = Colorado Domestic Violence Offender Management Board
|title = Standards for Treatment with Court Ordered Domestic Violence Offenders
|work = Revised 5.0 offender treatment standards
| year = 2010
|url = http://dcj.state.co.us/odvsom/Domestic_Violence/DV_Pdfs/5.0%20Draft%20CURRENT%20021810.pdf
| accessdate = May 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Groups are also standardized to be gender specific (male offenders only or female offenders only). It has been demonstrated that domestic violence offenders maintain a socially acceptable façade to hide abusive behavior, and therefore accountability is the recommended focus of offender treatment programs. Successful completion of treatment is generally associated with old age, higher levels of education, lower reported drug use, non-violent criminal histories, and longer intimate relationships.&lt;ref name=Pollard&gt;Pollard, Carrie (2004). ''[http://scholars.wlu.ca/etd/171/ Examining predictors of level of attendance in a group treatment program for men who abuse]'' (M.A. thesis) Wilfrid Laurier University&lt;/ref&gt; [[Anger management]] alone has not been shown to be effective in treating domestic violence offenders, as domestic violence is based on power and control and not on problems with regulating anger responses.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
|last = Roberts
|first = A
|title = Handbook of domestic violence intervention strategies: Policies, programs, and legal remedies
|publisher = Oxford University Press
|year = 2002
|location = New York
|isbn = 0-19-515170-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Anger management is recommended as a part of an offender treatment curriculum that is based on accountability, along with topics such as recognizing abusive patterns of behavior and re-framing communication skills. Treatment of offenders involves more than the cessation of abusive behaviour; it also requires a great deal of personal change and the construction of a self-image that is separate from former behaviour while still being held accountable for it.&lt;ref name=Bidgood&gt;Bidgood, Bruce Alan (1999). ''[http://scholars.wlu.ca/etd/222/ The social construction of a nonabuser image: A study of a post-treatment male abuser self-help group]'' (M.A. thesis) Wilfrid Laurier University&lt;/ref&gt; Any corresponding problems should also be addressed as part of domestic violence offender treatment, such as problems with substance abuse or other mental illness.&lt;ref name=&quot;Colorado Domestic Violence Offender Management Board 2010&quot;/&gt;

===Prevention and intervention===
[[File:Get Away by Latasha Lee (lyrics onscreen).ogg|thumb|right| education sample]]
There are many community organizations which work to prevent domestic violence by offering safe [[Women's shelter|shelter]], [[crisis intervention]], advocacy, and education and prevention programs. Community screening for domestic violence can be more systematic in cases of animal abuse, healthcare settings, emergency departments, behavioral health settings and court systems. Tools are being developed to facilitate domestic violence screening such as mobile apps.&lt;ref&gt;[http://mobihealthnews.com/13989/app-to-help-physicians-screen-for-domestic-abuse/ app to help physicians screen for domestic abuse]. Mobihealthnews.com (2011-10-20). Retrieved on 2011-12-23.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/r3-app/id491452316?mt=8 The R3 app and reviews, publisher apple.com, Retrieved on 2012-02-11]. Itunes.apple.com (2012-04-23). Retrieved on 2012-06-25.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Pregnancy==
{{Main|Domestic violence and pregnancy}}
[[Pregnancy]], when coupled with Domestic violence, may amplify health risks. Abuse during pregnancy, whether physical, verbal or emotional, produces adverse effects for both the mother and fetus. Domestic violence during pregnancy is categorized as abusive behavior towards a pregnant woman, where the pattern of abuse can often change in terms of severity and frequency of violence. Abuse may be a long-standing problem in a relationship that continues after a woman becomes pregnant or it may commence in pregnancy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid|12628266}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although female-to-male partner violence occurs in these settings, the overwhelming form of domestic violence is perpetrated by men against women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid|18853639}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Domestic abuse can be triggered by pregnancy for a number of reasons. Pregnancy itself can be used a form of coercion and the phenomenon of preventing an intimate partner’s reproductive choice is referred to as [[birth control sabotage]], or reproductive coercion. Studies on the birth control sabotage performed by males against female partners have indicated a strong correlation between domestic violence and birth control sabotage.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.impactresearch.org/documents/birthcontrolexecutive.pdf Domestic Violence and Birth Control Sabotage: A Report from the Teen Parent Project], Center for Impact Research, 1999.&lt;/ref&gt; Pregnancy can also lead to a hiatus of domestic violence when the abuser does not want to harm the unborn child. The risk of domestic violence for pregnant women is greatest immediately after [[childbirth]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1136/bmj.314.7090.1295}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010, the U.S. [[Centers for Disease Control and Prevention]] found that 4.8% of women reported having had an intimate partner who tried to get them pregnant when they did not want to while 8.7% of men reported having had an intimate partner who tried to get pregnant when they did not want to or tried to stop them from using birth control.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cdc.gov/ViolencePrevention/pdf/NISVS_Report2010-a.pdf National Intimate Partner and Sexual Violence Survey: 2010 Summary Report], Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, p. 48.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prognosis==
New research illustrates that there are strong associations between exposure to domestic violence and abuse in all their forms and higher rates of many chronic conditions. The strongest evidence comes from the Adverse Childhood Experiences' series of studies which show correlations between exposure to abuse or neglect and higher rates in adulthood of chronic conditions, high risk health behaviors and shortened life span.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Middlebrooks JS, Audage AC, |title=The Effects of Childhood Stress on Health Across the Lifespan |year=2008 |publisher=Centers for Disease Control}}&lt;/ref&gt; Evidence of the association between physical health and violence against women has been accumulating since the early 1990s.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite pmid|1341588}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, it is important to consider the effect of domestic violence and its psychophysiologic sequelae on women who are mothers of infants and young children. Several studies have shown that maternal interpersonal violence-related posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD) can, despite traumatized mother's best efforts, interfere with their child's response to the domestic violence and other traumatic events.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite pmid|18985165}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite pmid|18007959}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, practitioners and service agencies addressing the needs of domestic violence victims should assess the victim-as-parent and evaluate the safety and well-being of children in the home.

More recently work by such researchers as Corso&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite pmid|17533062}}&lt;/ref&gt; have begun to quantify the economic impact of exposure to violence and abuse. A recent publication, ''Hidden Costs in Health Care: The Economic Impact of Violence and Abuse, ''&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Dolezal T, McCollum D, Callahan M |title=Hidden Costs in Health Care: The Economic Impact of Violence and Abuse |year=20098 |publisher=Academy on Violence and Abuse}}&lt;/ref&gt; makes the case that such exposure represents a serious and costly public health issue that should be addressed by the health care system.

==Epidemiology==
{{Main|Epidemiology of domestic violence}}

Domestic violence occurs across the world, in various cultures,&lt;ref name=&quot;watts2002&quot;&gt;{{Cite pmid|11955557}}&lt;/ref&gt; and affects people of all economic statuses.&lt;ref name=&quot;waits1985&quot;/&gt; According to one study, the percentage of women who have reported being physically abused by an intimate partner vary from 69% to 10% depending on the country.&lt;ref&gt;Heise, Lori; Ellsberg, Mary; Gottemoeller, Megan. 1999. &quot;Ending Violence Against Women.&quot; Population Reports, Series L. No. 11.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[United States]], according to the Bureau of Justice Statistics in 1995 women reported a six times greater rate of intimate partner violence than men.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;[http://www.csulb.edu/~mfiebert/assault.htm References Examining Assaults By Women On Their Spouses Or Male Partners: An Annotated Bibliography]. Csulb.edu. Last updated: May 2011. Retrieved on 2011-12-23.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ncj154348&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|url=http://bjs.ojp.usdoj.gov/content/pub/pdf/FEMVIED.PDF|title=Violence against Women: Estimates from the Redesigned Survey |author=Bachman, Ronet and Linda E. Saltzman |publisher=Bureau of Justice Statistics|year=1995 |format=PDF{{ncj|154348}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[National Crime Victimization Survey]] (NCVS) indicates that in 1998 about 876,340 violent crimes were committed in the U.S. against women by their current or former spouses, or boyfriends.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.mmc.edu/www.meharry.org/Fl/Women%27s_Health/Domestic_Violence.html Domestic Violence]&quot;, Meharry Medical College.&lt;/ref&gt; According to the [[Centers for Disease Control and Prevention|Centers for Disease Control]], in the United States 4.8 million women suffer intimate partner related physical assaults and rapes and 2.9 million men are victims of physical assault from their partners.&lt;ref name=CDC2011&gt;{{cite web|title=Understanding Intimate Partner Violence|url=http://www.cdc.gov/ViolencePrevention/pdf/IPV_factsheet-a.pdf|publisher=Centers for Disease Control and Prevention|accessdate=7 September 2011|page=1|year=2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; However studies have found that men are much less likely to report victimization in these situations.&lt;ref name=Gender07&gt;{{Cite book|author=Tonia L. Nicholls; Hamel, John |title=Family interventions in domestic violence: a handbook of gender-inclusive theory and treatment |publisher=Springer Pub |location=New York |year=2007 |pages=5–6 |isbn=0-8261-0245-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to some studies, less than 1% of domestic violence cases are reported to the police.&lt;ref name=Roberts2007&gt;{{cite book|title=Social work in juvenile and criminal justice settings|year=2007|publisher=Charles C Thomas|location=Springfield, Illinois|isbn=978-0-398-07676-4|page=270|edition=3rd|editor1-first=Albert R.|editor1-last=Roberts|editor2-first=David W.|editor2-last=Springer}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Sigler|first=Robert T.|title=Domestic violence in context: an assessment of community attitudes|year=1989|publisher=Lexington Books|location=Lexington, Mass.|isbn=0-669-20936-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[United States]] 10–35% of the population will be physically aggressive towards a partner at some point in their lives.&lt;ref name=straus&gt;Straus, M. A. (1999). The controversy over domestic violence by women: A methodological, theoretical, and sociology of science analysis. In X. B.Arriaga &amp; S.Oskamp (Eds.), Violence in intimate relationships (pp. 17–44). Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Archer |first1=John|year=2000|title=Sex differences in aggression between heterosexual partners: A meta-analytic review |journal=Psychological Bulletin |volume=126 |issue=5 |pages=651–680|doi=10.1037/0033-2909.126.5.651 |quote= Meta-analyses of sex differences in physical aggression to heterosexual partners and in its physical consequences are reported. Women were slightly more likely (d = –.05) than men to use one or more acts of physical aggression and to use such acts more frequently. Men were more likely (d = .15) to inflict an injury, and overall, 62% of those injured by a partner were women. |pmid=10989615}}
*{{cite journal |last1=O'Leary|first1=K. Daniel|year=2000|title=Are women really more aggressive than men in intimate relationships? Comment on Archer |journal=Psychological Bulletin |volume=126 |issue=5 |pages=681–684 |doi=10.1037/0033-2909.126.5.685 |quote=J. Archer's conclusion that women engage in slightly more physical aggression than men in intimate relationships but sustain more injuries is reasonable in representative samples. |pmid=10989617}}
*{{cite journal |last1=Frieze|first1=Irene|year=2000|title=Violence in close relationships—development of a research area: Comment on Archer (2000) |journal=Psychological Bulletin |volume=126 |issue=5 |pages=681–684 |doi=10.1037/0033-2909.126.5.681|quote=Assumptions of and conclusions made by feminist researchers about the problems of battered wives are reviewed. It is argued that their focus on marital violence as a form of aggression against women by men and their concern for severely beaten wives may have caused them to ignore high levels of female violence in marriage and dating. J. Archer's meta-analysis of studies of marital and dating violence showed that both sexes display violence in these relationships, although women are more likely to be injured. |pmid=10989616}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://csulb.edu/~mfiebert/assault.htm |title=References examining assaults by women on their spouses or male partners: an annotated bibliography |last1=Fiebert |first1=Martin |date=May 2011 |publisher=California State University |accessdate=13 October 2011 |quote=This bibliography examines 282 scholarly investigations: 218 empirical studies and 64 reviews and/or analyses, which demonstrate that women are as physically aggressive, or more aggressive, than men in their relationships with their spouses or male partners. The aggregate sample size in the reviewed studies exceeds 369,800.}}&lt;/ref&gt; As abuse becomes more severe women become increasingly overrepresented as victims.&lt;ref name=straus/&gt;

Fighting the prevalence of domestic violence in [[Kashmir]] has brought [[Hindu]] and [[Muslim]] activists together.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.independent.co.uk/news/appeals/indy-appeal/independent-appeal-safe-haven-for-women-beaten-and-abused-in-kashmir-1851473.html Independent Appeal: Safe haven for women beaten and abused in Kashmir]&quot;. The Independent. December 28, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, aspects of [[Sharia|Islamic law]] have been criticized for promoting domestic violence&lt;ref&gt;Constable, Pamela. [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/05/07/AR2007050701936.html?hpid=topnews &quot;For Some Muslim Wives, Abuse Knows No Borders.&quot;] ''[[Washington Post]]'' (May 8, 2007).&lt;/ref&gt; One study found that half of [[Palestinian people|Palestinian]] women have been the victims of domestic violence.&lt;ref&gt;Alexander, Doug. [http://www.idrc.ca/en/ev-5311-201-1-DO_TOPIC.html &quot;Addressing Violence Against Palestinian Women&quot;.] [[International Development Research Centre]] (June 23, 2000).&lt;/ref&gt; 80% of women surveyed in rural [[Egypt]] said that beatings were common and often justified, particularly if the woman refused to have sex with her husband.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.afrol.com/Categories/Women/wom003_violence_unfpa.htm Widespread violence against women in Africa documented]. Source: [[UNFPA]].&lt;/ref&gt; The Human Rights Watch found that up to 90% of women in [[Pakistan]] were subject to some form of maltreatment, within their own homes.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.irinnews.org/Report.aspx?ReportId=77226 PAKISTAN: Domestic violence endemic, but awareness slowly rising]&quot;. [[IRIN]] [[UN]]. March 11, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Unofficial statistics estimate that 97% of Indian women experience violence at some point in their lives.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://web.archive.org/web/20110629021732/http://www.time.com/time/international/1995/950911/women.india.html Women: killed by greed and oppression]&quot;. TIME Magazine. September 11, 1995 Volume 146, No. 11&lt;/ref&gt; Up to two-thirds of women in certain communities in [[Nigeria]]'s [[Lagos State]] say they are victims to domestic violence.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.afrol.com/articles/16471 Half of Nigeria's women experience domestic violence]&quot;. Afrol News.&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Turkey]] 42% of women over 15 have suffered physical or sexual violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.economist.com/node/18682644?story_id=18682644|work=The Economist|title=Behind the veil|date=2011-05-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Statistics published in 2004, show that the rate of domestic violence victimisation for [[Indigenous Australians|Indigenous]] women in [[Australia]] may be 40 times the rate for non-Indigenous women.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.aph.gov.au/library/intguide/sp/Dom_violence.htm Domestic Violence in Australia—an Overview of the Issues]&quot;. Parliamentary Library.&lt;/ref&gt; In Canada, the Assembly of First Nations evaluation of the Canada Prenatal Nutrition Program conducted by CIET offers an inclusive and relatively unbiased national estimate. It documented domestic violence in a random sample of 85 First Nations across Canada: 22% (523/2359) of mothers reported suffering abuse in the year prior to being interviewed; of these, 59% reported physical abuse.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Andersson N, Nahwegahbow A | year = 2010 | title = Family violence and the need for prevention research in First Nations, Inuit and Métis communities. Pimatisiwin | journal = Journal of Aboriginal and Indigenous Community Health | volume = 8 | issue = 2| pages = 9–33 | pmc=2962655 | pmid=20975851}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Turkey]] 42% of women over 15 have suffered physical or sexual violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.economist.com/node/18682644?story_id=18682644&amp;CFID=170558324&amp;CFTOKEN=84234480|work=The Economist|title=Behind the veil|date=2011-05-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Results of studies which estimate the prevalence of domestic violence vary significantly, depending on specific wording of survey questions, how the survey is conducted, the definition of abuse or domestic violence used, the willingness or unwillingness of victims to admit that they have been abused and other factors. For instance, Straus (2005) conducted a study which estimated that the rate of minor assaults by women in the United States was 78 per 1,000 couples, compared with a rate for men of 72 per 1,000 and the severe assault rate was 46 per 1,000 couples for assaults by women and 50 per 1,000 for assaults by men. Neither difference is statistically significant. He claimed that since these rates were based exclusively on information provided by women respondents, the near-equality in assault rates could not be attributed to a gender bias in reporting.&lt;ref name=&quot;Straus, 2005&quot;&gt;Straus, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

One analysis found that &quot;women are as physically aggressive or more aggressive than men in their relationships with their spouses or male partners&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot; /&gt; However, studies have shown that women are more likely to be injured. Archer's meta-analysis&lt;ref name=archer2000/&gt; found that women in the United States suffer 65% of domestic violence injuries. A Canadian study showed that 7% of women and 6% of men were abused by their current or former partners, but female victims of spousal violence were more than twice as likely to be injured as male victims, three times more likely to fear for their life, twice as likely to be stalked, and twice as likely to experience more than ten incidents of violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.cbc.ca/canada/story/2005/07/14/domestic-violence-050714.html |title=CBC News&amp;nbsp;– Canada&amp;nbsp;– Domestic violence rate unchanged, Statistics Canada finds |publisher=Cbc.ca |date=2005-07-14 |accessdate=2010-04-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, Straus notes that Canadian studies on domestic violence have simply excluded questions that ask men about being victimized by their wives.&lt;ref name=&quot;Straus, 2005&quot;/&gt;

Some studies show that lesbian relationships have similar levels of violence as heterosexual relationships.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.musc.edu/vawprevention/lesbianrx/factsheet.shtml Fact Sheet: Lesbian Partner Violence]. Musc.edu. Retrieved on 2011-12-23.&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
[[File:Grandville Cent Proverbes page69.png|thumb|right|An illustration from [[Jean Ignace Isidore Gérard|JJ Grandville]]'s ''Cent Proverbes'' (1845) captioned &quot;Qui aime bien châtie bien&quot; (''Who loves well, punishes well'').]]
Prior to the mid 1800s, most legal systems accepted wife beating as a valid exercise of a husband's authority over his wife.&lt;ref name=Britannica&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|title=Domestic violence|encyclopedia=Encyclopedia Britannica Online|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/168589/domestic-violence|accessdate=October 31, 2011|quote=In the early 1800s most legal systems implicitly accepted wife-beating as a husband’s right, part of his entitlement to control over the resources and services of his wife.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Daniels1997&gt;{{cite book|last=Daniels|first=Cynthia R.|title=Feminists Negotiate the State: The Politics of Domestic Violence|year=1997|publisher=Univ. Press of America|location=Lanham|isbn=0-7618-0884-1|pages=5–10}}&lt;/ref&gt; One exception, however, was the 1641 [[Massachusetts Body of Liberties|Body of Liberties of the Massachusetts Bay colonists]], which declared that a married woman should be &quot;free from bodilie correction or stripes by her husband.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://history.hanover.edu/texts/masslib.html The Massachusetts Body of Liberties (1641)] at Hanover Historical Texts Project.&lt;/ref&gt;

Political agitation during the nineteenth century led to changes in both popular opinion and legislation regarding domestic violence within the [[United Kingdom]] and the [[United States]].&lt;ref name=Britannica&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|title=Domestic violence|encyclopedia=Encyclopedia Britannica Online|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/168589/domestic-violence|accessdate=October 31, 2011|quote=Feminist agitation in the 1800s produced a sea change in public opinion...}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Gordon2002&gt;{{cite book|last=Gordon|first=Linda|title=Heroes of Their Own Lives: The Politics and History of Family Violence|year=2002|publisher=University of Illinois Press|location=Urbana|isbn=0-252-07079-8|pages=253–255}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1850, Tennessee became the first state in the United States to explicitly outlaw wife beating.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Kleinberg|first=S. J.|title=Women in the United States, 1830–1945|year=1999|publisher=Rutgers University Press|isbn=0-8135-2729-5|page=143}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Pleck1989&gt;{{cite journal|last=Pleck|first=Elizabeth|title=Criminal Approaches to Family Violence|journal=Family Violence|year=1989|volume=11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other states soon followed suit.&lt;ref name=Daniels1997/&gt;&lt;ref name=Pleck1979&gt;{{cite journal|last=Pleck|first=Elizabeth|title=Wife Beating in Nineteenth-Century America|journal=Victimology: an International Journal|year=1979|volume=4|pages=64–65}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1878, the [[Matrimonial Causes Act]] made it possible for women in the UK to seek separations from abusive husbands.&lt;ref name=Arnot2003&gt;{{cite book|last=Arnot|first=Margaret L.|title=Gender and crime in modern Europe|year=2003|publisher=Routledge|location=London|isbn=1-85728-746-0|edition=[Online-Ausg.]|coauthors=Usborne, Cornelie|page=123}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of the 1870s, most courts in the United States were uniformly opposed to the right of husbands to physically discipline their wives.&lt;ref&gt;Green, Nicholas St. John. 1879. ''Criminal Law Reports: Being Reports of Cases Determined in the Federal and State Courts of the United States, and in the Courts of England, Ireland, Canada, etc. with notes''. Hurd and Houghton. &quot;The cases in the American courts are uniform against the right of the husband to use any [physical] chastisement, moderate or otherwise, toward the wife, for any purpose.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; By the early twentieth century, it was common for police to intervene in cases of domestic violence in the United States, but arrests remained rare.&lt;ref name=Feder1999&gt;{{cite book|last=Feder|first=Lynette|title=Women and Domestic Violence: An Interdisciplinary Approach|year=1999|publisher=Haworth Press|location=New York|isbn=0-7890-0667-7|page=22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Modern attention to domestic violence began in the [[women's movement]] of the 1970s, particularly within the contexts of [[feminism]] and [[women's rights]], as concern about wives being beaten by their husbands gained attention. The first known use of the expression &quot;domestic violence&quot; in a modern context, meaning &quot;spouse abuse, violence in the home&quot; was in an address to the [[Parliament of the United Kingdom]] in 1973. A few months later the world's first domestic violence services federation ([[Women's Aid]]) was set up in 1974, providing practical and emotional support as part of a range of services to women and children experiencing violence in England.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.womensaid.org.uk/landing_page.asp?section=00010001001900040004 National Women's Aid Federation]. womensaid.org.uk&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/commons/1973/jul/16/battered-wives House of Commons Sitting (1973)] Battered Women. hansard.millbanksystems.com&lt;/ref&gt; With the rise of the [[men's movement]] of the 1990s, the problem of domestic violence against men also gained significant attention.

==See also==
*[[Outline of domestic violence]]
*[[Christianity and domestic violence]]
*[[Effects of domestic violence on children]]
*[[Islam and domestic violence]]
*[[Parental abuse by children]]
*[[Relational disorder]]
*[[Victimization]]
*[[Violence Against Women Act]]
*[[Women's Aid]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Bibliography==
*{{Cite book|author=First M.B., Bell C.C., Cuthbert B., Krystal J..H, Malison R., Offord D.R., Riess D., Shea T., Widiger T., Wisner K.L. |chapter=Personality Disorders and Relational Disorders |editor=Regier D.A., Kupfer D.J., First M.B. |title=A Research Agenda for DSM-V |publisher=American Psychiatric Association |location=Washington, DC |year=2002 |isbn=0-89042-292-3 |url=http://psychrights.org/research/Digest/CriticalThinkRxCites/CharneyInKupfer.pdf}}
*{{Cite book|author=Shipway, Lynn |title=Domestic Violence: A Handbook for Health Professionals |year=2004 |publisher=Routledge |location=New York |isbn=978-0-415-28220-8|url=http://books.google.com/?id=jMV89zMsHwMC&amp;printsec=frontcover}}
*{{Cite book|author=Wallace, Harvey |year=2004 |title=Family Violence: Legal, Medical, and Social Perspectives |publisher=Allyn &amp; Bacon|isbn=0-205-41822-8}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite thesis|degree=M.A.|first=Jeffrey| last=Aguinaldo| title=''[http://scholars.wlu.ca/etd/697/ Partner abuse in gay male relationships: Challenging &quot;we are family&quot;]''|publisher=Wilfrid Laurier University|date=2000}}
*{{Cite book
|last=Dutton |first=Donald G.
|title= Rethinking Domestic Violence
|year=2006
|publisher= UBC Press
|location=Vancouver, BC, Canada
|isbn=0-7748-1304-0
|oclc=64670496}}
*{{cite thesis|degree=M.A.|first=Patrick| last=Fisher| title=''[http://scholars.wlu.ca/etd/580/ &quot;Lessons learned in the heart need to be changed in the heart&quot;: The development and evaluation of a primary prevention intervention of men's violence against women]''|publisher=Wilfrid Laurier University|date=1996}}
*{{Cite book
|last=Hamel |first=John |coauthors=Nicholls, Tonia L.
|title= Family Interventions in Domestic Violence: A Handbook of Gender-Inclusive Theory and Treatment
|year= 2007
|publisher=Springer
|location=New York, NY
|isbn=0-8261-0245-X
|oclc=70122424}}
*{{Cite book
|last=Hampton |first= Robert L. |coauthors=Gullotta, Thomas P. and Ramos, Jessica M.
|title=Interpersonal Violence in the African American Community: Evidence-Based Prevention and Treatment Practices
|year=2006
|publisher=Springer
|location=New York, NY
|isbn= 0-387-29597-6
|oclc=70200773}}
*{{cite thesis|degree=M.S.W.|first=Tenniel Melisa| last=Hanson| title=''[http://scholars.wlu.ca/etd/181/ &quot;No woman no cry&quot;: An examination of the use of feminist ideology in shelters for abused women when working with Caribbean-Canadian women]''|publisher=Wilfrid Laurier University|date=2005}}
*Helton, Peggy, 2011. [http://ecommons.txstate.edu/arp/351 &quot;Resources for Battering Intervention and Prevention Programs in Texas to Mitigate Risk Factors Which Increase the Likelihood of Participant Dropout&quot;]. Applied Research Projects, [[Texas State University-San Marcos]]. Paper 351.
*{{Cite book
|last=Jackson |first= Nicky Ali
|title=Encyclopedia of Domestic Violence
|year=2007
|publisher=Routledge
|location=New York, NY
|isbn=978-0-415-96968-0
|oclc=82772380}}
*{{Cite book
|last=McCue |first=Margi Laird
|title= Domestic Violence: A Reference Handbook
|year=2008 |edition=2nd
|publisher=ABC-CLIO
|location=Santa Barbara, CA
|isbn=978-1-85109-779-1
|oclc=123232304}}
*{{Cite book
|last=Mason |first=Darrin
|title= THE MASTER KEY, Unlocking The Power Within
|year=2011
|publisher= DMC Books
|location=Brisbane, QLD, Australia
|isbn=978-1-4663-9873-3
|url=http://www.amazon.com/Master-Key-Unlocking-Power-Within/dp/1466398736/ref=sr_1_8?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1319787811&amp;sr=8-8}}
*{{cite thesis|degree=M.S.W.|first=Carrie| last=Pollard| title=''[http://scholars.wlu.ca/etd/171/ Examining predictors of level of attendance in a group treatment program for men who abuse]''|publisher=Wilfrid Laurier University|date=2004}}
*{{Cite book
|last=Radford |first=Lorraine and |coauthors=Hester, Marianne
|title= Mothering through Domestic Violence
|year=2006
|publisher=Jessica Kingsley Publishers
|location=London, UK; Philadelphia, PA
|isbn=1-84310-473-3
|oclc=65205017}}
*{{Cite book
|last=Roberts |first=Albert R.
|title=Battered Women and their Families: Intervention Strategies and Treatment Programs
|year=2007 |edition=3rd
|publisher= Springer
|location=New York, NY
|isbn=978-0-8261-4592-5
|oclc=76791906}}
*{{Cite book
|last=Wilcox |first=Paula
|title= Surviving Domestic Violence: Gender, Poverty and Agency
|year= 2006
|publisher= Palgrave Macmillan
|location=Houndmills, England; New York, NY
|isbn=1-4039-4113-0
|oclc=62325091}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Domestic violence}}
*{{DMOZ|Society/Issues/Violence_and_Abuse/Family_Violence/|Family violence}}
*{{DMOZ|Society/People/Women/Issues/Violence_and_Abuse/Domestic_Violence/|Domestic violence against women}}

{{Domestic violence}}
{{Africa topic|Domestic violence in}}
{{Asia topic|Domestic violence in}}
{{Europe topic|Domestic violence in}}
{{North America topic|Domestic violence in}}
{{Oceania topic|Domestic violence in}}
{{South America topic|Domestic violence in}}

{{abuse}}
{{Psychological manipulation}}

[[Category:Domestic violence| ]]

{{Link FA|mk}}
[[ar:عنف منزلي]]
[[bg:Домашно насилие]]
[[ca:Violència domèstica]]
[[de:Häusliche Gewalt]]
[[es:Violencia doméstica]]
[[fa:خشونت خانگی]]
[[fr:Violence conjugale]]
[[ko:가정폭력]]
[[id:Kekerasan dalam rumah tangga]]
[[it:Violenza domestica]]
[[he:אלימות במשפחה]]
[[ln:Matatá na libála]]
[[hu:Családon belüli erőszak]]
[[mk:Семејно насилство]]
[[nl:Huiselijk geweld]]
[[ja:ドメスティックバイオレンス]]
[[pl:Przemoc domowa]]
[[pt:Violência doméstica]]
[[ro:Violență în familie]]
[[ru:Домашнее насилие]]
[[simple:Domestic violence]]
[[sr:Насиље у породици]]
[[sh:Nasilje u porodici]]
[[fi:Perheväkivalta]]
[[sv:Våld i nära relationer]]
[[ta:குடும்ப வன்முறை]]
[[tr:Aile içi şiddet]]
[[vi:Bạo hành gia đình]]
[[zh:家庭暴力]]</text>
      <sha1>gg4fvdn5k1ir4za2722qe6c3g1d45c3</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
