<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Human rights in the United States</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>23814321</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520336484</id>
      <parentid>519830701</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-28T22:48:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mogism</username>
        <id>16902756</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* History */[[WP:AWB/T|Typo fixing]] and cleanup, [[WP:AWB/T|typos fixed]]: are are → are using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (8414)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="148891">[[File:Us declaration independence.jpg|thumb|200px|In 1776, [[Thomas Jefferson]] proposed a philosophy of human rights inherent to all people in the [[United States Declaration of Independence|Declaration of Independence]], asserting that &quot;all men are created equal, that they are endowed by their Creator with certain unalienable Rights, that among these are Life, Liberty and the pursuit of Happiness.&quot; Historian [[Joseph J. Ellis]] calls the Declaration &quot;the most quoted statement of human rights in recorded history&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ellis-1998&quot;&gt;{{Cite book| last = Ellis | first = Joseph J. | authorlink = Joseph Ellis | title = [[American Sphinx: The Character of Thomas Jefferson]] | publisher = Vintage Books | origyear = 1996 | year = 1998 | page = 63 | isbn =0-679-76441-0 }}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

'''Human rights in the United States''' are legally protected by the [[Constitution of the United States]], including the [[United States Bill of Rights|amendments]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| last = Lauren | first = Paul Gordon | editors = Soohoo, Cynthia; Albisa, Catherine; Davis, Martha F. | title = Bringing Human Rights Home: Portraits of the Movement
 | chapter = A Human Rights Lens on U.S. History: Human Rights at Home and Human Rights Abroad | volume = III | page = 4 | publisher = Praeger Publishers | year = 2007 | isbn = 0-275-98824-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Brennan, William, J., ed. Schwartz, Bernard, The Burger Court: counter-revolution or confirmation?, Oxford University Press US, 1998,ISBN 0-19-512259-3, page 10&lt;/ref&gt;, state constitutions, conferred by treaty, and enacted legislatively through Congress, state legislatures, and plebiscites (state referenda). Federal courts in the United States have jurisdiction over international human rights laws as a federal question, arising under international law, which is part of the law of the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa3655/is_199807/ai_n8788427/pg_4/?tag=content;col1|title=Human rights in the United States courts: The role of lawyers|last=Schneebaum|first=Steven M. |date=Summer, 1998|publisher=Washington &amp; Lee Law Review|accessdate=2009-06-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Page needed|date=September 2010}}

==History==
The first human rights organization in the [[Thirteen Colonies]] of [[British America]], dedicated to the abolition of slavery, was formed by [[Anthony Benezet]] in 1775. A year later, the [[United States Declaration of Independence|Declaration of Independence]] advocated to the monarch of England (who was asserting sovereignty through a [[divine right of kings]]), for [[civil liberties]] based on the ''[[self-evident|self-evident truth]]'' “that all men are created equal, that they are endowed by their Creator with certain unalienable Rights, that among these are Life, Liberty and the pursuit of Happiness.”&lt;ref&gt;Declaration of Independence&lt;/ref&gt; This view of human liberties postulates that fundamental rights are not granted by a divine or supernatural being to monarchs who then grant them to subjects, but are granted by a divine or supernatural being to each man (but not woman) and are inalienable and inherent.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last1=Henkin|first1=Louis|last2=Rosenthal|first2=Albert J.|title=Constitutionalism and rights: the influence of the United States constitution abroad|publisher=Columbia University Press|year=1990|isbn=0-231-06570-1|pages=2–3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After the Revolutionary War, the former thirteen colonies, free of the English monarch's claim of sovereignty, went through a pre-government phase of more than a decade, with much debate about the form of government they would have.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Morgan|first=Edmund S.|title=Inventing the People: The Rise of Popular Sovereignty in England and America|year=1989|publisher=W. W. Norton &amp; Company|isbn=0393306232}}&lt;/ref&gt;   The United States Constitution, adopted in 1787 through ratification at a national convention and conventions in the colonies, created a [[republic]] that guaranteed several rights and civil liberties; the Constitution significantly referred to &quot;Persons&quot;, not &quot;Men&quot; as was used in the Declaration of Independence, omitted any reference to the supernatural imagination (such as a &quot;Creator&quot; or &quot;God&quot;) and any authority derived or divined therefrom, and allowed &quot;affirmation&quot; in lieu of an &quot;oath&quot; if preferred.&lt;ref&gt; See, e.g., {{cite book|title=U.S. Constitution|year=1787|chapter=Article VI|quote=&quot;The Senators and Representative before mentioned, and the Members of the several State Legislatures, and all executive and judicial Officers, both of the United Sates and of the several States, shall be bound by Oath or Affirmation, to support this Constitution; but no religious Test shall ever be required as a Qualification to any Office or public Trust under the United States.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;   The Constitution thus eliminated any requirement of supernatural grant of human rights and provided that they belonged to all Persons (presumably meaning men and women, and perhaps children, although the developmental distinction between children and adults poses issues and has been the subject of subsequent amendments, as discussed below).  Some of this conceptualization may have arisen from the significant [[Quakers|Quaker]] segment of the population in the colonies, especially in the Delaware Valley, and their religious views that all human beings, regardless of sex, age, or race or other characteristics, had the same [[Inner light]].  Quaker and Quaker-derived views would have informed the drafting and ratification of the Constitution, including through the direct influence of  some of the [[Framers of the Constitution]], such as [[John Dickinson (politician)]] and [[Thomas Mifflin]], who were either Quakers themselves or came from regions founded by or heavily populated with Quakers.&lt;ref&gt;See, e.g.,{{cite book|last=Fischer|first=David Hackett|title=Albion's Seed: Four British Folkways in America|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-506905-1|pages=490-498|quote=&quot;On the subject of gender, the Quakers had a saying: &quot;In souls, there is no sex.&quot; to g}}&lt;/ref&gt;   

Dickinson, Mifflin and other Framers who objected to slavery were outvoted on that question, however, and the original Constitution sanctioned slavery (although not based on race or other characteristic of the slave) and, through the [[Three-Fifths Compromise]], counted slaves (who were not defined by race) as three-fifths of a Person for purposes of distribution of taxes and representation in the House of Representatives (although the slaves themselves were discriminated against in voting for such representatives).  See [[Three-Fifths Compromise]].   

As the new Constitution took effect in practice, concern over individual liberties and concentration of power at the federal level, gave rise to the amendment of the Constitution through adoption of the [[United States Bill of Rights|Bill of Rights]] (the first ten amendments of the Constitution).   

Courts and legislatures also began to vary in the interpretation of &quot;Person,&quot; with some jurisdictions narrowing the meaning of &quot;Person&quot; to cover only people with property, only men, or only white men.  For example, although women had been voting in some states, such as New Jersey, since the founding of the United States, and prior to that in the colonial era, other states denied them the vote.  In 1756 [[Lydia Taft|Lydia Chapin Taft]] voted, casting a vote in the local town hall meeting in place of her deceased husband.&lt;ref name=&quot;blackstonedaily.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blackstonedaily.com/Journeys/cm-lt.htm |title=Blackstone Valley |publisher=Blackstonedaily.com |date= |accessdate=June 29, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;iwdc.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iwdc.org/resources/timeline.htm |title=Blackstone Valley |publisher=Blackstonedaily.com |date= |accessdate=June 29, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated3&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iwdc.org/resources/timeline.htm |title=Women in Politics: A Timeline |publisher=International Women's Democracy Center |work=Iwdc.org |accessdate=January 3, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1777 women lost the right to exercise their vote in New York, in 1780 women lost the right to exercise their vote in Massachusetts, and in 1784 women lost the right to exercise their vote in New Hampshire.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thelizlibrary.org/suffrage/ |title=The Liz Library Presents: The Woman Suffrage Timeline |publisher=Thelizlibrary.org |date=August 26, 1920 |accessdate=June 29, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
From 1775 until 1807, the state constitution in New Jersey permitted all persons worth over fifty pounds (about $7,800 adjusted for inflation, with the election laws referring to the voters as &quot;he or she&quot;) to vote; provided they had this property, free black men and single women regardless of race therefore had the vote until 1807, but not married women, who could have no independent claim to ownership of fifty pounds (anything they owned or earned belonged to their husbands by the [[Common law]] of [[Coverture]]).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oah.org/pubs/magazine/earlyrepublic/cohen.html]{{dead link|date=June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1790, the law was revised to specifically include women, but in 1807 the law was again revised to exclude them, an unconstitutional act since the state constitution specifically made any such change dependent on the general suffrage.  See [[Women's suffrage in the United States]].  Through the doctrine of [[coverture]], many states also denied married women the right to own property in their own name, although most allowed single women (widowed, divorced or never married) the &quot;Person&quot; status of men, sometimes pursuant to the common law concept of a [[femme sole]].   Over the years, a variety of claimants sought to assert that discrimination against women in voting, in property ownership, in occupational license, and other matters was unconstitutional given the Constitution's use of the term &quot;Person&quot;, but the all-male courts did not give this fair hearing.  See, e.g., [[Bradwell v. Illinois]].

In the 1860s, after decades of conflict over southern states' continued practice of slavery, and northern states' outlawing it, the [[Civil War (United States)|Civil War]] was fought, and in its aftermath the Constitution was amended to prohibit slavery and to prohibit states' denying rights granted in the Constitution.  Among these amendments was the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]], which included an [[Equal Protection Clause]] which seemed to clarify that courts and states were prohibited in narrowing the meaning of &quot;Persons&quot;.  After the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution]] was adopted, [[Susan B. Anthony]], buttressed by the equal protection language, voted.  She was prosecuted for this, however, and ran into an all-male court ruling that women were not &quot;Persons&quot;; the court leveed a fine but it was never collected. 

Fifty years later, in 1920, the Constitution was amended again, with the [[Nineteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Nineteenth Amendment]] to definitively prohibit discrimination against women's suffrage.   

In the 1970s, the [[Burger Court]] made a series of rulings clarifying that discrimination against women in the status of being Persons violated the Constitution and acknowledged that previous court rulings to the contrary had been [[Sui generis]] and an abuse of power.  The most often cited of these is [[Reed v. Reed]], which held that any discrimination against either sex in the rights associated with Person status must meet a strict scrutiny standard.

The 1970s also saw the adoption of the [[Twenty-seventh Amendment to the United States Constitution|Twenty-seventh Amendment]], which prohibited discrimination on the basis of age, for Persons 18 years old and over, in voting.  Other attempts to address the developmental distinction between children and adults in Person status and rights have been addressed mostly by the Supreme Court, with the Court recognizing in 2012, in [[Miller v. Alabama]] a political and biological principle that children are different from adults.  

In the 20th century, the United States took a leading role in the creation of the [[United Nations]] and in the drafting of the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Ignatieff1&quot;&gt;{{Cite book| last = Ignatieff | first = Michael | authorlink = Michael Ignatieff | chapter = Introduction: American Exceptionalism and Human Rights | title = American Exceptionalism and Human Rights | publisher = Princeton University Press | year = 2005 | isbn = 0-691-11648-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; Much of the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]] was modeled in part on the [[U.S. Bill of Rights]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Drafting and Adoption: The Universal Declaration of Human Rights|url=http://www.udhr.org/history/overview.htm|accessdate=02-07-2008|author=National Coordinating Committee for UDHR|publisher=Franklin and Eleanor Roosevelt Institute|year=1998}}&lt;/ref&gt; Even as such, the United States is in violation of the Declaration, in as much that &quot;everyone has the right to leave any country&quot; because the government may prevent the entry and exit of anyone from the United States for foreign policy, national security, or [[child support]] [[arrears|rearage]] reasons by revoking their passport.&lt;ref&gt;See [[Haig v. Agee]], [[s:Passport Act of 1926|Passport Act of 1926]], {{USC|18|1185(b)}} and the [[Personal Responsibility and Work Opportunity Act]] of 1996&lt;/ref&gt;  The United States is also in violation of the United Nations' human rights [[Convention on the Rights of the Child]] which requires both parents to have a relationship with the child.  Conflict between the human rights of the child and those of a mother or father who wishes to leave the country without paying child support or doing the personal work of child care for his child can be considered to be a question of [[Negative and positive rights]].

==Legal framework==
[[File:Constitution of the United States, page 1.jpg|thumb|Original page of the United States Constitution]]

===Domestic legal protection structure===
According to ''Human Rights: The Essential Reference'', &quot;the American Declaration of Independence was the first civic document that met a modern definition of human rights.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Devine|first=Carol|coauthors=Carol Rae Hansen, Ralph Wilde, Hilary Poole|title=Human rights: The essential reference|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|year=1999|pages=26–29|isbn=1-57356-205-X, 9781573562058|url=http://books.google.com/?id=4NjST_gT9WIC&amp;printsec=frontcover#PPA29,M1|accessdate=6/11/2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Constitution recognizes a number of inalienable human rights, including [[freedom of speech]], [[freedom of assembly]], [[freedom of religion]], the [[right to arms|right to keep and bear arms]], freedom from cruel and unusual punishment, and the right to a fair [[trial (law)|trial]] by jury.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Leebrick|first=Kristal|title=The United States Constitution|publisher=Capstone Press|year=2002|isbn=0-7368-1094-3|pages=26–39}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Constitutional amendment]]s have been enacted as the needs of the society evolved. The [[Ninth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Ninth Amendment]] and [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]] recognize that not all human rights have yet been enumerated. The [[Civil Rights Act of 1964|Civil Rights Act]] and the [[Americans with Disabilities Act]] are examples of human rights that were enumerated by Congress well after the Constitution's writing. The scope of the legal protections of human rights afforded by the US government is defined by case law, particularly by the precedent of the [[Supreme Court of the United States]].

Within the federal government, the debate about what may or may not be an emerging human right is held in two forums: the United States Congress, which may enumerate these; and the Supreme Court, which may articulate rights that the law does not spell out. Additionally, individual states, through court action or legislation, have often protected human rights not recognized at federal level. For example, Massachusetts was the first of several states to recognize same sex marriage.&lt;ref name=&quot;legal&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|first=Kathleen|last=Burge|url=http://www.boston.com/news/local/massachusetts/articles/2003/11/18/sjc_gay_marriage_legal_in_mass/|title=SJC: Gay marriage legal in Mass.|publisher=[[The Boston Globe]]|date=2003-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Effect of international treaties===
In the context of human rights and treaties that recognize or create individual rights, there are self-executing and non-self-executing treaties. Non-self-executing treaties, which ascribe rights that under the Constitution may be assigned by law, require legislative action to execute the contract (treaty) before it can apply to law.&lt;ref&gt;''Foster v. Neilson, 27 U.S. 253, 314-15 (1829) U.S. Supreme Court'', Chief Justice Marshall writing: “Our constitution declares a treaty to be the law of the land. It is, consequently, to be regarded in courts of justice as equivalent to an act of the legislature, whenever it operates of itself without the aid of any legislative provision. But when the terms of the stipulation import a contract, when either of the parties engages to perform a particular act, the treaty addresses itself to the political, not the judicial department, and the legislature must execute the contract before it can become a rule for the Court.” at 314, cited in Martin &lt;u&gt;International Human Rights and Humanitarian Law&lt;/u&gt; et al.&lt;/ref&gt; There are also cases that explicitly require legislative approval according to the Constitution, such as cases that could commit the U.S. to declare war or appropriate funds.

Treaties regarding human rights, which create a duty to refrain from acting in a particular manner or confer specific rights, are generally held to be self-executing, requiring no further legislative action. In cases where legislative bodies refuse to recognize otherwise self-executing treaties by ''declaring them to be non-self-executing'' in an act of legislative non-recognition, constitutional scholars argue that such acts violate the separation of powers{{mdash}}in cases of controversy, the judiciary, not Congress, has the authority under Article III to apply treaty law to cases before the court. This is a key provision in cases where the Congress declares a human rights treaty to be non-self-executing, for example, by contending it does not add anything to human rights under U.S. domestic law. The International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights is one such case, which, while ratified after more than two decades of inaction, was done so with reservations, understandings, and declarations.&lt;ref&gt;Martin, F.&lt;u&gt;International Human Rights and Humanitarian Law&lt;/u&gt;. Cambridge University Press. 2006. p. 221 and following. ISBN 0-521-85886-0, ISBN 978-0-521-85886-1&lt;/ref&gt;

==Equality==

=== Racial ===
{{See also|Civil Rights Act of 1964|African-American Civil Rights Movement}}
[[File:Lyndon Johnson signing Civil Rights Act, July 2, 1964.jpg|thumb|right|[[Lyndon B. Johnson]] signs the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]], the first comprehensive legislation prohibiting discrimination on the basis of race and national origin in the workplace in a major industrialized country. Among the guests behind him is [[Martin Luther King, Jr.]]]]
The [[Equal Protection Clause]] of the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution]] guarantees that &quot;the right of citizens of the United States to vote shall not be denied or abridged by the United States or by any State on account of race, color, or previous condition of servitude.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;McWhirter,Darien A.m ''Equal Protection', Oryx Press, 1995, page 1&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, [[Fifteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution]] prohibits the denial of a citizen of the right to vote based on that citizen's &quot;race, color, or previous condition of servitude&quot;.

The United States was the first major industrialized country to enact comprehensive legislation prohibiting discrimination on the basis of race and national origin in the workplace in the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]] (CRA),&lt;ref name=&quot;Gould27&quot;/&gt; while most of the world contains no such recourse for job discrimination.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nivola02127&quot;/&gt; The CRA is perhaps the most prominent civil rights legislation enacted in modern times, has served as a model for subsequent anti-discrimination laws and has greatly expanded civil rights protections in a wide variety of settings.&lt;ref name=&quot;Capozzi6&quot;&gt;Capozzi, Irene Y., ''The Civil Rights Act: background, statutes and primer'', Nova Publishers, 2006, ISBN 1-60021-131-3, page 6&lt;/ref&gt; The United States' 1991 provision of recourse for victims of such discrimination for [[punitive damages]] and full back pay has virtually no parallel in the legal systems of any other nation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nivola02127&quot;&gt;{{Cite book| last = Nivola | first = Pietro S. | title = ''Tense commandments: federal prescriptions and city problems'', | publisher = Brookings Institution Press | year = 2002 | isbn = 0-8157-6094-9| pages= 127–8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to individual civil recourse, the United States possesses anti-discrimination government enforcement bodies, such as the [[Equal Employment Opportunity Commission]], while only the United Kingdom and Ireland possess faintly analogous bureaucracies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nivola02127&quot;/&gt; Beginning in 1965, the United States also began a program of [[affirmative action]] that not only obliges employers not to discriminate, but requires them to provide preferences for groups protected under the Civil Rights Act to increase their numbers where they are judged to be underrepresented.&lt;ref name=&quot;russel147&quot;/&gt;

Such affirmative action programs are also applied in college admissions.&lt;ref name=&quot;russel147&quot;/&gt; The United States also [[National Voting Rights Act of 1965|prohibits the imposition of any &quot;...voting qualification or prerequisite to voting]], or standard, practice, or procedure ... to deny or abridge the right of any citizen of the United States to vote on account of race or color,&quot; which prevents the use of [[grandfather clause]]s, [[literacy test]]s, [[poll taxes]] and [[white primaries]].

[[File:Am I not a man.jpg|left|180px|thumb|[[Abolitionist]] [[Anthony Benezet]] and others formed the first human rights nongovernmental organization in the U.S. This image was used as a symbol for their cause.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| last = Lauren | first = Paul Gordon | chapter = My Brother's and Sister's Keeper: Visions and the Birth of Human Rights | title = The Evolution of International Human Rights: Visions Seen | publisher = University of Pennsylvania Press | edition = Second | pages = 33 | year = 2003 | isbn = 0-8122-1854-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Benezet also stated that &quot;Liberty is the right of every human creature, as soon as he breathes the vital air. And no human law can deprive him of the right which he derives from the law of nature.&quot; Grimm, Robert T., ''Anthony Benezet (1716-1784), Notable American Philanthropists: Biographies of Giving and Volunteering'', Greenwood Publishing Group, 2002, ISBN 1-57356-340-4, pages 26-28&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Prior to the passage of the [[Thirteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution]], [[slavery]] was legal in some states of the United States until 1865.&lt;ref&gt;Vorenberg, Michael, ''Final Freedom: The Civil War, the Abolition of Slavery, and the Thirteenth Amendment'', Cambridge University Press, 2001, page 1&lt;/ref&gt; Influenced by the principles of the [[Religious Society of Friends]], [[Anthony Benezet]] formed the [[Pennsylvania Abolition Society]] in 1775, believing that all ethnic groups were considered equal and that human slavery was incompatible with Christian beliefs. Benezet extended the recognition of human rights to [[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]] and he argued for a peaceful solution to the violence between the Native and European Americans. [[Benjamin Franklin]] became the president of Benezet's abolition society in the late 18th century. In addition, the Fourteenth Amendment was interpreted to permit what was termed ''[[Separate but equal]]'' treatment of minorities until the [[United States Supreme Court]] overturned this interpretation in 1954, which consequently overturned [[Jim Crow laws]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| last = Martin | first = Waldo E. | title = Brown v. Board of Education: a brief history with documents | publisher = Palgrave Macmillan|pages=3&amp;231 | year = 1998 | isbn = 0-312-12811-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Brown v. Board of Education'', [http://brownvboard.org/research/opinions/brownfsp.htm 98 F. Supp. 797] (August 3, 1951).&lt;/ref&gt; [[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]] did not have citizenship rights until the [[Dawes Act]] of 1887 and the [[Indian Citizenship Act of 1924]].

Following the 2008 presidential election, [[Barack Obama]] was sworn in as the first African-American president of the United States on January 20, 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;obama44&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.america.gov/st/usg-english/2009/January/20090120151307hmnietsua0.4407007.html |title=Barack Obama Becomes 44th President of the United States |publisher=America.gov |date= |accessdate=2009-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; In his Inaugural Address, President Obama stated &quot;A man whose father less than 60 years ago might not have been served at a local restaurant can now stand before you to take a most sacred oath....So let us mark this day with remembrance, of who we are and how far we have traveled&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;obama44&quot;/&gt;
{{Clear}}

===Gender===
{{See also|Women's suffrage in the United States}}
[[File:Rose-Sanderson-Votes-for-Women.jpeg|thumb|U.S. women suffragists demonstrating for the right to vote, February 1913]]
The [[Nineteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution]] prohibits the states and the federal government from denying any citizen the right to vote because of that citizen's sex.&lt;ref name=&quot;lc&quot;&gt;[http://www.law.cornell.edu/anncon/html/amdt19_user.html#amdt19_hd2 Nineteenth Amendment], CRS/LII Annotated Constitution&lt;/ref&gt; While this does not necessarily guarantee all women the right to vote, as [[suffrage]] qualifications are determined by individual states, it does mean that states' suffrage qualifications may not prevent women from voting due to their gender.&lt;ref name=&quot;lc&quot;/&gt;

The United States was the first major industrialized country to enact comprehensive [[Civil Rights Act of 1964|CRA]] legislation prohibiting discrimination on the basis of gender in the workplace&lt;ref name=&quot;Gould27&quot;&gt;Gould, William B., ''Agenda for Reform: The Future of Employment Relationships and the Law''&lt; MIT Press, 1996, ISBN 0-262-57114-5, page 27&lt;/ref&gt; while most of the world contains no such recourse for job discrimination.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nivola02127&quot;/&gt; The United States' 1991 provision of recourse for discrimination victims for [[punitive damages]] and full back pay has virtually no parallel in the legal systems of any other nation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nivola02127&quot;/&gt; In addition to individual civil recourse, the United States possesses anti-discrimination government enforcement bodies, such as the [[Equal Employment Opportunity Commission]], while only the United Kingdom and Ireland possess faintly analogous bureaucracies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nivola02127&quot;/&gt; Beginning in 1965, the United States also began a program of [[affirmative action]] that not only obliges employers not to discriminate, but also requires them to provide preferences for groups protected under the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964|CRA]] to increase their numbers where they are judged to be underrepresented.&lt;ref name=&quot;russel147&quot;&gt;James W. Russell, ''Double standard: social policy in Europe and the United States'', Rowman &amp; Littlefield, 2006, ISBN 0-7425-4693-4, pages 147-150&lt;/ref&gt; Such affirmative action programs are also applied in college admissions.&lt;ref name=&quot;russel147&quot;/&gt;

The United States was also the first country to legally define [[sexual harassment]] in the workplace.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zippel6&quot;&gt;Zippel, Kathrina, ''SEXUAL HARASSMENT AND TRANSNATIONAL RELATIONS:WHY THOSE CONCERNED WITH GERMAN-AMERICAN RELATIONS SHOULD CARE'', American Institute for Contemporary German Studies, The Johns Hopkins University, 2002, page 6&lt;/ref&gt; Because sexual harassment is therefore a [[Civil Rights]] violation, individual legal rights of those harassed in the workplace are comparably stronger in the United States than in most European countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zippel6&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Employment Discrimination Law Under Title VII'', Oxford University Press US, 2008, ISBN 0-19-533898-7&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Selective Service System]] does not require women to register for a possible [[military draft]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.american.edu/dgolash/rostker.htm Rostker v. Goldberg, 453 U.S. 57 (1981)]&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[United States military]] does not permit women to serve in some front-line combat units.

===Disability===
{{See also|Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990}}
The United States was the first country in the world to adopt sweeping antidiscrimination legislation for people with disabilities, the [[Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990]] (ADA).&lt;ref name=&quot;midgley&quot;&gt;Midgley, James, and Michelle Livermore, ''The Handbook of Social Policy'', SAGE, 2008, ISBN 1-4129-5076-7, page 448&lt;/ref&gt; The ADA reflected a dramatic shift toward the employment of persons with disabilities to enhance the labor force participation of qualified persons with disabilities and in reducing their dependence on government entitlement programs.&lt;ref name=&quot;blanck3&quot;&gt;Blanck, Peter David and David L. Braddock, ''The Americans with Disabilities Act and the emerging workforce: employment of people with mental retardation'', AAMR, 1998, ISBN 0-940898-52-7, page 3&lt;/ref&gt; The ADA amends the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964|CRA]] and permits plaintiffs to recover [[punitive damages]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Capozzi60&quot;&gt;Capozzi, Irene Y., ''The Civil Rights Act: background, statutes and primer'', Nova Publishers, 2006, ISBN 1-60021-131-3, page 60-61&lt;/ref&gt; The ADA has been instrumental in the evolution of disability discrimination law in many countries, and has had such an enormous impact on foreign law development that its international impact may be even larger than its domestic impact.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lawson89&quot;&gt;Lawson, Anna, Caroline Gooding, ''Disability rights in Europe: from theory to practice'', Hart Publishing, 2005, ISBN 1-84113-486-4, page 89&lt;/ref&gt; Although ADA Title I was [[Board of Trustees of the University of Alabama v. Garrett|found to be unconstitutional]], the [[Bragdon v. Abbott|Supreme Court has extended the protection]] to people with [[Acquired immune deficiency syndrome]] (AIDS).&lt;ref&gt;Jones, Nancy Lee, ''The Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA): overview, regulations and interpretations'', Nova Publishers, 2003, ISBN 1-59033-663-1, pages 7-13&lt;/ref&gt;

It is important to note that federal benefits such as [[Social Security Disability Insurance]] (SSDI) and [[Supplemental Security Income]] (SSI) are often administratively viewed in the United States as being primarily or near-exclusively the entitlement only of [[impoverished]] U.S. [[people with disabilities]], and not applicable to those with disabilities who make significantly above-[[poverty level]] income. This is proven in practice by the general fact that in the U.S., a disabled person on SSI without significant employment income who is suddenly employed, with a salary or wage at or above the [[living wage]] threshold, often discovers that government benefits they were previously entitled to have ceased, because supposedly the new job &quot;invalidates&quot; the need for this assistance. The U.S. is the only industrialized country in the world to have this particular approach to physical disability assistance programming.

===Sexual orientation===
{{See also|LGBT rights in the United States|Same-sex marriage in the United States}}
[[File:Iowa lgbt.jpg|thumb|Same-sex marriage rally in Iowa]]
The Constitution of the United States explicitly recognizes certain individual rights. The 14th Amendment has several times been interpreted using the [[living constitution]] doctrine, for example, civil rights for people of color, disability rights, and women's rights were long unrecognized. There may exist additional gender-related civil rights that are presently not recognized by US law but it does not explicitly state any sexual orientation rights. Some states have recognized sexual orientation rights, which are discussed below.

The United States Federal Government does not have any substantial body of law relating to marriage; these laws have developed separately within each state. The [[Full faith and credit clause]] of the US Constitution ordinarily guarantees the recognition of a marriage performed in one state by another. However, the [[United States Congress|Congress]] passed the [[Defense of Marriage Act]] of 1996,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.pbs.org/flashpointsusa/20040127/infocus/topic_02/|title=Flashpoints USA: God and Country|date=2007-01-27|accessdate=2007-06-03|publisher=[[Public Broadcasting Service|PBS]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; which affirmed that no [[U.S. state|state]] (or other [[Political divisions of the United States|political subdivision within the United States]]) need recognize a marriage between persons of the same sex, even if the marriage was concluded or recognized in another state and the [[Federal Government of the United States|Federal Government]] may not recognize [[same-sex marriage]]s for any purpose, even if concluded or recognized by one of the states. The US Constitution does not grant the federal government any authority to limit state recognition of sexual orientation rights or protections. DOMA only limits the interstate recognition of individual state laws and does not limit state law in any way. DOMA has been ruled to be unconstitutional by various US federal courts for violating the [[14th Amendment to the United States Constitution]] (specifically its [[due process]] and [[equal protection]] clauses) and will potentially be reviewed by the [[Supreme Court of the United States]].

====State laws====
[[File:Gay is the New Black.jpg|thumb|At an anti-[[California Proposition 8 (2008)|Proposition 8]] rally in [[New York City]] a protester compares the [[discrimination]] blacks experienced with the state of gay rights.]]
[[Wisconsin]] was the first state to pass a law explicitly prohibiting discrimination on the basis of [[sexual orientation]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrc.org/your_community/1149.htm HRC: Wisconsin Non-Discrimination Law] Wisconsin law explicitly prohibits discrimination based on sexual orientation in employment, housing, public education, credit and public accommodations. Citations: WIS. STAT. §36.12, § 106.50, § 106.52§ 111.31, § 230.18, § 224.77.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1996, [[Hawaii]] ruled same-sex marriage is a Hawaiian constitutional right. [[Massachusetts]], [[Connecticut]], [[Iowa]], [[Vermont]], [[New Hampshire]], [[New York]], [[Washington D.C.]], and [[Washington (state)|Washington State]] are the only states that allow [[same-sex marriage]]. Same-sex marriage rights were established by the California Supreme Court in 2008, and over 18,000 same-sex couples were married. In November 2008 voters passed [[California Proposition 8 (2008)|Proposition 8]], amending the state constitution to deny same-sex couples marriage rights, which was upheld in a May 2009 decision that also allowed existing same-sex marriages to stand.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2009/02/03/BAMB15MMOH.DTL|title=State high court to hear Prop. 8 case March 5|publisher=''[[San Francisco Chronicle]]''|date=2009-02-04|author=Egelko, Bob|accessdate=2009-02-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
  | url = http://www.courtinfo.ca.gov/courts/supreme/highprofile/prop8.htm
  | title = California Supreme Court filings pertaining to Proposition 8 | accessdate = 2009-01-14 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Privacy===
Privacy is not explicitly stated in the United States Constitution. In the ''[[Griswold v. Connecticut]]'' case, the Supreme Court ruled that it is implied in the Constitution. In the ''[[Roe v. Wade]]'' case, the Supreme Court used privacy rights to overturn most laws against [[abortion in the United States]]. In the ''[[Cruzan v. Director, Missouri Department of Health]]'' case, the Supreme Court held that the patient had a right of privacy to terminate medical treatment. In ''[[Gonzales v. Oregon]]'', the Supreme Court held that the Federal [[Controlled Substances Act]] can not prohibit [[Euthanasia|physician-assisted suicide]] allowed by the [[Oregon Death with Dignity Act]]. The Supreme Court upheld the constitutionality of criminalizing oral and anal sex in the ''[[Bowers v. Hardwick]]'' {{ussc|478|186|1986}} decision; however, it overturned the decision in the ''[[Lawrence v. Texas]]'' {{ussc|539|558|2003}} case and established the protection to sexual privacy.

===Accused===
The United States maintains a [[presumption of innocence]] in legal procedures. The [[Fourth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourth]], [[Fifth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fifth]], [[Sixth Amendment to the United States Constitution]] and [[Eighth Amendment to the United States Constitution]] deals with the rights of criminal suspects. Later the protection was extended to civil cases as well&lt;ref&gt;''McCarthy v. Arndstein'', 266 U.S. 34 (1924)&lt;/ref&gt; In the ''[[Gideon v. Wainwright]]'' case, the Supreme Court requires that indigent criminal defendants who are unable to afford their own attorney be provided counsel at trial. Since the ''[[Miranda v. Arizona]]'' case, the United States requires police departments to inform arrested persons of their rights, which is later called [[Miranda warning]] and typically begins with &quot;You have the right to remain silent.&quot;

==Freedoms==

===Freedom of religion===
{{Main|Freedom of religion in the United States}}

The [[Establishment Clause|establishment clause]] of the [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|first amendment]] prohibits the establishment of a national religion by Congress or the preference of one religion over another. The clause was used to limit [[school prayer|school praying]], beginning with ''[[Engel v. Vitale]]'', which ruled government-led prayer unconstitutional. ''[[Wallace v. Jaffree]]'' banned moments of silence allocated for praying. The Supreme Court also ruled clergy-led prayer at public high school graduations unconstitutional with ''[[Lee v. Weisman]]''.

The [[Free Exercise Clause of the First Amendment|free exercise clause]] guarantees the free exercise of religion. The Supreme Court's ''[[Lemon v. Kurtzman]]'' decision established the &quot;Lemon test&quot; exception, which details the requirements for legislation concerning religion. The ''[[Employment Division v. Smith]]'' decision, the Supreme Court maintained a &quot;neutral law of general applicability&quot; can be used to limit religion exercises. In the ''[[City of Boerne v. Flores]]'' decision, the [[Religious Freedom Restoration Act]] was struck down as exceeding congressional power; however, the decision's effect is limited by the ''[[Gonzales v. O Centro Espirita Beneficente Uniao do Vegetal]]'' decision, which requires states to express compelling interest in prohibiting illegal drug use in religious practices.

===Freedom of expression===
[[File:Four freedoms human rights.jpg|thumb|300px|The [[Four Freedoms]] are derived from the 1941 [[State of the Union Address]] by [[United States President]] [[Franklin Roosevelt]] delivered to the [[77th United States Congress]] on January 6, 1941. The theme was incorporated into the [[Atlantic Charter]], and it became part of the charter of the [[United Nations]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.usnews.com/usnews/documents/docpages/document_page70.htm|title=100 Documents That Shaped America:President Franklin Roosevelt's Annual Message (Four Freedoms) to Congress (1941)|accessdate=2008-04-11|publisher=U.S. News &amp; World Report, L.P.|work=[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; and appears in the preamble of the [[United Nations Declaration of Human Rights]].]]
{{Main|Freedom of speech in the United States|Censorship in the United States}}

The United States, like other [[liberal democracy|liberal democracies]], is supposed to be a [[constitutional republic]] based on founding documents that restrict the power of government to preserve the liberty of the people. The freedom of expression (including speech, [[Freedom of the press|media]], and [[Freedom of association|public assembly]]) is an important right and is given special protection, as declared by the [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First Amendment]] of the constitution. According to Supreme Court precedent, the federal and lower governments may not apply [[prior restraint]] to expression, with certain exceptions, such as national security and obscenity.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Near v. Minnesota]]''&lt;/ref&gt; There is no law punishing insults against the government, ethnic groups, or religious groups. Symbols of the government or its officials may be destroyed in protest, including the [[American flag]]. Legal limits on expression include:

*[[Solicitation]], [[fraud]], specific threats of violence, or disclosure of [[classified information]]
*Advocating the overthrow of the U.S. government through speech or publication, or organizing political parties that advocate the overthrow of the U.S. government (the [[Smith Act]])&lt;ref name=&quot;Dennis vs. United States&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=Dennis vs. United States|publisher=Audio Case Files|accessdate=2008-09-06|url=http://www.audiocasefiles.com/acf_cases/9769-dennis-v-united-states}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Civil offenses involving [[defamation]], fraud, or workplace [[harassment]]
*[[Copyright]] violations
*[[Federal Communications Commission]] rules governing the use of [[broadcast media]]
*Crimes involving sexual [[Obscenity#United States obscenity law|obscenity]] in [[Censorship in the United States#Censorship of pornography|pornography]] and [[Obscenity#Non image based obscenity cases in the USA|text only erotic stories]].
*Ordinances requiring mass demonstrations on public property to register in advance.
*The use of [[free speech zone]]s and [[exclusion zone|protest free zones]].
*Military censorship of [[blogs]] written by military personnel claiming some include [[OPSEC|sensitive information ineligible for release]]. Some critics view military officials as trying to suppress dissent from troops in the field.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=U.S. Army clamping down on soldiers' blogs|publisher=Reuters (CNN)|date=2007-05-02|accessdate=2007-05-27|url=http://www.cnn.com/2007/TECH/internet/05/02/army.blogs.reut/index.html |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070522034642/http://www.cnn.com/2007/TECH/internet/05/02/army.blogs.reut/index.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=3867981|title=Soldiers' Iraq Blogs Face Military Scrutiny|date=2004-08-24|accessdate=2007-06-14|publisher=[[National Public Radio|NPR]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The US Constitution specifically limits the human rights of active duty members, and this constitutional authority is used to limit speech rights by members in this and in other ways.

Some laws remain controversial due to concerns that they infringe on freedom of expression. These include the [[Digital Millennium Copyright Act]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://news.com.com/2100-1023-251627.html|publisher=[[CNET]]|first=John|last=Borland|title=Battle lines harden over Net copyright|date=2001-02-26|accessdate=2007-05-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Bipartisan Campaign Reform Act]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Fatal Flaws in the Bipartisan Campaign Reform Act of 2002|publisher=[[Brookings Institution]]|accessdate=2007-05-27|url=http://www.brookings.edu/dybdocroot/gs/cf/debate/Bopp.pdf|format=PDF |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070616101509/http://www.brookings.edu/dybdocroot/gs/cf/debate/Bopp.pdf |archivedate = 2007-06-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In two high profile cases, grand juries have decided that ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'' magazine reporter Matthew Cooper and ''[[New York Times]]'' reporter Judith Miller must reveal their sources in cases involving CIA leaks. Time magazine exhausted its legal appeals, and Mr. Cooper eventually agreed to testify. Miller was jailed for 85 days before cooperating. U.S. District Chief Judge Thomas F. Hogan ruled that the First Amendment does not insulate ''Time'' magazine reporters from a requirement to testify before a criminal grand jury that's conducting the investigation into the possible illegal disclosure of classified information.

Approximately 30,000 government employees and contractors are currently employed to monitor telephone calls and other communications.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.newsweek.com/2010/09/04/zakaria-why-america-overreacted-to-9-11.html |author=Fareed Zakaria |title=What America Has Lost |publisher=Newsweek |date=September 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Right to peaceably assemble====
Although Americans are supposed to enjoy the freedom to peacefully protest, protesters are sometimes mistreated, beaten, arrested, jailed or fired upon.

On February 19, 2011, Ray McGovern was dragged out of a speech by Hillary Clinton on Internet freedom, in which she said that people should be free to protest without fear of violence. McGovern, who was wearing a [[Veterans for Peace]] t-shirt, stood up during the speech and silently turned his back on Clinton. He was then assaulted by undercover and uniformed police, roughed up, handcuffed and jailed. He suffered bruises and lacerations in the attack and required medical treatment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-1358475/Protest-Egypt-America-message-war-veteran-dragged-Clinton-speech.html?ito=feeds-newsxml| author=Rachel Quigley| title=War veteran, 71, dragged out for staging silent protest during Hillary Clinton address... on freedom of speech| publisher=Mail Online| date=February 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Protesters have also been arrested for protesting outside of designated “free speech zones”.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.heraldtribune.com/article/20030807/NEWS/308070381| title=Anti-Bush protesters sue over arrests| publisher=Herald Tribune| date=August 7, 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the 2004 Republican National Convention in New York City, over 1,700 protesters were arrested.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2004/08/25/politics/main638348.shtml| author=Jarrett Murphy| title=A Raw Deal For RNC Protesters?| publisher=CBS News| date=September 3, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On May 4, 1970, Ohio National Guardsmen opened fire on protesting students at Kent State University, killing four students. Investigators determined that 28 Guardsmen fired 61 to 67 shots. The Justice Department concluded that the Guardsmen were not in danger and that their claim that they fired in self-defense was untrue. The nearest student was almost 100 yards away at the time of the shooting.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.usatoday.com/news/nation/2010-05-03-kent-state_N.htm| author=Rick Hampson| title=1970 Kent State shootings are an enduring history lesson| publisher=USA Today| date=May 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On March 7, 1965, approximately 600 civil rights marchers were violently dispersed by state and local police near the Edmund Pettus Bridge outside of Selma, Alabama.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.nps.gov/nr/travel/civilrights/al4.htm| title=Selma-to-Montgomery March| publisher=National Park Service| accessdate=February 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2009, the ACLU asked the Department of Defense to stop categorizing political protests as &quot;low-level terrorism&quot; in their training courses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,526972,00.html| title=Pentagon Exam Calls Protests 'Low-Level Terrorism,' Angering Activists| publisher=Fox News| date=June 17, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the fall of 2011, large numbers of protesters taking part in the &quot;[[Occupy movement]]&quot; in cities around the country were arrested on various charges during protests for economic and political reforms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://edition.cnn.com/2011/10/30/us/texas-occupy-austin/?hpt=ju_c2| title=Dozens of Occupy protesters arrested in Texas, Oregon| publisher=CNN News| date=October 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Freedom of movement===
{{Expand section|date=July 2009}}
{{Further|Freedom of movement under United States law}}
As per § 707(b) of the Foreign Relations Authorization Act, Fiscal Year 1979,&lt;ref&gt;{{USStatute|95|426|92|993|1978|10|07}}, {{USC|18|1185(b)}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[United States passport]]s are required to enter and exit the country, and as per the [[s:Passport Act of 1926|Passport Act of 1926]] and [[Haig v. Agee]], the Presidential administration may deny or revoke passports for [[foreign policy]] or [[national security]] reasons at any time. Perhaps the most notable example of enforcement of this ability was the 1948 denial of a passport to [[United States House of Representatives|U.S. Representative]] [[Leo Isacson]], who sought to go to Paris to attend a conference as an observer for the American Council for a Democratic Greece, a [[Communist front]] organization, because of the group's role in opposing the Greek government in the [[Greek Civil War]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Haig v. Agee]], 453 U.S. 280 (1981), at 302&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=FOREIGN RELATIONS: Bad Ammunition|date=12 April 1948|newspaper=[[Time (magazine)|TIME Magazine]]|url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,779776,00.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The United States prevents U.S. citizens to travel to [[Cuba]], citing national security reasons, as part of an [[United States embargo against Cuba|embargo against Cuba]] that has been condemned as an illegal act by the [[United Nations General Assembly]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;UN condemns US embargo on Cuba&quot;. BBC News. 12 Nov. 2007. Retrieved 14 Apr. 2009. http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/2455923.stm&lt;/ref&gt; The current exception to the ban on travel to the island, permitted since April 2009, has been an easing of travel restrictions for Cuban-Americans visiting their relatives. Restrictions continue to remain in place for the rest of the American populace.&lt;ref&gt;Padgett, Tim. &quot;Will Obama Open Up All U.S. Travel to Cuba?&quot; ''Time Magazine''. 14 Apr. 2009. Retrieved 14 Apr. 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

On June 30, 2010, the [[American Civil Liberties Union]] filed a lawsuit on behalf of ten people who are either U.S. citizens or legal residents of the U.S., challenging the constitutionality of the government's &quot;no-fly&quot; list. The plaintiffs have not been told why they are on the list. Five of the plaintiffs have been stranded abroad. It is estimated that the &quot;no-fly&quot; list contained about 8,000 names at the time of the lawsuit.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2010/07/01/us/01brfs-ACLUSUESOVER_BRF.html |author=Scott Shane |title=A.C.L.U. Sues Over No-Fly List |publisher=The New York Times |date=July 1, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Secretary of State can deny a passport to anyone imprisoned, on parole, or on supervised release for a conviction for international drug trafficking or sex tourism, or to anyone who is behind on their child support payments.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://edition.cnn.com/2010/CRIME/07/13/sex.offenders.passports/index.html?iref=NS1 |author=Abbie Boudreau and Scott Zamost |title=Thousands of sex offenders receive U.S. passports |publisher=CNN |date=July 14, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The following case precedents are typically cited in defense of unencumbered travel within the United States:

&quot;The use of the highway for the purpose of travel and transportation is not a mere privilege, but a common fundamental right of which the public and individuals cannot rightfully be deprived.&quot; Chicago Motor Coach v. Chicago, 337 Ill. 200; 169 N.E. 22 (1929).

&quot;The right of the citizen to travel upon the public highways and to transport his property thereon, either by carriage or by automobile, is not a mere privilege which a city may prohibit or permit at will, but a common law right which he has under the right to life, liberty, and the pursuit of happiness.&quot; Thompson v. Smith, Supreme Court of Virginia, 155 Va. 367; 154 S.E. 579; (1930).

&quot;Undoubtedly the right of locomotion, the right to move from one place to another according to inclination, is an attribute of personal liberty, and the right, ordinarily, of free transit from or through the territory of any State is a right secured by the 14th amendment and by other provisions of the Constitution.&quot; Schactman v. Dulles, 225 F.2d 938; 96 U.S. App. D.C. 287 (1955). 

&quot;The right to travel is a well-established common right that does not owe its existence to the federal government. It is recognized by the courts as a natural right.&quot; Schactman v. Dulles 225 F.2d 938; 96 U.S. App. D.C. 287 (1955) at 941.

&quot;The right to travel is a part of the liberty of which the citizen cannot be deprived without due process of law under the Fifth Amendment.&quot; [[Kent v. Dulles]], 357 US 116, 125 (1958).

===Freedom of association===
{{Further|Freedom of association}}
[[Freedom of association]] is the right of individuals to come together in groups for political action or to pursue common interests.

Freedom of association in the U.S. is restricted by the [[Smith Act]], which bans political parties that advocate the violent overthrow of the U.S. government.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dennis vs. United States&quot;/&gt;

Between 1956 and 1971, the [[FBI]] attempted to &quot;expose, disrupt, misdirect, discredit, or otherwise neutralize&quot; radical groups through the [[COINTELPRO]] program.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.pbs.org/hueypnewton/actions/actions_cointelpro.html |title=COINTELPRO |publisher=PBS | accessdate=June 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008, the Maryland State Police admitted that they had added the names of Iraq War protesters and death penalty opponents to a terrorist database. They also admitted that other &quot;protest groups&quot; were added to the terrorist database, but did not specify which groups. It was also discovered that undercover troopers used aliases to infiltrate organizational meetings, rallies and group e-mail lists. Police admitted there was &quot;no evidence whatsoever of any involvement in violent crime&quot; by those classified as terrorists.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/10/07/AR2008100703245.html |author=Lisa Rein |title=Md. Police Put Activists' Names On Terror Lists |publisher=The Washington Post |date=October 8, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===National security exceptions===
{{Further|National Security Strategy of the United States}}
The United States government has declared [[martial law]],&lt;ref name=&quot;ada.asn.au&quot;&gt;http://www.ada.asn.au/defender/Winter%202004/Review%20-%20Supreme%20Command%20(Defender,%20Winter%202004).pdf&lt;/ref&gt; suspended (or claimed exceptions to) some rights on national security grounds, typically in wartime and conflicts such as the [[United States Civil War]],&lt;ref name=&quot;ada.asn.au&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;constitutional2002&quot;&gt;Constitutional Dictatorship: Crisis Government in the Modern Democracies. Clinton Rossiter. 2002. Page X. ISBN 0-7658-0975-3&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cold War]] or the [[War on Terrorism|War against Terror]].&lt;ref name=&quot;constitutional2002&quot;/&gt; 70,000 Americans of Japanese ancestry were legally interned during [[World War II]] under [[Executive Order 9066]]. In some instances the federal courts have allowed these exceptions, while in others the courts have decided that the national security interest was insufficient. Presidents Lincoln, Wilson, and F.D. Roosevelt ignored such judicial decisions.&lt;ref name=&quot;constitutional2002&quot;/&gt;

====Historical restrictions====
Sedition laws have sometimes placed restrictions on freedom of expression. The [[Alien and Sedition Acts]], passed by President [[John Adams]] during an undeclared naval conflict with [[France]], allowed the government to punish &quot;false&quot; statements about the government and to deport &quot;dangerous&quot; immigrants. The [[Federalist Party]] used these acts to harass supporters of the [[Democratic-Republican Party]]. While [[Woodrow Wilson]] was president, another broad sedition law called the [[Sedition Act of 1918]], was passed during [[World War I]]. It also caused the arrest and ten year sentencing of [[Socialist Party of America]] Presidential candidate [[Eugene V. Debs]] for speaking out against the atrocities of World War I, although he was later released early by President [[Warren G. Harding]]. Countless others, labeled as &quot;subverts&quot; (especially the [[Wobblies]]), were investigated by the Woodrow Wilson Administration.

Presidents have claimed the power to imprison summarily, under military jurisdiction, those suspected of being combatants for states or groups at war against the United States. [[Abraham Lincoln]] invoked this power in the [[American Civil War]] to imprison [[Maryland]] secessionists. In that case, the Supreme Court concluded that only [[United States Congress|Congress]] could suspend the writ of [[habeas corpus]], and the government released the detainees. During [[World War II]], the United States [[Japanese American internment|interned thousands of Japanese-Americans]] on alleged fears that [[Japan]] might use them as saboteurs.

The [[Fourth Amendment of the United States Constitution]] forbids unreasonable search and seizure without a [[warrant (legal)|warrant]], but some administrations have claimed exceptions to this rule to investigate alleged [[conspiracy (political)|conspiracies]] against the government. During the [[Cold War]], the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation]] established [[COINTELPRO]] to infiltrate and disrupt left-wing organizations, including those that supported the rights of [[black Americans]].

National security, as well as other concerns like [[unemployment]], has sometimes led the United States to toughen its generally liberal [[immigration]] policy. The [[Chinese Exclusion Act (United States)|Chinese Exclusion Act]] of 1882 all but banned [[China|Chinese]] immigrants, who were accused of [[crowding out (economics)|crowding out]] American workers.

====Nationwide Suspicious Activity Reporting Initiative====
The federal government has set up a data collection and storage network that keeps a wide variety of data on tens of thousands of Americans who have not been accused of committing a crime. Operated primarily under the direction of the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation]], the program is known as the [[Nationwide Suspicious Activity Reporting Initiative]] or SAR. Reports of suspicious behavior noticed by local law enforcement or by private citizens are forwarded to the program, and profiles are constructed of the persons under suspicion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2010/12/20/politics/washingtonpost/main7167877.shtml| author=Dana Priest and William M. Arkin| title=Monitoring America: How the U.S. Sees You| publisher=CBS News| date=December 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; see also [[Fusion Center]].

==Labor rights==
{{Main|Labor rights}}
Labor rights in the United States have been linked to basic constitutional rights.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.workrights.org/issue_organize/ro_right_to_organize.html NWI Right to Organize&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Comporting with the notion of creating an economy based upon highly skilled and high wage labor employed in a capital-intensive dynamic growth economy, the United States enacted laws mandating the right to a safe workplace, [[Workers compensation]], [[Unemployment benefits|Unemployment insurance]], fair labor standards, [[collective bargaining]] rights, [[Social Security (United States)|Social Security]], along with laws prohibiting [[child labor]] and guaranteeing a [[minimum wage]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last1=Azari-Rad|first1=Hamid|last2=Philips|first2=Peter|last3=Prus|first3=Mark J. |title=The economics of prevailing wage laws|publisher=Ashgate Publishing, Ltd.|year=2005|isbn=0-7546-3255-5|pages=3}}&lt;/ref&gt; While U.S. workers tend to work longer hours than other industrialized nations, lower taxes and more benefits give them a larger disposable income than those of most industrialized nations, however the advantage of lower taxes have been challenged. See: [[Disposable and discretionary income]]. U.S. workers are among the most productive in the world.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationsencyclopedia.com/economies/Americas/United-States-of-America-WORKING-CONDITIONS.html United States of America Working conditions, Information about Working conditions in United States of America&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; During the 19th and 20th centuries, safer conditions and workers' rights were gradually mandated by law.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kentlaw.edu/ilhs/curricul.htm A Curriculum of United States Labor History for Teachers&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1935, the [[National Labor Relations Act]] recognized and protected &quot;the rights of most workers in the private sector to organize labor unions, to engage in collective bargaining, and to take part in strikes and other forms of concerted activity in support of their demands.&quot; However, many states hold to the principle of [[at-will employment]], which says an employee can be fired for any or no reason, without warning and without recourse, unless violation of State or Federal civil rights laws can be proven. In 2011, 11.8% of U.S. workers were members of labor unions&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.bls.gov/news.release/union2.nr0.htm| title=Union Members Summary| publisher=U.S. Dept. of Labor, Bureau of Labor Statistics| date=January 27, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; with 37% of public sector (government) workers in unions while only 6.9% of private sector workers were union members.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2012/01/28/business/union-membership-rate-fell-again-in-2011.html| author=Steven Greenhouse| title=Union Membership Rate Fell Again in 2011| publisher=New York Times| date=January 27, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Health care==
{{See also|Health care in the United States}}
The [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]], adopted by the [[United Nations]] in 1948, states that “everyone has the right to a standard of living adequate for the health and well-being of oneself and one’s family, including food, clothing, housing, and medical care.”&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.nhchc.org/humanright.html|title=Human Rights, Homelessness and Health Care|author=National Health Care for the Homeless Council}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, the ''Principles of Medical Ethics'' of the American Medical Association require medical doctors to respect the human rights of the patient, including that of providing medical treatment when it is needed.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.ama-assn.org/ama/pub/category/2512.html|title=Principles of medical ethics|author=American Medical Association}}&lt;/ref&gt; Americans' rights in health care are regulated by the [[US Patients' Bill of Rights]].{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}

Unlike most other industrialized nations, the United States does not offer most of its citizens subsidized health care. The United States [[Medicaid]] program provides subsidized coverage to some categories of individuals and families with low incomes and resources, including children, pregnant women, and very low-income people with disabilities (higher-earning people with disabilities do not qualify for Medicaid, although they do qualify for Medicare). However, according to Medicaid's own documents, &quot;the Medicaid program does not provide health care services, even for very poor persons, unless they are in one of the designated eligibility groups.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cms.hhs.gov/MedicaidGenInfo/ Overview - What is Not Covered], U.S. Department of Health &amp; Human Services&lt;/ref&gt; 

Nonetheless, some states offer subsidized health insurance to broader populations. Coverage is subsidized for persons age 65 and over, or who meet other special criteria through [[Medicare (United States)|Medicare]]. Every person with a permanent disability, both young and old, is inherently entitled to [[Medicare (United States)|Medicare]] health benefits — a fact not all disabled US citizens are aware of. However, just like every other Medicare recipient, a disabled person finds that his or her Medicare benefits only cover up to 80% of anything in the U.S. medical system, and that the other 20% must be paid by other means (typically supplemental, privately-held insurance plans, or cash out of the person's own pocket). Therefore, even the Medicare program is not truly [[national health insurance]] or [[universal health care]] the way most of the rest of the industrialized world understands it.

The [[Emergency Medical Treatment and Active Labor Act]] of 1986, an [[unfunded mandate]], mandates that no person may ever be denied emergency services regardless of ability to pay, citizenship, or immigration status.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cms.hhs.gov/EMTALA/ Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services: Emergency Medical Treatment &amp; Labor Act]&lt;/ref&gt; The Emergency Medical Treatment and Labor Act has been criticized by the [[American College of Emergency Physicians]] as an unfunded mandate.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.acep.org/patients.aspx?id=25936 American College of Emergency Physicians Fact Sheet: EMTALA]. Retrieved 2007-11-01.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Rowes |first=Jeffrey |year=2000 |month= |title=EMTALA: OIG/HCFA Special Advisory Bulletin Clarifies EMTALA, American College of Emergency Physicians Criticizes It
 |journal=Journal of Law, Medicine &amp; Ethics |volume=28 |issue=1 |page=9092 |id= |url=http://www.aslme.org/news/jlme/28.1e.html |accessdate= 2008-01-02 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080129005052/http://www.aslme.org/news/jlme/28.1e.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2008-01-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

46.6 million residents, or 15.9 percent, were without health insurance coverage in 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.cbpp.org/8-29-06health.htm|title=The number of uninsured Americans is at an all-time high|publisher=[[Center on Budget and Policy Priorities|CBPP]]|date=2006-08-29|accessdate=2007-05-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
This number includes about ten million non-citizens, millions more who are eligible for [[Medicaid]] but never applied, and 18 million with annual household incomes above $50,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|author=[[N. Gregory Mankiw]] |title=Beyond Those Health Care Numbers |publisher=The New York Times|date=November 4, 2007 |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2007/11/04/business/04view.html }}&lt;/ref&gt; According to a study led by the Johns Hopkins Children's Center, uninsured children who are hospitalized are 60% more likely to die than children who are covered by health insurance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.hopkinschildrens.org/Lack-of-Insurance-May-Have-Figured-In-Nearly-17000-Childhood-Deaths.aspx| title=Lack of Insurance May Have Figured In Nearly 17,000 Childhood Deaths, Study Shows| publisher=John Hopkins Children's Center| date=October 29. 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Justice system==
{{Unbalanced|section|date=May 2009}}
The Fourth, Fifth, Sixth and Eighteenth Amendments of the Bill of Rights, along with the Fourteenth Amendment, ensure that criminal defendants have significant procedural rights that are unsurpassed by any other justice system.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lieberman382&quot;&gt;{{Cite book| last = Lieberman | first = Jethro Koller | title = A practical companion to the Constitution: how the Supreme Court has ruled on issues from abortion to zoning | publisher = University of California Press | page = 382 | isbn =0-520-21280-0 | year = 1999 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Fourteenth Amendment's incorporation of [[due process]] rights adds these constitutional protections to the state and local levels of law enforcement.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lieberman382&quot;/&gt; Similarly, the United States possesses a system of judicial review over government action more powerful than any other in the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lieberman6&quot;&gt;Lieberman, Jethro Koller, ''A practical companion to the Constitution: how the Supreme Court has ruled on issues from abortion to zoning'', University of California Press, 1999, ISBN 0-520-21280-0, page 6&lt;/ref&gt;

===Death penalty===
{{Further|Capital punishment in the United States|Capital punishment debate}}
The USA was the only country in the [[G8]] to have carried out executions in 2011. Three countries in the [[G20]]
carried out executions in 2011: [[Human rights in China|China]], [[Human rights in Saudi Arabia|Saudi Arabia]] and the [[USA]]. The USA and [[Human rights in Belarus|Belarus]] were the only two of the 56 Member States of the [[Organization for Security and Cooperation in Europe]] to have carried out executions in 2011.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amnesty.org/en/library/asset/ACT50/001/2012/en/241a8301-05b4-41c0-bfd9-2fe72899cda4/act500012012en.pdf Death sentences and executions in 2011] Amnesty International March 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

Capital punishment is controversial. Death penalty opponents regard the death penalty as inhumane&lt;ref name=&quot;amnesty-ill&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Cruel and Unusual: Executing the mentally ill|url=http://www.amnestyusa.org/page.do?id=1105184In|author=Dan Malone|publisher=Amnesty International Magazine|year=2005|month=Fall}}&lt;/ref&gt; and criticize it for its irreversibility&lt;ref name=&quot;amnesty-irreversible&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.amnestyusa.org/Our_Issues/Death_Penalty/page.do?id=1011005&amp;n1=3&amp;n2=28|title=Abolish the death penalty|publisher=Amnesty International|accessdate=2008-01-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; and assert that it lacks a deterrent effect,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.amnestyusa.org/death-penalty-facts/the-death-penalty-and-deterrence/page.do?id=1101085&amp;n1=3&amp;n2=28&amp;n3=99 |title=The Death Penalty and Deterrence |publisher=Amnestyusa.org |date=2008-02-22 |accessdate=2009-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; as have several studies&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|author=Sheila Berry |url=http://www.truthinjustice.org/922death.htm |title=Death Penalty No Deterrent |publisher=Truthinjustice.org |date=2000-09-22 |accessdate=2009-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.math.dartmouth.edu/~lamperti/capitalpunishment.html |title=John W. Lamperti &amp;#124; Capital Punishment |publisher=Math.dartmouth.edu |date=1973-03-10 |accessdate=2009-05-23}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; and debunking studies that claim to show a deterrent effect.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/article.php?&amp;did=2374 |title=Discussion of Recent Deterrence Studies &amp;#124; Death Penalty Information Center |publisher=Deathpenaltyinfo.org |date= |accessdate=2009-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Amnesty International]], &quot;the death penalty is the ultimate, irreversible denial of human rights.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;amnesty-irreversible&quot; /&gt;

The 1972 US Supreme Court case ''[[Furman v. Georgia]]'' {{ussc|408|238|1972}} held that arbitrary imposition of the death penalty at the states' discretion constituted [[cruel and unusual punishment]] in violation of the [[Eighth Amendment to the United States Constitution]]. In ''[[California v. Anderson]]'' 64 Cal.2d 633, 414 P.2d 366 (Cal. 1972), the [[Supreme Court of California]] classified capital punishment as [[Cruel and unusual punishment|cruel and unusual]] and outlawed the use of capital punishment in California, until it was reinstated in 1976 after the federal supreme court rulings [[Gregg v. Georgia]], {{ussc|428|153|1976}}, ''[[Jurek v. Texas]]'', {{ussc|428|262|1976}}, and [[Proffitt v. Florida]], {{ussc|428|242|1976}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;alaska-law&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://justice.uaa.alaska.edu/death/history.html|title=History of the Death Penalty &amp; Recent Developments|year=2005|month=May|accessdate=2008-01-25|author=Melissa S. Green|note=In Focus on the Death Penalty (website)|publisher=Justice Center, University of Alaska Anchorage}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of January 25, 2008, the death penalty has been abolished in the [[Washington, D.C.|District of Columbia]] and fourteen [[U.S. State|states]], mainly in the [[Northeastern United States|Northeast]] and [[Midwestern United States|Midwest]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/article.php?did=121&amp;scid=11|title=Death Penalty Policy By State|publisher=[http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org Death Penalty Information Center]|accessdate=2008-01-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The UN special [[rapporteur]] recommended to a committee of the UN General Assembly that the United States be found to be in violation of Article 6 the [[International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights]] in regards to the death penalty in 1998, and called for an immediate capital punishment moratorium.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Rights Watch|url=http://www.un.org/Pubs/chronicle/1998/issue2/0298p72.html|title=Death Penalty Issue Addressed by Special Rapporteur|publisher=UN Chronicle|volume= XXXV|issue= 2 |year=1998}}&lt;/ref&gt; The recommendation of the special [[rapporteur]] is not legally binding under international law, and in this case the UN did not act upon the lawyer's recommendation.

Since the reinstatement of the death penalty in 1976 there have been 1077 executions in the United States (as of May 23, 2007).&lt;ref name = &quot;Death Penalty Info&quot;&gt;[http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org Death Penalty Info]&lt;/ref&gt; There were 53 executions in 2006.&lt;ref name = &quot;Death Row USA&quot;&gt;[http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/article.php?scid=8&amp;did=146 Death Penalty Info: Executions by Year]&lt;/ref&gt; Texas overwhelmingly leads the United States in executions, with 379 executions from 1976 to 2006;&lt;ref&gt;[[List of individuals executed in Texas]]&lt;/ref&gt; the second-highest ranking state is Virginia, with 98 executions.&lt;ref&gt;[[List of individuals executed in Virginia]]&lt;/ref&gt;

A ruling on March 1, 2005 by the Supreme Court in ''[[Roper v. Simmons]]'' prohibits the execution of people who committed their crimes when they were under the age of 18.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/4308881.stm|title=S court bans juvenile executions|publisher=BBC News|date=2005-03-01|accessdate=2007-06-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Between 1990 and 2005, [[Amnesty International]] recorded 19 executions in the United States for crime committed by a juvenile.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://web.amnesty.org/pages/deathpenalty-children-stats-eng|title=Executions of child offenders since 1990|publisher=[[Amnesty International]]|accessdate=2007-06-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It is the official policy of the [[European Union]] and a number of non-EU nations to achieve global abolition of the death penalty. For this reason the EU is vocal in its criticism of the death penalty in the US and has submitted ''[[amicus curiae]]'' briefs in a number of important US court cases related to capital punishment.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Abolition of the Death Penalty|publisher=The EU's Human rights &amp; Democratisation Policy|url=http://ec.europa.eu/external_relations/human_rights/adp/index.htm|accessdate=2007-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[American Bar Association]] also sponsors a project aimed at abolishing the death penalty in the United States,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.abanet.org/moratorium/|title=Death Penalty Moratorium Implementation Project|publisher=The American Bar Association|accessdate=2008-01-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; stating as among the reasons for their opposition that the US continues to execute minors and the mentally retarded, and fails to protect adequately the rights of the innocent.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Why a moratorium?|publisher=American Bar Association (Death Penalty Moratorium Implementation Project)|url=http://www.abanet.org/moratorium/why.html|accessdate=2008-01-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some opponents criticize the over-representation of blacks on death row as evidence of the unequal racial application of the death penalty. This over-representation is not limited to capital offenses, in 1992 although blacks account for 12% of the US population, about 34 percent of prison inmates were from this group.&lt;ref name=Free1997&gt;{{Cite journal
|title=The Impact of Federal Sentencing Reforms on African Americans|author=Free, Marvin D. Jr.|journal=Journal of Black Studies|volume=28 |issue=2| pages=268–286|accessdate=2007-05-31 |issn=0021-9347|month=November|year=1997|jstor=2784855}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[McCleskey v. Kemp]], it was alleged the capital sentencing process was administered in a racially discriminatory manner in violation of the [[Equal Protection Clause]] of the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]].

In 2003, [[Amnesty International]] reported those who kill whites are more likely to be executed than those who kill blacks, citing of the 845 people executed since 1977, 80 percent were put to death for killing whites and 13 percent were executed for killing blacks, even though blacks and whites are murdered in almost equal numbers.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|title=Death Penalty Discrimination: Those Who Murder Whites Are More Likely To Be Executed|date=2003-04-24|publisher=Associated Press ([[CBS News]])|url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2003/04/24/national/main550986.shtml|accessdate=2007-06-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Prison system===
{{main|Prisoner rights in the United States}}
{{See also|Incarceration in the United States|United States incarceration rate|Cutter v. Wilkinson}}

The United States is seen by social critics,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amnesty.org/en/region/usa Amnesty International, Human Rights in United States of America], Amnesty International&lt;/ref&gt; including international and domestic [[human rights]] groups and [[civil rights]] organizations, as a state that violates fundamental human rights, because of disproportionately heavy, in comparison with other countries, reliance on crime control, individual behavior control ([[civil liberties]]), and societal control of [[disadvantaged]] groups through a harsh police and [[criminal justice]] system. The U.S. penal system is implemented on the federal, and in particular on the state and local levels. This [[social policy]] has resulted in a [[United States incarceration rate|high rate of incarceration]], which [[The New Jim Crow|affects Americans]] from the lowest [[social class in the United States|socioeconomic backgrounds]] and [[minority group|racial minorities]] the hardest.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pewcenteronthestates.org/uploadedFiles/8015PCTS_Prison08_FINAL_2-1-1_FORWEB.pdf &quot;One in 100: Behind Bars in America 2008&quot;], [[Pew Research Center]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pewcenteronthestates.org/report_detail.aspx?id=49382 &quot;One in 31: The Long Reach of American Corrections&quot;], Pew Research Center, released March 2, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

Some have criticized the United States for having an extremely large prison population, where there have been reported abuses.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.thenation.com/doc/20040105/tuhusdubrow|title=Prison Reform Talking Points|publisher=[[The Nation]]|date=2003-12-19|accessdate=2007-05-27|first=Rebecca|last=Tuhus-Dubrow}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2004 the United States had the highest percentage of people in prison of any nation. There were more than 2.2 million in prisons or jails, or 737 per 100,000 population, or roughly 1 out of every 136 Americans. According to The National Council on Crime and Delinquency, since 1990 the incarceration of youth in adult jails has increased 208%.&lt;ref&gt;[The Consequences Aren’t Minor, The Impact of Trying Youth as Adults and Strategies for Reform - A [[Campaign for Youth Justice]] Report March 2007 pg 7.]&lt;/ref&gt; In some states youth - juvenile is defined as young as 13 years old. The researchers for this report found that Juveniles often were incarcerated to await trial for up to two years and subjected to the same treatment of mainstream inmates. The incarcerated adolescent is often subjected to a highly traumatic environment during this developmental stage. The long term effects are often irreversible and detrimental.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.sentencingproject.org/pdfs/1035.pdf|title=Facts about Prisons and Prisoners|publisher=[[Sentencing Project|The Sentencing Project]]|month=December | year=2006|accessdate=2007-05-27|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;[[Human Rights Watch]] believes the extraordinary rate of incarceration in the United States wreaks havoc on individuals, families and communities, and saps the strength of the nation as a whole.&quot;&lt;ref name=hrw20061201&gt;{{Cite web|author=Fellner, Jamie|title=US Addiction to Incarceration Puts 2.3 Million in Prison|publisher=Human Rights Watch|url=http://hrw.org/english/docs/2006/12/01/usdom14728.htm|accessdate=2007-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Examples of mistreatment claimed include prisoners left naked and exposed in harsh weather or cold air;&lt;ref name=&quot;UN&quot;&gt;Speech by [[Bonnie Kerness]], January 14, 2006, before the United Nations Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination Against Women [http://www.greens.org/s-r/40/40-18.html]&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;routine&quot; use of [[rubber bullet]]s&lt;ref name=&quot;JLP&quot;&gt;''Journal of Law &amp; Policy'' Vol 22:145 - http://law.wustl.edu/Journal/22/p145Martin.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; and [[pepper spray]];,&lt;ref name=&quot;UN&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JLP&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JLP&quot; /&gt; [[solitary confinement]] of violent prisoners in [[sensory deprivation|soundproofed]] cells for 23 or 24 hours a day;&lt;ref name=&quot;UN&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Amnesty International]] Report 1998 [http://www.amnesty.org/ailib/aireport/ar98/amr51.htm]&lt;/ref&gt; and a range of injuries from serious injury to fatal gunshot wounds, with force at one California prison &quot;often vastly disproportionate to the actual need or risk that prison staff faced.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;JLP&quot; /&gt; Such behaviors are illegal, and, &quot;Professional standards clearly limit staff use of force to that which is necessary to control prisoner disorder.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;JLP&quot; /&gt;

Human Rights Watch raised concerns with [[prisoner rape]] and medical care for inmates.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://hrw.org/english/docs/2005/02/28/usdom10223.htm |title=Inhumane Prison Conditions Still Threaten Life, Health of Alabama Inmates Living with HIV/AIDS, According to Court Filings |publisher=Human Rights Watch |accessdate=2006-06-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a survey of 1,788 male inmates in Midwestern prisons by [[Prison Journal]], about 21% claimed they had been coerced or pressured into sexual activity during their incarceration and 7% claimed that they had been raped in their current facility.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title=Sexual Coercion Rates in Seven Midwestern Prisons for Men| author=[[Cindy Struckman-Johnson]] &amp; David Struckman-Johnson| publisher=The Prison Journal|year=2000 |url=http://www.spr.org/pdf/struckman.pdf|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tolerance of serious [[sexual abuse]] and [[prison rape|rape in United States prisons]] are consistently reported as widespread.{{Citation needed|date=December 2007}}&lt;!-- note ref name=AI does not exist at this time --&gt; It has been fought against by organizations such as [[Stop Prisoner Rape]].

The United States has been criticized for having a high amount of non-violent and [[victim-less offender]]s incarcerated,&lt;ref name=hrw20061201/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|first=Sasha|last=Abramsky|title=Hard Time Blues: How Politics Built a Prison Nation|publisher=Thomas Dunne Books|date=January 22, 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=No Price Too High: Victimless Crimes and the Ninth Amendment|publisher=Praeger Publishers|isbn=0-275-95056-5|last=Hardaway|first=Robert|date=October 30, 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; as half of all persons incarcerated under State jurisdiction are for [[non-violent offence]]s and 20 percent are incarcerated for drug offences, mostly for possession of [[cannabis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Prisoners in 2005|publisher=[[United States Department of Justice]]: [[Office of Justice Programs]]|url=http://www.ojp.usdoj.gov/bjs/pub/pdf/p05.pdf|month=November | year=2006|accessdate=2007-06-03|format=PDF |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070409064857/http://www.ojp.usdoj.gov/bjs/pub/pdf/p05.pdf &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-04-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.cjcj.org/pubs/one_million/onemillionexec.html|title=America's One-Million Nonviolent Prisoners|publisher=Center on Juvenile and Criminal Justice|accessdate=2007-06-003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The United States is the only country in the world allowing sentencing of young adolescents to life imprisonment without the possibility of parole. There are currently 73 Americans serving such sentences for crimes they committed at the age of 13 or 14. In December 2006 the [[United Nations]] took up a resolution calling for the abolition of this kind of punishment for children and young teenagers. 185 countries voted for the resolution and only the United States against.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated3&quot;&gt;&quot;Lifers as Teenagers, Now Seeking Second Chance&quot;, ''[[The New York Times]]'' October 17, 2007, by [[Adam Liptak]]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Police brutality===
In a 1999 report, [[Amnesty International]] said it had &quot;documented patterns of ill-treatment across the U.S., including police beatings, unjustified shootings and the use of dangerous restraint techniques.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.amnestyusa.org/document.php?id=133746465C2D34CA8025690000692D98 |title=Race, Rights and Police Brutality |year=1999 |publisher=[[Amnesty International]] USA |accessdate=2007-12-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;
According to a 1998 Human Rights Watch report, incidents of police use of excessive force had occurred in cities throughout the U.S., and this behavior goes largely unchecked.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://hrw.org/english/docs/1998/07/07/usdom1224.htm |title=Report Charges Police Abuse in U.S. Goes Unchecked |date=July 7, 1998 |publisher=[[Human Rights Watch]]
 |accessdate=2007-12-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; An article in USA Today reports that in 2006, 96% of cases referred to the U.S. Justice Department for prosecution by investigative agencies were declined. In 2005, 98% were declined.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.usatoday.com/news/nation/2007-12-17-Copmisconduct_N.htm |title=Police brutality cases on rise since 9/11 |publisher=USA Today |date=2007-12-17 |accessdate=2007-12-22 | first=Kevin | last=Johnson}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2001, the ''New York Times'' reported that the U.S. government is unable or unwilling to collect statistics showing the precise number of people killed by the police or the prevalence of the use of excessive force.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E6DD1139F93AA15757C0A9679C8B63 |title=When the Police Shoot, Who's Counting? |publisher=The New York Times |date=2001-04-29 |accessdate=2007-12-22 | first=Fox | last=Butterfield}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Since 1999, at least 148 people have died in the United States and Canada after being shocked with Tasers by police officers, according to a 2005 ACLU report.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.aclu.org/police/abuse/19977prs20051006.html |title=Unregulated Use of Taser Stun Guns Threatens Lives, ACLU of Northern California Study Finds |publisher=[[ACLU]] |date=October 6, 2005 |accessdate=2007-12-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In one case, a handcuffed suspect was tasered nine times by a police officer before dying, and six of those taserings occurred within less than three minutes. The officer was fired and faced the possibility of criminal charges.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.cnn.com/2008/CRIME/07/22/taser.death/index.html|title=Man dies after cop hits him with Taser 9 times|publisher=CNN.com|date=undated article|accessdate=2008-09-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==War on Terrorism==
{{See also|War on Terrorism|Criticism of the War on Terrorism}}

===Inhumane treatment and torture of captured non-citizens===
{{See also|Torture and the United States|CIA prison system}}

International and U.S. law prohibits torture and other ill-treatment of any person in custody in all circumstances.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Human Rights Watch: Summary of International and U.S. Law Prohibiting Torture and Other Ill-treatment of Persons in Custody|date=May 24, 2004|url=http://www.hrw.org/english/docs/2004/05/24/usint8614.htm|accessdate=2007-05-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the United States Government has categorized a large number of people as [[unlawful combatants]], a United States classification used mainly as an excuse to bypass international law, which denies the privileges of [[prisoner of war]] (POW) designation of the [[Geneva Conventions]].&lt;ref name=ICRC-210705&gt;[[International Committee of the Red Cross|ICRC]] official statement: ''[http://www.icrc.org/web/eng/siteeng0.nsf/html/terrorism-ihl-210705 The relevance of IHL in the context of terrorism]'', 21 July 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

Certain practices of the [[United States military]] and [[Central Intelligence Agency]] have been condemned by some sources domestically and internationally as torture.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://abcnews.go.com/WNT/Investigation/story?id=1322866|title=CIA's Harsh Interrogation Techniques Described|date=2005-11-18|accessdate=2007-05-27|coauthors=Ross, Brain and Eposito, Richard}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.ohchr.org/english/bodies/cat/docs/AdvanceVersions/CAT.C.USA.CO.2.pdf|title=Conclusions and recommendations of the Committee against Torture|publisher=The United Nations Committee against Torture|date=2006-05-19|accessdate=2007-06-02|format=PDF |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20061211164104/http://www.ohchr.org/english/bodies/cat/docs/AdvanceVersions/CAT.C.USA.CO.2.pdf &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2006-12-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; A fierce debate regarding non-standard interrogation techniques&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Non-standard interrogation techniques&quot; are alleged to have at times included:&lt;br /&gt;Extended forced maintenance of &quot;[[stress position]]s&quot; such as standing or squatting; psychological tricks and &quot;mind games&quot;; [[sensory deprivation]]; exposure to loud music and noises; extended exposure to flashing lights; prolonged solitary confinement; denigration of religion; withholding of food, drink, or medical care; withholding of hygienic care or toilet facilities; prolonged hooding; forced injections of unknown substances; sleep deprivation; magneto-cranial stimulation resulting in mental confusion; threats of bodily harm; threats of rendition to torture-friendly states or Guantánamo; threats of rape or sodomy; threats of harm to family members; threats of imminent execution; prolonged constraint in contorted positions (including [[strappado]], or &quot;Palestinian hanging&quot;); facial smearing of real or simulated feces, urine, menstrual blood, or semen; sexual humiliation; beatings, often requiring surgery or resulting in permanent physical or mental disability; release or threat of release to attack dogs, both muzzled or un-muzzled; near-suffocation or asphyxiation via multiple detainment hoods, plastic bags, water-soaked towels or blankets, duct tape, or ligatures; gassing and chemical spraying resulting in unconsciousness; confinement in small chambers too small to fully stand or recline; underwater immersion just short of drowning (i.e. [[dunking]]); and extended exposure to extreme temperatures below freezing or above 120 °F (48 °C).&lt;/ref&gt; exists within the US civilian and military intelligence community, with no general consensus as to what practices under what conditions are acceptable.

Abuse of prisoners is considered a crime in the United States [[Uniform Code of Military Justice]]. According to a January 2006 [[Human Rights First]] report, there were 45 suspected or confirmed homicides while in US custody in Iraq and Afghanistan; &quot;Certainly 8, as many as 12, people were tortured to death.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.humanrightsfirst.org/media/2006_alerts/etn_0222_dic.htm|title=Human Rights First Releases First Comprehensive Report on Detainee Deaths in U.S. Custody|publisher=[[Human Rights First]]|date=2006-02-22|accessdate=2007-05-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Abu Ghraib prison abuse====
{{Summarize section|date=August 2012}}
{{Off-topic|date=September 2010}}
 {{See also|Abu Ghraib torture and prisoner abuse}}
In 2004, photos showing humiliation and abuse of prisoners were leaked from [[Abu Ghraib prison]], causing a political and media scandal in the US. Forced humiliation of the detainees included, but is not limited to nudity, rape, human piling of nude detainees, masturbation, eating food out of toilets, crawling on hand and knees while American soldiers were sitting on their back sometimes requiring them to bark like dogs, and hooking up electrical wires to fingers, toes, and penises.&lt;ref name=AbuGhraibAbuse&gt;{{Cite news|last=Higham|first=Scott|coauthors=Stephens, Joe|page=A01|date=2004-05-21|accessdate=2007-06-23|title=New Details of Prison Abuse Emerge|publisher=Washington Post|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A43783-2004May20.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Bertrand Ramcharan]], acting UN High Commissioner for Human Rights stated that while the removal of Saddam Hussein represented &quot;a major contribution to human rights in Iraq&quot; and that the United States had condemned the conduct at Abu Ghraib and pledged to bring violators to justice, &quot;willful killing, torture and inhuman treatment&quot; represented a grave breach of international law and &quot;might be designated as war crimes by a competent tribunal.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.globalpolicy.org/intljustice/general/2004/0604crime.htm &quot;UN Says Abu Ghraib Abuse Could Constitute War Crime&quot;, By Warren Hoge, New York Times, June 4, 2004]&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to the acts of humiliation, there were more violent claims, such as American soldiers sodomizing detainees (including an event involving an underage boy), an incident where a phosphoric light was broken and the chemicals poured on a detainee, repeated beatings, and threats of death.&lt;ref name=AbuGhraibAbuse/&gt; Six military personnel were charged with prisoner abuse in the [[Abu Ghraib torture and prisoner abuse]] scandal. The harshest sentence was handed out to [[Charles Graner]], who received a 10 year sentence to be served in a military prison and a demotion to private; the other offenders received lesser sentences.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://abcnews.go.com/International/popup?id=140764|publisher=[[ABC News]]|accessdate=2007-05-28|title=Prisoner Abuse: The Accused}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In their report ''The Road to Abu Ghraib'', [[Human Rights Watch]] describe how:
&lt;blockquote&gt;The severest abuses at Abu Ghraib occurred in the immediate aftermath of a decision by Secretary Rumsfeld to step up the hunt for &quot;actionable intelligence&quot; among Iraqi prisoners. The officer who oversaw intelligence gathering at Guantanamo was brought in to overhaul interrogation practices in Iraq, and teams of interrogators from Guantanamo were sent to Abu Ghraib. The commanding general in Iraq issued orders to &quot;manipulate an internee's emotions and weaknesses.&quot; Military police were ordered by military intelligence to &quot;set physical and mental conditions for favorable interrogation of witnesses.&quot; The captain who oversaw interrogations at the Afghan detention center where two prisoners died in detention posted &quot;Interrogation Rules of Engagement&quot; at Abu Ghraib, authorizing coercive methods (with prior written approval of the military commander) such as the use of military guard dogs to instill fear that violate the Geneva Conventions and the Convention against Torture and Other Cruel, Inhuman Degrading Treatment or Punishment.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/en/node/12123/section/2 The Road to Abu Ghraib, Human Rights Watch]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

====Enhanced interrogation and waterboarding====
{{See also|Waterboarding|Enhanced interrogation techniques}}
{{Summarize section|date=August 2012}}
On February 6, 2008, the CIA director General [[Michael Hayden (general)|Michael Hayden]] stated that the CIA had used waterboarding on three prisoners during 2002 and 2003, namely [[Khalid Shaikh Mohammed]], [[Abu Zubayda]] and [[Abd al-Rahim al-Nashiri]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite web|url=http://jurist.law.pitt.edu/paperchase/2008/02/cia-chief-confirms-use-of-waterboarding.php |title=CIA chief confirms use of waterboarding on 3 terror detainees | work=Jurist Legal News &amp; Research |publisher=University of Pittsburgh School of Law |accessdate=2008-05-13 |last=Price |first=Caitlin
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=TheAustralian&gt;{{Cite web|date=2008-02-07|url=http://www.theaustralian.news.com.au/story/0,25197,23170732-2703,00.html|title=CIA finally admits to waterboarding|publisher=The Australian|accessdate=2008-02-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The June 21, 2004 issue of ''[[Newsweek]]'' stated that the [[Bybee memo]], a 2002 legal memorandum drafted by former OLC lawyer [[John Yoo]] that described what sort of interrogation tactics against suspected terrorists or terrorist affiliates the Bush administration would consider legal, was &quot;...prompted by CIA questions about what to do with a top Qaeda captive, [[Abu Zubaydah]], who had turned uncooperative ... and was drafted after White House meetings convened by George W. Bush's chief counsel, [[Alberto Gonzales]], along with Defense Department general counsel [[William Haynes]] and [[David Addington]], Vice President [[Dick Cheney]]'s counsel, who discussed specific interrogation techniques,&quot; citing &quot;a source familiar with the discussions.&quot; Amongst the methods they found acceptable was waterboarding.&lt;ref name='Newsweek WB_062104'&gt;{{Cite news| first=Michael | last=Hirsh | coauthors= John Barry, Daniel Klaidman | title=A tortured debate: amid feuding and turf battles, lawyers in the White House discussed specific terror-interrogation techniques like 'water-boarding' and 'mock-burials' | date=2004-06-21 | publisher=Newsweek | url =http://www.newsweek.com/id/54093/page/1 | accessdate = 2007-12-20 | language = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 2005, [[ABC News]] reported that former CIA agents claimed that the CIA engaged in a modern form of waterboarding, along with five other &quot;[[enhanced interrogation techniques]],&quot; against suspected members of [[al Qaeda]].

[[UN High Commissioner for Human Rights]], [[Louise Arbour]], stated on the subject of waterboarding &quot;I would have no problems with describing this practice as falling under the prohibition of torture,&quot; and that violators of the UN [[Convention Against Torture]] should be prosecuted under the principle of [[universal jurisdiction]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Louise Arbour&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://news.ninemsn.com.au/article.aspx?id=96287 |title=Waterboarding qualifies as torture: UN |accessdate=2008-02-24 |work=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bent Sørensen, Senior Medical Consultant to the [[International Rehabilitation Council for Torture Victims]] and former member of the United Nations [[Committee Against Torture]] has said:

&lt;blockquote&gt;It’s a clear-cut case: Waterboarding can without any reservation be labeled as torture. It fulfils all of the four central criteria that according to the United Nations Convention Against Torture (UNCAT) defines an act of torture. First, when water is forced into your lungs in this fashion, in addition to the pain you are likely to experience an immediate and extreme fear of death. You may even suffer a heart attack from the stress or damage to the lungs and brain from inhalation of water and oxygen deprivation. In other words there is no doubt that waterboarding causes severe physical and/or mental suffering – one central element in the UNCAT’s definition of torture. In addition the CIA’s waterboarding clearly fulfills the three additional definition criteria stated in the Convention for a deed to be labeled torture, since it is 1) done intentionally, 2) for a specific purpose and 3) by a representative of a state – in this case the US.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bent Sørensen&quot;&gt;Bent Sørensen on waterboarding as torture
*[http://www.irct.org/Default.aspx?ID=3558&amp;M=News&amp;NewsID=1236 Former member of UN Committee Against Torture: &quot;Yes, waterboarding is torture&quot;] International Rehabilitation Council for Torture Victims, February 12, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Lt. Gen. [[Michael D. Maples]], the director of the [[Defense Intelligence Agency]], concurred by stating, in a hearing before the Senate Armed Services Committee, that he believes waterboarding violates [[Common Article 3 of the Geneva Conventions]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Maples&quot;&gt;Violating international law
*[http://opiniojuris.org/2008/02/27/yes-virginia-waterboarding-does-violate-international-law/ Yes, Virginia, Waterboarding Does Violate International Law] by [[Kevin Jon Heller]], [[Opinio Juris]], February 27, 2008
*[http://tpmmuckraker.talkingpointsmemo.com/2008/02/army_official_yes_waterboardin.php Army Official: Yes, Waterboarding Breaks International Law] By Paul Kiel, [[Talking Points Memo]], February 27, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

The CIA director testified that waterboarding has not been used since 2003.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usatoday.com/news/washington/2008-02-06-waterboarding_N.htm White House defends waterboarding; CIA chief uncertain], ''Associated Press'', February 7, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

In April 2009, the [[Obama administration]] released four memos in which government lawyers from the Bush administration approved tough interrogation methods used against 28 terror suspects. The rough tactics range from [[waterboarding]] (simulated drowning) to keeping suspects naked and denying them solid food.&lt;ref name=&quot;waterboarding1&quot;&gt;[http://www.wtop.com/?nid=116&amp;pid=0&amp;sid=1651572&amp;page=1 No charges against CIA officials for waterboarding: WTOP, April 16, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;

These memos were accompanied by the Justice Department's release of four Bush-era legal opinions covering (in graphic and extensive detail) the interrogation of 14 high-value terror detainees using harsh techniques beyond [[waterboarding]]. These additional techniques include keeping detainees in a painful standing position for long periods (Used often, once for 180 hours),&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/8006597.stm BBC website, CIA torture exemption 'illegal', Sunday, 19 April 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; using a plastic neck collar to slam detainees into walls, keeping the detainee's cell cold for long periods, beating and kicking the detainee, [[insects]] placed in a confinement box (the suspect had a fear of [[insects]]), sleep-deprivation, prolonged shackling, and threats to a detainee's family. One of the memos also authorized a method for combining multiple techniques.&lt;ref name=&quot;waterboarding1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2009/apr/16/torture-memos-bush-administration The Guardian, Obama releases Bush torture memos, 16 April 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;

Details from the memos also included the number of times that techniques such as [[waterboarding]] were used. A footnote said that one detainee was waterboarded 83 times in one month, while another was waterboarded 183 times in a month.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://documents.nytimes.com/justice-department-memos-on-interrogation-techniques#p=121|title=Justice Department Memos on Interrogation Techniques |accessdate=2009-04-30|publisher=New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;programme1&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/today/hi/today/newsid_8007000/8007770.stm BBC Today Programme, 20 April 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; This may have gone beyond even what was allowed by the CIA's own directives, which limit waterboarding to 12 times a day.&lt;ref name=&quot;programme1&quot;/&gt;
The [[Fox News]] website carried reports from an unnamed US official who claimed that these were the number of pourings, not the number of sessions.&lt;ref name=&quot;FNC20090428Abrams&quot;&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/politics/2009/04/28/despite-reports-khalid-sheikh-mohammed-waterboarded-times/ Despite Reports, Khalid Sheikh Mohammed Was Not Waterboarded 183 Times], Joseph Abrams, ''[[Fox News Channel]]'', April 28, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Physicians for Human Rights]] has accused the Bush administration of conducting illegal human experiments and unethical medical research during interrogations of suspected terrorists.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://articles.latimes.com/2010/jun/08/nation/la-na-torture-20100608 |author=Bob Drogin | title=Physicians group accuses CIA of testing torture techniques on detainees |publisher=The Los Angeles Times |date=June 8, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The group has suggested this activity was a violation of the standards set by the [[Nuremberg Trials]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://physiciansforhumanrights.org/library/news-2010-06-07.html |title=Evidence Indicates that the Bush Administration Conducted Experiments and Research on Detainees to Design Torture Techniques and Create Legal Cover |publisher=Physicians for Human Rights |date=June 7, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Guantánamo Bay====
The United States maintains a detention center at its military base at [[Guantánamo Bay]], Cuba where numerous [[enemy combatants]] of the war on terror are held. The detention center has been the source of various controversies regarding the legality of the center and the treatment of detainees.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal| title=One rule for them| first=George| last=Monbiot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Guantanamo1&quot;&gt;''In re Guantanamo Detainee Cases'', 355 F.Supp.2d 443 (D.D.C. 2005).&lt;/ref&gt; [[Amnesty International]] has called the situation &quot;a human rights scandal&quot; in a series of reports.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| url=http://web.amnesty.org/pages/guantanamobay-index-eng| publisher=Amnesty International| title=Guantánamo Bay - a human rights scandal| accessdate = 2006-03-15 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20060206065717/http://web.amnesty.org/pages/guantanamobay-index-eng &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2006-02-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; 775 detainees have been brought to Guantánamo. Of these, many have been released without charge. {{RemainingAtGuantanamo}} The United States assumed territorial control over Guantánamo Bay under the 1903 [[Cuban-American Treaty]], which granted the United States a perpetual lease of the area.&lt;ref&gt;http://avalon.law.yale.edu/20th_century/dip_cuba002.asp&lt;/ref&gt; United States, by virtue of its complete jurisdiction and control, maintains &quot;de facto&quot; sovereignty over this territory, while Cuba retained ultimate sovereignty over the territory. The current government of Cuba regards the U.S. presence in Guantánamo as illegal and insists the Cuban-American Treaty was obtained by threat of force in violation of international law.&lt;ref&gt;De Zayas, Alfred. (2003.) [http://www.law.ubc.ca/files/pdf/events/2003/november/GUANTANA.pdf The Status of Guantánamo Bay and the Status of the Detainees.]&lt;/ref&gt;

A delegation of [[UN Special Rapporteur]]s to [[Guantanamo Bay detention camp|Guantanamo Bay]] claimed that interrogation techniques used in the detention center amount to degrading treatment in violation of the ICCPR and the [[Convention Against Torture]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://daccessdds.un.org/doc/UNDOC/GEN/G06/112/76/PDF/G0611276.pdf?OpenElement ECONOMIC, SOCIAL AND CULTURAL RIGHTS CIVIL AND POLITICAL RIGHTS Situation of detainees at Guantánamo Bay Report of the Chairperson-Rapporteur of the Working Group on Arbitrary Detention, Leila Zerrougui; the Special Rapporteur on the independence of judges and lawyers, Leandro Despouy; the Special Rapporteur on torture and other cruel, inhuman or degrading treatment or punishment, Manfred Nowak; the Special Rapporteur on freedom of religion or belief, Asma Jahangir; and the Special Rapporteur on the right of everyone to the enjoyment of the highest attainable standard of physical and mental health, Paul Hunt]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005 [[Amnesty International]] expressed alarm at the erosion in civil liberties since the 9/11 attacks. According to Amnesty International:

:The Guantánamo Bay detention camp has become a symbol of the United States administration’s refusal to put human rights and the rule of law at the heart of its response to the atrocities of 11 September 2001. It has become synonymous with the United States executive’s pursuit of unfettered power, and has become firmly associated with the systematic denial of human dignity and resort to cruel, inhuman or degrading treatment that has marked the USA’s detentions and interrogations in the &quot;war on terror&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://web.amnesty.org/library/Index/ENGAMR510632005|title=Guantánamo and beyond: The continuing pursuit of unchecked executive power|publisher=Amnesty International|date=2005-05-13|accessdate=2007-05-29 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070509025445/http://web.amnesty.org/library/Index/ENGAMR510632005 |archivedate = 2007-05-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Amnesty International also condemned the Guantánamo facility as &quot;...the [[gulag]] of our times,&quot; which raised heated conversation in the United States. The purported legal status of &quot;''unlawful combatants''&quot; in those nations currently holding detainees under that name has been the subject of criticism by other nations and international human rights institutions including Human Rights Watch and the [[International Committee of the Red Cross]]. The ICRC, in response to the US-led military campaign in Afghanistan, published a paper on the subject.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.icrc.org/Web/eng/siteeng0.nsf/htmlall/5LPHBV/%24File/irrc_849_Dorman.pdf The legal situation of unlawful/unprivileged combatants (IRRC March 2003 Vol.85 No 849)]. See [[Unlawful combatant]].&lt;/ref&gt; HRW cites two sergeants and a captain accusing U.S. troops of torturing prisoners in Iraq and Afghanistan.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.hrw.org/english/docs/2005/09/25/usint11776.htm|publisher=Human Rights Watch|date=2005-09-24|accessdate=2007-05-29|title=New Account of Torture by U.S. Tropps, Soldiers Say Failures by Command Led to Abuse}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, former [[US Republican Party|Republican]] governor [[Mike Huckabee]], for example, has stated that the conditions in [[Guantanamo Bay detention camp|Guantánamo]] are better than most US prisons.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,280457,00.html |title=Huckabee Says Guantanamo Bay Offers Better Conditions to Detainees Than Most U.S. Prisons - You Decide 2008 |publisher=FOXNews.com |date=2007-06-11 |accessdate=2009-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The US government argues that even if detainees were entitled to POW status, they would not have the right to lawyers, access to the courts to challenge their detention, or the opportunity to be released prior to the end of hostilities—and that nothing in the Third Geneva Convention provides POWs such rights, and POWs in past wars have generally not been given these rights.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.defenselink.mil/news/Jul2007/Legal%20basis%20Guantanamo%20Detainees%20OGC%20FINAL.pdf|format=PDF|publisher=[[White House]]|accessdate=2007-11-17|title=Guantanamo Detainees Info Sheet #1 – November 14, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[U.S. Supreme Court]] ruled in ''[[Hamdan v. Rumsfeld]]'' on June 29, 2006 that they were entitled to the minimal protections listed under [[Geneva Conventions#Common Article 3|Common Article 3]] of the Geneva Conventions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| url=http://www.supremecourt.gov/opinions/05pdf/05-184.pdf| title=Hamdan v. Rumsfeld| month=June 29| year=2006| accessdate = 2007-02-10|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following this, on July 7, 2006, the [[United States Department of Defense|Department of Defense]] issued an internal memo stating that prisoners would in the future be entitled to protection under Common Article 3.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/5169600.stm|publisher=BBC|title=US detainees to get Geneva rights|date=2006-07-11 | accessdate=January 5, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.cnn.com/2006/POLITICS/07/11/congress.guantanamo.ap/|title=White House: Detainees entitled to Geneva Convention protections|date=2006-07-11|publisher=CNN}} {{Dead link|date=August 2010|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2006/07/11/politics/main1790470.shtml|title=White House Changes Gitmo Policy|publisher=CBS News|date=2006-07-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Extraordinary rendition====
{{See also|Extraordinary rendition by the United States}}

United States citizens and foreign nationals are occasionally captured and [[Kidnapping|abducted]] outside of the United States and transferred to secret US administered detention facilities, sometimes being held incommunicado for periods of months or years, a process known as [[Extraordinary rendition by the United States|extraordinary rendition]].

According to ''[[The New Yorker]]'', &quot;The most common destinations for rendered suspects are [[Egypt]], [[Morocco]], [[Syria]], and Jordan, all of which have been cited for human-rights violations by the State Department, and are known to torture suspects.&quot;&lt;ref name=NewYorker&gt;{{Cite news|first=Jane|last=Mayer|date=2005-02-14|accessdate=2007-05-29|title=Outsourcing Torture|publisher=[[The New Yorker]]|url=http://www.newyorker.com/archive/2005/02/14/050214fa_fact6?currentPage=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Notable cases=====
In November 2001, [[Yaser Esam Hamdi]], a U.S. citizen, was captured by [[Afghan Northern Alliance]] forces in [[Konduz]], [[Afghanistan]], amongst hundreds of surrendering [[Taliban]] fighters and was transferred into U.S. custody. The U.S. government alleged that Hamdi was there fighting for the Taliban, while Hamdi, through his father, has claimed that he was merely there as a relief worker and was mistakenly captured. Hamdi was transferred into CIA custody and transferred to the [[Guantanamo Bay Naval Base]], but when it was discovered that he was a U.S. citizen, he was transferred to naval brig in [[Norfolk, Virginia|Norfolk]], [[Virginia]] and then he was transferred brig in [[Charleston, South Carolina|Charleston]], [[South Carolina]]. The [[George W. Bush|Bush Administration]] identified him as an [[unlawful combatant]] and denied him access to an attorney or the court system, despite his [[Fifth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fifth Amendment]] right to [[due process]]. In 2002 Hamdi's father filed a ''[[habeas corpus]]'' petition, the Judge ruled in Hamdi's favor and required he be allowed a public defender; however, on appeal the decision was reversed. In 2004, in the case of ''[[Hamdi v. Rumsfeld]]'' the U.S. Supreme court reversed the dismissal of a ''habeas corpus'' petition and ruled detainees who are U.S. citizens must have the ability to challenge their detention before an impartial judge.

In December 2004, [[Khalid El-Masri]], a [[Germany|German]] citizen, was apprehended by [[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonian]] authorities when traveling to [[Skopje]] because his name was similar to [[Khalid al-Masri]], an alleged mentor to the al-Qaeda [[Hamburg cell]]. After being held in a motel in Macedonia for over three weeks he was transferred to the CIA and [[Extraordinary rendition by the United States|extradited]] to Afghanistan. While held in Afghanistan, El-Masri claims he was sodomized, beaten, and repeatedly interrorgated about alleged terrorist ties.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/05/18/AR2006051802107.html|title=Lawsuit Against CIA is Dismissed|first=Jerry|last=Markon|date=2006-05-19|accessdate=2007-05-29|publisher=Washington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt; After being in custody for five months, [[Condoleezza Rice]] learned of his detention and ordered his release. El-Masri was released at night on a desolate road in [[Albania]], without apology or funds to return home. He was intercepted by Albanian guards, who believed he was a terrorist due to his haggard and unkept appearance. He was subsequently reunited with his wife who had returned to her family in [[Lebanon]] with their children because she thought her husband had abandoned them. Using [[isotope analysis]], scientists at the Bavarian archive for [[geology]] in [[Munich]] analyzed his hair and verified that he was malnourished during his disappearance.&lt;ref name=&quot;derspiegel050214&quot;&gt;Georg Mascolo, Holger Stark: ''[http://service.spiegel.de/cache/international/spiegel/0,1518,341636,00.html The US Stands Accused of Kidnapping]''. SPIEGEL ONLINE, February 14, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, U.S. President Bush signed an [[Executive order (United States)|Executive order]] banning the use of torture in the [[CIA]]'s interrogation program.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.freedomhouse.org/template.cfm?page=363&amp;year=2008 |title=Map of Freedom in the World |publisher=freedomhouse.org |date=2004-05-10 |accessdate=2009-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the [[Human Rights Watch]] report (September 2012) the United States government during the U.S. President Bush republican administration “waterboarding” [[torture]]d opponents of [[Muammar Gaddafi]] during interrogations, then transferred them to mistreatment in [[Libya]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/news/2012/09/05/us-torture-and-rendition-gaddafi-s-libya US: Torture and Rendition to Gaddafi’s Libya [[Human Rights Watch]] September 6, 2012&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/sites/default/files/reports/libya0912webwcover_1.pdf Delivered Into Enemy Hands
US-Led Abuse and Rendition of Opponents to Gaddafi’s Libya]] [[Human Rights Watch]] 2012&lt;/ref&gt;
President [[Barack Obama]] has denied water torture.&lt;ref&gt;[http://yle.fi/uutiset/hrw_usa_kaytti_vesikidutusta_libyalaisiin/6284059 HRW: USA käytti vesikidutusta libyalaisiin] yle  6.9.2012 {{fi}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==International comparison==
According to Canadian historian [[Michael Ignatieff]], during and after the [[Cold War]], the United States placed greater emphasis than other nations on human rights as part of its foreign policy, awarded foreign aid to facilitate human rights progress, and annually assessed the human rights records of other national governments.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ignatieff1&quot;/&gt;

===Support===
The [[U.S. Department of State]] publishes a yearly report &quot;Supporting Human Rights and Democracy: The U.S. Record&quot; in compliance with a 2002 law that requires the Department to report on actions taken by the U.S. Government to encourage respect for human rights.&lt;ref name=StateDeptUSRecord&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/shrd//|accessdate=2007-06-22|title=Supporting Human Rights and Democracy: The U.S. Record|publisher=[[United States Department of State]]: [[Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; It also publishes a yearly &quot;Country Reports on Human Rights Practices.&quot;.&lt;ref name=StateDept&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/hrrpt/|accessdate=2007-05-28|title=Human Rights|publisher=[[United States Department of State]]: Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2006 the United States created a &quot;Human Rights Defenders Fund&quot; and &quot;Freedom Awards.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.state.gov/g/drl/hr/c20063.htm|accessdate=2007-05-28|title=International Human Rights Week|publisher=[[United States Department of State]]: Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070509003647/http://www.state.gov/g/drl/hr/c20063.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-05-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; The &quot;Ambassadorial Roundtable Series&quot;, created in 2006, are informal discussions between newly-confirmed U.S. [[Ambassador]]s and human rights and democracy non-governmental organizations.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.state.gov/g/drl/hr/c18970.htm|title=Ambassadorial Roundtable Series|publisher=[[United States Department of State]]: Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor|accessdate=2007-05-28 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070509003619/http://www.state.gov/g/drl/hr/c18970.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-05-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; The United States also support democracy and human rights through several other tools.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.state.gov/g/drl/|title=Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor|publisher=[[United States Department of State]]: Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor|accessdate=2007-06-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The &quot;Human Rights and Democracy Achievement Award&quot; recognizes the exceptional achievement of officers of foreign affairs agencies posted abroad.
*In 2006 the award went to Joshua Morris of the embassy in Mauritania who recognized necessary democracy and human rights improvements in Mauritania and made democracy promotion one of his primary responsibilities. He persuaded the Government of Mauritania to re-open voter registration lists to an additional 85,000 citizens, which includes a significant number of Afro-Mauritanian minority individuals. He also organized and managed the largest youth-focused democracy project in Mauritania in 5 years.
*Nathaniel Jensen of the embassy in Vietnam was runner-up. He successfully advanced the human rights agenda on several fronts, including organizing the resumption of a bilateral Human Rights Dialogue, pushing for the release of Vietnam’s prisoners of concern, and dedicating himself to improving religion freedom in northern Vietnam.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.state.gov/g/drl/|title=2006 Human Rights and Democracy Achievement Award|publisher=[[United States Department of State]]: Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor|accessdate=2007-06-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Under legislation by congress, the United States declared that countries utilizing child soldiers may no longer be eligible for US military assistance, in an attempt to end this practice.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|author=Jo Becker, children’s rights advocate |url=http://www.hrw.org/en/news/2008/12/11/us-limits-military-aid-nations-using-child-soldiers |title=US Limits Military Aid to Nations Using Child Soldiers &amp;#124; Human Rights Watch |publisher=Hrw.org |date=2008-12-11 |accessdate=2009-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Treaties ratified===
:''See also [[International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights#United States|International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights - United States]]''

The U.S. has signed and ratified the following human rights treaties:
* [[International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights]] (ICCPR) (ratified with 5 [[reservation (law)|reservations]], 5 understandings, and 4 declarations.)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www1.umn.edu/humanrts/usdocs/civilres.html U.S. reservations, declarations, and understandings, International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights, 138 Cong. Rec. S4781-01 (daily ed., April 2, 1992).]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Optional protocol on the involvement of children in armed conflict]]
* [[International Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination]]
* [[United Nations Convention Against Torture|Convention against Torture and Other Cruel, Inhuman or Degrading Treatment or Punishment]]
* [[Protocol relating to the Status of Refugees]]&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;[http://academic.udayton.edu/race/06hrights/unitednations/USStatus.htm Status of US international treaty ratifications]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Optional Protocol to the Convention on the Rights of the Child on the Sale of Children, Child Prostitution and Child Pornography]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.unhchr.ch/tbs/doc.nsf/newhvstatbytreaty?OpenView&lt;/ref&gt;

Non-binding documents voted for:
* [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unhchr.ch/udhr/miscinfo/carta.htm DPI Press Kit]&lt;/ref&gt;

===International Bill of Rights===
:''See also [[International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights#United States|International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights - United States]]''

The [[International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights]] (ICCPR) and the [[International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights]] (ICESCR) are the legal treaties that enshrine the rights outlined in the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]]. Together, and along with the [[First Optional Protocol to the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights|first]] and [[First Optional Protocol to the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights|second]] optional protocols of the [[ICCPR]] they constitute the [[International bill of rights]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www2.ohchr.org/english/law/|title=OHCHR International law|publisher=OHCHR|accessdate=2009-06-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu6/2/fs2.htm UN OHCHR Fact Sheet No.2 (Rev.1), The International Bill of Human Rights]&lt;/ref&gt; The US has not ratified the [[ICESCR]] or either of the optional protocols of the [[ICCPR]].

The US's ratification of the [[ICCPR]] was done with five [[Reservation (law)|reservations]] – or limits – on the treaty, 5 understandings and 4 declarations. Among these is the rejection of sections of the treaty that prohibit [[capital punishment]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.ohchr.org/english/bodies/ratification/docs/DeclarationsReservationsICCPR.pdf OHCHR Reservations and declarations on ratificatons]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.twnside.org.sg/title/1893-cn.htm America'S Problem With Human Rights&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Included in the Senate's ratification was the declaration that &quot;the provisions of Article 1 through 27 of the Covenant are not self-executing&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;138 Cong. Rec. S4781-84 (1992)&lt;/ref&gt; and in a [[Senate Executive Report]] stated that the declaration was meant to &quot;clarify that the Covenant will not create a private cause of action in U.S. Courts.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;S. Exec. Rep. No. 102-23 (1992)&lt;/ref&gt; This way of ratifying the treaty was criticized as incompatible with the Supremacy Clause by [[Louis Henkin]].&lt;ref&gt;Louis Henkin, U.S. Ratification of Human Rights Treaties: The Ghost of Senator Bricker, 89 Am. J. Int’l L. 341, 346 (1995)&lt;/ref&gt;

As a reservation that is &quot;incompatible with the object and purpose&quot; of a treaty is void as a matter of international law, Vienna Convention on the Law of Treaties, art. 19, 1155 U.N.T.S. 331 (entered into force Jan. 27, 1980) (specifying conditions under which signatory States can offer &quot;reservations&quot;), there is some issue as to whether the non-self-execution declaration is even legal under domestic law. At any rate, the United States is but a signatory in name only.

===International Criminal Court===
{{Further|United States and the International Criminal Court}}

The U.S. has not ratified the [[Rome Statute]] of the [[International Criminal Court]] (ICC), which was drafted for prosecuting individuals above the authority of national courts in the event of accusations of [[genocide]], [[crimes against humanity]], [[war crimes]], and [[crime of aggression]]. Nations that have accepted the Rome Statute can defer to the jurisdiction of the ICC or must surrender their jurisdiction when ordered.

The US rejected the Rome Statute after its attempts to include the nation of origin as a party in international proceedings failed, and after certain requests were not met, including recognition of gender issues, &quot;rigorous&quot; qualifications for judges, viable definitions of crimes, protection of national security information that might be sought by the court, and jurisdiction of the UN Security Council to halt court proceedings in special cases.&lt;ref name=&quot;US objections to RS&quot;/&gt; Since the passage of the statute, the US has actively encouraged nations around the world to sign &quot;bilateral immunity agreements&quot; prohibiting the surrender of US personnel before the ICC&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iccnow.org/?mod=bia Coalition for the ICC]&lt;/ref&gt; and actively attempted to undermine the [[Rome Statute]] of the [[International Criminal Court]].&lt;ref name=&quot;hrw.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/campaigns/icc/us.htm Human Rights Watch - The US and the International Criminal Court]&lt;/ref&gt; The US Congress also passed a law, [[American Service-Members' Protection Act]] (ASPA) authorizing the use of military force to free any US personnel that are brought before the court rather than its own court system.&lt;ref&gt;Human Rights Watch, “[http://www.hrw.org/press/2002/08/aspa080302.htm U.S.: 'Hague Invasion Act' Becomes Law].” 3 August 2002. Retrieved 8 January 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;John Sutherland, “[http://www.guardian.co.uk/Archive/Article/0,4273,4456801,00.html Who are America's real enemies?]” ''The Guardian'', 8 July 2002. Retrieved 8 January 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Human Rights Watch criticized the United States for removing itself from the Statute.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC News&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/1970312.stm BBC News]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Judge [[Richard Goldstone]], the first chief prosecutor at [[ICTY|The Hague war crimes tribunal on the former Yugoslavia]], echoed these sentiments saying:

&lt;blockquote&gt;I think it is a very backwards step. It is unprecedented which I think to an extent smacks of pettiness in the sense that it is not going to affect in any way the establishment of the international criminal court...The US have really isolated themselves and are putting themselves into bed with the likes of China, the Yemen and other undemocratic countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC News&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

While the US has maintained that it will &quot;bring to justice those who commit genocide, crimes against humanity and war crimes,&quot; its primary objections to the Rome Statute have revolved around the issues of jurisdiction and process. A US ambassador for War Crimes Issues to the UN Security Council said to the US Senate Foreign Relations Committee that because the Rome Statute requires only one nation to submit to the ICC, and that this nation can be the country in which an alleged crime was committed rather than defendant’s country of origin, U.S military personnel and US foreign peaceworkers in more than 100 countries could be tried in international court without the consent of the US. The ambassador states that &quot;most atrocities are committed internally and most internal conflicts are between warring parties of the same nationality, the worst offenders of international humanitarian law can choose never to join the treaty and be fully insulated from its reach absent a Security Council referral. Yet multinational peacekeeping forces operating in a country that has joined the treaty can be exposed to the court's jurisdiction even if the country of the individual peacekeeper has not joined the treaty.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;US objections to RS&quot;&gt;[http://www.state.gov/www/policy_remarks/1998/980723_scheffer_icc.html 98/07/23 Amb. Scheffer on international criminal court]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other treaties not signed or signed but not ratified===
Where the signature is subject to ratification, acceptance or approval, the signature does not establish the consent to be bound. However, it is a means of authentication and expresses the willingness of the signatory state to continue the treaty-making process. The signature qualifies the signatory state to proceed to ratification, acceptance or approval. It also creates an obligation to refrain, in good faith, from acts that would defeat the object and the purpose of the treaty.&lt;ref&gt;Vienna Convention on the Law of Treaties between States and International Organizations or between International Organizations 1986 Article 18. [http://untreaty.un.org/ilc/texts/instruments/english/conventions/1_2_1986.pdf][http://untreaty.un.org/English/guide.asp]&lt;/ref&gt;

The U.S. has not ratified the following international human rights treaties:&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt;
* [[First Optional Protocol to the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights]] (ICCPR)
* [[Second Optional Protocol to the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights]], aiming at the abolition of the death penalty
* [[Optional Protocol to the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women|Optional Protocol to CEDAW]]
* [[Optional Protocol to the Convention against Torture]]
* [[Convention relating to the Status of Refugees]] (1951)
* [[Convention Relating to the Status of Stateless Persons]] (1954)
* [[1961 Convention on the Reduction of Statelessness|Convention on the Reduction of Statelessness]] (1961)
* [[United Nations Convention on the Protection of the Rights of All Migrant Workers and Members of Their Families|International Convention on the Protection of the Rights of All Migrant Workers and Members of their Families]]

The US has signed but not ratified the following treaties:

* [[Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women]] (CEDAW) (signed but not ratified)
* [[Convention on the Rights of the Child]] (CRC) (signed but not ratified)
*[[International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights]] (signed but not ratified)

Non-binding documents voted against:
* [[Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples]] in September 2007.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iwgia.org/sw248.asp Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Inter-American human rights system===
The US is a signatory to the 1948 [[American Declaration of the Rights and Duties of Man]] and has signed but not ratified the 1969 [[American Convention on Human Rights]]. It is a member of Inter-American Convention on the Granting of Political Rights to Women (1948). It does not accept the adjudicatory jurisdiction of the [[Costa Rica]]-based [[Inter-American Court of Human Rights]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cidh.org/Basicos/English/Basic4.Amer.Conv.Ratif.htm Basic Documents - Ratifications of the Convention&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.state.gov/p/wha/rls/fs/2007/85564.htm Organization of American States&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The US has not ratified any of the other regional human rights treaties of the [[Organization of American States]],&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot; /&gt; which include:

* [[Protocol to the American Convention on Human Rights to Abolish the Death Penalty]] (1990)
* [[Additional Protocol to the American Convention on Human Rights in the Area of Economic, Social and Cultural Rights]]
* [[Inter-American Convention to Prevent and Punish Torture]] (1985)
* [[Inter-American Convention on the Prevention, Punishment and Eradication of Violence Against Women]] (1994)
* [[Inter-American Convention on Forced Disappearance of Persons]] (1994)
* [[Inter-American Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Persons with Disabilities]]

===Coverage of violations in the media===
Studies have found that the ''New York Times'' coverage of worldwide human rights violations is seriously biased, predominantly focusing on the human rights violations in nations where there is clear U.S. involvement, while having relatively little coverage of the human rights violations in other nations.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|journal=The Harvard International Journal of Press|url=http://muse.jhu.edu/login?uri=/journals/harvard_international_journal_of_press_politics/v004/4.4caliendo.html|title=All the News That's Fit to Print? New York Times Coverage of Human-Rights Violations|volume= 4|issue= 4, Fall 1999|pages=48–69|coauthors=Caliendo, Stephen; Gibney, Mark; Tables, Angela|accessdate=2007-05-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.allacademic.com/meta/p152798_index.html|title=Paper presented at the annual meeting of the American Political Science Association|publisher=[http://www.allacademic.com/ All Academic, Inc]|coauthors=Caliendo, Stephen and Gibney, Mark|accessdate=2007-05-28|date=2006-08-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Amnesty International]]'s Secretary General [[Irene Khan]] explains, &quot;If we focus on the U.S. it's because we believe that the U.S. is a country whose enormous influence and power has to be used constructively ... When countries like the U.S. are seen to undermine or ignore human rights, it sends a very powerful message to others.&quot;&lt;ref name=boston&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.boston.com/news/world/europe/articles/2007/05/24/report_hits_us_on_human_rights/?rss_id=Boston+Globe+--+World+News|title=Report hits US on human rights|publisher=Associated Press (published on Globe)|first=Raphael|last=Satter|date=2007-05-24|accessdate=2007-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Further assessments==
According to [[Freedom in the World]], an annual report by US based think-tank [[Freedom House]], which rates political rights and civil liberties, in 2007, the United States was ranked &quot;Free&quot; (the highest possible rating), together with 92 other countries.

The [[Polity data series]], which rate regime and authority characteristics, covering the years 1800-2004, has ranked the United States with the highest possible rating since 1871.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cidcm.umd.edu/polity/data/ Polity IV data sets]&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the [[Economist Magazine]]'s [[Democracy Index]], the US ranks 17 out of 167 nations.

According to the annual [[Reporters Without Borders#Worldwide Press Freedom Index|Worldwide Press Freedom Index]] published by [[Reporters Without Borders]], due to wartime restrictions the United States was ranked 53rd from the top in 2006 (out of 168), 44th in 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|month=October | year=2005|title=North Korea, Eritrea and Turkmenistan are the world’s &quot;black holes&quot; for news|url=http://www.rsf.org/rubrique.php3?id_rubrique=554|publisher=[[Reporters Without Borders]]|accessdate=2007-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; 22nd in 2004,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|month=October | year=2004|title=East Asia and Middle East have worst press freedom records|url=http://www.rsf.org/article.php3?id_article=11715|publisher=Reporters Without Borders|accessdate=2007-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; 31st in 2003&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|month=October | year=2003|title=Cuba second from last, just ahead of North Korea|url=http://www.rsf.org/article.php3?id_article=8247|publisher=Reporters Without Borders|accessdate=2007-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; and 17th in 2002.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|month=October | year=2002|title=Reporters Without Borders publishes the first worldwide press freedom index|url=http://www.rsf.org/article.php3?id_article=4116|publisher=Reporters Without Borders|accessdate=2007-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the annual [[Corruption Perceptions Index]], which was published by [[Transparency International]], the United States was ranked 20th from the top least corrupt in 2006 (out of 163), 17th in 2005, 18th in 2003, and 16th in 2002.&lt;!--Not sure if this is a human right issue--&gt;

According to the annual [[Privacy International]] index of 2007, the United States was ranked an &quot;endemic surveillance society&quot;, scoring only 1.5 out of 5 privacy points.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|month=December | year=2007|title=Leading surveillance societies in the EU and the World 2007|url=http://www.privacyinternational.org/article.shtml?cmd[347]=x-347-559597|publisher=[[Privacy International]]|accessdate=2009-01-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the [[Gallup International Association|Gallup International]] Millennium Survey, the United States ranked 23rd in citizens' perception of human rights observance when its citizens were asked, &quot;In general, do you think that human rights are being fully respected, partially respected or are they not being respected at all in your country?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.gallup-international.com/ContentFiles/millennium6.asp| title=Universal Human Rights?|publisher=Gallup International| year=1999}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Other issues==
In the aftermath of the devastation caused by [[Hurricane Katrina]], criticism by some groups commenting on human rights issues was made regarding the recovery and reconstruction issues&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| last = Klapper | first = Bradley | title = U.N. Panel Takes U.S. to Task Over Katrin | work = AP Online | publisher = ''The America's Intelligence Wire'' | date = 2006-07-28 | accessdate = 2009-05-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;26. The Committee, while taking note of the various rules and regulations prohibiting discrimination in the provision of disaster relief and emergency assistance, remains concerned about information that poor people and in particular African-Americans, were disadvantaged by the rescue and evacuation plans implemented when Hurricane Katrina hit the United States of America, and continue to be disadvantaged under the reconstruction plans. (articles 6 and 26) The State party should review its practices and policies to ensure the full implementation of its obligation to protect life and of the prohibition of discrimination, whether direct or indirect, as well as of the United Nations Guiding Principles on Internal Displacement, in the areas of disaster prevention and preparedness, emergency assistance and relief measures. In the aftermath of Hurricane Katrina, it should increase its efforts to ensure that the rights of poor people and in particular African-Americans, are fully taken into consideration in the reconstruction plans with regard to access to housing, education and health care. The Committee wishes to be informed about the results of the inquiries into the alleged failure to evacuate prisoners at the Parish prison, as well as the allegations that New Orleans residents were not permitted by law enforcement officials to cross the Greater New Orleans Bridge to Gretna, Louisiana. See: {{Cite web| title = Concluding Observations of the Human Rights Committee on the Second and Third U.S. Reports to the Committee (2006). | work = Human Rights Committee | publisher = University of Minnesota Human Rights Library | date = 2006-07-28 | url = http://www1.umn.edu/humanrts/usdocs/hruscomments2.html | accessdate = }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[American Civil Liberties Union]] and the National Prison Project documented mistreatment of the prison population during the flooding,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Hurricane Katrina and the Guiding Principles on Internal Displacement |publisher=[[Institute for Southern Studies]] |date = January 2008|pages=18–19 |url=http://www.southernstudies.org/ISSKatrinaHumanRightsJan08.pdf |format=PDF |accessdate=2009-05-18 }} See also: {{Cite news|last=Sothern |first= Billy |title=Left to Die |pages=19–22 |publisher=[[The Nation]] |date=2006-01-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Report says U.S. Katrina response fails to meet its own human rights principles |publisher=[[New Orleans CityBusiness]] |date=2008-01-16 |accessdate=2009-05-18}} See also: {{Cite web|title=Hurricane Katrina and the Guiding Principles on Internal Displacement |publisher=[[Institute for Southern Studies]] |date = January 2008|url=http://www.southernstudies.org/ISSKatrinaHumanRightsJan08.pdf |format=PDF |accessdate=2009-05-18 }}&lt;/ref&gt; while [[United Nations Special Rapporteur]] [[Doudou Diène]] delivered a 2008 report on such issues.&lt;ref name=&quot;UN-209&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.unhcr.org/cgi-bin/texis/vtx/refworld/rwmain?page=search&amp;amp;docid=4a093b1e2&amp;amp;skip=0&amp;amp;query=Hurricane%20Katrina |title=Report of the Special Rapporteur |date=April 28, 2009 |publisher=United Nations Human Rights Council|pages=30 |accessdate=2009-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; The United States was elected in 2009 to sit on the [[United Nations Human Rights Council]] (UNHRC),&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.aclu.org/intlhumanrights/gen/39575prs20090512.html?s_src=RSS|title=U.S. Elected To U.N. Human Rights Council |publisher=ACLU|accessdate=2009-06-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; which the U.S. State Department had previously asserted had lost its credibility by its prior stances&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.state.gov/r/pa/prs/dpb/2007/mar/81471.htm|publisher=[[United States Department of State]]|title=Daily Press Briefing|date=2007-05-06|accessdate=2006-06-24}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; and lack of safeguards against severe human rights violators taking a seat.&lt;ref&gt;{{UN document |docid=A-60-PV.72 |body=General Assembly |type=Verbotim Report |session=60 |meeting=72 |page=5 |anchor=pg005-bk02 |date=15 March 2006 |meetingtime=11:00 |speakername=Mr. Toro Jiménez | speakernation=Venezuela |accessdate=2007-09-19 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2006 and 2007, the UNHCR and Martin Scheinin were critical of the United States regard permitting executions by lethal injection, housing children in adult jails, subjecting prisoners to prolonged isolation in [[supermax|supermax prisons]], using enhanced interrogation techniques and domestic poverty gaps.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=U.N. Torture Committee Critical of U.S.|url=http://hrw.org/english/docs/2006/05/19/usdom13418.htm |publisher=Human Rights Watch |date=2006-05-19 |accessdate=2007-06-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|format=PDF |url=http://www.ohchr.org/english/bodies/cat/docs/AdvanceVersions/CAT.C.USA.CO.2.pdf |title=Conclusions and recommendations of the Committee}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/topNews/idUSN2519217620070526|title=U.N. expert faults U.S. on human rights in terror laws |date=2007-05-25 |accessdate=2007-06-03 |first=Evelyn|last=Leopold |publisher=Reuters}} Also published on [http://www.boston.com/news/nation/articles/2007/05/26/un_expert_faults_us_on_human_rights_in_terror_laws/ The Boston Globe], on [http://news.yahoo.com/s/nm/20070526/pl_nm/un_rights_usa_dc_2 Yahoo News], and on [http://www.abcnews.go.com/Politics/wireStory?id=3215782 ABC News].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rizvi, Haider. [http://www.commondreams.org/headlines05/1130-01.htm Racial Poverty Gaps in U.S. Amount to Human Rights Violation, Says U.N. Expert]. [http://us.oneworld.net/ OneWorld.net] (published on [[CommonDreams]]). 2005-11-30. Retrieved on 2007-08-13. ([http://web.archive.org/web/20060822044258/http://www.commondreams.org/headlines05/1130-01.htm archived link])&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Human rights|United States}}
'''Criticism of the US Human rights record
*[[Human Rights Record of the United States]], Report prepared by the [[People's Republic of China]]
'''US Human rights abuses
**[[Human experimentation in the United States]]
'''Organizations involved in US human rights
**[[Pennsylvania Abolition Society]]
**[[US Human Rights Network]]
'''People involved in US human rights
**[[Susan B. Anthony]]
**[[Anthony Benezet]]
**[[Louis Henkin]]
**[[Gay McDougall]]
'''Notable comments on Human Rights
**[[Four Freedoms]], A speech made by U.S. President [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=35em}}

==Further reading==
*{{Cite book
  | last = Ignatieff
  | first = Michael
  | authorlink = Michael Ignatieff
  | title = American Exceptionalism and Human Rights
  | publisher = Princeton University Press
  | year = 2005
  | isbn = 0-691-11648-2}}
*{{Cite book
  | last = Ishay
  | first = Micheline
  | title = The History of Human Rights: From Ancient Times to the Globalization Era
  | publisher = [[University of California Press]]
  | edition = Second
  | year = 2008
  | isbn = 0-520-25641-7 }}
*{{Cite book
  | last = Lauren
  | first = Paul Gordon
  | authorlink =
  | title = The Evolution of International Human Rights: Visions Seen
  | publisher = University of Pennsylvania Press
  | edition = Second
  | year = 2003
  | isbn = 0-8122-1854-X}}
*{{Cite book
  | last = Olyan
  | first = Saul M.
  | coauthor = Martha C. Nussbaum
  | title = Sexual Orientation and Human Rights in American Religious Discourse
  | location = New York
  | publisher = [[Oxford University Press]]
  | year = 1998
  | isbn = 0-19-511942-8}}
*{{Cite book
  | last = Rhoden
  | first = Nancy Lee
  | coauthor = Ian Kenneth Steele
  | title = The Human Tradition in the American Revolution
  | publisher = Rowman &amp; Littlefield
  | year = 2000
  | isbn = 0-8420-2748-3 }}
*{{Cite book
  | last = Shapiro
  | first = Steven R.
  | coauthors = Human Rights Watch, American Civil Liberties Union
  | title = Human Rights Violations in the United States: A Report on U.S. Compliance with The International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights
  | publisher = [[Human Rights Watch]]
  | year = 1993
  | isbn = 1-56432-122-3}}
*{{Cite book
  | editors = Soohoo, Cynthia; Albisa, Catherine; Davis, Martha F.
  | title = Bringing Human Rights Home: A History of Human Rights in the United States
  | volume = I
  | publisher = Praeger Publishers
  | year = 2007
  | isbn = 0-275-98822-8
  | author = ed. by Cynthia Soohoo ...}}
*{{Cite book
  | editors = Soohoo, Cynthia; Albisa, Catherine; Davis, Martha F.
  | title = Bringing Human Rights Home: From Civil Rights to Human Rights
  | volume = II
  | publisher = Praeger Publishers
  | year = 2007
  | isbn = 0-275-98823-6
  | author = ed. by Cynthia Soohoo ...}}
*{{Cite book
  | last = Quigley
  | first = William
  | coauthors = Sharda Sekaran
  | editors = Soohoo, Cynthia; Albisa, Catherine; Davis, Martha F.
  | title = Bringing Human Rights Home: Portraits of the Movement
  | volume = III
  | chapter = A Call for the Right to Return in the Gulf Coast
  | pages = 291–304
  | publisher = Praeger Publishers
  | year = 2007
  | isbn = 0-275-98824-4}}
*{{Cite book
  | last = Weissbrodt
  | first = David
  | coauthors = Connie de la Vega
  | authorlink =
  | title = International Human Rights Law: An Introduction
  | publisher = University of Pennsylvania Press
  | year = 2007
  | isbn = 0-8122-4032-4}}
*{{Cite book
  | last = Yount
  | first = David
  | authorlink =
  | title = How the Quakers Invented America
  | publisher = Rowman &amp; Littlefield
  | year = 2007
  | isbn = 0-7425-5833-9}}

==External links==
* [http://netnebraska.org/extras/humanrights/ Human Rights in the US and the International Community], UNL Initiative on Human Rights &amp; Human Diversity site{{mdash}}research and study source directed at secondary and post-secondary students
* [http://www.freedomhouse.org/template.cfm?page=22&amp;year=2006&amp;country=7084 Freedom in the World 2006: United States] from [[Freedom House]]
* [http://www.state.gov/g/drl/hr/ Human Rights] from [[United States Department of State]]
* [http://hrw.org/wr2k6/us/index.htm United States: Human Rights World Report 2006] from Human Rights Watch

{{North America topic|Human rights in}}
{{Life in the United States}}
{{United States topics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Human Rights In The United States}}
[[Category:Political repression in the United States]]
[[Category:Human rights in the United States|*]]

[[fr:Droits de l'homme aux États-Unis]]
[[id:Hak asasi manusia di Amerika Serikat]]
[[it:Diritti umani negli Stati Uniti d'America]]
[[ms:Hak asasi manusia di Amerika Syarikat]]
[[ru:Права человека в США]]
[[fi:Ihmisoikeudet Yhdysvalloissa]]
[[tr:ABD'de insan hakları]]
[[vi:Nhân quyền tại Hoa Kỳ]]
[[zh:美國人權]]</text>
      <sha1>l93rhps262su936h44rh7e4gv77l6ub</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
