<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Kashmir</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>17337</id>
    <revision>
      <id>518743895</id>
      <parentid>518699464</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-19T18:14:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Delljvc</username>
        <id>17088649</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Muslim rule */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="55962">{{About|the geographical region of Kashmir|the song by Led Zeppelin|Kashmir (song)|other uses|Kashmir (disambiguation)}}
{{Distinguish2|the Ukrainian surname [[Kushnir]]}}
{{pp-semi-indef}}
[[File:Kashmir region 2004.jpg|thumb|350px|'''Political Map:''' the Kashmir region districts, showing the [[Pir Panjal]] range and the ''[[Kashmir valley]]'' or ''Vale of Kashmir''.]]
[[File:Nanga parbat, Pakistan by gul791.jpg|thumb|300px|'''Ninth-highest:''' [[Nanga Parbat]], a dangerous mountain to climb, is in the Kashmiri region of [[Gilgit–Baltistan]] in Pakistan]]
'''Kashmir''' ({{lang-ks|کٔشِیر / कॅशीर}}; {{lang-ur|کشمیری}}; {{lang-ug|كەشمىر}}; {{lang-scl|کشمیر}}) is the northwestern region of the [[Indian subcontinent]]. Until the mid-19th century, the term ''Kashmir'' geographically denoted only the [[Kashmir Valley|valley]] between the [[Great Himalayas]] and the [[Pir Panjal]] mountain range.  Today ''Kashmir'' denotes a larger area that includes the [[India]]n-administered state of [[Jammu and Kashmir]] (which consists of the divisions: the [[Kashmir valley]], [[Jammu]] and [[Ladakh]]), the [[Pakistan]]i-administered [[Gilgit–Baltistan]] and the [[Azad Kashmir]] provinces, and the [[People's Republic of China|Chinese]]-administered regions of [[Aksai Chin]] and [[Trans-Karakoram Tract]].

In the first half of the first millennium, the Kashmir region became an important center of [[Hinduism]] and later of [[Buddhism]]; later still, in the ninth century, [[Kashmir Shaivism]] arose.&lt;ref&gt;Basham, A. L. (2005) ''The wonder that was India'', Picador. Pp. 572. ISBN 0-330-43909-X, p. 110.&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1349, Shah Mir became the first [[Islam|Muslim]] ruler of Kashmir and inaugurated the ''Salatin-i-Kashmir'' or [[Swati]] dynasty.&lt;ref name=imp-gazet-history&gt;''Imperial Gazetteer of [[India]], volume 15''. 1908. Oxford University Press, Oxford and London. pp. 93-95.&lt;/ref&gt; For the next five centuries, Muslim [[monarchy|monarchs]] ruled Kashmir, including the [[Mughals]], who ruled from 1526 until 1751, then the Afghan [[Durrani Empire]] that ruled from  1747 until 1820.&lt;ref name=imp-gazet-history/&gt; That year, the Sikhs, under [[Ranjit Singh]], annexed Kashmir.&lt;ref name=imp-gazet-history/&gt; In 1846, upon the purchase of the region from the British under the Treaty of Amritsar, the Dogras&amp;mdash;under [[Gulab Singh]]&amp;mdash;became the new rulers. [[Dogra]] Rule, under the ''paramountcy'' (or tutelage) of the British Crown, lasted until 1947, when the [[Jammu and Kashmir (princely state)|former princely state]] became a [[Kashmir conflict|disputed territory]], now administered by three countries: [[India]], [[Pakistan]], and the [[People's Republic of China]].

==Etymology==
[[File:Sun temple martand indogreek.jpg|thumb|''General view of [[Temple]] and Enclosure of [[Surya|Marttand]] (the [[Sun]]), at Bhawan, ca. 490–555; the colonnade ca. 693–729.'' [[Surya]] [[Mandir]] at [[Martand]], Jammu &amp; Kashmir, India, photographed by John Burke, 1868.]]

The word Kashmir is an ancient [[Sanskrit]] word which literally means Land of [[Kashyap]] Rishi. [[Kashyap]] Rishi was a [[Saraswat Brahmin]] and one of the [[Saptarshi]]s, who was key in formalizing the ancient [[Historical Vedic Religion]]. The [[Kashmiri Pandits]] are his descendants and have named the valley after him, in his honour. {{Citation needed|date=April 2012}}

==History==
{{Main|History of Kashmir}}{{Further|Timeline of the Kashmir conflict|Kashmir conflict}}

===Buddhism in Kashmir===
{{Further|Buddhism in Kashmir}}
[[File:Kashmir. Temple of Jyeshteswara -Shankaracharya-, on the Takht-i-Suliman Hill, near Srinagar. Probable date 220 B.C. 1.jpg|thumb|Hindu temple of Jyeshteswara ([[Shankaracharya]]), on the Shankaracharya Hill, near Srinagar.]]
[[File:Buddhist tope baramula1868.jpg|thumb|This general view of the unexcavated [[Buddhist]] stupa near [[Baramulla]], with two figures standing on the summit, and another at the base with measuring scales, was taken by John Burke in 1868. The stupa, which was later excavated, dates to 500 AD.]]

The Buddhist [[Maurya]]n emperor [[Ashoka]] is often credited with having founded the old capital of Kashmir, Shrinagari, now ruins on the outskirts of modern [[Srinagar]]. Kashmir was long to be a stronghold of Buddhism.&lt;ref&gt;A.K. Warder, ''Indian Buddhism''. Motilal Banarsidass 2000, page 256.&lt;/ref&gt;

As a [[Buddhism|Buddhist]] seat of learning, the [[Sarvastivada|Sarvāstivādan]] school strongly influenced Kashmir.&lt;ref&gt;A.K. Warder, ''Indian Buddhism''. Motilal Banarsidass 2000, pages 263-264.&lt;/ref&gt; East and [[Central Asia]]n Buddhist [[monk]]s are recorded as having visited the kingdom. In the late 4th century AD, the famous [[Kucha]]nese monk [[Kumārajīva]], born to an Indian noble family, studied [[Dirghagama|Dīrghāgama]] and [[Madhyāgama]] in Kashmir under [[Bandhudatta]]. He later became a prolific translator who helped take Buddhism to [[China]]. His mother Jīva is thought to have retired to Kashmir. [[Vimalaksa|Vimalākṣa]], a Sarvāstivādan Buddhist monk, travelled from Kashmir to Kucha and there instructed Kumārajīva in the ''[[Buddhist texts#Vinaya|Vinayapiṭaka]]''.

[[Adi Shankara]] visited the pre-existing  ''{{IAST|Sarvajñapīṭha}}'' ([[Sharada Peeth]]) in Kashmir in late 8th century or early 9th century AD. The ''Madhaviya Shankaravijayam'' states this [[mandir|temple]] had four doors for scholars from the four cardinal directions. The southern door (representing [[South India]]) had never been opened, indicating that no scholar from South India had entered the Sarvajna Pitha. Adi Shankara opened the southern door by defeating in debate all the scholars there in all the various scholastic disciplines such as [[Mimamsa]], [[Vedanta]] and other branches of [[Hindu philosophy]]; he ascended the throne of Transcendent wisdom of that temple.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last=Tapasyananda| first=Swami| year=2002| title=Sankara-Dig-Vijaya| pages=186–195}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Abhinavagupta]] (approx. 950 - 1020 AD&lt;ref&gt;Triadic Heart of Shiva, Paul E. Muller-Ortega, page 12&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Introduction to the Tantrāloka, Navjivan Rastogi, page 27&lt;/ref&gt;) was one of India's greatest [[Indian philosophy|philosophers]], [[Mysticism|mystics]] and [[Aesthetics|aestheticians]]. He was also considered an important [[Music of India|musician]], [[Indian poetry|poet]], [[Theatre in India|dramatist]], [[exegesis|exeget]], [[theology|theologian]], and [[Indian logic|logician]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Re-accessing Abhinavagupta page 4&quot;&gt;Re-accessing Abhinavagupta, Navjivan Rastogi, page 4&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Key to the Vedas, Nathalia Mikhailova, page 169&lt;/ref&gt; - a [[polymath]]ic personality who exercised strong influences on Indian culture.&lt;ref&gt;The Pratyabhijñā Philosophy, Ganesh Vasudeo Tagare, page 12&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Companion to Tantra, S.C. Banerji, page 89&lt;/ref&gt; He was born in the [[Kashmir region|Valley of Kashmir]]&lt;ref&gt;Doctrine of Divine Recognition, K. C. Pandey, page V&lt;/ref&gt; in a family of scholars and mystics and studied all the schools of philosophy and art of his time under the guidance of as many as fifteen (or more) teachers and [[guru]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Introduction to the Tantrāloka, Navjivan Rastogi, page 35&lt;/ref&gt; In his long life he completed over 35 works, the largest and most famous of which is [[Tantraloka|Tantrāloka]], an encyclopedic treatise on all the philosophical and practical aspects of [[Trika]] and [[Kaula]] (known today as [[Kashmir Shaivism]]). Another one of his very important contributions was in the field of philosophy of aesthetics with his famous [[Abhinavabharati|Abhinavabhāratī]] commentary of [[Natya Shastra|Nāṭyaśāstra]] of [[Bharata Muni]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;Luce dei Tantra, Tantrāloka, Abhinavagupta, Raniero Gnoli, page LXXVII&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 10th century AD ''[[Moksopaya]]'' or ''Moksopaya Shastra'', a philosophical text on salvation for non-ascetics (''moksa-upaya'': 'means to release'), was written on the Pradyumna hill in [[Śrīnagar]].&lt;ref&gt;Slaje, Walter. (2005). &quot;Locating the Mokṣopāya&quot;, in: Hanneder, Jürgen (Ed.). ''[http://books.google.com/books?ei=0SkSTb7XNJHEswaB4bDVDA The Mokṣopāya, Yogavāsiṣṭha and Related Texts]'' Aachen: Shaker Verlag. (Indologica Halensis. Geisteskultur Indiens. 7). p. 35.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.indologie.uni-halle.de/forschung/Moksopaya/pradyumna.htm Gallery - The journey to the Pradyumnaśikhara]&lt;/ref&gt; It has the form of a public sermon and claims human authorship and contains about 30,000 [[shloka]]'s (making it longer than the ''[[Ramayana]]''). The main part of the text forms a dialogue between [[Vasistha]] and [[Rama]], interchanged with [[Contents and stories of the Yoga Vasistha|numerous short stories and anecdotes]] to illustrate the content.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Leslie|2003|pp=104–107}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;lekh-state&quot;&gt;Lekh Raj Manjdadria. (2002?) ''[http://www.valmikisabhas.org.uk/YU-MUPatilaLekhRaj.pdf The State of Research to date on the Yogavastha (Moksopaya)]''.&lt;/ref&gt; This text was later (11th to the 14th century AD)&lt;ref&gt;Hanneder, Jürgen; Slaje, Walter. ''[http://www.indologie.uni-halle.de/forschung/Moksopaya/introduction.htm Moksopaya Project: Introduction].''&lt;/ref&gt; expanded and [[Vedanta|vedanticized]], which resulted in the ''[[Yoga Vasistha]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chapple1984-x-xi&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Chapple |first=Christopher |coauthors =translation: [[Swami Venkatesananda|Venkatesananda, Swami]] |title=The Concise Yoga Vāsiṣṭha |contribution=Introduction |publisher=State University of New York Press |location=Albany |year=1984 |isbn=0-87395-955-8 |oclc=11044869 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=1FFdOj2dv8cC |pages=x-xi}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Muslim rule===
[[File:Zeinulabuddin-tomb-srinagar1866.JPG|thumb|left|''Gateway of enclosure, (once a Hindu temple) of Zein-ul-ab-ud-din's Tomb, in Srinagar. Probable date A.D. 400 to 500'', 1868. John Burke. Oriental and India Office Collection. British Library.]]
The Muslims and [[Hindu]]s of Kashmir lived in relative harmony, since the [[Sufi]]-Islamic way of life that Muslims followed in Kashmir complemented the [[Rishi]] tradition of [[Kashmiri Pandit]]s, and Sufi saints such as [[Sheikh Noor-ud-din Wali]] were thought of as [[Rishi order|Muslim Rishis]]. This led to a syncretic culture where Hindus and Muslims revered the same local saints and prayed at the same [[shrines]] {{Citation needed|date=September 2007}}. Famous [[sufi]] saint Bulbul Shah was able to convert [[Rinchan]] to [[Islam]] and he adopted the name of [[Sultan Sadruddin]]. Rinchan who was then [[prince]] of Kashgar Ladakh to an Islamic lifestyle, thus founding the Sufiana composite culture. Under this rule, Muslim, Hindu and Buddhist Kashmiris generally co-existed peacefully. Over time, however, the Sufiana governance gave way to outright Muslim monarchs.

===First Muslim ruler: Shah Mir Swati-Shams Al-Din===

Shah Mir was the First Muslim ruler of Kashmir and the founder of the [[Swati dynasty]] named after him. Jonaraja, in his Rajatarangini mentioned him as Sahamera who was a Pashtun from Swat region, the (then) tribal belt of Pakhtunkhwa province of present day Pakistan. Shah Mir was succeeded by his eldest son Jamshid, but he was deposed by his brother Ali Sher probably within few months, who ascended the throne under the name of Alauddin[1] Following the Shahmiri Dynasty, was the Chak Dynasty that ruled until Mughal conquest in 1586. In his Book, the New Islamic Dynasties, Clifford Edmond Bosworth has referred to the King as Shah Mir Swati, Shams Al Din; p/310). 

Some Kashmiri rulers, such as Sultan [[Zain-ul-Abidin]] who was popularly known as [[Zain-ul-Abidin|Budshah(بڈشاہ)]] (the King) (r.1423-1474){{Citation needed|date=April 2011}}, were tolerant of all religions in a manner comparable to [[Akbar]]. However, several Muslim rulers of Kashmir were intolerant of other religions. Sultãn [[Sikandar Butshikan]] of Kashmir (AD 1389-1413) is often considered the worst of these. Historians have recorded many of his atrocities. The [[Tarikh-i-Firishta]] records that Sikandar [[persecuted]] the [[Hindus]] and issued orders proscribing the residence of any other than Muslims in Kashmir. He also ordered the breaking of all &quot;golden and silver images&quot;. The Tarikh-i-Firishta further states: &quot;Many of the [[Brahmin]]s, rather than abandon their religion or their country, poisoned themselves; some emigrated from their native homes, while a few escaped. After the emigration of the Brahmins, Sikandar ordered all the temples in Kashmir to be thrown down. Having broken all the images in Kashmir, (Sikandar) acquired the title of 'Destroyer of Idols'.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Muhammad Qãsim Hindû Shãh Firishta : Tãrîkh-i-Firishta,'' translated by John Briggs under the title &quot;History of the Rise of the Mahomedan Power in India.&quot; First published in 1829, [[New Delhi]] Reprint 1981.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Hazratbal.jpg|thumb|250px|Hazratbal shrine in Srinagar.]]

[[Kalhana|Kalhana's]] metrical chronicle of the kings of Kashmir, called the ''[[Rajatarangini]],'' has been pronounced by Professor H. H. Wilson to be the only [[Sanskrit]] composition yet discovered to which the appellation &quot;history&quot; can with any propriety be applied. It first became known to the Muslims when, on [[Akbar]]'s invasion of Kashmir in 1588, a copy was presented to the emperor. A translation into Persian was made at his order. A summary of its contents, taken from this Persian translation, is given by [[Abu'l-Fazl ibn Mubarak|Abul Fazl]] in the ''Ain-i-Akbari''. The ''Rajatarangini'' was written around the middle of the 12th century. His work, in six books, makes use of earlier writings that are now lost.

The ''Rajatarangini'' is the first of a series of four histories that record the annals of Kashmir. Commencing with a rendition of traditional history of very early times, the ''Rajatarangini'' comes down to the reign of [[Sangrama Deva]], (''c.''1006 AD). The second work, by [[Jonaraja]], continues the history from where Kalhana left off, and, entering the Muslim period, gives an account of the reigns down to that of [[Zain-ul-Abidin]], 1412{{Citation needed|date=April 2011}}. [[Srivara]] carried on the record to the accession of [[Fah Shah]] in 1486. The fourth work, called ''Rajavalipataka'', by [[Prajnia Bhatta]], completes the history to the time of the incorporation of Kashmir in the dominions of the [[Mogul Empire|Mogul]] emperor Akbar, 1588.

===Sikh rule===
In 1819, the [[Kashmir valley]] passed from the control of the [[Durrani Empire]] of [[Afghanistan]], and four centuries of [[Muslim]] rule under the [[Mughals]] and the [[Demographics of Afghanistan|Afghans]], to the conquering armies of the [[Sikh Kingdom|Sikhs]] under [[Ranjit Singh]] of [[Lahore]].&lt;ref name=imperialgazet-gulabsingh/&gt;  As the Kashmiris had suffered under the Afghans, they initially welcomed the new Sikh rulers.&lt;ref name=schofield_p5-6&gt;{{Harvnb|Schofield|2010|pp=5&amp;ndash;6}}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, the Sikh governors turned out to be hard taskmasters, and Sikh rule was generally considered oppressive,&lt;ref name=madan2008-p15&gt;{{Harvnb|Madan|2008|p=15}}&lt;/ref&gt; protected perhaps by the remoteness of Kashmir from the capital of the Sikh empire in Lahore;&lt;ref name=zutshi_p39-41&gt;{{Harvnb|Zutshi|2003|pp=39&amp;ndash;41}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Sikhs enacted a number of anti-Muslim laws,&lt;ref name=zutshi_p39-41/&gt; which included handing out death sentences for cow slaughter,&lt;ref name=schofield_p5-6/&gt; closing down the [[Jamia Masjid, Srinagar|Jamia Masjid]] in Srinagar,&lt;ref name=zutshi_p39-41/&gt; and banning the ''[[azaan]]'', the public Muslim call to prayer.&lt;ref name=zutshi_p39-41/&gt;  Kashmir had also now begun to attract European visitors, several of whom wrote of the abject poverty of the vast Muslim peasantry and of the exorbitant taxes under the Sikhs.&lt;ref name=schofield_p5-6/&gt;  High taxes, according to some contemporary accounts, had depopulated large tracts of the countryside, allowing only one-sixteenth of the cultivable land to be cultivated.&lt;ref name=schofield_p5-6/&gt;  However, after a famine in 1832, the Sikhs reduced the land tax to half the produce of the land and also began to offer interest-free loans to farmers;&lt;ref name=zutshi_p39-41/&gt;  Kashmir became the second highest revenue earner for the Sikh empire.&lt;ref name=zutshi_p39-41/&gt;  During this time [[Pashmina|Kashmiri shawl]]s became known world wide, attracting many buyers especially in the west.&lt;ref name=zutshi_p39-41/&gt;

Earlier, in 1780, after the death of Ranjit Deo, the [[Raja]] of Jammu, the kingdom of Jammu (to the south of the Kashmir valley) was also captured by the Sikhs and afterwards, until 1846, became a tributary to the Sikh power.&lt;ref name=imperialgazet-gulabsingh&gt;''Imperial Gazetteer of India, volume 15''. 1908. &quot;Kashmir: History.&quot; pp. 94-95.&lt;/ref&gt; Ranjit Deo's grandnephew, [[Gulab Singh of Jammu and Kashmir|Gulab Singh]], subsequently sought service at the court of Ranjit Singh, distinguished himself in later campaigns, especially the annexation of the Kashmir valley, and, for his services, was appointed governor of Jammu in 1820. With the help of his officer, [[General Zorawar Singh|Zorawar Singh]], Gulab Singh soon captured for the Sikhs the lands of Ladakh and [[Baltistan]] to the east and north-east, respectively, of Jammu.&lt;ref name=imperialgazet-gulabsingh/&gt;

===Princely state===
{{Main|Princely state of Kashmir and Jammu}}
[[File:NWFP-Kashmir1909-a.jpg|thumb|1909 Map of the [[Kashmir region|Princely State of Kashmir and Jammu]]. The names of regions, important cities, rivers, and mountains are underlined in red.]]

In 1845, the [[First Anglo-Sikh War]] broke out.  According to the [[Imperial Gazetteer of India]], &lt;blockquote&gt; &quot;Gulab Singh contrived to hold himself aloof till the battle of Sobraon (1846), when he appeared as a useful mediator and the trusted advisor of Sir [[Henry Montgomery Lawrence|Henry Lawrence]].  Two treaties were concluded.  By the first the State of Lahore (i.e. West [[Punjab region|Punjab]]) handed over to the British, as equivalent for one crore indemnity, the hill countries between the rivers Beas and Indus; by the second the British made over to Gulab Singh for 75 lakhs all the hilly or mountainous country situated to the east of the Indus and the west of the Ravi ''i.e.'' the [[Vale of Kashmir]]).&quot;&lt;ref name=imperialgazet-gulabsingh/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Drafted by a treaty and a bill of sale, and constituted between 1820 and 1858, the [[Kashmir and Jammu (princely state)|Princely State of Kashmir and Jammu]] (as it was first called) combined disparate regions, religions, and ethnicities:&lt;ref name=bowers&gt;Bowers, Paul. 2004. [http://www.parliament.uk/commons/lib/research/rp2004/rp04-028.pdf &quot;Kashmir.&quot; Research Paper 4/28], International Affairs and Defence, House of Commons Library, United Kingdom.&lt;/ref&gt; to the east, Ladakh was ethnically and culturally [[Tibetan people|Tibetan]] and its inhabitants practised Buddhism; to the south, Jammu had a mixed population of Hindus, Muslims and Sikhs; in the heavily populated central Kashmir valley, the population was overwhelmingly [[Sunni Islam|''Sunni'']] Muslim, however, there was also a small but influential Hindu minority, the Kashmiri [[brahmins]] or [[Kashmiri Pandits|pandits]]; to the northeast, sparsely populated [[Baltistan]] had a population ethnically related to Ladakh, but which practised [[Shia Islam|''Shi'a'' Islam]]; to the north, also sparsely populated, [[Gilgit Agency]], was an area of diverse, mostly ''Shi'a'' groups; and, to the west, [[Poonch District|Punch]] was Muslim, but of different ethnicity than the Kashmir valley.&lt;ref name=bowers/&gt; After the [[Indian Rebellion of 1857]], in which Kashmir sided with the British, and the subsequent assumption of [[British raj|direct rule]] by Great Britain, the [[princely state]] of Kashmir came under the [[suzerainty]] of the [[The Crown|British Crown]].

In the British census of India of 1941, Kashmir registered a Muslim majority population of 77%, a Hindu population of 20% and a sparse population of Buddhists and Sikhs comprising the remaining 3%.&lt;ref name=bose-sumantra-2005-p15-17&gt;{{Harvnb|Bose|2005|pp=15&amp;ndash;17}}&lt;/ref&gt;  That same year, Prem Nath Bazaz, a [[Kashmiri Pandit]] journalist wrote: “The poverty of the Muslim masses is appalling. ... Most are landless laborers, working as serfs for absentee [Hindu] landlords ...  Almost the whole brunt of official corruption is borne by the Muslim masses.”&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in {{Harvnb|Bose|2005|pp=15&amp;ndash;17}}&lt;/ref&gt;  For almost a century until the census, a small Hindu elite had ruled over a vast and impoverished Muslim peasantry.&lt;ref name=bose-sumantra-2005-p15-17/&gt;&lt;ref name=talbot-singh-p54&gt;{{Harvnb|Talbot|Singh|2009|p=54}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Driven into docility by chronic indebtedness to landords and moneylenders, having no education besides, nor awareness of rights,&lt;ref name=bose-sumantra-2005-p15-17/&gt; the Muslim peasants had no political representation until the 1930s.&lt;ref name=talbot-singh-p54/&gt;

=== 1947 and 1948 ===

{{Further|Kashmir conflict|Timeline of the Kashmir conflict|Indo-Pakistani War of 1947}}
[[File:Brit IndianEmpireReligions3.jpg|thumb|The prevailing religions by district in the 1901 Census of the Indian Empire.]]
Ranbir Singh's grandson [[Hari Singh]], who had ascended the throne of Kashmir in 1925, was the reigning monarch in 1947 at the conclusion of British rule of the subcontinent and the subsequent [[Partition of India|partition]] of the British [[British India|Indian Empire]] into the newly independent [[Union of India]] and the [[Dominion of Pakistan]].  According to [[Burton Stein]]'s ''History of India'', &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Kashmir was neither as large nor as old an independent state as [[Hyderabad State|Hyderabad]]; it had been created rather off-handedly by the British after the first defeat of the Sikhs in 1846, as a reward to a former official who had sided with the British.  The Himalayan kingdom was connected to India through a district of the Punjab, but its population was 77 per cent Muslim and it shared a boundary with Pakistan.  Hence, it was anticipated that the maharaja would accede to Pakistan when the British paramountcy ended on  14&amp;ndash;15 August.  When he hesitated to do this, Pakistan launched a guerrilla onslaught meant to frighten its ruler into submission.   Instead the Maharaja appealed to [[Louis Mountbatten, 1st Earl Mountbatten of Burma|Mountbatten]]&lt;ref&gt;Viscount Louis Mountbatten, the last Viceroy of British India, stayed on in independent India from 1947 to 1948, serving as the first Governor-General of the Union of India.&lt;/ref&gt; for assistance, and the [[Governor-General of India|governor-general]] agreed on the condition that the ruler accede to India. Indian soldiers entered Kashmir and drove the Pakistani-sponsored irregulars from all but a small section of the state. The [[United Nations]] was then invited to mediate the quarrel. The UN mission insisted that the opinion of Kashmiris must be ascertained, while India insisted that no referendum could occur until all of the state had been cleared of irregulars.&quot;&lt;ref name=stein&gt;Stein, Burton. 2010. ''A History of India''. Oxford University Press. 432 pages. ISBN 978-1-4051-9509-6. Page 358.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In the last days of 1948, a ceasefire was agreed under UN auspices, but since the [[plebiscite]] demanded by the UN was never conducted, relations between India and Pakistan soured,&lt;ref name=stein/&gt; and eventually led to two more wars over Kashmir in [[Indo-Pakistani War of 1965|1965]] and [[Kargil War|1999]]. India has control of about half the area of the former princely state of Jammu and Kashmir, while Pakistan controls a third of the region, the [[Northern Areas]] and [[Azad Kashmir]]. According to Encyclopædia Britannica, &quot;Although there was a clear Muslim majority in Kashmir before the 1947 partition and its economic, cultural, and geographic contiguity with the Muslim-majority area of the Punjab (in Pakistan) could be convincingly demonstrated, the political developments during and after the partition resulted in a division of the region. Pakistan was left with territory that, although basically Muslim in character, was thinly populated, relatively inaccessible, and economically underdeveloped. The largest Muslim group, situated in the Valley of Kashmir and estimated to number more than half the population of the entire region, lay in Indian-administered territory, with its former outlets via the Jhelum valley route blocked.&quot;&lt;ref name=britannica-kashmir/&gt;

[[File:Karakash River in the Western Kunlun Shan, seen from the Tibet-Xinjiang highway.jpg|thumb|The [[Karakash River]] (Black Jade River) which flows north from its source near the town of Sumde in Aksai Chin, to cross the [[Kunlun Mountains]].]]
[[File:Kashmir top.jpg|thumb|[[Topographic map]] of Kasmir.]]

==Current status and political divisions==
{{Main|Aksai Chin|Azad Kashmir|Jammu and Kashmir|Gilgit–Baltistan|Trans-Karakoram Tract}}
The eastern region of the former princely state of Kashmir has also been involved in a boundary dispute. In the late 19th- and early 20th centuries, although some boundary agreements were signed between Great Britain, Afghanistan and Russia over the northern borders of Kashmir, China never accepted these agreements, and the official Chinese position did not change with the [[Chinese Revolution (1949)|communist revolution in 1949]]. By the mid-1950s the [[People's Liberation Army|Chinese army]] had entered the north-east portion of Ladakh.&lt;ref name=britannica-kashmir&gt;Kashmir. (2007). In Encyclopædia Britannica. Retrieved March 27, 2007, from [http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-214222 Encyclopædia Britannica Online].&lt;/ref&gt;
: &quot;By 1956–57 they had completed a military road through the [[Aksai Chin]] area to provide better communication between [[Xinjiang]] and western [[Tibet Autonomous Region|Tibet]]. India's belated discovery of this road led to border clashes between the two countries that culminated in the [[Sino-Indian war]] of October 1962.&quot;&lt;ref name=britannica-kashmir/&gt;

The region is divided among three countries in a [[History of the Kashmir conflict|territorial dispute]]: Pakistan controls the northwest portion (Northern Areas and Azad Kashmir), India controls the central and southern portion (Jammu and Kashmir) and Ladakh, and [[People's Republic of China|China]] controls the northeastern portion (Aksai Chin and the Trans-Karakoram Tract). India controls the majority of the [[Siachen Glacier]] area including the [[Saltoro Ridge]] passes, whereas Pakistan controls the lower territory just southwest of the Saltoro Ridge. India controls {{convert|101338|km2|sqmi|abbr=on}} of the disputed territory, Pakistan {{convert|85846|km2|sqmi|abbr=on}} and China, the remaining {{convert|37555|km2|sqmi|0|abbr=on}}.

Jammu and Pakistan administered Kashmir lie outside Pir Panjal range, and are under [[India]]n and Pakistani control respectively. These are populous regions. The main cities are Mirpur, Dadayal, Kotli, Bhimber [[Jammu (city)|Jammu]], [[Muzaffarabad]] and [[Rawalakot]].

The Gilgit–Baltistan, formerly called ''Northern Areas'', are a group of territories in the extreme north, bordered by the [[Karakoram]], the western [[Himalaya]]s, the [[Pamir Mountains|Pamir]], and the [[Hindu Kush]] ranges. With its administrative center at the town of [[Gilgit]], the Northern Areas cover an area of 72,971&amp;nbsp;km² (28,174&amp;nbsp;mi²) and have an estimated population approaching 1,000,000. The other main city is [[Skardu]].

Ladakh is a region in the east, between the [[Kunlun Mountains|Kunlun]] mountain range in the north and the main Great [[Himalaya]]s to the south.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ladakh&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Ladakh: The Land and the People |last=Jina |first=Prem Singh |year=1996 |publisher=Indus Publishing |isbn=81-7387-057-8 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Main cities are [[Leh]] and [[Kargil town|Kargil]]. It is under Indian administration and is part of the state of Jammu and Kashmir. It is one of the most sparsely populated regions in the area and is mainly inhabited by people of [[Indo-Aryans|Indo-Aryan]] and [[Tibetan people|Tibetan]] descent.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ladakh&quot;/&gt;

Aksai Chin is a vast high-altitude [[desert]] of [[salt]] that reaches altitudes up to {{convert|5000|m|ft}}. Geographically part of the [[Tibetan Plateau]], Aksai Chin is referred to as the Soda Plain. The region is almost uninhabited, and has no permanent settlements.

Though these regions are in practice administered by their respective claimants, neither India nor Pakistan has formally recognised the accession of the areas claimed by the other. India claims those areas, including the area &quot;ceded&quot; to China by Pakistan in the [[Trans-Karakoram Tract]] in 1963, are a part of its territory, while Pakistan claims the entire region excluding Aksai Chin and Trans-Karakoram Tract. The two countries have fought several declared wars over the territory. The [[Indo-Pakistani War of 1947]] established the rough boundaries of today, with Pakistan holding roughly one-third of Kashmir, and India one-half, with a dividing line of control established by the United Nations. The [[Indo-Pakistani War of 1965]] resulted in a stalemate and a UN-negotiated ceasefire.

== Demographics ==

In the 1901 Census of the British Indian Empire, Muslims constituted 74.16% of the total population of the princely state of ''Kashmir and Jammu'' where Gujjar Muslims constitute 20% population, Hindus, 23.72%, and [[Buddhists]], 1.21%. The Hindus were found mainly in Jammu, where they constituted a little less than 70% of the population.&lt;ref name = imperialgazetteerkashmir/&gt; In the [[Kashmir Valley]], Muslims constituted 95.6% of the population and Hindus 3.24%.&lt;ref name=imperialgazetteerkashmir/&gt; These percentages have remained fairly stable for the last 100 years.&lt;ref name=mridurai/&gt; Forty years later, in the 1941 Census of British India, Muslims accounted for 93.6% of the population of the Kashmir Valley and the Hindus for 4%.&lt;ref name = mridurai&gt;Rai, Mridu. 2004. ''Hindu Ruler, Muslim Subjects: Islam and the History of Kashmir''. Princeton University Press. 320 pages.
ISBN 0-691-11688-1. p. 37.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2003, the percentage of Muslims in the Kashmir Valley was 95%&lt;ref name=BBC2003&gt;BBC. 2003. [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/shared/spl/hi/south_asia/03/kashmir_future/html/default.stm ''The Future of Kashmir? In Depth.'']&lt;/ref&gt; and those of Hindus 4%; the same year, in Jammu, the percentage of Hindus was 66% and those of Muslims 30%.&lt;ref name=BBC2003/&gt;
In the 1901 Census of the British [[Indian Empire]], the population of the [[princely state]] of ''Kashmir and Jammu'' was 2,905,578. Of these 2,154,695 were Muslims (74.16%), 689,073 Hindus (23.72%), 25,828 Sikhs, and 35,047 Buddhists.

[[File:Muslim-shawl-makers-kashmir1867.jpg|thumb|A Muslim shawl making family shown in ''Cashmere shawl manufactory'', 1867, chromolith., William Simpson.]]

Among the Muslims of the princely state, four divisions were recorded: &quot;Shaikhs, Saiyids, Mughals, and Pathans. The Shaikhs, who are by far the most numerous, are the descendants of Hindus, but have retained none of the caste rules of their forefathers. They have clan names known as ''krams'' ...&quot;&lt;ref name=imperialgazetteerkashmir/&gt; It was recorded that these ''kram'' names included &quot;Tantre,&quot; &quot;Shaikh,&quot;, &quot;Bhat&quot;, &quot;Mantu,&quot; &quot;Ganai,&quot; &quot;Dar,&quot; &quot;Damar,&quot; &quot;Lon&quot; etc. The [[Syed#Ibn Battutah on the usage of Sayyid in India|Saiyids]], it was recorded &quot;could be divided into those who follow the profession of religion and those who have taken to agriculture and other pursuits. Their ''kram'' name is &quot;Mir.&quot; While a Saiyid retains his saintly profession Mir is a prefix; if he has taken to agriculture, Mir is an affix to his name.&quot;&lt;ref name=imperialgazetteerkashmir/&gt; The ''Mughals'' who were not numerous were recorded to have ''kram'' names like &quot;Mir&quot; (a corruption of &quot;Mirza&quot;), &quot;Beg,&quot; &quot;Bandi,&quot; &quot;Bach,&quot; and &quot;Ashaye.&quot; Finally, it was recorded that the Pathans &quot;who are more numerous than the Mughals, ... are found chiefly in the south-west of the valley, where [[Pashtun people|Pathan]] colonies have from time to time been founded. The most interesting of these colonies is that of Kuki-Khel Afridis at Dranghaihama, who retain all the old customs and speak [[Pashtu]].&quot;&lt;ref name=imperialgazetteerkashmir/&gt; Among the main tribes of Muslims in the princely state are the Butts, Dar, Lone, Jat, Gujjar, Rajput, Sudhan and Khatri. A small number of Butts, Dar and Lone use the title Khawaja and the Khatri use the title Shaikh the Gujjar use the title of Chaudhary. All these tribes are indigenous of the princely state and many Hindus also belong to these tribes.

The [[Hindus]] were found mainly in [[Jammu]], where they constituted a little less than 60% of the population.&lt;ref name=imperialgazetteerkashmir&gt;''Imperial Gazetteer of India, volume 15''. 1908. Oxford University Press, Oxford and London. pp. 99-102.&lt;/ref&gt; In the ''[[Kashmir Valley]]'', the Hindus represented &quot;524 in every 10,000 of the population (''i.e.'' 5.24%), and in the frontier ''wazarats'' of Ladhakh and Gilgit only 94 out of every 10,000 persons (0.94%).&quot;&lt;ref name=imperialgazetteerkashmir/&gt; In the same Census of 1901, in the Kashmir Valley, the total population was recorded to be 1,157,394, of which the Muslim population was 1,083,766, or 93.6% and the Hindu population 60,641.&lt;ref name=imperialgazetteerkashmir/&gt; Among the Hindus of ''Jammu'' province, who numbered 626,177 (or 90.87% of the Hindu population of the princely state), the most important castes recorded in the census were &quot;[[Brahmins|Brahmans]] (186,000), the [[Rajputs]] (167,000), the [[Khatri|Khattris]] (48,000) and the Thakkars (93,000).&quot;&lt;ref name=imperialgazetteerkashmir/&gt;

In the 1911 Census of the British Indian Empire, the total population of ''Kashmir and Jammu'' had increased to 3,158,126. Of these, 2,398,320 (75.94%) were Muslims, 696,830 (22.06%) Hindus, 31,658 (1%) Sikhs, and 36,512 (1.16%) [[Buddhists]]. In the last census of British India in 1941, the total population of Kashmir and Jammu (which as a result of the second world war, was estimated from the 1931 census) was 3,945,000. Of these, the total Muslim population was 2,997,000 (75.97%), the Hindu population was 808,000 (20.48%), and the Sikh 55,000 (1.39%).&lt;ref name = brush&gt;Brush, J. E. 1949. &quot;The Distribution of Religious Communities in India&quot;
''Annals of the Association of American Geographers'', 39(2):81-98.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Kashmiri Pandits]], the only Hindus of the Kashmir valley, who had stably constituted approximately 4 to 5% of the population of the valley during Dogra rule (1846&amp;ndash;1947), and 20% of whom had left the Kashmir valley by 1950,&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Zutshi|2003|p=318}} Quote: &quot;Since a majority of the landlords were Hindu, the (land) reforms (of 1950) led to a mass exodus of Hindus from the state. ... The unsettled nature of Kashmir's accession to India, coupled with the threat of economic and social decline in the face of the land reforms, led to increasing insecurity among the Hindus in Jammu, and among Kashmiri Pandits, 20 per cent of whom had emigrated from the Valley by 1950.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; began to leave in much greater numbers in the 1990s.  According to a number of authors, approximately 100,000 of the total Kashmiri Pandit population of 140,000 left the valley during that decade.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Bose|1997|p=71}}, {{Harvnb|Rai|2004|p=286}}, {{Harvnb|Metcalf|Metcalf|2006|p=274}} Quote: &quot;The Hindu Pandits, a small but influential elite community who had secured a favourable position, first under the maharajas, and then under the successive Congress regimes, and proponents of a distinctive Kashmiri culture that linked them to India, felt under siege as the uprising gathered force.  Of a population of some 140,000, perhaps 100,000 Pandits fled the state after 1990; their cause was quickly taken up by the Hindu right.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;  Other authors have suggested a higher figure for the exodus, ranging from the entire population of over 150,000,&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Malik|2005|p=318}}&lt;/ref&gt; to 190,000 of a total Pandit population of 200,000,&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Madan|2008|p=25}}&lt;/ref&gt; to a number as high as 300,000.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/in.html#Issues CIA Factbook: India&amp;ndash;Transnational Issues]&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Administered by !! Area !! Population !! % [[Islam|Muslim]] !! % [[Hinduism|Hindu]] !! % [[Buddhism|Buddhist]] !! % Other
|-
|| {{IND}}
|[[Kashmir Valley]]
|~4 million
|95%
|4%*
|&amp;ndash;
|&amp;ndash;
|-
|
|[[Jammu]]
|~3 million
|30%
|66%
|&amp;ndash;
|4%
|-
|
|[[Ladakh]]
|~0.25 million
|46%
|&amp;ndash;
|50%
|3%
|-
|| {{PAK}}
|[[Azad Kashmir]]
|~2.6 million
|100%
|&amp;ndash;
|&amp;ndash;
|&amp;ndash;
|-
|
|[[Gilgit–Baltistan]]
|~1 million
|99%
|&amp;ndash;
|&amp;ndash;
|&amp;ndash;
|-
|| {{flag|China|name}}
|[[Aksai Chin]]
|&amp;ndash;
|&amp;ndash;
|&amp;ndash;
|&amp;ndash;
|&amp;ndash;
|-
| colspan =&quot;7&quot; |
* Statistics from the [[BBC]] [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/shared/spl/hi/south_asia/03/kashmir_future/html/default.stm In Depth] report.
|}

==Culture and cuisine==
[[File:Traditional Dresses of Kashmir.jpg|thumbnail|right|Traditional Dresses of Kashmir]]
{{further2|[[Cuisine of Kashmir]]|[[Wazwan]]|[[Kashmiri literature]]|[[Kashmiri music]]|[[Kashmiri Pandit Festivals]]}}
[[Cuisine of Kashmir|Kashmiri cuisine]] includes [[dum aloo]] (boiled potatoes with heavy amounts of spice), tzaman (a solid cottage cheese), [[rogan josh]] (lamb cooked in heavy spices), yakhiyn (lamb cooked in curd with mild spices), hakh (a spinach-like leaf), rista-gushtaba (minced meat balls in tomato and curd curry),danival korme and of course the signature rice which is particular to Asian cultures. The traditional [[wazwan]] feast involves cooking meat or vegetables, usually mutton, in several different ways.

Alcohol is strictly prohibited in most places. There are two styles of making tea in the region: [[Noon Chai]], or salt tea, which is pink in colour (known as chinen posh rang or peach flower colour) and popular with locals; and [[kahwah]], a tea for festive occasions, made with [[saffron]] and spices (cardamom, cinamon,sugar, noon chai leaves), and black tea.

==Economy==
{{further2|[[Azad Kashmir#Economy|Economy of Azad Kashmir]]|[[Jammu and Kashmir#Economy|Economy of Jammu and Kashmir]]}}
[[File:Kashmir Dal lake boat.jpg|thumb|Tourism is one of the main sources of income for vast sections of the Kashmiri population. Shown here is the famous [[Dal Lake]] in [[Srinagar]], [[India]].]]
[[File:SkarduFromFort1175.JPG|thumb|[[Skardu]] in the Northern Areas, is the point of departure for mountaineering expeditions in the [[Karakoram]]s.]]

Kashmir's economy is centred around agriculture. Traditionally the staple crop of the valley was rice, which formed the chief food of the people. In addition, Indian corn, wheat, barley and oats were also grown. Given its temperate climate, it is suited for crops like [[asparagus]], artichoke, seakale, broad beans, scarletrunners, beetroot, cauliflower and cabbage. Fruit trees are common in the valley, and the cultivated orchards yield pears, [[apple]]s, [[peach]]es, and cherries. The chief trees are [[deodar]], firs and [[pine]]s, [[chenar]] or plane, maple, birch and [[walnut]], apple, cherry.

Historically, Kashmir became known worldwide when [[Cashmere wool]] was exported to other regions and nations (exports have ceased due to decreased abundance of the cashmere goat and increased competition from China). Kashmiris are well adept at [[knitting]] and making [[Pashmina]] [[shawls]], silk carpets, rugs, [[kurta]]s, and pottery. [[Saffron]], too, is grown in Kashmir. Efforts are on to export the naturally grown fruits and vegetables as [[organic food]]s mainly to the [[Middle East]]. Srinagar is known for its silver-work, [[papier mache]], wood-carving, and the weaving of [[silk]].

The economy was badly damaged by the [[2005 Kashmir earthquake]] which, as of October 8, 2005, resulted in over 70,000 deaths in the Pakistan-controlled part of Kashmir and around 1,500 deaths in Indian controlled Kashmir.

The [[Jammu and Kashmir|Indian-administered portion of Kashmir]] is believed to have potentially rich rocks containing hydrocarbon reserves.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dailytimes.com.pk/default.asp?page=2008\10\22\story_22-10-2008_pg7_41|title=Italian company to pursue oil exploration in Kashmir|publisher=[[Daily Times (Pakistan)|Daily Times]]|author=Iftikhar Gilani|date=2008-10-22|accessdate=2009-11-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dnaindia.com/india/report_india-pakistan-to-explore-oil-jointly_1152227|title=India, Pakistan to explore oil jointly|publisher=[[Daily News and Analysis]]|author=Ishfaq-ul-Hassan|date=2008-02-22|accessdate=2009-11-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Transport===
Transport is predominantly by air or road vehicles in the region.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bharatonline.com/kashmir/travel-tips/local-transport.html |title=Local Transport in Kashmir - Means of Transportation Kashmir - Mode of Transportation Kashmir India |publisher=Bharatonline.com |date= |accessdate=2012-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;  
Kashmir has a {{convert|119|km|abbr=on|0}} long modern [[Kashmir railway|railway]] line that started in October 2009 and connects Baramulla in the western part of Kashmir to Srinagar and [[Qazigund]]. It will link the Kashmir to Banihal across the Pir Panjal mountains through the Banihal rail tunnel in 2013 and to the rest of India in another few years as the construction of the railway line from Jammu to Banihal progresses steadily.

==History of tourism in Kashmir==

The state of Jammu &amp; Kashmir is a region of widely varying people and geography. In the south, Jammu is a transition zone from the Indian plains to the Himalaya . Nature has lavishly endowed Kashmir with certain distinctive favors which hardly find a parallel in any alpine land of the world. It is the land of snow clad mountains that shares a common boundary with Afghanistan, China and Pakistan, Jammu and Kashmir is the northernmost state of the Indian Union. Known for its extravagant natural beauty this land formed a major caravan route in the ancient times.

Trade relations through these routes between China and Central Asia made it a land inhabited by various religious and cultural groups. It was during the reign of Kashyapa that the various wandering groups led a settled life Buddhism influenced Kashmir during the rule of Ashoka and the present town of Srinagar was founded by him. This place was earlier called 'Srinagari' or Purandhisthan. The Brahmins who inhabited these areas admired and adorned Buddhism too. From the regions of Kashmir Buddhism spread of Ladakh, Tibet, Central Asia and China. Various traditions co-existed till the advent of the Muslims.

The Mughal had a deep influence on this land and introduced various reforms in the revenue industry and other areas that added to the progress of Kashmir. In 1820 Maharaj Gulab Singh got the Jagir of Jammu from Maharaj Ranjit Sigh. He is said to have laid the foundation of the Dogra dynasty. In 1846 Kashmir was sold to Maharaj Gulab Singh. Thus the two areas of Kashmir and Jammu were integrated into a single political unit. A few chieftains who formed part of the administration were of the Hunza, Kishtwar, Gilgit Ladakh. During the Dogra dynasty trade improved, along with the preservation and promotion of forestry.

==See also==
*[[United Nations Security Council Resolution 47]]
*[[Line of Control]]
*[[Kashmir conflict]]
*[[List of Kashmiri people]]
*[[Kargil War]]
*[[2005 Kashmir earthquake]]
*[[List of Jammu and Kashmir related articles]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}
*{{1911}}

==Cited references==
{{Reflist|2}}
* {{Citation| last1=Bose| first1=Sugata| authorlink1=Sugata Bose| last2=Jalal| first2=Ayesha| authorlink2=Ayesha Jalal| year=2003| title=Modern South Asia: History, Culture, Political Economy| place=| publisher=London and New York: Routledge, 2nd edition. Pp. xiii, 304| isbn=0-415-30787-2}}.
*{{Citation|last=Bose|first=Sumantra|authorlink=Sumantra Bose|title=The Challenge in Kashmir: Democracy, Self Determination and a Just Peace|publisher=New Delhi: Sage Publications.  Pp. 211|year=1997|isbn=0-8039-9350-1}}
*{{Citation|last=Bose|first=Sumantra|title=Kashmir: roots of conflict, paths to peace|publisher=Harvard University Press.  Pp. 307|year=2005|isbn=978-0-674-01817-4}}
* {{Citation| last1=Brown| first1=Judith M.| authorlink=Judith M. Brown| year=1994| title=Modern India: The Origins of an Asian Democracy| place=| publisher=Oxford and New York: [[Oxford University Press]]. Pp. xiii, 474| isbn=0-19-873113-2}}.
* {{Citation | last1=Copland | first1=Ian | year=2002 | title=Princes of India in the Endgame of Empire, 1917-1947| place=| publisher=(Cambridge Studies in Indian History &amp; Society). Cambridge and London: Cambridge University Press. Pp. 316| isbn=0-521-89436-0}}.
*{{Citation|last=Evans|first=Alexander|chapter=Kashmiri Exceptionalism|pages=713&amp;ndash;741|editor-last=Rao|editor-first=Aparna|title=The Valley of Kashmir: The Making and Unmaking of a Composite Culture?|publisher=Delhi: Manohar.  Pp. xviii, 758|year=2008|isbn=978-81-7304-751-0}}
*{{Citation|last=Kaw|first=Mushtaq A.|chapter=Land Rights in Rural Kashmir: A Study in Continuity and Change from Late-Sixteenth to Late-Twentieth Centuries|page=207&amp;ndash;234|editor-last=Rao|editor-first=Aparna|title=The Valley of Kashmir: The Making and Unmaking of a Composite Culture?|publisher=Delhi: Manohar.  Pp. xviii, 758|year=2008|isbn=978-81-7304-751-0}}
*{{Citation|last=Keenan|first=Brigid|authorlink=Brigid Keenan|title=Travels in Kashmir: A Popular History of Its People, Places, and Crafts|publisher=Delhi: Oxford University Press.  Pp. xii, 226|year=1989|isbn=0-19-562236-7}}
*{{Citation|last=Khan|first=Mohammad Ishaq|chapter=Islam, State and Society in Medieval Kashmir: A Revaluation of Mir Sayyid Ali Hamadani's Historical Role|page=97&amp;ndash;198|editor-last=Rao|editor-first=Aparna|title=The Valley of Kashmir: The Making and Unmaking of a Composite Culture?|publisher=Delhi: Manohar.  Pp. xviii, 758|year=2008|isbn=978-81-7304-751-0}}
* {{Citation| last=Khan| first=Yasmin| year=2007| title=The Great Partition: The Making of India and Pakistan| publisher=New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 250 pages| isbn=0-300-12078-8}}
* {{Citation| last1=Kulke| first1=Hermann|authorlink1=Hermann Kulke|last2=Rothermund| first2=Dietmar| year=2004| title=A History of India| place=| publisher=4th edition. Routledge, Pp. xii, 448| isbn=0-415-32920-5| url=}}.
*{{Citation|last=Lamb|first=Alastair|title=Kashmir: a disputed legacy, 1846-1990|year=1991|publisher=Oxford University Press.  Pp. 368|isbn=978-0-19-577423-8}}
*{{Citation|last=Lamb|first=Alastair|year=1997|title=Incomplete partition: the genesis of the Kashmir dispute 1947-1948|publisher=Roxford.  Pp. 374|isbn=0-907129-08-0}}
*{{Citation|last=Madan|first=T. N.|authorlink=Triloki Nath Madan|chapter=Kashmir, Kashmiris, Kashmiriyat: An Introductory Essay|pages=1&amp;ndash;36|editor-last=Rao|editor-first=Aparna|title=The Valley of Kashmir: The Making and Unmaking of a Composite Culture?|publisher=Delhi: Manohar.  Pp. xviii, 758|year=2008|isbn=978-81-7304-751-0}}
*{{Citation|last=Malik|first=Iffat|title=Kashmir: Ethnic Conflict, International Dispute|publisher= Karachi and Oxford: Oxford University Press.  Pp. xxvi, 392|isbn=0-19-579622-5|year=2005}}
* {{Citation| last1=Metcalf| first1=Barbara|authorlink1=Barbara Metcalf| last2=Metcalf| first2=Thomas R.| authorlink2=Thomas R. Metcalf| year=2006| title=A Concise History of Modern India (Cambridge Concise Histories) | place=| publisher=Cambridge and New York: [[Cambridge University Press]]. Pp. xxxiii, 372 | isbn=0-521-68225-8| url=}}.
*{{Citation|last=Rai|first=Mridu|title=Hindu Rulers, Muslim Subjects: Islam, Rights, and the History of Kashmir|year=2004|publisher=Princeton University Press/Permanent Black.  Pp. xii, 335.|isbn=81-7824-202-8}}
* {{Citation | last = Ramusack | first = Barbara |authorlink=Barbara Ramusack| year = 2004 | title = The Indian Princes and their States (The New Cambridge History of India) | publisher = Cambridge and London: Cambridge University Press. Pp. 324 | isbn = 0-521-03989-4}}
*{{Citation|editor-last=Rao|editor-first=Aparna|title=The Valley of Kashmir: The Making and Unmaking of a Composite Culture?|publisher=Delhi: Manohar.  Pp. xviii, 758|year=2008|isbn=978-81-7304-751-0}}
*{{Citation|last=Reynolds|first=Nathalène|chapter=Revisiting Key Episodes in Modern Kashmir History|pages=563&amp;ndash;604|editor-last=Rao|editor-first=Aparna|title=The Valley of Kashmir: The Making and Unmaking of a Composite Culture?|publisher=Delhi: Manohar.  Pp. xviii, 758|year=2008|isbn=978-81-7304-751-0}}
*{{Citation|last=Schaffer|first=Howard B.|title=The Limits of Influence: America's Role in Kashmir|year = 2009|publisher=Brookings Institution Press/Viking Penguin India.  Pp. xii, 272|isbn=978-0-670-08372-5}}
*{{Citation|last=Schofield|first=Victoria|title=Kashmir in conflict: India, Pakistan and the unending war|year=2010|publisher=I. B. Tauris.  Pp. xvi, 318|isbn=978-1-84885-105-4}}
* {{Citation| last1=Stein| first1=Burton| authorlink=Burton Stein| year=2001| title=A History of India| place=| publisher=New Delhi and Oxford: Oxford University Press. Pp. xiv, 432| isbn=0-19-565446-3| url=}}.
*{{Citation|last1=Talbot|first1=Ian|last2=Singh|first2=Gurharpal|title=The Partition of India|year =2009|publisher=Cambridge University Press.  Pp. xviii, 206|isbn=978-0-521-76177-2}}
*{{Citation|last=Witzel|first=Michael|authorlink=Michael Witzel|chapter=The Kashmiri Pandits: Their Early History|pages=37&amp;ndash;96|editor-last=Rao|editor-first=Aparna|title=The Valley of Kashmir: The Making and Unmaking of a Composite Culture?|publisher=Delhi: Manohar.  Pp. xviii, 758|year=2008|isbn=978-81-7304-751-0}}
* {{Citation| last=Wolpert| first=Stanley| authorlink=Stanley Wolpert| year=2006| title=Shameful Flight: The Last Years of the British Empire in India| publisher=Oxford and New York: Oxford University Press. Pp. 272| isbn=0-19-515198-4}}.
*{{Citation|last=Zutshi|first=Chitralekha|title=Language of belonging: Islam, regional identity, and the making of Kashmir|year=2003|publisher=Oxford University Press/Permanent Black.  Pp. 359|isbn=978-0-19-521939-5}}
*{{Citation|last=Zutshi|first=Chitraleka|chapter=Shrines, Political Authority, and Religious Identities in Late-Nineteenth and Early-Twentieth-century Kashmir|pages=235&amp;ndash;258|editor-last=Rao|editor-first=Aparna|title=The Valley of Kashmir: The Making and Unmaking of a Composite Culture?|publisher=Delhi: Manohar.  Pp. xviii, 758|year=2008|isbn=978-81-7304-751-0}}

==Further reading==
{{Refbegin|2}}
* Blank, Jonah. &quot;Kashmir–Fundamentalism Takes Root,&quot; Foreign Affairs, 78,6 (November/December 1999): 36-42.
* Drew, Federic. 1877. &quot;The Northern Barrier of India: a popular account of the Jammoo and Kashmir Territories with Illustrations; 1st edition: Edward Stanford, London. Reprint: Light &amp; Life Publishers, Jammu. 1971.
* Evans, Alexander. Why Peace Won't Come to Kashmir, Current History (Vol 100, No 645) April 2001 p. 170-175.
* Hussain, Ijaz. 1998. &quot;Kashmir Dispute: An International Law Perspective&quot;, National Institute of Pakistan Studies.
* Irfani, Suroosh, ed &quot;Fifty Years of the Kashmir Dispute&quot;: Based on the proceedings of the International Seminar held at Muzaffarabad, Azad Jammu and Kashmir August 24–25, 1997: University of Azad Jammu and Kashmir, Muzaffarabad, AJK, 1997.
* [[Manoj Joshi|Joshi, Manoj]] Lost Rebellion: Kashmir in the Nineties (Penguin, New Delhi, 1999).
* Khan, L. Ali [http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=987561 The Kashmir Dispute: A Plan for Regional Cooperation] 31 Columbia Journal of Transnational Law, 31, p.&amp;nbsp;495 (1994).
* Knight, E. F. 1893. ''Where Three Empires Meet: A Narrative of Recent Travel in: Kashmir, Western Tibet, Gilgit, and the adjoining countries''. Longmans, Green, and Co., London. Reprint: Ch'eng Wen Publishing Company, Taipei. 1971.
* Knight, William, Henry. 1863. ''Diary of a Pedestrian in Cashmere and Thibet''. Richard Bentley, London. Reprint 1998: Asian Educational Services, New Delhi.
* [[Hans Köchler|Köchler, Hans]]. [http://i-p-o.org/Koechler-Kashmir_Discourse-European_Parliament-April2008.htm ''The Kashmir Problem between Law and Realpolitik. Reflections on a Negotiated Settlement'']. Keynote speech delivered at the &quot;Global Discourse on Kashmir 2008.&quot; European Parliament, Brussels, 1 April 2008.
* [[William Moorcroft (explorer)|Moorcroft, William]] and [[Trebeck, George]]. 1841. ''Travels in the Himalayan Provinces of Hindustan and the Panjab; in Ladakh and Kashmir, in Peshawar, Kabul, Kunduz, and Bokhara... from 1819 to 1825'', Vol. II. Reprint: New Delhi, Sagar Publications, 1971.
* Neve, Arthur. (Date unknown). ''The Tourist's Guide to Kashmir, Ladakh, Skardo &amp;amp;c''. 18th Edition. Civil and Military Gazette, Ltd., Lahore. (The date of this edition is unknown - but the 16th edition was published in 1938).
* Stein, M. Aurel. 1900. ''Kalhaṇa's Rājataraṅgiṇī–A Chronicle of the Kings of Kaśmīr'', 2 vols. London, A. Constable &amp; Co. Ltd. 1900. Reprint, Delhi, Motilal Banarsidass, 1979.
* Younghusband, Francis and Molyneux, Edward 1917. ''Kashmir''. A. &amp; C. Black, London.
* Norelli-Bachelet, Patrizia. &quot;Kashmir and the Convergence of Time, Space and Destiny&quot;, 2004; ISBN 0-945747-00-4. First published as a four-part series, March 2002 - April 2003, in 'Prakash', a review of the Jagat Guru Bhagavaan Gopinath Ji Charitable Foundation. [http://www.patrizianorellibachelet.com/Kashmir.html]
* Muhammad Ayub. ''An Army; Ita Role &amp; Rule (A History of the Pakistan Army from Independence to Kargil 1947-1999)'' Rosedog Books, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania USA 2005. ISBN 0-8059-9594-3.
{{Refend}}

==External links==
*[http://mha.nic.in/pdfs/AccessionDoc.pdf Instrument of Accession]
*[http://www.un.org/Depts/dpko/missions/unmogip/ United Nations Military Observers Group in Kashmir]
*[http://jammukashmir.nic.in/ Official website of the Jammu and Kashmir Government] (Indian-administered Kashmir)
*[http://www.ajk.gov.pk/ Official website of the Azad Jammu and Kashmir Government] (Pakistan-administered Kashmir)
*[http://www.kasheeronline.com/kashmir-resources.asp] (Kashmir resources)
{{Coord|34.5|N|76|E|scale:3000000|display=title}}
{{Azad Kashmir topics}}
{{Jammu and Kashmir topics}}
{{Territorial disputes in East, South, and Southeast Asia}}

[[Category:Kashmir| ]]
[[Category:Disputed territories in Asia]]
[[Category:Geography of India]]

[[ar:كشمير]]
[[an:Caixmir]]
[[az:Kəşmir]]
[[bn:কাশ্মীর]]
[[be:Кашмір]]
[[bg:Кашмир]]
[[bs:Kašmir]]
[[ca:Caixmir]]
[[cs:Kašmír]]
[[da:Kashmir]]
[[de:Kaschmir]]
[[et:Kashmir]]
[[el:Κασμίρ]]
[[es:Cachemira (región)]]
[[eo:Kaŝmiro]]
[[eu:Kaxmir]]
[[fa:کشمیر]]
[[fo:Kashmir]]
[[fr:Cachemire]]
[[gl:Caxemira]]
[[gu:કાશ્મીર]]
[[ko:카슈미르]]
[[hi:कश्मीर]]
[[hr:Kašmir]]
[[id:Kashmir]]
[[it:Kashmir]]
[[he:קשמיר]]
[[kn:ಕಾಶ್ಮೀರ]]
[[ks:کٔشِیر]]
[[kk:Кашмир]]
[[sw:Kashmir]]
[[la:Caspira]]
[[lv:Kašmīra]]
[[lt:Kašmyras]]
[[hu:Kasmír (régió)]]
[[ml:കശ്മീര്‍]]
[[mr:काश्‍मीर]]
[[mzn:کشمیر]]
[[ms:Kashmir]]
[[mn:Кашмир]]
[[nl:Jammu en Kasjmir (gebied)]]
[[new:काष्मीर् (सन् २००३या संकिपा)]]
[[ja:カシミール]]
[[no:Kashmir]]
[[nn:Kashmir]]
[[or:କାଶ୍ମୀର]]
[[pnb:کشمیر]]
[[ps:کشمير]]
[[nds:Kaschmir]]
[[pl:Dżammu i Kaszmir (region)]]
[[pt:Caxemira]]
[[ro:Cașmir]]
[[ru:Кашмир]]
[[simple:Kashmir]]
[[sr:Кашмир]]
[[sh:Kašmir]]
[[fi:Kashmir]]
[[sv:Kashmir]]
[[ta:காஷ்மீர்]]
[[tt:Кашмир]]
[[tg:Кашмир]]
[[tr:Keşmir]]
[[uk:Кашмір]]
[[ur:کشمیر]]
[[ug:كەشمىر]]
[[vi:Kashmir]]
[[diq:Keşmir]]
[[zh:克什米尔]]</text>
      <sha1>p7abmki2p9cdu6n2fdq12h604pxj4k5</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
