<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Masculism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>25454239</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520927127</id>
      <parentid>518303598</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-01T17:46:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>186.104.67.4</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18771">{{Refimprove|date=April 2012}}
'''Masculism''' or '''masculinism''' may refer to advocacy of the rights or needs of men and the adherence to or promotion of opinions, values, etc., regarded as typical of men. Two of the most prominent men's rights advocates, [[Warren Farrell]] and Jack Kammer, have been said to define &quot;masculism&quot; as &quot;1. the belief that equality between the sexes requires the recognition and redress of prejudice and discrimination against men as well as women. 2. the movement organized around this belief.&quot;&lt;ref name=reason&gt;{{cite news|publisher=''[[Reason magazine|Reason]]''|title=Man Troubles: Making Sense of the Men's Movement|author=[[Cathy Young]]|date=July 1994|quote=Mas*cu*lism, n. 1. the belief that equality between the sexes requires the recognition and redress of prejudice and discrimination against men as well as women. 2. the movement organized around this belief. Not to worry: This word is not in the dictionary. But it would be if the decision were up to Warren Farrell, Jack Kammer, and others activists in the men's movement.|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1568/is_n3_v26/ai_16075316/}} &quot;Not to worry&quot; there seems to imply that this conception of masculism poses a threat to women, or to the women's movement. A broader conception of the women's movement, however, recognizes that patriarchy is harmful to both men and women, and therefore that prejudice and discrimination against both genders will need to be recognized and redressed.&lt;/ref&gt; Adherents to such a philosophy may call themselves '''masculists''' or '''masculinists'''.

'''Masculism''' also refers to [[antifeminism]] and advocacy of male superiority and dominance.&lt;ref name=&quot;oedMasculinism&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=masculinism, n|url=http://dictionary.oed.com/cgi/entry/00302767|work=Oxford English Dictionary Online|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|accessdate=2010-11-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Masculinist&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=masculinist, n|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/masculinist|work=Merriam-Webster|publisher=[[Merriam-Webster]]|accessdate=2011-07-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Masculism&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=masculism, n|url=http://www.allwords.com/word-masculism.html|work=allwords|publisher=allwords|accessdate=2011-07-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Controversial definition==
{{Section OR|date=September 2012|reason=The entire &quot;morphological difference&quot; paragraph appears to be original research, in particular a mixture of personal opinion and novel synthesis.}}

What is contested in the definition of masculism is its attitude toward [[feminism]]. 

The [[Merriam-Webster|Merriam-Webster Dictionary]] defines a &quot;masculinist&quot; as &quot;an advocate of male superiority and dominance&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Masculinist&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=masculinist, n|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/masculinist|work=Merriam-Webster|publisher=[[Merriam-Webster]]|accessdate=2011-07-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Oxford English Dictionary]] regards it as &quot;Advocacy of the rights of men; adherence to or promotion of opinions, values, etc., regarded as typical of men; (more generally) anti-feminism, machismo.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;oedMasculinism&quot;&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Masculist concerns==

According to [[Cathy Young]], the main concerns raised by masculist men's rights activists are [[discrimination]] and [[prejudice]] against men:&lt;ref name=&quot;reason&quot;/&gt;

=== Discrimination against men ===

'''Education'''
* Some studies have indicated that because boys attract more teacher attention in classrooms compared to girls, boys also receive harsher forms of punishment as well as more frequent punishment than girls for the same offences.&lt;ref name=reason/&gt;

'''Employment'''

* Data from 1994 in the U.S. reported that 94% of workplace fatalities occur to men. Masculist Warren Farrell has argued that men are often clustered in dirty, physically demanding and hazardous jobs in an unjustifiably disproportionate manner.&lt;ref name=reason/&gt;

'''Violence'''
{{Violence against men}}
* Violence against men is depicted as humorous, in the media and elsewhere.&lt;ref name=MYTH&gt;Warren Farrell, ''The Myth of Male Power: Why Men Are the Disposable Sex'' (NY: Simon &amp; Schuster, 1993; ISBN 0-671-79349-7).&lt;/ref&gt; One prominent example addressed by the masculist men's rights movement is the [[Boys are stupid, throw rocks at them! controversy|Boys are stupid, throw rocks at them!]] controversy. In December 2003, radio-host and masculist men's rights activist Glenn Sacks started a campaign against the &quot;Boys are stupid, throw rocks at them!&quot; T-shirts, on the grounds of [[misandry]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first = D | last = Crary | url = http://seattletimes.nwsource.com/html/nationworld/2001847133_stupidboys30.html | title = 'Stores pull &quot;Boys Are Stupid&quot; merchandise' | work = [[The Seattle Times]] | date = 2004-01-30 | accessdate = 2009-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[People (magazine)|''People'' magazine]] ran a story on the T-shirt, opening with a quote from a then 10 year-old girl, &quot;I want to make boys feel bad because it's fun.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.people.com/people/archive/article/0,,20147751,00.html | title = Guy Trouble: Boys Are Stupid gear has some folks teed off, but creator Todd Goldman is cashing in | publisher = [[People (magazine)|People]] | date = 2005-06-06 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The campaign against the line received support from several masculist groups, such as the [[National Coalition of Free Men]], but also from groups with broader agendas, such as the [[Southern Poverty Law Center]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | first = D | last = Williams | url = http://www.tolerance.org/news/article_tol.jsp?id=929 | title = Clothing Designer Misses Point of 'Girl Power' | publisher = [[Southern Poverty Law Center|Tolerance.org]] | date = 2004-01-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Violence against men ignored, minimalized or taken less seriously than violence against women.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iol.co.za/index.php?click_id=13&amp;art_id=vn20081125064002133C731559&amp;set_id= iol.co.za]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Assumption of female innocence or sympathy for women, said to predictably result in problems such as disproportionate penalties for men and women for similar crimes,&lt;ref name=&quot;MYTH&quot; /&gt; lack of sympathy for male victims in [[domestic violence]] cases, and dismissal of female-on-male [[sexual assault]] and [[sexual harassment]] cases.

'''Custody'''
{{main|Fathers' rights movement}}
&quot;Custody law is perhaps the best-known area of men's rights activism&quot;, as it is more common for the mother to obtain custody of children in case of divorce. David Benatar, head of philosophy at the [[University of Cape Town]], argues: &quot;When the man is the primary care-giver his chances of winning custody are lower than when the woman is the primary care-giver. Even when the case is not contested by the mother, he's still not as likely to get custody as when the woman's claim is uncontested&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-17907534 &quot;Just who are men's rights activists?&quot;], BBC, 2 May 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

== Differences in masculist ideology ==
Because it is the name of a political and social movement, masculism is sometimes considered synonymous with the [[men's rights]] or [[fathers' rights]] movements. However, many in the fathers' rights movement make a clear distinction between masculism and their own often quite varied approaches to gender relations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://gendereconomy.com/main/index1.html Gender Economy &gt; ''Definitions'' &gt; ''Masculism'']: &quot;As a political and social movement masculism is considered by some feminists to be synonymous with the men's rights or fathers' rights movements. However, many of the fathers' rights movement make a clear distinction between masculism and their own often quite varied approaches to gender relations.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reactions==
===Feminism===
Feminists respond to the different ideologies of masculism in different ways. Masculists who promote gender equality are often considered [[male feminism|male feminists]].&lt;ref&gt;Janet M. Martin and Maryanne Borrelli, ''Other Elites: Women, Politics, &amp; Power in the Executive Branch'' (Lynne Rienner Publishers, 2000; ISBN 1-55587-971-3, ISBN 978-1-55587-971-6).&lt;/ref&gt; It is the general opinion of [[Feminism|modern feminists]] that masculism, when defined as &quot;male superiority or dominance&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Masculinist&quot;/&gt; is inherently opposed to the equality cause and is considered a form of [[misogyny]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Reaction and resistance: feminism, law, and social change|author1=Susan B. Boyd|author2=Dorothy E. Chunn|author3=Hester Lessard|pages=65–97|year=2007|publisher=UBC Press|ISBN=978-0-7748-1411-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
Some feminists are actively involved in promoting men's rights, especially father's rights and social equality, arguing that this position is necessary for feminism and women's equality.

===Criticisms and responses===

To the extent that masculism is associated with antifeminist masculininism, its primary focus is on “masculinity and the place of white heterosexual men in North America and European societies.”&lt;ref name=&quot;Blais, Melissa 2012&quot;&gt;Melissa Blais and Francis Dupuis-Déri. &quot;Masculinism and the Antifeminist Countermovement.&quot; ''Social Movement Studies: Journal of Social, Cultural and Political Protest'' 11:1 (2012): 21-39.&lt;/ref&gt;

As previously stated, some masculinists believe that differentiated gender roles are natural. There is considerable evidence for social influences (e.g. gender division of labor, socialization) as the sole or primary origin of gender differentiation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Risman, Barbara 2004&quot;&gt;Barbara Risman, &quot;Gender as a Social Structure: Theory Wrestling with Activism.&quot; ''Gender &amp; Society'' 18.4 (2004): 429-450.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Susan A. Basow, ''Gender Stereotypes and Roles'' (Pacific Grove, CA: Brooks/Cole, 1992).&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, belief in inherent gender differences allows for inequality and for the dominant group to assert power by means of perceived difference.&lt;ref name=&quot;Risman, Barbara 2004&quot;/&gt;

Despite the concern of some feminist groups towards the rights of men, some masculinist movements are explicitly antifeminist.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blais, Melissa 2012&quot;/&gt; According to Blais and Dupuis-Déri, “the contents of [masculinist] websites and the testimony of feminists that we questioned confirm that masculinists are generally critical of even moderate feminists and feminists at the head of official feminist organizations.”&lt;ref name=&quot;Blais, Melissa 2012&quot;/&gt; Masculinist activism has involved disruption of events organized by feminists and lawsuits against feminist academics, journalists, or activists.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blais, Melissa 2012&quot;/&gt; Furthermore, masculinist actions are sometimes extreme; father’s rights activists have bombed family courts in Australia and have issued bomb threats in the UK, although it is ambiguous whether there was public and organized militant group involvement.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blais, Melissa 2012&quot;/&gt; They have also engaged in “tire-slashing, the mailing of excrement-filled packages, threats against politicians and their children.”&lt;ref name=&quot;Blais, Melissa 2012&quot;/&gt; Spokesmen for these groups have also spoken out against public awareness campaigns to prevent sexual assault, arguing that they portray a negative image of men, and one masculinist group harassed administrators of dozens of battered women’s shelters and women’s centers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blais, Melissa 2012&quot;/&gt;

'''Education'''

*A study of children in preschools found that girls are punished by teachers for speaking, playing, and moving in general, while similar behavior is ignored when enacted by boys&lt;ref&gt;Karin Martin, “Becoming a Gendered Body: Practices of Preschools.” ''American Sociological Review'' 63 (1998): 494-511.&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Employment'''

*In reference to physical ability requirements in certain occupations (e.g. the army, police, fire service, etc.), women in male dominated occupations must prove themselves to be physically able to a larger degree than men, and women are likely to be hired at less pay and less likely to get promotions.&lt;ref&gt;Christine Williams, ''Gender Differences at Work: Women and Men in Nontraditional Occupations'' (Berkeley and LA: University of California Press, 1991).&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, these institutions are not likely to have established standards for maternity leave, or codes related to sexual harassment – which women in male dominated fields are very likely to experience.&lt;ref&gt;Barbara Gutek and Robert Done, Chapter 25: Sexual Harassment (2001).&lt;/ref&gt; Studies have also found that female police officers  are expected to do a larger amount of emotional labor than male police officers.{{citation needed|date=June 2012}}

'''Family'''

*In regard to masculinist concerns regarding child custody laws or practices, current statutes are gender-neutral. Despite this, men’s advocacy groups argue that custody decisions discriminate against fathers, while women’s advocacy groups (and the media)  counter that custody decisions discriminate against mothers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Warshak, Richard 1996&quot;&gt;Richard Warshak, &quot;Gender Bias in Child Custody Decisions.&quot; ''Family Court Review'' 34.3 (1996): 396-409.&lt;/ref&gt; However, “[g]ender stereotypes [such as nurturing caretaker] that favor mothers' preferential claims to custody are not supported by research”,&lt;ref name=&quot;Warshak, Richard 1996&quot;/&gt; despite widespread claims to the contrary. In custody decisions, gender biases can favor either men or women: “a judge may decline to consider a father a serious candidate for custody, just as he may decline to find fit for custody a divorced mother who works or one who is sexually active.”&lt;ref&gt;http://digitalcommons.law.umaryland.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1304&amp;context=fac_pubs&amp;sei-redir=1&amp;referer=http%3A%2F%2Fscholar.google.com%2Fscholar%3Fq%3Dgender%2Bbias%2Bchild%2Bsupport%26hl%3Den%26as_sdt%3D0%26as_vis%3D1%26oi%3Dscholart%26sa%3DX%26ei%3D1F9FT6SIKYfJtgeygpiEAw%26ved%3D0CB0QgQMwAA#search=%22gender%20bias%20child%20support%22&lt;/ref&gt; In some countries, the majority of fathers do not seek joint or primary custody. For example, during the early 21st century in Québec, 80% of child custody cases were settled outside of court because the majority of fathers did not seek joint custody, and still fewer sought primary custody.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blais, Melissa 2012&quot;/&gt; Further, 5% of cases were settled by default, usually due to the father failing to appear in court.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blais, Melissa 2012&quot;/&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Men's rights|Discrimination}}
* [[Antifeminism]]
* [[Chauvinism]]
* [[Complementarianism]]
* [[Hypermasculinity]]
* [[Kyriarchy]]
* [[Machismo]]
* [[Masculine psychology]]
* [[Masculinity]]
* [[Matriarchy]]
* [[Men's liberation]]
* [[Men's movement]]
* [[Men's spaces]]
* [[Misandry]]
* [[Patriarchy]]
* [[Reverse discrimination]]
* [[Sexism]]

===Men's organizations===
* [[Fathers 4 Justice]]
* [[International Men's Day]] (19 November: [[Trinidad and Tobago]], [[Jamaica]], [[Australia]], [[India]], [[United States]], [[Singapore]], [[United Kingdom]], [[Malta]], [[South Africa]], [[Hungary]], [[Ireland]], [[Ghana]], and [[Canada]])
* [[Promise Keepers]]
* [[Save Indian Family]]

===Notable persons associated with masculism===
* [[Warren Farrell]]
* [[Henry Makow]]
* [[Harvey Mansfield]]
* [[Glenn Sacks]]

===Books===
* ''[[Manliness (book)]]'' (2006)

==Bibliography==
*''[http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/6762 Politics]'' of [[Aristotle]] asserts excellence varies with social role, including gender.
*[[s:The Legal Subjection of Men|''The Legal Subjection of Men'']], 1908 antithesis of [[John Stuart Mill]]'s 1869 ''[[The Subjection of Women]]''.
*[[s:The Fraud of Feminism|''The Fraud of Feminism'']] by [[Ernest Belfort Bax]], 1914.
*''The Myth of the Monstrous Male and Other Feminist Fallacies''; John Gordon, Playboy Press, New York, 1982; ISBN 0-87223-758-3
*''The Myth of Male Power: Why Men Are the Disposable Sex''; Warren Farrell, Simon &amp; Schuster, New York, 1993: ISBN 0-671-79349-7
*''Manliness'' by [[Harvey Mansfield]] (2006) Yale Press [http://yalepress.yale.edu/yupbooks/book.asp?isbn=0300106645] ISBN 0-300-10664-5
*''Not Guilty: The Case in Defense of Men''; David Thomas, William Morrow and Co., Inc., New York, 1993; ISBN 0-688-11024-X
*''Good Will Toward Men''; Jack Kammer, St. Martin's Press, New York, 1994; ISBN 0-312-10471-5
*''Moral Panic: Biopolitics Rising''; John Fekete, Robert Davies Publishing, Montreal-Toronto, 1994: ISBN 1-895854-09-1
*''The New Men's Studies: A Selected and Annotated Interdisciplinary Bibliography'' (2nd Edition); Eugene R. August, Libraries Unlimited, Inc., Englewood, CO, 1994: ISBN 1-56308-084-2
*''A Man's World: How Real Is Male Privilege - And How High Is Its Price?''; Ellis Cose, Harper Collins, New York, 1995: ISBN 0-06-017206-1
*''Why Men Don't Iron: The Real Science of Gender Studies''; Anne &amp; Bill Moir, Harper Collins, Hammersmith, London, 1998; ISBN 0-00-257035-1 (Trade Paperback); ISBN 0-00-257048-3 (Hardcover)
*''The Church Impotent: The Feminization of Christianity''; Leon J. Podles, Spence Publishing Co., Dallas, TX, 1999. (The title is a play on the Christian theological terms [[Church militant and church triumphant|''church militant'' and ''church triumphant'']].)
*''Spreading Misandry: The Teaching of Contempt for Men in Popular Culture''; Paul Nathanson and Katherine K. Young, McGill-Queen's University Press, Montreal, 2001; ISBN 0-7735-2272-7

*''Sex Differences, Modern Biology and the Unisex Fallacy'', Yves Christen
*''Who Stole Feminism?: How Women Have Betrayed Women''; Christina Hoff Sommers ISBN 0-684-80156-6
*''The War Against Boys: How Misguided Feminism Is Harming Our Young Men''; Christina Hoff Sommers ISBN 0-684-84956-9
*''Domestic Violence: The 12 Things You Aren't Supposed to Know'' by Thomas B. James ISBN 1-59330-122-7
*''Ceasefire! : Why Women And Men Must Join Forces To Achieve True Equality''; Cathy Young ISBN 0-684-83442-1
*''The Masculine Mystique''; Andrew Kimbrell ISBN 0-345-38658-2

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|masculinism}}
{{Wiktionary}}
*[http://www.acfc.org American Coalition for Fathers and Children]
*[http://www.fathersforvirginia.org Equal Parental Rights for Fathers]
*[http://www.ncfm.org National Coalition of Free Men]

{{Navboxes
|list =
{{Masculism}}
{{Discrimination}}
}}

[[Category:Gender studies]]
[[Category:Gender]]
[[Category:Men's movement]]
[[Category:Neologisms]]
[[Category:Words coined in the 1980s]]
[[Category:Social theories]]
[[Category:Civil rights and liberties]]

[[ar:ذكورية]]
[[ceb:Maskulinismo]]
[[cs:Maskulinismus]]
[[de:Männerrechtsbewegung]]
[[es:Masculinismo]]
[[fa:مردسالاری]]
[[fr:Masculinisme]]
[[ko:남성주의]]
[[it:Mascolinismo]]
[[ja:マスキュリズム]]
[[pt:Masculinismo]]
[[ru:Маскулизм]]
[[sk:Maskulinizmus]]
[[fi:Maskulismi]]
[[sv:Maskulinism]]
[[tr:Maskülizm]]
[[zh:男性主義]]</text>
      <sha1>q7sb76lrmiwjekhdhqjhq6ofuvq1wbw</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
