<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Native American name controversy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2579018</id>
    <revision>
      <id>513947283</id>
      <parentid>513501627</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-22T00:04:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>70.26.160.51</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="36227">{{refimprove|date=July 2011}}
The '''Native American name controversy''' is a dispute about the acceptable terminology for the [[indigenous peoples of the Americas]] and broad subsets of these peoples, such as those sharing certain cultures and languages by which more discrete groups identify themselves (e.g., &quot;[[Algonquin language|Algonquin]]-speaking peoples,&quot; &quot;[[Pueblo]]-dwelling peoples&quot;).

Many [[English language|English]] [[exonyms]] have been used to refer to the indigenous peoples of what is now known as [[the Americas]], who were resident when European colonists arrived in the 15th and 16th centuries. Some of these names were based on [[French language|French]], [[Spanish language|Spanish]], or other European language terminology used by earlier explorers and/or colonists; some resulted from the colonists' attempt to translate [[endonyms]] from the native language into their own; and some were pejorative terms arising out of prejudice and fear, during periods of [[American Indian Wars|conflict]] between the cultures involved.

In the 20th and 21st centuries, indigenous peoples in the Americas have been more vocal about the ways they wish to be referred to, pressing for the elimination of terms widely considered to be obsolete, inaccurate, or [[racism|racist]]. During the latter half of the 20th century and the rise of the [[Indian rights movement]], the [[United States government]] responded by proposing the use of the term &quot;Native American,&quot; to recognize the primacy of indigenous peoples' tenure in the nation. The term has met with only partial acceptance. Other naming conventions have been proposed and used, but none are accepted by all indigenous groups. Typically, each name has a particular audience and political or cultural connotation, and regional usage varies.

== Salient issues affecting the debate ==
* Sentimental attachment to a previous name (example: &quot;Indian&quot; is a name which many [[American Indian elder|elders]] have known all their lives, and their families may continue to use the familiar term);
* Rejection of a word perceived as [[wikt:quaint|quaint]] or [[pejorative]] (example: &quot;[[Eskimo]]&quot;);
* Rejection of names used by outsiders and not the individual Tribe or Indian people at large (example: &quot;[[Nez Perce people|Nez Perce]]&quot; is a French phrase; &quot;Native American&quot; was coined by the US government);
* Perception that a name is inherently racist, or has over time acquired racist overtones;
* Rejection of names assigned by an occupying and oppressive colonial government or expedition;
* Belief that a name is too inclusive or not inclusive enough of all indigenous people, so does not effectively convey the group intended (example: &quot;Aboriginal&quot; has become associated with [[Australian Aborigines]] given its wide use on that continent; the UN uses &quot;Indigenous&quot; to refer to all tribal peoples around the world (as their representatives chose to be identified); &quot;Native American&quot; in general use has not applied to indigenous peoples within Canada or Mexico);
* Reluctance of members of individual Indian Nations to be referred to by a collective, racial name;
* Belief that a universal/collective name suggests, inaccurately, that the indigenous cultures referred to are homogenous, monolithic bodies, rather than the widely varied separate nations that they actually are.

==United States==
=== &quot;Indian&quot; and &quot;American Indian&quot; ===
[[File:1683 Mortier Map of North America, the West Indies, and the Atlantic Ocean - Geographicus - Atlantique-mortier-1693.jpg|250px|right|thumb|1693 nautical chart of the Atlantic Ocean marked with &quot;''Route de Europe aux Indes Occidentales''&quot; or &quot;West Indies&quot;]]

Europeans at the time of [[Christopher Columbus]]'s voyage often referred to all of [[South Asia|South]] and [[East Asia]] as &quot;[[India]]&quot; or &quot;the Indias/[[Indies]],&quot; sometimes dividing the area into &quot;[[Greater India]],&quot; &quot;Middle India,&quot; and &quot;Lesser India.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Biggest Misnomer of All Time?|url=http://www.visualthesaurus.com/cm/wordroutes/2015/|date=2009-10-12|first=Ben|last=Zimmer|authorlink=Ben Zimmer|publisher=VisualThesaurus}}&lt;/ref&gt; The oldest surviving terrestrial globe, by [[Martin Behaim]] in 1492 (before Columbus' voyage), labels [[Greater India|the entire Asian subcontinent region]] as &quot;India&quot;.&lt;ref name=Encarta&gt;''Microsoft Encarta Encyclopedia,'' 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

Columbus carried a passport in [[Latin]] from the Spanish monarchs that dispatched him ''ab partes Indie'' (&quot;toward the regions of India&quot;) on their behalf. When he landed in the [[Antilles]], Columbus referred to the resident peoples he encountered there as &quot;Indians&quot; in the mistaken belief that he had reached the [[Indian Ocean]].&lt;ref name=STRAIGHTDOPE&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.straightdope.com/columns/read/1966/does-indian-derive-from-columbuss-description-of-native-americans-as-una-gente-in-dios|title=Does &quot;Indian&quot; derive from Columbus's description of Native Americans as &quot;una gente in Dios&quot;?|date=2001-10-25|first=Cecil|last=Adams|authorlink=Cecil Adams|publisher=[[The Straight Dope]]|accessdate=2011-07-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although Columbus' mistake was soon recognized, the name stuck; for centuries the native people of the Americas were collectively called &quot;Indians.&quot; This misnomer was perpetuated in place naming; the islands of the [[Caribbean]] were named, and are still known as, the [[West Indies]].

In the late 20th century, some American public figures suggested that the origin of the term was not from a confusion with India, but from the [[Spanish language|Spanish]] expression ''En Dios'', meaning &quot;in God,&quot; or a similar one in Italian. Proponents of this idea include the American Indian [[activist]] [[Russell Means]];&lt;ref name=&quot;I AM&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.archive.org/web/20090503130744/http://www.peaknet.net/~aardvark/means.html|title=I am an american Indian, not a native American!|publisher=PeakNet|first=Russel|last=Means}}&lt;/ref&gt; the author [[Peter Matthiessen]], author of ''In the Spirit of Crazy Horse,'' a view of American Indian history through the life and trial of [[Lakota people|Lakota]] activist [[Leonard Peltier]]; and the comedian [[George Carlin]].&lt;ref name=WORDMYTHS&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=cp0r3aa8EM8C&amp;pg=PA163&amp;lpg=PA163&amp;dq=indian+%22in+dios%22+wilton&amp;source=web&amp;ots=W-NiF2NqFJ&amp;sig=fbsd08E-hqFNtusM30eS20dLky0#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|title=Word myths: debunking linguistic urban legends|first=David|last=Wilton|page=163|publisher=Oxford University Press, USA|isbn=978-0-19-517284-3|date=2004-12-02|accessdate=2011-07-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; In his book ''The Wind Is My Mother'', the [[Muscogee (Creek)|Muskogee]] writer Bear Heart (''Nokus Feke Ematha Tustanaki'') wrote, &quot;When Columbus found the natives here, they were gentle people who accepted him, so Columbus wrote in his journal, 'These are people of God' (&quot;''una gente in Dios''&quot;). Later the 's' was dropped and ''Indio'' became ''Indian''.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Bear Heart|title=The Wind Is My Mother|page=160}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, as the writer David Wilton noted in his book ''Word Myths: Debunking Linguistic Urban Legends'', this phrase does not appear in any of Columbus' writing. Wilton also says that since Greek and Roman times, more than a millennium before the voyages of Columbus, many European languages used variations of the term &quot;Indian&quot; to describe the peoples of the Indian subcontinent.&lt;ref name=WORDMYTHS/&gt;

As European colonists began to move into the Americas in the 17th and 18th centuries, and have more sustained contact with the resident peoples, it became clear that the residents were not a homogenous group sharing a unified culture and government, but discrete societies with their own distinct languages and social systems. Early historical accounts show that some colonists attempted to learn and record the autonyms of these individual groups, but the use of the general term &quot;Indian&quot; persisted.

In 1968, the [[American Indian Movement]] was founded. In 1977, a delegation from the [[International Indian Treaty Council]], an arm of AIM, elected to collectively identify as &quot;American Indian,&quot; at the [[United Nations]] [[Conference on Indians in the Americas]] at Geneva, Switzerland. Some activists and public figures of indigenous descent, such as [[Russell Means]], say that they prefer &quot;American Indian&quot; to the more recently adopted &quot;Native American.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|publisher=PBS|accessdate=2007-10-17|title=&quot;American Indian&quot; or &quot;Native American&quot;: Which Is Correct?|author=Dennis Gaffney|year=2006|url=http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/roadshow/series/highlights/2006/bismarck/fts_hour3_4.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Indian Eristic|date=January 5, 2007|accessdate=2007-10-17|publisher=Wisconsin Office of State Employment Relations|url=http://oser.state.wi.us/pgsub_detail.asp?linksubcat2id=639&amp;linksubcatid=1023&amp;linkcatid=352&amp;linkid=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Objections to the usage of &quot;Indian&quot; and &quot;American Indian&quot; include the fact that &quot;Indian&quot; arose from an historical error, and thus does not accurately reflect the derivation of the people to whom it refers; and some feel that the term has absorbed negative and demeaning connotations through its historical usage that render it objectionable in context. Additionally, &quot;American Indian&quot; is often understood to mean only the peoples of the main body of the United States, which excludes other indigenous groups of the Americas, including the [[Inuit]], [[Cup'ik]]/[[Yup'ik]] peoples, [[Iñupiat]], [[Alutiiq]], and [[Aleut people]]s (i. e., the groups whose traditional languages are [[Eskimo–Aleut languages]]).

Supporters of the terms &quot;Indian&quot; and &quot;American Indian&quot; argue that they have been in use for such a long period of time that many people have become accustomed to them and no longer consider them exonyms. Both terms are still widely used today. &quot;American Indian&quot; appears often in treaties between the United States and the indigenous peoples with whom they have been negotiating since the colonial period, and many [[United States federal law|federal]], state and local laws also use it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=American Indian vs. Native American: A note on terminology|url=http://www.learnnc.org/lp/editions/nc-american-indians/5526|accessdate=31 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===&quot;Native American&quot;===

The [[Oxford English Dictionary]] cites usage of the uncapitalized term &quot;native American&quot; in several publications reaching as far back as 1737,&lt;ref name=&quot;Oxford English Dictionary&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Oxford English Dictionary|publisher=Oxford University Press, 2011|accessdate=31 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; but it is unclear whether these texts refer to indigenous peoples or simply to persons born on American soil. During the 1850s, a group of [[Anglo-Saxon]] [[Protestant]] European-Americans used the capitalized term &quot;Native Americans&quot; to differentiate themselves from more recent [[Catholic]] [[Irish people|Irish]] and [[Germans|German]] immigrants. The group later formed the &quot;[[Know-Nothings]],&quot; a 19th-century political party that supported anti-[[immigrant]] policy in the United States.  The Know-Nothings also called themselves the &quot;Native American Party&quot; and were referred to in the press with the capitalized term.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Oxford English Dictionary|url=Oxford University Press, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; They hired the writer and orator George Copway (a member of the Ontario [[Ojibwa]] tribe) for some of their publications,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=ed|first=Paul Lauter, general|title=The Heath anthology of American literature|year=1994|publisher=Heath|location=Lexington, Mass. [u.a.]|isbn=0-669-32972-X|pages=1482–1483|edition=2. ed., 1. [Dr.]}}&lt;/ref&gt; but it is unclear whether they intended their usage of &quot;Native American&quot; to include indigenous peoples.

In 1918, leaders of the [[Native_American_Church#History_of_the_peyote_religion|Peyote Religion]] in Oklahoma incorporated as the [[Native American Church]] of Oklahoma.&lt;ref name=&quot;weston&quot;&gt;Weston La Barre, ''The Peyote Cult'', (Yale University Press, 1938, 5th ed. 1989), p. 169&lt;/ref&gt; In 1956, [[Aldous Huxley]] wrote a letter in which he thanks his correspondent for &quot;your most interesting letter about the Native American churchmen&quot; (note capitalization).&lt;ref name=&quot;Oxford English Dictionary&quot;/&gt;

The use of both &quot;native American&quot; and &quot;Native American&quot; to refer to the indigenous peoples of the Americas came into widespread common use during the [[civil rights movement]]s of the 1960s and 1970s. Activists believed that it more accurately represented historical fact (i.e., indigenous populations predated European colonization), and that it was free of negative historical connotations that had come to be associated with previous terms.

Between 1982 and 1993, most American manuals of style came to agree that &quot;color terms&quot; referring to ethnic groups should be capitalized as proper names, including &quot;Native American.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Wachal|first=Robert S.|title=The Capitalization of Black and Native American|journal=American Speech|date=Winter|year=2000|volume=75| issue =  4|pages=364–365}}&lt;/ref&gt; Critics argue that the [[typography|typographical]] detail of capitalizing &quot;native&quot; to differentiate between the term's use for indigeous peoples and other meanings is easily overlooked in written grammar, and ineffective in speech.

Other objections to &quot;Native American,&quot; whether capitalized or not, include a concern that it is often understood to exclude American groups outside the continental U.S. (i.e., Alaska, Hawaii, Puerto Rico), and indigenous groups in South America, Mexico and Canada. The word &quot;American&quot; is sometimes questioned because the peoples referred to resided in the Americas before they were so named, rendering the term a [[tautology (rhetoric)|tautology]].

As of 1995, according to the [[US Census Bureau]], 50% of people who identified as indigenous preferred the term &quot;American Indian,&quot; 37% preferred &quot;Native American&quot; and the remainder preferred other terms or had no preference.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Clyde Tucker, Brian Kojetin, and Roderick Harrison|title=A statistical analysis of the CPS supplement on race and ethnic origin|publisher=Bureau of Labor Statistics, Bureau of the Census|month=May | year=1995|accessdate=2007-10-18|url=http://www.census.gov/prod/2/gen/96arc/ivatuck.pdf|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===&quot;Indigenous&quot;===
The word &quot;indigenous&quot; comes from the [[Latin]] ''indigena'', meaning &quot;native,&quot; formed from ''indu'' &quot;in&quot; and ''gen-'' &quot;beget.&quot; It is unrelated to the formation of &quot;Indian.&quot;

According to The American Heritage Dictionary, &quot;indigenous specifies that something or someone is native rather than coming or being brought in from elsewhere: an indigenous crop; the [[Ainu people|Ainu]], a people indigenous to the northernmost islands of Japan.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language,'' Fourth Edition. Houghton Mifflin Company, 2004. http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/native (accessed: November 18, 2007).&lt;/ref&gt;

The United Nations World Summit on Sustainable Development used the term &quot;indigenous peoples&quot; for the first time in its official political declaration in 2002. Prior to this date, the terms was considered to be &quot;still under debate&quot; for usage in official UN documents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Deer|first=Kenneth|title=International Indian Treaty Council Press Release|url=http://www.treatycouncil.org/new_page_5242122.htm|accessdate=1 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Arguments against the use of the term &quot;Indigenous Peoples&quot; are that it does not refer specifically to peoples affected by European colonization during the 17th and 18th centuries, that it lumps all indigenous world groups into a single &quot;[[othering|other]],&quot; and that it fails to recognize migratory groups who do not technically meet the definition of &quot;indigenous.&quot;{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}}

===&quot;Aboriginal&quot; and &quot;Aborigine&quot;===
The English adjective &quot;aboriginal&quot; and the noun &quot;aborigine&quot; come from a Latin phrase meaning &quot;from the origin;&quot; the [[Ancient Rome|ancient Romans]] used it to refer to the native peoples of central [[Italy]] who were their contemporaries. Today throughout most of the English-speaking world, it is most commonly understood to refer to the [[Indigenous Australians]].

===&quot;Alaska Native&quot;===
&quot;[[Alaska Native]]&quot; refers to the indigenous peoples in [[Alaska]], including the [[Aleut]], Inuit, and [[Yupik peoples|Yupik]] peoples.

In [[Alaska]], the term &quot;Alaska Native&quot; predominates, because of its legal use in the Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act ([[ANCSA]]) and because it includes the Aleut, Inuit and Yupik peoples, the three groups of indigenous Alaskan peoples.

European Americans once used the term &quot;[[Eskimo]]&quot; for those groups, but this term is in disfavor because the people consider it derogatory; it was adopted from the exonym ''Eskimo'' used by the competing Algonquian-speaking tribes of the northern tier. The Inuit are &quot;a people inhabiting the Arctic (northern Canada or Greenland or Alaska or eastern Siberia); the Algonquian called them Eskimo ('eaters of raw flesh') but they call themselves the Inuit ('the people') [syn: {Esquimau}, {Eskimo}].&quot;&lt;ref name=Miller_WordNet&gt;{{cite book|url=http://wordnetweb.princeton.edu/perl/webwn?s=Eskimo |author=George A. Miller |month=August | year=2003|title=WordNet (r) 2.0|publisher=Princeton University|accessdate=2006-04-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===&quot;Amerind&quot;===
{{Main|Amerind (people)}}
The term &quot;Amerind&quot; is a blended form of &quot;American Indian,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;url=http://query.nytimes.com/mem/archive-free/pdf?_r=2&amp;res=9901EEDD1E3DEE32A25751C2A9669D946397D6CF|title=Americanists in dispute|date=October 22, 1902|publisher=The New York Times|accessdate=2009-01-14 | format=PDF&lt;/ref&gt; though it can also be parsed as a blend of &quot;American&quot; and &quot;Indigenous.&quot; It was coined in 1902 by the [[American Anthropological Association]] and is more commonly used in [[Latin America]].

==Canada==
===&quot;Aboriginal peoples&quot;===
In Canada, the term &quot;[[Aboriginal peoples in Canada]]&quot; is used for all indigenous peoples within the country, including the [[Inuit]] and [[First Nations]], as well as the [[Métis people (Canada)|Métis]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Mandel, Michael 1994 pp. 354-356&quot;&gt;Mandel, Michael. ''The Charter of Rights and the Legalization of Politics in Canada'', Revised edition. (Toronto: Thompson Educational Publishing, Inc., 1994), pp. 354-356&lt;/ref&gt;

===&quot;First Nations&quot;===

&quot;[[First Nations]]&quot; (most often used in the plural) has come into general use for the [[Indigenous peoples]] of [[North America]] located in what is now Canada, and their descendants, excluding the [[Inuit]] and [[Métis people (Canada)|Métis]], who have distinct identities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rights&quot;&gt;(R.S., 1985, c. I-5 )[[Canada|Canadian]] [[Constitution Act, 1982]], [[Section Twenty-five of the Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms|sections 25]] and [[Section Thirty-five of the Constitution Act, 1982|35]].&lt;/ref&gt; The singular commonly used is &quot;First Nations person&quot; (when gender-specific, &quot;First Nations man&quot; or &quot;First Nations woman&quot;).

Some tribal governments of Canada also use the term &quot;First Nations&quot; to refer to any indigenous, tribal or nomadic society, using the term for such diverse groups as the [[Roma (Romani subgroup)|Roma]], [[Sinti]], [[Sami people|Saami]], [[Māori people|Māori]], [[Hmong people|Hmong]], and the Australian Aborigines.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rights&quot; /&gt;

Although the Canadian government has formally adopted use of the term &quot;[[First Nations]]&quot; and &quot;Aboriginal peoples,&quot; the federal ministerial portfolio in charge of their affairs is named the [[Department of Indian and Northern Affairs]], and the historical term &quot;[[Indian Reserve]]&quot; is still a legal land description. Some First Nations peoples also use &quot;Indian Band&quot; in their official names.

===&quot;Canadian Indians&quot;===
The Canadian [[Indian Act (Canada)|Indian Act]], in defining the rights of people of recognized First Nations, refers to them as &quot;Indians.&quot; The responsible federal government department was the [[Department of Indian and Northern Affairs]], now the Department of Aboriginal Affairs and Northern Development, headed by the [[Minister of Indian Affairs and Northern Development]]. The act officially recognizes people commonly known as &quot;Status Indians,&quot; although &quot;Registered Indian&quot; is the official term for those on the [[Indian Register (Canada)|Indian Register]]. Lands set aside for the use of First Nations are known as [[Indian Reserve]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mandel, Michael 1994 pp. 354-356&quot;/&gt;

===&quot;Native Canadians&quot;===
&quot;Native&quot; or &quot;Native Canadian&quot; is an ambiguous term, but people frequently use it in conversation or informal writing. A great majority use this term for describing aboriginal peoples. Including aboriginal people themselves.

===&quot;First Peoples&quot;===
&quot;First Peoples&quot; is a broad term that includes First Nations, Inuit, Inuvialuit, and Métis (equivalent to &quot;Aboriginal&quot; or &quot;indigenous&quot; peoples)—and could be extended outside the Canadian context to comprise all descendents of pre-Columbian ethnic groups in the Americas, including (self-identified) ethnic groups whose ancestry is only partially of pre-Columbian groups (e.g. [[Mestizo]]).  Due to its similarity with the term &quot;First Nations,&quot; the two terms are sometimes used interchangeably.

===&quot;Anishinaabe&quot;===
The [[Algonquin language|Algonquin]] [[Ethnonym|autonym]], ''[[Anishinaabe]]'' or ''Anishinabe'', is used as a cross-tribal term in Algonquian-majority areas, such as Anishnabe Health and Anishnabe Education and Training Circle.  The term is also used among historically Anishinaabe peoples in the [[Upper Midwest]] region of the United States.

=== Canadian French nomenclature ===
In [[Canadian French]], the terms are ''première(s) nation(s)'' for &quot;First Nations&quot; and ''autochtone'' for &quot;Aboriginal&quot; (used both as a noun and adjective).

The term ''indien'' or ''indienne'' is used in the legislation, although the preferred term is now ''amérindien''. The term ''indigène'' is not used as it is seen as having negative connotations because of its similarity to the French equivalent of ''indigent'' (&quot;poor&quot;). The old French term ''sauvage'' (&quot;wild&quot;) is no longer used either, as it is considered racist.

=== Chinook Jargon nomenclature ===
The [[Chinook Jargon]], the old trade language of the Pacific Northwest, uses ''siwash'' (an adaptation of the French ''sauvage'') for &quot;Indian,&quot; &quot;Native American,&quot; or &quot;First Nations,&quot; either as adjective or noun. While normally meaning a male native, it is used in certain combinations, like ''siwash cosho'' (&quot;a seal,&quot; literally &quot;Indian pig&quot; or &quot;Indian pork&quot;).

Many native communities perceive the terms ''sauvage'' and ''siwash'' negatively, but others use it freely.  They consider use by non-natives to be derogatory. placenames and certain other usages. In the creolized form of Chinook Jargon spoken at the Grand Ronde Agency in Oregon, a distinction is made between ''siwash'' and ''sawash''. The accent in the latter is on the second syllable, resembling the French original, and is used in Grand Ronde Jargon meaning &quot;anything native or Indian&quot;.  By contrast, they consider ''siwash'' to be defamatory.{{citation needed|date=July 2011}}

The Chinook Jargon term for a native woman is ''klootchman'', an originally [[Nuu-chah-nulth language|Nootka]] word which was adopted in regional English to mean a native woman, or (as in the Jargon), all women and also anything female. It originated as a compound of Nootka ''łūts'' 'female' with the English suffix ''-man''. ''Hyas klootchman tyee'' means &quot;queen&quot;, ''klootchman cosho'', &quot;sow&quot;; ''klootchman tenas'' or ''tenas klootchman'' means &quot;girl&quot; or &quot;little girl&quot;.  Generally ''klootchman'' in regional English simply means a native woman and has not  acquired the derisive sense of ''siwash'' or ''squaw''.  The short form ''klootch'', encountered only in English-Chinook hybrid phrasings, is often derisive.

== Latin America ==
In [[Mexico]], the preferred expression is &quot;Indigenous Peoples&quot; (''pueblos indígenas'' in [[Spanish language|Spanish]]. ''Indios'' is still in common use, including among the indigenous peoples.

In [[Mexico]], [[Brazil]], and several other countries, these names are normally applied only to the ethnic groups that have maintained their identity and, to a some extent, their original way of life. In those countries there is also a large segment of the population with mixed native and European ancestry, who are largely integrated in mainstream society, and no longer identify themselves with their ancestral native groups. In some Spanish speaking countries, there are also [[Ladino people|Ladinos]] who do not have significant European ancestry, but have adopted the culture of the White and Mestizo population.

These people were originally called ''[[mestizo]]s'' in Mexico, ''caboclos'' in Brazil; however, those terms have largely fallen in disuse as that segment has come to predominate among the population.

In [[South America]], the preferred expression is ''Indigenous Peoples'' (''pueblos indígenas'' in [[Spanish language|Spanish]], ''povos indígenas'' in [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]]). However, ''Indians'' (''indios'', ''índios'') is often used too, even by indigenous peoples themselves, since this expression is not seen as derogatory.{{Citation needed|date=August 2008}} It should also be noted that in Portuguese ''índios'' does not conflict with the word for the people of India (''indianos'').

==International==
===&quot;Indigenous peoples&quot;===
During the late 20th century the term &quot;Indigenous peoples&quot; evolved into a political term that refers to ethnic groups with historical ties to groups that existed in a territory prior to [[colonization]] or formation of a [[nation state]]. In the Americas, the term &quot;Indigenous peoples of the Americas&quot; was adopted, and the term is tailored to specific geographic or political regions, such as &quot;[[Indigenous peoples of Panama]].&quot;  &quot;'Indigenous peoples' ... is a term that internationalizes the experiences, the issues and the struggles of some of the world's colonized peoples,&quot; writes [[Māori people|Maori]] educator [[Linda Tuhiwai Smith]]. &quot;The final 's' in 'indigenous peoples' ... [is] a way of recognizing that there are real differences between different indigenous peoples.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Smith 7&lt;/ref&gt;

==Obsolete and/or unacceptable terminology==
=== &quot;Redskin&quot;/&quot;Red Indian&quot; ===
Some Europeans called Native Americans [[redskin (slang)|redskin]]s; it was one of the [[Color terminology for race|color metaphors for race]] which colonists and settlers historically used in North America and Europe.  It is similar to the expressions &quot;pale face&quot; or &quot;pale skin&quot;, which some Native Americans used for Europeans.  Such terms are often considered pejorative.  Different individuals may hold differing opinions of the term's appropriateness. There is an [[American football]] team named the [[Washington Redskins]], and the Redskins serve as the mascot of Red Mesa High School on the [[Navajo Reservation]] in [[Teec Nos Pos]], [[Arizona]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.aiaonline.org/schools/school.php?id=142&lt;/ref&gt;

The term's use was not restricted to the United States or North America.  The English-speaking world and Europeans, in [[loan-translation]]s, used redskin and the similar term &quot;red Indian&quot; throughout the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries to refer to indigenous Americans.  For example, the French translation ''peaux-rouges'' was used by [[Arthur Rimbaud]] in ''[[Le Bateau ivre]]'' and [[Jean Raspail]] in several of his travelogues.

=== &quot;Savage&quot; ===
{{See also|Noble savage}}
[[anthropology|Anthropologists]] once used ''savage'' as a blanket word to refer to indigenous peoples worldwide (e.g. [[Bronisław Malinowski]] titled his 1929 study ''The Sexual Life of Savages'').  At the beginning of the nineteenth century, representatives of the relatively new United States government often used the term in official records when referring to Indian nations (see, e.g., Justice Baldwin's concurring opinion in ''[[Cherokee Nation v. Georgia]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Cherokee Nation v. Georgia|publisher=United States Supreme Court|url=http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?court=US&amp;vol=30&amp;invol=1|year=1831}}&lt;/ref&gt;). This was related to their association of non-Christian people as savages.

=== Other ===
European [[Christians]] once broadly used the word &quot;heathens&quot; to refer to Native Americans, a pejorative term related to their perceived lack of religious beliefs (because they were not Christian).

Today, &quot;Injun&quot; is an intentional-mispronunciation of &quot;Indian&quot;, generally used in a joking way to mock or impersonate Native Americans' or early settlers' supposed heavily-accented English (e.g. &quot;Honest Injun&quot;, &quot;Injun time&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Kagen apologizes for remark Congressional candidate says use of 'Injun time' wasn't meant to offend|publisher=Milwaukee Journal-Sentinel|author=Steve Schultze|date=October 23, 2006|url=http://www.jsonline.com/story/index.aspx?id=522021|accessdate=2007-10-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; The word and related terms have been defined as derogatory by indigenous people and are not widely used.

Some Native Americans consider the word &quot;[[squaw]]&quot; offensive, derogatory, or racist, although there is some controversy on the topic.&lt;ref&gt;[http://mytwobeadsworth.com/S-word106.html The Sociolinguistics of the 'S- Word': 'Squaw' in American Placenames], by [[William Bright]]&lt;/ref&gt;
Similarly, the term &quot;Indian princess&quot; is considered demeaning to Native American women. The Indian princess stereotype is in some ways the opposite of the squaw stereotype. However, this should not be confused with the practice of tribes, [[powwow]] organizations, colleges, and other indigenous groups choosing young women with exceptional knowledge of their cultures to represent the groups as tribal &quot;princesses.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.americaslibrary.gov/es/ok/es_ok_parade_1.html &quot;The American Indian Exposition in Anadarko, Oklahoma.&quot;] ''America's Story.'' (retrieved 1 Aug 2011)&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|Indigenous peoples of North America}}
* [[Abya Yala]], a proposed native (from the [[Panama]] [[Kuna (people)|Kuna]]s) name for the Americas, avoiding the mention of [[Amerigo Vespucci]] or [[Richard Amerike]].
* [[Eskimo#Origin of the name Eskimo|Origin of the name Eskimo]]
* [[Lamanite]]
* [[Squaw]]

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== References ==
* {{cite web
 |last=Means
 |first=Russell
 |coauthors=
 |date=1996 (c), last update 2000-12-16
 |month=
 |url=http://www.peaknet.net/~aardvark/means.html
 |title=I am an American Indian, Not a Native American!
 |work=
 |publisher=[http://www.peaknet.net/~aardvark/index2.html Jim Hickinbotham (Rabid Wolf, Choctaw)]
 |accessdate=not recorded
}}
*[[Smith, Linda Tuhiwai]]. ''Decolonizing Methodologies: Research and Indigenous Peoples.'' London: Zed Books, 1999. ISBN 978-1-85649-624-7.

==Further reading==
* {{cite book |last= |first= |authorlink= |coauthors= |editor= |year=2000 |title=The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language |accessdate=2006-08-06 |publisher=Houghton Mifflin |location=Boston |isbn=0-395-82517-2 (hardcover), ISBN 0-618-08230-1hardcover with CD ROM) |pages= |chapter=}}  &lt;br /&gt;Fourth Edition
* {{cite web
 |last=Brunner
 |first=Borgna
 |coauthors=
 |date=
 |year=2006
 |month=
 |url=http://www.infoplease.com/spot/aihmterms.html
 |title=American Indian versus Native American: A once-heated issue has sorted itself out
 |work=
 |publisher=
 |accessdate=not recorded
}}  &lt;br /&gt;Includes sources (including quotes Russel Means at [http://www.peaknet.net/~aardvark/means.html &quot;I am an American Indian, Not a Native American!&quot;] and Christina Berry at [http://www.allthingscherokee.com/atc_sub_culture_feat_events_070101.html &quot;What's in a Name? Indians and Political Correctness&quot;], also referenced on this page).
* {{cite book |last=Carlin |first=George |authorlink= |coauthors= |editor= |year=1997 |title=Brain droppings |accessdate= |publisher=Hyperion |location=New York |isbn=0-7868-6313-7 |pages= |chapter=}}
* {{cite web |last=Dailey |first=Tom |date=2006-06-14 |year= |month= |url=http://coastsalishmap.org/new_page_6.htm |title=Duwamish-Seattle |work=[http://coastsalishmap.org/start_page.htm &quot;Coast Salish Villages of Puget Sound&quot;] |publisher= |accessdate=2006-04-21}}  &lt;br /&gt;[http://coastsalishmap.org/Village_Descriptions_Duwamish-Seattle.htm Village Descriptions--Duwamish-Seattle.  &lt;br /&gt;Dailey referenced &quot;Puget Sound Geography&quot; by T. T. Waterman.  Washington DC:  National Anthropological Archives, mss. [n.d.] [ref. 2]; &lt;br /&gt;''Duwamish et al. vs. United States of America, F-275''.  Washington DC: US Court of Claims, 1927. [ref. 5]; &lt;br /&gt;&quot;Indian Lake Washington&quot; by David Buerge in the ''Seattle Weekly'', 1–7 August 1984 [ref. 8]; &lt;br /&gt;&quot;Seattle Before Seattle&quot; by David Buerge in the ''Seattle Weekly'', 17–23 December 1980. [ref. 9]; &lt;br /&gt;''The Puyallup-Nisqually'' by Marian W. Smith.  New York: Columbia University Press, 1940. [ref. 10].  &lt;br /&gt;Recommended start is &quot;[http://coastsalishmap.org/start_page.htm Coast Salish Villages of Puget Sound]&quot;.
* {{cite news
 |first=Peter
 |last=d'Errico
 |author=
 |coauthors=
 |url=http://www.indiancountry.com/content.cfm?id=1096412113
 |title=An interview with Charles C. Mann
 |work=
 |publisher=Indian Country Today
 |pages=
 |page=
 |date=2005-12-20
 |accessdate=2006-08-06
|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20060510204428/http://www.indiancountry.com/content.cfm?id=1096412113 &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2006-05-10}}  &lt;br /&gt;Part 1 and [http://www.indiancountry.com/content.cfm?id=1096412156 Part 2 of 2]
* {{cite web
 |last=d'Errico
 |first=Peter, Legal Studies Department, [[University of Massachusetts Amherst]]
 |coauthors=
 |date=2005-07-11
 |year=
 |month=
 |url=http://www.umass.edu/legal/derrico/name.html
 |title=Native American Indian Studies - A Note on Names
 |work=
 |publisher=[[University of Massachusetts Amherst]]
 |accessdate=2006-08-06
}}  &lt;br /&gt;Provides references.
* Dyck, Michael (ed.) (16 June 2002). [http://www.ibiblio.org/webster/ ibiblio - Open and Free Resources], the GNU version of ''The Collaborative International Dictionary of English'', presented in the Extensible Markup Language. Based on GCIDE version 0.46 (15 April 2002). Retrieved 21 April 2006.
* {{cite web
 |last=George; staff report, ''Straight Dope Science Advisory Board''
 |first=
 |coauthors=
 |date=2001-10-25
 |year=
 |month=
 |url=http://www.straightdope.com/mailbag/mgenteindios.html
 |title=Does 'Indian' derive from Columbus's description of Native Americans as ''una gente in Dios''?
 |work=
 |publisher=Chicago Reader, Inc.
 |accessdate=2006-04-21
}}
* {{cite book
 |last=Mann
 |first=Charles C.
 |authorlink=
 |coauthors=
 |editor=
 |year=2005
 |title=1491: New Revelations of the Americas before Columbus
 |accessdate=2006-08-06
 |publisher=Knopf
 |location=New York
 |isbn=1-4000-4006-X (alk. paper)
 |pages=
 |chapter=
}}
* {{cite web |last=Talbert |first=Paul |coauthors= |date=2006-05-01 |year= |month= |url=http://www.sewardpark.org/sewardpark/history.html |title='SkEba'kst': The Lake People and Seward Park |work=The History of Seward Park |publisher=SewardPark.org |accessdate=2006-06-06 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20051214035236/http://www.sewardpark.org/sewardpark/history.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2005-12-14}}
{{Refend}}

== External links ==
*[http://www.nativeweb.org/pages/legal/shoshone/indian.html &quot;American Indians - Native Americans: A Note on Terminology&quot;], Peter d'Errico (22 August 2002), NativeWeb.org. Condensed version of d'Errico (2005)
*[http://www.umass.edu/legal/derrico/name.html &quot;Native American Indian Studies - A Note on Names&quot;], Peter d'Errico (11 July 2005), Legal Studies Department, [[University of Massachusetts Amherst]]
*[http://www.allthingscherokee.com/atc_sub_culture_feat_events_070101.html &quot;What's in a Name? Indians and Political Correctness&quot;], by Christina Berry, All Things Cherokee

{{Indigenous peoples of the Americas}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Native American Name Controversy}}
[[Category:Indigenous peoples of the Americas]]
[[Category:Indigenous peoples of North America]]
[[Category:Native American topics]]
[[Category:First Nations culture]]
[[Category:Naming controversies]]
[[Category:Political correctness]]</text>
      <sha1>n8m4pab9l3n7zlzwpotl116ddt6h4hc</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
