<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Pioneer Fund</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>771182</id>
    <revision>
      <id>516492679</id>
      <parentid>516492260</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-07T15:51:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>WadeAllsopp</username>
        <id>469036</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Early history */  Account for rushton's death</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="33504">{{distinguish2|The Pioneer Fund, a Denver-based charity founded by [[Helen M. McLoraine]]}}

The '''Pioneer Fund''' is an American [[non-profit organization|non-profit foundation]] established in 1937 &quot;to advance the scientific study of heredity and human differences.&quot; Until his death on 2 October 2012, the fund was headed by psychology professor [[J. Philippe Rushton]], the fund states that it focuses on projects it perceives will not be easily funded due to controversial subject matter. The organization is frequently described as racist and &quot;white supremacist&quot; in nature,&lt;ref&gt;Avner Falk. Anti-semitism: a history and psychoanalysis of contemporary hatred. Abc-Clio, 2008, pg. 18&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;William H. Tucker, The funding of scientific racism: Wickliffe Draper and the Pioneer Fund. University of Illinois Press, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Andrew Wroe. The Republican party and immigration politics: from Proposition 187 to George W. Bush. University of Illinois Press, 2008, pg. 81&lt;/ref&gt; or as a &quot;[[hate group]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;splcmap&quot;&gt;Southern Poverty Law Center [http://www.splcenter.org/get-informed/intelligence-files/ideology/white-nationalist/active_hate_groups White Nationalist] Retrieved July 16, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

Two of the most notable studies funded by the Pioneer Fund are the [[Minnesota Twin Family Study#The Minnesota Study of Twins Reared Apart|Minnesota Study of Twins Reared Apart]] and the Texas Adoption Project, which studied the similarities and differences of [[identical twins]] and other children adopted into non-biological families.   The Pioneer Fund has also been an important source of funding for research on the partly genetic hypothesis of [[race and intelligence|IQ variation among races]].

The fund's grantees and publications have [[race and intelligence controversy|generated controversy]] including the 1994 publication of ''[[The Bell Curve]]'', which drew heavily from Pioneer-funded research. The fund has also been criticized for its ties to [[eugenics]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Lombardo, Paul A. |title=&quot;The American Breed&quot;: Nazi eugenics and the origins of the Pioneer Fund |journal=Albany Law Rev |volume=65 |issue=3 |pages=743–830 |year=2002 |pmid=11998853 }}&lt;br/&gt;{{cite journal |author=Rushton, J. Philippe |title=The Pioneer Fund and the Scientific Study of Human Differences |journal=Albany Law Rev |volume=66 |pages=209 |year=2002 }}&lt;br/&gt;{{cite journal |author=Lombardo, Paul A. |title=Pioneer's Big Lie |journal=Albany Law Rev |volume=66 |pages=1125 |year=2002 }}&lt;br/&gt;{{cite journal |author=Tucker, William H. |title=A Closer Look at the Pioneer Fund: Response to Rushton |journal=Albany Law Rev |volume=66 |pages=1145 |year=2002 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  

==Early history==
{{See also|History of the race and intelligence controversy}}
The Pioneer Fund was incorporated on March 11, 1937. The first five directors were:
*[[Wickliffe Preston Draper]], heir to a large fortune and the fund's de facto final authority, served on the Board of Directors from 1937 until 1972.  He founded the Pioneer Fund after having acquired an interest in the Eugenics movement, which was strengthened by his 1935 visit to Nazi Germany, where he met with the leading eugenicists of the Third Reich who used the inspiration from the American movement as a basis for the [[Nuremberg Laws]]. He served in the British army at the beginning of WWI, transferring to the US Army as the Americans entered the war. During WWII he was stationed as an intelligence officer in India.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Lombardo Paul A | year = | title = &quot;The American Breed&quot;: Nazi Eugenics and the Origins of the Pioneer Fund | url = | journal = Albany Law Review | volume = 65 | issue = 3| pages = 743–830 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Psychology professor and Pioneer Fund critic [[William H. Tucker]], however, describes Draper as someone who &quot;aside from his brief periods of military service&amp;nbsp;... never pursued a profession or held a job of any kind.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Tucker&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Tucker, William H |title=The Funding of Scientific Racism: Wickliffe Draper and the Pioneer Fund |publisher=University of Illinois Press |year=2002 |isbn=0-252-02762-0 |url=http://www.press.uillinois.edu/epub/books/tucker/toc.html }}&lt;/ref&gt; According to a 1960 article in ''[[The Nation]]'', an unnamed geneticist said Draper told him he &quot;wished to prove simply that Negroes were inferior.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;May&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=May, R.W. |title=Genetics and Subversion |journal=[[The Nation]] |volume=190 |pages=421 |date=May 14, 1960 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Draper funded advocacy of repatriation of blacks to Africa.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = J.P. | first = Jackson, | title = Science for segregation: race, law, and the case against Brown v. Board of Education | publisher = New York University Press | location = City | year = 2005 | isbn = 0-8147-4271-8 }page=34}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = T. | first = Hashaw, | title = Children of Perdition: Melungeons and the Struggle of Mixed America | publisher = Mercer University Press | location = City | year = 2007 | isbn = 0-88146-074-5 |page=158}}&lt;/ref&gt; Draper also made large financial contributions to efforts to oppose the [[American Civil Rights Movement (1955–1968)|American civil rights movement]] and the racial [[desegregation]] mandated by ''[[Brown v. Board of Education]],'' such as $215,000 to the [[Mississippi State Sovereignty Commission]] in 1963.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tucker&quot; /&gt;
*[[Harry Laughlin]] was the director of the [[Eugenics Record Office]] at the Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory on Long Island, New York, funded by the Carnegie Institute of Washington. He served as the president of the Pioneer Fund from its inception until 1941. He was one of the eugenics movement's most energetic legislative activists. He worried about [[miscegenation]] and had proposed a research agenda to assist in the enforcement of Southern &quot;race integrity laws&quot; by developing techniques for identifying the &quot;pass-for-white&quot; person who might &quot;successfully hide all of his black blood&quot;. He singled out Jews as a group &quot;slow to assimilate,&quot; a problem related to his doubts that their loyalty was directed primarily to &quot;American institutions and people&quot; rather than to &quot;Jews scattered through other nations.&quot; Eleven months after the [[Nuremberg Laws]], Laughlin wrote to an official at the University of Heidelberg, which had awarded him an honorary doctorate, arguing that the United States and the [[Third Reich]] shared &quot;a common understanding of&amp;nbsp;... the practical application&quot; of eugenic principles to &quot;racial endowments and&amp;nbsp;... racial health.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Tucker&quot; /&gt;
*[[Frederick Osborn]] wrote in 1937 that the Nazi [[Law for the Prevention of Hereditarily Diseased Offspring]] was &quot;the most exciting experiment that had ever been tried&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Osborn-sterilize&quot;&gt;Osborn, Frederick (24 February 1937). 'Summary of the proceedings' of the Conference on Eugenics in Relation to Nursing. American Eugenics Society Archives.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mehler-fascism&quot;/&gt; Osborn was the secretary of the [[American Eugenics Society]], which was part of an accepted and active field at the time, the Chairman of the Advisory Committee on Selective Service during [[World War II]] and later the Deputy U.S. Representative to the [[United Nations Atomic Energy Commission|U.N. Atomic Energy Commission]].
*[[Malcolm Donald]] was the Draper family lawyer, trustee of the Draper estate. He was a former editor of the ''[[Harvard Law Review]]'' and a [[brigadier general]] during World War II.
*[[John Marshall Harlan II]]. Harlan's firm had done legal work for the Pioneer Fund. He was the only director whose name did not appear on the incorporation papers. He was director of operational analysis for the [[Eighth Air Force]] in World War II, and was appointed to the [[Supreme Court of the United States]] by President [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]]. During his confirmation process, he voiced support for the decision in ''[[Brown v. Board of Education]]'', but on the bench limited civil rights in ''[[Swain v. Alabama]]'' and dissented on ''[[Miranda v. Arizona]]''.

The 1937 incorporation documents of the Pioneer Fund list two purposes. The first, modeled on the Nazi [[Lebensborn]] breeding program,&lt;ref name=&quot;crawford&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Crawford, James |title=Hold Your Tongue: Bilingualism and the Politics of &quot;English Only&quot; |publisher=Addison Wesley |year=1993 |isbn=978-0-201-62479-3 }}&lt;/ref&gt; was aimed at encouraging the propagation of those &quot;descended predominantly from white persons who settled in the original thirteen states prior to the adoption of the [[United States Constitution|Constitution of the United States]] and/or from related stocks, or to classes of children, the majority of whom are deemed to be so descended&quot;. Its second purpose was to support academic research and the &quot;dissemination of information, into the 'problem of heredity and eugenics{{'&quot;}} and &quot;the problems of race betterment&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mehler-fascism&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Mehler, Barry |title=Foundation for Fascism: the New Eugenics Movement in the United States |journal=Patterns of Prejudice |volume=23 |issue=4 |year=1989 |url=http://www.ferris.edu/ISAR/archives/mehler/foundation.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Pioneer Fund argues the &quot;race betterment&quot; has always referred to the &quot;human race&quot; referred to earlier in the sentence, and critics argue it referred to racial groups. The document was amended in 1985 and the phrase changed to &quot;human race betterment.&quot;

The Pioneer Fund supported the distribution of a eugenics film titled ''[[Erbkrank]]'' (&quot;Hereditary Defective&quot; or &quot;Hereditary Illness&quot;) which was published by the pre-war 1930s [[Nazi Party]]. William Draper obtained the film from the predecessor to the Nazi [[Office of Racial Policy]] (''Rassenpolitisches Amt'') prior to the founding of the Pioneer Fund.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tucker&quot; /&gt; According to the Pioneer Fund site, all founders capable of doing so participated in the war against the Nazis.&lt;ref name=&quot;pioneer-founders&quot;&gt;Pioneer Fund. [http://www.pioneerfund.org/Founders.html Founders and Former Directors.] Retrieved July 16, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

Draper secretly met Dr. C. Nash Herndon of Bowman Gray School of Medicine at [[Wake Forest University]] in 1949. Little is known about their meetings, but Herndon was playing a major role in the expansion of the [[compulsory sterilization]] program in [[North Carolina]].&lt;ref name=&quot;begos&quot;&gt;Begos, Kevin (December 11, 2002). [http://extras.journalnow.com/againsttheirwill/parts/two/storybody3.html Benefactor With a Racist Bent: Wealthy recluse apparently liked the looks and potential of Bowman Gray's new medical-genetics department.] ''[[Winston-Salem Journal]]''&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1950s and 1960s Draper supported two government committees that gave grants for both anti-immigration and genetics research. The committee members included Representative [[Francis E. Walter]] (chair of the [[House Un-American Activities Committee]] and head of the Draper Immigration Committee), [[Henry E. Garrett]] (an educator known for his belief in the genetic inferiority of blacks), and Senator [[James O. Eastland]] of Mississippi, head of the Draper Genetics Committee.&lt;ref name=&quot;lichtenstein&quot;&gt;Lichtenstein, Grace (December 11, 1977). Fund Backs Controversial Study of &quot;Racial Betterment.&quot; ''[[New York Times]]''&lt;/ref&gt;

Subsequent directors included:&lt;ref name=&quot;pioneer-founders&quot;/&gt;
*[[John M. Woolsey, Jr.]], a staff attorney at the [[Nuremberg Trials]]
*[[Henry E. Garrett]] (1972–1973), the former president of the [[American Psychological Association]]
*[[James P. Kranz, Jr.]] (1948)
*[[Henry Rice Guild]] (1948–1974)
*[[Charles Codman Cabot]] (1950–1973)
*[[Harry F. Weyher, Jr.]] (1958–2002)
*[[John B. Trevor, Jr.]] (1959–2000)
*[[John F. Walsh, Jr.]] (1971–1973)
*[[Marion A. Parrott]] (1973–2000)
*[[Thomas F. Ellis]] (1973–1977)
*[[Eugenie Mary Ladenburg Davie]] (Mrs. Preston) (1974–1975)
*[[Randolph L. Speight]] (1975–1999)
*[[William Dawes Miller]] (1983–1993)
*[[Karl Schakel]] (1993–2002)
*[[Edwin D. Morgan (businessman)|Edwin D. Morgan]] (2000–2001)
*[[R. Travis Osborne]] (2000–present)
*[[John Philippe Rushton]] (2002–2012)
*[[Michelle Weyher]] (2002–present)
*[[Richard Lynn]] (2002–present)

==Current funding==
Pioneer Fund's figures are from 1971 to 1996 and are adjusted to 1997 USD.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mehler-grantlist&quot;&gt;Mehler, Barry. [http://www.ferris.edu/ISAR/Institut/pioneer/pfspread/pfp6.htm Pioneer Fund Grant Totals, 1971-1996.] Retrieved July 16, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Scientific research===
{{Refimprove|date=August 2011}}
Many of the researchers whose findings support the [[hereditarianism|hereditarian]] hypothesis of [[Race and intelligence|racial IQ]] disparity have received grants of varying sizes from the Pioneer Fund.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mehler-funding&quot;&gt;Mehler, Barry (July 7, 1998). [http://www.ferris.edu/ISAR/Institut/pioneer/search.htm Race Science and the Pioneer Fund] Originally published as &quot;The Funding of the Science&quot; in ''Searchlight'', No. 277.&lt;/ref&gt; Large grantees, in order of amount received, are:
*[[Thomas J. Bouchard]] at the University of Minnesota. As compiled in 1997, the recipient of the largest amount of funding ($2.3 million USD) was [[Thomas J. Bouchard]]'s landmark [[twin study]], ''the Minnesota Study of Identical Twins Reared Apart'' (MISTRA), better known as the [[Minnesota Twins Project]].  The Minnesota Twins Project compared identical and fraternal twins who had been brought up in different families.
*[[Arthur Jensen]] at the Institute for the Study of Educational Differences.
*[[J. Philippe Rushton]] at the University of Western Ontario is the current head of the fund since 2002. In 1999, Rushton used some of his grant money from the Pioneer fund to send out tens of thousands of copies of an abridged version of his book ''[[Race, Evolution and Behavior]]'' to social scientists in anthropology, psychology, and sociology, causing a controversy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tucker-Conclusion&quot;&gt;Tucker, William H. [http://www.press.uillinois.edu/epub/books/tucker/concl.html Conclusion: Pioneer or Pamphleteer] ''The Funding of Scientific Racism: Wickliffe Draper and the Pioneer Fund''.&lt;/ref&gt;  Tax records from 2000 show that his Charles Darwin Institute received $473,835—73% of that year's grants.[http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?aid=83]
*[[Roger Pearson (anthropologist)|Roger Pearson]] at the Institute for the Study of Man. Eugenicist and anthropologist, founder of the ''[[Journal of Indo-European Studies]]'',&lt;ref name=&quot;jies&quot;&gt;[http://www.utexas.edu/cola/depts/lrc/iedocctr/jies.html The Journal of Indo-European Studies] via A. Richard Diebold Center for Indo-European Language and Culture.&lt;/ref&gt; received over a million dollars in grants in the eighties and the nineties.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tucker&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mehler-funding&quot;/&gt; Using the pseudonym of Stephan Langton, Pearson was the editor of ''The New Patriot'', a short-lived magazine published in 1966–67 to conduct &quot;a responsible but penetrating inquiry into every aspect of the [[Jewish Question]],&quot; which included articles such as &quot;Zionists and the Plot Against South Africa,&quot; &quot;Early Jews and the Rise of Jewish Money Power,&quot; and &quot;Swindlers of the Crematoria.&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mehler-funding&quot;/&gt; The [[Northern League (neo-Nazi)|Northern League]], an organization founded in England in 1958 by Pearson, supported Nazi ideologies and included former members of the Nazi Party.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tucker&quot; /&gt;
*[[Richard Lynn]] at Ulster Institute for Social Research (also on ''Mankind Quarterly'' editorial board)
*[[Linda Gottfredson]] at the University of Delaware.
Other notable recipients of funding include:
*[[Hans Eysenck]], the most-cited living psychologist at the time of his death (1997)
*[[Lloyd Humphreys]]
*[[Joseph M. Horn]]
*[[Robert A. Gordon]]
*[[Garrett Hardin]], author of the phrase the &quot;[[tragedy of the commons]]&quot;
*[[R. Travis Osborne]]
*[[Audrey M. Shuey]]
*[[Philip A. Vernon]]
*[[William Shockley]], winner of the [[Nobel prize]] in [[physics]] in 1956, received a series of grants in the 1970s. Shockley became famous in his later career for supporting the controversial genetic hypothesis of [[race and intelligence]] research and for being a proponent of [[eugenics]].

===Political and legal funding===
The Fund gave the [[Federation for American Immigration Reform]] (FAIR) a total of $1.3 million between 1985 and 1994.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Anti-Immigration Movement: From Shovels to Suits&quot; Solana Larsen. ''NACLA Report on the Americas''. New York: May/Jun 2007. Vol. 40, Iss. 3; p. 14, 5 pgs&lt;/ref&gt; Among the grants was $150,000 for 'studies in connection with immigration policies'.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lombardo&quot;&gt;Lombardo, P. [http://www.albanylawreview.org/archives/65/3/TheAmericanBreed-NaziEugenicsandtheOriginsofthePioneerFund.pdf &quot;THE AMERICAN BREED: NAZI EUGENICS AND THE ORIGINS OF THE PIONEER FUND&quot;] Retrieved May 21, 2008. ''Albany Law Review''&lt;/ref&gt; Funding was dropped after negative publicity during the campaign for California's [[California Proposition 187 (1994)|Proposition 187]] linked the Pioneer Fund to ads purchased by FAIR.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Pro-Prop. 187 group admits it bought ads POLITICS: FAIR says it only attempted to clear its name.&quot; MARILYN KALFUS: The Orange County Register. ''Orange County Register''. Santa Ana, Calif.: Oct 26, 1994. p. A.12&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;White Supremacist Link Trips Prop. 187&quot; Pamela Burdman, Chronicle Staff Writer. ''San Francisco Chronicle''. San Francisco, Calif.: Oct 13, 1994. p. A.4&lt;/ref&gt; Other [[immigration reduction]] groups that have received donations from the Pioneer Fund include [[ProjectUSA]], Californians for Population Stabilization,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Cannon critics sidestep FEC lists&quot; Deborah Bulkeley Deseret Morning News. ''Deseret News''. Salt Lake City, Utah: Jul 17, 2004. pg. B.01&lt;/ref&gt; and [[American Immigration Control Foundation]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;'Workers, go home!'&quot; David L Ostendorf. ''The Christian Century''. Chicago: Dec 19-Dec 26, 2001. Vol. 118, Iss. 35; pg. 8, 2 pgs&lt;/ref&gt;

A grantee is the [[paleoconservatism|paleoconservative]] and [[white nationalist]] journalist [[Jared Taylor]], the editor of ''[[American Renaissance (magazine)|American Renaissance]]'' and a member the advisory board of the white nationalist publication the ''[[Occidental Quarterly]]''. Another is Roger Pearson's Institute for the Study of Man.&lt;ref name=&quot;Berlet&quot;/&gt; Many of the key academic white nationalists in both ''[[Right Now! (magazine)|Right Now!]]'' and ''American Renaissance'' have been funded by the Pioneer Fund, which was also directly involved in funding the parent organization of ''American Renaissance'', the [[New Century Foundation]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Mehler-funding&quot;/&gt;

== Controversy ==

===Criticism===

The Pioneer Fund was described by the ''Sunday Telegraph'' (March 12, 1989) as a &quot;neo-Nazi organization closely integrated with the far right in American politics.&quot;&lt;ref&gt; {{cite news | first = B | last = MacIntyre | title = The new eugenics | date = 13 March 1989 | work = [[The Sunday Telegraph|London Sunday Telegraph]] | accessdate = 2011-04-15}}, cited in {{cite book | last = E.M. | first = Kramer, | title = The emerging monoculture: assimilation and the &quot;model minority&quot; | publisher = Praeger | location = City | year = 2003 | isbn = 0-275-97312-3 |pages=118, 302}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has also been criticized by some scientists and journalists, and in various peer-reviewed academic articles. Critics of the fund include the SPLC, professor of psychology [[William H. Tucker]], and historian [[Barry Mehler]] and his [[Institute for the Study of Academic Racism]].

The [[Southern Poverty Law Center]] (SPLC), a [[nonprofit]] organization, lists the Pioneer Fund as a [[hate group]], citing the fund's history, its funding of race and intelligence research, and its connections with [[racist]] individuals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Berlet&quot;&gt;Southern Poverty Law Center [http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?aid=50 Into the Mainstream; An array of right-wing foundations and think tanks support efforts to make bigoted and discredited ideas respectable.] Retrieved April 15, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mehler&quot;&gt;Southern Poverty Law Center [http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?pid=623 Race and 'Reason'; Academic ideas a pillar of racist thought.] Retrieved April 15, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; They also state: &quot;Race science has potentially frightening consequences, as is evident not only from the horrors of Nazi Germany, but also from the troubled racial history of the United States. If white supremacist groups had their way, the United States would return to its dark days. In publication after publication, hate groups are using this &quot;science&quot; to legitimize racial hatred. In Calling Our Nation, the neo-Nazi [[Aryan Nations]] publishes a piece by a New York psychologist surveying the work of Jensen, Garrett and numerous others. [[National Vanguard]], the publication of former physics professor [[William Pierce]] (see The Alliance and its Allies) and his neo-Nazi [[National Alliance (United States)|National Alliance]], runs a similar piece that concludes that &quot;it is the Negro's deficiency ... which kept him in a state of savagery in his African environment and is now undermining the civilization of a racially mixed America.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?pid=625&lt;/ref&gt;

The Center for New Community, a human rights advocacy organization, mentioned the Pioneer Fund in an article on their website. They characterize the Pioneer Fund as &quot;a white supremacist foundation that specializes in funding 'science' dedicated to demonstrating white intellectual and moral superiority.&quot; They draw particular attention to Rushton's theories about differences between races as evidence of the racial slant which they claim accompanies much of the research which is backed by the Fund.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.buildingdemocracy.org/reports/defendcoloradonow.pdf Defend Colorado Now: Lamm &amp; FAIR]&lt;/ref&gt;

In accord with the tax regulations governing nonprofit corporations, Pioneer does not fund individuals; under the law only other nonprofit organizations are appropriate grantees. As a consequence, many of the fund's awards go not to the researchers themselves but to the universities that employ them, a standard procedure for supporting work by academically based scientists. In addition to these awards to the universities where its grantees are based, Pioneer has made a number of grants to other nonprofit organizations, corporations Tucker feel have been created to channel resources to a particular academic recipient while circumventing the institution where the researcher is employed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tucker2007&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |title=The funding of Scientific Racism: Wickliffe Draper and the Pioneer Fund |last=Tucker |first=William H. |authorlink=William H. Tucker |publisher=[[University of Illinois Press]] |year=2007 |isbn=978-0-252-07463-9 |laysummary=http://www.press.uillinois.edu/books/catalog/65rwe7dm9780252074639.html |laydate=4 September 2010 |ref=harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ferris.edu/isar/Institut/pioneer/pfspread/pfp6.htm Pioneer Fund Grants, 1971-1996]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2002, William H. Tucker criticized the Pioneer's grant-funding techniques:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Pioneer's administrative procedures are as unusual as its charter. Although the fund typically gives away more than half a million dollars per year, there is no application form or set of guidelines. Instead, according to Weyher, an applicant merely submits &quot;a letter containing a brief description of the nature of the research and the amount of the grant requested.&quot; There is no requirement for peer review of any kind; Pioneer's board of directors—two attorneys, two engineers, and an investment broker—decides, sometimes within a day, whether a particular research proposal merits funding. Once the grant has been made, there is no requirement for an interim or final report or even for an acknowledgment by a grantee that Pioneer has been the source of support, all atypical practices in comparison to other organizations that support scientific research.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tucker2007&quot; /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Rushton, the current head, has spoken at conferences of the ''[[American Renaissance (magazine)|American Renaissance]]'' (AR) magazine, in which he has also published articles.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?pid=214#27&lt;/ref&gt; Anti-racist ''[[Searchlight Magazine]]'' described one such AR conference as a &quot;veritable 'who's who' of American [[white supremacy]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.searchlightmagazine.com/index.php?link=template&amp;story=162&lt;/ref&gt;

Steven J. Rosenthal has described the fund as a: &quot;A Nazi endowment specializing in production of justifications for eugenics since 1937, the Pioneer Fund is embedded in a network of right-wing foundations, think tanks, religious fundamentalists, and global anti-Communist coalitions&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;The Pioneer Fund Financier of Fascist Research. STEVEN J. ROSENTHAL. American Behavioral Scientist September 1995 vol. 39 no. 1 44-61 &lt;/ref&gt;

=== Responses to criticisms ===

Behavioral geneticist [[David T. Lykken]] has defended his acceptance of money from the fund, writing &quot;If you can find me some rich villains that want to contribute to my research—[[Muammar al-Gaddafi|Qaddafi]], the [[Mafia]], whoever—the worse they are, the better I'll like it. I'm doing a social good by taking their money... Any money of theirs that I spend in a legitimate and honorable way, they can't spend in a dishonorable way&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;ohman&quot;&gt;Patricia Ohman (7 March 1984). &quot;Do they get what they Pay for?&quot;, ''[[Minneapolis City Pages]]'', p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt;

Science writer [[Morton Hunt]] received Pioneer funding for his book and wrote: &quot;One could spend hundreds of pages on the pros and cons of the case of the Pioneer Fund, but what matters to me—and should matter to my readers—is that I have been totally free to research and write as I chose. I alerted Pioneer to my political views when making the grant proposal for this book but its directors never blinked.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hunt-intro&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Hunt, Morton |title=The New Know-Nothings: The Political Foes of the Scientific Study of Human Nature |publisher=Transaction Publishers |year=1998 |isbn=0-7658-0497-2 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a review of [[Richard Lynn]]'s book on the Pioneer Fund, psychologist [[Ulrich Neisser]], a prominent critic of race-based research, writes: &quot;All things considered, I doubt that the Pioneer Fund's political activities have made much difference one way or the other. The world would have been much the same without them. On the other hand, Lynn reminds us that Pioneer has sometimes sponsored useful research – research that otherwise might not have been done at all. By that reckoning, I would give it a weak plus.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Neisser 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Charles Murray (author)|Charles Murray]] defended the use of studies supported by the fund in his book ''[[The Bell Curve]]'' by saying: &quot;Never mind that the relationship between the founder of the Pioneer Fund and today's Pioneer Fund is roughly analogous to the relationship between [[Henry Ford]]'s antisemitism and today's [[Ford Foundation]].  The charges have been made, they have wide currency, and some people will always believe that ''The Bell Curve'' rests on data concocted by neo-Nazi eugenicists.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Spring | first = Joel | title = Political Agendas for Education | publisher = L. Erlbaum Associates | location = Hillsdale | year = 1997 | isbn = 0-8058-2766-8 |page=41}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Researchers who have been criticized for accepting grants from the fund have argued that the public debates have been disconnected from the expert debates. [[Robert A. Gordon]], for example, replied to media criticisms of grant-recipients: &quot;Politically correct disinformation about science appears to spread like wildfire among literary intellectuals and other nonspecialists, who have few disciplinary constraints on what they say about science and about particular scientists and on what they allow themselves to believe.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Gordon, Robert A. [http://www.pioneerfund.org/Gordon.pdf Open Letter to ABC news], Johns Hopkins University, 1997.&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
*[[History of the race and intelligence controversy]]
*[[Nature versus nurture]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
*{{Cite book |title=The Science of Human Diversity: A History of the Pioneer Fund |last=Lynn |first=Richard |authorlink=Richard Lynn |others=Harry F. Weyher (Preface) |year=2001 |publisher=University Press of America |location=Lanham (MD) |isbn=0-7618-2040-X |chapter=Preface: My Years with the Pioneer Fund |chapterurl=http://www.pioneerfund.org/Weyher_pdf.pdf |ref=harv }}
*{{cite journal |doi=10.1126/science.2218526 |author=Bouchard TJ, Lykken DT, McGue M, Segal NL, Tellegen A |title=Sources of human psychological differences: the Minnesota Study of Twins Reared Apart |journal=Science |volume=250 |issue=4978 |pages=223–8 |year=1990 |month=October |pmid=2218526 |url=http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&amp;pmid=2218526}}
*{{note|web_1}}{{cite journal |doi=10.1177/1469962002002002627 |author=Graves, Joseph L. |title=What a tangled web he weaves: Race, reproductive strategies and Rushton's life history theory |journal=Anthropological Theory |volume=2 |issue=2 |pages=131–54 |year=2002 |url=http://ant.sagepub.com/cgi/content/abstract/2/2/131}}&lt;br/&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Lieberman, Leonard |authorlink1=Leonard Lieberman |title=How 'Caucasoids' Got Such Big Crania and Why They Shrank |journal=Current Anthropology |volume=42 |issue=1 |pages=69–95 |year=2001 |pmid=14992214 |doi=10.1086/318434 |url=http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/cgi-bin/resolve?id=doi:}}&lt;br/&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1177/002193479502500602 |author=Cernovsky, Zack |title=On the similarities of American blacks and whites: A reply to J.P. Rushton |journal=Journal of Black Studies |volume=25 |issue=6 |pages=672 |year=1995 |url=http://www.mugu.com/cgi-bin/Upstream/People/Rushton/rushton-black-reply.html}}
*{{cite journal | last=Neisser | first=Ulric | title=Serious Scientists or Disgusting Racists? | journal=Contemporary Psychology: APA Review of Books | volume=49 | issue=1 | pages=5–7 | year=2004 | url=http://psycnet.apa.org/critiques/49/1/5 | doi=10.1037/004224 }}
*{{cite web | title=Pioneer Fund, Inc. - Form 990 | year=2011 | publisher=ERI Economic Research Institute, Inc. | url=http://www.eri-nonprofit-salaries.com/index.cfm?FuseAction=NPO.Form990&amp;EIN=510181036 | accessdate=09 January 2010 }}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book | last = Kuhl | first = Stefan | title = The Nazi Connection: Eugenics, American Racism, and German National Socialism | publisher = [[Oxford University Press]] | location = Oxford Oxfordshire | year = 1994 | isbn = 0-19-514978-5 }}

==External links==
*[http://www.pioneerfund.org The Pioneer Fund] Official website
*[http://www.mugu.com/cgi-bin/Upstream/Issues/psychology/IQ/delaware.html &quot;Big Brother in Delaware&quot;], ''[[National Review]]'', Thomas Short (1991)

===Critical===
==== Opinion pieces ====
*[http://www.hartford-hwp.com/archives/45/022.html The New York Times: Fund Backs Controversial Study of &quot;Racial Betterment] [12/11/77]
*&quot;[http://bethuneinstitute.org/documents/racialscientestrushton.html Racial Scientist Rushton Takes Over Pioneer Fund]&quot; by David Lethbridge. The Bethune Institute for Anti-Fascist Studies, January 2003.
*[http://www.nybooks.com/articles/2008 NY Review of Books: 'The Bell Curve' and its Sources]
*[http://dc.indymedia.org/newswire/display/76605 Eugenics, racism, and conservative ideology (pt. 1)]
*[http://www.hartford-hwp.com/archives/45/049.html The Bell Curve and the Pioneer Fund]  A special report by [[ABC World News Tonight]]. November 22, 1994 (Criticized by Gordon 1997 above)
*&quot;[http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/05030/450021.stm Weird Science]&quot; Pittsburgh (Pennsylvania) Post-Gazette, January 30, 2005.

==== Scholarly studies ====
*[http://www.ferris.edu/isar/Institut/pioneer/homepage.htm Pioneer Fund readings] from the [[Institute for the Study of Academic Racism]]
**[http://www.ferris.edu/ISAR/archives/mehler/foundation.htm Foundation for Fascism: the New Eugenics Movement in the United States, Patterns of Prejudice]
**[http://www.ferris.edu/ISAR/Institut/pioneer/search.htm Race Science and the Pioneer Fund]
*[http://www.press.uillinois.edu/epub/books/tucker/toc.html The Funding of Scientific Racism] Online book
*{{cite journal |author=Lombardo PA |title=&quot;The American Breed&quot;: Nazi eugenics and the origins of the Pioneer Fund |journal=Albany Law Rev |volume=65 |issue=3 |pages=743–830 |year=2002 |pmid=11998853 }}
*{{cite journal |author=Kenny MG |title=Toward a racial abyss: eugenics, Wickliffe Draper, and the origins of The Pioneer Fund |journal=J Hist Behav Sci |volume=38 |issue=3 |pages=259–83 |year=2002 |pmid=12115787 |doi=10.1002/jhbs.10063}}

===Pro===
*{{cite book |author=Lynn, Richard |authorlink=Richard Lynn |title=The Science of Human Diversity: A History of the Pioneer Fund |year=2001 |isbn=0-7618-2040-X }}
*{{cite journal |author=Weyher, Harry F. |authorlink=Harry F. Weyher |title=The Pioneer Fund, the Behavioral Sciences, and the Media's False Stories |journal=[[Intelligence (journal)|Intelligence]] |volume= |issue= |pages= |year=1999 |doi= |url=http://home.comcast.net/~neoeugenics/pioneer.htm}}

[[Category:Foundations based in the United States]]
[[Category:Race and intelligence controversy]]
[[Category:Eugenics in the United States]]
[[Category:Scientific racism]]

[[sv:Pioneer Fund]]</text>
      <sha1>hrw4kxkqbbyr1zi5bvmgpzvgfn22v2e</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
