<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Politics of North Korea</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>21259</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520665653</id>
      <parentid>519935914</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-30T23:24:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Hazhk</username>
        <id>13825260</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>add images</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="35618">[[File:Dprk pyongyang chuche monument 05.jpg|thumb|upright|The [[Juche Tower]] ('Tower of [[Juche]] Idea').]]
{{Politics of North Korea}}
The '''politics of North Korea''' take place within a nominally democratic [[multi-party system]] within the framework of the official state philosophy, [[Juche]], a concept created by [[Hwang Jang-yop|Hwang Chang-yŏp]] for and later attributed to [[Kim Il-sung]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Rogue&quot;&gt;{{Citation |title=Rogue Regime: Kim Jong Il and the Looming Threat of North Korea |last=Becker|first=Jasper |authorlink=Jasper Becker |coauthors= |year=2005 |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |location=[[New York City]] |isbn=0-19-517044-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=HwangJuche&gt;B. R. Myers: ''The Cleanest Race: How North Koreans See Themselves and Why It Matters.'' Pages 45–46. Paperback edition. (2011)&lt;/ref&gt; In practice, [[North Korea]] functions as a [[single-party state]] under a [[Totalitarianism|totalitarian]]&lt;ref name=fh&gt;{{Cite web| url = http://freedomhouse.org/template.cfm?page=22&amp;year=2006&amp;country=6993|title=Freedom in the World, 2006|publisher=Freedom House| accessdate=2007-02-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[family dictatorship]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://seattletimes.nwsource.com/html/nationworld/2017052114_kimfamily20.html|title=Key figures in North Korea's family dictatorship|publisher=The Seattle Times|author=Barbara Demick and John M. Glionna|date=December 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/asia/article2452356.ece|title=A tale of two dictatorships: The links between North Korea and Syria|last=Sheridan|first=Michael|date=16 September 2007|work=[[The Times]]|accessdate=2010-04-09 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; described even as an [[absolute monarchy]]&lt;ref&gt;Young W. Kihl, Hong Nack Kim. ''North Korea: The Politics of Regime Survival''. Armonk, New York, USA: M. E. Sharpe, Inc., 2006. Pp 56.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Robert A. Scalapino, Chong-Sik Lee. ''The Society''. University of California Press, 1972. Pp. 689.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bong Youn Choy. A history of the Korean reunification movement: its issues and prospects. Research Committee on Korean Reunification, Institute of International Studies, Bradley University, 1984. Pp. 117.&lt;/ref&gt; with Kim Il-sung and his heirs adopting many aspects similar to the [[Empire of Japan]], especially under Tennō [[Hirohito]] in the 1930s, including propaganda style, “paranoid nationalism”, xenophobia, and racism&lt;ref name=CleanestRace&gt;B. R. Myers: ''The Cleanest Race: How North Koreans See Themselves and Why It Matters.'' Pages 25–32. Paperback edition. (2011)&lt;/ref&gt; – leading to the most recent characterization by some academics as [[national-socialism|national-socialist]] state.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| author=[[Brian Reynolds Myers|Brian R. Myers]] | url = http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748704471504574445980801810944.html | title = The Constitution of Kim Jong Il. | work = [[Wall Street Journal]] | date = 1 October 2009 | accessdate = 20 December 2012 | quote = From its beginnings in 1945 the regime has espoused—to its subjects if not to its Soviet and Chinese aid-providers—a race-based, paranoid nationalism that has nothing to do with Marxism-Leninism. […] North Korea has always had less in common with the former Soviet Union than with the Japan of the 1930s, another ‘national defense state’ in which a command economy was pursued not as an end in itself, but as a prerequisite for rapid armament. North Korea is, in other words, a national-socialist country}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Andrei Lankov]]: [http://www.feer.com/reviews/2009/december51/the-cleanest-race-how-north-koreans-see-themselves-and-why-it-matters Review of ''The Cleanest Race.''] ''Far Eastern Economic Review. '' 4 December 2010. (Accessed February 1, 2012)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Christopher Hitchens]]: [http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/fighting_words/2010/02/a_nation_of_racist_dwarfs.html A Nation of Racist Dwarfs – Kim Jong-il’s regime is even weirder and more despicable than you thought] (2010)&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Economist Intelligence Unit]], while admitting that “there is no consensus on how to measure democracy” and that “definitions of democracy are contested”, lists North Korea in last place as the most [[authoritarian]] regime in its index of democracy assessing 167 countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.economist.com/media/pdf/DEMOCRACY_TABLE_2007_v3.pdf |title=Economist Intelligence Unit democracy index 2006 |accessdate=2007-10-09 |year=2007 |format=PDF |publisher=[[Economist Intelligence Unit]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;

North Korea's political system is built upon the principle of [[centralization]]. While the [[Constitution of North Korea|constitution]] guarantees the protection of [[Human rights in North Korea|human rights]], in practice there are severe limits on [[freedom of expression]], and the government supervises the lives of the people closely. The constitution defines North Korea as &quot;a dictatorship of the people's democracy&quot; under the leadership of the [[Workers' Party of Korea]], which is ''de facto'' the only legally permitted party. Despite the constitution's provisions for democracy, in practice, the [[Supreme leader of North Korea|Supreme Leader]], [[Kim Jong-il]] (son of the state's founder, [[Kim Il-sung]]), exercised absolute control over the government and the country, until 2011.

The ruling party, the WPK, is thought to allow some slight inner-party democracy (see [[Democratic centralism]]). The WPK has ruled since the creation in 1948. Two minor political parties exist but are legally bound to accept the ruling role of the WPK.&lt;ref name=wikisource/&gt; Elections occur only in single-candidate races{{Clarify|date=December 2011}} where the candidate has been selected by the WPK beforehand. [[Kim Il-sung]] served as General Secretary of the WPK from 1948 until his death in July 1994, simultaneously holding the office of [[Prime Minister of North Korea|Prime Minister]] from 1948 to 1972 and the office of President from 1972 to 1994. After his son won full power in 1998, the presidential post was written out of the constitution, and Kim Il-sung was designated the country's &quot;[[Eternal President of the Republic|Eternal President]]&quot;. Most analysts believe the title to be a product of the [[cult of personality]] he cultivated during his life.

The [[Western world]] generally views North Korea as a dictatorship; the government has formally replaced all references to [[Marxism-Leninism]] in its constitution with the locally developed concept of ''[[Juche]]'', or self-reliance. In recent years, there has been great emphasis on the ''[[Songun]]'' or &quot;military-first&quot; philosophy. All references to communism were removed from the North Korean constitution in 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://www.reuters.com/article/latestCrisis/idUSSEO253213 | work=Reuters | title=North Korea drops communism, boosts &quot;Dear Leader&quot; | first=Jon | last=Herskovitz | date=2009-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The status of the military has been enhanced and it appears to occupy the center of the North Korean political system; all the social sectors are forced to follow the military spirit and adopt military methods. Kim Jong-il's public activity focused heavily on on-the-spot guidance of places and events related to the military. The enhanced status of the military and military-centered political system was confirmed at the first session of the 10th [[Supreme People's Assembly]] (SPA) by the promotion of [[National Defense Commission of North Korea|National Defense Commission]] (NDC) members in the official power hierarchy. All ten NDC members were ranked within the top twenty on September 5, and all but one occupied the top twenty at the fiftieth anniversary of National Foundation Day on September 9.

==Government==
{{Main|Government of North Korea}}
{{Wikisource|Constitution of North Korea}}
{{wikisourcelang|ko|분류:조선민주주의인민공화국의 법령}}

The Cabinet of North Korea consists of the Premiers, Vice Premiers, and Ministers of the [[Government of North Korea|government]]. Their terms of office are concurrent with the [[Supreme People's Assembly]]. The Premier is the head of the cabinet. The cabinet exercises theoretical control over the executive ministries and has the authority to issue decrees concerning administration of the government, although in reality the government also took its directions from Kim Jong-il until 2011. The current cabinet consists of:

* [[List of Premiers of North Korea|Premier]]: [[Choe Yong-rim]]&lt;ref name='BBC News 07-06-10'&gt;{{Cite news| first= | last= | coauthors= | title=North Korea in leadership reshuffle | date=2010-06-07 | publisher= | url =http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/asia_pacific/10252477.stm | work =[[BBC News]] | pages = | accessdate = 2010-06-07 | language = }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Foreign Minister: [[Pak Ui-chun]]
** Vice Foreign Minister: [[Kim Kye Gwan]]
*** Vice Foreign Minister: [[Choe Su-hon]]
* Minister of State Construction Control: [[Pae Tal-jun]]
** President of the Central Bank of the Democratic People's Republic of Korea:  [[Ri Kwang-gon]] (since April 2009)
* Minister of Public Security: [[Kwak Pum Ji]]
** Deputy Director: [[Paek Hak-rim]]
* Minister of People's Armed Forces: Vice Marshal [[Kim Il-Chol]]&lt;ref name='KoreaHerald2007-10-04'&gt;{{Cite news| first=Jin | last=Dae-woong | coauthors= | title=Who's who in North Korea's power elite | date=2007-10-04 | publisher= | url =http://www.koreaherald.co.kr:8080/servlet/cms.article.view?tpl=print&amp;sname=National&amp;img=/img/pic/ico_nat_pic.gif&amp;id=200710040041 | work =[[Korea Herald|The Korea Herald]] | pages = | accessdate = 2007-10-05 | language = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Parliament===
According to the constitution, the legislative [[Supreme People's Assembly]] (SPA) is the highest organ of state power. It consists of 687 members, who are elected every five years. The Assembly usually holds only two meetings annually, each lasting a few days; this is the shortest meeting time of any parliament. A standing committee known as the [[Presidium of the Supreme People's Assembly]] and elected by the Assembly performs legislative functions when the Assembly is not in session.

The Assembly officially chooses between, compromises upon, and ratifies the political positions on subjects put forward by the three represented parties. The president of the Supreme People's Assembly is [[Kim Yong-nam]]. Nearly all outside sources regard the SPA as a [[Rubberstamp (politics)|rubberstamp]] body, due to the short period of its sessions, uncontested elections to office, and the fact that it passes all proposals submitted by the government over a period of a few days.&lt;ref name=fh/&gt;

In theory, North Korea's judiciary is accountable to the SPA and the Presidium.&lt;ref name=wikisource/&gt; The SPA's standing committee also appoints judges to the highest court for 5-year terms that are concurrent with those of the Assembly.

===Legal system===
[[Judiciary of North Korea|North Korea's judiciary]] is headed by the [[Central Court of North Korea]], which consists of a Chief Justice and two People's Assessors; three judges may be present in some cases [http://www.nyulawglobal.org/globalex/north_korea.htm]. Their terms of office coincide with those of the members of the Supreme People's Assembly. Every court in North Korea has the same composition as the Central Court. The judicial system is theoretically held accountable to the SPA and the Presidium of the SPA when the legislature is not in session.

The judiciary does not practice [[judicial review]]. The security forces so often interfere with the actions of the judiciary that the conclusion of most cases is foregone; experts outside North Korea and numerous defectors confirm this to be a widespread problem.&lt;ref name=state&gt;{{Cite web| url = http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/hrrpt/2005/61612.htm| title = Country Reports on Human Rights Practices | publisher = U.S. Department of State | accessdate = 2006-02-22 | date = March 8, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Freedom House states that, &quot;North Korea does not have an independent judiciary and does not acknowledge individual rights...reports of arbitrary detentions, 'disappearances,' and extrajudicial killings are common; torture is widespread and severe&quot;&lt;ref name=fh/&gt;

North Korea's fifth and current [[Constitution of North Korea|constitution]] was approved and adopted in September 1998, replacing the one previously adopted in 1972. The former constitution had last been amended in 1992. Under the constitution, North Korea has an unusual legal system based upon German [[Civil law (legal system)|civil law]] and influenced by [[Japan]]ese legal theory.&lt;ref&gt;Patricia Goedde. “Law “Of Our Own Style”: The Evolution and Challenges of the North Korean Legal System”, 27 FORDHAM INT’L L.J. 1265 (2004)&lt;/ref&gt; Criminal penalties can be stiff; one of the basic functions of the system is to uphold the power of the regime. Because so little information is available concerning what actually occurs inside of the country, the extent to which there is any [[rule of law]] is uncertain. In any case, North Korea is known for its poor [[Human rights in North Korea|human rights]] situation and regularly detains thousands of dissidents without trial or benefit of legal advice. According to a US Department of State report on human rights practices, the government of North Korea often punishes the family of a criminal along with the perpetrator.&lt;ref name=state/&gt;

The exists a very unique ideology or doctrine that shaped most of the legal frame of North Korea. That is the concept of &quot;Socialism of our own style&quot;. Internally, Kim Jong-il succeeded the regime but lacked political legitimacy in the beginning. In order to differentiate himself from his father's &quot;Juche&quot; ([[#Political developments|see below]]) and to skillfully secure his leadership, he enumerated this unprecedented doctrine that emphasized the uniqueness and subjectivity of North Korean system. Externally, as Soviet Union collapsed and China normalized its diplomatic relations with South Korea, North Korea's stance in international politics became very insecure. Thus, North Korea desperately needed a device or at least a justification to sustain its socialist system. Kim had to show the public that North Korea can better off, even without compromising to the outside liberal world. Both external and internal factors pressured Kim to isolate his regime from outside world and step on the end of a cliff. With this new ideology that reinforced the unique statism and nationalism, Kim could avoid internal complaints and external crisis. As other socialist countries weakened and domestic public suffered from severe famine, this strategy of isolation was the most effective for the Kim regime to maintain its power. In this sense, it can be said that the &quot;Socialism of Our Own Style&quot; doctrine by Kim Jong-il effectively framed North Korean legislature, administration and military as a whole.

==National Defence Commission==
{{Main|National Defence Commission of North Korea}}
According to the Constitution of North Korea (조선민주주의인민공화국 사회주의 헌법) Article 100, &quot;the [[National Defense Commission of North Korea|National Defence Commission]] is the highest military leadership body of State power.&quot; According to Article 102, &quot;the Chairman of the National Defence Commission of the Democratic People's Republic of Korea commands and directs all the armed forces and guides national defence as a whole.&quot;&lt;ref name=wikisource/&gt; The position of Chairman of the National Defence Commission has been declared the &quot;highest office of state&quot; and has the &quot;highest administrative authority&quot; according to decrees issued by the [[Supreme People's Assembly]].

Few people correctly anticipated that Kim Jong-il would officially terminate the transitional period by resuming the chairmanship of the National Defense Commission (NDC) and abolishing the post of president. Under the 1998 constitution, the NDC's role and status was strengthened. The 1998 constitution defines the NDC as &quot;the highest guiding organ of the military and the managing organ of military matters.&quot; The chairman of the NDC controls the armed forces.

In a speech endorsing Kim Jong-il as NDC chairman, [[Kim Yong-nam]] made it clear that chairman of the NDC is the highest position in the country, in charge of all matters regarding the country's politics, economy, and military. Thus Kim Jong-il was, until 2011, in substance head of the state, but theoretically the chairman of the SPA Presidium represents the state and is responsible for foreign affairs, such as reception.

In June 2010, Kim appointed his brother-in-law, [[Chang Sung-taek]], as vice-chairman of the NDC, in a move seen as propping his own position. Chang was already regarded as the second-most powerful person in North Korea and his appointment strengthens the probability that Kim's third son, [[Kim Jong-un]], will succeed him.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scmp.com/portal/site/SCMP/menuitem.2af62ecb329d3d7733492d9253a0a0a0/?vgnextoid=bdaf79fa7d129210VgnVCM100000360a0a0aRCRD&amp;ss=Insight&amp;s=Opinion Fading Kim sets the stage for power play], [[Donald Kirk]], [[South China Morning Post|SCMP]], 11 June 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

==Party-Government relations==
{{Unreferenced section|date=July 2008}}
The relationship between the party organ and the administrative organ is often compared to the relationship between the man who steers the boat and the man who rows the boat. Party workers in the back should steer so that administrative and economic workers can stay on the party track. Article 11 of the constitution repeats that &quot;the DPRK shall conduct all activities under the leadership of the KWP&quot;. Although relations between the party and the government have experienced both continuity and change, the party has maintained a guiding role over the government. 

First, North Korean leaders attribute the demise of the [[communist bloc]] in [[Eastern Europe]] to the failure of ideology. Thus, they emphasize the importance of ideology, which is led by the party. They also focus on the significance of popular support of the party. Second, Kim Jong Il started his career as a party cadre and his succession to power took place within the structure of the party. Moreover, most of his strong supporters are in the party and the party at large is his most loyal supporter.

Third, North Korea's hesitation to implement a policy aimed at integration into the international community makes one expect that the status of the party vis-à-vis that of the government will be strengthened. Although North Korea is very concerned with the opening policy, its economic policy is dictated by political considerations. North Korea's opening policy is implemented in a very limited way because of the fear of the side effects opening may bring. Thus the role of government technocrats is clearly limited, and it is not feasible to see the government outside the control of the party. Although the government gained in status under the new constitution, this does not affect the guiding role of the party over the government. Particularly in the area of organization and ideology, party guidance may be firmer.

===Elimination of factionalists or enemies of class===
{{see also|Human rights in North Korea}}
Political expression is tightly controlled in North Korea. Supporters of the government who deviate from the government line are subject to [[:wikt:reeducation|reeducation]] in sections of [[labor camp]]s set aside for that purpose. Those who are successfully [[Rehabilitation (penology)|rehabilitated]] may reassume responsible government positions on their release.&lt;ref&gt;[http://koreajoongangdaily.joinsmsn.com/news/article/article.aspx?aid=2952180 &quot;Report on political prisoners in North soon&quot;] article by Han Yeong-ik in Korea Joongang Daily April 30, 2012&lt;/ref&gt; Troublesome political dissidents, [[factionalism|factionalists]] and [[class enemy|class enemies]], who are considered irredeemable are incarcerated together with any close family members or children born in the camp in &quot;[[Kwalliso|Total Control Zones]]&quot; for [[life imprisonment|life]] at [[hard labor]]. [[Human_rights_in_North_Korea#The_prison_system|Labor camps in North Korea]] are actually areas of the country set aside for that purpose, [[Camp 22]] (also known as Kwan-li-so No.22 Haengyong) is 31 miles by 25 miles with a population of about 50,000. Those who attempt to escape or violate camp rules are executed or sent to a separate prison within the camp. The labor camps are reserved for political prisoners; common criminals are incarcerated in a separate system.&lt;ref name = &quot;WPNKCamps&quot; &gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/07/19/AR2009071902178.html &quot;Outside World Turns Blind Eye to N. Korea's Hard-Labor Camps&quot;] by Blaine Harden in ''The Washington Post'' July 20, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; There are six such areas in the central and northeastern part of North Korea.&lt;ref name = &quot;WPMap&quot; &gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/special/world/north-korean-prison-camps-2009/ &quot;On the Map: Five Major North Korean Prison Camps&quot;] interactive map in ''The Washington Post'' July 20, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; Three of them, [[Kaechon internment camp|Camp 14 in Kaechon]],&lt;ref name=guardian &gt;{{cite web| title=How one man escaped from a North Korean prison camp|author=Blaine Harden|date=16 March 2012| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/books/2012/mar/16/escape-north-korea-prison-camp|publisher=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Yodok concentration camp|Camp 15 in Yodok]]&lt;ref name=csw &gt;{{cite web | title=North Korea: A case to answer – a call to act (p. 25–26)| work=Christian Solidarity Worldwide, June 20, 2007| url= http://docs-eu.livesiteadmin.com/c8880e0f-f6ed-4585-8f09-4e4b6d11e698/north-korea-a-case-to-answer-a-call-to-act.pdf | accessdate= April 10, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Bukchang concentration camp|Camp 18 in Bukchang]],&lt;ref name=sub_ihr&gt;{{cite web| title=Subcommittee on International Human Rights, 40th Parliament, 3rd session, February 1, 2011: Testimony of Ms. Hye Sook Kim| work=Parliament of Canada| url=http://www.parl.gc.ca/HousePublications/Publication.aspx?DocId=4916717&amp;Language=E&amp;Mode=1&amp;Parl=40&amp;Ses=3#Int-3706941 | accessdate= April 10, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; are described in detailed testimonies.&lt;ref name=hrnk2&gt;{{cite web | title= The Hidden Gulag – Exposing Crimes against Humanity in North Korea’s Vast Prison System | work= The Committee for Human Rights in North Korea | url= http://www.hrnk.org/uploads/pdfs/HRNK_HiddenGulag2_Web_5-18.pdf| accessdate= September 14, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Factionalists or enemies of class, whoever they are, their seed must be eliminated through three generations. [[Kim Il-sung]] (1972)&lt;ref name = &quot;WPNKCamps&quot; /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Party-Military relations==
{{Unreferenced section|date=July 2008}}
The party has controlled the military in North Korea since the Korean War, when North Korea began to dispatch political officials to the military. In October 1950, party committees began to be organized within the military. The party organs within the military were strengthened after two incidents in 1956 and 1969 that resulted in a wide-scale purge of factions opposed to Kim Il Sung.

According to the Party Act (article 46) adopted in 1980, &quot;KPA is the revolutionary armed forces of the KWP.&quot; Some believe, however, that the [[Songun|military-centred political system]] of recent years may be damaging the party's control over the military. Kim Jong-il treated the military better than ever by frequently visiting events and places associated with it and by promoting military officials in the official power hierarchy.

==Political parties and elections==
{{see also|Elections in North Korea}}
According to the constitution, North Korea is a Democratic Republic and the Supreme People's Assembly and provincial People's Assemblies are elected by direct [[universal suffrage]] and [[secret ballot]]. Suffrage is guaranteed to all citizens aged 17 and over.&lt;ref name=wikisource&gt;{{Cite web| url = http://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Constitution_of_North_Korea | title = Constitution of North Korea | publisher = Wikisource | accessdate = 2007-02-22 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In reality, elections in North Korea are non-competitive and have only single candidate races. Those who want to vote against the sole candidate on the ballot must go to a special booth to cross out the candidate's name before dropping it into the ballot box—an act which, according to many [[North Korean defectors]], is far too risky to even contemplate.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://abcnews.go.com/International/wireStory?id=7032350 North Korea votes for new rubber-stamp parliament],&quot; Associated Press, March 8, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

All elected candidates are members of the [[Democratic Front for the Reunification of the Fatherland]], a [[popular front]] dominated by the WPK. The two minor parties in the coalition are the [[Chondoist Chongu Party]] and the [[Korean Social Democratic Party]]; they also have a few elected officials. The WPK exercises direct control over the candidates selected for election by members of the other two parties.&lt;ref name=fh/&gt;
{{North Korea parliamentary election, 2009}}

==Political developments==
[[File:Mangyongdae Children's Palace 09.JPG|thumb|right|Portraits of the [[Eternal President]], [[Kim Il-sung]] (left), and the [[Chairman of the National Defence Commission of North Korea|Eternal Chairman of the National Defence Commission]], [[Kim Jong-il]] (right).]]
For much of its history, North Korean politics have been dominated by its adversarial relationship with [[South Korea]]. During the [[Cold War]], North Korea aligned with the [[Soviet Union]] and the [[People's Republic of China]]. The North Korean government invested heavily in its military, hoping to develop the capability to reunify Korea by force if possible and also preparing to repel any attack by South Korea or the [[United States]]. As relations with the PRC and the Soviet Union loosened towards the end of the Cold War, North Korea developed an ideology, [[Juche]], based upon a high degree of economic independence and the mobilization of all the resources of the nation to defend against foreign powers seen as a threat to the country's sovereignty.

In the wake of the collapse of the Soviet Union and Soviet-supplied economic aid, North Korea has faced a long period of economic crisis, including severe agricultural and industrial shortages. North Korea's main political issue has been to find a way to sustain its economy without compromising the internal stability of its government or its ability to respond to perceived external threats. To date, North Korean efforts to improve relations with South Korea to increase trade and to receive development assistance have been mildly successful, but North Korea's determination to develop [[nuclear weapon]]s and [[ballistic missile]]s has prevented relations with Japan or the United States from improving. North Korea has also experimented with [[market economics]] in some sectors of its economy, but these have had limited impact. Some outside observers have suggested that Kim Jong-il himself favored such reforms but that some parts of the party and the military resist any changes that might threaten stability.{{Citation needed|date=September 2007}}

Although there exist occasional reports of opposition to the government, these appear to be isolated, and there is no evidence of major internal threats to the current regime. Some foreign analysts have pointed to widespread starvation, increased emigration through North Korea-China border, and new sources of information about the outside world for ordinary North Koreans as factors pointing to an imminent collapse of the regime, but North Korea has remained stable in spite of more than a decade of such predictions. The Workers' Party of Korea maintains a monopoly on political power and Kim Jong-il remained the leader of the country, until 2011, ever since he first gained power following the death of his father.

According to [[Cheong Seong-chang]] of [[Sejong Institute]], speaking on June 25, 2012, there is some possibility that the new leader [[Kim Jong-un]], who has greater visible interest in the welfare of his people and engages in greater interaction with them than his father did, will consider economic reforms and regularization of international relations.&lt;ref name=KH62712&gt;{{cite news|title=N.K. leader seen moving toward economic reform|url=http://view.koreaherald.com/kh/view.php?ud=20120627001074|accessdate=June 28, 2012|newspaper=The Korea Herald|date=June 27, 2012|author=Song Sang-ho}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Dismissal and possible death of Ri Yong-ho ===
On 16 July 2012, North Korean state media reported that the [[Chief of General Staff of the Korean People's Army]] Vice Marshal [[Ri Yong-ho]] had been relieved of all his Party duties, namely his Politburo Standing Committee membership, Politburo membership, and Party Central Military Commission vice-chairmanship, stating this move was due to unspecified illness.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc.co.uk&quot;&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-18851703&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2012-07-15/north-korea-relieves-army-chief-ri-yong-ho-of-all-posts.html &quot;North Korea Fires Army Chief Ri Yong Ho From All Posts&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; A spokesman for the South Korean [[Ministry of Unification]] said the move was &quot;very unusual&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc.co.uk&quot;/&gt; as the meeting at which his removal was announced was attended by the entire Politburo standing committee, Politburo members and candidate members, making ill health seem implausibly minor. Ri was replaced by [[Hyon Yong-chol]] in the role of the Chief of the General Staff.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/asia_pacific/kcna-north-korea-names-hyon-yong-chol-as-new-military-chief/2012/07/16/gJQA3KiSpW_story.html KCNA: North Korea names Hyon Yong Chol as new military chief]&lt;/ref&gt; On July 20, 2012, unconfirmed reports from North Korea alleged that Ri had died or been injured in a [[Battle|firefight]] with [[Political Bureau]] troops.&lt;ref&gt;http://english.chosun.com/site/data/html_dir/2012/07/20/2012072000583.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=theatlantic54858&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theatlanticwire.com/global/2012/07/north-korea-may-have-just-suppressed-coup/54858/|title=Kim Jong-Un May Have Just Suppressed a Coup|publisher=The Atlantic Wire|date=July 20, 2012|accessdate=2012-07-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some reports suggest that this may mark a shift in power between the political leadership and the armed forces, with the political leadership in the ascendant.&lt;ref name=theatlantic54858/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2012/07/20/us-korea-north-idUSBRE86J08X20120720|title=Exclusive: Kim plans economic change in North Korea|publisher=Reuters|date=July 20, 2012|accessdate=2012-07-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==State leaders==
Eternal President: [[Kim Il-sung]] 

'''National Defence Commission of DPRK'''

Eternal Chairman: [[Kim Jong-il]]

First Chairman: [[Kim Jong-un]] (from April 2012)

Vice Chairman: [[Kim Yong Chun]], [[Ri Yong Mu]], [[Jang Song Thaek]](from June 2010), [[O Kuk Ryol]] (from April 2009)

Members: [[Pak To Chun]], [[Kim Jong Gak]], [[Ju Kyu Chang]], [[Paek Se Bong]], and since 2012: [[Choe Ryong Hae]], [[Kim Won Hong]] and [[Ri Myong Su]]
 
'''Presidium of the SPA of the DPRK''' 

President: [[Kim Yong-nam]]

Vice presidents: [[Yang Hyong-sop|Yang Hyong Sop]] and [[Kim Yong Dae]] 

Honorary vice-president: [[Kim Yong Ju]] 

Secretary general of the Presidium: [[Thae Hyong Chol]] (from April 2012)

'''Supreme People's Assembly (SPA)'''

Chairman: [[Choe Thae-bok]] 

Vice-chairpersons: [[Kim Wan Su]] and [[Hong Son Ok]] 

'''Cabinet'''

Premier: [[Choe Yong Rim]] 

Vice Premiers: [[Ro Tu Chol]] (from April 2009), [[Pak Su Gil]] (from September 2009), and [[Kang Nung Su]], [[Kim Rak Hui]], [[Ri Thae Nam]], [[Jon Ha Chol]], [[Jo Pyong Ju]], [[Han Kwang Bok]] (from June 2010), [[Kang Sok Ju]] (from September 2010), [[Ri Sung Ho]], [[Ri Chol Man]], [[Kim In Sik]] (since April 2012)

Minister of Foreign Affairs: [[Pak Ui Chun]] 

Minister of People's Security: [[Ju Sang Song]]

Minister of Finance: [[Pak Su-gil]]

Minister of People’s Armed Forces: [[Kim Jong Gak]] 

'''WPK Central Committee'''

Eternal General Secretary: [[Kim Jong-il]]

First secretary of the WPK: [[Kim Jong-un]]

Presidium of the Political Bureau of the Workers' Party of Korea Central Committee (since September 2010): 

1.[[Kim Jong-un]] (since April 2012)
 
2.[[Kim Yong-nam]] 

3. [[Choe Yong Rim]]

4.[[Choe Ryong Hae]] (since April 2012)

Members and Alternate Members of Political Bureau: [[Kim Jong-un]], [[Kim Yong-nam]], [[Choe Yong Rim]], [[Choe Ryong Hae]], [[Kim Yong Chun]], [[Jon Pyong Ho]], [[Kim Kuk Thae]], [[Kim Ki Nam]], [[Choe Thae-bok]], [[Yang Hyong Sop]], [[Kang Sok Ju]], [[Pyon Yong Rip]], [[Ri Yong Mu]], [[Ju Sang Song]], [[Hong Sok Hyong]] and [[Kim Kyong Hui]], and since April 2012 [[Kim Jong Gak]], [[Jang Song Thaek]], [[Pak To Chun]], [[Hyon Chol Hae]], [[Kim Won Hong]] and [[Ri Myong Su]] (members), [[Kim Yang Gon]], [[Kim Yong Il]], [[Choe Ryong Hae]], [[Ju Kyu Chang]], [[Ri Thae Nam]], [[Kim Rak Hui]], [[Thae Jong Su]], [[Kim Phyong Hae]], [[U Tong Chuk]], [[Pak Jong Sun]], [[Kim Chang Sop]] and [[Mun Kyong Dok]] and since April 2012: [[Kwak Pom Gi]], [[O Kuk Ryol]], [[Ro Tu Chol]], [[Ri Pyong Sam]] and [[Jo Yon Jun]] (alternate members) 

Secretariat of WPK Central Committee: [[Kim Jong-un]], [[Kim Ki Nam]], [[Choe Thae-bok]], [[Choe Ryong Hae]], [[Mun Kyong Dok]], [[Pak To Chun]], [[Kim Yong Il]], [[Kim Yang Gon]], [[Kim Phyong Hae]], [[Thae Jong Su]] and [[Hong Sok Hyong]], and April 2012: [[Kim Kyong Hui]] and [[Kwak Pom Gi]] 

Central Military Commission of the Workers' Party of Korea: Chairman [[Kim Jong-un]] (since 2012), Vice - Chairmen [[Choe Ryong Hae]] and [[Hyon Yong-chol]] (since 2012), Members [[Kim Yong Chun]], [[Kim Jong Gak]], [[Kim Myong Guk]], [[Kim Kyong Ok]], [[Kim Won Hong]], [[Jong Myong Do]], [[Ri Pyong Chol]], [[Choe Pu Il]], [[Kim Yong Chol]], [[Yun Jong Rin]], [[Ju Kyu Chang]], [[Choe Sang Ryo]], [[Choe Kyong Song]], [[U Tong Chuk]], [[Jang Song Thaek]], and since April 2012: [[Hyon Chol Hae]], [[Ri Myong Su]] and [[Kim Rak Gyom]].

==See also==
*[[List of Korea-related topics]]
*[[Kim Jong-il]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
&lt;div class=&quot;external-small&quot;&gt;
*[http://www.uriminzokkiri.com/index.php?ptype=english Uriminzokkiri.com]
*[http://freedomhouse.org/template.cfm?page=22&amp;year=2006&amp;country=6993 Freedom House Country Report on North Korea]
*[http://www.house.gov/international_relations/nkhra.htm The North Korean Human Rights Act: Documents and Background Materials]
&lt;/div&gt;
*[http://www.wilsoncenter.org/nkidp The North Korean International Documentation Project]
*[http://www.nkeconwatch.com/north-korea-uncovered-google-earth North Korea Uncovered], a comprehensive mapping on [[Google Earth]] of the DPRK's political and economic infrastructure

{{Asia topic|Politics of}}

[[Category:Politics of North Korea| ]]

[[bn:উত্তর কোরিয়া#রাজনীতি]]
[[bg:Държавно устройство на Северна Корея]]
[[es:Gobierno y política de Corea del Norte]]
[[fr:Politique de la Corée du Nord]]
[[ko:조선민주주의인민공화국의 정치]]
[[he:פוליטיקה של קוריאה הצפונית]]
[[lt:Šiaurės Korėjos politinė sistema]]
[[ja:朝鮮民主主義人民共和国の政治]]
[[pl:Ustrój polityczny Korei Północnej]]
[[pt:Política da Coreia do Norte]]
[[ru:Политика КНДР]]
[[sk:Politika Kórejskej ľudovodemokratickej republiky]]</text>
      <sha1>h18gu819dwystdg0yzldnt5olhhx8e0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
