<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Political correctness</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>23213</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521159839</id>
      <parentid>521159759</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-03T04:45:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>219.64.67.122</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="36376">{{Redirect|Politically incorrect|the American television show|Politically Incorrect|other uses|Politically incorrect (disambiguation)}}
'''Political correctness''' (adjectivally, '''politically correct'''; both forms commonly abbreviated to '''PC''') is a term which denotes [[language]], ideas, policies, and behavior seen as seeking to minimize social and institutional offense in occupational, gender, racial, cultural, sexual orientation, certain other religions, beliefs or ideologies, disability, and age-related contexts, and, as purported by the term, doing so to an excessive extent.  In current usage, the term is primarily [[pejorative]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Perry-1992a&quot;&gt;Ruth Perry, (1992), “A short history of the term ‘politically correct’ ”, in ''Beyond PC: Toward a Politics of Understanding '', by Patricia Aufderheide, 1992&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Schultz-1993a&quot;&gt;Schultz, Debra L. (1993). To Reclaim a Legacy of Diversity: Analyzing the “Political Correctness” Debates in Higher Education. New York: National Council for Research on Women. [http://www.eric.ed.gov/ERICDocs/data/ericdocs2sql/content_storage_01/0000019b/80/13/34/5d.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt; while the term '''politically ''in''correct''' has been used as an implicitly positive self-description. Examples of the latter include the [[conservatism in the United States|conservative]] ''[[The Politically Incorrect Guide]]'' published by [[Regnery Publishing]] and the television talk show ''[[Politically Incorrect]]''. In these cases, the term ''politically incorrect'' connotes language, ideas, and behavior unconstrained by a perceived [[orthodoxy]] or by concerns about offending or expressing bias regarding various groups of people.

==History==

===Early usages===
Early usages of the phrase &quot;politically correct&quot; have been found in various contexts, which may not relate to the current terminology.&lt;ref&gt;[http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?navby=CASE&amp;court=US&amp;vol=2&amp;page=419 Chisholm v State of GA, 2 US 419 (1793)] ''Findlaw.com'' - Accessed February 6, 2007. “The states, rather than the People, for whose sakes the States exist, are frequently the objects which attract and arrest our principal attention. . . . Sentiments and expressions of this inaccurate kind prevail in our common, even in our convivial, language. Is a toast asked? ‘The United States’, instead of the ‘People of the United States’, is the toast given. This is not politically correct.”&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last= Flower|first=Newmas|title=The Journals of Arnold Bennett|publisher=READ BOOKS, |year=2006|isbn=978-1-4067-1047-2|url=http://books.google.com/?id=kRJblj1e4zsC&amp;pg=PA108&amp;lpg=PA108&amp;dq=%22Political+correctness%22+%22arnold+bennett%22}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Examples of the term can be found as early as the 18th century. The previous meaning was 'in line with prevailing political thought or policy'. The term previously used 'correctness' in its literal sense and without any particular reference to language that might be considered offensive or discriminatory. For example, J. Wilson's comments in U.S. Republic, 1793:

{{quote|The states, rather than the people, for whose sake the states exist, are frequently the objects which attract and arrest our principal attention... Sentiments and expressions of this inaccurate kind prevail in our common, even in our convivial, language... ‘The United States,’ instead of the ‘People of the United States,’ is the toast given. This is not politically correct.|&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.phrases.org.uk/meanings/287100.html |title=Politically correct |publisher=Phrases.org.uk |date= |accessdate=2011-05-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===New Left rhetoric===
By 1970, [[New Left]] proponents had adopted the term ''political correctness''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Perry-1992a&quot;/&gt; In the essay ''The Black Woman'', [[Toni Cade Bambara]] says: &quot;. . . a man cannot be politically correct and a [male] [[chauvinist]] too.&quot; The New Left later re-appropriated the term ''political correctness'' as [[satirical]] self-criticism; per Debra Shultz: &quot;Throughout the 1970s and 1980s, the New Left, feminists, and progressives . . . used their term ''politically correct'' ironically, as a guard against their own orthodoxy in social change efforts&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Perry-1992a&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Schultz-1993a&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Schultz citing Perry (1992) p.16&lt;/ref&gt; Hence, it is a popular English usage in the underground comic book ''Merton of the Movement'', by [[Bobby London]], while ''ideologically sound'', an alternative term, followed a like lexical path, appearing in [[Bart Dickon]]’s satirical comic strips.&lt;ref name=&quot;Perry-1992a&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url=http://www.inthesetimes.com/article/3027/a_politically_correct_lexicon/ |title=A Politically Correct Lexicon |journal=In These Times |author=Joel Bleifuss |month=February | year=2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, [[Ellen Willis]] says: &quot; . . . in the early ’80s, when [[feminism|feminists]] used the term ''political correctness'', it was used to refer sarcastically to the [[anti-pornography movement]]’s efforts to define a ‘feminist sexuality’ &quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Ellen Willis, &quot;Toward a Feminist Revolution&quot;, in ''No More Nice Girls: Countercultural Essays'' (1992) Wesleyan University Press, ISBN 0-8195-5250-X, p.19.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Current usage==
Widespread use of the term ''politically correct'' and its derivatives began when it was adopted as a pejorative term by the political right in the 1990s, in the context of the [[Culture Wars]]. Writing in the [[New York Times]] in 1990,&lt;ref name=&quot;urlIDEAS &amp; TRENDS; The Rising Hegemony of the Politically Correct - The New York Times&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1990/10/28/weekinreview/ideas-trends-the-rising-hegemony-of-the-politically-correct.html?pagewanted=all |title=IDEAS &amp; TRENDS; The Rising Hegemony of the Politically Correct - The New York Times |work= |accessdate= May 22, 2010| first=Richard | last=Bernstein | date=October 28, 1990}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Richard Bernstein]] noted &quot;The term 'politically correct,' with its suggestion of Stalinist orthodoxy, is spoken more with irony and disapproval than with reverence. But across the country the term p.c., as it is commonly abbreviated, is being heard more and more in debates over what should be taught at the universities.&quot; Bernstein referred to a meeting of the [http://www.humanities.uci.edu/wha/about/ Western Humanities Conference] in [[Berkeley, California]], on &quot;'Political Correctness' and Cultural Studies,&quot; which examined &quot;what effect the pressure to conform to currently fashionable ideas is having on scholarship&quot;. Bernstein also referred to &quot;p.c.p&quot; for &quot;politically correct people,&quot; a term which did not take root in popular discussion.

Within a few years, this previously obscure term featured regularly in the lexicon of the conservative social and political challenges against [[curriculum]] expansion and [[progressivism|progressive]] [[teaching]] methods in US high schools and universities.&lt;ref&gt;D’Souza 1991; Berman 1992; Schultz 1993; Messer Davidow 1993, 1994; Scatamburlo 1998&lt;/ref&gt; In 1991, addressing a graduating class of the [[University of Michigan]], U.S. President [[George H. W. Bush]] spoke against &quot;a movement [that would] declare certain topics 'off-limits,' certain expressions 'off-limits', even certain gestures 'off-limits'&quot; in allusion to liberal Political Correctness.&lt;ref&gt;[http://bushlibrary.tamu.edu/research/papers/1991/91050401.html Remarks at the University of Michigan Commencement Ceremony in Ann Arbor], May 4, 1991. George Bush Presidential Library.&lt;/ref&gt; The most common usage here is as a pejorative term to refer to excessive deference to particular sensibilities at the expense of other considerations. The converse term &quot;politically incorrect&quot; came into use as an implicit term of self-praise, indicating that the user was not afraid to ignore constraints associated with political correctness. Examples of the latter include the [[conservatism in the United States|conservative]] [[The Politically Incorrect Guide|Politically Incorrect Guides]] published by [[Regnery Publishing]]&lt;ref name=&quot;marji ross&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pittsburghlive.com/x/pittsburghtrib/opinion/s_604625.html | title=Regnery's Marji Ross profits in a liberal world | author=  Bill Steigerwald | work= [[Pittsburgh Tribune-Review]] | date= 2008-12-28 | accessdate= 2012-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the television talk show ''[[Politically Incorrect]]''.

The central uses of the term relate to particular issues of race, gender, disability, ethnicity, sexual orientation, culture and worldviews, and encompass both the language in which issues are discussed and the viewpoints that are expressed. Proponents of the view that differences in IQ test scores between blacks and whites are (primarily or largely) genetically determined state that criticism of these views is based on political correctness.&lt;ref name=&quot;urlThe Bell Curve Wars&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.galtoninstitute.org.uk/Newsletters/GINL9606/bell_curve_wars.htm |title=The Bell Curve Wars |work= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Examples of language commonly referred to as &quot;politically correct&quot; include:&lt;ref name=&quot;urlwww.amazon.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amazon.com/Official-Politically-Correct-Dictionary-Handbook/dp/078710146X |title=Official Politically Correct Dictionary Handbook|work=  |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Page needed|date=August 2011}}

* &quot;[[Intellectually disabled]]&quot; in place of &quot;Retarded&quot; and other terms
* &quot;[[African American]]&quot; in place of &quot;Black,&quot; &quot;Negro&quot; and other terms
* &quot;[[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]]&quot; (United States)/&quot;[[First Nations]]&quot; ([[Canada]]) in place of &quot;Indian&quot;
* &quot;[[White people|Caucasian]]&quot; in place of &quot;White&quot;, and other terms such as the more scientifically correct &quot;Caucasoid&quot;
* &quot;Gender-neutral&quot; terms such as &quot;[[firefighter]]&quot; in place of &quot;fireman,&quot; [[police officer]] in place of policeman.
* Terms relating to lack of various common human abilities, such as &quot;[[Visual impairment|visually impaired]]&quot; or &quot;[[Deafness|hearing impaired]]&quot; in place of &quot;blind&quot; or &quot;deaf&quot;
* &quot;Holiday&quot;, &quot;winter&quot; or &quot;festive&quot; in place of &quot;Christmas&quot;

In the [[United Kingdom]], &quot;political correctness gone mad&quot; is a [[catchphrase]] associated with the [[conservative]] ''[[Daily Mail]]'' newspaper.&lt;ref name=&quot;urlMulticulturalism and citizenship: responses to Tariq Modood | openDemocracy&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.opendemocracy.net/faith-terrorism/response_madood_4630.jsp |title=Multiculturalism and citizenship: responses to Tariq Modood &amp;#124; openDemocracy |work= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a more general sense, any policy regarded by the speaker as representing an imposed orthodoxy may be criticized as &quot;politically correct.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;isbn0-595-29797-8&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Mihkel M. Mathiesen |title=Global Warming in a Politically Correct Climate: How Truth Became Controversial |publisher=iUniverse Star |location= |year=2004 |pages= |isbn=0-595-29797-8 |oclc= |doi= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Linguistics==
{{main|Gender-neutral language|People-first language}}
In addressing the linguistic problem of naming, Edna Andrews says that using &quot;inclusive&quot; and &quot;neutral&quot; language is based upon the concept that &quot;language represents thought, and may even control thought.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;cs&quot;&gt;Cultural Sensitivity and Political Correctness: The Linguistic Problem of Naming, Edna Andrews, ''American Speech'', Vol. 71, No. 4 (Winter, 1996), pp.389-404.&lt;/ref&gt;
This claim has been derived from the [[Sapir–Whorf hypothesis]], which states that a language’s grammatical categories shape the speaker’s ideas and actions; although Andrews says that moderate conceptions of the relation between language and thought are sufficient to support the &quot;reasonable deduction&amp;nbsp;... [of] cultural change via linguistic change&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Development and Validation of an Instrument to Measure Attitudes Toward Sexist/Nonsexist Language Sex Roles: A Journal of Research, March 2000, by Janet B. Parks, Mary Ann Roberton [http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m2294/is_2000_March/ai_63993943/pg_1]&lt;/ref&gt;

Other [[cognitive psychology]] and [[cognitive linguistics]] works indicate that word-choice has significant &quot;[[Framing (social sciences)|framing effects]]&quot; on the perceptions, memories, and attitudes of speakers and listeners.&lt;ref&gt;Loftus, E. and Palmer, J. 1974. &quot;Reconstruction of Automobile Destruction: An example of the interaction between language and memory.&quot; ''Journal of Verbal Learning and Verbal Behavior'' 13, pp.585-9&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kahneman, D. and Amos Tversky. 1981. &quot;The Framing of Decisions and the Psychology of Choice.&quot; ''Science'', 211, pp.453-8&lt;/ref&gt; A relevant empirical question is whether or not [[Gender-neutral language|sexist language]] promotes sexism, i.e. sexist thought and action.

Advocates of inclusive language defend it as inoffensive-language usage whose goal is multi-fold:

# The rights, opportunities, and freedoms of certain people are restricted because they are reduced to [[stereotype]]s.
# Stereotyping is mostly implicit, unconscious, and facilitated by the availability of pejorative labels and terms.
# Rendering the labels and terms socially unacceptable, people then must consciously think about ''how'' they describe someone unlike themselves.
# When labeling is a conscious activity, the described person's ''individual'' merits become apparent, rather than their stereotype.

Critics of such arguments, and of inclusive language in general, commonly use the terminology of &quot;political correctness&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.catholicculture.org/culture/library/view.cfm?id=2623&amp;CFID=16394192&amp;CFTOKEN=66016122 |title=Library : Inclusive Language: Is It Necessary? |publisher=Catholic Culture |date= |accessdate=2011-05-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A common criticism is that terms chosen by an identity group, as acceptable descriptors of themselves, then pass into common usage, including usage by the racists and sexists whose racism and sexism, et cetera, the new terms mean to supersede. Alternately put, the new terms gradually acquire the same disparaging connotations of the old terms. The new terms are thus devalued, and another set of words must be coined, giving rise to lengthy progressions such as ''Negro'', ''Colored'', ''Black'', ''Afro-American'', ''African-American'', and so on, (cf. [[Euphemism treadmill]]).

==Criticisms==

Discussion of political correctness, to the extent that it uses the term and accepts the existence of political correctness as a significant force, is almost invariably critical.

===General===
Bulgarian-French philosopher [[Julia Kristeva]], a structuralist who has been identified as a theorist instrumental to providing the philosophical basis for American political correctness, denounced political correctness in 2001 in ''[[The New York Times]]'' and said her works have been distorted by Americans. She labeled [[identity politics]] and political correctness in general as [[totalitarian]].&lt;ref&gt;Riding, Alan, [http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/14/arts/correcting-her-idea-of-politically-correct.html?pagewanted=all Correcting Her Idea of Politically Correct]. New York Times. June 14, 2001&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''The Abolition of Britain'', [[Peter Hitchens]] says: “What Americans describe with the casual phrase . . . ‘political correctness’ is the most intolerant system of thought to dominate the British Isles since the [[Protestant Reformation|Reformation]]”.

The academic [[Camille Paglia]] said that PC empowers the enemies of the Left, and alienates the masses against [[feminism]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://dim.com/~randl/camille.htm Camille Paglia says it best--] Accessed February 2, 2007. “My message to the media is: ‘Wake up!’ The silencing of authentic debate among feminists just helps the rise of the far right. When the media get locked in their Northeastern ghetto and become slaves of the feminist establishment and fanatical special interests, the American audience ends up looking to conservative voices for common sense. As a libertarian Democrat, I protest against this self-defeating tyranny of political correctness.”&lt;/ref&gt;

===Exclusion of certain groups===
An article by [[Larry Elder]] in [[FrontPage Magazine]] referred to an incident on [[Bill Maher]]'s ''Politically Incorrect'' where the term &quot;[[white trash]]&quot; was used in reference to guests on the [[Jerry Springer Show]] and asked 'Why Is It Okay to Say &quot;White Trash?&quot;'.&lt;ref name=&quot;urlFrontPage Magazine - Why Is It Okay to Say White Trash?&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://97.74.65.51/readArticle.aspx?ARTID=22911 |title=FrontPage Magazine - Why Is It Okay to Say &quot;White Trash?&quot; |work= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Commenting on this, and citing an instance of the term in a glossy magazine, blogger Ed Driscoll asked &quot;Why Is &quot;White Trash&quot; An Acceptable Phrase In PC America?&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;urlEd Driscoll.com: Why Is White Trash An Acceptable Phrase In PC America?&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://eddriscoll.com/archives/007301.php |title=Ed Driscoll.com: Why Is &quot;White Trash&quot; An Acceptable Phrase In PC America? |work= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cultural Marxism===
{{main|Cultural Marxism}}
University of Pennsylvania professor [[Alan Charles Kors]] and lawyer [[Harvey A. Silverglate]] connect political correctness to Marxist philosopher [[Herbert Marcuse]]. They claim that liberal ideas of free speech are repressive, arguing that such &quot;Marcusean logic&quot; is the base of [[speech codes]], which are seen by some as [[censorship]], in US universities. Kors and Silvergate later established the [[Foundation for Individual Rights in Education]], which campaigns against PC speech codes.&lt;ref&gt;Kors, A.C. and Silvergate, H, [http://reason.com/9811/fe.kors.shtml &quot;Codes of silence - who's silencing free speech on campus -- and why&quot;] ''Reason Magazine (online)'', November 1998 - Accessed February 6, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some conservative critics claim that political correctness is a Marxist undermining of Western values.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.freecongress.org/PC_Essays/B_Intro_and_chapter_one.pdf ]{{Dead link|date=June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; William S. Lind and [[Patrick Buchanan]] have characterized PC as a technique originated by the [[Frankfurt School]], through what Buchanan describes as &quot;[[Cultural Marxism]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.academia.org/lectures/lind1.html |title=William S. Lind says Political Correctness is a form of what Buchanan describes as cultural Marxism |publisher=Academia.org |date= |accessdate=June 1, 2009}}{{Dead link|date=December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,157952,00.html |title=Buchanan interview on Fox News |publisher=Foxnews.com |date=May 27, 2005 |accessdate=June 1, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''[[The Death of the West]]'', Buchanan says: “Political Correctness is Cultural Marxism, a regime to punish dissent and to stigmatize social heresy as the [[Inquisition]] punished religious heresy. Its trademark is intolerance.” &lt;ref&gt;Buchanan, Patrick ''The Death of the West'', p.89&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Higher education ===
{{See also|Higher education in the United States#Political views}}
A conservative criticism of higher education in the United States is that the political views of the faculty are much more liberal than the general population, and that this situation contributes to an atmosphere of political correctness.&lt;ref&gt;The Politically Correct University Problems, Scope, and Reforms, Edited By Frederick M. Hess, Robert Maranto, Richard E. Redding, AEI Press, September 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Counterclaims==

===Engineered political term===
A major criticism of the term stems from critics' claims of how it has been used by conservatives for political gain, considering it to play to voters' fears as a [[red herring]] as well as an attack on the political left.  Some commentators claimed that after 1980, [[American conservatives]] re-engineered the term to ideologically re-frame US politics as a [[culture war]]. Hutton reports:

{{quote|Political correctness is one of the brilliant tools that the American Right developed in the mid-1980s, as part of its demolition of American liberalism. . . . What the sharpest thinkers on the American Right saw quickly was that by declaring war on the cultural manifestations of liberalism — by levelling the charge of &quot;political correctness&quot; against its exponents — they could discredit the whole political project.|&lt;ref&gt;Hutton W, [http://observer.guardian.co.uk/race/story/0,,619644,00.html “Words really are important, Mr Blunkett”] ''The Observer'', Sunday December 16, 2001 - Accessed February 6, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Moreover, the commentators claimed there never was a “Political Correctness movement” in the US, and that many who use the term do so to distract attention from substantive debate about racial, class and gender discrimination and unequal legal treatment.&lt;ref&gt;Messer–Davidow 1993, 1994; Schultz 1993; Lauter 1995; Scatamburlo 1998; and Glassner 1999.&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, [[Polly Toynbee]] argued that “the phrase is an empty right-wing smear designed only to elevate its user”.&lt;ref&gt;Toynbee P, [http://society.guardian.co.uk/regeneration/comment/0,7941,617436,00.html “Religion must be removed from all functions of state”], ''The Guardian'', Sunday December 12, 2001 - Accessed February 6, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

Commenting on the UK's 2009 [[Harriet Harman#Equality Bill|Equality Bill]], Toynbee wrote that:

{{quote|The phrase &quot;political correctness&quot; was born as a coded cover for all who still want to say Paki, spastic or queer, all those who still want to pick on anyone not like them, playground bullies who never grew up. The politically correct society is the civilised society, however much some may squirm at the more inelegant official circumlocutions designed to avoid offence.|&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2009/apr/28/toynbee-equality-bill-welfare | work=The Guardian | location=London | title=This bold equality push is just what we needed. In 1997 | first=Polly | last=Toynbee | date=April 28, 2009 | accessdate=May 22, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

=== False accusations ===
In the United Kingdom, some newspapers reported that a school had altered the nursery rhyme “Baa Baa Black Sheep” to read “Baa Baa Rainbow Sheep”.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Blair
  |first=Alexandra
  |title=Why black sheep are barred and Humpty can't be cracked
  |publisher=The Times
  |date=March 7, 2006
  |url=http://women.timesonline.co.uk/tol/life_and_style/women/families/article738220.ece
  |accessdate=October 5, 2007
| location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; But it is also reported that a better description is that the Parents and Children Together (PACT) nursery had the children “turn the song into an action rhyme. . . . They sing happy, sad, bouncing, hopping, pink, blue, black and white sheep etc.” &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/education/4782856.stm |title=Nursery opts for 'rainbow' sheep |accessdate=October 6, 2007 |work=BBC News | date=March 7, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; That nursery rhyme story was circulated and later extended to suggest that like language bans applied to the terms “black coffee” and “blackboard”.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://teenink.com/talk/showthread.php?s=cb96eb0a024fd73bbc9080f5184fd151&amp;postid=322528 |title=Teen Ink - Bah, Bah, Rainbow Sheep |accessdate=October 6, 2007 |work=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Private Eye (magazine)|Private Eye]] magazine reported that like stories, all baseless, ran in the British press since ''[[The Sun (newspaper)|The Sun]]'' first published them in 1986.&lt;ref name = &quot;BaaBaa-Bollocks&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.septicisle.info/2006/03/baa-baa-rainbow-bollocks.html |title=Obsolete: Baa Baa Rainbow Bollocks. |accessdate=October 6, 2007 |work=}}&lt;/ref&gt; See also [[Loony Left#Baa Baa White Sheep]].

==Science==
{{See also|Politicization of science}}

Among scientists, &quot;correctness&quot; (of procedures, results, or scientific claims) derives from the factual truth of the matter or the soundness of the reasoning by which it can be deduced from observations and first principles.
When publication, teaching, and public funding of science is decided by peer committees, academic standards, and elected or appointed boards, the allegation can arise that a work's acceptability has been assessed &quot;politically&quot;.  Professor J. I. Katz applies the term PC to censure characterized by emotional, rather than rational discourse.&lt;ref name=&quot;Katz&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wuphys.wustl.edu/~katz/pc.html |title=What Is Political Correctness? &amp;#124;author Jonathan I. Katz}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Groups opposing certain generally accepted scientific views on [[evolution]], [[second-hand smoke]], [[AIDS denialism|AIDS]], and other politically contentious scientific matters argue that PC is responsible for the failure of their perspectives to receive a fair public hearing; thus, in ''Lamarck's Signature: How Retrogenes are Changing Darwin's Natural Selection Paradigm'', Assoc. Prof. [[Edward J. Steele]] says: &quot;We now stand on the threshold of what could be an exciting new era of genetic research. . . . However, the 'politically correct' thought agendas of the neo-Darwinists of the 1990s are ideologically opposed to the idea of '[[Lamarckism|Lamarckian Feedback]]', just as the Church was opposed to the idea of evolution based on natural selection in the 1850s!&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;isbn0-7382-0171-5&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Robert V. Blanden; Steele, Edward David; Lindley, Robyn A. |title=Lamarck's signature: how retrogenes are changing Darwin's natural selection paradigm |publisher=Perseus Books |location=Reading, Mass |year=1999 |pages= |isbn=0-7382-0171-5 |oclc= |doi=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[The Politically Incorrect Guide to Science]]'', by [[Tom Bethell]], is a comprehensive presentation argument that mainstream science is dominated by politically correct thinking. Bethell rejects mainstream views about evolution and global warming, and supports [[AIDS denialism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Bethell, Tom |title=The Politically Incorrect Guide to Science |publisher=Regnery Publishing |location=Washington, D.C |year= 2005|pages= |isbn=0-89526-031-X |oclc= |doi=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Right-wing political correctness==
Accusations of political correctness, in the sense of enforced orthodoxy, have also been directed against the political right. For example, the intense [[Dixie Chicks political controversy|backlash]] against country band the [[Dixie Chicks]], for [[Dixie Chicks#Remarks about George W. Bush and the War in Iraq|remarks critical of President George W. Bush]] onstage in London in 2003, was described by newspaper columnist Don Williams as the price for freely speaking political views disapproved by supporters of the [[Iraq War]]. Williams went on to say, “the ugliest form of political correctness occurs whenever there’s a war on. Then you’d better watch what you say.” He noted that [[Ann Coulter]] and [[Bill O'Reilly (commentator)|Bill O'Reilly]] called the remarks in question &quot;treasonous&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mach2.com/williams/index.php?t=1&amp;c=20060602120901 |title=Don Williams Insights - Dixie Chicks Were Right |accessdate=November 9, 2007 |work=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Bill Maher]]'s show ''[[Politically Incorrect]]'' lost some of its main advertisers after remarks he made about the 9/11 hijackers including that the hijackers were not cowards but that it was cowardly for the United States to launch cruise missiles on targets thousands of miles away. He later apologized. White House press secretary under President Bush at the time, Ari Fleischer stated, &quot;people have to watch what they say and watch what they do&quot;. Fleischer later stated that this referred to both Maher and remarks against Arabs by Representative John Cooksey that were considered disparaging. Two journalists lost their jobs soon after the 9/11 attacks for statements critical of the president.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/28/us/a-nation-challenged-speech-and-expression-in-patriotic-time-dissent-is-muted.html |title=A National Challenged:Speech and Expression |publisher=Nytimes.com |date=2001-09-28 |accessdate=2011-05-28 |first1=Bill |last1=Carter |first2=Felicity |last2=Barringer}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Linguistic examples of right-wing adjustments to language criticized as examples of political correctness include renaming [[French fries]] “[[Freedom fries]]”.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url= http://www.parisvoice.com/voicearchives/03/apr/html/tips/tips1.html | title = Freedom fries and French toast}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004, then [[Australia]]n Labor leader [[Mark Latham]] described conservative calls for &quot;civility&quot; as &quot;The New Political Correctness&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.australianpolitics.com/news/2002/08/02-08-26.shtml |title=The New Political Correctness: Speech By Mark Latham [August 26, 2002&amp;#93; |publisher=Australianpolitics.com |date= |accessdate=June 1, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Satirical use==
Political correctness often is satirized, for example in the ''Politically Correct Manifesto'' (1992), by Saul Jerushalmy and Rens Zbignieuw X,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fiction.net/tidbits/politics/pc.html |title=TidBits: The PC Manifesto |publisher=Fiction.net |date= |accessdate=June 1, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''[[Politically Correct Bedtime Stories]]'' (1994), by [[James Finn Garner]], presenting [[fairy tale]]s re-written from an exaggerated PC perspective.

Other examples include the television program ''[[Politically Incorrect]]'', [[George Carlin]]’s &quot;Euphemisms&quot; routine, and ''The Politically Correct Scrapbook''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.capc.co.uk/PC%20_Scrapbook_Main.htm |title=Book - Buy Now |publisher=Capc.co.uk |date= |accessdate=June 1, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The popularity of the ''[[South Park]]'' cartoon program led to the creation of the term ''[[South Park Republican]]'' by [[Andrew Sullivan]], and later the book ''[[South Park Conservatives]]'' by [[Brian C. Anderson]].&lt;ref name = &quot;anderson&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal| last = Anderson | first = Brian C. | title = We're Not Losing the Culture Wars Anymore | url = http://www.city-journal.org/html/13_4_were_not_losing.html | date = Autumn 2003 | accessdate = November 9, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Replying to the “Freedom Fries” matter, wits suggested that the [[Eugene Fama|Fama-French]] model used in [[corporate finance]] be renamed the “Fama-Freedom” model.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://media.www.chibus.com/media/storage/paper408/news/2005/04/01/GsbNews/famaFrench.Model.Renamed.famaFreedom.Model-909279.shtml |title=&quot;Fama-French&quot; Model Renamed &quot;Fama-Freedom&quot; Model - GSB News, Chicago Business |accessdate=November 9, 2007 |work=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

British comedian [[Stewart Lee]] also satirized the oft-used phrase of criticism for political correctness: &quot;it's political correctness gone mad&quot;. In which Lee, himself, criticized people for overusing this phrase without even understanding the concept of political correctness (including many people's confusion of it with [[Health &amp; Safety]] laws). He in particular criticized [[The Daily Mail|Daily Mail]] columnist [[Richard Littlejohn]] for his overzealous use of the phrase.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Sean O'Hagan |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/culture/2009/dec/06/stewart-lee-comedy-interview |title=The Guardian Online - Stewart lee Interview |publisher=Guardian |date= December 6, 2009|accessdate=2011-05-28 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{portal|conservatism}}
* [[Anti-racist mathematics]]
* [[Christmas controversy]]
* [[Common Era]]
* [[Euphemism Treadmill]]
* [[Hate speech]]
* [[Identity Politics]]
* [[Kotobagari]], a similar concept in the [[Japanese language]]
* [[Logocracy]]
* [[Negative campaigning]]
* [[Newspeak]]
* [[Gender-neutral language]]; See [[Satiric misspelling]] ([[Alternative political spelling#&quot;@&quot; replacing &quot;A&quot; and/or &quot;O&quot;|Alternative political spelling]]) for a Spanish-language example.
* [[Pensée unique]]
* [[People-first language]]
* [[Political consciousness]]
* [[Politically Correct Bedtime Stories]]
* [[Power (communication)]]
* [[Push poll]]: push-polling
* [[Race-baiting]]
* [[Red-baiting]]
* [[Reverse discrimination]]
* [[Speech code]]
* [[Spin (public relations)|Spin]]
* [[Sprachregelung]]
* [[University of Pennsylvania controversies]]
* [[Wedge issue]] - wedge politics
* [[Xenocentrism]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* Aufderheide, Patricia. (ed.). 1992. Beyond P.C.: Toward a Politics of Understanding. Saint Paul, Minnesota: Graywolf Press.
* Berman, Paul. (ed.). 1992. Debating P.C.: The Controversy Over Political Correctness on College Campuses. New York, New York: Dell Publishing.

* [[David E. Bernstein]], [http://mason.gmu.edu/~dbernste/book/ &quot;You Can't Say That! The Growing Threat to Civil Liberties from Antidiscrimination Laws&quot;], Cato Institute 2003, 180 pages ISBN 1-930865-53-8
* [[William S. Lind]], [http://www.academia.org/lectures/lind1.html &quot;The Origins of Political Correctness&quot;], Accuracy in Academia, 2000.
* [[Nat Hentoff]], ''Free Speech for Me - But Not for Thee'', HarperCollins, 1992, ISBN 0-06-019006-X
* [[Diane Ravitch]], ''The Language Police: How Pressure Groups Restrict What Students Learn'', Knopf, 2003, hardcover, 255 page.
* Nigel Rees, ''The Politically Correct Phrasebook: what they say you can and cannot say in the 1990s'', Bloomsbury, 1993, 192 pages, ISBN 0-7475-1426-7
* [[Arthur Schlesinger Jr.]], ''The Disuniting of America: Reflections on a Multicultural Society'', W.W. Norton, 1998 revised edition, ISBN 0-393-31854-0
* Howard S. Schwartz, ''Revolt of the Primitive: An Inquiry into the Roots of Political Correctness'', Piscataway, NJ: Transaction Publishers, 2003 Revised Paperback Edition ISBN 0-7658-0537-5
* Howard S. Schwartz, ''Society against Itself: Political Correctness and Organizational Self-Destruction'', London: Karnac Books, 2010, ISBN 978-1-85575-763-9
*[http://www.sba.oakland.edu/faculty/schwartz/PCJABS.htm ''Psychodynamics of Political Correctness'' - Published in Journal of Applied Behavioural Science]
* Debra L. Schultz. 1993. ''To Reclaim a Legacy of Diversity: Analyzing the &quot;Political Correctness&quot; Debates in Higher Education.'' New York: National Council for Research on Women.
* Wilson, John. 1995. ''The Myth of Political Correctness: The Conservative Attack on High Education.'' Durham, North Carolina: Duke University Press.

==External links==
{{wiktionary|politically correct}}
*[http://politics.guardian.co.uk/columnist/story/0,9321,1293144,00.html Politically correct and proud of it Observer Special Report by Will Hutton]
*[http://www.linguistlist.org/issues/7/7-879.html Possible origins of the term at www.linguist.org]
*[http://www.lrb.co.uk/v27/n23/print/jone01_.html &quot;Shortcuts&quot;] by Thomas Jones, discusses the term &quot;political correctness&quot; in British discourse, ''[[London Review of Books]]'', December 1, 2005
*[http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-420729/Book-reveals-people-fall-foul-PC-police.html A list of examples cited by the Daily Mail of political correctness in the UK]


{{Discrimination}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Political Correctness}}
[[Category:Political correctness| ]]
[[Category:Etiquette]]
[[Category:Satire]]
[[Category:Sociolinguistics]]
[[Category:Postmodernism]]
[[Category:Pejoratives]]

[[ar:صواب سياسي]]
[[be:Палітычная карэктнасць]]
[[bg:Политическа коректност]]
[[bar:Politische Korrektheit]]
[[br:Dereadegezh politikel]]
[[ca:Correcció política]]
[[cs:Politická korektnost]]
[[da:Politisk korrekthed]]
[[de:Politische Korrektheit]]
[[et:Poliitiline korrektsus]]
[[el:Πολιτική ορθότητα]]
[[es:Corrección política]]
[[eo:Politika ĝusteco]]
[[fa:اظهارات سیاست‌پسند]]
[[fr:Politiquement correct]]
[[ko:정치적 올바름]]
[[hr:Politička ispravnost]]
[[is:Pólitískur rétttrúnaður]]
[[it:Politicamente corretto]]
[[he:תקינות פוליטית]]
[[la:Rectitudo politica]]
[[lb:Politesch Korrektheet]]
[[hu:Politikai korrektség]]
[[nl:Politieke correctheid]]
[[ja:ポリティカル・コレクトネス]]
[[no:Politisk korrekthet]]
[[pl:Poprawność polityczna]]
[[pt:Politicamente correto]]
[[ro:Corectitudine politică]]
[[ru:Политическая корректность]]
[[simple:Political correctness]]
[[sr:Politička korektnost]]
[[sh:Politička korektnost]]
[[fi:Poliittinen korrektius]]
[[sv:Politisk korrekthet]]
[[th:ความถูกต้องทางการเมือง]]
[[tr:Siyaseten doğruluk]]
[[uk:Політична коректність]]
[[zh:政治正確]]</text>
      <sha1>pmmiww36vdu59o7iz7gmwz9ko0ivcqj</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
