<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Racial quota</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>49444</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520124034</id>
      <parentid>520113850</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-27T15:20:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sjö</username>
        <id>202394</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 520113850 by [[Special:Contributions/Sikemafford|Sikemafford]] ([[User talk:Sikemafford|talk]]), rv,  POV and &quot;past&quot; is largely incorrect</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8492">{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Racial quotas''' in employment and education are numerical requirements for hiring, promoting, admitting and/or graduating members of a particular [[Race (classification of human beings)|racial group]]. Racial quotas are often established as means of diminishing racial [[discrimination]], addressing under-representation and evident [[racism]] against those racial groups. Some individuals consider racial quotas [[reverse racism]]. Racial quotas are closely linked to notions of [[group rights]], and [[special rights]].

These quotas may be determined by governmental authority and backed by governmental sanctions. When the total number of jobs or enrollment slots is fixed, this proportion may get translated to a specific number. In education, this kind of quota is also known as ''[[Numerus clausus]]''.

==History==
{{Globalize/US|section|date=July 2011}}
Racial quotas in the United States began to be implemented with government approval after the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]], especially during the 1970s.&lt;ref name=&quot;'80s 242&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= How We Got Here: The '60s|last= Frum|first= David|authorlink= David Frum|coauthors= |year= 2000|publisher= Basic Books|location= New York, New York|isbn= 0-465-04195-7|page= |pages= 242–244|url= }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Richard Nixon]]'s [[United States Secretary of Labor|Labor Secretary]] [[George P. Schultz]] demanded that anti-black construction unions allow a certain number of black people into the unions.&lt;ref name=&quot;'80s 242&quot;/&gt; The [[United States Department of Labor|Department of Labor]] began enforcing these quotas across the country.&lt;ref name=&quot;'70s 242&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= How We Got Here: The '70s|last= Frum|first= David|authorlink= David Frum|coauthors= |year= 2000|publisher= Basic Books|location= New York, New York|isbn= 0-465-04195-7|page= |pages= 242–244|url= }}&lt;/ref&gt; After a [[SCOTUS|Supreme Court]] case, ''[[Griggs v. Duke Power Company]]'', found that neutral application tests and procedures that still resulted in ''de facto'' segregation of employees (if previous discrimination had existed) were illegal, more companies began implementing quotas on their own.&lt;ref name=&quot;'70s 242&quot;/&gt;

In a 1973 court case, a federal judge created one of the first mandated quotas when he ruled that half of the [[Bridgeport, Connecticut]] Police Department's new employees must be either black or [[Puerto Rico|Puerto Rican]].&lt;ref name=&quot;'70s 242&quot;/&gt; In 1974, the [[United States Department of Justice|Department of Justice]] and the [[United Steelworkers of America]] came to an agreement on the largest-to-then quota program, for steel unions.&lt;ref name=&quot;'70s 242&quot;/&gt;

In 1978, the Supreme Court ruled in ''[[Bakke v. Regents]]'' that public universities (and other government institutions) could not set specific numerical targets based on race for admissions or employment.&lt;ref name=&quot;'80s 242&quot;/&gt; The Court said that &quot;goals&quot; and &quot;timetables&quot; for diversity could be set instead.&lt;ref name=&quot;'70s 242&quot;/&gt; A 1989 Supreme Court case, ''[[United Steelworkers v. Weber]]'', found that private employers could set rigid numerical quotas, if they chose to do so.&lt;ref name=&quot;'80s 242&quot;/&gt; In 1990, the Supreme Court found that a 10% racial quota for federal contractors was permitted.&lt;ref name=&quot;'70s 242&quot;/&gt;

Then in 1991, President [[George H. W. Bush]] made an attempt to abolish [[affirmative action]] altogether, maintaining that “any regulation, rule, enforcement practice or other aspect of these programs that mandates, encourages, or otherwise involves the use of quotas, preferences, set-asides or other devices on the basis of race, sex, religion or national origin are to be terminated as soon as is legally feasible.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;&lt;http://www.lexisnexis.com.proxy.longwood.edu/hottopics/lnacademic/&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; This claim led up to the creation of the [[Civil Rights Act of 1991]], however the document was not able to implement these changes. It only covered the terms for settling cases where discrimination has been confirmed to have occurred.&lt;ref&gt;http://finduslaw.com/civil_rights_act_of_1991_pub_l_102_166&lt;/ref&gt;

==Opposition==
{{See also|Meritocracy|Equality before the law}}
[[File:Protesto contra o sistema de cotas.jpg|thumb|right|160px|Students protesting against racial quotas in [[Brasília]], [[Brazil]]. The sign reads: &quot;Want the opening? Pass the [[Vestibular]]!&quot;]]
Opponents of quotas object that one group is favored at the expense of another whenever a quota is invoked (i.e., 8 out of 10 available positions) rather than factors such as grade point averages or test scores. They argue that using quotas displaces individuals that would normally be favored based on their individual achievements. Opponents of racial quotas believe that qualifications should be the only determining factor when competing for a job or admission to a school. This brings about the problem called &quot;[[reverse discrimination]]&quot; which causes the majority and sometimes more qualified individuals to lose out to a minority.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.businessdictionary.com/definition/reverse-discrimination.html&lt;/ref&gt; Another significant problem with racial quotas is the controversial process of reevaluating quota percentages after changes of racial ratios in a society{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}.

==Alternatives==
Advocates of affirmative action programs often deny that these programs involve quotas{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}, although some openly do, such as the admission program of the [[Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Jon|last=Jeter|title=Affirmative Action Debate Forces Brazil to Take Look in the Mirror|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn/A62685-2003Jun15?language=printer|publisher=[[The Washington Post]]|date=June 16, 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Advocates may regard the term &quot;racial quotas&quot; as particularly divisive in that it is assumed to be backed by the force of law to enable or disable certain linked programs or benefits based solely upon attainment of the one quota measure{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}.{{Clarify|what has this to do with &quot;Alternatives&quot;|date=June 2011}}

The law student organization [[Building a Better Legal Profession]] has developed a method to encourage politically liberal students to avoid [[law firms]] whose racial makeup is markedly different than that of the population as a whole. In an October 2007 press conference reported in ''[[The Wall Street Journal]]'',&lt;ref&gt;Amir Efrati, You Say You Want a Big-Law Revolution, Take II, &quot;Wall Street Journal&quot;, October 10, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; and the New York Times &lt;ref&gt; Adam Liptak, In Students’ Eyes, Look-Alike Lawyers Don’t Make the Grade, ''New York Times'', October 29, 2007, http://www.nytimes.com/2007/10/29/us/29bar.html?em&amp;ex=1193889600&amp;en=4b0cd84261ffe5b4&amp;ei=5087%0A&lt;/ref&gt; the group released data publicizing the numbers of African-Americans, Hispanics, and Asian-Americans at America's top law firms. The group has sent information to top law schools around the country, encouraging students who agree with this viewpoint to take the demographic data into account when choosing where to work after graduation.&lt;ref&gt; Henry Weinstein, Big L.A. law firms score low on diversity survey: The numbers of female, black, Latino, Asian and gay partners and associates lag significantly behind their representation in the city's population, according to a study, &quot;Los Angeles Times&quot;, October 11, 2007, http://www.latimes.com/news/local/la-me-diversity11oct11,1,661263.story?coll=la-headlines-california&lt;/ref&gt;  As more students choose where to work based on the firms' diversity rankings, firms face an increasing market pressure in order to attract top recruits.&lt;ref&gt; Thomas Adcock and Zusha Elinson, Student Group Grades Firms On Diversity, Pro Bono Work, &quot;New York Law Journal,&quot; October 19, 2007, http://www.law.com/jsp/nylj/PubArticleNY.jsp?hubtype=BackPage&amp;id=1192698212305&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Equality of opportunity]] vs [[Equality of outcome]]
* [[Racism]], [[Anti-racism]]
* [[Reverse discrimination]], [[Discrimination]]

'''Examples:'''
*[[Affirmative Action]]
*[[Diversity (business)]]
*[[Numerus clausus]]
*''[[Regents of the University of California v. Bakke]]''
*[[Reservation in India]]
*[[Reserved political positions]]

'''Related:'''
*[[All-women shortlists]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Racial Quota}}
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Affirmative action]]
[[Category:Quotas]]

[[fr:Quota ethnique]]
[[pt:Cota racial]]
[[ru:Расовая квота]]</text>
      <sha1>ox1j7o036z081wl47zcboelt9xbvztk</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
