<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Socialism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>26847</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520908082</id>
      <parentid>520901599</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-01T15:19:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Snowded</username>
        <id>1988889</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>not sure that really adds anything</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="133629">{{About|socialism as an economic system and political philosophy|socialism as a stage of economic development in Marxist theory|Socialism (Marxism)}}
{{Use British English|date=March 2012}}
{{pp-move|small=yes}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2012}}
{{Socialism sidebar}}

'''Socialism''' ({{IPAc-en|icon|ˈ|s|oʊ|ʃ|əɫ|ɪ|z|m̩}}) is an [[economic system]] characterised by [[social ownership]] of the [[means of production]] and co-operative management of the economy,&lt;ref&gt;
[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/551569/socialism ''socialism''] Britannica ACADEMIC EDITION. Retrieved 19 January 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; and a [[political philosophy]] advocating such a system. &quot;Social ownership&quot; may refer to [[cooperative]] enterprises, [[common ownership]], [[state ownership]], employee ownership, or citizen ownership of equity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= O'Hara|first= Phillip |title= Encyclopedia of Political Economy, Volume 2 |publisher= [[Routledge]]|year= 2003|month= September|isbn= 0-415-24187-1|page = 71|quote=In order of increasing decentralization (at least) three forms of socialized ownership can be distinguished: state-owned firms, employee-owned (or socially) owned firms, and citizen ownership of equity.}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are many varieties of socialism and there is no single definition encapsulating all of them.&lt;ref&gt;Peter Lamb, J. C. Docherty. ''Historical dictionary of socialism''. Lanham, Maryland, UK; Oxford, England, UK: Scarecrow Press, Inc, 2006. p. 1.&lt;/ref&gt; They differ in the type of social ownership they advocate, the degree to which they rely on [[Market socialism|markets]] or [[Economic planning|planning]], how management is to be organised within productive institutions, and the role of the state in constructing socialism.&lt;ref&gt;Nove, Alec. ''Socialism''. New Palgrave Dictionary of Economics, Second Edition (2008): http://www.dictionaryofeconomics.com/article?id=pde2008_S000173&lt;/ref&gt; 

A socialist economic system would consist of a system of production and distribution organized to directly satisfy economic demands and human needs, so that goods and services would be produced [[Production for use|directly for use]] instead of for private profit&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Socialism and Capitalism: Are They Qualitatively Different Socioeconomic Systems?&quot;, by Kotz, David M. Retrieved February 19, 2011, from University of Massachusetts: http://people.umass.edu/dmkotz/Soc_and_Cap_Diff_Syst_06_12.pdf: &quot;This understanding of socialism was held not just by revolutionary Marxist socialists but also by evolutionary socialists, Christian socialists, and even anarchists. At that time, there was also wide agreement about the basic institutions of the future socialist system: public ownership instead of private ownership of the means of production, economic planning instead of market forces, production for use instead of for profit.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;  driven by the [[Capital accumulation|accumulation of capital]]. Accounting would be based on [[Calculation in kind|physical quantities]], a common physical magnitude, or a direct measure of [[labour voucher|labour-time]] in place of financial calculation.&lt;ref&gt;''Market Socialism: The Debate Among Socialists'', by Schweickart, David; Lawler, James; Ticktin, Hillel; Ollman, Bertell. 1998. From &quot;The Difference Between Marxism and Market Socialism&quot; (P.61-63): &quot;More fundamentally, a socialist society must be one in which the economy is run on the principle of the direct satisfaction of human needs...Exchange-value, prices and so money are goals in themselves in a capitalist society or in any market. There is no necessary connection between the accumulation of capital or sums of money and human welfare. Under conditions of backwardness, the spur of money and the accumulation of wealth has led to a massive growth in industry and technology ... It seems an odd argument to say that a capitalist will only be efficient in producing use-value of a good quality when trying to make more money than the next capitalist. It would seem easier to rely on the planning of use-values in a rational way, which because there is no duplication, would be produced more cheaply and be of a higher quality.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Bockman|first= Johanna |title= Markets in the name of Socialism: The Left-Wing origins of Neoliberalism|publisher= Stanford University Press|year= 2011|month= |isbn= 978-0-8047-7566-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; Distribution of output would be based on the principle of [[to each according to his contribution|individual contribution]]. {{citation needed|date=October 2012}}

As a [[political movement]], socialism includes a diverse array of political philosophies, ranging from [[reformism]] to [[revolutionary socialism]]. Proponents of [[state socialism]] advocate the [[nationalisation]] of the means of production, distribution and exchange as a strategy for implementing socialism. In contrast, [[libertarian socialism]] proposes the traditional view of direct worker's control of the means of production and opposes the use of state power to achieve such an arrangement, opposing both parliamentary politics and state ownership over the means of production. [[Democratic socialism]] seeks to establish socialism through democratic processes and propagate its ideals within the context of a democratic system.

Modern socialism originated from an 18th-century intellectual and working class political movement that criticised the effects of [[industrialisation]] and [[private property]] on society. In the early 19th-century, &quot;socialism&quot; referred to any concern for the social problems of capitalism irrespective of the solutions to those problems. However, by the late 19th-century, &quot;socialism&quot; had come to signify opposition to capitalism and advocacy for an alternative system based on some form of social ownership.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Gasper|first= Phillip |title= The Communist Manifesto: a road map to history's most important political document |publisher=Haymarket Books|year= 2005|month= October|isbn= 1-931859-25-6|page = 24|quote=As the nineteenth century progressed, &quot;socialist&quot; came to signify not only concern with the social question, but opposition to capitalism and support for some form of social ownership.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Orthodox [[Marxism|Marxist]]s later considered scientific [[program evaluation|assessment]] and democratic [[Planned economy|planning]] to be critical elements of socialism. In the late 20th century, the term &quot;socialist&quot; has also been used by [[Third way]] [[Social democracy|social democrats]] to refer to an ethical political doctrine focusing on a common set of values emphasizing social cooperation, universal welfare, and equality.&lt;ref&gt;Anthony Giddens. ''Beyond Left and Right: The Future of Radical Politics''. 1998 edition. Cambridge, England, UK: Polity Press, 1994, 1998. Pp. 71.&lt;/ref&gt; It is used in this way by Third Way proponent [[Anthony Giddens]], who rejects conventional definitions and implementations of socialism.&lt;ref&gt;Anthony Giddens. ''Beyond Left and Right: The Future of Radical Politics''. 1998 edition. Cambridge, England, UK: Polity Press, 1994, 1998. Pp. 71.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the course of the [[20th century]], states run by [[Marxist-Leninist]] parties implemented various economic systems. The [[Soviet Union]] and the [[Eastern Bloc]] established [[Planned economy|centrally-planned economies]], while [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]] instituted a form of [[Autogestion|self-managed]] [[market socialism]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Market socialism,&quot; ''Dictionary of the Social Sciences''. Craig Calhoun, ed. Oxford University Press 2002; and &quot;Market socialism&quot; ''The Concise Oxford Dictionary of Politics''. Ed. Iain McLean and Alistair McMillan. Oxford University Press, 2003. See also [[Joseph Stiglitz]], &quot;Whither Socialism?&quot; Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1995 for a recent analysis of the market socialism model of mid–20th century economists [[Oskar R. Lange]], [[Abba P. Lerner]], and [[Fred M. Taylor]].&lt;/ref&gt; Following the collapse of the Eastern bloc, China and Vietnam implemented reforms that culminated in a model called the [[socialist market economy]], which consists of state-ownership and open-markets for both [[capital good]]s and consumer goods.

==Philosophy==
{{Further2|[[Socialist critique of capitalism]]}}
Socialists adhere to a diverse range of philosophical views. Marxian socialism is philosophically [[materialist]] as well as having at its centre a commitment to [[historical materialism]]. Many forms of socialist theory hold that human behaviour is largely shaped by the social environment. In particular, Marxism and socialists inspired by Marxist theory, holds that social [[mores]], values, cultural traits and economic practices are social creations, and are not the result of an immutable [[natural law]].&lt;ref&gt;Ferri, Enrico, &quot;Socialism and Modern Science&quot;, in ''Evolution and Socialism'' (1912), p. 79:&lt;blockquote&gt; Upon what point are orthodox political economy and socialism in absolute conflict? Political economy has held and holds that the economic laws governing the production and distribution of wealth which it has established are natural laws ... not in the sense that they are laws naturally determined by the condition of the social organism (which would be correct), but that they are absolute laws, that is to say that they apply to humanity at all times and in all places, and consequently, that they are immutable in their principal points, though they may be subject to modification in details. Scientific socialism holds, the contrary, that the laws established by classical political economy, since the time of Adam Smith, are laws peculiar to the present period in the history of civilized humanity, and that they are, consequently, laws essentially relative to the period of their analysis and discovery.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; The ultimate goal for [[Marxism|Marxist]] socialists is the emancipation of labour from [[Marx's theory of alienation|alienating work]]. Marxists argue that freeing the individual from the necessity of performing alienating work in order to receive goods would allow people to pursue their own interests and develop their own talents without being coerced into performing labour for others. For Marxists, the stage of economic development in which this is possible, sometimes called pure communism, is contingent upon advances in the [[Productive forces|productive capabilities]] of society.

Socialists generally argue that capitalism concentrates [[Power (philosophy)|power]] and wealth within a small segment of society that controls the means of production and derives its wealth through a system of [[exploitation]]. This creates a stratified society based on [[Social equality|unequal]] social relations that fails to provide equal opportunities for every individual to maximise their potential,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|title=Socialism|year=2009|publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica|accessdate=14 October 2009|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/551569/socialism|quote=Socialists complain that capitalism necessarily leads to unfair and exploitative concentrations of wealth and power in the hands of the relative few who emerge victorious from free-market competition—people who then use their wealth and power to reinforce their dominance in society.}}&lt;/ref&gt; and does not utilise available technology and resources to their maximum potential in the interests of the public.&lt;ref&gt;Marx and Engels Selected Works, Lawrence and Wishart, 1968, p. 40. Capitalist property relations put a &quot;fetter&quot; on the productive forces.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Economics==
{{See also|Socialist economics|Production for use}}

The original conception of socialism was an economic system whereby production was organised in a way to directly produce goods and services for their utility (or use-value in classical and Marxian economics): the ''direct allocation'' of resources in terms of physical units as opposed to  financial calculation and the economic laws of capitalism (see: [[Law of value]]), often entailing the end of capitalistic economic categories such as [[renting|rent]], [[interest]], [[Profit (economics)|profit]] and [[money]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Bockman|first= Johanna |title= Markets in the name of Socialism: The Left-Wing origins of Neoliberalism|publisher= Stanford University Press|year= 2011|month= |isbn= 978-0-8047-7566-3|page = 20|quote= According to nineteenth-century socialist views, socialism would function without capitalist economic categories - such as money, prices, interest, profits and rent - and thus would function according to laws other than those described by current economic science. While some socialists recognized the need for money and prices at least during the transition from capitalism to socialism, socialists more commonly believed that the socialist economy would soon administratively mobilize the economy in physical units without the use of prices or money.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a fully developed socialist economy, production and balancing factor inputs with outputs becomes a technical process to be undertaken by engineers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Gregory and Stuart|first= Paul and Robert |title= Comparing Economic Systems in the Twenty-First Century, Seventh Edition: &quot;Socialist Economy&quot; |publisher=George Hoffman|year= 2004 |isbn= 0-618-26181-8|page = 117|quote=In such a setting, information problems are not serious, and engineers rather than economists can resolve the issue of factor proportions.}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

This is contrasted with capitalism, where production is carried out for profit, and is thus based upon ''indirect allocation'' because the production of utility is an indirect process. In an ideal capitalism based on [[perfect competition]], competitive pressures compel business enterprises to respond to the needs of consumers, so that the pursuit of profit approximates production for use through an indirect process (competitive pressures on private firms).

[[Market socialism]] refers to an array of different economic theories and systems that utilise the market mechanism to organise production and to allocate factor inputs among socially owned enterprises, with the economic surplus (profits) accruing to society in a [[social dividend]] as opposed to private capital owners.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= O'Hara|first= Phillip |title= Encyclopedia of Political Economy, Volume 2 |publisher= [[Routledge]]|year= 2003|month= September|isbn= 0-415-24187-1|page = 70|quote=Market socialism is a general designation for a number of models of economic systems. On the one hand, the market mechanism is utilized to distribute economic output, to organize production and to allocate factor inputs. On the other hand, the economic surplus accrues to society at large rather than to a class of private (capitalist) owners, through some form of collective, public or social ownership of capital.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Variations of market socialism include [[libertarianism|Libertarian]] proposals such as [[Mutualism (economic theory)|mutualism]], based on classical economics, and neoclassical economic models such as the [[Lange Model]].

The ownership of the [[means of production]] can be based on direct ownership by the users of the productive property through [[worker cooperative]]; or [[common ownership|commonly owned]] by all of society with management and control delegated to those who operate/use the means of production; or [[public ownership]] by a state apparatus. ''Public ownership'' may refer to the creation of [[state-owned enterprises]], [[nationalisation]], [[municipalisation]] or autonomous collective institutions. The fundamental feature of a socialist economy is that publicly owned, worker-run institutions produce goods and services in at least the ''[[Commanding Heights: The Battle for the World Economy|commanding heights]]'' of the economy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amazon.com/dp/product-description/068483569X |title=Excerpt from Commanding Heights |publisher=Amazon.com |accessdate=30 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Management and control over the activities of enterprises is based on [[Autogestion|self-management]] and self-governance, with equal power-relations in the workplace to maximise occupational autonomy. A socialist form of organisation would eliminate controlling hierarchies so that only a hierarchy based on technical knowledge in the workplace remains. Every member would have decision-making power in the firm and would be able to participate in establishing its overall policy objectives. The policies/goals would be carried out by the technical specialists that form the coordinating hierarchy of the firm, who would establish plans or directives for the work community to accomplish these goals.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Political Economy of Socialism, 1982. P.197&quot;&gt;''The Political Economy of Socialism'', by Horvat, Branko. 1982. (P.197): &quot;The sandglass (socialist) model is based on the observation that there are two fundamentally different spheres of activity or decision making. The first is concerned with value judgments, and consequently each individual counts as one in this sphere. In the second, technical decisions are made on the basis of technical competence and expertise. The decisions of the first sphere are policy directives; those of the second, technical directives. The former are based on political authority as exercised by all members of the organization; the latter, on professional authority specific to each member and growing out of the division of labor. Such an organization involves a clearly defined coordinating hierarchy but eliminates a power hierarchy.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

The role and use of [[money]] in a hypothetical socialist economy is a contested issue. Socialists including [[Karl Marx]], [[Robert Owen]], [[Pierre-Joseph Proudhon]] and [[John Stuart Mill]] advocated various forms of [[labour voucher]]s or labour-credits, which like money would be used to acquire articles of consumption, but unlike money, they are unable to become [[Financial capital|capital]] and would not be used to allocate resources within the production process. Bolshevik revolutionary [[Leon Trotsky]] argued that, following a socialist revolution, money could not be arbitrarily abolished. Money had to exhaust its &quot;historic mission&quot; (continue to be used until it became redundant), and then would be transformed into bookkeeping receipts for statisticians, and only in the more distant future would it might not be required even for that role.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marxists.org/archive/trotsky/1936/revbet/ch04.htm ''Leon Trotsky'' - The Revolution Betrayed. 1936] Full Text. Chapter 4: &quot;Having lost its ability to bring happiness or trample men in the dust, money will turn into mere bookkeeping receipts for the convenience of statisticians and for planning purposes. In the still more distant future, probably these receipts will not be needed.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quotation|&quot;I am convinced there is only one way to eliminate (the) grave evils (of capitalism), namely through the establishment of a socialist economy, accompanied by an educational system which would be oriented toward social goals. In such an economy, the means of production are owned by society itself and are utilized in a planned fashion. A planned economy, which adjusts production to the needs of the community, would distribute the work to be done among all those able to work and would guarantee a livelihood to every man, woman, and child. The education of the individual, in addition to promoting his own innate abilities, would attempt to develop in him a sense of responsibility for his fellow-men in place of the glorification of power and success in our present society.&quot;| [[Albert Einstein]], ''[[Why Socialism?]]'', 1949&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.monthlyreview.org/598einstein.php ''Why Socialism?''] by [[Albert Einstein]], ''[[Monthly Review]]'', May 1949&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Planned economy===
{{Main|Planned economy}}
A planned economy is a type of economy consisting of a mixture of public ownership of the means of production and the coordination of production and distribution through [[economic planning]]. There are two major types of planning: decentralized-planning and centralized-planning. [[Enrico Barone]] provided a comprehensive theoretical framework for a planned socialist economy. In his model, assuming perfect computation techniques, simultaneous equations relating inputs and outputs to ratios of equivalence would provide appropriate valuations in order to balance supply and demand.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Gregory and Stuart|first= Paul and Robert |title= Comparing Economic Systems in the Twenty-First Century, Seventh Edition |publisher=George Hoffman|year= 2004 |isbn= 0-618-26181-8|pages = 120–121}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

The most prominent example of a planned economy was the [[Economy of the Soviet Union|economic system of the Soviet Union]], and as such, the centralised-planned economic model is usually associated with the [[Communist states]] of the 20th century, where it was combined with a single-party political system. In a centrally planned economy, decisions regarding the quantity of goods and services to be produced are planned in advance by a planning agency. (See also: [[Analysis of Soviet-type economic planning]]). The economic systems of the Soviet Union and the [[Eastern Bloc]] are further classified as ''command economies'', which are defined as systems where economic coordination is undertaken by commands, directives and production targets.&lt;ref&gt;Ericson, Richard E. &quot;Command Economy&quot;. http://econ.la.psu.edu/~bickes/rickcommand.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; 
Studies by economists of various political persuasions on the actual functioning of the Soviet economy indicate that it was not actually a planned economy. Instead of conscious planning, the Soviet economy was based on a process whereby the plan was modified by localized agents and the original plans went largely unfulfilled. Planning agencies, ministries and enterprises all adapted and bargained with each other during the formulation of the plan as opposed to following a plan passed down from a higher authority, leading some economists to suggest that planning did not actually take place within the Soviet economy and that a better description would be an &quot;administered&quot; or &quot;managed&quot; economy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Nove|first= Alec |title= The Economics of Feasible Socialism, Revisited|publisher= Routledge|year= 1991|month= |isbn= 978-0043350492|page = 78|quote=Several authors of the most diverse political views have stated that there is in fact no planning in the Soviet Union: Eugene Zaleski, J. Wilhelm, Hillel Ticktin. They all in their very different ways note the fact that plans are often (usually) unfulfilled, that information flows are distorted, that plan-instructions are the subject of bargaining, that there are many distortions and inconsistencies, indeed that (as many sources attest) plans are frequently altered within the period to which they are supposed to apply...}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although central planning was largely supported by [[Marxist Leninist]]s, some factions within the Soviet Union before the rise of [[Stalinism]] held positions contrary to central planning. Leon Trotsky rejected central planning in favor of decentralized planning. He argued that central planners, regardless of their intellectual capacity, would be unable to effective coordinate all economic activity within an economy because they operated without the input and tacit knowledge embodied by the participation of the millions of people who in the economy. As a result, central planners would be unable to respond to local economic conditions.&lt;ref&gt;''Writings 1932–33, P.96'', Leon Trotsky.&lt;/ref&gt;

Various economists and [[Political economy|political theorists]], including [[Richard D. Wolff]] and [[Stephen Resnick]], have criticised the notion that the Soviet-style planned economies represented a type of socialist economy. This analysis highlights the fact that the Soviet economy was structured upon the [[Capital accumulation|accumulation of capital]] and the extraction of [[surplus value]] from the working class by the planning agency in order to reinvest the surplus in new production in a perpetual cycle – or to distribute to managers and senior officials in the form of bonuses, indicating the Soviet Union (and other Soviet-type economies) were in reality [[state capitalist]] economies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rdwolff.com/sites/default/files/attachment/4/State%20Capitalism%20versus%20Communism%20CS%202008.pdf |title=State Capitalism versus Communism: What happened in the USSR and PRC? |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=19 September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other socialists have focused their analyses on the lack of [[Workers' self-management|self-management]], the continued existence of financial calculation and the existence of a bureaucratic elite based on hierarchical and centralised powers of authority in the Soviet model, leading them to conclude that the Soviet system was not socialist, instead categorising it as [[bureaucratic collectivism]], [[state capitalism]] or [[deformed workers' state]]s.

===Self-managed economy===
{{See also|Decentralized planning|Workers' self-management}}
A self-managed, decentralised economy is based upon autonomous self-regulating economic units and a decentralised mechanism of resource allocation and decision-making. This model has found support in notable classical and neoclassical economists including [[Alfred Marshall]], [[John Stuart Mill]] and [[Jaroslav Vanek]]. There are numerous variations of self-management, including labour-managed firms and worker-managed firms. The  goals of self-management are to eliminate exploitation and reduce [[Social alienation|alienation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= O'Hara|first= Phillip |title= Encyclopedia of Political Economy, Volume 2 |publisher= Routledge|year= 2003|month= September|isbn= 0-415-24187-1|pages = 8–9|quote=One finds favorable opinions of cooperatives also among other great economists of the past, such as, for example, John Stuart Mill and Alfred Marshall...In eliminating the domination of capital over labor, firms run by workers eliminate capitalist exploitation and reduce alienation.}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

One such system is the cooperative economy, a largely free [[market economy]] in which workers manage the firms and democratically determine remuneration levels and labour divisions. Productive resources would be legally owned by the [[cooperative]] and rented to the workers, who would enjoy [[usufruct]] rights.&lt;ref&gt;Vanek, Jaroslav, ''The Participatory Economy'' (Ithaca, NY.: Cornell University Press, 1971).&lt;/ref&gt; Another form of decentralised planning is the use of [[cybernetics]], or the use of computers to manage the allocation of economic inputs. The socialist-run government of [[Salvador Allende]] in Chile experimented with [[Project Cybersyn]], a real-time information bridge between the government, state enterprises and consumers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cybersyn.cl/ingles/cybersyn/cybernet.html |title=:::::CYBERSYN/Cybernetic Synergy:::: |publisher=Cybersyn.cl |date= |accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another, more recent, variant is [[participatory economics]], wherein the economy is planned by decentralised councils of workers and consumers. Workers would be remunerated solely according to effort and sacrifice, so that those engaged in dangerous, uncomfortable, and strenuous work would receive the highest incomes and could thereby work less.&lt;ref&gt;[[Michael Albert]] and [[Robin Hahnel]], ''The Political Economy of Participatory Economics'' (Princeton, NJ.: Princeton University Press, 1991).&lt;/ref&gt; A contemporary model for a self-managed, non-market socialism is [[Pat Devine]]'s model of negotiated coordination. Negotiated coordination is based upon social ownership by those affected by the use of the assets involved, with decisions made by those at the most localised level of production.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gesd.free.fr/devine.pdf |title=Participatory Planning Through Negotiated Coordination |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Michel Bauwens]] identifies the emergence of the open software movement and [[Social peer-to-peer processes|peer-to-peer production]] as a new, alternative [[mode of production]] to the capitalist economy and centrally planned economy that is based on collaborative self-management, common ownership of resources, and the production of use-values through the free cooperation of producers who have access to distributed capital.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ctheory&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ctheory.net/articles.aspx?id=499  |title=The Political Economy of Peer Production|date=12 January 2005  |publisher=CTheory}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Anarchist communism]] is a theory of [[anarchism]] which advocates the abolition of the [[State (polity)|state]], [[private property]], and capitalism in favour of [[common ownership]] of the [[means of production]].&lt;ref name=Mayne&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=6MkTz6Rq7wUC&amp;pg=PA131&amp;dq=Communist+anarchism+belives+in+collective+ownership |title=From Politics Past to Politics Future: An Integrated Analysis of Current and Emergent Paradigms Alan James Mayne Published 1999 Greenwood Publishing Group 316 pages ISBN 0-275-96151-6 |publisher=Google Books |accessdate=20 September 2010|isbn=978-0-275-96151-0|year=1999}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=jeiudz5sBV4C&amp;pg=PA14 |title=Anarchism for Know-It-Alls|publisher=Filiquarian Publishing|year=2008|accessdate=20 September 2010|isbn=978-1-59986-218-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The economy of the former [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia]] established a system based on market-based allocation, social ownership of the means of production and self-management within firms. This system substituted Yugoslavia's Soviet-type central planning with a decentralized, self-managed system after reforms in 1953.&lt;ref&gt;Estrin, Saul. 1991. &quot;Yugoslavia: The Case of Self-Managing Market Socialism.&quot; Journal of Economic Perspectives, 5(4): 187–194.&lt;/ref&gt; Another practical example of worker's self-management was syndicalism as practiced in Catalonia during the Spanish Civil War.

===State-directed economy===
{{See also|State socialism}}
State socialism can be used to classify any variety of [[socialist]] philosophies that advocates the ownership of the [[means of production]] by the [[State (polity)|state apparatus]], either as a transitional stage between capitalism and socialism, or as an end-goal in itself. Typically it refers to a form of technocratic management, whereby technical specialists administer or manage economic enterprises on behalf of society (and the public interest) instead of workers' councils or workplace democracy.

A state-directed economy may refer to a type of mixed economy consisting of public ownership over large industries, as promoted by various Social democratic political parties during the 20th century. This ideology influenced the policies of the British Labour Party during Clement Attlee's administration. In the biography of the 1945 UK Labour Party Prime Minister [[Clement Attlee]], Francis Beckett states: &quot;the government... wanted what would become known as a mixed economy&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Beckett, Francis, ''Clem Attlee'', (2007) Politico's.&lt;/ref&gt;

Nationalisation in the UK was achieved through compulsory purchase of the industry (i.e. with compensation). [[British Aerospace]] was a combination of major aircraft companies [[British Aircraft Corporation]], [[Hawker Siddeley]] and others. [[British Shipbuilders]] was a combination of the major shipbuilding companies including [[Cammell Laird]], [[Govan Shipbuilders]], [[Swan Hunter]], and [[Yarrow Shipbuilders]]; the nationalisation of the coal mines in 1947 created a coal board charged with running the coal industry commercially so as to be able to meet the interest payable on the bonds which the former mine owners' shares had been converted into.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|authorlink=Socialist Party of Great Britain |author=Socialist Party of Great Britain |title=The Strike Weapon: Lessons of the Miners' Strike |publisher=Socialist Party of Great Britain |location=London |year=1985 |url=http://www.worldsocialism.org/spgb/pdf/ms.pdf |format=PDF |accessdate=28 April 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Hardcastle |first=Edgar |authorlink=Edgar Hardcastle |title=The Nationalisation of the Railways |journal=Socialist Standard |volume=43 |issue=1 |publisher=Socialist Party of Great Britain |year=1947 |url=http://www.marxists.org/archive/hardcastle/1947/02/railways.htm |accessdate=28 April 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Market socialism===
{{Main|Market socialism}}
Market socialism consists of publicly owned or cooperatively owned enterprises operating in a [[market economy]]. It is a system that utilises the market and [[Price system|monetary prices]] for the allocation and accounting of the [[means of production]], thereby retaining the process of [[capital accumulation]]. The profit generated would be used to directly remunerate employees or finance public institutions.&lt;ref&gt;''Comparing Economic Systems in the Twenty-First Century'', 2003, by Gregory and Stuart. ISBN 0-618-26181-8. (P.142): &quot;It is an economic system that combines social ownership of capital with market allocation of capital...The state owns the means of production, and returns accrue to society at large.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; In state-oriented forms of market socialism, in which state enterprises attempt to maximise profit, the profits can be used to fund government programs and services through a [[social dividend]], eliminating or greatly diminishing the need for various forms of taxation that exist in capitalist systems. The neoclassical economist [[Léon Walras]] believed that a socialist economy based on state ownership of land and natural resources would provide a means of public finance to make income taxes unnecessary.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Bockman|first= Johanna |title= Markets in the name of Socialism: The Left-Wing origins of Neoliberalism|publisher= Stanford University Press|year= 2011|month= |isbn= 978-0-8047-7566-3|page = 21|quote= For Walras, socialism would provide the necessary institutions for free competition and social justice. Socialism, in Walras's view, entailed state ownership of land and natural resources and the abolition of income taxes. As owner of land and natural resources, the state could then lease these resources to many individuals and groups, which would eliminate monopolies and thus enable free competition. The leasing of land and natural resources would also provide enough state revenue to make income taxes unnecessary, allowing a worker to invest his savings and become 'an owner or capitalist at the same time that he remains a worker.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Yugoslavia implemented a market socialist economy based on cooperatives and worker self-management.

The current economic system in China is formally referred to as a [[Socialist market economy with Chinese characteristics]]. It combines a large state sector that comprises the 'commanding heights' of the economy, which are guaranteed their public ownership status by law,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chinadaily.com.cn/china/2006-12/19/content_762056.htm |title=China names key industries for absolute state control |work=China Daily  |date=19 December 2006 |accessdate=2 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; with a private sector mainly engaged in commodity production and light industry responsible from anywhere between 33%&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=English@peopledaily.com.cn |url=http://english.people.com.cn/200507/13/eng20050713_195876.html |title=People's Daily Online – China has socialist market economy in place |publisher=English.people.com.cn |date=13 July 2005 |accessdate=2 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; (People's Daily Online 2005) to over 70% of GDP generated in 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oecd.org/dataoecd/16/3/36174313.pdf |title=CHINA AND THE OECD|date=May 2006|format=PDF |accessdate=2 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although there has been a rapid expansion of private-sector activity since the 1980s, privatisation of state assets was virtually halted and were partially reversed in 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Talent |first=Jim |url=http://www.heritage.org/Research/Reports/2010/01/10-China-Myths-for-the-New-Decade#_ftn23 |title=10 China Myths for the New Decade &amp;#124; The Heritage Foundation |publisher=Heritage.org |accessdate=2 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The current Chinese economy consists of 150 [[Corporatization|corporatised]] state-owned enterprises that report directly to China's central government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.forbes.com/2008/07/08/china-enterprises-state-lead-cx_jrw_0708mckinsey.html |title=Reassessing China's State-Owned Enterprises |work=Forbes |accessdate=2 June 2010 |date=8 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; By 2008, these state-owned corporations had become increasingly dynamic and generated large increases in revenue for the state,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://us.ft.com/ftgateway/superpage.ft?news_id=fto031620081407384075 |title=InfoViewer: China's champions: Why state ownership is no longer proving a dead hand |publisher=Us.ft.com |date=28 August 2003 |accessdate=2 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://ufirc.ou.edu/publications/Enterprises%20of%20China.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; resulting in a state-sector led recovery during the 2009 financial crises while accounting for most of China's economic growth.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/business/8153138.stm |work=BBC News  | title=China grows faster amid worries | date=16 July 2009 | accessdate=7 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the Chinese economic model is widely cited as a contemporary form of state capitalism, the major difference between Western capitalism and the Chinese model being the degree of state-ownership of shares in publicly listed corporations.

The Socialist Republic of Vietnam has adopted a similar model after the [[Doi Moi]] economic renovation, but slightly differs from the Chinese model in that the Vietnamese government retains firm control over the state sector and strategic industries, but allows for private-sector activity in commodity production.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vietnamembassy-usa.org/news/story.php?d=20031117235404 |title=VN Embassy : Socialist-oriented market economy: concept and development soluti |publisher=Vietnamembassy-usa.org |date=17 November 2003 |accessdate=2 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Social and Political theory==
In this context, ''socialism'' has been used to refer to a [[political movement]], a [[political philosophy]] and a hypothetical form of society these movements aim to achieve. As a result, in a political context socialism has come to refer to the strategy (for achieving a socialist society) or policies promoted by socialist organisations and socialist political parties; all of which have no connection to socialism as a socioeconomic system.

===Marxism===
{{Main|Marxism|Socialism (Marxism)}}
{{quotation|''&lt;small&gt;&quot;At a certain stage of development, the material productive forces of society come into conflict with the existing relations of production or – this merely expresses the same thing in legal terms&amp;nbsp;– with the property relations within the framework of which they have operated hitherto. Then begins an era of social revolution. The changes in the economic foundation lead sooner or later to the transformation of the whole immense superstructure.“&lt;/small&gt;'' -Karl Marx, [[Critique of the Gotha Program]]&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;}}

{{Marxism}}
[[File:Karl_Marx_001.jpg|thumb|left|160px|The writings of Karl Marx provided the basis for the development of Marxist political theory and Marxian economics.]]

In the most influential of all economic theories on socialist thought, [[Karl Marx]] and [[Friedrich Engels]] argued that socialism would emerge out of historical necessity as capitalism rendered itself obsolete and unsustainable from increasing internal contradictions emerging from the development of the [[productive forces]] and technology. It was these advances in the productive forces combined with the old [[social relations of production]] of capitalism that would generate contradictions, leading to working-class consciousness.&lt;ref name=&quot;ComparingEconomic&quot;&gt;''Comparing Economic Systems in the Twenty-First Century'', 2003, by Gregory and Stuart. P.62, ''Marx's Theory of Change''. ISBN 0-618-26181-8.&lt;/ref&gt;

Marx and Engels held the view that the consciousness of those who earn a wage or salary (the &quot;working class&quot; in the broadest Marxist sense) would be moulded by their &quot;conditions&quot; of &quot;wage-slavery&quot;, leading to a tendency to seek their freedom or &quot;emancipation&quot; by overthrowing ownership of the means of production by capitalists, and consequently, overthrowing the state that upheld this economic order. For Marx and Engels, conditions determine consciousness and ending the role of the capitalist class leads eventually to a classless society in which the state would wither away.

The Marxist conception of socialism is that of a specific historical phase that will displace capitalism and precede [[communism]]. The major characteristics of socialism (particularly as conceived by Marx and Engels after the [[Paris Commune]] of 1871) are that the [[proletariat]] will control the means of production through a [[socialist state|workers' state]] erected by the workers in their interests. Economic activity would still be organised through the use of incentive systems and social classes would still exist, but to a lesser and diminishing extent than under capitalism.

For orthodox Marxists, socialism is the lower stage of communism based on the principle of &quot;from each according to his ability, [[to each according to his contribution]]&quot; while upper stage communism is based on the principle of &quot;[[from each according to his ability, to each according to his need]]&quot;; the upper stage becoming possible only after the socialist stage further develops economic efficiency and the automation of production has led to a superabundance of goods and services.&lt;ref name=&quot;KS&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|last=Schaff |first=Kory |title=Philosophy and the problems of work: a reader |publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield |location=Lanham, Md |year=2001 |pages=[http://books.google.com/books?id=mdLh5EMehwgC&amp;pg=PA224&amp;dq=isbn=0742507955&amp;source=gbs_search_r&amp;cad=0_1&amp;sig=ACfU3U2S6uiRNCig9mq_bY4yKB7877tY4A 224] |isbn=0-7425-0795-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;WA&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|last=Walicki |first=Andrzej |title=Marxism and the leap to the kingdom of freedom: the rise and fall of the Communist utopia |publisher=Stanford University Press |location=Stanford, Calif |year=1995 |isbn=0-8047-2384-2 |page=95}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Marx argued that the material productive forces (in industry and commerce) brought into existence by capitalism predicated a cooperative society since production had become a mass social, collective activity of the working class to create commodities but with private ownership (the relations of production or property relations). This conflict between collective effort in large factories and private ownership would bring about a conscious desire in the working class to establish collective ownership commensurate with the collective efforts their daily experience.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;Karl Marx, Preface to A Contribution to the Critique of Political Economy, 1859&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Che Guevara]] and [[Mao Zedong]] sought socialism based on the rural peasantry rather than the urban working class. Che Guevara attempted to inspire the peasants of Bolivia by his own example into a change of consciousness. Guevara said in 1965:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Socialism cannot exist without a change in consciousness resulting in a new fraternal attitude toward humanity, both at an individual level, within the societies where socialism is being built or has been built, and on a world scale, with regard to all peoples suffering from [[imperialism|imperialist]] oppression.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marxists.org/archive/guevara/1965/02/24.htm &quot;At the Afro-Asian Conference in Algeria&quot;] speech by [[Che Guevara]] to the Second Economic Seminar of Afro-Asian Solidarity in Algiers, Algeria on 24 February 1965&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Evolutionary and Institutional economics===
[[Thorstein Veblen]], a leading American [[Institutional economics|institutionalist]] and [[Evolutionary economics|evolutionary economist]], argued that a subset of the working-class, the technical specialists and engineers, would become the driving force behind socioeconomic change within capitalism. There is an antagonism between industry and business, where industry refers to the process of producing goods and services and business is defined as the process of &quot;making money&quot;. Thorstein Veblen saw socialism as an immediate stage in an ongoing evolutionary process in economics that would result from the natural decay of the system of business enterprise. In contrast to Marx, he did not believe socialism would be the result of political struggle or political revolution by the working class as a whole and did not believe it to be the ultimate goal of humanity.&lt;ref&gt;The life of Thorstein Veblen and perspectives on his thought,
 {{Cite book
 |last= Wood |first= John |others= introd. Thorstein Veblen
 |title= The life of Thorstein Veblen and perspectives on his thought
 |edition= |series=
 |year= 1993 |origyear=
 |publisher=Routledge |location= New York |isbn= 0-415-07487-8 |oclc= |chapter= |chapterurl=
 |quote=The decisive difference between Marx and Veblen lay in their respective attitudes on socialism. For while Marx regarded socialism as the ultimate goal for civilization, Veblen saw socialism as but one stage in the economic evolution of society.|ref= P.369 |bibcode= |laysummary= |laydate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; But like Marx, Veblen saw technology as the underlying force driving social change.

[[Joseph Schumpeter]] viewed intellectuals and the intelligentsia as the group within society that would gradually move society toward socialism. Socialism would be partially a result of socio-economic evolution, the growth of workers' self-management, industrial democracy and social planning, and partially from political pressure on the part of intellectuals in Western society.&lt;ref&gt;John Medearis, &quot;Schumpeter, the New Deal, and Democracy&quot;, ''The American Political Science Review'', 1997.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Role of the state===
Socialists have different perspectives on the [[State (polity)|state]] and its role in revolutionary struggles, constructing socialism, and within an established socialist economy.

Preceding the Bolshevik-led revolution in Russia, many socialists, including [[Reformism|reformists]], [[orthodox Marxist]] currents such as council communism and the Mensheviks, and Anarchists / Libertarian socialists criticised the idea of using the state to conduct central planning and own the means of production as a way to establish socialism.&lt;ref&gt;An Outline on the History of Economic Thought,
 {{Cite book
 |last= Screpanti and Zamagni|first=  |others= 
 |title= An Outline on the History of Economic Thought
 |edition= 2nd |series=
 |year= 2005 |origyear=
 |publisher=Oxford |location=  |isbn=  |oclc= |chapter= |chapterurl=
 |quote= It should not be forgotten, however, that in the period of the Second International, some of the reformist currents of Marxism, as well as some of the extreme left-wing ones, not to speak of the anarchist groups, had already criticised the view that State ownership and central planning is the best road to socialism. But with the victory of Leninism in Russia, all dissent was silenced, and socialism became identified with ‘democratic centralism’, ‘central planning’, and State ownership of the means of production.|ref= P.295 |bibcode= |laysummary= |laydate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Joseph Schumpeter rejected the association of socialism and social ownership with state ownership over the means of production, because the state as it exists in its current form is a product of capitalist society and cannot be transplanted into a different institutional framework. Schumpeter argued that, just as there were different institutions within [[feudalism]], there will be different institutions with different functions within socialism. The state, along with the concept of [[Private property|property]] and [[taxation]], are concepts exclusive to commercial society (capitalism); placing them within the context of a future socialist society amounts to a distortion of these concepts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Schumpeter|first= Joseph |title= Capitalism, Socialism and Democracy |publisher= Harper Perennial|year= 2008|month= |isbn= 978-0-06-156161-0|page = 169|quote=But there are still others (concepts and institutions) which by virtue of their nature cannot stand transplantation and always carry the flavor of a particular institutional framework. It is extremely dangerous, in fact it amounts to a distortion of historical description, to use them beyond the social world or culture whose denizens they are. Now ownership or property -also, so I believe, taxation- are such denizens of the world of commercial society, exactly as knights and fiefs are denizens of the feudal world. But so is the state (a denizen of commercial society).}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Utopian versus scientific===
{{Main|Utopian socialism|Scientific socialism}}
Utopian socialism is a label ascribed to earlier socialists whose emphasis was on designing or imagining ideal forms of society. A utopian socialist is based on an [[idealist]] philosophy, where an ideal is envisioned and then worked towards, in contrast to Marxisms materialist methodology.

For Marxists, the development of capitalism in western Europe provided a material basis for the possibility of bringing about socialism because, according to the ''[[Communist Manifesto]]'', &quot;What the bourgeoisie produces above all is its own grave diggers&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Marx and Engels, Communist Manifesto&lt;/ref&gt; namely the working class, which must become conscious of the historical objectives set it by society. 

===Reform versus revolution===
{{Main|Revolutionary socialism|Reformism}}
Revolutionary socialists believe that a social revolution is necessary to effect structural changes to the socio-economic structure of society. Among revolutionary socialists there are differences in strategy, theory and the definition of &quot;revolution&quot;. Orthodox Maxists and Left Communists take an [[Impossibilism|Impossibilist]] stance, believing revolution should be spontaneous as a result of contradictions in society resulting from technological changes in the productive forces. In contrast, [[Marxist-Leninists]] and most [[Trotskyists]] advocate [[Vanguardism]]: the creation of a democratic centralist revolutionary Vanguard party led by a cadre of [[professional revolutionaries]] to overthrow the capitalist state and, eventually, the institution of the state altogether. &quot;Revolution&quot; is not necessarily defined by revolutionary socialists as violent insurrection,&lt;ref&gt;Schaff, Adam, 'Marxist Theory on Revolution and Violence', p. 263. in Journal of the history of ideas, Vol 34, no.2 (Apr–Jun 1973)&lt;/ref&gt; but as a complete dismantling and rapid transformation of all areas of class society led by the majority of the masses: the working class.

Reformism is generally associated with social democracy and [[gradualist]] democratic socialism. Reformism is the belief that socialists should stand in parliamentary elections within capitalist society, and if elected, utilize the [[machinery of government]] to pass political and social reforms for the purposes of ameliorating the instabilities and inequities of capitalism.

==Politics==
The major socialist political movements are described below. Independent socialist theorists, [[utopian socialist]] authors, and academic supporters of socialism may not be represented in these movements. Some political groups have called themselves socialist while holding views that some consider antithetical to socialism. The term ''socialist'' has also been used by some politicians on the [[right-wing politics|political right]] as an epithet against certain individuals who do not consider themselves to be socialists, and against policies that are not considered socialist by their proponents.

There are many variations of socialism and as such there is no single definition encapsulating all of socialism. However there have been common elements identified by scholars.&lt;ref&gt;Peter Lamb, J. C. Docherty. ''Historical dictionary of socialism''. Lanham, Maryland, UK; Oxford, England, UK: Scarecrow Press, Inc, 2006. pp. 1–3.&lt;/ref&gt; Angelo S. Rappoport in his ''Dictionary of Socialism'' (1924) analysed forty definitions of socialism to conclude that common elements of socialism include: general criticisms of the social effects of [[private ownership]] and control of capital - as being the cause of poverty, low wages, unemployment, economic and social inequality, and a lack of economic security; a general view that the solution to these problems is a form of collective control over the [[means of production]], [[Distribution (economics)|distribution]] and [[Means of exchange|exchange]] (the degree and means of control vary amongst socialist movements); agreement that the outcome of this collective control should be a society based upon [[social justice]], including social equality, economic protection of people, and should provide a more satisfying life for most people.&lt;ref&gt;Peter Lamb, J. C. Docherty. ''Historical dictionary of socialism''. Lanham, Maryland, UK; Oxford, England, UK: Scarecrow Press, Inc, 2006. pp. 1–2.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Bhikhu Parekh]] in ''The Concepts of Socialism'' (1975) identifies four core principles of socialism and particularly socialist society: sociality, social responsibility, cooperation, and planning.&lt;ref name=&quot;Peter Lamb 2006. p. 2&quot;&gt;Peter Lamb, J. C. Docherty. ''Historical dictionary of socialism''. Lanham, Maryland, UK; Oxford, England, UK: Scarecrow Press, Inc, 2006. p. 2.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Michael Freeden]] in his study ''Ideologies and Political Theory'' (1996) states that all socialists share five themes: the first is that socialism posits that society is more than a mere collection of individuals; second, that it considers human welfare a desirable objective; third, that it considers humans by nature to be active and productive; fourth, it holds the belief of human equality; and fifth, that history is progressive and will create positive change on the condition that humans work to achieve such change.&lt;ref name=&quot;Peter Lamb 2006. p. 2&quot;/&gt;

===Anarchism===
{{main|Anarchism}}
Anarchism features the political philosophy which holds the state to be undesirable, unnecessary, and harmful, that the state cannot be used to establish a socialist economy and proposes a political alternative based on federated decentralised autonomous communities. It includes proponents of both [[individualist anarchism]] and [[social anarchism]]. [[Mutualism (economic theory)|Mutualists]] advocate free-market socialism, [[collectivist anarchist]]s [[workers cooperative]]s and salaries based on the amount of time contributed to production, [[anarcho-communists]] advocate a direct transition from capitalism to [[libertarian communism]] and [[anarcho-syndicalist]]s worker's [[direct action]] and the [[general strike]].

===Libertarian socialism===
{{main|Libertarian socialism}}
Libertarian socialism is a non-hierarchical, non-bureaucratic, [[stateless society]] without private property in the [[means of production]]. Libertarian socialists oppose all coercive forms of social organisation, promote [[Free association (communism and anarchism)|free association]] in place of government, and oppose the coercive social relations of capitalism, such as [[wage labor]]. They oppose hierarchical leadership structures, such as vanguard parties, and most are opposed to [[State socialism|using the state to create socialism]]. Currents within libertarian socialism include Marxist tendencies such as [[left communism]], [[council communism]] and [[autonomism]], as well as non-Marxist movements such as [[left anarchism]], [[Communalism (political philosophy)|Communalism]], [[Participism]], and [[Inclusive Democracy]].

===Democratic socialism===
{{main|Democratic socialism}}
Modern democratic socialism is a broad political movement that seeks to propagate the ideals of socialism within the context of a democratic system. Many democratic socialists support [[social democracy]] as a temporary measure to reform the current system, but others support more revolutionary tactics to establish socialism. Conversely, modern social democracy emphasises a program of gradual legislative reform of capitalism in order to make it more equitable and humane, while the theoretical end goal of building a socialist society is either completely forgotten or redefined in a pro-capitalist way. The two movements are widely similar both in terminology and in ideology, although there are a few key differences.

The major difference between social democracy and democratic socialism is the object of their politics: contemporary social democrats support a [[welfare state]] and unemployment insurance as a means to &quot;humanize&quot; capitalism, whereas democratic socialists seek to replace capitalism with a socialist economic system, arguing that any attempt to &quot;humanize&quot; capitalism through regulations and welfare policies would distort the market and create economic contradictions.&lt;ref&gt;Schweickart, David. ''Democratic Socialism''. Encyclopedia of Activism and Social Justice (2006): http://orion.it.luc.edu/~dschwei/demsoc.htm: &quot;Social democrats supported and tried to strengthen the basic institutions of the welfare state--pensions for all, public health care, public education, unemployment insurance.  They supported and tried to strengthen the labor movement.  The latter, as socialists, argued that capitalism could never be sufficiently humanized, and that trying to suppress the economic contradictions in one area would only see them emerge in a different guise elsewhere. (E.g., if you push unemployment too low, you'll get inflation; if job security is too strong, labor discipline breaks down; etc.)&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; 

Democratic socialism generally refers to any political movement that seeks to establish an economy based on [[economic democracy]] by and for the working class. Democratic socialists oppose [[democratic centralism]] and the revolutionary vanguard party of [[Leninism]]. Democratic socialism is difficult to define, and groups of scholars have radically different definitions for the term. Some definitions simply refer to all forms of socialism that follow an electoral, [[reformism|reformist]] or evolutionary path to socialism, rather than a revolutionary one.&lt;ref&gt;This definition is captured in this statement: [[Anthony Crosland]] &quot;argued that the socialisms of the pre-war world (not just that of the [[Marxist]]s, but of the democratic socialists too) were now increasingly irrelevant.&quot; (Chris Pierson, &quot;Lost property: What the Third Way lacks&quot;, ''Journal of Political Ideologies'' (June 2005), 10(2), 145–163 URL: http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/13569310500097265). Other texts which use the terms &quot;democratic socialism&quot; in this way include Malcolm Hamilton ''Democratic Socialism in Britain and Sweden'' (St Martin’s Press 1989).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Leninism===
{{main|Leninism}}
[[File:Lenin 1921.jpg|thumb|left|120px|Vladimir Lenin, 1921]]
{{quotation|''&lt;small&gt;&quot;We want to achieve a new and better order of society: in this new and better society there must be neither rich nor poor; all will have to work. Not a handful of rich people, but all the working people must enjoy the fruits of their common labour. Machines and other improvements must serve to ease the work of all and not to enable a few to grow rich at the expense of millions and tens of millions of people. This new and better society is called ''socialist society''. The teachings about this society are called 'socialism'.“&lt;/small&gt;'' -Vladimir Lenin, ''[http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1903/rp/1.htm &quot;To the Rural Poor&quot; (1903)]; ''Collected Works'', Vol 6, p. 366}}

[[Leninism]] is the revolutionary theories developed by [[Vladimir Lenin]], including the organizational principles of [[democratic centralism]], [[Vanguardism]] and the political theory of imperialism. Leninist theory postulates that, with the strongly determined will of the Bourgeoisie to establish [[Imperialism]], socialism will not arise spontaneously through the natural decay of capitalism, and that workers by themselves, who may be more or less sedated by reactionary propaganda, are unable to effectively organise and develop socialist [[Class consciousness|consciousness]], therefore requiring the leadership of a revolutionary vanguard organized on the basis of [[democratic centralism]]. As a result, Leninism promotes a [[Vanguard party]] in order to lead the working-class and peasants in a revolution. Because this revolution takes place in underdeveloped, largely pre-capitalist countries such as Russia, Leninism establishes a single-party, authoritarian state, justifying single-party control over the state and economy as a means to safeguard the [[Communist revolution|revolution]] against [[counter-revolutionary]] insurrection and foreign invasion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Flank|first= Lenny |title= Rise and Fall of the Leninist State: A Marxist History of the Soviet Union |publisher=Red and Black Publishers|year= 2008|month= August|isbn= 1-931859-25-6|page = 57|quote= Lenin defended his actions, arguing that the Revolution could be consolidated 'only through dictatorship, because the realization of the transformations immediately and unconditionally necessary for the proletariat and the peasantry will call forth the desperate resistance of the landlords, of the big bourgeoisie, and of Tsarism. Without dictatorship, it would be impossible to defeat counter-revolutionary efforts.}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Although the creation of a [[vanguard party]] was outlined by Marx and Engels in Chapter II: &quot;Proletarians and Communists&quot; of ''The Communist Manifesto'', Lenin modified this position my changing the role of the vanguards to [[Professional revolutionary|professional revolutionaries]], who were to hold power post-revolution and direct the national economy and society in developing world socialism. 

After disposing of the Bourgeois dictatorship through [[socialist revolution]], Leninists seek to create a [[socialist state]] in which the working class would be in power, which they see as being essential for laying the foundations for a transitional withering of the state towards communism (Stateless society). In this state, the vanguard party would act as a central nucleus in the organisation of socialist society, presiding over a [[Single-party state|single-party]] political system. Leninism rejects [[political pluralism]], seeing it as divisive and destructive. Instead, Leninism advocates the concept of [[democratic centralism]] as a process to ensure the voicing of concern and disagreement and to refine policy. Generally, the purpose of democratic centralism is &quot;diversity in ideas, unity in action.&quot;

Leninist revolutionary theory alongside [[Marxist economics|Marxist economic theory]] forms the ideology of [[Marxism-Leninism]]. After Lenin's death in 1924, Leninism branched into multiple (sometimes opposing) interpretations, including [[Trotskyism]], [[Stalinism]], and [[Maoism]].

===Religious socialism===
{{Main|Socialism and Islam|Christian socialism}}
Christian socialism is a broad concept involving an intertwining of the Christian religion with the politics and economic theories of socialism.

Islamic socialism is a term coined by various [[Muslim]] leaders to describe a more [[Spirituality|spiritual]] form of socialism. Muslim socialists believe that the teachings of the [[Qur'an]] and [[Muhammad]] are compatible with principles of [[social equality|equality]] and [[public ownership]] drawing inspiration from the early Medina welfare state established by the Prophet [[Muhammad]]. Muslim Socialists are more conservative than their western contemporaries and find their roots in [[Anti-imperialism]], [[anti-colonialism]] and [[Arab nationalism]]. Islamic Socialist leaders believe in Democracy and deriving legitimacy from public [[Mandate (politics)|mandate]] as opposed to religious texts.

Buddhist Socialism is another concept that seeks to reduce unnecessary consumption and create harmony while ensuring everyone's basic needs are met.{{cn|date=September 2012}}

===Social democracy===
{{main|Social democracy}}
Social democracy is not itself a socialist system. Rather, traditional [[social democrats]] advocated the creation of socialism through political reforms by operating within the existing political system of capitalism. The social democratic movement sought to elect socialists to political office to implement reforms. The modern social democratic movement has abandoned the goal of moving toward a socialist economy and instead advocates for social reforms to improve capitalism, such as a [[welfare state]] and unemployment benefits. It is best demonstrated by the economic format which has been used in Sweden, Denmark, Norway, and Finland in the past few decades.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sanders.senate.gov/legislation/issue/?id=55d57772-424b-409b-bf07-fc4895cb0455 |title=Legislation - Trade: Bernie Sanders - U.S. Senator for Vermont |publisher=Sanders.senate.gov |date= |accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; This approach has been called the [[Nordic model]].

In the late 20th century, the term &quot;socialist&quot; became used by [[Third Way]] [[Social democracy|social democrats]] to refer to a set of ethical ideals and values as opposed to a form of socio-economic system. It is used in this way by [[Anthony Giddens]], who rejects conventional definitions and implementations of socialism.&lt;ref&gt;Anthony Giddens. ''Beyond Left and Right: The Future of Radical Politics''. 1998 edition. Cambridge, England, UK: Polity Press, 1994, 1998. Pp. 71.&lt;/ref&gt; Giddens states: &quot;The only common characteristic of socialist doctrines is their ethical content.&quot; and says that &quot;Socialism is the pursuit of ideas of social cooperation, universal welfare, and equality - ideas brought together by a condemnation of the evils and injustices of capitalism&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Anthony Giddens. ''Beyond Left and Right: The Future of Radical Politics''. 1998 edition. Cambridge, England, UK: Polity Press, 1994, 1998. Pp. 71.&lt;/ref&gt; However Gidden's Third Way has faced condemnation by left-wing opponents, including anti-Third Way social democrats who denounce Giddens' Third Way for being anti-socialist and pro-capitalist in practice.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hale155&quot;&gt;Sarah Hale, Will Leggett, Luke Martell. The Third Way and Beyond: Criticisms, Futures and Alternatives. Manchester University Press, 2004, p. 155.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Syndicalism===
{{main|Syndicalism}}
Syndicalism is a social movement that operates through industrial trade unions and rejects [[state socialism]] and the use of establishment politics to establish or promote socialism. They reject using state power to construct a socialist society, favoring strategies such as the [[General strike]]. Syndicalists advocate a socialist economy based on federated unions or syndicates of workers who own and manage the means of production.

Some Marxist currents advocate Syndicalism, such as [[DeLeonism]].

==History==
{{Main|History of socialism}}
The term socialism is attributed to [[Pierre Leroux]],&lt;ref&gt;Leroux: socialism is &quot;the doctrine which would not give up any of the principles of Liberty, Equality, Fraternity&quot; of the [[French Revolution]] of 1789. &quot;Individualism and socialism&quot; (1834)&lt;/ref&gt; and to [[Marie Roch Louis Reybaud]]; and in Britain to [[Robert Owen]] in 1827, father of the [[cooperative movement]].&lt;ref&gt;Oxford English Dictionary, etymology of socialism&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Russell, Bertrand (1972). A History of Western Philosophy. Touchstone. p. 781&lt;/ref&gt; Socialist models and ideas espousing common or public ownership have existed since antiquity. [[Mazdak]], a Persian communal proto-socialist,&lt;ref&gt;''A Short History of the World''. Progress Publishers. Moscow, 1974&lt;/ref&gt; instituted communal possessions and advocated the public good. And it has been claimed, though controversially, that there were elements of socialist thought in the politics of classical Greek philosophers [[Plato]]&lt;ref&gt;pp. 276–277, [[Alfred Edward Taylor|A.E. Taylor]], ''Plato: The Man and His Work'', Dover 2001.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Aristotle]].&lt;ref&gt;p. 257, [[W. D. Ross]], ''Aristotle'', 6th ed.&lt;/ref&gt;

The first advocates of socialism favoured social levelling in order to create a [[meritocratic]] or [[technocratic]] society based upon individual talent. Count [[Henri de Saint-Simon]] is regarded as the first individual to coin the term ''socialism''.&lt;ref name=&quot;fsmitha.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fsmitha.com/h3/h44-ph.html |title=Adam Smith |publisher=Fsmitha.com |accessdate=2 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Saint-Simon was fascinated by the enormous potential of science and technology and advocated a socialist society that would eliminate the disorderly aspects of capitalism and would be based upon equal opportunities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.anu.edu.au/polsci/marx/contemp/pamsetc/socfrombel/sfb_2.htm |title=2:BIRTH OF THE SOCIALIST IDEA |publisher=Anu.edu.au |accessdate=2 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{verify credibility|date=December 2011}} He advocated the creation of a society in which each person was ranked according to his or her capacities and rewarded according to his or her work.&lt;ref name=&quot;fsmitha.com&quot;/&gt; The key focus of Saint-Simon's socialism was on administrative efficiency and industrialism, and a belief that science was the key to progress.&lt;ref name=&quot;SocialismAVeryShortIntroduction&quot;&gt;''Newman, Michael''. (2005) ''Socialism: A Very Short Introduction'', Oxford University Press, ISBN 0-19-280431-6&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Hw-fourier.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Charles Fourier]], influential early French socialist thinker]]
This was accompanied by a desire to implement a rationally organised economy based on planning and geared towards large-scale scientific and material progress,&lt;ref name=&quot;fsmitha.com&quot;/&gt; and thus embodied a desire for a more directed or [[planned economy]]. Other early socialist thinkers, such as Thomas Hodgkin and Charles Hall, based their ideas on [[David Ricardo]]'s economic theories. They reasoned that the equilibrium value of commodities approximated to prices charged by the producer when those commodities were in elastic supply, and that these producer prices corresponded to the embodied labour – the cost of the labour (essentially the wages paid) that was required to produce the commodities. The Ricardian socialists viewed profit, interest and rent as deductions from this exchange-value.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cepa.newschool.edu/het/schools/utopia.htm |title=Utopian Socialists |publisher=Cepa.newschool.edu |accessdate=2 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

West European social critics, including [[Robert Owen]], [[Charles Fourier]], [[Pierre-Joseph Proudhon]], [[Louis Blanc]], [[Charles Hall (economist)|Charles Hall]] and [[Claude Henri de Rouvroy, Comte de Saint-Simon|Saint-Simon]], were the first modern socialists who criticised the excessive poverty and inequality of the [[Industrial Revolution]]. They advocated reform, with some such as Robert Owen advocating the transformation of society to small communities without private property. Robert Owen's contribution to modern socialism was his understanding that actions and characteristics of individuals were largely determined by the social environment they were raised in and exposed to.&lt;ref name=&quot;SocialismAVeryShortIntroduction&quot;/&gt; On the other hand [[Charles Fourier]] advocated [[Phalanstère|phalansteres]] which were communities that respected individual desires (including sexual preferences), affinities and creativity and saw that work has to be made enjoyable for people.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;In Fourier's system of Harmony all creative activity including industry, craft, agriculture, etc. will arise from liberated passion—this is the famous theory of &quot;attractive labor.&quot; Fourier sexualizes work itself—the life of the Phalanstery is a continual orgy of intense feeling, intellection, &amp; activity, a society of lovers &amp; wild enthusiasts....The Harmonian does not live with some 1600 people under one roof because of compulsion or altruism, but because of the sheer pleasure of all the social, sexual, economic, &quot;gastrosophic,&quot; cultural, &amp; creative relations this association allows &amp; encourages&quot;.[http://hermetic.com/bey/lemonade.html &quot;The Lemonade Ocean &amp; Modern Times A Position Paper by [[Hakim Bey]]]&lt;/ref&gt; The ideas of Owen and Fourier were tried in practice in numerous [[intentional communities]] around Europe and the American continent in the mid-19th century.

Linguistically, the contemporary connotation of the words ''socialism'' and ''communism'' accorded with the adherents' and opponents' cultural attitude towards religion. In Christian Europe, of the two, communism was believed the [[Atheism|atheist]] way of life. In Protestant England, the word ''communism'' was too culturally and aurally close to the Roman Catholic ''[[communion rite]]'', hence English atheists denoted themselves socialists.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
|last=Williams
|first=Raymond
|authorlink=Raymond Williams
|title=[[Keywords: A Vocabulary of Culture and Society|Keywords: a vocabulary of culture and society]]
|publisher=Fontana
|year=1976
|isbn=0-00-633479-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Friedrich Engels]] argued that in 1848, at the time when the ''[[Communist Manifesto]]'' was published, &quot;socialism was respectable on the continent, while communism was not.&quot; The [[Owenites]] in England and the [[Fourierists]] in France were considered &quot;respectable&quot; socialists, while working-class movements that &quot;proclaimed the necessity of total social change&quot; denoted themselves communists. This latter branch of socialism produced the communist work of [[Étienne Cabet]] in France and [[Wilhelm Weitling]] in Germany.&lt;ref&gt;Engels, Frederick, ''Preface to the 1888 English Edition of the Communist Manifesto, p. 202. Penguin (2002)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Etymology===
The term &quot;socialism&quot; was created by Henri de Saint-Simon, a founder of utopian socialism. The term &quot;socialism&quot; was created to contrast against the [[Liberalism|liberal]] doctrine of &quot;[[individualism]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Marvin Perry 1600, p. 540&quot;&gt;Marvin Perry, Myrna Chase, Margaret Jacob, James R. Jacob. ''Western Civilization: Ideas, Politics, and Society-From 1600, Volume 2''. Ninth Edition. Boston, Massachusetts, USA: Houghton Mifflin Harcourt Publishing Company, 2009. p. 540.&lt;/ref&gt; The original socialists condemned liberal individualism as failing to address social concerns of poverty, social oppression, and gross inequality of wealth.&lt;ref name=&quot;Marvin Perry 1600, p. 540&quot;/&gt; They viewed liberal individualism as degenerating society into supporting selfish [[Egotism|egoism]] and that harmed community life through promoting a society based on competition.&lt;ref name=&quot;Marvin Perry 1600, p. 540&quot;/&gt; They presented socialism as an alternative to liberal individualism, that advocated a society based on cooperation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Marvin Perry 1600, p. 540&quot;/&gt;

===First International and Second International===
[[File:Bakunin speaking.png|thumb|[[Mikhail Bakunin]] speaking to members of the [[International Workingmen's Association|IWA]] at the Basel Congress in 1869]]
The [[International Workingmen's Association]] (IWA), also known as the First International, was founded in London in 1864. The IWA held a preliminary conference in 1865, and had its first congress at [[Geneva]] in 1866. Due to the wide variety of philosophies present in the First International, there was conflict from the start. The first objections to Marx's came from the [[Mutualism (economic theory)|Mutualist]]s who opposed communism and [[statism]]. However, shortly after [[Mikhail Bakunin]] and his followers (called ''[[Collectivist anarchism|Collectivists]]'' while in the International) joined in 1868, the First International became polarised into two camps, with Marx and Bakunin as their respective figureheads.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;It is unnecessary to repeat the accounts of the Geneva and Hague Congresses of the International in which the issues between Marx and Bakunin were fought out and the organization itself split apart into the dying Marxist rump centered around the New York General Council and the anti-authoritarian majority centred around the Bakuninist Jura Federation. But it is desirable to consider some of the factors underlying the final emergence of a predominantly anarchist International in 1872.&quot;[[George Woodcock]]. ''Anarchism: A History of Libertarian Ideas and Movements'' (1962). p. 243.&lt;/ref&gt; The clearest differences between the groups emerged over their proposed strategies for achieving their visions of socialism. The First International became the first major international forum for the promulgation of socialist ideas.

As the ideas of Marx and Engels took on flesh, particularly in central Europe, socialists sought to unite in an international organisation. In 1889, on the centennial of the French Revolution of 1789, the [[Second International (politics)|Second International]] was founded, with 384 delegates from 20 countries representing about 300 labour and socialist organisations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marxisthistory.org/subject/usa/eam/secondinternational.html ''The Second (Socialist) International 1889–1923'']. Retrieved 12 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; It was termed the &quot;Socialist International&quot; and Engels was elected honorary president at the third congress in 1893. [[Anarchist]]s were ejected and not allowed in mainly because of the pressure from marxists.&lt;ref&gt;[[George Woodcock]]. ''Anarchism: A History of Libertarian Ideas and Movements'' (1962). pp. 263–264&lt;/ref&gt;

===Revolutions of 1917–1936===
[[File:1919-Trotsky Lenin Kamenev-Party-Congress.jpg|thumb|[[Leon Trotsky]], [[Vladimir Lenin]], and [[Lev Kamenev]] at the Second Communist Party Congress, 1919.]]
{{rquote|right|If Socialism can only be realized when the intellectual development of all the people permits it, then we shall not see Socialism for at least five hundred years.| [[Vladimir Lenin]], November 1917&lt;ref&gt;''Ten Days That Shook the World'', by John Reed, 2007, ISBN 1-4209-3025-7, p. 165&lt;/ref&gt;}}

By 1917, the patriotism of [[World War I]] changed into political [[Political radicalism|radicalism]] in most of Europe, the [[Socialism in the United States|United States]], and Australia. In February 1917, [[February Revolution|revolution exploded in Russia]]. Workers, soldiers and peasants established [[Soviet (council)|soviets]] (councils), the monarchy fell, and a [[Provisional Government of Russia, 1917|provisional government]] convoked pending the election of a [[constituent assembly]].

In April of that year, [[Vladimir Lenin]] arrived in Russia from Switzerland, calling for &quot;All power to the soviets.&quot; In October, his party, the [[Bolsheviks]], won support of most soviets at the second [[All-Russian Congress of Soviets]], while he and [[Leon Trotsky]] simultaneously led the [[October Revolution]]. As a matter of political pragmatism, Lenin reversed Marx's order of economics over politics, allowing for a political revolution led by a vanguard party of [[revolutionary|professional revolutionaries]] rather than a spontaneous establishment of socialist institutions led by a spontaneous uprising of the working class as predicted by [[Karl Marx]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/commandingheights/shared/minitextlo/ess_leninscritique.html |title='&amp;#39;Commanding Heights: Lenin's Critique of Global Capitalism |publisher=Pbs.org |accessdate=30 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 25 January 1918, at the [[Petrograd Soviet]], Lenin declared &quot;Long live the world socialist revolution!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Lenin, Vladimir. ''Meeting of the Petrograd Soviet of workers and soldiers' deputies 25 January 1918'', Collected works, Vol 26, p. 239. Lawrence and Wishart, (1964)&lt;/ref&gt; He proposed an immediate armistice on all fronts, and transferred the land of the landed proprietors, the crown and the monasteries to the peasant committees without compensation.&lt;ref&gt;Lenin, Vladimir. ''To workers Soldiers and Peasants'', Collected works, Vol 26, p. 247. Lawrence and Wishart, (1964)&lt;/ref&gt;

On 26 January 1918, the day after assuming executive power, Lenin wrote ''Draft Regulations on Workers' Control'', which granted workers control of businesses with more than five workers and office employees, and access to all books, documents and stocks, and whose decisions were to be &quot;binding upon the owners of the enterprises&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Lenin, Vladimir. ''Collected Works'', Vol 26, pp. 264–5. Lawrence and Wishart (1964)&lt;/ref&gt; Governing through the elected soviets, and in alliance with the peasant-based [[Left Socialist-Revolutionaries]], the Bolshevik government began nationalising banks, industry, and disavowed the national debts of the deposed [[Romanov]] royal régime. It [[Sue for peace|sued for peace]], withdrawing from World War I, and convoked a [[Constituent Assembly]] in which the peasant [[Socialist-Revolutionary Party]] (SR) won a majority.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|last=Caplan
|first=Brian
|title=Lenin and the First Communist Revolutions, IV
|publisher=George Mason University
|url=http://www.gmu.edu/departments/economics/bcaplan/museum/his1d.htm
|accessdate=14 February 2008}}
Strictly, the Right Socialist Revolutionaries won – the Left SRs were in alliance with the Bolsheviks.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Constituent Assembly elected Socialist-Revolutionary leader [[Victor Chernov]] President of a Russian republic, but rejected the Bolshevik proposal that it endorse the Soviet decrees on land, peace and workers' control, and acknowledge the power of the Soviets of Workers', Soldiers' and Peasants' Deputies. The next day, the Bolsheviks declared that the assembly was elected on outdated party lists,&lt;ref&gt;''Declaration of the RSDLP (Bolsheviks) group at the Constituent Assembly meeting 5 January 1918'' Lenin, ''Collected Works'', Vol 26, p. 429. Lawrence and Wishart (1964)&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[All-Russian Central Executive Committee]] of the Soviets dissolved it.&lt;ref&gt;''Draft Decree on the Dissolution of the Constituent Assembly'' Lenin, ''Collected Works'', Vol 26, p. 434. Lawrence and Wishart (1964)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Payne, Robert; &quot;The Life and Death of Lenin&quot;, Grafton: paperback, pp. 425–440&lt;/ref&gt;

The Bolshevik Russian Revolution of January 1918 engendered Communist parties worldwide, and their concomitant [[revolutions of 1917-23]]. Few Communists doubted that the Russian success of socialism depended upon successful, working-class socialist revolutions in developed capitalist countries.&lt;ref&gt;Bertil, Hessel, Introduction, ''Theses, Resolutions and Manifestos of the first four congresses of the Third International'', pxiii, Ink Links (1980)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;We have always proclaimed, and repeated, this elementary truth of Marxism, that the victory of socialism requires the joint efforts of workers in a number of advanced countries.&quot; Lenin, ''Sochineniya'' (Works), 5th ed. Vol. XLIV, p. 418, Feb 1922. (Quoted by Mosche Lewin in ''Lenin's Last Struggle'', p. 4. Pluto (1975))&lt;/ref&gt; In 1919, Lenin and Trotsky organised the world's Communist parties into a new international association of workers{{spaced ndash}}the [[Communist International]], (Comintern), also called the Third International.
[[File:Rosa Luxemburg.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Rosa Luxemburg]], prominent Marxist revolutionary, martyr and leader of the German [[Spartacist uprising]], 1919.]]

By 1920, the [[Red Army]], under its commander Trotsky, had largely defeated the royalist White Armies. In 1921, War Communism was ended and, under the [[New Economic Policy]] (NEP), private ownership was allowed for small and medium peasant enterprises. While industry remained largely state-controlled, Lenin acknowledged that the NEP was a necessary capitalist measure for a country unripe for socialism. Profiteering returned in the form of &quot;NEP men&quot; and rich peasants ([[Kulak]]s) gained power in the countryside.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.soviethistory.org/index.php?action=L2&amp;SubjectID=1924nepmen&amp;Year=1924 |title='&amp;#39;Soviet history: NEPmen'&amp;#39; |publisher=Soviethistory.org |accessdate=2 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1922, the fourth congress of the [[Communist International]] took up the policy of the [[United Front]], urging Communists to work with rank and file Social Democrats while remaining critical of their leaders, whom they criticised for betraying the working class by supporting the war efforts of their respective capitalist classes. For their part, the social democrats pointed to the dislocation caused by revolution, and later, the growing authoritarianism of the Communist Parties. When the [[Communist Party of Great Britain]] applied to affiliate to the [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]] in 1920 it was turned down.

In 1923, on seeing the Soviet State's growing coercive power, the dying Lenin said Russia had reverted to &quot;a bourgeois tsarist machine... barely varnished with socialism.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Victor Serge|Serge, Victor]], ''From Lenin to Stalin'', p. 55&lt;/ref&gt; After Lenin's death in January 1924, the [[Communist Party of the Soviet Union]] – then increasingly under the control of Joseph Stalin – rejected the theory that socialism could not be built solely in the Soviet Union, in favour of the concept of ''[[Socialism in One Country]]''. Despite the marginalised [[Left Opposition]]'s demand for the restoration of Soviet democracy, Stalin developed a bureaucratic, [[authoritarian]] government, that was condemned by democratic socialists, anarchists and [[Trotskyists]] for undermining the initial socialist ideals of the Bolshevik Russian Revolution.&lt;ref&gt;Serge, Victor, ''From Lenin to Stalin'', p. 52.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|last=Brinton
|first=Maurice
|authorlink=Maurice Brinton
|title=The Bolsheviks and Workers' Control 1917–1921 : The State and Counter-revolution
|publisher=[[Solidarity (UK)|Solidarity]]
|year=1975
|url=http://www.spunk.org/texts/places/russia/sp001861/bolintro.html
|accessdate=22 January 2007 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20061220120533/http://www.spunk.org/texts/places/russia/sp001861/bolintro.html |archivedate = 20 December 2006}}
&lt;/ref&gt;{{self-published inline|date=December 2011}}{{verify credibility|date=December 2011}}

The [[October revolution|Russian Revolution]] of October 1917 brought about the definitive ideological division between Communists as denoted with a capital &quot;С&quot; on the one hand and other communist and socialist trends such as [[Anarchist communism|anarcho-communists]] and social democrats, on the other. The [[Left Opposition]] in the Soviet Union gave rise to [[Trotskyism]] which was to remain isolated and insignificant for another fifty years, except in Sri Lanka, where Trotskyism gained the majority and the pro-Moscow wing was expelled from the Communist Party.

===After World War II===
[[File:JStalin Secretary general CCCP 1942.jpg|thumb|left|upright|[[Joseph Stalin]], leader of the Soviet Union from 1922 to 1953.]]

In 1951, British Health Minister [[Aneurin Bevan]] expressed the view that, &quot;It is probably true that Western Europe would have gone socialist after the war if Soviet behaviour had not given it too grim a visage. Soviet Communism and Socialism are not yet sufficiently distinguished in many minds.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Bevan, Aneurin, ''In Place of Fear'', pp. 63, 91&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1951, the [[Socialist International]] was re-founded by the European social democratic parties. It declared: &quot;Communism has split the International [[Labour Movement]] and has set back the realisation of Socialism in many countries for decades... Communism falsely claims a share in the Socialist tradition. In fact it has distorted that tradition beyond recognition. It has built up a rigid theology which is incompatible with the critical spirit of Marxism.&quot;&lt;ref name = &quot;socialist-Frankfurt Declaration&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.socialistinternational.org/viewArticle.cfm?ArticleID=39 |title=The Frankfurt Declaration |publisher=Socialistinternational.org |accessdate=2 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the postwar years, socialism became increasingly influential throughout the so-called [[Third World]]. Countries in Africa, Asia, and Latin America frequently nationalised industries held by foreign owners. The Soviet Union had become a superpower through its adoption of a planned economy, albeit at enormous human cost. This achievement seemed hugely impressive from the outside, and convinced many nationalists in the former colonies, not necessarily communists or even socialists, of the virtues of state planning and state-guided models of social development. 

====Union of Soviet Socialist Republics====
Prior to its dissolution in 1991, the USSR had [[economy of the Soviet Union|the second largest economy in the world]] after the United States.&lt;ref name=cia1990&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.umsl.edu/services/govdocs/wofact90/world12.txt|publisher=[[Central Intelligence Agency]]|accessdate=9 March 2008|title=1990 CIA World Factbook}}&lt;/ref&gt; The economy of the Soviet Union was the modern world's first centrally planned economy. It was based on a system of state ownership of industry managed through [[Gosplan]] (the State Planning Commission), [[Gosbank]] (the State Bank) and the [[Gossnab]] (State Commission for Materials and Equipment Supply). Economic planning was conducted through a series of [[Five-Year Plans for the National Economy of the Soviet Union|Five-Year Plans]]. The emphasis was put on a very fast development of heavy industry and the nation became one of the world's top manufacturers of a large number of basic and heavy industrial products, but it lagged behind in the output of light industrial production and consumer durables.

As the Soviet economy grew more complex, it required more and more complex disaggregation of control figures (plan targets) and factory inputs. As it required more communication between the enterprises and the planning ministries, and as the number of enterprises, trusts, and ministries multiplied, the Soviet economy started stagnating. The Soviet economy was increasingly sluggish when it came to responding to change, adapting cost−saving technologies, and providing incentives at all levels to improve growth, productivity and efficiency. 

Most information in the Soviet economy flowed from the top down and economic planning was often done based on faulty or outdated information, particularly in sectors with large numbers of consumers. As a result, some goods tended to be under-produced, leading to shortages, while other goods were overproduced and accumulated in storage. Some factories developed a system of barter and either exchanged or shared raw materials and parts, while consumers developed a black market for goods that were particularly sought after but constantly under-produced.

Conceding the weaknesses of their past approaches in solving new problems, the leaders of the late 1980s, headed by [[Mikhail Gorbachev]], were seeking to mould a program of economic reform to galvanise the economy. However, by 1990 the Soviet government had lost control over economic conditions. Government spending increased sharply as an increasing number of unprofitable enterprises required state support and consumer price subsidies to continue operations.

The industrial production system in the Soviet Union suffered a political and economic collapse in 1991, after which two transitions occurred: first from centrally planned to market-based economies, and secondly, from state-ownership to private-ownership of economic enterprises. With the collapse of the Soviet Union, the economic integration of the Soviet republics was dissolved, and overall industrial activity declined substantially.&lt;ref&gt;Oldfield, J.D. (2000) Structural economic change and the natural environment in the Russian Federation. Post-Communist Economies, 12(1): 77–90)&lt;/ref&gt; A lasting legacy remains in the physical infrastructure created during decades of combined industrial production practices.

====Social democrats in power====
{{Main|Social democracy|Welfare state|Nordic model}}
The [[Australian Labor Party]], the first social democratic labour party in the world, was formed in 1891. In 1904, Australians elected the first Labor Party prime minister in the world: Chris Watson. In 1945, the British [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]], led by [[Clement Attlee]], was elected to office based upon a radical socialist programme. Social Democratic parties dominated post-war politics in countries such as France, Italy, Czechoslovakia, Belgium and Norway. In Sweden, the [[Sveriges socialdemokratiska arbetareparti|Social Democratic Party]] held power from 1936 to 1976, 1982 to 1991, and 1994 to 2006. At one point, France claimed to be the world's most state-controlled capitalist country. The nationalised public utilities included Charbonnages de France (CDF), Electricité de France (EDF), Gaz de France (GDF), Air France, Banque de France, and Régie Nationale des Usines Renault.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sund.ac.uk/~os0tmc/contem/trente1.htm |title=Les trente glorieuses: 1945–1975 |publisher=Sund.ac.uk |date= |accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Post-World War II social democratic governments introduced social reform and [[wealth redistribution]] via state welfare and taxation.

=====United Kingdom=====
[[File:Attlee BW cropped.jpg|thumb|left|[[Clement Attlee]], U.K. Prime Minister, [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]] government, 1945–51.]]
In the UK, the Labour Party was influenced by the British social reformer [[William Beveridge]], who had identified five &quot;Giant Evils&quot; afflicting the working class of the pre-war period: &quot;want&quot; (poverty), disease, &quot;ignorance&quot; (lack of access to education), &quot;squalor&quot; ([[poor housing]]), and &quot;idleness&quot; (unemployment).&lt;ref&gt;Beckett, Francis, ''Clem Attlee''(Politico, 2007), p. 243.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Unemployment benefits]], [[national insurance]] and [[state pension]]s were introduced by the 1945 Labour government. [[Aneurin Bevan]], who had introduced the Labour Party's [[National Health Service]] in 1948, criticised the Attlee government for not progressing further, demanding economic planning and criticising the implementation of [[nationalisation]] for not empowering the workers with democratic control of operations.

The UK Labour Government nationalised major public utilities such as mines, gas, coal, electricity, rail, iron, steel, and the Bank of England. British Petroleum, privatised in 1987, was officially nationalised in 1951,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://yourarchives.nationalarchives.gov.uk/index.php?title=Nationalisation_of_Anglo-Iranian_Oil_Company%2C_1951 |title=Nationalisation of Anglo-Iranian Oil Company, 1951 |publisher=Yourarchives.nationalarchives.gov.uk |date=11 June 2007 |accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and there was further government intervention during the 1974–79 Labour Government&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The New Commanding Height: Labour Party Policy on North Sea Oil and Gas, 1964–74&quot; in ''Contemporary British History'', vol., Issue 1, Spring 2002, pp. 89–118.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Anthony Crosland]] said that in 1956, 25 per cent of British industry was nationalised, and that public employees, including those in nationalised industries, constituted a similar percentage of the country's total employed population.&lt;ref&gt;Crosland, Anthony, ''The Future of Socialism'', pp. 9, 89. (Constable, 2006)&lt;/ref&gt; The Labour government, however, did not seek to end capitalism, and the &quot;government had not the smallest intention of bringing in the 'common ownership of the means of production, distribution, and exchange'&quot;,&lt;ref name = &quot;Beckett-p243&quot;&gt;Beckett, Francis, ''Clem Attlee'', Politico, 2007, p. 243&lt;/ref&gt; Labour re-nationalised steel (1967, British Steel) after the Conservatives denationalised it, and nationalised car production (1976, British Leyland).&lt;ref&gt;http://www.uksteel.org.uk/history.htm&lt;/ref&gt; In 1977, major aircraft companies and shipbuilding were nationalised.

The National Health Service provided taxpayer-funded health care to everyone, free at the point of service.&lt;ref&gt;Bevan, Aneurin, ''In Place of Fear'', 2nd ed. (MacGibbon and Kee, 1961), p. 104&lt;/ref&gt; Working-class housing was provided in [[council housing]] estates, and university education became available via a school grant system. [[Ellen Wilkinson]], Minister for Education, introduced taxpayer-funded milk in schools, saying, in a 1946 Labour Party conference: &quot;Free milk will be provided in [[Hoxton]] and [[Shoreditch]], in [[Eton College|Eton]] and [[Harrow School|Harrow]]. What more social equality can you have than that?&quot; Clement Attlee's biographer argued that this policy &quot;contributed enormously to the defeat of childhood illnesses resulting from bad diet. Generations of poor children grew up stronger and healthier, because of this one, small, and inexpensive act of generosity, by the Attlee government&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Beckett, Francis, ''Clem Attlee'' (Politico's, 2007) p. 247.&lt;/ref&gt;

=====The &quot;Nordic model&quot;=====
{{Main|Nordic model}}
The Nordic model refers to the economic and [[social model]]s of the [[Nordic countries]] ([[Denmark]], [[Iceland]], [[Norway]], [[Sweden]] and [[Finland]]). This particular adaptation of the [[mixed economy|mixed market economy]] is characterised by more generous [[welfare states]] (relative to other developed countries), which are aimed specifically at enhancing individual autonomy, ensuring the universal provision of basic [[human rights]] and stabilising the economy. It is distinguished from other welfare states with similar goals by its emphasis on maximising labour force participation, promoting gender equality, [[egalitarianism|egalitarian]] and extensive benefit levels, large magnitude of redistribution, and liberal use of expansionary fiscal policy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Esping-Andersen&quot;&gt;Esping-Andersen, G. (1991). ''The three worlds of welfare capitalism''. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; This has included high degrees of [[labour union]] membership. In 2008, labour union density was 67.5% in Finland, 67.6% in Denmark, and 68.3% in Sweden. In comparison, union membership was 11.9% in the United States and 7.7% in France.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://stats.oecd.org/Index.aspx?DataSetCode=UN_DEN |title=Trade Union Density |publisher=OECD - StatExtracts. 2009.Stats.oecd.org |date= |accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Nordic Model, however, is not a single model with specific components or rules; each of the Nordic countries has its own economic and social models, sometimes with large differences from its neighbours.

====Social democrats adopt free market policies====
{{Main|Third Way (centrism)}}
Many social democratic parties, particularly after the Cold war, adopted [[Neoliberalism|neoliberal]]-based market policies that include [[privatisation]], [[liberalisation]], [[deregulation]] and [[financialisation]]; resulting in the abandonment of pursuing the development of moderate socialism in favour of [[market liberalism]]. Despite the name, these pro-capitalist policies are radically different from the many non-capitalist [[Market socialism|free-market socialist]] theories that have existed throughout history.

In 1959, the German [[Social Democratic Party of Germany|Social Democratic Party]] adopted the [[Godesberg Program]], rejecting [[class struggle]] and Marxism. In 1980, with the rise of conservative [[neoliberal]] politicians such as [[Ronald Reagan]] in the U.S., [[Margaret Thatcher]] in Britain, and [[Brian Mulroney]] in Canada, the Western welfare state was attacked from within. [[Monetarism|Monetarists]] and [[neoliberalism]] attacked social welfare systems as impediments to private entrepreneurship at public expense.

In the 1980s and 1990s, western European socialists were pressured to reconcile their socialist economic programmes with a free-market-based communal European economy. In the UK, the [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]] leader [[Neil Kinnock]] made a passionate and public attack against the party's [[Militant Tendency]] at a Labour Party conference, and repudiated the demands of the defeated striking miners after the [[UK miners' strike (1984–1985)|1984–1985 strike against pit closures]]. In 1989, at Stockholm, the 18th Congress of the Socialist International adopted a new ''Declaration of Principles'', saying:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Democratic socialism is an international movement for freedom, social justice, and solidarity. Its goal is to achieve a peaceful world where these basic values can be enhanced and where each individual can live a meaningful life with the full development of his or her personality and talents, and with the guarantee of human and civil rights in a democratic framework of society''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.socialistinternational.org/4Principles/dofpeng2.html Socialist International – Progressive Politics For A Fairer World]{{Dead link|date=June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In the 1990s, released from the Left's pressure, the British Labour Party, under [[Tony Blair]], posited policies based upon the free market economy to deliver public services via private contractors. In 1995, the Labour Party re-defined its stance on socialism by re-wording [[clause IV]] of its constitution, effectively rejecting socialism by removing any and all references to public, direct worker or municipal ownership of the means of production. In 1995, the British Labour Party revised its political aims: &quot;The Labour Party is a democratic socialist party. It believes that, by the strength of our common endeavour we achieve more than we achieve alone, so as to create, for each of us, the means to realise our true potential, and, for all of us, a community in which power, wealth, and opportunity are in the hands of the many, not the few.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.labour.org.uk/labour_policies |title=Labour Party Clause Four |publisher=Labour.org.uk |date=30 October 2008 |accessdate=2 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The objectives of the [[Party of European Socialists]], the European Parliament's socialist bloc, are now &quot;to pursue international aims in respect of the principles on which the European Union is based, namely principles of freedom, equality, solidarity, democracy, respect of Human Rights and Fundamental Freedoms, and respect for the Rule of Law.&quot; As a result, today, the rallying cry of the French Revolution – &quot;Egalité, Liberté, Fraternité&quot; – which overthrew absolutism and ushered industrialisation into French society, are promoted as essential socialist values.&lt;ref&gt;R Goodin and P Pettit (eds), ''A Companion to Contemporary political philosophy''&lt;/ref&gt;

===Early 2000s===
Those who championed socialism in its various Marxist and class struggle forms sought out other arenas than the parties of social democracy at the turn of the 21st century. [[Anti-capitalism]] and [[anti-globalization movement]]s rose to prominence particularly through events such as the opposition to the [[WTO meeting of 1999]] in Seattle. Socialist-inspired groups played an important role in these new movements, which nevertheless embraced much broader layers of the population, and were championed by figures such as [[Noam Chomsky]]. The [[2003 invasion of Iraq]] led to a significant [[anti-war]] movement in which socialists argued their case.

The [[Financial crisis of 2007–2010]] led to mainstream discussions as to whether &quot;Marx was right&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=|url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/politics/article4981065.ece |title=Karl Marx: did he get it all right?|publisher=The Times (UK) - Timesonline.co.uk |date= 21 October 2008 |accessdate=30 October 2011 |location=London |first=Deirdre |last=Hipwell}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Ian Bell |url=http://www.heraldscotland.com/capitalism-has-proven-karl-marx-right-again-1.889708 |title=Capitalism has proven Karl Marx right again |publisher=Herald Scotland |date=17 September 2008 |accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Time (magazine)|Time magazine]] ran an article 'Rethinking Marx' and put Karl Marx on the cover of its European edition in a special for the 28 January 2009 [[World Economic Forum#Annual meeting in Davos|Davos meeting]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Gumbel |first=Peter |url=http://www.time.com/time/specials/packages/article/0,28804,1873191_1873190_1873188,00.html |title=Rethinking Marx - World Economic Forum |publisher=TIME |date=29 January 2009 |accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=HumanProject |url=http://cogsciandtheworld.blogspot.com/2009/01/karl-marx-makes-cover-of-time-magazine.html |title=I married a communist: Karl Marx makes cover of TIME magazine |publisher=Cogsciandtheworld.blogspot.com |date=28 January 2009 |accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; A Globescan BBC poll on the twentieth anniversary of the fall of the Berlin Wall (2009) found that 23% of respondents believe capitalism is &quot;fatally flawed and a different economic system is needed&quot;, with that figure rising to over 40% of the population in France; while a majority of respondents including over 50% of Americans believe capitalism &quot;has problems that can be addressed through regulation and reform&quot;. Of the 27 countries polled, majorities in 22 of them expressed support for governments to distribute wealth more evenly.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/in_depth/8347409.stm |work=BBC News  | title=Free market flawed, says survey | date=9 November 2009 | accessdate=7 April 2010 | first=James | last=Robbins}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Africa====
{{Main|African socialism}}
[[File:1989 CPA 6101.jpg|upright|left|thumb|[[Kwame Nkrumah]], the first President of Ghana and theorist of [[African socialism]] on a soviet postage stamp]]African socialism has been and continues to be a major ideology around the continent. [[Julius Nyerere]] was inspired by [[Fabian socialist]] ideals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=rUdmyzkw9q4C&amp;pg=PA880#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false) |title=Encyclopedia of the Cold War|publisher=Books.google.co.uk |accessdate=30 November 2010|isbn=978-0-415-97515-5|date=15 May 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;  He was a firm believer in rural Africans and their traditions and [[ujamaa]], a system of collectivisation that according to Nyerere was present before European imperialism. Essentially he believed Africans were already socialists. Other African socialists include [[Jomo Kenyatta]], [[Kenneth Kaunda]], and [[Kwame Nkrumah]]. Fela Kuti was inspired by socialism and called for a democratic African republic. In South Africa the [[African National Congress]] (ANC) abandoned its partial socialist allegiances after taking power, and followed a standard neoliberal route. From 2005 through to 2007, the country was wracked by many thousands of protests from poor communities. One of these gave rise to a mass movement of shack dwellers, [[Abahlali baseMjondolo]] that, despite major police suppression, continues to work for popular people's planning and against the creation of a market economy in land and housing. Today many African countries have been accused of being exploited under neoliberal economics. 

In his classic, &quot;How Europe Underdeveloped Africa&quot; Walter Rodney says that Africa`s development can only be possible through its delinking with international capitalism and embracing a socialist template. 

&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.naomiklein.org/articles/2005/06/noose-not-bracelet |title=A Noose, Not A Bracelet |publisher=Naomi Klein |date=9 June 2005 |accessdate=30 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Asia====
The People's Republic of China, North Korea, Laos and Vietnam are Asian countries remaining from the wave of Marxism-Leninist implemented socialism in the 20th century. States with socialist economies have largely moved away from centralised economic planning in the 21st century, placing a greater emphasis on markets. Forms include the Chinese [[socialist market economy]] and the Vietnamese [[socialist-oriented market economy]]. They utilise [[State enterprise|state-owned corporate]] management models as opposed to modelling socialist enterprise on traditional management styles employed by government agencies.

In the People's Republic of China, the Chinese Communist Party has led a transition from the command economy of the Mao period to an economic program they term the [[socialist market economy]] or &quot;[[socialism with Chinese characteristics]]&quot;. Under [[Deng Xiaoping]], the leadership of China embarked upon a programme of market-based reform that was more sweeping than had been Soviet leader [[Mikhail Gorbachev|Mikhail Gorbachev's]] [[perestroika]] program of the late 1980s. Deng's programme, however, maintained state ownership rights over land, state or cooperative ownership of much of the heavy industrial and manufacturing sectors and state influence in the banking and financial sectors.

Elsewhere in Asia, some elected socialist parties and communist parties remain prominent, particularly in India and Nepal. The Communist Party of Nepal in particular calls for multi-party democracy, social equality, and economic prosperity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cpnm.org/ |title='&amp;#39;Communist Party of Nepal' '&amp;#39; |publisher=Cpnm.org |date=15 February 2010 |accessdate=2 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Singapore, a majority of the GDP is still generated from the state sector comprising government-linked companies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Wilkin |first=Sam |url=http://www.countryrisk.com/editorials/archives/cat_singapore.html |title=CountryRisk Maintaining Singapore's Miracle |publisher=Countryrisk.com |date=17 August 2004 |accessdate=2 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Japan, there has been a resurgent interest in the [[Japanese Communist Party]] among workers and youth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Demetriou |first=Danielle |url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/japan/3218944/Japans-young-turn-to-Communist-Party-as-they-decide-capitalism-has-let-them-down.html |title=Japan's young turn to Communist Party as they decide capitalism has let them down |publisher=Telegraph.co.uk |date=17 October 2008 |accessdate=30 October 2011 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/8027397.stm &quot;Communism on rise in recession-hit Japan&quot;], BBC, 4 May 2009&lt;/ref&gt; In Malaysia, the [[Socialist Party of Malaysia]] got its first Member of Parliament, [[Michael Jeyakumar Devaraj|Dr. Jeyakumar Devaraj]], after the [[Malaysian general election, 2008|2008 general election]].

====Europe====
In Europe, [[The Left (Germany)|the socialist Left Party]] in Germany grew in popularity&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wsws.org/articles/2008/feb2008/hess-f15.shtml |title='&amp;#39;Germany's Left Party woos the SPD' '&amp;#39; |publisher=Wsws.org |date=15 February 2008 |accessdate=2 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; due to dissatisfaction with the increasingly neoliberal policies of the SPD, becoming the fourth biggest party in parliament in the general election on 27 September 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=|url=http://www.greenleft.org.au/2009/813/41841 |title=Germany: Left makes big gains in poll &amp;#124; Green Left Weekly |publisher=Greenleft.org.au |date=10 October 2009 |accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Communist candidate [[Dimitris Christofias]] won a crucial presidential runoff in Cyprus, defeating his conservative rival with a majority of 53%.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.elpasotimes.com/nationworld/ci_835244 ''Christofias wins Cyprus presidency'']{{Dead link|date=June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Greece, in the general election on 17 June 2012, [[Coalition of the Radical Left]] (Syriza) won 26.89% of the votes and became the second largest party in parliament.

In Ireland, in the [[European Parliament election, 2009 (Ireland)|2009 European election]], [[Joe Higgins]] of the [[Socialist Party (Ireland)|Socialist Party]] took one of three seats in the capital [[Dublin (European Parliament constituency)|Dublin European constituency]]. In Denmark, the [[Socialist People's Party (Denmark)|Socialist People's Party]] (SF or Socialist Party for short) more than doubled its parliamentary representation to 23 seats from 11, making it the fourth largest party.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/7091941.stm |title=Danish centre-right wins election |publisher=BBC News |date=14 November 2007 |accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2011, the socialist parties of [[Social Democrats (Denmark)|Social Democrats]], [[Socialist People's Party (Denmark)|Socialist People's Party]] and the [[Danish Social Liberal Party (Denmark)|Danish Social Liberal Part]] formed government, after a slight victory over the liberal parties. They were led by Helle Thorning-Schmidt, and had the [[Red-Green Alliance (Denmark)|Red-Green Alliance]] as a supporting party.

In the UK, the [[National Union of Rail, Maritime and Transport Workers]] put forward a slate of candidates in the 2009 European Parliament elections under the banner of [[No to EU – Yes to Democracy]], a broad left-wing [[alter-globalisation]] coalition involving socialist groups such as the [[Socialist Party (England and Wales)|Socialist Party]], aiming to offer an alternative to the &quot;anti-foreigner&quot; and pro-business policies of the [[UK Independence Party]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Wheeler |first=Brian |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk_politics/8059281.stm |title=Crow launches NO2EU euro campaign |publisher=BBC News |date=22 May 2009 |accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dailyrecord.co.uk/news/scottish-news/2009/03/10/exclusive-tommy-sheridan-to-stand-for-euro-elections-86908-21185994/ |title=Exclusive: Tommy Sheridan to stand for Euro elections |publisher=The Daily Record |date= |accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rmt.org.uk/Templates/Internal.asp?NodeID=127346&amp;int1stParentNodeID=89731&amp;int2ndParentNodeID=89763 |title=Conference: Crisis in Working Class Representation |publisher=RMT |date= |accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the following May 2010 UK general election, the [[Trade Unionist and Socialist Coalition]], launched in January 2010&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.socialistparty.org.uk/issue/607/8673/12-01-2010/launch-of-trade-unionist-and-socialist-coalition |title=Launch of Trade Unionist and Socialist Coalition |publisher=Socialistparty.org.uk |date=12 January 2010 |accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and backed by Bob Crow, the leader of the National Union of Rail, Maritime and Transport Workers union (RMT), other union leaders and the Socialist Party among other socialist groups, stood against Labour in 40 constituencies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Hélène Mulholland |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/politics/blog/2010/mar/26/hard-left-tusc-unions-labour-general-election |title=Hard left Tusc coalition to stand against Labour in 40 constituencies|publisher=Guardian |date= 27 March 2010|accessdate=30 October 2011 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tusc.org.uk/ |title=Trade Unionist and Socialist Coalition |publisher=TUSC |date= |accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Trade Unionist and Socialist Coalition plans to contest the 2011 elections, having gained the endorsement of the RMT June 2010 conference.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.socialistparty.org.uk/articles/10228/15-09-2010/how-do-we-vote-to-stop-the-cuts |title=How do we vote to stop the cuts? |publisher=Socialist Party |date= |accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In France, the [[Revolutionary Communist League (France)|Revolutionary Communist League]] (LCR) candidate in the 2007 presidential election, [[Olivier Besancenot]], received 1,498,581 votes, 4.08%, double that of the Communist candidate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.socialismtoday.org/110/france.html |title=Has France moved to the right? |publisher=Socialism Today |date= |accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The LCR abolished itself in 2009 to initiate a broad anti-capitalist party, the [[New Anticapitalist Party]], whose stated aim is to &quot;build a new socialist, democratic perspective for the twenty-first century&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://www.lepoint.fr/actualites-politique/le-nouveau-parti-anticapitaliste-d-olivier-besancenot-est-lance/917/0/256540|title= Le Nouveau parti anticapitaliste d'Olivier Besancenot est lancé|agency=Agence France-Presse  |date= 29 June 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Latin America====
{{Main|Pink tide}}
[[File:HugoChavez1824.jpeg|thumb|[[Hugo Chávez]], president of Venezuela.]]

{{quote|&quot;Every factory must be a school to educate, like [[Che Guevara]] said, to produce not only briquettes, steel, and aluminum, but also, above all, the new man and woman, the new society, the socialist society.&quot;| [[Hugo Chávez]], at a May 2009 socialist transformation workshop&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.venezuelanalysis.com/news/4464 Venezuela Nationalizes Gas Plant and Steel Companies, Pledges Worker Control], by James Suggett, Venezuelanalysis.com, 22 May 2009&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Venezuelan President [[Hugo Chávez]], Nicaraguan President [[Daniel Ortega]], Bolivian President [[Evo Morales]], and Ecuadorian president [[Rafael Correa]] refer to their political programmes as socialist. Chávez has adopted the term ''[[socialism of the 21st century]]''. After winning re-election in December 2006, Chávez said, &quot;Now more than ever, I am obliged to move Venezuela's path towards socialism.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.voanews.com/english/2007-07-09-voa37.cfm ''Many Venezuelans Uncertain About Chávez' '21st century Socialism' '']{{dead link|date=October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hugo Chávez was also reelected in October 2012 for his third six-year term as President.

&quot;[[Pink tide]]&quot; is a term being used in contemporary 21st century [[Political science|political analysis]] in the media and elsewhere to describe the perception that [[leftism|Leftist]] ideology in general, and [[Left-wing politics]] in particular, are increasingly influential in Latin America.&lt;ref name=&quot;boston&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Gross |first=Neil |url=http://www.boston.com/news/globe/ideas/articles/2007/01/14/the_many_stripes_of_anti_americanism/ |title=The many stripes of anti-Americanism - The Boston Globe |publisher=Boston.com |date=14 January 2007 |accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/4311957.stm |title=South America's leftward sweep |publisher=BBC News |date=2 March 2005 |accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pitts&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=McNickle |first=Colin |url=http://www.pittsburghlive.com/x/pittsburghtrib/s_310062.html |title=Latin America's 'pragmatic' pink tide - Pittsburgh Tribune-Review |publisher=Pittsburghlive.com |date=6 March 2005 |accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====North America====
In Canada, the [[Co-operative Commonwealth Federation]], the precursor to the [[New Democratic Party]], had some significant success in provincial politics.  In 1944, the Saskatchewan CCF formed the first socialist government in North America. On the federal level, the social democratic [[New Democratic Party]] now forms the [[Official Opposition (Canada)]] after winning 102/308 seats (up from 37) in the [[2011 Canadian federal election]].

Socialist parties in the United States reached their zenith in the early 20th century, but currently active parties and organisations include the [[Socialist Party USA]], the [[Socialist Workers Party (United States)|Socialist Workers Party]] and the [[Democratic Socialists of America]], the latter having approximately 10,000 members.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.commondreams.org/view/2008/12/10-3 |title=Where Are All The Socialists? Here, There and Everywhere |work=[[Common Dreams NewsCenter|Common Dreams]] |date=10 December 2008 |accessdate=18 November 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticism of socialism==
{{Main|Criticisms of socialism}}

[[Economic liberalism|Economic liberals]] and pro-capitalist [[libertarianism|libertarians]] see [[Private enterprise|private ownership]] of the [[means of production]] and the market exchange as natural entities or moral rights, which are central to their conceptions of freedom and liberty; they thusly perceive [[public ownership]] of the means of production, [[cooperatives]] and economic planning as infringements upon liberty. Some of the primary criticisms of socialism are [[Economic calculation problem|distorted or absent price signals]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Mises&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title= Economic calculation in the Socialist Commonwealth|accessdate=8 September 2008|last= Von Mises|first= Ludwig|authorlink= Ludwig von Mises|year= 1990|format= PDF|publisher=[[Ludwig von Mises Institute]]|url= http://mises.org/pdf/econcalc.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;hayek&quot;&gt;F. A. Hayek, (1935), &quot;The Nature and History of the Problem&quot; and &quot;The Present State of the Debate,&quot; om in F. A. Hayek, ed. ''Collectivist Economic Planning'', pp. 1–40, 201–43.&lt;/ref&gt; reduced incentives,&lt;ref&gt;Zoltan J. Acs &amp; Bernard Young. ''Small and Medium-Sized Enterprises in the Global Economy. University of Michigan Press, p. 47, 1999.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mill, John Stuart. ''The Principles of Political Economy'', Book IV, Chapter 7.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;John Kenneth Galbraith, ''The Good Society: The Humane Agenda,'' (Boston, MA: Houghton Mifflin Co., 1996), 59–60.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; reduced prosperity,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mises.org/etexts/Soc&amp;Cap.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Ludwig von Mises]], ''[[Socialism (book)|Socialism: An Economic and Sociological Analysis]]'', Indianapolis, IN: Liberty Fund, Inc.. 1981, trans. J. Kahane, IV.30.21&lt;/ref&gt; feasibility,&lt;ref name=&quot;Mises&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;hayek&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;milton&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sangam.org/taraki/articles/2006/11-25_Friedman_MGR.php?uid=2075 |title=On Milton Friedman, MGR &amp; Annaism |publisher=Sangam.org |date= |accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and its social and political effects.&lt;ref&gt;F.A. Hayek. ''[http://www.mises.org/etexts/hayekintellectuals.pdf The Intellectuals and Socialism]''. (1949).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Alan O. Ebenstein. ''Friedrich Hayek: A Biography.'' (2003). University of Chicago Press. ISBN 0-226-18150-2 p. 137&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Friedrich Hayek|title=The Road to Serfdom|publisher=University Of Chicago Press|year=1944|isbn=0-226-32061-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Bellamy, Richard|title=The Cambridge History of Twentieth-Century Political Thought|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2003|isbn=0-521-56354-2|page=60}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Self&quot;&gt;Self, Peter. ''Socialism''. A Companion to Contemporary Political Philosophy, editors Goodin, Robert E. and Pettit, Philip. Blackwell Publishing, 1995, p. 339 &quot;Extreme equality overlooks the diversity of individual talents, tastes and needs, and save in a utopian society of unselfish individuals would entail strong coercion; but even short of this goal, there is the problem of giving reasonable recognition to different individual needs, tastes (for work or leisure) and talents. It is true therefore that beyond some point the pursuit of equality runs into controversial or contradictory criteria of need or merit.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

Critics from the [[neoclassical school]] of economics criticise [[State enterprise|state-ownership]] and centralisation of capital on the grounds that there is a lack of incentive in state institutions to act on information as efficiently as capitalist firms do because they lack [[Budget constraint|hard budget constraints]], resulting in reduced overall economic welfare for society.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Heilbroner |first=Robert |url=http://www.econlib.org/library/Enc/Socialism.html |title=Socialism: The Concise Encyclopedia of Economics &amp;#124; Library of Economics and Liberty |publisher=Econlib.org |date= |accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Economists of the [[Austrian school]] argue that socialist systems based on economic planning are unfeasible because they lack the information to perform economic calculation in the first place, due to a lack of price signals and a [[free price system]], which they argue are required for rational economic calculation.&lt;ref&gt;Ludwig Von Mises, Socialism, p. 119&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Wikipedia books}}
{{Portal|Socialism|Social movements}}
{{div col |colwidth=20em}}
*[[Collective farming]]
*[[Dictatorship of the proletariat]]
*[[History of socialism in Great Britain]]
*[[History of the socialist movement in the United States]]
*[[List of communist ideologies]]
*[[List of socialist countries]]
*[[List of socialist economists]]
*[[List of socialist songs]]
*[[Luxemburgism]]
*[[Nanosocialism]]
*[[Proletarian revolution]]
*[[Social democracy]]
*[[Socialism and social democracy in Canada]]
*[[Socialization (economics)|Socialization of production]]
*[[Third World Socialism]]
*[[Tragedy of the commons]]
*[[List of far-left parties with parliamentary representation]]
*[[Workers' self-management]]
{{div col end}}
{{-}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin|30em}}
* Sassoon, Donald. ''One Hundred Years of Socialism: The West European Left in the Twentieth Century''. New Press. 1998. ISBN 1-56584-486-6
* Guy Ankerl, ''Beyond Monopoly Capitalism and Monopoly Socialism'', Cambridge MA: Schenkman, 1978.
* Beckett, Francis, ''Clem Attlee'', Politico's (2007) 978-1842751923
* G.D.H. Cole, ''History of Socialist Thought, in 7 volumes'', Macmillan and St. Martin's Press, 1965; Palgrave Macmillan, 2003 reprint; 7 volumes, hardcover, 3160 pages, ISBN 1-4039-0264-X.
* [[Friedrich Engels]], ''Socialism: Utopian and Scientific'', Pathfinder; 2r.e. edition (December 1989) 978-0873485791
*Friedrich Engels, ''The Origin of the Family, Private Property and the State'', Zurich, 1884. {{LCC|HQ504 .E6}}
* Albert Fried and Ronald Sanders, eds., ''Socialist Thought: A Documentary History'', Garden City, NY: Doubleday Anchor, 1964. {{LCCN|64011312}}.
* [http://www.selvesandothers.org/view804.html Phil Gasper], ''The Communist Manifesto: A Road Map to History's Most Important Political Document'', [http://www.haymarketbooks.org/Merchant2/merchant.mv?Screen=PROD&amp;Store_Code=Haymarket&amp;Product_Code=MSACM Haymarket Books], paperback, 224 pp., 2005. ISBN 1-931859-25-6.
* [[Élie Halévy]], ''Histoire du Socialisme Européen''. Paris, Gallimard, 1948.
* [[Michael Harrington]], ''Socialism'', New York: Bantam, 1972. {{LCCN|76154260}}.
* [[Jesús Huerta de Soto]], [http://www.jesushuertadesoto.com/pdf_socialismo/indice.pdf ''Socialismo, cálculo económico y función empresarial''] (''Socialism, Economic Calculation, and Entrepreneurship''), Unión Editorial, 1992. ISBN 84-7209-420-0.
* Makoto Itoh, ''Political Economy of Socialism''. London: Macmillan, 1995. ISBN 0-333-55337-3.
*{{Cite book|last=Kitching |first=Gavin |authorlink=Gavin Kitching |title=Rethinking Socialism |publisher=Meuthen |year=1983 |url=http://www.gavinkitching.com/marx_0.htm |isbn=0-416-35840-3 }}
* [[Oskar Lange]], ''On the Economic Theory of Socialism'', Minneapolis, MN: University of Minnesota Press, 1938. {{LCCN|38012882}}.
* Michael Lebowitz, ''[http://www.monthlyreview.org/builditnow.htm Build It Now: Socialism for the 21st century]'', [http://www.monthlyreview.org Monthly Review Press], 2006. ISBN 1-58367-145-5.
* Marx, Engels, ''The Communist Manifesto'', Penguin Classics (2002) 978-0140447576
* Marx, Engels, ''Selected works in one volume'', Lawrence and Wishart (1968) 978-0853151814
* [[Ludwig von Mises]], ''[[Socialism: An Economic and Sociological Analysis]]'' {{cite web|url=http://www.mises.org/books/socialism/contents.aspx |title=Socialism by Ludwig von Mises |publisher=Mises.org |accessdate=2 June 2010}}, Liberty Fund, 1922. ISBN 0-913966-63-0.
* [[Joshua Muravchik]], [http://www.pbs.org/heavenonearth/resources.html ''Heaven on Earth: The Rise and Fall of Socialism''], San Francisco: Encounter Books, 2002. ISBN 1-893554-45-7.
* Michael Newman, ''Socialism: A Very Short Introduction'', Oxford University Press, 2005. ISBN 0-19-280431-6.
*[[Bertell Ollman]], ed., ''Market Socialism: The Debate among Socialists'', Routledge, 1998. ISBN 0-415-91967-3
*[[Leo Panitch]], ''Renewing Socialism: Democracy, Strategy, and Imagination''. ISBN 0-8133-9821-5.
*Emile Perreau-Saussine, ''[http://www.polis.cam.ac.uk/contacts/staff/eperreausaussine/what_is_left_of_socialism.pdf What remains of socialism?]'', in Patrick Riordan (dir.), Values in Public life: aspects of common goods (Berlin, LIT Verlag, 2007), pp.&amp;nbsp;11–34
*[[Richard Pipes]], ''Property and Freedom'', Vintage, 2000. ISBN 0-375-70447-7.
* John Barkley Rosser and Marina V. Rosser, ''Comparative Economics in a Transforming World Economy''. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2004. ISBN 978-0-262-18234-8.
* [[Maximilien Rubel]] and John Crump, ''Non-Market Socialism in the Nineteenth and Twentieth Centuries''. ISBN 0-312-00524-5.
* [[David Selbourne]], ''Against Socialist Illusion'', London, 1985. ISBN 0-333-37095-3.
* Katherine Verdery, ''What Was Socialism, What Comes Next'', Princeton. 1996. ISBN 0-691-01132-X
*{{cite web |url= http://www.econlib.org/library/YPDBooks/Shaw/shwFS1.html#The%20Basis%20of%20Socialism,%20Historic,%20by%20Sidney%20Webb | title =The Basis of Socialism – Historic | author=Sidney Webb |year = 1889 |publisher=Library of Economics and Liberty |authorlink= Sidney Webb, 1st Baron Passfield}}
* [[James Weinstein]], ''Long Detour: The History and Future of the American Left'', [http://www.westviewpress.com/about.html Westview Press], 2003, hardcover, 272 pages. ISBN 0-8133-4104-3.
* Peter Wilberg, [http://www.newgnosis.co.uk/deep.html ''Deep Socialism: A New Manifesto of Marxist Ethics and Economics''], 2003. ISBN 1-904519-02-4.
* [[Edmund Wilson]], ''To the Finland Station: A Study in the Writing and Acting of History'', Garden City, NY: Doubleday, 1940. {{LCCN|40034338}}.
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
* {{dmoz|Society/Politics/Socialism/|Socialism}}
* [http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1880/soc-utop/index.htm &quot;Socialism: Utopian and Scientific&quot;] by [[Friedrich Engels]]
* [http://monthlyreview.org/2009/05/01/why-socialism &quot;Why Socialism?&quot;] by Albert Einstein
* [http://libcom.org/library/soul-of-man-under-socialism-oscar-wilde &quot;The Soul of Man under Socialism&quot;] by [[Oscar Wilde]]
* [http://monthlyreview.org/091109magdoff-yates.php What Needs to be Done: A Socialist View] by Fred Magdoff and Michael D. Yates, ''[[Monthly Review]]'', November 2009
*[http://repository.library.georgetown.edu/handle/10822/552531 Cuban Socialism] from the [http://repository.library.georgetown.edu/handle/10822/552494 Dean Peter Krogh Foreign Affairs Digital Archives]
*[http://home.vicnet.net.au/~dmcm/ The Socialism Website]
* {{cite web|url=http://www.wsu.edu/~brians/hum_303/socialism.html |date=28 March 2005 |author=Paul Brians |title=Introduction to 19th-Century Socialism |publisher=Washington State University}}
* {{Cite EB1922|Socialism|author=[[G. D. H. Cole]]}}
* {{Cite NIE|Socialism|author=[[Richard T. Ely]]; [[Thomas Sewall Adams]]}}

{{Navboxes
|list =
{{Socialism}}
{{Socialism by state}}
{{Social and political philosophy}}
{{Political ideologies}}
{{History of economic thought}}
}}

[[Category:Article Feedback 5 Additional Articles]]
[[Category:Socialism| ]]
[[Category:Collectivism]]
[[Category:Economic ideologies]]
[[Category:Economies]]
[[Category:Left-wing politics| ]]
[[Category:Political ideologies]]
[[Category:Political movements]]

{{Link GA|is}}

[[af:Sosialisme]]
[[als:Sozialismus]]
[[ar:اشتراكية]]
[[an:Socialismo]]
[[ast:Socialismu]]
[[az:Sosializm]]
[[bn:সমাজতন্ত্র]]
[[zh-min-nan:Siā-hōe-chú-gī]]
[[be:Сацыялізм]]
[[be-x-old:Сацыялізм]]
[[bg:Социализъм]]
[[bs:Socijalizam]]
[[br:Sokialouriezh]]
[[ca:Socialisme]]
[[cs:Socialismus]]
[[cy:Sosialaeth]]
[[da:Socialisme]]
[[de:Sozialismus]]
[[et:Sotsialism]]
[[el:Σοσιαλισμός]]
[[eml:Sozialîsum]]
[[es:Socialismo]]
[[eo:Socialismo]]
[[eu:Sozialismo]]
[[fa:سوسیالیسم]]
[[hif:Samajwaad]]
[[fo:Sosialisma]]
[[fr:Socialisme]]
[[fy:Sosjalisme]]
[[ga:An sóisialachas]]
[[gd:Sòisealachd]]
[[gl:Socialismo]]
[[ko:사회주의]]
[[hi:समाजवाद]]
[[hr:Socijalizam]]
[[io:Socialismo]]
[[bpy:সমাজতন্ত্র]]
[[id:Sosialisme]]
[[ia:Socialismo]]
[[is:Jafnaðarstefna]]
[[it:Socialismo]]
[[he:סוציאליזם]]
[[jv:Sosialisme]]
[[kn:ಸಮಾಜವಾದ]]
[[krc:Социализм]]
[[ka:სოციალიზმი]]
[[kk:Социализм]]
[[ku:Sosyalîzm]]
[[ky:Социализм]]
[[la:Socialismus]]
[[lv:Sociālisms]]
[[lt:Socializmas]]
[[ln:Sosialisimɛ]]
[[jbo:cemtrusi'o]]
[[hu:Szocializmus]]
[[mk:Социјализам]]
[[ml:സോഷ്യലിസം]]
[[mr:समाजवाद]]
[[arz:اشتراكيه]]
[[mzn:سوسیالیسم]]
[[ms:Sosialisme]]
[[mwl:Socialismo]]
[[my:ဆိုရှယ်လစ်ဝါဒ]]
[[nl:Socialisme]]
[[ne:समाजवाद]]
[[ja:社会主義]]
[[no:Sosialisme]]
[[nn:Sosialisme]]
[[oc:Socialisme]]
[[pnb:سوشلزم]]
[[nds:Sozialismus]]
[[pl:Socjalizm]]
[[pt:Socialismo]]
[[ro:Socialism]]
[[qu:Susyalismu]]
[[rue:Соціалізм]]
[[ru:Социализм]]
[[sah:Социализм]]
[[se:Sosialisma]]
[[sco:Socialism]]
[[scn:Sucialìsimu]]
[[si:සමාජවාදය]]
[[simple:Socialism]]
[[sk:Socializmus]]
[[sl:Socializem]]
[[so:Hantiwadaag]]
[[ckb:سۆسیالیزم]]
[[sr:Социјализам]]
[[sh:Socijalizam]]
[[fi:Sosialismi]]
[[sv:Socialism]]
[[ta:சமவுடமை]]
[[th:สังคมนิยม]]
[[tr:Sosyalizm]]
[[uk:Соціалізм]]
[[ur:اشتراکیت]]
[[vec:Sociałismo]]
[[vi:Chủ nghĩa xã hội]]
[[fiu-vro:Sotsialism]]
[[war:Sosyalismo]]
[[yi:סאציאליזם]]
[[yo:Ìṣesósíálístì]]
[[zh-yue:社會主義]]
[[diq:Sosyalizm]]
[[bat-smg:Suocēlėzmos]]
[[zh:社会主义]]</text>
      <sha1>jq2su2dm8ojmly3v46ynbspuugfxds0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
