<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Syrian Social Nationalist Party</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1337691</id>
    <revision>
      <id>518185469</id>
      <parentid>518179742</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-16T20:39:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>RJFF</username>
        <id>13720831</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>rev: not according to the cited sources</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="34069">{{citations missing|date=August 2012}}
{{Infobox political party
| name               = Syrian Social Nationalist Party
| native_name        = الحزب السوري القومي الاجتماعي
| logo               = [[File:Logo of the Syrian Social Nationalist Party.svg|150px]]
| colorcode          = black
| party_wikicolourid =
| foundation         = 1932
| founder            = [[Antun Saadeh]]
|leader              = [[Lebanon]]: [[Assaad Hardan]]&lt;br&gt;[[Syria]]: [[Ali Haidar (politician)|Ali Haidar]]
| ideology           = [[Syrian nationalism]],&lt;br&gt;[[Nationalism|Social nationalism]],&lt;br&gt;[[Secularism]],&lt;br&gt;[[Anti-Zionism]]
| position           = [[Far-right politics|Far-right]]
| religion           = [[Secular]]
| colours            = [[Black]], [[Red]], [[White]]
| headquarters       = [[Beirut]], [[Lebanon]] &lt;br&gt; [[Damascus]], [[Syria]]
| newspaper           = [[Al-Binaa (newspaper)|Al-Binaa]]
| national = [[Popular Front for Change and Liberation]] (Syria) &lt;br&gt; [[March 8 Alliance]] (Lebanon)
| seats1_title       = [[Parliament of Syria]]
| seats1             = {{Infobox political party/seats|4|250|hex=black}}
| seats2_title       = [[Parliament of Lebanon]]
| seats2             = {{Infobox political party/seats|2|128|hex=black}}
|seats3_title        = [[Cabinet of Lebanon]]
|seats3              = {{Infobox political party/seats|1|30|hex=black}}
|seats4_title        = [[Cabinet of Syria]]
|seats4              = {{Infobox political party/seats|2|35|hex=black}}
| flag               = [[Image:Flag of the Syrian Social Nationalist Party.svg|200px]]
| website            = {{URL|http://www.alqawmi.info}} and {{URL|http://www.ssnp.net}}
| country            = Lebanon
| country2           = Syria
}}

The '''Syrian Social Nationalist Party''' ('''SSNP''') ({{lang-ar|الحزب السوري القومي الاجتماعي}}, [[Romanization of Arabic|transliterated]]: ''Al-Ḥizb Al-Sūrī Al-Qawmī Al-'Ijtimā'ī'', often referred to in [[French language|French]] as ''Parti populaire syrien'' or ''Parti social nationaliste syrien''), is a  [[Secular state|secular]] [[Nationalism|nationalist]] [[political party]] operating in [[Lebanon]], [[Syria]], [[Jordan]] and [[Palestinian territories]].It advocates the establishment of a [[Greater Syria|Syria]]n [[nation state]] spanning the [[Fertile Crescent]], including present day Syria, Lebanon, [[Iraq]], [[Jordan]], the [[Palestinian Territories]], [[Israel]],  [[Cyprus]], [[Kuwait]], [[Sinai]], southeastern [[Turkey]] and southwestern [[Iran]].&lt;ref&gt;Irwin, p. 24; [http://www.ssnp.com/new/about.htm ssnp.com] &quot;Our Syria has distinct natural boundaries…&quot; (accessed 30 June 2006).&lt;/ref&gt; It is the largest political group in Syria after the [[Arab Socialist Ba'ath Party – Syria Region|Arab Socialist Ba'ath Party]],&lt;ref&gt;http://www.debka.com/headline.php?hid=5425 The SSNP is now Syria’s largest party after the ruling Ba'ath.&lt;/ref&gt; with over 100,000 members. In Lebanon, it is part of the [[March 8 Alliance]].  

Founded in [[Beirut]] in 1932 as a [[Nationalism|national liberation]] organization hostile to [[French colonialism]], the party played a significant role in Lebanese politics and was involved in attempted coup d'etats in 1949 and 1961 following which it was thoroughly repressed. It was active in the [[Resistance movement|resistance]] against the Israeli invasion of Lebanon from 1982 to 2000 while continuously supporting the Syrian presence in Lebanon. In Syria, the SSNP became a major political force in the early 1950s, but was thoroughly repressed in 1955. It remained organised, and in 2005 was legalised and joined the Ba'ath Party-led [[National Progressive Front (Syria)|National Progressive Front]]. As of 2012, the party is part of the [[Popular Front for Change and Liberation]].

==Foundation and early years==

[[Image:Antun Saadeh.jpg|thumb|left|[[Antun Saadeh]]]]
The SSNP was founded by [[Antun Saadeh]], a [[Lebanese people|Lebanese]] [[Syrian nationalism|Syrian nationalist]] [[Philosophy|philosopher]] from a [[Eastern Orthodox Church|Greek Orthodox]] family in the town of [[Dhour El Shuwayr|Dhour el Shweir]]. Saadeh had emigrated to [[South America]] in 1919 (via the USA where he stayed for about a year before continuing on to [[Brazil]]), at the age of fifteen, and in the years he lived there engaged in both Arabic-language journalism and [[Syrian nationalism|Syrian nationalist]] political activity. On his return to Lebanon in 1930 he continued working as a journalist and also taught German in the [[American University of Beirut]].&lt;ref name=goetz&gt;{{cite book | title = Nazism in Syria and Lebanon: The Ambivalence of the German Option, 1933-1945 | author = [[Nordbruch Goetz]] | publisher = [[Taylor &amp; Francis]] | year = 2009 | isbn = 0-203-88856-1, 9780203888568 | url = http://books.google.com/books?id=iAWBkDAv4TkC&amp;pg=PA45&amp;dq=Syrian+social+nationalist+nazi+fascist | quote = (...) during his speech of 1 June 1935 (...) Antun Saadeh declared (...) &quot;(...) The Syrian Social Nationalist Party is neither a Hitlerite nor a Fascist one, but a pure social nationalist one. It is not based on useless imitation, but is the result of an authentic invention. (...)&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|43}} 

In November 1932 he secretly established the first nucleus of the Syrian Social Nationalist Party, which operated underground for the first three years of its existence.&lt;ref name=&quot;goetz&quot;/&gt; In 1933 it started publishing a monthly journal called ''Al-Majalla'' which was distributed in the [[American University of Beirut]]. The articles written in that journal and the speeches given by Saadeh consolidated the ideological basis of the party, and contributed to its popularity.&lt;ref name=&quot;goetz&quot;/&gt;{{rp|43}} 

Since its founding, the party endorsed an open hostility to colonialism and advocated national [[self-determination]], which eventually led to its ban by French authorities and the incarceration of Saadeh in 1936. Saadeh was sent to trial in 1936 and spent six months in prison for creating a clandestine party.&lt;ref name=goetz/&gt; He was also accused in the trial of having been in contact with the fascist movements of Germany and Italy, but the charge was dropped as a letter was addressed from Germany denying any relationships.&lt;ref name=goetz/&gt; It is during his months in prison that Saadeh laid down the final ideological foundations of the party in ''The Genesis of Nations''.    

Saadeh emigrated again to Brazil in 1938 and afterwards to Argentina, only to return to Lebanon in 1947 following the [[Lebanese Independence Day|country's independence from the French in 1943]]. By that time, the SSNP had grown exponentially and had clashed on many occasions with its primary ideological rival, the [[Kataeb Party]]. 
[[File:The Return of Saadeh.ogv|thumb|thumbtime=3:42|Film in Arabic about Saadeh's return to Lebanon in 1947]] 
While the latter was committed to the notion of Lebanon as a [[nation state]] defined as an entity presiding over the borders outlined first by the [[Sykes-Picot agreement]] in 1916, and afterwards by the [[Greater Lebanon|French administrative division]] of its mandate into six states including the state of Greater Lebanon, the SSNP rejected this national claim on the basis that the borders outlining the newly-created states were fictitious, resulting from colonialism, and do not reflect any historical and social realities. The party claimed that [[Greater Syria]] as defined by Saadeh represents the national ideal encompassing the historical people of Mesopotamia and the Fertile Crescent, bound together by a clearly-defined geography and a common historical, social and cultural development path.&lt;ref name=&quot;Genesis&quot;&gt;A. Saadeh. The Genesis of Nations. Translated and Reprinted. Dar Al-Fikr. Beirut, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;{{third-party-inline|date=January 2012}} Furthermore, and with the start of the [[Arab-Israeli conflict]] in 1948, Saadeh radicalized the party's [[Anti-Zionism|Anti-Zionist stance]] by declaring that ''&quot;Our struggle with the enemy is not a struggle for borders but for existence&quot;''. 

On July 4, 1949, a year after the declaration of the establishment of the state of [[Israel]] and the [[Nakba]], and a response to a series of aggressions perpetrated by the Kataeb-backed central government,the SSNP attempted its first revolution. Following a violent crackdown by government forces, Saadeh traveled to Damascus to meet with [[Husni al-Za'im]] in an attempt to obtain his support. Viewed as a radical agitator and threat to the newly-created Syrian state, Al-Za'im handed Saadeh over to Lebanese authorities, who had him executed on July 8, 1949. It was the shortest and most secretive trial given to a political offender.&lt;ref&gt;Adel beshara (2010). Outright Assassination: The Trial and Execution of Antun Sa'adeh, 1949. Ithaca Press. ISBN 978-0-86372-348-3.&lt;/ref&gt;

==The SSNP in Lebanon==
{{main|Syrian Social Nationalist Party in Lebanon}}

[[Image:Syria Social Nationalist Party Flags Beirut Lebanon 5-9-08.jpg|thumb|left|Flags of the Syrian Social Nationalist Party in [[Beirut]] on May 9 during the [[2008 conflict in Lebanon]]]]

After Saadeh was executed and its high-ranking leaders were arrested, the party remained underground until 1958 when it sided with then-president [[Camille Chamoun]] against the Arab nationalist rebels.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20040820212918/http://home.iprimus.com.au/fidamelhem/ssnp/The+lebanese_crisis_of_1958_and_the+the+SSNp.htm Article on pro-SSNP website on the party's role in the 1958 civil war] accessed 19 January 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;{{Citation needed|date=February 2009}}

The party launched an abortive coup attempt in 1961, under the semi-authoritarian rule of General Fouad Chehab.  This resulted in a renewed proscription and the imprisonment of many of its leaders.&lt;ref&gt;U.S. Department of State, ''Foreign Relations of the United States Volume 17, Near East,1961-1963,'' (Washington, DC: GPO 1993), 383-384.&lt;/ref&gt; In prison, some of the SSNP militants came under the influence of [[Marxism]] with the left-wing [[Al Taware]] faction splitting off in the 1970s,{{Citation needed|date=March 2007}} a split that would remain until the end of the Lebanese Civil War.{{Citation needed |date=January 2012}}

With the outbreak of the [[Lebanese Civil War]] in 1975, the SSNP formed a militia that allied with the leftist [[Lebanese National Movement]] (LNM), against the [[Phalangists]] and their allies of the [[Lebanese Front]]. The SSNP saw the Lebanese Civil War as the inevitable result of the divisions of the Syrian nation into small states and away from a [[liberation war]] against [[Israel]].  After the defeat of leftist forces in the [[1982 Lebanon War]], the SSNP joined a number of the leftist organizations who regrouped to resist the Israeli occupation, including the killing of two Israeli soldiers in a Wimpy Cafe in west Beirut by party member Khalid Alwan. The [[FBI]] blames the SSNP for the assassination, in in 1982, of [[Bachir Gemayel]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title = U.S. Links Men in Bomb Case To Lebanon Terrorist Group | author = Neil A. Lewis |  date = 1988-05-18 | work = [[The New York Times]] | url = http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6D81039F93BA25756C0A96E948260&amp;n=Top/Reference/Times%20Topics/Subjects/B/Bombs%20and%20Explosives }}&lt;/ref&gt; Lebanon's newly elected president supported by the Israelis besieging Beirut. In 1983 the party joined the [[Lebanese National Salvation Front]].  

The SSNP participated in a number of general elections in Lebanon, winning 6 seats in [[Lebanese general election, 1992|1992]], although seeing a decline in subsequent elections winning 2 seats in both [[2005 Lebanese general elections|2005]] and [[Lebanese general election, 2009|2009]].  The SSNP were involved in the [[2008 conflict in Lebanon]], with gunmen attacking an SSNP office.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.smh.com.au/news/world/aussies-death-sparks-lebanon-alert/2008/05/12/1210444296256.html | work=The Sydney Morning Herald | title=Aussie's death sparks Lebanon alert | date=12 May 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.theage.com.au/news/national/man-killed-in-lebanon-was-on-holiday/2008/05/12/1210444292099.html | location=Melbourne | work=The Age | first=Andra | last=Jackson | title=Melbourne man killed in Lebanon 'was on holiday' | date=12 May 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;hawke&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Australian killed in Lebanon: DFAT|url=http://hawkesbury.yourguide.com.au/news/national/national/general/australian-killed-in-lebanon-dfat/768453.aspx|publisher=''The Hawkesbury Gazette''|accessdate=2008-05-12 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080802162738/http://hawkesbury.yourguide.com.au/news/national/national/general/australian-killed-in-lebanon-dfat/768453.aspx &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2008-08-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Day 5: Lebanese dare to hope worst is over|url=http://www.dailystar.com.lb/article.asp?edition_id=1&amp;categ_id=2&amp;article_id=91930|publisher=''[[Daily Star (Lebanon)]]''|accessdate=2008-05-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.heraldsun.com.au/news/victoria/melbourne-dad-mutilated-in-lebanon/story-e6frf7kx-1111116330346&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.theaustralian.com.au/news/aussies-body-is-mutilated-by-mob/story-e6frg6of-1111116321514 | first1=Martin | last1=Chulov | first2=Michael | last2=Davis | title=Australian Fahdi Sheikh's body mutilated by Beirut mob | date=13 May 2008 | work=The Australian}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==The SSNP in Syria==
In [[Syria]] the SSNP grew to a position of considerable influence in the years following the country's independence in 1946, and was a major political force immediately after the restoration of democracy in 1954. It was a fierce rival of the [[Syrian Communist Party]] and of the radical pan-Arab [[Ba'ath Party|Arab Socialist Ba'ath Party]], the other main ideological parties of the period. In April 1955 Colonel [[Adnan al-Malki]], a Ba'athist officer who was a very popular figure in the Syrian army, was assassinated by a party member. This provided the Communists and Ba'athists with the opportunity to eliminate their main ideological rival, and under pressure from them and their allies in the security forces the SSNP was practically wiped out as a political force in Syria.

The SSNP's stance during the Lebanese civil war was consistent with that of Syria, and that facilitated a rapprochement between the party and the Syrian government. During Hafez al-Assad's [[President of Syria|presidency]], the party was increasingly tolerated. After the succession of his son [[Bashar al-Asad|Bashar]] in 2000, this process continued. In 2001, although still officially banned, the party was permitted to attend meetings of the Ba'ath-led [[National Progressive Front (Syria)|National Progressive Front]] coalition of legal parties as an observer. In Spring 2005 the party was legalised in Syria. It is considered to be one of the largest political parties in the country, after the ruling Ba'ath Party, with perhaps 100,000 members.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.atimes.com/atimes/Middle_East/GD26Ak04.html ''Asia Times'' article by Syrian political analyst Sami Moubayed]. Accessed 19 January 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 22 April 2007 [[Syrian parliamentary election, 2007|election]] for the [[People's Council of Syria]], the party gained 3 out of 250 in the parliament.

===Notable SSNP politicians in Syria===
*[[Issam Al Mahayri]]
*[[Joseph Sweid]]
*[[Bushra Massouh]]
*[[Issam Bagdi]]
*[[Ali Haidar (politician)|Ali Haidar]]

==Ideology==
{{refimprove section|date=January 2012}}

===Political Tenets===
While in jail from early February to early May 1936, Saadeh completed ''The Genesis of Nations'' which he had started writing three months before the French authorities in Lebanon discovered the secret organization and arrested its leader and his assistants. In his book, Saadeh formulated his belief in the existence of a [[Greater Syria|Syrian nation]] in a homeland defined as embracing all historic Syria extended to the Suez Canal in the south, and that includes modern Syria, Palestine, Lebanon, Jordan, Iraq, and Kuwait. The boundaries of the historic environment in which the Syrian nation evolved went much beyond the scope usually ascribed to Syria, extending from the Taurus range in the north-east and the [[Zagros mountains]] in the north-west to the [[Suez Canal]] and the [[Red Sea]] in the south and includes the [[Sinai peninsula]] and the [[Gulf of Aqaba]], and from the [[Mediterranean Sea]] in the west, including the island of [[Cyprus]], to the arch of the Arabian desert and the [[Persian Gulf]] in the east.&lt;ref name=&quot;Genesis&quot;/&gt;{{third-party-inline|date=January 2012}} According to Saadeh, this region is also called the Syrian Fertile Crescent, the island Cyprus being its star. 

According to Saadeh, [[Geographical feature|geographical factors]] play an important role in setting the parameters for the process of association and thus for the establishment of a nation. He held that the process of [[human evolution]] from [[hunter-gatherer]] to settled agriculture was among the most important factors that led to the creation of [[private property]] and the [[class system]]. Saadeh highlighted the role that the class system played in the flourishing of [[trade]] and [[commerce]] and the creation of [[wealth]], ascribing it to be a characteristic of the [[Semitic]] peolples, namely the coastal [[Phoenicians]]. He also stressed the link between the economic [[modes of production]] and the establishment of cultural [[norm (social)|norm]]s and [[values]], a view he shared with [[Karl Marx]]. 

However, Saadeh believed that while the economic modes of production can create culture, culture acquires a life of its own with time and eventually becomes embedded and [[Cultural reproduction|perpetuated]] in its people, who come to recognize themselves as a living organism. Hence comes the importance of the [[state (polity)|state]] in serving the interest of the nation, and of national [[democracy]] as the legitimate source of political legislation. 

The party's foundations were that this development pattern is exemplary to the [[Syrian people|Syrians]] and they came to constitute a complete nation and civilization throughout history, from the [[Ancient Near East|Pre-Christian era]], to the [[Islamic history|Islamic]] era, all the way up until the present. The SSNP claimed that the [[Greater Syria]] is the natural home of the Syrian people with clearly defined geographic boundaries, yet that its people are suffering from an [[identity crisis]] due to [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] occupation, colonialism, and sectarianism. Saadeh claimed that the ''renaissance'' of the Syrian nation is inevitably linked to the purge of these &quot;decadent&quot; forces through the reinforcing of national solidarity, resistance against colonialism, and [[secularism]]. Saadeh's concept of the nation shaped mainly by geography, rather than ethnic origins, language or religion, led him also to conclude that the Arabs could not form one nation, but many nations could be called Arab.

===Economic Theory===

While the core of the party's political theory revolves around the establishment of a [[Greater Syria]]n nation state, the [[economic theory]] upon which the state is to be organized remains a topic of contention. As a matter of fact, Saadeh did not elaborate a comprehensive economic theory, yet proposed a [[Left-wing nationalism|social nationalist]] model which can be considered to some extent as a distinctive form of [[socialism]]. As a matter of fact, among the key tenets of ''social nationalism'' figured the abolition of [[feudalism]], the emancipation of the [[working class]], the establishment of economic [[dirigisme]] and the [[welfare state]], [[universal healthcare]] as well as [[universal education]] for the purpose of securing national solidarity. This remains a topic of debate, however, as the strongly pronounced nationalistic features of SSNP ideology would permit scholars to interpret ''social nationalism'' as a distinctive breed of [[National Syndicalism]].

===Organization===

The SSNP was organised with a hierarchical structure and a powerful leader. Its ideology was an entirely secular form of nationalism; indeed, it posited the complete separation of religion and politics as one of the two fundamental conditions for real national unity. The other condition was determined economic and social reform.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hourani, p. 326&quot;&gt;Hourani, p. 326&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:SadheeSYRIA.jpg|right|thumb|[[Greater Syria]]]]

===Emblem and Flag===

The party's emblem was designed by the SSNP students [[American University of Beirut]] while the party was still clandestine and before the French authorities had uncovered it in 1936. The SSNP emblem is a combination of the [[crescent]] and the [[cross]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = SSNP website | url=http://ssnp.net/content/view/378/100}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{third-party-inline|date=January 2012}} The party flag features a red hurricane, called the &quot;Zawba'a&quot;, within a white circle on a black background. Each arm symbolizes one of the four virtues of the party's mission: freedom, duty, discipline and power.&lt;ref name=&quot;goetz&quot;/&gt;{{rp|45}} According to SSNP lore, the black color symbolizes the Dark Ages of [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] rule, [[colonialism]], [[sectarian]] division, national division, and backwardness. The &quot;Zawba'a&quot; allegedly represents the blood of the SSNP [[martyr]]s bound together as [[Muslims]] and [[Christians]] through [[Liberty|freedom]], [[duty]], discipline and power as a [[hurricane]] to purge the Dark Ages and spark their nation's rejuvenation and renaissance. Critics claim that the symbol was modeled after the [[Nazi Party|Nazi]] [[swastika]].&lt;ref name=am1987/&gt;&lt;ref name=pipes1992/&gt;&lt;ref name=yamak1966/&gt;&lt;ref name=johnson2001/&gt;&lt;ref name=becker1984&gt;{{cite book | last=Becker | first=Jillian |title=The PLO: The Rise and Fall of the Palestine Liberation Organization |year= 1984 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=sgu7AAAAIAAJ&amp;q=SSNP+swastika&amp;dq=SSNP+swastika&amp;pgis=1 |publisher=Weidenfeld and Nicolson |isbn=0-297-78547-8 |quote=[The SSNP] had been founded in 1932 as a youth movement, deliberately modeled on Hitler's Nazi Party. For its symbol it invented a curved swastika, called the Zawbah. }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title = Political parties in Lebanon | author = Michael W. Suleiman | page = 134 | publisher = [[University of Wisconsin]] | year = 1965 | quote = The flag of the Syrian Social Nationalist Party has a black background with a red hurricane (reversed swastika) in the middle, encircled by a white rim (...) }} also pages 111-112 in the edition of Cornell University Press, 1967 &quot;Thus, the Syrian national anthem for the PPS sang &quot;syria, Syria uber alles&quot; to the same familiar tune of &quot;Deutschland, Deutschland uber alles&quot;(176) The hand gestures in saluting and the &quot;long live the leader&quot; bore striking resemblances to the Nazi practice. The swastika was replaced with a hurricane as a PPS symbol,(177) while the storm or combat troops were present in both. Both Hitler and Saadeh, in addition to having the same title of 'the leader', held and exercised all legislative and executive authority.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticism==
===Ideological criticism===

Despite Saadeh's claims, some authors state that when the party began overt activity, it was the object of many critiques due to having many ideological and organizational resemblances to European fascism, and due to the resemblance of its external symbols to those of German [[Nazism]].&lt;ref name=am1987&gt;{{cite news | last=Ya’ari | first=Ehud |title=Behind the Terror |work=Atlantic Monthly |year= 1987 | month=June |url=http://www.theatlantic.com/issues/87jun/yaari.htm |quote=[The SSNP] greet their leaders with a Hitlerian salute; sing their Arabic anthem, &quot;Greetings to You, Syria,&quot; to the strains of &quot;Deutschland, Deutschland über alles&quot;; and throng to the symbol of the red hurricane, a swastika in circular motion. }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=pipes1992&gt;{{cite book | last=Pipes | first=Daniel | authorlink=Daniel Pipes |title=Greater Syria |year= 1992 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=J3PsAb1uV94C | publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] | pages = 100–101 | isbn=0-19-506022-9 |quote=The SSNP flag, which features a curved swastika called the red hurricane (''zawba'a''), points to the party's fascistic origins. }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=yamak1966&gt;{{cite book | last=Yamak | first=Labib Zuwiyya |title=The Syrian Social Nationalist Party: An Ideological Analysis |year= 1966 |url= http://books.google.com/books?id=98tBAAAAIAAJ&amp;q=The+Syrian+Social+Nationalist+Party:+An+Ideological+Analysis&amp;dq=The+Syrian+Social+Nationalist+Party:+An+Ideological+Analysis&amp;pgis=1 |publisher=[[Harvard University Press]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; Such resemblances went against the idea that it was an authentic national ideology and couldn't be acknowledged by the party.&lt;ref name=goetz/&gt; The party's founder Saadeh was aware of these accusations and he addressed them during his speech of 1 June 1935 (long before the events of World War II, and before the party was given publicity and the accusations started appearing in the press):

{{cquote|The system of the Syrian Social Nationalist Party is not a Hitlerite or a Fascist system, but that it is purely a Syrian system which does not stand on unprofitable imitation, but on basic originality which is one of the characteristics of our people.|||[[Antun Saadeh]]|''June 1935''.&lt;ref name=&quot;goetz&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ssnp.com&quot;&gt;http://www.ssnp.com/new/library/saadeh/misc/en/june_1_35.htm&lt;/ref&gt;}}

According to Reeva S. Johnson, Saadeh, the party's 'leader for life', was an admirer of [[Adolf Hitler]] influenced by [[Nazi]] and [[fascist]] ideology.&lt;ref name=johnson2001/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Simon1996&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last=Simon | first=Reeva S. |title=Encyclopedia of the Modern Middle East |year= 1996 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=vKptAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=%22Syrian+Social+Nationalist+Party%22+nazi&amp;dq=%22Syrian+Social+Nationalist+Party%22+nazi&amp;pgis=1 | publisher=[[Macmillan Publishers|Macmillan Reference USA]] | isbn=0-02-896011-4 |quote=The Syrian Social Nationalist party (SSNP) was the brainchild of Antun Sa'ada, a Greek Orthodox Lebanese who was inspired by Nazi and fascist ideologies. }}&lt;/ref&gt; The party adopted a reversed swastika as the party's symbol, sang the party's anthem to ''[[Deutschland über alles]]'', and included developing the cult of a leader, advocating totalitarian government, and glorifying an ancient pre-Christian past and the organic whole of the Syrian ''Volk'' or nation.&lt;ref name=am1987/&gt;&lt;ref name=johnson2001&gt;{{cite book | last=Johnson | first=Michael |title=All Honourable Men |year= 2001 |page=150 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Zydtz0dDntQC |publisher=[[I.B. Tauris]] | isbn=1-86064-715-4 |quote=Saadeh, the party's 'leader for life', was an admirer of Adolf Hitler and influenced by Nazi and fascist ideology. This went beyond adopting a reversed swastika as the party's symbol and singing the party's anthem to ''Deutschland über alles'', and included developing the cult of a leader, advocating totalitarian government, and glorifying an ancient pre-Christian past and the organic whole of the Syrian Volk or nation. }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Arab nationalist thinker [[Sati' al-Husri]] considered that Saadeh &quot;misrepresented&quot; Arab nationalism, incorrectly associating it with a [[Bedouin]] image of the Arab and with Muslim sectarianism. Palestinian historian [[Maher Charif]] sees Saadeh's theory as a response to the religious diversity of Syria, and points to his later
extension of his vision of the Syrian nation to include [[Iraq]], a country also noted for its religious diversity, as further evidence for this.&lt;ref&gt;Charif, p. 216&lt;/ref&gt; The party also accepted that due to &quot;religious and political considerations&quot;, the separate existence of Lebanon was necessary for the time being.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hourani, p. 326&quot;/&gt;
From 1945 on, the party adopted a more nuanced stance regarding Arab nationalism, seeing Syrian unity as a potential first step towards an Arab union led by Syria.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hourani, p. 326&quot;/&gt;

===Scholarly criticism===

Lebanese historian [[Kamal Salibi]] gives a somewhat contrasting interpretation, pointing to the position of the Greek Orthodox community as a large minority in both Syria and Lebanon for whom &quot;the concept of pan-Syrianism was more meaningful than the concept of Arabism&quot; while at the same time they resented [[Maronite]] dominance in Lebanon. According to Salibi,
&lt;blockquote&gt; Saadeh found a ready following among his co-religionists. His idea of secular pan-Syrianism also proved attractive to many Druzes and Shiites; to Christians other than the Greek Orthodox, including some Maronites who were disaffected by both Lebanism and Arabism; and also to many Sunnite Muslims who set a high value on secularism, and who felt that they had far more in common with their fellow Syrians of whatever religion or denomination than with fellow Sunnite or Muslim Arabs elsewhere. Here again, an idea of nationalism had emerged which had sufficient credit to make it valid.  In the Lebanese context, however, it became ready cover for something more archaic, which was essentially Greek Orthodox particularism.&lt;ref&gt;Kamal Salibi (1988, 1998), pp. 54-55&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Prof. Salibi remarks on the beginnings of Saadeh's party in the 1930s: &quot;[A]mong its first members were students and young graduates of the American University of Beirut.&quot; This early party was &quot;mainly Greek Orthodox and Protestants with some Shi'ites and Druzes... .&quot; In Lebanon as a whole the party was not popular. &quot;Christians were generally opposed to their Syrian unionism, while Moslems were suspicious of their reservations with regard to pan-Arabism. The Lebanese authorities were able to suppress them without difficulty.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;K. S. Salibi, ''The Modern History of Lebanon'' (New York: Praeger 1965) at 180.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to historian [[Stanley G. Payne]], the Arab nationalism was influenced by European fascism, with the creation of at least seven Arab nationalist [[shirt movement]]s similar to the [[brown shirt]] movement by 1939, with the most influenced ones being the SSNP, the Iraqi [[Futawa youth movement]] and the [[Young Egypt]] movement.&lt;ref name=&quot;payne&quot;/&gt; These three movements would share characteristics like being territorially expansionist, with the SSNP wanting the complete control of Syria, belief in the superiority of their own people (with Saadeh theorizing a &quot;distinct and naturally superior&quot; Syrian race), being &quot;nonrationalist, anti-intellectual, and highly emotional&quot; and &quot;[emphasizing] military virtues and power [and stressing] self-sacrifice&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;payne&quot;/&gt; Also according to Payne, all these movements received strong influence from European fascism and praised the Italian and German fascism but &quot;[they never became] fully developed fascist movements, and none reproduced the full characteristics of European fascism&quot;; the influence in Arab nationalism remained long after 1945.&lt;ref name=&quot;payne&quot;/&gt; Also, Saadeh's superior race was not a pure one, but a fusion of all races in Syrian history.&lt;ref name=&quot;payne&quot;/&gt; The SSNP would be &quot;[a] elite group, with little structure for mobilization&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;payne&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title = A history of fascism, 1914-1945 | author = [[Stanley G. Payne]] | edition = illustrated, reprint | publisher = [[Routledge]] | year = 1996 | isbn = 1-85728-595-6, 9781857285956 | pages = 352–354 | url = http://books.google.com/books?id=9wHNrF7nFecC&amp;pg=PA353&amp;dq=Antun+Saadeh+fascism }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|2}}

==References==
*Charif, Maher, ''Rihanat al-nahda fi'l-fikr al-'arabi'', Damascus, Dar al-Mada, 2000
*[[Albert Hourani|Hourani, Albert]], ''La Pensée Arabe et l'Occident'' (French translation of ''Arab Thought in the Liberal Age'')
*Irwin, Robert, &quot;An Arab Surrealist&quot;. ''[[The Nation (U.S. periodical)|The Nation]]'', January 3, 2005, 23&amp;ndash;24, 37&amp;ndash;38. There is [http://past.thenation.com/doc/20050103/irwin an online version], but only the first two paragraphs are shown to non-subscribers.
*Salibi, K. S., ''The Modern History of Lebanon'' (New York: Praeger 1965)
*Salibi, Kamal, ''A House of Many Mansions: The History of Lebanon Reconsidered'', University of California, Berkeley, 1988; reprint: London, [[I.B. Tauris]], 1998 ISBN 1-86064-912-2
*Seale, Patrick, ''Asad: the Struggle for the Middle East'', Berkely, University of California Press, 1988 ISBN 0-520-06976-5
*[http://www.cedarland.org/teams.html#syrian Information on Lebanese parties, from Lebanese nationalist-leaning website www.cedarland.org]

==External links==
* [http://www.alqawmi.com/ SSNP website] (in Arabic)
* [http://www.esaadah.com/ SSNP School]
* [http://www.Tahawolat.com/ Tahawolat Magazine] Articles about society and culture
* [http://www.start.umd.edu/gtd/search/Results.aspx?page=1&amp;casualties_type=&amp;casualties_max=&amp;perpetrator=2186&amp;charttype=line&amp;chart=overtime&amp;ob=GTDID&amp;od=desc&amp;expanded=yes#results-table Terrorist attacks attributed to the SSNP]
{{Syrian political parties}}

[[Category:Political parties established in 1932]]
[[Category:Nationalist parties in Syria]]
[[Category:Fertile Crescent]]
[[Category:Secularism in Syria]]
[[Category:Secularist political parties]]
[[Category:National liberation movements]]
[[Category:Anti-Zionist political parties]]

[[ar:الحزب السوري القومي الاجتماعي]]
[[cs:Syrská národně sociální strana]]
[[de:Syrische Soziale Nationalistische Partei]]
[[fr:Parti social nationaliste syrien]]
[[it:Partito Nazionalista Sociale Siriano]]
[[he:המפלגה הסורית הסוציאלית-לאומית]]
[[nl:Syrische Socialistische Nationale Partij]]
[[ja:シリア社会民族党]]
[[no:Det syriske sosialistiske nasjonale parti]]
[[pl:Syryjska Partia Socjalno-Narodowa]]
[[ru:Сирийская социальная националистическая партия]]
[[sv:Syriska socialnationalistiska partiet]]
[[uk:Сирійська націонал-соціалістична партія Лівану]]</text>
      <sha1>1mefof4n8zy0zb7kwusp5gx0y3d6v15</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
