<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>World Trade Center site</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>67173</id>
    <revision>
      <id>517403379</id>
      <parentid>517072593</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-12T14:19:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yobot</username>
        <id>7328338</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[WP:CHECKWIKI]] error 61 fix, References after punctuation per [[WP:REFPUNC]] and [[WP:PAIC]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (8459)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="50393">{{Redirect|Ground Zero|other uses|Ground Zero (disambiguation)}}
[[File:Aerial photo of WTC groundzero.jpg|thumb|360px|Aerial photo of the World Trade Center site, as it appeared on September 23, 2001]]
The '''World Trade Center site''' ([[ZIP code]]: [[10048 (ZIP code)|10048]]), previously known as &quot;'''Ground Zero'''&quot; after the [[September 11 attacks]], sits on {{convert|16|acre|m2}} in [[Lower Manhattan]] in [[New York City]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
  | last=Barry
  | first=Dan
  | title=A Nation Challenged - The Site: 'At the Scene of Random Devastation, a Most Orderly Mission'
  | newspaper=[[The New York Times]]
  | date=September 24, 2001
  | url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DEFDD143AF937A1575AC0A9679C8B63
  | accessdate=2010-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; The previous [[World Trade Center]] complex stood on the site until it was destroyed in the [[September 11 attacks]]; [[Studio Daniel Libeskind]], the [[Port Authority of New York and New Jersey]], [[Silverstein Properties]], and the [[Lower Manhattan Development Corporation]] oversee the reconstruction of the site. The site is bounded by [[Vesey Street (Manhattan)|Vesey Street]] to the north, the [[West Side Highway]] to the west, [[Liberty Street (Manhattan)|Liberty Street]] to the south, and [[Church Street (Manhattan)|Church Street]] to the east. The Port Authority owns the site's land (except for [[7 World Trade Center]]). Developer [[Larry Silverstein]] holds the lease to retail and office space in four of the site's buildings.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
  | last=Hartocollis
  | first=Anemona
  | title=Developer Sues to Win $12.3 Billion in 9/11 Attack
  | newspaper=[[The New York Times]]
  | date=March 27, 2008
  | url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/03/27/nyregion/27rebuild.html
  | accessdate=2010-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While the [[Port Authority of New York and New Jersey]] is often identified as the owner of the WTC site, the ownership situation is actually somewhat complex and ambiguous.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
  | last=Dunlap
  | first=David W.
  | title=Who Owns Ground Zero? Don't Expect a Simple Answer
  | newspaper=[[New York Times]]
  | date=April 22, 2004
  | url=http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/22/nyregion/22blocks.html
  | accessdate=2010-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Port Authority indeed owns a &quot;significant&quot; internal portion of the site of {{convert|16|acre|m2}}, but has acknowledged &quot;ambiguities over ownership of miscellaneous strips of property at the World Trade Center site&quot; going back to the 1960s. It is unclear who owns {{convert|2.5|acre|m2}} of the site, being land where streets had been before the World Trade Center was built.

==Before the World Trade Center==
The western portion of the World Trade Center site was originally under the Hudson River, with the shoreline in the vicinity of Greenwich Street. It was on this shoreline close to the intersection of Greenwich and the former Dey Street that Dutch explorer [[Adriaen Block]]'s ship, the [[Tyger (ship)|''Tyger'']], burned to the waterline in November 1613, stranding Block and his crew and forcing them to overwinter on the island. They built the first European settlement, albeit a temporary one in what would be New York City. The remains of the ship were buried under landfill when the shoreline was extended starting in 1797, and were discovered during excavation work in 1916. The remains of a second ship from the eighteenth century were discovered in 2010 during excavation work at the site. The ship believed to be a Hudson River [[sloop]] was found just south of where the Twin Towers used to stand, about 20 feet below the surface.&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.cnn.com/2010-07-15/us/new.york.ground.zero.ship_1_ship-archaeologist-ground-zero?_s=PM:US CNN: Pieces of ship made in 1700s found at ground zero building site]&lt;/ref&gt;

The area that was cleared for construction of the original World Trade Center complex was previously occupied by various electronics stores in what was called [[Radio Row]]. These streets and stores were demolished in the 1960s to make way for the World Trade Center.

==Debris and clean-up==
{{See also|Rescue and recovery effort after the September 11 attacks|Health effects arising from the September 11 attacks}}
{{multiple image
 | align     = right
 | direction = horizontal
 | image1    = World Trade Center Site After 9-11 Attacks With Original Building Locations.jpg
 | width1    = 230
 | caption1  = Satellite image of the World Trade center site after the attacks with the location of the Twin Towers and other buildings in the complex superimposed over the debris field
 | image2    = FEMA - 4235 - Photograph by Andrea Booher taken on 09-28-2001 in New York.jpg
 | width2    = 258
 | caption2  = The World Trade Center site 17 days after the September 11, 2001 terrorist attacks. Buildings surrounding the site of the collapsed towers are fitted with mesh to prevent further damage and large construction vehicles are being used to clear debris.
}}
The collapse of the towers spread dust across New York City and left hundreds of thousands of tons of debris at the site.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
  | last=Barry
  | first=Dan
  | title=AFTER THE ATTACKS: THE TALLY; With No Miracle in the Rubble, Hope Grimly Shifts to Acceptance
  | newspaper=[[The New York Times]]
  | date=September 17, 2001
  | url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E1D8173BF934A2575AC0A9679C8B63
  | accessdate=2010-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; To organize the cleanup and search for survivors and for human remains, the [[New York City Fire Department]] divided the disaster site into four sectors, each headed by its own chief.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
  | last=Barry
  | first=Dan
  | title=A NATION CHALLENGED: THE SITE; At the Scene of Random Devastation, a Most Orderly Mission
  | newspaper=[[The New York Times]]
  | year=2001
  | date=September 24, 2010
  | url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DEFDD143AF937A1575AC0A9679C8B63
  | accessdate=2010-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; Early estimates suggested that debris removal would take a year, but cleanup ended in May 2002, under budget and without a single serious injury.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
  | last=Iovine
  | first=Julie V.
  | title=Designers Look Beyond Debris
  | newspaper=[[The New York Times]]
  | date=September 27, 2001
  | url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E7DB103AF934A1575AC0A9679C8B63
  | accessdate=2010-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
  | title=The Last Steel Column
  | url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E4D71E3BF933A05756C0A9649C8B63
  | newspaper=[[The New York Times]]
  | date=May 30, 2002
  | accessdate=2010-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; Three years later, in February 2005, the New York City Medical Examiner's office ended its process of identifying human remains at the site.&lt;ref name=&quot;cnn.com&quot;&gt;{{Cite news
  | last=Hirschkorn
  | first=Phil
  | author-link=
  | title=Identification of 9/11 remains comes to end
  | newspaper=[[CNN]]
  | volume=
  | issue=
  | pages=
  | date=February 23, 2005
  | url=http://www.cnn.com/2005/US/02/22/wtc.identifications/index.html
  | postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to NIST, when WTC 1 (the North Tower) collapsed, falling debris struck 7 World Trade Center and ignited fires on multiple floors. The uncontrolled fires ultimately led to the progressive collapse of the structure.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.nist.gov/public_affairs/releases/wtc082108.html
|title=NIST News Release: NIST WTC 7 Investigation Finds Building Fires Caused Collapse
|date=2008-08-21
|publisher=NIST
|accessdate=2008-09-11}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Portions of the South Tower also damaged the nearby [[Deutsche Bank Building]], which soon became filled with toxic dust. By 2002, [[Deutsche Bank]] determined that its building was unsalvageable. By January 2011, the Deutsche Bank Building was finally completely demolished.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
  | last=Varchaver
  | first=Nicholas
  | author-link=
  | title=The tombstone at Ground Zero
  | newspaper=[[CNN]]
  | volume=
  | issue=
  | pages=
  | date=March 20, 2008
  | url=http://money.cnn.com/2008/03/19/news/companies/ground_zero.fortune/index.htm
  | postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cleanup workers trucked most of the building materials and debris from Ground Zero to [[Fresh Kills Landfill]] in [[Staten Island]]. Some people, such as those affiliated with World Trade Center Families for Proper Burial, were worried that human remains might also have been (inadvertently) transported to the landfill.&lt;ref name=&quot;cnn.com&quot;/&gt;

In August 2008, New York City firefighters donated a cross made of steel from the World Trade Center to the Shanksville Volunteer Fire Company.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|last=GANASSI |first=MICHELLE
|title=NY firefighter donating steel to Shanksville
|url=http://www.dailyamerican.com/articles/2008/08/22/news/news/news808.txt
|date=2008-08-25
|work=Daily American   cv
|accessdate=2008-08-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; The beam, mounted atop a platform shaped like the Pentagon, was erected outside the [[Shanksville, Pennsylvania|Shanksville]] firehouse near the crash site of [[United Airlines Flight 93]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Gaskell |first=Stephanie |title=Pa. site of 9/11 crash gets WTC beam |url=http://www.nydailynews.com/ny_local/2008/08/24/2008-08-24_pa_site_of_911_crash_gets_wtc_beam.html |date=2008-08-25 |work=New York Daily news |accessdate=2008-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In December 2001, a temporary viewing platform at Fulton Street, between Church Street and Broadway, opened to the public.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
  | last=Hirschkorn
  | first=Phil
  | title=A NATION CHALLENGED: GROUND ZERO; First Viewing Platform Opens to the Public
  | newspaper=[[The New York Times]]
  | date=December 30, 2001
  | url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE0D71630F933A05751C1A9679C8B63
  | accessdate=2010-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On March 11, 2002, 88 searchlights were installed and arranged to form two beams of light shooting straight up into the sky. This is called the [[Tribute in Light]], and was originally lit every day at dusk until April 14, 2002. After that, the lights were lit on the two-year anniversary of the attack and have been lit on each subsequent September 11 since then.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
  | last=Dunlap
  | first=David W.
  | title=Twin Beams to Light Sky Again. But After 2008?
  | newspaper=[[The New York Times]]
  | date=September 9, 2006
  | url=http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/09/nyregion/09light.html
  | accessdate=2010-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Archaeology==
In July 2010 a team of [[archaeologist]]s at the site discovered the remains of a {{convert|32|ft|m|adj=on}}-long boat over 200 years old; it was probably made in the 18th century and dumped there along with wooden beams and trash in about 1810 to make up the land.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Daily Telegraph]]'', Friday 16 July 2010, page 16; [http://www.mirror.co.uk/news/top-stories/2010/07/16/ship-found-at-ground-zero-site-in-new-york-115875-22416662/], [http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/worldnews/article-1294911/Historic-18th-century-wooden-ship-unearthed-new-World-Trade-Centre-site.html with images], [http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2010/jul/15/world-trade-centre-hull-ship], [http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20100715/ap_on_re_us/us_ground_zero_buried_ship], [http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/interactive/2010/jul/15/new-york-ground-zero-ship], [http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2010/jul/15/world-trade-centre-hull-ship]&lt;/ref&gt; The boat had been weighted to make it sink as part of foundations for a new [[pier]]. Samples of its wood have been taken for [[dendrochronology]].

==Rebuilding==
{{multiple image
 | direction = horizontal 
 | width     = 200
 | header    = World Trade Center site layout
 | image1    = WTC Building Arrangement and Site Plan.svg
 | alt1      = WTC site plan prior to 9/11/2001
 | caption1  = Above: The World Trade Center site prior to the September 11 attacks.
 | image2    = WTC Building Arrangement in preliminary site plan.svg
 | alt2      = WTC site plan for reconstruction
 | caption2  = Above: Preliminary site plans for the World Trade Center rebuild.
}}
Soon after the September 11 attacks, Mayor [[Rudy Giuliani]], Governor [[George Pataki]], and President [[George W. Bush]] vowed to rebuild the World Trade Center site. On the day of the attacks, Giuliani proclaimed, &quot;We will rebuild. We're going to come out of this stronger than before, politically stronger, economically stronger. The skyline will be made whole again.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.architectureweek.com/2001/0926/today.html |title=Rebuilding in New York |date=September 26, 2001 |author=Taylor, Tess |publisher=Architecture Week}}&lt;/ref&gt; During a visit to the site on September 14, 2001, Bush spoke to a crowd of cleanup workers through a megaphone. An individual in the crowd shouted, &quot;I can't hear you,&quot; to which Bush replied, &quot;I can hear you. The rest of the world hears you. And the people who knocked these buildings down will hear all of us soon.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
  | last=Walsh
  | first=Edward
  | title=Bush Encourages N.Y. Rescuers
  | newspaper=[[The Washington Post]]
  | pages=A10
  | date=September 15, 2001
  | url=http://old.911digitalarchive.org/crr/documents/1126.pdf
  | format=PDF
  | accessdate=2010-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a later address before [[United States Congress|Congress]], the president declared, &quot;As a symbol of America's resolve, my administration will work with Congress, and these two leaders, to show the world that we will rebuild New York City.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://georgewbush-whitehouse.archives.gov/news/releases/2001/09/20010920-8.html |title=Address to a Joint Session of Congress and the American People |publisher=The White House |date=September 20, 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt; The immediate response from World Trade Center leaseholder [[Larry Silverstein]] was that &quot;it would be the tragedy of tragedies not to rebuild this part of New York. It would give the terrorists the victory they seek.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=In place of the Trade Center; Ideas range from building new towers to playground |author=Litt, Steven |publisher=Plain Dealer (Cleveland) |date=September 17, 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, ten years after the attacks, only one building, [[7 World Trade Center]], has been rebuilt. Two buildings are in the construction phase currently, [[One World Trade Center]] and [[Four World Trade Center|150 Greenwich Street]] (known as Four World Trade Center). The original twin towers took less than three years from start of construction to be finished, and 5 years from the beginning planning stages.   However, given the complexity and highly political nature of the rebuilding efforts, they are often cited as an example of a successful public-private collaboration and are taught as a case study in successful negotiations.&lt;ref&gt;Cornell Real Estate Review, Volume 10, Number 1 (July 2012), 39-53, http://cip.cornell.edu/cpre.crer/1342144023; http://www.cornell.edu/video/?videoID=1680&lt;/ref&gt;

===Lower Manhattan Development Corporation===
Governor Pataki established the [[Lower Manhattan Development Corporation]] (LMDC) in November 2001, as an official commission to oversee the rebuilding process.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
  | last=Pérez-Peña
  | first=Richard
  | title=A NATION CHALLENGED: DOWNTOWN; State Plans Rebuilding Agency, Perhaps Led by Giuliani
  | newspaper=[[The New York Times]]
  | date=November 3, 2001
  | url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFD81639F930A35752C1A9679C8B63
  | accessdate=2010-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; The LMDC coordinates [[Federal government of the United States|federal]] assistance in the rebuilding process, and works with the [[Port Authority of New York and New Jersey|Port Authority]], Larry Silverstein, and [[Studio Daniel Libeskind]], the master plan architect for the site's redesign. The corporation also handles communication with the local community, businesses, the city of New York, and relatives of victims of the September 11 attacks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=A Corporation to Rebuild Ground Zero |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/04/opinion/a-corporation-to-rebuild-ground-zero.html |newspaper=[[The New York Times]] |date=November 4, 2001 |accessdate=2010-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 16-member board of directors, half appointed by the governor and half by the mayor of New York, governs the LMDC.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release
  | title = Governor and Mayor Name Lower Manhattan Redevelopment Corporation
  | publisher = www.RenewNYC.org
  | date = November 29, 2001
  | url = http://www.renewnyc.com/displaynews.aspx?newsid=2b0bfde6-61b6-48f9-a6ca-70475846c95b
  | accessdate = 2008-06-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The LMDC had questionable legal status regarding the restoration of the World Trade Center site, because the Port Authority owns most of the property and Larry Silverstein leased the World Trade Center's office space in July 2001. But the LMDC, in an April 2002 articulation of its principles for action, asserted its role in revitalizing lower Manhattan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release
  | title = Lower Manhattan Development Corporation Announces Principles for Development and Blueprint for Renewal for World Trade Center Site
  | publisher = www.RenewNYC.org
  | date = April 9, 2002
  | url = http://www.renewnyc.com/displaynews.aspx?newsid=112d53af-0d20-44ec-89d7-23f397b5a569
  | accessdate = 2008-06-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Early proposals for redesign===
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:New wtc.jpg|thumb|Artist's rendering of proposed design with September 11 Memorial in the foreground]] --&gt;
In the months following the attacks, [[architect]]s and [[urban planning]] experts held meetings and forums to discuss ideas for rebuilding the site.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Up From The Ashes |publisher=Newsweek |date=November 12, 2001 |author=McGuigan, Cathleen}}&lt;/ref&gt; In January 2002, New York City [[art dealer]] [[Max Protetch]] solicited 50 concepts and [[Rendering (computer graphics)|renderings]] from artists and architects, which were put on exhibit in his [[Chelsea, Manhattan|Chelsea]] [[art gallery]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Everyone Weighs In With Rebuilding Ideas |first=Edward |last=Wyatt |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/12/nyregion/ground-zero-the-proposals-everyone-weighs-in-with-rebuilding-ideas.html |newspaper=[[The New York Times]] |date=January 11, 2002 |accessdate=2010-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In April 2002, the LMDC sent out requests for proposals to redesign the World Trade Center site to 24 Manhattan architecture firms, but then soon withdrew them. The following month, the LMDC selected [[Beyer Blinder Belle]] as planner for the redesign of the World Trade Center site.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=An Appraisal; Marginal Role for Architecture at Ground Zero |first=Herbert |last=Muschamp |authorlink=Herbert Muschamp |url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404EEDB1E38F930A15756C0A9649C8B63 |newspaper=[[The New York Times]] |date=May 23, 2002 |accessdate=2010-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On July 16, 2002, Beyer Blinder Belle unveiled six concepts for redesigning the World Trade Center site.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release
  | title = Port Authority and Lower Manhattan Developent (sic) Corporation Unveil Six Concepts Plans for World Trade Center Site, Adjacent Areas and Related Transportation
  | publisher = www.RenewNYC.org
  | date = July 16, 2002
  | url = http://www.renewnyc.com/displaynews.aspx?newsid=b3aa6fb4-ebb6-48e3-ba62-c92bce75a647
  | accessdate = 2008-06-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; All six designs were voted &quot;poor&quot; by the roughly 5,000 New Yorkers that submitted feedback, so the LDMC announced a new, international, open-design study.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release
  | title = Lower Manhattan Development Corporation and New York New Visions Announce Panel to Help Select Teams to Participate in Design Study of World Trade Center Site and Surrounding Areas
  | publisher = www.RenewNYC.org
  | date = September 17, 2002
  | url = http://www.renewnyc.com/displaynews.aspx?newsid=633a746a-8f04-40ea-85aa-4f58639a2d20
  | accessdate = 2008-06-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2002 World Trade Center site design competition===
In an August 2002 press release, the LMDC announced a design study for the World Trade Center site.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release
  | title = Lower Manhattan Development Corporation Announces Design Study for World Trade Center Site and Surrounding Areas
  | publisher = www.RenewNYC.org
  | date = August 14, 2002
  | url = http://www.renewnyc.com/displaynews.aspx?newsid=da800006-c35b-4f1c-a9ec-ff53cfe45ae2
  | accessdate = 2008-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; The following month, the LMDC, along with New York New Visions – a coalition of 21 architecture, engineering, planning, landscape architecture and design organizations – announced seven semifinalists. The following seven architecture firms were then invited to compete to be the master plan architect for the World Trade Center:
*[[Foster and Partners]] ([[Norman Foster, Baron Foster of Thames Bank|Norman Foster]])
*[[Studio Daniel Libeskind]] ([[Daniel Libeskind]])
*Meier Eisenman Gwathmey Holl ([[Peter Eisenman]], [[Richard Meier]], [[Charles Gwathmey]] and [[Steven Holl]]), sometimes known as &quot;The Dream Team&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Turning a Competition Into a Public Campaign; Finalist for Ground Zero Design Pull Out the Stops |first=Julie |last=Iovine |url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6DD173CF935A15751C0A9659C8B63 |newspaper=[[The New York Times]] |date=February 26, 2003 |accessdate=2010-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Skidmore, Owings and Merrill]]
*[[THINK Team]] ([[Shigeru Ban]], [[Frederic Schwartz]], [[Ken Smith (architect)|Ken Smith]], [[Rafael Vinoly]])
*United Architects
Peterson Littenberg, a small New York architecture firm, had been enlisted by the LMDC earlier that summer as a consultant, and was invited to participate as the seventh semifinalist.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release
  | title = Lower Manhattan Development Corporation Announces Six Teams of Architects and Planners to Participate in Design Study of World Trade Center Site
  | publisher = www.RenewNYC.org
  | date = September 26, 2002
  | url = http://www.renewnyc.com/displaynews.aspx?newsid=655798f4-b8ee-4583-bf27-b3b9a9c29f1f
  | accessdate = 2008-06-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The seven semifinalists presented their entries to the public on December 18, 2002 at the [[Winter Garden Atrium|Winter Garden]] of the [[World Financial Center]]. In the following weeks, Skidmore, Owings &amp; Merrill withdrew its entry from the competition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Beauty Contest: Two Firms Vie At W.T.C. Site |first=Tom |last=McGeveran |url=http://www.observer.com/node/47085 |newspaper=[[The New York Observer]] |date=February 9, 2003 |accessdate=2010-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Days before the announcement of the two finalists in February 2003, Larry Silverstein wrote to LMDC Chair [[John C. Whitehead|John Whitehead]] to express his disapproval of all of the semifinalists' designs. As the Twin Towers' insurance money recipient, Silverstein claimed that he had the sole right to decide what would be built. He announced that he had already picked Skidmore, Owings &amp; Merrill as his master planner for the site.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | last = Libeskind
  | first = Daniel
  | title = Breaking Ground
  | publisher = [[Riverhead Books]]
  | location = New York
  | year = 2004
  | pages = 164
  | isbn = 1-57322-292-5 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On February 1, 2003, the LMDC selected two finalists, the THINK Team and Studio Daniel Libeskind, and planned on picking a single winner by the end of the month.

Rafael Viñoly of the THINK Team and Studio Daniel Libeskind presented their designs to the LMDC, which selected the THINK design. Earlier the same day, however, [[Roland Betts]], a member of the LMDC, had called a meeting and the corporation had agreed to vote for the THINK design before hearing the final presentations. Governor Pataki, who had originally commissioned the LMDC, intervened and overruled the LMDC's decision.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | last = Libeskind
  | first = Daniel
  | title = Breaking Ground
  | publisher = [[Riverhead Books]]
  | location = New York
  | year = 2004
  | pages = 166, 181, 183
  | isbn = 1-57322-292-5 }}&lt;/ref&gt; On February 27, 2003, Studio Daniel Libeskind officially won the competition to be the master planner for the World Trade Center redesign.

Libeskind's original proposal, which is titled [[Memory Foundations]], underwent extensive revisions during collaboration with Larry Silverstein, and Skidmore, Owings and Merrill, whom Silverstein hired. Though Libeskind designed the site, the individual buildings have been designed by different architects.

Detailed information about Libeskind's Memory Foundations site plan can be accessed at LMDC's website.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.renewnyc.com/plan_des_dev/wtc_site/new_design_plans/Sept_2003_refined_design.asp&lt;/ref&gt;

While not all of Liebeskind's ideas were incorporated into the final design, his design and the public support it garnered did solidify the principle that the original footprints of the Twin Towers should be turned into a memorial and not be used for commercial purposes.  As a result, Liebeskind's lawyers at the New York firm of Wachtell Lipton embarked on the multi-year negotiation process to frame a master plan for the rebuilding.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.wtc.com/news/Silversteins-Army&lt;/ref&gt;  The first step in this process, completed in 2003, was the &quot;swap&quot; in which Silverstein gave up his rights to the footprints of the Twin Towers so that they could become a memorial, and in exchange received the right to build five new office towers around the memorial.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.americanlawyer-digital.com/americanlawyer/tal200709/?pg=5&lt;/ref&gt;  The &quot;swap&quot; and the ensuing negotiations, which lasted for many years, have been referred to as the most complex real estate transaction in human history because of the complexity of the issues involved, the many stakeholders, and the difficulty of reaching consensus. &lt;Scott Raab, Construction of World Trade Center, Esquire, May 24, 2007&gt;

===Towers===
[[Image:GroundZeroFrom7WTC.JPG|thumb|left|A view of Ground Zero, taken in September 2006, from the 45th floor of the completed [[7 World Trade Center]] with the future [[Greenwich Street]] running vertically through the center.]]
[[One World Trade Center]] (previously coined the &quot;Freedom Tower&quot; by Governor Pataki) is the centerpiece of Libeskind's design. The building will rise to {{convert|1368|ft|m}}, the height of the original World Trade Center north tower, and its antenna will rise to the symbolic height of 1,776 feet (541 m). The antenna's height refers to 1776, the year in which the [[United States Declaration of Independence]] was signed.

The tower was a collaboration between Studio Daniel Libeskind and Skidmore, Owings and Merrill architect [[David Childs]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wtc.com/about/freedom-tower|title=Freedom Tower: About the Building|accessdate=2008-01-21|publisher=Silverstein Properties}}&lt;/ref&gt; Childs acted as the design architect and project manager for the tower, and Daniel Libeskind collaborated on the concept and schematic design.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Libeskind and Silverstein reach an agreement for WTC site |first=Kevin |last=Lerner |magazine=[[Architectural Record]] |month=August |year=2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to a [[NY1]] article on March 8, 2011, a plan to build a restaurant on top of One World Trade Center (to duplicate the [[Windows on the World]] restaurant of old) was scrapped entirely because of potential risk of rising costs to build and maintain the establishment over the benefits of having one at all.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://manhattan.ny1.com/content/top_stories/135170/port-authority-scraps-plans-for-one-world-trade-center-restaurant |title=Port Authority Scraps Plans For One World Trade Center Restaurant |work=[[NY1]] |date=March 8, 2011 |accessdate=2011-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also, one of the main tenants of this tower to be confirmed is the [[Condé Nast Publications]] company, once it officially opens.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/05/18/nyregion/conde-nast-to-anchor-1-world-trade-center.html?_r=2&amp;hp |title=Condé Nast Will Be Anchor of 1 World Trade Center |work=[[The New York Times]] |first=Charles V. |last=Bagli |date=May 17, 2011| accessdate=2011-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.ny1.com/content/special_reports/911_a_decade_later/139715/9-11-a-decade-later--conde-nast-to-occupy-1-world-trade-center| title=9/11 A Decade Later: Conde Nast To Occupy 1 World Trade Center| work=[[NY1]]| first=Bobby| last=Cuza| date=May 25, 2011| accessdate=2011-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

British architect [[Norman Foster, Baron Foster of Thames Bank|Norman Foster]] designed [[Two World Trade Center|Tower Two]], also known as 200 Greenwich Street. The building's distinctive slanted, diamond-shaped roof echoes Libeskind's original sketches for the building.

[[Rogers Stirk Harbour + Partners|Richard Rogers Partnership]] designed [[Three World Trade Center|Tower Three]], or 175 Greenwich Street, which stands across Greenwich Street from the Memorial's two reflecting pools.

[[Fumihiko Maki|Maki and Associates]] designed [[Four World Trade Center|Tower Four]], also known as 150 Greenwich Street.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.renewnyc.com/ThePlan/world_trade_center_towers.asp
|title=World Trade Center Towers |publisher=Lower Manhattan Development Corporation |date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ny1.com/content/top_stories/123905/ny1-exclusive--developer-says-wtc-project-to-be-complete-in-five--six-years NY1 Exclusive: Developer Says WTC Project To Be Complete In Five, Six Years] [[NY1]]. Retrieved August 17, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Five World Trade Center|Tower 5]] was designed by [[Kohn Pedersen Fox]] and will stand where the [[Deutsche Bank Building]] once stood. On June 22, 2007, the Port Authority announced that [[JP Morgan Chase]] will lease the 42-story building for its investment banking headquarters.;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=JP Morgan releases WTC tower plans |first=Marlene |last=Naanes |url=http://www.amny.com/news/local/am-wtc0622,0,6464804.story?coll=am-local-headlines |newspaper=[[AM New York]] |date=June 22, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Kohn Responds to WTC5 Criticisms |first=Alec |last=Appelbaum |url=http://archrecord.construction.com/news/daily/archives/070730wtc.asp |magazine=[[Architectural Record]] |date=July 30, 2007 |accessdate=2010-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; however, JPMorgan's March 2008 acquisition of [[Bear Stearns]] had put the future of the 130 Liberty Street site in question, as the company is now planning to relocate its headquarters to 383 Madison Avenue. Construction began on September 9, 2011.

[[7 World Trade Center]] stands off of Port Authority property. David Childs of Skidmore, Owings and Merrill designed the tower, which opened in May 2006.  The project company also announced that all of the towers will be completed even with the effects of the [[late 2000s recession]] at the worst case before 2020.

===Memorial===
{{Main|World Trade Center Memorial}}
A memorial called &quot;Reflecting Absence&quot; honors the victims of the [[September 11 attacks]] and the [[1993 World Trade Center bombing]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.ny1.com/content/special_reports/911_a_decade_later/142578/9-11-a-decade-later--the-9-11-memorial-from-all-sides| title=9/11 A Decade Later: The 9/11 Memorial From All Sides| work=[[NY1]]| first=Bobby| last=Cuza| date=July 8, 2011| accessdate=2011-07-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; The memorial, designed by Peter Walker and [[Israeli American|Israeli-American]] architect [[Michael Arad]], consists of a field of trees interrupted by the footprints of the twin towers. Pools of water fill the footprints, underneath which sits a memorial space whose walls bear the names of the victims. The [[slurry wall]], which holds back the [[Hudson River]] in the west and was an integral part of Libeskind's proposal, remains exposed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.wtcsitememorial.org/fin7.html |title=Reflecting Absence |publisher=Lower Manhattan Development Corporation |year=2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Walker and Arad were selected from more than 5,000 entrants in the [[World Trade Center Site Memorial Competition]] in January 2004. Construction of the memorial was completed before September 11, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/925885.html The politics of remembering Ground Zero - Haaretz - Israel News&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Media Get Sneak Peek Of 9/11 Museum Site |first=Bobby |last=Cuza |url=http://www.ny1.com/content/top_stories/123505/media-get-sneak-peek-of-9-11-museum-site |work=[[NY1]] |date=August 10, 2010 |accessdate=2010-08-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ny1.com/content/top_stories/124556/first-trees-are-planted-at-september-11th-memorial-site First Trees Are Planted At September 11th Memorial Site] [[NY1|NY1 local news channel]]. Retrieved August 28, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ny1.com/content/top_stories/127484/wtc-memorial-to-display-mementos-of-attack-victims WTC Memorial To Display Mementos Of Attack Victims] [[NY1|NY1 local news channel]]. Retrieved October 20, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://manhattan.ny1.com/content/top_stories/127779/sept--11th-memorial-plaza-receives-its-50th-oak-tree Sept. 11th Memorial Plaza Receives Its 50th Oak Tree] [[NY1|NY1 local news channel]]. Made October 26, 2010. Retrieved October 27, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://manhattan.ny1.com/content/top_stories/129479/visitors-to-wtc-site-get-vivid-preview-of-9-11-memorial Visitors To WTC Site Get Vivid Preview Of 9/11 Memorial] [[NY1|NY1 local news channel]]. Retrieved November 23, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.ny1.com/content/top_stories/131094/-survivor-tree--replanted-at-wtc-site| title=&quot;Survivor Tree&quot; Replanted At WTC Site| work=[[NY1]]| first=Michael| last=Scotto| date=December 22, 2010| accessdate=2010-12-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.ny1.com/content/top_stories/133957/wtc-memorial-to-have-limited-access-on-10th-anniversary| title=WTC Memorial To Have Limited Access On 10th Anniversary| work=[[NY1]]| date=February 14, 2011| accessdate=2011-02-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.ny1.com/content/top_stories/142057/port-authority--wtc-memorial-needs-another--3m-for-construction| title=Port Authority: WTC Memorial Needs Another $3M For Construction| work=[[NY1]]| date=June 30, 2011| accessdate=2011-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Museum===
On October 12, 2004, the LMDC announced that [[Frank Gehry|Gehry Partners LLP]] and [[Snøhetta (company)|Snøhetta]], a [[Norway|Norwegian]] [[architectural firm]], would design the site's performing arts and museum complexes, respectively.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release
  | title = The Lower Manhattan Development Corporation Announces Selection of Architectural Firms to Design the Performing Arts Complex and the Museum Complex on the World Trade Center Site
  | publisher = www.RenewNYC.org
  | date = October 12, 2004
  | url =http://www.renewnyc.com/displaynews.aspx?newsid=b60c011b-187b-44b8-b764-1b4381427018
  | accessdate = 2008-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.ny1.com/content/top_stories/135293/9-11-a-decade-later--glass-atrium-rises-at-wtc-memorial-site| title=9/11 A Decade Later: Glass Atrium Rises At WTC Memorial Site| first=Rebecca| last=Spitz| work=[[NY1]]| date=March 9, 2011| accessdate=2011-03-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Snøhetta-designed museum&lt;ref name=nytimes&gt;{{cite news|first=Steven|last=Erlanger |title=Again in Norway, Events Provide Test for a King’s Mettle |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/16/world/europe/king-harald-of-norway-proves-mettle-with-response-to-july-22-deaths.html?partner=rss&amp;emc=rss |work=[[New York Times]] |publisher= |date=2011-10-15 |accessdate=2011-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;  will now act as a memorial museum and visitors' center, after family members of 9/11 victims objected to the building's original occupant, the [[International Freedom Center]].&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt-2007-03-28&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/28/arts/28zero.html |title=Ground Zero Arts Center Loses Theater Company |date=March 28, 2007 |author=Pogrebin, Robin |authorlink=Robin Pogrebin |newspaper=[[The New York Times]] |accessdate=2010-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Gehry's performing arts complex will now house only the Joyce Theater, because the Signature Theater Company dropped out due to space constraints and cost limitations.&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt-2007-03-28&quot;/&gt;

===Transportation Hub===
[[Image:WTC Path.JPG|right|thumb|Entrance to the PATH at the World Trade Center]]
[[Santiago Calatrava]] designed the [[World Trade Center Transportation Hub]] (its main asset being the [[Port Authority Trans Hudson|PATH]] station ) to replace the old [[World Trade Center (PATH station)|World Trade Center station]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/07/02/nyregion/02path.html |date=July 2, 2008 |author=Dunlap, David W. |newspaper=[[The New York Times]] | title=Design of Ground Zero Transit Hub Is Trimmed |accessdate=2010-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Transport Hub will connect the PATH station and 1 [[New York City Transit Authority]] subway train to the ferry terminal, the [[World Financial Center]] and [[One World Trade Center]] on the west and the {{NYCS Fulton Street Transit Center}} New York City Transit Authority subway trains through the [[Fulton Center]] on the East. One will be able to walk most of the way across lower Manhattan. The Port Authority will cool the new station, as well as the September 11 Memorial and Museum, via a heat exchanger fed by four pipes carrying water from the [[Hudson River]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Using the Hudson to Cool the Trade Center |first=David W. |last=Dunlap |url=http://cityroom.blogs.nytimes.com/2009/04/06/using-the-hudson-to-cool-the-trade-center/ |newspaper=[[The New York Times]] |date=April 6, 2009 |accessdate=2010-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; The cost for the transportation hub is estimated at $3.44 billion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Trade Center Transit Hub’s Cost Now Over $3.4 Billion| first=Michael M. |last=Grynbaum |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/02/25/nyregion/25ground-zero.html|date=February 24, 2011 |accessdate=2011-02-25|work= New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ny1.com/content/news_beats/transit/134565/port-authority-reports-increase-in-wtc-transit-hub-costs/ |title=Port Authority Reports Increase In WTC Transit Hub Costs |work=[[NY1]] |date=February 24, 2011 |accessdate=2011-02-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ny1.com/content/special_reports/911_a_decade_later/138224/9-11-a-decade-later--port-authority-downplays-wtc-transit-hub-s-rising-costs |title=9/11 A Decade Later: Port Authority Downplays WTC Transit Hub's Rising Costs |work=[[NY1]] |first=Bobby |last=Cuza |date=April 28, 2011| accessdate=2011-04-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other buildings===

====St. Nicholas Greek Orthodox Church====
Government officials have backed down from a July 2008 deal to relocate the [[St. Nicholas Greek Orthodox Church]], the only church destroyed in the September 11 attacks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.foxnews.com/politics/2010/08/18/leaders-disappointed-government-declares-deal-rebuild-ground-zero-church-dead/ |title=Decision Not to Rebuild Church Destroyed on 9/11 Surprises Greek Orthodox Leaders |author=David Lee Miller,Kathleen Foster and Judson Berger   |date=18 August 2010 |work= |publisher=Fox News |accessdate=26 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.ny1.com/content/top_stories/133950/church-destroyed-on-9-11-files-suit-against-port-authority| title=Church Destroyed On 9/11 Files Suit Against Port Authority| work=[[NY1]]| date=February 14, 2011| accessdate=2011-02-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A deal has been reached between church officials, Governor Andrew Cuomo, and the Port Authority to have the church rebuilt on the same site, but three times the original size on October 14, 2011, according to [[NY1]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.ny1.com/content/top_stories/148968/historic-church-destroyed-on-9-11-to-rise-again| title=Historic Church Destroyed On 9/11 To Rise Again| work=[[NY1]]| date=October 14, 2011| accessdate=2011-10-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Criticism of progress===

An episode of [[CBS]]'s ''60 Minutes'' in 2010 focused on the lack of progress at Ground Zero, particularly on the lack of completion dates for a majority of the buildings, the main tower, [[1 World Trade Center]] (previously known as the [[One World Trade Center|Freedom Tower]]) having gone through three different designs, and the delays and monetary expense involved.  Investor [[Larry Silverstein]] said that the Port Authority's estimated completion date for the entire site was 2037, and that billions of dollars had already been spent on the project, even though Ground Zero &quot;is still a hole in the ground.&quot; During an interview for the episode, Larry Silverstein said &quot;I am the most frustrated person in the world...I'm seventy-eight years of age; I want to see this thing done in my lifetime.&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2010/02/18/60minutes/main6220282.shtml?tag=contentMain;contentBody|title=Developer: Ground Zero a National Disgrace - 60 Minutes: Eight Years and Billions of Dollars Later, Part of 9/11 Site is Still Just a Big Hole|publisher=CBS News|date=2010-02-18|page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, it was noted that in early 2011, all 5 office towers of the World Trade Center are under construction with significant progress being made.  All of the towers will be opened between 2012–2016, with the [[National September 11 Memorial &amp; Museum]] already completed on the tenth anniversary of the attacks, on September 11, 2011.  Criticism of progress and calls for redesigns were mostly made in 2008 and 2009, when progress at the site was clearly not being made.

==Construction==
{{As of|2011|9}}, progress on the construction of the redesigned site is as follows:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ny1.com/content/top_stories/124930/developers--state-officials-to-discuss-progress-at-wtc-site Developers, State Officials To Discuss Progress At WTC Site] NY1 local news channel. Retrieved September 3, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ny1.com/content/top_stories/125031/officials-offer-update-on-progress-at-world-trade-center-site Officials Offer Update On Progress At World Trade Center Site] NY1 local news channel. Retrieved September 8, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ny1.com/content/special_reports/wtc_coverage/125257/9-11-anniversary--pace-picks-up-for-wtc-construction 9/11 Anniversary: Pace Picks Up For WTC Construction] NY1 local news channel. Retrieved September 10, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://manhattan.ny1.com/content/top_stories/131117/2010-world-trade-center-site-progress-in-review--major-milestones-reached-in-redevelopment |title=2010 World Trade Center Site Progress In Review: Major Milestones Reached In Redevelopment| work=[[NY1]]| first=Rebecca| last=Spitz| date=December 23, 2010| accessdate=2010-12-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ny1.com/content/special_reports/911_a_decade_later/137291/9-11-a-decade-later--reconstruction-effort-picks-up-at-wtc-site |title=9/11 A Decade Later: Reconstruction Effort Picks Up At WTC Site |work=[[NY1]] |first=Bobby |last=Cuza |date=April 12, 2011 |accessdate=2011-04-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.ny1.com/content/top_stories/146573/mayor--wtc-developer-say-trade-center-site-has-new-lease-on-life| title=Mayor, WTC Developer Say Trade Center Site Has New Lease On Life| work=[[NY1]]| first=Michael| last=Herzenberg| date=September 7, 2011| accessdate=2011-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[One World Trade Center|1 World Trade Center]] – Construction began in April 2006; two years later, tower-foundation steel columns, concrete, and rebar had been installed. In 2006, the Port Authority took over from Silverstein Properties as the project's developer. [[Tishman Realty &amp; Construction|Tishman Construction Corporation]] is the construction manager.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.wtc.com/about/freedom-tower |title=Freedom Tower |publisher=Silverstein Properties |year=2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;  One World Trade Center has just been topped out in August 2012, and should be completed in Summer 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.ny1.com/content/special_reports/911_a_decade_later/146319/9-11-a-decade-later--one-world-trade-center-rises-in-lower-manhattan| title=9/11 A Decade Later: One World Trade Center Rises In Lower Manhattan| work=[[NY1]]| first=Bobby| last=Cuza| date=September 2, 2011| accessdate=2011-09-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Two World Trade Center|2 World Trade Center]] – Groundbreaking in July 2008. A ground-level podium will be built to ground level by 2012, further construction will start while the real estate demands increase.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.wtc.com/about/office-tower-2/office-tower-2-schedule |title=Tower 2 |publisher=Silverstein Properties |year=2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Three World Trade Center|3 World Trade Center]] – Groundbreaking in March 2008.  Will be completed in 2014. In April 2008, excavation and preparations for foundation work took place.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.wtc.com/news/wtc-site-construction-update-april-2008 |title=WTC Construction Update, April |publisher=Silverstein Properties |year=2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Four World Trade Center|4 World Trade Center]] – Construction began in 2008.  Will be completed in 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.wtc.com/about/office-tower-4/office-tower-4-schedule |title=Tower 4 Schedule |publisher=Silverstein Properties |year=2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ny1.com/content/top_stories/124416/port-authority-approves-wtc-construction-plan Port Authority Approves WTC Construction Plan] NY1 local news channel. Retrieved August 26, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ny1.com/content/top_stories/134620/city-shells-out--32-9m-to-lease-space-at-world-trade-center |title=City Shells Out $32.9M To Lease Space At World Trade Center |work=[[NY1]] |date=February 25, 2011 |accessdate=2011-02-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.ny1.com/content/special_reports/911_a_decade_later/137886/9-11-a-decade-later--tower-four-emerges-from-the-ground| title=9/11 A Decade Later: Tower Four Emerges From The Ground| work=[[NY1]]| first=Bobby| last=Cuza| date=April 22, 2011| accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Five World Trade Center|5 World Trade Center]] – Construction began on September 9, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/05/01/nyregion/01deutsche.html |title=Work to Resume at Burned Bank Tower |date=May 1, 2008 |agency=The Associated Press |newspaper=[[The New York Times]] |accessdate=2010-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Port Authority acts as the building's developer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.wtc.com/about/office-tower-5 |title=Tower 5 |publisher=Silverstein Properties |year=2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[7 World Trade Center]] – Opened on May 23, 2006 and achieved [[Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design|LEED]] gold status.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.wtc.com/about/office-tower-7 |title=Tower 7 |publisher=Silverstein Properties |year=2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[National September 11 Memorial &amp; Museum]] – Partially complete. The Memorial opened on [[September 11 attacks|September 11]], 2011, coinciding with the 10th anniversary of the attacks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.wtc.com/about/memorial-and-museum-schedule |title=Memorial &amp; Museum, Schedule |publisher=Silverstein Properties |year=2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.ny1.com/content/911_tenth_anniversary/911_top_stories/146403/wtc-memorial-ready-for-public-unveiling| title=WTC Memorial Ready For Public Unveiling| work=[[NY1]]| first=Bobby| last=Cuza| date=September 5, 2011| accessdate=2011-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; The museum will open in September 2013.
*Performing Arts Center – Construction will begin after 2014 since a temporary exit from the PATH station will occupy the site until then.&lt;ref&gt;http://wtc.com/about/performing-arts-center&lt;/ref&gt;

===Construction gallery===
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:New York Ground Zero.png|A light still on at Ground Zero remains, 2001.
Image:GroundZeroExcavation.JPG|From the south, a view of ongoing excavation in July 2002. The slurry wall circumscribing the site is visible, as is the damaged [[Verizon Building]] in the background.
Image:Groundzero2002 cc.jpg|Aerial view of the site from the northwest, 2002.
Image:Wtcsite.JPG|The World Trade Center site after cleanup, 2003.
Image:Groundzero212292005.JPG|Visitor and observation plaza, 2005.
File:WTCConstruction-March-2010.jpeg|Construction as of March 2, 2010. The frame for Tower 4 can be seen rising on the left. 
File:World Trade Center site 2010.jpg|Overhead, April 2010
File:One WTC From W Hotel 7-28-10.JPG|From the 30th floor of the W Hotel, July 28, 2010
File:WTCJune1st1.JPG|One World Trade Center on June 1, 2011. Tower steel is prepared to grow up to the 68th floor.
File:1WTC28Jan2012.png|One World Trade Center on January 28, 2012. Glass has been placed higher than [[7 World Trade Center]].
File:4WTC-March 12, 2012.JPG|[[Four World Trade Center]] under construction on March 12, 2012.
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|New York City}}
{{Commons category|World Trade Center site}}
*[[Collapse of the World Trade Center]]
*[[Construction of One World Trade Center]]
*[[Health effects arising from the September 11 attacks]]
*[[Survivors' Staircase]]
*[[Verizon Building]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.wtc.com Official site] - Silverstein Properties
*[http://www.tributewtc.org 9/11 Tribute Center]
*[http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2010/09/10/nyregion/2010-wtc.html?ref=multimedia Reviving Ground Zero] - interactive slideshow with audio by ''[[The New York Times]]''
*[http://www.panynj.gov/drp/ Downtown Restoration Program] - Port Authority of New York &amp; New Jersey
*[http://www.national911memorial.org/ National September 11 Memorial &amp; Museum at the World Trade Center]
*[http://www.projectrebirth.org/ Project Rebirth]
*[http://www.wtcrising.com World Trade Center Rising]
*[http://www.rebuildgroundzero.org RebuildGroundZero.org, a community project based on Ground Zero's rebuilding.]
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AbZRL1mDtbI The Freedom Tower] (YouTube)
{{Coord|40.711641|N|74.012253|W|region:US-NY_type:landmark|display=title}}

{{WTC navigation}}
{{PANYNJ navbox}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:World Trade Center Site}}
[[Category:Buildings and structures under construction in the United States]]
[[Category:Mosque-related controversies]]
[[Category:World Trade Center]]
[[Category:Aftermath of the September 11 attacks]]

[[de:World Trade Center Site]]
[[fa:مرکز تجارت جهانی]]
[[fr:Site du World Trade Center]]
[[id:Lahan World Trade Center]]
[[ms:Tapak World Trade Center]]
[[no:Ground Zero (World Trade Center)]]
[[pt:Ground Zero (Nova Iorque)]]</text>
      <sha1>12hi9s64hlvjmdvhrmh1xg94yeri373</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
