<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Brüno</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>17997162</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519008427</id>
      <parentid>519007110</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-21T12:15:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Vsmith</username>
        <id>84417</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[Help:Reverting|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/85.210.12.234|85.210.12.234]] ([[User talk:85.210.12.234|talk]]) to last version by MinghamSmith</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="35312">{{about|the film|the character|Brüno (character)}}
{{Infobox film
| name           = Brüno
| image          = Bruno poster.jpg
| image_size     = 215px
| alt            =
| caption        = Promotional film poster
| director       = [[Larry Charles]]
| producer       = [[Sacha Baron Cohen]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Jay Roach]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Dan Mazer]]&lt;br&gt;[[Jonah Hill]]
| screenplay     = Sacha Baron Cohen&lt;br /&gt;Anthony Hines&lt;br /&gt;Dan Mazer&lt;br /&gt;[[Jeff Schaffer]]
| story          = Sacha Baron Cohen&lt;br /&gt;[[Peter Baynham]]&lt;br /&gt;Anthony Hines&lt;br /&gt;Dan Mazer
| starring       = Sacha Baron Cohen
| music          = [[Erran Baron Cohen]]
| cinematography = Anthony Hardwick&lt;br /&gt;Wolfgang Held
| editing        = Scott Davids&lt;br /&gt;James Thomas
| studio         = [[Media Rights Capital]]&lt;br /&gt;Everyman Pictures
| distributor    = [[Universal Pictures]]
| released       = {{Film date|df=yes|2009|7|10}}
| runtime        = 81 minutes&lt;!-- U.S. theatrical release: 81:17 --&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bbfc&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.bbfc.co.uk/website/Classified.nsf/ClassifiedWorks/c3c2314f90328d70802575e800461a4b | title=Brüno rated 18 by the BBFC | publisher=[[British Board of Film Classification|BBFC]] | date=2009-07-03 | accessdate=2009-07-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
| country        = United Kingdom
| language       = English&lt;br /&gt;German
| budget         =
| gross          = $138,805,831&lt;!-- When updating this number, be sure to update the accessdate in the reference immediately following!--&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;boxofficemojo&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=bruno.htm |title=Bruno (2009) |work=[[Box Office Mojo]] |accessdate=May 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

'''''Brüno'''''  is a 2009 British [[mockumentary]] [[comedy film]] directed by [[Larry Charles]] and starring [[Sacha Baron Cohen]], who produced, co-wrote, and played the [[homosexuality|gay]] [[Austria]]n [[Fashion journalism|fashion journalist]] [[Brüno (character)|Brüno]]. It is the third and final film based on Baron Cohen's characters from ''[[Da Ali G Show]]''; the first were ''[[Ali G Indahouse]]'' and ''[[Borat]]''.

==Plot==
[[Homosexuality|Gay]] [[Austria]]n [[Fashion journalism|fashion reporter]] [[Brüno (character)|Brüno]] is fired from his own television show, ''Funkyzeit mit Brüno (Funkytime with Brüno)'' after disrupting a [[Milan]] [[Fashion week]] catwalk (whose audience included [[Paul McCartney]]), and his lover Diesel ([[Clifford Bañagale]]) leaves him for another man. Accompanied by his assistant's assistant, Lutz ([[Gustaf Hammarsten]]), he travels to the [[United States]] to become &quot;the biggest Austrian superstar since [[Adolf Hitler|Hitler]]&quot;.

Brüno unsuccessfully attempts an acting career as an [[Extra (actor)|extra]] on [[NBC]]'s ''[[Medium (TV series)|Medium]]''. He then interviews [[Paula Abdul]], using &quot;Mexican chair-people&quot; in place of furniture (Abdul goes along with everything, explaining how she aspires to help people, until a naked man, adorned with [[sushi]], is wheeled into the room). He then produces a celebrity interview [[Television pilot|pilot]], showing him dancing erotically, criticizing [[Jamie-Lynn Spears]]' fetus with reality TV star [[Brittny Gastineau]], unsuccessfully attempting to “interview&quot; actor [[Harrison Ford]], and closing with a close-up of his [[penis]] being swung around by pelvic gyrations. A [[focus group]] reviewing the pilot hate it, calling it &quot;worse than cancer&quot;. Brüno then decides to make a [[sex tape]], so he interviews [[Ron Paul]], claiming to have mistaken him for [[drag queen]] [[RuPaul]]. While waiting in a hotel room with Paul, Brüno flirts with him before undressing, causing Paul to leave angrily and call him &quot;queer as blazes&quot;.

Brüno consults a [[Spiritualism|spiritualist]] (Gary Williams) to contact the deceased [[Rob Pilatus]] of [[Milli Vanilli]] for advice, [[Mime|miming]] various sex acts on the invisible &quot;Pilatus&quot;. He consults charity PR consultants Nicole and Suzanne DeFosset to select a world problem to maximize his fame, choosing the [[Israeli-Palestinian conflict]]. He flies to [[Jerusalem]] to interview former [[Mossad]] agent [[Yossi Alpher]] and [[Palestinian people|Palestinian]] politician [[Ghassan Khatib]] and confuses [[hummus]] and [[Hamas]]. In an interview with [[Israel]]i and Palestinian professors he sings his own &quot;Dove of Peace&quot; while forcing the two to caress each others hands. He also meets with Ayman Abu Aita, a &quot;terrorist group leader, [[Al-Aqsa Martyrs' Brigades]]&quot; in a location described as a Palestinian refugee camp in [[Lebanon]], where he hopes to be kidnapped.&lt;ref&gt;The actual location, according to Abu Aita, was a private section of a popular restaurant at the [http://www.palestinehotels.ps/hotel.php?hid=5 Everest Hotel] in the town of [[Beit Jala]], in a section of the [[West Bank]] opposite [[Bethlehem]] under Israeli control. [[Al-Aqsa Martyrs' Brigades]] is a coalition of Palestinian militias in the West Bank. Abu Aita claims to be unaffiliated with Al-Aqsa and pursued legal action against Cohen.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2009/07/13/ayman-abu-aita-brunos-ter_n_230443.html &quot;Ayman Abu Aita, Bruno's 'Terrorist', Threatens Legal Action&quot;, July 13, 2009, [[The Huffington Post]]]&lt;/ref&gt; Brüno insults Abu Aita's hair then says that &quot;King [[Osama bin Laden|Osama]]&quot; looks like a dirty [[Wizard (fantasy)|wizard]] or a homeless [[Santa Claus]]. Abu Aita's translator orders Brüno to leave. He stops off in [[Nairobi]] to pick up a few things, including a child, saying he is &quot;black gold&quot;.

Brüno interviews parents of [[child model]]s, asking if their toddlers would be ready to lose weight, undergo [[liposuction]], operate &quot;antiquated heavy machinery&quot; or &quot;amateur science&quot;, or dress in [[Nazi uniform]]s. On a talk show hosted by [[Richard Bey]], he shows the [[African American]] audience a baby he named [[O.J. Simpson|O.J.]], whom he acquired in Africa by &quot;swapping him&quot; for a [[U2]] [[Product Red]] [[iPod]]. He shows photographs of the boy covered with bees, on a [[crucifix]] and in a [[jacuzzi]] next to adults in a 69 position. The audience is appalled and [[social services]] take the baby from Brüno, driving him to depression. He goes to a [[diner]] to gorge on high-[[carbohydrate|carb]] junk food. Lutz carries him back to a hotel room. After a night of sex, they awake to find themselves trapped in a [[Bondage (BDSM)|bondage]] mechanism, unable to find the key. They call a hotel engineer for help and are asked to leave. After accosting a group of anti-gay protesters from the [[Westboro Baptist Church]] while still in bondage gear and boarding a bus, Brüno and Lutz remove their equipment at Madison County Office of Alternative Sentencing and Release in Huntsville, Alabama.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.co.madison.al.us/courts/courts/release.shtml |title=Office of Alternative Sentencing |publisher=Co.madison.al.us |date= |accessdate=2011-02-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; after being arrested. Lutz says he loves Brüno but Brüno tells him he does not love him, having been influenced by &quot;[[Beer goggles|carb goggles]]&quot;. Lutz leaves Brüno.

After realizing the biggest names in [[Hollywood]] are straight (citing [[Tom Cruise#Litigation|Tom Cruise]], [[Kevin Spacey#Personal life|Kevin Spacey]] and [[John Travolta]]), Brüno consults two Christian [[Conversion therapy|gay converter]]s to help him become [[heterosexual]]. He attempts activities, such as joining the [[National Guard of the United States|National Guard]], going [[hunting]] in Alabama, learning [[karate]] and attending a [[Swinging|swinger]]s party at which he is whipped by a [[dominatrix]] (played by pornstar Michelle McLaren). These attempts end miserably due to Brüno's failure to keep his gay traits hidden, but he vows to become straight.

Eight months later, a now-heterosexual Brüno, under the alias &quot;Straight Dave&quot;, hosts a [[cage fighting|cage-fight match]] in [[Arkansas]], &quot;Straight Dave's Man Slammin' Maxout&quot;. Lutz appears at the event and calls Brüno a [[Faggot (slang)|faggot]]. The two fight, only to rekindle their love, making out and stripping in front of the shocked spectators who throw objects into the cage. The clip gets international press and the now-famous Brüno attempts to marry Lutz and gets O.J. back in exchange for a [[MacBook Pro]]. Brüno records a charity song, &quot;Dove of Peace&quot;, featuring [[Bono]], [[Elton John]] (seated at a [[piano]] on a Mexican “chair-person“), [[Chris Martin]], [[Snoop Dogg]], [[Sting (musician)|Sting]] and [[Slash (musician)|Slash]] at [[Abbey Road Studios]].

==Deleted scenes==
The trailers for the film shown in the U.S. included a scene in which Brüno shops for clothing at [[Sears]], telling the sales clerk &quot;You might find this very hard to believe, but I'm gay&quot; to which the clerk responds &quot;Okay&quot;, while maintaining an awkward posture.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.npr.org/blogs/monkeysee/2009/06/monkey_see_presents_bruno_the.html Monkey See Presents: 'Bruno,' The Annotated Trailer]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Michael Jackson incident===
Following the sudden [[death of Michael Jackson]] on 25 June 2009, a scene from ''Brüno'' was hastily removed from the US theatrical version of the film before its [[Hollywood]] [[Film premiere|premiere]] later that evening. The scene involved Brüno tricking [[LaToya Jackson]] into an interview in which he asked her to take a seat on hunched over [[Mexican people|Mexican]] workers substituting for chairs and invited her to eat [[sushi]] from the torso of a naked man. Brüno then asked LaToya to let him look at her mobile phone in order to get her brother Michael's phone number. The scene was later confirmed to be removed from the film permanently, but is included in the DVD and Blu-ray release's special features.&lt;ref&gt;(26 June 2009)[http://news-briefs.ew.com/2009/06/bruno-michael-jackson.html Bruno: Michael Jackson-related scene permanently cut from film]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Production==

During Baron Cohen's Middle East interview of Alpher and Khatib, he repeatedly conflated [[Hamas]] and [[hummus]] and feigned belief that the conflict was between [[Jew]]s and [[Hindus]]. The two interviewees (who had received a fee to appear on camera), convinced by the elaborate production, were confused by the questions but generally went along, even when asked by Baron Cohen to hold hands.&lt;ref&gt;Alpher, Yossi  (July 11, 2008), [http://www.forward.com/articles/13679/ What Kind of Interviewer Confuses Hamas and Hummus?], [[The Forward]]&lt;/ref&gt;

On June 6, 2008, a riot ensued at a stunt orchestrated by Baron Cohen and the producers of the film as they staged a &quot;Blue Collar Brawlin'&quot; in [[Fort Smith, Arkansas]]. Patrons were lured to an event billed as [[cage fighting]], held at a convention center, by print and [[Craigslist]] advertisements, promoting &quot;hot girls&quot;, $1 beer, and $5 admission. Approximately 1500 people attended the event and were greeted by signs that informed them that they were being filmed. No mobile phones, video, or cameras were allowed inside. The acts taking place became homosexual in nature, with Brüno inviting a man up to fight him, who turned out to be Lutz. [[Celine Dion]]'s &quot;[[My Heart Will Go On]]&quot; starts to play and they both start kissing and stripping, the audience reacted violently and began throwing chairs and beer at the performers. The performers were Brüno (Baron Cohen) under the ironic gimmick, &quot;Straight Dave&quot;, and Gustaf Hammarsten portraying his opponent, Lutz.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thesmokinggun.com/archive/years/2008/0708081bruno1.html &quot;Bruno&quot; Pranks It Up]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dn.se/kultur-noje/film-tv/aktuell-i-sacha-baron-cohen-filmen-bruno-1.890119 Gustaf Hammarsten - stjärna med rätt att tiga]&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 2008, [[Tyler, Texas]] television station [[KETK-TV]] was approached by a &quot;[[documentary film]]-maker&quot; who was allowed to bring a crew to interview a few members of the staff, including news director Neal Barton and sports director Danny Elzner. They signed releases and expected to be talking about small-town news in the United States. Instead, the interviews conducted by the flamboyant Brüno character drifted towards the topic of [[homosexuality]].&lt;ref&gt;(July 11, 2008), [http://www.newsblues.com/Secure/Bluezette/2008/07-11-08.htm NewsBlues- Brüno Dupes KETK] (Subscription Required)&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2008, video and photographs were released showing Baron Cohen (as Brüno) storming the catwalk with objects on his velcro outfit during an [[Ágatha Ruiz de la Prada]] [[fashion show]] in [[Milan]] (at which [[Paul McCartney]] also was present). Baron Cohen managed to walk down the [[Runway (fashion)|runway]] for a few moments before lights were dimmed and security guards escorted him away. This occurred after Baron Cohen and his crew were allegedly stopped by security while attempting to enter back-stage at two other shows during Milan's [[fashion week]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dailymail.co.uk/tvshowbiz/article-1062374/VIDEO-Sacha-Baron-Cohen-held-police-outrageous-stunt-Milan-catwalk.html VIDEO: Sacha Baron Cohen Hashim Malik held by police after outrageous stunt on Milan catwalk]  ''[[Mail Online]]''. Retrieved September 26, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

On November 2, 2008, Baron Cohen, dressed as Brüno, and his film crew were spotted at a [[Los Angeles]] rally that was in support of [[California]]'s [[California Proposition 8 (2008)|Proposition 8]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.chicagotribune.com/entertainment/chi-sacha-baron-cohen-ft-1104nov04,0,6388234.story&lt;/ref&gt; 

On November 7, 2008, while appearing as an extra in a scene for the [[NBC]] TV series ''[[Medium (TV series)|Medium]]'', Baron Cohen interrupted a scene in character and was removed from the set. Production on the episode was shut down temporarily,&lt;ref&gt;Ausiello, Michael (November 7, 2008). &quot;[http://ausiellofiles.ew.com/2008/11/sacha-baron-coh.html?iid=top25-20081117-Exclusive%3A+Bruno+(a.k.a.)+Sacha+Baron+Cohen+Disrupts+%27Medium%27 Exclusive: Bruno (a.k.a.) Sacha Baron Cohen Disrupts 'Medium']&quot;, ''[[Entertainment Weekly]]'', Retrieved on November 19, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; though actor [[Miguel Sandoval]], who was told that a cousin of NBC executive Ben Silverman would appear as an extra in the jury, has stated that he recognized Baron Cohen and played along, commenting, &quot;It's one thing for Borat to go into an antique store in Georgia or Alabama. For Brüno to go on a TV show, he's among insiders. Most people knew who he was.&quot;&lt;ref name=TVGuide&gt;&quot;Is 'Brüno' Real or Fake?&quot; ''[[TV Guide]]''; July 27, 2009; Page 9&lt;/ref&gt;{{better source|date=July 2012}}

The production team also deceived presidential candidate [[Ron Paul]] into being interviewed by Brüno by posing as an Austrian television reporter looking to question the congressman about economic issues. As soon as Brüno drops his trousers, the congressman storms out of the room. A spokeswoman for Paul commented on the incident. She said Baron Cohen's people were very deceptive in their tactics. At the time, she thought they were &quot;legitimate&quot; but later confessed to some concern. &quot;I'm familiar with his work, so you can imagine how I feel about it,&quot; she said. Jesse Benton, senior vice-president of Ron Paul's [[Campaign for Liberty]] organization and former campaign spokesman for Paul, said Paul was not familiar with Baron Cohen's programme, ''[[Da Ali G Show]]''. &quot;If it's not on hard-core financial news, he doesn't follow it,&quot; Benton said. But, he added, &quot;It sounds like it's going to be pretty funny.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.slate.com/id/2213882/&lt;/ref&gt;

The scene filmed during a taping of ''[[The Richard Bey Show]]'', however, was staged, as [[Richard Bey|Bey]] was in on the joke, as his daytime show went off the air in 1996. The audience, however, was not made aware of the truth of the production. Similarly unaware of the true nature of the production was [[Paula Abdul]], who, during her interview scene in the film, sat atop a Mexican landscaper and was presented with food adorned upon a man lying down on a cart wearing nothing but a &quot;sock&quot; over his penis. Abdul told a radio interviewer that she was &quot;scarred&quot; by the incident.&lt;ref name=TVGuide/&gt;

Baron Cohen suffered a severe reaction to [[hydrogen peroxide]] after bleaching his hair in preparation for the role of Brüno. Although the incident temporarily slowed the production of the film, he suffered no long-lasting injuries.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/showbiz/bizarre/article2418138.ece&lt;/ref&gt;

==Release==
Though the film was originally slated for a May 15, 2009 release,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.variety.com/VR1117987606.html &quot;Universal sets a date for 'Bruno'.&quot;] Variety.com. June 17, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; the release was later moved to July 10, 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;BrunoBumped&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117999050.html?categoryid=1236&amp;cs=1|title=Universal bumps 'Bruno' to July|last=McClintock|first=Pamela|work=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|publisher=[[Reed Business Information|RBI]]|date=2009-01-25|accessdate=2009-01-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film received an early release in [[Australia]], [[Switzerland]], [[Belgium]], the [[Netherlands]], [[New Zealand]],&lt;ref name=&quot;NZ_Herald_10579056&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nzherald.co.nz/movies/news/article.cfm?c_id=200&amp;objectid=10579056 |title=Sneak {{sic|nolink=y|Peak}} at Bruno |date=June 18, 2009 |work=[[The New Zealand Herald]] |accessdate=September 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Iceland]] on July 8 and in [[Germany]], [[Greece]], [[Ireland]], [[Serbia]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.srbijanet.rs/kultura/film/21536-bruno.html Premijera filma &quot;Bruno&quot; u Domu sindikata], SrbijaNet {{Sr icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Slovenia]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kolosej.si/filmi/film/brueno/ Kolosej Slovenia]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Israel]],  and [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://sarajevo.co.ba/bruno-u-sarajevu-prije-ostatka-svijeta/ Bruno u Sarajevu prije ostatka svijeta]&lt;/ref&gt; on July 9, 2009. The film was then released internationally on July 10.{{citation needed|date=July 2012}}

===Promotion===
In a staged publicity stunt at the [[2009 MTV Movie Awards]], Baron Cohen appeared as Brüno to present the award for Best Male Performer. Dressed as a winged angel wearing a [[jockstrap]] and white [[go-go boots]], he was suspended on wires and flew over the audience towards the stage, but fell and landed on rapper [[Eminem]], with his head in Eminem's lap and his [[buttocks]] in front of Eminem's face. Eminem shouted, &quot;Are you fucking serious?&quot; and, &quot;Get this motherfucker off me!&quot;, Eminem and his entourage then walked out of the show and did not return. It was later revealed that Eminem and Baron Cohen had staged the incident, rehearsing it beforehand to make sure it went off without a hitch, and leaving Eminem laughing to himself in his hotel room about how the crowd was easily fooled.&lt;ref&gt;(June 2009), [http://hollywoodinsider.ew.com/2009/06/sources-eminembruno-stunt-on-mtv-movie-awards-was-staged.html Eminem vs. Bruno Staged], [[Hollywood Insider]]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ban in Ukraine===
In [[Ukraine]], the film was scheduled to premiere on July 23, but on July 14, the Minister of Culture and Tourism of Ukraine decided to ban the distribution and demonstration of the film in the country.&lt;ref name=UkraiBan&gt;[http://www.kyivpost.com/guide/guidenews/45221 &quot;'Bruno' banned in Ukraine&quot;], [[Kyiv Post]] (July 14, 2009)&lt;/ref&gt; The reason for the prohibition was that nine out of 14 experts of a commission of experts said the film contained &quot;obscene language, homosexual scenes, and other scenes of offensive nature never shown in Ukraine.&lt;ref name=UkraiBan/&gt;{{Failed verification|date=November 2010}} The &quot;[[Vinnytsya]] Human Rights Group&quot; immediately expressed its anger with the ban.&lt;ref&gt;[http://tsn.ua/ua/glamur/events/vinnitski-pravozahisniki-zaklikayut-oskarzhiti-rishennya-pro-zaboronu-bruno.html Вінницькі правозахисники закликають оскаржити рішення про заборону &quot;Бруно&quot;], TCH (July 16, 2009) {{uk icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; An unofficial premiere of the film in [[Kiev]] on July 22, 2009 was disrupted by a [[smoke bomb]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://tsn.ua/ua/glamur/skandali/u-kiyevi-ziravano-prem-yeru-bruno.html У Києві зірвано прем’єру “Бруно“], TCH (July 23, 2009) {{uk icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://photo.unian.net/eng/themes/13738 Events by themes: «Bruno» film unofficial premiere is wrecked in Kiev], [[UNIAN]] (July 22, 2009)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Home media===
The film was released on [[DVD]] and [[Blu-ray Disc|Blu-ray]] on November 17, 2009. Special features include [[Deleted scene|deleted/alternate/extended scenes]] and an [[audio commentary]] by Sacha Baron Cohen and Larry Charles.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.moviefone.com/movie/bruno/34365/dvd Bruno(2009) DVD Details - Moviefone]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reception==
===Reviews===
Among critics and the public, ''Brüno'' has received mixed to positive reviews, with general feelings about the film being not as strong as Baron Cohen's previous film, ''[[Borat]]''. However, reviews of the premiere screenings of ''Brüno'' were generally positive among audiences. Nick Curtis of the ''[[Evening Standard]]'' wrote that ''Brüno'' is &quot;funnier, more offensive, and more outrageous than Borat&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, Nick, (18 June 2009),[http://www.thisislondon.co.uk/film/film-23373524-details/Bruno/filmReview.do?reviewId=23709056 First review: Brüno is gay, offensive ... and very funny], ''[[London Evening Standard]]''&lt;/ref&gt; ''The Telegraph'' gave the film four stars out of four, saying &quot;impossible not to laugh and also praising Brüno's controversial style of comedy.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Hiscock, John, (18 June 2009), [http://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/sacha-baron-cohen/5570132/Bruno-review.html Brüno, review Gross, offensive, and very, very funny: Sacha Baron Cohen's new satire, Brüno, pushes the boundaries of bad taste to the limit], ''[[The Daily Telegraph|The Telegraph]]''&lt;/ref&gt; The BBC also gave the film a positive review, saying &quot;Brüno pushes the boundaries further than Borat ever did.&quot; However, they also said that &quot;It's not going to be everyone's cup of tea&quot; due to the offensive nature of the film.&lt;ref&gt;(18 June 2009) [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/8106729.stm Bruno Review] ''[[BBC]]''&lt;/ref&gt; [[Roger Ebert]] awarded the film three and a half out of four stars, and said &quot;Here is a film that is 82 minutes long and doesn't contain 30 boring seconds&quot;, although he noted that the film's R rating was &quot;very, very hard&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert, Roger, (July 8, 2009) [http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20090708/REVIEWS/907089995 Bruno]&lt;/ref&gt;

Andy Lowe from ''[[Total Film]]'' gave it a lower review, giving it three stars out of five and calling it &quot;as phony and frustrating as it is funny... The clothes may be new and more fabulous, but the emperor seriously needs to go shopping.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;tf&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.totalfilm.com/reviews/cinema/bruno|title=''Bruno'' Movie Reviews|work=[[Total Film]]|publisher=''Future Publishing''|accessdate=2009-07-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Others felt it was not as good, feeling it would insult and offend the gay community: [[A. O. Scott]] of ''[[The New York Times]]'' wrote that the film shows &quot;that lampooning homophobia has become an acceptable, almost unavoidable form of homophobic humor,&quot; and called the film &quot;a lazy piece of work that panders more than it provokes.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://movies.nytimes.com/2009/07/10/movies/10bruno.html &quot;Teutonic Fashion Plate Flaunts His Umlauts&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[At the Movies (U.S. TV series)|At the Movies]]'' critic [[Ben Mankiewicz]] criticized the film for being too demeaning and playing on homosexual stereotypes. He later named ''Brüno'' the worst film at the halfway point of 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://bventertainment.go.com/tv/buenavista/atm/ ]{{dead link|date=February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Metacritic]] gives ''Brüno'' an average score of 54, suggesting &quot;mixed or average reviews&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.metacritic.com/movie/bruno |title=Brüno Reviews, Ratings, Credits, and More at Metacritic |publisher=Metacritic.com |date=2009-07-10 |accessdate=2011-02-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;
However, it currently holds a 67% &quot;fresh&quot; rating on [[Rotten Tomatoes]] and is advertised as a &quot;Certified Fresh Pick&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/bruno/ |title = Bruno (2009) |accessdate = 2009-07-12 |publisher = [[Rotten Tomatoes]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;  For its opening weekend, it narrowly beat ''[[Ice Age: Dawn of the Dinosaurs]]'' (in its second week of release) for the highest gross, in the lowest attended second-weekend-in-July in 18 years.&lt;ref&gt;[http://boxofficemojo.com/news/?id=2603&amp;p=.htm Box Office Mojo report on opening weekend]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reception in Austria===
While ''Borat'' was [[Borat#Criticism by Kazakhstan|criticised in Kazakhstan]], [[Austria]]ns were generally positive about ''Brüno''. Some commented that the film places Austria in the spotlight, and that &quot;it might stop people confusing Austria with [[Australia]].&quot; Others regarded the humour as &quot;pretty average&quot; and &quot;inoffensive to Austria.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://au.news.yahoo.com/a/-/odd/5718144 Austrians say outrageous Bruno ist pretty funny - Yahoo!7 News]&lt;/ref&gt; Within the Austrian press, reactions have been generally mild and positive, although the film has also been labelled as &quot;repetitive&quot;. Christian Fuchs, from the Austrian radio station FM4, writes that &quot;hidden beneath the hard-as-nails satirist Cohen, lies a humanist who enlightens.&quot; However, the film has also met some opposition in Austria, due to its portrayal of homosexuality, and basing the portrayal of Austria on motifs such as [[Josef Fritzl]] and [[Adolf Hitler|Hitler]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://au.news.yahoo.com/a/-/odd/5716326/bruno-tells-austrians-to-get-uber-it/ Bruno tells Austrians to 'get über it' - Yahoo!7 News]&lt;/ref&gt; even going as far as calling [[Mel Gibson]] &quot;der [[Führer]]&quot;.{{Citation needed|date=July 2012}}

===Box office===
''Brüno'' opened with $30 million in its first weekend. It has made $136,933,838 worldwide of which $60,054,530 was from Canada and the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;boxofficemojo&quot;/&gt;

===LGBT response===
Some [[LGBT]] groups have criticised the character as perpetuating [[LGBT stereotypes]] while simultaneously enlightening institutionalised [[homophobia]] issues.&lt;ref name=&quot;News&quot;&gt;[http://www.reuters.com/article/domesticNews/idUSTRE55G06P20090617 Reuters &quot;Cohen camps it up as Queen's guard for UK premiere&quot;,By Cindy Martin and Mike Collett-White June 17, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Sacha Baron Cohen's well-meaning attempt at [[satire]] is problematic in many places and outright offensive in others,&quot; Rashad Robinson, senior director of media programs for the [[Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation]] (GLAAD) told ''[[The New York Times]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;CNN&quot;&gt;[http://edition.cnn.com/2009/SHOWBIZ/Movies/06/18/bruno.baron.cohen/ CNN Showbiz &quot;'Vassup!' 'Bruno' hits the carpet for London premiere&quot; by Mairi Mackay, June 18, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Title===
An alternative title for the film is '''''Brüno: Delicious Journeys Through America for the Purpose of Making Heterosexual Males Visibly Uncomfortable in the Presence of a Gay Foreigner in a Mesh T-Shirt'''''. It was initially a mock title proposed by Hollywood news and gossip blog [[Defamer]]&lt;ref name=&quot;the curious&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Abramovitch|first=Seth|title=The Curious Case Of The Fake Defamer 'Bruno' Title That Ate The Internets|work=[[Defamer]]|publisher=[[Gawker Media]]|date=2008-06-18|url=http://defamer.com/5017659/the-curious-case-of-the-fake-defamer-bruno-title-that-ate-the-internets|accessdate=2008-07-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Graham|first=Mark|title=Universal Bets $42 Million That Sacha Baron Cohen Can Continue To Taunt Middle America With Naive-Foreigner Characters|work=[[Defamer]]|publisher=[[Gawker Media]]|date=2006-10-30|url=http://defamer.com/hollywood/borat/universal-bets-42-million-that-sacha-baron-cohen-can-continue-to-taunt-middle-america-with-naiveforeigner-characters-211085.php|accessdate=2008-07-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; and mistakenly reported as genuine by a number of sources of film information, including [[MovieTome]], where it is still used in the search results,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.movietome.com/search/index.php?qs=Bruno&amp;tag=searchtop%3Bbutton |title=Movie Reviews, Articles, Trailers, and more at Metacritic |publisher=Movietome.com |date= |accessdate=2011-02-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; the ''[[Daily Star (United Kingdom)|Daily Star]]'',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dailystar.co.uk/news/view/38763/Borat-s-in-the-khazi/ Borat’s in the Khazi]&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[The Irish Times]]'', ''[[The Boston Globe]]'',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.boston.com/ae/movies/articles/2009/07/10/bruno_is_no_borat/ Bruno is No Borat, by Wesley Morris]&lt;/ref&gt; and (although no longer) the [[Internet Movie Database]]. However, the official ''Brüno'' website lists the extended 'title' in its metadata.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thebrunomovie.com/ |title=Starring Sacha Baron Cohen |publisher=Bruno Movie |date= |accessdate=2011-02-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ayman Abu Aita lawsuit and Al Aqsa Martyrs Brigades===
On December 2, 2009, it was reported that Ayman Abu Aita, who stated he was falsely portrayed as a terrorist in the film, is filing a lawsuit of $110 million in libel damages for defamation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
 | last = Zongker 
 | first = Brett
 | title = Ayman Abu Aita Sues 'Bruno,' Letterman For $110M 
 | publisher = Huffington Post 
 | date = 2009-12-09
 | url = http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2009/12/09/ayman-abu-aita-sues-bruno_n_386294.html
 | accessdate = 2012-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
Ayman Abu Aita was identified in the film as a member of the [[Al Aqsa Martyrs Brigades]].&lt;ref name=&quot;thelede&quot;&gt;{{Citation
 | last = Mackey
 | first = Robert 
 | title = Did a Fake Interview With a 'Real Terrorist' in 'Brüno' Cross a Line?
 | publisher = New York Times
 | date = 2009-08-06
 | url = http://thelede.blogs.nytimes.com/2009/08/06/did-a-fake-interview-with-a-terrorist-in-bruno-cross-a-line/
 | accessdate = 2012-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Abu Aita says that he was never a member of Al Aqsa Martyrs Brigades, though he identified as such in a 2002 Boston Globe article.&lt;ref name=&quot;mcclatchy&quot;&gt;{{Citation
 | last = Nissenbaum
 | first = Dion
 | title = Palestinian 'terrorist' plans suit over unwitting role in 'Bruno' 
 | newspaper = McClatchy Newspapers
 | date = 2009-07-16
 | url = http://www.mcclatchydc.com/2009/07/16/71988/palestinian-terrorist-plans-suit.html
 | accessdate = 2012-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
 | last = Shadid  
 | first = Anthony
 | title = Fatah's Young Militants Vow to Fight on
 | newspaper = Boston Globe
 | date = 2002-03-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Baron Cohen claims he set up a meeting with Abu Aita in the West Bank with the help of a CIA agent. According to the lawsuit, however, the interview with Abu Aita took place at a hotel chosen by Baron Cohen and located in a part of the West Bank that was under Israeli military control.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2009/12/09/ayman-abu-aita-sues-bruno_n_386294.html | work=Huffington Post | title=Ayman Abu Aita Sues 'Bruno,' Letterman For $110M | date=December 9, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The filing of the lawsuit was confirmed at a press conference on December 2, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://blogs.wsj.com/law/2009/12/02/palestinian-deemed-terrorist-in-bruno-sues-nbc-sacha-baron-cohen/ Palestinian Deemed Terrorist in 'Bruno' Sues NBC, Baron Cohen - Wall Street Journal News Blog]&lt;/ref&gt;  Included in the lawsuit are [[David Letterman]], [[NBC Universal]], [[CBS]], [[Worldwide Pants]], [[Gannett Company]] and [[Larry Charles]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://online.wsj.com/public/resources/documents/12209abuaitacompl.pdf Lawsuit Camplaint - Wall Street Journal News Blog]&lt;/ref&gt;
In November 2010, the lawsuit was dismissed in Washington D.C. Court so as to be refiled in the Supreme Court of New York.&lt;ref&gt;[http://iapps.courts.state.ny.us/iscroll/SQLData.jsp?IndexNo=102524-2011# Supreme Court Records Online Library], case 102524-2011&lt;/ref&gt;

Baron Cohen has said he had to increase his security detail following death threats from the Al Aqsa Martyrs Brigade after the release of the film.&lt;ref&gt;[http://jta.org/news/article/2009/07/28/1006866/palestinian-group-threatens-sacha-baron-cohen#When:18:40:00Z &quot;Palestinian group threatens Sacha Baron Cohen.&quot;] ''[[Jewish Telegraphic Agency|JTA]]'', 28 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The group was angered by the interview with Abu Aita in which he was linked with the group, an armed wing of the [[Fatah]] movement. In a statement to the media, Al Aqsa Martyrs Brigade denied that Abu Aita was a member and threatened that they &quot;reserve the right to respond in the way we find suitable against this man (Baron Cohen)&quot; and that they feel the segment was &quot;a dirty use of our brother Ayman&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/film/2009/jul/27/bruno-sacha-baron-cohen | location=London | work=The Guardian | first=Caroline | last=Davies | title=Militant group issues threat over mockery in Bruno film | date=July 27, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Motion Picture Association of America===
On October 11, 2010, it was revealed that the [[Motion Picture Association of America]]'s Classification and Rating Administration would specifically note in the future which films contained &quot;male nudity.&quot; A spokesman said this was in direct response to parental concerns about the content of Brüno.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.spanglemagazine.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=551 |title=The Slippery Slope of the MPAA's New Ratings Policy |publisher=Spangle Magazine |date=2010-10-11 |accessdate=2011-02-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes and references==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
* [http://www.thebrunomovie.com The Best Bruno Website]
* {{IMDb title|0889583|Brüno}}
* {{allmovie title|378108|Brüno}}
* {{mojo title|bruno|Brüno}}
* {{rotten-tomatoes|bruno|Brüno}}
* {{metacritic film|bruno|Brüno}}
* [http://www.thenation.com/blogs/notion/450642/et_tu_br_no Et Tu, Brüno?] by Richard Kim, ''The Nation'', July 10, 2009
* [http://www.dentonrc.com/sharedcontent/dws/dn/latestnews/stories/DN-cohen_0607gl.ART.State.Edition2.460cf7e.html Folks Duped by Sacha Baron Cohen in Carrollton are Really Mad] by Michael Granberry, ''The Dallas Morning News'', June 7, 2008

{{Sacha Baron Cohen}}
{{Larry Charles}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bruno}}
[[Category:2009 films]]
[[Category:2000s comedy films]]
[[Category:American comedy films]]
[[Category:American LGBT-related films]]
[[Category:American satirical films]]
[[Category:British films]]
[[Category:British comedy films]]
[[Category:British LGBT-related films]]
[[Category:British satirical films]]
[[Category:Columbia Pictures films]]
[[Category:English-language films]]
[[Category:Fashion films]]
[[Category:Film spin-offs]]
[[Category:Films set in Austria]]
[[Category:Films set in Los Angeles, California]]
[[Category:Films shot in Arkansas]]
[[Category:Films shot in Italy]]
[[Category:Films shot in Los Angeles, California]]
[[Category:Media Rights Capital films]]
[[Category:Mockumentary films]]
[[Category:Universal Pictures films]]

[[da:Brüno]]
[[de:Brüno]]
[[es:Brüno (película)]]
[[fr:Brüno]]
[[gl:Brüno]]
[[hr:Brüno (2009.)]]
[[it:Brüno]]
[[he:ברונו (סרט, 2009)]]
[[mk:Бруно (филм)]]
[[mr:ब्रुनो (इंग्लिश चित्रपट)]]
[[nl:Brüno]]
[[ja:ブルーノ (映画)]]
[[pl:Brüno]]
[[pt:Brüno]]
[[ru:Бруно (фильм)]]
[[sr:Бруно (филм)]]
[[fi:Brüno (elokuva)]]
[[sv:Brüno]]
[[zh:波兒出城之妖壇教祖3點「畢露」搞硬美國佬]]</text>
      <sha1>s5wz32qt8xrybbq623nejhesqtiskp5</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
