<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Death Note</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1028460</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521093710</id>
      <parentid>520724668</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T19:05:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>TheFarix</username>
        <id>928626</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* =========================================================== */Add [[Category:2007 anime films]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="68405">{{Redirect|Death note||Death Note (disambiguation)}}
&lt;!--
Note to editors: licensors/publishers/networks/etc in the infobox are sorted alphabetically by country; please maintain this order when adding new ones. Thanks!
--&gt;
{{Infobox animanga/Header
| name            = Death Note
| image           = [[File:SNote.jpg|230px]]
| caption         = Cover of the first ''[[tankōbon]]'' for ''Death Note'' featuring [[Ryuk (Death Note)|Ryuk]] and [[Light Yagami]]
| ja_kanji        = デスノート
| ja_romaji       = Desu Nōto
| genre           = &lt;!--Discuss in talk page before adding or removing genres, however, keep in mind [[WP:MOS-AM#Content]]. Thank you.--&gt;[[Mystery fiction|Mystery]], [[Psychological thriller]], [[Thriller (genre)|Supernatural thriller]] &lt;!--Discuss in talk page before adding or removing genres, however, keep in mind [[WP:MOS-AM#Content]]. Thank you.--&gt;
}}
{{Infobox animanga/Print
| type            = manga
| author          = [[Tsugumi Ohba]]
| illustrator     = [[Takeshi Obata]]
| publisher       = [[Shueisha]]
| publisher_en    = {{English manga publisher
  | AUS = [[Madman Entertainment]]
}}{{English manga publisher
  | [[Northern America|NA]] / [[United Kingdom|UK]]
  | [[Viz Media]]
}}
| demographic     = ''[[Shōnen manga|Shōnen]]''
| magazine        = [[Weekly Shōnen Jump]]
| first           = December 2003
| last            = May 2006
| volumes         = 12
| volume_list     = List of Death Note chapters
}}
{{Infobox animanga/Print
| type            = novel
| title           = [[Death Note Another Note: The Los Angeles BB Murder Cases]]
| author          = [[Nisio Isin]]
| publisher       = [[Shueisha]]
| publisher_en    = [[Canada]]/[[United Kingdom]]/[[United States]]: [[Viz Media]]
| published       = August 1, 2006
}}
{{Infobox animanga/Video
| type            = tv series
| director        = [[Tetsurō Araki]]
| producer        = 
| writer          = [[Toshiki Inoue]]
| music           = 
| studio          = [[Madhouse (company)|Madhouse]]
| production      = [[Nippon Television|NTV]], D.N. Dream Partners, [[VAP (company)|VAP]], [[Shueisha]], Madhouse
| licensee        = {{English anime licensee
  | AUS = [[Madman Entertainment]]
  | NA  = [[Viz Media]]
  | UK  = [[Manga Entertainment]]
}}
| network         = [[Nippon Television|NTV]], [[Sapporo Television Broadcasting|STV]], [[Yomiuri Telecasting Corporation|ytv]], [[Chūkyō Television Broadcasting|CTV]], [[Fukuoka Broadcasting Corporation|FBS]], [[Hiroshima Telecasting|HTV]], [[Shizuoka Daiichi Television|SDT]], [[Fukushima Central Television|FCT]]
| network_en      = {{English anime networks
  | AU  = [[ABC2]]
  | CA  = [[YTV (TV channel)|YTV]], [[SCREAM (TV Channel)|SCREAM]], [[Neon Alley]]
  | US  = [[Cartoon Network]] ([[Adult Swim]]), [[Neon Alley]]
  | ZA  = [[Animax South Africa]]
}}
| first           = October 3, 2006
| last            = June 26, 2007
| episodes        = 37
| episode_list    = List of Death Note episodes
}}
{{Infobox animanga/Game
| title           = Death Note Kira's Game
| developer       = [[Konami]]
| publisher       = Konami
| genre           = [[Action game|Action]]
| ratings         = [[Computer Entertainment Rating Organization|CERO]]: A
| platforms       = [[Nintendo DS]]
| released        = {{vgrelease|JP=February 15, 2007}}
}}
{{Infobox animanga/Game
| title           = Death Note: Successor to L
| developer       = Konami
| publisher       = Konami
| genre           = Action
| ratings         = CERO: A
| platforms       = Nintendo DS
| released        = {{vgrelease|JP=July 12, 2007}}
}}
{{Infobox animanga/Video
| type            = film
| title           = Death Note: Rewrite: Visions of a God
| director        = [[Tetsurō Araki]]
| producer        = 
| writer          = [[Toshiki Inoue]]
| music           = 
| studio          = [[Madhouse (company)|Madhouse]]
| released        = August 31, 2007
| runtime         = 130 minutes
}}
{{Infobox animanga/Game
| title           = L the Prologue to Death Note: Spiraling Trap
| developer       = Konami
| publisher       = Konami
| genre           = Action
| ratings         = CERO: A
| platforms       = Nintendo DS
| released        = {{vgrelease|JP=February 7, 2008}}
}}
{{Infobox animanga/Video
| type            = film
| title           = Death Note: Rewrite 2: L's Successors
| director        = [[Tetsurō Araki]]
| producer        = 
| writer          = [[Toshiki Inoue]]
| music           = 
| studio          = [[Madhouse (company)|Madhouse]]
| released        = August 22, 2008
| runtime         = 100 minutes
}}
{{Infobox animanga/Print
| type            = novel
| title           = Death Note: L: Change the World
| author          = M
| publisher       = VIZ Media, LLC
| published_en    = {{English manga publisher
  | NA  = [[Viz Media]]
}}
| published       = October 20, 2009
}}
{{Infobox animanga/Footer}}

{{Nihongo|'''''Death Note'''''|デスノート|Desu Nōto}} is a Japanese manga series created by writer [[Tsugumi Ohba]] and manga artist [[Takeshi Obata]]. The main character is [[Light Yagami]], a high school student who discovers a [[supernatural]] [[notebook]], the &quot;Death Note&quot;, dropped on Earth by a [[shinigami]] (a god of death) named [[Ryuk (Death Note)|Ryuk]]. The Death Note grants its user the ability to kill anyone whose name and face they know, by writing the name in the notebook while picturing their face. The series centers around Light's attempt to create and rule a world &quot;cleansed of evil&quot; as [[God complex|&quot;God&quot;]] using the notebook, and the efforts of a detective known as [[L (Death Note)|L]] to stop him. 

''Death Note'' was first serialized in 108 chapters by [[Shueisha]] in the Japanese manga magazine ''[[Weekly Shōnen Jump]]'' from December 2003 to May 2006. The series was also published in ''[[tankōbon]]'' format in Japan starting in May 2004 and ending in October 2006 with a total of twelve volumes. The series was adapted into [[live-action]] films released in Japan on June 17, 2006, November 3, 2006, and February 2, 2008. The [[anime]] series aired in Japan from October 3, 2006, to June 26, 2007. Composed of 37 episodes, the anime was developed by [[Madhouse (company)|Madhouse]] and directed by [[Tetsuro Araki]]. A [[light novel]] based on the series, written by [[Nisio Isin]], was released in Japan. Additionally, various video games have been published by [[Konami]] for [[Nintendo DS]].

[[Viz Media]] licensed the ''Death Note'' manga in North America and has published all the twelve volumes from the series, a 13th volume which serves as a &quot;reader's guide&quot;, as well as the light novels. The episodes from the anime first appeared in North America as downloadable by [[IGN]]. Viz later licensed the anime series and it aired on [[Bionix]]. The live-action films briefly played in certain North American theaters since 2008. However, none of the video games have thus far been published in North America or Europe.

To date, it is the twenty fourth best selling manga series of all time at total sales of 26.5 million copies.&lt;ref&gt;http://img.photobucket.com/albums/v711/OniTasku/1242468937829.jpg&lt;/ref&gt;

== Plot summary ==
{{See also|List of Death Note characters}}
[[Light Yagami]] is an intelligent young adult who resents all things evil. He also wishes to end crime in the world and create a utopia in which he reigns supreme. His life undergoes a drastic change when he discovers the Death Note, a notebook that contains five written instructions:
{{blockquote|
*The human whose name is written in this notebook shall die.
*This notebook will not take effect unless the writer has the subject's face in their mind when writing his/her name. Therefore, people sharing the same name will not be affected.
*If the cause of death is written within 40 seconds of writing the person's name, it will happen.
*If the cause of death is not specified, the person will simply die of a heart attack.
*After writing the cause of death, the details of the death should be written in the next 6 minutes and 40 seconds.
}}
There are many other rules that are revealed as the story develops, usually in the form of sequence breaks in between scenes.
After several experiments with the Death Note, Light realises the notebook's authenticity and encounters the previous owner, a ''[[Shinigami (Death Note)|shinigami]]'' called [[Ryuk (Death Note)|Ryuk]]. Light explains to Ryuk his plan of exterminating all the criminals in the world, until there are only people who he has judged to be honest and kind. Once he finishes this, he will begin his reign as the god of this new world.

Soon, the number of inexplicable deaths of criminals catches the attention of the [[Interpol|International Police Organization]] and the world-famous detective, &quot;''[[L (Death Note)|L]]''&quot;. L quickly learns that the serial killer, publicly known as {{nihongo|&quot;Kira&quot;|キラ||derived from the Japanese pronunciation of the word &quot;''killer''&quot;}}, is located in Japan and can kill people without laying a finger on them. Light realises that L will be his greatest nemesis, and begins a [[Wiktionary:cat and mouse|cat and mouse game]] with L.

Light attempts to create an alibi by helping L and his investigate team track down Kira. His plan is impeded by a second Kira, famous model [[Misa Amane]], and her ''shinigami'' [[Shinigami (Death Note)#Rem|Rem]]. Misa and Light meet and work together; they are increasingly suspected by L. To save themselves from execution, Misa and Light temporarily relinquish control of their Death Notes—erasing their memories of the ''shinigami'' and the notebooks—and are placed under constant surveillance by L.

During their detention, a third Kira under the employ of the [[List of Death Note characters#Yotsuba Group|Yotsuba Group]] appears. Light and Misa are freed when it becomes apparent that they are not responsible for the murders of Yotsuba's rivals. The investigative team infiltrate Yotsuba and discover the third Kira is Yotsuba member Kyosuke Higuchi and attempt to capture him. Upon Higuchi's capture, Light regains the Death Note &quot;just as [he] planned&quot; and kills Higuchi. He completes his complex plan by manipulating Rem into killing both L and herself. Light becomes the &quot;new L&quot; upon L's death, and continues a charade of searching for Kira.

The narrative continues four years later, with Kira attracting a large network of contacts and a swell of public support. Two children, [[Near (Death Note)|Near]] and [[Mello (Death Note)|Mello]], raised by L's former guardian Watari to follow L's legacy, serve as antagonists to Light: Near as an independent detective; and Mello as a member of the Mafia. Mello's first action to oppose Kira is to kidnap the director of the NPA, and after his murder, Light's sister Sayu, to use as a bargaining chip to obtain the Death Note. Light's Task Force recapture Sayu and learn Mello's real name after Light's father Soichiro trades half of his remaining life for the ability to discover anyone's names, but Soichiro later dies of gunshot wounds.

Concurrently, Near and several members of the Task Force begin to suspect Light of being Kira. In response, Light persuades Misa to give up her Death Note and raises another Kira, Teru Mikami, a prosecutor and fervent supporter of Kira. Mikami kills Kira's former spokesman for being greedy and recruits Kiyomi Takada, a newscaster and Light's former girlfriend, to replace him. Mello returns and kidnaps Kiyomi, who manages to kill Mello with a hidden Death Note piece. Light then makes Kiyomi commit suicide to prevent her from implicating him, but Mikami, unaware of Light's actions, attempts to kill her with his own Death Note. Near reveals that Mikami's notebook is a fake, and is therefore able to prove Light is Kira. In desperation, Light tries to use the last Death Note piece in his watch to kill the rest of the Task Force, but Matsuda shoots him repeatedly. Realizing Light has lost, Ryuk uses his Death Note to kill Light with a heart attack, which is a part of the agreement of the Shinigami with the first person who uses the death note. As for Light's partner Misa, she had been accidentally informed of Light's death and committed suicide.

==Production==
The ''Death Note'' concept derived from a rather general concept involving Shinigami and &quot;specific rules.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;HowtoRead59&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Ohba | first = Tsugumi | title = Death Note 13: How to Read | year = 2008 | page = 59 | publisher = [[Viz Media]] | isbn = 1-4215-1888-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tsugumi Ohba wanted to create a suspense series because he did not feel that he could have created a fight-style series and that the genre had few suspense series. After publication of the pilot chapter the series was not expected to be approved as a serialized comic by the author who did not consider it to &quot;fit with ''Jump''.&quot; Ohba said that when he learned that ''Death Note'' received approval and that Takeshi Obata would create the artwork he &quot;couldn't even believe it.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;HowtoRead174&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Ohba | first = Tsugumi | title = Death Note 13: How to Read | year = 2008 | page = 173 | publisher = [[Viz Media]] | isbn = 1-4215-1888-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; Due to positive reactions, ''Death Note'' became a serialized manga series.&lt;ref name=&quot;HowtoRead58&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Ohba | first = Tsugumi | title = Death Note 13: How to Read | year = 2008 | page = 58 | publisher = [[Viz Media]] | isbn = 1-4215-1888-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;Thumbnails&quot; were created incorporating dialog, panel layout, and basic drawings, and were sent to the illustrator. The editor reviewed the thumbnails and sent them to the illustrator (Obata) with the script set in stone and the panel layout &quot;mostly done.&quot; Obata then determined the expressions and &quot;camera angles&quot; and created the final artwork. Ohba concentrated on the tempo and the amount of dialogue, making sure that the text was as concise as possible. Ohba commented that he believed &quot;reading too much exposition&quot; would be tiring and would negatively affect the atmosphere and &quot;air of suspense.&quot; Significant artistic license was given to the illustrator who worked on basic descriptions, such as &quot;abandoned building&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;HowtoRead180&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Ohba | first = Tsugumi | title = Death Note 13: How to Read | year = 2008 | page = 180 | publisher = [[Viz Media]] | isbn = 1-4215-1888-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; and this extended to the design of the Death Notes with Obata possessing free rein. Obata originally thought of the books as &quot;'[[Bible]]-like'...something you would automatically think was a Death Note.&quot; He also felt this design would seem &quot;difficult to use&quot; and instead opted for an easy-to-use college notebook. At a later point the concept of Death Notes looking different from one another, depending on the human era (such as Death Notes in ancient Japan looking like scrolls and Death Notes in [[medieval Europe]] looking like [[The Old Testament]]) was conceived.&lt;ref name=&quot;HowtoRead140&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Ohba | first = Tsugumi | title = Death Note 13: How to Read | year = 2008 | page = 149 | publisher = [[Viz Media]] | isbn = 1-4215-1888-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

When Ohba decided on the plot he internally visualized the panels while being on his bed, drinking tea, or walking around his house, needing to feel relaxed while visualizing the panels. On many occasions the original draft was too long and needed to be refined various times before the desired &quot;tempo&quot; and &quot;flow&quot; for the chapter was finalised. The writer remarked on his preference for reading the previous &quot;two or four&quot; chapters carefully to ensure consistency in the story.&lt;ref name=&quot;HowtoRead59&quot;/&gt;

The typical weekly production schedule consisted of five days for creating and thinking and one day using pencil to insert dialogue into rough drafts; after this point the writer faxed any initial drafts to the editor. The illustrator's weekly production schedule involved one day with the thumbnails, layout, and pencils and one day with additional penciling and inking. Obata's assistants usually worked for four days and Obata spent one day to finish it. Obata said that sometimes he took a few extra days to color pages and that this &quot;messed with the schedule.&quot; In contrast, the writer took three or four days to create a chapter on some occasions, while on others he took a month. Obata said that his schedule remained consistent except when he had to create color pages.&lt;ref name=&quot;HowtoRead192&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Ohba | first = Tsugumi | title = Death Note 13: How to Read | year = 2008 | page = 192 | publisher = [[Viz Media]] | isbn = 1-4215-1888-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ohba and Obata rarely met in person during the creation of the serialized manga; instead the two met with the editor. The first time they met in person was at an editorial party in January 2004. Obata said that, despite the intrigue, he did not ask his editor about Ohba's plot developments as he anticipated the new thumbnails every week.&lt;ref name=&quot;HowtoRead174&quot;/&gt; The two did not discuss the final chapters with one another and they continued to talk with the editor. Ohba said that when he asked the editor if Obata had &quot;said anything&quot; about the story and plot the editor responded '&quot;No, nothing&quot; [''laughs''].'&lt;ref name=&quot;HowtoRead180&quot;/&gt;

Ohba claims that the series ended more or less in the manner that he intended for it to end; he considered the idea of [[L (Death Note)|L]] defeating Light Yagami with Light dying but instead chose to use the &quot;Yellow Box warehouse&quot; ending. According to Ohba the details had been set &quot;from the beginning.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;HowtoRead58&quot;/&gt; The writer wanted an ongoing plot line instead of an episodic series because ''Death Note'' was serialized and its focus was intended to be on a cast with a series of events triggered by the Death Note.&lt;ref name=&quot;HowtoRead60&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Ohba | first = Tsugumi | title = Death Note 13: How to Read | year = 2008 | pages = 60–61 | publisher = [[Viz Media]] | isbn = 1-4215-1888-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''13: How to Read'' states that the humorous aspects of ''Death Note'' originated from Ohba's &quot;enjoyment of humorous stories.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;HowtoRead194&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Ohba | first = Tsugumi | title = Death Note 13: How to Read | year = 2008 | page = 194 | publisher = [[Viz Media]] | isbn = 1-4215-1888-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ohba said that a theme that he wished to express throughout the series was that, &quot;no human has the right to pass judgement on another's actions. No one should play god.&quot; He said that he intended ''Death Note'' to push an ideology about good and evil, and that Near's statement in Volume 12 about deciding right and wrong came about from his own personal belief. 

When the writer was asked, during an interview, whether the series was meant to be about enjoying the plot twists and psychological warfare, Ohba responded by saying that this concept was the reason why he was &quot;very happy&quot; to place the story in ''Weekly Shōnen Jump''. 

Ohba was also asked what he considered the most important thing in ''Death Note'', and he responded by saying, &quot;the human whose name is written in this note shall die&quot;; in contrast, Obata responded to the same question by answering &quot;impossible to say.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;HowtoRead192&quot;/&gt;

===Pilot chapter===
The ''Death Note'' process began when Ohba brought thumbnails for two concept ideas to [[Shueisha]]; Ohba said that the ''Death Note'' pilot, one of the concepts, was &quot;received well&quot; by editors and attained positive reactions by readers.&lt;ref name=&quot;HowtoRead58&quot;/&gt; Ohba described keeping the story of the pilot to one chapter as &quot;very difficult&quot; and he said that he remembered it took over a month to begin writing the chapter. He added that the story had to revive the killed characters with the Death Eraser and that he &quot;didn't really care&quot; for that plot device.&lt;ref name=&quot;HowtoRead215&quot;/&gt;

Obata said that he wanted to draw the story after he heard of a &quot;horror story featuring Shinigami.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;HowtoRead174&quot;/&gt; According to Obata, when he first received the rough draft created by Ohba, he &quot;didn't really get it&quot; at first and he wanted to work on the project due to the presence of Shinigami and because the work &quot;was dark.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;HowtoRead215&quot;/&gt; He also said he wondered about the progression of the plot as he read the thumbnails, and if ''Jump'' readers would enjoy reading the comic. Obata said that while there is little action and the main character &quot;doesn't really drive the plot&quot; he enjoyed the atmosphere of the story. He stated that he drew the pilot chapter so that it would appeal to himself.&lt;ref name=&quot;HowtoRead215&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Ohba | first = Tsugumi | title = Death Note 13: How to Read | year = 2008 | page = 215 | publisher = [[Viz Media]] | isbn = 1-4215-1888-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ohba brought the rough draft of the pilot chapter to the editorial department. Obata came into the picture at a later point to create the artwork. They did not meet in person while creating the pilot chapter. Ohba said that the editor told him he did not need to meet with Obata to discuss the pilot; Ohba said &quot;I think it worked out all right.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;HowtoRead174&quot;/&gt;

===Anime adaptation===
Tetsuro Araki, the director, said that he wished to convey aspects that &quot;made the series interesting&quot; instead of simply &quot;focusing on morals or the concept of justice.&quot; Toshiki Inoue, the series organizer, agreed with Araki and added that, in anime adaptations, there is a lot of importance in highlighting the aspects that are &quot;interesting in the original.&quot; He concluded that Light's presence was &quot;the most compelling&quot; aspect; therefore the adaptation chronicles Light's &quot;thoughts and actions as much as possible.&quot; Inoue noted that, to best incorporate the manga's plot into the anime, he &quot;tweak[ed] the chronology a bit&quot; and incorporated flashbacks that appear after the openings of the episodes; he said this revealed the desired tensions. Araki said that, because in an anime the viewer cannot &quot;turn back pages&quot; in the manner that a manga reader can, the anime staff ensured that the show clarified details. Inoue added that the staff did not want to get involved with every single detail, so the staff selected elements to emphasize. Due to the complexity of the original manga, he described the process as &quot;definitely delicate and a great challenge.&quot; Inoue admitted that he placed more instructions and notes in the script than usual. Araki added that because of the importance of otherwise trivial details, the notes became crucial to the development of the series.&lt;ref name=&quot;Passionsdreams&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | last = Kimlinger | first = Carl | month = November | year = 2007 | title = Passion and dreams | journal = [[Newtype USA]] | volume=6 |issue=11 | pages = 50–51}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Araki said that when he discovered the ''Death Note'' anime project he &quot;literally begged&quot; to join the production team; when he joined he insisted that Inoue should write the scripts. Inoue added that, because he enjoyed reading the manga, he wished to use his effort.&lt;ref name=&quot;Passionsdreams&quot;/&gt;

==Media==

===Manga===
{{Main|List of Death Note chapters}}
The ''Death Note'' manga series was first serialized in the Japanese manga magazine ''[[Weekly Shōnen Jump]]'' published by [[Shueisha]] in December 2003. The series has since ended in Japan with a total of 108 chapters. Later, the individual chapters were collected into twelve separate ''tankōbon''. In April from 2005 ''Death Note'' was licensed for publication in North America by [[Viz Media]],&lt;ref name=&quot;VizLicense&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title = Death Note Licensed by Viz | url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/article.php?id=6525 | date = April 20, 2005 | accessdate = November 19, 2006 | publisher = [[Anime News Network]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the first [[English language|English-language]] volume was released on October 10, 2005.&lt;ref name=&quot;VizVol1&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://viz.com/products/products.php?product_id=5360 | title = Death Note Volume 1 | publisher = [[Viz Media]] | accessdate = June 8, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In February 2008, a [[One-shot (comics)|one-shot]] special was released. Set two years after the manga's epilogue, it sees the introduction of a new Kira and the reactions of the main characters in response to the copycat's appearance.&lt;ref name=&quot;OneShot&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2008-02-03/death-note-manga-returns-with-one-shot-manga-in-japan | title = Death Note Manga to Return with One-Shot Story in Japan | date = February 3, 2008 | publisher = [[Anime News Network]] | accessdate = June 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Several ''Death Note'' [[yonkoma]] (four-panel comics) appeared in ''[[Akamaru Jump]]''. The yonkoma were written to be humorous. The ''Akamaru Jump'' issues that printed the comics include 2004 Spring, 2004 Summer, 2005 Winter, and 2005 Spring. In addition ''[[Weekly Shōnen Jump]]'' Gag Special 2005 included some ''Death Note'' yonkoma in a ''Jump'' Heroes Super 4-Panel Competition.&lt;ref name=&quot;HowtoRead215&quot;/&gt; 

In addition, a guidebook for the manga was also released on October 13, 2006. It was named ''Death Note 13: How to Read'' and contained data relating to the series, including character profiles of almost every character that is named, creator interviews, behind the scenes info for the series and the pilot chapter that preceded ''Death Note''. It also reprinted all of the yonkoma serialized in ''Akamaru Jump'' and the ''Weekly Shōnen Jump'' Gag Special 2005.&lt;ref name=&quot;HowtoRead216to223&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Ohba | first = Tsugumi | title = Death Note 13: How to Read | year = 2008 | pages = 215–223 | publisher = [[Viz Media]] | isbn = 1-4215-1888-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Shueisha 13&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://books.shueisha.co.jp/CGI/search/syousai_put.cgi?isbn_cd=4-08-874095-5 | title = Death Note 13: How to Read | publisher = [[Shueisha]] | accessdate = June 13, 2008 | language = Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its first edition could be purchased with a Death Note themed diorama which includes five finger puppets inspired by Near's toys. The five finger puppets are Kira, L, [[Misa Amane|Misa]], [[Mello (Death Note)|Mello]], and [[Near (Death Note)|Near]]. In North America, ''13: How to Read'' was released on February 19, 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;Viz 13&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.viz.com/products/products.php?product_id=7228 | title = Death Note 13: How to Read | publisher = [[Viz Media]] | accessdate = June 13, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of February 2011, the manga is being re-released in omnibus format, dubbed &quot;Black Edition&quot;.&lt;ref name='ANN 7-24-10'&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2010-07-24/viz-to-print-death-note-black-edition-omnibus | title = Viz Hosts Ultimo/Shaman King's Takei at Comic-Con Int'l (Updated) | accessdate = 2011-11-22 | date = 2010-07-24 | publisher = [[Anime News Network]] | quote = Publisher to reprint Death Note in Black Edition omnibus}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.mania.com/death-note-black-tap_article_124308.html | title = Death Note Black On Tap | accessdate = 2011-11-22 | last = Beveridge | first = Chris | date = 2010-07-27 | quote = Starting in February of 2011, the new Black Edition versions of the series will contain two volumes of the series in on volume with slightly oversized trade paperback sizes that will have black trim.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Anime===
{{Main|List of Death Note episodes}}
The ''Death Note'' anime, directed by [[Tetsurō Araki]] and animated by [[Madhouse (company)|Madhouse]], began airing in Japan on October 3, 2006, and finished its run on June 26, 2007, totaling 37 twenty-minute episodes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.ntv.co.jp/english/pc/ntv-animation.pdf | title = Nippon Television Network Program Catalogue: Animation | page = 17 | publisher = [[Nippon Television]] | accessdate = November 6, 2006 | format = PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; It begins in the year 2006, instead of 2003. The series aired on the [[Nippon Television]] network &quot;every Tuesday at 23:34&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.ntv.co.jp/deathnote/infor/index.html | title = Official Death Note Anime Website | publisher = [[Nippon Television]] | accessdate = November 6, 2006 | language = Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt; The series was co-produced by Madhouse, Nippon Television, [[Shueisha]], [[D.N. Dream Partners]] and [[Video and Audio Project|VAP]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.ntv.co.jp/deathnote/staff/index.html | title = Official Death Note staff listing | publisher = [[Nippon Television]] | accessdate = March 28, 2007 | language = Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In North America, the series has been licensed by Viz for residents in the United States to use &quot;Download-to-Own&quot; and &quot;Download-to-Rent&quot; services while it was still airing in Japan. This move is seen as &quot;significant because it marks the first time a well known Japanese anime property will be made legally available to domestic audiences for download to own while the title still airs on Japanese television.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;licensed&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.mania.com/viz-media-secures-landmark-agreement-to-make-death-note-anime-series-available-for-download_article_85192.html | title = Viz Media Secures Landmark Agreement To Make Death Note Anime Series Available For Download | date = January 10, 2007 | publisher = Mania Entertainment | accessdate = January 11, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; The downloadable episodes contain the original Japanese audio track and English subtitles,&lt;ref name=&quot;DVD&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2007-01-13/death-note-release-won't-be-limited-to-downloads | title = Death Note Release Won't be Limited to Downloads | date = January 13, 2007 | publisher = [[Anime News Network]] | accessdate = January 13, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is available through [[IGN]]'s [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]]-only Direct2Drive service.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2007-05-03/viz-to-offer-death-note-downloads-via-direct2drive | title = Viz to Offer ''Death Note'' Downloads via Direct2Drive | date = May 3, 2007 | publisher = [[Anime News Network]] | accessdate = May 4, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; DVDs of the series are also being released,&lt;ref name=&quot;DVD&quot;/&gt; containing both an English dubbed audio track, produced by [[Ocean Productions]], and the original Japanese audio track with optional English subtitles.&lt;ref name=&quot;comiccon&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/convention/2007/new-york-comiccon/4 | title = New York ComicCon 2007 - Viz Media - Anime | last = Dong | first = Bamboo | date = February 24, 2007 | publisher = [[Anime News Network]] | accessdate = February 24, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Viz announced at [[Anime Expo|Anime Expo 2007]] that the first DVD was officially released on November 20, 2007, in both regular and special editions,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/press-release/2007-06-29/viz-media-announces-fall-dvd-release-of-death-note-anime-series | title = Viz Media Announces Fall DVD Release of Death Note Anime Series | date = June 29, 2007 | publisher = [[Anime News Network]] | accessdate = July 2, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; and also confirmed at [[Comic-Con International]] 2007 that the first 15,000 copies of each DVD contains collectible figures.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/convention/2007/comic-con-international/viz-media | title = Viz Media - Comic-Con International 2007 | last = Santos | first = Carlo | date = July 26, 2007 | publisher = [[Anime News Network]] | accessdate = July 27, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Death Note'' was slated to make its North American television premiere in Canada on [[YTV (TV channel)|YTV's]] [[Bionix]] programming block on September 7, 2007;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release | url = http://www.corusent.com/corporate/press_room/pressReleaseDetail.asp?id=1348 | title = YTV, Discovery Kids and Treehouse Ring in September with Exciting New Series and Returning Favourites | date = July 23, 2007 | publisher = [[Corus Entertainment]] | accessdate = July 10, 2008 |archiveurl=http://replay.waybackmachine.org/20080411153525/http://www.corusent.com/corporate/press_room/pressReleaseDetail.asp?id=1348 |archivedate=April 11, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; however, the show was removed from the schedule at the last minute.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2007-09-04/death-note-removed-from-canada's-ytv-schedule | title = Death Note Removed from Canada's YTV Schedule | date = September 4, 2007 | publisher = [[Anime News Network]] | accessdate = September 6, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Canadian premiere was pushed back to October 26, 2007, at 10:00 p.m., when it finally premiered. ''Death Note'' premiered in the U.S. on October 20, 2007, at 11:30 p.m. on Cartoon Network's [[Adult Swim]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2007-09-20/death-note-confirmed-to-air-on-adult-swim-october-20 | title = Death Note Confirmed to Air on Adult Swim October 20 | date = September 20, 2007 | publisher = [[Anime News Network]] | accessdate = January 16, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; until January 10, 2010, when the contract expired.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2010-01-11/adult-swim-loses-blood-and-death-note-hints-at-3-new-anime | title = Adult Swim Loses Blood+ &amp; Death Note, Hints at 3 New Anime | date = January 11, 2010 | publisher = [[Anime News Network]] | accessdate = January 21, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The last episode aired on Canada's YTV channel on July 4, 2008, and on [[Adult Swim]] two days later. YTV took away the show on July 5, 2008, with the last airing being the last episode rerun at 1:30 a.m. [[Eastern Time Zone|ET]], as part of YTV moving the Bionix block to a 2-hour only block on Saturdays.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.corusent.com/corporate/press_room/press_kids_tv/highlightsDetail.asp?id=1348 | title = Press room - Press kids | publisher = Corus Entertainment - Press_Corporate | accessdate = June 7, 2009 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080312190404/http://corusent.com/corporate/press_room/press_kids_tv/highlightsDetail.asp?id=1348 |archivedate = March 12, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The show also streamed online for free on Adult Swim Video, with a new episode available every Saturday afternoon, on the day of its broadcast premiere.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2007-10-19/death-note's-english-dub-premieres-on-web-television | title = ''Death Note's'' English Dub Premieres on Web, Television | date = October 19, 2007 | publisher = [[Anime News Network]] | accessdate = June 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A two-hour animated {{Nihongo|''Death Note Rewrite: Visions of a God'''|DEATH NOTEリライト·幻視する神|Desu Nōto Riraito: Genshisuru kami}} TV special aired on Nippon Television in Japan on August 31, 2007, at 8:00 p.m. It is a recap which takes place after the series end, where a Shinigami approaches Ryuk in the Shinigami realm in order to learn more about the human world. Instead, Ryuk tells him of all the events leading up to the last story arc, about Light Yagami and his rival L. Originally, this special was advertised as a retelling told from Ryuk's point of view, but it does not give a different point of view from what was originally told. However, it contains updated dialog, as well as a few new scenes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2007-07-12/death-note-tv-special-to-be-three-hour-director's-cut | title = ''Death Note'' TV Special to be Three-Hour Director's Cut | date = July 12, 2007 | publisher = [[Anime News Network]] | accessdate = July 13, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Japanese broadcaster NTV aired the {{nihongo|''Death Note: Rewrite: L's Successors''||Death Note Rewrite: L o Tsugu Mono}} special on August 22, 2008. Like the first special, this new compilation summarized a part of the 2006–2007 television anime series. Specifically, it recounted the final half of the suspenseful supernatural story, including the investigators Near and Mello's confrontations with the vigilante Kira.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2008-07-25/second-death-note-special-to-air-on-august-22-in-japan | title = Second ''Death Note'' Special to Air on August 22 in Japan | date = July 25, 2008 | publisher = [[Anime News Network]] | accessdate = June 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; This version features more updates than the previous one, most notably omission of the mafia plot.

===Soundtracks===
{{Main|Death Note original soundtracks}}
[[File:Deathnotesoundof.jpg|thumb|Cover of the live-action film soundtrack ''Sound of Death Note'' featuring [[Tatsuya Fujiwara]] (left) as [[Light Yagami]] and [[Kenichi Matsuyama]] (right) as [[L (Death Note)|L]].]]
Several soundtracks for the series have been released. The music from the anime was composed by [[Yoshihisa Hirano]] and [[Hideki Taniuchi]], while the CDs were also published by VAP. The first one was ''Death Note Original Soundtrack'', which was released in Japan on December 21, 2006. It contains music from the series with the first opening and ending themes sung by the Japanese band [[Nightmare (Japanese band)|Nightmare]] in the TV size format.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.amazon.co.jp/dp/B000K0YFIS/ | title = Death Note オリジナル・サウンドトラック | publisher = [[Amazon.com]] | accessdate = 2009-06-13 | language = Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Death Note Original Soundtrack II'' was first released in Japan on March 21, 2007. It features the new opening and closing themes by [[Maximum the Hormone]] in the TV size format.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.amazon.co.jp/dp/B000MX7VO8/ | title = Death Note オリジナル・サウンドトラックII | publisher = [[Amazon.com]] | accessdate = 2009-06-06 | language = Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt; The third CD, ''Death Note Original Soundtrack III'' was released on June 27, 2007. The tracks 1-21 were composed and arranged by Taniuchi, while the tracks 22-28 were composed and arranged by Hirano. The album features one track sung by [[Aya Hirano]], who was also the Japanese voice actress of [[Misa Amane]] in the anime series. Also appearing on this soundtrack is the ending theme ''Coda〜Death Note'', which can be heard at the end of the final episode of the anime as the credits are shown.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.amazon.co.jp/dp/B000PMGT0I/ | title = Death Note オリジナル・サウンドトラックIII | publisher = [[Amazon.com]] | accessdate = 2009-06-13 | language = Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Several soundtracks have also been released for the live action films. ''Sound of Death Note'' is a soundtrack featuring music from the first ''Death Note'' film composed and arranged by [[Kenji Kawai]]. It was released on June 17, 2006 by [[Video and Audio Project|VAP]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.amazon.co.jp/dp/B000FI8UFY/ | title = Sound of Death Note | publisher = [[Amazon.com]] | accessdate = 2009-06-13 | language = Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Sound of Death Note the Last name'' is the soundtrack from the second ''Death Note'' film, ''Death Note the Last name''. It was released on November 2, 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.amazon.co.jp/dp/B000I0SA68/ | title = Sound of Death Note the Last Name | publisher = [[Amazon.com]] | accessdate = 2009-06-06 | language = Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Death Note Tribute'' is a tribute album dedicated to the [[live action]] movie for the ''Death Note'' film. Published by [[BMG Japan]] on June 21, 2006 Japan, it contains 15 tracks performed by various artists, such as [[Shikao Suga]], [[M-Flo]], [[Buck-Tick]] and [[Aya Matsuura]]. The soundtrack came with a [[cosplay]] Death Note notebook.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.amazon.co.jp/dp/B000FP2MYM/ | title = Death Note Tribute | publisher = [[Amazon.com]] | accessdate = 2009-06-13| language = Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another tribute album is ''The Songs for Death Note the movie〜the Last name Tribute'' dedicated to the second film. Published by [[Sony Music Entertainment Japan]] on December 20, 2006, it contains 14 tracks performed by various artist, such as [[Orange Range]], [[abingdon boys school]], [[High and Mighty Color]], [[Doping Panda]] and [[Galneryus]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.amazon.co.jp/dp/B000K2UDIW/ | title = The Songs for Death Note the movie〜the Last name Tribute | publisher = [[Amazon.com]] | accessdate = 2009-06-13| language = Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Light novels===
A [[light novel]] adaptation of the series has been written by [[Nisio Isin]], called [[Death Note Another Note: The Los Angeles BB Murder Cases]]. The novel was released by Shueisha on August 1, 2006.&lt;ref name=&quot;novel&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/article.php?id=8835 | title = Death Note, XXXHOLiC Novels in the Works | date = May 9, 2006 | publisher = [[Anime News Network]] | accessdate = December 7, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://j-books.shueisha.co.jp/nisioisin/ | title = 西尾維新 × Death Note | publisher = [[Shueisha]] | accessdate = December 21, 2006 | language = Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt; It serves as a prequel to the manga series, with Mello narrating the story of L's first encounter with Naomi Misora during the Los Angeles &quot;BB Serial Murder Case&quot; mentioned in volume 2 of the manga. Beside Naomi's character, the novel focuses on how L works and one of the criminals L has to chase down. Insight was given into Watari's orphanage and how the whole system of geniuses such as L, Mello, Beyond Birthday, Matt and Near were put to work. Viz released the novel in English on February 19, 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;VizAnotherNote&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://viz.com/products/products.php?product_id=7222 | title = Death Note Another Note: The Los Angeles BB Murder Cases (Novel) | publisher = [[Viz Media]] | accessdate=June 8, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film ''[[L: Change the World]]'' was also adapted into a light novel with the same name on December 25, 2007 by &quot;M&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://books.shueisha.co.jp/CGI/search/syousai_put.cgi?isbn_cd=978-4-08-771210-0&amp;mode=1|title=L change the world|publisher=[[Shūeisha]]|accessdate=September 4, 2009|language=Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt; While the novel is similar to the movie, there are many significant changes to the plot (for example, Near is not a Thai boy, but the same Near that appears in the manga). It also reveals more information about L and his past. Viz released it on October 20, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amazon.com/dp/1421532255/ |title=L change the world|publisher=[[Amazon.com]]|accessdate=October 31, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Video games===
A ''Death Note'' [[video game]] developed and published by [[Konami]] for the [[Nintendo DS]], titled {{Nihongo|''Death Note Kira Game''|デスノート キラゲーム|Desu Nōto Kira Gēmu}}, was released on February 15, 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.gamespot.com/ds/action/deathnote/index.html | publisher = [[GameSpot]] | title = Death Note: Kira Game for DS | accessdate = December 17, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Kira Game'' is a [[Strategy video game|strategy game]] where the player takes on the role of Kira or L. These are just titles, as any character can be Kira or L. The player will attempt to deduce who their enemy is (Kira will try to uncover L's identity and vice versa). This will play out in 3 phases: Investigation, where the player will discuss the case and clues with other characters; Voting, where each member of the investigation team casts a vote on who they suspect is L or Kira based on the player's performance in the previous phase; L/Kira, where the player can either focus their investigation on one member to see if they are Kira (L part) or force a member off of the team (Kira part).&lt;ref name=&quot;game&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.konami.jp/gs/game/deathnote/ | title = Official Konami Website for Death Note | publisher = [[Konami]] | accessdate = February 3, 2007 | language = Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt;
A sequel to the game, {{Nihongo|''Death Note L o Tsugumono''|デスノート Lを継ぐ者|Desu Nōto Eru o Tsugu Mono|literally &quot;''Death Note: Successors to L''&quot;}}, was released in Japan on July 12, 2007. The storyline is based on the second part of the manga, featuring characters such as Mello and Near.&lt;ref name=&quot;game&quot;/&gt;

A third game, {{nihongo|''L the Prologue to Death Note -Rasen no Trap-''|L the proLogue to DEATH NOTE -螺旋の罠-|L the proLogue to DEATH NOTE -Rasen no Torappu-|literally &quot;''L the Prologue to Death Note: Spiraling Trap''&quot;}}, was released for the Nintendo DS in Japan on February 7, 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;game&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;prequel&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2007-12-17/promo-video-l-prequel-game-streamed | title = Promo Video for ''Death Note's L'' Prequel Game Streamed (Updated) | date = December 17, 2007 | publisher = [[Anime News Network]] | accessdate = December 17, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; The player assumes the role of a rookie FBI agent who awakens in a strange hotel and attempts to escape with the help of L, who provides assistance via an in-game PDA. The story is set before the Kira investigation in the original series.&lt;ref name=&quot;prequel&quot;/&gt;

Several characters from ''Death Note'' appear in ''[[Jump Super Stars]]'' and ''[[Jump Ultimate Stars]]'', a [[fighting game]] featuring a plethora of characters from [[Weekly Shōnen Jump|''Shōnen Jump'']] titles. Light, Ryuk and L appear in ''Jump Super Stars'' as support characters. In ''Jump Ultimate Stars'' Misa, Near, and Mello are added as support characters as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.nintendo.co.jp/ds/ajsj/p3.html | title = Jump Super Stars official website | publisher = [[Nintendo]] | accessdate = February 6, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.nintendo.co.jp/ds/ajuj/character/chara_38.html | title = Jump Ultimate Stars official website | publisher = [[Nintendo]] | accessdate = February 6, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Live-action films===
{{Main|Death Note (film)}}
''Death Note'' was adapted into a series of live-action films in 2006. The first 2 films were directed by [[Shūsuke Kaneko]] and the third was by [[Hideo Nakata]] and produced by [[Nippon Television]], CG production of all three films were done by [[Digital Frontier]] and distributed by [[Warner Bros.]] Pictures Japan. The first film, simply titled ''[[Death Note (film)|Death Note]]'', premiered in Japan on June 17, 2006 and topped the Japanese [[box office]] for two weeks, pushing ''[[The Da Vinci Code (film)|The Da Vinci Code]]'' into second place.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title = Death Note Tops Box Office Again |url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2006-06-27/death-note-tops-box-office-again |publisher = [[Anime News Network]] |date = June 27, 2006 |accessdate = December 18, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first movie briefly played in certain North American theaters on May 20–21, 2008&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title = 1st Death Note Film to Run in 300+ U.S. Theaters in May |url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2008-04-14/1st-death-note-film-to-run-in-300+u.s-theaters-in-may |work = [[Anime News Network]] |date = April 14, 2008 |accessdate = April 17, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film was broadcast in Canadian theaters for one night only on September 15, 2008. The DVD was released on September 16, 2008, one day after the Canadian showing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title = Death Note Live-Action!! Trailer |url = http://deathnotefilms.com/trailers.php |work = [[Viz Media]] |date = April 14, 2007 |accessdate = April 17, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; The sequel, ''[[Death Note: The Last Name]]'', premiered in Japan on November 3, 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title = Death Note 2 Trailer |url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2006-09-28/death-note-2-trailer|publisher = [[Anime News Network]] |date = September 28, 2006 |accessdate = June 27, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was featured in U.S. theaters in October 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title =2nd Death Note Film to Run in U.S. Theaters in October |url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2008-08-25/2nd-death-note-film-to-run-in-u.s-theaters-in-october|publisher = [[Anime News Network]] |date = August 25, 2008 |accessdate = June 27, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; A spinoff from the films named ''[[L: Change the World]]'' was released in Japan on February 9, 2008. It is focused on the final 23 days of L's life, as he solves one final case involving a bio-terrorist group.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title =Death Note's L Spinoff to Open on February 9 in Japan|url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2007-07-30/death-note's-l-spinoff-to-open-on-february-9-in-japan|publisher = [[Anime News Network]] |date = July 30, 2007 |accessdate = June 27, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two dubbed versions of the film were shown in the United States on April 29 and 30, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title =Death Note's L Spinoff Film in U.S. Theaters in April|url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2009-03-06/death-note-l-spinoff-film-in-u.s-theaters-in-april|publisher = [[Anime News Network]] |date = March 6, 2009 |accessdate = June 27, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====United States live action film====
''Death Note'' has been optioned for a live-action Hollywood remake. A 2007 article in ''[[The Star (Malaysia)|The Star]]'' ([[Malaysia]]) states that more than ten film companies in the United States expressed interest in creating a remake. 
On April 30, 2009, ''Variety'' magazine announced that [[Warner Bros.]] acquired the rights for the ''Death Note'' manga to be adapted into a live-action movie in the United States. Warner Bros. has hired screenwriters Charley and [[Vlas Parlapanides]] to adapt the manga into a screenplay. On January 13, 2011, it was announced that [[Shane Black]], the director of ''[[Kiss Kiss Bang Bang]]'', has been hired to direct the film, with the script being written by Anthony Bagarozzi and Charles Mondry.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url = http://www.deadline.com/2011/01/warner-bros-taps-shane-black-for-japanese-manga-death-note/ |title= Warner Bros Taps Shane Black For Japanese Manga 'Death Note' |accessdate = 2011-01-14 |date =2011-01-13 |work= Deadline.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title = Death Note Live-Action Director Confirmed Warner Bros. |url = http://www.tokyofever.com/2011/01/shane-black-to-direct-hollywood-version-of-death-note/ |publisher = Tokyofever via Variety |accessdate = January 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Warner's studios planned to change the background story of Yagami, into one of vengeance instead of justice, and also the removal of Shinigami. But Black opposed this change, and it has not been green-lit.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/interest/2011-11-02/shane-black-describes-changes-he-opposed-to-warner-death-note/ |title=Warner bros to change background |accessdate=2011-02-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reception==
{{As of|2006|6}}, ''Death Note'' had sold around twenty million copies in Japan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.comipress.com/news/2006/09/07/689 | title = Death Note Author Arrested on Weapons Offence | date = September 7, 2006 | publisher = ComiPress | accessdate = November 26, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; On December 31, 2008, Comipress reported that the twelve volumes from the series had sold 26,500,000 copies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://comipress.com/article/2008/12/31/3733|title=Top Manga Properties in 2008 - Rankings and Circulation Data|publisher=Comipress.com|date=December 31, 2008|accessdate=August 26, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was also nominated for Best Manga at the 2006 [[American Anime Awards]] but lost.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.icv2.com/articles/news/10043.html | title = Finalists for the American Anime Awards | date = February 8, 2007 | publisher = ICv2 | accessdate = May 30, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.icv2.com/articles/news/10138.html | title = American Anime Award Winners |date = February 26, 2007 | publisher = ICv2 | accessdate = February 13, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007, the first three volumes of ''Death Note'' were on the [[American Library Association]]'s 2007 Great Graphic Novels for Teens Top Ten list.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ala.org/ala/mgrps/divs/yalsa/booklistsawards/greatgraphicnovelsforteens/annotations/07toptengn.cfm|title=2007 Great Graphic Novels for Teens Top Ten|publisher=American Library Association|accessdate=June 28, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; On ICv2's &quot;Top 10 Shonen Properties Q2 2009&quot;, ''Death Note'' was the third best manga property from North America.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url =http://www.icv2.com/articles/news/15498.html | title = 'ICv2 Insider's Guide' #67: Top 10 Shonen  |date = July 30, 2009 | publisher = ICv2 | accessdate = August 19, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; During January from 2007, [[Oricon]] made a poll in which they asked Japanese fans from manga and anime which characters from any series they would most like to see in spinoff series. The overall winner from the poll was L, who also ranked first in the women's poll and second in the men's poll.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2007-01-08/oricon-fans-want-l-char-aznable-spinoffs | title = Oricon: Fans Want L, Char Aznable Spinoffs | date = January 8, 2007 | publisher = [[Anime News Network]] | accessdate = June 8, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Anime News Network]] (ANN) writer Zac Bertschy noted that the difference between ''Death Note'' and other manga from the same genre was very big due to the murders the main character ([[Light Yagami]]) commits as well as how he hides his identity of Kira. Although Bertchy mentioned some readers from other ''shōnen'' would be surprised with the dark themes of ''Death Note'', he praised the series for its &quot;great art, great story, compelling characters.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/review/death-note-gn-1 | title = Death Note GN 1 | last = Bertschy | first = Zac | date = September 29, 2005 | publisher = [[Anime News Network]] | accessdate = June 8, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Julie Rosato from Mania Entertainment found the story to be very entertaining, having liked Light's development in the story and L's introduction as well as how the latter starts suspecting of the former's identity. Additionally, he praised the story as it is &quot;building a climax&quot; with each detail introduced in the first chapter, making the reader to look forward to upcoming chapters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.mania.com/death-note-vol-02_article_82348.html | title = Death Note Vol. #02 | last = Rosato | first = Julie | date = November 3, 2005 | publisher = Mania Entertainment | accessdate = June 8, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Briana Lawrence from ANN liked the series' ending as most of the characters from the story were &quot;given a chance to shine&quot; and due to the fact the notebook and other aspects from the series had little importance in the focus of ''Death Note'' and now they play a more important part. However, she did not like how the epilogue made no mention of what happens with [[Misa Amane]] and how Near and Mello were still treated like parts of L.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/review/death-note/gn-12 | title = Death Note GN 12 | last = Lawrence | first = Briana | date = August 5, 2007 | publisher = [[Anime News Network]] | accessdate = June 8, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Douglas Wolk of ''[[Salon (magazine)|Salon]]'' said that a rumor circulated stating that the creators intended to create ''Death Note'' to last half as long as its actual run &amp; Ohba and Obata had been persuaded to lengthen the storyline when ''Death Note'''s popularity increased, noting that the rumor &quot;makes sense, since about halfway through the series, there's a point that seems like a natural ending&quot;. In addition he said that fans wrote &quot;thousands&quot; of ''Death Note'' [[fan fiction]] stories and posted them on the internet.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.salon.com/books/review/2007/07/26/death_note/print.html | title = Death strip | last = Wolk | first = Douglas | date = July 26, 2007 | publisher = [[Salon (magazine)|Salon]] | accessdate = June 15, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The anime was also commented with Tom S. Pepirium of IGN saying that ''Death Note''{{'}}s &quot;heavy serialized nature&quot; is what &quot;makes the show so engaging and discussion worthy.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://tv.ign.com/articles/836/836387p1.html  | title = Death Note: &quot;Tactics&quot; Review | last = Pepirium | first = Tom S. | date = November 19, 2007 | publisher = IGN | accessdate = June 15, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pepirium, saying that translating ''Death Note'' is &quot;no small task,&quot; said that Stephen Hedley created a dub with &quot;nothing clunky.&quot; Pepirium added that Karl Willems, director of the dub, assembled a &quot;stunning voice cast of professionals&quot; with a &quot;solid tone minus some of the cheesy yelling and screaming of other dubs.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://tv.ign.com/articles/855/855426p1.html | title = Death Note: &quot;Ally&quot; Review | last = Pepirium | first = Tom S. | date = February 27, 2008 | publisher = IGN | accessdate = June 15, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; John Powers of the [[NPR]] show ''[[Fresh Air]]'' finds the show &quot;addicting&quot; and equates its similarity to the American TV series ''[[Lost (TV series)|Lost]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=89999028 | title = Killer Penmanship in 'Death Note' | last = Powers | first = John | date = April 28, 2008 | publisher = [[NPR]] | accessdate = June 15, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was also listed as the 51st best animated show in IGN's Top 100 Animated Series.&lt;ref name=&quot;ign100&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=51. Death Note|url=http://tv.ign.com/top-100-animated-tv-series/51.html|publisher=IGN |accessdate=September 5, 2009 |date=January 23, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Running over thirty-seven 20 minutes episodes, the anime sticks much closer to the manga so takes a far more languid approach to storytelling, better fleshing out the fantastic characters of Light and his nemesis, L. Light in particular is one of the most layered characters to appear in anime in a long time. -''[[Hyper (magazine)|Hyper]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|date=March 2008|title=Death Note: Volume 1|journal=[[Hyper (magazine)|Hyper]]|publisher=[[Next Media]]|issue=173|page=79|issn=1320-7458}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The novelization ''L: Change the World'' became the second top selling light novel in Japan during 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2009-01-04/2008-top-selling-light-novels-in-japan| title = 2008's Top-Selling Light Novels in Japan (Updated)|date = January 4, 2009 | publisher = [[Anime News Network]] | accessdate = August 19, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; A.E. Sparrow of IGN reviewed the novel ''Another Note'' and gave it a 9.5 out of 10. Sparrow said that the author understood &quot;what made these characters click so well&quot; and &quot;captures everything that made the manga the compelling read that it is.&quot; Sparrow said that fans of ''Death Note'' who read ''Another Note'' will &quot;find a welcome home&quot; in the Nisio Isin's work that &quot;adds a few more fun layers&quot; to the ''Death Note'' franchise.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://comics.ign.com/articles/865/865077p1.html | title = Death Note - Another Note: The Los Angeles BB Murder Cases Review | last = Sparrow | first = A.E. | date = April 8, 2008 | publisher = IGN | accessdate = June 15, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Banning by People's Republic of China===
Early in 2005, school officials in [[Shenyang]], the capital of [[Liaoning Province]] (People's Republic of China), banned ''Death Note''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://news.xinhuanet.com/school/2005-01/11/content_2446984.htm | title = Chinese city bans Death Note | date = January 11, 2005 | publisher = Xihuanet | accessdate = September 4, 2008 | language = Chinese}}&lt;/ref&gt; The immediate cause was that students had been altering notebooks to resemble Death Notes and then writing the names of acquaintances, enemies, and teachers in the books.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2005-02-06/death-note-stirs-controversy-in-china | title = Death Note Stirs Controversy in China | date = February 6, 2005 | publisher = [[Anime News Network]] | accessdate = August 27, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://comipress.com/article/2007/03/26/1711 | title = Death Note in China - Success or Disaster? | date = March 26, 2007 | publisher = ComiPress | accessdate = August 27, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ban was designed to protect the &quot;physical and mental health&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Beijing&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.reuters.com/article/lifestyleMolt/idUSPEK30969020070515 | title = Beijing bans scary stories to protect young | date = May 15, 2007 | publisher = Reuters | accessdate = May 15, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; of students from horror material that &quot;misleads innocent children and distorts their mind and spirit.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;China Daily&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.chinadaily.com.cn/china/2007-05/26/content_880773.htm | title = 'Death Note' days numbered | last = Weifeng | first = Liu | date = May 26, 2007 | publisher = [[China Daily]] | accessdate = May 27, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jonathan Clements]] has suggested that the Chinese authorities acted partly against &quot;superstition&quot; but also against illegal, pirate publishers of ''Death Note''.&lt;ref name=&quot;ClementsNeo&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | last = Clements | first = Jonathan | year = 2007 | month = August | title = Manga Pulse | publisher = [[Neo (magazine)|NEO Magazine]] | issue = 35 | page = 19}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ban has been extended to other Chinese cities including Beijing,&lt;ref name=&quot;Beijing&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://news.xinhuanet.com/english/2007-05/15/content_6103672.htm | title = Beijing publisher to ignore Beijing's ban of its horror story | last = Jie | first = Xiao | date = May 15, 2007 | publisher = Xinhuanet | accessdate = August 27, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MacDonald&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://pwbeat.publishersweekly.com/blog/2007/05/15/death-note-banned-in-beijing-2 | title = Death Note banned in Beijing | last = MacDonald | first = Heidi | date = May 15, 2007 | publisher = [[Publishers Weekly]] | accessdate = August 28, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shanghai and [[Lanzhou]] in [[Gansu]] Province.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://comipress.com/news/2007/06/05/2067 | title = Chinese Students Fight Back at Death Note Ban | date = June 5, 2007 | publisher = ComiPress | accessdate = June 15, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Legally published Chinese language versions of ''Death Note'' are published in Hong Kong and in Taiwan.&lt;ref name=&quot;ClementsNeo&quot;/&gt;

==Copycat crimes and imitations==
[[File:Death Note, Book.svg|150px|thumb|A Death Note]]
There have been various [[copycat crime]]s around the world which were based on ''Death Note''. On September 28, 2007, two notes written with [[Latin alphabet|Latin characters]] stating &lt;!-- DO NOT &quot;correct&quot; this - the misspelling is sourced. --&gt; {{Nihongo|&quot;Watashi wa Kira dess&quot;,{{sic}} or &quot;I am Kira&quot;|私はキラです|watashi wa Kira desu}}&lt;ref name=&quot;La Dernière Heure&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.dhnet.be/infos/faits-divers/article/185914/forest-le-tueur-aux-mangas.html | title = Forest: le tueur aux mangas | date = October 1, 2007 | publisher = [[La Dernière Heure]] | accessdate = January 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; were found near the remains of a [[Caucasian race|Caucasian]] male in Belgium. The case has been called the &quot;[[Manga Murder|Mangamoord]]&quot; (Dutch for ''Manga Murder'') in Belgian media. Nothing was found on or near the victim besides these two notes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2007-10-01/notes-left-near-bodies-in-belgium-linked-to-death-note | title = Notes left near bodies in Belgium linked to Death Note | date = October 1, 2007 | publisher = [[Anime News Network]] | accessdate = May 24, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A senior at the Franklin Military Academy in [[Richmond, Virginia]], United States was suspended after being caught possessing a replica &quot;Death Note&quot; notebook with the names of fellow students.&lt;ref name=&quot;Franklin Military Academy&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2007-11-22/virginian-teen-suspended-over-names-in-death-note | title = Virginian Teen Suspended over Names in ''{{'}}Death Note{{'}}'' | date = November 22, 2007 | publisher = [[Anime News Network]] | accessdate = May 24, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[South Carolina]], U.S. in 2008, school officials seized a &quot;Death Note&quot; notebook from a Hartsville Middle School student. District officials linked the notebook to the anime/manga. The notebook listed seven students' names. The school planned a disciplinary hearing and contacted the seven students' parents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2008-03-02/south-carolina-student-removed-over-death-note-list | title = South Carolina Student Removed over ''&quot;Death Note&quot;'' List | date = March 2, 2008 | publisher = [[Anime News Network]] | accessdate = May 24, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Gadsden, Alabama]], U.S. two sixth grade boys were arrested for possessions of &quot;Death Notes&quot; that listed names of several staff members and fellow students. According to Etowah County Sheriff's Department Sgt. Lanny Handy, the notebook was found the previous afternoon by a staffer. The students were suspended from the county's schools. The students, their parents, and school officials had met with Handy and a junior probation officer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2008-04-04/2-alabama-6th-grade-boys-arrested-for-death-note-book | title = 2 Alabama 6th-Grade Boys Arrested for ''Death Note'' Book | date = April 4, 2008 | publisher = [[Anime News Network]] | accessdate = May 24, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Gig Harbor, Washington]], U.S. one middle school student was expelled and three were suspended on May 14, 2008 for having their own &quot;Death Note&quot; books.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2008-05-24/4-washington-middle-schoolers-disciplined-over-death-note | title = 4 Washington Middle Schoolers Disciplined over &quot;Death Note&quot; | date = May 24, 2008 | publisher = [[Anime News Network]] | accessdate = May 24, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Illinois]], U.S. a middle school student was suspended for two days around May 2012 after being caught carrying a mini version of the &quot;Death Note&quot; book with fellow students' names inside. The student claimed it was a joke and the people whose names were written agreed to that claim.

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Anime and manga}}
&lt;!--
==============================({{NoMoreLinks}})==============================
DO NOT ADD MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. WIKIPEDIA IS NOT A COLLECTION OF LINKS.
If you think that your link might be useful, instead of placing it here, put it on this article's discussion page first.
Links that have not been verified WILL BE DELETED
=======================================================================
--&gt;
*[http://www.j-deathnote.com/ ''Death Note'' official website] {{ja icon}}
*[http://www.ntv.co.jp/deathnote/ Official anime website] {{ja icon}}
*[http://deathnote.viz.com/ Viz Media's ''Death Note'' website]
*[http://deathnote.com.au Madman Entertainment's ''Death Note'' website]
*[http://deathnote.wikia.com/wiki/Main_Page ''Death Note''] at [[Wikia]]
*{{ann|manga|4354}}
*{{ann|anime|6592}}

{{Death Note}}
{{Weekly Shōnen Jump - 2000-2009}}

&lt;!--Discuss in talk page before adding or removing genre-related categories, however, keep in mind [[WP:MOS-AM#Content]]. Thank you.--&gt;

[[Category:Death Note| ]]
[[Category:2003 manga]]
[[Category:2006 anime]]
[[Category:2007 anime films]]
[[Category:2008 anime films]]
[[Category:Anime films]]
[[Category:Anime series]]
[[Category:Drama anime and manga]]
[[Category:Japanese novels]]
[[Category:Madhouse (company)]]
[[Category:Manga adapted into films]]
[[Category:Manga series]]
[[Category:Mystery anime and manga]]
[[Category:Nippon Television shows]]
[[Category:Shinigami anime and manga]]
[[Category:Shōnen manga]]
[[Category:Supernatural anime and manga]]
[[Category:Viz Media anime]]
[[Category:Viz Media manga]]

{{Link FA|es}}
[[ang:Death Note]]
[[ar:مفكرة الموت]]
[[ast:Death Note]]
[[bn:ডেথ নোট]]
[[bg:Death Note]]
[[br:Death Note]]
[[ca:Death Note]]
[[cs:Death Note]]
[[da:Death Note]]
[[de:Death Note]]
[[et:Death Note]]
[[el:Death Note]]
[[es:Death Note]]
[[eo:Death Note]]
[[fa:دفتر مرگ]]
[[fr:Death Note]]
[[gl:Death Note]]
[[ko:데스노트]]
[[hr:Death Note]]
[[id:Death Note]]
[[is:Death Note]]
[[it:Death Note]]
[[he:מחברת המוות]]
[[la:Death Note]]
[[lv:Death Note]]
[[lt:Death Note]]
[[hu:Death Note]]
[[mk:Death Note]]
[[ms:Death Note]]
[[nl:Death Note]]
[[ja:DEATH NOTE]]
[[no:Death Note]]
[[pl:Death Note]]
[[pt:Death Note]]
[[ro:Death Note]]
[[ru:Тетрадь смерти]]
[[sq:Death Note]]
[[scn:Death note]]
[[simple:Death Note]]
[[sk:Death Note – Desu Noto]]
[[sh:Death Note]]
[[su:Death note]]
[[fi:Death Note]]
[[sv:Death Note]]
[[tl:Death Note]]
[[kab:Death Note]]
[[th:เดธโน้ต]]
[[tr:Death Note]]
[[uk:Death Note]]
[[vi:Quyển sổ thiên mệnh]]
[[zh-yue:死亡筆記]]
[[zh:死亡笔记]]</text>
      <sha1>epxvdu2z5go6lgpqtnwa9ofq54vd6qs</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
