<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Pentagon Papers</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>230025</id>
    <revision>
      <id>517399237</id>
      <parentid>516091462</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-12T13:58:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yobot</username>
        <id>7328338</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Legal case */[[WP:CHECKWIKI]] error 61 fix, References after punctuation per [[WP:REFPUNC]] and [[WP:PAIC]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (8459)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27405">{{About|the U.S. Government documents|the 2003 film|The Pentagon Papers (film)}}

[[File:PentagonPapers.jpg|thumb|A CIA map of dissident activities in Indochina published as part of the Pentagon papers]]
{{wikisource}}
The '''Pentagon Papers''', officially titled '''''United States – Vietnam Relations, 1945–1967: A Study Prepared by the Department of Defense''''', is a [[United States Department of Defense]] history of the [[United States]]' political-military involvement in [[Vietnam]] from 1945 to 1967. The papers were first brought to the attention of the public on the front page of ''[[The New York Times]]'' in 1971.&lt;ref name=upi1971yearinreview&gt;{{Cite web| title=The Pentagon Papers|work=1971 Year in Review|publisher=UPI|year=1971|url=http://www.upi.com/Audio/Year_in_Review/Events-of-1971/The-Pentagon-Papers/12295509436546-7/|accessdate=2010-07-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;
A 1996 article in ''The New York Times'' said that the Pentagon Papers &quot;demonstrated, among other things, that the [[Lyndon Johnson|Johnson]] Administration had systematically lied, not only to the public but also to Congress, about a subject of transcendent national interest and significance&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Apple|first=R.W.|authorlink=R. W. Apple, Jr.|title=Pentagon Papers|newspaper= [[The New York Times]]|location=New York|date=1996-06-23|url=http://topics.nytimes.com/top/reference/timestopics/subjects/p/pentagon_papers/index.html?scp=1-spot&amp;sq=pentagon%20papers&amp;st=cse|accessdate=2010-07-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; The report was declassified and publicly released in June 2011.

==Contents==
[[United States Secretary of Defense|Secretary of Defense]] [[Robert McNamara]] created the Vietnam Study Task Force on June 17, 1967, for the purpose of writing an &quot;encyclopedic history of the [[Vietnam War]]&quot;. The secretary's motivation for doing so is unclear. McNamara claimed that he wanted to leave a written record for historians, but kept the study secret from the rest of the Johnson administration. Neither President [[Lyndon Johnson]] nor [[United States Secretary of State|Secretary of State]] [[Dean Rusk]] knew about the study until its publication; they believed McNamara might have planned to give the work to his friend [[Robert F. Kennedy]], who sought the [[Democratic Party (United States) presidential primaries, 1968|Democratic presidential nomination in 1968]].&lt;ref name=&quot;correll200702&quot;/&gt;

Instead of using existing Defense Department historians, McNamara assigned his close aide and [[Assistant Secretary of Defense]] [[John T. McNaughton]], McNaughton's aide [[Morton H. Halperin]], and Defense Department official [[Leslie H. Gelb]] to lead the task force. Thirty-six analysts—half of them active-duty military officers, the rest academics and civilian federal employees—worked on the study. The analysts largely used existing files in the [[Office of the Secretary of Defense]] and conducted no interviews or consultations with the armed forces, with the White House, or with other federal agencies in order to keep the study secret from others, including [[National Security Advisor (United States)|National Security Advisor]] [[Walt W. Rostow]].&lt;ref name=&quot;correll200702&quot;/&gt;

McNamara left the Defense Department in February 1968 and his successor [[Clark M. Clifford]] received the finished study on 15 January 1969, five days before [[Richard Nixon]]'s inauguration - although Clifford claimed he never read it. The study comprised 3,000 pages of historical analysis and 4,000 pages of original government documents in 47 volumes, and was classified as &quot;Top Secret - Sensitive&quot;. (&quot;Sensitive&quot; is not an [[Classified information in the United States|official security designation]]; it meant that the study's publication would be embarrassing.) The task force published 15 copies; the think-tank [[RAND Corp]] received two of the copies from Gelb, Halperin, and [[Paul Warnke]], with access granted if at least two of the three approved.&lt;ref name=&quot;correll200702&quot;&gt;Correll, John T. &quot;[http://www.airforce-magazine.com/MagazineArchive/Pages/2007/February%202007/0207pentagon.aspx The Pentagon Papers]&quot; ''Air Force Magazine'', February 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Leak==
[[Daniel Ellsberg]] knew the leaders of the task force well. He had worked as an aide to McNaughton from 1964 to 1965, had worked on the study for several months in 1967, and in 1969 Gelb and Halperin approved his access to the work at RAND.{{r|correll200702}} Now opposing the war, Ellsberg and his friend [[Anthony Russo (whistleblower)|Anthony Russo]]&lt;ref name=&quot;ellsberg20080807&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.antiwar.com/blog/2008/08/07/ellsberg-remembering-anthony-russo/ | title=Remembering Anthony Russo | publisher=Randolph Bourne Institute | work=Antiwar.com | date=2008-08-07 | accessdate=April 17, 2011 | author=Ellsberg, Daniel}}&lt;/ref&gt; photocopied the study in October 1969 intending to disclose it. He approached Nixon's National Security Advisor [[Henry Kissinger]], [[United States Senator|Senators]] [[William Fulbright]] and [[George McGovern]], and others, but none was interested.&lt;ref name=&quot;correll200702&quot;/&gt;

In February 1971 Ellsberg discussed the study with ''[[New York Times]]'' reporter [[Neil Sheehan]], and gave 43 of the volumes to him in March. The ''Times'' began publishing excerpts on June 13, 1971; the first article in the series was titled &quot;Vietnam Archive: Pentagon Study Traces Three Decades of Growing US Involvement&quot;. The name &quot;Pentagon Papers&quot; for the study arose during the resulting media publicity.&lt;ref name=&quot;correll200702&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Introduction to the Court Opinion on The New York Times Co. v. United States Case|url=http://usinfo.state.gov/usa/infousa/facts/democrac/48.htm|accessdate=2005-12-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; Street protests, political controversy and lawsuits followed.

To ensure the possibility of public debate about the content of the papers, on June 29, [[United States Senate|US Senator]] [[Mike Gravel]] (then [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democrat]], Alaska) entered 4,100 pages of the Papers to the record of his Subcommittee on Public Buildings and Grounds. These portions of the Papers were subsequently published by [[Beacon Press]], the publishing arm of the [[Unitarian Universalist Association]] of Congregations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Pentagon Papers, Senator Mike Gravel edition, Beacon Press|url=http://worldcat.org/oclc/248181?tab=editions}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Article One of the United States Constitution|Article I, Section 6]] of the [[United States Constitution]] provides that &quot;for any Speech or Debate in either House, [a Senator or Representative] shall not be questioned in any other Place&quot;, thus the Senator could not be prosecuted for anything said on the [[United States Senate|Senate]] floor, and, by extension, for anything entered to the ''Congressional Record'', allowing the Papers to be publicly read without threat of a [[treason]] trial and conviction. This was confirmed by the Supreme Court in the decision [[Gravel v. United States]].

Later, Ellsberg said the documents &quot;demonstrated unconstitutional behavior by a succession of presidents, the violation of their oath and the violation of the oath of every one of their subordinates&quot;.&lt;ref name=demnow&gt;http://www.democracynow.org/article.pl?sid=07/07/02/1331255&lt;/ref&gt; He added that he leaked the Papers to end what he perceived to be &quot;a wrongful war&quot;.&lt;ref name=demnow /&gt;

==Impact==
The Papers revealed that the U.S. had deliberately expanded its war with bombing of [[Cambodia]] and [[Laos]], coastal raids on [[North Vietnam]], and [[United States Marine Corps|Marine Corps]] attacks, none of which had been reported by media in the US.&lt;ref name=&quot;'70s 43&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=How We Got Here: The '70s|last=Frum|first=David|authorlink=David Frum|year= 2000| publisher=Basic Books|location=New York, New York|isbn=0-465-04195-7|page=43}}&lt;/ref&gt; The most damaging revelations in the papers revealed that four administrations, from Truman to Johnson, had misled the public regarding their intentions. For example, the [[John F. Kennedy]] administration had planned to overthrow South Vietnamese leader [[Ngo Dinh Diem]] before his death in a [[1963 South Vietnamese coup|November 1963 coup]]. President Johnson had decided to expand the war while promising &quot;we seek no wider war&quot; during his 1964 presidential campaign,&lt;ref name=&quot;correll200702&quot;/&gt; including plans to bomb [[North Vietnam]] well before the [[United States presidential election, 1964|1964 Election]]. President Johnson had been outspoken against doing so during the election and claimed that his opponent [[Barry Goldwater]] was the one that wanted to bomb North Vietnam.&lt;ref name=&quot;upi.com&quot;/&gt;

In another example, a memo from the Defense Department under the Johnson Administration listed the reasons for American persistence:

*70% - To avoid a humiliating U.S. defeat.
*20% - To keep [South Vietnam] (and the adjacent) territory from Chinese hands.
*10% - To permit the people [of South Vietnam] to enjoy a better, freer way of life.
*ALSO - To emerge from the crisis without unacceptable taint from methods used.
*NOT - To 'help a friend'&lt;ref name=&quot;correll200702&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Perlstein|first=Rick|authorlink=Rick Perlstein|title=[[Nixonland: The Rise of a President and the Fracturing of America]]|year=2008|publisher=Simon and Schuster|isbn=978-0-7432-4302-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another controversy was that President Johnson sent combat troops to Vietnam by July 17, 1965, before pretending to consult his advisors on July 21–July 27, per the cable stating that &quot;[[United States Deputy Secretary of Defense|Deputy Secretary of Defense]] [[Cyrus Vance]] informs McNamara that President had approved 34 Battalion Plan and will try to push through [[Reserve component of the Armed Forces of the United States|reserve]] call-up.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mtholyoke2&quot;&gt;[http://www.mtholyoke.edu/acad/intrel/pentagon4/pent6.htm Mtholyoke].&lt;/ref&gt; In 1988, when that cable was declassified, it revealed &quot;there was a continuing uncertainty as to [Johnson's] final decision, which would have to await Secretary McNamara's recommendation and the views of [[United States Congress|Congressional]] leaders, particularly the views of [[United States Senate|Senator]] [[Richard Russell, Jr.|[Richard] Russell]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;John Burke and Fred Greenstein, ''How Presidents Test Reality: Decisions on Vietnam, 1954 and 1965'' (1989) p. 215 n. 30.&lt;/ref&gt;

Nixon [[Solicitor General of the United States|Solicitor General]] [[Erwin N. Griswold]] later called the Papers an example of &quot;massive overclassification&quot; with &quot;no trace of a threat to the national security&quot;. The Papers' publication had little or no effect on the ongoing war because they dealt with documents written years before publication.&lt;ref name=&quot;correll200702&quot;/&gt;

After the release of the Pentagon Papers, Goldwater said:
{{quote|During the campaign, President Johnson kept reiterating that he would never send American boys to fight in Vietnam. As I say, he knew at the time that American boys were going to be sent. In fact, I knew about ten days before the Republican Convention. You see I was being called trigger-happy, warmonger, bomb happy, and all the time Johnson was saying, he would never send American boys, I knew damn well he would.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Pentagon Papers PI&quot;&gt;&quot;The Pentagon Papers: 1971 Year in Review, UPI.com&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Senator [[Birch Bayh]], who thought the publishing of the Pentagon Papers was justified, said:
{{quote|The existence of these documents, and the fact that they said one thing and the people were led to believe something else, is a reason we have a credibility gap today, the reason people don't believe the government. This is the same thing that's been going on over the last two-and-a-half years of this administration. There is a difference between what the President says and what the government actually does, and I have confidence that they are going to make the right decision, if they have all the facts.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Pentagon Papers PI&quot;/&gt;}}

==Legal case==
Prior to publication, ''The New York Times'' sought legal advice. The paper's regular outside counsel, [[Lord Day &amp; Lord]], advised against publication,&lt;ref name=&quot;correll200702&quot;/&gt; but house counsel [[James Goodale]] prevailed with his argument that the press had a [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First Amendment]] right to publish information significant to the people's understanding of their government's policy.

President Nixon's first reaction to the publication was that since the study embarrassed the Johnson and Kennedy administrations, not his, he should do nothing. However, Kissinger convinced the president that not opposing publication set a negative precedent for future secrets.&lt;ref name=&quot;correll200702&quot;/&gt; The administration argued Ellsberg and Russo were guilty of a [[felony]] under the [[Espionage Act of 1917]], because they had no authority to publish classified documents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Pentagon Papers Case|url=http://www.gwu.edu/~nsarchiv/NSAEBB/NSAEBB48/nixon.html|accessdate=2005-12-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; After failing to persuade the ''Times'' to voluntarily cease publication on June 14,&lt;ref name=&quot;correll200702&quot;/&gt; [[United States Attorney General|Attorney General]] [[John N. Mitchell]] and Nixon obtained a federal court injunction forcing the ''Times'' to cease publication after three articles.&lt;ref name=&quot;correll200702&quot;/&gt; ''Times'' publisher Arthur Ochs Sulzberger said:

{{quote|Newspapers, as our editorial said this morning, we're really a part of history that should have been made available, considerably longer ago. I just didn't feel there was any breach of national security, in the sense that we were giving secrets to the enemy.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.upi.com/Audio/Year_in_Review/Events-of-1971/12295509436546-1/#title &quot;The Pentagon Papers: 1971 Year in Review, UPI.com&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The newspaper appealed the injunction, and the case ''[[New York Times Co. v. United States]]'' (403 U.S. 713) quickly rose through the U.S. legal system to the [[United States Supreme Court|Supreme Court]].&lt;ref name=&quot;case&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=New York Times Co. v. United States, 403 U.S. 713 (1971)|url=http://supct.law.cornell.edu/supct/cases/403us713.htm|accessdate=2005-12-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On June 18, 1971, ''[[The Washington Post]]'' began publishing its own series of articles based upon the Pentagon Papers;&lt;ref name=&quot;correll200702&quot;/&gt; Ellsberg gave portions to editor [[Ben Bradlee]]. That day, Assistant U.S. Attorney General [[William Rehnquist]] asked the ''Times'' to cease publication. After the paper refused, Rehnquist sought an injunction in U.S. district court. Judge [[Murray Gurfein]] declined to issue such an injunction, writing that &quot;[t]he security of the Nation is not at the ramparts alone.  Security also lies in the value of our free institutions.  A cantankerous press, an obstinate press, an ubiquitous press must be suffered by those in authority in order to preserve the even greater values of freedom of expression and the right of the people to know.&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''[[United States v. N.Y. Times Co.]]'', 328 F. Supp. 324, 331 (S.D.N.Y. 1971).&lt;/ref&gt; The government appealed that decision, and on June 26 the Supreme Court agreed to hear it jointly with the ''New York Times'' case.&lt;ref name=&quot;case&quot;/&gt; Fifteen other newspapers received copies of the study and began publishing it.&lt;ref name=&quot;correll200702&quot;/&gt;

On June 30, 1971, the Supreme Court decided, 6–3, that the government failed to meet the heavy [[Legal burden of proof|burden of proof]] required for [[prior restraint]] injunction. The nine justices wrote nine opinions disagreeing on significant, substantive matters.

{{quote|Only a free and unrestrained press can effectively expose deception in government. And paramount among the responsibilities of a free press is the duty to prevent any part of the government from deceiving the people and sending them off to distant lands to die of foreign fevers and foreign shot and shell.|Justice Black&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=NEW YORK TIMES CO. v. UNITED STATES, 403 U.S. 713 (1971)|url=http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?court=US&amp;vol=403&amp;invol=713}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Thomas Tedford and Dale Herbeck summarize the reaction of editors and journalists at the time:
{{quote|As the press rooms of the ''Times'' and the ''Post'' began to hum to the lifting of the censorship order, the journalists of America pondered with grave concern the fact that for fifteen days the 'free press' of the nation had been prevented from publishing an important document and for their troubles had been given an inconclusive and uninspiring 'burden-of-proof' decision by a sharply divided Supreme Court. There was relief, but no great rejoicing, in the editorial offices of America's publishers and broadcasters.|Tedford and Herbeck, pp. 225–226.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Tedford &amp; Herbeck, Freedom of Speech in the United States, 5 ed.|url=http://www.stratapub.com/TedfordHerbeck/tedford_&amp;_herbeck_freedom_of_speech_in_the_united_states.htm|accessdate = 2005-12-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Ellsberg surrendered to authorities in Boston and admitted that he had given the papers to the press. He was later indicted on charges of stealing and holding secret documents by a grand jury in Los Angeles.&lt;ref name=&quot;upi.com&quot;&gt;http://www.upi.com/Audio/Year_in_Review/Events-of-1971/12295509436546-1/#title &quot;The Pentagon Papers: 1971 Year in Review, UPI.com&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Federal District Judge [[William Matthew Byrne, Jr.]] declared a [[mistrial (law)|mistrial]] and dismissed all charges against Ellsberg [and Russo] on May 11, 1973, after several irregularities appeared in the government's case, including its claim that it had lost records of illegal wiretapping against Ellsberg conducted by the [[White House Plumbers]] in the contemporaneous [[Watergate scandal]].&lt;ref name=&quot;correll200702&quot;/&gt; Byrne ruled: &quot;The totality of the circumstances of this case which I have only briefly sketched offend a sense of justice. The bizarre events have incurably infected the prosecution of this case.&quot;

{{quote|I felt that as an American citizen, as a responsible citizen, I could no longer cooperate in concealing this information from the American public. I did this clearly at my own jeopardy and I am prepared to answer to all the consequences of this decision.|
Ellsberg on why he released the Pentagon Papers to the press.&lt;ref name=&quot;upi.com&quot;/&gt;}}

''Times v. United States'' is generally considered a victory for an extensive reading of the First Amendment, but as the Supreme Court ruled on whether the government had made a successful case for prior restraint, its decision did not void the Espionage Act or give the press unlimited freedom to publish classified documents. Ellsberg and Russo were not acquitted of violating the Espionage Act; they were freed due to a mistrial from irregularities in the government's case.&lt;ref name=&quot;correll200702&quot;/&gt;

In March 1972, political scientist [[Samuel L. Popkin]], then assistant professor of Government at the [[University of California, San Diego]], was jailed for a week for his refusal to answer questions before a grand jury investigating the Pentagon Papers case, during a hearing before the [[Boston]] [[Federal District Court]].&lt;ref name=Meislin&gt;[[Richard J. Meislin]], [http://theharvardcrimson.com/article.aspx?ref=495202 Popkin Faces Jail Sentence In Contempt of Court Case], ''[[The Harvard Crimson]]'', March 22, 1972.&lt;/ref&gt; The Faculty Council later passed a resolution condemning the government's interrogation of scholars on the grounds that &quot;an unlimited right of grand juries to ask any question and to expose a witness to citations for contempt could easily threaten scholarly research.&quot;&lt;ref name=Meislin/&gt;

Gelb estimated that the ''Times'' only published about 5% of the study's 7,000 pages. The Beacon Press edition was also incomplete. Halperin, who had originally classified the study as secret, obtained most of the unpublished portions under the [[Freedom of Information Act]] and the [[University of Texas]] published them in 1983. The [[National Security Archive]] published the remaining portions in 2002. The study remained formally classified, however,&lt;ref name=&quot;correll200702&quot;/&gt; until 2011.

==Full release==
On 4 May 2011 the National Archives and Records Administration announced that the Papers would be declassified and released to the [[Richard Nixon Presidential Library and Museum]] in [[Yorba Linda, California]] on 13 June 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title=Pentagon Papers to be Officially Released|author=Steven Aftergood|publisher=Federation of American Scientists, Secrecy News|year=2011|month=May|url=http://www.fas.org/blog/secrecy/2011/05/pentagon_papers.html|accessdate=2011-05-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=Nixon Presidential Historical Materials: Opening of Materials|publisher=76 FR 27092 (2011-05-10)|url=http://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/FR-2011-05-10/pdf/2011-11533.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The release date included the Nixon, Kennedy, and LBJ Libraries, and the Archives office in [[College Park, Maryland]].&lt;ref name=Ukman&gt;{{cite news |title=Pentagon Papers to be declassified at last |first=Ukman |last=Jason |author2=Jaffe, Greg |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/national/national-security/pentagon-papers-to-be-declassified-at-last/2011/06/08/AGA0VuOH_story.html |newspaper=Washington Post |date=June 10, 2011 |accessdate=June 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The full release was coordinated by the Archives's [[National Declassification Center]] as a special project to mark the anniversary of the report.&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Keefe&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Pentagon Papers released: How they did it |first=Ed |last=O'Keefe |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/federal-eye/post/pentagon-papers-released-how-they-did-it/2011/06/13/AGpOnMTH_blog.html |newspaper=Washington Post |date=June 13, 2011 |accessdate=June 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The NDC worked with the agencies having classification control over the material to prevent the redaction of the last 11 words of the Papers that would not have been made available.&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Keefe&quot; /&gt; It is unknown which 11 words were at issue.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title=Finding the Secret 11 Words|author=Sam Roberts|publisher=The New York Times|year=2011|month=July|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/07/24/sunday-review/24words.html?_r=1|accessdate=2012-04-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Archives released each volume of the Papers as a separate PDF file,&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Keefe&quot; /&gt; available on their website.&lt;ref name=Archives&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.archives.gov/research/pentagon-papers/ |title=Pentagon Papers |author=National Archives and Records Administration |date=June 13, 2011 |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zQ4nLQ7q |archivedate=June 13, 2011 |accessdate=June 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Films==
''[[The Pentagon Papers (film)|The Pentagon Papers]]'' (2003) is a [[Historical drama film|historical film]] directed by [[Rod Holcomb]] about the Pentagon Papers and Daniel Ellsberg's involvement in their publication.
The film represents Ellsberg's life, beginning with his work for [[RAND Corp]]., and ending with the day on which his espionage trial was declared a mistrial by a federal court judge.

''[[The Most Dangerous Man in America: Daniel Ellsberg and the Pentagon Papers]]'' (2009) is a documentary film directed by Judith Ehrlich and Rick Goldsmith.
The film follows Daniel Ellsberg and explores the events leading up to the publication of the Pentagon Papers.

==See also==
{{portal|Freedom of speech}}
*[[James L. Greenfield]]
*[[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First Amendment]]
*[[United States diplomatic cables leak]]
*[[Wikileaks]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
*''The Pentagon Papers: The Defense Department History of United States Decisionmaking on Vietnam''. Boston: Beacon Press. 5 vols. &quot;Senator Gravel Edition&quot;; includes documents not included in government version. ISBN 0-8070-0526-6 &amp; ISBN 0-8070-0522-3.
*Neil Sheehan. ''The Pentagon Papers''. New York: [[Bantam Books]] (1971). ISBN 0-552-64917-1.
*Daniel Ellsberg. ''Secrets: A Memoir of Vietnam and the Pentagon Papers''. New York: Viking (2002). ISBN 0-670-03030-9.
*George C. Herring (ed.) ''The Pentagon Papers: Abridged Edition''. New York: [[McGraw-Hill]] (1993). ISBN 0-07-028380-X.
*George C. Herring (ed.) ''Secret Diplomacy of the Vietnam War: The Negotiating Volumes of the Pentagon Papers'' (1983).

==External links==
* [http://www.archives.gov/research/pentagon-papers/ The Pentagon Papers] the complete, unredacted report at the [[National Archives and Records Administration|U.S. National Archives]]
* [http://zinnedproject.org/posts/7325 Zinn Education Project: A Teaching Guide for the Most Dangerous Man in America]
*[http://www.mtholyoke.edu/acad/intrel/pentagon/pent1.html Complete text of the Gravel Edition of the Pentagon Papers] with supporting documents, maps, and photos.
*[http://www.topsecretplay.org &quot;Top Secret: Battle for the Pentagon Papers&quot; ] a resource site that supports a currently playing docu-drama about the Pentagon Papers. The site provides historical context, time lines, bibliographical resources, information on discussions with current journalists, and helpful links.
*[http://www.ellsberg.net Official website for &quot;''Secrets: A Memoir of Vietnam and the Pentagon Papers''&quot;] by [[Daniel Ellsberg]].
*''[[Democracy Now!]]'' Special: [http://www.democracynow.org/article.pl?sid=07/07/02/1331255 &quot;How the Pentagon Papers Came to Be Published by the Beacon Press&quot;:] [[Mike Gravel]] and [[Daniel Ellsberg]] (audio/video and transcript).
*[http://www.gwu.edu/~nsarchiv/NSAEBB/NSAEBB48/supreme.html Nixon Tapes &amp; Supreme Court Oral Arguments].
*[http://nytimes.whsites.net/talk/podcasts.html Podcast of a live panel discussion moderated by Jill Abramson, New York Times managing editor and former Washington bureau chief, marking the 35th anniversary of the Supreme Court ruling.]
*[http://www.clemson.edu/caah/history/FacultyPages/EdMoise/pentagon.html Article at Ed Moise's Vietnam Bibliography].
*[http://www.wcbs880.com/topic/play_window.php?audioType=Episode&amp;audioId=851936 1971 — The Pentagon Papers] A report from Steve Holt of WCBS Newsradio 880 (WCBS-AM New York) Part of WCBS 880's celebration of 40 years of newsradio.
*[http://www.beacon.org/client/pentagonpapers.cfm Beacon Press &amp; ''The Pentagon Papers'']
*[http://www.democracynow.org/2009/9/16/the_most_dangerous_man_in_america New Documentary Chronicles How Leak of the Pentagon Papers Helped End Vietnam War] - video report by ''[[Democracy Now!]]''
*[http://www.gwu.edu/~nsarchiv/NSAEBB/NSAEBB48/ The National Security Archive (The George Washington university), 2001]

[[Category:1971 in American politics]]
[[Category:Presidential scandals in the United States]]
[[Category:Nixon administration controversies]]
[[Category:Classified documents]]
[[Category:Reports of the United States government]]
[[Category:United States historical documents]]
[[Category:Vietnam War]]
[[Category:Whistleblowing]]
[[Category:Works originally published in The New York Times]]

[[cs:Pentagon Papers]]
[[da:Pentagon Papers]]
[[de:Pentagon-Papiere]]
[[fr:Pentagon Papers]]
[[ko:펜타곤 페이퍼]]
[[it:Pentagon Papers]]
[[he:פרשת מסמכי הפנטגון]]
[[nl:Pentagon Papers]]
[[ja:ペンタゴン・ペーパーズ]]
[[no:The Pentagon Papers]]
[[pl:Pentagon Papers]]
[[pt:Pentagon Papers]]
[[ru:Документы Пентагона]]
[[sv:Pentagon Papers]]
[[zh:五角大楼文件]]</text>
      <sha1>f45g6ekir4bxgztbp5vjx8pgvbweifu</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
