<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Pokémon</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>23745</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520601378</id>
      <parentid>520151953</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-30T15:30:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pikachu Bros.</username>
        <id>15722418</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Morality */ fancy dash</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="58846">{{Other uses}}
{{Redirect|Pocket Monsters|the unrelated media franchise|Monster in My Pocket}}
{{pp-semi-indef}}{{pp-move-indef}}
&lt;!--
******
If you came here to express your personal opinion about Pokémon, please go somewhere else.
Note that ALL your edits are logged and looked at.
If you make nonconstructive changes, you WILL be blocked.
Thanks.
******
--&gt;
[[File:English Pokémon logo.svg|frame|The official [[logo]] of Pokémon for its international release; &quot;Pokémon&quot; is short for the original Japanese title of &quot;Pocket Monsters&quot;.]]
{{nihongo|'''Pokémon'''|ポケモン|Pokemon|extra={{IPAc-en|pron|ˈ|p|oʊ|k|eɪ|m|ɒ|n}} {{respell|POH|kay-mon}}&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.loc.gov/nls/other/ABC.html NLS/BPH: Other Writings, The ABC Book, A Pronunciation Guide&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ssbbrawl&quot;&gt;{{cite video game| title = [[Super Smash Bros. Brawl]]| developer = [[Sora Ltd.]] | publisher = [[Nintendo]]| date = March 9, 2008 | platform = Wii| quote = (Announcer's dialog after the character Pokémon Trainer is selected ([[voice acting|voice acted]]))}}&lt;/ref&gt;}} is a [[media franchise]] published and owned by Japanese [[video game]] company [[Nintendo]] and created by [[Satoshi Tajiri]] in 1996. Originally released as a pair of interlinkable [[Game Boy line|Game Boy]] [[role-playing video game]]s developed by [[Game Freak]], Pokémon has since become the second-most successful and lucrative video game-based media franchise in the world, behind only Nintendo's own [[Mario (franchise)|''Mario'' franchise]].&lt;ref name=&quot;UK paper names top game franchises&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.gamespot.com/news/6164012.html |title = UK paper names top game franchises |accessdate = February 26, 2007 |last = Boyes |first = Emma |date = January 10, 2007 |work = GameSpot |publisher = GameSpot UK }}&lt;/ref&gt; Pokémon properties have since been [[Merchandising|merchandised]] into [[anime]], [[manga]], [[Collectible card game|trading cards]], toys, books, and other media. The franchise celebrated [[Pokémon: Tenth Anniversary|its tenth anniversary]] in 2006,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://ds.ign.com/articles/735/735858p1.html |publisher = IGN |title = Pokemon 10-Year Retrospective |accessdate = August 19, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and {{as of|2010|05|28|lc=y}}, cumulative sales of the video games (including home console versions, such as the &quot;Pikachu&quot; [[Nintendo 64]]) have reached more than 200 million copies.&lt;ref name=&quot;pokemon&quot;&gt;{{cite press release |url=http://nintendo.co.uk/NOE/en_GB/news/2010/pokmon_black_version_and_pokmon_white_version_for_nintendo_ds_coming_to_europe_in_spring_2011_17844.html |title=Pokémon Black Version and Pokémon White Version for Nintendo DS coming to Europe in Spring 2011 |accessdate=May 28, 2010 |date=May 29, 2010 | publisher=[[Nintendo]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; In November 2005, [[4Kids Entertainment]], which had managed the non-game related licensing of Pokémon, announced that it had agreed not to renew the Pokémon representation agreement. Pokémon USA Inc. (now [[The Pokémon Company|The Pokémon Company International]]), a subsidiary of Japan's Pokémon Co., now oversees all Pokémon licensing outside of Asia.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.gamasutra.com/php-bin/news_index.php?story=7615 Pokemon USA Moves Licensing In-House]&quot;, ''Gamasutra''.&lt;/ref&gt;

The name ''Pokémon'' is the [[Romanization of Japanese|romanized]] [[contraction (grammar)|contraction]] of the Japanese brand {{nihongo|'''Pocket Monsters''' |'''ポケ'''ット'''モン'''スター|'''Poke'''tto '''Mon'''sutā}},&lt;ref name=&quot;The Pokemon Series Pokedex @ Gaming Target&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.gamingtarget.com/article.php?artid=6531 |title = The Pokemon Series Pokedex |accessdate = February 28, 2007 |last = Swider |first = Matt |publisher = Gaming Target }}&lt;/ref&gt; as such contractions are quite common in Japan. The term ''Pokémon'', in addition to referring to the Pokémon franchise itself, also collectively refers to the [[List of Pokémon|649 fictional species]] that have made appearances in Pokémon media as of the release of the fifth generation titles [[Pokémon Black and White#Pokémon Black 2 and White 2|''Pokémon Black 2'' and ''White 2'']]. &quot;Pokémon&quot; is [[English plural#Nouns with identical singular and plural|identical in both the singular and plural]], as is each individual species name; it is grammatically correct to say &quot;one Pokémon&quot; and &quot;many Pokémon&quot;, as well as &quot;one [[Pikachu]]&quot; and &quot;many Pikachu&quot;.

==Concept==
The concept of the [[Pokémon universe]], in both the video games and the general fictional world of Pokémon, stems from the hobby of [[insect collecting]], a popular pastime which Pokémon executive director Satoshi Tajiri enjoyed as a child.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;{{cite news |url=http://www.time.com/time/asia/magazine/99/1122/pokemon6.fullinterview1.html |title=The Ultimate Game Freak: Interview with Satoshi Tajiri |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20050314021722/http://www.time.com/time/asia/magazine/99/1122/pokemon6.fullinterview1.html |archivedate=March 14, 2005 | work=Time | date=November 22, 1999 | accessdate=May 22, 2010}}&quot;, ''TimeAsia'' ([[Waybacked]]).&lt;/ref&gt; Players of the games are designated as [[Pokémon Trainer]]s, and the two general goals (in most Pokémon games) for such Trainers are: to complete the [[Pokédex]] by collecting all of the available Pokémon species found in the fictional region where that game takes place; and to train a team of powerful Pokémon from those they have caught to compete against teams owned by other Trainers, and eventually become the strongest Trainer: the Pokémon Master. These themes of collecting, training, and battling are present in almost every version of the Pokémon franchise, including the [[Pokémon (video game series)|video games]], the [[Pokémon (anime)|anime]] and manga series, and the [[Pokémon Trading Card Game]].

In most incarnations of the fictional Pokémon universe, a Trainer that encounters a wild Pokémon is able to capture that Pokémon by throwing a specially designed, mass-producible spherical tool called a [[Poké Ball]] at it. If the Pokémon is unable to escape the confines of the Poké Ball, it is officially considered to be under the ownership of that Trainer. Afterwards, it will obey whatever its new master commands, unless the Trainer demonstrates such a lack of experience that the Pokémon would rather act on its own accord. Trainers can send out any of their Pokémon to wage non-lethal battles against other Pokémon; if the opposing Pokémon is wild, the Trainer can capture that Pokémon with a Poké Ball, increasing his or her collection of creatures. Pokémon already owned by other Trainers cannot be captured, except under special circumstances in certain games. If a Pokémon fully defeats an opponent in battle so that the opponent is knocked out (i.e., &quot;faints&quot;), the winning Pokémon gains experience and may [[Experience point#Level-based progression|level up]]. When leveling up, the Pokémon's statistics (&quot;[[Gameplay of Pokémon#Stats|stats]]&quot;) of battling aptitude increase, such as Attack and Speed. From time to time the Pokémon may also learn new [[Pokémon moves|moves]], which are techniques used in battle. In addition, many species of Pokémon possess the ability to undergo a form of [[metamorphosis]] and transform into a similar but stronger species of Pokémon, a process called [[Pokémon evolution|evolution]].

In the main series, each game's single-player mode requires the Trainer to raise a team of Pokémon to defeat many [[non-player character]] (NPC) Trainers and their Pokémon. Each game lays out a somewhat linear path through a specific region of the Pokémon world for the Trainer to journey through, completing events and battling opponents along the way. Each game features eight especially powerful Trainers, referred to as [[Gym Leader]]s, that the Trainer must defeat in order to progress. As a reward, the Trainer receives a Gym Badge, and once all eight badges are collected, that Trainer is eligible to challenge the region's Pokémon League, where four immensely talented trainers (referred to collectively as the &quot;[[Elite Four]]&quot;) challenge the Trainer to four Pokémon battles in succession. If the trainer can overcome this gauntlet, he or she must then challenge the Regional Champion, the master Trainer who had previously defeated the Elite Four. Any Trainer who wins this last battle becomes the new champion and gains the title of Pokémon Master.

==List of Pokémon==
{{main article|List of Pokémon}}

==Video games==
{{Main|Pokémon (video game series)}}

===Generations===
&lt;!--Please don't delete/rename this header as it is linked to/from a number of places.--&gt;The original Pokémon games were role-playing games (RPGs) with an element of strategy, and were created by Satoshi Tajiri for the [[Game Boy]]. These RPGs, and their sequels, remakes, and English language translations, are still considered the &quot;main&quot; Pokémon games, and the games which most fans of the series are referring to when they use the term &quot;Pokémon games&quot;. All of the licensed Pokémon properties overseen by [[The Pokémon Company International]] are divided roughly by generation. These generations are roughly [[chronology|chronological]] divisions by release; every several years, when an official sequel in the main RPG series is released that features new Pokémon, characters, and gameplay concepts, that sequel is considered the start of a new generation of the franchise. The main games and their spin-offs, the anime, manga, and trading card game are all updated with the new Pokémon properties each time a new generation begins. The franchise began the fifth generation on September 18, 2010 in Japan.[[File:Bulbasaur pokemon red.png|thumb|right|A battle between a level 5 [[Bulbasaur]] and a level 5 [[Charmander]] in the first generation of Pokemon games; [[Pokémon Red and Blue|''Pokémon Red'' and ''Blue'']].&lt;ref&gt;MacDonald, Mark; Brokaw, Brian; Arnold; J. Douglas; Elies, Mark. Pokémon Trainer's Guide. Sandwich Islands Publishing, 1999. ISBN 0-439-15404-9. (pg73)&lt;/ref&gt;]]

The Pokémon franchise started off in its first generation with its initial release of [[Pokémon Red and Green|''Pocket Monsters Aka'' and ''Midori'']] (&quot;Red&quot; and &quot;Green&quot;, respectively) for the Game Boy in Japan. When these games proved extremely popular, an enhanced ''Ao'' (&quot;[[Pokémon Red and Blue#Pocket Monsters: Blue|Blue]]&quot;) version was released sometime after, and the ''Ao'' version was reprogrammed as ''Pokémon Red'' and ''Blue'' for international release. The games launched in the United States on September 30, 1998. The original ''Aka'' and ''Midori'' versions were never released outside of Japan.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gamefaqs.com/gameboy/924467-pokemon-green/data &quot;Pokémon Green Info on GameFAQs&quot;] ''gamefaqs.com''. Retrieved February 23, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Afterwards, a further enhanced version titled ''[[Pokémon Yellow: Special Pikachu Edition]]'' was released to partially take advantage of the color palette of the [[Game Boy Color]], as well as to feature more elements from the popular Pokémon anime. This first generation of games introduced the original 151 species of Pokémon (in National Pokédex order, encompassing all Pokémon from Bulbasaur to [[Mew (Pokémon)|Mew]]), as well as the basic game concepts of capturing, training, battling, and trading Pokémon with both computer and human players. These versions of the games take place within the fictional [[Kanto (Pokémon)|Kanto]] [[Pokémon regions|region]], though the name &quot;Kanto&quot; was not used until the second generation.

The second generation of Pokémon began in 1999 with the release of [[Pokémon Gold and Silver|''Pokémon Gold'' and ''Silver'']] for Game Boy Color. Like the previous generation, an enhanced version titled ''[[Pokémon Crystal]]'' was later released. The second generation introduced 100 new species of Pokémon (starting with [[Chikorita]] and ending with [[Celebi (Pokémon)|Celebi]]), with a total of 251 Pokémon to collect, train, and battle. The [[Pokémon mini]] is a [[handheld game console]] released in November 2001 in North America, December 2001 in Japan, and 2002 in Europe.

Pokémon entered its third generation with the 2002 release of [[Pokémon Ruby and Sapphire|''Pokémon Ruby'' and ''Sapphire'']] for [[Game Boy Advance]] and continued with the Game Boy Advance remakes of ''Pokémon Red and Blue'', [[Pokémon FireRed and LeafGreen|''Pokémon FireRed'' and ''LeafGreen'']], and an enhanced version of ''Pokémon Ruby and Sapphire'' titled ''[[Pokémon Emerald]]''. The third generation introduced 135 new Pokémon (starting with [[Treecko]] and ending with [[Deoxys]]) for a total of 386 species. However, this generation also garnered some criticism for leaving out several gameplay features, including the day-and-night system introduced in the previous generation, and it was also the first installment that encouraged the player to collect merely a selected assortment of the total number of Pokémon rather than every existing species (202 out of 386 species are catchable in the ''Ruby'' and ''Sapphire'' versions).

In 2006, Japan began the fourth generation of the franchise with the release of [[Pokémon Diamond and Pearl|''Pokémon Diamond'' and ''Pearl'']] for Nintendo DS. The fourth generation introduces another 107 new species of Pokémon (starting with [[Turtwig]] and ending with [[Arceus]]), bringing the total of Pokémon species to 493.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://au.ds.ign.com/articles/778/778464p1.html |title=The Countdown to Diamond and Pearl, Part 4|publisher=IGN|author=Lucas M. Thomas|date=April 4, 2007|accessdate=June 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Nintendo DS]] &quot;touch screen&quot; allows new features to the game such as cooking poffins with the stylus and using the &quot;Pokétch&quot;. New gameplay concepts include a restructured [[Types of Pokémon moves|move]]-classification system, online multiplayer trading and battling via [[Nintendo Wi-Fi Connection]], the return (and expansion) of the second generation's day-and-night system, the expansion of the third generation's Pokémon Contests into &quot;Super Contests&quot;, and the new region of [[Sinnoh]], which has an underground component for multiplayer gameplay in addition to the main overworld. ''[[Pokémon Platinum]]'', the enhanced version of Diamond and Pearl—much like ''Pokémon Yellow'', ''Crystal'', and ''Emerald''—was released September 2008 in Japan, March 2009 in North America, and was released in Australia and Europe in May 2009. Spin-off titles in the fourth generation include the ''Pokémon Stadium'' follow-up ''[[Pokémon Battle Revolution]]'' for [[Wii]], which has Wi-Fi connectivity as well.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.cubed3.com/news/5349 Cubed3 Pokémon Battle Revolution Confirmed for Wii]&quot; and soon Pokémon Mystery Dungeon 2: Darkness Exploration Team, and Time Exploration Team ''Cubed3.com''. Retrieved June 7, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Nintendo announced in May 2009 that enhanced remakes of ''Pokémon Gold'' and ''Silver'', entitled [[Pokémon HeartGold and SoulSilver|''Pokémon HeartGold'' and ''SoulSilver'']], released for the Nintendo DS system. ''HeartGold'' and ''SoulSilver'' are set in the [[Johto region]] and were released in September 2009 in Japan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=「ポケットモンスター」シリーズ最新作 2009年秋 ニンテンドーDSで発売決定! |url=http://www.pokemon.co.jp/info/game/g090508_01.html |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5gh1wU5k5 |archivedate=2009-05-11 |publisher=[[Nintendo]] |language=Japanese |accessdate=May 8, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The fifth generation of ''Pokémon'' began on September 18 with the release of [[Pokémon Black and White|''Pokémon Black'' and ''White'']] in Japan for Nintendo DS.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pokemon.co.jp/series/bw/|title=『ポケットモンスターブラック・ホワイト』公式サイト {{!}} ポケットモンスターオフィシャルサイト||accessdate=April 9, 2010|language=Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt; The games were originally announced by the Pokémon Company on January 29, 2010 with a tentative release [[2010 in video gaming|later that year]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pokemon.co.jp/info/game/g100129_02.html|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20100914222320/http://www.pokemon.co.jp/info/game/g100129_02.html|archivedate=2010-09-14|title=『ポケットモンスター』シリーズ完全新作 2010年内発売に向けて開発中！ {{!}} ゲーム関連 {{!}} ニュース {{!}} ポケットモンスターオフィシャルサイト|accessdate=January 29, 2010|date=January 29, 2010 |language=Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://kotaku.com/5459349/entirely-new-pokemon-series-coming-this-year|title= &quot;Entirely New&quot; Pokemon Series Coming This Year – Japan – Kotaku|author= Brian Ashcraft|publisher= Kotaku|date= Jan 28, 2010|accessdate= January 29, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; before the announcement on June 27, 2010, of the games' release on September 18, 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pokemon-sp.jp/series/bw/#/product|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20100519111512/http://www.pokemon-sp.jp/series/bw/#/product|archivedate=2010-05-19|title=商品情報 {{!}} 『ポケットモンスターブラック・ホワイト』公式サイト|accessdate=June 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; This version is set in the {{nihongo|[[Unova|Unova region]]|イッシュ地方|Isshu-chihō|Isshu region}} and utilizes the Nintendo DS's 3-D rendering capabilities to a greater extent than ''Platinum'', ''HeartGold'', and ''SoulSilver'', as shown in game footage of the player walking through the {{nihongo|Castelia City|ヒウンシティ|Hiun Shiti}} metropolis. A total of 156 new Pokémon were introduced,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=|first=|title=Pokémon Black &amp; White Versions: The Official Unova Pokédex &amp; Guide: Volume 2|editor=Micheal G. Ryan|publisher=[[The Pokémon Company]]|year=2011|pages=12–89|chapter=Unova Region Pokédex|accessdate=2011-10-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as new game mechanics such as the {{nihongo|C Gear|Cギア|C Gia}} wireless interactivity features&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pokemon-sp.jp/series/bw/#/connection/connection01.html|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20110501175448/http://www.pokemon-sp.jp/series/bw/#/connection/connection01.html|archivedate=2011-05-01|title=Cギア {{!}} 『ポケットモンスターブラック・ホワイト』公式サイト|accessdate=June 28, 2010|publisher=Nintendo|language=Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the ability to upload game data to the internet and the player's computer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pokemon-sp.jp/series/bw/#/connection/connection03.html|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20110501175448/http://www.pokemon-sp.jp/series/bw/#/connection/connection03.html|archivedate=2011-05-01|title=Webで広がる遊び {{!}} 『ポケットモンスターブラック・ホワイト』公式サイト|accessdate=June 28, 2010|publisher=Nintendo|language=Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Pokémon Black'' and ''White'' was released in Europe on March 4, 2011, in North America on March 6, 2011, and in Australia on March 10, 2011. On June 23, 2012, Nintendo released [[Pokemon Black 2 and White 2|''Pokemon Black 2'' and ''Pokemon White 2'']] in Japanese for Nintendo DS, with early October releases set to be released in North America and Europe.

===Game mechanics===
{{Main|Gameplay of Pokémon}}
The main staple of the ''Pokémon'' video game series revolves around the catching and battling of Pokémon. Starting with a starter Pokémon, the player can catch wild Pokémon by weakening them and catching them with Pokéballs. Conversely, they can choose to defeat them in battle in order to gain experience for their Pokémon, raising their levels and teaching them new moves. Certain Pokémon can evolve into more powerful forms by raising their levels or using certain items. Throughout the game, players will have to battle other trainers in order to progress, with the main goal to defeat various Gym Leaders and earn the right to become a tournament champion. Subsequent games in the series have introduced various side games and side quests, including the Battle Frontiers that display unique battle types and the Pokémon Contests where visual appearance is put on display.

====Starter Pokémon====
One of the consistent aspects of the Pokémon games—spanning from ''Pokémon Red'' and ''Blue'' on the Nintendo Game Boy to the Nintendo DS games ''Pokémon Black'' and ''White''—is the choice of one of three different Pokémon at the start of the player's adventures; these three are often labeled &quot;starter Pokémon&quot;. Players can choose a [[Pokémon types|Grass-type]], a Fire-type, or a Water-type.&lt;ref name=spy&gt;[http://uk.gba.gamespy.com/gameboy-advance/pokemon-ruby-version/498107p1.html ''Pokémon Ruby'' review (page 1)] ''Gamespy.com''. Retrieved May 30, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; For example, in ''Pokémon Red'' and ''Blue'' (and their respective reworks, ''Pokémon FireRed'' and ''Pokémon LeafGreen''), the player has the choice of starting with Bulbasaur, Charmander, or [[Squirtle]]. The exception to this rule is ''[[Pokémon Yellow]]'' (a remake of the original games that follows the story of the [[Pokémon (anime)|''Pokémon'' anime]]), where players are given a Pikachu, an [[Pokémon types|Electric-type]] mouse Pokémon, famous for being the mascot of the Pokémon media franchise; in this game, however, the three starter Pokémon from ''Red'' and ''Blue'' can be obtained during the quest by a single player, something that is not possible in any other installment of the franchise.&lt;ref&gt;[http://uk.gameboy.ign.com/articles/162/162045p1.html ''Pokémon Yellow'' Critical Review] ''Ign.com''. Retrieved March 27, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Another consistent aspect is that the player's rival will always choose as his or her starter Pokémon the one that has a type advantage over the player's Pokémon. For instance, if the player picks a Grass-type Pokémon, the rival will always pick the fire-type starter. An exception to this is again ''Pokémon Yellow'', in which the rival picks an [[Eevee]], but whether this Eevee evolves into [[Jolteon]], [[Vaporeon]], or [[Flareon]] is decided by when the player wins and loses to the rival through the journey.  The [[Nintendo GameCube|GameCube]] games, ''[[Pokémon Colosseum]]'' and ''[[Pokémon XD: Gale of Darkness]]'' also contain an exception; whereas most games start your initial Pokémon at Level 5, these games start your journey at Levels 10 and 25 respectively. In ''Colosseum'' the player's starter Pokémon are [[Espeon]] and [[Umbreon]] and in ''Gale of Darkness'' the player's starter is Eevee.

====Pokédex====
The [[Pokédex]] is a fictional electronic device featured in the Pokémon [[video game]] and [[Pokémon (anime)|anime]] series. In the games, whenever a Pokémon is first captured, its data will be added to a player's Pokédex, but in the anime or [[Pokémon Adventures|manga]], the Pokédex is a comprehensive electronic reference encyclopedia, usually referred to in order to deliver [[Exposition (literary technique)|exposition]]. &quot;Pokédex&quot; is also used to refer to a list of Pokémon, usually a list of Pokémon by number. In the video games, a [[Pokémon Trainer]] is issued a blank device at the start of the journey. A trainer must then attempt to fill the Pokédex by encountering and at least briefly obtaining each of the different species of Pokémon. A player will receive the name and image of a Pokémon after encountering one that was not previously in the Pokédex, typically after battling said Pokémon either in the wild or in a trainer battle (with the exceptions of link battles and tournament battles, such as in the Battle Frontier). In ''Pokémon Red'' and ''Blue'', some Pokémon's data is added to the Pokédex simply by viewing the Pokémon, such as in the zoo outside of the Safari Zone. Also, certain NPC characters may add to the Pokédex by explaining what a Pokémon looks like during conversation. More detailed information is available after the player obtains a member of the species, either through capturing the Pokémon in the wild, evolving a previously captured Pokémon, hatching a Pokémon egg (from the second generation onwards), or through a trade with another trainer (either an NPC or another player). This information includes height, weight, species type, and a short description of the Pokémon. Later versions of the Pokédex have more detailed information, like the size of a certain Pokémon compared to the player character, or Pokémon being sorted by their habitat (so far, the latter feature is only in the ''FireRed'' and ''LeafGreen'' versions). The most current forms of Pokédex are capable of containing information on all Pokémon currently known. The GameCube games, ''Pokémon Colosseum'' and ''Pokémon XD: Gale of Darkness'', have a Pokémon Digital Assistant ({{Unicode|P★DA}}) which is similar to the Pokédex, but also tells what types are effective against a Pokémon and gives a description of its abilities.&lt;ref&gt;Official Pokémon Scenario Guide Diamond and Pearl version p. 30-31&lt;/ref&gt;

==In other media==
[[File:Pokémon episode 1 screenshot.png|thumb|right|[[Ash Ketchum]] and Pikachu together in the pilot episode, &quot;[[Pokémon, I Choose You!]]&quot;]]

===Anime series===
{{Main|Pokémon (anime)}}
The Pokémon anime [[Television program|series]] and [[film]]s are a meta-series of adventures separate from the [[canon (fiction)|canon]] that most of the Pokémon video games follow (with the exception of ''Pokémon Yellow'', a game based loosely on the anime storyline). The anime follows the quest of the main character, Ash Ketchum&lt;ref name=ash&gt;[http://www.psypokes.com/anime/index.php Pokémon anime overview] ''Psypokes.com''. Retrieved May 25, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; (known as Satoshi in Japan) a Pokémon Master in training, as he and a small group of friends&lt;ref name=ash/&gt; travel around the fictitious world of Pokémon along with their Pokémon partners. The original series, titled ''Pocket Monsters'', or simply Pokémon in western countries (often referred to as ''Pokémon: Gotta Catch 'Em All'' to distinguish it from the later series), begins with Ash's first day as a Pokémon trainer. His first (and signature) Pokémon is a Pikachu, differing from the games, where only Bulbasaur, Charmander, or Squirtle could be chosen.&lt;ref&gt;''Pokémon 10th Anniversary, Vol. 1 – Pikachu'', Viz Video., June 6, 2006. {{OCLC|68967936}}&lt;/ref&gt; The series follows the storyline of the original games, ''Pokémon Red'' and ''Blue'', in the region of Kanto. Accompanying Ash on his journeys are [[Brock (Pokémon)|Brock]], the Pewter City Gym Leader, and [[Misty (Pokémon)|Misty]], the youngest of the Gym Leader sisters from Cerulean City. ''Pokémon: Adventures in the Orange Islands'' follows Ash's adventures in the Orange Islands, a place unique to the anime, and replaces Brock with [[Tracey Sketchit]], an artist and &quot;Pokémon watcher&quot;. The next series, based on the second generation of games, include ''Pokémon: Johto Journeys'', ''Pokémon: Johto League Champions'', and ''Pokémon: Master Quest'', following the original trio of Ash, Brock, and Misty in the western [[Johto]] region.

The saga continues in ''Pokémon: Advanced Battle'', based on the third generation games. Ash and company travel to [[Hoenn]], a southern region in the Pokémon World. Ash takes on the role of a teacher and mentor for a novice Pokémon trainer named [[May (Pokémon anime character)|May]]. Her brother [[Max (Pokémon anime character)|Max]] accompanies them, and though he isn't a trainer, he knows large amounts of handy information. Brock (from the original series) soon catches up with Ash, but Misty has returned to Cerulean City to tend to her duties as a gym leader (Misty, along with other recurring characters, appears in the spin-off series ''[[Pokémon Chronicles]]''). The Advanced Battle series concludes with the ''Battle Frontier'' saga, based on the ''Emerald'' version and including aspects of ''FireRed'' and ''LeafGreen''. The Advanced Generation series ended with Max leaving to pick his starter Pokémon, and May going to the Grand Festival in Johto.

In the ''Diamond and Pearl'' series, based on the fourth generation games, Ash, Brock, and a new companion, an aspiring Pokémon coordinator  named [[Dawn (Pokémon)|Dawn]] traveled through the region of [[Sinnoh]]. In the end of the series, Ash and Brock returned to their home region where Brock started to follow his newfound dream of becoming a Pokémon doctor himself.

''[[Pocket Monsters: Best Wishes!]]'', based on the fifth generation games, ''Pokémon Black'' and ''White'', is the newest installment of the Pokémon anime series being broadcast only Japan and the United States. It features Ash and Pikachu traveling through the new region of Unova (Isshu in Japan) along two new companions, Iris and Cilan (Dent in Japan).

In addition to the TV series, fourteen [[Pokémon (anime)#Movies|Pokémon films]] have been made, with the pair of films, [[Pokémon the Movie: Black—Victini and Reshiram and White—Victini and Zekrom|''Pokémon the Movie: Black—Victini and Reshiram'' and ''White—Victini and Zekrom'']] considered together as one. There is currently a fifteenth movie in the making. Collectible bonuses, such as promotional trading cards, have been available with some of the films.

===Films===
Given release dates are the original Japanese release dates.

{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
# ''[[Pokémon: The First Movie|Pokémon: The First Movie—Mewtwo Strikes Back]]'' (1998)
# ''[[Pokémon: The Movie 2000|Pokémon: The Movie 2000—The Power of One]]'' (1999)
# ''[[Pokémon 3: The Movie|Pokémon 3: The Movie—Spell of the Unown]]'' (2000)
# ''[[Pokémon 4Ever|Pokémon 4Ever—Celebi: Voice of the Forest]]'' (2001)
# ''[[Pokémon Heroes]]'' (2002)
# ''[[Pokémon: Jirachi Wish Maker]]'' (2003)
# ''[[Pokémon: Destiny Deoxys]]'' (2004)
# ''[[Pokémon: Lucario and the Mystery of Mew]]'' (2005){{col-2}}
&lt;ol start=&quot;9&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;''[[Pokémon Ranger and the Temple of the Sea]]'' (2006)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;''[[Pokémon: The Rise of Darkrai]]'' (2007)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;''[[Pokémon: Giratina and the Sky Warrior]]'' (2008)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;''[[Pokémon: Arceus and the Jewel of Life]]'' (2009)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;''[[Pokémon: Zoroark: Master of Illusions]]'' (2010)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;''[[Pokémon the Movie: Black—Victini and Reshiram and White—Victini and Zekrom|Pokémon the Movie: Black—Victini and Reshiram and &lt;br&gt; Pokémon the Movie: White—Victini and Zekrom]]'' (2011)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;''[[Pokémon the Movie: Kyurem vs. the Sword of Justice]]'' (2012)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
{{col-2}}
{{col-end}}

===Soundtracks===
Pokémon CDs have been released in North America, most of them in conjunction with the theatrical releases of the first three Pokémon films. These releases were commonplace until late 2001. On March 27, 2007, a tenth anniversary CD was released containing 18 tracks from the English dub; this was the first English-language release in over five years. Soundtracks of the Pokémon feature films have been released in Japan each year in conjunction with the theatrical releases.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Year
! Title
|-
| June 29, 1999&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cduniverse.com/search/xx/music/pid/1285647/a/2.B.A.+Master.htm |title=Pokémon 2.B.A. Master Soundtrack CD |accessdate=July 18, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| ''[[Pokémon 2.B.A. Master]]''
|-
| November 9, 1999&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cduniverse.com/search/xx/music/pid/1097954/a/Pokemon:+The+First+Movie.htm |title=Pokémon: The First Movie Soundtrack CD |accessdate=July 18, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| ''[[Pokémon: The First Movie (soundtrack)|Pokémon: The First Movie]]''
|-
| February 8, 2000
| ''[[Pokémon World (Single)|Pokémon World]]''
|-
| May 9, 2000
| ''[[Pokémon: The First Movie Original Motion Picture Score]]''
|-
| July 18, 2000
| ''[[Pokémon: The Movie 2000#Pokémon: The Movie 2000|Pokémon: The Movie 2000]]''
|-
| 2001
| ''[[Pokémon: The Movie 2000 Original Motion Picture Score]]''
|-
| January 23, 2001
| ''[[Totally Pokémon]]''
|-
| April 3, 2001
| ''[[Pokémon 3: The Ultimate Soundtrack]]''
|-
| October 9, 2001
| ''[[Pokémon Christmas Bash]]''
|-
| March 27, 2007
| ''[[Pokémon X]]''
|}

===Pokémon Trading Card Game===
{{Main|Pokémon Trading Card Game}}
[[File:DP01 011 Palkia.jpg|thumb|[[Palkia]], the Spacial Pokémon ''Trading Card Game'' card from ''Pokémon TCG Diamond and Pearl'']] The ''[[Pokémon Trading Card Game]]'' is a [[collectible card game]] with a goal similar to a Pokémon battle in the video game series. Players use Pokémon cards, with individual strengths and weaknesses, in an attempt to defeat their opponent by &quot;knocking out&quot; his or her Pokémon cards.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pokemon-tcg.com/p_strategy/rulebooks/book_68.jsp#433 |title= ''Pokémon Trading Card Game'' &quot;How to play&quot; guide |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20070522120208/http://www.pokemon-tcg.com/p_strategy/rulebooks/book_68.jsp |archivedate=May 22, 2007}} ''Pokemon-tcg.com''. Retrieved July 3, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; The game was first published in North America by [[Wizards of the Coast]] in 1999.&lt;ref name=wiz&gt;[http://ww2.wizards.com/Company/Misc/Index.aspx?doc=pr_20030312b ''Pokémon Trading Card Game'' News; &quot;Pokémon Ruby &amp; Sapphire TCG Releases&quot;] ''Wizards.com''. Retrieved July 3, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; However, with the release of [[Pokémon Ruby and Sapphire|''Pokémon Ruby'' and ''Sapphire'']] [[Game Boy Advance]] [[video game]]s, The Pokémon Company took back the card game from Wizards of the Coast and started publishing the cards themselves.&lt;ref name=wiz/&gt; The Expedition expansion introduced the ''Pokémon-e Trading Card Game'', where the cards (for the most part) were compatible with the [[Nintendo e-Reader]]. Nintendo discontinued its production of e-Reader compatible cards with the release of EX FireRed &amp; LeafGreen. In 1998, Nintendo released a [[Game Boy Color]] version of the trading card game in Japan; [[Pokémon Trading Card Game (video game)|Pokémon Trading Card Game]] was subsequently released to the US and Europe in 2000. The game included digital versions cards from the original set of cards and the first two expansions (Jungle and Fossil), as well as several cards exclusive to the game. A Japan-exclusive sequel was released in 2001.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gamefaqs.com/gbc/581059-pokemon-card-gb2/data &quot;Pokemon Card GB2 info on GameFAQs&quot;]. Retrieved June 8, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Manga===
{{Main|Pokémon (manga)}}
There are various Pokémon [[manga]] series, four of which were released in English by [[Viz Media]], and seven of them released in English by [[Chuang Yi]]. The manga differs greatly from the video games and anime in that the trainers were able to kill the opponent's Pokémon.
;Manga released in English
* ''[[Pokémon: The Electric Tale of Pikachu|The Electric Tale of Pikachu]]'' (a.k.a. ''Dengeki Pikachu''), a [[shōnen manga]] created by Toshihiro Ono. It was divided into four [[tankōbon]], each given a separate title in the North American and English Singapore versions: ''The Electric Tale of Pikachu'', ''Pikachu Shocks Back'', ''Electric Pikachu Boogaloo'', and ''Surf’s Up, Pikachu''. The series is based loosely on the anime.
* ''[[Pokémon Adventures]]'' (''Pocket Monsters SPECIAL'' in Japan), a shōnen manga based on the video games.
* ''[[Magical Pokémon Journey]]'' (a.k.a. Pocket Monsters PiPiPi ★ Adventures), a [[shōjo manga]]
* ''[[Pokémon (manga)|Pikachu Meets the Press]]'' (newspaper style comics, not released by Chuang Yi)
* ''[[Ash &amp; Pikachu]]'' (a.k.a. Satoshi to Pikachu, not released by Viz)
* ''[[Pokémon Gold &amp; Silver (manga)|Pokémon Gold &amp; Silver]]'' (not released by Viz)
* ''[[Pokémon Ruby-Sapphire]]'' and ''Pokémon Pocket Monsters'' (not released by Viz)
* ''[[List of Pokémon volumes#Pokémon Jirachi Wish Maker|Pokémon: Jirachi Wish Maker]]'' (not released by Viz)
* ''[[List of Pokémon volumes#Pokémon Destiny Deoxys|Pokémon: Destiny Deoxys]]'' (not released by Viz)
* ''[[List of Pokémon volumes#Pokémon Lucario and the Mystery of Mew|Pokémon: Lucario and the Mystery of Mew]]'' (the third movie-to-comic adaptation)
* ''[[List of Pokémon volumes#Pokémon Ranger and the Temple of the Sea|Pokémon Ranger and the Temple of the Sea]]''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amazon.com/dp/1421522888 Amazon.com: Pokemon: Ranger and the Temple of the Sea (Pokemon (Viz Paperback)) (9781421522883): Makoto Mizobuchi: Books&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; (the fourth movie-to-comic adaption)
* ''[[Pokémon Diamond and Pearl Adventure!]]''
* ''Pokémon Adventures: Diamond and Pearl Platinum''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amazon.com/Pok%C3%A9mon-Adventures-Diamond-Pearl-Platinum/dp/1421538172/ref=sr_1_2?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1332257514&amp;sr=1-2|title=Pokémon Adventures: Diamond and Pearl / Platinum, Vol. 2|publisher=Amazon.com|accessdate=2011-03-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''[[List of Pokémon volumes#Pokémon: The Rise of Darkrai|Pokémon: The Rise of Darkrai]]''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amazon.com/dp/1421522896 Amazon.com: Pokémon: The Rise of Darkrai (Pokemon) (9781421522890): Ryo Takamisaki: Books&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; (the fifth movie-to-comic adaption)
* ''[[List of Pokémon volumes#Pokémon: Giratina and the Sky Warrior|Pokémon: Giratina and the Sky Warrior]]''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amazon.com/dp/1421527014 Amazon.com: Pokemon: Giratina and the Sky Warrior! (Pokémon) (9781421527017): Makoto Hijioka: Books&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; (the sixth movie-to-comic adaption)
* ''[[List of Pokémon volumes#Pokémon: Arceus and the Jewel of Life|Pokémon: Arceus and the Jewel of Life]]''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amazon.com/dp/1421538024 Amazon.com: Pokémon: Arceus and the Jewel of LIfe (9781421538020): MIZOBUCHI MAKOTO: Books&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; (the seventh movie-to-comic adaption)
* ''[[List of Pokémon volumes#Pokémon: Zoroark: Master of Illusions|Pokémon: Zoroark: Master of Illusions]]'' &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amazon.com/dp/1421542218|title=Pokémon: Zoroark: Master of Illusions|publisher=Amazon.com|accessdate=August 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; (the eighth movie-to-comic adaption)
*''[[List of Pokémon volumes#Pokémon The Movie: White: Victini and Zekrom|Pokémon The Movie: White: Victini and Zekrom]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amazon.com/Pok%C3%A9mon-Movie-White-Victini-Zekrom/dp/1421549549/ref=sr_1_2?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1332256955&amp;sr=1-2|title=Pokémon the Movie: White: Victini and Zekrom|publisher=Amazon.com|accessdate=2012-03-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; (the ninth movie-to-comic adaption)
*''[[List of Pokémon Black and White chapters|Pokémon Black and White]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amazon.com/Pok%C3%A9mon-Black-White-Vol-1/dp/1421540908/ref=sr_1_3?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1336070245&amp;sr=1-3 |title=Pokémon Black and White, Vol. 1 (9781421540900): Hidenori Kusaka, Satoshi Yamamoto: Books |publisher=Amazon.com |date= |accessdate=2012-05-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amazon.com/Pok%C3%A9mon-Black-White-Vol-2/dp/1421540916/ref=sr_1_5?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1336070245&amp;sr=1-5 |title=Pokémon Black and White, Vol. 2 (9781421540917): Hidenori Kusaka, Satoshi Yamamoto: Books |publisher=Amazon.com |date= |accessdate=2012-05-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amazon.com/Pok%C3%A9mon-Black-White-Vol-3/dp/1421540924/ref=sr_1_2?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1336070245&amp;sr=1-2 |title=Pokémon Black and White, Vol. 3 (9781421540924): Hidenori Kusaka, Satoshi Yamamoto: Books |publisher=Amazon.com |date= |accessdate=2012-05-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amazon.com/Pok%C3%A9mon-Black-White-Vol-4/dp/1421541149/ref=sr_1_9?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1336070245&amp;sr=1-9 |title=Pokémon Black and White, Vol. 4 (9781421541143): Hidenori Kusaka, Satoshi Yamamoto: Books |publisher=Amazon.com |date= |accessdate=2012-05-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amazon.com/Pok%C3%A9mon-Black-White-Vol-5/dp/1421542803/ref=sr_1_8?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1336070245&amp;sr=1-8 |title=Pokémon Black and White, Vol. 5 (9781421542805): Hidenori Kusaka, Satoshi Yamamoto: Books |publisher=Amazon.com |date= |accessdate=2012-05-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amazon.com/Pok%C3%A9mon-Black-White-Vol-6/dp/1421542811/ref=sr_1_7?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1336070245&amp;sr=1-7 |title=Pokémon Black and White, Vol. 6 (9781421542812): Hidenori Kusaka, Satoshi Yamamoto: Books |publisher=Amazon.com |date= |accessdate=2012-05-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amazon.com/eacute-Black-White-Vol-Pok%C3%A9mon/dp/142154282X/ref=sr_1_10?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1336070245&amp;sr=1-10 |title=Pokémon Black and White, Vol. 7 (Pokémon Black and White) (9781421542829): Hidenori Kusaka, Satoshi Yamamoto: Books |publisher=Amazon.com |date= |accessdate=2012-05-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;
;Manga not released in English
* ''Pokémon Card ni Natta Wake'' (''How I Became a Pokémon Card'') by Kagemaru Himeno, an artist for the TCG. There are six volumes and each includes a special promotional card. The stories tell the tales of the art behind some of Himeno’s cards.
* ''Pokémon Get aa ze!'' by Miho Asada
* ''Pocket Monsters Chamo-Chamo ★ Pretty ♪'' by Yumi Tsukirino, who also made ''Magical Pokémon Journey''.
* ''Pokémon Card Master''
* ''Pocket Monsters Emerald Chōsen!! Battle Frontier'' by Ihara Shigekatsu
* ''[[Pocket Monsters Zensho]]'' by Satomi Nakamura

==Criticism and controversy==
&lt;!-- Do not add Controversy without providing reliable sources --&gt;

===Morality===
Pokémon has been criticized by some [[Christian]]s and [[Jews]]. Christian concerns over Pokémon have primarily addressed perceived [[occult]] and [[violence|violent]] themes and the concept of &quot;[[Pokémon evolution]]&quot; (although evolution in Pokémon is more akin to [[metamorphosis]], the [[ChildCare Action Project]] related it to the [[creation–evolution controversy|theory of evolution]]), which they claim goes against the Biblical creation account in Genesis,&lt;ref&gt;Carder, Thomas A. [http://www.capalert.com/capreports/pokemonthemovie.htm Pokémon: The Movie (1999)].ChildCare Action Project: 1999&lt;/ref&gt; which the majority of [[Japanese people|Japanese]], not adhering to [[Christianity]], do not believe in.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.asianinfo.org/asianinfo/japan/religion.htm |title=Japan's Religion and Philosophy (Shinto, Buddhism, Christianity, Religion in Japan Today) |publisher=Asianinfo.org |date= |accessdate=May 21, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Religion in Japan]]&lt;/ref&gt; A satellite TV station based in the Vatican, however, has countered that the Pokémon trading card game and video games are &quot;full of inventive imagination&quot; and have no &quot;harmful moral side effects&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Silverman, Stephen M. [http://www.people.com/people/article/0,26334,620818,00.html Pokemon Gets Religion]. ''[[People (magazine)|People]]''&lt;/ref&gt; In the United Kingdom, the &quot;Christian Power Cards&quot; game was introduced in 1999 by David Tate who stated, &quot;Some people aren't happy with Pokémon and want an alternative, others just want Christian games.&quot; The game was similar to the Pokémon TCG but used Biblical figures.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/808361.stm Pokémon trumped by pocket saints]. BBC: June 27, 2000.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1999, Nintendo stopped manufacturing the Japanese version of the &quot;Koga's Ninja Trick&quot; trading card because it depicted a [[swastika#Other Asian traditions|manji]], a traditionally [[Buddhist]] symbol with no negative connotations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Koga%27s_Ninja_Trick_%28Gym_Challenge_115%29|title=Koga's Ninja Trick|work=Bulbapedia|accessdate=August 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Judaism|Jewish]] civil rights group [[Anti-Defamation League]] complained because the symbol is the reverse of a [[swastika]], which is considered offensive to Jewish people. The cards were intended for sale in Japan only, but the popularity of Pokémon led to importation in to the United States with approval from Nintendo. The Anti-Defamation League understood that the issue symbol was not intended to offend and acknowledged the sensitivity that Nintendo showed by removing the product.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-4525479.html |title='Swastika' Pokemon card dropped |last=Fitzgerald|first=Jim|date=December 3, 1999|work=[[Chicago Sun-Times]]|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20071211235110/http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4155/is_19991203/ai_n13847438|archivedate=December 11, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2001, [[Saudi Arabia]] banned Pokémon games and cards, alleging that the franchise promoted [[Zionism]] by displaying the [[Star of David]] in the trading cards, and involved gambling, which is in violation of [[Islam|Muslim]] doctrine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://archives.cnn.com/2001/WORLD/meast/03/26/saudi.pokemon/ |title=Saudi bans Pokemon |date=March 26, 2001|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080118135529/http://archives.cnn.com/2001/WORLD/meast/03/26/saudi.pokemon/ |archivedate=January 18, 2008 | publisher=CNN}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/1243307.stm|title=Saudi Arabia bans Pokemon|date=March 26, 2001|work=BBC News|accessdate=February 13, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pokémon has been accused of promoting [[Economic materialism|materialism]].&lt;ref&gt;Ramlow, Todd R. [http://www.popmatters.com/pm/review/pokemon-the-movie-2000 Pokemon, or rather, Pocket Money]. Popmatters: 2000&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1999, two nine-year-old boys sued Nintendo because they claimed the Pokémon Trading Card Game caused their [[problem gambling|problematic gambling]].&lt;ref&gt;Crowley, Kieran. {{cite web |url=http://www.nypost.com/news/14579.htm |title=Lawsuit Slams Pokemon As Bad Bet for Addicted Kids |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20001022030204/http://www.nypost.com/news/14579.htm |archivedate=October 22, 2000}}. ''[[New York Post]]'': October 1999&lt;/ref&gt;

===Health===
&lt;!--The seizures were caused by ''flashing''' colors, stills will not blind people!--&gt;{{Main|Dennō Senshi Porygon}}
On December 16, 1997, more than 635 Japanese children were admitted to hospitals with epileptic [[seizures]]. It was determined the seizures were caused by watching an episode of Pokémon &quot;[[Dennō Senshi Porygon]]&quot;, (most commonly translated &quot;Electric Soldier Porygon&quot;, season 1, episode 38); as a result, this episode has not been aired since. In this particular episode, there were bright explosions with rapidly alternating blue and red color patterns.&lt;ref&gt;[http://faculty.washington.edu/chudler/pokemon.html Pokemon packs a punch]. Retrieved January 7, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; It was determined in subsequent research that these strobing light effects cause some individuals to have epileptic seizures, even if the person had no previous history of [[epilepsy]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;{{cite web |url=http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/1999/06/990601080722.htm |title=Color Changes in TV Cartoons Cause Seizures |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20041108175456/http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/1999/06/990601080722.htm |archivedate=November 8, 2004}}&quot;, ''ScienceDaily'' ([[Internet Archive|Waybacked]]).&lt;/ref&gt; This incident is the most common focus of Pokémon-related parodies in other media, and was lampooned by the ''[[The Simpsons|Simpsons]]'' episode &quot;[[Thirty Minutes over Tokyo]]&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.snpp.com/episodes/AABF20|title=Thirty Minutes Over Tokyo|publisher=The Simpsons Archive|accessdate=July 16, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the ''[[South Park]]'' episode &quot;[[Chinpokomon]]&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.arts.auckland.ac.nz/FileGet.cfm?ID=1cff12f4-03a2-4126-b886-16b7669da213|title=South Park Goes Global: Reading Japan in Pokemon |publisher=[[University of Auckland]] |accessdate=September 30, 2008}}{{dead link|date=December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; among others.

===Monster in My Pocket===
In March 2000, Morrison Entertainment Group, a small toy developer based at [[Manhattan Beach, California]], sued Nintendo over claims that Pokémon infringed on its own &quot;[[Monster in My Pocket]]&quot; characters. A judge ruled there was no infringement so Morrison appealed the ruling in November 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Bronstad|first=Amanda|title=Toy Firm Will Appeal 'Pocket Monster' Suit|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m5072/is_46_23/ai_80165415|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20071015132351/http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m5072/is_46_23/ai_80165415|archivedate=October 15, 2007|work=Los Angeles Business Journal|publisher=FindArticles.com|date=November 12, 2001|accessdate=September 1, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Cultural influence==
[[File:All Nippon Airways Boeing 747-400 yellow pokemon.jpg|thumb|[[All Nippon Airways]] [[Boeing 747|Boeing 747–400]] in Pokémon livery, and dubbed a [[Pokémon Jet]].]]
Pokémon, being a popular franchise, has undoubtedly left its mark on [[popular culture|pop culture]]. The Pokémon characters themselves have become pop culture icons; examples include two different [[Pikachu]] balloons in the [[Macy's Thanksgiving Day Parade]], Pokémon Jets operated by All Nippon Airways, thousands of merchandise items, and a [[Poképark|theme park]] in [[Nagoya|Nagoya, Japan]] in 2005 and [[Taipei]] in 2006. Pokémon also appeared on the cover of the U.S. magazine ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'' in 1999. The Comedy Central show ''[[Drawn Together]]'' has a character named [[Ling-Ling]] which is a direct parody of Pikachu.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://trsrockin.com/ripoffs.html |title=Pokemon Sightings and Rip-offs |accessdate=June 29, 2008 }} {{dead link |date=June 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Several other shows such as ''[[ReBoot]]'', ''The Simpsons'', ''South Park'', ''[[The Grim Adventures of Billy &amp; Mandy]]'', ''[[Robot Chicken]]'', ''[[All Grown Up!]]'' and ''[[Johnny Test]]'' have made references and spoofs of Pokémon, among other series. Pokémon was also featured on [[VH1]]'s ''[[I Love the '90s: Part Deux]]''. A live action show called ''[[Pokémon Live!]]'' toured the United States in late 2000. It was based on the popular [[Pokémon (anime)|Pokémon anime]], but had some continuity errors relating to it.  [[Jim Butcher]] cites Pokémon as one of the inspirations for the [[Codex Alera]] series of novels.

In November 2001, Nintendo opened a store called the Pokémon Center in New York, in New York's [[Rockefeller Center]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.auctionbytes.com/cab/abn/y01/m11/i19/s03 Opening Date of Store]&lt;/ref&gt; modeled after the two other Pokémon Center stores in Tokyo and [[Osaka]] and named after a staple of the videogame series; Pokémon Centers are fictional buildings where Trainers take their injured Pokémon to be healed after combat.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pokezam.com/pokemon/pokecenterny/ Information on the Store]&lt;/ref&gt; The store sold Pokémon merchandise on a total of two floors, with items ranging from collectible shirts to stuffed Pokémon [[stuffed animal|plushies]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bigapplevisitorscenter.com/kids.htm Tour Site Page]&lt;/ref&gt; The store also featured a ''Pokémon Distributing Machine'' in which players would place their game to receive an egg of a Pokémon that is being given out at that time. The store also had tables that were open for players of the Pokémon Trading Card Game to duel each other or an employee. The store was closed and replaced by the [[Nintendo World Store]] on May 14, 2005.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ml.wisdomdigital.com/listingsinfo.cfm?id=62&amp;table=Shopping&amp;lid=7&amp;cat=19 Manhattan Living Page On Store] [http://replay.waybackmachine.org/20090123041359/http://ml.wisdomdigital.com/listingsinfo.cfm?id=62&amp;table=Shopping&amp;lid=7&amp;cat=19 Archived] by the [[Wayback Machine]] beta.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:名鉄2201Fギラティナ・シェイミ号20080720.jpg|thumb|left|[[Meitetsu]] 2200 series train ''Giratina &amp; Shaymin'']]
Joseph Jay Tobin theorizes that the success of the franchise was mainly due to the long list of names that could be learned by children and repeated in their peer groups. The rich fictional universe provided a lot of opportunities for discussion and demonstration of knowledge in front of their peers. In the French version Nintendo took care to translate the name of the creatures so that they reflected the French culture and language. In all cases the names of the creatures were linked to its characteristics, which converged with the children's belief that names have symbolic power. Children could pick their favourite Pokémon and affirm their individuality while at the same time affirming their conformance to the values of the group, and they could distinguish themselves from other kids by asserting what they liked and what they didn't like from every chapter. Pokémon gained popularity because it provided a sense of identity to a wide variety of children, and lost it quickly when many of those children found that the identity groups were too big and searched for identities that would distinguish them into smaller groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Pikachu's global adventure: the rise and fall of Pokémon |author=Joseph Jay Tobin |publisher=[[Duke University Press]] |year=2004 |isbn=0-8223-3287-6 ISBN 9780822332879 |url=http://books.google.com/books?lr=&amp;hl=ca&amp;id=U7hthImoc5AC&amp;q=naming&amp;pa=193#v=snippet&amp;q=naming&amp;f=false }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In December 2009, a &quot;Pokémon profile picture month&quot; on popular [[social networking]] website [[Facebook]] started, with over 100,000 (by some estimates) Facebook users changing the image displayed on their profile webpages to that of a Pokémon. In 2010, more than 252,000 people replied as &quot;attending&quot;, or taking part in, the event, at least double the previous year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |publisher=Facebook |year=2010 |accessdate=December 5, 2010 |title=Pokemon Profile Picture Month |url=http://www.facebook.com/event.php?eid=347947515181 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:E311-1000.JPG|thumb|[[Shinkansen E3 Series]] train in Pokémon livery]]
''Pokémon''{{'}}s history has been marked at times by rivalry with the ''[[Digimon]]'' media franchise that debuted at a similar time. Described as &quot;the other 'mon{{'&quot;}} by [[IGN]]'s Juan Castro, ''Digimon'' has not enjoyed ''Pokémon''{{'}}s level of international popularity or success, but has maintained a dedicated fanbase.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=E3 2005: Digimon World 4 |url=http://xbox.ign.com/articles/617/617917p1.html |last=Castro |first=Juan |publisher=IGN |date=May 20, 2005 |accessdate=April 4, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; IGN's Lucas M. Thomas stated that ''Pokémon'' is ''Digimon''{{'}}s &quot;constant competition and comparison&quot;, attributing the former's relative success to the simplicity of its [[Pokémon evolution|evolution]] mechanic as opposed to [[Digivolution]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Cheers &amp; Tears: DS Fighting Games |url=http://ds.ign.com/articles/101/1015325p2.html |last=Thomas |first=Lucas M. |date=August 21, 2009 |publisher=IGN |accessdate=April 4, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The two have been noted for conceptual and stylistic similarities by sources such as [[GameZone]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Digimon World 3 Review |url=http://psx.gamezone.com/gzreviews/r19874.htm |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20100127124741/http://psx.gamezone.com/gzreviews/r19874.htm|archivedate=2010-01-27 |last=Bedigian |first=Louis |publisher=[[GameZone]] |date=July 12, 2002 |accessdate=May 1, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; A debate among fans exists over which of the two franchises came first.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Digimon World DS Review |url=http://ds.ign.com/articles/747/747449p1.html |last=DeVries |first=Jack |publisher=IGN |date=November 22, 2006 |accessdate=May 8, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In actuality, the first ''Pokémon'' media, ''Pokémon Red'' and ''Green'', were released initially on February 27, 1996;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Related Games |url=http://www.gamespot.com/gameboy/rpg/pokemonred/similar.html?mode=versions |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20110628230134/http://www.gamespot.com/gameboy/rpg/pokemonred/similar.html?mode=versions |archivedate=2011-06-28 |publisher=[[GameSpot]] |accessdate=May 8, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; whereas the [[Digimon virtual pet|''Digimon'' virtual pet]] was released on June 26, 1997.
{{clear}}

==See also==
{{portal|Pokémon}}
{{div col}}
;Pokémon general
* [[List of Pokémon]]
* [[List of Pokémon characters]]
* [[Pokémon regions]]
; Books
* [[Pokémon (manga)]]
* [[List of Pokémon chapters]]
;Video games
* [[Gameplay of Pokémon]]
* [[List of Pokémon video games]]
* [[Pokémon (video game series)]]
;Television
* [[Pokémon episodes removed from rotation]]
* [[List of Pokémon episodes]]
* [[Pokémon (anime)]]
;Similar video game series
* [[Dragon Quest Monsters]]
* [[Robotrek]]
* [[Azure Dreams]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
;Books
* Tobin, Joseph, ed. ''Pikachu's Global Adventure: The Rise and Fall of Pokémon.'' Duke University Press., February, 2004. ISBN 0-8223-3287-6

;Notes
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
&lt;!--Please do not add any more links to this section without first discussing it on the talk page --&gt;
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Wiktionary}}
{{Commons}}
*[http://www.pokemon.co.jp/ Official Japanese website of ''Pokémon''] {{ja icon}}
*[http://www.pokemon.com/ Official US website of ''Pokémon'']
*[http://www.pokemon.com/uk/ Official UK website of ''Pokémon'']
*[http://www.go-pokemon.com/ Official US website of ''Pokémon Trading Card Game'']
*[http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Main_Page Bulbapedia, the community driven Pokémon encyclopedia]

{{Pokémon}}
{{Main franchises by Nintendo}}

{{Good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Pokemon}}
[[Category:1996 introductions]]
[[Category:Media franchises]]
[[Category:Pokémon| ]]
[[Category:1990s toys]]
[[Category:2000s toys]]
[[Category:2010s toys]]
[[Category:Article Feedback 5 Additional Articles]]

{{Link GA|es}}
{{Link GA|fr}}
{{Link FA|hr}}
{{Link FA|id}}
{{Link GA|ru}}
{{Link FA|ru}}

[[af:Pokémon]]
[[als:Pokemon]]
[[ar:بوكيمون]]
[[bn:পোকিমন]]
[[bg:Покемон]]
[[bs:Pokémon]]
[[br:Pokémon]]
[[ca:Pokémon]]
[[ceb:Pokémon]]
[[cs:Pokémon]]
[[cy:Pokémon]]
[[da:Pokémon]]
[[de:Pokémon]]
[[el:Πόκεμον]]
[[es:Pokémon]]
[[eo:Pokemono]]
[[fa:پوکمون]]
[[fr:Pokémon]]
[[fy:Pokémon]]
[[ga:Pokémon]]
[[gl:Pokémon]]
[[ko:포켓몬스터]]
[[haw:Pokémon]]
[[hi:पॉकेमॉन]]
[[hr:Pokémon]]
[[id:Pokémon]]
[[ia:Pokémon]]
[[is:Pokémon]]
[[it:Pokémon]]
[[he:פוקימון]]
[[jv:Pokemon]]
[[la:Pokémon]]
[[lv:Pokemoni]]
[[lb:Pokémon]]
[[lt:Pokemon]]
[[hu:Pokémon]]
[[ml:പോകിമോൻ]]
[[ms:Pokémon]]
[[nl:Pokémon]]
[[ja:ポケットモンスター]]
[[no:Pokémon]]
[[nn:Pokémon]]
[[uz:Pokémon]]
[[pl:Pokémon]]
[[pt:Pokémon]]
[[ro:Pokémon]]
[[ru:Покемон]]
[[sah:Pokémon]]
[[sq:Pokémon]]
[[simple:Pokémon]]
[[sk:Pokémon]]
[[sl:Pokémon]]
[[so:Pokemon]]
[[sr:Покемони]]
[[su:Pokemon]]
[[fi:Pokémon]]
[[sv:Pokémon]]
[[tl:Pokémon]]
[[ta:பொகெமொன்]]
[[th:โปเกมอน]]
[[chr:ᏉᎨᎼᏂ]]
[[tr:Pokémon]]
[[uk:Покемон]]
[[vi:Pokémon]]
[[zh-classical:神奇寶貝]]
[[zh-yue:寵物小精靈]]
[[zh:神奇宝贝系列]]</text>
      <sha1>hj002jzyzh4ssl1dfrph2wn0kg9dca1</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
