<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Rave</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>43488</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520485509</id>
      <parentid>520427370</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-29T20:50:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>91.203.190.36</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Drug use */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="51302">{{Other uses}}
{{for|the genre &quot;rave music&quot;|rave music|breakbeat hardcore}}
{{Multiple issues
| original research = July 2008
| cleanup = April 2008
| external links = September 2010}}
{{Use British English|date=November 2011}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2011}}

[[File:Sensation White 08.03.2008 015.jpg|thumb|right|250px|A large rave event, held in a warehouse-sized venue, with elaborate lighting and a large [[Sound reinforcement system|sound system]]]]
'''Rave''', '''rave dance''', and '''rave party''' are parties that originated mostly because of [[acid house]] parties, which featured [[electronic music]] and light shows.&lt;ref name=pop/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;FD&quot;&gt;[http://www.thefreedictionary.com/rave Rave], Free Dictionary.&lt;/ref&gt; At these parties people dance and [[socialize]] to [[dance music]] played by [[disc jockeys]] and occasionally [[live music|live performers]]. The genres of [[electronic dance music]] played include [[House music|house]], [[Trance music|trance]], [[psytrance]], [[techno]], [[dubstep]], [[oldschool jungle|jungle]], [[drum and bass]], [[UK hardcore]], [[hardcore techno]], [[happy hardcore]], [[breakbeat]], [[hardstyle]] and most other electronic music genres with the accompaniment of [[Laser lighting display|laser light shows]], [[Image projector|projected images]], paint, [[glow stick]]s and [[Fog machine|smoke machines]].

==History==
In the late 1950s in London the term &quot;Rave&quot; was used to describe the &quot;wild [[bohemian]] parties&quot; of the [[Soho]] [[beatnik]] set.&lt;ref name=&quot;outofsight&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://hehe.org.free.fr/hehe/texte/rave/#hist
| title = OUT OF SIGHT, OUT OF MIND: An Analysis of Rave culture
| accessdate =25 October 2007 | author=Helen Evans
| quote = The term rave first came into use in late 50s Britain as a name for the wild bohemian parties of the time.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1958 [[Buddy Holly]] recorded the hit &quot;Rave On,&quot; citing the madness and frenzy of a feeling and the desire for it to never end.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.visualthesaurus.com/cm/wordroutes/1687/&lt;/ref&gt; The word &quot;rave&quot; was later used in the burgeoning [[Mod (subculture)|mod]] youth culture of the early 1960s as the way to describe any wild party in general.  People who were gregarious party animals were described as &quot;ravers&quot;. Pop musicians such as [[Steve Marriott]] of [[The Small Faces]] and [[Keith Moon]] of [[The Who]] were self-described &quot;ravers&quot;.

Presaging the word's subsequent 1980s association with [[electronic music]], the word &quot;rave&quot; was a common term used regarding the music of mid-1960s [[garage rock]] and [[psychedelia]] bands (most notably [[The Yardbirds]], who released an album in the US called ''[[Having a Rave Up]]'').  Along with being an alternative term for partying at such garage events in general, the &quot;rave-up&quot; referred to a specific crescendo moment near the end of a song where the music was played faster, heavier and with intense soloing or elements of controlled feedback. It was later part of the title of an [[electronic music]] performance event held on 28 January 1967 at London's [[Roundhouse (venue)|Roundhouse]] titled the &quot;Million Volt Light and Sound Rave&quot;. The event featured the only known public airing of an experimental sound collage created for the occasion by [[Paul McCartney]] of [[The Beatles]] – the legendary ''[[Carnival of Light]]'' recording.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.delia-derbyshire.org/unitdeltaplus.php
| title = Unit Delta Plus
| accessdate =25 October 2007
| publisher=Delia Derbyshire
| quote = Perhaps the most famous event that Unit Delta Plus participated in was the 1967 ''Million Volt Light and Sound Rave'' at London's Roundhouse, organised by designers Binder, Edwards and Vaughan (who had previously been hired by Paul McCartney to decorate a piano). The event took place over two nights (28 January and 4 February 1967) and included a performance of tape music by Unit Delta Plus, as well as a playback of the legendary ''Carnival of Light'', a fourteen minute sound collage assembled by McCartney around the time of the Beatles' ''Penny Lane'' sessions.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With the rapid change of British pop culture from the mod era of 1963–1966 to the [[hippie]] era of 1967 and beyond, the term fell out of popular usage. During the 1970s and early 1980s until its resurrection, the term was not in vogue, one notable exception being in the lyrics of the song &quot;[[Drive-In Saturday]]&quot; by [[David Bowie]] (from his 1973 album ''[[Aladdin Sane]]'') which includes the line &quot;It's a crash course for the ravers.&quot; Its use during that era would have been perceived as a quaint or ironic use of bygone slang: part of the dated 1960s lexicon along with words such as &quot;groovy&quot;. The perception of the word changed again in the late 1980s when the term was revived and adopted by a new youth culture, possibly inspired by the use of the term in Jamaica.&lt;ref name=&quot;outofsight&quot;/&gt;

In the mid to late 1980s a wave of psychedelic and other [[electronic dance music]], most notably [[acid house]] and Techno, emerged and caught on in the clubs, warehouses, and free-parties first in Manchester in the mid 80's and then later London . In many ways what would become known as the Rave scene , was influenced by the Northern Soul scene which throughout the late 1960's and through the 1970's and 80's had involved large groups of mainly working class kids dancing all night to rare US soul records while popping amphetamines. When Margaret Thatcher's policies in the late 70's lead to the closure of the UK's textile industry in the northwest , suddenly large mills and warehouses became empty and illegal parties were held in them. The first warehouse parties in Manchester were organised by the group The Stone Roses back in 1985 , when to get around the licensing laws they would play a gigg and book a line up of DJs under the dusused arches of Piccadilly train station. These parties were then advertised as an all night video shoot , and the kids who bought tickets for £5 would have a ip piece sellotaped to the back as their fee for being extras in a video shoot , thus for several months the forces of law and order were kept at bay. Dance music was always prominent with big electro, Jazz Funk and early house tunes being played in a somewhat balearic mix alongside New Order, The Clash and The Smiths.House music caught on very quickly in the north and midlands from 1986 onwards , even being played in mainstream night clubs. In 1988 London sudden;y adopted this scene , and rebranded it , so records which a week earlier had been House Records , were suddenly Acid House and smiley badges and other marketing paraphernalia became involved.These early raves were called [[Acid House Parties]]. They were mainstream events that attracted thousands of people (up to 25,000{{Citation needed|date=December 2007}}&lt;!-- Previously cited with a ref named &quot;Energy Flash&quot; if anyone knows what happened to that. --&gt; instead of the 4,000 that came to earlier warehouse parties). Acid House parties were first re-branded &quot;rave parties&quot; in the media, during the summer of 1989 by [[Genesis P-Orridge|Neil Andrew Megson]] during a television interview, however, the ambience of the rave was not fully formed until 28 May 1991. In the UK, in 1988–89, raves were similar to football matches in that they provided a setting for working-class unification, in a time with a union movement in decline and few jobs, and many of the attendees of raves were die-hard football fans.&lt;ref name=&quot;Generation Ecstasy&quot;&gt;Timeline and numbers {{cite book
| last = Reynolds | first = Simon | year = 1998
| title = Generation Ecstasy: into the world of Techno and Rave culture
| publisher=Picador | isbn = 0-330-35056-0 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the late 1980s, the word &quot;rave&quot; was adopted to describe the [[subculture]] that grew out of the acid house movement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hyperreal.org/raves/database/visuale/ve1.htm |title=Visual Energy |author=Simon Parkin |date=May 1999}}&lt;/ref&gt; Activities were related to the party atmosphere of [[Ibiza]], a Mediterranean island in Spain, frequented by British, Italians, and German youth on vacation.&lt;ref name=&quot;pop&quot;&gt;&quot;The Problem of Rave Parties&quot;, Michael S. Scott, Center for Problem Oriented Policing, 2009, webpage: [http://www.popcenter.org/problems/rave_parties/ popc-rave].&lt;/ref&gt; The fear that a certain number of rave party attendees used &quot;[[club drug]]s&quot; such as [[Methylenedioxymethamphetamine|MDMA]], [[cocaine]], [[amphetamines]] and, more recently, [[ketamine]], was taken by authorities as a pretext to ban those parties altogether.

British politicians responded with hostility to the emerging rave party trend. Politicians spoke out against raves and began to [[fine (penalty)|fine]] anyone who held illegal parties. Police crackdowns on these often-illegal parties drove the scene into the countryside. The word &quot;rave&quot; somehow caught on in the UK to describe common semi-spontaneous weekend parties occurring at various locations linked by the brand new [[M25 motorway|M25 London Orbital]] motorway that ringed London and the [[Home Counties]]. (It was this that gave the band [[Orbital (band)|Orbital]] their name.) These ranged from former warehouses and industrial sites, in London, to fields and country clubs in the countryside.

===United Kingdom===
{{see also|Second Summer of Love|Acid house|House music|Techno|Electronica|Electronic dance music}}

By 1991, organisations such as [[Fantazia (dance)|Fantazia]], Universe, [[Raindance (rave)|Raindance]] and Amnesia House were holding massive legal raves in fields and warehouses around the country. One Fantazia party, called One Step Beyond, was an open-air, all-night affair that attracted 30,000 people. Other notable events included Vision at Pophams airfield in August 1992, with 40,000 in attendance and Universe's [[Tribal Gathering]] in 1993.

In the early 1990s, the scene was slowly changing, with local councils passing by-laws and increasing fees in an effort to prevent or discourage rave organisations from acquiring necessary licenses.{{Citation needed|date=December 2011}} This meant that the days of legal one-off parties were numbered. By the mid-1990s, the scene had fragmented into many different styles of dance music, making large parties more expensive to set up and more difficult to promote. The happy [[Rave music|old skool]] style was replaced by the darker [[oldschool jungle|jungle]] and the faster [[happy hardcore]]. Although many ravers left the scene due to the split, promoters such as ESP Dreamscape and [[Helter Skelter (rave music promoter)|Helter Skelter]] still enjoyed widespread popularity and capacity attendances with multi-arena events catering to the various genres. Particularly notable events of this period included ESP's Dreamscape 20 on 9 September 1995 at Brafield aerodrome fields, [[Northamptonshire|Northants]] and Helter Skelter's Energy 97 event on 9 Aug 1997 at Turweston Aerodrome, Northants.

The illegal [[free party]] scene also reached its zenith for that time after a particularly large festival, when many individual sound systems such as [[Bedlam sound system|Bedlam]], Circus Warp, DIY, and [[Spiral Tribe]] set up near [[Castlemorton Common Festival|Castlemorton]] Common. In May 1992, the government acted. Under the ''[[Criminal Justice and Public Order Act 1994]]'', the definition of music played at a rave was given as:

{{bquote|&quot;music&quot; includes sounds wholly or predominantly characterised by the emission of a succession of repetitive beats.&lt;br&gt;{{Nb10}}–Criminal Justice and Public Order Act 1994&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.opsi.gov.uk/acts/acts1994/ukpga_19940033_en_8#pt5-pb2 |title=Public Order: Collective Trespass or Nuisance on Land – Powers to remove trespassers on land – Powers to remove persons attending or preparing for a rave |work=Criminal Justice and Public Order Act 1994 |publisher=[[Her Majesty's Stationery Office]] |accessdate=9 June 2008| year=1994}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Sections 63, 64 &amp; 65 of the Act targeted [[electronic dance music]] played at raves. The Criminal Justice and Public Order Act empowered police to stop a rave in the open air when a hundred or more people are attending, or where two or more are making preparations for a rave. Section 65 allows any uniformed constable who believes a person is on their way to a rave within a five-mile radius to stop them and direct them away from the area; non-compliant citizens may be subject to a maximum fine not exceeding level 3 on the [[standard scale]] (£1000). The Act was officially introduced because of the noise and disruption caused by all night parties to nearby residents, and to protect the countryside. However, it has also been claimed that it was introduced to kill a popular youth movement that was taking many drinkers out of town centres, where they would drink taxable alcohol, and into fields to take untaxed illicit drugs.{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}} In November 1994, the Zippies staged an act of [[Intervasion of the UK|electronic civil disobedience]] to protest against the CJB.

After 1993, the main outlet for raves in the UK were a number of licensed venues, amongst them [[Helter Skelter (rave music promoter)|Helter Skelter]], Life at Bowlers (Trafford Park, Manchester), The Edge (formerly the Eclipse [Coventry]), The Sanctuary (Milton Keynes) and Club Kinetic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.rezerection.net/main.html
| title = REZERECTION – THE OFFICIAL WEBSITE (z)
| accessdate =25 October 2007 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070928062044/http://www.rezerection.net/main.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 28 September 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- Please add a quote to this one --&gt;. In London, itself, there were a few large clubs that staged raves on a regular basis, most notably &quot;The Laser Dome&quot;, &quot;The Fridge&quot;, &quot;The Hippodrome&quot;, &quot;Club U.K.&quot;, and &quot;Trade.&quot; &quot;The Laser Dome&quot; featured two separate dance areas, &quot;Hardcore&quot; and &quot;Garage&quot;, as well as over 20 video game machines, a silent-movie screening lounge, replicas of the &quot;Statue of Liberty&quot;, &quot;San Francisco Bridge&quot;, and a large glass maze. At capacity &quot;The Laser Dome&quot; held in excess of 6,000 people. Events proved to be one of the main forces in rave, holding legendary events across the north-east and [[Scotland]]. Initially playing Techno, [[Breakbeat]], Rave and drum and bass, it later embraced [[hardcore techno]] including happy hardcore and [[bouncy techno]]. Judgement Day, History of Dance, and now REGENeration continued the Rezerection legacy. Scotland's clubs, such as the [[FUBAR (nightclub)|FUBAR]] in [[Stirling, Scotland|Stirling]], [[Hangar 13]] in [[Ayr]], and [[Nosebleed (nightclub)|Nosebleed]] in [[Rosyth]] played important roles in the development of these dance music styles.

These were nearly all pay-to-enter events; however, it could be argued that rave organisers saw the writing on the wall and moved towards more organised and &quot;legitimate&quot; venues, enabling a continuation of large-scale indoor raves well into the mid-nineties. One might remember that the earliest house and acid house clubs were themselves effectively &quot;nightclubs&quot;. Public perception of raves was also overshadowed in the press by the 1995 death of [[Leah Betts]], a teenager who died after taking [[MDMA]]; journalists and billboard campaigns focused on drug use, despite Betts cause of death being [[water intoxication]] in her home, not an MDMA overdose at a rave.

Genuine illegal raves have continued throughout the UK to this day and unlicensed parties have been organised in venues including disused quarries, warehouses, and condemned night clubs. The rise of the Internet has both helped and hindered the cause, with much wider and more accessible communication resulting in bigger parties, but consequently increasing the risk of police involvement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.whathappenedlastnight.net/manchester/news/Illegal%20rave%20attracts%20undesirables | title = 2007 – police close down illegal rave }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 2006 [[M.I.A. (artist)|M.I.A.]] song &quot;[[Kala (album)|XR2]]&quot; is an ode to the rave scene of early 1990s London.

There are also types of Rave clothes, such as 'pumps', 'Three button Shirts', [[High-visibility clothing|'Fluorescent Yellow Jackets']], 'White Gloves' and White belts. This is known as 'Rave gear'.

As well as clothing there were a range of accessories carried by many ravers including: [[Vicks VapoRub]], which ravers find pleasant under the influence of MDMA, [[pacifier]]s to satiate the need to grind one's teeth ([[bruxism]]) caused by taking MDMA, and [[glow stick]]s which adjunct the mild [[psychedelia]] of MDMA's effect. This led some clubs and event organizers to search participants on entry and confiscate such items due to it being evidence of drug use inside the venue.{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}}

===Continental Europe===

{{See also|Love Parade|Street Parade|Hardcore techno|Gabber|Electronic body music}}
[[File:Rave nel Salento 2.JPG|thumb|right|300px|Rave party in [[Salento]] (August 2009)]]
By 1987, a German party scene, started by Tauseef Alam, based on the [[House music|Chicago House]] sound was well established. The following year (1988) saw acid house making as significant an impact on popular consciousness in Germany as it had in England.&lt;ref&gt;Short [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HpC0qlWKb_Q excerpt] from special on German &quot;Tele 5&quot; from Dec.8, 1988. The show is called &quot;Tanzhouse&quot; hosted by a young Fred Kogel. It includes footage from Hamburg's &quot;Front&quot; with Boris Dlugosch, Kemal Kurum's &quot;Opera House&quot; and the &quot;Prinzenbar&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1989 German DJs [[Westbam]] and Dr. Motte established the [[Ufo (Club, Berlin)|Ufo Club]], an illegal party venue, and co-founded the [[Love Parade]].&lt;ref name=ROBB&gt;Robb, D. (2002), Techno in Germany: Its Musical Origins and Cultural Relevance, ''German as a Foreign Language Journal'', No.2, 2002, (p. 134).&lt;/ref&gt; On 9 November 1989 the [[Berlin Wall]] fell, free underground Techno parties mushroomed in [[East Berlin]], and a rave scene comparable to that in the UK was established.&lt;ref name=ROBB/&gt; East German DJ [[Paul van Dyk]] has remarked that the Techno based rave scene was a major force in re-establishing social connections between East and West Germany during the unification period.&lt;ref&gt;Messmer, S. (1998), ''Eierkuchensozialismus'', TAZ, 10.7.1998, (p. 26).&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1991 a number of party venues closed, including [[Ufo (Club, Berlin)|Ufo]], and the Berlin Techno scene centred itself around three locations close to the foundations of the Berlin Wall: the ''E-Werk'', ''Der Bunker'' and the now legendary ''[[Tresor]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Henkel, O.; Wolff, K. (1996) Berlin Underground: Techno und Hiphop; Zwischen Mythos und Ausverkauf, Berlin: FAB Verlag, (pp. 81–83).&lt;/ref&gt; In the same period German DJs began intensifying the speed and abrasiveness of the sound, as an acid infused techno began transmuting into [[hardcore techno|hardcore]].&lt;ref&gt;Schuler, M.(1995),''Gabber + Hardcore'', (p. 123), in Anz, P.; Walder, P. (Eds) (1999 rev. edn, 1st publ. 1995, Zurich: Verlag Ricco Bilger)''Techno''. Reinbek: Rowohlt Taschenbuch Verlag.&lt;/ref&gt; This emerging sound was influenced by Dutch [[gabber]] and Belgium hardcore. Other influences on the development of this style were European [[Electronic Body Music]] groups of the mid 1980s such as [[Deutsch-Amerikanische Freundschaft|DAF]], [[Front 242]], and [[Nitzer Ebb]].&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds, S.(1998), ''Energy Flash: a Journey Through Rave Music and Dance Culture'', Pan Macmillan, (p. 110).&lt;/ref&gt;

Across Europe, rave culture was becoming part of a new youth movement. DJs and electronic-music producers such as Westbam proclaimed the existence of a &quot;raving society&quot; and promoted [[electronic music]] as legitimate competition for [[rock and roll]]. Indeed, [[electronic dance music]] and rave subculture became mass movements. Raves had tens of thousands of attendees, youth magazines featured styling tips, and television networks launched music magazines on House and Techno music. The annual Love Parade festivals in Berlin (in the Metropolitan Ruhr area onwards) attracted more than one million party-goers between 1997 and 2000. Meanwhile, the more commercial sound of [[happy hardcore]] topped the music charts across Europe. Nowadays there are only a few popular raving acts on the case in Germany, but many underground acts in Berlin and Frankfurt (Main). That is why Berlin (especially the east side) is still called the capital city of electro music and rave. Although electro composer Paul Kalkbrenner from Friedrichshain, Berlin made &quot;Berlin Techno&quot; world popular again, he is touring on his Berlin Calling (named after the movie he acted the main character and the soundtrack he produced for) tour through Europe and America.
[[File:RaveOn.jpg|thumb|right|In Vienna, Austria in 2005]]

==Regional expansion==

===United States===
The upsurge in popularity of rave culture in the United States at a certain period in time often lends it characteristics common to a 'movement' or [[subculture]]. As the [[Disco]] era came to a close by the early 80's, Rave culture began to see significant growth. Rave culture incorporated Disco culture's same love of dance music, and hedonism. Although disco culture had thrived in the mainstream, the rave culture would make an effort to stay underground to avoid the animosity that was still surrounding disco and dance music.

In the late 1980s, rave culture began to filter through from English ex-pats and DJs who would visit Europe. However, rave culture's major expansion in North America is often credited to [[Frankie Bones]], who after spinning a party in an aircraft hangar in England helped organise some of the earliest known American raves in New York City that maintained a consistent core audience. After this, hundreds of smaller promotional groups sprung up across the east coast, and later the west coast, causing a true &quot;scene&quot; to develop.

Raves were also represented in mainstream culture, even this early in their existence. The film ''[[Party Monster (2003 film)|Party Monster]]'' (2003) shared aspects of the rave scene via anachronism, since it was set during the &quot;Club Kid&quot; era of the late 1980s and early 1990s.


===Hippies of a New Era===

American ravers, following their early UK &amp; European counterparts, have been compared to both the hippies of the 1960s and the new wavers of the 1980s, due to their interest in non-violence and music.
In the 1990's, one of the most influential Rave organisers / promoters in America was San Diego's G.U.N. ,Global Underworld Network known as Nicholas Luckinbill and Branden Powers. They were made famous for organising and throwing the internationally known OPIUM and NARNIA raves that reached in size of 60,000 plus people in attendance, a feat unheard of at that time. Narnia which would become famous for a morning hand holding circle of unity was featured on Mtv and twice in LIFE magazine being honored with Event of the Year in 1995. Narnia quickly became known as the &quot;Woodstock of Generation X&quot;. These festivals were mostly held on Indian Reservations and Ski Resorts during the Summer months and were headlined by well known DJs such as Doc Martin,Dimitri of Dee-lite,Afrika Islam and the Hardkiss brothers from San Francisco. They also featured exceptional local San Diego DJ's Jon Bishop, Steve Pagan,Alien Tom,Jeff Skot and Mark E. Quark. Global Underworld's events were the first prop heavy , themed parties in America. Global Underworld Network were also the first production company to throw Raves within Mexico, thus launching the entire rave culture movement within South America as well. The iconic fairy and pixie craze with ravers getting fairy tattoos and wearing wings to parties all started from an image of a winged fairy on the first Narnia flyer. The Crystal Method played their first out of town show for Global Underworld's Universary event. Fearing reprisals from the police Global Underworld Network advertised the event as &quot;A thousand Points of Light&quot; referring to the power of healing crystals and not the obvious drug reference of the Crystal Methods name. A fact that tickled the upcoming artist so much they would refer to it years later in their biography. The Chemical Brothers were also in awe of Nicholas and Branden's Global Underworld headquarters in downtown San Diego. A multi story building of the arts, much like Warhol's factory. There Global Underworld fed starving artists and provided space for all the arts. The Chemical Brothers played an intimate show at Global's offices in front of a few hundred lucky fans on the eve of a Global event that was shut down by the authorities. In an interview with Virgin Airways The Chemical Brothers referred to Global Underworld as a cult with cult like followers, a fact that wasnt to far from the truth. Nicholas Luckinbill step grandson of the late Lucille Ball and Branden Powers were the Tim Leary and Ken Keaseys of the Rave Generation, and were instrumental in creating their political movement called RTD or RIGHT TO DANCE. RTD was a non violent protest held in San Diego and later in Los Angeles on the steps of the Cities administrators proving that Rave was about community , peace, love and not a dirty word. These protest by Global Underworld helped lay the foundation for future growth within the rave scene. Almost 25 years to the date of their first party &quot;The Birth of Baby X&quot; Global Underworld has risen like a Phoenix from the ashes , reborn anew and is bringing back their world famous festival NARNIA in the Summer of 2013.

===Canada===
{{Unreferenced section|date=July 2008}}
Rave culture in Canada reached its peak in the 1990s and early 2000s. Scenes were established within the major Canadian cities, but most notably Montreal, Toronto, Vancouver and Edmonton. While the Toronto rave scene subsided about 2003, Montreal has thrived. Toronto during the late 1990s was home to the largest raves in Canada with attendance of 20,000. The shrinking of the Toronto rave scene was due to the actions of various Ontario based politicians and media. The Ontario Rave Act&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Pupatello|first=Sandra|title=Bill 73, Ontario Rave Act|accessdate=4 April 2011|date=3 May 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;  and City TV were especially influential on the scene. By creating a scare to the venue owners, it was difficult if not impossible for promoters to establish locations to house the events, and insurance companies would create a trade barrier by preventing the execution of a certificate thus preventing the event from occurring. Requirements were also created for an arbitrary amount of paid duty police constables to be on-site at events, thus greatly raising the expenses to the promoter. Montreal regularly holds large scale events with the biggest international headliners. [[Bal en Blanc]] being one of the best known single night parties in Canada. Toronto is now more known for its shift to the Club/Drum 'n' Bass scene. The [[Hullabaloo (rave)|Hullabaloo]] production company held its final party on 9 July 2005. Outdoor raves are still a mainstay of the Vancouver scene. Edmonton continues to hold a following and is currently experiencing a small resurgence.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Canadian Rave community forum&quot; http://www.skyscrapercity.com/showthread.php?t=528354&lt;/ref&gt;

Canadian ravers listen and dance to a variety of electronic music such as [[hardstyle]], [[Trance music|trance]], [[drum and bass]], [[techno]], [[Hardcore techno|hardcore]], [[happy hardcore]], [[Psychedelic trance|psytrance]], [[Goa trance|Goa]], [[house music|house]] and [[dubstep]]. A number of Canadian DJs and producers have emerged from the Canadian rave scene to reach international acclaim, including [[Deadmau5]], ill.Gates, [[Richie Hawtin]], [[Excision (musician)|Excision]], [[Datsik]], [[Downlink]], [[Max Graham]], [[Jay Tripwire]], Mathew Jonson, Robert DeLaGauthier, [[Fred Everything]] and [[Tiga (musician)|Tiga]], among others. There is a well established and ever changing rave scene on [[Vancouver Island]] spawning many [[DJ's]], [[Record producer|Producers]] and Performers.
Commercial Raves in Canada are concentrated in [[Montreal]], [[Toronto]], [[Edmonton]], [[Halifax Regional Municipality|Halifax]], [[Saskatoon]], [[Calgary]], [[Ottawa]], [[Vancouver]] and [[Winnipeg]], with the exception of house raves which can be found in smaller cities.

===Australia===
{{Unreferenced section|date=July 2008}}
Raves flourished in Australia in the 1980s where they were generally called Dance Parties due to the parties being promoted by the gay and straight/gay scenes, until the 1990s when they began being referred to as &quot;raves&quot; with more US style promoters taking it on.

In Sydney from 1983 [[Rat Parties]] saw the opening up of Sydney's underground gay dance party scene to a broader community where it found an enormous appetite. By 1990 the standard setting [[Sydney Gay and Lesbian Mardi Gras]] party, its winter off-shoot Sleazeball and the regular Rat Parties which ran until 1992, were attracting huge crowds of gays and straights alike, while young entrepreneurs behind events like FUN, Sweatbox and Bacchanalia were booking inner city warehouses and tired old venues and transforming them into vibrant, packed party palaces. The DJ [[Peewee Ferris]] played at the first Sweatbox parties (Let them eat cake and Sign of the times) and RAT Parties from 1987. The biggest RAT Party was in 1999 with Grace Jones with 20,000 people at the Hordern Pavilion.

After the Hordern Pav lost its 24 hour license in 1990 (or thereabouts) the scene went quiet for a bit with attempts at doing similar parties in the newly constructed Darling Harbour Convention centre. These were fairly uncomparable in terms of vibe. UK magazine ID came through on its 'ID world tour' and put on an OK party there but it took a few months before real underground parties emerged in Sydney. Flim Flam, Love and other promotion entities took over inner city venues and some less than legit impromptu spaces that had incredible vibe and aesthetics. The term Rave started to be used in Sydney due to this distinct connection to the scene in the UK.

In Melbourne, the underground dance style called the &quot;[[Melbourne Shuffle]]&quot; originated at these parties. Some early parties such as [[Every Picture Tells A Story Melbourne|Every Picture Tells A Story]] were broadcast live on free-to-air television from the party's own TV station.{{Citation needed|date=November 2007}} The Melbourne raves tended to have a greater amount of artwork, video art, decor and performance as the underground arts community of Melbourne was heavily involved in producing the parties.{{Citation needed|date=November 2007}} Fashion was also a very important component, as many party goers were in the fashion industry which is very large in Melbourne,{{Citation needed|date=July 2009}} and they designed and made their own 'party' clothes and accessories. The parties became a fashion show for the designers and created strong retail sales for their works.{{Citation needed|date=November 2007}} Often outstanding dancers were sponsored to wear designers' ranges at parties.

[[File:Allphones Arena.jpg|thumb|left|300px|Raves in Sydney were sometimes held at the [[Sydney Super Dome]].]]
The Melbourne underground rave community was very large with its own street press, radio stations, TV shows, clothing shops, bars, cafes, theatres, performance venues, record labels, clothing labels, and free street raves associated with the Brunswick Street festival (pictured) which regularly drew large crowds.

The first novel dedicated to the Australian rave and dance scene was set in Melbourne. Written by Tom Griffin and titled, [[Playgrounds: a portrait of rave culture]], it was launched at a rave at Kryal Castle in 2005.

Driven by a need to be away from residential areas due to noise pollution complaints of residents, as well as in many cases a desire to evade the attention of the authorities, the Australian rave scene held their events in industrial areas.

In [[Perth, Western Australia|Perth]], Western Australia, parties were either held in warehouses in the outer eastern and southern suburbs, or on fields in semi-rural areas easily reachable from the city, such as [[Wanneroo, Western Australia|Wanneroo]] and [[Serpentine, Western Australia|Serpentine]]. Large events included the Deja Vu rave in 1992, RUSH and Emotion in 1993, and Space Garden in 1994, as well as the infamous Sunrise held on New Year's Eve every year since its conception until New Year's Eve 2010. 2009 was an extremely successful year for the scene, seeing multiple events a month and very little grief from the authorities. This was until an event held in a cinema theatre in which the seats provided excessive amounts of cover to buy and sell drugs, the organiser prematurely ended the event 4 hours short of the ticketed time. 
The Perth rave scene was subject to a bit of turmoil in 2010, after an over-promoted and over-sold rave failed to re-ignite the scene after an abnormally long lack of events. After the closing down of the long-running Rise nightclub in early 2011 the scene was left with no dedicated dance clubs in central Perth, although hardly rave, events continue to occur on a weekly basis at venues such as Ambar, The Velvet Lounge, and The Rosemount, as well as monthly dark raves at Gilkisons, and occasional large parties at Metro City. A large amount of rave fans have simply moved to the drum'n'bass and dubstep scene, with artists such as ShockOne,&lt;ref&gt;ShockOne http://www.discogs.com/artist/Shock+One+(2)&lt;/ref&gt; Kito &lt;ref&gt;Kito http://www.discogs.com/artist/Kito+%285%29&lt;/ref&gt; and Greg Packer &lt;ref&gt;Greg Packer http://www.discogs.com/artist/Greg+Packer&lt;/ref&gt; successfully releasing tunes and mix CDs. The Origin festival &lt;ref&gt;Origin festival http://www.theorigin.com.au/&lt;/ref&gt; each New Year continues to provide a line-up that reflects these musical tendencies, but not the true essence of the scene, however as to be expected as it is a music festival. Smaller underground events continue to occur, spread mostly by word-of-mouth and social media. Western Australia is the only state to host its own annual dance music industry awards, the [[Perth Dance Music Awards|PDMAs]].

For the Sydney rave scene the industrial areas of the Western suburbs were quite common in the late 1990s and early 2000s. Following the [[2000 Sydney Olympics]] the [[Sydney Olympic Park]] at Homebush proved a popular venue as it had ample large warehouse space available and the advantage of no close by residential areas. The &quot;[[Acer Arena|Superdome]]&quot; at Olympic Park has hosted a number of events due to the large capacity. Events at these venues often have ample room for amusement rides, open air &quot;chill out&quot; areas and food stalls. Several amusement parks have hosted dance party events ([[Wonderland Sydney]] and [[Luna Park Sydney]]).
Public attention was brought upon rave culture in Australia following the death of Sydney teenager [[Anna Wood (schoolgirl)|Anna Wood]] who died after consuming an [[MDMA]] tablet at a rave on 25 October 1995. Similar to the death of [[Leah Betts]], Woods had died from [[water intoxication]] secondary to the use of the drug, not the drug itself, because the drug had altered the way she consumed water, rendering her body unable to release it. The incident saw the closure of the club in which she purchased the drug and attended after consuming it and prompted moral panic and further drug awareness in Australia.

In Victoria, the Docklands area of Melbourne hosted numerous raves in the 1990s. Bushland areas out side of Melbourne provided [[Doof]] venues, notably Mt Disappointment for [[Earthcore]] and [[Kryal Castle]] just outside of Ballarat.

The Newcastle Rave scene made use of unused warehouses in the Newcastle CBD and at licensed entertainment venues throughout the late 1990s and early 2000s. Events such as &quot;Vital beats&quot; and under-age dance parties were held in these venues.

===South Africa===
The first mega-rave in South Africa was held in a warehouse on Cape Town's foreshore. Dubbed the [[World Peace Party]], it featured a cross-over crowd of Cape Flats rappers, fashionistas and Clubbers dancing to [[rave music]] and [[progressive house]]. The first electronic South African Bands who performed live at the Raves were the Kraftreaktor and The Kiwi Experience. The first large Johannesburg rave was held at an old cinema in Yeoville in early 1992. Amongst the first Johannesburg rave organisers in the early 1990s were Fourth World Productions (run by Preston van Wyk who was also responsible for the legendary 1993 nightclub 4th World) World's End Productions and Damn New Thing Productions.

Other production companies achieved notoriety during the 1990s and included ICE (Incubated Cyber Energy) and Mother Productions, with tours by Boy George, Northern Exposure and Carl Cox adding to the growing international recognition of South Africa as a premier RAVE destination. The most famous club at the time (and still going) is ESP in Doornfontein, renowned for its Sunday parties where the roof was thrown open and ravers danced the day away.

===Kenya===
Raves in Kenya begun in the late 1990s, and were attended only by over-21 youths. As time went by electronic music begun to spread throughout the country. By 2005, they had their own International Dance Festivals and these were attended by many teens and adults.

Electronic music only clubs have begun to spread through Nairobi.

==Culture==

===Dancing===
Raving in itself is a syllabus free dance, whereby the movements are [[freestyle dance|not predefined and the dance is performed randomly]], harmonised with beats from music. Rave dance refers to the [[street dance]] styles that evolved alongside rave culture. Such dances are street dances since they evolved alongside the underground rave movements, thus without the intervention of [[dance studios]]. Sometimes club-oriented dances would be danced to rave music, too, for example, [[tecktonik]] is sometimes danced to fast-paced [[electro house]].{{citation needed|date=October 2011}}

Such dances are usually freestyle in nature, since they are very rarely choreographed in preparation for such events (although some ravers may create personal dance routines). Dances like [[Jumpstyle]], [[Tecktonik]], [[Liquid and digits]], [[Melbourne Shuffle|Shuffling]] and [[Industrial dance]] may be sometimes highly dependent on pre-planned choreography for performances at raves, therefore such dance styles may be practised professionally. Nonetheless, rave dance styles can be completely freeform due to their simple footwork and arm movements.{{citation needed|date=October 2011}}
[[File:Rave xxxperience bh.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Rave in [[Brazil]] ]]

===Light shows===
Some ravers participate in one of four light-oriented dances, called ''glowsticking'', ''glowstringing'', ''gloving'', and ''lightshows''.
Other types of light-related dancing include [[LED]] lights, flash-lights and blinking strobe lights. LEDs come in various colours with different settings. The &quot;low intensity&quot; setting causes a strobe effect, leaving trails of dots, while &quot;high intensity&quot; leaves a solid line. There are many techniques used to make the lights &quot;flow&quot; with the music in order to create a visually pleasing and mesmerising combination of patterns. There are also a nearly infinite variety of other moves with varying levels of difficulty applied in their execution. These such moves are called a &quot;figure eight&quot; along with &quot;finger rolls&quot;. 

Regardless, [[glow stick]]s and LEDs can be used at raves for interesting dance effects, because most raves (except some open air raves, e.g. [[technoparade]]s) are held in dark or nearly dark rooms. Because rave parties are popular with people who wish to show off their dancing, glowsticks can be an ancillary material for creative freestyle dance. LEDs and glowsticks now not only show up at most every rave event, but also are becoming more prominent at many [[electronic dance music]] clubs.

===Rave names and marriages===
Rave names are pseudonyms that people use when interacting with other members of the rave community.  They are usually names bestowed upon you by a fellow raver.  It is considered a social faux pas to &quot;name&quot; someone else unless you have been raving for longer than a year.  These names are given much the same way that a Native American 'deed name' is given and usually have deep symbolic meaning for people. {{Citation needed|date=June 2012}}

Ceremonies are sometimes done to 'rave marry' two people together.  This shows a union of two people who are very good friends and promise to be there for each other when they need it most.  It is one way in which the rave community shows the unity aspect of the acronym [[PLUR]] (Peace Love Unity Respect). {{Citation needed|date=June 2012}}

===Rave magazines===
{{Unreferenced section|date=July 2008}}

During the 1990s American rave scene, publications played a huge part in advertising and promoting parties, and also featured interviews with artists unknown in commercial publications. These publications, which ranged from single-sheet photocopied [[zines]] to expensive glossy magazines, usually started as free enterprises, surviving only on an advertising revenue-based model. Later on, some magazines, such as ''[[URB (magazine)|URB]]'' and ''[[XLR8R]]'', were able to legitimize and become proper publications that can now be found at local bookstores. Others, like ''[[Massive Magazine]]'', ended with a fire, which consumed their offices in the winter of 2004, destroying all the films and back issues. This resulted in placing back-issues of ''Massive Magazine'' in great demand, fetching prices of up to 100 dollars for early issues on [[eBay]].{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}

Many of the rave magazines had dedicated audiences that centered around the journal's respective city of publication. The Midwest was known for the Milwaukee-based ''[[Massive Magazine]]'' and Chicago-based ''Reactor'' and ''A Thousand Words'' photo magazine. On the East Coast there was New York City DJ Heather Heart's ''Under One Sky'' (founded in 1990 or 1991), and a few years later the debut of ''[[Vice (magazine)|Vice]]''. Later, in 1996 and 1997, NYC had ''DROP Magazine'', which was a continuation of ''PROJECT X Magazine.'' On the West Coast there was the Los Angeles-based ''[[URB (magazine)|URB]]'', San Diego's ''Hypno'', ''[[BPM (magazine)|BPM]]'', and ''Sin'' magazines; and San Francisco-based ''Lotus'' and ''[[XLR8R]]''.

In Europe, there was Germany's ''Frontpage'' and ''[[De Bug (magazine)|De:Bug]]'', and the United Kingdom's ''[[Mixmag]]'', ''Atmosphere'', and ''[[Knowledge Magazine|Knowledge]]'' magazines, the latter two dedicated to the UK's [[breakbeat]] and [[drum and bass]] markets.

==Drug use==
In the U.S., the mainstream media and law enforcement agencies have branded the subculture as a purely [[Recreational drug use|drug-centric]] culture, usually drugs such as [[Cannabis (drug)|marijuana]], [[MDMA]], [[Lysergic acid diethylamide|LSD]], [[amphetamine]] and [[ketamine]],  similar to the [[hippie]] movement of the 1960s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.mapinc.org/drugnews/v01/n817/a11.html?
| title = Media Awareness Project
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Groups that have addressed drug use at raves include the [http://www.emdef.org/ Electronic Music Defense and Education Fund] (EMDEF), [http://www.tripproject.ca/ The Toronto Raver Info Project], and [[DanceSafe]], all of which advocate [[harm reduction]] approaches. Paradoxically, drug safety literature (such as those distributed by DanceSafe) is used as evidence of condoned drug use. Other groups, such as Drug Free America Foundation, Inc., characterize raves as being rife with gang activity, rape, robbery, and drug-related deaths.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.dfaf.org/familyguide/raves.php
| title = Raves and Paraphernalia
| quote = In today’s culture it is not uncommon for gang violence to take place at these events – a kind of &quot;turf war&quot;.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005, Antonio Maria Costa, Executive Director of the [[United Nations Office on Drugs and Crime]], advocated drug testing on highways as a countermeasure against drug use at raves.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.unis.unvienna.org/unis/pressrels/2005/unisnar891.html
| title = UN Drug Officials Discuss Issues and Challenges at 48th Session of Commission on Narcotic Drugs
| publisher=United Nations Information Service
| quote = He also offered support for drug testing on highways and in sensitive industries, and called for action on the dangers of Raves, international drug festivals fuelled by ecstasy and other synthetic drugs.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In recent times, as opposed to the past decades, rave venues have taken to hiring local law enforcement to reduce drug use.

===MDMA===
[[MDMA]], commonly known as &quot;ecstasy&quot;, is a psychoactive drug of the [[phenethylamine]] and [[amphetamine]] [[Chemical classification|classes of drugs]]. It produces [[stimulant]], mild [[Psychedelic drug|psychedelic]], and [[empathogen-entactogen|entactogen]]ic effects. Its common effects include: [[euphoria]], mild [[psychedelia]], physical and mental stimulation, feelings of emotional warmth and empathy, openness, reduced hostility, and negative short-term physical symptoms common with stimulants ([[bruxism]], rapid heart rate, [[nystagmus]] etc.).

Since the beginning of rave [[culture]], MDMA use has been linked to it and the culture was branded by the media as a drug-centric culture. MDMA has been a major excuse for the US government to pass bills against raves, for instance the [[Reducing Americans' Vulnerability to Ecstasy Act]] (commonly known as the RAVE Act). To the present day, raves are often portrayed as drug filled parties by the media mainly due to MDMA.{{or|date=July 2012}}

The likely reason that MDMA is associated with raves more than other drugs is because of the role it had in building the rave culture.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} Colorful clothing, [[glow stick]]s, [[menthol]] inhalers, [[pacifier]]s, and other rave accessories are either meant to enhance the MDMA high or are the indirect result of its use, often relating either to its mild psychedelic effect (i.e. stimulating colors to complement the psychedelic sensory enhancement) or to ameliorating its negative side effects (i.e. pacifiers to prevent [[bruxism|teeth grinding]] and bottled water to prevent [[dehydration]]).

==Video==
Sunrise was one of the biggest raves to hit Europe during what some people called the [[Second Summer of Love]]. An estimated 20,000 people attended the event.

==See also==
* [[Acid house party]] – Forerunner of raves typically staged in UK warehouses around 1987–89.
* [[Circuit party]]
* [[Doof]]
* [[Free party]] – The modern, illegal version of raves.
* [[Melbourne Shuffle]] – A rave dance style culture that has evolved in Melbourne, Australia over the past 15 years.
* [[Merry Pranksters]] – Their early escapades were best chronicled by Tom Wolfe in The Electric Kool-Aid Acid Test.
* [[New Rave]] – A new genre of music mixing elements of rave culture, disco and rock.
* [[Rat Parties]] – When Sydney's gay dance party scene opened up to the broader community in the 1980s.
* [[RAVE Act]] – An American law targeting raves.
* [[Rave Board Game]] – 1991 board game based on the UK Rave scene
* [[Rave music]] – Music and music styles at raves
* [[Technoshamanism]] – A technique employed by some ravers, often utilising [[electronic music]] and [[psychoactive]] drugs.
* [[Tecktonik]], a dance style based on rave music, developed in Paris, France and well known throughout Europe.
* [[Zippies]]

==Notes and references==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* [[Janelly Del Pinal|Del Pinal, Janelly]]. ''Altered State: The Story of Ecstasy and Acid House''. London: 1997 : Serpent's Tail – How rave dances began in [[Manchester, England|Manchester]], England in the Summer of 1988 (the [[Second Summer of Love]]) and the aftermath. ISBN 1-85242-604-7
* [[Simon Reynolds|Reynolds, Simon]]. ''Generation Ecstasy: Into the world of Techno and Rave culture''. New York: Little, Brown and Company, 1998. ISBN 0-316-74111-6
* Ott, Brian L. and Herman, Bill D. [http://www.questia.com/googleScholar.qst?docId=5002554420 Excerpt from Mixed Messages: Resistance and Reappropriation in Rave Culture]. 2003.
* Evans, Helen. [http://hehe.org.free.fr/hehe/texte/rave/ Out of Sight, Out of Mind: An Analysis of Rave culture]. Wimbledon School of Art, London. 1992. Includes bibliography through 1994.
* St John, Graham (ed). 2004. [http://www.edgecentral.net/rcr.htm Rave Culture and Religion]. New York: Routledge. ISBN 0-415-31449-6
&lt;/div&gt;
* St John, Graham. 2009. [http://www.edgecentral.net/technomad.htm Technomad: Global Raving Countercultures]. London: Equinox. ISBN 978-1-84553-626-8.
* Griffin, Tom. ''[[Playgrounds: a portrait of rave culture]]''. 2005. ISBN 0-646-45135-9. Official Website [http://www.whatisplaygrounds.com] WALLAWALLA
* Kotarba, Joseph. 1993. [http://www.dshs.state.tx.us/sa/research/populations/houstonrave.pdf The Rave Scene in Houston, Texas: An Ethnographic Analysis]. Austin: Texas Commission on Alcohol and Drug Abuse.

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|rave}}
&lt;!--
     Please do not add links to regional community sites;
     see talk page and open directory links
--&gt;
* [http://hardcorewillneverdie.com/Flash/historyHWND.html Rave Timeline 1987-1993]
* [http://dj.dancecult.net/ Dancecult: Journal of Electronic Dance Music Culture]
* [http://volterock.blogspot.com/p/em-culture.html Volterock Archive: Rave culture, communities, dance, art, and history]
* [http://www.gridface.com/ Gridface: Reviews from 1996 to present]
* [http://www.raveguide.co.uk Raveguide Eflyers Listings and more]
* [http://www.underave.net Underave. Underground music, party pics, videos, art images and much more]
* [http://ravearchive.com Zines, flyers and mixtapes from 1990–1999]
* [http://www.simfonik.com mixed tapes and rave culture in early 1990s Los Angeles]
* [http://ravehistory.co.uk Rave Footage from 1988 – 1994]
* [http://www.ultimatebuzz.net – History of the Northeast of England Rave Scene 1990+]
* [http://hyperreal.org/~mike/pub/altraveFAQ.html Rave FAQ] from 1995.
* {{dmoz|Society/Subcultures/Rave/Regional/|Regional community links}}
* [http://www.xlr8r.com XLR8R Magazine]
* [http://www.thecommunic8r.com Chronicles the Toronto rave scene through flyers and music]
* [http://www.beginnerdj.com/the-10-best-rave-movies-of-all-time Movies About Raves]
* [http://www.loftsites.co.uk/old_school_rave/diaries/index.html Rave Diaries from 1992]

{{Drug use}}

[[Category:Parties]]
[[Category:Electronic music]]
[[Category:Dance culture]]
[[Category:Electronic music festivals]]
[[Category:Musical subcultures]]

[[ca:Rave (música)]]
[[cs:Rave]]
[[da:Rave]]
[[de:Rave]]
[[es:Rave]]
[[fr:Rave party]]
[[bpy:রাৱের]]
[[id:Rave]]
[[it:Rave party]]
[[he:רייב]]
[[nl:Rave (feest)]]
[[ja:レイブ (音楽)]]
[[no:Rave]]
[[pl:Rave]]
[[pt:Rave]]
[[ro:Rave]]
[[ru:Рейв]]
[[sl:Rave]]
[[sr:Рејв]]
[[fi:Rave]]
[[sv:Rave]]
[[th:เรฟ]]
[[tr:Rave]]
[[uk:Рейв]]
[[zh:銳舞]]</text>
      <sha1>h3qs6tbo6c4zcng6guv9c4ofdp4o8pk</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
