<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk radio</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>30077</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520844124</id>
      <parentid>517062910</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-01T03:05:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MOAI12</username>
        <id>12974859</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Wikilink Barry Jones</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="36905">{{Other uses|Talk Radio (disambiguation)}}
{{refimprove|date=September 2010}}

'''Talk radio''' is a [[radio format]] containing discussion about topical issues. Most shows are regularly hosted by a single individual, and often feature interviews with a number of different guests. Talk radio typically includes an element of listener participation, usually by broadcasting live conversations between the host and listeners who &quot;call in&quot; (usually via telephone) to the show. Listener contributions are usually [[Call screening|screened]] by a show's producer(s) in order to maximize audience interest and, in the case of commercial talk radio, attract advertisers. Generally, the shows are organized into segments, each separated by a pause for [[advertisement]]s; however, in public or non-commercial radio, music is sometimes played in place of commercials to separate the program segments. Variations of talk radio include [[conservative talk]], [[hot talk]], [[liberal talk]] and [[sports talk]].

While talk radio has historically been associated with AM/FM, starting around 2005 the technology for Internet-based talk-radio shows became cost effective in the form of [[podcasts]]. Now, it is possible for an individual to use a variety of services to host an Internet-based talk-radio show without carriage by a traditional radio station. In addition TV programming from talk and news outlets such as [[BBC]], [[CNN]], [[Bloomberg L.P.|Bloomberg]] and [[Fox]] are now often available expanding the world of talk radio further. Talk radio listening is now enjoyed not only on radios, but a wide variety of other devices and services including PCs using [[iTunes]], station directories such as [[Tunein]], show directory smartphones with apps such as [[Stitcher]].

==Talk radio in the United States==
Talk radio is not limited to the [[AM band]]. &quot;Non-commercial&quot; usually referred to as &quot;[[public radio]]&quot;, which is located in a reserved spectrum of the [[FM band]], also broadcasts talk programs. Commercial all-talk stations can also be found on the FM band in many cities across the US. These shows often rely less on political discussion and analysis than their AM counterparts, and often employ the use of pranks and &quot;bits&quot; for entertainment purposes. In the [[United States]] and [[Canada]], [[satellite radio]] services offer uncensored &quot;free-wheeling&quot; original programming, such as ''[[The Howard Stern Show]]'' and ''[[The Opie &amp; Anthony Show]]'', formerly featured on terrestrial, government-censored radio. [[ABC News &amp; Talk]] is an example of &quot;rebagging&quot; for the digital airwaves shows featured on their terrestrial radio stations.

===History===
Expressing and debating political opinions has been a staple of radio since the medium's infancy. [[Aimee Semple McPherson]] began her radio broadcasts in the early 1920s and even purchased her own station, [[KFSG]] which went on the air in February 1924; by the mid-1930s, controversial radio priest Father [[Charles Coughlin]]'s radio broadcasts were reaching millions per week. There was also a national current events forum called [[America's Town Meeting of the Air]] which broadcast once a week starting in 1935. It featured panel discussions from some of the biggest newsmakers and was among the first shows to allow audience participation: members of the studio audience could question the guests or even heckle them.

Talk radio as a listener-participation format has existed since at least the mid-1940s. Working for [[New York]]'s [[WMCA]] in 1945, [[Barry Gray (radio)|Barry Gray]] was bored with playing music and put a telephone receiver up to his microphone to talk with bandleader [[Woody Herman]]. Soon followed by listener call-ins, this is often credited as the first instance of talk radio, and Gray is often billed as &quot;The hot mama of Talk Radio.&quot;

Author Bill Cherry proposed George Roy Clough as the first to invite listeners to argue politics on a call-in radio show at KLUF, his station in Galveston, Texas, as a way to bring his own political views into listeners' homes. (He later became [[Free State of Galveston|mayor of Galveston]].) Cherry gives no specific date, but the context of events and history of the station would seem to place it also in the 1940s, perhaps earlier. The format was the classic mode in which the announcer gave the topic for that day, and listeners called in to debate the issue.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Bill|last=Cherry|url=http://www.texasescapes.com/BillCherry/George-Roy-Clough-Invents-Call-in-Radio.htm|title=George Roy Clough Invents Call-in Radio|publisher=TexasEscapes.com|date=|accessdate=2008-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1948 Alan Courtney — New York disk jockey and co-composer of the popular song, &quot;Joltin' Joe Dimaggio&quot; — began a call-in program for the Storer station in Miami, Florida (WGBS) and then on Miami's WQAM, WINZ and WCKR the &quot;Alan Courtney Open Phone Forum&quot; flourished as an avowedly conservative and anti-communist political forum with a coverage area over the Southeastern U.S. and Cuba.

[[Joe Pyne]], [[John Nebel]], [[Jean Shepherd]], and [[Jerry Williams (radio)|Jerry Williams]] ([[WUFC (AM)|WMEX]]-Boston) were among the first to explore the medium in the 1950s.

Two [[radio station]]s — [[KMOX]], 1120 [[AM radio|AM]] in [[St. Louis, Missouri]], and [[KABC radio|KABC]], 790 [[AM radio|AM]] in [[Los Angeles]] — adopted an all-[[talk show]] format in 1960, and both claim to be the first to have done so. KABC station manager Ben Hoberman and KMOX station manager [[Robert Hyland]] independently developed the all-talk format. [[KTKK]], 630 in Salt Lake City, then known as KSXX, adopted a full-time talk schedule in 1965 and has claimed to have been the third station in the country to have done so. KSXX started with all local talent, and KTKK today has a larger portion of its schedule featuring local talent than most other stations that run a full schedule of talk.

In the 1970s and early 1980s, as many listeners abandoned AM music formats for the [[high fidelity]] sound of the [[FM radio]] dial, the Talk Radio format began to catch on in more large cities. Former music stations such as [[KLIF (AM)|KLIF]], [[Dallas]], [[Texas]]), [[WLW]] ([[Cincinnati, Ohio]]), [[WHAS (AM)|WHAS]] ([[Louisville, Kentucky]]), [[WHAM (AM)|WHAM]] ([[Rochester, New York]]), [[WLS (AM)|WLS]] ([[Chicago|Chicago, Illinois]]), [[KFI (AM)|KFI]] ([[Los Angeles]], [[California]]), [[WRKO]] ([[Boston]], [[Massachusetts]]), [[WWKB|WKBW]] ([[Buffalo, New York]]), and [[WABC (AM)|WABC]] ([[New York, New York]]) made the switch to all-talk as their ratings slumped due to listener migration to the FM band.

===Politically oriented talk radio===
{{Main|Conservative talk radio}}
The [[United States]] saw dramatic growth in the popularity of talk radio during the 1990s due to the repeal of the [[Federal Communications Commission]]'s post-war  [[Fairness Doctrine]] of 1949, in 1987. The mandate of the [[Fairness Doctrine]] was to require that audiences were exposed to a diversity of viewpoints.
It had required the holders of broadcast licenses  to &quot;present controversial issues of public importance&quot; and to do so in a manner that was, in the Commission's view, &quot;honest, equitable and balanced&quot;. Its repeal  provided an opportunity for a kind of partisan political programming with commercial appeal that had not previously existed. 

Pew researchers found in 2004 that 17% of the public regularly listens to talk radio. This audience is mostly male, middle-aged and conservative. Among those who regularly listen to talk radio, 41% are Republican and 28% are Democrats. Furthermore, 45% describe themselves as conservatives, compared with 18% who say they are liberals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://people-press.org/reports/display.php3?PageID=834|title=News Audiences Increasingly Politicized|publisher=People-press.org|date=June 8, 2004|accessdate=2008-11-24}}{{dead link|date=July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The most successful pioneer in the 1990s' talk radio movement in the US was the [[American conservatism|politically conservative]] commentator [[Rush Limbaugh]]. Limbaugh's success demonstrated that there was a nationwide market for passionately delivered conservative commentary on contemporary news, events, and social trends, and changed the face of how the talk radio business was conducted. 

Limbaugh's unprecedented success is illustrated by [[Fresno, California]]'s then number-one radio station, [http://www.kmj580.com/ KMJ] &quot;news-talk radio,&quot; a typical example of how the talk radio format was changed nation wide. Before Limbaugh, their day time talk show hosts were local and not particularly partisan, each quite a bit different from the other, and had diverse conversations on a wide variety of topics from both local and national politics, to food, to interviews with interesting people, book authors, and so forth.  There was a local morning host plus a local afternoon host. The evenings (with less advertising revenue) typically included nationally syndicated hosts such as family finance pundit [[Bruce Williams]].  KMJ, seeking to cut corners, brought in Limbaugh at 09:00 from New York and within three months had become wildly popular among Fresno's conservatives. The station presented news from 6 to 9, Limbaugh from 9 to noon, then news, then the local Ray Appleton, a moderate Democrat from 1 to 4.  Stations across the nation soon discovered that less diverse programming sold even better, and Appleton became a Republican and KMJ along with most talk radio across the nation became all-conservative.  As of 2011, KMJ has filled the afternoon slot with various other nationally syndicated conservative political shows, and Appleton does his conservative show during the lunch hour.

Other radio talk show hosts (who describe themselves as either conservative or [[Libertarianism|libertarian]]) have also had success as nationally [[broadcast syndication|syndicated]] hosts, including [[Hugh Hewitt]], [[Sean Hannity]], [[Jon Arthur (radio host)|Jon Arthur]], [[Glenn Beck]], [[Michael Medved]], [[Laura Ingraham]], [[Neal Boortz]], [[Michael Savage (commentator)|Michael Savage]], [[Bill O'Reilly (commentator)|Bill O'Reilly]], and [[Mark Levin]].

The [[Salem Radio Network]] syndicates a group of religiously oriented Republican activists, including [[evangelicalism|evangelical]] Christian [[Hugh Hewitt]] and Jewish conservatives [[Dennis Prager]] and [[Michael Medved]]; these are mostly distributed in a 24-hour network format among Salem's own stations, and they generally earn ratings much less than their syndicated counterparts.

In the summer of 2007, conservative talk show hosts mobilized public opposition to the [[Comprehensive Immigration Reform Act of 2007|McCain-Kennedy immigration reform bill]], which eventually failed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Duncan|last=Currie|url=http://www.weeklystandard.com/Content/Public/Articles/000/000/014/628wcxju.asp|title=Beyond the Border|publisher=Weeklystandard.com|date=2008-01-22|accessdate=2008-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Conservative hosts Limbaugh, Ingraham, Bennett, Prager, Hannity, Beck, Levin and Hewitt coalesced around endorsing former Massachusetts governor [[Mitt Romney]] for [[president]] at the end of January 2008 (after [[Fred Thompson]], the described favorite of some of the hosts, dropped out), in an effort to oppose the nomination of Sen. [[John McCain]];&lt;ref&gt;[http://dotan.wordpress.com/2008/02/02/limbaugh-ingraham-bennett-prager-beck-hannity-levin-and-hewitt-plan-concerted-attack-on-sen-mccain-over-the-airwaves-to-promote-romneys-candidacy/ Limbaugh, Ingraham, Bennett, Prager, Beck, Hannity, Levin, and Hewitt plan concerted attack on Sen. McCain over the airwaves to promote Romney’s candidacy « who is willard milton romney?&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; however, Romney suspended his campaign in February of the same year, and endorsed McCain. During the primaries, Limbaugh in particular had endorsed a plan to do whatever it took to prolong the Democrats' nomination by encouraging political conservatives to cross over to the [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democrats]] and voting for the trailing candidate, a plan he calls &quot;[[The Rush Limbaugh Show#Operation Chaos|Operation Chaos]]&quot;. Conservative talk show hosts also lent their unified support for Congressional candidate [[Doug Hoffman]], a conservative third-party candidate who was running in [[New York's 23rd congressional district special election, 2009]] against a liberal Republican ([[Dierdre Scozzafava]]) and a mainstream Democrat ([[Bill Owens (congressman)|Bill Owens]]). The unified support from the conservative base helped propel Hoffman to frontrunner status and effectively killed Scozzafava's campaign, forcing her to drop out of the race several days before the election. This effort backfired on the conservative hosts, as the Democratic candidate Owens won in part thanks to Scozzafava's endorsement of Owens. Local hosts, such as Los Angeles's [[John and Ken]], have also proven effective in influencing the political landscape.

[[Libertarianism|Libertarian]]s such as [[Dennis Miller]] (based in [[Los Angeles]]), Jon Arthur, Host Of Jon Arthur Live! (based in Florida), Patti Brooks [[KGMI]] (based in the Pacific Northwest), [[Free Talk Live]] (based in [[New Hampshire]]), [[Penn Jillette]] (based in [[Las Vegas Valley|Las Vegas]]), [[Jay Severin]] (based in [[Boston]], [[Massachusetts]]), and [[Mark Davis (talk show host)|Mark Davis]] (based in [[Ft. Worth]] and [[Dallas]], [[Texas]]) have also achieved some success. Many of these hosts also publish books, write newspaper columns, appear on television, and give public lectures (Limbaugh, again, was a pioneer of this model of multi-media [[Pundit (politics)|pundit]]ry).

There had been some precursors for talk radio show stars, such as the [[Los Angeles]]-area controversialist [[Joe Pyne]], who would attack callers on his program in the early 1960s – one of his famous insults was &quot;gargle with razor blades!&quot;; the similar [[Bob Grant (radio)|Bob Grant]] in [[New York City]]; and [[Wally George]] in Southern California.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video|url=http://www.americanfilms.com/play.cfm?clipid=86&amp;cid=0|title=Wally George vs. Morton Downey, Jr|publisher=AmericanFilms.com|date=|accessdate=2008-11-24}}{{dead link|date=July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Grant remains on the air to this day.

Politically [[liberal talk radio]] aimed at a national audience has also emerged. [[Air America (radio network)|Air America]], a network featuring ''[[The Al Franken Show]],'' was founded in 2004. It billed itself as a &quot;progressive alternative&quot; to the conservative talk radio shows.

Some prominent examples of liberal talk radio shows currently in national syndication include: [[Dial Global]] talk show hosts [[Ed Schultz]], [[Stephanie Miller]], [[Thom Hartmann]], and [[Bill Press]]; [[The Young Turks (talk show)|The Young Turks]]; Fox News host [[Alan Colmes]], First Amendment Radio Network Libertarian host [[Jon Arthur]], self-distributed [[Norman Goldman]] and [[Mike Malloy]], and Premiere's [[Randi Rhodes]]. In some markets, local liberal hosts have existed for years, such as the British talk host [[Michael Jackson (radio commentator)|Michael Jackson]] (who was on the air at [[KABC (AM)|KABC]] in [[Los Angeles]] beginning in 1968 and is currently at [[KGIL]]); [[Bernie Ward]] in [[San Francisco]]; Jack Ellery in New Jersey and Tampa; [[Dave Ross]] in Seattle, and [[Marc Germain]] in Los Angeles. A few earlier syndicated programs were hosted by prominent Democrats who were not experienced broadcasters, such as [[Jim Hightower]], [[Jerry Brown]], [[Mario Cuomo]] and [[Alan Dershowitz]]; these met with limited success, and Air America has been faced with various legal and financial problems.

Air America was sold to a new owner in March 2007, hired well-known programmer David Bernstein, and began its &quot;re-birth.&quot; Bernstein subsequently left in early 2008, but the struggling network remained on the air with a revamped line-up.

On January 21, 2010, Air America Radio ceased live programming citing a difficulty with the current economic environment, and announced that it would file for Chapter 7 bankruptcy production and liquidate itself. The network ended operations on January 25, 2010.{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}}

Liberal opinion radio has long existed on the [[Pacifica Radio|Pacifica]] network, though only available in a small number of major cities, and in formats that more often act as a volunteer-run community forum than as a platform for charismatic hosts who would be likely to attract a large audience. The one major host to become popular on the network is [[Amy Goodman]], whose ''[[Democracy Now!]]'' interview and journalism program is broadcast nationwide. Conservative critics have long complained that the long-format news programming on [[National Public Radio]] (NPR) shows a liberal bias, although this is disputed by [[Fairness and Accuracy in Reporting]] (FAIR), a progressive media criticism organization, which found that, for example, &quot;representatives of think tanks to the right of center outnumbered those to the left of center by more than four to one: 62 appearances to 15.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fair.org/index.php?page=1180|title=How Public Is Public Radio?|publisher=FAIR.org|date=May/June 2004|accessdate=2009-05-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;
NPR itself denies any partisan agenda.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.npr.org/about/ethics/|title=NPR News Code of Ethics|publisher=National Public Radio|date=undated|accessdate=2009-09-30}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}} Section III of the code states that NPR &quot;...separate&lt;nowiki&gt;[s]&lt;/nowiki&gt; our personal opinions - such as an individual's religious beliefs or political ideology - from the subjects we are covering. We do not approach any coverage with overt or hidden agendas.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Politically oriented talk programs on the network are in the mold of ''[[Talk of the Nation]]'', which is designed to be a soundboard for the varied opinions of listeners.

Clear Channel, with nearly 1,300 radio stations under its ownership – along with other owners – has in recent years added more [[liberal talk]] stations to their portfolio. These have primarily come from the conversion of AM facilities, most of which formerly had [[adult standards]] formats. Many complaints (all radio stations are required by the FCC to maintain, in their public files, copies of all correspondence from the public relating to station operations – for a period of three years from receipt) have been received from fans of this musical genre ([[Tony Bennett]], [[Frank Sinatra]], [[big band music]],&quot; etc.) – but the left-leaning talk programming leans toward a much younger [[demographic]], a group that advertisers covet. More recently, however, Clear Channel has been dropping liberal formats in favor of their own [[Fox Sports Radio]] network.

===Hot talk===
&quot;Hot talk&quot;, also called &quot;[[FM broadcasting|FM]] talk&quot; or &quot;shock talk&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|journal=[[Mediaweek]]|date=1999-04-05|volume=9|issue=14|page=16|url=http://www.allbusiness.com/services/business-services-miscellaneous-business/4805045-1.html|last=Bachman|first=Katy|title=Ed Tyll Fires Up Growing 'Hot Talk' Category}}{{dead link|date=July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; is a talk radio format geared predominantly to a male demographic between the ages of 18-49. The subject matter generally consists of subjects pertaining to [[pop culture]] rather than the political talk found on [[AM radio]]. Hosts of hot talk shows are usually known as [[shock jock]]s.

[[Clear Channel Communications]] has a select few hot talk stations under the moniker ''Real Radio'', while [[CBS Radio]] once had a larger chain of hot talkers known as [[Free FM]], though this brand has been abandoned. It is usually found on [[FM radio]] music stations in morning drive, as the actual hot talk formatted stations have only achieved mediocre success as a whole compared to AM or conservative talk radio, or even FM music radio. More recently the genre has been showing up on [[satellite radio]] and [[Internet radio]], media that are beyond the reach of the FCC's obscenity rules, allowing the hosts of such shows to be as vulgar and outrageous as they desire. Advertising tends to be more limited on these media, because of reliance on subscription revenues (in the case of satellite) and smaller audience and fewer connections to advertisers (in the case of Internet-only shows, which usually lack the full sales departments of terrestrial and satellite broadcasters).

Other US hosts specialize in talk radio [[comedy]], such as [[Phil Hendrie]], who voices his own fictional guests and occasionally parodies other programs. [[Sports radio|Sports talk radio]] can be found locally and nationally in the US (with the networks [[ESPN Radio]], [[Fox Sports Radio]], and [[Sporting News Radio]], as well as nationally syndicated hosts [[Jim Rome]] and [[Dan Patrick]]). Sports talk stations like [[WFAN]] in New York City and [[WEEI]] in Boston have done well in the ratings (aided by baseball and football game broadcasts).

==Talk radio in the United Kingdom==
Talk radio in the [[United Kingdom]] is popular, though not as much as music radio. Nationwide talk stations include [[BBC Radio 4]], [[BBC Radio 5 Live]], [[BBC Radio 4 Extra]] and [[talkSPORT]]. Regional stations include [[BBC Radio Scotland]] and [[BBC Radio Wales]]. Many [[BBC Local Radio]] stations and some commercial stations offer a talk format, for example, [[BBC London]], the BBC's flagship local station. Other notable commercial talk stations include [[London]]'s [[LBC]] which pioneered the newstalk format in [[Europe]]. LBC currently operates two services in London - [[LBC 97.3]], a newstalk station on FM; and [[LBC News 1152 AM|LBC News 1152]], a rolling news station on AM; also, [[Talk 107]] in [[Edinburgh]]. There are many specialised talk services such as [[Bloomberg Television|Bloomberg]], a financial news station.

Talk radio expanded dramatically when the BBC's monopoly on radio broadcasting was ended in the 1970s with the launch of [[Independent Local Radio]].

Some notable British talk radio presenters include [[Tommy Boyd]], [[James Whale]], [[Steve Allen (radio presenter)|Steve Allen]], [[Jon Gaunt]], [[Nick Abbot]], [[James Stannage]], [[George Galloway]], [[Ian Collins (radio presenter)|Ian Collins]], [[Brian Hayes (broadcaster)|Brian Hayes]], [[Scottie McClue]], [[Nicky Campbell]] and [[Simon Mayo]]. [[Pete Price]] on [[CityTalk]] is also known as the DJ who rushed to the aid of a regular caller who died live on air during a call.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/merseyside/4587550.stm|work=BBC News|title=Radio talkshow caller dies on air|date=2006-01-06|accessdate=2010-04-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Previously, he kept a suicidal teenager talking for 45 minutes before meeting him to convince him against that course of action.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/merseyside/3465181.stm|title=Radio DJ 'saves boy's life'|publisher=BBC News|date=February 6, 2004|accessdate=2008-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Talk radio in Canada==
In contrast to talk radio stations in the United States, where syndicated programs tend to make up a significant part of most schedules, privately owned Canadian talk radio stations tend to be predominantly local in programming and focus. There is no [[Canadian content]] requirement for talk radio, or &quot;spoken word,&quot; programming, unless the individual station's license expressly stipulates such a requirement; most do not. (In Canada, prospective radio stations may propose certain restrictions on their license in order to gain favor with the [[Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission]] and have an easier time obtaining a license.)

The only nationally syndicated, politically oriented weekday talk radio show in Canada is ''Adler On Line'', hosted by [[Charles Adler (broadcaster)|Charles Adler]] and heard on eleven stations across the country. Until 2006, [[Peter Warren (radio)|Peter Warren's]] ''[[Warren on the Weekend]]'' was heard Saturdays and Sundays. Both programs are or were distributed by the [[Corus Entertainment|Corus Radio Network]] and, coincidentally, both hosts had hosted different morning call-in programs in the same time slot on [[Winnipeg, Manitoba]]'s [[CJOB]] 680 before they became nationally syndicated (Adler's show still originates from CJOB and retained its original title, while Warren was based in [[Victoria, British Columbia]].) Prior to ''Adler On Line'', Corus had syndicated ''Rutherford'', hosted by conservative [[Dave Rutherford]] and originating from its [[Calgary]] station, [[CHQR|QR77]]. ''Rutherford'' is no longer syndicated nationally but continues to air in Calgary, [[Edmonton, Alberta|Edmonton]], and [[London, Ontario|London]].

Other Canadian talk radio programs which have been syndicated to different markets include:
* ''The [[George Stroumboulopoulos]] Show'' airs on Sunday nights on stations in [[Toronto]] and [[Montreal]].
* ''The Home Discovery Show'', a call-in home renovation program hosted by Shell Busey.
* ''[[Live Audio Wrestling]]''; a 2 hour show focusing on [[Mixed Martial Arts]] and [[Professional Wrestling]], distributed on [[Live Audio Wrestling#Fight Network Radio|Fight Network Radio]].
* ''Love and Romance'', a [[Personal relationship|relationship]] advice program hosted by Sue McGarvie.
* ''[[Prime Time Sports]]'', a [[sports radio|sports talk]] program hosted by [[Bob McCown]]. A three-hour program originating from [[CJCL|The Fan 590]], usually only the third hour is broadcast nationally.
* ''Renovations Cross Canada'', a weekend program about home renovations hosted by Ren Molnar. It is the most widely distributed talk radio program in Canada.
* ''The Roy Green Show'', a political and entertainment based show hosted by Roy Green that airs on Saturday and Sunday afternoons, primarily on the Corus Radio Network.
* ''[[The 'X' Zone]]'', a nightly show about [[paranormal]] topics hosted by Rob McConnell. It is also syndicated throughout the United States.

The two largest talk radio networks in Canada are the publicly owned [[Canadian Broadcasting Corporation]]'s [[English language]] [[CBC Radio One]] and [[French language]] [[Première Chaîne]]. These stations typically produce their own local morning and afternoon programs and regional noon hour programs to go along with the network programming that is aired during the rest of the day. Both networks are commercial-free. CBC Radio One's flagship national talk program is the weekend ''[[Cross Country Checkup]]'', which has been broadcast since 1965.

CFRA (580 AM) in Ottawa (formerly part of the CHUM network, which is now part of CTV) has a large and dedicated listening audience. The station is heard throughout the Ottawa valley and on the Internet. Several key programs focus on local political and world issues. Christina Sgro offers a bit of both worlds on her show, Christina's Corner, which has been gaining popularity since its inception in 2010.

Privately owned talk radio syndication networks in Canada are generally formed for the purposes of sharing programs across a group of stations with common ownership, although some are formed to distribute their one or two talk radio programs to a number of stations regardless of ownership. The largest of these is the [[Corus Entertainment|Corus]] Radio Network. [[TSN Radio]], the successor to the long-defunct [[The Team (radio network)|The Team]], is one of the newest national networks in Canada, with operations in three of its major markets, and has room for expansion.

Syndicated programs from the United States which air on Canadian radio stations include:
*''[[Coast to Coast AM]]'' with [[George Noory]], arguably the most widely distributed U.S.-based program in Canada
*''[[Joy Browne|The Dr. Joy Browne Show]]''
*''GameTime React with [[J. T. the Brick]]''
*''[[The Jim Rome Show]]''

Traditionally, politically driven talk radio from the United States does not air on Canadian stations, with a few scattered exceptions (e.g. the now-defunct [[CFBN]], which carried political programming such as the ''[[Glenn Beck Program]]'' and [[Dennis Miller]], and the also-discontinued talk format of [[CHAM]], which carried Miller). Top political programs such as ''[[The Rush Limbaugh Show]]'' are never broadcast in Canada mainly due to high rights fees.

==Talkback radio in Australia==
In [[Australia]], talk radio is known as &quot;talkback radio&quot;. The most popular talkback radio station historically was [[Sydney Media#Radio|Sydney's]] [[2UE]], whose [[Populism|populist]] programs like [[John Laws|''The John Laws Morning Show'']], are widely syndicated across the continent. In recent years though, 2UE been eclipsed by its Sydney rival [[2GB]] after the defection of 2UE most popular talkback host, [[Alan Jones (radio broadcaster)|Alan Jones]]. In
[[Melbourne]], [[3AW]] is the highest rating talkback radio station, and has also been the highest rating Melbourne radio station for several decades in a row.

6PR personality Garry Meadows was the first announcer to use talkback radio in early 1967.  'Talkback' radio, using a seven-second time lapse mechanism, began in Australia in April 1967, simultaneously on [[2SM]], Sydney (with [[Mike Walsh (TV host)|Mike Walsh]]) and 3DB, Melbourne (with [[Barry Jones (Australian politician)|Barry Jones]]).

In the 1990s and 2000s, &quot;Talkback&quot; on FM has been attempted. ''[[The Spoonman]]'' was a program hosted by [[Brian Carlton]] on the triple m network in the late 1990s and returned in 2005 for 3 and a half years, the show wrapping up in 2008. It was a show which covered many topics, but the 'Hot Talk' format in the USA would probably be the best way to describe the program.

Talkback radio has historically been an important political forum in Australia and functions much like the cable news televisions in the United States, with live and 'saturated' coverage of political issues.

==Talkback radio in New Zealand==
In [[New Zealand]], as in Australia, the talk radio format is popularly known as talkback radio. The major radio networks broadcasting in the talk radio format are [[Newstalk ZB]] and [[Radio Live]]. Their sports sister networks, [[Radio Sport]] and [[LiveSport]] also largely broadcast in talk format. Other stations such as [[Radio New Zealand National]] have a large component of talk-based content, but do not have talk-back (i.e. listener phone-ins).

Newstalk ZB is the New Zealand market leader, but Radio Live is continuing to try to establish itself with a greater presence in the talk radio market since its inception in 2005.

==Talk radio in Spain==
Talk radio on Spanish National Radio and many municipal stations is highly political with actual radio networks either supporting the major parties PP and POSE so bias is a particular aspect of the output. Talk Radio in English was originally served by Coastline Radio, the first truly English language station in [[Nerja]], [[Costa del Sol]]. It still operates today but more music oriented. Then some local English ex-broadcasters put OCI International together. Based in [[Marbella]] on the Costa del Sol, it was owned by the ONCE National Spanish Network but provided a very much needed link to the English speaking Expats living on the coast. It also provided limited coverage for Scandinavian expats. This started in the early 90s' and was only met with a similar motivated competitor in 2004 called REM FM. Most of the on air talent moved over to this independent English language project. OCI was subsequently closed down in 2007 to make way for Radio Europa music. In 2009 REM FM was acquired and subsequently rebranded as Talk Radio Europe ([http://www.talkradioeurope.com/ Talk Radio Europe]). This station offers a full daytime schedule of news, interviews, discussion and debate. TRE is affiliated to [[Independent Radio News|IRN]]/[[SKY News]] and a [[World Media]] Partner with [[BBC World Service]], so they can provide sustaining services overnight. Talk Radio Europe is broadcast in FM on the Costa del Sol, [[Costa Almeria]], [[Costa Blanca]] and across the island of [[Mallorca]] in English. It is distributed on the Internet and also available on all smartphone platforms.

==Talk radio in the Philippines==
Almost all [[Amplitude modulation|AM]] radio stations are talk stations. A few stations from [[Radio Mindanao Network]] and [[Bombo Radyo]] are on FM. [[DWFM|Radyo 5 News FM]] is the first talk radio station in Metro Manila.

==Talk radio in France==
Talk radio is one of the popular form of radio entertainment in France, examplified by RTL and RMC, plus state-owned France Inter. A premier English language talk radio in France is the [[Gascony Show]]. Launched in early 2011, this show is broadcast weekly into the Gascony region of the south west of France, as well as to the rest of France via Internet streaming.

==Talk radio in Brazil==
In Brazil, there are few talk radios.{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}} The most important talk radio in Brazil is [[Jovem Pan|Jovem Pan AM]], which have also sports and news broadcasts.

==Talk radio in Poland==
There is only one talk radio station in Poland, called TOK FM, which is owned by [[Agora SA]], a Polish media company. Its programmes are broadcast in 10 large cities including [[Warsaw]], [[Krakow]], [[Gdansk]], [[Poznan]] and [[Katowice]]. The programme is also available via Internet and transmitted by the [[Hot Bird]] [[Satellite constellation|constellation]]. It was founded in 1998 as &quot;Inforadio&quot;.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==

* History of Talk Radio
**Donna L.Halper, &quot;Icons of Talk:  The Media Mouths That Changed America.&quot;  Greenwood Press, 2008.

* Politically oriented talk radio:
** David C. Barker; ''Rushed to Judgment: Talk Radio, Persuasion, and American Political Behavior'' Columbia University Press, 2002
** Stephen Earl Bennett; &quot;Americans' Exposure to Political Talk Radio and Their Knowledge of Public Affairs&quot; in ''Journal of Broadcasting &amp; Electronic Media'', Vol. 46, 2002
** Randy Bobbitt. ''Us Against Them: The Political Culture of Talk Radio'' (Lexington Books; 2010) 275 pages. Traces the history of the medium since its beginnings in the 1950s and examines its varied impact on elections through 2008.
** Christopher L. Gianos and C. Richard Hofstetter; &quot;Political Talk Radio: Actions Speak Louder Than Words,&quot; ''Journal of Broadcasting &amp; Electronic Media''. Volume: 41. Issue: 4. : 1997. pp 501+.
** Ian Hutchby; ''Confrontation Talk: Arguments, Asymmetries, and Power on Talk Radio'' Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, 1996
* Hot talk:
** {{cite book|last=Fisher|first=Marc|year=2007|url=http://www.amazon.com/Something-Air-Revolution-Shaped-Generation/dp/0375509070|publisher=[[Random House]]|title=Something in the Air: Radio, Rock, and the Revolution That Shaped a Generation|isbn=0-375-50907-0}}
** {{cite news|work=[[The Boston Globe]]|date=2000-02-13|last=Jurkowitz|first=Mark|coauthors=Globe Staff|url=http://nl.newsbank.com/nl-search/we/Archives?p_product=BG&amp;p_theme=bg&amp;p_action=search&amp;p_maxdocs=200&amp;p_topdoc=1&amp;p_text_direct-0=0EADDE2EB3C5154B&amp;p_field_direct-0=document_id&amp;p_perpage=10&amp;p_sort=YMD_date:D&amp;s_trackval=GooglePM|title=Talk Radio's Blue Streak as Political Issues Lose Their Pull, Programmers Are Wooing Younger Audiences with a Mix of Shock Talk, Jock Talk, and R-Rated Banter}}
** {{cite news|work=[[Fort Worth Star-Telegram]]|date=1998-11-01|url=http://nl.newsbank.com/nl-search/we/Archives?p_product=ST&amp;s_site=dfw&amp;p_multi=ST&amp;p_theme=realcities&amp;p_action=search&amp;p_maxdocs=200&amp;p_topdoc=1&amp;p_text_direct-0=0EB042E584467764&amp;p_field_direct-0=document_id&amp;p_perpage=10&amp;p_sort=YMD_date:D&amp;s_trackval=GooglePM|title=War of the Words More FM stations switching from hard rock to all talk}}
** {{cite news|work=[[Los Angeles Times]]|date=1995-07-16|last=Goldstein|first=Patrick|authorlink=Patrick Goldstein|url=http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/latimes/access/22642186.html?dids=22642186:22642186&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;date=Jul+16%2C+1995&amp;author=Patrick+Goldstein&amp;pub=Los+Angeles+Times+(pre-1997+Fulltext)&amp;desc=YAKITY+YAK%2C+PLEASE+TALK+BACK+Inside+the+Intense+and+Screwy+World+of+Talk+Radio+and+the+Search+for+the+Next+LarrykingrushlimbaughhowardsterngordonliddyWhomever&amp;pqatl=google|title=Yakity Yak, Please Talk Back: Inside the Intense and Screwy World of Talk Radio and the Search for the Next LarrykingrushlimbaughhowardsterngordonliddyWhomever}}

==External links==
* {{dmoz|Arts/Radio/Formats/Talk_Radio/|Talk Radio}}
* [http://talkers.com/top-talk-radio-audiences/ Talker's Magazine &quot;The Top Talk Radio Audiences Spring 2010&quot;]

{{Broadcasting}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Talk Radio}}
[[Category:Radio formats]]
[[Category:Talk radio| ]]

[[de:Talkradio]]
[[id:Radio wicara]]
[[yi:שמועס פראגראם (ראדיא)]]</text>
      <sha1>e9bcfulugftm1rx4rsh8i5bj9657sf2</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
