<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Telemundo</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>10839777</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521056358</id>
      <parentid>520086928</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T14:29:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>69.203.113.14</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="32934">{{Infobox broadcasting network
| name                = Telemundo
| logo                = [[Image:Telemundo.svg|160px|The current logo of Telemundo]]
| type                = [[Spanish language|Spanish-language]] [[Terrestrial television|broadcast television network]]
| country             = {{flag|United States}},&lt;br&gt;{{flag|Puerto Rico}}
| headquarters        = [[Hialeah, Florida]]
| available           = National — Latin America
| founder             = [[Ángel Ramos (industrialist)|Ángel Ramos]]
| slogan              = ''Tu Canal''&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(''Your Channel'')&lt;/small&gt;
| broadcast_area      = [[United States]], including [[Puerto Rico]]
| owner               = [[NBCUniversal]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;([[Telemundo Communications Group]])&lt;/small&gt;
| key_people          = [[Emilio Romano]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(President)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Jacqueline Hernández]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(COO, Telemundo Communications Group)&lt;/small&gt;
| launch_date         = 1954 &lt;small&gt;(as [[WKAQ-TV]] in [[San Juan, Puerto Rico|San Juan]], [[Puerto Rico]])&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1984 &lt;small&gt;(in the continental [[United States]])&lt;/small&gt;
| dissolved           = 
| picture format      =  (HD)&lt;br/&gt;[[720p]]/[[1080p]] (HD)
| former_names        = NetSpan (1984-1987)
| website             = http://www.telemundo.com
}}
{{Infobox TV channel
| name              = 
| logofile          =
| logosize          =
| logocaption       =
| logoalt           =
| logo2             =
| launch            =
| closed date       =
| picture format    = 1080i Full HD
| share             =
| share as of       =
| share source      =
| network           =
| owner             =
| slogan            =
| country           =
| language          =
| broadcast area    =
| affiliates        =
| headquarters      =
| former names      = 
| replaced names    =
| replaced by names =
| sister names      = [[Telemundo Puerto Rico (cable network)|Telemundo Puerto Rico]]&lt;br&gt; [[mun2]]&lt;br&gt;[[Syfy (Latin America)|Syfy Latin America]]&lt;br&gt;[[Syfy Universal (Spain)|Syfy Spain]]
| terr serv 1       = Available throughout the U.S.
| terr chan 1       = see [[List of Telemundo affiliates]]
| sat serv 1        = [[DirecTV]] (US)
| sat chan 1        = Channel 406 (East)&lt;br&gt;Channel 407 (West)
| sat serv 2        = [[Dish Network]] (USA)
| sat chan 2        = Channel 835 (East)
| sat serv 3        = DirecTV (Latin America)
| sat chan 3        = Channel 162 (Puerto Rican feed)
| cable serv 1      = Available in Most Cables Providers
| cable chan 1      = Time Warner Cable Inc  (East &amp; West Coast)
| sat radio serv 1  =
| sat radio chan 1  =
| iptv serv 1       = [[AT&amp;T U-Verse]] 
| iptv chan 1       = Channel 3007
}}

'''Telemundo''' ({{IPA-es|teleˈmundo}}) is an [[United States|American]]  television network that broadcasts in Spanish. The network is the second-largest Spanish-language content producer in the world,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thefutoncritic.com/news.aspx?id=20060227nuts01 Breaking News - In Landmark Move, [[NBCUniversal]] Television Group Signs Development Deal With Galan Entertainment For Production Of Telenovelas In English Across Its Many Networks | Thefutoncritic.Com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and the second-largest Spanish-language network in the United States, behind [[Univision]]. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adweek.com/news/television/hispanic-tv-market-grows-univision-reshuffles-execs-137594 As Hispanic TV Market Grows, Univision Reshuffles Execs]&lt;/ref&gt;

Telemundo reaches 58 percent of [[Hispanic and Latino Americans|Hispanic and Latino American]] households in 142 markets via over-the-air, cable, and satellite television.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thefutoncritic.com/news.aspx?id=20060227nuts01 Breaking News - In Landmark Move, Nbc Universal Television Group Signs Development Deal With Galan Entertainment For Production Of Telenovelas In English Across Its Many Networks | Thefutoncritic.Com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; An average of 1,035,000 total viewers (aged 2 and older) tuned in for its weekday prime time lineup during 2007.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.worldscreen.com/newscurrent.php?filename=telemundo011008.htm ]{{dead link|date=April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Telemundo is the only Spanish-language network that produces most of its [[telenovela]]s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://home.businesswire.com/portal/site/google/index.jsp?ndmViewId=news_view&amp;newsId=20070626006499&amp;newsLang=en Clorox and Wal-Mart Team up With Telemundo on New Episodes of ''Dame Chocolate'' Telenovela&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Many programs on Telemundo air with [[closed captioning|closed captions]] in both Spanish and English. Univision did not provide English subtitles for its weekday primetime telenovelas and some of its programs (e.g., ''[[Mira Quien Baila (U.S.)|Mira Quien Baila]]'', ''[[Nuestra Belleza Latina]]'') in addition to Spanish closed captioning until January 30, 2012. &lt;ref name=&quot;quickstart.clari.net&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/entertainmentnewsbuzz/2012/01/univision-telenovelas-with-a-twist-english-subtitles-.html |title=Univision telenovelas with a twist: English subtitles |publisher=''[[Los Angeles Times]]''|date=2012-01-24 |accessdate=2012-01-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Selected footage from Telemundo is available to the public through the [[NBCUniversal Archives]].

Telemundo was founded by [[Ángel Ramos (industrialist)|Ángel Ramos]] with a television station in [[San Juan, Puerto Rico]] in 1954. [[Telemundo Communications Group]], the network's parent company, is part of [[NBCUniversal]], a joint venture of [[Comcast]] and [[General Electric]]. [[Emilio Romano]] is Telemundo's president. Telemundo has 1,800 employees,&lt;ref name=&quot;latimes&quot;&gt;James, Meg. [http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/business/la-fi-gaspin26jul26,1,4482109.story?coll=la-headlines-business-enter NBC tacks on Telemundo oversight to Gaspin's tasks]. [[Los Angeles Times]], July 26, 2007. Retrieved on May 14, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; and is headquartered in [[Hialeah, Florida|Hialeah]], a [[Miami, Florida]] suburb.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://msnlatino.telemundo.com/legal_corporate_english Legal corporate english].&quot; ''Telemundo''. Retrieved on February 3, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The majority of Telemundo shows and programs are filmed in their Miami studios. In 2011, 85% of Telemundo's [[telenovela]]s were filmed in Miami.&lt;ref&gt;http://miamitodaynews.com/news/110623/story4.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;


==History==
===1954–1987===
[[WKAQ-TV]] launched the Telemundo brand on March 28, 1954. The station was founded by Ángel Ramos, owner of ''[[El Mundo (Puerto Rico)|El Mundo]]'', [[Puerto Rico]]'s main newspaper at the time, and of Puerto Rico's first radio station, [[WKAQ (AM)|WKAQ]], also known as &quot;Radio El Mundo&quot;. Ramos wanted to maintain a consistent branding for his properties using the ''mundo'' theme (Spanish for &quot;world&quot;), and thus named WKAQ-TV ''Telemundo'' (in effect, &quot;Teleworld&quot; or &quot;World TV&quot;). He had tried to obtain a television license as early as the mid-1940s, but due to a [[Federal Communications Commission]] (FCC) licensing freeze for all new American television stations due to [[World War II]], Ramos had to wait until 1954 to obtain the license.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://msnlatino.telemundo.com/legal_corporate/ Corporate Information].&quot; ''Telemundo''. Retrieved on February 3, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; 

In the beginning, Ramos maintained continuity between his radio and television stations by signing an exclusive deal with the most famous and influential actor/comedian/producer in Puerto Rico, [[Ramón Rivero (Diplo)|Ramón Rivero]], better known as Diplo, whose &quot;El Tremendo Hotel&quot;, broadcast through WKAQ Radio, was the most popular radio show ever in Puerto Rico. It was Rivero who produced the first comedy/variety television shows for WKAQ Telemundo, ''[http://www.diplo.org/tv/us/tv2_us.htm La Taberna India]'', and then ''[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lYeLKyBeQ8w La Farándula Corona]'', shows that catapulted WKAQ to the top of the ratings.&lt;!--other TV stations were on the air? This should be stated, then--&gt;

During the 1970s and 1980s, WKAQ-TV, then branded as Telemundo Canal 2, was a major producer of soap operas. The channel was also known by its &quot;fingers&quot; logo—a bold number &quot;2&quot; with the silhouette of two upright fingers inside the number—and called itself &quot;El canal de los dedos&quot; (the channel of the fingers).

===1984–1987===
[[File:Telemundo historic logos.jpg|thumb|left|400px|Historic Telemundo logos.]]
In 1984, [[WNJU]] in [[Linden, New Jersey]] (serving the [[New York metropolitan area]]) and [[KSTS]] in [[San Jose, California]] formed NetSpan, the second Spanish-language television network in the continental United States.  They were joined in 1985 by [[KVEA]] in [[Los Angeles]]. The next year, KVEA's part-owner, Reliance Group Holdings, acquired the Telemundo brand when it purchased Blair Broadcasting. The purchase included [[WSCV]] in [[Ft. Lauderdale]]/[[Miami]] and Puerto Rico's [[WKAQ-TV]] (known for decades as &quot;Telemundo Canal 2&quot;). In late 1986, Reliance purchased WNJU.

In 1987, [[Saul Steinberg (business)|Saul Steinberg]] and [[Henry Silverman]] of Reliance Capital Group merged all these stations into the Telemundo Group.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.museum.tv/archives/etv/T/htmlT/telemundo/telemundo.htm |title=TELEMUNDO - The Museum of Broadcast Communications |publisher=Museum.tv |date= |accessdate=2010-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The new corporation quickly went public, and in 1987 changed NetSpan's name to Telemundo. Later that year, it purchased additional stations in San Francisco, Houston and San Antonio.

===Expansion===
Between 1988 and 1991, Telemundo acquired stations in [[Texas]], [[New Mexico]], [[Arizona]], and [[Washington, DC]]. The network decided to outsource its news division in 1988; [[CNN]] produced two newscasts, branded ''Noticiero Telemundo CNN'' (lit. &quot;Telemundo CNN News&quot;). Produced in Atlanta, Noticiero Telemundo CNN was anchored by [[Jorge Gestoso]] and [[María Elvira Salazar]]. Lana Montalbán, who anchored the show known then as ''Telemundo HBC'', returned to New York City, where she anchored the WNJU, Telemundo's O&amp;O, newscast for four years. When Salazar decided to take a reporter's position at ''Noticiero Univision'' back in Miami, [[Chile|Chilean]] former Miss Universe [[Cecilia Bolocco]] joined Gestoso. The final incarnation produced in Atlanta was co-anchored by [[Patricia Janiot]].

In 1994, Telemundo caught the fever of producing 24-hour news; the network launched Telenoticias partnering with Argentina's [[Artear]] Network, [[Antena 3 (Spain)|Antena 3]] of Spain, and [[Reuters]]. The venture was not successful and the service was sold to [[CBS]]. Rebranded as ''CBS Telenoticias'', the network did air all over the Americas. CBS Telenoticias was sold back to Telemundo and the network branded it [[Telemundo Internacional]].

===1992–1998===
In 1992, Telemundo went through another management change, as it received former Univision president Joaquin Blaya, who left Univison with four other executives. The next year, Telemundo branded itself with the campaign ''Arriba, Telemundo, Arriba'' (lit. &quot;Upwards, Telemundo, Upwards&quot;). Around the same time, the framed Telemundo's &quot;T&quot; letter logo was introduced.

In 1993, Telemundo began the ongoing practice of producing original telenovelas. The first soaps were ''Angélica, mi vida'', ''Marielena'', ''Guadalupe'', ''Señora Tentación'', and ''Tres Destinos''. International markets and syndicators soon courted these shows. Telemundo's effort faced an initial setback when Mexico's industry leader, [[Televisa]], bought Capitalvision, the production house that had been making the new soap operas.

In 1995, under the direction of Harry Abraham Castillo, the network's Executive Vice-President of Programming, Telemundo opened its first network studio on the [[West Coast of the United States|West Coast]]. On the Raleigh Studios lot in Hollywood, three shows began daily production: ''La Hora Lunática'', hosted by LA radio personality Humberto Luna; ''[[Gigi Graciette|El y Ella]]'', a daily talkshow created and hosted by [[Gigi Graciette]]; and ''Dando y Dando'', a gameshow hosted by Rafael Sigler.

===1998–2001===
In 1998, Telemundo was bought by a partnership between cable's [[Liberty Media]] and conglomerate [[Sony Pictures Entertainment]]. Helmed by yet another management team under the leadership of former [[CBS]] executive Peter Tortoricci, hopes of attracting the bilingual market were explored. The ''Lo mejor de los dos Mundos'' (&quot;The best of both Worlds&quot;) campaign was launched. Several billboards went up in cities such as Miami and San Francisco heralding a &quot;new era&quot; for Telemundo. Former CBS News Vice President [[Joe Peyronnin]] founded Telemundo's network news division in 1999 and served as its Executive Vice-President until 2006.

After Tortoricci's resignation Telemundo was led by Jim McNamara as CEO and Alan Sokol as COO. Their programming strategy followed a more traditional approach to Spanish-language television than their predecessors, since the new team incorporated several telenovelas from Colombia and Brazil and entertainment programs. It was under McNamara that Telemundo incorporated ''[[Laura en América]]'', hosted by Peruvian lawyer [[Laura Bozzo]]; ''[[Betty La Fea]]'' (&quot;Ugly Betty&quot;; lit. &quot;Betty The Ugly&quot;), starring [[Ana Maria Orozco]]; [[A Oscuras Pero Encendidos]], hosted by [[Paul Bouche]]; ''[[Xica]]'', starring [[Tais Araujo]]; the Spanish game show ''Números Rojos''; and the Argentine children's program ''Agrandaditos''.&lt;ref&gt;Sutter, Mary. [http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117781664.html?categoryid=19&amp;cs=1 Telemundo sets fall sked]. ''[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]'', May 16, 2000. Retrieved 2008-02-24.&lt;/ref&gt;

===2001–present, and future===
On April 12, 2002, Telemundo was purchased by [[NBC]] for $2.7 billion and is now a part of [[NBCUniversal]].&lt;ref name=&quot;latimes&quot;/&gt; Jim McNamara remained at the helm of the network. Local stations began producing early morning news to be more competitive in their respective markets; The Telemundo &quot;T&quot; logo received an overhaul. Telemundo's main competitor, [[Univision]], continued to have an upper hand in the ratings, although not in all time slots.

News programs were created in the wake of [[September 11, 2001 attacks|9/11]]:  ''Today in the World'', anchored by [[Marian de la Fuente]] and [[Jose Diaz-Balart]], went on the air informing viewers of national and international events. This program and its companion show ''In Early Morning'' were cancelled due to the much heralded arrival of [[Maria Antonieta Collins]] from Univision. ''Every Day with Maria Antonieta'' went on the air in October 2005; she continued to host the program along with the much recycled Diaz-Balart as co-host. Diaz-Balart was anchor of Telemundo's morning news program called  ''Telemundo Newscast: Early Morning'', later to be anchored by Ana Patricia Candiani. ''Cada Dia con Maria Antonieta'' was cancelled two years later in May 2008 after Collins announced in 2008 that she was planning to leave Telemundo when her contract expired in August that year and that she wished to return to news anchoring and due to low ratings;&lt;ref&gt;In an interview in &quot;People En Espanol&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; it was replaced by a new morning show called ''[[¡Levántate!|Get Up En Espanol]]'', another hybrid of news, cooking and information, which aired live from the studios of [[WKAQ-TV]], and was produced by Telemundo of Puerto Rico when it began airing. The hybrid included local participation of Telemundo O&amp;0 station [[WSCV]] in the Miami suburb of [[Miramar, Florida]], and also out of bureaus in New York City, Los Angeles and Mexico City. The show was later revamped, dropped the local cut-ins and began production at the Telemundo headquarters in [[Hialeah, Florida]].

In 2004, Telemundo created [[Telemundo Television Studios]] in Miami. The network also began subtitling many of its telenovelas into English via closed captioning. Under NBC, Telemundo gave greater emphasis to original programming and [[product placement]]. The network was spending $100 million a year producing its own shows around mid-decade.&lt;ref name=&quot;latimes&quot;/&gt; After it was purchased by NBCUniversal, Telemundo decided to stop importing telenovelas from Latin America and to start producing its own. To that end, Telemundo partnered with Colombian production company [[RTI Colombia]] and the Mexican production company [[Argos Comunicación]]. Telemundo's telenovelas follow the [[telenovela#Mexico|Mexican model]]. To have its telenovelas recognized by the audiences of the U.S. and Latin America, Telemundo hired famous actors and actresses from Mexico, Colombia, Venezuela, Argentina, and Puerto Rico; Telemundo now also hires American-born Hispanic actors and actresses who fluently speak Spanish. NBC officials asked McNamara to resign and replaced him with Don Browne, who had been head of Miami's NBC owned-and-operated station [[WTVJ]], in 2005.

In March 2007, NBC Universal announced that it had restructured Telemundo's entertainment division in an effort to narrow Univision's ratings dominance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117961551.html?categoryid=14&amp;cs=1 | work=Variety | title=Telemundo divisions to be revamped | date=March 21, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Starting in the fall of 2007, the network was to have cut the first commercial break in every prime time show to only 60 seconds in length.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nbcumv.com/telemundo/release_detail.nbc/telemundo-20070604000000-telemundoreformats.html?rss=1 ]{{dead link|date=April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; It also planned to air the 2008 series ''[[Idolos de Juventud]]'' uninterrupted, using pervasive product placement instead of traditional ad spots.&lt;ref&gt;[http://nbcumv.com/telemundo/release_detail.nbc/telemundo-20070524000000-telemundopresentsf.html]{{dead link|date=April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; NBC also announced the intention to dispose of the original Telemundo station in Puerto Rico (WKAQ-TV) and Los Angeles' [[KWHY]] to finance the acquisition of Oxygen Media. On December 21, 2007, NBCUniversal announced that [[WKAQ-TV]] was no longer for sale, indicating that [[Telemundo Puerto Rico (cable network)|Telemundo Puerto Rico]] would stay within the NBC family.&lt;ref&gt;WKAQ-TV &quot;Telenoticias a las 5:00 P.M.&quot; in a short message by Don Browne (NBC/Telemundo Network president).&lt;/ref&gt;

On March 18, 2008 [[Grupo Televisa]] and NBC Universal announced a 10-year multiplatform agreement that would allow 1000 hours of Telemundo programming, including news, entertainment, specials, and sports, to be broadcast over not only Televisa's free-to-air channels, but also Televisa's [[SKY México]] and cable system starting in April of that year, as well as a planned Telemundo pay channel to be launched later in the year. On October 8, 2008, Hillary Hattler the station's president gathered several employees and offered them a &quot;retirement plan&quot;, but the initiative gathered criticism from most of those present in the meeting.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.primerahora.com/noticia/otros_asi/espectaculos_asi/¿telemundo_los_quiere_retirar_temprano?/237639| title=¿Telemundo los quiere retirar temprano?| author=Rosalina Marrero-Rodríguez | publisher=Primera Hora| language=Spanish| date=2008-10-10| accessdate=2008-10-11}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:6.6.10CubanParadeUCByLuigiNovi10.jpg|thumb|right|A Telemundo float in the 2010 North Hudson Cuban Day Parade in [[Union City, New Jersey]].]]
On November 14, 2008 it was announced that Telemundo would end its two-year online relationship with [[Yahoo!]] on January 1, 2009 to launch a standalone hub at [[telemundo.com]], with [[Microsoft]] as content distributor.&lt;ref&gt;[http://finance.yahoo.com/news/Telemundo-Drops-Yahoo-For-paidcontent-13601161.html]{{dead link|date=April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On April 23, 2009, Telemundo became the first U.S.-based Spanish-language network to begin airing its prime time programming in [[1080p]] [[Aspect ratio (image)#16:9 standard|16:9]] [[High-definition television|high definition]]. Initially, Telemundo [[Owned-and-operated television stations in the United States|O&amp;Os]] in nine markets ([[WNJU|New York]], [[KVEA|Los Angeles]], [[WSNS-TV|Chicago]], [[KXTX-TV|Dallas-Fort Worth]], [[KSTS|San Francisco]], [[KTMD|Houston]], [[WSCV|Miami]], [[KBLR (TV)|Las Vegas]], and [[WKAQ-TV|Puerto Rico]]) were to air Telemundo programming in HD. The remaining O&amp;Os were to phase in HD programming over the next twelve months. It was unknown if and when third-party-owned affiliates would follow suit.

Telemundo and Televisa launched a jointly owned network in Mexico in August 2009. The new network is available on cable and satellite in Mexico.

On January 28, 2011, [[Comcast]] completed its $6.5 billion dollar acquisition of a 51% majority stake in NBC Universal, acquiring control of Telemundo as part of the deal.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.variety.com/article/VR1118031139?refcatid=14 Comcast, NBC U Merger a Done Deal], ''Variety'', January 29, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thewrap.com/television/column-post/comcast-nbcu-deal-closes-24288 Comcast-NBCU Deal Done: $30B Later, Comcast Is Proud Owner of the Peacock], ''The Wrap'', January 29, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://abcnews.go.com/Entertainment/wireStory?id=12792681 Comcast Takes Over NBC Universal After Long Review], ''ABC News'', January 29, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

Emilio Romano was named president of Telemundo in October 2011. Romano leads the Telemundo broadcast network, its 15 owned stations, the Entertainment Division and Telemundo Studios – the No. 1 producer of original Spanish-language prime time content for U.S. Hispanics. Additionally, he will oversee the Emmy Award-winning news and sports divisions, Telemundo International, Telemundo’s digital media group, and the network’s sales and marketing units. He will also have oversight of mun2, the fastest growing lifestyle cable network for young bicultural Latinos. &lt;ref&gt;http://telemundomediakit.com/2011/10/25/telemundos-president-emilio-romano/&lt;/ref&gt;

In the Fall of 2011, Univision forced [[Cristina Saralegui]] into involuntary retirement from the network after canceling the 20 year old &quot;[[El Show de Cristina]]&quot;, and she moved over to Telemundo for a Sunday evening program. However, without the strong resources of Univision's relationship with Televisa which allowed for exclusives with the casts of telenovelas after their ''gran finale'' episodes, Saralegui was forced to do shows with lower-tier celebrities and subjects, and her Telemundo program ended without ceremony in May 2012.

On May 14, 2012, Telemundo announced that it will launch a new branding campaign for the 2012-13 television season, that will include a new slogan and on-air identity, including the replacement of its 1999 logo design with a new logo with two red partial spheres forming the &quot;T&quot;, described to &quot;capture the duality of Telemundo’s audience, balancing the strong connection to their Latin roots with their contemporary mindset of living in the U.S.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mediamoves.com/2012/05/telemundo-unveils-new-logo-rebrands-network.html Telemundo unveils new logo, rebrands network], ''Media Moves'', May 14, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; Unfortunately, for Telemundo, the 2012-13 television season had just started in October 2012, and it seemed that the new logo got cancelled for unknown reasons, making the current 1999 logo present until further notice. 


==Programming==
{{Main|List of programs broadcast by Telemundo}}

===Primetime and daytime schedule===
Telemundo airs its 7–11 p.m. (ET/PT) weekday programs (usually telenovelas) using a form of the [[TBS (TV network)#Turner Time|Turner Time]] scheduling strategy used by [[TBS (TV network)#Turner Time|TBS]] from 1981 until 1997. That is to say, each program starts a few minutes after its officially scheduled time, typically three or four minutes after the hour. Shows also bleed over into the next time slot. This encourages viewers to stay tuned to Telemundo instead of joining another channel's program in progress. The 11 p.m. news broadcasts (both those aired by local stations and those aired by the network itself) start at the conventional time, however. The reverse is the case on weekends when [[Association football|football]] matches are aired, when all programs airing prior to the game are aired five minutes before the hour or half-hour; on weekend days when football matches are not aired, regularly scheduled programming is aired in their conventional timeslots.

The movie blocks aired on weekend afternoons and evenings typically showcase Hollywood feature films, dubbed from English to Spanish; however the network does air Spanish-language films during the late night hours, as well as on certain major holidays (in the latter case, often the movie marathon showcases films starring Mexican comedic actor [[Cantinflas]]). The Disney anthology series, ''[[Disney anthology television series|El Maravilloso Mundo de Disney]]'' (based on the ''Wonderful World of Disney'', which ironically has aired in different incarnations on sister network NBC from 1961 to 1981 and 1988 to 1990), airs Sunday evenings on a monthly basis.

Telemundo also airs the [[Qubo]] children's programming block, which is split into two 90-minute blocks on Saturday and Sunday mornings, to fulfill [[Federal Communications Commission|FCC]] [[E/I|educational program content requirements]]. Programming featured in the blocks includes ''[[Jane and the Dragon]]'', ''[[Babar (TV series)|Babar]]'' and ''[[The Zula Patrol]]'' on Saturdays, while ''[[Shelldon]]'', ''[[Willa's Wild Life]]'' and ''[[Pearlie]]'' air on Sundays.

==English subtitles==
[[Image:Cc3tout.jpg|thumb|150px|right|Screen bug]]
Telemundo provides English subtitles of its weekday prime-time programming, appearing as [[closed captioning|closed captions]] on [[Closed captioning#Caption channels|CC3]] in standard definition and digital service 2 in [[HDTV]]. The network produces the translations in-house and intends them to attract Hispanic viewers who may not be fluent in Spanish.&lt;ref name=&quot;quickstart.clari.net&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://quickstart.clari.net/qs_se/webnews/wed/da/Uus-telemundo-captions.Rylp_DS7.html |title=Commentary: Telemundo will use English captions |publisher=Quickstart.clari.net |date=2003-09-07 |accessdate=2010-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Programs appear with a special digital on-screen graphic at the start of each episode (see right).

Programs which had English captions during their original broadcast will also have them in repeats airing outside of the primetime schedule. Some programs (notably the long-running erotic anthology ''[[Decisiones]]''), have translations in some episodes but not others, depending on when they were produced. The programs that use the English captions are primarily telenovelas, though a few shows outside the genre (such as primetime court show ''[[Caso Cerrado|Caso Cerrado: Edićion Especial]]'') are also transcribed in both languages. Availability of English subtitles is limited to the technical capacity of the local station, cable or satellite provider, or other outlet to pass them on.

Telemundo was the first Spanish-language network in the United States to incorporate English captions during its programming, beginning with the premieres of ''La Cenicienta'' and ''Amor Descarado'' on September 8, 2003;&lt;ref name=&quot;quickstart.clari.net&quot;/&gt; this generated a small, loyal fan base among English-speaking viewers.&lt;ref name=&quot;telenovelas-carolina.blogspot.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://telenovelas-carolina.blogspot.com/2008/08/doa-barbara-and-picture-in-my-head.html |title=Telenovelas: Doña Barbara And &quot;The Picture In My Head&quot; |publisher=Telenovelas-carolina.blogspot.com |date=2008-08-05 |accessdate=2010-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Subtitles briefly disappeared without notice starting October 14, 2008, amid budget cuts and the change from analog to digital at Telemundo; the network cited the need to concentrate resources on its core Spanish-speaking audience, but soon reversed the cancellation due to popular demand.&lt;ref name=&quot;telenovelas-carolina.blogspot.com&quot;/&gt; The English captions returned on March 30, 2009. The network's primary competitor Univision has since joined Telemundo in utilizing English subtitles on its evening programming (primarily with its weeknight telenovelas, along with select weekend primetime series) on January 30, 2012; in the same manner as Telemundo, Univision transmits the English subtitling as closed captions on CC3.&lt;ref name=&quot;quickstart.clari.net&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/entertainmentnewsbuzz/2012/01/univision-telenovelas-with-a-twist-english-subtitles-.html |title=Univision telenovelas with a twist: English subtitles |publisher=''[[Los Angeles Times]]''|date=2012-01-24 |accessdate=2012-01-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal box|Miami|Companies|Puerto Rico}}
*[[List of United States television networks]]
*[[List of Telemundo affiliates]] (by state and city)
*[http://msnlatino.telemundo.com/entretenimiento/Crossover/ Crossover: Telemundo's Bilingual Online Site]

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://msnlatino.telemundo.com Official Site]
*[http://m.telemundo.com Telemundo Mobile Site, available only on Mobile Devices]
*[http://msnlatino.telemundo.com/entretenimiento/Crossover Crossover: Telemundo's Bilingual Online Site]
*[http://www.telemundointernacional.com Telemundo International]
*[http://www.museum.tv/archives/etv/T/htmlT/telemundo/telemundo.htm Telemundo], from the [[Museum of Broadcast Communications]] website
*[http://www.nbcumv.com/telemundo NBC Universal's media village website]
*[http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/telemundo-novelas/id430350805 Telemundo Novelas Application for iPhone and iPad]
*[https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.gloto.telemundo&amp;feature=search_result Telemundo Novelas Application for Android]
*[http://itunes.apple.com/app/deportes-telemundo/id466454789 Deportes Telemundo Application for iPhone and iPad]
*[http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/telemundo-entertainment/id512060314 Telemundo Entertainment Application for iPhone and iPad]
*[http://msnlatino.telemundo.com/especiales/Telemundo_Movil Telemundo Mobile Page Online]
*[http://msnlatino.telemundo.com/especiales/Telemundo_On_Demand Telemundo On Demand Page]
*[http://www.clubdenoveleras.com Club De Noveleras] (Bilingual)
*[http://www.lomejordelomejorla.com lo mejor de lo mejor] (Bilingual)

{{Navboxes|title=[[Telemundo]]'s [[telenovela]]s |list1=
{{Navbox
| name = Telemundo 2001–2002 telenovelas
| title = Telemundo's 2001–2002 [[telenovela]]s (USA)
| list1 = ''[[Amantes del Desierto]]''
}}&lt;noinclude&gt;
{{Navbox
| name = Telemundo 2002–2003 telenovelas
| title = Telemundo's 2002–2003 [[telenovela]]s (USA)
| list1 = ''[[Vale Todo]]''{{·}}''[[Cara o Cruz]]''{{·}} ''[[Daniela (Telemundo series)]]''{{·}}''[[La Venganza (2002 telenovela)|La Venganza]]''
}}&lt;noinclude&gt;
{{Navbox
| name = Telemundo 2003–2004 telenovelas
| title = Telemundo's 2003–2004 [[telenovela]]s (USA)
| list1 = ''[[Ladrón de Corazones]]''{{·}}''[[Amor Descarado]]''{{·}}''[[Sofía Dame Tiempo]]''{{·}}''[[El Alma Herida]]''{{·}}''[[Ángel de la Guarda: Mi Dulce Compañía]]''{{·}} ''[[Pasión de Gavilanes]]''
}}&lt;noinclude&gt;
{{Navbox
| name = Telemundo 2004–2005 telenovelas
| title = Telemundo's 2004–2005 [[telenovela]]s (USA)
| list1 = ''[[Prisionera]]''{{·}}''[[Gitanas]]''{{·}} ''[[Los Plateados]]''{{·}}''[[¡Anita, no te rajes!]]''{{·}} ''[[La Mujer en el Espejo]]''{{·}}''[[Te Voy a Enseñar a Querer]]''
}}&lt;noinclude&gt;
{{Navbox
| name = Telemundo 2005–2006 telenovelas
| title = Telemundo's 2005–2006 [[telenovela]]s (USA)
| list1 = ''[[La Ley del Silencio]]''{{·}}''[[Amarte Así]]''{{·}}''[[El Cuerpo del Deseo]]''{{·}}''[[Corazón partido]]''{{·}} ''[[Tierra de Pasiones]]''{{·}}''[[Amores de Mercado]]''{{·}}''[[La Viuda de Blanco]]''
}}&lt;noinclude&gt;
{{Telemundo 2006-2007 telenovelas}}
{{Telemundo 2007-2008 telenovelas}}
{{Telemundo 2008-2009 telenovelas}}
{{Telemundo 2009-2010 telenovelas}}
{{Telemundo 2010-2011 telenovelas}}
{{Telemundo 2011-2012 telenovelas}}
}}
{{NBC Universal}}
{{Broadcast Television}}

[[Category:Spanish-language television networks in the United States]]
[[Category:Telemundo television network]]
[[Category:Companies based in Miami-Dade County, Florida]]&lt;!--NOT in Miami - in Hialeah--&gt;
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1954]]
[[Category:NBCUniversal]]
[[Category:NBCUniversal networks]]
[[Category:Companies based in Hialeah, Florida]]

[[ar:تيلموندو]]
[[bg:Телемундо]]
[[ca:Telemundo]]
[[el:Telemundo]]
[[es:Telemundo]]
[[fa:تلموندو]]
[[fr:Telemundo]]
[[ko:텔레문도]]
[[hr:Telemundo]]
[[id:Telemundo]]
[[it:Telemundo]]
[[ka:ტელემუნდო]]
[[ja:テレムンド]]
[[pl:Telemundo]]
[[pt:Telemundo]]
[[ro:Telemundo]]
[[ru:Telemundo]]
[[sq:Telemundo]]
[[simple:Telemundo]]
[[sr:Телемундо]]
[[sh:Telemundo]]
[[fi:Telemundo]]
[[sv:Telemundo]]
[[tr:Telemundo]]</text>
      <sha1>p7l61whc2c6br6nm72trk9s7kc4qzzt</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
