<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Trinity Broadcasting Network</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>348486</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520800775</id>
      <parentid>520570757</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-31T20:51:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Azumanga1</username>
        <id>632987</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Growth */ The New Moon translators are planed on sale.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="39500">{{pp-semi-indef}}{{Infobox TV channel
|name = Trinity Broadcasting Network (TBN)
|logofile = TBN Crest.png
|logosize = 127px
|logoalt =
|launch = 1973
|closed date =
|founders = [[Paul Crouch]], [[Jan Crouch]]
|share as of =
|share source =
|picture format = [[480i]] (SD)&lt;br&gt;[[720p]]/[[1080i]] (HD)
|slogan = &quot;Worlds Largest Faith Channel&quot;
|country = [[United States]]
|language = [[English language|English]]
|broadcast area = [[United States]] and [[International]]
|headquarters = [[Costa Mesa, California]], [[United States]]
|former names = Trinity Broadcasting Systems
|replaced names =
|affiliates = ''(see article)''
|timeshift names =
|web = http://tbn.org/
|sat serv 1 = [[DirecTV]]
|sat chan 1 = Channel 372
|sat serv 2 = [[Dish Network]]
|sat chan 2 = Channel 260
|sat serv 3 = [[Cignal Digital TV]]
|sat chan 3 = Channel 26
|sat serv 2 = [[Glorystar]]|
|sat chan 2 = Channel 101|
|sat serv 5 = [[C-Band]]|
|sat chan 5 = AMC 18-Channel 223 (H2H [[4DTV]])|
|cable serv 1 = [[Verizon FiOS]]
|cable chan 1 = Channel 295
|cable serv 2 = [[First Media]]
|cable chan 2 = Channel 60
|cable serv 3 = [[TelstraClear]]
|cable chan 3 = Channel 18
|cable serv 4 = Available on many cable systems
|cable chan 4 = Check your local listings for details
|adsl serv 1  = [[AT&amp;T U-Verse]]
|adsl chan 1  = Channel 560 (SD) &lt;br&gt; Channel 1560 (HD)
|adsl serv 2  = [[Sky Angel]]
|adsl chan 2  = Channel 127
|online serv 1  = [[Digital media receiver]]
|online chan 1  = [[Roku]]
}}

The '''Trinity Broadcasting Network''' ('''TBN''') is a major [[United States|American]] [[Christian]] television network.&lt;ref name=&quot;mediabiz.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.mediabiz.com/thebridge/?release_id=154#1052 Is Content Kaput?], The BRIDGE, March 2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;highbeam.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-102725178.html Heavenly success: TV's largest religious network continues to expand around the world, while adding shows aimed at reaching a much wider audience. (30th Anniversary). - Multichannel News | HighBeam Research - FREE trial]. Highbeam.com (2003-05-26). Retrieved on 2010-11-11.&lt;/ref&gt; TBN is based in [[Costa Mesa, California]], with auxiliary studio facilities in [[Irving, Texas]]; [[Hendersonville, Tennessee]]; [[Gadsden, Alabama]]; [[Decatur, Georgia]]; [[Miami, Florida]]; [[Tulsa, Oklahoma]]; [[Orlando, Florida]]; and [[New York City]].

TBN broadcasts programs hosted by a diverse group of ministries from traditional Protestant and Catholic denominations, Interdenominational and Full Gospel churches, non profit charities, Messianic Jewish and well-known Christian and Mormon media personalities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tbn.org/watch/pdf/schedule.pdf.php NOV. 6 - 12, 2010 Program]&lt;/ref&gt; TBN also offers a wide range of original programming, and faith-based films.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tbn.org/tbn-films TBN Films]. Tbn.org. Retrieved on 2010-11-11.&lt;/ref&gt;

TBN owns and operates five broadcast networks, each reaching separate demographics; in addition to the main TBN network, TBN owns [[The Church Channel]], [[Smile of a Child TV]], [[TBN Enlace USA|TBN Enlace]] and [[JCTV]].

As of 2010, [[Paul Crouch]] is TBN's President and Chairman, [[Jan Crouch]] is its vice-president and Director of Programming, and their son [[Matthew Crouch]] is Vice President.

==History==
The Trinity Broadcasting Network was co-founded by [[Paul Crouch]], [[Jan Crouch]], [[Jim Bakker]] and [[Tammy Faye Messner|Tammy Faye Bakker]] in 1973 as Trinity Broadcasting Systems; the Bakkers would leave by 1975 to start their own ministry, ''[[The PTL Club]]''. TBN began national distribution through cable systems in 1978. The network was a member of the [[National Religious Broadcasters]] association until 1990.

The Crouches began their broadcasting activities by renting time on KBSA (now [[KFTR-DT]]) in [[Ontario, California]].  After that station was sold, he began buying two hours a day on KLXA-TV in [[Fontana, California]] in early 1974. That station was put up for sale shortly after. Paul Crouch then put in a bid to buy it for a million dollars and raised $100,000 for a down payment. After many struggles, the Crouches managed to raise the down payment and took over the station outright, with the station becoming [[KTBN-TV]] in 1977 and its city of license changed to TBN's original home base, [[Santa Ana, California|Santa Ana]], in 1983. Initially, the station ran Christian programs about six hours a day. They continued to expand to 12 hours a day by 1975 and began selling time to outside Christian organizations to supplement their local programming, with the station instituting a 24-hour schedule in 1978.

The fledgling network was so weak in its first days, that, according to Crouch in his autobiography, ''Hello World!'', it almost went bankrupt after just two days on the air. TBN, then known as the Trinity Broadcasting Systems, spread from UHF stations to cable outlets and then to satellite distribution. Over the years, TBN has been purchasing independent television stations to gain cable carriage, due to [[Federal Communications Commission|FCC]] [[must-carry]] rules. As a result, TBN is available to 95% of American households, as of early 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.broadcastingcable.com/article/CA527238.html|title= TV's Religious Revival|publisher=Broadcasting&amp;Cable|year=2005|accessdate=2008-06-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Growth==
{{main|List of Trinity Broadcasting Network affiliates}}
[[Image:TCC-TBN.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Trinity Christian City International – CA.|Trinity Christian City International.]]
TBN owns 35 full-power television stations serving larger metropolitan areas, and, at its peak, 252 low power television stations in the United States, which are mixed among stations serving medium-sized cities and rural translator stations in order to maximize the network's reach as much as is permissible. TBN also has several hundred affiliate stations throughout the United States, although just 61 of these stations are regular UHF or VHF stations. The rest are low-powered stations, requiring a viewer to be within several miles of the transmitter. According to ''TVNewsCheck'', TBN currently is the third largest over-the-air television station group in the country, besting the station groups of [[CBS]], [[Fox Television Stations|FOX]], and [[NBC]], but behind [[ION Media Networks|Ion]] and [[Univision]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tvnewscheck.com/article/2010/04/07/41240/top-station-groups-stay-the-course Top Station Groups Stay The Course], ''TVNewsCheck'', April 7, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

Worldwide, TBN's channels are broadcast on 70 satellites and over 18,000 TV and cable affiliates. TBN is also seen on the internet globally, where viewers can watch TBN programming live,&lt;ref name=&quot;TBN.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.tbn.org/watch-us Watch Us]. Tbn.org. Retrieved on 2010-11-11.&lt;/ref&gt; as well as select archived shows on demand, through the website and select [[IPTV]] services.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pr.com/press-release/20478 IPTV Service Provider Auroras Entertainment Signs Content Deals with Eight New Programming Partners]. PR.com (2006-10-19). Retrieved on 2010-11-11.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.onscreenasia.com/article-2037-trinityschannelstoblessjapanviaiptv-onscreenasia.html Trinity's channels to bless Japan via IPTV | OnScreenAsia.com: The One Stop for TV / Entertainment News]. OnScreenAsia.com (2007-10-29). Retrieved on 2010-11-11.&lt;/ref&gt; TBN also offers [[mobile app]]s in the [[iTunes Store]] and [[Google Play]],&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;[http://tbn.org/watch-us/mobile-viewing Mobile Viewing - Watch Us]. Tbn.org. Retrieved on 2010-11-11.&lt;/ref&gt; which gives users access to TBN and its channels, plus the Arabic language ''Healing Channel'', and ''Nejat TV'' in Persian.&lt;ref name=&quot;TBN.org&quot;&gt;[http://tbn.org/announcements/tbn-to-feature-new-high-tech-apps-hd-network-at-cable-show-2010 TBN to Feature New High-Tech Apps, HD Network at ‘Cable Show 2010’ - Announcements]. Tbn.org (2010-05-11). Retrieved on 2010-11-11.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.tbn.org/announcements/all-tbn-channels-now-available-on-iphone-ipad-ipod-touch-blackberry-android-and-windows-mobile&lt;/ref&gt;

During 2010, citing economic problems and a lack of donations, TBN closed down and sold many of its low-powered television repeaters. 17 of these were sold to the competing [[Daystar Television Network]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.raptureforums.com/forum/apostasy-local-church/33782-tbn-losing-lptv-stations-minnesota-north-dakota-wisconsin.html Northpine.com, via Rapture Forums: &quot;TBN losing LPTV stations in Minnesota and North dakota and Wisconsin&quot;, March 30, 2010.]&lt;/ref&gt; while 151 of these will be donated to the Minority Media and Television Council (MMTC),&lt;ref&gt;[http://mmtconline.org/lp-pdf/LPTV%20Comments%20121710.pdf FCC document: &quot;COMMENTS OF LPTV ENTREPRENEURS&quot;, December 17, 2010.]&lt;/ref&gt; an organisation designed to preserve equal opportunity and civil rights in the media;&lt;ref&gt;[http://mmtconline.org/ Per MMTC website.]&lt;/ref&gt; MMTC would later sell 78 of these translators to [[Luken Communications]], parent company of the [[Retro Television Network]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tvnewscheck.com/article/2011/06/16/51942/rtn-parent-buys-78-tv-translators TV News Check: &quot;RTN Parent Buys 78 TV Translators&quot;, June 16, 2011.]&lt;/ref&gt; Four more translators in [[Dothan, Alabama]]; [[Kirksville, Missouri]]; [[Jonesboro, Arkansas]]; and [[Jackson, Tennessee]] were sold by MMTC to New Moon Communications, with the intent to convert them to [[NBC]] affiliates;&lt;ref name=b&amp;c-mmtcnewmoon&gt;{{cite news|last=Malone|first=Michael|title=New Moon Brings NBC to Four Tiny Markets|url=http://www.broadcastingcable.com/article/470358-New_Moon_Brings_NBC_to_Four_Tiny_Markets.php|accessdate=June 28, 2011|newspaper=[[Broadcasting &amp; Cable]]|date=June 28, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; however, as of September 2012, New Moon has placed all four of these translators on sale, leaving plans for local NBC affiliates in these communities in doubt.&lt;ref&gt;Per [http://www.radiotvdeals.com/ radiotvdeals.com]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- Unable to present full URL, as coding in URL interferes with Wikipedia's markup language. Also unable to provide shortcut version, as it is blacklisted by Wikipedia. --&gt; 44 of the licenses that were donated by TBN to the MMTC would later be cancelled on December 1, 2011 for remaining silent over a year.&lt;ref name=fcc-tbndeletions&gt;{{cite web|title=Re: Applications for Assignment of License…|url=http://licensing.fcc.gov/cgi-bin/prod/cdbs/forms/prod/getimportletter_exh.cgi?import_letter_id=29804|format=PDF|date=November 30, 2011|work=CDBS Public Access|publisher=[[Federal Communications Commission]]|accessdate=December 3, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; On April 13, 2012, TBN sold 36 of its translators to Regal Media, a broadcasting group headed by George Cooney, the CEO of the [[EUE/Screen Gems]] studios.&lt;ref&gt;[https://licensing.fcc.gov/cdbs/CDBS_Attachment/getattachment.jsp?appn=101499020&amp;qnum=5030&amp;copynum=1&amp;exhcnum=1 FCC document: &quot;Asset Purchase Agreement: Trinity Christian Center Of Santa Ana, Inc. / Trinity Broadcasting Of Arizona, Inc. (Sellers) and Regal Media, Inc. (Buyer)]&lt;/ref&gt;

On October 22, 2012, it was announced that TBN has acquired [[Jackson, Mississippi]] [[The CW|CW]] affiliate [[WRBJ (TV)|WRBJ]] from [[Roberts Broadcasting]]. Once the sale is approved by the FCC, WRBJ will drop all secular and CW network program and become a full-time satellite of TBN. (The network was previously available in the Jackson area on [[WJKO-LP]], which was later sold to the [[Daystar Television Network]].) &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.clarionledger.com/article/20121023/BIZ/310230036/Roberts-brothers-TV-station-new-hands?nclick_check=1 &quot;Roberts brothers' TV station in new hands&quot;] from The Clarion-Ledger (October 22, 2012)&lt;/ref&gt;

==TBN HD==
On December 15, 2009, TBN became the first Christian television network to broadcast completely in [[High-definition television|high definition]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Web Wire.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.webwire.com/ViewPressRel.asp?aId=111013 TBN Launches High Definition Channel on AT&amp;T’s U-Verse TV Service]. Webwire.com (2010-01-15). Retrieved on 2010-11-11.&lt;/ref&gt; However, only the national feed on cable and satellite is transmitted in HD, as its owned-and-operated terrestrial stations are currently not equipped for HD broadcast due in part to technical limitations caused by the number of subchannels TBN requires its stations to carry that prevent the main TBN subchannel on its owned-and-operated stations to be carried in high definition or [[widescreen]] [[standard definition television|standard definition]].

Programs produced in the widescreen format that are available in high definition on the cable/satellite HD feed are downconverted to [[480i]] SD and broadcast in a [[letterbox]]ed [[4:3]] picture format on all five of TBN's U.S. channels carried on the network's over-the-air digital stations.

==Charitable and humanitarian initiatives==

===Smile of a Child Foundation===
''Smile of a Child Foundation'' is a compassion-focused ministry, founded in 2005 by TBN co-founder Jan Crouch initially as a vehicle to reach the children of [[Haiti]], providing food, medical care, toys and disaster relief to people in need. Crouch has over twenty years of personal involvement with the island country, having established a children’s hospital, an orphanage, and a school in Haiti. TBN spent millions on these humanitarian projects.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://larrykinglive.blogs.cnn.com/2010/01/29/filmmaker%E2%80%99s-bond-to-haiti/?utm_source=feedburner&amp;utm_medium=feed&amp;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+rss%2Fcnn_lkl+%28Blog%3A+Larry+King+Live%29 | work=CNN | title=Filmmakerâs bond to Haiti | date=2010-01-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the [[2010 Haiti earthquake|earthquake in Haiti on January 12, 2010]], TBN made immediate contributions of $100,000 through [[Lake Charles, Louisiana]]-based ''Friend Ships'', which speeds emergency relief aid and medical expertise all over the world in its fleet of dedicated cargo/ministry ships.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.friendships.org/haiti.html Haiti Mission 2006 - Friend Ships reaches out with tender loving care to the people of Haiti]. Friendships.org. Retrieved on 2010-11-11.&lt;/ref&gt; Friend Ships has been partnering with TBN and Smile since 1992, Paul Crouch personally donated a [[Bell 206]] Jet Ranger helicopter to the humanitarian organization.

In May, 2009, the [[United Nations]] officially recommended Smile of a Child to receive special consultative status with the Economic and Social Council for the Democracy Coalition Project.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs/2009/ecosoc6396.doc.htm COMMITTEE ON NON-GOVERNMENTAL ORGANIZATIONS REJECTS SPECIAL STATUS FOR GROUP, CLOSES FILE ON ANOTHER, APPROVES 10 APPLICATIONS WHILE DEFERRING 15 OTHERS]. Un.org (2009-05-26). Retrieved on 2010-11-11.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Hurricane Katrina Relief ===
TBN partnered with Friend Ships to assist thousands of individuals and families affected by the flooding in [[New Orleans]] following [[Hurricane Katrina]] in 2005.  The group's 180- foot cutter, named the &quot;Hope&quot;, sailed out of Lake Charles on September 5 for [[Gretna, Louisiana]], near New Orleans. &quot;Hope&quot; delivered food, water and other needed supplies.  The Crouches authorized an initial gift of $100,000 specifically for Friend Ships' effort, and also sending 10,000 Bibles for distribution to affected areas.  Jan Crouch is arranging to have over 85,000 dolls and other toys shipped for children whose families have lost everything.&lt;ref name=&quot;http://www.tbn.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.tbn.org Trinity Broadcasting Network]. TBN. Retrieved on 2010-11-11.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== TBN Second Chance ===
''TBN Second Chance'' is a free, 24-hour, faith-based rehabilitative TV programming helping to rebuild lives of imprisoned inmates and reduce [[recidivism]]. Four TBN networks are offered to prisons across the US via satellite, including free satellite reception equipment and installation to qualified prisons and re-entry centers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tbnsecondchance.org/ TBN Second Chance]. TBN Second Chance. Retrieved on 2010-11-11.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Programs and other media==
TBN produces a variety of original Christian programs, such as gospel music concerts, live coverage of major Christian events, talk shows, health/fitness/nutrition programs with Christian family doctors, children's shows, contemporary Christian music videos, marriage enrichment series, holiday specials, Christian dramas, and full length, family-friendly movies. In February 2008, TBN was awarded the [[Parents Television Council]] Entertainment Seal of Approval for its entire network.&lt;ref name=&quot;parentstv.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.parentstv.org/PTC/news/release/2008/0228.asp TBN Awarded Seal of Approval by Parents Television Council]. Parentstv.org (2008-02-28). Retrieved on 2010-11-11.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Programming seen on TBN===
&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;&gt;[http://www.tbn.org/watch-us/broadcast-schedule Broadcast Schedule - Watch Us]. Tbn.org. Retrieved on 2010-11-11.&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''Behind The Scenes''
* ''Believer's Voice of Victory'' with [[Ken Copeland]]
* [[Billy Graham]] Crusade
* Bishop [[TD Jakes]]
* ''Breakthrough'' with [[Rod Parsley]]
* ''Changing your Life'' with Gregory Dickow
* ''Changing your World'' with [[Creflo A. Dollar]]
* ''Destined to Reign'' with [[Joseph Prince]]
* Dr. [[Robert H. Schuller]]
* ''End of the Age'' with [[Irvin Baxter, Jr.]]
* ''Enjoying Everyday Life'' with [[Joyce Meyer]]
* ''Gospel Truth'' with [[Andrew Wommack]]
* In Touch With [[Dr. Charles Stanley]]
* ''[[It Is Written]]'' with John Bradshaw
* [[Jack Hayford]]
* [[Jesse Duplantis]]
* [[Joel Osteen]]
* [[John Hagee]] Today
* ''Kingdom Connection'' with Jentezen Franklin
* ''Leading the Way'' with Michael Youssef
* ''Life Today'' with [[James Robison]]
* ''Manna-Fest&quot; with Perry Stone
* &quot;Praise the Lord&quot;
* &quot;Taking Authority&quot; with Bishop Eddie Long
* ''[[The 700 Club]]'' with [[Pat Robertson]]
* &quot;Touching Lives&quot; with Dr. James Merritt
* &quot;Turning Point&quot; with [[David Jeremiah]]
* &quot;Winning Walk&quot; with Ed Young Sr.

Other personalities featured or have been featured on TBN include: [[A.R. Bernard]], [[Carl Baugh]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://tbn.org/index.php/2/4/p/3.html Creation in the 21st Century page] TBN.org&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kirk Cameron]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://tbn.org/index.php/2/4/p/158.html The Way of the Master page] TBN.org&lt;/ref&gt; [[MC Hammer]], [[Katy Hudson]], [[Marilyn Hickey]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://tbn.org/index.php/2/4/p/35.html Today with Marilyn and Sarah page], TBN.org&lt;/ref&gt; [[Benny Hinn]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://tbn.org/index.php/2/4/p/37.html This Is Your Day page], TBN.org&lt;/ref&gt; [[D. James Kennedy]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://tbn.org/index.php/2/4/p/43.html The Coral Ridge Hour page], TBN.org&lt;/ref&gt; [[Carol Lawrence]], [[Gavin MacLeod]], [[Jay Sekulow]], [[Fulton J. Sheen]], [[Nasir Siddiki]], [[Charles Stanley]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://tbn.org/index.php/2/4/p/69.html In Touch Ministries], TBN.org&lt;/ref&gt; [[Paula White]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://tbn.org/index.php/2/4/p/76.html Paula White Today page], TBN.org&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Jack Van Impe]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://tbn.org/index.php/2/4/p/140.html Jack Van Impe Presents page], TBN.org&lt;/ref&gt;

===TBN's films===
Films produced by or for TBN included &quot;The Revolutionary&quot; and &quot;The Revolutionary II,&quot; based on the life of Jesus; &quot;The Emissary,&quot; a film on the life of the apostle Paul; &quot;[[The Omega Code]]&quot;; &quot;Carman: The Champion&quot;; &quot;[[Megiddo: The Omega Code 2]]&quot;; &quot;Time Changer&quot;; and &quot;Six: The Mark Unleashed&quot; starring [[Stephen Baldwin]] and [[David A.R. White]].&lt;ref name=&quot;TBN.org&quot;/&gt; Some of these films were produced by [[Gener8Xion Entertainment]], TBN's Christian motion picture studio, based in [[Hollywood, California]]. The founders of Gener8Xion Entertainment are [[Matthew Crouch]] and his wife, Laurie.

On occasion, TBN would show films from other producers on its main network. One notable film was [[Mel Gibson]]'s ''[[The Passion of the Christ]]'', which had its television premiere on TBN April 17, 2011 ([[Palm Sunday]]). TBN presented the film with much of the graphic violence left in; as a result, TBN rated the film &quot;[[TV Parental Guidelines|TV-MA-V]]&quot;—a rarity for many Christian networks.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tbn.org/watch-us/our-programs/the-passion-of-the-christ TBN: &quot;The Passion of the Christ&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.skyangel.com/blog/index.php/2011/04/11/the-passion-movie-premier-alert/ Sky Angel: &quot;“The Passion” Movie Premier Alert!&quot;, April 11, 2011.]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Attractions==
Aside from its television ministry, TBN also has several attractions used as an outreach service.

Three of these—Trinity Music City, Trinity Christian City International and the International Production Center—include special [[virtual reality]] theaters, with two more planned for Hawaii and Jerusalem. The 50-seat theaters present visitors with high definition digital video technology and a 48-channel digital audio system. The theater’s showcase four original productions from TBN Films: &quot;The Revolutionary&quot;, parts I and II, portraying the life and miracles of Jesus Christ, &quot;The Emissary&quot;, depicting miraculous events from the book of Acts and the life of Paul, and &quot;The Omega Code&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tbn.org/about-us/visit-tbn Visit TBN - About Us]. Tbn.org. Retrieved on 2010-11-11.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Trinity Music City===
[[Image:TrinityMusicCity2.jpg|thumb|alt=Trinity Music City, USA TN|Trinity Music City.]]
TBN’s newest tourist attraction is [[Trinity Music City]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
  | last = Trinity Music City, USA
  | first =
  | title = Website
  | url=http://www.tbn.org/index.php/3/11.html
  | accessdate = 2009-04-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;
an entertainment complex in [[Hendersonville, Tennessee]]. Formerly known as &quot;Twitty City&quot;, the former estate of country music legend [[Conway Twitty]], the complex includes the 2000-seat Trinity Music City Church Auditorium where audiences attend TBN-produced concerts, dramas, seminars and special events. A 50-seat virtual reality theater showcases four original productions from TBN Films.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tbn.org/about-us/tennessee Tennessee - About Us]. Tbn.org. Retrieved on 2010-11-11.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Trinity Christian City International ===
TBN World Headquarters in [[Costa Mesa, California]] offers a variety of activities and tours. Virtual Reality Theater debuted &quot;The Revolutionary&quot;, an original motion picture, filmed entirely on location in Israel. This high definition virtual reality theater features a 48 channel sound system. Visitors can also walk along a recreation of the Via Dolorosa, the street in the old walled city of Jerusalem where Jesus carried His cross to Calvary. Visitors can tour the Demos Shakarian Memorial Building, which houses the TBN studios that are seen regularly on international television broadcasts.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tbn.org/about-us/southern-california Southern California - About Us]. Tbn.org. Retrieved on 2010-11-11.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Lake Trinity Estates===
Lake Trinity Estates (formerly known as Trinity Towers) is an [[recreational vehicle|RV]] park in [[Hollywood, Florida]], adjacent to [[WHFT-TV]]'s studios. The facility is an {{convert|11|acre|m2|adj=on}} [[recreational vehicle|RV]] park. Full hook-ups are available with 30 AMP sites and propane sales. Swimming, fishing, Shuffleboard, Patanque, Basketball, and nearby golfing are available for guests.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tbn.org/about-us/florida Florida - About Us]. Tbn.org. Retrieved on 2010-11-11.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== International Production Center ===
[[Image:InternationalProductionCenter.jpg|thumb|alt=International Production Center - Irving, Texas|International Production Center]]
[[Dallas, Texas]] TBN affiliate [[KDTX-TV]] offers tours through a recreation of the Via Dolorosa, the street in the old walled city of Jerusalem where Jesus carried His cross to Calvary, and The Virtual Reality Theater, featuring a 48 channel sound system. Visitors can walk through The Angel Gardens, or shop at the Family Christian Store. Audiences can also watch live, television broadcasts, including &quot;Praise the Lord!&quot;, TBN’s signature television show.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tbn.org/about-us/texas Texas - About Us]. Tbn.org. Retrieved on 2010-11-11.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Holy Land Experience ===
[[Image:HolyLand01.jpg|thumb|alt=Holy Land Experience - Orlando, Florida|Holy Land Experience]]
In June 2007, TBN purchased the bible-themed adventure park [[Holy Land Experience]] in [[Orlando, Florida]] for $37 million.&lt;ref name=&quot;Orlando Sentinel&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.orlandosentinel.com/orl-holyland2107oct21,0,3805392.story?coll=orl-home-utility-sports | title=Scores lose jobs as Holy Land undergoes extreme makeover | publisher=[[Orlando Sentinel]] |date= October 21, 2007| accessdate =2007-09-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.holylandexperience.com/ Home]. The Holy Land Experience. Retrieved on 2010-11-11.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Controversy==

===Theology===

Trinity Broadcasting Network has come under heavy criticism for its promotion of the [[prosperity gospel]], teaching viewers that they will receive a reward if they donate or give offerings.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Give, and it will be given to you. A large quantity, pressed together, shaken down, and running over will be put into your lap, because you will be evaluated by the same standard with which you evaluate others.&quot;http://bible.cc/luke/6-38.htm&lt;/ref&gt; In a 2004 interview with the ''Los Angeles Times'', Paul Crouch, Jr. expressed his disappointment that &quot;the prosperity gospel is a lightning rod for the Body of Christ. It's not what drives TBN.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.latimes.com/2004/sep/20/local/me-tbn20 TBN's Promise: Send Money and See Riches], ''Los Angeles Times'', 20 September 2004&lt;/ref&gt; 

Non-denominational programmers on TBN's schedule include: [[Joel Osteen]], [[Nasir Siddiki]], [[Steve Munsey]], [[Benny Hinn]], [[Rod Parsley]], [[Creflo Dollar]], [[Joyce Meyer]], [[Eddie L. Long]], [[Jesse Duplantis]], [[Paula White]], and [[Kenneth Copeland]]. Traditional Protestant pastors that air on TBN include: [[Dr. Charles Stanley]], [[Franklin Graham]], [[Billy Graham]], Michael Youseff, [[David Jeremiah]], and [[Robert Jeffress (pastor)]]. Senator [[Chuck Grassley]], the chairman of the [[United States Senate Committee on Finance]] has conducted investigations into whether Hinn, White, Copeland, Dollar, Meyer, or Long mishandled their finances; none were found to have committed wrongdoing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2007/11/06/cbsnews_investigates/main3462147.shtml | title=Televangelists Living Like Kings? | publisher=[[CBS News]] |date= November 6, 2007| accessdate =2007-09-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.christianpost.com/article/20080709/two-televangelists-making-reforms-amid-financial-probe/index.html | title=Two Televangelists Making Reform | publisher=[[The Christian Post]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Wealth and transparency===

TBN is a 501-3 C non-profit company. Full disclosure of TBN’s financial statements have been evaluated by [[Charity Navigator]], the nation’s largest evaluator of charities and non-profit companies. TBN has received a 3/4 star rating for 4 consecutive years, and in 2009 earned a 2/4 star rating due to a 2% increase in administrative costs in 2009; the report also revealed that for the fiscal year ending December 2009, TBN president Paul F. Crouch Sr. earned $419,500, Vice-President Janice Crouch earned $361,000, and Vice-President Paul F. Crouch Jr. earned $214,137.&lt;ref name=&quot;charitynavigator.org&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.charitynavigator.org/index.cfm?bay=search.summary&amp;orgid=4574 | title=charitynavigator.org | publisher=[[Charity Navigator]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another charity watchdog group, [[Ministry Watch]], has given TBN an &quot;F&quot; in 2011, for its failure to provide financial statements, lack of timeliness in responding to correspondence, and its lack of clarity in the provided information. As a result, TBN was placed on their alert list annually since 2009.&lt;ref name=MinistryWatchTBN&gt;[http://www.ministrywatch.com/profile/trinity-broadcasting-network.aspx Ministry Watch: Trinity Broadcasting Network]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ministrywatch.com/pdf/donoralert2011.pdf Ministry Watch: &quot;30 Donor Alerts of 2011&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

TBN’s annual financial information is monitored by the [[Chronicle of Philanthropy]] where it is ranked 243 out of the top 400 non-profit corporations in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;http://philanthropy.com/premium/stats/philanthropy400/index.php?keyword=trinity+broadcasting&amp;search=search&lt;/ref&gt; 

TBN is not a member of the [[Evangelical Council for Financial Accountability]]. 

In February 2012, Brittany B. Koper, TBN's former Director of Finance, filed a lawsuit against her former attorneys, Davert &amp; Loe. The 3 counts of the complaint were: Breach of Fiduciary Duties; Intentional Infliction of Emotional Distress; and Professional Negligence. Koper filed the suit following the termination of her employment with TBN. Davert &amp; Loe, who also represented TBN, denied her claims. Koper’s suit against Davert &amp; Loe is pending. No official judicial ruling has been made in this matter.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.charismanews.com/us/33409-exclusive-lawsuit-against-tbn-dismissed&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2012/05/05/us/tbn-fight-offers-glimpse-inside-lavish-tv-ministry.html?_r=1&amp;smid=fb-share Family Battle Offers Look Inside Lavish TV Ministry], ''The New York Times'', 4 May 2012&lt;/ref&gt;  

In a May 2012 interview with ''[[The New York Times]]'', Koper claimed that, &quot;My job as finance director was to find ways to label extravagant personal spending as ministry expenses&quot;.  Koper alleged that the network had herself and [[chauffeur]]s and [[sound engineer]]s&amp;mdash;ordained as ministers in order to avoid paying [[Social Security (United States)|Social Security]] taxes on their salaries.

Paul Crouch, Jr. resigned his position at TBN. As of November 10, 2011, Paul Crouch, Jr. has joined The Word Network as Director of Project Development.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cbn.com/cbnnews/us/2011/November/Paul-Crouch-JrJoins-The-Word-Network&lt;/ref&gt;

===Lawsuits===

In September 2004, the ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'' reported that Paul Crouch had paid Enoch Lonnie Ford, a former TBN employee, a $425,000 formal settlement to end a wrongful termination lawsuit in 1998.&lt;ref name=&quot;1996scandal&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.ctlibrary.com/ct/2004/septemberweb-only/9-13-11.0.html | title=Former TBN Employee Alleges Gay Tryst With Paul Crouch |publisher=[[Christianity Today]] | date=September 1, 2004 | first=Ted | last=Olsen | accessdate = 2006-12-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ford alleged that he and Crouch had a homosexual tryst during his employment.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.multichannel.com/article/79701-TBN_s_Crouch_Rebuts_Sexual_Harassment_Story.php&lt;/ref&gt; TBN officials acknowledged the settlement but contested Ford's credibility, noting that he had been previously convicted for [[child molestation]] and drug abuse. In 1996, Ford was fired by TBN after he was arrested for drug-related violations and returned to prison for a year. Ford allegedly threatened to sue TBN for [[wrongful termination]] and [[sexual harassment]] after the network refused to hire him following his release, resulting in his claims against Paul Crouch. TBN officials stated that the settlement was made in order to avoid a lengthy and expensive lawsuit.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://news.independent.co.uk/world/americas/article32197.ece | title=Bad faith, blackmail and a troubled TV evangelist  | publisher=[[The Independent]] |date= 14 September 2004| accessdate =2007-09-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In late 2003, Ford attempted to [[extort]] Crouch, threatening to release an autobiographical [[manuscript]] of their alleged affair if TBN didn't purchase the document for $10 million. In October 2004, Judge [[Robert J. O'Neill]] awarded Crouch $136,000 in legal fees to be paid by Ford for his violation of the terms of the settlement agreement, specifically the prohibition of discussing the settlement's details. On March 15, 2005, Ford appeared on the [[Ion Television]] show ''[[Lie Detector (TV series)|Lie Detector]]'' to be given a [[polygraph test]]; the results of the test were never broadcast or made public.&lt;ref&gt;Lloyd Grove, &quot;Born again: Evangelist sex scandal,&quot; New York Daily News, March 31, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2012, ''[[The Orange County Register]]'' reported that Carra Crouch, the granddaughter of Paul and Jan Crouch, filed a lawsuit claiming that TBN covered-up her [[rape]] by a network employee when she was thirteen years old.&lt;ref&gt;[http://taxdollars.ocregister.com/2012/06/21/suit-alleges-tbn-covered-up-rape-of-13-year-old/157357/ Suit alleges TBN covered up rape of 13-year-old], ''The Orange County Register]]'', 21 June 2012&lt;/ref&gt; Carra Crouch claimed to have been given a [[date rape drug]] and [[sexual abuse|sexually abused]] while staying at an [[Atlanta, Georgia]], hotel during TBN's &quot;Praise-a-thon&quot; in the spring of 2006. She also claimed that when she informed Jan Crouch and TBN attorney John Casoria of the rape, they professed disbelief in her claims and blamed her for the incident. However, according to the lawsuit, Crouch and Casoria fired the employee, agreeing to not turn him in to the authorities if he didn't file for [[unemployment]], [[worker's compensation]], or [[Equal Employment Opportunity Commission|EEOC]] benefits. As ordained ministers, Crouch, Casoria, and other Crouch family members are legally obligated to report a sexual assault. TBN attorney Colby May &quot;vehemently denied&quot; Carra Crouch's claims, calling them &quot;without merit and baseless.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://blogs.ocweekly.com/navelgazing/2012/06/granddaughter_of_paul_and_jan-crouch_alleges_cover-up.php Granddaughter of Paul and Jan Crouch Alleges Cover-up of Rape by TBN Employee When She Was 13], ''OCWeekly'', 25 June 2012&lt;/ref&gt; Her lawsuit against TBN is ongoing.

===Hal Lindsay Show Cancellation===

From 1994 to 2005, [[Bible prophecy]] scholar [[Hal Lindsey]] hosted a program on TBN titled ''International Intelligence Briefing'', in which Lindsey occasionally aired commentary segments criticizing [[Muslims]] and [[Islam]]. In December 2005, TBN pre-empted ''International Intelligence Briefing'' for the entire month. Lindsey accused the network of [[censorship]], saying, &quot;some at the network apparently feel that my message is too pro-[[Israel]] and too anti-Muslim.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hallindseyoracle.com/articles.asp?ArticleID=12130] {{Dead link|date=July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Paul Crouch issued a press release insisting that Lindsey's show was only pre-empted for [[Christmas]] programming,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tbn.org/index.php/7.html?nid=87 TBN - Trinity Broadcasting Network&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; but eventually admitted that TBN management was concerned that Lindsey &quot;placed [[Arabs]] in a negative light.&quot; Lindsey resigned from TBN on January 1, 2006, effectively cancelling ''International Intelligence Briefing''. However, one year later, Crouch and Lindsey reconciled and a new program, ''The Hal Lindsey Report'', premiered on the network.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tbnnetworks.org/affiliate/prArticle.php?ID=100 TBN Welcomes Popular Christian Author Hal Lindsey with New Weekly Program], TBN Networks, 22 January 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2011, TBN refused to rebroadcast an episode of [[Jack Van Impe]]'s weekly television program, in which the evangelist criticized pastors [[Rick Warren]] and [[Robert Schuller]] for participating in [[interfaith]] conferences alongside Muslim leaders and accused them of promoting &quot;[[Chrislam]]&quot;. Both Warren and Schuller denied the accusations.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.christianpost.com/news/pastors-answer-does-rick-warren-endorse-chrislam-52833/&lt;/ref&gt; Paul Crouch defended TBN's decision, stating that it is against network policy for personalities to attack each other on the air.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.tbn.org/announcements/files/JVI%20NEW%20RESPONSE%206-24-11b.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, Jack Van Impe Ministries announced that it would no longer air Van Impe's show on TBN.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.detnews.com/article/20110621/METRO/106210436/1361/Jack-Van-Impe-off-TBN-after-criticizing-two-pastors Jack Van Impe off TBN after criticizing two pastors], ''The Detroit News'', 21 June 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Travel the Road'' in Afghanistan===
TBN produces and airs a Christian [[reality television|reality]] show called ''[[Travel the Road]]'', which features missionaries Tim Scott and Will Decker in remote and often war-torn locations overseas in search of converts. In December 2008, the program attracted criticism from the [[Military Religious Freedom Foundation]] (MRFF), a watchdog group that looks for acts of [[religious discrimination]] in the [[United States military]]. The MRFF claimed that Scott and Decker were embedded with American troops stationed in [[Afghanistan]], despite the fact that, according to MRFF president Mikey Weinstein, the military exercises a &quot;complete prohibition of the proselytizing of any religion, faith, or practice...You see [Scott and Decker] wearing American helmets. It is obvious they were completely embedded.&quot; When [[ABC News]] contacted the [[U.S. Army]] in Afghanistan about Scott and Decker's alleged embed, which had taken place four years previously, they said that they no longer have the documentation of the missionaries' status with the troops.&lt;ref name=&quot;abcnews.go.com&quot;&gt;[http://abcnews.go.com/Nightline/FaithMatters/Story?id=6786701&amp;page=3 Missionaries Face Death, Criticism to Preach], ABCNews.com, 2 February 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

Scott defended the trip to Afghanistan, telling ABC, &quot;It wasn't like we were hiding in the back saying we're going to preach. [The military] knew what we were doing. We told them that we were born again Christians, we're here doing ministry, we shoot for this TV station and we want to embed and see what it was like. We were interviewing the chaplains and we talked to them. We spoke at the services and things like that. So we did do our mission being over there as far as being able to document what the soldiers go through, what it's like in Afghanistan. So I could say that we were on a secular mission as well as far as documenting. I would say we were news reporters as well, we were delivering news of what was actually happening there, but we were also there to document the Christian side.&quot; Scott argued that since the pair were acting as Christian journalists, they had the same right to cover the war in Afghanistan as secular networks.&lt;ref name=&quot;abcnews.go.com&quot;/&gt;

==See also==
* [[Christian Broadcasting Network]]
* [[Community Educational Television]]
* [[Glorystar]]
* [[Well to Hell hoax]]

==References==
{{Ibid|date=June 2010}}
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
*{{Official website|http://www.tbn.org}}
*[http://www.charitynavigator.org/index.cfm?bay=search.summary&amp;orgid=4574 Income Statement] from [[Charity Navigator]]
*[http://www.ministrywatch.com/profile/trinity-broadcasting-network.aspx Summary Report] from [[Ministry Watch]]
*[http://www.ohiolink.edu/etd/send-pdf.cgi?miami1154624326 Modern Day Heroes of Faith], an analysis of technology and religion on TBN.

{{TBN|state=collapsed}}
{{programs}}
{{Broadcast Television}}

[[Category:Trinity Broadcasting Network| ]]
[[Category:American television networks]]
[[Category:Evangelicalism]]
[[Category:Christian media companies]]
[[Category:Political organizations in the United States]]
[[Category:Religious media]]
[[Category:Religious television stations in the United States]]
[[Category:Christian television networks]]
[[Category:Gospel music media]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1973]]
[[Category:Companies based in Costa Mesa, California]]

[[fr:Trinity Broadcasting Network]]
[[id:TBN]]
[[it:Trinity Broadcasting Network]]
[[pt:Trinity Broadcasting Network]]</text>
      <sha1>h8prpcufh6qz842s05qhtrn3bpruiu0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
