<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Virgin Records</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>93767</id>
    <revision>
      <id>518939665</id>
      <parentid>515516894</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-20T23:12:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ZéroBot</username>
        <id>11969601</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>r2.7.1) (Robot: Adding [[ro:Virgin Records]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17621">{{Refimprove|date=December 2008}}
{{infobox record label
 | image = [[Image:Virgin Records.svg]]
 | parent = [[Universal Music Group]]
 | founded = {{start-date|1972}}
 | founder = [[Richard Branson]]
 | status = &lt;!--Leave blank unless &quot;Inactive&quot; or &quot;Defunct&quot;--&gt;
 | distributor = Virgin Music Group (in the U.S.)&lt;br&gt;[[EMI]]
 | genre = Various
 | country = United Kingdom
 | url = [http://www.virginrecords.com/ virginrecords.com]
}}
'''Virgin Records''' is a British [[record label]] founded by English entrepreneur [[Richard Branson]], Simon Draper, and [[Nik Powell]] in 1972. The company grew to be a worldwide music phenomenon, with platinum performers such as [[Roy Orbison]], [[Devo]], [[Genesis (band)|Genesis]], [[Keith Richards]], [[Janet Jackson]], [[Culture Club]], [[Simple Minds]], [[Lenny Kravitz]], [[The Smashing Pumpkins]], [[Mike Oldfield]], and more on their list of artists.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books/about/Virgin.html?id=reg8NAAACAAJ ''Virgin: A History of Virgin Records''] by Terry Southern, URL accessed 6 July 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; It was later sold to [[Thorn EMI]] in 1992. Its American operations were merged with [[Capitol Records]] in 2007 to create the [[Capitol Music Group]]. 

==Kraut- and prog-rock origins==
[[Image:virginrecordlogo.jpg|left|200 px|thumb|Virgin logo designed by [[Roger Dean (artist)|Roger Dean]] for the fledgling Virgin Records label]]
Branson and Powell had initially run a small record shop called ''Virgin Records and Tapes'' on [[Notting Hill Gate]], London, specialising particularly in &quot;[[krautrock]]&quot; imports, and offering bean bags and free vegetarian food for the benefit of customers listening to the music on offer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last = Lott | first = Tim | title = The day my music died  | publisher = [[The Guardian]] | date = 26 March 2004 | url = http://books.guardian.co.uk/departments/generalfiction/story/0,6000,1177956,00.html | accessdate = 2007-09-17 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 
After making the shop into a success, they turned their business into a fully fledged record label. The name '''Virgin''', according to Branson (in his autobiography), arose from [[Tessa Watts]], a colleague of his, when they were brainstorming business ideas. She suggested Virgin - as they were all new to business - like &quot;virgins&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.inc.com/magazine/19871101/6069_pagen_2.html ''Then Came Branson''] by Erik Larson at Inc Magazine Online, Nov 1, 1986, URL accessed 7 July 2011&lt;/ref&gt;  The original Virgin logo (known to fans as the &quot;Gemini&quot; or &quot;Twins&quot; logo) was designed by English artist and illustrator [[Roger Dean (artist)|Roger Dean]]: a young naked woman in mirror image with a large long-tailed serpent and the word &quot;Virgin&quot; in Dean's familiar script. A variation on the logo was used for the spin-off [[Caroline Records]] label.

The first release on the label was the [[progressive rock]] album ''[[Tubular Bells]]'' by multi-instrumentalist [[Mike Oldfield]] in 1973, for which the fledgling label garnered unprecedented acclaim.&lt;ref name=&quot;timeline&quot;&gt;[http://www.google.com/search?client=safari&amp;rls=en&amp;q=simon+draper+virgin+records&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;oe=UTF-8#q=%22virgin+records%22+company+history&amp;hl=en&amp;client=safari&amp;rls=en&amp;prmd=ivns&amp;tbs=tl:1&amp;tbo=u&amp;ei=m04WTpC8EY72swO-u8TsDQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=timeline_result&amp;ct=title&amp;resnum=11&amp;ved=0CGUQ5wIwCg&amp;bav=on.2,or.r_gc.r_pw.&amp;fp=47420160db229f25&amp;biw=970&amp;bih=772 ''Google Timeline''] URL accessed 6 July 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; This was soon followed by some notable krautrock releases, including electronic breakthrough album ''[[Phaedra (album)|Phaedra]]'' by  [[Tangerine Dream]] (which went Top 10), and ''[[The Faust Tapes]]'' and ''[[Faust IV]]'' by [[Faust (band)|Faust]]. ''The Faust Tapes'' album retailed for 49p (the price of a 7&quot; single) and as a result allowed this relatively unknown band to reach number 12 in the album charts{{Citation needed|reason=no UK top 40 chartings for artists named Faust as per everyhit.com|date=March 2012}}. Other early albums include [[Gong (band)|Gong]]'s ''[[Flying Teapot (album)|Flying Teapot (Radio Gnome Invisible, Pt. 1)]]'', which [[Daevid Allen]] has been quoted as having never been paid for.{{Citation needed|reason=no mention of this on Daevid Allen, Gong, or album articles|date=January 2010}}

==Post-punk rebranding==
{{Unreferenced section|date=September 2009}}
Although Virgin was initially one of the key labels of English and European progressive rock, the 1977 signing of the [[Sex Pistols]] (who had already been signed and then dropped by both [[EMI Records|EMI]] and [[A&amp;M Records|A&amp;M]]) reinvented the label as a new-wave outpost, a move that plunged the record company into the mainstream of the punk rock era.&lt;ref name=&quot;timeline&quot;/&gt; Under the guidance of [[Tessa Watts]], Virgin's Head of Publicity (and later, also Director of Production), the Pistols rocketed the label to success.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.transatlanticrecords.com/biography.html ''Nathan Joseph - Renaissance Man''] by Transatlantic Records at Transatlantic Records Online, URL accessed 2 June 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly afterwards, the Notting Hill record shop (above which the label's office was located) was raided by police for having a window display of the Sex Pistols' album ''[[Never Mind the Bollocks, Here's the Sex Pistols]]'' in the window. Afterwards they signed other new wave groups: [[Boxer (band)|Boxer]], [[Culture Club]], [[Fingerprintz]], [[Gillan]], [[Holly and the Italians]], [[Human League]], [[Magazine (band)|Magazine]], [[The Motors]], [[Penetration (band)|Penetration]], [[The Ruts]], [[Shooting Star (band)|Shooting Star]], [[Simple Minds]], and [[XTC]].

After experimenting with several alternate short-lived Virgin label designs in 1975 and 1976, the current Virgin logo (known informally as &quot;the scrawl&quot;) was created in 1978, commissioned by Simon Draper, then managing director of Virgin Records Limited.  Brian Cooke of Cooke Key Associates commissioned a graphic designer to produce a stylised signature.  The logo was first used on Mike Oldfield's ''[[Incantations (album)|Incantations]]'' album in 1978 and by the Virgin Records label exclusively until gradually other parts of the Virgin Group adopted it, including [[Virgin Atlantic Airlines]].

==Subsidiary labels==

'''Caroline Records''' was a budget label used from 1973 to 1977.  The name and logo were later used for some American editions of Virgin records in the 1980s and 1990s.

'''[[Front Line (record label)|Front Line Records]]''' (or '''Virgin's Front Line''') was a label for issuing Jamaican and English reggae music from 1978 to approximately 1987.  It became an actual label name in 1978 when it succeeded a category of Virgin albums and singles marketed as &quot;The Front line Series&quot; which went back to 1976, when a reggae compilation album titled ''The Front Line'' was issued on Virgin.  Front Line artists included [[U-Roy]], [[U Brown]], [[The Mighty Diamonds]], [[Keith Hudson]], [[Althea and Donna]], [[Jah Lloyd]], [[Johnny Clarke]], [[The Gladiators (band)|The Gladiators]], [[Peter Tosh]], [[I Roy]], [[Tappa Zukie]], [[Sly Dunbar]], [[The Twinkle Brothers]], [[Prince Far I]], [[Big Youth]], [[The Abyssinians]], [[Culture]], [[Gregory Isaacs]] and [[Linton Kwesi Johnson]].

A short-lived associated label, '''[[Dindisc Records]]''', had [[Orchestral Manoeuvres in the Dark]] and [[The Monochrome Set]] during its brief existence (1980–1981), after which its recordings became part of Virgin's catalogue.

In 1983 Virgin purchased [[Charisma Records]], renaming it '''Charisma/Virgin''', then later '''Virgin/Charisma''', before folding the label in 1986 and transferring its remaining artists to Virgin.  In the process they acquired [[Genesis (band)|Genesis]] and comedy group [[Monty Python]].  The Charisma label was reactivated in the U.S. in 1990 and enjoyed success with signings such as [[Maxi Priest]], [[Right Said Fred]], [[38 Special (band)|38 Special]] and [[Enigma (musical project)|Enigma]]. When this Charisma label was retired in 1992, all of its artists were, as before, transferred to Virgin.

In 1987, '''Venture Records''' was created for new age and modern classical artists including [[Klaus Schulze]], who had been associated with Virgin since the early 1970s. (Virgin had distributed UK editions of his German albums since 1974, and he had almost been signed as a Virgin artist in 1976, but the deal was cancelled after a conflict between Virgin and his German label.)

==American editions==

The Virgin label was distributed in the USA by Atlantic from 1973 to 1975.  During this period, 14 albums were issued.  All had been previously issued in the UK on Virgin, although one album, ''[[Marjory Razorblade]]'' by Kevin Coyne, was truncated from a 20-song double album to an 11-song single album.

Beginning with Mike Oldfield's ''[[Ommadawn]]'' album in 1975, American distribution switched to [[Columbia Records]].  Columbia was unwilling to release all Virgin artists, and so many were licenced to other labels: [[Epic Records|Epic]] (the sister company of Columbia) ([[Mike Oldfield]] (in the 1980s), [[Culture Club]], [[Holly and the Italians]] and Shooting Star), [[Atlantic Records|Atlantic]] ([[Julian Lennon]]), [[A&amp;M Records|A&amp;M]] (UB40, Human League, Simple Minds, Breathe), [[Warner Bros. Records|Warner Bros.]] (Sex Pistols), and [[RSO Records|RSO]] (XTC).  Some of these records had a small Virgin logo added to the regular company design on the label.
One of Virgin's and Epic's biggest acts of the 1980s was Culture Club.

In 1978, Virgin set up U.S. operations first in New York on Perry Street under [[Atlantic Records|Atlantic]] distribution, and then moved operations to New Jersey along with a short-lived subdivision called '''Virgin International''', handled by independent New Jersey-based distributor [[Jem Records]].  Virgin International used mainly for progressive rock artists with a smaller following in the USA, including reissues of earlier Virgin / Atlantic albums such as ''[[Hergest Ridge]]'' by Mike Oldfield, and ''[[Fish Rising]]'' by Steve Hillage, which Columbia chose not to reissue.  Virgin International also issued albums by some of Virgin's reggae artists, including [[Gregory Isaacs]].  At the same time, Virgin releases distributed by Columbia continued, distribution returning to Atlantic (later WEA) in 1980, at which time Virgin International ceased operations.

In 1986, Virgin Records opened up another American division, '''Virgin Records America'''. Its first release was the debut album by [[Cutting Crew]] which included the hit single &quot;[[I Just Died In Your Arms]]&quot;. Other Virgin America signings included [[Camper Van Beethoven]], [[Bob Mould]], [[Warren Zevon]], [[Paula Abdul]], [[T'Pau (band)|T'pau]], [[Ziggy Marley &amp; The Melody Makers]], [[Redhead Kingpin and the F.B.I.|Redhead Kingpin &amp; The F.B.I.]], [[Neneh Cherry]], [[Steve Winwood]] and Hindsight. Virgin Records America's releases were distributed by [[Warner Music Group|WEA]] again by [[Atlantic Records]] until 1992.

Another American company called '''Caroline Records''' co-existed during this time.  Caroline records rarely mentioned a connection with Virgin, and some UK and European Virgin albums that were distributed internationally (instead of being manufactured in each country) named Caroline as their American distributor.  Some Caroline records bore the label name '''Caroline Blue Plate'''.

==Canadian editions==

The first Canadian editions were distributed by WEA, and were parallel issues of the same early 14 albums issued in the USA by Virgin/Atlantic.

In 1975, distribution transferred to Columbia (as it had in the USA), but the following year distribution was transferred again to [[Polydor Records]] (which changed its yes to [[Polygram Records|Polygram]] by 1980), and issued a different and larger selection of records from what was being issued in the USA.  Canadian editions of the Dindisc label were issued as Dindisc/Virgin.  Virgin's Canadian division arranged to have Canadian artists [[Martha and the Muffins]] and [[Nash the Slash]] signed to Dindisc in the UK as well; both artists had releases in Canada and the UK on Dindisc.

In 1983, an independent '''Virgin Records Canada Inc.''' company was created, three years before a similar move occurred in the USA.  From this time onward, Virgin Canada used unique label designs not seen in other countries: a red label with five horizontal bars across the top and an extra-large &quot;scrawl&quot; logo from 1983 to 1985, followed by a purple label with round logo up to 1992 when Virgin was acquired internationally by EMI.

==Purchase by Thorn EMI==
Virgin Records was sold by Branson to [[Thorn EMI]] in June 1992 for a reported US$1 billion (around £560 million) [http://www.virgin.com/aboutvirgin/allaboutvirgin/thewholestory/default.asp?era=199][http://ec.europa.eu/comm/competition/mergers/cases/index/m4.html#m_202], with a special non-competition clause that would prevent Branson from founding another recording company during the five years following the agreement (see the final paragraph in  [http://europe.eu.int/comm/competition/mergers/cases/decisions/m202_en.pdf  E.U. Merger Decision IV/M202 of 27.04.1992]{{Dead link|date=December 2010}}). It now faces competition from Branson's new label: [[V2 Records]]. Branson sold Virgin Records to fund [[Virgin Atlantic Airways]] which at that time was coming under intense anti-competitive pressure from [[British Airways]]. (In 1993 BA settled a libel action brought by Branson, giving him £500,000 and a further £110,000 to his airline).

After being acquired by [[Thorn EMI]], Virgin launched several subsidiaries like [[Real World Studios|Realworld Records]], [[Innocent Records]], blues specialty label [[Point Blank Records]], and [[Hut Records]], and continued signing new and established artists like [[Korn]], [[A Fine Frenzy]], [[30 Seconds to Mars]], [[Tina Turner]], [[Depeche Mode]], [[Beenie Man]], [[The Rolling Stones]], [[Spice Girls]], [[The Smashing Pumpkins]], [[We Are Scientists]], [[Darren Hayes]], [[The Kooks]], [[Lenny Kravitz]], [[Captain Beefheart]], [[Meat Loaf]], [[Placebo (band)|Placebo]], [[Janet Jackson]] (contract ended in 2006), [[Daft Punk]], [[My Favorite Highway]], [[Does It Offend You, Yeah?]], [[Massive Attack]], [[The Future Sound of London]], [[Blur (band)|Blur]] (US), [[The Chemical Brothers]], [[Gorillaz]], [[Paula Abdul]] (contract ended in 1999), [[Brooke Allison]], [[The Red Jumpsuit Apparatus]], [[The Almost]], [[Mariah Carey]] (contract ended in 2002), [[N.E.R.D.]], [[Laura Marling]], [[Swami (band)|Swami]], [[RBD]], [[Thalía]] and [[Priscilla Renea]]. In 2000, Virgin opened a country music division, Virgin Nashville, where then country newcomer [[Chris Cagle]] recorded his debut album ''[[Play It Loud (Chris Cagle album)|Play It Loud]]'', which was later released through sister label [[Capitol Nashville]] after the country division shut down after one year.

==Merger==
{{Main|Capitol Music Group}}
Capitol Records and Virgin Records were merged in 2007 to create [[Capitol Music Group]] after a massive restructuring of EMI Group Ltd.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rapbasement.com/content/view/2380/35/ Capitol Records Merges With Virgin | Rap | Rap Basement&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Stepping down as chief executive of Capitol Records was Andy Slater, with Jason Flom, former executive of Virgin, taking the reins as Chairman and CEO of the newly created company.

==Virgin Music international companies==
[[EMI]] international companies directly operate Virgin Records imprint divisions known as &quot;Virgin Music&quot; in many countries, including Germany, France, and the UK. Most of these markets previously operated standalone &quot;Virgin Records&quot; labels before being merged and consolidated into their national [[EMI]] companies in the early part of the twenty-first century when [[EMI Group]] businesses underwent drastic restructuring.

==See also==
*[[List of record labels]]
*[[Virgin Group]]
*[[Virgin Records artists]]
*[[Virgin Schallplatten]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.virginrecords.com Official Web Site]
*[http://www.hitquarters.com/index.php3?page=search.php3&amp;artistsearch=&amp;relation=+&amp;genre=+&amp;country=+&amp;freesearch=Virgin+Records&amp;search.x=53&amp;search.y=13 Virgin A&amp;R team contact list]
*[http://music.virgin.com/ Official Virgin Music Blog]
*[http://www.virginradio.co.uk/ Official Virgin Music News Channel], as well as the [http://www.virginradio.com/ international] and [http://virginradio.ca/ Canadian branches]
{{Virgin Records}}
{{Virgin Group}}

[[Category:Record labels established in 1972]]
[[Category:British record labels]]
[[Category:Virgin Records|*]]
[[Category:Rock record labels]]
[[Category:Pop record labels]]
[[Category:IFPI members]]
[[Category:Labels distributed by Universal Music Group]]

[[ar:فيرجن]]
[[be:Virgin Records]]
[[bg:Върджин Рекърдс]]
[[ca:Virgin Records]]
[[cs:Virgin Records]]
[[da:Virgin Records]]
[[es:Virgin Records]]
[[fa:ویرجین رکوردز]]
[[fr:Virgin Records]]
[[gl:Virgin Records]]
[[ko:버진 레코드]]
[[it:Virgin Records]]
[[ka:Virgin Records]]
[[sw:Virgin Records]]
[[lv:Virgin Records]]
[[lt:Virgin Records]]
[[nl:Virgin Records]]
[[ja:ヴァージン・レコード]]
[[no:Virgin Records]]
[[nn:Virgin Records]]
[[pms:Virgin Records]]
[[pl:Virgin Records]]
[[pt:Virgin Records]]
[[ro:Virgin Records]]
[[ru:Virgin Records]]
[[simple:Virgin Records]]
[[sk:Virgin Records]]
[[fi:Virgin Records]]
[[sv:Virgin Records]]
[[th:เวอร์จินเรเคิดส์]]
[[tr:Virgin Records]]
[[uk:Virgin Records]]
[[zh:維京唱片]]</text>
      <sha1>1qsmyre2okqedsprsa8s8sp62g7rndl</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
