<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Development hell</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>310331</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521144084</id>
      <parentid>521143742</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-03T02:00:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>76.10.122.252</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Examples */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10296">In the jargon of the media industry, &quot;'''development hell'''&quot; (or &quot;'''development limbo'''&quot;) is a period during which a film or other project is trapped in [[development (film)|development]]. A [[film]], [[television program]], [[screenplay]], [[computer program]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Interactive development: The new hell |last=Marx |first=Andy |journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]] |location=New York |date=February 28, 1994 |volume=354 |issue=4 |page=1 }}&lt;/ref&gt; concept, or idea stranded in development hell takes an especially long time to start [[film production|production]], or never does.

The film industry buys [[film rights|rights]] to many popular novels, video games, and comics, but it may take years for such properties to be successfully brought to the cinema, and often with considerable changes to the plot, characters, and general tone.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=How My Novel Was Almost 'Developed' Into Oblivion |first=Warren |last=Adler |newspaper=[[New York Times]] |date=October 3, 1999 |page=AR11 |url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F50E11F93D5A0C708CDDA90994D1494D81 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Overview==
In the case of a film or television screenplay, the [[screenwriter]] may have successfully sold a screenplay to a certain set of [[Film producer|producer]]s or [[film studio|studio]] executives, but then new executives assigned to the project may raise objections to all the scripts and casting decisions they oversee, mandating rewrites and recasting. As [[film director|director]]s and [[actor]]s become &quot;attached&quot; to the project, further rewrites and recasting may be done, to accommodate the needs of the new talents involved in the project. Should the project fail to meet their needs, they might leave the project or simply refuse to complete it, causing further rewrites and recasting. At any point, a project may be forced to begin again from scratch. 

It may also be the case that the screenwriters have an issue with the final rights agreement after signing an option, but aren't happy with the full terms, and the project may go in endless circles until either the situation is resolved, or the project is abandoned.

When a film is in development but never receives the necessary production funds, another studio may do a [[turnaround (filmmaking)|turnaround]] and produce the film to make it successful. An example of this is when [[Columbia Pictures]] developed but dropped ''[[E.T. the Extra-Terrestrial]]''. [[Universal Pictures]] picked up the movie and made it a success.  If a studio completely abandons a film project, the costs are written off as part of the studio's overhead.&lt;ref&gt;McDonald, Paul &amp; Wasko, Janet (2008) ''Hollywood Film Industry''. Malden, MA: Blackwell Publishing. p. 54&lt;/ref&gt;

Sometimes studios or producers will deliberately halt production in order to stop competition on a different project, or to ensure that people invested will be available for other projects that the studio prefers.

This process can last for months or years. More often than not, a project trapped in this state will be abandoned by all interested parties or canceled outright. As Hollywood starts ten times as many projects as are released, many scripts will end up in this state.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Cover Story: Writers Paid for Movies Never Made,&quot; Spillman, Susan. USA Today. McLean, Va.: January 16, 1991. pg. D1&lt;/ref&gt; This happens most often with projects that have multiple interpretations and affect several points of view.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Dept. of development hell,&quot; Kerrie Mitchell. Premiere. (American edition). New York: February 2005.Vol.18, Iss. 5; pg. 40&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Books Into Movies: Part 2,&quot; Warren, Patricia Nell. Lambda Book Report. Washington: April 2000.Vol.8, Iss. 9; pg. 9. (Best selling novel [[The Front Runner]] has spent over 25 years in development hell)&lt;/ref&gt;

During a potential writer's strike in 2001, major studios wanted to spend less time and energy bidding on longer-term developments such as film rights to books and focus more on buying projects that would immediately receive a [[green-light]].  They were more interested in developing the big budget action thrillers and high concept comedies written by established and credible writers.  Studio executives put all uncertain scripts and pitches on the shelves during this time to avoid taking a chance on a long-term development and only wanted projects that were ready to go into production.

Some studios and producers still bought film rights to books but only ones that had successful sales. Examples of this are [[Dino De Laurentiis]]' $9 million acquisition of Thomas Harris' ''[[Hannibal (novel)|Hannibal]]'' and [[Miramax]] purchasing [[Mario Puzo]]'s ''[[Omertà (novel)|Omertà]]'' for $2-$3 million.&lt;ref&gt;Lyons, Charles (2001) Development Hell freezing over? ''Variety'' 382(1). 1-71&lt;/ref&gt;

==Related concepts==
In [[Software release life cycle|software development]], unreleased products that have been in long-term development are considered a type of [[vaporware]]. In film and television screenplay, unreleased products that have been in long-term development are considered as &quot;vaporfilm&quot;.  The [[anime]] [[OVA]] adaptation of ''[[Alien Nine]]'' has been cited by fans and critics as an example of &quot;vaporfilm&quot; because of its unfinished status after four episodes (extending halfway through the manga) and its hiatus since 2002.

==Examples==
* '''''Akira''''': Warner Bros. has been developing a [[Akira (film)#Live action film|live-action American version]] of the [[Akira (film)|animated film ''Akira'']] for years; as of January 6, 2012, Warners has &quot;shut down&quot; production for the fourth time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url =http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/heat-vision/akira-production-shut-down-budget-warner-bros-278729|title='Akira' Production Offices Shut Down As Warner Bros. Scrutinizes Budget (Exclusive)|date=2012-01-05|first=Borys|last=Kit|work=The Hollywood Reporter}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''''[[AI: Artificial Intelligence]]'''''.
* '''''[[Atuk]]'''''.
* A live-action film version of the [[anime]] ''[[Bleach (manga)|Bleach]]''.{{fact|date=July 2012}}
* A live-action film version of the anime ''[[Cowboy Bebop]],'' originally slated for 2011 release.
* '''''[[Beverly Hills Cop III]]''''': Went through multiple script revisions, including a treatment that had Axel Foley teaming up with a Scotland Yard detective to be played by [[Sean Connery]].
* '''''[[Dragon's Lair]]'''''. According to [[Don Bluth]] and [[Gary Oldman]], there would have been a movie adaption of the 1983 video game. Bluth and Oldman are looking for funding to put filming for this movie in production.
* '''''[[Duke Nukem Forever]]''''', a video game which had many development issues leading to over a decade's delay before its release.
* '''''[[Escape from New York]]''''' remake
* '''''[[Freddy vs. Jason]]''''', a 2003 crossover of the ''[[Friday the 13th (franchise)|Friday the 13th]]'' and ''[[A Nightmare on Elm Street (franchise)|Nightmare on Elm Street]]'': Plans for the film dated back to 1987.
* '''''[[Ghostbusters III]]''''' has been in development hell since 1989. 
* '''''[[Godzilla (1998 film)|Godzilla]]'''''.{{fact|date=July 2012}}
* '''''[[Independence_Day_(film)#Sequels|Independence Day 2]]''''', also known as ''ID4-2'', has been in development hell since 1997.
* '''''[[Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull]]''''', remained in development hell since 1989 and was released in 2008. 
* '''''[[Les Misérables (2012 film) |Les Misérables]]''''': A [[Les Misérables (2012 film)|film adaptation]] of [[Les Misérables (musical)|the stage musical]] began in the late 1980s. After the musical's 25th anniversary concert, producer Cameron Mackintosh announced that the film had resumed development, to be released Christmas 2012. 
* '''''[[Mad Max 4: Fury Road]]''''', originally meant to follow 1985's [[Mad Max Beyond Thunderdome]], began filming in 2012.
* '''''[[Superman Lives]]''''', a scrapped [[Reboot (fiction)|reboot]] of the [[Superman film series]], very loosely based on the comic book storyline &quot;[[The Death of Superman]]&quot;.
* '''''[[The_Postman_(film)|The Postman]]''''': Author [[David Brin]] described the ten-year long effort to get his novel produced as a film. In the process, the screenplay went through so much revision as to barely resemble the book, even leading writers to &quot;borrow&quot; from the book they were supposed to be creating as a film.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
 |url=http://www.davidbrin.com/postmanmovie.htm
 |title=The Postman: An Impression by the Author of the Original Novel
 |first=David |last=Brin |author-link=David Brin
 |year=1998 |accessdate=January 15, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''''[[Watchmen (2009 film)|Watchmen]]''''': Film rights to the 1986–1987 comic book series were first acquired in 1986; [[Production of Watchmen#Failed projects|numerous versions]] were attempted, with a film adaptation finally released in 2009.
* [[Rocky_Horror_sequels_and_other_media#Untitled_stage_sequel|An unnamed sequel]] to [[Richard O'Brien]]'s ''[[The Rocky Horror Show]]'' has had multiple false starts. Planned to be a stage play like its predecessor, with the possibility of becoming a film if the play had become a financial hit.
*'''''[[Sadness (video game)]]''''': One of the earliest Titles for the [[Nintendo Wii]], cancelled 2010.
*'''''[[Jurassic_Park_(franchise)#Jurassic_Park_IV|Jurassic Park 4]]'''''
*'''''[[Hulk (2003 film)|Hulk]]''''': Development began as far back in 1990's. Released on 2003.
*'''''[[Soul_(series)#Film|Soul Calibur: The Movie]]''''': a film adoption of the [[Soul_(series)|Soul Calibur]] video game series.
*'''''[[Star Wars Episode VII]]''''', planned since 1975, it remained in devolopment hell beginning in 1983. After later being ababdoned, the project was brought brought back in 2012 for a 2015 release. 
*Valve Software's [[Half-Life_2:_Episode_Three#Episode_Three|Half-Life 2: Episode 3]] was announced in 2007 to be released around December 2008. In 2012 Valve stated that Half-Life 3 will be released, but did not provide a release date.

==See also==
* [[Turnaround (filmmaking)]]
* [[Vaporware]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Development Hell}}
[[Category:Film production]]
[[Category:Vaporware]]

[[it:Development hell]]
[[ru:Производственный ад]]
[[sv:Development hell]]</text>
      <sha1>d1rvzxxdq2ee27het0zep884liz3cng</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
