<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Disc jockey</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8683</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521132292</id>
      <parentid>521098833</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-03T00:10:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Versageek</username>
        <id>146418</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[Help:Reverting|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/164.92.9.25|164.92.9.25]] ([[User talk:164.92.9.25|talk]]) to last version by Famspear</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="29786">{{redirect4|DJ|DJs}}
{{redirect|Deejay|a person who verbalizes with music in the Jamaican style|Deejay (Jamaican)}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}

[[Image:DJ SPANGDAHLEM AIR BASE.jpg|right|thumb|[[Club Eifel]]'s [[DJ Blaze]] performing at the 2009 Air Force Ball.]]

A '''disc jockey''', also known as '''DJ''', is a person who plays recorded music for an audience. Originally, &quot;disc&quot; (sometimes spelled &quot;disk&quot;, although this is now uncommon) referred to [[phonograph]] records, not the later [[Compact Disc]]s. Today, the term includes all forms of music playback, no matter the medium.

There are several types of disc jockeys. Radio DJs or [[radio personality|radio personalities]] introduce and play music that is broadcast on [[AM broadcasting|AM]], [[FM broadcasting|FM]], [[shortwave]], [[Digital radio|digital]], or [[internet radio]] stations. Club DJs select and play music in [[Bar (establishment)|bars]], [[nightclub]]s, or [[discothèque]]s, or at parties or [[rave]]s, or even in [[stadium]]s. [[Hip hop]] disc jockeys select and play music using multiple [[Phonograph|turntable]]s, often to back up one or more [[master of ceremonies|MC]]s, and they may also do turntable [[scratching]] to create percussive sounds. In [[reggae]], the DJ (deejay) is a vocalist who [[rapping|raps]], &quot;[[Deejay (Jamaican)|toasts]]&quot;, or chats over pre-recorded rhythm tracks while the individual choosing and playing them is referred to as a [[selector (disc jockey)|selector]].&lt;ref&gt;Last Night a DJ Saved My Life, written by Bill Brewster and Frank Broughton, Published by Headline, updated 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Mobile DJs travel with portable sound systems and play recorded music at a variety of events. According to a 2012 study there are approximately 1¼ million professional disk jockeys in the world.&lt;ref&gt;[http://djrankings.org/#?about_rankings The Official Global DJ Rankings]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Equipment and techniques==

[[File:DJ Set Up.jpg|thumb|Technics 1200 MK2, Technics 1210 MK2 &amp; Pioneer DJM-500 shown in a common DJ configuration]]

[[File:Spooky.jpg|thumb|left|A DJ at Sundance Film Festival 2003]]	
Club DJ equipment may consist of:
*Sound recordings in a DJ's preferred medium (for example, [[vinyl record]]s, Compact Discs, computer media files, etc.);
*A combination of two devices (or only one, if playback is digital) to play sound recordings, for alternating back and forth to create a continuous playback of music (for example, record players, Compact Disc players, computer media players such as an [[MP3]] player, etc.);
*A multiple [[Music sequencer|Sequencer]] which can mix MIDI tracks with Digital Audio;
*A [[sound reinforcement system|sound system]] for amplification or broadcasting of the recordings (for example, portable audio system, [[PA system]]) or a radio broadcasting system;
*A [[DJ mixer]], which is an  (usually 2- or 4-channel) [[Mixing console|audio mixer]] usually equipped with a [[Fade (audio engineering)|crossfader]] used to smoothly go from one song to another, using two or more playback devices;
*[[Headphones]], used to listen to one recording while the other recording is being played to the audience, or to listen to both recordings simultaneously; and
*Optionally, a [[microphone]], so that the DJ can introduce songs and speak to the audiences.
Other equipment could or can be added to the basic DJ setup (above), providing unique sound manipulations. Such devices include, but are not limited to:
*Electronic [[effects unit]]s ([[Delay (audio effect)|delay]], [[reverb]], [[octave]], [[Equalization (audio)|equalizer]], [[chorus effect|chorus]], etc.). Some club DJs use a subharmonic synthesizer effect which either doubles low frequencies with energy added an octave lower or synthesizes harmonics such that the impression of a very low bass sound is added to the mix.
*A computerised performance system, which can be used with [[vinyl emulation software]] to manipulate digital files on the computer in real time.
*Multi-stylus headshells, which allow a DJ to play different grooves of the same record at the same time.
*Special [[DJ digital controller]] hardware that can manipulate digital files on a PC or laptop;
*[[Sampler (musical instrument)|Sampler]]s, sequencers, electronic musical keyboards (synthesizers), or [[drum machine]]s.
*A Midi Controller used to trigger different aspects of DJ Software, such as Serato Scratch Live, Virtual Dj, and Traktor.
Several techniques are used by DJs as a means to better mix and blend recorded music. These techniques primarily include the [[cueing (playback)|cueing]], [[Equalization (audio)|equalization]], and [[audio mixing (recorded music)|audio mixing]] of two or more sound sources. The complexity and frequency of special techniques depends largely on the setting in which a DJ is working. Radio DJs are less likely to focus on music-mixing procedures than club DJs, who rely on a smooth transition between songs using a range of techniques.

Club DJ turntable techniques include [[beatmatching]], [[phrasing (DJ)|phrasing]], and [[slip-cueing]] to preserve energy on a dancefloor. [[Turntablism]] embodies the art of [[cutting (music)|cutting]], [[beat juggling]], [[scratching]], [[Needle drop (DJing)|needle drop]]s, [[phase shifting]], [[back spinning]], and more to perform the transitions and overdubs of [[Sampling (music)|samples]] in a more creative manner (although turntablism is often considered a use of the turntable as a [[musical instrument]] rather than a tool for blending recorded music). Professional DJs may use [[harmonic mixing]] to choose songs that are in compatible musical keys.{{Citation needed|date=July 2012}}

Recent advances in technology in both DJ hardware and software can provide assisted or automatic completion of some traditional DJ techniques and skills. Examples include [[phrasing (DJ)|phrasing]] and [[beatmatching]], which can be partially or completely automated by utilizing DJ software that performs automatic [[Synchronization]] of sound recordings, a feature commonly labelled &quot;Sync&quot;. Most [[DJ mixer]]s now include a beat-counter which analyzes the tempo of an incoming sound source and displays its tempo in [[Beats Per Minute]] (BPM), which may assist with [[beatmatching]] analog sound sources. Software has also been written to assist with the identification of musical keys for use in [[harmonic mixing]], which analyze computer media files for musical content and automatically determine the musical key.{{Citation needed|date=July 2012}}

==History==
{{update-section|The history section of this article needs to be updated, starting with the end of 1999 to the start of 2011.|date=May 2012}}

===19th century to 1920s===
In 1892, [[Emile Berliner]] began commercial production of his gramophone records, the first disc records to be offered to the public. In 1906, [[Reginald Fessenden]] transmitted the first audio radio [[Broadcasting|broadcast]] in history also playing the first record, that of a [[contralto]] singing [[William Handel|Handel's]] ''Largo'' from ''[[Xerxes (opera)|Xerxes]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Brewster|first=Bill|authorlink=Bill Brewster (DJ)|title=Last Night a DJ Saved my Life|publisher=Headline|pages=29|year=2006|isbn=0-7553-1398-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The world's first radio disc jockey was Ray Newby, of Stockton, California. In 1909, at 16 years of age, Newby began regularly playing records on a small [[spark transmitter]] while a student at Herrold College of Engineering and Wireless, located in San Jose, California, under the authority of radio pioneer [[Charles Herrold|Charles &quot;Doc&quot; Herrold]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Secret&quot;&gt;Ray Newby appearance on [[CBS]]' ''[[I've Got a Secret]]'', 27 September 1965. Secret listed as: &quot;'I was the world's first radio disc jockey' (in 1909).&quot; Rebroadcast on the [[Game Show Network]] on 22 May 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Bay Area Radio Museum|url=http://www.sfradiomuseum.com/schneider/radio113.shtml |title= Doc Herrold and Ray Newby |accessdate=21 May 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote|We used popular records at that time, mainly Caruso records, because they were very good and loud; we needed a boost... we started on an experimental basis and then, because this is novel, we stayed on schedule continually without leaving the air at any time from that time on except for a very short time during World War I, when the government required us to remove the antenna... Most of our programming was records, I'll admit, but of course we gave out news as we could obtain it...&lt;ref name=&quot;Secret&quot; /&gt;|Ray Newby, ''I've Got a Secret'' (1965)}}

By 1910, regular radio broadcasting had started to use &quot;live&quot; as well as prerecorded sound. In the early radio age, content typically included comedy, drama, news, music, and sports reporting. The on-air announcers and programmers would later be known as disc jockeys. In the 1920s, [[juke joint]]s became popular as places for dancing and drinking to recorded jukebox music. In 1927, [[Christopher Stone (broadcaster)|Christopher Stone]] became the first radio announcer and programmer in the [[United Kingdom]], on the [[BBC]] radio station.

===1930s–1950s===
In 1935, American radio commentator [[Walter Winchell]] coined the term &quot;disc jockey&quot; (the combination of ''disc'', referring to the disc records, and ''jockey'', which is an operator of a machine) as a description of radio announcer [[Martin Block]], the first announcer to become a star. While his audience was awaiting developments in the [[Lindbergh kidnapping]], Block played records and created the illusion that he was broadcasting from a ballroom, with the nation’s top dance bands performing live. The show, which he called ''Make Believe Ballroom'', was an instant hit. The term &quot;disc jockey&quot; appeared in print in ''[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]'' in 1941.&lt;ref name=Fisher&gt;{{cite book | last = Fisher | first = Marc | authorlink = | coauthors = | title = Something in the Air | publisher = Random House | date = | location = | pages = 13| url = | doi =  | isbn = 978-0-375-50907-0 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Alan Freed WJW-AM promotional photo.jpg|thumbnail|right|Disc jockey Alan Freed]]
Prior to this, most music heard on radio was live; most radio stations had an orchestra or band on the payroll.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.americahurrah.com/NBC/RadioCity.htm |title=NBC's Radio City, San Francisco|author=Roddy, Bill|publisher=Roddy, Bill|accessdate=26 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.richsamuels.com/nbcmm/joeg.html |title=The NBC Chicago Orchestra|author=Samuels, Rich|publisher=Samuels, Rich|accessdate=26 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Federal Communications Commission]] also clearly favored live music, providing accelerated license approval to stations promising not to use any recordings for their first three years on the air.&lt;ref name=Fisher/&gt; Many noted recording artists tried to keep their recorded works off the air by having their records labeled as not being legal for airplay. It took a Federal court ruling in 1940 to establish that a recording artist had no legal right to control the use of a record after it was sold.&lt;ref name=Fisher/&gt;

In 1943, [[Jimmy Savile]] launched the world's first DJ dance party by playing [[jazz]] records in the upstairs function room of the [[Loyal Order of Ancient Shepherds]] in [[Otley]], [[England]]. In 1947, he claims to have become the first DJ to use twin turntables for continuous play, and in 1958 became a radio DJ at [[Radio Luxembourg (English)|Radio Luxembourg]]. Also in 1947, the Whiskey à Go-Go nightclub opened in [[Paris, France]], considered to be the world's first commercial discothèque, or disco (deriving its name from the French word meaning a nightclub where the featured entertainment is recorded music rather than an on-stage band). [[Regine]] began playing on twin turntables there in 1953. Discos began appearing across Europe and the United States.

The postwar period coincided with the rise of the radio disc jockey as a celebrity separate from the radio station, also known as a &quot;[[radio personality]]&quot;. In the days before station-controlled playlists, the DJ often followed their personal tastes in music selection. DJs also played a role in exposing rock and roll artists to large, national audiences. While at [[WJMO|WERE (1300&amp;nbsp;AM)]] in [[Cleveland, Ohio]], DJ [[Bill Randle]] was one of the first to introduce [[Elvis Presley]] to radio audiences in the northeastern US.&lt;ref name=&quot;Curtis&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Curtis|first=James M. |title=Rock eras: interpretations of music and society, 1954-1984|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=F0xAUXaBYqoC&amp;pg=PA42&amp;dq=disc+jockey#v=onepage&amp;q=disc%20jockey&amp;f=false|year=1987|publisher=Popular Press|isbn=978-0-87972-369-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Notable [[United States|US]] radio disc jockeys of the period include [[Alan Freed]], [[Wolfman Jack]], [[Kasey Kasem]],&lt;ref name=&quot;SissonZacher2007&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=Richard Sisson|author2=Christian K. Zacher|author3=Andrew Robert Lee Cayton|title=The American Midwest: an interpretive encyclopedia|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=n3Xn7jMx1RYC&amp;pg=PA636|accessdate=13 October 2011|year=2007|publisher=Indiana University Press|isbn=978-0-253-34886-9|pages=636–}}&lt;/ref&gt; and their [[England|British]] counterparts such as the [[BBC]]'s Brian Matthew, Radio London's [[John Peel]], and later in the 60s, [[Radio Caroline]]'s [[Tony Blackburn]].&lt;ref name=&quot;SterlingKeith2004&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=Christopher H. Sterling|author2=Michael C. Keith|author3=Communications Museum of Broadcast|title=Encyclopedia of radio|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Z4XJQD4O_TkC&amp;pg=PA375|accessdate=13 October 2011|year=2004|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|isbn=978-1-57958-249-4|pages=375–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Freed is commonly referred to as the &quot;father of rock and roll&quot; due to his promotion of the music and his introduction of the phrase &quot;rock and roll&quot; on radio in the early 1950s. Freed also made a practice of presenting music by African-American artists rather than cover versions by white artists on his radio program. Freed's career ended when it was shown that he had accepted [[payola]], a practice that was highly controversial at the time, resulting in his being fired from his job at [[WABC (AM)|WABC]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Altschuler2003&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Glenn C. Altschuler|title=All shook up: how rock 'n' roll changed America|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=lMyC2FndXwkC&amp;pg=PA152|accessdate=13 October 2011|date=16 July 2003|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-513943-3|pages=152–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1950s, American radio DJs would appear live at &quot;sock hops&quot; and &quot;platter parties&quot; and assume the role of a human jukebox. They would usually play 45-rpm records, featuring hit singles on one turntable while talking between songs. In some cases, a live drummer was hired to play beats between songs to maintain the dance floor. In 1955, [[Bob Casey (DJ)|Bob Casey]], a well-known &quot;sock hop&quot; DJ, brought the two-turntable system to the U.S. Throughout the 1950s, payola continued to be a problem and one result of the payola scandal was tighter control of the music by station management. The [[Top 40]] format emerged, where popular songs are played repeatedly.

In the late 1950s, [[Reggae sound system|sound system]]s, a new form of public entertainment, were developed in the [[ghetto]]s of [[Kingston, Jamaica]]. Promoters, who called themselves DJs, would throw large parties in the streets that centered on the disc jockey, called the &quot;selector,&quot; who played dance music from large, loud [[PA systems]] and bantered over the music with a boastful, rhythmic chanting style called &quot;[[Deejay (Jamaican)|toasting]]&quot;. These parties quickly became profitable for the promoters, who would sell admission, food, and alcohol, leading to fierce competition between DJs for the biggest sound systems and newest records.

===1960s and 1970s===
In the mid-1960s, nightclubs and discothèques continued to grow in Europe and the United States. Specialized DJ equipment, such as [[Rudy Bozak]]'s classic CMA-10-2DL mixer, began to appear on the market. In 1969, American club DJ [[Francis Grasso]] popularized beatmatching at [[New York]]'s Sanctuary nightclub. Beatmatching is the technique of creating seamless transitions between records with ''matching'' ''beats'', or tempos. Grasso also developed [[slip-cueing|slip-cuing]], the technique of holding a record still while the turntable is revolving underneath, releasing it at the desired moment to create a sudden transition from the previous record. (This technique had long been used in radio.)

By 1968, the number of dance clubs started to decline; most American clubs either closed or were transformed into clubs featuring live bands. Neighborhood block parties that were modelled after Jamaican sound systems gained popularity in Europe and in the [[borough]]s of [[New York City]].

In 1973, [[Jamaica|Jamaican-born]] [[DJ Kool Herc]], widely regarded as the &quot;father of [[hip-hop culture]],&quot; performed at block parties in his [[The Bronx|Bronx]] neighborhood and developed a technique of mixing back and forth between two identical records to extend the rhythmic instrumental segment, or ''[[break (music)|break]]''. Turntablism, the art of using turntables not only to play music but to manipulate sound and create original music, began to develop.

In 1974, [[Technics (brand)|Technics]] released the first [[Technics SL-1200|SL-1200]] turntable, which evolved into the SL-1200 MK2 in 1979—which, as of the early-2010s, remains an industry standard for DJing. In 1974, German [[electronic music]] band [[Kraftwerk]] released the 22-minute song &quot;Autobahn,&quot; which takes up the entire first side of that LP. Years later, Kraftwerk would become a significant influence on [[hip hop music|hip-hop]] artists such as [[Afrika Bambaataa]] and [[house music]] pioneer [[Frankie Knuckles]]. During the mid-1970s, [[Hip hop music|Hip-hop music]] and culture began to emerge, originating among urban [[African American]]s and [[Latino]]s in New York City. The four main elements of [[hip hop|Hip Hop culture]] are [[graffiti]], DJing, [[breakdance|breakdancing]], and [[Rapping|MCing (rapping)]].

In the mid-1970s, the soul-funk blend of dance pop known as disco took off in the mainstream pop charts in the [[United States]] and [[Europe]], causing discothèques to experience a rebirth. Unlike many late-1960s clubs, which featured live bands, discothèques used the DJ's selection and mixing of records as the entertainment. In 1975, [[record pool]]s began, providing disc jockeys access to newer music from the industry in an efficient method.

In 1975,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rane.com/dj/gwtheo.html Rane.com]&lt;/ref&gt; hip-hop DJ [[Grand Wizard Theodore]] invented the scratching technique by accident. In 1976, American DJ, editor, and producer [[Walter Gibbons]] remixed &quot;Ten Percent&quot; by [[Double Exposure (band)|Double Exposure]], one of the earliest commercially released 12&amp;Prime; singles (aka &quot;maxi-single&quot;). In 1979, the [[Sugar Hill Gang]] released &quot;[[Rapper's Delight]]&quot;, the first hip-hop record to become a hit. It was also the first real breakthrough for [[sampling (music)|sampling]], as the bassline of [[Chic (band)|Chic]]'s &quot;[[Good Times (Chic song)|Good Times]]&quot; laid the foundation for the song.

In 1977, [[Saratoga Springs, NY]] disc jockey Tom L. Lewis introduced the Disco Bible (later renamed Disco Beats), which published hit disco songs listed by beats per minute (tempo), as well as by either artist or song title. Billboard ran an article on the new publication, and it went national relatively quickly. The list made it easier for beginning DJs to learn how to create seamless transitions between songs without dancers having to change their rhythm on the dance floor. Today, DJs can find the beats per minute of songs in the BPM List.

===1980s===
In 1981, the cable television network [[MTV]] was launched, originally devoted to music videos, especially popular rock music. The term &quot;[[video jockey]]&quot;, or VJ, was used to describe the fresh-faced youth who introduced the music videos. In 1982, the demise of disco in the mainstream by the summer of 1982 forced many nightclubs to either close or change entertainment styles, such as by providing MTV-style video dancing or live bands. Released in 1982, the song &quot;Planet Rock&quot; by DJ [[Afrika Bambaataa]] was the first hip-hop song to feature [[synthesizer]]s. The song melded [[Electro music|electro]] hip-hop beats influenced by [[Yellow Magic Orchestra]] with the melody from Kraftwerk's &quot;Trans-Europe Express.&quot; In 1982, the [[Compact Disc]] reached the public market in Asia, and early the following year in other markets. This event is often seen as the &quot;Big Bang&quot; of the [[digital audio]] revolution.

In the early 1980s, NYC disco DJ [[Larry Levan]], known for his eclectic mixes, gained a cult following, and the [[Paradise Garage]], the nightclub at which he spun, became the prototype for the modern dance club where the music and the DJ were showcased. Around the same time, the disco-influenced electronic style of dance music called [[house music]] emerged in Chicago. The name was derived from the [[Warehouse Club]] in [[Chicago]], where resident DJ [[Frankie Knuckles]] mixed old disco classics and Eurosynth pop. House music is essentially disco music with electronic drum machine beats. The common element of most house music is a 4/4 beat generated by a [[drum machine]] or other electronic means (such as a sampler), together with a solid (usually also electronically generated) synth [[bassline]]. In 1983, [[Jesse Saunders]] released what some consider the first house music track, &quot;On &amp; On.&quot; The mid-1980s also saw the emergence of [[New York house|New York Garage]], a house music hybrid that was inspired by Levan's style and sometimes eschewed the accentuated high-hats of the [[Chicago house]] sound.

During the mid-1980s, [[techno music]] emerged from the [[Detroit]] club scene. Being geographically located between Chicago and New York, Detroit techno artists combined elements of Chicago house and New York garage along with European imports. Techno distanced itself from disco's roots by becoming almost purely electronic with synthesized beats. In 1985, the Winter Music Conference started in [[Fort Lauderdale, Florida|Fort Lauderdale]] Florida and became the premier electronic music conference for dance music disc jockeys.

In 1985, TRAX Dance Music Guide was launched by [[American Record Pool]] in Beverly Hills. It was the first national DJ-published music magazine, created on the [[Macintosh]] computer using extensive music market research and early desktop publishing tools. In 1986, &quot;[[Walk This Way]]&quot;, a rap/rock collaboration by [[Run DMC]] and [[Aerosmith]], became the first hip-hop song to reach the Top 10 on the [[Billboard Hot 100]]. This song was the first exposure of hip-hop music, as well as the concept of the disc jockey as band member and artist, to many mainstream audiences. In 1988, ''DJ Times'' magazine was first published. It was the first US-based magazine specifically geared toward the professional mobile and club DJ.

Starting in the mid-1980s, the wedding and banquet business changed dramatically with the introduction of DJ music, replacing the bands that had been the norm. Bandleaders, like Jerry Perell and others, started DJ companies, such as NY Rhythm DJ Entertainers. Using their knowledge of audience participation, MC charisma, and &quot;crowd-pleasing&quot; repertory selection, the wedding music industry became almost all DJ while combining the class and elegance of the traditional band presentation. New DJs as well as bandleaders with years of experience and professionalism transformed the entire industry.

===1990s===
During the early 1990s, the rave scene built on the [[acid house]] scene. The rave scene changed dance music, the image of DJs, and the nature of promoting. The innovative marketing surrounding the rave scene created the first [[superstar]] DJs who established marketable &quot;brands&quot; around their names and sound. Some of these celebrity DJs toured around the world and were able to branch out into other music-related activities. During the early 1990s, the Compact Disc surpassed the gramophone record in popularity, but gramophone records continued to be made (although in very limited quantities) into the 21st century—particularly for club DJs and for local acts recording on small regional labels.

In 1991, ''Mobile Beat'' magazine, geared specifically toward mobile DJs, began publishing. In 1992, [[MPEG]] which stands for the [[Moving Picture Experts Group]], released The MPEG-1 standard, designed to produce reasonable sound at low bit rates. The lossy compression scheme MPEG-1 Layer-3, popularly known as [[MP3]], later revolutionized the digital music domain. In 1993, the first [[internet]] &quot;radio station&quot;, Internet Talk Radio, was developed by [[Carl Malamud]]. Because the audio was relayed over the internet, it was possible to access internet radio stations from anywhere in the world. This made it a popular service for both amateur and professional disc jockeys operating from a personal computer.

In 1998, the first MP3 digital audio player was released, the Eiger Labs MPMan F10. [[Final Scratch]] debuted at the BE Developer Conference, marking the first digital DJ system to allow DJs control of MP3 files through special time-coded [[vinyl record]]s or CDs. While it would take sometime for this novel concept to catch on with the &quot;die hard Vinyl DJs&quot;, This would soon become the first step in the new Digital DJ revolution. Manufacturers joined with [[computer DJ]]ing pioneers to offer professional endorsements, the first being Professor Jam (aka William P. Rader), who went on to develop the industry's first dedicated computer DJ convention and learning program, the &quot;CPS (Computerized Performance System) DJ Summit&quot;, to help spread the word about the advantages of this emerging technology.

In 1999, [[Shawn Fanning]] released [[Napster]], the first of the massively popular [[peer-to-peer file sharing]] systems. During this period, the AVLA (Audio Video Licensing Agency) of Canada announced an MP3 DJing license, administered by the Canadian Recording Industry Association. This meant that DJs could apply for a license giving them the right to perform publicly using music stored on a hard drive, instead of having to cart their whole CD collections around to their gigs.

==Photo gallery==
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Dj2can_club_dj.jpg|Club Sevillas's DJ 2CAN performing in a local club in the Inland Empire of California.
Image:Romina Cohn @ Sobremonte (Mar del Plata, Argentina) Photo by dj Lucho Randazzo.JPG|Romina Cohn @ Sobremonte (Mar del Plata, Argentina)
Image:JasonJollinsPachaBsAs.jpg|[[Jason Jollins]] performing at [[Pacha]], [[Buenos Aires]]
Image:JeffMills.jpg|[[Jeff Mills]], live with 3 CD and a Roland TR-909 drum machine, 2007
Image:Ferry_Corsten.jpg|Trance DJ [[Ferry Corsten]] in Canada
Image:DJ HAZEL2.JPG|DJ Hazel
Image:Dj Markus.png|DJ Markus radio DJ (exDFM)
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
* [[Computer DJ]]
* [[Digital DJ licensing]]
* [[Spelling of disc|Disc or disk (spelling)]]
* [[Live PA]]
* [[Mixset]]
* [[Record collecting]]
* [[Seoul World DJ Festival]]
* [[Stage lighting]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
* Assef, Claudia (2000). ''Todo DJ Já Sambou: A História do Disc-Jóquei no Brasil''. São Paulo: Conrad Editora do Brasil. ISBN 85-87193-94-5.
* Brewster, Bill, and Frank Broughton (2000). ''Last Night a DJ Saved My Life: The History of the Disc Jockey''. New York: Grove Press. ISBN 0-8021-3688-5 (North American edition). London: Headline. ISBN 0-7472-6230-6 (UK edition).
* Broughton, Frank, and Bill Brewster. ''How to DJ Right: The Art and Science of Playing Records''. New York: Grove Press, 2003.
* Graudins, Charles A. ''How to Be a DJ''. Boston: Course Technology PTR, 2004.
* Lawrence, Tim (2004). ''Love Saves the Day: A History of American Dance Music Culture, 1970–1979 ''. Duke University Press. ISBN 0-8223-3198-5.
* Miller, Paul D. aka DJ Spooky, ''Sound Unbound: Writings on DJ Culture and Electronic Music'', MIT Press 2008. ISBN 0-262-63363-9 ISBN 978-0-262-63363-5.
* Poschardt, Ulf (1998). ''DJ Culture''. London: Quartet Books. ISBN 0-7043-8098-6.
* Zemon, Stacy. ''The Mobile DJ Handbook: How to Start &amp; Run a Profitable Mobile Disc Jockey Service'', Second Edition. St. Louis: Focal Press, 2002

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
{{Commons category|Deejays|Disc jockey}}
*{{dmoz|Arts/Music/DJs/|DJs}}

{{DJing}}
{{Hip hop}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Disc Jockey}}
[[Category:DJing]]
[[Category:Disco]]
[[Category:Audio mixing]]
[[Category:Radio presenters| ]]
[[Category:Broadcasting occupations]]
[[Category:Media occupations]]
[[Category:Occupations in music]]
[[Category:DJing| ]]

[[ar:دي جي]]
[[az:Disk jokey]]
[[be:Дыджэй]]
[[be-x-old:Дыджэй]]
[[bg:Диджей]]
[[bs:Disc jockey]]
[[ca:Discjòquei]]
[[cs:Diskžokej]]
[[da:Dj]]
[[de:DJ]]
[[es:Disc jockey]]
[[eo:Diskĵokeo]]
[[eu:Disk Jockey]]
[[fa:دی‌جی]]
[[fo:DJ]]
[[fr:Disc jockey]]
[[ko:디스크 자키]]
[[hy:Դիջեյ]]
[[hr:Disc Jockey]]
[[id:Disjoki]]
[[is:Plötusnúður]]
[[it:Disc jockey]]
[[he:DJ]]
[[ka:დისკ-ჟოკეი]]
[[kk:Ди-джей]]
[[la:Discimpositor]]
[[lv:Diskžokejs]]
[[lb:DJ]]
[[lt:Diskžokėjus]]
[[hu:Lemezlovas]]
[[mk:Диџеј]]
[[ms:DJ]]
[[nl:Diskjockey]]
[[ja:ディスクジョッキー]]
[[no:Disc jockey]]
[[nn:DJ]]
[[mhr:Диджей]]
[[pl:DJ]]
[[pt:DJ]]
[[ro:Disc jockey]]
[[ru:Диджей]]
[[sq:Disc jockey]]
[[simple:Disc jockey]]
[[sk:Diskotekár]]
[[sl:Didžej]]
[[sr:Диск-џокеј]]
[[sh:Disk džokej]]
[[fi:DJ]]
[[sv:DJ]]
[[th:ดีเจ]]
[[tr:DJ]]
[[uk:Ді-джей]]
[[vi:DJ]]
[[yi:דידזשיי]]
[[zh:唱片騎師]]</text>
      <sha1>9ee5s862968pexh0658ado35jq56exw</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
