<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Rapping</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>25421</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520998716</id>
      <parentid>518631211</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T03:12:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ctomarctus</username>
        <id>3127847</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="38868">{{Redirect|Rap}}
{{Hatnote|&quot;MCing&quot; redirects here. For the hosting of events in general, see [[Master of Ceremonies]]. See also: [[Master of Ceremonies#Hip hop]].}}
{{about|rapping as a technique or activity|more information on the music genre|Hip hop music}}
{{pp-semi-indef}}{{pp-move-indef}}
'''Rapping''' (also known as '''emceeing''',{{sfn|Edwards|2009|p=xii}} '''MCing''',{{sfn|Edwards|2009|p=xii}} '''spitting (bars)''',{{sfn|Edwards|2009|p=3}} or '''rhyming'''{{sfn|Edwards|2009|p=81}}) refers to &quot;spoken or chanted rhyming lyrics&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Rapping&quot; definition, 2009, ''The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language, Fourth Edition'', [[Houghton Mifflin Company]], [http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/Rapping. Dictionary.reference.com]&lt;/ref&gt; The art form can be broken down into different components, as in the book ''[[How to Rap]]'' where it is separated into “content”, “flow” ([[rhythm]] and [[rhyme]]), and “delivery”.{{sfn|Edwards|2009|p=x}} Rapping is distinct from [[spoken word poetry]] in that it is performed in time to a beat.&lt;ref name=&quot;Attridge, Derek 2002, p. 90&quot;/&gt;{{sfn|Edwards|2009|p=63}}

Rapping is a primary ingredient in [[hip hop music]] and [[reggae]], but the phenomenon predates hip hop culture by centuries. It can also be found in [[alternative rock]] such as that of [[Cake (band)|Cake]] and the [[Red Hot Chili Peppers]]. Rapping is also used in [[Kwaito|Kwaito music]], a genre that originated in  [[Johannesburg]], [[South Africa]] and is composed of hip hop elements. Rapping can be delivered over a [[beats (music)|beat]] or without accompaniment. Stylistically, rap occupies a gray area among speech, prose, poetry, and song. The use of the word to describe quick speech or repartee long predates the musical form,&lt;ref&gt;''Oxford English Dictionary''&lt;/ref&gt; meaning originally &quot;to hit&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://dictionary.reference.com/search?q=rap| title = Dictionary.com| accessdate = February 2, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The word had been used in [[British English]] since the 16th century, and specifically meaning &quot;to say&quot; since the 18th. It was part of the [[African American Vernacular English|African American dialect of English]] in the 1960s meaning &quot;to converse&quot;, and very soon after that in its present usage as a term denoting the musical style.&lt;ref&gt;[[William Safire|Safire, William]]. (1992). On language; The rap on hip-hop. ''[[The New York Times Magazine]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; Today, the terms &quot;rap&quot; and &quot;rapping&quot; are so closely associated with hip hop music that many use the terms interchangeably.

==History==
{{see also|African American music|Music of the United States|History of poetry|Jamaican music|Roots of hip hop|Old school hip hop|Talking blues}}
[[Image:Memphis jugband.jpg|frame|right|The [[Memphis Jug Band]], an early blues group, whose lyrical content and rhythmic singing predated rapping.]]
{{Listen||type=music|header = The roots of rapping
   |filename=DeepDowninMyHeart.ogg
   |title=Deep Down in My Heart
   |description=A [[spiritual (music)|spiritual]] performed by W. M. Givens in Darien, Georgia in 1926.
   |filename2=DollarMamie.ogg
   |title2=Dollar Mamie
   |description2=A Southern [[work song]] performed by Judge &quot;Bootmouth&quot; Tucker and Alexander &quot;Neighborhood&quot; Williams in 1939.
   |filename3=
   |title3=Small Talk at 125th and Lennox
   |description3=[[Gil Scott Heron]]'s spoken word poetry has had a significant influence on hip hop through its political and socially conscious lyrics.
}}

===Etymology===
Rap etymologically means &quot;fast read&quot; or &quot;spoke fast&quot;. It may be from a shortening of [[repartee]].&lt;ref&gt;''rap''[5, noun] Webster's Third New International Dictionary, Unabridged&lt;/ref&gt;

===Roots===
{{Refimprove section|date=February 2012}}
Rapping can be traced back to its African roots. Centuries before [[hip hop music]] existed, the [[griot]]s of [[West Africa]] were delivering stories rhythmically, over [[drum]]s and sparse instrumentation. Such connections have been acknowledged by many modern artists, modern day &quot;griots&quot;, [[spoken word]] artists, mainstream news sources, and academics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/3622406.stm| title = BBC News: Africa| accessdate = December 21, 2005 | date=September 2, 2004| first=Lawrence| last=Pollard}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://rap.about.com/mbiopage.htm| title = About.com: Rap| accessdate = December 21, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.pbs.org/theblues/classroom/deftradition.html| title = PBS lesson plan on the blues| accessdate = December 21, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.yale.edu/ynhti/curriculum/units/2001/3/01.03.08.x.html#b| title = Yale University Teachers Association| accessdate = December 21, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Blues music]], [[Origins of the blues|rooted]] in the [[work songs]] and [[spiritual (music)|spirituals]] of [[Slavery in the United States|slavery]] and influenced greatly by West African musical traditions, was first played by blacks, and later by some whites, in the [[Mississippi Delta]] region of the United States around the time of the [[Emancipation Proclamation]]. Grammy-winning blues musician/historian [[Elijah Wald]] and others have argued that the blues were being rapped as early as the 1920s.&lt;ref name=&quot;r12&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.elijahwald.com/hipblues.html| title = Hip Hop and Blues| accessdate = December 21, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.yazoorecords.com/2018.htm| title = The Roots of Rap| accessdate = December 21, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; Wald went so far as to call hip hop &quot;the living blues.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;r12&quot; /&gt; [[Jazz]], which developed from the blues and other African-American and European musical traditions and originated around the beginning of the 20th century, has also influenced hip hop and has been cited as a precursor of hip hop. Not just jazz music and lyrics but also [[Jazz poetry]]. According to John Sobol, the jazz musician and poet who wrote ''Digitopia Blues'', rap &quot;bears a striking resemblance to the evolution of jazz both stylistically and formally.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;digitopia&quot;&gt;Sobol, John. (2002). ''Digitopia Blues''. Banff Centre Press. ISBN 978-0-920159-89-7&lt;/ref&gt;
One of the main influences on Hip Hop artists was [[James Brown]]. James Brown is credited for inventing funk music in the middle '60s. The characteristic funk drum beat is the most common rhythm used for rap music. Two of the earliest recordings which have a funk beat and lyrics which are rhymed in rhythm over this type of beat were released by comedian [[Pigmeat Markham]], &quot;Here Come the Judge&quot; which was released in 1968 by the Chess label and in 1969 another song about running numbers called &quot;Who Got The Number?&quot;.
&quot;Here Comes the Judge&quot; peaked at number 19 on the [[Billboard charts]]. While it was primarily a comical song about a Judge and his courtroom it is also notable for the political lyrics &quot;I'm goin' to Paris to stop this war&quot; and &quot;I had a chat with [[Ho Chi Minh]]&quot; both social commentary references about wanting to go to the Paris Peace Accord negotiations to stop the war in Vietnam.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

The spoken word [[jazz poetry]] of the United States was also a predecessor for [[beat poetry]], as well as the rapping in hip hop music. [[Gil Scott-Heron]], a [[Jazz poetry|jazz poet]]/musician who wrote and released such seminal songs as &quot;[[The Revolution Will Not Be Televised]]&quot;, &quot;H2OGate Blues Part 2: We Beg Your Pardon America,&quot; and &quot;Johannesberg,&quot; has been cited as an influence on many rappers. His collaborations with musician [[Brian Jackson (musician)|Brian Jackson]] (''[[Pieces of a Man]]'', ''[[Winter in America]]'') have been cited as major influences on hip hop, in terms of sound and lyrical style. Similar in style, the [[Last Poets]] who formed in 1969 recited political poetry over drum beats and other instrumentation, and were another predecessor for rap music. They released their debut album in 1970 reaching the top ten on the Billboard charts.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

Precursors also exist in non-African/African-American traditions, especially in vaudeville and musical theater. One such tradition is the [[patter song]] exemplified by [[Gilbert and Sullivan]] but that has origins in earlier Italian opera. &quot;Rock Island&quot;  from [[Meredith Willson|Meridith Wilson's]] &quot;[[The Music Man]]&quot; is wholly spoken by an ensemble of travelling salesmen, as are most of the numbers for British actor [[Rex Harrison]] in the 1964 [[Lerner and Loewe]] musical [[My Fair Lady]]. Glenn Miller's &quot;The Lady's in Love With You&quot; and &quot;The Little Man Who Wasn't There&quot; (both 1939), each contain distinctly rap-like sequences set to a driving beat. In musical theater, the term &quot;[[Ostinato#Vamp|vamp]]&quot; is identical to its meaning in Jazz, gospel, and funk, and it fulfills the same function. Semi-spoken music has long been especially popular in British entertainment, and such examples as David Croft's theme to the 1970s' sitcom [[Are You Being Served?]], the 1979 song [[Mickey (song)|Mickey]] as performed by [[Toni Basil]] in 1982, and the 1984 title song, &quot;[[One Night in Bangkok]]&quot; for the musical [[Chess (musical)|Chess]] have elements indistinguishable from modern rap. In the realm of classical music, semi-spoken music was popular stylized by composer [[Arnold Schoenberg]] as [[Sprechstimme]], and famously used in [[Ernst Toch|Ernst Toch's]] 1924 [[Geographical Fugue]] for spoken chorus and the final scene in [[Darius Milhaud|Darius Milhaud's]] 1915 ballet ''Les Choéphores''.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}} Although these probably did not have a direct influence on rap's development in the African American cultural sphere, they paved the way for acceptance of spoken word music in the media market. 

More directly related to the African American community were items like schoolyard chants and taunts, [[clapping games]],&lt;ref&gt;K. D. Gaunt, The games black girls play: learning the ropes from Double-dutch to Hip-hop (New York, NU., New York University Press, 2006)&lt;/ref&gt; [[Skipping-rope rhyme|jump-rope rhymes]], some with unwritten folk histories going back hundreds of years across many nationalities. Sometimes these items contain racially offensive lyrics.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.beachnet.com/~jeanettem/chants.html&lt;/ref&gt; A related area that is not strictly folklore is rhythmical [[cheering]] and [[cheerleading]] for military and sports.

During the mid-20th century, the musical culture of the Caribbean was constantly influenced by the concurrent changes in [[Music of the United States|American music]]. As early as 1956,&lt;ref&gt;Howard Johnson &amp; Jim Pines. (1982). Reggae – Deep Roots Music ''Proteus Books''.&lt;/ref&gt; [[deejay (Jamaican)|deejays]] were toasting (an African tradition of &quot;rapped out&quot; tales of heroism) over [[dub music|dubbed]] [[Jamaican]] beats. It was called &quot;rap&quot;, expanding the word's earlier meaning in the African-American community—&quot;to discuss or debate informally.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;r0&quot;&gt;The earlier meaning being &quot;a usage well established among African-Americans by the 1960s.&quot;, according to ''[[The American Heritage Dictionary]]'', 4th Edition.&lt;/ref&gt;

One of the first rappers in the beginning of the hip hop period, in the end of '70s, was also hip hop's first [[DJ]], [[Kool Herc]]. Herc, a Jamaican immigrant, started delivering simple raps at his parties, inspired by the Jamaican tradition of [[deejay (Jamaican)|toasting]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.daveyd.com/interviewkoolherc89.html| title = Davey D's Hip-Hop Corner| accessdate = December 20, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Old school rap===
[[Old school rap]] (1979–1984)&lt;ref&gt;David Toop, Rap Attack, 3rd. ed., London: Serpent's Tail, 2000. (p. 216) ISBN 978-1-85242-627-9&lt;/ref&gt; was &quot;easily identified by its relatively simple raps&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;allmusic.com&quot;&gt;[{{Allmusic|class=explore|id=style/d2926|pure_url=yes}} Allmusic.com]&lt;/ref&gt; according to [[Allmusic]], &quot;the emphasis was not on lyrical technique, but simply on good times&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;allmusic.com&quot;/&gt; one notable exception being [[Melle Mel]], who set the way for future rappers through his socio-political content and creative wordplay.&lt;ref name=&quot;allmusic.com&quot;/&gt;

===The golden age===
[[Golden age hip hop]] (cited as either just the late '80s&lt;ref&gt;Cheo H. Coker, [http://www.rollingstone.com/artists/slickrick/albums/album/103326/review/5945316/behind_bars &quot;Slick Rick: Behind Bars&quot;]{{dead link|date=May 2011}}, ''Rolling Stone'', March 9, 1995.&lt;/ref&gt; or the late 80s to early 90s&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes.com&quot;&gt;Jon Caramanica, [http://www.nytimes.com/2005/06/26/arts/music/26jon.html &quot;Hip-Hop's Raiders of the Lost Archives&quot;], ''New York Times'', June 26, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;) was the time period where hip-hop lyricism went through its most drastic transformation – writer William Jelani Cobb says &quot;in these golden years, a critical mass of mic prodigies were literally creating themselves and their art form at the same time&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Cobb, Jelani William, 2007, ''To the Break of Dawn'', NYU Press, p. 47.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Allmusic]] writes, &quot;rhymers like [[Public Enemy (group)|PE]]'s [[Chuck D]], [[Big Daddy Kane]], [[KRS-One]], and [[Rakim]] basically invented the complex wordplay and lyrical kung-fu of later hip-hop”.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;[{{Allmusic|class=explore|id=style/d12014|pure_url=yes}} Allmusic.com]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Golden age hip hop|golden age]] is considered to have ended around '93–'94, marking the end of rap lyricism's most innovative period.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

==Flow==
{{Listen|type=music|header=Rapping
   |filename=Planet_Rock.ogg
   |title=Planet Rock
   |description=Hip hop pioneer [[Afrika Bambaataa]] mixed [[electro music|electro]] with old school rapping and beats. Bambaataa, the DJ, is also the rapper in this song; the first rapping in hip hop was done from behind the turntables.
   |filename2=
   |title2=Niggas Bleed
   |description2=[[Notorious B.I.G.]] tells vivid stories about his everyday life as a criminal in [[Brooklyn]]. Note the constant changing up of the lyrical flow and cadence characteristic of [[new school hip hop]].
}}

&quot;Flow&quot; is defined as &quot;the rhythms and rhymes&quot;{{sfn|Edwards|2009}}{{sfn|Kool Moe Dee|2003|p=inside cover, 10, 17}}{{sfn|Krims|2001|p=48–49}} of a hip-hop song's lyrics and how they interact – the book ''[[How to Rap]]'' breaks flow down into [[rhyme]], [[rhyme scheme]]s, and [[rhythm]] (also known as [[cadence (music)|cadence]]).{{sfn|Edwards|2009|p=63-130}} 'Flow' is also sometimes used to refer to elements of the delivery ([[Pitch (music)|pitch]], [[timbre]], [[Loudness|volume]]) as well,{{sfn|Krims|2001|p=44}} though often a distinction is made between the flow and the delivery.{{sfn|Kool Moe Dee|2003|p=inside cover, 10, 17}}{{sfn|Edwards|2009}}

Staying on the beat is central to rap's flow{{sfn|Edwards|2009|p=63–79}} – many [[MC]]s note the importance of staying on-beat in ''[[How to Rap]]'' including [[Sean Price]], Mighty Casey, [[Zion I]], [[Vinnie Paz]], [[Fredro Starr]], [[Del The Funky Homosapien]], [[Tech N9ne]], [[People Under The Stairs]], [[Twista]], [[B-Real]], [[Mr Lif]], [[2Mex]], and [[Cage (rapper)|Cage]].{{sfn|Edwards|2009|p=63–79}}

[[MC]]s stay on-beat by stressing syllables in time to the four beats of the musical backdrop.&lt;ref name=&quot;Attridge, Derek 2002, p. 90&quot;&gt;Attridge, Derek, 2002, ''[http://www.google.com/books?id=UbALbvMiM6UC&amp;lpg=PR13&amp;ots=lZH9J8lFo0&amp;dq=Poetic%20Rhythm%3A%20An%20Introduction&amp;lr&amp;hl=iw&amp;pg=PR13#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Poetic Rhythm: An Introduction]'', Cambridge University Press, p. 90.&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Edwards|2009|p=71–72}} Poetry scholar [[Derek Attridge]] describes how this works in his book ''Poetic Rhythm'' – &quot;rap lyrics are written to be performed to an accompaniment that emphasizes the metrical structure of the verse&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Attridge, Derek 2002, p. 90&quot;/&gt; He says rap lyrics are made up of, &quot;lines with four stressed beats, separated by other syllables that may vary in number and may include other stressed syllables. The strong beat of the accompaniment coincides with the stressed beats of the verse, and the rapper organizes the rhythms of the intervening syllables to provide variety and surprise&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Attridge, Derek 2002, p. 90&quot;/&gt;

The same technique is also noted in the book ''[[How to Rap]]'', where diagrams are used to show how the lyrics line up with the beat – &quot;stressing a syllable on each of the four beats gives the lyrics the same underlying rhythmic pulse as the music and keeps them in rhythm... other syllables in the song may still be stressed, but the ones that fall in time with the four beats of a bar are the only ones that need to be emphasized in order to keep the lyrics in time with the music&quot;.{{sfn|Edwards|2009|p=72}}

===History of flow===
[[Old School Hip-Hop|Old School]] flows were relatively basic and used only few syllables per bar, simple rhythmic patterns, and basic rhyming techniques and [[rhyme scheme]]s.{{sfn|Krims|2001|p=44}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = {{Allmusic|class=explore|id=genre/d1|pure_url=yes}}|title = Allmusic| accessdate = December 22, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Melle Mel]] is cited as an [[Old School Hip-Hop|Old School]] MC who epitomizes the [[Old School Hip-Hop|Old School]] flow – [[Kool Moe Dee]] says, “from 1970 to 1978 we rhymed one way [then] Melle Mel, in 1978, gave us the new cadence we would use from 1978 to 1986{{sfn|Kool Moe Dee|2003|p=325}}... he’s the first emcee to explode in a new rhyme cadence, and change the way every emcee rhymed forever. [[Rakim]], [[Biggie]], and [[Eminem]] have flipped the flow, but [[Melle Mel]]’s downbeat on the two, four, kick to snare cadence is still the rhyme foundation all emcees are building on&quot;.{{sfn|Kool Moe Dee|2003|p=334}}

Artists and critics often credit [[Rakim]] with creating the overall shift from the more simplistic [[Old School Hip-Hop|Old School]] flows to more complex flows near the beginning of Hip Hop’s [[New school hip hop|new school]]{{sfn|Kool Moe Dee|2003|p=224}}  – [[Kool Moe Dee]] says, “any emcee that came after 1986 had to study [[Rakim]] just to know what to be able to do{{sfn|Kool Moe Dee|2003|p=324}}... [[Rakim]], in 1986, gave us flow and that was the rhyme style from 1986 to 1994{{sfn|Kool Moe Dee|2003|p=325}}... from that point on, anybody emceeing was forced to focus on their flow”.{{sfn|Kool Moe Dee|2003|p=326}} [[Kool Moe Dee]] explains that before [[Rakim]], the term ‘flow’ wasn’t widely used – “[[Rakim]] is basically the inventor of flow. We were not even using the word flow until [[Rakim]] came along. It was called rhyming, it was called cadence, but it wasn’t called flow. [[Rakim]] created flow!”{{sfn|Kool Moe Dee|2003|p=328}} He adds that while [[Rakim]] upgraded and popularized the focus on flow, “he didn’t invent the word”.{{sfn|Kool Moe Dee|2003|p=324}}

[[Kool Moe Dee]] states that [[Biggie]] introduced a newer flow which “dominated from 1994 to 2002”,{{sfn|Kool Moe Dee|2003|p=325}} and also says that [[Method Man]] was “one of the emcees from the early to mid-’90s that ushered in the era of flow... [[Rakim]] invented it, [[Big Daddy Kane]], [[KRS-One]], and [[Kool G Rap]] expanded it, but [[Biggie]] and [[Method Man]] made flow the single most important aspect of an emcee’s game”.{{sfn|Kool Moe Dee|2003|p=206}} He also cites [[Craig Mack]] as an artist who contributed to developing flow in the ‘90s.{{sfn|Kool Moe Dee|2003|p=39}}

Music scholar Adam Krims says, “the flow of MCs is one of the profoundest changes that separates out new-sounding from older-sounding music... it is widely recognized and remarked that rhythmic styles of many commercially successful MCs since roughly the beginning of the 1990s have progressively become faster and more ‘complex’”.{{sfn|Krims|2001|p=44}} He cites “members of the [[Wu-Tang Clan]], [[Nas]], [[AZ (rapper)|AZ]], [[Big Pun]], and [[Ras Kass]], just to name a few”{{sfn|Krims|2001|p=49}} as artists who exemplify this progression.

[[Kool Moe Dee]] adds, “in 2002 [[Eminem]] created the song that got the first Oscar in Hip-Hop history [[Lose Yourself#Success and legacy|[Lose Yourself]]]... and I would have to say that his flow is the most dominant right now (2003)”.{{sfn|Kool Moe Dee|2003|p=325}}

===Styles===
There are many different styles of flow, with different terminology used by different people – [[stic.man]] of [[Dead Prez]] uses the following terms –
*“The Chant”, which he says is used by [[Lil Jon]] and [[Project Pat]]{{sfn|stic.man|2005|p=63}}
*“The Syncopated Bounce”, used by [[Twista]] and [[Bone Thugs N Harmony]]{{sfn|stic.man|2005|p=63}}
*“Straight Forward”, used by [[Scarface (rapper)|Scarface]], [[2Pac]], [[Melle Mel]], [[KRS-One]] circa [[Boogie Down Productions]] era, [[Too Short]], [[Jay-Z]], [[Ice Cube]], and [[Snoop Dogg]]{{sfn|stic.man|2005|p=63–64}}
*“The Rubik’s Cube”, used by [[Nas]], [[Black Thought]] of [[The Roots]], [[Common (artist)|Common]], [[Kurupt]], and [[Lauryn Hill]]{{sfn|stic.man|2005|p=64}}
*“2-5-Flow”, a [[pun]] of [[Kenya]]'s [[List of country calling codes|calling code]] &quot;+254&quot;, used by [[Camp Mulla]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://willpress.blogspot.com/2011/04/camp-mulla-cool-kids-on-edge-of-new.html Camp Mulla: Cool Kids on the Edge of A New Frontier?] Open Mic, April 29, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

Alternatively, music scholar Adam Krims uses the following terms –
*“sung rhythmic style”, used by [[Too Short]], [[Grandmaster Flash and The Furious Five]], and the [[Beastie Boys]]{{sfn|Krims|2001|p=50}}
*“percussion-effusive style”, used by [[B-Real]] of [[Cypress Hill]]{{sfn|Krims|2001|p=51}}
*“speech-effusive style”, used by [[Big Pun]]{{sfn|Krims|2001|p=51}}

===Rhyme===
MCs use many different rhyming techniques, including complex [[rhyme scheme]]s, as Adam Krims points out – “the complexity... involves multiple rhymes in the same rhyme complex (i.e. section with consistently rhyming words), [[internal rhyme]]s, [and] offbeat rhymes”.{{sfn|Krims|2001|p=49}} There is also widespread use of [[multisyllabic rhymes]], by artists such as [[Kool G Rap]],&lt;ref&gt;Shapiro, Peter, 2005, ''The Rough Guide To Hip-Hop, 2nd Edition'', Penguin, p. 213&lt;/ref&gt; [[Big Daddy Kane]], and [[Eminem]].

It has been noted that rap’s use of rhyme is some of the most advanced in all forms of poetry – music scholar Adam Bradley notes, “rap rhymes so much and with such variety that it is now the largest and richest contemporary archive of rhymed words. It has done more than any other art form in recent history to expand rhyme’s formal range and expressive possibilities”.&lt;ref&gt;Bradley, Adam, 2009, ''[[Book of Rhymes]]: The Poetics of Hip-Hop'', Basic Civitas Books, p. 51–52.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the book ''[[How to Rap]]'', [[Masta Ace]] explains how [[Rakim]] and [[Big Daddy Kane]] caused a shift in the way [[MC]]s rhymed: “Up until [[Rakim]], everybody who you heard rhyme, the last word in the sentence was the rhyming [word], the connection word. Then [[Rakim]] showed us that you could put rhymes within a rhyme... now here comes [[Big Daddy Kane]] — instead of going three words, he’s going multiple”.{{sfn|Edwards|2009|p=105}} ''[[How to Rap]]'' explains that &quot;rhyme is often thought to be the most important factor in rap writing... rhyme is what gives rap lyrics their musicality.{{sfn|Edwards|2009|p=xii}}

==Delivery/performance==
To successfully deliver a rap, a rapper must also develop vocal presence, [[enunciation]], and [[Vocal technique|breath control]]. Vocal presence is the distinctiveness of a rapper's voice on record. Enunciation is essential to a flowing rap; some rappers choose also to exaggerate it for comic and artistic effect. Breath control, taking in air without interrupting one's delivery, is an important skill for a rapper to master, and a must for any MC. An MC with poor breath control cannot deliver difficult verses without making unintentional pauses.

Raps are sometimes delivered with melody. West Coast rapper [[Egyptian Lover]] was the first notable MC to deliver &quot;sing-raps.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;r10&quot; /&gt; Popular rappers such as [[50 Cent]] and [[Ja Rule]] add a slight melody to their otherwise purely percussive raps whereas some rappers such as [[Cee-Lo Green]] are able to [[harmony|harmonize]] their raps with the beat. The Midwestern group Bone Thugs-n-Harmony was one of the first groups to achieve nationwide recognition for using the fast-paced, melodic and harmonic raps that are also practiced by [[Do or Die]], another Midwestern group. Another rapper that harmonized his rhymes was [[Nate Dogg]], a rapper part of the group 213. [[Rakim]] experimented not only with following the beat, but also with complementing the song's melody with his own voice, making his flow sound like that of an instrument (a saxophone in particular).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.maximumfun.org/blog/2006/07/rakim-allah-interview.html Rakim Allah Interview] – YoungAmerica, from Friday, July 7, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

The ability to rap quickly and clearly is sometimes regarded as an important sign of skill. In certain [[list of genres of hip hop|hip hop subgenres]] such as [[chopped and screwed]], slow-paced rapping is often considered optimal. The current record for fastest rapper is held by Spanish rapper Domingo Edjang Moreno, known by his alias Chojin, who rapped 921 syllables in one minute on December 23, 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.guinnessworldrecords.com/records/arts_and_media/music_feats_and_facts/fastest_rap_mc.aspx | title = Guinness World Records | accessdate = August 27, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Subject matter==
&quot;Party rhymes&quot;, meant to pump up the crowd at a party, were nearly the exclusive focus of old school hip hop, and they remain a staple of hip hop music to this day. In addition to party raps, rappers also tend to make references to love and sex. Love raps were first popularized by [[Spoonie Gee]] of the [[Treacherous Three]], and later, in the golden age of hip hop, [[Big Daddy Kane]], [[Heavy D]], and [[LL Cool J]] would continue this tradition.
Hip hop artists such as [[KRS One]], [[Hopsin]], [[Public Enemy (band)|Public Enemy]], [[Lupe Fiasco]], [[Mos Def]], [[Talib Kweli]], [[Jay-Z]], [[Nas]], [[The Notorious B.I.G.]], and [[dead prez]] are known for their sociopolitical subject matter. Their West Coast counterparts include [[Emcee Lynx]], [[The Coup]], [[Paris]], and [[Michael Franti]]. [[Tupac Shakur]] was also known for rapping about social issues such as [[police brutality]], [[teenage pregnancy]], and [[racism]].

Other rappers take a less critical approach to urbanity, sometimes even embracing such aspects as crime. [[Schoolly D]] was the first notable MC to rap about crime.&lt;ref name=&quot;r10&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Blow |first=Kurtis |authorlink=Kurtis Blow |coauthors=|date= |url=http://rhino.com/Features/liners/72851lin.html|title=Kurtis Blow Presents: The History of Rap, Vol. 1: The Genesis (liner notes)|work=Kurtis Blow Presents: The History Of Rap, Vol. 1: The Genesis|accessdate=May 14, 2006}}{{dead link|date=May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Early on [[KRS-One]] was accused of celebrating crime and a hedonistic lifestyle, but after the death of his DJ, [[Scott La Rock]], KRS-One went on to speak out against violence in hip hop and has spent the majority of his career condemning violence and writing on issues of race and class. [[Ice-T]] was one of the first rappers to call himself a &quot;playa&quot; and discuss guns on record, but his theme tune to the 1987 film ''[[Colors]]'' contained warnings against joining gangs. [[Gangsta rap]], made popular largely because of [[N.W.A]], brought rapping about crime and the gangster lifestyle into the musical mainstream.

Materialism has also been a popular topic in hip-hop since at least the early 1990s, with rappers boasting about their own wealth and possessions, and name-dropping specific brands: liquor brands [[Cristal (champagne)|Cristal]] and [[Rémy Martin]], car manufacturers [[Bentley]] and [[Mercedes-Benz]] and clothing brands [[Gucci]] and [[Versace]] have all been popular subjects for rappers.

Various politicians, journalists, and religious leaders have accused rappers of fostering a culture of violence and hedonism among hip hop listeners through their lyrics.&lt;ref name=&quot;criticism1&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,2088-2272091,00.html|title=The hoodie needs a daddy, not a hug|accessdate= July 22, 2006|first=Jill|last=Kirby|date=2006-07-16|publisher=The Times|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;criticism2&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,61546,00.html|title=Challenging Pepsi|accessdate=July 22, 2006|first=Bill|last=O'Reilly|date=2002-08-28|publisher=Fox News}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;criticism3&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://arts.guardian.co.uk/filmandmusic/story/0,,1824848,00.html|title='We need heroes'|accessdate= July 22, 2006|first=Dorian|last=Lynskey|date=2006-07-21|publisher= The Guardian|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, there are also rappers whose messages may not be in conflict with these views, for example [[Christian hip hop]]. Others have praised the &quot;political critique, innuendo and sarcasm&quot; of hip hop music.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sampling&quot;&gt;Demers, Joanna. “Sampling the 1970s in Hip-Hop”, Cambridge University Press, 2003, pp. 41–42.&lt;/ref&gt;

In contrast to the more hedonistic approach of gangsta rappers, some rappers have a spiritual or religious focus. Christian rap is currently the most commercially successful form of religious rap. Aside from [[Christianity]], the [[The Nation of Gods and Earths|Five Percent Nation]], an [[Islamic]] [[esotericist]] religious/spiritual group, has been represented more than any religious group in popular hip hop. Artists such as Rakim, the members of the Wu-Tang Clan, [[Brand Nubian]], [[X-Clan]], [[Busta Rhymes]], and Nas, have had success in spreading the [[theology]] of the Five Percenters.

===Literary technique===
Rappers use the [[literary technique]]s of [[double entendre]]s, [[alliteration]], and other forms of wordplay that are also found in classical poetry. [[Simile]]s and [[metaphor]]s are used extensively in rap lyrics; rappers such as [[Fabolous]] and [[Lloyd Banks]] have written entire songs in which every line contains similes, whereas MCs like [[Rakim]], [[GZA]], and [[Jay-Z]] are known for the metaphorical content of their raps. Rappers such as [[Lupe Fiasco]] are known for the complexity of their songs that contain metaphors within extended metaphors.

===Diction and dialect===
Many hip hop listeners believe that a rapper's lyrics are enhanced by a complex vocabulary. [[Kool Moe Dee]] claims that he appealed to older audiences by using a complex vocabulary in his raps.{{sfn|Kool Moe Dee|2003|p=224}} Rap is famous, however, for having its own vocabulary—from international hip hop slang to regional slang. Some artists, like the Wu-Tang Clan, develop an entire lexicon among their clique. African American Vernacular English has always had a significant effect on hip hop slang and vice versa. Certain regions have introduced their unique regional slang to hip hop culture, such as the [[Oakland, California|Bay Area]] ([[Mac Dre]], [[E-40]]), [[Houston]] ([[Chamillionaire]], [[Paul Wall]]), [[Atlanta]] ([[Ludacris]], [[Lil Jon]], [[T.I.]]), and [[Kentucky]] ([[Nappy Roots]]). [[The Nation of Gods and Earths]], aka The Five Percenters, has influenced mainstream hip hop slang with the introduction of phrases such as &quot;word is bond&quot; that have since lost much of their original spiritual meaning. Preference toward one or the other has much to do with the individual; GZA, for example, prides himself on being very visual and metaphorical but also succinct, whereas underground rapper [[Daniel Dumile|MF DOOM]] is known for heaping similes upon similes. In still another variation, 2Pac was known for saying exactly what he meant, literally and clearly.

==Freestyle and battle==
There are two kinds of [[freestyle rap]]: one is scripted (recitation), but having no particular overriding subject matter, the second typically referred to as &quot;freestyling&quot; or &quot;spitting&quot;, is the improvisation of rapped lyrics. When freestyling, some rappers inadvertently reuse old lines, or even &quot;cheat&quot; by preparing segments or entire verses in advance. Therefore, freestyles with proven spontaneity are valued above generic, always usable lines.&lt;ref&gt;Freestyle: The Art of Rhyme (2000)&lt;/ref&gt;  Rappers will often reference places or objects in their immediate setting, or specific (usually demeaning) characteristics of opponents, to prove their authenticity and originality.

[[Battle rap]]ping, which can be freestyled, is the competition between two or more rappers in front of an audience. The tradition of insulting one's friends or acquaintances in rhyme goes back to [[the dozens]], and was portrayed famously by [[Muhammad Ali]] in his boxing matches. The winner of a battle is decided by the crowd and/or preselected judges. According to [[Kool Moe Dee]], a successful battle rap focuses on an opponent's weaknesses, rather than one's own strengths. Television shows such as [[MTV]]'s ''DFX'' and [[Black Entertainment Television|BET]]'s ''[[106 and Park]]'' host weekly freestyle battles live on the air. Battle rapping gained widespread public recognition outside of the African-American community with rapper [[Eminem]]'s movie, ''[[8 Mile (film)|8 Mile]].''

The strongest battle rappers will generally perform their rap fully freestyled. This is the most effective form in a battle as the rapper can comment on the other person, whether it be what they look like, or how they talk, or what they wear. It also allows the rapper to reverse a line used to &quot;diss&quot; him or her if they are the second rapper to battle.  This is known as a 'flip'. [[Jin the Emcee]] was considered 'World Champion' battle rapper in the mid 2000's.

==Social impact==
===Derivatives and influence===
Throughout hip hop's history, new musical styles and genres have developed that contain rapping. Entire genres, such as [[rap rock]] and its derivatives [[rapcore]] and [[rap metal]] ([[rock music|rock]]/[[metal music|metal]]/[[punk music|punk]] with rapped vocals), or [[hip house]] have resulted from the fusion of rap and other styles. Many popular music genres with a focus on percussion have contained rapping at some point; be it [[disco]] ([[DJ Hollywood]]), [[jazz]] ([[Gang Starr]]), [[New Wave music|new wave]] ([[Blondie (band)|Blondie]]), [[funk]] ([[Fatback Band]]), [[contemporary R&amp;B]] ([[Mary J. Blige]]), [[reggaeton]] ([[Daddy Yankee]]), or even Japanese dance music ([[Soul'd Out]]). [[UK garage]] music has begun to focus increasingly on rappers in a new subgenre called [[Grime (music)|grime]], pioneered and popularized by the MC [[Dizzee Rascal]]. Increased popularity with the music has shown more UK rappers going to America as well as tour there, such as [[Sway DaSafo]] possibly signing with [[Akon]]'s label [[Konvict]]. [[Hyphy]] is the latest of these spin-offs. It is typified by slowed-down atonal vocals with instrumentals that borrow heavily from the [[hip hop]] scene and lyrics centered on illegal street racing and car culture. Another Oakland, California group, Beltaine's Fire, has recently gained attention for their [[Celtic fusion]] sound which blends hip hop beats with Celtic melodies. Unlike the majority of hip hop artists, all their music is performed live without samples, synths, or drum machines, drawing comparisons to [[The Roots]] and [[Rage Against the Machine]].

[[Bhangra (music)|Bhangra]], a widely popular style of music from [[Punjab, India|Punjab]], [[India]] has been mixed numerous times with reggae and hip hop music. The most popular song in this genre in the United States was &quot;[[Mundian To Bach Ke|Mundian to Bach Ke&quot; or &quot;Beware the Boys]]&quot; by [[Panjabi MC]] and Jay-Z. Although &quot;Mundian To Bach Ke&quot; had been released previously, the mixing with Jay-Z popularized the genre further.

Though the majority of rappers are male, there have been a number of female rap stars, including  [[Lauryn Hill]], [[MC Lyte]], [[Lil' Kim]], [[Missy Elliott]], [[Queen Latifah]], [[Da Brat]], [[Eve (entertainer)|Eve]], [[Trina (rapper)|Trina]], [[Nicki Minaj]], [[Khia]], [[M.I.A. (artist)|M.I.A.]], [[Foxy Brown (rapper)|Foxy Brown]], and [[Lisa Lopes]] from [[TLC (band)|TLC]]. As these all are hearing rap artists, there is also deaf rap artist [[Signmark]].

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite book|last=Edwards |first=Paul | coauthors = [[Kool G Rap]] (foreword)| year = 2009| month = December| title = [[How to Rap]]: The Art &amp; Science of the Hip-Hop MC| page = 340| publisher = Chicago Review Press| isbn  = 1-55652-816-7 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book| author = Kool Moe Dee| coauthors = et al.| year = 2003| month = November| title = [[There's A God On The Mic]]: The True 50 Greatest MCs| page = 224| publisher = Thunder's Mouth Press| isbn  = 1-56025-533-1| authorlink = Kool Moe Dee |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|author=stic.man | year=2005 | title=The Art Of Emceeing | publisher = Boss Up Inc. |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Krims|first=Adam | year=2001 | title=Rap Music And The Poetics Of Identity | publisher = [[Cambridge University Press]] |ref=harv}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
{{portal|Hip hop}}
*{{cite book| author = Alan Light| coauthors = et al.| year = 1999| month = October| title = The Vibe History of Hip Hop| page = 432| publisher = Three Rivers Press| isbn  = 0-609-80503-7}}
*{{cite book| author = Jeff Chang| coauthors = D.J. Kool Herc | year = 2005 | month = December| title = Can't Stop Won't Stop: A History of the Hip-Hop Generation | page = 560| publisher = Picador| isbn  = 0-312-42579-1}}
*{{cite book | author = Sacha Jenkins | coauthors = et al. | year = 1999 | month = December | title = Ego Trip's Book of Rap Lists | page = 352 | publisher = St. Martin's Griffin | isbn  = 0-312-24298-0 }}

{{hiphop}}

[[Category:Rapping| ]]
[[Category:Reggaeton]]

[[af:Kletsrym]]
[[als:Rap]]
[[ar:راب]]
[[ast:Rap]]
[[be:Рэп]]
[[be-x-old:Рэп]]
[[bg:Рап]]
[[br:Rap]]
[[ca:Música rap]]
[[cs:Rap]]
[[cy:Rapio]]
[[da:Rap]]
[[de:Rap]]
[[et:Räpp]]
[[el:Ραπ μουσική]]
[[es:Rap]]
[[eo:Repo]]
[[eu:Rap]]
[[fa:رپ]]
[[fr:Rap]]
[[fy:Rap]]
[[gd:Rap]]
[[gl:Rap]]
[[ko:랩 (음악)]]
[[id:Rap]]
[[is:Rapp]]
[[it:Rap]]
[[he:ראפ]]
[[kk:Рэп]]
[[sw:Kurap]]
[[ku:Rap]]
[[la:Rap]]
[[lv:Reps]]
[[lb:Rap]]
[[lt:Repas]]
[[hu:Rap]]
[[mk:Рап]]
[[mwl:Rap]]
[[nl:Rap (muziekstijl)]]
[[ja:ラップ]]
[[no:Rapping]]
[[nn:Rapping]]
[[uz:Rap]]
[[nds:Rap]]
[[pl:Rap]]
[[pt:Rap]]
[[ro:Rap]]
[[ru:Рэп]]
[[sc:Musica rap]]
[[stq:Rapmusik]]
[[sq:Rap]]
[[scn:Rap]]
[[sk:Rep (hudba)]]
[[sl:Rap]]
[[fi:Rap]]
[[sv:Rap]]
[[ta:சொல்லிசை]]
[[th:แร็ป]]
[[tr:Rap]]
[[uk:Реп]]
[[vec:Mùxega rap]]
[[wo:Rap]]
[[yi:ראפ מוזיק]]
[[zh-yue:Rap]]
[[zh:饒舌]]</text>
      <sha1>3zaougj2x4sq5pvnwfalliqb7fhjinr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
