<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Napster</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>21113</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519650809</id>
      <parentid>519605375</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-24T22:14:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bbb23</username>
        <id>7583140</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[WP:RBK|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/Sea282|Sea282]] ([[User talk:Sea282|talk]]) to last version by Bbb23 - need source</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24941">{{About|the defunct peer-to-peer service|the modern service operating as Napster|Napster (pay service)}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=October 2011}}
{{Infobox software
| name                   = Napster
| logo                   = [[File:Napster corporate logo.svg|220px]]
| developer              =  [[John Fanning]], [[Shawn Fanning]], and [[Sean Parker]]
| released               = 1999
| frequently_updated     = yes &lt;!-- Release version update? Don't edit this page, just click on the version number! --&gt;
| programming language   =
| operating system       = [[Cross-platform]]
| language               = Multilingual
| genre                  = [[media player (application software)|Media player]]
| license                =
| website                = {{URL|www.napster.com}}
}}

'''Napster''' is a name given to two music-focused online services. It was originally founded as a pioneering [[peer-to-peer file sharing]] Internet service that emphasized sharing audio files, typically music, encoded in [[MP3]] format. The original company ran into legal difficulties over [[copyright infringement]], ceased operations and was eventually acquired by [[Roxio]]. In its second incarnation Napster became an [[online music store]] until it merged with [[Rhapsody (online music service)|Rhapsody]] on 1 December 2011.

Later companies and projects successfully followed its P2P filesharing example such as [[Gnutella]], [[Freenet]] and many others. Some services, like [[Grokster]], [[Madster]] and the original [[eDonkey network]], were brought down or changed due to similar circumstances.

==Origin==
Napster was co-founded by [[Shawn Fanning]], [[John Fanning]], and [[Sean Parker]].&lt;ref name=wiredspotify&gt;Pollack, Neal. [http://www.wired.com/magazine/2010/12/mf_spotify/ Spotify Is the Coolest Music Service You Can't Use]. ''Wired''. December 27, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Schonfeld, Erick. [http://techcrunch.com/2011/10/06/fanning-parker-airtime/ Shawn Fanning And Sean Parker Talk About Airtime And “Smashing People Together”]. ''TechCrunch''. October 6, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rosen, Ellen. [http://www.nytimes.com/2005/05/26/business/26sbiz.html Student's Start-Up Draws Attention and $13 Million]. ''The New York Times''. May 26, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bradshaw, Tim. [http://www.ft.com/intl/cms/s/2/7a289b4e-249b-11df-8be0-00144feab49a.html#axzz1U5W8Lyq9 Spotify-MOG battle heats up]. ''Financial Times''. February 28, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Emerson, Ramona. [http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/10/18/sean-parker-facebook-web-summit_n_1017918.html Sean Parker At Web 2.0 Summit Defends 'Creepy' Facebook]. ''The Huffington Post''. October 18, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=cnnblazing&gt;Simon, Dan. [http://articles.cnn.com/2011-09-27/tech/tech_social-media_adventures-sean-parker_1_sean-parker-shawn-fanning-napster?_s=PM:TECH Internet pioneer Sean Parker: 'I'm blazing a new path']. ''CNN''. September 27, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=alltherave&gt;{{cite book |last= Menn |first= Joseph |coauthors=  |title= All the Rave: The Rise and Fall of Shawn Fanning’s Napster |publisher= Crown Business |year= 2003 |month=  |isbn= 0-609-61093-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Kirkpatrick, David|title=With a Little Help From His Friends|url=http://www.vanityfair.com/culture/features/2010/10/sean-parker-201010?currentPage=all|work=Vanity Fair |accessdate=July 1, 2011|date=October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Initially, Napster was envisioned as an independent [[peer-to-peer file sharing]] service.  The service, named after Fanning's hairstyle-based nickname, operated between June 1999 and July 2001.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.businessweek.com/2000/00_33/b3694003.htm Napster's High and Low Notes] – Businessweek – August 14, 2000&lt;/ref&gt; Its technology allowed people to easily share their [[MP3]] files with other participants. Its ease of use led to massive copyright violations of music and film media, as well as other intellectual property.{{Citation needed|date=October 2011}} Although the original service was shut down by court order, the Napster brand survived after the company's assets were liquidated and purchased by other companies through bankruptcy proceedings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last=Evangelista | first=Benny | title=Napster runs out of lives – judge rules against sale | date=September 4, 2002 |accessdate=October 18, 2011 | publisher=San Francisco Chronicle | url= http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/chronicle/archive/2002/09/04/BU138263.DTL}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
Although there were already networks that facilitated the distribution of files across the Internet, such as IRC, [[Hotline Communications|Hotline]], and [[USENET]], Napster specialized exclusively in music in the form of MP3 files and presented a user-friendly interface. The back-end system was built by Napster's chief architect, [[Jordan Mendelson]].&lt;ref name=&quot;amazon.com&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.amazon.com/dp/0609610937 | title=All the Rave: The Rise and Fall of Shawn Fanning's Napster}}&lt;/ref&gt; The result was a robust system whose popularity generated an enormous selection of music to download – at its peak there were 25 million users and 80 million songs, and the system never once crashed.

Napster made it relatively easy for music enthusiasts to download copies of songs that were otherwise difficult to obtain, like older songs, unreleased recordings, and songs from concert [[bootleg recording]]s. Some users felt justified in downloading digital copies of recordings they had already purchased in other formats, like [[Gramophone record|LP]] and [[cassette tape]], before the [[compact disc]] emerged as the dominant format for music recordings.

These reasons aside, many other users simply enjoyed trading and downloading music for free. They created a username and password and were able to make their own compilation albums on [[recordable CD]]s, without paying any royalties to the artist/composer or the estate of the artist/composer. High-speed networks in college dormitories became overloaded, with as much as 61% of external network traffic consisting of MP3 file transfers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last=Fusco | first=Patricia | title=The Napster Nightmare | date=March 13, 2000 | publisher=ISP-Planet | url=http://www.isp-planet.com/politics/napster.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many colleges blocked its use for this reason,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last=Anderson | first=Kevin | title=Napster expelled by universities | date=September 26, 2000 | publisher=BBC News | url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/business/942090.stm}}&lt;/ref&gt; even before concerns about liability for facilitating copyright violations on campus.

===Macintosh version===
[[Image:Napster-MacOS9-2001.png|right|thumb|Napster running on Mac OS 9 (using Kaleidoscope theme utility) in March 2001.]]
The service and software program were initially Windows-only, but in 2000 [[Black Hole Media]] wrote a Macintosh client called [[Macster]]. Macster was later bought by Napster and designated the official Mac Napster client (&quot;Napster for the Mac&quot;), at which point the Macster name was discontinued.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.macobserver.com/article/2000/10/25.2.shtml Official Napster Client For Mac OS, OS X || The Mac Observer&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  Even before the acquisition of Macster, the Macintosh community had a variety of independently developed Napster clients. Most notable was the [[open source]] client called [[MacStar]], released by [[Squirrel Software]] in early 2000 and Rapster, released by Overcaster Family in Brazil.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.applelinks.com/mooresviews/players.shtml Eight MP3 Players For The Macintosh]. Applelinks.com (October 31, 2003). Retrieved on January 29, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  The release of MacStar's source code paved the way for third-party Napster clients across all computing platforms, which gave users advertisement-free music distribution options.

===Legal challenges===
{{Filesharing}}

Heavy metal band [[Metallica]] discovered that a demo of their song &quot;[[I Disappear]]&quot; had been circulating across the network even before it was released. This eventually led to the song being played on several radio stations across the United States and brought to Metallica’s attention that their entire back catalogue of studio material was also available. The band responded in 2000 by filing a [[Metallica v. Napster, Inc.|lawsuit]] against Napster. A month later, rapper and producer [[Dr. Dre]], who shared a litigator and legal firm with Metallica, filed a similar lawsuit after Napster would not remove his works from their service, even after he issued a written request. Separately, both Metallica and Dr. Dre later delivered thousands of usernames to Napster who they believed were pirating their songs. One year later, Napster settled both suits, but this came after being shut down by the [[Ninth Circuit Court of Appeals]] in a separate lawsuit from several major record labels (see below).

Also in 2000, [[Madonna (entertainer)|Madonna]]'s [[Single (music)|single]] &quot;[[Music (Madonna song)|Music]]&quot; leaked out on to the web and Napster prior to its commercial release, causing widespread media coverage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last=Borland | first=John | title=Unreleased Madonna Single Slips On To Net | date=June 1, 2000 | publisher=CNET News.com | url= http://news.com.com/2100-1023-241341.html?legacy=cnet}}&lt;/ref&gt; Verified Napster use peaked with 26.4 million users worldwide in February 2001.&lt;ref&gt;Jupiter Media Metrix (July 20, 2001). [http://web.archive.org/web/20080413104420/http://www.comscore.com/press/release.asp?id=249 Global Napster Usage Plummets, But New File-Sharing Alternatives Gaining Ground]. Press Release.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2000, [[A&amp;M Records]] and several other recording companies, via the RIAA,  sued Napster (''[[A&amp;M Records, Inc. v. Napster, Inc.]]'') for contributory and vicarious copyright infringement under the US [[Digital Millennium Copyright Act]] (DMCA).&lt;ref&gt;17 U.S.C. A&amp;M Records. Inc. v. Napster. Inc. 114 F. Supp. 2d 896 (N. D. Cal. 2000).&lt;/ref&gt; The music industry made the following claims against Napster:

# That its users were directly infringing the plaintiffs' copyrights.
# That Napster was liable for contributory infringement of the plaintiffs' copyrights.
# That Napster was liable for vicarious infringement of the plaintiffs' copyrights.

Napster lost the case in the District Court and appealed to the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit. Although the Ninth Circuit found that Napster was capable of commercially significant non-infringing uses, it affirmed the District Court's decision. On remand, the District Court ordered Napster to monitor the activities of its network and to block access to infringing material when notified of that material's location. Napster was unable to do this and shut down its service in July 2001. Napster finally declared itself bankrupt in 2002 and sold its assets. It had already been offline since the previous year owing to the effect of the court rulings.&lt;ref&gt;.A&amp;M Records, Inc. v. Napster, Inc., 239 F.3d 1004 (9th Cir. 2001). For a summary and analysis, see Guy Douglas, Copyright and Peer-To-Peer Music File Sharing: The Napster Case and the Argument Against Legislative Reform http://www.murdoch.edu.au/elaw/issues/v11n1/douglas111.html&lt;/ref&gt;

===Promotional power===
[[Image:Napster Unique Users.svg|thumb|right|300px|Napster peaked in February 2001.]]

Along with the accusations that Napster was hurting the sales of the record industry, there were those who felt just the opposite, that file trading on Napster actually stimulated, rather than hurt, sales. Some evidence may have come in July 2000 when tracks from [[England|English]] rock band [[Radiohead]]'s album ''[[Kid A]]'' found their way to Napster three months before the CD's release. Unlike Madonna, Dr. Dre or Metallica, Radiohead had never hit the top 20 in the US. Furthermore, ''Kid A'' was an experimental album without any [[single (music)|singles]], and received relatively little radio airplay. By the time of the record's release, the album was estimated to have been downloaded for free by millions of people worldwide, and in October 2000 ''Kid A'' captured the number one spot on the [[Billboard 200]] sales chart in its debut week. According to Richard Menta of [[MP3 Newswire]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last=Menta | first=Richard | title=Did Napster Take Radiohead's New Album to Number 1? | date=October 28, 2000 | publisher=MP3 Newswire | url=http://www.mp3newswire.net/stories/2000/radiohead.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; the effect of Napster in this instance was isolated from other elements that could be credited for driving sales, and the album's unexpected success suggested that Napster was a good promotional tool for music.

One of the most successful bands to owe its success to Napster was [[Dispatch (band)|Dispatch]]. Being an independent band, it had no formal promotion or radio play, yet it was able to tour to cities they had never played and sell out concerts, thanks to the spread of their music on Napster.  In July 2007, the band became the first independent band to ever headline [[New York City]]'s [[Madison Square Garden]], selling it out for three consecutive nights.  The band members were avid supporters of Napster, promoting it at their shows, playing a Napster show around the time of the Congressional hearings, and attending the hearings themselves.  [[Shawn Fanning]], the founder of Napster, is a known Dispatch fan.

Since 2000, many musical artists, particularly those not signed to major labels and without access to traditional mass media outlets such as radio and television, have said that Napster and successive Internet file-sharing networks have helped get their music heard, spread word of mouth, and may have improved their sales in the long term{{Citation needed|date=September 2007}}. One such musician to publicly defend Napster as a promotional tool for independent artists was [[Dj xealot]], who became directly involved in the 2000 A&amp;M Records Lawsuit.&lt;ref name=&quot;Declaration of D.J. Xealot in Supp. of. Napster&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Case Nos. C 99-5183 and C 00-0074 MHP (ADR) |url=http://news.findlaw.com/hdocs/docs/napster/napster/dec_xeal.pdf |publisher=[[FindLaw.com]] |accessdate=February 12, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Chuck D]] from [[Public Enemy (band)|Public Enemy]] also came out and publicly supported Napster.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title=Rapper Chuck D throws weight behind Napster | date=May 1, 2000 | publisher=Cnet News | url=http://news.cnet.com/2100-1023-239917.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although some [[underground music]]ians and [[Independent record label|independent labels]] have expressed support for Napster and the p2p model it popularized, others have criticized the unregulated and extra-legal nature of these networks, and some seek to implement models of Internet promotion in which they can control the distribution of their own music, such as providing free tracks for download or streaming from their official websites, or co-operating with pay services such as [[Insound]], [[Rhapsody (online music service)|Rhapsody]] and [[Apple Inc.|Apple]]'s [[iTunes Store]].

===Lawsuit===
Napster's facilitation of transfer of copyrighted material raised the ire of the [[Recording Industry Association of America]] (RIAA), which almost immediately—on December 7, 1999—filed a [[lawsuit]] against the popular service.&lt;ref&gt;''[[A&amp;M Records, Inc. v. Napster, Inc.]]'', 114 F. Supp. 2d 896 ([[N.D. Cal.]] 2000), aff'd in part, rev'd in part, 239 F.3d 1004 ([[9th Cir.]] 2001)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last=Menta | first=Richard | title= RIAA Sues Music Startup Napster for $20 Billion | date=December 9, 1999 | publisher=MP3 Newswire | url=http://www.mp3newswire.net/stories/napster.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; The service would only get bigger as the trial, meant to shut down Napster, also gave it [[Streisand effect|a great deal of publicity]]. Soon millions of users, many of them college students, flocked to it.
After a failed appeal to the [[United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit|Ninth Circuit Court]], an injunction was issued on March 5, 2001 ordering Napster to prevent the trading of copyrighted music on its network.&lt;ref&gt;2001 US Dist. LEXIS 2186 (N.D. Cal. Mar. 5, 2001), aff’d, 284 F. 3d 1091 (9th Cir. 2002).&lt;/ref&gt;

Lessig&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Lessig |first= Lawrence |authorlink= Lawrence Lessig
|title= Free Culture:  The Nature and Future of Creativity
|url= Free Culture (book)|year= 2004 |publisher= Penguin
|isbn= 978-0-14-303465-0 |pages= 73–74 }}&lt;/ref&gt; claimed, however, that this decision made little sense from the perspective of copyright protection:  &quot;When Napster told the district court that it had developed a technology to block the transfer of 99.4 percent of identified infringing material, the district court told council for Napster 99.4 percent was not good enough.  Napster had to push the infringements 'down to zero.' If 99.4 percent is not good enough&quot;, Lessig concluded, &quot;then this is a war on file-sharing technologies, not a war on copyright infringement.&quot;

===Shutdown===
In July 2001, Napster shut down its entire network in order to comply with the injunction. On September 24, 2001, the case was partially settled. Napster agreed to pay music creators and copyright owners a $26 million settlement for past, unauthorized uses of music, as well as an advance against future licensing royalties of $10 million. In order to pay those fees, Napster attempted to convert their free service to a subscription system. Thus traffic to Napster was reduced. A prototype solution was tested in the spring of 2002: the Napster 3.0 Alpha, using the &quot;.nap&quot; secure file format from [[PlayMedia Systems]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.theregister.co.uk/2001/07/23/napster_to_ditch_mp3/&lt;/ref&gt; and audio fingerprinting technology licensed from [[Relatable]]. Napster 3.0 was, according to many former Napster employees, ready to deploy, but it had significant trouble obtaining licenses to distribute major-label music.

On May 17, 2002, Napster announced that its assets would be acquired by German media firm [[Bertelsmann]] for $85 million. Pursuant to terms of that agreement, on June 3 Napster filed for [[Chapter 11]] protection under [[United States]] [[bankruptcy]] laws. On September 3, 2002, an American bankruptcy judge blocked the sale to Bertelsmann and forced Napster to liquidate its assets according to [[Chapter 7, Title 11, United States Code|Chapter 7]] of the U.S. bankruptcy laws.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last=Evangelista | first=Benny | title=Napster runs out of lives – judge rules against sale | date=September 4, 2002 | publisher=San Francisco Chronicle | url= http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/chronicle/archive/2002/09/04/BU138263.DTL}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Current status==
{{Main|Napster (pay service)}}

After a US$2.43 million takeover offer by the [[Private Media Group]], an [[adult entertainment]] company,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title=Porno company offers to buy Napster | date=September 12, 2002 | publisher=CNET News.com | url=http://news.com.com/2100-1023-957784.html?tag=fd_top}}&lt;/ref&gt; Napster's brand and logos were acquired at bankruptcy auction by [[Roxio]] which used them to rebrand the [[Pressplay]] music service as [[Napster (pay service)|Napster 2.0]].

In September 2008, Napster was purchased by US electronics retailer [[Best Buy]] for US $121 million.&lt;ref name=&quot;urlThe Next Chapter: Best Buy To Acquire Napster For $121 Million | paidContent.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.paidcontent.org/entry/419-breaking-best-buy-to-acquire-napster-for-121-million/ |title=The Next Chapter: Best Buy To Acquire Napste121 Million | work=paidContent.org |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On December 1, 2011, pursuant to a deal with Best Buy, Napster merged with Rhapsody. Best Buy will receive a minority stake in Rhapsody.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://money.cnn.com/2011/11/30/technology/napster_rhapsody/?source=cnn_bin | work=CNN | title=Today is Napster's last day of existence | date=November 30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Media about Napster ==
There have been several books that document the experiences of people working at Napster, including Joseph Menn's Napster biography, ''All the Rave: The Rise and Fall of Shawn Fanning's Napster'',&lt;ref name=&quot;amazon.com&quot;/&gt; John Alderman's &quot;''Sonic Boom: Napster, MP3, and the New Pioneers of Music'',&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=John Alderman |title=Sonic boom: Napster, MP3, and the new pioneers of music |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=XH_uAAAAMAAJ |accessdate=January 29, 2011 |date=August 8, 2001 |publisher=Perseus Pub. |isbn=978-0-7382-0405-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Steve Knopper's &quot;''Appetite for Self Destruction: The Spectacular Crash of the Record Industry in the Digital Age''.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rockymountainnews.com/news/2009/jan/02/napster-wounds-the-giant/ Napster wounds the giant : Music]. The Rocky Mountain News (January 5, 2009). Retrieved on January 29, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

The 2010 film ''[[The Social Network]]'' features Napster co-founder [[Sean Parker]] (played by [[Justin Timberlake]]) in the rise of the popular website [[Facebook]].&lt;ref name=vanityfair&gt;Kirkpatrick, David. [http://www.vanityfair.com/culture/features/2010/10/sean-parker-201010 With a Little Help From His Friends]. ''Vanity Fair''. October 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[OpenNap]]
* [[Snocap]]
* [[TekNap]]
* [[imeem]]
* [[Kazaa]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
*{{Cite journal |last=Carlsson |first=Bengt |last2=Gustavsson |first2=Rune |year=2001 |title=The Rise and Fall of Napster – An Evolutionary Approach |journal=Proceedings of the 6th International Computer Science Conference on Active Media Technology |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}
*{{Cite journal |last=Giesler |first=Markus |last2=Pohlmann |first2=Mali |year=2003 |title=The Social Form of Napster: Cultivating the Paradox of Consumer Emancipation |journal=Advances in Consumer Research |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}
*{{Cite journal |last=Giesler |first=Markus |last2=Pohlmann |first2=Mali |year=2003 |title=The Anthropology of File Sharing: Consuming Napster as a Gift |journal=Advances in Consumer Research |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}
*{{Cite journal |last=Green |first=Matthew |year=2002 |title=Napster Opens Pandora’s Box: Examining How File-Sharing Services Threaten the Enforcement of Copyright on the Internet |journal=Ohio State Law Journal |volume=63 |page=799 |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}
*InsightExpress. 2000. Napster and its Users Not violating Copyright Infringement Laws, According to a Survey of the Online Community.
*{{Cite journal |last=Ku |first=Raymond Shih Ray |title=The Creative Destruction of Copyright: Napster and the New Economics of Digital Technology |journal=University of Chicago Law Review |ssrn=266964 |doi=10.2139/ssrn.266964 |year=2001 |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}
*{{Cite journal |last=McCourt |first=Tom |last2=Burkart |first2=Patrick |year=2003 |title=When Creators, Corporations and Consumers Collide: Napster and the Development of On-line Music Distribution |journal=Media, Culture, &amp; Society |volume=25 |issue=3 |pages=333–350 |doi=10.1177/0163443703025003003 |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}
*{{Cite journal |last=Orbach |first=Barak |title=Indirect Free Riding on the Wheels of Commerce: Dual-Use Technologies and Copyright Liability |year=2008 |journal=Emory Law Journal |volume=57 |pages=409–461 |url=http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=965720 |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}
* {{cite book|last=Abramson|first=Bruce|title=Digital Phoenix; Why the Information Economy Collapsed and How it Will Rise Again|year=2005|publisher=MIT Press|isbn=978-0-262-51196-4}}
* [http://www.wired.com/news/mp3/0,1285,50625,00.html Judge criticises both parties in Napster case]
* &quot;The File Sharing Movement&quot; in Jack Goldsmith and Tim Wu, ''Who Controls the Internet: Illusions of a Borderless World'' Oxford University Press, 2006, pp.&amp;nbsp;105–125. ISBN 978-0-19-515266-1

==External links==
* {{Official website|http://www.napster.com}}

{{Digital distribution platforms}}

[[Category:Companies disestablished in 2001]]
[[Category:Companies established in 1999]]
[[Category:1999 software]]
[[Category:Companies that have filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy in 2002]]
[[Category:Companies that have filed for Chapter 7 bankruptcy]]
[[Category:Defunct digital music services or companies]]
[[Category:File sharing networks]]
[[Category:File sharing programs]]
[[Category:Internet services shut down by a legal challenge]]
[[Category:Mac OS software]]
[[Category:Virtual communities]]
[[Category:Windows software]]
[[Category:Metallica]]

[[ar:نابستار]]
[[ca:Napster]]
[[cs:Napster]]
[[da:Napster]]
[[de:Napster]]
[[et:Napster]]
[[es:Napster]]
[[fa:نپستر]]
[[fr:Napster]]
[[ko:냅스터]]
[[hi:नैप्स्टर]]
[[id:Napster]]
[[it:Napster]]
[[he:נאפסטר]]
[[kn:ನಾಪ್‌ಸ್ಟರ್]]
[[lt:Napster]]
[[ms:Napster]]
[[nl:Napster]]
[[ja:Napster]]
[[no:Napster]]
[[pl:Napster]]
[[pt:Napster]]
[[ru:Napster]]
[[simple:Napster]]
[[sk:Napster]]
[[fi:Napster]]
[[sv:Napster]]
[[uk:Napster]]
[[zh:Napster]]</text>
      <sha1>rhx7v0usapwof311ghrv1zjl3gcsog5</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
