<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Peer-to-peer file sharing</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4279208</id>
    <revision>
      <id>507261462</id>
      <parentid>505513340</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-08-13T20:04:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Albertttt</username>
        <id>13804113</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* See also */  added F2F, darknet, private, anonymous</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20600">{{NPOV language|date=April 2011}}
{{cleanup|date=October 2010}}
{{Filesharing}}

'''Peer-to-peer file sharing''' (known in [[Internet jargon|internet shorthand]] as &quot;P2P&quot;) allows users to download media files such as music, movies, and games using a P2P software client that searches for other connected computers.&lt;ref&gt;Carmack,Carman. [http://computer.howstuffworks.com/bittorrent1.htm] “How Bit Torrent Works”&lt;/ref&gt; The &quot;peers&quot; are computer systems connected to each other through the Internet. Thus, the only requirements for a computer to join peer-to-peer networks are an Internet connection and P2P software.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.techterms.com/definition/p2p]&quot;techterm&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;  The first generation of P2P software is '''Napster''', a central server-based model that was eventually shut down. The second generation of P2P software is '''Gnutella''' and '''Kazaa''', which are user-based models. '''BitTorrent''' became the third generation of P2P networks. The difference between BitTorrent and previous generations is that it creates a new network for every set of files instead of trying to create one big network of files using SuperNodes, web caches or servers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://filesharingz.com/guides/filesharing-history.php] &quot;file sharing&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

There are a number of factors that contribute to the widespread adoption and facilitation of peer-to-peer [[file sharing]]. These include increasing Internet bandwidth, the widespread digitization of physical media files, and the capabilities of home PC's increasing to better handle playing and storing digitized audio and video files. Users were able to transfer either one or more files from one computer to another across the Internet through various [[file transfer]]s and file-sharing networks.&lt;ref&gt;Carmack,Carman [http://computer.howstuffworks.com/bittorrent.htm] &quot;How Bit Torrent Works&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legal aspects==
{{Main|Legal aspects of file sharing}}
The act of file sharing ''itself'' is not illegal and peer-to-peer networks are also used for legitimate purposes; the legal issues in file sharing involve violating the laws of ''[[copyrighted]]'' material. Most discussions about the legality of &quot;file sharing&quot; are implied to be about solely copyright material. Many countries have some sort of [[fair use]] exception that permits limited use of copyrighted material without acquiring permission from the rights holders; such as commentary, news reporting, research and scholarship. Copyrights are territorial- they do not extend beyond the territory of a specific state unless that state is a party to an international agreement. However, most countries today are parties to at least one such agreement.

==History==
Peer-to-peer file sharing began in 1999 with the introduction of [[Napster]], a file sharing program and central servers that linked people who had files with those who requested files. The central index server was meant to index all of the current users and to search their computers. When someone searched for a file, the server would find all of the available copies of that file and present them to the user. The files would be transferred between the two private computers. One limitation was that only music files could be shared.&lt;ref&gt;Tyson, Jeff.[http://computer.howstuffworks.com/napster2.htm]. ''How the Old Napster Workded”.&lt;/ref&gt; Because this process occurred on a central server, however, Napster was held liable for copyright infringement and shut down in July 2001. It later reopened as a pay service.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.murdoch.edu.au/elaw/issues/v11n1/douglas111.html].” Copyright and Peer-To-Peer Music File Sharing: The Napster Case and the Argument Against Legislative Reform”, March 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

After Napster shut down, the most popular peer-to-peer services were [[Gnutella]] and [[Kazaa]]. While Napster connected users through a centralized server, these new services connected users remotely to each other.&lt;ref&gt;Watson, Stephanie.[http://computer.howstuffworks.com/kazaa3.htm] “ How Kazaa Works”.&lt;/ref&gt; These services also allowed users to download files other than music, such as movies and games.&lt;ref&gt;Tyson,Jeff.[http://computer.howstuffworks.com/napster4.htm].  “How the Old Napster Worked”.&lt;/ref&gt;

Another protocol that emerged after Napster shut down is [[BitTorrent (protocol)|Bittorrent]]. Bittorrent allows users to create an index file containing the metadata of the files they want to share, and uploads them to dedicated websites where people can download them.

== Economic impact ==
:''Main article: [[File sharing#Effects of file sharing|Effects of file sharing]]''
There is still ongoing discussion about the economic impact of P2P file-sharing. Norbert Michel, a Policy Analyst at The Heritage Foundation, said that because of &quot;econometric and data issues, studies thus far have produced disparate estimates of file sharing's impact on album sales.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;heritage.org&quot;&gt;J. Michel, Norbert. [http://www.heritage.org/research/reports/2004/08/internet-file-sharing-the-evidence-so-far-and-what-it-means-for-the-future Internet File Sharing and The Evidence So far], heritage.org, August 23, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the book ''[[The Wealth of Networks]]'', [[Yochai Benkler]] says that peer-to-peer file sharing is economically efficient and that the users pay the full transaction cost and marginal cost of such sharing even if it &quot;throws a monkey wrench into the particular way in which our society has chosen to pay musicians and re-cording executives. This trades off efficiency for longer-term incentive effects for the recording industry. However, it is efficient within the normal meaning of the term in economics in a way that it would not have been had Jack and Jane used subsidized computers or network connections&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Yochai Benkler&quot;&gt;{{cite book | author = Yochai Benkler | url = http://books.google.com/books?id=McotnvNSjQ4C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=benkler&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=qBjATOSkC8zBca-V1fAL&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCUQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=falsee | title = Wealth of Networks | publisher = Google Books | accessdate = 2010-04-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Music industry ===
The economic effect of copyright infringement through peer-to-peer file sharing on music revenue has been controversial and difficult to determine. Music sales dropped globally from approximately $38 billion in 1999 to $32 billion in 2003, and an increasing number{{What|date=August 2012}} of studies found that file sharing had a negative impact on record sales.&lt;ref&gt;Alejandro Zentner, [http://www.bepress.com/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1452&amp;amp;context=bejeap &quot;File Sharing and International Sales of Copyrighted Music: An Empirical Analysis with a Panel of Countries&quot;], ''The B.E. Journal of Economic Analysis &amp; Policy'', Vol. 5, Issue 1 (2005)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stan J. Liebowitz, &quot;File Sharing: Creative Destruction or Just Plain Destruction?&quot;; Rafael Rob and Joel Waldfogel, &quot;Piracy on the High C's: Music Downloading, Sales Displacement, and Social Welfare in a Sample of College Students&quot;; Alejandro Zentner, &quot;Measuring the Effect of File Sharing on Music Purchases&quot;, [http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/toc/jle/2006/49/1 ''The Journal of Law and Economics'', Vol. 49, No. 1 (April 2006)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stan J. Liebowitz in a series of papers (2005, 2006) &lt;!--&quot;File sharing: creative destruction or just plain destruction?&quot; Liebowitz, Stan J. ''Journal of Law and Economics'' (0022-2186) 1 Apr 2006. Vol.49, Iss.1; p.1-28--&gt;&lt;!--&quot;Copyright reconsidered&quot;. Liebowitz, Stan J. ''Issues in Science and Technology'' (0748-5492) 22 Mar 2005. Vol.21, Iss.3; p.92(4)--&gt;&lt;!--&quot;Seventeen famous economists weigh in on copyright: the role of theory, empirics, and network effects&quot;. Liebowitz, Stan J. ''Harvard Journal of Law &amp; Technology'' (0897-3393) 22 Mar 2005. Vol. 18, Iss. 2; p. 435–457--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; It has proven difficult to untangle the cause and effect relationships among a number of different trends, including an increase in legal online purchases of music; illegal file-sharing; drops in the prices of CDs; and the extinction of many independent music stores with a concomitant shift to sales by big-box retailers.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;&gt;Smith, Ethan. March 21, 2007. [http://online.wsj.com/public/article/SB117444575607043728-oEugjUqEtTo1hWJawejgR3LjRAw_20080320.html?mod=rss_free &quot;Sales of Music, Long in Decline, Plunge Sharply: Rise in Downloading Fails to Boost Industry; A Retailing Shakeout&quot;], ''Wallstreet Journal Website''&lt;/ref&gt;

===Film industry===
The [[MPAA]] reported that American studios lost $2.3 billion to Internet piracy in 2005, representing approximately one third of the total cost of film piracy in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|format=PDF|url=http://www.MPAA.org/press_releases/2006_05_31.pdf|title=SWEDISH AUTHORITIES SINK PIRATE BAY: Huge Worldwide Supplier of Illegal Movies Told No Safe Harbors for Facilitators of Piracy!|date=2006-05-31|publisher=[[MPAA]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The MPAA's estimate was doubted by commentators since it was based on the assumption that one download was equivalent to one lost sale, and downloaders might not purchase the movie if illegal downloading was not an option.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2004/11/21/business/yourmoney/21view.html?ex=1258693200&amp;en=a210357f5dcc8523&amp;ei=5088&amp;partner=rssnyt |title=Does a Free Download Equal a Lost Sale? |first=Daniel |last=Gross |date=2004-11-21 |accessdate=2007-07-16 |work=[[The New York Times]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.unc.edu/~cigar/papers/FileSharing_March2004.pdf|first=Felix|last=Oberholzer|coauthors=Strumpf, Koleman|title=The Effect of File Sharing on Record Sales: An Empirical Analysis|year=2004|month=March|publisher=[[UNC Chapel Hill]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?sec=technology&amp;res=9C02E2D91139F936A35757C0A9629C8B63|title=A Heretical View of File Sharing|first=John|last=Schwartz|date=2004-04-05|accessdate=2007-07-16|publisher=[[The New York Times]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Due to the private nature of the study, the figures could not be publicly checked for methodology or validity,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://arstechnica.com/news.ars/post/20060505-6761.html|publisher=[[Ars Technica]]|first=Ken|last=Fisher|date=2006-05-05|accessdate=2007-07-15|title=The problem with MPAA's shocking piracy numbers}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web|url=http://torrentfreak.com/movie-piracy-cost-61-billion/|title=Movie Piracy Cost 6.1 Billion|publisher=[[Torrent Freak]]|date=2006-05-03|accessdate=2007-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news|url=http://news.zdnet.com/2100-9595_22-6068198.html|title=Hollywood study examines costs of film piracy|publisher=[[ZDNet]] ([[Reuters]])|date=2006-05-03|accessdate=2007-07-16 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070417092540/http://news.zdnet.com/2100-9595_22-6068198.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-04-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; and on January 22, 2008, as the MPAA was lobbying for a bill which would compel universities to crack down on piracy, it was admitted that MPAA figures on piracy in colleges had been inflated by up to 300%.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web|url=http://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/news/2008/01/oops-mpaa-admits-college-piracy-numbers-grossly-inflated.ars|title=MPAA admits college piracy numbers grossly inflated|publisher=[[Ars Technica]]|date=2008-01-22|first=Nate|last=Anderson}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web|url=http://arstechnica.com/old/content/2008/01/filtering-could-come-to-isps-colleges-in-2008.ars|title=2008 shaping up to be &quot;Year of Filters&quot; at colleges, ISPs|publisher=[[Ars Technica]]|date=2008-01-15|first=Nate|last=Anderson}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2010 study, commissioned by the [[International Chamber of Commerce]] and conducted by independent Paris-based economics firm TERA, estimated that unlawful downloading of music, film and software cost Europe's creative industries several billion dollars in revenue each year.&lt;ref&gt;Mundell, Ian. [http://www.variety.com/article/VR1118016618.html?categoryId=1338&amp;cs=1 Piracy in Europe costs $13.7 billion], ''Variety''. March 18, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, the TERA study entitled “Building a Digital Economy: The Importance of Saving Jobs in the EU's Creative Industries” predicted losses due to piracy reaching as much as 1.2 million jobs and €240 billion in retail revenue by 2015 if the trend continued.  Researchers applied a substitution rate of ten percent to the volume of copyright infringements per year. This rate corresponded to the number of units potentially traded if unlawful file sharing were eliminated and did not occur.&lt;ref&gt;Geoffron, Patrice. [http://www.iccwbo.org/bascap/id35360/index.html Building a Digital Economy], iccwbo.org, March 17, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Piracy rates of one-quarter or more{{vague|date=January 2012}} for popular [[software]] and [[operating system]]s have been common, even in countries and regions with strong intellectual property enforcement, such as the [[United States]] or the [[EU]].&lt;ref&gt;Moisés Naím (2007). ''Illicit: How smugglers, traffickers and copycats are hijacking the global economy'', p. 15. Arrow Books, London. ISBN 1-4000-7884-9.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Public perception and usage ==
In 2004, an estimated 70 million people participated in online file sharing.&lt;ref&gt;Delgado, Ray. [http://news-service.stanford.edu/news/2004/march17/fileshare-317.html Law professors examine ethical controversies of peer-to-peer file sharing]. ''Stanford Report'', March 17, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; According to a [[CBS News]] poll, nearly 70 percent of 18 to 29 year olds thought file sharing was acceptable in some circumstances and 58 percent of all [[United States|Americans]] who followed the file sharing issue considered it acceptable in at least some circumstances.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2003/09/18/opinion/polls/main573990.shtml Poll: Young Say File Sharing OK] ''CBS News'', Bootie Cosgrove-Mather, 2003-09-18&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2006, 32 million Americans over the age of 12 had downloaded at least one feature length movie from the Internet, 80 percent of whom had done so exclusively over P2P. Of the population sampled, 40 percent felt that downloading copyrighted movies off the Internet constituted a very serious offense, however 78 percent believed taking a DVD from a store without paying for it constituted a very serious offense.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.srgnet.com/pdf/Movie%20File-Sharing%20Booming%20Release%20Jan%2024%2007%20Final.pdf Solutions Research Group - Movie File-Sharing Booming: Study]&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 2008, 20 percent of Europeans used file sharing networks to obtain music, while 10 percent used paid-for digital music services such as iTunes.&lt;ref&gt;17:41 GMT, Thursday, 3 July 2008 18:41 UK. [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/technology/7486743.stm Technology: &quot;Warning letters to 'file-sharers'&quot;], ''BBC NEWS''.&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2009, a Tiscali UK survey found that 75 percent of the English public polled were aware of what was legal and illegal in relation to file sharing, however there was a divide as to where they felt the legal burden should be placed: 49 percent of people believed P2P companies should be held responsible for illegal file sharing on their networks, 18 percent viewed individual file sharers as the culprits, while 18 percent either didn’t know or chose not to answer.&lt;ref&gt;MarkJ - 24 February 2009 (1:46 PM).  [http://www.ispreview.co.uk/news/EkFVulFEAVbPsdkYcg.html &quot;Tiscali UK Survey Reveals Illegal File Sharing Attitudes&quot;], ''ISPreview UK News''.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to an earlier poll, 75 percent of young voters in [[Sweden]] (18-20) supported file sharing when presented with the statement: &quot;I think it is OK to download files from the Net, even if it is illegal.&quot; Of the respondents, 38 percent said they &quot;adamantly agreed&quot; while 39 percent said they &quot;partly agreed&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;TT/Adam Ewing. 8 Jun 06 09:54 CET. [http://www.thelocal.se/article.php?ID=4014&amp;date=20060608 &quot;Young voters back file sharing&quot;], ''The Local''.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Risks ==
Researchers have examined potential security risks including the release of personal information, bundled [[spyware]], and [[Computer virus|viruses]] downloaded from the network.&lt;ref&gt;By M. Eric Johnson, Dan McGuire, Nicholas D. Willey [http://csdl2.computer.org/comp/proceedings/hicss/2008/3075/00/30750383.pdf The Evolution of the Peer-to-Peer File Sharing Industry and the Security Risks for Users]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Where Only Fools Dare to Tread: An Empirical Study on the Prevalence of Zero-day Malware|author=Håvard Vegge, Finn Michael Halvorsen and Rune Walsø Nergård|publisher=2009 Fourth International Conference on Internet Monitoring and Protection|year=2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some proprietary file sharing clients have been known to bundle [[malware]], though [[open source]] programs typically have not. Some open source file sharing packages have even provided integrated anti-virus scanning.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.turnkeylinux.org/torrentserver Open source file sharing software with integrated anti-virus scanning]&lt;/ref&gt;
A drastic increase in inadvertent P2P file sharing of personal and sensitive information became evident in 2009 at the beginning of President Obama's administration when the blueprints to the helicopter [[Marine One]] were made available to the public through a breach in security via a P2P file sharing site. Access to this information has the potential of being detrimental to US security.&lt;ref name=&quot;CNET&quot;&gt;Greg Sandoval. April 21, 2009 10:41 AM PDT. [http://news.cnet.com/8301-1023_3-10224080-93.html &quot;Congress to probe P2P sites over 'inadvertent sharing'&quot;], ''CNET News''&lt;/ref&gt;

Furthermore, shortly before this security breach, the ''[[Today (NBC program)|Today]]'' show had reported that more than 150,000 tax returns, 25,800 student loan applications and 626,000 credit reports had been inadvertently made available through file sharing.&lt;ref name=&quot;CNET&quot;/&gt;

Since approximately 2004 [[identity theft]] has become more prevalent, and in July 2008 there was another inadvertent revealing of vast amounts of personal information through careless use of a P2P site. The &quot;names, dates of birth, and [[Social Security number]]s of about 2,000 of (an investment) firm's clients&quot; were exposed, &quot;including [those of] [[Stephen Breyer|Supreme Court Justice Stephen Breyer]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;CNET&quot;/&gt;

Researchers have discovered thousands of documents containing sensitive patient information on popular peer-to-peer (P2P) networks, including insurance details, personally identifying information, physician names and diagnosis codes on more than 28,000 individuals. Many of the documents contained sensitive patient communications, treatment data, medical diagnoses and psychiatric evaluations.&lt;ref&gt;Jaikumar Vijayan. May 17, 2010 [http://www.computerworld.com/s/article/9176883/P2P_networks_a_treasure_trove_of_leaked_health_care_data_study_finds?source=CTWNLE_nlt_pm_2010-05-17 &quot;P2P networks a treasure trove of leaked health care data, study finds&quot;], ComputerWorld&lt;/ref&gt;

The United States government has attempted to make users more aware of the potential risks involved with P2P file sharing programs through legislation such as H.R. 1319, the Informed P2P User Act.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.barrow.house.gov/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=346&amp;Itemid=72 &quot;Hearing on Barrow P2P Legislation Held on Tuesday&quot;], ''Congressman John Barrow''&lt;/ref&gt; According to this act, it would be mandatory for individuals to be aware of the risks associated with peer-to-peer file sharing before purchasing software with informed consent of the user required prior to use of such programs. In addition, the act would allow users to block and remove P2P file sharing software from their computers at any time,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.govtrack.us/congress/billtext.xpd?bill=h111-1319 &quot;Text of H.R. 1319: Informed P2P User Act&quot;], ''GovTrack.us''&lt;/ref&gt; with the [[Federal Trade Commission]] enforcing regulations.

== See also ==
{{Portal|Internet}}

* [[Anonymous P2P]]
* [[Comparison of file sharing applications]]
* [[Darknet]]
* [[Disk sharing]]
* [[File sharing in Canada]]
* [[File sharing timeline]]
* [[Friend-to-friend]] or F2F
* [[Open Music Model]]
* [[Privacy in file sharing networks]]
* [[Private P2P]]
* [[Trade group efforts against file sharing]]
* [[Warez]]
* [[Torrent poisoning]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

{{File sharing protocols}}
{{intellectual property activism}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Peer-To-Peer File Sharing}}
[[Category:Peer-to-peer file sharing| ]]
[[Category:Internet terminology]]
[[Category:Intellectual property law]]

[[de:Filesharing]]
[[fr:Partage de fichiers en pair à pair]]
[[ru:Файлообменная сеть]]
[[uk:Файлообмінна мережа]]</text>
      <sha1>rd7b65ztkrug01gvmyqr7ewe8lyzxge</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
