<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Advocacy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>171156</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520738538</id>
      <parentid>520738487</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-31T12:38:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>140.234.255.9</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10998">{{About|promotion of a cause or point of view|legal representation|Advocate}}
{{More footnotes|date=March 2009}}

'''Advocacy''' is a [[political science|political process]] by an individual or [[advocacy group|group]] which aims to influence public-policy and resource allocation decisions within political, economic, and social systems and institutions. Advocacy may be motivated from moral, ethical or faith principles or simply a desire to protect an asset of interest. Advocacy can include many activities that a person or organization undertakes including media campaigns, public speaking, commissioning and publishing research or polls or the filing of an [[amicus curiae|amicus brief]]. [[Lobbying]] (often by [[lobby groups]]) is a form of advocacy where a direct approach is made to legislators on an issue which plays a significant role in modern politics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.npaction.org/article/articleview/76/1/248|title=Lobbying Versus Advocacy: Legal Definitions|publisher=NP Action|accessdate=2010-03-02| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20100402225054/http://www.npaction.org/article/articleview/76/1/248| archivedate= 2 April 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; Research is beginning to explore how advocacy groups use social media to facilitate civic engagement and collective action.&lt;ref name=&quot;Advocacy 2.0&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Obar|first=Jonathan, et al|title=Advocacy 2.0: An Analysis of How Advocacy Groups in the United States Perceive and Use Social Media as Tools for Facilitating Civic Engagement and Collective Action|journal=Journal of Information Policy|year=2012|url=http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1956352}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Forms of advocacy ==
There are several forms of advocacy, which each represent a different approach in the way change is brought into society. One of the most popular forms is social justice advocacy. 

Although it is true, the initial definition does not encompass the notions of power relations, people’s participation and a vision of a just society as promoted by social justice advocates. For them, advocacy represents the series of actions taken and issues highlighted to change the “what is” into a “what should be”, considering that this “what should be” is a more decent and a more just society (ib., 2001.){{full}} Those actions, which vary with the political, economic and social environment in which they are conducted, have several points in common (ib., 2001.){{full}} They:

* Question the way policy is administered
* Participate in the agenda setting as they raise significant issues
* Target political systems “because those systems are not responding to people’s needs”
* Are inclusive and engaging
* Propose policy solutions
* Open up space for public argumentation.

Some of the other forms of advocacy include:

* [[Budget advocacy]]: Budget advocacy is another aspect of advocacy that ensures proactive engagement of Civil Society Organizations with the government budget to make the government more accountable to the people and promote transparency. Budget advocacy also enables citizens and social action groups to compel the government to be more alert to the needs and aspirations of people in general and the deprived sections of the community.
* Bureaucratic advocacy: people considered “experts” have more chance to succeed at presenting their issues to decision-makers. They use bureaucratic advocacy to influence the agenda, however at a slower pace.
* [[Issue advocacy ads|Express versus issue advocacy]]: these two types of advocacy when grouped together usually refers to a debate in the United States whether a group is expressly making their desire known that voters should cast ballots in a particular way, or whether a group has a long term issue that isn't campaign and election season specific.
* [[Health advocacy|Health advocacy:]] Health advocacy supports and promotes patient's health care rights as well as enhance community health and policy initiatives that focus on the availability, safety and quality of care.
* Ideological advocacy: in this approach, groups fight, sometimes during protests, to advance their ideas in the decision-making circles.
* Interest-group advocacy: lobbying is the main tool used by interests groups doing mass advocacy. It is a form of action that does not always succeed at influencing political decision-makers as it requires resources and organisation to be effective.
* Legislative advocacy:  legislative advocacy is the “reliance on the state or federal legislative process” as part of a strategy to create change.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Loue|first=S.|last2=Lloyd|first2=L.S.|last3=O'Shea|first3=D.J.|title=Community health advocacy|year=2003|publisher=Kluwer Academic/Plenum Publishers|location=New York|page={{page needed|date=March 2012}}|nopp=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Mass advocacy: is any type of action taken by large groups (petitions, demonstrations, etc.)
* Media advocacy: is “the strategic use of the mass media as a resource to advance a social or public policy initiative” (Jernigan and Wright, 1996.) In Canada for example, the Manitoba Public Insurance campaigns illustrate how media advocacy was used to fight alcohol and tobacco-related health issues.  We can also consider the role of health advocacy and the media in “the enactment of municipal smoking bylaws in Canada between 1970 and 1995.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Asbridge|first=M.|title=Public place restrictions on smoking in Canada: assessing the role of the state, media, science and public health advocacy|journal=Social science &amp; medicine|year=2004|volume=58|issue=1|pages=13–24|pmid=14572918}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Different contexts in which advocacy is used:
* In a legal/law context: An 'advocate' is the title of a specific person who is authorized/appointed (in some way) to speak on behalf of a person in a legal process. See [[advocate]].
* In a political context: An 'advocacy group' is an organized collection of people who seek to influence political decisions and policy, without seeking election to public office. See [[Advocacy group]] and [[Lobbying]].
* In a social care context: Both terms (and more specific ones such as 'independent advocacy') are used in the UK in the context of a network of interconnected organisations and projects which seek to benefit people who are in difficulty (primarily in the context of disability and mental health).
* In the context of inclusion: [[Citizen Advocacy organisations]] (citizen advocacy programmes) seek to cause benefit by reconnecting people who have become isolated. Their practice was defined in two key documents: CAPE, and Learning from Citizen Advocacy Programs.

== Advocacy groups ==
{{see also|Advocacy group}}

== Transnational advocacy ==

Advocates and advocacy groups represent a wide range of categories and support several issues as listed on [http://www.worldadvocacy.com WorldAdvocacy.com].  The Advocacy Institute,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.advocacyinstitute.org/index.shtml Advocacyinstitute.org]&lt;/ref&gt; a US-based global organization, is dedicated to strengthening the capacity of political, social, and economic justice advocates to influence and change public policy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Cohen|first=D.|last2=de la Vega|first2=R.|last3=Watson|first3=G.|title=Advocacy for social justice|year=2001|publisher=[[Kumarian Press]]|location=Bloomfield, CT|page={{page needed|date=March 2012}}|nopp=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The phenomenon of globalization draws a special attention to advocacy beyond countries’ borders. The core existence of networks such as World Advocacy or the Advocacy Institute demonstrates the increasing importance of transnational advocacy and international advocacy. Transnational advocacy networks are more likely to emerge around issues where external influence is necessary to ease the communication between internal groups and their own government. Groups of advocates willing to further their mission also tend to promote networks and to meet with their internal counterparts to exchange ideas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Keck|first=M.E.|last2=Sikkink|first2=K.|title=Activists beyond borders: advocacy networks in international politics|year=1998|publisher=[[Cornell University Press]]|location=Baltimore, MD|page={{page needed|date=March 2012}}|nopp=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Advocacy and the Internet==

For more than ten years, groups involved in advocacy work have been using the Internet to accomplish organizational goals. It has been argued that the Internet helps to increase the speed, reach and effectiveness of advocacy-related communication as well as mobilization efforts, and as a result has had a positive impact on the advocacy community.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Ope;|first=J.A.M.|title=From the Streets to the Internet: The Cyber-Diffusion of Contention|journal=The ANNALS of the American Academy of Political and Social Science|year=1999|volume=566|pages=132–143}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Eaton|first=M.|title=Manufacturing Community in an Online Activity Organization: The Rhetoric of MoveOn.org’s E-mails|journal=Information, Communication and Society|year=2010|volume=13|issue=2|pages=174–192}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Obar|first=J.A.|coauthors=Zube, P. &amp; Lampe, C.|title=Advocacy 2.0: An analysis of how advocacy groups in the United States perceive and use social media as tools for facilitating civic engagement and collective action|journal=Journal of Information Policy|year=2012|volume=2|pages=1–25|url=http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1956352}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Advocate]]
* [[Advocacy Evaluation]]
* [[Budget advocacy]]
* [[Health advocacy]]
* [[Issue advocacy ads|Issue advocacy versus express advocacy]]
* [[Lobbying]]
* [[Public Library Advocacy]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== Further reading ==
* {{cite journal|last=Jerningan|first=D.H.|last2=Wright|first2=P.|title=Media advocacy: lessons from community experiences|journal=Journal of Public Health Policy|year=1996|volume=17|issue=3|pages=306–330}}
* {{cite book|last=Young|first=L.|last2=Everitt|first2=J.|title=Advocacy groups|year=2004|publisher=[[University of British Columbia Press]]|location=Vancouver, BC}}
* 'Those Who Suffer Much, Know Much' 5th 2010 edition, Cris Kerr, Advocate for the value of Patient Testimony http://www.ldnresearchtrustfiles.co.uk/docs/2010.pdf

== External links ==
{{wiktionary}}
* [http://advocacy.collegeboard.org/ Advocacy &amp; Policy Center] The College Board Advocacy &amp; Policy Center was established to help transform education in America.
* [http://www.publicaffairsworld.com Public Affairs World] The world's first global news and information site on the subject of lobbying.

[[Category:Advocacy groups]]
[[Category:Activism by method]]

[[es:Incidencia política]]
[[fr:Plaidoyer (politique)]]
[[ja:アドボカシー]]
[[pt:Manifestação]]
[[ru:Общественная кампания]]
[[sr:Заступање]]
[[fi:Vaikuttaminen]]
[[uk:Адвокація]]
[[zh:倡導]]</text>
      <sha1>9yqi4cgdu4q2mpjabqjv1h8ub3i34g7</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
