<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Alta controversy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7287601</id>
    <revision>
      <id>511249572</id>
      <parentid>507254681</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-07T17:17:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tec15</username>
        <id>1269086</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added [[Category:Dam controversies]] using [[WP:HC|HotCat]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="4792">The '''Alta controversy''' refers to a political controversy in [[Norway]] in the late 1970s and early 1980s concerning the construction of a [[hydroelectric power plant]] in the [[Altaelva|Alta river]] in [[Finnmark]], [[Northern Norway]].

==Key events==
[[Image: Folkeaksjonen mot utbygging av Alta-Kautokeinovassdraget knapp samisk.jpg|left|150px|thumb|Sami language button (campaign against development of the Alta)]]

The background for the controversy was a published plan by the [[Norwegian Water Resources and Energy Directorate]] (NVE) that called for the construction of a dam and hydroelectric power plant that would create an artificial lake and inundate the [[Sami people|Sami]] village of [[Masi, Norway|Máze]]. After the initial plan met political resistance, a less ambitious project was proposed that would cause less displacement of Sami residents and less disruption for [[reindeer]] migration and wild [[salmon]] fishing.

In 1978, the popular movement against development of the Alta-Kautokeino waterway ([[Folkeaksjonen mot utbygging av Alta-Kautokeinovassdraget]]) was founded, creating an organizational platform for first opposing and then resisting construction work. This group and others filed for an injunction in Norwegian courts against the Norwegian government to prevent construction from beginning.

In the fall of 1979, as construction was ready to start, protesters performed two acts of [[civil disobedience]]: at the construction site itself at Stilla, activists sat down on the ground and blocked the machines, and at the same time, Sami activists began a [[hunger strike]] outside the [[Stortinget|Norwegian parliament]].

Documents that have since been declassified, show that the government planned to use military forces as logistical support for police authorities in their efforts to stop the protests.[http://www.aftenposten.no/nyheter/iriks/article1280217.ece]

The prime minister at the time, [[Odvar Nordli]], pre-empted such an escalation by promising a review of the parliament's decision, but the Norwegian parliament subsequently confirmed its decision to dam the river. More than one thousand protesters chained themselves to the site when the work started again in January 1981. The police responded with large forces; at one point 10% of all Norwegian police officers were stationed in Alta (during which time they were quartered in a cruise ship). The protesters were forcibly removed by police.

For the first time since World War II, Norwegians were arrested and charged with violating laws against rioting. The central organizations for the Sami people discontinued all cooperation with the Norwegian government. Two Sami women even travelled to Rome to petition the Pope. 

The Supreme Court ruled in favor of the government in early 1982, at which point organized opposition to the power plant ceased, and the power plant was built.

==Legacy==

As the first serious political upheaval since the [[Norwegian EC referendum, 1972|debate about Norwegian EC membership]] in 1972, the Alta controversy was important in several ways:
* It put the rights of the Sami as an indigenous people with distinct rights over the lands in Northern Norway, onto the national political agenda. This process reached a key milestone in 2005, when the [[Finnmark Act]] was passed. It is considered that though the Sami lost the battle over this particular issue, they made important long-term gains.
* It unified formerly disparate environmental groups with respect to a common cause.
* Revived Sami interest in their culture and rolled back efforts of the Norwegian government's ''[[Norwegianization]]'' policy.

==See also==
*[[Folkeaksjonen mot utbygging av Alta-Kautokeinovassdraget]]

==References==
* Norwegian Ministry of Foreign Affairs [http://odin.dep.no/odin/engelsk/norway/history/032005-990463/index-dok000-b-n-a.html The Sami in Norway]
* Bård Berg: ''[http://www.galdu.org/govat/doc/25_aar_i_skyttergravene.pdf 25 år i skyttergravene? Fra kampen om Alta/Kautokeino-vassdraget til Bondevik-regjeringens forslag til Finnmarkslov]'' {{no icon}}
* Knut Nilsen: [http://www.aftenposten.no/fakta/tusenarsskiftet/article448340.ece Ungdom som ville redde naturen], in [[Aftenposten]] {{no icon}}
* Lars Martin Hjorthol: ''Alta -  Kraftkampen som utfordret statens makt'', Gyldendal, 2006 ISBN 82-05-33943-0 {{no icon}}

[[Category:Political history of Norway]]
[[Category:Environmental protests in Norway]]
[[Category:Sami politics]]
[[Category:Political controversies in Europe]]
[[Category:Alta, Norway]]
[[Category:1978 in Norway]]
[[Category:1979 in Norway]]
[[Category:1980 in Norway]]
[[Category:1981 in Norway]]
[[Category:1982 in Norway]]
[[Category:Dam controversies]]

[[no:Alta-konflikten]]
[[nn:Altasaka]]
[[sv:Alta-konflikten]]</text>
      <sha1>qllejqk6fbslwmj1zaqvfelg0taan3p</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
