<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Anti-communism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18940658</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521731339</id>
      <parentid>520665251</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-06T21:34:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>184.18.174.216</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* far-right politics */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="60774">{{For|opposition to the [[Soviet Union]]|Anti-Sovietism}}
{{POV|date=June 2011}}
{{Communism sidebar |expanded=all}}

'''Anti-communism''' is opposition to [[communism]]. Organized anti-communism developed in reaction to the rise of communism, especially after the 1917 [[October Revolution]] in Russia and reaching global dimensions during the [[Cold War]].

Most anti-communists reject the concept of [[historical materialism]], which is a central idea in [[Marxism]]. Anti-communists reject the Marxist belief that capitalism will be followed by socialism and communism, just as [[feudalism]] was followed by capitalism. Anti-communists question the validity of the Marxist claim that the socialist state will &quot;wither away&quot; when it becomes unnecessary in a true communist society.

Anti-communists argue that the repression in the early years of [[Bolshevik]] rule, while not as extreme as that during [[Joseph Stalin]]'s rule, was still severe by reasonable standards, citing examples such as [[Felix Dzerzhinsky]]'s secret police, which eliminated numerous political opponents by extrajudicial executions, and the brutal crushing of the [[Kronstadt rebellion]] and [[Tambov rebellion]]. Some anti-communists refer to both Communism and [[fascism]] as [[totalitarianism]], seeing similarity between the actions of communist and fascist governments. Historian [[Robert Conquest]] has argued that Communism was responsible for tens of millions of deaths during the 20th century.

Opponents{{Who|date=July 2011}} argue that Communist parties that have come to power have tended to be rigidly intolerant of political opposition. These opponents claim that most Communist countries have shown no signs of advancing from Marx's socialist stage of economy to an ideal communist stage. Rather, Communist governments have been accused of creating a new [[ruling class]] (a ''[[Nomenklatura]]''), with powers and privileges greater than those previously enjoyed by the upper classes in the non-communist regimes.

==Anti-communist movements==

===Left-wing anti-communism===
{{Main|Anti-Stalinist left}}
Since the split of the Communist Parties from the [[socialist]] [[Second International]] to form the Communist [[Third International]], [[democratic socialists]] and [[social democrats]] have been in conflict with Communism, criticising it for its anti-democratic nature. Examples of left-wing critics of Communist states and parties are [[George Orwell]], [[Boris Souveraine]], [[Bayard Rustin]], [[Irving Howe]] and [[Max Shachtman]].

====Anarchists====
{{Refimprove section|date=December 2009}}
Although many{{Who|date=February 2012}} anarchists describe themselves as [[Anarchist communism|communists]] (spelled with a lower case ''c''), all anarchists criticize authoritarian Communist parties and states. They argue that Marxist concepts such as [[dictatorship of the proletariat]] and state ownership of the [[means of production]] are [[wikt:anathema|anathema]] to anarchism. Some anarchists criticize communism from an [[Individualism|individualist]] or [[anarcho-capitalist]] point of view.

The anarchist [[Mikhail Bakunin]] debated with [[Karl Marx]] in the [[First International]], arguing that the Marxist state is another form of oppression.&lt;ref&gt;[http://dwardmac.pitzer.edu:16080/Anarchist_Archives/bakunin/Bakuninarchive.html Texts by Bakunin at Anarchy Archives]; [http://dwardmac.pitzer.edu:16080/Anarchist_Archives/bakunin/Bakuninarchive.html Texts by Marx on Bakunin at Marxist Internet Archive]&lt;/ref&gt; He loathed the idea of a [[vanguard party]] ruling the masses from above. Anarchists initially participated in, and rejoiced over, the [[February revolution|1917 revolution]] as an example of workers taking power for themselves. However, after the [[October revolution]], it became evident that the Bolsheviks and the anarchists had very different ideas. Anarchist [[Emma Goldman]], deported from the United States to Russia in 1919, was initially enthusiastic about the revolution, but was left sorely disappointed, and began to write her book ''[[My Disillusionment in Russia]]''. Anarchist [[Peter Kropotkin]], proffered trenchant criticism of the emergent Bolshevik bureaucracy in letters to [[Vladimir Lenin]], noting in 1920: &quot;[a party dictatorship] is positively harmful for the building of a new socialist system. What is needed is local construction by local forces ... Russia has already become a Soviet Republic only in name.&quot;{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}} Many anarchists fought against Russian, Spanish and Greek Communists; many were killed by them, such as [[Lev Chernyi]], [[Camillo Berneri]] and [[Constantinos Speras]].

=== Capitalists ===
The communist principle of [[redistribution of wealth]] acquired in [[capitalist accumulation]] is held by anti-communists to be opposed to the principle of voluntary [[free trade]].{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}} Furthermore many capitalist theorists believe that communism interferes with the price mechanism that is only optimized in private competition. See [[economic calculation debate]].

In the ''[[Communist Manifesto]]'', Marx lays out a 10-point plan advising the redistribution of land and production, and [[Ludwig von Mises]] argues that the initial and ongoing forms of redistribution constitute direct coercion.&lt;ref&gt;Von Mises, Human Action&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[coercion]]&lt;/ref&gt; Neither Marx's 10-point plan nor the rest of the manifesto say anything about who has the right to carry out the plan.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Politics and Participation under Communist Rule&quot; by Peter J. Potichnyj and Jane Shapiro Zacek (Hardcover - Jan 1, 1983)&lt;/ref&gt; [[Milton Friedman]] argued that the absence of voluntary economic activity makes it too easy for repressive political leaders to grant themselves coercive powers. Friedman's view was also shared by [[Friedrich Hayek]] and [[John Maynard Keynes]], both of whom believed that capitalism is vital for freedom to survive and thrive.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Friedrich Hayek|title=The Road to Serfdom|publisher=University Of Chicago Press|year=1944|isbn=0-226-32061-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Bellamy, Richard|title=The Cambridge History of Twentieth-Century Political Thought|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2003|isbn=0-521-56354-2|page=60}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many capitalist critics{{Who|date=July 2011}} see a key error in communist economic theory, which predicts that in capitalist societies, the bourgeoisie will accumulate ever-increasing capital and wealth, while the lower classes become more dependent on the ruling class for survival, selling their [[labor power]] for the most minimal of salaries, blaming the effect on capitalism. Anti-communists{{Who|date=July 2011}} point to the overall rise in the average [[standard of living]] in the non-communist West and claim that both the rich and poor have steadily gotten richer.{{citation needed|date=February 2011}} Anti-communists argue that former [[Third World]] countries that have successfully escaped poverty in recent decades have done so using capitalism, most notably [[India]] and [[People's Republic of China|China]]. Anti-communists{{Who|date=July 2011}} cite the [[Mengistu]] regime in [[Ethiopia]] as an example how a Communist regime in the Third World failed to achieve development or economic growth.{{citation needed|date=February 2011}}

====Objectivism====
[[Objectivism (Ayn Rand)|Objectivists]] argue that wealth (or any other human value) is the creation of individual minds, that human nature requires motivation by personal incentive, and therefore, that only political and economic freedom are consistent with human prosperity. This is demonstrated, they believe, by the comparative prosperity of [[free market]] and [[socialism|socialist]] economies. Objectivist [[Ayn Rand]] writes that communist leaders typically claim to work for the common good, but many or all of them have been corrupt and totalitarian.&lt;ref&gt;[[Ayn Rand]], ''[[Capitalism: the Unknown Ideal]]'', 1966, New American Library.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ex-communists===
Many ex-communists have turned into anti-communists. [[Mikhail Gorbachev]] turned from a Communist into a [[social democrat]]. [[Milovan Đilas]], was a former [[Yugoslavs|Yugoslav]] Communist official, who became a prominent [[dissident]] and critic of Communism. [[Leszek Kołakowski]] was a Polish Communist who became a famous anti-communist. He was best known for his critical analyses of [[Marxism|Marxist]] thought, especially his acclaimed three-volume history, ''[[Main Currents of Marxism]]'', which is &quot;considered by some&lt;ref&gt;[http://entertainment.timesonline.co.uk/tol/arts_and_entertainment/the_tls/article5418361.ece TimesOnline.co.uk]&lt;/ref&gt; to be one of the most important books on political theory of the 20th century.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/8157014.stm &quot;Polish anti-Marxist thinker dies&quot;], Adam Easton, BBC News, 17 July 2009&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[The God That Failed]]'' is a 1949 book which collects together six [[essay]]s with the testimonies of a number of famous ex-[[Communism|Communists]], who were writers and journalists. The common theme of the essays is the authors' disillusionment with and abandonment of Communism. The promotional [[byline]] to the book is ''&quot;Six famous men tell how they changed their minds about Communism.&quot;'' Another notable anti-communist was [[Whittaker Chambers]], a former [[Soviet Union]] spy who testified against his fellow spies before the [[House Un-American Activities Committee]].&lt;ref&gt;
  {{cite book
  | last = Chambers
  | given = Whittaker
  | authorlink = http://www.whittakerchambers.org/
  | title = Witness
  | publisher = Random House
  | year = 1952
  | isbn = 0-89526-571-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other anti-communists who were once Marxists include the writers [[Max Eastman]], [[John Dos Passos]], [[James Burnham]], [[Morrie Ryskind]], [[Frank Meyer]], [[Will Herberg]], [[Sidney Hook]],&lt;ref&gt;[[John Patrick Diggins|John Diggins]], ''Up From Communism'', Harper &amp; Row, 1975.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Louis Fischer]], [[André Gide]], [[Arthur Koestler]], [[Ignazio Silone]], [[Stephen Spender]], [[Peter Hitchens]], [[Zita Seabra]] and [[Richard Wright]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Richard Crossman]], ''[[The God That Failed]]'' (1949).&lt;/ref&gt; Anti-communists who were once [[socialism|socialists]], [[modern liberalism in the United States|modern liberals]] or [[social democracy|social democrats]] include: [[John Chamberlain]],&lt;ref&gt;[[John Chamberlain]], ''A Life With the Printed Word'', Regnery, 1982, p.136.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Friedrich Hayek]],&lt;ref&gt;[[Friedrich Hayek]], ''[[The Fatal Conceit]]: The Errors of Socialism'', 1988.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Raymond Moley]],&lt;ref&gt;[[Raymond Moley]], ''After Seven Years'', 1939.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Norman Podhoretz]] and [[Irving Kristol]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Irving Kristol]], ''Neoconservatism: The Autobiography of an Idea'', 1995.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fascism and Socialism ===
{{See also|Fascism|Nazism}}

Fascism is often considered a reaction to communist and socialist uprisings in Europe.&lt;ref&gt;Walter Laqueur. ''Fascism - a reader's guide: analyses, interpretations, bibliography''. Berkeley and Los Angeles, California, USA: University of California Press, 1976. pp. 16-17&lt;/ref&gt; Italian fascism, founded and led by [[Benito Mussolini]], took power with the blessing of Italy's king after years of leftist unrest led many [[conservatism|conservatives]] to fear that a communist revolution was inevitable. Historians [[Ian Kershaw]] and [[Joachim Fest]] argue that in post-[[World War I]] Germany, the Nazis or Nazism ( English long form National Socialism)were one of many nationalist socialist and fascistic political parties contending for the leadership of Germany’s anti-communist movement, and of the German state. The Nazis claimed that communism was dangerous to the well-being of nations because of its intention to dissolve [[private property]], its support of [[class conflict]], its aggression against the [[Middle-class|middle class]], its hostility to small businessmen, and its [[atheism]]. Nazism rejected class conflict-based socialism and economic [[egalitarianism]], favouring instead a [[Social stratification|stratified]] economy with classes based on merit and talent, retaining [[private property]], and the creation of national [[Social solidarity|solidarity]] that transcends class distinction.

===Far-Right Politics===
In Europe, numerous [[Aristocracy|aristocrats]], conservative intellectuals, capitalists and industrialists lent their support to fascist movements. During the late 1930s and the 1940s, several other anti-communist regimes and groups supported Nazism: the [[Falange]] in [[Spain]]; the [[Vichy France|Vichy regime]] and the [[Legion of French Volunteers against Bolshevism]] (''[[Wehrmacht]]'' Infantry Regiment 638) in France; the [[Cliveden set]], [[Lord Halifax]], and associates of [[Neville Chamberlain]] in Britain.;&lt;ref&gt;Carroll Quigley, Tragedy and Hope, 1966, p. 619.&lt;/ref&gt; and, in South America, movements such as [[Brazilian Integralism]].

Anti-communism remained a theme in far right politics after the war. For example, in the US, Frank L. Britton, editor of ''[[The American Nationalist]]'' published a book, ''Behind Communism'', in 1952 which disseminated the myth that Communism was a Jewish conspiracy originating in [[Palestine]].&lt;ref&gt;Hall-Hoag Collection ''[http://microformguides.gale.com/Data/Download/9049000C.rtf Radicalism and Reactionary Politics in America]'' [[Brown University]]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Religions===

====Buddhists====
[[Thích Huyền Quang]] was a prominent [[Vietnam]]ese [[Bhikkhu|Buddhist monk]] and anti-communist dissident. In 1977, Huyền Quang wrote a letter to [[Prime Minister of Vietnam|Prime Minister]] [[Phạm Văn Đồng]] detailing counts of oppression by the Communist regime.&lt;ref name=&quot;hdvnbtdt.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.hdvnbtdt.org/article.php3?id_article=109 Vietnamese Federation For Fatherland's Integrity]&lt;/ref&gt; For this, he and five other senior monks were arrested and detained.&lt;ref name=&quot;hdvnbtdt.org&quot;/&gt; In 1982, Huyền Quang was arrested and subsequently put into permanent house arrest for opposition to government policy after publicly denouncing the establishment of the state-controlled Vietnam Buddhist Church.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iht.com/articles/reuters/2008/07/06/asia/OUKWD-UK-VIETNAM-MONK.php International Herald Tribune - Dissident patriarch of Vietnam Buddhist group dies]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Thích Quảng Độ]] is a Vietnamese Buddhist monk and anti-communist dissident. In January 2008, the Europe-based magazine ''[[A Different View]]'' chose Ven. Thích Quảng Độ as one of the 15 Champions of World Democracy.

====Catholics====
{{See also|Persecution of Christians in the Soviet Union|Persecution of Christians in Warsaw Pact countries|Clerical collaboration with Communist secret services|Christianity in China|Roman Catholicism in China|Protestantism in China|Chinese house church}}
The Catholic Church has a history of anti-communism. The most recent [[Catechism of the Catholic Church]] states: &quot;The [[Catholic Church]] has rejected the totalitarian and [[atheism|atheistic]] ideologies associated in modern times with 'communism' or 'socialism.' … Regulating the economy solely by centralized planning perverts the basis of social bonds … [Still,] reasonable regulation of the marketplace and economic initiatives, in keeping with a just hierarchy of values and a view to the common good, is to be commended.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;See relevant excerpt of the Catechism, paragraph 2425, available at [http://www.scborromeo.org/ccc/para/2425.htm SCborromeo.org]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Pope John Paul II]] was a harsh critic of communism,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cnn.com/WORLD/9801/21/papal.politics/index.html CNN - Pope John Paul's crusade against communism - Jan. 21, 1998&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and other popes shared this view as well, for example [[Pope Pius IX]] issued a [[pope|Papal]] [[encyclical]], entitled ''[[Quanta Cura]]'', in which he called &quot;Communism and Socialism&quot; the most fatal error.&lt;ref&gt;[[Pius IX]]. ''Quanta Cura (Condemning Current Errors)''. 8 December 1864. Retrieved on 11-12-2007 from [http://www.ewtn.com/library/ENCYC/P9QUANTA.htm EWTN.com].&lt;/ref&gt; During the [[Spanish Civil War]], the Catholic Church opposed the left-leaning Republican forces due to their ties to communism and atrocities against Catholicism in Spain, and in many churches and schools prayers were made for the victory of [[Francisco Franco|Franco]].{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}}

[[Lúcia Santos]], a visionary of the [[Marian apparition]] at [[Fátima, Portugal]] was known for her anti-communist beliefs, as well as the message of Fatima in general.

From 1945 onward [[Australian Labor Party]] leadership&lt;ref&gt;H.M.Cremean, Deputy Leader of State Parliamentary Labor Party and Santamaria met with Labor’s political and industrial leaders to discuss the movements assisting their fight against communist subversion of Australian Trade Unionism, F. McManus, The Shouting and the Tumult, page 35&lt;/ref&gt; accepted the assistance of an anti-Communist Roman Catholic movement, led by [[B.A. Santamaria]] to oppose communist subversion of Australian Trade Unions (Catholics being an important traditional support base). To oppose communist infiltration of unions [[Industrial Groups]] were formed to regain control of them. The groups were active from 1945 to 1954, with the knowledge support of ALP leadership&lt;ref&gt;See McManus, pages 35-58 and Jack Kane, &quot;Exploding the Myths, The political memoirs of Jack Kane (1989), pages 18-37&lt;/ref&gt; until after Labor's loss of the 1954 election, when federal leader Dr H.V. Evatt, in the context of his response to the [[Petrov affair]], blamed “subversive” activities of the &quot;Groupers&quot;, for the defeat. After bitter public dispute many Groupers (including most members of the NSW and Victorian state executives and most Victorian Labor branches) were expelled from the ALP and formed the [[Democratic Labor Party (historical)]]. In an attempt to force the ALP reform and remove communist influence, with a view to then rejoining the “purged” ALP, the DLP preferenced (see [[Australian electoral system]]) the [[Liberal Party of Australia]], enabling them remain in power for over two decades. Their negative strategy failed, and after the Whitlam Labor Government during the 1970s it, the majority of the DLP decided to wind up the party in 1978, although a small Federal and State party continued based in Victoria (see [[Democratic Labor Party]]) with state parties reformed in NSW and Qld in 2008.

After the Soviet occupation of Hungary During the final stages of the Second World War, many clerics were arrested. The case of the [[Archbishop]] [[József Mindszenty]] of [[Esztergom]], head of the Catholic Church in Hungary was the most known. He was accused of treason to the communist ideas and was sent to trials and tortured during several years between 1949 and 1956. During the [[Hungarian Revolution of 1956]] against communism he was set free and after the failure of the movement he was forced to move to the United States' embassy on [[Budapest]]. There he lived until 1971 when the Vatican and the communist government of Hungary pacted his way out to [[Austria]]. In the following years Mindszenty travelled all over the world visiting the Hungarian colonies in [[Canada]], United States, Germany, [[Austria]], [[South Africa]] and [[Venezuela]]. He led a high critical campaign against the communist regime denouncing the atrocities committed by them against him and the Hungarian people. The communist government accused him and demanded that the Vatican remove him the title of Archbishop of Esztergom and forbid him to keep giving public speech about the communist torture methods and freedom privations. After a lot of political interventions, the Vatican was forced to accomplish what the sovietic regime demanded. However Mindszenty kept travelling all over the world being a real symbol of unity, cultural preservation, and hope for the Hungarian people, no matter their religion (Lutherans, Calvinists, Catholics, etc.).&lt;ref&gt;Közi Horváth József: Mindszenty bíboros, München, 1980&lt;/ref&gt;

====Falun Gong====
{{See also|Falun Gong|Persecution of Falun Gong}}
[[File:Falun Gong Demonstration.jpg|right|thumb|A demonstration by [[Falun Gong]] supporters.]]

In April 1999, over ten thousand Falun Gong practitioners gathered at [[Communist Party of China]] headquarters, [[Zhongnanhai]], in a silent protest following an [[history of Falun Gong#Zhongnanhai incident|incident]] in [[Tianjin]].&lt;ref&gt;Controversial New Religions, The Falun Gong: A New Religious Movement in Post-Mao China, David Ownby P.195 ISBN 0-19-515683-8&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReidG&quot;&gt;Reid, Graham (29 Apr-5 May 2006) [http://www.listener.co.nz/issue/3442/features/5972/nothing_left_to_lose.html &quot;Nothing left to lose&quot;], ''New Zealand Listener''. Retrieved 6 July 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Schechter&quot;&gt;Danny Schechter, ''Falun Gong's Challenge to China: Spiritual Practice or Evil Cult?'', Akashic books: New York, 2001, p. 66&lt;/ref&gt; Two months later the CPC banned the practice, initiated a security crackdown, and began a propaganda campaign against it.&lt;ref name=&quot;heretical&quot;&gt;(23 March 2000) [http://web.archive.org/web/20030711022606/http://web.amnesty.org/library/Index/engASA170112000 The crackdown on Falun Gong and other so-called ''heretical organizations''], [[Amnesty International]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://fpc.state.gov/documents/organization/67820.pdf | title = CRS Report for Congress: China and Falun Gong | publisher = [[Congressional Research Service]] | author = Thomas Lum | date = 25 May 2006|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;wildgrass&quot;&gt;Johnson, Ian, ''Wild Grass: three portraits of change in modern china'', Vintage (8 March 2005)&lt;/ref&gt; Since 1999, Falun Gong practitioners in China have been reportedly subject to torture,&lt;ref name = &quot;UN.org-2004&quot;&gt;[[United Nations]] (4 February 2004) [http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs/2004/hrcn1073.doc.htm Press Release HR/CN/1073]. Retrieved 12 September 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; arbitrary imprisonment,&lt;ref name=&quot;Leung&quot;&gt;Leung, Beatrice (2002) 'China and Falun Gong: Party and society relations in the modern era', Journal of Contemporary China, 11:33, 761 – 784&lt;/ref&gt; beatings, forced labor, alleged [[Organ harvesting in the People's Republic of China|organ harvesting]], and psychiatric abuses.&lt;ref name=sunnygalli&gt;Sunny Y. Lu, MD, PhD, and Viviana B. Galli, MD, “Psychiatric Abuse of Falun Gong Practitioners in China”, ''J Am Acad Psychiatry Law'', 30:126–30, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=munro2002&gt;Robin J. Munro, &quot;Judicial Psychiatry in China and its Political Abuses&quot;, ''Columbia Journal of Asian Law'', [[Columbia University]], Volume 14, Number 1, Fall 2000, p 114&lt;/ref&gt; Falun Gong has responded with their own media campaign, and have emerged as a notable voice of dissent against the Communist Party of China, by founding organizations such as the ''[[Epoch Times]]'', [[NTDTV]] and others that criticize the CPC.&lt;ref&gt;[http://online.wsj.com/article/SB119508926438693540.html Wall Street Journal: Chinese dissidents take on Beijing via Media Empire]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Muslims====
{{See also|Islam in China}} 

After the taming of Central Asian Muslim Khanates by the Soviet Union, Soviet-style Communists did not have any largescale interaction with Muslim populations until the [[Saur Revolution]] in Afghanistan, 1978. Before this, traditional Muslim clerics rallied against Communist influences in Muslim societies, but any action beyond the sermons was rare. After the declaration in Kabul of the [[Democratic Republic of Afghanistan]], began a civil war that spiralled into the invasion of Afghanistan by the Soviet Union. This event elevated the ideology of [[Islamism]], which was rooted in Afghanistan's anti-Communist struggle, into a regional influence throughout Southwest Asia.

==Literature==
[[File:Herta Müller.jpg|thumb|left|120px|[[Herta Müller]].]] [[George Orwell]], a [[democratic socialism|democratic socialist]], wrote two of the most widely read and influential [[Anti-authoritarianism|anti-totalitarian]] novels: ''[[Nineteen Eighty-Four]]'' and ''[[Animal Farm]]'', both of which featured allusions to the [[Soviet Union]] under [[Joseph Stalin]].

Also on the left, [[Arthur Koestler]] — a former member of the Communist Party — explored the ethics of revolution from an anti-communist perspective in a variety of works. His trilogy of early novels testified to Koestler's growing conviction that utopian ends do not justify the means often used by revolutionary governments. These novels are: ''[[The Gladiators]]'' (which explores the slave uprising led by [[Spartacus]] in the Roman Empire as an [[allegory]] for the [[Russian Revolution (1917)|Russian Revolution]]), ''[[Darkness at Noon]]'' (based on the [[Moscow Trials]], this was a very widely read novel that made Koestler one of the most prominent anti-communist intellectuals of the period), and ''[[Arrival and Departure]]''.

[[Whittaker Chambers]] — an American ex-communist who became infamous for his cooperation with the [[House Un-American Activities Committee]] (HUAC), where he implicated [[Alger Hiss]] — published an influential anti-communist memoir, ''Witness'', in 1952.

[[Boris Pasternak]], a Russian writer, rose to international fame after his anti-communist novel ''[[Doctor Zhivago (novel)|Doctor Zhivago]]'' was smuggled out of the Soviet Union (where it was banned) and published in [[Western world|the West]] in 1957. He received the [[Nobel Prize for Literature]], much to the chagrin of the Soviet authorities.

[[File:A solzhenitsin.JPG|thumb|[[Aleksandr Isayevich Solzhenitsyn]]]]
[[Aleksandr Isayevich Solzhenitsyn]] was a [[Russians|Russian]] novelist, dramatist and [[historian]]. Through his writings, — particularly ''[[The Gulag Archipelago]]'' and ''[[One Day in the Life of Ivan Denisovich]]'', his two best-known works — he made the world aware of the [[Gulag]], the Soviet Union's forced labor camp system. For these efforts, Solzhenitsyn was awarded the [[Nobel Prize in Literature]] in 1970, and was exiled from the Soviet Union in 1974.

[[Herta Müller]] is a [[Romania]]n-born [[Germany|German]] novelist, poet and essayist noted for her works depicting the harsh conditions of life in [[Communist Romania]] under the repressive [[Nicolae Ceauşescu]] regime, the history of the Germans in the [[Banat]] (and more broadly, [[Transylvania]]), and the persecution of Romanian [[Germans of Romania|ethnic Germans]] by [[Stalinism|Stalinist]] [[Soviet occupation of Romania|Soviet occupying forces in Romania]] and the Soviet-imposed Communist regime of Romania. Müller has been an internationally-known author since the early 1990s, and her works have been translated into more than 20 languages.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dw-world.de/dw/article/0,,4774078,00.html DW-World.de]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.goethe.de/ins/us/bos/en5124021.htm Goethe.de]&lt;/ref&gt; She has received over 20 awards, including the 1994 [[Kleist Prize]], the 1995 [[Aristeion Prize]], the 1998 [[International IMPAC Dublin Literary Award]], the 2009 [[Franz Werfel Human Rights Award]] and the 2009 [[Nobel Prize in Literature]].

[[Ayn Rand]] was a Russian-American 20th century writer who was an enthusiastic supporter of ''[[laissez-faire]]'' [[capitalism]]. She wrote ''[[We the Living]]'' about the effects of Communism in Russia.

==Performing arts==
[[The Love-Girl and the Innocent]] (also translated ''The Tenderfoot and the Tart'') is a play in four acts by [[Russians|Russian]] author [[Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn]]. It is set over the course of about one week in 1945 in a Stalin-era Soviet prison camp. As in many of Solzhenitsyn's works{{Citation needed|date=February 2010}}, depicts the perceived suffering of the prisoners and their incompetent but powerful wardens. Most of the prisoners depicted in the play are serving 10 year sentences for violations of Soviet Penal Code [[Article 58]]. In this play, the author first explores the analogy of the camp system to a separate nation within the [[Soviet Union]], an analogy which would dominate his later work, most clearly in [[The Gulag Archipelago]].

==Evasion of censorship==
[[Samizdat]] was a key form of dissident activity across the [[Soviet-bloc]]; individuals reproduced censored publications by hand and passed the documents from reader to reader, thus building a foundation for the successful resistance of the 1980s. This [[grassroots]] practice to evade officially imposed [[censorship]] was fraught with danger as harsh punishments were meted out to people caught possessing or copying [[censorship|censored]] materials. [[Vladimir Bukovsky]] defined it as follows: &quot;I myself create it, edit it, censor it, publish it, distribute it, and get imprisoned for it.&quot;

During the Cold War, Western countries invested heavily in powerful transmitters which enabled broadcasters to be heard in the Eastern Bloc, despite attempts by authorities to [[radio jamming|jam]] such signals. In 1947, VOA started broadcasting in [[Russian language|Russian]] with the intent to counter Soviet propaganda directed against American leaders and policies.&lt;ref name='whitton'&gt;''Cold War Propaganda'' by John B. Whitton, [[The American Journal of International Law]], Vol. 45, No. 1 (Jan., 1951), pp. 151–153&lt;/ref&gt; These included [[Radio Free Europe]] (RFE)), [[Rundfunk im amerikanischen Sektor|RIAS (Berlin)]] the [[Voice of America]] (VOA), [[Deutsche Welle]], [[Radio France International]] and the [[British Broadcasting Corporation]] (BBC).&lt;ref name=&quot;frucht490&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Frucht|2003|p=490}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Soviet Union responded by attempting aggressive, electronic [[radio jamming|jamming]] of VOA (and some other Western) broadcasts on 1949.&lt;ref name='whitton'/&gt; The [[BBC World Service]] similarly broadcast language-specific programming to countries behind the [[Iron Curtain]].

In the People's Republic of China, people have to bypass the [[Internet censorship in the People's Republic of China|Chinese Internet censorship]] and other forms of censorship.

==Anti-communism in different countries and regions==

===Council of Europe and European Union===
{{Main|Council of Europe resolution 1481}}
Resolution 1481/2006 of the [[Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe]] (PACE), issued on January 25, 2006 during its winter session, &quot;strongly condemns crimes of totalitarian communist regimes&quot;.

The European Parliament has proposed making 23 August a Europe-wide day of remembrance for 20th-century Nazi and communist crimes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.euractiv.com/en/culture/europe-ponders-remembrance-day-communist-nazi-past/article-180794 Europe ponders 'remembrance day' for communist, Nazi past]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Albania===
{{See also|Albanian Subversion}}

In 1945, [[Mit'hat Frashëri]] compiled a political platform proposing the formation of a coalition government including, members of nationalist [[Legaliteti]], [[Balli Kombëtar]], and other anti-communist movements in addition to the winning communist group. Stemming was the unsuccessful Western-backed campaign of toppling the communist government through the infiltration of dissidents into the country that was made possible from the unification of the four anti-communist groups Legaliteti, [[Balli Kombëtar]], Independents' Block, and the Kosovars' Group.

In 1946, an armed uprising took place in [[Postribë]] whereby more than a dozen participants were killed and others imprisoned. In 1973, a number of prisoners at the [[Spac]] concentration camp staged a rebellion where the non-communist flag{{Clarify|date=September 2010}} was raised. In 1984, a similar rebellion took place at the prison of [[Qafë Bar]].

Albania has enacted the [[Law on Communist Genocide]] with the purpose&lt;ref name=omri&gt;&quot;The [[OMRI]] annual survey of Eastern Europe and the former Soviet Union, 1995&quot;, ISBN	1563249243, 1996, [http://books.google.com/books?id=T1vFM-R34TYC&amp;pg=PA149&amp;lpg=PA149&amp;dq=%22Genocide+and+Crimes+Against+Humanity%22+albania+law&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=dIAZImrBtC&amp;sig=rqJtNdxAiMLikmflD5NkOe-eBX0&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=DNSSSqaGMIWKsgPb8pgM&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=5#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Genocide%20and%20Crimes%20Against%20Humanity%22%20albania%20law&amp;f=false pp. 149-150], the text of the introductory provisions of the law, translated from the &quot;Official Journal of the Republic of Albania&quot;, no. 21, September 1995, pp. 923-924&lt;/ref&gt; of expediting the prosecution of the violations of the basic [[human rights]] and freedoms by the former [[communist|communist governments]] of the [[Socialist People's Republic of Albania]]. The law has also been referred to in English as the &quot;Genocide Law&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Albania as Dictatorship and Democracy: From Isolation to the Kosovo War, 1946-1998'' by Owen Pearson ISBN 978-1-84511-105-2 [http://books.google.com/books?id=D4wx7kQp4bgC&amp;pg=PP1&amp;dq=%22Albania+as+dictatorship+and+democracy:+from+isolation+to+the+Kosovo+War%22#v=onepage&amp;q=%22genocide%20law%22&amp;f=false p.659]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Post-Communist Transitional Justice in Albania by RC Austin, J Ellison. East European Politics and Societies, Vol. 22, No. 2, 373-401 (2008).[http://scholar.google.com/scholar?hl=en&amp;q=%22Post-Communist+Transitional+Justice+in+Albania%22+%2B%22genocide+law%22&amp;btnG=Search Scholar.Google.com]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;This usage of the term &quot;Genocide Law&quot; is not to be confused with the application of Article 73 &quot;Genocide&quot; of the [http://preventgenocide.org/law/domestic/albania.htm Criminal Code of the Republic of Albania, Special Part, Chap. 1, Crimes Against Humanity]&lt;/ref&gt; and the &quot;Law on Communist Genocide&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''Freedom of Religion and Belief: A World Report'' by Kevin Boyle, Juliet Sheen. ISBN 0-203-41102-1 [http://books.google.com/books?id=MFUZkWWgOtMC&amp;pg=PA262&amp;dq=%22Law+on+Communist+Genocide%22#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Law%20on%20Communist%20Genocide%22&amp;f=true p. 262]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The Balkans:A Post-Communist History by Robert Bideleux, Ian Jeffries. ISBN 978-0-203-96911-3 [http://www.scribd.com/doc/17379442/balkans-post-communist-history p. 78]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Czechoslovakia===
The [[uprising in Plzeň]] was an anti-communist revolt by Czechoslovakian workers in 1953.

The [[Velvet Revolution]] or [[Gentle Revolution]] was a [[nonviolence|non-violent]] [[revolution]] in [[Czechoslovakia]] that saw the overthrow of the [[Communist]] government.&lt;ref&gt;[http://archiv.radio.cz/history/history15.html RP's History Online - Velvet Revolution&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; It is seen as one of the most important of the [[Revolutions of 1989]].

On November 17, 1989, a Friday, riot police suppressed a peaceful [[student activism|student demonstration]] in [[Prague]]. That event sparked a series of popular demonstrations from November 19 to late December. By November 20 the number of peaceful protesters assembled in Prague had swollen from 200,000 the previous day to an estimated half-million. A two-hour [[general strike]], involving all citizens of Czechoslovakia, was held on November 27. In June 1990 Czechoslovakia held its first [[democracy|democratic]] [[election]]s since 1946.

===Hong Kong===
[[File:2009candlevigil1.jpg|thumb|left|A [[Memorials for the Tiananmen Square protests of 1989|Hong Kong demonstration]] in 2009]]

Hong Kong has had numerous anti-communist protests. Some are even opposed to the end of the HKSAR on July 1, 2047, the day on which Hong Kong is scheduled to be fully assimilated into communist China.

[[Memorials for the Tiananmen Square protests of 1989]] are held every year in Hong Kong. Tens of thousands people have attended the candlelight vigil.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cnn.com/2009/WORLD/asiapcf/06/02/tiananmen.hong.kong/index.html Organizers: 150,000 at Tiananmen vigil in Hong Kong]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hungary===
The [[Hungarian Revolution of 1956]] was a spontaneous nationwide [[revolt]] in favour of &quot;genuine&quot; socialism against the [[Stalinist]] government of the [[People's Republic of Hungary]], lasting from 23 October until 10 November 1956. The revolt began as a student demonstration which attracted thousands as it marched through central [[Budapest]] to the [[Hungarian Parliament Building|Parliament building]]. A student delegation entering the [[Hungarian Radio|radio building]] in an attempt to broadcast [[Demands of Hungarian Revolutionaries of 1956|its demands]] was detained. When the delegation's release was demanded by the demonstrators outside, they were fired upon by the [[State Protection Authority|State Security Police]] (ÁVH) from within the building. The news spread quickly and disorder and violence erupted throughout the capital. The revolt spread quickly across [[People's Republic of Hungary|Hungary]], and the government fell. After announcing a willingness to negotiate a withdrawal of Soviet forces, the [[Politburo of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union]] changed its mind and moved to crush the revolution.

===Indonesia===
From 1965 to 1966, over a period of five months, an estimated 500,000 Communists were killed by the [[Indonesia]]n government and allied [[militia]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.insideindonesia.org/edition-99/the-killings-of-1965-66-24011267  ]{{dead link|date=August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Online Encyclopedia of Mass Violence |url=http://www.massviolence.org/The-Indonesian-Killings-of-1965-1966?artpage=2-17 |title=The Indonesian Killings of 1965-1966 - Online Encyclopedia of Mass Violence |publisher=Massviolence.org |date= |accessdate=2012-08-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Japan===
In 1948-1951, in the period of American occupation, a &quot;red purge&quot; occurred in [[Japan]], in which over 20,000 people accused of being Communists were purged from their places of employment.&lt;ref&gt;[[Hirata Tetsuo]] and [[John W. Dower]], [http://www.zmag.org/content/showarticle.cfm?SectionID=17&amp;ItemID=13261 &quot;Japan's Red Purge: Lessons from a Saga of Suppression of Free Speech and Thought&quot;], originally in ''[[Shukan Kinyobi]]'', no. 616, July 28, 2006, translation ''[[Japan Focus]]'' on July 7, 2007, republished [Zmag.org|Zcommunications.org] 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

===People's Republic of China===
{{See also|Chinese democracy movement|Tiananmen Square protests of 1989|Weiquan movement|List of Chinese dissidents}}

The [[Chinese democracy movement]] is a loosely organized anti-communist movement in the [[People's Republic of China]]. The movement began during [[Beijing Spring]] in 1978 and played an important role in the [[Tiananmen Square protests of 1989]]. The [[1959 Tibetan Rebellion]] had some anti-communist leanings.&lt;ref&gt;Chen Jian, [http://www.fas.harvard.edu/~hpcws/jcws.2006.8.3.pdf The Tibetan Rebellion of 1959 and China’s Changing Relations with India and the Soviet Union], Cold War Studies at Harvard University&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1990s, the movement underwent a decline both within [[China]] and overseas; it is currently fragmented and most analysts do not consider it a serious threat to communist rule.

[[Charter 08]] is a [[manifesto]] signed by over 303 Chinese [[intellectual]]s and [[human rights]] activists to promote political reform and [[Chinese democracy movement|democratization]] in the [[People's Republic of China]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.boxun.com/news/gb/china/2008/12/200812171239.shtml|title=Over 5000 people have signed the Charter 08 (《零八宪章》签名已超过5000人)|date=17 December 2008|publisher=Boxun|accessdate=2008-12-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It declares a calling for greater [[Freedom of speech|freedom of expression]] and for free [[election]]s. It was published on 10 December 2008, the 60th anniversary of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights, and its name is a reference to [[Charter 77]], issued by [[dissident]]s in [[History of Czechoslovakia (1948–1989)|Czechoslovakia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/china/3690568/Chinese-dissidents-emulate-anti-Soviet-heroes-with-Charter-08.html|title=Chinese dissidents emulate anti-Soviet heroes with Charter 08 |last= Spencer|first=Richard |date=9 December 2008|publisher=Telegraph.co.uk|accessdate=2008-12-10 | location=London| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20081210153429/http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/china/3690568/Chinese-dissidents-emulate-anti-Soviet-heroes-with-Charter-08.html| archivedate= 10 December 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since its release, more than 8,100 people inside and outside the PRC have signed the charter.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/01/29/AR2009012903758.html Why China's leadership should talk to the Charter 08 movement], ''Washington Post'', January 30, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/world/2009/0131/1232923379427.html Small green shoots of rebellion among ordinary Chinese], ''Irish Times'', January 31, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Poland===
{{Main|Anti-communist resistance in Poland}} {{Main|Cursed soldiers}}

[[Vladimir Lenin|Lenin]] saw Poland as the bridge which the [[Red Army]] would have to cross in order to assist the [[Soviet empire|other communist movements]] and help bring about other European revolutions. Poland was the first country which successfully stopped a communist military advance. Between February 1919 and March 1921, Poland's successful defence of its independence was known as the [[Polish–Soviet War]]. According to American sociologist Alexander Gella, &quot;the Polish victory had gained twenty years of independence not only for Poland, but at least for an entire central part of Europe.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Gella&quot;&gt;[[Aleksander Gella]], ''Development of Class Structure in Eastern Europe: Poland and Her Southern Neighbors'', [[SUNY Press]], 1988, ISBN 0-88706-833-2, [http://books.google.com/books?id=8keIXDyF_EoC&amp;pg=PA23&amp;lpg=PA23&amp;sig=e4aU5iIjo6Khe0AHopBdgU988dw Google Print, p. 23]&lt;/ref&gt;

After the German and Soviet [[invasion of Poland]] in 1939, the first Polish uprising during [[World War II]] was against the Soviets. The [[Czortków Uprising]] occurred during January 21&amp;ndash;22, 1940, in the Soviet-occupied [[Podolia]]. Teenagers from local high schools stormed the local [[Red Army]] barracks and a prison, in order to release Polish soldiers who had been imprisoned there.&lt;ref&gt;{{en icon}} [http://books.google.com/books?id=XKtOr4EXOWwC&amp;pg=PA172&amp;lpg=PA172&amp;dq=czortkow+uprising&amp;source=web&amp;ots=4UPYBcLA19&amp;sig=n2OfmnK2ZszKkwDqcr4G8CR-i5c&amp;hl=en Books.Google.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the latter years of the war, there were [[Soviet partisans in Poland|increasing conflicts between Polish and Soviet partisans]], and some groups continued to oppose the Soviets long after the war.&lt;ref&gt;[[Norman Davies]], Rising '44, 2004, Viking Penguin, ISBN 0-670-03284-0&lt;/ref&gt; Between 1944 and 1946, soldiers of the anti-communist armed groups, known as the [[cursed soldiers]], made a series of [[Raids on communist prisons in Poland (1944&amp;ndash;1946)|attacks on communist prisons]] immediately following the end of [[World War II]] in [[Poland]].&lt;ref&gt;''The Atlas of the Independence Underground in Poland 1944&amp;ndash;1956'', Instytut Pamieci Narodowej, Warszawa-Lublin, 2007. ISBN 978-83-60464-45-8&lt;/ref&gt; The last of the [[cursed soldiers]], members of the militant [[anti-communist resistance in Poland]], was [[Józef Franczak]], who was killed with a pistol in his hand by [[ZOMO]] in 1963.&lt;ref&gt;Violetta Gut: Józef Franczak ps. Lalek. Ostatni partyzant poakowskiego podziemia, [http://www.marszalek.com.pl Wydawnictwo Adam Marszałek (en): Adam Marszałek's Publishing House], [[Toruń]], 2004, ISBN 83-7322-990-6&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Poznań 1956 protests]] were massive anti-communist protests in the [[People's Republic of Poland]]. Protesters were repressed by the regime.

The [[Polish 1970 protests]] ({{lang-pl|Grudzień 1970}}) were anti-Comintern protests which occurred in northern [[Poland]] in December 1970. The protests were sparked by a sudden increase in the prices of food and other everyday items. As a result of the riots, brutally put down by the [[Polish People's Army]] and the [[Milicja Obywatelska|Citizen's Militia]], at least 42 people were killed and more than 1,000 were wounded.
[[File:Politechnika.warszawska.may.1988.png|thumb|Polish anti-communist university students.]]
[[Solidarity (Polish trade union)|Solidarity]] was an anti-communist trade union in a [[Warsaw Pact]] country. In the 1980s, it constituted a broad anti-communist movement. The government attempted to destroy the union during the [[Martial law in Poland|period of martial law in the early 1980s]], and several years of repression, however, in the end, it had to start negotiating with the union. The [[Polish Round Table Agreement|Round Table Talks]] between the government and the Solidarity-led opposition led to [[Polish legislative elections, 1989|semi-free elections in 1989]]. By the end of August, a Solidarity-led coalition government was formed, and in December 1990, Wałęsa was elected [[President of Poland]]. Since then, it has become a more traditional trade union.

===Romania===
{{Further|Romanian anti-communist resistance movement}}

The [[Romanian anti-communist resistance movement]] lasted between 1948 and the early 1960s. Armed resistance was the first and most structured form of resistance against the communist regime. It was not until the overthrow of [[Nicolae Ceauşescu]] in late 1989 that details about what was called “anti-communist armed resistance” were made public. It was only then that the public learned about the numerous small groups of &quot;[[haiduc]]s&quot; who had taken refuge in the [[Carpathian Mountains]], where some resisted for ten years against the troops of the [[Securitate]]. The last “haiduc” was killed in the mountains of [[Banat]] in 1962. The Romanian resistance was one of the longest lasting armed movement in the former [[Eastern bloc|Soviet bloc]].&lt;ref&gt;Consiliul National pentru Studierea Ahivelor Securităţii, ''Bande, bandiţi si eroi. Grupurile de rezistenţă şi Securitatea (1948-1968)'', Editura Enciclopedica, Bucureşti, 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Romanian Revolution of 1989]] was a week-long series of increasingly violent riots and fighting in late December 1989 that overthrew the Government of [[Nicolae Ceauşescu]]. After a trial, Ceauşescu and his wife [[Elena Ceauşescu|Elena]] were executed. [[Romania]] was the only [[Eastern Bloc]] country to overthrow its government violently or to execute its leaders.

===Moldova===
[[File:Chisinau-eu.jpg|thumb|The flag of the [[European Union]] was a symbol for [[Moldovans|Moldovan]] anti-communists in 2009.]]
The [[2009 Moldova civil unrest|Moldovan anti-communist social movement]] emerged on April 7, 2009, in major cities of [[Moldova]] after the [[Party of Communists of the Republic of Moldova]] (PCRM) had allegedly rigged elections.

The anti-communists organized themselves using an online [[social network service]], [[Twitter]], hence its moniker used by the media, the [[Twittered revolution|Twitter Revolution]]&lt;ref name=&quot;twitterrevolution&quot;&gt;[http://www.spiegel.de/international/europe/0,1518,618563,00.html &quot;Twitter Revolution: Fearing Uprising, Russia Backs Moldova's Communists&quot;], Spiegel, April 10, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rferl.org/content/Moldovas_Twitter_Revolution/1605005.html &quot;Moldova's &quot;Twitter Revolution&quot;&quot;], RFE/RL, April 8, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; or [[Colour revolution#Reactions and connected movements in other countries|Grape revolution]].

===Serbia===
[[Serbs|Serbian]] anti-Communist partisans fought during World War II, on the [[Yugoslav Front]]: nationalist and royalist paramilitary [[Chetniks]] conducted a [[guerilla war]] against much the stronger Communist-led [[Yugoslav Partisans]], the latter heavily sponsored by the [[Allies of World War II|Allied powers]], in the last two years of war.{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}}

===South America===
During the 1970s, the [[right-wing]] [[military junta]]s of [[South America]] implemented [[Operation Condor]], a campaign of [[political repression]] involving assassinations and other intelligence operations. The campaign was aimed at eradicating alleged communist and socialist influences in their respective countries, and control opposition against the government, which resulted in a large number of deaths.&lt;ref name=&quot;shock-doc-126&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Klein|first=Naomi|title=Shock Doctrine|publisher=Picador|location=New York|year=2007|page=126|isbn=978-0-312-42799-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; Participatory governments include [[Argentina]], [[Bolivia]], [[Brazil]], [[Chile]], [[Paraguay]] and [[Uruguay]], with limited support from the [[United States]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa3821/is_200610/ai_n17195860|title=Predatory States. Operation Condor and Covert War in Latin America/When States Kill. Latin America, the U.S., and Technologies of Terror|accessdate=2007-10-24 | work=Journal of Third World Studies | year=2006 | first=Ruth | last=Stanley}}&lt;/ref&gt;
===South Korea===
[[Choi ji-ryong]] is an outspoken anti-communist cartoonist in [[South Korea]]. His [[editorial cartoon]]s have been critical of Korean Presidents [[Kim Dae-jung]] and [[Roh Moo Hyun]].

===United States===
{{Unreferenced section|date=February 2009}}
[[File:JFK speech lch bin ein berliner 1.jpg|thumb|[[John F. Kennedy]]: [[Ich bin ein Berliner]].]]
[[File:Is this tomorrow.jpg|thumb|Cover to the 1947 propaganda comic book &quot;Is This Tomorrow&quot;]]
{{main|Red Scare}}

The first major manifestation of anti-communism in the United States occurred in 1919 and 1920, during the [[First Red Scare]], led by Attorney General [[Alexander Mitchell Palmer]]. During the Red Scare, the [[Lusk Committee]] investigated those suspected of sedition, and many laws were passed in the US that sanctioned the firings of Communists. First came the [[Hatch Act of 1939]] which was sponsored by [[Carl Hatch]] of [[New Mexico]]. This law attempted to drive Communism out of public work places. The Hatch Act outlawed the hiring of federal workers who advocated the &quot;overthrow of our Constitutional form of government&quot;. This phrase was specifically directed at the [[Communist Party of the USA|Communist Party]]. Later in the spring of 1941 another anti-communist law, [[Public Law 135]], was passed. This law sanctioned the investigation of any federal worker suspected of being communist and the firing of any communist worker.&lt;ref&gt;Evans, M. S. Blacklisted by History: the Untold Story of Senator Joe McCarthy and His Fight against America's Enemies. New York: Crown Forum, 2007. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

Following [[World War II]] and the rise of the Soviet Union, many anti-communists in the United States feared that Communism would triumph throughout the entire world and eventually be a direct threat to the US government. This fear led to the [[domino theory]], which stated that a Communist takeover in any nation could not be tolerated because it would lead to a chain reaction that would result in worldwide Communism. There were fears that powerful Communist states such as the [[Soviet Union]] and the [[People's Republic of China]] were using their power to forcibly assimilate other countries into Communist rule. The Soviet Union's expansion into [[central Europe]] after World War II was seen as evidence of this. The US policy of halting further Communist expansion came to be known as [[containment]]. This period, up to 1957, is known as the [[Second Red Scare]].

The deepening of the [[Cold War]] in the 1950s saw a dramatic increase in anti-communism in the United States, including the anti-communist campaign known as [[McCarthyism]]. Thousands of Americans, such as the filmmaker [[Charlie Chaplin]], were accused of being Communists or sympathizers, and many became the subject of aggressive investigations by government committees such as the [[House Committee on Un-American Activities]]. As a result of sometimes vastly exaggerated accusations, many of the accused lost their jobs and became [[blacklisted]], although most of these verdicts were later overturned. This was also the period of the [[McCarran Internal Security Act]] and the [[Julius and Ethel Rosenberg]] trial. After the collapse of the Soviet Union many records were made public that in fact verified that many of those thought to be falsely accused for political purposes were in fact Communist spies or sympathizers (see [[Venona Project]]).

During the 1980s, the [[Ronald Reagan]] administration pursued an aggressive policy against the Soviet Union and its allies by building up weapons programs, including the [[Strategic Defense Initiative]]. The [[Reagan Doctrine]] was implemented to reduce the influence of the Soviet Union worldwide by providing aid to anti-Soviet resistance movements, including the [[Contras]] in [[Nicaragua]] and the [[Mujahideen]]s in [[Afghanistan]]. The accidental downing of [[Korean Air Lines Flight 007]] near [[Moneron Island]] by the Soviets on Sept. 1, 1983 contributed to the anti-communism sentiment of the 1980s. KAL 007 had been carrying 269 people, including a sitting U.S. Congressman, [[Larry McDonald]].
[[File:Thatcher Reagan Camp David sofa 1984.jpg|thumb|[[Ronald Reagan]] and [[Margaret Thatcher]]]]
The US government usually argued its anti-communist policies by citing the human rights record of communist states, most notably the Soviet Union during the [[Joseph Stalin]] era, [[Maoism|Maoist]] China, [[North Korea]], and the [[Pol Pot]]-led [[Khmer Rouge]] government and the pro-[[Hanoi]] [[People's Republic of Kampuchea]] in [[Cambodia]]. During the 1980s, the [[Kirkpatrick Doctrine]] was particularly influential in American politics; it advocated US support of anti-communist governments around the world, including [[authoritarian]] regimes.  In support of the Reagan Doctrine and other anti-communist foreign and defense policies, prominent U.S. and Western anti-communists warned that the U.S. needed to avoid repeating the West's perceived mistakes of [[appeasement]] of Nazi Germany.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unz.org/Pub/PolicyRev-1987q3-00069 &quot;Peace in Our Time: The Spirit of Munich Lives On&quot;, by Michael Johns, ''Policy Review'', Summer 1987]&lt;/ref&gt; 

In one of the most prominent anti-communist speeches of any U.S. President, Reagan labeled the Soviet Union an &quot;[[evil empire]]&quot; and anti-communist intellectuals prominently defended the label. In 1987, for instance, in commemoration of the 70th anniversary of the 1917 [[Bolshevik Revolution]], Michael Johns of the [[Heritage Foundation]] cited 208 perceived acts of evil by the Soviets since the revolution.&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.orlandosentinel.com/1987-11-17/news/0160160268_1_soviet-union-soviet-tanks-evil-empire &quot;Cite Soviets' Dark Side While Holding U.S. to High Standards,&quot; by Howard Means, ''The Orlando Sentinel'', November 17, 1987.]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unz.org/Pub/PolicyRev-1987q4-00010 &quot;Seventy Years of Evil: Soviet Crimes from Lenin to Gorbachev&quot;, by Michael Johns, ''Policy Review'', The Heritage Foundation, Fall 1987.]&lt;/ref&gt;

Anti-communism became significantly muted after the fall of the Soviet Union and [[Eastern bloc]] Communist governments in Europe between 1989 and 1991; the fear of a worldwide Communist takeover was no longer a serious concern. Remnants of anti-communism remain, however, in US foreign policy toward [[Cuba]] and [[North Korea]]. In the case of Cuba, the US continues to maintain [[United States embargo against Cuba|economic sanctions]] against the country. Tensions with North Korea have heightened as the result of reports that it is stockpiling [[nuclear weapons]], and the assertion that it is willing to sell its nuclear weapons and [[ballistic missile]] technology to any group willing to pay a high enough price. Much of the US foreign policy establishment does not regard the [[People's Republic of China]] as communist in any meaningful sense.{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}}

===Vietnam===
{{POV-section|date=April 2010}}
In [[Vietnam]], anti-communist movements, including those from pro-democracy and pro-human rights groups, had largely been limited before the advent of the [[Internet]]. This was due to repression of dissidents as well as the Vietnamese government's efforts in censorship and propaganda regarding foreign and domestic policies, including examination of personal mails (especially those sent from overseas), and a heavy censorship of foreign media broadcasts.

Prior to the arrival of the Internet, much of the global anti-communist activities directed towards Vietnam were religious in nature. Clerical North American and European organizations voiced concerns about religious oppressions. Of particular robustness were the organizations of [[Monsignor Tran Van Hoai]], the first Director of the Vatican's Center of Pastoral Apostolate for Overseas Vietnamese.

In recent years, there have been many Vietnamese [[bloggers]] who, with the aid of the [[World Wide Web]], have disseminated information critical of [[Ho Chi Minh]] and the Vietnamese government's relations with the [[People's Republic of China]], the most controversial of which are deals struck between the two communist countries' leaders, such as territorial claims of islands in the [[South China Sea]]. These have sparked intense nationalism and led to much outrage felt even on the part of many Vietnamese themselves. The culmination of the sentiments can be seen in many recent protests held in both former [[North Vietnam]]'s capital [[Hanoi]] and former [[South Vietnam]]'s capital [[Saigon]].

Frequent arrests of some democracy advocates by the government have also led to activism among many Vietnamese who demand a release of all political dissidents as well as greater clarity in their trials. Recently, there have also been protests against the government blocking access to free [[Computer network|networking]] and [[blogging]] services such as [[Facebook]], [[Wordpress]], as well as calls for a unified effort in boycotting government sanctioned blogging services like the so-called &quot;Yahoo! Việt Nam 360plus&quot;.

Anti-Communist organizations that are located outside Vietnam but also hold demonstrations in Vietnam are [[Khmers Kampuchea-Krom Federation]], [[Viet Tan]], [[People's Action Party of Vietnam]], [[Government of Free Vietnam]], [[Montagnard Foundation, Inc.]], [[Vietnamese Constitutional Monarchist League]] and [[Nationalist Party of Greater Vietnam]].

==See also==
* [[:Category:Anti-communists|Anti-communists]]
* [[Anti-Stalinist left]]
* [[The Black Book of Communism]]
* [[Charter 08]]
* [[Chinese democracy movement]]
* [[Criticisms of communism]]
* [[Criticisms of Communist party rule]]
* [[Criticisms of socialism]]
* [[Criticisms of Marxism]]
* [[Mass killings under Communist regimes]]
* [[McCarthyism]]
* [[Rock Against Communism]]
* [[Russophobia]]
* [[Sinophobia]]
* [[Soviet dissidents]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
* [http://communistcrimes.org/ Foundation for the Investigation of Communist Crimes]
* [http://www.globalmuseumoncommunism.org/ Global Museum on Communism]
* [http://www.victimsofcommunism.org/ The Victims of Communism Memorial Foundation]
* [http://www.gmu.edu/departments/economics/bcaplan/museum/musframe.htm Museum of Communism]
* [http://www.cooper.edu/humanities/core/hss3/Blackbook.html ''The Black Book of Communism''], by [[Stephane Courtois]]
* [http://www.unz.org/Pub/PolicyRev-1987q4-00010 &quot;Seventy Years of Evil: Soviet Crimes from Lenin to Gorbachev&quot;], by Michael Johns, ''Policy Review'', Fall 1987.
* [http://izput.narod.ru/rvpimokEN.html Russians In Support of the Idea of International Condemnation of Communism], an open Letter from Leaders of Russian Anti-Communist Organizations to the Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe

{{Fall of Communism}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Anti-Communism}}
[[Category:Anti-communism| ]]
[[Category:Communism]]
[[Category:Political movements]]

[[ar:معاداة الشيوعية]]
[[ast:Anticomunismu]]
[[be:Антыкамунізм]]
[[be-x-old:Антыкамунізм]]
[[bg:Антикомунизъм]]
[[ca:Anticomunisme]]
[[cs:Antikomunismus]]
[[cy:Gwrth-gomiwnyddiaeth]]
[[da:Antikommunisme]]
[[de:Antikommunismus]]
[[et:Antikommunism]]
[[el:Αντικομμουνισμός]]
[[es:Anticomunismo]]
[[eo:Antikomunismo]]
[[fr:Anticommunisme]]
[[gl:Anticomunismo]]
[[ko:반공주의]]
[[hr:Protukomunizam]]
[[it:Anticomunismo]]
[[kk:Антикоммунизм]]
[[ky:Антикоммунизм]]
[[lv:Antikomunisms]]
[[lt:Antikomunizmas]]
[[hu:Antikommunizmus]]
[[nl:Anticommunisme]]
[[ja:反共主義]]
[[no:Antikommunisme]]
[[pl:Antykomunizm]]
[[pt:Anticomunismo]]
[[ro:Anticomunism]]
[[ru:Антикоммунизм]]
[[sk:Antikomunizmus]]
[[sr:Антикомунизам]]
[[sh:Antikomunizam]]
[[fi:Antikommunismi]]
[[sv:Antikommunism]]
[[tg:Анти-коммунизм]]
[[tr:Antikomünizm]]
[[uk:Антикомунізм]]
[[vi:Chủ nghĩa chống cộng]]
[[zh:反共主义]]</text>
      <sha1>igqdw0uyrnu3vyfta8go559p3lv0v2b</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
