<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Anti-cult movement</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1589765</id>
    <revision>
      <id>511351661</id>
      <parentid>502080080</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-08T09:24:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MKFI</username>
        <id>9969665</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Further reading */ +[[fi:Antikulttiliike]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="38946">The '''anti-cult movement''' (abbreviated '''ACM''' and sometimes called the '''countercult movement''') is a term used by academics and others to refer to groups and individuals who oppose [[cult]]s and new religious movements. Sociologists [[David G. Bromley]] and [[Anson Shupe]] initially defined the ACM in 1981 as a collection of groups embracing [[brainwashing]]-theory,&lt;ref name=&quot;bromley-shupe-strangegods&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Bromley | first = David G. | authorlink = David G. Bromley | coauthors = [[Anson Shupe]] | title = Strange Gods: The Great American Cult Scare | publisher = Beacon Press | year = 1981 | location = Boston}}&lt;/ref&gt;
but later observed a significant shift in ideology towards a &quot;medicalization&quot; of the memberships of [[new religious movement]]s (NRMs).&lt;ref&gt;Shupe, Anson and David G. Bromley. 1994. &quot;,&quot; pp. 3-32 in Anson Shupe and David G. Bromley ''Anti-Cult Movements in Cross-Cultural Perspective'', New York, NY: Garland, pp. 9-14.&lt;/ref&gt;

Publications of the [[International Cultic Studies Association]] have disputed the appropriateness of the term &quot;Anti-cult movement&quot;; (see for example Kropveld&lt;ref&gt;
Kropveld, Michael: [http://csj.org/infoserv_articles/kropveld_michael_anexampleforcontroversy.htm An Example for Controversy: Creating a Model for Reconciliation], ''Cultic Studies Review'', Vol. 2 No. 2, 2003.
&lt;/ref&gt;
) with one writer preferring the label &quot;cult critics&quot; rather than &quot;anti-cult&quot; activists.&lt;ref&gt;
Langone, Michael D.: &quot;[http://csj.org/infoserv_articles/langone_michael_academicdialoguepreface.htm Academic Disputes and Dialogue Collection: Preface],&quot; ICSA E-Newsletter Vol. 4, No. 3, September 2005.
&lt;/ref&gt;

== The concept of an ACM ==
&lt;!--Social Bases--&gt;
The anti-cult movement is conceptualized as a collection of individuals and groups, whether formally organized or not, who oppose new religious movements (or &quot;[[cult]]s&quot;). This [[countermovement]] has reportedly recruited from family members of &quot;cultists&quot;; former cult members, (or [[apostates]]); church groups (including Jewish groups);&lt;ref&gt;
Feher, Shoshanah. 1994. &quot;Maintaining the Faith: The Jewish Anti-Cult and Counter-Missionary Movement, pp. 33-48 in Anson Shupe and David G. Bromley ''Anti-Cult Movements in Cross-Cultural Perspective'', New York, NY: Garland.
&lt;/ref&gt; and associations of health professionals.&lt;ref&gt;
Shupe, Anson and David G. Bromley. 1994. &quot;The Modern Anti-Cult Movement in North America,&quot; pp. 3-31 in Anson Shupe and David G. Bromley ''Anti-Cult Movements in Cross-Cultural Perspective'', New York, NY: Garland, p. 3.&lt;br&gt;Barker, Eileen. 1995 The Scientific Study of Religion? You Must Be Joking!&quot;, ''Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion'' 34 (3): 287-310, p. 297.
&lt;/ref&gt; Although there is a trend towards globalization,&lt;ref&gt;Shupe, Anson and David G. Bromley. 1994. &quot;Introduction,&quot; pp. vii-xi in Anson Shupe and David G. Bromley ''Anti-Cult Movements in Cross-Cultural Perspective'', New York, NY: Garland, p. x.&lt;/ref&gt; the social and organizational bases vary significantly from country to country according to the social and political [[opportunity structures]] in each place.&lt;ref&gt;[[James Richardson (sociologist)|Richardson, James T.]] and Barend von Driel. 1994 &quot;New Religious Movements in Europe: Developments and Reactions,&quot; pp. 129-170 in Anson Shupe and David G. Bromley ''Anti-Cult Movements in Cross-Cultural Perspective'', New York, NY: Garland, p. 137ff.&lt;/ref&gt;

As are many aspects of the social sciences, the movement is variously defined. A significant minority opinion suggests that analysis should treat the secular anti-cult movement separately from the religiously motivated (mainly Christian) groups.&lt;ref&gt;Cowan, Douglas E. 2002. [http://journalsonline.tandf.co.uk/link.asp?id=uul6l9b0cc8cy0lw &quot;Exits and Migrations: Foregrounding the Christian Counter-cult&quot;], ''[[Journal of Contemporary Religion]]'' 17 (3): 339-354.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
[http://religiousmovements.lib.virginia.edu/cultsect/anticounter.htm &quot;Cult Group Controversies: Conceptualizing 'Anti-Cult' and 'Counter-Cult'&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The anti-cult movement might be divided into four classes:

* secular counter-cult groups;
* Christian evangelical counter-cult groups;
* groups formed to counter a specific cult;
* organizations that offer some form of exit counseling.&lt;ref&gt;Chryssides, George D. 1999. ''Exploring New Religions.'' London &amp; New York: Cassell, p. 345.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--Ideology--&gt;
As is typical in social and religious movements, no unified ideology exists,{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}} &lt;!-- the given citation by Barker does not support this statement, see talk --&gt;&lt;ref&gt;See for example Barker, Eileen. 2002. &quot;Watching for Violence: A Comparative Analysis of the Roles of Five Types of Cult-Watching Groups.&quot; pp. 123-148 in David Bromley and J. Gordon Melton, eds., ''Cults, Religion &amp; Violence''. Cambridge, England &amp; New York, NY: Cambridge University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; but most, if not all, the groups involved express the view that there are potentially deleterious effects associated with New Religious Movements.&lt;ref&gt;Possamaï, Adam and Murray Lee. 2004. &quot;New Religious Movements and the Fear of Crime,&quot; ''[[Journal of Contemporary Religion]]'' 19 (3): 337-352, p. 338.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--Practices--&gt;

== History ==
===Heresy in Christianity===
{{main|Christian heresy}}
Concern against heretical teaching and heretical groups is part of Christianity from the New Testament onwards. The apostle Paul rebukes the Galatians for accepting &quot;another Gospel,&quot; and the Corinthians for &quot;another Jesus.&quot; [[Irenaeus]] of Lyons (c.115 - c.202) was the first major Christian heresiologist identifying many groups as [[Gnostic]]s (from ''gnostikos'' &quot;learned&quot;). The greatest, and most persistant, of the early church &quot;heresies&quot; was [[Arianism]]. Though [[history of persecutions by Christians|orthodox Christian persecution of non-orthodox Christians]] did not start until a century after [[Arius]]. The [[Middle Ages]] saw persecution of [[Bogomil]]s, [[Cathar]]s and other groups, and the [[Inquisition]] (from the 12th century) formalised the use of torture and execution. Protestantism also combatted heresy with the methods of the Inquisition, most notably the [[Anabaptists]], [[John Calvin|Calvin]]'s burning of the Arian [[Servetus]], and the Anglican burning of another Arian, [[Edward Wightman]] (1612). [[Christian debate on persecution and toleration]] began from the [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]].&lt;ref&gt;Jonathan Wright Heretics: The Creation of Christianity from the Gnostics to the Modern Church (9780151013876) &lt;/ref&gt;
===18th and 19th Centuries===
In both Britain and America civil penalties against [[English Dissenters]] were progressively reduced during the 18th century, and following the [[Doctrine of the Trinity Act 1813]] removed entirely. However orthodox Christian concern against groups such as [[Unitarianism|Unitarians]], [[Quakers]], and others continued, and unorthodox groups proliferated in America.

===20th and 21st centuries===
In the first half of the 20th century, some [[Confessing Movement|conservative Christian]] scholars, mostly [[Protestants]], conducted [[apologetic]]s defending what they saw as Christian [[Mainstream (terminology)|mainstream]] [[theology]] against the teachings of perceived fringe groups. More-or-less mainstream churches and groups continue this activity today on various levels of theological expertise, collectively described as the [[Christian countercult movement]].

Members of this movement normally defined a &quot;cult&quot; as any group which provides its own, unconventional, translation of the Bible or which regards non-canonical writings as equivalent to Biblical teachings.{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}} The Calvinist writer [[Anthony A. Hoekema]] (1963) considered that &quot;cults&quot; included [[Seventh-day Adventist Church|Seventh-day Adventist]]s, [[Mormon]]s, [[Christian Scientists]], [[Jehovah's Witness]]es,&lt;ref&gt;
 {{cite book
 | last = Hoekema
 | first = Anthony A.
 | title = Four Major Cults: Christian Science, Jehovah's Witnesses, Mormonism, Seventh-Day Adventism
 | year =  1963
 | publisher = William B. Eerdmans Publishing Company
 | location = Grand Rapids, Michigan,
 | isbn =  978-0-8028-0445-7
 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and their splinter-groups, such as the [[Branch Davidians]].) Most proponents of the Christian countercult movement keep a distance from secular opposition to new religious movements.

In the 1960s and early 1970s, [[middle-class]] youths and adults started to follow [[new religious movement]]s and other groups (then — as now — usually lumped together as  &quot;[[cult]]s&quot;), such as the [[Children of God (cult)|Children of God]], the [[Unification Church]], the [[International Society for Krishna Consciousness|Hare Krishnas]], the [[Divine Light Mission]], [[Scientology]], and [[Synanon]]. These movements often stood at odds with traditional [[middle class|middle-class]] values and ideas. The families of these young people became worried about the behavior of their children, and about what they (the families) considered bizarre [[belief systems|belief-system]]s. They started to organize themselves into [[grassroot]] movements, some of which merged and became regional or national organizations. One of the first such organized groups in the USA, [[FREECOG]], originated in 1971 with parents whose children had become involved in the [[Children of God (cult)|Children of God]] group.

In its early days, some such groups lobbied for [[conservatorship]]-laws to forcibly &quot;treat&quot; cult members. They tried (and failed) to legalize this practice by lobbying for [[deprogramming]] laws.

The opposition to cults soon consisted not only of concerned parents but of a range of people. Protagonists of the 1970s and 1980s included psychiatrists [[John Gordon Clark]] and [[Louis Jolyon West]], psychologists [[Margaret Singer]] and [[Michael Langone]], congressman [[Leo J. Ryan]], deprogrammer [[Ted Patrick]], and lawyers Kay Barney and Herbert Rosedale, as well as former members like [[Steven Hassan]].

Public opposition to [[new religious movements|NRMs]] grew after the mass-suicide of members of the [[Peoples Temple]] at [[Jonestown]] in 1978.

The cult controversies in the 1960s and 1970s also resulted in growing interest in scholarly research on alternative religions, and in the setting-up of academic organizations for their study.

The controversy divided scholars into two opposing camps:

# The first camp Langone describes as a &quot;religion coalition&quot;, which defended the right of (new) religions and religious groups to continue with their beliefs and practices. This coalition consisted mainly of scholars of religion.
# The second camp comprised the &quot;individual rights coalition&quot;, which defended the rights of individuals against abuse by religious or non-religious groups and individuals. This coalition consisted mainly of [[psychologists]] and [[psychiatrists]]. [[Sociologists]] surfaced in both camps.

Each camp has in the last twenty years produced not only scientific works but also [[polemic]]s, and some proponents still regard the &quot;other&quot; camp as unscientific. In recent years, though, some scholars in each camp have sought some understanding with the opposing position.

== Taxonomies ==
=== Religious and secular critics ===

Commentators differentiate two main types of opposition to cults:

* religious opposition (related to [[theology|theological]] issues).
* secular opposition (generally more concerned about emotional, social, financial, and economic consequences of cultic involvement, where &quot;cult&quot; can refer to a religious or to a secular group). For this type of opposition against cults (which covers a wide variation of backgrounds and motives{{Citation needed|date=October 2007}}), Bromley and Hadden coined in the 1980s the designation ''anti-cult movement'' (ACM). Secular critics of cults realize the diversity of the groups popularly filed under the &quot;cult&quot; label and do not express concerns with all of those groups, but differentiate (for example) between harmful and harmless &quot;cults&quot;, using allegations or evidence of [[communal totalism]], [[authoritarianism]], [[charisma]]tic [[leadership]], manipulative and heavy-handed [[indoctrination]], [[deceptive proselytization]], [[violence]] and [[child abuse|child-abuse]], [[Sexual slavery|sexual exploitation]], emotional intensity in [[group behaviour|group life]], and the use of [[mind control|mind-control]]. Some individual groups get criticized for alleged [[tax]]-privileges, public [[solicitation]], [[faith healing|faith-healing]] and rejection of modern medicine, mental health jeopardy to participants, and [[corporal punishment]].

=== Barker's five types of cult-watching groups ===

According to sociologist [[Eileen Barker]], cult-watching groups (CWGs) disseminate information about &quot;cults&quot; with the intent of changing public and government perception as well as of changing public policy regarding [[new religious movements|NRMs]].

Barker has identified five types of CWG:&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cesnur.org/2001/london2001/barker.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
# cult-awareness groups (CAGs) focusing on the harm done by &quot;destructive cults&quot;
# counter-cult groups (CCGs) focusing on the (heretical) teaching of non-mainstream groups
# research-oriented groups (ROGs) focusing on beliefs, practices and comparisons
# human-rights groups (HRGs) focusing on the human rights of religious minorities
# cult-defender groups (CDGs) focusing on defending cults and exposing CAGs

Barker is an active participant &lt;!-- of what? --&gt;on the subject of cult watching groups.

=== Hadden's taxonomy of the anti-cult movement ===

[[Jeffrey K. Hadden]] sees four distinct classes in the organizational opposition to cults:&lt;ref&gt;
[[Jeffrey K. Hadden|Hadden, Jeffrey K.]], ''SOC 257: New Religious Movements Lectures: The Anti-Cult Movement'', University of Virginia, Department of Sociology
&lt;/ref&gt;

#''Religiously grounded opposition''
#*''opposition usually defined in theological terms''
#*''cults viewed as engaging in heresy''
#*''sees its mission as exposing the heresy and correcting the beliefs of those who have strayed from a truth''
#*''prefers metaphors of deception rather than of possession''
#*''opposition serves two important functions:''
#**''protects members (especially youth) from heresy''
#**''increases solidarity among the faithful ''
#''Secular opposition''
#*''regards individual autonomy as the manifest goal — achieved by getting people out of groups using mind control and deceptive proselytization.
#*''identifies the struggle as about control, not as about theology.
#*''organized around families who have or have had children involved in a cult.
#*''has a latent goal of disabling or destroying NRMs organizationally.
#''Apostates
#*''apostasy = the renunciation of a religious faith
#*''apostate = one who engages in active opposition to their former faith
#*''the anti-cult movement has actively encouraged former members to interpret their experience in a &quot;cult&quot; as one of being egregiously wronged and encourages participation in organized anti-cult activities.
#''Entrepreneurial opposition
#*''individuals who take up a cause for personal gain
#*'' ''ad hoc'' alliances or coalitions to promote shared views
#*''broadcasters and journalists as leading examples.
#*''a few &quot;[[entrepreneur]]s&quot; have made careers by setting up organized opposition.''

== Cult-watching groups and individuals, and other opposition to cults ==

=== Family-members of adherents ===

Some opposition to cults (and to new religious movements) started with family-members of cult-adherents who had problems with the sudden changes in character, lifestyle and future plans of their young adult children who had joined NRMs. [[Ted Patrick]], widely known as &quot;the Father of [[deprogramming]]&quot;, exemplifies members of this group. The former [[Cult Awareness Network]] (old CAN) grew out of a [[grassroots]]-movement by parents of cult-members. The [[American Family Foundation]] ({{As of|2007|alt= today}} the [[International Cultic Studies Association]]) originated from a father whose daughter had joined a high-control group.

=== Clinical psychologists and psychiatrists ===

From the 1970s onwards some psychiatrists and clinical psychologists accused cults of harming some of their members. These accusations were sometimes based on observations made during therapy, and sometimes were related to research regarding brainwashing or mind-control. Examples include [[Margaret Singer]], [[John Gordon Clark]], [[Louis Jolyon West]], [[Robert Cialdini]], and [[Louise Samways]].

=== Former members ===
{{See also|Apostasy#Other religious movements|l1=Apostasy in alleged cults and new religious movements}}

Some former members have taken an active stance in opposition to their former religion/group. Some of those opponents have &quot;affiliated&quot; with the ACM. Some have founded cult-watching groups (often with an active presence on the [[Internet]]), made their experiences public in books and on the Internet, or work as expert witnesses or as [[exit counseling|exit counselors]]. Most of them have associations with cult-awareness groups, for example:

* [[Steven Hassan]]
* [[Arnie Lerma]]
* [[Robert Vaughn Young]]
* [[Lawrence Wollersheim]]
* [[Jan Groenveld]]

Some former members operate in the counter-cult movement, such as [[Edmond C. Gruss]] and [[J. P. Moreland]].

Cult-watching groups often use [[testimony|testimonies]] of former members of cults. The validity and reliability of such testimonies can occasion intense controversy amongst scholars:

[[Anson Shupe]], [[David G. Bromley]] and [[Joseph Ventimiglia]] coined the term [[atrocity story|''atrocity tales'']] in 1979,&lt;ref&gt;
Bromley, David G., Shupe, Anson D., Ventimiglia, G.C.: &quot;Atrocity Tales, the Unification Church, and the Social Construction of Evil&quot;, ''Journal of Communication'', Summer 1979, p. 42-53.
&lt;/ref&gt;
which [[Bryan R. Wilson]] later took up in relation to former members' narratives. Bromley and Shupe defined an &quot;atrocity tale&quot; as the symbolic presentation of action or events (real or imaginary) in such a context that they come flagrantly to violate the (presumably) shared premises upon which a given set of social relationships should take place. The recounting of such tales has the intention of reaffirming normative boundaries. By sharing the reporter's disapproval or horror, an audience reasserts normative prescription and clearly locates the violator beyond the limits of [[public morality]].&lt;ref&gt;
Duhaime, Jean ([[Université de Montréal]]) ''Les Témoigagnes de Convertis et d'ex-Adeptes'' (English: ''The testimonies of converts and former followers'', an article that appeared in the otherwise English-language book ''New Religions in a Postmodern World'' edited by [[Mikael Rothstein]] and [[Reender Kranenborg]] RENNER Studies in New religions [[Aarhus University]] press, ISBN 87-7288-748-6
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
Shupe, A.D. and D.G. Bromley 1981 ''[[Apostasy|Apostates]] and Atrocity Stories: Some parameters in the Dynamics of [[Deprogramming]]'' In: B.R. Wilson (ed.) ''The Social Impact of [[New Religious Movement]]s '' Barrytown NY: Rose of Sharon Press, 179-215
&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Massimo Introvigne]] argues that the majority of former members hold no strong feelings concerning their past [[experience]]s, while former members who dramatically reverse their loyalties and become &quot;professional enemies&quot; of their former group form a vociferous minority. The term &quot;atrocity story&quot; has itself become controversial as it relates to the opposing views amongst scholars about the credibility of the accounts of former cult-members.

[[Phillip Charles Lucas]] came{{Citation needed|date=October 2007}} to the conclusion that former members have as much credibility as those who remain in the fold.  [[Benjamin Beit-Hallahmi]], a professor of psychology at the [[University of Haifa]], argues{{Citation needed|date=October 2007}} that in the cases of cult-catastrophes such as [[People's Temple]], or [[Heaven's Gate (cult)|Heaven's Gate]], allegations by hostile outsiders and detractors matched reality more closely than other accounts, and that in that context statements by ex-members turned out more accurate than those offered by apologists and NRM-researchers.

=== Christian countercult movement ===
{{Main|Christian countercult movement}}

A somewhat similar movement, generally not considered part of the ACM, exists within a recognized religion: the [[Christian countercult movement]] (CCM). The CCM offers two basic arguments for opposition to cults and new religious movement: one based mainly on theological differences; the other based on defending human self-determinism and targeting mainly groups (religious and non-religious) with alleged cultic behavior (according to the definition of the secular opposition to cults).

The trend focusing on theological differences has a very long tradition in Christian [[apologetics]]. Since the 1970s, &quot;countercult apologetics&quot; has developed, out of which the [[Christian countercult movement]] grew. The &quot;CCM&quot; label does not actually designate a movement but a conglomerate of individuals and groups of very different backgrounds and levels of scholarship. Other designations include ''countercult ministries'', ''discernment ministries'' (mainly used by such groups themselves) or &quot;heresy hunters&quot; (mainly used by their critics).

Countercult ministries mainly consist of conservative Christians — the majority of them Protestant, but also including Catholics and Orthodox. They express concerns about religious groups which they feel hold dangerous, non-traditional beliefs, especially regarding the central Christian doctrines (which they define according to conservative views in their respective denomination{{Citation needed|date=October 2007}}). These ministries appear motivated by a concern for the spiritual welfare of people in the groups that they attack. They believe that any group which rejects one or more of the historical Christian beliefs poses a danger to the welfare of its members. Such ministries include:

* [[Reachout Trust]]
* [[Christian Apologetics and Research Ministry]]
* [[Probe Ministries]]
* [[Watchman Fellowship]]
* [[Walter Ralston Martin|Walter Martin]]

=== National and international entities ===

:''For more details see: [[Cult#Cults and governments|Cults and governments]] and the [[FECRIS|European Federation of Centres of Research and Information on Sectarianism]].''

The secular opposition to cults and to new religious movements operates internationally, though a number of sizable and sometimes expanding groups originated in the United States. Some European countries, such as France, Germany, Belgium and Switzerland, as well as China, have introduced legislation or taken other measures against cults or &quot;cultic deviations.&quot;

=== Cult-watchers ===
Cult-watchers include [[Rick Ross (consultant)|Rick Ross]], [[Andreas Heldal-Lund]], [[Hank Hanegraff]], [[Steven Hassan]] and [[Tilman Hausherr]], as well as anti-cult organizations such as [http://infosekta.ch/ Infosekta] in Switzerland, [http://unadfi.org UNADFI] (National Association for the Defense of Families and Individuals Victims of Cults) in France, and the [http://www.agpf.de/english.htm AGPF] (Action for Mental and Psychological Freedom) in Germany.

Specific cult-watching [[government agency|government agencies]] exist (for example) in France ([[MIVILUDES]]) and in Belgium ([http://www.ciaosn.be/ CIAOSN: Centre d'information et d'avis sur les organisations sectaires nuisibles]).

== Anti-cult movement in Russia ==

In the [[USSR]], all the important questions of the state-religious relations were resolved by [[Central Committee]] of the [[Communist Party of the Soviet Union]], [[KGB]], the Counsel about religions. There was no background for any ACM as a social initiative. But some party functionaries thought that all the religions were reaction force and “sects” were especially dangerous.

In [[Russia]] “anticultism” appeared in early 1990s. Some Russian [[protestants]] used to take part in criticizing of foreigner [[missionaries]], [[sects]] and [[new religious movements]]. Their chiefs hoped that taking part in anti-cult declarations could demonstrate that they were not “[[sectarians]]”.&lt;ref name=&quot;iv&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Сергей Иваненко|date=2009-08-17|url=http://www.sclj.ru/news/detail.php?ID=2546|title=О религиоведческих аспектах «антикультового движения»|lang=ru|publisher=|accessdate=2009-12-04}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

Now anti-cult movements, better known as “anti-sectarian movements” take part in making laws about religion in Russia.

Some religious studies have shown that anti-cult movements, especially with support of the government, can provoke serious religious conflicts in Russian society.&lt;ref name=&quot;iv&quot; /&gt;

== Controversies ==
=== Polarized views among scholars ===

Social scientists, sociologists, religious scholars, psychologists and psychiatrists have studied the modern field of cults and new religious movements since the early 1980s. [[Cult debate]]s about certain purported cults and about cults in general often become polarized with widely divergent opinions, not only among current followers and disaffected former members, but sometimes even among scholars as well.

All academics agree that some groups have become problematic and sometimes very problematic; but they disagree over the extent to which new religious movements in general cause harm.

Scholars come from a variety of fields, many of them sociologists of religion, psychologists, or researchers in religious studies. [[Eileen Barker]], [[David G. Bromley]], [[Anson Shupe]], [[J. Gordon Melton]], [[Benjamin Beith-Hallahmi]], [[Benjamin Zablocki]], and [[Philip Zimbardo]] have a research-orientation. Some like [[John Gordon Clark]], [[Margaret Singer]], [[Stephen A. Kent]] and [[David C. Lane]] are opposed to cults, and promote &quot;cult-awareness&quot;. Others such as [[J. P. Moreland]] or [[Edmond C. Gruss]] are considered &quot;counter-cult&quot;. [[Jeffrey Hadden]] and [[Douglas E. Cowan]] focus on the human rights of members of religious groups. Other scholars studying and researching NRMs include [[Irving Hexham]], [[James R. Lewis (scholar)|James R. Lewis]], and [[James T. Richardson]].

Several scholars have questioned Hadden's attitude towards NRMs and cult critics as one-sided.&lt;ref&gt;
Robbins and Zablocki 2001, Beit-Hallahmi 2001, Kent and Krebs 1998.&lt;/ref&gt;

Scholars in the field of new religious movements confront many controversial subjects:
* the validity of the testimonies of former members (see [[#Former members|Former members]])
* the validity of the testimonies of current members
* the validity of and differences between [[exit counseling|exit-counseling]] and coercive [[deprogramming]]
* the validity of evidence of harm caused by cults, for example: [[post-cult trauma]]
* ethical concerns regarding new religious movements, for example: [[free will]], [[freedom of speech]]
* opposition to cults vs. [[freedom of religion]] and [[religious intolerance]]
* the objectivity of all scholars studying new religious movements (see [[cult apologist]]s)
* the acceptance or rejection of the [[APA taskforce on Deceptive and Indirect Techniques of Persuasion and Control]] report (Amitrani &amp; di Marzio, 2000, [[Massimo Introvigne]]), see also [[Mind control#Scholarly positions|Scholarly positions on mind-control]]

Janet Jacobs expresses the range of views on the membership of the perceived ACM itself, ranging from those who comment on &quot;the value of the Cult Awareness Network, the value of exit therapy for former members of new religious movements, and alternative modes of support for family members of individuals who have joined new religions&quot; and extending to &quot;a more critical perspective on [a perceived] wide range of ACM activities that threaten religious freedom and individual rights.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;
Janet L Jacobs: Review of Anson Shupe and David G. Bromley: ''Anti-Cult Movements in Cross-Cultural Perspective'', New York, NY: Garland in ''Sociology of religion'', Winter 1996. Online at http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0SOR/is_n4_v57/ai_19178617/pg_2. Retrieved 2007-09-17
&lt;/ref&gt;
Compare [[conspiracy theory|conspiracy-theory]].

=== Brainwashing and mind-control ===

:''For details, see [[Brainwashing#Brainwashing controversy in new religious movements and cults|Brainwashing controversy in new religious movements and cults]]

Both sympathizers and critics of new religious movements have found the topic(s) of [[brainwashing]] or [[mind control|mind-control]] extremely controversial. The controversy between sympathizers and critics of new religious movements starts with discrepancies regarding the definition and concept of &quot;brainwashing&quot; and of &quot;mind-control,&quot; extends to the possibility or probability of their application by cultic groups and to the state of acceptance by various scholarly communities.

=== Deprogramming and exit-counseling ===

:''For details, see [[Deprogramming]], [[Exit counseling]]''

Some members of the secular opposition to cults and to new religious movements have argued that if brainwashing has deprived a person of their free will, treatment to restore their free will should take place — even if the &quot;victim&quot; initially opposes this.

Precedents for this exist in the treatment of certain [[mental illness]]es: in such cases medical and legal authorities recognize the condition(s) as depriving sufferers of their ability to make appropriate decisions for themselves. But the practice of forcing treatment on a presumed victim of &quot;brainwashing&quot; (one definition of &quot;[[deprogramming]]&quot;) has constantly proven controversial, and courts have frequently{{Citation needed|date=October 2007}} adjudged it illegal{{Citation needed|date=September 2007}}. [[human rights|Human-rights]] organizations (including the [[ACLU]] and [[Human Rights Watch]]) have also criticized deprogramming. While only a small fraction of the anti-cult movement has had involvement in deprogramming, several deprogrammers (including a deprogramming-pioneer, [[Ted Patrick]]) have served prison-terms for the practice, while courts have acquitted others.

The anti-cult movement in the USA has apparently{{Or|date=October 2007}} abandoned deprogramming in favor of the voluntary practice of [[exit counseling]].{{Citation needed|date=October 2007}} However, this remains a subject of controversy between sympathizers and critics of new religious movements, who continue to debate deprogramming's basic assumptions and its relation to rights of freedom of religion.

=== Responses of targeted groups and scholars ===
The Foundation against Intolerance of Religious Minorities, associated with the [[Adidam]] NRM, sees the use of terms &quot;cult&quot; and &quot;cult leader&quot; as detestable and as something to avoid at all costs. The Foundation regards such usage as the exercise of prejudice and discrimination against them in the same manner as the words &quot;[[nigger]]&quot; and &quot;commie&quot; served in the past to denigrate [[black (people)|blacks]] and [[communism|Communists]].&lt;ref&gt;
[http://www.firmstand.org/ The Foundation Against Intolerance of Minority Religions]
&lt;/ref&gt;

[[CESNUR]]’s president [[Massimo Introvigne]], writes in his article ''&quot;So many evil things: Anti-cult terrorism via the Internet&quot;'',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cesnur.org/testi/anticult_terror.htm CESNUR - &quot;So Many Evil Things&quot;: Anti-Cult Terrorism via the Internet&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
that fringe and extreme anti-cult activists resort to tactics that may create a background favorable to extreme manifestations of [[discrimination]] and [[hate]] against individuals that belong to new religious movements. Critics of CESNUR, however, call Introvigne a [[cult]]-[[apologist]] who defends harmful religious groups and cults. Professor [[Eileen Barker]] points out in an interview that the controversy surrounding certain new religious movements can turn violent by a process called [[deviancy amplification spiral]].&lt;ref&gt;
Interview with Eileen Barker, ''Introducing New Religious Movements'' [http://www.fathom.com/feature/121938/ Available online] (Retrieved 2007-10-17 'What can be observed in most of these tragedies is a process which sociologists sometimes call &quot;deviance amplification&quot; building up. The antagonists on each side behave rather badly, and that gives permission for the other side to behave more badly, so you get this spiral and increasing polarisation with each side saying: &quot;Look what they did.&quot;')
&lt;/ref&gt;

In a paper presented at the 2000 meeting of the Society for the Scientific Study of Religion, Anson Shupe and Susan Darnell argued that although the [[International Cultic Studies Association]] (ICSA, formerly known as AFF or American Family Foundation) has presented &quot;slanted, stereotypical images and language that has inflamed persons to perform extreme actions,&quot; the extent to which one can classify the ICSA and other anti-cult organizations as &quot;[[hate group|hate-group]]s&quot; (as defined by law in some jurisdictions or by racial/ethnic criteria in sociology) remains open for debate. See also [[Hate group#Verbal violence|Verbal violence in hate groups]].

An article on the categorization of new religious movements in US media published by ''The Association for the Sociology of Religion'' (formerly the American ''Catholic Sociological Society'', criticizes the print media for failing to recognize social-scientific efforts in the area of new religious movements, and its tendency to use anti-cultist definitions rather than social-scientific insight, and asserts that ''The failure of the print media to recognize social-scientific efforts in the area of religious movement organizations (as our previous research [van Driel and Richardson, 1985] also shows) impels us to add yet another failing mark to the media report card Weiss (1985) has constructed to assess the media's reporting of the social sciences.''&lt;ref&gt;van Driel, Barend and James T. Richardson. ''Research Note Categorization of New Religious Movements in American Print Media''. Sociological Analysis 1988, 49, 2:171-183&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==

* [[Cult apologist]]
* [[Parliamentary Commission about Cults in France]] (1995)
* [[Cult Awareness Network]]
* [[International Cultic Studies Association]]
* [[Ronald Enroth]]
* [[Project Chanology]]
* [[Persecution of Falun Gong]]

== Footnotes ==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==

* Amitrani, Alberto and di Marzio, Raffaella: &quot;Mind Control&quot; in New Religious Movements and the American Psychological Association, Cultic Studies Journal Vol 17, 2000.
* Beckford, James A., ''Cult Controversies: The Societal Response to New Religious Movements'', London, Tavistock, 1985, p.&amp;nbsp;235
* [[David G. Bromley|Bromley, David G.]] &amp; Anson Shupe, ''Public Reaction against New Religious Movements''  article that appeared in ''Cults and new religious movements: a report of the Committee on Psychiatry and Religion of the American Psychiatric Association'', edited by Marc Galanter, M.D., (1989)  ISBN 0-89042-212-5
* [[Michael Langone|Langone, Michael]]: ''Cults, Psychological Manipulation, and Society: International Perspectives - An Overview'' [http://www.csj.org/infoserv_articles/langone_michael_cults_psymanip.htm]
* Langone, Michael: ''Secular and Religious Critiques of Cults:  Complementary Visions, Not Irresolvable Conflicts'', Cultic Studies Journal, 1995, Volume 12, Number 2 [http://csj.org/infoserv_articles/langone_michael_secularandreligiouscritiquesofcults.htm]
* Langone, Michael, ''On Dialogue Between the Two Tribes of Cultic Researchers'' Cultic Studies Newsletter Vol. 2, No. 1, 1983, pp.&amp;nbsp;11–15 [http://csj.org/infoserv_articles/langone_michael_twotribes.htm]
* Robbins, Thomas. (2000). “Quo Vadis” the Scientific Study of New Religious Movements? Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion, 39(4), 515-523.
* Thomas Robbin and Dick Anthony, ''Cults in the late Twentieth Century'' in Lippy, Charles H. and Williams, Peter W. (edfs.) ''Encyclopedia of the American Religious experience. Studies of Traditions and Movements''. Charles Scribner's sons, New York (1988) Vol II pp.&amp;nbsp;ISBN 0-684-18861-9
* Victor, J. S. (1993). ''Satanic panic: The creation of a contemporary legend.'' Chicago: Open Court Publishing. In [[James Richardson (sociologist)|J. T. Richardson]], J. Best, &amp; D. G. Bromley (Eds.), ''The satanism scare'' (pp.&amp;nbsp;263–275). Hawthorne, NY: Aldine de Gruyter.
* [[Brian R. Wilson|Wilson, Brian R.]], ''Apostates and New Religious Movements'', Oxford, England 1994
* Robbins, Thomas and Zablocki, Benjamin, ''Misunderstanding Cults: Searching for Objectivity in a Controversial Field''. Toronto and Buffalo: University of Toronto Press, 2001, ISBN 0-8020-8188-6

==Further reading==

* Anthony, D. ''Pseudoscience and Minority Religions: An Evaluation of the Brainwashing Theories of Jean-Marie Abgrall''. Social Justice Research, Kluwer Academic Publishers, December 1999, vol. 12, no. 4, pp.&amp;nbsp;421–456(36)
* [[David G. Bromley|Bromley, David G.]] &amp; [[Anson Shupe]] ''Public Reaction against New Religious Movements''  article that appeared in ''Cults and new religious movements: a report of the Committee on Psychiatry and Religion of the American Psychiatric Association'', edited by Marc Galanter, M.D., (1989)  ISBN 0-89042-212-5
* [[Massimo Introvigne|Introvigne, Massimo]], ''Fighting the three Cs: Cults, Comics, and Communists &amp;ndash; The Critic of Popular Culture as Origin of Contemporary Anti-Cultism'', CESNUR 2003 conference, Vilnius, Lithuania, 2003 [http://www.cesnur.org/2003/vil2003_introvigne.htm]
* Introvigne, Massimo ''The Secular Anti-Cult and the Religious Counter-Cult Movement: Strange Bedfellows or Future Enemies?'', in Eric Towler (Ed.), ''New Religions and the New Europe'', Aarhus University Press, 1995, pp.&amp;nbsp;32–54.
* [[Thomas Robbins (sociologist)|Thomas Robbins]] and [[Benjamin Zablocki]], ''Misunderstanding Cults: Searching for objectivity in a controversial field'', 2001, ISBN 0-8020-8188-6
* AD Shupe Jr, DG Bromley, DL Olive, ''The Anti-Cult Movement in America: A Bibliography and Historical Survey'', New York: Garland 1984.
* [[Michael Langone|Langone, Michael]] D. Ph.D., (Ed.), ''[[Recovery from Cults (book)|Recovery from cults: help for victims of psychological and spiritual abuse]]'' (1993), a publication of the ''American Family Foundation'', W.W. Norton &amp; Company, ISBN 0-393-31321-2

{{New Religious Movements, Cults, and Sects}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Anti-Cult Movement}}
[[Category:Anti-cult organizations and individuals| ]]
[[Category:Anti-cult terms and concepts| ]]
[[Category:Religious activism]]
[[Category:Social movements]]

[[cs:Antikultovní hnutí]]
[[lt:Antikultinis judėjimas]]
[[pl:Ruch antykultowy]]
[[ru:Антикультовое движение]]
[[fi:Antikulttiliike]]
[[sr:Покрет против култова]]</text>
      <sha1>bay8herlfk2ef8pozsga2zyt29hm3ec</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
