<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Anti-nuclear movement in Australia</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>14517800</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521581993</id>
      <parentid>521581184</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-05T23:01:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Prosopon</username>
        <id>11261637</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Ban on nuclear reactors */ the legislation applies only to New South Wales, not Australia</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="39785">{{Use Australian English|date=May 2011}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2011}}
{{good article}}
[[Nuclear testing]], [[uranium mining]] and export, and [[List of books about nuclear issues|nuclear energy]] have often been the subject of public debate in Australia, and the '''anti-nuclear movement in Australia''' has a long history. Its origins date back to the 1972–73 debate over [[French nuclear testing]] in the Pacific and the 1976–77 debate about [[uranium mining in Australia]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Jim Green (activist)|Green, Jim]] (26 August 1998). [http://www.greenleft.org.au/1998/330/20531 Australia's anti-nuclear movement: a short history] ''Green Left Online''. Retrieved 15 December 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=romps&gt;Koutsoukis, Jason (25 November 2007). [http://www.theage.com.au/articles/2007/11/24/1195753376406.html Rudd romps to historic win] ''The Age''. Retrieved 15 December 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;  

Several groups specifically concerned with nuclear issues were established in the mid-1970s, including the Movement Against Uranium Mining and [[Campaign Against Nuclear Energy]] (CANE), cooperating with other environmental groups such as [[Friends of the Earth Australia|Friends of the Earth]] and the [[Australian Conservation Foundation]].&lt;ref name=bau&gt;McLeod, Roy (1995). &quot;Resistance to Nuclear Technology: Optimists, Opportunists and Opposition in Australian Nuclear History&quot; in Martin Bauer (ed) ''Resistance to New Technology'', Cambridge University Press, pp. 171–173.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hutton&quot; /&gt; The movement suffered a setback in 1983 when the newly elected Labor Government failed to implement its stated policy of stopping uranium mining.&lt;ref&gt;Friends of the Earth (Canberra) (January 1984). [http://www.bmartin.cc/pubs/86sa.html Strategy against nuclear power]&lt;/ref&gt; But by the late 1980s, the price of uranium had fallen, the costs of [[nuclear power]] had risen, and the anti-nuclear movement seemed to have won its case; CANE was disbanded in 1988.&lt;ref name=mc&gt;McLeod, Roy (1995). &quot;Resistance to Nuclear Technology: Optimists, Opportunists and Opposition in Australian Nuclear History&quot; in Martin Bauer (ed) ''Resistance to New Technology'', Cambridge University Press, pp. 175–177.&lt;/ref&gt; 

About 2003, proponents of nuclear power advocated it as a solution to [[global warming]] and the Australian government began taking an interest.  [[Anti-nuclear]] campaigners and some scientists in Australia argued that nuclear power could not significantly substitute for other power sources, and that [[uranium mining]] itself could become a significant source of greenhouse gas emissions.&lt;ref name=md/&gt;&lt;ref name=jg/&gt;

As of 2010, Australia has no nuclear power stations and the current [[Gillard Government|Gillard Labor government]] is opposed to [[Nuclear power in Australia|nuclear power for Australia]].&lt;ref name=support&gt;Lewis, Steve and Kerr, Joseph (30 December 2006). [http://www.theaustralian.news.com.au/story/0,20867,20989451-601,00.html Support for N-power falls]{{dead link|date=September 2012}} ''The Australian''.&lt;/ref&gt; Australia has three operating uranium mines at [[Olympic Dam, South Australia|Olympic Dam]] (Roxby) and [[Beverley Uranium Mine|Beverley]] – both in [[South Australia]]'s north – and at [[Ranger Uranium Mine|Ranger]] in the Northern Territory. As of April 2009, construction has begun on South Australia's third uranium mine—the [[Honeymoon Uranium Mine]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2009/04/24/2552242.htm?section=justin Work begins on Honeymoon uranium mine] (24 April 2009), ''ABC News''. Retrieved 15 December 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Australia has no [[nuclear weapons]].

{{Anti-nuclear movement}}

==History==
===1950s and 1960s===
{{See also|Nuclear weapons tests in Australia}}
[[File:AusNucTestSites.svg|300px|thumb|Map showing nuclear test sites in Australia]]

In 1952 the Australian Government established the [[Rum Jungle, Northern Territory|Rum Jungle Uranium Mine]] 85 kilometres south of Darwin. Local aboriginal communities were not consulted and the mine site became an environmental disaster.&lt;ref name=jv/&gt; 

Also in 1952, the [[Liberal Party of Australia|Liberal Government]] passed legislation, the ''Defence (Special Undertakings) Act 1952'', which allowed the British Government access to remote parts of Australia to undertake atmospheric nuclear weapons tests. The general public were largely unaware of the risks from the testing program, stemming from official secrecy about the testing program and the remote locations of the test sites.&lt;ref name=brit&gt;Australian Government. [http://www.aic.gov.au/en/publications/previous%20series/lcj/1-20/wayward/ch16.aspx A toxic legacy: British nuclear weapons testing in Australia].&lt;/ref&gt; But as the &quot;Ban the Bomb&quot; movement gathered momentum in Western societies throughout the 1950s, so too did opposition to the British tests in Australia. An opinion poll taken in 1957 showed 49 per cent of the Australian public were opposed to the tests and only 39 per cent in favour.&lt;ref name=brit/&gt; In 1964, Peace Marches which featured &quot;Ban the bomb&quot; placards, were held in several Australian capital cities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://espace.library.uq.edu.au/view/UQ:114192 Women with Ban the Bomb banner during Peace march on Sunday 5 April 1964, Brisbane, Australia] Retrieved 15 December 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://espace.library.uq.edu.au/view/UQ:114194 Girl with placard Ban nuclear tests during Peace march on Sunday 5 April 1964, Brisbane, Australia] Retrieved 15 December 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1969, a 500 MW nuclear power plant was [[Jervis Bay Nuclear Power Plant|proposed for the Jervis Bay Territory]], 200&amp;nbsp;km south of [[Sydney]].&lt;ref name=bau/&gt; A local opposition campaign began, and the South Coast Trades and Labour Council (covering workers in the region) announced that it would refuse to build the reactor.&lt;ref&gt;Falk, Jim (1982). ''Gobal Fission:The Battle Over Nuclear Power'', p. 260.&lt;/ref&gt; Some environmental studies and site works were completed, and two rounds of tenders were called and evaluated, but in 1971 the Australian government decided not to proceed with the project, citing economic reasons.&lt;ref name=bau/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;'Gorton gave nod to nuclear power plant', (1 January 2000), ''The Age''.&lt;/ref&gt;

===1970s===
[[File:Ranger Uranium Mine in Kakadu National Park.jpeg|right|thumb| [[Ranger Uranium Mine]] in [[Kakadu National Park]]]]
[[File:Aerial view of the Ranger 3 site at Kakadu's Ranger Uranium Mine.jpg|thumb|right|Aerial view of the Ranger 3 site located within Kakadu National Park.]]

The 1972–73 debate over [[French nuclear testing]] in the Pacific mobilised several groups, including some trade unions.&lt;ref name=Martin/&gt; In 1972 the [[International Court of Justice]] in a case launched by Australia and New Zealand, ordered that the French cease atmospheric nuclear testing at [[Mururoa]] atoll.&lt;ref&gt;Dewes, Kate and Green, Robert (1999). [http://www.disarmsecure.org/Aotearoa_New_Zealand_At_The_World_Court.pdf Aotera/ New Zealand at the World Court] The Raven Press, pp. 11–15.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1974 and 1975 this concern came to focus on uranium mining in Australia and several [[Friends of the Earth]] groups were formed.&lt;ref name=Martin/&gt; The [[Australian Conservation Foundation]] also began voicing concern about uranium mining and supporting the activities of the grass-roots organisations. Concern about the environmental effects of uranium mining was a significant factor and poor management of waste at an early uranium mine, [[Rum Jungle, Northern Territory|Rum Jungle]], led it to become a significant pollution problem in the 1970s.&lt;ref name=Martin/&gt; The Australian anti-nuclear movement also acquired initial impetus from notable individuals who publicly voiced nuclear concerns, such as nuclear scientists Richard Temple and Rob Robotham, and poets [[Dorothy Auchterlonie|Dorothy Green]] and [[Judith Wright]].&lt;ref name=Martin&gt;Martin, Brian (Summer 1982). [http://www.bmartin.cc/pubs/82alternatives.html The Australian anti-uranium movement] ''Alternatives: Perspectives on Society and Environment'', Volume 10, Number 4, pp. 26–35. Retrieved 15 December 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

The years 1976 and 1977 saw uranium mining become a major political issue, with the [[Russell Walter Fox|Ranger Inquiry (Fox) report]] opening up a public debate about uranium mining.&lt;ref name=mb&gt;Bauer, Martin (ed) (1995). ''Resistance to New Technology'', Cambridge University Press, p. 173.&lt;/ref&gt; Several groups specifically concerned with nuclear issues were established, including the Movement Against Uranium Mining (founded in 1976) and [[Campaign Against Nuclear Energy]] (formed in South Australia in 1976), cooperating with other environmental groups such as Friends of the Earth (which came to Australia in 1975) and the Australian Conservation Foundation (formed in 1975).&lt;ref name=&quot;Hutton&quot;&gt;Hutton, Drew and Connors, Libby (1999). ''A History of the Australian Environmental Movement'', Cambridge University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=mb/&gt; 

In November and December 1976, 7,000 people marched through the streets of Australian cities, protesting against uranium mining. The Uranium Moratorium group was formed and it called for a five-year moritorium on uranium mining.  In April 1977 the first national demonstration co-ordinated by the Uranium Moratorium brought around 15,000 demonstrators into the streets of Melbourne, 5,000 in Sydney, and smaller numbers elsewhere.&lt;ref name=jf&gt;Falk, Jim (1982). ''Gobal Fission:The Battle Over Nuclear Power'', pp. 264–5.&lt;/ref&gt; A National signature campaign attracted over 250,000 signatures calling for a five-year moratorium.  In August, another demonstration brought 50,000 people out nationally and the opposition to uranium mining looked like a potential political force.&lt;ref name=jf/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cawte, Alice (1992). ''Atomic Australia 1944–1990'', New South Wales University Press, p. 156.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1977, the [[Australian Labor Party]] (ALP) national conference passed a motion in favour of an indefinite moratorium on uranium mining, and the anti-nuclear movement acted to support the Labor Party and help it regain office.  However, a setback for the movement occurred in 1982 when another ALP conference overturned its anti-uranium policy in favour of a &quot;one mine policy&quot;.  After the ALP won power in 1983, the 1984 ALP conference voted in favour of a &quot;[[Three mine policy]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Burgmann, Verity (2003). [http://books.google.com.au/books?id=atpiAdA9IEMC&amp;pg=PA172&amp;lpg=PA172&amp;dq=%22Campaign+Against+Nuclear+Energy%22+australia&amp;source=web&amp;ots=C1VPjptDVC&amp;sig=EtLkUVNTkS__H7zeNbY_0liKq9o&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;resnum=10&amp;ct=result#PPA174,M1 Power, Profit and Protest] pp. 174–175. Retrieved 15 December 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; This referred to the then three existing uranium mines in Australia, [[Nabarlek Uranium Mine|Nabarlek]], [[Ranger Uranium Mine|Ranger]] and [[Olympic Dam, South Australia|Roxby Downs/Olympic Dam]], and articulated ALP support for pre-existing mines and contracts, but opposition to any new mining.&lt;ref&gt;Evans, Chris (23 March 2007). Labor &amp; uranium: an evolution, ''Labor E-herald''.&lt;/ref&gt;

===1980s and 1990s===
Between 1979 and 1984, the majority of what is now [[Kakadu National Park]] was created, surrounding but not including the Ranger uranium mine. Tension between mining and conservation values led to long running [[Uranium mining in Kakadu National Park|controversy around mining in the Park region]].

The two themes for the 1980 [[Hiroshima Day]] march and rally in Sydney, sponsored by the [[Movement Against Uranium Mining]] (MAUM), were:  &quot;Keep uranium in the ground&quot; and &quot;No to nuclear war.&quot;  Later that year, the Sydney city council officially proclaimed Sydney nuclear-free, in an action similar to that taken by many other local councils throughout Australia.&lt;ref name=lsw/&gt;

In the 1980s, academic critics (such as [[Jim Falk]]) discussed the &quot;deadly connection&quot; between uranium mining, nuclear reactors and nuclear weapons, linking Australia's nuclear policy to [[nuclear proliferation]] and the &quot;plutonium economy&quot;.&lt;ref name=mc/&gt; 

In the 1980s, Australia experienced a significant growth of nuclear disarmament activism: 
&lt;blockquote&gt;
On Palm Sunday 1982, an estimated 100,000 Australians participated in anti-nuclear rallies in the nation's biggest cities. Growing year by year, the rallies drew 350,000 participants in 1985.&lt;ref name=lsw/&gt; The movement focused on halting Australia's uranium mining and exports, abolishing nuclear weapons, removing foreign military bases from Australia's soil, and creating a nuclear-free Pacific. Public opinion surveys found that about half of Australians opposed uranium mining and export, as well as the visits of U.S. nuclear warships, that 72 percent thought the use of nuclear weapons could never be justified, and that 80 percent favoured building a nuclear-free world.&lt;ref name=lsw&gt;Wittner, Lawrence S. (22 June 2009). [http://www.japanfocus.org/-Lawrence_S_-Wittner/3179 Nuclear Disarmament Activism in Asia and the Pacific, 1971–1996] ''The Asia-Pacific Journal'', Vol. 25-5-09.&lt;/ref&gt;  
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The [[Nuclear Disarmament Party]] won a Senate seat in 1984, but soon faded from the political scene.&lt;ref name=chron/&gt; The years of the Hawke-Keating ALP governments (1983–1996) were characterised by an &quot;uneasy standoff in the uranium debate&quot;. The ALP acknowledged community feeling against uranium mining but was reluctant to move against the industry.&lt;ref name=past&gt;Martin, Brian (Second Quarter 2007). [http://www.bmartin.cc/pubs/07sa.html Opposing nuclear power: past and present] ''Social Alternatives'', Vol. 26, No. 2, pp. 43–47. Retrieved 15 December 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=bb/&gt;  

The 1986 Palm Sunday anti-nuclear rallies drew 250,000 people.  In Melbourne, the seamen's union boycotted the arrival of foreign nuclear warships.&lt;ref name=lsw/&gt; 

Australia's only nuclear energy education facility, the former School of Nuclear Engineering at the [[University of New South Wales]], closed in 1986.&lt;ref name=agelidis&gt;Agelidis, Vassilios (7 December 2010). [http://www.abc.net.au/unleashed/41882.html Too late for nuclear] ''ABC News''.&lt;/ref&gt; 

By the late 1980s, the price of uranium had fallen, and the costs of nuclear power had risen, and the anti-nuclear movement seemed to have won its case. The Campaign Against Nuclear Energy disbanded itself in 1988,&lt;ref name=mc/&gt; two years after the [[Chernobyl Disaster]].  

The government policy preventing new uranium mines continued into the 1990s, despite occasional reviews and debate. Following protest marches in Sydney, Melbourne and Brisbane during 1998, a proposed mine at [[Jabiluka]] was blocked.&lt;ref name=past/&gt;&lt;ref name=bb/&gt;

Also in 1998, there was a proposal from an international consortium, [[Pangea Resources]], to establish a [[nuclear waste]] dump in Western Australia. The plan, to store 20 per cent of the world's spent nuclear fuel and weapons material, was &quot;publicly condemned and abandoned&quot;.&lt;ref name=chron&gt;[[Four Corners (TV program)|Four Corners]].  (2005). [http://www.abc.net.au/4corners/content/2005/20050822_nuclear/nuclear-chronology.htm Chronology – Australia's Nuclear Political History] Retrieved 15 December 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Holland, Ian (2002). 'Waste Not Want Not? Australia and the Politics of High-level Nuclear Waste', ''Australian Journal of Political Science'', Vol. 37, No. 2, pp. 283–301.&lt;/ref&gt;

===2000s===
In 2000, the [[Ranger Uranium Mine]] in the [[Northern Territory]] and the [[Olympic Dam, South Australia|Roxby Downs/Olympic Dam]] mine in [[South Australia]] continued to operate, but [[Narbarlek Uranium Mine]] had closed. A third uranium mine, [[Beverley Uranium Mine]] in SA, was also operating. Several advanced projects, such as Honeymoon in SA, Jabiluka in the Northern Territory and Yeelirrie in WA were on hold because of political and indigenous opposition.&lt;ref name=chron/&gt;&lt;ref name=bb&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/74196.stm Anti-uranium demos in Australia] (5 April 1998), ''BBC News''. Retrieved 15 December 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
 
In May 2000 there was an anti-nuclear demonstration at the [[Beverley Uranium Mine]], which involved about 100 protesters. Ten of the protesters were mistreated by police and were later awarded more than $700,000 in damages from the South Australian government.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.smh.com.au/national/antinuke-protesters-awarded-700000-for-feral-treatment-20100409-rxyv.html Anti-nuke protesters awarded $700,000 for 'feral' treatment] (9 April 2010), ''Sydney Morning Herald''.&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the [[McClelland Royal Commission]], a large clean-up was completed in outback South Australia in 2000, after [[British nuclear tests at Maralinga|nuclear testing at Maralinga]] during the 1950s contaminated the region. The cleanup lasted three years, and cost over A$100&amp;nbsp;million, but there was controversy over the methods used and success of the operation.&lt;ref name=chron/&gt;

As uranium prices began rising from about 2003, proponents of nuclear power advocated it as a solution to global warming and the Australian government began taking an interest. However, in June 2005, the Senate passed a motion opposing nuclear power for Australia.&lt;ref name=chron/&gt; Then, in November 2006, the House of Representatives Standing Committee on Industry and Resources released a pro-nuclear report into Australia's uranium.&lt;ref&gt;House of Representatives Standing Committee on Industry and Resources (2006). [http://www.aph.gov.au/house/committee/Isr/uranium/report/fullreport.pdf Australia’s uranium – Greenhouse friendly fuel for an energy hungry world]{{dead link|date=September 2012}} Retrieved 15 December 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;  In late 2006 and early 2007, then Prime Minister [[John Howard]] made widely reported statements in favour of nuclear power, on environmental grounds.&lt;ref name=past/&gt; 

Faced with these proposals to examine nuclear power as a possible response to climate change, anti-nuclear campaigners and scientists in Australia emphasised claims that nuclear power could not significantly substitute for other power sources, and that uranium mining itself could become a significant source of greenhouse gas emissions.&lt;ref name=md&gt;Diesendorf, Mark (2007). [http://www.sustainabilitycentre.com.au/Wedges_final.pdf Paths to a Low-Carbon Future: Reducing Australia’s Greenhouse Gas Emissions by 30 per cent by 2020 (PDF)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=jg&gt;Green, Jim (2005). [http://www.foe.org.au/anti-nuclear/issues/nfc/nuclear-climate Nuclear Power: No Solution to Climate Change (PDF)]{{dead link|date=September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Anti-nuclear campaigns were given added impetus by public concern about the sites for possible reactors: fears exploited by anti-nuclear power political parties in the lead-up to a national election in 2007.&lt;ref&gt;Franklin, Matthew and Wardill,  Steven (6 June 2006). PM nukes Labor's &quot;campaign of fear&quot;, ''Courier-Mail''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kerr, Joseph and Lewis, Steve (30 December 2006). Support for N-power plants falls, ''The Australian''.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Kevin Rudd|Rudd]] Labor government elected in 2007 opposed nuclear power for Australia.&lt;ref name=romps/&gt;&lt;ref name=support/&gt; The anti-nuclear movement continues to be active in Australia, opposing expansion of existing uranium mines,&lt;ref&gt;Pedersen, Ty (26 January 2008). [http://www.greenleft.org.au/2008/737/38157 Olympic Dam expansion: a risk too great], ''Green Left Weekly''. Retrieved 15 December 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; lobbying against the development of nuclear power in Australia, and criticising proposals for nuclear waste disposal sites, the main candidate being [[Muckaty station]] in the Northern Territory.&lt;ref&gt;Anti-nuclear campaigners say Muckaty will be dumped, (26 November 2007). ''ABC News''.&lt;/ref&gt;

As of October 2009, the Australian government was continuing to plan for a nuclear waste dump in the Northern Territory. However, there has been opposition from indigenous people, the NT government, and wider NT community.&lt;ref&gt;Sweeney, Dave (October 2009). Australia's Nuclear Landscape, ''Habitat Australia'', pp. 15–16.&lt;/ref&gt; In November 2009, about 100 anti-nuclear protesters assembled outside the Alice Springs parliamentary sittings, urging the Northern Territory Government not to approve a nearby uranium mine site.&lt;ref&gt;Nancarrow, Kirsty (24 November 2009). [http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2009/11/24/2751998.htm 100 protest in Alice against uranium mine], ''ABC News''.&lt;/ref&gt;

===2010s===
As of early April 2010, more than 200 environmentalists and indigenous people gathered in [[Tennant Creek]] to oppose a radioactive waste dump being built on Muckaty Station in the Northern Territory.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2010/04/05/2864076.htm Hundreds rally to stop nuclear dump] (5 April 2010), ''ABC News''.&lt;/ref&gt;

Western Australia has a significant share of the Australia's uranium reserves, but between 2002 and 2008, a state-wide ban on uranium mining was in force. The ban was lifted when the Liberal Party was voted into power in the state and, as of 2010, many companies are exploring for uranium in Western Australia. One of the industry's major players, the mining company [[BHP Billiton]], plans to develop the [[Yeelirrie uranium project]] in 2011 in a 17&amp;nbsp;billion dollar project.&lt;ref&gt;Boylan, Jessie (9 August 2010).  [http://www.guardian.co.uk/environment/2010/aug/09/austrailia-aboriginal-uranium-mining Australia's aboriginal communities clamour against uranium mining] ''The Guardian''.&lt;/ref&gt; Two other projects in Western Australia are further advanced then BHP's Yeelirrie, these being the [[Lake Way uranium project]], which is pursued by Toro Energy and scheduled for production by 2013, and the [[Lake Maitland uranium project]], pursued by Mega Uranium, which has a proposed start-of-production date of 2012.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.perthnow.com.au/news/special-features/great-science-debates-of-the-next-decade-spotlight-on-uranium/story-e6frg1ac-1225825647309 Great science debates of the next decade: Spotlight on uranium] perthnow.com.au, published: 1 February 2010, accessed: 13 February 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Native&quot; &gt;[http://news.smh.com.au/breaking-news-business/toro-gets-approval-for-uranium-project-20100107-lvkv.html Toro gets approval for uranium project] ''[[The Sydney Morning Herald]]'', published: 7 January 2010, accessed: 13 February 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ABARE1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.abareconomics.com/interactive/09ac_mar/htm/uranium.htm|title=Uranium Outlook to 2013–14|work=[[Australian Bureau of Agricultural and Resource Economics]]|author=Michael Lampard|accessdate=2011-02-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As of late 2010, there are calls for Australians to debate whether the nation should adopt nuclear power as part of its energy mix. Nuclear power is seen to be &quot;a divisive issue that can arouse deep passions among those for and against&quot;.&lt;ref name=agelidis/&gt;

Following the March 2011 [[Fukushima I nuclear accidents|Fukushima nuclear emergency]] in Japan, where three nuclear reactors were damaged by explosions, [[Ian Lowe]] sees the nuclear power option as being risky and unworkable for Australia. Lowe says nuclear power is too expensive, with insurmountable problems associated with waste disposal and weapons proliferation. It is also not a fast enough response to address climate change. Lowe advocates [[renewable energy]] which is &quot;quicker, less expensive and less dangerous than nuclear&quot;.&lt;ref name=lowenuke&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.theage.com.au/opinion/politics/no-nukes-now-or-ever-20110319-1c1ed.html |title=No nukes now, or ever |author=Ian Lowe  |date=20 March 2011 |work=The Age }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In December 2011, the sale of uranium to India was a contentious issue. MPs clashed over the issue and protesters were marched from Sydney's convention centre before Prime Minister [[Julia Gillard]]'s motion to remove a party ban on uranium sales to India was narrowly supported 206 votes to 185. Long-time anti-nuclear campaigner [[Peter Garrett]] MP spoke against the motion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.heraldsun.com.au/news/more-news/anti-nuclear-protesters-interrupt-labors-national-conference/story-fn7x8me2-1226213375804 |title=Labor supports Julia Gillard's plan to sell uranium to India |author=Matthew Johnston  |date=4 December 2011 |work=Herald Sun }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2012, hundreds of anti-nuclear demonstrators converged on the Australian headquarters of global mining giants BHP Billiton and Rio Tinto. The 500-strong march through southern Melbourne called for an end to uranium mining in Australia, and included speeches and performances by representatives of the expatriate Japanese community as well as Australia's Indigenous communities, who are concerned about the effects of uranium mining near tribal lands. There were also events in Sydney.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.voanews.com/english/news/asia/east-pacific/Australian-Rallies-Remember-Fukushima-Disaster-142242575.html |title= Australian Rallies Remember Fukushima Disaster |author=Phil Mercer |date=11 March 2012 |work=VOA News }}{{dead link|date=September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A site within [[Muckaty Station]] is being considered for Australia's [[Low level waste|low-level]] and intermediate-level [[radioactive waste]] storage and disposal facility. However, the plan is subject to a Federal Court challenge due to be heard early in 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.theage.com.au/national/nuclear-dump-court-battle-begins-20120625-20ylj.html#ixzz1ywJoIUdo |title=Nuclear dump court battle begins |author=Farah Farouque |date=26 June 2012 |work=The Age }}&lt;/ref&gt;

More than 400 people joined a &quot;Lizard's Revenge march&quot; to the Olympic Dam site in July 2012. The anti-nuclear activists, including Elder [[Kevin Buzzacott]], protested against the mine expansion and the uranium industry. They say the company and the government have put short-term economic gain ahead of environmental and health concerns. Organiser Nectaria Calan said police harassed protesters, demanding identification and controlling access to and from their campsite.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.theaustralian.com.au/national-affairs/state-politics/police-accused-over-olympic-dam-protest/story-e6frgczx-1226426656207 |title=Police accused over Olympic Dam protest  |author=Sarah Martin |date=16 July 2012 |work=The Australian }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ban on nuclear reactors==

Nuclear reactors are banned in [[Queensland]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.aar.com.au/pubs/ener/cuemar07.htm |title=Queensland bans nuclear facilities |author= |date=1 March 2007 |work=Allens Arthur Robinson }}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Tasmania]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hg.org/articles/article_1774.html |title=Australias States React Strongly to Switkowski Report |author=Minter Ellison |date=10 December 2006 |work=World Services Group }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Uranium mining was previously prohibited in [[New South Wales]] under the Uranium Prohibition Act of 1986, however in 2012 Premier Barry O'Farrell amended the legislation to allow prospecting and mining of uranium in that State. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/legis/nsw/num_act/umanfa1986n194506.pdf |title=Uranium Mining and Nuclear Facilities |author=New South Wales Government |year=1986 |work= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Issues==
{{See also|Nuclear power debate|Uranium mining debate|Nuclear power in Australia}}

The case against nuclear power and uranium mining in Australia has been concerned with the environmental, political, economic, social and cultural impacts of nuclear energy; with the shortcomings of nuclear power as an energy source; and with presenting a [[sustainable energy]] strategy. The most prominent adverse impact of nuclear power is seen to be its potential contribution towards proliferation of nuclear weapons. For example, the 1976 Ranger Inquiry report stated that &quot;The nuclear power industry is unintentionally contributing to an increased risk of nuclear war. This is the most serious hazard associated with the industry&quot;.&lt;ref name=Martin/&gt;

The health risks associated with nuclear materials have also featured prominently in Australian anti-nuclear campaigns. This has been the case worldwide because of incidents like the [[Chernobyl disaster]], but Australian concerns have also involved specific local factors such as controversy over the health effects of nuclear testing in Australia and the South Pacific, and the emergence of prominent anti-nuclear campaigner [[Helen Caldicott]], who is a medical practitioner. 

The economics of nuclear power has been a factor in anti-nuclear campaigns, with critics arguing that such power is uneconomical in Australia,&lt;ref&gt;See, for example, Brian Martin (1982). Nuclear Power and the Western Australia Electricity Grid, ''Search'', Vol. 13, No. 5-6.&lt;/ref&gt; particularly given the country's abundance of coal resources.

According to the anti-nuclear movement, most of the problems with nuclear power today are much the same as in the 1970s. Nuclear reactor accidents still occur and there is no convincing solution to the problem of long-lived radioactive waste. Nuclear weapons proliferation continues to occur, notably in Pakistan and North Korea, building on facilities and expertise from civilian nuclear operations. The alternatives to nuclear power, [[efficient energy use]] and [[renewable energy]] (especially [[wind power]]), have been further [[Renewable energy commercialization|developed and commercialised]].&lt;ref name=past/&gt;

==Public opinion==
A 2009 poll conducted by the Uranium Information Centre found that Australians in the 40 to 55 years age group are the &quot;most trenchantly opposed to nuclear power&quot;.&lt;ref name=gf/&gt; This generation was raised during the [[Cold War]], experienced the [[anti-nuclear movement]] of the 1970s, witnessed the 1979 partial meltdown of the [[Three Mile Island accident|Three Mile Island]] reactor in the USA, and the 1986 [[Chernobyl disaster]]. It was the generation which was also subject to cultural influences including feature films such as the &quot;nuclear industry conspiracies&quot; ''[[The China Syndrome]]'' and ''[[Silkwood]]'' and the apocalyptic ''[[Dr Strangelove]]''. Younger people are &quot;less resistant&quot; to the idea of nuclear power for Australia.&lt;ref name=gf&gt;Strong, Geoff and  Munro, Ian (13 October 2009). [http://www.theage.com.au/national/going-fission-20091012-gu24.html Going Fission] ''The Age''.&lt;/ref&gt;

Indigenous land owners have consistently opposed uranium mining and have spoken out about the adverse impact it has on their communities.&lt;ref name=jv&gt;Vaisutis, Justine (April 2010). Indigenous communities getting dumped in it. Again. ''Habitat Australia'', Vol. 38, No. 2, p. 22.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Active groups==
{|
|- valign=top
|  style=&quot;width:1200px; text-align:left;&quot;|
*Anti-Nuclear Alliance of Western Australia&lt;ref&gt;Anti-Nuclear Alliance of Western Australia. [http://www.anawa.org.au/ Anti-Nuclear Alliance of Western Australia] Retrieved 5 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Australian Conservation Foundation]]&lt;ref&gt;Australian Conservation Foundation. [http://www.acfonline.org.au/default.asp?section_id=25 Nuclear Free] Retrieved 5 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Australian Greens]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://greens.org.au/policies/climate-change-and-energy/nuclear Greens Nuclear Policy]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Australian Nuclear Free Alliance&lt;ref name=&quot;Peter Watts&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.greenleft.org.au/node/49872 |title=Uranium should stay in the ground |author=Peter Watts |date=31 January 2012  |work=Green Left }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://ausnukefreealliance.wordpress.com/ Australian Nuclear Free Alliance] Retrieved 31 January 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Australian Conservation Foundation. [http://www.acfonline.org.au/articles/news.asp?news_id=1423 Australian Nuclear Free Alliance] Retrieved 31 January 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2007/08/13/2003808.htm New alliance to mount anti-nuclear election fight] ''ABC News'', 13 August 2007. Retrieved 31 January 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
*Cycle Against the Nuclear Cycle&lt;ref&gt;Cycle Against the Nuclear Cycle. [http://canc.org.au/welcome Cycle Against the Nuclear Cycle] Retrieved 5 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
*EnergyScience&lt;ref&gt;EnergyScience. [http://www.energyscience.org.au/index.html The Energy debate] Retrieved 5 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Friends of the Earth Australia]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foe.org.au/anti-nuclear/issues/oz Australian Nuclear Issues] Retrieved 5 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Greenpeace Australia Pacific]]&lt;ref&gt;Greenpeace Australia Pacific. [http://www.greenpeace.org/australia/issues/nuclear-power Nuclear power]{{dead link|date=September 2012}} Retrieved 5 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
|  style=&quot;width:1200px; text-align:left;&quot;|
*[[Kupa Piti Kungka Tjuta]]&lt;ref&gt;Friends of the Earth International (2004). [http://www.foei.org/en/publications/link/env-rights/30.html Aboriginal women win battle against Australian Government] Retrieved 5 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Mineral Policy Institute]]
*[[Peace Organisation of Australia]]
*[[The Australia Institute]]&lt;ref&gt;The Australia Institute. [http://www.tai.org.au/documents/downloads/MR235.pdf Nuclear Plants – Where would they go?] ''Media release'', 30 January 2007. Retrieved 5 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
*The Sustainable Energy and Anti-Uranium Service Inc.&lt;ref&gt;The Sustainable Energy and Anti-Uranium Service Inc. [http://www.sea-us.org.au/ The Sustainable Energy and Anti-Uranium Service Inc.] Retrieved 5 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[The Wilderness Society (Australia)|The Wilderness Society]]&lt;ref&gt;The Wilderness Society. [https://secure.wilderness.org.au/nuclear/? The Nation said YES! to a Nuclear Free Australia] Retrieved 5 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wilderness.org.au/articles/nuclear-ad The Wilderness Society launches new anti-nuclear TV Ad] Retrieved 5 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
*Women Against Nuclear Energy&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00080b.htm Women Against Nuclear Energy]&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

==Individuals==
There are several prominent Australians who have publicly expressed anti-nuclear views:

{|
|- valign=top
|  style=&quot;width:1200px; text-align:left;&quot;|
*[[Dorothy Auchterlonie]]
*[[David Bradbury (film maker)]]
*[[Bob Brown]]
*[[Eileen Kampakuta Brown]]
*[[Kevin Buzzacott]]
*[[Helen Caldicott]]
*Joseph Camilleri&lt;ref name=gf/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;J.A. Camilleri. [http://www.josephcamilleri.com/doc/MythOfPeacefulAtom.pdf  The Myth of the Peaceful Atom] ''Journal of International Studies'', Vol. 6, No. 2, Autumn 1977, pp. 111–127.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Ian Cohen]]
*[[Mark Diesendorf]]
*[[Jim Falk]]
*[[Peter Garrett]]
|  style=&quot;width:1200px; text-align:left;&quot;|
*[[Jim Green (activist)]]
*[[Margaret Holmes]]
*[[Jacqui Katona]]
*[[Sandra Kanck]]
*[[Ian Lowe]]
*[[Scott Ludlam]]
*[[Yvonne Margarula]]
*[[Dee Margetts]]
*[[Jillian Marsh]]
*[[Brian Martin (professor)]]
|  style=&quot;width:1200px; text-align:left;&quot;|
*[[Kerry Nettle]]
*Mia Pepper&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.watoday.com.au/wa-news/get-with-the-times-parliament-told-nuclear-power-is-so-last-century-20110621-1gddv.html?from=watoday_sb |title=Get with the times: Parliament told nuclear power is 'so last century' |author=Courtney Trenwith  |date=22 June 2011  |work=WAtoday }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2011/06/07/3237714.htm |title=Uranium forum addresses Japan crisis fallout |author= |date=7 June 2011  |work=ABC News }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Nancy Shelley]]
*[[Jo Vallentine]]
*Peter Watts&lt;ref name=&quot;Peter Watts&quot;/&gt;
*[[Patrick White]]
*[[Stuart White]]
*Bill Williams&lt;ref&gt;Bill Williams. [http://www.theage.com.au/opinion/politics/nuclear-delusions-keep-mushrooming-20091014-gxc5.html Nuclear delusions keep mushrooming] ''The Age'', 15 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;James Norman and Bill Williams. [http://www.theage.com.au/opinion/politics/stars-align-in-quest-to-rid-the-world-of-nukes-20090923-g2m8.html Stars align in quest to rid the world of nukes] ''The Age'', 24 September 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Eileen Wani Wingfield]]
|}

==See also==
{{Portal|Social movements|Australia}}
*[[Anti-nuclear protests]]
*[[Australian Uranium Association]]
*[[Clean Energy Future Group]]
*[[History of the anti-nuclear movement]]
*[[International Commission on Nuclear Non-proliferation and Disarmament]]
*[[List of anti-nuclear groups]]
*[[List of Australian inquiries into uranium mining]]
*[[Lists of nuclear disasters and radioactive incidents]]
*[[Renewable energy commercialization]]
*[[Renewable energy in Australia]]
*[[Say Yes demonstrations]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
{{Commons category|Protests against nuclear energy}}
{{See also|List of books about nuclear issues|List of films about nuclear issues}}
*[[Stephanie Cooke|Cooke, Stephanie]] (2009). ''[[In Mortal Hands: A Cautionary History of the Nuclear Age]]'', Black Inc.
*Diesendorf, Mark (2009).  ''Climate Action: A Campaign Manual for Greenhouse Solutions'', University of New South Wales Press.
*[[Mark Diesendorf|Diesendorf, Mark]] (2007).  ''[[Greenhouse Solutions with Sustainable Energy]]'', University of New South Wales Press.
*[[David Elliott (professor)|Elliott, David]] (2007).  ''[[Nuclear or Not?|Nuclear or Not? Does Nuclear Power Have a Place in a Sustainable Energy Future?]]'', Palgrave.
*Falk, Jim (1982). ''Global Fission: The Battle Over Nuclear Power'', Oxford University Press.
*Giugni, Marco (2004). ''Social Protest and Policy Change: Ecology, Antinuclear, and Peace Movements in Comparative Perspective'', Rowman and Littlefield.
*[[Amory Lovins|Lovins, Amory B.]] (1977). ''[[Soft energy path|Soft Energy Paths: Towards a Durable Peace]]'', Friends of the Earth International, ISBN 0-06-090653-7
*Lovins, Amory B. and Price, John H. (1975). ''[[Non-Nuclear Futures: The Case for an Ethical Energy Strategy]]'', Ballinger Publishing Company, 1975, ISBN 0-88410-602-0
*[[Ian Lowe|Lowe, Ian]] (2007). ''[[Reaction Time: Climate Change and the Nuclear Option]]'', [[Quarterly Essay]].
*Parkinson, Alan (2007). ''[[Maralinga: Australia’s Nuclear Waste Cover-up]]'', ABC Books.
*[[Ron Pernick|Pernick, Ron]] and [[Clint Wilder|Wilder, Clint]] (2007). ''[[The Clean Tech Revolution|The Clean Tech Revolution: The Next Big Growth and Investment Opportunity]]'',  Collins, ISBN 978-0-06-089623-2
*[[Mycle Schneider|Schneider, Mycle]], [[Stephen Thomas (professor)|Steve Thomas]], Antony Froggatt, Doug Koplow (August 2009). ''[[The World Nuclear Industry Status Report]]'', [[Federal Ministry for Environment, Nature Conservation and Nuclear Safety|German Federal Ministry of Environment, Nature Conservation and Reactor Safety]].
*Smith, Jennifer  (Editor), (2002). ''The Antinuclear Movement'', Cengage Gale.
*Walker, J. Samuel (2004). ''[[Three Mile Island (book)|Three Mile Island: A Nuclear Crisis in Historical Perspective]]'', University of California Press.

==External links==
*[http://www.energyscience.org.au/ Contemporary critiques of nuclear power by Australian scientists]
*[http://www.uow.edu.au/~bmartin/pubs/80nk/ ''Nuclear Knights''], a book by anti-nuclear campaigner Brian Martin.
*[http://www.bmartin.cc/pubs/86sa.html ''Strategy against nuclear power''], an anti-nuclear campaign strategy produced by Friends of the Earth.
*[http://australianscreen.com.au/titles/backs-blast/ ''Backs to the Blast, an Australian Nuclear Story''], a documentary about nuclear testing in Australia.
*[http://books.google.com/books?id=IqIdBaSN_98C&amp;pg=PA43&amp;lpg=PA43&amp;dq=%22anti+nuclear%22+books&amp;source=web&amp;ots=XGWAKZwueD&amp;sig=6srGG41FZH6VMUKXD7V3tk4qI9c#PPA1,M1 ''Stop Uranium Mining! Australia's Decade of Protest 1975–1985''], a history of anti-nuclear protest in the 1970s and 1980s.
*[http://alsos.wlu.edu/adv_rst.aspx?keyword=anti*nuclear&amp;results=10 ALSOS Digital Library for Nuclear Issues]

{{Australian anti-nuclear}}
{{Anti-nuclear}}

[[Category:Anti-nuclear movement by country|Australia]]
[[Category:Nuclear energy in Australia]]
[[Category:Political movements in Australia]]
[[Category:Environmentalism in Australia]]
[[Category:Protests in Australia]]

[[de:Antiatomkraftbewegung in Australien]]
[[simple:Anti-nuclear movement in Australia]]</text>
      <sha1>5fmienui2memuxxjm6pfx6srmi9bhxt</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
