<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Anti-capitalism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>44443</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521454961</id>
      <parentid>513446135</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-05T02:53:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Djr13</username>
        <id>2896805</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* External links */ add some categories</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16305">{{Hatnote|This article lists ideologies opposed to capitalism and describes them briefly. For arguments against capitalism, see [[criticism of capitalism]].}}

[[File:Anti-capitalism color.jpg|right|thumb|300px|An [[Industrial Workers of the World]] poster (1911)]]
'''Anti-capitalism''' describes a wide variety of movements, ideas, and attitudes that oppose [[capitalism]]. Anti-capitalists, in the strict sense of the word, are those who wish to completely replace capitalism with another system. 
== Conservatism and traditionalism ==
There are strands of [[conservatism]] that are uncomfortable with liberal capitalism. Particularly in continental Europe, many conservatives have been uncomfortable with the impact of capitalism upon culture and traditions. The conservative opposition to the [[Renaissance]], [[the Enlightenment]], the [[American Revolution]], the [[French Revolution]], and especially the development of individualistic liberalism as a political theory and as institutionalized social practices sought to retain traditional social hierarchies, practices and institutions. There is also a conservative [[protectionism|protectionist]] opposition to certain types of international capitalism.

[[Paleoconservatives]] and other traditionalist ideologies are often in opposition to capitalist ethics and the effects they have on society as a whole, which they see as infringing upon or decaying social traditions or hierarchies that are essential for social order. Some of these ideas are intertwined with [[religious communism]]. More [[nationalist]]-oriented groups believe that aspects of capitalism, such as [[free trade]] infringe upon [[national sovereignty]], that domestic industries and national traditions must be safeguarded, and that preserving this is of greater importance than profit for business.

== Ecofeminism ==
{{Main|Ecofeminism}}
[[Ecofeminism|Ecofeminists]] criticise capitalism for defining the natural world as simply a body of resources to be exploited and reshaped to serve human purposes and interests. They also see it as inherently sapping the relationship between humans to one another and to the natural world. Ecofeminists see capitalism as a patriarchal construction &quot;based on the colonization of women, nature, and other peoples.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Mies|first=Maria|coauthors=Maria Mies and Vandana Shiva|authorlink=Maria Mies|title=Ecofeminism|page=298|year=1993|isbn=1-85649-156-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Fascism ==
{{Main|Fascism and anti-capitalism}}
[[Fascism]] has mixed stances on capitalism; while supportive of private property rights, fascism upholds [[statism]] and [[corporatism]] and is hostile to the concepts of [[laissez-faire]] capitalism, [[free market]] systems, [[free trade]], economic individualism, [[consumerism]], and [[bourgeois]] culture. Like [[Marxism|Marxists]], fascists maintain that [[class conflict]] is a feature inherent in capitalist societies{{fact|date=July 2012}} and seek to remedy it by [[Class collaboration|government means]].

==Participatory economics and inclusive democracy==
{{Quote box
| quote  = &quot;Capitalism is the astounding belief that the most wickedest of men will do the most wickedest of things for the greatest good of everyone.&quot;
| source = — [[John Maynard Keynes]]&lt;ref&gt;''The Origin of Wealth: Evolution, Complexity, and the Radical Remaking of Economics'', by Eric D. Beinhocker, Harvard Business Press, 2006, ISBN 1-57851-777-X, pg 408&lt;/ref&gt;
 | width = 25%
 | align = right
}}

{{Main|Participatory economics}}
[[Participatory economics]], often abbreviated as Parecon, is a proposed economic system that uses participatory decision making as an economic mechanism to guide the production, consumption and allocation of resources in a given society. Proposed as an alternative to contemporary capitalist market economies and also an alternative to centrally planned socialism, it is described as &quot;an anarchistic economic vision&quot;, although it could be considered a form of socialism as under Parecon, the [[means of production]] are owned by the [[working class]]. It emerged from the work of activist and political theorist [[Michael Albert]] and that of radical economist [[Robin Hahnel]], beginning in the 1980s and 1990s.

{{Main|Inclusive Democracy}}
[[Inclusive Democracy]] as envisaged by [[Takis Fotopoulos]], is a form of [[direct democracy]]. It is a political theory and political project that aims for direct democracy in all fields of social life: political democracy in the form of face-to-face assemblies which are confederated, [[economic democracy]] in a [[stateless society|stateless]], moneyless and marketless economy, democracy in the social realm, i.e., [[self-managed economy|self-management]] in places of work and education, and ecological democracy which aims to reintegrate society and nature. Here, all decisions are taken by the Demos, and basic economic needs could be met for all based upon a certain amount of work.  Additional non-necessary items could be earned by contributing above the minimum required to meet society's basic needs.   This approach is markedly anti-capitalist as well as anti-market, including an absence of ability to accumulate wealth, where each person earns for himself only, thereby avoiding the imbalance of power inherent in a capitalist system.&lt;ref&gt;Takis Fotopolous ''International Journal of Inclusive Democracy'' vol.4 no.2, [http://www.inclusivedemocracy.org/journal/vol4/vol4_no2_takis_finnish_interview.htm] (2008).&lt;/ref&gt;

== Religion ==
[[File:Christus austreibt.JPG|right|thumb|145px|''Christ drives the Usurers out of the Temple'', a woodcut by [[Lucas Cranach the Elder]] in ''Passionary of Christ and Antichrist''.&lt;ref&gt;The references cited in the Passionary for this woodcut: {{bibleverse|1|John|2:14-16|9}}, {{bibleverse||Matthew|10:8|9}}, and [http://www.bookofconcord.com/defense_6_church.php The Apology of the Augsburg Confession, Article 8, Of the Church]&lt;/ref&gt;]]
{{Further2|[[Religious communism]]|[[Christian communism]]|[[Christian socialism]]|[[Islamic socialism]]}}

The [[Catholic Church]] forbids [[usury]], but with the [[Protestant Reformation|Reformation]] and its revolt against Papal dogmatic teaching and then the [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]] and its rejection of Papal moral teaching, &quot;Christian Europe&quot; over time accepted some forms of interest-charging, allowing for some societal changes after feudalism was replaced by other forms of government.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}

Christianity has been the source of many criticisms of capitalism, particularly its [[economic materialism|materialist]] aspects. {{Citation needed|date=February 2012}} Many early and pre-socialist movements&lt;ref&gt;[[Diggers]], [[Levellers]], etc.&lt;/ref&gt; as well as later ones drew principles from the Gospels (see [[Christian socialism]] and the [[Social Gospel movement]]) and against the &quot;values&quot; of [[profiteering (business)|profiteering]], greed, selfishness and hoarding.  However many [[Christian right|Conservative Christians]] in the US are in favour of capitalism in opposition to secular socialism.

[[Islam]] [[Riba|forbids]] lending money at interest, the mode of operation of capitalist [[finance]];{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}} however Islamic banks have developed ways to make a profit in transactions that are traditionally arranged using interest. These include profit sharing (Mudharabah), safekeeping (Wadiah), joint venture (Musharakah), cost plus (Murabahah), and leasing (Ijarah).

==Socialism==
{{Main|Socialism}}
[[File:Day 8 Occupy Wall Street September 24 2011 Shankbone 19.JPG|thumb|A man marching against capitalism with [[Democratic Socialists of America]] members at the [[Occupy Wall Street]] protest event, September 24, 2011]]Socialism includes various theories of economic organization that advocate public or direct worker ownership and administration of the [[means of production]] and allocation of resources, and a society characterized by equal access to resources for all individuals, with an [[Egalitarianism|egalitarian]] method of compensation.&lt;ref name=&quot;SocialismAVeryShortIntroduction&quot;&gt;''Newman, Michael''. (2005) ''Socialism: A Very Short Introduction'', Oxford University Press, ISBN 0-19-280431-6&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Socialism&quot;. Oxford English Dictionary.
&quot;1. A theory or policy of social organisation which aims at or advocates the ownership and control of the means of production, capital, land, property, etc., by the community as a whole, and their administration or distribution in the interests of all.

2. A state of society in which things are held or used in common.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Socialism&quot;.Merriam-Webster Unabridged Dictionary&lt;/ref&gt; Socialists argue for [[Cooperative|cooperative/community]] or [[Nationalization|state control]] of the economy, or the &quot;commanding heights&quot; of the economy,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-9109587 &quot;Socialism&quot;] ''[[Encyclopædia Britannica]]''. 2006. Encyclopædia Britannica Online.&lt;/ref&gt; with democratic control by the people over the state, although there have been some undemocratic philosophies. &quot;State&quot; or &quot;worker cooperative&quot; ownership is in fundamental opposition to &quot;private&quot; ownership of the means of production, which is the defining feature of capitalism. Most socialists argue that capitalism unfairly concentrates power, wealth and profit, among a small segment of society that controls [[Capital (economics)|capital]] and derives its wealth through [[exploitation]], stifling technological and economic progress by maintaining an anarchy of production.

===Anarchism===
{{Main|Anarchism and capitalism}}
[[Libertarian socialist]]s argue for a total abolition of the [[State (polity)|state]], with most anarchists (including proponents of [[left anarchism]], [[social anarchism]] and [[anarchist communism]]) opposing [[capitalism]] on the grounds that it entails social domination (through [[inequalities of wealth]]), involuntary relations and coercive [[hierarchy]] (through the perceived pressure on individuals to engage in [[wage labour]]). Some forms of anarchism oppose capitalism as a whole while supporting some institutions associated with capitalism, such as [[market]]s (supported by some [[mutualism (economic theory)|mutualists]]) and some even go as far as supporting [[private property]] (supported by some [[individualist anarchism|individualist anarchists]]). Many anarchists will make the distinction between [[Anarchist_economics#Alternate_currency|decentralized currencies]] being a practical tool for exchange within a community as opposed to capitalism as a politically enforced authoritarian system.

===Communism===
{{Main|Communism}}
[[Communism]], [[Marxism]], and [[revolutionary socialism]] disagrees with capitalism and [[economic liberalism]] on a fundamental basis, in that communism advocates communal ownership over the means of production and economic decision-making of a [[society]], with the abolishment of private property and government. [[Friedrich Engels]], one of the founders of modern socialist theory, advocated the creation of a society that allows for the widespread application of modern technology to rationalise economic activity by eliminating the anarchy in production of capitalism.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1880/soc-utop/ch03.htm Socialism: Utopian and Scientific] at Marxists.org&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| url= http://books.google.com/books?id=6avaAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA47&amp;dq=Socialism:+Utopian+and+Scientific#v=onepage&amp;q=anarchy&amp;f=false |author= [[Frederick Engels]] |title= Socialism: Utopian and Scientific |pages= 92-11 | year=1910 | publisher=C.H. Kerr}}Chapter III: Historical Materialism&lt;/ref&gt; Marxism argues for collective ownership of the means of production, the elimination of the exploitation of labor,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| url= http://www.marxists.org/archive/guevara/1961/04/09.htm |title= Cuba: Historical Exception or Vanguard in the Anticolonial Struggle?}} speech by [[Che Guevara]] on April 9, 1961 &quot;The people are weary of being oppressed, persecuted, exploited to the maximum. They are weary of the wretched selling of their labor-power day after day — faced with the fear of joining the enormous mass of unemployed — so that the greatest profit can be wrung from each human body, profit later squandered in the orgies of the masters of capital.&quot; - [[Che Guevara]], [[Marxist]] revolutionary, 1961&lt;/ref&gt; and the eventual abolition of the [[State (polity)|state]], with an intermediate stage, of indeterminate length, in which the state will be used to eliminate the vestiges of capitalism. Some [[Communist state]]s claimed to have abolished capitalism, although some Marxist theorists describe them as [[State capitalism|state capitalist]], rather than anti-capitalist.

&lt;ref&gt;Friedrich Pollock, &quot;State Capitalism: Its Possibilities and Limitations&quot;, Studies in Philosophy and Social Science, IX, 2 (1941), 200-255.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Tony Cliff, [http://www.marxists.org/archive/cliff/works/1955/statecap/index.htm ''State Capitalism in Russia''] (1955)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Anti-globalization movement==
{{Main|Anti-globalization movement}}
The anti-globalization movement is a worldwide [[Activism|activist]] movement that is critical of the [[globalization]] of [[capitalism]]. Anti-globalization activists are particularly critical of the undemocratic nature of capitalist globalization and the promotion of [[neoliberalism]] by international institutions such as the [[International Monetary Fund]] (IMF) and the [[World Bank]] without much regard to the often devastating effects of global capital on local conditions. Meetings of such bodies are often met with [[List of demonstrations against corporate globalization|strong protests]].

==See also==
*[[Anti-corporate activism]]
*[[The Black Book of Capitalism]]
*[[Corporatocracy]]
*[[List of communist and anti-capitalist parties with parliamentary representation]]
*[[Occupy Wall Street]]
*[[Post-capitalism]]
*[[Transformative Studies Institute]]
*[[Yasunize]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
*  [http://zedbooks.co.uk/book.asp?bookdetail=3837 ''The Anti-Capitalist Dictionary''] by David E Lowes 2006, London: Zed Books
* [http://www.tidsskriftcentret.dk/index.php?id=142 &quot;Anti-Capitalism : A Guide To The Movement&quot;]

==External links==
{{Commons category|Anti-capitalism}}
* [http://www.fifthinternational.org/content/publications/pamphlets/rough-guide-anticapitalist-movement Rough Guide to the Anti-Capitalist Movement], [[League for the Fifth International]]
* [http://www.infoshop.org/ Infoshop.org Anarchists Opposed to Capitalism], Infoshop.org
* [http://economicdemocracy.org/miners.html How The Miners Were Robbed] 1907 anti-capitalist pamphlet hosted at EconomicDemocracy
* Sam Ashman [http://pubs.socialistreviewindex.org.uk/isj98/ashman.htm &quot;The anti-capitalist movement and the war&quot;] ''International Socialist Journal 2003
* [http://www.marxists.org/ Marxists Internet Archive]
* Dr. Wladyslaw Jan Kowalski [http://www.aerobiologicalengineering.com/wxk116/Anticapitalism/ ''Anti-Capitalism: Modern Theory and Historical Origins'']
* [http://libcom.org/library/anti-capitalist-aufheben-10 Anti-Capitalism as an ideology... and as a movement], Libcom.org
* [http://www.studiesinanti-capitalism.net Studies in Anti-Capitalism]
*[http://www.polyarchy.org/essays/english/capitalism.html Capitalism/Anticapitalism: a survey and a view]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Anti-Capitalism}}
[[Category:Political movements]]
[[Category:Political ideologies]]
[[Category:Economic ideologies]]
[[Category:Heterodox economics]]
[[Category:Anti-capitalism| ]]
[[Category:Labor]]
[[Category:Labour relations]]

[[ast:Anticapitalismu]]
[[ca:Anticapitalisme]]
[[cs:Antikapitalismus]]
[[da:Antikapitalisme]]
[[de:Antikapitalismus]]
[[es:Anticapitalismo]]
[[eo:Kontraŭkapitalismo]]
[[eu:Antikapitalismo]]
[[fr:Anticapitalisme]]
[[gl:Anticapitalismo]]
[[hr:Antikapitalizam]]
[[id:Antikapitalisme]]
[[it:Anticapitalismo]]
[[he:אנטי-קפיטליזם]]
[[ja:反資本主義]]
[[pl:Antykapitalizm]]
[[pt:Anticapitalismo]]
[[ru:Антикапитализм]]
[[simple:Anti-capitalism]]
[[sk:Antikapitalizmus]]
[[fi:Antikapitalismi]]
[[sv:Antikapitalism]]
[[tr:Antikapitalizm]]
[[uk:Антикапіталізм]]
[[vi:Chủ nghĩa chống tư bản]]
[[zh:反資本主義]]</text>
      <sha1>q1z6iri28fenhrig2tvxhzsylabkj41</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
