<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Anti-environmentalism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8149492</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522021029</id>
      <parentid>521855445</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-08T16:21:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sarmariemack</username>
        <id>17529355</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added better citations to two of the quotes</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6710">{{Multiple issues|POV=August 2008|refimprove=November 2008|expert=May 2011|histinfo=May 2011|inappropriate tone=May 2011|pov-check=May 2011|unbalanced=May 2011|date=September 2012}}

'''Anti-environmentalism''' is a backlash against the [[Environmentalism|environmental movement]]. Anti-environmentalism disregards the current “environmental crisis&quot; due to specific scientific and economical reasoning. The Anti-environmentalism movement is oppression to the environmental movement; it focuses on job-creation, wage enhancement and industry. Anti-environmentalists believe that the Earth is not as fragile as environmentalists maintain. Generally, chemical manufacturers, oil producers, mining producers, timber companies, real estate developers, nuclear power industries, and electric utilities have anti-environmental motives. Anti-environmentalists are generally right-winged with conservative views, however there may be exceptions. Anti-environmentalism labels environmentalism as an extreme, false and exaggerated reaction to the human contribution of climate change. Anti-environmentalism often seeks to portray environmentalists as anti-human advancement.

==History of Anti-Environmentalism in North America==

Anti-environmentalism is a movement against the environmentalism movement. This backlashes’ origination in [[North America]] can be marked by an infamous speech delivered by [[Lewis Powell]] to the [[US Chamber of Commerce]] in 1971. Several acts had been passed in years prior to Powell’s speech in favor of [[environmentalism]], such the Wilderness Act 1964, [[Wild and Scenic Rivers Act|Federal Wild and Scenic Rivers Act 1968]], [[National Environmental Policy Act|National Environmental Policy Act 1969]]. Powell directed his audience against the environmental movement and promoted a pro-industry and anti-environmental view. [[James Watt]] was initially the most well-known Anti-environmentalist. He advocated free for all [[mining]], [[ranching]], and [[drilling]]. 

In 1988 a [[Wise Use]] Campaign was introduced by republican senator, Mark Hatfield. The [[Wise Use]] Campaign supported unrestricted access to [[timber]] and other resources. Wise Use activists exploited the population’s fear of job and property security loss. The Campaign placed a barrier between workers and environmentalists. The Wise Use Campaign used bumper stickers, phone-ins and faxes to promote their views. Wise Use and Republicans kicked off anti-environmentalism.

The [[recession]] that began in 1990 enhanced anti-green and pro-industry views. A group called Alliance for America was created with 125 anti-environment and pro-industry groups. In 1994, the US did not pass a Biodiversity Treaty.  Another group that was created in the 90’s was called Earth Day Alternatives. They were also counter-environmentalists. This group labelled environmentalists as “anti-human” and extremists.  The Earth Day Alternative group promoted three things. They aimed to privatise resources for exploitation, advocate pollution to be permitted as trade between companies, to discredit environmental science. Heritage was a group that was also created with a laissez-faire approach toward the environment. Anti-environmentalists were motivated by the fact that the [[ICI]] created deceptive green advertising.

==Anti-environmentalism Quotes==

“Environmental acts are mindless proposals that would sacrifice the people of the US on the altar of nature” &lt;ref name=&quot;Leonard Theberge&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Rowell|first=Andrew|title=Green Backlash|year=1996|publisher=Routledge}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

“Our goal is to destroy and eradicate environmental movement” – &lt;ref name=Arnold&gt;{{cite book|last=Powell|first=Andrew|title=Green Backlash|year=1996|publisher=Routledge}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

“The environmental community has only itself to blame for the rise of Wise Use sentiments” – [[Philip Brick]]

“Strangle the environmental movement. It’s the greatest single threat to American economy. It doesn’t just include a few extremists. It is extremist.” – [[Heritage Foundation Policy Review 1990]]

==Overview==
Paula Snyder, Tom Denton and Peter Millson characterize environmentalist ideology as unscientific, irrational and anti-humanist.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ourcivilisation.com/aginatur/ Against Nature], [[Channel 4]]&lt;/ref&gt;

:&quot;What we today call 'environmentalism' is ... based on a fear of change,&quot; says Frank Furedi. &quot;It's based upon a fear of the outcome of human action. And therefore it's not surprising that when you look at the more xenophobic right-wing movements in Europe in the 19th century, including German fascism, it quite often had a very strong environmentalist dynamic to it.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ourcivilisation.com/aginatur/prog1.htm The Lack Of Scientific Rigour In Environmentalist Ideology], ''[[Against Nature (documentary)|Against Nature]]'', Part 1.&lt;/ref&gt;

The British [[Trades Union Congress|trade union movement]], until the 1990s, argued that environmentalism was a form of middle class protectionism intended to protect their economic and political interests from the proletariat. 

:&quot;Trees and forests provide a good example of how it's possible to have a growing economy and a growing population and a thriving environment,&quot; says Steve Hayward of the Pacific Research Centre. &quot;The lesson from trees really applies across the environment. We have cleaner air today; we have cleaner water; we grow more food at less impact on the land; we have more wildlife diversity— and we've done all this while having a growing economy and a growing population.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ourcivilisation.com/aginatur/prog2.htm Tyranny Imposed By Environmentalists Fearful Of Overpopulation], ''[[Against Nature (documentary)|Against Nature]]'', Part 2.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Astroturfing]]
* [[Vicente Canas]]
* [[Rachel Carson]]
* [[Climate change denial]]
* [[Energy lobby]]
* [[Global Climate Coalition]]
* [[Greenhouse Mafia]]
* [[Chico Mendes]]
* [[Wilson Pinheiro]]
* [[Dorothy Stang]]

==Further reading==
* John Stauber and Sheldon Rampton (2002). ''Toxic Sludge is Good For You''. Common Courage Press. ISBN 978-1-56751-060-7 
* {{cite book| author = Matthew Watkinson| title = On the Destiny of Species by Means of Natural Selection, or the Elimination of Unfavoured Races in the Struggle for Life (free pdf) | url = http://www.scribd.com/doc/20205887/On-the-Destiny-of-Species-a-work-in-progress| publisher = Troubador Publishing Ltd | year = 2009| isbn = 1-84876-306-9}}

==References==
{{reflist}}


{{DEFAULTSORT:Anti-Environmentalism}}
[[Category:Environmentalism]]
[[Category:Political ideologies]]
[[Category:Social philosophy]]


{{Environment-stub}}

[[pt:Antiambientalismo]]</text>
      <sha1>8xnejaonn04eevd50l1ez1g4gvay3r4</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
