<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Aristotelianism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>309909</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521328146</id>
      <parentid>513756475</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-04T08:27:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>EmausBot</username>
        <id>11292982</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>r2.7.2+) (Robot: Modifying [[fa:سیستم فلسفی ارسطو]] to [[fa:ارسطوگری]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23610">{{Aristotelianism}}
[[File:Francesco Hayez 001.jpg|thumb|upright|Aristotle, by [[Francesco Hayez]]]]

'''Aristotelianism''' ({{IPAc-en|icon|ˌ|ær|ɨ|s|t|ə|ˈ|t|iː|l|i|ə|n|ɨ|z|əm}} {{respell|ARR|i-stə|TEE|li-ə-niz-əm}}) is a [[Tradition#Philosophical tradition|tradition]] of [[philosophy]] that takes its defining inspiration from the work of [[Aristotle]]. The works of Aristotle were initially defended by the members of the [[Peripatetic school]], and, later on, by the [[Neoplatonists]], who produced many [[Commentaries on Aristotle|commentaries on Aristotle's writings]]. In the Islamic world, the works of Aristotle were translated into [[Arabic language|Arabic]], and under philosophers such as [[Al-Kindi]], [[Al-Farabi]], [[Avicenna]], and [[Averroes]], Aristotelianism became a major part of [[early Islamic philosophy]]. Although some knowledge of Aristotle's logical works was known to western Europe, it wasn't until the [[Latin translations of the 12th century]] that the works of Aristotle and his Arabic commentators became widely available. Scholars such as [[Albertus Magnus]] and [[Thomas Aquinas]] interpreted and systematized Aristotle's works in accordance with [[Christian theology]].

==History==
===Ancient Greece===
{{Main|Peripatetic school}}
The original followers of Aristotle were the members of the [[Peripatetic school]]. The most prominent members of the school after Aristotle were [[Theophrastus]] and [[Strato of Lampsacus]], who both continued Aristotle's researches. During the [[Roman era]] the school concentrated on preserving and defending his work.&lt;ref&gt;Furley, David (2003), ''From Aristotle to Augustine: Routledge History of Philosophy'', 2, Routledge&lt;/ref&gt; The most important figure in this regard was [[Alexander of Aphrodisias]] who commentated on Aristotle's writings. With the rise of [[Neoplatonism]] in the 3rd century, Peripateticism as an independent philosophy came to an end, but the Neoplatonists sought to incorporate Aristotle's philosophy within their own system, and produced many [[commentaries on Aristotle]].

===Islamic world===
In the [[Abbasid Empire]], many foreign works were translated into [[Arabic language|Arabic]], large libraries were constructed, and scholars were welcomed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wiet-Baghdad&quot;&gt;[http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/med/wiet.html Gaston Wiet, ''Baghdad: Metropolis of the Abbasid Caliphate''] Retrieved 2010-04-16&lt;/ref&gt; Under the [[caliphs]] [[Harun al-Rashid]] and his son [[Al-Ma'mun]], the [[House of Wisdom]] in [[Baghdad]] flourished. Christian scholar [[Hunayn ibn Ishaq]] (809–873) was placed in charge of the translation work by the caliph. In his lifetime, Ishaq translated 116 writings, including works by Plato and Aristotle, into [[Syriac language|Syriac]] and Arabic.&lt;ref name=&quot;Opth&quot;&gt;Opth: Azmi, Khurshid. &quot;Hunain bin Ishaq on Opthalmic Surgery.&quot; Bulletin of the Indian Institute of History of Medicine 26 (1996): 69–74. Web. 29 Oct. 2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lindberg&quot;&gt;Lindberg, David C. The Beginnings of Western Science: Islamic Science. Chicago: The [[University of Chicago]], 2007. Print.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Al-Kindi]] (801–873) was the first of the Muslim [[Peripatetic school|Peripatetic]] philosophers, and is known for his efforts to introduce [[Greek philosophy|Greek]] and [[Hellenistic philosophy]] to the [[Arab world]].&lt;ref&gt;Klein-Frank, F. ''Al-Kindi''. In Leaman, O &amp; Nasr, H (2001). ''History of Islamic Philosophy''. London: Routledge. p 165&lt;/ref&gt; He incorporated Aristotelian and Neoplatonist thought into an Islamic philosophical framework. This was an important factor in the introduction and popularization of Greek philosophy in the Muslim intellectual world.&lt;ref&gt;Felix Klein-Frank (2001) ''Al-Kindi'', pages 166–167. In Oliver Leaman &amp; Hossein Nasr. ''History of Islamic Philosophy''. London: Routledge.&lt;/ref&gt;

The philosopher [[Al-Farabi]] (872–950) had great influence on science and philosophy for several centuries, and was widely regarded to be second only to Aristotle in knowledge (alluded to by his title of &quot;the Second Teacher&quot;) in his time. His work, aimed at synthesis of philosophy and [[Sufism]], paved the way for the work of [[Avicenna]] (980–1037).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url =http://www.iep.utm.edu/avicenna/| title =Avicenna (Ibn Sina) (c.980–1037)| accessdate =2007-07-13 | publisher =The Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy}}&lt;/ref&gt; Avicenna was one of the main interpreters of Aristotle.&lt;ref name=&quot;Avicenna Abu Ali Sina&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sjsu.edu/depts/Museum/avicen.html |title=Avicenna (Abu Ali Sina) |publisher=Sjsu.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-01-19| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20100111184611/http://www.sjsu.edu/depts/Museum/avicen.html| archivedate= 11 January 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; The school of thought he founded became known as [[Avicennism]], which was built on ingredients and conceptual building blocks which are largely Aristotelian and Neoplatonist.&lt;ref name=&quot;Iranica&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|last= |first= | authorlink= |title=Avicenna |year=| encyclopedia=Encyclopedia Iranica |accessdate=2010-04-14|location=|publisher=|url=http://www.iranicaonline.org/articles/avicenna-iv}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At the western end of the [[Mediterranean Sea]], during the reign of [[Al-Hakam II]] (961 to 976) in [[Córdoba, Spain|Córdoba]], a massive translation effort was undertaken, and many books were translated into Arabic. [[Averroes]] (1126–1198), who spent much of his life in Cordoba and [[Seville]], was especially distinguished as a commentator of Aristotle. He often wrote two or three different commentaries on the same work, and some 38 commentaries by Averroes on the works of Aristotle have been identified.&lt;ref name=&quot;grant30&quot;&gt;Edward Grant, (1996), ''The foundations of modern science in the Middle Ages'', page 30. Cambridge University Press&lt;/ref&gt; Although his writings had only marginal impact in Islamic countries, his works would eventually have a huge impact in the [[Latin West]],&lt;ref name=&quot;grant30&quot;/&gt; and would lead to the school of thought known as [[Averroism]].

===Europe===
Although some knowledge of Aristotle seems to have lingered on in the ecclesiastical centres of western Europe after the fall of the Roman empire, by the ninth century nearly all that was known of Aristotle consisted of [[Boethius]]'s commentaries on the ''[[Organon]]'', and a few abridgments made by Latin authors of the declining empire, [[Isidore of Seville]] and [[Martianus Capella]].&lt;ref name=&quot;schmolders&quot;&gt;Auguste Schmolders, ''History of Arabian Philosophy'' in ''The eclectic magazine of foreign literature, science, and art'', Volume 46. February 1859&lt;/ref&gt; From that time until the end of the eleventh century, little progress is apparent in Aristotelian knowledge.&lt;ref name=&quot;schmolders&quot;/&gt;

The [[renaissance of the 12th century]] saw a major search by European scholars for new learning. [[James of Venice]], who probably spent some years in [[Constantinople]], translated Aristotle's ''[[Posterior Analytics]]'' from Greek into [[Medieval Latin|Latin]] in the mid-twelfth century,&lt;ref&gt;L.D. Reynolds and Nigel G. Wilson, ''Scribes and Scholars,'' Oxford, 1974, p. 106.&lt;/ref&gt; thus making the complete Aristotelian logical corpus, the ''Organon'', available in Latin for the first time. Scholars travelled to areas of Europe that once had been under Muslim rule and still had substantial Arabic-speaking populations. From central [[Spain]], which had come under Christian rule in the eleventh century, scholars produced many of the [[Latin translations of the 12th century]]. The most productive of these translators was [[Gerard of Cremona]],&lt;ref&gt;C. H. Haskins, ''Renaissance of the Twelfth Century,'' p. 287. &quot;more of Arabic science passed into Western Europe at the hands of Gerard of Cremona than in any other way.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; (c. 1114–1187), who translated 87 books,&lt;ref&gt;For a list of Gerard of Cremona's translations see: Edward Grant (1974) ''A Source Book in Medieval Science'', (Cambridge: Harvard Univ. Pr.), pp. 35–8 or Charles Burnett, &quot;The Coherence of the Arabic-Latin Translation Program in Toledo in the Twelfth Century,&quot; ''Science in Context'', 14 (2001): at 249-288, at pp. 275–281.&lt;/ref&gt; which included many of the works of [[Aristotle]] such as his ''[[Posterior Analytics]]'', ''[[Physics (Aristotle)|Physics]]'', ''[[On the Heavens]]'', ''[[On Generation and Corruption]]'', and ''[[Meteorology (Aristotle)|Meteorology]]''. [[Michael Scot]] (c. 1175–1232) translated  [[Averroes]]' commentaries on the scientific works of [[Aristotle]].&lt;ref&gt;{{BBKL|m/michael_sco|band=5|autor=Christoph Kann|artikel=Michael Scotus|spalten=1459–1461}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Aristotle's physical writings began to be discussed openly, and at a time when Aristotle's method was permeating all theology, these treatises were sufficient to cause his prohibition for [[heterodoxy]] in the [[Condemnations of 1210–1277]].&lt;ref name=&quot;schmolders&quot;/&gt; In the first of these, in [[Paris]] in 1210, it was stated that &quot;neither the books of Aristotle on natural philosophy or their commentaries are to be read at Paris in public or secret, and this we forbid under penalty of [[excommunication]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Grant42&quot;&gt;Edward Grant, ''A Source Book in Medieval Science'', page 42 (1974). Harvard University Press&lt;/ref&gt; However, despite further attempts to restrict the teaching of Aristotle, by 1270 the ban on Aristotle's natural philosophy was ineffective.&lt;ref&gt;Rubenstein, Richard E. ''Aristotle's Children: How Christians, Muslims, and Jews Rediscovered Ancient Wisdom and Illuminated the Middle Ages'', page 215 (2004). Houghton Mifflin Harcourt&lt;/ref&gt;

[[William of Moerbeke]] (c. 1215–1286) undertook a complete translation of the works of Aristotle or, for some portions, a revision of existing translations. He was the first translator of the ''[[Politics (Aristotle)|Politics]]'' (c. 1260) from Greek into Latin. Many copies of Aristotle in Latin then in circulation were assumed to have been influenced by Averroes, who was suspected of being a source of philosophical and theological errors found in the earlier translations of Aristotle. Such claims were without merit, however, as the ''Alexandrian'' Aristotelianism of Averroes followed &quot;the strict study of the text of Aristotle, which was introduced by Avicenna, [because] a large amount of traditional [[Neoplatonism]] was incorporated with the body of traditional Aristotelianism&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmolders1842&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Schmölders |first=Auguste |editor1-last=Telford |editor1-first=John |editor2-last=Barber |editor2-first=Benjamin Aquila |editor3-last=Watkinson |editor3-first=William Lonsdale |editor4-last=Davison |editor-first4=William Theophilus |title=The London Quarterly Review |volume=11 |year=1859 |publisher=J.A. Sharp |format=full–text/pdf |page=60 |chapter=‘Essai sur les Ecoles Philosophiques chez les Arabes’ par Auguste Schmölders, (Paris 1842) |trans_chapter=Essay on the Schools of Philosophy in Arabia |chapterurl=http://books.google.com/books?id=CnhIAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA60 |quote=We have said already that the most interesting and important of the Arabian schools is that which was the simple expression of Alexandrian Aristotelianism, the school of Avicenna and Averroes; or, as the Arabians themselves called it par excellence, that of the 'philosophers.' In no material point did they differ from their master, and, therefore, an exposition of their doctrines would be useless to those who know anything of the history of philosophy; but, before the strict study of the text of Aristotle, which was introduced by Avicenna, a large amount of traditional Neo-Platonism was incorporated with the body of traditional Aristotelianism, so as to take them sometimes far astray from their master's track.}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Albertus Magnus]] (c. 1200–1280) was among the first among medieval scholars to apply Aristotle's philosophy to Christian thought. He produced paraphrases of most of the works of Aristotle available to him.&lt;ref name=&quot;sep-albert&quot;&gt;{{sep entry|albert-great|Albert the Great|Markus Fhrer}}&lt;/ref&gt; He digested, interpreted and systematized the whole of Aristotle's works, gleaned from the Latin translations and notes of the Arabian commentators, in accordance with Church doctrine. His efforts resulted in the formation of a Christian reception of Aristotle in the Western Europe.&lt;ref name=&quot;sep-albert&quot;/&gt; [[Thomas Aquinas]] (1225–1274), the pupil of Albertus Magnus, wrote a dozen commentaries on the works of Aristotle.&lt;ref name=&quot;sep-thomas&quot;&gt;{{sep entry|aquinas|Saint Thomas Aquinas|Ralph McInerny}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thomas was emphatically Aristotelian, he adopted Aristotle's analysis of physical objects, his view of place, time and motion, his proof of the prime mover, his cosmology, his account of sense perception and intellectual knowledge, and even parts of his [[Aristotelian ethics|moral philosophy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;sep-thomas&quot;/&gt; The philosophical school that arose as a legacy of the work of Thomas Aquinas was known as [[Thomism]], and was especially influential among the [[Dominicans]], and later, the [[Jesuits]].&lt;ref name=&quot;sep-thomas&quot;/&gt;

===Modern era===
After retreating under criticism from modern natural philosophers, the distinctively Aristotelian idea of [[teleology]] was transmitted through [[Christian Wolff (philosopher)|Wolff]] and [[Immanuel Kant|Kant]] to [[Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel|Hegel]], who applied it to history as a totality.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}} Although this project was criticized by [[Friedrich Adolf Trendelenburg|Trendelenburg]] and [[Franz Brentano|Brentano]] as un-Aristotelian,{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}} Hegel’s influence is now often said to be responsible for an important Aristotelian influence upon [[Karl Marx|Marx]].&lt;ref&gt;For example, George E. McCarthy (ed.), ''Marx and Aristotle: Nineteenth-Century German Social Theory and Classical Antiquity'', Although many disagree Rowman &amp; Littlefield, 1992.&lt;/ref&gt; Postmodernists, in contrast, reject Aristotelianism’s claim to reveal important theoretical truths.&lt;ref&gt;For example, Ted Sadler, ''Heidegger and Aristotle: The Question of Being'', Athlone, 1996.&lt;/ref&gt; In this, they follow [[Martin Heidegger|Heidegger]]’s critique of Aristotle as the greatest source of the entire tradition of Western philosophy.

==Contemporary Aristotelianism==
Aristotelianism is understood by its proponents as critically developing Plato’s theories.&lt;ref&gt;For contrasting examples of this, see Hans-Georg Gadamer, ''The Idea of the Good in Platonic-Aristotelian Philosophy'' (trans. P. Christopher Smith), Yale University Press, 1986, and Lloyd P. Gerson, ''Aristotle and Other Platonists'', Cornell University Press, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; Recent [[Aristotelian ethics|Aristotelian ethical]] and ‘practical’ philosophy, such as that of [[Hans-Georg Gadamer|Gadamer]] and [[John McDowell|McDowell]], is often premised upon a rejection of Aristotelianism’s traditional metaphysical or theoretical philosophy.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}} From this viewpoint, the early modern tradition of political [[republicanism]], which views the ''res publica'', public sphere or state as constituted by its citizens’ virtuous activity, can appear thoroughly Aristotelian.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}

The contemporary Aristotelian philosopher [[Alasdair MacIntyre]] is specially famous for helping to revive [[virtue ethics]] in his book ''[[After Virtue]]''. MacIntyre revises Aristotelianism with the argument that the highest temporal goods, which are internal to human beings, are actualized through participation in social practices. He opposes Aristotelianism to the managerial institutions of capitalism and its state, and to rival traditions—including the philosophies of [[David Hume|Hume]], [[Immanuel Kant|Kant]], [[Søren Kierkegaard|Kierkegaard]], and [[Nietzsche]]—that reject its idea of essentially human goods and virtues and instead legitimize [[capitalism]]. Therefore, on MacIntyre’s account, Aristotelianism is not identical with Western philosophy as a whole; rather, it is &quot;the best theory so far, [including] the best theory so far about what makes a particular theory the best one.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Alasdair MacIntyre, 'An Interview with Giovanna Borradori', in Kelvin Knight (ed.), ''The MacIntyre Reader'', Polity Press / University of Notre Dame Press, 1998, p. 264.&lt;/ref&gt; Politically and socially, it has been characterized as a newly 'revolutionary Aristotelianism'. This may be contrasted with the more conventional, apolitical and effectively conservative uses of Aristotle by, for example, Gadamer and McDowell.&lt;ref&gt;Kelvin Knight, ''Aristotelian Philosophy: Ethics and Politics from Aristotle to MacIntyre'', Polity Press, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Other important contemporary Aristotelian theorists include Fred D. Miller, Jr.&lt;ref&gt;Fred D. Miller, Jr., ''Nature, Justice, and Rights in Aristotle's Politics'', Oxford University Press, 1997.&lt;/ref&gt; in politics and Rosalind Hursthouse in ethics.&lt;ref&gt;Rosalind Hursthouse, ''On Virtue Ethics'', Oxford University Press, 1999.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticism==

[[Bertrand Russell]] criticizes Aristotle's logic on the following points &lt;ref&gt;{{harvtxt|Russell|1967}}, Chapter XXII Aristotle's Logic&lt;/ref&gt;: 

# The Aristotelian system allows formal defects leading to &quot;bad metaphysics&quot;. For example, the following [[syllogism]] is permitted: &quot;All golden mountains are mountains, all golden mountains are golden, therefore some mountains are golden&quot;, which insinuates the existence of at least one golden mountain.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvtxt|Russell|1967|p=197}}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, according to Russell, a predicate of a predicate can be a predicate of the original subject, which blurs the distinction between names and predicates with disastrous consequences; for example, a class with only one member is erroneously identified with that one member, making impossible to have a correct theory of the number one.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvtxt|Russell|1967|p=198}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# The [[syllogism]] is overvalued in comparison to other forms of deduction. For example, syllogisms are not employed in mathematics since they are less convenient.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvtxt|Russell|1967|p=198}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition, Russell ends his review of the Aristotelian logic with these words:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
I conclude that the Aristotelian doctrines with which we have been concerned in this chapter are wholly false, with the exception of the formal theory of the syllogism, which is unimportant. Any person in the present day who wishes to learn logic will be wasting his time if he reads Aristotle or any of his disciples. None the less, Aristotle's logical writings show great ability, and would have been useful to mankind if they had appeared at a time when intellectual originality was still active. Unfortunately, they appeared at the very end of the creative period of Greek thought, and therefore came to be accepted as authoritative. By the time that logical originality revived, a reign of two thousand years had made Aristotle very difficult to dethrone. Throughout modern times, practically every advance in science, in logic, or in philosophy has had to be made in the teeth of the opposition from Aristotle's disciples.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvtxt|Russell|1967|p=202}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==See also==
*[[Hylomorphism]]
*[[Phronesis]]
*[[Platonism]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin|30em}}
* {{Citation | last1=[[Bertrand Russell|Russell]] | first1=Bertrand | title=[[A History of Western Philosophy]] | publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster | year = 1967 | isbn =0671201581 }}
*Chappell, Timothy (ed.), ''Values and Virtues: Aristotelianism in Contemporary Ethics'', Oxford University Press, 2006.
*Ferrarin, Alfredo, ''Hegel and Aristotle'', Cambridge University Press, 2001.
*[[Anthony Kenny|Kenny, Anthony]], ''Essays on the Aristotelian Tradition'', Oxford University Press, 2001.
*Knight, Kelvin, ''Aristotelian Philosophy: Ethics and Politics from Aristotle to MacIntyre'', Polity Press, 2007. ISBN 978-0-7456-1976-7.
*Knight, Kelvin &amp; Paul Blackledge (eds.), ''Revolutionary Aristotelianism: Ethics, Resistance and Utopia'', Lucius &amp; Lucius (Stuttgart, Germany), 2008.
*Lobkowicz, Nicholas, ''Theory and Practice: History of a Concept from Aristotle to Marx'', University of Notre Dame Press, 1967.
*MacIntyre, Alasdair, ''After Virtue: A Study in Moral Theory'', University of Notre Dame Press, 1984 / Duckworth, 1985 (2nd edn.).
*MacIntyre, Alasdair, ''Whose Justice? Which Rationality?'', University of Notre Dame Press / Duckworth, 1988.
*MacIntyre, Alasdair, ''Three Rival Versions of Moral Enquiry: Encyclopaedia, Genealogy, and Tradition'', University of Notre Dame Press / Duckworth, 1990.
*MacIntyre, Alasdair, ‘The Theses on Feuerbach: A Road Not Taken’, in Kelvin Knight (ed.), ''The MacIntyre Reader'', University of Notre Dame Press / Polity Press, 1998.
*MacIntyre, Alasdair, ''Dependent Rational Animals: Why Human Beings Need the Virtues'', Open Court / Duckworth, 1999.
*MacIntyre, Alasdair, ‘Natural Law as Subversive: The Case of Aquinas’ and ‘Rival Aristotles: 1. Aristotle Against Some Renaissance Aristotelians; 2. Aristotle Against Some Modern Aristotelians’, in MacIntyre, ''Ethics and Politics: Selected Essays'' volume 2, Cambridge University Press, 2006.
*Moraux, Paul, ''Der Aristotelismus bei den Griechen, Von Andronikos bis Alexander von Aphrodisias'': Vol. I:  Die Renaissance des Aristotelismus im I. Jh.v. Chr. (1973); Vol. II: Der Aristotelismus im I. und II. Jh.n. Chr. (1984); Vol. III: Alexander von Aphrodisias (2001) – Edited by Jürgen Wiesner, with a chapter on Ethics by Robert W. Sharples.
*Riedel, Manfred (ed.), ''Rehabilitierung der praktischen Philosophie'', Rombach, volume 1, 1972; volume 2, 1974.
*Ritter, Joachim, ''Metaphysik und Politik: Studien zu Aristoteles und Hegel'', Suhrkamp, 1977.
*Schrenk, Lawrence P. (ed.), ''Aristotle in Late Antiquity'', Catholic University of America Press, 1994.
*Sharples, R. W. (ed.), ''Whose Aristotle? Whose Aristotelianism?'', Ashgate, 2001.
*Shute, Richard, ''On the History of the Process by Which the Aristotelian Writings Arrived at Their Present Form'', Arno Press, 1976 (originally 1888).
*Sorabji, Richard (ed.), ''Aristotle Transformed: The Ancient Commentators and Their Influence'', Duckworth, 1990.
*Stocks, John Leofric, ''Aristotelianism'', Harrap, 1925.
*[[Henry B. Veatch|Veatch, Henry B.]], ''Rational Man: A Modern Interpretation of Aristotelian Ethics'', Indiana University Press, 1962.
{{refend}}

==External links==
* [http://www.ontology.co/corpus-aristotelicum.htm The Peripatos after Aristotle: Origin of the Corpus Aristotelicum] with an annotated bibliography
* Clayton, Edward. (2005)  [http://www.iep.utm.edu/p/p-macint.htm Political Philosophy of Alasdair MacIntyre], [[Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy]]
* [http://www.macintyreanenquiry.org International Society for MacIntyrean Enquiry]
{{Philosophy topics}}
[[Category:Aristotelianism| ]]
[[Category:History of ideas]]
[[Category:History of philosophy]]
[[Category:Ethical theories]]
[[Category:Metaphysical theories]]
[[Category:Philosophical traditions]]

[[ca:Aristotelisme]]
[[cs:Aristotelismus]]
[[de:Aristotelismus]]
[[es:Aristotelismo]]
[[fa:ارسطوگری]]
[[fr:Aristotélisme]]
[[gl:Aristotelismo]]
[[id:Aristotelianisme]]
[[it:Aristotelismo]]
[[ka:არისტოტელიზმი]]
[[hu:Arisztoteliánusok]]
[[pl:Arystotelizm]]
[[pt:Aristotelismo]]
[[sk:Aristotelizmus]]
[[sl:Aristotelizem]]
[[fi:Aristotelismi]]
[[sv:Aristotelism]]
[[tr:Aristotelesçilik]]
[[uk:Аристотелізм]]
[[zh:亚里士多德學派]]</text>
      <sha1>amm1tq51lqrtsapof8j5h7uulvjlznq</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
