<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Asian values</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>327630</id>
    <revision>
      <id>514363120</id>
      <parentid>514361594</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-24T18:28:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>173.219.79.137</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* See also */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14005">'''Asian values''' was a concept that came into vogue briefly in the 1990s to justify [[authoritarian]] regimes in Asia, predicated on the belief in the existence within [[Asia]]n countries of a unique set of institutions and political ideologies which reflected the region's culture and history. In particular, this idea was strongly advocated by former Prime Minister [[Mahathir Mohamad]] of [[Malaysia]] and former Prime Minister [[Lee Kuan Yew]] of [[Singapore]] in 1995. The theory is that there are many differences in Eastern and Western [[idea]]s, [[philosophy]] and [[religion]]. For instance, [[collectivism]], the idea that human beings are an integral part of the universe and people are fundamentally connected, is stronger in Asian society.&lt;ref name=Liu&gt; Liu Qingxue (2003), [http://www.staff.amu.edu.pl/~inveling/pdf/liu_quingxue_inve9.pdf/] Understanding Different Cultural Patterns or Orientations Between East and West&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, [[individualism]], the idea that a human being is an independent part of the universe and society, is stronger in [[Western society]].&lt;ref name=Liu /&gt; Nevertheless, there is no single set of &quot;Asian&quot; values. Main schools of Asian values include [[Buddhism]], [[Confucianism]], [[Hinduism]], [[Integral yoga]], [[Islam]], [[Taoism]], [[Zen]], along with other philosophies, movements and religions.

The debate over Asian values, which used to be conducted heatedly, gradually declined during the 1997 [[Asian Financial Crisis]] when it became evident that Asia as a whole lacked a regional institution mechanism, let alone any collective action to deal with imminent problems and thus had been subdued recently.&lt;ref name=Gred&gt;Gred Langguth (2003), [http://www.springerlink.com/content/tc9dt6eqk9jj1ll0/  Asian Values revisited]''Asia Europe journal'', ''2003''&lt;/ref&gt; The term has continuously challenged the western interpretation, which remained uncontested since the [[French Revolution]]. During the booming economy, especially in [[East Asia|eastern Asia]], the initiators of the debate on ‘‘Asian values’’ wished to create a pan-Asian identity as a counterpart to the identity of ‘‘the West’’.&lt;ref name=Gred /&gt; The handover of [[Hong Kong]] and [[Macao]] may have symbolized the removal of the final colonial remnants in Asia. The response of the [[Western world|West]] to the new self-confidence manifested by numerous Asian political leaders was of a decidedly defensive nature. &lt;ref name=Gred /&gt;

== Definition ==
Because the proponents of the concept came from different cultural backgrounds, no single definition of the term exists, but typically &quot;Asian values&quot; encompass some influences of [[Confucianism]], in particular loyalty towards the family, corporation, and nation; the forgoing of personal [[Freedom (political)|freedom]] for the sake of society's stability and prosperity; the pursuit of academic and technological excellence; and work ethic and [[thrift]]. Proponents of &quot;Asian values&quot;, who tend to support Asian-style [[authoritarian]] governments claim they are more appropriate for the region than [[Western democracy]].&lt;ref&gt;Mark R Thompson, [http://sites.asiasociety.org/asia21summit/wp-content/uploads/2010/11/PacificAsia.pdf &quot;Pacific Asia after 'Asian values'&quot;], ''Third World Quarterly'', 2004&lt;/ref&gt; These values found expression in the [[universal human rights#Bangkok Declaration|Bangkok Declaration of 1993]], which reemphasized the principles of sovereignty, self-determination, and noninterference.

'''A brief list of such &quot;Asian Values&quot; includes:'''{{Citation needed|date=January 2009}}

# Predisposition towards [[Single-party state|single-party]] rule rather than [[political pluralism]]
# Preference for [[social]] harmony (see [[Fraternization]]) and [[consensus]] as opposed to [[confrontation]] and [[dissent]]
# Concern with [[socio-economic]] well-being instead of [[civil liberties]] and [[human rights]]
# Preference for the [[welfare]] and collective well-being of the community over [[individual rights]]
# Loyalty and respect towards forms of authority including parents, teachers and government
# [[Collectivism]] and [[communitarianism]] over [[individualism]] and [[liberalism]]
# [[Authoritarian]] governments (which have certain responsibilities as well as privileges) as opposed to [[liberal democracy]].

== Political significance ==
The concept of &quot;Asian values&quot; was a popular idea in [[People's Republic of China]], [[Malaysia]], [[Singapore]], [[Indonesia]] and also in some political circles in [[Japan]].{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}} In Malaysia and Singapore, the concept of Asian values was embraced partly because it reconciled [[Islam]], the religion of the [[Malay people|Malays]], with the [[Confucianism]] of the [[overseas Chinese|ethnic Chinese]], and [[Hinduism]], thereby helping to create a sense of common values between different ethnic and religious groups in those countries, as well as forming an ideology that they could call their own which is different from their understanding of the West.&lt;ref&gt;Nishida, Kitaro (1989), Nishida Kitaro Zenshu (Complete Works of Nishida Kitaro in nineteen volumes), 4th ed., Iwanami Shoten, Tokyo&lt;/ref&gt; In Japan, it was popular among some nationalist circles because it challenged the West and also offered the possibility of Japanese leadership in a new Asia.&lt;ref&gt;Okakura, Kakuzo (1904/2002), The Ideals of the East, Tuttle Publishing, North Clarenton&lt;/ref&gt; From the 1960s to the 1980s, the East and Southeast Asian regions were the only developing regions that grew exponentially in terms of economic wealth; some proponents of Asian Values have credited this success to a distinctive &quot;third-way&quot; Asian political model that was touted as an alternative to both totalitarism and liberal democracy.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}

[[Mahathir Mohamad]] and [[Lee Kuan Yew]], at that time the prime ministers of Malaysia and Singapore, respectively, were particularly vocal advocates of Asian values. Lee maintained that more than economics, more than politics, a nation's culture will determine its fate. &lt;ref&gt;&quot;A Conversation with Lee Kwan Yu,&quot; Fareed Zakaria,''Foreign Affairs'' (March/April 1994) &lt;div&gt;[http://www.foreignaffairs.com/articles/49691/fareed-zakaria/a-conversation-with-lee-kuan-yew]. &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; [[Fareed Zakaria]] has written extensively on Asian values, while [[Amartya Sen]] has been one of the concept's strongest critics. Some critics of the term argue that no universal &quot;Asian&quot; value system exists, because the cultural diversity of Asia is too great for there to be a single set of common values across the region.&lt;ref&gt;Joy Hendry, Heung Wah Wong, edited by, (2006), ''Dismantling the East-West Dichotomy: Essays in Honour of Jan van Bremen'', New York: Routledge,  ISBN 0-415-39738-3&lt;/ref&gt; The suggestion that a set of 'Asian values' operated throughout the Asian region, or even just in East Asia, contradicts what we know about the presence of long-standing religious (Islamic, Hindu, Confucian, [[Buddhist]], and [[Christian]]) and other divisions in the region, and of the major social and cultural transformation that has been underway, especially in the last decade or so.&lt;ref&gt;Milner, Anthony (1999), [http://dspace.anu.edu.au/html/1885/41912/values.html What's Happened to Asian Values?]&lt;/ref&gt;

The concept of &quot;Asian values&quot; began to lose currency after the [[Asian financial crisis]] weakened the economies of many Asian countries, leading to the [[Fall of Suharto|collapse]] of the [[New Order (Indonesia)|Suharto regime]] in [[Indonesia]].{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}} Some consider these values to have contributed to the crisis.&lt;ref name=Krugman/&gt; When the crisis spread worldwide, the blame subsided.&lt;ref name=Krugman&gt;{{cite web |first=Paul |last=Krugman |authorlink=Paul Krugman |url=http://web.mit.edu/krugman/www/swansong.html |title=Latin America's Swan Song |accessdate=October 30, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A sharp observation may suggest that speaking in the name of Asian values (as opposed to Western, or universal values) serves the purpose of forming a robust ideological counter force in Asia, and most particularly in China, to the nations which most clearly aim at the imposition of western ideology on the East.&lt;ref&gt;Mahbubani, Kishore (2008), The New Asian Hemisphere: The Irresistible Shirt of Global Power to the East, PublicAffairs Publisher, New York&lt;/ref&gt; One way or the other, the use of the term is capable in itself of creating a significant [[Dialogue Among Civilizations]] between human ideas in all fields.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.dialoguecentre.org/ |title=Web site of the International Center for Dialogue Among Civilizations}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[The End of History and the Last Man]] written by [[Francis Fukuyama]], a strong propoenent of Western liberal democracy, is one of the key examples to provide such ideological counter force against Asian values. In his book, Fukuyama notes that democracy &quot;...conquered rival ideologies like hereditary monarchy, fascism and most recently communism&quot;, marked by the end of the Cold War. His thesis is that &quot;Liberal democracy may constitute the &quot;end point of mankind's ideological evolution&quot; and the &quot;final form of human government&quot; and as such constituted the end of history.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Francis Fukuyama, The End of History and the Last Man. Free Press. ISBN 0-02-910975-2.(1992)&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 2006 [[Indonesia]]n [[Vice President]] [[Jusuf Kalla]] linked the concepts of Asian values with the proposed East Asian Free Trade Agreement and East Asian Community arising from the [[East Asia Summit]]. He partly defends Asian values by placing emphasis on co-operation over competition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |publisher=People's Daily Online |url=http://english.people.com.cn/200612/01/eng20061201_327303.html |title=Indonesia calls for countries to bear Asian values}}&lt;/ref&gt; Even until recently, there have been a number of efforts promote East Asian regional institution such as the idea of single regional FTA like the East Asia Free Trade Area(EAFTA) among the ASEAN+3 countries — the 10 ASEAN members plus the People’s Republic of China (PRC), Japan and the Republic of Korea — or a Comprehensive Economic Partnership in East Asia (CEPEA) among the ASEAN+6 countries — also including Australia, India and New Zealand. These initiatives may be seen as a first step towards the creation of a region-wide economic community. According to the Asian Development Bank (ADB) study Institutions for Asian Integration: Toward an Asian Economic Community (2010), Asia is supported by a dense web of 40 overlapping regional and sub-regional institutions that promote regional cooperation and integration at the intergovernmental level.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Clear benefits in stronger Asian regional institutions&quot; 26 October 2011. East Asia Forum Quarterly, ‘Asia’s global impact‘. Retrieved 03 June 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; The realization of a single Asian community would strengthen the idea of Asian values.

== Criticism==
Taiwan social-politics critic [[Lung Ying-tai|Lung Ying-Tai]]&lt;ref&gt;[[:zh:wikipedia.org/wiki/%E9%BE%8D%E6%87%89%E5%8F%B0|龍應台]]{{zh icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; argues that Asian values are merely a [[doublespeak]] on suppressing universal values of [[freedom of speech]] and [[human rights]].

Several Asian political figures have expressed criticism of the idea of Asian values, including former [[President of the Republic of China|President]] of the [[Republic of China|Republic of China (Taiwan)]], [[Lee Teng-hui]], and former [[President of South Korea|President]] of the [[Republic of Korea]] (South Korea), [[Kim Dae Jung]].

Also, in his article &quot;Democracy as a Universal Value&quot;, [[Amartya Sen]] pointed out that no universal &quot;Asian&quot; value system could possibly exist, because the cultural diversity of Asia is far too great for there to be a single set of common values across the region.&lt;ref&gt;Amartya Sen, &quot;Democracy as a Universal Value&quot;, Journal of Democracy, 10.3, 3-17.(1999)&lt;/ref&gt;

== Media ==
The concept of Asian values is the main theme of the 2002 film ''[[Hero (2002 film)|Hero]]'' which was directed by internationally acclaimed Chinese filmmaker [[Zhang Yimou]] and starred famed martial arts actor [[Jet Li]]. The film was criticised for its perceived pro-[[totalitarianism|totalitarian]] subtext and ulterior meaning of triumph of [[security]] and [[Economic stability|stability]] over [[liberty]] and [[human rights]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.villagevoice.com/2004-08-17/film/man-with-no-name-tells-a-story-of-heroics-color-coordination/ Man With No Name Tells a Story of Heroics, Color Coordination]&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|Asia}}
*[[Guided democracy]]
*[[Liberal democracy]]
*[[Nihonjinron]]
*[[Pan-Asianism]]
*[[Recalcitrant Interdependence]]
*[[Traditionalism]] - The Western equivalent of &quot;Asian Values&quot;

==References==
{{reflist}}


===Other===
* Loh kok Wah, Francis &amp; Khoo Boo Teik. &quot;Democracy in Malaysia: Discourses and Practices&quot; Curzon Press, Richmond Surrey, 2002.
* [[Surain Subramaniam]]. &quot;The Asian Values Debate: Implications for the Spread of Liberal Democracy&quot; [[Asian Affairs]]. March 2000.
* Ankerl, Guy.  Coexisting Contemporary Civilizations: Arabo-Muslim, Bharati, Chinese, and Western. INUPRESS, Geneva, 2002 ISBN 2-88155-004-5

==External links==

*[http://www.hmb.utoronto.ca/HMB303H/weekly_supp/week-02/Sen_Asian_Values.pdf Human Rights and Asian Values: What Lee Kuan Yew and Le Peng don't understand about Asia] by [[Amartya Sen]].
*[http://academic2.american.edu/~dfagel/Markets&amp;democracyfukuyama.html The Illusion of Exceptionalism] by [[Francis Fukuyama]]
* [http://www.puaf.umd.edu/IPPP/li.htm &quot;Asian Values&quot; and the Universality of Human Rights] by Xiaorong Li
* [http://dspace.anu.edu.au/html/1885/41912/values.html What's Happened to Asian Values?] by Anthony Milner

{{DEFAULTSORT:Asian Values}}
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Asian studies]]
[[Category:Political ideologies]]

[[ko:아시아적 가치]]
[[ro:Valori asiatice]]
[[sh:Azijske vrijednosti]]</text>
      <sha1>ji7aej0bm65n37sttbs4xsddacycw4a</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
