<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Assembly of the Poor</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>534537</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519944366</id>
      <parentid>509437740</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-26T13:31:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Coyets</username>
        <id>1644213</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Categories added</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7983">{{Wikify|date=November 2011}}
'''The Assembly of the Poor''' (Thai: สมัชชาคนจน) is a [[non-governmental organization]] in [[Thailand]]. Its aim is to help those affected by development projects and industries to become involved in the process of development, so that they benefit from those projects.

The Assembly of the Poor is now considered to be a political voice for villagers and marginalized members of society.  As an organization, it is allied with other NGOs in Thailand.  When the Assembly of the Poor first began, it was accused of dismantling Thailand's unity and the democratic principles of Thai ideologies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Phongpaichit|first=Pasuk|title=Civilising the State: state, civil society and politics in Thailand|year=1999|publisher=Amsterdam : Centre for Asian Studies Amsterdam|location=Amsterdam|pages=1–14|url=http://www.iias.nl/asia/wertheim/lectures/WL_Phongpaichit.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; The non-governmental organization is an amalgamation of seven districts representing every region of Thailand. It is composed of [[urban area|urban]] and [[rural area|rural]] small-scale agriculturists and manual laborers. Due to its variety of members, the Assembly is able to transcend regional and [[social stratification|class divisions]].

==Background==
In the 1950s, Thailand underwent a plan of development, supported by the [[World Bank]], intended to help the country [[industrialization|industrialize]]. Subsequent foreign investment in the company's economy assisted it towards meeting its goals, but while it would by the 1990s be considered a leader among developing nations, along with other Southeast Asian countries, by the World Bank and other economists, development was uneven through the country, with a long-term problem of unequal distribution of wealth and technology. The agricultural community, which had both sacrificed natural resources and contributed significant capital to the development of infrastructure to benefit the plan without seeing significant gains for themselves, grew resentful.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Palmgren|first=Pei|title=Claims to Globalization: Thailand's Assembly of the Poor and the Multilevel Resistance to Capitalist Development|url=http://rsmag.org/wp-content/uploads/2008/06/claimsto200802.html|publisher=New York University|accessdate=15 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Formation==
The Assembly of the Poor grew out of this unrest, beginning with villagers angry about local impact of the [[Pak Mun dam]]. One of the co-founders of the group, Vanida Tantiwittayapitak had become involved in Pak Mun after her relocation to the country following the [[Thammasat University massacre]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationmultimedia.com/2007/12/07/headlines/headlines_30058452.php Poor mourn loss of hero], ''The Nation (Thailand)''; retrieved 2007-12-06&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationmultimedia.com/2007/12/07/national/national_30058462.php Hero of the poor], ''The Nation (Thailand)''; retrieved 2007-12-06&lt;/ref&gt; While it started as a rural assembly, city workers were also welcomed. 

The grass-roots organization became official on International [[Human Rights Day]], 10 December, in 1995, becoming the first rural political voice after the 1975 suppression of the Peasants' Federation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Baker|first=Chris|title=South East Asia Research|year=2000|publisher=IP Publishing LTD|pages=5–29}}&lt;/ref&gt; This took place on the opening day of their first conference,  &quot;Assembly of the Poor: The consequences of Large-Scale Development Projects&quot;, held at Thammasat University of Bangkok and intended to coincide with the [[ASEAN Summit]] scheduled in [[Bangkok]] on 14–15 December.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Missingham|first=Bruce|title=Forging Solidarity and Identity in the Assembly of the Poor: from Local Struggles to a National Social Movement in Thailand|journal=Asian Studies Review|date=November 2003|year=2003|volume=27|doi=10.1111/1467-8403.00154|url=http://web.ebscohost.com/ehost/pdfviewer/pdfviewer?sid=9fcc9ddf-33df-4d6d-ae22-5783b972534f%40sessionmgr15&amp;vid=2&amp;hid=13}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Conference attendees spent several days developing the &quot;Mun River Declaration&quot;, which both announced their existence and cricitized the prioritization of industrial development at the expense of local communities. It also fired a warning shot against the bow of government, forming a petition detailing their grievances to the government,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Missingham|first=Bruce|title=Forging Solidarity and Identity in the Assembly of the Poor: From Local Struggles to National Social Movement in Thailand|journal=Asian Studies Review|year=2003|month=September|volume=27|issue=3|doi=10.1111/1467-8403.00154|url=ttp://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;db=aph&amp;AN=10832894&amp;site=ehost-live}}&lt;/ref&gt; punctuated by a march through Bangkok of hundreds of AOP members and sympathizers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Palmgren|first=Pei|title=Claims to Globalization: Thailand's Assembly of the Poor and the Multilevel Resistance to Capitalist Development|url=http://rsmag.org/wp-content/uploads/2008/06/claimsto200802.html|publisher=New York University|accessdate=15 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Goals==
The Assembly of the Poor's first strategy connecting the issues experienced by local communities plainly to national policy. Their second was creating a sense of shared identity among those who identified themselves as suffering from developmental policies or being excluded from developmental benefits.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Missingham|first=Bruce|title=Forging Solidarity and Identity in the Assembly of the Poor: From Local Struggles to National Social Movement in Thailand|journal=Asian Studies Review|year=2003|month=September|volume=27|issue=3|doi=10.1111/1467-8403.00154|url=http://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;db=aph&amp;AN=10832894&amp;site=ehost-live}}&lt;/ref&gt; AoP both demands compensation for those injured by developmental strategies and access to resources by their own communities, but does not limit its political activities to self-interest.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Sivaraska|first=Sulak|title=Assembly of the Poor: Siam's Poor Take Action on Their Own Behalf|url=http://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;db=aph&amp;AN=7717995&amp;site=ehost-live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Challenges==
{{unreferenced section|date=May 2012}}
According to the ''[[Bangkok Post]]'' the recent issues in Thailand have a lot to do with the political divisions trying to undermine the AOP.{{vague|date=May 2012}} The lack of unity among the poor poses a major obstacle in the battle to a more democratic society. In the 21st century, political divisions in Thailand have weakened the movements of the Assembly of the Poor. In order for the NGO to stay in a positive direction the ''Bangkok Post'' states they must focused on;
#Natural resources
#Protection of local people's rights to manage those resources
#They also to need to move certain issues to the forefront of their political voice.
#Community rights
#An aggressive tax rate on land holdings
#Establishment of a land development fund
#Fair land distribution&lt;/b&gt;

The rural farmers and peasants need to form a foundation of community rights that is the constitution of how they country should run. They need to do this to enhance the future of Thailand and it rank in the global economy and that of a developing nation.

==References==
*''The Assembly of the Poor in Thailand, From Local Struggles to National Protest Movement'', Bruce D. Missingham, ISBN 974-9575-28-8
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.internationalrivers.org/en/southeast-asia/thailand/pak-mun-dam International Rivers information about the AOP]

[[Category:Non-governmental organisations based in Thailand]]
[[Category:Thai society]]
[[Category:Civic and political organizations]]
[[Category:Political advocacy groups in Thailand]]
[[Category:Organizations established in 1995]]
[[Category:1995 establishments in Thailand]]

[[de:Assembly of the Poor]]
[[th:สมัชชาคนจน]]</text>
      <sha1>om89jtlqhyfi1wdnib4cdqlf55cx4ph</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
