<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Autism Speaks</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>22282057</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521861094</id>
      <parentid>521858395</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-07T18:27:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>3geek14</username>
        <id>17843119</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23120">[[File:Autism Speaks Logo.jpg|right|250px]]
{{Autism cure movement}}
'''Autism Speaks''' is the world's largest [[autism]] advocacy organization that sponsors autism research and conducts awareness and outreach activities aimed at families, governments, and the public.&lt;ref name=Singh/&gt; It was founded in February 2005 by [[Bob Wright]], vice chairman of [[General Electric]], and by his wife Suzanne, a year after their grandson Christian was diagnosed with autism.&lt;ref name=FamilyStrain/&gt;

In January 2008, child clinical psychologist [[Geraldine Dawson]], Ph.D., became Autism Speaks chief science officer. In April 2010, the organization named [[Yoko Ono]] its first &quot;Global Autism Ambassador.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;monsters&quot;&gt;http://www.monstersandcritics.com/people/news/article_1545374.php/Yoko-Ono-named-first-Global-Autism-Ambassador&lt;/ref&gt; Since its founding, Autism Speaks has merged with three existing autism organizations and raised millions of dollars for autism research.&lt;ref name=FamilyStrain/&gt;

Since February 2009, Autism Speaks has used the Wubbzy character from ''[[Wow! Wow! Wubbzy!]]'' as a mascot.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.autismspeaks.org/press/wubbzy_waad.php|title=Autism Speaks and 'Wow! Wow! Wubbzy!' Team Up to Shine a Spotlight on World Autism Awareness Day|publisher=Autism Speaks press release|date=February 19, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Autism Speaks is often criticized by [[autism rights]] advocates including many autistic people who claim that it excludes autistic people from leadership positions, uses stigmatizing rhetoric, and focuses on issues that are not relevant to the autistic community .&lt;ref name=ASconsiderfacts&gt;{{cite web |url=http://autisticadvocacy.org/wp-content/uploads/2012/05/Autism_Speaks_Flyer.pdf |title=Autism Speaks – Consider the Facts |date=May 16, 2012 |work=Autistic Self Advocacy Network |publisher=Autistic Self Advocacy Network |type=Flyer |format=PDF |archiveurl= |archivedate= |deadurl= |accessdate=2012-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Activities==

Autism Speaks is an [[autism]] charity that, along with its predecessor organizations, has been a critical source of funding directed towards the prevention, cure and treatment of [[autism spectrum disorder]]s; it also conducts awareness and outreach activities aimed at families, governments, and the public.&lt;ref name=Singh&gt;{{cite journal |author= Singh J, Hallmayer J, Illes J |title= Interacting and paradoxical forces in neuroscience and society |journal= Nat Rev Neurosci |volume=8 |issue=2 |pages=153–60 |year=2007 |pmid=17237806 |pmc=1885680 |doi=10.1038/nrn2073}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a 2006 press release, Autism Speaks stated as its goal &quot;to accelerate and fund biomedical research into the causes, prevention, treatments and cure for autism spectrum disorders; to increase awareness of the disorder; and to improve the quality of life of affected individuals and their families&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |url=http://www.autismspeaks.org/press/autism_speaks_can_merger.php |title= Cure Autism Now and Autism Speaks announce plans to combine operations |publisher= Autism Speaks |date=2006-11-29 |accessdate=2008-11-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Research===

Autism Speaks and its predecessor organizations have strengthened public awareness for autism research, raised funds directly for research, and lobbied Congress to leverage the privately raised money with much greater public funds. From 1997 to 2006 their advocacy in the areas of treatment and environmental factors shifted research priorities in the U.S. from basic research to translational and clinical research, with less emphasis on the underlying biology and greater emphasis on putting what was known to practical use.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Trends in US autism research funding |author=Singh J, Illes J, Lazzeroni L, Hallmayer J |journal=J Autism Dev Disord |year=2009 |volume=39 |issue=5 |pages=788–95 |doi=10.1007/s10803-008-0685-0 |pmid=19148735 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Autism Speaks supports research in four main areas:&lt;ref name=Dawson-interview&gt;{{cite journal |journal= Autism Spectr Q |year=2008 |issue=16 |pages=8–11 |url=http://asquarterly.com/articles/dawson_interview.pdf |format=PDF |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20090530061231/http://www.asquarterly.com/articles/dawson_interview.pdf |archivedate=2009-05-30 |title= Dr. Geraldine Dawson: setting the research agenda for Autism Speaks |author= Twachtman-Cullen D}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Etiology]] includes genetic and environmental factors that may cause autism. This research includes searches for autism susceptibility genes, animal models for autism, environmental toxins, maternal viral infections, and vaccine schedules.
* [[Biology]] studies cells, the brain, and the body.  This focuses on brain development and includes the Autism Tissue Program discussed further below.
* [[Diagnosis]] includes [[epidemiology]], early diagnosis, and biomarkers.
* [[Autism therapies]] include medication, behavioral, and psychological interventions.  It includes treatments for children's medical conditions such as [[sleep disorder]]s and [[gastrointestinal]] conditions that may hinder behavioral interventions, along with treatments for older individuals, and [[complementary and alternative medicine]].&lt;!-- ref name=Dawson-interview/ --&gt;

Autism Speaks funds the [[Autism Genetic Resource Exchange]] (AGRE), a [[DNA]] repository and family registry of genotypic and phenotypic information that is available to autism researchers worldwide.&lt;ref name=AGRE&gt;{{cite journal |journal= Am J Hum Genet |year=2001 |volume=69 |issue=2 |pages=463–6 |title= The Autism Genetic Resource Exchange: a resource for the study of autism and related neuropsychiatric conditions |author= Geschwind DH, Sowinski J, Lord C ''et al.'' |pmid=11452364 |pmc=1235320 |doi=10.1086/321292}}&lt;/ref&gt; The AGRE was established in the 1990s by a predecessor organization, Cure Autism Now.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.usatoday.com/life/2004-01-12-autism-main_x.htm |author= Painter K |title= Science getting to roots of autism |work= USA Today |date=2004-01-12 |accessdate=2008-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Autism Speaks funds the Autism Tissue Program, a network of researchers that manages and distributes brain tissues donated for autism research.  These donations are rare and are a vital component of research into the causes of autism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |journal= Brain Pathol |year=2007 |volume=17 |issue=4 |pages=412–21 |title= Autism brain tissue banking |author= Haroutunian V, Pickett J |doi=10.1111/j.1750-3639.2007.00097.x |pmid=17919127}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Autism Speaks supports the Clinical Trials Network, which focuses on new pharmacological treatments.  It also supports the Toddler Treatment Network, which develops new interventions for infants and toddlers.&lt;ref name=Dawson-interview/&gt;

Autism Speaks believes that [[vaccine]]s have been shown to be safe for the vast majority of children, and that vaccines are important for preventing serious diseases such as [[measles]] and [[mumps]]. It recognizes that some individuals may have [[adverse reaction]]s to, or respond poorly to, vaccines, and advocates research into identifying any subgroups of such individuals and mechanisms behind any such reactions.&lt;ref name=Dawson-interview/&gt; This has strained relations between the Wrights and their daughter Katie, the mother of an autistic boy. Katie believes her son's autism was caused by [[thiomersal]], a preservative that was formerly common in children's vaccines in the U.S.; no major scientific studies have confirmed this hypothesis.&lt;ref name=FamilyStrain&gt;{{cite news |title= Autism debate strains a family and its charity |author= Gross J, Strom S |work= New York Times |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/18/us/18autism.html |date=2007-06-18 |accessdate=2007-10-09| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20071015212551/http://nytimes.com/2007/06/18/us/18autism.html| archivedate= 15 October 2007 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Awareness===

The Walk for Autism Research program conducts an annual autism walk on [[Long Island, New York]]; the walk attracted 20,000 participants in October, 2006, and raised $2 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.autismspeaks.org/walk_events/long_island_kickoff.php |title= Long Island Walk holds enthusiastic 2007 kick off |publisher= Autism Speaks |year=2007 |accessdate=2008-11-21| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20081007131938/http://www.autismspeaks.org/walk_events/long_island_kickoff.php| archivedate= 7 October 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Suzanne Wright appeared on [[NBC]]'s ''[[Today (NBC program)|The Today Show]]'' to discuss the [[Ad Council]] campaign launched in conjunction with Autism Speaks to raise autism awareness and to highlight the importance of early detection.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.autismspeaks.org/inthenews/today_suzanne_wright_alert.php |title= Suzanne Wright discusses new Autism Speaks awareness campaign on Today Show, MSNBC |publisher= Autism Speaks |accessdate=2008-11-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''The Today Show'' aired a week-long series of stories in February, 2005, highlighting autism research and treatment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.autismspeaks.org/inthenews/naar_archive/nbc_networks_focus_on_autism.php |title= NBC networks to focus on autism |publisher= Autism Speaks |date=2005-02-17 |accessdate=2007-11-21| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20071202073512/http://www.autismspeaks.org/inthenews/naar_archive/nbc_networks_focus_on_autism.php| archivedate= 2 December 2007 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Autism Speaks sponsored and distributes the short film ''[[Autism Every Day]]'', produced by Lauren Thierry and Eric Solomon.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= Hard-hitting look at autism is being shown at Sundance |author= Moore AS |work= New York Times |url=http://nytimes.com/2007/01/21/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/21lifilm.html |date=2007-01-21 |accessdate=2008-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thierry accused Autism Speaks of not paying her for her work on the feature version of the film; Autism Speaks asserted that Thierry was paid in full.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author= Friedman R |title= Celebrity autism group in civil war |date=2007-06-07 |work=FOX News |url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,278814,00.html#2 |accessdate=2007-10-09| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20071009065218/http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,278814,00.html| archivedate= 9 October 2007 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; Autism Speaks staff member Alison Singer was reportedly criticized for a scene in which she said, in the presence of her autistic daughter, that when faced with having to place the girl in an inadequate school, she contemplated driving her car off a bridge with her child in the car. Thierry said that these feelings were not unusual among the non-autistic mothers of autistic children.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= Autism: the art of compassionate living |author= Liss J |work=WireTap |url=http://wiretapmag.org/education/38631 |date=2006-07-11 |accessdate=2008-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Mergers==

Autism Speaks, through a series of mergers, has combined organizations that funded [[peer review]]ed research into genetic causes, championed alternative theories and therapies, and advocated for individuals with autism.&lt;ref name=FamilyStrain/&gt;

===National Alliance for Autism Research===

In early 2006, a year after its founding, Autism Speaks merged with the [[National Alliance for Autism Research]] (NAAR).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |url=http://www.autismspeaks.org/press/autism_speaks_naar_merger.php |title= Autism Speaks and the National Alliance for Autism Research complete merger |publisher= Autism Speaks |date=2006-02-13 |accessdate=2008-11-21| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20081121165437/http://www.autismspeaks.org/press/autism_speaks_naar_merger.php| archivedate= 21 November 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; NAAR, founded in 1994, was the first U.S. nonprofit organization dedicated to supporting research into causes, treatment, and cures for autism spectrum disorders.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_go2827/is_/ai_n7046769 |title=National Alliance for Autism Research: committed to accelerating biomedical autism research to unlock the mysteries of autism spectrum disorders |work= The Exceptional Parent |date=April 2002 |pages=103–5 |accessdate=2008-11-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; The founders comprised a small group of parents, including two psychiatrists, a lawyer and a chemistry professor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://www.psychiatrictimes.com/display/article/10168/49991 |title= A psychiatrist's journey from parent to founder of research advocacy organization |author= London E |journal= Psychiatr Times |year=1997 |volume=14 |issue=11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

NAAR raised money to provide research grants focusing on autism, and had committed an excess of $20 million to over 200 autism research projects, fellowships and collaborative programs—more than any other non-governmental organization.  NAAR focused intently on its role in establishing and funding the Autism Tissue Program, a post-mortem brain tissue donation program designed to further autism research studies at the cellular and molecular level.  Other major programs included the 'High Risk Baby Sibling Autism Research Project', and the 'NAAR Genome Project'.  NAAR also published the ''NAARRATIVE'', a newsletter on autism biomedical research.

===Cure Autism Now===

In 2007, Autism Speaks completed its merger with Cure Autism Now (CAN).&lt;ref name=MergeCAN/&gt; CAN was founded in 1995 by Jonathan Shestack and Portia Iversen, the parents of a child with autism whose story is told in the book ''[[Strange Son]]''. It was an organization of parents, doctors and scientists devoted to research to prevent, treat and cure autism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.pbs.org/kcet/closertotruth/explore/show_03.html |title= How does the autistic brain work? |publisher=PBS |date=2003-04-06 |accessdate=2008-11-21| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20081025023214/http://www.pbs.org/kcet/closertotruth/explore/show_03.html| archivedate= 25 October 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; Iversen and Shestack were invited to join NAAR's board but declined, impatient with what they considered NAAR's excess of caution in staying with the scientific establishment.&lt;ref name=Coukell/&gt; In 1997 CAN established the [[Autism Genetic Resource Exchange]]; CAN was successful in establishing AGRE despite an initially negative reaction from scientists who were concerned whether CAN could carry out rigorous work, and despite what CAN considered to be scientists' reluctance to share their data.&lt;ref name=Coukell&gt;{{cite news |title= You can hurry science |author= Coukell A |work=proto |date=Winter 2006 |pages=26–31 |url=http://protomag.com/assets/you-can-hurry-science |publisher= [[Massachusetts General Hospital]] |accessdate=2009-01-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; During its existence, Cure Autism Now provided more than $39 million for research grants and other programs. Its flagship programs included the AGRE, Autism Treatment Network, Clinical Trials Network, and Innovative Technology for Autism. It also funded education and outreach efforts.&lt;ref name=MergeCAN&gt;{{cite press release |url=http://www.autismspeaks.org/press/autism_speaks_can_complete.php |title= Autism Speaks and Cure Autism Now complete merger |publisher=Autism Speaks |date=2007-02-05 |accessdate=2007-11-01| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20071027121719/http://www.autismspeaks.org/press/autism_speaks_can_complete.php| archivedate= 27 October 2007 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Autism Coalition for Research and Education===

Autism Speaks is also allied with Autism Coalition for Research and Education, an advocacy group.&lt;ref name=FamilyStrain/&gt;

== Controversies ==
=== View of autism as a disease ===

Autism Speaks's advocacy has been based on the mainstream medical view of autism as a disease: “This disease has taken our children away. It’s time to get them back.” This is a view that &quot;many but not all autism scientists would endorse.&quot;&lt;ref name=Living-Googles/&gt; In contrast, some autistic activists have asserted that people with autism are [[neurodiversity|&quot;different but not diseased&quot;]], challenging &quot;how we conceptualize such medical conditions.&quot;&lt;ref name=Living-Googles&gt;{{cite journal |journal=Nature |year=2008 |volume=454 |issue=7205 |pages=695–6 |title= Living Googles? |author= [[Simon Baron-Cohen|Baron-Cohen S]] |doi=10.1038/454695a |url=http://autismresearchcentre.com/docs/papers/2008_BC_Review_of_Living_Googles.pdf |format=PDF |accessdate=2009-06-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2008, an autistic [[blog]]ger upset with some charities' portrayal of autism created a critical parody of the Autism Speaks website, and later took the site down in response to legal demands from Autism Speaks to stop using the Autism Speaks name and logo without permission. Autism Speaks claimed the spoof could confuse people looking for information about autism. New parody sites were later launched by Gareth Nelson, founder of the autism rights group [[Aspies for Freedom]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author= Biever C |title= Voices of autism 'silenced' by charity |url=http://www.newscientist.com/channel/being-human/mg19726414.300-voices-of-autism-silenced-by-charity.html |work=New Scientist |date=2008-02-01 |accessdate=2008-02-05| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20080204132554/http://www.newscientist.com/channel/being-human/mg19726414.300-voices-of-autism-silenced-by-charity.html| archivedate= 4 February 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In September 2009, Autism Speaks screened the short video ''I Am Autism'' at its annual World Focus on Autism event; the video was created by [[Alfonso Cuarón]] and by Autism Speaks board member [[Billy Mann]]. With narration closely resembling the 1954 short ''Taming the Crippler'', which personified [[poliomyelitis]] as a kind of [[grim reaper]] figure, ''I Am Autism'' has been criticized by autism advocates and researchers for its negative portrayal of autism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=  Biever C |title='Poetic' autism film divides campaigners |date=2009-09-29 |work=New Scientist |url=http://www.newscientist.com/article/dn17878-poetic-autism-film-divides-campaigners.html |accessdate=2009-10-08 | archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20091003122813/http://www.newscientist.com/article/dn17878-poetic-autism-film-divides-campaigners.html| archivedate= 3 October 2009 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=Wallis C |title='I Am Autism': an advocacy video sparks protest |work=TIME |date=2009-11-06 |url=http://www.time.com/time/health/article/0,8599,1935959,00.html |accessdate=2009-12-07 | archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20091109022116/http://www.time.com/time/health/article/0,8599,1935959,00.html?| archivedate= 9 November 2009 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Position on vaccines ===
{{see also|Causes_of_autism#Vaccines}}
Autism Speaks assigns a high priority to research into the [[MMR vaccine controversy|now-discredited]] [[Fringe theory|fringe claim]] that [[immunization]] is associated with an increased [[Causes of autism|risk of autism]]. This priority has raised concerns among parents and scientific researchers, because &quot;...funding such research, in addition to being wasteful, unduly heightens parents' concerns about the safety of immunization.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Stokstad E |title=Resignations highlight disagreement on vaccines in autism group |journal=Science |volume=325 |issue=5937 |pages=135 |year=2009 |pmid=19589974 |doi=10.1126/science.325_135a }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Alison Singer, a senior executive of Autism Speaks, resigned in January 2009 rather than vote for committing money to new research studies into vaccination and autism. The U.S. Interagency Autism Coordinating Committee, of which Singer was a member, voted against committing the research funds; this was contrary to the Autism Speaks policy on vaccine safety research. Singer said:

: &quot;There isn't an unlimited pot of money, and every dollar spent looking where we know the answer isn't is one less dollar we have to spend where we might find new answers. The fact is that vaccines save lives; they don't cause autism.&quot;

She said that numerous scientific studies have disproved the link first suggested more than a decade ago and that Autism Speaks needs to &quot;move on.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= Charity chief quits over autism row |author= Luscombe R |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/lifeandstyle/2009/jan/25/autism-mmr-vaccine |date=2009-01-25 |accessdate=2009-02-01 |work=Observer | archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20090129042022/http://www.guardian.co.uk/lifeandstyle/2009/jan/25/autism-mmr-vaccine| archivedate= 29 January 2009 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later that year, along with NAAR's cofounder Karen London, Singer launched the [[Autism Science Foundation]] (ASF), a nonprofit organization supporting autism research premised on the principles that autism has a strong genetic component, that vaccines do not cause autism, and that evidence-based early diagnosis and intervention are critical.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |title= Autism Science Foundation launches operations: new advocacy group will focus on non-vaccine-related autism research |url=http://autismsciencefoundation.org/pressreleases.html |date=2009-04-18 |accessdate=2009-04-20 |publisher= Autism Science Foundation }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Eric London resigned from Autism Speaks's Scientific Affairs Committee in June 2009, saying that arguments that &quot;there might be rare cases of 'biologically-plausible' vaccine involvement ... are misleading and disingenuous&quot;, and that Autism Speaks was &quot;adversely impacting&quot; autism research. London is a founding member of the ASF's Scientific Advisory Board.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Kalb C |title=Another resignation at Autism Speaks |date=2009-07-01 |url=http://blog.newsweek.com/blogs/thehumancondition/archive/2009/07/01/claudia-kalb-another-resignation-at-autism-speaks.aspx |accessdate=2009-07-03 |work=The Human Condition |publisher=Newsweek }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{portal|Pervasive Developmental Disorders}}
*[[World Autism Day]]
*[[Light It Up Blue]]

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==External links==
* {{Official website|http://www.autismspeaks.org/}}
* {{Official website|http://www.lightitupblue.org/}}
* {{cite web |url=http://agre.org/ |title= Autism Genetic Resource Exchange |accessdate=2008-05-29| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20080511221317/http://www.agre.org/| archivedate= 11 May 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}
* {{cite web |url=http://brainbank.org/ |title= Autism Tissue Program |accessdate=2008-05-29| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20080509132627/http://www.brainbank.org/| archivedate= 9 May 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}

{{Pervasive developmental disorders}}

{{Autism resources}}
{{Autism films}}
{{Pervasive developmental disorders}}

[[Category:Organizations established in 2005]]
[[Category:Medical activism]]
[[Category:Vaccination-related organizations]]
[[Category:Autism-related organizations]]
[[Category:Health and disability rights organizations in the United States]]

[[de:Autism Speaks]]</text>
      <sha1>4v8czmwnl6pc3kwkp7glauh02xo1ldx</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
