<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Ballot</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>193553</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521906733</id>
      <parentid>521903247</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-07T23:31:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cowards1</username>
        <id>17846356</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>There was a unneeded and ignorant sentence in the beginning of the introduction.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11676">{{other uses}}
{{Weasel|date=February 2009}}
{{Refimprove|date=October 2008}}
{{Voting}}

[[File:Papizadeh11.JPG|thumb|Leaves the second round of parliamentary elections in Iran election]]

A '''ballot''' is a device used to cast votes in an election, and may be a piece of paper or a small ball used in secret voting.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/ballot|title=Ballot|publisher=Merriam-Webster |accessdate=2012-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was originally a small ball—see [[blackball (blacklist)|blackball]]) used to record decisions made by [[vote]]rs. 

Each voter uses one ballot, and ballots are not shared. In the simplest elections, a ballot may be a simple scrap of paper on which each voter writes in the name of a [[candidate]], but [[government]]al elections use pre-printed to protect the [[secret ballot|secrecy of the votes]]. The voter casts his/her ballot in a [[Ballot box|box]] at a [[polling station]]. 

In British English, this is usually called a &quot;'''ballot paper'''&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.learnersdictionary.com/search/ballot[1]|title=Ballot|publisher=Merriam-Webster Learner’s Dictionary |accessdate=2012-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; The word &quot;ballot&quot; is used for an election process within an organisation (such as a trade union &quot;holding a ballot&quot; of its members).

==Etymology==
The word ballot comes from the Italian ''ballotta'', from Italian dialect.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/ballot|title=Ballot|publisher=Merriam-Webster|accessdate=2012-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1540s, the word ballot was used to describe a “small ball was used in voting” or a “secret vote taken by ballots”. The earliest use of the word is referenced to Venice, Italy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url= http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?allowed_in_frame=0&amp;search=ballot&amp;searchmode=none|title=Ballot|publisher=Online tymology Dictionary|accessdate=2012-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
In [[ancient Greece]], citizens used [[Ostracon|pieces of broken pottery]] to scratch in the name of the candidate in the procedures of [[ostracism]]. This was done because while papyrus was expensive and had to be imported from [[Egypt]], broken pottery was abundant and virtually free.{{Citation needed|date=October 2008}}

The first use of paper ballots to conduct an election appears to have been in [[Ancient Rome|Rome]] in 139 BC. 

In Ancient [[India]], around 920 AD, in [[Tamil Nadu]], Palm leaves were used for village assembly elections. The palm leaves with candidate names, will be put inside a mud pot, for counting. This was called ''Kudavolai'' system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.tn.gov.in/policynotes/pdf/rural_development.pdf |title=Panchayat Raj, Policy notes 2011-2012 |author= |date= |work= |publisher=Rural development &amp; panchayat raj department, TN Government, India |accessdate=3 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Heritage in a park|url=http://www.hindu.com/fr/2010/04/02/stories/2010040251170100.htm|accessdate=|newspaper=The Hindu|date=2 April 2010|location=Chennai, India}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Handbook on Kongu archaeological treasures|url=http://www.hindu.com/lf/2005/06/27/stories/2005062701170200.htm|accessdate=|newspaper=The Hindu|date=27 June 2005|location=Coimbatore, India}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first use of paper ballots in North America was in 1629 within the [[Massachusetts Bay Colony]] to select a pastor for the Salem Church.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cs.uiowa.edu/~jones/ Jones, Douglas W.]. [http://www.cs.uiowa.edu/~jones/voting/pictures/ A Brief Illustrated History of Voting]. ''[http://www.uiowa.edu/ University of Iowa] [http://www.cs.uiowa.edu/ Department of Computer Science]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[United States]] initially paper ballots were pieces of paper marked and supplied by voters. Later on, political parties and candidates provided preprinted ballots for voters to cast.{{Citation needed|date=October 2008}}

==Types of voting systems==
[[File:Butterfly Voters View.jpg||thumb|left|150px|Perspective view of the infamous 2000 [[Florida]] &quot;butterfly ballot&quot;.]]
[[File:Butterfly large.jpg|thumb|150px|left|Top view of the same 2000 Florida &quot;butterfly ballot&quot;.]]

Depending on the type of [[voting system]] used in the election, different ballots may be used. [[Ranked ballot]]s allow voters to rank candidates in order of preference, while ballots for [[first-past-the-post]] systems only allow voters to select one candidate for each position. In [[party-list proportional representation|party-list]] systems, lists may be [[open list|open]] or [[closed list|closed]].

The United States has a unique politics of long and short ballot. Before the [[American Civil War|Civil War]], many{{Who|date=October 2008}} believed [[democracy]] was enhanced by increasing the number of elective offices to include such comparatively minor posts as the state-level [[secretary of state]], [[county surveyor]], [[register of deeds]], [[county coroner]], and [[city clerk]]. A larger number of elected offices required longer ballots, and at times the long ballot undoubtedly resulted in confusion and blind voting, though the seriousness of either problem can be disputed. [[Progressivism in the United States|Progressivists]] attacked the long ballot during the [[Progressive Era]] (circa 1893–1917). In the United States today, the term ballot reform sometimes refers to efforts to reduce the number of elected offices.{{Citation needed|date=October 2008}}

==Design==
Ballot design can aid or inhibit clarity in an election. Poor designs lead to confusion and potentially chaos if large numbers of voters spoil or mismark a ballot. The '''butterfly ballot''' used in the [[United States presidential election in Florida, 2000|Florida]] [[U.S. presidential election, 2000]] (a ballot paper that has names down both sides, with a single column of punch holes in the center, which has been likened to a [[maze]]){{by whom|date=January 2010}} led to widespread allegations of mismarked ballots.&lt;ref&gt;Dershowitz, 'Supreme Injustice: how the High Court hijacked Election 2000, p. 22-28&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Bulleten Gosduma 2011.jpg|thumb|right|150|[[Russia|Russian]] ballot to the [[Russian legislative election, 2011|2011 State Duma elections]] with list of [[Political parties in Russia|political parties]]]]

Some political scientists{{Who|date=October 2008}} prefer more explicit statement of the voter's actual tolerances and preferences, and believe that failure to reflect these in ballot design and voting system alternatives causes many problems and leads for calls for [[electoral reform]]. For instance, a non-binding [[referendum]] or [[opinion poll|poll]], carried out on a ballot, carries much more weight than one carried out with only a public sampling in a less politically committed event than an election. For example, one might count the number of ballots whereon the voter had crossed out the name of the [[political party]] that nominated the candidate, even if (maybe only if) that voter had voted for him or her. This would indicate support for candidates but would be able to send signals to them that the &quot;party line&quot; was not why that voter voted for them, but rather, she or he expected them to act independently.

Such marking and counting could be carried out on an ordinary ballot with no provision for it, however, there would be risk of counting it as &quot;spoiled&quot; if the marks were unclear, and if ballot design had not allowed for it initially.

==Methods==
{{Unreferenced section|date=October 2008}}

{{further2|[[Vote counting system]]}}
* In a jurisdiction using a paper system, voters choose by marking a ballot. In most jurisdictions the ballots are pre-printed with names of candidates and the text of the referenda. [[The Philippines]] (until 2007) and [[Japan]] are an exception. There, voters must write the names of their candidates on the ballot. Election officials [[Vote counting system#Manual counting|manually count]] the ballots after the polls close and may be recounted in the event of a dispute.
* In a jurisdiction using an [[optical scan voting system]], voters choose by filling an oval or by completing an arrow on the printed ballot next to their chosen candidate or referendum position. Optical scan technology has also been used by many standardized tests. Tabulating machines count the ballots either after the polls close or as the voters feed the ballots into the machine, in which case the results are not known until after the polls close. Officials often will manually count any ballots that cannot be read or with a [[write-in]] candidate and may recount the ballots in the event of a dispute.
* In a jurisdiction using a [[Voting machine#Punched Card|punched card system]], voters choose by removing or &quot;punching out&quot; a perforated [[Chad (paper)|chad]] from the ballot next each choice. The ballot may be pre-printed with candidates and referenda, or may be a generic ballot placed under a printed list of candidates and referenda. Tabulating machines count ballots after the polls close. Officials may manually count the ballots in the event of a dispute. Punched card voting systems are being replaced by other voting systems because of a high rate of inaccuracy related to the incomplete removal of the perforated chad and the inaccessibility to voters with disabilities.
* In a jurisdiction using a mechanical voting system, often called a &quot;voting machine&quot;, voters choose by pulling a lever next to their choice. There is a printed list of candidates, parties and referenda next to the levers indicating which lever is assigned to which choice. When the voter pulls a lever, it turns a connected gear in the machine, which turns a counter wheel. Each counter wheel shows a number, which is the number of votes cast using that lever. After the polls close, election officials check the wheels' positions and record the totals. No physical ballot is used in this system, except when the voter chooses to write-in a candidate. Other systems are replacing mechanical voting systems because they are inaccessible to disabled voters, do not have a physical ballot and are getting old.
* In a jurisdiction using an electronic [[DRE voting machine|direct record voting system]] (DRE), voters choose by pushing a button next to a printed list of candidates and referenda, or by touching the candidate or referenda box on a [[touchscreen]] interface. As the voter makes a selection, the DRE creates an electronic ballot stored by in the memory components of the system. After the polls close, the system counts the votes and reports the totals to the election officials. Many DREs include a communication device to transmit vote totals to a central tabulator. The touchscreen systems remind people of an [[automated teller machine|automated teller machine (ATM)]] and often are described as such.

==See also==
{{Wiktionary|ballot}}
{{Wikisource1911Enc}}
*[[Ballot box]]
*[[Chad (paper)]]
*[[Democracy]]
*[[Direct democracy]]
*[[E-democracy]]
*[[Election fraud]]
*[[List of democracy and elections-related topics]]
*[[Ostracism]]
*[[Secret ballot]]
*[[Vote counting systems]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Elections terminology]]

[[ar:ورقة اقتراع]]
[[ca:Papereta electoral]]
[[cy:Balod]]
[[da:Stemmeseddel]]
[[de:Stimmzettel]]
[[es:Boleta electoral]]
[[fa:برگه انتخاباتی]]
[[fr:Bulletin de vote]]
[[id:Surat suara]]
[[it:Scheda elettorale]]
[[he:פתק הצבעה]]
[[kk:Бюллетень]]
[[nl:Stembiljet]]
[[no:Stemmeseddel]]
[[pt:Cédula eleitoral]]
[[ru:Избирательный бюллетень]]
[[sv:Valsedel]]
[[chr:ᎧᏁᏨᎢ]]
[[uk:Виборчий бюлетень]]
[[zh-yue:選票]]
[[zh:選票]]</text>
      <sha1>c295ozycusw2y0uxgtlspaaj8km8vwz</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
