<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Barbara Kay controversy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7266537</id>
    <revision>
      <id>480890161</id>
      <parentid>473647263</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-03-08T20:42:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>LWG</username>
        <id>12607721</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>rm dead pov tag</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15237">{{Multiple issues
 | weasel=March 2009
 | notability=March 2010
}}
[[Image:2006-08-06-Montreal Demo.jpg|thumb|right|A view looking down on the August 6, 2006 demonstration in Montreal.]]
[[Barbara Kay]] is a columnist for the Canadian national [[broadsheet]] the ''[[National Post]]'', wherein she expressed, in a series of three articles, beginning with a column entitled &quot;The Rise of Quebecistan,&quot; on August 9, 2006,
her concern at the involvement of [[Quebec]] politicians in a demonstration in support of [[Lebanon]] during the [[2006 Israel-Lebanon conflict]] that took place on August 6, 2006, in the city of [[Montreal]], [[Quebec]], [[Canada]]. Kay wrote: &quot;'The Rise of Quebecistan,' has become a focus for great controversy in Quebec. In the past week, I have been interviewed by numerous radio stations, both French and English, and declared an enemy of the people, in so many words, in no less than three newspapers, including in a Post column... .&quot;&lt;ref name=kay1&gt;[http://www.barbarakay.ca/archive/20060817QuebecersindenialCounterpoint.html Quebecers in denial: Counterpoint] by Barbara Kay, ''National Post'', August 17, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

Kay claimed that both she, and what she described as her &quot;criticism&quot; of the demonstration, were attacked by elements of the French Quebec media and politicians—some of whom support the separation of the province of Quebec from Canada—was seemingly because her criticisms were expressed in the English language; and not French.&lt;ref name=kay2&gt;[http://www.barbarakay.ca/archive/20061122saywhatyouwant.html Say what you want (as long as it's in French)] by Barbara Kay, ''National Post'', November 22, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

== &quot;Virulently anti-Israel rally&quot; ==

On August 6, 2006, [[Parti Québécois]] (PQ) leader [[André Boisclair]], [[Bloc Québécois]] (BQ) leader [[Gilles Duceppe]], [[Québec solidaire]] (QS) spokesperson [[Amir Khadir]] and [[Liberal Party of Canada]] Member of Parliament (MP) [[Denis Coderre]] participated in a rally in opposition to Israel's actions in the [[2006 Israel-Lebanon conflict]].  The event was described by Kay as: &quot;...a virulently anti-Israel rally, and scattered amongst the crowd were a number of [[Flag of Hezbollah|Hezbollah flags]] and placards.&quot;  Kay wrote of the four politicians that participated in the rally:

&lt;blockquote&gt;All four, along with prominent Quebec union leaders, signed a manifesto that did not condemn [[Hezbollah]]'s aggression, then endorsed and willingly undertook a dominant role in a march at which [[Flag of Hezbollah|Hezbollah flags]] were in evidence, along with placards, reading &quot;Juifs assassins,&quot; [translation: [[Jewish]] assassins], (not &quot;Israelis&quot; -- Jews), &quot;Nous sommes tous [[Hezbollah]],&quot; [translation: We are all [[Hezbollah]]], &quot;Longue vie a [[Nasrallah]],&quot; [translation: Long life to [[Nasrallah]]], &quot;Vive le Hezbollah,&quot; [translation: Long live [[Hezbollah]]].
Gleeful separatist cineaste [[Pierre Falardeau]] was photographed brandishing a [[fleur-de-lys]] in one hand, a [[Flag of Hezbollah|Hezbollah flag]] in the other. Graffiti on a building read: &quot;God f--- the Jews.&quot; A Jewish [[prayer shawl]] was torn to pieces.&lt;ref name=kay1/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; 

Kay wrote that these Quebec politicians participated in the rally despite [[Hezbollah]] being an organization officially classified as a terrorist group by the Canadian government.  She also asserted that the rally's organizing committee &quot;deliberately excluded a Jewish presence&quot;, which was &quot;in itself an [[anti-Semitic]] act and a warning to any politician, whose business it is to remain neutral in affairs of this kind, to stay away.&quot; The rally also didn't call for &quot;peace&quot; but a cease fire or [[hudna]]. Kay asked: &quot;If these signs had read: 'We are all [[KKK]],' 'Long life to [[Osama Bin Laden]],' 'We are all [[Nazis]],' 'Women are pigs,' would these same leaders have turned the blind eye they did at the time? Hezbollah's mission is to eradicate Jews—not just Israelis—from the earth.&quot; And Kay felt that the involvement of politicians in the rally was troubling: &quot;It is true that similar marches have taken place in other cities. The difference is that politicians in Toronto and elsewhere in Canada do not march at the head of these hatefests.&quot;&lt;ref name=kay1/&gt;

Kay commented on the motivations of the politicians, noting: 

&lt;blockquote&gt;Their cultural and historical sympathy for Arab countries from the [[francophonie]] -- Morocco, Algeria, Lebanon -- joined with reflexive [[anti-Americanism]] and a fat streak of [[anti-Semitism]] that has marbled the intellectual discourse of Quebec throughout its history, has made Quebec the most anti-Israel of the provinces, and therefore the most vulnerable to tolerance for Islamist terrorist sympathizers.&lt;ref name=kay1/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; 

Kay speculated that these politicians may also have been cynically seeking votes from [[Canadians of convenience]] asserting:

&lt;blockquote&gt;These politicians are playing a dangerous game. They have no political support from Jews (who are all federalists), so have nothing to lose in courting anti-Israel Arab groups. There are at least 50,000 Lebanese-Canadians in the Montreal area. We can expect those numbers to swell as Hezbollah-supporting residents of southern Lebanon cash in on their Canadian citizenship and flee to the safety of Quebec. Under the circumstances, it may be politically convenient for some left-wing Quebec politicians to stoke fires of enthusiasm for Hezbollah -- an organization officially classified as a terrorist group by the Canadian government. Yet it would be disastrous for the future of the province.&lt;ref name=kay1/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

She concluded her second editorial on the subject as follows:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;The complicity of politicians, not with terrorism itself, but with those who support terrorism, indicates a penchant for appeasement of hateful attitudes... Quebec politicians and union leaders have, by their silence and weakness and acts of overt complicity, legitimated rather than defused anti-Jewish sentiment in Quebec. For this reason, I stand behind my previous statement that Quebec in the hands of these people might very well become a Quebecistan.&quot;&lt;ref name=kay1/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

== Criticism of Kay ==
The French Quebec politicians defended their participation in the impugned rally. [[Gilles Duceppe]] stated that he was there in the interest of Israel and Lebanese civilian populations alike and [[André Boisclair]] said the Hezbollah flag had no place in Quebec. A press release from Duceppe's [[Bloc Québécois]] pointed out the presence of Jews at the rally and noted that Duceppe's presence was conditional on no pro-Hezbollah demonstrators and no anti-Israel slogans.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.blocquebecois.org/archivage/com_duceppe_marcheisraelliban_060816.pdf#search=%22Israel%20site%3Awww.blocquebecois.org%22 &quot;J’estime avoir agi dans l'intérêt des populations civiles victimes du conflit, qu'elles soient israëliennes ou libanaises&quot;] by the Bloc Québécois, official press release, August 16, 2006, retrieved September 24, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;  Duceppe also indicated that the Bloc and others tried to get Hezbollah supporters to leave the event.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.canada.com/edmontonjournal/news/story.html?id=54bc6573-fbd5-494c-95aa-feb2f3a01b2d PM pledges strong pro-Israel foreign policy] by Andrew Mayeda and Meagan Fitzpatrick, ''Edmonton Sun'', September 11, 2008, page A4.&lt;/ref&gt;

Montreal journalist Mark Abley also criticized Kay's piece, noting that both Duceppe and Coderre called for an immediate ceasefire and the disarming of Hezbollah in their speeches. He also indicated that Hezbollah banners were described by those in attendance as &quot;few and far between&quot;, and described Kay's categorization of the rally as &quot;Hezbollah-dominated&quot; as &quot;intellectually untrue&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Mark Abley, &quot;Sympathy for Lebanon widespread; But that doesn't make Quebecers anti-Semitic&quot;, ''Toronto Star'', 19 August 2006, F05.&lt;/ref&gt;

The French [[Saint-Jean-Baptiste Society]] lodged a complaint regarding Kay's piece to the Quebec Press Council. Kay was criticized by ''[[La Presse (Canadian newspaper)|La Presse]]'' French Canadian editorialist and &quot;[[Quebec federalist ideology|federalist]]&quot; [[André Pratte]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The myth of ’Quebecistan’&quot; by André Pratte, ''The National Post'', August 16, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; and'' [[The Gazette (Montreal)|The Gazette]]'' &quot;[[Quebec sovereignty movement|sovereigntist]]&quot;-columnist and French Canadian [[Josée Legault]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.canada.com/montrealgazette/news/editorial/story.html?id=bd84b0b3-9211-432e-a31b-cadc09219e44&amp;p=2 Francophones unjustly labelled intolerant] by Josée Legault, ''The Montreal Gazette'', August 18, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; as well as ''La Presse'' French Canadian journalist Vincent Marissal.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;L’incontinence&quot; by Vincent Marissal, ''La Presse'', August 18, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; The Montreal French-language daily ''La Presse'', on August 7, 2006, (p. A4), contended: “Aucun drapeau du mouvement chiite controversé n’était visible durant la marche.&quot; (Translation:
&quot;No flag of the controversial Shia movement was visible during the march&quot;).
French Canadian activist [[Gilles Rhéaume]] announced his intention to lodge a complaint to the police for hate speech. [[William Tetley]], a [[McGill University]] professor and past [[Robert Bourassa]] provincial cabinet minister, wrote a letter to ''The National Post'' where he stated that, as an [[English-speaking Quebecker|anglophone]], he viewed Quebec society as holding a long-standing tolerance toward Jews by asserting that, at a time when his own English-language McGill University imposed [[Jewish quota|quotas on Jews]], the French-language [[Université de Montréal]] welcomed Jews.

The French-Canadian premier of the province of Quebec [[Jean Charest]] called the expression &quot;Quebecistan&quot; ''&quot;une grossièreté&quot;'' (something rude, crude, a &quot;vulgarity&quot;). However, he also stated that &quot;No one in my government supports Hezbollah,&quot; and that he would not participate in a demonstration where there was a Hezbollah flag.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.canada.com/montrealgazette/news/story.html?id=cf78708a-d0f9-4daf-96be-40e27bf9ff24&amp;k=57547 Charest rejects &quot;Quebecistan&quot; label] by Kevin Dougherty, The Montreal Gazette, August 16, 2006. (retrieved on October 13, 2008)&lt;/ref&gt;

== Kay's supporters ==
Reacting to the controversy, ''[[National Post]]'' Comment Pages Editor, and Barbara's son, Jonathan Kay declared that his newspaper had no reason to offer apologies. In a statement to ''La Presse'', he asserted that &quot;[t]here is no doubt that Quebec has an antisemitic past.&quot; Barbara Kay was also defended by [[Howard Galganov]] and ''[[Ottawa Citizen]]'' French Canadian journalist Brigitte Pellerin.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.canada.com/ottawacitizen/news/story.html?id=7acf5e44-59ad-4869-af82-c46e1bbff14e The 'Quebecistan' question] by Brigitte Pellerin, ''The Ottawa Citizen'', August 24, 2006,&lt;/ref&gt;  

[[Beryl Wajsman]], the president of the Institute for Public Affairs of Montreal, wrote an article in the [[Canadian Free Press]] (CFP) in support of Kay.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.canadafreepress.com/2006/wajsman082106.htm Hey Quebec! Ca Suffit, The Quebec Media and Barbara Kay] by Beryl Wajsman, August 21, 2006. (retrieved on October 13, 2008)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Quebec Press Council decision==
In 2007, the Quebec Press Council released a decision condemning Kay for &quot;undue provocation&quot; and &quot;generalizations suitable to perpetuate prejudices&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.conseildepresse.qc.ca/decisions/D2006-08-009.htm &quot;Décision 2006-08-09&quot;] , ''Conseil de Presse du Québec'', March 4, 2007, retrieved April 15, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; 

&quot;The Council noted throughout the chronicle of Mrs. Kay a lack of rigour in the presentation of the context surrounding the walk for peace of August 2006, which tends to encourage the reader to lend intentions to public personalities without providing concrete facts to support these intentions. On several occasions in the chronicle, the journalist deformed facts, to present only a part of the situation, aiming only at supporting her point of view that the leaders of independent Quebec would withdraw the Hezbollah of the list of the terrorist movements and that this new country would become a harbour for them. The Council points out that, if the chroniclers can denounce with strength the ideas and the actions which they reject and carry judgements with complete freedom, nothing however authorizes them to deteriorate facts to justify interpretation that they draw. Deontology of the Council Press clearly established that the media and the professionals of information must avoid cultivating or to maintain the prejudices. They must imperatively avoid using, at the place of the people or the groups, the representations or the terms which tend to raise the contempt, to run up against the dignity of a person or a category of people because of a discriminatory reason. The Council estimated that the remarks of the journalist were equivalent to an undue provocation, in addition to establishing generalizations suitable to perpetuate the prejudices rather than to dissipate them.&quot;

===Kay's Response===
Kay later responded that while the QPC claimed she was guilty of ''&quot;undue provocation,&quot;'' it never defined the term &quot;undue.&quot; She also stated that the while QPC claimed she was guilty of ''&quot;altering the facts&quot;'' upon which she based her opinions, it never cited any specific facts that she had allegedly altered. Kay explained that the National Post viewed the QPC's &quot;verdict&quot; as a &quot;mere irritation&quot; since the QPC had no power to take any action against her beyond issuing statements. However, Kay stated that she took the QPC's statement very seriously because:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I quickly realized that my opinion piece would never have been published in a Quebec-based newspaper. Representatives from all the mainstream media sit on the QPC, and they would all know instinctively what would pass muster and what wouldn't. So in fact, even though the council has no legal power, it has strong moral power amongst its constituents. So they self-censure before they publish.&lt;/blockquote&gt; 

Kay added that this episode was:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
A reminder to other journalists to stay away from the sensitive issues I had the freedom to raise because I wrote for a medium beyond the reach of the QPC's ability to intimidate.&lt;ref&gt;[http://network.nationalpost.com/np/blogs/fullcomment/archive/2009/02/12/barbara-kay-the-perils-of-a-national-press-council-been-there-done-that.aspx  Barbara Kay, The perils of a national press council: Been there, done that] by Barbara Kay, National Post, February 12, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

== External links ==
*[http://www.nationalpost.com/news/story.html?id=10524e16-36f2-4975-910d-9407471f2261&amp;k=91928 The rise of Quebecistan], Barbara Kay, [[National Post]]
*[http://www.vigile.net/The-myth-of-Quebecistan The myth of Quebecistan], André Pratte, [[National Post]]

== Footnotes ==
{{Reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Kay, Barbara Controversy}}
[[Category:Anti-Arabism]]
[[Category:Anti-Quebec sentiment]]
[[Category:Antisemitism]]
[[Category:2006 in Canada]]
[[Category:Political controversies in Canada]]
[[Category:Canadian journalism]]
[[Category:Political history of Canada]]
[[Category:National Post]]</text>
      <sha1>dltqqxazr79lok6p9wenhskoiz7ormu</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
