<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Bicameralism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>204299</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522230831</id>
      <parentid>521238451</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T20:33:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Haeinous</username>
        <id>9331666</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Theory of Bicameral Congress */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="29694">{{about|the government structure|the psychological hypothesis|Bicameralism (psychology)}}
In [[government]], '''bicameralism''' (Latin ''bi'', two + ''camera'', chamber) is the practice of having two legislative or parliamentary chambers [[compromise]] [[Bill (proposed law)|bill]]s.{{clarify|date=July 2012}}

Bicameralism is an essential and defining feature of the [[classical antiquity|classical]] notion of [[mixed government]]. Bicameral legislatures tend to require a [[concurrent majority]] to pass legislation.

==Theory of Bicameral Congress==
{{Globalize/US|section|date=October 2012}}
Although the ideas on which bicameralism are based can be traced back to the theories developed in Ancient [[Sumer]] and later [[ancient Greece]], [[History of India|ancient India]], and [[Ancient Rome|Rome]], recognizable bicameral institutions first arose in [[Medieval Europe]] where they were associated with separate representation of different [[estates of the realm]]. For example, one house would represent the aristocracy, and the other would represent the commoners.&lt;ref name=&quot;HG1&quot;&gt;[http://www.rules.house.gov/archives/jcoc2br.htm Rules.House.gov]&lt;/ref&gt; 

The [[Founding Fathers of the United States]] also favored a bicameral legislature. The idea was to have the Senate be wealthier, and (apparently) wiser. The Senate was created to be a stabilizing force, elected not by mass electors, but selected by the State legislators. Senators would be more knowledgeable and more deliberate—a sort of republican nobility—and a counter to what [[James Madison|Madison]] saw as the &quot;fickleness and passion&quot; that could absorb the House.&lt;ref name=&quot;HG1&quot;/&gt;

He noted further that the &quot;use of the Senate is to consist in its proceeding with more coolness, with more system and with more wisdom, than the popular branch&quot;. Madison's argument led the Framers to grant the Senate prerogatives in foreign policy, an area where steadiness, discretion, and caution were deemed especially important&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;HG1&quot;/&gt; The Senate was chosen by state legislators, and senators had to possess a significant amount of property in order to be deemed worthy and sensible enough for the position. In fact, it was not until the year 1913 that the [[Seventeenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|17th Amendment]] was passed, which &quot;mandated that Senators would be elected by popular vote rather than chosen by the State legislatures&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;HG1&quot;/&gt;

As part of the [[Great Compromise]], they invented a new rationale for bicameralism in which the upper house would have states represented equally, and the lower house would have them represented by population.

[[Image:United States Capitol - west front.jpg|thumb|280px|right|The bicameral [[legislature]] of the [[United States]] is housed in the [[United States Capitol|Capitol]], a building with two wings. The north wing ''(left)'' houses the [[United States Senate|Senate]], while the south wing ''(right)'' houses the [[United States House of Representatives|House of Representatives]].]]

In subsequent constitution making, federal states have often adopted bicameralism, and the solution remains popular when regional differences or sensitivities require more explicit representation, with the second chamber representing the constituent states. Nevertheless, the older justification for second chambers—providing opportunities for second thoughts about legislation—has survived.{{Citation needed|date=January 2009}}

Growing awareness of the complexity of the notion of representation and the multifunctional nature of modern legislatures may be affording incipient new rationales for second chambers, though these do generally remain contested institutions in ways that first chambers are not. An example of political controversy regarding a second chamber has been the debate over the powers of the [[Canadian Senate]] or the election of the [[Senate of France]].&lt;ref&gt;{{fr icon}} [http://www.liberation.fr/politiques/010132156-senat-le-triomphe-de-l-anomalie Liberation.fr], Sénat, le triomphe de l'anomalie&lt;/ref&gt;

The relationship between the two chambers varies; in some cases, they have equal power, while in others, one chamber is clearly superior in its powers. The first tends to be the case in federal systems and those with presidential governments. The latter tends to be the case in unitary states with [[parliamentary system]]s.

There are two streams of thought: Critics believe bicameralism makes meaningful political reforms more difficult to achieve and increases the risk of gridlock—particularly in cases where both chambers have similar powers—while proponents argue the merits of the &quot;[[checks and balances]]&quot; provided by the bicameral model, which they believe help prevent the passage into law of ill-considered legislation.

==Types==

===Federal===
Some countries, such as [[Argentina]], [[Australia]], [[Austria]], [[Belgium]], [[Brazil]], [[Canada]], [[Germany]], [[India]], [[Malaysia]], [[Mexico]], [[Pakistan]], [[Russia]], [[Switzerland]], and the [[United States]], link their bicameral systems to their [[federation|federal]] political structure.

In the United States, Australia, and Mexico, for example, each state is given the same number of seats in the legislature's upper house. This takes account of population differences between states — it is designed to ensure that smaller states are not overshadowed by larger states, which have more representation in the lower house. In Canada, the country as a whole is divided into a number of [[Canadian Senate Divisions|Senate Divisions]], each with a different number of Senators, based on a number of factors. These Divisions are [[Quebec]], [[Ontario]], [[Western Canada|Western Provinces]], and [[the Maritimes]], each with 24 Senators, [[Yukon]], [[Northwest Territories]], [[Nunavut]], each with 1 Senator, and [[Newfoundland and Labrador]] has 6 Senators, making for a total of 105 Senators. 

Senators in Canada are not elected by the people but are appointed by the [[Governor General of Canada|Governor General]] on the [[Advice (constitutional)|advice]] of the [[Prime Minister of Canada|Prime Minister]]. The Senate does not originate most legislation (although a small fraction of government bills are introduced in the Senate and Senators may introduce [[private members' bills]] in the same way as MPs) but acts as a chamber of revision almost always passing legislation approved by the House of Commons, made up of Members of Parliament (MPs) who are elected. The Senate must pass legislation before it becomes law and can therefore act as a wise facilitator or engage in filibuster. The Senate does not have to endure the accountability and scrutiny of parliamentary elections. Therefore, the bicameral structure of Canadian parliament is more de ''jure'' than ''de facto''.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

In the German, Indian, and Pakistani systems, the upper houses (the [[Bundesrat (Germany)|Bundesrat]], the [[Rajya Sabha]], and the [[Senate of Pakistan|Pakistani Senate]] respectively) are even more closely linked with the federal system, being appointed or elected directly by the governments or legislatures of each [[States of Germany|German Bundesland]], [[States and territories of India|Indian State]], or [[Provinces of Pakistan|Pakistani Province]]. (This was also the case in the United States before the [[Seventeenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|17th Amendment]].) The Indian Upper House does not have the states represented equally, but on the basis of their population. In the German Bundesrat, the various Länder have between three and seven votes; thus, while the less populated states have a lower weight, they still have a stronger voting power than would be the case in a system based ''purely'' on population, as the most populous Land currently has about 27 times the population of the least populous.

There are also instances of bicameralism in countries that are not federations, but which have upper houses with representation on a territorial basis. For example in [[South Africa]], the [[National Council of Provinces]] (and before 1997, the [[Senate of South Africa|Senate]]) has its members chosen by each [[Provinces of South Africa|Province]]'s legislature. &quot;

In Spain the [[Spanish Senate]] functions as a ''de facto'' territorial-based upper house, and there has been some pressure from the [[Autonomous Communities]] to reform it into a strictly territorial chamber.

The [[European Union]] maintains a bicameral legislative system which consists of the [[European Parliament]], which is elected in general elections on the basis of universal suffrage, and the [[Council of the European Union]] which consists of members of the governments of the Member States which are competent for the relevant field of legislation. Although the European Union is not considered a state, it enjoys the power to legislate in many areas of politics; in some areas, those powers are even exclusively reserved to it.

===Aristocratic===
In a few countries, bicameralism involves the juxtaposition of democratic and aristocratic elements.

The best known example is the [[United Kingdom|British]] [[House of Lords]], which includes a number of [[hereditary peer]]s. The House of Lords represents a vestige of the aristocratic system which once predominated in British politics, while the other house, the [[British House of Commons|House of Commons]], is entirely elected. Over the years, there have been proposals to reform the House of Lords, some of which have been at least partly successful — the [[House of Lords Act 1999]] limited the number of hereditary peers (as opposed to [[life peer]]s, appointed by [[Elizabeth II|Her Majesty]] on the advice of the [[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom|Prime Minister]] ) to 92, down from around 700. Of these 92, 1 is the [[Earl Marshal]], a hereditary office always held by the [[Duke of Norfolk]], 1 is the [[Lord Great Chamberlain]], a hereditary office held in gross, currently by the [[Marquess of Cholmondeley]], and the other 90 are [[Representative peer|elected by other Hereditary Peers]]. The ability of the House of Lords to block legislation is curtailed by the [[Parliament Acts 1911 and 1949]]. Peers can introduce bills except Money Bills, and all legislation must be passed by both [[Lords Spiritual and Temporal and Commons|Houses of Parliament]]. If it is not passed within two sessions, the [[House of Commons]] can override the Lords delay by invoking the Parliament Act. Certain pieces of legislation however must be approved by both Houses and are not able to be forced through by the Commons under the Parliament Act. This includes any bill which would extend the time length of a Parliament, private bills, bills which are sent to the House of Lords less than one month before the end of a session, and bills which originate in the House of Lords. 

Further reform of the Lords has been proposed, however not supported by many. Members of the House of Lords all have an aristocratic title, or are from the [[Lord Spiritual|Clergy]]. 26 Archbishops and Bishops of the [[Church of England]] sit as [[Lord Spiritual|Lords Spiritual]], being the [[Archbishop of Canterbury]], [[Archbishop of York]], the [[Bishop of London]], the [[Bishop of Durham]], the [[Bishop of Winchester]] and the next 21 longest-serving Bishops. It is usual that retiring Archbishops, and certain other Bishops, are appointed to the [[Crossbencher|Crossbenches]] and given a life peerage. Until 2009, 12 [[Lord of Appeal in Ordinary|Lords of Appeal in Ordinary]] sat in the House as the highest court in the land. At present, 786 people sit in the House of Lords, with 92 Hereditary, 26 being Bishops or Archbishops (the Lords Spiritual) and the rest being Life Peers. Membership is not fixed and only decreases on the death of a life peer.

Another example of aristocratic bicameralism was the [[Japan]]ese [[House of Peers (Japan)|House of Peers]], abolished after [[World War II]] and replaced with the present [[House of Councillors]].

===Unitary states===
Many bicameral countries like the [[Netherlands]], the [[Philippines]], the [[Czech Republic]], the [[Republic of Ireland]] and [[Romania]] are examples of bicameral systems existing in [[unitary state]]s. In countries such as these, the upper house generally focuses on scrutinizing and possibly vetoing the decisions of the lower house.

On the other hand, in [[Italy]] the [[Italian Parliament|Parliament]] consists of two chambers that have same role and power: the [[Italian Senate|Senate]] (Senate of the Republic, commonly considered the ''upper house'') and the [[Italian Chamber of Deputies|Chamber of Deputies]], considered the ''lower house'').

In some of these countries, the upper house is indirectly elected. Members of France's [[French Senate|Senate]], Ireland's [[Seanad Éireann]] are chosen by [[electoral college]]s consisting of members of the lower house, local councillors, the [[Taoiseach]], and graduates of selected universities, while the Netherlands' [[Senate of the Netherlands|Senate]] is chosen by members of provincial assemblies (which in turn are directly elected).

[[Norway]] had a kind of semi-bicameral legislature with two chambers, or departments, within the same elected body, the [[Storting]]. These were called the Odelsting and Lagting and were abolished after the general election of 2009. According to Morten Søberg, there was a related system in the 1798 constitution of the [[Batavian Republic]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.minerva.as/?vis=artikkel&amp;fid=3018&amp;id=0604200909214912460&amp;magasin=ja&amp;t=Senatet-som-aldri-vart Minerva.as]&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Hong Kong]], members of the unicameral [[Legislative Council (Hong Kong)|Legislative Council]] returned from geographical constituencies and [[functional constituencies]] are required to vote separately since 1997 on motions, bills or amendments to government bills not introduced by the government. The passage of these motions, bills or amendments to government bills requires double majority in both groups simultaneously. (Before 2004, when elections to the Legislative Council  from the [[Election Committee]] was abolished, members returned through the Election Committee vote with members returned from geographical constituencies.) The double majority requirement does not apply to motions, bills and amendments introduced by the [[Hong Kong Government|government]].

==Subnational entities==
In some countries with federal systems, individual states (like those of the [[United States]], [[States and territories of Australia|Australia]] and a few [[States of India]]) may also have bicameral legislatures. Only three such states, [[Nebraska]] in the US, [[Queensland]] in Australia and [[Bavaria]] in Germany have later adopted unicameral systems. Canadian provinces had all their upper houses abolished.

===United States===

During the 1930s, the Legislature of the State of Nebraska was reduced from [[bicameral]] to unicameral with the 43 members that once comprised that state's Senate. One of the arguments used to sell the idea at the time to Nebraska voters was that by adopting a unicameral system, the perceived evils of the &quot;[[conference committee]]&quot; process would be eliminated.

A conference committee is appointed when the two chambers cannot agree on the same wording of a proposal, and consists of a small number of legislators from each chamber. This tends to place much power in the hands of only a small number of legislators. Whatever legislation, if any, the conference committee finalizes must then be approved in an unamendable &quot;take-it-or-leave-it&quot; manner by both chambers.

During his term as [[Governor]] of the State of [[Minnesota]], [[Jesse Ventura]] proposed converting the Minnesotan legislature to a single chamber with [[proportional representation]], as a reform that he felt would solve many legislative difficulties and impinge upon legislative corruption. In his book on political issues, ''Do I Stand Alone?'', Ventura argued that bicameral legislatures for provincial and local areas were excessive and unnecessary, and discussed unicameralism as a reform that could address many legislative and budgetary problems for states.

===Argentina===
in [[Argentina]], eight [[Provinces of Argentina|provinces]] have bicameral legislatures, with a [[Senate]] and a [[Chamber of Deputies]]: [[Buenos Aires Province|Buenos Aires]], [[Catamarca Province|Catamarca]], [[Corrientes]], [[Entre Ríos Province|Entre Ríos]], [[Mendoza Province|Mendoza]], [[Salta Province|Salta]], [[San Luis Province|San Luis]] (since 1987) and [[Santa Fe Province|Santa Fe]]. [[Córdoba Province, Argentina|Córdoba]] and [[Tucumán Province|Tucumán]] changed to [[unicameral]] systems in 2001 and 2003 respectively.

===Australia===
In Australian states, the lower house was traditionally elected based on the one-vote-one-value principle, whereas the upper house was partially appointed and elected, with a bias towards country voters. In Queensland, the appointed [[Queensland Legislative Council|upper house]] was abolished in 1922, while in [[New South Wales]] there were similar attempts at abolition, before the [[New South Wales Legislative Council|upper house]] was reformed in the 1970s to provide for direct election. Nowadays, the upper house is elected using proportional voting and the lower house through preferential voting, except in [[Tasmania]], where proportional voting is used for the [[Tasmania House of Assembly|lower house]], and preferential voting for the [[Tasmania Legislative Council|upper house]].

===India===
Six Indian States of [[Andhra Pradesh]], [[Bihar]], [[Jammu-Kashmir]], [[Karnataka]], [[Maharashtra]] and [[Uttar Pradesh]]  have Bicameral Legislatures, these are called legislative councils ([[Vidhan Parishad]]), one third of who get elected every 6 years, there are graduate constituencies (members elected exclusively by graduates), teachers constituencies (members elected exclusively by teachers), municipal constituencies (members elected exclusively by Mayors and council members of the city Governments).From 1956 to 1958 the Andhra Pradesh Legislature was Unicameral and from 1958 when the Council was formed, it became bicameral and continued until 1 June 1985 when the Legislative Council was abolished.This continued until March 2007 when the Legislative Council was reestablished and elections were held for its seats. Since then the Andhra Pradesh Legislature has become once again Bicameral.

===Germany===
The German Land of [[Bavaria]] had a bicameral legislature from 1946 to 1999, when the [[Senate of Bavaria|Senate]] was abolished by a referendum amending the state's constitution. The other 15 Länder have used a unicameral system since their founding.

===Russia===
Under [[Soviet regime]] regional and local [[Soviet (council)|Soviets]] were unicameral. After the adoption of [[Constitution of Russia|1993 Russian Constitution]] bicameralism was introduced in some regions. Bicameral regional legislatures are still technically allowed by federal law but this clause is dormant now. The last region to switch from bicameralism to unicameralism was [[Sverdlovsk Oblast]] in 2012.

==Reform==

===Arab political reform===
A [http://www.cfr.org/pdf/Arab_Democracy_TF.pdf 2005 report] on democratic reform in the Arab world by the US [[Council on Foreign Relations]] co-sponsored by former Secretary of State [[Madeleine Albright]] urged Arab states to adopt bicameralism, with upper chambers appointed on a 'specialised basis'. The Council claimed that this would protect against the '[[Tyranny of the majority]]', expressing concerns that without a system of checks and balances extremists would use the single chamber parliaments to restrict the rights of [[minority group|minority]] groups.

In 2002, [[Bahrain]] adopted a bicameral system with an elected lower chamber and an appointed upper house. This led to a boycott of parliamentary elections that year by the [[Al Wefaq]] party, who said that the government would use the upper house to veto their plans. Many secular critics of bicameralism were won around to its benefits in 2005, after many MPs in the lower house voted for the introduction of so-called [[morality police]].

===Romania===
A [[Romanian parliamentary reform referendum, 2009|referendum]] on introducing a unicameral Parliament instead of the current bicameral [[Parliament of Romania|Parliament]] was held in [[Romania]] on 22 November 2009. The turnout rate was 50.95%, with 77.78% of &quot;Yes&quot; votes for a unicameral Parliament.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.news-ro.info/referendum-turnout-5095-7778-said-yes-for-a-unicameral-parliament-8884-voted-for-the-decrease-in-the-number-of-parliamentarians.html Referendum turnout 50.95%. 77.78 said YES for a unicameral Parliament, 88.84% voted for the decrease in the number of Parliamentarians], Official reuslts from the Romanian Central Electoral Commission&lt;/ref&gt; This referendum had a consultative role, thus requiring a parliamentary initiative and another referendum to ratify the new proposed changes.

==Examples==
[[Image:Unibicameral Map.svg|500px|thumb|center|{{legend|#38b4d8|Nations with bicameral legislatures.}}{{legend|#f09c30|Nations with unicameral legislatures.}}{{legend|#303030|No legislature.}}{{legend|#a0989f|No data.}}]]

* [[Afghanistan]] - The '''[[National Assembly of Afghanistan|National Assembly]]''' consists of [[Meshrano Jirga|Masharano Jirga]] and [[Wolesi Jirga]]
* [[Argentina]] - The '''[[Argentine National Congress|National Congress]]''' consists of [[Argentine Senate|Senate]] and [[Argentine Chamber of Deputies|Chamber of Deputies]]. Of the twenty-three provincial legislatures, eight are bicameral, while the remaining fifteen and the legislature of the [[Autonomous City of Buenos Aires]] are unicameral.
* [[Australia]] - The '''[[Parliament of Australia|Parliament]]''' consists of the [[Australian House of Representatives|House of Representatives]] and [[Australian Senate|Senate]]; all of the state parliaments except [[Queensland]]'s are also bicameral.
* [[Austria]] - The '''[[Parliament of Austria|Parliament]]''' consists of the {{lang|de|[[National Council of Austria|Nationalrat]]}} and the {{lang|de|[[Federal Council of Austria|Bundesrat]]}}; all of the {{lang|de|''[[States of Austria|Bundesländer]]''}} have unicameral parliaments.
* [[Belgium]] - The '''[[Belgian Federal Parliament|Federal Parliament]]''' consists of the [[Belgian Chamber of Representatives|Chamber of Representatives]] and [[Belgian Senate|Senate]]; all of the [[Communities, regions and language areas of Belgium|community and regional]] parliaments are unicameral.
* [[Brazil]] - The '''[[National Congress of Brazil|National Congress]]''' consists of the [[Senate of Brazil|Senate]] and the [[Chamber of Deputies of Brazil|Chamber of Deputies]]; all of the 26 state legislatures and the Federal District legislature are unicameral.
* [[Canada]] - The '''[[Parliament of Canada|Parliament]]''' consists of the [[Canadian House of Commons|House of Commons]] and the [[Canadian Senate|Senate]]; all of the provincial legislatures are unicameral.
* [[France]] - The '''[[Parliament of France|Parliament]]''' in the [[France|Fifth French Republic]] consists of the [[French National Assembly|National Assembly]] and the [[French Senate|Senate]]
* [[Germany]] - The '''{{lang|de|[[Bundestag]]}}''' and {{lang|de|[[Bundesrat (Germany)|Bundesrat]]}} in [[Germany]], which form two distinct bodies not framed by a comprehensive institution; all of the {{lang|de|''[[States of Germany|Länder]]''}} today have unicameral parliaments.
* [[India]] - The '''[[Parliament of India|Parliament]]''' in [[India]], which consists of the {{lang|hi|[[Lok Sabha]]}} (House of the People) and the {{lang|hi|[[Rajya Sabha]]}} (Council of States); some of the states also have bicameral legislatures namely {{lang|hi|[[Vidhan Sabha]]}} (Legislative Assembly) and {{lang|hi|[[Vidhan Parishad]]}} (Legislative Council).
* [[Republic of Ireland|Ireland]] - The {{lang|ga|'''[[Oireachtas]]'''}} consists of {{lang|ga|[[Dáil Éireann]]}} (the House of Representatives) and {{lang|ga|[[Seanad Éireann]]}} (the Senate).
* [[Italy]] - The '''[[Italian Parliament|Parliament]]''' consists of two chambers that have same role and power: the [[Italian Senate|Senate]] (Senate of the Republic, commonly considered the ''upper house'') and the [[Italian Chamber of Deputies|Chamber of Deputies]], considered the ''lower house'') with twice as many members as the Senate.
* [[Japan]] - The '''[[Diet of Japan|Diet]]''' is bicameral, consisting of the [[House of Representatives of Japan|House of Representatives]] as the lower house and the [[House of Councillors of Japan|House of Councillors]] as the upper house.
* [[Malaysia]] - The '''[[Parliament of Malaysia|Parliament]]''' consists of the {{lang|ms|''[[Dewan Rakyat]]''}} (House of Representatives) and the {{lang|ms|''[[Dewan Negara]]''}} (Senate); all of the state legislatures are unicameral.
* [[Mexico]] - The '''[[Congress of Mexico|Congress]]''' consists of the [[Senate of Mexico|Senate]] and the [[Chamber of Deputies of Mexico|Chamber of Deputies]]; all the 31 State Congresses and the Legislative Assembly of the Federal District are unicameral.
* [[Netherlands]] - The '''[[States-General of the Netherlands]]''' consists of the {{lang|nl|[[House of Representatives of the Netherlands|Tweede Kamer]]}} (House of Representatives, literally ''Second Chamber'') and the {{lang|nl|[[Senate of the Netherlands|Eerste Kamer]]}} (Senate, literally ''First Chamber'')
* [[Pakistan]] - The '''[[Parliament of Pakistan|Parliament]]''' consists of the [[National Assembly of Pakistan|National Assembly]] and the [[Senate of Pakistan|Senate]]; all of the provincial assemblies are unicameral.
* [[Philippines]] - The '''[[Congress of the Philippines|Congress]]''' consists of a [[Senate of the Philippines|Senate]] and a [[House of Representatives of the Philippines|House of Representatives]]; all local legislatures are unicameral.
* [[Russian Federation]] - The '''[[Federal Assembly of Russia|Federal Assembly]]''' consists of the [[State Duma]] and the [[Federation Council of Russia|Federation Council]]; all the regional legislatures are now unicameral while bicameralism in regions is technically allowed by the Federation.
* [[South Africa]] - The '''[[Parliament of South Africa|Parliament]]''' consists of the [[National Assembly of South Africa|National Assembly]] and the [[National Council of Provinces]]; all of the provincial legislatures are unicameral.
* [[Spain]] - The {{lang|es|'''[[Cortes Generales]]'''}} consists of a lower house, the [[Spanish Congress of Deputies|Congress of Deputies]] and an upper house, the [[Spanish Senate|Senate]]. Moreover, each Spanish [[Autonomous communities of Spain|autonomous region]] has its own unicameral regional parliament, with wide-ranging legislative powers on their own.
* [[Switzerland]] - The '''[[Federal Assembly of Switzerland|Federal Assembly]]''' consists of the [[National Council of Switzerland|National Council]] and the [[Swiss Council of States|Council of States]]; all of the cantons have unicameral parliaments.
* [[United Kingdom]] - The '''[[Parliament of the United Kingdom|Parliament]]''' consists of the [[British House of Commons|House of Commons]] and the [[House of Lords]]. [[Scotland]], [[Wales]] and [[Northern Ireland]] have devolved unicameral legislatures with limited devolved powers.
* [[United States]] - The '''[[United States Congress|Congress]]''' consists of the [[United States Senate|Senate]] and the [[United States House of Representatives|House of Representatives]]; all of the state legislatures except [[Nebraska legislature|Nebraska]] are also bicameral.

==See also==
* [[List of national legislatures]]
* [[Lower house]]
* [[Tetracameralism]]
* [[Tricameralism]]
* [[Unicameralism]]
* [[Upper house]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}&lt;!--added above categories/infobox footers by script-assisted edit--&gt;

==External links==
* [http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=505822 ''Noncontemporaneous Lawmaking: Can the 110th Senate Enact a Bill Passed by the 109th House?'', 16 Cornell J.L. &amp; Pub. Pol'y 331 (2007).]
* [http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=932574 Aaron-Andrew P. Bruhl, ''Against Mix-and-Match Lawmaking'', 16 '''Cornell J.L. &amp; Pub. Pol'y''' 349 (2007).]
* [http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=956155 ''Defending the (Not So) Indefensible: A Reply to Professor Aaron-Andrew P. Bruhl'', 16 '''Cornell J.L. &amp; Pub. Pol'y''' 363 (2007).]

{{National upper houses}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2010}}

[[Category:Government]]
[[Category:Liberalism]]
[[Category:Bicameral legislatures|*]]

[[ar:برلمان من مجلسين]]
[[ca:Bicameralitat]]
[[cs:Bikameralismus]]
[[da:Tokammersystem]]
[[de:Zweikammersystem]]
[[es:Bicameralidad]]
[[eo:Duĉambra parlamento]]
[[eu:Ganbera-bitasun]]
[[fr:Bicamérisme]]
[[gl:Bicameralismo]]
[[ko:양원제]]
[[id:Sistem dua kamar]]
[[it:Bicameralismo]]
[[kk:Екі палаталы жүйе]]
[[lb:Zweekummersystem]]
[[mk:Дводомен парламент]]
[[ms:Dwidewan]]
[[nl:Tweekamerstelsel]]
[[ja:両院制]]
[[no:Tokammersystem]]
[[nn:Tokammersystem]]
[[pl:Bikameralizm]]
[[pt:Bicameralismo]]
[[ro:Bicameralism]]
[[ru:Двухпалатный парламент]]
[[simple:Bicameral]]
[[fi:Kaksikamarijärjestelmä]]
[[sv:Tvåkammarsystem]]
[[ta:ஈரவை]]
[[th:ระบบสองสภา]]
[[tr:Çift meclislilik]]
[[uk:Двопалатний парламент]]
[[zh:兩院制]]</text>
      <sha1>t9allrhowp91lsqb9s0h9l04p27yw93</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
