<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Brights movement</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>251456</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519464631</id>
      <parentid>519463806</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-23T21:43:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>McGeddon</username>
        <id>455421</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>more specific ref</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17347">{{Redirect|Brights|other uses|Bright (disambiguation)}}

[[Image:Bright Logo.png|right|thumb|Symbol of the Brights]]

The '''Brights movement''' is a social movement that aims to promote public understanding and acknowledgment of the [[naturalism (philosophy)|naturalistic]] worldview, including equal civil rights and acceptance for people who hold a naturalistic worldview. It was co-founded by [[Mynga Futrell]] and [[Paul Geisert]] in 2003. The movement aims to create an [[Internet]] [[constituency]] that will pursue the following aims:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.the-brights.net/action/documentation/press_kit.html |title=The Brights' Net Media Kit |publisher=The-brights.net |date= |accessdate=2011-04-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# Promote public understanding and acknowledgment of the naturalistic worldview, which is free of supernatural and mystical elements.
# Gain public recognition that persons who hold such a worldview can bring principled actions to bear on matters of civic importance.
# Educate society toward accepting the full and equitable civic participation of all such people.

The Brights movement distinguishes itself from traditional membership organizations by focusing on the development of a broad public constituency capable of including members of many narrower categories.  For example: [[atheism|atheists]], [[agnosticism|agnostics]], [[humanism|humanists]], [[skepticism|skeptics]], and members of religious traditions who observe the cultural practices without believing literally in a deity might all pursue shared civic goals respecting [[egalitarianism|egalitarian]] laws and a political discourse informed by the [[science|natural sciences]]. Also, unlike a typical membership organization, the Brights movement does not appoint individuals empowered to speak for the whole; individual brights speak for themselves or speak collectively by proposing statements to which all registered Brights may join in assent (or not) as they see fit. Instead, the focus is on making visible to society the largest possible constituency of people who hold a naturalistic worldview.

The noun ''bright'' was coined by Geisert as a positive-sounding [[umbrella term]], and Futrell defined it as &quot;an individual whose worldview is naturalistic (free from [[supernatural]] and [[mystical]] elements)&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;FAQ1&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.the-brights.net/vision/faq.html#1| work=Frequently Asked Questions| publisher=The Brights' Net| title=Bright (n.)--What is the definition?| accessdate=2006-11-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Daniel Dennett]] has since suggested that people that believe in the supernatural could choose to be referred to as ''supers''.

As of 2009, the Brights' tagline is &quot;Illuminating and Elevating the Naturalistic Worldview&quot;.

==History==
Paul Geisert was a biology teacher in Chicago in the 1960s, a [[professor]] in the 1970s, an entrepreneur and writer in the 1980s, and the co-developer of learning materials and a web site regarding teaching about religion in public schools in the 1990s.

In deciding to attend the &quot;[[Godless Americans March on Washington]]&quot; in 2002, Paul disliked the label &quot;godless&quot; and resolved to identify a better term to unite the &quot;community of reason.&quot; He sought a new, positive word that might become well-accepted, in the same way that the term &quot;[[gay]]&quot; has come to mean &quot;homosexual.&quot; In late 2002, Paul coined the noun &quot;bright,&quot; but did not announce it immediately.

Working with Mynga Futrell, the co-founders of the Brights movement wanted to connect and galvanize the many individuals who were non-religious, but who were not associated with the many philosophical organisations already in existence. To achieve this they created not only the definition of &quot;a bright,&quot; but also the idea of a civic constituency that would coalesce through the Internet.

Having tested this idea during the early months of 2003, they launched the Brights' Net website on June 4, 2003. The movement gained early publicity through articles by [[Richard Dawkins]] in ''[[The Guardian]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=The future looks bright|date=2003-06-21|publisher=The Guardian|url=http://books.guardian.co.uk/review/story/0,12084,981412,00.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''[[Wired magazine|Wired]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Religion Be Damned|date=October 2003|publisher=Wired|url=http://www.wired.com/wired/archive/11.10/view.html?pg=2}}&lt;/ref&gt; and by [[Daniel Dennett]] in  ''[[The New York Times]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=The Bright Stuff|date=2003-07-12|publisher=The New York Times|url=http://www.edge.org/3rd_culture/bright/bright_index.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; Within a year, registered Brights numbered in five figures and spanned 85 nations.

The movement has continued to grow and experienced accelerated registrations following media debate around &quot;new atheism&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=The Church of the Non-Believers|date=November 2006|publisher=Wired|url=http://www.wired.com/wired/archive/14.11/atheism.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; prompted by a series of book releases in late 2006 including ''[[The God Delusion]]'', ''[[Breaking the Spell: Religion as a Natural Phenomenon|Breaking the Spell]]'', ''[[God Is Not Great]]'', ''[[The End of Faith]]'', and ''[[Letter to a Christian Nation]]''. As of January 2010 over 50,000 Brights registered from 186 nations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://the-brights.net/movement/bulletin/bulletin.html?b=79 | title= Now &gt;50,000 Brights
 | work=The Brights' Bulletin Issue #79 | publisher=The Brights' Net }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==The Brights' Net==
The Brights' Net web site serves as the hub of communication and action projects in the Brights movement. 

The Brights' Net recommends project priorities and facilitates the formation of local groups, known as Brights' Local Constituencies (BLCs). There are BLCs in [[London]], [[Paris]], several cities in the [[United States]] and [[Canada]], and various other locations worldwide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.the-brights.net/community/blc/list.html |title=The Brights' Net – Brights Clusters |publisher=The-brights.net |date= |accessdate=2010-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, Brights act autonomously in doing their part for the furtherance of the Brights movement. No person or entity, including The Brights' Net co-directors, can speak for all Brights.

==Brights==
Within the definition of ''bright'',&lt;ref name=&quot;FAQ1&quot;/&gt; many, but not all, brights also identify variously under other terms or identities, including [[atheism|atheist]], [[humanism|humanist]], [[secular humanism|secular humanist]], [[freethought|freethinker]], [[Objectivism (Ayn Rand)|objectivist]], [[rationalist movement|rationalist]], [[naturalism (philosophy)|naturalist]], [[materialism|materialist]], [[agnosticism|agnostic]], [[skepticism|skeptic]], [[apatheism|apatheist]], or even [[Naturalistic pantheism|naturalistic pantheists]] or classical [[Deist]]s, and so on. Even so, the &quot;movement is not associated with any defined beliefs,&quot; as written on The Brights' Net website. One of the purposes of the Brights' Net is to include the umbrella term ''bright'' in the vocabulary of this existing &quot;community of reason&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.the-brights.net/vision/faq.html#8| title = What is the purpose of the Brights' Net? | work=Frequently Asked Questions| publisher=The Brights' Net|accessdate=2006-11-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, &quot;the broader intent is inclusive of the many-varied persons whose worldview is naturalistic&quot; but are in the &quot;general population&quot;, as opposed to associating solely with the &quot;community of reason&quot;. So persons who can declare their naturalistic worldview using the term ''bright'' extend beyond the familiar [[secularism|secularist]] categories, as long as they do not hold theistic worldviews.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://the-brights.net/movement/bulletin/bulletin.html?b=70 | title= Theistic Brights? – Not So! | work=The Brights' Bulletin Issue #70 | publisher=The Brights' Net }}&lt;/ref&gt; Registrations even include some members of the clergy, such as [[Presbyterian]] ministers and a Church History Professor and ordained priest.

Dawkins' analogy in the aforementioned ''Guardian'' article is instructive, comparing the coining of ''bright'' to the &quot;triumph of consciousness-raising&quot; from the term ''gay'':
&lt;blockquote&gt;[[Gay]] is succinct, uplifting, positive: an &quot;up&quot; word, where homosexual is a down word, and [[queer]], [[faggot (epithet)|faggot]] and pooftah are insults. Those of us who subscribe to no religion; those of us whose view of the universe is natural rather than supernatural; those of us who rejoice in the real and scorn the false comfort of the unreal, we need a word of our own, a word like &quot;gay&quot;. ... Like gay, it should be a noun hijacked from an adjective, with its original meaning changed but not too much. Like gay, it should be catchy: a potentially prolific meme. Like gay, it should be positive, warm, cheerful, bright.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Despite the explicit difference between the noun and adjective, there have been comments on the comparison. In his ''Wired'' article Dawkins states, &quot;Whether there is a statistical tendency for brights [noun] to be bright [adjective] is a matter for research.&quot; Daniel Dennett, in his book ''Breaking the Spell'', suggests that if non-naturalists are concerned with this connotation of the word ''bright'', then they should invent an equally positive sounding word for themselves, like ''supers'' (i.e., one whose worldview contains supernaturalism). Geisert and Futrell maintain that the neologism has always had a kinship with [[the Enlightenment]], an era which celebrated science, free inquiry, and a spirit of skepticism; they have endorsed the use of ''super'' as the antonym to ''bright''.

Notable brights include biologists [[Richard Dawkins]] and [[Richard J. Roberts]], cognitive scientist [[Steven Pinker]], philosopher [[Daniel Dennett]], and stage magicians and [[debunker]]s [[James Randi]] and [[Penn &amp; Teller]]. Other brights include [[Amy Alkon]], [[Sheldon Lee Glashow]], [[Babu Gogineni]], [[Edwin Kagin]], [[Mel Lipman]], [[Piergiorgio Odifreddi]],  [[Air America Radio]] talk show host [[Lionel (radio personality)|Lionel]] and [[Massimo Pigliucci]].

==Symbology==
The Brights' avatar represents a celestial body viewed from space. As there is no up or down or right or left in outer space, the arrangement of planet and darkness and starlight is changeable.&lt;ref name=&quot;symbology&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Brights Symbology|url=http://www.the-brights.net/vision/symbolism.html|publisher=The Brights|accessdate=16 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the symbol is open to the viewer’s interpretation, it is generally meant to invoke transition and a sense of gradual illumination.  The intentional ambiguity of avatar is meant to symbolically reflect an important question: Is the future of humankind becoming luminous or more dim?  The Brights “wish to take the promising route, whereby the imagery brings to mind a gradually increasing illumination for this earth of ours, an escalation of enlightenment.”.&lt;ref name=&quot;symbology&quot;/&gt;

==Criticism==
The movement has been criticised by some (both religious and non-religious) who have objected to the adoption of the title &quot;bright&quot; because they believe it suggests that the individuals with a naturalistic [[worldview]] are more intelligent (&quot;brighter&quot;) than non-naturalists, such as [[philosophical skepticism|philosophical skeptics]] or [[idealism|idealists]], believers in the [[paranormal]], [[philosophical theism|philosophical theists]] or the [[religiosity and intelligence|religious]].&lt;ref name=&quot;not so bright&quot;&gt;{{cite news| last = D'Souza| first = Dinesh| title = Not So 'Bright'| work = The Wall Street Journal| publisher = Dow Jones &amp; Co.| date = 12 October 2003| url = http://www.opinionjournal.com/extra/?id=110004153| accessdate = 2007-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, the [[Committee for Skeptical Inquiry]] published an article by [[Chris Mooney (journalist)|Chris Mooney]] titled &quot;Not Too 'Bright'&quot; in which he stated that, although he agreed with the movement, Richard Dawkins' and Daniel Dennett's &quot;campaign to rename religious unbelievers 'brights' could use some rethinking&quot; because of the possibility that the term would be misinterpreted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Chris Mooney |url=http://www.csicop.org/specialarticles/show/not_too_bright/ |title=Brights: Not Too &quot;Bright&quot; (Doubt and About) |publisher=Csicop.org |date= |accessdate=2011-04-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; The journalist and noted atheist [[Christopher Hitchens]] likewise found it a &quot;cringe-making proposal that atheists should conceitedly nominate themselves to be called 'brights.'&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.slate.com/id/2165033/entry/2165035/ |title=Exclusive excerpts from Christopher Hitchens' God Is Not Great. – By Christopher Hitchens – Slate Magazine |publisher=Slate.com |date= |accessdate=2010-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Dennett posed the idea that ''super'' may serve well as a positive title for those who believe in the supernatural. He also suggested this during his presentation at the Atheist Alliance International '07 convention.&lt;ref&gt;[http://saliental.blogspot.com/2006/09/dan-dennett-at-aaic-07.html Dan Dennett at AAIC '07] Oct. 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=26 oktober 2007 |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gyyRAE7PDvw&amp;feature=related |title=Dan Dennet: Award &amp; Speech at AAI 07 pt1 of 2 |publisher=YouTube |date= |accessdate=2010-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Similarly, [[Michael Shermer]], who is an Enthusiastic Bright,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title = Enthusiastic Brights| work = The-Brights.net| url = http://www.the-brights.net/people/enthusiastic/index2.html| accessdate = 2007-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; has nevertheless resisted using the term to describe himself, saying, &quot;I don't call myself a 'Bright'.”

'Bright' is also a term used in 'Star, Bright' a science fiction story by Ross Rocklynne, featured on the April 10, 1956 episode of radio show 'X-1' that featured humans who developed vastly superior intellects. 'Brights' is the name they choose for themselves in the story, while 'Tween' is the term the 'Brights' used for humans of ordinary intelligence. Whether or not this is known to proponents of the term currently is unknown but it adds some weight to the suggestion that the term has a connotation to it that could be seen as superior.

In response to this Daniel Dennett has stated in his book ''Breaking the Spell'':

&lt;blockquote&gt;There was also a negative response, largely objecting to the term that had been chosen [not by me]: ''bright'', which seemed to imply that others were dim or stupid. But the term, modeled on the highly successful hijacking of the ordinary word &quot;gay&quot; by homosexuals, does not have to have that implication. Those who are not gays are not necessarily glum; they're ''straight''. Those who are not brights are not necessarily dim.&lt;ref&gt;Dennett, Daniel. ''Breaking The Spell'' (2006). London: Penguin. p.21.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Another common criticism {{Citation needed|date=March 2010}} of the Bright movement is that the proposed terminology is superfluous, being virtually synonymous with already accepted descriptive terms such as [[secular humanism|secular humanist]], [[metaphysical naturalism|naturalist]], and [[rationalist]].

==See also==
* [[Atheism]]
* [[Metaphysical naturalism]]
* [[Naturalistic pantheism]]
* [[Out Campaign]]
* [[Religiosity and intelligence]]
* [[Scientific skepticism]]
* [[Sea of Faith]]
* [[Secular humanism]]

==References==
{{Reflist|35em}}

==External links==
* [http://www.the-brights.net/ The Brights' Net] – The originating hub of the Brights' constituency
* [http://www.teachingaboutreligion.org/ Teaching About Religion In Public Schools: Worldview Education]

&lt;!--======================== {{No more links}} ============================
    | PLEASE BE CAUTIOUS IN ADDING MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. Wikipedia  |
    | is not a collection of links nor should it be used for advertising. |
    |                                                                     |
    |           Excessive or inappropriate links WILL BE DELETED.         |
    | See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.  |
    |                                                                     |
    | If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or   |
    | replacements on this article's discussion page, or submit your link |
    | to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org)   |
    | and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.         |
    ======================= {{No more links}} =============================--&gt;

{{DEFAULTSORT:Brights movement}}
[[Category:Social movements]]
[[Category:Activism]]
[[Category:Secularism]]
[[Category:Humanism]]
[[Category:Antitheism]]
[[Category:Atheism]]
[[Category:Agnosticism]]
[[Category:Scientific skepticism]]
[[Category:Organizations established in 2003]]
[[Category:Words coined in the 2000s]]

[[ca:Bright]]
[[cs:Hnutí Brights]]
[[da:Brights]]
[[de:Brights]]
[[el:Κίνημα των Μπράιτ]]
[[es:Movimiento Brights]]
[[eo:Movado Brights]]
[[fa:جنبش روشن‌ها]]
[[fr:Mouvement des brights]]
[[it:The Brights]]
[[he:ברייטס]]
[[lt:Šviesuolių judėjimas]]
[[nl:Bright (naturalisme)]]
[[ja:ブライト運動]]
[[nds:The Brights]]
[[pl:Brights movement]]
[[pt:Movimento bright]]
[[ru:Движение Brights]]
[[simple:Brights]]
[[fi:Bright]]
[[sv:Brights]]</text>
      <sha1>ivvrhg62irry0xtdbalyh0kwizqvccn</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
