<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Brown Berets (Watsonville)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3338831</id>
    <revision>
      <id>515592252</id>
      <parentid>454525546</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-02T08:23:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>24.205.240.86</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Added Oscar Rios interview quote and references to website.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3640">{{multiple issues|orphan=April 2011|refimprove=April 2011}}

The '''Brown Berets''' are a race based [[political extremist]] [[youth group|youth organization]] and secret society based in [[Watsonville, California]] modeled after the [[Brown Berets]] of the [[Civil Rights Movement]]. An excerpt from their website states, &quot;we serve as a community defense force acting for the liberation and amelioration of our barrios&quot;. Their beliefs are anti-military, anti-police, and anti-border patrol.&lt;ref&gt;http://brownberets.info/&lt;/ref&gt; Their members are encouraged to study the [[Black Panthers]] and American Militant Resistance.&lt;ref&gt;http://brownberets.info/calmecac&lt;/ref&gt;. Brown Beret member and former Watsonville Mayor Oscar Rios was quoted in an interview as saying,&quot;It (California) belonged to us, Mexico, 1848. It was taken away okay, so it's no surprise we're taking it back slowly but surely.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uF6OvljIUeo&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
On April 6, 1994 a group of Chicano students from Watsonville, inspired by the legacy of the [[Mexican nationalist]]-tinged community activism of the original Brown Berets, decided to resurrect the movement. They felt that similar conditions existed there in 1994 that had existed in 1967, and wanted to respond to the gang-related murders of 9-year-old Jessica Cortez and her 16-year-old brother, George.

In order to address the increasing [[gang violence]], the Watsonville Brown Berets organized an annual march that passed through all the different [[barrio]]s of Watsonville in order to bring the message of ''Peace and Unity.'' {{Citation needed|date=May 2007}} In doing this, the Brown Berets believed that young people involved in gangs could redirect that energy into more constructive avenues — cultural awareness and social-political activism leading to grassroots local change.

Since then, the group has established firm relations with other left-wing community organizations such as Students Against War (UCSC), Barrios Unidos, and the Resource Center for Non-Violence of Santa Cruz. In 2004, the Watsonville Brown Berets opened &quot;Liberation School&quot;, which provides tutoring and career guidance as well as an extensive revolutionary library.

Watsonville city councilman and Brown Beret member Oscar Rios claimed, “The Watsonville Brown Berets have been one of the strongest youth organizations in this community and have led by example by providing our young people with constructive alternatives and the tools to make progressive change.” {{Citation needed|date=May 2007}}

On May 27, 2005, the Watsonville Brown Berets organized their fourth annual ''Youth and Power'' event, which took place at the Vets Hall in Watsonville. Over 400 young people were in attendance. The event featured counter-military recruitment activist [[Fernando Suarez del Solar]]. Over 20 organizations hosted information tables providing literature about college opportunities as well as political, community and environmental activism. “It is events like this that empower our young people and remind them that their voice is a powerful weapon,” said Brown Beret member Jennifer Laskin.


== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.fightbacknews.org/2003winter/brownberets.htm Interview with original Brown Berets co-founder Carlos Montes]
*[http://www.brownberets.info Watsonville Brown Berets website]
*[http://santacruz.indymedia.org/newswire/display/17911/index.php Watson Brown Berets on Santa Cruz Indymedia]

[[Category:Nationalism]]
[[Category:Activism]]
[[Category:Latin American culture]]
[[Category:Watsonville, California]]


{{US-org-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>8z0n34ejyuzwi0auawib5zoa4xhh41o</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
