<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Campaign for Innocent Victims in Conflict</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1756412</id>
    <revision>
      <id>500643863</id>
      <parentid>482926441</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-07-04T12:48:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Chowbok</username>
        <id>54304</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Note */[[WP:GENFIXES|General fixes]], replaced: 1 1/2 → 1{{fraction|1|2}} using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (8062)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11187">'''Campaign for Innocent Victims in Conflict''' (CIVIC) is a [[Washington, D.C.]]-based [[non-profit organization]] and advocacy founded in 2003 by [[Marla Ruzicka]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CIVIC|Campaign for Innocent Victims&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title= About Us | url=http://www.civicworldwide.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=12&amp;Itemid=41 | publisher= CIVIC|Campaign for Innocent Victims in Conflict | accessdate= 2010-11-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Zunia&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=The Campaign For Innocent Victims in Conflict | url=http://zunia.org/post/the-campaign-for-innocent-victims-in-conflict/?rank=c&amp;cHash=54f0af882e6c09316c987687767fd715 | publisher= Zunia | accessdate= 2010-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; CIVIC works on behalf of war victims, providing research and advocating policymakers.&lt;ref name=&quot;CIVIC|Campaign for Innocent Victims in Conflict&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title= What We Do | url=http://www.civicworldwide.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=13&amp;Itemid=174 | publisher= CIVIC|Campaign for Innocent Victims in Conflict | accessdate= 2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReliefWeb&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title= Civilians Harm and Conflict in Northwest Pakistan | url=http://www.reliefweb.int/rw/rwb.nsf/db900SID/MUMA-8A7978?OpenDocument | publisher= ReliefWeb | accessdate= 2010-12-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; CIVIC is a part of the Making Amends Campaign.&lt;ref name=&quot;CIVIC|Campaign for Innocent Victims in Conflict&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title= Help us sustain CIVIC's work! | url=https://secure.democracyinaction.org/dia/organizations/civic/shop/custom.jsp?donate_page_KEY=284 | publisher= CIVIC|Campaign for Innocent Victims in Conflict | accessdate= 2010-12-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Foundations==

Campaign for Innocent Victims in Conflict (CIVIC) was founded by [[Marla Ruzicka]] in 2003.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Washington Post&quot;&gt;{{cite news | title=U.S. Activist Mends Lives Torn by War | url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A24737-2004Aug22.html | publisher= The Washington Post | accessdate= 2010-12-02 | first=Glenn | last=Kessler | date=2004-08-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Marla, with the help of [[Senator Patrick Leahy]], created the first-ever US-funded aid program dedicated to helping rebuild the lives of civilians unintentionally harmed by US combat operations.{{citation needed|date=December 2010}} CIVIC works closely with the military and organizations such as NATO. Although Marla was killed by a [[Suicide attack|suicide bomb]] in [[Baghdad]] in April 2005, her colleagues, friends and family continue to run CIVIC. A staff was hired in early 2006&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.rollingstone.com/politics/story/7371965/the_girl_who_tried_to_save_the_world
|title=The Girl Who Tried to Save the World: The heroic life and final days of Marla Ruzicka, an American martyr
|work=Rolling Stone |first=JANET |last=REITMAN |date=Jun 02, 2005
|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080617183058/http://www.rollingstone.com/politics/story/7371965/the_girl_who_tried_to_save_the_world/
|archivedate=2008-06-17
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2005/04/24/BAG02CEA1V1.DTL&amp;hw=ruzicka&amp;sn=003&amp;sc=836 |title=LAKEPORT: More than 600 mourn peace activist at service |first=Jason B. |last=Johnson |work=San Francisco Chronicle |date=April 24, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the organization expanded its mandate in early 2007 beyond Iraq and Afghanistan. CIVIC achievements include persuading the [[US Congress]] to develop programs that aid victims caught in the middle of widespread conflict.&lt;ref name=&quot;A San Francisco Bay Area Progressive Directory&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title= Campaign for Innocent Victims In Conflict (CIVIC) | url=http://www.civicworldwide.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=12&amp;Itemid=41 | publisher= A San Francisco Bay Area Progressive Directory | accessdate= 2010-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Findings==

CIVIC released a report in 2009 on civilian harm in Northwest Pakistan.&lt;ref name=&quot;CIVIC|Campaign for Innocent Victims in Conflict&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title= CIVILIANS IN WAR: PAKISTAN | url=http://www.civicworldwide.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=445&amp;Itemid=202 | publisher= CIVIC|Campaign for Innocent Victims in Conflict | accessdate= 2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was based on a [[United Nations Assistance Mission in Afghanistan]] report that estimated a 40% increase in the number of [[civilian]] deaths in 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Huffington Post&quot;&gt;{{cite news | title= Losing the People: The Cost and Consequences of Civilian Suffering in Afghanistan | url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/erica-gaston/losing-the-people-the-cos_b_170084.html | publisher= The Huffington Post | accessdate= 2010-11-23 | first=Erica | last=Gaston | date=2009-02-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Civic report concludes that civilian harm is compounded by widespread [[poverty]] and that while the Pakistani government does make amends most do not receive any due to deficiencies in compensation mechanisms and no effort from the US.&lt;ref name=&quot;CIVIC|Campaign for Innocent Victims in Conflict&quot;/&gt; Another survey released by an individual associated with CIVIC counted two thousand killed and four thousand injured.&lt;ref name=&quot;IRAQI WAR CASUALTIES&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title= IRAQI CIVILIAN WAR CASUALTIES | url=http://www.civilians.info/ | publisher= IRAQI WAR CASUALTIES | accessdate= 2010-12-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; CIVICs reports suggest that the number of civilians killed and injured in war conflicts exceeds the number that the [[United States]] admits to.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wonders of Pakistan|Blogspot&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title= CIVILIANS IN ARMED CONFLICT: Civilian Harm and Conflict in Northwest Pakistan | url=http://www.civicworldwide.org/storage/civicdev/documents/civic%20pakistan%202010%20final.pdf| publisher= CIVIC| accessdate= 2010-12-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Mandate==

CIVICs goals are to urge warring parties to take responsibility and provide help to civilians they've harmed, to adopt a new international norm dictating recognition and making amends to war victims and to be the voice for war victims. They work to achieve these goals by creating US-funded programs to aid war victims in [[Iraq]] and [[Afghanistan]] and are working with [[NATO]] to develop compensation funds.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Huffington Post&quot;/&gt; They also try to focus media attention onto victims of war and create a wider recognition of war victims among policy-makers. CIVIC actively gathers stories from war victims in an attempt to show the human cost of conflict.

==Accomplishments==

CIVIC partnered with the [[United States armed forces|United States military]] to train [[United States Army|U.S. soldiers]] shipping out to [[Iraq]] and [[Afghanistan]] on avoiding civilians and how to compensate for any harm caused. CIVIC also worked with the [[American Civil Liberties Union]] to analyze civilian claims of damages and craft legislation to address shortfalls in the current system (the Civilian Claims Act). CIVIC successfully pressed the [[North Atlantic Treaty Organization]] member states to develop, fund, and ensure that a [[Trust law|trust fund]] for war victims was in place.{{citation needed|date=December 2010}}

CIVIC provided a military lawyer that worked with [[Harvard University]] to document US efforts to make amends to civilians suffering losses. They also organised for someone living in Afghanistan to help coordinate delivery of aid from NATO and the US to war victims. Over one-third of contributions to CIVIC come from individual contributions.{{citation needed|date=December 2010}}

CIVIC received 10 million dollars from Congress as part of their initiative to advocate and help design a new US program for Pakistani war victims.&lt;ref name=&quot;CIVIC|Campaign for Innocent Victims in Conflict&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title= Accomplishments | url=http://www.civicworldwide.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=18&amp;Itemid=47 | publisher= CIVIC|Campaign for Innocent Victims in Conflict | accessdate= 2010-12-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; CIVIC has conducted interviews with Pakistani and US policymakers, humanitarians and officials from international organizations, and over 160 Pakistani civilians.

==See also==
* [[Marla Ruzicka]]
* [[United Nations Assistance Mission in Afghanistan]]
* [[United Nations]]
* [[War in North-West Pakistan]]
* [[Human rights in Pakistan]]
* [[NATO]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

&lt;references/&gt;

==External links==
*[http://www.civicworldwide.org CIVIC Website]
*[http://www.civilians.info The results of CIVIC's massive campaign in Iraq]

==Note==
#{{note|Guardian}} Rory McCarthy, &quot;Iraq: after the war: Campaigners count bodies to ensure US compensation&quot;, [[The Guardian]] (London), May 17, 2003.

Photographer Julien Bryan described the scene: &quot;As we drove by a small field at the edge of town we were just a few minutes too late to witness a tragic event, the most incredible of all. Seven women had been digging potatoes in a field. There was no flour in their district, and they were desperate for food. Suddenly two German planes appeared from nowhere and dropped two bombs only two hundred yards away on a small home. Two women in the house were killed. The potato diggers dropped flat upon the ground, hoping to be unnoticed. After the bombers had gone, the women returned to their work. They had to have food.

But the Nazi fliers were not satisfied with their work. In a few minutes they came back and swooped down to within two hundred feet of the ground, this time raking the field with machine-gun fire. Two of the seven women were killed. The other five escaped somehow.

While I was photographing the bodies, a little ten-year old girl came running up and stood transfixed by one of the dead. The woman was her older sister. The child had never before seen death and couldn't understand why her sister would not speak to her...

The child looked at us in bewilderment. I threw my arm about her and held her tightly, trying to comfort her. She cried. So did I and the two Polish officers who were with me...&quot; [Source: Bryan, Julien. &quot;Warsaw: 1939 Siege; 1959 Warsaw Revisited.&quot;] 

In September 1959 Julien Bryan wrote more about it in [[:en:Look (American magazine)|''Look'' magazine]]:
:''In the offices of the Express, that child, Kazimiera Mika, now 30, and I were reunited. I asked her if she remembered anything of that tragic day in the potato field. &quot;I should,&quot; she replied quietly. &quot;It was the day I lost my sister, the day I first saw death, and the first time I met a foreigner - you.&quot; Today, Kazimiera is married to a Warsaw streetcar motorman. They have a 12-year-old girl and a boy, 9, and the family lives in a 1{{fraction|1|2}}-room apartment, typical of the overcrowded conditions of war-racked Poland. She is a charwoman at a medical school (she told me her biggest regret is that her education ended when the war began), and all of the $75 earned each month by her husband and herself goes for food. Kazimiera and her husband, like most Poles, supplement their income with odd jobs, and are sometimes forced to sell a piece of furniture for extra money. But they celebrated my visit to their home with that rare treat, a dinner with meat.''

{{DEFAULTSORT:Campaign For Innocent Victims In Conflict}}
[[Category:Activism]]
[[Category:Non-profit organizations based in Washington, D.C.]]

[[pt:Campaign for Innocent Victims in Conflict]]</text>
      <sha1>nqpm2eqcywvsijmzusiccng0bmrpyh8</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
