<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Camp Trans</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1262223</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522083974</id>
      <parentid>515442308</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-08T23:18:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bgwhite</username>
        <id>264323</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Allegations of Violence and Vandalism During 2010 Festivals */[[WP:CHECKWIKI]] error fix #38.  Convert HTML to wikicode.  Do Do [[Wikipedia:GENFIXES|general fixes]] and cleanup if needed using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (8512)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16772">'''Camp Trans''' is an annual demonstration and event held outside the [[Michigan Womyn's Music Festival]] by [[trans women]] and their allies to protest the Festival's policy of excluding trans women from attending.

==Background==
[[Michigan Womyn's Music Festival]] has its roots in [[lesbian feminism|lesbian-feminist]] and [[lesbian separatism|lesbian-separatist]] analysis of [[patriarchy]], and is intended to provide a week-long safe space for attendees to enjoy music created exclusively by [[women]], immerse themselves in woman's culture and celebrate their womanhood in a safe environment without domination, oppression or interference by men. Its primary organizers adhere to a belief that a defining quality of womanhood comes from being born and raised in a female body.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scribd.com/doc/57431453/Festival-Program-MWMF-Mission-Statement-Timeline-August-2005 From MWMF Festival Program (Lisa Vogel, August 2005)]&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
Camp Trans was sparked by a 1991 incident in which a woman named [[Nancy Burkholder]] was ejected from the festival after her transsexual status became known to festival [[security guards]] &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.villagevoice.com/2000-09-12/columns/trouble-in-utopia/ |title=Trouble in Utopia |accessdate=10 January 2009 |publisher= The Village Voice|date=12 September 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the festival has maintained a women-born-women policy since its inception, as evidenced by posters from the first festival in 1975 {{Citation needed|date=September 2007}}, the 1991 incident falsely led to the belief that the policy was only articulated as a means of preventing transsexual women from attending.  Each year afterwards a group of women, both trans and female assigned at birth, protested the exclusion of trans women from the event. Initially these protests were small and sometimes carried on inside of the camp.&lt;ref&gt;[http://groups.google.com/group/soc.motss/msg/4d6c5aa745d61e87?output=gplain  To:  Women Concerned About Transsexual Oppression (April 28, 1993)]&lt;/ref&gt; 

A more organized group of trans women and their allies began camping and holding [[Demonstration (people)|demonstrations]] outside the gate. After a five-year hiatus, Camp Trans returned in 1999, led by transgender activists [[Riki Wilchins|Riki Ann Wilchins]] and [[Leslie Feinberg]], as well as many members of the [[Boston]] and [[Chicago]] [[Lesbian Avengers]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.camp-trans.org/pages/ct-history.html |title=Camp Trans History |accessdate=10 January 2009 |publisher= Camp Trans}}&lt;/ref&gt; The events of this year drew attention and controversy, culminating in tensions as a small group of transgender activists were admitted into the festival to exchange dialogue with organizers and to negotiate a short-lived compromise allowing only [[sex reassignment surgery|post-operative]] trans women on the festival land.&lt;ref&gt;Son of Camp Trans Press Release: Protest Called For Women's Music Festival Discriminatory Policy Still In Effect (June 26, 1999)[http://legalminds.lp.findlaw.com/list/queerlaw-edit/msg03071.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the early 1980s and in 1999, a [[stealth (transgender)|stealth]] transgender musician who had transitioned 10 years earlier did perform in MWMF, and during 1999's Camp Trans event, a number of [[trans women]] purchased tickets and were admitted to [[MWMF]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20081002092021/http://www.confluere.com/store/pdf-zn/mich-handbook.pdf  A Handbook on Discussing The Michigan Womyn's Music Festival For Trans Activists and Allies (Koyama, Emi: Portland: Confluere, 2003: 28-36)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://intermargins.net/repression/deviant/transgender/trans_book/mich-handbook.pdf  Active link for Koyama 2003 handbook]&lt;/ref&gt; A similar claim of victory was published by Camp Trans that year.&lt;ref&gt;Son of Camp Trans Press Release: Protest Called For Women's Music Festival
Discriminatory Policy Still In Effect (June 26, 1999) [http://legalminds.lp.findlaw.com/list/queerlaw-edit/msg03071.html]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://community.livejournal.com/wbw_is_bullshit/7865.html  Camp Trans Needs Us! (August 26, 2006)]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Events of 2006 ==
By 2005, activists at Camp Trans and MWMF had become frustrated with the boycott effort and felt that a combined effort of external and internal activism on the grounds of MWMF might be more effective in securing inclusion.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scribd.com/doc/57432037/Festival-Program-Camp-Trans-Information-August-2005 Camp Trans Festival Program (August 2005)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scribd.com/doc/57434110/Camp-Trans-Trans-Inclusion-Festival-Attendee-Info-Sheet-August-2005 Camp Trans &amp; Yellow Armbands Info. Sheet (August 2005)]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2006, a trans woman organizer of Camp Trans named [[Lorrraine Donaldson]] was sold a ticket to the 31st annual Michigan Womyn's Music Festival.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scribd.com/doc/58594439/Festival-Program-Camp-Trans-August-2006 Camp Trans Festival Program (August 2006)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scribd.com/doc/57420131/News-Is-the-Michigan-Debate-Over-Curve-Magazine-07-2007 Is The Michigan Debate Over? (July 2007)]&lt;/ref&gt; On Tuesday, August 8, 2006, Donaldson approached the workers at the front gate of the festival and asked if she could purchase a ticket. She was instructed to read an outdated handout that was printed by the festival office in 2000 following the controversial events surrounding the Michigan 8 protest.&lt;ref&gt;'Michigan Eight' Evicted Over Festival's New 'Don't Ask, Don't Tell' (August 12, 2000) [http://eminism.org/michigan/20000812-camptrans.txt]&lt;/ref&gt; This paper indicated that the festival was still enforcing a policy of exclusion for transsexual women. When Donaldson pointed out that the document was outdated and asked for a current version from the workers, they told her that none was available. Donaldson requested that the workers seek up-to-date policy information in writing from the office and informed them that she would return the next morning. That same day, the newly organized Yellow Armbands pro-inclusion support group held their first meeting at the Watermelon Tree in the common dining area of the festival. 

On the morning of Wednesday, August 9, Donaldson again approached the box office workers near the front gate and asked to purchase a ticket.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scribd.com/doc/57420131/News-Is-the-Michigan-Debate-Over-Curve-Magazine-07-2007 Curve Magazine – Is The Michigan Debate Over? (July 2007)]&lt;/ref&gt; She was met at the gate by three members of the Yellow Armbands and one organizer of Camp Trans, all of whom witnessed Donaldson disclosing her trans status to the box office manager, before being sold a ticket and given an orange wristband that designated her as a &quot;festie&quot;.  Donaldson attended the festival for the remainder of the week and participated at a trans inclusion workshop that was presented by trans woman Emilia Lombardi, who was also an organizer with Camp Trans and who was  sold a ticket to the festival on Friday, August 11, as well.  The workshop was listed as part of the official festival program and both Donaldson and Lombardi were open about being trans women at the workshop that was attended by over 50 people.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scribd.com/doc/57433853/Festival-Program-MWMF-featuring-Trans-Inclusion-Discussion-August-2006 From MWMF 2006 festival program (Lisa Vogel, August 2006)]&lt;/ref&gt; Donaldson and Lombardi also continued to join the Yellow Armbands mealtime gatherings, where they were met with support from festies and workers. The conclusion of the 2006 festivals in Hart, Michigan was marked with noted optimism and collaborative spirit between Camp Trans constituents and their pro-inclusion supporters at MWMF, as was noted immediately by members of the community and media.&lt;ref&gt;[http://dykestowatchoutfor.com/episode-495 Dykes To Watch Out For (09-19-06)]&lt;/ref&gt; A camper also captured the good news as it was presented onstage by a Camp Trans committee member and later posted it on [[YouTube]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KtJ_syB5Gq4 Camp Trans - Saturday Night Video Speech (August 19, 2006)]&lt;/ref&gt;

== 2006 press release controversy and resulting organizational changes==
Following the 2006 festival, a small group of Camp Trans organizers issued a [[press release]] that stated that the MWMF had &quot;ended its policy of exclusion.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scribd.com/doc/57420131/News-Is-the-Michigan-Debate-Over-Curve-Magazine-07-2007 Is The Michigan Debate Over? (July 2007)]&lt;/ref&gt; A disagreement ensued within the Camp Trans and Yellow Armbands organizations over whether or not this press release was ethical due to issues of transparency and consent.&lt;ref&gt;[http://community.livejournal.com/camptrans/18945.html  Let's Everybody Take A Deep Breath (September 20, 2006)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scribd.com/doc/57421336/Email-Lina-Corvus-Conversation-with-Lorraine-Donaldson-on-AOL-IM-regarding-fall-out-from-2006-press-releases-09-18-06 Lorraine Donaldson and Lina Corvus Conversation (September 18, 2006)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scribd.com/doc/57429484/Blog-Former-organizer-of-Camp-Trans-Sean-admits-no-elections-occurred-at-Camp-Trans-prior-to-2007-04-08-07 Hard Questions (04-08-07)]&lt;/ref&gt;

Camp Trans argued that the press release was a deliberate and necessary tactic designed to bait Vogel into responding with a transphobic press release which would make the parameters of the &quot;wbw-policy&quot; officially known.  Supporters of this tactic felt that because Vogel hadn't given the Camp Trans organization permission to republish the letter, nor was the policy (or what Vogel referred to as an &quot;intention&quot;) available in writing on the MichFest website or elsewhere, that this was the only way that Camp Trans could ostensibly prove that the policy actually existed. Others felt that the motivation behind the press release was nebulous and not supportive or inclusive of Donaldson or others who were involved in the positive developments that occurred in the summer of 2006. They also believed that the press release caused unnecessary conflict between inclusion activists and the festival office and they preferred to focus on the larger community who were clearly supportive of trans women attending in 2006.  Regardless, Vogel did in fact issue a response where she stated again that the festival is intended for women-born-women, and that they hope and expect trans women to respect that intention.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scribd.com/doc/57422924/Press-Release-Michigan-Womyn-s-Music-Festival-Sets-The-Record-Straight-08-22-06 MWMF Press Release: Michigan Womyn's Music Festival Sets The Record Straight (August 22, 2006)]&lt;/ref&gt; Following the press release fallout, Donaldson resigned from Camp Trans and joined the Yellow Armbands as an organizer.&lt;ref&gt;[http://community.livejournal.com/camptrans/17743.html  Transitioning Organizational Roles (August 25, 2006)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://community.livejournal.com/camptrans/18668.html  Message In A Bottle (To CT07 Organizers) (September 18, 2006)]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, the Yellow Armbands blog was frozen by an organizer who resigned from the activism due to lingering issues regarding lack of transparency in the inclusion movement.&lt;ref&gt;[http://community.livejournal.com/yellowarmbands/2007/05/28/ Farewell (May 28, 2007)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scribd.com/doc/57424801/AOL-IM-Conversation-Dandypants-announces-her-resignation-from-the-Yellow-Armbands-05-27-07 dandypants resignation dialog between Yellow Armbands organizers (May 27, 2007)]&lt;/ref&gt; Other activists also resigned over concerns that Camp Trans was privileging the voices of trans men over trans women in their organization. The remaining inclusion activists at Yellow Armbands created a new online community and blog and renamed their organization Fest For All Womyn.&lt;ref&gt;[http://community.livejournal.com/festforallwomyn/profile  Fest For All Womyn Community on LiveJournal]&lt;/ref&gt;

Donaldson returned to MWMF in 2007 with the newly renamed Fest For All Womyn/Yellow Armbands and camped in The Twilight Zone area of the festival along with other trans women and female assigned at birth inclusion supporters.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scribd.com/doc/57420131/News-Is-the-Michigan-Debate-Over-Curve-Magazine-07-2007 Is The Michigan Debate Over? (July 2007)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://community.livejournal.com/festforallwomyn/2927.html#cutid1  On Boycotts (July 23, 2007)]&lt;/ref&gt;   

2007 was also a landmark year for Camp Trans, because for the first time in their 16-year history, they held elections for their organizational positions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://community.livejournal.com/camptrans/20833.html Camp Trans 2007 Organization Update (April 16, 2007)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scribd.com/doc/57429484/Blog-Former-organizer-of-Camp-Trans-Sean-admits-no-elections-occurred-at-Camp-Trans-prior-to-2007-04-08-07 Hard Questions (04-08-07)]&lt;/ref&gt; Camp Trans organizers celebrated this as a positive step in the right direction when the majority of elected positions were filled by trans women.

== Allegations of Violence and Vandalism During 2010 Festivals ==

According to an online news site, Anarchist News, there were several incidents of violence and vandalism during the 2010 festivals.&lt;ref&gt;[http://anarchistnews.org/?q=node/11968 Let The Trans Women Speak! Anarchist News Online (August 12, 2010)&lt;/ref&gt; A printed version of the statements found at Anarchist News, as well as further details regarding the incidents  was first published by Pink and Black Attack in early September 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://zinelibrary.info/pink-and-black-attack-6 Pink and Black Attack #6 (September 2, 2010)]&lt;/ref&gt; A confrontation ensued between attendees of Camp Trans and a tow-truck driver near the gates of MichFest during a reading of the history of Camp Trans.&lt;ref&gt;[http://notyrcisterpress.tumblr.com/post/1408829853/let-trans-women-speak-a-response-to-camp-trans Let Trans Women Speak: A Response to Camp Trans; Not Yr Sister Press (October 26, 2010)]&lt;/ref&gt;  

In the Pink and Black #6 zine issue, the publishers included the following description of the vandalism left at one of the Michigan kitchens: 

''&quot;August 7. Hart , MI: Vandalism at Michfest
This year at MichFest, the words “Real Womyn Have Cocks” were painted on the MichFest kitchen and other damage was allegedly done to MichFest property. A flyer was distributed with the following text: 'Second-Wave ‘Feminists’, A hot load from my monstrous tranny-cock embodies womanhood more than the pieces of menstral (sic) art your transphobic cunts could ever hope to create. Love, Womyn-born-Monsters&quot;''

Despite these unofficial statements, neither the MichFest office nor the Camp Trans organization has confirmed the veracity of these accounts, nor whether the vandalism occurred at the worker or main kitchen. Although workshops were allegedly held to resolve the matter, no one has specified whether or not Lisa Vogel made an official response. 

A thread from the MichFest bulletin board created on August 9, 2011 contains statements from numerous long time MichFest attendees and workers, who confirmed that trans women attended the festival in 2011.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.michfest.com/forums/viewtopic.php?f=9&amp;t=7024 Many Thanks to The Trans Women Belong Here Group (August 9, 2011)]&lt;/ref&gt; There has been no comment from Camp Trans in regards to their attendance or participation in the 2011 festival.

==As of 2012==
Camp Trans doesn't exist.
As seen above, Camp Trans was a protest. The goal of that protest was to educate and gain access for trans women to Michfest. The struggle continues, as Michfest continues to exclude many trans women, and has not issued a statement retracting their transmisogynist policies. There have been groups created &quot;on the land&quot; like [http://transwomenbelonghere.blogspot.com/ Trans Women Belong Here] for support, care, and acquiring space within fest that is a &quot;safer space&quot;.

==See also==
*[[Transphobia]]
*[[Michigan Womyn's Music Festival]]
*[[List of transgender-related topics]]
*[[Lesbian Avengers]]
*[[Sexism]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.camp-trans.org/ Official Camp Trans site]
*[http://eminism.org/michigan/faq-protest.html Detailed History of Camp Trans from 1991 to 2000]
*[http://www.scribd.com/collections/3039294/ Trans Inclusion Archive of MWMF, Camp Trans and The Yellow Armbands (1991-2011)]
*[http://community.livejournal.com/yellowarmbands Yellow Armbands Trans-Inclusion Activism Community Blog on Livejournal from 2004 to 2008]

[[Category:Feminism and transgender topics]]
[[Category:LGBT rights movement]]
[[Category:Michigan culture]]
[[Category:Transgender events]]
[[Category:Transgender in the United States]]
[[Category:Transgender rights]]
[[Category:LGBT history in the United States]]
[[Category:Protests in the United States]]
[[Category:LGBT in Michigan]]</text>
      <sha1>1t4j5966xdqy7nxre06zz4wh6ycwwtk</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
