<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Center for Biological Diversity</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8991651</id>
    <revision>
      <id>514058791</id>
      <parentid>514058182</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-22T19:25:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>68.228.44.114</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>fixed abbreviation, minor clarifications</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6901">{{Infobox organization
|name         = Center for Biological Diversity
|image        = Center for Biological Diversity logo.jpg
|image_border = 
|size         = &lt;!-- default 200 --&gt;
|alt          = &lt;!-- alt text; see [[WP:ALT]] --&gt;
|caption      = 
|abbreviation = The Center
|motto        = 
|formation    = 1989
|type         = [[Non-governmental organization|NGO]]
|status       = &lt;!-- ad hoc, treaty, foundation, etc --&gt;
|purpose      = Protection of [[endangered species]]
|headquarters = [[Tucson]], [[Arizona]]
|location     = 
|coords       = &lt;!-- Coordinates of location using a coordinates template --&gt;
|region_served =
|membership   = 
|language     = &lt;!-- official languages --&gt;
|leader_title = &lt;!-- position title for the leader of the org --&gt;
|leader_name  = &lt;!-- name of leader --&gt;
|main_organ   = &lt;!-- gral. assembly, board of directors, etc --&gt;
|parent_organization = &lt;!-- if one --&gt;
|affiliations = &lt;!-- if any --&gt;
|num_staff    = 
|num_volunteers =
|website      = [http://biologicaldiversity.org/ biologicaldiversity.org]
}}
The '''Center for Biological Diversity''' (Center) based in [[Tucson]], [[Arizona]], is a nonprofit membership organization with approximately 220,000 members and online activists, known for its work protecting [[endangered species]] through legal action and scientific petitions.  The Center has offices and staff in [[New Mexico]], [[Arizona]], [[Nevada]], [[California]], [[Oregon]], [[Illinois]], [[Minnesota]], [[Alaska]], [[Vermont]] and [[Washington, D.C.]] It was founded in 1989 by Kieran Suckling, Peter Galvin, Todd Schulke, and Robin Silver.&lt;ref name=about /&gt;

==Background==
Given a small grant by the [[Fund for Wild Nature]], the organization started in 1989 as a small group by the name of ''Greater Gila Biodiversity Project'', with the objective to protect endangered species and critical habitat in the southwest.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fundwildnature.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=3&amp;Itemid=4 |title=Success Stories |publisher=Fundwildnature.org |date= |accessdate=2010-09-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; The organization later grew and became the Center for Biological Diversity. Kieran Suckling, Peter Galvin, and Todd Schulke founded the organization in response to what they perceived as a failure on the part of the [[United States Forest Service]] to protect imperiled species from logging, grazing, and mining. As surveyors in New Mexico, the three men discovered &quot;a rare [[Mexican Spotted Owl]] nest in an old-growth tree&quot;,&lt;ref name=about&gt;[http://www.biologicaldiversity.org/about/story/index.html Our Story] Center for Biological Diversity - May 10, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt; but their discovery was overshadowed by Forest Service plans to lease the land to timber companies; Suckling, Galvin, and Schulke believed that it was within the Forest Service’s mission to save sensitive species like the Mexican Spotted Owl from harm, and that the government had shirked its duty in deference to corporate interests.

Suckling, Galvin, and Schulke went to the media to register their outrage; the old-growth tree was allowed to stand, and this success led to the founding of the Center for Biological Diversity. 

Initially, the Center focused on issues specific to the [[Southwestern United States]], but today its mission encompasses far-reaching problems such as global threats to biological diversity and climate change. The Center employs a group of paid and [[pro bono]] attorneys to use litigation to effect change, and claims a 93 percent success rate for their lawsuits.&lt;ref name=about /&gt;

==Press==
On 13 June 2007, the Center spoke out against a [[George W. Bush administration|Bush administration]] proposal to reduce the protected area for [[spotted owl]]s in the [[United States]] [[Pacific Northwest]]. According to Noah Greenwald, the group's representative in the Northwest, the proposed habitat cut is &quot;typical of an administration that is looking to reduce protections for endangered species at every turn.&quot; Greenwald said that the rollback is part of a series of &quot;sweetheart deals,&quot; in which the administration settles an environmental lawsuit out of court and, &quot;at the industry's wishes, reduces the critical habitat.&quot; According to the Center, the move conforms to a broad trend that includes at least 25 earlier Bush administration decisions on habitat protections for [[endangered species]]. In those cases, the protected areas were reduced an average of 36 percent.&lt;ref name=epi&gt;[http://www.seattlepi.com/local/319483_owl13.html Bush administration wants cut in protection for spotted owl: Proposal would trim preserved habitat]&lt;/ref&gt;

On 16 December 2008, the Center announced intent to sue the United States government for introducing &quot;regulations... that would eviscerate our nation’s most successful wildlife law by exempting thousands of federal activities, including those that generate greenhouse gases, from review under the Endangered Species Act.&quot; The lawsuit, which is critical of [[United States Department of the Interior|U.S. Interior Department]] [[Dirk Kempthorne|Secretary Dirk Kempthorne]] and President [[George W. Bush]], was filed in the Northern District of California by the Center, [[Greenpeace]] and [[Defenders of Wildlife]]. According to the Center, &quot;The lawsuit argues that the regulations violate the Endangered Species Act and did not go through the required public review process. The regulations, first proposed on August 11th, were rushed by the Bush administration through an abbreviated process in which more than 300,000 comments from the public were reviewed in 2-3 weeks, and environmental impacts were analyzed in a short and cursory environmental assessment, rather than a fuller environmental impact statement.&quot;&lt;ref name=esalawsuit&gt;[http://www.biologicaldiversity.org/news/press_releases/2008/endangered-species-regulations-12-16-2008.html Bush Administration Regulations Gutting Protections for Nation's Endangered Species Published Today - Conservation Groups' Challenge to 11th Hour Reductions in Protections for Nation’s Wildlife Moves ForwarD]&lt;/ref&gt;

August 26, 2009 letter with [http://www.foe.org/letter-senator-boxer  300+ Groups Ask Senate for Stronger Climate Bill], included the Center.

==See also==
* [[Environmental journalism]]
* [[List of environment topics]]
* [[Wildlife conservation]]
* [[Wildlife management]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://biologicaldiversity.org Center for Biological Diversity website]
* [http://publicservice.evendon.com/CenterBioDiv_v_DOIM.htm Center for Biological Diversity v Dept of the Interior] 17Apr2009 DC Appellate Decision stopping offshore Alaska Oil Leases.

[[Category:Environmental organizations based in the United States]]
[[Category:Organizations established in 1989]]
[[Category:Conservation in the United States]]
[[Category:Biodiversity]]

[[ja:生物多様性センター (アメリカ)]]</text>
      <sha1>r1bkqzs7dd6r0yzod77wlwzxibfb6m0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
