<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Chandragupta Maurya</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>187726</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521685005</id>
      <parentid>521505815</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-06T16:12:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sitush</username>
        <id>4782151</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted [[WP:AGF|good faith]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/Kempcoach|Kempcoach]] ([[User talk:Kempcoach|talk]]): These are not minor edits. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="31091">{{Infobox monarch
| name = Chhatrapati Chandragupta Maurya
| title =Samraat (Emperor)
| image =
| caption =
| reign =320–298 BCE
| religion = [[Jain]], gave up his throne and became a Jain monk
| coronation =
| othertitles = [[Samraat]] [[Chakravartin]]
| full name =
| predecessor = Dhanananda of [[Nanda Dynasty]]
| successor =[[Bindusara]]
| consort = Durdhara
| issue =
| royal house = [[Mauryan dynasty]]
| father =
| mother =Mura
| brothers =
|birth_date = 340 BCE
|birth_place = [[Pataliputra|Pataliputra (Patna)]], [[Bihar, India]]
|death_date = 298 BCE (aged 42)
|death_place = [[Shravanabelagola|Sravana Belgola]], [[Karnataka, India]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=i-y6ZUheQH8C&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Chandragupta Maurya and his times] By Radha Kumud Mookerji, 4th ed. 1966, p.40.  ISBN 81-208-0405-8; 81-208-0433-3&lt;/ref&gt;
|date of burial =
|place of burial =
|}}
'''Chandragupta Maurya''' ({{lang-sa|चन्द्रगुप्त मौर्यः}}), (born c. 340 BCE, ruled c. 320 BCE,&lt;ref name=Kulke&gt;{{cite book | last = Kulke | first = Hermann | coauthors = Rothermund, Dietmar | title = A History of India | origyear = 1986 | edition = Third | year = 1998 | publisher = Routledge | location = London | isbn = 0-415-15481-2 | pages = 59}}&lt;/ref&gt; – 298 BCE&lt;ref&gt;Kulke and Rothermund 1998:62&lt;/ref&gt;) was the founder of the [[Maurya Empire]]. He succeeded in conquering almost all of the [[Indian subcontinent]] and is considered the first unifier of India as well as its first genuine emperor.&lt;ref name=Boesche&gt;{{cite journal | first = Roger | last = Boesche | year = 2003 | month = January | title = Kautilya's ''Arthaśāstra'' on War and Diplomacy in Ancient India | journal = The Journal of Military History | volume = 67 | issue = 1 | pages = 9–37 | doi = 10.1353/jmh.2003.0006 | url=http://muse.jhu.edu/demo/journal_of_military_history/v067/67.1boesche.pdf | issn = 0899-3718}}&lt;/ref&gt; In foreign [[Greek language|Greek]] and [[Latin]] accounts, Chandragupta is known as '''Sandrokyptos''' (''Σανδρόκυπτος''), '''Sandrokottos'''  (''Σανδρόκοττος'') or '''Androcottus'''.&lt;ref&gt;[[William Smith (lexicographer)|William Smith]] (ed), ''[[Dictionary of Greek and Roman Biography and Mythology]]'', 1870, [http://www.ancientlibrary.com/smith-bio/3038.html Vol 3 p. 705-6]&lt;/ref&gt;

Prior to Chandragupta's consolidation of power, small regional kingdoms dominated the northwestern subcontinent, while the [[Nanda Dynasty]] dominated the middle and lower basin of the [[Ganges]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Shastri | first = Nilakantha |title = Age of the Nandas and Mauryas | year = 1967 | publisher = Motilal Banarsidass | location = Delhi | isbn = 81-208-0465-1 | page = 26 | unused_data = Second Edition }}&lt;/ref&gt; After Chandragupta's conquests, the Maurya Empire extended from [[Bengal]] and [[Assam]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Vaughn | first1 = Bruce | year = 2004 | title = Indian Geopolitics, the United States and Evolving Correlates of Power in Asia | url = | journal = Geopolitics | volume = 9 | issue = 2| pages = 440–459 [442] | doi = 10.1080/14650040490442944 }}&lt;/ref&gt; in the east, to [[Afghanistan]] and [[Balochistan (region)|Balochistan]],some part of the eastern and south-east [[Iran]] in the west, to [[Kashmir]] and [[Nepal]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Goetz | first1 = H. | year = 1955 | title = Early Indian Sculptures from Nepal | url = | journal = Artibus Asiae | volume = 18 | issue = 1| pages = 61–74 | doi = 10.2307/3248838 }}&lt;/ref&gt; in the north, and to the [[Deccan Plateau]] in the south.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kamat.com/kalranga/ancient/maurya.htm The Span of the Mauryan Empire], [http://www.kamat.com/index.htm Kamat's Potpurri], accessed 9 September 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

Tradition holds that Chandragupta abdicated his throne to become a [[Digambara]] Jain monk and led such an ascetic life that he starved himself to death. He was succeeded by his son [[Bindusara]] in 298 BC.

Chandragupta's achievements, which ranged from conquering Macedonian [[satrap]]ies in the northwest and conquering the [[Nanda Empire]] by the time he was only about 20 years old, to achieving an alliance with [[Seleucus I Nicator]] and establishing centralized rule throughout the [[Indian Subcontinent]], remain some of the most celebrated in the [[history of India]]. Over two thousand years later, the accomplishments of Chandragupta stand out in the [[history of India]].

==Origins==
{{See|Ancestry of Chandragupta  Maurya}}
Many Indian literary traditions connect him with the [[Nanda Dynasty]] of [[Magadha]] in modern day [[Bihar]] in eastern India. More than half a millennium later, the [[Sanskrit]] drama [[Mudrarakshasa]] calls him a &quot;Nandanvaya&quot; i.e. the descendant of Nanda (Act IV). Again more than a millennium later, Dhundiraja, a commentator of 18th century on Mudrarakshasa states that Chandragupta was the son of the Nanda king Sarvarthasiddhi by a wife named Mura, daughter of a Vrishala ([[Shudra]]). Mudrarakshasa uses terms like ''kula-hina'' and ''Vrishala'' for Chandragupta's lineage. This reinforces [[Junianus Justinus|Justin]]'s contention that Chandragupta had a humble origin.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;He (Seleucus) next made an expedition into India, which, after the death of Alexander, had shaken, as it were, the yoke of servitude from its neck, and put his governors to death. The author of this liberation was Sandrocottus, who afterwards, however, turned their semblance of liberty into slavery; for, making himself king, he oppressed the people whom he had delivered from a foreign power, with a cruel tyranny. This man was of mean origin, but was stimulated to aspire to regal power by supernatural encouragement; for, having offended Alexander by his boldness of speech, and orders being given to kill him, he saved himself by swiftness of foot; and while he was lying asleep, after his fatigue, a lion of great size having come up to him, licked off with his tongue the sweat that was running from him, and after gently waking him, left him. Being first prompted by this prodigy to conceive hopes of royal dignity, he drew together a band of robbers, and solicited the Indians to support his new sovereignty. Some time after, as he was going to war with the generals of Alexander, a wild elephant of great bulk presented itself before him of its own accord, and, as if tamed down to gentleness, took him on its back, and became his guide in the war, and conspicuous in fields of battle. Sandrocottus, having thus acquired a throne, was in possession of India&quot; ([http://www.forumromanum.org/literature/justin/english/trans15.html Justin &quot;Epitome of the Philippic History&quot; XV-4])&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;There is a controversy about Justin's account. Justin actually refers to a name ''Nandrum'', which many scholars believe is reference to Nanda (Dhana Nanda of Magadha), while others say that it refers to ''Alexandrum'', i.e., Alexander. It makes some difference which version one believes&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, the same play describes the Nandas as of Prathita-kula, i.e. illustrious, lineage. The medieval commentator on the [[Vishnu Purana]] informs us that Chandragupta was the son of a [[Nanda dynasty|Nanda]] prince and a {{lang-hi|''dasi''}} ({{lang-en|maid}}) named Mura. The poets [[Kshmendra]] and [[Somadeva]] call him Purvananda-suta, son of the genuine Nanda, as opposed to Yoga-Nanda, i.e. pseudo-Nanda. The Nanda dynasty was started by [[Mahapadma Nanda]], who is considered the first [[Shudra]] king of [[Magadha]].

The Buddhist text the [[Mahavamsa]] calls Chandragupt a member of a division of the Khattiya ([[Kshatriya]]) clan called the Moriya (Maurya). [[Divyāvadāna]] calls Bindusara, son of Chandragupt, an anointed Kshatriya, Kshatriya Murdhabhishikata, and in the same work King [[Ashoka]], son of Bindusara, is also styled a Kshatriya. The [[Mahaparinibbana Sutta]] states that the Moriyas (Mauryas) belonged to the Kshatriya community of Pippalivana. These traditions indicate that Chandragupt came from a Kshatriya lineage. The ''Mahavamshatika'' connects him with the [[Shakya]] clan of the Buddha, a clan which also belongs to the race of [[Ādityas]].

A medieval inscription represents the Maurya clan as belonging to the solar race of Kshatriyas. It is stated that the Maurya line sprang from Suryavamsi Mandhatri, son of prince Yuvanashva of the solar race.{{Citation needed|date=August 2012}}
chandragupt was a student of chankya.

==Early life==
Very little is known about Chandragupt's youth.  What is known is gathered from later classical [[Sanskrit literature]], as well as classical [[Greek language|Greek]] and [[Latin]] sources which refer to Chandragupta by the names &quot;Sandracottos&quot; or &quot;Andracottus&quot;. 

[[Plutarch]] reports that he met with [[Alexander the Great]], probably around [[Takshasila]] in the northwest, and that he viewed the ruling [[Nanda Dynasty|Nanda Empire]] in a negative light:

{{quote|text=Androcottus, when he was a stripling, saw Alexander himself, and we are told that he often said in later times that Alexander narrowly missed making himself master of the country, since its king was hated and despised on account of his baseness and low birth.|sign=&lt;small&gt;[[Plutarch]]&lt;/small&gt;|source=''[[Parallel Lives]]: Life of Alexander'' [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Plutarch/Lives/Alexander*/9.html#62.9 62.9]}}

According to this text, the encounter would have happened around 326 BCE, suggesting a birth date for Chandragupta around 340 BCE. Plutarch and other Greco-Roman historians appreciated the gravity of Chandragupta Maurya's conquests.
[[Junianus Justinus]] (Justin) describes the humble origins of Chandragupta, and explains how he later led a popular uprising against the Nanda king.

==Foundation of the Maurya Empire==
{{See|Magadha|Maurya Empire}}
[[Image:MauryanCoin.JPG|thumb|left|278px|Silver punch mark coin of the [[Maurya empire]], with symbols of wheel and elephant. 3rd century BCE.]]
Chandragupt Maurya, with the help of Chanakya, defeated the Magadha kings and the army of the Chandravanshi clan. Following his victory, the defeated generals of Alexander settled in Gandhara (the [[Kambojas|Kamboja]] kingdom), today's [[Afghanistan]]. At the time of [[Alexander the Great|Alexander]]'s invasion, [[Chanakya]] was a teacher in [[Takshasila]]. The king of [[Takshasila]] and [[Gandhara]], [[Taxiles|Ambhi]] (also known as Taxiles), made a peace treaty with Alexander. Chanakya, however, planned to defeat the foreign invasion and sought help from other kings to unite and fight Alexander. Parvateshwara ([[King Porus|Porus]]), a king of [[Punjab region|Punjab]], was the only local king who was able to challenge Alexander at the [[Battle of the Hydaspes River]], but he was defeated.

Chanakya then went further east to [[Magadha]], to seek the help of Dhana Nanda, who ruled the vast [[Nanda Dynasty|Nanda Empire]] which extended from [[Bihar]] and [[Bengal]] in the east to [[Punjab region|Punjab]] and [[Sindh]] in the west,&lt;ref name=Mookerji/&gt; but Dhana Nanda refused to help him. After this incident, Chanakya began to persuade his disciple Chandragupta of the need to build an empire that could protect Indian territories from foreign invasion. It is also said that Chandragupta was sent to Greece{{Citation needed|date=October 2012}} in Europe by Chanakya to receive military and war training{{Disambiguation needed|date=October 2012}}.

===Nanda army===
[[Image:Nanda Empire.gif|thumb|200px|left| The [[Nanda Dynasty|Nanda Empire]] at its greatest extent under Dhana Nanda ''circa'' 323 BCE.]]
{{Main|Nanda Dynasty}}
According to [[Plutarch]], at the time of the [[Battle of the Hydaspes River]], the Nanda Empire's army numbered 200,000 [[infantry]], 80,000 [[cavalry]], 8,000 [[chariot]]s, and 7,000 [[war elephant]]s, which discouraged Alexander's men and prevented their further progress into India:

{{cquote|&quot;As for the Macedonians, however, their struggle with [[King Porus|Porus]] blunted their courage and stayed their further advance into India. For having had all they could do to repulse an enemy who mustered only twenty thousand infantry and two thousand horse, they violently opposed Alexander when he insisted on crossing the river Ganges also, the width of which, as they learned, was thirty-two furlongs, its depth a hundred fathoms, while its banks on the further side were covered with multitudes of men-at‑arms and horsemen and elephants. For they were told that the kings of the Ganderites and Praesii were awaiting them with eighty thousand horsemen, two hundred thousand footmen, eight thousand chariots, and six thousand fighting elephants. And there was no boasting in these reports. For Androcottus, who reigned there not long afterwards, made a present to Seleucus of five hundred elephants, and with an army of six hundred thousand men overran and subdued all India.&quot;  |20px|20px|[[Plutarch]]|''[[Parallel Lives]]'', &quot;Life of Alexander&quot; [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Plutarch/Lives/Alexander*/9.html#62 62.1-4]}}

In order to defeat the powerful Nanda army, Chandragupta needed to raise a formidable army of his own.&lt;ref name=Mookerji&gt;Radha Kumud Mookerji, ''Chandragupta Maurya and His Times'', 4th ed. (Delhi: Motilal Banarsidass, 1988 [1966]), pp. 31, 28–33.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Conquest of the Nanda Empire===
{{See|Nanda Dynasty}}
{{Main|Nanda War}}
[[Image:Chandragupta Empire 320 BC.gif|thumb|250px|Chandragupta's empire when he founded it c. 320 BCE, by the time he was about 20 years old.]]
Chanakya had trained and guided Chandragupta and together they planned the destruction of Dhana Nanda. The ''[[Mudrarakshasa]]'' of Visakhadutta as well as the [[Jain]] work ''Parisishtaparvan'' talk of Chandragupta's alliance with the Himalayan king Parvatka, sometimes identified with [[King Porus|Porus]].&lt;ref&gt;John Marshall ''Taxila'', p. 18, and al.&lt;/ref&gt;

It is noted in the ''Chandraguptakatha'' that Chandragupta and Chanakya were initially rebuffed by the Nanda forces. Regardless, in the ensuing war, Chandragupta faced off against Bhadrasala, the commander of Dhana Nanda's armies. He was eventually able to defeat Bhadrasala and Dhana Nanda in a series of battles, culminating in the siege of the capital city [[Pataliputra]]&lt;ref name=Mookerji/&gt; and the conquest of the Nanda Empire around 321 BCE,&lt;ref name=Mookerji/&gt; thus founding the powerful Maurya Empire in Northern India by the time he was about 20 years old.

===Conquest of Macedonian territories in India===
{{Main|Seleucid–Mauryan war}}
[[Image:EasternSatrapsAfterAlexander.jpg|thumb|250px|left|Chandragupta had defeated the remaining [[Macedon]]ian [[satrap]]ies in the northwest of the Indian subcontinent by 317 BCE.]]
After Alexander's death in 323 BCE, Chandragupta, turned his attention to Northwestern India (modern [[Pakistan]]), where he defeated the [[satrap]]ies (described as &quot;prefects&quot; in classical Western sources) left in place by Alexander (according to Justin), and may have [[assassination|assassinated]] two of his governors, [[Nicanor]] and [[Philip_(son_of_Machatas)|Philip]].{{Disambiguation needed|date=July 2011}}&lt;ref name=Boesche/&gt;&lt;ref name=Mookerji/&gt; The satrapies he fought may have included [[Eudemus (general)|Eudemus]], ruler in western Punjab until his departure in 317 BCE; and [[Peithon, son of Agenor]], ruler of the Greek colonies along the [[Indus River|Indus]] until his departure for [[Babylon]] in 316 BCE. The Roman historian [[Junianus Justinus|Justin]] described how Sandrocottus ([[Greek language|Greek]] version of Chandragupta's name) conquered the northwest:

{{cquote|&quot;Some time after, as he was going to war with the generals of Alexander, a wild elephant of great bulk presented itself before him of its own accord, and, as if tamed down to gentleness, took him on its back, and became his guide in the war, and conspicuous in fields of battle. Sandrocottus, having thus acquired a throne, was in possession of India, when Seleucus was laying the foundations of his future greatness; who, after making a league with him, and settling his affairs in the east, proceeded to join in the war against Antigonus. As soon as the forces, therefore, of all the confederates were united, a battle was fought, in which Antigonus was slain, and his son Demetrius put to flight. &quot;|20px|20px|[[Junianus Justinus]]|''Historiarum Philippicarum libri XLIV'', [http://www.forumromanum.org/literature/justin/english/trans15.html XV.4.19]}}

==Expansion==
By the time he was only about 20 years old, Chandragupta, who had succeeded in defeating the Macedonian satrapies in India and conquering the Nanda Empire, had founded a vast empire that extended from the [[Bay of Bengal]] in the east, to the [[Indus River]] in the west. In later years he would expand this empire.

===Conquest of Seleucus' eastern territories===
[[Image:SeleucosCoin.jpg|thumb|Silver coin of [[Seleucus I Nicator]], who fought Chandragupta Maurya, and later made an alliance with him.]]
[[Image:Chandragupta mauryan empire 305 BC.gif|thumb|250px|Chandragupta extended the borders of his empire towards [[Seleucid Empire|Seleucid]] [[History of Iran|Persia]] after his conflict with [[Seleucus I Nicator|Seleucus]] c. 305 BCE.]]
[[Seleucus I Nicator]], a Macedonian [[satrap]] of Alexander, reconquered most of Alexander's former empire and put under his own authority the eastern territories as far as [[Bactria]] and the Indus ([[Appian]], History of Rome, The Syrian Wars 55), until in 305 BCE he entered into conflict with Chandragupta:

{{quote|text=Always lying in wait for the neighboring nations, strong in arms and persuasive in council, he acquired Mesopotamia, Armenia, 'Seleucid' Cappadocia, Persis, Parthia, Bactria, Arabia, Tapouria, Sogdia, Arachosia, Hyrcania, and other adjacent peoples that had been subdued by Alexander, as far as the river Indus, so that the boundaries of his empire were the most extensive in Asia after that of Alexander. The whole region from Phrygia to the Indus was subject to Seleucus. He crossed the Indus and waged war with Sandrocottus [Maurya], king of the Indians, who dwelt on the banks of that stream, until they came to an understanding with each other and contracted a marriage relationship. Some of these exploits were performed before the death of Antigonus and some afterward.|sign=&lt;small&gt;[[Appian]]&lt;/small&gt;|source=''History of Rome'', The Syrian Wars [http://www.livius.org/ap-ark/appian/appian_syriaca_11.html 55]}}

The exact details of engagement are not known. As noted by scholars such as R. C. Majumdar&lt;ref name=Majumdar&gt;Ramesh Chandra Majumdar (1977). ''Ancient India''. Motilal Banarsidass Publ. ISBN 81-208-0436-8.&lt;/ref&gt; and D. D. Kosambi, Seleucus appears to have fared poorly, having ceded large territories west of the Indus to Chandragupta. Due to his defeat, Seleucus surrendered [[Arachosia]], [[Gedrosia]], [[Paropamisadae]], and [[Aria (satrapy)|Aria]].

Mainstream scholarship asserts that Chandragupta received vast territory west of the Indus, including the [[Hindu Kush]], modern day [[Afghanistan]], and the [[Balochistan (region)|Balochistan]] province of [[Pakistan]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Vincent Arthur Smith|Vincent A. Smith]] (1998). ''Asoka''. Asian Educational Services. ISBN 81-206-1303-1.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Walter Eugene | first1 = Clark | year = 1919 | title = The Importance of Hellenism from the Point of View of Indic-Philology | url = | journal = Classical Philology | volume = 14 | issue = 4| pages = 297–313 | doi = 10.1086/360246 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Archaeologically, concrete indications of Mauryan rule, such as the inscriptions of the [[Edicts of Ashoka]], are known as far as [[Kandhahar]] in southern Afghanistan.

{{quote|text=After having made a treaty with him [Sandrakotos] and put in order the Orient situation, Seleucos went to war against [[Antigonus I Monophthalmus|Antigonus]].|sign=&lt;small&gt;[[Junianus Justinus]]&lt;/small&gt;|source=''Historiarum Philippicarum libri XLIV'', [http://www.forumromanum.org/literature/justin/trad15.html XV.4.15]}}

It is generally thought that Chandragupta married [[Seleucus I Nicator|Seleucus's]] daughter to formalize an alliance.  In a return gesture, Chandragupta sent 500 [[war]]-[[elephants]],&lt;ref name=Majumdar/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ancient India, (Kachroo ,p.196)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The Imperial Gazetteer of India, (Hunter,p.167)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The evolution of man and society, (Darlington ,p.223)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Tarn | first1 = W. W. | year = 1940 | title = Two Notes on Seleucid History: 1. Seleucus' 500 Elephants, 2. Tarmita | url = | journal = The Journal of Hellenic Studies | volume = 60 | issue = | pages = 84–94 | doi = 10.2307/626263 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Partha Sarathi Bose (2003). ''Alexander the Great's Art of Strategy''. Gotham Books. ISBN 1-59240-053-1.&lt;/ref&gt; a military asset which would play a decisive role at the [[Battle of Ipsus]] in 302 BCE.  In addition to this treaty, Seleucus dispatched an ambassador, [[Megasthenes]], to Chandragupta, and later [[Deimakos]] to his son [[Bindusara]], at the Mauryan court at [[Pataliputra]] (modern [[Patna]] in [[Bihar state]]). Later [[Ptolemy II Philadelphus]], the ruler of [[Ptolemaic Egypt]] and contemporary of [[Ashoka the Great]], is also recorded by [[Pliny the Elder]] as having sent an ambassador named [[Dionysius (ambassador)|Dionysius]] to the Mauryan court.&lt;ref&gt;[http://perseus.mpiwg-berlin.mpg.de/cgi-bin/ptext?lookup=Plin.+Nat.+6.21 Pliny the Elder, &quot;The Natural History&quot;, Chap. 21]&lt;/ref&gt;

Classical sources have also recorded that following their treaty, Chandragupta and Seleucus exchanged presents, such as when Chandragupta sent various [[aphrodisiac]]s to Seleucus:

{{quote|And Theophrastus says that some contrivances are of wondrous efficacy in such matters [as to make people more amorous]. And Phylarchus confirms him, by reference to some of the presents which Sandrakottus, the king of the Indians, sent to Seleucus; which were to act like charms in producing a wonderful degree of affection, while some, on the contrary, were to banish love.|sign=&lt;small&gt;[[Athenaeus of Naucratis]]&lt;/small&gt;|source=''[[Deipnosophistae]]'', [http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/Literature/Literature-idx?type=turn&amp;entity=Literature000701860036&amp;isize=M&amp;pview=hide I.32]}}

===Southern conquest===

After annexing Seleucus' eastern Persian provinces, Chandragupta had a vast empire extending across the northern parts of [[Indian Sub-continent]], from the [[Bay of Bengal]] to the [[Arabian Sea]]. Chandragupta then began expanding his empire further south beyond the barrier of the [[Vindhya Range]] and into the [[Deccan Plateau]] except the Tamil regions ([[Early Pandyan Kingdom|Pandya]], [[Chera dynasty|Chera]], [[Early Cholas|Chola]] and [[Velirs|Satyaputra]]) and [[Kalinga]] (modern day [[Orissa]]).&lt;ref name=Mookerji/&gt; By the time his conquests were complete, Chandragupta had succeeded in unifying most of Southern Asia. Megasthenes later recorded the size of Chandragupta's army as 400,000 soldiers, according to [[Strabo]]:

{{quote|text=Megasthenes was in the camp of Sandrocottus, which consisted of 400,000 men.|sign=&lt;small&gt;[[Strabo]]&lt;/small&gt;|source=''[[Geographica (Strabo)|Geographica]]'', [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Strabo/15A3*.html#1.53 15.1.53]}}

On the other hand, [[Pliny the Elder|Pliny]], who also drew from Megasthenes' work, gives even larger numbers of 600,000 infantry, 30,000 cavalry, and 9,000 war elephants:

{{quote|text=But the Prasii surpass in power and glory every other people, not only in this quarter, but one may say in all India, their capital Palibothra, a very large and wealthy city, after which some call the people itself the Palibothri,--nay even the whole tract along the Ganges. Their king has in his pay a standing army of 600,000-foot-soldiers, 30,000 cavalry, and 9,000 elephants: whence may be formed some conjecture as to the vastness of his resources.|sign=&lt;small&gt;[[Pliny the Elder|Pliny]]&lt;/small&gt;|source=''[[Natural History (Pliny)|Natural History]]'' [http://www.mssu.edu/projectsouthasia/history/primarydocs/Foreign_Views/GreekRoman/Megasthenes-Indika.htm VI, 22.4]}}

==Jainism and Sallekhana==
Chandragupt gave up his throne in 298 BCE, when he was 42 years old, and became an ascetic under the [[Jain monasticism|Jain saint]] [[Bhadrabahu|Acharya Bhadrabahu]], migrating south with them and ending his days in &quot;[[sallekhana]]&quot; at [[Shravanabelagola|Śravaṇa Beḷgoḷa]] in present day [[Karnataka]], though fifth-century inscriptions in the area support the concept of a larger southern migration around that time.&lt;ref&gt;[http://philtar.ucsm.ac.uk/encyclopedia/jainism/digam.html Digambaras], [http://philtar.ucsm.ac.uk/encyclopedia/index.html Overview of World Religions], accessed 9 September 2007&lt;/ref&gt; A small temple marks the cave (Bhadrabahu Cave) where he is said to have died by fasting.

There are two hills in Śravaṇa Beḷgoḷa, Chandragiri (Chikkabetta) and Vindyagiri. The last shruta-kevali, Bhadrabahu and his pupil Chandragupta Maurya, are believed to have meditated there. Chandragupta Basadi, which was dedicated to Chandragupta Maurya, was originally built there by Emperor Ashoka in the third century BCE.

==Successors==
{{Main|Maurya Empire}}
Chandragupta Maurya renounced his throne to his son, [[vaman
], who became the new Mauryan Emperor. [[Bindusara]]'s son [[Ashoka the Great]] became one of the most influential kings in India's history due to his important role in the [[history of Buddhism]].

==In popular culture==
Chanakya's role in the formation of the Mauryan Empire is the essence of a historical/spiritual novel ''The Courtesan and the Sadhu'' by Dr. Mysore N. Prakash.&lt;ref&gt;''The Courtesan and the Sadhu, A Novel about Maya, Dharma, and God'', October 2008, Dharma Vision LLC., ISBN 978-0-9818237-0-6, Library of Congress Control Number: 2008934274&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Santosh Sivan]]'s 2001 epic Hindi language film [[Asoka (2001 film)|Asoka]], portrays the last moments of Chandragupt as emperor. The sword of Chandragupt plays an important role in the film.

The television series ''[[Chanakya (TV series)|Chanakya]]'' is archetypal account of the life and times of Chanakya, based on the play &quot;Mudra Rakshasa&quot; (The Signet Ring of &quot;Rakshasa&quot;).

There is a television series on Imagine TV called [[Chandragupt Maurya (TV series)|Chandragupt Maurya]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=TV|first=Imagine|title=Channel|url=http://www.imagine.tv/in/shows/subhome/123/1779/|work=TV Channel}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Indian Postal Service]] issued a [[Commemorative stamp | commemorative postage stamp]] honoring Chandragupta Maurya in 2001.&lt;ref name=PIBRelease&gt;[http://pib.nic.in/archieve/lreleng/lyr2001/rjul2001/19072001/r190720012.html COMMEMORATIVE POSTAGE STAMP ON CHANDRAGUPTA MAURYA], Press Information Bureau, Govt. of India&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|History|India}}
*[[Bhagrathi community (Western UP)]]
*[[Ancient Macedonian army]]
*[[Arthashastra]]
*[[Ashoka]]
*[[Bindusara]]
*[[Chanakya]]
*[[Dasaratha Maurya]]
*[[Samprati]]
*[[Greco-Bactrian]]
*[[Gupta]]
*[[Indo-Greek Kingdom]]
*[[List of Indian monarchs]]
*[[List of people known as The Great]]
*[[Mauryan art]]
*[[Sulehria]]

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* Kosambi, D.D. ''An Introduction to the Study of Indian History,'' Bombay: Popular Prakashan, 1985
* Bhargava, P.L. ''Chandragupta Maurya'', New Delhi:D.K. Printworld, 160 pp., 2002.
* Habib, Irfan. and Jha, Vivekanand. ''Mauryan India: A People's History of India'',New Delhi:Tulika Books, 2004; 189pp
* Swearer, Donald. ''Buddhism and Society in Southeast Asia'' (Chambersburg, Pennsylvania: Anima Books, 1981)  ISBN 0-89012-023-4
* Nilakanta Sastri, K. A.  ''Age of the Nandas and Mauryas'' (Delhi : Motilal Banarsidass, [1967] c1952) ISBN 0-89684-167-7
* Bongard-Levin, G. M. ''Mauryan India'' (Stosius Inc/Advent Books Division May 1986) ISBN 0-86590-826-5
* Chand Chauhan, Gian. ''Origin and Growth of Feudalism in Early India: From the Mauryas to AD 650'' (Munshiram Manoharlal January 2004) ISBN 81-215-1028-7
* Keay, John. ''India: A History'' (Grove Press; 1 Grove Pr edition May 10, 2001) ISBN 0-8021-3797-0
* Radha Kumud Mukherji. '' Chandragupta Maurya aur Uska Kaal'' (Rajkamal Prakashan, Re Print 1990) ISBN-81-7171-088-1

==External links==
*[http://webcache.googleusercontent.com/search?q=cache:p94jguEdtEQJ:rajyasabha.nic.in/rsnew/picture_gallery/p1.asp+was+chandragupta+maurya+a+shepherd&amp;cd=10&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;gl=uk Shepherd boy Chandragupta Maurya]
* [http://46.1911encyclopedia.org/C/CH/CHANDRAGUPTA_MAURYA.htm 1911encyclopedia.org article on Chandragupta Maurya]
* [http://www.third-millennium-library.com/readinghall/GalleryofHistory/CHANDRAGUPTA/MAURYA-DOOR.html Chandragupta Maurya by Purushottam Lal Bhargava (BTM format)]

{{-}}
{{s-start}}
{{succession box|title=[[Maurya Empire|Mauryan Emperor]] | before=''[[Nanda Dynasty]]''|after=[[Bindusara]]|years=322–298 BC}}
{{s-end}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Maurya, Chandragupt
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Magadha]], [[Bihar]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    = [[Shravanabelagola]], [[Karnataka]]
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Maurya, Chandragupt}}
[[Category:298 BC deaths]]
[[Category:Hindu monarchs]]
[[Category:Indian monarchs]]
[[Category:Maurya Empire]]
[[Category:Santhara]]
[[Category:3rd-century BC rulers]]
[[Category:4th-century BC rulers]]
[[Category:340 BC births]]

[[bn:চন্দ্রগুপ্ত মৌর্য্য]]
[[bg:Чандрагупта]]
[[ca:Chandragupta Maurya]]
[[cs:Čandragupta Maurja]]
[[de:Chandragupta Maurya]]
[[es:Chandragupta Maurya]]
[[eo:Ĉandragupto Maŭrjo]]
[[eu:Chandragupta Maurya]]
[[fa:چاندراگوپتا مائوریا]]
[[fr:Chandragupta Maurya]]
[[ko:찬드라굽타]]
[[hi:चन्द्रगुप्त मौर्य]]
[[id:Candragupta Maurya]]
[[it:Chandragupta Maurya]]
[[kn:ಚಂದ್ರಗುಪ್ತ ಮೌರ್ಯ]]
[[ka:ჩანდრაგუპტა მაურია]]
[[la:Candragupta Maurya]]
[[ml:ചന്ദ്രഗുപ്ത മൗര്യൻ]]
[[mr:चंद्रगुप्त मौर्य]]
[[nl:Chandragupta Maurya]]
[[new:चन्द्रगुप्त मौर्य]]
[[ja:チャンドラグプタ (マウリヤ朝)]]
[[no:Chandragupta Maurya]]
[[nn:Tsjandragupta Maurya]]
[[pnb:چندرگپت موریہ]]
[[pl:Ćandragupta Maurja]]
[[pt:Chandragupta Máuria]]
[[ru:Чандрагупта Маурья]]
[[sa:चन्द्रगुप्तमौर्यः]]
[[sk:Čandragupta (Maurjovská ríša)]]
[[sh:Chandragupta Maurya]]
[[fi:Chandragupta Maurya]]
[[sv:Chandragupta Maurya]]
[[ta:சந்திரகுப்த மௌரியர்]]
[[te:చంద్రగుప్త మౌర్యుడు]]
[[th:พระเจ้าจันทรคุปต์เมารยะ]]
[[uk:Чандрагупта Маур'я]]
[[ur:چندر گپت موریا]]
[[vi:Chandragupta Maurya]]
[[zh:旃陀罗笈多 (孔雀王朝)]]</text>
      <sha1>7arpolb472yjaju8wqzv7be83vf86rf</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
