<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Christian democracy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>328969</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520730040</id>
      <parentid>520729602</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-31T11:04:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>RJFF</username>
        <id>13720831</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>rev: probably original research</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27216">{{other uses|Christian Democracy (disambiguation)}}
{{more footnotes|date=October 2012}}
{{Christian Democracy sidebar|Christian democracy|expanded=all}}

'''Christian democracy''' is a political ideology that seeks to apply [[Christianity|Christian]] principles to [[public policy]]. It emerged in nineteenth-century [[Europe]] under the influence of [[conservatism]] and [[Catholic social teaching]].&lt;ref&gt;A. Heywood, ''Political ideologies. An introduction'', New York, Macmillan, 2003, 89&lt;/ref&gt; It continues to be influential in Europe and [[Latin America]], though in a number of countries its Christian ethos has been diluted by [[secularisation]].

In practice, Christian democracy is often considered conservative on cultural, social and moral issues (social conservatism) and advocates a [[social market economy]] in the economic field (crossing over with [[social democratic]] economics but based on the family). In Europe, where their opponents have traditionally been secularist [[socialism|socialists]], Christian democratic parties are moderately conservative overall, whereas in the very different cultural and political environment of South America they tend to lean to the left{{Citation needed|date=September 2012}}.

Examples of Christian democratic parties include the German [[Christian Democratic Union (Germany)|Christian Democratic Union]] (CDU), the [[Christian Democratic Party of Chile]], the [[Christian Democratic People's Party of Switzerland]], the [[Christian Democratic Appeal]] (CDA) in the Netherlands, and the historical [[Christian Democracy (Italy)|Christian Democracy]] in Italy.

==Political viewpoints==
As with any political ideology, Christian democracy has had different manifestations over time and between countries; there are some broad ideologies that are called Christian Democracy.

As a generalisation, it can be said that Christian democratic parties in Europe tend to be moderately [[conservatism|conservative]], and in several cases form the main conservative party in their respective countries (e.g. in Germany, Spain, and Belgium).{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}} In Latin America, by contrast, Christian democratic parties tend to be [[progressivism|progressive]] and to some degree influenced by [[liberation theology]].&lt;ref name=Szulc&gt;Tad Szulc, 'Communists, Socialists and Christian Democrats', ''[[Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science]]'', 360, pp. 99-109, p. 102&lt;/ref&gt; These generalisations, however, must be nuanced by the consideration that Christian democracy does not fit precisely into the usual categories of political thought, but rather includes elements common to several other political ideologies:
*In ''common'' with '''conservatism''', traditional moral values (on marriage, abortion, etc.), opposition to [[secularization]], a view of the evolutionary (as opposed to revolutionary) development of society, an emphasis on law and order, and a rejection of [[communism]].
*In ''contrast'' to '''conservatism''', open to change (for example, in the structure of society) and not necessarily supportive of the social status quo.
*In ''common'' with '''liberalism''', an emphasis on human rights and individual initiative.
*In ''contrast'' to '''liberalism''', a rejection of [[secularism]], and an emphasis on the fact that the individual is part of a community and has duties towards it.
*In ''common'' with '''socialism''', an emphasis on the community, social justice and solidarity, support for a [[welfare state]] and support for some regulation of market forces.
*In ''contrast'' to '''socialism''', most European Christian Democrats support a [[market economy]] and do not adhere to the doctrine of [[class struggle]]. This has not always carried over to some Latin American Christian Democratic Parties, which have been influenced by [[liberation theology]].
Geoffrey K. Roberts and Patricia Hogwood have noted that &quot;Christian democracy has incorporated many of the views held by liberals, conservatives and socialists within a wider framework of moral and Christian principles.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Roberts and Hogwood, ''European Politics Today'', Manchester University Press, 1997&lt;/ref&gt;

Christian democrats are usually [[social conservatism|socially conservative]], and, as such, generally have a relatively skeptical stance towards [[abortion]] and [[same-sex marriage]], though some Christian democratic parties have accepted the limited legalization of both. Christian democratic parties are often likely to assert the [[Christianity|Christian]] heritage of their country, and to affirm explicitly Christian ethics, rather than adopting a more liberal or secular stance.

On economic issues, Christian democrats normally do not completely oppose [[capitalism]] as an economic system, unlike their repudiation of atheistic [[communism]] and similar ideologies,&lt;ref name=Moos&gt;Moos, M. (1945) 'Don Luigi Sturzo – Christian Democrat', ''[[American Political Science Review]]'', 39(2), pp. 269-292, p. 269&lt;/ref&gt; though they do see the economy as being at the service of humanity. The duty of the state towards society is of real importance for Christian democrats, though some would see this duty as being mostly to create the conditions for civil society to flourish, while others would see it as a more direct duty of the state towards citizens. In recent decades, some right-leaning Christian democratic parties in Europe have adopted policies consistent with an [[economic liberalism|economically liberal]] point of view, while by contrast other Christian democrats at times seem to hold views not dissimilar from [[Christian socialism]].

== History ==
Christian democracy as a political movement was born at the end of the 19th century, largely as a result of the [[Pope|papal]] encyclical ''[[Rerum Novarum]]'' of [[Pope Leo XIII]], in which the [[Holy See|Vatican]] recognized workers' misery and agreed that something should be done about it, in reaction to the rise of the [[socialism|socialist]] and [[trade union]] movements. The position of the [[Roman Catholic Church]] on this matter was further clarified in subsequent encyclicals, such as [[Quadragesimo Anno]], by [[Pope Pius XI]] in 1931, [[Populorum Progressio]] by [[Pope Paul VI]] in 1967, [[Centesimus Annus]], by [[Pope John Paul II]] in 1991, and [[Caritas in Veritate]] by [[Pope Benedict XVI]] in 2009.&lt;ref name=Sturzo&gt;Sturzo, L. (1947) ‘The Philosophic Background of Christian Democracy’, ''The Review of Politics'', 9(1), pp. 3-15, p. 5&lt;/ref&gt; Christian democracy has evolved considerably since then, and it is no longer the Catholic ideology of [[Distributism]], although it is based on Catholic social teaching, as outlined in the 2006 official &quot;Catechism of the Social Doctrine of the Catholic Church&quot;. (In Germany, for example, the Christian Democratic Party emerged as a grouping dominated by Rhenish and Westphalian Catholics, but also encompassed the more conservative elements of the  [[Protestantism|Protestant]] population.) Following World War II, Christian democracy was seen as a neutral and unifying voice of compassionate conservatism, and distinguished itself from the [[far right]]. It gave a voice to 'conservatives of the heart', particularly in Germany, who had detested [[Adolf Hitler]]'s regime yet agreed with the right on many issues.

In [[Protestantism|Protestant]] countries, Christian democratic parties were founded by more conservative Protestants in reaction to the political power of [[liberalism|liberal]] tendencies within the Protestant churches. In the Netherlands, for instance, the [[Anti Revolutionary Party]] was founded in 1879 by conservative Protestants. It institutionalized early 19th century opposition against the ideas from the French Revolution on popular sovereignty. It held the position that government derived its authority from God and not from the people. This Burkean position is sometimes also called Christian Historian. It was a response to the liberal ideas that predominated in political life. The [[Christian Democrats (Sweden)|Christian Democrats of Sweden]], rooted in the [[Pentecostal]] religious tradition, has a similar history.

While Christian democracy is of Roman Catholic origin, it has been adopted by many [[Protestantism|Protestant]] and [[Eastern Orthodox Church|Eastern Orthodox]] Christians as well. Some Christian democratic parties, particularly in Europe, no longer emphasize religion and have become much more [[secular]] in recent years.  Also within Europe, two essentially Islamic parties, the [[Democratic League of Kosovo]] and Turkey's ruling [[Justice and Development Party (Turkey)|Justice and Development Party]] (usually known by the [[Turkish language|Turkish]] acronym AKP, for ''Adalet ve Kalkınma Partisi'') have moved towards the tradition.  The Democratic League of Kosovo is now a full member of the Centrist Democrat International ''(see [[#Christian democracy around the world|below]])''.

Christian democracy can trace its philosophical roots back to [[Thomas Aquinas]] and his thoughts about [[Aristotle|Aristotelian]] [[ontology]] and the [[Christianity|Christian]] tradition. According to him, human rights are based on [[natural law]] and defined as the things that humans need to function properly. For example, food is a human right because without food humans cannot function properly. Modern authors important to the formation of Christian democratic ideology include [[Emmanuel Mounier]], [[Étienne Gilson]], and [[Jacques Maritain]].

== Christian democracy around the world == &lt;!--Linked from above text.--&gt;
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Propaganda Dc.jpg|360px|right]] --&gt;
The international organization of Christian democratic parties, the [[Centrist Democrat International]] (CDI), formerly known as the Christian Democratic International, is the second largest international political organization in the world (second only to the [[Socialist International]]). European Christian democratic parties have their own regional organization called the [[European People's Party]], which form the largest group in the [[European Parliament]], the [[European People's Party (European Parliament group)|EPP Group]].

=== Christian democracy in Europe ===
{{unreferenced|date=October 2012}}
{{Expand section|date=June 2008}}&lt;!--If Malta gets a summary, so should the rest, or no such summaries at all.--&gt;
Christian democracy has been especially important in the politics of [[Politics of Italy|Italy]] (inspired by [[Luigi Sturzo]]; ''see [[Christian Democracy (Italy)]]''), [[Politics of Norway|Norway]] ''(see [[Christian Democratic Party of Norway]])'', and [[Politics of Germany|Germany]] ''(see [[Christian Democratic Union (Germany)]] and [[Christian Social Union in Bavaria]])''. Major Christian democratic influence can also be seen in the politics of Austria ''(see [[Austrian People's Party]])'', Belgium ''(see [[Christene Volkspartij]], [[Christen-Democratisch en Vlaams|Christian Democratic and Flemish]] and [[Humanist Democratic Centre]])'', Finland (see ''[[Christian Democrats (Finland)]]''), France, Ireland ''(see [[Fine Gael]])'', [[Luxembourg]], [[Malta]], the Netherlands ''(see [[Christian Democratic Appeal]])'', Portugal ''(see [[Democratic and Social Centre – People's Party]])'', Poland ''(see [[Civic Platform]] and [[Polish People's Party|Polish Peasants' Party]])'', [[Ukraine]] ''(see [[Christian Democratic Union (Ukraine)]])'', Spain ''(see, [[People's Party (Spain)|Partido Popular]], [[Democratic Union of Catalonia]])'', and Sweden ''(see [[Christian Democrats (Sweden)]])''. Christian democracy is not very strong in the United Kingdom where the [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative Party]] dominates conservative politics and does not advocate Christian democratic platforms but Christian democratic parties do exist.The [[Christian Peoples Alliance (CPA)]], [[The Common Good (political party)]], the [[Christian Party (UK)]] and the [[Christian Democratic Party (UK)]] are the four Christian democratic parties currently in the UK. Christian Democratic Parties in the UK such as The Christian Peoples Alliance, seek new candidates and members, in order to represent people considerately through a Christian democratic process. 

The [[Nationalist Party (Malta)|Nationalist Party of Malta]] is a Christian democratic party and has won seven out of ten general elections since [[Malta]]'s independence in 1964. Currently governing, it has won its third consecutive general election in 2008.  It advocates staunch Christian values including bans on abortion and, until recently, [[Maltese divorce referendum, 2011|divorce]].

=== Christian democracy in Latin America ===
{{unreferenced|date=October 2012}}
{{Expand section|date=June 2008}}&lt;!--&quot;Among others&quot; doesn't cut it.--&gt;
Christian democracy has been especially important in [[Politics of Chile|Chile]] ''(see [[Christian Democrat Party of Chile]])'' and Venezuela (see [[COPEI]] - Christian Democratic Party of Venezuela), among others, and partly also in [[Politics of Mexico|Mexico]], starting with the ascendancy of [[President of Mexico|President]] [[Vicente Fox]] in 2000, followed by [[Felipe Calderón]] ''(see [[National Action Party (Mexico)]])''. Cuba counts with several Christian Democratic political associations, both on the island and in exile.  The most significant is perhaps the Movimiento Cristiano de Liberación (MCL) ([[www.oswaldopaya.org]]), led by well-known Cuban dissident [[Oswaldo Payá]], who was killed in a tragic automobile accident in the summer of 2012 and has been nominated for the [[Nobel Peace Prize]].

===Christian democracy in Australia and the United States===
Christian democratic parties in Australia are said to include not only the party called 'The Christian Democratic Party&quot;, but also the [[Democratic Labor Party]] (which is a social democratic party) and [[Family First Party]] (which is regarded by some as a liberal democratic party).

In [[Victoria (Australia)|Victoria]], and NSW [[Australian Labor Party]] (ALP) state executive members, parliamentarians and branch members associated (rightly or wrongly) with the Industrial Groups or [[B. A. Santamaria]] and The Movement, were expelled from the party (against that party's rules). They formed a new party, soon to be known as the [[Democratic Labor Party]] (DLP). Later in 1957, a similar split occurred in [[Queensland]], with the resulting group subsequently joining the DLP.  The party also had sitting members from [[Tasmania]] and [[New South Wales]] at various times, though it was much stronger in the former mentioned states.

The party was in agreement with the ruling conservative [[Liberal Party of Australia|Liberal]] and [[National Party of Australia|Country]] parties on many issues, which resulted in their [[Ranked voting systems|preferencing]] of these parties over the ALP. However, it was more morally conservative, militantly anti-communist and socially compassionate than the Liberals. The DLP was defeated by the federal election of 1974 that saw its primary vote cut by nearly two thirds, and the entry of an ALP government.  The DLP never regained its previous support in subsequent elections and formally disbanded in 1978, but a small group within the party refused to accept this decision and created a small, reformed successor party.

Though his party was effectively gone, Santamaria and his National Civic Council took a strong diametrically opposed stance to dominant [[neoliberal]]/[[New Right]] tendencies within both the ALP and Liberal parties throughout the eighties and early nineties.

A new Christian party that found its first strength in 1981 was the [[Christian Democratic Party (Australia)|Christian Democratic Party]] (initially known as the &quot;Call to Australia&quot; party). It gained 9.1% of the vote in the [[New South Wales]] (NSW) state election of 1981, but its vote rapidly declined thereafter. This Protestant party had some very similar social policies to the DLP. Its support base has generally been restricted to NSW and [[Western Australia]], where it usually gains between 2–4% of votes, with its support being minuscule in other states.  It has had two members of the NSW state parliament for most of its existence.

Another Australian Christian democratic party of note is the [[Family First Party]]. It has had one or two members in the SA parliament since 2002, and in 2004 also managed to elect a Victorian senator. Its electoral support is small, with the largest constituencies being [[South Australia]] (4–6%), and [[Victoria (Australia)|Victoria]] (around 4%). Family First generally receives lower support in national elections than in state elections.

In 2006, the new DLP experienced a resurgence. The successor party struggled through decades of Victorian elections before finally gaining a parliamentary seat when the Victorian upper house was redesigned. Nevertheless, its electoral support is still very small in Victoria (around 2%). It has recently reformed state parties in Queensland and New South Wales. In the [[Australian federal election, 2010]], the DLP won the sixth senate seat in Victoria, giving it representation in the [[Australian Senate]].&lt;ref&gt;'It’s official – DLP wins Vic Senate seat', '''Australian Conservative''', http://australianconservative.com/2010/09/its-official-%E2%80%93-dlp-wins-vic-senate-seat/&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[United States]] there have been various attempts to create Christian Democratic parties, similar to their European and Latin American counterparts, but efforts have generally run against the formidable strength of the existing bipartisan Republican/Democratic party system. The Christian Democratic Union of the United States of America ([[www.cdu-usa.org]]), formed in 2007, claims to be growing in membership and support, attracting persons disaffected with the two established parties.  CDU-USA defines itself as conservative on moral and cultural issues, while progressive on economic and social ones. Among its positions, The Christian Democratic Union is supportive of a [[universal health care]] system for the United States, through [[publicly funded health care]] and [[single-payer health care]], as proposed, for example, by the American Physicians for a National Health Program ([[www.PNHP.org]]).  CDU-USA is also supportive of national energy self-sufficiency and of more equitable and [[progressive tax]] rates so as to achieve the goal of a balanced budget without decreasing social expenditures or raising taxes on the middle class.

== Notable Christian democrats ==
{{unreferenced|date=October 2012}}
* [[Konrad Adenauer]], first chancellor of [[West Germany]] after World War II, and architect of the [[social market economy]].
* [[Giulio Andreotti]], long-time Prime Minister of Italy.
* [[Iuliu Maniu]], former Prime Minister of [[Romania]].
* [[Patricio Aylwin]], [[Chile]]an politician who served as president when Chile returned to democracy after the [[dictatorship]] of [[Augusto Pinochet]].
* [[Jerzy Buzek]], president of [[European Parliament]] since 2009.
* [[Rafael Caldera]], two-time [[Venezuela]]n president, and author.
* [[Felipe Calderón]], president of Mexico.
* [[Alcide De Gasperi]], Italian prime minister and pro-[[European Union|European]] leader.
* [[Éamon de Valera]], president and prime minister of [[Republic of Ireland|Ireland]], whose [[Constitution of Ireland]] was influenced by Catholic social teaching
* [[José Napoleón Duarte]], democratically-elected president of [[El Salvador]] during its [[Salvadoran Civil War|Civil War]].
* [[Eddie Fenech Adami]], former leader of the [[Nationalist Party (Malta)|Nationalist Party]] in [[Malta]] (''Partit Nazzjonalista''); former prime minister and former President of the Republic of Malta.
* [[Eduardo Frei Montalva]], [[Chile]]an politician and former president.
* [[Claudio Avelar]], an politician and suppleant deputy in [[Brazil]], member of [[Partido Trabalhista Cristão]].
* [[Helmut Kohl]], chancellor of [[West Germany]] and later the unified Germany.
* [[Abraham Kuyper]], founder of the Netherlands' [[Anti Revolutionary Party]] (the first Christian democratic party), as well as the [[Neo-Calvinist]] [[Protestant]] movement, and a [[prime minister of the Netherlands]].
* [[Giorgio La Pira]], Italian politician, from the [[left wing]] of [[Democrazia Cristiana]].
* [[Ruud Lubbers]], a prime minister of the Netherlands and [[United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees]].
* [[Wilfried Martens]], former Prime Minister of Belgium, president of the [[European People's Party]].
* [[Kjell Magne Bondevik]], former [[Prime Minister of Norway]].
* [[Angela Merkel]], became, in 2005, the first female chancellor of Germany.
* [[Oswaldo Payá]], founder and leader of the dissident Cuban Christian Liberation Movement (Movimiento Cristiano de Liberación - MCL) ([[www.oswaldopaya.org]]). Died in a car accident in 2012. Has been nominated for the [[Nobel Peace Prize]].
* [[Xabier Arzalluz]], leader of the Basque Nationalist Party for two decades, until 2004.
* [[Luigi Sturzo]], Italian politician and one of the founders of the [[Partito Popolare Italiano]] in 1919.
* [[Aldo Moro]], prime minister of Italy, killed by the [[Brigate Rosse]].
* [[Boris Trajkovski]], President of the [[Republic of Macedonia]]
* [[Mariano Rajoy]], Prime Minister of [[Spain]]
* [[Fidel V. Ramos]], first Protestant president of the [[Roman Catholic|Catholic]]-dominated [[Philippines]], and founder and chair ''emeritus'' of the political party [[Lakas-Christian Muslim Democrats]].
* [[Herman Van Rompuy]], first fixed-term [[President of the European Council]].
* [[Robert Schuman]], French politician who has served both as head of government and foreign minister, leader of [[Popular Republican Movement]]; one of the founders of the [[European Union]].
* [[Wolfgang Schüssel]], former Austrian chancellor.
* [[Joaquín Balaguer]], former President of the [[Dominican Republic]].
* [[Adone Zoli]], former Prime Minister of Italy.
* [[Aleksandar Vučić]], Defence Minister of Serbia
* [[Lech Wałęsa]], Polish politician, trade-union organizer, and human-rights activist. A charismatic leader, he co-founded [[Solidarity (Polish trade union)|Solidarity]], the Soviet bloc's first independent trade union, won the Nobel Peace Prize in 1983, and served as President of Poland 1990–95.
* [[Lech Aleksander Kaczyński]], President of Poland from 2005 until his sudden death in 2010.
* [[Ludwig Windthorst]], German politician and leader of [[Centre Party (Germany)|Centre Party]]
* [[Joseph Görres]], German writer and journalist, co-founder of an idea of the [[political catholicism|political Catholic movement]]
* [[José Maria Eymael]],  a Bazillian politician, lawyer, and businessman, and founder of the [[Partido Social Democrata Cristão]] (PSDC).

== See also ==
*[[Catholic social teaching]]
*[[Christianity and politics]]
*[[List of Christian democratic parties]] around the world
*[[Political Catholicism]]

===International Christian democratic organizations===
*[[Centrist Democrat International]] (CDI){{spaced ndash}} formerly Christian Democratic International
*[[Christian Democratic Organization of America]] (ODCA){{spaced ndash}} a CDI regional organization for the Americas
*[[European Christian Political Movement]] (ECPM){{spaced ndash}} a European party (non-CDI)
*[[European Democratic Party]] (EDP){{spaced ndash}} a European party (non-CDI)
*[[European People's Party]] (EPP){{spaced ndash}} the largest transnational European  party of Christian democratic and conservative parties (a CDI and IDU regional)

===Related concepts===
*[[Theocracy]]
*[[Communitarianism]]
*[[Compassionate conservatism]]
*[[Christian left]]
*[[Christian right]]
*[[Christian socialism]]
*[[Distributism]]
*[[Liberation theology]]
*[[Moderation theory]]
*[[Neo-Calvinism]]
*[[Radical center (politics)]]
*[[Social conservatism]]
*[[Social market economy]]
*[[Third Way (centrism)]]

==Literature==
*{{Citation |first1=Michael |last1=Gehler |first2=Wolfram |last2=Kaiser |title=Political Catholicism in Europe 1918—1945 |publisher=Routledge |year=2004 |isbn=0-7146-5650-X}}
*{{Citation |first1=Michael |last1=Gehler |first2=Wolfram |last2=Kaiser |title=Christian Democracy in Europe since 1945 |publisher=Routledge |year=2004 |isbn=0-7146-5662-3}}
*{{Citation |first=Wolfram |last=Kaiser |title=Christian Democracy and the Origins of European Union |publisher=Cambridge University Press |year=2007 |isbn=9780521883108}}
*{{Citation |first1=Scott |last1=Mainwaring |first2=Timothy R. |last2=Scully |title=Christian Democracy in Latin America: Electoral Competition and Regime Conflicts |publisher=Stanford University Press |year=2003 |isbn=0-8047-4597-8}}
*{{Citation |first1=Steven |last1=Van Hecke |first2=Emmanuel |last2=Gerard |title=Christian Democratic Parties in Europe since the End of the Cold War |publisher=Leuven University Press |year=2004 |isbn=9058673770}}

==References==
{{Refimprove|date=June 2008}}
{{Reflist}}
* Kalyvas, Stathis N. and Kees van Kersbergen (2010). ''Christian Democracy''. Annual Review of Political Science 2010. 13:183–209.

==External links==
{{Commons category|Christian Democracy}}
*[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/04708a.htm ''New Advent Catholic Encyclopedia'' — an article on Christian Democracy]
*[http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=22115363 ''Christian Democracy in Western Europe: 1820-1953'' — a book by Michael Fogarty]
*[http://www.davidwilletts.org.uk/ccoarticle.jsp?type=speech&amp;sectionID=2&amp;objectID=81937 ''Conservativism and Christian Democracy'' — an essay by UK Conservative MP David Willetts]
*[http://thecommoner.us/ ''The Commoner'' — a Christian Democratic blog]
*[http://www.cdu-usa.org/ Christian Democratic Union (USA)]

{{Navboxes
|list =
{{Christian Democracy}}
{{Christianity and politics}}
{{Political ideologies}}
}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2011}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Christian Democracy}}
[[Category:Christian democracy| ]]
[[Category:Democracy]]
[[Category:Political ideologies]]

{{Link GA|ru}}
[[ar:ديمقراطية مسيحية]]
[[bg:Християндемокрация]]
[[ca:Democràcia cristiana]]
[[cs:Křesťanská demokracie]]
[[da:Kristendemokrati]]
[[de:Christdemokratie]]
[[el:Χριστιανοδημοκρατία]]
[[es:Democracia cristiana]]
[[eo:Kristana demokratio]]
[[eu:Kristau demokrazia]]
[[fa:مردم‌سالاری مسیحی]]
[[fr:Démocratie chrétienne]]
[[fy:Kristendemokrasy]]
[[gl:Democracia cristiá]]
[[ko:기독교 민주주의]]
[[hr:Kršćanska demokracija]]
[[id:Demokrasi Kristen]]
[[it:Cristianesimo democratico]]
[[ka:ქრისტიანული დემოკრატია]]
[[hu:Kereszténydemokrácia]]
[[nl:Christendemocratie]]
[[ja:キリスト教民主主義]]
[[no:Kristendemokrati]]
[[pl:Chrześcijańska demokracja]]
[[pt:Democracia cristã]]
[[ro:Creștin democrație]]
[[ru:Христианская демократия]]
[[sr:Хришћанска демократија]]
[[sh:Hrišćanska demokratija]]
[[fi:Kristillisdemokratia]]
[[sv:Kristdemokrati]]
[[uk:Християнська демократія]]
[[zh:基督教民主主義]]</text>
      <sha1>fn8t9s6otg23oivwcqfr1r4pqywk3vg</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
