<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Christian socialism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>328794</id>
    <revision>
      <id>515357420</id>
      <parentid>515357113</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-30T19:46:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>72.94.93.55</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* New Testament */ major error, obviously the author doesn't understand the passage</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="28113">{{Socialism sidebar |expanded=Religious}}
{{Social Christianity}}
'''Christian socialism''' is a form of [[religious socialism]] based on the teachings of [[Jesus]]. Many Christian socialists believe [[capitalism]] to be [[idolatrous]] and rooted in [[greed]], which some Christians denominations consider a [[mortal sin]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Adrian Hastings Pp. 678&quot;&gt;Adrian Hastings, Alistair Mason, Hugh S. Pyper. ''The Oxford Companion to Christian Thought''. Oxford, England, UK: Oxford University Press Pp. 678.&lt;/ref&gt; Christian socialists identify the cause of inequality to be associated with the greed that they associate with capitalism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Adrian Hastings Pp. 678&quot;/&gt;

Christian socialism became a major movement in the [[United Kingdom]] beginning in the 1960s through the [[Christian Socialist Movement (UK)|Christian Socialist Movement]].&lt;ref&gt;Adrian Hastings, Alistair Mason, Hugh S. Pyper. ''The Oxford Companion to Christian Thought''. Oxford, England, UK: Oxford University Press Pp. 677.&lt;/ref&gt;

The term also pertains to such earlier figures as the nineteenth century writers [[Frederick Denison Maurice]] (''The Kingdom of Christ'', 1838), [[Charles Kingsley]] ([[The Water-Babies, A Fairy Tale for a Land Baby|''The Water-Babies'']], 1863), [[Thomas Hughes]] (''[[Tom Brown's Schooldays]]'', 1857), [[Frederick James Furnivall]] (co-creator of the ''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]''), [[Adin Ballou]] (''Practical Christian Socialism'', 1854), and [[Francis Bellamy]] (a Baptist minister and the author of the United States' [[Pledge of Allegiance]]).

==History==
===Biblical age===
Elements that would form the basis of Christian socialism are found in the [[Old Testament|Old]] and [[New Testament]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cort (1988), 19&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Cort|first=John C.|title=Christian Socialism: An Informal History|year=1988|publisher=Orbis Books|location=Maryknoll, New York, USA|isbn=0883445743|pages=19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Old Testament====
The Old Testament had divided perspectives on the issue of poverty. One part of the Jewish tradition held that poverty was judgement of God upon the wicked while viewing prosperity as a reward for the good, stating that &quot;The righteous has enough to satisfy his appetite, but the belly of the wicked suffers want&quot; (Prov. 13:25).&lt;ref name=&quot;Cort (1988), 20&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Cort|first=John C.|title=Christian Socialism: An Informal History|year=1988|publisher=Orbis Books|location=Maryknoll, New York, USA|isbn=0883445743|pages=20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However there are other sections that instruct generosity to the [[have nots]] of society. The [[Torah]] instructs followers to treat neighbours equally and to be generous to have nots, such as stating:
{{quote|''You shall not oppress your neighbour...but you shall love your neighbour as yourself: I am the Lord''|(Lev 19:13, 18).&lt;ref name=&quot;Cort (1988), 21&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Cort|first=John C.|title=Christian Socialism: An Informal History|year=1988|publisher=Orbis Books|location=Maryknoll, New York, USA|isbn=0883445743|pages=21}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
{{quote|''He [the Lord your God] executes justice for the fatherless and the widow, and loves the sojourner, giving him food and clothing. Love the sojourner therefore; for you were sojourners in the land of Egypt''|(Deut. 10:18-19).&lt;ref name=&quot;Cort (1988), 21&quot;/&gt;}}
{{quote|''When you reap in your harvest in the field, and have forgotten a sheaf in the field, you shall not go back to get it...When you beat your olive trees, you shall not go over the boughs again...When you gather the grapes of your vineyard, you shall not glean it afterward; it shall be for the sojourner, the fatherless and the widow. You shall remember that you were a slave in the land of Egypt; therefore I command you to do this''|(Deut. 24:19-22).&lt;ref name=&quot;Cort (1988), 21&quot;/&gt;}}
However this does not imply that the poor are always right, as Moses warns &quot;You shall not be partial to the poor or defer to the great but in righteousness shall you judge your neighbour&quot; (Lev. 19:15).&lt;ref name=&quot;Cort (1988), 21&quot;/&gt;

The [[Psalms]] that were written in a period of eight hundred years from 1300-500 B.C. include many references to social justice for the poor:
{{quote|''Give justice to the weak and the fatherless; maintain the right of the afflicted and the destitute. Rescue the weak and the needy; deliver them from the hand of the wicked''|(Ps. 82 (81): 3, 4).&lt;ref name=&quot;Cort (1988), 22&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Cort|first=John C.|title=Christian Socialism: An Informal History|year=1988|publisher=Orbis Books|location=Maryknoll, New York, USA|isbn=0883445743|pages=22}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
{{quote|''Blessed is the man who fears the Lord, who greatly delights in his commandments!...He has distributed freely, he has given to the poor; his righteousness endures forever; his horn is exalted in honour''|(Ps. 112 (111): 1, 9).&lt;ref name=&quot;Cort (1988), 22&quot;/&gt;}}

[[Amos (prophet)|Amos]] emphasizes the need for &quot;justice&quot; and &quot;righteousness&quot; that is described as conduct that emphasizes love for those who are poor and to oppose oppression and injustice towards the poor.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cort (1988), 23&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Cort|first=John C.|title=Christian Socialism: An Informal History|year=1988|publisher=Orbis Books|location=Maryknoll, New York, USA|isbn=0883445743|pages=23}}&lt;/ref&gt; The prophet [[Isaiah]] (759-694 B.C.) to whom is attributed the first thirty-nine chapters of the [[Book of Isaiah]], followed upon Amos' themes of justice and righteousness involving the poor as necessary for followers of God, denouncing those who do not do these things, stating:
{{quote|''Even though you make many prayers, I will not listen; your hands are full of blood...cease to do evil, learn to do good; seek justice, correct oppression; defend the fatherless, plead for the widow''|(Isa. 1:15-17).&lt;ref name=&quot;Cort (1988), 23&quot;/&gt;}}

The [[Book of Sirach]] denounces the [[Profit-seeking|pursuit of wealth]], stating:
{{quote|''He who loves gold will not be justified, and he who pursues money will be led astray by it. Many have come to ruin because of gold, and their destruction has met them face to face. It is a stumbling block to those who are devoted to it, and every fool will be taken captive by it''|(Sir. 31: 5-7).&lt;ref name=&quot;Cort (1988), 28&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Cort|first=John C.|title=Christian Socialism: An Informal History|year=1988|publisher=Orbis Books|location=Maryknoll, New York, USA|isbn=0883445743|pages=28}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The most important quote of the Old Testament that has been recognized by Christian socialists is the verse from Ecclesiastes 3:13 that describes God as promoting an egalitarian society, stating:
{{quote|''It is God's gift to humankind that everyone should eat and drink and take pleasure in all their toil''|(Ecc. 3: 13).&lt;ref name=&quot;Cort (1988), 29&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Cort|first=John C.|title=Christian Socialism: An Informal History|year=1988|publisher=Orbis Books|location=Maryknoll, New York, USA|isbn=0883445743|pages=29}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

====New Testament====
In the New Testament, [[Jesus]] in Matthew 25:31-46 identifies himself with the hungry, the poor, the sick, and the prisoners.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cort (1988), 31&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Cort|first=John C.|title=Christian Socialism: An Informal History|year=1988|publisher=Orbis Books|location=Maryknoll, New York, USA|isbn=0883445743|pages=31}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the passage, Jesus states that &quot;to feed the hungry&quot; is not simple but requires planning and says that the planning will have to be just as complex,  sophisticated, and as long-range as the demand and provision for food, clothing, and shelter requires.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cort (1988), 31&quot;/&gt; Matthew 25:31-46 is a major component of Christianity and is considered the cornerstone of Christian socialism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cort (1988), 31&quot;/&gt; Another key statement in the New Testament that is an important component of Christian socialism is Luke 10:25-37 that follows up on the statement &quot;You shall love your neighbour as yourself&quot; with the follow-up question &quot;And who is my neighbour?&quot; With the revolutionary response that the neighbour includes the [[Samaritans]] of this world, all those who are most despised and rejected.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cort (1988), 32&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Cort|first=John C.|title=Christian Socialism: An Informal History|year=1988|publisher=Orbis Books|location=Maryknoll, New York, USA|isbn=0883445743|pages=32}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Samaritans were considered a heretical sect and were the objects of hostility and contempt by ancient Jews.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cort (1988), 32&quot;/&gt;

In the [[Sermon on the Plain]], Jesus says, &quot;Blessed are you poor, for yours is the kingdom of God. Blessed are you that hunger now, for you shall be satisfied&quot; (Luke 6:20, 21).&lt;ref name=&quot;Cort (1988), 37&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Cort|first=John C.|title=Christian Socialism: An Informal History|year=1988|publisher=Orbis Books|location=Maryknoll, New York, USA|isbn=0883445743|pages=37}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Christian socialists note that [[James the Just]], the brother of Jesus of Nazareth, in the [[Epistle of James]] criticizes the rich intensely and in strong language:
{{Quote|''Come now, you rich, weep and howl for the miseries that are coming upon you. Your riches have rotted and your garments are moth-eaten. Your gold and silver have rusted, and their rust will be evidence against you and will eat your flesh like fire. You have laid up for treasure for the last days. Behond, the wages of the labourers who mowed your fields, which you have kept back by fraud, cry out; and the cries of the harvesters have reached the ears of the Lord of hosts. You have lived on the earth in luxury and in pleasure; you have fattened your hearts in a day of slaughter''|(Jam. 5:1-6).&lt;ref name=&quot;Cort (1988), 40-41&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Cort|first=John C.|title=Christian Socialism: An Informal History|year=1988|publisher=Orbis Books|location=Maryknoll, New York, USA|isbn=0883445743|pages=40–41}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Eastern Orthodox Church ===
[[Basil of Caesarea]] (c. 330-379), the [[patriarch]] of the Eastern monks who became Bishop of Caesarea, established a complex around the church and monastery that included hostels, almshouses, and hospitals for infectious diseases.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cort (1988), 43&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Cort|first=John C.|title=Christian Socialism: An Informal History|year=1988|publisher=Orbis Books|location=Maryknoll, New York, USA|isbn=0883445743|pages=43}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the great famine of 368, Basil denounced against profiteers and the indifferent rich.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cort (1988), 43&quot;/&gt; Basil wrote the sermon on ''The Rich Fool'' in which he states:
{{quote|''Who is the covetous man? One for whom plenty is not enough. Who is the defrauder? One who takes away what belongs to everyone. And are not you covetous, are you not a defrauder, when you keep for private use what you were given for distribution? When some one strips a man of his clothes we call him a thief. And one who might clothe the naked and does not—should not he be given the same name? The bread in your hoard belongs to the hungry; the cloak in your wardrobe belongs to the naked; the shoes you let rot belong to the barefoot; the money in your vaults belongs to the destitute. All you might help and do not—to all these you are doing wrong''|Basil of Caesarea from the ''The Rich Fool''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cort (1988), 43-44&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Cort|first=John C.|title=Christian Socialism: An Informal History|year=1988|publisher=Orbis Books|location=Maryknoll, New York, USA|isbn=0883445743|pages=43-44}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Basil held sympathy for those who were [[Unemployment|unemployed]] for no fault of their own, but he held no sympathy for [[:wikt:deadbeat|deadbeat]]s and [[able-bodied]] [[beggar]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cort (1988), 44&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Cort|first=John C.|title=Christian Socialism: An Informal History|year=1988|publisher=Orbis Books|location=Maryknoll, New York, USA|isbn=0883445743|pages=44}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[John Chrysostom]] declared his reasons for his attitude towards the rich and position of attitude towards wealth by saying:
{{quote|''I am often reproached for continually attacking the rich. Yes, because the rich are continually attacking the poor. But those I attack are not the rich as such, only those who misuse their wealth. I point out constantly that those I accuse are not the rich, but the [[rapacious]]; wealth is one thing, covetousness another. Learn to distinguish.''|John Chrysostom.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cort (1988), 45&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Cort|first=John C.|title=Christian Socialism: An Informal History|year=1988|publisher=Orbis Books|location=Maryknoll, New York, USA|isbn=0883445743|pages=45}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===19th century===
In [[Victorian era|Victorian]] Britain, the art critic [[John Ruskin]] in his later life expounded theories about social justice in ''[[Unto This Last]]'' (1860). The painters of the [[Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood]] were influenced and sponsored by Ruskin. The artist [[William Morris]] was a leader of the [[Socialist League (UK, 1885)|Socialist League]] founded in December 1884. The [[Fabian Society]] was founded in the same year; [[Sydney Webb|Sydney]] and [[Beatrice Webb]] were its leading members. [[George Bernard Shaw]] and the members of the [[Bloomsbury Group]] were also influenced by the Fabians. Such Christian socialist thinkers were important in the early history of the [[British Labour party]].

In the November 1914 issue of the ''The Christian Socialist'', Episcopal bishop [[Franklin Spencer Spalding]] of Utah, U.S.A. stated:
&quot;The Christian Church exists for the sole purpose of saving the human race. So far she has failed, but I think that Socialism shows her how she may succeed. It insists that men cannot be made right until the material conditions be made right. Although man cannot live by bread alone, he must have bread. Therefore the Church must destroy a system of society which inevitably creates and perpetuates unequal and unfair conditions of life. These unequal and unfair conditions have been created by competition. Therefore competition must cease and cooperation take its place.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;D.Berman&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Berman|first=David|title=Radicalism in the Mountain West 1890-1920|year=2007|publisher=University Press of Colorado|pages=11–12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the explicit rejection of Socialism, in the more Catholic countries of [[Europe]] the encyclical's teaching was the inspiration that led to the formation of new [[Christian democracy|Christian democratic parties]].

A number of Christian socialist movements and political parties throughout the world group themselves into the [[International League of Religious Socialists]]. It has member organizations in 21 countries representing 200,000 members.

Christian socialists draw parallels between what some have characterized as the [[egalitarian]] and anti-establishment message of [[Jesus]], who&amp;ndash;according to the [[Gospel]]&amp;ndash;spoke against the religious authorities of his time, and the egalitarian, anti-establishment, and sometimes [[anti-clerical]] message of most contemporary socialisms. Some Christian Socialists have become active [[Communism|Communists]]. This phenomenon was most common among [[missionary|missionaries]] in [[China]], the most notable being [[James Gareth Endicott]], who became supportive of the struggle of the [[Communist Party of China]] in the 1930s and 1940s. 

Christian socialism is not to be confused with certain parties with &quot;Christian Social&quot; in their names which are found in the [[German language|German]]-speaking world, such as the contemporary [[Christian Social Union in Bavaria]] or the [[Christian Social Party (Austria)|Christian Social Party]] in [[Austria-Hungary]] c. 1900. Such parties do not claim to be socialist, nor are they considered socialist by others. The term [[Christian Democrat]] is more appropriately applied to the contemporary parties.

==Catholic criticisms==
In [[Catholicism|Roman Catholicism]], Socialism was strongly criticized in the 1878 papal encyclical ''[[Quod Apostolici Muneris]]'' by Pope [[Leo XIII]]. It was again denounced in the 1931 letter ''[[Quadragesimo Anno]]''. Socialists were accused of attempting to overthrow all existing civil society, and Christian socialism was deemed to be an [[oxymoron]] because of this. Pius XI famously wrote at the time that &quot;no one can be at the same time a good Catholic and a true socialist&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,825096,00.html Socialism &amp;amp; the Vatican] ''Time'' magazine, July 8, 1957.&lt;/ref&gt;

The encyclical ''[[Rerum Novarum]]'' [[encyclical]] of Pope Leo XIII from 1891 was the starting point of a teaching on social questions that was expanded and updated all through the 20th century. Despite the introduction of social thought as an object of religious thought, ''Rerum Novarum'' explicitly rejects what it calls &quot;the main tenet of socialism&quot;:

{{quote|&quot;Hence, it is clear that the main tenet of socialism, community of goods, must be utterly rejected, since it only injures those whom it would seem meant to benefit, is directly contrary to the natural rights of mankind, and would introduce confusion and disorder into the commonwealth. The first and most fundamental principle, therefore, if one would undertake to alleviate the condition of the masses, must be the inviolability of private property.&quot; ''Rerum Novarum, paragraph 16''}}

==Christian socialist parties==
* [[Social Christians]] (Italy)
* [[Christian Left Party (Chile)]]
* [[Marc Sangnier]]'s [[Le Sillon]] and then [[Ligue de la jeune République]] (France)
* [[League of Christian Socialists]] (the Netherlands)
* [[Christian Social Party (Netherlands)]]
* [[Christian Social Party (Switzerland)]]
* [[Christian Social Democratic Party]] (Brazil)
* [[Democratic Revival]] (Greece)

==Prominent Christian socialists==
The [[British Labour Party]], [[Australian Labor Party]] and [[New Democratic Party]] of Canada have both been influenced by Christian socialism, and some figures from both parties could be considered to be Christian socialists, depending on the definition of &quot;socialism&quot; used.{{citation needed|date=May 2011}}

Former British Labour leader [[Tony Blair]] is a member of the [[Christian Socialist Movement]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rationalistinternational.net/article/20030827_3_en.htm UK: Tony Blair's pact with God] rationalistinternational.net.&lt;/ref&gt; although his adherence to Christian Socialist ideals is highly disputed, as he is much further to the right than most &quot;socialists&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.workersliberty.org/node/8841 Poplarism, Christianity and Socialism] workersliberty.org, July 14, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

Former [[Australian Prime Minister]] [[Kevin Rudd]] identified himself as an &quot;old-fashioned Christian socialist&quot; in a 2003 interview with ''[[The Australian Financial Review]]'',&lt;ref&gt;Samantha Maiden and Verity Edwards: [http://www.theaustralian.news.com.au/story/0,20867,20930265-2702,00.html Rudd backtracks on socialism] ''The Australian,'' December 15, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; later writing in 2006: &quot;A Christian perspective, informed by a social gospel or Christian socialist tradition, should not be rejected contemptuously by secular politicians as if these views are an unwelcome intrusion into the political sphere.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Kevin Rudd: [http://www.themonthly.com.au/monthly-essays-kevin-rudd-faith-politics--300 Faith in Politics] ''The Monthly,'' October 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; However he also described socialism as an &quot;arcane, 19th century&quot; doctrine and stated that &quot;I am not a socialist. I have never been a socialist and I never will be a socialist.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Michael Gordon and Michelle Grattan: [http://www.theage.com.au/news/national/rudd-rejects-socialism/2006/12/13/1165685753120.html Rudd rejects socialism] ''The Age,'' December 14, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

The following list includes other well-known Christian socialists:
*[[Benigno S. Aquino, Jr.]], martyr of [[Philippines|Philippine]] democracy, who described himself as a &quot;born again&quot; Catholic and a Christian Socialist
*[[Edward Bellamy]], author of ''[[Looking Backward]]''
*[[Francis Bellamy]], original author of the [[Pledge of Allegiance]]
*[[Karl Barth]]
*[[Tony Benn]]
*[[Robert Malachy Burke]]
*[[Walt Brown]]
*[[Hugo Chávez]]
*[[Mauricio Funes]]
*[[Rafael Correa]]
*[[Dorothy Day]]
*[[Percy Dearmer]]
*[[Tommy Douglas]], former Premiere of the Canadian province of Saskatchewan; leader of the first socialist government in North America; father of Canadian medicare. Former leader of the socialist [[Cooperative Commonwealth Federation]] in Canada, which won five back-to-back majority provincial governments in Saskatchewan. Later, when the CCF merged with the Canadian Labour Congress to become the modern-day secular and more social-democratic [[New Democratic Party]] of Canada, Douglas was elected its first leader. The [[New Democratic Party|NDP]] is currently the second largest party in the Canadian House of Commons and the holder of the title of The Official Opposition. According to polls/surveys conducted by the [[Canadian Broadcasting Corporation]] (Canada's public broadcaster), Tommy Douglas has been consistently voted as &quot;The Most Important Canadian&quot; for three years in a row.
*[[Diane Drufenbrock]]
*[[Paulo Freire]], a Brazilian educator and [[critical pedagogy]] theorist
*[[Vekoslav Grmič]], a [[Slovenia]]n [[Roman Catholic]] bishop, writer, essayist and public figure
*[[Thomas J. Hagerty]]
*[[Keir Hardie]]
*[[Chris Hedges]]
*[[Thomas Hughes]]
*[[Fletcher Jones|Sir David Fletcher Jones]]
*[[Toyohiko Kagawa]]
*[[Tetsu Katayama]]
*[[Helen Keller]]
*[[Michael Joseph Savage]], former Prime Minister of New Zealand and leader of the [[New Zealand Labour Party]]
*[[Charles Kingsley]]
*[[Edvard Kocbek]], a [[Slovenia]]n thinker, poet and politician
*[[Janez Evangelist Krek]]
*[[George Lansbury]]
*Father [[Walter Lini]], for whom Christianity and socialism held strong similarities and could be combined to form the basis of [[Melanesian socialism]]
*[[John Malcolm Forbes Ludlow|John Ludlow]]
*[[Margaret MacDonald (spouse)|Margaret MacDonald]], the wife of UK Prime Minister [[Ramsay MacDonald]]
*[[F. O. Matthiessen]]
*[[Frederick Denison Maurice]], founding father of British Christian Socialism, and founder of [[The Working Men's College]].
*[[Jürgen Moltmann]]
*[[Brian Moore (politician)|Brian P. Moore]], a candidate for the 2008 US Presidential elections
*[[Morrissey]]
*[[Reinhold Niebuhr]]
*[[Huub Oosterhuis]]
*[[Karl Polanyi]]
*[[J. K. Rowling]], author, prominently known for the ''[[Harry Potter]]'' series {{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}
*[[Dorothee Sölle]]
*[[Donald Soper, Baron Soper]]
*[[R. H. Tawney]]
*[[Norman Thomas]]
*[[Paul Tillich]]
*[[Cornel West]]
*[[Brooke Foss Westcott]]
*[[Jackson Stitt Wilson]] (1868–1942), a Methodist minister and socialist mayor of Berkeley, California from 1911 to 1913.
*[[Frank P. Zeidler]], ex-Milwaukee mayor and [[Socialist Party USA]] presidential candidate
*[[Michael Moore]], American documentary film-maker.

==Quotes==
&lt;blockquote&gt;
If we all came of the same father and mother, of Adam and Eve, how can they say or prove that they are better than we, if it be not that they make us gain for them by our toil what they spend in their pride? [[John Ball (priest)|John Ball]]&lt;ref&gt;John Richard Green, [http://www.humanitiesweb.org/human.php?s=s&amp;p=l&amp;ID=1904#John%20Ball ''History of the English People'']. Accessed 2007-07-22.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Socialism which means love, cooperation and brotherhood in every department of human affairs, is the only outward expression of a Christian's faith. I am firmly convinced that whether they know it or not, all who approve and accept competition and struggle against each other as the means whereby we gain our daily bread, do indeed betray and make of no effect the &quot;will of God.&quot; [[George Lansbury]]
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Capitalism is the way of the devil and exploitation. If you really want to look at things through the eyes of Jesus Christ&amp;ndash;who I think was the first socialist&amp;ndash;only socialism can really create a genuine society. [[Hugo Chávez]]&lt;ref&gt;Tim Padgett: [http://www.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,1538296,00.html Chavez: &quot;Bush Has Called Me Worse Things&quot;] ''Time'' magazine, September 22, 2006. Accessed 2007-07-22.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==See also==
{{portal|Christianity}}
* [[Agrarian socialism]]
* [[Catholic trade unions]]
* [[Catholic social teaching]]
* [[Christian anarchism]]
* [[Christian communism]]
* [[Christian democracy]]
* [[Liberal Christianity]]
* [[Christian left]]
* [[Christian trade unions]]
* [[Ethical socialism]]
* [[International League of Religious Socialists]]
* [[Liberation theology]]
* [[Political Catholicism]]
* [[Postmodern Christianity]]
* [[Spiritual left]]
* [[Utopian socialism]]
* [[Working Men's College]]
* [[Radical center (politics)]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

===Further reading===
'''Primary sources'''
*Gray, John. ''The Life of Frederick Denison Maurice: Chiefly Told in His Own Letters'' (1885) [http://books.google.com/books?id=llNFAAAAIAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=inauthor:Frederick+inauthor:Maurice&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3 online edition]
*Kingsley, Charles. ''The Works of Charles Kingsley'' (1899) [http://books.google.com/books?id=K53M7IGeFm8C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=inauthor:charles+inauthor:Kingsley&amp;lr=&amp;num=30&amp;as_brr=3 online edition]
*Kingsley, Frances Eliza Grenfell. ''Charles Kingsley: His Letters and Memories of His Life'' (1877) [http://books.google.com/books?id=_uP32Zdvb3cC&amp;pg=PA34&amp;dq=inauthor:charles+inauthor:Kingsley&amp;lr=&amp;num=30&amp;as_brr=3 online edition]
*[[John Bedford Leno|Leno, John Bedford]]. ''The Aftermath with Autobiography of the Author'', Reeves &amp; Turner, London 1892

'''Secondary sources'''
*Bissett, Jim. ''Agrarian socialism in America: Marx, Jefferson, and Jesus in the Oklahoma Countryside, 1904-1920'' [[University of Oklahoma Press]], 1999
*Boyer, John. ''Culture and Political Crisis in Vienna: Christian Socialism in Power, 1897-1918'' (1995)
*Cort, John C. ''Christian Socialism: An Informal History'' (1988)
*Hopkins, Charles Howard. ''The Rise of the Social Gospel in American Protestantism, 1865-1915'' (1940) (Chap. X &quot;Christian Socialism&quot;)
*Phillips, Paul T. ''A Kingdom on Earth: Anglo-American Social Christianity, 1880-1940.'' (1996)
*Young, Shawn David. &quot;[http://www.usask.ca/relst/jrpc/art22%282%29-jesusfreaks.html From Hippies to Jesus Freaks: Christian Radicalism in Chicago’s Inner-City].&quot; ''Journal of Religion and Popular Culture''. Vol 22(2) Summer 2010.

==External links==
{{commons category}}
* [http://www.thecsm.org.uk/ Official site of Christian Socialist Movement (UK)]
* [http://www.religioussocialism.com/vision.html Religious Socialists] Vision Statement of the Religion and Socialism Commission of the Democratic Socialists of America
*[http://faithandsocialism.org/ Socialism and Faith Commission of the Socialist Party USA]
* [http://www.spartacus.schoolnet.co.uk/REsocialism.htm Spartacus Educational on nineteenth-century Christian socialism]
*[http://skeptically.org/bible/id14.html New Testament Supports Socialism]
* [http://www.anglocatholicsocialism.org Anglo-Catholic Socialism]
*[http://www.zompist.com/meetthepoor.html The Bible on the Poor: Or Why God is a Liberal]
* [http://www.americansocialistvoter.com/ American Socialist Voter] Educational and interactive network (non-partisan)

{{Christianity and politics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Christian Socialism}}
[[Category:Christian socialism| ]]
[[Category:Christian philosophy]]
[[Category:Christian politics|Socialism]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]

[[ca:Socialisme cristià]]
[[cs:Křesťanský socialismus]]
[[da:Kristensocialismen]]
[[es:Socialismo cristiano]]
[[fr:Christianisme social]]
[[fy:Kristensosjalisme]]
[[ko:기독교사회주의]]
[[hr:Kršćanski socijalizam]]
[[it:Socialismo cristiano]]
[[kk:Христиан социализмі]]
[[lt:Krikščioniškas socializmas]]
[[nl:Christensocialisme]]
[[ja:キリスト教社会主義]]
[[pl:Socjalizm chrześcijański]]
[[pt:Socialismo cristão]]
[[ru:Христианский социализм]]
[[sk:Kresťanský socializmus]]
[[fi:Kristillinen sosialismi]]
[[sv:Kristen socialism]]
[[zh:基督教社會主義]]</text>
      <sha1>3anaxkrfwhvwhm2ofmp6rj1x0laz1qz</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
