<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Civil registry</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2013678</id>
    <revision>
      <id>518906445</id>
      <parentid>515721468</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-20T18:34:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>95.96.167.155</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* See also */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14703">{{more footnotes|date=June 2011}}
'''Civil registration''' is the system by which a [[government]] records the vital events of its [[citizen]]s and [[Residency (domicile)|resident]]s. The resulting repository or [[database]] is called '''civil register''' or '''registry''', or '''population registry'''. The primary purpose of civil registration is to create legal [[document]]s that are used to establish and protect the [[civil rights]] of individuals. A secondary purpose is to create a data source for the compilation of [[vital statistics (government records)|vital statistics]]. In most countries, there is a legal requirement to notify the relevant authority of any life event which affects the registry.

The [[United Nations]] defines civil registration as &quot;the continuous, permanent, compulsory and universal recording of the occurrence and characteristics of vital events pertaining to the population as provided through [[decree]] or [[regulation]] in accordance with the legal requirements of a country. Civil registration is carried out primarily for the purpose of establishing the legal documents provided by the law. These records are also a main source of vital statistics. Complete coverage, accuracy and timeliness of civil registration are essential for quality vital statistics.&lt;ref&gt;[http://unstats.un.org/UNSD/demographic/sources/civilreg/default.htm United Nations Statistics Division: Civil registration systems]&lt;/ref&gt;

Vital events that are typically recorded include live [[birth]], [[death]], [[stillbirth|foetal death]], [[marriage]], [[divorce]], [[annulment of marriage]], [[legal separation|judicial separation of marriage]], [[adoption]], [[legitimation|legitimization]] and recognition.&lt;ref&gt;[http://unstats.un.org/unsd/publication/SeriesF/SeriesF_84E.pdf  United Nations Handbook on Training in Civil Registration and Vital Statistics Systems (PDF, 33.5MB)]&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, in some countries, [[immigration]], [[emigration]], and any change of residence may require notification. Among the legal documents that are derived from civil registration are [[birth certificate]]s, [[death certificate]]s, and [[marriage certificate]]s.

A [[family register]] is a type of civil register which is more concerned with events within the [[family]] unit and is common in Continental European and Asian countries, such as Germany (''{{lang|de|[[familienbuch]]}}''), France, Spain, Russia (''[[Propiska]]''), China (''[[Hukou system|Hukou]]''), Japan (''[[Koseki]]''), and [[North Korea|North]] and [[South Korea]] (''[[Hoju]]''). A [[resident registration|register of residents]] is a type of civil register primarily concerned with the current [[residency (domicile)|residence]].

==Countries==

===Australia===

In [[Australia]] civil registrations are carried out and held by individual states. [[Tasmania]] began theirs in 1838, [[South Australia]] and [[Western Australia]] both in 1842, [[Victoria (Australia)|Victoria]] in 1854,&lt;ref&gt;[http://access.prov.vic.gov.au/public/component/daPublicBaseContainer?component=daViewFunction&amp;breadcrumbPath=Home/Access%20the%20Collection/Browse%20The%20Collection/Function%20Details&amp;entityId=39 Public Record]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Queensland]] and [[New South Wales]] in 1856,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.justice.qld.gov.au/justice-services/births-deaths-and-marriages Registry of Births, Deaths and Marriages - Queensland]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Northern Territory]] in 1870 and [[Australian Capital Territory]] in 1911. Because early civil registration often involved the churches, it is sometimes difficult to distinguish whether early records are civil or church records. From 1856 civil registration was carried out by government employees and was independent of the church. Information recorded in records varies from state to state. Most states call the appropriate central registry for the state the Office of the Registrar General of Births, Deaths and Marriages. In South Australia it is the Principal Registrar of Births, Deaths and Marriages and in Victoria it is the Government Statist Registry of Births, Deaths and Marriages.

===Iceland===

{{main|Registers Iceland}}

===Mexico===

In Mexico, vital records (birth, death and marriage certificates) are registered in offices named Registro Civil (Civil Registry of Mexico). Each state has its own registration format, but is often standardized if copies are asked at Central Office in Mexico City. In the past decades (until the 1960s), birth certificates were written by hand, on a styled-curive calligraphy (almost incomprehensible by the new generations)and typically issued on green-security paper. After the 1960s, the format in Mexico City didn't change at all, except for instead hand calligraphy, they were issued on typewriter.
But later after, persons who were born in the 1960s or before, if they asked for copies in an office, they had the same hand copy they registered at first, just in the final part, the judge established the new date of issue and the place of.
In the 1980s and 1990s, copies were written by typewriter, but only with capital letters and in the same green-security paper. 
Now, all the copies (from people born before and after 1960s) are standardized in brown-security paper and are typed automatically by a computer, they have already issued the [[CURP]], (national identification number in Mexico) and specific dates of issuing.

===Netherlands===

In the [[Netherlands]], maintaining the civil registry (''Gemeentelijke basisadministratie'') is the duty of the municipalities.

Before the [[History_of_the_Netherlands#Revolution.2C_Republic_and_French_rule|French Rule]], the Netherlands did not have a central registration of its population, which was introduced in some part of the country in 1796 by the French. In 1811, this registration was introduced throughout the country. The Dutch differentiate between the ''Gemeentelijke basisadministratie'', an ongoing database of citizens' information, and the ''Burgerlijke Stand'', which is a collection (at the municipal level) of documents evidencing certain events taking place in a given municipality, such as birth, marriage, [[civil union]], and death.&lt;ref name=seegers/&gt;

Beginning on 1 January 1850, municipalities were obliged to keep citizen's records in bookform. Early in the twentieth century this system was replaced by a card system that registered families. The move toward individual registration took place in 1939 with the introduction of the ''persoonskaart'', a single card registering a single individual, kept in the municipality. Information gathered on this card included family name, first names, gender, position within the family, date and place of birth, marital status, address, and church affiliation, besides information on when a person entered and left a municipality.&lt;ref name=seegers/&gt;

In 1940, the Dutch government did not want to mandate citizen's identification, but during [[World War II]] the German occupying government mandated it so they could assess who was to be sent to Germany as forced labor and to select Jewish citizens from the general population. When the war was over, mandatory identification was done away with.&lt;ref name=seegers&gt;{{cite book|last=Seegers|first=G.H.J.|title=Persoonlijk gegeven - Grepen uit de geschiedenis van bevolkingsregistratie in Nederland|year=1993|publisher=Bekking|location=Amersfoort|coauthors=M.C.C. Wens}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1990s all local registries were automated, and starting on 1 October 1994 the individual registration card was replaced with a digital list containing a person's information as collected by the ''Gemeentelijke basisadministratie van persoonsgegevens'', kept and maintained at the municipal level. Municipalities exchange information through a closed network at the end of each day to a nationwide database, which can be consulted by officials online. Though it was generally considered &quot;un-Dutch,&quot; in 1 January 2005 mandatory identification was reintroduced for everyone over 14; official identification is to be presented for all important transactions between citizens and government.

===South Africa===

In South Africa, vital records are contained in the National Population Register, which is maintained by the national [[Department of Home Affairs (South Africa)|Department of Home Affairs]]. Any Home Affairs office can record a vital event or issue a certified copy of a vital record.

===Sweden===

{{main|Population registration in Sweden}}

In Sweden, the civil registry is maintained by the [[Swedish Tax Agency]] (''Skatteverket''); up into the 1990s the [[Church of Sweden]] was responsible. Recording of births and deaths was stipulated in the early 17th century, formal national [[census]]es have been made since the mid-18th century, and Sweden has one of the longest and most comprehensive suites of civil records of any country.

===United Kingdom===

In the [[United Kingdom]], maintaining the ''civil registry'' is the duty of the [[General Register Office]].

The mandatory civil registration of [[birth]]s, [[marriage]]s, and [[death]]s in [[England and Wales]] was introduced on 1 July 1837.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Herber|first=Mark D.|coauthors=Society of Genealogists (Great Britain)|title=Ancestral trails: the complete guide to British genealogy and family history|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=IFhmAAAAMAAJ|accessdate=30 June 2011|date=1998-03|publisher=Genealogical Pub. Co., Inc|isbn=978-0-8063-1541-6|page=36}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Initially the onus lay on registrars to discover and record events. Subsequent legislation introduced similar systems in [[Ireland]] (all of which was then part of the United Kingdom), and [[Scotland]].

The administration of individual [[registration district]]s is the responsibility of ''registrars'' in the relevant [[local authority]].  There is also a national body for each [[jurisdiction]].  The local offices are generally responsible both for maintaining the original registers and for providing copies to the national body for central retention.  A ''superintendent registrar'' facilitates the legal preliminaries to marriage, conducts civil marriage ceremonies and retains in his/her custody all completed birth, death and marriage registers for the district. The office of the [[superintendent registrar]] is the district  [[Register office]], often referred to (informally) in the media as the &quot;Registry office&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://dictionary.cambridge.org/dictionary/british/registry-office registry office] Cambridge Advanced Learner's Dictionary. Accessed August 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

Today, both officers may also conduct statutory civil partnership preliminaries and ceremonies, citizenship ceremonies and other non statutory ceremonies such as naming or renewal of vows.  Certified copies of the entries made by the registrars over the years are issued on a daily basis either for genealogical research or for modern legal purposes such as supporting passport applications or ensuring eligibility for the appropriate junior sports leagues.  

On 1 December 2007 Registrars and Superintendent Registrars became employees of their local authority for the first time following the enactment of the [[Statistics and Registration Service Act 2007]].

====England and Wales====

Births in England and Wales must be registered within 42 days, whilst deaths must be registered within 5 days unless an inquest is called or a post mortem is held.

Marriages are registered at the time of the ceremony by either (1) the officiating [[Minister (Christianity)|minister]] of the [[Church of England]] or the [[Church in Wales]],   (2) an Authorised Person at a [[Registered Building]], religious,  or (3) a registrar at a [[Register Office]], [[Registered Building]] or [[Approved Premise]].

The official registers are not directly accessible by the general public.  Instead, indexes are made available which can be used to find the relevant register entry and then request a certified copy of the details.  Increasingly local indexes are being published on the internet, for example:  [http://www.nebmd.co.uk]

The [[General Register Office]]&amp;mdash;now merged into the [[Office for National Statistics]]&amp;mdash; has overall responsibility for registration administration.

====Scotland====

Civil registration came into force in [[Scotland]] on January 1, 1855.  A significant difference from the English system is the greater detail required for a registration.  This means that if a certified copy of an entry is requested, it will contain much more information.

The [[General Register Office for Scotland]] has overall responsibility for registration administration and drafting legislative changes in this area (as well as census data).  They are governed by the [[Registration of Births, Deaths and Marriages (Scotland) Act 1965]] and subsequent legislation (responsibility for which has now been devolved to the [[Scottish Parliament]]).

===United States===
In the United States, [[vital records]] such as [[birth certificates]], [[death certificates]], and frequently [[marriage certificate]]s are maintained by the Office of Vital Statistics or Office of Vital Records in each individual state. Other documents such as [[deed]]s, [[Mortgage law|mortgage]] documents, [[name change]] documents, and [[divorce|divorce records]], as well as marriage certificates for those states not centralizing these records,  are maintained by the [[Clerk of Court]] of each individual [[County (United States)|county]]. However, the term 'civil registry' is not used.

==See also==
*[[Births and Deaths Registration Act]]
*[[Resident registration]]
*[[Family register]]

==References==

{{reflist}}

==External links==

'''Australia''':
* [http://www.ntl.nt.gov.au/ask/guides/genealogy Guide to Australian Vital Records at the Northern Territory Library]

'''Republic of Ireland''':
* [http://www.groireland.ie General Register Office]

'''United Kingdom''':
* [http://www.gro.gov.uk General Register Office] (England and Wales)
* [http://www.gro-scotland.gov.uk General Register Office for Scotland]
* [http://www.groni.gov.uk General Register Office Northern Ireland]

'''United States''':
* [http://www.cdc.gov/nchs/w2w.htm Where to Write for U.S. Vital Records]

[[Category:Public records]]
[[Category:Vital statistics]]
[[Category:Genealogy]]
[[Category:Government]]
[[Category:Administrative law]]
[[Category:Civil registries]]

[[cs:Matrika]]
[[da:Civilregistrering]]
[[de:Standesamt]]
[[es:Registro civil]]
[[fr:État civil]]
[[is:Þjóðskrá]]
[[it:Registro dello stato civile]]
[[he:מרשם האוכלוסין]]
[[lt:Civilinės metrikacijos įstaiga]]
[[nl:Burgerlijke stand]]
[[ja:登記所]]
[[pt:Registro civil]]
[[ru:ЗАГС]]
[[vi:Đăng ký hộ tịch]]</text>
      <sha1>3xqusk5yuus5ahfiyl1h6qvj5qrvmp6</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
