<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Class conflict</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>35938460</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521707357</id>
      <parentid>521112900</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-06T18:48:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>50.137.239.154</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Alfred Herrhausen, Germany */ This should be deleted entirely. Herrhausen was assassinated by the RAF, a sect of middle-class &quot;revolutionaries&quot; supported for years by the East German government, not by some sort of Marxian proletarian uprising.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="28757">{{Redirect|Class struggle||Class Struggle (disambiguation){{!}}Class Struggle}}
'''Class conflict''', frequently referred to as '''class warfare''' or '''class struggle''', is the tension or antagonism which exists in [[society]] due to competing [[socioeconomics|socioeconomic]] interests and desires between people of different [[Social class|classes]]. 

Class conflict can take many different forms: direct violence, such as wars fought for resources and cheap labor; indirect violence, such as deaths from poverty, starvation, illness or unsafe working conditions; coercion, such as the threat of losing a job or pulling an important investment; or ideology, either intentionally (as with books and articles promoting [[capitalism]]) or unintentionally (as with the promotion of [[consumerism]] through [[advertising]]). Additionally, political forms of class conflict exist; legally or illegally lobbying or bribing government leaders for passage of partisan desirable legislation including labor laws, tax codes, consumer laws, acts of congress or other sanction, injunction or tariff. The conflict can be open, as with a [[Lockout (industry)|lockout]] aimed at destroying a [[trade union|labor union]], or hidden, as with an informal slowdown in production protesting low wages or [[unfair labor practice]]s.

==Usage==
[[Image:battle strike 1934.jpg|thumb|300px|Teamsters wild-cat strike in Minneapolis, 1934]]
In the past the term ''Class conflict'' was a term used mostly by [[socialism|socialist]]s, who define a class by its relationship to the [[means of production]] — such as factories, land and machinery. From this point of view, the social control of production and labor is a contest between classes, and the division of these resources necessarily involves conflict and inflicts harm. (Marx, 1848) However, in more contemporary times this term is striking chords and finding new definition amongst capitalistic societies in the United States and other Westernized countries. 

[[Marxism|Marxists]] argue that class conflict plays a pivotal role in the history of class-based hierarchical systems such as [[capitalism]] and [[feudalism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=[[The Communist Manifesto]] |last=Marx |first=Karl |coauthors=and others |authorlink=Karl Marx |year=1848 |publisher=www.marxists.org |location=[http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1848/communist-manifesto/ch01.htm]  }}&lt;/ref&gt; Marxists refer to its overt manifestations as class war, a struggle whose resolution in favor of the [[working class]] is viewed by them as inevitable under plutocratic [[capitalism]].

===Pre-capitalist societies===
Where societies are socially divided based on status, wealth, or control of social production and distribution, conflict arises. This conflict is both everyday, such as the common medieval insistence on the right of lords to control access to grain mills and baking ovens, or it can be exceptional such as the Roman [[Conflict of the Orders]], the uprising of [[Spartacus]], or [[Popular revolt in late medieval Europe|the various popular uprisings in late medieval Europe]]. One of the earliest analysis of these conflicts is [[Friedrich Engels]]' [[German Peasants War]].&lt;ref&gt;Frederick Engels, German Peasants War, marxists.org&lt;/ref&gt; One of the earliest analyses of the development of class as the development of conflicts between emergent classes is available in [[Peter Kropotkin]]'s ''[[Mutual Aid: A Factor of Evolution|Mutual Aid]]''. In this work, Kropotkin analyzes the disposal of goods after death in pre-class societies, and how inheritance produces early class divisions and conflict.&lt;ref&gt;Peter Kropotkin, Mutual Aid&lt;/ref&gt;

===21st Century USA===

Predicated on the proposed tax legislation aimed at the wealthy in the USA, conservative news hosts and talk-show commentators are bringing pejorative application to the term class warfare.  Perhaps an ''ad hominem'' attack on the man who reintroduced the term to main-stream America, [[Warren Buffett]], the term in its classic sense, is now being used to describe President Obama's efforts to create the [[Buffett Rule]]. The rule would set a minimum effective tax rate of 30% for those individuals making over $1 million USD annually. FOX News Business Network anchor and investor [[Eric Bolling]], Fox News commentator Steve Moore, political and legal analyst for Fox News Channel [[Andrew Napolitano]], and former speech writer for President [[George W. Bush]], [[Marc Thiessen]] have all used the words class warfare to describe the tax initiative.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Fox Cries Class Warfare|url=http://mediamatters.org/research/201204130001|work=April 13, 2012|publisher=Fox News|accessdate=24 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

In response fellow billionaire and friend to Warren Buffett, [[George Soros]] addresses the pejorative use of the term by the conservative-right by stating, ''&quot;Speaking as a person who would be most hurt by this, I think my fellow hedge fund managers call this class warfare because they don't like to pay more taxes.&quot;''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Sahadi|first=Jeanne|title=Soros: Why I Support the Buffett Rule|url=http://money.cnn.com/2012/02/22/news/economy/obama_corporate_taxes/index.htm|accessdate=24 May 2012|newspaper=CNN|date=April 12, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 

==The USA and similar societies==
The typical example of class conflict described is class conflict within capitalism.  This class conflict is seen to occur primarily between the [[bourgeoisie]] and the [[proletariat]], and takes the form of conflict over hours of work, value of wages, cost of consumer goods, the culture at work, control over [[parliament]] or [[bureaucracy]], and economic inequality.  The particular implementation of government programs which may seem purely humanitarian, such as disaster relief, can actually be a form of class conflict.&lt;ref&gt;Greg Palast, Burn baby burn http://www.gregpalast.com/burn-baby-burnthe-california-celebrity-fires/&lt;/ref&gt; [[Image:Warren Buffett KU Visit.jpg|thumb|left|150px|Philanthropist and billionaire Warren Buffett acknowledging war on the middle-class in the USA]] In the USA class conflict is often noted in labor/management disputes. As far back as 1933 representative Edward Hamilton of ALPA, the [[Air Line Pilots Association, International|Airline Pilot's Association]], used the term &quot;class warfare&quot; to describe airline management's opposition at the National Labor Board hearings in October of that year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Kaps|first=Robert W.|title=Air Transport Labor Relations|year=1997|publisher=Southern Illinois Press|location=Section 3: Major Collective Bargaining Legislation|isbn=0-8093-1776-1|pages=51}}&lt;/ref&gt; Apart from these day-to-day forms of class conflict, during periods of crisis or revolution class conflict takes on a violent nature and involves repression, assault, restriction of civil liberties, and murderous violence such as assassinations or death squads. (Zinn, ''People's History'')

===Thomas Jefferson, USA===
Although [[Thomas Jefferson]] (1744–1826) led the United States as president from 1801–1809 and is considered one of the founding fathers, he died with immense amounts of debt. About class warfare, Thomas Jefferson is quoted as saying, &quot;''Experience demands that man is the only animal which devours his own kind, for I can apply no milder term to the general prey of the rich on the poor.''&quot;
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Jefferson|first=Thomas|title=On Class Warfare|url=http://www.brainyquote.com/quotes/quotes/t/thomasjeff157223.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Warren Buffett, USA===

In 2012, and the years leading up to it, renowned investor and [[philanthropist]] [[Warren Buffett]] has often found himself on the list of the top 10 wealthiest men in the world. In November 2006 Buffett commented in an interview with [[The New York Times]], &quot;''There’s class warfare all right, but it’s my class, the rich class, that’s making war, and we’re winning.''&lt;ref name=&quot;Warren Buffet Admits the Middle-Class are under Siege&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Buffett|first=Warren|title=Market Watch|url=http://articles.marketwatch.com/2011-11-01/commentary/30790373_1_class-warfare-warren-buffett-rich-class|newspaper=The Wall Street Journal|date=Nov. 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&quot; Shortly after issuing the quote Warren gave away more than half of his fortune to charitable causes through a program developed by himself and computer software tycoon [[Bill Gates]].&lt;ref name=&quot;The Giving Pledge&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Warren Buffett Gives Away Fortune|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/04/20/giving-pledge-warren-buffett-bill-gates_n_1441387.html|accessdate=16 May 2012|newspaper=Huffington Post|date=4/12/2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Later in 2011 Buffett called on government legislators to, &quot;''...stop coddling the super rich.''&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Buffett|first=Warren|title=Stop Coddling the Super Rich|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/08/15/opinion/stop-coddling-the-super-rich.html|accessdate=16 May 2012|newspaper=The New York Times|date=Nov. 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Max Weber, Germany===
[[Max Weber]] (1864–1920) agrees with the fundamental ideas of Karl Marx about the economy causing class conflict, but claims that class conflict can also stem from prestige and power.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blackwell&quot;/&gt; Weber argues that classes come from the different property locations. Different locations can largely affect one's class by their education and the people they associate with.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blackwell&quot;/&gt; He also states that prestige results in different status groupings. This prestige is based upon the social status of one's parents. Prestige is an attributed value and many times cannot be changed. Weber states that power differences led to the formation of [[political parties]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Blackwell&quot;/&gt; Weber disagrees with Marx about the formation of classes. While Marx believes that groups are similar due to their economic status, Weber argues that classes are largely formed by [[social status]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Blackwell&quot;/&gt; Weber does not believe that communities are formed by economic standing, but by similar social prestige.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blackwell&quot;/&gt; Weber does recognize that there is a relationship between social status, social prestige and classes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blackwell&quot;/&gt;

==Muslim societies (Arab Spring)==

Numerous factors have culminated in what's known as the [[Arab Spring]]. Agenda behind the civil unrest, and the ultimate overthrow of totalitarian governments throughout the [[Middle-East]] included issues such as dictatorship or [[absolute monarchy]], [[human rights|human rights violations]], [[government corruption]] (demonstrated by [[United States diplomatic cables leak|Wikileaks diplomatic cables]]),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.counterpunch.org/cockburn02182011.html|title=The Tweet and Revolution|first=Alexander|last=Cockburn|date=18–20 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; economic decline, unemployment, extreme poverty, and a number of demographic structural factors,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=[[Korotayev]] A, Zinkina J |url=http://cliodynamics.ru/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=276&amp;Itemid=70 |title=Egyptian Revolution: A Demographic Structural Analysis |journal=Entelequia. Revista Interdisciplinar |volume=13 |year=2011 |pages=139–165}}&lt;/ref&gt; such as a large percentage of educated but dissatisfied youth within the population.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=arab+league+demographics|title=Demographics of the Arab League, computed by Wolfram Alpha}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also, some, like Slovenian philosopher [[Slavoj Žižek]] attribute the [[2009 Iranian protests]] as one of the reasons behind the Arab Spring.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aljazeera.com/news/middleeast/2011/05/201156113955925329.html|title=Ahmadinejad row with Khamenei intensifies|date=6 May 2011|work=Al Jazeera}}&lt;/ref&gt; The catalysts for the revolts in all [[North Africa|Northern African]] and [[Persian Gulf countries]] have been the concentration of wealth in the hands of autocrats in power for decades, insufficient transparency of its redistribution, corruption, and especially the refusal of the youth to accept the status quo.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Ecker, Al-Riffai, Perrihan|title=Economics of the Arab awakening|url=http://www.ifpri.org/publication/economics-arab-awakening|publisher=International Food Policy Research Institute|accessdate=25 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2012/04/08/opinion/sunday/friedman-the-other-arab-spring.html ''The Other Arab Spring''] April 7, 2012 [[Thomas L. Friedman]] New York Times Op Ed&lt;/ref&gt; as they involve threats to [[food security]] worldwide and prices that approach levels of the [[2007–2008 world food price crisis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Javid|first=Salman Ansari|title=Arab dictatorships inundated by food price protests|url=http://www.tehrantimes.com/index_View.asp?code=234768|accessdate=13 February 2011|newspaper=Tehran Times|date=27 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Amnesty International]] singled out [[Wikileaks]]' release of [[United States diplomatic cables leak|US diplomatic cables]] as a catalyst for the revolts.&lt;ref&gt;Peter Walker ''[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/may/13/amnesty-international-wikileaks-arab-spring? Amnesty International hails WikiLeaks and Guardian as Arab spring 'catalysts']'', in ''[[The Guardian]]'', Friday 13 May 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

==The Soviet Union and similar societies==
A variety of predominantly Marxist and anarchist thinkers argue that class conflict exists in [[Soviet Union|Soviet-style societies]].  These arguments describe as a class the bureaucratic [[stratum]] formed by the ruling [[political party]] (known as the Nomenklatura in the Soviet Union) — sometimes termed a &quot;[[new class]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | first = Milovan | last = Đilas | authorlink = Milovan Đilas | year = 1983, 1957 | title = The New Class: An Analysis of the Communist System | edition = paperback | publisher = Harcourt Brace Jovanovich | location = San Diego | isbn = 0-15-665489-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; --that controls the means of production. This ruling class is viewed to be in opposition to the remainder of society, generally considered the [[proletariat]].  This type of system is referred to by its detractors as [[state capitalism]], [[state socialism]], [[bureaucratic collectivism]] or [[new class]] societies. (Cliff; Ðilas 1957) Marxism was such a predominate ideological power in what became the Soviet Union since a Marxist group known as the Russian Social Democratic Labour Party was formed in the country, prior to 1917. This party soon divided into two main factions; the Bolsheviks, who were led by [[Vladimir Lenin]], and the Mensheviks, who were led by Julius Martov.

==Marxist perspectives==
[[Image:Karl Marx 001.jpg|thumb|right|175px|Karl Marx, 1875]]
Karl Marx (1818–1883) was a German born philosopher who lived the majority of his adult life in England. In ''[[The Communist Manifesto]]'', [[Karl Marx]]  argued that a [[Social class|class]] is formed when its members achieve class consciousness and solidarity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blackwell&quot;&gt;Blackwell Reference Online.''[http://www.blackwellreference.com.libproxy.lib.unc.edu/subscriber/uid=834/tocnode?id=g9781405124331_chunk_g97814051243319_ss1-50]''. Retrieved November 24, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; This largely happens when the members of a class become aware of their [[exploitation]] and the conflict with another class. A class will then realize their shared interests and a common identity. According to Marx, a class will then take action against those that are exploiting the lower classes.

What Marx points out is that members of each of the two main classes have interests in common. These class or collective interests are in conflict with those of the other class as a whole. This in turn leads to conflict between individual members of different classes. 

Marxist analysis of society identifies two main social groups: 
* ''Labour'' (the [[proletariat]] or workers) includes anyone who earns their livelihood by selling their [[labor power]] and being paid a wage or salary for their labor time. They have little choice but to work for capital, since they typically have no independent way to survive.
* ''Capital'' (the [[bourgeoisie]] or capitalists) includes anyone who gets their income not from labor as much as from the [[surplus value]] they appropriate from the workers who create wealth. The income of the capitalists, therefore, is based on their [[Exploitation (Marxism)|exploitation]] of the workers (proletariat).

Not all class struggle is violent or necessarily radical, as with strikes and lockouts. Class antagonism may instead be expressed as low worker morale, minor sabotage and pilferage, and individual workers' abuse of petty authority and hoarding of information. It may also be expressed on a larger scale by support for socialist or populist parties. On the employers' side, the use of union busting legal firms and the lobbying for anti-union laws are forms of class struggle.

Not all class struggle is a threat to capitalism, or even to the authority of an individual capitalist. A narrow struggle for higher wages by a small sector of the working-class, what is often called &quot;economism&quot;, hardly threatens the status quo. In fact, by applying the craft-union tactics of excluding other workers from skilled trades, an economistic struggle may even weaken the working class as a whole by dividing it. Class struggle becomes more important in the historical process as it becomes more general, as industries are organized rather than crafts, as workers' class consciousness rises, and as they self-organize away from political parties. Marx referred to this as the progress of the proletariat from being a class &quot;in itself&quot;, a position in the social structure, to being one &quot;for itself&quot;,an active and conscious force that could change the world.

Marx largely focuses on the capital industrialist society as the source of [[social stratification]], which ultimately results in class conflict.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blackwell&quot;/&gt; He states that capitalism creates a division between classes which can largely be seen in manufacturing factories. The proletariat, is separated from the bourgeoisie because production becomes a social enterprise. Contributing to their separation is the technology that is in factories. Technology de-skills and alienates workers as they are no longer viewed as having a specialized skill.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blackwell&quot;/&gt; Another effect of technology is a homogenous [[workforce]] that can be easily replaceable. Marx believed that this class conflict would result in the overthrow of the bourgeoisie and that the private property would be communally owned.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blackwell&quot;/&gt; The mode of [[Production (economics)|production]] would remain, but communal ownership would eliminate class conflict.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blackwell&quot;/&gt;

Even after a revolution, the two classes would struggle, but eventually the struggle would recede and the classes dissolve. As class boundaries broke down, the state apparatus would wither away. According to Marx, the main task of any state apparatus is to uphold the power of the ruling class; but without any classes there would be no need for a state. That would lead to the classless, stateless communist society.

== Non-Marxist perspectives ==
{{Expand section|date=November 2010}}
Social commentators, historians and socialist theorists had commented on class struggle for some time before Marx, as well as the connection between class struggle, property, and law: [[Augustin Thierry]],&lt;ref&gt;Augustin Thierry: [http://books.google.lu/books?id=c5A1lIZb5H8C&amp;dq=Histoire+du+Tiers+%C3%89tat&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s Recueil des monuments inédits de l'histoire du Tiers état]&lt;/ref&gt; [[François Guizot]], [[François-Auguste Mignet]] and [[Adolphe Thiers]]. The [[Physiocrat]]s, [[David Ricardo]], and after Marx, [[Henry George]] noted the inelastic supply of land and argued that this created certain privileges ([[economic rent]]) for landowners. According to the historian [[Arnold Toynbee]], stratification along lines of class appears only within civilizations, and furthermore only appears during the process of a civilization's decline while not characterizing the growth phase of a civilization.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Toynbee|first=Arnold|title=A Study of History: Abridgment of Volumes I - VI|year=1947|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=New York, NY|isbn=0-19-505081-9|editor=Dorothea Grace Somervell|page=365|language=English|chapter=The Nature of Disintegration}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Proudhon, in ''[[What is Property?]]'' (1840) states that &quot;certain classes do not relish investigation into the pretended titles to property, and its fabulous and perhaps scandalous history.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Pierre Proudhon, ''What is Property?'', chapter 2, remark 2.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Fascists]] have often opposed class struggle and instead have attempted to appeal to the working class while promising to preserve the existing social classes and have proposed an alternative concept known as [[class collaboration]].

== Class vs. race struggle ==
[[File:NORTH PHILADELPHIA JOBLESS BLACKS. MAN STANDING AT RIGHT IS GERALD &quot;HEAT WAVE&quot; JONES, WHO WORKS FOR &quot;THE NETWORK&quot;, A... - NARA - 552754.tif|left|400px|thumb|Jobless Black workers in the heat of the Philadelphia summer, 1973]] 
According to [[Michel Foucault]], in the 19th century the [[essentialist]] notion of the &quot;[[Race (classification of human beings)|race]]&quot; was incorporated by [[racism|racists]], [[biologists]], and [[eugenicists]], who gave it the modern sense of &quot;biological race&quot; which was then integrated to &quot;[[state racism]]&quot;. On the other hand, Foucault claims that when [[Marxists]] developed their concept of &quot;class struggle&quot;, they were partly inspired by the older, non-biological notions of the &quot;race&quot; and the &quot;race struggle&quot;. In a letter to Friedrich Engels in 1882 Karl Marx wrote: ''You know very well where we found our idea of class struggle; we found it in the work of the French historians who talked about the race struggle.''&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in ''Society Must be Defended'' by Michel Foucault (trans. [[David Macey]]), London: Allen Lane, Penguin Press (1976, 2003), p. 79&lt;/ref&gt; For Foucault, the theme of social war provides the overriding principle that connects class and race struggle.&lt;ref&gt;Ann Laura Stoler, ''Race and the Education of Desire: Foucault's &quot;History of Sexuality&quot; and the Colonial Order of Things '', Duke University Press (1995), p.71-72&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Moses Hess]], an important theoretician of the early socialist movement, in his &quot;Epilogue&quot; to &quot;[[Rome and Jerusalem]]&quot; argued that &quot;the race struggle is primary, the class struggle secondary... With the cessation of race [[antagonism (philosophy)|antagonism]], the class struggle will also come to a standstill. The equalization of all classes of society will necessarily follow the [[emancipation]] of all the races, for it will ultimately become a scientific question of social economics.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;quoted in ''Prophecy and Politics: Socialism, Nationalism, and the Russian Jews'' by Jonathan Frankel, Cambridge University Press (1981), p. 22.&lt;/ref&gt;  

In modern times, emerging schools of thought in the U.S. and other countries hold the opposite to be true.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Eastwood|first1=John H.|authorlink1=John H. Eastwood|title=The Wonder of Grace|year=1995|publisher=Companion Press|location=Shippensburg, Pennsylvania|isbn=1-56043-572-0|page=18|chapter=Chapter 3: Ye Are the Salt of the Earth|quote=The system that was supposed to treat all men equally actually created a class society.}}&lt;/ref&gt; They argue that the race struggle is less important, because the primary struggle is that of class since labor of all races face the same problems and injustices.  The main example given is the United States, which has the most politically weak working class of any developed nation, where race is held as a distraction that has kept labor divided and unorganized.&lt;ref&gt;The Tavis Smiley Show/NPR, various interviews.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Chronology==
Riots with a basically nationalist background are not included.

===Classical antiquity===
*[[Roman Servile Wars]]

===Middle Ages===
*[[Ciompi]] in Florence 1378
*[[Jacquerie]] - France 14th century

===Modern era===
*[[German Peasants' War]] since 1524
*[[English Civil War]] (1642–1651) ([[Diggers]])
*[[French Revolution]] since 1789&lt;ref&gt;see Daniel Guérin, Class Struggle in the First French Republic, Pluto Press 1977&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Canut revolts]] in [[Lyon]] since 1831 - often considered as the beginning of the modern [[labor movement]]
*[[Revolutions of 1848]] France (et al.)
*[[Paris Commune]] 1871
*[[Donghak Peasant Revolution]] in Korea 1893/94
*[[1907 Romanian Peasants' Revolt]]
*[[Mexican Revolution]] since 1910
*[[October Revolution]] in 1917
*[[Spartacist uprising]] in Germany 1919
*[[Seattle General Strike of 1919]] in [[Seattle]]
*[[Anarchism in Spain#General Strike of 1919|General Strike of 1919]] in [[Spain]]
*[[Winnipeg General Strike]] 1919
*[[Ruhr Uprising]] in Germany 1920
*[[Kronstadt rebellion]] 1921
*[[Hamburg Uprising]] 1923
*[[1926 United Kingdom general strike]]
*[[1934 West Coast waterfront strike]]
*[[Spanish Civil War]] 1936-1939
*[[Uprising of 1953 in East Germany]]
*[[Cuban Revolution]] 1953-1959
*[[Hungarian Revolution of 1956]] - foundation of [[worker's council]]s
*[[Poznań 1956 protests]]
*[[Mai 68]] in France
*[[Battle of Valle Giulia]] 1968 [[Italy]]
*[[Wildcat strike action|Wild cat]]s in Western Germany in 1969
*[[Winter of Discontent]] 1978/79
*[[UK miners' strike (1984–1985)]]
*[[1993 Russian constitutional crisis]]
*[[2006 Oaxaca protests]] in Mexico
*[[2008 Greek riots]]
*[[2010 Kyrgyzstani uprising]]
*[[Egyptian Revolution of 2011]]
*[[2011 England riots]]

==See also==
{{wikiquote}}
{|
*[[Class consciousness]]
*[[Classism]]
*[[Classless society]]
*[[Conflict of the Orders]]
*[[Deformed workers state]]
*[[Degenerated workers state]]
*[[Economic inequality]]
*[[Economic stratification]]
*[[Exploitation]]
|
*[[Harmonious Society]]
*[[Johnson County War]]
*[[trade union|Labor union]]
*[[No War But The Class War]]
*[[Popular revolt in late medieval Europe]]
*[[Revolution]]
*[[Social class]]
*[[Sharecropping]]
*[[Slave rebellion]]
*[[Taxation]]
|}

== References ==
{{refimprove|date=January 2012}}
{{Reflist}}

== Further reading ==
*&lt;cite&gt; Class &amp; Class Conflict in Industrial Society&lt;/cite&gt;,Ralf Dahrendorf, Stanford University Press, 1959, trade paperback, 336 pages, ISBN 0-8047-0561-5 (also available in hardback as ISBN 0-8047-0560-7 and ISBN 1-131-15573-4).
*&lt;cite&gt;The Global Class War: How America's Bipartisan Elite Lost Our Future and What It Will Take to Win It Back &lt;/cite&gt; Jeff Faux, John Wiley and Sons.  2006. ISBN 978-0-471-69761-9
*&lt;cite&gt;Li Yi. 2005. The Structure and Evolution of Chinese Social Stratification. &lt;/cite&gt; University Press of America. ISBN 0-7618-3331-5
*''The International Encyclopedia of Revolution and Protest: 1500 to the Present'', ed. by Immanuel Ness, Malden, MA [etc.]: Wiley &amp; Sons, 2009.
*[[Louis Adamic]], ''Dynamite: The story of class violence in America'', Revised Edition (1934)
* Leo Zeilig (Editor), ''Class Struggle and Resistance in Africa'', New Clarion Press, 2002.
*Gerson Antell/Walter Harris, &quot;Economics For Everybody&quot;, Amsco School Publications, 2007

==External links==
*[http://www.democracynow.org/2010/9/3/study_ceos_who_fired_most_workers 2008-2010 Study: CEOs Who Fired Most Workers Earned Highest Pay] - video report by ''[[Democracy Now!]]''
* [http://www.blairmountainmuseum.org/ Blair Community Center and Museum] to help preserve and understand the largest labor uprising in US history -- the Battle of Blair Mountain.

{{DEFAULTSORT:Class Conflict}}
[[Category:Socialism]]
[[Category:Political science]]
[[Category:Social classes]]

[[br:Emgann ar renkadoù]]
[[ca:Lluita de classes]]
[[cs:Třídní boj]]
[[da:Klassekamp]]
[[de:Klassenkampf]]
[[el:Πάλη των τάξεων]]
[[en:Class struggle]]
[[eo:Klasbatalo]]
[[es:Lucha de clases]]
[[et:Klassivõitlus]]
[[eu:Klase-borroka]]
[[fi:Luokkataistelu]]
[[fr:Lutte des classes]]
[[gl:Loita de clases]]
[[he:מלחמת מעמדות]]
[[hi:वर्ग संघर्ष]]
[[hr:Klasna borba]]
[[id:Perjuangan kelas]]
[[it:Prospettiva del conflitto]]
[[ja:階級闘争]]
[[ka:პროლეტარიატის ბრძოლა]]
[[kk:Антагонизм]]
[[ko:계급 투쟁]]
[[lt:Klasių kova]]
[[mk:Класна борба]]
[[nl:Klassenstrijd]]
[[nn:Klassekamp]]
[[no:Klassekamp]]
[[pl:Walka klas]]
[[pt:Luta de classes]]
[[ro:Luptă de clasă]]
[[ru:Классовая борьба]]
[[simple:Class struggle]]
[[sk:Triedny boj]]
[[sv:Klasskamp]]
[[th:การต่อสู้ระหว่างชนชั้น]]
[[tr:Sınıf mücadelesi]]
[[uk:Класова боротьба]]
[[uz:Sinfiy kurash]]
[[zh:阶级斗争]]</text>
      <sha1>fosvouwpeqxx94qie6yegmiuytvqq0u</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
