<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Collective action</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>194072</id>
    <revision>
      <id>516749142</id>
      <parentid>514386627</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-09T02:24:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>198.147.127.104</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Collective action problem */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="19888">{{sociology}}

'''Collective action''' is traditionally defined as any action aiming to improve the group’s conditions (such as status or power), which is enacted by a representative of the group.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wright, Taylor &amp; Moghaddam (1990)&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last = Wright|first = S.C.|last2=Taylor|first2=D.M.|last3=Moghaddam|first3=F.M.|title = Responding to membership in a disadvantaged group: From acceptance to collective protest|journal = Journal of Personality and Social Psychology|volume = 58| pages = 994–1003|year = 1990}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is a term that has formulations and theories in many areas of the social sciences including psychology, sociology, political science and economics.

==In social psychology==

===Social Identity Model of Collection Action===
Researchers Martijn van Zomeren, Tom Postmes, and Russell Spears conducted a meta-analysis of over 180 studies of collective action, in an attempt to integrate three dominant socio-psychological perspectives explaining antecedent conditions to this phenomenon – injustice, efficacy, and identity.&lt;ref name=&quot;van Zomeren, Postmes, &amp; Spears (2008)&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last = van Zomeren|first = M.|last2=Postmes|first2=T.|last3=Spears|first3=R.|title = Toward an integrative social identity model of collective action: A quantitative research synthesis of three socio-psychological perspectives|journal = Psychological Bulletin|volume = 134| issue = 4| pages = 504–535|year = 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; In their resultant 2008 review article, an integrative Social Identity Model of Collective Action (SIMCA) was proposed which accounts for interrelationships among the three predictors as well as their predictive capacities for collective action.&lt;ref name=&quot;van Zomeren, Postmes, &amp; Spears (2008)&quot;/&gt; An important assumption of this approach is that people tend to respond to subjective states of disadvantage, which may or may not flow from objective physical and social reality.

====Perceived injustice====
Examining collective action through perceived injustice was initially guided by [[Relative deprivation theory|relative deprivation theory (RDT)]]. RDT focuses on a subjective state of unjust disadvantage, proposing that engaging in fraternal (group-based) social comparisons with others may result in feelings of relative deprivation that foster collective action. Group-based emotions resulting from perceived injustice, such as anger, are thought to motivate collective action in an attempt to rectify the state of unfair deprivation.&lt;ref name=&quot;van Zomeren, Postmes, &amp; Spears (2008)&quot;/&gt; Meta-analysis results confirm that effects of injustice causally predict collective action, highlighting the theoretical importance of this variable.&lt;ref name=&quot;van Zomeren, Postmes, &amp; Spears (2008)&quot;/&gt;

====Perceived efficacy====
Moving beyond RDT, scholars suggested that in addition to a sense of injustice, people must also have the objective, structural resources necessary to [[Resource mobilization|mobilize change]] through social protest. An important psychological development saw this research instead directed towards subjective expectations and beliefs that unified effort (collective action) is a viable option for achieving group-based goals – this is referred to as perceived collective efficacy. Empirically, collective efficacy is shown to causally affect collective action among a number of populations across varied contexts.&lt;ref name=&quot;van Zomeren, Postmes, &amp; Spears (2008)&quot;/&gt;

====Social identity====
[[Social identity theory|Social Identity Theory (SIT)]] suggests that people strive to achieve and maintain positive social identities associated with their group memberships.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tajfel &amp; Turner (1979)&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last = Tajfel|first = H.|last2=Turner|first2=J.C.|title = An integrative theory of inter-group conflict. In W.G. Austin &amp; S. Worchel (Eds.)|journal = The social psychology of inter-group relations|volume = (pp. 33-47)| pages = Monterey, CA: Brooks/Cole|year = 1979}}&lt;/ref&gt; Where a group membership is disadvantaged (for example, low status), SIT implicates three variables in the evocation of collective action to improve conditions for the group – permeability of group boundaries,&lt;ref name=&quot;Wright, Taylor &amp; Moghaddam (1990)&quot;/&gt; legitimacy of the intergroup structures, and the stability of these relationships. For example, when disadvantaged groups perceive intergroup status relationships as illegitimate and unstable, collective action is predicted to occur, in an attempt to change status structures for the betterment of the disadvantaged group.

Meta-analysis results also confirm that social identity causally predicts collective action across a number of diverse contexts. Additionally, the integrated SIMCA affords another important role to social identity – that of a psychological bridge forming the collective base from which both collective efficacy and group injustice may be conceived.

===Model refinement===
While there is sound empirical support for the causal importance of SIMCA’s key theoretical variables on collective action,&lt;ref name=&quot;van Zomeren, Postmes, &amp; Spears (2008)&quot;/&gt; more recent literature has addressed the issue of reverse causation, finding support for a related, yet distinct, encapsulation model of social identity in collective action (EMSICA).&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas, Mavor &amp; McGarty (2011)&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last = Thomas|first = E.F.|last2=Mavor|first2=K.I.|last3=McGarty|first3=C.|title = Social identities facilitate and encapsulate action-relevant constructs: A test of the social identity model of collective action|journal = Group Processes and Intergroup Relations|volume = 15| issue = 1| pages = 75–88|year = 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; This model suggests that perceived group efficacy and perceived injustice provide the basis from which social identity emerges, highlighting an alternative causal pathway to collective action. Recent research has sought to integrate SIMCA with [[Contact hypothesis|intergroup contact theory]] (see Cakal, Hewstone, Schwär, &amp; Heath&lt;ref name=&quot;Cakal, Hewstone, Schwär &amp; Heath (2011)&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last = Cakal|first = H.|last2=Hewstone|first2=M.|last3=Schwär|first3=G.|last4=Heath|first4=A.|title = An investigation of the social identity model of collective action and the 'sedative' effect of intergroup contact among Black and White students in South Africa|journal = British Journal of Social Psychology|volume = 50| pages = 606–627|year = 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;) and others have extended SIMCA through bridging morality research with the collective action literature (see van Zomeren, Postmes, &amp; Spears&lt;ref name=&quot;van Zomeren, Postmes, &amp; Spears (2012)&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last = van Zomeren|first = M.|last2=Postmes|first2=T.|last3=Spears|first3=R.|title = On conviction's collective consequences: Integrating moral conviction with the social identity model of collective action|journal = British Journal of Social Psychology|volume = 51| pages = 52–71|year = 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; for a review).

==In sociology==
As an explanation of social movements, an inquiry into collective action involves examining those factors that cause the setting of standards of social integration, as well as those factors which lead to standards of deviance and conflict. An explanation of a collective action in sociology will involve the explanation of those things which are similar or dissimilar to collective actions at different times and in different places. Theories of collective action emphasise how group behavior can, in some sense, be linked to social [[institution]]s.

== In political science and economics ==
The economic theory of collective action is concerned with the provision of [[public good]]s (and other collective consumption) through the [[collaboration]] of two or more individuals, and the impact of [[externality|externalities]] on group behavior. It is more commonly referred to as [[Public Choice]].  [[Mancur Olson]]'s 1965 book ''[[The Logic of Collective Action|The Logic of Collective Action: Public Goods and the Theory of Groups]],'' is an important early analysis of the problems of public good cost.

Besides economics, the theory has found many applications in [[political science]], [[sociology]], [[communication]], [[anthropology]] and [[environmentalism]].

===Collective action problem===
The term &quot;collective action problem&quot; describes the situation in which multiple individuals would all benefit from a certain action, but has an associated cost making it implausible that any one individual can or will undertake and solve it alone. The rational choice is then to undertake this as a collective action the cost of which is shared.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |last=Dowding |first=Keith |authorlink=Keith Dowding |year=1996 |title=Power |pages=31&amp;nbsp;''ff.'' |publisher=University of Minnesota Press |isbn= 0-8166-2941-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Exploitation of the great by the small===
[[Mancur Olson]] made the highly controversial claim that individual [[Rational choice theory|rational choice]] leads to situations where individuals with more resources will carry a higher burden in the provision of the public good than poorer ones.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=Olson|first=Mancur|title=logic of collective action: Public goods and the theory of groups|year=1965|publisher=Harvard University Press|location=Cambridge, MA}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- why exactly is this so controversial? --&gt; Poorer individuals will usually have little choice but to opt for the [[Free rider problem|free rider]] strategy, i.e. they will attempt to benefit from the public good without contributing to its provision. This may also encourage the under-production (inefficient production) of the public good.

===Institutional design===
While public goods are often provided by governments, this is not always the case.  Various institutional designs have been studied with the aim of reducing the collaborative failure.  The best design for a given situation depends on the production costs, the utility function, and the collaborative effects, amongst other things.  Here are only some examples:

====Joint products====
A joint-product model analyzes the collaborative effect of joining a private good to a public good.  For example, a tax deduction (private good) can be tied to a donation to a charity (public good).

It can be shown that the provision of the public good increases when tied to the private good, as long as the private good is provided by a monopoly (otherwise the private good would be provided by competitors without the link to the public good).

====Clubs====
Some institutional design, e.g. [[Intellectual property|intellectual property rights]], can introduce an exclusion mechanism and turn a pure [[public good]] into an impure public good artificially.

If the costs of the exclusion mechanism are not higher than the gain from the [[collaboration]], clubs can emerge.  [[James M. Buchanan]] showed in his seminal paper that clubs can be an efficient alternative to government interventions.{{Citation needed|date=August 2007}}

A [[nation]] can be seen as a club whose members are its citizens.  Government would then be the manager of this club.

====Federated structure====
In some cases, theory shows that collaboration emerges spontaneously in smaller groups rather than in large ones (see e.g. [[Dunbar's number]]). This explains why [[trade union|labor unions]] or [[Charitable organization|charities]] often have a federated structure.

==In philosophy==
Over the past twenty years or so analytic philosophers have been exploring the nature of collective action in the sense of acting together, as when people paint a house together, go for a walk together, or together execute a pass play. These particular examples have been central for three of the philosophers who have made well known contributions to this literature:  [[Michael Bratman]], [[Margaret Gilbert]], and [[John Searle]], respectively.

In {{Harv|Gilbert|1989}} and subsequent articles and book chapters including Gilbert (2006, chapter 7) Gilbert argues for an account of collective action according to which this rests on a special kind of interpersonal commitment, what Gilbert calls a &quot;joint commitment&quot;. A joint commitment in Gilbert's sense is not a matter of a set of personal commitments independently created by each of the participants, as when each makes a personal decision to do something. Rather, it is a single commitment to whose creation each participant makes a contribution. Thus suppose that one person says &quot;Shall we go for a walk?&quot; and the other says &quot;Yes, let's&quot;. Gilbert proposes that as a result of this exchange the parties are jointly committed to go for a walk, and thereby obligated to one another to act as if they were parts of a single person taking a walk. Joint commitments can be created less explicitly and through processes that are more extended in time. One merit of a joint commitment account of collective action, in Gilbert's view, is that it explains the fact that those who are out on a walk together, for instance, understand that each of them is in a position to demand corrective action of the other if he or she acts in ways that affect negatively the completion of their walk. In {{Harv|Gilbert|2006a}} she discusses the pertinence of joint commitment to collective actions in the sense of the theory of rational choice.

In Searle (1990) Searle argues that what lies at the heart of a collective action is the presence in the mind of each participant of a &quot;we-intention&quot;. Searle does not give an account of we-intentions or, as he also puts it, &quot;collective intentionality&quot;, but insists that they are distinct from the &quot;I-intentions&quot; that animate the actions of persons acting alone.

In Bratman (1993) Bratman proposed that, roughly, two people &quot;share an intention&quot; to paint a house together when each intends that the house is painted by virtue of the activity of each, and also intends that it is so painted by virtue of the intention of each that it is so painted. That these conditions obtain must also be &quot;common knowledge&quot; between the participants.

Discussion in this area continues to expand, and has influenced discussions in other disciplines including anthropology, developmental psychology, and economics. One general question is whether it is necessary to think in terms that go beyond the personal intentions of individual human beings properly to characterize what it is to act together. Bratman's account does not go beyond such personal intentions. Gilbert's account, with its invocation of joint commitment, does go beyond them. Searle's account does also, with its invocation of collective intentionality. The question of whether and how one must account for the existence of mutual obligations when there is a collective intention is another of the issues in this area of inquiry.

==Collective action as a response to climate change==
{{See also|Climate change}}
[[Climate change]] has been described by the [[Stern Review]] as a problem to be solved by international cooperation. It stated that 'no two countries will face exactly the same situation in terms of impacts or the costs and benefits of action, and no country can take effective action to control the risks that they face alone. International collective action to tackle the problem is required because climate... is a global [[public good]] — and because co-operative action will greatly reduce the costs of both mitigation and adaption.  The international collective response to the climate change problem required is therefore unique, both in terms of its complexity and depth'.&lt;ref name=Stern2007&gt;
Stern, N. (2007). [http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/sternreview_index.htm Stern Review of the Economics of Climate Change. Part VI: International Collective Action.] HM Treasury, London
&lt;/ref&gt;

International collective actions that are presently taking place include:
* [[Multilateralism|multilateral]] frameworks such as [[UNFCCC]] and [[Kyoto Protocol]]
* partnerships, networks, and organisations such as the [[International Energy Agency]], that enable coordinated international action
* mutual understanding of domestic policy goals.&lt;ref name=Stern2007 /&gt;

International collective action has been shown to be more likely to succeed where there is mutual self-interest, when it is in response to a shared threat, and where there is leadership by a dominant country.&lt;ref name=Stern2007 /&gt;

[[Game theory]] has been used to identify key criteria for designing international collective action on climate change. Lessons from game theory include:
* changing the structure of ''incentives'' to make cooperation more appealing
* understanding the role of ''reciprocity'', particularly when faced with [[prisoner's dilemma]] situations: players may adopt strategies of conditional cooperation, where the more others contribute to the public good, the more they will contribute themselves
* increasing the ''frequency of contact and transparency'' (institutional structures and repeated negotiations)
* offering opportunities to ''renegotiate rules'' at key stages
* understanding the role of ''reputation'' in influencing outcomes.&lt;ref name=Stern2007 /&gt;

==FLOSS development as collective action including private actors==
The development of Free and Libre Open Source Software [[FLOSS]] is an example of collective action where individuals create a public good: the source code freely available to everyone. The uniqueness is that not only individuals contribute to the common good but also private firms invest into the production of the freely available knowledge. Therefore this phenomenon is called [[Private-Collective Model of Innovation|private-collective innovation]].

==See also==
* [[Collaborative innovation network]]
* [[Collective intelligence]]
* [[Common Property Resource]]
* [[Constitutional economics]]
* [[Free rider problem]]
* [[Mass collaboration]]
* [[Nash equilibrium]]
* [[Pareto efficiency]]
* [[Polytely]]
* [[Prisoner's dilemma]]
* [[Private-Collective Model of Innovation]]
* [[Public good]]
* [[Social fact]]
* [[Tragedy of the Commons]]
* [[Tragedy of the anticommons]]

==References==
{{reflist}}
{{refbegin}}
* Bratman, Michael (1993). 'Shared Intention'. ''Ethics.''
* {{Citation
 | last=Gilbert | first=Margaret
 | year=1989
 | title=On Social Facts
 | publisher=Princeton University Press
}}
* {{Citation
 | last=Gilbert | first=Margaret
 | year=2006a
 | title=Rationality in Collective Action
 | journal=Philosophy of the Social Sciences
 | volume=36 | issue=1
 | pages=3–17
 | url=http://pos.sagepub.com/cgi/content/abstract/36/1/3
 | doi=10.1177/0048393105284167
}}
* {{Citation
 | last=Gilbert | first=Margaret
 | year=2006
 | title=A Theory of Political Obligation: Membership, Commitment, and the Bonds of Society
 | publisher=Oxford University Press
}}
* Hardin, Russell (1982). ''Collective Action.'' Johns Hopkins University Press. Baltimore. ISBN 0-8018-2818-X
* Olson, Mancur (1965). ''The Logic of Collective Action''. Harvard University Press. ISBN 0-674-53751-3
* Ostrom, Elinor. (1990). Governing the Commons: The Evolution of Institutions for Collective Action.  Cambridge University Press.ISBN 978-0-521-40599-7
* Sandler Todd (1992) ''Collective action: Theory and applications''. University of Michigan Press.
* Searle, John (1990). 'Collective Intentions and Actions'.
* Meinzen-Dick, R. and M. di Gregorio, eds. (2004) Collective Action and Property Rights for Sustainable Development. 2020 Focus No. 11. International Food Policy Research Institute: Washington, DC. http://www.ifpri.org/2020/focus/focus11.asp
{{refend}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Collective Action}}
[[Category:Community building]]
[[Category:Public choice theory]]
[[Category:Political science terms]]
[[Category:Sociological terms]]
[[Category:Social sciences terminology]]
[[Category:Sociology index]]

[[de:Kollektives Handeln]]
[[es:Acción colectiva]]
[[pt:Ação coletiva]]
[[sv:Kollektivt handlande]]</text>
      <sha1>dd0x2l4uk5wal8zw21i6h5kmuw9l5y3</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
