<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Communitarianism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>43375</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522244587</id>
      <parentid>521062491</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T22:20:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>184.5.123.174</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Influence in the United States */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21901">{{Refimprove|article|date=January 2008}}
'''Communitarianism''' is an ideology that emphasizes the connection between the individual and the community. That community may be the family unit, but it can also be understood in a far wider sense of personal interaction, of geographical location, or of shared history.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

==Terminology==
Though the term ''communitarianism'' is of 20th-century origin, it is derived from the 1840s term ''communitarian'', which was coined by [[Goodwyn Barmby]] to refer to one who was a member or advocate of a [[communalist]] society. The modern use of the term is a redefinition of the original sense. Many communitarians trace their philosophy to earlier thinkers. The term is primarily used in two senses:

* [[Communitarianism#Philosophical communitarianism|'''Philosophical communitarianism''']] considers [[classical liberalism]] to be [[ontology|ontologically]] and [[epistemology|epistemologically]] incoherent, and opposes it on those grounds. Unlike classical liberalism, which construes communities as originating from the voluntary acts of pre-community [[individual]]s, it emphasizes the role of the community in defining and shaping individuals. Communitarians believe that the value of community is not sufficiently recognized in liberal theories of justice.
* [[Communitarianism#Ideological communitarianism|'''Ideological communitarianism''']] is characterized as a [[radical center (politics)|radical centrist]] [[ideology]] that is sometimes marked by leftism on economic issues and moralism or conservatism on social issues. This usage was coined recently. When the term is capitalized, it usually refers to the Responsive Communitarian movement of [[Amitai Etzioni]] and other philosophers.

==Origins==
Communitarianism has been traced back to early [[monasticism]], but in the twentieth century began to be formulated as a philosophy by [[Dorothy Day]] and the [[Catholic Worker movement]]. In an early article the ''Catholic Worker'' clarified the dogma of the Mystical Body of Christ as the basis for the movement's communitarianism. Communitarianism is also related to the [[personalist]] philosophy of [[Emmanuel Mounier]].

Later secular communitarians began from analysis of [[classical republicanism]], focusing on ancient Greek and Classicist writers. Since 1990 they became the apologists of the idea of [[civil society]] as a result of work of communist propaganda in Poland using it as a tool of [[neo-liberalism|neoliberal]] transformation, legitimizing development of the third sector as a substitute for the [[welfare state]].&lt;ref&gt;Pawel Stefan Zaleski, ''Neoliberalizm i spoleczenstwo obywatelskie (Neoliberalism and Civil Society)'', Wydawnictwo Uniwersytetu Mikołaja Kopernika, Torun 2012&lt;/ref&gt; Soon, due to work of [[Robert Putnam]], they started to treat [[Tocqueville]] as a main theoretician of civil society and their primary ancestor. Thus they got under influence of neoliberal ideologies since Tocqueville was a liberal, not a republican theorist, giving new impetus to their work.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
  | last = Zaleski
  | first = Pawel
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = Tocqueville on Civilian Society. A Romantic Vision of the Dichotomic Structure of Social Reality
  | journal = Archiv für Begriffsgeschichte
  | volume = 50
  | issue =
  | pages =
  | publisher = Felix Meiner Verlag
  | location =
  | year = 2008
  | url =
  | issn =
  | doi =
  | id =
  | accessdate = }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

==Philosophical communitarianism==
&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Communitarianism]] --&gt;Communitarianism in philosophy, like other schools of thought in contemporary political philosophy{{Citation needed|date=April 2011}}, can be defined by its response to [[John Rawls]]' ''[[A Theory of Justice]]''. Communitarians criticize the image Rawls presents of humans as atomistic individuals.

Communitarians claim values and beliefs are formed in public space, in which debate takes place. Both linguistic and non-linguistic traditions are communicated to children and form the backdrop against which individuals formulate and understand beliefs. The dependence of the individual upon community members is typically meant as descriptive. It does not mean that individuals should accept majority beliefs. Rather, if an individual rejects a majority belief, such as the historic belief that slavery is acceptable, he or she will do so for reasons that make sense within the community (for example, the Judeo-Christian conception of the ''[[imago Dei]]'', or reasons deriving from secular Enlightenment [[humanism]]) rather than simply any reason at all. In this sense, the rejection of a single majority belief relies on other majority beliefs.

The following authors have communitarian tendencies in the philosophical sense, but have all taken pains to distance themselves from the political ideology known as communitarianism, which is discussed further below:

*[[Alasdair MacIntyre]]{{spaced ndash}}''After Virtue''
*[[Michael Sandel]]{{spaced ndash}}''Liberalism and the Limits of Justice''
*[[Charles Taylor (philosopher)|Charles Taylor]]{{spaced ndash}}''Sources of the Self''
*[[Michael Walzer]]{{spaced ndash}}''Spheres of Justice''

==Ideological communitarianism==&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Communitarianism]] --&gt;

===Communitarian political philosophy===
====Social capital====
Beginning in the late 20th century, many authors began to observe a deterioration in the social networks of the United States. In the book ''[[Bowling Alone]]'', [[Robert Putnam]] observed that nearly every form of civic organization has undergone drops in membership exemplified by the fact that, while more people are bowling than in the 1950s, there are fewer bowling leagues.  In recent years, Putnam has revised this argument.{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}

This results in a decline in &quot;[[social capital]]&quot;, described by Putnam as &quot;the collective value of all '[[social networks]]' and the inclinations that arise from these networks to do things for each other&quot;. According to Putnam and his followers, social capital is a key component to building and maintaining democracy.

Communitarians seek to bolster social capital and the institutions of [[civil society]]. The Responsive Communitarian Platform described it thus&lt;ref name=&quot;platform&quot;&gt;The Communitarian Network, ''[http://www.gwu.edu/~icps/RCP%20text.html Responsive Communitarian Platform Text]''.&lt;/ref&gt;:

:&quot;Many social goals . . . require partnership between public and private groups. Though government should not seek to replace local communities, it may need to empower them by strategies of support, including revenue-sharing and technical assistance. There is a great need for study and experimentation with creative use of the structures of civil society, and public-private cooperation, especially where the delivery of health, educational and social services are concerned.&quot;

====Positive rights====
Central to the communitarian philosophy is the concept of [[positive rights]], which are rights or guarantees to certain things. These may include state subsidized education, state subsidized housing, a safe and clean environment, universal health care, and even the right to a job with the concomitant obligation of the government or individuals to provide one. To this end, communitarians generally support social security programs, public works programs, and laws limiting such things as pollution.

A common objection is that by providing such rights, communitarians violate the negative rights of the citizens; rights to ''not'' have something done for you. For example, taxation to pay for such programs as described above dispossesses individuals of property. Proponents of positive rights, by attributing the protection of negative rights to the society rather than the government, respond that individuals would not have any rights in the absence of societies—a central tenet of communitarianism—and thus have a personal responsibility to give something back to it. Some have viewed this as a negation of [[natural right]]s. However, what is or is not a &quot;natural right&quot; is a source of contention in modern politics, as well as historically; for example, whether or not universal health care, private property or protection from polluters can be considered a birthright.

Alternatively, some agree that negative rights may be violated by a government action, but argue that it is justifiable if the positive rights protected outweigh the negative rights lost. In the same vein, supporters of positive rights further argue that negative rights are irrelevant in their absence. Moreover, some communitarians &quot;experience this less as a case of being used for others' ends and more as a way of contributing to the purposes of a community I regard as my own&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Sandel, ''Liberalism and the Limits of Justice'', 143.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Comparison to other political philosophies===
Communitarianism cannot be classified as being wholly left or right, and many theorists claim to represent a sort of [[radical center (politics)|radical center]]. [[Progressivism in the United States|Progressives]] in the American sense or [[social democracy|social democrat]]s in the European sense generally share the communitarian position on issues relating to the economy, such as the need for environmental protection and public education, but not on cultural issues. Communitarians and conservatives generally agree on cultural issues, such as support for character education and faith-based programs, but communitarians do not support capitalism generally embraced by American conservatives.

====Authoritarianism====
Some people have argued&lt;ref&gt;Simons, R. (1996) A Community of Freedoms. Aust. Q. 68(1): 31-42&lt;/ref&gt; that communitarianism's focus on social cohesion raises similarities with [[nationalistic]] [[communism]], or various forms of [[authoritarianism]], although supporters contend that there are substantial differences between communitarianism and authoritarianism, and that communitarianism has very little in common with Communism, which they see as not really valuing individual liberty at all.

Authoritarian governments often embrace extremist ideologies and rule with brute force, accompanied with severe restrictions on personal freedom, political and civil rights. Authoritarian governments are overt about the role of the government as director and commander. [[Civil society]] and democracy are not generally characteristic of authoritarian regimes. For the most part, communitarians emphasize the use of [[non-governmental organizations]], such as private businesses, churches, non-profits, or labor unions, in furthering their goals. This places communitarianism close to [[neoliberalism]], while development of the third sector is a part of the politics of dismantling of the institutions of [[welfare state]].&lt;ref&gt;Pawel Stefan Zaleski, ''Neoliberalizm i spoleczenstwo obywatelskie (Neoliberalism and Civil Society)'', Wydawnictwo Uniwersytetu Mikolaja Kopernika, Torun 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

==Communitarian movement==
The modern communitarian movement was first articulated by the Responsive Communitarian Platform, written in the United States by a group of ethicists, activists, and social scientists including [[Amitai Etzioni]], [[Mary Ann Glendon]], and William Galston.

The Communitarian Network, founded in 1993 by Amitai Etzioni, is the best-known group advocating communitarianism. One of the network's many initiatives to reach out to a broader public is the transnational project Diversity within Unity, which advocates a communitarian approach towards immigration and minority rights in today's diversifying societies. The project is endorsed by a diverse and international group of supporters, including former Dutch prime-minister [[Jan-Peter Balkenende]] from the [[Christian Democratic Appeal]]; [[Rita Süssmuth]] from the [[Christian Democratic Union (Germany)|Christian Democratic Union]]; the Hungarian dissident and philosopher [[György Bence]]; British political scholar [[David Miller (political theorist)|David Miller]]; and others.&lt;ref&gt;List of sponsors of the 'Diversity in Unity&quot; platform: [http://www.gwu.edu/~icps/DWU%20Endorse.html http://www.gwu.edu/~icps/DWU%20Endorse.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

A think tank called the Institute for Communitarian Policy Studies is also directed by Etzioni. Other voices of communitarianism include Don Eberly, director of the Civil Society Project and Robert Putnam.

===Influence in the United States===
[[Image:Multi-axis political spectrum.svg|thumb|250px|A variant of the [[Nolan chart]] using traditional political color coding ([[Red#Use_by_political_movements|red leftism]] versus [[Blue#Politics|blue rightism]]) with communitarianism on the top left.]]

Reflecting the dominance of [[Left-Right politics|liberal and conservative politics]] in the United States, no major party and few elected officials advocate communitarianism. Thus there is no consensus on individual policies, but some that most communitarians endorse have been enacted.

It is quite possible that the United States' [[Right-libertarianism|right-libertarian]] ideological underpinnings have suppressed major communitarian factions from emerging.&lt;ref&gt;The Responsive Community, Vol. 3, Issue 1. Winter 1992/93. Retrieved May 27, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Communitarians are often easily villainized as those seeking [[big government]]s and [[nanny state]]s.

President Bill Clinton was open about his support for much of Amitai Etzioni's philosophy, though whether this reflected on his actual policy program is debatable. It has also been suggested that the &quot;[[compassionate conservatism]]&quot; espoused by President Bush during his 2000 presidential campaign was a form of conservative communitarian thinking, though he too did not implement it in his policy program. Cited policies have included economic and rhetorical support for education, volunteerism, and community programs, as well as a social emphasis on promoting families, character education, traditional values, and faith-based projects. President Barack Obama's support for public works programs, such as Americorps could also be interpreted as a communitarian possition.

[[Dana Milbank]], writing in the ''[[Washington Post]]'', remarked of modern communitarians, &quot;There is still no such thing as a card-carrying communitarian, and therefore no consensus on policies. Some, such as [[John DiIulio]] and outside Bush adviser [[Marvin Olasky]], favor religious solutions for communities, while others, like Etzioni and Galston, prefer secular approaches.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.janda.org/b20/News%20articles/GW%2C%20the%20Communitarian.htm Needed: Catchword For Bush Ideology; 'Communitarianism' Finds Favor]&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2011, the libertarian ''[[Reason Magazine]]'' worked with the Rupe organization to survey 1,200 Americans by telephone. The Reason-Rupe poll found that &quot;Americans cannot easily be bundled into either the 'liberal' or 'conservative' groups&quot;. Specifically, 28% expressed conservative views, 24% expressed libertarian views, 20% expressed communitarian views, and 28% expressed liberal views. The margin of error was ±3.&lt;ref name=poll&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://reason.com/blog/2011/08/29/reason-rupe-poll-finds-24-of-a|title=Reason-Rupe Poll Finds 24 Percent of Americans are Economically Conservative and Socially Liberal, 28 Percent Liberal, 28 Percent Conservative, and 20 Percent Communitarian|first=Emily|last=Ekins|date=August 29, 2011|publisher=''[[Reason Magazine]]''|accessdate=January 1, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A similar Gallup survey in 2011 included possible [[centrism|centrist/moderate]] responses. That poll reported that 17% expressed conservative views, 22% expressed libertarian views, 20% expressed communitarian views, 17% expressed centrist views, and 24% expressed liberal views. The organization used the terminology &quot;the bigger the better&quot; to describe communitarianism.&lt;ref name=poll/&gt;

==Criticisms==
Liberal theorists such as Simon Caney&lt;ref&gt;'Liberalism and communitarianism: a misconceived debate'. Political Studies 40, 273-290&lt;/ref&gt; disagree that philosophical communitarianism has any interesting criticisms to make of liberalism. They reject the communitarian charges that liberalism neglects the value of community, and holds an &quot;atomized&quot; or asocial view of the self. If they are correct in this, then communitarian doctrine reduces to little more than traditionalism and cultural [[moral relativism]].

According to [[Peter Sutch]] the principal criticisms of communitarianism are:
#That communitarianism leads necessarily to moral relativism.
#That this relativism leads necessarily to a re-endorsement of the status quo in international politics, and
#That such a position relies upon a discredited ontological argument that posits the foundational status of the community or state.&lt;ref&gt;Peter Sutch, Ethics, Justice, and International Relations, p.62&lt;/ref&gt;
However, he goes on to show that such arguments cannot be leveled against the particular communitarian theories of [[Michael Walzer]] and [[Mervyn Frost]].{{Citation needed|date=May 2009}}

Other critics emphasize close relation of communitarianism to [[neoliberalism]] and new policies of dismantling the [[welfare state]] institutions through development of the third sector.&lt;ref&gt;Pawel Stefan Zaleski, ''Neoliberalizm i spoleczenstwo obywatelskie (Neoliberalism and Civil Society)'', Wydawnictwo Uniwersytetu Mikołaja Kopernika, Torun 2012&lt;/ref&gt; 

===Opposition===
*[[Bruce Frohnen]] - author of ''The New Communitarians and the Crisis of Modern Liberalism'' (1996)
*[[Charles Arthur Willard]] - author of ''Liberalism and the Problem of Knowledge: A New Rhetoric for Modern Democracy'', University of Chicago Press, 1996.
*[[Niki Raapana]] and [[Nordica Friedrich]] - authors of &quot;''The Anti Communitarian Manifesto''&quot; (2003) ACL Books, Anchorage, Alaska and founders of the Anti-Communitarian League website.

==See also==
{{multicol}}
*[[Christian democracy]]
*[[Civics]]
*[[Civil religion]]
*[[Collectivism]]
*[[Communalism (South Asia)]]
*[[Communalism before 1800]]
*[[Distributism]]
*[[Europeanism]]
*[[Identity politics]]
*[[Public sphere]]
*[[Radical center (politics)|Radical center]]
*[[Republicanism]]
*[[Social conservatism]]
*[[Singaporean communitarianism]]
*[[Third Way (centrism)|Third Way]]
*[[Ubuntu (philosophy)|Ubuntu]]
{{multicol-break}}
;Earlier theorists
*[[Aristotle]]
*[[Confucius]]
*[[Martin Buber]]
*[[Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel]]
*[[Niccolò Machiavelli]]
*[[Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
*[[Alexis de Tocqueville]]
{{multicol-break}}
;Contemporary theorists
*[[Benjamin Barber]]
*[[Gad Barzilai]]
*[[Robert Bellah]]
*[[Phillip Blond]]
*[[Amitai Etzioni]]
*[[William Galston]]
*[[Mark Kuczewski]]
*[[Costanzo Preve]]
*[[Robert Putnam]]
*[[Jose Perez Adan]]
*[[Joseph Raz]]
*[[Charles Taylor (philosopher)|Charles Taylor]]
*[[Michael Walzer]]
*[[Stephen Marglin]]
{{multicol-end}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* [[Amitai Etzioni]], 1996, ''The New Golden Rule'', Basic Books ISBN 0465049990
* [[Charles Taylor]], 1992, ''Sources of the Self'', Cambridge: Harvard University Press ISBN 0674824261
* [[Daniel Bell]], 2000, ''East Meets West'', Princeton: Princeton University Press ISBN 0691005087
*[[David L. Kirp]], 2001, ''Almost Home: America's Love-Hate Relationship with Community'', Princeton University Press ISBN 0691095175
* [[Gad Barzilai]], 2003, ''Communities and Law: Politics and Cultures of Legal Identities'', Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press ISBN 978-0-472-03079-8
* [[Michael J. Sandel]], 1998, ''Liberalism and the Limits of Justice'', Cambridge: Cambridge University Press ISBN 0521567416
* [[Sterling Harwood]], 1996, ''Against MacIntyre's Relativistic Communitarianism'', in Sterling Harwood, ed., Business as Ethical and Business as Usual, Belmont, CA: Wadsworth Publishing Company), Chapter 3, ISBN 0-534-54251-4 and ISBN 978-0-534-54251-1

==External links==
{{Wiktionary}}
*[http://www.sourcewatch.org/wiki.phtml?title=Communitarianism Sourcewatch]
*{{sep entry|communitarianism|Communitarianism|Daniel Bell}}
*[http://www.infed.org/biblio/communitarianism.htm &quot;Communitarianism&quot;], ''Infed'' Encyclopedia.
*[[Fareed Zakaria]], [http://slate.msn.com/id/2380 The ABCs of Communitarianism. A devil's dictionary], ''Slate'', July 26, 1996.
*Robert Putnam, [http://discover.npr.org/features/feature.jhtml?wfId=1118012 Communitarianism], [[National Public Radio]], February 5, 2001: &quot;The term 'Third Way' was used to describe President Clinton's form of liberalism. Now 'Communitarianism' is being used in the same way to describe President Bush's form of conservatism. They're both an attempt to create a middle ground...an alternative to the liberal-conservative paradigm.&quot;
* [http://www.cpn.org/tools/dictionary/communitarian.html Civil Practices Network]

{{Political ideologies}}

[[Category:Collectivism]]
[[Category:Communalism]]
[[Category:Community building]]
[[Category:Community organizing]]
[[Category:Political ideologies]]
[[Category:Political science theories]]
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Anti-capitalism]]

[[ca:Comunitarisme]]
[[cs:Komunitarismus]]
[[cy:Cymunedoliaeth]]
[[da:Kommunitarisme]]
[[de:Kommunitarismus]]
[[es:Pensamiento comunitario]]
[[eo:Komunumismo]]
[[fr:Communautarisme (sociologie)]]
[[fy:Kommunitarisme]]
[[ko:공동체주의]]
[[id:Komunitarianisme]]
[[is:Félagshyggja (stjórnmálaheimspeki)]]
[[it:Comunitarismo]]
[[he:קהילתנות]]
[[krc:Коммунитаризм]]
[[nl:Communitarisme]]
[[ja:共同体主義]]
[[pl:Komunitaryzm]]
[[pt:Comunitarismo]]
[[ro:Comunitarianism]]
[[ru:Коммунитаризм]]
[[sr:Комунитаризам]]
[[sh:Komunitarizam]]
[[fi:Kommunitarismi]]
[[sv:Kommunitarism]]
[[uk:Комунітаризм]]
[[vi:Chủ nghĩa cộng đồng]]
[[zh:社群主義]]</text>
      <sha1>0xj6egukmrkjqp14w446ranxueqfm9n</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
