<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Communization</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4283625</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521348331</id>
      <parentid>501582542</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-04T12:28:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Omnipaedista</username>
        <id>8524693</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>italic type per MOS</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11360">{{Libertarian socialism}}
{{Marxism}}

'''Communization''' (or '''communisation''' in [[British English]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://libcom.org/tags/communisation As can be seen in the british libertarian communist website libcom.org]&lt;/ref&gt;) mainly refers to a contemporary [[communist]] theory in which we find a &quot;mixing-up of [[insurrectionist anarchism]], the [[Left communism|communist ultra-left]], post-[[Autonomism|autonomists]], anti-political currents, groups like [[The Coming Insurrection|the Invisible Committee]], as well as more explicitly ‘communizing’ currents, such as ''Théorie Communiste'' and ''Endnotes''. Obviously at the heart of the word is communism and, as the shift to communization suggests, communism as a particular activity and process...&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Benjamin Noys (ed). [http://www.minorcompositions.info/?p=299 ''Communization and its Discontents: Contestation, Critique, and Contemporary Struggles.''] Minor Compositions, [[Autonomedia]]. 2011. 1st ed.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Theory ==
In [[communist]] political theory, communization is the process of abolishing [[ownership]] of the [[means of production]], which, in societies dominated by the [[capitalist]] [[mode of production]], are owned by individual capitalists, [[Sovereign state|states]], or other collective bodies. In some versions of communist theory, communization is understood as the transfer of ownership from [[Privately held company|private]] capitalist hands to the collective hands of producers, whether in the form of [[co-operative enterprises]] or [[communes]], or through the mediation of a state or federation of [[workers' councils]] on a local, national, or global scale. In other programs, such as those of some [[left communists]] (e.g. [[Gilles Dauvé]]), [[autonomists]] (e.g., [[Mario Tronti]]), and [[libertarian communists]] (e.g. [[Peter Kropotkin]]), communization means the abolition of [[property]] itself along with any state-like institutions claiming to represent a given subset of humanity. In these accounts humanity as a whole, directly or indirectly, would take over the task of the production of goods for use (and not for exchange). People would then have free access to those goods rather than exchanging labor for money, and distribution would take place according to the maxim &quot;[[from each according to his ability, to each according to his need]].&quot;

== History ==
=== Origins and Precedents ===
The term communization was not used by [[Karl Marx]] and [[Friedrich Engels]], but it was employed in the above sense by early Marxists.&lt;ref&gt;e.g. [http://www.marxists.org/archive/morris/works/1887/policy.htm William Morris &quot;The Policy of Abstention&quot;] (1887)  and  [http://www.marxists.org/archive/bax/1888/06/impera.htm E. Belfort Bax &quot;Et Impera&quot;] (1888) &lt;/ref&gt; Communization in this sense is equivalent to the establishment  of the &quot;higher phase&quot; of communist society described by Marx in ''[[Critique of the Gotha Program]]''. In ''[[State and Revolution]]'' [[Vladimir Lenin]] referred to the lower phase, organized around the principle &quot;[[To each according to his contribution]]&quot;, as &quot;socialism&quot;, with the higher phase as &quot;complete communism&quot;, or &quot;full communism&quot; as [[Joseph Stalin]] will later put it. Thus both Lenin and Stalin gave grounds for thinking of communization not as a transition from capitalism to communism, but as a transition from socialism to communism, a transition that would take place after the working class had seized power, and which may last a long time (in the 1930s Stalin conceived of &quot;full communism&quot; as still a long way off&lt;ref&gt;See e.g. Stalin’s “Economic Problems of Socialism of the U.S.S.R.” (1939)&lt;/ref&gt;). Thus the interval between the two transitions came to be seen as a necessary &quot;period of transition&quot; between the workers' revolution and communism.

It appears that within so-called &quot;communist&quot; regimes the demand for &quot;communization&quot; was associated with an impatience with the &quot;period of transition&quot; and a desire to break with the remaining capitalist forms (e.g., money, wage labor) still in place in those regimes.&lt;ref&gt;e.g. some  [[Chinese Ultra-Left]] tendencies during the so-called &quot;[[Great Proletarian Cultural Revolution]].&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Those pushing for a move toward &quot;communizing&quot; in this sense were typically denounced as &quot;[[ultra-left]]&quot;, with their suggestions dismissed as impractical and [[utopian]], but they were able to point to the historical examples of the [[Paris Commune]] and the [[Spanish Revolution]], where more radical measures of popular collectivization had been taken than in the [[Russian Revolution (1917)|Russian]] and [[Chinese Revolution (1949)|Chinese]] revolutions, as well as to the [[German Revolution of 1918–19]] and the Italian councils movement of 1919-1920 in which the historic &quot;[[left communist]]&quot; tendencies had been formed.

=== Late 20th Century ===
The association of the term communization with a self-identified &quot;[[ultra-left]]&quot; was cemented in France in the 1970s, where it came to describe not a transition to a higher phase of communism but a vision of communist revolution itself. Thus the 1975 Pamphlet ''A World Without Money'' states: “insurrection and communisation are intimately linked.  There would not be first a period of insurrection and then later, thanks to this insurrection, the transformation of social reality.  The insurrectional process derives its force from communisation itself.”&lt;ref&gt;[http://libcom.org/library/world-without-money-les-amis-de-4-millions-de-jeunes-travailleurs &quot;A World Without Money&quot;] by Les amis de 4 millions de jeunes travailleurs. (quoted passage not included in this English extract)&lt;/ref&gt; This vision was opposed to the [[statism]] and [[vanguardism]] of the [[Leninist]] conception of revolution, but it also identified the perceived failure of the [[Russian Revolution (1917)|Russian]] and [[Chinese Revolution (1949)|Chinese]] revolutions (carried out on the Leninist politico-military model) with the insufficiency of measures taken to abolish capitalist social relations (e.g. lack of direct collectivization, persistence of monetary relations). It also reversed the supposed &quot;pragmatism&quot; of the Leninist focus on the state, arguing that the final goal of the &quot;withering away of the state&quot; could hardly be advanced by the seizure of state power and the establishment of a &quot;revolutionary&quot; bureaucracy, but that the most practical means to achieve this goal would rather be the abolition of the capitalist relations (money, capital, wages) on which state power depends. Thus La Banquise writes:
{{quote|&quot;one can foresee that a movement of communisation that destroys the State, undermines the social base of the enemy, and spreads under the effect of the irresistible appeal arousing the birth of new social relations between men, will bond together the revolutionary camp far better than any power which, while waiting to conquer the world before communising it, would behave no differently than... a State.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://libcom.org/library/the-story-of-our-origins-la-banquise &quot;The Story of Our Origins&quot;]''La Banquise'' No. 2 (1983)&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Within this 1970s French tendency &quot;communization&quot; thus came to represent the absence of a period of transition and a conception of revolution as the application of communist measures throughout the economy and society.&lt;ref&gt;For an historical account see: Endnotes [http://endnotes.org.uk/articles/8 &quot;Bring Out Your Dead&quot;], Endnotes no. 1 (2008). Although they do not use the term a very similar conception can be found in the early works of [[Antonio Negri]], e.g. the chapter ‘Communism and Transition’ in his ''Marx Beyond Marx'' (1978), as well as in the 1980s works of the insurrectionist anarchist [[Alfredo M. Bonanno]].&lt;/ref&gt; The term is still used in this sense in France today and has spread into English usage as a result of the translation of texts by [[Gilles Dauvé]] and ''Théorie Comuniste'', two key figures in this tendency.

===Early 21st Century===
But in the late 1990s a close but not identical sense of &quot;communization&quot; was developed by the French post-situationist group [[Tiqqun]]. In keeping with their ultra-left predecessors, Tiqqun's predilection for the term seems to be its emphasis on communism as an immediate process rather than a far-off goal, but for Tiqqun it is no longer synonymous with &quot;the revolution&quot; considered as an historical event, but rather becomes identifiable with all sorts of activities – from squatting and setting up communes to simply &quot;sharing&quot; – that would typically be understood as &quot;pre-revolutionary&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;As we apprehend it, the process of instituting communism can only take the form of a collection of acts of ''communisation'', of making common such-and-such space, such-and-such machine, such-and-such knowledge. That is to say, the elaboration of the mode of sharing that attaches to them. Insurrection itself is just an accelerator, a decisive moment in this process.&quot; Anonymous, [http://www.bloom0101.org/call.pdf ''Call'']&lt;/ref&gt; From an ultra-left perspective such a politics of &quot;dropping-out&quot; or, as Tiqqun put it, &quot;desertion&quot; — setting up spaces and practices that are held to be partially autonomous from capitalism — is typically dismissed as either naive or reactionary.&lt;ref&gt;For a critique of Tiqqun from an ultra-left perspective, as well as a description of the opposition between the two sense of &quot;communization&quot; see &quot;[http://libcom.org/library/reflexions-around-call Reflexions Around Call]&quot; Letters Journal #3. See also Dauvé and Nesic, [http://troploin0.free.fr/ii/index.php/textes/19-communisation-un-appel-et-une-invite &quot;Un Appel et une Invite&quot;].&lt;/ref&gt; Due to the popularity of the Tiqqun-related works ''Call'' and ''[[The Coming Insurrection]]'' in US [[anarchist]] circles it tended to be this latter sense of &quot;communization&quot; that was employed in US anarchist and &quot;[[insurrectionist]]&quot; communiques, notably within the [[2009 California college tuition hike protests|Californian student movement of 2009-2010]].&lt;ref&gt;See e.g. [http://afterthefallcommuniques.info/ &quot;After the Fall: Communiqués from Occupied California&quot;] &lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
*[http://endnotes.org.uk/articles/8 &quot;Bring Out Your Dead&quot;] by Endnotes
*[http://libcom.org/library/invisible-politics-introduction-contemporary-communisation-john-cunningham &quot;Invisible Politics - An Introduction to Contemporary Communisation&quot;] by John Cunningham
*[http://libcom.org/library/reflexions-around-call &quot;Reflexions Around Call&quot;] ''Letters Journal'' #3 (2009)
*[http://libcom.org/library/the-story-of-our-origins-la-banquise &quot;The Story of Our Origins&quot;] by La Banquise
*[http://www.bloom0101.org/call.pdf ''Call''] by Anonymous
*&quot;Communism and Transition&quot; by Antonio Negri in ''Marx Beyond Marx'' (1978)
*[http://libcom.org/library/eclipse-re-emergence-giles-dauve ''The Eclipse and Re-emergence of the Communist Movement''] by Gilles Dauve and Francois Martin
*[http://libcom.org/tags/communisation Archive of texts on communisation] at the Libertarian Communist Library.
*[http://afterthefallcommuniques.info/ &quot;After the Fall: Communiqués from Occupied California&quot;]

[[Category:Communism]]
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Anarchist theory]]
[[Category:Marxism]]
[[Category:Left communism]]
[[Category:Libertarian socialism]]

[[es:Comunización]]
[[fr:Communisation]]</text>
      <sha1>q6swsbdc86w54nwuedmqlsagn1rqvcd</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
