<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Committee</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>158196</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522386713</id>
      <parentid>520576469</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T21:33:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>R'n'B</username>
        <id>2300502</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Remove [[WP:DPL|links]] to [[WP:D|disambiguation]] page [[ICS]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13597">{{Other uses}}
{{refimprove|date=December 2009}}

[[File:C19 interior 053.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Committee room, designed 1901, in [[Halifax Town Hall]]]]
A '''committee''' (or &quot;commission&quot;) is a type of small [[deliberative assembly]] that is usually intended to remain subordinate to another, larger deliberative assembly&amp;mdash;which when organized so that action on committee requires a vote by all its entitled members, is called the &quot;[[Committee of the Whole]]&quot;.  Committees often serve several different functions:
* '''Governance''':  in organizations considered too large for all the members to participate in decisions affecting the organization as a whole, a committee (such as a Board of Directors or &quot;Executive Committee&quot;) is given the power to make decisions, spend money, or take actions. Some or all such powers may be limited or effectively unlimited. For example of the later case, the Board of directors can frequently enter into [[contract law|binding contract]]s and make decisions which once taken or made, can't be taken back or undone under the law.

{{Anchor|Coordination committee|Coordination subcommittee}}
* '''Coordination''': individuals from different parts of an organization (for example, all senior vice presidents) might meet regularly to discuss developments in their areas, review projects that cut across organizational boundaries, talk about future options, etc.  Where there is a large committee, it is common to have smaller committees with more specialized functions - for example, Boards of Directors of large corporations typically have an (ongoing) audit committee, finance committee, compensation committee, etc. Large [[academic conference]]s are usually organized by a co-ordinating committee drawn from the relevant professional body.

{{Anchor|Research committee|Research subcommittee}}
* '''Research and recommendations''':  committees are often formed to do [[research]] and make recommendations on a potential or planned project or change.  For example, an organization considering a major [[capital investment]] might create a temporary working committee of several people to review options and make recommendations to upper management or the Board of Directors.  Such committees are typically dissolved after issuing recommendations (often in the form of a final report).

* '''Tabling''': as a means of [[public relations]] by sending sensitive, inconvenient, or irrelevant matters to committees, organizations may bypass, stall, or disacknowledge matters without declaring a formal policy of inaction or indifference.

==Procedures==
* It is common for a [[chairperson]] to organize a committee meeting through an [[Agenda (meeting)|agenda]], which is usually distributed in advance.
* The chairperson is responsible for running meetings:  keeping the discussion on the appropriate subject, recognizing members (calling on them to speak) [often omitted in smaller committees], and calling for votes after a debate has taken place [formal voting is normally only done in committees involved in governance].  Governance committees often have formal processes (for example, they might follow [[Roberts Rules of Order]]); other types of committees typically operate informally, with the chairperson being responsible for deciding how formal the committee processes will be.
* [[Minutes]], a record of the discussion and decisions of the meeting, are often taken by a person designated as the [[secretary]] of the committee; they may be legally obligatory (again, typically for governance committees, especially boards of directors).
* For committees that meet regularly, the minutes of the most recent meeting are often circulated to committee members before the next meeting, and are available to the membership of the whole.
* Committees may meet on a regular basis, often weekly or yearly, or meetings may be called irregularly as the need arises. During an emergency, a committee may meet more than once per day, or sit in permanent session, as, for example, ExComm (the President's Executive Committee) did during the [[Cuban Missile Crisis]].

==Subcommittees==
A committee that is a [[subset]] of a larger committee is called a '''subcommittee'''.

Where the larger group has a name other than &quot;committee&quot; - for example, &quot;Board&quot; or &quot;Commission&quot;, the smaller group(s) would usually be called committee(s), not subcommittee(s), and might go by an entirely different name, or substitute &quot;Commission&quot; for &quot;Committee&quot;. For example in the [[earth sciences|sciences]], the &quot;[[International Commission on Stratigraphy]]&quot; (ICS) a ''standing working committee'' is doing organizational work establishing uniform naming and [[Global Boundary Stratotype Section and Point|benchmark]]s in the [[geologic record]] and timeline since 1974, all under the auspices of the [[International Union of Geological Sciences]] ([[IUGS]]). It is technically the &quot;International Stratigraphy Committee&quot; (ISC), which has limited executive committee powers to impanel other subcommittees (also called commissions) to resolve certain matters involving the [[Geologic time scale]]&amp;mdash;its deliberations and those of its subcommittees must be adopted by the IUGS which meets in a committee-of-the-whole or Congress, every four years or so to deliberate on the subcommittee recommendations and officially adopt or not-adopt such.

From the foregoing, it can easily be seen subcommittees can generally be classified further by the adjectives: &lt;!--[[executive committee| --&gt;&quot;Executive&quot;&lt;!--]]--&gt;, &lt;!--[[standing committee|--&gt;&quot;Standing&quot;&lt;!--]]--&gt;,  and &lt;!--[[working committee|--&gt;&quot;Working&quot;&lt;!--]]--&gt;:

===Executive committees===
{{Anchor|Executive committee}}
A subcommittee which has well defined [[executive power]]s usually spelled out in the charter or [[by-law]]s and which meets frequently to manage the affairs and further the purposes of an organization or entity. These are commonly empanelled as well when an organization has a large Board of Directors such as an international [[labor union]], large corporations (with thousands of stock holders) or national and international organizations. A [[Board of directors]] is itself a kind of Executive committee established by the charter and by-laws of the entity and elected by the overall [[Suffrage|franchised]] membership. For organizations where the Board of Directors is large - say 20 people or more - it is common to have an Executive Committee of the Board&amp;mdash;an executive subcommittee of Board members, which is authorized to make some decisions on behalf of the entire Board.

===Standing committees===
{{Anchor|Standing committee|Permanent committee}}
A committee established by an official and providing for its scope and powers. Most governmental legislative subcommittees are standing committees, which by another name is a '''permanent committee'''. Standing committees meet on a regular or irregular basis dependent upon their enabling act, and retain any power or oversight claims originally given them until subsequent official actions of the committee of the whole (changes to law or by-laws) disbands the committee.

===Working committees===
{{Anchor|Standing committee|Working committee}}
An [[ad hoc]] committee established to accomplish a particular task or to oversee an ongoing area in need of control or oversight. Many are research or co-ordination committees in type or purpose, and can be temporary. Some are a sub-group of a larger society with a particular area of interest which decides to meet and discuss matters pertaining to their interests. For example a group of astronomers might get together ''ad hoc'' to discuss how to get the larger society to address [[near earth object]]s; A subgroup of engineers and scientists of a large project's development team could meet ad hoc to solve some particular issue with offsetting considerations and trade-offs. The term when used officially, generally means a group with specific duties and related authority, so when encountered in official contexts subsumes all other official types of committees. The International Commission on Stratigraphy and its subcommittees (commissions in name) are working committees that meet both far more regularly and more frequently both in deliberation and co-ordination furthering the needs of the IUGS (which regularly schedules meetings only every fourth year) and the larger scientific community.

==Need==
Committees are a necessary aspect of organizations of any significant size (say, more than 15 or 20 people).  They keep the number of participants manageable; with larger groups, either many people do not get to speak (and feel left out), or discussions are quite lengthy (and many participants find them duplicative and often boring).

===Cross-field reasons===
Committees are a way to formally draw together people of relevant expertise from different parts of an organization who otherwise would not have a good way to share information and coordinate actions.  They may have the advantage of widening viewpoints and sharing out responsibilities. They can also be empaneled with experts to recommend actions by the committee of the whole in matters that require specialized knowledge or technical judgment. A &quot;Defense&quot; or &quot;Banking&quot; subcommittee in legislative bodies or the many International science commissions such as the ICS mentioned above, or a local &quot;[[board of health]]&quot; are or may be such.

==Conference committee==
&lt;!-- This is not the proper wa to merge articles! {{:conference committee}} --&gt;
{{Merge from|Conference committee|date=March 2010|discuss=Talk:Committee#Propose merge-in of Conference committee}}

==Standing committees==
A '''standing committee''' is a subunit of a political or deliberative body established in a permanent fashion to aid the parent assembly in accomplishing its duties.  A standing  committee is usually [[wikt:granted|granted]] jurisdiction over a particular area of legislation by the parent body.

Under the laws of the United States of America, a '''standing committee''' is a [[Congressional committee]] permanently authorized by [[United States House of Representatives]] and [[United States Senate]] rules. The [[Legislative Reorganization Act of 1946]] greatly reduced the number of committees, and set up the legislative committee structure still in use today, as modified by authorized changes via the orderly mechanism of rules changes.

===Executive standing committee===

===Legislatures=== &lt;!-- merged in from very short [[standing committee]] stub --&gt;
The phrase is used in the [[legislature]]s of the following countries:
* [[Australia]]
** [[Australian House of Representatives committees]]
** [[Australian Senate committees]]
* [[Canada]]
** [[List of committees of the Canadian House of Commons]]
** [[Standing committee (Canada)]]
* [[China]]
** [[Standing Committee of the National People's Congress]]
** [[Politburo Standing Committee of the Communist Party of China]]
* [[Iceland]]
** [[List of standing committees of the Icelandic parliament]]
* [[India]]
** [[Standing committee (India)]]
* [[United Kingdom]]
** [[Public bill committee]]
* [[United States]]
** [[Standing committee (United States Congress)]]

====Parliamentary committees==== &lt;!-- not sure what to do with this, or it's context. Redirected from [[Parliamentary committee]] --&gt;
The following take part in the [[parliamentary procedure]]:
* [[Fiscal committee]], if the  [[Bill (proposed law)|bill]] contains an [[Appropriation (law)|appropriation]] or has financial implications for the state  or federation.
* [[Policy committee]]. Appropriate committee to the subject matter.
* [[Rules committee]]. The rules committee of the [[United States House of Representatives|House]] assigns each bill to a policy committee.

== Steering committees ==
A steering committee is a committee that provides guidance, direction and control to a project within an organization.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mcleod2008&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Mcleod|title=Management Information Systems | edition = 10 | year = 2008|publisher=Pearson Education|isbn=978-81-317-1949-7|page=201}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term is derived from the [[steering]] mechanism that changes the steering angle of a vehicle's wheels.

Project Steering Committees are frequently used for guiding and monitoring the [[information technology]] projects in large organizations, as part of [[project governance]]. The functions of the committee might including building a business case for the project, planning, providing assistance and guidance, monitoring the progress, controlling the project scope and resolving conflicts.

==See also==
{{Div col|2}}
* [[Committee of the Whole]]
* [[List of Committees of the United Kingdom Parliament]]
* [[List of IEC Technical Committees]]
* [[List of the Czech Republic Senate committees]]
* [[Quorum]]
* [[Standing Committees of the European Parliament]]
* [[United States Congressional committee]]
{{Div col end}}

== References ==
{{reflist}}

{{Parliamentary Procedure}}

[[Category:Political organizations]]
[[Category:Human communication]]
[[Category:Clubs and societies]]
[[Category:Community organizing]]
[[Category:Committees]]
[[Category:Legislatures]]
[[Category:Meetings]]
[[Category:Parliamentary procedure]]
[[Category:Political communication]]

[[ca:Comitè]]
[[cs:Komise]]
[[da:Komite]]
[[es:Comité]]
[[eo:Komitato]]
[[fa:کمیسیون]]
[[ko:위원회]]
[[hi:समिति]]
[[is:Nefnd]]
[[it:Comitato (collegio)]]
[[he:ועדה]]
[[nl:Commissie]]
[[ja:委員会]]
[[no:Nemnd]]
[[pt:Comitê]]
[[so:Guddi]]
[[fi:Komitea]]
[[sv:Utskott]]
[[th:คณะกรรมการ]]</text>
      <sha1>fnh4l6jnfvz28gs7jw5dwqo622vd9z9</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
