<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Consumer organization</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>930420</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519461023</id>
      <parentid>516891622</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-23T21:19:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bluerasberry</username>
        <id>7830073</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* References */ added navbox...</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9952">{{Refimprove|date=June 2009}}

'''Consumer organizations''' are [[advocacy]] groups that seek to protect people from [[corporate abuse]] like unsafe products, [[predatory lending]], [[false advertising]], [[astroturfing]] and [[pollution]].

Consumer organizations may operate via [[protest]]s, [[Advertising campaign|campaigning]] or [[lobbying]]. They may engage in [[single-issue]] advocacy (e.g., the [[United Kingdom|British]] [[Campaign for Real Ale]] (CAMRA), which campaigned against [[keg beer]] and for [[cask ale]]){{Fact|date=June 2009}}  or they may set themselves up as more general consumer [[List of consumer organizations|watchdog]]s, such as the [[Which?|Consumers' Association]] in the UK.

One common means of providing consumers useful information is the independent comparative survey or test of products or services, involving different manufacturers or companies (e.g., ''[[Which?]]'', ''[[Consumer Reports]]'', etcetera).

Another arena where consumer organizations have operated is [[food safety]]. The needs for campaigning in this area are less easy to reconcile with their traditional methods, since the scientific, dietary or medical evidence is normally more complex than in other arenas, such as the electric safety of [[white goods]]. The current standards on [[mandatory labelling]], in developed countries, have in part been shaped by past lobbying by consumer groups.

The aim of consumer organizations may be to establish and to attempt to enforce [[consumer rights]]. Effective work has also been done, however, simply by using the threat of bad publicity to keep companies' focus on the consumers' point of view.{{Fact|date=June 2009}}

Consumer organizations may attempt to serve consumer interests by relatively direct actions such as creating and/or disseminating market information, and prohibiting specific acts or practices,or by promoting competitive forces in the markets which directly or indirectly affect consumers (such as transport, electricity, communications, etc.). {{Fact|date=June 2009}}

==Consumer organizations in various countries==

===International Organization===
* [[Consumers International]] - International NGO
* [[ANEC]] (Europe; focus on standardization)
* [[BEUC]] (Europe; {{lang-fr|Bureau Européen des Unions de Consommateurs}})
* [[International Consumer Research &amp; Testing|ICRT]] The only independent international organization for consumer research and testing

===National Organization===

====Australia====
* [[Consumers' Federation of Australia]]
* [[Australian Consumers Association]]

====Belgium====
* Test-Aankoop[http://www.test-aankoop.be] / Test-Achats[http://www.test-achats.be]

====Botswana====
* [[Consumer Watchdog (Botswana)|Consumer Watchdog]]

====Brazil====
* Proteste [http://www.proteste.org.br]

====Fiji====
[[Consumer council of Fiji|Consumer Council of Fiji]]

[[Fiji Consumers Association]]

====France====
[[UFC Que Choisir]]

====Germany====
* [[Stiftung Warentest]]
* [[Öko-Test]]
* [[Verbraucherzentrale Bundesverband]] (vzbv)

====India====
* [[Consumer Guidance Society of India]]
* [[The Consumers Eye India]] 

Grahak Shakti-Bengaluru-Karnataka-Non profit Non Political Voluntary Consumer Organisation working for the empowerment of Consumer for over two and half decades.Very dedicated and doing yeomen service to the society. They have a large membership base with about 21 Life Timers who contribute their time and energy honorarily. It is driven by a passionate Managing Trustee who leads from front and puts in his money to steer the organisation. They are very principled and have earned Consumer Confidence. They have faced several crisis for being bold and uncompromising in their outlook. Remarkable indeed.

====Italy====
* AltroConsumo[http://www.altroconsumo.it]
* [[Unione nazionale consumatori]][http://consumatori.it]
* Federconsumatori[http://www.federconsumatori.it]

====Japan====
* [[Consumers Union of Japan]] (founded in 1969)
* [[Japan Offspring Fund]] (founded in 1984)

====Korea====
* [[Korea Consumer Agency]] (founded in 1987)[http://www.kca.go.kr]

====The Netherlands====
* De [[Consumentenbond]] (founded in 1953)
====Pakistan====
* The Consumers Eye Pakistan (founded in 2005) [http://www.theconsumerseye.org]

The Consumers Eye Pakistan (TCEP) is a registered social welfare non governmental organization(NGO) of Pakistan an independent and authoritative voice for consumers since year 2005, building a powerful movement to help protect and empower consumers in Pakistan and to create consumer awareness against substandard, unregistered, counterfeit, and adulterated products. The Consumers Eye Pakistan is working   to promote and serve for standardization and Quality consciousness culture in Pakistan. The Consumers Eye Pakistan is organizer of Quality Standard Award in Pakistan, collaboration with Pakistan Standards and Quality Control Authority (PSQCA) Ministry of Science and Technology Government of Pakistan and actively involved in improving quality and standards of the citizens of Pakistan. 



* Consumer Voice Pakistan (CVP) (founded in 1999) [http://www.consumervoicepk.com]

Consumer VOICE Pakistan (CVP) is a Voluntary Organization in Interest of Consumer Education-is the Voice of and for the consumers in every sense. A voluntary action group in Pakistan, it consists of academicians, professionals and volunteers channelising their energies towards creating informed consumers. It raises awareness in consumers not only about malpractices perpetuated in the market place, but also about her/his rights. Consumer VOICE aims at being the most powerful tool in the hands of the consumer to help them fight for value for their money. Consumer awareness has become important because of the liberalizing economy. Consumers need guidance to make informed choice in the products and services available. They need protection against deficient services and products with timely information and intervention. Our Mission is to promote right choices in a volatile and dynamic market place by providing consumer education for all through integrating experiential good practices and scientific knowledge for the safety and health of consumers and the environment.. Consumer VOICE Pakistan (CVP) publishes monthly Consumer VOICE magazine in Pakistan.

====Poland====
* Federacja Konsumentów [http://www.federacja-konsumentow.org.pl] 
* Stowarzyszenie Konsumentów Polskich (founded in 1985) [http://konsumenci.org]

====Portugal====
* DECO.ProTeste [http://www.deco.proteste.pt]

====Republic of Ireland====
* The [[National Consumer Agency]] (NCA) is a statutory body that defends consumer interests in the [[Republic of Ireland]]

====Romania====
* Asociatia Nationala pentru Protectia Consumatorilor si Promovarea Programelor si Strategiilor din Romania/ National Association for Consumers Protection and Promotion of Programs and Strategies from Romania

====Spain====
* Organización de Consumidores y Usuarios (OCU) [http://www.ocu.org]

====Uganda====
* Uganda Consumer Action Network (U-CAN) [http://www.uganda-can.org] is a non-government, not-for profit organisation founded in 2007 and registered as a company limited by guarantee. It works towards ensuring that consumers, especially the most vulnerable (rural poor, disabled, elderly and women) get value for their money through quick, easy, accessible and affordable alternate dispute resolution mechanisms. 

====United Kingdom====
{{main|Consumer protection in the United Kingdom}}
In the United Kingdom, the [[Enterprise Act 2002]] allows consumer bodies that have been approved by the [[Secretary of State for Trade and Industry]] to be designated as &quot;super-complainants&quot; to the [[Office of Fair Trading]]. These [[super-complainant]]s are intended to, &quot;strengthen the voice of consumers,&quot; who are &quot;unlikely to have access individually to the kind of information necessary to judge whether markets are failing for them.&quot; Eight have been designated {{As of|2007|lc=on}}:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dti.gov.uk/consumers/enforcement/super-complaints/page17902.html Super-Complaints - BERR&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Campaign For Real Ale|CAMRA]] - a lobbying group concerned with the tradition and quality of beer.
* The [[Citizen's Advice Bureau]], a free service that provides legal advice, practical help and information on consumer rights across the country.
* [[Consumer Council for Water]] (formerly known as Watervoice)
* [[Consumer Direct]]
* [[General Consumer Council of Northern Ireland]]
* [[Good Garage Scheme]], an [[automobile repair shop]] motoring scheme
* [[National Consumer Council]]
* [[Postwatch]]
* [[Which?]] - formerly the Consumers Association - a consumer advocacy organisation which has substantial powers (for example to take representative actions under the [[Competition Act 1998]]) but which is primarily a lobbying organisation funded entirely by subscriptions to its regular consumer information magazine.

====United States====
* [[Alliance_for_Justice]]
* [[American Consumer Institute]]
* [[Better Business Bureau]]
* [[Consumer Action]]
* [[Consumer Federation of California]]
* [[Consumers Union]], publishers of ''[[Consumer Reports]]''
* [[Consumer Watchdog (USA)]], formerly the Foundation for Taxpayer and Consumer Rights
* [[Public Citizen]]
* [[Consumer Federation of America]]
* [[Center for Science in the Public Interest]] (food/nutrition)
* [[National Consumers League]]
* U.S. [[Public Interest Research Group]]
* [https://rn.ftc.gov/pls/dod/wsolcq$.startup?Z_ORG_CODE=PU01 Consumer Complaint Form, Federal Trade Commission]

==See also==
*[[Actor analysis]]
*[[Transparency (market)]]
*[[Cost the limit of price]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

{{Consumerism}}
{{Business organizations}}

[[Category:Consumer protection]]
[[Category:Advocacy groups]]
[[Category:Consumer organizations]]

[[de:Verbraucherorganisation]]
[[fr:Association de consommateurs]]
[[nl:Consumentenorganisatie]]</text>
      <sha1>g6lhxfujoviiovsx900c0w0egfw1ba7</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
