<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Constitutional crisis</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>192803</id>
    <revision>
      <id>514555325</id>
      <parentid>510442330</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-25T22:02:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Robthepiper</username>
        <id>13704161</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Canada */ typo - added period</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17213">{{refimprove|date=April 2011}}
A '''constitutional crisis''' is a situation that the legal system's [[constitution]] or other basic principles of operation appear unable to resolve; it often results in a breakdown in the orderly operation of [[government]].  Often, generally speaking, a constitutional crisis is a situation in which separate factions within a [[government]] disagree about the extent to which each of these factions hold [[sovereignty]].  Most commonly, constitutional crises involve some degree of conflict between different [[branches of government]] (e.g., [[executive branch|executive]], [[legislature]], and/or [[judiciary]]), or between different levels of government in a federal system (e.g., [[State (non-sovereign)|state]] and federal governments).

A constitutional crisis may occur because one or more parties to the dispute willfully chooses to violate a provision of a [[constitution]] or an unwritten [[Constitutional convention (political custom)|constitutional convention]], or it may occur when the disputants disagree over the interpretation of such a provision or convention.  If the dispute arises because some aspect of the constitution is ambiguous or unclear, the ultimate resolution of the crisis often establishes a precedent for the future.  For instance, the [[United States constitution]] is silent on the question of whether states are allowed to secede from the Union; however, after the secession of several states was forcibly prevented in the [[American Civil War]], it has become generally accepted that states cannot leave the Union.

A constitutional crisis is distinct from a [[rebellion]], which is defined as when factions ''outside'' of a government challenge that government's sovereignty, as in a [[coup]] or [[revolution]] led by the military or civilian protesters.

A constitutional crisis can lead to government paralysis, collapse, or [[civil war]].

==African Constitutional crises==
===Democratic Republic of the Congo===
[[File:PatricelumumbaIISG.jpg|thumb|220px|Patrice Lumumba]]
*President [[Joseph Kasavubu]] and Prime Minister [[Patrice Lumumba]] attempted to dismiss each other in September 1960. General [[Mobutu Sese Seko]] deposed both in a coup later that month, then restored Kasavubu as president.

==Asian Constitutional crises==
===Iran===
*[[Mohammed Reza Pahlavi]]'s 1953 dismissal of Prime Minister [[Mohammed Mossadegh]] and Mossadegh's subsequent refusal to quit the office
===Pakistan===
*Supreme Court Chief Justice [[Sajjad Ali Shah]] clashed repeatedly with Prime Minister [[Nawaz Sharif]] in late 1997, accusing him of undermining the court's independence. After Ali Shah suspended a constitutional amendment that prevented dismissal of the prime minister, Sharif ordered President [[Farooq Leghari]] to appoint a new chief justice. When Leghari refused, Sharif considered [[impeach]]ing him, but backed down after a warning from the armed forces. Faced with a choice of accepting Sharif's demands or dismissing him, Leghari resigned. Ali Shah resigned shortly afterward, establishing Sharif's dominance.
===Thailand===
*In March 2006, 60 seats of the [[National Assembly of Thailand]] could not be elected{{clarification needed|date=July 2012}}, and Prime Minister [[Thaksin Shinawatra]] refused to resign. The judicial system did not lead up to Supreme Court as the top arbitrator so there were inconsistent rulings from the civil, criminal, administrative, and constitutional Courts.

==European Constitutional crises==
===Belgium===
*The [[Leopold III of Belgium#World War II|World War II conduct of Leopold III]] included violation of constitutional principles, including surrender to Germany against [[advice (constitutional)|ministerial advice]].  When he returned to Belgium in 1950, a [[general strike against Leopold III of Belgium|general strike against him]] pushed him into [[abdication]].
*In 1990, [[Baudouin I of Belgium|King Baudouin]] refused routine [[Royal Assent]] to the law on [[abortion in Belgium]].  The issue was resolved by (constitutionally but controversially) having Badouin temporarily declared incapable of reigning, the Council of Ministers giving assent as provided for in the [[Belgian Constitution]], and Badouin declared capable again.
===Denmark===
*The [[Easter Crisis of 1920]], when [[Christian X of Denmark|King Christian X]] of [[Denmark]] dismissed the country's cabinet
===England===
:''For events after 1707, see [[#United Kingdom|below]].''

[[Image:Joao sem terra assina carta Magna.jpg|thumb|220px|right|''John of England signs Magna Carta''. Illustration from ''Cassell's History of England'' (1902)]]
*The 1215 Barons' revolt against the rule of [[John of England|King John]], which led to the [[Magna Carta]].  Immediately, John repudiated Magna Carta, leading to the [[First Barons' War]]
*The [[History of the Church of England#Separation from Papal authority|Break with Rome]], in which [[Henry VIII of England|King Henry VIII]] repudiated [[papal authority]] and created himself [[Supreme Head of the Church of England]], leading to the [[English Reformation]]
*[[Charles I of England|King Charles I]]'s insistence on the [[Divine Right of Kings]], manifest in his [[Personal Rule]] from 1629 to 1640, and leading directly to the [[Wars of the Three Kingdoms]]
*The [[Glorious Revolution]] of 1688-89: The flight of [[James II of England|King James II/VII]] from the country left no king in his place to rule England or Scotland or to summon a [[Parliament]].  When [[William and Mary|King William and Queen Mary]] jointly replaced him there was therefore no legally recognised Parliament to legitimise their irregular succession to the throne. This led to the [[Crown and Parliament Recognition Act 1689]].

===France===
*The [[16 May 1877 crisis|constitutional crisis of the 16 May 1877]]: President [[Patrice de Mac-Mahon]] dismisses Prime Minister [[Jules Simon]] and names [[Albert de Broglie]] to replace him. The [[National Assembly]] refuses to recognize the new government and a crisis, which ends with the dissolution of the Assembly and new elections, ensues.

===Germany===
*In 2011, the Berlin Court upheld the City of Berlin's decision to not register the marriage of two homosexual men, which is in contradition to the 2009 ruling of the Federal Constitutional Court that demanded full marriage equality for gay persons.

===Malta===
*The 1981 election, when, due to a quirk in that country's [[Single Transferrable Vote]] system, the party winning more than half the votes won fewer than half the seats
===Norway===
*[[Dissolution of the union between Norway and Sweden in 1905]]
===Rome===
*The crossing of the [[Rubicon]] by [[Julius Caesar]] in 49 BC with his legions. This action, which had no precedent, precipitated a crisis only fully resolved in 31 BC, when [[Augustus|Octavian]] defeated all his enemies to become the sole master of the Roman world.
===Russia===
[[Image:Tanks before Russian White house.jpg|thumb|220px|Tanks of the [[2nd Guards Tamanskaya Motor Rifle Division|Taman Division]] shelling the [[White House (Moscow)|Russian White House]] on 4 October 1993.]]
*The [[Russian constitutional crisis of 1993|constitutional crisis of 1993]]: a conflict between [[President of Russia|Russian President]] [[Boris Yeltsin]] and the Russian parliament led by [[Ruslan Khasbulatov]], which resulted in a military siege of the parliament building and street fighting, claiming 187 lives. [[Aleksandr Rutskoy]] assumed the powers of the Acting President of Russia for a few days.

===Scotland===
This covers the [[Kingdom of Scotland]], which became part of the [[Kingdom of Great Britain]] after 1707. For constitutional crises since then, see [[Constitutional crisis#Constitutional Crises in the United Kingdom|United Kingdom]] below.
*The succession crisis resulting from the death of [[Margaret of Scotland (Maid of Norway)|Queen Margaret]] in 1290.  [[Edward I of England]], whose [[Edward II of England|son Edward]] was to marry Margaret, was asked to arbitrate, and chose [[John Balliol]], who swore an [[oath of fealty]] to Edward, turning Scotland into an English vassal in 1292.  Soon, Balliol and the [[Scottish nobility]] revolted, leading to the [[Wars of Scottish Independence]].
===United Kingdom===&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Constitutional crisis]] --&gt;
*The rejection of the 1909 [[People's Budget]] by the [[House of Lords]]. This caused a two-year impasse, leading to the [[Parliament Act 1911]].
*The 1936 [[Edward VIII abdication crisis]], when [[Edward VIII of the United Kingdom|King Edward VIII]] proposed to marry divorcee [[Wallis, The Duchess of Windsor|Wallis Simpson]] against the advice of his ministers.

==North American Constitutional crises==
===Canada===
*In the [[King-Byng Affair]] of 1926, [[Governor General of Canada|Governor General]] [[Viscount Byng of Vimy]] refused the request of [[Prime Minister of Canada|Prime Minister]] [[William Lyon Mackenzie King]] to [[dissolution of parliament|dissolve Parliament]] and call new elections after King had, months before, refused to resign.  Instead, Byng dismissed King and appointed [[Arthur Meighen]] as Prime Minister, after which Meighen found himself unable to retain [[confidence (politics)|confidence]], triggering his own resignation and an election.  Reaction to the affair was reflected in the [[Balfour Declaration of 1926]], the resulting separation of [[British Dominions|Dominion]] [[Governors-General]] from the British government, and the [[Statute of Westminster 1931]] that made each realm of the Crown independent.
*The 1982 [[patriation]] of the [[British North America Act]] was contentious, as there were conflicting opinions from the federal government, provincial governments, and [[Supreme Court of Canada|Supreme Court]] over what exactly the procedure was whereby Canada could request a [[constitutional amendment]] from [[the United Kingdom]].  The Supreme Court's decision in the [[Quebec Veto Reference]] found that [[Québec]] did not have a veto on patriation, and the process was legitimate and binding.The [[National Assembly of Québec]] symbolically refuses to ratify the Constitution Act in its current form.&lt;!-- Is this a crisis?  The government seems to have continued operating since 1982. --&gt;
*The [[2008–2009 Canadian parliamentary dispute]], in which [[Liberal Party of Canada|Liberal]], [[New Democratic Party|NDP]], and [[Bloc Quebecois]] Members of Parliament attempted to have a vote of non-confidence against the [[Conservative Party of Canada|Conservative]] government and replace it with a coalition government, was unprecedented in the Canadian constitutional system, as formal party based co-operation was rare.  [[Stephen Harper|Prime Minister Stephen Harper]] controversially, but successfully, gained a [[prorogation]] of Parliament from the Governor General.  The coalition effort subsequently fell apart, leaving the key questions around the dispute unanswered.

===Honduras===
*The [[2009 Honduran constitutional crisis]] saw President [[Manuel Zelaya]] attempting to hold a non-binding referendum which [[National Congress of Honduras|Congress]] and the [[Supreme Court of Honduras|Supreme Court]] deemed unconstitutional. The military, following orders from the Supreme Court, arrested President Zelaya.

===United States===
[[Image:Florida Case.jpg|right|thumb|220px|The Electoral Commission was a panel that resolved the disputed presidential election of 1876.]]
*The [[Stamp Act 1765]], by which the British Parliament sought to tax the [[Thirteen Colonies]], set off protests against [[taxation without representation]]. Parliament continued to assert its authority in subsequent acts, leading the colonists to declare total independence from Britain.
*The [[Nullification Crisis]] of 1832, in which [[South Carolina]] declared that it would not permit collection of a federal tariff.
*The death of [[William Henry Harrison]], the ninth [[president of the United States]], in 1841: no President had ever before died in office, and the Constitution did not specify whether the incumbent [[Vice President of the United States|Vice President]] [[John Tyler]] became President or [[Acting President of the United States|Acting President]].
*The [[Secession in the United States|secession]] of seven [[Southern United States|Southern]] [[U.S. state|states]], which the federal government did not recognize, leading to the [[American Civil War]].
*[[United States presidential election, 1876|1876 presidential election]]: [[Republican Party (United States)|Republicans]] and [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democrats]] disputed voting results in three states. The [[Electoral Commission (United States)|Electoral Commission]], created by [[United States Congress|Congress]], voted along party lines in favor of Republican candidate [[Rutherford B. Hayes]], who damped Southern fury by withdrawing federal troops from the South.

==Oceanian Constitutional crises==
===Australia===
*The [[1975 Australian constitutional crisis]] saw the [[Prime Minister of Australia|Prime Minister]] [[Gough Whitlam]] dismissed by the nation's [[Governor-General of Australia|Governor-General]] [[John Kerr (governor-general)|Sir John Kerr]], in response to a prolonged budget deadlock in Parliament.  This occurred even though Whitlam's government had the [[confidence (politics)|confidence]] of the lower house, the [[Australian House of Representatives|House of Representatives]]. In the [[Australian Constitution]] the [[Senate|Australian Senate]] has equal powers with the House of Representatives, except it may not initiate or amend a [[supply bill]]. It can, however, reject or defer consideration of a money bill, and that is what it did on this occasion.

===Fiji===
*In the [[Fiji constitutional crisis of 1977]], the winning party in a general election failed to name a government due to internal conflicts. The [[Governor-General of Fiji|Governor-General]] intervened, appointing a prime minister from the opposition party.
===Malaysia===
* The [[1983 Malaysian constitutional crisis]] saw Prime Minister [[Mahathir bin Mohamad|Mahathir]] pushing forward an amendment of Article 66 of the Federal Constitution, which set the time limit of the [[Yang di-Pertuan Agong|Agong]] to veto a law within 30 days.{{clarify|date=November 2010}}  The proposals generated a great deal of controversy between the government and the monarchy, of which the former had to launch a public campaign to pressure the monarchy to assent to the amendments.
* The [[1988 Malaysian constitutional crisis]] was a series of events that began with the [[United Malays National Organization]] (UMNO) general election in 1987 and ended with the suspension and the eventual removal of [[Lord President of the Supreme Court]] of Malaysia [[Malay titles#Tun|Tun]] [[Salleh Abas]] from his seat.
* The [[1993 amendments to the Constitution of Malaysia]] (by some interpretations a constitutional crisis) involved the limitation of monarchs' power in Malaysia. Prime Minister [[Mahathir bin Mohamad]] successfully amended the constitution to make the monarchies more accountable to their actions.
*The [[2009 Perak constitutional crisis]] occurred in the Malaysian state of [[Perak]] when [[party switching|party defections]] caused the state ruling coalition, [[Pakatan Rakyat]], to lose its majority in the [[Dewan Undangan Negeri|state assembly]]. The [[Sultan of Perak]] refused to dissolve the state assembly when requested and dismissed the [[Menteri Besar]] (Chief Minister) while the [[Menteri Besar]] technically still had the [[motion of confidence|confidence]] of the assembly.
===New Zealand===
*The [[New Zealand constitutional crisis, 1984|New Zealand constitutional crisis of 1984]] was caused by [[Prime Minister of New Zealand|Prime Minister]] [[Robert Muldoon|Sir Robert Muldoon]]'s refusal to devalue the [[New Zealand dollar|dollar]] as per the instructions of the Prime Minister-elect, [[David Lange]].  The cabinet rebelled against Muldoon, who relented.  The upshot was the passage of the [[Constitution Act 1986 (NZ)|Constitution Act]], which patriated the constitution from the United Kingdom.

==South American Constitutional crises==
===Chile===
*[[1973 Chilean coup d'état]]: In response to the increasing authoritarianism of [[Salvador Allende]]'s government during a US-instigated economic crisis, the Supreme Court and lower house declared him out of order and urged the military to put an end to constitutional breaches. The military deposed Allende a few weeks later and abolished the constitution.

===Peru===
*[[Peruvian Constitutional Crisis of 1992]]: President [[Alberto Fujimori]], with the support of the armed forces, dissolved the Congress after it rejected his proposal for stronger action against [[Shining Path]] and [[MRTA]]. Then, he called for elections for a [[Democratic Constitutional Congress]] to write the 1993 [[Peruvian Constitution]]. Until the new constitution was written, he ruled by decree.

==Footnotes==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Constitutional law]]
[[Category:Politics by issue]]

[[de:Verfassungskrise]]
[[es:Crisis constitucional]]
[[hr:Ustavna kriza]]</text>
      <sha1>gdj56etvyqp9o1m3jp4oozodiv2eo6r</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
