<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Contentious politics</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2195817</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520322012</id>
      <parentid>401963434</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-28T21:02:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>66.27.98.27</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3778">'''Contentious politics''' is the use of disruptive techniques to make a [[politics|political]] point, or to change government policy. Examples of such techniques are actions that disturb the normal activities of society such as [[Demonstration (people)|demonstrations]], general [[strike action]], [[riot]], [[terrorism]], [[civil disobedience]], and even [[revolution]] or [[insurrection]]. [[Social movements]] often engage in contentious politics.  The concept distinguishes these forms of contention from the everyday acts of resistance explored by [[James C. Scott]], interstate warfare, and forms of contention employed entirely within institutional settings, such as elections or sports.  Tilly defines contentious politics as:

*&quot;interactions in which actors make claims bearing on someone else's interest, in which governments appear either as targets, initiators of claims, or third parties.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Tilly, Charles. Contentious Performances. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2008: 5.&lt;/ref&gt;

Contentious politics has existed forever, but its form varies over time and space.  For example, historical sociologist [[Charles Tilly]] argues that the nature of contentious politics changed fairly dramatically with the birth of [[social movements]] in 18th century Europe.  

The concept of contentious politics was developed throughout the 1990s and into the 21st century by its most prominent scholars in the United States: [[Sidney Tarrow]], Charles Tilly, and [[Doug McAdam]].  Until its development, the study of contentious politics was divided among a number of traditions each of which were concerned with the description and explanation of different contentious political phenomena, especially the social movement, the strike, and revolution.  One of the primary goals of these three authors was to advance the explanation of these phenomena and other contentious politics under a single research agenda.&lt;ref&gt;McAdam, Doug, Sidney Tarrow, and Charles Tilly. Dynamics of Contention. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt; There remains a significant plurality of agendas in addition to the one these three propose.

==Prominent scholars==
*[[Doug McAdam]]
*[[Alberto Melucci]]
*[[Charles Tilly]]
*[[Sidney Tarrow]]
*[[Alain Touraine]]

==Academic Journals==
*[[Mobilization: The International Quarterly Review of Social Movement Research]]
*[[Social Movement Studies]]

==Notes and references==
{{reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
*Gamson, William A. The Strategy of Social Protest, 2nd ed. Belmont, CA: Wadsworth Publishing, 1990.
*Goodwin, Jeff, and James M. Jasper, eds. Rethinking Social Movements: Structure, Meaning and Emotion. Lanham, MD: Rowman &amp; Littlefield, 2004.
*Jasper, James. The Art of Moral Protest: Culture, Biography, and Creativity in Social 	Movements. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1997.
*McAdam, Doug. Political Process and the Development of Black Insurgency, 1930–1970, 2nd ed. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1999.
*Melucci, Alberto. Challenging Codes: Collective Action in the Information Age.  Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1996.
*Piven, Frances Fox and Richard A Cloward. Poor People‘s Movements: Why They Succeed, How They Fail. New York: Vintage Books, 1979.
*Tarrow, Sidney. Power in Movement: Social Movements and Contentious Politics, 2nd ed.	Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1998.
*Tilly, Charles. The Contentious French. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1986.
*Tilly, Charles. Popular Contention in Great Britain, 1758-1834. Boulder, CO: Paradigm Publishers, 1995b.

==See also==
*[[Social movement theory]]

[[Category:Civil disobedience]]
[[Category:Social movements]]
[[Category:Political activism]]
[[Category:Political communication]]


{{poli-term-stub}}
{{socio-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>lid923a9qce4cxo3q1e3dkex9bb39t2</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
