<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Contempt of Parliament</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7999739</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519135093</id>
      <parentid>519135021</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-22T03:29:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>50.99.254.87</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Contempt citation cases for governments */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14622">In some countries, '''contempt of parliament''' is the offence of obstructing the [[legislature]] in the carrying out of its functions, or of hindering any [[legislator]] in the performance of his or her duties. The offence is known by various other names in jurisdictions in which the legislature is not called &quot;[[parliament]]&quot;. Actions that may constitute contempt of parliament include:
* Deliberately misleading a house of the legislature, or a legislative [[committee]];
* refusing to [[testify]] before, or to produce documents to, a house or committee; and
* attempting to influence a member of the legislature by bribery or threats.

In some jurisdictions, a house of parliament may declare any act to constitute contempt, and this is not subject to judicial review. In others, contempt of parliament is defined by [[statute]]; while parliament makes the initial decision of whether to punish for contempt, the person or organisation in contempt may appeal to the [[court]]s. Some jurisdictions consider contempt of parliament to be a criminal offence. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.claruspress.ie/contempt_of_parl.html Contempt of Parliament, by Kieron Wood (Clarus Press, 2012)]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Australia==
In the [[Commonwealth of Australia]], the ''Parliamentary Privileges Act 1987'' defines contempt of Parliament as follows:

''Conduct (including the use of words)... [which] amounts, or is intended or likely to amount, to an improper interference with the free exercise by a House or committee of its authority or functions, or with the free performance by a member of the member's duties as a member.''

Contempt decisions by the [[Australian House of Representatives|House of Representatives]] or the [[Australian Senate|Senate]] are thus subject to review by the Federal Courts.

Punishments are limited under the Act to (for individuals) a [[Fine (penalty)|fine]] of $5,000 and/or six months' imprisonment, or (for corporations) a fine of $25,000.

In the Senate, allegations of contempt are heard by the Privileges Committee, which decides whether or not contempt was committed, and if so, what punishment is to be imposed.  In practice, there have been very few times when a hearing determined that anyone was in contempt, and on no occasions has anyone been punished beyond a warning, with an apology and/or appropriate remedial action.

==Canada==
:''See also: [[Censure#Canada|Parliamentary censure in Canada]] and [[Parliamentary_privilege#Parliamentary_privilege_in_Canada|Parliamentary Privilege in Canada]]''

The power to find a person in contempt of Parliament stemmed from Section 18 of the [[Constitution Act, 1867]] in which &quot;The privileges, immunities, and powers to be held, enjoyed... shall not confer any privileges, immunities, or powers exceeding those at the passing of such Act held, enjoyed, and exercised by the Commons House of Parliament of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland, and by the members thereof.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://laws.justice.gc.ca/en/const/2.html#anchorbo-ga:s_17 Constitution Acts, 1867]&lt;/ref&gt;

Regarding the above-mentioned &quot;privileges,&quot; there is an important difference between the &quot;individual parliamentary privileges&quot; and &quot;collective parliamentary privileges.&quot; This difference is also important in any case of &quot;[[breach of privilege]]&quot; as it applies to [[Parliamentary_privilege#Parliamentary_privilege_in_Canada|Parliamentary privilege in Canada]].

===Contempt citation cases for individuals===

Rarely has the [[Parliament of Canada|Canadian federal parliament]] invoked its power to find an individual in contempt:  There were &quot;contempt citation&quot; cases in 1913,&lt;ref name=&quot;rare&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.canada.com/topics/news/story.html?id=42920e1a-7f36-4dbc-902b-8b6cf9ae96bb |title=Examples of 'rare' contempt of Parliament cases |author=Canwest News Service |date= April 10, 2008|work= |publisher= CanWest MediaWorks Publications Inc|accessdate=21 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 1976,&lt;ref name=&quot;rare&quot;/&gt; 2003,&lt;ref name=&quot;rare&quot;/&gt; 2008&lt;ref name=&quot;rare&quot;/&gt; and 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;PM&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=PM on rulings: 'win some, lose some' |author= Laura Payton|url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/politics/story/2011/03/09/pol-speaker-rulings.html |newspaper= [[CBC News]]|date=March 9, 2011 |accessdate=26 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The April 10, 2008 case involved [[Royal Canadian Mounted Police]] deputy commissioner [[Barbara George (deputy commissioner)|Barbara George]] who was cited for contempt for deliberately misleading a [[parliamentary committee]] over an [[Giuliano_Zaccardelli#Controversy over income trust file|income trust scandal]]. She was ultimately found in contempt but was not punished further than the [[Motion (legal)|motion]] itself.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbc.ca/canada/story/2008/04/10/rcmp-contempt.html RCMP deputy commissioner found in contempt of Parliament]&lt;/ref&gt;

The March 2011 contempt citation case involved [[Conservative Party of Canada|Conservative]] MP [[Bev Oda]].&lt;ref name=&quot;PM&quot;/&gt; While she was found to be ''[[prima facie]]'' in contempt by the [[Speaker of the Canadian House of Commons|Speaker]], Oda was not formally held in contempt because Parliament was dissolved before a vote could be held on the matter.&lt;ref name=&quot;hook&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Oda off the hook |author=Mike De Souza |url= http://www.montrealgazette.com/business/hook/4507178/story.html|newspaper= [[Montreal Gazette]]|date= March 26, 2011|accessdate=26 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Contempt citation cases for governments===

On March 9, 2011, [[Speaker of the Canadian House of Commons|Speaker]] of the [[House of Commons of Canada|Canadian House of Commons]] [[Peter Milliken]] made two Contempt of Parliament rulings: The first found that a [[Conservative Party of Canada|Conservative Party]] cabinet minister, [[Bev Oda]], could possibly be in contempt of Parliament.&lt;ref name=&quot;PM&quot;/&gt; The second ruling found the [[Cabinet of Canada|Cabinet]] could possibly be in contempt of Parliament for not meeting Opposition members' requests for details of proposed bills and their cost estimates, an issue which had &quot;been dragging on since the fall of 2010.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;PM&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;findings&quot;/&gt; Milliken ruled that both matters must go to their responsible parliamentary committees and that the committee was required to report its findings to the Speaker by March 21, 2011 — one day before the proposal of the budget.

Concerning the Speaker's first ruling, on March 18, 2011, Opposition members of the committee (who outnumbered the government members) said they still judged Oda to be in contempt of Parliament, despite her testimony that day,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/story/2011/03/18/pol-oda-privilege.html |title=MPs to return Monday on contempt debate |author=Laura Payton |date=March 18 |work= |publisher= [[CBC News]]|accessdate=21 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; but the committee process never proceeded far enough to make a finding as to whether Oda was in contempt.&lt;ref name=&quot;hook&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;findings&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/politics/story/2011/03/21/pol-privilege-contempt.html |title=MPs' report finds government in contempt |author= |date=March 21 |work= |publisher= [[CBC News]] |accessdate=24 March 211}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Concerning the Speaker's second ruling, on March 21, 2011, the committee tabled a report&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www2.parl.gc.ca/content/hoc/Committee/403/PROC/Reports/RP5047570/procrp27/procrp27-e.pdf |title=Question of Privilege Relating to the Failure of the Government To Fully Provide the Documents as Ordered by the House: Report of the Standing Committee on Procedure and House Affairs |accessdate=2011-04-26 |date=2011-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; that found the Government of Canada in contempt of Parliament.&lt;ref name=&quot;findings&quot;/&gt; As such, a [[motion of no confidence]] was introduced in the House.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.globaltvcalgary.com/personalities/Liberals+introduce+confidence+motion/4489986/story.html&lt;/ref&gt; On March 25, 2011, [[Member of Parliament (Canada)|Members of Parliament]] voted on this motion, declaring a lack of confidence by a vote of 156 to 145 and [[Canadian federal election, 2011|forcing an election]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/politics/story/2011/03/25/pol-defeat.html |title=MPs gather for historic vote |author=[[CBC News]] |publisher=[[Canadian Broadcasting Corporation|CBC]] |date=25 March 2011 |accessdate=25 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Mayeda|first=Andrew|title=Harper government falls|url=http://www.vancouversun.com/Harper+government+falls/4503131/story.html|accessdate=25 March 2011|newspaper=Vancouver Sun|date=March 25, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The contempt finding is unique in Canadian history. In a wider context, it is the first time that a government in the 54-member [[Commonwealth of Nations]] has been found in contempt of Parliament.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://winnipeg.ctv.ca/servlet/an/local/CTVNews/20110325/wpg_election_110325/20110325/?hub=WinnipegHome |title= Harper government topples on contempt motion, triggering May election|author= Bruce Cheadle|date=Mar. 25 2011 |work= |publisher= [[The Canadian Press]]; [[CTV news]]|accessdate=25 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Walkom: Yes, contempt of Parliament does matter |author= Thomas Walkom|url=http://www.thestar.com/news/canada/politics/article/962022--walkom-yes-contempt-of-parliament-does-matter |newspaper=[[Toronto Star]] |date=March 25, 2011 |accessdate=25 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although it led to a successful vote of non-confidence that forced an election. Earlier that week, all three opposition parties had indicated that they would oppose the government's budget, and though that vote was never scheduled, a budget is a confidence matter in its own right.&lt;ref name=&quot;macleans1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Wells |first=Paul |url=http://www2.macleans.ca/2011/05/05/not-feeling-the-love/ |title=The untold story of the 2011 election: Chapter 2 |publisher=Macleans.ca |date=2011-05-05 |accessdate=2012-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The resulting election devastated two of the opposition parties who supported the contempt motion, with the [[Liberal Party of Canada|Liberals]] losing more than half their seats to drop to third place in the Commons for the first time, while the [[Bloc Québécois]] was nearly wiped out, with both their leaders also personally losing their ridings. The [[Conservative Party of Canada|Conservatives]] gained seats to form a [[majority government]], while the [[New Democratic Party]] won a record number of seats to form the [[Official Opposition (Canada)|Official Opposition]].

== Hong Kong ==
Contempt of the Legislative Council is a criminal offence.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.legislation.gov.hk/blis_ind.nsf/B505654FA2FD062B4825647A00339D10/64C13573F10A5859C825648300293C0E?OpenDocument ]&lt;/ref&gt;

==United Kingdom==
{{Refimprove section|date=July 2011}}
Contempt of Parliament consists of interference with parliamentary privilege and of certain acts that obstruct the house and its members in their business.

The same rules as apply to the [[House of Commons of the United Kingdom|House of Commons]] apply to the [[House of Lords]] ''[[mutatis mutandis]]'' (i.e. with the necessary modifications).

Parliamentary privilege consists of freedom of speech on the floor of the House and in committee, freedom from arrest, regulating its membership and exclusive cognisance of internal affairs.

Privilege extends to the publication of papers and reports by order of the House, including the official record 'Hansard'.

Freedom from arrest originally prevented the arrest (on criminal as well as civil grounds) of members, their goods and their staff.  The freedom from arrest of servants and goods were removed in the 18th century as the privilege was open to abuse, as was immunity from arrest for criminal acts.  MPs today are only protected from arrest on civil grounds, for contempt of court.

Regulation of composition extends to determining who is elected and whether they may take their seat.  The result of elections is now ''de facto'' a matter for an Election Court composed of [[High Court of Justice|High Court]] judges, who issue a certificate to the [[Speaker of the House of Commons (United Kingdom)|Speaker]] in the case of elections where the result is disputed.  The House also has exclusive right to determine whether members may take up their seat, including whether a member is eligible to take the relevant oath.

Exclusive cognisance of internal affairs extends to the right to determine the oaths to be taken by members and who may take them (''Bradlaugh v Gossett''), the right to determine who may use House of Commons facilities and the exclusion of the jurisdiction of the courts as to alcohol sale offences within the Palace of Westminster.

In the [[United Kingdom]], it has been alleged that arresting a member of Parliament in the course of carrying out his duties may constitute contempt of Parliament,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Allegation made by [[Michael Howard]], a lawyer and former Home Secretary|url= http://www.guardian.co.uk/politics/2008/nov/28/conservatives1 | location=London | work=The Guardian|first1=Nicholas|last1=Watt|first2=Andrew|last2=Sparrow|date=28 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; although immunity from criminal arrest was removed by the Parliamentary Privilege Acts of the 18th century.

It is further contempt to bribe or attempt to bribe any member (and for any member to accept or solicit a bribe), to disrupt the sittings of the House or a committee—wherever it is sitting, to refuse to appear before a committee to testify, to refuse to answer any question put by a committee, to lie to a committee or to refuse to swear an oath when testifying, or to otherwise obstruct the business of the House.

MPs accused of Contempt of Parliament may be suspended or expelled.&lt;ref name=Lyne&gt;{{cite news |title=Contempt Drama Grips Parliament |author=Peter Lyne |newspaper=The Christian Science Monitor |date= March 26, 1964 |page=13 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  They may also be committed to the clock tower under [[Big Ben]],&lt;ref name=Lyne /&gt; although this practice hasn't been used since [[Charles Bradlaugh]] was detained in 1880.  Strangers (those who are not members of the House) may be committed to prison during the life of the Parliament.  The House of Lords has the power to fine as well as to order imprisonment for a term of years.

==See also==
* [[Contempt of Congress]], United States
* [[Contempt of court]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Contempt Of Parliament}}
[[Category:Australian political terms]]
[[Category:Canadian political terms]]
[[Category:Political terms in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Parliamentary procedure]]

[[fr:Outrage au parlement]]</text>
      <sha1>p4pusq1qzvy2szpa4b712amy7q04oic</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
