<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>CountyWatch</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2827293</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519760927</id>
      <parentid>519759324</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-25T13:58:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dave.Dunford</username>
        <id>144047</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Berkshire */ copy edit</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17644">{{Refimprove|date=August 2007}}
{{Cleanup|date=December 2007}}
'''CountyWatch''' is a [[direct action]] group in the [[United Kingdom]] that was set up in 2004 to remove what they consider to be wrongly placed county boundary signs that do not mark the historic or ancient county boundaries of [[Historic counties of England|England]] and [[Historic counties of Wales|Wales]]. Since 2005, Count [[Nikolai Tolstoy]] has been Patron of CountyWatch. CountyWatch and its supporters claim to have removed, re-sited or erected 80 county boundary signs in [[Dorset]], [[County Durham]], [[Greater Manchester]], [[Hampshire]], [[Lancashire]], [[Lincolnshire]], [[North Yorkshire]], [[Somerset]] and [[Warwickshire]].

A prominent member of the group is [[Anthony Bennett (English politician)|Anthony Bennett]], a British politician. In May 2002 Bennett was prosecuted for removing 29 metric road signs that he claimed were illegal and that he was preventing the law from being broken. He buried the signs in four locations under bushes. Initially found guilty of theft and criminal damage, his theft conviction was overturned in October 2002 on appeal. The judge stated that &quot;there was no evidence of dishonesty or that he intended to permanently deprive the owners of their signs.&quot; His conviction for criminal damage was upheld, but the Judge discharged the sentence, which had been 50 hours of community service.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC News2002118&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title='Imperial vigilante' guilty of theft |publisher=[[BBC News]] |date=2002-05-22 |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/2002118.stm|accessdate=2007-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC News2384065&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title='Imperial vigilante' wins legal appeal |publisher=[[BBC News]] |date=2002-10-31 |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/2384065.stm |accessdate=2007-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Beliefs==
{{cquote|The [[Anglo-Saxons]] set up a network of shires whose boundaries, in some cases, have been unchanged for over 1,000 years. The [[Normans]] may have conquered us in 1066 but at least they left our shire boundaries in place, just changing the name to &quot;Counties&quot; when they placed their own Counts in charge of the shires. The Conservatives under [[Edward Heath]] started the process of dismantling our network of shire Counties when they created the hugely unpopular new &quot;Counties&quot; of [[Avon (county)|Avon]], [[Humberside]] and [[Cleveland, England|Cleveland]]. Now it seems [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour]] wants to finish them off. Many [[English people]] have a strong sense of place and we are sure many of them will fight hard to keep alive and healthy the names and the real boundaries of our Counties.|20px|20px|Derek Norman, Chairman of CountyWatch&lt;ref&gt;2005 CountyWatch newsletter from the time that Count Nikolai Tolstoy was announced as patron&lt;/ref&gt;}}

CountyWatch sees the abolition of democratically elected [[county council]]s in the UK as part of a long-term project to weaken the constituent nations of Europe, notably the UK, and to concentrate power at two levels: [[Brussels]] (the [[European Commission]]) and the &quot;regions&quot; within countries. CountyWatch believes in taking direct action within the law to counter aspects of this project.&lt;ref&gt;Tony Bennett, &quot;The Counties&quot; [[Association of British Counties]] newsletter, Spring 2006&lt;/ref&gt;{{Or|date=August 2007}}

There have been similar illegal acts before. The former county of [[Humberside]] was extremely unpopular with some of its residents.  The book ''The Fight for Yorkshire'' by Michael Bradford detailed a series of cases where signs were altered to read &quot;East Riding of Yorkshire&quot; in North Humberside.&lt;ref&gt;''The Fight for Yorkshire'', Michael Bradford, Hutton Press, Beverley, 1988&lt;/ref&gt;  None of these acts were ever prosecuted and in 1996 [[Humberside]] was abolished.

==Direct action==
===Bedfordshire===
In August 2007, CountyWatch took its campaign to [[Bedfordshire]], where, in November 2006, [[Bedfordshire County Council]] erected four signs on the main roads on the north, west and south sides out of [[Luton]] proclaiming 'Welcome to Bedfordshire'. [[Luton]] is the largest town within the historic and [[Ceremonial counties of England|ceremonial county]] of Bedfordshire. Some letter writers still address mail to &quot;Luton Beds&quot;. Some organisations based in Luton, such as the [[University of Bedfordshire]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.beds.ac.uk/contactus |title=Contact/Find us |publisher=University of Bedfordshire |accessdate=25 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; include 'Bedfordshire' as part of their address. In 1996, the [[Royal Mail]] stopped using [[Postal counties of the United Kingdom|Postal Counties]] as a method of sorting mail, using instead the post code. However, they have a &quot;flexible addressing policy&quot; whereby historic counties can be used. Luton became a [[unitary authority]] on 1 April 1997.&lt;ref name=&quot;LH001&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
  | last = Lambert
  | first = Tim
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = A brief history of Luton
  | work =
  | publisher = Local Histories
  | date = 
  | url = http://www.localhistories.org/luton.html 
  | doi =
  | accessdate = 2007-08-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Bedfordshire County Council no longer runs any services in the area covered by [[Luton Borough Council]].

The County Council erected the signs only in November 2006 in a struggle to save Bedfordshire County Council from extinction against rival bids from the [[Bedford (borough)|Borough of Bedford]] to become a unitary Borough Council and from [[Mid Bedfordshire (district)|Mid Bedfordshire]] and [[South Bedfordshire]] Councils to become another unitary authority, to be called ''[[Central Bedfordshire]]''.

The signs were unpopular with some Luton residents, some of whom called the signs &quot;snooty&quot;. Bedfordshire County Council responded by saying, &quot;Luton has been a unitary authority since 1997 and is therefore not part of Bedfordshire.&lt;ref name=&quot;LS46700&quot;&gt;
{{cite news 
  | last =
  | first =
  | coauthors =
  | title = County welcome road signs spark snootiness charge
  | work =
  | pages =
  | language =
  | publisher = Luton on Sunday
  | date = 2007-02-27
  | url = http://www.lutononsunday.com/lutononsunday-news/DisplayArticle.asp?id=46700
  | accessdate = 2007-08-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2007, the government announced that Bedfordshire County Council would be abolished in 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;Guardian2134502&quot;&gt;
{{cite news 
  | last = Vaughan
  | first = Paul
  | coauthors =
  | title = Government gives go-ahead to councils shake-up
  | work =
  | pages =
  | language =
  | publisher = [[The Guardian]]
  | date = 2007-07-25
  | url = http://society.guardian.co.uk/localgovt/news/0,,2134502,00.html 
  | accessdate = 2007-08-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 9 August 2007, CountyWatch removed four ''Welcome to Bedfordshire'' signs from Luton, claiming they were misleading to the public. One sign was removed from the B653 to [[Wheathampstead]] and re-erected on the A505 near [[Stopsley]] in front of a ''Welcome to Luton'' sign. The other three signs were removed from the A6, the A505 and the B579. CountyWatch claimed these were being stored at a secure location and added that the signs would be returned to the County Council if they were re-sited on what CountyWatch deem to be the ''true'' Bedfordshire boundaries. The County Council responded by stating that, &quot;This is absolutely crazy. We are proud of our county and we like to ensure that visitors are given a warm welcome. The signs on the edge of Luton mark the boundaries of their responsibilities and the beginnings of ours.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;LS131344&quot;&gt;
{{cite news 
  | last = Cunniffe
  | first = Jessica
  | coauthors =
  | title = County vigilantes seize 'misleading' road signs
  | work =
  | pages =
  | language =
  | publisher = Luton on Sunday
  | date = 2007-08-12
  | url = http://www.lutononsunday.com/lutononsunday-news/DisplayArticle.asp?ID=131344
  | accessdate = 2007-08-12 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
For anyone still interested in finding a 'Welcome to Bedfordshire' sign, look no further than the A428 at Eynesbury, just South of St. Neots as you travel westbound under the bridge.

===Berkshire===
In April 2006 the group set up &quot;Royal County of Berkshire&quot; signs on the ancient border between [[Berkshire]] and [[Oxfordshire]].  The signs were quickly removed. The Mayor of [[Abingdon, Oxfordshire|Abingdon]], once the county town of Berkshire, now administered by Oxfordshire County Council, said &quot;I still get letters addressed to me with Abingdon, Berkshire, and many older people still have allegiances.&quot; The Mayor of [[Wantage]], however, noted, &quot;I think Count Tolstoy and his supporters are living in the past. They need to face reality. I know there are many older people in Wantage who still think of themselves as Berkshire people, but the reality is that time has moved on and we can't go backwards.&quot; The Mayor of Faringdon said that &quot;Faringdon should stay in Oxfordshire&quot;, noting that &quot;when we were in Berkshire, County Hall in Reading was so far away. It's much better for us to get into Oxford.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;AH92745&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Pirates cross the border  |publisher=[[Abingdon Herald]] |date=2006-04-06 |url=http://archive.thisisoxfordshire.co.uk/2006/4/6/92745.html|accessdate=2007-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Dorset and Hampshire border===
On 10 November 2005, Tony Bennett removed a [[Dorset]] sign from Chewton Bunny at [[Highcliffe]] and moved it to its historic location at the original County Gates border between [[Bournemouth]] and [[Poole]], claiming that while Bournemouth and neighbouring [[Christchurch, Dorset|Christchurch]] had been administered by Dorset County Council for the past 30 years, they remained historically [[Hampshire]] towns.&lt;ref name=&quot;DE112193&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=A sign of disapproval  |publisher=[[Dorest Echo]] |date=2006-04-06 |url=http://archive.thisisdorset.net/2005/11/12/112193.html|accessdate=2007-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Durham===
In May 2006, CountyWatch announced that it has been contacted by Durham residents who were unhappy that [[Durham County Council]] had recently relocated signs from the historic boundary between [[Durham]] and Yorkshire and relocated them to the Darlington boundary. It would be travelling around Durham looking to see whether signs were on what it consider to be the correct, true border and would remove County Durham signs from the border with the [[unitary authority]] of [[Darlington]] to the historic and currently ceremonial border with [[North Yorkshire]] on the [[River Tees]] on 25 May 2006 and re-erect them on suitable posts along the River Tees.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC News5018856&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Boundary group targets road signs   |publisher=[[BBC News]] |date=2006-05-26 |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/5018856.stm|accessdate=2007-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The [[BBC]] and [[Tyne Tees Television]] filmed CountyWatch removing the boundary signs at [[Royal Oak, County Durham|Royal Oak]]. Twelve signs with, &quot;County Durham: Land of the [[Prince Bishops]]&quot; were removed. Three of them were re-erected along the historic border between Yorkshire and [[Durham]] &amp;ndash; the River Tees, also the current ceremonial border. The Council were informed by CountyWatch of the location of the other signs they removed. Durham County Council issued a statement saying that CountyWatch's actions were &quot;nothing more than sheer vandalism, no less mindless or anti-social than smashing bus stops or phone boxes&quot;.

On 31 May 2006, an article in ''[[The Northern Echo]]'' newspaper praised the group's actions, calling the council's statement &quot;a trifle wide of the mark&quot; and ended the article - &quot;Carry on CountyWatch&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;NE777712&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Mead| first=Harry| title=Defending the land of our fathers  |publisher=[[The Northern Echo]] |date=2006-05-31 |url=http://www.thenorthernecho.co.uk/features/columnists/harrymead/display.var.777712.0.defending_the_land_of_our_fathers.php|accessdate=2007-08-05 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070326104136/http://www.thenorthernecho.co.uk/features/columnists/harrymead/display.var.777712.0.defending_the_land_of_our_fathers.php &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Lancashire===
In November 2005 CountyWatch removed over thirty 'Welcome to Lancashire' signs from Blackburn, Blackpool, Skelmersdale and Southport, placing all of them on the historic Lancashire/Yorkshire border at [[Blacko]] near [[Nelson, Lancashire|Nelson]], where they telephoned the Council's Solicitor. [[Lancashire County Council]] reacted by stating that &quot;the cost of replacing the signs would be met from taxpayers' money.&quot; and also that it would be speaking to the police about the group. The Welcome to Lancashire signs were erected on the boundaries with Blackburn with Darwen and Blackpool unitary authorities by the county council in 2004 to show where its services begin. CountyWatch responded stating that, &quot;The sign says 'Welcome to Lancashire', it doesn't say 'Welcome to the administrative unit of Lancashire County Council - that would be all right.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC News4436170&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Boundary protest 'to be reported'  |publisher=[[BBC News]] |date=2002-11-14 |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/lancashire/4436170.stm|accessdate=2007-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; The signs which were dumped by the side of the A682 in Blacko, near to the historic border with Yorkshire, were recovered by [[Lancashire County Council]] who stated that they would re-erect them.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC News4439228&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=County signs dumped after protest  |publisher=[[BBC News]] |date=2002-11-15 |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/lancashire/4439228.stm|accessdate=2007-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

CountyWatch also claimed to have removed the larger brown-coloured motorway signs on the M6, M66 and M61 which read &quot;Welcome to Lancashire the Red Rose County&quot;. They also claimed that they  had a legal right to remove signs under the section 131 of the Highways Act 1980 because &quot;they misinform the public&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;LET875975&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Lancs signs were dumped at border  |publisher=[[Lancashire Evening Telegraph]] |date=2002-11-15 |url=http://archive.thisislancashire.co.uk/2005/11/15/875975.html|accessdate=2007-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Lincolnshire===
On 27 July 2005, the BBC TV Look North regional news programme featured the group and filmed it in the act of removing a &quot;Welcome to the County of Lincolnshire&quot; sign near [[Brigg]]. [[Lincolnshire County Council]] Area Highways Manager Eric Jorgensen described the group as &quot;self-appointed and unelected&quot; and stated that taxpayers would be forced to pay for the signs to be replaced.

On 22 September 2005, CountyWatch removed ten road signs stating: &quot;Welcome to the County of Lincolnshire&quot; between [[Brigg]] and [[Immingham]], which the group claimed there was no point in putting up a welcome sign 15 miles into the historic county. CountyWatch claimed, &quot;Lincolnshire starts where Yorkshire finishes – not 20 miles into Lincolnshire. We want them erected on the proper boundary&quot;. Lincolnshire County Council however attacked the group for taking council property and said &quot;it will cost the taxpayer to put the signs back up&quot;. The signs were deposited at a council depot after being removed.&lt;ref name=&quot;YP1199795&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Wood |first=Alexandra |title=Protest group seizes the day in boundary row|publisher=[[Yorkshire Post]] |date=2005-09-23 |url=http://www.yorkshirepost.co.uk/ViewArticle.aspx?SectionID=55&amp;articleid=1199795|accessdate=2007-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Somerset===
In August 2004, CountyWatch's first action was the removal of five signs saying 'Welcome to the County of Somerset', on the northern border of the non-metropolitan county of [[Somerset]] with either [[Bath and North East Somerset]] or [[North Somerset]]. The signs were taken down by CountyWatch members and relocated on the historic borders of [[Somerset]] with neighbouring historic counties [[Gloucestershire]] and [[Wiltshire]].&lt;ref name=&quot;DT01&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Booker |first=Christopher |title=A borderline case|publisher=[[The Daily Telegraph]] |date=2004-08-22 |url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2004/08/22/nbook22.xml |accessdate=2007-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Nine new local authorities==
On 25 July 2007, the Local Government Minister, John Healey from the Department for Communities and Local Government announced that nine all-purpose local authorities would be created in 2009 in England.&lt;ref name=&quot;CLG2470&quot;&gt;{{cite press release |title=Healey announces nine successful unitary proposals |publisher=Dep't for Communities and Local Government |date=2007-07-25|url=http://www.communities.gov.uk/news/corporate/healey-announces-nine |accessdate=2007-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

CountyWatch see this as the next phase of attempts to replace the administration of England and Wales by county and district councils with a series of so-called 'unitary' authorities, which combine the administrative functions of both district councils and county councils.&lt;ref name=&quot;CC105274&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Nine new councils to be created by 2009|publisher=Community Care |date=2007-07-26|url=http://www.communitycare.co.uk/Articles/2007/07/26/105274/nine-new-councils-to-be-created-by-2009.html |accessdate=2007-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; Region-wide functions will be carried out by [[Regional Development Agencies]] and new government quangos, following the announcement earlier in the month of the abolition of unelected [[Regional Assemblies in England|Regional Assemblies]] from 2010.

== See also ==
*[[Association of British Counties]]
*[[Friends of Real Lancashire]]
*[[Yorkshire Ridings Society]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

[[Category:Activism]]
[[Category:2004 establishments in the United Kingdom]]</text>
      <sha1>czqqlc9tem8chuzy3dypc4foiltmk9n</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
