<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Culture jamming</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>29547142</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522285954</id>
      <parentid>522275317</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T04:56:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SQGibbon</username>
        <id>861016</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/208.105.86.92|208.105.86.92]] ([[User talk:208.105.86.92|talk]]): Non-notable. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="19206">{{Anti-consumerism}}
'''Culture jamming''' (name coined in 1984&lt;ref name=&quot;Lloyd03&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dery90Nyt&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dery2010Revisited&quot;/&gt;) is a tactic used by many [[anti-consumerism|anti-consumerist]] [[social movement]]s&lt;ref name=&quot;Binay&quot;&gt;Binay, Ayse (2005) `Investigating the Anti-consumerism Movement in North America: The Case of Adbusters', unpublished dissertation, University of Texas.&lt;/ref&gt; to disrupt or subvert [[media culture]] and its [[mainstream]] cultural institutions, including corporate advertising. It purports to &quot;expose the methods of domination&quot; of [[mass society]] to foster [[Progressivism|progressive]] change.&lt;ref&gt;Nomai, Afsheen Joseph (2008) ''Culture Jamming: Ideological Struggle and the Possibilities for Social Change'' [http://books.google.com/books?id=Y4auF2ysN0wC&amp;pg=PA5&amp;lpg=PA5 p.5]&lt;/ref&gt;

Culture jamming is often seen{{By whom|date=October 2012}} as a form of [[subvertising]]. Many culture jams are intended to expose apparently questionable political assumptions behind commercial culture. Common tactics include re-figuring logos, fashion statements, and product images as a means to challenge the idea of &quot;what's cool&quot; along with assumptions about the personal freedoms of consumption.&lt;ref name=&quot;Boden&quot;&gt;Boden, Sharon and Williams, Simon J. (2002) &quot;Consumption and Emotion: The Romantic Ethic Revisited&quot;, Sociology 36(3):493–512&lt;/ref&gt;

Culture jamming sometimes entails transforming [[mass media]] to produce ironic or [[satirical]] commentary about mass media, using the original medium's communication method. Culture jamming is usually employed in opposition to a perceived appropriation of public space, or as a reaction against social [[conformity]]. Prominent examples of culture jamming include the adulteration of billboard advertising by the [[Billboard Liberation Front|BLF]] and [[Ron English (artist)|Ron English]] and the street parties and protests organised by [[Reclaim the Streets]]. While most culture jamming focuses on subverting or critiquing political or advertising messages, some practitioners focus on a more positive, musically inspired form of jamming that brings together artists, scholars and activists to create new forms of cultural production that transcend rather than merely criticize or negate the status quo.&lt;ref name=&quot;LeVine&quot;&gt;LeVine, Mark (2005)'' Why They Don't Hate Us: Lifting the Veil on the Axis of Evil''. Oxford, UK: Oneworld Publications.&lt;/ref&gt;

Terms sometimes used synonymously with the term ''culture jamming'' include '''Guerrilla [[semiotics]]''' and '''night discourse'''&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=w0TSfW4MU4QC&amp;pg=PA274 ''Images of the street: planning, identity, and control in public space''] By Nicholas R. Fyfe, p.274
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gavin Grindon [http://books.google.com/books?id=U4fpAAAAMAAJ ''Aesthetics and Radical Politics'']
&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origins of the term, etymology and history==
===1984 coinage===
The term was coined in 1984 by the [[sound collage]] band [[Negativland]], with the release of their album ''[[JamCon '84]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lloyd03&quot;&gt;Lloyd, Jan (2003) [http://www.hums.canterbury.ac.nz/cult/research/lloyd.htm ''Culture Jamming: Semiotic Banditry in the Streets''], in ''Cultural Studies Department'': University of Canterbury,
Christchurc&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dery90Nyt&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dery2010Revisited&quot;&gt;Dery, Mark (2010) New Introduction and revisited edition of [http://markdery.com/?page_id=154 ''Culture Jamming: Hacking, Slashing, and Sniping in the Empire of the Signs]'', October 8th, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; The phrase &quot;culture jamming&quot; comes from the idea of [[radio jamming]]:&lt;ref name=&quot;Dery90Nyt&quot;/&gt; that public frequencies can be pirated and subverted for independent communication, or to disrupt dominant frequencies.&lt;ref&gt;[http://disruptdominantfrequencies.net/ Disrupt Dominant Frequencies]&lt;/ref&gt; In one of the tracks of the album, they declared:&lt;ref name=&quot;Dery90Nyt&quot;/&gt;

{{quotation|As awareness of how the media environment we occupy affects and directs our inner life grows, some resist. The skillfully reworked billboard . . . directs the public viewer to a consideration of the original corporate strategy. The studio for the cultural jammer is the world at large.}}

===Origins and preceding influences===
According to [[Vince Carducci]], although the term was coined by Negativland, culture jamming can be traced as far back as the 1950s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carducci&quot;&gt;[[Vince Carducci|Carducci, Vince]] (2006) &quot;Culture Jamming: A Sociological Perspective&quot;, Journal of Consumer Culture 6(1): 116–38&lt;/ref&gt; One particularly influential group that was active in Europe was the [[Situationist International]] and was led by [[Guy Debord]]. Their main argument was based on the idea that in the past humans dealt with life and the consumer market directly. They argued that this spontaneous way of life was slowly deteriorating as a direct result of the new &quot;modern&quot; way of life. Situationists saw everything from television to radio as a threat.&lt;ref name =&quot;Lasn&quot;&gt;Lasn, Kalle (1999) Culture Jam: How to Reverse America's Suicidal Consumer Binge – And Why We Must. New York: HarperCollins&lt;/ref&gt;

The cultural critic [[Mark Dery]] traces the origins of culture jamming to medieval carnival, which [[Mikhail Bakhtin]] interpreted, in ''Rabelais and his World,'' as an officially sanctioned subversion of the social hierarchy.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}} Modern precursors might include: the media-savvy agit-prop of the anti-Nazi photomonteur [[John Heartfield]], the sociopolitical street theater and staged media events of '60s radicals such as [[Abbie Hoffman]], the [[Germany|German]] concept of [[Spaßguerilla]], and in the [[Situationist International]] (SI) of the 1950s and '60s.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}} The SI first compared its own activities to [[radio jamming]] in 1968, when it proposed the use of [[guerrilla communication]] within [[mass media]] to sow confusion within the dominant culture.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}

[[Mark Dery]]'s [[New York Times]] article on culture jamming, ''The Merry Pranksters And the Art of the Hoax''&lt;ref name=&quot;Dery90Nyt&quot;&gt;[[Mark Dery|Dery, Mark]] (1990)[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DF123EF930A15751C1A966958260&amp;pagewanted=all ''The Merry Pranksters And the Art of the Hoax''], NYtimes article, December 23, 1990.&lt;/ref&gt; was the first mention, in the mainstream media, of the phenomenon; Dery later expanded on this article in his 1993 Open Magazine pamphlet, ''Culture Jamming: Hacking, Slashing, and Sniping in the Empire of the Signs'',&lt;ref name=&quot;Dery93OpenMag&quot;&gt;Dery, Mark (1993) [http://project.cyberpunk.ru/idb/culture_jamming.html ''Culture Jamming: Hacking, Slashing, and Sniping in the Empire of the Signs]'', in ''Open Magazine Pamphlet Series'', 1993&lt;/ref&gt; a seminal essay that remains the most exhaustive historical, sociopolitical, and philosophical theorization of culture jamming to date. [[Adbusters]], a Canadian publication espousing an environmentalist critique of consumerism, began promoting aspects of culture jamming after Dery introduced editor [[Kalle Lasn]] to the term through a series of articles he wrote for the magazine. In her critique of consumerism, &quot;[[No Logo]]&quot;, the Canadian cultural commentator and political activist [[Naomi Klein]] examines culture jamming in a chapter that cites Dery and focuses on the work of [[Jorge Rodriguez-Gerada]].

==Tactics==
[[File:Vorsprung durch Graffit cropped.jpg|thumb|240px|Graffitied text on billboard in [[Cambridge]], [[UK]]]]
Culture jamming is a form of disruption that plays on the [[emotions]] of viewers and bystanders. Jammers want to disrupt the unconscious thought process that takes place when most consumers view a popular advertising and bring about a [[détournement]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Lasn&quot;/&gt; Activists that utilize this tactic are counting on their [[meme]] to pull on the emotional strings of people and evoke some type of reaction. The reactions that most cultural jammers are hoping to evoke are behavioral change and political action. There are four emotions that activists often want viewers to feel. These emotions – shock, shame, fear, and anger, are believed to be the catalysts for social change.&lt;ref name=&quot;Summers&quot;&gt;Summers-Effler, Erika (2002) &quot;The Micro Potential for Social Change: Emotion, Consciousness, and Social Movement Formation&quot;, Sociological Theory 20(1): 41–60&lt;/ref&gt;

The basic unit in which a message is transmitted in culture jamming is the [[meme]]. Memes are condensed images that stimulate visual, verbal, musical, or behavioral associations that people can easily imitate and transmit to others. The term meme was first popularized by geneticist Richard Dawkins but later used by cultural critics such as Douglas Rushkoff  that claimed memes were a type of media virus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rushkoff&quot;&gt;Rushkoff, Douglas (1996) Media Virus! New York: Ballantine&lt;/ref&gt; Memes are seen as genes that can jump from outlet to outlet and replicate themselves or mutate upon transmission just like a virus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dawkins&quot;&gt;Dawkins, Richard (1989) The Selfish Gene. Oxford: Oxford University Press&lt;/ref&gt; Culture jammers will often use common memes to such as the McDonald's golden arches or Nike swoosh to engage people and force them to think about their eating habits or fashion sense.&lt;ref name=&quot;website&quot;&gt;[http://depts.washington.edu/ccce/polcommcampaigns/CultureJamming.htm Center for Communication and Civic Engagement], [[Seattle, Washington]] Retrieved November 20, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; In one example, jammer Jonah Perreti used the Nike symbol to stir debate on sweatshop child labor and consumer freedom. Perreti made public exchanges between himself and Nike over a disagreement. Perreti had requested custom Nikes with the word &quot;sweatshop&quot; placed in the Nike symbol. Nike naturally disagreed. Once this story was made public over Perreti's website it spread world wide and sparked conversation and dialogue about Nike's use of sweatshops.&lt;ref name=&quot;website&quot;/&gt; Jammers can also organize and participate in mass campaigns. Examples of cultural jamming like Perreti's are more along the lines of tactics that radical consumer social movements would use. These movements push people to question the taken-for-granted assumption that consuming is natural and good and aim to disrupt the naturalization of consumer culture; they also seek to create systems of production and consumption that are more humane and less dominated by global corporate hypercapitalism.&lt;ref name = &quot;Princen&quot;&gt;Princen, Thomas, Maniates, Michael and Conca, Ken (2002) Confronting Consumption. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.&lt;/ref&gt;
Past mass events and ideas have included &quot;Buy Nothing Day&quot;, &quot;Digital Detox Week&quot;, virtual sit-ins and protests over the Internet, producing ‘subvertisements’ and placing them in public spaces, and creating and enacting ‘placejamming’ projects
where public spaces are reclaimed and nature is re-introduced into urban
places.&lt;ref name= &quot;harold&quot;&gt;Harold, Christine (2004) `Pranking Rhetoric: &quot;Culture jamming&quot; as Media Activism', Critical Studies in Media Communication 21(3): 189–211&lt;/ref&gt;

The most effective form of jamming is to use an already widely recognizable meme to transmit the message. Once viewers are forced to take a second look at the mimicked popular meme they are forced out of their comfort zone. Viewers are presented with another way to view the meme and forced to think about the implications presented by the jammer.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lasn&quot;/&gt; More often than not, when this is used as a tactic the jammer is going for shock value. For example, to make consumers aware of the negative body image that big name apparel brands are causing, a subvertisement of Calvin Klein's 'Obsession' was created and played world wide. It depicted a young woman with an eating disorder throwing up into a toilet.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordwell&quot;&gt;Bordwell, Marilyn (2002) `Jamming Culture: Adbusters' Hip Media Campaign against Consumerism', in Thomas Princen, Michael Maniates and Ken Conca (eds) Confronting Consumption, pp. 237–53. Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press&lt;/ref&gt;

Another way that social consumer movements hope to utilize culture jamming effectively is by employing a metameme. A metameme is a two-level message that punctures a specific commercial image, but does so in a way that challenges some larger aspect of the political culture of corporate domination.&lt;ref name=&quot;website&quot;/&gt; An example would be the &quot;true cost&quot; campaign set in motion by Adbusters. &quot;True Cost&quot; forced consumers to compare the human labor cost and conditions and environmental drawbacks of products to the sales costs. Another example would be the &quot;Truth&quot; campaigns that frequented television in the past years that exposed the deception tobacco companies used to sell their products.

==Criticism==

Culture jamming is sometimes confused with [[Appropriation (art)|artistic appropriation]] or with acts of [[vandalism]] which have destruction or defacement as their primary goal.  Although the end result is not always easily distinguishable from these activities, the intent of those participating in culture jamming differs from that of people whose intent is either artistic or merely destructive.  The lines are not always clear-cut; some activities, notably [[street art]], will fall into two or even all three categories.

Recently there have been arguments against the validity and effectiveness of culture jamming. Some argue that culture jamming is easily co-opted and commodified by the market, which tends to &quot;defuse&quot; its potential for consumer resistance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rumbo&quot;&gt;Rumbo, Jospeh D. (2002) &quot;Consumer Resistance in a World of Advertising Clutter: The Case of Adbusters&quot;, Psychology &amp; Marketing 19(2): 127–48.&lt;/ref&gt; Others posit that the culture jamming strategy of rhetorical sabotage, used by Adbusters, is easily incorporated and appropriated by clever advertising agencies, and thus is not a very powerful means of social change.&lt;ref name=&quot;harold&quot;/&gt; Yet other critics argue that without moving beyond mere critique to offering an alternative economic, social, cultural and/or political vision, jams quickly lose their power and resonance.&lt;ref name=&quot;LeVine&quot;&gt;LeVine, Mark (2005) ''Why They Don't Hate Us: Lifting the Veil on the Axis of Evil''. Oxford, UK: Oneworld Publications.&lt;/ref&gt;

==List of culture jamming organizations or people==
{{colbegin|3}}
*[[3kStatic]]
*[[Abbie Hoffman]]
*[[Above (artist)|Above]]
*[[Alan Abel]]
*[[Adbusters]]
*[[Anomie Belle]]
*[[Anonymous (group)]]
*[[André the Giant Has a Posse]]
*[[Anti-Pearlman Permanent Poster League]]
*[[Temporary Autonomous Zone|The Association for Ontological Anarchy]]
*[[Banksy]]
*[[Barbie Liberation Organization]]
*[[Benjamin Lay]]
*[[Billboard Liberation Front]]
*[[Billionaires for Bush]]
*[[Billionaires for Wealthcare]]
*[[Bleeps.gr]]
*[[Borat]]
*[[Brass Eye]]
*[[The Bubble Project]]
*[[BUGAUP]]
*[[Burning Man]]
*[[Cacophony Society]]
*[[Chumbawamba]]
*[[Church of the SubGenius]]
*[[Crass]]
*[[Critical Mass]]
*[[Cutup]]
*[[Discordianism|The Discordian Society]]
*[[Meadow House|Dan Wilson]]
*[[Guy Debord]]
*[[Emergency Broadcast Network]]
*[[Evan Coyne Maloney]]
*[[The Evolution Control Committee]]
*[[Francis E. Dec]]
*[[Guerilla Girls]]
*[[Graffiti Research Lab]]
*[[Improv Everywhere]]
*[[Improv Toronto|Improv in Toronto]]
*[[Infringement Festival]]
*[[Jeff Wassmann]]
*[[Jello Biafra]]
*[[Joey Skaggs]]
*[[John Lydon]]
*[[John Fekner]]
*[[Jorge Rodriguez-Gerada]]
*[[The KLF]] and the [[K Foundation]]
*[[Kalle Lasn]]
*[[Mark LeVine]]
*[[Lumber Cartel]]
*[[Luther Blissett (nom de plume)|Luther Blissett Project]]
*[[Mark Dice]]
*[[M.I.A. (artist)|M.I.A.]]
*[[Michael Moore]]
*[[Molleindustria]]
*[[Monochrom]]
*[[Negativland]]
*[[Newmindspace]]
*[[Nikolas Schiller]]
*[[Norm Magnusson]]
*[[Nsumi]]
*[[Operation Mindfuck]]
*[[Over the Edge (radio)]]
*[[Poster Boy (street artist)|Poster Boy]]
*[[Public Image Ltd.]]
*[[Publixtheatre Caravan]]
*[[Pussy Riot]]
*[[®™ark]]
*[[Ron English (artist)|Ron English]]
*[[Reject False Icons]]
*[[Regurgitator]]
*[[Rémi Gaillard]]
*[[Reverend Billy and the Church of Stop Shopping]]
*[[Sal Randolph]]
*[[Schwa (art)]]
*[[Shepard Fairey]]
*[[Snog]]
*[[Space Hijackers]]
*[[Stay Free!]]
*[[Stephen Colbert]]
*[[StreetWars]]
*[[The Yes Men]]
*[[Yippies]]
*[[Yomango]]
*[[Whirl-Mart]]
*[[Zippies]]
*[[0100101110101101.ORG]]
{{colend}}

==See also==
*[[Crimethinc]]
*[[Merry Pranksters]]
*[[Happening]]
*[[The Firesign Theatre]]
*[[Anti-consumerism]]
*[[Artivist]]
*[[Broadcast signal intrusion]]
*[[Détournement]]
*[[Flash mob]]
*[[Little Red Songbook]]
*[[Operation Mindfuck]]
*[[Scratch video]]
*[[Situationist International]]
*[[Steal This Book]]
*[[Subvertising]]
*[[Minority influence]]
*[[Critical theory]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
* Dery, Mark (1993). Culture Jamming: Hacking, Slashing, and Sniping in the Empire of Signs. Open Magazine Pamphlet Series: NJ.{{cite web|url=http://www.markdery.com/archives/books/culture_jamming/ |title=Shovelware |publisher=Markdery.com |date= |accessdate=2009-07-23}}
* King, Donovan (2004). University of Calgary. [http://www.optative.net/ebook.html ''Optative Theatre: A Critical Theory for Challenging Oppression and Spectacle'']
* Klein, Naomi (2000). ''No Logo'' London: Flamingo.
*[http://www.kyotojournal.org/kjselections/lasn.htm Kyoto Journal: Culture Jammer's Guide to Enlightenment]
*Lasn, Kalle (1999) Culture Jam. New York: Eagle Brook.
*LeVine, Mark (2005)'' Why They Don't Hate Us: Lifting the Veil on the Axis of Evil''. Oxford, UK: Oneworld Publications.
*Tietchen, T. ''Language out of Language: Excavating the Roots of Culture Jamming and Postmodern Activism'' from William S. Burroughs' ''Nova'' Trilogy ''Discourse: Berkeley Journal for Theoretical Studies in Media and Culture.'' 23, Part 3 (2001): 107–130.

==External links==
* [http://depts.washington.edu/ccce/polcommcampaigns/CultureJamming.htm Culture Jamming page from the Center for Communication and Civic Engagement]
* [http://helterskelter.in/2010/08/culture-jamming/ Feature on Culture Jamming in Helter Skelter Magazine]
* [http://www.woostercollective.com/culture_jamming/ Wooster Collective Collection Tagged 'Culture Jamming']
* [http://creative.arte.tv/fr/space/Culture_Jamming/messages/ Documentary about Culture Jamming]
* [http://www.memefest.org/ Memefest: Festival of Socially Responsive Communication and Art]
*[http://itwashim.com/latest/ it was him! - subvertising by amateurs, for amateurs]

{{Culture jamming}}
{{Guerrilla theatre}}
{{Media culture}}
{{Media manipulation}}
{{Street Art}}
{{Conformity}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Culture Jamming}}
[[Category:Activism by method]]
[[Category:Culture jamming|*]]
[[Category:Underground culture]]
[[Category:Anti-corporate activism]]
[[Category:Practical jokes]]

[[bg:Културно заглушаване]]
[[de:Culture Jamming]]
[[es:Culture jamming]]
[[fr:Culture jamming]]
[[it:Culture jamming]]
[[he:שיבוש תרבות]]
[[ms:Kesulitan budaya]]
[[ja:カルチャー・ジャミング]]
[[pl:Culture jamming]]
[[pt:Culture jamming]]
[[ru:Культура глушения]]
[[simple:Culture jamming]]
[[sr:Kulturno ometanje]]
[[sv:Culture jamming]]
[[uk:Культурне глушіння]]</text>
      <sha1>rvjfms6h15jrl1zyy0e99ozhyktf43j</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
