<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3590444</id>
    <revision>
      <id>517568264</id>
      <parentid>491061937</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-13T13:07:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Magioladitis</username>
        <id>1862829</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>clean up using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (8459)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24225">[[File:DSOC-button-1978.jpg|thumb|right|280px|This 1978 DSOC [[Campaign button (political)|pinback button]] features the logo of the [[Socialist International]]—a fist representing socialism with a rose representing democracy—and a prominent [[union label|union&amp;nbsp;label (&quot;bug&quot;)]].]]

The '''Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (DSOC)''' was founded in 1973 by [[Michael Harrington]], who had led a minority caucus in the [[Socialist Party of America]]. Harrington's caucus supported [[George McGovern]]'s call for a cease-fire and immediate withdrawal of U.S. forces from Vietnam. In contrast to the traditional emphasis on strengthening the working class by organizing labor unions, Harrington reduced the emphasis on labor of previous socialist organizations. Instead, while continuing to work with unionists, Harrington placed more emphasis on middle-class political activists, especially those drawn to activism through the McGovern campaign. Developing a &quot;realignment&quot; strategy common to Socialists since the 1960s, DSOC (pronounced &quot;DEE-sock&quot;) tried to help to build a [[democratic socialism|democratic-socialist]] (&quot;democratic left&quot;) movement from the political movements participating in the [[Democratic Party (U.S.)|Democratic Party]].

In 1982 the DSOC merged with the [[New American Movement]] to form the [[Democratic Socialists of America]].

==Organizational history==

===Origins===
{{Main|Socialist Party of America}}

After nearly a decade of internal acrimony, the [[Socialist Party of America|Socialist Party of America-Social Democratic Federation]] was clearly headed for a split as the decade of the 1970s opened. The organization, while sharing a common antipathy to the worldwide [[communism|communist]] movement, was divided over two primary issues
#Should democratic socialists call for ''either'' an immediate withdrawal of U.S. forces from Vietnam ''or'' a negotiated peace settlement along with an immediate end to the bombing of North Vietnam?
#Should the democratic left continue its traditional focus of organizing the [[working class]] in [[labor unions]] or should it shift its focus to (predominantly middle class) peace activists?

====1972 Convention of the Socialist Party====
{{See also|Social Democrats, USA}}
In its 1972 Convention, the [[Socialist Party of America|Socialist Party]] had two Co-Chairmen, [[Bayard Rustin]] and [[Charles&amp;nbsp;S. Zimmerman]] (of the [[International Ladies Garment&amp;nbsp;Workers' Union]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Sorin149&quot;&gt;Gerald Sorin, ''The Prophetic Minority: American Jewish Immigrant Radicals, 1880-1920.'' Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1985; pg. 155.&lt;/ref&gt; ILGWU) and a First National Vice Chairman, James&amp;nbsp;S. Glaser, who were re-elected by [[acclamation]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NYTimes&quot;/&gt; In his opening speech to the Convention, Co-Chairman Bayard Rustin called for SDUSA to organize against the  &quot;reactionary policies of the Nixon Administration&quot;; Rustin also criticized the &quot;irresponsibility and élitism of the 'New Politics' liberals&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYTimes&quot;/&gt;

The Party changed its name to &quot;Social Democrats,&amp;nbsp;USA&quot; by a vote of 73 to&amp;nbsp;34.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYTimes&quot;&gt;
* {{cite article|title=Socialist Party now the Social&amp;nbsp;Democrats,&amp;nbsp;U.S.A.|newspaper=New&amp;nbsp;York Times|year=1972|month=31 December|page=36|author=Anonymous|url=http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F00B16FC3E5A137A93C3AA1789D95F468785F9|accessdate=February 8, 2010|url2=http://www.marxisthistory.org/personal/721231-sdusa-news.pdf|ref=harv}}

The ''[[New York Times]]'' reported on the 1972 Convention on other days, e.g.,
* {{cite article|title=Young Socialists support Meany; Group urges the Democrats to join labor movement|year=1972|month=31 December|page=36|last=Johnston|first=Laurie|ref=harv|url=http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F20B16FC3E5A137A93C3AA1789D95F468785F9&amp;scp=11&amp;sq=Young+socialists&amp;st=p|url2=|newspaper=New&amp;nbsp;York Times}}
* {{cite article|title=Young Socialists defeat motion favoring recognition of Cuba|newspaper=New&amp;nbsp;York Times|year=1972|month=28 December|page=15|last=Johnston|first=Laurie|ref=harv|url=http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F10D12FF3E59107A93CAAB1789D95F468785F9&amp;scp=4&amp;sq=Young+socialists&amp;st=p|url2=http://www.marxisthistory.org/personal/721228-sdusa-news.pdf}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Renaming the Party as SDUSA was meant to be &quot;realistic&quot;. ''[[The New York Times]]'' observed that the Socialist Party had last sponsored a [[Darlington Hoopes|candidate for President]] in [[Presidential Election Of 1956|1956]], who received only 2,121 votes, which were cast in only 6 states. Because the Party no longer sponsored candidates in Presidential Elections, the name &quot;Party&quot; had been &quot;misleading&quot;; &quot;Party&quot; had hindered the recruiting of activists who participated in the Democratic Party, according the majority report. The name &quot;Socialist&quot; was replaced by &quot;[[social democracy|Social Democrats]]&quot; because many American associated the word &quot;[[democratic socialism|socialism]]&quot; with [[Soviet communism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NYTimes&quot;/&gt; Also, the Party wished to distinguish itself from two  small Marxist parties, the [[Socialist Workers Party (United States)|Socialist Workers Party]] and the [[Socialist Labor Party of America|Socialist Labor Party]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT27&quot;&gt;{{cite article|title=Young Socialists open parley; to weigh 'New&amp;nbsp;Politics' split|newspaper=New York Times|year=1972|month=27 December|ref=harv|page=25|author=Anonymous|url=http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F70B10FF3B5C177B93C5AB1789D95F468785F9&amp;scp=7&amp;sq=Young+socialists&amp;st=p|url2=http://www.marxisthistory.org/personal/721227-sdusa-news.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the convention, the majority (&quot;unity Caucus&quot;) won every vote, by a ratio of two to one. The Convention elected a national committee of 33 members, with 22 seats for the majority caucus, 8 seats for the &quot;coalition caucus&quot; of [[Michael Harrington]], 2 for &quot;a Debs caucus&quot;, and one for the &quot;independent&quot; [[Samuel&amp;nbsp;H. Friedman]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT73&quot;&gt;{{cite article|title='Firmness' urged on &lt;!-- CAPITALIZED! --&gt;Communists: Social&amp;nbsp;Democrats reach end of U.S.&amp;nbsp;Convention here|newspaper=New&amp;nbsp;York Times|year=1973|month=1 January|page=11|author=Anonymous|url=http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F50C15F73F551A7493C3A9178AD85F478785F9|url2=http://www.marxisthistory.org/personal/730101-sdusa-news.pdf|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; Friedman and the minority caucuses had opposed the name change.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYTimes&quot;/&gt;

The convention voted on and adopted proposals for its program by a two-one vote. On foreign policy, the program called for &quot;firmness toward Communist aggression&quot;. However, on the Vietnam War, the program opposed &quot;any efforts to bomb Hanoi into submission&quot;; instead, it endorsed negotiating a peace agreement, which should protect Communist political cadres in South Vietnam from further military or police reprisals. Harrington's proposal for a [[ceasefire]] and [[immediate withdrawal]] of U.S. forces was defeated.&lt;!--  A Vice Chairman of the Young People's Socialist League (YPSL), [[Carl Gershman]] introduced the international program that was approved. --&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT73&quot;/&gt; Harrington complained that, after its convention, the Socialist Party had endorsed [[George McGovern]] only with a  statement loaded with &quot;constructive criticism&quot; and that it had not mobilized enough support for McGovern. The majority caucus's Arch Puddington replied that the California branch was especially active in supporting McGovern, while the New York branch were focusing on a congressional race.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT27 &quot;/&gt;

===Harrington founds DSOC===
{{See also|Socialist Party USA}}
Even before the convention, Michael Harrington had resigned as an Honorary Chairperson of the Socialist Party.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYTimes&quot;/&gt; Some months after the convention, he resigned his membership in SDUSA. Harrington and his supporters from the Coalition Caucus soon formed the Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (DSOC). (Many members of the Debs caucus resigned from SDUSA and formed the [[Socialist Party USA]].){{Citation needed|date=January 2012}} Despite opposing the majority of the Socialist Party, [[Michael Harrington]], acknowledged the validity of its members' concerns:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;The anti-war activists of the sixties were overwhelmingly white and middle class. Many of them were unconcerned about the domestic political consequences of their actions and were even contemptuous of that majority of Americans who supported the war. There was a profoundly elitist tendency in the movement that [the majority of the Socialist Party leadership] denounced as dilettantish and collegiate. Moreover, there was a vocal, and regularly televised, fringe of confrontationists, exhibitionists, and [[Vietcong]] flag wavers who could plausibly be dismissed as freakish, or sinister, or both.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Harrington, Fragments&quot;&gt;Harrington, ''Fragments of the Century,'' pp. 212-213.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Harrington's caucus in the Socialist Party endorsed the &quot;New Politics&quot; movement and sought to expand that tendency into a viable left-wing pressure-group within the Democratic Party, advancing an explicitly socialist agenda and attempting to win influence over elected officials for that program. Harrington led many members of this caucus and from his networks to establish the Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (DSOC) in 1973.

The writer Michael Harrington, a former editor of the Socialist Party's weekly newspaper, ''New America,''&lt;ref&gt;Michael Harrington, ''Fragments of the Century.'' New York: Saturday Review Press/E.P. Dutton &amp; Co., 1973; pg. 199.&lt;/ref&gt; was the most important figure in the establishment of DSOC. Harrington had resigned as National Co-Chairman of the Socialist Party, many of whose leaders criticized McGovern, when Harrington focused his efforts on electing McGovern in October 1972.&lt;ref&gt;Harrington, ''Fragments of the Century,'' pg. 195.&lt;/ref&gt;

In his first memoir, published in 1973, Harrington defended his choice of peace activists over trade unionists:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;But in their derogatory comparison of this movement with the trade unionists, my comrades failed to notice two of its historic aspects. First, the anti-war young were right: Vietnam was not only an immoral conflict, it was counterproductive from all points of view, including that of progressive anti-communism. Secondly, the new strata of the issue-oriented and college-educated who provided the mass bass for this phenomenon were, and are, extremely important to the creation of a new majority for change in this country.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Harrington, Fragments&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
And so DSOC was founded. 

At its start, DSOC had 840 members, of which 2 percent served on its national board; approximately 200 had previously had membership in [[Social&amp;nbsp;Democrats,&amp;nbsp;USA]] or its predecessors&lt;!--  (the [[Socialist Party of America#Max_Shachtman.2C_Civil_Rights.2C_and_the_War_on_Poverty|Socialist&amp;nbsp;Party Social&amp;nbsp;Democratic Federation]], &quot;formerly the Socialist Party,&amp;nbsp;USA&quot;), --&gt; in 1973 when SDUSA stated its membership at 1,800, according to a 1973 profile of Harrington.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvtxt|O'Rourke|1993|pp=195–196}}: &lt;p&gt;{{cite book|last=O'Rourke|first=William|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=5iUJfPxlTCcC&amp;pg=PA195|chapter=L: Michael Harrington|title=Signs of the literary times: Essays, reviews, profiles, 1970-1992'|pages=192–196|publisher=SUNY Press|series=The Margins of Literature (SUNY Series)|year=1993|isbn=0-7914-1681-X|id={{ISBN-13|9780791416815}}|ref=harv}}
&lt;p&gt;Originally:  {{cite journal|last=O'Rourke|first=William|title=Michael Harrington: Beyond Watergate, Sixties, and reform|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=5iUJfPxlTCcC&amp;pg=PA197&amp;dq=%22Socialist+Party%22+OR+%22Social+Democrats%22,+%22Michael+Harrington%22,+%22New+York+Times%22&amp;source=gbs_toc_r&amp;cad=4#v=onepage&amp;q=Michael%20Harrington&amp;f=false|pages=6–7|journal=SoHo Weekly News|volume=3|number=2|month=13 November|year=1973|ref=harv}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

==Publications==

The publication that would eventually become the official organ of DSOC, initially an 8-page letter-sized monthly called ''Newsletter of the Democratic Left,'' predated the formal establishment of DSOC as a national organization in October 1973. The first issue of ''Newsletter of the Democratic Left'' (the name was later shortened to ''Democratic Left'') appeared in March 1973, under the editorship of Mike Harrington, assisted by Jack Clark as Managing Editor.&lt;ref name=&quot;DL001&quot;&gt;[http://www.marxisthistory.org/history/usa/parties/dsa/1973/0300-dsoc-dl001.pdf ''Newsletter of the Democratic Left], vol. 1, no. 1 (March 1973).&lt;/ref&gt; A front page essay by Harrington, entitled &quot;The Shape of Our Politics,&quot; made nary a mention of the bitter faction fight within the Socialist Party:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;Liberalism is in transition. Important ideologists announce their 'deradicalization.' *  *  * &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;On the other wing, many trade unionists and middle-class liberals have become aware of the need for structural change in our society. In the McGovern campaign, for instance, the frankly [[redistribution of wealth|redistributionist]] principle that revenue should be raised by levies on [[unearned income]]s was a major step forward.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;On the campus there is a decline of activism, a revival of private concerns. The [[New Left]] is dead. But a large and serious constituency of the Left remains, even if unorganized and uncertain. If presented with a clear and reasoned perspective for basic change, it might be won to a lifetime commitment, even in the Nixon years; if not, it could vanish. *  *  *&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;The Left, more than ever before, needs thought, self-criticism, candor, and communication. We hope this ''Newsletter'' will make a modest contribution to that end.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;DL001&quot; /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

''Democratic Left'' continues today as the publication of DSA, the organizational successor to DSOC. The organization also published a number of issues of an internal discussion bulletin, containing typewritten content submitted by its members about various issues of concern.

===Formal establishment===

The June 1973 issue of ''Newsletter of the Democratic Left,'' the fourth monthly magazine off the press, announced to its subscribers that the never-before-mentioned &quot;National Board&quot; of the &quot;Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee&quot; had issued a call for the launch of &quot;a new, nationwide socialist organization.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Journey&quot;&gt;[http://www.marxisthistory.org/history/usa/parties/dsa/1973/0600-dsoc-dl004.pdf &quot;The Journey of Ten Thousand Miles,&quot;] ''Newsletter of the Democratic Left,'' vol. 1, no. 4 (June 1973), pg. 6.&lt;/ref&gt; The founding convention of DSOC was initially slated to begin on October 12, 1973, in New York City.&lt;ref name=&quot;Journey&quot; /&gt; For the first time, membership dues were solicited, with rates of $3.50 for Students and $7.00 for Regular membership accepted until January 1, 1974.&lt;ref name=&quot;Journey&quot; /&gt;

The Founding Convention was to be a three day long affair, beginning at 8 pm at the Eisner and Lubin Auditorium of [[New York University]].&lt;ref name=&quot;New&quot;&gt;[http://www.marxisthistory.org/history/usa/parties/dsa/1973/1000-dsoc-dl006.pdf &quot;A New Beginning for American Socialism,&quot;] ''Newsletter of the Democratic Left,'' vol. 1, no. 6 (October 1973), pg. 6.&lt;/ref&gt; The convention was not composed of elected delegates, but was rather open to a general admission, and about 500 people were in attendance.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Harrington, ''The Long-Distance Runner: An Autobiography.'' New York: Henry Holt &amp; Co., 1988; pg. 17.&lt;/ref&gt; The keynote speaker chosen by the organizers of DSOC to address this gathering was [[David Lewis (politician)|David Lewis]], one of the key architects of the [[New Democratic Party]], the social democratic [[Parliament of Canada|parliamentary]] opposition party of [[Canada]].&lt;ref name=&quot;New&quot; /&gt;

The following day, October 13, the convention moved to the [[McAlpin Hotel]], located at the corner of Broadway and 34th Street in New York City and began in earnest. Harrington delivered an address to those attending the gathering, which was undelegated and open to all desiring to attend from the general public, and then the attendees broke up into various small workshops.&lt;ref name=&quot;New&quot; /&gt; Small group subjects included &quot;the unions,&quot; &quot;[[feminism]],&quot; &quot;racial equality,&quot; &quot;Democratic Party,&quot; &quot;equality,&quot; and &quot;[[detente]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;New&quot; /&gt; Workshop chairs were appointed in advance and included [[Michael Walzer]], Bogdan Denitch, [[Christopher Lasch]], and others.&lt;ref name=&quot;New&quot; /&gt; A panel discussion on &quot;Socialism and the Welfare State&quot; was also held, featuring prominently Harrington's close political associate, the historian and magazine editor [[Irving Howe]], an individual who would become one of the organization's leading faces.&lt;ref name=&quot;New&quot; /&gt;

The final day saw the election of a governing National Board and ratification of a constitution for the new organization.&lt;ref name=&quot;New&quot; /&gt;

===Membership size and structure===

According to the group's founder, Michael Harrington, DSOC began with a core of about 250 members.&lt;ref name=&quot;LD19&quot;&gt;Harrington, ''The Long-Distance Runner,'' pg. 19.&lt;/ref&gt; The group's first paid staffer was Jack Clark, a 23 year old from [[Boston, Massachusetts|Boston]] who received $50 a month and use of a spare bed in the home of Debbie Meier, herself a second generation socialist and important figure in the DSOC inner circle.&lt;ref name=&quot;LD19&quot; /&gt; Meier's home served as the group's base of operations up to the October 1973 convention, at which time DSOC rented a tiny basement office.&lt;ref&gt;Harrington, ''The Long-Distance Runner,'' pg. 23.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ideology and strategy==

DSOC presented itself as an explicitly socialist organization. In electoral politics, it worked within the [[United States Democratic Party|Democratic Party]], in which it dedicated itself to building a base of support for democratic-socialist (&quot;democratic-left&quot;) ideas. In Michael Harrington's view, the task facing the American movement was &quot;to build a new American majority for social change.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Realism&quot;&gt;Michael Harrington, &quot;The Left Wing of Realism,&quot; ''Democratic Left,'' vol. 1, no. 1 (March 1973), pg. 5.&lt;/ref&gt; The union movement, while important, could not win political power in its own right, Harrington wrote. Harrington instead argued that it needed to unite with the &quot;college-educated and issue-oriented&quot; adherents of the so-called &quot;New Politics&quot; in the Democratic Party:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;In 1968, the Center-Right of [[Richard Nixon|Nixon]] and [[George Wallace|Wallace]] received almost 58% of the votes; in 1972, in a two-way race, Nixon got over 61%. In 1968, the American unions were a major, and sometimes sole, force behind [[Hubert Humphrey]], proving that the organized workers are the most cohesive element that can be mobilized for social change. But the '68 election also proved that labor by itself cannot come close to winning.... In 1968 many [[Eugene McCarthy|McCarthyites]] did not understand that Humphrey was infinitely preferable to Nixon; in 1972, the [[George Meany|Meanyites]] did not understand that McGovern was infinitely preferable to Nixon. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;If this split continues, the [[Republican Party (U.S.)|Republicans]] will hold the Presidency for the foreseeable future. Therefore, the only way to build a new majority for social change is for labor and the new politics to come together.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Realism&quot; /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

DSOC proposed  winning power through the tactic of &quot;realignment&quot; — uniting of forces within the Democratic Party around a democratic-socialist program.

Its members ran for political office almost always within the Democratic Party. In addition,  DSOC publicized and promoted the individual efforts of its dues payers and supporters, many of whom wer active in labor unions or other political organizations. There were members of DSOC who were elected to the [[United States Congress|Congress]] ([[Berkley, California]] Rep. [[Ron Dellums]]) and the [[New York City Council]] ([[Ruth Messinger]]). DSOC had public support from [[Labor unions|union]] leaders as [[Victor Reuther]] of the [[United Auto Workers]], [[William W. Winpisinger]] of the [[International Association of Machinists]], and various officials of the [[Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America]].

==From DSOC to the Democratic Socialists of America (DSA)==

DSOC ceased to exist in 1982 when it merged with the [[New American Movement]] (NAM) to form the [[Democratic Socialists of America]] (DSA).

Discussions with representatives of NAM, a successor organization to [[Students for a Democratic Society]], began as early as 1977.&lt;ref name=&quot;LD64&quot;&gt;Harrington, ''The Long-Distance Runner,'' pg. 64.&lt;/ref&gt; The move was favored by DSOC's left wing, led by historian Jim Chapin, which sought to bring into DSOC many former participants in the [[New Left]] of the 1960s who were in search of a new home.&lt;ref name=&quot;LD64&quot; /&gt; DSOC formally endorsed the idea of merger with NAM at its 1979 Houston convention.&lt;ref name=&quot;LD65&quot;&gt;Harrington, ''The Long-Distance Runner,'' pg. 65.&lt;/ref&gt;

The proposal for merger generated vocal opposition, however. Forces on the organization's right wing, led by Howe and calling themselves the Committee Against the NAM Merger (CATNAM), urged that instead of courting New Left survivors that DSOC should instead continue to place its emphasis on outreach to larger forces in the labor movement and the Democratic Party. In addition to noting NAM's deep distrust of the Democratic Party, many adherents of CATNAM had grave misgivings about NAM's position towards [[Israel]], with DSOC maintaining belief in a two state solution in the [[Middle East]], guaranteeing the existence of [[Israel]], while many in NAM saw the [[Palestine Liberation Organization]] as engaged in an anti-[[colonialism|colonial]] liberation struggle.&lt;ref name=&quot;LD65&quot; /&gt; Ultimately a careful statement was worked out on the Middle East based upon a two-state solution and merger talks moved forward.

The 1981 DSOC national convention was marked by a very heated debate on the question of merger with NAM, which was ultimately resolved by a vote of approximately 80% of the delegates in favor, none against, with the 20% or so supporting the CATNAM position abstaining.&lt;ref  name=&quot;LD66&quot;&gt;Harrington, ''The Long-Distance Runner,'' pg. 66.&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Our opponents wanted to indicate they were unhappy — and that they were staying,&quot; Harrington later noted.&lt;ref  name=&quot;LD66&quot; /&gt;

The unity convention joining NAM and DSOC was held in Detroit in 1982, and the Democratic Socialists of America was thereby established. The gathering was addressed by [[George W. Crockett, Jr.|George Crockett]], a member of the [[Congressional Black Caucus]] in the [[U.S. House of Representatives]], with Harrington delivering the keynote address.&lt;ref  name=&quot;LD66&quot; /&gt; The new organization claimed a membership of 6,000 at the time of its formation.&lt;ref  name=&quot;LD66&quot; /&gt;

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* [http://onlinebooks.library.upenn.edu/webbin/serial?id=demleft ''Newsletter of the Democratic Left,'' First ten issues] New York: Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee, 1973.
* [http://www.archive.org/details/WeAreSocialistOfTheDemocraticLeft ''We are Socialists of the Democratic Left.''] Fifth Anniversary edition. New York: Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee, 1982.
* Social Democrats, USA [http://www.archive.org/details/ForTheRecord1973 ''For the Record: The Report by the Social Democrats, USA on the Resignation of Michael Harrington and his Attempt to Split the American Socialist Movement.''] New York: Social Democrats USA, n.d. [1973]. &lt;small&gt;—Polemic against Michael Harrington from the time of the 1973 SP split.&lt;/small&gt;

==External links==
* [http://www.dsausa.org/dsa.html Democratic Socialists of America official website.] dsausa.org —''successor organization to DSOC.''

[[Category:Political parties established in 1973]]
[[Category:Political parties disestablished in 1982]]
[[Category:Political advocacy groups in the United States]]
[[Category:Democratic socialist and social democratic parties and organizations in the United States]]</text>
      <sha1>e3q4bz49sdm55nd4a6yolyuodopuj10</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
