<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Demonstration (people)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6787314</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521359558</id>
      <parentid>520330540</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-04T14:19:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>TheOriginalSoni</username>
        <id>16646252</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Disambiguated: [[militant]] → [[militant (disambiguation)]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15632">{{too many images}}
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-1989-1106-405, Plauen, Demonstration vor dem Rathaus.jpg|thumb|220px|[[Monday demonstrations in East Germany]] helped to bring down the [[Berlin Wall]].]] 
[[File:2010-2011 Greek protests collage.png|thumb|Protest in [[Athens]], on account of the [[Greek government-debt crisis|government-debt crisis]]]]
[[File:La Unión i el Fènix P1160234.JPG|thumb|220px|right|View of the [[2012 Catalan independence demonstration]] running through [[Passeig de Gràcia, Barcelona|Passeig de Gràcia]] in [[Barcelona]].]]

A '''demonstration''' or '''street protest''' is action by a mass group or collection of groups of people in favor of a [[political]] or other cause; it normally consists of walking in a mass march formation and either beginning with or meeting at a designated endpoint, or rally, to hear [[speech|speakers]]. 

Actions such as blockades and [[sit-in]]s may also be referred to as demonstrations. Demonstrations can be [[nonviolent]] or [[violent]] (usually referred to by participants as &quot;[[militant (disambiguation)|militant]]&quot;), or can begin as nonviolent and turn violent dependent on circumstances. Sometimes [[riot police]] or other forms of [[Law enforcement agency|law enforcement]] become involved. In some cases this may be in order to try to prevent the protest from taking place at all. In other cases it may be to prevent clashes between rival groups, or to prevent a demonstration from spreading and turning into a [[riot]].

The term has been in use since the mid-19th century, as was the term 'monster meeting', which was coined initially with reference to the huge assemblies of protesters inspired by [[Daniel O'Connell]] in Ireland.&lt;ref name=&quot;OED&quot;&gt;[[Oxford English Dictionary]]&lt;/ref&gt; Demonstrations are a form of [[activism]], usually taking the form of a public gathering of people in a rally or walking in a march.   Thus, the opinion is ''demonstrated'' to be significant by gathering in a crowd associated with that opinion.

Demonstrations can be used to show a viewpoint (either positive or negative) regarding a public issue, especially relating to a perceived [[grievance]] or [[social injustice]].  A demonstration is usually considered more successful if more people participate.  Topics of demonstrations often deal with [[politics|political]], [[economics|economic]], and [[society|social]] issues.

== Forms ==
[[Image:1963 march on washington.jpg|thumb|220px|right|[[American Civil Rights Movement (1955-1968)|American Civil Rights]] [[March on Washington]], leaders marching from the [[Washington Monument]] to the [[Lincoln Memorial]], August 28, 1963.]]
There are many types of demonstrations, including a variety of elements.  These may include:
* Marches, in which a [[parade]] of people proceeds from one location to another.
* Rallies, in which people gather to listen to speakers or musicians.
* [[Picketing (protest)|Picketing]], in which people surround an area.
* [[Sit-in]]s, in which demonstrators occupy an area, sometimes for a stated period of time and sometimes indefinitely, until they feel their issue has been addressed, or they are otherwise convinced or forced to leave.
* [[Nudity and protest|Nudity]], either threatened or carried out.


Demonstrations are sometimes spontaneous gatherings, but are also utilized as a tactical choice by movements. They often form part of a larger campaign of [[nonviolent resistance]], often also called [[civil resistance]]. Demonstrations are generally staged in public, but private demonstrations are certainly possible, especially if the demonstrators wish to influence the opinions of a small or very specific group of people.  Demonstrations are usually physical gatherings, but virtual or [[online]] demonstrations are certainly possible.

Sometimes, particularly with controversial issues, groups of people opposed to the aims of a demonstration may themselves launch a counter-demonstration with the aim of opposing the demonstrators and presenting their view.  Clashes between demonstrators and counter-demonstrators may turn violent.

[[Government-organized demonstrations]] are demonstrations which are organized by a government. The [[Islamic Republic of Iran]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rferl.org/featuresarticle/2004/11/9965bfb5-1917-4d01-a7b7-19d5de7692cd.html Analysis: Iran Sends Terror-Group Supporters To Arafat's Funeral Procession] &quot;...state-organized rallies...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thehedgefundjournal.com/commentary/index.php?articleid=23056981 Why Washington and Tehran are headed for a showdown] ''[[The Hedge Fund Journal]]'' 16 April 200&lt;/ref&gt; the [[People's Republic of China]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://lists.asu.edu/cgi-bin/wa?A2=ind9905e&amp;L=china-nn&amp;P=173 Global News, No. GL99-072] ''[[China News Digest]]'' June 3, 1989&lt;/ref&gt; [[Republic of Cuba]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washtimes.com/world/20060802-124603-7186r.htm Cubans ponder life without Fidel] ''The [[Washington Times]]'' 2 August 2006&lt;/ref&gt;, the [[Soviet Union]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pinr.com/report.php?ac=view_report&amp;report_id=249&amp;language_id=1 &quot;Democracy in the Former Soviet Union: 1991-2004&quot;] ''Power and Interest News Report'' 28 December 2004&lt;/ref&gt;{{dead|date=December 2011}} and [[Argentina]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.clarin.com/zona/Militancia-terreno_0_745725575.html|title= Militancia todo terreno: Sacan a presos de la cárcel para actos del kirchnerismo|trans_title= All-terrain militants: Prisoners are taken out of jail to take part in Kirchnerist demonstrations|language= Spanish|author= Nicolás Pizzi|date= 29/07/2012|work= |publisher= Clarín|accessdate=July 29, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; among other nations, have had government-organized demonstrations.

== Times and locations ==
[[File:Orange rev2.jpg|thumb|220px|[[Orange Revolution]] demonstrations lasted so long that demonstrators set up tents.]]
Sometimes the date or location chosen for the demonstration is of historical or cultural significance, such as the [[anniversary]] of some event that is relevant to the topic of the demonstration.

Locations are also frequently chosen because of some relevance to the issue at hand.  For example, if a demonstration is targeted at issues relating to foreign [[nation]], the demonstration may take place at a location associated with that nation, such as an [[embassy]] of the nation in question.

{{break}}
== Nonviolence or violence ==
[[File:Rally_Against_Asset_Sales,_Palmerston_North,_14_July_2012_07.JPG|thumb|220px|right|A nonviolent protest in New Zealand]]
Protest marches and demonstrations are a common [[nonviolent]] tactic. They are thus one tactic available to proponents of strategic [[nonviolence]]. However, the reasons for avoiding the use of violence may also derive, not from a general doctrine of [[nonviolence]] or [[pacifism]], but from considerations relating to the particular situation that is faced, including its legal, cultural and power-political dimensions: this has been the case in many campaigns of [[civil resistance]].&lt;ref&gt; [[Adam Roberts (scholar)|Adam Roberts]] and [[Timothy Garton Ash]] (eds.), ''Civil Resistance and Power Politics: The Experience of Non-violent Action from Gandhi to the Present'', Oxford University Press, 2009, especially at pp. 14-20.[http://books.google.com/books?id=BxOQKrCe7UUC&amp;dq=Civil+resistance+and+power+politics&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s] Includes chapters by specialists on the various movements.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some demonstrations and [[protests]] can turn, at least partially, into [[riot]]s or mob [[violence]] against objects such as [[automobile]]s and [[business]]es, bystanders and the [[police]].{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}} Police and military authorities often use [[non-lethal force]] or less-lethal weapons, such as [[Electroshock gun|tasers]], [[rubber bullet]]s, [[pepper spray]], and [[tear gas]] against demonstrators in these situations.{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}}  Sometimes violent situations are caused by the preemptive or offensive use of these weapons which can provoke, destabilize, or escalate a conflict.

As a known tool to prevent the infiltration by [[agents provocateurs]],&lt;ref&gt;Stratfor (2004) ''[http://www.stratfor.com/radical_anarchist_groups_pose_their_own_threat Radical, Anarchist Groups Pose Their Own Threat]'' published by [[Stratfor]], June 4, 2004 quote: &lt;blockquote&gt;Another common tactic is to infiltrate legitimate demonstrations in the attempt to stir widespread violence and rioting, seen most recently in a spring anti-Iraq war gathering in Vancouver, Canada. This has become so commonplace that sources within activist organizations have told STRATFOR they police their own demonstrations to prevent infiltration by fringe groups.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; the organizers of large or controversial assemblies may deploy and coordinate [[demonstration marshal]]s, also called stewards.&lt;ref name=&quot;OCSE2007&quot;&gt;Belyaeva et al. (2007) ''[http://www.osce.org/item/23835.html Guidelines on Freedom of Peaceful Assembly]'', published by OSCE's [[Office for Democratic Institutions and Human Rights]]. Alternative [http://www.venice.coe.int/docs/2008/CDL(2008)062-e.asp#_ednref148 version], Sections § 7-8, 156-162&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bryan06&quot;&gt;Bryan, Dominic ''[http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/berghahn/antiac/2006/00000013/F0020001/art00005?crawler=true The Anthropology of Ritual: Monitoring and Stewarding Demonstrations in Northern Ireland]'', ''Anthropology in Action'', Volume 13, Numbers 1-2, January 2006, pp.22-31(10)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Law by country==
===Russia===
{{main|Freedom of assembly in Russia}}
[[Freedom of assembly]] in the [[Russia|Russian Federation]] is granted by Art. 31 of the [[Constitution of the Russian Federation|Constitution]] adopted in 1993: &lt;blockquote&gt;Citizens of the Russian Federation shall have the right to gather peacefully, without weapons, and to hold meetings, rallies, [[demonstration (people)|demonstrations]], marches and [[Picketing (protest)|pickets]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.russianembassy.org/RUSSIA/CONSTIT/chapter2.htm Chapter 2 of the Constitution of the Russian Federation]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; 

Demonstrations and protests are further regulated by the Federal Law of the Russian Federation No.54-FZ &quot;''On Meetings, Rallies, Demonstrations, Marches and Pickets''&quot;. If the assembly in public is expected to involve more than one participant, its organisers are obliged to notify executive or local self-government authorities of the upcoming event few days in advance in writing. However, legislation does not foresee an authorisation procedure, hence the authorities have no right to prohibit an assembly or change its place unless it threatens the security of participants or is planned to take place near hazardous facilities, important [[Rail transport in Russia|railway]]s, [[viaduct]]s, [[Pipeline transport|pipeline]]s, [[high voltage#Power lines|high voltage electric power lines]], [[prison]]s, [[court]]s, presidential residences or in the border control zone. The right to gather can also be restricted in close proximity of cultural and historical monuments.

=== United Kingdom ===
[[Image:Manifs à londres contre la guerre en irak.JPG|right|thumb|220px|Demonstration in front of the [[British parliament]]]]
Under the [[Serious Organised Crime and Police Act 2005]] and the [[Terrorism Act 2006]], there are areas designated as 'protected sites' where people are not allowed to go. Previously, these were military bases and nuclear power stations, but the law is changing to include other, generally political areas, such as [[Downing Street]], the [[Palace of Westminster]], and the headquarters of [[MI5]] and [[MI6]]. Previously, [[trespasser]]s to these areas could not be arrested if they had not committed another crime and agreed to be escorted out, but this will change following amendments to the law.&lt;ref&gt;Morris, Steven, &quot;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/monarchy/story/0,,2041802,00.html New powers against trespassers at key sites]&quot;, ''[[The Guardian]]'', 24 March 2007. Retrieved on 23 June 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Human rights]] groups fear the powers could hinder peaceful protest. [[Nick Clegg]], the then [[Liberal Democrats|Liberal Democrat]] home affairs spokesman, said: &quot;I am not aware of vast troops of trespassers wanting to invade MI5 or MI6, still less running the gauntlet of security checks in [[Whitehall]] and Westminster to make a point. It's a sledgehammer to crack a nut.&quot; [[Liberty (pressure group)|Liberty]], the [[civil liberties]] pressure group, said the measure was &quot;excessive&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Brown, Colin, &quot;[http://news.independent.co.uk/uk/legal/article2611749.ece  No-go Britain: Royal Family and ministers protected from protesters by new laws]&quot;, ''[[The Independent]]'', 4 June 2007. Retrieved on 23 June 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===
The [[First Amendment of the United States Constitution]] specifically allows peaceful demonstrations and the [[freedom of assembly]] as part of a measure to facilitate the redress of such grievances.  &quot;Amendment I: Congress shall make no law ... abridging ... the right of the people peaceably to assemble, and to petition the Government for a redress of grievances.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.archives.gov/national-archives-experience/charters/bill_of_rights_transcript.html NARA | The National Archives Experience&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

A growing trend in the [[United States]] has been the implementation of &quot;[[free speech zone]]s,&quot; or fenced-in areas which are often far-removed from the event which is being protested; critics of free-speech zones argue that they go against the First Amendment of the [[United States Constitution]] by their very nature, and that they lessen the impact the demonstration might otherwise have had. In many areas it is required to get permission from the government to hold a demonstration.

== See also ==
{{Commons category|Demonstrations}}
* [[Civil resistance]]
* [[Civil Rights Movement]]
* [[Crowd control]]
* [[Fare strike]]
* [[Nonviolent resistance]]
* [[Protest]]
* [[List of uprisings led by women]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.thefreelibrary.com/Controlling+public+protest%3a+First+Amendment+implications.-a016473804 ''Controlling Public Protest: First Amendment Implications''] An article about restrictions that may legally be imposed on public protests, by Daniel L. Schofield, S.J.D., published in the November 1994 issue of the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation|FBI]]'s [[FBI Law Enforcement Bulletin|''Law Enforcement Bulletin'']].

{{Media culture}}
{{Media manipulation}}

[[Category:Activism by method]]
[[Category:Community organizing]]
[[Category:Protest tactics]]
[[Category:Revolutionary tactics]]

[[ar:تظاهر]]
[[an:Manifestación]]
[[ast:Manifestación]]
[[bg:Демонстрация (обществена проява)]]
[[ca:Manifestació]]
[[cs:Demonstrace (protest)]]
[[da:Demonstration]]
[[de:Demonstration]]
[[et:Meeleavaldus]]
[[es:Manifestación]]
[[eo:Manifestacio]]
[[eu:Manifestazio]]
[[fa:تظاهرات]]
[[fr:Manifestation]]
[[gl:Manifestación]]
[[ko:시위]]
[[hr:Prosvjed]]
[[id:Unjuk rasa]]
[[it:Manifestazione]]
[[he:הפגנה]]
[[la:Manifestatio]]
[[ms:Tunjuk perasaan]]
[[nl:Betoging]]
[[ja:デモ活動]]
[[no:Politisk demonstrasjon]]
[[pl:Demonstracja]]
[[pt:Manifestação]]
[[ro:Manifestație]]
[[ru:Демонстрация (публичное мероприятие)]]
[[sq:Manifestimi]]
[[simple:Demonstration]]
[[ckb:خۆپیشاندان]]
[[sr:Демонстрација]]
[[sh:Demonstracija]]
[[fi:Mielenosoitus]]
[[sv:Demonstration (folk)]]
[[th:การเดินขบวน]]
[[uk:Демонстрація]]
[[vi:Biểu tình]]
[[zh:示威]]</text>
      <sha1>m1vafrdf2ie324lqf069osqlxndon1a</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
