<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Direct action</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>105976</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522219543</id>
      <parentid>521492478</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T19:10:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Chaoticneutral77</username>
        <id>17858511</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Violent direct action */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="19475">{{Other uses}}
[[Image:Gandhi Salt March.jpg|thumb|[[Mohandas Gandhi]] and supporters [[Salt Satyagraha|Salt March]] on March 12, 1930. This was an act of [[non-violent resistance|non-violent]] direct action.]]
[[Image:Bardouxha Mont 1893-mw-c.jpg|thumb|right|Depiction of the [[Belgian general strike of 1893]]. A [[general strike]] is an example of confrontational direct action.]]
'''Direct action''' occurs when a group of people take an action which is intended to reveal an existing problem, highlight an alternative, or demonstrate a possible solution to a social issue. This can include nonviolent and less often violent activities which target persons, groups, or property deemed offensive to the direct action participants. Examples of direct action can include [[strike action|strikes]], [[workplace occupation]]s, [[political violence]], [[nonviolent resistance]], [[sabotage]], [[property destruction]], [[blockade]]s, etc. By contrast, [[election|electoral]] [[politics]], [[diplomacy]], [[negotiation]], and [[arbitration]] are not usually described as direct action, as they are politically mediated. Non-violent actions are sometimes a form of [[civil disobedience]], and may involve a degree of intentional law-breaking where persons place themselves in arrestable situations in order to make a political statement  but other actions (such as strikes) may not violate [[criminal law]]. The aim is to either obstruct another political agent or political organization from performing some practice to which the activists object; or to solve perceived problems which traditional societal institutions ([[government]]s, powerful churches or establishment [[trade union]]s) are not addressing to the satisfaction of the direct action participants.

In general, direct action is often used by those seeking social change, and non violent direct action in particular has historically been a regular feature of the tactics employed by social change movements.

==History==

Direct action tactics have been around for as long as conflicts have existed but it is not known when the term first appeared. The radical union the [[Industrial Workers of the World]] first mentioned the term &quot;direct action&quot; in a publication in reference to a Chicago strike conducted in 1910.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated46&quot;&gt;The I.W.W.: Its First Seventy Years, 1905-1975, Fred W. Thompson and Patrick Murfin, 1976, page 46.&lt;/ref&gt;  Other noted historical practitioners of direct action include the [[Civil rights movement#Civil rights movement in the United States|US Civil Rights Movement]], the [[Global Justice Movement]],  the [[Women's Suffrage|Suffragettes]], revolutionary [[Che Guevara]], and certain [[Environmentalist|environmental]] [[advocacy group]]s. 

American anarchist [[Voltairine de Cleyre]] wrote a famous essay called &quot;Direct Action&quot; in 1912&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theanarchistlibrary.org/HTML/Voltairine_de_Cleyre__Direct_Action.html Voltairine de Cleyre.&quot;Direct Action&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; which is widely cited today. In this essay, de Cleyre points to historical examples such as the [[Boston Tea Party]] and the American [[anti-slavery movement]], noting that &quot;direct action has always been used, and has the historical sanction of the very people now reprobating it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|De Cleyre|2004|p=50}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In his 1920 book, ''[[Direct Action (Mellor book)|Direct Action]]'', [[William Mellor]] placed direct action firmly in the [[Class conflict|struggle]] between worker and employer for control &quot;over the economic life of society.&quot;  Mellor defined direct action &quot;as the use of some form of economic [[power (sociology)|power]] for securing of ends desired by those who possess that power.&quot; Mellor considered direct action a tool of both owners and workers and for this reason he included within his definition [[Lockout (industry)|lockout]]s and [[cartel]]s, as well as strikes and [[sabotage]].  However, by this time the US [[anarchist]] and [[feminist]] [[Voltairine de Cleyre]] had already given a strong defense of direct action, linking it with struggles for [[civil rights]]:

:&quot;...the [[Salvation Army]], which was started by a gentleman named [[William Booth]] was vigorously practising direct action in the maintenance of the freedom of its members to speak, assemble, and pray.  Over and over they were arrested, fined, and imprisoned ... till they finally compelled their persecutors to let them alone.&quot; (de Cleyre, undated)

[[Dr. Martin Luther King]] felt that non-violent direct action's goal was to &quot;create such a crisis and foster such a tension&quot; as to demand a response.&lt;ref name=&quot;mlk jail&quot;&gt;{{cite web
	| title		= Letter from Birmingham Jail
	| last		= King	| first = Martin Luther, Jr.
	| date		= 16 April 1963
	| url		= http://abacus.bates.edu/admin/offices/dos/mlk/letter.html
	| postscript		= .
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The rhetoric of both [[Martin Luther King]] and [[Mohandas Gandhi]] promoted [[nonviolence|non-violent]] [[revolutionary]] direct action as a means to social change.

By the middle of the 20th century, the sphere of direct action had undoubtedly expanded, though the meaning of the term had perhaps contracted.  Most campaigns for social change&amp;mdash;notably those seeking [[suffrage]], improved working conditions, [[civil rights]], [[abortion]] rights or an end to abortion, an end to [[gentrification]], and environmental protection&amp;mdash; claim to employ at least some types of violent or nonviolent direct action.

Some sections of the [[Nuclear disarmament|anti-nuclear movement]] used direct action, particularly during the 1980s. Groups opposing the introduction of [[cruise missile]]s into the United Kingdom employed tactics such as breaking into and occupying United States air bases, and blocking roads to prevent the movement of military convoys and disrupt military projects. In the US, mass protests opposed nuclear energy, weapons, and military intervention throughout the decade, resulting in thousands of arrests. Many groups also set up semi-permanent &quot;[[peace camp]]s&quot; outside air bases such as [[Molesworth peace camp|Molesworth]] and [[Greenham Common Women's Peace Camp|Greenham Common]], and at the [[Nevada Test Site]].

[[Anti-abortion groups]] in the United States, particularly [[History of Operation Rescue|Operation Rescue]], often used non-violent sit-ins at the entrances of abortion clinics as a form of direct action in the late 1980s and early 1990s. 

[[Anti-globalization]] activists made headlines around the world in 1999, when they forced the [[Seattle]] [[WTO Ministerial Conference of 1999]] to end early with direct action tactics.  The goal that they had, shutting down the meetings, was directly accomplished by placing their bodies and other debris between the WTO delegates and the building they were meant to meet in.  Activists also engaged in [[property destruction]] as a direct way of stating their opposition to [[corporate culture]]—this can be viewed as a direct action if the goal was to shut down those stores for a period of time, or an indirect action if the goal was influencing corporate policy.

One of the largest direct actions in recent years took place in San Francisco the day after the [[Iraq War]] began in 2003. Twenty-thousand people occupied the streets and over 2,000 people were arrested in [[affinity group]] actions throughout downtown San Francisco, home to [[military-related corporation]]s such as [[Bechtel]]. (See [[March 20, 2003 anti-war protest]]).

Direct action has also been used on a smaller scale. [[Refugee]] [[Salim Rambo]] was saved from being [[deported]] from the UK back to the [[Democratic Republic of the Congo]] when one person stood up on his flight and refused to sit down.  After a two-hour delay the man was arrested, but the pilot refused to fly with Rambo on board.  Salim Rambo was ultimately released from state custody and remains free today.

== Nonviolent direct action ==
&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Ruckus Society]] --&gt;
[[Image:Cutters1.preview.jpg|thumb|Destroying fences at the border by the [[Anarchists Against the Wall|AATW]], 2007]]

Non-violent direct action (NVDA) is any form of direct action that does not rely on violent tactics. [[Mohandas Gandhi]]'s teachings of [[Satyagraha]] (or ''truth force'') have inspired many practitioners of [[nonviolent]] direct action, although the use of nonviolence does not always imply an ideological commitment to pacifism.  In 1963, civil rights leader [[Martin Luther King Jr.]] described the goal of NVDA in his ''[[Letter from Birmingham Jail]]'':
&lt;blockquote&gt;Nonviolent direct action seeks to create such a crisis and foster such a tension that a community which has constantly refused to negotiate is forced to confront the issue. It seeks so to dramatize the issue that it can no longer be ignored.&lt;ref name=&quot;mlk jail&quot; /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

One major debate is whether destruction of property can be included within the realm of nonviolence. This debate can be illustrated by the response to groups like the [[Earth Liberation Front]] and [[Animal Liberation Front]], which use property destruction and sabotage as direct action tactics. Although these types of actions are prosecuted as violence, those groups justify their actions by claiming that violence is harm directed towards living things and not property. The issue of whether sabotage is a form of violence is difficult to resolve in purely philosophical terms, but the use of sabotage as a methodology can be contrasted with minor property damage that is a small but necessary part of a non-violent campaign methodology such as breaking locks and fences to gain entry to a site.

In the United States, the term has largely come to signify civil disobedience, and protest in general. In the 1980s, a California direct action protest group called [[Livermore Action Group]] called its newspaper ''Direct Action''. The paper ran for 25 issues, and covered hundreds of nonviolent actions around the world. The book ''Direct Action: An Historical Novel'' took its name from this paper, and records dozens of actions in the San Francisco Bay Area. 

Human rights activists have used direct action in the ongoing campaign to close the [[School of the Americas]], renamed in 2001 the [[Western Hemisphere Institute for Security Cooperation]]. As a result, 245 [[SOA Watch]] human rights defenders have collectively spent almost 100 years in prison. More than 50 people have served probation sentences. 

&quot;Direct Action&quot; has also served as the moniker of at least two groups: the French ''[[Action Directe (gang)|Action Directe]]'' as well as the Canadian group more popularly known as the [[Squamish Five]]. ''Direct Action'' is also the name of the magazine of the Australian [[Wobblies]]. The [[United Kingdom|UK's]] [[Solidarity Federation]] currently publishes a magazine called ''Direct Action''.

Until 1990, Australia's Socialist Workers Party published a party paper also named &quot;Direct Action&quot;, in honour of the Wobblies' history. One of the group's descendants, the Revolutionary Socialist Party, has again started a publication of this name.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
	| title		= Direct Action – two earlier versions
	| last		= Percy	| first	= John
	| publisher	= Revolutionary Socialist Party
	| date		= June 2008
	| url		= http://directaction.org.au/issue1/direct_action_two_earlier_versions
	| accessdate	= 15 June 2009
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Food Not Bombs]] is often described as direct action because individuals involved directly act to solve a social problem; people are hungry and yet there is food available. Food Not Bombs is inherently dedicated to non-violence.

A museum that chronicles the history of direct action and [[grassroots]] activism in the Lower East Side of New York City, the [[Museum of Reclaimed Urban Space]], opened in 2012.

== Violent direct action ==
Violent direct action is any direct action which utilizes physical injurious force against persons or property{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}. While groups such as Animal Liberation Front and Sea Shepherd claim that destruction of property is not violence, US and international law include acts against property in the definition of violence{{Citation needed|date=November 2012}}. Examples of violent direct action include: destruction of property, rioting, [[lynching]], [[terrorism]], [[political assassination]], [[graffiti]], freeing political prisoners, fighting against wartime occupation, interfering with police actions, [[self-defense]], and armed [[insurgency|insurrection]].

However, under this definition [[Jesus]], [[Muhammad]] and [[Nelson Mandela]] are examples of individuals who have practised violent direct action. The Christian pacifist group, the [[Plowshares Movement]], and the women's right-to-vote group, the [[Suffragettes]], would have also used violent direct action to advance their aims. Historically, the [[Boston Tea Party]] is an early example of American violent direct action. 
An example group that promotes direct action against property is the [[Sea Shepherd Conservation Society]], which boasts of having sunk several whaling or fisheries vessels, though intentionally without loss of life.

==United Kingdom==
{{Main|Environmental direct action in the United Kingdom}}
The [[Environmentalism|environmental]] direct action movement in the United Kingdom started in 1990 with the forming of the first UK [[Earth First!]] group. The movement rapidly grew from the 1992 [[Twyford Down]] protests, culminating in 1997. For a fictional representation of this read Birds, Booze &amp; Bulldozers by Peter Styles.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.smashwords.com/books/view/138107 Birds, Booze &amp; Bulldozers] by Peter Styles&lt;/ref&gt;

There are now several organisations in the United Kingdom campaigning for action on climate change that use non-violent direct action, including [[Camp for Climate Action]], [[Plane Stupid]] and [[Greenpeace]]. This has resulted in environmental campaigners being labelled as extremists by the [[Ministry of Justice (United Kingdom)|Ministry of Justice]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/environment/2010/jan/26/ministry-justice-environmental-campaigners-terrorism | work=[[The Guardian]] | location=London | title=Ministry of Justice lists eco-activists alongside terrorists | first=Matthew | last=Taylor | date=26 January 2010 | accessdate=1 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|Anarchism|Politics|Social and political philosophy|Sociology}}
{{div col|3}}
*[[Active citizenship]]
*[[Anarchism]]
*[[Citizen journalism]]
*[[Civil disobedience]]
*[[Civil resistance]]
*[[Direct democracy]]
*[[Direct Action Day]]
*[[Dual power]]
*[[General strike]]
*[[Independent Media Center]]
*[[Nonviolence]]
*[[Nonviolent resistance]]
*[[Propaganda of the deed]]
*[[Sabotage]] and/or [[Ecotage]]
*[[Satyagraha]]
*[[Security culture]]
*[[Tax resistance]]
*[[Tree sitting]]
*[[Tree spiking]]
{{div col end}}

;Some groups which employ direct action
{{div col|3}}
*[[ADAPT]]
*[[Anarchists Against the Wall]] (Israeli group)
*[[Animal Liberation Front]]
*[[AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power]] (ACT UP)
*[[Camp for Climate Action]]
*[[Campus Antiwar Network]]
*[[Committee of 100 (United Kingdom)]]
*[[Code Pink]]
*[[Confederación Nacional del Trabajo]]
*[[Cymdeithas yr Iaith Gymraeg]]
*[[Cypherpunk]]
*[[Direct Action Committee]]
*[[Direct Action to Stop the War]]
*[[Earth First!]]
*[[Earth Liberation Front]]
*[[Food Not Bombs]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=FREQUENTLY ASKED QUESTIONS|url=http://www.foodnotbombs.net/faq.html|publisher=Food Not Bombs|accessdate=7 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[GetEQUAL]]
*[[Greenpeace]]
*[[Homes Not Jails]]
*[[Industrial Workers of the World]]
*[[Landless Workers' Movement]]
*[[Lesbian Avengers]]
*[[MindFreedom International]]
*[[National Bolshevik Party]]
*[[No Border network]]
*[[Not Dead Yet (group)]]
*[[Occupy Wall Street]]
*[[Operation Save America]]
*[[PETA]]
*[[Plane Stupid]]
*[[Reclaim the Streets]]
*[[Rising Tide North America]]
*[[Sea Shepherd Conservation Society]]
*[[School of the Americas Watch]] (SOA Watch)
*[[Sons of Liberty]]
*[[Squamish Five]]
*[[Students for a Democratic Society]]
*[[Take Back the Land]]
*[[Trident Ploughshares]]
*[[UkUncut]]
*[[WOMBLES]]
*[[War Resisters' International]]
*[[Vetëvendosje!]] - Movement for Self-determination in Kosova
{{div col end}}

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
*[[Voltairine de Cleyre|de Cleyre, Voltairine]]. (1912) ''Direct Action''. Available at [http://www.spunk.org/library/writers/decleyre/sp001334.html Spunk Online Anarchist Library].
*Hauser, Luke (2003) ''Direct Action: An Historical Novel''. Available at [http://www.directaction.org/index.html www.directaction.org].
*Lunori, G. (1999) ''Direct Action''.  Available at [http://www.sniggle.net/Manifesti/directAction.php sniggle.net].
*Sparrow, R. (undated) ''Anarchist Politics and Direct Action''. Available at [http://www.spunk.org/library/intro/sp001641.html Spunk Online Anarchist Library].

== External links ==
{{Commons category}}
*[http://www.dagallery.co.uk DA! (Direct Action) Gallery]. Direct Action in Londons Art scene.
*[http://theanarchistlibrary.org/HTML/Various_Authors__Ecodefense__A_Field_Guide_to_Monkeywrenching.html Ecodefense: A Field Guide to Monkeywrenching]
* [https://directactionde.ucrony.net/en/ Direct Action News from Germany]
*[http://www.activistmagazine.com ACTivist Magazine]
*[http://www.actupny.org/documents/CDdocuments/CDindex.html Civil Disobedience Manual from ACT-UP/NY]
*[http://www.reclaimingquarterly.org ReclaimingQuarterly.org features photo-coverage of contemporary nonviolent direct actions]
*[http://www.directaction.org DirectAction.org offers online organizing resources]
*[http://www.greenpeace.org.au/getactive/happen/nvda.html Greenpeace encourages its activists to use Non-Violent Direct Action]
*[http://www.vcn.bc.ca/citizens-handbook The Citizen's Handbook]
*[http://ruckus.org Ruckus]
*[http://bostondirectactionproject.blogspot.com The Boston Direct Action Project]
*[http://www.iww.org/organize IWW Organizing Department]
*[http://libcom.org/organise libcom.org/organise] - organising direct action at work, in the community or anywhere else tips and guidelines
* [http://wri-irg.org War Resisters' International ]
*[http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m2386/is_2_112/ai_79548469/pg_1 The Scouring of the Shire: Fairies, Trolls and Pixies in Eco-Protest Culture] by Andy Letcher (2001)
*[http://www.back-of-beyond.org/downloads/da/english.html Video clips] of some direct action
*[http://directactiongr.blogspot.com A bi-lingual database on all known direct action news in Greece since September 2007]
*[http://www.projektwerkstatt.de/da www.direct-action.de.vu] German Direct-Action-Site

{{-}}
{{Anarchism}}
{{Tax resistance}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Direct Action}}
[[Category:Direct action| ]]
[[Category:Industrial Workers of the World]]

[[ca:Acció directa]]
[[cs:Přímá akce]]
[[de:Direkte Aktion]]
[[et:Otsene tegevus]]
[[es:Acción directa]]
[[eu:Ekintza zuzen]]
[[fr:Action directe (théorie politique)]]
[[ko:직접행동]]
[[is:Beinar aðgerðir]]
[[he:פעולה ישירה]]
[[lt:Tiesioginiai veiklos metodai]]
[[hu:Közvetlen akció]]
[[nl:Directe actie]]
[[ja:直接行動]]
[[no:Direkte aksjon]]
[[pl:Akcja bezpośrednia]]
[[pt:Ação direta]]
[[ru:Прямое действие (теория)]]
[[sr:Direktna akcija]]
[[sh:Direktna akcija]]
[[fi:Suora toiminta]]
[[sv:Direkt aktion]]
[[uk:Пряма дія]]
[[ur:راست اقدام]]
[[zh:直接行动]]</text>
      <sha1>24s06h1jhpfi3sdrbf23x1npqc1y0c1</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
