<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Drug policy reform</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2751670</id>
    <revision>
      <id>516261739</id>
      <parentid>510389792</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-06T04:45:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Aeusoes1</username>
        <id>306522</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>nix redundant &quot;term used to describe&quot;</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13925">[[Image:Rational scale to assess the harm of drugs (mean physical harm and mean dependence).svg|thumb|right|Relative harm assessment of various drugs from the scientific journal ''The Lancet''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid|17382831}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

'''Drug policy reform''', also known as '''drug law reform''', is any proposed changes to the way [[government]]s respond to the socio-cultural influence on perception of psychoactive substance use. Proponents of [[Psychoactive drug|drug]] policy reform believe that [[prohibition (drugs)|prohibition]] of drugs—such as [[cannabis]], [[opioid]]s, [[cocaine]], [[amphetamine]]s and [[hallucinogen]]s—has been ineffectual and counterproductive. They argue that, rather than using [[law]]s and enforcement as the primary means to responding to substance use, governments and citizens would be better served by [[harm reduction|reducing harm]] and regulating the production, [[marketing]], and distribution of currently illegal drugs in a manner similar to (or some would say better than) how [[alcohol]] and [[tobacco]] are regulated.

Proponents of drug law reform argue that relative harm should be taken into account in the scheduling of controlled substances. Addictive drugs such as [[alcohol]], [[tobacco]] and [[caffeine]] have been a traditional part of Western culture for centuries and are legal, when in fact the first two are more harmful than some substances scheduled under Schedule I.&lt;ref name=&quot;WHO&quot;&gt;[http://www.who.int/whr/2002/en World health report 2002: reducing risks, promoting healthy life]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;goodguidefaq&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.thegooddrugsguide.com/mushrooms/faq.htm#01|title=Magic Mushrooms&amp;ndash;Frequently Asked Questions|accessdate=2007-01-04|publisher=The Good Drugs Guide|author=The Good Drugs Guide|work=Frequently Asked Questions}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;erowid&quot;&gt;[http://www.erowid.org/plants/mushrooms/mushrooms_health1.pdf Report by the Dutch Government Stating Psilocybin's Relative Harmlessness]&lt;/ref&gt; The U.S. [[National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health]], a branch of the U.S. [[Centers for Disease Control]], rated the hallucinogen psilocybin (Schedule I) less [[toxic]] than [[Aspirin]].&lt;ref name=&quot;goodguidefaq&quot;/&gt; The Dutch government found this also to be true.&lt;ref name=&quot;erowid&quot;/&gt;

The addictive properties of the drug [[nicotine]] in [[tobacco]] are often compared with heroin or cocaine,&lt;ref name=&quot;American Heart Association&quot;&gt;[http://www.americanheart.org/presenter.jhtml?identifier=4753 American Heart Association] and Nicotine addiction.&lt;/ref&gt; but [[tobacco]] is legal, even though the [[World Health Organization]] (WHO) in the 2002 World Health Report estimates that in developed countries, 26% of male deaths and 9% of female deaths can be attributed to tobacco smoking.&lt;ref name=&quot;WHO&quot;/&gt; According to the [[American Heart Association]], &quot;Nicotine [[Substance dependence|addiction]] has historically been one of the hardest addictions to break.&quot; The pharmacologic and behavioral characteristics that determine tobacco addiction are similar to those that determine addiction to drugs such as [[heroin]] and [[cocaine]].&lt;ref name=&quot;American Heart Association&quot;/&gt;

==History of drug policy reform==
Initial attempts to change the punitive drug laws which were introduced all over the world from the late 1800s onwards were primarily based around recreational use. [[Timothy Leary]] was one of the most prominent campaigners for the legal and recreational use of LSD. In 1967, a &quot;Legalise pot&quot; rally was held in Britain.&lt;ref name=TransformTimeline&gt;{{cite web|title=A history of drug prohibition and a prediction for its abolition and replacement|url=http://www.tdpf.org.uk/Policy_Timeline.htm|publisher=Transform Drug Policy Foundation|accessdate=2011-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, as death toll from the [[War on Drugs|drug war]] rose, other organisations began to form to campaign on a more political and humanitarian basis. [[The Drug Policy Foundation]] formed in America and [[Release (agency)|Release]], a charity which gives free legal advice to drugs users and currently campaigns for [[drug decriminalization]], also incorporated in the 1970s.

Today, the focus of the world's drug policy reform organisations is on the promotion of [[harm reduction]] in the Western World, and attempting to prevent the catastrophic loss of human life in developing countries where much of the world's supply of heroin, cocaine, and marijuana are produced. Drug policy reform advocates points to efforts such as the [[Mexican Drug War]], which has claimed some 36,000 lives{{Citation needed|date=December 2011}}, as signs that a new approach to drug policy is needed.

==Proposed Alternatives==
===Harm reduction===
{{Main|Harm reduction}}
Harm reduction refers to a range of [[public health]] policies designed to reduce the harmful consequences associated with [[recreational drug use]] and other high risk activities. Harm reduction is put forward as a useful perspective alongside the more conventional approaches of [[Demand reduction|demand]] and [[supply reduction]].&lt;ref name=&quot;marlatt&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Marlatt |first=G. Alan |title=Harm Reduction: Pragmatic Strategies for Managing High-Risk Behaviors |chapter=Highlights of Harm Reduction |chapterurl=http://books.google.com/books?id=n-XmJZ5cvnwC&amp;pg=PA3 |year=2002 |publisher=Guilford Press |page=3 |isbn=978-1-57230-825-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many advocates argue that prohibitionist laws criminalize people for suffering from a disease and cause harm, for example by obliging drug addicts to obtain drugs of unknown purity from unreliable criminal sources at high prices, increasing the risk of [[overdose]] and death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first1=James A. |last1=Inciardi |first2=Lana D. |last2=Harrison |year=2000 |title=Harm reduction: national and international perspectives |location=Thousand Oaks, California |publisher=SAGE |pages=vii–viii}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its critics are concerned that tolerating risky or illegal behaviour sends a message to the community that these behaviours are acceptable.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.incb.org/pdf/e/ar/2001/incb_report_2001_3_oceania.pdf |title=INCB 2001 Annual Report - Oceania |accessdate=2010-03-28 |page=559 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.encyclopedia.com/doc/1P2-17571220.html |title=Anger as Vice Girls Get Free Condoms |accessdate=2010-04-20 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Decriminalization===
{{Main|Drug liberalization}}
Drug decriminalization calls for reduced control and penalties compared to existing laws. Proponents of drug decriminalization generally support the use of [[Fine (penalty)|fines]] or other punishment to replace [[prison]] terms, and often propose systems whereby illegal drug users who are caught would be fined, but would not receive a permanent criminal record as a result. A central feature of drug decriminalization is the concept of [[harm reduction]].

Drug decriminalization is in some ways an intermediate between prohibition and legalisation, and has been criticised as being &quot;the worst of both worlds&quot;, in that drug sales would still be illegal, thus perpetuating the problems associated with leaving production and distribution of drugs to the criminal underworld, while also failing to discourage illegal drug use by removing the criminal penalties that might otherwise cause some people to choose not to use drugs.{{Citation needed|date=May 2008}}

Currently, [[Portugal]] is the only country in the world that has decriminalized the use of all drugs,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.time.com/time/health/article/0,8599,1893946,00.html | work=Time | first=Maia | last=Szalavitz | title=Drugs in Portugal: Did Decriminalization Work? | date=2009-04-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; meaning anyone caught with any type of drug, if its for consumption, will not be imprisoned. However, Mexico City has decriminalized certain drugs and Greece has just announced that it is going to do so.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

===Legalization===

Drug legalization calls for the end of government-enforced prohibition on the distribution or sale and personal use of specified (or all) currently banned drugs. Proposed ideas range from full legalization which would completely remove all forms of government control, to various forms of regulated legalization, where drugs would be legally available, but under a system of government control which might mean for instance:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tdpf.org.uk/blueprint%20download.htm After the War on Drugs: Blueprint for Regulation], [[Transform Drug Policy Foundation]] (12 Nov 2009)&lt;/ref&gt;
* mandated labels with dosage and medical warnings,
* restrictions on advertising,
* age limitations,
* restrictions on amount purchased at one time,
* requirements on the form in which certain drugs would be supplied,
* ban on sale to intoxicated persons,
* special user licenses to purchase particular drugs.
The regulated legalization system would probably have a range of restrictions for different drugs, depending on their perceived risk, so while some drugs would be sold over the counter in pharmacies or other licensed establishments, drugs with greater risks of harm might only be available for sale on licensed premises where use could be monitored and emergency medical care made available. Examples of drugs with different levels of regulated distribution in most countries include: caffeine (coffee, tea), nicotine (tobacco),&lt;ref&gt;[http://transform-drugs.blogspot.com/2010/02/regulation-saves-lives.html Tobacco regulation: Saving livings vs personal freedom], [[Transform Drug Policy Foundation]] (3 Feb 2010)&lt;/ref&gt; ethyl alcohol (beer, wine, spirits), and antibiotics.

Full legalization is often proposed by groups such as [[libertarians]] who object to drug laws on moral grounds, while regulated legalization is suggested by groups such as [[Law Enforcement Against Prohibition]] who object to the drug laws on the grounds that they fail to achieve their stated aims and instead greatly worsen the problems associated with use of prohibited drugs, but who acknowledge that there are harms associated with currently prohibited drugs which need to be minimized. Not all proponents of drug re-legalization necessarily share a common ethical framework, and people may adopt this viewpoint for a variety of reasons. In particular, favoring drug re-legalization does not imply approval of drug use.&lt;ref&gt;[http://transform-drugs.blogspot.com/2009/12/reformers-are-not-pro-drug-mr-costa.html Reformers and not 'pro-drug' Mr Costa], [[Transform Drug Policy Foundation]] (7 Dec 2009)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Groups advocating change==
[[The Senlis Council]], a European development and policy [[thinktank]], has, since it conception in 2002, advocated that drug addiction should be viewed as a [[public health]] issue rather than a purely criminal matter. The group does not support the [[decriminalisation]] of illegal drugs. Since 2003, the Council has called for the licensing of poppy cultivation in Afghanistan in order to manufacture poppy-based medicines, such as morphine and codeine, and to combat poverty in rural communities, breaking ties with the illicit drugs trade. The [[Senlis Council]] outlined proposals for the implementation of a village based poppy for medicine project and calls for a pilot project for Afghan morphine at the next planting season.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.senliscouncil.net/modules/events/London_event_on_afghanistan/documents/poppy_medicine_technical_dossier Poppy for Medicine]&quot; (June 2007)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Organisations involved in lobbying, research and advocacy==
===Canada===
* [[Le Dain Commission of Inquiry into the Non-Medical Use of Drugs]]

===Europe===
* [[ENCOD|European Coalition for Just and Effective Drug Policies (ENCOD)]] (Branches in Austria, Germany and Norway)
* [[Transform Drug Policy Foundation]]
* [[Drug Equality Alliance (DEA)]]
* [[Release (agency)]] (United Kingdom)
* [http://www.revisiondrugs.org Re:Vision Drug Policy Network] (United Kingdom)

===United States===
* [[American Civil Liberties Union]]&lt;ref&gt;American Civil Liberties Union [http://www.aclu.org/drug-law-reform Drug Law Reform] Accessed 2010-02-15&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Americans for Safe Access]]
* [[Drug Policy Alliance]]
* [[High Times]]
* [[High Times Freedom Fighters]]
* [[Law Enforcement Against Prohibition]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.leap.cc/ LEAP]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Lindesmith Center]]
* [[Marijuana Policy Project]]
* [[MASS CANN/NORML]]
* [[Multidisciplinary Association for Psychedelic Studies]] (MAPS)
* [[National Organization for the Reform of Marijuana Laws]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.norml.org/ NORML]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Students for Sensible Drug Policy]]
* [[Veterans for Medical Marijuana Access]]
* [[November Coalition]] (United States)

==Political parties with drug law reform policies==
* [[Liberal Democrats]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk_politics/1861242.stm | work=BBC News | title=Lib Dems back radical drug policy | date=2002-03-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.libdemvoice.org/libdem-conference-passes-drugs-motion-25314.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;www.tdpf.org.uk/lib%20dem%20drugs%20policy%20paper47.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Green Party of England and Wales]]
* [[Green Party of Aotearoa New Zealand]]&lt;ref&gt;Green Party of Aotearoa New Zealand. [http://www.greens.org.nz/policy/drugs Drug Law Reform Policy - Towards a Harm Reduction Model] Accessed 2010-02-15&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Cannabis Social Club]]
* [[Drug liberalization]]
* [[Drug prohibition law]]
* [[Decriminalization]]
* [[Harm reduction]]
* [[Legalization]]
* [[School district drug policies]]
* [[Students for Sensible Drug Policy]]
* [[Transform Drug Policy Foundation]]
* [[War on drugs]]
* [[Arguments for and against drug prohibition]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
* [http://www.druglibrary.org/schaffer/ Schaffer Library of Drug Policy]

{{drug use}}
{{Public policy}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Drug Policy Reform}}
[[Category:Drug control law]]
[[Category:Drug policy reform| ]]

[[pt:Reforma da política antidrogas]]</text>
      <sha1>j4h8r7b9ekmliy7q5hy5vow9s8m894s</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
