<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Economic interventionism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>436940</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521287366</id>
      <parentid>521178432</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-04T01:09:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Battlecry</username>
        <id>615520</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* See also */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10355">{{about|macroeconomic activity undertaken by a government in market-based economies|economic planning conducted by the state as an alternative mechanism to the market|Economic planning}}
{{Economics sidebar}}
[[Image:Redtape1.JPG|right|thumb|Red tape binds 19th century documents, the origin of phrase &quot;[[red tape]]&quot; to describe economic interventionist laws and regulations]]

'''Economic interventionism''' (sometimes '''state interventionism''') is an [[Economic policy|economic position]] favoring interventions in the market in the public interest on behalf of the government. An '''economic intervention''' is any action taken by a government or an [[international institution]] in a [[market economy]] or market-based [[mixed economy]] in an effort to impact the [[economics|economy]] beyond the basic regulation of fraud and enforcement of contracts and provision of public goods.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Ellen Frankel|first=Paul|title=Laissez Faire in Nineteenth Century Britain: Fact or Myth|journal=Literature of Liberty|year=1980|volume=iii|issue=4|pages=5–38|url=http://www.econlib.org/library/Essays/LtrLbrty/fplLNB1.html|accessdate=5 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Karagiannis|first=Nikolaos|title=KEY ECONOMIC AND POLITICO-INSTITUTIONAL ELEMENTS OF MODERN INTERVENTIONISM.|journal=Social and Economic Studies|year=2001|volume=50|issue=3/4|pages=17–47|jstor=27865245}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;von Mises Ed.1998 10–12&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=von Mises|first=Ludwig|title=INTERVENTIONISM:  AN ECONOMIC ANALYSIS|year=Ed.1998|publisher=The Foundation for Economic Education, Inc.|location=New York|pages=10–12|url=http://www.hacer.org/pdf/Mises09.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Economic intervention]] can be aimed at a variety of political or economic objectives, such as promoting economic growth, increasing employment, raising wages, raising or reducing prices, promoting equality, managing the money supply and interest rates, increasing profits, or addressing [[market failure]]s. 

The term ''intervention'' assumes, on a philosophical level, that the state and economy are separate spheres of activity from each other;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Lu|first=Catherine|title=Intervention|url=http://sage-ereference.com.ezproxy.library.ubc.ca/view/politicaltheory/n233.xml?rskey=lrs7HL&amp;result=1&amp;q=intervention|work=Encyclopedia of Political Theory|publisher=SAGE|accessdate=5 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; therefore the terminology applies to capitalist market-based economies where government action interrupts the market forces at play through regulations, economic policies or subsidies in order to change market outcomes (although intervention does not apply to [[state-owned enterprises]] that operate in the market).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=von Mises|first=Ludwig|title=INTERVENTIONISM: AN ECONOMIC ANALYSIS|year=Ed. 1998|publisher=The Foundation  for Economic Education, Inc|location=New York|pages=10–12|url=http://www.hacer.org/pdf/Mises09.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Indicative planning|Economic planning]] in market economies is sometimes considered to be a form of intervention when it intervenes in the setting of prices and the distribution of goods determined by the market.

==Types of interventions==
Economic interventions common in contemporary market-based economies{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}} targeted [[tax]]es, targeted [[tax credit]]s, [[minimum wage]] legislation, [[union shop]] rules, contracting preferences, direct subsidies to certain classes of producers, [[price support]]s, price caps, [[production quota]]s, import quotas, and [[tariff]]s.
[[Demand management]] and [[Keynesian economics]] ([[helicopter money]]) are sometimes cited as mild forms of economic planning, designed to overcome cyclical instability inherent in market economies, or to make market economies function properly in a desired fashion.

[[Regulation|Government regulation]] over markets and/or firms can also be a type of intervention when it inhibits, corrects or distorts the market mechanism in setting the price of a good or service.

==Effects==
The effects of government economic interventionism are widely disputed. Libertarians and other advocates of free market or laissez-faire economics generally view government interventions as harmful, due to the fallacy of central planning, the law of unintended consequences, and other considerations. Government officials tend to be naturally disposed to seek more power and authority, and the money that usually goes with those things, and this quest often takes the form of economic interventionism which they then seek to justify. Many on the political left are inclined to support this agenda, seeing state economic interventionism as an important means of achieving wealth redistribution or other social engineering goals. A minority of Marxists and those on the far left, meanwhile, feel that government welfare programs in the context of a mixed economy might interfere with the ultimate overthrow of capitalism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gamble et al&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Pierson|first=Chris|title=Marxism and Social Science Ed. Gamble et al.|year=Ed. 1999|publisher=University of Illinois Press|location=Urbana  and Chicago|pages=176–177|url=http://www.revalvaatio.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/gamble_et_all-marxism_and_social_science.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; Political conservatives of the nationalist variety also frequently support economic interventionism as a means of protecting the power and wealth of a country or its people, particularly via advantages granted to industries seen as nationally vital.

Regulatory authorities do not consistently close markets, yet as seen in economic liberalization efforts by states and various institutions ([[International Monetary Fund]] and [[World Bank]])  in Latin America, &quot;...financial liberalization and privatization coincided with democratization&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Karagiannis 2001 19–21&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Karagiannis|first=Nikolaos|title=KEY ECONOMIC AND POLITICO-INSTITUTIONAL ELEMENTS OF MODERN INTERVENTIONISM.|journal=Social and Economic Studies|year=2001|volume=50|issue=3/4|pages=19–21|jstor=27865245}}&lt;/ref&gt; One study suggests that after the [[lost decade]] an increasing &quot;diffusion of regulatory authorities&quot; emerged,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Jordana|first=Jacint|coauthors=David Levi-Faur|title=The Diffusion of Regulatory Capitalism in Latin America: Sectoral and National Channels in the Making of a New Order|journal=Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science|year=2005|month=Mar|volume=598|issue=The Rise of Regulatory Capitalism: The Global Diffusion of a new Order|pages=102–124|jstor=25046082}}&lt;/ref&gt; these actors engaged in restructuring the economies within Latin America. Latin America through the 1980s had undergone a debt crisis and ''hyperinflation'' (during 1989 and 1990). These international  stakeholders restricted the state's economic leverage, and bound it in contract to co-operate.&lt;ref name=&quot;FONDAD&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=FONDAD|title=The Argentine Drama:  A View from the IMF Board|url=fondad.org|work=The Crisis That Was Not Prevented: Argentina, the IMF, and Globalisation|publisher=FONDAD|accessdate=2 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Multiple projects and years of failed attempts, for the Argentine state to comply, the renewal and intervention seemed stalled.  Two key intervention factors that instigated economic progress in Argentina, were substantially increasing privatization and the establishment of a currency board.&lt;ref name=&quot;FONDAD&quot;/&gt;
As one can see this exemplifies global institutions including the [[International Monetary Fund]] and the [[World Bank]]instigate and propagate openness to increase foreign investments and economic development within places including Latin America.&lt;ref name=&quot;von Mises Ed.1998 10–12&quot;/&gt;

'''Why the government intervenes in the market:'''
(Within a Western Liberal Democracy) government officials theoretically weigh the [[cost benefit]] for an intervention for the population or they succumb beneath coercion by a third private party and must take action.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lanchester&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Lanchester|first=John|title=Bankocracy|journal=London Review of Books|date=November 5, 2009|volume=31|issue=21}}&lt;/ref&gt;   Also intervention for economic development is at the discretion and self-interest of the stake holders, the multifarious interpretations of ''progress'' and [[development theory]] could mean.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=von Mises|first=Ludwig|title=INTERVENTIONISM:  AN ECONOMIC ANALYSIS|year=Ed.1998|publisher=The Foundation for Economic Education, Inc.|location=New York|pages=1–51|url=http://www.hacer.org/pdf/Mises09.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; To illustrate this during the 2008 debt crisis; the government and international institutions did not prop [[Lehman Brothers]] up therefore allowing them to file bankruptcy. Days later when [[AIG]] waned towards collapsing, the state spent public money to keep it from falling.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lanchester&quot;/&gt;  These corporations have interconnected interests with the state. Therefore their incentive is to influence the government to designate regulatory policies&lt;ref name=&quot;Lanchester&quot;/&gt; that will not inhibit their accumulation of assets.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gamble et al&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Pierson|first=Chris|title=Marxism and Social Science|year=Ed. 1999|publisher=University of Illinois Press|location=Urbana  and Chicago|pages=176–177|url=http://www.revalvaatio.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/gamble_et_all-marxism_and_social_science.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[American School (economics)]]
*[[Crowding out (economics)|Crowding out]]
*[[Demand management]]
*[[Dirigisme]]
*[[Economic planning]]
*[[Fiscal policy]]
*[[Keynesian economics]]
*[[Market economy]]
*[[Mixed Economy]]
*[[Monetary policy]]
*[[Indicative Planning]]
*[[Regulation]]
*[[Red tape]]

'''References'''

{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Political economy]]
[[Category:Market failure]]
[[Category:Socioeconomics]]
[[Category:Macroeconomics]]

[[bg:Икономически интервенционализъм]]
[[bs:Intervencionizam]]
[[ca:Intervencionisme]]
[[cs:Intervencionismus]]
[[de:Staatsinterventionismus]]
[[es:Intervencionismo]]
[[fr:Interventionnisme]]
[[gl:Intervencionismo]]
[[it:Interventismo (economia)]]
[[he:מעורבות ציבורית]]
[[lt:Intervencionizmas]]
[[pl:Interwencjonizm]]
[[pt:Intervencionismo]]
[[ru:Экономическое вмешательство]]</text>
      <sha1>c8higjxvbt6ttnj8t2oyw27qfbk5qtg</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
