<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Environmentalism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1866009</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522423983</id>
      <parentid>522423386</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-11T03:10:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DASonnenfeld</username>
        <id>2922608</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Add &lt;Green politics sidebar&gt;</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="33627">{{EnvironmentalTopics}}
{{Green politics sidebar}}

'''Environmentalism''' is a broad philosophy, ideology&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www-formal.stanford.edu/jmc/progress/ideology.html |title=Ideology and Sustainability |publisher=Formal.stanford.edu |date= |accessdate=2012-06-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Ronald Bailey from the February 2002 issue |url=http://reason.com/archives/2002/02/01/debunking-green-myths |title=Debunking Green Myths |publisher=Reason.com |date= |accessdate=2012-06-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Donald Gibson. Environmentalism: Ideology and Power. Nova Science Pub Inc. 2003&lt;/ref&gt; and [[social movement]] regarding concerns for environmental [[Conservation movement|conservation]] and improvement of the health of the [[environment (biophysical)|environment]], particularly as the measure for this health seeks to incorporate the concerns of non-human elements. Environmentalism advocates the preservation, restoration and/or improvement of the natural environment, and may be referred to as a movement to control [[pollution]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/environmentalism |title=Environmentalism - Definition and More from the Free Merriam-Webster Dictionary |publisher=Merriam-webster.com |date=2010-08-13 |accessdate=2012-06-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; For this reason, concepts such as a [[land ethic]], [[environmental ethics]], [[biodiversity]], [[ecology]] and the [[biophilia hypothesis]] figure predominantly. At its crux, environmentalism is an attempt to balance relations between humans and the various natural systems on which they depend in such a way that all the components are accorded a proper degree of respect. The exact nature of this balance is controversial and there are many different ways for environmental concerns to be expressed in practice.  Environmentalism and environmental concerns are often represented by the color [[Green#In culture|green]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Light, Dark and Bright Green Environmentalism&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.greendaily.com/2009/04/23/light-dark-and-bright-green-environmentalism/ |title=Light, Dark and Bright Green Environmentalism |accessdate=2009-11-02 |author=Cat Lincoln |year=2009 |month=Spring |publisher=Green Daily}}&lt;/ref&gt; but this association has been appropriated by the marketing industries and is a key tactic of [[greenwashing]].

==Environmentalism as a social movement==
Environmentalism denominates a [[environmental movement|social movement]] that seeks to influence the political process by lobbying, activism, and education in order to protect natural resources and [[ecosystem]]s. An [[environmentalist]] is a person who may speak out about our natural environment and the sustainable management of its resources through changes in public policy or individual behavior. This may include supporting practices such as informed consumption, conservation initiatives, investment in [[renewable energy]], improved efficiencies in the materials economy, transitioning to new accounting paradigms such as [[Ecological economics]] and renewing and revitalizing our connections with non-human life. In various ways (for example, grassroots activism and protests), environmentalists and [[environmental organization]]s seek to give the natural world a stronger voice in human affairs.&lt;ref&gt;Robert Gottlieb, ''Forcing the Spring: The Transformation of the American Environmental Movement'' (2005)&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{{Main|Timeline of history of environmentalism}}

A concern for environmental protection has recurred in diverse forms, in different parts of the world, throughout history. For example, in Europe, [[Edward I of England|King Edward I]] of England banned the burning of [[coal|sea-coal]] by proclamation in [[London]] in 1272, after its smoke had become a problem.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pea-souper&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.epa.gov/history/topics/perspect/london.htm |title=London's Historic 'Pea-Soupers' |accessdate=2006-08-02 |author=David Urbinato |year=1994 |month=Summer |publisher=[[United States Environmental Protection Agency]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Deadly&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pbs.org/now/science/smog.html |title=Deadly Smog |accessdate=2006-08-02 |date=2003-01-17 |publisher=PBS}}&lt;/ref&gt; The fuel was so common in England that this earliest of names for it was acquired because it could be carted away from some shores by the wheelbarrow. Air pollution would continue to be a problem in England, especially later during the [[Industrial Revolution]], and extending into the recent past with the [[Great Smog of 1952]].

===Origins of the modern environmental movement===
In [[Europe]], the [[Industrial Revolution]] gave rise to modern environmental pollution as it is generally understood today. The emergence of great factories and consumption of immense quantities of [[coal]] and other [[fossil fuel]]s gave rise to unprecedented [[air pollution]] and the large volume of industrial [[chemical]] discharges added to the growing load of untreated human waste.&lt;ref name=&quot;Donora&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ametsoc.org/sloan/cleanair/ |title=History of the Clean Air Act |accessdate=2006-02-14 |first=James R. |last=Fleming |coauthors=Bethany R. Knorr |publisher=American Meteorological Society}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first large-scale, modern environmental laws came in the form of the [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|British]] [[Alkali Acts]], passed in 1863, to regulate the deleterious air pollution ([[gaseous]] [[hydrochloric acid]]) given off by the [[Leblanc process]], used to produce [[soda ash]]. Environmentalism grew out of the amenity movement, which was a reaction to [[industrialization]], the growth of cities, and worsening air and [[water pollution]].

In Victorian Britain, an early &quot;Back-to-Nature&quot; movement that anticipated modern environmentalism was advocated by intellectuals such as [[John Ruskin]], [[William Morris]] and [[Edward Carpenter]], who were all against [[consumerism]], [[pollution]] and other activities that were harmful to the natural world.&lt;ref&gt;Gould, Peter C. (1988). ''Early Green Politics'', Brighton,Harvester Press, pgs. 15-19, and [[Derek Wall|Wall, Derek]], (1994) ''Green History: A Reader.'' London,Routledge, pgs. 9-14.&lt;/ref&gt;
Their ideas also inspired various proto-environmental groups in the UK, such as the [[Commons Preservation Society]], the [[Kyrle Society]], the [[Royal Society for the Protection of Birds]] and the [[Garden city movement]], as well as encouraging the [[Socialist League (UK, 1885)|Socialist League]] and [[The Clarion]] movement to advocate measures of [[nature conservation]].&lt;ref&gt;Gould,(1988) pgs. 16, 23-4,36-8,84-6.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:John Muir Cane.JPG|thumb|left|[[John Muir]] in 1907]]
In the [[United States]], the beginnings of an environmental movement can be traced as far back as 1739, though it was not called environmentalism and was still considered conservation until the 1950s. [[Benjamin Franklin]] and other [[Philadelphia]] residents, citing &quot;public rights,&quot; petitioned the Pennsylvania Assembly to stop waste dumping and remove [[tanneries]] from Philadelphia's commercial district. The US movement expanded in the 1800s, out of concerns for protecting the natural resources of the West, with individuals such as [[John Muir]] and [[Henry David Thoreau]] making key philosophical contributions. Thoreau was interested in peoples' relationship with nature and studied this by living close to nature in a simple life. He published his experiences in the book ''[[Walden]],'' which argues that people should become intimately close with nature. Muir came to believe in nature's inherent right, especially after spending time hiking in [[Yosemite Valley]] and studying both the ecology and geology. He successfully lobbied congress to form [[Yosemite National Park]] and went on to set up the [[Sierra Club]]. The conservationist principles as well as the belief in an inherent right of nature were to become the bedrock of modern environmentalism.

In the 20th century, environmental ideas continued to grow in popularity and recognition. Efforts were starting to be made to save some wildlife, particularly the [[American Bison]]. The death of the last [[Passenger Pigeon]] as well as the endangerment of the American Bison helped to focus the minds of conservationists and popularize their concerns. In 1916 the [[National Park Service]] was founded by US President [[Woodrow Wilson]].

The Nazis had elements which were supportive of animal rights, zoos and wildlife,&lt;ref name=&quot;BHTFSN153&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author= Thomas R. DeGregori|title= [[Bountiful Harvest|Bountiful Harvest: Technology, Food Safety, and the Environment]]|publisher= Cato Institute|location= |year= 2002|pages= p153|isbn= 1-930865-31-7|oclc=|doi=}}&lt;/ref&gt; and took several measures to ensure their protection.&lt;ref name=&quot;RA132&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author= Arnold Arluke, Clinton Sanders|title= Regarding Animals|publisher= Temple University Press|location= |year= 1996|pages= p132|isbn= 1-56639-441-4|oclc=|doi=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1933 the government enacted a stringent animal-protection law.&lt;ref&gt;Hartmut M. Hanauske-Abel, ''[http://www.bmj.com/cgi/content/full/313/7070/1453#R101 Not a slippery slope or sudden subversion: German medicine and National Socialism in 1933]'', BMJ 1996; pp. 1453–1463 (7 December)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;www_kaltio_fi5&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.kaltio.fi/index.php?494 | title = kaltio.fi | accessdate = 2007-08-15 | publisher = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many [[List of Nazi Party leaders and officials|NSDAP leaders]] including [[Adolf Hitler]] and [[Hermann Göring]] were supporters of animal protection. Several Nazis were [[environmentalists]] (notably [[Rudolf Hess]]), and species protection and [[animal welfare]] were significant issues in the regime.&lt;ref name=&quot;NWC5&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author= Robert Proctor|title= The Nazi War on Cancer|publisher= Princeton University Press|location=|year= 1999|pages= p5|isbn= 0-691-07051-2|oclc=|doi=}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Heinrich Himmler]] made efforts to ban the hunting of animals.&lt;ref name=&quot;HMG278&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author= Martin Kitchen|title= A History of Modern Germany, 1800-2000|publisher= Blackwell Publishing|location=|year= 2006|pages= p278|isbn= 1-4051-0040-0|oclc=|doi=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Göring was an animal lover and [[conservation movement|conservationist]].&lt;ref name=&quot;HWJ79&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author= Seymour Rossel|title= The Holocaust: The World and the Jews, 1933-1945|publisher= Behrman House, Inc|location= |year= 1992|pages= p79|isbn= 0-87441-526-8|oclc=|doi=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The current animal welfare laws in [[Germany]] are more or less modification of the laws introduced by the National Socialist regime.&lt;ref name=&quot;RRNM92&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author= Bruce Braun, Noel Castree|title= Remaking Reality: Nature at the Millenium&lt;!-- PLEASE NOTE that &quot;Millenium&quot; is deliberately spelled incorrectly here, reflecting the mistake on the external page. --&gt;|publisher= Routledge|location= |year= 1998|pages= p92|isbn=0-415-14493-0|oclc=|doi=}}{{sic}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1935, the regime enacted the &quot;Reich Nature Protection Act&quot;. The concept of the ''Dauerwald'' (best translated as the &quot;perpetual forest&quot;) which included concepts such as [[forest management]] and protection was promoted and efforts were also made to curb [[air pollution]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://muse.jhu.edu/login?uri=/journals/technology_and_culture/v048/48.1olsen.html JONATHAN OLSEN &quot;How Green Were the Nazis? Nature, Environment, and Nation in the Third Reich (review)&quot;] Technology and Culture – Volume 48, Number 1, January 2007, pp. 207–208&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.h-net.org/reviews/showrev.cgi?path=163701165517304 Review of Franz-Josef Brueggemeier, Marc Cioc, and Thomas Zeller, eds, &quot;How Green Were the Nazis?: Nature, Environment, and Nation in the Third Reich&quot;] Wilko Graf von Hardenberg, H-Environment, H-Net Reviews, October, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1949, ''[[A Sand County Almanac]]'' by [[Aldo Leopold]] was published. It explained Leopold’s belief that humankind should have moral respect for the environment and that it is unethical to harm it. The book is sometimes called the most influential book on conservation.

Throughout the 1950s, 1960s, 1970s and beyond, photography was used to enhance public awareness of the need for protecting land and recruiting members to environmental organizations. [[David Brower]], [[Ansel Adams]] and [[Nancy Newhall]] created the Sierra Club Exhibit Format Series, which helped raise public environmental awareness and brought a rapidly increasing flood of new members to the Sierra Club and to the environmental movement in general. &quot;This Is Dinosaur&quot; edited by [[Wallace Stegner]] with photographs by [[Martin Litton (environmentalist)|Martin Litton]] and [[Philip Hyde (photographer)|Philip Hyde]] prevented the building of dams within [[Dinosaur National Monument]] by becoming part of a new kind of activism called environmentalism that combined the conservationist ideals of Thoreau, Leopold and Muir with hard-hitting advertising, lobbying, book distribution, letter writing campaigns, and more. The powerful use of photography in addition to the written word for conservation dated back to the creation of [[Yosemite National Park]], when photographs convinced Abraham Lincoln to preserve the beautiful glacier carved landscape for all time. The Sierra Club Exhibit Format Series galvanized public opposition to building dams in the [[Grand Canyon]] and protected many other national treasures. The Sierra Club often led a coalition of many environmental groups including the [[The Wilderness Society (United States)|Wilderness Society]] and many others. After a focus on preserving wilderness in the 1950s and 1960s, the Sierra Club and other groups broadened their focus to include such issues as air and water pollution, population control, and curbing the exploitation of natural resources.

In 1962, ''[[Silent Spring]]'' by American biologist [[Rachel Carson]] was published. The book cataloged the environmental impacts of the indiscriminate spraying of [[DDT]] in the US and questioned the logic of releasing large amounts of chemicals into the environment without fully understanding their effects on ecology or human health. The book suggested that DDT and other pesticides may cause [[cancer]] and that their agricultural use was a threat to wildlife, particularly birds.&lt;ref name=&quot;Silent Spring&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=[[Silent Spring]] |first=Rachel |last=Carson |authorlink=Rachel Carson |year=1962 |publisher=[[Houghton Mifflin]] |location=[[Boston]] |isbn=0-8093-2218-8}}{{Page needed|date=September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The resulting public concern led to the creation of the [[United States Environmental Protection Agency]] in 1970 which subsequently banned the agricultural use of DDT in the US in 1972. The limited use of DDT in [[Vector (epidemiology)|disease vector]] control continues to this day in certain parts of the world and remains controversial. The book's legacy was to produce a far greater awareness of environmental issues and interest into how people affect the environment. With this new interest in environment came interest in problems such as air pollution and petroleum spills, and environmental interest grew. New pressure groups formed, notably [[Greenpeace]] and [[Friends of the Earth]], as well as notable local organizations such as the [[Wyoming Outdoor Council]], which was founded in 1967.
[[File:The Earth seen from Apollo 17.jpg|thumb|The historic [[The Blue Marble|Blue Marble]] photograph. Environmentalism is a concern for humanity's impact on the Earth and its natural systems.]]

===1970s===
In the 1970s the environmental movement gained rapid speed in the U.S. and around the world. The [[Chipko movement]] was formed in India; influenced by [[Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi|Mohandas Gandhi]], they set up peaceful resistance to [[deforestation]] by literally hugging trees (leading to the term &quot;tree huggers&quot;). Their peaceful methods of protest and slogan &quot;ecology is permanent economy&quot; were very influential. 

Another milestone in the movement was the creation of an [[Earth Day]]. Earth Day was first observed in [[San Francisco]] and other cities on March 21, 1970, the first day of Spring. It was created to give awareness to environmental issues. On March 21, 1971, United Nations Secretary-General U Thant spoke of a [[spaceship Earth]] on Earth Day, hereby referring to the [[ecosystem services]] the earth supplies to us, and hence our obligation to protect it (and with it, ourselves). Earth Day is now coordinated globally by the [[Earth Day Network]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.earthday.net/ |title=Resource temporarily unavailable |publisher=Earthday.net |date= |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is celebrated in more than 175 countries every year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://chemistry.about.com/od/environmentalchemistry/f/earthday.htm |title=What Is Earth Day? |publisher=Chemistry.about.com |date=2012-04-15 |accessdate=2012-06-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The UN's first major conference on international environmental issues, the [[United Nations Conference on the Human Environment]] (also known as the Stockholm Conference), was held on June 5–16, 1972. It marked a turning point in the development of international environmental politics.&lt;ref name=&quot;Baylis3&quot;&gt;John Baylis, Steve Smith. 2005. The Globalization of World Politics (3rd ed). Oxford. Oxford University Press. P.454-455&lt;/ref&gt;

By the mid-1970s, many felt that people were on the edge of environmental catastrophe. The [[Back-to-the-land movement]] started to form and ideas of environmental ethics joined with [[anti-Vietnam War]] sentiments and other political issues. These individuals lived outside normal society and started to take on some of the more radical environmental theories such as [[deep ecology]]. Around this time more mainstream environmentalism was starting to show force with the signing of the [[Endangered Species Act]] in 1973 and the formation of [[CITES]] in 1975. Significant amendments were also enacted to the United States [[Clean Air Act (United States)|Clean Air Act]]&lt;ref&gt;Clean Air Act Extension of 1970, {{usstat|84|1676}}, {{uspl|91|604}}, 1970-12-31.&lt;/ref&gt;  and [[Clean Water Act]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.glin.gov/download.action?fulltextId=68261&amp;documentId=70515&amp;glinID=70515 Pub.L. 95-217], December 27, 1977.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1979, [[James Lovelock]], a British scientist, published ''Gaia: A new look at life on Earth'', which put forth the [[Gaia Hypothesis]]; it proposes that life on [[Earth]] can be understood as a single organism. This became an important part of the [[Deep Green Resistance|Deep Green]] ideology. Throughout the rest of the history of environmentalism there has been debate and argument between more radical followers of this Deep Green ideology and more mainstream environmentalists.

===1980s===

During the 1980s the growing awareness of global warming and other climate change issues brought environmentalism into greater public debate. In 1986 the international conservation organisation the World Wildlife Fund renamed itself the [[Worldwide Fund For Nature]] to reflect a shift to a more strategic approach. Still known as WWF, however, the organisation brought together religious authorities representing the five major world religions (Buddhism, Christianity, Hinduism, Islam, and Judaism) to prepare the 1986 Assisi Declarations. These theological statements, published by the WWF and UNEP, identified the responsibilities towards the care of nature expected of followers of each religion thus providing spiritual motivation for environmental action. The full texts, with additional similar declarations from Bahá’ísm, Jainism, Shintoism, Sikhism and Zoroastrianism were later included in the 2003 World Bank publication 'Faith In Conservation'.&lt;ref&gt;[http://siteresources.worldbank.org/EXTDEVDIALOGUE/Resources/Faith_conservation.pdf] Faith In Conservation, Martin Palmer &amp; Victoria Finlay, World Bank Publications 2003 (downloadable PDF retrieved 12-06-12.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Environmentalism today===
Environmentalism has also changed to deal with new issues such as [[global warming]], [[overpopulation]] and [[genetic engineering]]. Many youth of today's society have become more aware of the state of the planet and are deeming themselves environmentalists. School Eco Clubs are now working to create new ideals for the future through sustainable schools and other minor changes in student lives like buying organic food, clothing and personal care items. In the future, many of the jobs opening up will have environmentalist aspects.
{{expand section|date=September 2011}}

==Environmental movement==
{{Main|Environmental movement}}
[[File:Air .pollution 1.jpg|thumb|right|Before [[flue-gas desulfurization]] was installed, the [[air pollution|air-polluting]] emissions from this power plant in [[New Mexico]] contained excessive amounts of [[sulfur dioxide]].]]

The [[environmental movement]] (a term that sometimes includes the [[conservation movement|conservation]] and [[Green politics|green]] movements) is a diverse scientific, [[Social movement|social]], and [[political movement]]. In general terms, environmentalists advocate the [[sustainability|sustainable]] management of resources, and the protection (and restoration, when necessary) of the [[natural environment]] through changes in public policy and individual behavior. In its recognition of humanity as a participant in ecosystems, the movement is centered around [[ecology]], [[health]], and [[human rights]]. Though the movement is represented by a range of organizations, because of the inclusion of environmentalism in the classroom curriculum,&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig Kridel&quot;&gt;{{Cite book
  | author = Craig Kridel
  | title = Encyclopedia of Curriculum Studies
  | publisher = Sage Publications, Inc
  | page = 341
  | date = 2010-02-16
  | isbn = 978-1-4129-5883-7
  | url = http://books.google.com/?id=GgMyFqxsXWoC&amp;pg=PA341&amp;dq=environmentalism+in+the+classroom+curriculum&amp;q=environmentalism%20in%20the%20classroom%20curriculum
  | accessdate = 2010-04-16 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;LessonPlanet-Sinsel&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | author = Jennifer Sinsel
  | title = Earth Day Activities
  | publisher = Lesson Planet
  | date = 2010-04-15
  | url = http://www.lessonplanet.com/directory_articles/elementary_science_lesson_plans/15_April_2010/360/earth_day_activities
  | accessdate = 2010-04-16 }}
&lt;/ref&gt; the environmental movement has a younger demographic than is common in other social movements (see [[green seniors]]).

Environmentalism as a movement covers broad areas of institutional oppression. Examples of these oppressions are: consumption of ecosystems and natural resources into waste, dumping waste into disadvantaged communities, air pollution, water pollution, weak infrastructure, exposure of organic life to toxins, mono-culture, anti-polythene drive (jhola movement) and various other focuses. Because of these divisions, the environmental movement can be categorized into these primary focuses: [[Environmental Science]], Environmental Activism, Environmental Advocacy, and [[Environmental Justice]].

==Free market environmentalism==
{{Main|Free-market environmentalism}}

Free market environmentalism is a theory that argues that the [[free market]], [[property rights]], and [[tort]] law provide the best tools to preserve the health and [[sustainability]] of the environment. It considers environmental stewardship to be natural, as well as the expulsion of polluters and other aggressors through individual and [[class action]].&lt;ref name=Stroup&gt;
{{Cite journal |url=http://www.econlib.org/library/Enc/FreeMarketEnvironmentalism.html |last=Stroup |first=Richard L. |title=Free-Market Environmentalism |year=2008 |publisher=The Library of Economics and Liberty |archiveurl=http://www.nesgeorgia.org/files/free_market_environmentalism.pdf |archivedate=2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Evangelical environmentalism==
{{Main|Evangelical environmentalism}}
Evangelical environmentalism is an environmental movement in the United States in which some Evangelicals have emphasized biblical mandates concerning humanity's role as steward and subsequent responsibility for the caretaking of Creation. While the movement has focused on different environmental issues, it is best known for its focus of addressing climate action from a biblically grounded theological perspective. The Evangelical Climate Initiative argues that human-induced climate change will have severe consequences and impact the poor the hardest, and that God's mandate to Adam to care for the Garden of Eden also applies to evangelicals today, and that it is therefore a moral obligation to work to mitigate climate impacts and support communities in adapting to change.&lt;ref name=&quot;eci-call-to-action&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Climate Change: An Evangelical Call to Action|url=http://christiansandclimate.org/learn/call-to-action/|work=christiansandclimate.org|publisher=Evangelical Climate Initiative|accessdate=18 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Preservation and conservation==
'''Environmental preservation''' in the United States and other parts of the world, including Australia, is viewed as the setting aside of natural resources to prevent damage caused by contact with humans or by certain human activities, such as logging, mining, hunting, and fishing, often to replace them with new human activities such as tourism and recreation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
  | last = Cunningham
  | first = William P.
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors = et al.
  | title = Environmental encyclopedia
  | publisher = Gale Research
  | year = 1998
  | location =
  | pages =
  | url =
  | doi =
  | id =
  | isbn = 0-8103-9314-X }}&lt;/ref&gt; Regulations and laws may be enacted for the preservation of natural resources.

==Environmental organizations and conferences==
{{Main|List of environmental organizations}}
[[File:Reefdoctor-work sation.jpg|thumb|Reef doctor work station in [[Tsifota|Ifaty]], [[Madagascar]]]]

Environmental organizations can be global, regional, national or local; they can be government-run or private ([[NGO]]). Environmentalist activity exists in almost every country. Moreover, groups dedicated to community development and social justice also focus on environmental concerns.

There are some volunteer organizations. For example [[Ecoworld]] and [[Paryawaran Sachetak Samiti]] which is about the environment and is based in team work and volunteer work. Some US environmental organizations, among them the [[Natural Resources Defense Council]] and the [[Environmental Defense Fund]], specialize in bringing lawsuits (a tactic seen as particularly useful in that country). Other groups, such as the US-based [[National Wildlife Federation]], [[the Nature Conservancy]], and [[The Wilderness Society (United States)|The Wilderness Society]], and global groups like the [[World Wide Fund for Nature]] and [[Friends of the Earth]], disseminate information, participate in [[Hearing (law)|public hearings]], [[Lobbying|lobby]], [[Demonstration (people)|stage demonstrations]], and may purchase land for [[Nature reserve|preservation]]. Statewide nonprofit organizations such as the [[Wyoming Outdoor Council]] often collaborate with these national organizations and employ similar strategies. Smaller groups, including [[Wildlife Conservation International]], conduct research on [[endangered species]] and [[ecosystems]]. More radical organizations, such as [[Greenpeace]], [[Earth First!]], and the [[Earth Liberation Front]], have more directly opposed actions they regard as environmentally harmful. While [[Greenpeace]] is devoted to nonviolent confrontation as a means of bearing witness to environmental wrongs and bringing issues into the public realm for debate, the underground ''Earth Liberation Front'' engages in the clandestine destruction of property, the release of caged or penned animals, and other criminal acts. Such tactics are regarded as unusual within the movement, however.

On an international level, concern for the environment was the subject of a [[United Nations Conference on the Human Environment]] in Stockholm in 1972, attended by 114 nations. Out of this meeting developed [[UNEP]] ([[United Nations Environment Programme]]) and the follow-up [[Earth Summit|United Nations Conference on Environment and Development]] in 1992. Other international organizations in support of environmental policies development include the [[Commission for Environmental Cooperation]] (as part of [[NAFTA]]), the [[European Environment Agency]] (EEA), and the [[Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change]] (IPCC).

==Usage in popular culture==
From at least 1946,{{citation needed|date=July 2012}} American comics with an environmental, [[Conservation movement|conservation]] or [[wilderness|outdoor]] theme have appeared; including ''[[Mark Trail]]'', [[Smokey the Bear]] and ''[[Woodsy Owl]]''.

==Criticisms==
{{Unreferenced section|date=December 2010}}

Criticism of environmentalism tend to fall into two major categories: [[environmental skepticism]] and [[anti-environmentalism]]. Environmental skeptics, such as [[Bjørn Lomborg]] (the author of [[The Skeptical Environmentalist]]) dispute the claims of environmentalists, claiming they are either inaccurate or exaggerated. Anti-environmentalists, on the other hand, accept many of the claims made by environmentalists while simultaneously accepting that change is inevitable, regardless of cause and speed. They do not deny the impact of humanity, but they dispute the argument that humanity can kill the planet, citing life's several billion year history as evidence that it is more resilient than many environmentalists realize.

==See also==
{{Portal box|Sustainable development|Environment|Earth sciences|Ecology|Sociology}}
{{div col|cols=2}}
* [[Conservation ethic]]
* [[Conservation movement]]
* [[Curbing fossil fuel usage]]
* [[Do it yourself]] (DIY)
* [[Ecofeminism]]
* [[Ecology movement]]
* [[Environmental movement]]
* [[Environmental organization]]s
* [[Environmental sociology]]
* [[Environmentalism in film and television]]
* [[Environmentalism in music]]
* [[Evangelical environmentalism]]
* [[Free-market environmentalism]]
* [[Green politics]] 
* [[Human impact on the environment]]
* [[List of environmental websites]]
* [[Permaculture]]
* [[Planetary boundaries]]
* [[Positive environmentalism]]
* [[Satya]]
* [[Stewardship (theology)]]
* [[Sustainability and systemic change resistance]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* Daynes, Byron W., and Glen Sussman, eds. ''White House Politics and the Environment: Franklin D. Roosevelt to George W. Bush'' (Texas A&amp;M University Press; 2010) 300 pages; evaluates how 12 presidents helped or hindered the cause of environmental protection.
* {{cite web
 | last = Hall
 | first = Jeremiah
 | authorlink =
 | date =
 | url = http://www.mtmultipleuse.org/endangered/esahistory.htm
 | title = History Of The Environmental Movement
 | work =
 | publisher =
 | accessdate = 2006-11-25
}}
* {{cite web
 | last = Kovarik
 | first = William
 | authorlink =
 | date =
 | url = http://www.environmentalhistory.org/
 | title = Environmental History Timeline
 | work =
 | publisher =
 | accessdate = 2006-11-25
}}
* {{cite web
 | last =Martell
 | first = Luke
 | authorlink =
 | date =
 | url = http://www.sussex.ac.uk/Users/ssfa2/ecology.html
 | title = Ecology and Society: An Introduction
 | work =
 | publisher = Polity Press, 1994
 | accessdate =
}}
* de Steiguer, J. Edward.  2006.  ''The Origins of Modern Environmental Thought.'' The [[University of Arizona Press]].  Tucson.  246 pp.
* [[John McCormick (political scientist)|John McCormick]]. 1995. The Global Environmental Movement. John Wiley. London. 312 pp.
* Marco Verweij and Michael Thompson (eds), 2006, ''Clumsy Solutions for a Complex World: Governance, Politics and Plural Perceptions'', Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan, ISBN 978-0-230-00230-2
* [[World Bank Group|World Bank]], 2003, [http://go.worldbank.org/3I9K0DUDC0 &quot;Sustainable Development in a Dynamic World: Transforming Institutions, Growth, and Quality of Life&quot;], World Development Report 2003, [[International Bank for Reconstruction and Development]] and Oxford University Press.
* Keith M. Woodhouse. &quot;The Politics of Ecology: Environmentalism and Liberalism in the 1960s,&quot; ''Journal for the Study of Radicalism,'' Volume 2, Number 2, 2009, pp.&amp;nbsp;53–84

==External links==
{{commons category}}
*{{dmoz|Society/Issues/Environment|Environment}}
* [http://www.kucoba.com/2011/07/go-green-selamatkan-nafas-bumi.html Go Green Indonesia]
{{Environmental science}}
{{Sustainability}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2011}}

[[Category:Environment| ]]
[[Category:Environmentalism| ]]
[[Category:Green politics]]
[[Category:Habitat (ecology) terminology]]

{{Link FA|eu}}

[[als:Umweltschutz]]
[[ar:حماية البيئة]]
[[ast:Ecoloxismu]]
[[ca:Ecologisme]]
[[cs:Environmentalismus]]
[[cy:Amgylcheddaeth]]
[[da:Økologisme]]
[[de:Ökologismus]]
[[eo:Naturprotektismo]]
[[eu:Ekologismo]]
[[fa:محیط زیست‌گرایی]]
[[fr:Écologisme]]
[[ko:생태주의]]
[[hr:Zaštita okoliša]]
[[id:Pelestarian lingkungan hidup]]
[[he:סביבתנות]]
[[ka:გარემოს დაცვა]]
[[la:Oecologismus]]
[[hu:Környezetvédelem]]
[[ja:環境主義]]
[[pt:Ecologismo]]
[[qu:Muyuriq pacha amachay]]
[[ru:Энвайронментализм]]
[[simple:Environmentalism]]
[[sk:Environmentalizmus]]
[[sr:Енвиронментализам]]
[[fi:Ympäristönsuojelu]]
[[sv:Ekologism]]
[[ta:சூழலியம்]]
[[tg:Дифоъ аз муҳити зист]]
[[tr:Çevrecilik]]
[[uk:Енвайронменталізм]]
[[zh:环境保护主义]]</text>
      <sha1>tdyqa9orxh6nlmvs8s1n8frf4rx37zn</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
