<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Epistemology</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9247</id>
    <restrictions>move=:edit=</restrictions>
    <revision>
      <id>521772179</id>
      <parentid>521640604</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-07T03:22:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>FrescoBot</username>
        <id>9021902</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Bot: [[User:FrescoBot/Links|link syntax/spacing]] and minor changes</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="51914">{{Philosophy-sidebar}}
{{redirect|Theory of knowledge|the [[International Baccalaureate]] course|Theory of knowledge (IB course)}}
'''Epistemology''' {{IPAc-en|audio=En-uk-epistemology.ogg|ɪ-|ˌ|p|ɪ|s|t|ɪ-|ˈ|m|ɒ|l|ə|dʒ|i}} ({{ety|gre|''[[wiktionary:ἐπιστήμη|ἐπιστήμη]]'' (epistēmē)|knowledge, understanding||''[[wiktionary:λόγος|λόγος]]'' ([[logos]])|study of}}) is the branch of [[philosophy]] concerned with the nature and scope (limitations) of [[knowledge]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last1 = G &amp; C. Merriam Co. | authorlink1 = Merriam-Webster | title = Webster's Revised Unabridged Dictionary | edition = 1913 | editors = Noah Porter | publisher = G &amp; C. Merriam Co. | year = 1913 | page = 501 | url = http://machaut.uchicago.edu/?resource=Webster%27s&amp;word=epistemology&amp;use1913=on | accessdate = 2012-05-13 | quote = E*pis`te*mol&quot;o*gy (?), n. [Gr. knowledge + -logy.] The theory or science of the method or grounds of knowledge.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Encyclopedia of Philosophy, Volume 3, 1967, Macmillan, Inc.&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;br&gt;It addresses mainly the following questions:
* What is knowledge?
* How is knowledge acquired?
* To what extent is it possible for a given subject or entity to be known?

Much of the debate in this field has focused on [[Philosophical analysis|analyzing]] the nature of knowledge and how it relates to connected notions such as [[truth]], [[belief]], and [[Theory of justification|justification]].  One view is the objection that there is very little or no knowledge at all—[[skepticism]].  The field is sometimes referred to as the ''theory of knowledge.''

The term was introduced by the Scottish philosopher [[James Frederick Ferrier]] (1808–1864).&lt;ref&gt;Encyclopaedia Britannica Online, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

==Knowledge==
{{Certainty}}

===Knowledge that, knowledge how, and knowledge by acquaintance===
In this article, and in epistemology in general, the kind of knowledge usually discussed is [[propositional knowledge]], also known as &quot;knowledge that.&quot; This is distinct from &quot;[[Know-how|knowledge how]]&quot; and &quot;acquaintance-knowledge.&quot; For example: in mathematics, it is known ''that'' 2 + 2 = 4, but there is also knowing ''how'' to add two numbers and knowing a ''person'' (e.g., oneself), ''place'' (e.g., one's hometown), ''thing'' (e.g., cars), or ''activity'' (e.g., addition). Some{{Who|date=May 2011}} philosophers think there is an important distinction between &quot;knowing that,&quot; &quot;knowing how,&quot; and &quot;acquaintance-knowledge,&quot; with epistemology primarily interested in the first.&lt;ref&gt;It is sometimes suggested that these distinctions are recognized linguistically in some languages, even if not in modern Standard English (N.B. some languages related to English have been said to retain these verbs, e.g. [[Scots language|Scots]]: &quot;wit&quot; and &quot;[[Wiktionary:ken#Scots|ken]]&quot;).  In French, Portuguese and Spanish, ''to know (a person)'' is translated using ''connaître,'' ''conhecer,'' and ''conocer,'' respectively, whereas ''to know (how to do something)'' is translated using ''savoir'', ''saber'', and ''saber''. Modern Greek has the verbs ''γνωρίζω'' (gnorízo) and ''ξέρω'' (kséro). Italian has the verbs ''conoscere'' and ''sapere'' and the nouns for ''knowledge'' are ''conoscenza'' and ''sapienza.'' German has the verbs ''kennen'' and ''wissen.''  ''Wissen'' implies knowing a fact, ''kennen'' implies knowing in the sense of being acquainted with and having a working knowledge of; there is also a noun derived from ''kennen,'' namely ''erkennen,'' which has been said to imply knowledge in the form of recognition or acknowledgment. The verb itself implies a process: you have to go from one state to another, from a state of &quot;not-''erkennen''&quot; to a state of true ''erkennen.'' This verb seems to be the most appropriate in terms of describing the &quot;episteme&quot; in one of the modern European languages, hence the German name &quot;[[:de:Erkenntnistheorie|Erkenntnistheorie]].&quot; The theoretical interpretation and significance of these linguistic issues remain controversial.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Bertrand Russell]] is famous for distinguishing &quot;[[knowledge by description]]&quot; (a form of knowledge that) and &quot;[[knowledge by acquaintance]]&quot; in ''Problems of Philosophy.'' [[Gilbert Ryle]] is often credited with emphasizing the distinction between knowing how and knowing that in ''The Concept of Mind.'' In ''Personal Knowledge,'' [[Michael Polanyi]] argues for the epistemological relevance of knowledge how and knowledge that; using the example of the act of balance involved in riding a [[bicycle]], he suggests that the theoretical knowledge of the [[physics]] involved in maintaining a state of [[Bicycle and motorcycle dynamics#Balance|balance]] cannot substitute for the practical knowledge of how to ride, and that it is important to understand how both are established and grounded. This position is essentially Ryle's, who argued that a failure to acknowledge the distinction between knowledge that and knowledge how leads to vicious regresses.

In recent times, some epistemologists ([[Ernest Sosa|Sosa]], [[John Greco (philosopher)|Greco]], [[Jonathan Kvanvig|Kvanvig]], [[Linda Trinkaus Zagzebski|Zagzebski]]) have argued that epistemology should evaluate people's properties (i.e., intellectual virtues) and not just the properties of propositions or propositional mental attitudes.{{Citation needed|date=May 2012}}

===Belief===
{{Main|Belief}}

[[File:Classical-Definition-of-Kno.svg|thumb|[[Euler diagram]] representing a definition of knowledge.]]
Statements of &quot;belief&quot; sometimes mean the speaker has faith that something would prove to be useful or successful in some sense—perhaps the speaker might &quot;believe in&quot; his or her favorite football team.  This is not the kind of belief usually addressed within epistemology. The kind dealt with is when &quot;to believe something&quot; simply means any cognitive content held as true in spite of the absence of proof or even evidence.  For example, to believe that the sky is blue is to think that the proposition &quot;The sky is blue&quot; is true even if the sky is visibly red.

===Truth===
{{Main|Truth}}
Whether someone's belief is true is not a prerequisite for (its) belief.  On the other hand, if something is actually ''known'', then it categorically cannot be false.  For example, a person believes that a particular bridge is safe enough to support him, and attempts to cross it; unfortunately, the bridge collapses under his weight. It could be said that he ''believed'' that the bridge was safe, but that this belief was mistaken. It would ''not'' be accurate to say that he ''knew'' that the bridge was safe, because plainly it was not. By contrast, if the bridge actually supported his weight then he might say he &quot;thought&quot; that the bridge was safe, and now after proving it to himself, he knows.

Epistemologists argue over whether belief is the proper [[truth-bearer]].  Some would rather describe knowledge as a system of justified true propositions, and others as a system of justified true sentences.  But belief is the most commonly invoked truth bearer, since [[Plato]]'s day.{{Citation needed|date=November 2011}}
{{See also|Criteria of truth}}

===Justification===
In many of [[Plato]]'s dialogues, such as the ''[[Meno]]'', and in particular the ''[[Theaetetus (dialogue)|Theaetetus]]'', [[Socrates]] considers a number of theories as to what knowledge is, the last being that knowledge is true belief that has been &quot;given an account of&quot; — meaning explained or defined in some way. According to the theory that knowledge is justified true belief, in order to know that a given proposition is true, one must not only believe the relevant true proposition, but one must also have a good reason for doing so. One implication of this would be that no one would gain knowledge just by believing something that happened to be true. For example, an ill person with no medical training, but with a generally optimistic attitude, might believe that he will recover from his illness quickly. Nevertheless, even if this belief turned out to be true, the patient would not have ''known'' that he would get well since his belief lacked justification.
The definition of knowledge as justified true belief was widely accepted until the 1960s. At this time, a paper written by the American philosopher [[Edmund Gettier]] provoked major widespread discussion.  See [[theory of justification|theories of justification]]  for other views on the idea.

===The Gettier problem===
{{Main|Gettier problem}}

Edmund Gettier is remembered for his 1963 argument, which called into question the theory of knowledge that had been dominant among philosophers for thousands of years.&lt;ref name=gettier&gt;
{{cite journal
|author=Gettier, Edmund
|year= 1963
|title=Is Justified True Belief Knowledge?
|jstor=3326922
|journal = Analysis
|volume = 23
|issue=6
|pages=121–23
|doi = 10.2307/3326922
}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In a few pages, Gettier argued that there are situations in which one's belief may be justified and true, yet fail to count as knowledge.  That is, Gettier contended that while justified belief in a true proposition is necessary for that proposition to be known, it is not sufficient.  As in the diagram above, a true proposition can be believed by an individual (purple region) but still not fall within the &quot;knowledge&quot; category (yellow region).

According to Gettier, there are certain circumstances in which one does not have knowledge, even when all of the above conditions are met.  Gettier proposed two [[thought experiment]]s, which have come to be known as &quot;Gettier cases,&quot; as [[counterexample]]s to the classical account of knowledge.  One of the cases involves two men, Smith and Jones, who are awaiting the results of their applications for the same job.  Each man has ten coins in his pocket.  Smith has excellent reasons to believe that Jones will get the job and, furthermore, knows that Jones has ten coins in his pocket (he recently counted them).  From this Smith infers, &quot;the man who will get the job has ten coins in his pocket.&quot;  However, Smith is unaware that he also has ten coins in his own pocket.  Furthermore, Smith, not Jones, is going to get the job.  While Smith has strong evidence to believe that Jones will get the job, he is wrong.  Smith has a justified true belief that a man with ten coins in his pocket will get the job; however, according to Gettier, Smith does not ''know'' that a man with ten coins in his pocket will get the job, because Smith's belief is &quot;...true by virtue of the number of coins in ''Jones's'' pocket, while Smith does not know how many coins are in Smith's pocket, and bases his belief...on a count of the coins in Jones's pocket, whom he falsely believes to be the man who will get the job.&quot; (see&lt;ref name = gettier/&gt; p.&amp;nbsp;122.) These cases fail to be knowledge because the subject's belief is justified, but only happens to be true by virtue of luck. In other words, he made the correct choice (in this case predicting an outcome) for the wrong reasons. This example is similar to those often given when discussing belief and truth, wherein a person's belief of what will happen can coincidentally be correct without them having the actual knowledge to base it on.

====Responses to Gettier====
The responses to Gettier have been varied. Usually, they have involved substantive attempts to provide a definition of knowledge different from the classical one, either by recasting knowledge as justified true belief with some additional fourth condition, or as something else altogether.

=====Infallibilism, indefeasibility=====
In one response to Gettier, the American philosopher [[Richard Kirkham]] has argued that the only definition of knowledge that could ever be immune to all counterexamples is the [[infallibilism|infallibilist]] one.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.centenary.edu/attachments/philosophy/aizawa/courses/epistemologyf2008/kirkham1984.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; To qualify as an item of knowledge, goes the theory, a belief must not only be true and justified, the justification of the belief must ''necessitate'' its truth. In other words, the justification for the belief must be infallible.

Yet another possible candidate for the fourth condition of knowledge is ''indefeasibility.''  Defeasibility theory maintains that there should be no overriding or defeating truths for the reasons that justify one's belief. For example, suppose that person ''S'' believes he saw Tom Grabit steal a book from the library and uses this to justify the claim that Tom Grabit stole a book from the library.  A possible defeater or overriding proposition for such a claim could be a true proposition like, &quot;Tom Grabit's identical twin Sam is currently in the same town as Tom.&quot;  When no defeaters of one's justification exist, a subject would be epistemically justified.

The Indian philosopher [[B K Matilal]] has drawn on the [[Navya-Nyaya]] [[fallibilism]] tradition to respond to the Gettier problem.
Nyaya theory distinguishes between ''know p'' and ''know that one knows p'' – these are different events, with different causal conditions.
The second level is a sort of implicit inference that usually follows immediately the episode of knowing p (knowledge ''simpliciter'').  The Gettier
case is analyzed by referring to a view of [[Gangesha]] (13th c.), who takes any true belief to be knowledge; thus a true belief acquired through a wrong
route may just be regarded as knowledge simpliciter on this view.
The question of justification arises only at the second level, when one
considers the knowledgehood of the acquired belief.
Initially, there is lack of uncertainty, so it becomes a true belief.
But at the very next moment, when the hearer is about to embark upon the venture of knowing whether he ''knows p'', doubts may arise.  &quot;If, in
some Gettier-like cases, I am wrong in my inference about the
knowledgehood of the given occurrent belief (for the evidence may be
pseudo-evidence), then I am mistaken about the truth of my belief – and
this is in accordance with Nyaya fallibilism: not all knowledge-claims can be
sustained.&quot;&lt;ref name=Matilal&gt;
{{cite book
| author =      Bimal Krishna Matilal
| title =       Perception: An essay on Classical Indian Theories of Knowledge
| publisher =   Oxford India 2002
| year =        1986
| isbn =      0-19-824625-0
}}The Gettier problem is dealt with in Chapter 4, ''Knowledge as a mental episode''. The thread continues in the next chapter
''Knowing that one knows''.  It is also discussed in Matilal's ''Word and the World'' p. 71-72.&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Reliabilism=====
{{Main|Reliabilism}}

Reliabilism has been the main line of response to the Gettier challenge among philosophers, originating with work by [[Alvin Goldman]] in the 1960s.  According to reliabilism, a belief is justified (or otherwise supported in such a way as to count towards knowledge) only if it is produced by processes that typically yield a sufficiently high ratio of true to false beliefs. In other words, this theory states that a true belief counts as knowledge only if it is produced by a reliable belief-forming process.

Reliabilism has been challenged by Gettier cases. Another argument that challenges reliabilism, like the Gettier cases (although it was not presented in the same short article as the Gettier cases), is the case of Henry and the barn façades. In the thought experiment, a man, Henry, is driving along and sees a number of buildings that resemble barns. Based on his perception of one of these, he concludes that he has just seen barns. While he has seen one, and the perception he based his belief that the one he saw was of a real barn, all the other [[barn]]-like buildings he saw were façades. Theoretically, Henry doesn't know that he has seen a barn, despite both his belief that he has seen one being true and his belief being formed on the basis of a reliable process (i.e. his vision), since he only acquired his true belief by accident.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Appearing as Irreducible in Perception |first=Alan H. |last=Goldman |journal=Philosophy and Phenomenological Research |volume=37 |issue=2 |month=December |year=1976 |pages=147–164 |publisher=International Phenomenological Society |jstor=2107188|doi=10.2307/2107188 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Other responses=====
The American philosopher [[Robert Nozick]] has offered the following definition of knowledge:

''S'' knows that ''P'' if and only if:
* ''P'';
* ''S'' believes that ''P'';
* if ''P'' were false, ''S'' would not believe that ''P'';
* if ''P'' is true, ''S'' will believe that ''P''.&lt;ref name=Nozick&gt;
{{cite book
| author =      Robert Nozick
| title =       Philosophical Explanations
| publisher =   Harvard University Press
| year =        1981
| isbn =      0-674-66448-5
}}[[Philosophical Explanations]] Chapter 3 &quot;Knowledge and Skepticism&quot; I. Knowledge ''Conditions for Knowledge'' p. 172-178.&lt;/ref&gt;
Nozick believed that the third subjunctive condition served to address cases of the sort described by Gettier. Nozick further claims this condition addresses a case of the sort described by [[D. M. Armstrong]]:&lt;ref name=Armstrong&gt;
{{cite book
| author =      D. M. Armstrong
| title =       Belief, Truth and Knowledge
| publisher =   Cambridge University Press
| year =        1973
| isbn =      0-521-09737-1 }}
&lt;/ref&gt; A father believes his daughter innocent of committing a particular crime, both because of faith in his baby girl and (now) because he has seen presented in the courtroom a conclusive demonstration of his daughter's innocence. His belief via the method of the courtroom satisfies the four subjunctive conditions, but his faith-based belief does not. If his daughter were guilty, he would still believe her innocent, on the basis of faith in his daughter; this would violate the third subjunctive condition.

The British philosopher [[Simon Blackburn]] has criticized this formulation by suggesting that we do not want to accept as knowledge beliefs, which, while they &quot;track the truth&quot; (as Nozick's account requires), are not held for appropriate reasons.  He says that &quot;we do not want to award the title of knowing something to someone who is only meeting the conditions through a defect, flaw, or failure, compared with someone else who is not meeting the conditions.&quot;.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}} In addition to this, externalist accounts of knowledge, like Nozick's, are often forced to reject closure in cases where it is intuitively valid.

[[Timothy Williamson]] has advanced a theory of knowledge according to which knowledge is not justified true belief plus some extra condition(s). In his book ''[[Knowledge and its Limits]],'' Williamson argues that the concept of knowledge cannot be analyzed into a set of other concepts—instead, it is ''[[sui generis]].'' Thus, though knowledge requires justification, truth, and belief, the word &quot;knowledge&quot; can't be, according to Williamson's theory, accurately regarded as simply shorthand for &quot;justified true belief.&quot;

[[Alvin Goldman]] writes in his [[Causal Theory of Knowledge|Causal Theory of Knowing]] that in order for knowledge to truly exist there must be a [[causal chain]] between the proposition and the belief of that proposition.

===Externalism and internalism===
{{Main|Internalism and externalism}}
Part of the debate over the nature of knowledge is a debate between epistemological externalists on the one hand, and epistemological internalists on the other.
Externalists think that factors deemed &quot;external&quot;, meaning outside of the psychological states of those who gain knowledge, can be conditions of knowledge. For example, an externalist response to the Gettier problem is to say that, in order for a justified true belief to count as knowledge, it must be caused, in the right sort of way, by relevant facts. Such causation, to the extent that it is &quot;outside&quot; the mind, would count as an external, knowledge-yielding condition. Internalists, contrariwise, claim that all knowledge-yielding conditions are within the psychological states of those who gain knowledge.

While unfamiliar with the internalist/externalist debate himself, many point to [[René Descartes]] as an early example of the internalist approach to justification. He wrote that, because the only method by which we perceive the external world is through our senses, and that, because the senses are not infallible, we should not consider our concept of knowledge to be infallible. The only way to find anything that could be described as &quot;indubitably true,&quot; he advocates, would be to see things &quot;clearly and distinctly&quot;.&lt;ref name=Regulae&gt;{{cite book|last=Descartes|first=Rene|title=The Philosophical Writings of Rene Descartes Vol. I|year=1985|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-0-521-28807-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; He argued that if there is an omnipotent, good being who made the world, then it's reasonable to believe that people are made with the ability to know. However, this does not mean that man's ability to know is perfect. God gave man the ability to know, but not omniscience. Descartes said that man must use his capacities for knowledge correctly and carefully through methodological doubt.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meditations on First Philosophy&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Descartes|first=Rene|title=Philosophical Writings of Rene Descartes Vol. II|year=1985|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-0-521-28808-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The phrase &quot;Cogito ergo sum&quot; (I think, therefore I am) is also commonly associated with Descartes' theory, because in his own methodological doubt, doubting everything he previously knew in order to start from a blank slate, the first thing that he could not logically bring himself to doubt was his own existence: &quot;I do not exist&quot; would be a contradiction in terms; the act of saying that one does not exist assumes that someone must be making the statement in the first place. Though Descartes could doubt his senses, his body and the world around him, he could not deny his own existence, because he was able to doubt and must exist in order to do so. Even if some &quot;evil genius&quot; were to be deceiving him, he would have to exist in order to be deceived. This one sure point provided him with what he would call his Archimedean point, in order to further develop his foundation for knowledge. Simply put, Descartes' epistemological justification depended upon his indubitable belief in his own existence and his clear and distinct knowledge of god.&lt;ref name=Refutations&gt;{{cite book|last=Descartes|first=Rene|title=The Philosophical Writings of Rene Descartes|year=1985|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-0-521-28808-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Acquiring knowledge==
The second question that will be dealt with is the question of how knowledge is acquired. This area of epistemology covers:
#Issues concerning epistemic distinctions such as that between empirical and non-empirical methods of formulating knowledge.
#Distinguish between synthesis and analysis used as means of proof
#Debates such as the one between empiricists and rationalists.
#What is called &quot;the regress problem&quot;

===''A priori'' and ''a posteriori'' knowledge===
{{Main|A priori and a posteriori}}
The nature of this distinction has been disputed by various philosophers; however, the terms may be roughly defined as follows:
*''A priori'' knowledge is knowledge that is known independently of experience (that is, it is non-empirical, or arrived at beforehand, usually by reason). It will henceforth be acquired through anything that is independent from experience.
*''A posteriori'' knowledge is knowledge that is known by experience (that is, it is empirical, or arrived at afterward).

[[Evolutionary psychology]] makes a novel approach to the problem. It says that there is an innate predisposition for certain types of learning. &quot;Only small parts of the brain resemble a [[tabula rasa]]; this is true even for human beings. The remainder is more like an exposed negative waiting to be dipped into a developer fluid&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, E. O., Sociobiology: The New Synthesis. Cambridge, Massachusetts: The Belknap Press of Harvard University Press. 1975&lt;/ref&gt;

===Analytic&amp;ndash;synthetic distinction===
{{Main|Analytic-synthetic distinction}}

Some propositions are such that we appear to be justified in believing them to be true just by understanding their meaning. For example, consider, &quot;My father's brother is my uncle.&quot; We seem to be justified in believing it to be true by virtue of our knowledge of what its terms mean. Philosophers call such propositions &quot;analytic.&quot; Synthetic propositions, on the other hand, have distinct subjects and predicates. An example of a synthetic proposition would be, &quot;My father's brother has black hair.&quot; [[Immanuel Kant|Kant]] stated that all mathematical and scientific statements are synthetic a priori propositions because they are necessarily true but our knowledge about the attributes of the mathematical or physical subjects we can only get by logical inference.

The American philosopher [[W. V. O. Quine]], in his &quot;[[Two Dogmas of Empiricism]]&quot;, famously challenged the distinction, arguing that the two have a blurry boundary.

===Branches or 'tendencies' within epistemology===
====Empiricism====
{{Main|Empiricism}}
In philosophy, empiricism is generally a theory of knowledge emphasizing the role of experience, especially experience based on [[perception|perceptual observations]] by the [[sense]]s.  Certain forms treat all knowledge as empirical,{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}} while some regard disciplines such as [[mathematics]] and [[logic]] as exceptions.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}

There are many variants of empiricism, [[positivism]] and [[realism]] being among the most commonly expounded but central to all empiricist epistemologies is the notion of the epistemologically privileged status of [[sense data]].

====Idealism====
{{Main|Idealism}}
Idealists believe that knowledge is primarily (at least in some areas) acquired by ''a priori'' processes or is [[innatism|innate]]—for example, in the form of concepts not derived from experience. The relevant theoretical processes often go by the name &quot;[[intuition (philosophy)|intuition]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|last=Markie
|first=Peter
|title=Rationalism vs. Empiricism
|url=http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/rationalism-empiricism/#1.1
|work=The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy
|publisher=Stanford University
|accessdate=17 July 2012}}
&lt;/ref&gt; The relevant theoretical concepts may purportedly be part of the structure of the human [[mind]] (as in [[Kant]]'s theory of [[transcendental idealism]]), or they may be said to exist independently of the mind (as in Plato's [[theory of Forms]]).

The main concept, however, common to all idealist epistemologies is the centrality of Reason: ''a priori'' knowledge can only be, ultimately, a product of the mind and is therefore, by definition, 'ideal'.

====Rationalism====
{{Main|Rationalism}}
By contrast with empiricism and idealism, which emphasize the epistemologically privileged status of sense data (empirical) and the primacy of Reason (theoretical) respectively, modern rationalism adds a third 'system of thinking', (as [[Gaston Bachelard]] has termed these areas) and holds that all three are of equal importance: The empirical, the theoretical and the ''abstract''. For Bachelard, rationalism makes equal reference to all three systems of thinking.

An example of abstract thinking is Pythagoras' concept of 'pure' geometric forms: perfect triangles, squares, circles. Etc. Another example is imaginary numbers, in mathematics.

====Constructivism====
{{Main|Constructivist epistemology}}
Constructivism is a view in philosophy according to which all &quot;knowledge is a compilation of human-made constructions&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Raskin, J. D. (2002). Constructivism in psychology: Personal construct psychology, radical constructivism, and social constructivism. In J. D. Raskin &amp; S. K. Bridges (Eds.), ''Studies in meaning: Exploring constructivist psychology'' (pp. 1-25). New York , NY: Pace University Press. p. 4&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;not the neutral discovery of an objective truth&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Castelló M., &amp; Botella,L. (2006). Constructivism and educational psychology. In J. L. Kincheloe &amp; R. A. Horn (Eds.), ''The Praeger handbook of education and psychology'' (Vol. 2, pp. 263-270). Westport, CT: Praeger. p. 263&lt;/ref&gt;  Whereas objectivism is concerned with the &quot;object of our knowledge&quot;, constructivism emphasises &quot;how we construct knowledge&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Jonassen, D. H. (1991). Objectivism versus constructivism, Do we need a new philosophical paradigm? ''Educational technology research and development'', ''39''(3), 5-14. p. 10&lt;/ref&gt; Constructivism proposes new definitions for [[knowledge]] and [[truth]] that form a new [[paradigm]], based on inter-subjectivity instead of the classical [[objectivity (philosophy)|objectivity]], and on viability instead of truth. Piagetian constructivism, however, believes in objectivity—constructs can be validated through experimentation. The constructivist point of view is pragmatic; as [[Giambattista Vico|Vico]] said: &quot;The norm of the truth is to have made it.&quot;

===The regress problem===
{{Main|Regress argument}}
&quot;... to justify a belief one must appeal to a further justified belief. This means that one of two things can be the case. Either there are some [epistemologically basic] beliefs that we can be justified for holding, without being able to justify them on the basis of any other belief, or else for each justified belief there is an infinite regress of (potential) justification [the nebula theory]. On this theory there is no rock bottom of justification. Justification just meanders in and out through our network of beliefs, stopping nowhere.&quot;&lt;ref name=Pollock&gt;
{{cite book
| author =      John L. Pollock
| title =       Knowledge and Justification
| publisher =   Princeton University Press, Princeton, New Jersey
| year =       1975
| isbn =      0-691-07203-5
}} p. 26.&lt;/ref&gt; The apparent impossibility of completing an infinite chain of reasoning is thought by some to support [[skepticism]]. Socrates said, &quot;The only true wisdom is in knowing you know nothing.&quot;

====Response to the regress problem====
Many epistemologists studying justification have attempted to argue for various types of chains of reasoning that can escape the regress problem.

=====Infinitism=====
It is not impossible for an infinite justificatory series to exist. This position is known as &quot;[[infinitism]]&quot;. Infinitists typically take the infinite series to be merely potential, in the sense that an individual may have indefinitely many reasons available to him, without having consciously thought through all of these reasons when the need arises. This position is motivated in part by the desire to avoid what is seen as the arbitrariness and circularity of its chief competitors, foundationalism and coherentism.  In mathematics, an [[infinite series]] will sometimes converge –
(this is the basis of [[calculus]]) – one can therefore have an infinite series of logical arguments
and analyze it for a convergent (or non-convergent) solution.

=====Foundationalism=====
[[Foundationalism|Foundationalists]] respond to the regress problem by claiming that &quot;foundations&quot; or &quot;basic beliefs&quot; support other beliefs but do not themselves require justification from other beliefs. These beliefs might be justified because they are self-evident, infallible, or derive from reliable cognitive mechanisms. Perception, memory, and a priori intuition are often considered to be possible examples of basic beliefs.

The chief criticism of foundationalism is that if a belief is not supported by other beliefs, accepting it may be arbitrary or unjustified.&lt;ref&gt;{{sep entry|justep-foundational|Foundational Theories of Epistemic Justification}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Coherentism=====
Another response to the regress problem is [[coherentism]], which is the rejection of the assumption that the regress proceeds according to a pattern of linear justification.  To avoid the charge of circularity, [[coherentism|coherentists]] hold that an individual belief is justified circularly by the way it fits together (coheres) with the rest of the belief system of which it is a part.  This theory has the advantage of avoiding the infinite regress without claiming special, possibly arbitrary status for some particular class of beliefs. Yet, since a system can be coherent while also being wrong, coherentists face the difficulty of ensuring that the whole system [[correspondence theory of truth|corresponds]] to reality. Additionally, most logicians agree that any argument that is circular is inherently invalid. That is, arguments must be linear with conclusions that flow directly from stated premises.

=====Foundherentism=====
A position known as &quot;[[foundherentism]]&quot;, advanced by [[Susan Haack]], is meant to be a unification of foundationalism and coherentism. One component of this theory is what is called the &quot;analogy of the crossword puzzle.&quot; Whereas, for example, infinitists regard the regress of reasons as &quot;shaped&quot; like a single line, Susan Haack has argued that it is more like a crossword puzzle, with multiple lines mutually supporting each other.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title = Evidence and Inquiry: Towards Reconstruction in Epistemology | author = Susan Haack | publisher = Wiley-Blackwell | year = 1993 | isbn=0-631-19679-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==What do people know?==
The last question that will be dealt with is the question of what people know. At the heart of this area of study is [[skepticism]], with many approaches involved trying to disprove some particular form of it.

===Skepticism===
{{Main|Philosophical skepticism}}
Skepticism is related to the question of whether a certain knowledge is possible. &quot;If we cannot move on to point B until we have proved point A, and if in order to prove point A we must establish it with absolute certainty, then it looks as though we will have a very hard time proving any point at all.&quot; Skeptics argue that the belief in something does not necessarily justify an assertion of knowledge of it. In this skeptics oppose [[foundationalism]], which states that there have to be some basic beliefs that are justified without reference to others. The skeptical response to this can take several approaches.  First, claiming that &quot;basic beliefs&quot; must exist, amounts to the logical fallacy of [[argument from ignorance]] combined with the [[slippery slope]].  While a foundationalist would use [[Münchhausen Trilemma]] as a justification for demanding the validity of basic beliefs, a skeptic would see no problem with admitting the result.

===Developments from skepticism===
Early in the 20th century, the notion that belief had to be justified as such to count as knowledge lost favour. [[Fallibilism]] is the view that knowing something does not entail certainty regarding it. [[Charles Sanders Peirce]] was a fallibilist and the most developed form of fallibilism can be traced to [[Karl Popper]] (1902–1994) whose first book ''Logik Der Forschung'' (''[[The Logic of Scientific Discovery]]''), 1934 introduced a &quot;conjectural turn&quot; into the philosophy of science and epistemology at large. He [[wiktionary:adumbrate|adumbrated]] a school of thought that is known as Critical Rationalism with a central tenet being the rejection of the idea that knowledge can ever be justified in the strong form that is sought by most schools of thought. His two most helpful exponents are the late William W Bartley and David Miller, recently retired from the University of Warwick. A major source of on-line material is the [[Critical rationalism|Critical Rationalist]] website and also the Rathouse of [[Rafe Champion]].

{{Expand section|date=June 2008}}

=== Epistemic culture ===
Epistemic culture distinguishes between various settings of knowledge production and emphasizes their contextual aspects. Coined by [[Karin Knorr|Karin Knorr-Cetina]] in her book ''[[Epistemic Cultures]]''; she defines epistemic cultures as an &quot;amalgam of arrangements and mechanisms - bonded through affinity, necessity and historical coincidence - which in a given field, make up how we know what we know&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Knorr-Cetina, K. (1999). Epistemic Cultures: How the Sciences Make Knowledge. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press. p.1.&lt;/ref&gt; The term provides the [[conceptual framework]] used to demonstrate that different laboratories do not share the same &quot;scientific&quot; knowledge production model, but rather each is endowed with a different epistemic culture prescribing what is adequate knowledge and how it is obtained. Since its introduction, the term has been picked up and used by various researchers engaging in [[Science and technology studies]].

==Practical applications==
Far from being purely academic, the study of epistemology is useful for a great many applications. It is particularly commonly employed in issues of law where proof of guilt or innocence may be required, or when it must be determined whether a person knew a particular fact before taking a specific action (e.g., whether an action was premeditated).  Another practical application is to the design of [[user interfaces]].  For example, the [[Ecological interface design#The Skills, Rules, Knowledge (SRK) framework|skills, rules, and knowledge]] taxonomy of human behavior has been used by designers to develop systems{{vague|date=February 2012}} that are compatible with multiple &quot;ways of knowing&quot;: abstract analytic reasoning, experience-based 'gut feelings', and 'craft' sensorimotor skills.

Other common applications of epistemology include:
{|
|-
|width=50%|
* [[Education Theory]]
* [[Education Technology]]
* [[Artificial intelligence]]
* [[Cognitive science]]
* [[Cultural anthropology]] (do different cultures have different systems of knowledge?)
* [[History]] and [[archaeology]]
* [[Information gathering|Intelligence (information) gathering]]
* [[Knowledge management]]
* [[Mathematics]] and [[science]]
* [[Medicine]] (diagnosis of disease)
* [[Neurology]]
* [[Behavioral neuroscience]]
|width=50%|
* [[Product testing]] (how can we know that the product will not fail?)
* [[Psychology]]
* [[Philosophy]]
* [[Linguistics]]
* [[Logic]]
* [[Literature]]
* [[Theology]] and [[apologetics]]
* [[Sociology]]
* [[Philosophical problems of testimony|Testimony]]
|}
{{Expand section|date=June 2008}}

==See also==
{{Main|Outline of epistemology}}
{{Wikipedia books|Epistemology}}
{{Portal|Epistemology}}
{{columns-list|3|
* [[Adaptive representation]]
* [[Agnotology]]
* [[Agrippa's Trilemma]]
* [[Bayesian probability]]
* [[Conveyed concept]]
* [[Cybernetic epistemology]]
* [[Eastern epistemology]]
* [[Editology]]
* [[Evidentialism]]
* [[Evidentiality]]
* [[Evolutionary epistemology]]
* [[Explanatory model]]
* [[Formal epistemology]]
* [[Gödel's incompleteness theorems]]
* [[Meta-epistemology]]
* [[Methodology]]
* [[Methods of obtaining knowledge]]
* [[Monopolies of knowledge]]
* [[Noology|Noölogy]]
* [[Nyaya]]
* [[Participatory epistemology]]
* [[Phaneron]]
* [[Physical ontology]]
* [[Reformed epistemology]]
* [[Scientific method]]
* [[Self-evidence]]
* [[Social epistemology]]
* [[Sociology of knowledge]]
* [[Transcendence (philosophy)]]
* [[Uncertainty principle]]
* [[Virtue epistemology]]
}}

==Sources==
===Footnotes===
{{Reflist|3}}

===Bibliography===
&lt;!-- Please order books alphabetically by the author's last name --&gt;
{{Refbegin|2}}
* The [http://www.ucl.ac.uk/philosophy/LPSG/ London Philosophy Study Guide] offers many suggestions on what to read, depending on the student's familiarity with the subject: [http://www.ucl.ac.uk/philosophy/LPSG/Ep&amp;Meth.htm Epistemology &amp; Methodology]
* {{Cite journal | last1 = Annis | first1 = David | year = 1978 | title = A Contextualist Theory of Epistemic Justification | url = | journal = American Philosophical Quarterly | volume = 15 | issue = | pages = 213–219 }}
* [[Alfred Jules Ayer|Ayer, Alfred Jules]]. 1936. ''[[Language, Truth, and Logic]]''.
* BonJour, Laurence. 2002. ''Epistemology: Classic Problems and Contemporary Responses''. Lanham, MD: Rowman &amp; Littlefield.
* {{Cite journal | last1 = Boufoy-Bastick | first1 = Z. | year = 2005 | title = Introducing 'Applicable Knowledge' as a Challenge to the Attainment of Absolute Knowledge | url = | journal = Sophia Journal of Philosophy | volume = 8 | issue = | pages = 39–51 }}
* [[Bovens, Luc]] &amp; Hartmann, Stephan. 2003. ''Bayesian Epistemology''. Oxford: Oxford University Press.
* [[Panayot Butchvarov|Butchvarov, Panayot]]. 1970. ''The Concept of Knowledge''. Evanston, Northwestern University Press.
* {{Cite journal | doi = 10.1080/00048409812348411 | last1 = Cohen | first1 = Stewart | year = 1998 | title = Contextualist Solutions to Epistemological Problems: Skepticism, Gettier, and the Lottery | url = | journal = Australasian Journal of Philosophy | volume = 76 | issue = 2| pages = 289–306 }}
* Cohen, Stewart. 1999. &quot;Contextualism, Skepticism, and Reasons&quot;, in Tomberlin 1999.
* [[Jonathan Dancy|Dancy, Jonathan]]. 1991. ''An Introduction to Contemporary Epistemology'' (Second Edition). John Wiley &amp; Sons. ISBN 0-631-13622-3
* {{Cite journal | last1 = DeRose | first1 = Keith | authorlink = Keith DeRose | year = 1992 | title = Contextualism and Knowledge Attributions | url = | journal = Philosophy and Phenomenological Research | volume = 15 | issue = | pages = 213–19 }}
* DeRose, Keith. 1999. &quot;Contextualism: An Explanation and Defense&quot;, in Greco and Sosa 1999.
* [[René Descartes|Descartes, Rene]]. 1641. ''[[Meditations on First Philosophy]]''
* Feldman, Richard. 1999. &quot;Contextualism and Skepticism&quot;, in Tomberlin 1999, pp.&amp;nbsp;91–114.
* [[Edmund Gettier|Gettier, Edmund]]. 1963. &quot;Is Justified True Belief Knowledge?&quot;, ''Analysis'', Vol. 23, pp.&amp;nbsp;121–23. [http://www.ditext.com/gettier/gettier.html Online text].
* Greco, J. &amp; Sosa, E. 1999. ''Blackwell Guide to Epistemology'', Blackwell Publishing.
* [[Errol Harris|Harris, Errol E.]] 1970. ''Hypothesis And Perception'', George Allen and Unwin, London, Reprinted 2002 Routledge, London.
* {{Cite journal | doi = 10.1111/j.1467-9205.1989.tb00275.x | last1 = Harwood | first1 = Sterling | authorlink = Sterling Harwood | year = 1989 | title = Taking Skepticism Seriously – And In Context | url = | journal = Philosophical Investigations | volume = 12 | issue = 3| pages = 223–233 }}
* Hay, Clare. 2008. ''The Theory of Knowledge: A Coursebook'', The Lutterworth Press, Cambridge. ISBN 978-0-7188-3088-5
* Hawthorne, John. 2005. &quot;The Case for Closure&quot;, ''Contemporary Debates in Epistemology'', Peter Sosa and Matthias Steup (ed.): 26–43.
* [[Vincent F. Hendricks|Hendricks, Vincent F]]. 2006. ''Mainstream and Formal Epistemology'', New York: [[Cambridge University Press]].
* [[Kant, Immanuel]]. 1781. ''[[Critique of Pure Reason]]''.
* [[Keeton, Morris T.]] 1962. &quot;Empiricism&quot;, in ''Dictionary of Philosophy'', Dagobert D. Runes (ed.), Littlefield, Adams, and Company, Totowa, NJ, pp.&amp;nbsp;89–90.
* [[Søren Kierkegaard|Kierkegaard, Søren]]. 1844. ''[[Philosophical Fragments]]''.
* [[Richard Kirkham|Kirkham, Richard]]. 1984. &quot;Does the Gettier Problem Rest on a Mistake?&quot; ''Mind'', 93.
* [[Peter D. Klein|Klein, Peter]]. 1981. ''Certainty: a Refutation of Skepticism'', Minneapolis, MN: [[University of Minnesota Press]].
* [[Henry E. Kyburg, Jr.|Kyburg, H.E.]] 1961. ''Probability and the Logic of Rational Belief'', Middletown, CT: Wesleyan University Press.
* [[Alfred Korzybski|Korzybski, Alfred]]. 1994 (1933). ''Science and Sanity: An Introduction to Non-Aristotelian Systems and General Semantics'', Fifth Edition. Ft. Worth, TX: Institute of General Semantics.
* {{Cite journal | doi = 10.1080/00048409612347521 | last1 = Lewis | first1 = David | authorlink = David Kellogg Lewis | year = 1996 | title = Elusive Knowledge | url = | journal = Australian Journal of Philosophy | volume = 74 | issue = 4| pages = 549–67 }}
* [[Morin, Edgar]]. 1986. ''La Méthode, Tome 3, La Connaissance de la connaissance'' (Method, 3rd volume : The knowledge of knowledge)
* [[Adam Morton|Morton, Adam]]. 2002. ''A Guide Through the Theory of Knowledge'' (Third Edition) Oxford: Blackwell Publishing. ISBN 1-4051-0012-5
* Nelson, Quee. 2007. ''The Slightest Philosophy'', Indianapolis, IN: Dog Ear Publishing, 296 pages.
* [[Ilkka Niiniluoto|Niiniluoto, Ilkka]]. 2002. ''Critical Scientific Realism'', Oxford: Oxford Univ. Press.
* [[Plato]]. ''[[Meno]]''.
* [[Karl Popper|Popper, Karl R.]] 1972. ''Objective Knowledge: An Evolutionary Approach'', Oxford: Oxford Univ. Press.
* Preyer, G./Siebelt, F./Ulfig, A. 1994. ''Language, Mind and Epistemology'', Dordrecht: Kluwer Academic Publishers.
* [[Ayn Rand|Rand, Ayn]]. 1979. ''Introduction to Objectivist Epistemology'', New York: Meridian.
* [[Bertrand Russell|Russell, Bertrand]]. 1912. ''The Problems of Philosophy'', New York: Oxford University Press.
* [[Bertrand Russell|Russell, Bertrand]]. 1940. ''An Inquiry into Meaning and Truth'', Nottingham: Spokesman Books.
* [[George Santayana|Santayana, George]]. 1923. ''[[Scepticism and Animal Faith]]'', New York: Charles Scribner's Sons – London: Constable and Co.
* [[African Spir|Spir, African]]. 1877. ''Denken und Wirklichkeit: Versuch einer Erneuerung der kritischen Philosophie'' (Thought and Reality: Attempt at a Renewal of Critical Philosophy), (Second Edition) Leipzig: J. G. Findel.
* {{Cite journal | last1 = Schiffer | first1 = Stephen | authorlink = Stephen Schiffer | year = 1996 | title = Contextualist Solutions to Skepticism | url = | journal = Proceedings of the Aristotelian Society | volume = 96 | issue = | pages = 317–33 }}
* Steup, Matthias. 2005. &quot;Knowledge and Skepticism&quot;, ''Contemporary Debates in Epistemology'', Peter Sosa and Matthias Steup (eds.): 1–13.
* Tomberlin, James (ed.). 1999. ''Philosophical Perspectives 13, Epistemology'', Blackwell Publishing.
* [[Ludwig Wittgenstein|Wittgenstein, Ludwig]]. 1922. ''[[Tractatus Logico-Philosophicus]]'', C.K. Ogden (trns.), Dover. [http://www.kfs.org/~jonathan/witt/tlph.html Online text].
&lt;/div&gt;

==External links and references==
{{Wiktionary|epistemology}}
{{Wikiquote|epistemology}}
{{Commons category|epistemology}}
'''''Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy'' articles:'''
* [http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/epistemology-bayesian/ Bayesian Epistemology] by William Talbott.
* [http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/epistemology/ Epistemology] by Matthias Steup.
* [http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/epistemology-evolutionary/ Evolutionary Epistemology] by Michael Bradie &amp; William Harms.
* [http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/feminism-epistemology/ Feminist Epistemology and Philosophy of Science] by Elizabeth Anderson.
* [http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/epistemology-naturalized/ Naturalized Epistemology] by Richard Feldman.
* [http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/epistemology-social/ Social Epistemology] by Alvin Goldman.
* [http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/epistemology-virtue/ Virtue Epistemology] by John Greco.

'''Other links:'''
* {{PhilPapers|category|epistemology}}
* {{InPho|taxonomy|2374}}
* {{SEP|Epistemology}}
* {{IEP|Epistemo|Epistemology}}
* [http://pantheon.yale.edu/~kd47/What-Is-Epistemology.htm What Is Epistemology?] — a brief introduction to the topic by Keith DeRose.
* [http://el-prod.baylor.edu/certain_doubts/ Certain Doubts] — a group blog run by Jonathan Kvanvig, with many leading epistemologists as contributors.
* [http://www.db.dk/jni/lifeboat/ The Epistemological Lifeboat] by Birger Hjørland &amp;  Jeppe Nicolaisen (eds.)
* [http://pantheon.yale.edu/~kd47/e-page.htm The Epistemology Page] by Keith DeRose.
* [http://dostoevskiansmiles.blogspot.com/2008/10/justified-true-belief-and-critical.html Justified True Belief and Critical Rationalism] by Mathew Toll
* [http://www.studysocietypublications.org] The White Book by Tinky Brass.
* [http://home.sprynet.com/~owl1/epistemo.htm Epistemology Papers] a collection of Michael Huemer's.
* [http://www.galilean-library.org/int5.html Epistemology Introduction, Part 1] and [http://www.galilean-library.org/int20.html Part 2] by Paul Newall at the Galilean Library.
* [http://www.ditext.com/clay/know.html ''Teaching Theory of Knowledge'' (1986)] — Marjorie Clay (ed.), an electronic publication from The Council for Philosophical Studies.
* [http://www.rustyspigot.com/groovyweb/?page_name=philosophy%20of%20knowledge&amp;category=philosophy Epistemology: The Philosophy of Knowledge] — an introduction at Groovyweb.
* [http://ThePeripatetic.com The Peripatetic] A practical introduction to the theory of knowledge
* [http://www.theoryofknowledge.info/ Theory of Knowledge] — an introduction to epistemology, exploring the various theories of knowledge, justification, and belief.
* [http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=904833 A Theory of Knowledge] by Clóvis Juarez Kemmerich, on the Social Science Research Network, 2006.
* [http://www.galilean-library.org/manuscript.php?postid=43783 An Introduction to Epistemology] by Paul Newall, aimed at beginners.
* [http://www.sofiatopia.org/equiaeon/clearings.htm On a Critical Epistemology]
* [http://www.percepp.com/meaning.htm Language Perception and Action: Philosophical Issues]

{{Navboxes
|title = Articles related to epistemology
|list  =
{{Philosophy topics}}
{{epistemology}}
{{philosophy of science}}
{{Positivism}}
}}

&lt;!-- Please don't change this interwiki link without considering the arguments on the talk page --&gt;
&lt;!-- Please don't change this interwiki link without considering the arguments on the talk page --&gt;
&lt;!-- Please don't change this interwiki link without considering the arguments on the talk page --&gt;

[[Category:Epistemology| ]]
[[Category:Branches of philosophy]]
[[Category:Greek loanwords]]

{{Link GA|sv}}
{{Link GA|de}}

[[af:Epistemologie]]
[[ar:نظرية المعرفة]]
[[an:Epistemolochía]]
[[az:Epistemologiya]]
[[zh-min-nan:Jīn-sek-lūn]]
[[be:Эпістэмалогія]]
[[be-x-old:Эпістэмалёгія]]
[[bg:Епистемология]]
[[bs:Epistemologija]]
[[ca:Epistemologia]]
[[cs:Gnozeologie]]
[[cy:Epistemoleg]]
[[da:Erkendelsesteori]]
[[de:Erkenntnistheorie]]
[[et:Epistemoloogia]]
[[es:Epistemología]]
[[eo:Sciteorio]]
[[eu:Epistemologia]]
[[fa:معرفت‌شناسی]]
[[fr:Épistémologie]]
[[fy:Epistemology]]
[[gl:Epistemoloxía]]
[[gan:知識論]]
[[ko:인식론]]
[[hi:ज्ञानमीमांसा]]
[[hr:Teorija spoznaje]]
[[io:Epistemologio]]
[[id:Epistemologi]]
[[ia:Epistemologia]]
[[is:Þekkingarfræði]]
[[it:Gnoseologia]]
[[he:תורת ההכרה]]
[[jv:Epistemologi]]
[[ka:ეპისტემოლოგია]]
[[kk:Эпистемология]]
[[sw:Epistemolojia]]
[[ky:Гносеология]]
[[la:Epistemologia]]
[[lv:Epistemoloģija]]
[[lt:Epistemologija]]
[[hu:Ismeretelmélet]]
[[mk:Епистемологија]]
[[ml:വിജ്ഞാനശാസ്ത്രം]]
[[ms:Epistemologi]]
[[nl:Kennistheorie]]
[[ja:認識論]]
[[no:Erkjennelsesteori]]
[[nn:Sannkjenningsteori]]
[[oc:Epistemologia]]
[[uz:Epistemologiya]]
[[pnb:ایپسٹیمولوجی]]
[[ps:پوهنپوهنه]]
[[pms:Epistemologìa]]
[[nds:Kennistheorie]]
[[pl:Epistemologia]]
[[pt:Epistemologia]]
[[ro:Epistemologie]]
[[rue:Епістемолоґія]]
[[ru:Эпистемология]]
[[sah:Эпистемология]]
[[stq:Epistemologie]]
[[sq:Epistemologjia]]
[[scn:Epistemoluggìa]]
[[simple:Epistemology]]
[[sk:Teória poznania]]
[[sl:Epistemologija]]
[[ckb:مەعریفەتناسی]]
[[sr:Епистемологија]]
[[sh:Gnoseologija]]
[[fi:Tietoteoria]]
[[sv:Epistemologi]]
[[tl:Epistemolohiya]]
[[ta:அறிவாய்வியல்]]
[[th:ญาณวิทยา]]
[[tg:Маърифатшиносӣ]]
[[tr:Epistemoloji]]
[[uk:Епістемологія]]
[[ur:علمیات]]
[[vi:Nhận thức luận]]
[[fiu-vro:Epistemoloogia]]
[[war:Epistemolohiya]]
[[yi:עפיסטעמאלאגיע]]
[[zh-yue:知識論]]
[[zh:知识论]]</text>
      <sha1>0l47ovk2bn04atsiwxhe1az2u1x5gwy</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
