<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Equality of outcome</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>354800</id>
    <revision>
      <id>508802757</id>
      <parentid>504571012</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-08-23T16:49:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ground Zero</username>
        <id>232133</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="34914">'''Equality of outcome''', '''equality of condition''', or '''equality of results''' is a controversial [[politics|political]] concept.&lt;ref name=twsO42xx/&gt; Although it is not always clearly defined, it usually describes a state in which people have approximately the same material wealth or, more generally, in which the general economic conditions of their lives are similar. Achieving this requires reducing or eliminating material inequalities between individuals or households in a society. This could involve a transfer of [[income]] and/or [[wealth]] from wealthier to poorer individuals, or adopting other institutions designed to promote equality of condition from the start. The concept is central to some political ideologies and is used regularly in political discourse, often in contrast to the term [[equality of opportunity]]. A related way of defining equality of outcome is to think of it as &quot;equality in the central and valuable things in life.&quot;&lt;ref name=twsO24/&gt;

==Comparisons with related concepts==
''Equality of outcome'' is often compared to related concepts of equality. Generally, the concept is most often contrasted with the concept of ''equality of opportunity'', but there are other concepts as well. The term has been seen differently from differing political perspectives, but of all of the terms relating to ''equality'', ''equality of outcome'' is the most &quot;controversial&quot; or &quot;contentious&quot;.&lt;ref name=twsO42xx&gt;{{cite news
 |author= Mark E. Rushefsky
 |title= Public Policy in the United States: At the Dawn of the Twenty-First Century
 |publisher= ''M. E. Sharpe Inc.''
 |year= 2008
 |url= http://books.google.com/books?id=C3WF8anbYsIC&amp;pg=PA36&amp;dq=equality+of+outcome+vs+equality+of+opportunity#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false
 |accessdate= 2011-07-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Equality of opportunity]]. This conception generally describes fair competition for important jobs and positions such that contenders have equal chances to win such positions,&lt;ref name=twsL13&gt;{{cite news
 |author= Nicole Richardt, Torrey Shanks
 |title= Equal Opportunity 
 |publisher= ''International Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences''
 |quote= via Encyclopedia.com
 |year= 2008
 |url= http://www.encyclopedia.com/topic/Equal_Opportunity.aspx
 |accessdate= 2011-09-12
}}&lt;/ref&gt; and applicants are not judged or hampered by unfair or arbitrary [[discrimination]].&lt;ref name=twsL16bb&gt;{{cite news
 |title= equal opportunity
 |publisher= ''Collins English Dictionary''
 |quote= the offering of employment, pay, or promotion equally to all, without discrimination as to sex, race, colour, disability, etc.
 |year= 2003
 |url= http://www.thefreedictionary.com/equal+opportunity
 |accessdate= 2011-09-12
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=twsL16cc&gt;{{cite news
 |title= equal opportunity
 |publisher= ''Princeton University''
 |quote= (thesaurus) equal opportunity - the right to equivalent opportunities for employment regardless of race or color or sex or national origin
 |year= 2008
 |url= http://www.thefreedictionary.com/equal+opportunity
 |accessdate= 2011-09-12
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=twsL22&gt;{{cite news
 |author= Carol Kitman
 |title= equal opportunity
 |publisher= ''Merriam-Webster Dictionary''
 |quote= nondiscrimination in employment esp. as offered by an equal opportunity employer -- : a context in which there is no discrimination esp. with regard to sex, race, or social standing &lt;alcoholism has become an equal opportunity disease — Carol Kitman&gt; 
 |date= 2011-09-12
 |url= http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/equal%20opportunity
 |accessdate= 2011-09-12
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=twsL16aa&gt;{{cite news
 |title= equal opportunity
 |publisher= ''The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language'' (Houghton Mifflin)
 |quote= Absence of discrimination, as in the workplace, based on race, color, age, gender, national origin, religion, or mental or physical disability
 |year= 2009
 |url= http://www.thefreedictionary.com/equal+opportunity
 |accessdate= 2011-09-12
}}&lt;/ref&gt; It entails the &quot;elimination of arbitrary discrimination in the process of selection.&quot;&lt;ref name=twsO26&gt;{{cite news
 |author= Ed Rooksby
 |title= The complexity of equality: Equality for the left is a complex concept, which bears little resemblance to the caricatures drawn by the right
 |publisher= ''The Guardian''
 |quote= ... &quot;equality of outcome&quot; which, as every Telegraph journalist knows, is a Bad Thing and, anyway, &quot;impossible&quot;. ...
 |date= 14 October 2010
 |url= http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2010/oct/14/complexity-of-equality
 |accessdate= 2011-07-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term is usually applied in workplace situations but has been applied in other areas as well such as housing, lending, and voting rights.&lt;ref name=twsL19&gt;{{cite news
 |author= Paul de Vries 
 |title= equal opportunity
 |publisher= ''Blackwell Reference''
 |quote= his standard has been used to define fairness in lending, housing, hiring, wage and salary levels, job promotion, voting rights ...
 |date= 2011-09-12
 |url= http://www.blackwellreference.com/public/tocnode?id=g9780631233176_chunk_g97814051001378_ss1-15
 |accessdate= 2011-09-12
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The essence is that job seekers have &quot;an equal chance to compete within the framework of goals and the structure of rules established,&quot; according to one view.&lt;ref name=twsH77c&gt;{{cite news
 |author= John W. Gardner
 |title= Excellence: Can we be equal and excellent too?
 |publisher= ''Norton''
 |quote= (see page 47)...
 |year= 1984
 |isbn= 0-393-31287-9
 |url= http://books.google.com/books?id=liE59woX624C&amp;pg=PA46&amp;dq=%22equality+of+opportunity%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=QBxqTqTfLeLv0gG27byuCQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CDAQ6AEwATge#v=onepage&amp;q=%22equality%20of%20opportunity%22&amp;f=false
 |accessdate= 2011-09-08
}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is generally seen as a procedural value of fair treatment by the rules.&lt;ref name=twsO42&gt;{{cite news
 |author= Mark E. Rushefsky
 |title= Public Policy in the United States: At the Dawn of the Twenty-First Century
 |publisher= ''M. E. Sharpe Inc.''
 |quote= (page 36)  ... A second meaning of equality is equality of opportunity, giving each person the right to develop to his or her potential....
 |year= 2008
 |url= http://books.google.com/books?id=C3WF8anbYsIC&amp;pg=PA36&amp;dq=equality+of+outcome+vs+equality+of+opportunity#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false
 |accessdate= 2011-07-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Equality of autonomy]]. This relatively new concept, a sort of hybrid notion, has been developed by philosopher [[Amartya Sen]] and can be thought of as &quot;the ability and means to choose our life course should be spread as equally as possible across society.&quot;&lt;ref name=twsO23&gt;{{cite news
 |author= Sunder Katwala
 |title= It's equality of life chances, not literal equality, that the left espouses
 |publisher= ''The Guardian''
 |quote= ... more equal life chances. Amartya Sen calls this equality of autonomy: that the ability and means to choose our life course should be spread as equally as possible across society. ...
 |date= 21 October 2010
 |url= http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2010/oct/21/equality-life-chances-not-literal-left
 |accessdate= 2011-07-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is an equal shot at empowerment or a chance to develop up to his or her potential rather than equal goods or equal chances. In a teaching guide, ''equality of autonomy'' was explained as &quot;equality in the degree of empowerment people have to make decisions affecting their lives, how much choice and control they have given their circumstances.&quot;&lt;ref name=twsO24&gt;{{cite news
 |title= Equality Impact Assessments
 |publisher= ''Hull Teaching Primary Care''
 |quote= Equality of autonomy - that is, equality in the degree of empowerment people have to make decisions affecting their lives, how much choice and control they have given their circumstances....
 |date= 2011-07-15
 |url= http://www.hullpct.nhs.uk/impact_assessments/
 |accessdate= 2011-07-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sen's approach requires &quot;active intervention of institutions like the state into people's lives&quot; but with an aim towards &quot;fostering of people's self-creation rather than their living conditions.&quot;&lt;ref name=twsO25&gt;{{cite news
 |author= Todd May
 |title= The political thought of Jacques Rancière: creating equality
 |publisher= ''The Pennsylvania State University Press''
 |quote= (equality of autonomy) Amartya Sen ... aims that intervention at the fostering of people's self-creation rather than their living conditions. ...
 |year= 2008
 |url= http://books.google.com/books?id=JJYjY8sG85kC&amp;pg=PA19&amp;lpg=PA19&amp;dq=%22equality+of+autonomy%22#v=onepage&amp;q=%22equality%20of%20autonomy%22&amp;f=false
 |accessdate= 2011-07-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sen argued that &quot;the ability to convert incomes into opportunities is affected by a multiplicity of individual and social differences that mean some people will need more than others to achieve the same range of capabilities.&quot;&lt;ref name=twsO45/&gt;

* '''Equality of process''' is related to the general notion of fair treatment, and can be thought of as &quot;dealing with inequalities in treatment through discrimination by other individuals and groups, or by institutions and systems, including not being treated with dignity and respect,&quot; according to one definition.&lt;ref name=twsO24bbr&gt;{{cite news
 |title= Equality Impact Assessments
 |publisher= ''Hull Teaching Primary Care''
 |quote=  ... Equality of process - dealing with inequalities in treatment through discrimination by other individuals and groups, or by institutions and systems, including not being treated with dignity and respect.
 |date= 2011-07-15
 |url= http://www.hullpct.nhs.uk/impact_assessments/
 |accessdate= 2011-07-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Equality of perception'''. This is an uncommonly used term meaning that &quot;person should be perceived as being of equal worth.&quot;&lt;ref name=twsO47&gt;{{cite news
 |title= Equality, the goal not the signpost
 |publisher= ''Sociology''
 |quote= There are three forms of equality: equality of outcome, of opportunity, and of perception. Equality of perception is the most basic: it dictates that for people to be equal, each person should be perceived as being of equal worth. ...
 |date= 27 April 2008 
 |url= http://anthologyoi.com/sociology/equality-of-outcome-equality-of-oportunity.html
 |accessdate= 2011-07-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Political philosophy==
[[File:Lenin-Trotsky 1920-05-20 Sverdlov Square (original).jpg|thumb|right|325px|After the [[Russian Revolution of 1917]], the political structure of the [[Soviet Union]] (1917&amp;ndash;1989) tried to emphasize ''equality of outcome'' as a primary goal. Photo: [[Vladimir Lenin]] addresses a crowd in [[Moscow]] in 1920.]]
In [[political philosophy]], there are differing views whether equal outcomes are beneficial or not. One view is that there is a moral basis for equality of outcome, but that means to achieve such an outcome can be malevolent. ''Equality of outcome'' can be a good thing ''after'' it has been achieved since it reflects the natural &quot;interdependence of citizens in a highly organized economy&quot; and provides a &quot;basis for social policies&quot; which foster harmony and good will, including social cohesion and reduced jealousy. One writer suggested greater socioeconomic equality was &quot;indispensable if we want to realise our shared commonsense values of societal fairness.&quot;&lt;ref name=twsO28&gt;{{cite news
 |author= Martin O'Neill
 |title= Talk of fairness is hollow without material equality: Greater socioeconomic equality is indispensable if we want to realise our shared commonsense values of societal fairness
 |publisher= ''The Guardian''
 |date= 12 October 2010 
 |url= http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2010/oct/12/fairness-is-hollow-without-equality
 |accessdate= 2011-07-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Analyst Kenneth Cauthen in his 1987 book ''The Passion for Equality'' suggested that there were moral underpinnings for having equal outcomes because there is a common good&amp;ndash;&amp;ndash;which people both contribute to and receive benefits from&amp;ndash;&amp;ndash;and therefore should be enjoyed in common; Cauthen argued that this was a fundamental basis for both equality of opportunity as well as equality of outcome.&lt;ref name=twsO43&gt;{{cite news
 |author= Kenneth Cauthen
 |title= The Passion for Equality
 |publisher= ''Rowman &amp; Littlefield''
 |quote= (page 136) There is a common good to which we contribute and from which we receive as members of a common system....
 |year= 1987
 |url= http://books.google.com/books?id=uH4D-XJox-0C&amp;pg=PA57&amp;dq=equality+of+outcome+vs+equality+of+opportunity#v=snippet&amp;q=%22equality%20of%20outcome%22&amp;f=false
 |accessdate= 2011-07-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Analyst George Packer, writing in the journal ''[[Foreign Affairs (journal)|Foreign Affairs]]'', argued that &quot;inequality undermines democracy&quot; in the [[United States]] partially because it &quot;hardens society into a class system, imprisoning people in the circumstances of their birth.&quot;&lt;ref name=twsfhffhsl/&gt; Packer elaborated that inequality &quot;corrodes trust among fellow citizens&quot; and compared it to an &quot;odorless gas which pervades every corner&quot; of the nation.&lt;ref name=twsfhffhsl&gt;{{cite news
 |author= George Packer
 |title= The Broken Contract
 |publisher= ''Foreign Affairs'' 
 |date= November 2011
 |quote= Volume 90, Number 6 (see pages 29 and 31)
 |accessdate= 2011-07-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An opposing view is that equality of outcomes is not beneficial overall for society since it dampens motivation necessary for humans to achieve great things, such as new inventions, intellectual discoveries, and artistic breakthroughs. According to this view, wealth and income is a reward needed to spur such activity, and with this reward removed, then achievements which would benefit everybody may not happen.

If equality of outcomes is seen as beneficial for society, and if people have differing levels of material wealth in the present, then methods to transform a society towards one with greater equality of outcomes is problematic. A mainstream view is that mechanisms to achieve equal outcomes&amp;ndash;&amp;ndash;to take a society and with unequal wealth and force it to equal outcomes&amp;ndash;&amp;ndash;are fraught with moral as well as practical problems since they often involve force to compel the transfer.&lt;ref name=twsO43/&gt; 

[[File:Paul Krugman-press conference Dec 07th, 2008-3.jpg|thumb|right|Economist [[Paul Krugman]] in 2008.]]
And there is general agreement that outcomes matter. In one report in Britain, unequal outcomes in terms of personal wealth had a strong impact on average [[life expectancy]], such that wealthier people tended to live seven years longer than poorer people, and that egalitarian nations tended to have fewer problems with societal issues such as [[mental illness]], [[violence]], [[teenage pregnancy]], and other social problems.&lt;ref name=twsO35&gt;{{cite news
 |author= Bagehot
 |title= On equality: The lessons of the Spirit Level debate for the left, the right and the British public 
 |publisher= ''The Economist''
 |quote= ...“more equal societies almost always do better”. ...
 |date= Aug 19 2010 
 |url= http://www.economist.com/node/16844516
 |accessdate= 2011-07-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Authors of the book ''The Spirit Level'' contended that &quot;more equal societies almost always do better&quot; on other measures, and as a result, striving for equal outcomes can have overall beneficial effects for everybody.&lt;ref name=twsO35/&gt; 

Philosopher [[John Rawls]], in his ''[[A Theory of Justice]]'' (1971), developed a &quot;second principle of justice&quot; that economic and social inequalities can only be justified if they benefit the most disadvantaged members of society. Further, Rawls claims that all economically and socially privileged positions must be open to all people equally. Rawls argues that the inequality between a doctor's salary and a grocery clerk's is only acceptable if this is the only way to encourage the training of sufficient numbers of doctors, preventing an unacceptable decline in the availability of medical care (which would therefore disadvantage everyone). Analyst [[Paul Krugman]] writing in ''[[The New York Times]]'' agreed with Rawls' position in which both [[equality of opportunity]] and equality of outcome were linked, and suggested that &quot;we should try to create the society each of us would want if we didn’t know in advance who we’d be.&quot;&lt;ref name=twsO22/&gt; Krugman favored a society in which hard-working and talented people can get rewarded for their efforts but in which there was a &quot;[[social safety net]]&quot; created by taxes to help the less fortunate.&lt;ref name=twsO22&gt;{{cite news
 |author= Paul Krugman
 |title= More Thoughts on Equality of Opportunity
 |publisher= ''The New York Times''
 |quote= My vision of economic morality is more or less Rawlsian: we should try to create the society each of us would want if we didn’t know in advance who we’d be....
 |date= January 11, 2011
 |url= http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/01/11/more-thoughts-on-equality-of-opportunity/
 |accessdate= 2011-07-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Comparing equalities: outcome vs opportunity==
[[File:FactoryProcessing.png|thumb|350px|right|In a lamp assembly factory, for example, ''equality of outcome'' might mean that workers are all '''''paid equally''''' regardless of how many lamps they make. This can be contrasted with a payment system such as [[piece work]], which requires that every worker is paid a fixed amount of money per lamp. The relationship between ''equality of opportunity'' and ''equality of outcome'' is an important controversial topic in politics and economics.]]
Both ''equality of outcome'' and ''equality of opportunity'' have been contrasted to a great extent. When evaluated in a simple context, the more preferred term in contemporary political discourse is ''equality of opportunity'' which the public, as well as individual commentators, see as the nicer or more &quot;well-mannered&quot;&lt;ref name=twsO45/&gt; of the two terms.&lt;ref name=twsO27&gt;{{cite news
 |author= Lexington
 |title= Fat cats and corporate jets: Why is it so unrewarding for politicians to bash the rich in America? 
 |publisher= ''The Economist''
 |quote= The point here is only that Americans do not seem to mind about the widening inequality of income and wealth as much as you might expect them to in current circumstances. ...
 |date= Jul 7 2011
 |url= http://www.economist.com/node/18928384
 |accessdate= 2011-07-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt; And the term ''equality of outcome'' is seen as more controversial which connotes [[socialism]] or possibly [[communism]] and is viewed skeptically. A mainstream political view is that the comparison of the two terms is valid, but that they are somewhat [[mutually exclusive]] in the sense that striving for either type of equality would require sacrificing the other to an extent, and that achieving ''equality of opportunity'' necessarily brings about &quot;certain inequalities of outcome.&quot;&lt;ref name=twsO26/&gt;&lt;ref name=twsO41&gt;{{cite news
 |author= Edward Seidman, Julian Rappaport (editors)
 |title= Redefining social problems
 |publisher= ''Plenum Press''
 |quote= (page 292+) Conflict 3: Equal Opportunity versus Equality of Outcome ...  By emphasizing on principle, the other conflicting one may have to be sacrificed.
 |year= 1986
 |url= http://books.google.com/books?id=sDtMoSq93gAC&amp;pg=PA292&amp;dq=equality+of+outcome+vs+equality+of+opportunity#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false
 |accessdate= 2011-07-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, striving for equal outcomes might require discriminating between groups to achieve these outcomes; or striving for equal opportunities in some types of treatment might lead to unequal results.&lt;ref name=twsO41/&gt; Policies that seek an equality of outcome often require a deviation from the strict application of concepts such as [[meritocracy]], and legal notions of [[equality before the law]] for all citizens.{{citation needed|date=February 2012}} 'Equality seeking' policies may also have a [[Redistribution (economics)|redistributive focus]].

The two concepts, however, are not always cleanly contrasted, since the notion of ''equality'' is complex. Some analysts see the two concepts not as polar opposites but as highly related such that they can not be understood without considering the other term. One writer suggested it was unrealistic to think about ''equality of opportunity'' in isolation, without considering inequalities of income and wealth.&lt;ref name=twsO28/&gt; Another agreed that it is impossible to understand ''equality'' without some assessment of outcomes.&lt;ref name=twsO45/&gt; A third writer suggested that trying to pretend that the two concepts were &quot;fundamentally different&quot; was an error along the lines of a [[conceit]].&lt;ref name=twsO35/&gt;

[[File:Nietzsche187a.jpg|thumb|right|Philosopher [[Friedrich Nietzsche]] in 1875.]]
In contemporary political discourse, of the two concepts, ''equality of outcome'' has sometimes been criticized as the &quot;politics of envy&quot; and is often seen as more &quot;controversial&quot; than ''equality of opportunity''.&lt;ref name=twsO45/&gt; One wrote that &quot;equality of opportunity is then set up as the mild-mannered alternative to the craziness of outcome equality.&quot;&lt;ref name=twsO45/&gt; One theorist suggested that an over-emphasis on either type of equality can &quot;come into conflict with individual freedom and merit.&quot;&lt;ref name=twsO43/&gt; The [[philosophy|philosopher]] [[Friedrich Nietzsche]] did not like either type of ''equality'' and was opposed in principle to [[democracy]], and he associated equality with what he termed &quot;slave morality.&quot;&lt;ref name=twsO43/&gt;

Critics of [[equality of opportunity]] note that while it is relatively easier to deal with unfairness for people with different races or genders, it is much harder to deal with [[social class]] since &quot;one can never entirely extract people from their ancestry and upbringing.&quot;&lt;ref name=twsO33&gt;{{cite news
 |author= Phillip Blond and John Milbank
 |title= No equality in opportunity: By synthesising old Tory and traditional left ideas a genuinely egalitarian society can be achieved
 |publisher= ''The Guardian''
 |quote= ...Society and government can refuse race or gender prejudice simply by not being prejudicial. But class is not so easy: one can never entirely extract people from their ancestry and upbringing....
 |date= 27 January 2010
 |url= http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2010/jan/27/inequality-opportunity-egalitarian-tory-left
 |accessdate= 2011-07-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, critics contend that efforts to bring fairness by equal opportunity are stymied by the difficulty of people having differing starting points at the beginning of the socio-economic competition. A person born into an upper-middle-class family will have greater advantages by the mere fact of birth than a person born into poverty.&lt;ref name=twsO33/&gt;

One newspaper account criticized discussion by politicians on the subject of ''equality'' as &quot;weasely&quot;, and thought that terms using the word were [[political correctness|politically correct]] and bland. Nevertheless, when comparing ''equality of opportunity'' with ''equality of outcome'', the sense was that the latter type was &quot;worse&quot; for society.&lt;ref name=twsO32&gt;{{cite news
 |author= Lucy Mangan
 |title= This week: Theresa May, Prince William and Kate Middleton and the Arnolds
 |publisher= ''The Guardian''
 |quote= &quot;Equality&quot;, you see, is a weaselly, politically correct word that means either nothing or, worse, &quot;equality of outcome&quot;. Imagine. From now on, we are going to have &quot;fairness&quot; and equality of opportunity. ...
 |date= 20 November 2010
 |url= http://www.guardian.co.uk/theguardian/2010/nov/20/this-week-theresa-may-prince-william
 |accessdate= 2011-07-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Equality of outcome may be incorporated into a philosophy that ultimately seeks equality of opportunity. Moving towards a higher equality of outcome (albeit not perfectly equal) can lead to an environment more adept at providing equality of opportunity by eliminating conditions that restrict the possibility for members of society to fulfill their potential. For example, a child born in a poor, dangerous neighborhood with poor schools and little access to healthcare may be significantly disadvantaged in his attempts to maximize use of talents, no matter his [[work ethic]]. Thus, even proponents of meritocracy may promote some level of equality of outcome in order to create a society capable of truly providing equality of opportunity.

While outcomes can usually be measured with a great degree of precision, it is much more difficult to measure the intangible nature of ''opportunities''. That is one reason why many proponents of equal opportunity use measures of equality of outcome to judge success. Analyst Anne Phillips argued that the proper way to assess the effectiveness of the hard-to-measure concept of ''equality of opportunity'' is by the extent of the actual and easier-to-measure ''equality of outcome''.&lt;ref name=twsO45/&gt; Nevertheless, she described single criteria to measure ''equality of outcome'' as problematic: the metric of &quot;preference satisfaction&quot; was &quot;ideologically loaded&quot; while other measures such as [[income]] or [[wealth]] were insufficient, according to her view, and she advocated an approach which combined data about resources, occupations, and roles.&lt;ref name=twsO45&gt;{{cite news
 |author= Anne Phillips
 |title= Defending Equality of Outcome
 |publisher= ''Journal of Political Philosophy''
 |year= 2004
 |pages= 1–19
 |url= http://eprints.lse.ac.uk/533/
 |accessdate= 2011-07-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

To the extent that incidental inequalities can be passed from one [[generation]] to another through substantial gifts and wealth [[inheritance]], some claim that equality of opportunity for children cannot be achieved without greater equality of outcome for parents. Moreover, access and opportunity to various social institutions is partially dependent on equality of outcome. Proponents argue that rigging equality of outcome can be a force preventing co-optation of non-economic institutions important to social control and policy formation, such as the legal system, media or the electoral process, by individuals and coalitions of wealthy people.

Greater equality of outcome is likely to reduce [[relative poverty]], purportedly leading to a more cohesive society. However, if taken to an extreme it may lead to greater [[absolute poverty]] if it negatively affects a country's [[GDP]] by damaging workers' sense of [[work ethic]] by destroying incentives to work harder. Critics of equality of outcome believe that it is more important to raise the [[standard of living]] of the poorest in absolute terms{{Citation needed|date=May 2009}}. Some critics additionally disagree with the concept of equality of outcome on philosophical grounds{{Citation needed|date=July 2009}} .

A related argument is often encountered in education and more specifically in the [[debates on the grammar school]] in the [[United Kingdom]] and in the debates on [[gifted education]] in various countries. According to that argument, people by nature have differing levels of ability and initiative which lead some to achieve better outcomes than others. Therefore, it is considered impossible to ensure equality of outcome without imposing ''in''equality of opportunity.

==The concept in political argument==
[[File:Sanzio 01 Plato Aristotle.jpg|thumb|right|275px|Debate about economic issues surrounding equality is as old as [[civilization]]. Painting: Ancient Greek philosophers [[Plato]] (left) and [[Aristotle]] by [[Raffaello Sanzio]] (1509).]]
The concept of ''equality of outcome'' is an important one in battling between differing political positions, since the concept of ''equality'', overall, was seen as positive and an important foundation which is &quot;deeply embedded in the fabric of modern politics.&quot;&lt;ref name=twsO26/&gt; There is much political jousting over what, exactly, equality means.&lt;ref name=twsO26/&gt; It is not a new phenomenon; battling between so-called ''haves'' and ''have-nots'' has happened throughout human civilization, and was a focus of philosophers such as [[Aristotle]] in his treatise ''[[Politics (Aristotle)|Politics]]''. Analyst Julian Glover in ''[[The Guardian]]'' wrote that ''equality'' challenged both left-leaning and right-leaning positions, and suggested that the task of left-leaning advocates is to &quot;understand the impossibility and undesirability of equality&quot; while the task for right-leaning advocates was to &quot;realise that a divided and hierarchical society cannot – in the best sense of that word – be fair.&quot;&lt;ref name=twsO31&gt;{{cite news
 |author= Julian Glover
 |title= The left should recognise that equality is undesirable: It sounds horribly rightwing, but a fair society may be one in which people have the right to strive for inequality
 |publisher= ''The Guardian''
 |quote= In the early days of New Labour it is said a media adviser whispered into an ambitious minister's ear after an interview: &quot;We don't say equality, we say fairness.&quot; The former reeked of socialism – all taxes, empowerment schemes and regulation. The latter was as inoffensive as a scented candle. Everyone can agree to be fair – which is the problem.
 |date= 10 October 2010
 |url= http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2010/oct/10/left-equality-fair-society-rightwing
 |accessdate= 2011-07-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Conservatives'''. Analyst Glenn Oliver wrote that conservatives believed in neither equality of opportunity nor outcome.&lt;ref name=twsO34&gt;{{cite news
 |author= Glenn Oliver
 |title= What is the difference between Liberalism and Socialism ? I'd appreciate general rather than party political answers.
 |publisher= ''The Guardian''
 |quote= Conservatives believe in inequality of opportunity and inequality of outcome. Liberals believe in equality of opportunity and inequality of outcome. Socialists believe in inequality of opportunity and equality of outcome. 
 |date= 
 |url= http://www.guardian.co.uk/notesandqueries/query/0,5753,-18035,00.html
 |accessdate= 2011-07-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In their view, life is not fair, but that is how it is. They criticize attempts to try to fight poverty by redistributive methods as ineffective since more serious cultural and behavioral problems lock poor people into poverty.&lt;ref name=twsO35/&gt; Sometimes right-leaning positions have been criticized by liberals for over-simplifying what is meant by the term ''equality of outcome'',&lt;ref name=twsO28/&gt; and for construing outcomes strictly to mean precisely equal amounts for everybody. Commentator Ed Rooksby in ''[[The Guardian]]'' criticized the right's tendency to oversimplify, and suggested that serious left-leaning advocates would not construe ''equality'' to mean &quot;absolute equality of everything&quot;.&lt;ref name=twsO26/&gt; Rooksby wrote that [[Karl Marx|Marx]] favored the position described in the phrase &quot;from each according to his ability, to each according to his need&quot;, and argued that this did not imply strict equality of things, but that it meant that people required &quot;different things in different proportions in order to flourish.&quot;&lt;ref name=twsO26/&gt;

* '''Libertarians''' such as [[Milton Friedman]] tend to see equality of outcome negatively and argue that any effort to cause equal outcomes would necessarily and unfortunately involve [[coercion]] by government. Friedman wrote that striving for ''equality of outcome'' leaves most people &quot;without equality and without opportunity.&quot;&lt;ref name=twsO47/&gt;

* '''Liberals'''. Analyst Glenn Oliver suggested that liberals believed in &quot;equality of opportunity and inequality of outcome.&quot;&lt;ref name=twsO34/&gt; One liberal position is that it is simplistic to define equality in strict outcomes since questions such as what is being equalized as well as huge differences in preferences and tastes and needs is considerable. They ask: exactly ''what'' is being equalized?&lt;ref name=twsO45/&gt; In the 1960s in the [[United States]], mainstream liberal president [[Lyndon Johnson]], examining the plight of [[African Americans]] locked in poverty, argued for ending policies which promoted [[Racial segregation|segregation]] and [[discrimination]] as well as steps to end &quot;economic injustice&quot; by turning &quot;equality of opportunity into equality of outcome,&quot;&lt;ref name=twsO37&gt;{{cite news
 |author= Kevin Boyle
 |title= James T. Patterson's &quot;Freedom Is Not Enough,&quot; reviewed by Kevin Boyle
 |publisher= ''The Washington Post''
 |quote= ... Now it was time to address the economic injustice that kept almost half the black population below the poverty line, to turn equality of opportunity into equality of outcome.... 
 |date= July 18, 2010
 |url= http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/07/16/AR2010071602877.html
 |accessdate= 2011-07-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt; that is, with programs to transfer wealth in varying amounts. Fairness is emphasized; one writer expounding a centrist position wrote &quot;people would neither be left to fend for themselves nor guaranteed equality of outcome - they would be given the tools they needed to achieve the American dream if they worked hard.&quot;&lt;ref name=twsO36&gt;{{cite news
 |author= Mark Penn
 |title= How Obama can find his center
 |publisher= ''Washington Post''
 |quote= The fundamental principle of centrism in the 1990s was that people would neither be left to fend for themselves nor guaranteed equality of outcome - they would be given the tools they needed to achieve the American dream if they worked hard....
 |date= January 31, 2011 
 |url= http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2011/01/31/AR2011013105146.html
 |accessdate= 2011-07-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt; There has been cynicism expressed in the media that neither side, including mainstream political positions, wants to do anything substantive, but that the nebulous term ''fairness'' is used to cloak the inactivity because it is difficult to measure what, in fact, &quot;fairness&quot; means. Julian Glover wrote that fairness &quot;compels no action&quot; and compared it to an &quot;atmospheric ideal, an invisible gas, a miasma,&quot; and to use an expression by [[Winston Churchill|Churchill]], a &quot;happy thought.&quot;&lt;ref name=twsO31/&gt;

* '''Socialists''' believe in &quot;inequality of opportunity and equality of outcome&quot; according to Oliver. They often see ''equality of outcome'' as a positive good, and that policies such as the [[redistribution of wealth]] as well as less extreme measures such as [[progressive taxation]] are morally good if they achieve equal outcomes. Although only a small minority of socialist theories advocate complete economic equality of outcome in practice ([[anarcho-communism]] is one such school) and instead see an ideal economy as one where remuneration is proportional to the degree of effort and personal sacrifice expended by individuals in the productive process.

==See also==
*[[Income inequality metrics]]
*[[Inequity aversion]]
*[[Equality under the law]]
*[[Relative deprivation]]
*[[Harrison Bergeron]]
*[[Communism]]
*[[Egalitarianism]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Equality Of Outcome}}
[[Category:Social inequality]]
[[Category:Egalitarianism]]
[[Category:Affirmative action]]
[[Category:Identity politics]]</text>
      <sha1>6t0uwwzlbw7pu85ws6za8i2vuz5rw9y</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
