<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Ethnic nationalism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9900</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522092395</id>
      <parentid>508173230</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T00:25:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>LoneWolf1992</username>
        <id>15575031</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Added a link</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7109">'''Ethnic nationalism''' or '''Ethnicism''' is a form of [[nationalism]] wherein the &quot;[[nation]]&quot; is defined in terms of [[ethnicity]]. Whatever specific ethnicity is involved, ethnic nationalism always includes some element of [[Kinship|descent]] from previous generations and the implied claim of '''ethnic essentialism''', i.e. the understanding of ethnicity as an essence that remains unchanged over time.

The central theme of ethnic nationalists is that &quot;..nations are defined by a shared heritage, which usually includes a common language, a common faith, and a common ethnic ancestry.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;Muller, Jerry Z. &quot;Us and Them.&quot; Current  Issue 501 Mar/Apr 2008 9-14&lt;/ref&gt;  It also includes ideas of a [[culture]] shared between members of the group, and with their ancestors, and usually a shared language; however it is different from purely cultural definitions of &quot;the nation&quot; (which allow people to become members of a nation by [[cultural assimilation]]) and a purely linguistic definitions (which see &quot;the nation&quot; as all speakers of a specific language). [[Herodotus]] is the first who stated the main characteristics of ethnicity, with his famous account of what defines [[Greeks|Greek]] identity, where he lists kinship (Greek: ὅμαιμον - ''homaimon'', &quot;of the same blood&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0057%3Aentry%3Do%28%2Fmaimos ὅμαιμος], Henry George Liddell, Robert Scott, ''A Greek-English Lexicon'', on Perseus&lt;/ref&gt;), language (Greek: ὁμόγλωσσον - ''homoglōsson'', &quot;speaking the same language&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0057%3Aentry%3Do%28mo%2Fglwssos ὁμόγλωσσος], Henry George Liddell, Robert Scott, ''A Greek-English Lexicon'', on Perseus&lt;/ref&gt;), cults and customs (Greek: ὁμότροπον - ''homotropon'', &quot;of the same habits or life&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0057%3Aentry%3Do%28mo%2Ftropos ὁμότροπος], Henry George Liddell, Robert Scott, ''A Greek-English Lexicon'', on Perseus)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Herodotus, 8.144.2: ''&quot;The kinship of all Greeks in blood and speech, and the shrines of gods and the sacrifices that we have in common, and the likeness of our way of life.&quot;''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Athena S. Leoussi, Steven Grosby, ''Nationalism and Ethnosymbolism: History, Culture and Ethnicity in the Formation of Nations'', Edinburgh University Press, 2006, p. 115&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ideology==
The central political tenet of ethnic nationalism is that [[ethnic group]]s can be identified unambiguously, and that each such group is entitled to [[self-determination]]. 

The outcome of this right to self-determination may vary, from calls for self-regulated administrative bodies within an already-established society, to an [[autonomous entity]] separate from that society, to a [[sovereign state]] removed from that society. In international relations, it also leads to policies and movements for [[irredentism]] — to claim a common nation based upon ethnicity.

In scholarly literature, ethnic nationalism is usually contrasted with [[civic nationalism]]. Ethnic nationalism bases membership of the nation on descent or heredity—often articulated in terms of common blood or kinship—rather than on political membership. Hence, nation-states with strong traditions of ethnic nationalism tend to define nationality or citizenship by [[jus sanguinis]] (the law of blood, descent from a person of that nationality) while countries with strong traditions of civic nationalism tend to define nationality or citizenship by [[jus soli]] (the law of soil, birth within the nation-state). Ethnic nationalism is therefore seen as exclusive, while civic nationalism tends to be inclusive. Rather than allegiance to common civic ideals and cultural traditions, then, ethnic nationalism tends to emphasise   narratives of common descent.

The theorist [[Anthony D. Smith]] uses the term 'ethnic nationalism' for non-[[Western culture|Western]] concepts of nationalism as opposed to Western views of a nation defined by its geographical territory. Diaspora studies scholars extend this non-geographically bound concept of &quot;nation&quot; among [[diasporic]] communities, at times using the term ethnonation or ethnonationalism to describe a conceptual collective of dispersed ethnics.&lt;ref&gt;Safran, William (January 2008). &quot;[http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/bpl/nana/2008/00000014/00000001/art00009 Language, ethnicity and religion: a complex and persistent linkage].&quot; ''Nations and Nationalism'' 14(1) 171–190. {{doi|10.1111/j.1469-8129.2008.00323.x}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ethnic nationalism is also present in many states' immigration policies in the form of [[repatriation laws]].  States such as [[Armenia]], [[Bulgaria]], [[Croatia]], [[Finland]], [[Germany]], [[Greece]], [[Hungary]], [[Italy]], [[Republic of Ireland|Ireland]], [[Israel]], [[Romania]], [[Serbia]], and [[Turkey]] provide automatic or rapid citizenship to members of diasporas of their own dominant ethnic group, if desired.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;  For example, [[Italy]] allows citizenship almost entirely on the basis of jus sanguinis (having an Italian Ancestor).  Israel's [[Law of Return]], grants every Jew the right to 
settle in Israel and automatically acquire citizenship.&lt;ref&gt;Hadary, Amnon. &quot;Reclaiming Zionism.&quot; Judaism Vol. 48. Issue 1Winter 1999 1-14.&lt;/ref&gt; 
In [[Germany]], citizenship is open to [[ethnic Germans]].{{Clarify|date=December 2011}} According to the [[Greek nationality law]], Greeks born abroad may transmit citizenship to their children from generation to generation indefinitely.

On the other hand, [[civic nationalism]] defines membership as an individual's duty to observe given laws and in turn receive legal privileges.

A [[nation-state]] for the ethnic group derives political legitimacy from its status as [[homeland]] of that ethnic group, from its protective function against [[colonization]], [[persecution]] or [[racism]], and from its claim to facilitate the shared cultural and social life, which may not have been possible under the ethnic group's previous status as an [[ethnic minority]].

==See also==
*[[Ethnic group]]
*[[Identity politics]]
*[[Diaspora politics]]
*[[Essentialism]]
*[[Nationalism]]
*[[Ethnic nepotism]]
*[[Ethnocentrism]]
*[[Ethnocracy]]
*[[Historiography and nationalism]]
*[[Nationalization of history]]
*[[Identity politics]]
*[[List of irredentist claims or disputes]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.nationalismproject.org/ The Nationalism Project]
{{Nationalism}}
{{Ethnicity}}
{{Ethnic nationalism}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Nationalism}}
[[Category:Nationalism|Ethnic]]
[[Category:Ethnocentrism]]
[[Category:Politics and race]]
[[Category:Ethnicity in politics]]
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Ethnic conflict]]

[[bg:Етнически национализъм]]
[[de:Völkischer Nationalismus]]
[[eo:Etna naciismo]]
[[fr:Ethnisme]]
[[nl:Etnisch nationalisme]]
[[ru:Национализм (типология)]]
[[tr:Etnik milliyetçilik]]</text>
      <sha1>saptp6ntyytvusc6du1j7cs0x9qqt25</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
