<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Fahrenheit 9/11 controversy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1056228</id>
    <revision>
      <id>511341850</id>
      <parentid>511341572</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-08T07:18:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Instaurare</username>
        <id>1364504</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Children of members of Congress serving in Iraq */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="37506">{{Use mdy dates|date=May 2012}}
{{DISPLAYTITLE:''Fahrenheit 9/11'' controversy}}
[[File:Fahrenheit 911 poster.jpg|thumb|''[[Fahrenheit 9/11]]'' poster]]
The documentary film '''''[[Fahrenheit 9/11]]''''' generated, and even courted controversy since it was first announced, even before its release just prior to the [[U.S. presidential election, 2004]].
The film by [[Michael Moore]] criticizes the [[George W. Bush administration|Bush administration]]'s attempt to pursue [[Osama bin Laden]] in the aftermath of the [[September 11, 2001, attacks]], as well as the [[Iraq War]]. 
Bush defenders and some commentators have criticized the film for factual and contextual inaccuracies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://today.msnbc.msn.com/id/5342052/ns/today-entertainment/t/fahrenheit-web-leak-stirs-controversy/ |title= 'Fahrenheit 9/11' Web leak stirs controversy |publisher=MSNBC}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://articles.cnn.com/2004-06-25/entertainment/moore.film_1_bin-michael-moore-iraq-war?_s=PM:SHOWBIZ |title= Moore defends ‘Fahrenheit’ |publisher=CNN}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Ray Bradbury's title dispute ==
The title of the film refers to [[Ray Bradbury|Ray Bradbury's]] novel ''[[Fahrenheit 451]]'' and the September 11 attacks of 2001. The ''Fahrenheit 451'' reference is emphasized by the film's tagline &quot;''The temperature where freedom burns''&quot; (compare with ''Fahrenheit 451's'' tagline, &quot;''The temperature at which books burn''&quot;). Moore has stated that the title came from the subject of an e-mail he received from a fan shortly after September 11.

Bradbury was upset by what he considered the appropriation of his title.  He wanted the film renamed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/5324876/|title= &quot;Fahrenheit 451&quot; author wants title back|work=Hardball with Chris Matthews|date=June 29, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://www.msnbc.msn.com/ID/5319756/ |title=Call it a tale of two 'Fahrenheits'|publisher=MSNBC|date= June 29, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Attacks on the film  ==
=== ''Move America Forward'''s letter-writing campaign===
The conservative political action group [[Move America Forward]] mounted a letter-writing campaign pressuring theater chains not to screen the film, which it compared to &quot;an [[al-Qaeda]] training video.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.philly.com/mld/philly/entertainment/columnists/howard_gensler/8933698.htm?1c |author=Howard Gensler|title=Moore controversy over '9/11 Fahrenheit'|work=Philadelphia Daily News|date=June 16, 2004 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20041119212806/http://www.philly.com/mld/philly/entertainment/columnists/howard_gensler/8933698.htm?1c |archivedate = November 19, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;We've been causing them [the cinemas] an enormous amount of aggravation&quot;, said group member and talk radio host [[Melanie Morgan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://archive.salon.com/ent/feature/2004/06/23/fahrenhype/index_np.html | title =Michael Moore terrorizes the Bushies!|author=John Gorenfeld|work=Salon|date=June 23, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Citizens United's FEC challenge ===
[[Citizens United]], a conservative group run by [[David Bossie]], filed a complaint before the [[Federal Election Commission]] charging that ads for the film constitute political advertising and thus may not be aired 60 days before an election or 30 days before a party convention. On August 5, the FEC unanimously dismissed the complaint finding no evidence that the movie's ads had broken the law.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fec.gov/press/press2004/20040806mur.html FEC finding] August 6, 2004&lt;/ref&gt; A further complaint filed in 2005 was also rejected.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fec.gov/press/press2005/20050809mur.html FEC finding] August 9, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

== Controversy over the film's content ==

Shailagh Murray described ''Fahrenheit 9/11'' in ''[[The Wall Street Journal]]'' as a &quot;harshly satirical and controversial portrait of the Bush presidency.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Murray, Shailagh. &quot;Fahrenheit 9/11 Has Recruited Unlikely Audience: U.S. Soldiers&quot;, ''The Wall Street Journal''. July 12, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; Stephen Dalton of ''[[The Times]]'' wrote that the movie &quot;hits enough of its satirical targets to qualify as an important and timely film.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Dalton, Stephen. [http://entertainment.timesonline.co.uk/tol/arts_and_entertainment/film/dvd/article493041.ece Fahrenheit 9/11], ''The Times''. October 16, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Desson Thomson]] says &quot;there is more to ''Fahrenheit 9/11'' than partisan ridicule. ... What's remarkable here isn't Moore's political animosity or ticklish wit. It's the well-argued, heartfelt power of his persuasion.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Thomson, Desson. &quot;Fahrenheit 9/11: Connecting with a Hard Left'', ''Washington Post''. May 18, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; Author and blogger [[Andrew Sullivan]] expressed the opposite view, writing that Moore's film is &quot;deeply corrosive of the possibility of real debate and reason in our culture.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Sullivan, Andrew. [http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,994630,00.html Blinded By The Light], ''Time'' magazine. July 12, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; Canadian journalist [[Linda McQuaig]] wrote in response to Sullivan: &quot;Hell, the media shut down real debate long ago. It is precisely because the debate has been so thoroughly corroded by the mainstream media ... that Moore's film is being so gratefully received by so many.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;McQuaig, Linda. &quot;Fahrenheit 9/11 Places Real Issues in the Spotlight&quot;, ''The Toronto Star''. July 11, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; Denis Hamill considers ''Fahrenheit 9/11'' to be a &quot;corrective to the daily drumbeat of right-wing [[talk radio]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;hamill&quot;&gt;Hamill, Denis. [http://www.nydailynews.com/archives/ny_local/2004/06/29/2004-06-29_moore_s_message_delivered__b.html Moore's Message Delivered, Big-Time], New York ''Daily News''. June 29, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[English-American]] journalist and literary critic [[Christopher Hitchens]] and [[U.S. Democratic Party|Democratic]] politician [[Ed Koch]] contend that ''Fahrenheit 9/11'' contains distortions and untruths and is propaganda.&lt;ref name=&quot;slate&quot;&gt;Hitchens, Christopher. [http://www.slate.com/id/2102723 Unfairenheit 9/11: The lies of Michael Moore], ''Slate'' magazine. June 21, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;koch&quot;&gt;Koch, Edward. &quot;Moore’s propaganda film cheapens debate, polarizes nation&quot;, ''World Tribune''. June 28, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;lateline&quot;&gt;Jones, Terry. [http://www.abc.net.au/lateline/content/2004/s1162379.htm Truth or tale, experts analyse 'Fahrenheit 9/11'], ABC ''Lateline''. July 26, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; Hitchens also compared Michael Moore to [[Leni Riefenstahl]] in his critique for ''Slate'' magazine: &quot;Here we glimpse a possible fusion between the turgid routines of [[MoveOn.org]] and the filmic standards, if not exactly the filmic skills, of [[Sergei Eisenstein]] or Leni Riefenstahl.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;slate&quot; /&gt; He later labeled Moore &quot;a completely promiscuous opportunist [and] extremely callous person.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;scarborough&quot; /&gt;

Author and political commentator Peter Holding called Hitchens' analogy &quot;hysterical, unfair and offensive,&quot; adding that &quot;some of the criticism directed towards Moore's film displays the very same characteristics for which Moore's film has been criticised&quot;. Fellow ''Slate'' columnist and Iraq war critic [[David Edelstein]], though generally supportive of the film, wrote ''Fahrenheit 9/11'' &quot;is an act of counterpropaganda that has a boorish, bullying force&quot;, but called it a &quot;legitimate abuse of power.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Edelstein, David. [http://www.slate.com/id/2102859/ Proper Propaganda: Michael Moore's Fahrenheit 9/11 is unfair and outrageous. You got a problem with that?], ''Slate'' magazine. June 24, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; Prominent left-wing intellectual [[Bernard-Henri Lévy]] agreed the war was &quot;a bad idea&quot;, but was sympathetic to the [[neoconservative]] point of view and disagreed with what he perceived to be the film's &quot;core&quot; argument, that &quot;we have no reason to be interfering&quot; in the Middle East.&lt;ref&gt;Broudy, Oliver. [http://www.salon.com/books/int/2006/01/23/levy/index2.html America's unlikely defender], ''Salon'' magazine. April 6, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Joe Scarborough]] alleges that Moore has ducked criticism and dodged interviews from both himself and Hitchens.&lt;ref name=&quot;scarborough&quot;&gt;Scarborough Country for June 30, [http://www.webcitation.org/5sl6q6ps3 Transcript], MSNBC ''Scarborough Country'', July 1, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

Moore has published both a list of facts and sources for ''Fahrenheit 9/11'' and a document establishing agreements between the points made in his film and the findings of the [[National Commission on Terrorist Attacks Upon the United States|9/11 Commission]] (the independent, bipartisan panel directed by Congress and Bush to investigate the facts and circumstances surrounding the September 11 attacks).&lt;ref&gt;Moore, Michael. [http://www.michaelmoore.com/warroom/f911notes/ Factual Back-Up For Fahrenheit 9/11], michaelmoore.com, July 10, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Bush reading to school children ===
[[Image:George_W._Bush_being_told_about_second_plane_hitting_WTC.png|thumb|right|US President George W. Bush being told about the second plane hitting the [[World Trade Center]] in a classroom at Emma E. Booker Elementary School.]]
Early on in the film, Moore explains that Bush continued reading &quot;[[The Pet Goat]]&quot; with a classroom of second graders at [[Emma E. Booker Elementary School]] in [[Sarasota, Florida]] for an extended period of time after being told of the attacks.

The school's principal, Gwendolyn Tose'-Rigell, explained, &quot;I don't think anyone could have handled it better. What would it have served if he had jumped out of his chair and ran out of the room?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title=Sarasota principal defends Bush from 'Fahrenheit 9/11' portrayal | publisher=THE ASSOCIATED PRESS |date=2004-06-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some of the schoolchildren, now grown, have expressed similar views; Mariah Williams, one of the students, stated in 2011 that, &quot;I'm just glad he didn't get up and leave because then I would have been more scared and confused.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/nation/article/0,8599,2069327,00.html#ixzz1LKYKu5YU The Interrupted Reading: The Kids with George Bush on 9/11], Time.com, May 3, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

A [[9/11 Commission]] Staff Report entitled ''Improvising a Homeland Defense'' said: &quot;The President felt he should project strength and calm until he could better understand what was happening.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.9-11commission.gov/staff_statements/staff_statement_17.pdf| title=Improvising a Homeland Defense| format=PDF}}, page 22&lt;/ref&gt;

According to senior White House correspondent [[Bill Sammon]] and his inside look at the Bush administration's response to 9/11, ''Fighting Back: The War on Terrorism from Inside the White House'', Press Secretary [[Ari Fleischer]] was holding up a legal pad upon which he had written a message telling Bush not to say anything yet.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title=Suddenly, a time to lead | author=Bill Sammon |work=THE WASHINGTON TIMES |date=2002-10-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Alleged discrepancy on Osama's presumed innocence ===
[[File:Christopher Hitchens crop 2.jpg|thumb|Christopher Hitchens]]
According to Christopher Hitchens, Moore had argued in a previous public debate that [[Osama bin Laden]] was to be presumed innocent until proven guilty, and thus questions the treatment of bin Laden in the film. &quot;Something – I cannot guess what, since we knew as much then as we do now – has since apparently persuaded Moore that Osama Bin Laden is as guilty as hell. Indeed, Osama is suddenly so guilty and so all-powerful that any other discussion of any other topic is a dangerous 'distraction' from the fight against him. I believe that I understand the convenience of this late conversion.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;slate&quot; /&gt; Hitchens was subsequently invited to appear on Joe Scarborough's [[MSNBC]] talk show, ''[[Scarborough Country]]'', at which point a tape recording of his debate with Moore at the [[Telluride Film Festival]] in 2002 was replayed.&lt;ref name=&quot;scarborough&quot; /&gt;

{{bquote|'''Moore:''' It seems as if he and his group were the ones who did this, then they should be tracked down, captured, and brought to justice.&lt;br&gt;
'''Hitchens:'''  What is the &quot;if&quot; doing in that last sentence of yours?&lt;br&gt;
'''Moore:'''  Well, all people are innocent until proven guilty in this country. ...  Even the worst piece of scum.&lt;br&gt;
'''Hitchens:'''  I feel I have to press you on that.  You regard it as an open question, the responsibility of Osama bin Laden?&lt;br&gt;
'''Moore:'''  Until anyone is convicted of any crime, no matter how horrific the crime, they are innocent until proven guilty.  And as Americans...&lt;br&gt;
'''Hitchens:'''  No, that's all I asked you.&lt;br&gt;
'''Moore:'''  Never leave that position.&lt;br&gt;
'''Hitchens:''' I'm sorry. So bin Laden's claims of responsibility strike you as the ravings of a clown's, say?}}

When the video ended, Hitchens proceeded to explain: &quot;Why does someone who thought that Osama was innocent and Afghanistan was no problem suddenly switch in this way?  Because unless he says that he was dead wrong all along and Osama Laden was innocent and wronged, he can't say that everything else is a distraction from the hunt for Osama.&quot; Host Joe Scarborough agreed with Hitchens and criticised Moore for inconsistency, accusing him of &quot;hypocrisy&quot; for assuming bin Laden is innocent one minute &quot;and yet, in this movie, at the very beginning, he criticizes George Bush for not assuming the [[bin Laden family]] is somehow guilty, then letting them out of the country.&quot;

''[[Flak Magazine|Flak]]'' magazine editor Stephen Himes, after watching ''Scarborough Country'' and reviewing a transcript of the Telluride debate, wrote that Hitchens had misconstrued Moore's remarks: &quot;Hitchens actually performs some [[Bill Clinton|Clintonian]] semantic gymnastics here. Moore's ''if'' is not intending 'I think Osama is innocent and the Afghan war is unjustified;' he's trying to make an argument for American [[due process]]: 'If he and his group were the ones who did this, then they should be tracked down, captured and brought to justice'.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;himes&quot;&gt;Himes, Stephen. [http://flakmag.com/film/fahrenheit2.html Doublethink: Michael Moore, Christopher Hitchens, George Orwell and the Soul of the American Left], ''Flak'' magazine. August 6, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; Film critic Christopher Parry also took issue with Hitchens' interpretation of Moore's remarks, writing &quot;If you've got to build a case against [[Jeffery Dahmer]], you've got to build a case against Bin Laden.&quot;

{{bquote|Allow me to explain Moore's motivation, as if it needed explaining to anyone with a concept of logic, law and due process. Bin Laden ''is'' innocent until proven guilty in the eyes of the law. That ''is'' the American Way. Indeed, it's the World Way. But in order to prove his guilt, one must build a case, capture him and put him to trial... But in ''Fahrenheit 9/11'', Moore has a different point to make. What he's saying in ''Fahrenheit 9/11'' is, why, exactly, when the pursuit of Osama Bin Laden is completely justified, have only 14,000 troops been sent after him, while ten times that number have been sent into Iraq to take over a country that had ''nothing to do with 9/11''?&lt;ref name=&quot;parry&quot;&gt;Parry, Christopher. [http://efilmcritic.com/hbs.cgi?reviewer=1 Slate's Chris Hitchens does a hatchet job on Michael Moore], eFilmCritic, September 27, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

[[CNN]] news anchor [[Daryn Kagan]] asked Moore why, if he is so willing to uphold the law, he could also be critical of the Bush administration for pursuing Osama bin Laden at the same time. Moore replied:

{{bquote|Because if you have a suspect and the suspect gets away, the police, or our military, have a right to go after and get that suspect. In fact, they should go get the suspect. And [[Richard A. Clarke|Richard Clarke]]'s point, and my point is, is that they make a half-hearted effort ... because they didn't want to divert resources from what their main goal was, which was to go in and invade Iraq. And that's what they've been about since Day 1.&lt;ref&gt;Kagan, Daryn. [http://www.webcitation.org/5sl6Wxlzl Interview With Michael Moore], CNN ''Live Today'', June 25, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

=== Saudi flights ===
Moore implicates the [[White House]] in allowing relatives of Osama bin Laden to leave the United States without being interviewed at length by the [[FBI]]. In his narration in the movie, Moore states that &quot;At least six private jets and nearly two dozen commercial planes carried the Saudis and the Bin Ladens out of the U.S. after September 13.&quot; Moore based this statement on the research of [[Craig Unger]], author of ''[[House of Bush, House of Saud]]'', whom he interviewed for the film. Passenger lists can be found at the House of Bush website.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.houseofbush.com/files.php |title=The Bush-Saudi Files: The Documents|author=Craig Unger|work=House of Bush, House of Saud |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070927231352/http://www.houseofbush.com/files.php |archivedate = 2007-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Approval of the flights====
[[File:Richard clarke.jpg|thumb|Richard Clarke]]
Christopher Hitchens points to a statement by former [[counterterrorism]] chief [[Richard A. Clarke|Richard Clarke]] when interviewed by ''[[The Hill (newspaper)|The Hill]]'' newspaper in May 2004, in which &quot;he, and he alone, took the responsibility for authorizing [the] Saudi departures.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;slate&quot; /&gt; Hitchens says that Moore interviewed Clarke and &quot;either he didn't ask Clarke, who authorized those flights, or Clarke told him it was me and only me, and he didn't think it was good enough to use. ... Either way, that's below the level of trash TV, trash journalism.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;scarborough&quot; /&gt; After quitting his White House position, Clarke became a prominent critic of the Bush administration's war on terrorism. Hitchens contends that the film does not mention Clarke's remarks so that it can criticize Bush for not going after Bin Laden's family, while holding up Clarke as a heroic, anti-war figure.&lt;ref name=slate /&gt;

The filmmaker defended himself in an interview with [[ABC News]] correspondent [[Jake Tapper]], answering: &quot;Actually I do [display the] article and it's blown up 40 foot on the screen, you can see Richard Clarke's name right there saying that he approved the flights based on the information the FBI gave him. It's right there, right up on the screen. I don't agree with Clarke on this point. Just because I think he's good on a lot of things doesn't mean I agree with him on everything.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;tapper&quot;&gt;Tapper, Jake. [http://abcnews.go.com/print?id=116504 Having His Say … Michael Moore Calls Fahrenheit 9/11 a Valid, Alternate View], ABC News. June 25, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

Moore, on his website and in ''The Official Fahrenheit 9/11 Reader'', points to additional statements by Richard Clarke, also published in ''The Hill'', which he believes support his contention that the White House approved the flights.&lt;ref name=&quot;official_reader&quot;&gt;Moore, Michael. ''The Official Fahrenheit 9/11 Reader'', Penguin Books, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; The following is a chronological summary:

* '''September 3, 2003''': In his testimony before the [[Senate Judiciary Committee]]'s [[U.S. Senate Judiciary Subcommittee on Terrorism, Technology and Homeland Security|Subcommittee on Terrorism]], Clarke said: &quot;It is true that members of the bin Laden family were among those who left. We knew that at the time. I can't say much more in open session, but it was a conscious decision with complete review at the highest levels of the State Department and the [[FBI]] and the [[White House]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;York, Byron. [http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1282/is_18_55/ai_109411350 How did assorted bin Ladens get out of America after September 11?] ''National Review''. September 29, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''March 24, 2004''': In testimony to the [[9/11 Commission]], Clarke indicated that the request was not abnormal, &quot;The Saudi embassy, therefore, asked for these people to be evacuated; the same sort of thing that we do all the time in similar crises, evacuating Americans. The request came to me and I refused to approve it.&quot; He goes on to explain that the FBI eventually approved the flights and he describes conversations in which the FBI has said that there was no one who left on those flights who the FBI now wants to interview.

* '''March 24, 2004''': &quot;I would love to be able to tell you who did it, who brought this proposal to me, but I don't know. The two – since you press me, the two possibilities that are most likely are either the [[U.S. State Department|Department of State]] or the [[White House Chief of Staff]]'s Office. But I don't know.&quot;

* '''May 25, 2004''': In an interview with ''The Hill'' newspaper, published the following day, Clarke said: &quot;I take responsibility for it. I don't think it was a mistake, and I'd do it again.&quot; He went on to say that &quot;It didn't get any higher than me... On 9&amp;ndash;11, 9&amp;ndash;12 and 9&amp;ndash;13, many things didn't get any higher than me. I decided it in consultation with the FBI.&quot;

====The FBI's denial that it had a role in approving the flights====
On May 18, 2004, Washington newspaper ''The Hill'' quoted [[FBI]] spokesman on counterterrorism [[John Iannarelli]] as denying that the FBI had any &quot;role in facilitating these flights one way or another.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;wholetblsleave&quot;&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20040629082831/http://www.hillnews.com/news/051804/binladen.aspx &quot;Who let bin Ladens leave U.S.?&quot;]; Bolton, Alexander; ''The Hill''. May 18, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; The FBI's denial of involvement was repeated to ''The Hill'' by another spokesperson, Donna Spiser, in a May 26, 2004 article. She is quoted as saying &quot;We haven't had anything to do with arranging and clearing the flights.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;clarkeclaimsresp&quot;&gt;Bolton, Alexander. &quot;Clarke claims responsibility&quot;, ''The Hill''. May 26, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; She states that the FBI's involvement was limited to interviewing those people on the flight it thought were of interest: &quot;We did know who was on the flights and interviewed anyone we thought we needed to.&quot;

====Alleged lack of cooperation from the White House====

The May 18 article in ''The Hill'', which was published prior to Clarke's May 25 claim of responsibility, quoted 9/11 Commission vice-chair [[Lee H. Hamilton]] as saying: &quot;We don't know who authorized [the flights]. We've asked that question 50 times.&quot; A May 26 article in ''The Hill'' quoted another Commission member, Tim Roemer, as being unconvinced by Clarke's claim of sole responsibility for approving the flights: &quot;It doesn't seem that Richard Clarke had enough information to clear it... I just don't think that the questions are resolved, and we need to dig deeper... Clarke sure didn't seem to say that he was the final decisionmaker. I believe we need to continue to look for some more answers.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;clarkeclaimsresp&quot; /&gt;

Allegations concerning the Bush administration's refusal to provide information to the 9/11 Commission about the Saudi flights are disputed. The May 18, 2004 article in ''The Hill'' says that Commission vice-chairman Lee Hamilton &quot;disclosed the administration's refusal to answer questions on the sensitive subject during a recent closed-door meeting with a group of Democratic senators, according to several Democratic sources.&quot; It also says that Republican Commission member [[John Lehman]] &quot;said... that he told the senators the White House has been fully cooperative.&quot; President Bush, who met privately with the Saudi Arabian ambassador on the morning of Sept. 13, 2001, is suspected of personally authorizing the controversial flights while all other air travel had been halted.&lt;ref name=&quot;wholetblsleave&quot; /&gt;

====Interviewing of bin Laden relatives====
Moore interviews author Craig Unger and retired FBI agent Jack Cloonan, both of whom say bin Laden family members were not questioned in a serious manner at length before being allowed to leave. The [[National Commission on Terrorist Attacks Upon the United States|September 11 Commission]] has found that 22 of the 26 people on the &quot;bin Laden&quot; flight were interviewed before being allowed to leave the country with many being asked &quot;detailed questions&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.9-11commission.gov/staff_statements/staff_statement_10.pdf|title=Immediate Response to 9/11: The Saudi Flights|pages=12|format=PDF|work=National Commission On Terrorist Attacks Upon the United States}}&lt;/ref&gt; A September 2, 2004 CNN news article reported that &quot;However, in a recent interview with the AP, bin Laden's estranged sister-in-law said she does not believe that family members have cut [Osama] off entirely. [[Carmen Binladin]], who has changed the spelling of her name and lives in [[Switzerland]], said bin Laden is not the only religious brother in the family, and she expects his sisters to support him as well. 'They are very close to Osama,' she said.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.archive.org/web/*/http://www.cnn.com/2004/WORLD/meast/09/02/binladen.wealth.ap/|title=Bin Laden's wealth not the force behind 9/11|author=The Associated Press|date=September 2, 2004|publisher=CNN}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Declassified FBI documents====

In June 2007, [[Judicial Watch]] released partially declassified FBI documents on the flights obtained under a [[Freedom of Information Act (United States)|Freedom of Information Act]] request.&lt;ref name=&quot;jwatch&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.judicialwatch.org/jwnews/062207.htm
|title = JW Releases New FBI Documents: Osama bin Laden May Have Chartered Saudi Flight Out of U.S. after 9/11
|author=Federal Bureau of Investigation
|publisher=[[Judicial Watch]]
|date = June 22, 2007
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eric Lichtblau, writing in the ''[[New York Times]]'', said the heavily [[redaction|redacted]] documents &quot;do not appear to contradict directly any of those central findings [of the Sept. 11 commission] but they raise some new questions about the episode.&quot; In several cases, &quot;Saudi travelers were not interviewed before departing the country, and F.B.I. officials sought to determine how what seemed to be lapses had occurred.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Lichtblau, Eric. [http://www.nytimes.com/2005/03/27/politics/27exodus.html New Details on F.B.I. Aid for Saudis After 9/11] ''New York Times''. March 27, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; Judicial Watch President [[Tom Fitton]] said: &quot;The documents contain numerous errors and inconsistencies which prove the FBI conducted a slapdash investigation of the Saudi flights.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;jwatch&quot; /&gt;

=== War in Iraq ===
[[File:Iraq, Saddam Hussein (222).jpg|thumb|Saddam Hussein]]
The film suggests that the invasion of Iraq was an illegitimate attack on a sovereign nation – an unnecessary attack against an exaggerated threat. It makes a case against components of the [[Bush Doctrine]], specifically against the concepts of [[pre-emptive war]] combined with American [[unilateralism]]. The film also contends that the focus of the United States should have been directed elsewhere.

Christopher Hitchens criticized the film for not mentioning the history of repression, aggression, [[war crime]]s and the general state of [[human rights in Saddam Hussein's Iraq]], nor Iraq's noncompliance with numerous United Nations resolutions.&lt;ref name=slate /&gt; Hitchens writes, &quot;in this peaceable kingdom, according to Moore's flabbergasting choice of film shots, children are flying little kites, shoppers are smiling in the sunshine, and the gentle rhythms of life are undisturbed. Then—wham! From the night sky come the terror weapons of American [[imperialism]]. Watching the clips Moore uses, and recalling them well, I can recognize various Saddam palaces and military and police centers getting the treatment. But these sites are not identified as such. In fact, I don't think [[Al Jazeera]] would, on a bad day, have transmitted anything so utterly propagandistic.&quot;&lt;ref name=slate /&gt; While interviewing Hitchens on his show, Scarborough claimed to be outraged at Moore's portrayal of the [[Iraqi insurgency]], claiming Moore's film suggests &quot;those killing Americans in Iraq aren't the enemy, but rather they are the revolution and the [[Minutemen]], who are sure to win their battle against the occupation&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;scarborough&quot; /&gt; and that &quot;Moore says that the enemy is George Bush and Saddam Hussein and [[Abu Musab al-Zarqawi|Mr. Zarqawi]] and Mr. Bin Laden are no problem. ... Indeed, they are the Minutemen. They're the staunch American revolutionaries.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;scarborough&quot; /&gt;

Moore has frequently stated his opinion that Saddam was a brutal tyrant, though this opinion is not mentioned in the film. He said calling attention to Saddam's crimes was unnecessary considering the corporate media had continually pressed that point themselves, making it public knowledge.
{{cquote|Who doesn't know that Saddam was a bad guy? The media did a wonderful job hammering that home every day in order to convince the public that they should support the war. For 20 seconds in this film, I become essentially the only person to say, I want you to take a look at the human beings that were living in Iraq in 2003. [...] Anyone who takes that and says that I'm trying to say that Saddam's Iraq was some utopia is just a crackpot.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Fierman|first=Daniel|title=The Passion Of Michael Moore|work=Entertainment Weekly|date=2004-07-09|url=http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,659914,00.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Christopher Hitchens criticizes Moore for stating, in his film, that Iraq had not killed or attacked an American: &quot;Moore asserts that Iraq under Saddam had never attacked or killed or even threatened (his words) any American. I never quite know whether Moore is as ignorant as he looks, or even if that would be humanly possible.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;slate&quot; /&gt; Hitchens writes that [[Palestine|Palestinian]] terrorists [[Muhammad Zaidan]] and [[Abu Nidal]] had been free to move in and out of [[Baghdad]], and that Saddam's armed forces had exchanged fire and killed American soldiers during the first [[Gulf War]]. When interviewed by Jake Tapper, Moore denied having said Hussein's regime had not ever killed an American, insisting his movie had been misquoted: &quot;That isn't what I said. Quote the movie directly. ''Murdered''. The government of Iraq did not commit a premeditated murder on an American citizen.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;tapper&quot; /&gt; His narration is reproduced verbatim in ''The Official Fahrenheit Reader'', including a chapter on critiques and supporting evidence.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Iraq,&quot; Moore's narration proceeds, is &quot;a nation that had never attacked the United States. A nation that had never threatened to attack the United States. A nation that had never murdered a single American citizen.&quot; Moore, Michael. ''The Official Fahrenheit 9/11 Reader'', Penguin Books, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Children of members of Congress serving in Iraq====
[[File:Mark Kennedy, official photo portrait, color.jpg|thumb|Congressman Mark Kennedy]]
Moore says that only one member of Congress had a child serving in Iraq: [[United States Army|Army]] [[Staff Sergeant]] Brooks Johnson, the son of Senator [[Tim Johnson (U.S. Senator)|Tim Johnson]] (D-SD).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.michaelmoore.com/words/fahrenheit-911-facts/factual-back-up-for-fahrenheit-911-section-six|title=Factual Back-Up for Fahrenheit 9/11: Section Six|publisher=Michael Moore}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Karen Kucher, when ''Fahrenheit 9/11'' was nearing release to the home-video market, two additional Congressmen's children were stationed in Iraq: the son of Congressman [[Duncan L. Hunter]] (R-CA), [[United States Marine Corps|USMC]] Lieutenant [[Duncan D. Hunter]] (who was later elected to Congress himself); and the son of [[Joe Wilson (U.S. politician)|Joe Wilson]] (R-SC), [[United States Army National Guard|Army National Guard]] [[Captain (land)|Captain]] Alan Wilson.&lt;ref name=&quot;SDUnion-Tribune&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.signonsandiego.com/uniontrib/20040913/news_1m13duncan.html|title=Serving on two fronts|work=[[San Diego Union-Tribune]]|author=Karen Kucher}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Fahrenheit 9/11'' also used footage of Moore confronting various members of Congress, encouraging them to enlist their own children to fight in Iraq. Moore approached Congressman [[Mark Kennedy (politician)|Mark Kennedy]] (R-MN) and showed Kennedy giving Moore a quizzical, confused look. Kennedy expressed displeasure about his portrayal, saying he offered to help Moore and also indicated he had a nephew serving in Afghanistan, but this was edited out of the film.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A849-2004Jun23_3.html|title='Fahrenheit 9/11' Is a Red-Hot Ticket|work=Washington Post|authors=Hanna Rosin and Mike Allen|date=June 24, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Peter Damon lawsuit ===

Moore's inclusion of a 10-second clip with amputee Peter Damon has been criticized. Damon said the filmmaker &quot;should be ashamed of himself&quot; for claiming that soldiers were deceived into supporting the Iraq war and for using his injuries as reason to oppose the conflict. Damon &quot;agree[s] with the President 100%. A lot of the guys down at [[Walter Reed Hospital|Walter Reed]] feel the same way.&quot; According to Damon's doctor, Lt. Col. Chester Buckenmaier, Moore took &quot;a very positive thing we're doing for soldiers&quot; who lost limbs and &quot;used it to tell a lie.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;sisk&quot;&gt;Sisk, Richard. [http://www.nydailynews.com/archives/news/2004/08/15/2004-08-15_g_i__pans__9-11__role__hurt_.html G.I. pans '9/11' role], New York ''Daily News''. August 15, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; Responding to the criticism, associate producer Joanne Doroshow said, &quot;Anybody who has seen the film knows we have nothing but the deepest respect for the soldiers who were wounded. One of the purposes of the movie was to examine the impossible situation they were put into and to raise questions about why they were sent there.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;sisk&quot; /&gt;

Peter Damon sued Moore in federal court for $85 million, alleging that the film gave a false impression and was [[defamation|defamatory]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,197637,00.html|title=Iraq Vet Sues Michael Moore for Misleading Interview in 'Fahrenheit 9/11'|author=Jennifer Fermino|publisher=Fox News|date=June 1, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moore's attorney argued in response that the film quoted Damon verbatim and did not take his statements out of context nor give a false impression. The judge agreed and dismissed Damon's suit.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iht.com/articles/ap/2006/12/20/america/NA_GEN_US_Veteran_Lawsuit_Fahrenheit_9-11.php|title=US judge rejects Iraq war veteran's lawsuit over 'Fahrenheit 9/11'|author=Associated Press|work=International Herald Tribune|date=December 20, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; In March 2008, the [[United States Court of Appeals for the First Circuit|First Circuit Court of Appeals]] unanimously affirmed the ruling in Moore's favor.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbc.ca/arts/film/story/2008/03/28/moore-suit.html Disabled veteran's suit against Michael Moore dismissed], CBC News. March 28, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Unauthorized copying==
Unauthorized copying of the film was widespread. An early version taped at a cinema was distributed using the [[peer-to-peer file sharing]] protocol [[BitTorrent (protocol)|BitTorrent]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20040705013810/http://www.sundayherald.com/43167 Moore: pirate my film, no problem] ''The Sunday Herald'' July 4, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; The distributors expressed unhappiness and suggested potential legal action, but according to the ''[[Sunday Herald]]'', Moore's responded, &quot;I don't have a problem with people downloading the movie and sharing it with people as long as they're not trying to make a profit off of my labor&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.afterdawn.com/news/archive/5386.cfm | title=Moore: Go ahead, pirate my movie | date=July 5, 2004 | author=Iain S Bruce | work=Sunday Herald }}&lt;/ref&gt; A &quot;mint copy&quot; of the film possibly appeared on the [[Lions Gate Entertainment|Lions Gate]] website itself, reported ''[[The Inquirer]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theinquirer.net/?article=17066 Michael Moore gives thumbs up to file sharers] [[The Inquirer]] July 7, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; Unlicensed screenings were also held in [[Cuba]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/film/3534028.stm Fahrenheit clear of Oscar threat] [[BBC News]] August 4, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=35em}}

==External links==
* [http://www.michaelmoore.com/warroom/ ''Fahrenheit 9/11'' War Room] Contains notes, sources and Michael Moore's response to various critics of his film
* [http://www.democracynow.org/article.pl?sid=04/06/29/1420223 Interview with Urban Hamid] Embedded filmmaker who shot some of the Iraqi footage in the film
* [http://slate.msn.com/id/2102723/ Unfairenheit 9/11] A critical essay by [[Christopher Hitchens]]
** [http://www.overcast.pwp.blueyonder.co.uk/f911/hitch-moore.htm A Defense of ''Fahrenheit 9/11''] A point-by-point response to Christopher Hitchens
* [http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/5251769/site/newsweek Under the Hot Lights] by [[Michael Isikoff]]
** [http://www.michaelmoore.com/warroom/smackdown/index.php?id=6 Michael Isikoff and Newsweek Magazine Deceive the Public About ''Fahrenheit 9/11''] By [[Michael Moore]]
*[http://www.thenation.com/doc.mhtml?i=20040712&amp;s=klawans&amp;c=1 By Way of Deception] by [[Stuart Klawans]]
*[http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn/A43295-2001Jun8?language=printer The Wrong Way to Fix the Vote] by [[Greg Palast|Gregory Palast]]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Fahrenheit 9/11 Controversy}}
[[Category:Michael Moore]]
[[Category:2004 controversies]]
[[Category:Media-related controversies in the United States]]
[[Category:Political controversies in the United States]]</text>
      <sha1>27p2e2hlq02gezkel9yvukrlpm4gzfz</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
