<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Favourite</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5670063</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521114811</id>
      <parentid>520447226</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T21:46:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>108.36.133.159</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20721">{{dablink|For other uses of &quot;favorite&quot; or &quot;favourite&quot;, see [[Favorite (disambiguation)]].}}
[[Image:Count-Duke of Olivares.jpg|thumb|[[Equestrian portrait of Duke de Olivares|Equestrian portrait of the Count-Duke of Olivares]] by [[Diego Velázquez]].]]

A '''favourite''' ([[British English]]&lt;ref&gt;Also [[Australian English]], [[New Zealand English]], [[South African English]], [[Indian English]] and [[Canadian English]]&lt;/ref&gt;), or '''favorite''' ([[American English]]), was the intimate companion of a ruler or other important person. In medieval and [[Early Modern Europe]], among other times and places, the term is used of individuals delegated significant political power by a ruler. It is especially a phenomenon of the 16th and 17th centuries, when government had become too complex for many hereditary rulers with no great interest or talent for it, and political constitutions were still evolving.  The period 1600-1660 saw particular successions of all-powerful minister-favourites in much of Europe, particularly in Spain, England, France and Sweden.&lt;ref&gt;Elliott:5, summarising the work of French historian Jean Bérenger&lt;/ref&gt;  
The term is also sometimes employed by conservative writers who want to avoid terms such as &quot;[[royal mistress]]&quot;, or &quot;friend&quot;, &quot;companion&quot; or &quot;lover&quot; of either sex. Several favourites had sexual relations with the monarch (or their spouse), but the feelings of the monarch for the favourite covered the full gamut from a simple faith in the favourite's abilities, through various degrees of emotional affection and dependence, to sexual infatuation. 

The term has an inbuilt element of disapproval, and is defined by the ''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]'' as &quot;One who stands unduly high in the favour of a prince&quot;, citing Shakespeare:&quot;Like favourites/ Made proud by Princes&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[Much Ado about Nothing]] 3.1.9&lt;/ref&gt;

==Rises and falls of favourites==
[[Image:GeorgeVilliers.jpg|thumb|[[George Villiers, 1st Duke of Buckingham|The Duke of Buckingham]] by [[Rubens]]]]
Favourites inevitably tended to incur the envy and loathing of the rest of the [[nobility]], and [[monarch]]s were sometimes obliged by political pressure to dismiss or execute them; in the Middle Ages nobles often rebelled in order to seize and kill a favourite. Too close a relationship between monarch and favourite was seen as a breach of the natural order and hierarchy of society. Since many favourites had flamboyant &quot;over-reaching&quot; personalities, they often led the way to their own downfall with their rash behaviour. As the opinions of the [[gentry]] and [[bourgeoisie]] grew in importance, they too often strongly disliked favourites. Dislike from all classes could be especially intense in the case of favourites who were elevated from humble, or at least minor, backgrounds by royal favour. Titles and estates were usually given lavishly to favourites, who were compared to [[mushroom]]s because they sprang up suddenly overnight, from a bed of [[excrement]]. The King's favourite [[Piers Gaveston, 1st Earl of Cornwall|Piers Gaveston]] is a &quot;night-grown mushrump&quot; (mushroom) to his enemies in [[Christopher Marlowe]]'s ''[[Edward II (play)|Edward II]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[[s:Edward the Second]]&lt;/ref&gt; 

Their falls could be even more sudden, although after about 1650, executions tended to give way to quiet retirement. Favourites who came from the higher nobility, such as [[Robert Dudley, 1st Earl of Leicester|Leicester]], [[Francisco Goméz de Sandoval y Rojas, Duke of Lerma|Lerma]], [[Gaspar de Guzmán, Count-Duke of Olivares|Olivares]], and [[Axel Oxenstierna|Oxenstierna]], were often less resented and lasted longer. Successful minister-favourites also usually needed networks of their own favourites and relatives to help them carry out the work of government - [[Cardinal Richelieu|Richelieu]] had his &quot;créatures&quot; and Olivares his &quot;hechuras&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Elliott:6&lt;/ref&gt; Oxenstierna and [[William Cecil, 1st Baron Burghley|William Cecil]], who both died in office, successfully trained their sons to succeed them. 

The favourite can often not be easily distinguished from the successful royal administrator, who at the top of the tree certainly needed the favour of the monarch, but the term is generally used of those who first came into contact with the monarch through the social life of the court, rather than the business of politics or administration. Figures like [[Thomas More]], William Cecil and [[Jean-Baptiste Colbert]], whose accelerated rise through the administrative ranks owed much to their personal relations with the [[monarch]], but who did not attempt to behave like grandees of the nobility, were also often successful.  [[Cardinal Wolsey]] was one figure who rose through the administrative hierarchy, but then lived extremely ostentatiously, before falling suddenly from power. In the [[Middle Ages]] in particular, many royal favourites were promoted in the church, English examples including Saints [[Dunstan]] and [[Thomas Becket]]; Bishops [[William Waynflete]], [[Robert Burnell]] and [[Walter Reynolds]]. [[Antoine Perrenot de Granvelle|Cardinal Granvelle]], like his father, was a trusted Habsburg minister who lived grandly, but not really a favourite, not least because his career was mostly spent away from the monarch. 

Some favourites came from very humble backgrounds: [[Archibald Armstrong]], [[jester]] to [[James I of England]] infuriated everyone else at court but managed to retire a wealthy man, unlike [[Robert Cochrane (architect)|Robert Cochrane]], a [[stonemason]] (probably a senior one, more like an [[architect]] than an [[artisan]]) who became [[Earl of Mar]] before the [[Kingdom of Scotland|Scottish]] nobles revolted against him, and hanged him and other &quot;low-born&quot; favourites of [[James III of Scotland]].  [[Olivier le Daim]], the barber of [[Louis XI of France|Louis XI]], acquired a title and important military commands before being executed on vague charges brought by nobles shortly after his master died, without the knowledge of the new king. It has been claimed that le Daim's career was the origin of the term, as ''favori'' (the French word) first appears around the time of his death in 1484. ''Privado'' in Spanish was older, but was later partly replaced by the term ''valido''; in Spanish both terms were less derogatory than in French and English.&lt;ref&gt;Elliott:1&lt;/ref&gt;

Such rises from &quot;menial&quot; positions became progressively harder as the centuries progressed; one of the last families able to jump the widening chasm between servants and nobility was that of [[Louis XIV of France|Louis XIV]]'s valet, [[Alexandre Bontemps]], whose descendants, holding the office for a further three generations, married into many great families, even eventually including the extended royal family itself.  Queen Victoria's [[John Brown (servant)|John Brown]] came much too late; the devotion of the monarch and ability to terrorize her household led to hardly any rise in social or economic position.

==Decline of the favourite==
[[Image:Kardinaal de Richelieu.jpg|thumb|[[Cardinal Richelieu]], one of the most successful from the golden age of the favourite]] 
In England, the scope for giving political power to a favourite was reduced by the growing importance of [[British Parliament|Parliament]]. After the &quot;mushroom&quot; [[George Villiers, 1st Duke of Buckingham|Buckingham]] was assassinated by [[John Felton]] in 1628, Charles I turned to [[Thomas Wentworth, 1st Earl of Strafford]], who had been a leader of Parliamentary opposition to Buckingham and the King, but had become his supporter after Charles made concessions. Strafford can therefore hardly be called a favourite in the usual sense, even though his relationship with Charles became very close. He was also from a well-established family, with powerful relations. After several years in power, Strafford was [[impeachment|impeached]] by a Parliament now very hostile to him. When this process failed, they passed a [[bill of attainder]] for his execution without trial, and put enough pressure on Charles that, to his subsequent regret, he signed it, and Strafford was executed in 1641. There were later minister-favourites in England, but they knew that the favour of the monarch alone was not sufficient to rule, and most also had careers in Parliament. 

In France, the movement was in the opposite direction. On the death of [[Cardinal Mazarin]] in 1661, the 23-year-old Louis XIV determined that he would rule himself, and not allow the delegation of power to ministers that had marked the previous 40 years. The [[absolute monarchy]] pioneered by [[Cardinal Richelieu]], Mazarin's predecessor, was to be led by the monarch himself. Louis had many powerful ministers, notably Colbert heading the Finances, and [[François-Michel le Tellier, Marquis de Louvois|Louvois]] the Armies, but overall direction was never delegated, and no subsequent French minister ever equaled the power of the two Cardinals. 

The [[Spanish Habsburgs]] were not capable of so much energy, but when Olivares was succeeded by his nephew [[Luis de Haro]], the last real ''valido'', the control of government into a single pair of hands was already weakened.

==Favourites in literature==
[[Image:Princepotemkin.jpg|thumb|left|Prince [[Grigori Potemkin]]]]
Favourites were the subject of much contemporary debate, some of it involving a certain amount of danger for the participants.  There were a large number of English plays on the subject, amongst the best known being Marlowe's ''Edward II'', in which Piers Gaveston is a leading character, and ''[[Sejanus His Fall]]'' (1603), for which [[Ben Jonson]] was called before the [[Privy Council]], accused of &quot;Popery and treason&quot;, as the play was claimed by his enemies to contain allusions to the contemporary court of [[James I of England]]. [[Sejanus]], whose career under Tiberius was vividly described by [[Tacitus]], was the subject of numerous works all around Europe.&lt;ref&gt;Elliott:2-3&lt;/ref&gt; [[Shakespeare]] was more cautious, and with the exceptions of [[Falstaff]], badly disappointed in his hopes of becoming a favourite, and Cardinal Wolsey in ''[[Henry VIII (play)|Henry VIII]]'', he gives no major parts to favourites.&lt;ref&gt;Blair Worden in Elliott:171&lt;/ref&gt;  

[[Francis Bacon]], almost a favourite himself, devoted much of his [[essay]] ''On Friendship'' to the subject, no doubt writing with some care as a rising politician under Elizabeth I:

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;It is a strange thing to observe, how high a rate great kings and monarchs do set upon this fruit of friendship, whereof we speak: so great, as they purchase it, many times, at the hazard of their own safety and greatness. For princes, in regard of the distance of their fortune from that of their subjects and servants, cannot gather this fruit, except (to make themselves capable thereof) they raise some persons to be, as it were, companions and almost equals to themselves, which many times sorteth to inconvenience. The modern languages give unto such persons the name of favorites,&lt;!-- this spelling in the original --&gt; or privadoes ....  And we see plainly that this hath been done, not by weak and passionate princes only, but by the wisest and most politic that ever reigned; who have oftentimes joined to themselves some of their servants; whom both themselves have called friends, and allowed other likewise to call them in the same manner; using the word which is received between private men.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Published 1597, perhaps the earliest use of the word in English, it is missed by the [[OED]], who give the Shakespeare use quoted above, perhaps written in 1598.[http://www.authorama.com/essays-of-francis-bacon-27.html Essay in full]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Writing of [[George III of England|George III's]] old tutor, [[John Stuart, 3rd Earl of Bute|the Earl of Bute]], who became [[Prime Minister]], [[Lord Macaulay|Macaulay]] wrote in 1844: &quot;He was a favourite; and favourites have always been odious in this country.  No mere favourite had been at the head of the government since the dagger of Felton had reached the heart of the Duke of Buckingham&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Essay on &quot;The Earl of Chatham&quot;, quoted Elliott:1&lt;/ref&gt;

==Some famous favourites==
[[File:0024MAN-Antinous.jpg|190px|thumb|Bust of Antinous from [[Patras]], ([[National Archaeological Museum of Athens]])]]
[[Image:BNMsFr2643FroissartFol97vExecHughDespenser.jpg|thumb|upright|The execution of Hugh, the younger Despenser, from [[Froissart of Louis of Gruuthuse (BnF Fr 2643-6)|a manuscript of Froissart]].]]
[[Image:Sarah Churchill, Duchess of Marlborough by Sir Godfrey Kneller, Bt.jpg|thumb|right|[[Sarah Churchill, Duchess of Marlborough]] wearing the symbol of her office and authority: the gold key. Sir [[Godfrey Kneller]], 1702&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.npg.org.uk/live/search/portrait.asp?search=ss&amp;sText=Sarah+Churchill&amp;LinkID=mp02960&amp;rNo=1&amp;role=sit Portraits of Sarah Churchill]. [[National Portrait Gallery (United Kingdom)]]. Retrieved on 7 August 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
[[Image:Manuel Godoy Spain.jpg|thumb|[[Manuel de Godoy]], Príncipe de la Paz, portrait by [[Goya]].]]

*Biblical characters with many elements of the favourite are [[David]] (of Saul) and [[Joseph (Hebrew Bible)|Joseph]] (of Pharaoh).
*[[Jiru]], favourite of [[Emperor Gaozu of Han|Gaozu of Han]] in China (2nd century BC)
*[[Sejanus]], favourite of [[Tiberius]], who executed him in 31.
*[[Marcus Aurelius Cleander|Cleander]], [[freedman]] favourite of [[Commodus]], who executed him in 190.
*[[Antinous]], favourite of Emperor [[Hadrian]], d. 130.
*[[Ibn Ammar]] came to the attention of the Muslim ruler of the ''[[taifa]]'' of [[Seville]] through his poetry and skill at [[chess]], but tried to seize part of the kingdom for himself, and was strangled personally by his monarch in 1086.
*[[Piers Gaveston]], 1st Earl of Cornwall, possibly the lover of [[Edward II of England]], was given high office, including being [[Regent]] when Edward went abroad, but was executed after capture by rebels in 1312.
*[[Hugh the younger Despenser]], also possibly the lover of Edward II, was captured and killed in a rebellion led by [[Isabella of France|Edward's Queen]] in 1326.
*[[Álvaro de Luna]] executed in 1453 after pressure from the nobility of [[Crown of Castile|Castile]]
*[[Robert Cochrane (architect)|Robert Cochrane]], favourite of [[James III of Scotland]], taken by a cabal of nobles led by [[Archibald Douglas, 5th Earl of Angus|Archibald &quot;Bell the Cat&quot; Douglas, 5th Earl of Angus]] and hanged along with his confederates from [[Lauder]] bridge.
*[[Robert Dudley, 1st Earl of Leicester]] favourite of [[Elizabeth I of England]] for 30 years, rumoured lover and long-term candidate for her hand; also a leading [[patron]] and statesman. He was succeeded by his rasher stepson [[Robert Devereux, 2nd Earl of Essex]] who was executed in 1601 after an abortive coup.
*&quot;[[Les Mignons]]&quot; (&quot;the Darlings&quot;), a group of favourites of [[Henry III of France]]
*[[Francisco Goméz de Sandoval y Rojas, Duke of Lerma]], died 1625, the first &quot;valido&quot;, a semi-official title for Spanish favourites. Ran Spain for 20 years before falling from favour and being replaced by [[Gaspar de Guzmán y Pimentel, Count-Duke of Olivares]] who ran Spain for a further 20 years.
*[[Charles de Luynes]] in France, the ''[[Les Mignons|mignon]]'' of [[Louis XIII of France|Louis XIII]], arranged the murder of the Queen Mother's favourite [[Concino Concini]] in 1617. Concini owed his favour to his wife's close relationship with [[Marie de' Medici]].
*[[George Villiers, 1st Duke of Buckingham]], very influential politically and assassinated in 1628, was favourite to both [[James I of England|James I]] and his son [[Charles I of England]]. James, who had been effectively orphaned as a baby, and was probably homosexual, was [[Personal relationships of James I of England|very prone to dependency]] on favourites, although whether sexual activity took place remains unclear. [[Esmé Stewart, 1st Duke of Lennox]], 37 to James' 13 when they met, was forced into exile by opponents, and eventually succeeded by [[Robert Carr, 1st Earl of Somerset]]; despite titles and wealth, both ended unhappily.
*[[Axel Oxenstierna]] ran the government of [[Sweden]], very successfully, for over 40 years until his death in 1654, when his [[Erik Oxenstierna|son]] took over.
*[[Henri Coiffier de Ruzé, Marquis of Cinq-Mars]] in France, executed in 1642 after leading a conspiracy against his rival and patron [[Cardinal Richelieu]], who governed France for 18 years.
*[[Cardinal Mazarin]], governed France for almost 20 years until his death in 1661; [[Louis XIV]]'s public decision that he would thence forward &quot;govern alone&quot; marked the end of the golden age of the favourite.
*[[Corfitz Ulfeldt (1606-1664)|Corfitz Ulfeldt]] became son-in-law to [[Christian IV of Denmark]] before trying to kill him, and then defecting to Swedish service.
*[[Sidney Godolphin, 1st Earl of Godolphin]], a transitional figure as a protégé of [[Charles II of England]] who also had a successful career in [[Parliament of England|Parliament]].
*[[Marie-Anne de la Trémoille, princesse des Ursins]] (died 1722) through force of character enjoyed extraordinary power successively in the courts of France, Spain and the English [[Jacobitism|Jacobite]] exiles.
*[[Constantine Phaulkon]], Greek first counsellor of King [[Narai]] of [[Ayutthaya Kingdom|Ayutthaya]], his influences over the King led to the [[Siamese revolution of 1688]].
*[[Sarah Churchill, Duchess of Marlborough]], domineering friend of Queen [[Anne of Great Britain]], eventually supplanted by her cousin [[Abigail Masham, Baroness Masham]].
*[[Alexander Menshikov]], lifelong best friend of [[Peter I of Russia]], came from the most humble origins and attained enormous power, not least after the Tsar's death, when he was ''de facto'' ruler for two years until he was banished to [[Siberia]].
*[[Johann Friedrich Struensee]] in Denmark, the royal doctor, who ran the government of the schizophrenic [[Christian VII of Denmark|Christian VII]] whilst having an affair with [[Caroline Matilda of Wales|the Queen]], before being executed in 1772.
*[[Heshen]], who amassed an enormous fortune during the latter part of the reign of Chinese emperor [[Qianlong]].
*[[Grigori Alexandrovich Potemkin]] (died 1791) was the lover of the Empress [[Catherine II of Russia]] for two years, but continued to have enormous power in the government for a further fifteen.
*[[Platon Zubov|Platon Alexandrovich Zubov]] was the last favourite of the Empress [[Catherine II of Russia]] who later took substantial part in the murder of her [[Paul I of Russia|son and heir]].
*[[Marie-Louise, princesse de Lamballe]] (died 1792) was the dear friend of [[Marie-Antoinette]] and stayed faithful to her until the very moment of her gory death.
*[[Gabrielle de Polastron, duchesse de Polignac]] (died 1793) was the favourite of the last queen of France, Marie-Antoinette, and one of the few women that [[King Louis XVI]] liked and trusted.
*[[Manuel de Godoy]], whose unpopularity led, along with Napoleon's dynastic ambitions, to the abdication of [[Charles IV of Spain]] in 1808, after which Godoy spent over 40 years in exile.
*[[Grigori Rasputin]], Mystic favourite of the last [[House of Romanov|Royal Family]] of [[Russia]], murdered in 1916

===Mistresses===
{{see also|Royal mistress|Maîtresse-en-titre|Mistress (lover)}}
*[[Hong Yu]], favourite of [[Emperor Hui of Han]]
*[[Margaret Erskine]], mistress of [[James V of Scotland]] and mother of [[James Stewart, 1st Earl of Moray]]
*[[Louise de La Vallière]], mistress of Louis XIV of France, succeeded by [[Françoise-Athénaïs, marquise de Montespan|Madame de Montespan]]
*[[Françoise d'Aubigné, marquise de Maintenon|Madame de Maintenon]] refused to become the mistress of Louis XIV, and became his second, [[morganatic]] wife.
*[[Madame de Pompadour]], mistress of [[Louis XV of France]]
*[[Madame du Barry]], later lover of [[Louis XV of France]], guillotined during the [[French Revolution]]
*[[Mary Boleyn]], one of the many mistresses of Henry VIII, sister of his second wife [[Anne Boleyn]] and cousin to his fifth wife [[Katherine Howard]].

==See also==
*[[Cardinal-nephew]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|20em}}

==References==
*J.H. Elliott and LWB Brockliss, eds, ''The World of the Favourite'',1999, Yale UP, ISBN 0-300-07644-4

[[Category:Royalty]]
[[Category:Monarchy]]
[[Category:Modern Europe]]
[[Category:Government]]
[[Category:Royal favourites|*]]

[[ca:Privat]]
[[cs:Favorit]]
[[es:Valido]]
[[eo:Favoratulo]]
[[fr:Favori]]
[[gl:Valido]]
[[he:מועדף]]
[[pl:Faworyt]]
[[pt:Favorito]]
[[ru:Фаворитизм]]
[[sh:Miljenik]]
[[sv:Gunstling]]
[[uk:Фаворитизм]]</text>
      <sha1>5kqr439z95va6mm80scepew3emezcze</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
