<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Fiscal conservatism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4032505</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521354941</id>
      <parentid>519117663</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-04T13:32:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bobrayner</username>
        <id>156494</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>not a reliable source</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20223">{{refimprove|date=August 2012}}
{{Conservatism}}
'''Fiscal conservatism''' is a [[fiscal policy]] that advocates avoiding [[deficit spending]]. Fiscal conservatives often consider reduction of overall [[government spending]] and [[national debt]] as well as ensuring [[balanced budget]] of paramount importance. [[Free trade]], [[deregulation]] of the economy, [[Tax cut|lower taxes]], and other conservative policies are also often but not necessarily affiliated with fiscal conservatism.{{cn|date=August 2012}}

==United States==
===Late 18th century===
The [[Democratic-Republican Party]] of [[Thomas Jefferson]] supported a weak [[central government]] and a more ''[[laissez-faire]]'' approach than that of the [[Federalist Party]] of Jefferson's rival [[Alexander Hamilton]]. They opposed Hamilton's plan to pay off the debts owed by the states for the expense of the American Revolution, because some of the debt was held by financiers and speculators (rather than the original holders) and because most of the debt was held by northern states. Hamilton passed his legislation and set up taxes to pay the debts. In exchange, he agreed to let Jefferson move the nation's capital to [[Washington, D.C.]]

===Early 19th century===
Jefferson strongly opposed having any national debt, but he relented in 1803 for the sake of the [[Louisiana Purchase]]. [[James Madison]] and [[James Monroe]] were elected by the Democratic-Republican Party, but after the fiscal disasters of the [[War of 1812]], they came to support most Federalist positions and decided that the nation needed a central bank and a steady income flow from tariffs.

===Mid-to-late 19th century ===
In the mid-19th century, a new fiscal conservative political party emerged, the [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party]]. Unlike the modern fiscal conservatives, these fiscal conservatives were [[paleoconservatism|paleoconservative]] supporters of [[protectionism]] and [[tariffs]], similar in some ways to today's [[Reform Party of the United States of America|Reform Party]].

They were also generally supporters of big business and (internally) laissez-faire economics, although by 1890 they had been convinced into supporting [[Sherman Anti-Trust Act]] and the [[Interstate Commerce Commission]] following massive complaints.

===Early 20th century===
In the early 20th century fiscal conservatives were often at odds with [[progressivism|progressive]]s who desired economic reform.
During the 1920s, President [[Calvin Coolidge]]'s pro-business economic policies were credited for the successful period of economic growth known as the &quot;Roaring Twenties.&quot;  His actions, however, may have been due more to a sense of [[federalism]] than fiscal conservatism: [[Robert Sobel]] notes that &quot;[a]s Governor of Massachusetts, Coolidge supported wages and hours legislation, opposed child labor, imposed economic controls during World War I, favored safety measures in factories, and even worker representation on corporate boards.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Coolidge and American Business|url=http://www.calvin-coolidge.org/html/coolidge_and_american_business.html|publisher=Calvin-Coolidge.org|accessdate=18 April 2012|author=Robert Sobel|year=1988}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reagan era===
{{Main|Reaganomics}}
Fiscal Conservatism was rhetorically promoted during the presidency of [[Ronald Reagan]] (1981–1989). During Reagan's tenure, income tax rates of the top personal [[tax bracket]] dropped from 70% to 28% in 7 years,&lt;ref name=&quot;The Historical Lessons of Lower Tax Rates&quot;&gt;{{cite web | author = Daniel J. Mitchell, Ph.D. | url=http://www.heritage.org/Research/Taxes/BG1086.cfm|title= The Historical Lessons of Lower Tax Rates|publisher = The Heritage Foundation | date = July 19, 1996 | accessdate=2007-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; while payroll taxes increased as well as the effective tax rates on the lower two income quintiles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.ssa.gov/OACT/ProgData/taxRates.html |title= Social Security and Medicare Tax Rates | publisher = Social Security Administration| date = July 10, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.cbo.gov/ftpdoc.cfm?index=5324&amp;type=0&amp;sequence=0 |title= Effective Federal Tax Rates: 1979–2001 | publisher = Bureau of Economic Analysis | date = July 10, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Real [[Gross domestic product]] (GDP) growth recovered strongly after the 1982 recession and grew during Reagan's remaining years in office at an annual rate of 3.4% per year.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gross Domestic Product&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url= http://www.bea.gov/national/xls/gdpchg.xls |title= Gross Domestic Product | publisher = Bureau of Economic Analysis| date = May 31, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Unemployment peaked at over 10.7% percent in 1982 then dropped during the rest of Reagan's terms, and inflation significantly decreased.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|url=http://encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761560259_2/Ronald_Reagan.html|title=Ronald Reagan|publisher=Microsoft Corporation|year= 2007|accessdate=2007-07-27|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5kwcDdeGk|archivedate=2009-10-31|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; Federal tax receipts nearly doubled from $517 billion in 1980 to $1,032 billion in 1990. A net job increase of about 16 million also occurred (about the rate of population growth).

According to a [[United States Department of the Treasury]] non-partisan economic study, the major tax bills enacted under Reagan, as a whole, significantly reduced (~-1% of GDP) government tax receipts.&lt;ref name=taxtable&gt;{{cite journal|author=[http://www.treasury.gov/offices/tax-policy/offices/ota.shtml Office of Tax Analysis]|publisher=[[United States Department of the Treasury]]|title=Revenue Effects of Major Tax Bills|date=2003, rev. Sept 2006|url=http://www.ustreas.gov/offices/tax-policy/library/ota81.pdf|id=Working Paper 81, Table 2|accessdate=2007-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Economic Recovery Tax Act of 1981]] was a massive (~-3% of GDP) decrease in revenues (the largest tax cuts ever enacted)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Thorndike, Joseph J|publisher=Taxhistory.org|title=Historical Perspective: The Reagan Legacy|date=14 June 2004|url=http://www.taxhistory.org/thp/readings.nsf/cf7c9c870b600b9585256df80075b9dd/3df8b954567e6c8c85256eb300588d4b?OpenDocument|accessdate=2007-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of Reagan's second term the national debt held by the public ballooned from 26 percent of the GDP in 1980 to 41 percent in 1989. By 1988, the debt totaled $2.6 trillion, in part because of both increased military spending at the end of the [[Cold War]] and according to some, the tax cuts. The country owed more to foreigners than it was owed, and the United States moved from being the world's largest international creditor to the world's largest debtor nation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A26402-2004Jun8.html | work=The Washington Post | title=Reagan Policies Gave Green Light to Red Ink | date=June 9, 2004 | accessdate=May 2, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ross Perot===
{{Main|Ross Perot presidential campaign, 1992}}
In the 1992 Presidential election, [[Ross Perot]], a successful American businessman, ran as a third-party candidate.  Despite significant campaign stumbles, and the uphill struggles involved in mounting a third-party candidacy, Perot received 18.9% of the popular vote (the largest percentage of any third-party candidate in modern history), largely on the basis of his central platform plank of limited-government, balanced-budget fiscal conservatism.

===Clinton era===
{{Main|Clintonomics}}
While the mantle of fiscal conservatism is most commonly claimed by Republicans and [[Libertarians]], it is also claimed by many [[Democratic Party (United States)#Centrists|centrist]] or [[Factions in the Democratic Party (United States)#Moderate Democrats|moderate]] [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democrats]] who often refer to themselves as &quot;[[New Democrats]]&quot;. Former President [[Bill Clinton]], who was a New Democrat and part of the fiscally conservative [[Third Way (centrism)|Third Way]] advocating [[Democratic Leadership Council]], is a prime example of this as his administration along with the Democratic-majority congress of 1993 passed on a party-line vote the [[Omnibus Budget Reconciliation Act of 1993]] which cut government spending, created a 36% individual income tax bracket, raised the top tax bracket, which encompassed the top 1.2% earning taxpayers, from 31% to 39.6%, and created a 35% income tax rate for corporations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bill Clinton’s economic legacy&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/business/1110165.stm|title= Bill Clinton’s economic legacy|author=Steve Schifferes|publisher=BBC News|date= January 15, 2001 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 1993 Budget Act also cut taxes for fifteen million low-income families and 90% of small businesses. Additionally, during the Clinton years, the [[PAYGO]] (pay-as-you-go) system originally introduced with the passing of the [[Budget Enforcement Act of 1990]] (which required that all increases in direct spending or revenue decreases be offset by other spending decreases or revenue increases and was very popular with [[deficit hawk]]s) had gone into effect, and was used regularly until the system's expiration in 2002.

In the 1994 midterm elections, Republicans ran on a platform that included fiscal responsibility drafted by then-Congressman [[Newt Gingrich]] called the [[Contract with America]], which advocated such things as balancing the budget, providing the president with a [[line-item veto]], and [[Personal Responsibility and Work Opportunity Act|welfare reform]]. After the [[Republican Revolution|elections]] gave the Republicans a majority in the [[United States House of Representatives|House of Representatives]], newly minted [[Speaker of the United States House of Representatives|Speaker of the House]] Gingrich pushed aggressively for reduced government spending, which created a confrontation with the White House that climaxed in the [[United States federal government shutdown of 1995 and 1996|1995–1996 government shutdown]]. After Clinton's re-election in 1996, they were able to cooperate and pass the [[Taxpayer Relief Act of 1997]], which lowered the top [[capital gains]] [[Capital gains tax|tax rate]] from 28% to 20% and the 15% rate to 10%.

After this combination of tax hikes and spending reductions, the United States was able to reduce the $3.8 trillion [[public debt]] by $360 billion and create the largest federal [[budget surplus]] ($236 billion in fiscal year 2000) as well as the longest period of sustained [[economic growth]] in United States history.&lt;ref name=&quot;President Clinton announces another record budget surplus&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://archives.cnn.com/2000/ALLPOLITICS/stories/09/27/clinton.surplus/ |title= President Clinton announces another record budget surplus| author=Kelly Wallace|publisher=CNN|date= September 27, 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Clinton announces record payment on national debt&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://archives.cnn.com/2000/ALLPOLITICS/stories/05/01/clinton.debt/|title= Clinton announces record payment on national debt|author=John King|publisher=CNN|date= May 1, 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, the claimed surplus was only recorded against public debt which was calculated with the exclusion of intragovernmental holdings. This meant that the administration was able to record loans deducted from the social security trust fund as revenue on budget reports, which accounted for the bulk of the surplus money. The total national debt (gross federal debt) rose every year of the Clinton Administration from $4.3 trillion to $5.6 trillion and from $5.4 trillion to $5.6 trillion over the years where the surplus was claimed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Historical Tables&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/BUDGET-2013-TAB/pdf/BUDGET-2013-TAB.pdf
|title= Historical Tables Budget of the U.S. Government
| publisher= Office of Management and Budget
| year= 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===George W. Bush Era===

The Bush administration accounted for the second largest increase of the Federal debt of any other president in United States history. In fact, the increase of the Federal debt during Bush's tenure was almost as much as the entire debt accumulated during the previous 200+ years, totaling around $5 trillion.  However, since taking office, President [[Barack Obama]] has increased the Federal debt by more than $5 trillion. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Congressional Budget Office|url=http://www.cbo.gov/publication/21728|accessdate=22 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Modern fiscal conservatism in the United States===
Modern fiscal conservatives remain wary of government spending. They believe strongly in free trade and are committed to lowering the [[Government budget|federal budget]], paying off national debt, and acquiring a balanced budget.&lt;ref name=&quot;Are You A Fiscal Conservative?&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://usconservatives.about.com/od/typesofconservatives/a/FiscalCons.htm|title=Are You A Fiscal Conservative?| author=Justin Quinn|publisher=[[About.com]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Where fiscal conservatism gets more diverse in ideals is what steps should be taken to balance the budget. Deficit hawks are more willing to increase taxes in addition to cutting spending to balance the budget than [[Libertarianism|libertarians]], who want to &quot;[[starve the beast]]&quot; by cutting taxes for the purpose of decreasing tax revenue which they hope will cause the government to spend less, and [[Supply-side economics|supply-siders]], who believe the best way to gain tax revenue is through deep across-the-board tax cuts that they believe will end up completely paying for themselves through the economic growth they cause.&lt;ref name=&quot;What Is A Fiscal Conservative Anyway?&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.centristpolicynetwork.org/archives/000056.html|title= What Is A Fiscal Conservative Anyway?| author=Jeff Lemieux|publisher=CentristPolicyNetwork.Org|date= February 15, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;What Killed Off The GOP Deficit Hawks?&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.businessweek.com/magazine/content/04_52/b3914021_mz007.htm |title= What Killed Off The GOP Deficit Hawks?|author=Robert Kuttner|publisher=[[BusinessWeek]]|date= December 27, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

American businessman, politician, and current [[Mayor of New York City]], [[Michael Bloomberg]], considers himself a fiscal conservative and expressed his definition of the term at the 2007 [[Conservative Party (UK)|United Kingdom Conservative Party]] Conference.

{{cquote|
To me, fiscal conservatism means balancing budgets – not running deficits that the next generation can't afford. It means improving the efficiency of delivering services by finding innovative ways to do more with less. It means cutting taxes when possible and prudent to do so, raising them overall only when necessary to balance the budget, and only in combination with spending cuts. It means when you run a surplus, you save it; you don't squander it. And most importantly, being a fiscal conservative means preparing for the inevitable economic downturns – and by all indications, we've got one coming. —Michael Bloomberg&lt;ref name=&quot;Mayor Bloomberg Delivers Remarks At 2007 Conservative Party Conference&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nyc.gov/portal/site/nycgov/menuitem.c0935b9a57bb4ef3daf2f1c701c789a0/index.jsp?pageID=mayor_press_release&amp;catID=1194&amp;doc_name=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.nyc.gov%2Fhtml%2Fom%2Fhtml%2F2007b%2Fpr348-07.html&amp;cc=unused1978&amp;rc=1194&amp;ndi=1|title=Mayor Bloomberg Delivers Remarks At 2007 Conservative Party Conference|publisher=NYC.gov|date= September 30, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}


==United Kingdom==
Fiscal conservatism in the UK was arguably most popular during the premiership of [[Margaret Thatcher]], who, after a number of years of deficit spending under the previous [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour]] government, advocated spending cuts and selective tax increases to balance the budget. However, despite being elected in 1979, Britain's budget was not balanced until 1988 – and from 1979 to 1987 the government deficit exceeded those seen during [[James Callaghan]]'s time as prime minister.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/news/datablog/2010/oct/18/deficit-debt-government-borrowing-data#_ |title=Deficit, national debt and government borrowing - how has it changed since 1946? |publisher=Guardian data blog |date=21 February 2012 |accessdate=4 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010, as a result of the deterioration in the UK's public finances caused by the [[Late-2000s recession]] and by the [[European sovereign debt crisis]], the [[United Kingdom coalition government (2010–present)|Liberal Democrat-Conservative Coalition]] embarked on an austerity programme – featuring a combination of spending cuts and tax rises – in an attempt to halve the [[Government budget deficit|deficit]], and completely eliminate the [[structural deficit]] over the five-year parliament.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.fundstrategy.co.uk/markets/britain/budget-structural-deficit-to-be-balanced-by-2015/1013834.article&lt;/ref&gt;

==Australia==
===Howard Government===
Fiscal conservatism become popular during the Howard government where large importance was placed on first balancing the budget and then running consistent surpluses to pay down the debt that had been taken on by Keating Government in response to the early 1990s recession.  In first term of government Howard made large cuts to government expenditure by laying off employees, and reducing social spending.  Throughout his term of office Howard used the surplus budgets that he achieved to contrast his economic management to that of the Australian Labor Party. By 2006, the Howard government paid off the debt held by the Australian national government.

==See also==
{{portal|conservatism}}
*[[Austerity]]
*[[Balance of payments]]
*[[Balance of trade]]
*[[Capitalism]]
*[[Criticisms of welfare]]
*[[Economic Freedom]]
*[[Economic Liberalism]]
*[[Market economy]]
*[[Minarchism]]
*[[Right-wing politics]]

'''US specific:'''
*[[Concord Coalition]]
*[[Citizens Against Government Waste]]
*[[Republican Main Street Partnership]]

==Further reading==
*Barber, William J. ''From New Era to New Deal: Herbert Hoover, the economists, and American economic policy.'' Cambridge University Press. (1985)
*Beito, David. ''Taxpayers in revolt: Tax resistance during the Great Depression.'' University of North Carolina Press. (1989)
*Brownlee, W. Elliot. ''Federal taxation in America: A short history.'' Cambridge University Press. 1996.
*Kimmel, Lewis. ''Federal budget and fiscal policy, 1789–1958.'' Brookings Institution Press. 1959.
*Left, Mark. 1983. Taxing the &quot;forgotten man&quot;: The politics of Social Security finance in the New Deal. Journal of American History 70 (September): 359-81. online in JSTOR
*Morgan, Iwan W. ''Deficit government: Taxing and spending in modern America.'' Ivan Dee. 1995.
*Sargent, James E. &quot;Roosevelt's Economy Act: Fiscal conservatism and the early New Deal.&quot; ''Congressional Studies'' 7 (winter 1980): 33–51.
*Savage, James D. ''Balanced budgets &amp; American politics.'' Cornell University Press. 1988.
*Herbert Stein. ''Presidential Economics, 3rd Edition: The Making of Economic Policy From Roosevelt to Clinton'' (1994)
*Julian E. Zelizer; &quot;The Forgotten Legacy of the New Deal: Fiscal Conservatism and the Roosevelt Administration, 1933–1938.&quot; ''Presidential Studies Quarterly''. 30#2. (2000). pp 331+. [http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=5001752830 online]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.taemag.com/issues/articleID.18938/article_detail.asp The Senate's Fiscal Conservatism]
*[http://www.FiscalRangers.com  FiscalRangers.com blog on local government spending and conservative fiscal control recommendations]
*[http://www.centristpolicynetwork.org/archives/000056.html What Is a Fiscal Conservative Anyway?]
*[http://usconservatives.about.com/od/typesofconservatives/a/FiscalCons.htm Are You a Fiscal Conservative?]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Fiscal Conservatism}}
[[Category:Classical liberalism]]
[[Category:Conservatism]]
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Fiscal policy]]
[[Category:Criticisms of welfare]]

[[es:Conservadurismo fiscal]]
[[it:Conservatorismo fiscale]]
[[pt:Conservadorismo fiscal]]
[[uk:Фіскальний консерватизм]]
[[zh:財政保守主義]]</text>
      <sha1>88e9qomfkyybh2fia5ajvql9l7g1yv2</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
