<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Foreign policy analysis</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4360694</id>
    <revision>
      <id>518877182</id>
      <parentid>517720202</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-20T14:39:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jarry1250</username>
        <id>2899122</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>{{Redirect}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6655">{{Redirect|Foreign Policy Analysis|the journal|International Studies Association}}

'''Foreign policy analysis''' (FPA) is a branch of [[political science]] dealing with theory development and empirical study regarding the processes and outcomes of [[foreign policy]].

==Study==
Foreign policy analysis involves the study of how a [[Sovereign state|state]] makes foreign policy
.As it analyzes the decision making process, FPA involves the study of both international and domestic politics. FPA also draws upon the study of [[diplomacy]], [[war]], [[intergovernmental organisations]], and [[economic sanctions]], each of which are means by which a state may implement foreign policy. In academia, foreign policy analysis is most commonly taught within the discipline of public policy within [[political science]] or [[political studies]], and the study of [[international relations]]. FPA can also be considered a sub-field of the study of international relations, which aims to understand the processes behind foreign policy decision making. The most prominent scholars in this field of study are Snyder, Rosenau, and Allison.&lt;ref&gt;Jean A. Garrison, ''&quot;Foreign Policy Analysis in 20/20: A Symposium.&quot;'' International Studies Review 5, 2003, pp. 155-202&lt;/ref&gt;

According to foreignpolicyanalysis.org, &quot;As a field of study, foreign policy analysis is characterized by its actor-specific focus. In the simplest terms, it is the study of the process, effects, causes, or outputs of foreign policy decision-making in either a comparative or case-specific manner. The underlying and often implicit argument theorizes that human beings, acting as a group or within a group, compose and cause change in international politics.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Foreign Policy Analysis, Department of Political Science, College of Arts &amp; Science, and the University of Missouri. http://foreignpolicyanalysis.org/&lt;/ref&gt;
==Stages in decision making==
The making of foreign policy involves a number of stages:

* '''Assessment of the international and domestic political environment''' - Foreign policy is made and implemented within an international and domestic political context, which must be understood by a state in order to determine the best foreign policy option. For example, a state may need to respond to an [[international crisis]].
* '''Goal setting''' - A state has multiple foreign policy goals. A state must determine which goal is affected by the international and domestic political environment at any given time. In addition, foreign policy goals may conflict, which will require the state to prioritise.
* '''Determination of policy options''' - A state must then determine what policy options are available to meet the goal or goals set in light of the political environment. This will involve an assessment of the state's capacity implement policy options and an assessment of the consequences of each policy option.
* '''Formal decision making action''' - A formal foreign policy decision will be taken at some level within a government. Foreign policy decisions are usually made by the [[executive branch]] of government. Common governmental actors or institutions which make foreign policy decisions include: the [[head of state]] (such as a [[president]]) or [[head of government]] (such as a [[prime minister]]), [[Cabinet (government)|cabinet]], or [[minister (government)|minister]].
* '''Implementation of chosen policy option''' - Once a foreign policy option has been chosen, and a formal decision has been made, then the policy must be implemented. Foreign policy is most commonly implemented by specialist foreign policy arms of the state bureaucracy, such as a [[Ministry of Foreign Affairs]] or [[State Department]]. Other departments may also have a role in implementing foreign policy, such as departments for: [[international trade|trade]], [[defence (military)|defence]], and [[aid]].

==Key approaches==
===Rational actor model===
The rational actor model is based on [[rational choice theory]]. The model adopts the state as the primary unit of analysis, and inter-state relations (or international relations) as the context for analysis. The state is seen as a monolithic unitary actor, capable of making rational decisions based on preference ranking and value maximisation.
According to the rational actor model, a rational decision making process is used by a state. This process includes:
* Goal setting and ranking.
* Consideration of options.
* Assessment of consequences.
* Profit-maximization. 
The rational actor model has been subject to criticism. The model tends to neglect a range of political variables, of which Michael Clarke includes: &quot;political decisions, non-political decisions, bureaucratic procedures, continuations of previous policy, and sheer accident.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;M. Clarke, ‘The Foreign Policy System: A Framework for Analysis’, in M. Clarke and B. White (eds) Understanding Foreign Policy: The Foreign Policy Systems Approach (Cheltenham: Edward Elgar 1989), pp. 27-59.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Bureaucratic Politics Model===
In this model the state is not seen as a monolithic unitary actor. Instead it is a collection of different bureaucracies vying for increasing their funding and size. Things are often viewed as a zero sum game where one bureaucracies' &quot;win&quot; or increasing their level of funding is seen as a loss for another bureaucracy. Here decisions are made by bureaucracies competing against each other and suggesting solutions to problems that would involve using their resources so as to increase their level of importance.

===Organizational Process Model===  
In this model different bureaucracies have different standard operating procedures. These procedures are made in order to allow day to day operations to be carried out. Oftentimes an order or decision will have to work around these standard procedures. It is often exceedingly difficult for a bureaucracy to do something &quot;out of character&quot; or contrary to their standard procedures.    

===Other models===
* Inter-branch politics model
* Self-aggrandizement model- In this model one leader acts on behalf of his or her interests.
* Political process model- In this model the decision making body is effected by many non-governmental actors such as NGOs or the media.

==Institutions==
* [[Council on Foreign Relations]]
* [[Chatham House]]
* [[American Enterprise Institute]]
* [[Brookings Institution]]
* [[Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars]]

==Notes==
&lt;references/&gt;

== External links ==
* [http://www.ericdigests.org/1994/war.htm Teaching Foreign Policy in the Post-Cold War Era]

[[Category:Foreign policy]]
[[Category:Public policy research]]</text>
      <sha1>4ms7tdve50ag82xlfymoeds2ypleozi</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
