<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>French Directory</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>172180</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521080234</id>
      <parentid>521064902</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T17:30:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ESkog</username>
        <id>88149</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/205.213.212.15|205.213.212.15]] ([[User talk:205.213.212.15|talk]]) to last revision by Olegvm7 ([[WP:HG|HG]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="30035">{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2011}}
{{refimprove|date=December 2011}}
{{Infobox Legislature Historic
 | name          = French Directory
 | native_name   = Directoire exécutif
 | entity        = [[French First Republic]]
 | image         = 1799-Verninac-David.jpg
 | image size    = 250px
 | caption       = Madame Raymond de Verninac by [[Jacques-Louis David]], with clothes and chair in [[Directoire style]]. Year 7, that is 1798-99.
 | type          =
 | houses        =
 | members       = 
 | location      =
 | year          =  2 November 1795
 | year2         = 10 November 1799
 | before        = [[National Convention]]
 | after         = [[French Consulate]]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;with [[Napoleon Bonaparte]] as First Consul&lt;/small&gt;
 | notes         =
}}
{{History of France}}
{{Governments of France}}

The '''Directory''' ({{lang-fr|Directoire exécutif}}) was a body of five ''Directors'' that held [[executive branch|executive power]] in France following the [[French Convention|Convention]] and preceding the [[French Consulate|Consulate]]. The period of this regime (2 November 1795 until 10 November 1799), commonly known as the '''Directory''' (or &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;'''Directoire'''&lt;/span&gt;) era, constitutes the second to last stage of the [[French Revolution]].

The Directory era itself is further split into two eras, the '''First Directory''' and the '''Second Directory''', divided by the [[Coup of 18 Fructidor]].  [[Directoire style]] refers to the [[Neoclassicism|Neoclassical]] styles in the [[decorative arts]] and fashion that characterize the period.

The directory system of government was also used in several [[French client republic]]s and modern Switzerland; see [[directorial system]].

== Constitution of Year III ==

Under the [[French Constitution of 1795]], qualified property holders elected 750 legislators, who divided themselves into the [[Council of Five Hundred]] and the [[Council of Ancients]]. This bicameral legislature had a term of three years, with one-third of the members renewed every year. The Ancients held a suspensory veto, but possessed no initiative in legislation.

The constitution specified the executive as consisting of five directors, chosen by the Ancients out of a list sent to them by the Five Hundred. One director faced retirement each year. Ministers for the various departments of State aided the directors. These ministers did not form a council or cabinet and had no general powers of government.

The system made provision for the stringent control of all local authorities by the central government. Since the new constitution sought to create a [[separation of powers]], the directors had no voice in legislation or taxation, nor could directors or ministers sit in either house. The law guaranteed freedom of religion, freedom of the press, and freedom of labour, but forbade armed assemblies and even public meetings of political societies. Only individuals or public authorities could tender petitions.

From the beginning, however, circumstances restricted the free play of the constitution. The Convention had acquired so much unpopularity that, if its members had retired into private life, they would have courted danger and risked the undoing of their work. Therefore a decree required that two-thirds of the first legislature must come from among the members of the Convention.

When the constitution went before the primary assemblies, most electors held aloof, {{formatnum:1057000}} voting for and {{formatnum:49000}} voting against it. On 23 September it officially became law. Then all the parties which resented the limit upon freedom of election combined in Paris to rise in revolt. The government entrusted its defense to &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Paul François Jean Nicolas Barras|Barras]]&lt;/span&gt;, but on &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[13 Vendémiaire]]&lt;/span&gt; (5 October 1795) the young General &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Napoléon Bonaparte]]&lt;/span&gt; quelled ill-equipped and ill-led Parisian insurgents with a few thousand regular troops and well-placed artillery. Further resistance seemed impossible. The Convention dissolved itself on 26 October 1795.

After the selection of the Council of the Ancients by lot, it remained to name the directors. For its own security the Left resolved that all five must be old members of the Convention and [[regicides]]. The Ancients chose
*[[Jean-François Rewbell]], an able, although unscrupulous, man of action
*[[Paul François Jean Nicolas, vicomte de Barras]], a dissolute and shameless adventurer
*[[Louis Marie de La Révellière-Lépeaux]], the chief of a new sect, the [[Theophilanthropy|Theophilanthropists]], was therefore a bitter foe to other religions, especially the Roman Catholic Church
*[[Lazare Nicolas Marguerite Carnot]], renowned for his integrity and memorable public services, but not a statesman and hampered by his past
*[[Étienne-François Le Tourneur]], an insignificant person who admired and followed Carnot


&lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Rewbell&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Barras&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;La Révellière Lépeaux&lt;/span&gt; had a full measure of the [[Jacobin Club|Jacobin]] spirit; &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Carnot&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Le Tourneur&lt;/span&gt; favoured a more temperate policy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sparknotes.com/history/european/frenchrev/section6.rhtml SparkNotes: the French Revolution (1789–1799): The Directory: 1795–1799]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Unpopularity of the Directory ==
With the establishment of the Directory, the Revolution seemed on the verge of ending. The nation was tired of the violence of the [[Reign of Terror|Terror]] and needed time to recover. Those who wished to restore [[Louis XVIII of France]] and the &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;''[[Ancien Régime]]''&lt;/span&gt; and those who would have renewed the [[Reign of Terror]] were insignificant in number. The possibility of foreign interference had vanished with the failure of the [[First coalition|First Coalition]]. Nevertheless, the four years of the Directory were a time of chronic disquiet and the late atrocities had made goodwill between parties impossible. The same instinct of self-preservation which had led the members of the Convention to claim so large a part in the new legislature and the whole of the Directory impelled them to keep their predominance.

As the majority of Frenchmen wanted to be rid of them, they could achieve their purpose only by extraordinary means. They disregarded the terms of the constitution, and, when the elections went against them, they prolonged the war to stay in power. They were thus driven to rely upon the armies, which also desired war and were becoming less and less civic in temper.

Other reasons influenced them in this direction. The finances had been so thoroughly ruined that the government could not have met its expenses without the plunder and the tribute of foreign countries. If peace were made, the armies would return home and the directors would have to face the exasperation of the rank-and-file who had lost their livelihood, as well as the ambition of generals who could, in a moment, brush them aside. &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Barras&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Rewbell&lt;/span&gt; were notoriously corrupt themselves and screened corruption in others. The patronage of the directors was ill-bestowed, and the general maladministration heightened their unpopularity.

The constitutional party in the legislature desired toleration of the [[Civil Constitution of the Clergy#Jurors and non-jurors|nonjuring clergy]], the repeal of the laws against the relatives of the &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[émigré]]s&lt;/span&gt;, and some merciful discrimination toward the &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;émigrés&lt;/span&gt; themselves. The directors baffled all such endeavours. On the other hand, the socialist conspiracy of &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[François-Noël Babeuf|Babeuf]]&lt;/span&gt; was easily quelled. Little was done to improve the finances, and the &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[assignat]]s&lt;/span&gt; continued.

== Military successes ==

However, the Directory was sustained by the military successes of 1796. &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Louis Lazare Hoche|Hoche]]&lt;/span&gt; again suppressed the [[Revolt in the Vendée]]. Bonaparte's victories in Italy more than compensated for the reverses of &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Jean-Baptiste Jourdan|Jourdan]]&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Jean Victor Moreau|Moreau]]&lt;/span&gt; in Germany. The [[Victor Amadeus III of Savoy|king of Sardinia]] made peace in May 1796, ceding &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Nice]]&lt;/span&gt; and [[Savoy]] to the French Republic and consenting to receive French garrisons in his [[Piedmont (Italy)|Piedmontese fortresses]]. By the [[Second Treaty of San Ildefonso|Treaty of San Ildefonso]], concluded in August, Spain became the ally of France. In October 1796, the [[Kingdom of Naples]] made peace.

In 1797, Bonaparte finished the conquest of northern Italy and forced Austria to make the [[Treaty of Campo Formio]] (October), whereby [[Francis II, Holy Roman Emperor|the emperor]] ceded [[Lombardy]] and the [[Austrian Netherlands]] to the French Republic in exchange for [[Venice]] and undertook to urge upon the [[Diet of the Holy Roman Empire|Diet]] the surrender of the lands beyond the [[Rhine]]. Notwithstanding the victory of [[Battle of Cape St. Vincent (1797)|Cape St Vincent]], the United Kingdom was brought into such extreme peril by the mutinies in its fleet that it offered to acknowledge the French conquest of the Netherlands and to restore the French colonies.

The selfishness of the three Directors threw away this golden opportunity. In March and April, the election of a new third of the Councils had been held. It gave a majority to the constitutional party. Among the directors, the lot fell on &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Le Tourneur&lt;/span&gt; to retire, and he was succeeded by &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[François Barthélemy|Barthélemy]]&lt;/span&gt;, an eminent diplomatist, who allied himself with &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Carnot&lt;/span&gt;. The political disabilities imposed upon the relatives of &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;émigrés&lt;/span&gt; were repealed. Priests who would declare their submission to the Republic were restored to their rights as citizens. It seemed likely that peace would be made and that moderate men would gain power.

== &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;18 Fructidor&lt;/span&gt; ==
{{Main|Coup of 18 Fructidor}}
&lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Barras&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Rewbell&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;La Révellière-Lépeaux&lt;/span&gt; then sought help from the armies. Although [[House of Bourbon|Royalists]] formed but a petty fraction of the majority, they accused that fraction of seeking to restore monarchy and to undo the work of the Revolution. &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Hoche&lt;/span&gt;, then in command of the [[Army of Sambre-et-Meuse]], visited Paris and sent troops. Bonaparte sent &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Pierre Augereau|General Augereau]]&lt;/span&gt;, who executed the &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;''coup d'état''&lt;/span&gt; of &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;18 Fructidor&lt;/span&gt; (4 September 1797).

The councils were purged, the elections in forty-nine departments were cancelled, and many deputies and other men of note were arrested. Some of them, including &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Barthélemy&lt;/span&gt;, Pichegru, Barbé-Marbois and Laffon de Ladebat were deported to &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Cayenne]]&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;ref&gt;See: Seuls les morts ne reviennent jamais : les pionniers de la guillotine sèche en Guyane française, Philippe de Ladebat, ed. Amalthée, France, 2008 – http://site.voila.fr/fructidor/page1.html&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Carnot&lt;/span&gt; made good his escape. The two vacant places in the Directory were filled by &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Philippe Antoine, comte Merlin|Merlin de Douai]]&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Nicolas-Louis François de Neufchâteau]]&lt;/span&gt;. Then the government frankly returned to [[Jacobin Club|Jacobin]] methods. The law against the relatives of &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;''émigrés''&lt;/span&gt; was reenacted, and military tribunals were established to condemn &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;''émigrés''&lt;/span&gt; who should return to France.

The nonjuring priests were again persecuted. Many hundreds were either sent to &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Cayenne&lt;/span&gt; or imprisoned in the hulks of &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Ré&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Oléron&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Louis Marie de La Révellière-Lépeaux|La Révellière Lépeaux]]&lt;/span&gt; seized the opportunity to propagate his religion. Many churches were turned into [[Theophilanthropic]] temples. The government strained its power to secure the recognition of the &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;''décadi''&lt;/span&gt; as the day of public worship and the non-observance of Sunday. [[Freedom of the press|Liberty of the press]] ceased. Newspapers were confiscated and journalists were deported wholesale. It was proposed to banish from France all members of the old &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[aristocracy|''noblesse'']]&lt;/span&gt;. Although the proposal was dropped, they were all declared to be foreigners and were forced to obtain naturalisation if they would enjoy the rights of other citizens. A formal bankruptcy of the state, the cancelling of two-thirds of the interest on the [[public debt]], crowned the misgovernment of this disastrous time.

== 1798 ==
In the spring of 1798, not only a new third of the legislature had to be chosen, but the places of the members expelled by the revolution of &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Fructidor&lt;/span&gt; had to be filled. The constitutional party had been rendered helpless, and the mass of the electors were indifferent. However, among the [[Jacobin Club|Jacobins]] themselves, there had arisen an extreme party hostile to the directors. With the support of many who were not Jacobins but detested the government, it bade fair to gain a majority. Before the new deputies could take their seats, the directors forced through the councils the [[Law of 22 Floréal Year VI|law of 22 Floréal]], annulling or perverting the elections in thirty departments and excluding forty-eight deputies by name. Even this &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;''coup d'état''&lt;/span&gt; did not secure harmony between the executive and the legislature. In the councils, the directors were loudly charged with corruption and misgovernment. The retirement of &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;François de Neufchâteau&lt;/span&gt; and the choice of &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Jean-Baptiste Treilhard|Treilhard]]&lt;/span&gt; as his successor (15 May 1798) made no difference in the position of the Directory.

While France was thus inwardly convulsed, its rulers were doubly bound to husband the national strength and practise moderation towards other states. Since December 1797, a congress had been sitting at &lt;span lang=&quot;de&quot;&gt;[[Rastatt]]&lt;/span&gt; to regulate the future of Germany. That it should be brought to a successful conclusion was of the utmost importance for France. However, the directors were driven by self-interest to new adventures abroad. &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Bonaparte&lt;/span&gt; was resolved not to sink into obscurity, and the directors were anxious to keep him as far as possible from Paris. They, therefore, sanctioned the expedition to [[Egypt]] which deprived the Republic of its best army and most renowned captain. Coveting the treasures of [[Bern]], the Directors sent &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Guillaume Marie Anne Brune|Brune]]&lt;/span&gt; to invade Switzerland and remodel its constitution. In revenge for the murder of General &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Mathurin-Léonard Duphot|Duphot]]&lt;/span&gt; (28 December 1797), they sent &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Louis Alexandre Berthier|Berthier]]&lt;/span&gt; to invade the [[Papal States]] and erect the [[Roman Republic (18th century)|Roman Republic]]. They also occupied and virtually annexed [[Piedmont (Italy)|Piedmont]]. In all these countries, they organised such an effective pillage that the French became universally hated.

As the armies were far below the strength required by the policy of unbounded conquest and rapine, the first permanent law of [[conscription]] was passed in the summer of 1798. The attempt to enforce it caused a revolt of the peasants in the Belgian departments. The priests were held responsible and some eight thousand were condemned to deportation &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;''en masse''&lt;/span&gt;, although the much greater part escaped by the goodwill of the people. Few soldiers were obtained by the conscription, for the government was as weak as it was tyrannical.

Under these circumstances, [[Horatio Nelson]]'s victory of [[Battle of the Nile|Aboukir]] (1 August 1798), which gave the British full command of the [[Mediterranean]] and isolated &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Bonaparte&lt;/span&gt; in Egypt, was the signal for a [[second coalition]]. Naples, Austria, Russia and [[Turkey]] joined Great Britain against France. [[Ferdinand I of the Two Sicilies|Ferdinand IV of Naples]], rashly taking the offensive before his allies were ready, was defeated and forced to seek a refuge in [[Sicily]].

== 1799 ==
In January 1799, the French occupied Naples along with Togar and set up the [[Parthenopaean Republic]]. But the consequent dispersion of their weak forces only exposed them to greater peril. At home, the Directory was in a most critical position. In the elections of April 1799, a large number of [[Jacobin Club|Jacobins]] gained seats. A little later &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Rewbell&lt;/span&gt; retired. It was imperative to fill his place with a man of ability and influence. The choice fell upon &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Emmanuel Joseph Sieyès|Sieyès]]&lt;/span&gt;, who had kept aloof from office and retained not only his immeasurable self-conceit but the respect of the public.

&lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Sieyès&lt;/span&gt; felt that the Directory had bankrupted its own reputation, and he intended to do far more than merely serve as a member of a board. He hoped to concentrate power in his own hands, to bridle the Jacobins, and to remodel the constitution. With the help of &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Barras&lt;/span&gt;, he proceeded to rid himself of the other directors. An irregularity having emerged in &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Treilhard&lt;/span&gt;'s election, he retired, and &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Louis Jérôme Gohier|Gohier]]&lt;/span&gt; took his place (&lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;30 Prairial&lt;/span&gt;, 18 June 1799). &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Merlin de Douai&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;La Révellière Lépeaux&lt;/span&gt; were driven to resign in June 1799; &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Jean-François-Auguste Moulin|Moulin]]&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Roger Ducos|Ducos]]&lt;/span&gt; replaced them. The three new directors so lacked significance that they could give no trouble, but for the same reason they could give little service.

Such a government proved ill-fitted to cope with the dangers then gathering round France. The directors resolved on a French offensive in Germany. The French crossed the Rhine early in March, but [[Archduke Charles of Austria]] defeated them, first at [[Battle of Ostrach|Ostrach]] on 23&amp;nbsp;March and then at &lt;span lang=&quot;de&quot;&gt;[[Battle of Stockach (1799)|Stockach]]&lt;/span&gt; on 25 March 1799. Jourdan's [[Army of the Danube]] withdrew to the Rhine under the command of Lecourbe, while Jourdan himself returned to Paris to plea for more and better soldiers. The [[Second Congress of Rastatt|congress at Rastatt]], which had sat for fifteen months without actually accomplishing anything, broke in April, and Austrian hussars murdered the French envoys.{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}} In Italy, the allies took the offensive with an army partly Austrian, partly Russian, under the command of the Russian field marshal (future generalissimo) [[Alexander Suvorov|Suvorov]]. After defeating &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Moreau&lt;/span&gt; at &lt;span lang=&quot;it&quot;&gt;[[Cassano d'Adda]]&lt;/span&gt; on 27 April 1799, he occupied [[Milan]] and [[Turin]]. The puppet republics established by the French in Italy collapsed, and Suvorov defeated the French army on the [[Trebbia]] as it retreated from Naples.

Thus threatened with invasion on her German and Italian frontiers, France seemed disabled by anarchy within. The finances stood in the last distress; the anti-religious policy of the government kept many &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;''[[département in France|départements]]''&lt;/span&gt; on the verge of revolt; and commerce almost ground to a halt due to the decay of roads and the increase of bandits. The French lacked any real political freedom, yet also lacked the ease or security which [[enlightened despotism]] can bestow. The Terrorists lifted their heads in the Council of Five Hundred. A [[Law of Hostages]], which was really a new [[Law of Suspects]], and a [[Progressive tax|progressive]] [[income tax]] showed the temper of the majority. The Jacobin Club re-opened and became once more the focus of disorder. The Jacobin press renewed the licence of &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Jacques René Hébert|Hébert]]&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Jean-Paul Marat|Marat]]&lt;/span&gt;. Never since the outbreak of the Revolution had the public temper seemed so gloomy.

In this extremity, &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Sieyès&lt;/span&gt; chose as minister of police the old Terrorist &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Joseph Fouché]]&lt;/span&gt;, who best understood how to deal with his brethren. &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Fouché&lt;/span&gt; closed the Jacobin Club and deported a number of journalists. However, like his predecessors, &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Sieyès&lt;/span&gt; felt that for the revolution which he meditated, he must have the help of a soldier. As his man of action, he chose General &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Barthelemy Catherine Joubert|Joubert]]&lt;/span&gt;, one of the most distinguished among French officers. The Directory sent &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Joubert&lt;/span&gt; to restore the fortunes of the war in Italy. At &lt;span lang=&quot;it&quot;&gt;[[Novi Ligure|Novi]]&lt;/span&gt;, on 15 August 1799, he encountered Suvorov. He was killed at the outset of the battle and his men suffered defeat.

After this disaster, the French held scarcely any territory south of the [[Alps]] save [[Genoa]]. The Russian and Austrian governments then agreed to drive the enemy out of Switzerland and to invade France from the east. At the same time, the joint forces of Great Britain and Russia [[Anglo-Russian Invasion of Holland|assailed the Netherlands]]. However, the narrow views and conflicting interests of the members of the second coalition doomed it to failure like the first. Lack of co-ordination between Austrians and Russians, and &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[André Masséna]]&lt;/span&gt;'s victory at &lt;span lang=&quot;de&quot;&gt;[[Zürich]]&lt;/span&gt; (25–26 September 1799) stalled the invasion of Switzerland. In October, the British and the Russians had to evacuate the Netherlands. All immediate danger to France ended, but the issue of war remained in suspense. The Directors had felt forced to recall Bonaparte from Egypt. He anticipated their order and on 9 October 1799 landed at &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Fréjus]]&lt;/span&gt;.

== End of the Directory ==
&lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;{{Main|18 Brumaire}}&lt;/span&gt;
The Directory and the French Revolution itself came to an end with the &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;''coup d'état''&lt;/span&gt; of &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[18 Brumaire]]&lt;/span&gt; (9 November 1799) in which General Napoléon Bonaparte overthrew the Directory and replaced it with the [[French Consulate|Consulate]].

In November 1799, France was suffering the effects of military reverses brought on by &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Bonaparte&lt;/span&gt;'s adventurism in the Middle East. The looming threat of opportunistic invasion by the [[Second Coalition]] had provoked internal unrest, with &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Bonaparte&lt;/span&gt; stuck in Egypt. A return to [[Jacobin (politics)|Jacobinism]] seemed possible.

The &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;coup&lt;/span&gt; was first prepared by the &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Abbé Sieyès]]&lt;/span&gt;, then one of the five Directors. &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Bonaparte&lt;/span&gt; returned from [[Egypt]] a hero to the public despite his reverses. &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Sieyès&lt;/span&gt; believed he had found the general indispensable to his coup. However, &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Bonaparte&lt;/span&gt; promptly began a &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;coup&lt;/span&gt; within the &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;coup&lt;/span&gt;. Ultimately, the &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;coup&lt;/span&gt; brought to power &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Bonaparte&lt;/span&gt;, not &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Sieyès&lt;/span&gt;.

The plan was, through the use of troops conveniently arrayed around Paris, first to persuade the Directors to resign, then to persuade the two Councils to appoint a pliant commission to draw up a new constitution.

On the morning of &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;18 Brumaire&lt;/span&gt;, members of the [[Council of Ancients]] sympathetic to the coup warned their colleagues of a Jacobin conspiracy and persuaded them to relocate to &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Saint-Cloud]]&lt;/span&gt;, west of Paris. &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Bonaparte&lt;/span&gt; was charged with the safety of the two Councils. Three directors, including &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Sieyès&lt;/span&gt; himself resigned, destroying quorum. However, the two Jacobin Directors, &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Louis-Jérôme Gohier|Gohier]]&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Jean-François-Auguste Moulin|Moulin]]&lt;/span&gt;, refused to resign. &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Moulin&lt;/span&gt; escaped, &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Gohier&lt;/span&gt; was taken prisoner, and the two Councils were not immediately intimidated and continued to meet.

By the following day, the deputies had worked out that they were facing an attempted coup rather than being protected from a Jacobin rebellion. Faced with their recalcitrance, Bonaparte stormed into the chambers accompanied by a small escort of grenadiers. He met with heckling in both houses; he was first jostled, then outright assaulted. His brother &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Lucien Bonaparte|Lucien]]&lt;/span&gt;, President of the Council, called upon the grenadiers to defend their leader. Napoleon escaped, but only through the use of military force. Ultimately, military force also dispersed the legislature.

The Consulate was declared, with &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Bonaparte&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Sieyès&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Roger Ducos]]&lt;/span&gt; as consuls.

The lack of reaction from the streets proved that the revolution was, indeed, over. In the words of the [[1911 Encyclopædia Britannica]], &quot;A shabby compound of brute force and imposture, the 18th &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Brumaire&lt;/span&gt; was nevertheless condoned, nay applauded, by the French nation. Weary of revolution, men sought no more than to be wisely and firmly governed.&quot; Resistance by Jacobin officeholders in the provinces was quickly crushed, twenty Jacobin legislators were exiled, and others were arrested.

Bonaparte completed his &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;''coup''&lt;/span&gt; within a &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;''coup''&lt;/span&gt; by the adoption of a constitution under which the First Consul, a position he was sure to hold, had greater power than the other two.

== List of &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;''Directeurs''&lt;/span&gt; ==

{| width=100% class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
|width=20% rowspan=&quot;2&quot;|'''[[Lazare Carnot|L. Carnot]]'''&lt;br /&gt;4 November 1795 –&lt;br /&gt;5 September 1797
|'''[[Étienne-François Le Tourneur|E. F. Le Tourneur]]'''&lt;br /&gt;2 November 1795 –&lt;br /&gt;26 May 1797
|width=20% rowspan=&quot;4&quot;|'''[[Jean-François Rewbell|J. F. Rewbell]]'''&lt;br /&gt;2 November 1795 –&lt;br /&gt;19 May 1799
|width=20% rowspan=&quot;5&quot;|'''[[Louis-Marie de La Révellière|L.-M. de La Révellière]]'''&lt;br /&gt;2 November 1795 –&lt;br /&gt;18 June 1799
|width=20% rowspan=&quot;6&quot;|'''[[Paul Barras|P. Barras]]'''&lt;br /&gt;2 November 1795 –&lt;br /&gt;10 November 1799
|-
||'''[[François Barthélemy|F. Barthélemy]]'''&lt;br /&gt;26 May 1797 –&lt;br /&gt;5 September 1797
|-
|width=20% rowspan=&quot;3&quot;|'''[[Philippe-Antoine Merlin|P.-A. Merlin]]'''&lt;br /&gt;8 September 1797 –&lt;br /&gt;18 June 1799
||'''[[François de Neufchâteau|F. de Neufchâteau]]'''&lt;br /&gt;9 September 1797 –&lt;br /&gt;19 May 1798
|-
|rowspan=&quot;2&quot;|'''[[Jean-Baptiste Treilhard|J. B. Treilhard]]'''&lt;br /&gt;20 May 1798 –&lt;br /&gt;17 June 1799
|-
|rowspan=&quot;2&quot;|'''[[Emmanuel-Joseph Sieyès|E. J. Sieyès]]'''&lt;br /&gt;20 May 1799 –&lt;br /&gt;10 November 1799
|-
||'''[[Jean-François-Auguste Moulin|J. F. A. Moulin]]'''&lt;br /&gt;20 June 1799 –&lt;br /&gt;10 November 1799
||'''[[Louis-Jérôme Gohier|L. J. Gohier]]'''&lt;br /&gt;17 June 1799 –&lt;br /&gt;10 November 1799
||'''[[Pierre-Roger Ducos|P.-R. Ducos]]'''&lt;br /&gt;19 June 1799 –&lt;br /&gt;10 November 1799
|-
|}

{{Heads of state of France}}

== See also ==
*[[Timeline of the French Revolution]]
*[[1795–1820 in fashion#Directoire (1795–1799)|Directoire fashion]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist|2}}

== References ==
{{1911}}

== External links ==
*[http://www.archontology.org/nations/france/directory_1795_99/01_directoire_member.php Members of the Executive Directory]
*[http://www.archontology.org/nations/france/directory_1795_99/ Presidents of the Executive Directory]
*[http://www.worldstatesmen.org/Italy_states.htm WorldStatesmen] (here Italy linked)
*[http://www.worldstatesmen.org/Italy_states.htm WorldStatesmen] (here Italy linked)
*The coup d'état of 18 Fructidor [http://18_fructidor_anV.site.voila.fr]

{{French Revolution footer}}
{{France topics}}

{{Persondata
| NAME              = Directory, French
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Directory, French}}
[[Category:1795 events of the French Revolution]]
[[Category:1796 events of the French Revolution]]
[[Category:1797 events of the French Revolution]]
[[Category:1798 events of the French Revolution]]
[[Category:1799 events of the French Revolution]]
[[Category:Government of France]]
[[Category:Historical legislatures]]
[[Category:1795 establishments in France]]
[[Category:1799 disestablishments]]
[[Category:Collective heads of state]]

[[az:Fransa Direktoriyası]]
[[bg:Директория]]
[[ca:Directori francès]]
[[cs:Direktorium (Francie)]]
[[da:Direktoriet]]
[[de:Direktorium (Frankreich)]]
[[el:Διευθυντήριο]]
[[es:Directorio (Francia)]]
[[eu:Direktorio (Frantzia)]]
[[fa:دیرکتوار فرانسه]]
[[fr:Directoire]]
[[ko:프랑스 총재정부]]
[[io:Direktorio (Francia)]]
[[it:Direttorio]]
[[ka:საფრანგეთის დირექტორია]]
[[lb:Directoire]]
[[lt:Direktorija]]
[[hu:Francia direktórium]]
[[nl:Directoire]]
[[ja:総裁政府]]
[[pl:Dyrektoriat]]
[[pt:Diretório (Revolução Francesa)]]
[[ro:Directoratul]]
[[ru:Директория (Французская революция)]]
[[sk:Výkonné direktórium]]
[[sl:Francoski direktorij]]
[[fi:Direktorio]]
[[sv:Direktoriet]]
[[tr:Direktuvar]]
[[uk:Директорія (Франція)]]
[[zh:督政府]]</text>
      <sha1>lw44gkllqdh950jpyi9xj3xxqe7oo1x</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
