<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Globalization</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>46313</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522449807</id>
      <parentid>522449777</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-11T08:25:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sue Rangell</username>
        <id>3799777</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/117.197.254.46|117.197.254.46]] ([[User talk:117.197.254.46|talk]]) to last revision by HiLo48 ([[WP:HG|HG]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="154113">{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2012}}
{{pp-move-indef|small=yes}}
{{Lead too short|date=October 2012}}

'''Globalization''' is the process of international integration arising from the interchange of [[world view]]s, products, ideas, and other aspects of [[culture]].&lt;ref name=GCSP&gt;Al-Rodhan, Nayef R.F. and Gérard Stoudmann. (2006, 19 June). &quot;Definitions of Globalization: A Comprehensive Overview and a Proposed Definition.&quot; [http://www.sustainablehistory.com/articles/definitions-of-globalization.pdf''Globalization definition)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Albrow&gt;Albrow, Martin and Elizabeth King (eds.) (1990). ''Globalization, Knowledge and Society ''London: Sage. ISBN 978-0803983243 p. 8. &quot;…all those processes by which the peoples of the world are incorporated into a single world society.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; In particular, advances in [[transportation]] and [[telecommunication]]s infrastructure, including the rise of the [[Internet]], are major factors in globalization and precipitate further [[interdependence]] of economic and cultural activities.&lt;ref name=Stever_1972&gt;Stever, H. Guyford (1972). &quot;Science, Systems, and Society.&quot; ''Journal of Cybernetics'', 2(3):1-3. {{doi|10.1080/01969727208542909}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:1901 Eastern Telegraph cables.png|thumb|275px|[[Cable &amp; Wireless Worldwide|Eastern Telegraph Company]] 1899 chart of undersea [[telegraph]] cabling. An example of modern globalizing [[technology]] in the beginning of the 20th century.]]

Though several scholars situate the origins of globalization in [[modernity]], others map&lt;!-- or sketch, or mark out you may also help ---&gt; its history long before the European [[age of discovery]] and voyages to the [[New World]]. Some even trace the origins to the third millennium B.C.E.&lt;ref name=GL-H-09/&gt;&lt;ref name=GL-H-10&gt;{{cite web|title=''Globalization and Global History'' (p.127)|url=http://58.192.114.227/humanities/sociology/htmledit/uploadfile/system/20110522/20110522005012939.pdf|accessdate=3 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Overview==
Human interaction over long distances has existed for thousands of years. The overland [[Silk Road]] that connected [[Asia]], [[Africa]] and [[Europe]] is a good example of the transformative power of international exchange that existed in the &quot;[[Old World]]&quot;. Philosophy, religion, language, the arts, and other aspects of culture spread and mixed as nations exchanged products and ideas. In the 15th and 16th centuries, Europeans made important discoveries in their exploration of the [[World ocean]] and in beginning cross-Atlantic travel to the &quot;[[New World]]&quot; of the [[Americas]]. Global movement of people, goods, and ideas expanded significantly in the following centuries. Early in the 19th century, the development of new forms of transportation (such as the [[steamship]] and [[railroads]]) and [[telecommunication]]s that &quot;compressed&quot; time and space allowed for increasingly rapid rates of global interchange.&lt;ref name=&quot;When Did Globalization Begin&quot;&gt;O'Rourke, Kevin H. and Jeffrey G. Williamson. (2000). &quot;When Did Globalization Begin?&quot; [http://www.nber.org/papers/w7632  NBER Working Paper No. 7632.]&lt;/ref&gt; In the 20th century, [[road vehicle]]s and [[airline]]s made transportation even faster, and the advent of electronic communications, most notably [[mobile phones]] and [[the Internet]], connected billions of people in new ways leading into the 21st century.

==Etymology and usage==
The term ''globalization'' is derived from the word ''globalize'', which refers to the emergence of an international network of social and economic systems.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Globalization|url=http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=globalization|publisher=Online Etymology Dictionary|accessdate=7 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; One of the earliest known usages of the term as the noun was in 1930 in a publication entitled ''Towards New Education'' where it denoted a holistic view of human experience in education.&lt;ref name=oed&gt;{{cite web|title=Globalization|work=Oxford English Dictionary Online|url=http://dictionary.oed.com/cgi/entry/50297775?single=1&amp;query_type=word&amp;queryword=Globalization&amp;first=1&amp;max_to_show=10|date=September 2009|accessdate=5 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; A related term, ''corporate giants'', was coined by [[Charles Taze Russell]] in 1897&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pastor-russell.com/volumes/V4/Study_07.html |title='&amp;#39;The Battle of Armageddon'&amp;#39;, October, 1897 pages 365–370 |publisher=Pastor-russell.com |accessdate=31 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; to refer to the largely national trusts and other large enterprises of the time. By the 1960s, both terms began to be used as synonyms by economists and other social scientists. It then reached the mainstream press in the later half of the 1980s. Since its inception, the concept of globalization has inspired competing definitions and interpretations, with antecedents dating back to the great movements of trade and empire across Asia and the Indian Ocean from the 15th century onwards.&lt;ref&gt;Hopkins, A.G. (ed.). (2004). ''Globalization in World History.'' London: Norton, pp. 4–8. ISBN 978-0393979428&lt;/ref&gt;
Due to the complexity of the concept, research projects, articles, and discussions often remain focused on a single aspect of globalization.&lt;ref name=GCSP /&gt;

Roland Robertson, professor of sociology at University of Aberdeen, was the first person to define globalization as &quot;the compression of the world and the intensification of the consciousness of the world as a whole.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Robertson|first=Roland|title=Globalization : social theory and global culture|year=1992|publisher=Sage|location=London|isbn=0803981872|edition=Reprint.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sociologists [[Martin Albrow]] and Elizabeth King define globalization as:
{{quote|…all those processes by which the peoples of the world are incorporated into a single world society.&lt;ref name=Albrow&gt;p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In ''The Consequences of Modernity'', [[Anthony Giddens]] uses the following definition:
{{quote|Globalization can thus be defined as the intensification of worldwide social relations which link distant localities in such a way that local happenings are shaped by events occurring many miles away and vice versa.&lt;ref&gt;Giddens, Anthony. (1991). ''The Consequences of Modernity'' Cambridge: Polity Press. p. 64. ISBN 9780745609232&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In ''Global Transformations'' [[David Held]], et al., study the definition of globalization:
{{quote|Although in its simplistic sense globalization refers to the widening, deepening and speeding up of global interconnection, such a definition begs further elaboration. … Globalization can be located on a continuum with the local, national and regional. At one end of the continuum lie social and economic relations and networks which are organized on a local and/or national basis; at the other end lie social and economic relations and networks which crystallize on the wider scale of regional and global interactions. Globalization can be taken to refer to those spatial-temporal processes of change which underpin a transformation in the organization of human affairs by linking together and expanding human activity across regions and continents. Without reference to such expansive spatial connections, there can be no clear or coherent formulation of this term. … A satisfactory definition of globalization must capture each of these elements: extensity (stretching), intensity, velocity and impact.&lt;ref&gt;Held, David, et al. (1999). ''Global Transformations'' Cambridge: Polity Press. ISBN 9780745614984&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Swedish journalist [[Thomas Larsson (journalist)|Thomas Larsson]], in his book ''The Race to the Top: The Real Story of Globalization'', states that globalization:
{{quote|is the process of world shrinkage, of distances getting shorter, things moving closer. It pertains to the increasing ease with which somebody on one side of the world can interact, to mutual benefit, with somebody on the other side of the world.&lt;ref&gt;Larsson, Thomas. (2001). ''The Race to the Top: The Real Story of Globalization'' Washington, D.C.: Cato Institute. p. 9. ISBN 978-1930865150&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The journalist [[Thomas L. Friedman]] popularized the term [[The World Is Flat|&quot;flat world&quot;]], arguing that [[Global trade|globalized trade]], [[outsourcing]], [[supply chain|supply-chaining]], and political forces had permanently changed the world, for better and worse. He asserted that the pace of globalization was quickening and that its impact on business organization and practice would continue to grow.&lt;ref&gt;Friedman, Thomas L. &quot;The Dell Theory of Conflict Prevention&quot;. ''Emerging: A Reader.'' Ed. Barclay Barrios. Boston: Bedford, St. Martins, 2008. 49&lt;/ref&gt;

Economist [[Takis Fotopoulos]] defined &quot;economic globalization&quot; as the opening and deregulation of commodity, capital and labor markets that led toward present [[neoliberal]] globalization. He used &quot;political globalization&quot; to refer to the emergence of a transnational elite and a phasing out of the [[nation-state]]. &quot;[[Cultural globalization]]&quot;, he used to reference the worldwide homogenization of culture. Other of his usages included &quot;[[Ideology|ideological]] globalization&quot;, &quot;[[Technology|technological]] globalization&quot; and &quot;[[social]] globalization&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Fotopoulos, Takis. (2001). &quot;Globalization, the reformist Left and the Anti-Globalization 'Movement.'&quot; [http://www.inclusivedemocracy.org/dn/vol7/takis_globalisation.htm ''Democracy &amp; Nature: The International Journal of Inclusive Democracy'', 7:(2) (July 2001).]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2000, the [[International Monetary Fund]] (IMF) identified four basic aspects of globalization: trade and transactions, capital and investment movements, migration and movement of people and the dissemination of knowledge.&lt;ref&gt;International Monetary Fund . (2000). &quot;Globalization: Threats or Opportunity.&quot;  [http://www.imf.org/external/np/exr/ib/2000/041200to.htm 12th April, 2000: IMF Publications.]&lt;/ref&gt; With regards to trade and transactions, developing countries increased their share of world trade, from 19 percent in 1971 to 29 percent in 1999. However, there is great variation among the major regions. For instance, the [[newly industrialized country|newly industrialized economies]] (NIEs) of Asia prospered, while African countries as a whole performed poorly. The makeup of a country's exports is an important indicator for success. Manufactured goods exports soared, dominated by developed countries and NIEs. Commodity exports, such as food and raw materials were often produced by developing countries: commodities' share of total exports declined over the period. Following from this, capital and investment movements can be highlighted as another basic aspect of globalization. Private capital flows to developing countries soared during the 1990s, replacing &quot;aid&quot; or development assistance which fell  significantly after the early 1980s. [[Foreign Direct Investment]] (FDI) became the most important category. Both portfolio investment and bank credit rose but they have been more volatile, falling sharply in the wake of the financial crisis of the late 1990s. The migration and movement of people can also be highlighted as a prominent feature of the globalization process. In the period between 1965–90, the proportion of the labor forces migrating approximately doubled. Most migration occurred between developing countries and [[Least developed country|Least Developed Countries]] (LDCs). The flow of migrants to advanced economic countries was claimed to provide a means through which global wages converge. They noted the potential for skills to be transferred back to developing countries as wages in those a countries rise. Lastly, the dissemination of knowledge has been an integral aspect of globalization. Technological innovations (or technological transfer) benefit most the developing and Least Developing countries (LDCs), as for example the advent of [[mobile phones]].

==History==
{{main|History of globalization}}
{{See also|Timeline of international trade}}
[[File:Silk route.jpg|thumb|Extent of the [[Silk Road]] and [[Spice trade]] routes blocked by the [[Ottoman Empire]] in 1453 spurring exploration]]
There are both [[Proximate and ultimate causation|distal and proximate causes]] that can be traced in the historical factors affecting globalization. Large-scale globalization began in the 19th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;When Did Globalization Begin&quot;/&gt;

===Archaic===
{{Main|Archaic globalization}}

The [[German people|German]] historical [[economist]] and [[sociologist]] [[Andre Gunder Frank]] argues that a form of globalization began with the rise of trade links between [[Sumer]] and the [[Indus Valley Civilization]] in the [[third millennium]] [[Common Era|B.C.E.]]&lt;ref name=GL-H-09&gt;Frank, Andre Gunder. (1998). ''ReOrient: Global economy in the Asian age.'' Berkeley: University of California Press. ISBN 978-0520214743&lt;/ref&gt;  This [[archaic globalization]] existed during the [[Hellenistic civilization|Hellenistic Age]], when commercialized urban centers enveloped the axis of [[Greek people|Greek]] culture that reached from [[India]] to [[Spain]], including [[Alexandria]] and the other [[Alexander the Great|Alexandrine]] cities. Early on, the geographic position of Greece and the necessity of [[import]]ing wheat forced the Greeks to engage in maritime trade. Trade in ancient Greece was largely unrestricted: the state controlled only the supply of grain.

There were trade links between the [[Roman Empire]], the [[Parthian Empire]], and the [[Han Dynasty]]. The increasing commercial links between these powers took form in the [[Silk Road]], which began in western [[China]], reached the boundaries of the Parthian empire, and continued to [[Rome]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Lee, Adela C.Y.|url=http://www.silk-road.com/artl/srtravelmain.shtml |title=Ancient Silk Road Travellers |publisher=Silkroad Foundation: Silk-road.com |accessdate=31 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; As many as three hundred Greek ships sailed each year between the [[Greco-Roman world]] and [[South Asia|India]]. Annual trade volume may have reached 300,000 tons.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis, David and Karl Moore. (2009). &quot;The origins of globalization: a Canadian perspective.&quot; [http://www.iveybusinessjournal.com/topics/the-organization/the-origins-of-globalization-a-canadian-perspective ''Ivey Business Journal'', (May/June).]&lt;/ref&gt;

By traveling past the [[Tarim Basin]] region, the Chinese of the [[Han Dynasty]] learned of powerful kingdoms in [[Central Asia]], [[Persia]], [[India]], and the [[Middle East]] with the travels of the [[Han Dynasty]] [[envoy (title)|envoy]] [[Zhang Qian]] in the 2nd century BC. From 104 BC to 102 BC  [[Emperor Wu of Han]] waged war against the [[Yuezhi]] who controlled [[Dayuan]], a [[Hellenized]] kingdom of [[Fergana]] established by [[Alexander the Great]] in 329 BC. [[Gan Ying]], the emissary of General [[Ban Chao]], perhaps traveled as far as [[Roman Empire|Roman]]-era [[Syria]] in the late 1st century AD. After these initial discoveries the focus of Chinese exploration shifted to the [[Maritime trade|maritime]] sphere, although the [[Silk Road]] leading all the way to [[Europe]] continued to be China's most lucrative source of trade.

From about the 1st century, [[Greater India|India started to strongly influence]] Southeast Asian countries. Trade routes linked India with southern [[Burma]], central and southern [[Siam]], lower [[Cambodia]] and southern [[Vietnam]] and numerous urbanized coastal settlements were established there.

The [[Islamic Golden Age]] added another stage of globalization, when [[Radhanite]] (Jewish) and [[Islamic economics in the world|Muslim traders]] and [[Geography in medieval Islam|explorers]] established trade routes, resulting in a [[Muslim Agricultural Revolution|globalization of agriculture]], trade, knowledge and technology. Crops such as sugar and cotton became widely cultivated across the [[Muslim world]] in this period, while widespread knowledge of [[Arabic]] and the [[Hajj]] created a cosmopolitan culture.&lt;ref name=Hobson-29-30&gt;Hobson, John M. (2004), ''The Eastern Origins of Western Civilisation''. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, ISBN 0-521-54724-5.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:NanbanCarrack.jpg|thumb|right|Portuguese [[carrack]] in [[Nagasaki]], 17th century Japanese [[Nanban trade|Nanban art]]]]
[[File:New World Domesticated plants.JPG|thumb|left|Native [[New World]] crops [[Columbian Exchange|exchanged globally]]: Maize, tomato, potato, [[vanilla]], rubber, [[Cacao bean|cacao]], tobacco]]

The advent of the [[Mongol Empire]], though destabilizing to the commercial centers of the Middle East and China, greatly facilitated travel along the Silk Road. The [[Pax Mongolica]] of the thirteenth century included the first international [[postal service]], as well as the rapid transmission of [[infectious diseases|epidemic disease]]s such as [[bubonic plague]] across Central Asia.&lt;ref&gt;Weatherford, Jack. (2004). ''Genghis Khan and the Making of the Modern World'', NY: Three Rivers Press. ISBN 0-609-80964-4&lt;/ref&gt; Up to the sixteenth century, however, the largest systems of international exchange were limited to southern Eurasia (an area where the Balkans and Greece interact with Turkey, Egypt, the Levant, Persia and the Arabian Peninsula, continuing over the Arabian Sea to India).

Many Chinese merchants chose to settle down in the Southeast Asian ports such as Champa, Cambodia, Sumatra, Java, and married the native women. Their children carried on trade.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=heEdZziizrUC&amp;pg=PA405&amp;dq=chinese+merchant+sojourners+southeast+asian+trade#v=onepage&amp;q=chinese%20merchant%20sojourners%20southeast%20asian%20trade&amp;f=false|title=The Rise of merchant empires: long-distance trade in the early modern world, 1350-1750|author=Tracy, James D.|year=1993|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=|page=405|isbn=0-521-45735-1|pages=|accessdate=28 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=EwnzBiM0LmAC&amp;pg=PA11&amp;dq=chinese+merchant+sojourners+southeast+asian+trade#v=onepage&amp;q=chinese%20merchant%20sojourners%20southeast%20asian%20trade&amp;f=false|title=Connecting and Distancing: Southeast Asia and China|author=Leong, Ho Khai and Khai Leong Ho|year=2009|publisher=Institute of Southeast Asian Studies|location=|page=11|isbn=981-230-856-3|pages=|accessdate=28 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Italian city states embraced free trade and merchants established trade links with faraway places, giving birth to the [[Renaissance]]. [[Marco Polo]] was a merchant traveler&lt;ref name=HFH&gt;{{cite book|title=Venice and Its Merchant Empire|first= Kathryn|last= Hinds|year=2002 |place=New York|publisher=Benchmark Books}}&lt;/ref&gt; from the [[Republic of Venice|Venetian Republic]] in modern-day Italy whose travels are recorded in ''[[The Travels of Marco Polo|Il Milione]]'', a book that played a significant role in introducing Europeans to Central Asia and China. The pioneering journey of Marco Polo inspired [[Christopher Columbus]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Landström 1967 27&quot;&gt;Landström, Björn. (1967). ''Columbus: the story of Don Cristóbal Colón, Admiral of the Ocean''. New York City: Macmillan.&lt;/ref&gt; and other European explorers of the following centuries.

===Proto-globalization===
{{Main|Proto-globalization}}
The next phase, known as [[proto-globalization]], was characterized by the rise of maritime European empires, in the 16th and 17th centuries, first the [[Portuguese Empire|Portuguese]] and [[Spanish Empire]]s, and later the [[Dutch Empire|Dutch]] and [[British Empire]]s. In the 17th century, world trade developed further when [[chartered companies]] like the [[British East India Company]] (founded in 1600) and the [[Dutch East India Company]] (founded in 1602, often described as the first [[multinational corporation]] in which stock was offered) were established.&lt;ref&gt;Chaudhuri, K.N. (1965\1999). ''The English East India Company: The Study of an Early Joint-stock Company 1600-1640 (Vol. 4).'' London: Routledge/Thoemmes Press.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Age of Discovery]] added the [[New World]] to the equation,&lt;ref&gt;MSN. (2009). &quot;The Age of Exploration&quot;. ''Microsoft Encarta Online Encyclopedia.''[http://www.webcitation.org/query?id=1257036909599733 Archived, 31 October 2009.]&lt;/ref&gt; beginning in the late 15th century.  [[Kingdom of Portugal|Portugal]] and [[Kingdom of Castile|Castile]] sent the first exploratory voyages&lt;ref&gt;MSN. (2009). &quot;Portuguese Empire&quot;. ''Microsoft Encarta Online Encyclopedia''.[http://www.webcitation.org/query?id=1257023597989801 Archived, 31 October 2009.]&lt;/ref&gt; around the [[Horn of Africa]] and to the Americas, reached in 1492 by the Italian explorer [[Christopher Columbus]]. Global trade growth continued with the [[European colonization of the Americas]] initiating the [[Columbian Exchange]],&lt;ref&gt;Crosby, Alfred W. (2003). &quot;The Columbian exchange: biological and cultural consequences of 1492.&quot;, Westport, Conn. : Praeger. ISBN 0-275-98073-1&lt;/ref&gt; the exchange of plants, animals, foods, human populations (including [[slave labor|slaves]]), [[communicable disease]]s, and culture between the [[Eastern Hemisphere|Eastern]] and [[Western Hemisphere|Western]] hemispheres. [[Columbian Exchange|New crops]] that had come from the Americas via the European seafarers in the 16th century significantly contributed to world population growth.&lt;ref&gt;McNeill, J.R. (2008). &quot;The Columbian Exchange&quot;. [http://www.learnnc.org/lp/editions/nchist-twoworlds/1866 ''North Carolina Digital History'', The University of North Carolina.]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Colonisation2.gif|thumb|Animated map showing the development of European [[colonial empire]]s from 1492 to present]]
[[File:Marshall's flax-mill, Holbeck, Leeds - interior - c.1800.jpg|thumb|19th century [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|Great Britain]] become the first global economic superpower, because of superior manufacturing technology and improved global communications such as [[steamship]]s and railroads.]]

===Modern===
In the 19th century, [[steamship]]s reduced the cost of international transport significantly and [[railroad]]s made inland transport cheaper. The transport revolution occurred some time between 1820 and 1850.&lt;ref name=&quot;When Did Globalization Begin&quot;/&gt; More nations embraced international trade.&lt;ref name=&quot;When Did Globalization Begin&quot;/&gt; Globalization in this period was decisively shaped by nineteenth-century [[imperialism]] such as in [[Scramble for Africa|Africa]] and [[Imperialism in Asia|Asia]].

Globalization took a big step backwards during the First World War, the [[Great Depression]], and the Second World War. Integration of rich countries didn't recover to previous levels before the 1980s.{{citation needed|date = July 2012}}

After the Second World War, work by politicians led to the [[Bretton Woods conference]], an agreement by major governments to lay down the framework for international monetary policy, commerce and finance, and the founding of several international institutions intended to facilitate economic growth multiple rounds of trade opening simplified and lowered trade barriers. Initially, the [[General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade]] (GATT), led to a series of agreements to remove trade restrictions. GATT's successor was the [[World Trade Organization]] (WTO), which created an institution to manage the trading system. Exports nearly doubled from 8.5% of total gross world product in 1970 to 16.2% in 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.globalpolicy.org/socecon/trade/tables/exports2.htm | title = World Exports as Percentage of Gross World Product | publisher=[[Global Policy Forum]] | archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080712023541/http://www.globalpolicy.org/socecon/trade/tables/exports2.htm | archivedate = 12 July 2008 | accessdate =11 November 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/s&gt; The approach of using global agreements to advance trade stumbled with the failure of the [[Doha round]] of trade-negotiation. Many countries then shifted to bilateral or smaller multilateral agreements, such as the 2011 [[South Korea–United States Free Trade Agreement]].

Since the 1970s, aviation has become increasingly affordable to middle classes in developed countries. [[Open skies]] policies and [[low-cost carrier]]s have helped to bring competition to the market.

In the 1990s, the growth of low cost communication networks cut the cost of communicating between different countries. More work can be performed using a computer without regard to location. This included accounting, software development, and engineering design. In late 2000s, much of the industrialized world entered into the [[Late 2000s recession|Great Recession]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | url = http://www.forbes.com/2009/01/14/global-recession-2009-oped-cx_nr_0115roubini.html | title = A Global Breakdown Of The Recession In 2009 | author=Roubini, Nouriel | date = 15 January 2009 | work=Forbes | authorlink = Nouriel Roubini}}&lt;/ref&gt; which may have slowed the process, at least temporarily.&lt;ref&gt;Faiola, Anthony. (2009). &quot;A Global Retreat As Economies Dry Up.&quot; [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/03/04/AR2009030404221.html ''The Washington Post'', 5 March 2009.]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gjelten, Tom. (2009). &quot;Economic Crisis Poses Threat To Global Stability.&quot; [http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=100781975 NPR, 18 February 2009.]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lodge, George C. (1995). ''Managing Globalization in the Age of Interdependence''. Golden Books Center: Kuala Lumpur. p.2.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aspects==

===Global business organization===
[[Image:Global Competitiveness Index 2008-2009.svg|thumb|left|[[Global Competitiveness Index]] (2008-2009): [[competitiveness]] is an important determinant for the well-being of nation-states in an international environment]]

{{Main|International business}} 

With improvements in transportation and communication, international business grew rapidly after the beginning of the 20th century.  International business includes all commercial transactions ([[Privately-held company|private]]   [[sales]], [[investments]], [[logistics]],and [[transportation]]) that take place between two or more [[regions]], [[countries]] and [[nations]] beyond their political boundary. Usually, private companies undertake such [[Financial transaction|transactions]] for [[Profit (accounting)|profit]].&lt;ref&gt;Daniels, J., Radebaugh, L., Sullivan, D. (2007). International Business: environment and operations, 11th edition. Prentice Hall. ISBN 0-13-186942-6&lt;/ref&gt; Such business transactions involve economic resources such as [[capital (economics)|capital]], natural and human resources used for international production of physical goods and services such as [[finance]], [[banking]], [[insurance]], [[construction]] and other [[Production (economics)|productive]] activities.&lt;ref&gt;[[Rakesh Mohan Joshi|Joshi, Rakesh Mohan]], (2009) ''International Business''. Oxford University Press, ISBN 0-19-568909-7&lt;/ref&gt;

International business arrangements have led to the formation of [[multinational corporation|multinational enterprises]] (MNE), companies that have a worldwide approach to markets and production or one with operations in more than one country. An MNE is often called multinational corporation (MNC) or transnational company (TNC). Well known MNCs include [[fast food]] companies such as [[McDonald's]] and [[Yum Brands]], vehicle manufacturers such as [[General Motors Corporation|General Motors]], [[Ford Motor Company]] and [[Toyota]], consumer electronics companies like [[Samsung]], [[LG]] and [[Sony]], and energy companies such as [[ExxonMobil]], [[Royal Dutch Shell|Shell]] and [[BP]].  Most of the largest corporations operate in multiple national markets.

Businesses argue that survival in the new global marketplace requires companies to source [[Good (economics)|goods]], [[Service (economics)|services]], [[Manual labour|labor]] and materials overseas to continuously upgrade their products and technology in order to survive increased competition.

====International trade====
{{Main|International trade}}
[[File:1 singapore city skyline dusk panorama 2011.jpg|thumb|alt=Singapore skyline|[[Singapore]], the top country in the [[Global Enabling Trade Report|Enabling Trade Index]], embraced globalization and became a highly developed country]]

An [[Absolute advantage|absolute trade advantage]] exists when countries can produce a commodity with less costs per unit produced than could its trading partner. By the same reasoning, it should import commodities in which it has an absolute disadvantage.&lt;ref name=&quot;ingham&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= International economics: a European focus |last= Ingham |first= Barbara |authorlink= |coauthors= |year= 2004 |publisher= Pearson Education |location= |isbn= 0-273-65507-8|page= 336 |url= http://books.google.com/?id=zIaS9R7HUGIC&amp;printsec=frontcover#PPT37,M1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  While there are possible [[gains from trade]] with absolute advantage, [[comparative advantage]]—that is, the ability to offer goods and services at a lower [[Marginal cost|marginal]] and [[opportunity cost]]—extends the range of possible mutually beneficial exchanges. In a globalized business environment, companies argue that the comparative advantages offered by international trade have become essential to remaining competitive.

=====Trade agreements, economic blocks and special trade zones=====

A [[Special Economic Zone]] ('''SEZ''') is a geographical region that has economic and other laws that are more free-market-oriented than a country's typical or national laws. &quot;Nationwide&quot; laws may be suspended inside these special zones.  The category 'SEZ' covers many areas, including [[Free Trade Zones]] (FTZ), Export Processing Zones (EPZ), [[free economic zone|Free Zone]]s (FZ), [[Industrial park]]s or Industrial Estates (IE), [[Free Port]]s, Urban Enterprise Zones and others. Usually the goal of a structure is to increase [[foreign direct investment]] by foreign investors, typically an [[international business]] or a [[multinational corporation]] (MNC). These are designated areas in which companies are taxed very lightly or not at all in order to encourage economic activity.  Free ports have historically been endowed with favorable customs regulations, e.g., the free port of [[Trieste]]. Very often free ports constitute a part of free economic zones.

A FTZ is an area within which goods may be landed, handled, manufactured or reconfigured, and reexported without the intervention of the customs authorities. Only when the goods are moved to consumers within the country in which the zone is located do they become subject to the prevailing [[customs duties]]. Free trade zones are organized around major seaports, international airports, and national frontiers—areas with many geographic advantages for trade.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/218417/free-trade-zone] Definition of Free Trade Zone-Source-Britannica&lt;/ref&gt; It is a region where a group of countries has agreed to reduce or eliminate trade barriers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | authorlink = Arthur O' Sullivan
  | coauthors = Steven M. Sheffrin
  | title = Economics: Principles in action
  | publisher = Pearson Prentice Hall
  | year = 2003
  | location = Upper Saddle River, New Jersey 07458
  | page = 454
  | url = http://www.pearsonschool.com/index.cfm?locator=PSZ3R9&amp;PMDbSiteId=2781&amp;PMDbSolutionId=6724&amp;PMDbCategoryId=&amp;PMDbProgramId=12881&amp;level=4
  | doi =
  | id =
  | isbn = 0-13-063085-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A [[free trade area]] is a [[trade bloc]] whose member countries have signed a free-trade agreement, which eliminates [[tariff]]s, [[import quota]]s, and preferences on most (if not all) [[good (economics)|goods]] and services traded between them. If people are also free to move between the countries, in addition to free-trade area, it would also be considered an [[open border]].  The [[European Union]], for example, a confederation of 27 member states, provides both a free trade area and an open border.

[[File:Jakarta Welcome ASEAN Delegates Billboard.jpg|thumb|upright|left|A Billboard in Jakarta welcoming [[ASEAN]] Summit 2011 delegates.]]

[[Qualifying Industrial Zones]] ('''QIZ''') are industrial parks that house manufacturing operations in Jordan and Egypt. They are a special free trade zones established in collaboration with neighboring [[Israel]] to take advantage of the free trade agreements between the United States and Israel. Under the trade agreements with Jordan as laid down by the United States, goods produced in QIZ-notified areas can directly access US markets without [[tariff]] or [[Import quota|quota]] restrictions, subject to certain conditions. To qualify, goods produced in these zones must contain a small portion of Israeli input. In addition, a minimum 35% value to the goods must be added to the finished product. The brainchild of Jordanian businessman Omar Salah, the first QIZ was authorized by the [[United States Congress]] in 1997. 

The [[Asia-Pacific]] has been described as &quot;the most integrated trading region on the planet&quot; because its intra-regional trade accounts probably for as much as 50-60% of the region's total imports and exports.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theaustralian.com.au/business/economics/asia-pacific-leads-in-integrated-trade/story-e6frg926-1226119214899 Asia-Pacific leads world in integration of trade]&lt;/ref&gt;
It has also extra-regional trade: consumer goods exports such as televisions, [[radios]], bicycles, and textiles into the United States, Europe, and Japan fueled the economic expansion.&lt;ref&gt;Vogel, Ezra F. 1991. ''The Four Little Dragons: The Spread of Industrialization in East Asia.'' Cambridge, Massachusetts: Harvard University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; 

The [[ASEAN Free Trade Area]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aseansec.org/4920.htm AFTA &amp; FTAs (ASEAN Secretariat)]&lt;/ref&gt; is a [[trade bloc]] agreement by the [[Association of Southeast Asian Nations]] supporting local manufacturing in all ASEAN countries. The AFTA agreement was signed on 28 January 1992 in Singapore. When the AFTA agreement was originally signed, ASEAN had six members, namely, [[Brunei]], [[Indonesia]], [[Malaysia]], [[Philippines]], [[Singapore]] and [[Thailand]]. [[Vietnam]] joined in 1995, [[Laos]] and [[Myanmar]] in 1997 and [[Cambodia]] in 1999.

=====Drug trade=====
In 2010 the United Nations Office on Drugs and Crime ([[UNODC]]) reported that the global drug trade generated more than $320&amp;nbsp;billion a year in revenues.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs/2009/gashc3947.doc.htm |title=UN.org |publisher=United Nations |accessdate=31 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Worldwide, the UN estimates there are more than 50 million regular users of heroin, cocaine and synthetic drugs.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/hi/english/static/in_depth/world/2000/drugs_trade/default.stm Drug Trade]&quot;. BBC News.&lt;/ref&gt; The international trade of [[endangered species]] was second only to drug trafficking among smuggling &quot;industries&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/11/11/TR10T8RBN.DTL Will traditional Chinese medicine mean the end of the wild tiger?]&quot;. San Francisco Chronicle. 11 November 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Traditional Chinese medicine#Animal products|Traditional Chinese medicine]] often incorporates ingredients from all parts of plants, the leaf, stem, flower, root, and also ingredients from animals and minerals. The use of parts of endangered species (such as [[Seahorse (fish)|seahorses]], [[rhinoceros]] horns, [[saiga antelope]] horns, and [[tiger]] bones and claws) resulted in a [[black market]] of poachers who hunt restricted animals.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.reuters.com/article/environmentNews/idUSTRE58G4XQ20090917 India says Chinese medicine fuels tiger poaching]&quot;. Reuters. 17 September 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.newscientist.com/channel/life/endangered-species/dn3376 Rhino rescue plan decimates Asian antelopes]&quot;. New Scientist. 12 February 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Tax havens====
[[File:German GDP in tax havens.png|thumb|The ratio of German assets in tax havens in relation to the total German GDP.&lt;ref&gt;Shafik Hebous (2011) [http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1934164 &quot;Money at the Docks of Tax Havens: A Guide&quot;], CESifo Working Paper Series No. 3587, p. 9&lt;/ref&gt; The &quot;Big 7&quot; shown are Hong Kong, Ireland, Lebanon, Liberia, Panama, Singapore, and Switzerland.]]
{{Main|Tax haven}}

A tax haven is a state, country or territory where certain [[tax]]es are levied at a low rate or not at all, which are used by businesses for [[tax avoidance and tax evasion]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ssrn&quot;&gt;Dharmapala, Dhammika und Hines Jr., James R. (2006) [http://ssrn.com/abstract=952721 Which Countries Become Tax Havens?]&lt;/ref&gt; Individuals and/or corporate entities can find it attractive to establish [[shell corporation|shell subsidiaries]] or move themselves to areas with reduced or nil taxation levels. This creates a situation of [[tax competition]] among governments. Different [[jurisdiction]]s tend to be havens for different types of taxes, and for different categories of people and/or companies.&lt;ref&gt;Moran Harari, Markus Meinzer and Richard Murphy (October 2012) [http://www.taxjustice.net/cms/upload/pdf/FSI2012_BanksBig4.pdf &quot;Financial Secrecy, Banks and the Big 4 Firms of Accountants&quot;] ''Tax Justice Network''&lt;/ref&gt; States that are [[Sovereignty|sovereign]] or self-governing under [[international law]] have theoretically unlimited powers to enact tax laws affecting their territories, unless limited by previous international treaties. The central feature of a tax haven is that its laws and other measures can be used to evade or avoid the tax laws or regulations of other jurisdictions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.taxjustice.net/cms/upload/pdf/Identifying_Tax_Havens_Jul_07.pdf |title=The Truth About Tax Havens - retrieved 28 December 2007 |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2011-03-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; In its December 2008 report on the use of tax havens by American corporations,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gao.gov/products/GAO-09-157|title=''International Taxation: Large U.S. Corporations and Federal Contractors with Subsidiaries in Jurisdictions Listed as Tax Havens or Financial Privacy Jurisdictions'' GAO:GAO-09-157 |publisher=[[Government Accountability Office]]|date=December 18, 2008|accessdate=2009-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; the U.S. [[Government Accountability Office]] was unable to find a satisfactory definition of a tax haven but regarded the following characteristics as indicative of it:
* nil or nominal taxes;
* lack of effective exchange of tax information with foreign tax authorities;
* lack of transparency in the operation of legislative, legal or administrative provisions;
* no requirement for a substantive local presence; and
* self-promotion as an [[offshore financial centre|offshore financial center]].

A 2012 report from the [[Tax Justice Network]] estimated that between USD $21 trillion and $32 trillion is sheltered from taxes in unreported tax havens worldwide. If such wealth earns 3% annually and such [[capital gains]] were taxed at 30%, it would generate between $190 billion and $280 billion in tax revenues, more than any other [[tax shelters]].&lt;ref name=tjn12&gt;Tax Justice Network (July 22, 2012) [http://www.taxjustice.net/cms/upload/pdf/The_Price_of_Offshore_Revisited_Presser_120722.pdf &quot;Revealed: Global super-rich has at least $21 trillion hidden in secret tax havens&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; If such hidden offshore assets are considered, many countries with governments nominally in debt are shown to be net creditor nations.&lt;ref name=cbc12&gt;Canadian Broadcasting Co. (July 22, 2012) [http://www.cbc.ca/news/world/story/2012/07/22/tax-havens.html &quot;Wealthy hiding $21 trillion in tax havens, report says&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; However, the tax policy director of the [[Chartered Institute of Taxation]] expressed skepticism over the accuracy of the figures.&lt;ref&gt;John Whiting, tax policy director at the [[Chartered Institute of Taxation]] commented &quot;There clearly are some significant amounts hidden away, but if it really is that size what is being done with it all?&quot; and &quot;If the suggestion is that such amounts are actively hidden and never accessed, that seems odd - not least in terms of what the tax authorities are doing. In fact, the US, UK and German authorities are doing a lot&quot;, and noting that if the figures were accurate &quot;you would expect the havens to be more conspicuously wealthy than they are&quot;.  However, he also admitted that &quot;I cannot disprove the figures at all, but they do seem staggering&quot; {{citeweb|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-18944097|title=Tax havens: Super-rich 'hiding' at least $21tn|date=2012-07-22|accessdate=2012-10-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Daniel J. Mitchell]] of the [[Cato Institute]] says that the report also assumes, when considering notional lost tax revenue, that 100% money deposited offshore is evading payment of tax.&lt;ref&gt;{{citeweb|url=http://sovereign-investor.com/2012/07/30/fighting-anti-tax-haven-demagoguery-on-cnn/|title=Fighting Anti-Tax Haven Demagoguery on CNN|date=2012-07-30|accessdate=2012-10-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Information systems====
{{Main|Global information system}}

Multinational corporations face the challenge of developing global information systems for global data processing and decision-making.  The [[Internet]] provides a broad area of services to business and individual users. Because the [[World Wide Web]] (WWW) can reach any Internet-connected computer in the world, the Internet is closely related to [[global information system]]s. A global information system is a data communication network that crosses national boundaries to access and process data in order to achieve corporate goals and strategic objectives.&lt;ref&gt;Gensler, P. J. &amp; Chou, D. C. (1991). &quot;Managing global information systems.&quot; ''Information Executive'', 4(4):35-37.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Across companies and continents, information standards ensure desirable characteristics of products and services such as quality, environmental friendliness, safety, reliability, efficiency and interchangeability at an economical cost.  For businesses, widespread adoption of international standards means that suppliers can develop and offer products and services meeting specifications that have wide international acceptance in their sectors. According to the [[ISO]], businesses using their International Standards are competitive in more markets around the world. The ISO develops standards by organizing technical committees of experts from the industrial, technical and business sectors who have asked for the standards and which subsequently put them to use. These experts may be joined by representatives of government agencies, testing laboratories, consumer associations, non-governmental organizations and academic circles.&lt;ref&gt;(2011.) ''Economic benefits of standards - International case studies''. ISO. ISBN 978-92-10556-7&lt;/ref&gt;

====International tourism====
[[File:boarding.easyjet.a319.arp.jpg|thumb|Modern aviation has made it possible to travel long distances quickly.]]
{{Main|Tourism}}

[[Tourism]] is [[travel]] for [[recreation]]al, [[leisure]] or [[business]] purposes. The [[World Tourism Organization]] defines tourists as people &quot;traveling to and staying in places outside their usual environment for not more than one consecutive year for leisure, business and other purposes&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|year=1995|url=http://pub.unwto.org/WebRoot/Store/Shops/Infoshop/Products/1034/1034-1.pdf|title=UNWTO technical manual: Collection of Tourism Expenditure Statistics|page=14|publisher=World Tourism Organization|accessdate=26 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are many forms of tourism such as [[agritourism]], [[birth tourism]], [[culinary tourism]], [[cultural tourism]], [[eco-tourism]],[[extreme tourism]], [[geotourism]], [[heritage tourism]], [[LGBT tourism]], [[medical tourism]], [[nautical tourism]], [[pop-culture tourism]], [[religious tourism]], [[slum tourism]], [[war tourism]], and [[wildlife tourism]]

Globalization has made tourism a popular global leisure activity. The World Health Organization ([[WHO]]) estimates that up to 500,000 people are in flight at any one time.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/feedarticle/8477508 Swine flu prompts EU warning on travel to US]. ''The Guardian.'' 28 April 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, international tourism reached $919B, growing 6.5% over 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=UNWTO World Tourism Barometer June 2009|url=http://mkt.unwto.org/sites/all/files/pdf/unwto_pisa_2011_1.pdf|year=2011|month=June|publisher=World Tourism Organization|journal=UNWTO World Tourism Barometer|volume=7|issue=2|accessdate=3 August 2009|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, there were over 940 million international tourist arrivals worldwide, representing a growth of 6.6% when compared to 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;WTO2011Highlights&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://mkt.unwto.org/sites/all/files/docpdf/unwtohighlights11enlr.pdf|title=2011 Highlights |journal=UNWTO World Tourism Highlights |accessdate=9 January 2012|publisher=UNWTO |month=June |year=2011 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; International tourism receipts grew to {{USD|919}} billion ({{euro|693}} billion) in 2010, corresponding to an increase in [[Real versus nominal value (economics)|real terms]] of 4.7%.&lt;ref name=WTO2011Highlights/&gt;

As a result of the [[late-2000s recession]], international [[Travel behavior|travel demand]] suffered a strong slowdown from the second half of 2008 through the end of 2009. After a 5% increase in the first half of 2008, growth in international tourist arrivals moved into negative territory in the second half of 2008, and ended up only 2% for the year, compared to a 7% increase in 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://www.unwto.org/facts/eng/pdf/barometer/UNWTO_Barom09_1_en.pdf|title=International tourism challenged by deteriorating global economy|publisher=[[World Tourism Organization]]|journal=UNWTO World Tourism Barometer|month=January |year=2009|volume=7|issue=1|accessdate=17 November 2011 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; This negative trend intensified during 2009, exacerbated in some countries due to the outbreak of the [[2009 flu pandemic|H1N1 influenza virus]], resulting in a worldwide decline of 4.2% in 2009 to 880 million international tourists arrivals, and a 5.7% decline in international tourism receipts.&lt;ref name=WTOaugust10&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.unwto.org/facts/eng/pdf/barometer/UNWTO_Barom10_update_august_en.pdf|title=UNWTO World Tourism Barometer Interim Update|journal=UNWTO World Tourism Barometer|publisher=[[World Tourism Organization]]|month=August|year=2010|accessdate=17 November 2011|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Economic globalization===
{{Main|Economic globalization}}
[[File:Shanghai-pudong night.jpg|thumb|right|[[Shanghai]] becomes a symbol of the recent economic boom of [[China]]. In 2011, China had 960,000 millionaires.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://articles.economictimes.indiatimes.com/2011-04-13/news/29413775_1_chinese-millionaires-yuan-chinese-economy China close to have $1 million millionaires]&quot;. ''[[The Economic Times]]''. 13 April 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;]]

Economic globalization is the increasing economic interdependence of national economies across the world through a rapid increase in [[cross-border]] movement of goods, service, technology and capital.&lt;ref name=&quot;Joshi, Rakesh Mohan 2009&quot;&gt;Joshi, Rakesh Mohan, (2009) International Business, Oxford University Press, New Delhi and New York ISBN 0-19-568909-7.&lt;/ref&gt; Whereas the globalization of business is centered around the diminution of international trade regulations as well as tariffs, taxes, and other impediments that suppresses global trade, economic globalization is the process of increasing [[economic integration]] between countries, leading to the emergence of a global marketplace or a single world market.&lt;ref&gt;Riley, T: &quot;Year 12 Economics&quot;, page 9. Tim Riley Publications, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; Depending on the paradigm, economic globalization can be viewed as either a positive or a negative phenomenon.

Economic globalization comprises the globalization of [[Production (economics)|production]], [[markets]], [[Competitiveness|competition]], technology, and corporations and industries.&lt;ref name=&quot;Joshi, Rakesh Mohan 2009&quot;/&gt; Current globalization trends can be largely accounted for by [[Developed country|developed economies]] integrating with [[Developing country|less developed economies]], by means of [[foreign direct investment]], the reduction of [[trade barrier]]s as well as other [[economic reform]]s and, in many cases, [[immigration]].

As an example, [[Chinese economic reform]] began to open China to the globalization in the 1980s. Scholars find that China has attained a degree of openness that is unprecedented among large and populous nations&quot;, with competition from foreign goods in almost every sector of the economy. Foreign investment helped to greatly increase quality, knowledge and standards, especially in heavy industry. China's experience supports the assertion that globalization greatly increases wealth for poor countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;Loren 13&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Brandt|2008|p=13}}&lt;/ref&gt;
As of 2005–2007, the [[Port of Shanghai]] holds the title as the [[World's busiest port]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title =World Port Rankings 2005 | publisher=American Association of Port Authorities | year = 2005 | url =http://www.infoplease.com/business/world-port-ranking-2005.html | accessdate =15 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title =World Port Rankings 2006 | publisher=American Association of Port Authorities | year = 2006 | url =http://www.infoplease.com/business/world-port-ranking.html | accessdate =15 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://aapa.files.cms-plus.com/Statistics/WORLD%20PORT%20RANKINGS%2020081.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Economic liberalization in India]] is the ongoing economic reforms in [[Economy of India|India]] that started in 1991. As of 2009, about 300 million people—equivalent to the entire population of the United States—have [[Poverty in India|escaped extreme poverty]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.reason.com/blog/show/131810.html|title=What Slumdog Millionaire can teach Americans about economic stimulus|year=2008|author=Nick Gillespie|publisher=Reason}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In [[India]], [[business process outsourcing]] has been described as the &quot;primary engine of the country's development over the next few decades, contributing broadly to GDP growth, employment growth, and poverty alleviation&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kuruvilla 2008 39–72&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Kuruvilla|coauthors=Ranganathan|title=ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT STRATEGIES AND MACRO- AND MICRO-LEVEL HUMAN RESOURCE POLICIES: THE CASE OF INDIA'S &quot;OUTSOURCING&quot; INDUSTRY|journal=Industrial &amp; Labor Relations Review|year=2008|month=October|volume=62|issue=1|pages=39–72|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.economist.com/node/15777592?story_id=E1_TVSSSVJN|accessdate=16 April 2011|title=Outsourcing to Africa: The world economy calls &amp;#124; The Economist|date=16 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Measures====

=====Indices=====
{{Main|Globalization Index}}

Measurement of economic globalization focuses on variables such as [[trade]], [[Foreign Direct Investment]] (FDI), [[portfolio investment]], and [[income]].  However, newer indices attempt to measure globalization in more general terms, including variables related to political, social, cultural, and even environmental aspects of globalization.&lt;ref&gt;Vujakovic, Petra. (2010). &quot;How to Measure Globalization? A New Globalization Index (NGI).&quot; ''Atlantic Economic Journal'',
38(2): 237. [http://www.springerlink.com/content/d5q1337j314n7275/ ] {{doi|10.1007/s11293-010-9217-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One index of globalization is the KOF Index, which measures the three main dimensions of globalization:  economic, social, and political.&lt;ref&gt;Dreher, Axel (2006): &quot;Does Globalization Affect Growth? Evidence from a new Index of Globalization.&quot; ''Applied Economics'' 38(10): 1091-1110.&lt;/ref&gt;

{|
|-
| '''2010 List by the KOF Index of Globalization'''
| '''2006 List by the A.T. Kearney/Foreign Policy Magazine'''
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;margin-left:auto;margin-right:auto&quot;
|-
! Rank !! Country
|-
|1||{{flagcountry|Belgium}}
|-
|2||{{flagcountry|Austria}}
|-
|3||{{flagcountry|Netherlands}}
|-
|4||{{flagcountry|Switzerland}}
|-
|5||{{flagcountry|Sweden}}
|-
|6||{{flagcountry|Denmark}}
|-
|7||{{flagcountry|Canada}}
|-
|8||{{flagcountry|Portugal}}
|-
|9||{{flagcountry|Finland}}
|-
|10||{{flagcountry|Hungary}}
|}
|
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
!Rank || Country
|-
|1|| {{flagcountry|Singapore}}
|-
|2||{{flagcountry|Switzerland}}
|-
|3||{{flagcountry|United States}}
|-
|4||{{flag|Ireland}}
|-
|5||{{flagcountry|Denmark}}
|-
|6||{{flagcountry|Canada}}
|-
|7||{{flagcountry|Netherlands}}
|-
|8||{{flagcountry|Australia}}
|-
|9||{{flagcountry|Austria}}
|-
|10||{{flagcountry|Sweden}}
|}
|}

=====Measuring free trade policies=====
{{Main|Global Enabling Trade Report}}

The [[Global Enabling Trade Report|Enabling Trade Index]] measures the factors, policies and services that facilitate the trade in goods across borders and to destination. It is made up of four sub-indexes: market access; border administration; transport and communications infrastructure; and business environment. The top 20 countries are:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url= http://www.weforum.org/pdf/GETR10/GETR10-Overall-Rankings.pdf |title = Rankings: Global Enabling Trade Report 2010| author = World Economic Forum}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{col-begin}}
{{col-break}}
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt; {{SIN}} 6.06&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; [[Image:Flag of Hong Kong.svg|border|22px]] [[Hong Kong]] 5.70&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; {{DEN}} 5.41&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; {{SWE}} 5.41&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; {{SUI}} 5.37&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; {{NZL}} 5.33&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; {{NOR}} 5.32&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; {{CAN}} 5.29&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; {{LUX}} 5.28&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; {{NED}} 5.26&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;

{{col-break}}
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li value=&quot;11&quot;&gt; {{ISL}} 5.26&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt; {{FIN}} 5.25&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; {{GER}} 5.20&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; [[Image:Flag of Austria.svg|border|22px]] [[Austria]] 5.17&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; {{AUS}} 5.13&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; {{UAE}} 5.12&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; {{UK}} 5.06&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; {{CHI}} 5.06&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; {{USA}} 5.03&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; {{FRA}} 5.02&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
{{col-end}}

=== Sociocultural globalization ===

====Culture====
{{Main|Cultural globalization}}

[[File:Shakira Rio 03.jpg|thumb|upright|left|[[Shakira]], a Colombian multilingual singer-songwriter, playing outside her home country.]]
[[Cultural globalization]] has increased cross-cultural contacts but may be accompanied by a decrease in the uniqueness of once-isolated communities: [[sushi]] is available in Germany as well as Japan, but Euro-Disney outdraws the city of Paris, potentially reducing demand for &quot;authentic&quot; French pastry.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.cato.org/pubs/policy_report/v25n3/globalization.pdf |title=Globalization and Culture |last1=Cowen |first1=Tyler |last2=Barber |first2=Benjamin |journal=Cato Policy Report |date=May/June 2003 |accessdate=November 2011|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Nadeem, S (2009) [http://nadeem.commons.gc.cuny.edu/files/2010/04/CS_Nadeem.pdf Macaulay's (Cyber) Children: The Cultural Politics of Outsourcing in India]. Cultural Sociology&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hacker, Violaine (2011), &quot;Building Medias Industry while promoting a community of values in the globalization: from quixotic choices to pragmatic boon for EU Citizens&quot;, Politické Védy-Journal of Political Science, Slovakia&lt;/ref&gt; Globalisation's contribution to the alienation of individuals from their traditions may be modest compared to the impact of modernity itself, as alleged by [[existentialists]] such as [[Jean-Paul Sartre]] and [[Albert Camus]].  Globalization has expanded recreational opportunities by spreading pop culture, particularly via the Internet and satellite television.

Religious movements were among the earliest cultural forces to globalize, spread by force, migration, [[evangelism|evangelists]], imperialists and traders. [[Christianity]], [[Islam]], [[Buddhism]] and more recently sects such as [[Mormonism]] have taken root and influenced endemic cultures in places far from their origins.&lt;ref&gt;McAlister, Elizabeth. 2005.
&quot;[http://wesscholar.wesleyan.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1038&amp;context=div2facpubs Globalization and the Religious Production of Space.]&quot; Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion, Vol. 44, No 3, September 2005, 249–255.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Mac Japan.jpg|thumb|alt=Japanese McDonald's|A McDonald's in [[Osaka]], [[Japan]] illustrates the [[McDonaldization]] of global society]]
Conversi claimed in 2010 that globalization was predominantly driven by the outward flow of culture and economic activity from the United States and was better understood as [[Americanization]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://easyweb.easynet.co.uk/conversi/agora Americanization]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://criticalglobalisation.com/Issue3/36_59_LIMITS_CULTURAL_GLOBALISATION_JCGS3.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; or [[Westernization]]. For example, the two most successful global food/beverage outlets are American companies, [[List of countries with McDonald's franchises|McDonald's]] and [[Starbucks]], are often cited as examples of globalization, with over 32,000&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/63908/000119312511046701/d10k.htm|title=2010 Form 10-K, McDonald's Corporation|publisher=United States Securities and Exchange Commission|accessdate=3 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and 18,000 locations operating worldwide, respectively as of 2008.&lt;ref&gt;Steger, Manfred.''[http://books.google.com/books?id=1ExsTX8z4j8C&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;dq=globalization&amp;pg=PA90#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Globalization]''. New York: Sterling Publishing, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

The term globalization implies transformation. Cultural practices including traditional music can be lost and/or turned into a fusion of traditions. Globalization can trigger a state of emergency for the preservation of musical heritage. Archivists must attempt to collect, record or transcribe repertoire before melodies are assimilated or modified. Local musicians struggle for [[authenticity in art|authenticity]] and to preserve local musical traditions. Globalization can lead performers to discard traditional instruments. Fusion genres can become interesting fields of analysis.&lt;ref&gt;Clayton, Thomas. 2004. &quot;Competing Conceptions of Globalization&quot; Revisited: Relocating the Tension between World-Systems Analysis and Globalization Analysis. In: Comparative Education Review, vol. 48, no.3, 274-294.&lt;/ref&gt;

Globalization gave support to the [[World Music]] phenomenon by allowing locally-recorded to reach western audiences searching for new ideas and sounds. For example, Western musicians have adopted many innovations that originated in other cultures.&lt;ref&gt;Throsby, David. (2002.) &quot;The music industry in the new millenium: Global and Local Perspectives.&quot; [http://portal.unesco.org/culture/en/files/25428/11066604353The_Music_Industry_in_the_new_Millenium.pdf/The+Music+Industry+in+the+new+Millenium.pdf Paper prepared for The Global Alliance for Cultural Diversity Division of Arts and Cultural Enterprise UNESCO, Paris.]&lt;/ref&gt;

The term was originally intended for ethnic-specific music, though globalization is expanding its scope; it now often includes [[Hybrid genre|hybrid]] sub-genres such as ''World fusion'', ''Global fusion'', ''Ethnic fusion''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.allmusic.com/explore/style/ethnic-fusion-d224 |title=Ethnic fusion Music |publisher=Allmusic |date= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Worldbeat]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.allmusic.com/explore/style/worldbeat-d248 |title=Worldbeat |publisher=Allmusic |date= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://worldmusic.nationalgeographic.com/view/page.basic/genre/content.genre/world_fusion_800/en_US#contents_top |title=World Fusion Music |publisher=worldmusic.nationalgeographic.com |date= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Music flowed outward from the west as well. Anglo-American pop music spread across the world through [[MTV]]. Dependency Theory explained that the world was an integrated, international system. Musically, this translated into the loss of local musical identity.&lt;ref&gt;Wallerstein, Immanuel. 2004. World-Systems Analysis. An Introduction. London: Duke University Press, pp.23-59.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Coca-Cola does Chinese New Year.jpg|thumb|left|A [[Coca-Cola]] stall outside the [[Grand Gateway Shanghai|Grand Gateway 66]] shopping mall in [[Xujiahui]], [[Shanghai]]]]Bourdieu claimed that the perception of consumption can be seen as self-identification and the formation of identity. Musically, this translates into each being having his own musical identity based on likes and tastes. These likes and tastes are greatly influenced by culture as this is the most basic cause for a person's wants and behavior. The concept of one's own culture is now in a period of change due to globalization. Also, globalization has increased the interdependency of political, personal, cultural and economic factors.&lt;ref&gt;Beard, David and Keneth Gloag. 2005. Musicology: The Key Concepts. London and New York: Routledge.&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2005 UNESCO report&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uis.unesco.org/template/pdf/cscl/IntlFlows_EN.pdf |title=International Flows of Selected Goods and Services |format=PDF |accessdate=31 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; showed that cultural exchange is becoming more frequent from Eastern Asia but Western countries are still the main exporters of cultural goods. In 2002, China was the third largest exporter of cultural goods, after the UK and US. Between 1994 and 2002, both North America's and the European Union's shares of cultural exports declined, while Asia's cultural exports grew to surpass North America. Related factors are the fact that Asia's population and area are several times that of North America.  Americanization related to a period of high political American clout and of significant growth of America's shops, markets and object being brought into other countries. So globalization, a much more diversified phenomenon, relates to a multilateral political world and to the increase of objects, markets and so on into each other's countries. The Indian experience particularly reveals the plurality of the impact of cultural globalization (Biswajit Ghosh 2011 'Cultural Changes in the Era of Globalisation’, Journal of Developing Societies, 27 (2): 153-175).

=====Multilingualism and the emergence of lingua francas=====
{{Main|Multilingualism|Lingua franca|List of lingua francas}}

Multilingual speakers outnumber [[monolingual]] speakers in the world's population.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cal.org/resources/Digest/digestglobal.html A Global Perspective on Bilingualism and Bilingual Education (1999), G. Richard Tucker, Carnegie Mellon University]&lt;/ref&gt; Multilingualism is becoming a social phenomenon governed by the needs of globalization and cultural openness.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://multilingualism.org/multilingualism/the-importance-of-multilingualism |title=The importance of multilingualism |publisher=multilingualism.org |date= |accessdate=16 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thanks to the ease of access to information facilitated by the Internet, individuals' exposure to multiple languages is getting more and more frequent, and triggering therefore the need to acquire more and more languages.

A [[lingua franca]] is a language systematically used to make communication possible between people not sharing a [[mother tongue]], in particular when it is a third language, distinct from both mother tongues.&lt;ref&gt;Viacheslav A. Chirikba, &quot;The problem of the Caucasian Sprachbund&quot; in Pieter Muysken, ed., ''From Linguistic Areas to Areal Linguistics'', 2008, p. 31. ISBN 90-272-3100-1&lt;/ref&gt;

Today, the most popular [[second language]] is English.
Some 3.5 billion people have some acquaintance of the language.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/science/2011/nov/27/translation-creating-global-language
|title=From the Bible to the latest Swedish thriller: 2011 is the year of the translator
|first=Robert |last=McCrum
|publisher=The Observer
|date=26 November 2011 |accessdate=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
English is the dominant language on the Internet.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://anthro.palomar.edu/language/language_1.htm |title=Anthro.palomar.edu |publisher=Anthro.palomar.edu |date=27 July 2009 |accessdate=31 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
About 35% of the world's mail, telexes, and cables are in English.
Approximately 40% of the world's radio programs are in English.

[[Language contact]] occurs when two or more languages or [[Variety (linguistics)|varieties]] interact. [[Multilingualism]] has likely been common throughout much of human history, and today most people in the world are multilingual.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cal.org/resources/Digest/digestglobal.html ''A Global Perspective on Bilingualism and Bilingual Education'' (1999), G. Richard Tucker, Carnegie Mellon University]&lt;/ref&gt; Language contact occurs in a variety of phenomena, including [[language convergence]], [[loanword|borrowing]], and [[relexification]]. The most common products are [[pidgins]], [[Creole language|creoles]], [[code-switching]], and [[mixed language]]s.

====Politics====
{{Main|Global politics}}

[[File:The United Nations Building.jpg|thumb|upright|upright|The [[United Nations Headquarters]] in [[New York City]].]]
In general, globalization may ultimately reduce the importance of [[nation state]]s. Sub-state and supra-state institutions such as the [[European Union]], the [[WTO]], the [[G8]] or the [[International Criminal Court]], replace national functions with international agreement.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scholte, 2005&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Scholte|first=Jan-Aart|title=Globalization: A Critical Introduction (Chapter 6: Globalization and Governance))|year=2005|publisher=Palgrave}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some observers attribute the relative decline in US power to globalization, particularly due to the country's high trade deficit. This led to a global power shift towards Asian states, particularly China, which unleashed market forces and achieved tremendous growth rates. As of 2011, China was on track to overtake the United States by 2025.&lt;ref name=&quot;PWC, 2011&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=PriceWaterhouseCoopers|title=Beyond the BRICs|url=http://www.pwc.co.uk/eng/publications/beyond_the_brics.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Increasingly, [[non-governmental organization]]s influence public policy across national boundaries, including humanitarian aid and developmental efforts.&lt;ref name=&quot;globall&quot;&gt;Pawel Zaleski ''Global Non-governmental Administrative System: Geosociology of the Third Sector'', [in:] Gawin, Dariusz &amp; Glinski, Piotr [ed.]: &quot;Civil Society in the Making&quot;, IFiS Publishers, Warszawa 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

As a response to globalization, some countries have embraced [[isolationism|isolationist]] policies. For example, the [[North Korea]]n government makes it very difficult for foreigners to enter the country and strictly monitors their activities when they do. Aid workers are subject to considerable scrutiny and excluded from places and regions the government does not wish them to enter. Citizens cannot freely leave the country.&lt;ref name=nkr&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.northkoreanrefugees.com/2008-exodus.htm |title=North Korean Refugees NGO |publisher=Northkoreanrefugees.com |date=20 October 2008 |accessdate=23 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=unhcr&gt;{{cite web|author=United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees |url=http://www.unhcr.org/refworld/country,,,,PRK,4562d8cf2,487ca236c0,0.html |title=UNHCR Freedom in the World 2008 - North Korea |publisher=Unhcr.org |date=2 July 2008 |accessdate=23 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Media and public opinion=====
{{Main|Media (communication)|Public opinion}}

A 2005 study by Peer Fiss and Paul Hirsch found large increase in articles negative towards globalization in the years prior. By 1998, negative articles outpaced positive articles by two to one.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fiss 2005&quot;&gt;Fiss, Peer and Hirsch, Pal: &quot;The Discourse of Globalization: Framing and Sensemaking of an Emerging Concept. American Sociological Review, February 2005. vol. 70 no 1: 29–52.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008 Greg Ip claimed this rise in opposition to globalization can be explained, at least in part, by economic self-interest.&lt;ref name=ip08&gt;Greg Ip: &quot;The Declining Value Of Your College Degree&quot;, ''[[Wall Street Journal]]''. 17 July 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; The number of newspaper articles showing negative framing rose from about 10% of the total in 1991 to 55% of the total in 1999. This increase occurred during a period when the total number of articles concerning globalization nearly doubled.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fiss 2005&quot;/&gt;

A number of international polls have shown that residents of developing countries tend to view globalization more favorably.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Africans and Asians Tend to View Globalization Favorably. Europeans and Americans are More Skeptical&quot;. World Public Opinion.org. 7 November 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; The BBC found a growing feeling in developing countries that globalization was proceeding too rapidly. Only a few countries, including Mexico, the countries of Central America, Indonesia, Brazil and Kenya, where a majority felt that globalization is growing too slowly.&lt;ref name=bbc08/&gt;

Philip Gordon stated that &quot;(as of 2004) a clear majority of Europeans believe that globalization can enrich their lives, while believing the European Union can help them take advantage of globalization's benefits while shielding them from its negative effects.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Gordon, Philip. 2004. &quot;Globalization: Europe's Wary Embrace&quot;. ''Yale Global'', 1 November 2004. http://yaleglobal.yale.edu/content/globalization-europes-wary-embrace&lt;/ref&gt; The main opposition consisted of socialists, environmental groups, and nationalists.

Residents of the EU did not appear to feel threatened by globalization in 2004. The EU job market was more stable and workers were less likely to accept wage/benefit cuts. Social spending was much higher than in the US.&lt;ref&gt;Gordon, Philip. 2004. &quot;Globalization: Europe's Wary Embrace&quot;. Yale Global, 1 November 2004. http://yaleglobal.yale.edu/content/globalization-europes-wary-embrace&lt;/ref&gt;

In a Danish poll in 2007, 76% responded that globalisation is a good thing.&lt;ref&gt;Time Magazine: [http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1684528,00.html Why Denmark Loves Globalisation]&lt;/ref&gt;

Fiss, ''et al.'', surveyed U.S. opinion in 1993. Their survey showed that in 1993 more than 40% of respondents were unfamiliar with the concept of globalization. When the survey was repeated in 1998, 89% of the respondents had a polarized view of globalization as being either good or bad. At the same time, discourse on globalization, which began in the financial community before shifting to a heated debate between proponents and disenchanted students and workers. Polarization increased dramatically after the establishment of the WTO in 1995; this event and subsequent protests led to a large-scale anti-globalization movement.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fiss 2005&quot;/&gt;
Initially, college educated workers were likely to support globalization. Less educated workers, who were more likely to compete with immigrants and workers in developing countries, tended to be opponents. The situation changed after the [[Financial crisis of 2007–2010|financial crisis of 2007]]. According to a 1997 poll 58% of college graduates said globalization had been good for the U.S. By 2008 only 33% thought it was good. Respondents with high school education also became more opposed.&lt;ref name=ip08/&gt;

According to Takenaka Heizo and Chida Ryokichi, as of 1998 there was a perception in Japan that the economy was &quot;Small and Frail&quot;. However Japan was resource poor and used exports to pay for its raw materials. Anxiety over their position caused terms such as ''internationalization'' and ''globalization'' to enter everyday language. However, Japanese tradition was to be as self-sufficient as possible, particularly in agriculture.&lt;ref&gt;Takenaka Heizo and Chida Ryokichi. 1998. &quot;Japan,&quot; ''Domestic Adjustments to Globalization''; (ed, Charles E. Morrison and Hadi Soesastro), Tokyo: Japan center for International Exchange, 1998, pp. 76–102.&lt;/ref&gt;

The situation may have changed after the 2007 financial crisis. A 2008 [[BBC]] World Public Poll as the crisis began suggested that opposition to globalization in developed countries was increasing. The BBC poll asked whether globalization was ''growing too rapidly''. Agreement was strongest in France, Spain, Japan, South Korea, and Germany. The trend in these countries appears to be stronger than in the United States. The poll also correlated the tendency to view globalization as proceeding too rapidly with a perception of growing economic insecurity and social inequality.&lt;ref name=bbc08&gt;&quot;Widespread Unease about Economy and Globalization&quot;. ''BBC World Service Pol''l. http://www.worldpublicopinion.org/pipa/pdf/feb08/BBCEcon_Feb08_rpt.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

Many in the Third World see globalization as a positive force that lifts countries out of poverty.&lt;ref name=&quot;bhagwati&quot;/&gt; The opposition typically combined environmental concerns with nationalism. Opponents consider governments as agents of [[neo-colonialism]] that are subservient to [[multinational corporations]].&lt;ref name=&quot;visuality.org&quot;&gt;Shoa S. Rajgopal. 2002. Reclaiming Democracy, the Anti-globalization Movement in South Asia&quot;. Feminist review 70, 2002. http://visuality.org/globalization/wmst250_readings/the_antiglobalization_mvmnt.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; Much of this criticism comes from the middle class; the [[Brookings Institute]] suggested this was because the middle class perceived upwardly mobile low-income groups to threaten their economic security.&lt;ref&gt;Carol Graham &quot;Winners and Losers: Perspectives on Globalization from the Emerging Market Economies&quot; Brookings. Saturday 1 January 2011 http://www.brookings.edu/articles/2001/fall_globaleconomics_graham.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;

Although many critics blame globalization for a [[middle class squeeze|decline of the middle class]] in industrialized countries, the middle class is growing rapidly in the Third World.&lt;ref&gt;John Parker, Burgeoning bourgeoisie, A special report on the new middle classes in emerging markets. The Economist .12 February 2009. http://www.economist.com/node/13063298?story_id=13063298&amp;source=hptextfeature&lt;/ref&gt; Coupled with growing urbanization, this led to increasing disparities in wealth between urban and rural areas.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Globalization and the Rural-Urban Divide&quot;. IATRC Summer Symposium, 30 June – 2 July 2008.http://aede.osu.edu/programs/anderson/trade/Seoul_Symposium_Report.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; In 2002, in '''[[India]]''' 70% of the population lived in rural areas and depended directly on natural resources for their livelihood.&lt;ref name=&quot;visuality.org&quot;/&gt; As a result, mass movements in the countryside at times objected to the process.&lt;ref&gt;Shoa S. Rajgopal. 2002. Reclaiming Democracy, the Anti-globalization Movement in South Asia&quot;. ''Feminist review'' 70, 2002. http://visuality.org/globalization/wmst250_readings/the_antiglobalization_mvmnt.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

====Internet====
{{Main|World Wide Web|Internet}}
{{See also|List of countries by number of Internet users}}
Both a product of globalization as well as a catalyst, the [[Internet]] connects computer users around the world. From 2000 to 2009, the number of Internet users globally rose from 394 million to 1.858 billion.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.itu.int/ITU-D/ict/statistics/ Internet users graphs], Market Information and Statistics, International Telecommunications Union&lt;/ref&gt; By 2010, 22 percent of the world's population had access to computers with 1 billion [[Google]] searches every day, 300 million Internet users reading blogs, and 2 billion videos viewed daily on YouTube.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.antaranews.com/en/news/71940/google-earth-demonstrates-how-technology-benefits-ris-civil-society-govt |title=Google Earth demonstrates how technology benefits RI`s civil society, govt |publisher=Antara News |date=26 May 2011 |accessdate=13 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An [[online community]] is a [[virtual community]] that exists online and whose members enable its existence through taking part in membership ritual. Significant socio-technical change may have resulted from the proliferation of such Internet-based [[social network]]s.&lt;ref&gt;[[Ilkka Tuomi|Tuomi, Ilkka]] ''Internet, Innovation and Open Source: Actors in the Network'' 2000 [[First Monday (journal)|First Monday]]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Population growth====
{{Main|World population|Overpopulation}}
The world population has experienced [[population growth|continuous growth]] since the end of the [[Great Famine of 1315–1317|Great Famine]] and the [[Black Death]] in 1350, when it stood at around 370&amp;nbsp;million.&lt;ref&gt;Jean-Noël Biraben, 1980, &quot;An Essay Concerning Mankind's Evolution&quot;, Population, Selected Papers, Vol. 4, pp. 1–13.  Original paper in French: (b)  Jean-Noël Biraben, 1979, &quot;Essai sur l'évolution du nombre des hommes&quot;, Population, Vol. 34 (no. 1), pp. 13–25.
&lt;/ref&gt; The highest rates of growth&amp;nbsp;– global population increases above 1.8% per year&amp;nbsp;– were seen briefly during the 1950s, and for a longer period during the 1960s and 1970s. The growth rate peaked at 2.2% in 1963, and had declined to 1.1% by 2011. Total annual births were highest in the late 1980s at about 138&amp;nbsp;million,&lt;ref&gt;UN World Population Prospects, the 2010 Revision: [http://esa.un.org/unpd/wpp/Excel-Data/DB01_Period_Indicators/WPP2010_DB1_F04_BIRTHS_BOTH_SEXES.XLS] (686 million births from 1985–1990).&lt;/ref&gt; and are now expected to remain essentially constant at their 2011 level of 134&amp;nbsp;million, while deaths number 56&amp;nbsp;million per year, and are expected to increase to 80&amp;nbsp;million per year by 2040.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.census.gov/population/international/data/idb/region.php?N=%20Region%20Results%20&amp;T=7&amp;A=aggregate&amp;RT=0&amp;Y=2011,2012,2013,2014,2015,2016,2017,2018,2019,2020,2021,2022,2023,2024,2025,2026,2027,2028,2029,2030,2031,2032,2033,2034,2035,2036,2037,2038,2039,2040&amp;R=1&amp;C= |title=World Population estimates by the US Census Bureau}}&lt;/ref&gt; Current projections show a continued increase in population (but a steady decline in the population growth rate), with the global population expected to reach between 7.5&amp;nbsp;and 10.5&amp;nbsp;billion by 2050.&lt;ref name=WorldOMeterSite&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.worldometers.info/world-population/ |title=World Population Clock — Worldometers |publisher=Worldometers.info |date= |accessdate=12 April 2012}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web|url=http://www.census.gov/ipc/www/idb/worldpopinfo.php |title=International Data Base (IDB) — World Population |publisher=Census.gov |date=28 June 2010 |accessdate=1 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:World energy consumption, 1970-2025, EIA.png|thumb|World energy consumption &amp; predictions, 1970-2025. ''Source: International Energy Outlook 2004.'']]
With human consumption of seafood having doubled in the last 30 years, seriously depleting multiple seafood fisheries and destroying the marine ecosystem as a result, awareness is prompting steps to be taken to create a more sustainable seafood supply.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Jacquet J. L &amp; D. Pauly|title=The rise of seafood awareness campaigns in an era of collapsing fisheries|journal=Marine Policy|year=2007|volume=31|pages=308–313.|doi=10.1016/j.marpol.2006.09.003|issue=3|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The head of the [[International Food Policy Research Institute]], stated in 2008 that the gradual change in diet among newly prosperous populations is the most important factor underpinning the [[2007–2008 world food price crisis|rise in global food prices]].&lt;ref&gt;von Braun, &quot;High and Rising Food Prices&quot;, 2008, p 5, slide 14&lt;/ref&gt; From 1950 to 1984, as the [[Green Revolution]] transformed agriculture around the world, grain production increased by over 250%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Kindall, Henery W &amp; Pimentel, David|title=Constraints on the Expansion of the Global Food Supply |journal=Ambio. |volume=23 |issue=3 |year=1994 |month=May |url= http://dieoff.org/page36.htm |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[World population]] has grown by about 4&amp;nbsp;billion since the beginning of the Green Revolution and without it, there would be greater [[famine]] and [[malnutrition]] than the UN presently documents (approximately 850 million people suffering from chronic malnutrition in 2005).&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/in_depth/6496585.stm The limits of a Green Revolution?]&quot;. BBC News. 29 March 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/environment/2008/feb/26/food.unitednations Feed the world? We are fighting a losing battle, UN admits]&quot;. The Guardian. 26 February 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

It is becoming increasingly difficult to maintain [[food security]] in a world beset by a confluence of &quot;peak&quot; phenomena, namely [[peak oil]], [[peak water]], [[peak phosphorus]], [[peak grain]] and [[peak fish]]. Growing populations, falling energy sources and food shortages will create the &quot;perfect storm&quot; by 2030, according to UK chief government scientist John Beddington. He noted that food reserves were at a 50-year low and the world would require 50% more energy, food and water by 2030.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/science/2009/mar/18/perfect-storm-john-beddington-energy-food-climate World faces 'perfect storm' of problems by 2030, chief scientist to warn]&quot;. The Guardian. 18 March 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/7951838.stm Global crisis 'to strike by 2030']&quot;. BBC News. 19 March 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The world will have to produce 70% more food by 2050 to feed a projected extra 2.3&amp;nbsp;billion people and as incomes rise according to the United Nations' [[Food and Agriculture Organisation]] (FAO).&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.finfacts.ie/irishfinancenews/article_1017966.shtml Global food production will have to increase 70% for additional 2.3&amp;nbsp;billion people by 2050]&quot;. Finfacts.com. 24 September 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Social scientists have warned of the possibility that global civilization is due for a period of contraction and economic re-localization, due to the decline in fossil fuels and resulting crisis in transportation and food production.&lt;ref&gt;Tainter, JA 1996. Complexity, Problem Solving, and Sustainable Societies. In Costanza, R, Segura,O &amp; Martinez-Alier, J (eds) Getting Down to Earth: Practical Applications of Ecological Economics. Washington, D.C.: Island Press:61–76.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Pimentel, D &amp; Pimentel, M 2008. Food, Energy, and Society. 3rd edition. Boca Raton, Florida: CRC Press:137–159.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Catton, WR Jr 1980. Overshoot: The Ecological Basis of Revolutionary Change. Urbana: University of Illinois Press.&lt;/ref&gt; Helga Vierich predicted that a restoration of sustainable local economic activities based on [[Hunter-gatherer|hunting and gathering]], shifting [[horticulture]], and [[pastoralism]].&lt;ref&gt;Helga Vierich &quot;Before farming and after globalization: the future of hunter- gatherers may be brighter than you think&quot;, In Before Farming 2008/4 article 4(1). See also discussion at: [http://www.waspress.co.uk/journals/beforefarming/journal_20084/editorial/index.php Waspress.co.uk]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Health====
{{Main|Global health|Globalization and disease}}
[[Image:Tauyuan SARS Checkpoint 1.jpg|thumb|[[SARS]] checkpoint at Taiwan Taoyuan International Airport's International Arrivals in Terminal 1]]

'''Global health''' is the [[health]] of populations in a global context and transcends the perspectives and concerns of individual nations.&lt;ref&gt;The World Health Organization and the Transition From &quot;International&quot; to &quot;Global&quot; Public Health. Brown et al., AJPH: Jan 2006, Vol 96, No 1. http://www.ajph.org/cgi/reprint/96/1/62&lt;/ref&gt; Health problems that transcend national borders or have a global political and economic impact, are often emphasized.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Global Health Initiative | first = | authorlink = | title = Why Global Health Matters | publisher = FamiliesUSA | year = 2008 | location = Washington, DC| url = http://www.familiesusa.org/issues/global-health/matters/}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has been defined as 'the area of study, research and practice that places a priority on improving health and achieving equity in [[health for all]] people worldwide'.&lt;ref name=Koplan&gt;Koplan JP, Bond TC, Merson MH, et al; Consortium of Universities for Global Health Executive Board. Towards a common definition of global health. Lancet. 2009;373:1993-1995.&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, global health is about worldwide improvement of health, reduction of disparities, and protection against global threats that disregard national borders.&lt;ref&gt;Macfarlane SB, Jacobs M, Kaaya EE. In the name of global health: trends in academic institutions. J Public Health Policy. 29(4):383-401. 2008&lt;/ref&gt; The application of these principles to the domain of [[mental health]] is called [[Global Mental Health]].&lt;ref name=Patel&gt;Patel V, Prince M. Global mental health - a new global health field comes of age. JAMA. 2010;303:1976-1977.&lt;/ref&gt;

The major international agency for health is the [[World Health Organization]] (WHO). Other important agencies with impact on global health activities include [[UNICEF]], [[World Food Programme]] (WFP), [[United Nations University]] International Institute for Global Health and the [[World Bank]]. A major initiative for improved global health is the United Nations Millennium Declaration and the globally endorsed [[Millennium Development Goals]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/millenniumgoals/ |title=Climate change deal reached in Durban |publisher=Un.org |date= |accessdate=13 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

International travel has helped to spread some of the deadliest [[infectious disease]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Dr. Daulaire. ''Globalization and Health''. http://econpapers.repec.org/article/paldevelp/v_3a42_3ay_3a1999_3ai_3a4_3ap_3a22-24.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Modern modes of transportation allow more people and products to travel around the world at a faster pace, but they also open the airways to the transcontinental movement of infectious disease vectors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nap.edu/books/0309100984/html/22.html |title=The Impact of Globalization on Infectious Disease Emergence and Control: Exploring the Consequences and Opportunities, Workshop Summary – Forum on Microbial Threats |publisher=Nap.edu |date=1 June 2003 |accessdate=31 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; One example of this occurring is [[AIDS/HIV]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.latimes.com/news/science/la-sci-aids30oct30,0,1617683.story?coll=la The virus from Africa reached the U.S. by way of Haiti, a genetic study shows]&quot;. [[Los Angeles Times]]. 30 October 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Due to immigration, approximately 500,000 people in the United States are believed to be infected with [[Chagas disease]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.healthcentral.com/ency/408/001372.html Chagas disease]&quot;, HealthCentral.com.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2006, the [[tuberculosis]] (TB) rate among foreign-born persons in the United States was 9.5 times that of U.S.-born persons.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/preview/mmwrhtml/mm5611a2.htm Trends in Tuberculosis Incidence --- United States, 2006]&quot;. CDC.gov. 23 March 2007 / 56(11);245–250.&lt;/ref&gt;
Starting in Asia, the [[Black Death]] killed at least one-third of Europe's population in the 14th century.&lt;ref&gt;Stéphane Barry and Norbert Gualde, in ''[[L'Histoire]]'' n° 310, June 2006, pp.45–46, say &quot;between one-third and two-thirds&quot;; Robert Gottfried (1983). &quot;Black Death&quot; in ''[[Dictionary of the Middle Ages]]'', volume 2, pp.257–67, says &quot;between 25 and 45&amp;nbsp;percent&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; Even worse devastation was inflicted on the American supercontinent by European arrivals. 90% of the populations of the civilizations of the &quot;[[New World]]&quot; such as the [[Aztec]], [[Maya civilization|Maya]], and [[Inca]] were killed by [[small pox]] brought by [[European colonization]].

====Sports====
[[File:78 ACPS Atlanta 1996 Track Louise Sauvage.jpg|thumb|[[1996 Summer Paralympics]]]]
{{Main|Olympic Games|List of world championships}}

Globalization has continually increased international competition in sports.

The [[FIFA World Cup]] is the world's most widely viewed sporting event; an estimated 715.1 million people watched the [[2006 FIFA World Cup Final|final match]] of the [[2006 FIFA World Cup]] held in [[Germany]].&lt;ref name=&quot;2006coverage&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.fifa.com/aboutfifa/organisation/marketing/news/newsid=111247/index.html |title=2006 FIFA World Cup broadcast wider, longer and farther than ever before |work=FIFA.com |publisher=[[FIFA|Fédération Internationale de Football Association]] |accessdate=11 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Ancient [[Olympic Games]] were a series of competitions held between representatives of several [[city-states]] and kingdoms from [[Ancient Greece]], which featured mainly athletic but also combat and chariot racing events. During the Olympic games all struggles against the participating city-states were postponed until the games were finished.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Swaddling|first=Judith|title=The Ancient Olympic Games|publisher=University of Texas Press|location=Austin|year=2000|edition=2|page=54|isbn=0-292-70373-2|oclc=10759486|url=http://books.google.com/?id=2-HQMnDiLqIC&amp;printsec=frontcover#PPA54,M1|accessdate=6 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The origin of these Olympics is shrouded in mystery and legend.&lt;ref&gt;Young (2004), p. 12&lt;/ref&gt; During the 19th century Olympic Games became a popular event.

===Global natural environment===
{{Main|Global warming|Climate change|Deforestation}}

[[File:Global Warming Map.jpg|thumb|left|Plot based on the [[NASA]] GISS Surface Temperature Analysis (GISTEMP) data set.]]

Environmental challenges such as [[climate change]], cross-boundary water and air pollution and over-fishing of the ocean, require trans-national/global solutions. Since factories in developing countries increased global output and experienced less environmental regulation, globalism substantially increased pollution and impact on water resources.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hoekstra and Chapagain (2008&quot;&gt;Globalization of Water: Sharing the Planet's Freshwater resources|url=http://eu.wiley.com/WileyCDA/WileyTitle/productCd-1405163356.html&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[State of the World (book series)|State of the World]]'' 2006 report said India and China's high economic growth was not sustainable. The report stated:

:''The world's ecological capacity is simply insufficient to satisfy the ambitions of China, India, Japan, Europe and the United States as well as the aspirations of the rest of the world in a sustainable way''&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/science/nature/4604556.stm Booming nations 'threaten Earth']&quot;. BBC News. 12 January 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; In a 2006 news story, [[BBC]] reported, &quot;...if China and India were to consume as much resources per capita as United States or Japan in 2030 together they would require a full planet Earth to meet their needs.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc&quot;/&gt; In the longterm these effects can lead to increased conflict over dwindling resources&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.globalissues.org/EnvIssues/Population/Result.asp Effects of Over-Consumption and Increasing Populations]&quot;. 26 September 2001. Retrieved on 19 June 2007&lt;/ref&gt; and in the worst case a [[Malthusian catastrophe]].

[[Image:NASAburningbrazil.jpg|thumb|Burning forest in [[Brazil]]. The removal of forest to make way for [[cattle ranching]] was the leading cause of deforestation in the [[Brazilian Amazon]] from the mid 1960s. [[Soybean]]s have become one of the most important contributors to deforestation in the Brazilian Amazon.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/7206165.stm Brazil Amazon deforestation soars]&quot;. BBC News. 24 January 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The advent of global environmental challenges that might be solved with international cooperation include climate change, cross-boundary water and air pollution, over-fishing of the ocean, and the spread of invasive species. Since many factories are built in developing countries with less environmental regulation, globalism and free trade may increase pollution and impact on precious fresh water resources.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hoekstra and Chapagain (2008&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Hoekstra|first=A.Y|title=The Globalization of water. Sharing the Planet's Freshwater Resources.|year=2008|publisher=Blackwell Publishing|location=United Kingdom}}&lt;/ref&gt;

International foreign investment in developing countries could lead to a &quot;race to the bottom&quot; as countries lower their environmental and resource protection laws to attract foreign capital.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bridges2002&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Bridges|first=G.|title=Grounding Globalization: The Prospects and Perils of Linking Economic Processes of Globalization to Environmental Outcomes|journal=Economic Geography|year=2002|volume=78|pages=361–386.|doi=10.2307/4140814|issue=3|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Revesz|first=R.L|title=Federalism and Environmental Regulation: A Normative Critique. The New Federalism: Can the States Be Trusted?|year=1997|publisher=Hoover Institution Press|location= Stanford, CA|pages=97–127|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; The reverse of this theory is true, however, when developed countries maintain positive environmental practices, imparting them to countries they are investing in and creating a &quot;race to the top&quot; phenomenon.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bridges2002&quot; /&gt;

The distances are shrinking between continents and countries due to globalization, causing developing and developed countries to find ways to solve problems on a global rather than regional scale.
Agencies like the United Nations now must be the global regulators of pollution, whereas before, regional governance was enough.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Global Environmental Governance|url=http://www.csa.com/discoveryguides/ern/05aug/overview.php|work=Discovery Guides|publisher=ProQuest|accessdate=11/05/11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Action has been taken by the United Nations to monitor and reduce atmospheric pollutants through the Kyoto Protocol, the Clean Air Initiative, and studies of air pollution and public policy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=United Nations Air Pollution and Public Policy|url=http://esa.un.org/techcoop/flagship.asp?Code=CPR97008|work=United Nations Technical Co-operation|publisher=United Nations|accessdate=11/02/11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Global traffic, production, and consumption are causing increased global levels of air pollutants.  The northern hemisphere is the leading producer of carbon monoxide and sulfur oxides.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Almqvist|first=E.|title=Ambio|year=2002|volume=3|pages=161–176.|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Changes in natural capital are beginning to erode the economic logic of one major aspect of economic globalization: an international division of labor and production based on global supply chains.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Curtis|first=Fred|title=Peak Globalization: Climate Change, oil depletion, and global trade|journal=Ecological Economics|year=2009|year=2009|month=December|volume=69|issue=2|pages=427-434|accessdate=2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Over time, peak oil and climate change will result in “peak globalization,” measured in terms of decreasing ton-miles of freight transported, particularly across oceans and continents. The economic logic of the comparative advantage of global supply chains will be overcome by both increasing transportation costs and interruptions and delays in the transit of freight.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Curtis|first=Fred|title=Peak Globalization: Climate Change, oil depletion, and global trade|journal=Ecological Economics|year=2009|year=2009|month=December|volume=69|issue=2|pages=427-434|accessdate=2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

China and India substantially increased their [[fossil fuel]] consumption as their economies switched from [[subsistence farming]] to industry and urbanization.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/business/7387203.stm Oil price 'may hit $200 a barrel'], BBC News&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.nytimes.com/2008/04/21/opinion/21krugman.html Running Out of Planet to Exploit]&quot;. The New York Times. 21 April 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Chinese oil consumption grew by 8% yearly between 2002 and 2006, doubling from 1996–2006.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
 |url=http://www.eia.doe.gov/emeu/international/oilconsumption.html
 |title=International Petroleum (Oil) Consumption Data
 |publisher=U.S. Energy Information Administration
 |accessdate=20 December 2007
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007, [[People's Republic of China|China]] surpassed the United States as the top emitter of [[carbon dioxide|{{chem|CO|2}}]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/environment/2007/jun/19/china.usnews China overtakes US as world's biggest CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; emitter]&quot;. Guardian.co.uk. 19 June 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
Only 1 percent of the country's 560 million city inhabitants (2007) breathe air deemed safe by the [[European Union]]. In effect, this means that developed countries may &quot;outsource&quot; some of the pollution associated with consumption in countries where pollution-intensive industries have been moved.

A major source of [[deforestation]] is the [[logging industry]], driven by China and Japan.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://news.mongabay.com/2006/0710-itto.html Japan depletes Borneo's rainforests; China remains largest log importer]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

Societies utilize forest resources in order to reach a sustainable level of economic development. Historically, forests in earlier developing nations experience &quot;[[forest transition]]s&quot;, a period of deforestation and reforestation as a surrounding society becomes more developed, industrialized and shift their primary resource extraction to other nations via imports. For nations at the [[World-systems theory#Periphery nations|periphery]] of the globalized system however, there are no others to shift their extraction onto, and forest degradation continues unabated. Forest transitions can have an effect on the hydrology, climate change, and biodiversity of an area by impacting water quality and the accumulation of greenhouse gases through the re-growth of new forest into second and third growth forests.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Rudel,R.L. &amp; Coomes, O.T|title=Forest transitions: towards a global understanding of land use change|year=2005|volume=15|pages=23–31.|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MeyfroidtLambin2011&quot;&gt;Meyfroidt, P., Lambin, E.F. 2011. Global Forest Transition: Prospects for an End to Deforestation. ''Annual Review of Environment and Resources 36: 343-371&lt;/ref&gt;

Without more recycling, [[zinc]] could be used up by 2037, both [[indium]] and [[hafnium]] could run out by 2017, and [[terbium]] could be gone before 2012.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newscientist.com/article/mg19426051.200-earths-natural-wealth-an-audit.html?page=1 Earth's natural wealth: an audit]. [[New Scientist]]. 23 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2003, 29% of open sea [[fisheries]] were in a state of collapse.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/science/nature/6108414.stm 'Only 50 years left' for sea fish]&quot;, BBC News. 2 November 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; The journal ''[[Science (journal)|Science]]'' published a four-year study in November 2006, which predicted that, at prevailing trends, the world would run out of wild-caught seafood in 2048.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 |author=Juliet Eilperin
 |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/11/02/AR2006110200913.html
 |title=Seafood Population Depleted by 2048, Study Finds
 |work=The Washington Post
 |date=2 November 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Conversely, globalisation created a global market for [[aquaculture|farm-raised fish and seafood]], which as of 2009 was providing 38% of global output, potentially reducing fishing pressure.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=FAO|title=The State of World Fisheries and Aquaculture|url=http://www.fao.org/docrep/013/i1820e/i1820e.pdf|publisher=[[FAO]]|accessdate=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The global trade in goods depends upon reliable, inexpensive transportation of freight along complex and long-distance supply chains. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Curtis|first=Fred|title=Peak Globalization: Climate Change, oil depletion, and global trade|journal=Ecological Economics|year=2009|year=2009|month=December|volume=69|issue=2|pages=427-434|accessdate=2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Global warming and peak oil undermine globalization by their effects on both transportation costs and the reliable movement of freight.  Countering the current geographic pattern of comparative advantage with higher transportation costs, climate change and peak oil will thus result in peak globalization, after which the volume of exports will decline as measured by ton-miles of freight.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Held|first=David|title=Global Transformations|year=1999|publisher=Polity Press|location=Cambridge}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Global workforce===
{{Main|Global workforce}}

The global workforce is the international labor pool of immigrant workers or those employed by multinational companies and connected through a global system of networking and production.  As of 2005, the global labor pool of those employed by multinational companies consisted of approximately 3 billion workers.&lt;ref&gt;Sloan Foundation http://wfnetwork.bc.edu/glossary_entry.php?term=Global%20Workforce,%20Definition(s)%20of&amp;area=All&lt;/ref&gt;

The current global workforce is competitive as ever. Some go as far as to describe it as &quot;A war for talent.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;BusinessWeek http://www.businessweek.com/magazine/content/08_04/b4068034072937.htm?chan=magazine+channel_in+depth+--+davos+special+report&lt;/ref&gt; This competitiveness is due to specialized jobs becoming available world wide due to [[Communication|communications technology]]. As workers get more adept at using technology to communicate, they give themselves the options to be employed in an office half way around the world. These newer technologies not only benefit the workers, but companies may now find highly specialized workers that are very skilled with greater ease, as opposed to limiting their search locally.

However, production workers and service workers have been unable to compete directly with much lower-cost workers in developing countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;Reich, Robert. (1992). ''The Work of the Nations, Preparing Ourselves for 21st century Capitalism''. Toronto: Alfred A. Knopf,&lt;/ref&gt; Low-wage countries gained the low-value-added element of work formerly done in rich countries, while higher-value work remained; for instance, the total number of people employed in manufacturing in the US declined, but value added per worker increased.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.economist.com/node/18484080|accessdate=16 April 2011|title=Economics focus: Cash machines &amp;#124; The Economist|date=16 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Imported Crude Oil as a Percent of US Consumption 1950-2003.jpg|thumb|right|Imported crude oil as a percent of U.S. consumption.]] 
In 2011, the [[United States]] imported $332 billion worth of [[crude oil]], up 32% from 2010.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.census.gov/foreign-trade/statistics/historical/petr.txt U.S. Imports of Crude Oil]&quot;. U.S. Census Bureau.&lt;/ref&gt; Chinese success cost jobs in developing countries as well as in the West.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.reuters.com/article/idUSN238294820100323 China trade blamed for 2.4 mln lost US jobs-report]&quot;. Reuters. 23 March 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; From 2000 to 2007, the U.S. lost a total of 3.2&amp;nbsp;million manufacturing jobs.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.usatoday.com/money/economy/2007-04-20-4155011268_x.htm Factory jobs: 3 million lost since 2000]&quot;. USATODAY.com. 20 April 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;  As of 26 April 2005 &quot;In regional giant [[South Africa]], some 300,000 textile workers have lost their jobs in the past two years due to the influx of Chinese goods&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.atimes.com/atimes/Global_Economy/GD26Dj01.html Asia strips Africa's textile industry]&quot;. ''[[Asia Times Online]]''. 26 April 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

====International migration====
[[File:Mall dubai.jpg|thumb|About 85% of [[Dubai]]'s population consists of migrant workers, a majority of whom are from India.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |title=Migrants demand labour rights in Gulf |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/7266610.stm |newspaper=BBC |date=27 February 2008 |first=Roger |last=Hardy}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
{{Main|Immigration|Emigration|Foreign worker|List of countries by net migration rate}}

Many countries have some form of [[guest worker program]] with policies similar to those found in the  U.S.  that permit U.S. employers to sponsor non-U.S. citizens as laborers for approximately three years, to be [[deportation|deported]] afterwards if they have not yet obtained a [[United States Permanent Resident Card|green card]]. 

As of 2009, over 1,000,000 guest workers reside in the U.S.; the largest program, the [[H-1B visa]], has 650,000 workers in the U.S.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=North|first=David|title=Estimating the Size of the H-1B Population in the U.S.|url=http://www.cis.org/estimating-h1b-population-2-11|publisher=Center for Immigration Studies}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the second-largest, the [[L-1 visa]], has 350,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Hira|first=Ron|title=Bridge to Immigration or Cheap Temporary Labor?|url=http://epi.3cdn.net/60b75ba377ebc081b5_hem6b5qjc.pdf|publisher=Economic Policy Institute}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many other [[United States visas]] exist for guest workers as well, including the [[H-2A visa]], which allows farmers to bring in an unlimited number of agricultural guest workers.

The United States ran a Mexican guest-worker program in the period 1942–1964, known as the [[Bracero Program]].

An article in ''[[The New Republic]]'' criticized a guest worker program by equating the visiting workers to [[second-class citizen]]s, who would never be able to gain citizenship and would have less residential rights than Americans.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tnr.com/article/thats-hospitality The New Republic. ''That's Hospitality'' April 17, 2006]&lt;/ref&gt;

Migration of educated and skilled workers is called [[brain drain]]. For example, the U.S.welcomes many nurses to come work in the country.&lt;ref&gt;[http://cgs.illinois.edu/content/culture-and-globalization Culture and Globalization: Center for Global Studies at the University of Illinois]&lt;/ref&gt; The brain drain from Europe to the United States means that some 400,000 European science and technology graduates now live in the U.S. and most have no intention to return to Europe.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | first= Jeff| last= Chu| title=How To Plug Europe's Brain Drain | url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,574849-1,00.html |work=Time magazine | date= 11 January 2004| id= | ref= harv | postscript= &lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}} }}&lt;/ref&gt; Nearly 14 million immigrants came to the United States from 2000 to 2010.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://news.yahoo.com/immigrant-population-record-40-million-2010-100108933.html Immigrant Population at Record 40 Million in 2010]&quot;. Yahoo! News. 6 October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

Immigrants to the United States and their children founded more than 40 percent of the 2010 [[Fortune 500]] companies. They founded seven of the ten most valuable brands in the world.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nyc.gov/html/om/pdf/2011/partnership_for_a_new_american_economy_fortune_500.pdf The &quot;New American&quot; Fortune 500]. The partnership for a new American economy. June 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.cnn.com/2011-11-25/opinion/opinion_wilkinson-jobs-immigration_1_visa-petition-job-generators-immigrant?_s=PM:OPINION Want jobs? Encourage immigration]. ''CNN''. 25 November 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Reverse brain drain]] is the movement of [[human capital]] from a more developed country to a less developed country. It is considered a logical outcome of a calculated strategy where migrants accumulate savings, also known as [[remittances]], and develop skills overseas that can be used in their home country.&lt;ref&gt;Stark, O &amp; Bloom, D.E. (1985). The new economics of labor migration. The American Economic Review. 75(2) p.173-178.[http://www.jstor.org/stable/1805591]&lt;/ref&gt;  

Reverse brain drain can occur when scientists, engineers, or other intellectual elites migrate to a less developed country to learn in its universities, perform research, or gain working experience in areas where education and employment opportunities are limited in their home country. These professionals then return to their home country after several years of experience to start a related business, teach in a university, or work for a multi-national in their home country.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nature-Feb09&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Cyranoski |first=David |date=19 February 2009 |journal=[[Nature (journal)|Nature]] |volume=457 |issue=7232 |pages=953–5 |quote=High-temperature superconductor specialist Hong Ding had several attractive offers last year. But neither Boston University in Massachusetts, where he had been for a decade, nor any other institution could match the deal he was offered at the Institute of Physics in Beijing. &quot;It is a matter of time before the United States becomes alarmed by this rapid '''reverse of the brain drain''',&quot; says Ding. Dessau, who tried and failed to recruit Ding, says that &quot;10 years ago it would have been unheard of [for a Chinese person to turn down a position in the United States]. But I wouldn't be surprised if the trend continues.&quot; |doi=10.1038/457953a |pmid=19225494 |title=Materials science: China's crystal cache |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

A [[remittance]] is a [[Wire transfer|transfer of money]] by a [[migrant worker|foreign worker]] to his or her home country. Remittances are playing an increasingly large role in the economies of many countries, contributing to economic growth and to the livelihoods of less prosperous people (though generally not the poorest of the poor). According to [[World Bank]] estimates, remittances totaled [[US$]]414 billion in 2009, of which [[US$]]316 billion went to developing countries that involved 192 million [[migrant worker]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;go.worldbank.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://go.worldbank.org/NPD63OTRR0 |title=Payment Systems and Remittances - Remittance Market Outlook |publisher=Go.worldbank.org |date=30 March 2009 |accessdate=13 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; For some individual recipient countries, remittances can be as high as a third of their GDP.&lt;ref name=&quot;go.worldbank.org&quot;/&gt; As remittance receivers often have a higher propensity to own a bank account, remittances promote access to financial services for the sender and recipient, an essential aspect of leveraging remittances to promote economic development. The top recipients in terms of the share of remittances in [[GDP]] included many smaller economies such as [[Tajikistan]] (45%), [[Moldova]] (38%), and [[Honduras]] (25%).&lt;ref&gt;[http://peoplemove.worldbank.org/en/content/remittance-flows-to-developing-countries Remittance flows to developing countries are estimated to exceed $300 billion in 2008]. 18 February 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; 

The [[International Organization for Migration|IOM]] found more than 200 million migrants around the world in 2008,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.migrationinformation.org/Feature/display.cfm?id=733&amp;feed=rss Migration in the Asia-Pacific Region]&quot;. Stephen Castles, University of Oxford. Mark J. Miller, University of Delaware. July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; including [[illegal immigration]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/3568329.stm Guinea: Unstoppable exodus]&quot;, BBC News, 18 May 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.foxnews.com/wires/2008Dec02/0,4670,EUWorldMigrationReport,00.html Rich world needs more foreign workers: report]&quot;. FOXNews.com, 2 December 2008&lt;/ref&gt; [[Remittance]] flows to developing countries reached $328&amp;nbsp;billion in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://econ.worldbank.org/WBSITE/EXTERNAL/EXTDEC/EXTDECPROSPECTS/0,,contentMDK:21121930~menuPK:3145470~pagePK:64165401~piPK:64165026~theSitePK:476883,00.html Migration and Remittances]&quot;. The World Bank.&lt;/ref&gt;
 
A [[transnational marriage]] is a [[marriage]] between two people from different countries. A variety of special issues arise in marriages between people from different countries, including those related to [[citizenship]] and culture, which add complexity and challenges to these kinds of relationships. In an age of increasing globalization, where a growing number of people have ties to networks of people and places across the globe, rather than to a current geographic location, people are increasingly marrying across national boundaries. Transnational marriage is a by-product of the movement and migration of people.

==Support and criticism==
Reactions to processes contributing to globalization have varied widely with a history as long as extraterritorial contact and trade. [[philosophy|Philosophical]] differences regarding the costs and benefits of such processes give rise to a broad-range of [[ideology|ideologies]] and [[social movements]].  Proponents of [[economic growth]], [[economic expansion|expansion]] and [[economic development|development]], in general, view globalizing processes as desirable or necessary to the well-being of human [[society]]&lt;ref name=Sen1970&gt;Sen, Amartya K. (1970).  ''Collective choice and social welfare.'' San Francisco, CA: Holden-Day.&lt;/ref&gt;  Antagonists view one or more globalizing processes as detrimental to social well-being on a global or local scale;&lt;ref name=Sen1970 /&gt; this includes those who question either the [[Social sustainability|social]] or [[natural environment|natural]] [[sustainability]] of long-term and continuous economic expansion, the social [[structural inequality]] caused by these processes, and the [[Colonialism|colonial]], [[Imperialism|Imperialistic]], or [[Hegemony|hegemonic]] [[ethnocentrism]], [[cultural assimilation]] and [[cultural appropriation]] that underlie such processes.

As summarized by [[Noam Chomsky]]:

{{quote|The dominant propaganda systems have appropriated the term &quot;globalization&quot; to refer to the specific version of international economic integration that they favor, which privileges the rights of investors and lenders, those of people being incidental. In accord with this usage, those who favor a different form of international integration, which privileges the rights of human beings, become &quot;anti-globalist.&quot; This is simply vulgar propaganda, like the term &quot;anti-Soviet&quot; used by the most disgusting commissars to refer to dissidents. It is not only vulgar, but idiotic. Take the [[World Social Forum]] [(WSF)], called &quot;anti-globalization&quot; in the propaganda system – which happens to include the media, the educated classes, etc., with rare exceptions. The WSF is a paradigm example of globalization. It is a gathering of huge numbers of people from all over the world, from just about every corner of life one can think of, apart from the extremely narrow highly privileged elites who meet at the competing [[World Economic Forum]], and are called &quot;pro-globalization&quot; by the propaganda system.&lt;ref&gt;Noam Chomsky Znet 7 May 2002 / The Croatian Feral Tribune 27 April 2002 [http://www.zmag.org/content/TerrorWar/chomskygab.cfm ZMAG.org]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Proponents===
In general, corporate businesses, particularly in the area of [[finance]], see globalization as a positive force in the world.  Many [[economists]] cite statistics that seem to support such positive impact.  For example, per capita [[Gross Domestic Product]] (GDP) growth among post-1980 globalizing countries accelerated from 1.4 percent a year in the 1960s and 2.9 percent a year in the 1970s to 3.5 percent in the 1980s and 5.0 percent in the 1990s. This acceleration in growth seems even more remarkable given that the rich countries saw steady declines in growth from a high of 4.7 percent in the 1960s to 2.2 percent in the 1990s. Also, the non-globalizing developing countries seem to fare worse than the globalizers, with the former's annual growth rates falling from highs of 3.3 percent during the 1970s to only 1.4 percent during the 1990s. This rapid growth among the globalizers is not simply due to the strong performances of China and India in the 1980s and 1990s—18 out of the 24 globalizers experienced increases in growth, many of them quite substantial.&lt;ref name=&quot;DDollar&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Dollar, David|first=Kraay, Aart|title=Trade, Growth, and Poverty|url=http://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/fandd/2001/09/dollar.htm|work=Finance and Development|publisher=International Monetary Fund|accessdate=6 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Economic liberalism and free trade====
{{Main|Economic liberalism}}
[[Economic liberal]]s generally argue that higher degrees of political and [[economic freedom]] in the form of [[free trade]] in the developed world are ends in themselves,  producing higher levels of overall material wealth. Globalization is seen as the beneficial spread of [[liberty]] and [[capitalism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;The End of Poverty&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Sachs | first = Jeffrey | year = 2005 | title = The End of Poverty | publisher=The Penguin Press | location = New York, New York | isbn = 1-59420-045-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Jagdish Bhagwati]], a former adviser to the U.N. on globalization, holds that, although there are obvious problems with overly rapid development, globalization is a very positive force that lifts countries out of poverty by causing a virtuous economic cycle associated with faster economic growth.&lt;ref name=&quot;bhagwati&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Bhagwati | first = Jagdish | title = In Defense of Globalization | publisher=Oxford University Press | year = 2004 | location = Oxford, New York | url = | id = | isbn = }}&lt;/ref&gt; Economist [[Paul Krugman]] is another staunch supporter of globalization and free trade with a record of disagreeing with many critics of globalization. He argues that many of them lack a basic understanding of [[comparative advantage]] and its importance in today's world.&lt;ref&gt;Conversi, Daniele (2009) '[http://easyweb.easynet.co.uk/conversi/Globalization.pdf Globalization, ethnic conflict and nationalism]', in B. Turner (ed.) Handbook of Globalization Studies. London: Routledge/ Taylor &amp; Francis; Barkawi, Tarak (2005) Globalization and War. Rowman &amp; Littlefield; Smith, Dennis (2006) Gobalization: The Hidden Agenda. Cambridge: Polity Press. See also Barber, Benjamin R., [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jihad_vs._McWorld|Jihad vs. McWorld]. Ballantine Books, 1996&lt;/ref&gt;

====Global democracy====
{{Main|Democratic globalization}}
'''Democratic globalization''' is a movement towards an institutional system of global [[democracy]] that would give world citizens a say in political organizations. This would, in their view, bypass nation-states, corporate oligopolies, ideological [[Non-governmental organization]]s (NGO), political cults and mafias.  One of its most prolific proponents is the [[United Kingdom|British]] political thinker [[David Held]]. Advocates of [[democratic globalization]] argue that economic expansion and development should be the first phase of democratic globalization, which is to be followed by a phase of building [[International political economy|global political institutions]]. Dr. [[Francesco Stipo]], Director of the United States Association of the [[Club of Rome]], advocates unifying nations under a [[world government]], suggesting that it &quot;should reflect the political and economic balances of world nations. A world confederation would not supersede the authority of the State governments but rather complement it, as both the States and the world authority would have power within their sphere of competence&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usacor.org/archive/index.html |title=USACOR.org |publisher=USACOR.org |date=28 July 2009 |accessdate=31 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Former [[Canadian Senate|Canadian Senator]] [[Douglas Roche]], [[Order of Canada|O.C.]], viewed globalization as inevitable and advocated creating institutions such as a [[direct election|directly elected]] [[United Nations Parliamentary Assembly]] to exercise oversight over unelected international bodies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Roche|first=Douglas|title=The Case for a United Nations  Parliamentary Assembly|url=http://www.wfm-igp.org/site/files/Roche_UN_Parliamentary_Assembly_2002.pdf|publisher=The World Federalist Movement–Institute for Global Policy|accessdate=28 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Global civics====
[[File:Reach Toronto.jpg|right|thumb|''Monument to Multiculturalism'' by Francesco Perilli in [[Toronto]], [[Canada]]. Four identical sculptures are located in [[Buffalo City Local Municipality|Buffalo City]], [[South Africa]]; [[Changchun]], [[China]]; [[Sarajevo]], [[Bosnia]] and [[Sydney]], [[Australia]]]]
{{Main|Global civics|Multiculturalism}}
Global civics suggests that [[civics]] can be understood, in a global sense, as a [[social contract]] between [[world citizen]]s in the age of interdependence and interaction. The disseminators of the concept define it as the notion that we have certain rights and responsibilities towards each other by the mere fact of being human on Earth.&lt;ref name = case&gt;{{Cite journal| last = Altinay| first = Hakan| title =The Case for Global Civics| journal = Global Economy and Development at Brookings| year = 2010 | url = http://www.brookings.edu/papers/2010/03_global_civics_altinay.aspx}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[World citizen]] has a variety of similar meanings, often referring to a person who disapproves of traditional [[geopolitical]] divisions derived from national [[citizenship]]. An early incarnation of this sentiment can be found in [[Socrates]], who [[Plutarch]] quoted as saying: &quot;I am not an Athenian, or a Greek, but a citizen of the world.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.worldcitizens.org.au WORLD CITIZENS AUSTRALIA]&lt;/ref&gt; In an increasingly interdependent world, [[world citizen]]s need a compass to frame their mindsets and create a shared consciousness and sense of global responsibility in world issues such as environmental problems and [[nuclear proliferation]].&lt;ref name = feasible&gt;{{cite journal | last = Altinay| first = Hakan| title= A Global Civics: Necessary? Feasible?| journal = Global Policy| date = June 2010| url = http://www.globalpolicyjournal.com/articles/international-law-and-human-rights/global-civics-necessary-feasible}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Cosmopolitanism]] is the notion that all human ethnic groups belong to a single [[community]] based on a shared [[morality]]. A person who adheres to the idea of cosmopolitanism in any of its forms is called a cosmopolitan or cosmopolite.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Cosmopolitan|url=http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/cosmopolitan?s=t|work=Dictionary.com|accessdate=7 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
A cosmopolitan community might be based on an inclusive morality, a shared economic relationship, or a political structure that encompasses different nations. The cosmopolitan community is one in which individuals from different places (e.g. nation-states) form relationships based on mutual respect. For instance, [[Kwame Anthony Appiah]] suggests the possibility of a cosmopolitan community in which individuals from varying locations (physical, economic, etc.) enter relationships of mutual respect despite their differing beliefs (religious, political, etc.).&lt;ref&gt;Kwame Anthony Appiah, &quot;Cosmopolitan Patriots,&quot; Critical Inquiry 23, no. 3 (Spring, 1997): 617-639.&lt;/ref&gt;

Canadian philosopher [[Marshall McLuhan]] popularized the term ''[[Global village (term)|Global Village]]'' beginning in 1962.&lt;ref&gt;Marshall McLuhan and Bruce R. Powers (17 September 1992) The Global Village: Transformations in World Life and Media in the 21st century . Oxford University Press: 17 September 1992&lt;/ref&gt; His view suggested that globalization would lead to a world where people from all countries will become more integrated and aware of common interests and shared humanity.&lt;ref&gt;Chapman, Roger. ''Culture wars: an encyclopedia of issues, viewpoints, and voices, Volume 1.'' 2009: M.E.Sharp&lt;/ref&gt;

===Critiques===
{{Main|Criticisms of globalization}}
Critiques of globalization generally stem from discussions surrounding the impact of such processes on the planet as well as the human costs. They challenge directly traditional metrics, such as GDP, and look to other measures, such as the [[Gini coefficient]] or the [[Happy Planet Index]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.neweconomics.org/gen/uploads/dl44k145g5scuy453044gqbu11072006194758.pdf |title=The Happy Planet Index |publisher=Neweconomics.org |accessdate=31 July 2010}}{{dead link|date=July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.neweconomics.org/gen The New Economics Foundation]{{dead link|date=July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and point to a &quot;multitude of interconnected fatal consequences–social disintegration, a breakdown of democracy, more rapid and extensive deterioration of the environment, the spread of new diseases, increasing poverty and alienation&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Hidden Connections&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Capra | first = Fritjof | year = 2002 | title = The Hidden Connections | publisher=Random House | location = New York, New York | isbn = 0-385-49471-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; which they claim are the unintended consequences of globalization.

[[File:Gini Coefficient World CIA Report 2009-1.png|thumb|left|Differences in national income equality around the world as measured by the national [[Gini coefficient]], 2009]]

Criticisms have arisen from church groups, national liberation factions, [[peasant]] unionists, intellectuals, artists, [[protectionist]]s, [[anarchism|anarchists]], those in support of relocalization (e.g., consumption of nearby production) and others. Some have been [[Reformism|reformist]] in nature, (arguing for a more moderate form of capitalism) while others are more revolutionary (power shift from private to public control) or [[reactionary]] (public to private).  

Some opponents of globalization see the phenomenon as the promotion of [[corporatism|corporatist]] interests.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| first = Laurence
| last = Lee
| title = WTO blamed for India grain suicides
| url = http://english.aljazeera.net/NR/exeres/2ED53A8B-1058-49CF-B9FF-3D96639456D1.htm
|publisher=Al Jazeera
| date = 17 May 2007
| accessdate =17 May 2007

}}&lt;/ref&gt; They also claim that the increasing autonomy and strength of [[corporate entity|corporate entities]] shapes the political policy of countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Corporation&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Bakan | first = Joel | authorlink =Joel Bakan | year = 2004 | title = The Corporation | publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster | location = New York, New York | isbn = 0-7432-4744-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Confessions of an Economic Hit Man&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Perkins | first = John | authorlink = John Perkins (author)| year = 2004 | title = Confessions of an Economic Hit Man | publisher=Berrett-Koehler | location = San Francisco, California | isbn = 1-57675-301-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; They advocate global institutions and policies that they believe better address the moral claims of poor and working classes as well as environmental concerns.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.forumsocialmundial.org.br/index.php?cd_language=2&amp;id_menu= |title=Fórum Social Mundial |publisher=Forumsocialmundial.org.br |accessdate=31 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Economic arguments by [[fair trade]] theorists claim that unrestricted free trade benefits those with more [[financial leverage]] (i.e. the rich) at the expense of the poor.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.epi.org/publication/webfeatures_viewpoints_nafta_legacy_at10/ NAFTA at 10, Jeff Faux, Economic Policy Institute, D.C.]&lt;/ref&gt;

Critics argue that globalization results in:

* '''Poorer countries suffering disadvantages''': While it is true that free trade encourages globalization among countries, some countries try to protect their domestic suppliers. The main export of poorer countries is usually agricultural goods. Larger countries often subsidise their [[Agricultural subsidy|farmers]] (e.g., the EU's [[Common Agricultural Policy]]), which lowers the market price for foreign crops.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hurst E. Charles P.41&quot;&gt;Hurst E. Charles. Social Inequality: Forms, Causes, and consequences, 6th ed. P.41&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''The shift to [[outsourcing]]''': Globalization allowed corporations to move manufacturing and service jobs from high cost locations, creating economic opportunities with the most competitive wages and worker benefits.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kuruvilla 2008 39–72&quot;/&gt;
* '''Weak labor unions''': The surplus in cheap labor coupled with an ever growing number of companies in transition weakened labor unions in high-cost areas. Unions lose their effectiveness and workers their enthusiasm for unions when membership begins to decline.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hurst E. Charles P.41&quot;/&gt;
* '''An increase in exploitation of child labor''': Countries with weak protections for children are vulnerable to infestation by rogue companies and criminal gangs who exploit them. Examples include quarrying, salvage, and farm work as well as trafficking, bondage, forced labor, prostitution and pornography.&lt;ref name=&quot;Edmonds_Pavcni&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
 | last = Pavcnik
 | first = Nina
 | year = 2005
 | month = September
 | title = Child Labor in the Global Economy
 | journal=Journal of Economic Perspectives
 | volume = 19
 | issue = 1
 | pages = 199–220
 | doi = 10.1257/0895330053147895
 | last2 = Pavcnik
 | first2 = Nina
 | ref = harv
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Helena Norberg-Hodge]], the director and founder of ISEC, criticizes globalization in many ways. In her book ''[[Ancient Futures: Learning from Ladakh|Ancient Futures]]'', Norberg-Hodge claims that &quot;centuries of ecological balance and social harmony are under threat from the pressures of development and globalization.&quot; She also criticizes the standardization and rationalization of globalization, as it does not always yield the expected growth outcomes. Although globalization takes similar steps in most countries, scholars such as Hodge claim that it might not be effective to certain countries, for globalization has actually moved some countries backward instead of developing them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Norberg-Hodge|first=Helena|title=Ancient futures : learning from Ladakh|year=1992|publisher=Sierra Club Books|location=San Francisco|isbn=0871566435|edition=Sierra Club Books pbk.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Anti-globalization movement====
{{Main|Anti-globalization movement}}

Anti-globalization, or counter-globalisation,&lt;ref&gt;[[Jacques Derrida]] (May 2004) ''[http://mondediplo.com/2004/11/06derrida Enlightenment past and to come]'', speech at the party for 50 years of ''[[Le Monde diplomatique]]''&lt;/ref&gt; consists of a number of criticisms of globalization but, in general, is critical of the globalization of [[corporate capitalism]].&lt;ref&gt;Morris, Douglas &quot;Globalization and Media Democracy: The Case of Indymedia&quot;, ''Shaping the Network Society'', [[MIT Press]] 2003. Courtesy link to (pre-publication version) [http://www3.fis.utoronto.ca/research/iprp/c3n/CI/DMorris.htm FIS.utoronto.ca]&lt;/ref&gt; The movement is also commonly referred to as the [[alter-globalization]] movement, anti-globalist movement, [[anti-corporate activism|anti-corporate]] globalization movement,&lt;ref name=Juris&gt;{{cite book | last = Juris | first = Jeffrey S. | title =Networking Futures: The Movements against Corporate Globalization | publisher = Duke University Press | location = Durham | year = 2008 | page = 2 | isbn = 978-0-8223-4269-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; or movement against [[neoliberal]] globalization.   Although British sociologist [[Paul Hirst|Paul Q. Hirst]] and political economist Grahame F. Thompson note the term is vague;&lt;ref&gt;Thompson, Grahame F. and Paul Q. Hirst. (2002). The Future of Globalisation.&quot; In ''Cooperation and Conflict'', 37(3): 247–265. {{doi|10.1177/0010836702037003671}} [http://cac.sagepub.com/cgi/content/short/37/3/247 CAC.sagepub.com]&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;anti-globalization movement&quot; activities may include attempts to demonstrate sovereignty, practice local democratic decision-making, or restrict the international transfer of people, goods and capitalist  ideologies, particularly [[free market]] deregulation. Canadian author and social activist [[Naomi Klein]] argues that the term could denote either a single [[social movement]] or encompass multiple social movements such as nationalism and socialism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=No Logo: No Space, No Choice, No Jobs |first=Naomi |last=Klein|publisher=Picador |date=6 April 2002 |isbn= 0-312-42143-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Bruce Podobnik, a sociologist at Lewis and Clark College, states that &quot;the vast majority of groups that participate in these protests draw on international networks of support, and they generally call for forms of globalization that enhance democratic representation, human rights, and egalitarianism.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Podobnik, Bruce, ''Resistance to Globalization: Cycles and Evolutions in the Globalization Protest Movement'', p. 2.&lt;/ref&gt;  Economists [[Joseph Stiglitz]] and Andrew Charlton write:
{{quote|The anti-globalization movement developed in opposition to the perceived negative aspects of globalization. The term 'anti-globalization' is in many ways a misnomer, since the group represents a wide range of interests and issues and many of the people involved in the anti-globalization movement do support closer ties between the various peoples and cultures of the world through, for example, aid, assistance for refugees, and global environmental issues.&lt;ref&gt;Stiglitz, Joseph &amp; Charlton ''Fair Trade for All: How Trade Can Promote Development''. 2005 p. 54 n. 23&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In general, opponents of globalization in developed countries are disproportionately middle-class and college-educated. This contrasts sharply with the situation in developing countries, where the anti-globalization movement has been more successful in enlisting a broader group, including millions of workers and farmers.&lt;ref&gt;Marable, Manning. (2006.) &quot;Globalization and Racialization.&quot; [http://www.greens.org/s-r/39/39-06.html ''Synthesis/Regeneration'', 39 (Winter).]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Opposition to capital market integration====
{{Main|Anti-capitalist movements}}
[[Image:Worldbank protest jakarta.jpg|thumb|World Bank Protester, [[Jakarta]], [[Indonesia]].]]

Capital markets have to do with raising and investing moneys in various human enterprises.  Increasing integration of these [[financial market]]s between countries leads to the emergence of a global capital marketplace or a single world market. In the long run, increased movement of capital between countries tends to favor owners of capital more than any other group; in the short run, owners and workers in specific sectors in capital-exporting countries bear much of the burden of adjusting to increased movement of capital.&lt;ref&gt;Frieden, Jeffry A. (1991).  &quot;Invested Interests: The Politics of National Economic Policies in a World of Global Finance.&quot; ''International Organization'', 45(4): 425-451. [http://www.jstor.org/stable/2706944 Published by: The MIT Press.]&lt;/ref&gt; It is not surprising that these conditions lead to political divisions about whether or not to encourage or increase international capital market integration.

Those opposed to capital market integration on the basis of [[human rights]] issues  are especially disturbed by the various abuses which they think are perpetuated by global and international institutions that, they say, promote [[neoliberalism]] without regard to ethical standards. Common targets include the [[World Bank]] (WB), [[International Monetary Fund]] (IMF), the [[Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development]] (OECD) and the [[World Trade Organization]] (WTO) and [[free trade]] treaties like the [[North American Free Trade Agreement]] (NAFTA), [[Free Trade Area of the Americas]] (FTAA), the [[Multilateral Agreement on Investment]] (MAI) and the [[General Agreement on Trade in Services]] (GATS). In light of the economic gap between rich and poor countries, movement adherents claim &quot;free trade&quot; without measures in place to protect the under-capitalized will contribute only to the strengthening the power of industrialized nations (often termed the &quot;North&quot; in opposition to the developing world's &quot;South&quot;).

[[File:Occupy Wall Street Washington Square Park 2011 Shankbone.JPG|thumb|General Assembly meeting of the [[Occupy movement]] in [[Washington Square Park]], [[New York City]], USA, on 8 October 2011]]

====Global justice and inequality====
{{Main|Global justice movement}}

The global justice movement is the loose collection of individuals and groups&amp;mdash;often referred to as a &quot;[[movement of movements]]&quot;&amp;mdash;who advocate [[fair trade]] rules and perceive current institutions of global economic integration as problems.&lt;ref&gt;Tom Mertes, &quot;A Movement of Movements&quot;, New York: Verso, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;  The movement is often labeled an anti-globalization movement by the mainstream media. Those involved, however, frequently deny that they are [[anti-globalization]], insisting that they support the globalization of communication and people and oppose only the global expansion of corporate power.&lt;ref&gt;della Porta, D. 2005. &quot;The Social Bases of the Global Justice Movement: Some Theoretical Reflections and Empirical Evidence from the First European Social Forum.&quot; Civil Society and Social Movements Programme Paper No. 21.Geneva: UNRISD (United Nations Research Institute for Social Development).&lt;/ref&gt; The movement is based in the idea of [[social justice]], desiring the creation of a society or institution based on the principles of [[social equality|equality]] and [[solidarity]], the values of human rights, and the dignity of every human being.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2006&quot;&gt;Education and Social Justice By J. Zajda, S. Majhanovich, V. Rust, 2006, ISBN 1-4020-4721-5&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2005&quot;&gt;Nursing ethics: across the curriculum and into practice By Janie B. Butts, Karen Rich, Jones and Bartlett Publishers 2005, ISBN 978-0-7637-4735-0&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.legislature.mi.gov/documents/mcl/pdf/mcl-act-135-of-2004.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; [[Structural inequality|Social inequality]] within and between nations, including a growing [[global digital divide]], is a focal point of the movement.
[[File:Global Digital Divide1.png|thumb|left|The [[global digital divide]]: Computers per 100 people.]]

====Anti-consumerism====
{{Main|Anti-consumerism}}

Anti-consumerism is the socio-political movement against the equating of personal happiness with consumption and the purchase of material possessions. The term &quot;consumerism&quot; was first used in 1915 to refer to &quot;advocacy of the rights and interests of consumers&quot; (''Oxford English Dictionary''), but here the term &quot;[[consumerism]]&quot; refers to the sense first used in 1960, &quot;emphasis on or preoccupation with the acquisition of consumer goods&quot; (''Oxford English Dictionary'').
Concern over the treatment of consumers has spawned substantial activism, and the incorporation of [[consumer education]] into school [[curriculum|curricula]]. 
Anti-consumerist activism draws parallels with environmental activism, anti-globalization, and animal-rights activism in its condemnation of modern corporations, or organizations that pursue a solely economic interest. One variation on this topic is activism by ''postconsumers'', with the strategic emphasis on moving ''beyond'' addictive consumerism.[http://www.postconsumers.com]

In recent years, there have been an increasing number of books ([[Naomi Klein]]'s 2000 ''[[No Logo]]'' for example) and films (''e.g. [[The Corporation (film)|The Corporation]]'' &amp; ''[[Surplus (film)|Surplus]]''), popularizing an [[Anti-corporate activism|anti-corporate]] [[ideology]] to the public.

Opposition to [[economic materialism]] comes primarily from two sources: [[religion]] and [[social activism]]. Some religions assert materialism interferes with connection between the individual and the [[divinity|divine]], or that it is inherently an [[immorality|immoral]] lifestyle. Social activists believe materialism is connected to [[Big-box store|global retail merchandizing]] and [[supplier convergence]], [[war]], greed, [[anomie]], [[crime]], environmental degradation, and general social [[malaise]] and discontent.

====Anti-global governance====
{{Main|Global governance}}

Since the two [[world war]]s, there has been solid opposition to the idea of a [[world government]], as advocated by organizations such as the [[World Federalist Movement]] (WFM).   Those who oppose global governance do so on objections that the idea is infeasible, inevitably oppressive, or simply unnecessary.&lt;ref&gt;Kennedy, Paul. (2006.) ''The Parliament of Man: The Past, Present, and Future of the United Nations.'' New York: Harper Collins. ISBN 978-0375501654&lt;/ref&gt; In general, these opponents are wary of the concentration of power or wealth that such governance might represent.  Religious reasons are also cited, in which global governance is seen as the [[Biblical]] [[Antichrist]] or a representation thereof (see [[New World Order (conspiracy theory)]]).  Such reasoning dates back to the founding of the [[League of Nations]] and the [[United Nations]].

====Environmentalist opposition====

[[File:Madagascar highland plateau.jpg|thumb|[[Deforestation]] of the [[Madagascar]] Highland Plateau has led to extensive [[siltation]] and unstable flows of western [[river]]s.]]
{{Main|Environmentalism}}

[[Environmentalism]] is a broad philosophy, ideology&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www-formal.stanford.edu/jmc/progress/ideology.html |title=Ideology and Sustainability |publisher=Formal.stanford.edu |date= |accessdate=13 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Ronald Bailey from the February 2002 issue |url=http://reason.com/archives/2002/02/01/debunking-green-myths |title=Debunking Green Myths |publisher=Reason.com |date= |accessdate=13 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Donald Gibson. Environmentalism: Ideology and Power. Nova Science Pub Inc. 2003&lt;/ref&gt; and social movement regarding concerns for environmental [[Conservation movement|conservation]] and improvement of the health of the [[environment (biophysical)|environment]], particularly as the measure for this health seeks to incorporate the concerns of non-human elements. Environmentalism advocates the preservation, restoration and/or improvement of the natural environment in an attempt to balance relations between humanity and their broader [[natural environment]].  The exact nature of this balance is controversial and there are many different ways for environmental concerns to be expressed in practice.  Environmentalism and environmental concerns are often represented by the color [[Green#In culture|green]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Light, Dark and Bright Green Environmentalism&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.greendaily.com/2009/04/23/light-dark-and-bright-green-environmentalism/ |title=Light, Dark and Bright Green Environmentalism |accessdate=2 November 2009 |author=Cat Lincoln |year=2009 |month=Spring |publisher=Green Daily}}&lt;/ref&gt; but this association has been appropriated by the marketing industries and is a key tactic in the art of [[Greenwashing]].  Environmentalist concerns with globalization include issues such as [[global warming]], [[climate change]], global [[water supply]] and [[Water crisis|water crises]], inequity in [[energy consumption]] and [[energy conservation]], transnational [[air pollution]] and pollution of the [[world ocean]], [[overpopulation]], world [[habitat]] [[sustainability]], [[deforestation]], [[biodiversity]] and [[species extinction]].

== Key journals ==
{{main|List of globalization-related journals}}
Key academic journals examining globalization include:

* ''[[Antipode (journal)|Antipode]]''
* ''[[Economic Geography (journal)|Economic Geography]]''
* ''[[Globalization and Health]]''
* ''[[Journal of Critical Globalisation Studies]]''
* ''[[Journal of Globalization and Development]]''
* ''[[Journal of World-Systems Research]]''

==See also==
{{div col|4}}
* [[Civilizing mission]]
* [[Columbian Exchange]]
* [[Development criticism]]
* [[Global civics]]
* [[Globality]]
* [[Great Transition]]
* [[Interdependence]]
* [[Jet Age]]
* [[Lisbon Strategy]]
* [[Middle East and globalization]]
* [[Mundialization]]
* [[Technocapitalism]]
* [[Transnational cinema]]
* [[Transnational citizenship]]
* [[Triadization]]
* ''[[Vermeer's Hat: The Seventeenth Century and the Dawn of the Global World|Vermeer's Hat]]''
* [[United Nations Millennium Declaration]]
* [[Washington Consensus]]
* [[World Englishes]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin|2}}

* {{cite book | last = Angioni | first = Giulio | authorlink = Giulio Angioni | title = Fare, dire, sentire: l'identico e il diverso nelle culture | publisher=Il Maestrale | year = 2011 | location =Nuoro| isbn=978-88-6429-020-1}}
* {{cite book | last = Barbara | first = Christopher | title = International legal personality: Panacea or pandemonium? Theorizing about the individual and the state in the era of globalization| publisher=[[Verlag Dr. Müller]] | year = 2008 |location =Saarbrücken| url = http://www.amazon.com/International-legal-personality-pandemonium-globalization/dp/3639115147/ | id = | isbn = 3-639-11514-7}}
* {{cite book | last = von Braun | first = Joachim | coauthors = Eugenio Diaz-Bonilla | title = Globalization of Food and Agriculture and the Poor| publisher=Oxford University Press | year = 2007 |location = Oxford| url = http://www.ifpri.org/PUBS/otherpubs/globalpoor.asp | id = | isbn = 978-0-19-569528-1}}
*{{Cite book | last= Chanda | first = Nayan | authorlink = Nayan Chanda | title=Bound Together: How Traders, Preachers, Warriors and Adventurers Shaped Globalization | publisher=Yale University Press, New Haven | year=2007 | isbn=978-0-300-11201-6}}
* {{cite book | last = Fernando | first = Salvetti (ed.) | title = &quot;Glocal&quot; Working. Living and Working across the World with Cultural Intelligence | publisher=Franco Angeli| year = 2010 |location =Milan| url = http://www.cultural-intelligence.info | id = | isbn = 978-88-568-2733-0}}
* {{cite book | last = Glyn | first = Andrew | authorlink = Andrew Glyn | title = Capitalism Unleashed: Finance, Globalization, and Welfare | year = 2006 | publisher=Oxford University Press | location = Oxford | url= http://www.oup.com/us/catalog/general/subject/Economics/International/?view=usa&amp;ci=9780199226795 | isbn = 0-19-922679-2}}
* {{cite book | last = Kitching | first = Gavin | authorlink = Gavin Kitching | title = Seeking Social Justice through Globalization. Escaping a Nationalist Perspective | publisher=Penn State Press | year= 2001 | url = http://www.gavinkitching.com/africa_3.htm | isbn = 0-271-02162-4 }}
* {{cite book | last = Kohler | first = Gernot | coauthors =  Emilio José Chaves (eds.) | title = Globalization: Critical Perspectives | year = 2003 | publisher=Hauppauge, New York: Nova Science Publishers  |ISBN = 1-59033-346-2.|url = http://www.novapublishers.com/}} With contributions by [[Samir Amin]], [[Christopher Chase-Dunn]], [[Andre Gunder Frank]], [[Immanuel Wallerstein]]
* {{cite book | last = [[Jerry Mander|Mander, Jerry]] | coauthors = [[Edward Goldsmith]] | title = The case against the global economy : and for a turn toward the local | publisher=[[Sierra Club Books]] | year = 1996 | location = San Francisco | url = | id = | isbn = 0-87156-865-9 }}
* {{cite book | last = Moore | first = Karl | authorlink = Karl Moore (academic) | coauthors = David Charles Lewis | title = Origins of Globalization | publisher=Routledge | year = 2009 | location = New York | url = http://www.routledgehistory.com/books/The-Origins-of-Globalization-ISBN 978-0-415-80598-8 |isbn=978-0-415-80598-8}}
* {{cite book | last = Murray | first = Warwick E. | title = Geographies of Globalization | publisher=Routledge | year = 2006 | location = New York | isbn = 0-415-31799-1 }}
* {{cite book | last = Neumann | first = Iver B. | coauthors = Ole Jacob Sending | title = Governing the Global Polity: Practice, Mentality, Rationality | publisher=University of Michigan Press| year = 2010 | location = Ann Arbor | url = http://www.press.umich.edu/titleDetailDesc.do?id=371804| isbn = 978-0-472-07093-0}}
* {{cite book | last = Osterhammel | first = Jürgen | authorlink = Jürgen Osterhammel | coauthors = Niels P. Petersson | title = Globalization: A Short History | publisher=Princeton University Press | year = 2005 | location = Princeton, New Jersey | url = http://www.amazon.com/Globalization-Short-History-Jurgen-Osterhammel/dp/0691121656/ | id = | isbn = 0-691-12165-6 }}
* {{cite book | last = Pfister | first = Ulrich | authorlink = | title = Globalization | year = 2012 | publisher=[[Institute of European History]], | location = Mainz | url= http://nbn-resolving.de/urn:nbn:de:0159-2012060507 | isbn = }}
*{{cite book |author=Reinsdorf, Marshall and Matthew J. Slaughter |title=International Trade in Services and Intangibles in the Era of Globalization |year=2009 |isbn=978-0-226-70959-8 |publisher=The University of Chicago Press |location=Chicago}}
* {{cite book | last = Sen | first = Amartya | authorlink = Amartya Sen | title = [[Development as Freedom]] | publisher=Oxford University Press | year = 1999 | location = Oxford, New York | url = | id = | isbn = 019289330 }}
* {{cite book | last = Sirkin | first = Harold L | coauthors = James W. Hemerling and Arindam K. Bhattacharya | title = Globality: Competing with Everyone from Everywhere for Everything| publisher=Business Plus | year = 2008 |location = New York | page = 292 | url = http://www.bcg.com/globality| id = | isbn = 0-446-17829-2}}
* {{cite book | last = Smith | first = Charles | authorlink = Charles Emrys Smith | title = International Trade and Globalisation, 3rd edition | publisher=Anforme | year = 2007 | location = Stocksfield | url = | id = | isbn = 1-905504-10-1 }}
* {{cite book | last = Steger | first = Manfred | title = Globalism: the new market ideology | publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers | year = 2002 | location = Lanham, Maryland | url = | id = | isbn = 0-7425-0072-1 }}
* {{cite book | last = Steger | first = Manfred | title = Globalization: A Very Short Introduction | publisher=Oxford University Press | year = 2003 | location = Oxford, New York | url = | id = | isbn = 0-19-280359-X }}
* {{cite book | last = Stiglitz | first = Joseph E. | authorlink = Joseph E. Stiglitz | title = [[Globalization and Its Discontents]] | publisher=W.W. Norton | year = 2002 | location = New York | url = | id = | isbn = 0-393-32439-7 }}
* {{cite book | last = Stiglitz | first = Joseph E. | authorlink = Joseph E. Stiglitz | title = [[Making Globalization Work]] | publisher=W.W. Norton | year = 2006 | location = New York | url = | id = | isbn = 0-393-06122-1 }}
* {{cite book | last = Tausch | first = Arno | title = Multicultural Europe: Effects of the Global Lisbon Process | publisher=Nova Science Publishers | year = 2008 | location = Hauppauge, New York | url = | id = | isbn = 978-1-60456-806-6}}
* {{cite book | last =  Osle | first = Rafael Domingo | title = The New Global Law | publisher=Cambridge University Press| year = 2010| location = Cambridge | url = | id = | isbn = 9780521193870 }}
* {{cite book | last = Wolf | first = Martin | authorlink = Martin Wolf | title = Why Globalization Works | publisher=Yale University Press | year = 2004 | location = New Haven | url = | id = | isbn = 978-0-300-10252-9 }}

{{refend}}

==External links==

*[http://www.polity.co.uk/global/whatisglobalization.asp Comprehensive discussion of the term at the Site Global Transformations]
{{wikiquote}}
{{Wiktionary|globalisation|globalization}}{{Commons}}
* [http://www.sociology.emory.edu/globalization/ Globalization Website (Emory University) Links, Debates, Glossary etc.]
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/in_depth/business/2007/globalisation/default.stm BBC News Special Report – &quot;Globalisation&quot;]
*{{Guardiantopic|world/globalisation}}
* [http://www.ecologyandsociety.org/vol12/iss1/art24/main.html &quot;Resilience, Panarchy, and World-Systems Analysis&quot;], from the ''[[Ecology and Society]]'' Journal
* [http://stats.oecd.org/Index.aspx?DataSetCode=AFA_CALC_IN3 OECD Globalization statistics]
* [http://www.canadianencyclopedia.ca/index.cfm?PgNm=TCE&amp;Params=A1ARTA0010595 &quot;Globalization&quot;], from ''[[The Canadian Encyclopedia]]''
* [http://zinnov.com/pdf/Globalization_An_Innovation_Imperative.pdf &quot;Globalization: An Innovation Imperative&quot; (Keynote Presentation by Mr. Pari Natarajan, CEO, Zinnov)] {{dead link|date=October 2012}}
* [http://yaleglobal.yale.edu YaleGlobal Online]

{{Globalization|state=expanded}}
{{Trade|state=collapsed}}
{{Aspects of capitalism}}

[[Category:Globalization| ]]
[[Category:Theories of history]]
[[Category:Sociocultural evolution]]
[[Category:Economic geography]]
[[Category:Cultural geography]]
[[Category:Postmodernism]]
[[Category:International trade]]

{{Link FA|id}}
{{Link GA|id}}
[[af:Globalisering]]
[[ar:عولمة]]
[[an:Globalización]]
[[ast:Globalización]]
[[az:Qloballaşma]]
[[bn:বিশ্বায়ন]]
[[zh-min-nan:Choân-kiû-hoà]]
[[be:Глабалізацыя]]
[[be-x-old:Глябалізацыя]]
[[bg:Глобализация]]
[[bs:Globalizacija]]
[[ca:Globalització]]
[[cs:Globalizace]]
[[cy:Globaleiddio]]
[[da:Globalisering]]
[[de:Globalisierung]]
[[et:Globaliseerumine]]
[[el:Παγκοσμιοποίηση]]
[[es:Globalización]]
[[eo:Tutmondiĝo]]
[[eu:Globalizazio]]
[[fa:جهانی‌سازی]]
[[hif:Vaisvikaran]]
[[fr:Mondialisation]]
[[fy:Globalisearring]]
[[ga:Domhandú]]
[[gl:Globalización]]
[[gu:વૈશ્વિકરણ]]
[[ko:세계화]]
[[hi:वैश्वीकरण]]
[[hr:Globalizacija]]
[[id:Globalisasi]]
[[is:Hnattvæðing]]
[[it:Globalizzazione]]
[[he:גלובליזציה]]
[[jv:Globalisasi]]
[[kn:ಜಾಗತೀಕರಣ]]
[[krc:Глобализация]]
[[ka:გლობალიზაცია]]
[[kk:Жаһандану]]
[[sw:Utandawazi]]
[[la:Globalizatio]]
[[lv:Globalizācija]]
[[lb:Globaliséierung]]
[[lt:Globalizacija]]
[[li:Globalisering]]
[[hu:Globalizáció]]
[[mk:Глобализација]]
[[ml:ആഗോളവത്കരണം]]
[[ms:Globalisasi]]
[[mwl:Globalizaçon]]
[[my:ဂလိုဘယ်လိုက်ဇေးရှင်း]]
[[nl:Mondialisering]]
[[new:हलिमिकरण]]
[[ja:グローバリゼーション]]
[[no:Globalisering]]
[[nn:Globalisering]]
[[oc:Globalizacion]]
[[pnb:گلوبلائزیشن]]
[[ps:نړيوالتوب]]
[[pms:Mondialisassion]]
[[pl:Globalizacja]]
[[pt:Globalização]]
[[ro:Globalizare]]
[[rue:Ґлобалізація]]
[[ru:Глобализация]]
[[sah:Глобализация]]
[[sq:Globalizimi]]
[[scn:Glubbalizzazzioni]]
[[si:ගෝලීයකරණය]]
[[simple:Globalization]]
[[sk:Globalizácia]]
[[sl:Globalizacija]]
[[ckb:گلۆڤەرایەتی]]
[[sr:Глобализација]]
[[sh:Globalizacija]]
[[fi:Globalisaatio]]
[[sv:Globalisering]]
[[tl:Globalisasyon]]
[[ta:உலகமயமாதல்]]
[[tt:Globalizasía]]
[[te:ప్రపంచీకరణ]]
[[th:โลกาภิวัตน์]]
[[tg:Ҷаҳонишавӣ]]
[[tr:Küreselleşme]]
[[uk:Глобалізація]]
[[ur:عالمگیریت]]
[[vi:Toàn cầu hóa]]
[[fiu-vro:Üleilmastuminõ]]
[[war:Globalisasyon]]
[[yi:גלאבאליזאציע]]
[[zh-yue:全球化]]
[[bat-smg:Gluobalėzacėjė]]
[[zh:全球化]]</text>
      <sha1>kae7gmo9332hzdw273jsgtiwgmi3s1c</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
