<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Goulash Communism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6085873</id>
    <revision>
      <id>514175294</id>
      <parentid>514171279</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-23T15:32:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>213.219.87.80</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>reclassify category</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8639">'''Goulash Communism''' (Hungarian: ''gulyáskommunizmus'') or '''Kadarism'''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.osaarchivum.org/files/holdings/300/8/3/text/36-7-72.shtml William F. Robinson: Kadarism - Is it Here to Stay?]&lt;/ref&gt; (after [[János Kádár]]) refers to the variety of [[communism]] as practised in the [[Hungarian People's Republic]] from the 1960s until the collapse of Communism in Hungary in 1989. With elements of [[free market]] economics, as well as an improved [[human rights]] record, it represented a quiet reform and deviation from the [[Stalinism|Stalinist]] principles applied on Hungary in the previous decade. 

The name is a semi-humorous [[metaphor]] derived from &quot;[[goulash]]&quot;, a popular Hungarian dish. As goulash is made with an assortment of unlike ingredients, it represents how Hungarian communism was a mixed ideology and no longer strictly adhering to Stalinist interpretations as in the past.&lt;ref&gt;Watkins, Thayer. &quot;[http://www.sjsu.edu/faculty/watkins/hungary.htm Economic History and the Economy of Hungary]&quot;. Department of Economics, San José State University.&lt;/ref&gt;
Sometimes described as &quot;the happiest barrack in the [[Eastern Bloc|socialist camp]],&quot; Hungary in this particular period enjoyed many amenities not available to other socialist states in the [[Eastern bloc]].

== Origins ==
[[File:Hungary socialism.JPG|thumb|250px|The physical legacy of the socialist system in present-day (2009) Hungary, in the form of a [[Ikarus Bus]] and [[panelház]], [[Budapest]]-[[Újpalota]].]]
In 1962, six years after the [[Hungarian Revolution of 1956]], the 8th Congress of the [[Hungarian Socialist Workers' Party]] declared the period of &quot;consolidation of socialism&quot; after 1956 to be over and that the &quot;foundations for the establishment of a socialist society&quot; had been achieved which enabled a general [[amnesty]] of most people sentenced in connection with 1956. The party, under [[János Kádár]], gradually curbed some of the excesses of the [[secret police]], and introduced a relatively liberal cultural and economic course aimed at overcoming the post-1956 hostility toward the Kádár government.&lt;ref name = &quot;Stokes1&quot;&gt;Stokes, Gale. The Walls Came Tumbling Down: The Collapse of Communism in Eastern Europe, (Oxford, 1993), pp. 81-7.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1966, the Central Committee approved the &quot;[[New Economic Mechanism]]&quot; which eased foreign trade restrictions, gave limited freedom to the workings of the market, and allowed a limited number of small businesses to operate in the services sector. Though liberal in comparison to Stalinist socialism, the first relaxation of economic control was far from posing the same threat of the 1956 reforms. Official policy employed different methods of administering the [[collectives]], leaving the pace of [[mechanization]] up to each [[cooperative]].&lt;ref name = &quot;Stokes1&quot;&gt;Stokes, Gale. The Walls Came Tumbling Down: The Collapse of Communism in Eastern Europe, (Oxford, 1993), pp. 81-7.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Additionally, rather than enforcing the system of compulsory crop deliveries and of workdays credit the collectivizers used monthly cash wages.&lt;ref name = &quot;Stokes1&quot;/&gt; Later in the ‘60s, cooperatives were permitted to enter into related and then general auxiliary businesses such as food processing, light industry, and service industry.&lt;ref name = &quot;Stokes1&quot;/&gt;

== Ideology ==
Goulash Communism showed a far greater concern for [[public opinion]] and an increased focus on the present (rather than future) material well-being of the citizens than had been the case in the period preceding 1956. It provided a wider latitude for [[dissent]] than was the case in the rest of the Soviet bloc (in the words of Kádár, &quot;who is not against us is with us&quot;), modified the role of the Communist Party in the development of socialism (now interpreted as &quot;serving&quot; rather than &quot;commanding&quot;), reduced the formality of relations between the party and the populace at large, increased the scope of societal self-expression and self-management, and refined the guiding [[Marxist-Leninist]] [[ideology]] with modified means of dissemination. Marxist-Leninist ideology is invoked in the desire to reform as seen in [[Imre Nagy]]’s 'Reform Communism' (1955-6). He argues that Marxism is a “science that cannot remain static but must develop and become more perfect”.&lt;ref name = &quot;Stokes2&quot;&gt;Stokes, Gale, ed. From Stalinism to Pluralism: A Documentary History of Eastern Europe Since 1945, (Oxford, 1996), pp. 81-93.&lt;/ref&gt; 

He attributes Marx to having created a method, meant to guide yet not entirely encompass socialism or its development. “The theory of Marx - as Lenin stated – gives general guiding principles, which must be utilized in Britain in another fashion than in France, in France differently than…”.&lt;ref name = &quot;Stokes2&quot;/&gt; This interpretation was not shared by the Soviet leadership, [[Nikita Khrushchev]]’s response to Hungary in 1956 and [[Leonid Brezhnev]]’s to Czechoslovakia in 1968 and the resulting [[Brezhnev Doctrine]] stating that though “each socialist country had the right to determine the concrete form of its development along the path of socialism by taking account of the specific nature of their national conditions… the Soviet Union would not tolerate deviation from the principles of socialism and the restoration of capitalism”.&lt;ref name = &quot;Janos&quot;&gt;Janos, Andrew C. East Central Europe in the Modern World: The Politics of the Borderlands From Pre- to Postcommunism, (Stanford, 2000), pp. 267.&lt;/ref&gt;

The result was a regime far more humane than other Communist regimes—and certainly more so than the first seven years of undisguised Communist rule in Hungary.  Generally, Hungarians had much more freedom to speak, write and travel than their counterparts in the Soviet bloc. For instance, [[samizdat]] publications were tolerated to some extent, and conversations with foreigners didn't attract much official scrutiny.  However, while Kádár's regime was not nearly as repressive as most of its counterparts, it wasn't a liberal one either.  The Communist Party still retained a monopoly of power, with the [[National Assembly of Hungary|National Assembly]] being little more than a rubber stamp.  The media, while having somewhat more latitude than in other Communist regimes, were still subjected to fairly onerous restrictions.  The secret police operated with somewhat more restraint than in other Communist states, but were still a feared tool of control.

== Economy ==
Hungary's economic resources were mobilized to better satisfy consumer demand by providing a more extensive assortment of [[good (economics and accounting)|consumer goods]]. Some economic reform measures were introduced to integrate limited market mechanisms into the framework of the planned [[socialist economy]]. An unfortunate result of this policy were rising economic stresses and high indebtedness which became evident by the late 1980s. Yet these economic crises were prevalent throughout the collapsing communist world. Hungary’s mild diversity left it slightly better equipped.

Being a comparatively well-organized country in the East bloc, Hungary was the destination for tourists from other communist nations, for whom visits to the West were much more difficult. Queues for groceries, for instance, were virtually non-existent, unlike in other communist countries in the 1960s and 1970s.

== Transition to capitalism ==
Since 1989, after the general disintegration of communist control in [[Central Europe]], [[Hungary]] has adopted a Western-style multiparty political system and introduced thorough reforms aimed at establishing a capitalist market economy, enabling [[European Union]] membership and integration into a global market economy.

== See also ==
* [[Market socialism]]
* [[Barracks communism]]

'''General:'''
* [[History of Hungary]]
* [[Eastern Bloc economies]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.sjsu.edu/faculty/watkins/hungary.htm Article on economic history of Hungary including goulash communism]
* [http://www.unc.edu/~wmckinne/hungarytoday.html Discussion of goulash communism and its aftermath]
* [http://www.kadarism.com Kadarism business directory]

{{Cold War}}
{{Eastern Bloc economies}}

[[Category:People's Republic of Hungary]]
[[Category:Political terms]]
[[Category:Socialism]]
[[Category:Economic history of Hungary]]

[[cs:Gulášový socialismus]]
[[de:Gulaschkommunismus]]
[[fr:Socialisme du goulash]]
[[lt:Guliašo komunizmas]]
[[hu:Gulyáskommunizmus]]
[[pl:Gulaszowy komunizm]]
[[ru:Кадаризм]]
[[fi:Gulassikommunismi]]
[[vi:Chủ nghĩa cộng sản Gulyás]]</text>
      <sha1>t6rnv1t72nh24ut1cajw641v3u7i4u8</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
