<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Government</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>12229</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521686381</id>
      <parentid>521671666</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-06T16:22:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>TommyBoy</username>
        <id>131807</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>revert vandalism</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="38221">{{For|government in linguistics|Government (linguistics)}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2012}}
{{Forms of government}}
'''Government''' is broadly defined as the administrative group of people with authority to govern a [[state (polity)|political state]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Oxford English Dictionary|edition=Online|publisher=Oxford University Press|date=November 2010|url=http://oxforddictionaries.com/definition/government}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[British English]] (and that of the [[Commonwealth of Nations]]), a ''government'' more narrowly refers to the particular administrative [[bureaucracy]] in control of a state at a given time&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|editor=Bealey, Frank|chapter=government|title=The Blackwell dictionary of political science: a user's guide to its terms|publisher=Wiley-Blackwell|year=1999| ISBN =`Fuchs u -0-631-20695-8|page=147|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=6EuKLlzYoTMC&amp;pg=PA147}}&lt;/ref&gt;—known in [[American English]] as an ''[[administration (government)#United States|administration]]''. In American English, ''government'' refers to the larger system by which any state is organized.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web||title=Oxford English Dictionary: American English|edition=Online|publisher=Oxford University Press|date=2012|url=http://oxforddictionaries.com/definition/american_english/government}}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, ''government'' is occasionally used in English as a [[synonym]] for ''[[governance]]''.

In the case of its broad definition, government normally consists of [[legislators]], [[Executive (government)|administrators]], and [[Judiciary|arbitrators]]. Government is the means by which state policy is enforced, as well as the mechanism for determining the [[policy]] of the state. A form of government, or form of state governance, refers to the set of political institutions by which a government of a state is organized.

[[Sovereign state|States]] are served by a continuous succession of different governments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|authors=Flint, Colin &amp; Taylor, Peter|title=Political Geography: World Economy, Nation-State, and Locality|edition=5th|publisher=Pearson/Prentice Hall|year=2007|isbn=978-0-13-196012-1|page=137|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=GXz9xHdHeZcC}}&lt;/ref&gt; Each successive government is composed of a body of individuals who control and exercise control over political decision-making. Their function is to make and enforce [[laws]] and arbitrate conflicts. In some societies, this group is often a self-perpetuating or hereditary class. In other societies, such as [[democracies]], the political roles remain, but there is frequent turnover of the people actually filling the positions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Barclay, Harold|title=People Without Government: An Anthropology of Anarchy|publisher=Left Bank Books|year=1990|isbn=1-871082-16-1|page=31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Government of any kind currently affects every human activity in many important ways. For this reason, [[Political science|political scientists]] generally argue that government should not be studied by itself. They argue that government should be studied along with [[anthropology]], [[economics]], [[history]], [[philosophy]], [[science]], and [[sociology]].

== Forms of government ==
Nearly every country in the world is ruled by a system that combines 2 or more of the following attributes (for example, the [[United States]] is not a true capitalist society, since the government actually provides social services for its citizens). Additionally, one person's opinion of the type of government may differ from another's (for example, some may argue that the United States is a plutocracy rather than a democracy since they may believe it is ruled by the wealthy).{{clarify|date=October 2012}}

Descriptions of governments can be based on the following attributes:

=== By elements of where power is held ===
==== Aristarchic attributes ====
Governments with ''Aristarchy'' attributes are traditionally ruled by the &quot;best&quot; people.
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Term
!Definition
|-
| [[Aristocracy]] || Rule by elite citizens; a system of governance in which a person who rules in an aristocracy is an aristocrat. It has come to mean rule by &quot;the aristocracy&quot; who are people of noble birth. An aristocracy is a government by the &quot;best&quot; people. A person who rules in an aristocracy is an aristocrat. Aristocracy is different from nobility, in that nobility means that one bloodline would rule, an aristocracy would mean that a few or many bloodlines would rule, or that rulers be chosen in a different manner.
|-
| [[Geniocracy]] || Rule by the intelligent; a system of governance where creativity, innovation, intelligence and wisdom are required for those who wish to govern. See [[Noocracy|Aristocracy of the wise]].
|-
| [[Kratocracy]] || Rule by the strong; a system of governance where those strong enough to seize power through physical force, social maneuvering or political cunning.
|-
| [[Meritocracy]] || Rule by the meritorious; a system of governance where groups are selected on the basis of people's ability, knowledge in a given area, and contributions to society.
|-
| [[Technocracy]] || Rule by the educated; a system of governance where people who are skilled or proficient govern in their respective areas of expertise in technology would be in control of all decision making. Doctors, engineers, scientists, professionals and technologists who have knowledge, expertise, or skills, would compose the governing body, instead of politicians, businessmen, and economists.&lt;ref&gt;Ernst R. Berndt, (1982).[http://dspace.mit.edu/bitstream/handle/1721.1/2023/SWP-1353-09057784.pdf “From Technocracy To Net Energy Analysis: Engineers, Economists And Recurring Energy Theories Of Value”], Studies in Energy and the American Economy, Discussion Paper No. 11, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Revised September 1982&lt;/ref&gt; In a technocracy, decision makers would be selected based upon how knowledgeable and skillful they are in their field.
|}

==== Autocratic attributes ====
Governments with ''Autocratic '' attributes are ruled by one person who has all the power over the people in a country. The [[Roman Republic]] made ''Dictators'' to lead during times of war. The Roman dictators (and Greek tyrants) were not always bad. The Roman dictators only held power for a small time. In modern times, an Autocrat's rule is not stopped by any rules of law, [[constitution]]s, or other social and political institutions. After World War II, many governments in Latin America, Asia, and Africa were ruled by autocratic governments. Examples of Autocrats include [[Idi Amin]], [[Muammar Gaddafi]], and [[Gamal Abdul Nasser]].

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Term
!Definition
|-
| [[Authoritarianism|Authoritarian]]||Rule by authoritarian governments are characterized by an emphasis on the authority of the state in a [[republic]] or union. It is a [[political system]] controlled by unelected rulers who usually permit some degree of [[individual freedom]].
|-
| [[Autocracy]]||Rule by one individual, whose decisions are subject to neither external legal restraints nor regularized mechanisms of popular control (except perhaps for implicit threat). Autocrat needs servants while despot needs slaves.
|-
| [[Despotism]]||Rule by a single entity with absolute power. That entity may be an individual, as in an autocracy, or it may be a group,[1] as in an oligarchy. The word despotism means to &quot;rule in the fashion of a despot&quot; and does not necessarily require a single, or individual, &quot;despot&quot;. Despot needs slaves while Autocrat needs servants.
|-
| [[Dictatorship]]||Rule by an individual who has full power over the country. The term may refer to a system where the dictator came to power, and holds it, purely by force; but it also includes systems where the dictator first came to power legitimately but then was able to amend the constitution so as to, in effect, gather all power for themselves.&lt;ref&gt;American 503&lt;/ref&gt; In a military dictatorship, the army is in control. Usually, there is little or no attention to public opinion or individual rights. See also [[Autocracy]] and [[Stratocracy]].
|-
| [[Fascism]]||Rule by leader base only. Focuses heavily on patriotism and national identity. The leader(s) has the power to make things illegal that do not relate to nationalism, or increase belief in national pride. They believe their nation is based on commitment to an organic national community where its citizens are united together as one people through a national identity. It exalts nation and race above the individual and stands for severe economic and social regimentation, and forcible suppression of opposition.
|-
| [[Totalitarianism|Totalitarian]]||Rule by a totalitarian government that regulates nearly every aspect of public and private life.
|}

==== Democratic attributes ====
Governments with ''Democratic'' attributes are most common in the Western world and in some countries of the east. In democracies, all of the people in a country can vote during elections for representatives or political parties that they prefer. The people in democracies can elect representatives who will sit on legislatures such as the Parliament or Congress. Political parties are organizations of people with similar ideas about how a country or region should be governed. Different political parties have different ideas about how the government should handle different problems. Democracy is the government of the people, by the people, for the people.
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Term
!Definition
|-
| [[Democracy]]||Rule by a government chosen by election where most of the populace are enfranchised. The key distinction between a democracy and other forms of constitutional government is usually taken to be that the right to vote is not limited by a person's wealth or race (the main qualification for enfranchisement is usually having reached a certain age). A Democratic government is, therefore, one supported (at least at the time of the election) by a [[majority]] of the populace (provided the election was held fairly). A &quot;majority&quot; may be defined in different ways. There are many &quot;power-sharing&quot; (usually in countries where people mainly identify themselves by race or religion) or &quot;electoral-college&quot; or &quot;constituency&quot; systems where the government is not chosen by a simple one-vote-per-person headcount.
|-
| [[Direct democracy]]|| Government in which the people represent themselves and vote directly for new laws and public policy
|-
| [[Representative democracy]]|| Also known as a republic, wherein the people or citizens of a country elect representatives to create and implement public policy in place of active participation by the people.
|-
| [[Social democracy]]|| Social democracy rejects the &quot;either/or&quot; polarization interpretation of capitalism versus socialism. It claims that fostering a progressive evolution of capitalism will gradually result in the evolution of capitalist economy into socialist economy. Social democracy argues that all citizens should be legally entitled to certain social rights. These are made up of universal access to public services such as: education, health care, workers' compensation, and other services including child care and care for the elderly. Social democracy is connected with the trade union labour movement and supports collective bargaining rights for workers. Contemporary social democracy advocates freedom from discrimination based on differences of: ability/disability, age, ethnicity, gender, language, race, religion, sexual orientation, and social class.
|}

==== Monarchic attributes ====
Governments with ''Monarchic'' attributes are ruled by a king or a queen who inherits their position from their family, which is often called the &quot;royal family.&quot; There are at two opposing types of monarchies: absolute monarchies and constitutional monarchies. In an absolute monarchy, the ruler has no limits on their wishes or powers. In a constitutional monarchy a ruler's powers are limited by a document called a constitution.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Term
!Definition
|-
| [[Absolute monarchy]]||Rule by a government in which a [[monarch]] exercises ultimate governing authority as [[head of state]] and [[head of government]].
|-
| [[Constitutional monarchy]]||Rule by a government that has a [[monarch]], but one whose powers are limited by law or by a formal [[constitution]], such as that in the [[United Kingdom]]&lt;ref&gt;[[Takis Fotopoulos|Fotopoulos, Takis]], ''The Multidimensional Crisis ad [[Inclusive Democracy]]''. (Athens: Gordios, 2005).([http://www.inclusivedemocracy.org/fotopoulos/english/brbooks/multi_crisis_id.htm English translation]{{dead link|date=April 2012}} of the book with the same title published in Greek).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;victoria&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.parliament.vic.gov.au/SARC/E-Democracy/Final_Report/Glossary.htm |title=Victorian Electronic Democracy : Glossary |date=28 July 2005| accessdate= |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071213045132/http://www.parliament.vic.gov.au/SARC/E-Democracy/Final_Report/Glossary.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 13 December 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Elective monarchy]]||Rule by a government that has an elected monarch, in contrast to a ''hereditary monarchy'' in which the office is automatically passed down as a family inheritance. The manner of election, the nature of candidate qualifications, and the electors vary from case to case.
|-
| [[Emirate]]||Similar to a [[monarchy]] or sultanate, but a government in which the supreme power is in the hands of an emir (the ruler of a [[Muslim]] state); the emir may be an absolute overlord or a sovereign with constitutionally limited authority.&lt;ref name=&quot;CIAgovttype&quot;&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/fields/2128.html CIA||The World Factbook||Field Listing :: Government type]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Monarchy]]||Rule by an individual who has inherited the role and expects to bequeath it to their heir.&lt;ref&gt;American 1134&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

==== Oligarchic attributes ====
Governments with ''Oligarchic'' attributes are ruled by a small group of powerful and/or influential people. These people may spread power equally or not equally. An oligarchy is different from a true democracy because very few people are given the chance to change things. An oligarchy does not have to be hereditary or monarchic. An oligarchy does not have one clear ruler, but several powerful people. Some historical examples of oligarchy are the former [[Union of Soviet Socialist Republic]]s and [[Apartheid in South Africa]]. Fictional oligarchic examples include the dystopian society of ''Oceania'' displayed in the book [[Nineteen Eighty-Four]], the ''stratocracy'' government of [[Starship Troopers]], and the [[Judge (2000 AD)|kritarchic &quot;Street Judges&quot;]] of [[Judge Dredd]]. Some critics of [[representative democracy]] think of the [[United States]] as an oligarchy. This view is shared by anarchists.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Term
!Definition
|-
| [[Bureaucracy]] || Rule by a system of governance with many bureaus, administrators, and petty officials
|-
| [[Ergatocracy]] || Rule by a system of governance ruled by [[proletariat]]s, the workers, or the working class. Examples of ergatocracy include communist revolutionaries &amp; rebels which control almost society and create alternative economy for people`s and workers. See [[Dictatorship of the proletariat]]. {{clarify|date=October 2012}}
|-
| [[Kritarchy]] || Rule by judges; a system of governance composed of law enforcement institutions in which the state and the [[legal system]]s are traditionally the same thing.
|-
| [[Netocracy]] || Rule by social connections; a term invented by the editorial board of the American technology magazine Wired in the early 1990s. A portmanteau of Internet and aristocracy, netocracy refers to a perceived global upper-class that bases its power on a technological advantage and networking skills, in comparison to what is portrayed as a bourgeoisie of a gradually diminishing importance. The netocracy concept has been compared with [[Richard Florida]]'s concept of the [[creative class]]. Bard and Söderqvist have also defined an under-class in opposition to the [[netocracy]], which they refer to as the [[consumtariat]].
|-
| [[Oligarchy]] || Rule by a system of governance with small group of people who share similar interests or family relations.&lt;ref&gt;American 1225&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Plutocracy]] || Rule by the rich; a system of governance composed of the wealthy class. Any of the forms of government listed here can be plutocracy. For instance, if all of the voted representatives in a republic are wealthy, then it is a republic and a plutocracy.
|-
| [[Stratocracy]] || Rule by military service; a system of governance composed of military government in which the state and the military are traditionally the same thing. Citizens with military service have the right to govern. (Not to be confused with ''&quot;[[military junta]]&quot;'' or ''&quot;[[military dictatorship]]&quot;''.)
|-
| [[Timocracy]] || Rule by honor; a system of governance ruled by honorable citizens and property owners. European-feudalism and post-Revolutionary America are historical examples of this type.
|-
| [[Theocracy]] || Rule by a religious elite; a system of governance composed of religious institutions in which the state and the church are traditionally the same thing. Citizens who are clergy have the right to govern.&lt;ref&gt;American 1793&lt;/ref&gt; [[Holy See|The Vatican]]'s (see [[Pope]]) and the [[Tibetan government]]'s (see [[Dalai Lama]]) are historically considered ''theocracies''.
|}

==== Pejorative attributes ====
Regardless of whichever forms of government a nation, and its people, may choose for themselves; all must be safeguarded against [[Passion (emotion)|passion]] and [[corruption]]. A democracy spoiled by [[demagoguery]] can become a ''Mobocracy''. An aristocracy spoiled by corruption can become an &quot;Oligarchy''.  A monarchy spoiled by lack of virtue can become tyrannical.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Term
!Definition
|-
| [[Bankocracy]] || Rule by banks;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Dictionary of Philosophical Terms vol. II - English-German / Englisch-Deutsch
|last1=Waibl |first1=Elmar|last2=Herdina|first2=Philip|authorlink= |year=1997 |publisher= Walter de Gruyter|location= |isbn=3110979497 |page= 345|url=http://books.google.fi/books?id=r7OiXFVasZEC&amp;dq=bankokratie&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s&amp;redir_esc=y |accessdate=September 18, 2012|page=33 }}&lt;/ref&gt; a system of governance where the excessive power or influence of banks on public policy-making. It can also refer to a form of government where financial institutions rule society. See [[Trapezocracy]].
|-
| [[Corporatocracy]] || Rule by corporations; a system of governance where an economic and political system is controlled by corporations or corporate interests.&lt;ref name=&quot;oxford dictionary&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title= Corporatocracy|newspaper= Oxford Dictionaries|quote= /ˌkôrpərəˈtäkrəsē/ .... a society or system that is governed or controlled by corporations:|url= http://oxforddictionaries.com/definition/corporatocracy|accessdate= May 29, 2012
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its use is generally pejorative. Fictional examples include ''OCP'' in [[Robocop]]
|-
| [[Nepotism|Nepotocracy]] || Rule by nephews; [[favoritism]] granted to [[relatives]] regardless of [[:wikt:merit|merit]]; a system of governance in which importance is given to the relatives of those already in power, like a ''nephew'' (where the word comes from). In such governments even if the relatives aren't qualified they are given positions of authority just because they know someone who already has authority. [[Pope Alexander VI]] ([[Borgia]]) was accused of this.
|-
| [[Kakistocracy]] || Rule by the stupid; a system of governance where the worst or least-qualified citizens govern or dictate policies. See [[Idiocracy]].
|-
| [[Kleptocracy]] ([[Mafia state]]) || Rule by thieves; a system of governance where its officials and the ruling class in general pursue personal wealth and political power at the expense of the wider population. In strict terms kleptocracy is not a form of government but a ''characteristic'' of a government engaged in such behavior. Examples include Mexico as being considered a ''Narcokleptocracy'', since its democratic government is perceived to be corrupted by those who profit from trade in illegal drugs smuggled into the United States.
|-
| [[Ochlocracy]] || Rule by the general populace; a system of governance where '''mob rule''' is government by mob or a mass of people, or the [[intimidation]] of legitimate authorities. As a pejorative for [[majoritarianism]], it is akin to the [[Latin]] phrase '''''mobile vulgus''''' meaning &quot;the fickle crowd&quot;, from which the English term &quot;mob&quot; was originally derived in the 1680s. Ochlocratic goverments are often a democracy spoiled by [[demagoguery]], &quot;[[tyranny of the majority]]&quot; and the rule of passion over reason; such governments can be ''more oppressive'' then autocratic-Tyrants. Ochlocracy is synonymous in meaning and usage to the modern, informal term &quot;Mobocracy,&quot; which emerged from a much more recent colloquial etymology.
|}

==== Other characteristic attributes ====
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Term
!Definition
|-
| [[Adhocracy]]||Rule by a government based on type of organization that operates in opposite fashion to a [[w:Bureaucracy|bureaucracy]].
|-
| [[Anarchism]]||Sometimes said to be non-governance; it is a structure which strives for non-hierarchical voluntary associations among agents.
|-
| [[Band society|Band Society]]||Rule by a government based on small (usually family) unit with a semi-informal hierarchy, with strongest (either physical strength or strength of character) as leader. Very much like a pack seen in other animals, such as wolves.
|-
| [[Chiefdom]] ([[Tribal]])||Rule by a government based on small complex society of varying degrees of centralization that is led by an individual known as a chief.
|-
| [[Constitutional republic]]||Rule by a government whose powers are limited by law or a formal constitution, and chosen by a vote amongst at least some sections of the populace (Ancient Sparta was in its own terms a republic, though most inhabitants were disenfranchised. The United States is a federal republic). Republics that exclude sections of the populace from participation will typically claim to represent all citizens (by defining people without the vote as &quot;non-citizens&quot;).
|-
| [[Project Cybersyn|Cybersynacy]]||Ruled by a data fed group of secluded individuals that regulates aspects of public and private life using data feeds and technology having no interactivity with the citizens but using &quot;facts only&quot; to decide direction.
|-
| [[Nomocracy]]||Rule by a government under the sovereignty of rational laws and civic right as opposed to one under theocratic systems of government. In a nomocracy, ultimate and final authority (sovereignty) exists in the law.
|-
| [[Republic]]||Rule by a form of government in which the people, or some significant portion of them, have supreme control over the government and where offices of state are elected or chosen by elected people.&lt;ref&gt;[[Montesquieu]], ''[[The Spirit of the Laws]]'' (1748), Bk. II, ch. 1.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|title=Republic|encyclopedia=Encyclopædia Britannica}}&lt;/ref&gt; In modern times, a common simplified definition of a republic is a government where the head of state is not a monarch.&lt;ref name=&quot;WordNet&quot;&gt;{{citation |title=republic |journal=WordNet 3.0 |publisher=Dictionary.com |accessdate=20 March 2009 |url=http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/republic}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;M-W&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|title=Republic|encyclopedia=Merriam-Webster|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/republic|accessdate=14 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Montesquieu]] included both [[democracy|democracies]], where all the people have a share in rule, and [[aristocracy|aristocracies]] or [[oligarchy|oligarchies]], where only some of the people rule, as republican forms of government.&lt;ref&gt;Montesquieu, ''Spirit of the Laws'', Bk. II, ch. 2–3.&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

===== Speculative attributes =====
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Term
!Definition
|-
| [[Magocracy]]||Rule by a government ruled by the highest and main authority being either a [[Magician (fantasy)|magician]], sage, sorcerer, wizard or witch. This is often similar to a theocratic structured regime and is largely portrayed in fiction and fantasy genre categories.
|-
| [[Technological singularity|Uniocracy]]||Ruled by a singularity of all human minds connected via some form of technical or non technical telepathy acting as a form of super computer to make decisions based on shared patterned experiences to deliver fair and accurate decisions to problems as they arrive. Also known as the hive mind principle, differs from voting in that each person would make a decision while in the &quot;hive&quot; the synapses of all minds work together following a longer path of memories to make &quot;one&quot; decision.
|}

=== By socio-economic attributes ===
Historically, most political systems originated as [[socio-economic]] movements; experience with those movements in power, and the strong ties they may have to particular forms of government, can cause them to be considered as forms of government in themselves.
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Term
!Definition
|-
| [[Capitalism]] || In a capitalist or free-market economy, people own their own businesses and property and must buy services for private use, such as healthcare.
|-
| [[Communism]] || In a communist country, the government owns all businesses and farms and provides its people's healthcare, education and welfare.
|-
| [[Feudalism]] || A system of land ownership and duties. Under feudalism, all the land in a kingdom was the king's. However, the king would give some of the land to the lords or nobles who fought for him. These presents of land were called manors. Then the nobles gave some of their land to vassals. The vassals then had to do duties for the nobles. The lands of vassals were called fiefs.
|-
| [[Socialism]] || Socialist governments own many of the larger industries and provide education, health and welfare services while allowing citizens some economic choices
|-
| [[Welfare state]] || Concept of government in which the state plays a key role in the protection and promotion of the economic and social well-being of its citizens. It is based on the principles of [[equality of opportunity]], equitable [[distribution of wealth]], and [[public responsibility]] for those unable to avail themselves of the minimal provisions for a good life.
|}

=== By significant attributes ===
Certain major characteristics are defining of certain types; others are historically associated with certain types of government.

* [[Rule according to higher law]]
* [[Separation of church and state]]
* [[Civilian control of the military]]
* [[Totalitarianism]]/[[Authoritarianism]] vs. [[liberty]]
** [[Police state]]
* [[Economic system]] (e.g. [[capitalism]], [[socialism]], [[welfare state]], [[feudalism]])
* [[Patriarchy]] or [[matriarchy]] - dominance of a particular gender

=== By approach to regional autonomy ===
This list focuses on differing approaches that political systems take to the distribution of [[sovereignty]], and the [[Autonomous entity|autonomy]] of regions within the state.

* Sovereignty located exclusively at the center of political jurisdiction.
** [[Empire]]
** [[Unitary state]]
* Sovereignty located at the centre and in peripheral areas.
** [[Hegemony]]
** [[Federation]] and [[Federal republic]]
** [[Confederation]]
* Diverging degrees of sovereignty.
** [[Asymmetrical federalism]]
** [[Federacy]]
** [[Associated state]]
** [[Devolution (politics)|Devolved state]] - sovereignty can be abolished without changing the constitution.

== Classifying governments ==
In political science, it has long been a goal to create a typology or taxonomy of [[polities]], as typologies of political systems are not obvious.&lt;ref&gt;Lewellen, Ted C. ''Political Anthropology: An Introduction Third Edition''. Praeger Publishers; 3rd edition (30 November 2003)&lt;/ref&gt; It is especially important in the [[political science]] fields of [[comparative politics]] and [[international relations]].

On the surface, identifying a form of government appears to be easy, as all governments have an official form. The United States is a [[federal republic]], while the former Soviet Union was a [[socialist republic]]. However self-identification is not objective, and as Kopstein and Lichbach argue, defining regimes can be tricky.&lt;ref&gt;Kopstein and Lichbach (2005:4)&lt;/ref&gt;  For example, [[election]]s are a defining characteristic of a democracy{{cn|date=October 2012}}, but in practice elections in the former Soviet Union were not &quot;free and fair&quot; and took place in a [[single party state]].  Thus in many practical classifications it would not be considered democratic.

Another complication is that a large number of [[political systems]] originate as [[socio-economic movement]]s and are then carried into governments by specific [[political party|parties]] naming themselves after those movements. Experience with those movements in power, and the strong ties they may have to particular forms of government, can cause them to be considered as forms of government in themselves.

== Etymology ==
From Middle English government,{{citation needed|date=September 2012}} from Old French government{{citation needed|date=September 2012}} (French gouvernement), from Latin gubernatio (&quot;management, government&quot;), from Ancient Greek κυβερνισμός (kubernismos), κυβέρνησις (kubernēsis, &quot;steering, pilotage, guiding&quot;), from κυβερνάω (kubernaō, &quot;I steer, drive, guide, pilot&quot;) + -ment.

== Maps ==
[[Image:Forms of government.svg|left|600px|thumb|States by their systems of government. For the complete list of systems by country, see [[List of countries by system of government]]. &lt;hr&gt; {{Form of government legend}}]]
[[File:Electoral democracies.png|left|600px|thumb|Countries highlighted in &lt;span style=&quot;color: navy&quot;&gt;'''blue'''&lt;/span&gt; are designated &quot;[[representative democracy|electoral democracies]]&quot; in Freedom House's 2010 survey &quot;Freedom in the World&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.freedomhouse.org/uploads/fiw10/FIW_2010_Tables_and_Graphs.pdf|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20110208040624/http://www.freedomhouse.org/uploads/fiw10/FIW_2010_Tables_and_Graphs.pdf|archivedate=8 February 2011 |title=Freedom in the World |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=13 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Freedom House considers democracy in practice, not merely official claims.]]
[[File:Formas de governo.PNG|left|600px|thumb|A world map distinguishing countries of the world as [[monarchy|monarchies]] (red) from other forms of government (blue).  Many monarchies are considered electoral democracies because the monarch is largely ritual; in other cases the monarch is the only powerful political authority.]]
{{clr}}

== See also ==
{{wikiquote}}

{{Div col|cols=3}}
* [[Central government]]
* [[Civics]]
* [[Comparative government]]
* [[Constitutional economics]]
* [[Legal rights]]
* [[List of countries by system of government]]
* [[List of European Union member states by political system]]
* [[Political economy]]
* [[Politics]]
* [[State (polity)]]
* [[Voting system]]
* [[World government]]
{{Div col end}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}
Arnheim, M.T.W. Aristocracy in Greek Society. London: Thames and Hudson, 1997.

== Further reading ==
&lt;!-- * {{cite book|author=|title=|publisher=|year=|isbn=|url=}} --&gt;
* {{cite book|author=Kjaer, Anne Mette|title=Governance|publisher=Wiley-Blackwell|year=2004|isbn=978-0-7456-2979-7|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=AY5SIsf1nI4C}}
* {{cite book|authors=Newton, Kenneth &amp; Van Deth, Jan W.|title=Foundations of Comparative Politics|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2005|isbn=0-521-53620-0|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=jkPIY_lVKUIC}}
* {{cite book|author=Sharma, Urmila &amp; Sharma, S.K.|chapter=Forms of Government|title=Principles and Theory of Political Science|publisher=Atlantic Publishers &amp; Distributors|year=2000|isbn=978-81-7156-938-0|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=qdZ3VRRLDrgC&amp;pg=PA406}}
*{{cite book | first=Carles | last=Boix | title=Democracy and Redistribution | publisher=Cambridge University Press | location=New York | year=2003 }}
* Bunce, Valerie. 2003. &quot;Rethinking Recent Democratization: Lessons from the Postcommunist Experience.&quot; World Politics 55(2):167-192.
*{{cite book | first=Josep M.| last=Colomer| title=Political Institutions | publisher=Oxford University Press | location=Oxford| year=2003 }}
* [[Robert Dahl|Dahl, Robert]] ''[[Polyarchy]]'' Yale University Press (1971)
* Heritage, Andrew, Editor-in-Chief. 2000. World Desk Reference
*{{cite book | first=Arend | last=Lijphart | title=Democracy in Plural Societies: A Comparative Exploration | publisher=Yale University Press | location=New Haven | year=1977 }}
*Linz, Juan. 2000. Totalitarian and Authoritarian Regimes. Boulder: Lynne Rienner.
*Linz, Juan, and Stepan, Alfred. 1996. Problems of Democratic Transition and Consolidation: Southernn Europe, South America, and Post-Communist Europe. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins Press.
*Lichbach, Mark and Alan Zukerman, eds. 1997. Comparative Politics: Rationality, Culture, and Structure, Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1997.
*Luebbert, Gregory M. 1987. &quot;Social Foundations of Political Order in Interwar Europe,&quot; World Politics 39, 4.
*Moore, Barrington, Jr. 1966. Social Origins of Dictatorship and Democracy: Lord and Peasant in the Making of the Modern World. Cambridge: Beacon Press, ch. 7-9.
* Comparative politics : interests, identities, and institutions in a changing global order/edited by Jeffrey Kopstein, Mark Lichbach, 2nd ed, Cambridge University Press, 2005.
* O'Donnell, Guillermo. 1970. Modernization and Bureaucratic-Authoritarianism. Berkeley: University of California.
* O'Donnell, Guillermo, Schmitter, Philippe C., and Whitehead, Laurence, eds., Transitions from Authoritarian Rule: comparative Perspectives. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press.
* Przeworski, Adam. 1992. Democracy and the Market: Political and Economic Reforms in Eastern Europe and Latin America, New York: Cambridge University Press.
*Przeworski, Adam, Alvarez, Michael, Cheibub, Jose, and Limongi, Fernando. 2000. Democracy and Development: Political Institutions and Well Being in the World, 1950-1990. New York: Cambridge University Press.
*Shugart, Mathhew and John M. Carey, Presidents and Assemblies: Constitutional Design and Electoral Dynamics'', New York, Cambridge Univ. Press, 1992.
*[[Taagepera, Rein]] and Matthew Shugart. 1989. Seats and votes: The effects and determinants of electoral systems, Yale Univ. Press.

== External links ==
{{Wiktionary|government}}
{{Wiktionary|Appendix:List of forms of government}}
* [http://phrontistery.info/govern.html The Phrontistery Word List: Types of Government and Leadership]
* [http://www.lifeslittlemysteries.com/1096-what-are-the-different-types-of-governments.html What Are the Different Types of Governments?]
* [http://users.erols.com/mwhite28/20c-govt.htm Types of Governments from Historical Atlas of the 20th Century]
* [http://users.erols.com/mwhite28/othergov.htm Other classifications examples from Historical Atlas of the 20th Century]
* http://stutzfamily.com/mrstutz/WorldAffairs/typesofgovt.html
* [http://www.polisci.ccsu.edu/brown/regime_types.htm Regime Types]
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/cbbcnews/hi/find_out/guides/world/united_nations/types_of_government/ CBBC Newsround : types of government]

&lt;!-- From [[Form of government]]--&gt;
&lt;!-- From [[List of forms of government]]--&gt;

{{Autonomous types of first-tier administration}}
{{World government}}
[[Category:Government| ]]
[[Category:Forms of government]]
[[Category:Government institutions]]
[[Category:Political terms]]

[[af:Regering]]
[[am:መንግሥት]]
[[ar:حكومة]]
[[an:Gubierno]]
[[arc:ܫܘܠܛܢܘܬܐ (ܫܘܬܐܣܐ)]]
[[ast:Gobiernu]]
[[az:Hökumət]]
[[bn:সরকার]]
[[zh-min-nan:Chèng-hú]]
[[map-bms:Pemerentahan]]
[[be:Урад]]
[[be-x-old:Урад]]
[[bg:Държавно управление]]
[[bs:Vlada]]
[[ca:Govern]]
[[ceb:Gobyerno]]
[[cs:Vláda]]
[[ch:Gobietnu]]
[[ny:Boma]]
[[cy:Llywodraeth]]
[[da:Regering]]
[[de:Regierung]]
[[et:Valitsus]]
[[el:Κυβέρνηση]]
[[es:Gobierno]]
[[eo:Registaro]]
[[eu:Gobernu]]
[[fa:حکومت]]
[[hif:Sarkar]]
[[fr:Gouvernement]]
[[ga:Rialtas]]
[[gv:Reiltys]]
[[gl:Goberno]]
[[ko:정부]]
[[haw:Aupuni]]
[[hi:सरकार]]
[[hr:Vlada]]
[[id:Pemerintah]]
[[ia:Governamento]]
[[ie:Guvernament]]
[[is:Ríkisstjórn]]
[[it:Governo]]
[[he:ממשלה]]
[[jv:Pamaréntah]]
[[kn:ಸರಕಾರ]]
[[krc:Правительство]]
[[ka:მთავრობა]]
[[kk:Кабинет]]
[[sw:Serikali]]
[[ht:Gouvènman]]
[[ky:Өкмөт]]
[[lo:ລັດຖະບານ]]
[[la:Rectio]]
[[lv:Valdība]]
[[lb:Regierung]]
[[lt:Ministrų kabinetas]]
[[ln:Guvɛnɛmá]]
[[hu:Kormány (állami szerv)]]
[[mk:Влада]]
[[mg:Governemanta]]
[[ml:ഗവൺമെന്റ്]]
[[mi:Kāwanatanga]]
[[arz:حكومه]]
[[ms:Pemerintahan]]
[[mwl:Goberno]]
[[my:အစိုးရ]]
[[nl:Regering]]
[[ne:सरकार]]
[[new:अरचु (सन् २००३या संकिपा)]]
[[ja:政府]]
[[no:Styresmakt]]
[[nn:Styresmakt]]
[[nrm:Gouvèrnément]]
[[oc:Govèrn]]
[[pnb:سرکار]]
[[ps:حکومت]]
[[tpi:Gavman]]
[[pl:Rząd]]
[[pt:Governo]]
[[ro:Guvern]]
[[rue:Влада]]
[[ru:Правительство]]
[[sah:Дьаhалта]]
[[se:Ráđđehus]]
[[sco:Govrenment]]
[[sq:Qeveria]]
[[scn:Cuvernu]]
[[si:ආණ්ඩුව]]
[[simple:Government]]
[[sk:Vláda]]
[[sl:Vladavina]]
[[cu:Дрьжавьно строѥниѥ]]
[[ckb:حکوومەت]]
[[sr:Влада]]
[[sh:Vlada]]
[[su:Pamaréntah]]
[[fi:Hallinto]]
[[sv:Regering]]
[[tl:Pamahalaan]]
[[ta:அரசாங்கம்]]
[[th:รัฐบาล]]
[[tr:Hükûmet]]
[[uk:Уряд]]
[[ur:حکومت]]
[[za:Cwngfuj]]
[[vec:Goerno]]
[[vi:Chính phủ]]
[[zh-classical:政府]]
[[war:Punuan]]
[[yi:רעגירונג]]
[[yo:Ìjọba]]
[[zh-yue:政府]]
[[zh:政府]]</text>
      <sha1>1vlb1z2gujj2y4kt6umog2nzkgyai55</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
