<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Great power</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>372836</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521994385</id>
      <parentid>520336970</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-08T13:04:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>92.231.87.29</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Aftermath of the Cold War */ adjusted wording as mentioned in discussion</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="34166">{{Further|Power (international relations)|Hyperpower|Superpower|Second Superpower|Potential superpowers}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
[[Image:United Nations Security Council.jpg|thumb|350px|right|Great powers are recognized in an international structure such as the [[United Nations Security Council]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Encarta&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The world we want&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The law of the United Nations&quot;&gt;{{cite book 
| last = Kelsen
| first = Hans
| coauthors = 
| title=The law of the United Nations: a critical analysis of its fundamental ...
| publisher=The Lawbook Exchange, Ltd.
| year=2000
| location=United States of America 
| pages = 272–281, 911
| isbn = 1-58477-077-5
| url=http://www.google.com/books?id=BWPa0MB_AyQC&amp;pg=PA272#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shown here is the [[Security Council Chamber]].]]
A '''great power''' is a [[Sovereign state|state]] that is recognized as having the ability to exert its influence on a global scale. Great powers characteristically possess military and economic strength and diplomatic and [[soft power]] influence which may cause [[small powers]] to consider the opinions of great powers before taking actions of their own. [[International relations]] theorists have posited that great power status can be characterized into power capabilities, spatial aspects, and status dimensions. Sometimes the status of great powers is formally recognized in conferences such as the [[Congress of Vienna]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Encarta&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;World history, 1815-1920&quot;&gt;{{cite book 
| last = Fueter
| first = Eduard 
| coauthors = 
| title=World history, 1815–1920
| publisher=Harcourt, Brace and Company
| year=1922
| location=United States of America 
| pages = 25–28, 36–44
| isbn = 1-58477-077-5
| url=http://books.google.com/?id=XeKyv9l-3QEC&amp;pg=PA25&amp;dq=%22Great+Powers%22+%22Congress+of+Vienna%22&amp;q=%22Great%20Powers%22%20%22Congress%20of%20Vienna%22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;When the Stakes Are High—Deterrence and Conflict among Major Powers&quot;&gt;Danilovic, Vesna. &quot;When the Stakes Are High—Deterrence and Conflict among Major Powers&quot;, University of Michigan Press (2002), p 27, p225-p228 [http://www.press.umich.edu/titleDetailLookInside.do?id=16953 (PDF chapter downloads)] [http://www.press.umich.edu/pdf/0472112872-appb.pdf (PDF copy)].&lt;/ref&gt; or an international structure such as the [[United Nations Security Council]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Encarta&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The world we want&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Balance of Power&quot;/&gt;

The term &quot;great power&quot; was first used to represent the most important powers in Europe during the post-[[Napoleon I of France|Napoleonic]] era.  The &quot;Great Powers&quot; constituted the &quot;Concert of Europe&quot; and claimed the right to joint enforcement of the postwar treaties.&lt;ref name=&quot;British Diplomacy 1813–1815&quot;&gt;Charles Webster, (ed), ''British Diplomacy 1813–1815: Selected Documents Dealing with the Reconciliation of Europe,'' (1931), p307.&lt;/ref&gt; The formalization of the division between [[small powers]]&lt;ref&gt;Toje, A. (2010). The European Union as a small power: After the post-Cold War. New York: Palgrave Macmillan.&lt;/ref&gt; and great powers came about with the signing of the [[Treaty of Chaumont]] in 1814. Since then, the international [[Balance of power in international relations|balance of power]] has shifted numerous times, most dramatically during World War I and World War II. While some nations are widely considered to be great powers, there is no definitive list of them.

==Characteristics==
There are no set or defined characteristics of a great power. These characteristics have often been treated as empirical, self-evident to the assessor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=Theory of International Politics | last=Waltz | first=Kenneth N | publisher=McGraw-Hill | year=1979 | page=131 | isbn=0-201-08349-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, this approach has the disadvantage of subjectivity. As a result, there have been attempts to derive some common criteria and to treat these as essential elements of great power status.

Early writings on the subject tended to judge states by the [[Realism (international relations)|realist]] criterion, as expressed by the historian [[A. J. P. Taylor]] when he noted that &quot;The test of a great power is the test of strength for war.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=The Struggle for Mastery in Europe 1848–1918 | last=Taylor | first=Alan JP | publisher=Clarendon |location=Oxford| year=1954 | page=xxiv | isbn=0-19-881270-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later writers have expanded this test, attempting to define power in terms of overall military, economic, and political capacity.&lt;ref&gt;Organski, AFK – World Politics, Knopf (1958)&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kenneth Waltz]], the founder of the [[Neorealism (international relations)|neorealist]] theory of international relations, uses a set of five criteria to determine great power: population and territory; resource endowment; economic capability; political stability and competence; and military strength. These expanded criteria can be divided into three heads: power capabilities, spatial aspects, and status.&lt;ref name=&quot;When the Stakes Are High—Deterrence and Conflict among Major Powers&quot;/&gt;

===Power dimensions===
[[Image:Leopold Von Ranke 1877.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Leopold von Ranke]] was one of the first to attempt to scientifically document the great powers.]]
As noted above, for many, power capabilities were the sole criterion. However, even under the more expansive tests, power retains a vital place.

This aspect has received mixed treatment, with some confusion as to the degree of power required. Writers have approached the concept of great power with differing conceptualizations of the world situation, from multi-polarity to overwhelming [[hegemony]]. In his essay, 'French Diplomacy in the Postwar Period', the French historian Jean-Baptiste Duroselle spoke of the concept of multi-polarity: &quot;A Great power is one which is capable of preserving its own independence against any other single power.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;contained on page 204 in: Kertesz and Fitsomons (eds) – Diplomacy in a Changing World, University of Notre Dame Press (1959)&lt;/ref&gt;

This differed from earlier writers, notably from [[Leopold von Ranke]], who clearly had a different idea of the world situation. In his essay 'The Great Powers', written in 1833, von Ranke wrote: &quot;If one could establish as a definition of a Great power that it must be able to maintain itself against all others, even when they are united, then [[Frederick the Great|Frederick]] has raised Prussia to that position.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Iggers and von Moltke &quot;In the Theory and Practice of History&quot;, Bobbs-Merril (1973)&lt;/ref&gt; These positions have been the subject of criticism.&lt;ref name=&quot;When the Stakes Are High—Deterrence and Conflict among Major Powers&quot;/&gt;

===Spatial dimension===
All states have a geographic scope of interests, actions, or projected power. This is a crucial factor in distinguishing a great power from a regional power; by definition the scope of a regional power is restricted to its region. It has been suggested that a great power should be possessed of actual influence throughout the scope of the prevailing international system. [[Arnold J. Toynbee]], for example, observes that &quot;Great power may be defined as a political force exerting an effect co-extensive with the widest range of the society in which it operates. The Great powers of 1914 were 'world-powers' because Western society had recently become 'world-wide'.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=The World After the Peace Conference | last=Toynbee | first=Arnold J | publisher=Humphrey Milford and Oxford University Press | year=1926 | page=4 | url=http://www.archive.org/details/TheWorldAfterThePeaceConference}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other suggestions have been made that a great power should have the capacity to engage in extra-regional affairs and that a great power ought to be possessed of extra-regional interests, two propositions which are often closely connected.&lt;ref&gt;Stoll, Richard J – State Power, World Views, and the Major Powers, Contained in: Stoll and Ward (eds) – Power in World Politics, Lynne Rienner (1989)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Status dimension===
Formal or informal acknowledgment of a nation's great-power status has also been a criterion for being a great power. As political scientist [[George Modelski]] notes, &quot;The status of Great power is sometimes confused with the condition of being powerful, The office, as it is known, did in fact evolve from the role played by the great military states in earlier periods ... But the Great power system institutionalizes the position of the powerful state in a web of rights and obligations.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=Principles of World Politics | last=Modelski | first=George | publisher=Free Press | year=1972 | page=141 | isbn=978-0-02-921440-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This approach restricts analysis to the post-Congress of Vienna epoch; it being there that great powers were first formally recognized.&lt;ref name=&quot;When the Stakes Are High—Deterrence and Conflict among Major Powers&quot;/&gt; In the absence of such a formal act of recognition it has been suggested that great power status can arise by implication, by judging the nature of a state's relations with other great powers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Power in World Politics&quot;&gt;Domke, William K – Power, Political Capacity, and Security in the Global System, Contained in: Stoll and Ward (eds) – Power in World Politics, Lynn Rienner (1989)&lt;/ref&gt;

A further option is to examine a state's willingness to act as a great power.&lt;ref name=&quot;Power in World Politics&quot;/&gt; As a nation will seldom declare that it is acting as such, this usually entails a retrospective examination of state conduct. As a result this is of limited use in establishing the nature of contemporary powers, at least not without the exercise of subjective observation.

Other important criteria throughout history are that great powers should have enough influence to be included in discussions of political and diplomatic questions of the day, and have influence on the final outcome and resolution. Historically, when major political questions were addressed, several great powers met to discuss them. Before the era of groups like the United Nations, participants of such meetings were not officially named, but were decided based on their great power status. These were conferences which settled important questions based on major historical events. This might mean deciding the political resolution of various geographical and nationalist claims following a major conflict, or other contexts.

There are several historical conferences and treaties which display this pattern, such as the [[Congress of Vienna]], the [[Congress of Berlin]], the discussions of the [[Treaty of Versailles]] which redrew the map of Europe, and the [[Treaty of Westphalia]].

==History==
[[Image:CongressVienna.jpg|thumb|350px|right|''The [[Congress of Vienna]]'' by [[Jean-Baptiste Isabey]], 1819.]]
Different sets of great, or significant, powers have existed throughout history; however, the term &quot;great power&quot; has only been used in scholarly or diplomatic discourse since the Congress of Vienna in 1815.&lt;ref name=&quot;World history, 1815-1920&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;When the Stakes Are High—Deterrence and Conflict among Major Powers&quot;/&gt; The Congress established the [[Concert of Europe]] as an attempt to preserve peace after the years of [[Napoleonic Wars]].

[[Lord Castlereagh]], the [[Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs|British Foreign Secretary]], first used the term in its diplomatic context, in a letter sent on February 13, 1814: &quot;It affords me great satisfaction to acquaint you that there is every prospect of the Congress terminating with a general accord and Guarantee between the Great powers of Europe, with a determination to support the arrangement agreed upon, and to turn the general influence and if necessary the general arms against the Power that shall first attempt to disturb the Continental peace.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;British Diplomacy 1813–1815&quot;/&gt;

The Congress of Vienna consisted of five main powers: the [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|United Kingdom]], the [[Austrian Empire]], [[Prussia]], [[France]], and [[Russian Empire|Russia]]. These five primary participants constituted the original great powers as we know the term today.&lt;ref name=&quot;When the Stakes Are High—Deterrence and Conflict among Major Powers&quot;/&gt; Other powers, such as [[Spain]], [[Kingdom of Portugal|Portugal]], and [[Sweden]] were consulted on certain specific issues, but they were not full participants. [[Kingdom of Hanover|Hanover]], [[Bavaria]], and [[Württemberg]] were also consulted on issues relating to Germany. 

Of the five original great powers recognised at the Congress of Vienna, only France and the United Kingdom have maintained that status continuously to the present day, although France was defeated in the [[Franco-Prussian War]] and occupied during World War II. After the Congress of Vienna, the [[British Empire]] emerged as the pre-eminent power, due to its navy and the extent of its territories, which signalled the beginning of the [[Pax Britannica]] and of [[The Great Game]] between Britain and Russia. The [[Balance of power in international relations|balance of power]] between the Great Powers became a major influence in European politics, prompting [[Otto von Bismarck]] to say &quot;All politics reduces itself to this formula: try to be one of three, as long as the world is governed by the unstable equilibrium of five great powers.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=eVPQWWqHbi8C&amp;pg=PA106&amp;lpg=PA106&amp;dq=%22try+to+be+one+of+three%22+%22five+great+powers%22&amp;source=web&amp;ots=RTFf5BgiqV&amp;sig=GIpRg4plsUbafYB-F4S5xnkPluw&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ct=result |title=Peace, War, and the European Powers, 1814–1914 |publisher=Books.google.com |date= |accessdate=2011-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=DkN6M2mvh9EC&amp;pg=PA86&amp;lpg=PA86&amp;dq=%22be+one+of+three%22+%22five+great+powers%22&amp;source=web&amp;ots=94EEpqiR5I&amp;sig=rbQ08zhwPnJQx3GaoHlNE79aQ74&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;resnum=5&amp;ct=result |title=Ideology and International Relations in the Modern World |publisher=Books.google.com |date= |accessdate=2011-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sscnet.ucla.edu/polisci/faculty/trachtenberg/cv/SCHROEDE.doc |title=The Transformation of European Politics, 1763–1848 |date= |accessdate=2011-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gresham.ac.uk/printtranscript.asp?EventId=302 Britain And Germany: from Ally to Enemy]{{dead link|date=June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Over time, the relative power of these five nations fluctuated, which by the dawn of the 20th century had served to create an entirely different balance of power. Some, such as the United Kingdom and Prussia (as part of the newly formed [[German Empire|German state]]), experienced continued economic growth and political power.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.courses.rochester.edu/stone/PSC272/lectures/05-Pro%20Waltz.ppt 
|title=Multi-polarity vs Bipolarity, Subsidiary hypotheses, Balance of Power 
|accessdate=2008-12-20 
|format=PPT 
|publisher=University of Rochester}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Others, such as Russia and Austria-Hungary, stagnated.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.historyhome.co.uk/europe/aus-hun.htm 
|title=European History ''Austria-Hungary 1870–1914'' 
|accessdate=2008-12-20 
|last=Tonge 
|first=Stephen 
|coauthors=head of history at Catholic University School in Dublin }}&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, other states were emerging and expanding in power, largely through the process of [[industrialization]]. The foremost of these emerging powers were [[Empire of Japan|Japan]] after the [[Meiji Restoration]] and the [[United States]] after its [[American Civil War|civil war]], both of which had been minor powers in 1815. By the dawn of the 20th century the balance of world power had changed substantially since the Congress of Vienna. The [[Eight-Nation Alliance]] was a belligerent alliance of eight nations against the [[Boxer Rebellion]] in China. It formed in 1900 and consisted of the five Congress powers plus [[Kingdom of Italy (1861–1946)|Italy]], Japan, and the United States, representing the great powers at the beginning of 20th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Rise of Russia in Asia&quot;&gt;{{cite book 
| last = Dallin 
| first = David 
| authorlink = 
| coauthors = 
| title = The Rise of Russia in Asia 
| publisher = Read Books 
| date = 2006-11-30
| location = 
| pages = 
| url = http://books.google.com/?id=Q5nIUd_mlEcC&amp;pg=PA62&amp;lpg=PA62&amp;dq=%22boxer+rebellion%22+%22great+powers%22 
| doi = 
| id = 
| isbn =978-1-4067-2919-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Great powers at war===
[[Image:Council of Four Versailles.jpg|thumb|350px|[[The Big Four (World War I)|The &quot;Big Four&quot;]] at the [[Treaty of Versailles]]: [[David Lloyd George]], [[Vittorio Emanuele Orlando]], [[Georges Clemenceau]] and [[Woodrow Wilson]].]]

Shifts of international power have most notably occurred through major conflicts.&lt;ref&gt;[http://jcr.sagepub.com/cgi/content/abstract/32/1/87 Power Transitions as the cause of war].&lt;/ref&gt; The conclusion of the [[World War I|Great War]] and the resulting treaties of [[Treaty of Versailles|Versailles]], [[Treaty of Saint-Germain-en-Laye (1919)|St-Germain]], and [[Treaty of Trianon|Trianon]] witnessed Great Britain, France, Italy, Japan and the United States as the chief arbiters of the new world order.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.globalautonomy.ca/global1/glossary_entry.jsp?id=EV.0003 Globalization and Autonomy] by Julie Sunday, McMaster University.&lt;/ref&gt; In the aftermath of World War I the [[German Empire]] was defeated, the Austria-Hungarian empire was divided into new, less powerful states and the [[Russian Empire]] fell to a [[Russian Revolution (1917)|revolution]]. During the [[Treaty of Versailles]] the &quot;Big Three&quot; — France, Great Britain and the United States — held noticeably more power and influence on the proceedings and outcome of the treaty than Italy or Japan.&lt;ref name=&quot;Margaret MacMillan&quot;&gt;
{{cite book 
| last = MacMillan 
| first = Margaret 
| authorlink = Margaret MacMillan 
| title = [[Peacemakers: The Paris Peace Conference of 1919 and Its Attempt to End War|Paris 1919]] 
| publisher = Random House Trade 
| year = 2003 
| location = United States of America 
| pages = 36, 306, 431 
| isbn = 0-375-76052-0 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book 
| last = Boemeke 
| first = Manfred 
| coauthors = Gerald D. Feldman, Elisabeth Glaser-Schmidt 
| title=The Treaty of Versailles: 75 Years After 
| publisher=Cambridge University Press 
| year=1998 
| location=United States of America 
| pages = 
| isbn = 0-521-62132-1 
| url=http://books.google.com/?id=zqj-oHp4KsgC&amp;pg=PA272&amp;dq=%22Big+Three%22+Versailles+%22great+powers%22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Peacemakers: The Paris Peace Conference of 1919 and Its Attempt to End War|Paris 1919]] by Margaret MacMillan has the Council of Five (Britain, France, Italy, Japan and the United States) as the main victors and remaining Great Powers.&lt;/ref&gt; 

The victorious great powers also gained an acknowledgement of their status through permanent seats at the [[League of Nations]] Council, where they acted as a type of [[Executive (government)|executive]] body directing the Assembly of the League. However, the Council began with only four permanent members — Great Britain, France, Italy, and Japan – because the United States, meant to be the fifth permanent member, left because the [[United States Senate|US Senate]] voted on 19 March 1920 against the [[ratification]] of the [[Treaty of Versailles]], thus preventing American participation in the League.

When [[World War II]] started in 1939, it divided the world into two alliances – the [[Allies of World War II|Allies]] (the [[United Kingdom]] and France at first, followed in 1941 by the [[Soviet Union]], the United States, and China); and the [[Axis powers]] consisting of [[Nazi Germany|Germany]], Italy and Japan.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Economics of World War II&quot;&gt;Harrison, M (2000) [http://www.google.com/books?id=ZgFu2p5uogwC&amp;dq=great+powers&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=bn#PPA1,M1 The Economics of World War II: Six Great Powers in International Comparison], Cambridge University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;Even though the book ''The Economics of World War II'' lists seven great powers at the start of 1939 (the British Empire, the Empire of Japan, France, the Kingdom of Italy, Nazi Germany, the Soviet Union and the United States), it focuses only on six of them, because France surrendered shortly after the war began{{Citation needed|date = May 2012}} .&lt;/ref&gt; The end of World War II saw the United States, United Kingdom, and Soviet Union emerge as the primary victors. The importance of the [[Republic of China]] and France was acknowledged by their inclusion, along with the other three, in the group of countries allotted permanent seats in the [[United Nations Security Council]]. 

[[File:Yalta Conference cropped.jpg|thumb|250px|[[Allies of World War II|The &quot;Big Three&quot; of Europe]] at the [[Yalta Conference]]: [[Winston Churchill]], [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]] and [[Joseph Stalin]].]]Since the end of the World Wars, the term &quot;great power&quot; has been joined by a number of other power classifications. Foremost among these is the concept of the [[superpower]], used to describe those nations with overwhelming power and influence in the rest of the world. It was first coined in 1944 by [[William Thornton Rickert Fox|William T.R. Fox]]&lt;ref name=&quot;The Superpowers&quot;/&gt; and according to him, there were three superpowers: the [[British Empire]], the [[United States]], and the [[Soviet Union]]. But by the mid 1950s the British Empire lost its superpower status, leaving the United States and the Soviet Union as the world's superpowers.&lt;ref group=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;''The 1956 [[Suez Crisis]] suggested that the United Kingdom, financially weakened by two world wars, could not then pursue its [[foreign policy]] objectives on an equal footing with the new superpowers without sacrificing [[convertibility]] of its [[reserve currency]] as a central goal of policy.'' – from [[superpower]] cited by Adam Klug and Gregor W. Smith, 'Suez and Sterling', ''Explorations in Economic History'', Vol. 36, No. 3 (July 1999), pp. 181–203.&lt;/ref&gt; The term [[middle power]] has emerged for those nations which exercise a degree of global influence, but are insufficient to be decisive on international affairs. [[Regional power]]s are those whose influence is generally confined to their region of the world.

During the [[Cold War]], the Asian power of Japan and the European powers of the United Kingdom, France, and [[West Germany]] rebuilt their economies. France and the United Kingdom maintained technologically advanced armed forces with power projection capabilities and maintain large defence budgets to this day. Yet, as the Cold War continued, authorities began to question if France and the United Kingdom could retain their long-held statuses as great powers.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.com/index.cfm?PgNm=TCE&amp;Params=A1ARTA0005274 
|title=Middle Power 
|accessdate=2008-12-20 
|last=Holmes 
|first=John 
|publisher=The Canadian Encyclopedia }}&lt;/ref&gt;
China, with the world's largest population, has slowly risen to great power status, with large growth in economic and military power in the post-war period. After 1949, the Republic of China began to lose its recognition as the sole legitimate government of China by the other great powers, in favour of the [[People's Republic of China]]. Subsequently, in 1971, it lost its permanent seat at the UN Security Council to the People's Republic of China.

===Aftermath of the Cold War===
[[Image:Great Powers Map.png|349px|thumb|right|
----
{{legend|#2c5aa0|Conventional great powers: [[Permanent members of the United Nations Security Council|UN P5]] and [[Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty|recognized]] [[Nuclear weapon|nuclear weapons]] states: China, France, Russia, the United Kingdom and the United States.}} 
{{legend|#00B600|Economic great powers: Germany and Japan.}}]]

China, France, Russia, the United Kingdom and the United States are referred to as great powers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Adriansyah&quot;&gt;Yasmi Adriansyah, 'Questioning Indonesia's place in the world', ''Asia Times'' (20 September 2011): 'Though there are still debates on which countries belong to which category, there is a common understanding that the GP [great power] countries are the United States, China, United Kingdom, France and Russia. Besides their political and economic dominance of the global arena, these countries have special status in the United Nations Security Council with their permanent seats and veto rights.'&lt;/ref&gt; These five nations are the only states to have [[United Nations Security Council#Permanent members|permanent seats]] with veto power on the UN Security Council. They are also the recognized &quot;[[Nuclear Weapons States]]&quot; under the [[Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty]], and have the [[List of countries by military expenditures|five largest military expenditures]] in the world.

After the [[dissolution of the Soviet Union]], its UN Security Council permanent seat was transferred to the [[Russian Federation]] in 1991, as its [[successor state]]. The newly formed Russian Federation emerged on the level of a great power, leaving the United States as the only remaining global superpower&lt;ref group=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;''The fall of the [[Berlin wall]] and the breakup of the [[Soviet Union]] left the United States as the only remaining superpower in the 90's.&lt;/ref&gt; (although some support a [[Polarity in international relations#Multipolarity|multipolar world view]]).

However, there is no unanimous agreement among authorities as to the current status of these powers or what precisely defines a &quot;great&quot; power. Sources have at times referred to China,&lt;ref&gt;Gerald Segal, [http://www.foreignaffairs.com/articles/55401/gerald-segal/does-china-matter Does China Matter?], ''[[Foreign Affairs]]'' (September/October 1999).&lt;/ref&gt; France, the United Kingdom,&lt;ref name=&quot;European Security After 9/11'&quot;&gt;according to P. Shearman, M. Sussex, ''European Security After 9/11'', Ashgate, 2004, both UK and France were global powers now reduced to middle-power status.&lt;/ref&gt; and Russia&lt;ref&gt;Iver B Neumanna, &quot;Russia as a great power, 1815–2007&quot;, ''Journal of International Relations and Development'' (2008) 11, p. 128: &quot;As long as Russia's rationality of government deviates from present-day hegemonic neo-liberal models by favouring direct state rule rather than indirect governance, the West will not recognize Russia as a fully fledged great power.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sherman Garnett, &quot;Russia ponders its nuclear options&quot;, ''The Washington Times'' (6 November 1995), p. 2: &quot;Russia must deal with the rise of other middle powers in Eurasia at a time when it is more of a middle power itself.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Geoff Kitney, &quot;Putin It To The People&quot;, ''Sydney Morning Herald'' (25 March 2000), p. 41: &quot;The Council for Foreign and Defence Policy, which includes senior figures believed to be close to Putin, will soon publish a report saying Russia's superpower days are finished and that the country should settle for being a middle power with a matching defence structure.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; as middle powers. 

Japan and Germany are sometimes classified as middle powers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sperling&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
| journal=British Journal of Political Science
| title=Neither Hegemony nor Dominance: Reconsidering German Power in Post Cold-War Europe
| author=Sperling, James
| year=2001 | doi=10.1017/S0007123401000151
| url=http://journals.cambridge.org/action/displayAbstract;jsessionid=BAF3F6B6103D4CEF49834F52571F68B0.tomcat1?fromPage=online&amp;aid=68015
| volume=31
| issue=2 
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Otte2000&gt;{{cite book
| author=Max Otte, Jürgen Greve
| year=2000
| title=A Rising Middle Power?: German Foreign Policy in Transformation, 1989–1999
| place=Germany
| page=324
| isbn=0-312-22653-5
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Er&quot;&gt;Er LP (2006) [http://muse.jhu.edu/demo/contemporary_southeast_asia_a_journal_of_international_and_strategic_affairs/v028/28.1er.html Japan's Human Security Rolein Southeast Asia]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Merkel as a world star - Germany's place in the world&quot;, ''The Economist'' (November 18, 2006), p.27: &quot;Germany, says Volker Perthes, director of the German Institute for International and Security Affairs, is now pretty much where it belongs: squarely at the centre. Whether it wants to be or not, the country is a ''Mittelmacht'', or middle power.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Susanna Vogt, &quot;Germany and the G20&quot;, in Wilhelm Hofmeister, Susanna Vogt,  ''G20: Perceptions and Perspectives for Global Governance'' (Singapore: Oct. 19, 2011), p. 76, citing Thomas Fues and Julia Leininger (2008): &quot;Germany and the Heiligendamm Process&quot;, in Andrew Cooper and Agata Antkiewicz (eds.): ''Emerging Powers in Global Governance: Lessons from the Heiligendamm Process'', Waterloo: Wilfrid Laurier University Press, p. 246: &quot;Germany’s motivation for the initiative had been '… driven by a combination of leadership qualities and national interests of a middle power with civilian characteristics'.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Change of Great Powers&quot;, in ''Global Encyclopaedia of Political Geography'', by M.A. Chaudhary and Guatam Chaudhary (New Delhi, 2009.), p. 101: &quot;Germany is considered by experts to be an economic power. It is considered as a middle power in Europe by Chancellor Angela Merkel, former President Johannes Rau and leading media of the country.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Gratius&gt;Susanne Gratius, ''Is Germany still a EU-ropean power?'', FRIDE Policy Brief, No. 115 (February 2012), pp. 1, 2: &quot;Being the world's fourth largest economic power and the second largest in terms of exports has not led to any greater effort to correct Germany's low profile in foreign policy ... For historic reasons and because of its size, Germany has played a middle-power role in Europe for over 50 years.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; However, they are also included among the great powers,&lt;ref name=&quot;PaulWirtz2004&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=T.V. Paul|author2=James Wirtz|author3=Michel Fortmann|title=Balance of Power: Theory and Practice in the 21st Century|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=9jy28vBqscQC&amp;pg=PA59|accessdate=14 October 2012|date=8 September 2004|publisher=Stanford University Press|isbn=978-0-8047-5017-2|pages=59–}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.webcitation.org/5kwqEr8pe&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/haass17/English&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.worldcrunch.com/europes-superpower-germany-new-indispensable-and-resented-nation/4176&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/germany/8898945/Germany-The-reluctant-superpower.html | work=The Daily Telegraph | first=Simon | last=Winder | title=Germany: The reluctant superpower | date=2011-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; due to their economic status (having the [[List of countries by GDP (nominal)|third and fourth largest economies]] respectively), despite their lack of permanent seats and veto power on the UN Security Council or strategic military reach. 

With continuing [[European integration]], the [[European Union]] is increasingly being seen as a great power in its own right,&lt;ref name=&quot;The United States and the Great Powers&quot;&gt;{{cite book 
| last =Buzan
| first =Barry
| coauthors =
| title=The United States and the Great Powers
| publisher=Polity Press
| year=2004
| location=Cambridge, United Kingdom
| page =70
| isbn =0-7456-3375-7
| url=}}&lt;/ref&gt; with representation at the [[World Trade Organization|WTO]] and at [[G8]] and [[G-20 major economies|G-20]] summits. This is most notable in areas where the European Union has exclusive competence (i.e. economic affairs). It also reflects a non-traditional conception of Europe's world role as a global &quot;civilian power&quot;, exercising collective influence in the functional spheres of trade and diplomacy, as an alternative to military dominance.&lt;ref&gt;Veit Bachmann and James D Sidaway, &quot;Zivilmacht Europa: A Critical Geopolitics of the European Union as a Global Power&quot;, ''Transactions of the Institute of British Geographers'', New Series, Vol. 34, No. 1 (Jan., 2009), pp. 94-109.&lt;/ref&gt; The European Union is not a [[sovereign state]] and has limited scope in the areas of foreign affairs and defense policy. These remain with the [[member states of the European Union]], which include three larger powers (referred to as the &quot;[[EU three]]&quot;): France, Germany and the United Kingdom.

{{List of Great powers by date}}

==See also==
{{div col|2}}
*[[Power in international relations]]
*[[Historical powers]]
*[[G7]] and [[G8]] respectively
*[[Middle power]]
*[[Regional power]]
*[[Superpower]]
*[[Potential superpowers]]
*[[Hyperpower]]
{{div col end}}

==Notes==
&lt;references group=&quot;nb&quot; /&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|2}}
&lt;/div&gt;

==Further reading==
*''The Tragedy of Great Power Politics'' by [[John J. Mearsheimer]]
*''Theory of International Politics'' by [[Kenneth Waltz|Kenneth N Waltz]]
*''World Politics: Trend and Transformation'' by Eugene R. Witkopf
*''[[The Rise and Fall of the Great Powers]]'' by Paul Kennedy
* ''France and the Nazi Threat: The Collapse of French Diplomacy 1932–1939'' by Jean-Baptiste Duroselle, Introduction by Anthony Adamthwaite (Enigma Books, ISBN 1-929631-15-4)

{{International power}}
{{Great power diplomacy}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Great Power}}
[[Category:States by power status|Power]]

[[ar:قوة عظمى]]
[[be:Вялікія дзяржавы]]
[[bg:Велика сила]]
[[cs:Velmoc]]
[[da:Stormagt]]
[[de:Großmacht]]
[[el:Μεγάλες Δυνάμεις]]
[[es:Potencia mundial]]
[[eo:Mondpotenco]]
[[fr:Grande puissance]]
[[gl:Potencia mundial]]
[[ko:강대국]]
[[hr:Velesila]]
[[id:Kekuatan besar]]
[[it:Grande potenza]]
[[he:מעצמה]]
[[kk:Ұлы державалар]]
[[nl:Grote mogendheid]]
[[ja:列強]]
[[no:Stormakt]]
[[nn:Stormakt]]
[[pl:Mocarstwo]]
[[pt:Grande potência]]
[[ro:Mare putere]]
[[ru:Великая держава]]
[[si:ලෝක මහා බලවතා]]
[[simple:Great power]]
[[sk:Veľmoc]]
[[sh:Velika sila]]
[[fi:Suurvalta]]
[[sv:Stormakt]]
[[tl:Bansang makapangyarihan]]
[[ta:உலக வல்லமை]]
[[th:มหาอำนาจ]]
[[tr:Düvel-i Muazzama]]
[[uk:Велика держава]]
[[vi:Cường quốc]]
[[zh:大国]]</text>
      <sha1>7e5fjhqdlhm8jx3i8yfk51ils1o8w4r</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
