<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Hacktivism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>162600</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519095206</id>
      <parentid>516755359</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-21T22:27:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Loremaster</username>
        <id>58926</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Reality hacking */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="42407">
'''Hacktivism''' (a [[portmanteau]] of ''[[Hack (computer security)|hack]]'' and ''[[activism]]'') is the use of computers and computer networks as a means of protest to promote political ends. The term was first coined in 1996 by a member of the [[Cult of the Dead Cow]] hacker collective named Omega.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.cnet.com/8301-27080_3-57406793-245/old-time-hacktivists-anonymous-youve-crossed-the-line/ &quot;Old-time hacktivists: Anonymous, you've crossed the line&quot;].&quot; ''[[CNet News]]'', March 30, 2012. Retrieved March 30, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; If ''hacking'' as &quot;illegally breaking into computers&quot; is assumed, then ''hacktivism'' could be defined as &quot;the use of legal and/or illegal digital tools in pursuit of political ends&quot;. These tools include [[web site defacement]]s, [[URL redirection|redirects]], [[denial-of-service attack]]s, [[information theft]], web site [[parody|parodies]], [[virtual sit-in]]s, [[typosquatting]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://fallwell.com/ fallwell.com]&lt;/ref&gt; and virtual [[sabotage]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.alexandrasamuel.com/dissertation/index.html | first = Alexandra | last = Samuel | title = Hacktivism and the Future of Political Participation | accessdate = 2008-04-19 | date = August 2004 }}&lt;/ref&gt; If ''hacking'' as &quot;clever computer usage/programming&quot; is assumed, then ''hacktivism'' could be understood as the writing of [[code]] to promote [[political ideology]]: promoting expressive [[politics]], [[free speech]], [[human rights]], and information [[ethics]] through [[software development]]. Acts of hacktivism are carried out in the belief that proper use of code will be able to produce similar results to those produced by regular [[activism]] or [[civil disobedience]].

==Overview==
Hacktivist activities span many political ideals and issues. [[Freenet]] is a prime example of translating political thought (anyone should be able to speak) into code. [[Hacktivismo]] is an offshoot of [[Cult of the Dead Cow]]; its beliefs include access to information as a basic human right. The loose network of programmers, artists and radical militants [[1984 network liberty alliance]] is more concerned with issues of [[free speech]], [[surveillance]] and [[privacy]] in an era of increased technological surveillance.

Hacktivism is a controversial term, and since it covers a range of passive to active and non-violent to violent activities, it can often be construed as [[cyberterrorism]]. It was coined to describe how electronic [[direct action]] might work toward [[social change]] by combining [[computer programming|programming]] skills with [[critical thinking]]. Others use it as practically synonymous with malicious, destructive acts that undermine the [[computer security|security]] of the [[Internet]] as a [[technology|technical]], [[economics|economic]], and [[political platform]].

Essentially, the controversy reflects two divergent philosophical strands within the hacktivist movement. One strand thinks that malicious cyber-attacks are an acceptable form of [[direct action]]. The other strand thinks that all protest should be peaceful, refraining from destruction.{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}

As a principle of political activism, reality hacking takes advantage of the insight of linguists and sociologists who argue that post-twentieth-century [[popular culture]] in the advanced world has become particularly impervious to either positive or negative rethinking of community. Negative assertions about community—in the form of negative news stories and mass political [[protest]]s—tend to fall on ears overloaded by daily tragedy in the news, even when the causes and facts they relate are valid and deserving. Positive reimaginings of community—in the form of [[utopia]]n havens, [[New religious movement|alternative religious]] or political structures, or idealistic protest against the status quo—equally tend to fall upon unbelieving ears of busy individuals who have already accepted the standards, sacrifices, and limits of the reality in which they normally operate.

As an alternative to these dead ends of twentieth-century political activism, reality hacking tries to capture the attention of individuals in their normal course of regular information consumption. It may involve attracting [[mass media]] attention to an [[media prank|attention-getting fringe political issue]] more liable to generate rethinking of cultural norms than standard debates to which the public has already become jaded. Or it may involve harnessing the means of information dissemination itself, using online information sources to [[advocacy journalism|disseminate alternative definitions of commonly accepted facts]].

==Controversy==
Some people describing themselves as hacktivists have taken to [[defacement (vandalism)|defacing]] websites for political reasons, such as attacking and defacing government websites as well as web sites of groups who oppose their [[ideology]]. Others, such as [[Oxblood Ruffin]] (the &quot;[[foreign affairs]] minister&quot; of [[Cult of the Dead Cow]] and Hacktivismo), have argued forcefully against definitions of hacktivism that include web defacements or [[denial-of-service attack]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.cultdeadcow.com/cDc_files/cDc-0384.php | first = Oxblood | last = Ruffin | title = Hacktivism, From Here to There | date = 3 June 2004 | accessdate = 2008-04-19 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Within the hacking community, those who carry out automated attacks are generally known as [[script kiddie]]s.

Critics suggest that DoS attacks are an attack on free speech; that they have [[unintended consequence]]s; that they waste resources; and that they could lead to a &quot;DoS war&quot; that nobody will win. In 2006, [[Blue Security]] attempted to automate a DoS attack against spammers; this led to a massive DoS attack against Blue Security which knocked them, their old ISP and their DNS provider off the internet, destroying their business.&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite journal | url = http://www.securityfocus.com/news/11392 | title = Blue Security folds under spammer's wrath | first = Robert | last = Lemos | journal = SecurityFocus | date = 17 May 2006 | accessdate = 2008-04-19 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following [[Denial-of-service attack|denial-of-service]] attacks by [[Anonymous (group)|Anonymous]] on multiple sites, in reprisal for the apparent suppression of [[Wikileaks]], [[John Perry Barlow]], a founding member of the [[Electronic Frontier Foundation|EFF]], said &quot;I support freedom of expression, no matter whose, so I oppose DDoS attacks regardless of their target... they're the poison gas of cyberspace...&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2010/12/09/us-wikileaks-cyberwarfare-amateur-idUSTRE6B81K520101209 | title = Analysis: WikiLeaks&amp;nbsp;— a new face of cyber-war? |accessdate= 2010-12-09 | author = Reuters |date=2010-12-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Depending on who is using the term, hacktivism can be a politically constructive form of [[anarchism|anarchic]] civil disobedience or an undefined anti-systemic gesture; it can signal [[anti-capitalism|anticapitalist]] or political protest; it can denote anti-[[spam (electronic)|spam]] activists, security experts, or [[open source]] advocates. Critics of hacktivism fear that the lack of a clear agenda makes it a politically immature gesture, while those given to [[conspiracy theory]] hope to see in hacktivism an attempt to precipitate a crisis situation online.

==Elements of hacktivism==
{{unreferenced section|date=March 2012}}
A Haction usually has the following elements.
* Political motivation
* A premium on humor, and often resembles a digital form of clowning
* Has a moderate &quot;outlaw orientation&quot; as opposed to severe
* Result of aggressive policy circumvention, rather than a gradual attempt to change a policy
* Capacity for solo activity: while most forms of political activism require the strength of masses, hacktivism is most often the result of the power of one, or small group.
* Most often carried out anonymously, and can take place over transnational borders.

==Forms of hacktivism==
In order to carry out their operations, hacktivists use a variety of software tools readily available on the Internet. In many cases the software can be downloaded from a popular website, or launched from a website with click of a button. Some of the more well-known hacktivist tools are below:

# Defacing Web Pages: Between 1995 and 1999 Attrition.org reported 5,000 website defacements. In such a scenario, the hacktivist will significantly alter the front page of a company's or governmental agency's website.
# Web Sit-ins: In this form of hacktivism, hackers attempt to send so much traffic to the site that the overwhelmed site becomes inaccessible to other users in a variation on a [[denial of service]].
# E-mail Bombing: Hacktivists send scores of e-mails with large file attachments to their target's e-mail address.
# Code: Software and websites can achieve political purposes. For example, the encryption software [[Pretty Good Privacy|PGP]] can be used to secure communications; PGP's author, [[Phil Zimmermann]] said he distributed it first to the peace movement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.philzimmermann.com/EN/news/PGP_10thAnniversary.html | title = PGP Marks 10th Anniversary | publisher = Phil Zimmermann | date = |accessdate=2010-08-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jim Warren (computer specialist)|Jim Warren]] suggests PGP's wide dissemination was in response to Senate Bill 266, authored by Senators Biden and DeConcini, which demanded that &quot;...communications systems permit the government to obtain the plain text contents of voice, data, and other communications...&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.contra.org/pgp/PhilZimmerman.html | title = The Persecution of Phil Zimmermann, American | publisher = Jim Warren | date = 1996-01-08 |accessdate=2011-02-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[WikiLeaks]] is an example of a politically motivated website: it seeks to &quot;keep governments open&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wikileaks.ch/ | title = WikiLeaks homepage | publisher = WikiLeaks | date = |accessdate=2011-02-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
# Website Mirroring: is used as a circumvention tool to bypass censorship blocks on websites. It is a technique that copies the content of a censored website and posts it to other domains and subdomains that are not censored.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://advocacy.globalvoicesonline.org/projects/mirroring-a-censored-wordpress-blog/ | title = Mirroring a Censored Wordpress Blog | first = Sami | last = Ben Gharbia |publisher = Global Voices Advocacy | accessdate = 2011-02-09 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
# [http://advocacy.globalvoicesonline.org/projects/advocacy-20-guide-tools-for-digital-advocacy/geo-bombing-youtube-google-earth/ Geo-bombing]: a technique in which [[netizens]] add a [[geotagging|geo-tag]] while editing [[YouTube]] videos so that the location of the video can be displayed in [[Google Earth]].
# Anonymous blogging: a method of speaking out to a wide audience about human rights issues, government oppression, etc. that utilizes various web tools such as free email accounts, IP masking, and blogging software to preserve a high level of anonymity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://advocacy.globalvoicesonline.org/projects/guide/ | title = Anonymous Blogging with Wordpress and Tor | first = Ethan | last = Zuckerman | Global Voices Advocacy | accessdate = 2011-02-09 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
# [[Doxing]] is the practice of outing of private information about individuals,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Bright |first=Peter |url=http://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/news/2012/03/doxed-how-sabu-was-outed-by-former-anons-long-before-his-arrest.ars |title=Doxed: how Sabu was outed by former Anons long before his arrest |publisher=Ars Technica |date=2012-03-07 |accessdate=2012-09-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; but the term is sometimes used more broadly to refer to exposing embarrassing information about organizations (such as [[Project Chanology]]).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.informationweek.com/news/galleries/security/attacks/232600322 Who Is Anonymous: 10 Key Facts Mathew J. Schwartz 02/07/2012]
&lt;/ref&gt; Doxing is sometimes used to deter collaboration with law enforcement,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theatlanticwire.com/technology/2011/07/did-lulzsec-trick-police-arresting-wrong-guy/40522/ |title=Did LulzSec Trick Police Into Arresting the Wrong Guy? - Technology |publisher=The Atlantic Wire |date=2011-07-28 |accessdate=2012-09-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; or for more self-proclaimed revolutionary purposes. For example in the 2011 [[Stratfor]] hacking incident, the password lists and credit card information were published allegedly in order &quot;to wreak unholy havoc upon the systems and personal e-mail accounts of these rich and powerful oppressors&quot;; later the rooted email spools were passed to [[WikiLeaks]] for publication.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Anderson |first=Nate |url=http://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/news/2012/03/stakeout-how-the-fbi-tracked-and-busted-a-chicago-anon.ars |title=Stakeout: how the FBI tracked and busted a Chicago Anon |publisher=Ars Technica |date=2012-03-07 |accessdate=2012-09-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# [[Swatting]] is the act of triggering a police raid, usually that of an anti-terrorist team [[SWAT]] in the United States, typically for retaliation or harassment and based on providing false information to law enforcement.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.cnet.com/8301-17852_3-57377796-71/xbox-360-threat-leads-to-swat-team-raid/ Xbox 360 threat leads to SWAT team raid by Chris Matyszczyk February 14, 2012 3:03 PM PST]&lt;/ref&gt; Swatting sometimes involves [[caller ID spoofing]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wired.com/threatlevel/2011/05/neff/ Veteran of 90’s Cyber Gang GlobalHell Charged in Swatting Conspiracy. By Kevin Poulsen. May 9, 2011]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable hacktivist events==
{{Example farm|date=June 2011}}
* The earliest known instance of hacktivism as documented by [[Julian Assange]] is as follows:&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite journal | first = Julian | last = Assange | title = The Curious Origins of Political Hacktivism | journal = CounterPunch | date = 25 November 2006 | url = http://www.counterpunch.org/assange11252006.html | accessdate = 2008-04-19 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Hacktivism is at least as old as October 1989 when DOE, HEPNET and SPAN (NASA) connected VMS machines world wide were penetrated by the anti-nuclear WANK worm. [...] WANK penetrated machines had their login screens altered to:
&lt;source lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;

   W O R M S    A G A I N S T    N U C L E A R    K I L L E R S
 _______________________________________________________________
 \__  ____________  _____    ________    ____  ____   __  _____/
  \ \ \    /\    / /    / /\ \       | \ \  | |    | | / /    /
   \ \ \  /  \  / /    / /__\ \      | |\ \ | |    | |/ /    /
    \ \ \/ /\ \/ /    / ______ \     | | \ \| |    | |\ \   /
     \_\  /__\  /____/ /______\ \____| |__\ | |____| |_\ \_/
      \___________________________________________________/
       \                                                 /
        \    Your System Has Been Officially WANKed     /
         \_____________________________________________/

  You talk of times of peace for all, and then prepare for war.
&lt;/source&gt;

* The first public use of DDoS as a form of protest was the [[Intervasion of the UK]] orchestrated by a group called the Zippies on [[Guy Fawkes Night|Guy Fawkes Day]], 1994.
* One of the earliest documented hacktivist events was the &quot;Strano Network sit-in&quot;, defined &quot;Netstrike&quot;, a [[strike action]] directed against [[Government of France|French government]] computers in 1995.
* The term itself was coined by techno-culture writer Jason Sack in a piece about media artist Shu Lea Cheang published in InfoNation in 1995.
* On the night of Monday, 30 June 1997, at 4:30am the [[Portuguese people|Portuguese]] hacking group UrBaN Ka0s hacked the site of the Republic of Indonesia and 25 other military and government sites as part of the hacking community campaign against the Indonesian government and the state of affairs in East Timor. This was one of the first mass hacks and the biggest in history.
* The hacking group [[milw0rm]] hacked into the [[Bhabha Atomic Research Centre]] (BARC) in 1998, replacing the center's website with an anti-nuclear message; the same message reappeared later that year in what was then an unprecedented mass hack by milw0rm of over 300 websites on the server of hosting company Easyspace.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ottawa&quot;&gt;{{ cite news | url=http://hrea.org/lists/huridocs-tech/markup/msg00014.html | title=E-Guerrillas in the mist | publisher=Ottawa Citizen | date=October 27, 1998 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 1998, the [[Electronic Disturbance Theater]] conducted &quot;[[virtual sit-in]]s&quot; on the Web sites of the Pentagon and the Mexican government to bring the world's attention to the plight of indigenous rights in the Mexican state of Chiapas. A Mexican hacking group took over Mexico's finance department website in support of the same cause.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ottawa&quot;/&gt;
* Another one of the more notorious examples of hacktivism, and the continuation of the 1997 attacks, was the modification of more [[Indonesia]]n web sites with appeals to &quot;Free [[East Timor]]&quot; in 1998 by [[Portuguese people|Portuguese]] hackers.&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite news | last = Harmon | first = Amy | title = 'Hacktivists' of All Persuasions Take Their Struggle to the Web|url=http://www.nytimes.com/library/tech/98/10/biztech/articles/31hack.html|newspaper=The New York Times | date = October 31, 1998 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* On December 29, 1998, the Legions of the Underground (LoU) declared [[cyberwar]] on [[Iraq]] and [[China]] with the intention of disrupting and disabling internet infrastructure. On January 7, 1999, an international coalition of hackers (including Cult of the Dead Cow, [[2600: The Hacker Quarterly|''2600'']]'s staff, ''[[Phrack]]'''s staff, [[L0pht]], and the [[Chaos Computer Club]]) issued a joint statement condemning the LoU's declaration of war.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.cultdeadcow.com/news/statement19990107.html | title= LoU Strike Out with International Coalition of Hackers: A Joint Statement by 2600, The Chaos Computer Club, The Cult of the Deadcow, !Hispahack, L0pht Heavy Industries, Phrack and Pulhas| accessdate = 2008-04-19 | date = 7 January 1999 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The LoU responded by withdrawing its declaration.
* Hacktivists attempted to disrupt [[ECHELON]] (an international electronic communications surveillance network filtering any and all satellite, microwave, cellular, and fiber-optic traffic) by holding &quot;Jam Echelon Day&quot; (JED) on October 21, 1999. On the day, hacktivists attached large keyword lists to many messages, taking advantage of listservers and newsgroups to spread their keywords further. The idea was to give the Echelon computers so many &quot;hits&quot; they overloaded. It is not known whether JED was successful in actually jamming Echelon, although NSA computers were reported to have crashed &quot;inexplicably&quot; in early March, 2000. A second Jam Echelon Day (JEDII) was held in October 2000, however the idea never regained its initial popularity. JED was partly denial-of-service attack and partly [[agitprop]].
* The Federation of Random Action calls for a virtual sit-in on Occidental Petroleum in support of the U’wa’s protest against drilling on indigenous land during 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nettime.org/Lists-Archives/nettime-l-0002/msg00016.html | title = Federation of Random Action Calls for a VR Sit-In on Occidenta | publisher = &lt;nettime | date = |accessdate=2011-06-03 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Electronic Disturbance Theater and others staged a week of disruption during the [[2004 Republican National Convention]] in [[New York City]], conducting [[sit-in]]s against Republican web sites and flooding web sites and communication systems identified with [[conservatism|conservative]] causes. This received mixed reviews from the hacktivist community.{{Citation needed|date=November 2008}}
* The Hackbloc collective started publishing [[Hack This Zine]], a hacktivist research journal
* Hacktivists worked to slow, block, or reroute traffic for [[web server]]s associated with the [[World Trade Organization]], the [[World Economic Forum]], and the [[World Bank]].{{Citation needed|date=November 2008}}
* Throughout 2006, [[Electronic Disturbance Theater]] joined the [[borderlands Hacklab]] for a number of virtual sit-ins, against the massacre in Atenco, in solidarity with striking French students and against the [[Minutemen]] and immigration laws.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bang.calit2.net/sdhacklab/previous-updates.html | title = borderLands hackLab | publisher = Bang.calit2.net | date = |accessdate=2010-09-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* On March 25, 2007, hacktivists organized the event freEtech in response to the O'Reilly Etech conference, and started a series of West coast hackmeetings.
* Electronic Disturbance Theater stages a virtual sit-in against the Michigan Legislature against cuts to Medicaid.
* On January 21, 2008, a message appeared on [[YouTube]] from a group calling itself '[[Anonymous (group)|Anonymous]]'. The group declared &quot;[[Project Chanology]]&quot;, essentially a war on The [[Church of Scientology]], and promised to systematically expel The Church from the internet. Over the following week, Scientology websites were intermittently knocked offline, and the Church of Scientology moved its website to a host that specializes in protection from [[denial-of-service]] attacks.
* A computer hacker leaks the personal data of 6 million Chileans (including ID card numbers, addresses, telephone numbers and academic records) from government and military servers to the internet, to protest Chile's poor data protection.&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/7395295.stm | work=BBC News | title=Hacker leaks 6m Chileans' records | date=May 12, 2008 | accessdate=April 2, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Throughout early 2008, Chinese hackers have hacked the [[CNN]] website on numerous occasions in response to the protests during the [[2008 Olympic Torch Relay]] and claims of [[Anti-CNN|biased reporting from western media]]. The majority of the [[DDoS]] attacks took place between March and August, at a time where Chinese nationalistic pride was at an [[Heart China|all time high]] due to the [[2008 Olympic Games]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bbs.lehu.shu.edu.cn/Article.aspx?aid=20756 | title = CNN被黑。。。。。。 - 电脑数码 网络 - CNN 黑客 - 上海大学乐乎论坛 (Original Primary Source) | publisher = Bbs.lehu.shu.edu.cn | date = |accessdate=2011-06-03 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cyberinsecure.com/one-of-cnn-sports-websites-hacked-by-chinese-anti-cnn-group/ | title = One Of CNN Sports Websites Hacked By Chinese Anti-CNN Group | publisher = CyberInsecure.com | date = 2008-04-21 |accessdate=2011-06-03 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Electronic Disturbance Theater and the Hacklab stage a virtual sit-in against the war on Iraq and biotech and nanotech war profiteers, on the 5 year anniversary of the war, in solidarity with widespread street actions.
* Intruders hacked the website of commentator Bill O'Reilly and posted personal details of more than 200 of its subscribers, in retaliation for remarks O'Reilly made on Fox News condemning the attack on Palin's Yahoo email account.&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite news | last = Goodin | first = Dan | title = FoxNews commentator Bill O'Reilly's website hacked|url=http://www.theregister.co.uk/2008/09/20/fox_news_bill_oreilly_hacked/|newspaper=The Register | date = 20 September 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 2008 hacktivists developed a communications and monitoring system for the 2008 RNC protests called Tapatio.
* In early 2009, the [[2008–2009 Israel–Gaza conflict|Israeli invasion of Gaza]] motivated a number of website defacements, denial-of-service attacks, and domain name and account hijackings, from both sides.&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite document | url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/technology/7827293.stm | accessdate = 2009-01-15 | work=BBC News | date=January 14, 2009 | title=Gaza crisis spills onto the web | publisher = [[BBC News Online]] | first=Flora | last=Graham }}&lt;/ref&gt; These attacks are notable in being amongst the first ever politically motivated domain name hijackings.
* During the [[2009 Iranian election protests]], [[Anonymous (group)|Anonymous]] played a role in disseminating information to and from Iran by setting up the website Anonymous Iran;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://iran.whyweprotest.net/ | title = Anonymous Iran @WhyWeProtest.net | publisher = Iran.whyweprotest.net | date = |accessdate=2011-06-03 }}&lt;/ref&gt; they also released a video [[manifesto]] to the Iranian government.
* On August 1, 2009, the [[Melbourne International Film Festival]] was forced to shut down its website after DDoS attacks by Chinese vigilantes, in response to [[Rebiya Kadeer]]'s planned guest appearance, the screening of a film about her which is deemed &quot;anti-China&quot; by Chinese state media, and strong sentiments following the [[July 2009 Ürümqi riots]]. The hackers booked out all film sessions on its website, and replaced festival information with the Chinese flag and anti-Kadeer slogans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=August 01, 2009 11:50AM |url=http://www.news.com.au/story/0,27574,25866348-29277,00.html |title=Hack attack hits Melbourne Film Festival |publisher=News.com.au |date=2009-08-01 |accessdate=2011-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* August 24, 2009, New Hacktivism: From Electronic Civil Disobedience to Mixed Reality Performance&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://hemisphericinstitute.org/hemi/en/workshops/item/320-09-new-hacktivism-from-electronic-civil-disobedience-to-mixed-reality-performance | accessdate = 2010-07-01 | work=Hemispheric Institute of Performance and Politics at NYU | date=August 24, 2009 | title=New Hacktivism: From Electronic Civil Disobedience to Mixed Reality Performance | publisher = hemi.nyu.edu }}&lt;/ref&gt; workshop at the Hemispheric Institute of Performance and Politics led by [[Micha Cárdenas]] in Bogotá, Colombia.
* In November 2009, computers of the [[Climatic Research Unit e-mail hacking incident|Climate Research Unit of East Anglia University]] were hacked, and email purporting to expose a conspiracy by scientists to suppress data that contradicted their conclusions regarding global warming was made available on a Russian [[FTP]] server.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/11/20/AR2009112004093.html?hpid=sec-nation | title = Hackers steal electronic data from top climate research center | publisher = Washingtonpost.com | date = 2009-11-21|accessdate=2011-06-03 | first=Juliet | last=Eilperin}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* On February 10, 2010, Anonymous DDoS-attacked Australian government websites against the Australian governments attempt to filter the Internet.
* On July 23, 2010, [[European Climate Exchange]]'s website was targeted by hacktivists operating under the name of [[Decocidio|decocidio#ϴ]]. The website showed a [[parody|spoof]] [[homepage]] for around 22 hours in an effort to promote the contention that [[carbon emission trading|carbon trading]] is a false solution to the [[Global warming|climate crisis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/environment/2010/jul/26/eu-carbon-trading-website-hacked| title= Hackers shut down EU carbon-trading website| work= [[The Guardian]]| date= 26 July 2010| first= Leigh | last = Phillips | location=London }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* On December 8, 2010, the websites of both [[Mastercard]] and [[Visa Inc.|Visa]] were the subject of an attack by hacktivist group [[Anonymous (group)|Anonymous]], reacting to the two companies' decision to stop processing payments to the whistle-blowing site [[Wikileaks]], following a series of leaks by the site. Mastercard said the attack had no impact on people's ability to use their cards, though there were claims by an unnamed payment firm that their customers had experience a complete loss of service.&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite news| url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-11935539| title=Hackers 'hit Mastercard payments', attack Visa| work= [[BBC News Online]]| date=8 December 2010 |accessdate=2010-12-09 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Anonymous was later blamed for the DDoS attacks on om.nl and politie.nl (Dutch government websites).
* In January 2011, the websites of the government of [[Zimbabwe]] were targeted by anonymous due to censorship of the Wikileaks documents.&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite news | title = Anonymous activists target Tunisian government sites | author = |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-12110892|newspaper=BBC | date = 7 January 2011|accessdate=December 12, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In January 2011, [[Anonymous (group)|Anonymous]] launches DDOS attacks against the Tunisian government websites due to censorship of the Wikileaks documents and the [[2010–2011 Tunisian protests]].&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite news | title = Anonymous activists target Tunisian government sites | author = |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-12110892|newspaper=BBC | date = 4 January 2011|accessdate=January 7, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Tunisians were reported to be assisting in these denial-of-service attacks launched by Anonymous.&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite news | title = Hackers hit Tunisian websites | author = Evan Hill|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/africa/2011/01/201113111059792596.html|newspaper=ALJAZEERA | date = 03 Jan 2011|accessdate=January 7, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Anonymous released an online message denouncing the government clampdown on recent protests. Anonymous has named their attacks as &quot;Operation Tunisia&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite news | title = Timeline: Tunisia's civil unrest | author = Ryan Rifai|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/indepth/spotlight/tunisia/2011/01/201114142223827361.html|newspaper=ALJAZEERA | date = 04 Jan 2011|accessdate=January 7, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Anonymous successfully ddossed eight Tunisian government websites. They planned attacks on Internet Relay Chat networks. An unknown user subsequently attacked Anonymous's website with a ddos on January 5.&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite news | title = Tunisia's bitter cyberwar | author = Yasmine Ryan|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/indepth/features/2011/01/20111614145839362.html|newspaper=ALJAZEERA | date = 06 Jan 2011|accessdate=January 7, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In January 2011, [[Anonymous (group)|Anonymous]], in response to the [[2011 Egyptian protests]], attacked Egyptian government websites and voiced support for the people of [[Egypt]].
* Google worked with engineers from SayNow and Twitter to provide communications for the Egyptian people in response to the government sanctioned internet blackout during the 2011 protests. The result, [[Speak To Tweet]], was a service in which voicemail left by phone was then tweeted via Twitter with a link to the voice message on Google's SayNow.&lt;ref name=&quot;Google Blog&quot;&gt;{{cite web | last = Singh | first = Ujjwal | title = Some weekend work that will (hopefully) allow more Egyptians to be heard|url=http://googleblog.blogspot.com/2011/01/some-weekend-work-that-will-hopefully.html | publisher = Google|accessdate=3 May 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* During the Egyptian internet black out, Jan 28- Feb 2 of 2011, Telecomix provided dial up services, and technical support for the Egyptian people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2011/02/egypts-internet-blackout-highlights-danger-weak | title = Egypt's Internet Blackout Highlights Danger of Weak Links, Usefulness of Quick Links | first = Eva | last = Galperin | publisher = Electric Frontier Foundation | accessdate = 2011-02-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* On April 20, 2011, hackers took down Sony's PlayStation Network. Anonymous was suspected of hacking PSN for their previous threats to Sony for suing Geohotz, who jailbroke the PlayStation 3 but they later claimed that they didn't. Afterwards, a group of hackers claimed to have 2.2 million credit card numbers from PSN users for sale.
* In June 2011, LulzSec and Anonymous launched [[Operation AntiSec]], an enormous hactivist operation that a large number of hackers and hacking organizations have taken part in. It has included breaches of many companies and government agencies.
* On November 5, 2011, a Fire Sale, made famous by the film [[Live Free or Die Hard]], attempt was reportedly made but was an obvious failure but was still the first of its kind. A hacker called [[AnonymousPEF]] attempted this with a software acting virus.
*On January 20, 2012, the websites for [[United States Department of Justice|Department of Justice]] and the [[FBI]] experienced difficulties after suffering a denial of service attack. The hackers group Anonymous claimed responsibility, in response to the shut down of the file sharing website [[Megaupload]].

==Related notions==
===Media hacking===
''Media hacking'' refers to the usage of various [[electronic media]] in an innovative or otherwise abnormal fashion for the purpose of conveying a message to as large a number of people as possible, primarily achieved via the [[World Wide Web]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | year = 2005 | url = http://www.seanbohan.com/?p=6 | title = Media Hacking | publisher = SeanBohan.com | author = Bohan, S. | accessdate = February 9, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | year = 2005 | url = http://www.meskelsquare.com/archives/2005/11/hacking_baby_cheetahs_and_hung.html | title = Hacking Baby Cheetahs and Hunger Strikes | publisher = Meskel Square | author = Heavens, A. | accessdate = February 9, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; A popular and effective means of media hacking is posting on a [[blog]], as one is usually controlled by one or more independent individuals, uninfluenced by outside parties. The concept of [[social bookmarking]], as well as Web-based [[Internet forum]]s, may cause such a message to be seen by users of other sites as well, increasing its total reach.

Media hacking is commonly employed for political purposes, by both political parties and [[dissident|political dissidents]]. A good example of this is the 2008 US Election, in which both the [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic]] and [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]] parties used a wide variety of different media in order to convey relevant messages to an increasingly Internet-oriented audience.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Peter Kafka | Jun. 20, 2008, 12:34 PM | 458 | 46 |url=http://www.alleyinsider.com/2008/6/presidential_debates_come_to_twitter_how_to_follow_along |title=Obama, McCain Debate Via Twitter: How To Follow Along* |publisher=Alleyinsider.com |date=2008-06-20 |accessdate=2011-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, political dissidents used [[blog]]s and other social media like [[Twitter]] in order to reply on an individual basis to the Presidential candidates. In particular, sites like Twitter are proving important means in gauging popular support for the candidates, though the site is often used for dissident purposes rather than a show of positive support.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://goodgearguide.com.au/index.php/id;1823349553 |title=Twitter backlash over McCain campaign 'suspension' |publisher=Good Gear Guide |date=2008-09-25 |accessdate=2011-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Mobile technology has also become subject to media hacking for political purposes. [[Short message service|SMS]] has been widely used by political dissidents as a means of quickly and effectively organising [[smart mobs]] for political action. This has been most effective in the Philippines, where SMS media hacking has twice had a significant impact on whether or not the country's Presidents are elected or removed from office.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=August 22nd, 2006 by Howard Rheingold |url=http://www.smartmobs.com/2006/08/22/wikipedia-on-sms-political-impacts/ |title=Blog Archive » Wikipedia on SMS, political impacts |publisher=Smart Mobs |date=2006-08-22 |accessdate=2011-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reality hacking===
{{Expert-subject|date=November 2010}}
{{Original research|date=January 2010}}

''Reality hacking'' is a term used to describe any phenomenon which emerges from the nonviolent use of illegal or legally ambiguous [[digital]] tools in pursuit of politically, socially or [[culture jamming|culturally subversive]] ends. These tools include [[website defacement]]s, [[URL redirection]]s, [[denial-of-service attack]]s, information theft, web-site parodies, [[virtual sit-in]]s, and virtual [[sabotage]].{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}

Art movements such as [[Fluxus]] and [[Happening]]s in the 1970s created a climate of receptibility in regard to loose-knit organizations and group activities where spontaneity, a [[modern primitive|return to primitivist behavior]], and an ethics where activities and [[artivism|socially engaged art]] practices became tantamount to [[aesthetic]] concerns.{{Clarify | date = January 2010}}

The conflation of these two histories in the mid-to-late 1990s {{Citation needed|date=January 2010}} resulted in cross-overs between virtual sit-ins, [[electronic civil disobedience]], denial-of-service attacks, as well as mass protests in relation to groups like the [[International Monetary Fund]] and the [[World Bank]]. The rise of collectivies, [[net.art]] groups, and those concerned with the fluid interchange of technology and [[real life (reality)|real life]] (often from an environmental concern) gave birth to the practice of &quot;reality hacking&quot;.

The 1999 science fiction-action film ''[[The Matrix]]'' is most responsible for popularizing the [[simulation hypothesis]]—the suggestion that [[reality]] is in fact a [[simulation]] of which those affected by the simulants are generally unaware—and &quot;reality hacking&quot; as reading and understanding the [[Matrix digital rain|code which represents the activity of the simulated reality environment]] but also modifying it in order to bend the [[laws of physics]] within [[simulated reality]].{{Or|date=July 2011}}

Reality hacking as a mystical practice is explored in the [[Goth subculture|Gothic-Punk]] aesthetics-inspired [[White Wolf, Inc.|White Wolf]] [[urban fantasy]] role-playing game ''[[Mage: The Ascension]]''. In this game, the Reality Coders (also known as Reality Hackers or Reality Crackers) are a faction within the [[Virtual Adepts]], a secret society of mages whose [[Magic (fantasy)|magick]] revolves around [[digital]] technology. They are dedicated to bringing the benefits of [[cyberspace]] to [[real space]]. To do this, they had to identify, for lack of a better term, the &quot;[[source code]]&quot; that allows our [[Universe]] to function. And that is what they have been doing ever since. Coders infiltrated a number of levels of society in order to gather the greatest compilation of knowledge ever seen. One of the Coders' more overt agendas is to acclimate the masses to the world that is to come. They spread Virtual Adept ideas through [[video game]]s and a whole spate of &quot;[[reality show]]s&quot; that mimic [[virtual reality]] far more than &quot;real&quot; reality. The Reality Coders consider themselves the future of the Virtual Adepts, creating a world in the image of visionaries like [[Grant Morrison]] or [[Terence McKenna]].{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}}

In a [[location-based game]] (also known as a pervasive game), reality hacking refers to tapping into phenomena that exist in the real world, and tying them into the game story universe.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://delivery.acm.org/10.1145/1510000/1501803/p224-jonsson.pdf?key1=1501803&amp;key2=0230940921&amp;coll=DL&amp;dl=ACM&amp;CFID=115438113&amp;CFTOKEN=21447210 |title=The art of game-mastering pervasive games |doi=10.1145/1501750.1501803 |publisher=Delivery.acm.org |date= |accessdate=2011-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Reality hacking relies on [[tweaking]] the every-day communications most easily available to individuals with the purpose of awakening the political and [[social connectedness|community conscience]] of the larger population. The term first came into use among New York and San Francisco artists, but has since been adopted by a [[school of thought|school]] of political activists centered around [[culture jamming]].

In the video game [[Saints Row: The Third]], the player fights multiple criminal gangs, including a gang of hacktivists.

==See also==
{{Div col}}
;Ideologies
* [[Crypto-anarchism]]
* [[Culture jamming]]
* [[E-democracy]]
* [[Electronic civil disobedience]]
* [[Hacker culture]]
* [[Hacker ethic]]
* [[Internet activism]]
* [[Open source government]]
* [[Patriot hacking]]
* [[Reality hacking]]
* [[Tactical media]]

;Hactivists
* [[1984 network liberty alliance]]
* [[Anonymous (group)|Anonymous]]
* [[Chaos Computer Club]]
* [[Cult of the Dead Cow]]
* [[Decocidio]]
* [[HEC (Hacktivism group)|HEC]]
* [[The Jester (hacktivist)|Jester]]
* [[LulzSec]]
* [[milw0rm]]
* [[Telecomix]]

;Supporters and Organizations
* [[2600: The Hacker Quarterly]]
* [[Citizen Lab]]
* [[HackThisSite]]
{{Div col end}}
;Other
* [[Cypherpunk]]
* [[Project Chanology]]
* [[Script kiddie]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite newspaper |first=Joseph |last=Menn |url=http://www.ft.com/intl/cms/s/2/3645ac3c-e32b-11e0-bb55-00144feabdc0.html |title=They’re watching. And they can bring you down |newspaper= [[The Financial Times]] |date=September 23, 2011 |accessdate=2012-09-01 }}

==External links==
{{External links|date=August 2010}}
* [http://www.hacktivismo.com/projects/ Hacktivismo's Projects Page]
* [http://www.alexandrasamuel.com/dissertation/pdfs/index.html Hacktivism and the Future of Political Participation] Political science dissertation on the history and political significance of hacktivism
* [http://www.hackbloc.org Hackbloc] Home of the hacktivist zine &quot;HackThisZine&quot;
* [http://www.thehacktivist.com/?pagename=hacktivism What is Hacktivism?]
* [http://www.aracnet.com/~kea/Papers/Politically%20Motivated%20Computer%20Crime.pdf Hacktivism and Politically Motivated Computer Crime] History, types of activity and cases studies
* [http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-11935539 Wikileaks defended by Anonymous hacktivists] BBC News, 7 December 2010.
* [http://www.usatoday.com/tech/news/story/2012-07-19/hactivism-anonymous-attacks/56464792/1 ''Hacktivist attacks grow as governments get in on the action''] 19.July.2012 [[USA Today]]

{{Media manipulation}}

[[Category:Activism by method]]
[[Category:Hacking (computer security)]]
[[Category:Intellectual property activism]]
[[Category:Politics and technology]]
[[Category:Internet terminology]]
[[Category:Technology in society]]
[[Category:Words coined in the 2000s]]
[[Category:Culture jamming techniques]]

[[de:Hacktivismus]]
[[es:Hacktivismo]]
[[fa:هکتیویسم]]
[[fr:Hacktivisme]]
[[ko:핵티비즘]]
[[it:Hacktivism]]
[[he:האקטיביזם]]
[[nl:Hacktivisme]]
[[pt:Hacktivismo]]
[[fi:Haktivismi]]</text>
      <sha1>patqhr7hma37sztj05msi7eikqkqu9f</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
