<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Hierarchical organization</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>14031</id>
    <revision>
      <id>516296048</id>
      <parentid>516295473</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-06T11:16:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>O.Koslowski</username>
        <id>13863430</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/203.101.161.82|203.101.161.82]] ([[User talk:203.101.161.82|talk]]) to last revision by Pm master ([[WP:HG|HG]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8042">{{redirect|Institutional hierarchy|social institutions|Social hierarchy|other potential uses|Hierarchy (disambiguation)}}

A '''hierarchical organization''' is an [[organizational structure]] where every entity in the [[organization]], except one, is [[subordinate]] to a single other entity. This arrangement is a form of a [[hierarchy]]. In an organization, the hierarchy usually consists of a singular/group of power at the top with subsequent levels of power beneath them. This is the dominant mode of organization among large organizations; most [[corporation]]s, [[government]]s, and [[organized religion]]s are hierarchical organizations with different levels of [[management]], [[power (philosophy)|power]] or [[authority]]. For example, the broad, top-level overview of the general organization of the [[Catholic Church hierarchy|Catholic Church]] consists of the [[Pope]], then the [[Cardinal (Catholic)|Cardinals]], then the [[Archbishop]]s, and so on. 

Members of hierarchical organizational structures chiefly communicate with their immediate superior and with their immediate subordinates. Structuring organizations in this way is useful partly because it can reduce the communication overhead by limiting information flow; this is also its major limitation.{{Citation needed|date=July 2012}}

==Visualization==
A hierarchy is typically visualized as a [[pyramid (geometry)|pyramid]], where the height of the ranking or person depicts their power status and the width of that level represents how many people or business divisions are at that level relative to the whole—the highest-ranking people are at the [[Apex (geometry)|apex]], and there are very few of them; the [[Base (geometry)|base]] may include thousands of people who have no subordinates). These hierarchies are typically depicted with a [[tree structure|tree]] or [[triangle]] [[diagram]], creating an [[organizational chart]] or organigram. Those nearest the top have more power than those nearest the bottom, and there being fewer people at the top then at the bottom. As a result, superiors in a hierarchy generally have higher status and command greater rewards than their subordinates.

==Common models==
All governments and most companies have similar structures. Traditionally, the [[monarch]] was the pinnacle of the [[State (polity)|state]]. In many countries, [[feudalism]] and [[manorialism]] provided a formal social structure that established hierarchical links at every level of society, with the monarch at the top. 

In modern post-feudal states the nominal top of the hierarchy still remains the [[head of state]], which may be a [[president]] or a [[constitutional monarch]], although in many modern states the powers of the head of state are delegated among different bodies. Below the head, there is commonly a [[senate]], [[parliament]] or [[congress]], which in turn often delegate the day-to-day running of the country to a [[prime minister]]. In many [[democracies]], the people are considered to be the notional top of the hierarchy, over the head of state; in reality, the people's power is restricted to voting in elections.

In business, the business owner traditionally occupied the pinnacle of the organization. In most modern large companies, there is now no longer a single dominant shareholder, and the collective power of the business owners is for most purposes delegated to a [[board of directors]], which in turn delegates the day-to-day running of the company to a [[managing director]] or [[CEO]]. Again, although the shareholders of the company are the nominal top of the hierarchy, in reality many companies are run at least in part as personal fiefdoms by their management; [[corporate governance]] rules are an attempt to mitigate this tendency.

== Studies of hierarchical organizations ==
The [[organizational development]] theorist [[Elliott Jacques]] identified a special role for hierarchy in his concept of [[requisite organization]]. 
 
The [[iron law of oligarchy]], introduced by [[Robert Michels]], describes the inevitable tendency of hierarchical organizations to become [[oligarchy|oligarchic]] in their decision making.

[[Hierarchiology]] is the term coined by Dr. Laurence J. Peter, originator of the [[Peter principle|Peter Principle]] described in his humorous book of the same name, to refer to the study of hierarchical organizations and the behavior of their members.

{{quote|Having formulated the Principle, I discovered that I had inadvertently founded a new science, hierarchiology, the study of hierarchies. The term hierarchy was originally used to describe the system of church government by priests graded into ranks. The contemporary meaning includes any organization whose members or employees are arranged in order of rank, grade or class. Hierarchiology, although a relatively recent discipline, appears to have great applicability to the fields of public and private administration.|Dr. [[Laurence J. Peter]] and [[Raymond Hull]]|''[[The Peter Principle]]: Why Things Always Go Wrong''}}

[[The IRG Solution - hierarchical incompetence and how to overcome it]] argued that hierarchies were inherently incompetent, and were only able to function due to large amounts of informal [[lateral communication]] fostered by private informal networks.

==Criticism and alternatives==
In the work of diverse theorists such as [[William James]] (1842–1910), [[Michel Foucault]] (1926–1984) and [[Hayden White]], important critiques of hierarchical epistemology are advanced. James famously asserts in his work &quot;Radical Empiricism&quot; that clear distinctions of type and category are a constant but unwritten goal of scientific reasoning, so that when they are discovered, success is declared. But if aspects of the world are organized differently, involving inherent and intractable ambiguities, then scientific questions are often considered unresolved. A hesitation to declare success upon the discovery of ambiguities leaves heterarchy at an artificial and subjective disadvantage in the scope of human knowledge. This bias is an artifact of an aesthetic or pedagogical preference for hierarchy, and not necessarily an expression of objective observation.

Hierarchies and hierarchical thinking has been criticized by many people, including [[Susan McClary]] and one political philosophy which is vehemently opposed to hierarchical organization: [[anarchism]] is generally opposed to hierarchical organization in any form of human relations. [[Heterarchy]] is the most commonly proposed alternative to hierarchy and this has been combined with [[responsible autonomy]] by [[Gerard Fairtlough]] in his work on [[Triarchy]] theory.

Amidst constant innovation in information and communication technologies, hierarchical authority structures are giving way to greater decision-making latitude for individuals and more flexible definitions of job activities and this new style of work presents a challenge to existing organizational forms, with some research studies contrasting traditional organizational forms against groups that operate as online communities that are characterized by personal motivation and the satisfaction of making one's own decisions.&lt;ref&gt;Zhao, Rosson, Rosson (2007). The Future of Work: What Does Online Community Have to Do with It? 40th Annual Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences (HICSS'07)&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Authoritarianism]]
* [[Command hierarchy]]
* [[Flat organization]]
* [[Matrix management]]
* [[Hierarchical incompetence]]
* ''[[The Nature of the Firm]]''
* [[Reverse hierarchy]]
* [[Corporate governance]]
* [[Social hierarchy]]
* [[Anarchism]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Aspects of organizations}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Hierarchical Organization}}
[[Category:Hierarchy]]
[[Category:Management]]
[[Category:Government]]
[[Category:Corporate governance]]
[[Category:Bureaucratic organization]]

[[cs:Hierarchická organizace]]
[[fr:Structure du pouvoir]]
[[ru:Иерархическая организация]]
[[sv:Linjeorganisation]]</text>
      <sha1>50mvixvg7t5duzmgudgjnodincact9r</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
