<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>History of terrorism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6999780</id>
    <revision>
      <id>517154816</id>
      <parentid>515890430</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-11T07:53:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Edward</username>
        <id>4261</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>link [[concession (politics)|political concessions]] using [[User:Edward/Find link|Find link]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="99847">{{Lead too short|date=October 2010}}
{{POV|date=August 2011}}
{{terrorism}}

The '''history of terrorism''' is a history of well-known and historically significant individuals, entities, and incidents associated, whether rightly or wrongly, with [[terrorism]]. Scholars agree that terrorism is a disputed term, and very few of those labelled terrorists describe themselves as such. It is common for opponents in a violent conflict to describe the other side as terrorists.&lt;ref name=tws11janbcvc&gt;{{cite news
|author= Paul Reynolds, quoting David Hannay, Former UK ambassador
|title= UN staggers on road to reform
|quote= This would end the argument that one man's terrorist is another man's freedom fighter...
|publisher= BBC News
|date= 14 September 2005
|url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/4244842.stm
|accessdate= 2010-01-11
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Those called terrorists can often be referred to as militants, paramilitaries, guerrillas, resistance movements or freedom fighters. However, they are united in the range of tactics they commonly employ which involves non-systemic covert or semi-covert warfare, driven by an ideological basis often political religious or socially based. They often seek to use propaganda of the deed to cause a psychological impact alongside the actions themselves to drive the aspired change.

==Definition==
{{See also|Definition of terrorism}}

Though many have been proposed, there is no consensus definition of the term &quot;terrorism.&quot;&lt;ref name=Record-p6-fn11&gt;Jeffrey Record. [http://www.strategicstudiesinstitute.army.mil/Pubs/Display.Cfm?pubID=207 Bounding the Global War on Terrorism], December 1, 2003, ISBN 1-58487-146-6. p. 6 (page 12 of the PDF document) citing in footnote 11: Walter Laqueur, ''The New Terrorism: Fanaticism and the Arms of Mass Destruction'', New York: Oxford University Press, 1999, p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Angus Martyn, [http://www.aph.gov.au/library/Pubs/CIB/2001-02/02cib08.htm The Right of Self-Defence under International Law-the Response to the Terrorist Attacks of 11 September], Australian Law and Bills Digest Group, Parliament of Australia Web Site, February 12, 2002&lt;/ref&gt; This in part derives from the fact that the term is politically and emotionally charged, “a word with intrinsically negative connotations that is generally applied to one's enemies and opponents.”&lt;ref name=&quot;Hoffman-1998-p32&quot;&gt;Hoffman (1998), p. 32, See review in The [[New York Times]][http://www.nytimes.com/books/first/h/hoffman-terrorism.html Inside Terrorism]&lt;/ref&gt; Listed below are some of the historically important understandings of terror and terrorism, and enacted but non-universal definitions of the term:
&lt;!-- Listed oldest to newest --&gt;
*'''1795'''. &quot;Government intimidation during the Reign of Terror in France.&quot; The general sense of &quot;systematic use of terror as a policy&quot; was first recorded in English in 1798.&lt;ref&gt;[http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/terrorism]&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''1916'''. [[Gustave LeBon]]: “Terrorization has always been employed by revolutionaries no less than by kings, as a means of impressing their enemies, and as an example to those who were doubtful about submitting to them....&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Gustave LeBon, The Psychology of the Great War, 1916, p. 391. Google Books: [http://books.google.com/books?id=7KcMAAAAYAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=%22The+Psychology+of+the+Great+War%22&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=0&amp;ei=aDi2S_f8LojIMoeDjaQP&amp;cd=1#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''1937'''. League of Nations convention language: &quot;All criminal acts directed against a State and intended or calculated to create a state of terror in the minds of particular persons or a group of persons or the general public.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=9nH0kSUMwGIC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_v2_summary_r&amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false from Criminology, by Larry Siegel, p. 328. Google Books]&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''1987'''. A definition proposed by [[Iran]] at an international Islamic conference on terrorism: “Terrorism is an act carried out to achieve an inhuman and corrupt ''(mufsid)'' objective, and involving [a] threat to security of any kind, and violation of rights acknowledged by religion and mankind.” &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.justresponse.net/defining_terrorism.html]&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''1988'''. A proposed academic consensus definition: &quot;Terrorism is an anxiety-inspiring method of repeated violent action, employed by (semi-) clandestine individual, group or state actors, for idiosyncratic, criminal or political reasons, whereby - in contrast to assassination - the direct targets of violence are not the main targets. The immediate human victims of violence are generally chosen randomly (targets of opportunity) or selectively (representative or symbolic targets) from a target population, and serve as message generators.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;un&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.unodc.org/unodc/terrorism_definitions.html
 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20070129121539/http://www.unodc.org/unodc/terrorism_definitions.html
 |archivedate=2007-01-29
 |title=Definitions of Terrorism
 |publisher=[[United Nations]]
 |accessdate=2007-07-10
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''1989'''. [[United States of America|United States]]: premeditated, politically motivated violence perpetrated against noncombatant targets by sub-national groups or clandestine agents.&lt;ref&gt;U.S. Code Title 22, Ch.38, Para. 2656f(d)&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''1992'''. A definition proposed by [[Alex P. Schmid]] to the United Nations Crime Branch: &quot;Act of Terrorism = Peacetime Equivalent of War Crime.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=9nH0kSUMwGIC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_v2_summary_r&amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false Criminology, by Larry Siegel, p. 328. Google Books]&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''2002'''. [[European Union]]: &quot;. . . given their nature or context, [acts which] may seriously damage a country or an international organisation where committed with the aim of seriously intimidating a population.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Art. 1 of the Framework Decision on Combating Terrorism (2002)&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''2003'''. India: Referencing Schmid's 1992 proposal, the [[Supreme Court of India]] described terrorist acts as the &quot;peacetime equivalents of war crimes.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Schmid's definition of terrorism was adopted in a 2003 ruling (Madan Singh vs. State of Bihar); See http://www.sacw.net/hrights/judgementjehanabad.doc&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''2008'''. Carsten Bockstette, a German military officer serving at the [[George C. Marshall Center for European Security Studies]], proposed the following definition: “political violence in an [[asymmetrical conflict]] that is designed to induce terror and psychic fear (sometimes indiscriminate) through the violent [[victimisation|victimization]] and destruction of [[noncombatant]] [[Targeting (warfare)|targets]] (sometimes iconic symbols).&quot;&lt;ref name=Bockstette2008&gt;{{cite journal | author = Bockstette, Carsten | year = 2008 | title = Jihadist Terrorist Use of Strategic Communication Management Techniques | issue = 20 | url = http://www.marshallcenter.org/mcpublicweb/MCDocs/files/College/F_ResearchProgram/occPapers/occ-paper_20-en.pdf | accessdate = 2009-01-01 | journal = George C. Marshall Center Occasional Paper Series | issn = 1863-6039|format=PDF}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early terrorism==
{{Expand section|date=August 2011}}
[[File:Asabah2.jpg|thumb|right|Artistic rendering of [[Hassan-i Sabbah]].]]Scholars dispute whether the roots of terrorism date back to the 1st century and the [[Sicarii Zealots]], to the 11th century and the Al-[[Hashshashin]], to the 19th century and [[Narodnaya Volya (organization)|Narodnaya Volya]], or to other eras.&lt;ref name=&quot;cdi.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.cdi.org/friendlyversion/printversion.cfm?documentID=1502 History of Terrorism article by Mark Burgess]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hoffman, Bruce. ''Inside Terrorism''. New York: Columbia University Press, 1988. p. 17&lt;/ref&gt; The Sicarii and Hashshashin are described below, while the Narodnaya Volya is discussed in the 19th Century sub-section. Other pre-Reign of Terror historical events sometimes associated with terrorism are the [[Gunpowder Plot]], an attempt to destroy the English [[Palace of Westminster|Parliament]] in 1605,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.berr.gov.uk/fireworks/download/FW1434_Keystage2_07.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Boston Tea Party]], an attack on British property by the [[Sons of Liberty]] in 1773, three years prior to the [[American Revolution]].

During the [[1st century AD]], the [[Zealotry|Jewish Zealots]] in [[Judaea Province]] rebelled, killing prominent collaborators with Roman rule.&lt;ref name=&quot;cdi.org&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hoffman, Bruce. ''Inside Terrorism''. New York: Columbia University Press, 1988. p. 83&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Chaliand, Gerard. ''The History of Terrorism: From Antiquity to al Qaeda''. Berkeley: University of California Press, 2007. p.56&lt;/ref&gt; In 6 CE, according to contemporary historian [[Josephus]], [[Judas of Galilee]] formed a small and more extreme offshoot of the Zealots, the [[Sicarii]] (&quot;dagger men&quot;).&lt;ref name=&quot;Chaliand, Gerard 2007. p.68&quot;/&gt; Their efforts also directed against Jewish &quot;collaborators,&quot; including temple priests, Sadducees, Herodians, and other wealthy elites.&lt;ref&gt;Hoffman, Bruce. ''Inside Terrorism''. New York: Columbia University Press, 1988. p. 167&lt;/ref&gt; According to Josephus, the Sicarii would hide short daggers under their cloaks, mingle with crowds at large festivals, murder their victims, and then disappear into the panicked crowds. Their most successful assassination was of the high priest Jonathan.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chaliand, Gerard 2007. p.68&quot;/&gt;

In the late 11th century AD, the [[Hashshashin]] (a.k.a. the Assassins) arose, an offshoot of the [[Ismā'īlī]] sect of [[Shia]] [[Muslim]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rapoport, David 1984. p.658&quot;&gt;Rapoport, David. &quot;Fear and Trembling: Terrorism in Three Religious Traditions.&quot; ''Ameaican Political Science Review'', 1984. p.658&lt;/ref&gt; Led by [[Hassan-i Sabbah]] and opposed to [[Fatimid]] rule, the Hashshashin militia seized Alamut and other fortress strongholds across Persia.&lt;ref&gt;Willey, Peter. ''The Castles of the Assassins''. New York: Linden Press, 2001. p.19&lt;/ref&gt; Hashshashin forces were too small to challenge enemies militarily, so they assassinated city governors and military commanders in order to create alliances with militarily powerful neighbors. For example, they killed Janah al-Dawla, ruler of [[Homs]], to please [[Ridwan of Aleppo]], and assassinated [[Mawdud]], [[Seljuq dynasty|Seljuk]] emir of [[Mosul]], as a favor to the regent of [[Damascus]].&lt;ref&gt;Daftary, Farhad. ''The Assassin Legends: Myths of the Isma'ilis''. London: I. B. Tauris, 1995. p.42&lt;/ref&gt; The Hashshashin also carried out assassinations as retribution.&lt;ref&gt;Hodgson, Marshall G. S. ''The Secret Order of Assassins: The Struggle of the Early Nizari Ismai'lis Against the Islamic World''. University of Pennsylvania Press, 2005. p.83&lt;/ref&gt; Under some definitions of terrorism, such [[assassinations]] do not qualify as terrorism, since killing a political leader does not intimidate political enemies or inspire revolt.&lt;ref name=&quot;cdi.org&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Chaliand, Gerard 2007. p.68&quot;&gt;Chaliand, Gerard. ''The History of Terrorism: From Antiquity to al Qaeda''. Berkeley: University of California Press, 2007. p.68&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hoffman, Bruce. ''Inside Terrorism''. New York: Columbia University Press, 1988. p. 84&lt;/ref&gt;

==19th century==
[[File:McKinley last photo.jpg|170px|left|thumb|McKinley shortly before his assassination.]]
Terrorism was associated with the [[Reign of Terror]] in France until the mid-19th century,&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes.com&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2007/10/28/opinion/28furstenberg.html?em&amp;ex=1193803200&amp;en=62eaa390a911d2d4&amp;ei=5087%0A | work=The New York Times | title=Bush's Dangerous Liaisons | first=François | last=Furstenberg | date=October 28, 2007 | accessdate=May 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; when the term began to be associated with non-governmental groups.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/recent/sept_11/changing_faces_02.shtml&lt;/ref&gt; [[Anarchism]], often in league with rising [[nationalism]], was the most prominent ideology linked with terrorism.&lt;ref&gt;The Dynamite Club by John Merriman&lt;/ref&gt; Attacks by various anarchist groups led to the assassination of a Russian [[Tsar]] and a [[William McKinley assassination|U.S. President]].&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt;[http://www.terrorism-research.com/history/early.php Early History of Terrorism&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 19th century, powerful, stable, and affordable explosives were developed, and the gap closed between the firepower of the state and dissidents.&lt;ref&gt;Chaliand, Gerard. ''The History of Terrorism: From Antiquity to al Qaeda''. Berkeley: University of California Press, 2007. p.124&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc.co.uk&quot;&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/recent/sept_11/changing_faces_02.shtml Adam Roberts on new weapon technologies available to anarchists]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Dynamite]], in particular, inspired American and French anarchists and was central to their strategic thinking.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;A History of Terrorism’’, by Walter Laqueur, Transaction Publishers, 2000, ISBN 0-7658-0799-8, p. 92 [http://books.google.com/books?id=RlqQHKpLfL8C&amp;dq=dynamite+terrorism+history&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s]&lt;/ref&gt;

In mid-19th century Russia, many grew impatient with the slow pace of Tsarist reforms, and [[anarchists]] such as [[Mikhail Bakunin]] maintained that progress was impossible without violence.&lt;ref&gt;Chaliand, Gerard. ''The History of Terrorism: From Antiquity to al Qaeda''. Berkeley: University of California Press, 2007. p.116&lt;/ref&gt; Founded in 1878 and inspired by Bakunin and others, [[Narodnaya Volya (organization)|Narodnaya Volya]] used dynamite-packed bombs to kill Russian state officials, in an effort to incite state retribution and mobilize the populace against the government.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hoffman, Bruce 1988. p. 5&quot;&gt;Hoffman, Bruce. ''Inside Terrorism''. New York: Columbia University Press, 1988. p. 5&lt;/ref&gt; Inspired by Narodnaya Volya, several nationalist groups in the ailing Ottoman Empire began using violence against public figures in the 1890s. These included the [[Hunchakian Revolutionary Party]], the [[Armenian Revolutionary Federation]], and the [[Internal Macedonian Revolutionary Organization]] (IMRO).&lt;ref name=&quot;Ross, Jeffrey Ian 2006. p.34&quot;&gt;Ross, Jeffrey Ian. ''Political Terrorism: An Interdisciplinary Approach''. New York: Peter Lang Press, 2006. p.34&lt;/ref&gt;

===The United States===
[[File:Kkk-carpetbagger-cartoon.jpg|thumb|right|A cartoon threatening that the KKK will [[lynching in the United States|lynch]] [[carpetbagger]]s, in the ''[[Independent Monitor]]'', [[Tuscaloosa, Alabama]], 1868.]]
In the 1850s, [[John Brown (abolitionist)|John Brown]] (1800–1859) was an [[abolitionist]] who advocated and practiced armed opposition to [[slavery]]. Brown led a series of attacks between 1856 and 1859, the most famous in 1859 against the [[Harpers Ferry Armory|armory]] at [[Harpers Ferry, West Virginia|Harpers Ferry]]. Local forces soon recaptured the fort and Brown was tried and executed for [[treason]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/04/22/AR2005042201172_pf.html | work=The Washington Post | title=The Good Terrorist | first=David W. | last=Blight | accessdate=May 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; A biographer of Brown has written that his purpose was &quot;to force the nation into a new political pattern by creating terror.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Otto Scott, ''The Secret Six: John Brown and the Abolitionist Movement'' (Murphys, Calif.: Uncommon Books, 1979, 1983), 3.&lt;/ref&gt;

After the [[U.S. Civil War|Civil War]], on December 24, 1865, six [[Confederate States of America|Confederate]] veterans created the [[Ku Klux Klan]] (KKK).&lt;ref&gt;Horn, 1939, p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt; The KKK used violence, lynching, murder and acts of intimidation such as [[cross burning]] to oppress in particular [[African American]]s, and created a sensation with its masked forays' dramatic nature.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jackson 1992 ed., pp. 241-242&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fbi.gov/filelink.html?file=/publications/terror/terror2000_2001.pdf|title=Terrorism 2000/2001|accessdate=2009-03-08}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; The group's politics are generally perceived as [[white supremacy]], [[anti-Semitism]], [[racism]], [[anti-Catholicism]], and [[Nativism (politics)|nativism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Jackson 1992 ed., pp. 241-242&quot;&gt;Jackson 1992 ed., pp. 241-242.&lt;/ref&gt; A KKK founder boasted that it was a nationwide organization of 550,000 men and that it could muster 40,000 Klansmen within five days' notice, but as a secret or &quot;[[Invisible dictatorship|invisible]]&quot; group with no membership rosters, it was difficult to judge the Klan's actual size. The KKK has at times been politically powerful, and at various times controlled the governments of [[Tennessee]], [[Oklahoma]], and [[South Carolina]], in addition to several legislatures in [[Southern United States|the South]].{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}}

===Europe===
In 1867 the [[Irish Republican Brotherhood]], a revolutionary Irish nationalist group,&lt;ref&gt;Irish Freedom, by Richard English Publisher: Pan Books (2 Nov 2007), ISBN 0-330-42759-8 p179&lt;/ref&gt; carried out attacks in England.&lt;ref&gt;Irish Freedom, by Richard English Publisher: Pan Books (2 Nov 2007), ISBN 0-330-42759-8 p. 180&lt;/ref&gt; Writer Richard English has referred to such attacks as the first acts of &quot;[[Irish republicanism|republican]] terrorism,&quot; which would became a recurrent feature of [[British history|British]] and [[Irish history]]. The group is considered a precursor to the [[Irish Republican Army]].&lt;ref&gt;Irish Freedom, by Richard English Publisher: Pan Books (2 Nov 2007), ISBN 0-330-42759-8 p3&lt;/ref&gt; The first police unit to combat terrorism [[Special Branch]],&lt;ref&gt;Secret War Exhibition, Imperial War Museum London&lt;/ref&gt; or Special Irish Branch, as it was known, was a unit of London's [[Metropolitan Police]] formed in March 1883 to combat the Irish Republican Brotherhood. The name became Special Branch as the unit's remit widened.

[[File:I Grinevizky.jpg|170px|thumb|left|[[Ignaty Gryniewietsky]].]]
Europeans invented the &quot;[[Propaganda of the deed]]&quot; (or &quot;propaganda by the deed,&quot; from the [[French language|French]] ''propagande par le fait'') theory, a concept that advocates physical [[violence]] or other provocative public acts against political enemies in order to inspire mass rebellion or [[revolution]]. One of the first individuals associated with this concept was the Italian revolutionary [[Carlo Pisacane]] (1818–1857), who wrote in his &quot;Political Testament&quot; (1857) that &quot;ideas spring from deeds and not the other way around.&quot; [[Anarchist]] [[Mikhail Bakunin]] (1814–1876), in his &quot;Letters to a Frenchman on the Present Crisis&quot; (1870) stated that &quot;we must spread our principles, not with words but with deeds, for this is the most popular, the most potent, and the most irresistible form of propaganda.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://marxists.org/reference/archive/bakunin/works/1870/letter-frenchman.htm &quot;Letter to a Frenchman on the Present Crisis&quot; (1870) by Mikhail Bakunin]&lt;/ref&gt; The phrase itself was popularized by the French [[anarchist]] [[Paul Brousse]] (1844–1912), who in 1877 cited as examples the 1871 [[Paris Commune]] and a workers' demonstration in [[Berne]] provocatively using the socialist red flag.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Anarchism: A Documentary History of Libertarian Ideas]]''&lt;/ref&gt; By the 1880s, the slogan had begun to be used to refer to bombings, [[regicide]]s and [[tyrannicide]]s. Reflecting this new understanding of the term, Italian anarchist [[Errico Malatesta]] in 1895 described &quot;propaganda by the deed&quot; (which he opposed the use of) as violent communal insurrections meant to ignite an imminent revolution.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.blackrosebooks.net/anarism1.htm &quot;Violence as a Social Factor,&quot; (1895) by Malatesta]:&lt;/ref&gt;

Founded in [[Russia]] in 1878, [[Narodnaya Volya (organization)|Narodnaya Volya]] (''Народная Воля'' in [[Russian language|Russian]]; ''People's Will'' in English) was a revolutionary anarchist group inspired by [[Sergei Nechayev]] and &quot;propaganda by the deed&quot; theorist Pisacane.&lt;ref name=&quot;cdi.org&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hoffman, Bruce 1988. p. 5&quot;/&gt; The group developed ideas—such as [[targeted killing]] of the 'leaders of oppression'—that were to become the hallmark of subsequent violence by small non-state groups, and they were convinced that the developing technologies of the age—such as the invention of dynamite, which they were the first anarchist group to make widespread use of&lt;ref&gt;''A History of Terrorism’’, by Walter Laqueur, Transaction Publishers, 2000, ISBN 0-7658-0799-8, p. 92 [http://books.google.com/books?id=RlqQHKpLfL8C&amp;dq=dynamite+terrorism+history&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s]&lt;/ref&gt;—enabled them to strike directly and with discrimination.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc.co.uk&quot;/&gt; Attempting to spark a popular revolt against Russia's Tsars, the group killed prominent political figures by gun and bomb, and on March 13, 1881, assassinated Russia's Tsar [[Alexander II of Russia|Alexander II]].&lt;ref name=&quot;cdi.org&quot;/&gt; The assassination, by a bomb that also killed the Tsar's attacker, [[Ignacy Hryniewiecki]], failed to spark the expected revolution, and an ensuing crackdown brought the group to an end.&lt;ref&gt;Chaliand, Gerard. ''The History of Terrorism: From Antiquity to al Qaeda''. Berkeley: University of California Press, 2007. p.133&lt;/ref&gt;

Individual Europeans also engaged in politically motivated violence. For example, in 1893, [[Auguste Vaillant]], a French [[Anarchism|anarchist]], threw a bomb in the French [[Chamber of Deputies]] in which one person was injured.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9502E3D91031E033A25755C0A9649C94659ED7CF The Guillotine's Sure Work; Details of the Execution of Vaillant, the Anarchist]&quot;, ''[[The New York Times]]'', 1984-02-06.&lt;/ref&gt; In reaction to Vaillant's bombing and other bombings and assassination attempts, the [[France|French]] government passed a set of [[law]]s restricting freedom of the press that were pejoratively known as the ''[[lois scélérates]]'' (&quot;villainous laws&quot;). From 1894 to 1896, President of France [[Marie Francois Carnot]], Prime Minister of Spain [[Antonio Cánovas del Castillo]], and Austria-Hungary Empress [[Elisabeth of Bavaria]] were killed by anarchists.

===The Ottoman Empire===
Several nationalist groups used violence against an Ottoman Empire in apparent decline. One was the [[Armenian Revolutionary Federation]] (in Armenian ''Dashnaktsuthium'', or &quot;The Federation&quot;), a revolutionary movement founded in Tiflis (Russian Transcaucasia) in 1890 by [[Christopher Mikaelian]]. Many members had been part of [[Narodnaya Volya (organization)|Narodnaya Volya]] or the [[Hunchakian Revolutionary Party]].&lt;ref&gt;Balakian, Peter. ''The Burning Tigris: The Armenian Genocide and America's Response.'' New York: Harper Perennial, 2004. p.104&lt;/ref&gt; The group published newsletters, smuggled arms, and hijacked buildings as it sought to bring in European intervention that would force the Ottoman Empire to surrender control of its Armenian territories.&lt;ref&gt;Chaliand, Gerard. ''The History of Terrorism: From Antiquity to al Qaeda''. Berkeley: University of California Press, 2007. p.193&lt;/ref&gt; On August 24, 1896, 17-year-old Babken Suni led twenty-six members in [[1896 Ottoman Bank Takeover|capturing the Imperial Ottoman Bank in Constantinople]]. The group demanded European intervention to stop the [[Hamidian Massacres]] and the creation of an Armenian state, but backed down on a threat to blow up the bank. An ensuing security crackdown destroyed the group.&lt;ref&gt;Hoffman, Bruce. ''Inside Terrorism''. New York: Columbia University Press, 2006. Page 51.&lt;/ref&gt;

Also inspired by Narodnaya Volya, the [[Internal Macedonian Revolutionary Organization]] (IMRO) was a revolutionary movement founded in 1893 by Hristo Tatarchev in the Ottoman-controlled Macedonian territories.&lt;ref&gt;Hoffman, Bruce. ''Inside Terrorism''. New York: Columbia University Press, 1988. p. 11&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kaplan, Robert. ''Balkan Ghosts: A Journey Through History''. New York: Picador, 2005. p.56&lt;/ref&gt; Through assassinations and by provoking uprisings, the group sought to coerce the Ottoman government into creating a Macedonian nation.&lt;ref&gt;Chaliand, Gerard. ''The History of Terrorism: From Antiquity to al Qaeda''. Berkeley: University of California Press, 2007. p.189&lt;/ref&gt; On July 20, 1903, the group incited the Ilinden uprising in the Ottoman villayet of Monastir. The IMRO declared the town's independence and sent demands to the [[European Powers]] that all of Macedonia be freed.&lt;ref&gt;Danforth, Loring. ''The Macedonian Conflict.'' Princeton University Press, 1997. p.87&lt;/ref&gt; The demands were ignored and Turkish troops crushed the 27,000 rebels in the town two months later.&lt;ref&gt;Kaplan, Robert. ''Balkan Ghosts: A Journey Through History''. New York: Picador, 2005. p.57&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early 20th century==
[[File:Portrait of Micheál Ó Coileáin.jpg|170px|thumb|right|Michael Collins, IRA leader]]
Revolutionary nationalism continued to motivate political violence in the 20th century, much of it directed against [[the British Empire]]{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}. The [[Irish Republican Army]] campaigned against the British in the 1910s and inspired the [[Zionism|Zionist]] groups [[Hagannah]], [[Irgun]] and [[Lehi (group)|Lehi]] to fight the British throughout the 1930s in the Palestine mandate.&lt;ref&gt;Bell, J. Bowyer. ''Terror Out of Zion: Irgun Zvai Leumi, Lehi and the Palestine Underground, 1929-1949''. Avon, 1985. p.14&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://guardian.150m.com/palestine/jewish-terrorism.htm]&lt;/ref&gt; Like the IRA and the Zionist groups, the [[Muslim Brotherhood]] used bombings and assassinations to try to free Egypt from British control.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lia, Brynjar 2006. p.53&quot;&gt;Lia, Brynjar. ''The Society of the Muslim Brothers in Egypt: The Rise of an Islamic Mass Movement 1928-1942''. Ithica Press, 2006. p.53&lt;/ref&gt;

===Europe===
Political assassinations continued into the 20th century, its first victim [[Umberto I of Italy]], killed in July 1900. Political violence became especially widespread in [[Imperial Russia]], and several ministers were killed in the opening years of the century. The highest ranking was prime minister [[Pyotr Stolypin]], killed in 1911 by a leftist radical.

On June 28, 1914, [[Archduke Franz Ferdinand of Austria]], heir to the [[Austria-Hungary|Austro-Hungarian]] throne, and his wife, [[Sophie, Duchess of Hohenberg]], were shot and killed in [[Sarajevo]], capital of [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]], by [[Gavrilo Princip]], one of a group of six assassins. The assassinations produced widespread shock across Europe, setting in motion a series of events which led to [[World War I]].

In an action called the [[Easter Rising]] or [[Easter Rebellion]], on April 24, 1916, members of the [[Irish Volunteers]] and [[Irish Citizen Army]] seized the [[General Post Office (Dublin)|Dublin General Post Office]] and several other buildings, proclaiming an independent Irish Republic.&lt;ref&gt;Chaliand, Gerard. ''The History of Terrorism: From Antiquity to al Qaeda''. Berkeley: University of California Press, 2007. p.185&lt;/ref&gt; The rebellion failed militarily but was a success for [[physical force Irish republicanism]], leaders of the uprising becoming Irish heroes after their eventual execution by the British government.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/british/easterrising/aftermath/af01.shtml BBC retrospective on the Easter Rising]&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly after the rebellion, [[Michael Collins (Irish leader)|Michael Collins]] and others founded the [[Irish Republican Army]] (IRA), which from 1916 to 1923 carried out numerous attacks against symbols of British power. For example, it attacked over 300 police stations simultaneously just before Easter 1920,&lt;ref&gt;Chaliand, p.185: &quot;Just before Easter 1920, the IRA simultaneously attacked more than 300 police stations...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; and, in November 1920, publicly killed a dozen police officers and burned down the Liverpool docks and warehouses, an action that came to be known as [[Bloody Sunday (1920)|Bloody Sunday]].&lt;ref&gt;Hart, Peter. ''Mick: The Real Michael Collins''. p.241&lt;/ref&gt; After years of warfare, London agreed to the 1921 Anglo-Irish treaty creating a free Irish state encompassing 26 of the island's 32 counties.&lt;ref&gt;Coogan, Tim. ''Michael Collins: The Man Who Made Ireland.'' New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2002. p.92&lt;/ref&gt; IRA tactics were an inspiration to other groups, including the [[British Mandate of Palestine|Palestine Mandate]]'s [[Zionism|Zionists]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Colin Shindler p.177&quot;&gt;Colin Shindler, ''The Land Beyond Promise:Israel, Likud and the Zionist Dream'', I.B.Tauris, 2001 p.177&lt;/ref&gt; and to British special operations during World War II.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;&gt;Hugh Dalton letter to Lord Halifax 2/7/1940&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;thefirstpost.co.uk&quot;&gt;http://www.thefirstpost.co.uk/5754,opinion,how-churchill-helped-britain-perfect-terrorism article by Matthew Carr Author The Infernal Machine: A History of Terrorism&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Bedouins]] seized French planes during the 1920s.&lt;ref name=Time77&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,945801-5,00.html TERRORISTS: War Without Boundaries Time Magazine October 31, 1977 issue]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Middle East===

Following the [[1929 Hebron massacre]] of sixty-seven Jewish settlers in the [[British Mandate of Palestine]], the [[Zionism|Zionist]] settlers militia [[Haganah]] transformed itself into a paramilitary force. In 1931, however, a more militant [[Irgun]] broke away from Haganah, objecting to Haganah's policy of [[Havlagah|restraint]] toward Arabs fighting Jewish settlers.&lt;ref&gt;Chaliand, Gerard. ''The History of Terrorism: From Antiquity to al Qaeda''. Berkeley: University of California Press, 2007. P. 212-213.&lt;/ref&gt; Founded by [[Avraham Tehomi]],&lt;ref&gt;Zadka, Saul. ''Blood in Zion: How the Jewish Guerrillas Drove the British Out of Palestine.'' London: Brassey Press, 2003. P. 42.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Juergensmeyer, Mark. ''Terror in the Mind of God: The Global Rise of Religious Violence. '' Berkeley, University of California Press, 2001. P. 64.&lt;/ref&gt; Irgun sought to aggressively defend Jews from Arab attacks. Its tactic of attacking Arab communities, including the bombing a crowded Arab market, is considered among the first examples of terrorism directed against civilians.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hoffman, Bruce 1988. P. 26.&quot;&gt;Hoffman, Bruce. ''Inside Terrorism''. New York: Columbia University Press, 1988. P. 26.&lt;/ref&gt; After the British restricted Jewish immigration to Palestine in 1939, the Irgun began a campaign against Bitish rule by assassinating police, capturing British government buildings and arms, and sabotaging British railways.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sachar, Howard 2007. P. 247.&quot;&gt;Sachar, Howard. ''A History of Israel: From the Rise of Zionism to Our Time''. New York: Knopf, 2007. P. 247.&lt;/ref&gt;  Irgun's best known attack was the [[King David Hotel bombing|1946 bombing of the King David Hotel]] in Jerusalem, parts of which housed the headquarters of the British civil and military administrations. Ninety-one people were killed and forty-six injured in what was the most deadly attack during the Mandate era.&lt;ref name=&quot;tclarke81&quot;&gt;[[Thurston Clarke|Clarke, Thurston]]. ''By Blood and Fire'', G. P. Puttnam's Sons, New York, 1981&lt;/ref&gt; After the creation of Israel in 1948, Menachem Begin (Irgun leader from 1943 to 1948) transformed the group into the political party which later became part of [[Likud]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Howard Sachar]]: '[['A History of the State of Israel]]'', pps{{Clarify|date=September 2011}} 265-266&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:King david hotel bombing1.jpg|170px|thumb|The [[King David Hotel]] after the 1946 bombing]]
Operating in the [[British Mandate of Palestine]] in the 1930s, [[Izz ad-Din al-Qassam]] organized and established the [[Black Hand (Palestine)|Black Hand]], an anti-Zionist militia. He recruited and arranged military training for peasants, and by 1935 had enlisted between 200 and 800 men. Al-Qassam obtained a [[fatwa]] from Shaykh [[Badr al-Din al-Taji al-Hasani]], the [[Mufti]] of [[Damascus]], authorizing armed resistance against the British and Jews of Palestine.  Black Hand cells were equipped with bombs and firearms, which they used to kill Zionist settlers.&lt;ref name=segev&gt;{{cite book |last=Segev |first=Tom |authorlink=Tom Segev |title=One Palestine, Complete |year=1999 |publisher=Metropolitan Books |isbn=0-8050-4848-0 |pages=360–362 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Shai Lachman, &quot;Arab Rebellion and Terrorism in Palestine 1929-39: The Case of Sheikh Izz al-Din al-Qassam and His Movement&quot;, in Zionism and Arabism in Palestine and Israel, edited by Elie Kedourie and Sylvia G. Haim, Frank Cass, London, 1982, p. 55.&lt;/ref&gt; Although al-Qassam's revolt was unsuccessful in his lifetime, many organizations gained inspiration from his revolutionary example.&lt;ref name=segev/&gt; He became a popular hero and an inspiration to subsequent Arab militants, who in the [[1936–1939 Arab revolt in Palestine|1936-1939 Arab Revolt]], called themselves [[Qassamiyun]], followers of al-Qassam.

[[Lehi (group)|Lehi]] (''Lohamei Herut Yisrael'', a.k.a. &quot;Freedom Fighters for Israel&quot;, a.k.a. Stern Gang) was a [[Revisionist Zionism|revisionist Zionist]] group that splintered off from [[Irgun]] in 1940.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hoffman, Bruce 1988. p. 26&quot;&gt;Hoffman, Bruce. ''Inside Terrorism''. New York: Columbia University Press, 1988. P. 26.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Abraham Stern]] formed Lehi from disaffected Irgun members after Irgun agreed to a truce with Britain in 1940.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sachar, Howard 2007. P. 247.&quot;/&gt; Lehi assassinated prominent politicians as a strategy. For example, on November 6, 1944, [[Lord Moyne]], the [[uK|British]] Minister of State for the Middle East, was assassinated.&lt;ref&gt;Chaliand, Gerard. ''The History of Terrorism: From Antiquity to al Qaeda''. Berkeley: University of California Press, 2007. P. 213.&lt;/ref&gt; The act was controversial among Zionist militant groups, [[Hagannah]] sympathizing with the British and launching [[the Hunting Season|a massive man-hunt]] against members of Lehi and Irgun. After Israel's 1948 founding, Lehi was formally dissolved and its members integrated into the [[Israeli Defense Forces]].&lt;ref&gt;Pedahzur, Ami. ''The Israeli Response to Jewish terrorism and violence. Defending Democracy''. New York: Manchester University Press, 2002. P. 77.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Elsewhere===
The first in-flight [[skyjacking]] took place in 1931, when a plane was commandeered by antiregime forces during a coup in Peru.&lt;ref name=Time77/&gt;

==World War II==
===The resistance movement in Europe===
Some of the tactics of the [[Resistance during World War II|guerrilla, partisan, and resistance movements]] organised and supplied by the Allies during World War II, according to historian M. R. D. Foot, can be considered terrorist.&lt;ref&gt;Resistance - An Analysis of European Resistance to Nazism 1940-1945, by M. R. D. Foot&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;John Keegan as quoted in The Irish War, by Tony Geraghty&lt;/ref&gt; [[Colin Gubbins]], a key leader within the British [[Special Operations Executive]] (SOE), made sure the organization drew much of its inspiration from the IRA.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;thefirstpost.co.uk&quot;/&gt; On the eve of D-Day, the SOE organised with the French resistance the complete destruction of the rail&lt;ref&gt;http://www.channel4.com/history/microsites/H/history/c-d/cross.html&lt;/ref&gt; and communication infrastructure of western France&lt;ref&gt;SOE in France. An Account of the Work of the British Special Operations Executive in France 1940-1944. By M. R. D. Foot (1966).&lt;/ref&gt; perhaps the largest coordinated attack of its kind in history{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}}. Allied supreme commander [[Dwight Eisenhower]] later wrote that &quot;the disruption of enemy rail communications, the harassing of German road moves and the continual and increasing strain placed on German security services throughout occupied Europe by the organised forces of Resistance, played a very considerable part in our complete and final victory&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/worldwars/wwtwo/soe_04.shtml]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Mid-20th century==
After World War II, largely successful [[anti-imperialism|anti-colonial]] campaigns were launched against the collapsing European empires, as many World War II resistance groups became militantly anti-colonial. The [[Viet Minh]], for example, which had fought against the Japanese, now fought the returning [[First Indochina War|French]] colonists. In the Middle East, the [[Muslim Brotherhood]] used bombings and assassinations against British rule in Egypt.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lia, Brynjar 2006. p.53&quot;/&gt; Also during the 1950s, the [[National Liberation Front (Algeria)|National Liberation Front]] (FLN) in French-controlled Algeria and the [[EOKA]] in British-controlled Cyprus waged [[guerrilla]] and open war against colonial powers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hoffman, Bruce 1988. p. 33&quot;&gt;Hoffman, Bruce. ''Inside Terrorism''. New York: Columbia University Press, 1988. p. 33&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:1964 Brinks Hotel bombing.JPG|thumb|Aftermath of the [[1964 Brinks Hotel bombing]] in Vietnam.]]

In the 1960s, inspired by [[Mao Zedong|Mao's]] Chinese revolution of 1949 and [[Fidel Castro|Castro's]] [[Cuban revolution]] of 1959, national independence movements in formerly colonized countries often fused nationalist and [[socialism|socialist]] impulses. This was the case with Spain's [[ETA]], the [[Front de libération du Québec]], and the [[Palestine Liberation Organization]]{{Clarify|date=April 2009}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chaliand, Gerard 2007. p.227&quot;&gt;Chaliand, Gerard. ''The History of Terrorism: From Antiquity to al Qaeda''. Berkeley: University of California Press, 2007. p.227&lt;/ref&gt;

In the late 1960s and 1970s violent [[left-wing politics|leftist]] groups were on the rise, sympathizing with [[Third World]] guerrilla movements and seeking to spark anti-capitalist revolt. Such groups included the [[Kurdistan Workers' Party|PKK]] in Turkey, Armenia's [[ASALA]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Chaliand, Gerard 2007. p.227&quot;/&gt; the [[Japanese Red Army]], the [[German Red Army Faction]], the [[Italian Red Brigades]], and, in the U.S., the [[Weather Underground]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://terrorism.about.com/od/originshistory/a/LeftWingTerror.htm]&lt;/ref&gt; Nationalist groups such as the [[Provisional Irish Republican Army|Provisional IRA]] and the [[Tamil tigers]] also began operations at this time.

Throughout the [[Cold War]], both the U.S. and the [[Soviet Union]] made extensive use of violent nationalist organizations to carry on a war by proxy. For example, Soviet and Chinese military advisers provided training and support to the [[Viet Cong]] during the [[Vietnam War]],&lt;ref&gt;Vietnam: A History, Stanley Karnow,1983&lt;/ref&gt; while the U.S. funded groups such as the [[Contras]] in [[Nicaragua]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.presidency.ucsb.edu/PS157/assignment%20files%20public/TOWER%20EXCERPTS.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Ironically, many [[Islamic Terrorism|violent Islamic militants]] of the late 20th and early 21st century had been funded in the 1980s by the US and the UK because they were fighting the USSR in [[Afghanistan]].&lt;ref&gt;The Power of Nightmares, BBC, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last = Crile| first = George| title = Charlie Wilson's War| publisher = Atlantic Monthly Press| year = 2004| pages = 111–112| isbn = 0-8021-4124-2 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Middle East===

Founded in 1928 as a nationalist social-welfare and political movement in British-controlled [[Egypt]], the [[Muslim Brotherhood]] in the late 1940s began to attack British soldiers and police stations.&lt;ref&gt;Lia, Brynjar. ''The Society of the Muslim Brothers in Egypt: The Rise of an Islamic Mass Movement 1928-1942''. Ithica Press, 2006. P. 35.&lt;/ref&gt; Founded and led by [[Hassan al-Banna]], it also assassinated politicians seen as collaborating with British rule,&lt;ref&gt;Chaliand, Gerard. ''The History of Terrorism: From Antiquity to al Qaeda''. Berkeley: University of California Press, 2007. P. 274.&lt;/ref&gt; most prominently Egyptian Prime Minister Nuqrashi in 1948.&lt;ref&gt;Mitchell, Richard. ''The Society of the Muslim Brothers''. Oxford, 1993. P. 74.&lt;/ref&gt; British rule was overthrown in a 1952 military coup, and shortly thereafter the Muslim Brotherhood went underground in the face of a massive crackdown.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Moderate Muslim Brotherhood.&quot; Robert S. Leiken &amp; Steven Brooke, ''Foreign Affairs Magazine''.&lt;/ref&gt; Though sometimes banned or otherwise oppressed, the group continues to exist in present-day Egypt.

The [[National Liberation Front (Algeria)|Front de Libération Nationale]] (FLN) was a nationalist group founded in French-controlled Algeria in 1954.&lt;ref&gt;Stora, Benjamin. ''Algeria, 1830-2000: A Short History''. Cornell University Press, 2004. P. 36.&lt;/ref&gt; The group was a large-scale resistance movement against French occupation, with alleged terrorism only part of its operations. The FLN leadership was inspired by the [[Viet Minh]] rebels who had made French troops withdraw from Vietnam.&lt;ref&gt;Galula, David. ''Pacification in Algeria, 1956-1958''. RAND Corporation Press, 2006. P. 14.&lt;/ref&gt; The FLN was one of the first anti-colonial groups to use large scale compliance violence. The FLN would establish control over a rural village and coerce its peasants to execute any French loyalists among them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hoffman, Bruce 1988. p. 33&quot;/&gt; On the night of October 31, 1954, in a coordinated wave of seventy bombings and shootings known as the [[Toussaint attacks]], the FLN attacked French military installations and the homes of Algerian loyalists.&lt;ref&gt;Chaliand, Gerard. ''The History of Terrorism: From Antiquity to al Qaeda''. Berkeley: University of California Press, 2007. P. 216.&lt;/ref&gt; In the following year, the group gained significant support for an uprising against loyalists in [[Philippeville]]. This uprising — and the heavy-handed response by the French — convinced many Algerians to support the FLN and the independence movement.{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}} The FLN eventually secured Algerian independence from France in 1962, and transformed itself into Algeria's ruling party.&lt;ref&gt;S. N. Millar, 'Arab Victory: Lessons from the Algerian War (1954–62)', British Army Review No 145 Autumn 2008, p. 49&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Connollystraße 31 - Gedenktafel.jpg|thumb|left|Plaque commemorating the eleven Israeli athletes killed during the 1972 Munich Olympics massacre.]]
[[Fatah]] was organized as a Palestinian nationalist group in 1954, and exists today as a political party in [[Palestine]]. In 1967 it joined the [[Palestine Liberation Organization]] (PLO), an umbrella organization for secular Palestinian nationalist groups formed in 1964. The PLO began its own armed operations in 1965.&lt;ref&gt;Rubin, Barry. ''Revolution Until Victory?: The Politics and History of the PLO''. Harvard University Press, 1996. P. 7. [http://books.google.com.ph/books?id=zbQKILIgAwQC&amp;dq=Revolution+Until+Victory%3F:+The+Politics+and+History+of+the+PLO&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=bn&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=jPC5SdTBH5z47AOjoZTuBA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ct=result#PPA7,M1].&lt;/ref&gt; The PLO's membership is made up of separate and possibly contending paramilitary and political factions, the largest of which are [[Fatah]], [[Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine]] (PFLP), and [[Democratic Front for the Liberation of Palestine]] (DFLP).&lt;ref&gt;Hoffman, Bruce. ''Inside Terrorism''. New York: Columbia University Press, 1988. P. 47.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;fas.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.fas.org/irp/world/para/plo.htm Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO)]&lt;/ref&gt; Factions of the PLO have advocated or carried out acts of terrorism.&lt;ref name=&quot;fas.org&quot;/&gt; [[Abu Iyad]] organized the Fatah splinter group [[Black September (group)|Black September]] in 1970; the group is best known for seizing eleven Israeli athletes as hostages at the September [[1972 Summer Olympics]] in Munich. All the athletes and five Black September operatives died during a gun battle with the West German police, in what was later known as the [[Munich massacre]].&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Simon. ''One Day in September: The Full Story of the 1972 Munich Olympics Massacre and the Israeli Revenge Operation''. Arcade, 2006. P. 32.&lt;/ref&gt; The PFLP was founded in 1967 by [[George Habash]],&lt;ref&gt;Hoffman, p. 46.&lt;/ref&gt; and on September 6, 1970, the group [[aircraft hijacking|hijacked]] three international passenger planes, landing two of them in Jordan and blowing up the third.&lt;ref&gt;Cobban, Helena.''The Palestinian Liberation Organisation: People, Power and Politics''. Cambridge, 1985. P. 147.&lt;/ref&gt; Fatah leader and PLO Chairman [[Yasser Arafat]] publicly renounced terrorism in December 1988 on behalf of the PLO, but Israel has stated it has proof that Arafat continued to sponsor terrorism until his death in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fas.org/irp/world/para/plo.htm Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO)] ''Federation of American Scientists''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cfr.org/publication/9515/terrorism_havens.html?breadcrumb=%2Fpublication%2Fpublication_list%3Fgroupby%3D0%26type%3Dbackgrounder%26filter%3D411 Terrorism Havens: Palestinian Authority] ''Council on Foreign Relations'' Updated December 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1974 [[Ma'alot massacre]] 22 [[Israel]]i high school students, aged 14–16, from [[Safed]] were killed by three members of the [[Democratic Front for the Liberation of Palestine]].&lt;ref name=Haaretz2007&gt;Khoury, Jack. [http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/833554.html &quot;U.S. filmmakers plan documentary on Ma'alot massacre&quot;], ''[[Haaretz]]'', March 7, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Before reaching the school, the trio shot and killed two Arab women, a Jewish man, his pregnant wife, and their 4 year old son, and wounded several others.&lt;ref name=Time1972&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,911276,00.html?iid=chix-sphere &quot;Bullets, Bombs and a Sign of Hope&quot;], ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'', May 27, 1974.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[People's Mujahedin of Iran]] (PMOI) or [[Mujahedin-e Khalq]], is a socialist Islamic group that has fought [[Iran]]'s government since the [[Khomeini revolution]]. The group was originally founded to oppose capitalism and what it perceived as western exploitation of Iran under the Shah.{{Citation needed|date=July 2009}} The group would go on to play an important role in the Shah's overthrow but was unable to capitalize on this in the following power vacuum. The group is suspected of having a membership of between 10,000 and 30,000. The group renounced violence in 2001 but remains a proscribed terror organization in Iran and the U.S. The EU, however, has removed the group from its terror list. The PMOI is accused of supporting other groups such as the [[Jundallah]].{{Citation needed|date=July 2009}}

The [[Armenian Secret Army for the Liberation of Armenia]] (ASALA) was founded in 1975 in [[Beirut]] during the [[Lebanese Civil War]] by [[Hagop Tarakchian]] and [[Hagop Hagopian]] with the help of sympathetic Palestinians. At the time, [[Turkey]] was in political turmoil, and Hagopian believed that the time was right to avenge the Armenians who died during the [[Armenian Genocide]] and to force the Turkish government to cede the territory of [[Wilsonian Armenia]] to establish a nation state also incorporating the [[Armenian Soviet Socialist Republic|Armenian SSR]]. In its [[Esenboga airport attack]], on 7 August 1982, two ASALA rebels opened fire on civilians in a waiting room at the [[Esenboga International Airport]] in [[Ankara]]. Nine people died and 82 were injured. By 1986, the ASALA had virtually ceased all attacks.&lt;ref&gt;Roy, Olivier. ''Turkey Today: A European Nation?'' P. 170.&lt;/ref&gt;

The &quot;Partiya Karkerên Kurdistan&quot; ([[Kurdistan Workers Party]] or PKK) was established in Turkey in 1978 as a Kurdish nationalist party. Founder [[Abdullah Ocalan]] was inspired by the [[Maoism|Maoist]] theory of [[people's war]], and like Algeria's FLN he advocated the use of compliance terror.{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}} The group seeks to create an independent Kurdish state consisting of parts of south-eastern Turkey, north-eastern [[Iraq]], north-eastern [[Syria]] and north-western [[Iran]]. In 1984, the PKK transformed itself into a paramilitary organisation and launched conventional attacks as well as bombings against Turkish governmental installations. In 1999, Turkish authorities captured Öcalan. He was tried in Turkey and sentenced to life imprisonment. The PKK has since gone through a series of name changes.&lt;ref name=csm&gt;{{cite news|title=Turkish Kurds: some back the state|work=[[Christian Science Monitor]]|date=2007-07-06|url=http://www.csmonitor.com/2007/0706/p06s02-wosc.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Europe===

Founded in 1959 and still active, the [[Euskadi Ta Askatasuna]] (or ETA ([[Basque language|Basque]] for &quot;Basque Homeland and Freedom&quot;, pronounced {{IPA-eu|ˈeta|}})) is an armed [[Basque nationalist]] separatist organization.&lt;ref&gt;Kurlansky, Mark. ''The Basque History of the World: The Story of a Nation''. New York: Penguin, 2001. P. 224.&lt;/ref&gt; Formed in response to General [[Francisco Franco]]'s suppression of the Basque language and culture, ETA evolved from an advocacy group for traditional Basque culture into an armed [[Marxism|Marxist]] group demanding Basque independence.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.goizargi.com/2003/queeselmlnv3.htm &quot;What is the MNLV (3)&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; Many ETA victims are government officials, the group's first known victim a police chief killed in 1968. In 1973 ETA operatives killed Franco's apparent successor, Admiral Luis Carrero Blanco, by planting an underground bomb under his habitual parking spot outside a Madrid church.&lt;ref&gt;Hoffman, Bruce. ''Inside Terrorism''. New York: Columbia University Press, 1988. P. 191.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1995, an ETA car bomb nearly killed Jose Maria Aznar, then the leader of the conservative Popular Party, and the same year investigators disrupted a plot to assassinate King Juan Carlos.&lt;ref&gt;Weinberg, Leonard. ''Global Terrorism: A Beginner's Guide''. New York: Oneworld, 2008. P. 43.&lt;/ref&gt; Efforts by Spanish governments to negotiate with the ETA have failed, and in 2003 the Spanish Supreme Court banned the Batasuna political party, which was determined to be the political arm of ETA.&lt;ref&gt;Chaliand, Gerard. ''The History of Terrorism: From Antiquity to al Qaeda''. Berkeley: University of California Press, 2007. P. 251.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Provisional Irish Republican Army]] (IRA) was an Irish nationalist movement founded in December 1969 when several militants including [[Seán Mac Stíofáin]] broke off from the [[Official IRA]] and formed a new organization.&lt;ref&gt;Chaliand, p. 250&lt;/ref&gt; Led by Mac Stíofáin in the early 1970s and by a group around [[Gerry Adams]] since the late 1970s, the Provisional IRA sought to create an all-island Irish state. Between 1969 and 1997, during a period known as [[the Troubles]], the group conducted an [[Provisional IRA campaign 1969-1997|armed campaign]], including bombings, gun attacks, assassinations and even a [[Downing Street mortar attack|mortar attack on 10 Downing Street]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cfr.org/publication/9240/#5]&lt;/ref&gt; On July 21, 1972, in an attack later known as [[Bloody Friday (1972)|Bloody Friday]], the group set off twenty-two bombs, killing nine and injuring 130. On July 28, 2005, the Provisional IRA Army Council announced an end to its armed campaign.&lt;ref&gt;Chaliand, p. 251&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Coogan, p. 356&lt;/ref&gt; The IRA is believed to have been a major exporter of arms to and provided military training to groups such as the [[FARC]] in Colombia&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/this-britain/suspected-ira-men-arrested-in-colombia-751521.html | work=The Independent | location=London | title=Suspected IRA men arrested in Colombia | first=Nigel | last=Morris | date=August 14, 2001 | accessdate=May 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the PLO.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/middleeast/israel/1387326/IRA-link-to-PLO-examined-in-hunt-for-deadly-sniper.html | work=The Daily Telegraph | location=London | title=IRA link to PLO examined in hunt for deadly sniper | first=Sean | last=Rayment | date=March 10, 2002 | accessdate=May 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the case of the latter there has been a long held solidarity movement, which is evident by the many murals around [[Belfast]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/home-news/as-three-men-go-before-a-colombian-judge-today-will-their-fate-seal-the-course-of-peace-in-ireland-607796.html | work=The Independent | location=London | title=As three men go before a Colombian judge today, will their fate seal the course of peace in Ireland? | first=David | last=McKittrick | date=October 4, 2002 | accessdate=May 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Ulrike Meinhof als junge Journalistin (retuschiert).jpg|thumb|right|150px|Ulrike Meinhof]]
The [[Red Army Faction]] (RAF) was a New Leftist group founded in 1968 by [[Andreas Baader]] and [[Ulrike Meinhof]] in [[West Germany]]. Inspired by [[Che Guevara]], Maoist socialism, and the [[Vietcong]], the group sought to raise awareness of the Vietnamese and Palestinian independence movements through kidnappings, taking embassies hostage, bank robberies, assassinations, bombings, and attacks on U.S. air bases. The group is best known for 1977's &quot;[[German Autumn]]&quot;. The buildup leading to [[German Autumn]] began on April 7, when the RAF shot Federal Prosecutor [[Siegfried Buback]]. On July 30, it shot [[Jurgen Ponto]], then head of the Dresdner Bank, in a failed kidnapping attempt; on September 5, the group kidnapped [[Hanns Martin Schleyer]] (a former SS officer and an important West German industrialist), executing him on October 19.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/7745705.stm | work=BBC News | title=Red Army Faction boss to be freed | date=November 24, 2008 | accessdate=May 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The hijacking of the [[Lufthansa]] jetliner &quot;[[Lufthansa Flight 181|Landshut]]&quot; by the [[PFLP]], a Palestinian group, is also considered to be part of German Autumn.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}

The [[Red Brigades]] were a New Leftist group founded by [[Renato Curcio]] and [[Alberto Franceschini]] in 1970 that sought to create a revolutionary state. The group carried out a series of bombings and kidnappings until Curcio and Franceschini were arrested in the mid-1970s. Their successor as leader, [[Mario Moretti]], led the group toward more militarized and violent actions, including the kidnapping of former Prime Minister [[Aldo Moro]] on March 16, 1978. Moro was killed 56 days later. This led to an all-out assault on the group by Italian law enforcement and security forces and condemnation from Italian left-wing radicals and even imprisoned ex-leaders of the Brigades. The group lost most of its social support and public opinion turned strongly against it. In 1984, the group split, the majority faction becoming the Communist Combatant Party (Red Brigades-PCC) and the minority faction reconstituting itself as the Union of Combatant Communists (Red Brigades-UCC). Members of these groups carried out a handful of assassinations before almost all were arrested in 1989.&lt;ref&gt;[[Ed Vulliamy]], [http://www.cambridgeclarion.org/press_cuttings/vinciguerra.p2.etc_graun_5dec1990.html Secret agents, freemasons, fascists... and a top-level campaign of political 'destabilisation'], ''[[The Guardian]]'', December 5, 1990&lt;/ref&gt;

===The Americas===
The [[Front de libération du Québec]] (FLQ) was a Marxist nationalist group that sought to create an independent, socialist [[Quebec]].&lt;ref&gt;Hoffman, p.16&lt;/ref&gt; [[Georges Schoeters]] founded the group in 1963 and was inspired by [[Che Guevara]] and Algeria's FLN.&lt;ref&gt;Chaliand, p.227&lt;/ref&gt; The group was accused of bombings, kidnappings, and assassinations of politicians, soldiers, and civilians.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.canadiansoldiers.com/history/domesticmissions/flqcrisis.htm See Canadian Soldier]&lt;/ref&gt; On October 5, 1970, the FLQ kidnapped [[James Richard Cross]], the British Trade Commissioner, and on October 10, the Minister of Labor and Vice-Premier of Quebec, [[Pierre Laporte]]. Laporte was killed a week later. After these events support for violence in order to attain Quebec independence declined, and support increased for the Parti Québécois, which took power in Quebec in 1976.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.com/index.cfm?PgNm=TCE&amp;Params=A1ARTA0003082 FLQ entry in the Canadian Encyclopedia]&lt;/ref&gt;

In Colombia [[Narcoterrorism|several paramilitary and guerrilla groups]] formed during the 1960s and afterwards. In 1983, President [[Fernando Belaúnde Terry]] of [[Peru]] described armed attacks on his nation's anti-narcotics police as &quot;[[narcoterrorism]]&quot;, i.e., which refers to &quot;violence waged by drug producers to extract [[concession (politics)|political concessions]] from the government.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://terrorism.about.com/od/n/g/Narcoterrorism.htm&lt;/ref&gt; [[Pablo Escobar]]'s ruthless violence in his dealings with the Colombian and Peruvian governments has been probably one of the best known and best documented examples of narcoterrorism.{{Citation needed|date=July 2009}} Paramilitary groups associated with narcoterrorism include the [[National Liberation Army (Colombia)|Ejército de Liberación Nacional]] (ELN), the [[Revolutionary Armed Forces of Colombia|Fuerzas Armadas Revolucionarias de Colombia]] (FARC), and the [[United Self-Defense Forces of Colombia|Autodefensas Unidas de Colombia]] (AUC). While the ELN and FARC were originally leftist revolutionary groups and the AUC was originally a right-wing paramilitary, all have conducted numerous attacks on civilians and civilian infrastructure, and the U.S. and some European governments consider them terrorist organizations.&lt;ref&gt;http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/site/en/oj/2005/l_340/l_34020051223en00640066.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.state.gov/s/ct/rls/fs/37191.htm Foreign Terrorist Organizations (FTOs)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Jewish Defense League]] (JDL) was founded in 1969 by Rabbi [[Meir Kahane]] in New York City, with its declared purpose the protection of Jews from harassment and [[antisemitism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;backgrounder&quot;&gt;[http://www.adl.org/extremism/jdl_chron.asp Anti-Defamation League on JDL]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Federal Bureau of Investigation]] statistics state that, from 1980 to 1985, 15 attacks the FBI classified as acts of terrorism were attempted in the U.S. by members of the JDL.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|title=The Achille Lauro Hijacking: Lessons in the Politics and Prejudice of Terrorism
|first=Michael K.
|last=Bohn
|page=67
|year=2004
|publisher=Brassey's Inc.}}
&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Terrorism Knowledge Base|National Consortium for the Study of Terror and Responses to Terrorism]] states that, during the JDL's first two decades of activity, it was an &quot;active terrorist organization.&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;backgrounder&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MIPT&quot;&gt;[http://www.start.umd.edu/start/data/tops/terrorist_organization_profile.asp?id=183 JDL group profile from ''National Consortium for the Study of Terror and Responses to Terrorism'']&lt;/ref&gt; Kahane later founded the far-right [[Israel]]i political party [[Kach and Kahane Chai|Kach]], which was banned from elections in Israel on the ground of racism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/1988/10/06/world/israel-bans-kahane-party-from-election.html | work=The New York Times | title=Israel Bans Kahane Party From Election | first=Joel | last=Brinkley | date=October 6, 1988 | accessdate=May 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The JDL's present-day website condemns all forms of terrorism.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.jdl.org/index.php/ideology-advocacy/anti-terrorism-racism/&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Fuerzas Armadas de Liberación Nacional Puertorriqueña|Fuerzas Armadas de Liberación Nacional]] (FALN, &quot;Armed Forces of National Liberation&quot;) is a nationalist group founded in [[Puerto Rico]] in 1974. Over the decade that followed the group used bombings and targeted killings of civilians and police in pursuit of an independent Puerto Rico. The FALN in 1975 took responsibility for four nearly simultaneous bombings in New York City.&lt;ref&gt;Gina M. Pérez. [http://www.encyclopedia.chicagohistory.org/pages/489.html ''Fuerzas Armadas de Liberación Nacional (FALN)'']. [http://www.encyclopedia.chicagohistory.org/ Encyclopedia of Chicago]. Retrieved on 2007-09-05&lt;/ref&gt; The United States [[Federal Bureau of Investigation]] (FBI) has classified the FALN as a terrorist organization.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.fbi.gov/congress/congress01/freeh051001.htm| title=Congressional testimony of Louis J. Freeh| publisher=Federal Bureau of Investigation| date= 2001-05-10| accessdate=2007-10-10}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Weather Underground]] (a.k.a. the Weathermen) began as a militant faction of the leftist [[Students for a Democratic Society (1960 organization)|Students for a Democratic Society]] (SDS) organization, and in 1969 took over the organization. Weathermen leaders, inspired by China's [[Maoism|Maoists]], the [[Black Panthers]], and the [[May 1968 in France|1968 student revolts in France]], sought to raise awareness of its revolutionary anti-capitalist and anti-[[Vietnam War]] platform by destroying symbols of government power. From 1969 to 1974 the Weathermen bombed corporate offices, police stations, and [[Washington, D.C.|Washington]] government sites such as the [[The Pentagon|Pentagon]]. After the end of the Vietnam War in 1975, most of the group disbanded.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Weather Underground&quot;&gt;''[[The Weather Underground]]'', produced by Carrie Lozano, directed by Bill Siegel and Sam Green, New Video Group, 2003, DVD.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Asia===
The [[Japanese Red Army]] was founded by [[Fusako Shigenobu]] in Japan in 1971 and attempted to overthrow the Japanese government and start a world revolution. Allied with the [[Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine]] (PFLP), the group committed assassinations, hijacked a commercial Japanese aircraft, and sabotaged a Shell oil refinery in Singapore. On May 30, 1972, [[Kōzō Okamoto]] and other group members launched a machine gun and grenade attack at Israel's Lod Airport in Tel Aviv, killing 26 people and injuring 80 others. Two of the three attackers then killed themselves with grenades.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tkb.org/Group.jsp?groupID=59 Japanese Red Army (JRA) Profile] The [[National Memorial Institute for the Prevention of Terrorism]] Terrorism Knowledge Base (online)&lt;/ref&gt;

Founded in 1976, the [[Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam]], (also called &quot;LTTE&quot; or Tamil Tigers) was a militant [[Tamil people|Tamil]] nationalist political and paramilitary organization based in northern [[Sri Lanka]].&lt;ref&gt;Richardson, John. ''Paradise Poisoned: Learning About Conflict, Terrorism and Development from Sri Lanka's Civil Wars''. International Center for Ethnic Studies, 2005. p.29&lt;/ref&gt; From its founding by [[Velupillai Prabhakaran]], it waged a [[secessionist]] resistance campaign that sought to create an independent Tamil state in the northern and eastern regions of [[Sri Lanka]].&lt;ref&gt;Hoffman, p.139&lt;/ref&gt; The conflict originated in measures the majority [[Sinhalese people|Sinhalese]] took that were perceived as attempts to marginalize the Tamil minority.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceC&quot;&gt;Globalisation, Democracy and Terror, Eric Hobsbawm&lt;/ref&gt; The resistance campaign evolved into the [[Sri Lankan Civil War]], one of the longest-running armed conflicts in Asia.&lt;ref&gt;Chaliand, p.353&lt;/ref&gt; The group carried out many bombings, including an April 21, 1987, car bomb attack at a [[Colombo]] bus terminal that killed 110 people.&lt;ref name=&quot;pbs.org&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.pbs.org/frontlineworld/stories/srilanka/thestory.html |title=Sri Lanka - Living With Terror |date = May 2002|publisher=PBS |work=Frontline |accessdate=2009-02-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009 the Sri Lankan military launched a major military offensive against the secessionist movement and claimed that it had effectively destroyed the LTTE.

===Africa===
Founded in 1961, [[Umkhonto we Sizwe]] (MK) was the military wing of the [[African National Congress]]; it waged a guerrilla campaign against the South African [[History of South Africa in the apartheid era|apartheid]] regime and was responsible for many bombings.&lt;ref name=mk&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.anc.org.za/ancdocs/history/manifesto-mk.html |title=Manifesto of Umkhonto we Sizwe|publisher=[[African National Congress]]|date=16 December 1961|accessdate=2006-12-30 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20061217090228/http://www.anc.org.za/ancdocs/history/manifesto-mk.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2006-12-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; MK launched its first [[Guerrilla warfare|guerrilla attacks]] against government installations on 16 December 1961. South Africa subsequently banned the group after classifying it as a terrorist organization. MK's first leader was [[Nelson Mandela]], who was tried and imprisoned for the group's acts.&lt;ref name=mandela&gt;[http://www.anc.org.za/ancdocs/history/rivonia.html Statement of Nelson Mandela at Rivonia trial]&lt;/ref&gt; With the end of apartheid in South Africa, Umkhonto we Sizwe was incorporated into the South African armed forces.

==Late 20th century==
In the 1980s and 1990s, [[Islamic]] militancy in pursuit of religious and political goals increased,{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}} many militants drawing inspiration from [[Iran]]'s 1979 Islamic Revolution.&lt;ref name=&quot;meforum.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.meforum.org/1826/contrasting-secular-and-religious-terrorism]&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1990s, well-known violent acts that targeted civilians were the [[Sarin gas attack on the Tokyo subway]] by [[Aum Shinrikyo]] and the [[Oklahoma City bombing|bombing of Oklahoma City's Murrah Federal Building]]. This period also saw the rise of what is sometimes categorised as [[Single issue terrorism]]. If terrorism is the extension of domestic politics by other means, just as war is for diplomacy, then this represents the extension of [[pressure groups]] into violent action. Notable examples that grow in this period are [[Eco-terrorism]] and [[Anti-abortion terrorism]].

===The Americas===
[[Contras|The Contras]] were a counter-revolutionary militia formed in 1979 to oppose [[Nicaragua]]'s [[Sandinista]] government. The Catholic Institute for International Relations asserted the following about contra operating procedures in 1987: &quot;The record of the contras in the field... is one of consistent and bloody abuse of human rights, of murder, torture, mutilation, rape, arson, destruction and kidnapping.&quot;&lt;ref name=CIIR&gt;{{cite news|title=Right to Survive: Human Rights in Nicaragua|format=print|author=The Catholic Institute for International Relations|publisher=The Catholic Institute for International Relations|year=1987}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Human Rights Watch|Americas Watch]] - subsequently folded into [[Human Rights Watch]] - accused the Contras of targeting health care clinics and health care workers for assassination; kidnapping civilians, torturing civilians; executing civilians, including children, who were captured in combat; raping women; indiscriminately attacking civilians and civilian houses; seizing civilian property; and burning civilian houses in captured towns.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/reports/1989/WR89/Nicaragu.htm Nicaragua]&lt;/ref&gt; The contras disbanded after the election of [[Violetta Chamorro]] in 1990.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| title = Turnover in Nicaragua; NICARAGUAN OPPOSITION ROUTS SANDINISTAS; U.S. PLEDGES AID, TIED TO ORDERLY TURNOVER
| publisher = New York Times
| url = http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDF173DF934A15751C0A966958260
| date = February 27, 1990
| first=Mark A.
| last=Uhlig
| accessdate=May 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1985, [[Air India Flight 182]] flying from Canada was blown up by a bomb while in Irish airspace, killing 329 people, including 280 Canadian citizens, mostly of Indian birth or descent, and 22 Indians.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbc.ca/news/background/airindia/victims.html In Depth: Air India] – The Victims, CBC News Online, 16 March 2005&lt;/ref&gt; The incident was the deadliest act of air terrorism before 9/11, and the first bombing of a 747 Jumbo Jet which would set a pattern for future air terrorism plots. The crash occurred within an hour of the fatal [[1985 Narita International Airport bombing|Narita Airport Bombing]] which also originated from Canada without the passenger for the bag that exploded on the ground. Evidence from the explosions, witnesses and wiretaps of militants pointed to an attempt to actually blow up two airliners simultaneously by members of the [[Babbar Khalsa]] [[Khalistan movement]] militant group based in Canada to punish India for [[Operation Blue Star|attacking the Golden Temple]].

The April 19, 1995, [[Oklahoma City bombing]] was directed at the [[Federal government of the United States|U.S. government]], according to the prosecutor at the murder trial of [[Timothy McVeigh]], who was convicted of carrying out the crime.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.law.umkc.edu/faculty/projects/ftrials/mcveigh/prosecutionopen.html Opening statement of prosecutor Joseph Hartzler in the Timothy McVeigh trial&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The bombing of the [[Alfred P. Murrah Federal Building]] in downtown Oklahoma City claimed 168 lives and left over 800 injured.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.indystar.com/library/factfiles/crime/national/1995/oklahoma_city_bombing/ok.html The Oklahoma City Bombing], 2004-8-9&lt;/ref&gt; McVeigh, who was convicted of first degree murder and [[Capital punishment in the United States|executed]], said his motivation was revenge for U.S. government actions at [[Waco Siege|Waco]] and [[Ruby Ridge]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rickross.com/reference/mcveigh/mcveigh6.html McVeigh Remorseless About Bombing]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Middle East===

[[File:Beirutbarracks bombing 2.jpg|150px|thumb|right|Explosion at U.S. Marine Corps barracks in Beirut, Lebanon, 1983]]

[[Hezbollah]] (&quot;Party of God&quot;) is an [[Islamist]] movement and political party founded in [[Lebanon]] shortly after that country's 1982 [[Lebanese Civil War|civil war]]. Inspired by [[Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini]] and the [[Iranian revolution]], the group originally sought an Islamic revolution in Lebanon and has long fought for the withdrawal of Israeli forces from Lebanon. Led by Sheikh Sayyed [[Hassan Nasrallah]] since 1992, the group has kidnapped Israeli soldiers and carried out missile attacks and suicide bombings against Israeli military and civilian targets.&lt;ref name=&quot;HG20Ak02&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.atimes.com/atimes/Middle_East/HG20Ak02.html |title=Hezbollah's transformation |first=Dahr |last=Jamail |publisher=Asia Times |date=2006-07-20 |accessdate=2007-10-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Between 1982 and 1986, there were 36 suicide attacks in Lebanon directed against American, French and Israelis forces by 41 individuals with predominantly leftist political beliefs and of both major religions,&lt;ref&gt;[http://amconmag.com/2005_07_18/article.html &quot;... eight were Islamic fundamentalists. Twenty-seven were Communists and Socialists. Three were Christians]. The American Conservative, July 18, 2005. Verified 22nd June 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; killing 659. The [[1983 Beirut barracks bombing]] (by the [[Islamic Jihad Organization]]), which killed more than 200 U.S. marines at their barracks in Beirut, was particularly deadly.&lt;ref name=&quot;cfr hezbollah&quot;&gt;[http://www.cfr.org/publication/9155/#6 Hezbollah] The US [[Council on Foreign Relations]], 2006-07-17&lt;/ref&gt; Hezbollah denied involvement in any of the attacks.&lt;ref&gt;Sites, Kevin (Scripps Howard News Services). &quot;[http://www.redding.com/redd/nw_columnists/article/0,2232,REDD_17528_4389698,00.html Hezbollah denies terrorist ties, increases role in government]&quot; 2006-01-15&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/target/etc/cron.html Frontline: Target America: Terrorist attacks on Americans, 1979-1988]&quot;, PBS News, 2001. Accessed 4 February 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;leb1&quot;&gt;[http://www.lebanon.com/news/local/2003/3/20.htm Hezbollah again denies involvement in deadly Buenos Aires bombing Beirut, March 19 (AFP)]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Egyptian Islamic Jihad]] (a.k.a. [[Al-Gama'a al-Islamiyya|Al-Gamaa Al-Islamiyya]]) is a militant [[Egypt]]ian [[Islamist]] movement dedicated to the establishment of an [[Islamic republic|Islamic state]] in Egypt. The group formed in 1980 as an umbrella organization for militant student groups formed after the leadership of the [[Muslim Brotherhood]] renounced violence. It is led by [[Omar Abdel-Rahman]], who has been accused of participation in the [[World Trade Center 1993 bombings]]. In 1981, the group assassinated Egyptian president [[Anwar Sadat]]. On November 17, 1997, in what became known as the [[Luxor massacre]], it attacked tourists at the Temple of [[Hatshepsut]] ([[Deir el-Bahri]]); six men dressed as police machine-gunned 58 Japanese and European vacationers and four Egyptians.&lt;ref&gt;Wright, Lawrence, ''Looming Tower'', Knopf, 2006, p. 123&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:PA103cockpit4.png|thumb|left|Nose section of [[Pan Am Flight 103]]]]

On December 21, 1988, [[Pan Am Flight 103]], a [[Pan American World Airways]] flight from London's [[Heathrow International Airport]] to [[New York City|New York]]'s [[John F. Kennedy International Airport]], was destroyed mid flight over the [[Scotland|Scottish]] town of [[Lockerbie]]. On January 31, 2001, Libyan [[Abdelbaset al-Megrahi]] was convicted by a panel of three Scottish judges of bombing the flight, and was sentenced to 27 years imprisonment. In 2002 Libya offered financial compensation to victims' families in exchange for lifting of UN and U.S. sanctions. In 2007 Megrahi was granted leave to appeal against his conviction, and in August 2009 was released on compassionate grounds by the Scottish executive due to his terminal cancer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/scotland/south_of_scotland/8197370.stm | work=BBC News | title=Lockerbie bomber freed from jail | date=August 20, 2009 | accessdate=May 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first Palestinian [[suicide attack]] took place in 1989 when a member of the [[Palestinian Islamic Jihad]] ignited a bomb onboard [[Tel Aviv Jerusalem bus 405 attack|Tel Aviv bus]], killing 16 people.&lt;ref&gt;Moshe Elad, [http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-3563322,00.html Why were we surprised?], Ynet News 07-02-2008&lt;/ref&gt; In the early 1990s another group, [[Hamas]], also became well known for suicide bombings. Sheikh [[Ahmed Yassin]], [[Abdel Aziz al-Rantissi]] and [[Mohammad Taha]] of the Palestinian wing of Egypt's [[Muslim Brotherhood]] had created Hamas in 1987, at the beginning of the [[First Intifada]], an uprising against Israeli rule in the Palestinian Territories that featured little deadly violence.&lt;ref&gt;Chaliand, p.356&lt;/ref&gt; Hamas's militia, the [[Izz ad-Din al-Qassam Brigades]], began its own [[Suicide attack|suicide bombings]] against Israel in 1993, eventually accounting for about 40% of them.&lt;ref&gt;Levitt, Matthew ''Hamas: Politics, Charity, and Terrorism in the Service of Jihad''. Yale University Press, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The Brigades ceased suicide attacks in 2005 and renounced them in April 2006.&lt;ref name=&quot;guardian.co.uk&quot;&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2006/apr/09/israel &quot;Hamas in call to end suicide bombings&quot;] ''The Observer''. April 9, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; They have also been responsible for Israel-targeted rocket attacks, [[Improvised explosive device|IED]] attacks, and shootings, but reduced most of those operations by 2006.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/world/para/hamas.htm HAMAS (Islamic Resistance Movement)]&lt;/ref&gt; After winning legislative elections, Hamas since June 2007 has governed the Gaza portion of the [[Occupied Palestinian Territories|Palestinian Territories]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/middle_east/article2641289.ece|title=Islamist leader hints at Hamas pull-out from Gaza|last=Hider|first=James|date=2007-10-12|publisher=The Times Online|accessdate=2009-01-28 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Flag of Kach and Kahane Chai.svg|thumb|right|Flag of Kach and Kahane Chai.]]

February 25, 1994, [[Baruch Goldstein]], an American-born Israeli physician, perpetrated the [[Cave of the Patriarchs massacre]] in the city of [[Hebron]], Goldstein shot and killed between 30 and 54 Muslim worshippers inside the [[Ibrahimi Mosque]] (within the [[Cave of the Patriarchs]]), and wounded another 125 to 150.&lt;ref name=&quot;news.bbc.co.uk&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/february/25/newsid_4167000/4167929.stm 1994: Jewish settler kills 30 at holy site] ''BBC'' On This Day&lt;/ref&gt; Goldstein, who was lynched and killed in the mosque,&lt;ref name=&quot;news.bbc.co.uk&quot;/&gt; was a supporter of [[Kach and Kahane Chai|Kach]], an Israeli political party founded by Rabbi [[Meir Kahane]] that advocated the expulsion of Arabs from [[Israel]] and the [[Palestinian Territories]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;[http://www.cdi.org/terrorism/kach.cfm In the Spotlight: Kach and Kahane Chai ] ''Center for Defense Information'' October 1, 2002&lt;/ref&gt; In the aftermath of the Goldstein attack and Kach statements praising it, Kach was outlawed in Israel.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; Today, [[Kach and Kahane Chai|Kach]] and a breakaway group, [[Kahane Chai]], are considered [[terrorist organisations]] by [[Israel]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?sec=technology&amp;res=9402E7DD1339F93AA25751C1A9669C8B63&amp;n=Top%2fReference%2fTimes%20Topics%2fPeople%2fK%2fKahane%2c%20Meir Terror Label No Hindrance To Anti-Arab Jewish Group] New York Times, 19 December 2000&lt;/ref&gt; Canada,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.psepc-sppcc.gc.ca/prg/ns/le/cle-en.asp#kach26 Kahane Chai (KACH)] Public Safety Canada&lt;/ref&gt; the [[European Union]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://europa.eu.int/eur-lex/lex/LexUriServ/site/en/oj/2005/l_340/l_34020051223en00640066.pdf Council Decision of 21 December 2005 implementing Article 2(3) of Regulation (EC) No 2580/2001 on specific restrictive measures directed against certain persons and entities with a view to combating terrorism and repealing Decision 2005/848/EC] Official Journal of the European Union, 23 December 2005&lt;/ref&gt; and the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;USSD&quot;&gt;[http://www.state.gov/s/ct/rls/fs/37191.htm Foreign Terrorist Organizations (FTOs)] U.S. Department of State, 11 October 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

===Asia===
[[Aum Shinrikyo]], now known as Aleph, was a Japanese [[New religious movement|religious group]] founded by [[Shoko Asahara]] in 1984 as a yogic meditation group. Later, in 1990, Asahara and 24 other members campaigned for election to the House of Representatives under the banner of Shinri-tō (Supreme Truth Party). None were voted in, and the group began to militarize. Between 1990 and 1995, the group attempted several apparently unsuccessful [[biological terrorism|violent attacks]] using the methods of [[biological warfare]], using [[Botulinum toxin|botulin toxin]] and [[anthrax]] spores.&lt;ref name=olson/&gt; On June 28, 1994, Aum Shinrikyo members released sarin gas from several sites in the Kaichi Heights neighborhood of [[Matsumoto, Nagano|Matsumoto]], Japan, killing eight and injuring 200 in what became known as the [[Matsumoto incident]].&lt;ref name=olson&gt;[http://www.cdc.gov/ncidod/EID/vol5no4/olson.htm CDC website], [[Centers for Disease Control and Prevention]], ''Aum Shinrikyo: Once and Future Threat?'', Kyle B. Olson, Research Planning, Inc., [[Arlington, Virginia]]&lt;/ref&gt; Seven months later, on March 20, 1995, Aum Shinrikyo members released sarin gas in a coordinated attack on five trains in the Tokyo subway system, killing 12 commuters and damaging the health of about 5,000 others&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/asia-pacific/4365417.stm | work=BBC News | title=Sarin attack remembered in Tokyo | date=March 20, 2005 | accessdate=May 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; in what became known as the [[Sarin gas attack on the Tokyo subway|subway sarin incident]] (地下鉄サリン事件, chikatetsu sarin jiken). In May 1995, Asahara and other senior leaders were arrested and the group's membership rapidly decreased.

===Europe===
[[File:Beslan school no 1 victim photos.jpg|thumb|right|Hostage crisis victim photos, on the walls of the former School Number One]]
[[Chechnya]]n separatists, led by [[Shamil Basayev]], carried out several attacks on Russian targets between 1994 and 2006.&lt;ref&gt;Hoffman, p.154&lt;/ref&gt; In the June 1995 [[Budyonnovsk hospital hostage crisis]], Basayev-led separatists took over 1,000 civilians hostage in a hospital in the southern Russian city of [[Budyonnovsk]]. When Russian special forces attempted to free the hostages, 105 civilians and 25 Russian troops were killed.&lt;ref&gt;Smith, Sebastian. ''Allah's Mountains: The Battle for Chechnya''. Tauris, 2005. p.200&lt;/ref&gt;

==21st century==
Major events after the [[September 11 attacks]] in 2001 include the [[Moscow Theatre Siege]], the [[2003 Istanbul bombings]], the [[11 March 2004 Madrid train bombings|Madrid train bombings]], the [[Beslan school hostage crisis]], the [[July 2005 London bombings|2005 London bombings]], the [[29 October 2005 Delhi bombings|October 2005 New Delhi bombings]], the [[2008 Mumbai attacks|2008 Mumbai Hotel Siege]], and the [[2011 Norway attacks]].

===Europe===
The [[Moscow theatre hostage crisis]] was the seizure of a crowded [[Moscow]] theatre on 23 October 2002 by some 40 to 50 armed [[Chechen people|Chechens]] who claimed allegiance to the [[Chechen Republic of Ichkeria|Islamist militant separatist movement in Chechnya]]. They took 850 hostages and demanded the withdrawal of [[Russia]]n forces from [[Chechnya]] and an end to the [[Second Chechen War]]. The siege was officially led by [[Movsar Barayev]]. After a two-and-a-half day siege, Russian [[Spetsnaz]] forces pumped an [[Moscow hostage crisis chemical agent|unknown chemical agent]] (thought to be fentanyl, [[3-methylfentanyl]]), into the building's [[Mechanical ventilation|ventilation]] system and raided it.&lt;ref name=&quot;today&quot;&gt;[http://www.russiatoday.ru/spotlight/release/830/video Modest Silin, Hostage, Nord-Ost siege, 2002], [[Russia Today]], 27 October 2007&lt;/ref&gt; Officially, 39 of the attackers were killed by Russian forces, along with at least 129 and possibly many more of the hostages (including nine foreigners). All but a few of the hostages who died were killed by the gas pumped into the theatre,&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/2365383.stm Gas &quot;killed Moscow hostages&quot;], BBC News, 27 October 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/2602945.stm &quot;Moscow court begins siege claims&quot;], [[BBC News]], 24 December 2002&lt;/ref&gt; and many condemned use of the gas as heavy handed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/2371691.stm &quot;widely condemned as heavy handed&quot;.]&lt;/ref&gt; Roughly, 170 people died in all.

On September 1, 2004, in what became known as the [[Beslan school hostage crisis]], 32 Chechnyan separatists took 1,300 children and adults hostage at [[Beslan]]'s School Number One. When Russian authorities did not comply with the rebel demands that Russian forces withdraw from Chechnya, 20 adult male hostages were shot. After two days of stalled negotiations, Russian special forces stormed the building. In the ensuing melee, over 300 hostages died, along with 19 Russian servicemen and all but perhaps one of the rebels. Basayev is believed to have participated in organizing the attack.&lt;ref name=&quot;g&quot;&gt;{{cite news | title=''Shamil Basayev -Chechen politician seeking independence through terrorism'' | author=Jonathan Steele | publisher=[[Guardian Unlimited]] | work=Obituary |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/chechnya/Story/0,,1817558,00.html |date=July 11, 2006 | accessdate= |quote=&quot;one-time guerrilla commander who turned into a mastermind of spectacular and brutal terrorist actions ... served for several months as prime minister&quot; | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Clarify|date=April 2009}}

===Middle East===
[[File:Osama bin Laden portrait.jpg|130px|thumb|left|Osama bin Laden]][[Osama bin Laden]], closely advised by [[Egyptian Islamic Jihad]] leader [[Ayman al-Zawahiri]], in 1988 founded [[Al-Qaeda]] (Arabic: القاعدة, meaning &quot;The Base&quot;), an [[Islam]]ic [[jihad]]ist movement to replace Western-controlled or dominated Muslim countries with Islamic fundamentalist regimes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cfr.org/publication/9126/ &quot;Backgrounder: al-Qaeda (a.k.a. al-Qaida, al-Qa'ida)&quot;] Jayshree Bajoria &amp; Greg Bruno. ''Council on Foreign Relations'', Updated: December 30, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; In pursuit of that goal, bin Laden issued a 1996 manifesto that vowed violent jihad against U.S. military forces based in Saudi Arabia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=tYHi5qBaM7MC&amp;pg=PA30&amp;dq=al+qaeda+zawahiri+1988+bin+laden+afghanistan&amp;ei=8zvXS4PMH5TONfbkqN4H&amp;cd=2#v=onepage&amp;q=al%20qaeda%20United%20states%20jihad%20against%201996%20%20bin%20laden%20afghanistan&amp;f=falseUnfunding terror: the legal response to the financing of global terrorism] Jimmy Gurulé, 2009, p. 63&lt;/ref&gt; On August 7, 1998, individuals associated with Al Qaeda and Egyptian Islamic Jihad carried out simultaneous [[1998 United States embassy bombings|bombings of two U.S. embassies in Africa]] which resulted in 224 deaths.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/binladen/bombings/bombings.html The U.S. Embassy Bombings Trial - A Summary] PBS, Oriana Zill&lt;/ref&gt; On October 12, 2000, Al-Qaeda carried out the [[USS Cole bombing]], a suicide bombing of the U.S. Navy destroyer USS Cole harbored in the Yemeni port of Aden. The bombing killed seventeen U.S. sailors.&lt;ref name=&quot;al-Fadl&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://cns.miis.edu/pubs/reports/binladen.htm |title=Testimony of Jamal Ahmad Al-Fadl |date=February 6, 2001 |publisher=James Martin Center for Nonproliferation Studies |author=United States District Court, Southern District of New York |work=United States v. Usama bin Laden et al., defendants |accessdate=2008-09-03}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; The group's most well known attack, however, took place on September 11, 2001.

[[File:National Park Service 9-11 Statue of Liberty and WTC fire.jpg|210px|thumb|right|September 11, 2001 - The towers of the World Trade Center burn.]]
On [[September 11, 2001]], nineteen men affiliated with al-Qaeda hijacked four commercial passenger jet airliners, crashing two of them into the [[World Trade Center]] in [[New York City]] and one into [[the Pentagon]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cbc.ca/world/story/2004/10/29/binladen_message041029.html | work=CBC News | title=Bin Laden claims responsibility for 9/11 | date=October 29, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2001/09/12/AR2005033107980.html Terrorists Hijack 4 Airliners, Destroy World Trade Center, Hit Pentagon; Hundreds Dead]&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of the attacks, the World Trade Center's twin towers completely collapsed, and 2,973 victims and the 19 hijackers died.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbc.ca/world/story/2004/10/29/binladen_message041029.html Bin Laden claims responsibility for 9/11]&lt;/ref&gt;

The United States responded to the attacks by launching the [[War on Terror]]. Specifically, on October 7, 2001, it invaded [[Afghanistan]] to depose [[the Taliban]], which had harbored al-Qaeda terrorists. On October 26, 2001, the U.S. enacted the [[USA PATRIOT Act|Patriot Act]], anti-terrorism legislation that expanded the powers of U.S. law enforcement and intelligence agencies. Many countries followed with similar legislation.

On Israel's northern border, after its unilateral withdrawal from southern Lebanon in May 2000, [[Hezbollah]] launched numerous [[Katyusha rocket launcher|Katyusha]] rocket attacks against non-civilian and civilian areas within northern Israel.&lt;ref name=&quot;a&quot;&gt;[http://www.aijac.org.au/resources/hezb_00-06.html Hezbollah Attacks Since May 2000] Mitchell Bard, the Jewish [[AIJAC]], 2006-07-24&lt;/ref&gt; Within Israel, the 1993–2008 [[Second Intifada]] involved in part a [[List of Palestinian suicide attacks|series of suicide bombings]] against civilian and non-civilian targets.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harel 2004 274–275&quot;&gt;{{Cite book
| publisher = Yedioth Aharonoth Books and Chemed Books
| isbn = 965-511-767-7 9789655117677
| last = Harel
| first = Amos
| coauthors = Avi Isacharoff
| title = The Seventh War
| pages = 274–275
| location = Tel-Aviv
| year = 2004
}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2007 study of Palestinian suicide bombings from September 2000 through August 2005 found that 40% percent were carried out by [[Hamas]]'s [[Izz ad-Din al-Qassam Brigades]], and roughly 26% by the [[Palestinian Islamic Jihad]] (PIJ) and [[Fatah]] militias.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harel 2004 274–275&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.economics.harvard.edu/faculty/benmelech/files/JEP_0807.pdf Human Capital and the Productivity of Suicide Bombers pdf] [[Journal of Economic Perspectives]] Volume 21, Number 3, Summer 2007. Pages 223–238&lt;/ref&gt; Also, between 2001 and January 2009, over 8,600 [[Palestinian rocket attacks on Israel|rocket attacks]] were launched from the [[Gaza Strip]] were launched into civilian areas and non-civilian areas inside Israel, causing deaths, injuries, and psychological trauma.&lt;ref name=BBC_Q&amp;A&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/7818022.stm Q&amp;A: Gaza conflict], BBC News 18-01-2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/3702088.stm Gaza's rocket threat to Israel], BBC 21-01-2008&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=BBC_catandmouse&gt;Martin Patience, [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/7270168.stm Playing cat and mouse with Gaza rockets], BBC News 28-02-2008&lt;/ref&gt;

Formed in 2003, [[Jundallah]] is a Sunni insurgent group from the Baloch region of Iran and neighboring Pakistan. It has committed numerous attacks within Iran, stating that it is fighting for the rights of the Sunni minority there. In 2005 the group attempted to assassinate Iran's president, [[Mahmoud Ahmadinejad]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foreignpolicy.com/articles/2009/10/20/irans_enemy_is_not_americas_friend &quot;Iran's Enemy Is Not America's Friend&quot;] Jamsheed K. Choksy. ''Foreign Policy'', October 10, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The group takes credit for other bombings, including the [[2007 Zahedan bombings]]. Iran and other sources accuse the group of being a front for or supported by other nations, in particular the U.S. and [[Pakistan]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newyorker.com/reporting/2008/07/07/080707fa_fact_hersh &quot;Preparing the Battlefield&quot;] Seymour Hersh. ''New Yorker'', July 7, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://blogs.abcnews.com/theblotter/2007/04/abc_news_exclus.html &quot;The Secret War Against Iran&quot;] Brian Ross. ''ABC News'', April 3, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Asia===
The [[2008 Mumbai attacks]] were more than ten coordinated shooting and bombing attacks across [[Mumbai]], [[India]]'s largest city, by [[Islamic terrorism|Islamic terrorists]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=No Way, No How, Not Here |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/02/18/opinion/18friedman.html |newspaper=[[The New York Times]] |date=2009-02-17 |accessdate=2010-05-17|first=Thomas|last=Friedman}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |title=Indian Muslims hailed for not burying 26/11 attackers |publisher=Sify News |url=http://sify.com/news/indian-muslims-hailed-for-not-burying-26-11-attackers-news-international-jegsNXehjhc.html |date=2009-02-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; from [[Pakistan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Mumbai Terror Attacks: 7 Pakistanis Charged - Action Comes a Year After India's Worst Terrorist Attacks; 166 Die. |url=http://abcnews.go.com/International/mumbai-terror-attacks-pakistanis-charged/story?id=9176592 |newspaper=[[ABC News]] |date=2009-11-25 |accessdate=2010-05-17|first=Nick|last=Schifrin}}&lt;/ref&gt; The attacks, which drew widespread condemnation across the world, began on 26 November 2008 and lasted until 29 November, killing at least 173 people and wounding at least 308.&lt;ref name=&quot;Casualties&quot;&gt;{{cite press release|url=http://pib.nic.in/release/release.asp?relid=45446|publisher=Press Information Bureau ([[Government of India]]) |date= 2008-12-11|title=HM announces measures to enhance security|accessdate=2008-12-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Casualties2&quot;&gt;{{cite press release|url=http://www.chicagotribune.com/news/nationworld/sns-ap-as-india-terror-anniversary,0,7693599.story?track=rss|publisher=Chicago Tribune |date= 2009-11-26|title=A year after attacks, Mumbai is just as vulnerable; at vigils, many call for police reform|accessdate=2009-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = Guardian-condemn&gt;{{cite news |last= Black |first=Ian | title=
Attacks draw worldwide condemnation |publisher=''[[The Guardian]]'' |date=2008-11-28 |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2008/nov/28/mumbai-terror-attacks-international-response |accessdate=2008-12-05 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Americas===
2001 also saw the first act of [[Bioterror]] with the [[2001 anthrax attacks]] when letters carrying anthrax spores were posted to several major American media outlets and two [[Democratic]] politicians. There were several fatalities.

==Table of non-state groups accused of terrorism==
{{Unreferenced|section|date=September 2012}}
{| class=&quot;sortable wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left; font-size:90%; width:100%;&quot;
|- valign=bottom
! NAME !! LOCATION !! FOUNDED !! CEASED ATTACKS !! FOUNDER !! SUBSEQUENT LEADERS !! TACTICS !! FAMOUS ATTACK !! INFLUENCED BY !! ACCUSED OF TERRORISM BY
|-
||  ||  ||  ||  ||  || ||  || || ||
|-
||  [[Fenians]] || [[Ireland]] || [[1798]] || ||  ||  || || [[young Irelanders rebellion]]  ||  ||[[Government of the United Kingdom]]
|-
|| [[Narodnaya Volya (organization)|Narodnaya Volya]] || [[Russian Empire]] || 1878 || 1883|| || || bombings, assassinations || Assassinated [[Tsar Alexander II]], 1881 || ||
|-
|| [[Hunchakian Revolutionary Party]] || [[Ottoman Empire]] || 1887 || 1896 || [[Avetis Nazarbekian]] || || || Destroyed Ottoman coat of arms, 1890 || [[Narodnaya Volya (organization)|Narodnaya Volya]] ||
|-
|| [[Armenian Revolutionary Federation]] || [[Ottoman Empire]] || 1890 || 1897|| Christopher Mikaelian || || || Held hostages at Ottoman Bank, 1896 || [[Hunchakian Revolutionary Party]] ||
|-
|| [[Internal Macedonian Revolutionary Organization]] || [[Ottoman Empire]] || 1893 || 1903|| [[Hristo Tatarchev]] || || || Led [[Ilinden–Preobrazhenie Uprising]], 1903 || [[Narodnaya Volya (organization)|Narodnaya Volya]] ||
|-
|| [[Irish Republican Army]] || [[Ireland]] || 1916 || 1923|| [[Eamon de Valera]] || [[Michael Collins (Irish leader)|Michael Collins]] || || [[Kilmichael Ambush]], 1920 || [[Irish Republican Brotherhood]]; ||[[Government of the United Kingdom]]
|-
|| [[Irgun]] || [[British Mandate Palestine]] || 1931 || 1948 || [[Avraham Tehomi]] ||[[Menachem Begin]] || bombings || [[King David Hotel bombing]], 1946 || [[Irish Republican Army]] || [[British Colonial Office]]
|-
|| [[Lehi (group)|Lehi]] || [[British Mandate Palestine]] || 1940|| 1948|| [[Abraham Stern]] || [[Yitzhak Shamir]] || assassinations || [[Lord Moyne]] assassination, 1944 || [[Irish Republican Army]] || [[British Colonial Office]]
|-
|| [[Muslim Brotherhood]] || [[Egypt]] || 1928 || || [[Hassan al-Banna]] || || assassinations || Assassinated former PM Mahmud Fahmi al-Nuqrashi, 1948 || || [[British Colonial Office]]
|-
|| [[Front de Liberation National]] || [[Algeria]] || 1954 || 1962|| || || || Toussaint Rouge attacks, 1954 || Indochina rebels || [[French Government]]
|-
|| [[EOKA]] || [[Cyprus]] || 1955 || 1959|| [[George Grivas]] || || || || ||
|-
|| [[ETA]] || Spain || 1959 || || || || bombings, assassinations || Assassinated &quot;President&quot; Blanco, 1978 || || [[Spanish Government]]
|-
|| [[Fatah]] || [[Palestine]] || 1959 || || [[Yasser Arafat]] || || ||[[Munich Olympics massacre]], 1972 || Algerian rebels || [[Israeli Government]]
|-
|| [[PLO]] || [[Palestine]] || 1964 || || || [[Yasser Arafat]] || [[1978 Coastal Road massacre]] || || ||[[Israeli Government]]
|-
|| [[PFLP]] || [[Palestine]] || 1967 || || || || || [[Black September]] skyjacking, 1970 ||[[Che Guevara]] ||[[Israeli Government]]
|-
|| [[PFLP-GC]] || [[Palestine]] || 1968 || || || || || Hangglider shooting, 1970 || ||[[Israeli Government]]
|-
|| [[DFLP]] || [[Palestine]] || 1969 || || || || || [[Avivim school bus massacre]], 1970 || ||[[Israeli Government]]
|-
|| [[Front de libération du Québec]] || [[Quebec]] || 1963 || 1971 || [[Georges Schoeters]] || || bombings, kidnappings, assassinations || [[October Crisis]] kidnappings, 1970 || [[Che Guevara]]; the [[National Liberation Front (Algeria)|FLN]] || [[Canadian Government]]
|-
|| [[Provisional IRA]] || Ireland || 1969 || 2005 || [[Seán Mac Stíofáin]] || || bombings, assassinations || [[Bloody Friday (1972)|Bloody Friday]] bombings, 1972 || || [[Government of the United Kingdom]], [[Government of the Republic of Ireland]]
|-
|| [[Ulster Defence Association|Ulster Defence Association (UDA)]] || [[Ireland]] || 1972 ||  || || [[Johnny Adair]] || assassinations, mass shootings  ||  [[Castlerock killings]], 1993 &amp; [[Greysteel massacre]], 1993 || [[Ulster Unionist Party|Ulster Unionist Party (UUP)]], [[Democratic Unionist Party|Democratic Unionist Party (DUP)]]|| [[Government of the United Kingdom]], [[Government of the Republic of Ireland]]
|-
|| [[Ulster Volunteer Force (1966)|Ulster Volunteer Force (UVF)]] || [[Ireland]] || 1966 ||  || [[Gusty Spence]] || || assassinations, bombings  || [[Dublin and Monaghan Bombings]], 1974 &amp; [[Loughinisland massacre]], 1994 || [[Ulster Unionist Party|Ulster Unionist Party (UUP)]]|| [[Government of the United Kingdom]], [[Government of the Republic of Ireland]]
|-
|| [[Fuerzas Armadas de Liberación Nacional Puertorriqueña|FALN]] || [[Puerto Rico]] || 1974 || || || || bombings || Four NYC bombs, 1975 || || [[Government of the United States]]
|-
|| [[ASALA]] || [[Turkey]] || 1975 || 1986 || [[Hagop Tarakchian]] || || || Attack on Ankara airport, 1982 || || [[Turkish Government]]
|-
|| [[Kurdistan Workers' Party|PKK]] || [[Turkey]] || 1978 || || [[Abdullah Ocalan]] || || || [[Başbağlar massacre]] || [[Mao Zedong]]; [[National Liberation Front (Algeria)|FLN]]{{Citation needed|date=May 2011}} || [[Turkish Government]]
|-
|| [[Red Army Faction]] || Germany || 1968 || 1998 || [[Andreas Baader]] and [[Ulrike Meinhof]] || || || [[German Autumn]] killings, 1977 || [[Che Guevara]]; [[Mao Zedong]]; [[Vietcong]] || [[German Government]]
|-
|| [[Weather Underground Organization|Weathermen]] || [[U.S.A.]] || 1969 || 1977 || || || || Chicago police statue bombing, 1969 || [[Mao Zedong]]; [[Black Panthers]] ||
|-
|| [[Italian Red Brigade]] || Italy || 1970 || 1989 || [[Renato Curcio]] || || || Assassinated former Prime Minister [[Aldo Moro]], 1978 || ||
|-
|| [[Japanese Red Army]] || Japan || 1971 || 2001 || [[Fusako Shigenobu]] || || || [[Lod Airport]] Massacre, 1972 || ||
|-
|| [[Tamil Tigers]] || [[Sri Lanka]] || 1976 || || || || || Columbus bus terminal bombing, 1987 || ||
|-
|| [[Hezbollah]] || [[Lebanon]] || 1982 || || || [[Hassan Nasrallah]] || || [[April 1983 U.S. Embassy bombing]],  [[1983 Beirut barracks bombing]] || Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini ||
|-
|| [[Egyptian Islamic Jihad]] || [[Egypt]] || 1980 || || || [[Omar Abdel-Rahman]] || || [[Luxor massacre]], 1997 || ||
|-
|| [[Hamas]] || [[Gaza]] || 1987 || || Sheikh [[Ahmed Yassin]] || || ||  [[Passover massacre]], [[Sbarro restaurant suicide bombing]] || [[Muslim Brotherhood]] ||
|-
|| [[Al-Qaeda]] || [[Saudi Arabia]] || 1988 || || [[Osama bin Laden]] || || || [[9/11 attacks]], 2001 || ||
|-
|| [[East Turkestan Liberation Organization]] || China || 1990 || || || || || || ||
|-
|| [[Aum Shinrikyo]] || Japan || 1990 || 1995 || [[Shoko Asahara]] || || || [[Sarin gas attack on the Tokyo subway]], 1995|| ||
|-
|| [[Lashkar-e-Taiba]] || Pakistan || 1991 || || || || || [[Mumbai train bombings]], 2006 and [[2008 Mumbai attacks]]. || ||
|-
|| [[Chechnyan Separatists]] || Russia || 1994 || || || [[Shamil Basayev]] || || [[Beslan school hostage crisis]], 2004 || ||
|-
|| [[Jundallah]] || [[Iran]] || 2003 || || || [[Abdolmalek Rigi]] || || [[2007 Zahedan bombings|Zahedan bombings]], 2007 || || [[Government of Iran]]
|}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Terrorism}}
[[Category:Terrorism| ]]
[[Category:History by topic]]
[[Category:Political science]]

[[id:Sejarah terorisme]]</text>
      <sha1>c3bd8o4mulgds7z0szogfqrpbyd2got</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
