<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Husting</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1572595</id>
    <revision>
      <id>510691391</id>
      <parentid>504671588</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-04T01:48:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>68.109.116.86</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* North America */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8196">A '''husting''' (called a '''stump''' in the [[United States]]) originally referred to a physical platform from which representatives presented their views or cast votes before a parliamentary or other election body. By [[metonymy]], the term may now refer to any event, such as debates or speeches, during an election campaign where one or more of the representative candidates are present.

==Development of the term==
The origin of the term comes from the [[Old English language|Old English]] word ''hasting'' or [[Old Norse]] term ''húsþing'', literally the house &quot;[[Thing (assembly)|thing]],&quot; meaning the assembly of the household of personal followers or retainers of a king, earl or chief, contrasted with the &quot;[[folkmoot]],&quot; the assembly of the whole people.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

&quot;[[Thing (assembly)|Thing]]&quot; literally meant any inanimate object, but also could refer to a cause, suit, or assembly; a similar development of meaning is found in the Latin ''res'', as in the word 'republic' or ''res publica'' ('public thing'), meaning 'commonwealth'. The word still appears in the names of some of the legislative assemblies throughout [[Scandinavia]], for example the [[Folketing]] of [[Denmark]], the [[Alþingi|Althing]] of [[Iceland]] and the [[Storting]] of [[Norway]].{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

&quot;Husting,&quot; or more usually the plural &quot;hustings,&quot; developed to mean a court of the [[city of London]]. This court was formerly the county court for the city and was held before the [[lord mayor]], the sheriffs and aldermen, for the purpose of hearing pleas of land, common pleas and appeals from the sheriffs. It had probate jurisdiction and the ability to register wills. The [[charter of Canute]] (1032) contains a reference to &quot;hustings&quot; weights, which points to the early establishment of this court. It is doubtful{{says who|date=November 2010}} whether courts of this name were held in other towns, but [[John Cowell (jurist)|John Cowell]] (1554–1611) in his ''Interpreter'' (1601) s.v., &quot;Hustings,&quot; says that according to [[Fleta]] there were such courts at Winchester, York, Lincoln, Sheppey and elsewhere. However, the passage from Fleta, as the New English Dictionary points out,{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}} does not necessarily imply this (II. lv. ''Habet etiam Rex curiam in civitatibus ... et in locis ... sicut in Hustingis London'', Winton, est.).

This hustings court jurisdiction eventually became obsolete, but the court still sits occasionally for registering gifts made to the city. Today, the [[Hustings Court]] tradition can be found in some areas of in the United States, such as in [[Virginia]], where Hustings Courts formerly decided local criminal and other matters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.randomhouse.com/wotd/index.pperl?date=20000509 | title=Word of the Day | publisher=RandomHouse.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;In 1973 Virginia's Hustings Courts and Corporation Courts were reorganized as city Circuit Courts. Virginia Acts of Assembly 1973, c. 544. See also [http://leg1.state.va.us/cgi-bin/legp504.exe?000+cod+17.1-500 Code of Virginia, § 17.1-500].&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Richmond, Virginia]], there is also a park called Hustings Court Square,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.courses.vcu.edu/ENG-nae/parks_in_richmond.htm | title=Major Parks in our Richmond's Urban Park System| publisher=Virginia Commonwealth University}}&lt;/ref&gt; where polling votes used to take place.

==The Husting in eighteenth and early nineteenth century practice==
The Husting referred to a platform or pavilion, a temporary structure erected at the place of an election. The returning officer (in most borough constituencies the Mayor or equivalent civic dignitary and in county elections the High Sheriff of the county) was responsible for the detailed timing of the election and the provision of a suitable husting. County elections took place at a single place of election, which was usually the county town or a large town.

On the appointed day the returning officer attended at the husting with the prospective candidates (or the agent of a candidate who was not present in person). The candidates, with a proposer and a seconder for each, addressed the assembled voters. This could sometimes be a difficult task in a large urban constituency, where unpopular speakers might be shouted down.

At the conclusion of the speeches, a show of hands was taken. This was an informal indication of the opinion of the voters and no official record was kept of how many voted for a particular candidate. Sometimes a candidate who found he had little support or otherwise did not want to continue declined to call for a poll. One example of this was seen in the 1784 election for the four seats of the [[City of London (UK Parliament constituency)|City of London]]. [[William Pitt the Younger]] was proposed and &quot;was returned on the show of hands, but removed himself from consideration before the polling was completed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last=Smith | first=Henry Stooks | title=The Parliaments of England | publisher= Political Reference Publications | year=1973}}&lt;/ref&gt;

If after this process there were not more candidates nominated and willing to go to the poll than seats to be filled, the existing candidates were declared elected. This was called an &quot;unopposed return&quot;. But if there remained more candidates than vacancies, the polling commenced.

During polling, each vote was declared openly on the husting, with the elector orally declaring for whom he was casting a ballot. The vote was recorded in a poll book, along with the name of each voter (which enabled further enquiries to be made about his eligibility to vote, if a scrutiny was called for at the end of the polling). In certain occasions, additional candidates were nominated as the polling continued, since this gave an opportunity for more speeches. Polling could continue for many days, so long as there were voters wanting to participate and the candidates desired to continue. A maximum limit of fifteen days for polling was imposed by law in the eighteenth century.

At the end of the polling, the returning officer was required to declare the result from the hustings and return the members elected. This could be a problem after a hotly contested election, and rioting was not unheard of. The 1722 election in [[Westminster (UK Parliament constituency)|Westminster]] was declared void on account of such rioting.

==Modern usage==
[[Image:Hustings20050204 CopyrightKaihsuTai.jpg|thumb|A pre-election husting at the [[Oxford West and Abingdon (UK Parliament constituency)|Oxford West and Abingdon]] constituency, England]]
{{citations missing|section|date=November 2010}}

In using the term in reference to the British parliament during the 1800s, husting referred to a platform in the Guildhall on which the London court was held, and evolved to mean any platform upon which the public nomination of candidates for a parliamentary election is made, and from which the candidate addressed the electors.

The [[Ballot Act 1872]] did away with the public declaration of the nomination, however, so the term has not been used in that context since then. The usage of the word now refers to any meeting at which more than one candidate participates. This may involve a combination of a debate, speeches or questions from the electors.

===North America===
In American political usage, there is no exactly equivalent term.  The closest phrase is that a person is said to be &quot;stumping&quot; or &quot;on the stump&quot; when involved in any political campaigning, especially speech making.

In current Canadian usage the word is found only in the plural, to mean on the campaign trail, or to refer to events of the campaign.&lt;ref&gt; See for example, [http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/national/little-talk-on-the-hustings-of-canadas-role-in-libya/article1964142/ Little talk on the hustings of Canada's role in Libya], Globe and Mail March 30, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}
*''Electoral Reform in England and Wales'', by Charles Seymour (David &amp; Charles Reprints 1970)

----
{{1911}}

[[Category:Elections]]
[[Category:Elections in England]]
[[Category:Election law in the United Kingdom]]</text>
      <sha1>l35ywsaxe3eqv47vrxwt25f07u41hdt</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
