<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Idealism in international relations</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2040766</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520836576</id>
      <parentid>508765728</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-01T01:51:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>8ty3hree</username>
        <id>17369702</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* See also */ added link</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12435">In the American study of international relations, '''idealism''' usually refers to the school of thought personified in [[United States|American]] [[Diplomacy|diplomatic]] history by [[Woodrow Wilson]], such that it is sometimes referred to as '''Wilsonianism''', or '''Wilsonian Idealism'''.  Idealism holds that a state should make its internal political [[philosophy]] the goal of its foreign policy.  For example, an idealist might believe that ending poverty at home should be coupled with tackling poverty abroad. Wilson's idealism was a precursor to [[liberal international relations theory]], which would arise amongst the &quot;institution-builders&quot; after [[World War II]]. It particularly emphasized the ideal of [[American exceptionalism]].

More generally, the Anglo-Australian scholar of international relations [[Hedley Bull]] wrote:&lt;ref&gt;Quoted from [[Donald Markwell]], ''[[John Maynard Keynes]] and International Relations: Economic Paths to War and Peace'', Oxford University Press, 2006, page 3. &lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|&quot;By the 'idealists' we have in mind writers such as Sir [[Alfred Zimmern]], S. H. Bailey, [[Philip Noel-Baker]], and David Mitrany in the United Kingdom, and James T. Shotwell, Pitman Potter, and Parker T. Moon in the United States. ... The distinctive characteristic of these writers was their belief in progress: the belief, in particular, that the system of international relations that had given rise to the First World War was capable of being transformed into a fundamentally more peaceful and just world order; that under the impact of the awakening of democracy, the growth of 'the international mind', the development of the League of Nations, the good works of men of peace or the enlightenment spread by their own teaching, it was in fact being transformed; and that their responsibility as students of international relations was to assist this march of progress to overcome the ignorance, the prejudices, the ill-will, and the sinister interests that stood in its way.&quot;}}

Since the 1880s, there has been growing study of the major writers of this idealist tradition of thought in international relations, including Sir [[Alfred Zimmern]]&lt;ref&gt;[[Donald Markwell]] (1986), 'Sir Alfred Zimmern Revisited: Fifty Years On', Review of International Studies. [[Donald Markwell]], 'Sir Alfred Eckhard Zimmern', Oxford Dictionary of National Biography, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;, [[Norman Angell]], [[John Maynard Keynes]]&lt;ref&gt;E.g. [[Donald Markwell]], ''John Maynard Keynes and International Relations: Economic Paths to War and Peace'', Oxford University Press,2006.&lt;/ref&gt;, [[John A. Hobson]], [[Leonard Woolf]], [[Gilbert Murray]], [[Florence Stawell]] (known as Melian Stawell), [[Philip Henry Kerr, 11th Marquess of Lothian]], [[Arnold J. Toynbee]], [[Lester Pearson]] and [[David Davies, 1st Baron Davies|David Davies]]. 

Much of this writing has contrasted these idealist writers with 'realists' in the tradition of [[E.H. Carr]], whose ''The Twenty Years' Crisis'' (1939) both coined the term 'idealist' and was a fierce and effective assault on the inter-war idealists.

Idealism is also marked by the prominent role played by [[international law]] and [[international organizations]] in its conception of policy formation.  One of the most well-known tenets of modern idealist thinking is [[democratic peace theory]], which holds that states with similar modes of democratic governance do not fight one another.  Wilson's idealistic thought was embodied in his [[Fourteen points]] speech, and in the creation of the [[League of Nations]].

Idealism transcends the [[Left-wing politics|left]]-[[Right-wing politics|right]] political spectrum.  Idealists can include both [[human rights]] campaigners (traditionally, but not always, associated with the left) and [[Neoconservatism in the United States|American neoconservatism]] which is usually associated with the right.

Idealism may find itself in opposition to [[Realism (international relations)|Realism]], a [[worldview]] which argues that a nation's [[national interest]] is more important than [[ethics|ethical]] or [[Morality|moral]] considerations; however, there need be no conflict between the two (see [[Neoconservatism]] for an example of a confluence of the two). Realist thinkers include [[Hans Morgenthau]], [[Niccolò Machiavelli]], [[Otto von Bismarck]], [[George F. Kennan]] and others. Recent practitioners of Idealism in the United States have included [[Ronald Reagan]] and [[George W. Bush]].&lt;ref name=&quot;fl100204&quot;&gt;{{Cite news | first=Michael | last=Gerson | title=Syndicated column:Realism and regime change - US solidarity could aid Iran's Green Revolution| url=http://townhall.com/columnists/MichaelGerson/2010/02/03/realism_and_regime_change_in_iran| work= | publisher=Florida Today | location=Melbourne, Florida | pages= 11A | date=4 February 2010 | id= | accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!---reference is internally consistent with print version but not online version---&gt;

==Wilsonian idealism==
[[File:Ww28.gif|thumb|right|200px|Official White House portrait of Woodrow Wilson]]
Link finds that Wilson from his earliest days had imbibed the beliefs of his denomination - in the omnipotence of God, the morality of the Universe, a system of rewards and punishments and the notion that nations, as well as man, transgressed the laws of God at their peril.&lt;ref&gt;Arthur S. Link, &quot;A Portrait of Wilson,&quot; ''Virginia Quarterly Review''1956 32(4): 524-541&lt;/ref&gt; Blum (1956) argues that  he learned from [[William Ewart Gladstone]] a mystic conviction in the superiority of Anglo-Saxons, in their righteous duty to make the world over in their image. Moral principle, constitutionalism, and faith in God were among the prerequisites for alleviating human strife. While he interpreted international law within such a brittle, moral cast, Wilson remained remarkably insensitive to new and changing social forces and conditions of the 20th century. He expected too much justice in a morally brutal world which disregarded the self-righteous resolutions of parliaments and statesmen like himself. Wilson's triumph was as a teacher of international morality to generations yet unborn.&lt;ref&gt;John Morton Blum, ''Woodrow Wilson and the Politics of Morality'' (1956), p p10, 197-99&lt;/ref&gt; [[Daniel Patrick Moynihan]] sees Wilson's vision of world order anticipated humanity prevailing through the &quot;Holy Ghost of Reason,&quot; a vision which rested on religious faith.&lt;ref&gt;David Steigerwald, ''Wilsonian Idealism in America'' (1994), 230&lt;/ref&gt; 

Wilson's diplomatic policies had a profound influence on shaping the world. Diplomatic historian [[Walter Russell Mead]] has explained:&lt;ref&gt;Walter Russell Mead, [http://www.randomhouse.com/knopf/authors/mead/excerpt.html ''Special Providence''], (2001)&lt;/ref&gt;

:Wilson's principles survived the eclipse of the Versailles system and they still guide European politics today: self-determination, democratic government, collective security, international law, and a league of nations. Wilson may not have gotten everything he wanted at [[Paris Peace Conference, 1919|Versailles]], and his treaty was never ratified by the Senate, but his vision and his diplomacy, for better or worse, set the tone for the twentieth century. [[French Third Republic|France]], [[German Empire|Germany]], [[Kingdom of Italy (1861–1946)|Italy]], and [[United Kingdom|Britain]] may have sneered at Wilson, but every one of these powers today conducts its European policy along Wilsonian lines. What was once dismissed as visionary is now accepted as fundamental. This was no mean achievement, and no European statesman of the twentieth century has had as lasting, as benign, or as widespread an influence.

American foreign relations since 1914 have rested on Wilsonian idealism, says historian David Kennedy, even if adjusted somewhat by the &quot;realism&quot; represented by [[Franklin Delano Roosevelt]] and [[Henry Kissinger]]. Kennedy argues that every president since Wilson has &quot;embraced the core precepts of Wilsonianism. Nixon himself hung Wilson's portrait in the White House Cabinet Room. Wilson's ideas continue to dominate American foreign policy in the twenty-first century. In the aftermath of 9/11 they have, if anything, taken on even greater vitality.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;David M. Kennedy, &quot;What 'W' Owes to 'WW': President Bush May Not Even Know It, but He Can Trace His View of the World to Woodrow Wilson, Who Defined a Diplomatic Destiny for America That We Can't Escape&quot;, ''The Atlantic Monthly'' Vol: 295. Issue: 2. (March 2005) pp 36ff.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Descendant theories ==
&lt;!-- Unsourced image removed: [[Image:Woodrow wilson.jpg|thumb|200px|right|Former [[President of the United States]] [[Woodrow Wilson]], is considered to be a founder of idealism.|{{deletable image-caption|1=Saturday, 27 December 2008}}]] --&gt;
Idealism proper was a relatively short-lived school of thought, and suffered a crisis of confidence following the failure of the League of Nations and the outbreak of [[World War]] II.  However, subsequent theories of international relations would draw elements from Wilsonian Idealism when constructing their world views.

=== Liberalism ===
{{main|Liberal international relations theory}}

Liberalism manifested a tempered version of Wilson's idealism in the wake of World War I.  Cognizant of the failures of Idealism to prevent renewed [[isolationism]] following World War I, and its inability to manage the [[balance of power in international relations|balance of power]] in Europe to prevent the outbreak of a new war, liberal thinkers devised a set of international institutions based on rule of law and regularized interaction.  These international organizations, such as the [[United Nations]]  and the [[NATO]], or even international regimes such as the [[Bretton Woods system]], and [[General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade]] (GATT), were calculated both to maintain a balance of power as well as regularize cooperation between nations.

=== Neoconservatism ===
{{main|Neoconservatism}}

Neoconservatism drew from Liberalism its intense focus on the promotion of &quot;[[universal value]]s&quot;, in this case [[democracy]], [[human rights]], [[free trade]], [[women's rights]] and [[minority group|minority]] protections. However, it differs in that it is less wedded to the importance of preserving international institutions and treaties while pursuing assertive or aggressive stances which it deems morally worthy, and is willing to use force or the threat of force, unilaterally if necessary, to push for its goals.

== See also ==
*[[Idealism]]
*[[Lofty idealism]]
*[[International relations theory]]
*&quot;[[New world order (politics)]]&quot;
*[[Liberal internationalism]]

== Notes ==
&lt;references/&gt;

==External references==
* Martin Ceadel, ''Semi-detached Idealists: the British peace movement and international relations, 1854-1945'', 2000.
* Tim Dunne, Michael Cox, Ken Booth (eds), ''The Eighty Years' Crisis: International Relations 1919-1999'', Cambridge University Press, 1999.
* F. H. (Sir Harry) Hinsley, ''Power and the Pursuit of Peace'', Cambridge University Press, 1967.
* David Long, ''Towards a New Liberal Internationalism: The International Theory of J.A. Hobson'', Cambridge University Press, 1996.
* David Long and Peter Wilson (eds), ''Thinkers of the Twenty Years' Crisis: Inter-War Idealism Reassessed'', Oxford University Press, 1995. 
* [[Donald Markwell]], ''[[John Maynard Keynes]] and International Relations: Economic Paths to War and Peace'', Oxford University Press, 2006.
* [[Donald Markwell]] (1986), 'Sir [[Alfred Zimmern]] Revisited: Fifty Years On', Review of International Studies. 
* [[Donald Markwell]], 'Sir Alfred Eckhard Zimmern', Oxford Dictionary of National Biography, 2004. 
* J. D. B. Miller, ''[[Norman Angell]] and the Futility of War: Peace and the Public Mind'', London, Macmillan, 1986.
* Peter Wilson, ''The International Thought of [[Leonard Woolf]]: A Study in Twentieth Century Idealism'', 2003.
{{international relations theories}}
[[Category:International relations theory]]
[[Category:Idealism]]
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Woodrow Wilson]]

[[da:Idealisme (international politik)]]
[[es:Idealismo en política internacional]]
[[fa:آرمان‌گرایی در نظریه روابط بین‌الملل]]
[[fr:Idéalisme (relations internationales)]]
[[ja:理想主義]]
[[pt:Idealismo (relações internacionais)]]
[[sv:Idealism (internationella relationer)]]</text>
      <sha1>gd82lbqf2a66x3tnrd3stg19pk5pcab</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
