<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Industrialisation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>210545</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519544931</id>
      <parentid>519544917</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-24T10:16:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contributions/1.23.42.83|1.23.42.83]] to version by Velella. False positive? [[User:ClueBot NG/FalsePositives|Report it]]. Thanks, [[User:ClueBot NG|ClueBot NG]]. (1292825) (Bot)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27237">{{Refimprove|date=August 2010}}
[[File:Maddison GDP per capita 1500-1950.svg|thumb|350px|right|The effect of Industrialisation shown by rising income levels since 1500. The graph shows the [[gross domestic product]] (at [[purchasing power parity]]) [[per capita]] between 1500 and 1950 in [[International dollar|1990 International dollar]]s for selected nations.&lt;ref&gt;Depicting data excerpted from ''Contours of the World Economy, 1–2030 AD. Essays in Macro-Economic History'' by Angus Maddison, Oxford University Press, 2007, [[commons:Special:BookSources/9780199227211|ISBN 978-0-19-922721-1]], p. 382, Table A.7.&lt;/ref&gt; ]]

[[File:2005gdpIndustrial.png|thumb|350px|right|Map showing the global distribution of industrial output{{clarify|date=April 2012}} in 2005, based on a percentage of the top producer, which is the United States]]
'''Industrialisation''' ([[American and British English spelling differences#-ise, -ize (-isation, -ization)|or]] '''industrialization''') is the period of social and economic change that transforms a human group from an [[agrarian society]] into an [[industry|industrial]] one. It is a part of a wider [[modernisation]] process, where [[social change]] and [[economic development]] are closely related with [[technological]] [[innovation]], particularly with the development of large-scale [[energy]] and [[metallurgy]] production. It is the extensive organisation of an [[economy]] for the purpose of [[manufacturing]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book  | last = Sullivan  | first=Arthur  | authorlink = Arthur O' Sullivan  | coauthors = Steven M. Sheffrin  | title = Economics: Principles in action  | publisher = Pearson Prentice Hall  | year = 2003  | location = Upper Saddle River, New Jersey 07458  | page =472  | url = http://www.pearsonschool.com/index.cfm?locator=PSZ3R9&amp;PMDbSiteId=2781&amp;PMDbSolutionId=6724&amp;PMDbCategoryId=&amp;PMDbProgramId=12881&amp;level=4  | isbn = 0-13-063085-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Industrialisation also introduces a form of [[philosophy|philosophical]] change where people obtain a different attitude towards their perception of [[nature]], and a [[sociological]] process of ubiquitous [[rationalization (sociology)|rationalisation]].

There is considerable literature on the factors facilitating industrial modernisation and enterprise development.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis F. Abbott, ''Theories Of Industrial Modernisation &amp; Enterprise Development: A Review'', ISM/Google Books, revised 2nd edition, 2003.  ISBN 978-0-906321-26-3.[http://books.google.com/books?q=theories+of+industrial+modernisation+and+enterprise+development&amp;btnG=Search+Books]&lt;/ref&gt;  Key positive factors identified by researchers have ranged from favourable political-legal environments for industry and commerce, through abundant [[natural resources]] of various kinds, to plentiful supplies of relatively low-cost, skilled and adaptable [[Wage labour|labour]].

As industrial workers incomes rise, markets for consumer goods and services of all kinds tend to expand and provide a further stimulus to industrial [[investment]] and [[economic growth]]. 

The first country to industrialise was the [[United Kingdom]] during the [[Industrial Revolution]], commencing in the eighteenth century.&lt;ref name=&quot;Industrial Revolution&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ace.mmu.ac.uk/eae/Global_Warming/Older/Industrial_Revolution.html|title=Industrial Revolution|accessdate=27 April 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By the end of the 20th century, [[East Asia]] had become one of the most recently industrialised regions of the world .&lt;ref&gt;''Industry &amp; Enterprise: An International Survey Of Modernisation &amp; Development'', ISM/Google Books, revised 2nd edition, 2003. ISBN 978-0-906321-27-0. [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=lZS7OXZUsnMC&amp;dq=isbn:0906321271]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Description==
According to the original [[Three-sector hypothesis|sector classification]] of [[Jean Fourastié]], an economy consists of a &quot;[[Primary sector of economic activity|Primary sector]]&quot; of commodity production (farming, livestock breeding, exploitation of mineral resources), a &quot;[[Secondary sector of economic activity|secondary sector]]&quot; of manufacturing and processing (as paid work), and a &quot;[[Tertiary sector of economic activity|Tertiary Sector]]&quot; of service industries. The industrialisation process is historically based on the expansion of the secondary sector in an economy dominated by primary activities.

The first transformation to an industrial economy from an agricultural one is called the [[Industrial Revolution]] and took place from the mid 18th to early 19th century in certain areas in [[Europe]] and North America; starting in Great Britain, followed by Belgium, Germany, and France. This now is called the first industrial revolution.&lt;ref name=&quot;Industrial Revolution&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Pollard, Sidney: Peaceful Conquest.The Industrialisation of Europe 1760–1970, Oxford 1981.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Second Industrial Revolution]] describes the later changes that came about in the mid 19th century after the invention of steam engine, [[internal combustion engine]], [[electric power|electricity]] and the construction of canals, railways and electric power lines. The invention of the [[assembly line]] gave this phase a boost.&lt;ref&gt;Buchheim, Christoph: Industrielle Revolutionen. Langfristige Wirtschaftsentwicklung in Großbritannien, Europa und in Übersee, München 1994, S. 11-104.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jones, Eric: The European Miracle: Environments, Economics and Geopolitics in the History of Europe and Asia, 3. ed. Cambridge 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Henning, Friedrich-Wilhelm: Die Industrialisierung in Deutschland 1800 bis 1914, 9. Aufl., Paderborn/München/Wien/Zürich 1995, S. 15-279.&lt;/ref&gt;

The lack of an [[Industry|industrial]] sector in a country can be a handicap in improving the country's economy and power, so governments encourage or enforce industrialisation. On the other hand, the presence of industry in a country does not mean in general that it will bring wealth and prosperity to the people of that country. And third, the presence of an industry in one country can make it more difficult for other countries to develop the same type of industry. This can be seen in the computer software, and internet industries. Started from the U.S.A. around the 1990s these industries seemed to spread over the world. But after a period of monopolisation less than a decade long, the globally leading companies are concentrated in the U.S.A. Their economic power and capacity to dominate the media work against the developing of the same types of industry in other states.

==History of industrialisation==
{{Main|Pre-industrial society}}

[[File:Maquina vapor Watt ETSIIM.jpg|250px|thumb|A [[Watt steam engine]], the [[steam engine]] fuelled primarily by [[coal]] that propelled the [[Industrial Revolution]] in the [[United Kingdom]] and the world.&lt;ref&gt;[[Watt steam engine]] image: located in the lobby of the Superior Technical School of Industrial Engineers of the UPM ([[Madrid]])&lt;/ref&gt;]]

Most pre-industrial economies had standards of living not much above [[List of subsistence techniques|subsistence]], among that the majority of the population were focused on producing their means of survival. For example, in [[Middle Ages|medieval]] Europe, as much as 80% of the labour force was employed in subsistence [[agriculture]].{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}

Some pre-industrial economies, such as [[classical Athens]], had trade and commerce as significant factors, so native Greeks could enjoy wealth far beyond a sustenance standard of living through the use of [[slavery]]{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}. [[Famine]]s were frequent in most pre-industrial societies, although some, such as the Netherlands and England of the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries, the [[Medieval commune|Italian city states]] of the fifteenth century, the medieval Islamic [[Caliphate]], and the ancient [[Ancient Greece|Greek]] and [[Ancient Rome|Roman]] [[civilisation]]s were able to escape the famine cycle through increasing trade and [[commercialisation]] of the [[Agriculture|agricultural sector]]{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}. It is estimated that during the seventeenth century Netherlands [[import]]ed nearly 70% of its grain supply and in the fifth century BC Athens imported three quarters of its total food supply.{{Citation needed|date=April 2011}}

Industrialisation through [[innovation]] in manufacturing processes first started with the Industrial Revolution in the north-west and Midlands of England in the eighteenth century.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.historyguide.org/intellect/lecture17a.html The Origins of the Industrial Revolution in England] by Steven Kreis. Last Revised 11 October 2006. Accessed April 2008&lt;/ref&gt; It spread to Europe and North America in the nineteenth century.

===Industrial revolution in Europe===
{{Main|Industrial Revolution}}
[[File:Aplerbecker Hütte2.JPG|thumb|250px|Aplerbecker Hütte, an industrialised area of [[Dortmund]], Germany around 1910. The old town can be seen beyond and some remaining agricultural land is in the foreground]]
In the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries, the United Kingdom experienced a massive increase in agricultural productivity known as the [[British Agricultural Revolution]], which enabled an unprecedented [[population growth]], freeing a significant percentage of the workforce from farming, and helping to drive the [[Industrial Revolution]].

Due to the limited amount of arable land and the overwhelming efficiency of [[mechanisation|mechanised]] farming, the increased population could not be dedicated to agriculture. New agricultural techniques allowed a single [[peasant]] to feed more [[worker]]s than previously; however, these techniques also increased the demand for [[machine]]s and other [[Household hardware|hardware]], which had traditionally been provided by the [[Urban area|urban]] [[artisan]]s. Artisans, collectively called [[bourgeoisie]], employed [[rural]] [[Human migration#Ravenstein's 'laws of migration'|exodus]] workers to increase their output and meet the country's needs.

The growth of their [[business]] coupled with the lack of experience of the new workers pushed a [[Rationalization (economics)|rationalisation]] and [[standardisation]] of the duties the in [[workshop]]s, thus leading to a [[division of labour]], that is, a primitive form of [[Fordism]]. The process of creating a [[Good (economics and accounting)|good]] was divided into simple tasks, each one of them being gradually mechanised in order to boost [[productivity]] and thus increase [[income]].{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}

The accumulation of [[capital (economics)|capital]] allowed [[investment]]s in the [[scientific research|conception and application of new technologies]], enabling the industrialisation process to continue to evolve. The industrialisation process formed a class of industrial workers who had more money to spend than their agricultural cousins. They spent this on items such as tobacco and sugar, creating new mass markets that stimulated more investment as merchants sought to exploit them.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/british/abolition/industrialisation_article_01.shtml Enslavement and industrialisation] Robin Blackburn , BBC British History. Published: 18 December 2006 Accessed April 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

The mechanisation of production spread to the countries surrounding England geographically in Europe such as France and to British [[Settler colonialism|settler colonies]], helping to make those areas the wealthiest, and shaping what is now known as the [[Western world]].
[[Image:Crystal Palace - interior.jpg|thumb|right|200px|[[The Crystal Palace]] [[Great Exhibition]]. The United Kingdom was the first country in the world to industrialise.&lt;ref name=&quot;Industrial Revolution&quot;/&gt;]]
Some economic historians argue that the possession of so-called ‘exploitation colonies’ eased the accumulation of capital to the countries that possessed them, speeding up their [[Economic development|development]].{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}} The consequence was that the [[Colony|subject country]] integrated a bigger [[economic system]] in a subaltern position, emulating the countryside, which demands manufactured goods and offers raw materials, while the colonial power stressed its urban posture, providing goods and importing food. A classical example of this mechanism is said to be the [[triangular trade]], which involved England, southern United States and western Africa. Critics argue that this polarity still affects the world, and has deeply retarded industrialisation of what is now known as the [[Third World]].{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}

Some have stressed the importance of natural or financial resources that Britain received from its many overseas colonies or that profits from the British [[slave trade]] between Africa and the Caribbean helped fuel industrial investment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Pomeranz|first=Kenneth|title=The Great Divergence|year=2000|publisher=Princeton University Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Early industrialisation in other countries===
After the [[Convention of Kanagawa]] issued by Commodore [[Matthew C. Perry]] forced Japan to open the ports of Shimoda and Hakodate to American trade, the Japanese government realised that drastic reforms were necessary to stave off Western influence. The [[Bakumatsu|Tokugawa shogunate]] abolished the [[Feudalism|feudal system]]. The government instituted military reforms to modernise the Japanese army and also constructed the base for industrialisation. In the 1870s, the [[Meiji period|Meiji]] government vigorously promoted technological and industrial development that eventually changed Japan to a [[Regional power|powerful]] modern country.

In a similar way, Russia suffered during the [[Allied intervention in the Russian Civil War]]. The [[Soviet Union]]'s [[Planned economy|centrally controlled economy]] decided to invest a big part of its resources to enhance its industrial production and [[infrastructure]]s to assure its survival, thus becoming a world [[superpower]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.learningcurve.gov.uk/heroesvillains/g4/ Joseph Stalin and the industrialisation of the USSR] Learning Curve website, The UK National Archives. Accessed April 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[Cold war]], the other [[Eastern Bloc|European socialist countries]], organised under the [[Comecon]] framework, followed the same developing scheme, albeit with a less emphasis on [[heavy industry]].

Southern European countries such as [[Spanish miracle|Spain]] or [[Italian economic miracle|Italy]] saw a moderate industrialisation during the 1950s-1970s, caused by a healthy integration of the [[Economy of Europe|European economy]], though their level of development, as well as those of Socialist European Countries, do not match the more advanced standards of other European countries like Germany.&lt;ref&gt;[http://cronologia.leonardo.it/storia/tabello/tabe1565.htm BOOM E MIRACOLO ITALIANO ANNI '50-60 (CRONOLOGIA)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=0qgvdlWlXnQC&amp;pg=PA18&amp;lpg=PA18&amp;dq=milagro+espa%C3%B1ol+franco&amp;source=web&amp;ots=KTvntPpytP&amp;sig=GfgfbZwAwZx7Y5425fgjeHOMdDI&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ct=result#PPA18,M1 Queer transitions in contemporary Spanish culture: from Franco to la movida], By Gema Pérez-Sánchez&lt;/ref&gt;

===The Third World===
{{Main|Third World}}

A similar state-led developing programme was pursued in virtually all the Third World countries during the [[Cold War]], including the [[Socialism|socialist]] ones, but especially in [[Sub-Saharan Africa]] after the [[decolonisation]] period.{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}} The primary scope of those projects was to achieve [[self-sufficiency]] through the local production of previously [[import]]ed goods, the mechanisation of agriculture and the spread of [[education]] and [[health care]]. However, all those experiences failed bitterly due to a lack of realism: most countries did not have a pre-industrial bourgeoisie able to carry on a [[Capitalism|capitalistic]] development or even a stable and peaceful [[State (polity)|state]]. Those aborted experiences left [[Developing countries' debt|huge debts]] toward western countries and fuelled [[Political corruption|public corruption]].

===Petrol-producing countries===
Oil-rich countries saw similar failures in their economic choices.
An [[Energy Information Administration|EIA]] report stated that [[OPEC]] member nations were projected to earn a net amount of $1.251 trillion in 2008 from their oil exports.&lt;ref&gt;[http://in.reuters.com/article/businessNews/idINIndia-34433820080708 OPEC to earn $1.251 trillion from oil exports - EIA], Reutrs&lt;/ref&gt; Because oil is both important and expensive, regions that had big [[Oil reserves|reserves of oil]] had huge [[liquidity]] incomes. However, this was rarely followed by economic development. Experience shows that local [[elite]]s were unable to re-invest the [[petrodollar]]s obtained through oil export, and currency is wasted in [[luxury good]]s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.koreatimes.co.kr/www/news/opinon/2008/10/198_12838.html Understanding New Middle East], Behzad Shahandeh, The Korea Times, 31 October 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

This is particularly evident in the [[Arab states of the Persian Gulf#Economy|Persian Gulf states]], where the [[per capita income]] is comparable to those of western nations, but where no industrialisation has started. Apart from two little countries ([[Economy of Bahrain|Bahrain]] and the [[Economy of the United Arab Emirates|United Arab Emirates]]), [[Arab world#Modern economies|Arab states]] have not [[Diversity (business)|diversified their economies]], and no replacement for the [[Oil depletion|upcoming end of oil reserves]] is envisaged.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/3584.htm Background Note: Saudi Arabia]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Industrialisation in Asia===
Apart from Japan, where industrialisation began in the late 19th century, a different pattern of industrialisation followed in [[East Asia]]. One of the fastest rates of industrialisation occurred in the late 20th century across four countries known as the [[Four Asian Tigers|Asian tiger]] (Hong Kong, Singapore, South Korea and Taiwan), thanks to the existence of stable governments and well structured societies, strategic locations, heavy foreign [[investment]]s, a low cost skilled and motivated [[workforce]], a competitive [[exchange rate]], and low custom duties.

In the case of South Korea, the largest of the four Asian tigers, a very fast paced industrialisation took place as it quickly moved away from the manufacturing of value added goods in the 1950s and 60s into the more advanced steel, shipbuilding and automobile industry in the 1970s and 80s, focusing on the high-tech and service industry in the 1990s and 2000s. As a result, South Korea became a major [[G20 industrial nations|economic power]].

This starting model was afterwards successfully copied in other larger Eastern and Southern Asian countries, including [[communist]] ones. The success of this phenomenon led to a huge wave of [[offshoring]] – i.e., Western factories or [[Tertiary sector of economic activity|Tertiary Sector]] corporations choosing to move their activities to countries where the workforce was less expensive and less collectively organised.

China and India, while roughly following this development pattern, made adaptations in line with their own histories and cultures, their major size and importance in the world, and the [[Geopolitics|geo-political]] ambitions of their governments (etc.).

Meanwhile, India's government is investing in economic sectors such as [[bioengineering]], [[nuclear technology]], [[pharmaceutics]], [[Information technology|informatics]], and technologically-oriented [[higher education]], exceeding its needs, with the goal of creating several specialisation poles able to conquer foreign markets.

Both China and India have also started to make significant investments in other developing countries, making them significant players in today's world economy.

===Newly industrialised countries===
{{Main|Newly industrialized country|l1=Newly industrialised country}}
[[Image:NewlyIndustrializedCountries.png|right|350px|thumb|The countries in green are considered to be newly industrialising nations. China and India (in dark green) are a special case.]]

In recent decades,{{when|date=March 2012}} a few countries in Latin America, Asia, and Africa, such as [[Indonesia]], [[Turkey]], South Africa, [[Malaysia]], Philippines, Mexico, [[Costa Rica]], and [[El Salvador]] have experienced substantial industrial growth, fueled by exporting to countries that have bigger economies: the United States, China, India and the EU. They are sometimes called [[Newly industrialized country|newly industrialised countries]].{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}}

Despite this [[Market trends|trend]] being artificially influenced by the [[oil price increases since 2003]], the phenomenon is not entirely new nor totally speculative (for instance see: [[Maquiladora]]).

Japan and Russia both were successful in the fact that they imitated many other societies giving them flexibility.  Yet they both had very little in common before the 19th century. Japan was isolated from the world with its ongoing traditions and forms of centralised government.  Russia featured a more strong centralised government under the emperor.

Both would soon discover that westernisation and industrialism were expanding and their own ways would not hold up against the new changing world of industrialisation. In the late 19th century the force for them to being industrializing would become even more prevalent for the success of their nation in this new growing societies.

==Social and environmental consequences==
{{Expand section|date=November 2010}}

===Urbanisation===
{{Main|Urbanization|l1=Urbanisation}}

The concentration of labour into factories has brought about the rise of [[conurbation|large towns]] to serve and house the factory workers.

===Exploitation===
{{Main|Exploitation|Exploitation of natural resources}}
Workers have to leave their family in order to come to work in the towns and cities where the industries are found.

===Change to family structure===
The family structure changes with industrialisation. The sociologist [[Talcott Parsons]] noted that in pre-industrial societies there is an [[extended family]] structure spanning many generations who probably remained in the same location for generations. In industrialised societies the [[nuclear family]], consisting of only of parents and their growing children, predominates. Families and children reaching adulthood are more mobile and tend to relocate to where jobs exist. Extended family bonds become more tenuous.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.blacksacademy.net/content/3236.html ''The effect of industrialisation on the family, Talcott Parsons, the isolated nuclear family.''] Blacks Academy. Educational Database . Accessed April 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Current situation==
{{Confusing|date=March 2008}}
[[Image:Gdp-and-labour-force-by-sector.png|thumbnail|320px|right|[[Gross domestic product|GDP]] composition of sector and labour force by occupation. The green, red, and blue components of the colours of the countries represent the percentages for the agriculture, industry, and services sectors, respectively.]]

Currently the &quot;international development community&quot; ([[World Bank]], [[Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development|OECD]], many United Nations departments, and some other organizations){{Citation needed|date=March 2008}} endorses development policies like water purification or [[primary education]].{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}} The community does not recognize traditional industrialization policies as being adequate to the Third World or beneficial in the longer term, with the perception that it could only create [[inefficiency|inefficient]] local industries unable to compete in the [[free trade|free-trade]] dominated political order which it has erected.

The relationship between economic growth, employment and poverty reduction is complex. Higher productivity is argued to be leading to lower employment (see [[jobless recovery]]).&lt;ref name=ODI2&gt;Claire Melamed, Renate Hartwig and Ursula Grant 2011. [http://www.odi.org.uk/resources/details.asp?id=5752&amp;title=jobs-growth-poverty-employment Jobs, growth and poverty: what do we know, what don't we know, what should we know?] London: [[Overseas Development Institute]]&lt;/ref&gt; There are differences across sectors, whereby manufacturing is less able than the [[tertiary sector]] to accommodate both increased productivity and employment opportunities; over 40% of the world's employees are &quot;working poor&quot; whose incomes fail to keep themselves and their families above the $2 a day [[poverty line]].&lt;ref name=ODI2/&gt; There is also a phenomenon of [[deindustrialization]], such as in the former [[Soviet Union|USSR]] countries' transition to market economies, and the [[agriculture sector]] often is the key sector in absorbing the resultant unemployment.&lt;ref name=ODI2/&gt;

==See also==
* [[Division of labour]]
* [[Deindustrialization|Deindustrialisation]]
* [[Newly industrialized country|Newly industrialised country]]
* [[Urbanization|Urbanisation]]
* [[Idea of Progress]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* Hewitt, T., Johnson, H. and Wield, D. (Eds) (1992) ''industrialisation and Development'', Oxford University Press: Oxford.
* Hobsbawm, Eric (1962): ''The Age of Revolution.'' Abacus.
* Kiely, R (1998) ''industrialisation and Development: A comparative analysis'', UCL Press:London.
* Pomeranz, Ken (2001)''The Great Divergence: China, Europe and the Making of the Modern World Economy'' (Princeton Economic History of the Western World) by (Princeton University Press; New Ed edition, 2001)
* Kemp, Tom (1993) ''Historical Patterns of Industrialisation'', Longman: London. ISBN 0-582-09547-6
* Tilly, Richard H.: [http://nbn-resolving.de/urn:nbn:de:0159-2010101103 ''Industrialization as an Historical Process''], [[European History Online]], Mainz: [[Institute of European History]], 2010, retrieved: February 29, 2011.

{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2010}}

[[Category:Industry]]
[[Category:Economic growth]]
[[Category:Economic development]]

[[zh-min-nan:Kang-gia̍p-hoà]]
[[bg:Индустриализация]]
[[cs:Industrializace]]
[[da:Industrialisering]]
[[de:Industrialisierung]]
[[es:Industrialización]]
[[eo:Industriiĝo]]
[[eu:Industrializazio]]
[[fa:صنعتی‌سازی]]
[[fo:Ídnaðarsamfelagið]]
[[fr:Industrialisation]]
[[gl:Industrialización]]
[[ko:산업화]]
[[hi:औद्योगीकरण]]
[[hr:Industrijalizacija]]
[[id:Industrialisasi]]
[[is:Iðnvæðing]]
[[it:Industrializzazione]]
[[lt:Industrializacija]]
[[nl:Industrialisatie]]
[[ja:工業化]]
[[no:Industrialisering]]
[[nn:Industrialisering]]
[[pl:Industrializacja]]
[[pt:Industrialização]]
[[ru:Индустриализация]]
[[simple:Industrialization]]
[[fi:Teollistuminen]]
[[sv:Industrialisering]]
[[ta:தொழில்மயமாதல்]]
[[te:పారిశ్రామీకరణ]]
[[uk:Індустріалізація в СРСР]]
[[ur:صنعت کاری]]
[[vi:Công nghiệp hóa]]
[[zh:工業化]]</text>
      <sha1>6f9n8hl4s3rgugk0vxi1cnch7doqtej</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
