<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Internationalism (politics)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>99224</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521761055</id>
      <parentid>520349398</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-07T01:25:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SchreiberBike</username>
        <id>5839411</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>[[WP:DPL|You can help.]] Repaired link to the disambiguation page, [[Global village]].</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13696">{{POV|date=December 2007}}
{{Refimprove|date=May 2009}}

'''Internationalism''' is a [[political movement]] which advocates a greater economic and political cooperation among nations for the theoretical benefit of all. Partisans of this movement, such as supporters of the [[World Federalist Movement]], claim that nations should cooperate because their long-term mutual interests are of greater value than their individual short term needs.

Internationalism is by nature opposed to [[ultranationalism]], [[jingoism]], [[political realism|realism]] and national [[chauvinism]]. Internationalism teaches that the people of all nations have more in common than they do differences, and thus that nations should treat each other as equals. The term internationalism is often wrongly used as a [[synonym]] for [[cosmopolitanism]]. 'Cosmopolitanist' is also sometimes used as a term of abuse for internationalists. Internationalism is not necessarily [[anti-nationalism]], as in the [[People's Republic of China]] and [[stalinism|stalinist]] countries.

==Modern expression==
Internationalism is most commonly expressed as an appreciation for the diverse cultures in the world, and a desire for [[world peace]]. People who express this view believe in not only being a citizen of their respective countries, but of being a [[World citizen|citizen of the world]]. Internationalists feel obliged to assist the world through leadership and charity.

Internationalists also advocate the presence of an international organization, such as the [[United Nations]], and often support a stronger form of a world government.

Contributors to the current version of internationalism include [[Albert Einstein]], who believed in a world government, and classified the follies of [[nationalism]] as &quot;an infantile sickness&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Albert Einstein, The World as I see it, 1934&lt;/ref&gt;

===International Organizations and Internationalism===
For both intergovernmental organizations and international non-governmental organizations to emerge, nations and peoples had to be strongly aware that they shared certain interests and objectives across national boundaries and they could best solve their many problems by pooling their resources and effecting transnational cooperation, rather than through individual countries' unilateral efforts. Such a view, such global consciousness, may be termed internationalism, the idea that nations and peoples should cooperate instead of preoccupying themselves with their respective national interests or pursuing uncoordinated approaches to promote them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Iriye|first=Akira|title=Global Community|year=2002|publisher=University of California Press|location=London|pages=9, 10}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

===Sovereign nations vs. supernational powers balance===
Internationalism, in the strict meaning of the word, is still based on the existence of [[sovereign nation]]s. Its aims are to encourage [[multilateralism]] (world leadership not held by any single country) and create some formal and informal interdependence between countries, with some limited [[supranationalism|supranational power]]s given to [[international organisation]]s controlled by those nations via [[intergovernmental]] treaties and institutions.

The ideal of many internationalists, among them [[world citizen]]s, is to go a step further towards [[alter-globalization|democratic globalization]] by creating a [[world government]]. However, this idea is opposed and/or thwarted by other internationalists, who believe any World Government body would be inherently too powerful to be trusted, or because they dislike the path taken by supranational entities such as the [[United Nations]] or the [[European Union]] and fear that a world government inclined towards [[fascism]] would emerge from the former. These internationalists are more likely to support a loose world [[federation]] in which most power resides with the national governments.

===United States===
The [[United States of America]] is a member of the [[North American Free Trade Agreement]], the [[United Nations]], [[Central American Free Trade Agreement]], the [[Security and Prosperity Partnership]], among others.  The United States nearly became a member in the [[Free Trade Agreement of the Americas]], which would have initially opened trade with all nations in North and South America except Cuba.

However, many [[economic nationalism|economic nationalists]] suspect that &quot;free&quot; trade, one of the aspects of internationalism, with [[China]] is not &quot;free&quot; and not under control{{Citation needed|date=June 2009}}.  What assists in this argument is the fact that China subsidizes their industries 17%  to keep their currency artificially low and to tariff American goods.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thenewamerican.com/reviews/commentary/453/ The John Birch Society: 50 Years and Beyond, The New American]&lt;/ref&gt;

====George Washington and Thomas Jefferson====
[[George Washington|Washington]] advised the United States, in [[George Washington's Farewell Address|his Farewell Address]], to remain a neutral player in the international political game. He urged the new republic to avoid conflicts and alliances with other nations. Although he felt that economic ties with other nations should be promoted to encourage trade and commerce, political ties should be minimal. He was concerned that having close relations could force the United States to unite with allies to promote their interest and be drawn into their war, such as what later occurred in [[World War I]] and [[World War II]]. Likewise, he was concerned that strongly discordant relations would do the same and that both situations could force the US into conflicts that may not be important to the US. In addition, he was concerned that these types of relations would cause passion-driven foreign policy rather than policy based upon the nation's interest. Quoting him, &quot;It is our true policy to steer clear of permanent alliances with any portion of the foreign world.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://avalon.law.yale.edu/18th_century/washing.asp George Washington, Presidential Farewell Address, September 17, 1796]&lt;/ref&gt; 

However, George Washington was not the only Founding Father of the United States to advise neutrality in foreign affairs.  [[Thomas Jefferson]], stated as early as 1799 that &quot;Commerce with all nations, alliance with none, should be our motto&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gutenberg.org/files/16783/16783-h/16783-h.htm#2H_4_0253 Thomas Jefferson, LETTER CCLII.—TO T. LOMAX, March 12, 1799]&lt;/ref&gt; and in 1801 &quot;I deem [one of] the essential principles of our government [to be] peace, commerce, and honest friendship with all nations, entangling alliances with none.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Thomas Jefferson, 1801&lt;/ref&gt; However, Jefferson did believe that nations could work together when faced with common threats. As a diplomat in Europe during the 1780s, Jefferson unsuccessfully attempted to organize a multi-national coalition to mount a naval campaign against the [[Barbary Pirates]] of North Africa.

===Britain===
In nineteenth century [[United Kingdom|Britain]] there was a [[Liberal international relations theory|liberal]] internationalist strand of political thought epitomised by [[Richard Cobden]] and [[John Bright]]. Cobden and Bright were against the [[protectionist]] [[Corn Law]]s and in a speech at [[Covent Garden]] on September 28, 1843 Cobden outlined this brand of internationalism:

''[[Free Trade]]! What is it? Why, breaking down the barriers that separate nations; those barriers behind which nestle the feelings of [[pride]], [[revenge]], [[hatred]] and jealously, which every now and then burst their bounds and deluge whole countries with blood...''&lt;ref&gt;[http://cafehayek.typepad.com/hayek/2004/09/peace_and_free_.html Peace and Freedom, Cafe Hayek]&lt;/ref&gt;

Cobden therefore believed that Free Trade would pacify the world by [[interdependence]] (see [[Cobdenism]]), an idea also expressed by [[Adam Smith]] in his [[The Wealth of Nations]] and common to many liberals of the time. A belief in the idea of the [[moral law]] and an inherent goodness in [[human nature]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.archive.org/stream/richardcobdenlan00cobduoft/richardcobdenlan00cobduoft_djvu.txt Full text of &quot;Richard Cobden and the land of the people&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; also inspired their faith in internationalism. 

In the twentieth century a [[Gladstonian Liberalism|Gladstonian liberal]] who became a [[socialist]] after [[World War I]], [[J. A. Hobson]] in his book ''Imperialism'' (1902), anticipated the growth of international courts and congresses which would hopefully settle international disputes between nations in a peaceful way. Sir [[Norman Angell]] in his work ''The Great Illusion'' (1910) claimed that the world was united by trade, finance, industry and communications and that therefore nationalism was an anachronism and that war would not profit anyone involved but would only result in destruction.

[[Philip Kerr, 11th Marquess of Lothian|Lord Lothian]] was an internationalist and an [[imperialist]] who in December 1914 looked forward to:

''the voluntary federation of the free civilised nations which will eventually exorcise the spectre of competitive armaments and give lasting peace to mankind.''.&lt;ref&gt;J.R.M. Butler, ''Lord Lothian 1882-1940''. Macmillan, 1960, p. 56&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 1915 he thought the [[British Empire]] was 'the perfect example of the eventual world [[Commonwealth]]'.&lt;ref&gt;J.R.M. Butler, ''Lord Lothian 1882-1940''. Macmillan, 1960, p. 57&lt;/ref&gt;

Internationalism expressed itself in Britain through the endorsement of the [[League of Nations]] by such people as [[Gilbert Murray]]. Both the [[Liberal Party (UK)|Liberal Party]] and more so the [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]] had prominent internationalist members, like the Labour [[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom|Prime Minister]] [[Ramsay Macdonald]] who believed that '''our true [[nationality]] is mankind'''.&lt;ref&gt;[[Lord Vansittart]], ''The Mist Procession'', p. 373&lt;/ref&gt;

==Other uses==
*In a less restricted sense, '''internationalism''' is a word describing the impetus and motivation for the creation of any [[international organization]]s. The earliest such example of broad internationalism would be the drive to replace feudal systems of measurement with the [[metric system]], long before the creation of international organizations like the [[World Court]], the [[League of Nations]], and the [[United Nations]].

*In [[linguistics]], an &quot;'''internationalism'''&quot; is a [[loanword]] that, originating in one language, has been borrowed by most other languages. Other examples of such borrowings include &quot;OK&quot;, &quot;[[microscope]]&quot;, and &quot;[[tokamak]]&quot;.

*There is also '''[[proletarian internationalism]]''', the [[Marxist]] form of internationalism.

*An ''Islamic Internationalist'' viewpoint is emerging from the anti-war and post-colonial movements, based on Islamic history and culture. This appears to be distinct from the [[Nation of Islam (politics)|Nation of Islam]] movement. {{Citation needed|date=December 2010}}

*A Chinese government policy has recently been described as their '''internationalism''' plan. Broadly, this involves encouraging governmental and non-governmental Chinese companies to purchase foreign companies that own or control key resources established as critical to the growth of the Chinese economy and nation. One recent acquisition was the purchase of the American theatre company, AMC Theatres, for approximately 2.6 billion dollars. Although AMC Theatres registered a large loss in profits in the previous year, the Chinese purchasing company, Dalian Wanda Group, nevertheless acquired the weak company in order to enlarge their presence in North America. This was described as in line with the Chinese &quot;internationalism&quot; plan to grow their interests worldwide. http://www.inquisitr.com/240226/amc-theaters-purchased-by-chinese-conglomerate/

==See also==
*[[Anti-nationalism]]
*[[Cosmopolitanism]]
*[[Cross-culturalism]]
*[[Global Citizens Movement]]
*[[Global justice]]
*[[Global village (term)|Global village]]
*[[Globalisation]]
*[[International community]]
*[[Transnationalism]]
*[[World community]]

&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Geyer|first=Martin|title=The Mechanics of Internationalism|year=2001|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; == References ==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book|last= Ankerl |first= Guy |title= Global communication without universal civilization |year= 2000 |series= INU societal research |volume= Vol.1: Coexisting contemporary civilizations : Arabo-Muslim, Bharati, Chinese, and Western |publisher= INU Press |location= Geneva |isbn= 2-88155-004-5 |pages= }}

==External links==
* [http://www.santafe.edu/~shalizi/reviews/pop-internationalism/ ''Pop Internationalism'' by Paul Krugman]

{{World government}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Internationalism (Politics)}}
[[Category:Human migration]]
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Politics and race]]
[[Category:World government]]

[[ca:Internacionalisme]]
[[de:Internationalismus]]
[[et:Internatsionalism]]
[[es:Internacionalismo]]
[[eo:Internaciismo]]
[[eu:Internazionalismo]]
[[fa:بین‌الملل‌گرایی]]
[[gl:Internacionalismo (política)]]
[[ko:국제주의]]
[[ky:Интернационализм]]
[[lt:Internacionalizmas]]
[[ml:അന്താരാഷ്ട്രീയത]]
[[nl:Internationalisme]]
[[no:Internasjonalisme]]
[[pl:Internacjonalizm]]
[[pt:Internacionalismo]]
[[ru:Интернационализм]]
[[ckb:ئینتەرناسیۆنالیزم (سیاسی)]]
[[sr:Интернационализам]]
[[sh:Internacionalizam (politika)]]
[[sv:Internationalism]]
[[uk:Інтернаціоналізм]]
[[zh:国际主义]]</text>
      <sha1>mr6fmzvuhneuzvu51ib095wowakzauc</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
