<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Islamic state</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2646438</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520118593</id>
      <parentid>513160198</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-27T14:36:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>110.139.12.110</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Early Islamic Governments */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12987">{{Islamism  sidebar}}
{{Forms of government}}  
An '''Islamic state''' ({{lang-ar|الدولة الإسلامية}} ''{{transl|ar|ALA-LC|al-dawlah al-islamīyah}}'') is a type of government, in which the primary basis for government is [[sharia|Islamic religious law]].   From the early years of Islam, numerous governments have been founded as &quot;Islamic&quot;, beginning most notably with the [[Caliphate]] established by [[Mohammad]] himself and including subsequent governments ruled under the direction of a [[caliph]] (meaning, &quot;successor&quot; to the prophet Mohammad).

However, the term &quot;Islamic state&quot; has taken on a more specific modern connotation since the 20th century. The concept of the modern Islamic state has been articulated and promoted by ideologues such as [[Abul Ala Maududi]], Ayatollah [[Ruhallah Khomeini]], and [[Sayyid Qutb]]. Like the earlier notion of the [[caliphate]], the modern Islamic state is rooted in [[shari'a|Islamic law]]. It is modeled after the rule of [[Mohammad]].  However, unlike caliph-led governments which were imperial [[despotism]]s or [[monarchies]] (Arabic: &quot;[[mulk]]&quot;), a ''modern'' Islamic state can incorporate modern political institutions such as [[elections]], [[parliamentary]] rule, [[judicial review]], and [[popular sovereignty]]. 
{{See also|Islamic democracy|Islamic republic|Guardianship of the Islamic Jurists}}

==The Historical Islamic state==
===Early Islamic Governments===
{{Main|Caliphate}}
The term [[caliphate]] refers to the first system of government established by [[Muhammad]] (S.A.W) in 622 CE, under the [[Constitution of Medina]].  It represented the political unity of the Muslim [[Ummah]] (nation), although it did not always incorporate the full ''religious'' community of Muslims (for example, [[Kharijites]] and [[Shia]]).  It was subsequently led by [[Muhammad]]'s disciples who were known as the Rightly Guided (''[[Rashidun]]'') [[Caliphs]] (632-661 CE).  The [[Arabian Empire]] significantly expanded under the [[Umayyad Caliphate]] (622-750) and the [[Abbasid Caliphate]] (750-1258).

===The Essence of Islamic Governments===
The essence or guiding principles of an Islamic government or Islamic state, is the concept of 'Al-Shura'. Different scholars have different understandings or thoughts, with regard to the concept al-Shura, However, most Muslim scholars are of the opinion that Islamic al-Shura should consist of:&lt;ref&gt; Jeong Chun Hai &amp; Nor Fadzlina Nawi. (2007). ''Principles of Public Administration: An Introduction.'' Kuala Lumpur: Karisma Publications. ISBN 978-983-195-253-5&lt;/ref&gt;

* Meeting or consultation, that follows the teachings of Islam.
* Consultation following the guidelines of the Quran and Sunnah.
* There is a leader elected among them to head the meeting.
* The discussion should be based on mushawarah and mudhakarah. 
* All the members are given fair opportunity to voice out their opinions. 
* The issue should be of maslahah ammah or public interest.
* The voices of the majority are accepted, provided that it does not violate with the teachings of the Quran or Sunnah.   

Prophet Muhammad himself respected the decision of the shura members. He is the champion of the notion of al-shura, and this was illustrated in one of the many historical events, such as, in the Battle of Khandaq (Battle of the Ditch), where the Prophet was faced with two decisions, i.e. to fight the unbelievers outside Medina or within Medina. After consultation with the sahabahs (companions), it was suggested by Salman al-Farsi that it would be better if the Muslim fought the unbelievers within Medina by building a big ditch on the northern periphery of Medina to prevent the enemies from entering Medina. This idea was later supported by the majority of the sahabahs, and thereafter, the Prophet also  approved it.

The raison d'être the Prophet placed great emphasis on the agreement of the decision of the shura, is to respect the decree of the shura members, and because the majority of opinion (by the sahabah) are supposedly better than the decision made by one individual. However, it should be emphasized here that the decision of the shura should not in any way violate the teaching of Islam, Quran and Sunnah.

===The Revival and Abolition of the Ottoman Caliphate===
{{Main|Ottoman Caliphate}}
The Ottoman Sultan Selim I (1876–1909) reclaimed the title of Caliph, which had been in dispute and asserted by a diversity of rulers and &quot;shadow caliphs&quot; in the centuries of the Abbasid-Mamluk Caliphate since the [[Siege of Baghdad (1258)|Mongols' sacking of Baghdad]] and the killing of the last Abbasid Caliph in Baghdad in Iraq 1258.

The [[Ottoman Caliphate|abolition of the Ottoman Caliphate]] as an office of the Ottoman Empire occurred under [[Mustafa Kemal Ataturk]] in 1924 as part of [[Ataturk's reforms]].  This move was most vigorously protested in India, as [[Gandhi]] and Indian Muslims united behind the ''symbolism'' of the Ottoman Caliph in the [[Khilafat Movement|Khilafat (or &quot;Caliphate&quot;) Movement]], which sought to reinstate the Caliph deposed by [[Ataturk]].  This [[Khilafat Movement]] leveraged the [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] political resistance to the [[British Empire]], and this international anti-imperial connection proved to be a galvanizing force during [[Indian Nationalism|India's nascent nationalism movement]] of the early 1900s, for Hindus and Muslims alike, even though India was far from the seat of the Ottoman Caliphate in Istanbul.

==The Modern &quot;Islamic State&quot;==
===Origins in 20th-century nationalist and anti-imperialist movements===
{{See also|Abul Ala Maududi}}
&quot;The very term, 'Islamic State', was never used in the theory or practice of Muslim political science, before the twentieth century,&quot; a Pakistani scholar wrote,&lt;ref&gt;Khan, Qamaruddin. 1982. ''Political Concepts in the Quran.'' Lahore: Islamic Book Foundation, p. 74&lt;/ref&gt; and western scholars of Islam agree.&lt;ref&gt;Eickelman, D. F., &amp; Piscatori, J. (1996). ''Muslim politics.'' Princeton: Princeton University Press, p. 53.&lt;/ref&gt;

The modern conceptualization of the &quot;Islamic state&quot; is attributed to [[Abul Ala Maududi]] (1903–1979), an Indian Muslim theologian who founded the political party [[Jamaat-e-Islami]] and inspired other Islamic revolutionaries such as Ayatollah [[Ruhallah Khomeini]].&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1996&quot;&gt;Nasr, S.V.R. 1996. Mawdudi and the Making of Islamic Revivalism, Ch. 4. New York: Oxford University Press&lt;/ref&gt; [[Abul Ala Maududi]]'s early political career was influenced greatly by anti-colonial agitation in India, especially after the tumultuous abolition of the Ottoman Caliphate in 1924 stoked anti-British sentiment (see [[Khilafat Movement]]).&lt;ref&gt;Minault, G. The Khilafat Movement: Religious Symbolism and Political Mobilization in India. New York: Columbia University Press, 1982.&lt;/ref&gt; 

The Islamic state was perceived as a &quot;third way&quot; between the rival political systems of [[democracy]] and [[socialism]] (see also [[Islamic Modernism]]).&lt;ref&gt;Kurzman, Charles. “Introduction,” in Modernist Islam 1840-1940: A Sourcebook. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;  Maududi's seminal writings on [[Islamic economics]] argued as early as 1941 against [[free-market capitalism]] and [[socialist]] state intervention in the economy, similar to [[Mohammad Baqir al-Sadr]]'s later ''[[Our Economics]]'' written in 1961. Maududi envisioned the ideal Islamic state as combining the democratic principles of electoral politics with the socialist principles of concern for the poor.&lt;ref&gt;Khir, B.M. “The Islamic Quest for Sociopolitical Justice.” In Blackwell Companion to Political Theology, edited by W.T. Cavanaugh &amp; P. Scott, 503-518. Malden, MA: Blackwell Publishing, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

===Islamic States Today===
[[Islamic republic]] is the official name given to several Islamic modeled contemporary states&lt;ref&gt;Elliesie, Hatem. [http://wikis.fu-berlin.de/download/attachments/69533704/Elliesie+Islamic+Modeled+States.pdf ''Rule of Law in Islamic Modeled States'']. In: Matthias Koetter / Gunnar Folke Schuppert (Eds.), Understanding of the Rule of Law in various Legal Orders of the World: Working Paper Series Nr. 13 of SFB 700: Governance in Limited Areas of Statehood, Berlin 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; in the [[Muslim world]], including the Islamic Republics of [[Pakistan]], [[Iran]]&lt;ref&gt;Moschtaghi, Ramin. [http://wikis.fu-berlin.de/download/attachments/22347860/Moschtaghi+Iran.pdf?version=3&amp;modificationDate=1309541940000  ''Rule of Law in Iran'']. In: Matthias Koetter / Gunnar Folke Schuppert (Eds.), Understanding of the Rule of Law in various Legal Orders of the World: Working Paper Series Nr. 11 of SFB 700: Governance in Limited Areas of Statehood, Berlin 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Afghanistan]].&lt;ref&gt;Elliesie, Hatem. [http://wikis.fu-berlin.de/download/attachments/22347868/Elliesie+Afghanistan.pdf  ''Rule of Law in Afghanistan'']. In: Matthias Koetter / Gunnar Folke Schuppert (Eds.), Understanding of the Rule of Law in various Legal Orders of the World: Working Paper Series Nr. 4 of SFB 700: Governance in Limited Areas of Statehood, Berlin 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Pakistan]] adopted the title under the constitution of 1956. [[Mauritania]] adopted it on 28 November 1958. [[Iran]] adopted it after the [[Iranian Revolution|1979 Iranian Revolution]] that overthrew the [[Pahlavi dynasty]]. In Iran, the form of government is known as &quot;[[Guardianship of the Islamic Jurists]]&quot;.  [[Afghanistan]] was run as an Islamic state in areas controlled by the Taliban from 1992–2001, and after the 2001 overthrow of the [[Taliban]] the country is still known as the [[Afghanistan|&quot;Islamic Republic of Afghanistan&quot;]]. Despite the similar name, the countries differ greatly in their governments and laws.

[[Saudi Arabia]] can be considered an Islamic state, but it is an [[absolute monarchy]] ruled by a king and therefore not known as an &quot;Islamic Republic&quot;. 

[[Pan-Islamism]] is a form of [[religious nationalism]] within [[political Islam]] which advocates the unification of the [[Muslim world]] under a single Islamic state, often described as a [[caliphate]].

The [[Libyan interim Constitutional Declaration]] of 3 August 2011 declares Islam to be official religion of [[Libya]].

==Muslim criticism of Islamic states==
Prominent Muslim intellectuals{{who|date=April 2012}} have argued that Islamic states destroy the purity of Islam.{{fact|date=April 2012}}  
{{See|Criticism of Islamism}}

===Indonesia===
Indonesian scholar [[Nurcholish Madjid]] (1939–2005) believed that the instrumental use of Islam for political ends violates the central principle of Islamic theology, [[monotheism]] (or &quot;[[tawhid]]&quot;), by mixing divine oneness with worldly politics. {{Citation needed|date=December 2011}}

===Iran===
Leading up to the [[Iranian Revolution]] of 1979, many of the highest-ranking clergy in [[Shi'a]] Islam held to the standard doctrine of the [[Imamah (Shi'a doctrine)|Imamate]], which allows political rule only by the prophet [[Mohammad]] or one of his true successors.  They were opposed to creating an Islamic state (see Ayatollah [[Abdul-Karim Ha'eri Yazdi|Ha'eri Yazdi]] ([[Khomeini]]'s own teacher), Ayatollah [[Seyyed Hossein Borujerdi|Borujerdi]], Grand Ayatollah [[Mohammad Kazem Shariatmadari|Shariatmadari]], and Grand [[Ayatollah Khui]]).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jstor.org/pss/20025388 Chehabi, H. E. 1991. Religion and Politics In Iran: How Theocratic is the Islamic Republic?. ''Daedalus, Vol 120'', No. 3, Summer 1991, pp. 69-91.]&lt;/ref&gt;  Today, contemporary theologians who were once part of the [[Iranian Revolution]] have also become disenchanted and critical of the unity of religion and state in [[Islamic Republic of Iran]], and are advocating [[secularization]] of the state to preserve the purity of the [[Islam]]ic faith (see [[Abdolkarim Soroush]] and [[Mohsen Kadivar]]).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.drsoroush.com/PDF/E-CMO-20010100-Kurzman_Critics_Within.pdf Kurzman, Charles. 2001. Critics Within: Islamic Scholars' Protest Against the Islamic State in Iran. ''International Journal of Politics,Culture and Society, Vol. 15'', No. 2, Winter 2001.].&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Criticism of Islamism]]
* [[Guardianship of the Islamic Jurists]] (in Iran)
* [[Hussein-Ali Montazeri]]
* [[Islamic republic]]
* [[Islamism]]
* [[Shariah]]
* [[Theocracy]]
* [[Hizb ut-Tahrir]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Islamic state}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Islamic State}}
[[Category:Forms of government]]
[[Category:Islamic politics and Islamic world studies|State]]
[[Category:Islamic states|*]]
[[Category:Islamism]]

[[ar:الدولة الإسلامية]]
[[bn:মুসলিম রাষ্ট্র]]
[[ca:Estat islàmic]]
[[da:Islamisk stat]]
[[es:Estado islámico]]
[[fa:حکومت اسلامی]]
[[id:negara Islam]]
[[hy:Մահմեդական պետություն]]
[[ms:Daulah Islamiyah]]
[[pt:Estado islâmico]]
[[ru:Исламское государство]]
[[simple:Islamic state]]
[[uk:Ісламська держава]]
[[zh:伊斯兰国家]]</text>
      <sha1>b628j0mxvbvo42sd5694ck8tg83gpmj</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
