<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Isolationism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>15048</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522099522</id>
      <parentid>522011915</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T01:24:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>199.106.103.57</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* INtroduction */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15499">{{distinguish|international isolation}}
{{Redirect|Isolationist|the fictional character|Isolationist (comics)}}
{{About||ambient music subgenre|Isolationism (music)|the electronic album |Isolationism (album)}}
{{Refimprove|date=September 2010}}

'''Isolationism''' is the policy or doctrine of isolating one's country from the affairs of other nations by declining to enter into alliances, foreign economic commitments, foreign trade, international agreements, etc., seeking to devote the entire efforts of one's country to its own advancement and remain at peace by avoiding foreign entanglements and responsibilities.  Two other terms often associated with Isolationism, but not necessarily the same as Isolationism, are:

#[[Non-interventionism]]&amp;nbsp;– Says that political rulers should avoid [[entangling alliances]] with other nations and avoid all wars not related to direct territorial differences ([[self-defense]]).  However, most non-interventionists are supporters of free trade, travel, and support certain international agreements, and therefore differ from isolationists.
#[[Protectionism]]&amp;nbsp;– Relates more often to economics, there should be legal barriers to control trade and cultural exchange with people in other states.

==Introduction==

&quot;Isolationism&quot; has always been a debated political topic. Whether or not a country should be or should not be isolationist affects both living standards and the ability of political rulers to benefit favored firms and industries.

{{quote|The policy or doctrine of trying to isolate one's country from the affairs of other nations by declining to enter into alliances, foreign economic commitments, international agreements, and generally attempting to make one's economy entirely self-reliant; seeking to devote the entire efforts of one's country to its own advancement, both diplomatically and economically, while remaining in a state of peace by avoiding foreign entanglements and responsibilities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.encyclopedia.com/doc/1G2-3045301744.html  &quot;Neutrality, Political,&quot;] (2008). ''International Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences''; retrieved 2011-09-18&lt;/ref&gt;}}
All the [[First World]] countries (the [[United Kingdom|UK]], [[United States]], etc.) trade in a [[world economy]], and experienced an expansion of the [[division of labor]], which generally raised [[living standard]]s. However, some characterize this as &quot;a wage [[race to the bottom]]&quot; in the [[manufacturing industry|manufacturing industries]] that should be curtailed by protectionism. Some argue that isolating a country from a global division of labor—i.e. employing protectionist trading policies—could be potentially helpful. The consensus amongst most [[economist]]s is that such a policy is detrimental, and point to the [[mercantilism]] of the pre-industrial era as the classic example. Others argue that as the world's biggest consumer, with its own natural resources, the U.S. can wisely dictate what conditions can apply to goods and services imported for U.S. consumption, misunderstanding the nature of prices and their emergent, non-centrally planned, nature. Countries and regions generally enjoy a [[comparative advantage]] over others in some area. [[Free trade]] between countries allows each country to do what it does best, and benefit from the products and services that others do best. But &quot;best&quot; too often means monetary, excluding human and [[environmentalism|ecological]] costs, due to firms externalizing costs as a result of inadequately defined [[property right]]s. Protectionism allegedly interferes in the market process, making people poorer than they would be otherwise.

==Isolationism by country==

===Albania===
{{Main|People's Socialist Republic of Albania}}
[[Albania]] was isolated from other states while it was under communist control from 1944 to 1990. Known officially as the [[People's Republic of Albania]] from 1946 to 1976, and then as the People's Socialist Republic of Albania from 1976 to 1991, Albania spent much of this time under the regime of [[Enver Hoxha]], who severely restricted citizens' freedom and contact with the outside world.

===Bhutan===
Before 1999, [[Bhutan]] had banned television and internet to preserve its culture, environment, its identity etc. Eventually, [[Jigme Singye Wangchuck]] lifted the ban on Television and Internet. His son, [[Jigme Khesar Namgyel Wangchuck]] was elected as Druk Gyalpo of Bhutan which is being transformed into a democracy.

===China===
{{Main|Haijin}}

After the [[Zheng He]] voyages in the 15th century, the foreign policy of the [[Ming Dynasty]] in [[China]] became increasingly isolationist. [[Hongwu Emperor]] was the first to propose the policy to ban all maritime shipping in 1371.&lt;ref&gt;Vo Glahn, Richard.  [1996] (1996).  Pit of Money: money and monetary policy in China, xc1000-1700. University of California Press.  ISBN 0-520-20408-5&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Qing Dynasty]] that came after the Ming often continued the latter dynasty's isolationist policies. [[Wokou]] or Japanese pirates were one of the key primary concerns, although the maritime ban was not without some control.

At the end of China’s bloody civil war, in the early and mid 1900s, the country quickly closed off its borders to many outside countries and only maintained diplomatic ties with the Soviet Union. For a period of time the Chinese attempted to become self-reliant, but found that in doing so the country could not break even economically, especially when attempting to maintain a communist vision when it came to economics. In the 1970s the People Republic of China began large radical economic reforms, which forced the country from a zero competition nation to one of the most capitalistic in the world. In doing so it quickly began to open its borders to the trade of various other countries thus adding itself to a global trade economy. While the government still regulates many of the country's cultural interactions with others, it is very open to the concept of an open market and competition with other countries, allowing the flow of technological innovations to flow in and out of its borders freely.  Mao in 1949 set China in an isolationist, and communist country, along with their Soviet benefactors.

===FR Yugoslavia===
{{Main|Yugoslav Wars}}

During the Yugoslav Wars, nearly every single nation that had ties with Serbia, had broken off diplomacy for the wars in Yugoslavia, and the rule of [[Slobodan Milošević]]. Before [[Vojislav Koštunica|Koštunica]], the country was placed under international sanctions. After the [[1999 NATO bombing of Yugoslavia]], the only foreign aide Belgrade received from was from [[Russia]], [[Greece]], and [[People's Republic of China|the PRC]]. It has been said that FR Yugoslavia was sometimes called the &quot;European North Korea&quot;.

===Japan===
{{Main|Sakoku}}

From 1641 to 1853, the [[Tokugawa shogunate]] of [[Japan]] enforced a policy which it called ''kaikin''. The policy prohibited foreign contact with most outside countries. However, the commonly held idea that Japan was entirely closed is misleading. In fact, Japan maintained limited-scale trade and diplomatic relations with [[China]], [[Korea]], the [[Ryūkyū Kingdom|Ryukyu Islands]] and the [[Netherlands]].&lt;ref&gt;Ronald P. Toby, ''State and Diplomacy in Early Modern Japan: Asia in the Development of the Tokugawa Bakufu'', Stanford, Calif.: Stanford University Press, (1984) 1991.&lt;/ref&gt;

The culture of Japan developed with limited influence from the outside world and had one of the longest stretches of peace in history. During this period, Japan developed thriving cities and castle towns and increasing commodification of agriculture and domestic trade,&lt;ref&gt;Thomas C. Smith, ''The Agrarian Origins of Modern Japan'', Stanford Studies in the Civilizations of Eastern Asia, Stanford, Calif., 1959,: Stanford University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; wage labor, increasing literacy and concomitant print culture,&lt;ref&gt;Mary Elizabeth Berry, ''Japan in Print: Information and Nation in the Early Modern Period'', Berkeley: University of California Press, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; laying the groundwork for modernization, even as the shogunate itself grew weak.&lt;ref&gt;Albert Craig, ''Chōshū in the Meiji Restoration'', Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press, 1961; Marius B. Jansen, ''Sakamoto Ryōma and the Meiji Restoration'', Princeton, N.J.: Princeton University Press, 1961.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Korea===

====Joseon Dynasty====
{{See also|Heungseon Daewongun}}

In 1863, [[Gojong of the Korean Empire|King Gojong]] took the throne of [[Joseon Dynasty]] when he was a child. His father, Regent [[Heungseon Daewongun]], ruled for him until Gojong reached adulthood. During the mid 1860s he was the main proponent of isolationism and the instrument of the persecution of native and foreign Catholics.

====North Korea====
{{Main|Foreign relations of North Korea}}
The foreign relations of [[North Korea]] are often tense and unpredictable. Since the [[s:Korean Armistice Agreement|Korean Armistice Agreement]] ended the armed conflict that existed during the active part of the [[Korean War]] in 1953, leaving a de facto truce in place ever since, the North Korean government has been largely isolationist, becoming one of the world's most authoritarian societies. While no formal peace treaty exists between North and South Korea, both diplomatic discussions and clashes have occurred between the two.  North Korea has maintained close relations with China and often limited ones with other nations. They have banned all media from other countries (such as video games, newspapers, and goods), especially [[South Korea]] and the [[United States]] and smuggling these products is illegal.

===Paraguay===

Just after independence was achieved, [[Paraguay]] was governed from 1814 by the [[dictator]] [[José Gaspar Rodríguez de Francia]], who closed the borders of the country and prohibited trade or any relation with the exterior until his death in 1840.

Francia had a particular dislike of foreigners, and the recently pre-independence settled [[Spanish people|Spanish]] had to intermarry with either the old colonists or the [[Guarani people|Guarani]], to create a single Paraguayan people. Any foreigners who came to Paraguay during his rule (which would have been very difficult) were not allowed to leave for the rest of their life. An independent character, he hated European influences and the church, turning church courtyards into artillery parks and confession boxes into border sentry posts, to keep foreigners at bay.

===Switzerland===

[[Switzerland]] is well known for staying neutral in foreign relations. The Swiss did not participate in either [[World War I]] or [[World War II]]. Switzerland also joined the [[United Nations]] much later than most other countries, and is not a member of the [[European Union]] .

===United States===

Isolationist sentiment kept the US out of both World Wars until it found itself under threat. Problems of the Old World were not relevant to the New World in the eyes of many citizens.

==See also==

*[[Imperium]]
*[[International isolation]]
*[[Monroe Doctrine]]
*[[Non-intervention]]
*[[Non-interventionism]]
*[[Sakoku]]
*[[Splendid isolation]]
*[[United States non-interventionism]]

==Works cited==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
* Barry, Tom. [http://www.irc-online.org/fpif/pdf/gac/0211power.pdf “A Global Affairs Commentary: The Terms of Power,”] ''Foreign Policy in Focus'', November 6, 2002)], University Press.
* [[Mary Elizabeth Barry|Berry, Mary Elizabeth]]. (2006). ''Japan in Print: Information and Nation in the Early Modern Period.'' Berkeley: University of California Press.	10-ISBN 0520237668/13-ISBN 9780520237667; [http://www.worldcat.org/title/japan-in-print-information-and-nation-in-the-early-modern-period/oclc/60697079&amp;referer=brief_results  OCLC 60697079]
* Chalberg, John C. (1995). ''Isolationism: Opposing Viewpoints.'' San Diego: Greenhaven Press.	10-ISBN 1565102231/13-ISBN 9781565102231; 10-ISBN 1565102223/13-ISBN 9781565102224; [http://www.worldcat.org/title/isolationism-opposing-viewpoints/oclc/30078579&amp;referer=brief_results  OCLC 30078579]
* [[Albert M. Craig|Craig, Albert]]. (1961). ''Chōshū in the Meiji Restoration.'' Cambridge: Harvard University Press. 10-ISBN 0674128508/13-ISBN 9780674128507; [http://www.worldcat.org/title/choshu-in-the-meiji-restoration/oclc/413558&amp;referer=brief_results  OCLC 413558]
* Glahn, Richard Von. (1996). ''Fountain of Fortune: Money and Monetary Policy in China,  1000-1700.'' Berkeley: University of California Press.	10-ISABN 0520204085/13-ISBN 9780520204089; [http://www.worldcat.org/title/fountain-of-fortune-money-and-monetary-policy-in-china-1000-1700/oclc/34323424?referer=br&amp;ht=edition  OCLC 34323424]
* Graebner, Norman A. (1956). ''The New Isolationism; a Study in Politics and Foreign Policy Since 1950.'' New York: Ronald Press. [http://www.worldcat.org/title/new-isolationism-a-study-in-politics-and-foreign-policy-since-1950/oclc/256173&amp;referer=brief_results  OCLC 256173]
* [[Marius Jansen|Jansen, Marius B.]]  (1961). ''Sakamoto Ryoma and the Meiji Restoration.'' Princeton: Princeton University Press. [http://www.worldcat.org/title/sakamoto-ryoma-and-the-meiji-restoration/oclc/413111&amp;referer=brief_results OCLC 413111]
* Nichols, Christopher McKnight (2011). &quot;Promise and Peril: America at the Dawn of a Global Age.&quot; Cambridge, Massachusetts: Harvard University Press, 2011. [http://www.worldcat.org/title/promise-and-peril-america-at-the-dawn-of-a-global-age/oclc/676725368&amp;referer=brief_result ]
* Nordlinger, Eric A. (1995). ''Isolationism Reconfigured: American Foreign Policy for a New Century.'' Princeton: Princeton University Press. 10-ISBN 0691043272/13-ISBN 9780691043272; [http://www.worldcat.org/title/isolationism-reconfigured-american-foreign-policy-for-a-new-century/oclc/31515131&amp;referer=brief_results  OCLC 31515131]
* Smith, Thomas C. (1959).  ''The Agrarian Origins of Modern Japan.'' Stanford: Stanford University Press. [http://www.worldcat.org/title/agrarian-origins-of-modern-japan/oclc/263403&amp;referer=brief_results OCLC 263403]
* [[Ronald Toby|Toby, Ronald P.]] (1984). ''State and Diplomacy in Early Modern Japan: Asia in the Development of the Tokugawa Bakufu.''  Princeton: Princeton University Press. 10-ISBN 0691054010/13-ISBN 9780691054018; [http://www.worldcat.org/title/state-and-diplomacy-in-early-modern-japan-asia-in-the-development-of-the-tokugawa-bakufu/oclc/9557347&amp;referer=brief_results  OCLC 9557347]
&lt;!-- in 2011, outdated hyperllink? [http://www.whitehouse.gov/nsc/nss.pdf White House, The. ''The National Security Strategy of The United States.'' (September 2002)] --&gt;

&lt;!-- interwiki links to this article in other languages, below; please maintain alphabetical order --&gt;

[[Category:International relations theory]]

[[be:Ізаляцыянізм]]
[[bg:Изолационизъм]]
[[ca:Aïllacionisme]]
[[cs:Izolacionismus]]
[[da:Isolationisme]]
[[de:Isolationismus]]
[[et:Isolatsionism]]
[[es:Aislacionismo]]
[[fr:Isolationnisme]]
[[gl:Isolacionismo]]
[[ko:고립주의]]
[[hr:Izolacionizam]]
[[it:Isolazionismo]]
[[he:בדלנות]]
[[lt:Izoliacionizmas]]
[[hu:Izolacionizmus]]
[[nl:Isolationisme]]
[[ja:孤立主義]]
[[no:Isolasjonisme]]
[[pl:Izolacjonizm]]
[[pt:Isolacionismo]]
[[ru:Изоляционизм]]
[[sk:Izolacionizmus]]
[[sr:Изолационизам]]
[[fi:Eristäytymispolitiikka]]
[[sv:Isolationism]]
[[uk:Ізоляціонізм]]
[[zh:孤立主义]]</text>
      <sha1>1lz8gbh8iebmco28h8o6dwqx78qigbu</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
