<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Jan Wong controversy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7266217</id>
    <revision>
      <id>516551406</id>
      <parentid>510951207</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-08T00:01:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ross Fraser</username>
        <id>2860013</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Journalistic reaction */  edit for brevity</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23274">{{POV|date=August 2010}}
On September 16, 2006, three days after the [[Dawson College shooting|shooting at Dawson College]] in Montreal, Canada’s nationally distributed [[newspaper of record]], ''[[The Globe &amp; Mail]]'', published a front-page article titled, “Get under the desk,”&lt;ref name=&quot;Wong&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20060915.wxshooting-main16/BNStory/National/ |title=Get under the desk |first=Jan last=Wong |newspaper=The Globe and Mail date=September 16, 2006 |accessdate= September 20, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; by [[Jan Wong]].&lt;ref name=&quot;vastel&quot;&gt;&quot;Le racisme sournois du Globe &amp; Mail&quot; by Michel Vastel, Blog for ''L'actualité'', September 18, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;  In the article, Ms. Wong controversially linked all three [[Quebec]] [[school shooting]]s of the last two decades—1989 [[École Polytechnique Massacre]] (15 deaths), 1992 [[Concordia University massacre|Concordia University Massacre]] (4 deaths), and 2006 [[Dawson College shooting|Dawson College Shooting]] (2 deaths)—to the purported [[social alienation|alienation]] brought about by “the decades-long linguistic struggle” within the province. Public outcry and political condemnation soon followed in many venues. In response, a ''Globe and Mail'' editorial attempted to minimize the controversy as a &quot;small uproar&quot; over journalistic freedom, but this caused further condemnation. Jan Wong maintained her perspective and wrote extensively about the whole experience in her book ''Out of the Blue, A Memoir of Workplace Depression, Recovery, Redemption and, Yes, Happiness''.&lt;ref name=janwong&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.janwong.ca/outoftheblue.html |title=Jan Wong - Out of the Blue |publisher=Janwong.ca |date= |accessdate=May 24, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Article ==
Wong suggested that the school shootings might have been related to the fact that the perpetrators were not old-stock French Québécois: ([[Marc Lépine]] was [[Algeria|half-Algerian]], [[Valery Fabrikant]] was a [[Russian Jews|Russian Jew]], and [[Kimveer Gill]] was of [[India]]n heritage); and they had been alienated by a Quebec society concerned with “racial purity.” Citing the history of the use of the antiquated&lt;ref name=&quot;Charest&quot;&gt;[http://www.canada.com/montrealgazette/news/story.html?id=7e75959e-b11b-4a7f-865d-2ec86fc78f4d&amp;k=53879 &quot;Charest seeks Globe apology over notion culture a factor in school shootings&quot;] by the Canadian Press, ''The Gazette'', September 19, 2006, retrieved September 20, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Robitaille&quot;&gt;&quot;Les « pures laines » coupables ?&quot; by Antoine Robitaille, ''La Presse'', September 19, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; term “[[pur laine|pure laine]],” (“pure wool”), Wong postulated the existence of a uniquely Québécois brand of racism, writing: “Elsewhere, to talk of racial ‘purity’ is repugnant. Not in Quebec.”

The article also portrayed school shootings in Canada as a Quebec phenomenon, citing Jan Bryan, columnist for the ''[[The Gazette (Montreal)|Montreal Gazette]]'', saying, “Three doesn’t mean anything. But three out of three in Quebec means something.” It also presented the Montreal anglophone community as a small-town, close-knit community.

== Public reaction ==
Hundreds of letters of complaints were received by ''The Globe and Mail''.&lt;ref name=&quot;GMEDITO&quot;&gt;&quot;Today’s Quebec&quot;, Editorial, ''The Globe and Mail'', September 21, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; As in [[Barbara Kay controversy|Barbara Kay's case]], the [[Saint-Jean-Baptiste Society]] (SSJB) lodged a complaint to the Quebec Press Council. SSJB president [[Jean Dorion]] declared &quot;There is no obsession for racial purity in Quebec, definitely not. [...] The expression 'pure laine' is absolutely obsolete.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Charest&quot;/&gt; The [[blogosphere]] soon saw a flood of posts against Wong's allegations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.ca/blogsearch?hl=fr&amp;q=%22Jan+Wong%22+Quebec&amp;lr= Google blogsearch], retrieved September 21, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

Wong received [[hate mail]], including [[racist]] comments about her Chinese ethnicity and post containing excrement. She also received a death threat that resulted in Wong's family contacting the police.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.davidhayes.ca/wong.htm |title=wong |publisher=Davidhayes.ca |date= |accessdate=2012-05-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Journalistic reaction ==

A number of Quebec journalists denounced Wong's article. [[France|French-born]] journalist [[Michel Vastel]], in his blog for the news magazine ''[[L'actualité]]'', called the article &quot;deceitful racism&quot; and the interpretation &quot;repugnant&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;vastel&quot;/&gt; His opposition was advanced again in a following ''[[Le Journal de Québec|Journal de Québec]]'' piece by Vastel.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;La semaine de toutes les hontes&quot; by Michel Vastel, ''The Globe and Mail'', September 23, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Wong's article was condemned by [[Quebec federalist ideology|federalist]] ''[[La Presse (Canadian newspaper)|La Presse]]'' editorialist [[André Pratte]] (in a letter to the ''Globe''&lt;ref&gt;&quot;’Pure laine’ is simply pure nonsense&quot; by André Pratte, ''The Globe and Mail'', September 20, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; and a ''La Presse'' editorial),&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Un journal national ?&quot; by André Pratte, ''La Presse'', September 22, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; journalists [[Michel C. Auger]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;L'arrogance&quot; by Michel C. Auger, ''La Presse'', September 21, 2006, retrieved September 21, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; of ''[[Le Journal de Montréal]]'', [[Michel David]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Mieux que le verglas!&quot; by Michel David, ''Le Devoir'', September 21, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Michel Venne]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Le droit de nous définir&quot; by Michel Venne, ''Le Devoir'', September 25, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; ([[Quebec sovereignty movement|sovereigntist]]) of ''[[Le Devoir]]'', [[Alain Dubuc]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Le crime de Jan Wong&quot; by Alain Dubuc, ''La Presse'', September 23, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; (federalist),  Vincent Marissal,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;La tribu&quot; by Vincent Marissal, ''La Presse'', September 21, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Yves Boisvert&lt;ref&gt;&quot;La loi 101 qui tue&quot; by Yves Boisvert, ''La Presse'', September 20, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Stéphane Laporte]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;What’s wrong, Mrs. Wong ?&quot; by Stéphane Laporte, ''La Presse'', September 21, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; of ''La Presse'', [[Josée Legault]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;It was outrageous for Globe writer to attack Quebecers&quot; by Josée Legault, ''The Gazette'', September 22, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; (sovereigntist) of ''[[The Gazette (Montreal)|The Gazette]]'', Jean-Jacques Samson&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Délire de journaliste&quot; by Jean-Jacques Samson, ''[[Le Journal de Québec]]'', September 21, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; of ''[[Le Soleil]]'', sovereigntist militant and author Patrick Bourgeois&lt;ref&gt;&quot;La maison de verre de Jan Wong&quot; by Patrick Bourgeois, ''Le Québécois'', September 21, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; of ''[[Le Québécois]]'', Gérald Leblanc,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Fin de la récréation!&quot; by Gérald Leblanc, ''La Presse'', September 22, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; retired journalist of ''La Presse'' and [[Joseph Facal]],&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Le Canada réel&quot; by Joseph Facal, ''Le Journal de Montréal'', September 27, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Journal de Montréal'' columnist and former [[Parti Québécois]] minister.

Although the ''Gazette'' called it &quot;nonsense&quot; in an editorial,&lt;ref name=&quot;Gazette1stWongEditorial&quot;&gt;&quot;Nonsense about language&quot;, Editorial, ''The Gazette'', September 20, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; it found the reaction to be out of proportion, as did Lysiane Gagnon from ''La Presse'', who nonetheless called the theory &quot;delirious&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;L’exploitation d’une calomnie&quot; by Lysiane Gagnon, ''La Presse'', September 21, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Gazette'' journalist [[Don Macpherson (journalist)|Don Macpherson]] wrote: &quot;By the standards of Wong’s article, one could just as easily blame the [three] shootings on federalism, since all three happened to occur while the Quebec Liberals were in power&quot;. He advanced that, on the contrary, the tragedy and the controversy around Wong's article had shown a remarkable unity between French and English-speaking Quebecers.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Tragedy brings us together&quot;, by [[Don Macpherson (journalist)|Don Macpherson]], ''The Gazette'', September 21, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Barbara Kay, author of the [[Barbara Kay controversy|&quot;Quebecistan&quot; controversy]], herself criticized Wong, calling the analysis &quot;bullshit&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Robitaille&quot;/&gt; [[Jack Jedwab]], Executive Director of the Association for Canadian Studies in Montreal and former Executive Director of the Quebec Region of the [[Canadian Jewish Congress]], noted that the expression &quot;pure laine&quot; was &quot;no longer quite common&quot;. He also called the analysis &quot;nonsense&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Robitaille&quot;/&gt; ''The Globe and Mail'' remarked that &quot;[i]n English Canada, unsurprisingly, the response has been considerably more muted&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;GMEDITO&quot;/&gt; However, on September 28, 2006, [[Warren Kinsella]] wrote a harsh criticism of Wong's work in ''[[The National Post]]''.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Jan Wong, disgrace to journalism&quot; by Warren Kinsella, ''The National Post'', September 28, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Kinsella was born in Montreal, Quebec.

Critics{{Who|date=March 2009}} of the piece contend that linguistic factors were never claimed by the assassins. According to them, Lépine had a grudge against women and feminists; Fabrikant against rival scholars; and Gill, a bullied child, targeted students and said in his notorious internet blog that Quebec was a “good place to live in.” These critics{{Who|date=March 2009}} maintain that it is incorrect to consider Lépine as not having been part of Francophone, Québécois society given that, while he may have been estranged from his Algerian-born father, he was raised mainly by his French-speaking, Québécoise mother, whose name he had adopted (he was born Gamil Gharbi). Moreover, they note that both Fabrikant and Gill targeted [[English-speaking Quebecker|anglophones]], not [[francophone]]s.
&lt;ref name=&quot;Robitaille&quot;/&gt;

== Political reaction ==

Micheline Labelle, director of the ''Centre de recherche sur l’immigration, l’ethnicité et la citoyenneté'' (CRIEC, &quot;Centre for research on immigration, ethnicity and citizenship&quot;) at the [[Université du Québec à Montréal]] stated that she saw in the arguments something akin to &quot;neoracism&quot;, that is to say, a generalization of a cultural trait applied to a given population. &quot;For less than that, minorities go to the courts&quot;, she said.&lt;ref name=&quot;Robitaille&quot;/&gt;

On September 19, 2006, the [[Canadian Press]] reported that [[Quebec federalist ideology|federalist]] Premier of Quebec [[Jean Charest]] demanded an apology, calling the article a &quot;disgrace&quot;. He sent an open letter&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.canada.com/montrealgazette/story.html?id=7558331f-14b9-4b1a-bfc1-e5a68dbe3999&amp;k=47772 Open letter] by Jean Charest, ''The Gazette'', September 19, 2006, retrieved September 20, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; to the ''Globe'' vigorously defending Quebec's society and its language protection.

{{cquote|In this kind of situation, anyone who ventures to put forward explanations or comparisons at the very least risks making a fool of himself. Jan Wong has certainly discredited herself with her gamble.&lt;br&gt;
I was shocked and disappointed by the narrow-minded analysis published in the Saturday, September 16 edition, in which Ms Wong sought to identify the affirmation of French culture in Québec as the deeper cause of the Dawson College shootings and the killings at the Polytechnique in 1989.&lt;br&gt;
Quebecers make up less than 3% of the North American population. Over the centuries, through the vicissitudes of history, we have managed to preserve our language and culture, and in so doing, cherished the highest democratic ideals. Every year, we welcome tens of thousands of individuals from the four corners of the earth, people who contribute to building a free society in Québec, a society that is proud of its difference. [...]&lt;br&gt;
Ms Wong’s article is a disgrace. It betrays an ignorance of Canadian values and a profound misunderstanding of Québec. She should have the decency to apologize to all Quebecers.|quote height in pixels|Jean Charest}}

[[Conservative Party of Canada|Conservative]] Prime Minister of Canada [[Stephen Harper]] called Wong's argument &quot;prejudiced&quot;, &quot;absurd&quot;, &quot;irresponsible&quot; and &quot;without foundation&quot;.{{Citation needed|date=June 2009}} He sent the ''Globe'' a similar letter. &quot;These actions (the killings) deserve our unqualified moral condemnation, not an excuse for printing prejudices masked in the language of social theory,&quot; Harper wrote.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harper&quot;&gt;[http://cnews.canoe.ca/CNEWS/MediaNews/2006/09/21/1872721-cp.html &quot;Harper takes Wong to task for column&quot;] by Alexander Panetta, CNEWS, September 20, 2006, retrieved September 20, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; [[Parti Québécois]] leader [[André Boisclair]] declared that the journalist had, on the intellectual level, &quot;slipped into the dregs&quot; (&quot;''glissé dans les bas fonds''&quot;).&lt;ref name=&quot;GMSRC&quot;&gt;[http://www.radio-canada.ca/nouvelles/societe/2006/09/21/001-globe-excuse-non.shtml &quot;Le Globe and Mail se défend&quot;], Société Radio-Canada, retrieved September 21, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Former Premier of Quebec [[Bernard Landry]] declared to ''[[La Tribune]]'' &quot;if she is of good faith, she will have to apologize [...] It is incredible that it is still possible today to convey such delirious opinions on Quebec. Especially in an era when Quebec is more cosmopolitan than ever. [...] It is insulting for Quebec and dishonouring for Canada. In the same way as if I saw a similar article about Ontario in La Tribune, I would be ashamed for La Tribune.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cyberpresse.ca/article/20060921/CPACTUALITES/60921049/6128/CPSPECIAL12 &quot;«Elle devra s'excuser», dit Landry&quot;] by Jean-Pierre Boisvert, ''La Tribune'', September 21, 2006, retrieved September 21, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Cameroon|Cameroon-born]] [[Bloc Québécois]] Member of Parliament [[Maka Kotto]] issued a declaration at the [[House of Commons (Canada)|Canadian House of Commons]] stating &quot;to pretend that there could be a link of any kind of cause-and-effect between the dramatic episode of Dawson College and Bill 101 — described as infamous by the journalist — pertains of a defamatory delirium disconnected from the Quebec reality. [...] Quebec is an inclusive, welcoming society where it is pleasant to live. As an immigrant, I felt very rapidly welcome there and I deplore that the openness of the Quebec people can be put into question.&quot; He invited the federal government to denounce the writings of Jan Wong as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kotto&quot;&gt;&quot;Charest exige des excuses du Globe and Mail&quot; by Jocelyne Richer, Canadian Press, September 19, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; On September 20 the House of Commons unanimously passed a motion requesting an apology &quot;to the Quebec people&quot; for the column.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cyberpresse.ca/article/20060920/CPACTUALITES/60920106/6128/CPSPECIAL12 &quot;Harper dénonce à son tour le Globe and Mail&quot;] by the Canadian Press, ''La Presse'', September 20, 2006, retrieved September 20, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; [[Denis Coderre]], the Liberal MP who tabled the motion, called the column &quot;classless&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;CBC1&quot;&gt;[http://www.cbc.ca/cp/media/060921/X092153U.html &quot;One of Harper's own MPs made same comments PM dubbed prejudiced&quot;] by Isabelle Rodrigue, Canadian Press, Canadian Broadcasting Corporation, September 21, 2006, retrieved September 22, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;People feel there's a sort [...] of trend.&quot;, he said. &quot;I think that it's enough. We're not &quot;Quebecistan&quot;, we're not a people that ostracizes, we're a model of integration.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.radio-canada.ca/util/zapmedia/version10/WMleftframe.asp?directLink=http://www.radio-canada.ca/Medianet/2006/CBF/Radiojournal200609210800_2.asx&amp;promo=&amp;duree=court Radio report], Société Radio-Canada, retrieved September 22, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Coderre was in the group of politicians attacked by Barbara Kay in the [[Barbara Kay controversy|&quot;Quebecistan&quot; controversy]], also accused of &quot;[[Quebec bashing]]&quot;. Marie-Hélène Paradis, press attaché of Quebec Minister of Immigration [[Lise Thériault]], said &quot;No data can support what Ms. Wong advances.&quot; She declared that such allegations feed &quot;the type of fast judgements that lead to discrimination.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Robitaille&quot;/&gt;

Despite having voted for the motion, Conservative Member of Parliament [[Daniel Petit]] declared that there might be a link, as Wong suggested. &quot;I think that the billion (dollars) that we put in [the [[Canadian gun registry]] ] should have been put into education and integration of immigrants in Montreal&quot;, Petit said. Dimitri Soudas, press attaché for Conservative Prime Minister Harper, said &quot;The comments of Mr. Petit are unacceptable, he should retract them and it does not reflect in any case the position of the government&quot;, adding that Petit was met by the Prime Minister's cabinet on the subject. MPs of the House of Commons criticized him for his statements, including [[Michel Gauthier]], of the Bloc Québécois, and [[Denis Coderre]], of the Liberal Party of Canada, who demanded apologies. He offered them promptly. &quot;I made inappropriate remarks,&quot; Petit said in a statement. &quot;I withdraw them entirely because you cannot draw any link between the integration of immigrants in Quebec and the terrible tragedy at Dawson College.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;CBC1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Petit&quot;&gt;[http://www.cyberpresse.ca/article/20060921/CPACTUALITES/60921157/6128/CPSPECIAL12 &quot;Un député de Québec tient des propos semblables à ceux de Wong&quot;] by the Canadian Press, ''La Presse'', September 21, 2006, retrieved September 21, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

== Globe and Mail editorial response ==
On September 21, 2006, ''The Globe and Mail'' published an editorial on the affair. Calling the controversy a &quot;small uproar&quot;, it defended the right of the journalist to question such phenomena, the &quot;need to ask hard questions and explore uncomfortable avenues&quot;, saying that it &quot;merely wondered&quot;. The editor claimed not to be surprised by the hundreds of letters of protest received, including those of [[First Minister]]s Charest and Harper. The editorial validated Wong's claims of alienation in Quebec, which the ''Globe'' called &quot;politics of exclusion&quot;. Asking whether this exclusion led to marginalization and perhaps alienation, it said that the answer is &quot;arguable&quot;. However, it called the marginalization and alienation of the three shooters &quot;obvious&quot;. About whether it could be associated with the murders, it answered that &quot;[n]o such evidence exists&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;GMEDITO&quot;/&gt; In a sentence apparently intended to balance the assertions, it implied at the same time that an even worse discrimination existed in the Quebec of the past, as it wrote: &quot;By the same token, it would be remiss to forget that today’s Quebec is not the Quebec of yesteryear.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;GMEDITO&quot;/&gt; ''The Globe and Mail'' did not issue an apology for Jan Wong's piece, as requested by many, including the unanimous House of Commons.

=== Reactions to the editorial ===
Leader of the Bloc Québécois [[Gilles Duceppe]] declared that he considered the editorial an attempt at justification.&lt;ref name=&quot;Petit&quot;/&gt; &quot;It even suggests there might be some problems in Quebec because of the language laws. It's unacceptable and it's deplorable and it's shameful for a newspaper of that stature&quot;, he said. &quot;Try imagining the opposite — If I'd made such nonsensical, absurd remarks (about English Canada). Then all the editorial writers across Canada would get involved.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;CBC1&quot;/&gt;  Premier of Quebec Jean Charest was said to be disappointed by the ''Globe and Mail'' response. He was also said to be offended by the little consideration the paper gave his open letter, that was published in the readers' opinion page (like the one from Prime Minister Harper). &quot;The (House of Commons) motion is totally ignored&quot;, said the Premier's press attaché.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Déçu de la réponse du Globe and Mail&quot; by Michel Corbeil, ''Le Soleil'', September 22, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; On September 23, 2006, the [[Canadian Press]] reported that [[Edward Greenspon]], editor of ''The Globe and Mail'', expressed regrets. In a ''Globe and Mail'' column, without making formal apologies, he wrote that the personal opinions of Wong should have been excised from the piece, not because they were unacceptable, but because they constituted a &quot;thesis&quot;, not a &quot;statement of fact&quot;. He wrote that &quot;they should have been put into a separate piece clearly marked opinion&quot;. He however believed the reaction to be clearly disproportionate.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Le Globe and Mail exprime des regrets&quot; by the Canadian Press, ''La Presse'', September 23, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Despite Greenspon's insinuation that the piece was not &quot;clearly marked opinion&quot;, it had in fact been accompanied by a headshot of Wong, the traditional means of designating opinion pieces.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.davidhayes.ca/wong.htm |title=wong |publisher=Davidhayes.ca |date= |accessdate=2012-05-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Jan Wong's response ==

Jan Wong declined the invitation of host [[Guy A. Lepage]] to explain herself at the popular Québécois talk show ''[[Tout le monde en parle (Quebec)|Tout le monde en parle]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;GMSRC&quot;/&gt; She has declared: &quot;I brought forward a point of view [...] and I maintain it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''La Presse'', September 21, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; She has claimed that, during the controversy, she was the target of sexist and racist attacks, citing a ''Le Devoir'' cartoon that caricatured Wong with thick glasses and buck teeth opening a [[fortune cookie]] that said &quot;Beware of Bill 101&quot;. The newspaper claimed that it was a reference to the [[Chinese cuisine|Chinese restaurant]]s of her well-known father, Bill Wong, not her ethnicity. Jan Wong wrote extensively about the whole experience in her book ''Out of the Blue, A Memoir of Workplace Depression, Recovery, Redemption and Yes, Happiness''.&lt;ref name=janwong&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.janwong.ca/outoftheblue.html |title=Jan Wong - Out of the Blue |publisher=Janwong.ca |date= |accessdate=May 24, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In it, Jan Wong described in detail the backlash she received immediately after her article published, how the Globe and Mail management, in her view, abandoned her in front of the torrent of negative reactions from all sides, and how she spiraled down into depression.  She described when she found the ‘exact moment I began my descent into depression’ when she was shattered by racial attack. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://fullcomment.nationalpost.com/2012/05/20/jan-wong-why-i-was-hated-in-quebec-and-abandoned-in-toronto/|title=Why I was hated in Quebec and abandoned in Toront|author=Wong, Jan|publisher=[[National Post]]|date=May 20, 2012|accessdate=May 24, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This book was self-published after [[Doubleday]], the publisher of her previous books, pulled out mere days before print although Doubleday denied any legal interference from ''The Globe''. &lt;ref name&gt;{{cite news|last=Gessell|first=Paul|title=Jan Wong's blues|url=http://www.ottawacitizen.com/entertainment/Wong+blues/6566814/story.html|accessdate=May 24, 2012|newspaper=[[Ottawa Citizen]]|date=May 4, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It was released on May 5, 2012. &lt;ref name=janwong&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.janwong.ca/outoftheblue.html |title=Jan Wong - Out of the Blue |publisher=Janwong.ca |date= |accessdate=May 24, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
*[[Anti-Quebec sentiment]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Jan Wong Controversy}}
[[Category:Anti-Quebec sentiment]]
[[Category:Political history of Quebec]]
[[Category:2006 in Canada]]
[[Category:Political controversies in Canada]]
[[Category:Canadian journalism]]
[[Category:The Globe and Mail]]</text>
      <sha1>g73z25hkw5npqyb5p1qk61bc88hpzjq</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
