<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Jean-Jacques Rousseau</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>15941</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522094746</id>
      <parentid>522086261</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T00:44:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Alcmaeonid</username>
        <id>3780190</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/68.48.2.59|68.48.2.59]] ([[User talk:68.48.2.59|talk]]). ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="94981">{{About|the philosopher|other uses|Rousseau (disambiguation)}}
{{Infobox philosopher
|region = Western Philosophers
|era = [[18th century philosophy]]&lt;br /&gt;([[Modern philosophy]])
|image = Jean-Jacques Rousseau (painted portrait).jpg
|caption = Rousseau in 1753, by [[Maurice Quentin de La Tour]]
|birth_date  = {{Birth date|df=yes|1712|6|28}}
|birth_place = [[Geneva]], [[Republic and Canton of Geneva#History|Republic of Geneva]]
|death_date  = {{Death date and age|df=yes|1778|7|2|1712|6|28}}
|death_place = [[Ermenonville]], [[Kingdom of France]]
|school_tradition = [[Social contract theory]]&lt;br&gt;[[Romanticism]]
|main_interests = [[Political philosophy]], music, education, literature, autobiography
|signature=
|influences = [[Aristotle]], [[Cicero]], [[Niccolò Machiavelli]], [[Baruch Spinoza]], [[Michel de Montaigne]], [[Hugo Grotius]], [[Samuel von Pufendorf]], [[Thomas Hobbes]], [[John Locke]], [[Jean Barbeyrac]], [[Jean-Jacques Burlamaqui]], [[Denis Diderot]]
|influenced = [[Immanuel Kant|Kant]], the [[French Revolution]], [[Maximillien Robespierre|Robespierre]], [[Louis de Saint-Just]], [[The Counter-Enlightenment]], [[Johann Gottlieb Fichte|Fichte]], [[Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel|Hegel]], [[Johann Wolfgang von Goethe|Goethe]], [[Alexis de Tocqueville]], [[Friedrich Nietzsche]], [[Romanticism]], [[Thomas Paine|Paine]], [[Marquis de Sade|de Sade]], [[Auguste Comte|Comte]], [[Simón Bolívar|Bolívar]], [[Karl Marx|Marx]], [[Friedrich Engels|Engels]], [[Jacques Derrida|Derrida]], [[Paul de Man]], [[Benedetto Croce]], [[Galvano Della Volpe]], [[Claude Lévi-Strauss]], [[Leo Strauss]], [[Mary Shelley]], [[Maine de Biran]], [[Émile Durkheim]], [[Mikhail Bakunin]], [[Maria Montessori]], [[Leo Tolstoy]], [[John Rawls]], [[Michel Clouscard]], [[Juan José Castelli]], [[Mustafa Kemal Atatürk]]
|notable_ideas = [[General will]], [[amour-propre]], [[Human nature#State of nature|moral simplicity of humanity]], [[child-centered learning]], [[civil religion]], [[popular sovereignty]], [[positive liberty]]
}}

'''Jean-Jacques Rousseau''' ({{IPA-fr|ʒɑ̃ʒak ʁuso|lang}}; 28 June 1712{{spaced ndash}}2 July 1778) was a [[Geneva]]n philosopher, writer, and composer of 18th-century [[Romanticism]] of French expression. His [[political philosophy]] influenced the [[French Revolution]] as well as the overall development of modern political, sociological and educational thought.

His novel ''[[Émile: or, On Education]]'' is a treatise on the education of the whole person for citizenship. His [[sentimental novel]] [[Julie, or the New Heloise]] was of importance to the development of pre-romanticism&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.enotes.com/literary-criticism/preromanticism |title=Preromanticism Criticism |publisher=Enotes.com |accessdate=23 February 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[romanticism]] in fiction.&lt;ref&gt;See also Robert Darnton, ''The Great Cat Massacre'', chapter 6: &quot;Readers Respond to Rousseau: The Fabrication of Romantic Sensitivity&quot; for some interesting examples of contemporary reactions to this novel.&lt;/ref&gt; Rousseau's autobiographical writings—his ''[[Confessions (Jean-Jacques Rousseau)|Confessions]]'', which initiated the modern autobiography, and his ''[[Reveries of a Solitary Walker]]''—exemplified the late 18th-century movement known as the ''Age of Sensibility'', featuring an increasing focus on subjectivity and introspection that has characterized the modern age. His ''[[Discourse on the Origin of Inequality]]'' and his ''[[On the Social Contract]]'' are cornerstones in modern political and social thought.

Rousseau was a successful composer of music. He wrote seven operas as well as music in other forms, and he made contributions to music as a theorist.

During the period of the French Revolution, Rousseau was the most popular of the ''philosophes'' among members of the [[Jacobin Club]]. Rousseau, a [[Freemason]],&lt;ref&gt;Leo Damrosch, ''Jean-Jacques Rousseau: Restless Genius'' (New York: Houghton Mifflin, 2005) p. 492.&lt;/ref&gt; was interred as a national hero in the [[Panthéon (Paris)|Panthéon]] in Paris, in 1794, 16 years after his death.

==Biography==

===Youth===
Rousseau was born in [[Geneva]], which was at the time a city-state and a Protestant associate of the [[Old Swiss Confederacy|Swiss Confederacy]]. Since 1536, Geneva had been a [[Huguenot]] republic and the seat of [[Calvinism]]. Rousseau was proud that his family, of the ''moyen'' order (or middle-class), had voting rights in the city. Throughout his life, he generally signed his books &quot;Jean Jacques Rousseau, Citizen of Geneva&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Leo Damrosch, ''Jean-Jacques Rousseau: Restless Genius'' (New York: Houghton Mifflin, 2005) p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt;

Geneva, in theory, was governed democratically by its male voting citizens, a minority of the population. In fact, the city was ruled by a secretive executive committee, called the &quot;[[Little Council]]&quot;, which was made up of 25 members of its wealthiest families. In 1707, a patriot called [[Pierre Fatio]] protested at this situation, and the Little Council had him shot. Jean-Jacques Rousseau's father Isaac was not in the city at this time, but Jean-Jacques's grandfather supported Fatio and was penalized for it.&lt;ref&gt;Leo Damrosch, ''Jean-Jacques Rousseau: Restless Genius'' (New York: Houghton Mifflin, 2005) p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Rousseau Geneve House.JPG|thumb|The house where Rousseau was born at number 40, place du Bourg-de-Four.]]
Rousseau's father, Isaac Rousseau, was a watchmaker who, notwithstanding his artisan status, was well educated and a lover of music. &quot;A Genevan watchmaker,&quot; Rousseau wrote, &quot;is a man who can be introduced anywhere; a Parisian watchmaker is only fit to talk about watches.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;And indeed, a British visitor commented, ‘Even the lower class of people [of Geneva] are exceedingly well informed, and there is perhaps no city in Europe where learning is more universally diffused&quot;; another at midcentury noticed that Genevan workmen were fond of reading the works of Locke and Montesquieu.” See Leo Damrosch, ''Jean-Jacques Rousseau: Restless Genius'', p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt;

Rousseau's mother, Suzanne Bernard Rousseau, the daughter of a Calvinist preacher, died of [[puerperal fever]] nine days after his birth. He and his older brother François were brought up by their father and a paternal aunt, also named Suzanne.

Rousseau had no recollection of learning to read, but he remembered how when he was 5 or 6 his father encouraged his love of reading:{{cquote2|Every night, after supper, we read some part of a small collection of romances [i.e., adventure stories], which had been my mother's. My father's design was only to improve me in reading, and he thought these entertaining works were calculated to give me a fondness for it; but we soon found ourselves so interested in the adventures they contained, that we alternately read whole nights together and could not bear to give over until at the conclusion of a volume. Sometimes, in the morning, on hearing the swallows at our window, my father, quite ashamed of this weakness, would cry, &quot;Come, come, let us go to bed; I am more a child than thou art.&quot;|Confessions, Book 1}} Not long afterward, Rousseau abandoned his taste for escapist stories in favor of the antiquity of [[Plutarch]]'s ''[[Parallel Lives|Lives of the Noble Greeks and Romans]]'', which he would read to his father while he made watches.

When Rousseau was 10, his father, an avid hunter, got into a legal quarrel with a wealthy landowner on whose lands he had been caught trespassing. To avoid certain defeat in the courts, he moved away to Nyon in the territory of Bern, taking Rousseau's aunt Suzanne with him. He remarried, and from that point Jean-Jacques saw little of him.&lt;ref&gt;Damrosch, p. 24.&lt;/ref&gt; Jean-Jacques was left with his maternal uncle, who packed him, along with his own son, Abraham Bernard, away to board for two years with a Calvinist minister in a hamlet outside Geneva. Here the boys picked up the elements of mathematics and drawing. Rousseau, who was always deeply moved by religious services, for a time even dreamed of becoming a Protestant minister.

[[File:LesCharmettes.jpg|thumb|250px|Les Charmettes: where Rousseau lived with [[Françoise-Louise de Warens|Mme de Warens]] in 1735-6, now a museum dedicated to Rousseau.]]
Virtually, all our information about Rousseau's youth has come from his posthumously published ''Confessions'', in which the chronology is somewhat confused, though recent scholars have combed the archives for confirming evidence to fill in the blanks. At age 13, Rousseau was apprenticed first to a [[civil law notary|notary]] and then to an engraver who beat him. At 15, he ran away from Geneva (on 14 March 1728) after returning to the city and finding the city gates locked due to the curfew. 

In adjoining [[Savoy]] he took shelter with a Roman Catholic priest, who introduced him to [[Françoise-Louise de Warens]], age 29. She was a noblewoman of Protestant background who was separated from her husband. As professional lay proselytizer, she was paid by the King of [[Piedmont]] to help bring Protestants to Catholicism. They sent the boy to [[Turin]], the capital of Savoy (which included Piedmont, in what is now Italy), to complete his conversion. This resulted in his having to give up his Genevan citizenship, although he would later revert to Calvinism in order to regain it.

In converting to Catholicism, both De Warens and Rousseau were likely reacting to Calvinism's insistence on the [[total depravity]] of man. Leo Damrosch writes, &quot;an eighteenth-century Genevan liturgy still required believers to declare ‘that we are miserable sinners, born in corruption, inclined to evil, incapable by ourselves of doing good'.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Rousseau: Restless Genius'', p. 121.&lt;/ref&gt; De Warens, a [[deist]] by inclination, was attracted to Catholicism's doctrine of forgiveness of sins.

===Adulthood===
Finding himself on his own, since his father and uncle had more or less disowned him, the teenage Rousseau supported himself for a time as a servant, secretary, and tutor, wandering in Italy (Piedmont and Savoy) and France. During this time, he lived on and off with De Warens, whom he idolized and called his &quot;''maman''&quot;. Flattered by his devotion, De Warens tried to get him started in a profession, and arranged formal music lessons for him. At one point, he briefly attended a seminary with the idea of becoming a priest. 

When Rousseau reached 20, De Warens took him as her lover, while intimate also with the steward of her house. The sexual aspect of their relationship (in fact a ''[[ménage à trois]]'') confused Rousseau and made him uncomfortable, but he always considered De Warens the greatest love of his life. A rather profligate spender, she had a large library and loved to entertain and listen to music. She and her circle, comprising educated members of the Catholic clergy, introduced Rousseau to the world of letters and ideas. 

Rousseau had been an indifferent student, but during his 20s, which were marked by long bouts of [[hypochondria]], he applied himself in earnest to the study of philosophy, mathematics, and music. At 25, he came into a small inheritance from his mother and used a portion of it to repay De Warens for her financial support of him. At 27, he took a job as a tutor in [[Lyon]].

In 1742, Rousseau moved to Paris in order to present the [[Académie des Sciences]] with a new system of [[numbered musical notation]] he believed would make his fortune. His system, intended to be compatible with [[typography]], is based on a single line, displaying numbers representing [[interval (music)|intervals]] between notes and dots and commas indicating rhythmic values. Believing the system was impractical, the Academy rejected it, though they praised his mastery of the subject, and urged him to try again.

[[File:Rousseauvenicembassy.jpg|thumb|250px|Palazzo belonging to Tommaso Querini at 968 Cannaregio [[Venice]] that served as the French Embassy during Rousseau's period as Secretary to the Ambassador]]
From 1743 to 1744, Rousseau had an honorable but ill-paying post as a secretary to the Comte de Montaigue, the French ambassador to [[Venice]]. This awoke in him a lifelong love for Italian music, particularly opera: &lt;blockquote&gt;I had brought with me from Paris the prejudice of that city against Italian music; but I had also received from nature a sensibility and niceness of distinction which prejudice cannot withstand. I soon contracted that passion for Italian music with which it inspires all those who are capable of feeling its excellence. In listening to barcaroles, I found I had not yet known what singing was...&amp;nbsp;—''Confessions''&lt;/blockquote&gt; Rousseau's employer routinely received his stipend as much as a year late and paid his staff irregularly.&lt;ref&gt;Leo Damrosch describes the count as “a virtual parody of a parasitic aristocrat, incredibly stupid, irascible, and swollen with self importance.&quot; He spoke no Italian, a language in which Rousseau was fluent. Although Rousseau did most of the work of the embassy, he was treated like a valet. (See Damrosch, p. 168).&lt;/ref&gt; After 11 months, Rousseau quit, taking from the experience a profound distrust of government bureaucracy.

==== Return to Paris ====
Returning to Paris, the penniless Rousseau befriended and became the lover of [[Thérèse Levasseur]], a seamstress who was the sole support of her mother and numerous ne'er-do-well siblings. At first, they did not live together, though later Rousseau took Thérèse and her mother in to live with him as his servants, and himself assumed the burden of supporting her large family. According to his ''Confessions'', before she moved in with him, Thérèse bore him a son and as many as four other children (there is no independent verification for this number&lt;ref&gt;Some of Rousseau's contemporaries believed the babies were not his. George Sand has written an essai, &quot;Les Charmettes&quot; (1865. Printed in the same volume as &quot;Laura&quot; from the same year) in which she explains why Rousseau may have accused himself falsely. She quotes her grandmother, in whose family Rousseau had been a tutor, and who stated that Rousseau could not get children.&lt;/ref&gt;). 

Rousseau wrote that he persuaded Thérèse to give each of the newborns up to a foundling hospital, for the sake of her &quot;honor&quot;. &quot;Her mother, who feared the inconvenience of a brat, came to my aid, and she [Thérèse] allowed herself to be overcome&quot; (''Confessions''). In his letter to Madame de Francueil in 1751, he first pretended that he wasn't rich enough to raise his children but in book IX of the confessions, he gave the true reasons of his choice : &quot; ''I trembled at the thought of intrusting them to a family ill brought up, to be still worse educated. The risk of the education of the [[foundling hospital]] was much less.''&quot;

Ten years later, Rousseau made inquiries about the fate of his son, but no record could be found. When Rousseau subsequently became celebrated as a theorist of education and child-rearing, his abandonment of his children was used by his critics, including [[Voltaire]] and [[Edmund Burke]], as the basis for ''ad hominem'' attacks. In an irony of fate, Rousseau's later injunction to women to breastfeed their own babies (as had previously been recommended by the French natural scientist [[Georges-Louis Leclerc, Comte de Buffon|Buffon]]), probably saved the lives of thousands of infants.{{Citation needed|date=September 2012}}

While in Paris, Rousseau became a close friend of French philosopher [[Denis Diderot|Diderot]] and, beginning with some articles on music in 1749,&lt;ref&gt;Rousseau in his musical articles in the Encyclopedie engaged in lively controversy with other musicians, e.g. with Rameau, as in his article on Temperament, for which see [http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/text-idx?c=did;cc=did;rgn=main;view=text;idno=did2222.0000.897 Encyclopédie: Tempérament] (English translation), also [[Temperament Ordinaire]].&lt;/ref&gt; contributed numerous articles to Diderot and [[D'Alembert]]'s great [[Encyclopédie]], the most famous of which was an article on political economy written in 1755.

Rousseau's ideas were the result of an almost obsessive dialogue with writers of the past, filtered in many cases through conversations with Diderot. His genius lay in his strikingly original way of putting things rather than in the originality, ''per se'', of his thinking. In 1749, Rousseau was paying daily visits to Diderot, who had been thrown into the fortress of [[Vincennes]] under a ''[[lettre de cachet]]'' for opinions in his &quot;''[[Lettre sur les aveugles à l'usage de ceux qui voient|Lettre sur les aveugles]]'',&quot; that hinted at [[materialism]], a belief in [[atoms]], and natural selection. 

Rousseau had read about an essay competition sponsored by the [[Académie de Dijon]] to be published in the ''Mercure de France'' on the theme of whether the development of the arts and sciences had been morally beneficial. He wrote that while walking to Vincennes (about three miles from Paris), he had a revelation that the arts and sciences were responsible for the moral degeneration of mankind, who were basically good by nature. According to Diderot, writing much later, Rousseau had originally intended to answer this in the conventional way, but his discussions with Diderot convinced him to propose the paradoxical negative answer that catapulted him into the public eye. Rousseau's 1750 &quot;''[[Discourse on the Arts and Sciences]]''&quot; was awarded the first prize and gained him significant fame.

Rousseau continued his interest in music. He wrote both the words and music of his opera ''[[Le Devin du Village]]'' (''The Village Soothsayer''), which was performed for [[Louis XV of France|King Louis XV]] in 1752. The king was so pleased by the work that he offered Rousseau a lifelong pension. To the exasperation of his friends, Rousseau turned down the great honor, bringing him notoriety as &quot;the man who had refused a king's pension.&quot; He also turned down several other advantageous offers, sometimes with a brusqueness bordering on truculence that gave offense and caused him problems. The same year, the visit of a troupe of Italian musicians to Paris, and their performance of [[Giovanni Battista Pergolesi]]'s ''[[La Serva Padrona]]'', prompted the [[Querelle des Bouffons]], which pitted protagonists of French music against supporters of the Italian style. Rousseau as noted above, was an enthusiastic supporter of the Italians against [[Jean-Philippe Rameau]] and others, making an important contribution with his ''Letter on French Music''.

==== Return to Geneva (1754) ====
On returning to Geneva in 1754, Rousseau reconverted to [[Calvinism]] and regained his official Genevan citizenship. In 1755, Rousseau completed his second major work, the ''Discourse on the Origin and Basis of Inequality Among Men'' (the [[Discourse on Inequality]]), which elaborated on the arguments of the ''Discourse on the Arts and Sciences''.

He also pursued an unconsummated romantic attachment with the 25-year-old [[Sophie d'Houdetot]], which partly inspired his [[epistolary novel]], ''[[Julie, ou la nouvelle Héloïse]]'' (also based on memories of his idyllic youthful relationship with Mme de Warens). Sophie was the cousin and houseguest of Rousseau's patroness and landlady [[Madame d'Epinay]], whom he treated rather highhandedly. He resented being at Mme d'Epinay's beck and call and detested the insincere conversation and shallow atheism of the ''Encyclopedistes'' whom he met at her table. Wounded feelings gave rise to a bitter three-way quarrel between Rousseau and Madame d'Epinay; her lover, the philologist [[Friedrich Melchior, baron von Grimm|Grimm]]; and their mutual friend, Diderot, who took their side against Rousseau. Diderot later described Rousseau as being, &quot;false, vain as Satan, ungrateful, cruel, hypocritical, and wicked ... He sucked ideas from me, used them himself, and then affected to despise me&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Damrosch (2005), p. 304.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Pierre Alexandre du Peyrou.jpg|thumb|l250px|The [[mestizo]] Pierre Alexandre du Peyrou, rich inhabitant of Neufchâtel, plantation owner, writer, friend and publisher of some of Rousseau's oeuvre. His mansion was [[Le Palais du Peyrou]].]]
Rousseau's break with the ''Encyclopedistes'' coincided with the composition of his three major works, in all of which he emphasized his fervent belief in a spiritual origin of man's soul and the universe, in contradistinction to the [[materialism]] of Diderot, [[La Mettrie]], and [[d'Holbach]]. During this period Rousseau enjoyed the support and patronage of the [[Charles François Frédéric de Montmorency-Luxembourg|Duc de Luxembourg]], and the [[Louis François I de Bourbon, prince de Conti|Prince de Conti]], two of the richest and most powerful nobles in France. These men truly liked Rousseau and enjoyed his ability to converse on any subject, but they also used him as a way of getting back at [[Louis XV]] and the political faction surrounding his mistress, [[Mme de Pompadour]]. Even with them, however, Rousseau went too far, courting rejection when he criticized the practice of [[tax farming]], in which some of them engaged.&lt;ref&gt;''Damrosch (2005), p. 357.&lt;/ref&gt;

Rousseau's 800-page novel of [[Sentimentality|sentiment]], ''[[Julie, ou la nouvelle Héloïse]]'', was published in 1761 to immense success. The book's rhapsodic descriptions of the natural beauty of the Swiss countryside struck a chord in the public and may have helped spark the subsequent nineteenth century craze for Alpine scenery. In 1762, Rousseau published ''Du Contrat Social, Principes du droit politique'' (in English, literally ''[[Social Contract (Rousseau)|Of the Social Contract, Principles of Political Right]]'') in April.
Even his friend [[Antoine-Jacques Roustan]] felt impelled to write a polite rebuttal of the chapter on Civil Religion in the ''Social Contract'', which implied that the concept of a [[Christian Republic]] was paradoxical since Christianity taught submission rather than participation in public affairs. Rousseau even helped Roustan find a publisher for the rebuttal.&lt;ref name=Rosenblatt1997&gt;{{cite book
 |url=http://books.google.ca/books?id=0hGoNncv-CkC&amp;pg=PA264
 |pages=264–5
 |title=Rousseau and Geneva: from the first discourse to the social contract, 1749–1762
 |author=Helena Rosenblatt
 |publisher=Cambridge University Press
 |year=1997
 |ISBN=0-521-57004-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Rousseau published ''[[Emile: or, On Education]]'' in May. The final section of ''Émile'', &quot;The Profession of Faith of a Savoyard Vicar,&quot; was intended to be a defense of religious belief. Rousseau's choice of a Catholic vicar of humble peasant background (plausibly based on a kindly prelate he had met as a teenager) as a spokesman for the defense of religion was in itself a daring innovation for the time. The vicar's creed was that of [[Socinianism]] (or [[Unitarianism]] as it is called today). Because it rejected original sin and divine [[Revelation]], both Protestant and Catholic authorities took offense.&lt;ref&gt;Rousseau's biographer Leo Damrosch, believes that the authorities chose to condemn him on religious rather than political grounds for tactical reasons. See Damrosch ''Jean-Jacques Rousseau, Restless Genius'' (New York: Houghton Mifflin, 2005).&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Allan Ramsay 003.jpg|thumb|250px|A 1766 portrait of Rousseau by [[Allan Ramsay (1713-1784)|Allan Ramsay]].]]
Moreover, Rousseau advocated the opinion that, insofar as they lead people to virtue, all religions are equally worthy, and that people should therefore conform to the religion in which they have been brought up. This religious [[indifferentism]] caused Rousseau and his books to be banned from France and Geneva. He was condemned from the pulpit by the Archbishop of Paris, his books were burned, and warrants were issued for his arrest.&lt;ref&gt;Rousseau's biographer Leo Damrosch, believes that the authorities chose to condemn him on religious rather than political grounds for tactical reasons. See Damrosch ''Jean-Jacques Rousseau, Restless Genius'' (New York: Houghton Mifflin, 2005).&lt;/ref&gt;
Former friends such as [[Jacob Vernes]] of Geneva could not accept his views, and wrote violent rebuttals.&lt;ref name=Blackwoods1842&gt;{{cite journal
 |url=http://books.google.ca/books?id=f7ECAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA165
 |page=165
 |chapter=Protestantism in Geneva
 |work=Blackwood's magazine, Volume 51
 |year=1842}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Rousseau is forced to flee ====
A sympathetic observer, British philosopher [[David Hume]], &quot;professed no surprise when he learned that Rousseau's books were banned in Geneva and elsewhere.&quot; Rousseau, he wrote, &quot;has not had the precaution to throw any veil over his sentiments; and, as he scorns to dissemble his contempt for established opinions, he could not wonder that all the zealots were in arms against him. The liberty of the press is not so secured in any country ... as not to render such an open attack on popular prejudice somewhat dangerous.'&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Peter Gay, ''The Enlightenment, The Science of Freedom'', p. 72.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Rousseau, who thought he had been defending religion, was crushed. Forced to flee arrest, he made his way, with the help of the Duc of Luxembourg and Prince de Conti, to [[Canton of Neuchâtel|Neuchâtel]], a [[Cantons of Switzerland|Canton]] of the Swiss Confederation that was a protectorate of the [[Prussian]] crown. His powerful protectors discreetly assisted him in his flight, and they helped to get his banned books (published in Holland by [[Marc-Michel Rey]]) distributed in France disguised as other works, using false covers and title pages. In the town of [[Môtiers]], he sought and found protection under [[Lord Keith]], who was the local representative of the free-thinking [[Frederick the Great of Prussia]]. While in Môtiers, Rousseau wrote the ''Constitutional Project for Corsica''  ([[Corsican Constitution|''Projet de Constitution pour la Corse'']], 1765).

==== In Britain (1765) ====
After his house in Môtiers was stoned on the night of 6 September 1765, Rousseau took refuge in Great Britain with Hume, who found lodgings for him at a friend's country estate in [[Weaver Hills|Wootton]] in Staffordshire. Neither Thérèse nor Rousseau was able to learn English or make friends. Isolated, Rousseau, never very emotionally stable, suffered a serious decline in his mental health and began to experience paranoid fantasies about plots against him involving Hume and others. “He is plainly mad, after having long been maddish”, Hume wrote to a friend.&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in Damrosch, p. 432&lt;/ref&gt; Rousseau's letter to Hume, in which he articulates the perceived misconduct, sparked an exchange which was published in Paris and received with great interest at the time.

[[File:Jean-Jacques Rousseau (photo of his crypt).jpg|thumb|upright|The tomb of Rousseau in the crypt of the [[Panthéon (Paris)|Panthéon]], Paris]]

==== France (1767) ====
Although officially barred from entering France before 1770, Rousseau returned in 1767 under a false name. In 1768 he went through a marriage of sorts to Thérèse (marriages between Catholics and Protestants were illegal), whom he had always hitherto referred to as his &quot;housekeeper&quot;. Though she was illiterate, she had become a remarkably good cook, a hobby her husband shared. 

In 1770 they were allowed to return to Paris. As a condition of his return he was not allowed to publish any books, but after completing his ''Confessions'', Rousseau began private readings in 1771. At the request of Madame d'Epinay, who was anxious to protect her privacy, however, the police ordered him to stop, and the ''Confessions'' was only partially published in 1782, four years after his death. All his subsequent works were to appear posthumously.

In 1772, Rousseau was invited to present recommendations for a new constitution for the [[Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth]], resulting in the ''[[Considerations on the Government of Poland]]'', which was to be his last major political work. In 1776, he completed ''Dialogues: Rousseau Judge of Jean-Jacques'' and began work on the ''[[Reveries of a Solitary Walker|Reveries of the Solitary Walker]]''. In order to support himself, he returned to copying music, spending his leisure time in the study of botany.

==== Final years ====
Although a celebrity, Rousseau's mental health did not permit him to enjoy his fame. His final years were largely spent in deliberate withdrawal. However, he did respond favorably to an approach from the composer [[Gluck]], whom he met in 1774. Gluck admired Rousseau as &quot;a pioneer of the expressive natural style&quot; in music.&lt;ref&gt;Leo Damrosch, ''Jean-Jacques Rousseau: Restless Genius'', Houghton Mifflin Harcourt, 2007, p.473&lt;/ref&gt; One of Rousseau's last pieces of writing was a critical yet enthusiastic analysis of Gluck's opera [[Alceste (Gluck)|Alceste]]. While taking a morning walk on the estate of the marquis [[René Louis de Girardin]] at [[Ermenonville]] (28 miles northeast of Paris), Rousseau suffered a [[hemorrhage]] and died, aged 66.

Rousseau was initially buried at Ermenonville on the Ile des Peupliers, which became a place of pilgrimage for his many admirers. Sixteen years after his death, his remains were moved to [[Panthéon (Paris)|the Panthéon]] in Paris in 1794, where they are located directly across from those of his contemporary, [[Voltaire]]. His tomb, in the shape of a rustic temple, on which, in [[bas relief]] an arm reaches out, bearing the torch of liberty, evokes Rousseau's deep love of nature and of classical antiquity. 

In 1834, the Genevan government somewhat reluctantly erected a statue in his honor on the tiny [[Île Rousseau]] in [[Lake Geneva]]. Today he is proudly claimed as their most celebrated native son. In 2002, the [http://www.espace-rousseau.ch/e/jean-jacques-rousseau.asp Espace Rousseau] was established at 40 Grand-Rue, Geneva, Rousseau's birthplace.

==Philosophy==

===Theory of Natural Human===
[[File:Rousseau Geneve.JPG|thumb|250px|The statue of Rousseau on the Île Rousseau, Geneva.]]

{{Cquote2|The first man who, having fenced in a piece of land, said &quot;This is mine,&quot; and found people naïve enough to believe him, that man was the true founder of civil society. From how many crimes, wars, and murders, from how many horrors and misfortunes might not any one have saved mankind, by pulling up the stakes, or filling up the ditch, and crying to his fellows: Beware of listening to this impostor; you are undone if you once forget that the fruits of the earth belong to us all, and the earth itself to nobody.|Jean-Jacques Rousseau, ''[[Discourse on Inequality]]'', 1754}}

In common with other philosophers of the day, Rousseau looked to a hypothetical [[State of Nature]] as a normative guide.

Rousseau criticized [[Hobbes]] for asserting that since man in the &quot;state of nature  . . . has no idea of goodness he must be naturally wicked; that he is vicious because he does not know virtue&quot;. On the contrary, Rousseau holds that &quot;uncorrupted morals&quot; prevail in the &quot;state of nature&quot; and he especially praised the admirable moderation of the Caribbeans in expressing the sexual urge&lt;ref&gt;Rousseau, ''Discourse on Inequality'', 72–73&lt;/ref&gt; despite the fact that they live in a hot climate, which &quot;always seems to inflame the passions&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''Discourse'', 78.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Rousseau asserted that the stage of human development associated with what he called &quot;savages&quot; was the best and most optimal in human development, between the less-than optimal extreme of brute animals on the one hand and the extreme of decadent civilization on the other.  &quot;...nothing is so gentle as man in his primitive state, when placed by nature at an equal distance from the stupidity of brutes and the fatal enlightenment of civil man.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Discourse on the Origin of Inequality (1754), Part Two, pg 64 of Jean-Jacques Rousseau: The Basic Political Writings. Hackett Publishing Company&lt;/ref&gt; Referring to the stage of human development which Rousseau associates with savages, Rousseau writes:

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Hence although men had become less forebearing, and although natural pity had already undergone some alteration, this period of the development of human faculties, maintaining a middle position between the indolence of our primitive state and the petulant activity of our egocentrism, must have been the happiest and most durable epoch. The more one reflects on it, the more one finds that this state was the least subject to upheavals and the best for man, and that he must have left it only by virtue of some fatal chance happening that, for the common good, ought never to have happened. The example of savages, almost all of whom have been found in this state, seems to confirm that the human race had been made to remain in it always; that this state is the veritable youth of the world; and that all the subsequent progress has been in appearance so many steps toward the perfection of the individual, and in fact toward the decay of the species.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Discourse on the Origin of Inequality (1754), Part Two, pg 65 of Jean-Jacques Rousseau: The Basic Political Writings. Hackett Publishing Company&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==== Stages of human development ====
Rousseau believed that the savage stage was not the first stage of human development, but the third stage. Rousseau held that this third savage stage of human societal development was an optimum, between the extreme of the state of brute animals and animal-like &quot;ape-men&quot; on the one hand, and the extreme of decadent civilized life on the other. This has led some critics to attribute to Rousseau the invention of the idea of the [[noble savage]],&lt;ref&gt;An early recorded use in French language of a specific expression explicitly associating the words 'savage' and 'noble' is in the early 17th century, that of Marc Lescarbot in his ''Histoire de la Nouvelle France'' (1609). In the chapter heading &quot;Sauvages sont vrayement nobles&quot;, Lescarbot states about those he calls savages: &quot;...revenons à notre Nouvelle-France, ou les hommes sont plus humains et ne vivent que de ce que Dieu a donné à l'homme, sans devorer leurs semblables. Aussi faut-il dire d'eux qu'ils sont vrayment Nobles...&quot; pg 786 Histoire de la Nouvelle France. Some writers still use the term &quot;[[Noble Savage]]&quot; in describing race relations in New France, see for example: ''The Libertine Colony'' by Doris Garraway, ''There are No Slaves in France'' by Sue Peabody, ''The Avengers of the New World'' by Laurent Dubois, and ''The French Atlantic Triangle'' by Christopher Miller; for information about the relationship between the French and English colonial contexts, see ''Sentimental Figures of Empire'' by Lynn Festa.&lt;/ref&gt; which [[Arthur Oncken Lovejoy|Arthur Lovejoy']] conclusively showed misrepresents Rousseau's thought.&lt;ref&gt;A. O. Lovejoy, &quot;The Supposed Primitivism of Rousseau's Discourse on Inequality&quot; in ''Essays in the History of Ideas'' (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins Press, [1923], 1948, 1960). Mario Einaudi speaks of &quot;Arthur Lovejoy's crucial role in dispelling the myth cultivated with such care by many eighteenth-century ''philosophes'', see Mario Einaudi, ''The Early Rousseau'' (Cornell University Press, 1967), n. p. 5. For a history of how the phrase became associated with Rousseau, see Ter Ellingson's, ''The Myth of the Noble Savage'' (Berkley, CA: University of California Press, 2001). See also below on Babbitt in article section: Legacy: Criticisms of Rousseau.&lt;/ref&gt; 

The expression, &quot;the noble savage&quot; was first used in 1672 by British poet [[John Dryden]] in his play ''[[The Conquest of Granada]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=27Av0zEmlqkC&amp;pg=PA106&amp;dq=Dryden+first+to+use+phrase+the+noble+savage&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=u_22T6zLM8bw6AHd-NDRCg&amp;ved=0CF4Q6AEwBw#v=onepage&amp;q=Dryden%20first%20to%20use%20phrase%20the%20noble%20savage&amp;f=false  Earl Miner, &quot;The Wild Man Through the Looking Glass&quot;, in Edward Dudley and Maximillian E. Novak, editors, ''The Wild Man Within: An Image in Western Thought from the Renaissance to Romanticism'', University of Pittsburgh Press, 1972, p. 106] and Ellingson (2001), p. 8 and passim. In 2009, Peter Gay remarked, &quot;As far as the noble savage is concerned, that phrase is from Dryden and does not appear in Rousseau’s writings. In the years I taught the history of political theory at Columbia to a sizable class of undergraduates, I would offer students a hundred dollars if they could find 'Noble Savage' anywhere in Rousseau. I never had to pay up'&quot;, [http://www.bookforum.com/inprint/016_01/3519  Peter Gay, &quot;Breeding is Fundamental&quot;, ''Book Forum'', (April/May, 2009.]&lt;/ref&gt;
Rousseau wrote that morality was not a societal construct, but rather &quot;natural&quot; in the sense of &quot;innate,&quot; an outgrowth from man's instinctive disinclination to witness suffering, from which arise the emotions of compassion or empathy. These were sentiments shared with animals, and whose existence even [[Hobbes]] acknowledged.&lt;ref&gt;In locating the basis of ethics in emotions rather than reason Rousseau agreed with [[Adam Smith]]'s 1759 ''Theory of Moral Sentiments''.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:DOI Rousseau.jpg|thumb|right|350px|Frontispiece and title page of an edition of Rousseau's ''[[Discourse on Inequality]]'' (1754), published in 1755 in Holland.]]

Contrary to what his many detractors have claimed, Rousseau never suggests that humans in the [[state of nature]] act morally; in fact, terms such as  &quot;justice&quot; or &quot;wickedness&quot; are inapplicable to prepolitical society as Rousseau understands it. Morality proper, i.e., self-restraint, can only develop through careful education in a civil state. Humans &quot;in a state of Nature&quot; may act with all of the ferocity of an animal. They are good only in a negative sense, insofar as they are self-sufficient and thus not subject to the vices of political society. 

In fact, Rousseau's natural man is virtually identical to a solitary [[chimpanzee]] or other [[ape]], such as the [[orangutan]] as described by [[Georges-Louis Leclerc, Comte de Buffon|Buffon]]; and the &quot;natural&quot; goodness of humanity is thus the goodness of an animal, which is neither good nor bad. Rousseau, a deteriorationist, proposed that, except perhaps for brief moments of balance, at or near its inception, when a relative equality among men prevailed, human civilization has always been artificial, creating inequality, envy, and unnatural desires.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}

In Rousseau's philosophy, society's negative influence on men centers on its transformation of ''[[amour de soi]]'', a positive self-love, into ''[[amour-propre]]'', or [[pride]]. ''Amour de soi'' represents the instinctive human desire for [[self-preservation]], combined with the human power of [[reason]]. In contrast, ''amour-propre'' is artificial and encourages man to compare himself to others, thus creating unwarranted [[fear]] and allowing men to take pleasure in the pain or weakness of others.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}} Rousseau was not the first to make this distinction. It had been invoked by [[Luc de Clapiers, marquis de Vauvenargues|Vauvenargues]], among others.

In ''[[Discourse on the Arts and Sciences]]'' Rousseau argues that the arts and sciences have not been beneficial to humankind, because they arose not from authentic human needs but rather as a result of pride and [[vanity]]. Moreover, the opportunities they create for idleness and luxury have contributed to the corruption of man. He proposed that the progress of [[knowledge]] had made governments more [[power (sociology)|power]]ful and had crushed individual [[liberty]]; and he concluded that material progress had actually undermined the possibility of true [[friendship]] by replacing it with [[jealousy]], [[fear]], and suspicion.

In contrast to the optimistic view of other Enlightenment figures, for Rousseau, [[social progress|progress]] has been inimical to the well-being of humanity, that is, unless it can be counteracted by the cultivation of civic morality and duty.

Only in [[civil society]], can man be ennobled—through the use of reason: &lt;blockquote&gt;The passage from the state of nature to the civil state produces a very remarkable change in man, by substituting justice for instinct in his conduct, and giving his actions the morality they had formerly lacked. Then only, when the voice of duty takes the place of physical impulses and right of appetite, does man, who so far had considered only himself, find that he is forced to act on different principles, and to consult his reason before listening to his inclinations. Although, in this state, he deprives himself of some advantages which he got from nature, he gains in return others so great, his faculties are so stimulated and developed, his ideas so extended, his feelings so ennobled, and his whole soul so uplifted, that, did not the abuses of this new condition often degrade him below that which he left, he would be bound to bless continually the happy moment which took him from it for ever, and, instead of a stupid and unimaginative animal, made him an intelligent being and a man.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.constitution.org/jjr/socon_01.htm ''The Social Contract'', Book I Chapter 8]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; Society corrupts men only insofar as the Social Contract has not ''de facto'' succeeded, as we see in contemporary society as described in the ''[[Discourse on Inequality]]'' (1754).

In this essay, which elaborates on the ideas introduced in the ''[[Discourse on the Arts and Sciences]]'', Rousseau traces man's social evolution from a primitive [[state of nature]] to modern society. The earliest solitary humans possessed a basic drive for self-preservation and a natural disposition to [[compassion]] or pity. They differed from animals, however, in their capacity for free will and their potential perfectibility. As they began to live in groups and form clans they also began to experience family love, which Rousseau saw as the source of the greatest happiness known to humanity. 

As long as differences in wealth and status among families were minimal, the first coming together in groups was accompanied by a fleeting golden age of human flourishing. The development of agriculture, metallurgy, private property, and the [[division of labour]] and resulting dependency on one another, however, led to [[economic inequality]] and conflict. As population pressures forced them to associate more and more closely, they underwent a psychological transformation: They began to see themselves through the eyes of others and came to value the good opinion of others as essential to their [[self esteem]]. 

Rousseau posits that the original, deeply flawed [[Social Contract]] (i.e., that of Hobbes), which led to the modern state, was made at the suggestion of the rich and powerful, who tricked the general population into surrendering their liberties to them and instituted inequality as a fundamental feature of human society. Rousseau's own conception of the Social Contract can be understood as an alternative to this fraudulent form of association. 

At the end of the ''[[Discourse on Inequality]]'', Rousseau explains how the desire to have value in the eyes of others comes to undermine personal integrity and authenticity in a society marked by interdependence, and [[hierarchy]]. In the last chapter of the ''Social Contract'', Rousseau would ask &quot;What is to be done?&quot; He answers that now all men can do is to cultivate virtue in themselves and submit to their lawful rulers. To his readers, however, the inescapable conclusion was that a new and more equitable Social Contract was needed.

Like other Enlightenment philosophers, Rousseau was critical of the [[Atlantic slave trade]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://abolition.nypl.org/print/abolition/ The Abolition of The Slave Trade]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

===Political theory===
[[File:Ile Rousseau Geneva Switzerland.JPG|thumb|250px|Île Rousseau, Geneva.]]

Perhaps Rousseau's most important work is ''[[The Social Contract]]'', which outlines the basis for a legitimate political order within a framework of [[classical republicanism]]. Published in 1762, it became one of the most influential works of political philosophy in the Western tradition. It developed some of the ideas mentioned in an earlier work, the article ''Economie Politique'' (''Discourse on Political Economy''), featured in Diderot's ''[[Encyclopédie]]''. The treatise begins with the dramatic opening lines, &quot;Man is born free, and everywhere he is in chains. Those who think themselves the masters of others are indeed greater slaves than they.&quot;

Rousseau claimed that the state of nature was a primitive condition without law or morality, which human beings left for the benefits and necessity of cooperation. As society developed, division of labor and private property required the human race to adopt institutions of law. In the degenerate phase of society, man is prone to be in frequent competition with his fellow men while also becoming increasingly dependent on them. This double pressure threatens both his survival and his freedom. 

According to Rousseau, by joining together into civil society through the social contract and abandoning their claims of natural right, individuals can both preserve themselves and remain free. This is because submission to the authority of the [[general will]] of the people as a whole guarantees individuals against being subordinated to the wills of others and also ensures that they obey themselves because they are, collectively, the authors of the law.

Although Rousseau argues that [[sovereignty]] (or the power to make the laws) should be in the hands of the people, he also makes a sharp distinction between the sovereign and the government. The government is composed of magistrates, charged with implementing and enforcing the general will. The &quot;sovereign&quot; is the rule of law, ideally decided on by [[direct democracy]] in an assembly. Rousseau was opposed to the idea that the people should exercise sovereignty via a [[Representative democracy|representative assembly]] (Book III, Chapter XV). The kind of republican government of which Rousseau approved was that of the city state, of which Geneva was a model, or would have been, if renewed on Rousseau's principles. France could not meet Rousseau's criterion of an ideal state because it was too big. Much subsequent controversy about Rousseau's work has hinged on disagreements concerning his claims that citizens constrained to obey the general will are thereby rendered free:&lt;blockquote&gt;The notion of the general will is wholly central to Rousseau's theory of political legitimacy. ... It is, however, an unfortunately obscure and controversial notion. Some commentators see it as no more than the dictatorship of the proletariat or the tyranny of the urban poor (such as may perhaps be seen in the French Revolution). Such was not Rousseau's meaning. This is clear from the ''Discourse on Political Economy'', where Rousseau emphasizes that the general will exists to protect individuals against the mass, not to require them to be sacrificed to it. He is, of course, sharply aware that men have selfish and sectional interests which will lead them to try to oppress others. It is for this reason that loyalty to the good of all alike must be a supreme (although not exclusive) commitment by everyone, not only if a truly general will is to be heeded but also if it is to be formulated successfully in the first place&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Entry, &quot;Rousseau&quot; in the ''Routelege Encyclopedia of Philosophy'', Edward Craig, editor, Volume Eight, p. 371&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Education and child rearing===
{{Main|Emile: or, On Education}}
{{Cquote2|‘The noblest work in education is to make a reasoning man, and we expect to train a young child by making him reason! This is beginning at the end; this is making an instrument of a result. If children understood how to reason they would not need to be educated.”&amp;nbsp;–Rousseau, ''Emile''.}}

Rousseau’s philosophy of education is not concerned with particular techniques of imparting information and concepts, but rather with developing the pupil’s character and moral sense, so that he may learn to practice self-mastery and remain virtuous even in the unnatural and imperfect society in which he will have to live. The hypothetical boy, Émile, is to be raised in the countryside, which, Rousseau believes, is a more natural and healthy environment than the city, under the guardianship of a tutor who will guide him through various learning experiences arranged by the tutor. Today we would call this the disciplinary method of &quot;natural consequences&quot; since, like modern psychologists{{Who|date=November 2009}}, Rousseau felt that children learn right and wrong through experiencing the consequences of their acts rather than through physical punishment. The tutor will make sure that no harm results to Émile through his learning experiences.

Rousseau was one of the first to advocate developmentally appropriate education; and his description of the stages of [[child development]] mirrors his conception of the evolution of culture. He divides childhood into stages: the first is to the age of about 12, when children are guided by their emotions and impulses. During the second stage, from 12 to about 16, reason starts to develop; and finally the third stage, from the age of 16 onwards, when the child develops into an adult. Rousseau recommends that the young adult learn a manual skill such as carpentry, which requires creativity and thought, will keep him out of trouble, and will supply a fallback means of making a living in the event of a change of fortune. (The most illustrious aristocratic youth to have been educated this way may have been [[Louis XVI]], whose parents had him learn the skill of locksmithing.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Jordan|first=Michael|title=Famous Locksmiths|url=http://www.americanchronicle.com/articles/view/72616|publisher=American Chronicle|accessdate=14 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;) The sixteen-year-old is also ready to have a companion of the opposite sex.

Although his ideas foreshadowed modern ones in many ways, in one way they do not: Rousseau was a believer in the moral superiority of the [[patriarchal]] family on the antique Roman model. Sophie, the young woman Émile is destined to marry, as a representative of ideal womanhood, is educated to be governed by her husband while Émile, as representative of the ideal man, is educated to be self-governing. This is not an accidental feature of Rousseau's educational and political philosophy; it is essential to his account of the distinction between private, personal relations and the public world of political relations. The [[private sphere]] as Rousseau imagines it depends on the subordination of women, in order for both it and the public political sphere (upon which it depends) to function as Rousseau imagines it could and should. Rousseau anticipated the modern idea of the [[bourgeois]] [[nuclear family]], with the mother at home taking responsibility for the household and for childcare and early education.

Feminists, beginning in the late 18th century with [[Mary Wollstonecraft]] in 1792&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Wollstonecraft, Mary|title=A Vindication of the Rights of Woman  (ed. Miriam Brody).|publisher=Penguin Group|year=2004|first=1792|isbn=978-0-14-144125-2|chapter=V}}&lt;/ref&gt; have criticized Rousseau for his confinement of women to the domestic sphere—unless women were [[Domestication|domesticated]] and constrained by modesty and shame, he feared&lt;ref name=Tuana&gt;{{Cite book|author=Tuana, Nancy|title=The Less Noble Sex: Scientific, Religious and Philosophical Conceptions of Women's Nature|year=1993|pages=161|publisher=Indiana University Press|isbn=0-253-36098-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;men would be tyrannized by women... For, given the ease with which women arouse men's senses... men would finally be their victims....&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Rousseau, ''Emile'', book V, p. 359&lt;/ref&gt; His contemporaries saw it differently because Rousseau thought that mothers should breastfeed their children.&lt;ref&gt;Damrosch, p. 341-42.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jean-François Marmontel|Marmontel]] wrote that his wife thought, &quot;One must forgive something,&quot; she said, &quot;in one who has taught us to be mothers.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Marmontel, Jean François|title=Memoirs of Marmontel, written by himself: containing his literary and political life, and anecdotes of the principal characters of the eighteenth century|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=SiQoAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA125|publisher=Whittaker via Google Books|year=1826|pages=125–126}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Rousseau's detractors have blamed him for everything they do not like in what they call modern &quot;child-centered&quot; education. John Darling's 1994 book ''Child-Centered Education and its Critics'' argues that the history of modern [[pedagogy|educational theory]] is a series of footnotes to Rousseau, a development he regards as bad. Good or bad, the theories of educators such as Rousseau's near contemporaries [[Johann Heinrich Pestalozzi|Pestalozzi]], [[Stéphanie Félicité Ducrest de St-Albin, comtesse de Genlis|Mme de Genlis]], and later, [[Maria Montessori]], and [[John Dewey]], which have directly influenced modern educational practices do have significant points in common with those of Rousseau.

==Religion==
Having converted to Roman Catholicism early in life and returned to the austere [[Calvinism]] of his native Geneva as part of his period of moral reform, Rousseau maintained a profession of that religious philosophy and of [[John Calvin]] as a modern lawgiver throughout the remainder of his life.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/510932/Jean-Jacques-Rousseau/23965/Major-works-of-political-philosophy Britannica.com]&lt;/ref&gt; His views on religion presented in his works of philosophy, however, may strike some as discordant with the doctrines of both Catholicism and Calvinism.

At the time, however, Rousseau's strong endorsement of religious toleration, as expounded by the Savoyard vicar in ''[[Emile: or, On Education|Émile]]'', was interpreted as advocating [[indifferentism]], a heresy, and led to the condemnation of the book in both Calvinist [[Geneva]] and Catholic Paris. His assertion in the ''[[Social Contract (Rousseau)|Social Contract]]'' that true followers of Jesus would not make good citizens may have been another reason for Rousseau's condemnation in Geneva.

Unlike many of the more radical Enlightenment philosophers, Rousseau affirmed the necessity of religion. But he repudiated the doctrine of [[original sin]], which plays so large a part in Calvinism (in ''Émile'', Rousseau writes &quot;there is no original perversity in the human heart&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;''il n’y a point de perversité originelle dans le cœur humain'' [[:s:Émile, ou De l’éducation/Édition 1852/Livre II|Émile, ou De l’éducation/Édition 1852/Livre II]]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 18th century, many [[deists]] viewed God merely as an abstract and impersonal creator of the universe, which they likened to a giant machine. Rousseau's deism differed from the usual kind in its intense emotionality. He saw the presence of God in his creation, including mankind, which, apart from the harmful influence of society, is good, because God is good. Rousseau's attribution of a spiritual value to the beauty of nature anticipates the attitudes of 19th-century [[Romanticism]] towards nature and religion.

Rousseau was upset that his deistic views were so forcefully condemned, while those of the more atheistic ''philosophes'' were ignored. He defended himself against critics of his religious views in his &quot;Letter to [[Christophe de Beaumont]], the Archbishop of Paris in which he insists that freedom of discussion in religious matters is essentially more religious than the attempt to impose belief by force.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;The full text of the letter is available online only in the French original: [http://alain-leger.mageos.com/docs/Rousseau.pdf Lettre à Mgr De Beaumont Archevêque de Paris (1762)]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
{{Unbalanced|section|date=September 2011}}
[[File:Rousseauplaque.jpg|thumb|250px|A plaque commemorating the bicentenary of Rousseau's birth. Issued by the city of Geneva on 28 June 1912. The legend at the bottom says &quot;Jean-Jacques, aime ton pays&quot; (&quot;love your country&quot;), and shows Rousseau's father gesturing towards the window. The scene is drawn from a footnote to the [[Letter to M. D'Alembert on Spectacles|Letter to d'Alembert]] where Rousseau recalls witnessing the popular celebrations following the exercises of the St Gervais regiment.]]

Rousseau's idea of the ''volonté générale'' (&quot;[[general will]]&quot;) was not original with him but rather belonged to a well-established technical vocabulary of juridical and theological writings in use at the time. The phrase was used by [[Diderot]] and also by [[Montesquieu]] (and by his teacher, the [[Oratorian]] friar [[Nicolas Malebranche]]). It served to designate the common interest embodied in legal tradition, as distinct from and transcending people's private and particular interests at any particular time. 

The concept was also an important aspect of the more radical 17th-century republican tradition of [[Spinoza]], from whom Rousseau differed in important respects, but not in his insistence on the importance of equality. This emphasis on equality is Rousseau's most important and consequential legacy, causing him to be both reviled and applauded:

&lt;blockquote&gt;While Rousseau's notion of the progressive moral degeneration of mankind from the moment civil society established itself diverges markedly from Spinoza's claim that human nature is always and everywhere the same ... for both philosophers the pristine equality of the state of nature is our ultimate goal and criterion ... in shaping the &quot;common good&quot;, ''volonté générale'', or [[Spinoza]]'s ''mens una,'' which alone can ensure stability and political salvation. Without the supreme criterion of equality, the general will would indeed be meaningless. ... When in the depths of the French Revolution the Jacobin clubs all over France regularly deployed Rousseau when demanding radical reforms. and especially anything—such as land redistribution—designed to enhance equality, they were at the same time, albeit unconsciously, invoking a radical tradition which reached back to the late seventeenth century.&lt;ref&gt;Jonathan I. Israel, ''Radical Enlightenment: Philosophy and the Making of Modernity'' (Oxford University Press, 2002), p. 274.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

=== French Revolution ===

The cult that grew up around Rousseau after his death, and particularly the radicalized versions of Rousseau's ideas that were adopted by [[Robespierre]] and [[Louis Antoine de Saint-Just|Saint-Just]] during the [[Reign of Terror]], caused him to become identified with the most extreme aspects of the [[French Revolution]].&lt;ref&gt;Robspierre and Saint-Just's conception of ''L’intérêt général,'' or the will of the people, was derived from Rousseau's &quot;general will&quot;, and they considered themselves &quot;highly principled republicans, charged with stripping away what was superfluous and corrupt, inspired above all by Rousseau&quot;, Jonathan Israel, p. 717.&lt;/ref&gt; Among other things, the ship of the line [[French ship Jean-Jacques Rousseau (1795)|Jean-Jacques Rousseau]] (launched in 1795) was named after the philosopher. The revolutionaries were also inspired by Rousseau to introduce Deism as the new official [[civil religion]] of France, scandalizing traditionalists:&lt;blockquote&gt;Ceremonial and symbolic occurrences of the more radical phases of the Revolution invoked Rousseau and his core ideas.

Thus the ceremony held at the site of the demolished Bastille, organized by the foremost artistic director of the Revolution, [[Jacques-Louis David]], in August 1793 to mark the inauguration of the new republican constitution, an event coming shortly after the final abolition of all forms of feudal privilege, featured a cantata based on Rousseau's democratic pantheistic deism as expounded in the celebrated &quot;''Profession de foi d'un vicaire savoyard''&quot; in Book Four of ''Émile''.&lt;ref&gt;Jonathan Israel, p. 717.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Opponents of the Revolution and defenders of religion, most influentially the Irish essayist [[Edmund Burke]], therefore placed the blame for the excesses of the French Revolution directly on the revolutionaries' misplaced (as he considered it) adulation of Rousseau. Burke's &quot;Letter to a Member of the National Assembly&quot;, published in February 1791, was a diatribe against Rousseau, whom he considered the paramount influence on the French Revolution (his ''ad hominem'' attack did not really engage with Rousseau's political writings). Burke maintained that the excesses of the Revolution were not accidents but were designed from the beginning and were rooted in Rousseau's personal vanity, arrogance, and other moral failings. He recalled Rousseau's visit to Britain in 1766, saying: &quot;I had good opportunities of knowing his proceedings almost from day to day and he left no doubt in my mind that he entertained no principle either to influence his heart or to guide his understanding, but vanity&quot;. Conceding his gift of eloquence, Burke deplored Rousseau's lack of the good taste and finer feelings that would have been imparted by the education of a gentleman:&lt;blockquote&gt;Taste and elegance ... are of no mean importance in the regulation of life. A moral taste ... infinitely abates the evils of vice. Rousseau, a writer of great force and vivacity, is totally destitute of taste in any sense of the word. Your masters [i.e., the leaders of the Revolution], who are his scholars, conceive that all refinement has an aristocratic character. The last age had exhausted all its powers in giving a grace and nobleness to our mutual appetites, and in raising them into a higher class and order than seemed justly to belong to them. Through Rousseau, your masters are resolved to destroy these aristocratic prejudices.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|first=Edmund |last=Burke |url=http://ourcivilisation.com/smartboard/shop/burkee/tonatass/index.htm |title=A letter to a member of the National Assembly, 1791 |publisher=Ourcivilisation.com |accessdate=23 February 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

The American founders rarely cited Rousseau, but came independently to their [[Republicanism in the United States|Republicanism]] and  enthusiastic admiration for the austere virtues described by [[Livy]] and in [[Plutarch]]'s portrayals of the great men of ancient [[Sparta]] and the [[classical republicanism]] of early Rome, as did many, if not most other enlightenment figures.&lt;ref&gt;In the eighteenth century, Sparta was generally identified with [[classical republicanism]].  For Rousseau and Sparta see Judith N. Shklar, &quot;Sparta and the Age of Gold&quot; in ''Men and Citizens: A Study of Rousseau's Social Theory'', p. 12. For role of Sparta during the Enlightenment see Peter Gay's ''The Party of Humanity'' (New York: W. W. Norton, 1971), especially pp. 242–244. and ''The Enlightenment: An Interpretation : the Rise of Modern Paganism'' (New York: W. W. Norton [1966], 1977, Chapter one.&lt;/ref&gt; Rousseau’s praise of Switzerland and Corsica’s economies of isolated and self-sufficient independent homesteads, and his endorsement of a well-regulated citizen militia, such as Switzerland’s, recall the ideals of [[Jeffersonian democracy]]. To Rousseau we owe the invention of the concept of a &quot;[[civil religion]]&quot;, one of whose key tenets is religious toleration. Yet despite their mutual insistence on the self-evidence that &quot;all men are created equal&quot;, their insistence that the citizens of a republic be educated at public expense, and the evident parallel between the concepts of the &quot;[[general welfare]]&quot; and Rousseau's &quot;[[general will]]&quot;, some scholars maintain there is little to suggest that Rousseau had that much effect on [[Thomas Jefferson]] and other founding fathers.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Rousseau, whose romantic and egalitarian tenets had practically no influence on the course of Jefferson's, or indeed any American, thought.&quot; Nathan Schachner, ''Thomas Jefferson: A Biography.'' (1957), p. 47. Jefferson never mentioned Rousseau in any of his writings, but made frequent references to Locke. On the other hand, he did have a well-thumbed copy of Rousseau's work in his library and was known to have been influenced by &quot;French philosophers.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; They argue that the American constitution owes as much or more to the English Liberal philosopher [[John Locke]]'s emphasis on the rights of property and to [[Montesquieu]]'s theories of the [[separation of powers]].&lt;ref&gt;A case for Rousseau as an enemy of the Enlightenment is made in Graeme Garrard, ''Rousseau's Counter-Enlightenment: A Republican Critique of the Philosophes'' (Albany: SUNY Press, 2003).&lt;/ref&gt; 

Rousseau's writings had an indirect influence on American literature through the writings of [[Wordsworth]] and [[Kant]], whose works were important to the New England [[Transcendentalist]] [[Ralph Waldo Emerson]], as well as on such Unitarians as theologian [[William Ellery Channing]]. American novelist [[James Fennimore Cooper]]'s ''[[Last of the Mohicans]]'' and other novels reflect republican and egalitarian ideals present alike in Rousseau, [[Thomas Paine]], and also in English Romantic [[primitivism]].&lt;ref&gt;Cooper was a follower of Tom Paine, who in turn was an admirer of Rousseau. For the classical origins of American ideals of liberty, see also &quot;''Sibi Imperiosus'': Cooper's Horatian Ideal of Self-Governance in The Deerslayer&quot;(Villa Julie College) Placed on line July 2005 [http://external.oneonta.edu/cooper/articles/suny/2003suny-tamer.html external.oneonta.edu]&lt;/ref&gt; Another American admirer was lexicographer [[Noah Webster]].&lt;ref&gt;Mark J. Temmer, &quot;Rousseau and Thoreau,&quot; ''Yale French Studies,'' No. 28, ''Jean-Jacques Rousseau'' (1961), pp. 112–121.&lt;/ref&gt; The Paraguayan dictator [[José Gaspar Rodríguez de Francia]] sought to found a society based on the principles set forth in Rousseau's ''[[The Social Contract|Social Contract]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://warofthepacific.com/warofthetriplealliance.htm War of The Triple Alliance] Retrieved 14 November 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;In truth,&quot; wrote [[Kingsley Martin]], &quot;Rousseau was a genius whose real influence cannot be traced with precision because it pervaded all the thought that followed him.&quot; He goes on:&lt;blockquote&gt;Men will always be sharply divided about Rousseau: for he released imagination as well as sentimentalism;; he increased men’s desire for justice as well as confusing their minds , and he gave the poor hope even though the rich could make use of his arguments. In one direction at least Rousseau’s influence was a steady one: he discredited force as a basis for the State, convinced men that authority was legitimate only when founded in rational consent and that no arguments from passing expediency could justify a government in disregarding individual  freedom or in failing to promote social equality.&lt;ref&gt;Kingsley Martin, ''French Liberal Thought in the Eighteenth Century'' [1962] quoted in Nicholas Dent, Rousseau in series ''The Routledge Philosophers'' (London and New York: Routledge, 2005), p. 20.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Criticisms of Rousseau===
[[File:Rousseau in later life.jpg|thumb|250px|A portrait of Rousseau in later life.]]

The first to criticize Rousseau were his fellow ''[[Philosophe]]s'', above all, Voltaire. According to Jacques Barzun: &lt;blockquote&gt;Voltaire, who had felt annoyed by the first essay [''On the Arts and Sciences''], was outraged by the second, [''Discourse on the Origin of Inequality Among Men''], declaring that Rousseau wanted us to “walk on all fours” like animals and behave like savages, believing them creatures of perfection. From these interpretations, plausible but inexact, spring the clichés [[Noble Savage]] and Back to Nature.&lt;ref&gt;''From Dawn to Decadence: 500 Years of Western Cultural Life: 1500 to the Present'' (Harper Collins, 2001), p. 384&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Barzun states that, contrary to myth, Rousseau was no primitivist; for him:&lt;blockquote&gt;The model man is the independent farmer, free of superiors and self-governing. This was cause enough for the ''philosophes''' hatred of their former friend. Rousseau’s unforgivable crime was his rejection of the graces and luxuries of civilized existence. Voltaire had sung “The superfluous, that most necessary thing.&quot; For the high bourgeois standard of living Rousseau would substitute the middling peasant’s. It was the country versus the city—an exasperating idea for them, as was the amazing fact that every new work of Rousseau’s was a huge success, whether the subject was politics, theater, education, religion, or a novel about love.&lt;ref&gt;Jacques Barzun, ''From Dawn to Decadence'' (2001) p. 384&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Following the French Revolution, other commentators fingered a potential danger of Rousseau’s project of realizing an “antique” conception of virtue amongst the citizenry in a modern world (e.g. through education, physical exercise, a citizen militia, public holidays, and the like). Taken too far, as under the [[Jacobin (politics)|Jacobin]]s, such social engineering could result in tyranny.

As early as 1819, in his famous speech “On Ancient and Modern Liberty,” the political philosopher [[Benjamin Constant]], a proponent of constitutional monarchy and representative democracy, criticized Rousseau, or rather his more radical followers (specifically the [[Gabriel Bonnot de Mably|Abbé de Mably]]), for allegedly believing that &quot;everything should give way to collective will, and that all restrictions on individual rights would be amply compensated by participation in social power.”

Common also were attacks by defenders of social hierarchy on Rousseau's &quot;romantic&quot; belief in equality. In 1860, shortly after the [[Sepoy Rebellion]] in India, two British white supremacists, [[John Crawfurd]] and [[James Hunt (speech therapist)|James Hunt]], mounted a defense of British [[imperialism]] based on “[[scientific racism]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;See Ter Ellingson, ''The Myth of the Noble Savage'', 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;  Crawfurd, in alliance with Hunt, took over the presidency of the British Anthropological Society, which had been founded with the mission to defend indigenous peoples against slavery and colonial exploitation. Invoking &quot;science&quot; and &quot;realism&quot;, the two men derided their &quot;philanthropic&quot; predecessors for believing in human equality and for not recognizing that mankind was divided into superior and inferior races. Crawfurd, who opposed Darwinian evolution, &quot;denied any unity to mankind, insisting on immutable, hereditary, and timeless differences in racial character, principal amongst which was the 'very great' difference in 'intellectual capacity.'&quot; For Crawfurd, the races had been created separately and were different species. Since Crawfurd was Scottish, he thought the Scottish &quot;race&quot; superior and all others inferior; whilst Hunt, on the other hand, believed in the supremacy of the Anglo-Saxon &quot;race&quot;. Crawfurd and Hunt routinely accused those who disagreed with them of believing in &quot;Rousseau’s Noble Savage&quot;. (The pair ultimately quarreled because Hunt believed in slavery and Crawfurd did not). &quot;As Ter Ellingson demonstrates, Crawfurd was responsible for re-introducing the Pre-Rousseauian concept of 'the Noble Savage' to modern anthropology, attributing it wrongly and quite deliberately to Rousseau.”&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://epress.anu.edu.au/foreign_bodies/mobile_devices/ch03s02.html |title=John Crawfurd—'two separate races' |publisher=Epress.anu.edu.au |accessdate=23 February 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1919 [[Irving Babbitt]], founder of a movement called the &quot;[[New Humanism]]&quot;, wrote a critique of what he called &quot;sentimental humanitarianism&quot;, for which he blamed Rousseau.&lt;ref&gt;''Rousseau and Romanticism'' (Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1919).&lt;/ref&gt; Babbitt's depiction of Rousseau was countered in a celebrated and much reprinted essay by A. O. Lovejoy in 1923.&lt;ref&gt;Lovejoy ([1923], 1948..&lt;/ref&gt; In France, fascist theorist and anti-Semite [[Charles Maurras]], founder of ''[[Action Française]]'', “had no compunctions in laying the blame for both ''Romantisme et Révolution'' firmly on Rousseau in 1922.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;See R. Simon Harvey, who goes on: &quot;and mere concern for the facts has not inhibited others from doing likewise. Irving Babbitt’s ''Rousseau &amp; Romanticism'' still remains the only general work on this subject though printed as long ago as 1919, but it is grossly inaccurate, discursive and biased ....”See ''Reappraisals of Rousseau: studies in honor of R. A. Leigh'', R, Simon Harvey, Editor (Manchester University press. 1980).&lt;/ref&gt;

During the Cold War, [[Karl Popper]] criticized Rousseau for his association with nationalism and its attendant abuses{{citation needed|date=November 2011}}. This came to be known among scholars as the &quot;[[totalitarian]] thesis&quot;. An example is J. L. Talmon's, ''The Origins of Totalitarian Democracy'' (1952).&lt;ref&gt;Talmon's thesis is rebutted by Ralph A. Leigh in “''Liberté et autorité dans le Contrat Social''” in ''Jean-Jacques Rousseau et son ouevre'' (Paris 1963). Another tenacious proponent of the totalitarian thesis was Lester C. Crocker, author of  ''Rousseau’s Social Contract, An interpretive Essay'' (Case Western Reserve Press, Cleveland, 1968). Two reviews of the debate are: J. W. Chapman, ''Rousseau: Totalitarian or Liberal?'' (AMS Press New York, 1968) and Richard Fralin, ''Rousseau and Representation'' (Columbia University Press, NY, 1978).&lt;/ref&gt; Political scientist J. S. Maloy states that “the twentieth century added Nazism and Stalinism to Jacobinism on the list of horrors for which Rousseau could be blamed. ... Rousseau was considered to have advocated just the sort of invasive tampering with human nature which the totalitarian regimes of mid-century had tried to instantiate.&quot; But Maloy adds that &quot;The totalitarian thesis in Rousseau studies has, by now, been discredited as an attribution of real historical influence.”&lt;ref&gt;J. S. Maloy,  “The Very Order of Things: Rousseau's Tutorial Republicanism,” ''Polity'', Vol. 37 (2005).&lt;/ref&gt; 

Arthur Melzer, however, while conceding that Rousseau would not have approved of modern nationalism, observes that his theories do contain the &quot;seeds of nationalism&quot;, insofar as they set forth the &quot;politics of identification&quot;, which are rooted in sympathetic emotion. Melzer also believes that in admitting that people's talents are unequal, Rousseau therefore tacitly condones the tyranny of the few over the many.&lt;ref&gt;Arthur Melzer, &quot;Rousseau, Nationalism, and the Politics of Sympathetic Identification&quot; in ''Educating the Prince: Essays in Honor of Harvey C. Mansfield'', Mark Kristol and William Blitz, editors (Rowman &amp; Littlefield, 2000). Others counter, however, that Rousseau was concerned with the concept of equality under the law, not equality of talents.&lt;/ref&gt; For Stephen T. Engel, on the other hand, Rousseau's nationalism anticipated modern theories of &quot;imagined communities&quot; that transcend social and religious divisions within states.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Rousseau and Imagined Communities&quot;, ''The Review of Politics'', Vol. 67, No. 3 (Summer, 2005), pp. 515–537.&lt;/ref&gt;

On similar grounds, one of Rousseau's strongest critics during the second half of the 20th century was political philosopher [[Hannah Arendt]]. Using Rousseau's thought as an example, Arendt identified the notion of [[sovereignty]] with that of the general will. According to her, it was this desire to establish a single, unified will based on the stifling of opinion in favor of public passion that contributed to the excesses of the French Revolution.&lt;ref&gt;Hannah Arendt, ''On revolution'' (1990 p. 76&lt;/ref&gt;

==Major works==
*''Dissertation sur la musique moderne'', 1736
*''[[Discourse on the Arts and Sciences]]'' (''Discours sur les sciences et les arts''), 1750
*''Narcissus, or The Self-Admirer: A Comedy'', 1752
*''[[Le Devin du Village]]: an opera'', 1752, {{PDFlink|[http://www.library.unt.edu/music/virtual/Rousseau_Devin/Rousseau.pdf score]|21.7&amp;nbsp;MB}}
*''[[Discourse on the Origin and Basis of Inequality Among Men]]'' (''Discours sur l'origine et les fondements de l'inégalité parmi les hommes''), 1754
*''[[Discourse on Political Economy]]'', 1755
*''[[Letter to M. D'Alembert on Spectacles]]'', 1758 (''Lettre à d'Alembert sur les spectacles'')
*''[[Julie, ou la nouvelle Héloïse|Julie, or the New Heloise]]'' (''Julie, ou la nouvelle Héloïse''), 1761
*''[[Emile: Or, On Education|Émile: or, on Education]]'' (''Émile ou de l'éducation''), 1762
*''[[The Creed of a Savoyard Priest]]'', 1762 (in ''Émile'')
*''[[Social Contract (Rousseau)|The Social Contract, or Principles of Political Right]]'' (''Du contrat social''), 1762
*''[[Four Letters to M. de Malesherbes]]'', 1762
*''[[Pygmalion (1762 play)|Pygmalion: a Lyric Scene]]'', 1762
*''[[Letters Written from the Mountain]]'', 1764 (''Lettres de la montagne'')
*''[[Confessions of Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]'' (''Les Confessions''), 1770, published 1782
*''[[Constitutional Project for Corsica]]'', 1772
*''[[Considerations on the Government of Poland]]'', 1772
*''[[Essay on the Origin of Languages]]'', published 1781 (''Essai sur l'origine des langues'')
*''[[Reveries of a Solitary Walker]]'', incomplete, published 1782 (''Rêveries du promeneur solitaire'')
*''[[Dialogues: Rousseau Judge of Jean-Jacques]]'', published 1782

==Editions in English==
*''Basic Political Writings'', trans. Donald A. Cress. Indianapolis: Hackett Publishing, 1987.
*''Collected Writings'', ed. [[Roger Masters]] and Christopher Kelly, Dartmouth: University Press of New England, 1990–2010, 13 vols.
*''The Confessions'', trans. Angela Scholar. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2000.
*''Emile, or On Education'', trans. with an introd. by [[Allan Bloom]], New York: Basic Books, 1979.
*&quot;On the Origin of Language,&quot; trans. John H. Moran. In ''On the Origin of Language: Two Essays''. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1986.
*''Reveries of a Solitary Walker'', trans. Peter France. London: Penguin Books, 1980.
*'' 'The Discourses' and Other Early Political Writings'', trans. Victor Gourevitch. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1997.
*'' 'The Social Contract' and Other Later Political Writings'', trans. Victor Gourevitch. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1997.
*'' 'The Social Contract'', trans. Maurice Cranston. Penguin: Penguin Classics Various Editions, 1968–2007.
*''The Political writings of Jean-Jacques Rousseau'', edited from the original MCS and authentic editions with introduction and notes by C.E.Vaughan, Blackwell, Oxford, 1962. (In French but the introduction and notes are in English).

==Online texts==
*[http://www.4literature.net/Jean_Jacques_Rousseau/Discourse_on_the_Moral_Effects/ A Discourse on the Moral Effects of the Arts and Sciences] English translation
*[http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/3913 Confessions of Jean-Jacques Rousseau] English translation, as published by Project Gutenberg, 2004 [EBook #3913]
*[http://www.constitution.org/jjr/poland.htm Considerations on the Government of Poland] English translation
*[http://www.constitution.org/jjr/corsica.htm Constitutional Project for Corsica] English translation
*[http://www.constitution.org/jjr/polecon.htm Discourse on Political Economy] English translation
*[http://www.constitution.org/jjr/ineq.htm Discourse on the Origin and Basis of Inequality Among Men] English translation
*[http://www.constitution.org/jjr/socon.htm The Social Contract, Or Principles of Political Right] English translation
*{{PDFlink|[http://web.archive.org/web/20091023175105/http://geocities.com/avisolo3/rousseaubotany.pdf 'Elementary Letters on Botany', 1771-3]|4.23&amp;nbsp;MB}}{{Dead link|date=May 2010}} English translation
*[http://projects.ilt.columbia.edu/pedagogies/rousseau/ Emile ] French text and English translation (Grace G. Roosevelt's revision and correction of Barbara Foxley's Everyman translation, at Columbia)
*[http://www.laphilosophie.fr/livres-de-Rousseau-texte-integral.html Full Ebooks of Rousseau in french] on the website 'La philosophie'
*[http://www.mondopolitico.com/library/thesocialcontract/thesocialcontracttoc.htm Mondo Politico Library's presentation of Jean-Jacques Rousseau's book, ''The Social Contract'' (G.D.H. Cole translation; full text)]
*[http://userwww.service.emory.edu/~cjcampb/sourcedocs/narcissus.html Narcissus, or The Self-Admirer: A Comedy] English translation
*[http://web.archive.org/web/20081220013534/http://www.normanschmidt.net/~abc/Rousseau.htm Project Concerning New Symbols for Music] French text and English translation, archived from [http://www.normanschmidt.net/%7Eabc/Rousseau.htm the original] on 2008-12-20
*[http://www.marxists.org/reference/subject/philosophy/works/fr/rousseau.htm The Creed of a Savoyard Priest] English translation
*{{gutenberg author|id=Jean-Jacques_Rousseau|name=Jean-Jacques Rousseau}}
* {{fr}} [http://athena.unige.ch/athena/rousseau/rousseau.html Texts of J.-J. Rousseau and biography at athena.unige.ch]
* {{fr}} [http://www.rousseauonline.ch Full Text of J.-J. Rousseau]

==See also==
*[[Age of Enlightenment]]
*[[Anarchism]]
*[[Anarcho-Primitivism]]
*[[Civil militia]]
*[[Classical republicanism]]
*[[Deism]]
*[[Georges Hébert]], a physical culturist influenced by Rousseau's teachings
*[[Let them eat cake]], a saying of Rousseau's
*[[List of Freemasons|List of Notable Freemasons]]
*[[Modernity]]
*[[Natural rights]]
*[[Rousseau Institute]]
*[[Philosophy of education#Jean-Jacques Rousseau|Rousseau's educational philosophy]]
*[[Social Contract]]
*[[State of Nature]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
*Abizadeh, Arash (2001). [http://profs-polisci.mcgill.ca/abizadeh/Banishing.htm &quot;Banishing the Particular: Rousseau on Rhetoric, ''Patrie,'' and the Passions&quot;] ''Political Theory'' 29.4: 556–82.
*[[Irving Babbitt|Babbitt, Irving]] ([1919] 1991).'' Rousseau and Romanticism''. Edison, New Jersey: Transaction Publishers (Library of Conservative Thought)
*Bertram, Christopher (2003). ''Rousseau and The Social Contract''. London: Routledge.
*[[Ernst Cassirer|Cassirer, Ernst]] (1945). ''Rousseau, Kant, Goethe''. Princeton University Press.
*Cassirer, Ernst ([1935]1989). ''The Question of Jean-Jacques Rousseau''. Peter Gay, editor and translator. Series editor, [[Jacques Barzun]]. Yale University Press.
*Conrad, Felicity (2008). &quot;Rousseau Gets Spanked, or, Chomsky's Revenge.&quot; ''The Journal of POLI 433.'' 1.1: 1–24.
*Cooper, Laurence (1999).'' Rousseau, Nature and the Problem of the Good Life''. Pennsylvania: Pennsylvania State University Press.
*Cottret, Monique and Bernard Cottret. ''Jean-Jacques Rousseau en son temps'', Paris, Perrin, 2005.
*[[Maurice Cranston|Cranston, Maurice]] (1982). ''Jean-Jacques: The Early Life and Work''. New York: Norton.
*Cranston, Maurice (1991). ''The Noble Savage''. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.
*Cranston, Maurice (1997). ''The Solitary Self''. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.
*[[Leo Damrosch|Damrosch, Leo]] (2005). ''Jean-Jacques Rousseau: Restless Genius''. New York: Houghton Mifflin.
*Dent, Nicholas, J.H. (1988). ''Rousseau : An Introduction to his Psychological, Social, and Political Theory''. Oxford: Blackwell.
*Dent, Nicholas, J. H. (1992). ''A Rousseau Dictionary''. Oxford: Blackwell.
*Dent, Nicholas. (2005). ''Rousseau''. London: Routledge.
*Derathé, Robert.(1948)''. Le Rationalism de J.-J. Rousseau''. Press Universitaires de France.
*Derathé, Robert ([1950] 1988). ''Jean-Jacques Rousseau et la Science Politique de Son Temps''. Paris: Vrin,
*[[Derrida, Jacques]] (1976). ''Of Grammatology'', trans. Gayatri Chakravorty Spivak. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins Press.
*[[Mario Einaudi|Einaudi, Mario]] (1968). ''Early Rousseau''. Ithaca: Cornell University Press.
*Ellingson, Ter. (2001). ''The Myth of the Noble Savage''. Berkeley, CA: University of California Press.
*Farrell, John (2006). ''Paranoia and Modernity: Cervantes to Rousseau.'' New York: Cornell University Press.
*[[Bernard Faÿ|Faÿ, Bernard]] (1974). ''Jean-Jacques Rousseau ou le Rêve de la vie'', Paris: Perrin
*Garrard, Graeme (2003). ''Rousseau's Counter-Enlightenment: A Republican Critique of the Philosophes''. Albany: State University of New York Press.
*Gauthier, David (2006). ''Rousseau: The Sentiment of Existence''. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.
*Hendel, Charles W. (1934). ''Jean-Jacques Rousseau: Moralist''. 2 Vols. (1934) Indianapolis, IN: Bobbs Merrill.
*Israel, Jonathan I., ''Radical Enlightenment: Philosophy and the Making of Modernity'', (Oxford University Press, 2002).
*[[Bertrand de Jouvenel|de Jouvenel, Bertrand]] (1962). &quot;Rousseau the Pessimistic Evolutionist.&quot; ''Yale French studies'' 27 83–96
*[[George Kateb|Kateb, George]] (1961). “Aspects of Rousseau’s Political Thought,” ''Political Science Quarterly'', December 1961.
*[[Dimitri Kitsikis|Kitsikis, Dimitri]] (2006).''Jean-Jacques Rousseau et les origines françaises du fascisme''. Nantes: Ars Magna Editions.
*LaFreniere, Gilbert F. (1990). &quot;Rousseau and the European Roots of Environmentalism.&quot; ''Environmental History Review'' 14 (No. 4): 41–72
*Lange, Lynda (2002). ''Feminist Interpretations of Jean-Jacques Rousseau''. University Park: Penn State University Press.
*[[Arthur Oncken Lovejoy|Lovejoy, Arthur O.]] ([1923] 1948). &quot;The Supposed Primitivism of Rousseau's 'Discourse on Inequality'&quot;. ''Modern Philology'': XXI: 165–186. Reprinted in ''Essays in the History of Ideas'' (Baltimore: John Hopkins Press). &quot;A classic treatment of the ''Second Discourse''&quot;—Nicholas Dent.
*Marks, Jonathan (2005).  ''Perfection and Disharmony in the Thought of Jean-Jacques Rousseau''. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.
*[[Masters, Roger D.|Roger Masters]] (ed.), 1964. ''The First and Second Discourses by Jean-Jacques Rousseau'', translated by Roger D Masters and Judith R Masters. New York: St. Martin's Press. ISBN 0-312-69440-7
*[[Masters, Roger D.|Roger Masters]], 1968. ''The Political Philosophy of Rousseau''. Princeton, N.J., Princeton University Press (ISBN 978-0-691-01989-5), also available in French (ISBN 2-84788-000-3).
*[[Masters, Roger D.|Roger Masters]] (ed.), 1978. ''On the Social Contract, with the Geneva Manuscript and Political Economy'' by Jean-Jacques Rousseau, translated by Judith R Masters. New York: St Martin’s Press (ISBN 0-312-69446-6).
*Melzer, Arthur (1990). ''The Natural Goodness of Man: On the System of Rousseau's Thought''. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.
*Pateman, Carole (1979). ''The Problem of Political Obligation: A Critical Analysis of Liberal Theory''. Chichester: John Wiley &amp; Sons.
*[[Patrick T. Riley|Riley, Patrick]] (1970). “A Possible Explanation of the General Will”. ''American Political Science Review'' 64:88
*Riley, Patrick (1978). &quot;General Will Before Rousseau&quot;. ''Political Theory'', vol. 6, No. 4: 485–516.
*Riley, Patrick (ed.) (2001). ''The Cambridge Companion to Rousseau''. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.
*Robinson, Dave &amp; Groves, Judy (2003). ''Introducing Political Philosophy''. Icon Books. ISBN 1-84046-450-X.
*Scott, John, T., editor (2006). ''Jean Jacques Rousseau, Volume 3: Critical Assessments of Leading Political Philosophers''. New York: Routledge.
*Simpson, Matthew (2006). ''Rousseau's Theory of Freedom''. London: Continuum Books.
*Simpson, Matthew (2007). ''Rousseau: Guide for the Perplexed''. London: Continuum Books.
*[[Jean Starobinski|Starobinski, Jean]] (1988). ''Jean-Jacques Rousseau: Transparency and Obstruction''. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.
*[[Strauss, Leo]] (1953). ''Natural Right and History''. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, chap. 6A.
*Strauss, Leo (1947). &quot;On the Intention of Rousseau,&quot; ''Social Research'' 14: 455–87.
*Strong, Tracy B. (2002). ''Jean Jacques Rousseau and the Politics of the Ordinary''. Lanham, MD: Rowman and Littlefield.
*[[Jacob Talmon|Talmon, Jacob R.]] (1952). ''The Origins of Totalitarian Democracy''. New York: W. W. Norton.
*Virioli, Maurizio ([1988] 2003). ''Jean-Jacques Rousseau and the 'Well-Ordered Society'''. Hanson, Derek, translator. Cambridge University Press, 2003 ISBN 0-521-53138-1, ISBN 978-0-521-53138-2
*Williams, David Lay (2007). ''Rousseau’s Platonic Enlightenment''. Pennsylvania State University Press.
*Wokler, Robert. (1995). ''Rousseau''. Oxford: Oxford University Press.
*Wokler, Robert. (2012) ''Rousseau, the Age of Enlightenment, and Their Legacies'' ed. by Bryan Garsten; introduction by Christopher Brooke
*Wraight, Christopher D. (2008), ''Rousseau's The Social Contract: A Reader's Guide''. London: Continuum Books.

==External links==

{{Sister project links|wikt=no|n=no|s=Author:Jean-Jacques Rousseau}}

*{{Britannica|510932}}
*{{IEP|rousseau|Jean-Jacques Rousseau}}
*{{SEP|rousseau|Jean Jacques Rousseau}}
*[http://www.rousseauassociation.org/ Rousseau Association/Association Rousseau], a bilingual association {{en icon}} {{fr icon}} devoted to the study of Rousseau's life and works
*[http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-9109503/Jean-Jacques-Rousseau Encyclopædia Britannica] entry of the Internet version &lt;!--Full EB articles are free when linked from Wikipedia. See &quot;next page&quot; link to see full article. 13 Feb 2009 No &quot;next page&quot; link found and no access to full article. --&gt;
*[http://philosophybites.com/2008/07/melissa-lane-on.html Philosophy Bites Audio Lecture, Professor Melissa Lane, Princeton University]
*[http://www.sciencelive.org/component/option,com_mediadb/task,play/idstr,Open-feeds_aa311_political_philosophy_aa311philosophy04_mp3/vv,-1/Itemid,26 Science Live Audio Lecture, Professor Timothy O'Hogan, Oxford University]
*{{IMSLP|id=Rousseau,_Jean-Jacques}}
*[http://www.earlymoderntexts.com A version of The Social Contract, slightly modified for easier reading]


{{Reflist}}

{{Age of Enlightenment}}
{{Social and political philosophy}}
{{French Revolution navbox}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2012}}
{{Authority control|LCCN=n/79/008220}}

&lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
{{Persondata
|NAME=Rousseau, Jean-Jacques
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=
|SHORT DESCRIPTION=Genevan philosopher
|DATE OF BIRTH={{Birth date|df=yes|1712|6|28}}
|PLACE OF BIRTH=[[Geneva]], Switzerland
|DATE OF DEATH={{Death date|df=yes|1778|7|2}}
|PLACE OF DEATH=[[Ermenonville]], France
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Rousseau, Jean-Jacques}}
[[Category:1712 births]]
[[Category:1778 deaths]]
[[Category:18th-century Swiss people]]
[[Category:18th-century philosophers]]
[[Category:Burials at the Panthéon, Paris]]
[[Category:Converts to Roman Catholicism from Calvinism]]
[[Category:Christian philosophers]]
[[Category:Continental philosophers]]
[[Category:Deists]]
[[Category:Early modern philosophers]]
[[Category:Enlightenment philosophers]]
[[Category:Music copyists]]
[[Category:French encyclopedists]]
[[Category:French memoirists]]
[[Category:French music theorists]]
[[Category:French novelists]]
[[Category:French political philosophers]]
[[Category:French republicans]]
[[Category:French Protestants]]
[[Category:People from Geneva]]
[[Category:Philosophes]]
[[Category:Political theorists]]
[[Category:Swiss autobiographers]]
[[Category:Swiss educationists]]
[[Category:Swiss emigrants to France]]
[[Category:Swiss memoirists]]
[[Category:Swiss music theorists]]
[[Category:Swiss novelists]]
[[Category:Swiss philosophers]]
[[Category:Swiss Protestants]]
[[Category:Swiss writers]]
[[Category:Romanticism]]
[[Category:Philosophers of education]]
[[Category:Jean-Jacques Rousseau| ]]
[[Category:18th-century French people]]
[[Category:French autobiographers]]
[[Category:French socialists]]
[[Category:Freemasons]]

{{Link FA|it}}
[[af:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[ar:جان جاك روسو]]
[[an:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[az:Jan Jak Russo]]
[[bn:জঁ-জাক রুসো]]
[[zh-min-nan:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[be:Жан-Жак Русо]]
[[be-x-old:Жан-Жак Русо]]
[[bg:Жан-Жак Русо]]
[[bs:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[br:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[ca:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[cs:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[cy:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[da:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[de:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[et:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[el:Ζαν Ζακ Ρουσσώ]]
[[es:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[eo:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[ext:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[eu:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[fa:ژان-ژاک روسو]]
[[hif:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[fr:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[fy:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[ga:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[gd:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[gl:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[ko:장자크 루소]]
[[hy:Ժան Ժակ Ռուսո]]
[[hi:रूसो]]
[[hr:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[io:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[id:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[ia:Jean Jacques Rousseau]]
[[is:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[it:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[he:ז'אן-ז'אק רוסו]]
[[jv:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[ka:ჟან-ჟაკ რუსო]]
[[kk:Руссо Жан-Жак]]
[[sw:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[ku:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[ky:Руссо, Жан-Жак]]
[[mrj:Руссо, Жан-Жак]]
[[la:Ioannes-Iacobus Rousseau]]
[[lv:Žans Žaks Ruso]]
[[lb:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[lt:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[hu:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[mk:Жан-Жак Русо]]
[[ml:റുസ്സോ]]
[[xmf:ჟან-ჟაკ რუსო]]
[[arz:جان جاك روسو]]
[[mn:Жан Жак Руссо]]
[[nl:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[ja:ジャン＝ジャック・ルソー]]
[[no:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[nn:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[oc:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[pnb:روسو]]
[[pms:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[nds:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[pl:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[pt:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[ro:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[qu:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[rue:Жан-Жак Руссо]]
[[ru:Руссо, Жан-Жак]]
[[sah:Жан-Жак Руссо]]
[[sc:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[sco:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[sq:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[scn:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[simple:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[sk:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[sl:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[so:Jaan Jaak Rosoo]]
[[ckb:ژان ژاک رۆسۆ]]
[[sr:Жан Жак Русо]]
[[sh:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[fi:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[sv:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[tl:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[ta:இழான் இழாக்கு உரூசோ]]
[[kab:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[roa-tara:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[te:జాన్ జాక్విస్ రూసో]]
[[th:ฌ็อง-ฌัก รูโซ]]
[[tr:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[uk:Жан-Жак Руссо]]
[[ur:جین جیکس روسو]]
[[vec:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[vi:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[vo:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[war:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[yi:זשאן-זשאק רוסא]]
[[yo:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[diq:Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[bat-smg:Žans Žaks Ruso]]
[[zh:让-雅克·卢梭]]</text>
      <sha1>1yrdyi5g9zrwj7bo6ljthqyf6hxcdz9</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
