<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>John Locke</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>16143</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522260501</id>
      <parentid>517799219</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T00:43:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>VIAFbot</username>
        <id>17215358</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Robot: Changing template: Normdaten</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="44232">{{Spoken Wikipedia|John Locke.ogg|2012-09-16}}
{{Other people}}
{{Use British English|date=August 2011}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2011}}
{{pp-semi-protect|small=yes}}
{{Infobox philosopher
| region = Western Philosophers
| era = [[17th-century philosophy]]&lt;br /&gt;(Modern Philosophy)
| colour = #B0C4DE
| image =JohnLocke.png
| alt = 
| caption =
| name = John Locke
| signature = John Locke Signature.svg
| birth_date = 29 August 1632
| birth_place = [[Wrington]], Somerset, England
| death_date = 28 October 1704 (aged 72)
| death_place = [[Essex]], England
| nationality = [[English people|English]]
| school_tradition = [[Empiricism|British Empiricism]], [[Social Contract]], [[Natural Law]]
| main_interests = [[Metaphysics]], [[Epistemology]], [[Political Philosophy]], [[Philosophy of Mind]], Education, [[Economics]]
| influences = [[Plato]], [[Aristotle]], [[Cicero]], [[Avicenna]], [[Ibn Tufail]], [[Thomas Aquinas|Aquinas]], [[Hugo Grotius|Grotius]], [[Samuel Rutherford]], [[René Descartes|Descartes]], [[Richard Hooker|Hooker]], [[Robert Filmer]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Two Treatises on Government|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|author=Peter Laslett|page=68|chapter=Introduction: Locke and Hobbes|year=1988|isbn=978-0-521-35730-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Thomas Hobbes|Hobbes]], [[Polish Brethren]] (religious group, whose ideas were incorporated into Locke's theories)
| influenced = [[David Hume|Hume]], [[Immanuel Kant|Kant]], [[George Berkeley|Berkeley]], [[Thomas Paine|Paine]], [[Adam Smith|Smith]] and many subsequent political philosophers, including the [[Founding Fathers of the United States|American Founding Fathers]], [[Arthur Schopenhauer]]
| notable_ideas = [[Tabula rasa]], &quot;government with the consent of the governed&quot;; [[state of nature]]; rights of life, [[liberty]] and [[property]]
}}
{{John Locke}}

'''John Locke''' [[Fellow of the Royal Society|FRS]] ({{IPAc-en|icon|ˈ|l|ɒ|k}}; 29 August 1632&amp;nbsp;– 28 October 1704), widely known as the ''Father of [[Classical Liberalism]]'',&lt;ref&gt;Locke, John. ''A Letter Concerning Toleration'' Routledge, New York, 1991. p. 5 (Introduction)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Delaney, Tim. ''The march of unreason: science, democracy, and the new fundamentalism'' Oxford University Press, New York, 2005. p. 18&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Godwin, Kenneth et al. ''School choice tradeoffs: liberty, equity, and diversity'' University of Texas Press, Austin, 2002. p. 12&lt;/ref&gt; was an English philosopher and physician regarded as one of the most influential of [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]] thinkers. Considered one of the first of the British [[Empiricism|empiricists]], following the tradition of [[Francis Bacon]], he is equally important to [[social contract]] theory. His work had a great impact upon the development of [[epistemology]] and [[political philosophy]]. His writings influenced [[Voltaire]] and [[Rousseau]], many [[Scottish Enlightenment]] thinkers, as well as the [[American Revolution|American revolutionaries]]. His contributions to [[classical republicanism]] and [[List of liberal theorists|liberal theory]] are reflected in the [[United States Declaration of Independence]].&lt;ref&gt;Becker, Carl Lotus. ''The Declaration of Independence: A Study in the History of Political Ideas'' Harcourt, Brace, 1922. p. 27&lt;/ref&gt;

Locke's [[philosophy of mind|theory of mind]] is often cited as the origin of modern conceptions of [[Identity (philosophy)|identity]] and the [[self (psychology)|self]], figuring prominently in the work of later philosophers such as [[David Hume|Hume]], [[Jean-Jacques Rousseau|Rousseau]] and [[Immanuel Kant|Kant]]. Locke was the first to define the self through a continuity of ''[[consciousness]]''. He postulated that the [[mind]] was a blank slate or ''[[tabula rasa]]''. Contrary to pre-existing [[Descartes|Cartesian]] philosophy, he maintained that we are born without [[innate ideas]], and that [[knowledge]] is instead determined only by [[experience]] derived from [[the senses|sense]] [[perception]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Baird |first=Forrest E. |coauthors=Walter Kaufmann |title=From Plato to Derrida |publisher=Pearson Prentice Hall |year=2008 |location=Upper Saddle River, New Jersey |pages=527–529 |url= |id= |isbn=0-13-158591-6 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Biography==
Locke's father, also called John, was a [[country lawyer]] and clerk to the Justices of the Peace in [[Chew Magna]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Broad, C.D.|year=2000 |title=Ethics And the History of Philosophy |publisher=Routledge|location=UK|isbn=0-415-22530-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; who had served as a captain of cavalry for the [[roundhead|Parliamentarian]] forces during the early part of the [[English Civil War]]. His mother was Agnes Keene. Both parents were [[Puritan]]s.
Locke was born on 29 August 1632, in a small thatched [[cottage]] by the church in [[Wrington]], Somerset, about twelve miles from [[Bristol]]. He was [[baptism|baptised]] the same day. Soon after Locke's birth, the family moved to the [[market town]] of [[Pensford]], about seven miles south of Bristol, where Locke grew up in a rural [[Tudor architecture|Tudor]] house in [[Belluton]].

In 1647, Locke was sent to the prestigious [[Westminster School]] in London under the sponsorship of [[Alexander Popham]], a member of Parliament and his father's former commander. After completing his studies there, he was admitted to [[Christ Church, Oxford]]. The dean of the college at the time was [[John Owen (theologian)|John Owen]], vice-chancellor of the university. Although a capable student, Locke was irritated by the undergraduate curriculum of the time. He found the works of modern philosophers, such as [[René Descartes]], more interesting than the [[classics|classical]] material taught at the university. Through his friend Richard Lower, whom he knew from the Westminster School, Locke was introduced to medicine and the experimental philosophy being pursued at other universities and in the [[Royal Society]], of which he eventually became a member.

Locke was awarded a [[bachelor's degree]] in 1656 and a master's degree in 1658. He obtained a [[bachelor of medicine]] in 1674, having studied medicine extensively during his time at [[Oxford]] and worked with such noted scientists and thinkers as [[Robert Boyle]], [[Thomas Willis]], [[Robert Hooke]] and [[Richard Lower (physician)|Richard Lower]]. In 1666, he met Lord [[Anthony Ashley Cooper, 1st Earl of Shaftesbury]], who had come to Oxford seeking treatment for a [[liver]] infection. Cooper was impressed with Locke and persuaded him to become part of his retinue.

Locke had been looking for a career and in 1667 moved into Shaftesbury's home at Exeter House in London, to serve as Lord Ashley's personal physician. In London, Locke resumed his medical studies under the tutelage of [[Thomas Sydenham]]. Sydenham had a major effect on Locke's natural philosophical thinking{{spaced ndash}}an effect that would become evident in ''[[An Essay Concerning Human Understanding]].''

Locke's medical knowledge was put to the test when Shaftesbury's liver infection became life-threatening. Locke coordinated the advice of several physicians and was probably instrumental in persuading Shaftesbury to undergo an operation (then life-threatening itself) to remove the cyst. Shaftesbury survived and prospered, crediting Locke with saving his life.

It was in Shaftesbury's household, during 1671, that the meeting took place, described in the Epistle to the reader of the Essay, which was the genesis of what would later become the Essay. Two extant Drafts still survive from this period. It was also during this time that Locke served as Secretary of the [[Board of Trade|Board of Trade and Plantations]] and Secretary to the [[Lords Proprietor|Lords and Proprietors of the Carolinas]], helping to shape his ideas on international trade and economics.
[[File:Locke-John-LOC.jpg|thumb|left|upright|John Locke]]
Shaftesbury, as a founder of the [[British Whig Party|Whig]] movement, exerted great influence on Locke's political ideas. Locke became involved in politics when Shaftesbury became [[Lord Chancellor]] in 1672. Following Shaftesbury's fall from favour in 1675, Locke spent some time travelling across France as tutor and medical attendant to [[Caleb Banks]].&lt;ref name=Henning&gt;{{cite web|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=HW1_upECKUwC&amp;pg=PA590&amp;lpg=PA590&amp;dq=%22Caleb+Banks%22+Aylesford&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=MrFiH8wo58&amp;sig=BSwNCUPELs2IqH8aXK6QiDan7zA&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=0D3gTMmkMdeqhAeFkNnCDQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CBkQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Caleb%20Banks%22%20Aylesford&amp;f=false |title=Basil Duke Henning '&amp;#39;The House of Commons, 1660–1690, Volume 1'&amp;#39; |publisher=Books.google.com |date= |accessdate=28 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; He returned to England in 1679 when Shaftesbury's political fortunes took a brief positive turn. Around this time, most likely at Shaftesbury's prompting, Locke composed the bulk of the ''[[Two Treatises of Government]]''. While it was once thought that Locke wrote the Treatises to defend the [[Glorious Revolution]] of 1688, recent scholarship has shown that the work was composed well before this date,&lt;ref&gt;Peter Laslett, &quot;''Two Treatises of Government'' and the Revolution of 1688,&quot; section III of Laslett's editorial &quot;Introduction&quot; to John Locke, ''Two Treatises of Government'', Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1988.&lt;/ref&gt; and it is now viewed as a more general argument against [[absolute monarchy]] (particularly as espoused by [[Robert Filmer]] and [[Thomas Hobbes]]) and for individual consent as the basis of [[political legitimacy]]. Though Locke was associated with the influential Whigs, his ideas about [[natural and legal rights|natural right]]s and government are today considered quite revolutionary for that period in English history.

Locke fled to the [[Netherlands]] in 1683, under strong suspicion of involvement in the [[Rye House Plot]], although there is little evidence to suggest that he was directly involved in the scheme. In the Netherlands, Locke had time to return to his writing, spending a great deal of time re-working the Essay and composing the Letter on Toleration. Locke did not return home until after the [[Glorious Revolution]]. Locke accompanied [[William III of England|William of Orange]]'s wife back to England in 1688. The bulk of Locke's publishing took place upon his return from exile{{spaced ndash}}his aforementioned ''Essay Concerning Human Understanding'', the ''Two Treatises of Civil Government'' and ''[[A Letter Concerning Toleration]]'' all appearing in quick succession.

Locke's close friend Lady Masham invited him to join her at the Mashams' country house in Essex. Although his time there was marked by variable health from [[asthma]] attacks, he nevertheless became an intellectual hero of the Whigs. During this period he discussed matters with such figures as [[John Dryden]] and [[Isaac Newton]].

He died on 28 October 1704, and is buried in the churchyard of the village of [[High Laver]],&lt;ref&gt;''Britannica Online'', s.v. John Locke&lt;/ref&gt; east of [[Harlow]] in Essex, where he had lived in the household of Sir Francis Masham since 1691. Locke never married nor had children. &lt;!-- He is buried at Christ Church Cathedral in Oxford. [http://www.findagrave.com/cgi-bin/fg.cgi?page=cr&amp;GRid=5746831&amp;CRid=658455&amp;]. Note: appears to be just a memorial.--&gt;

Events that happened during Locke's lifetime include the [[English Restoration]], the [[Great Plague of London]] and the [[Great Fire of London]]. He did not quite see the [[Act of Union 1707|Act of Union]] of 1707, though the thrones of England and Scotland were held in [[personal union]] throughout his lifetime. [[Constitutional monarchy]] and [[parliamentary democracy]] were in their infancy during Locke's time.

==Influence==
Locke exercised a profound influence on political philosophy, in particular on modern liberalism. Michael Zuckert has argued that Locke launched liberalism by tempering Hobbesian absolutism and clearly [[separation of church and state|separating the realms of Church and State]]. He had a strong influence on [[Voltaire]] who called him &quot;le sage Locke&quot;. His arguments concerning [[liberty]] and the [[social contract]] later influenced the written works of [[Alexander Hamilton]], [[James Madison]], [[Thomas Jefferson]], and other [[Founding Fathers of the United States]]. In fact, one passage from the ''Second Treatise'' is reproduced verbatim in the Declaration of Independence, the reference to a &quot;long train of abuses.&quot; Such was Locke's influence that Thomas Jefferson wrote: &quot;[[Francis Bacon|Bacon]], Locke and [[Isaac Newton|Newton]] ... I consider them as the three greatest men that have ever lived, without any exception, and as having laid the foundation of those superstructures which have been raised in the Physical and Moral sciences&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| title       = The Three Greatest Men
| url         = http://www.loc.gov/exhibits/treasures/trm033.html
| accessdate  =13 June 2009
| quote       = Jefferson identified [[Francis Bacon|Bacon]], Locke, and [[Isaac Newton|Newton]] as &quot;the three greatest men that have ever lived, without any exception&quot;. Their works in the physical and moral sciences were instrumental in Jefferson's education and world view.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| title       = The Letters of Thomas Jefferson: 1743–1826 Bacon, Locke, and Newton
| url         = http://www.let.rug.nl/usa/P/tj3/writings/brf/jefl74.htm
| accessdate  =13 June 2009
| quote       = Bacon, Locke and Newton, whose pictures I will trouble you to have copied for me: and as I consider them as the three greatest men that have ever lived, without any exception, and as having laid the foundation of those superstructures which have been raised in the Physical &amp; Moral sciences.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://explorer.monticello.org/text/index.php?id=82&amp;type=4 |title=Jefferson called Bacon, Newton, and Locke, who had so indelibly shaped his ideas, &quot;my trinity of the three greatest men the world had ever produced&quot; |publisher=Explorer.monticello.org |date= |accessdate=28 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Today, most contemporary [[libertarians]] claim Locke as an influence.

But Locke's influence may have been even more profound in the realm of epistemology. Locke redefined subjectivity, or self, and intellectual historians such as [[Charles Taylor (philosopher)|Charles Taylor]] and Jerrold Seigel argue that Locke's ''[[An Essay Concerning Human Understanding]]'' (1690) marks the beginning of the modern Western conception of the self.&lt;ref&gt;Seigel, Jerrold. ''The Idea of the Self: Thought and Experience in Western Europe since the Seventeenth Century.'' Cambridge: Cambridge University Press (2005) and Charles Taylor, ''Sources of the Self: The Making of Modern Identity''. Cambridge: Harvard University Press (1989).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Theories of religious tolerance===
Locke, writing his ''Letters Concerning Toleration'' (1689–92) in the aftermath of the [[European wars of religion]], formulated a classic reasoning for religious tolerance. Three arguments are central: (1) Earthly judges, the state in particular, and human beings generally, cannot dependably evaluate the truth-claims of competing religious standpoints; (2) Even if they could, enforcing a single &quot;true religion&quot; would not have the desired effect, because belief cannot be compelled by violence; (3) Coercing religious uniformity would lead to more social disorder than allowing diversity.&lt;ref&gt;McGrath, Alistair. 1998. ''Historical Theology, An Introduction to the History of Christian Thought.'' Oxford: Blackwell Publishers. p.214-5.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Constitution of Carolina===
Appraisals of Locke have often been tied to appraisals of liberalism in general, and also to appraisals of the United States. Detractors note that (in 1671) he was a major investor in the English slave-trade through the [[Royal African Company]], as well as through his participation in drafting the ''[[Fundamental Constitutions of Carolina|Fundamental Constitution of the Carolinas]]'' while [[Anthony Ashley-Cooper, 1st Earl of Shaftesbury|Shaftesbury]]'s secretary, which established a feudal aristocracy and gave a master absolute power over his slaves. For example, [[Martin Cohen (philosopher)|Martin Cohen]] notes that as a secretary to the Council of Trade and Plantations (1673–4) and a member of the Board of Trade (1696–1700) Locke was, in fact, &quot;one of just half a dozen men who created and supervised both the colonies and their iniquitous systems of servitude&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Martin Cohen, ''Philosophical Tales'' (Blackwell, 2008), 101.&lt;/ref&gt; Some see his statements on [[enclosure|unenclosed]] [[property]] as having been intended to justify the displacement of the Native Americans.&lt;ref&gt;James Tully, ''An Approach to Political Philosophy: Locke in Contexts'' (New York: Cambridge University Press, 2007).{{pn|date=October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1177/0090591786014002005 |title=I. 'So Vile and Miserable an Estate': The Problem of Slavery in Locke's Political Thought |year=1986 |last1=Farr |first1=J. |journal=Political Theory |volume=14 |issue=2 |pages=263–89 |jstor=191463}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Because of his opposition to aristocracy and slavery in his major writings, he is accused of hypocrisy and racism, or of caring only for the liberty of English capitalists.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1177/0090591708317899 |title=Locke, Natural Law, and New World Slavery |year=2008 |last1=Farr |first1=J. |journal=Political Theory |volume=36 |issue=4 |pages=495–522}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Theory of value and property===
Locke uses the word ''property'' in both broad and narrow senses. In a broad sense, it covers a wide range of human interests and aspirations; more narrowly, it refers to material goods. He argues that property is a natural right and it is derived from [[manual labour|labour]].

In Chapter V of his ''[[Two Treatises of Government|Second Treatise]]'', Locke argues that the individual ownership of goods and property is justified by the labour exerted to produce those goods or utilise property to produce goods beneficial to human society.&lt;ref name=labortheory&gt;{{cite journal|last=Vaughn|first=Karen|title=John Locke and the Labor Theory of Value|journal=Journal of Libertarian Studies|year=1978|volume=2|issue=4|pages=311–326|url=https://mises.org/journals/jls/2_4/2_4_3.pdf|accessdate=13 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Locke stated his belief, in his ''Second Treatise'', that nature on its own provides little of value to society; he provides the implication that the labour expended in the creation of goods gives them their value. This is used as supporting evidence for the interpretation of Locke's [[labour theory of property]] as a [[labour theory of value]], in his implication that goods produced by nature are of little value, unless combined with labour in their production and that labour is what gives goods their value.&lt;ref name=labortheory/&gt;

Locke believed that ownership of [[property]] is created by the application of labour. In addition, he believed property precedes government and government cannot &quot;dispose of the estates of the subjects arbitrarily.&quot; [[Karl Marx]] later critiqued Locke's theory of property in his own social theory.

===Political theory===
{{See also|Two Treatises of Government}}

Locke's political theory was founded on [[social contract]] theory. Unlike [[Thomas Hobbes]], Locke believed that [[human nature]] is characterised by reason and tolerance. Like Hobbes, Locke believed that human nature allowed men to be selfish. This is apparent with the introduction of currency. In a [[State of nature#Locke's view on the state of nature|natural state]] all people were equal and independent, and everyone had a natural right to defend his “Life, health, Liberty, or Possessions&quot;.&lt;ref name = &quot;locke&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Locke | first = John | title = [[Second Treatise of Government]] (10th edition) | publisher=[[Project Gutenberg]] | year = 1690 | url = http://www.gutenberg.org/files/7370/7370-h/7370-h.htm | accessdate =25 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most scholars trace the phrase, &quot;[[life, liberty, and the pursuit of happiness]],&quot; in the American Declaration of Independence to Locke's theory of rights,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Zuckert|first=Michael|title=The Natural Rights Republic|year=1996|publisher=Notre Dame University Press|pages=73–85}}&lt;/ref&gt; though other origins have been suggested.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Wills|first=Garry|title=Inventing America: Jefferson's Declaration of Independence|location=Boston|publisher=Houghton Mifflin Co|year=2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Like Hobbes, Locke assumed that the sole right to defend in the state of nature was not enough, so people established a [[civil society]] to resolve conflicts in a civil way with help from government in a state of society. However, Locke never refers to Hobbes by name and may instead have been responding to other writers of the day.&lt;ref&gt;Skinner, Quentin ''Visions of Politics''. Cambridge.&lt;/ref&gt; Locke also advocated governmental [[separation of powers]] and believed that revolution is not only a [[Right of revolution|right]] but an obligation in some circumstances. These ideas would come to have profound influence on the [[United States Declaration of Independence|Declaration of Independence]] and the [[Constitution of the United States]].

====Limits to accumulation====
Labour creates property, but it also does contain limits to its accumulation: man’s capacity to produce and man’s capacity to consume. According to Locke, unused property is waste and an offence against nature.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Locke|first=John|title=Two Treatises on Government: A Translation Into Modern English|year=2009|publisher=Industrial Systems Research|isbn=978-0-906321-47-8|page=81|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=S3eB0IgzJjoC&amp;pg=PA81&amp;lpg=PA81&amp;dq=John+Locke+unused+property+waste+offence+against+nature&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=W8lZU26AMR&amp;sig=NWdG1m9YODIVfTm1857aa2Rbuzc&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=IadfTsLcM4G68gObiOnGAw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=10&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CGgQ6AEwCQ#v=onepage&amp;q=unused%20property&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, with the introduction of “durable” goods, men could exchange their excessive perishable goods for goods that would last longer and thus not offend the natural law. The introduction of money marks the culmination of this process. Money makes possible the unlimited accumulation of property without causing waste through spoilage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=John Locke: �Inequality is inevitable and necessary|url=http://www0.hku.hk/philodep/courses/ac/Phil1003-2008/Locke2.ppt|publisher=Department of Philosophy The University of Hong Kong|accessdate=1 September 2011 | format=PowerPoint}}&lt;/ref&gt;  He also includes gold or silver as money because they may be “hoarded up without injury to anyone,”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=John Locke, Second Treatise, §§ 25--51, 123--26|url=http://press-pubs.uchicago.edu/founders/documents/v1ch16s3.html|publisher=The Founders Constitution|accessdate=1 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; since they do not spoil or decay in the hands of the possessor. The introduction of money eliminates the limits of accumulation. Locke stresses that inequality has come about by tacit agreement on the use of money, not by the social contract establishing civil society or the law of land regulating property. Locke is aware of a problem posed by unlimited accumulation but does not consider it his task. He just implies that government would function to moderate the conflict between the unlimited accumulation of property and a more nearly equal distribution of wealth and does not say which principles that government should apply to solve this problem. However, not all elements of his thought form a consistent whole. For example, [[labour theory of value]] of the [[Two Treatises of Government]] stands side by side with the demand-and-supply theory developed in a letter he wrote titled ''Some Considerations on the Consequences of the Lowering of Interest and the Raising of the Value of Money''. Moreover, Locke anchors property in labour but in the end upholds the unlimited accumulation of wealth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=John Locke on Property|url=http://www.cooperativeindividualism.org/cobb-cliff-and-fred-foldvary_john-locke-on-property-1999.html|publisher=The School of Cooperative Individualism|accessdate=14 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===On price theory===
Locke’s general theory of value and price is a [[supply and demand]] theory, which was set out in a letter to a Member of Parliament in 1691, titled ''Some Considerations on the Consequences of the Lowering of Interest and the Raising of the Value of Money''.&lt;ref&gt;John Locke (1691) [http://www.marxists.org/reference/subject/economics/locke/contents.htm ''Some Considerations on the consequences of the Lowering of Interest and the Raising of the Value of Money'']&lt;/ref&gt; Supply is quantity and demand is [[Economic rent|rent]]. “The price of any commodity rises or falls by the proportion of the number of buyer and sellers.” and “that which regulates the price... [of goods] is nothing else but their quantity in proportion to their rent.” The quantity theory of money forms a special case of this general theory. His idea is based on “money answers all things” (Ecclesiastes) or “rent of money is always sufficient, or more than enough,” and “varies very little...” Regardless of whether the [[demand for money]] is unlimited or constant, Locke concludes that as far as money is concerned, the demand is exclusively regulated by its quantity. He also investigates the determinants of demand and supply. For supply, goods in general are considered valuable because they can be exchanged, consumed and they must be scarce. For demand, goods are in demand because they yield a flow of income. Locke develops an early theory of [[capitalisation]], such as land, which has value because “by its constant production of saleable commodities it brings in a certain yearly income.” Demand for money is almost the same as demand for goods or land; it depends on whether money is wanted as medium of exchange or as [[loanable funds]]. For medium of exchange “money is capable by exchange to procure us the necessaries or conveniences of life.” For loanable funds, “it comes to be of the same nature with land by yielding a certain yearly income ... or interest.”

====Monetary thoughts====
Locke distinguishes two functions of money, as a &quot;counter&quot; to measure value, and as a &quot;pledge&quot; to lay claim to [[good (economics)|goods]]. He believes that silver and gold, as opposed to paper money, are the appropriate currency for international transactions. Silver and gold, he says, are treated to have equal value by all of humanity and can thus be treated as a pledge by anyone, while the value of paper money is only valid under the government which issues it.

Locke argues that a country should seek a favourable [[balance of trade]], lest it fall behind other countries and suffer a loss in its trade. Since the world money stock grows constantly, a country must constantly seek to enlarge its own stock. Locke develops his theory of foreign exchanges, in addition to commodity movements, there are also movements in country stock of money, and movements of capital determine exchange rates. The latter is less significant and less volatile than commodity movements. As for a country’s [[money supply|money stock]], if it is large relative to that of other countries, it will cause the country’s exchange to rise above par, as an export balance would do.

He also prepares estimates of the [[cash]] requirements for different economic groups (landholders, labourers and brokers). In each group the cash requirements are closely related to the length of the pay period. He argues the brokers&amp;nbsp;– middlemen&amp;nbsp;– whose activities enlarge the monetary circuit and whose profits eat into the earnings of labourers and landholders, had a negative influence on both one's personal and the public economy that they supposedly contributed to.

===The self===
Locke defines the self as &quot;that conscious thinking thing, (whatever substance, made up of whether spiritual, or material, simple, or compounded, it matters not) which is sensible, or conscious of pleasure and pain, capable of happiness or misery, and so is concerned for itself, as far as that consciousness extends&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Locke, John. ''An Essay Concerning Human Understanding''. Ed. Roger Woolhouse. New York: [[Penguin Books]] (1997), p. 307.&lt;/ref&gt;  He does not, however, ignore &quot;substance&quot;, writing that &quot;the body too goes to the making the man.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Locke, ''Essay'', p. 306.&lt;/ref&gt;  The Lockean self is therefore a self-aware and self-reflective consciousness that is fixed in a body.

In his ''Essay'', Locke explains the gradual unfolding of this conscious mind. Arguing against both the [[Augustine of Hippo|Augustinian]] view of man as [[original sin|originally sinful]] and the [[René Descartes|Cartesian]] position, which holds that man innately knows basic logical propositions, Locke posits an &quot;empty&quot; mind, a ''tabula rasa'', which is shaped by experience; [[Wikt:sensation|sensations]] and [[human self-reflection|reflection]]s being the two sources of '''all''' our [[idea]]s.&lt;ref&gt;The American International Encyclopedia, J.J. Little Company, New York 1954, Volume 9.&lt;/ref&gt;

John Locke's formulation of tabula rasa in ''[[An Essay Concerning Human Understanding]]'' was influenced by a 17th century [[Latin]] translation ''Philosophus Autodidactus'' (published by [[Edward Pococke]]) of the [[Arabic literature|Arabic philosophical novel]] ''[[Hayy ibn Yaqzan]]'' by the 12th century [[Al-Andalus|Andalusian]]-[[Early Islamic philosophy|Islamic philosopher]] and novelist [[Ibn Tufail]] (known as &quot;Abubacer&quot; or &quot;Ebn Tophail&quot; in the West). [[Ibn Tufail]] demonstrated the theory of tabula rasa as a [[thought experiment]] through his [[Arabic literature|Arabic philosophical novel]] novel ''[[Hayy ibn Yaqzan]]'' in which he depicted the development of the mind of a [[feral child]] &quot;from a tabula rasa to that of an adult, in complete isolation from society&quot; on a [[desert island]], through [[experience]] alone.&lt;ref name=Russell&gt;G. A. Russell (1994), ''The 'Arabick' Interest of the Natural Philosophers in Seventeenth-Century England'', pp. 224–262, [[Brill Publishers]], ISBN 90-04-09459-8.&lt;/ref&gt;

Locke's ''[[Some Thoughts Concerning Education]]'' is an outline on how to educate this mind: he expresses the belief that education maketh the man, or, more fundamentally, that the mind is an &quot;empty cabinet&quot;, with the statement, &quot;I think I may say that of all the men we meet with, nine parts of ten are what they are, good or evil, useful or not, by their education.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Locke, John. ''Some Thoughts Concerning Education and Of the Conduct of the Understanding''. Eds. Ruth
W. Grant and Nathan Tarcov. [[Indianapolis]]: [[Hackett Publishing Company|Hackett Publishing Co.]], Inc. (1996), p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt;

Locke also wrote that &quot;the little and almost insensible impressions on our tender infancies have very important and lasting consequences.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Locke, ''Some Thoughts'', 10.&lt;/ref&gt;  He argued that the &quot;[[Association of Ideas|associations of ideas]]&quot; that one makes when young are more important than those made later because they are the foundation of the self: they are, put differently, what first mark the ''tabula rasa''. In his ''Essay'', in which is introduced both of these concepts, Locke warns against, for example, letting &quot;a foolish maid&quot; convince a child that &quot;goblins and sprites&quot; are associated with the night for &quot;darkness shall ever afterwards bring with it those frightful ideas, and they shall be so joined, that he can no more bear the one than the other.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Locke, ''Essay'', 357.&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;Associationism&quot;, as this theory would come to be called, exerted a powerful influence over eighteenth-century thought, particularly [[education theory|educational theory]], as nearly every educational writer warned parents not to allow their children to develop negative associations. It also led to the development of [[psychology]] and other new disciplines with [[David Hartley (philosopher)|David Hartley]]'s attempt to discover a biological mechanism for associationism in his ''[[Observations on Man]]'' (1749).

==Religious beliefs==
Some scholars have seen Locke's political convictions as deriving from his religious beliefs.&lt;ref&gt;Greg Forster ''John Locke's politics of moral consensus'' 2005&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kim Ian Parker ''The biblical politics of John Locke'' 2004 Canadian Corporation for Studies in Religion&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''John Locke: writings on religion'' ed. Victor Nuovo, Oxford 2002&lt;/ref&gt; Locke's religious trajectory began in [[Calvinist]] [[trinitarianism]], but by the time of the ''Reflections'' (1695) Locke was advocating not just [[Socinianism|Socinian]] views on tolerance but also Socinian Christology; with veiled denial of the [[pre-existence of Christ]].&lt;ref&gt;John Marshall ''John Locke: resistance, religion and responsibility'' Cambridge 1994. extensive discussion p.426&lt;/ref&gt; However Wainwright (Oxford, 1987) notes that in the posthumously published ''Paraphrase'' (1707) Locke's interpretation of one verse, Ephesians 1:10, is markedly different from that of Socinians like [[John Biddle (Unitarian)|Biddle]], and may indicate that near the end of his life Locke returned nearer to an [[Arian]] position.&lt;ref&gt;John Locke, ed. Arthur William Wainwright ''A paraphrase and notes on the Epistles of St. Paul to the Galatians, 1 and 2 Corinthians, Romans, Ephesians,'' Oxford 1987 p806&lt;/ref&gt;

==List of major works==
*(1689) ''[[A Letter Concerning Toleration]]''
**(1690) ''A Second Letter Concerning Toleration''
**(1692) ''A Third Letter for Toleration''
*(1689) ''[[Two Treatises of Government]]''
*(1690) ''[[An Essay Concerning Human Understanding]]''
*(1693) ''[[Some Thoughts Concerning Education]]''
*(1695) ''The Reasonableness of Christianity, as Delivered in the Scriptures''
**(1695) ''A Vindication of the Reasonableness of Christianity''

===Major unpublished or posthumous manuscripts===
*(1660) ''First Tract of Government'' (or ''the English Tract'')
*(''c.''1662) ''Second Tract of Government'' (or ''the Latin Tract'')
*(1664) ''Questions Concerning the Law of Nature'' (definitive Latin text, with facing accurate English trans. in Robert Horwitz et al., eds., John Locke, ''Questions Concerning the Law of Nature'', Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 1990).
*(1667) ''Essay Concerning Toleration''
*(1706) ''[[Of the Conduct of the Understanding]]''
*(1707) ''A paraphrase and notes on the Epistles of St. Paul to the Galatians, 1 and 2 Corinthians, Romans, Ephesians''

==See also==
{{Portal|Liberalism}}
*[[Libertarianism]]
*[[List of liberal theorists]]
*[[U.S. Constitution#Republics and fundamental law |U.S. Constitution]], influences

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin|30em}}
*Ashcraft, Richard, 1986.  ''Revolutionary Politics &amp; Locke's Two Treatises of Government.''  Princeton: Princeton University Press. (Discusses the relationship between Locke's philosophy and his political activities.)
*Ayers, Michael., 1991. ''Locke. Epistemology &amp; Ontology'' Routledge (The standard work on Locke's Essay Concerning Human Understanding.)
*Bailyn, Bernard, 1992 (1967). ''The Ideological Origins of the American Revolution''. Harvard Uni. Press. (Discusses the influence of Locke and other thinkers upon the American Revolution and on subsequent American political thought.)
*[[Gerald Cohen|Cohen, Gerald]], 1995. 'Marx and Locke on Land and Labour', in his ''Self-Ownership, Freedom and Equality'', Oxford University Press.
*Cox, Richard, ''Locke on War and Peace'', Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1960. (A discussion of Locke's theory of international relations.)
*Chappell, Vere, ed., 19nn. ''The Cambridge Companion to Locke''. Cambridge Uni. Press.
*Dunn, John, 1984. ''Locke''. Oxford Uni. Press. (A succinct introduction.)
*—, 1969. ''The Political Thought of John Locke: An Historical Account of the Argument of the &quot;Two Treatises of Government&quot;''. Cambridge Uni. Press. (Introduced the interpretation which emphasises the theological element in Locke's political thought.)
*Hudson, Nicholas, &quot;John Locke and the Tradition of Nominalism,&quot; in: ''Nominalism and Literary Discourse'', ed. Hugo Keiper, [[Christoph Bode]], and Richard Utz (Amsterdam: Rodopi, 1997), pp.&amp;nbsp;283–99.
*[[C. B. Macpherson|Macpherson. C. B.]] ''The Political Theory of Possessive Individualism: Hobbes to Locke'' (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1962). (Establishes the deep affinity from Hobbes to Harrington, the Levellers, and Locke through to nineteenth-century utilitarianism).
*{{cite book|last=Moseley|first=Alexander|year=2007|title=John Locke: Continuum Library of Educational Thought|publisher=Continuum|isbn=0-8264-8405-0}}
*[[Thomas Pangle|Pangle, Thomas]], ''The Spirit of Modern Republicanism: The Moral Vision of the American Founders and the Philosophy of Locke'' (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1988; paperback ed., 1990), 334 pages. (Challenges Dunn's, Tully's, Yolton's, and other conventional readings.)
*{{cite book|last=Robinson|first=Dave|coauthors=Judy Groves|year=2003|title=Introducing Political Philosophy|publisher=Icon Books|isbn=1-84046-450-X}}
*{{cite book|last=Rousseau|first=George S.|year=2004|title=Nervous Acts: Essays on Literature, Culture and Sensibility|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|isbn=1-4039-3453-3}}
*[[Strauss, Leo]]. ''Natural Right and History'', chap. 5B (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1953). (Argues from a non-Marxist point of view for a deep affinity between Hobbes and Locke.)
*{{cite journal |first1=Leo |last1=Strauss |year=1958 |title=Critical Note: Locke's Doctrine of Natural Law |journal=The American Political Science Review |volume=52 |issue=2 |pages=490–501 |jstor=1952329 |doi=10.2307/1952329}} (A critique of W. von Leyden's edition of Locke's unpublished writings on natural law.)
*Tully, James, 1980.  ''A Discourse on Property : John Locke and his Adversaries''. Cambridge Uni. Press
*[[Jeremy Waldron|Waldron, Jeremy]], 2002. ''God, Locke and Equality''. Cambridge Uni. Press.
*Yolton, J. W., ed., 1969. ''John Locke: Problems and Perspectives''. Cambridge Uni. Press.
*Zuckert, Michael, ''Launching Liberalism: On Lockean Political Philosophy''. Lawrence, KS: University Press of Kansas.
*''Locke Studies'', appearing annually, publishes scholarly work on John Locke.
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Wikisource author}}
{{Wikiquote}}

===Works===
*[http://john-locke.com/ John Locke eText Archive]
*{{gutenberg author|id=John+Locke+(1632–1704) | name=John Locke}}
*[http://onlinebooks.library.upenn.edu/webbin/book/search?amode=start&amp;author=Locke,%20John Links to online books by John Locke]
*''The Works of John Locke''
**[http://socserv2.mcmaster.ca/~econ/ugcm/3ll3/locke/index.html 1823 Edition, 10 Volumes on PDF files, and additional resources]
**[http://oll.libertyfund.org/index.php?option=com_staticxt&amp;staticfile=show.php%3Fperson=131&amp;Itemid=28 1824 Edition, 9 volumes in multiple formats]
*[http://www.libraries.psu.edu/tas/locke/mss/index.html John Locke Manuscripts]
*[http://www.earlymoderntexts.com/ Updated versions of ''Essay Concerning Human Understanding'', ''Second Treatise of Government'', and ''Letter on Toleration''], edited by [[Jonathan Bennett (philosopher)|Jonathan Bennett]]
* Locke, ''Two Treatises of Government,'' ed. Thomas Hollis (A. Millar et al., 1764) ''See original text in [http://oll.libertyfund.org/index.php?option=com_staticxt&amp;staticfile=show.php%3Ftitle=222&amp;Itemid=99999999 The Online Library of Liberty]''
*{{Worldcat id|lccn-n79-90225}}

===Resources===
*{{Sep entry|locke|John Locke|William Uzgalis|2007-05-05}}
*[http://mind.ucsd.edu/syllabi/99_00/Empiricism/Readings/Encyc_Phil/Locke.html Macmillan Encyclopedia of Philosophy entry on Locke]
*[http://www.libraries.psu.edu/tas/locke/index.html John Locke Bibliography]
*[http://thegreatdebate.org.uk/LockeEpistem.html John Locke’s Theory of Knowledge] by Caspar Hewett
*[http://www.digitallockeproject.nl/ The Digital Locke Project]
*[http://www.npg.org.uk/live/search/person.asp?LinkID=mp02773 Portraits of Locke]
*A complex and positive answer to question [http://www.independent.org/pdf/tir/tir_01_4_huyler.pdf Was Locke a Liberal?]&amp;nbsp;– by Jerome Huyler
*Timeline of the Life and Work of John Locke at [http://oll.libertyfund.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=1181&amp;Itemid=273 The Online Library of Liberty]
*Locke on Property: A Bibliographical Essay by Karen Vaughn [http://oll.libertyfund.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=166&amp;Itemid=259 The Online Library of Liberty.]
{{Navboxes
|title=Articles and topics related to John Locke
|state=collapsed
|list1=&lt;/span&gt;
{{Age of Enlightenment}}
{{metaphysics}}
{{epistemology}}
{{Social and political philosophy}}
{{Authority control|LCCN=n/79/90225}}
}}

&lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
{{Persondata
|NAME=Locke, John
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=
|SHORT DESCRIPTION=English philosopher
|DATE OF BIRTH= 29 August 1632
|PLACE OF BIRTH=[[Wrington]], Somerset, England
|DATE OF DEATH=29 October 1704
|PLACE OF DEATH=[[Essex]], England
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Locke, John}}
[[Category:John Locke| ]]
[[Category:Alumni of Christ Church, Oxford]]
[[Category:Christian philosophers]]
[[Category:Classical liberals]]
[[Category:Early modern philosophers]]
[[Category:Empiricists]]
[[Category:English Anglicans]]
[[Category:English Christian theologians]]
[[Category:English political philosophers]]
[[Category:Enlightenment philosophers]]
[[Category:Epistemologists]]
[[Category:Fellows of Christ Church, Oxford]]
[[Category:Fellows of the Royal Society]]
[[Category:Metaphysicians]]
[[Category:People educated at Westminster School, London]]
[[Category:People from Wrington]]
[[Category:People of the Rye House Plot]]
[[Category:Philosophers of language]]
[[Category:Philosophers of law]]
[[Category:Political theorists]]
[[Category:1632 births]]
[[Category:1704 deaths]]
[[Category:17th-century English medical doctors]]
[[Category:17th-century philosophers]]

{{Link GA|de}}
{{Link GA|no}}
{{Link GA|zh}}
{{Link FA|vi}}

[[af:John Locke]]
[[am:ጆን ሎክ]]
[[ar:جون لوك]]
[[an:John Locke]]
[[az:Con Lokk]]
[[bn:জন লক]]
[[zh-min-nan:John Locke]]
[[be:Джон Лок]]
[[be-x-old:Джон Лок]]
[[bg:Джон Лок]]
[[bs:John Locke]]
[[br:John Locke]]
[[ca:John Locke]]
[[cs:John Locke]]
[[cy:John Locke]]
[[da:John Locke]]
[[de:John Locke]]
[[et:John Locke]]
[[el:Τζων Λοκ]]
[[es:John Locke]]
[[eo:John Locke]]
[[ext:John Locke]]
[[eu:John Locke]]
[[fa:جان لاک]]
[[hif:John Locke]]
[[fo:John Locke]]
[[fr:John Locke]]
[[fy:John Locke]]
[[ga:John Locke]]
[[gl:John Locke]]
[[gan:約翰·洛]]
[[ko:존 로크]]
[[hy:Ջոն Լոկ]]
[[hi:जॉन लॉक]]
[[hr:John Locke]]
[[io:John Locke]]
[[id:John Locke]]
[[is:John Locke]]
[[it:John Locke]]
[[he:ג'ון לוק]]
[[jv:John Locke]]
[[ka:ჯონ ლოკი]]
[[kk:Джон Локк]]
[[sw:John Locke]]
[[ku:John Locke]]
[[ky:Локк, Жон]]
[[la:Ioannes Lockius]]
[[lv:Džons Loks]]
[[lb:John Locke]]
[[lt:John Locke]]
[[lmo:John Locke]]
[[hu:John Locke]]
[[mk:Џон Лок]]
[[ml:ജോണ്‍ ലോക്ക്]]
[[arz:جون لوك]]
[[ms:John Locke]]
[[mn:Жон Локк]]
[[nl:John Locke (filosoof)]]
[[ja:ジョン・ロック]]
[[no:John Locke]]
[[nn:John Locke]]
[[oc:John Locke]]
[[pnb:جان لاک]]
[[pms:John Locke]]
[[nds:John Locke]]
[[pl:John Locke]]
[[pt:John Locke]]
[[kaa:John Locke]]
[[ro:John Locke]]
[[rue:Джон Локк]]
[[ru:Локк, Джон]]
[[sco:John Locke]]
[[sq:John Locke]]
[[scn:John Locke]]
[[simple:John Locke]]
[[sk:John Locke]]
[[sl:John Locke]]
[[ckb:جۆن لۆک]]
[[sr:Џон Лок]]
[[sh:John Locke]]
[[fi:John Locke]]
[[sv:John Locke]]
[[tl:John Locke]]
[[ta:ஜான் லாக்]]
[[tt:Джон Локк]]
[[th:จอห์น ล็อก]]
[[tr:John Locke]]
[[uk:Джон Локк]]
[[ur:جان لوک]]
[[vi:John Locke]]
[[war:John Locke]]
[[yi:דזשאן לאק]]
[[yo:John Locke]]
[[diq:John Locke (filozof)]]
[[bat-smg:Džuons Luoks]]
[[zh:约翰·洛克]]</text>
      <sha1>q8cb180x4ji9rm6i3jpv5xgoqzu23a3</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
