<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Joseph de Maistre</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>213143</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522405904</id>
      <parentid>520198577</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-11T00:21:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Gregbard</username>
        <id>1193764</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Political and moral philosophy */[[Logical consequence]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="28235">{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2011}}{{Infobox philosopher
|region           = [[Western philosophy]]
|era              = [[18th-century philosophy]]
|color            = lightsteelblue
|image       = Jmaistre.jpg
|image_size       = 200px
|caption    = Portrait of de Maistre by [[Carl Christian Vogel von Vogelstein|von Vogelstein]], {{circa|1810}}
|name             = Joseph-Marie de Maistre
|birth_date       = {{Birth date|df=yes|1753|04|01}} &lt;br /&gt; [[Chambéry]], [[Kingdom of Sardinia]], [[Duchy of Savoy]]
|death_date       = {{Death date and age|df=yes|1821|02|26|1753|04|01}} &lt;br /&gt; [[Turin]], [[Kingdom of Sardinia]]
|school_tradition = Conservatism, [[counter-Enlightenment]], [[ultramontanism]], [[royalism]], [[mysticism]]
|main_interests   =
|notable_ideas    = [[Divine Providence|Providentialism]], [[sacrifice]], precursor of [[sociology]]
|influences       = [[Holy Bible]], [[Plato]], [[Aristotle]], [[Cicero]], [[Plutarch]], [[Origen]], [[Augustine of Hippo]], [[Thomas Aquinas]], [[Robert Bellarmine]], [[Nicolas Malebranche]], [[Jacques-Bénigne Bossuet]], [[Fénelon]], [[Giambattista Vico]], [[Edmund Burke]], [[Louis-Claude de Saint-Martin]], [[Louis de Bonald]]
|influenced       = [[Louis de Bonald]], [[Karl Ludwig von Haller]], [[Juan Donoso Cortés]], [[Antonio Rosmini-Serbati]], [[Charles Baudelaire]], [[Jules Barbey D'Aurevilly]], [[Honoré de Balzac]], [[Léon Bloy]], [[Charles Maurras]], [[Paul Claudel]], [[Julius Evola]], [[Carl Schmitt]], [[George Fitzhugh]], [[Orestes Brownson]], [[Francisco Franco]], [[Pat Buchanan]]
|signature        =
}}
'''Joseph-Marie, [[Count|comte]] de Maistre''' ({{IPA-fr|də mɛstʁ}}&lt;ref&gt;Maistre is traditionally pronounced {{IPA-fr|mɛstʁ|}} (sounding the S, rhymes with ''[[wikt:bourgmestre|bourgmestre]]''); that's how it is usually heard at university and in historical movies (e.g. in [[Sacha Guitry]]'s 1948 film {{link-interwiki|en=Le Diable boiteux (film)|en_text=''Le Diable boiteux''|lang=fr|lang_title=Le Diable boiteux (film)}}). The pronunciation {{IPA-fr|mɛtʁ|}} (rhymes with ''[[wikt:maître|maître]]'') is sometimes heard, under the influence of the modernized pronunciation adopted by some descendants (such as {{link-interwiki|en=Patrice de Maistre|lang=fr|lang_title=Patrice de Maistre}}).&lt;/ref&gt; 1 April 1753 – 26 February 1821) was a [[French language|French-speaking]] [[Savoy]]ard philosopher, writer, lawyer, and diplomat. He defended [[social hierarchy|hierarchical]] societies and a [[Monarchy|monarchical State]] in the period immediately following the [[French Revolution]]. Maistre was a subject of the [[Kingdom of Sardinia|King of Piedmont-Sardinia]], whom he served as member of the Savoy Senate (1787–1792), ambassador to Russia (1803–1817), and minister of state to the court in [[Turin]] (1817–1821).&lt;ref&gt;The issue of Maistre's national identity has long been contentious. In 1802, after the invasion of Savoy and [[Piedmont]] by the armies of the [[French First Republic]], Maistre had fled in [[Cagliari]], the ancient capital of Kingdom of Sardinia that resisted to the French invasion, wrote to the French ambassador in [[Naples]], objecting to having been classified as a French ''[[émigré]]'' and thus subject to confiscation of his properties and punishment should he attempt to return to Savoy. According to the biographical notice written by his son Rodolphe and included in the ''Complete Works'', on that occasion Maistre wrote that {{quote|He had not been born French, and did not desire to become French, and that, never having set foot in the lands conquered by France, he could not have become French.|''Œuvres complètes de Joseph de Maistre'', Lyon, 1884, vol. I, p. XVIII.}}  Sources such as the [http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/358824/Joseph-de-Maistre ''Encyclopaedia Britannica''] and the [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/09554a.htm ''Catholic Encyclopedia''] identify Maistre as French, by culture if not by law. In 1860 Albert Blanc, professor of law at the [[University of Turin]], in his preface to a collection of Maistre's diplomatic correspondence wrote that: {{quote|... this philosopher [Maistre] was a politician; this Catholic was an Italian; he foretold the destiny of the [[House of Savoy]], he supported the end of the [[Kingdom of Lombardy–Venetia|Austrian rule]] [of northern Italy], he has been, during this century, one of the first defenders of [Italian] independence.|''Correspondance diplomatique de Joseph de Maistre'', Paris, 1860, vol. I, pp. III-IV.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Maistre, a key figure of the [[Counter-Enlightenment]], saw monarchy both as a [[Divine right of kings|divinely sanctioned institution]] and as the only stable form of government. He called for the restoration of the [[House of Bourbon]] to the throne of France and argued that the Pope should have ultimate authority in temporal matters.  Maistre also claimed that it was the [[rationalism|rationalist]] rejection of [[Christianity]] which was directly responsible for the disorder and bloodshed which followed the French Revolution of 1789.

== Biography ==
Maistre was born in 1753 at [[Chambéry]], in the [[Duchy of Savoy]], which at that time was part of the [[Kingdom of Sardinia|Kingdom of Piedmont-Sardinia]], ruled by the [[House of Savoy]].&lt;ref name=berlin&gt;{{cite web|url=http://berlin.wolf.ox.ac.uk/lists/nachlass/maistre.pdf |title=The Second Onslaught: Joseph de Maistre and Open Obscurantism |work=Two Enemies of the Enlightenment |publisher=[[Wolfson College, Oxford]] |date=25–8 October 1965 |accessdate=11 December 2008 |format=[[PDF]] |last=Berlin |first=Isaiah}}&lt;/ref&gt; His family was of French origin. His grandfather André Maistre, who came from [[Provence]], had been a draper and councilman in [[Nice]] (then under the rule of the House of Savoy), and his father François-Xavier, who moved to Chambéry in 1740, became a magistrate and senator, eventually receiving the title of [[count]] from the King of Piedmont-Sardinia. His mother's family, whose surname was Desmotz, were from [[Rumilly, Haute-Savoie|Rumilly]].&lt;ref name=&quot;triomphe&quot;&gt;{{cite book|first=Robert |last=Triomphe |title=Joseph de Maistre | location=Genève | publisher=Droz | year=1968 |pages=39–41}}  Preview available [http://books.google.com/books?id=CkrcFHJB5cQC&amp;pg here]&lt;/ref&gt;  Joseph's younger brother, [[Xavier de Maistre|Xavier]], who became an army officer, was a popular writer of fiction.&lt;ref name=cath&gt;{{CathEncy| wstitle = Joseph-Marie, Comte de Maistre}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=xav&gt;{{CathEncy| wstitle = Xavier de Maistre}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Joseph de Maistre by Villain.jpg|200px|thumb|left|Lithograph of Maistre, from a painting by [[Pierre Bouillon]]. He is shown wearing the insignia of the [[Order of Saints Maurice and Lazarus]].]]

Joseph was probably educated by the [[Society of Jesus|Jesuits]].&lt;ref name=cath/&gt; After the Revolution, he became an ardent defender of their Order, increasingly associating the spirit of the Revolution with the Jesuits' traditional enemies, the [[Jansenism|Jansenists]]. After completing his training in the law at the [[University of Turin]] in 1774, he followed in his father's footsteps by becoming a Senator in 1787.

A member of the progressive [[Scottish Rite]] [[Freemasonry|Masonic]] lodge at Chambéry from 1774 to 1790, Maistre originally favoured political reform in France, supporting the efforts of the magistrates in the [[Parlement]]s to force King [[Louis XVI of France|Louis XVI]] to convene the [[Estates General (France)|Estates General]]. As a landowner in France, Maistre was eligible to join that body, and there is some evidence that he contemplated that possibility.&lt;ref name=&quot;lebrun&quot;&gt;{{cite web|first=Richard |last=Lebrun |url=http://www.maistre.polthought.cam.ac.uk/maistrebio.html |title=A Brief Biography of Joseph de Maistre|publisher=[[University of Manitoba]] |accessdate=1 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was alarmed, however, by the decision of the States-General to combine clergy, [[Aristocracy (government)|aristocracy]], and [[commoner]]s into a single legislative body, which became the [[National Constituent Assembly]].  After the passing of the [[August Decrees]] on 4 August 1789 he decisively turned against the course of political events in France.

Maistre fled Chambéry when it was taken by a French revolutionary army in 1792, but unable to find a position in the royal court in Turin, he returned the following year. Deciding that he could not support the French-controlled regime, he departed again, this time for [[Lausanne]], in Switzerland. There he discussed politics and theology at the salon of [[Anne Louise Germaine de Staël|Madame de Staël]], and began his career as a counter-revolutionary writer, with works such as ''Lettres d'un royaliste savoisien'' (&quot;Letters from a Savoyard Royalist&quot;, 1793), ''Discours à Mme. la marquise Costa de Beauregard, sur la vie et la mort de son fils'' (&quot;Discourse to the Marchioness Costa de Beauregard, on the Life and Death of her Son&quot;, 1794) and ''Cinq paradoxes à la Marquise de Nav...'' (&quot;Five Paradoxes for the Marchioness of Nav...&quot;, 1795).&lt;ref name=berlin/&gt;

From Lausanne, Maistre emigrated to [[Venice]], and then [[Cagliari]], where the King of Piedmont-Sardinia was exiled after French armies took Turin in 1798. Maistre's relations with the court at Cagliari were not always easy&lt;ref name=berlin/&gt; and in 1803 he was sent to [[Saint Petersburg]] in Russia, as ambassador to [[Tsar]] [[Alexander I of Russia|Alexander I]]. His diplomatic responsibilities were few, and he became a well-loved fixture in aristocratic circles, converting some of his friends to Roman Catholicism, and writing his most influential works on political philosophy.

Maistre's observations on Russian life, contained in his diplomatic memoirs and in his personal correspondence, were among [[Leo Tolstoy|Tolstoy]]'s sources for his novel ''[[War and Peace]]''.&lt;ref name=berlin/&gt;  After the defeat of [[Napoleon]] and the restoration of the House of Savoy's dominion over [[Piedmont]] (under the terms of the [[Congress of Vienna]]), Maistre returned in 1817 to Turin, and served there as [[magistrate]] and minister of state until his death. He died on 26 February 1821 is buried in the Jesuit Church of the Holy Martyrs (''Chiesa dei Santi Martiri'').

== Political and moral philosophy ==
{{conservatism}}

In ''Considérations sur la France'' (&quot;Considerations on France,&quot; 1796), Maistre claimed that France has a divine mission as the principal instrument of good and evil on Earth. He interpreted the Revolution of 1789 as a [[Divine Providence|Providential]] event: the monarchy, the [[Aristocracy (government)|aristocracy]], and the ''[[Ancien Régime]]'' in general, instead of directing the influence of French civilization to the benefit of mankind, had promoted the [[atheism|atheistic]] doctrines of the [[Age of Enlightenment|eighteenth-century philosophers]]. He claimed that the crimes of the [[Reign of Terror]] were the [[logical consequence]] of [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightened]] thought, as well as its divinely-decreed punishment.

In his short book ''Essai sur le principe générateur des constitutions politiques et des autres institutions humaines'' (&quot;Essay on the Generative Principle of Political Constitutions and other Human Institutions,&quot; 1809), Maistre argued that constitutions are not the product of human reason, but come from God, who slowly brings them to maturity. After the appearance in 1816 of his French translation of [[Plutarch]]'s treatise ''On the Delay of Divine Justice in the Punishment of the Guilty'', in 1819 Maistre published ''Du Pape'' (&quot;[[On the Pope]]&quot;), the most complete exposition of his authoritarian conception of politics.

According to Maistre, any attempt to justify government on rational grounds will only lead to unresolvable arguments about the legitimacy and expediency of any existing government, and that this, in turn, will lead to violence and chaos.  Maistre therefore argued that the legitimacy of government must be based on compelling but non-rational grounds, which its subjects must not be allowed to question. Maistre went on to argue that authority in politics should therefore derive from religion, and that in Europe this religious authority must ultimately lie with the Pope.

What was novel in Maistre's writings was not his enthusiastic defense of monarchical and religious authority ''per se'', but rather his arguments concerning the practical need for ultimate authority to lie with an individual capable of decisive action, as well as his analysis of the social foundations of that authority's legitimacy.  In his own words, which he addressed to a group of aristocratic French émigrés, &quot;you ought to know how to be royalists.  Before, this was an instinct, but today it is a science.  You must love the sovereign as you love order, with all the forces of intelligence.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Sénart&quot;&gt;Quoted by Philippe Sénart in [http://books.google.com/books?id=kiDaH4ll41oC&amp;pg=PA646 &quot;Maistre et Tocqueville&quot;], ''Joseph de Maistre.  Les Dossiers H'', (Lausanne: Editions L'Age d'Homme, 2005), p. 646.  ISBN 2825118710&lt;/ref&gt;  Maistre's analysis of the problem of authority and its legitimacy foreshadows some of the concerns of early sociologists such as [[Auguste Comte|Comte]] and [[Claude Henri de Rouvroy, comte de Saint-Simon|Saint-Simon]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Levy-Bruhl&quot;&gt;[[Lucien Lévy-Bruhl]], ''The Philosophy of Auguste Comte'', (New York: Putnam and Sons, 1903), pp. 297-8.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Pickering&quot;&gt;Mary Pickering, ''Auguste Comte: An Intellectual Biography'', vol. 1, (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1993), pp. 261-8.  ISBN 052143405X&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to his voluminous correspondence, Maistre left two books that were published posthumously.  ''Soirées de St. Pétersbourg'' (&quot;The Saint Petersburg Dialogues&quot;, 1821) is a [[theodicy]] in the form of a [[Plato#Plato's Dialogues|Platonic dialogue]], in which Maistre argues that evil exists because of its place in the divine plan, according to which the blood sacrifice of innocents returns men to God, via the expiation of the sins of the guilty; Maistre saw this is a law of human history, as indubitable as it is mysterious.  ''Examen de la philosophie de Bacon'', (&quot;An Examination of the Philosophy of Bacon,&quot; 1836), is a critique of the thought of [[Francis Bacon]], whom Maistre considers to be the fountainhead of the destructive [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightened]] thought.

== Repute and influence ==
Maistre, together with the [[Anglo-Irish]] statesman and philosopher [[Edmund Burke]], is commonly regarded as one of the founders of European conservatism, but since the 19th century, Maistre's authoritarian, &quot;throne-and-altar&quot; conception of conservatism has declined in influence in comparison with the more liberal conservatism of Burke.  Maistre's skills as a writer and polemicist however ensure that he continues to be read. The ''Catholic Encyclopedia'' of 1910 describes his writing style as &quot;strong, lively, picturesque,&quot; and that his &quot;animation and good humour temper his dogmatic tone. He possesses a wonderful facility in exposition, precision of doctrine, breadth of learning, and [[dialectic]]al power.&quot;&lt;ref name=cath/&gt; [[Alphonse de Lamartine]], though a political opponent, admired the splendour of his prose:

{{quote|That brief, nervous, lucid style, stripped of phrases, robust of limb, did not at all recall the softness of the eighteenth century, nor the declamations of the latest French books: it was born and steeped in the breath of the Alps; it was virgin, it was young, it was harsh and savage; it had no human respect, it felt its solitude; it improvised depth and form all at once… That man was new among the ''enfants du siècle'' [children of the century].|Alphonse de Lamartine|''Souvenirs et portraits''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Alphonse |last=de Lamartine|title=Souvenirs et portraits |edition=3rd |volume=2 |location=Paris |year=1874 |chapter=I |pages=188–9}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

[[File:Joseph de Maistre by Vallotton.jpg|thumb||Portrait by Swiss painter [[Félix Vallotton]], from ''La Revue blanche'', 1er semestre, 1895.]]

[[Émile Faguet]] described Maistre as &quot;a fierce absolutist, a furious theocrat, an intransigent legitimist, apostle of a monstrous trinity composed of pope, king and hangman, always and everywhere the champion of the hardest, narrowest and most inflexible dogmatism, a dark figure out of the Middle Ages, part learned doctor, part inquisitor, part executioner.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Émile Faguet, ''Politiques et moralistes du dix-neuvieme siecle'', 1st series, Paris 1899. Cited in: {{cite book | last = de Maistre | first = Joseph | title = Considerations on France | publisher=Cambridge University Press | location = Cambridge | year = 1994 | isbn = 0-521-46628-8 |page=xi |chapter=Introduction |author=Isaiah Berlin}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Isaiah Berlin]] in his ''Freedom and Its Betrayal'' notes that many view his writings as &quot;the last despairing effort of feudalism...to resist the march of progress.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Isaiah Berlin, ''Freedom and its Betrayal: Six Enemies of Human Liberty'', 2002, p.132.&lt;/ref&gt; but he claims that Maistre imposes &quot;an official [[Legitimists|legitimist]] Catholic framework upon what is really a deeply violent, deeply revolutionary, ultimately Fascist inner passion&quot; which rejects what it sees as the shallow optimism of the Enlightenment.&lt;ref&gt;Isaiah Berlin, ''Freedom and its Betrayal: Six Enemies of Human Liberty'', 2002, p.154&lt;/ref&gt; His fundamental doctrine according to Berlin is that nature is red in tooth and claw&lt;ref&gt;Isaiah Berlin, ''Freedom and its Betrayal: Six Enemies of Human Liberty'', 2002, p.137&lt;/ref&gt; and what really fascinates him is power.&lt;ref&gt;Isaiah Berlin, ''Freedom and its Betrayal: Six Enemies of Human Liberty'', 2002, p.151&lt;/ref&gt;

Amongst those who admired him was the poet [[Charles Baudelaire]], who described himself a disciple of the Savoyard counter-revolutionary, claiming that he had taught him &quot;how to think.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Lombard|1976|p=123}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Maistre also exerted a powerful influence on the Spanish political thinker [[Juan Donoso Cortés]] and, later, on the French monarchist [[Charles Maurras]] and his counter-revolutionary political movement ''[[Action Française]]''.

According to Carolina Armenteros, Maistre's writings influenced not only conservative political thinkers, but also the [[Utopian socialism|Utopian socialists]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Armenteros&quot;&gt;Carolina Armenteros, ''The French Idea of History: Joseph de Maistre and his Heirs, 1794-1854'' (Ithaca, NY and London: Cornell University Press, 2011). ISBN 0-8014-4943-X&lt;/ref&gt;  Early sociologists such as [[Claude Henri de Rouvroy, comte de Saint-Simon|Saint-Simon]] and [[Auguste Comte|Comte]] explicitly acknowledged the influence of Maistre on their own thinking about the sources of social cohesion and political authority.&lt;ref name=&quot;Levy-Bruhl&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Pickering&quot; /&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Latin Conservatism]]

== Notes ==

{{reflist|2}}

== Works ==
* ''Nobilis Ioseph Maistre Camberiensis ad i.u. lauream anno 1772. die 29. Aprilis hora 5. pomeridiana'' (Turin, 1772) – Joseph de Maistre's decree thesis, kept in the National Library of the University of Turin ([http://www.sbn.it/opacsbn/opaclib?db=iccu&amp;select_db=iccu&amp;nentries=1&amp;from=5&amp;searchForm=opac/iccu/error.jsp&amp;resultForward=opac/iccu/full.jsp&amp;do=search_show_cmd&amp;rpnlabel=+Autore+%3D+Joseph+de+Maistre+%28parole+in+AND%29++Anno+di+pubblicazione%3E%3D1700++AND+Anno+di+pubblicazione%3C%3D1810+&amp;rpnquery=%40attrset+bib-1+%40and+%40and++%40attr+1%3D31+%40attr+4%3D4++%40attr++2%3D4+%221700%22++%40attr+1%3D1003+%40attr+4%3D2+%22Joseph+de+Maistre%22++%40attr+1%3D31+%40attr+4%3D4++%40attr++2%3D2+%221810%22&amp;totalResult=9&amp;fname=none&amp;brief=brief link]).
* ''Éloge de Victor-Amédée III'' (Chambéry, 1775)
* ''Lettres d'un royaliste savoisien à ses compatriotes'' (1793)
* ''Étude sur la souveraineté'' (1794)
* ''De l'État de nature, ou Examen d'un écrit de Jean-Jacques Rousseau'' (1795)
* ''Considérations sur la France'' (London [Basel], 1796)
* ''Intorno allo stato del Piemonte rispetto alla carta moneta'' (Turn, Aosta, Venice, 1797–1799)
* ''Essai sur le principe générateur des constitutions politiques'' (St Petersborg, 1809)
* ''Du Pape'' (Lyon, 1819)
* ''De l'Église gallicane'', édit. Rodolphe de Maistre (Lyon, 1821)
* ''Les Soirées de Saint-Pétersbourg ou Entretiens sur le gouvernement temporel de la Providence'', édit. Rodolphe de Maistre  (Paris, 1821)
* ''Lettres à un gentilhomme russe sur l'Inquisition espagnole'', édit. Rodolphe de Maistre (Paris, 1822)
* ''Examen de la philosophie de Bacon'', édit. Rodolphe de Maistre  (Paris, 1836)
* ''Lettres et opuscules inédits du comte Joseph de Maistre'', édit. Rodolphe de Maistre  (Paris, 1853)
* ''Mémoires politiques et correspondance diplomatique'', édit. Albert Blanc (Paris, 1858)

=== Work in English translation ===
* ''Memoir on the Union of Savoy and Switzerland'' (1795).
* ''Essay on the Generative Principle of Political Constitutions'' (1809, English translation 1847).
* ''The Pope: Considered in His Relations with the Church, Temporal Sovereignties, Separated Churches and the Cause of Civilization'' (1817, English translation 1850).
* ''Letters to a Russian Gentleman on the Spanish Inquisition'' (1822, English translation 1851)
* Blum, Christopher Olaf (editor and translator), 2004. ''Critics of the Enlightenment''. [[Wilmington, Delaware|Wilmington]], Delaware : ISI Books.
** 1798, &quot;Reflections on Protestantism in its Relations to Sovereignty&quot;. 133-56.
** 1819, &quot;On the Pope&quot;. 157-96.
* Lively, Jack, 1965. ''The Works of Joseph de Maistre''. Macmillan.

== References ==
* Armenteros, Carolina, ''The French Idea of History: Joseph de Maistre and his Heirs, 1794-1854'' (Ithaca, NY and London: Cornell University Press, 2011).
* Armenteros, Carolina and Richard Lebrun, ''Joseph de Maistre and his European Readers: From Friedrich von Gentz to Isaiah Berlin'' (Leiden and Boston: Brill, 2011).
* Armenteros, Carolina and Richard Lebrun, ''Joseph de Maistre and the Legacy of Enlightenment'', ''SVEC'' (Oxford: The Voltaire Foundation, 2011).
* Armenteros, Carolina and Richard Lebrun, [http://research-repository.st-andrews.ac.uk/bitstream/10023/847/1/The%20New%20Enfant%20du%20Siecle%20%28ed%20Armenteros%20and%20Lebrun%29.pdf''The New'' enfant du siècle: ''Joseph de Maistre as a Writer''], in ''St Andrews Studies in French History and Culture'' 1 (2010).
* Armenteros, Carolina, &quot;From Human Nature to Normal Humanity: Joseph de Maistre, Rousseau, and the Origins of Moral Statistics,&quot; ''Journal of the History of Ideas'', 68, 1 (2007): 107–30.
* Armenteros, Carolina, &quot;Parabolas and the Fate of Nations: Early Conservative Historicism in Joseph de Maistre's ''De la souveraineté du peuple'',&quot; ''History of Political Thought'', 28, 2 (2007): 230–52.
* Barthelet, Philippe, ''Joseph de Maistre: Les Dossiers H'' (Geneva: L'Age d'homme, 2005).
* Bradley, Owen, ''A Modern Maistre: The Social and Political Thought of Joseph de Maistre|'' (Lincoln and London: University of Nebraska Press, 1999).
* Camcastle, Cara, ''The more moderate side of Joseph de Maistre'', Ottawa, McGill-Queen's University Press, 2005.
* [[Benedetto Croce|Croce, Benedetto]], ''Il duca di Serra-Capriola e Giuseppe de Maistre'' (in ''Archivio storico per le province napoletane'', XLVII, pp.&amp;nbsp;313–335), 1922.
* {{Cite book | last = Buchanan | first = Patrick | title = State of Emergency | publisher=St. Martin's Griffin | location = New York | year = 2007 | isbn = 0-312-37436-4 }}
* {{Cite book|last=Ghervas |first=Stella |year=2008 |title=Réinventer la tradition: Alexandre Stourdza et l'Europe de la Sainte-Alliance |location=Paris |publisher=Honoré Champion |isbn=2-7453-1669-9}}
* Glaudes, Pierre, ''Joseph de Maistre et les figures de l'histoire: trois essais sur un précurseur du romantisme français'', in ''Cahiers romantiques'' (1997).
* {{Cite book|last=Lebrun |first=Richard A. |title=Joseph de Maistre: An Intellectual Militant |publisher=McGill-Queen's University Press| location = Montreal | year = 1988 | isbn = 0-7735-0645-4 }}
* {{Cite book | last = Lombard | first = Charles | title = Joseph de Maistre | publisher=Twayne | location = Boston | year = 1976 | isbn = 0-8057-6247-7 }}
* [[Domenico Fisichella|Fisichella, Domenico]], ''Giusnaturalismo e teoria della sovranità in Joseph de Maistre''. Messina-Firenze, 1963. (now in Id. ''Politica e mutamento sociale''. Costantino Marco Editore, Lungro di Cosenza, 2002, pp.&amp;nbsp;191–243. ISBN 88-85350-97-6.)
* [[Domenico Fisichella|Fisichella, Domenico]], ''Il pensiero politico di Joseph de Maistre''. Laterza, Roma-Bari, 1993. ISBN 88-420-4157-2.
* [[Domenico Fisichella|Fisichella, Domenico]], ''Joseph de Maistre, pensatore europeo''. Laterza, Roma-Bari, 2005. ISBN 88-420-7598-1.
* Gianturco, Elio, ''Joseph de Maistre and Giambattista Vico (Italian roots of the Maistre's political culture)'', New York, Columbia University, 1937.
* Gianturco, Elio, ''Juridical culture and politico-historical judgement in Joseph de Maistre'' (in ''Roman revue'' n. 27), 1936.
* Lebrun, Richard, ''Joseph de Maistre's life, thought and influence: selected studies'', Ottawa, McGill-Queen's University Press, 2001.
* Legittimo, Gianfranco, ''Sociologi cattolici italiani: De Maistre, Taparelli, Toniolo'', Il Quadrato, Roma, 1963.
* {{Catholic|wstitle=Joseph-Marie, Comte de Maistre}}
* Mandoul, Jean, ''Un homme d'État italien: Joseph de Maistre et la politique de la Maison de Savoie'', Alcan, Paris, 1900.
* Monteton, Charles Philippe Dijon de, ''Die Entzauberung des Gesellschaftsvertrags. Ein Vergleich der Anti-Sozial-Kontrakts-Theorien von Carl Ludwig von Haller und Joseph Graf de Maistre im Kontext der politischen Ideengeschichte'', Frankfurt am Main ''et al.'', 2007, 164 S., 2 Abb. ISBN 978-3-631-55538-5.
* Pranchère, Jean-Yves, ''L'Autorité contre les Lumières: la philosophie de Joseph de Maistre'' (Geneva: Droz, 2005).
* Pranchère, Jean-Yves, ''Qu'est-ce que la royauté? Joseph de Maistre'' (Paris: Vrin, 1992).
* Vermale, François, ''Notes sur Joseph de Maistre inconnu'' (Chambéry: Perrin, M. Dardel successeur, 1921).

== External links ==
{{Wikiquote}}
* [http://www.maistre.polthought.cam.ac.uk The Joseph de Maistre Homepage] at the University of Cambridge
* [http://maistre.ath.cx:8000 Works of Joseph de Maistre in English Translation]

{{Persondata
| NAME              = Maistre, Joseph De
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1 April 1753
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     = 26 February 1821
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Maistre, Joseph De}}
[[Category:1753 births]]
[[Category:1821 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Chambéry]]
[[Category:People from Savoy]]
[[Category:People from the Kingdom of Sardinia]]
[[Category:19th-century French writers]]
[[Category:Italian writers in French]]
[[Category:French counter-revolutionaries]]
[[Category:Savoyard counter-revolutionaries]]
[[Category:Italian philosophers]]
[[Category:Political theorists]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic writers]]
[[Category:French monarchists]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic philosophers]]
[[Category:Anti-Protestantism]]
[[Category:Knights of the Order of Saints Maurice and Lazarus]]
[[Category:Conservatism]]
[[Category:French Ultra-royalists]]
[[Category:Freemasons]]
[[Category:Counter-Enlightenment]]
[[Category:Ambassadors to Russia]]
[[Category:19th-century philosophers]]
[[Category:18th-century philosophers]]

[[ca:Joseph de Maistre]]
[[cs:Joseph de Maistre]]
[[da:Joseph de Maistre]]
[[de:Joseph Marie de Maistre]]
[[et:Joseph de Maistre]]
[[es:Joseph de Maistre]]
[[eo:Joseph de Maistre]]
[[fa:ژوزف دو مستر]]
[[fr:Joseph de Maistre]]
[[hy:Ժոզեֆ դը Մեսթր]]
[[it:Joseph de Maistre]]
[[la:Iosephus Maria de Maistre]]
[[mzn:ژوزف دو مستر]]
[[nl:Joseph de Maistre]]
[[ja:ジョゼフ・ド・メーストル]]
[[no:Joseph de Maistre]]
[[nn:Joseph de Maistre]]
[[pl:Joseph de Maistre]]
[[pt:Joseph de Maistre]]
[[ru:Де Местр, Жозеф]]
[[sk:Joseph Maria de Maistre]]
[[fi:Joseph de Maistre]]
[[sv:Joseph de Maistre]]
[[uk:Жозеф де Местр]]</text>
      <sha1>dxubh5q7tkt16e9mrtf2l65odw6y36v</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
