<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Jurisdiction</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>16392</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522169039</id>
      <parentid>520781333</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T12:44:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Kalkühl</username>
        <id>7193171</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20473">{{Refimprove|date=September 2008}}
:''For an article on the use of jurisdiction to mean a state or country, see [[Jurisdiction (area)]]''.
[[File:&quot;Authority of Law&quot; by James Earle Fraser.jpg|thumb|200px|right|Statue titled &quot;Authority of Law&quot; by [[James Earle Fraser (sculptor)|James Earle Fraser]].  A single tablet is held by the figure, which is located to the right of the front steps of the [[United States Supreme Court Building]].]]
'''Jurisdiction''' (from the [[Latin]] ''ius, [[Wikt:iuris|iuris]]'' meaning &quot;law&quot; and ''[[Wikt:dicere|dicere]]'' meaning &quot;to speak&quot;) is the practical [[authority]] granted to a formally [[constituted body|constituted]] [[legal]] body or to a [[political leader]] to deal with and make pronouncements on legal matters and, by implication, to administer [[justice]] within a defined area of responsibility. The term is also used to denote the geographical area or subject-matter to which such authority applies.

Jurisdiction draws its substance from [[public international law]], [[conflict of laws]], [[constitutional law]] and the powers of the [[Executive (government)|executive]] and [[Legislature|legislative branches]] of [[government]] to allocate resources to best serve the needs of its native [[society]].

==International Dimension==
International laws and treaties provide agreements which [[nations]] agree to be bound to.

===Political issue===
[[supranationalism|Supranational]] organizations provide mechanisms whereby disputes between states may be resolved through [[arbitration]] or [[mediation]]. When a [[country]] is recognized as ''[[de jure]]'', it is an acknowledgment by the other ''de jure'' nations that the country has [[sovereignty]] and the right to exist. 

However, it is often at the discretion of each state whether to co-operate or participate. If a state does agree to participate in activities of the supranational bodies and accept decisions, the state is giving up its sovereign authority and thereby allocating power to these bodies. 

Insofar as these bodies or nominated individuals may resolve disputes in a judicial or quasi-judicial fashion, or promote [[treaty]] obligations in the nature of laws, the power ceded to these bodies cumulatively represents its own jurisdiction. But no matter how powerful each body may appear to be, the extent to which any of the [[Legal judgment|judgment]]s may be enforced, or proposed treaties and conventions may become or remain effective within the territorial boundaries of each nation is a political matter under the sovereign control of the relevant representative government(s) which, in a democratic context, will have electorates to satisfy.

===International and municipal jurisdiction===
The fact that international organizations, courts and tribunals have been created raises the difficult question of how to co-ordinate their activities with those of national courts. If the two sets of bodies do not have ''concurrent'' jurisdiction but, as in the case of the [[International Criminal Court]] (ICC), the relationship is expressly based on the principle of ''complementarity'', i.e. the international court is subsidiary or complementary to national courts, the difficulty is avoided. But if the jurisdiction claimed is concurrent, or as in the case of [[International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia]] (ICTY), the international tribunal is to prevail over national courts, the problems are more difficult to resolve politically.

The idea of [[universal jurisdiction]] is fundamental to the operation of [[global organization]]s such as the [[United Nations]] and the [[International Court of Justice]] (ICJ), which jointly assert the benefit of maintaining legal entities with jurisdiction over a wide range of matters of significance to states (the ICJ should not be confused with the ICC and this version of &quot;universal jurisdiction&quot; is not the same as that enacted in the [[War Crimes Law (Belgium)]] which is an assertion of extraterritorial jurisdiction that will fail to gain implementation in any other state under the standard provisions of [[public policy (law)|public policy]]). Under Article 34 Statute of the ICJ&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.icj-cij.org/icjwww/ibasicdocuments/Basetext/istatute.htm ICJ-CIJ.org]&lt;/ref&gt; only states may be parties in cases before the Court and, under Article 36, the jurisdiction comprises all cases which the parties refer to it and all matters specially provided for in the Charter of the United Nations or in treaties and conventions in force. But, to invoke the jurisdiction in any given case, all the parties have to accept the prospective judgment as binding. This reduces the risk of wasting the Court's time.

Despite the safeguards built into the constitutions of most of these organizations, courts and tribunals, the concept of universal jurisdiction is controversial among those states which prefer unilateral to multilateral solutions through the use of executive or military authority, sometimes described as [[realpolitik]]-based diplomacy.

Within other international contexts, there are [[International organization|intergovernmental organizations]] such as the [[World Trade Organization]] (WTO) that have socially and economically significant dispute resolution functions but, again, even though their jurisdiction may be invoked to hear the cases, the power to enforce their decisions is at the will of the states affected, save that the WTO is permitted to allow retaliatory action by successful states against those states found to be in breach of [[international trade law]]. At a regional level, groups of states can create political and legal bodies with sometimes complicated patchworks of overlapping provisions detailing the jurisdictional relationships between the member states and providing for some degree of [[harmonization]] between their national legislative and judicial functions, for example, the [[European Union]] and [[African Union]] both have the potential to become federated states although the political barriers to such unification in the face of entrenched [[nationalism]] will be very difficult to overcome. Each such group may form transnational institutions with declared legislative or judicial powers. For example, in Europe, the [[European Court of Justice]] has been given jurisdiction as the ultimate appellate court to the member states on issues of European law. This jurisdiction is entrenched and its authority could only be denied by a member state if that member State asserts its sovereignty and withdraws from the union.

==International and municipal law==
The standard treaties and conventions leave the issue of implementation to each state, i.e. there is no general rule in international law that treaties have [[direct effect]] in municipal law, but some states, by virtue of their membership of supranational bodies, allow the direct incorporation of rights or enact [[legislation]] to honor their international commitments. Hence, [[citizen]]s in those states can invoke the jurisdiction of local courts to enforce rights granted under international law wherever there is incorporation. If there is no direct effect or legislation, there are two theories to justify the courts incorporating international into municipal law:
*Monism
:This theory characterizes international and municipal law as a single legal system with municipal law subordinate to international law. Hence, in the [[Netherlands]], all treaties and the orders of international organizations are effective without any action being required to convert international into municipal law. This has an interesting consequence because treaties that limit or extend the powers of the Dutch government are automatically considered a part of their constitutional law, for example, the [[European Convention for the Protection of Human Rights and Fundamental Freedoms]] and the [[International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights]]. In states adopting this theory, the local courts automatically accept jurisdiction to adjudicate on [[lawsuit]]s relying on international law principles.
*Dualism
:This theory regards international and municipal law as separate systems so that the municipal courts can only apply international law either when it has been incorporated into municipal law or when the courts incorporate international law on their own motion. In the [[United Kingdom]], for example, a treaty is not effective until it has been incorporated at which time it becomes enforceable in the courts by any private citizen, where appropriate, even against the UK Government. Otherwise the courts have a discretion to apply international law where it does not conflict with [[statute]] or the [[common law]]. The constitutional principle of [[parliamentary supremacy]] permits the legislature to enact any law inconsistent with any international treaty obligations even though the government is a signatory to those treaties.

In the [[United States]], the [[Supremacy Clause]] of the [[United States Constitution]] makes all treaties that have been ratified under the authority of the United States and customary international law, …the &quot;Supreme Law of the Land&quot; (U.S. Const.art. VI Cl. 2) and, as such, the law of the land is binding on the federal government as well as on state and local governments. According to the [[Supreme Court of the United States]], the treaty power authorizes [[United States Congress|Congress]] to legislate under the [[Necessary and Proper Clause]] in areas beyond those specifically conferred on Congress (''[[Missouri v. Holland]]'', 252 U.S. 416 (1920)).

==The jurisdiction between and within states==
This concerns the relationships both between courts in different [[jurisdiction (area)|jurisdiction]]s, and between courts within the same jurisdiction.  The usual legal doctrine under which questions of jurisdiction are decided is termed ''[[forum non conveniens]]''.

===International===
To deal with the issue of [[forum shopping]], states are urged to adopt more positive rules on conflict of laws. The [[Hague Conference on Private International Law|Hague Conference]] and other international bodies have made recommendations on jurisdictional matters, but [[litigant]]s with the encouragement of [[lawyer]]s on a [[contingent fee]] continue to shop for forums.

===Supranational===
At a supranational level, countries have adopted a range of treaty and convention obligations to relate the right of individual litigants to invoke the jurisdiction of state courts and to enforce the judgments obtained. For example, the [[member state]]s of the [[European Economic Community|EEC]] signed the [[Brussels Regime|Brussels Convention]] in 1968 and, subject to amendments as new states joined, it represents the default law for all twenty-seven Member States of what is now termed the [[European Union]] on the relationships between the courts in the different countries. In addition, the [[Brussels Regime|Lugano Convention]] (1988) binds the European Union and the [[European Free Trade Association]]. 

In effect from 1 March, 2002, all the member states of the EU except Denmark accepted [[Brussels Regime|Council Regulation (EC) 44/2001]], which makes major changes to the Brussels Convention and is [[direct effect|directly effective]] in the member states. Council Regulation (EC) 44/2001 now also applies as between the rest of the EU Member States and Denmark due to an agreement reached between the European Community and Denmark.&lt;ref&gt;http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2005:299:0062:0070:EN:PDF&lt;/ref&gt;  In some legal areas, at least, the CACA [[enforcement of foreign judgments]] is now more straightforward. At a state level, the traditional rules still determine jurisdiction over persons who are not [[domicile (law)|domiciled]] or habitually resident in the European Union or the Lugano area.

===National===
Many nations are subdivided into states and [[province]]s (i.e. a [[state (subnational)|subnational &quot;state&quot;]]). [[Federation]] (as can be found in [[States and territories of Australia|Australia]], [[States of Brazil]], [[States and territories of India|India]], [[States of Mexico|Mexico]] and the [[U.S. State|United States]]) and these subunits will exercise ''jurisdiction'' through the court systems as defined by the executives and legislatures. 

When the jurisdictions of governmental entities overlap, one another&amp;mdash;for example, between a state and the federation to which it belongs&amp;mdash;their jurisdiction is shared or concurrent jurisdiction. 

Otherwise, one government entity will have exclusive jurisdiction over the shared area. When jurisdiction is concurrent, one governmental entity may have supreme jurisdiction over the other entity if their laws conflict. If the executive or legislative powers within the jurisdiction are not restricted or restricted only by a number of limited restrictions, these government branches have plenary power such as a national [[police power|policing power]]. 
Otherwise, an [[enabling act]] grants only limited or enumerated powers. 

The problem of forum shopping also applies as between federal and state courts.

==United States==
{{US fed civ pro}}
{{Main|Federal jurisdiction (United States)}}
The primary distinctions between areas of jurisdiction are [[Codification (law)|codified]] at a national level. As a [[common law]] system, jurisdiction is conceptually divided between jurisdiction over the ''[[subject-matter jurisdiction|subject matter]]'' of a case and jurisdiction over the ''person'' of the [[litigant]]s.  (See [[personal jurisdiction]].)  Sometimes a court may exercise jurisdiction over property located within the perimeter of its powers without regard to personal jurisdiction over the litigants; this is called ''[[jurisdiction in rem]]''.

A court whose subject-matter jurisdiction is limited to certain types of controversies (for example, suits in [[admiralty law|admiralty]] or suits where the monetary amount sought is less than a specified sum) is sometimes referred to as a ''court of special jurisdiction'' or ''court of limited jurisdiction''.

A court whose subject-matter is not limited to certain types of controversy is referred to as a ''court of general jurisdiction''. In the [[U.S. state]]s, each state has courts of general jurisdiction; most states also have some courts of limited jurisdiction.  Federal courts (those operated by the [[Federal government of the United States|federal government]]) are courts of limited jurisdiction.  [[Federal jurisdiction (United States)|Federal jurisdiction]] is divided into [[federal question jurisdiction]] and [[diversity jurisdiction]].  The [[United States district court]]s may hear only cases arising under federal law and treaties, cases involving ambassadors, admiralty cases, controversies between states or between a state and citizens of another state, lawsuits involving citizens of different states, and against foreign states and citizens.

Certain courts, particularly the [[United States Supreme Court]] and most [[state supreme court]]s, have [[discretionary jurisdiction]], meaning that they can choose which cases to hear from among all the cases presented on appeal. Such courts generally only choose to hear cases that would settle important and controversial points of law. Though these courts have discretion to deny cases they otherwise could adjudicate, no court has the discretion to hear a case that falls outside of its subject-matter jurisdiction.

It is also necessary to distinguish between [[original jurisdiction]] and [[appellate jurisdiction]].  A court of original jurisdiction has the power to hear cases as they are first initiated by a [[plaintiff]], while a court of appellate jurisdiction may only hear an action after the court of original jurisdiction (or a lower appellate court) has heard the matter.  For example, in [[United States federal courts]], the United States district courts have original jurisdiction over a number of different matters (as mentioned above), and the [[United States court of appeals]] have appellate jurisdiction over matters appealed from the district courts.  The U.S. Supreme Court, in turn, has appellate jurisdiction (of a discretionary nature) over the Courts of Appeals, as well as the state supreme courts, by means of [[writ of certiorari]].

However, in a special class of cases, the U.S. Supreme Court has the power to exercise original jurisdiction. Under {{UnitedStatesCode|28|1251}}, the Supreme court has original and exclusive jurisdiction over controversies between two or more states, and original (but non-exclusive) jurisdiction over cases involving officials of foreign states, controversies between the [[Federal government of the United States|federal government]] and a state, actions by a state against the citizens of another state or foreign country.

The word &quot;jurisdiction&quot; is also used, especially in informal writing, to refer to a [[state (country subdivision)|state]] or political subdivision generally, or to its government, rather than to its legal authority.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/jurisdiction|title=Jurisdiction - Definition from the Merriam-Webster Online Dictionary}}  ''See also, e.g.'', [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/story/2008/09/22/ST2008092201168.html &quot;Metro's $11 Billion To-Do List,&quot;] in ''The [[Washington Post]]'':  &quot;Local jurisdictions are also facing shortfalls, and much will depend on the economy and political decisions at the local, state and federal levels&quot;; [http://www.baltimoresun.com/news/opinion/editorial/bal-ed.pensions24sep24,0,2581549.story &quot;Teacher pension pinch,&quot;] in ''The [[Baltimore Sun]]'':  &quot;Large, affluent jurisdictions have scores of high-salaried teachers with correspondingly higher pension costs.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Franchise jurisdiction==
In the history of English common law, a jurisdiction could be held as a form of property (or more precisely an [[incorporeal hereditament]]) called a [[exclusive right|franchise]]. Traditional franchise jurisdictions of various powers were held by [[corporations|municipal corporations]], [[abbey|religious houses]], [[guilds]], early [[universities]], [[Welsh Marches]], and [[County Palatine|Counties Palatine]]. Types of franchise courts included [[court baron|Courts Baron]], [[court leet|Courts Leet]], [[Court of Piepowder|merchant courts]], and the [[Stannary Courts and Parliaments|Stannary Courts]] which dealt with disputes involving the tin miners of [[Cornwall]]. The original [[royal charter]]s of the [[Thirteen Colonies|American colonies]] included broad grants of franchise jurisdiction along with other governmental powers to [[corporation]]s or individuals, as did the charters for many other colonial companies such as the [[British East India Company]] and [[British South Africa Company]]. Analogous jurisdiction existed in medieval times on the European Continent. Over the course of the 19th and 20th centuries, franchise jurisdictions were largely eliminated.  Several formerly important franchise courts were not officially abolished until [[Courts Act 1971|Courts Act of 1971]].

==See also==
*[[Guantánamo Bay Naval Base]]
*[[Labor unions in the United States]] - a different use of the word jurisdiction
*[[Law enforcement agency]] - a different use of the word jurisdiction
*[[Lawsuits against God]]
*''[[Rasul v. Bush]]''
*[[Private jurisdiction]]
*[[Universal jurisdiction]]
===Footnotes===
{{reflist}}

===External links===
{{wikiquote}}
*[http://www.law.cornell.edu/topics/jurisdiction.html Cornell.edu]
*[http://www.cdi.org/news/law/gtmo-sct-decision.cfm Supreme Court Decision] on the Guantánamo Bay jurisdiction
*[http://szabo.best.vwh.net/JurisdictionAsProperty.pdf Jurisdiction As Property] - franchise jurisdiction

[[Category:International law]]
[[Category:Conflict of laws]]
[[Category:Jurisdiction| ]]

[[ar:قضاء]]
[[bg:Юрисдикция]]
[[ca:Jurisdicció]]
[[cs:Jurisdikce]]
[[da:Jurisdiktion]]
[[de:Gerichtsbarkeit]]
[[es:Jurisdicción]]
[[fr:Compétence (droit)]]
[[gl:Xurisdición]]
[[ko:관할]]
[[id:Yurisdiksi]]
[[it:Giurisdizione]]
[[jv:Yurisdiksi]]
[[lt:Jurisdikcija]]
[[hu:Joghatóság]]
[[nl:Jurisdictie]]
[[ja:裁判管轄]]
[[no:Jurisdiksjon]]
[[oc:Competéncia (drech)]]
[[pl:Jurysdykcja]]
[[pt:Jurisdição]]
[[ru:Юрисдикция]]
[[sk:Právomoc]]
[[sv:Jurisdiktion]]
[[uk:Юрисдикція]]
[[zh:司法管轄權]]</text>
      <sha1>0wsdp932ngxmuwl6fkpa9s3latymlmp</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
