<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Labour movement</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>19287687</id>
    <revision>
      <id>510511355</id>
      <parentid>510511081</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-03T00:35:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>108.72.244.157</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* History */  Removed uncited opinion maked as needing citation for five years</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12962">The '''labour movement''' or '''labor movement''' is a broad term for the development of a collective organization of [[working class|working people]], to campaign for better working conditions and treatment from their employers and governments, in particular through the implementation of [[labour and employment law|specific laws governing labour relations]]. [[Trade union]]s are collective organizations within societies, organized for the purpose of representing the interests of workers and the working class. Many [[ruling class]] individuals and political groups may also be active in and part of the labour movement.

In some countries, especially the [[United Kingdom]] and [[Australian labour movement|Australia]] the labour movement is understood to encompass a formal &quot;political wing&quot;, frequently known by the name [[List of Labour Parties|labour party]] or [[workers' party]], which complements the aforementioned &quot;industrial wing&quot;.

{{labour}}

== History ==
{{Expand section|Apprentice laws, agricultural labour laws, illegal combination, Peterloo, Chartism, friendly societies and cooperatives, New Unionism, political party formation, socialism, anarchism, communism, craft unionism|date=April 2011}}

{{Quote box
| quote  = Labor is prior to, and independent of, capital. Capital is only the fruit of labor, and could never have existed if labor had not first existed. Labor is the superior of capital, and deserves much the higher consideration.
| source = — [[Abraham Lincoln|U.S. President Abraham Lincoln]], December 3, 1861&lt;ref&gt;''Selections from the Letters, Speeches, and State Papers of Abraham Lincoln'', by Abraham Lincoln, edited by Ida Minerva Tarbell, Ginn, 1911 / 2008, pg 77&lt;/ref&gt;
 | width = 28%
 | align =
}}

In [[Europe]], the labour movement began during the [[industrial revolution]], when agricultural jobs declined and employment moved to more industrial areas.  The idea met with great resistance. In the 18th century and early 19th century, groups such as the [[Tolpuddle Martyrs]] of [[Dorset]] were punished and [[penal transportation|transported]] for forming unions, which was against the laws of the time.

The labour movement was active in the early to mid 19th century and various labour parties and trade unions were formed throughout the industrialised world. The [[International Workingmen's Association]], the first attempt at international coordination, was founded in London in 1864.  The key points were the right of the workers to organize themselves, the right to an 8 hour working day etc. In 1871 the workers in France rebelled and the Paris Commune was formed.

The movement gained major impetus in the late nineteenth and early 20th centuries from the [[Catholic Social Teaching]] tradition which began in 1891 with the publication of [[Pope Leo XIII]]'s foundational document, ''[[Rerum Novarum]]'', also known as &quot;On the Condition of the Working Classes,&quot; in which he advocated a series of reforms including limits on the length of the work day, a living wage, the elimination of child labour, the rights of labour to organize, and the duty of the state to regulate labour conditions.

Throughout the world, action by the labour movement has led to reforms and [[labor rights|workers' rights]], such as the two-day [[Workweek|weekend]], [[minimum wage]], paid [[holiday]]s, and the achievement of the [[eight-hour day]] for many workers.  There have been many important labour activists in modern history who have caused changes that were revolutionary at the time and are now regarded as basic. For example, [[Mary Harris Jones]], better known as &quot;Mother Jones&quot;, and the [[National Catholic Welfare Council]] were central in the campaign to end [[child labour]] in the [[United States]] during the early 20th century. An active and free labour movement is considered by many to be an important element in maintaining [[democracy]] and for economic development.

==Labour parties==
{{see also|List of Labour Parties}}
Modern labour parties originated from an upsurge in organizing activities in [[Europe]] and [[European colonialism|European colonies]] during the 19th century, such as the [[Chartism|Chartist movement]] in [[United Kingdom|Britain]] during 1838&amp;ndash;50.

In 1891, localised labour parties were formed, by trade union members in the British colonies of [[Australia]]. They later amalgamated to form the [[Australian Labor Party]] (ALP). In 1893, Members of Parliament in the [[Queensland|Colony of Queensland]] briefly formed the world's first labour [[government]].

The [[Labour Party (UK)|British Labour Party]] was created as the [[British Labour Party#Labour Representation Committee|Labour Representation Committee]], as a result of an 1899 resolution by the [[Trade Union Congress]].

While archetypal labour parties are made of direct union representatives, in addition to members of geographical branches, some union federations or individual unions have chosen not to be represented within a labour party and/or have severed ties with them.

==Labour and racial equality==
{{Expand section|date=July 2011}}

A degree of strategic bi-racial cooperation existed among [[New Orleans Dock Workers and Unionization|black and white dockworkers on the waterfronts of New Orleans, Louisiana]] during the turn of the 20th century.  Although the groups maintained racially separate labor unions, they coordinated efforts to present a united front when making demands of their employers.  These pledges included a commitment to the &quot;50-50&quot; or &quot;half-and-half&quot; system wherein a dock crew would consist of 50% black and 50% white workers and agreement on a single wage demand to reduce the risk of ship owners pitting one race against the other.  Black and white dockworkers also stood together during protracted labor strikes, including general levee strikes in 1892 and 1907 as well as smaller strikes involving skilled workers such as screwmen in the early 1900s.&lt;ref&gt;See content, references and citations at [[New Orleans Dock Workers and Unionization]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;See content, references and citations at [[1892 New Orleans general strike]]&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quotation|Negroes in the United States read the history of labor and find it mirrors their own experience. We are confronted by powerful forces telling us to rely on the good will and understanding of those who profit by exploiting us [...] They are shocked that action organizations, sit-ins, civil disobedience and protests are becoming our everyday tools, just as strikes, demonstrations and union organization became yours to insure that bargaining power genuinely existed on both sides of the table [...] Our needs are identical to labor's needs: decent wages, fair working conditions, livable housing, old age security, health and welfare measures [...] That is why the labor-hater and labor-baiter is virtually always a twin-headed creature spewing anti-Negro epithets from one mouth and anti-labor propaganda from the other mouth.| [[Dr. Martin Luther King]], ''&quot;If the Negro Wins, Labor Wins&quot;'', December 11, 1961&lt;ref&gt;''A Testament of Hope: The Essential Writings and Speeches of Martin Luther King, Jr'', edited by James Melvin Washington, HarperCollins, 1991, ISBN 0-06-064691-8, pg 202-203&lt;/ref&gt;}}

== Development of labour movements within nation states ==
Historically [[Labour economics|labour markets]] have often been constrained by national borders that have restricted movement of workers. Labour laws are also primarily determined by individual nations or states within those nations. While there have been some efforts to adopt a set of international labour standards through the [[International Labour Organization]] (ILO), international sanctions for failing to meet such standards are very limited. In many countries labour movements have developed independently and reflect those national boundaries.

== Development of an international labour movement ==
With ever increasing levels of international trade and rising influence of multinational corporations, there has been debate and action within the labour movement broadly to attempt international co-operation. This has led to renewed efforts to organize and collectively bargain internationally. A number of international union organizations have been established in an attempt to facilitate international collective bargaining, to share information and resources and to advance the interests of workers generally.

== List of national labour movements ==
*[[Trade unions in Albania]]
*[[Trade unions in Algeria]]
*[[Trade unions in Andorra]]
*[[Trade unions in Angola]]
*[[Trade unions in Antigua and Barbuda]]
*[[Trade unions in Argentina]]
*[[Trade unions in Armenia]]
*[[Australian labour movement]]
*[[Trade unions in Benin]]
*[[Trade unions in Botswana]]
*[[Trade unions in Burkina Faso]]
*[[Trade unions in Egypt]]
*[[Trade unions in Ethiopia]]
*[[Trade unions in Germany]]
*[[Trade unions in Ghana]]
*[[Trade unions in India]]
*[[Iraqi Federation of Trade Unions]]
*[[Trade unions in Ireland]]
*[[Labor unions in Japan]]
*[[Trade unions in Malaysia]]
*[[Trade unions in Maldives]]
*[[Trade unions in Nauru]]
*[[Labour unions in Nepal]]
*[[Trade unions in Nepal]]
*[[Trade unions in Niger]]
*[[Trade unions in Oman]]
*[[Trade unions in Pakistan]]
*[[Trade unions in Qatar]]
*[[Trade unions in Senegal]]
*[[Trade unions in South Africa]]
*[[Swedish labour movement]]
*[[Trade unions in Switzerland]]
*[[Trade unions in Tanzania]]
*[[Trade unions in the United Kingdom]]
*[[Labor unions in the United States]]

== See also ==
{{Portal|Organized labour}}
{|
|-
|valign=top|
*[[Activism industry]]
*[[AFL-CIO]]
*[[Anarchism]]
*[[Anarcho-syndicalism]]
*[[Canadian Labour Congress]]
*[[Catholic social teaching]]
*[[Catholic trade unions]]
*[[Change to Win]]
*[[Christian socialism]]
*[[Christian trade unions]]
*[[Class struggle]]
*[[Communism]]
*[[Council communism]]
*[[Democratic socialism]]
*[[Eight hour day]]
|width=20px|
|valign=top|
*[[Far-left]]
*[[Filippo Turati]]
*[[Freelancers Union]]
*[[Industrial Workers of the World]]
*[[Labour and employment law]]
*[[Labor history (discipline)|Labor history]] including art and culture
*[[Left-wing politics]]
*[[List of international labor organizations]]
*[[Living wage]]
*[[Marxism]]
*[[New Unionism]]
*[[Social criticism]]
*[[Social democracy]]
*[[Socialism]]
*[[Trade unionism]]
|}

==References==
{{Refimprove|date=March 2009}}
&lt;references/&gt;

== Further reading ==
*Robert N. Stern, Daniel B. Cornfield, ''The U.S. labor movement:References and Resources'', G.K. Hall &amp; Co 1996
*John Hinshaw and Paul LeBlanc (ed.), ''U.S. labor in the twentieth century : studies in working-class struggles and insurgency'', Amherst, NY : Humanity Books, 2000
*Philip Yale Nicholson, ''Labor's story in the United States'', Philadelphia, Pa. : Temple Univ. Press 2004 (Series ‘Labor in Crisis’), ISBN 1-59213-239-1
* Beverly Silver: ''Forces of Labor. Worker's Movements and Globalization since 1870'', Cambridge University Press, 2003, ISBN 0-521-52077-0
*St. James Press Encyclopedia of Labor History Worldwide, St. James Press 2003 ISBN 1-55862-542-9
*Lenny Flank (ed), ''IWW: A Documentary History'', Red and Black Publishers, St Petersburg, Florida, 2007. ISBN 978-0-9791813-5-1
* Tom Zaniello: ''Working Stiffs, Union Maids, Reds, and Riffraff: An Expanded Guide to Films about Labor'' (ILR Press books), Cornell University Press, revised and expanded edition 2003, ISBN 0-8014-4009-2

==External links==
*[http://www.civilization.ca/cmc/exhibitions/hist/labour/lab01e.shtml The Canadian Museum of Civilization - Canadian Labour History, 1850-1999]
*[http://www.labourstart.org/ LabourStart: Trade union web portal]
*[http://www.labornet.org/ LaborNet: Global online communication for a democratic, independent labor movement]
*[http://www.cec-india.org/ CEC: A Labour Resource Centre in India ]
*[http://www.massaflcio.org/labor-quote Labor Quotes]
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SS79fLQGhY4 Justice Thunders Condemnation: A Video History of Labor Legislation]
{{Organized labor navbox}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Labour Movement}}
[[Category:Labor]]
[[Category:Labor movement| ]]

[[ar:حركة عمّالية]]
[[ast:Movimientu obreru]]
[[bg:Работническо движение]]
[[ca:Moviment obrer]]
[[cs:Dělnické hnutí]]
[[da:Arbejderbevægelsen]]
[[de:Arbeiterbewegung]]
[[et:Töölisliikumine]]
[[es:Movimiento obrero]]
[[eo:Laborista movado]]
[[eu:Langileen mugimendua Espainian]]
[[fa:جنبش کارگری]]
[[fr:Mouvement ouvrier]]
[[hi:श्रम आंदोलन]]
[[it:Movimento operaio]]
[[hu:Munkásmozgalom]]
[[ms:Pergerakan pekerja]]
[[mn:Ажилчны хөдөлгөөн]]
[[nl:Arbeidersbeweging]]
[[ja:労働運動]]
[[no:Arbeiderbevegelsen]]
[[nn:Arbeidarrørsla]]
[[pl:Ruch robotniczy]]
[[pt:Trabalhismo]]
[[ru:Рабочее движение]]
[[fi:Työväenliike]]
[[sv:Arbetarrörelsen]]
[[tr:Emek hareketi]]
[[uk:Робітничий рух]]
[[zh:勞工運動]]</text>
      <sha1>49rumgai552zwfoq89edposiyek6cle</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
