<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Laissez-faire</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>165451</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521903925</id>
      <parentid>521903912</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-07T23:10:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contributions/24.190.27.172|24.190.27.172]] to version by Rick Norwood. False positive? [[User:ClueBot NG/FalsePositives|Report it]]. Thanks, [[User:ClueBot NG|ClueBot NG]]. (1321811) (Bot)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27147">{{Italic title}}
{{Capitalism}}
'''''Laissez-faire'''''  ({{IPAc-en|audio=En-us-laissez-faire.ogg|ˌ|l|ɛ|s|eɪ|ˈ|f|ɛər|-}}, {{IPA-fr|lɛsefɛʁ|lang|laissez-faire.ogg}}) is an economic environment in which transactions between private parties are free from [[tariffs]], [[government]] [[subsidies]], and enforced [[monopolies]], with only enough government [[regulation]]s sufficient to protect [[property rights]] against [[theft]] and [[aggression]]. The phrase ''laissez-faire'' is [[French language|French]] and literally means &quot;let [them] do&quot;, but it broadly implies &quot;let it be,&quot; &quot;let them do as they will,&quot; or &quot;leave it alone.&quot;  Scholars generally believe a ''laissez-faire'' state or a completely free market has never existed.&lt;ref&gt;Buder, Stanley. 2009. [http://books.google.is/books?id=Ywa0F1R9lXYC&amp;pg=PA13&amp;dq=laissez+faire+has+never+existed&amp;hl=is&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=cJEuT-6pB82n8gPzwcmKDw&amp;ved=0CEQQ6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;q=has%20never%20existed&amp;f=false ''Capitalizing on Change: A Social History of American Business''] Pg. 13. ISBN 978-0-8078-3231-8.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.econlib.org/library/Enc/Capitalism.html &quot;A fully free economy, true laissez-faire, never has existed...&quot;, Robert Hessen, senior research fellow at Stanford University’s Hoover Institution&lt;/ref&gt;

== Etymology ==
According to historical legend, the phrase stems from a meeting in about 1680 between the powerful French finance minister [[Jean-Baptiste Colbert]] and a group of French businessmen led by a certain M. Le Gendre. When the eager [[mercantilist]] minister asked how the French state could be of service to the merchants and help promote their commerce, Le Gendre replied simply &quot;''Laissez-nous faire''&quot; (&quot;Leave us be&quot;, lit. &quot;Let us do&quot;).{{Citation needed|date=April 2012}}

The anecdote on the Colbert-Le Gendre meeting was related in a 1751 article in the ''Journal Oeconomique'' by the French minister and champion of free trade, [[René Louis de Voyer de Paulmy d'Argenson|René de Voyer, Marquis d'Argenson]]—which happens to also be the phrase's first known appearance in print.&lt;ref&gt;M. d'Argenson, &quot;Lettre au sujet de la dissertation sur le commerce du marquis de Belloni', Avril 1751, ''Journal Oeconomique'' [http://books.google.com/books?id=k4ABAAAAYAAJ&amp;vq=morbleu&amp;dq=editions%3ANYPL33433007441680&amp;lr&amp;pg=RA3-PA111#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false p.111]. See A. Oncken, ''Die Maxime Laissez faire et laissez passer, ihr Ursprung, ihr Werden'', 1866&lt;/ref&gt;  Argenson himself had used the phrase earlier (1736) in his own diaries, in a famous outburst:

 {{quote|''Laissez faire, telle devrait être la devise de toute puissance publique, depuis que le monde est civilisé&amp;nbsp;... Détestable principe que celui de ne vouloir grandir que par l'abaissement de nos voisins! Il n'y a que la méchanceté et la malignité du coeur de satisfaites dans ce principe, et l’intérêt y est opposé. Laissez faire, morbleu! Laissez faire!!'' &lt;ref&gt;as quoted in J.M. Keynes, 1926, &quot;The End of Laissez Faire&quot;.  Argenson's ''Mémoirs'' were published only in 1858, ed. Jannet, Tome V, p.362.  See A. Oncken (''Die Maxime Laissez faire et laissez passer, ihr Ursprung, ihr Werden'', 1866)&lt;/ref&gt;

(Trans: &quot;Leave it be, that should be the motto of all public powers, as the world is civilized ... That we cannot grow except by lowering our neighbors is a detestable notion! Only malice and malignity of heart is satisfied with such a principle and our (national) interest is opposed to it. Leave it be, for heaven's sake! Leave it be!)}}

The ''laissez faire'' slogan was popularized by [[Vincent de Gournay]], a French intendant of commerce in the 1750s. Gournay was an ardent proponent of the removal of restrictions on trade and the deregulation of industry in France. Gournay was delighted by the Colbert-LeGendre anecdote,&lt;ref&gt;According to J. [[Anne-Robert-Jacques Turgot, Baron de Laune|Turgot]]'s &quot;Eloge de Vincent de Gournay,&quot; '' Mercure'', August, 1759 (repr. in ''Oeuvres of Turgot'', vol. 1 [http://books.google.com/books?id=5KQALAckPr8C&amp;dq=Eloge%20de%20Gournay&amp;pg=PA288#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false p.288].&lt;/ref&gt; and forged it into a larger maxim all his own: &quot;''Laissez faire et laissez passer''&quot; ('Let do and let pass'). His motto has also been identified as the longer &quot;''Laissez faire et laissez passer, le monde va de lui même!''&quot; (&quot;Let do and let pass, the world goes on by itself!&quot;). Although Gournay left no written tracts on his economic policy ideas, he had immense personal influence on his contemporaries, notably the [[Physiocrats]], who credit both the ''laissez-faire'' slogan and the doctrine to Gournay.&lt;ref&gt;Gournay was credited with the phrase by [[Jacques Turgot]] (&quot;Eloge a Gournay&quot;, ''Mercure'' 1759), the [[Victor de Riqueti, marquis de Mirabeau|Marquis de Mirabeau]] (''Philosophie rurale'' 1763 and ''Ephémérides du Citoyen'', 1767.), the [[Comte d'Albon]] (,&quot;Éloge Historique de M. Quesnay&quot;, ''Nouvelles Ephémérides Économiques'', May, 1775, p.136-7. ) and [[Pierre Samuel du Pont de Nemours|DuPont de Nemours]] (Introduction to ''Ouevres de Jacques Turgot'', 1808–11, Vol. I, p.257 and p.259 (Daire ed.)) among others&lt;/ref&gt;

Before d'Argenson or Gournay, [[Pierre Le Pesant, sieur de Boisguilbert|P.S. de Boisguilbert]] had enunciated the phrase &quot;on laisse faire la nature&quot; ('let nature run its course').&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Tant, encore une fois, qu'on laisse faire la nature, on ne doit rien craindre de pareil&quot;, P.S. de Boisguilbert, 1707, ''Dissertation de la nature des richesses, de l'argent et des tributs''.&lt;/ref&gt;  D'Argenson himself, during his life, was better known for the similar but less-celebrated motto &quot;''Pas trop gouverner''&quot; (&quot;Govern not too much&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;DuPont de Nemours, ''op cit'', p.258. Oncken (''op.cit'') and Keynes (''op.cit''.) also credit the Marquis d'Argenson with the phrase &quot;''Pour gouverner mieux, il faudrait gouverner moins''&quot; (&quot;To govern best, one needs to govern less&quot;), possibly the source of the famous &quot;That government is best which governs least&quot; motto popular in American circles, attributed variously to [[Thomas Paine]], [[Thomas Jefferson]] and [[Henry Thoreau]].&lt;/ref&gt; But it was Gournay's use of the 'laissez-faire' phrase (as popularized by the [[Physiocracy|Physiocrats]]) that gave it its cachet.

In England, a number of &quot;free trade&quot; and &quot;non-interference&quot; slogans had been coined already during the 17th century.{{Citation needed|date=April 2012}} But the French phrase ''laissez faire'' gained currency in English-speaking countries with the spread of Physiocratic literature in the late 18th century.  The Colbert-LeGendre anecdote was relayed in [[George Whatley]]'s 1774 ''Principles of Trade'' (co-authored with [[Benjamin Franklin]]) - which may be the first appearance of the phrase in an English language publication.&lt;ref&gt;Whatley's ''Principles of Trade'' are reprinted in ''Works of Benjamin Franklin, Vol.2'', [http://books.google.com/books?id=C2QUAAAAYAAJ&amp;dq=Benjamin%20Franklin%20%22Principles%20of%20Trade%22&amp;pg=PA401#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false p.401]&lt;/ref&gt;

Notably, [[classical economics|classical economists]], such as [[Thomas Malthus]], [[Adam Smith]]&lt;ref name=asoae /&gt; and [[David Ricardo]], did not use the phrase. [[Jeremy Bentham]] used the term, but it was probably [[James Mill]]'s reference to the &quot;''laissez-faire''&quot; maxim (together with &quot;''pas trop gouverner''&quot;) in an 1824 entry for the ''Encyclopædia Britannica'' that really brought the term into wider English usage. With the advent of the [[Anti-Corn Law League]], the term received much of its (English) meaning.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Abbott P. Usher|title=Economic History—The Decline of Laissez Faire|year=1931|journal=American Economic Review|volume=22|issue=1, Supplement|pages=3–10|author-separator=,|display-authors=1|author2=&lt;Please add first missing authors to populate metadata.&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Adam Smith]] first used the metaphor of an &quot;[[invisible hand]]&quot; in his book ''[[The Theory of Moral Sentiments]]'' to describe the unintentional effects of economic self-organization from economic self-interest.&lt;ref&gt;Andres Marroquin, ''Invisible Hand: The Wealth of Adam Smith'', The Minerva Group, Inc., 2002, ISBN 1-4102-0288-7, page 123.&lt;/ref&gt; Some have characterized this metaphor as one for ''laissez-faire'',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/books?id=zAIar8Ee80QC&amp;lpg=PA122&amp;dq=laissez%20faire%20invisible%20hand&amp;pg=PA122#v=onepage&amp;q=laissez%20faire%20invisible%20hand&amp;f=false ''The mathematical century: the 30 greatest problems of the last 100 years'' (2006) Piergiorgio Odifreddi, Arturo Sangalli, Freeman J Dyson, p. 122]&lt;/ref&gt; but Smith never actually used the term himself.&lt;ref name=asoae&gt;Roy C. Smith, Adam Smith and the Origins of American Enterprise: How the Founding Fathers Turned to a Great Economist's Writings and Created the American Economy, Macmillan, 2004, ISBN 0-312-32576-2, pp. 13–14.&lt;/ref&gt;

==History of laissez-faire debate==

===China===
During the [[Han Dynasty|Han]], [[Tang Dynasty|Tang]], [[Song Dynasty|Song]], and [[Ming Dynasty|Ming]] dynasties, Chinese scholar-officials would often debate about the interference the government should have in the economy, such as setting monopolies in lucrative industries and instating price controls. Such debates were often heated with Confucian factions tending to oppose extensive government controls and &quot;Reform&quot; factions favoring such moves. During the Han and Tang, emperors sometimes instated [[government monopolies]] in times of war, and abolished them later when the fiscal crisis had passed. Eventually, in the later Song and Ming dynasties, state monopolies were abolished in every industry and were never reinstated during the length of that dynasty, with the government following laissez-faire policies. During the Manchu Qing Dynasty, [[Government monopoly|state monopolies]] were reinstated, and the government interfered heavily in the economy; many scholars believe this prevented China from developing capitalism.&lt;ref&gt;Li Bo and Zheng Yin, 5000 years of Chinese history, Inner Mongolian People's publishing corp , ISBN 7-204-04420-7, 1017&lt;/ref&gt;

===Europe===
In Europe the laissez faire movement was first widely promoted by the [[physiocracy|physiocrats]], a movement that originated with [[Jean-Claude Vincent de Gournay]], a successful merchant.  Gournay held that the government should allow the laws of nature to govern economic activity, with the state only intervening to protect life, liberty, and property.  His ideas were taken up by [[Francois Quesnay]] and [[Turgot]], Baron de l'Aulne.  Quesnay had the ear of the King of France, [[Louis XV of France|Louis XV]], and in 1754 persuaded him to give laissez faire a try.  On September 17, the King abolished all tolls and restraints on the sale and transport of grain, and for more than a decade the experiment was a success.  But then, in 1768, there was a poor harvest, and the cost of bread rose so high that there was widespread starvation, while merchants exported grain in order to obtain the best profit.  In 1770, the edict allowing free trade was revoked.&lt;ref&gt;Will &amp; Ariel Durant, ''Rousseau and the Revolution'', pp. 71-77, Simon and Schuster, 1967, ISBN 067163058X.&lt;/ref&gt;
 
Many of the ideas of the physiocrats spread throughout Europe, and were adopted to a greater or lesser extent in Sweden, Tuscany, Spain, and after 1776 in the newly created United States. [[Adam Smith]], author of ''[[The Wealth of Nations]]'', met Quesnay and acknowledged his influence.&lt;ref&gt;Will &amp; Ariel Durant, ''Rousseau and the Revolution'', p. 76, Simon and Schuster, 1967, ISBN 067163058X.&lt;/ref&gt;

In Britain, in 1843, the newspaper ''[[The Economist]]'' was founded and became an influential voice for ''laissez-faire'' capitalism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Scott Gordon|title=The London Economist and the High Tide of Laissez Faire|year=1955|journal=Journal of Political Economy|volume=63|issue=6|pages=461–488|doi=10.1086/257722}}&lt;/ref&gt;  ''Laissez-faire'' advocates  opposed food aid for famines occurring within the British empire; in 1847, referring to the famine then underway in Ireland, ''The Economist's'' founder [[James Wilson (businessman)|James Wilson]] wrote that &quot;It is no man's business to provide for another&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book 
|author = [[Cormac Ó Gráda]]
|title= The Great Irish Famine
|year=  1995
|chapter = section: ''Ideology and relief'' in Chpt. 2
|isbn= 9780521557870
|publisher= [[Cambridge University Press]]
}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
However, ''The Economist'' campaigned against the [[Corn Laws]] that protected landlords in the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland against competition from less expensive foreign imports of cereal products. The [[Great Famine (Ireland)|Great Famine]] in Ireland in 1845 led to the repeal of the Corn Laws in 1846.  The tariffs on grain which kept the price of bread artificially high were repealed.&lt;ref&gt;George Miller. ''On Fairness and Efficiency''. The Policy Press, 2000. ISBN 978-1-86134-221-8 p.344&lt;/ref&gt; However, repeal of the Corn Laws came too late to stop Irish famine, partly because it was done in stages over three years.&lt;ref&gt;Christine Kinealy. ''A Death-Dealing Famine:The Great Hunger in Ireland''. Pluto Press, 1997. ISBN 978-0-7453-1074-9. p. 59&lt;/ref&gt;

A group calling itself the [[Manchester Liberalism|Manchester Liberals]], to which [[Richard Cobden]] and Richard Wright belonged, were staunch defenders of free trade, and their work was carried on, after the death of Richard Cobden in 1866, by ''The Cobden Club''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=London Clubs in the Late Nineteenth Century|url=http://www.nuff.ox.ac.uk/economics/history/paper28/28taddeiweb1.pdf|format=PDF|author=Antonia Taddei|year=1999|accessdate=2008-12-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1867, a free trade treaty was signed between Britain and France, after which several of these treaties were signed among other European countries.

===United States===

Frank Bourgin's 1989 study of the [[Constitutional Convention]] shows that direct government involvement in the economy was intended by the Founders.&lt;ref name=bourgin&gt;{{Cite book|first=Frank|last=Bourgin|title=The Great Challenge: The Myth of Laissez-Faire in the Early Republic|isbn=0-06-097296-3|year=1989|publisher=George Braziller Inc.|location=New York, NY|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; The reason for this was the economic and financial chaos the nation suffered under the [[Articles of Confederation]].  The goal was to ensure that dearly won political independence was not lost by being economically and financially dependent on the powers and princes of Europe. The creation of a strong central government able to promote science, invention, industry and commerce, was seen as an essential means of promoting the general welfare and making the economy of the United States strong enough for them to determine their own destiny.

In his 1973 study of the economic principles established at the foundation of the United States, E.A.J. Johnson wrote:
{{quote|The general view, discernible in contemporaneous literature, was that the responsibility of government should involve enough surveillance over the enterprise system to ensure the social usefulness of all economic activity. It is quite proper, said Bordley, for individuals to “choose for themselves” how they will apply their labor and their intelligence in production. But it does not follow from this that “legislators and men of influence” are freed from all responsibility for giving direction to the course of national economic development. They must, for instance, discountenance the production of unnecessary commodities of luxury when common sense indicates the need for food and other essentials.  Lawmakers can fulfill their functions properly only when they “become benefactors to the public”; in new countries they must safeguard agriculture and commerce, encourage immigration, and promote manufactures. Admittedly, liberty “is one of the most important blessings which men possess,” but the idea that liberty is synonymous with complete freedom from restraint “is a most unwise, mistaken apprehension.” True liberty demands a system of legislation that will lead all members of society “to unite their exertions” for the public welfare. It should therefore be the policy of government to aid and foster certain activities or kinds of business that strengthen a nation, even as it should be the duty of government to repress “those fashions, habits, and practices, which tend to weaken, impoverish, and corrupt the people.” &lt;ref name=johnson&gt;{{Cite book|first=E.A.J.|last=Johnson|title=The Foundations of American Economic Freedom: Government and Enterprise in the Age of Washington|isbn=0-8166-0664-1|year=1973|publisher=University of Minnesota Press|location=New York, NY|pages=194–195|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Notable examples of government intervention in the period prior to the Civil War include the establishment of the [[Patent Office]] in 1802; the establishment of the Office of Standard Weights and Measures in 1830; the creation of the [[Coast and Geodetic Survey]] in 1807 and other measures to improve river and harbor navigation; the various Army expeditions to the west, beginning with Lewis and Clark's [[Corps of Discovery]] in 1804 and continuing into the 1870s, almost always under the direction of an officer from the Army [[Corps of Topographical Engineers]], and which provided crucial information for the overland pioneers that followed; the assignment of Army Engineer officers to assist or direct the surveying and construction of the early railroads and canals; the establishment of the [[First Bank of the United States]] and [[Second Bank of the United States]] as well as various protectionist measures (e.g., the [[tariff of 1828]]). Several of these proposals met with serious opposition, and required a great deal of horse trading to be enacted into law. For instance, the First National Bank would not have reached the desk of President [[George Washington]] in the absence of an agreement that was reached between [[Alexander Hamilton]] and several southern members of Congress to locate the capital in the [[District of Columbia]]. In contrast to Hamilton and the Federalists was the opposing political party the [[Democratic-Republican Party|Democratic-Republicans]].

Most of the early opponents of ''laissez-faire'' capitalism in the United States subscribed to the [[American School (economics)|American School]]. This school of thought was inspired by the ideas of Alexander Hamilton, who proposed the creation of a [[First Bank of the United States|government-sponsored bank]] and increased tariffs to favor northern industrial interests. Following Hamilton's death, the more abiding protectionist influence in the antebellum period came from [[Henry Clay]] and his ''[[American System (economic plan)|American System]]''.

In the early 19th century, &quot;it is quite clear that the laissez faire label is an inappropriate one&quot; to apply to the relationship between the US government and industry.&lt;ref name = &quot;Prince Taylor&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last1= Prince |first1= Carl E. |last2= Taylor |first2= Seth |year= 1982 |title= Daniel Webster, the Boston Associates, and the U.S. Government's Role in the Industrializing Process, 1815–1830 |journal= Journal of the Early Republic |volume= 2 |issue= 3 |pages= 283–299 |jstor= 3122975 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In the mid-19th century, the [[United States]] followed the [[Whig Party (United States)|Whig]] tradition of [[Economic nationalism]], which included increased state control, regulation and [[macroeconomic]] development of [[infrastructure]].&lt;ref name=guelzo&gt;{{Cite book|first=Allen C.|last=Guelzo|title=Abraham Lincoln: Redeemer President|isbn=0-8028-3872-3|year=1999|url=http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=99466893|publisher=W.B. Eerdmans Pub. Co|location=Grand Rapids, Mich.|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Public works]] such as the provision and regulation [[transportation]] such as railroads took effect. The [[Pacific Railway Acts]] provided the development of the [[First Transcontinental Railroad]].&lt;ref name=&quot;guelzo&quot;/&gt; In order to help pay for its war effort in the [[American Civil War]], the [[United States government]] imposed its first personal [[income tax]], on August 5, 1861, as part of the [[Revenue Act of 1861]] (3% of all incomes over US $800; rescinded in 1872).

Following the Civil War, the movement towards a [[mixed economy]] accelerated.  [[Protectionism]] increased with the [[McKinley Tariff]] of 1890 and the [[Dingley Tariff]] of 1897.  [[Government regulation]] of the economy expanded with the enactment of the [[Interstate Commerce Act of 1887]] and the [[Sherman Anti-trust Act]].

The [[Progressive Era]] saw the enactment of more controls on the economy, as evidenced by the Wilson Administration's [[The New Freedom|New Freedom]] program.

Following [[World War I]] and the [[Great Depression]], the United States turned to a [[mixed economy]], which combined free enterprise with a progressive income tax, and in which, from time to time, the government stepped in to support and protect American industry from competition from overseas. For example in the 1980s the government sought to protect the automobile industry by &quot;voluntary&quot; export restrictions from Japan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Robert W. Crandall|year=1987|title=The Effects of U.S. Trade Protection for Autos and Steel|journal=Brookings Papers on Economic Activity|volume=1987|issue=1|pages=271–288|doi=10.2307/2534518|publisher=Brookings Papers on Economic Activity, Vol. 1987, No. 1|jstor=2534518}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pietro S. Nivola wrote in 1986:{{quote|By and large, the comparative strength of the dollar against major foreign currencies has reflected high U.S. interest rates driven by huge federal budget deficits. Hence, the source of much of the current deterioration of trade is not the general state of the economy, but rather the government's mix of fiscal and monetary policies– that is, the problematic juxtaposition of bold tax reductions, relatively tight monetary targets, generous military outlays, and only modest cuts in major entitlement programs. Put simply, the roots of the trade problem and of the resurgent protectionism it has fomented are fundamentally political as well as economic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Pietro S. Nivola|year=1986|title=The New Protectionism: U.S. Trade Policy in Historical Perspective|journal=[[Political Science Quarterly]]|volume=101|issue=4|pages=577–600|doi=10.2307/2150795|publisher=Political Science Quarterly, Vol. 101, No. 4|jstor=2150795}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==See also==
* [[Anarcho-capitalism]]
* [[Austrian school]]
* [[Capitalism]]
* [[Classical liberalism]]
* [[Economic liberalism]]
* [[Free market]]
* [[Free-market anarchism]]
* [[Market fundamentalism]]
* [[Minarchism]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Bibliography==
* {{cite journal|author=Brebner, John Bartlet|year=1948|title=Laissez Faire and State Intervention in Nineteenth-Century Britain|journal=Journal of Economic History|volume=8|pages=59–73}}
* {{cite journal|author=Fisher, Irving|year=1907|month=January|title=Why has the Doctrine of Laissez Faire been Abandoned?|journal=[[Science (journal)|Science]]|volume=25|issue=627|pages=18–27|doi=10.1126/science.25.627.18|pmid=17739703|authorlink=Irving Fisher}}
* {{cite journal|author=Taussig, Frank W.|year=1904|title=The Present Position of the Doctrine of Free Trade|journal=[[American Economic Association|Publications of the American Economic Association]]|volume=6|issue=1|pages=29–65|authorlink=Frank William Taussig}}
&lt;/div&gt;

==Further reading==
*Bourgin, Frank ''The Great Challenge: The Myth of Laissez-Faire in the Early Republic'' (George Braziller Inc., 1989; Harper &amp; Row, 1990)
{{Spoken Wikipedia|En-us-laissez-faire.ogg|2008-06-27}}
* {{PDFlink|[http://hsozkult.geschichte.hu-berlin.de/daten/2005/gerlach_christian_wu-wei.pdf Wu-Wei in Europe. A Study of Eurasian Economic Thought]|773&amp;nbsp;KB}} by Christian Gerlach, London School of Economics – March 2005
*[http://www.panarchy.org/keynes/laissezfaire.1926.html John Maynard Keynes, The end of laissez-faire (1926)]
*Carter Goodrich, ''[http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=100695027 Government Promotion of American Canals and Railroads, 1800–1890]'' (Greenwood Press, 1960)
** Goodrich, Carter. &quot;American Development Policy: the Case of Internal Improvements,&quot; ''Journal of Economic History'', 16 (1956), 449–60. in JSTOR
** Goodrich, Carter. &quot;National Planning of Internal Improvements,&quot; ;;Political Science Quarterly'', 63 (1948), 16–44. in JSTOR
*Johnson, E.A.J., ''The Foundations of American Economic Freedom: Government and Enterprise in the Age of Washington'' (University of Minnesota Press, 1973)
*{{cite web |url= http://www.econlib.org/library/YPDBooks/Shaw/shwFS1.html#I.1.18| title=Fabian Essays in Socialism - The Basis of Socialism - The Period of Anarchy | author=Sidney Webb |year = 1889 |publisher=Library of Economics and Liberty |quote=Women working half naked in the coal mines; young children dragging trucks all day in the foul atmosphere of the underground galleries; infants bound to the loom for fifteen hours in the heated air of the cotton mill, and kept awake only by the overlooker's lash; hours of labor for all, young and old, limited only by the utmost capabilities of physical endurance; complete absence of the sanitary provisions necessary to a rapidly growing population: these and other nameless iniquities will be found recorded as the results of freedom of contract and complete laissez faire in the impartial pages of successive blue-book reports. |authorlink= Sidney Webb, 1st Baron Passfield}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Laissez-Faire}}
[[Category:Classical liberalism]]
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Economic liberalism]]
[[Category:Political movements]]
[[Category:Political economy]]
[[Category:Paleolibertarianism]]
[[Category:Minarchism]]
[[Category:French words and phrases]]
[[Category:Capitalism]]
[[Category:Right-wing politics]]
[[Category:Individualism]]
[[Category:French loanwords]]

{{Link GA|zh}}
[[ar:اقتصاد عدم التدخل]]
[[bn:অবাধনীতি]]
[[zh-min-nan:Chū-iû hòng-jīm]]
[[bg:Лесе-фер]]
[[bs:Ekonomski liberalizam]]
[[ca:Laissez faire]]
[[cs:Laissez faire]]
[[cy:Laissez-faire]]
[[da:Laissez faire]]
[[de:Laissez-faire]]
[[et:Laissez faire]]
[[es:Laissez faire]]
[[eu:Laissez faire]]
[[fr:Laissez-faire]]
[[ko:자유방임주의]]
[[hr:Laissez faire]]
[[id:Laissez-faire]]
[[it:Laissez-faire]]
[[he:לסה פר]]
[[hu:Laissez-faire]]
[[arz:اقتصاد عدم التدخل]]
[[ms:Laissez-faire]]
[[my:Laissez-faire]]
[[nl:Laisser faire]]
[[ja:レッセフェール]]
[[no:Laissez-faire]]
[[pl:Leseferyzm]]
[[pt:Laissez-faire]]
[[ru:Laissez-faire]]
[[sah:Laissez-faire]]
[[sco:Laissez-faire]]
[[simple:Laissez faire]]
[[sk:Laissez-faire]]
[[sr:Лесе фер]]
[[fi:Laissez-faire]]
[[sv:Laissez faire]]
[[tl:Laissez-faire]]
[[ta:தலையிடாமைக் கொள்கை]]
[[th:นโยบายไม่แทรกเซง]]
[[tr:Laissez faire]]
[[uk:Laissez-faire]]
[[vi:Laissez-faire]]
[[war:Laissez-faire]]
[[zh:自由放任]]</text>
      <sha1>hkxcozvll6tuir3pzwfcvn9q8aic13k</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
