<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Legislative Assembly (France)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>758831</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519519102</id>
      <parentid>519518748</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-24T05:45:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JSquish</username>
        <id>11953178</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8693">{{more footnotes|date=September 2011}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2011}}
{{Infobox Legislature Historic
 | name          = Legislative Assembly
 | native_name   = Assemblée législative
 | image         = 
 | image size    = 
 | caption       =
 | entity        = [[Kingdom of France (1791–1792)]]
 | type          = Unicameral
 | houses        =
 | members       = 745 in total
 | location      = Variable
 | year          = 1 October 1791
 | year2         = September 1792
 | before        = [[National Constituent Assembly]]
 | after         = [[National Convention]]
 | notes         =
}}

The '''Legislative Assembly''' was the legislature of [[France]] from 1 October 1791 to September 1792 during the years of the [[French Revolution]]. It provided the focus of political debate and revolutionary law-making between the periods of the [[National Constituent Assembly]] and of the [[National Convention]]. 

The Legislative Assembly was driven by two opposing groups. The members of the first group were primarily moderate members of the bourgeoisie that favored a [[constitutional monarchy]], represented by the [[Feuillant (political group)|Feuillants]], who felt that the revolution had already achieved its goal.&lt;ref&gt;[[Albert Mathiez]], ''La Révolution française'', Librairie Armand Colin 1922, p. 170&lt;/ref&gt;  The second group was the democratic faction, for whom the [[Louis XVI of France|king]] could no longer be trusted, represented by the new members of the [[Jacobin Club|Jacobin club]].&lt;ref&gt;Bernardine Melchior-Bonnet, ''Les Girondins'', Tallandier 1989, p. 52&lt;/ref&gt; This group claimed that more revolutionary measures were necessary.&lt;ref&gt;Jean-Paul Bertaud, ''La Révolution française'', Perrin 1989 « rééd. coll. Tempus », 2004, p. 81-133&lt;/ref&gt;{{,}}{{#tag:ref| Immediately there was a great deal of dissension between the [[Feuillant (political group)|Feuillants]] and the democratic faction due to changes made to the [[French constitution of 1791|Constitution]] and the [[Flight to Varennes]]. The democrats felt that the influence of the majority of the populace was minimized due to [[Suffrage#Census_suffrage|census suffrage]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bertaud81&quot;&gt;Jean-Paul Bertaud, ''La Révolutions française'', p. 81&lt;/ref&gt;|group=&quot;note&quot;}}

==Background==
The [[National Constituent Assembly]] dissolved itself on 30 September 1791. Upon [[Maximilien Robespierre|Robespierre]]'s motion it had decreed that none of its members should be capable of sitting in the next legislature. Its successor body, the Legislative Assembly, operating under the [[Liberalism|liberal]] [[French Constitution of 1791]], did not last a year and was generally deemed a failure. It left behind an empty treasury, an undisciplined army and navy, and enormous domestic turmoil.

The Legislative Assembly entrenched the perceived [[Left-right politics|left-right]] [[political spectrum]] that is still commonly used today.

==Election of the Legislative Assembly==
Despite a limited franchise, the elections of 1791 brought in a legislature which – perhaps even disproportionately to the will of the country – desired to carry the Revolution further. Prominent among this legislature were the [[Jacobin Club]] and its affiliated societies throughout France. 

The Legislative Assembly first met on 1 October 1791. It consisted of 745 members, and some historians have attempted to argue that they were mostly from the middle class, though this is not universally accepted. The members were generally young, and, since none had sat in the previous Assembly, they largely lacked national political experience. They tended to be people who had made their name through successful political careers in local politics.

The [[Right-wing politics|Right]] within the assembly (in the wider picture of national politics they are better seen as moderates, since the 'real' right wing of monarchists were outside the assembly and in some cases outside the country as émigrés at this time) consisted of about 165 &quot;[[Feuillant (political group)|Feuillant]]s&quot;, guided chiefly by persons outside the House, because those had been made incapable of re-election. The [[Left-wing politics|Left]], generally dominant during this period, consisted of about 330 &quot;[[Jacobin (politics)|Jacobins]]&quot;, a term which still included the party afterwards known as the [[Girondin]]s or Girondists. The Left as a whole was openly anti-''émigré'' and [[anticlericalism|anticlerical]]. They also generally, although often not openly, favored a republic. In these views, they were reinforced by the less privileged classes in Paris and throughout France. The remainder of the House, about 250 deputies, generally belonged to no definite party. The king's ministers, named by him and excluded from the Assembly, are described by the [[1911 Encyclopædia Britannica|1911 ''Encyclopædia Britannica'']] as &quot;mostly persons of little mark.&quot;

==History==
''For a detailed description of the proceedings of the Legislative Assembly and related events, see [[The Legislative Assembly and the fall of the French monarchy]].''

The 27 August 1791 [[Declaration of Pillnitz]] already threatened France with attack by its neighbors. With both King [[Louis XVI of France|Louis XVI]] and the majority of the legislature favoring war, albeit for different reasons, this led in April 1792 to the first of the [[French Revolutionary Wars]].

In the early days of the Legislative Assembly, the king vetoed many of their radical measures: 

* Legislation against the ''émigrés'', passed 9 November 1791 but vetoed by Louis.
* Enforcement of the [[Civil Constitution of the Clergy]]: on 29 November 1791 the Assembly decreed that every non-juring clergyman must take the civic oath within eight days, on pain of losing his pension and, if any troubles broke out, of being deported. Louis vetoed this decree as a matter of conscience.


A sparsely populated session of the Legislative Assembly, almost all of them [[Jacobin Club|Jacobins]], suspended Louis from office and voted that a convention should be summoned to give France a new constitution. At this point, the government of France descended into chaos. The new, anti-monarchical government had no root in law and little hold on [[public opinion]].{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}} It could not lean on the Assembly, a mere shrunken remnant, whose days were numbered. It remained dependent on the power which had set it up, the revolutionary Commune of Paris. The Commune could therefore extort what concessions it pleased.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}} It got the custody of the king and his family, who were imprisoned in the [[Temple (Paris)|Temple]]. Having obtained an indefinite power of arrest, it soon filled the prisons of Paris. With the invasion of France on 19 August 1792 under the leadership of the [[Charlie Boy William Ferdinand, Duke of Brunswick|Duke of Brunswick]], a prison bloodbath ensued, a prelude to the [[Reign of Terror]].

The ensuing elections to the Convention were by almost universal suffrage, but indifference or intimidation reduced the voters to a small number.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}} Many who had sat in the National Constituent Assembly and many more who had sat in the Legislative Assembly were returned. The Convention met on 20 September 1792 and became the new ''de facto'' government of France.

==Marriage Reform==

On 15 February 1792 [[Honoré Muraire]], reporting for the Legislative Committee, presented a series of recommendations on marriage reform,  including the implementation of registers of civil status (replacing registers maintained by the clergy), and allowing young people the age of twenty-one years old to marry without the consent of their parents. A law on divorce was passed 20 June 1792.

==References==
{{Reflist|group=note}}
{{reflist}}
{{1911}}
{{French Revolution navbox}}
[[Category:1791 events of the French Revolution]]
[[Category:1792 events of the French Revolution]]
[[Category:Defunct unicameral legislatures|France 1791]]

[[cs:Zákonodárné národní shromáždění]]
[[de:Gesetzgebende Nationalversammlung]]
[[es:Asamblea Legislativa (Francia)]]
[[fr:Assemblée nationale législative (Révolution française)]]
[[gl:Asemblea Lexislativa (Francia)]]
[[ko:입법의회]]
[[io:Legifant asemblo (Francia)]]
[[it:Assemblea legislativa (Rivoluzione francese)]]
[[nl:Wetgevende Vergadering]]
[[ja:立法議会]]
[[pl:Legislatywa (1791)]]
[[pt:Assembleia Nacional Legislativa (Revolução Francesa)]]
[[ro:Adunarea Legislativă Franceză]]
[[ru:Законодательное собрание Франции (1791—1792)]]
[[uk:Законодавчі збори Франції (1791-1792)]]</text>
      <sha1>bjv59ipxotmie7gbahlhcs45o4kvrz9</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
