<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Liberty</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>936385</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521401024</id>
      <parentid>521381186</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-04T19:51:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>66.168.90.167</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20896">{{About|the political philosophy}}

{{Freedom}}
'''Liberty''' is the ability of individuals to have [[Agency (philosophy)|agency]] (control over their own actions). Different conceptions of liberty articulate the relationship of individuals to society in different ways—including some that relate to life under a ''[[social contract]]'' or to existence in a ''[[state of nature]]'', and some that see the active exercise of freedom and rights as essential to liberty.  Understanding liberty involves how we imagine the individual's roles and responsibilities in society in relation to concepts of [[free will]] and [[determinism]], which involves the larger domain of [[metaphysics]].

[[Individualism|Individualist]] and [[Classical liberalism|classical liberal]] conceptions of liberty typically consist of the freedom of individuals from outside compulsion or [[coercion]], also known as [[negative liberty]].  This conception of liberty, which coincides with the [[Libertarianism (metaphysics)|Libertarian]] point-of-view, suggests that people should, must, and ought to behave according to their own [[free will]], and take [[Moral responsibility|responsibility]] for their actions, while in contrast, [[Social liberalism|Social liberal]] conceptions of ([[positive liberty]]) liberty place an emphasis upon social [[structure and agency]] and is therefore directed toward ensuring [[egalitarianism]]. In feudal societies, a &quot;liberty&quot; was an area of [[allodial title|allodial]] land where the rights of the ruler or [[monarchy|monarch]] were waived.

==Philosophy==

{{Refimprove section|date=December 2009}}
Liberty is a historically controversial philosophy. One understanding of liberty asserts that freedom is found in a person's ability to exercise [[Agency (philosophy)|agency]], particularly in the sense of one having the freedom to choose what authorities one will submit to agency with in exchange for rights derived from that authority to develop resources to carry out their own will, without being inhibited; [[Social Contract]]. According to [[Thomas Hobbes]], for example, &quot;a free man is he that... is not hindered to do what he hath the will to do.&quot;

[[File:John-stuart-mill-sized.jpg|thumb|145px|right|[[John Stuart Mill]].]]

[[John Stuart Mill]], in his work, ''[[On Liberty]]'', was the first to recognize the difference between liberty as the freedom to act and liberty as the absence of coercion.&lt;ref&gt;Westbrooks, Logan Hart (2008) &quot;Personal Freedom&quot; [http://books.google.com/books?id=4gxaa371USUC&amp;pg=PA134 page 134] ''In'' Owens, William (compiler) (2008) ''Freedom: Keys to Freedom from Twenty-one National Leaders'' Main Street Publications, Memphis, Tennessee, pages 133–138, ISBN 978-0-9801152-0-8&lt;/ref&gt; In his book, ''[[Two Concepts of Liberty]]'', [[Isaiah Berlin]] formally framed the differences between these two perspectives as the distinction between two opposite concepts of liberty: [[positive liberty]] and [[negative liberty]]. The latter designates a negative condition in which an individual is protected from [[tyranny]] and the [[arbitrary]] exercise of [[authority]], while the former refers to having the means or opportunity, rather than the lack of restraint, to do things.

Mill offered insight into the notions of ''soft tyranny'' and ''[[mutual liberty]]'' with his ''[[harm principle]]''.&lt;ref&gt;John Stuart Mill, ''On Liberty and Utilitarianism'', (New York: Bantam Books, 1993), 12–16.&lt;/ref&gt; It can be seen as important to understand these concepts when discussing liberty since they all represent little pieces of the greater puzzle known as freedom. In a philosophical sense, it can be said that [[morality]] must supersede [[tyranny]] in any legitimate form of [[government]]. Otherwise, people are left with a societal [[system]] rooted in [[backwardness]], [[wikt:disorder|disorder]], and [[wikt:regression|regression]].

[[Image:Majestic Liberty Large.jpg|thumb|left|The [[Statue of Liberty]], donated to the US by France, an artistic personification of the concept.]]

The concept of negative liberty has several noteworthy aspects. First, negative liberty defines a realm or &quot;zone&quot; of freedom (in the &quot;silence of [[law]]&quot;). In Berlin's words, &quot;Liberty in the negative sense involves an answer to the question 'What is the area within which the subject—a person or group of persons—is or should be left to do or be what he is able to do or be, without interference by other persons.&quot; Some philosophers disagree on the extent of this realm, while accepting the main point that liberty defines the realm in which one may act unobstructed by others. Second, the restriction (on the freedom to act) implicit in negative liberty is imposed by a person or persons and not due to causes such as nature, lack, or incapacity. [[Claude Adrien Helvétius|Helvetius]] expresses this point clearly: &quot;The free man is the man who is not in irons, nor imprisoned in a gaol (jail), nor terrorized like a slave by the fear of punishment... it is not lack of freedom not to fly like an eagle or swim like a whale.&quot;

The dichotomy of positive and negative liberty is considered specious by political philosophers in traditions such as [[socialism]], [[social democracy]], [[libertarian socialism]], and [[Marxism]] {{citation needed|date=January 2012}}. Some of them argue that positive and negative liberty are indistinguishable in practice, while others claim that one kind of liberty cannot exist independently of the other. A common argument is that the preservation of negative liberty requires positive action on the part of the government or society to prevent some individuals from taking away the liberty of others.

==Freedom as a triadic relation==
In 1980, Gerald MacCallum argued that proponents of positive and negative liberty converge on a single definition of liberty, but simply have different approaches in establishing it. According to MacCallum, freedom is a triadic relationship: &quot;x is/is not free from y to do/not to do or become/not become z&quot;. In this way, rather than defining liberty in terms of two separate paradigms, positive and negative liberty, he defined liberty as a single, complete formula.

The question is whether this formula fully captures what positive liberty means. Positive liberty, understood as internal forces that determine how a person must act&quot;&lt;ref name=miller&gt;Miller, David, 'Introduction', in Miller, ed., Liberty, 1991&lt;/ref&gt; is saying more than 'x is free to do z.' One is free when one ''becomes'' the ideal of oneself, which includes MacCallum's triadic relation; but the latter alone is insufficient to fully capture what positive liberty means.{{Citation needed|date=May 2008}}

==Liberty and political thought==

===Concepts of liberty in history===
[[Image:Ama-gi.svg|right|thumb|Freedom (''[[ama-gi]]'') written in [[Sumerian language|Sumerian]] [[Cuneiform (script)|cuneiform]] ]]
The first known use of the word ''freedom'' in a political context dates back to the [[24th century BC]], in a text describing the restoration of social and economic liberty in [[Lagash]], a [[Sumer]]ian city-state. [[Urukagina]], the king of [[Lagash]], established the first known legal code to protect citizens from the rich and powerful. Known as a great reformer, Urukagina established laws that forbade compelling the sale of [[property]] and required the charges against the accused to be stated before any man accused of a crime could be punished. This is the first known example of any form of [[due process]] in the history of humanity.

Like Urukagina, most ancient freedoms focused on ''negative liberty'', protecting the less fortunate from harassment or imposition. Other ancient legal codes, such as the [[Code of Hammurabi]], similarly forbade compulsion in economic matters, like the sale of land, and made it clear that when a rich man murders a poor one, it is still murder.
Still, these codes depended on a certain virtuousness of kings and ministers, which was far from reliable.

The modern concept of liberty has its origins in the Greek concepts of freedom and slavery. To be free, to the Greeks, was to not have a master, to be independent from a master (to live like one likes).&lt;ref&gt;Mogens Herman Hansen, 2010, Democratic Freedom and the Concept of Freedom in Plato and Aristotle&lt;/ref&gt; That was the original Greek concept of freedom. It is closely linked with the concept of democracy, as Aristotle put it:

&quot;This, then, is one note of liberty which all democrats affirm to be the principle of their state. Another is that a man should live as he likes. This, they say, is the privilege of a freeman, since, on the other hand, not to live as a man likes is the mark of a slave. This is the second characteristic of democracy, whence has arisen the claim of men to be ruled by none, if possible, or, if this is impossible, to rule and be ruled in turns; and so it contributes to the freedom based upon equality.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Aristotle, Politics&lt;/ref&gt;

So to the Greeks democracy was the system of government of a free society.

The populations of the [[Persian Empire]] enjoyed some degree of freedom. Citizens of all [[religion]]s and [[ethnic group]]s were given the same rights and had the same [[freedom of religion]], women had the same rights as men, and [[slavery]] was abolished(550 BC).  All the palaces of the kings of Persia were built by paid workers in an era where slaves typically did such work.&lt;ref&gt;Arthur Henry Robertson, John Graham Merrills (1996). ''Human Rights in the World: An Introduction to the Study of the International Protection of Human Rights''. [[Manchester University Press]]. ISBN 0-7190-4923-7.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the Buddhist [[Maurya Empire]] of [[History of India|ancient India]], citizens of all religions and ethnic groups had some rights to [[Freedom (political)|freedom]], [[Toleration|tolerance]], and [[equality before the law|equality]]. The need for tolerance on an [[Egalitarianism|egalitarian]] basis can be found in the [[Edicts of Ashoka|Edicts]] of [[Ashoka the Great]], which emphasize the importance of tolerance in public policy by the government. The slaughter or capture of [[Prisoner of war|prisoners of war]] was also condemned by Ashoka.&lt;ref&gt;[[Amartya Sen]] (1997). ''Human Rights and Asian Values''. ISBN 0-87641-151-0.&lt;/ref&gt; Slavery was also non-existent in the Maurya Empire.&lt;ref&gt;[[Arrian]], ''[[Indica (Arrian)|Indica]]'':
&lt;br&gt;{{quote|&quot;This also is remarkable in [[History of India|India]], that all Indians are free, and no Indian at all is a slave. In this the Indians agree with the [[Lacedaemonian]]s. Yet the Lacedaemonians have [[Helot]]s for slaves, who perform the duties of slaves; but the Indians have no slaves at all, much less is any Indian a slave.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, according to Hermann Kulke and Dietmar Rothermund, &quot;Ashoka's orders seem to have been resisted right from the beginning.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Hermann Kulke, Dietmar Rothermund (2004). &quot;''[http://books.google.com/books?id=V73N8js5ZgAC&amp;pg=PA66&amp;dq&amp;hl=en#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false A history of India]''&quot;. Routledge. p.66. ISBN 0-415-32920-5&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Roman law]] also embraced certain limited forms of liberty, even under the rule of the Roman Emperors. However, these liberties were accorded only to [[Roman citizenship|Roman citizens]]. Still, the Roman citizen enjoyed a combination of positive liberty (the right to a trial, a right of appeal, law and contract enforcement) and negative liberty (unhindered right to contract and the right to not be tortured). Many of the liberties enjoyed under Roman law endured through the Middle Ages, but were enjoyed solely by the [[nobility]], never by the common man. The idea of unalienable and universal liberties had to wait until the Age of Enlightenment.

In [[Chinese language|Chinese]], freedom is written 自由(ziyou). 自(zi) is the character for self, and 由(you) is the character to follow, with an additional connotation of reason. Liberty thus implies a necessary connection between individualism and a rational duty.

===Social contract===
[[File:Eugène Delacroix - La liberté guidant le peuple.jpg|thumb|Right|[[Eugène Delacroix]] – ''La liberté guidant le peuple'' (1830)]]
[[Image:French-Liberty-British-Slavery-Gillray.jpeg|thumb|In ''French Liberty. British Slavery'' (1792), [[James Gillray]] caricatured French &quot;liberty&quot; as the opportunity to starve, and British &quot;slavery&quot; as bloated complaints about taxation.]]

The [[social contract]] theory, invented by [[Hobbes]], [[John Locke]] and [[Rousseau]], were among the first to provide a political classification of [[rights]], in particular through the notion of [[sovereignty]] and of [[natural rights]]. The thinkers of the [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]] [[logic|reasoned]] the assertion that [[law]] governed both heavenly and human affairs, and that law gave the [[monarch|king]] his power, rather than the king's power giving force to law. The [[divine right of kings]] was thus opposed to the [[sovereignty|sovereign]]'s unchecked ''[[auctoritas]]''. This conception of law would find its culmination in [[Montesquieu]]'s thought. The conception of law as a relationship between individuals, rather than families, came to the fore, and with it the increasing focus on [[individualism|individual liberty]] as a fundamental reality, given by &quot;[[Nature]] and [[God|Nature's God]],&quot; which, in the [[utopia|ideal state]], would be as expansive as possible. The Enlightenment created then, among other ideas, ''liberty'': that is, of a free individual being most free within the context of a state that provides stability of the laws.  Within the context of social liberty, in [[On Liberty]], [[John Stuart Mill]] sought to define the &quot;...nature and limits of the power which can be legitimately exercised by society over the individual,” and as such, he describes an inherent and continuous antagonism between liberty and authority and thus, the prevailing question becomes &quot;how to make the fitting adjustment between individual independence and social control&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Mill, J.S. (1869)., &quot;Chapter I: Introductory&quot;, On Liberty. {http://www.bartleby.com/130/1.html}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Modern perspectives===
The modern conceptions of [[Democracy (varieties)|democracy]], whether [[representative democracies]] or other types of democracies, are all found on the [[Jean-Jacques Rousseau|Rousseauist]] idea of [[popular sovereignty]].{{Or|date=September 2007}}

Liberalism is a [[politics|political]] current embracing several historical and present-day ideologies that claim defense in relation to external authority and coercion.  Within this context, there is sense the government has a responsibility to ensure individual liberty while at the same time improving the situation of those with the least advantage. In this sense, we can understand [[economic liberalism]] as the right of the individual to contract, trade and operate in a market free of constraint and [[social liberalism]] as the belief that liberalism should include social justice. Both are core political issues, and are highly contentious.&lt;ref&gt;Rawls, J. (1971). A Theory of Justice.  Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press., p. 13&lt;/ref&gt;

Article 3 of the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]] states that &quot;Everyone has the right to life, liberty, and security of person.&quot;

===United States===
In the United States Supreme Court decision [[Griswold v. Connecticut]], Justice [[William O. Douglas]] argued that liberties relating to personal relationships, such as marriage, have a unique primacy of place in the hierarchy of freedoms.&lt;ref&gt;GRISWOLD v. CONNECTICUT U.S. Supreme Court 381 U.S. 479 (1965) Decided June 7, 1965&lt;/ref&gt; Jacob M. Appel has summarized this principle:
{{quote|I am grateful that I have rights in the proverbial public square – but, as a practical matter, my most cherished rights are those that I possess in my bedroom and hospital room and death chamber. Most people are far more concerned that they can control their own bodies than they are about petitioning Congress.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.huffingtonpost.com/jacob-m-appel/a-culture-of-liberty_b_242402.html A Culture of Liberty]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

A school of thought popular among U.S. [[libertarians]] holds that there is no tenable distinction between the two sorts of liberty – that they are, indeed, one and the same, to be protected (or opposed) together. In the context of U.S. [[constitutional law]], for example, they point out that the constitution twice lists &quot;life, liberty, and property&quot; without making any distinctions within that troika.

[[Anarcho-individualism|Anarcho-Individualists]], such as [[Max Stirner]], demanded the utmost respect for the liberty of the individual. Some in the U.S. see protecting the ideal of liberty as a [[Conservatism|conservative]] policy, because this would conform to the spirit of individual liberty that they consider is at the heart of the American constitution. Some think liberty is almost synonymous with [[democracy]], at least in one sense of that word, while others see conflicts or even opposition between the two concepts, with democracy being nothing more than the tyranny of the majority.{{Citation needed|date=February 2008}}

===Republican liberty===
According to republican theorists of freedom, like the historian [[Quentin Skinner]] or the philosopher [[Philip Pettit]], one's liberty should not be viewed as the absence of interference in one's actions, but as non-dependence. According to this view, that originates in the Roman [[Digest (Roman law)|Digest]], to be a ''liber homo'', a free man, means being in a state of non-dependence from another's arbitrary will. The second step of the argument of these neo-Roman writers, like [[Machiavelli]], was that you have to be a member of a free self-governing civil association, a republic, if you are to enjoy individual liberty.

The predominance of this view of liberty among parliamentarians during the [[English Civil War]] resulted to the creation of the liberal concept of freedom as non-interference in Thomas Hobbes's [[Leviathan (book)|Leviathan]].

==Historical writings on liberty==
*{{Cite book | publisher = Awnsham Churchill | author = [[John Locke]] | title = [[Two Treatises of Government]]: In the Former, the False Principles, and Foundation of Sir Robert Filmer, and His Followers, Are Detected and Overthrown. the Latter Is an Essay Concerning the True Original, Extent, and End of Civil Government. | location = London | year = 1689 }}
*{{Cite book | publisher = Guillaumin &amp; Co | last = [[Frédéric Bastiat]] | title = [[The Law (1850 book)|The Law]] | location = Paris | year = 1850 }}
*{{Cite book | publisher = John W Parker and Son | author = [[John Stuart Mill]] | title = [[On Liberty]] | location = London | year = 1859 }}
* {{Cite book | publisher = Smith, Elder, &amp; Co. | author = [[James Fitzjames Stephen]] | title = Liberty, Equality, Fraternity | location = London | year = 1874 | url= http://oll.libertyfund.org/?option=com_staticxt&amp;staticfile=show.php%3Ftitle=572 }}

==See also==
&lt;div style=&quot;column-count:2;-moz-column-count:2;-webkit-column-count:2&quot;&gt;
* [[Civil liberty]]
* [[Constitution]]
* [[Constitutional economics]]
* [[Freedom (philosophy)]]
* [[Freedom (political)]]
* [[Gratis versus Libre]]
* [[Libertarian Party (disambiguation)]]
* [[Liberté, égalité, fraternité]]
* [[List of freedom indices]]
* [[Rule according to higher law]]
* [[Social liberty]]
* [[National Council for Civil Liberties|Liberty]] (formerly the National Council for Civil Liberties, of the United Kingdom)

&lt;/div&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Articles of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights}}
{{Particular human rights}}

[[Category:Social concepts]]
[[Category:Liberty symbols]]
[[Category:Political concepts]]

[[af:Vryheid]]
[[am:አርነት]]
[[ar:حرية]]
[[arc:ܚܐܪܘܬܐ]]
[[ast:Llibertá]]
[[ay:Atiniña]]
[[az:Azadlıq]]
[[bm:Hɔrɔnya]]
[[be:Свабода]]
[[be-x-old:Свабода]]
[[bg:Свобода]]
[[bo:རང་དབང་།]]
[[bs:Sloboda]]
[[ca:Llibertat]]
[[cs:Svoboda]]
[[da:Frihed]]
[[de:Freiheit]]
[[et:Vabadus]]
[[el:Ελευθερία]]
[[es:Libertad]]
[[eo:Libereco]]
[[eu:Askatasun]]
[[fa:آزادی]]
[[fr:Liberté]]
[[gl:Liberdade]]
[[ko:자유]]
[[hr:Sloboda]]
[[it:Libertà]]
[[he:חופש]]
[[kk:Бостандық]]
[[la:Libertas]]
[[lv:Brīvība]]
[[lt:Laisvė]]
[[hu:Szabadság (filozófia)]]
[[ms:Kebebasan]]
[[cdo:Cê̤ṳ-iù]]
[[nl:Vrijheid (filosofie)]]
[[ja:自由]]
[[no:Frihet]]
[[nn:Fridom]]
[[oc:Libertat (filosofia)]]
[[pl:Wolność]]
[[pt:Liberdade]]
[[ro:Libertate (filozofie)]]
[[qu:Qispi kay]]
[[ru:Свобода]]
[[sq:Liria]]
[[scn:Libbirtati]]
[[simple:Freedom]]
[[sk:Sloboda]]
[[sr:Слобода]]
[[sh:Sloboda]]
[[fi:Vapaus]]
[[sv:Frihet]]
[[th:เสรีภาพ]]
[[tg:Озодӣ]]
[[tr:Özgürlük]]
[[uk:Свобода]]
[[ur:حریت]]
[[fiu-vro:Vabahus]]
[[yi:פריי]]
[[zh:自由]]</text>
      <sha1>dltyohwbra37400jtqxtpfxr8zmxqjv</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
