<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Libertarian Marxism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3661758</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521798143</id>
      <parentid>521011213</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-07T08:57:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Snotbot</username>
        <id>13752234</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Fixing section headings [[Wikipedia:Bots/Requests for approval/Snotbot 5|(task 5)]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="29922">{{Left communism sidebar}}
{{Marxism}}
{{Libertarian socialism}}
'''Libertarian Marxism''' refers to a broad scope of economic and political philosophies that emphasize the [[anti-authoritarian]] aspects of [[Marxism]]. Early currents of libertarian Marxism, known as [[left communism]],&lt;ref&gt;Pierce, Wayne.[http://www.utopianmag.com/files/in/1000000034/12___WayneLibMarx.pdf &quot;Libertarian Marxism's Relation to Anarchism&quot;] &quot;The Utopian&quot; 73-80.&lt;/ref&gt; emerged in opposition to [[Marxism–Leninism]]&lt;ref&gt;[[Herman Gorter]], [[Anton Pannekoek]], [[Sylvia Pankhurst]], Otto Ruhl ''Non-Leninist Marxism: Writings on the Workers Councils''. Red and Black, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; and its derivatives, such as [[Stalinism]], [[Maoism]], and [[Trotskyism]].&lt;ref&gt;Marot, Eric. [http://libcom.org/library/trotsky-left-opposition-rise-stalinism-theory-practice-john-eric-marot &quot;Trotsky, the Left Opposition and the Rise of Stalinism: Theory and Practice&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; Libertarian Marxism is also critical of [[reformist]] positions, such as those held by [[social democrats]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://libcom.org/library/social-democracy-1-aufheben-8 &quot;The Retreat of Social Democracy ... Re-imposition of Work in Britain and the 'Social Europe'&quot;] &quot;Aufheben&quot; Issue #8 1999.&lt;/ref&gt; Libertarian Marxist currents often draw from Marx and Engels' later works, specifically the ''[[Grundrisse]]'' and ''[[The Civil War in France]]'';&lt;ref&gt;Ernesto Screpanti, Libertarian communism: Marx Engels and the Political Economy of Freedom, Palgrave Macmillan, London, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; emphasizing the Marxist belief in the ability of the [[working class]] to forge its own destiny without the need for a revolutionary party or [[State (polity)|state]] to mediate or aid its liberation.&lt;ref&gt;Draper, Hal. [https://jps.library.utoronto.ca/index.php/srv/article/view/5333&quot;The Principle of Self-Emancipation in Marx and Engels&quot;] &quot;The Socialist Register.&quot; Vol 4.&lt;/ref&gt; Along with [[anarchism]], Libertarian Marxism is one of the main currents of [[libertarian socialism]].&lt;ref&gt;Chomsky, Noam. [http://chomsky.info/audionvideo/19700216.mp3 &quot;Government In The Future&quot;] Poetry Center of the New York YM-YWHA. Lecture.&lt;/ref&gt;

Libertarian Marxism includes such currents as [[council communism]], [[left communism]], ''[[Socialisme ou Barbarie]]'' [[Lettrism]]/[[Situationist International|Situationism]] and  [[operaismo]]/[[autonomism]], and [[New Left]].&lt;ref&gt;http://libcom.org/library/libertarian-marxist-tendency-map&lt;/ref&gt; Libertarian Marxism has often had a strong influence on both [[Post-left anarchism|post-left]] and [[Social anarchism|social anarchists]]. Notable theorists of libertarian Marxism have included [[Anton Pannekoek]], [[Raya Dunayevskaya]], [[CLR James]], [[Antonio Negri]], [[Cornelius Castoriadis]], [[Maurice Brinton]], [[Guy Debord]], [[Daniel Guérin]], [[Ernesto Screpanti]], and [[Raoul Vaneigem]].

== Overview ==
[[File:William Morris age 53.jpg|200px|right|thumb|[[William Morris]], early English libertarian Marxist]]Marxism started to develop a libertarian strand of thought after specific circumstances. &quot;One does find early expressions of such perspectives in [[William Morris|(William) Morris]] and the [[Socialist Party of Great Britain]] (the SPGB), then again around the events of 1905, with the growing concern at the bureaucratisation and de-radicalisation of international socialism&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;'Advance Without Authority'&quot;&gt;&quot;The [http://www.democracynature.org/dn/vol7/ojeili_intellectuals.htm 'Advance Without Authority']: Post-modernism, Libertarian Socialism and Intellectuals&quot; by Chamsy Ojeili, ''[[Democracy &amp; Nature]]'' vol.7, no.3, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt; Morris established the [[Socialist League (UK, 1885)|Socialist League]] in December 1884, which was encouraged by [[Friedrich Engels]] and [[Eleanor Marx]]. As the leading figure in the organization Morris embarked on a relentless series of speeches and talks on street corners, in working men's clubs and lecture theatres across England and Scotland. From 1887, [[anarchism|anarchists]] began to outnumber socialists in the Socialist League.&lt;ref name=&quot;Beer, pg. 256&quot;&gt;Beer, ''A History of British Socialism,'' vol. 2, pg. 256.&lt;/ref&gt; The 3rd Annual Conference of the League, held in London on 29 May 1887 marked the change, with a majority of the 24 branch delegates voting in favor of an anarchist-sponsored resolution declaring that &quot;This conference endorses the policy of abstention from parliamentary action, hitherto pursued by the League, and sees no sufficient reason for altering it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Marx-Engels Collected Works: Volume 48.'' New York: International Publishers, 2001; pg. 538, fn. 95.&lt;/ref&gt;  Morris played peacemaker but sided with the anti-Parliamentarians, who won control of the League, which consequently lost the support of Engels and saw the departure of Eleanor Marx and her partner [[Edward Aveling]] to form the separate [[Socialist League (UK, 1885)#Anarchist control|Bloomsbury Socialist Society]].

However, &quot;the most important ruptures are to be traced to the insurgency during and after the First World War. Disillusioned with the capitulation of the social democrats, excited by the emergence of workers’ councils, and slowly distanced from Leninism, many communists came to reject the claims of socialist parties and to put their faith instead in the masses.&quot; For these socialists, “The intuition of the masses in action can have more genius in it than the work of the greatest individual genius”. Luxemburg’s workerism and spontaneism are exemplary of positions later taken up by the far-left of the period – [[Anton Pannekoek|Pannekoek]], Roland Holst, and [[Herman Gorter|Gorter]] in Holland, [[Sylvia Pankhurst]] in Britain, Gramsci in Italy, Lukacs in Hungary. In these formulations, the dictatorship of the proletariat was to be the dictatorship of a class, “not of a party or of a clique”.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;'Advance Without Authority'&quot;/&gt; However within this line of thought &quot;The tension between anti-vanguardism and vanguardism has frequently resolved itself in two diametrically opposed ways: the first involved a drift towards the party; the second saw a move towards the idea of complete proletarian spontaneity...The first course is exemplified most clearly in Gramsci and Lukacs...The second course is illustrated in the tendency, developing from the Dutch and German far-lefts, which inclined towards the complete eradication of the party form.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;'Advance Without Authority'&quot;/&gt;

For &quot;many Marxian libertarian socialists, the political bankruptcy of socialist orthodoxy necessitated a theoretical break. This break took a number of forms. The [[Bordigists]] and the SPGB championed a super-Marxian intransigence in theoretical matters. Other socialists made a return “behind Marx” to the [[anti-positivist]] programme of [[German idealism]]. Libertarian socialism has frequently linked its anti-authoritarian political aspirations with this theoretical differentiation from orthodoxy...[[Karl Korsch]]...remained a libertarian socialist for a large part of his life and because of the persistent urge towards theoretical openness in his work. Korsch rejected the eternal and static, and he was obsessed by the essential role of  practice in a theory’s truth. For Korsch, no theory could escape history, not even Marxism. In this vein, Korsch even credited the stimulus for Marx’s Capital to the movement of the oppressed classes. &quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;'Advance Without Authority'&quot;/&gt;

In rejecting both capitalism and the state, some libertarian socialists align themselves with anarchists in opposition to both capitalist [[representative democracy]] and to authoritarian forms of [[Marxism]]. Although anarchists and Marxists share an ultimate goal of a stateless society, anarchists criticise most Marxists for advocating a transitional phase under which the state is used to achieve this aim. Nonetheless, libertarian Marxist tendencies such as [[autonomist Marxism]] and [[council communism]] have historically been intertwined with the anarchist movement.

Anarchist movements have come into conflict with both capitalist and Marxist forces, sometimes at the same time, as in the [[Spanish Civil War]], though as in that war Marxists themselves are often divided in support or opposition to anarchism. Other political persecutions under [[Bureaucracy|bureaucratic]] parties have resulted in a strong historical antagonism between anarchists and libertarian Marxists on the one hand and [[Leninism|Leninist]] Marxists and their derivatives such as [[Maoism|Maoists]] on the other. In recent history, however, libertarian socialists have repeatedly formed temporary alliances with Marxist-Leninist groups for the purposes of protest against institutions they both reject.

Part of this antagonism can be traced to the [[International Workingmen's Association]], the ''[[First International]]'', a congress of [[Radicalism (historical)|radical]] workers, where [[Mikhail Bakunin]], who was fairly representative of anarchist views, and [[Karl Marx]], whom anarchists accused of being an &quot;authoritarian&quot;, came into conflict on various issues. Bakunin's viewpoint on the illegitimacy of the state as an institution and the role of [[electoral politics]] was starkly counterposed to Marx's views in the First International. Marx and Bakunin's disputes eventually led to Marx taking control of the First International and expelling Bakunin and his followers from the organization. This was the beginning of a long-running feud and schism between libertarian socialists and what they call &quot;authoritarian communists&quot;, or alternatively just &quot;authoritarians&quot;.

Some Marxists have formulated views that closely resemble [[syndicalism]], and thus express more affinity with anarchist ideas. Several libertarian socialists, notably Noam Chomsky, believe that anarchism shares much in common with certain variants of Marxism such as the [[council communism]] of Marxist [[Anton Pannekoek]]. In Chomsky's ''[[Notes on Anarchism]]'',&lt;ref&gt;Noam Chomsky [http://www.chomsky.info/articles/1970----.htm Notes on Anarchism]&lt;/ref&gt; he suggests the possibility &quot;that some form of council communism is the natural form of [[revolutionary socialism]] in an [[industrialization|industrial]] society. It reflects the belief that democracy is severely limited when the industrial system is controlled by any form of autocratic elite, whether of owners, managers, and technocrats, a '[[Vanguard party|vanguard' party]], or a State bureaucracy.&quot;

In 1969 French [[platformist]] anarcho-communist [[Daniel Guerin]] published an essay called &quot;Libertarian Marxism?&quot; in which he dealt with the debate between [[Karl Marx]] and [[Mikhail Bakunin]] at the [[First International]] and afterwards he suggested that &quot;Libertarian marxism rejects determinism and fatalism, giving the greator place to individual will, intuition, imagination, reflex speeds, and to the deep instincts of the masses, which are more far-seeing in hours of crisis than the reasonings of the ‘elites’; libertarian marxism thinks of the effects of surprise, provocation and boldness, refuses to be cluttered and paralysed by a heavy ‘scientific’ apparatus, doesn’t equivocate or bluff, and guards itself from adventurism as much as from fear of the unknown.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://theanarchistlibrary.org/HTML/Daniel_Guerin__Libertarian_Marxism_.html Libertarian Marxism? by [[Daniel Guerin]]]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Autonomist Marxism]], [[Neo-Marxism]], and [[Situationist International|Situationist theory]] are also regarded as being [[anti-authoritarian]] variants of Marxism that are firmly within the libertarian socialist tradition.

==Notable libertarian marxist tendencies==

===Council communism===

{{Main|Council Communism}}
Council communism was a radical [[left-wing politics|Left]] movement originating in Germany and the Netherlands in the 1920s. Its primary organization was the [[Communist Workers Party of Germany]] (KAPD). Council communism continues today as a theoretical and [[activist]] position within [[Marxism]], and also within libertarian socialism. The central argument of council communism, in contrast to those of [[Social democracy]] and [[Leninism|Leninist]] [[communism]], is that [[workers' councils]] arising in the factories and municipalities are the natural and legitimate form of [[working class]] organisation and government power. This view is opposed to the [[reformist]] and [[Bolshevik]] stress on [[Vanguard party|vanguard parties]], [[parliament]]s, or the [[State (polity)|state]].
[[File:Antonie Pannekoek.jpg|200px|left|thumb|[[Antonie Pannekoek]], theorist of [[council communism]]]]
The core principle of council communism is that the state and the economy should be managed by [[workers' councils]], composed of delegates elected at workplaces and recallable at any moment. As such, council communists oppose state-run &quot;bureaucratic socialism&quot;. They also oppose the idea of a &quot;revolutionary party&quot;, since council communists believe that a revolution led by a party will necessarily produce a party [[dictatorship]]. Council communists support a workers' democracy, which they want to produce through a federation of workers' councils.

The [[Russian language|Russian]] word for council is &quot;[[Soviet (council)|soviet]]&quot;, and during the early years of the revolution worker's councils were politically significant in Russia. It was to take advantage of the [[Aura (paranormal)|aura]] of workplace power that the word became used by [[Lenin]] for various political organs. Indeed, the name &quot;[[Supreme Soviet]]&quot;, by which the parliament was called; and that of the Soviet Union itself make use of this terminology, but they do not imply any [[decentralization]].

Furthermore, council communists held a critique of the Soviet Union as a capitalist state, believing that the [[Bolshevik]] revolution in Russia became a &quot;[[bourgeois]] revolution&quot; when a party bureaucracy replaced the old [[feudal]] [[aristocracy]]. Although most felt the [[October Revolution|Russian Revolution]] was working class in character, they believed that, since capitalist relations still existed (because the workers had no say in running the economy), the Soviet Union ended up as a [[state capitalist]] country, with the state replacing the individual capitalist. Thus, council communists support workers' revolutions, but oppose one-party dictatorships.

Council communists also believed in diminishing the role of the party to one of [[agitprop|agitation]] and [[propaganda]], rejected all participation in [[elections]] or parliament, and argued that workers should leave the reactionary trade unions and form one big revolutionary union.

===Left communism===

{{Main|Left communism}}
Left communism' is the range of [[Communism|communist]] viewpoints held by the communist left, which criticizes the political ideas of the [[Bolsheviks]] at certain periods, from a position that is asserted to be more authentically [[Marxism|Marxist]] and [[Proletariat|proletarian]] than the views of [[Leninism]] held by the [[Communist International]] after its first and during its second congress.

Left Communists see themselves to the left of [[Leninism|Leninists]] (whom they tend to see as 'left of capital', not socialists), [[Anarchist Communism|Anarchists]] (some of whom they consider internationalist socialists) as well as some other revolutionary socialist tendencies (for example [[De Leonism|De Leonists]], who they tend to see as being internationalist socialists only in limited instances).
{{Left communism sidebar}}
Although she lived before left communism became a distinct tendency, [[Rosa Luxemburg]] has heavily influenced most left communists, both politically and theoretically. Proponents of left communism have included [[Amadeo Bordiga]], [[Herman Gorter]], [[Anton Pannekoek]], [[Otto Rühle]], [[Karl Korsch]], [[Sylvia Pankhurst]], and [[Paul Mattick]].

Prominent [[list of left communist internationals|left communist groups existing today]] include the [[International Communist Current]] and the [[International Bureau for the Revolutionary Party]]. Also, different factions from the old Bordigist [[International Communist Party]] are considered left communist organizations.

===''Socialisme ou Barbarie''===
{{Main|Socialisme ou Barbarie}}
''Socialisme ou Barbarie'' (Socialism or Barbarism) was a French-based radical [[libertarian socialist]] group of the post-[[World War II]] period (the name comes from a phrase [[Rosa Luxemburg]] used in a 1916 essay, 'The Junius Pamphlet'). It existed from 1948 until 1965. The animating personality was [[Cornelius Castoriadis]], also known as Pierre Chaulieu or Paul Cardan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author=Dick Howard | title=Introduction to Castoriadis | journal=Telos | year=1975 | issue=23 | page=118}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Situationist International===
{{Main|Situationist International}}
The Situationist International was a restricted group of international revolutionaries founded in 1957, and which had its peak in its influence on the unprecedented [[general strike|general]] [[wildcat strikes]] of [[May 1968 in France]].

With their ideas rooted in Marxism and the 20th century European artistic [[avant-garde]]s, they advocated experiences of life being alternative to those admitted by the [[capitalism|capitalist order]], for the fulfillment of human primitive desires and the pursuing of a superior passional quality. For this purpose they suggested and experimented with the ''construction of situations'', namely the setting up of environments favorable for the fulfillment of such desires. Using methods drawn from the arts, they developed a series of experimental fields of study for the construction of such situations, like [[unitary urbanism]] and [[psychogeography]].
{{Situationists}}
They fought against the main obstacle on the fulfillment of such superior passional living, identified by them in [[advanced capitalism]]. Their theoretical work peaked on the highly influential book ''[[The Society of the Spectacle]]'' by [[Guy Debord]]. Debord argued in 1967 that spectacular features like mass media and advertising have a central role in an advanced capitalist society, which is to show a fake reality in order to mask the real capitalist degradation of human life. To overthrow such a system, the Situationist International supported the May '68 revolts, and asked the workers to [[Council for Maintaining the Occupations|occupy the factories]] and to run them with [[direct democracy]], through [[workers' councils]] composed by instantly revocable delegates.

After publishing in the last issue of the magazine an analysis of the May 1968 revolts, and the strategies that will need to be adopted in future revolutions,&lt;ref name=&quot;SI12BeginningOfAnEra&quot;&gt;''The Beginning of an Era'' ([http://www.bopsecrets.org/SI/12.era1.htm part1], [http://www.bopsecrets.org/SI/12.era2.htm part 2]) Situationist International #12, 1969&lt;/ref&gt; the SI was dissolved in 1972.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Situationism in a nutshell | author=Karen Elliot | url=http://www.barbelith.com/cgi-bin/articles/00000011.shtml | publisher=Barbelith Webzine | date=2001-06-01 | accessdate=2008-06-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== ''Solidarity'' ===
{{Main|Solidarity (UK)}}
''Solidarity'' was a small [[libertarian socialist]] organisation from 1960 to 1992  in the [[United Kingdom]]. It published a magazine of the same name. Solidarity was close to [[council communism]] in its prescriptions and was known for its emphasis on workers' self-organisation and for its radical [[anti-Leninism]]. Solidarity was founded in 1960 by a small group of expelled members of the [[Trotskyist]] [[Socialist Labour League]]. It was initially known as ''Socialism Reaffirmed''.  The group published a journal, ''Agitator'', which after six issues was renamed ''Solidarity'', from which the organisation took its new name. Almost from the start it was strongly influenced by the French [[Socialisme ou Barbarie]] group, in particular by its intellectual leader [[Cornelius Castoriadis]], whose essays were among the many pamphlets Solidarity produced. Solidarity existed as a nationwide organisation with groups in [[London]] and many other cities until 1981, when it imploded after a series of political disputes. ''Solidarity'' the magazine continued to be published by the London group until 1992; other former Solidarity members were behind ''Wildcat'' in [[Manchester]] and ''Here and Now'' magazine in [[Glasgow]]. The intellectual leader of the group was Chris Pallis, whose pamphlets  (written under the name [[Maurice Brinton]]) included ''Paris May 1968'', [http://libcom.org/library/the-bolsheviks-and-workers-control-solidarity-group The Bolsheviks and Workers' Control 1917-21] and [http://libcom.org/library/Irrational-in-politics-Maurice-Brinton 'The Irrational in Politics'].&lt;ref&gt;(now collected in a book, Maurice Brinton, ''For Workers' Power'')&lt;/ref&gt; Other key Solidarity writers were [[Andy Anderson (Solidarity UK)|Andy Anderson]]  (author of [http://libcom.org/library/hungary-56-andy-anderson Hungary 1956]), [[Ken Weller]] (who wrote several pamphlets on industrial struggles and oversaw the group's Motor Bulletins on the car industry), [[Joe Jacobs (Solidarity)|Joe Jacobs]] (''Out of the Ghetto''), [[John Quail]] (''The Slow-Burning Fuse''), [[Phil Mailer]] (''Portugal:The Impossible Revolution'') [[John King (Solidarity UK)|John King]] (''The Political Economy of Marx'', ''A History of Marxian Economics''), George Williamson (writing as James Finlayson, ''Urban Devastation -  The Planning of Incarceration''), [David Lamb] (''Mutinies'') and [[Liz Willis]] (''Women in the Spanish Revolution'').

===De Leonism===
{{Main|De Leonism}}
De Leonism, occasionally known as Marxism-Deleonism, is a form of [[syndicalist]] [[Marxism]] developed by [[Daniel De Leon]]. De Leon was an early leader of the first United States socialist political party, the [[Socialist Labor Party of America]]. De Leon combined the rising theories of syndicalism in his time with [[orthodox Marxism]]. According to De Leonist theory, militant [[industrial unions]] (specialized [[trade unions]]) are the vehicle of [[class struggle]]. Industrial Unions serving the interests of the [[proletariat]] will bring about the change needed to establish a socialist system. The only way this differs from some currents in [[anarcho-syndicalism]] is that, according to De Leonist thinking, a revolutionary political party is also necessary to fight for the proletariat on the political field.

De Leonism lies outside the [[Leninist]] tradition of communism. It predates Leninism as De Leonism's principles developed in the early 1890s with De Leon's assuming leadership of the [[Socialist Labor Party]]; Leninism and its [[vanguard party]] idea took shape after the 1902 publication of Lenin's [[What Is to Be Done?]].
The highly [[decentralized]] and [[democratic]] nature of the proposed De Leonist government is in contrast to the [[democratic centralism]] of [[Marxism–Leninism]] and what they see as the [[dictatorial]] nature of the Soviet Union and the People's Republic of China and other &quot;communist&quot; states. The success of the De Leonist plan depends on achieving majority support among the people both in the workplaces and at the polls, in contrast to the Leninist notion that a small vanguard party should lead the working class to carry out the revolution.

===Autonomism===
{{Main|Autonomism}}
[[File:AntonioNegri SeminarioInternacionalMundo.jpg|upright|thumb|left|[[Antonio Negri]], main theorist of Italian autonomism]]Autonomism refers to a set of left-wing political and social movements and theories close to the socialist movement. As an identifiable theoretical system it first emerged in [[History of Italy as a Republic|Italy in the 1960s]] from [[workerist]] (''[[operaismo]]'') communism. Later, post-Marxist and anarchist tendencies became significant after influence from the [[Situationist International|Situationists]], the failure of Italian far-left movements in the 1970s, and the emergence of a number of important theorists including [[Antonio Negri]], who had contributed to the 1969 founding of ''[[Potere Operaio]]'', Mario Tronti, [[Paolo Virno]], etc.

Through translations made available by Danilo Montaldi and others, the Italian autonomists drew upon previous activist research in the United States by the [[Johnson–Forest Tendency]] and in France by the group [[Socialisme ou Barbarie]].

It influenced the German and Dutch Autonomen, the worldwide [[Social Centre movement]], and today is influential in Italy, France, and to a lesser extent the English-speaking countries. Those who describe themselves as autonomists now vary from Marxists to [[post-structuralism|post-structuralists]] and anarchists. The Autonomist Marxist and ''Autonomen'' movements provided inspiration to some on the revolutionary left in English speaking countries, particularly among anarchists, many of whom have adopted autonomist tactics. Some English-speaking anarchists even describe themselves as ''Autonomists''. The Italian ''operaismo'' movement also influenced Marxist academics such as [[Harry Cleaver]], [[John Holloway (economist)|John Holloway]], Steve Wright, and [[Nick Dyer-Witheford]].

=== Communization ===
{{Main|Communization}}
Communization mainly refers to a contemporary [[communist]] theory in which we find is a &quot;mixing-up of [[insurrectionist anarchism]], the [[Left communism|communist ultra-left]], post[[Autonomism|autonomists]], anti-political currents, groups like [[The Coming Insurrection|the Invisible Committee]], as well as more explicitly ‘communizing’ currents, such as ''Théorie Communiste'' and ''Endnotes''. Obviously at the heart of the word is communism and, as the shift to communization suggests, communism as a particular activity and process...&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Benjamin Noys (ed). [http://www.minorcompositions.info/?p=299 ''Communization and its Discontents: Contestation, Critique, and Contemporary Struggles.''] Minor Compositions, [[Autonomedia]]. 2011. 1st ed.&lt;/ref&gt;

The association of the term communization with a self-identified &quot;[[ultra-left]]&quot; was cemented in France in the 1970s, where it came to describe not a transition to a higher phase of communism but a vision of communist revolution itself. Thus the 1975 Pamphlet ''A World Without Money'' states: “insurrection and communisation are intimately linked. There would not be first a period of insurrection and then later, thanks to this insurrection, the transformation of social reality. The insurrectional process derives its force from communisation itself.”&lt;ref&gt;[http://libcom.org/library/world-without-money-les-amis-de-4-millions-de-jeunes-travailleurs &quot;A World Without Money&quot;] by Les amis de 4 millions de jeunes travailleurs. (quoted passage not included in this English extract)&lt;/ref&gt;

The term is still used in this sense in France today and has spread into English usage as a result of the translation of texts by [[Gilles Dauvé]] and ''Théorie Comuniste'', two key figures in this tendency. But in the late 1990s a close but not identical sense of &quot;communization&quot; was developed by the French post-situationist group [[Tiqqun]]. In keeping with their ultra-left predecessors, Tiqqun's predilection for the term seems to be its emphasis on communism as an immediate process rather than a far-off goal, but for Tiqqun it is no longer synonymous with &quot;the revolution&quot; considered as an historical event, but rather becomes identifiable with all sorts of activities – from squatting and setting up communes to simply &quot;sharing&quot; – that would typically be understood as &quot;pre-revolutionary&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;As we apprehend it, the process of instituting communism can only take the form of a collection of acts of ''communisation'', of making common such-and-such space, such-and-such machine, such-and-such knowledge. That is to say, the elaboration of the mode of sharing that attaches to them. Insurrection itself is just an accelerator, a decisive moment in this process.&quot; Anonymous, [http://www.bloom0101.org/call.pdf ''Call'']&lt;/ref&gt; From an ultra-left perspective such a politics of &quot;dropping-out&quot; or, as Tiqqun put it, &quot;desertion&quot; — setting up spaces and practices that are held to partially autonomous from capitalism — is typically dismissed as either naive or reactionary.&lt;ref&gt;For a critique of Tiqqun from an ultra-left perspective, as well as a description of the opposition between the two sense of &quot;communization&quot; see &quot;[http://libcom.org/library/reflexions-around-call Reflexions Around Call]&quot; Letters Journal #3. See also Dauvé and Nesic, [http://troploin0.free.fr/ii/index.php/textes/19-communisation-un-appel-et-une-invite &quot;Un Appel et une Invite&quot;].&lt;/ref&gt; Due to the popularity of the Tiqqun-related works ''Call'' and ''[[The Coming Insurrection]]'' in US [[anarchist]] circles it tended to be this latter sense of &quot;communization&quot; that was employed in US anarchist and &quot;[[insurrectionist]]&quot; communiques, notably within the [[2009 California college tuition hike protests|Californian student movement of 2009–2010]].&lt;ref&gt;See e.g. [http://afterthefallcommuniques.info/ &quot;After the Fall: Communiqués from Occupied California&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Libertarian socialism]]
* [[Marxist humanism]]
* [[Neo-Marxism]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://libcom.org/library Libertarian Communist Library]
** [http://libcom.org/library/libertarian-marxist-tendency-map A libertarian Marxist tendency map]
* [http://www.cddc.vt.edu/sionline/index.html Situationist International online]

[[Category:Communism]]
[[Category:Left communism]]
[[Category:Libertarian socialism]]
[[Category:Marxism]]
[[Category:Situationist International]]

[[ca:Marxisme llibertari]]
[[es:Marxismo libertario]]
[[fr:Marxisme libertaire]]
[[gl:Marxismo libertario]]
[[pt:Marxismo libertário]]
[[sv:Frihetlig marxism]]</text>
      <sha1>goj6b4da9b70h67419efa37zfhhc3ba</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
