<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Liberation theology</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>37349</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520988566</id>
      <parentid>519646982</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T01:32:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Saxophilist</username>
        <id>16393978</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Church is capitalized</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="33101">{{Multiple issues
 | criticisms=September 2010
 | external links=August 2010
|incomplete = March 2012}}
&lt;!--You cant mention this without the Roman Catholics Lugo, Aristide and Romero--&gt;
{{Social Christianity}}

'''Liberation theology'''&lt;ref&gt;Hamford .In the mass media, 'Liberation Theology' can sometimes be used loosely, to refer to a wide variety of activist [[Roman Catholic]] Christian thought. In this article the term will be used in the narrow sense outlined here.&lt;/ref&gt; is a [[political movement]] in [[Christian theology]] which interprets the teachings of [[Jesus Christ]] in terms of a liberation from unjust economic, political, or social conditions. It has been described by proponents as &quot;an interpretation of Christian faith through the poor's suffering, their struggle and hope, and a critique of society and the Catholic faith and Christianity through the eyes of the poor&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[[Phillip Berryman|Berryman, Phillip]], ''Liberation Theology: essential facts about the revolutionary movement in Latin America and beyond''(1987)&lt;/ref&gt; and by detractors as Christianized [[Marxism]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[David] Horowitz first describes liberation theology as 'a form of Marxised Christianity,' which has validity despite the awkward phrasing, but then he calls it a form of 'Marxist–Leninist ideology,' which is simply not true for most liberation theology...&quot; Robert Shaffer, &quot;[http://www.oah.org/pubs/nl/2007nov/shaffer.html Acceptable Bounds of Academic Discourse],&quot; Organization of American Historians Newsletter 35, November, 2007. URL retrieved 12 July 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although liberation theology has grown into an international and inter-denominational movement, it began as a movement within the [[Catholic Church]] in Latin America in the 1950s–1960s. Liberation theology arose principally as a moral reaction to the poverty caused by [[social injustice]] in that region. The term was coined in 1971 by the [[Peruvian]] priest [[Gustavo Gutiérrez]], who wrote one of the movement's most famous books, ''[[A Theology of Liberation]]''. Other noted exponents are [[Leonardo Boff]] of Brazil, [[Jon Sobrino]] of [[El Salvador]], [[Óscar Romero]] of El Salvador, and [[Juan Luis Segundo]] of Uruguay.&lt;ref&gt;Richard P. McBrien, ''Catholicism'' (Harper Collins, 1994), chapter IV.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gustavo Gutierrez, ''A Theology of Liberation'', First (Spanish) edition published in Lima, Peru, 1971; first English edition published by Orbis Books (Maryknoll, New York), 1973.&lt;/ref&gt;

The influence of liberation theology diminished after proponents were accused of using &quot;Marxist concepts&quot; leading to admonishment by the [[Holy See|Vatican]]'s [[Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith]] (CDF) in 1984 and 1986. The Vatican criticized certain strains of liberation theology for focusing on institutionalized or systemic sin, apparently to the exclusion of individual offenders/offences; and for allegedly misidentifying Catholic Church hierarchy in South America as members of the same privileged class that would had long been oppressing indigenous populations since the arrival of [[Francisco Pizarro|Pizarro]] onward.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wojda, Paul J. 1995&quot;&gt;Wojda, Paul J., &quot;Liberation theology&quot;, in R.P. McBrien, ed., ''The Catholic Encyclopedia'' (Harper Collins, 1995).&lt;/ref&gt;

==Theology==
Liberation theology could be interpreted as a western attempt to return to the gospel of the [[early church]] where Christianity is politically and culturally decentralized.&lt;ref&gt;ON THE DEVELOPMENT OF PEOPLES, Populorum Progressio, Encyclical Letter of His Holiness Pope Paul VI promulgated on March 26, 1967&lt;/ref&gt;

Liberation theology proposes to fight poverty by addressing its supposed source: sin. In so doing, it explores the relationship between [[Christian theology]] — especially [[Roman Catholic theology]] — and political activism, especially in terms of [[social justice]], [[poverty]], and [[human rights]]. The principal methodological innovation is seeing theology from the perspective of the poor and the oppressed. For example [[Jon Sobrino]], S.J., argues that the poor are a privileged channel of [[God's grace]].

Some liberation theologians base their social action upon the [[Bible]] scriptures describing the mission of [[Jesus Christ]], as [[But to bring a sword|bringing a sword]] ([[social unrest]]), e.g. {{bible verse||Isaiah|61:1|KJV}}, {{bible verse||Matthew|10:34|KJV}}, {{bible verse||Luke|22:35–38|KJV}} — and ''not'' as bringing peace ([[social order]]){{Better source|date=May 2010}}. This Biblical interpretation is a call to ''action'' against poverty, and the sin engendering it, to effect Jesus Christ's mission of justice in this world.

Gustavo Gutierrez gave the movement its paradigmatic expression with his book ''A Theology of Liberation'' (1971). In this book, Gutierrez combined populist ideas with the social teachings of the Catholic Church. He was influenced by an existing socialist current in the Church which included organizations such as the [[Catholic Worker Movement]] and the French Christian youth worker organization, ''&quot;[[Jeunesse Ouvrière Chrétienne]]&quot;.'' He was also influenced by [[Paul Gauthier (theologian)|Paul Gauthier]]'s ''&quot;[[The Poor, Jesus and the Church]]&quot;'' (1965). Gutierrez's book is based on an understanding of history in which the human being is seen as assuming conscious responsibility for human destiny, and yet Christ the Savior liberates the human race from sin, which is the root of all disruption of friendship and of all injustice and oppression.&lt;ref&gt;Gustavo Gutierrez, ''A Theology of Liberation''(London: SCM Press,1974) 36f&lt;/ref&gt;

Gutierrez also popularized the phrase &quot;[[preferential option for the poor]]&quot;, which became a slogan of liberation theology and later appeared in addresses of the Pope.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last = Ratzinger
  | first = Joseph
  | authorlink = Pope Benedict XVI
  | title = Address of His Holiness Benedict XVI to the Fathers of the General Congregation of the Society of Jesus
  | work = Speeches February 2008
  | publisher = The Holy See
  | date = 2008-02-21
  | url = http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/benedict_xvi/speeches/2008/february/documents/hf_ben-xvi_spe_20080221_gesuiti_en.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Drawing from the biblical motif on the poor, Gutierrez asserts that God is revealed as having a preference for those people who are “insignificant,” “marginalized,” “unimportant,” “needy,” despised” and “defenseless.&quot; Moreover, he makes clear that terminology of &quot;the poor&quot; in scripture has social and economic connotations that etymologically go back to the Greek word, ''ptōchos''.&lt;ref&gt;Gutierrez, Gustavo. The God of Life. Maryknoll, N.Y.: Orbis, 1991. (Original: El Dios de la vida. Lima: CEP, 1989.) p. 112&lt;/ref&gt; To be sure, as to not misinterpret Gutierrez’s definition of the term &quot;preferential option,&quot; he stresses, “Preference implies the universality of God’s love, which excludes no one. It is only within the framework of this universality that we can understand the preference, that is, 'what comes first.'&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Nickoloff, James B. ed. Gustavo Gutierrez: Essential Writings. Maryknoll, N.Y.: Orbis, 1996, p. 145&lt;/ref&gt;

Gutierrez emphasized practice (or, more technically, &quot;[[praxis (process)|praxis]]&quot;) over doctrine.  Gutierrez clarified his position by advocating a circular relationship between [[orthodoxy]] and [[orthopraxis]] seeing the two as having a symbiotic relationship.&lt;ref&gt;Gutierrez, Gustavo. The Truth Shall Make You Free: Confrontations. Maryknoll, N.Y.: Orbis, 1990. (Original: La verdad los hara libres: confrontaciones. Lima: CEP, 1986)&lt;/ref&gt; Gutierrez' reading of prophets condemning oppression and injustice against the poor (i.e. Jeremiah 22:13–17) informs his assertion that to know God (orthodoxy) is to do justice (orthopraxis).&lt;ref&gt;Gutierrez, Gustavo. The Power of Poor in History. Maryknoll, N.Y.: Orbis, 1983. (Original: La fuerza historica de los obres: seleccion de trabajos. Lima: CEP, 1971.)&lt;/ref&gt; Cardinal Ratzinger, however, criticized liberation theology for elevating orthopraxis to the level of orthodoxy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Ratzinger, Joseph Cardinal (2007). &quot;Liberation Theology: Preliminary Notes&quot;, in The Ratzinger Report.|title=Reprinted in: J.F. Thornton and S.B. Varenne, eds., The Essential Pope Benedict XVI.|year=2007|publisher=Online version: Harper Collins,}}&lt;/ref&gt;   Richard McBrien summarizes this concept as follows:

&lt;blockquote&gt;God is disclosed in the historical ‘’praxis’’ of liberation. It is the situation, and our passionate and reflective involvement in it, which mediates the Word of God. Today that Word is mediated through the cries of the poor and the oppressed.&lt;ref&gt;McBrien, R.P. ‘’Catholicism’’ (Harper Collins, 1995), pp. 249–250.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Another important hallmark for Gutierrez's brand of liberation theology is an interpretation of revelation as &quot;history&quot;. For example Gutierrez wrote:

&lt;blockquote&gt;History is the scene of the revelation God makes of the mystery of his person. His word reaches us in the measure of our involvement in the evolution of history.&lt;ref&gt;Gutierrez, G. &quot;Faith as Freedom&quot;, ‘’Horizons’’ 2/1, Spring 1975, p.32&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Gutierrez also considered the Church to be the &quot;sacrament of history&quot;, an outward and visible sign of an inward and spiritual grace, thus pointing to the doctrine of universal salvation as the true means to eternal life, and assigning the Church itself to a somewhat temporal role, namely, liberation.

The struggle of women for social justice has given rise to its own liberation theology, frequently known as [[feminist theology]] in Europe and North America.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rowland2007&quot; /&gt; Black and other women of colour in the United States speak of [[womanist theology]], while [[Mujerista theology]] denotes the liberation theology of Hispanic women.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rowland2007&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Christopher Rowland|title=The Cambridge companion to liberation theology|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=L6dCEHGx_LkC&amp;pg=PA105|accessdate=13 February 2011|date=17 December 2007|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-0-521-86883-9|page=105}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
A major player in the formation of liberation theology was [[Latin American Episcopal Conference|CELAM]], the Latin American Episcopal Conference. Created in 1955 in [[Rio de Janeiro]] (Brazil), CELAM pushed the [[Second Vatican Council]] (1962–65) toward a more socially oriented stance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pelton 1995&quot;&gt;Robert Pelton, &quot;Latin America, Catholicism in&quot; in R.P. McBrien, ed., ''The Harper Collins Encyclopedia of Catholicism'', Harper Collins, 1995.&lt;/ref&gt; However, CELAM never supported liberation theology as such, since liberation theology was frowned upon by the Vatican, with Pope Paul VI trying to slow the movement after the Second Vatican Council.&lt;ref&gt;According to Cardinal [[Alfonso López Trujillo]], liberation theology was simultaneously created by the [[Reflection Task Force]] of CELAM, and by [[Rubem Alves]]'s book, ''[[Towards a Theology of Liberation]]'' (1968). However, Cardinal Trujillo had himself been general secretary of CELAM, and president of CELAM's Reflection Task Force. [[Antonio Samoré|Cardinal Samore]], who as leader of the [[Pontifical Commission for Latin America]] was in charge of relations between the [[Roman Curia]] and CELAM, was ordered to put a stop to liberation theology, which was judged antithetical to the Catholic Church's global teachings.&lt;/ref&gt;

After the Second Vatican Council, CELAM held two conferences which were important in determining the future of liberation theology: the first was held in [[Medellín]], Colombia, in 1968, and the second in [[Puebla]], Mexico, in January 1979.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pelton 1995&quot; /&gt; The Medellín conference debated how to apply the teachings of Vatican II to Latin America, and its conclusions were strongly influenced by liberation theology.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wojda, Paul J. 1995&quot;/&gt;

Cardinal [[Alfonso López Trujillo]] was a central figure at the Medellín Conference, and was elected in 1972 as general secretary of CELAM. He represented a more orthodox position, becoming a favorite of pope [[John Paul II]] and the &quot;principal scourge of liberation theology.&quot;&lt;ref name = Curti&gt;Elena Curti, &quot;Study in Scarlet&quot;, ''The Tablet'', 8 May 2010, p.4.&lt;/ref&gt; Trujillo's faction became predominant in CELAM after the 1972 [[Sucre]] conference, and in the Roman Curia after the CELAM conference in [[Puebla]], Mexico, in January 1979.

Despite the orthodox bishops' predominance in CELAM, a more radical form of liberation theology remained much supported in South America. Thus, the 1979 Puebla Conference was an opportunity for orthodox bishops to reassert control of the radical elements; but they failed. At the Puebla Conference, the orthodox reorientation was met by strong opposition from the liberal part of the clergy, which supported the concept of a &quot;[[preferential option for the poor]]&quot;. This concept had been approved at the Medellín conference by [[Bishop Ricard Durand]], president of the [[Commission about Poverty]].

Pope John Paul II gave the opening speech at the Puebla Conference. The general tone of his remarks was conciliatory. He criticized radical liberation theology, saying, &quot;this conception of Christ, as a political figure, a revolutionary, as the subversive of Nazareth, does not tally with the Church's catechisms&quot;; however, he did speak of &quot;the ever increasing wealth of the rich at the expense of the ever increasing poverty of the poor&quot;, and affirmed that the ''principle'' of private property &quot;must lead to a more just and equitable distribution of goods...and, if the common good demands it, there is no need to hesitate at [[Nationalization|expropriation]], itself, done in the right way&quot;; on balance, the Pope offered neither praise nor condemnation.

Some liberation theologians, however, including Gutierrez, had been barred from attending the Puebla Conference. Working from a seminary and with aid from sympathetic, liberal bishops, they partially obstructed other clergy's efforts to ensure that the Puebla Conference documents satisfied conservative concerns. Within four hours of the Pope's speech, Gutiérrez and the other priests wrote a twenty-page refutation, which was circulated at the conference, and has been claimed to have influenced the final outcome of the conference. According to a socio-political study of liberation theology in Latin America, twenty-five per cent of the final Puebla documents were written by theologians who were ''not invited'' to the conference.&lt;ref&gt;Smith, Christian. ''The Emergence of Liberation Theology''&lt;/ref&gt; Cardinal Trujillo said that this affirmation is &quot;an incredible exaggeration&quot; (Ben Zabel 2002:139).

==Practice==
One of the most radical aspects of liberation theology was the social organization, or re-organization, of church practice through the model of [[Christian base communities]] (CBCs).  Liberation theology strove to be a [[Top-down and bottom-up design|bottom-up]] movement in practice, with Biblical interpretation and liturgical practice designed by lay practitioners themselves, rather than by the orthodox Church hierarchy. In this context, sacred text interpretation is understood as &quot;praxis&quot;.

Journalist and writer [[Penny Lernoux]] described this aspect of liberation theology in her numerous and committed writings intended to explain the movement's ideas in North America. Base communities were small gatherings, usually outside of churches, in which the Bible could be discussed, and Mass could be said.  They were especially active in rural parts of Latin America where parish priests were not always available, as they placed a high value on [[Laity|lay]] participation.  As of May 2007, it was estimated that 80,000 base communities were operating in Brazil alone.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes&quot;&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/07/world/americas/07theology.html?pagewanted=1&amp;ei=5089&amp;en=34f757c655dbef9f&amp;ex=1336190400&amp;partner=rssyahoo&amp;emc=rss &quot;As Pope Heads to Brazil, a Rival Theology Persists&quot;] ''The New York Times'' 2007-05-07.&lt;/ref&gt; Contemporaneously [[Fanmi Lavalas]] in [[Haiti]], the [[Landless Workers' Movement]] in [[Brazil]], and [[Abahlali baseMjondolo]] in South Africa are three organizations that make use of liberation theology.&lt;ref&gt;[http://betacanadaandtheworld.com/liberationtheology.html Liberation Theology], Canada &amp; the World, 10 February 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reaction within the Catholic Church===

In March 1983, [[Cardinal Ratzinger]] (now [[Pope Benedict XVI]]) head of the Vatican's [[Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith]] (CDF), made ten observations of Gutiérrez's theology, accusing Gutiérrez of politically interpreting the Bible in supporting temporal messianism, and stating that the predominance of [[orthopraxis]] over orthodoxy in his thought proved a Marxist influence. Ratzinger objected that the spiritual concept of the Church as &quot;People of God&quot; is transformed into a &quot;Marxist myth.&quot; In liberation theology he declared, the &quot;people is the antithesis of the hierarchy, the antithesis of all institutions, which are seen as oppressive powers. Ultimately anyone who participates in the class struggle is a member of the &quot;people&quot;; the &quot;Church of the people&quot; becomes the antagonist of the hierarchical Church.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Ratzinger|first=Joseph Cardinal|title=&quot;Liberation Theology: Preliminary Notes&quot;, in The Ratzinger Report. Reprinted in: J.F. Thornton and S.B. Varenne, eds., The Essential Pope Benedict XVI,|year=2007|publisher=Harper Collins, 2007|location=Online version}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cardinal Ratzinger did praise liberation theology in some respects, including its ideal of justice, its rejection of violence, and its stress on &quot;the responsibility which Christians necessarily bear for the poor and oppressed.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;idem&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=idem}}&lt;/ref&gt;  He subsequently stated that no one could be neutral in the face of injustice, and referred to the &quot;crimes&quot; of [[colonialism]] and the &quot;scandal&quot; of the [[arms race]]. Nonetheless, media reports tended to assume that the condemnation of &quot;liberation theology&quot; meant a rejection of such attitudes and an endorsement of [[conservative]] politics.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}

In 1984, it was reported that a meeting occurred between the CDF and the CELAM bishops, during which a rift developed between Ratzinger and some of the bishops&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Curti,|first=Elena|title=&quot;Study in Scarlet&quot;, The Tablet,|date=8 May 2010,|pages=4}}&lt;/ref&gt;  with Ratzinger issuing official condemnations of certain elements of liberation theology.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith,|title=&quot;Instruction on certain aspects of the 'Theology of Liberation'&quot;, Origins 14/13|date=September 13, 1984.|location=Online version}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith, .|title=&quot;Instruction on Christian Freedom and Liberation&quot;, Origins 15/44|date=(April 17, 1986)}}&lt;/ref&gt; These &quot;Instructions&quot; refuted the Marxist-based idea that [[class struggle]] is fundamental to history, and rejected the interpretation of religious phenomena such as the [[The Exodus|Exodus]] and the [[Eucharist]] in exclusively political terms.  Ratzinger further stated that liberation theology had a major flaw in that it attempted to apply Christ's sermon on the mount teachings about the poor to present social situations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Ratzinger|first=Cardinal|title=op cit|year=1985}}&lt;/ref&gt;  He asserted that Christ's teaching on the poor meant that we will be judged when we die, with particular attention to how we personally have treated the poor.

Ratzinger also argued that liberation theology is not originally a &quot;grass-roots&quot; movement among the poor, but rather, a creation of Western intellectuals: &quot;an attempt to test, in a concrete scenario, ideologies that have been invented in the laboratory by European theologians&quot; and in a certain sense itself a form of &quot;cultural imperialism&quot;. Ratzinger saw this as a reaction to the demise or near-demise of the &quot;Marxist myth&quot; in the West.&lt;ref name=&quot;idem&quot;/&gt;

Throughout the 1990s, Ratzinger, as prefect of the CDF, continued to condemn these elements in liberation theology, and prohibited dissident priests from teaching such doctrines in the Catholic Church's name. [[Leonardo Boff]] was suspended and others were censured. [[Tissa Balasuriya]], in [[Sri Lanka]], was excommunicated. [[Sebastian Kappen]], an Indian theologian, was also censured for his book ''Jesus and Freedom''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Kappen|first=Sebastian|title=Jesus and Freedom. In 1980, the CDF asked the General of the Society of Jesus (of which Kappen was a member) to disavow this book. Kappen responded with a pamphlet entitled &quot;Censorship and the Future of Asian Theology&quot;. No further action was taken by the Vatican on this matter.|year=1977}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Under Cardinal Ratzinger's influence, theological formation schools were forbidden from using the Catholic Church's organization and grounds to teach liberation theology in the sense of theology using unacceptable Marxist ideas, not in the broader sense.

Roman Catholic priest and author [[Andrew Greeley]] also criticized liberation theology in his 2009 fictional book ''Irish Tweed''. In Greeley's book, a [[Chicago]] Catholic school is taken over by a principal and priest practicing liberation theology, and its ideas, as Greeley saw them, are applied in the school environment. For instance, basketball team members are chosen based on their family's economic status rather than on their ability.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Greeley,|first=Andrew.|title=Irish Tweed.|year=2009.|publisher=Forge Books,|isbn=0-7653-2223-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Counter criticism===

Such criticisms have provoked counter-criticisms that orthodox Catholics are in effect casting the Catholic Church as a friend of [[authoritarian]] regimes; and that the [[Holy See|Vatican]] is not so much trying to defend pure doctrine as to maintain an established ecclesiastical and political order. This conflict could be compared to some aspects of the [[Protestant Reformation]]. Outside Latin America, some of liberation theology's most ardent advocates are [[Protestant]] thinkers (e.g., [[Jürgen Moltmann]]  and [[Frederick Herzog]].)

There is also a [[Christian humanist]] response that calls for a complete breakaway from clerical hierarchies and the formulation of an entirely new Christian theology, one based on recent historical analysis by biblical scholars like [[JD Crossan]] highlighting the social revolutionary dimension of Jesus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Drake-Brockman|first=Tom|title=Christian Humanism:the compassionate theology of a Jew called Jesus.|year=2012|publisher=Denis Jones|location=Sydney:|pages=p12 &amp; pp 212–213}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Christianity|Catholicism}}
&lt;div style=&quot;column-count:2;-moz-column-count:2;-webkit-column-count:2&quot;&gt;
*[[Affirmative action]]
*[[Black liberation theology]]
*[[Black theology]]
*[[Christian anarchism]]
*[[Christian communism]]
*[[Christian humanism]]
*[[Christian left]]
*[[Christian socialism]]
*[[Christology]]
*[[Dependency theory]]
*[[Evangelical left]]
*[[Feminist theology]]
*[[Journal of World Systems Research]]
*[[Neo-Marxism]]
*[[New Monasticism]]
*[[Orbis Books]]
*[[Political revolution]]
*[[Progressive Christianity]]
*[[Queer Theology]]
*[[Radical Christianity]]
*[[Redistribution (economics)]]
*[[Reparations for slavery]]
*[[Social Gospel]]
*[[Social justice]]
*[[Social revolution]]
*[[Spiritual left]]
*[[World-systems theory]]
*[[Liberation Theology in Canada]]
&lt;/div&gt;

===Related movements===
* [[Abahlali baseMjondolo]] in [[South Africa]]&lt;ref name=&quot;info.interactivist.net&quot;&gt;[http://info.interactivist.net/node/12222 Interactivist article on liberation theology]{{dead link|date=December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Dalit theology]] in [[India]]
* [[Landless Workers' Movement]] in [[Brazil]]
* [[Fanmi Lavalas|Lavalas]] in [[Haiti]]&lt;ref name=&quot;info.interactivist.net&quot;/&gt;
* [[FSLN]] in [[Nicaragua]] (see [[The Catholic Church and the Nicaraguan Revolution]])

===People===

====Theologians====
{{Category see also|Liberation theologians}}
&lt;div style=&quot;column-count:2;-moz-column-count:2;-webkit-column-count:2&quot;&gt;
* [[Marcella Althaus-Reid]], [[Argentina]] – [[Scotland]] (1952–2009)
* [[Jean-Bertrand Aristide]], [[Haiti]] (b. 1953)
* [[Paulo Evaristo Arns]], [[Brazil]] (b. 1921)
* [[Naim Ateek]], [[Palestine]] (b. 1937)
* [[Alan Boesak]], South Africa (b. 1945)
* [[Leonardo Boff]], [[Brazil]] (b. 1938)
* [[Robert McAfee Brown]], U.S. (1920–2001)
* [[Hélder Câmara]], [[Brazil]] (1909–1999), Archbishop of [[Olinda]] and [[Recife]]
* [[Katie Geneva Cannon]], U.S.
* [[Pedro Casaldáliga]], Spain – [[Brazil]] (b. 1928)
* [[James Hal Cone|James Cone]], U.S. (b. 1938)
* [[Ernesto Cardenal]], [[Nicaragua]] (b. 1925)
* [[Miguel A. De La Torre]], U.S. Cuban
* [[Jean Marc Ela]], [[Cameroon]] (b. 1936)
* [[Virgilio Elizondo]], U.S.
* [[Ignacio Ellacuría]], S.J., Spain – [[El Salvador]] (1930–1989)
* [[Marc H. Ellis]], U.S. (b. 1952)
* [[Paul Gauthier (theologian)|Paul Gauthier]], France (1914–2002)
* [[Rutilio Grande]], [[El Salvador]] (1925–1977)
* [[Gustavo Gutiérrez]], [[Peru]] (b. 1928)
* [[François Houtart]], Belgium (b. 1925)
* [[Gérard Jean-Juste]], [[Haiti]] (b. 1947)
* [[Sebastian Kappen]], India (1924–1993)
* [[Hans Küng]], Switzerland – Germany (b. 1928)
* [[Aloisio Leo Arlindo Lorscheider]], [[Brazil]] (1924–2007)
* [[Martin Maier]], S.J. Germany
* [[Ignacio Martín-Baró]], S.J., Spain – [[El Salvador]] (1942–1989)
* [[Herbert McCabe]], O.P., UK (1926–2001)
* [[Johann Baptist Metz]], Germany (b. 1928)
* [[Jürgen Moltmann]], Germany (b. 1926)
* [[Segundo Montes]], S.J., Spain – [[El Salvador]] (1933–1989)
* [[Henri Nouwen]], Netherlands (1932–1996)
* [[Rubin Phillip]], South Africa (b. 1948)
* [[Camilo Torres Restrepo|Camilo Torres]], [[Colombia]] (1929–1966)
* [[Samuel Ruiz]], Mexico (b. 1924)
* [[Edward Schillebeeckx]], Belgium – Netherlands (b. 1914–2009)
* [[Juan Luis Segundo]], S.J., [[Uruguay]] (1925–1996)
* [[Stephen Sizer]], England (b. 1953)
* [[Jon Sobrino]], S.J., Spain – [[El Salvador]] (b. 1938)
* [[Dorothee Sölle]], Germany (1929–2003)
* [[William Stringfellow]], U.S. (1929–1985)
* [[Jung Mo Sung]], [[Brazil]] (b. 1957)
&lt;/div&gt;

====Influence on others====
* [[Anthony B. Pinn]], U.S.
* [[Diane Drufenbrock]], U.S.
* [[Paul Farmer]], U.S. (b. 1959)
* [[Brian P. Moore]], U.S.
* [[Óscar Romero]], [[El Salvador]]
* [[Paulo Freire]], [[Brazil]] (1921–1997)
* [[Vekoslav Grmič]], [[Yugoslavia]]
* [[Robert McAfee Brown]], U.S. (1920–2001)
* [[Fernando Lugo]]
* [[John Dear]], S.J., U.S.
* [[Jan de Vos (historian)|Jan de Vos van Gerven]], Belgium / Mexico (b. 1936)
* [[Ali Shari'ati]], [[Iran]] (1933–1977)&lt;ref name=nasr&gt;Nasr, Vali, ''The Shia Revival'', Norton, (2006), p.129&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==See Also==
*[[Hélder Câmara]]

==Further reading==
'''Introductory works (all by Penny Lernoux)'''
*Lernoux, Penny, ''Cry of the people: United States involvement in the rise of fascism, torture, and murder and the persecution of the Catholic Church in Latin America.'' Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday, 1980.
*Lernoux, Penny, ''In banks we trust.'' Garden City, N.Y.: Anchor Press/Doubleday, 1984.
*Lernoux, Penny, ''People of God : the struggle for world Catholicism.'' New York: Viking, 1989.

'''Principal texts'''
[[Rubem Alves]], a Brazilian theologian working at [[Princeton University|Princeton]], wrote ''Towards a Theology of Liberation'' (1968).

Peruvian Catholic priest, Fr. [[Gustavo Gutiérrez]], [[Ordo Praedicatorum|O.P.]] wrote ''A Theology of Liberation'' (1972).

'''Other readings:'''
*[[Miguel A. De La Torre|De La Torre, Miguel A.]], ''Handbook on U.S. Theologies of Liberation'' (Chalice Press, 2004).
* [[Pope Benedict XVI|Ratzinger, Joseph Cardinal]],  &quot;Liberation Theology&quot; (preliminary notes to 1984 Instruction)
* Berryman, Phillip, ''Liberation Theology'' (1987).
* Damico, Linda H., ''The Anarchist Dimension of Liberation Theology'' (1987). ISBN 978-1620323441
* Sigmund, P.E., ''Liberation Theology at the Crossroads'' (1990).
* Hillar, Marian, ''Liberation Theology: Religious Response to Social Problems. A Survey'', published in ''Humanism and Social Issues. Anthology of Essays''. M. Hillar and H.R. Leuchtag, eds., American Humanist Association, Houston, 1993, pp.&amp;nbsp;35–52.
* Gutiérrez, Gustavo, ''A Theology of Liberation: History, Politics and Salvation'', Orbis Books, 1988.
* Gutiérrez, Gustavo. We Drink from Our Own Wells: The Spiritual Journey of a People. London: SCM Press, 1983.
* Kirylo, James D. ''Paulo Freire: The Man from Recife''. New York: Peter Lang, 2011.
* Petrella, Ivan, ''The Future of Liberation Theology: An Argument and Manifesto'' Aldershot: Ashgate, 2004.
* Piedra, Alberto M. &quot;Some Observations on Liberation Theology.&quot; ''World Affairs'' Vol. 148 no 3. (Winter 1985–86)pg 151–158
* Smith, Christian, ''The Emergence of Liberation Theology: Radical Religion and the Social Movement Theory'', University of Chicago Press, 1991.
*Lucia Ceci, ''La teologia della liberazione in America Latina. L'opera di Gustavo Gutierrez'', F. Angeli, Milano 1999.
*Lucia Ceci, ''Chiesa e liberazione in America Latina (1968–1972)'', in ''L’America Latina fra Pio XII e Paolo VI. Il cardinale Casaroli e le politiche vaticane in una chiesa che cambia'', a cura di A. Melloni e S. Scatena, Il Mulino, Bologna 2006;
* Mahan, Brian and L. Dale Richesin, ''The Challenge of Liberation Theology: A First World Response'', 1981, Orbis Books, Maryknoll, New York.
* Mueller, Andreas, OFM, [[Arno Tausch]] and Paul Michael Zulehner (Eds.) ''Global capitalism, liberation theology, and the social sciences&quot; Hauppauge, New York: Nova Science Publishers
* ''Marxism and Missions / Missions et Marxisme'', special issue of the journal [http://www2.unil.ch/lefaitmissionnaire/pages/tables_publi/lfm22_2%20tbl.html Social Sciences and Missions], Volume 22/2, 2009

==External links==

=*[http://repository.library.georgetown.edu/handle/10822/552613 Liberation Theology Video] from the [https://repository.library.georgetown.edu/handle/10822/552494/browse?type=title Dean Peter Krogh Foreign Affairs Digital Archives].
*[http://www.con-spiration.de/texte/english/2006/liberation-e.html Complex and Alive. Recent Developments of the Theology of Liberation]
*[http://www.landreform.org/boff2.htm A short history of Liberation theology]
*[http://home.comcast.net/~chtongyu/liberation/ Excerpts on and Chronology of liberation theology]
*[http://home.earthlink.net/~ronrhodes/Liberation.html &quot;Christian Revolution in Latin America: The Changing Face of Liberation Theology&quot;], Ron Rhodes
*[http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/christianity/beliefs/liberationtheology.shtml BBC Religion and Ethics theological obituary of Pope John Paul II: his views on liberation theology]
*[http://www.theo.kuleuven.ac.be/clt/index.htm Centre for Liberation Theologies, Faculty of Theology, Katholieke Universiteit Leuven, Belgium]
*[http://www.catholicculture.org/docs/doc_view.cfm?recnum=643 Edward A. Lynch, &quot;The Retreat of Liberation Theology&quot;, 1994]
*[http://www.liberationtheology.org/ Liberation Theology Resources Online] – articles, organizations, biographies, book links
*[http://www.blackliberationtheology.info/ Black Liberation Theology: Information]
*[http://www.centropian.com/religion/issues/wright/index.html Liberation Theology at Centropian]
*[http://abahlali.org/node/691 Article by Brother Fillipo Mondini on Praxis]
*[http://www.zompist.com/meetthepoor.html The Bible on the Poor: Or Why God is a Liberal]

{{commons category|Liberation theology}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Liberation Theology}}
[[Category:Catholic theology and doctrine]]
[[Category:Christian theological movements]]
[[Category:Marxism]]
[[Category:Religion and politics]]
[[Category:Liberation theology| ]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]

[[ar:لاهوت التحرير]]
[[ast:Teoloxía de la Lliberación]]
[[zh-min-nan:Tháu-pa̍k sîn-ha̍k]]
[[ca:Teologia de l'alliberament]]
[[cs:Teologie osvobození]]
[[da:Befrielsesteologi]]
[[de:Befreiungstheologie]]
[[es:Teología de la liberación]]
[[eo:Teologio de liberigo]]
[[eu:Askapenaren teologia]]
[[fr:Théologie de la libération]]
[[gl:Teoloxía da liberación]]
[[ko:해방신학]]
[[hr:Teologija oslobođenja]]
[[id:Teologi pembebasan]]
[[ia:Theologia del liberation]]
[[it:Teologia della liberazione]]
[[la:Theologia liberationis]]
[[hu:Felszabadítási teológia]]
[[nl:Bevrijdingstheologie]]
[[ja:解放の神学]]
[[no:Frigjøringsteologi]]
[[pl:Teologia wyzwolenia]]
[[pt:Teologia da Libertação]]
[[qu:Qispichiy yaya yachay]]
[[ru:Теология освобождения]]
[[simple:Liberation theology]]
[[sk:Teológia oslobodenia]]
[[sr:Teologija oslobođenja]]
[[sh:Teologija oslobođenja]]
[[fi:Vapautuksen teologia]]
[[sv:Befrielseteologi]]
[[uk:Теологія визволення]]
[[vi:Thần học giải phóng]]
[[zh:解放神學]]</text>
      <sha1>gtivdba4l72l2vteqgi8uz4u24nffwe</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
