<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Louis XVIII of France</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>62114</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522085112</id>
      <parentid>521196535</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-08T23:26:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>R'n'B</username>
        <id>2300502</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Remove [[WP:DPL|links]] to [[WP:D|disambiguation]] page [[Third Estate]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="60062">{{Infobox royalty|monarchy
|name=Louis XVIII
|succession=[[List of French monarchs|King of France and of Navarre]]
|image=Louis XVIII2.jpg
|caption=Louis XVIII, in his coronation robes, by [[François Gérard]]
|reign=''[[De jure]]'' 11 June 1795&amp;nbsp;– &lt;br&gt;16 September 1824 &lt;br&gt; ''De facto'' 11 April 1814&amp;nbsp;–&lt;br&gt; 20 March 1815; ''then''&lt;br&gt;8 July 1815&amp;nbsp;– &lt;br&gt;16 September 1824
|full name=Louis Stanislas Xavier de France
|predecessor= [[Napoleon I]]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;As Emperor of the French.
|successor=[[Charles X of France|Charles X]]
|spouse=[[Marie Joséphine of Savoy]]
|royal house=[[House of Bourbon]]
|royal anthem =
|father=[[Louis, Dauphin of France (1729-1765)|Louis, Dauphin of France]]
|mother=[[Maria Josepha of Saxony (1731–1767)|Maria Josepha of Saxony]]
|birth_date={{Birth date|1755|11|17|df=y}}
|birth_place=[[Palace of Versailles]], France
|death_date={{Death date and age|1824|9|16|1755|11|17|df=y}}
|death_place=[[Louvre Palace]], Paris, France
|place of burial=[[Basilica of Saint Denis]], France|}}

'''Louis XVIII''' (Louis Stanislas Xavier; 17 November 1755&amp;nbsp;– 16 September 1824), known as &quot;the Desired&quot; (''le Desiré'')&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.herodote.net/histoire/synthese.php?ID=191] He was called « Désiré » because the royalists had been hoping for him for a long time, but also because many of the people were tired of the wars and wanted the return of the monarchy, restored after the First Empire, as the Révolution of Bordeaux [[:fr:Histoire de Bordeaux#L'époque contemporaine]] will attest.&lt;/ref&gt;, was a [[House of Bourbon|Bourbon]] King of [[list of French monarchs|France]] and of [[List of Navarrese monarchs|Navarre]] from 1814 to 1824, omitting the [[Hundred Days]] in 1815. Louis XVIII spent twenty-three years in exile, from 1791 to 1814, during the [[French Revolution]] and the [[First French Empire]], and again in 1815, for 111 days, upon the return of [[Napoleon I]] from [[Elba]].

Until his accession to the throne of France, Louis held the title of [[Count of Provence]], being the brother of King [[Louis XVI of France|Louis XVI]]. On the 21 September 1792, the [[National Convention]] abolished the monarchy and deposed King Louis XVI, who was [[Execution of Louis XVI|later executed]] by [[guillotine]].&lt;ref&gt;Hibbert, Christopher, ''The French Revolution'', Penguin Books (London), 1982, ISBN 978-0-14-004945-9, pp. 331–332&lt;/ref&gt; When the young [[Louis XVII of France|Louis XVII]], Louis XVI's son, died in [[Temple (Paris)|prison]] in June 1795, Louis XVIII succeeded his nephew as [[Titular ruler|titular]] King, although the monarchy had been disestablished.&lt;ref&gt;Nagel, Susan, ''Marie-Thérèse: Child of Terror'' Bloomsbury, USA, Reprint Edition 2008, ISBN 1-59691-057-7, pp. 152–153&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[French Revolution]] and the [[Napoleonic era]], Louis XVIII lived in exile in [[Prussia]], the [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|United Kingdom]] and [[Russian Empire|Russia]].&lt;ref&gt;Fraser, Antonia, ''Marie Antoinette: The Journey'', ORION, London 2002, [[ISBN]] 978-0-7538-1305-8, p. 532.&lt;/ref&gt; When the [[War of the Sixth Coalition|Sixth Coalition]] finally defeated Napoleon, [[Bourbon Restoration|Louis XVIII was restored]] to what he, and Royalists, considered his rightful place. This period was marked by an [[Ultra-royalist]] [[Reactionary|reaction]]. However Napoleon escaped from his exile in Elba, marched on Paris and restored the French Empire. Louis XVIII fled and a [[War of the Seventh Coalition|Seventh Coalition]] declared war on the French Empire, defeated Napoleon and for a second time restored Louis XVIII on the French throne. In 1823, Louis XVIII sent an expeditionary corps, known as the &quot;[[Hundred Thousand Sons of Saint Louis]]&quot;, in [[Spain]] to restore the absolute [[Ferdinand VII of Spain|King of Spain]].

Louis XVIII ruled as king for slightly less than a decade. The Bourbon Restoration regime was a [[constitutional monarchy]] (unlike the ''Ancien Régime'', which was [[absolute monarchy|absolute]]). As a [[constitutional monarch]], Louis XVIII's royal prerogative was reduced substantially by the [[Charter of 1814]], France's new constitution. Louis had no children; therefore, upon his death, the crown passed to his brother, [[Charles X of France|Charles, Count of Artois]].&lt;ref&gt;Fraser, 532&lt;/ref&gt; Louis XVIII was the last French monarch to die while reigning.

==Youth==
[[File:Maurice_Quentin_de_La_Tour,_Portrait_de_Louis_Stanislas_Xavier_de_France,_comte_de_Provence_(1762).jpg|thumb|Portrait of the young Count of Provence]]'''Louis Stanislas Xavier''', titled ''[[comte de Provence]]'' at birth, was born on 17 November 1755 in the [[Palace of Versailles]], the son of [[Louis, Dauphin of France (1729–1765)|Louis, Dauphin of France]], and of his wife, [[Princess Maria Josepha of Saxony (1731–1767)|Princess Maria Josepha of Saxony]]. He was the grandson of the reigning King [[Louis XV of France|Louis XV]]. As a son of the Dauphin he was a [[Fils de France]]. Louis Stanislas was christened Louis Stanislas Xavier six months after his birth, in accordance with Bourbon family tradition, being nameless before his [[baptism]]. By this act, he became also a Knight of the Order of the Holy Spirit.
The name of ''Louis'' was bestowed because it was typical of a Prince of France; Stanislas after his great-grandfather King [[Stanisław Leszczyński]] of Poland; and Xavier for Saint [[Francis Xavier]], whom his mother's family held as one of their patron saints.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 10&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:François hubert drouais - duque berry conde provença.jpg|left|250 px|thumb|The comte de Provence and his brother Louis Auguste, duc de Berry, depicted in 1757 by [[François-Hubert Drouais]].]]
At the time of his birth, Louis Stanislas was fourth in line to the throne of France, behind his father, the [[Dauphin of France|Dauphin]]; and his two elder brothers, [[Louis, Duke of Burgundy (1751–1761)|Louis Joseph Xavier, Duke of Burgundy]] and [[Louis XVI of France|Louis Auguste, Duke of Berry]]. The former died in 1761, leaving Louis Auguste as heir apparent until the Dauphin's own premature death in 1765. The two deaths elevated Louis Stanislas to second in the line of succession, while Louis Auguste acquired the title of ''Dauphin''.&lt;ref&gt;Fraser, 41&lt;/ref&gt;

Louis Stanislas found comfort in his governess, [[Marie Louise de Rohan|Madame de Marsan]], [[Governess of the Children of France]], (''Gouvernante des Enfants de France''), as he was her favourite among his siblings.&lt;ref name=Mansel11&gt;Mansel, 11&lt;/ref&gt; Louis Stanislas was taken away from his governess when he turned seven, age at which the education of boys of royal blood and of the nobility was turned over to men. [[Antoine de Quélen de Stuer de Caussade, duc de La Vauguyon (1705–1772)|Antoine de Quélen de Stuer de Caussade, Duke of La Vauguyon]], a friend of his father, was named his governor.
Louis Stanislas was an intelligent boy, excelling in classics. His education was of the same quality and consistency as that of his older brother, Louis Auguste, despite the fact that Louis Auguste was heir and Louis Stanislas was not.&lt;ref name=Mansel11/&gt; Louis Stanislas' education was quite religious in nature, several of his teachers being ecclesiastics. La Vauguyon drilled into young Louis Stanislas and his brothers the way he thought princes should &quot;know how to withdraw themselves, to like to work,&quot; and &quot;to know how to reason correctly&quot;.

In April 1771, Louis Stanislas's education was formally concluded, and his own independent household was established,&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 12&lt;/ref&gt; which astounded contemporaries with its extravagance: in 1773, the number of servants reached 390.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mansel, 20&quot;&gt;Mansel, 20&lt;/ref&gt; In the same month his household was founded, Louis was granted several titles by his grandfather, Louis XV: Duke of Anjou, Count of Maine, Count of Perche and Count of Senoches.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mansel, 24&quot;&gt;Mansel, 24&lt;/ref&gt;

On 17 December 1773 he was ordained as Grand Master of the Order of St. Lazarus.

==Marriage==

On 14 May 1771, Louis Stanislas married [[Marie Joséphine of Savoy|Princess Maria Giuseppina of Savoy]]. Marie Joséphine (as she was known in France) was a daughter of the then [[Duke of Savoy|Duke]] and [[Maria Antonia Ferdinanda of Spain|Duchess of Savoy]], future king [[Victor Amadeus III of Sardinia]].

A luxurious ball followed the wedding on 20 May.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 3&lt;/ref&gt; Louis Stanislas was repulsed by his wife, the new Countess of Provence, who was considered to be ugly, tedious and ignorant of the court at Versailles. The marriage remained unconsummated; biographers disagree about the reason, maintaining that it was due to Louis Stanislas' alleged impotence (according to biographer [[Antonia Fraser]]) or his unwillingness to sleep with his wife, due to her poor personal hygiene. She never brushed her teeth, plucked her eyebrows, or used any perfumes.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 13–14&lt;/ref&gt; At the time of his marriage, Louis Stanislas was obese and waddled instead of walked. He never exercised and continued to eat enormous amounts of food.&lt;ref&gt;Fraser, 114&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the fact that Louis Stanislas was not infatuated with his wife, he boasted that the two enjoyed vigorous conjugal relations&amp;nbsp;— such declarations were held in low esteem by courtiers at Versailles. He also proclaimed his wife to be pregnant, merely to spite Louis Auguste and his wife [[Marie Antoinette|Archduchess Marie Antoinette of Austria]], who had not yet consummated their marriage.&lt;ref&gt;Fraser, 115&lt;/ref&gt; The Dauphin and Louis Stanislas did not enjoy a harmonious relationship, and often quarrelled,&lt;ref&gt;Fraser, 120&lt;/ref&gt; as did their wives.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mansel, 111&quot;&gt;Mansel, 111&lt;/ref&gt; Louis Stanislas impregnated his wife in 1774, having conquered his aversion to Marie Joséphine. However, the pregnancy ended in a miscarriage.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 14–15&lt;/ref&gt; A second pregnancy in 1781 was also miscarried. The marriage was, ultimately, childless.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 10&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Louis XVII. John Murray. pp. 13–14. ISBN 0-7195-6709-2&lt;/ref&gt;

==At his brother's court==
[[Image:JoungLouisXVIII.jpg|thumb|Louis Stanislas, Count of Provence, during the reign of [[Louis XVI of France]].]]
[[Image:MarieJosephinedeSavoie.jpg|thumb|[[Princess Marie Josephine Louise of Savoy|Marie Joséphine]], Countess of Provence, Louis Stanislas' wife, by Jean-Baptiste-André Gautier d'Agoty, 1775.]]

On 27 April 1774, Louis XV fell ill after having contracted [[smallpox]], and died the following 10 May.&lt;ref&gt;Fraser, 136–138&lt;/ref&gt;  The Dauphin, Louis Auguste, succeeded his grandfather as King Louis XVI.&lt;ref&gt;Fraser, 143&lt;/ref&gt; Louis Stanislas longed for political influence. He attempted to gain admittance to the King’s council in 1774, ultimately failing. Louis Stanislas was left in a political limbo that he called &quot;a gap of 12 years in my political life&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 16&lt;/ref&gt; Louis XVI granted Louis Stanislas revenues from the [[Counts and Dukes of Alençon|Duchy of Alençon]] in December 1774. The duchy was given to enhance Louis Stanislas' prestige; however, his [[appanage]] turned over only 300,000 [[French livre|livres]] ''per annum'', an amount much lower than it had been at its peak in the fourteenth century.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mansel, 24&quot;/&gt; King Louis XVI, his brothers, and Marie Antoinette became fellows of the [[masonic lodge]] Trois Frères à l'Orient de Versailles.&lt;ref&gt;Charles Porset, Hiram sans-culotte? Franc-maçonnerie, lumières et révolution: trente ans d'études et de recherches, Paris: Honoré Champion, 1998
p. 207.{{Fr:icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Louis Stanislas travelled more through France than other members of the royal family, who rarely left the [[Île-de-France (province)|Île-de-France]]. In 1774, he accompanied his sister [[Clotilde de France|Madame Clotilde]] to [[Chambéry]], on the journey to meet her bridegroom [[Charles Emmanuel IV of Sardinia|Charles Emmanuel, Prince of Piedmont]], heir to the throne of Sardinia. In 1775, he visited [[Lyon]] and also his spinster aunts, [[Princess Marie Adélaïde of France|Madame Adélaïde]] and [[Princess Victoire of France|Madame Victoire]], while they were taking the waters at [[Vichy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Mansel, 20&quot;/&gt; The four provincial tours that Louis Stanislas took before the year 1791 amounted to a total of three months.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 21&lt;/ref&gt;

On 5 May 1778, Dr. Lassonne, Marie Antoinette's private physician, confirmed her pregnancy.&lt;ref&gt;Castelot, André, ''Madame Royale'', Librairie Académique Perrin, Paris, 1962, p. 15, ISBN &lt;small&gt;2-262-00035-2&lt;/small&gt;, (French).&lt;/ref&gt; On 19 December 1778, the Queen gave birth to a daughter, who was named [[Marie-Thérèse Charlotte de France]], and given the honorific title [[Fils de France|Madame Royale]]. The birth of a girl came as a relief to the ''comte de Provence'', who kept his position as heir to Louis XVI, since [[Salic Law]] excluded women from acceding to the throne of France.&lt;ref&gt;Fraser, 199&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Fraser201&gt;Fraser, 201&lt;/ref&gt; However, Louis Stanislas did not remain heir to the throne much longer, as on 22 October 1781, Marie Antoinette gave birth to the Dauphin, [[Louis-Joseph, Dauphin of France|Louis Joseph]]. Louis Stanislas and the [[Charles X of France|Comte d’Artois]] served as godfathers by proxy for the [[Joseph II, Holy Roman Emperor|Holy Roman Emperor]], the Queen’s brother.&lt;ref&gt;Fraser, 221&amp;nbsp;– 223&lt;/ref&gt;  When Marie Antoinette gave birth to her second son, [[Louis XVII of France|Louis Charles]], in March 1785, Louis Stanislas slid further down the line of succession.&lt;ref&gt;Fraser, 224 &amp;nbsp;–225&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1780, [[Anne Nompar de Caumont|Anne Nompar de Caumont de La Force, comtesse de Balbi]] entered the service of Marie Joséphine. Louis Stanislas soon fell in love with his wife's new lady-in-waiting, and installed her as his mistress,&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 28&lt;/ref&gt; which resulted in the couple's already small affection for each other cooling entirely.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 30&lt;/ref&gt; Louis Stanislas commissioned a pavilion for his mistress on a parcel that became known as the ''Parc Balbi'', near the [[Gardens of Versailles|''Pièce d’eau des Suisses'']] and the ''[[Potager du Roi]]'' at Versailles.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 29&lt;/ref&gt;

Louis Stanislas lived a quiet and sedentary lifestyle at this point, not having a great deal to do since his self-proclaimed political exclusion in 1774. He kept himself occupied with his vast library of over 11,000 books at Balbi's pavilion, reading for several hours each morning.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 34&lt;/ref&gt; In the early 1780, he also incurred huge debts totaling 10&amp;nbsp;million livres, which his brother Louis XVI paid for him.&lt;ref&gt;Fraser, 178&lt;/ref&gt;

An [[Assembly of Notables]] (the members consisted of magistrates, mayors, nobles and clergy) was convened in February 1787 to ratify the financial reforms sought by the Controller-General of Finance [[Charles Alexandre de Calonne]]. This provided Louis Stanislas, who abhorred the radical reforms proposed by Calonne, the opportunity he had long been waiting for to establish himself in politics.&lt;ref&gt;Hibbert, p 38&lt;/ref&gt; The reforms proposed a new property tax,&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 40&lt;/ref&gt; and new elected provincial assemblies that would have a say in local taxation.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 41&lt;/ref&gt; Calonne's proposition was rejected outright by the notables, and, as a result, Louis XVI dismissed him. The Archbishop of Toulouse, [[Étienne Charles de Loménie de Brienne]], acquired Calonne's ministry. Brienne attempted to salvage Calonne's reforms, but ultimately failed to convince the notables to approve them. A frustrated Louis XVI dissolved the assembly.&lt;ref&gt;Hibbert, 39&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Boiler hard paste porcelain Manufacture de Monsieur 1780.jpg|thumb|Louis had a venture in [[hard-paste porcelain]], which was called &quot;[[Clignancourt porcelain|Porcelaine de Monsieur]]&quot;, 1780.]]
Brienne's reforms were then submitted to the ''[[Parlement de Paris]]'' in the hopes that they would be approved. (A ''parlement'' was responsible for ratifying the King’s edicts. Each province had its own ''parlement'', but the ''parlement de Paris'' was the most significant of all.) The ''Parlement de Paris'' refused to accept Brienne’s proposals, and pronounced that any new taxation would have to be approved by an [[French States-General|Estates-General]] (the nominal parliament of France). Louis XVI and Brienne took a hostile stance against the ''parlement's'' rejection, and Louis XVI had to implement a ''[[Lit de justice]]'' (which automatically registered an edict in the ''Parlement de Paris'') to ratify the desired reforms. On 8 May, [[Jean-Jacques Duval d'Eprémesnil]] and [[Goislard de Montsabert]], two of the leading members of the ''Parlement de Paris'' were arrested. There was rioting in [[Brittany]], Provence, [[Burgundy (region)|Burgundy]] and [[Béarn]] in reaction to their arrest. This unrest was engineered by local magistrates and nobles, who enticed the people to revolt against the ''Lit de Justice'', which was quite unfavourable to the nobles and magistrates. The clergy also joined the provincial cause, and condemned Brienne's tax reforms. Brienne conceded defeat in July and agreed to calling the Estates-General to meet in 1789. He resigned from his post in August and was replaced by the Swiss magnate [[Jacques Necker]].&lt;ref&gt;Hibbert, 40&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 1788, a second Assembly of Notables was convened by Jacques Necker, to consider the makeup of the next Estates-General.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 44&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Parlement de Paris'' recommended that the Estates should be the same as they were at the last assembly, in 1614 (this would mean that the clergy and nobility would have more representation than the [[Estates General (France)|Third Estate]]).&lt;ref&gt;Hibbert, 329&lt;/ref&gt; The notables rejected the &quot;dual representation&quot; proposal. Louis Stanislas was the only notable to vote to increase the size of the Third Estate.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 45&lt;/ref&gt; Necker disregarded the notables' judgment, and convinced Louis XVI to grant the extra representation&amp;nbsp;— Louis duly obliged on 27 December.&lt;ref&gt;Hibbert, 44&lt;/ref&gt;

===The outbreak of the French Revolution===
{{Main|French Revolution}}

The [[Estates-General of 1789|Estates-General]] were convened in May 1789 to ratify financial reforms.&lt;ref&gt;Fraser, 326&lt;/ref&gt; Louis Stanislas favoured a stalwart position against the Third Estate and its demands for tax reform. On 17 June, the Third Estate declared itself a [[National Assembly (French Revolution)|National Assembly]], an Assembly not of the Estates, but of the People.

Louis Stanislas urged the King to act strongly against the declaration, while the King's popular minister, [[Jacques Necker]], intended to compromise with the new assembly. Louis XVI was characteristically indecisive. On 9 July, the assembly declared itself a [[National Constituent Assembly]], that would give France a Constitution. On 11 July, Louis XVI dismissed Jacques Necker, which led to widespread rioting across Paris. On 12 July, the sabre charge of [[Charles-Eugène de Lorraine, prince de Lambesc]]'s cavalry regiment, the ''[[Royal-Allemand]]'', on a crowd gathered at the [[Tuileries Palace|Tuileries gardens]], sparked the [[Storming of the Bastille]] two days later.&lt;ref&gt;''Le Petit Robert 2'', Dictionnaire universel des noms propres, Dictionnaires Le Robert, Paris, 1988, p. 1017.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lever, Evelyne, ''Louis XVI'', Fayard, Paris, 1985, p. 508.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 16 July, the ''comte d’Artois'' left France with his wife and children, along with many other courtiers.&lt;ref&gt;Fraser, 338&lt;/ref&gt; Artois and his family took up residence in [[Turin]], the capital city of his father-in-law’s [[Kingdom of Sardinia]], with the [[Princes of Condé|Condé family]].&lt;ref&gt;Nagel, 65&lt;/ref&gt;

Louis Stanislas decided to remain at [[Palace of Versailles|Versailles]].&lt;ref&gt;Fraser, 340&lt;/ref&gt; When the royal family plotted to abscond from Versailles to [[Metz]], Louis Stanislas advised the King not to leave, to which the latter duly agreed.&lt;ref&gt;Fraser, 342&lt;/ref&gt;

The royal family was ripped away from their Palace at Versailles, the day after the 5 October 1789 [[The Women's March on Versailles|women's march on Versailles]].&lt;ref&gt;Fraser, 357&lt;/ref&gt; In Paris, the ''Comte'' and his wife lodged in the [[Luxembourg Palace]], while the rest of the royal family stayed in the [[Tuileries Palace]].&lt;ref&gt;Fraser, 361–362&lt;/ref&gt; In March 1791, the National Assembly created a law outlining the regency of Louis Charles in case his father died while he was still too young to reign. The law created the potential regency as follows: Louis Charles' nearest male relative in France (presently the ''comte de Provence'' Louis Stanislas), and after him, the regency would be given to the [[Louis Philippe II, Duke of Orléans|''duc d’Orléans'']], and if he were unavailable, the regency would go to election.&lt;ref&gt;Fraser, 383&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''comte de Provence'' and his wife fled to the [[Austrian Netherlands]] in conjunction with the royal family’s failed [[Flight to Varennes]] in June 1791.&lt;ref&gt;Fraser, 412&lt;/ref&gt;

==Exile==
===The early years===
When the ''comte de Provence'' arrived in the [[Low Countries]], he proclaimed himself ''de facto'' [[regent]] of France. Louis Stanislas exploited a document that he and Louis XVI had written&lt;ref&gt;Nagel, 113&lt;/ref&gt; before the latter's failed escape to Varennes. The document gave Louis Stanislas the regency in the event of his brother's death, or inability to perform his role as King. Louis Stanislas would join the other princes-in-exile at [[Coblenz]] soon after his escape. It was there that the comte d’Artois, the Condés and the comte de Provence, proclaimed that their objective was to invade France. Louis XVI was greatly annoyed by his brothers' behaviour. Provence sent emissaries to various European courts asking for financial aid, soldiers, and munition. Artois secured a castle for the court in exile in the [[Electorate of Trier]], where their maternal uncle, [[Clemens Wenceslaus of Saxony]], was the [[Prince-elector|Archbishop-Elector]]. Louis Stanislas' rallying bore fruit when the rulers of [[Prussia]] and [[Archduchy of Austria|Austria]] gathered at [[Dresden]]. They released the [[Declaration of Pillnitz]] in August 1791, which urged Europe to intervene in France if Louis XVI or his family were threatened. Provence's endorsement of the declaration was not well received in France, by the people, or by Louis XVI.&lt;ref&gt;Nagel 113&amp;nbsp;– 114&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 1792, the Legislative Assembly declared that all the ''émigrés'' were traitors to France. Their property and titles were confiscated.&lt;ref&gt;Nagel, 118&lt;/ref&gt; The monarchy of France was abolished by the [[National Convention]] on 21 September 1792.&lt;ref&gt;Hibbert, 180&lt;/ref&gt;

Louis XVI was executed in January 1793. This left his young son, Louis Charles, as titular King [[Louis XVII of France]]. The princes-in-exile proclaimed Louis Charles &quot;King Louis XVII&quot;. Louis Stanislas now unilaterally declared himself regent for his nephew, who was too young to be head of the House of Bourbon (since the French monarchy had been abolished for several months, Louis XVII never actually ruled, and any claim to regency would have been in name only).&lt;ref&gt;Nagel, 136&lt;/ref&gt;

Young Louis XVII's reign did not last long as he died in June 1795. His only surviving sibling was his sister [[Marie-Thérèse Charlotte de France]], ''Madame Royale,'' who was not considered a candidate for the throne because of France's traditional adherence to [[Salic Law]]. Thus on 16 June, the princes-in-exile declared the comte de Provence &quot;King Louis XVIII&quot;. The new King accepted their declaration soon after.&lt;ref&gt;Nagel, 152–153&lt;/ref&gt; Louis XVIII busied himself drafting a manifesto in response to Louis XVII's death. The manifesto, known as &quot;The Declaration of Verona&quot; was Louis XVIII's attempt to introduce the French people to his politics. The Declaration of Verona beckoned France back into the arms of the monarchy, &quot;which for fourteen centuries was the glory of France&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mansel, 111&quot;/&gt;

Louis XVIII negotiated Marie-Thérèse’s release from her Paris prison in 1795. Louis XVIII desperately wanted Marie-Thérèse to marry her first cousin, [[Louis-Antoine, Duke of Angoulême|Louis Antoine, duc d’Angoulême]], the son of the comte d'Artois. Louis XVIII deceived his niece by telling her that her parents' last wishes were for her to marry Louis Antoine, and Marie-Thérèse duly agreed to her uncle-king's wishes.&lt;ref&gt;Nagel, 165&lt;/ref&gt;

Louis XVIII was forced to abandon Verona when [[Napoleon Bonaparte]] invaded the [[Republic of Venice]].&lt;ref name=Nagel190&gt;Nagel, 190&lt;/ref&gt;

===1796&amp;nbsp;– 1807===
[[Image:Pils Jelgava.jpg|thumb|500px|[[Jelgava Palace]], Louis XVIII's residence from 1798 to 1801, and from 1804 to 1807.]]

Louis XVIII had been vying for the custody of his niece Marie-Thérèse since her release from the Temple Tower in December 1795. Louis succeeded when [[Francis II, Holy Roman Emperor]] agreed to relinquish custody of Marie-Thérèse in 1796. She had been staying in [[Vienna]] with her [[Habsburg]] relatives since January 1796.&lt;ref name=Nagel190/&gt; Louis XVIII moved to [[Blankenburg]] in the [[Duchy of Brunswick]] (Braunschweig) after his departure from Verona. He lived in a modest two-bedroom apartment over a shop.&lt;ref name=Nagel203&gt;Nagel, 203&lt;/ref&gt; Louis XVIII was forced to leave Blankenberg when King [[Frederick William II of Prussia]] died. In light of this, Marie-Thérèse decided to wait a while longer before reuniting with her uncle.&lt;ref&gt;Nagel, 201&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1798, [[Paul I of Russia|Emperor Paul I]] of [[Empire of Russia|Russia]] offered Louis the use of [[Jelgava Palace]] in [[Courland]] (now Latvia). Paul I also guaranteed Louis's safety and bestowed upon him a generous pension,&lt;ref name=Nagel203/&gt; however, the Emperor later disregarded this allowance.&lt;ref name=Nagel216&gt;Nagel, 216&lt;/ref&gt; Marie-Thérèse finally joined Louis XVIII at Jelgava in 1799.&lt;ref&gt;Nagel, 206&lt;/ref&gt; In the winter of 1798–1799, Louis XVIII wrote a biography on [[Marie Antoinette]] titled ''Réflexions Historiques sur Marie Antoinette''. He attempted to recreate the court life of Versailles at Jelgava, where many old courtiers lived, reestablishing all the court ceremonies, including the ''lever'' and ''coucher'' (ceremonies that accompanied waking and bedding, respectively).&lt;ref name=&quot;Nagel, 213&quot;&gt;Nagel, 213&lt;/ref&gt;

Marie-Thérèse married her cousin Louis Antoine on 9 June 1799, at Jelgava Palace. Louis XVIII ordered his wife to attend the marriage ceremony in [[Courland]] without her long-time friend (and rumoured lover) [[Madame de Gourbillon]]. [[Princess Marie Josephine Louise of Savoy|Queen Marie Joséphine]] lived apart from her husband in [[Schleswig Holstein]]. Louis XVIII was trying desperately to display to the world a united family front. The Queen refused to leave her friend behind with unpleasant consequences that rivalled the wedding in notoriety.&lt;ref&gt;Nagel, 210–211&lt;/ref&gt; Louis XVIII knew that his nephew Louis Antoine was not compatible with Marie-Thérèse. Despite this, he still pressed for the marriage, which proved to be quite unhappy and produced no children.&lt;ref&gt;Nagel, 208&lt;/ref&gt;

Louis XVIII attempted to strike up a correspondence with Napoleon Bonaparte (now First Consul of France) in 1800. Louis XVIII urged Bonaparte to restore the Bourbons to their throne, but the future emperor was immune to Louis's requests and continued to consolidate his position as ruler of France.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 128&lt;/ref&gt;

Louis XVIII encouraged his niece to write her memoirs, as he wished them to be used as Bourbon propaganda. Louis also used the diaries of Louis XVI's final attendants in the same way, in 1796 and in 1803.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nagel, 213&quot;/&gt; In January 1801, Tsar Paul told Louis XVIII that he could no longer live in Russia. The court at Jelgava was so low on funds that it had to auction some of its possessions to afford the journey out of Russia. Marie-Thérèse even sold a diamond necklace that the Emperor Paul had given her as a wedding gift.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nagel216&quot;/&gt;

Marie-Thérèse persuaded [[Queen Louise of Prussia]] to give her family refuge in Prussian territory. Louise consented, but the Bourbons were forced to assume pseudonyms. With Louis XVIII using the title ''Comte d'Isle'' (named after his estate in [[Languedoc]]), he and his family assumed residence in [[Warsaw]] in the Lazienki Palace from 1801 to 1804, after an arduous voyage from Jelgava.&lt;ref&gt;Nagel 218–219&lt;/ref&gt; It was very soon after their arrival that they learned of the death of Paul I. Louis hoped that Paul's successor, [[Alexander I of Russia]], would repudiate his father's banishment of the Bourbons (which he later did). Louis XVIII then intended to set off to the Neapolitan court. Charles, comte d'Artois, asked Louis to send his son, Louis Antoine, and daughter-in-law, Marie-Thérèse, to him in [[Edinburgh]]. Charles had an allowance from King [[George III of Great Britain]] and sent some money to Louis. He requested that his son Louis Antoine and daughter-in-law Marie Thérèse to join him in Edinburgh, but they did not at this time. Louis XVIII's court in exile was being spied on by French police.&lt;ref&gt;Nagel, 220&lt;/ref&gt; The court-in-exile was being financed mainly by interest owed from Francis II on valuables his aunt, Marie Antoinette, had removed from France and had to cut its expenses significantly.&lt;ref&gt;Nagel, 222&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1803, Napoleon tried to force Louis XVIII to renounce his right to the throne of France, but Louis refused.&lt;ref&gt;Nagel, 223&lt;/ref&gt; In May 1804, Napoleon Bonaparte declared himself [[Emperor of the French]]. Louis XVIII and his nephew departed for Sweden in July for a Bourbon family conference, where Louis XVIII, the comte d’Artois, and the duc d'Angoulême issued a statement condemning Napoleon's decision to declare himself emperor.&lt;ref&gt;Nagel, 227 – 228&lt;/ref&gt; The King of Prussia issued a proclamation saying that Louis XVIII would have to leave Prussian territory, which meant leaving Warsaw. Alexander I of Russia invited Louis XVIII to resume residence in Jelgava. Louis XVIII had to live under less generous conditions than those enjoyed under Paul I, and he intended to embark for England as soon as possible.&lt;ref&gt;Nagel, 228–229&lt;/ref&gt;

Louis XVIII created another policy in 1805: a declaration that was far more liberal than his former ones. It repudiated his Declaration of Verona, promised to abolish conscription, keep Napoleon I's administrative and judicial system, reduce taxes, eliminate political prisons, and guarantee amnesty to everyone who did not oppose a Bourbon Restoration. The opinions expressed in the declaration were largely those of the [[Avaray|comte d’Avaray]] (Louis's best friend in exile).&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 119&lt;/ref&gt;

Louis XVIII was forced once again to leave Jelgava when Alexander of Russia informed him that his safety could not be guaranteed on continental Europe. In July 1807, Louis boarded a Swedish [[frigate]] to [[Stockholm]], bringing with him only the duc d'Angoulême. Louis did not stay in Sweden for long, and arrived in [[Great Yarmouth]], Norfolk, England, in November 1807. He took up residence in [[Gosfield Hall]], leased to him by the [[Richard Temple-Grenville, 1st Duke of Buckingham and Chandos|Marquess of Buckingham]].&lt;ref&gt;Nagel, 233–234&lt;/ref&gt;

===England===
[[Image:Hartwell House, Bucks.jpg|thumb|280 px|[[Hartwell House, Buckinghamshire]], Louis XVIII's court-in-exile from 1808 until the Restoration.]]
Louis brought his wife and Queen, Marie Joséphine, from mainland Europe in 1808. Louis's stay at Gosfield Hall did not last long, and he moved to [[Hartwell House, Buckinghamshire|Hartwell House]] in Buckinghamshire, where over one hundred courtiers were housed.&lt;ref&gt;Nagel, 235&lt;/ref&gt;  The King paid £500 in rent each year to the proprietor, [[Sir George Lee]]. The [[George IV of the United Kingdom|Prince Regent]] of the United Kingdom was very charitable to the exiled Bourbons, granting them permanent [[right of asylum|asylum]] and giving them extremely generous allowances.&lt;ref&gt;Nagel, 243&lt;/ref&gt;

The comte d'Artois did not join the court-in-exile in Hartwell, continuing his frivolous life in London. Louis's friend the comte d'Avaray left Hartwell for [[Madeira]] in 1809, and died there in 1811. Louis replaced Avaray with the [[Pierre Louis Jean Casimir de Blacas|Comte de Blacas]]. Louis XVIII's wife, Queen Marie Joséphine, died on 13 November 1810.&lt;ref&gt;Nagel, 241&lt;/ref&gt; That same winter, Louis suffered a particularly severe case of gout, which was a recurring problem for him at Hartwell, and he had to be put in a wheelchair.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 147&lt;/ref&gt;

Napoleon I embarked on an [[French invasion of Russia|invasion of Russia]] in 1812. This war would prove to be the turning point in his fortunes, as the expedition failed miserably and Napoleon was forced to retreat with an army in tatters.

In 1813, Louis XVIII issued another declaration while at Hartwell. &quot;The Declaration of Hartwell&quot; was more liberal than his &quot;Declaration of 1805&quot;, asserting that all those who served Napoleon or the Republic would not suffer repercussions for their acts, and that the original owners of the ''[[Biens nationaux]]'' (lands confiscated from the nobles and clergy during the Revolution) were to be compensated for their losses.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 162&lt;/ref&gt;

Allied troops entered Paris on 31 March 1814.&lt;ref&gt;Price, Munro, ''The Perilous Crown'', Pan Books, 2 May 2008,ISBN 978-0-330-42638-1, p. 143&lt;/ref&gt; Louis was, however, unable to walk, and so sent the comte d'Artois to France in January 1814. Louis XVIII issued [[letters patent]] appointing Artois Lieutenant General of the Kingdom in the event of the Bourbons being restored. Napoleon I abdicated on 11 April, five days after his [[French Senate|Senate]] had invited the Bourbons to re-assume the throne of France.&lt;ref&gt;[http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k4861135.image.f36.langFR], [http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k4861135.image.f57.langFR]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Bourbon Restoration==
{{Main|Bourbon Restoration}}
[[Image:Louis XVIII relevant la France.jpg|280 px|thumb|''Allégorie du retour des Bourbons le 24 avril 1814 : Louis XVIII relevant la France de ses ruines'', by [[Louis-Philippe Crépin]]]]

===Restoration I===
The comte d'Artois ruled as Lieutenant-General of the Kingdom until his brother's arrival in Paris on 3 May. Upon his return, the King displayed himself to his subjects by creating a procession through the city. He took up residence in the [[Tuileries Palace]] the same day. His niece, the duchesse d'Angoulême, fainted at the sight of the Tuileries.&lt;ref&gt;Price, 113&lt;/ref&gt;

Napoleon's senate called Louis XVIII to the throne on the condition that he would accept the new constitution, which entailed recognition of the Republic and the Empire, a bicameral parliament elected every year, and the tri-colour flag of the aforementioned regimes.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 175&lt;/ref&gt; Louis XVIII opposed the senate's constitution, and stated that he was &quot;disbanding the current senate in all the crimes of Bonaparte, and appealing to the French people&quot;. The senatorial constitution was burned in a theatre in royalist Bordeaux, and the Municipal Council of Lyon voted for a speech that defamed the senate.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 176&lt;/ref&gt;

The armies occupying Paris demanded that Louis XVIII implement a constitution.&lt;ref&gt;Price, 52&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Charter of 1814]] that Louis created entailed all that Saint-Ouen wished for and more: [[Freedom of Religion]], a legislature composed of the [[Chamber of Deputies (France)|Chamber of Deputies]]&lt;ref&gt;The Chamber of Deputies is comparable to the [[House of Commons of Great Britain|House of Commons]]. To have the right to vote for the Chamber of Deputies, one had to be an adult male and pay 300 francs a year in tax.&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Chamber of Peers (France)|Chamber of Peers]],&lt;ref&gt;The Chamber of Peers was the upper house of the legislature, and was akin to the UK House of Lords.&lt;/ref&gt; the press would enjoy a degree of freedom, the ''[[biens nationaux]]''&lt;ref&gt;The ''biens nationaux'' were estates and goods, including art works, that the Republic confiscated from the ''clergé'', ''noblesse'' and ''émigrés'' during the Revolution. Those who lost their estate and/or other valuables would later be compensated in the reign of Louis XVIII’s brother, Charles X.&lt;/ref&gt; would remain in the hands of their current owners.&lt;ref&gt;Price, 53&lt;/ref&gt; The constitution had 76 articles. Taxation was to be voted on by the chambers.

Catholicism was the official religion of France. To be eligible for election to the Chamber of Deputies, one had to pay over 1,000 [[francs]] per year in tax, and be over the age of forty. The King appointed peers to the Chamber of Peers on a hereditary basis, or for life at his discretion. Deputies were elected every five years, with one fifth of them up for election each year.&lt;ref&gt;Price, 54&lt;/ref&gt; There were 90,000 citizens eligible to vote.&lt;ref&gt;Price, 55&lt;/ref&gt;

Louis XVIII signed the [[Treaty of Paris (1814)|Treaty of Paris]] on 30 May 1814. The treaty gave France her 1792 borders, which extended east of the [[Rhine]]. She had to pay no war indemnity, and the occupying armies of the [[War of the Sixth Coalition|Sixth Coalition]] withdrew instantly from French soil. These generous terms would be reversed in the next Treaty of Paris after the [[Hundred Days]] (Napoleon's return to France in 1815).&lt;ref&gt;Price, 69&lt;/ref&gt;

It did not take Louis XVIII long to go back on one of his many promises. He and his Controller-General of Finance [[Joseph Dominique, baron Louis|Baron Louis]] were determined not to let the exchequer fall into deficit (there was a 75&amp;nbsp;million franc debt inherited from Napoleon I), and took fiscal measures to ensure this. Louis XVIII assured the French that the unpopular tax on tobacco, wine and salt would be abolished when he was restored, but he failed to do so, which led to rioting in Bordeaux. Expenditure on the army was slashed in the 1815 budget&amp;nbsp;— in 1814, the military had accounted for 55% of government spending.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 190&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Coin image box 1 double
| header = Gold coin of Louis XVIII, struck 1815
| image = Image:LouisXVIIIGoldCoin.jpg
| caption_left = &lt;SMALL&gt;Obverse: (French) ''LOUIS XVIII, ROI DE FRANCE,'' in English: &quot;Louis XVIII, King of France&quot;&lt;/SMALL&gt;
|caption_right = &lt;SMALL&gt;Reverse: (French) ''PIECE DE 20 FRANCS, 1815,'' in English: &quot;20 Franc Piece, 1815.&quot;&lt;/SMALL&gt;
|width = 220
|position = left
|margin = 0
}}
Louis XVIII admitted the comte d'Artois and his nephews, the duc d'Angoulême, and the duc de Berry into the King's council in May 1814, upon its establishment. The council was informally headed by the [[Charles Maurice de Talleyrand-Périgord|Prince de Talleyrand]].&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 192&lt;/ref&gt; Louis XVIII took a large interest in the goings-on of the [[Congress of Vienna]] (set up to redraw the map of Europe after Napoleon's demise). Talleyrand represented France at the proceedings. Louis was horrified by Prussia's intention to annex the [[Kingdom of Saxony]], to which he was attached because his mother was born a Saxon princess, and he was also concerned that Prussia would dominate Germany. He also wished the [[Duchy of Parma]] to be restored to the Parmese Bourbons, and not to [[Marie Louise, Duchess of Parma|Empress Marie Louise of France]], as was being suggested by the Allies.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 196&lt;/ref&gt; Louis also protested the Allies' inaction in Naples, where he wanted the Napoleonic usurper [[Joachim Murat]] removed in favour of the Neapolitan Bourbons.

On behalf of the Allies, Austria agreed to send a force to the [[Kingdom of Naples]] to depose Murat in February 1815, when it became apparent that Murat corresponded with Napoleon I, which was explicitly forbidden by a recent treaty. Murat never actually wrote to Napoleon, but Louis, intent on restoring the Neapolitan Bourbons at any cost, forged the correspondence, and subsidised the Austrian expedition with 25&amp;nbsp;million francs.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 197&lt;/ref&gt;

Louis XVIII succeeded in getting the Neapolitan Bourbons restored immediately. Parma was bestowed upon Empress Marie Louise for life, and the Parmese Bourbons were given the [[Duchy of Lucca]] until the death of Marie Louise.

===Hundred Days===
{{Main|Hundred Days}}
[[Image:Andrieux - La bataille de Waterloo.jpg|thumb|The Battle of Waterloo put a definite end to Napoleon Bonaparte's attempt to return to France and thus secured the Bourbon restoration]]
On 26 February 1815, Napoleon Bonaparte escaped his island prison of [[Elba]] and embarked for France. He arrived with about 1,000 troops near [[Cannes]] on 1 March. Louis XVIII was not particularly worried by Bonaparte's excursion, as such small numbers of troops could be easily overcome. There was, however, a major underlying problem for the Bourbons: Louis XVIII had failed to purge the military of its [[Bonapartist]] troops. This led to mass desertions from the Bourbon armies to Bonaparte's. Furthermore, Louis XVIII could not join the campaign against Napoleon in the south of France because he was suffering from another case of gout.&lt;ref&gt;Price, 75&lt;/ref&gt; Minister of War [[Jean-de-Dieu Soult|Marshall Soult]] dispatched Louis Philippe d'Orléans, the comte d'Artois and [[Jacques MacDonald|Marshall MacDonald]] to apprehend Napoleon.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 222&lt;/ref&gt;

Louis XVIII's underestimation of Bonaparte proved disastrous. On 19 March, the army stationed outside Paris defected to Bonaparte, leaving the city vulnerable to attack.&lt;ref&gt;Price, 79&lt;/ref&gt; That same day, Louis XVIII quit the capital with a small escort at midnight. Louis decided to go first to [[Lille]], and then crossed the border into the [[United Kingdom of the Netherlands]], staying in [[Ghent]].&lt;ref&gt;Price, 80&lt;/ref&gt; Other leaders, most prominently [[Alexander I of Russia]], debated that in case of a second victory over the [[First French Empire|French Empire]], the [[Prince du Sang|First Prince of the Blood]] [[Louis-Philippe I, King of the French|Louis Philippe d'Orléans]] should be proclaimed king instead of Louis XVIII.&lt;ref&gt;Price, 81&lt;/ref&gt;

However, Napoleon did not rule France again for very long, suffering a decisive defeat at the hands of the armies of the [[Arthur Wellesley, 1st Duke of Wellington|Duke of Wellington]] and [[Gebhard Leberecht von Blücher|Field Marshal Blücher]] at the [[Battle of Waterloo]] on 18 June. Leaders came to the consensus that Louis XVIII should be restored to the throne of France.&lt;ref&gt;Price, 82–83&lt;/ref&gt;

===1815&amp;nbsp;– 1824===
[[Image:Louis XVIII2.jpg|thumb|Louis XVIII in ''robes du sacre'' by [[François Gérard]].]]
[[Image:Cruikshank - Old Bumblehead.png|right|thumb|''Old Bumblehead the 18th trying on the Napoleon Boots – or, Preparing for the Spanish Campaign'', by [[George Cruikshank]], mocked the [[Hundred Thousand Sons of Saint Louis|French Intervention in Spain]].]]
[[Image:La famille royale by Gautier.jpg|right|thumb|The Royal Family. From left to right: [[Charles X|Charles, comte d'Artois]], Louis XVIII, [[Princess Caroline Ferdinande of Bourbon-Two Sicilies|Marie Caroline, duchesse de Berry]], [[Marie-Thérèse Charlotte de France|Marie Thérèse, duchesse d'Angoulême]], [[Louis-Antoine, Duke of Angoulême|Louis Antoine, duc d'Angoulême]] and [[Charles Ferdinand, Duke of Berry|Charles Ferdinand, duc de Berry.]]]]
Louis XVIII returned to France promptly after Napoleon's defeat, to ensure his second restoration &quot;in baggage train of the enemy&quot;, i.e. with Wellington's troops.&lt;ref&gt;Price, 83&lt;/ref&gt; The Duke of Wellington used King Louis's person to open up the route to Paris, as some fortresses refused to surrender to the Allies, but agreed to do so for their King. King Louis arrived at [[Cambrai]] on 26 June, where he released a proclamation stating that all those who served the Emperor in the Hundred Days would not be persecuted, except for the &quot;instigators&quot;. It was also acknowledged that Louis XVIII's government might have made mistakes during the First Restoration.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 253&lt;/ref&gt; On 29 June, a deputation of five from the Chamber of Deputies and the Chamber of Peers approached Wellington about putting a foreign Prince on the throne of France. Wellington rejected their pleas outright, declaring that &quot;[Louis XVIII is] the best way to preserve the integrity of France&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 254&lt;/ref&gt; Wellington ordered the deputies to espouse King Louis's cause.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 255&lt;/ref&gt; Louis XVIII entered Paris on 8 July to a boisterous reception: the Tuileries Palace gardens were thronged with bystanders, and, according to the Duke of Wellington, the acclamation of the crowds there were so loud that evening, that he could not converse with the King.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 256&lt;/ref&gt;

Louis XVIII's role in politics from the Hundred Days onward was voluntarily diminished; he resigned most of his duties to his council. He and his ministry embarked on a series of reforms through the summer of 1815. The King's council, an informal group of ministers that advised Louis XVIII, was dissolved and replaced by a tighter knit [[privy council]], the ''&quot;Ministère de Roi&quot;''. Artois, Berry and Angoulême were purged from the new ''&quot;ministère&quot;'', and Talleyrand was appointed as the first ''Président du Conseil'', i.e. Prime Minister of France.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 260&lt;/ref&gt; On 14 July, the ministry dissolved the units of the army deemed &quot;rebellious&quot;. Hereditary peerage was re-established to Louis's behest by the ministry.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 261&lt;/ref&gt;

In August elections for the Chamber of Deputies returned unfavourable results for Talleyrand. The ministry wished for moderate deputies, but the electorate voted almost exclusively for [[ultra-royalists]], resulting in the ''[[Chambre introuvable]]''. The duchesse d'Angoulême and the comte d'Artois pressured King for the dismissal of his obsolete ministry. Talleyrand tendered his resignation on 20 September. Louis XVIII chose [[Armand-Emmanuel du Plessis, duc de Richelieu]] to be his new Prime Minister. Richelieu was chosen because he was accepted by Louis's family and the reactionary Chamber of Deputies.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 266&lt;/ref&gt;

Anti-Napoleonic sentiment was high in Southern France, and this was prominently displayed in the [[Second White Terror|White Terror]]. The White Terror saw the purge of all important Napoleonic officials from government, and the execution of others. The people of France committed barbarous acts against some of these officials. [[Guillaume Marie Anne Brune]] (a Napoleonic marshal) was savagely assassinated, and his remains thrown into the [[Rhône River]].&lt;ref&gt;Lever, Évelyne, ''Louis XVIII'', Fayard, Paris, 1988, p. 417.&lt;/ref&gt; Louis XVIII deplored such illegal acts, but vehemently supported the prosecution of those marshals that helped Napoleon I in the Hundred Days.&lt;ref&gt;Price, 84&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 424&lt;/ref&gt; Louis XVIII’s government executed Napoleon's Marshal Ney, [[Michel Ney|Prince de la Moskowa]], in December 1815 for treason. His confidants the Marquis de Bonnay and the Duc de la Chatre advised him to inflict firm punishments on the “traitors”.

The King was reluctant to shed blood, and this greatly irritated the ultra-reactionary chamber of deputies, who felt that Louis XVIII was not executing enough.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 425&lt;/ref&gt; The government issued a proclamation of amnesty to the “traitors” in January 1816, but the trials that had already begun were finished in due course. That same declaration also banned any member of the [[House of Bonaparte]] from owning property in, or entering, France.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 426&lt;/ref&gt; It is estimated that between 50,000&amp;nbsp;– 80,000 officials were purged from the government during what was known as the [[Second White Terror]].&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 427&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 1815, Louis XVIII’s government had to sign another [[Treaty of Paris (1815)|Treaty of Paris]], formally ending Napoleon’s hundred days. The previous treaty had been quite favourable to France, but this one took a hard-line. France’s borders were retracted to their extent at 1790. France had to pay for an army to occupy her, for at least five years, at a cost of 150&amp;nbsp;million francs per year. France also had to pay a [[war indemnity]] of 700&amp;nbsp;million francs to the allies.&lt;ref&gt;Price, 89&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1818, the Chambers passed a military law, which increased the size of the army by over 100,000. In October of the same year, Louis XVIII’s foreign minister, the [[Armand-Emmanuel du Plessis, Duc de Richelieu|Duc de Richelieu]], succeeded in convincing the powers to withdraw their armies early, in exchange for a sum of over 200&amp;nbsp;million francs.&lt;ref&gt;Price, 95–96&lt;/ref&gt;

Louis XVIII chose many centrist cabinets, as he wanted to appease the populace. Much to the dismay of his brother, the [[ultra-royalist]] comte d’Artois,&lt;ref&gt;Price, 93&lt;/ref&gt; he always dreaded the day he would die, believing that his brother, and heir, Artois, would abandon the centrist government for an ultra-royalist autocracy, which would not bring favourable results.&lt;ref&gt;Price, 94&lt;/ref&gt;

King Louis disliked the [[Prince of the Blood|First Prince of the Blood]], Louis-Philippe d'Orléans, and took every opportunity to snub him.&lt;ref&gt;Price, 98&lt;/ref&gt; King Louis's nephew, the [[Charles Ferdinand, Duke of Berry|duc de Berry]], was assassinated at the Paris Opera, on 14 February 1820. The royal family was grief-stricken&lt;ref name=Prince106-107&gt;Price, 106–107&lt;/ref&gt; and Louis XVIII broke an ancient tradition to attend his nephew's funeral, as previous Kings of France could not have any association with death.&lt;ref&gt;Mansel, 194&lt;/ref&gt;

Berry was the only member of the family thought to be able to beget children. His wife gave birth to a posthumous son in September [[Henri, comte de Chambord|Henri, duc de Bordeaux]].&lt;ref name=Prince106-107/&gt; The future of the Bourbons as kings of France was in still doubt. The Chamber of Deputies proposed amending the [[Salic law]] to allow the Duchesse d’Angoulême to accede to the throne.&lt;ref&gt;Nagel, 287&lt;/ref&gt; On 12 June 1820, the Chambers ratified legislation that increased the number of deputies from 258 to 430. The extra deputies were to be elected by the wealthiest quarter of the population in each département. These individuals now effectively had two votes.&lt;ref&gt;Price, 108&lt;/ref&gt; Around the same time as the “law of the two votes”, Louis XVIII began to receive visits every Wednesday from a lady named [[Zoé Talon, comtesse du Cayla]], and ordered that nobody should disturb him while he was with her. It was rumoured that he inhaled [[snuff]] from her breasts,&lt;ref&gt;Price, 109&lt;/ref&gt; which earned her the nickname of ''tabatière'' (snuffbox).&lt;ref&gt;Lever, ''Louis XVIII'', 537&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1823, France embarked on a military intervention in Spain, where a revolt had occurred against the King [[Ferdinand VII of Spain|Ferdinand VII]]. France succeeded in crushing the rebellion,&lt;ref&gt;Price, 110&lt;/ref&gt; which the duc d’Angoulême headed.&lt;ref&gt;Nagel&lt;/ref&gt;

===Death===
[[Image:Tombe louis XVIII roi de france saint-denis.JPG|left|thumb|Louis XVIII's grave, at the [[Basilica of St Denis]], Paris.]]

Louis XVIII's health began to fail in the spring of 1824. He was suffering from obesity, [[gout]] and [[gangrene]], both dry and wet, in his legs and spine. Louis died on 16 September 1824, surrounded by the extended royal family and some government officials. He was succeeded by his youngest brother, the comte d’Artois, as [[Charles X of France|Charles X]].&lt;ref&gt;Nagel, 297–298&lt;/ref&gt;

Louis XVIII was the only French monarch of the 19th century to die while still ruling. He was interred at the [[Basilica of St Denis]], the necropolis of French kings.

==Ancestors==
&lt;center&gt;{{ahnentafel-compact5
|style=font-size: 90%; line-height: 110%;
|border=1
|boxstyle=padding-top: 0; padding-bottom: 0;
|boxstyle_1=background-color: #fcc;
|boxstyle_2=background-color: #fb9;
|boxstyle_3=background-color: #ffc;
|boxstyle_4=background-color: #bfc;
|boxstyle_5=background-color: #9fe;
|1= 1. '''Louis XVIII of France'''
|2= 2. [[Louis, Dauphin of France (1729-1765)|Louis, Dauphin of France]]
|3= 3. [[Maria Josepha of Saxony (1731–1767)|Princess Maria Josepha of Saxony]]
|4= 4. [[Louis XV of France]]
|5= 5. [[Marie Leszczyńska]]
|6= 6. [[Augustus III of Poland]]
|7= 7. [[Maria Josepha of Austria|Archduchess Maria Josepha of Austria]]
|8= 8. [[Louis of France, Duke of Burgundy|Louis, Dauphin of France and Duke of Burgundy]]
|9= 9. [[Princess Marie Adélaïde of Savoy]]
|10= 10. [[Stanisław Leszczyński]]
|11= 11. [[Katarzyna Opalińska]]
|12= 12. [[Augustus II the Strong|Augustus II of Poland]]
|13= 13. [[Christiane Eberhardine of Brandenburg-Bayreuth]]
|14= 14. [[Joseph I, Holy Roman Emperor]]
|15= 15. [[Wilhelmina Amalia of Brunswick]]
|16= 16. [[Louis, Dauphin of France (1661-1711)|Louis, Dauphin of France]]
|17= 17. [[Duchess Maria Anna Victoria of Bavaria]]
|18= 18. [[Victor Amadeus II of Sardinia]]
|19= 19. [[Anne Marie d'Orléans]]
|20= 20. [[Rafał Leszczyński (1650–1703)|Rafał Leszczyński]]
|21= 21. [[Anna Leszczyńska (1660-1727)|Anna Jabłonowska]]
|22= 22. [[Jan Karol Opaliński]]
|23= 23. [[Zofia Czarnkowska Opalińska|Zofia Czarnkowska]]
|24= 24. [[John George III, Elector of Saxony]]
|25= 25. [[Anne Sophie of Denmark]]
|26= 26. [[Christian Ernst, Margrave of Brandenburg-Bayreuth]]
|27= 27. Sophie Luise of Württemberg
|28= 28. [[Leopold I, Holy Roman Emperor]]
|29= 29. [[Eleonore-Magdalena of Neuburg]]
|30= 30. [[John Frederick, Duke of Brunswick-Lüneburg]]
|31= 31. [[Benedicta Henrietta of the Palatinate]]
}}&lt;/center&gt;

==In fiction==

Louis XVIII appears briefly in the novel ''[[The Count of Monte Cristo]]'', by [[Alexandre Dumas, père|Alexandre Dumas]]. The Count of Provence was portrayed by [[Sebastian Armesto]] in the 2006 film ''[[Marie Antoinette (2006 film)|Marie Antoinette]]'', a biographical film written and directed by [[Sofia Coppola]], based on the book, ''[[Marie Antoinette: The Journey]]'' by [[Lady Antonia Fraser]]. In contradiction with historical facts, he is portrayed in the film as having a son.
In the 1970 film ''[[Waterloo (1970 film)|Waterloo]]'', Louis XVIII was portrayed by [[Orson Welles]].

==References==
{{Portal|Kingdom of France}}

===Notes===
{{Reflist|3}}

===Sources===
* [[Évelyne Lever|Lever, Évelyne]], ''Louis XVIII'', Fayard, Paris, 1988. (paperback, ISBN 2-213-78010-1{{Please check ISBN|reason=Check digit (1) does not correspond to calculated figure.}} (French)
* Mansel, Philip. ''Louis XVIII''. Thrupp, Stroud, Gloucestershire, UK: Sutton Publishing, 1999 (paperback, ISBN 0-7509-2217-6).

==External links==
{{Commons category|Louis XVIII of France}}
*[http://www.nndb.com/people/834/000093555/ Louis XVIII at NNDB.COM]
*[http://thinkexist.com/quotation/punctuality_is_the_politeness_of/180612.html Quotes of Louis XVIII]

{{S-start}}
{{s-hou|[[House of Bourbon]]|17 November|1755|16 September|1824|[[Capetian dynasty]]}}
{{s-reg}}
|-
{{S-bef|before=[[Napoleon I of France|Napoléon I]]|as=[[List of French monarchs|Emperor of the French]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[List of French monarchs|King of France and Navarre]]|years=11 April 1814&amp;nbsp;– 20 March 1815}}
{{S-aft|after=[[Napoleon I of France|Napoléon I]]|as=[[List of French monarchs|Emperor of the French]]}}
|-
{{S-bef|before=[[Napoleon I of France|Napoléon I]]|as=[[List of French monarchs|Emperor of the French]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=King of France and Navarre|years=7 July 1815&amp;nbsp;– 16 September 1824}}
{{S-aft|after=[[Charles X of France|Charles X]]}}
|-
{{s-reg|fr}}
|-
{{s-vac|last=[[Philippe, Duke of Anjou|Philippe]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Counts and Dukes of Anjou|Duke of Anjou]]|years=1771&amp;nbsp;– 1790}}
{{s-vac|next=[[Jaime, Duke of Madrid|Jacques]]}}
|-
{{S-pre}}
|-
{{S-bef|before=[[Louis XVII of France|Louis XVII]]}}
{{s-tul|title=[[List of French monarchs|King of France]] and [[List of Navarrese monarchs|Navarre]]|years=8 June 1795&amp;nbsp;– 11 April 1814|reason=[[French Revolution]]}}
{{s-non|reason=Became king|reason2=[[Bourbon Restoration|Bourbon Restoration I]]}}
|-
{{s-new|loss|reason=[[Hundred Days|Return of Napoléon I]]}}
{{s-tul|title=[[List of French monarchs|King of France]] and [[List of Navarrese monarchs|Navarre]]|years=20 March&amp;nbsp;– 7 July 1815|reason=[[Hundred Days|Reign of the Hundred Days]]}}
{{s-non|reason=Regained title|reason2=[[Bourbon Restoration|Bourbon Restoration II]]}}
|-
{{s-roy|other}}
{{S-bef|before=[[Philippe I, Duke of Orléans|Philippe de France]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Fils de France|Monsieur]]|years=1774–1793}}
{{S-aft|after=[[Charles X of France|Charles Philippe de France]]}}
{{end}}

{{Princes of France (House of Bourbon)}}
{{Monarchs of France}}
{{French Pretenders}}
{{Dukes of Anjou}}
{{French Revolution navbox}}
{{France topics}}

{{Use British English|date=August 2010}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2011}}

{{Good article}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Louis 18 Of France
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = King of France
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 17 November 1755
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Palace of Versailles]], France
| DATE OF DEATH     = 16 September 1824
| PLACE OF DEATH    = Paris, France
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Louis 18 Of France}}
[[Category:1755 births]]
[[Category:1824 deaths]]
[[Category:People of the Bourbon Restoration]]
[[Category:Kings of France]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic monarchs]]
[[Category:French monarchs]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of the Black Eagle]]
[[Category:Regents of France]]
[[Category:People of the French Revolution]]
[[Category:House of Bourbon (France)]]
[[Category:Dukes of Anjou]]
[[Category:Dukes of Perche]]
[[Category:Dukes of Vendôme]]
[[Category:Counts of Provence]]
[[Category:Knights of the Garter]]
[[Category:Knights of the Golden Fleece]]
[[Category:Politicians with physical disabilities]]
[[Category:Princes of Andorra]]
[[Category:Princes of France (Bourbon)]]
[[Category:People from Versailles]]
[[Category:Heirs presumptive to the French throne]]
[[Category:House of Bourbon]]
[[Category:18th-century French people]]
[[Category:19th-century French people]]
[[Category:Grand Masters of the Order of the Holy Spirit]]
[[Category:Grand Masters of the Order of Saint Michael]]
[[Category:Dukes of Alençon|501]]

[[ar:لويس الثامن عشر]]
[[an:Loís XVIII de Francia]]
[[be:Людовік XVIII]]
[[bg:Луи XVIII]]
[[bs:Luj XVIII, kralj Francuske]]
[[br:Loeiz XVIII (Bro-C'hall)]]
[[ca:Lluís XVIII de França]]
[[cs:Ludvík XVIII.]]
[[cy:Louis XVIII, brenin Ffrainc]]
[[da:Ludvig 18. af Frankrig]]
[[de:Ludwig XVIII.]]
[[et:Louis XVIII]]
[[el:Λουδοβίκος ΙΗ΄ της Γαλλίας]]
[[es:Luis XVIII de Francia]]
[[eo:Ludoviko la 18-a (Francio)]]
[[eu:Luis XVIII.a Frantziakoa]]
[[fa:لوئی هجدهم]]
[[fr:Louis XVIII de France]]
[[gl:Luís XVIII de Francia]]
[[ko:루이 18세]]
[[hr:Luj XVIII., kralj Francuske]]
[[io:Louis 18ma]]
[[id:Louis XVIII dari Perancis]]
[[is:Loðvík 18.]]
[[it:Luigi XVIII di Francia]]
[[he:לואי השמונה עשר, מלך צרפת]]
[[ka:ლუი XVIII (საფრანგეთი)]]
[[la:Ludovicus XVIII]]
[[lv:Luijs XVIII]]
[[lt:Liudvikas XVIII]]
[[hu:XVIII. Lajos francia király]]
[[mk:Луј XVIII]]
[[mr:अठरावा लुई, फ्रान्स]]
[[arz:لويس التمنتاشر]]
[[ms:Louis XVIII dari Perancis]]
[[nl:Lodewijk XVIII van Frankrijk]]
[[ja:ルイ18世 (フランス王)]]
[[no:Ludvig XVIII av Frankrike]]
[[pl:Ludwik XVIII]]
[[pt:Luís XVIII de França]]
[[ro:Ludovic al XVIII-lea al Franței]]
[[ru:Людовик XVIII]]
[[simple:Louis XVIII of France]]
[[sk:Ľudovít XVIII.]]
[[sr:Луј XVIII]]
[[sh:Luj XVIII., kralj Francuske]]
[[fi:Ludvig XVIII]]
[[sv:Ludvig XVIII av Frankrike]]
[[th:พระเจ้าหลุยส์ที่ 18 แห่งฝรั่งเศส]]
[[tr:XVIII. Louis]]
[[uk:Людовик XVIII]]
[[vec:Luigi XVIII de Fransa]]
[[vi:Louis XVIII của Pháp]]
[[yo:Louis 18k ilẹ̀ Fránsì]]
[[zh:路易十八]]</text>
      <sha1>46e52ynm6f5inve2wer1ippjw5ugqx1</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
