<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Machiavellianism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2525856</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521884125</id>
      <parentid>517363998</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-07T20:55:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>71.171.98.247</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added hyperlink to &quot;theory of mind&quot; wikipedia page</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11916">[[File:Niccolo Machiavelli.jpg|thumb|[[Niccolò Machiavelli]]]]
'''Machiavellianism''' (or '''machiavellian mask''') is, according to the ''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]'', &quot;the employment of cunning and [[wikt:duplicity|duplicity]] in statecraft or in general conduct&quot;, deriving from the [[Italian Renaissance]] diplomat and writer [[Niccolò Machiavelli]], who wrote ''[[The Prince|Il Principe]]'' (''The Prince'') and other works. The word has a similar use in modern [[psychology]] where it describes one of the [[dark triad]] personalities, characterised by a duplicitous interpersonal style associated with [[Cynicism (contemporary)|cynical]] beliefs and pragmatic morality.&lt;ref name=handbook/&gt; &quot;Machiavellian&quot; (and variants) as a word became very popular in the late 16th century in English, though &quot;Machiavellianism&quot; itself is first cited by the [[Oxford English Dictionary]] from 1626.

==Political thought==
{{Main|Niccolò Machiavelli}} 
In the 16th century, immediately following the publication of the Prince, Machiavellianism was seen as a foreign plague infecting northern European politics, originating in Italy, and having first infected France. It was in this context that the [[St. Bartholomew's Day massacre]] of 1572 in Paris came to be seen as a product of Machiavellianism, a view greatly influenced by the [[Huguenot]] Innocent Gentillet, who published his ''Discours contre Machievel'' in 1576, which was printed in ten editions in three languages over the next four years.&lt;ref&gt;Anglo, 283 – see also the whole chapter&lt;/ref&gt; Gentillet held, quite wrongly according to Sydney Anglo, that Machiavelli's &quot;books [were] held most dear and precious by our Italian and Italionized [sic] courtiers&quot; in France (in the words of his first English translation), and so (in Anglo's paraphrase) &quot;at the root of France's present degradation, which has culminated not only in the St Bartholemew massacre but the glee of its perverted admirers&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Anglo, 286&lt;/ref&gt;  In fact there is little trace of Machiavelli in French writings before the massacre, not that politicians telegraph their intentions in writing, until Gentillet's own book, but this concept was seized upon by many contemporaries, and played a crucial part in setting the long-lasting popular concept of Machiavellianism.&lt;ref&gt;Anglo, Chapters 10 and 11; p. 328 etc.&lt;/ref&gt;

The English playwright [[Christopher Marlowe]] was an enthusiastic proponent of this view.  In ''[[The Jew of Malta]]'' (1589–90) &quot;Machievel&quot; in person speaks the Prologue, claiming not to be dead, but to have possessed the soul of (the Duke of) Guise, &quot;And, now the Guise is dead, is come from France/ To view this land, and frolic with his friends&quot; (Prologue, lines 3–4)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gutenberg.org/files/901/901-h/901-h.htm Project Gutenberg ''Jew of Malta'' text]&lt;/ref&gt; His last play, ''[[The Massacre at Paris]]'' (1593) takes the massacre, and the following years, as its subject, with [[Henry I, Duke of Guise|the Duke of Guise]] and [[Catherine de' Medici]] both depicted as Machiavellian plotters, bent on evil from the start.

The ''[[Anti-Machiavel]]'' is an 18th century essay by [[Frederick the Great]], King of [[Prussia]] and patron of [[Voltaire]], rebutting ''The Prince'', and Machiavellianism. It was first published in September 1740, a few months after Frederick became king, and is one of many such works.

==Psychology==
{{Main|Machiavellian intelligence}}
Machiavellianism is also a term that some social and personality [[Psychology|psychologists]] use to describe a person's tendency to be emotionally cool and detached, and thus more able to detach from conventional morality and to [[deceive]] and [[Psychological manipulation|manipulate]] others. In the 1960s, Richard Christie and Florence L. Geis developed a test for measuring a person's level of Machiavellianism. Their MACH-IV test, a twenty-statement personality survey, became the standard self-assessment tool of Machiavellianism. People scoring high on the scale (''high Machs'') tend to endorse statements such as, &quot;Never tell anyone the real reason you did something unless it is useful to do so,&quot; (No. 1) but not ones like, &quot;Most people are basically good and kind&quot; (No. 4), &quot;There is no excuse for [[lie|lying]] to someone else,&quot; (No. 7) or &quot;Most people who get ahead in the world lead clean, moral lives&quot; (No. 11). Using their scale, Christie and Geis conducted multiple experimental tests that showed that the interpersonal strategies and behavior of &quot;High Machs&quot; and &quot;Low Machs&quot; differ.&lt;ref name=basic&gt;Christie, R. &amp; Geis, F. (1970) &quot;Studies in Machiavellianism&quot;. NY: Academic Press.&lt;/ref&gt; Their basic results have been widely replicated.&lt;ref name=McIlwain&gt;McIlwain, D. 2003. Bypassing empathy: mapping a Machiavellian theory of mind and sneaky power. In Individual Differences In Theory Of Mind, eds. B. Repacholi and V. Slaughter. Macquarie Monographs in Cognitive Science. NY: Psychology Press. 39-68.&lt;/ref&gt; Measured on the Mach-IV scale, males are on average slightly more Machiavellian than females.&lt;ref name=&quot;basic&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=instrument&gt;Gunnthorsdottir, A., McCabe, K. &amp; Smith, V. 2002 &quot;Using the Machiavellianism instrument to predict trustworthiness in a bargaining game&quot;. Journal of Economic Psychology 23, 49-66&lt;/ref&gt;

===Motivation===
A 1992 review described Machiavellian motivation as related to cold selfishness and pure instrumentality, and those high on the trait were assumed to pursue their motives (e.g. sex, achievement, sociality) in duplicitous ways. More recent research on the motivations of high Machs compared to low Machs found that they gave high priority to money, power, and competition and relatively low priority to community building, self-love, and family concerns. High Machs admitted to focusing on unmitigated achievement and winning at any cost.&lt;ref name=handbook/&gt;

===Abilities===
Due to their skill at interpersonal manipulation, there has often been an assumption that high Machs possess superior intelligence, or ability to understand other people in social situations. However, research has firmly established that Machiavellianism is unrelated to [[IQ]]. Furthermore, studies on [[emotional intelligence]] have found that high Machiavellianism actually tends to be associated with low emotional intelligence as assessed by both performance and questionnaire measures. Both empathy and emotion recognition have been shown to have negative correlations with Machiavellianism. Additionally, research has shown that Machiavellianism is unrelated to a more advanced [[theory of mind]], that is, the ability to anticipate what others are thinking in social situations. If high Machs actually are skilled at manipulating others this appears to be unrelated to any special cognitive abilities as such.&lt;ref name=handbook/&gt;

=== Relations with other personality traits ===
Machiavellianism is one of the three personality traits referred to as the [[dark triad]], along with [[narcissism]] and [[psychopathy]]. Some psychologists consider Machiavellianism to be essentially a subclinical form of psychopathy,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Social Intelligence|last=Goleman |first=Daniel|authorlink=Daniel Goleman|year= 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; although recent research suggests that while Machiavellianism and psychopathy overlap, they are distinct personality constructs.&lt;ref name=handbook/&gt;&lt;ref name=Dark_Triad&gt;Paulhus, D.L. &amp; Williams, K.M. 2002. &quot;The Dark Triad of personality: Narcissism, Machiavellianism, and psychopathy&quot;. Journal of Research in Personality 36 (2002) 556–563&lt;/ref&gt;
Machiavellianism has been found to be negatively correlated with the [[Agreeableness]] (r = -.47) and [[Conscientiousness]] (r = -.34) dimensions of the [[Big five personality traits|Big Five]] personality model (NEO-PI-R).&lt;ref name=Dark_Triad/&gt; However, machiavellianism correlates more highly with the [[Honesty-humility]] dimension of the six-factor [[HEXACO model]] than with any of the Big Five dimensions.&lt;ref name=handbook&gt;{{cite book|title=Handbook of Individual Differences in Social Behavior|year=2009|publisher=The Guildford Press|location=New York/London|isbn=978-1-59385-647-2|pages=257–273|author=Jones, Daniel N.|coauthors=Paulhus, Delroy L.|editor=Leary, Mark R. &amp; Hoyle, Rick H|chapter=Chapter 7.  Machiavellianism}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Machiavellianism has also been located within the [[interpersonal circumplex]], which consists of the two independent dimensions of agency and communion. Agency refers to motivation to succeed and to individuate the self, whereas communion refers to motivation to merge with others and to support group interests. Machiavellianism lies in the quadrant of the circumplex defined by high agency and low communion.&lt;ref name=handbook/&gt; Machiavellianism has been found to lie diagonally opposite from a circumplex construct called ''self-construal'', a tendency to prefer communion over agency. This suggests that people high in machiavellianism do not simply wish to achieve, they wish to do so at the expense of (or at least without regard to) others.&lt;ref name=handbook/&gt;

===Game theory===

In 2002, the Machiavellianism scale of Christie and Geis was applied by behavioral game theorists Anna Gunnthorsdottir, [[Kevin McCabe]] and [[Vernon L. Smith]]&lt;ref name=&quot;instrument&quot;/&gt; in their search for explanations for the spread of observed behavior in experimental games, in particular individual choices which do not correspond to assumptions of material self-interest captured by the standard [[Nash equilibrium]] prediction. It was found that in a [[trust (social sciences)|trust]] game, those with high MACH-IV scores tended to follow [[homo economicus]]' equilibrium strategies while those with low MACH-IV scores tended to deviate from the equilibrium, and instead made choices that reflected widely accepted moral standards and [[social preferences]].

==See also==
{{columns-list|2|

*[[Antisocial personality disorder]]
*[[Egotism]]
*[[Gaming the system]]
*[[Social dominance orientation]]
}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Sources==
*Anglo, Sydney. ''Machiavelli – the First Century: Studies in Enthusiasm, Hostility, and Irrelevance'', p.&amp;nbsp;229, Oxford University Press, 2005, ISBN 0-19-926776-6, ISBN 978-0-19-926776-7 [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=-K6zI1iw90AC&amp;pg=PA232&amp;lpg=PA232&amp;dq=The+Massacre+at+Paris+Machiavelli&amp;source=web&amp;ots=GYo-AXvd8Y&amp;sig=GKc_EArpWV-N2LMkCtgQ-Cyw3y0&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;resnum=6&amp;ct=result#PPA229,M1 Google Books]
*Spielberger, Charles D; Butcher, James N. ''Advances in Personality Assessment'', vol. 9. (Hillsdale, NJ): Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, 1992

==External links==
*[http://xtf.lib.virginia.edu/xtf/view?docId=DicHist/uvaBook/tei/DicHist3.xml;chunk.id=dv3-15 Machiavellianism] in ''The Dictionary of the History of Ideas'', online
*[http://personality-testing.info/tests/MACH-IV.php Machiavellianism test (MACH-VI)] is an interactive version of the MACH-IV test of Machiavellianism.
*[http://www.evilgenes.com/ Barbara Oakley's Evil Genes page] Oakley has written a book [[Evil Genes]], which is mostly about Psychological Machiavellianism

{{Psychological manipulation}}

[[Category:Machiavellianism| ]]
[[Category:Political terms]]
[[Category:Psychopathy]]
[[Category:Article Feedback 5]]

[[az:Makiavellizm]]
[[bg:Макиавелизъм]]
[[cs:Machiavellismus]]
[[de:Machiavellismus]]
[[et:Makjavellism]]
[[el:Μακιαβελισμός]]
[[es:Maquiavelismo]]
[[fa:ماکیاولیسم]]
[[fr:Machiavélisme]]
[[ko:마키아벨리즘]]
[[it:Machiavellismo]]
[[kk:Макиавеллизм]]
[[ky:Макиавеллизм]]
[[mk:Макијавелизам]]
[[nl:Machiavellisme]]
[[ja:マキャヴェリズム]]
[[pl:Makiawelizm (polityka)]]
[[pt:Maquiavelismo]]
[[ro:Machiavelism]]
[[ru:Макиавеллизм]]
[[sk:Machiavelizmus]]
[[sr:Макијавелизам]]
[[fi:Machiavellismi]]
[[tg:Мокиовелисм]]
[[tr:Makyavelizm]]
[[zh:权术]]</text>
      <sha1>msn42ul8f7d1kjnbv8w9bx4c6zv1fxy</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
