<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Majoritarianism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>617451</id>
    <revision>
      <id>517086428</id>
      <parentid>497745946</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-10T22:48:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Haeinous</username>
        <id>9331666</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Concept in depth */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9640">'''Majoritarianism''' is a traditional [[political philosophy]] or agenda which asserts that a [[majority]] (sometimes categorized by [[religion]], [[language]], [[social class]] or some other identifying factor) of the population is entitled to a certain degree of primacy in society, and has the right to make decisions that affect the society. This traditional view has come under growing criticism and democracies have increasingly included constraints in what the parliamentary majority can do, in order to protect citizens' fundamental rights.&lt;ref&gt;A Przeworski, JM Maravall, I NetLibrary ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=EMB-F6Forx8C Democracy and the Rule of Law]'' (2003) p.223&lt;/ref&gt;

This should not be confused with the concept of a [[majoritarian]] electoral system, which is a simple electoral system which usually gives a majority of seats to the party with a [[Plurality (voting)|plurality]] of votes. A parliament elected by this method may be called a '''majoritarian''' parliament (e.g., the [[Parliament of the United Kingdom]]).

Under a democratic majoritarian political structure, the majority would not exclude any minority from future participation in the democratic process. Majoritarianism is sometimes [[pejorative]]ly referred to by its opponents as &quot;[[ochlocracy]]&quot; (literally, &quot;mob rule&quot;) or &quot;[[tyranny of the majority]]&quot;. Majoritarianism is often referred to as '''majority rule''', but which may be referring to a majority class ''ruling'' over a minority class, while not referring to the decision process called ''[[majority rule]]''.

==Concept in depth==
Advocates of majoritarianism argue that [[majority]] decision making is intrinsically democratic and that any restriction on majority decision making is intrinsically undemocratic. If democracy is restricted by a [[constitution]] which cannot be changed by a [[majority|simple majority]] decision then yesterday's majority is being given more weight than today's. One critique of majoritarianism is that systems without [[supermajority]] requirements for changing the rules for voting can be shown to likely be unstable.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Choosing How to Choose: Self-Stable Majority Rules and Constitutions|doi=10.1162/0033553041502207|journal=[[Quarterly Journal of Economics]]|volume=119|issue=3|pages=1011–1048|year=2004|first1=Barbera|last1=Salvador|first2=Matthew O.|last2=Jackson|url=http://restud.oxfordjournals.org/content/78/1/1.full#ref-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; If it is restricted by some small group, such as [[Aristocracy (class)|aristocrat]]s, [[judge]]s, [[priest]]s, [[soldier]]s, or [[philosopher]]s, then society becomes an [[oligarchy]]. The only restriction acceptable in a majoritarian system is that a current majority has no right to prevent a different majority emerging in the future (this could happen, for example, if a minority persuades enough of the majority to change its position). In particular, a majority cannot exclude a minority from future participation in the democratic process. It should be noted, as it is often a subject of misunderstanding, that majoritarianism does not prohibit a decision being made by representatives as long as this decision is made via majority rule, as it can be altered at any time by any different majority emerging in the future.

Among critiques of majoritarianism is that most decisions in fact take place not by majority rule, but by plurality, unless the [[voting system]] artificially restricts candidates or options to two only.&lt;ref name=liberalism_vs_populism /&gt; In turn, due to [[Arrow's paradox]], it is not possible to have plurality voting systems with more than two options that retain adherence to both certain &quot;fairness&quot; criteria and rational decision-making criteria.&lt;ref name=liberalism_vs_populism&gt;{{cite book|title=Liberalism Against Populism|first=William|last=Riker|authorlink=William H. Riker|isbn=0-88133-367-0|year=1988|origyear=First published in 1982|publisher=Waveland Press|location=Prospect Heights, Illinois, USA}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Types==
Majoritarianism, as a concept of government, branches out into several forms. The classic form includes [[unicameral]]ism and a [[unitary state]].

Qualified majoritarianism is a more inclusionary form, with degrees of decentralization and federalism.

Integrative majoritarianism incorporates several institutions to preserve minority groups and foster moderate political parties.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nd.edu/~kellogg/pdfs/Reynolds.pdf{{dead link|date=December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History and legacy==
There are relatively few instances of large-scale majority rule in recorded history, most notably the majoritarian system of [[Athenian democracy]] and other [[ancient Greece|ancient Greek]] [[city-state]]s. However, some argue that none of those Greek city-states were truly majority rule, particularly due to their exclusion of women, non-landowners, and slaves from decision-making processes. Most of the famous ancient philosophers staunchly opposed majoritarianism, because decisions based on the will of the uneducated and/or uninformed 'masses' are not necessarily wise or just. [[Plato]] is a prime example with his ''Republic'', which describes a societal model based on a tripartite class structure.

Anthropologist [[David Graeber]] offers a reason as to why majority democratic government is so scarce in the historical record. &quot;Majority democracy, we might say, can only emerge when two factors coincide: 1. a feeling that people should have equal say in making group decisions, and 2. a coercive apparatus capable of enforcing those decisions.&quot; Graeber argues that those two factors almost never meet: &quot;Where egalitarian societies exist, it is also usually considered wrong to impose systematic coercion. Where a machinery of coercion did exist, it did not even occur to those wielding it that they were enforcing any sort of popular will.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Graeber, David. ''[http://www.prickly-paradigm.com/paradigm14.pdf Fragments of an Anarchist Anthropology]'' (2004) p.89&lt;/ref&gt;

Majoritarianism (as a theory), similar to democracy, has often been used as a pretext by sizable or aggressive minorities to politically oppress other smaller (or civically inactive) minorities, or even sometimes a civically inactive majority (see [[Richard Nixon]]'s reference to the &quot;[[Silent Majority (Politics)|Silent Majority]]&quot; that he asserted supported his policies).

This agenda is most frequently encountered in the realm of religion: In essentially all [[Western world|Western]] nations, for instance, [[Christmas Day]]—and in some countries, other important dates in the [[Christian]] calendar as well—are recognized as legal holidays; plus a particular denomination may be designated as the [[state religion]] and receive financial backing from the government (examples include the [[Church of England]] in [[England]] and the [[Lutheran Church]] in the [[Scandinavia]]n countries). Virtually all countries also have one or more official languages, often to the exclusion of some minority group or groups within that country who do not speak the language or languages so designated. In most cases, those decisions have not been made using a majoritarian [[referendum]], and even in the rare case when a referendum has been used, a new majority is not allowed to emerge at any time and repeal it.

{{POV|date=September 2011}}
{{Syn|date=September 2011}}
{{Or|date=September 2011}}

==Reform and backlash==
{{globalize|date=October 2010}}
{{Unreferenced|section|date=October 2010}}
{{quote|TYRANNY OF THE MAJORITY.&lt;ref&gt;Title of a section in Chapter XV of de Tocqueville's book [http://xroads.virginia.edu/~HYPER/DETOC/1_ch15.htm Democracy in America] (1835)&lt;/ref&gt; ... In America the majority raises formidable barriers around the liberty of opinion; within these barriers an author may write what he pleases, but woe to him if he goes beyond them.|[[Alexis de Tocqueville]]|''[[Democracy in America]]'', Volume I, Chapter XV (1835)}}
In recent times—especially beginning in the 1960s—some forms of majoritarianism have been countered by [[liberalism|liberal]] reformers in many countries{{clarifyme|reason=Which countries? Only US example is mentioned and no sources|date=January 2012}}: in the 1963 case ''[[Abington School District v. Schempp]]'', the [[United States Supreme Court]] declared that school-led [[prayer]] in the nation's [[Public school (government funded)|public schools]] was unconstitutional, and since then many localities have sought to limit, or even prohibit, religious displays on public property.{{clarifyme|reason=How is this an attack on majoritarianism?|date=December 2011}} The movement toward greater consideration for the rights of minorities within a society is often referred to as [[Pluralism (political philosophy)|pluralism]].{{clarifyme|reason=Relevance in this section|date=December 2011}}

This has provoked a backlash from some advocates of majoritarianism, who lament the [[Balkanization]] of society they claim has resulted from the gains made by the multicultural agenda; these concerns were articulated in a 1972 book, ''The Dispossessed Majority'', written by [[Wilmot Robertson]]. Multiculturalists, in turn, have accused majoritarians of [[racism]] and/or [[xenophobia]].{{fact|date=December 2011}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Politics}}
*[[Absolute majority]]
*[[Consensus decision-making]]
*[[Consensus democracy]]
*[[Meritocracy]]
*[[Minoritarianism]] (Minority rule)
*[[Argumentum ad populum]]
*[[Democracy]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Social issues]]
[[Category:Liberalism]]

[[id:Mayoritarianisme]]
[[hu:Többségi demokrácia]]</text>
      <sha1>touybfl5p8xhhjs4ztqc4mfoky4be7r</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
