<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Management</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>19881</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521720566</id>
      <parentid>521719619</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-06T20:20:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Moe Epsilon</username>
        <id>327589</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edit(s) by [[Special:Contributions/76.7.220.134|76.7.220.134]] identified as test/vandalism using [[WP:STiki|STiki]].</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27071">{{other uses}}
'''Management''' in all [[business]] and organizational activities is the act of getting people together to accomplish desired goals and [[objective (goal)|objectives]] using available resources efficiently and effectively. Management comprises [[planning]], [[organizing]], [[Human resources|staffing]], [[leadership|leading]] or directing, and [[Control (management)|controlling]] an [[organization]] (a group of one or more people or entities) or effort for the purpose of accomplishing a goal. [[Resourcing]] encompasses the deployment and manipulation of [[human resources]], [[financial]] resources, [[technological]] resources and [[natural resources]]. 

Since organizations can be  viewed as [[systems]], management can also be defined as human action, including design, to facilitate the production of useful outcomes from a system. This view opens the opportunity to 'manage' oneself, a pre-requisite to attempting to manage others.

==History==
The verb ''manage'' comes from the [[Italian language|Italian]] ''maneggiare'' (to handle — especially tools), which in turn derives from the [[Latin]] ''manus'' (hand). The French word ''mesnagement'' (later ''ménagement'') influenced the development in meaning of the English word ''management'' in the 17th and 18th centuries.&lt;ref&gt;[[Oxford English Dictionary]]&lt;/ref&gt;

Some definitions of management are:
* Organization and coordination of the activities of an enterprise in accordance with certain policies and in achievement of clearly defined objectives. Management is often included as a factor of production along with machines, materials and money. According to the management guru [[Peter Drucker]] (1909–2005), the basic task of a management is twofold: [[marketing]] and [[innovation]].

* Directors and managers have the power and responsibility to make decisions to manage an enterprise when given the authority by the shareholders. As a discipline, management comprises the interlocking functions of formulating corporate policy and organizing, planning, controlling, and directing the firm's resources to achieve the policy's objectives. The size of management can range from one person in a small firm to hundreds or thousands of managers in multinational companies. In large firms the board of directors formulates the policy which is implemented by the chief executive officer.

===Theoretical scope===
At first, one views management functionally, such as measuring quantity,  adjusting [[plan]]s, meeting [[goal]]s. This applies even in situations planning does not take place. From this perspective, [[Henri Fayol]] (1841–1925)&lt;ref&gt;
''Administration industrielle et générale - prévoyance organization - commandment, coordination – contrôle'', Paris : Dunod, 1966
&lt;/ref&gt; 
considers management to consist of six [[function (engineering)|functions]]: forecasting, planning, organizing, commanding, coordinating and controlling. He was one of the most influential contributors to modern concepts of management.

Another way of thinking, [[Mary Parker Follett]] (1868–1933), defined management as &quot;the art of getting things done through people&quot;. She described management as philosophy.&lt;ref&gt;
''Vocational Business: Training, Developing and Motivating People'' by Richard Barrett - Business &amp; Economics - 2003. - Page 51.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some people, however, find this definition useful but far too narrow. The phrase &quot;management is what managers do&quot; occurs widely, suggesting the difficulty of defining management, the shifting nature of definitions and the connection of managerial practices with the existence of a managerial cadre or [[social class|class]].

One habit of thought regards management as equivalent to &quot;business administration&quot; and thus excludes management in places outside [[commerce]], as for example in [[Charitable organization|charities]] and in the [[public sector]]. More realistically, however, every organization must manage its work, people, processes, technology, etc. to maximize effectiveness. Nonetheless, many people refer to university departments which teach management as &quot;[[business school]]s.&quot; Some institutions (such as the [[Harvard Business School]]) use that name while others (such as the [[Yale School of Management]]) employ the more inclusive term &quot;management.&quot;

English speakers may also use the term &quot;management&quot; or &quot;the management&quot; as a collective word describing the managers of an organization, for example of a [[corporation]]. Historically this use of the term was often contrasted with the term [[Industrial relations|&quot;Labor&quot;]] referring to those being managed.

==Nature of managerial work==
In for-profit work, management has as its primary function the satisfaction of a range of [[Stakeholder (corporate)|stakeholders]]. This typically involves making a profit (for the shareholders), creating valued products at a reasonable cost (for customers) and providing rewarding employment opportunities (for employees). In nonprofit management, add the importance of keeping the faith of donors. In most models of management/[[governance]], shareholders vote for the [[board of directors]], and the board then hires senior management. Some organizations have experimented with other methods (such as employee-voting models) of selecting or reviewing managers; but this occurs only very rarely. 

In the [[public sector]] of countries constituted as [[representative democracy|representative democracies]], voters elect politicians to public office. Such politicians hire many managers and administrators, and in some countries like the [[United States]] political appointees lose their jobs on the election of a new president/governor/mayor.

==Historical development==
Difficulties arise in tracing the history of management. Some see it (by definition) as a late modern (in the sense of late [[modernity]]) conceptualization. On those terms it cannot have a pre-modern history, only harbingers (such as [[Steward (office)|stewards]]). Others, however, detect management-like-thought back to [[Sumer]]ian traders and to the builders of the pyramids of [[ancient Egypt]]. Slave-owners through the centuries faced the problems of exploiting/motivating a dependent but sometimes unenthusiastic or recalcitrant workforce, but many pre-industrial [[business|enterprises]], given their small scale, did not feel compelled to face the issues of management systematically. However, innovations such as the spread of [[Arabic numerals]] (5th to 15th centuries) and the codification of [[Double-entry bookkeeping system|double-entry book-keeping]] (1494) provided [[management tool|tools]] for management assessment, planning and control.

Given the scale of most commercial operations and the lack of mechanized record-keeping and recording before the [[industrial revolution]], it made sense for most [[ownership|owners]] of enterprises in those times to carry out management functions by and for themselves. But with growing size and complexity of organizations, the split between owners (individuals, industrial dynasties or groups of [[shareholder]]s) and day-to-day managers (independent specialists in planning and control) gradually became more common.

===Early writing===
While management has been present for millennia, several writers have created a background of works that assisted in modern management theories.&lt;ref name=&quot;management_gomez-mejia_p19&quot;&gt;{{cite book
 | last = Gomez-Mejia
 | first = Luis R.
 | authorlink = 
 | coauthors = David B. Balkin and Robert L. Cardy
 | title = Management: People, Performance, Change, 3rd edition
 | publisher = [[McGraw-Hill]]
 | year = 2008
 | location = New York, New York USA
 | pages = 19
 | url = 
 | doi = 
 | id = 
 | isbn = 978-0-07-302743-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Sun Tzu's ''The Art of War''====
Written by Chinese general [[Sun Tzu]] in the 6th century BC, ''[[The Art of War]]'' is a military strategy book that, for managerial purposes, recommends being aware of and acting on strengths and weaknesses of both a manager's organization and a foe's.&lt;ref name=&quot;management_gomez-mejia_p19&quot; /&gt;

====Chanakya's ''Arthashastra''====
[[Chanakya]] wrote the [[Arthashastra]] around 300BC in which various strategies, techniques and management theories were written which gives an account on the management of empires, economy and family.  The work is often compared to the later works of [[Machiavelli]] {{citation needed|date=September 2012}}.

====Niccolò Machiavelli's ''The Prince''====
Believing that people were motivated by self-interest, [[Niccolò Machiavelli]] wrote ''[[The Prince]]'' in 1513 as advice for the city of [[Florence]], Italy.&lt;ref name=&quot;management_gomez-mejia_p20&quot;&gt;{{cite book
 | last = Gomez-Mejia
 | first = Luis R.
 | authorlink = 
 | coauthors = David B. Balkin and Robert L. Cardy
 | title = Management: People, Performance, Change, 3rd edition
 | publisher = [[McGraw-Hill]]
 | year = 2008
 | location = New York, New York USA
 | pages = 20
 | url = 
 | doi = 
 | id = 
 | isbn = 978-0-07-302743-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; Machiavelli recommended that leaders use fear—but not hatred—to maintain control {{citation needed|date=September 2012}}.

====Adam Smith's ''The Wealth of Nations''====
Written in 1776 by [[Adam Smith]], a [[Scotland|Scottish]] [[Ethics|moral philosopher]], ''[[The Wealth of Nations]]'' aims for efficient organization of work through [[Specialization of labor]].&lt;ref name=&quot;management_gomez-mejia_p20&quot; /&gt; Smith described how changes in processes could boost productivity in the manufacture of [[Pin (device)|pins]]. While individuals could produce 200 pins per day, Smith analyzed the steps involved in manufacture and, with 10 specialists, enabled production of 48,000 pins per day.&lt;ref name=&quot;management_gomez-mejia_p20&quot; /&gt;

===19th century===
Classical economists such as [[Adam Smith]] (1723–1790) and [[John Stuart Mill]] (1806–1873) provided a theoretical background to [[resource allocation|resource-allocation]], [[production, costs, and pricing|production]], and [[pricing]] issues. About the same time, innovators like [[Eli Whitney]] (1765–1825), [[James Watt]] (1736–1819), and [[Matthew Boulton]] (1728–1809) developed elements of technical production such as [[standardization]], [[quality control|quality-control]] procedures, [[cost accounting|cost-accounting]], interchangeability of parts, and [[plan|work-planning]]. Many of these aspects of management existed in the pre-1861 slave-based sector of the [[United States of America|US]] economy. That environment saw 4 million people, as the contemporary usages had it, &quot;managed&quot; in profitable quasi-[[mass production]].

===20th century===
By about 1900 one finds managers trying to place their theories on what they regarded as a thoroughly scientific basis (see [[scientism]] for perceived limitations of this belief). Examples include [[Henry R. Towne]]'s ''Science of management'' in the 1890s, [[Frederick Winslow Taylor]]'s ''[[The Principles of Scientific Management]]'' (1911), [[Frank Bunker Gilbreth|Frank]] and [[Lillian Moller Gilbreth|Lillian Gilbreth]]'s ''Applied motion study'' (1917), and [[Henry L. Gantt]]'s charts (1910s). J. Duncan wrote the first [[college]] management [[textbook]] in 1911. In 1912 [[Yoichi Ueno]] introduced [[Taylorism]] to [[Japan]] and became first [[management consultant]] of the &quot;Japanese-management style&quot;. His son [[Ichiro Ueno]] pioneered Japanese [[quality assurance]].

The first comprehensive theories of management appeared around 1920. The [[Harvard Business School]] offered the first [[Master of Business Administration]] degree (MBA) in 1921. People like [[Henri Fayol]] (1841–1925) and [[Alexander Hamilton Church|Alexander Church]] described the various branches of management and their inter-relationships. In the early 20th century, people like Ordway Tead (1891–1973), [[Walter Scott]] and J. Mooney applied the principles of [[psychology]] to management, while other writers, such as [[Elton Mayo]] (1880–1949), [[Mary Follett|Mary Parker Follett]] (1868–1933), [[Chester Barnard]] (1886–1961), [[Max Weber]] (1864–1920), [[Rensis Likert]] (1903–1981), and [[Chris Argyris]] (1923 - ) approached the phenomenon of management from a [[sociology|sociological]] perspective. 

[[Peter Drucker]] (1909–2005) wrote one of the earliest books on applied management: ''[[Concept of the Corporation]]'' (published in 1946). It resulted from [[Alfred Sloan]] (chairman of [[General Motors Corporation|General Motors]] until 1956) commissioning a study of the [[organisation]]. Drucker went on to write 39 books, many in the same vein.

H. Dodge, [[Ronald Fisher]] (1890–1962), and Thornton C. Fry introduced statistical techniques into management-studies. In the 1940s, [[Patrick Maynard Stuart Blackett|Patrick Blackett]] combined these statistical theories with [[microeconomics|microeconomic]] [[theory]] and gave birth to the [[science]] of [[operations research]]. Operations research, sometimes known as &quot;management science&quot; (but distinct from Taylor's [[scientific management]]), attempts to take a [[science|scientific]] approach to solving management problems, particularly in the areas of [[logistics]] and operations.

Some of the more {{As of|2006|alt=recent}} developments include the [[Theory of Constraints]], [[management by objectives]], [[Business process reengineering|reengineering]], [[Six Sigma]] and various [[information technology|information-technology]]-driven theories such as [[agile software development]], as well as group management theories such as [[Cog's Ladder]]. 

As the general recognition of managers as a class solidified during the 20th century and gave perceived practitioners of the art/science of management a certain amount of prestige, so the way opened for [[business philosophies and popular management theories|popularised systems of management ideas]] to peddle their wares. In this context many [[management fad]]s may have had more to do with [[pop psychology]] than with scientific theories of management. 

Towards the end of the 20th century, business management came to consist of six separate branches, namely:
* [[Human resources|Human resource]] management
* [[Operations management]] or production management
* [[Strategic management]]
* [[Marketing management]]
* [[Finance|Financial management]]
* [[Information technology management]] responsible for [[management information systems]]

===21st century===
In the 21st century observers find it increasingly difficult to subdivide management into functional categories in this way. More and more processes simultaneously involve several categories. Instead, one tends to think in terms of the various processes, tasks, and objects subject to management.

Branches of management theory also exist relating to [[Non-profit organization|nonprofits]] and to government: such as [[public administration]], [[public management]], and educational management. Further, management programs related to [[civil society|civil-society]] organizations have also spawned programs in [[nonprofit]] management and [[social entrepreneurship]]. 

Note that many of the assumptions made by management have come under attack from [[business ethics]] viewpoints, [[critical management studies]], and [[anti-corporate activism]]. 

As one consequence, [[workplace democracy]] has become both more common, and more advocated, in some places distributing all management functions among the workers, each of whom takes on a portion of the work. However, these models predate any current political issue, and may occur more naturally than does a [[command hierarchy]]. All management to some degree embraces democratic principles in that in the long term workers must give majority support to management; otherwise they leave to find other work, or go on strike. Despite the move toward workplace democracy, command-and-control organization structures remain commonplace and the ''de facto'' organization structure. Indeed, the entrenched nature of command-and-control can be seen in the way that recent layoffs have been conducted with management ranks affected far less than employees at the lower levels. In some cases, management has even rewarded itself with bonuses after laying off level workers.&lt;ref&gt;Craig, S. (2009, January 29). Merrill Bonus Case Widens as Deal Struggles. ''Wall Street Journal''. [http://online.wsj.com/article/SB123318892645426723.html?mod=googlenews_wsj]&lt;/ref&gt;

According to leading leadership academic [[Manfred F.R. Kets de Vries]], it's almost inevitable these days that there will be some [[personality disorders]] in a senior management team.&lt;ref&gt;Manfred F. R. Kets de Vries The Dark Side of Leadership - Business Strategy Review 14(3), Autumn Page 26 (2003).&lt;/ref&gt;

==Topics==
===Basic functions===
Management operates through various functions, often classified as planning, organizing, staffing, leading/directing,  controlling/monitoring and motivation.
* '''Planning''': Deciding what needs to happen in the future (today, next week, next month, next year, over the next five years, etc.) and generating plans for action.
* '''Organizing''': (Implementation)pattern of relationships among workers, making optimum use of the resources required to enable the successful carrying out of plans.
* '''Staffing''': Job analysis, recruitment and hiring for appropriate jobs.
* '''Leading/directing''': Determining what needs to be done in a situation and getting people to do it.
* '''Controlling/monitoring''': Checking progress against plans.
*''' Motivation''': Motivation is also a kind of basic function of management, because without motivation, employees cannot work effectively. If motivation does not take place in an organization, then employees may not contribute to the other functions (which are usually set by top-level management).

===Basic roles===
* '''Interpersonal''': roles that involve coordination and interaction with employees.
* '''Informational''': roles that involve handling, sharing, and analyzing information.
* '''Decisional''': roles that require decision-making.

===Management skills===
* '''Political''': used to build a power base and establish connections.
* '''Conceptual''': used to analyze complex situations.
* '''Interpersonal''': used to communicate, motivate, mentor and delegate.
* '''Diagnostic''': ability to visualize most appropriate response to a situation.
* '''Technical''': Expertise in one's particular functional area.&lt;ref&gt;Kleiman, Lawrence S. &quot;Management and Executive Development.&quot; Reference for Business: Encyclopedia of Business (2010): n. pag. Web. 25 Mar 2011. [http://www.referenceforbusiness.com/management/Log-Mar/Management-and-Executive-Development.html].&lt;/ref&gt;

===Formation of the business policy===
* The mission of the business is the most obvious purpose—which may be, for example, to make soap.
* The vision of the business reflects its aspirations and specifies its intended direction or future destination.
* The objectives of the business refers to the ends or activity at which a certain task is aimed.
* The business's policy is a guide that stipulates rules, regulations and objectives, and may be used in the managers' decision-making. It must be flexible and easily interpreted and understood by all employees.
* The business's strategy refers to the coordinated plan of action that it is going to take, as well as the resources that it will use, to realize its vision and long-term objectives. It is a guideline to managers, stipulating how they ought to allocate and utilize the factors of production to the business's advantage. Initially, it could help the managers decide on what type of business they want to form.

====Implementation of policies and strategies====

* All policies and strategies must be discussed with all managerial personnel and staff.
* Managers must understand where and how they can implement their policies and strategies.
* A plan of action must be devised for each department.
* Policies and strategies must be reviewed regularly.
* Contingency plans must be devised in case the environment changes.
* Assessments of progress ought to be carried out regularly by top-level managers.
* A good environment and team spirit is required within the business.
* The missions, objectives, strengths and weaknesses of each department must be analysed to determine their roles in achieving the business's mission.
* The forecasting method develops a reliable picture of the business's future environment.
* A planning unit must be created to ensure that all plans are consistent and that policies and strategies are aimed at achieving the same mission and objectives.
All policies must be discussed with all managerial personnel and staff that is required in the execution of any departmental policy.
* Organizational change is strategically achieved through the implementation of the eight-step plan of action established by [[John Kotter|John P. Kotter]]: Increase urgency, get the vision right, communicate the buy-in, empower action, create short-term wins, don't let up, and make change stick.&lt;ref&gt;[[John Kotter|Kotter, John P.]] &amp; Dan S. Cohen. (2002). ''The Heart of Change''. Boston: Harvard Business School Publishing.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Policies and strategies in the planning process====
* They give mid and lower-level managers a good idea of the future plans for each department in an organization.
* A framework is created whereby plans and decisions are made.
* Mid and lower-level management may add their own plans to the business's strategies.

===Levels of management===
Most organizations have three management levels: first-level, middle-level, and top-level managers.{{fact|date=November 2011}} These managers are classified in a hierarchy of authority, and perform different tasks. In many organizations, the number of managers in every level resembles a pyramid.  Each level is explained below in specifications of their different responsibilities and likely job titles.&lt;ref&gt;Juneja hu Juneja, FirstHimanshu, and Prachi Juneja. &quot;Management.&quot; Management Study Guide. WebCraft Pvt Ltd, 2011. Web. 17 Mar 2011.[http://www.managementstudyguide.com/management_levels.htm].&lt;/ref&gt;

====Top-level managers====
Consists of [[board of directors]], president, vice-president, [[CEO]]s, etc. They are responsible for controlling and overseeing the entire organization. They develop goals, strategic plans, company policies, and make decisions on the direction of the business. In addition, top-level managers play a significant role in the mobilization of outside resources and are accountable to the shareholders and general public.

According to Lawrence S. Kleiman, the following skills are needed at the top managerial level.
&lt;ref&gt;Kleiman, Lawrence S. &quot; MANAGEMENT AND EXECUTIVE DEVELOPMENT.&quot;Reference for Business:Encyclopedia of Business(2010): n. pag. Web. 25 Mar 2011. [http://www.referenceforbusiness.com/management/Log-Mar/Management-and-Executive-Development.html].&lt;/ref&gt;

* Broadened understanding of how: competition, world economies, politics, and social trends effect organizational effectiveness .

The role of the top management can be summarized as follows -

* Top management lays down the objectives and broad policies of the enterprise.
* It issues necessary instructions for preparation of department budgets, procedures, schedules             etc.
* It prepares strategic plans &amp; policies for the enterprise.
* It appoints the executive for middle level i.e. departmental managers.
* It controls &amp; coordinates the activities of all the departments.
* It is also responsible for maintaining a contact with the outside world.
* It provides guidance and direction.
* The top management is also responsible towards the shareholders for the performance of the enterprise.

====Middle-level managers====
Consist of [[general manager]]s, branch managers and department managers. They are accountable to the top management for their  department's function. They devote more time to organizational and directional functions. Their roles can be emphasized as executing organizational plans in conformance with the company's policies and the objectives of the top management, they define and discuss information and policies from top management to lower management, and most importantly they inspire and provide guidance to lower level managers towards better performance.
Some of their functions are as follows:
* Designing and implementing effective group and intergroup work and information systems.
* Defining and monitoring group-level performance indicators.
* Diagnosing and resolving problems within and among work groups.
* Designing and implementing reward systems supporting cooperative behavior.

====First-level managers====
Consist of supervisors, section leads, foremen, etc. They focus on controlling and directing.  They usually have the responsibility of assigning employees tasks, guiding and supervising employees on day-to-day activities, ensuring quality and quantity production, making recommendations, suggestions, and upchanneling employee problems, etc. First-level managers are role models for employees that provide:
* Basic supervision.
* Motivation.
* Career planning.
* Performance feedback.

==See also==
{{Main|Outline of business management}}

* [[Scientific management]]
* [[Human relations movement]]
* [[Strategic management]]
* [[Total quality management]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}

{{Management}}
{{Social sciences-footer}}

[[Category:Innovation Management]]
[[Category:Management occupations| ]]
[[Category:Management| ]]

[[ar:إدارة]]
[[as:ব্যৱস্থাপনা]]
[[az:Menecment]]
[[bn:ব্যবস্থাপনা]]
[[be-x-old:Мэнэджмэнт]]
[[bar:Gschäftsleitung]]
[[bs:Menadžment]]
[[br:Management]]
[[bg:Мениджмънт]]
[[ca:Gestió]]
[[cs:Management]]
[[da:Ledelse]]
[[de:Unternehmensführung]]
[[et:Juhtimine]]
[[el:Διοίκηση]]
[[es:Administración]]
[[eu:Kudeaketa]]
[[fa:مدیریت]]
[[fr:Management]]
[[fy:Bestjoer]]
[[ko:경영]]
[[hy:Մենեջմենթ]]
[[hi:प्रबन्धन]]
[[hr:Menadžment]]
[[id:Manajemen]]
[[it:Direzione aziendale]]
[[he:ניהול]]
[[ka:მენეჯმენტი]]
[[kk:Менеджмент]]
[[ky:Менеджмент]]
[[sw:Usimamizi]]
[[lo:ການຈັດການ]]
[[lv:Vadībzinība]]
[[lt:Vadyba]]
[[hu:Menedzsment]]
[[mk:Менаџмент]]
[[ml:മാനേജ്മെന്റ്]]
[[mn:Менежмент]]
[[nl:Management]]
[[ja:経営管理論]]
[[no:Ledelse]]
[[ps:سمبالښت]]
[[pl:Zarządzanie]]
[[pt:Administração]]
[[ro:Management]]
[[ru:Менеджмент]]
[[sq:Menaxhimi]]
[[scn:Amministraturi]]
[[si:කළමනාකරණය]]
[[sk:Plánovanie]]
[[sl:Menedžment]]
[[sr:Руковођење]]
[[sh:Menadžment]]
[[sv:Management]]
[[tl:Pamamahala]]
[[ta:மேலாண்மை]]
[[th:การจัดการ]]
[[tr:İşletme]]
[[uk:Менеджмент]]
[[vi:Quản lý]]
[[yi:פירערשאפט]]
[[bat-smg:Vadība]]
[[zh:管理学]]</text>
      <sha1>ajcgfvh9nu3cwa7zg4ue81euhfly3ji</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
