<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>May Day</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>19829</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520177760</id>
      <parentid>520166283</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-27T22:42:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Hair</username>
        <id>17252003</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edit(s) by [[Special:Contributions/2.100.81.158|2.100.81.158]] identified as test/vandalism using [[WP:STiki|STiki]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24484">{{Hatnote|This article is about the holidays celebrated on May 1. For more information on the labour-related holiday, see [[International Workers' Day]]. For the distress signal, see [[Mayday]]. For other uses, see [[May Day (disambiguation)]].}}
{{Refimprove|date=May 2012}}
[[File:Notenkraker10.jpg|thumb|right]]
[[File:Maibaum1.jpg|thumb|right|''Maibaum'' in Ellbach]]
[[File:Viktualienmarkt Maibaum Nahaufnahme 1999.jpg|thumb|right|''Maibaum'' in [[Munich]], [[Germany]].]]

'''May Day''' on May 1 is an ancient [[Northern Hemisphere]] [[Spring (season)|spring]] [[festival]] and usually a [[public holiday]];&lt;ref&gt;Anthony Aveni, &quot;May Day: A Collision of Forces,&quot; ''The Book of the Year: A Brief History of Our Seasonal Holidays'' (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2004), 79-89.&lt;/ref&gt; it is also a traditional spring holiday in many cultures.

==Traditional May Day celebrations==
May Day is related to the [[Celt]]ic festival of [[Beltane]] and the [[Germanic peoples|Germanic]] festival of [[Walpurgis Night]].  May Day falls exactly half a year from November 1, another [[cross-quarter day]] which is also associated with various northern European [[Paganism|pagan]] and the year in the Northern hemisphere, and it has traditionally been an occasion for popular and often raucous celebrations.

As Europe became [[Christian]]ized, the [[Paganism|pagan]] holidays lost their religious character and either changed into popular secular celebrations, as with May Day, or were [[Syncretism#Religious syncretism|merged with]] or replaced by new Christian holidays as with [[Christmas]], [[Easter]], [[Pentecost]] and [[All Saint's Day]].  In the twentieth and continuing into the twenty-first century, many [[Neopaganism|neopagans]] began reconstructing the old traditions and celebrating May Day as a pagan religious festival again.

===Origins===
The earliest May Day celebrations appeared in pre-Christian times, with the festival of [[Flora (mythology)|Flora]], the Roman goddess of flowers, and the [[Walpurgis Night]] celebrations of the [[Germanic peoples|Germanic]] countries.  It is also associated with the [[Gaels|Gaelic]] [[Beltane]].  Many pagan celebrations were abandoned or [[Christianization|Christianized]] during the process of conversion in Europe.  A more secular version of May Day continues to be observed in Europe and America.  In this form, May Day may be best known for its tradition of dancing the maypole dance and crowning of the [[Queen of the May]].  Various [[Neopaganism|Neopagan]] groups celebrate reconstructed (to varying degrees) versions of these customs on May 1st.

The day was a traditional summer holiday in many pre-Christian [[Europe]]an pagan cultures.  While February 1 was the first day of [[Spring (season)|Spring]], May 1 was the first day of [[summer]]; hence, the [[summer solstice]] on June 25 (now June 21) was [[Midsummer]].  In the [[Roman Catholic]] tradition, May is observed as Mary's month, and in these circles May Day is usually a celebration of the Blessed [[Virgin Mary]].  In this connection, in works of art, school skits, and so forth, Mary's head will often be adorned with flowers in a [[May crowning]].  Fading in popularity since the late 20th century is the giving of &quot;May baskets,&quot; small baskets of sweets and/or flowers, usually left anonymously on neighbours' doorsteps.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.seedsofknowledge.com/holidays/maybaskets.html Charming May Day Baskets]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Europe===

====Great Britain====

[[File:Melmerby May Queen on Village Green - geograph.org.uk - 233648.jpg|thumb|right|May Queen on village green, [[Melmerby, Cumbria|Melmerby]]]]
Traditional British May Day [[rite]]s and [[celebration (party)|celebrations]] include [[Morris dance|Morris dancing]], crowning a [[May Queen]] and celebrations involving a [[Maypole]]. Much of this tradition derives from the [[Anglo-Saxon polytheism|pagan Anglo-Saxon]] customs held during &quot;[[Germanic calendar|Þrimilci-mōnaþ]]&quot;&lt;ref name=CAPTXV&gt;''Caput XV:
De mensibus Anglorum'' from ''De mensibus Anglorum''. Available online: [http://www.nabkal.de/beda/beda_15.html]&lt;/ref&gt; (the [[Old English]] name for the month of May meaning ''Month of Three Milkings'') along with many [[Celts|Celtic]] traditions.
[[File:Queen of the May, in June - geograph.org.uk - 1346819.jpg|thumb|right|May blossom, the flower of the [[Crataegus monogyna|May tree]]]]
May Day has been a traditional day of festivities throughout the centuries.  May Day is most associated with towns and villages celebrating springtime [[fertility]] and revelry with village fetes and community gatherings. Since the reform of the Catholic Calendar, May 1st is the Feast of St Joseph the Worker, the patron saint of workers.  Seeding has been completed by this date and it was convenient to give farm labourers a day off. Perhaps the most significant of the traditions is the [[Maypole]], around which traditional dancers circle with ribbons.

The May Day [[bank holiday]], on the first Monday in May, was traditionally the only one to affect the [[state school]] calendar, although new arrangements in some areas to even out the length of [[Academic term#United Kingdom|school terms]] mean that the [[Good Friday]] and [[Easter Monday]] bank holidays, which [[Moveable feast|vary from year to year]], may also fall during term time. The May Day bank holiday was created in 1978. In February 2011, the UK Parliament was reported to be considering scrapping the bank holiday associated with May Day, replacing it with a bank holiday in October, possibly co-inciding with [[Trafalgar Day]] (celebrated on 21 October), to create a &quot;United Kingdom Day&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= Mayday for May Day: bank holiday may move to 'best of British' October slot |author= Polly Curtis |url= http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/feb/04/may-day-bank-holiday-under-threat |newspaper= The Guardian |date= 4 February 2011 |accessdate=7 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

May Day was abolished and its celebration banned by [[puritan]] parliaments during the [[Interregnum (England)|Interregnum]], but reinstated with the [[English Restoration|restoration]] of [[Charles II of England|Charles II]] in 1660.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Hutton|first=Ronald|title=The rise and fall of Merry England|year=1996|publisher=Oxford university press|location=Oxford|isbn=0-19-285447-X|pages=27–8|edition=New ed.}}&lt;/ref&gt;  1 May 1707 was the day the [[Acts of Union 1707|Act of Union]] came into effect, joining [[England]] and [[Scotland]] to form the [[Kingdom of Great Britain]].

[[File:John Collier Queen Guinevre's Maying.jpg|thumb|right|&lt;center&gt;[[Queen Guinevere]]'s Maying&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
For thus it chanced one morn when all the court,&lt;br&gt;
Green-suited, but with plumes that mocked the may,&lt;br&gt;
Had been, their wont, a-maying and returned,&lt;br&gt;
That Modred still in green, all ear and eye,&lt;br&gt;
Climbed to the high top of the garden-wall&lt;br&gt;
To spy some secret scandal if he might,&lt;/center&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Idylls of the King : Guinevere, Alfred Lord Tennyson 1859&lt;/ref&gt;]]
In '''[[Oxford]]''', it is traditional for [[May Morning]] revellers to gather below the Great Tower of [[Magdalen College, Oxford|Magdalen College]] at 6:00&amp;nbsp;am to listen to the college choir sing traditional madrigals as a conclusion to the previous night's celebrations. It is then thought to be traditional for some people to jump off [[Magdalen Bridge]] into the [[River Cherwell]]. However this has actually only been fashionable since the 1970s, possibly due to the presence of TV cameras. In recent years, the bridge has been closed on 1 May to prevent people from jumping, as the water under the bridge is only {{convert|2|ft|cm}} deep and jumping from the bridge has resulted in serious injury in the past. There are still people who insist on climbing the barriers and leaping into the water, causing themselves injury.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/oxfordshire/7376954.stm May Day revellers party on bridge]&lt;/ref&gt;

In '''[[Durham]]''', students of the [[University of Durham]] gather on [[Prebend's Bridge]] to see the sunrise and enjoy festivities, folk music, dancing, madrigal singing and a barbecue breakfast. This is an emerging Durham tradition, with patchy observance since 2001.

'''[[Whitstable|Whitstable, Kent]]''', hosts a good example of more traditional May Day festivities, where the Jack in the Green festival was revived in 1976 and continues to lead an annual procession of [[morris dance]]rs through the town on the May Bank Holiday. A separate revival occurred in '''Hastings''' in 1983 and has become a major event in the town calendar.  A traditional Sweeps Festival is performed over the May bank holiday in '''[[Rochester, Kent]]''', where the [[Jack in the Green]] is woken at dawn on 1  May by Morris dancers.
[[File:CotswoldMorrisHandkerchiefs20040501 CopyrightKaihsuTai.jpg|thumb|right|[[Morris dance|Morris dancing]] on May Day in [[Oxford]], [[England]] 2004.]]
At 7:15&amp;nbsp;p.m. on 1 May each year, the Kettle Bridge Clogs &lt;ref name=KBClogs&gt;[http://www.kettlebridgeclogs.org.uk Kettle Bridge Clogs]&lt;/ref&gt; morris dancing side dance across [[Barming]] Bridge (otherwise known as the Kettle Bridge), which spans the [[River Medway]] near [[Maidstone]], to mark the official start of their morris dancing season. Also know as Ashtoria Day in Northern parts of rural Cumbria. A celebration of unity and female bonding. Although not very well known, it is often cause for huge celebration.

The '''[[Maydayrun]]''' involves thousands of motorbikes taking a {{convert|55|mi|km|sing=on}} trip from '''[[London]]''' ('''[[Locksbottom]]''') to the '''[[Hastings]] seafront''', [[East Sussex]]. The event has been taking place for almost 30 years now and has grown in interest from around the country, both commercially and publicly. The event is not officially organised; the police only manage the traffic, and volunteers manage the parking.

'''[[Padstow]]''' in [[Cornwall]] holds its annual '[['Obby 'Oss festival|Obby-Oss]]' (Hobby Horse) day of festivities. This is believed to be one of the oldest fertility rites in the UK; revellers dance with the Oss through the streets of the town and even through the private gardens of the citizens, accompanied by accordion players and followers dressed in white with red or blue sashes who sing the traditional 'May Day' song. The whole town is decorated with springtime greenery, and every year thousands of onlookers attend. Prior to the 19th century distinctive [[West Cornwall May Day celebrations|May day celebrations]] were widespread throughout West Cornwall, and are being revived in '''[[St Ives, Cornwall|St. Ives]]''' and '''[[Penzance]]'''.

'''[[Kingsand]]''', '''[[Cawsand]]''' and '''[[Millbrook, Cornwall|Millbrook]]''' in Cornwall celebrate [[Flower Boat Ritual]] on the May Day bank holiday. A model of the ship [[The Black Prince]] is covered in flowers and is taken in procession from the Quay at Millbrook to the beach at Cawsand where it is cast adrift. The houses in the villages are decorated with flowers and people traditionally wear red and white clothes. There are further celebrations in Cawsand Square with [[Morris dancing]] and [[May pole]] dancing.

In '''[[University of St Andrews|St Andrews]]''', some of the students gather on the beach late on April 30 and run into the [[North Sea]] at sunrise on May Day, occasionally naked. This is accompanied by torchlit processions and much elated celebration.

Both '''[[Edinburgh]]''' and '''[[Glasgow]]''' organize Mayday festivals and rallies. In [[Edinburgh]], the [[Beltane Fire Festival]] is held on the evening of May eve and into the early hours of May Day on the city's Calton Hill. An older Edinburgh tradition has it that young women who climb [[Arthur's Seat, Edinburgh|Arthur's Seat]] and wash their faces in the morning dew will have lifelong beauty.

====Romania====
On May Day the Romanians celebrate the &quot;arminden&quot; (or “armindeni”), the beginning of summer, symbolically tied with the protection of crops and farm animals. The name comes from Slavonic ''Jeremiinŭ dĭnĭ'' meaning prophet '''[[Jeremiah]]'''’s day but the celebration rites and habits of this day are '''[[apotropaic]]''' and '''[[pagan]]''' (possibly originating in the cult of the god '''[[Pan (mythology)|Pan]]''').
The day is also called &quot;ziua pelinului&quot; ('''[[mugwort]]''' day) or &quot;ziua bețivilor&quot; (drunkards’ day) and it is celebrated, in order to insure good wine in autumn and, for people and farm animals alike, good health and protection from the elements of nature (storms, hail, illness, pests). People would have parties in the nature with “lăutari” (fiddlers), for those who can afford. There, it is customary to roast and eat lamb, also eat new mutton cheese and drink mugwort flavoured wine or just red wine to refresh the blood and get protection from diseases. On the way back, the men wear '''[[lilac]]''' or '''[[mugwort]]''' flowers at their hats.
Other '''[[apotropaic]]''' rites include, in some areas of the country, people washing their faces with the morning dew (for good health) and adorning the gates for good luck and abundance with green branches or with '''[[birch]]''' saplings (for the houses with maiden girls). The entries to the animals shelters are also adorned with green branches. All branches are left in place until the wheat harvest when they are used in the fire which will bake the first bread from the new wheat.
On May Day eve, country women won’t work in the field as well as in the house to avoid devastating storms and hail coming down on the village. Arminden is also “ziua boilor” (oxen day) and thus the animals won’t be used for work, or else they could die or their owners could get ill.

It is said that the weather is always good on May Day to allow people to celebrate.

====Ireland====
May Day has been celebrated in Ireland since pagan times as the feast of [[Beltane|Bealtaine]] and in latter times as Mary's day. Traditionally, bonfires were lit to mark the coming of summer and to banish the long nights of winter. Officially Irish May Day holiday is the first Monday in May. Old traditions such as bonfires are no longer widely observed, though the practice still persists in some communities, such as Arklow, County Wicklow.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wicklowpeople.ie/news/council-faces-cleanup-bill-after-maybush-fires-1021379.html Council faces cleanup after Maybush fires.] Wicklow People, 5 May 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

====France====
On May 1, 1561, King [[Charles IX of France]] received a [[lily of the valley]] as a lucky charm. He decided to offer a [[lily of the valley]] each year to the ladies of the court. At the beginning of the 20th century, it became custom to give a sprig of lily of the valley, a symbol of springtime, on May 1. The government permits individuals and workers' organisations to sell them tax-free. Nowadays, people may present loved ones either with bunches of [[lily of the valley]] or dog rose flowers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timeanddate.com/holidays/france/labor-day May Day in France Timeanddate.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Germany====
In rural regions of Germany, especially the [[Harz]] Mountains, [[Walpurgisnacht]] celebrations of pagan origin are traditionally held on the night before May Day, including [[bonfire]]s and the wrapping of a ''Maibaum'' ([[maypole]]). Young people use this opportunity to party, while the day itself is used by many families to get some fresh air. Motto: &quot;Tanz in den Mai!&quot; (''&quot;Dance into May!&quot;''). In the [[Rhineland]], May 1 is also celebrated by the delivery of a maypole, a tree covered in streamers to the house of a girl the night before. The tree is typically from a love interest, though a tree wrapped only in white streamers is a sign of dislike. Females usually place roses or rice in form of a heart at the house of their beloved one. It is common to stick the heart to a window or place it in front of the doormat.
On [[leap years]], it is the responsibility of the females to place the maypole.
All the action is usually done secretly and it is an individual's choice whether to give a hint of their identity or stay anonymous.
May Day was not established as a public holiday until 1933. As [[Labour Day]], many political parties and unions host activities related to work and employment.

====Finland====
Celebrations among the younger generations take place on May Day Eve, see [[Walpurgis Night#Finland|Walpurgis Night in Finland]], most prominent being the afternoon 'crowning' of statues in towns around the country with a [[student cap]].

May Day is known as Vappu, from the Swedish term. This is a public holiday that is the only carnival-style street festivity in the country. People young and old, particularly students, party outside,  picnic and wear caps or other decorative clothing.

Some Finns make a special lemonade from lemons, brown sugar, and yeast called &quot;[[Sima (mead)|sima]]&quot;. It contains very little alcohol, so even children can drink it. You can also buy a similar product in all stores. Some Finns also make doughnuts and a crisp pastry fried in oil made from a similar, more liquid dough. 

Balloons and other decorations like serpentines are seen everywhere.

====Sweden====
The more traditional festivities have moved to the day before, [[Walpurgis night]] (&quot;Valborgsmässoafton&quot;), known in some locales as simply &quot;Last of April&quot;.

The first of May is instead celebrated as [[International Workers' Day]].

===North America===

====Canada====
May Day is celebrated in some parts of the Province of British Columbia. Celebrations often take place not on May 1 but during the Victoria Day long weekend, later in the month and when the weather is likely to be better. The honour of having the longest continually-observed May Day in the British Commonwealth—since 1870—is claimed by the BC city of New Westminster.

====United States====
[[File:National-Park-Seminary-May-Day-1907.jpg|thumb|right|May Day festivities at [[National Park Seminary]] in [[Maryland]], 1907.]]
May Day was also celebrated by some early European settlers of the [[Americas|American]] continent. In some parts of the [[United States]], May Baskets are made. These are small baskets usually filled with flowers or treats and left at someone's doorstep. The giver rings the bell and runs away. The person receiving the basket tries to catch the fleeing giver. If they catch the person, a kiss is exchanged.{{Citation needed|date=May 2009}}

Modern May Day ceremonies in the U.S. vary greatly from region to region and many unite both the holiday's &quot;Green Root&quot; (pagan) and &quot;Red Root&quot; (labor) traditions.&lt;ref&gt;Colleen J. Sheehy (Ed.), ''Theatre of Wonder: 25 Years in the Heart of the Beast'' (Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 1999), 79-89.&lt;/ref&gt;

May 1 is also recognized in the U.S. as [[Law Day]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abanet.org/publiced/lawday/2008/lawday50th.pdf &quot;The Rule of Law&quot; American Bar Association]&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Hawaii=====
In [[Hawaii]], May Day is also known as [[Lei (Hawaii)|Lei]] Day, and is normally set aside as a day to celebrate island culture in general and native Hawaiian culture in particular. Invented by a poet and a local newspaper columnist Eric Kosciuszko in the 1920s, it has since been adopted by state and local government as well as the residents, and has taken on the sense of a general spring celebration. The first Lei Day was proposed in 1927 in Honolulu by poet and artist Don Blanding. Leonard &quot;Red&quot; and Ruth Hawk composed &quot;[[May Day is Lei Day in Hawaii|May Day is Lei Day in Hawai'i]],&quot; the traditional holiday song. Originally it was a contemporary [[Foxtrot|fox trot]], later rearranged as the Hawaiian [[hula]] song performed today.

==International Workers' Day==
{{Main|International Workers' Day}}

==See also==
*[[Maypole]]
*''[[Fiesta de las Cruces]]''

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|May Day}}
* [http://www.ancientlights.org/morton.html] Extensive visual, textual and musical studies of American May Day customs since the first Maypole Revels were held at the Ma-Re Mount or Merrymount plantation on Massachusetts Bay in May 1627, hosted by Englishman Thomas Morton; and, last year the state of Massachusetts' Governor Deval Patrick proclaimed May 1 as Thomas Morton Day.
* [http://www.marxists.org/espanol/tematica/1demayo/index.htm#eventos Annual listing of May Day events around the world]
* [http://www.londonmayday.org/home.php London May Day Organising Committee]
* [http://www.lessonplanet.com/lesson_planning_articles/social_studies_lesson_plans/29_April_2010/404/may_day_activities May Day classroom resources]
* [http://www.havanatimes.org/?p=7872 May Day in Cuba, a Retrospective] Photos by Bill Hackwell, ''Havana Times'' Apr 27 2009
* [http://www.pretanicworld.com/Calendar.html Pretanic World] Holiday Traditions from England, Scotland, Wales and Ireland that may pre-date the Christian Era
* [http://www.britishpathe.com/record.php?id=17172 &quot;Children Maypole Dancing - Archive Footage&quot;]
* [http://www.homestead.com/englishheathenism/folkcustoms.html English Heathenism] - Roots of May Day in English heathenism.
* [http://www.theholidayspot.com/mayday/history.htm May Day history at The Holiday Spot]
* [http://www.struggle.ws/anarchism/writers/ramor/berlinMAYDAY.html Mayday in Berlin]
* [http://www.rfi.fr/actuen/articles/113/article_3645.asp The history of May Day - Radio France Internationale in English]
* [http://www.rfi.fr/actuen/articles/113/article_3642.asp Round-up of 2009 May Day marches - Radio France Internationale in English]
* [http://www.kaahelehawaii.com/pages/culture_lei.htm Website with information on modern Hawaiian Lei Day celebration with information on the lei as a traditional Hawaiian cultural art]
* [http://www.leiday.net Website on modern Lei Day and May Day celebrations in Hawai`i]
* [http://piereligion.org/mayday.html Traditional May Day Songs with references]
* [http://rgoldman.org/morris/mayday.htm Dancing up the Sun - May Day Morris Dancing celebrations in North America]

==Histories of May Day==
* [http://www.counterpunch.org/2006/04/29/may-day-with-heart/ May Day with Heart], Peter Linebaugh, ''CounterPunch'', 2006
* [http://libcom.org/history/incomplete-true-authentic-wonderful-history-may-day-peter-linebaugh The Incomplete, True, Authentic and Wonderful History of May Day], Peter Linebaugh, ''Midnight Notes'', 2010
* [http://www.counterpunch.org/2012/04/27/ypsilanti-vampire-may-day/ Ypsilanti Vampire May Day], by [[Peter Linebaugh]], ''CounterPunch'', April 2012

{{Navboxes|list1=
{{US Holidays}}
{{UK Holidays}}
}}

[[Category:May observances]]
[[Category:Germanic paganism]]
[[Category:Paganism]]
[[Category:Secular holidays]]
[[Category:Summer holidays]]
[[Category:Holidays in the Republic of Ireland]]
[[Category:Spring holidays]]

{{Link FA|ka}}
{{Link FA|ms}}
[[ar:عيد العمال]]
[[gn:Mba'apohára Ára]]
[[bn:আন্তর্জাতিক শ্রমিক দিবস]]
[[zh-min-nan:Lô-tōng-cheh]]
[[bg:Ден на труда и на международната работническа солидарност]]
[[br:Devezh al labourerien]]
[[ca:Dia Internacional dels Treballadors]]
[[da:Arbejdernes internationale kampdag]]
[[de:Erster Mai]]
[[el:Πρωτομαγιά]]
[[es:Día Internacional de los Trabajadores]]
[[eo:Tago de la Laboro]]
[[fa:روز جهانی کارگر]]
[[fr:Fête du Travail]]
[[gl:Día Internacional dos Traballadores]]
[[ko:노동절]]
[[hi:मई दिवस]]
[[hr:Praznik rada]]
[[id:Hari Buruh]]
[[is:Fyrsti maí]]
[[it:Calendimaggio]]
[[he:אחד במאי]]
[[ka:მშრომელთა საერთაშორისო დღე]]
[[ku:Roja Karker û Kedkarên Cîhanê]]
[[hu:A munka ünnepe]]
[[mk:Меѓународен ден на трудот]]
[[ml:മേയ്‌ ദിനം]]
[[ms:Hari Pekerja]]
[[my:ကမ္ဘာ့အလုပ်သမားနေ့]]
[[nl:Dag van de Arbeid]]
[[ne:मे दिवस]]
[[ja:五月祭]]
[[no:Arbeidernes internasjonale kampdag]]
[[nn:Første mai]]
[[pl:Święto Pracy]]
[[pt:Dia do Trabalhador]]
[[ro:Ziua Muncii]]
[[ru:Первое мая (праздник)]]
[[scn:Jurnata ntirnazziunali dû travagghiu]]
[[simple:May Day]]
[[sl:Praznik dela]]
[[sr:Празник рада]]
[[sh:Međunarodni praznik rada]]
[[fi:Vappu]]
[[sv:Första maj]]
[[tl:Araw ng Mayo]]
[[ta:மே நாள்]]
[[th:เมย์เดย์]]
[[vi:Ngày Quốc tế Lao động]]
[[diq:1ê Gulane]]
[[zh:五朔節]]</text>
      <sha1>gz1vi06x59mwc3h1b4rftc1rwdkyz16</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
