<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Means of production</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>47155</id>
    <revision>
      <id>517309537</id>
      <parentid>503073224</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-12T02:05:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>68.196.57.211</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Marxist analysis of ownership of the Means of Production within capitalism */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9461">:''Not to be confused with [[Mode of production]].''
{{Economics sidebar}}
'''Means of production''' refers to physical, non-human inputs used in production—the factories, machines, and tools used to produce wealth&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Essentials of Sociology|author=James M. Henslin|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis US|year=2002|page=159|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=852vjh_IwusC&amp;pg=PA159}}&lt;/ref&gt; — along with both [[infrastructural capital]] and [[natural capital]]. This includes the [[Classical economics|classical]] [[factors of production]] minus [[financial capital]] and minus [[human capital]]. They include two broad categories of objects: ''instruments of labour'' (tools, factories, [[infrastructure]], ''etc.'') and ''subjects of labour'' (natural resources and raw materials). People operate on the subjects of labour, using the instruments of labour, to create a product; or, stated another way, labour acting on the means of production creates a product.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Evans, ''Karl Marx'', London, England, 1975. Part II, Chap. 2, sect. a; page 63.&lt;/ref&gt; When used in the broad sense, the &quot;means of production&quot; includes the &quot;means of distribution&quot; which includes stores, banks, and railroads.&lt;ref&gt;Flower, B.O. The Arena, Volume 37. The Arena Pub. Co, originally from Princeton University. p. 9&lt;/ref&gt;

The term can be simply and picturesquely described in an agrarian society as the soil and the shovel; in an industrial society, the mines and the factories.

==Related terms==
''[[Factors of production]]'' are defined by [[Karl Marx]] in ''[[Das Kapital]]'' as labour, subjects of labour, and instruments of labour; i.e., the term is equivalent to means of production plus labour. The factors of production are often listed in economic writings derived from the [[Classical economics|classical school]] as &quot;land, labour and capital&quot;. Marx sometimes used the term &quot;productive forces&quot; equivalently with &quot;factors of production;&quot; in ''Capital'', he uses &quot;factors of production,&quot; in his famous Preface to the ''[[Critique of Political Economy]]'', he uses &quot;productive forces&quot; (note that this is in the English versions and may depend on the translation.)

''Production relations'' (Marx: ''Produktionsverhältnis'') are the relations humans enter into with each other in using the means of production to produce. Examples of such relations are employer/employee, buyer/seller, the technical division of labour in a factory, and property relations.

''[[Mode of production]]'' (Marx: ''Produktionsweise'')&lt;!-- is factors of production, plus relations of production. Capitalism is a mode of production. Marx's use of the term &quot;mode of production&quot; is, however, quite loose; sometimes he uses it primarily to refer to the relations of production (''eg.,'' Preface to the ''Critique of Pol. Econ.''), sometimes primarily to the --&gt;

(In political context) - the facilities and resources for producing goods.
Study of how people take over other governments using force and violence, not talks and agreements.

==Marxist analysis of ownership of the Means of Production within capitalism==
{{Unreferenced section|date=August 2011}}
The analysis of people's relationships with the means of production is one element that stands at the basis of [[Marxism]].  Marx argued that, while in pre-capitalist societies it is clearly the laborer that uses the means of production to create product; in capitalism, whose nature as a mode of production is embodied in its drive to [[Reproduction (economics)|reproduce]] and [[Accumulation of capital|increase]] capital, it is more realistic to say that the means of production uses the laborer.&lt;ref&gt;Even
under these circumstances, capital is not always in the form of means of production, rather the process or ''circuit of capital'' requires capital to change from means of production into finished products into money and back into means of production. This particular circuit is called the circuit of productive capital (see ''Capital'' vol2 ch1)&lt;/ref&gt;

The idea of ''factors of production'' is typically used as an explanation for income as duly paid to owners of each means of production and also to the workers themselves within [[capitalism]]. By comparison, the term ''means of production'' applies to these means independent of their ownership and their compensation, and regardless of whether the mode of production is capitalist, [[feudalism|feudal]], [[slave labour|slave]], [[group labour|communal]], or otherwise.

To the question of why classes exist in human societies in the first place, Karl Marx offered an historical explanation that it was the cultural practice of '''Ownership of the Means of Production''' that gives rise to them.  This explanation differs dramatically from other explanations based on &quot;differences in ability&quot; between individuals or on religious or political affiliations giving rise to castes.  This explanation is consistent with the bulk of Marxist theory in which Politics and Religion are seen as mere outgrowths (superstructures) of the basic underlying economic reality of a people{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}}.

There are two subtle but important points to the Ownership of the Means of Production.  The first being that owning the '''Means of Production''' is not the same thing as owning physical property, nor is it equal to owning money.  Rather OMP refers to a cultural practice in which a few individuals within a larger corporation (or company) control and decide what is done with the entire profit created by that corporation{{Or|date=October 2010}}.

The conclusion ultimately reached is that while the &quot;owners&quot; of a corporation only contribute a tiny fraction of the total labor and time in creating profit, they have complete control over that profit and how it is used{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}}.  The practice of OMP in human societies is then a type of game where some people are labeled owners (or [[Bourgeoisie]]) and other people are labeled workers (or [[Proletariat]]).  The bourgeoisie have complete control over both how the proletariat are paid in wages and complete control over how the profit from production is used, thus giving rise to a class division.

Contrarian interpretations of this practice might state that wages paid to workers are subsumed under the regular costs of maintaining business.  However, Marx considered it a [[reification (Marxism)|reification]] to treat labor as just another &quot;factor&quot; in production; it implied an inversion of means and ends, so that people were effectively used as things{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}}.

Marx's ideas are often employed in economic analysis by [[socialism|socialists]] who advocate [[Public property|public ownership]] of some or all of the means of production. The affinity between [[labor movement]] causes and this advocacy is very strong - and often shared by [[social democracy|social democrats]], [[socialism|socialists]], [[communism|communists]] and [[green movement|greens]]{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}}. Marxists define [[economic system]]s in terms of how the means of production are used, and which [[social class]] controls them. Thus, in capitalism, the means of production are controlled by the bourgeoisie, (the capitalists - the owners of capital). In the pure ideal of upper-stage socialism (see: [[Pure communism]]), such as that communism is supposed to be, the MoP are controlled by the workers production cooperative associations directly. In fact this situation has only been historically realized temporarily such as in the Israeli [[kibbutz]] or the very early Soviets before the adoption of state capitalism and entrenchment of the communist party as a [[New Class]], or in isolated or preliminary form such as in the final phase of the [[Second Spanish Republic]], or various experimental [[utopian]] communities{{Or|date=October 2010}}; although in embryonic form{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}}.

==See also==
*[[Clause IV]]
*[[Distributism]]
*[[Information revolution]]
*[[Gross fixed capital formation]]
*[[Nationalization]]
*[[Productive forces]]
*[[Property]]
*[[Private property]]
*[[Privatization]]
*[[Relations of production]]
*[[Socialization (economics)]]

==References==
Institute of Economics of the Academy of Sciences of the U.S.S.R. (1957). ''Political Economy: A Textbook''. London: Lawrence and Wishart.

== Footnotes ==
&lt;references /&gt;

{{Marxist &amp; Communist phraseology}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Means Of Production}}
[[Category:Marxist terminology]]
[[Category:History of economic thought]]
[[Category:Socialism]]
[[Category:Capitalism]]
[[Category:Marxism]]
[[Category:Production economics]]
[[Category:Economics]]
[[Category:Labor]]
[[Category:Capital]]
[[Category:Factors of production]]

[[an:Medios de producción]]
[[bg:Средства за производство]]
[[ca:Mitjans de producció]]
[[cs:Výrobní prostředek]]
[[da:Produktionsmidler]]
[[de:Produktionsmittel]]
[[es:Medios de producción]]
[[eo:Produktadrimedoj]]
[[fr:Moyens de production]]
[[it:Mezzi di produzione]]
[[he:אמצעי ייצור]]
[[kk:Өндіріс құралдары]]
[[ku:Navgînên hilberînê]]
[[hu:Termelőeszköz]]
[[ja:生産手段]]
[[no:Produksjonsmiddel]]
[[pl:Środki produkcji]]
[[pt:Meios de produção]]
[[ru:Средства производства]]
[[simple:Means of production]]
[[sv:Produktionsmedel]]
[[tr:Üretim araçları]]
[[uk:Засоби виробництва]]
[[zh:生产资料]]</text>
      <sha1>ejy1nxy27a9hey9i8fcfwxd4q3bc6wy</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
