<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Militarism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>199160</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522346270</id>
      <parentid>520399565</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T16:07:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dolescum</username>
        <id>11312068</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* North Korea */ Reformat ref</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21605">{{distinguish|Militarization|Millerism|Millenarism}}
{{POV|date=March 2009}}
{{Expert-subject-multiple|Military history/Military science task force|Politics|date=October 2009}}
{{history of war}}
[[File:CaptainJ.R.Jellicoe.jpg|thumb|At the height of the [[British Empire]], photographs of naval and military commanders were a popular subject for eagerly collected [[cigarette card]]s. The one shown here, from the turn of the 20th century, depicts then-Captain Jellicoe (later [[John Jellicoe, 1st Earl Jellicoe|Admiral Jellicoe]] of [[World War I]]) in command of [[HMS Centurion (1892)|H.M.S. ''Centurion'']], the flagship of the [[Royal Navy]]'s [[China station]].]]'''Militarism'''  is defined as: &lt;blockquote&gt;
the belief or desire of a government or people that a country should maintain a strong [[military]] capability and be prepared to use it aggressively to defend or promote national interests.&lt;ref&gt;New Oxford American Dictionary (2007)&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Alternative definitions include &quot;aggressiveness that involves the threat of using military force&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[http://dictionary.die.net/militarism Online die.net dictionary]&lt;/ref&gt; the &quot;glorification of the ideals of a professional military class&quot; and the &quot;predominance of the [[armed forces]] in the administration or policy of the state&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thefreedictionary.com/militaristic American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language]&lt;/ref&gt; (see also: [[stratocracy]] and [[military junta]]).

Militarism has been a significant element of the [[imperialism|imperialist]] or [[expansionism|expansionist]] ideologies of several nations throughout history. Prominent examples include the Ancient [[Assyria]]n Empire, the Greek city state of [[Sparta]], the [[Roman Empire]], the [[Aztec]] nation, the [[Kingdom of Prussia]], the [[British Empire]], the [[Empire of Japan]], the [[Russian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic]] (which would later become part of the [[Soviet Union]]), the [[Italian Colonial Empire]] during the reign of [[Benito Mussolini]], [[Nazi Germany]] and [[American Imperialism]].

After [[World War II]], militarism appeared in many of the [[post-colonial]] nations of [[Asia]] (i.e. [[North Korea]], [[Myanmar]] and [[Thailand]]) and [[Africa]] (i.e. [[Liberia]], [[Nigeria]] and [[Uganda]]). Militarist regimes also emerged in [[Latin America]]; some, such as the right-wing administration of [[Augusto Pinochet]] in [[Chile]], gained power in [[coup]]s through [[U.S.]] support, while others, such as the leftist [[Hugo Chavez]] of [[Venezuela]], were elected.{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}}

==By nation==
{{seealso|Nationalism}}
&lt;!-- == National and Imperial Militarism Section Place Holders == --&gt;
&lt;!-- === British Militarism === --&gt;
&lt;!-- === Chinese Militarism === --&gt;
&lt;!-- === Dutch Militarism === --&gt;
&lt;!-- === Egyptian Militarism === --&gt;
&lt;!-- === French Militarism === --&gt;
&lt;!-- === Swedish Militarism === --&gt;
=== Korean Militarism ===
====North Korea====
{{mainarticle|Songun}}
'''Sŏn'gun''', often spelled '''Songun''', is [[North Korea]]'s &quot;Military First&quot; policy, which prioritizes the [[Korean People's Army]]  in the affairs of state and allocates national resources to the army first. &quot;Military First&quot; as a principle guides political and economic life in North Korea, with &quot;Military First Politics&quot; dominating the political system, &quot;a line of Military First Economic Construction&quot; acting as an economic system, and &quot;Military First Ideology&quot; serving as the guiding ideology.

''Songun'' elevates the Korean People's Army within North Korea as an organization and as a state function, granting it the primary position in the [[Government of North Korea|North Korean government]] and society.  It guides [[Politics of North Korea|domestic policy]] and [[Foreign relations of North Korea|international interactions]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Vorontsov&quot;&gt;{{cite web |first=Alexander V |last=Vorontsov | title=North Korea's Military-First Policy: A Curse or a Blessing? |publisher=Brookings Institution|date=26 May 2006 |url=http://www.brookings.edu/views/op-ed/fellows/vorontsov20060526.htm| accessdate=26 March 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It is the framework for the government, designating the military as the &quot;supreme repository of power.&quot;  The North Korean government grants the Korean People's Army the highest economic and resource-allocation priority, and positions it as the model for society to emulate.&lt;ref&gt;Jae Kyu Park, &quot;North Korea since 2000 and prospects for Inter Korean Relations&quot; ''Korea.net'', 19 Jan 2006, &lt;http://www.korea.net/News/Issues/IssueDetailView.asp?board_no=11037&gt; 12 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;  ''Songun'' is also the ideological concept behind a shift in policies since 1994 which emphasize the people's military over all other aspects of state and society.
&lt;!-- ====South Korea==== --&gt;

=== Russian Militarism ===
{{seealso|Putinism|Russian Nationalism}}

===Germany===
[[Image:BismarckRoonMoltke.jpg|thumb|Prussian (and later German) Chancellor [[Otto von Bismarck]], left, with Generals [[Albrecht von Roon]] (center) and [[Helmuth von Moltke the Elder]] (right) in the 1860s. Although Bismarck was a civilian politician and not a military officer, he wore a military uniform as part of the Prussian militarist culture of the time.]]
The roots of German militarism can be found in 19th-century [[Prussia]] and the subsequent unification of [[German Empire|Germany]] under Prussian leadership. After [[Napoleon]] conquered Prussia in 1806, one of the conditions of peace was that Prussia should reduce its army to no more than 42,000 men. In order that the country should not again be so easily conquered, the [[King of Prussia]] enrolled the permitted number of men for one year, then dismissed that group, and enrolled another of the same size, and so on. Thus, in the course of ten years, he was able to gather an army of 420,000 men who had at least one year of military training. The officers of the army were drawn almost entirely from among the land-owning [[nobility]]. The result was that there was gradually built up a large class of professional officers on the one hand, and a much larger class, the rank and file of the army, on the other. These enlisted men had become conditioned to obey implicitly all the commands of the officers, creating a [[Social class|class]]-based culture of [[deference]].

This system led to several consequences. Since the officer class also furnished most of the officials for the civil administration of the country, the interests of the army came to be considered as identical to the interests of the country as a whole. A second result was that the governing class desired to continue a system which gave them so much power over the common people, contributing to the continuing influence of the [[Junker]] noble classes.

Militarism in Germany continued after [[World War I]] and the fall of the German monarchy. During the period of the [[Weimar Republic]] (1919–1933), the [[Kapp Putsch]], an attempted [[coup d'état]] against the republican government, was launched by disaffected members of the armed forces. After this event, some of the more radical militarists and nationalists were subsumed into the [[NSDAP]], while more moderate elements of militarism declined. [[The third reich]] was a strongly militarist state; after its fall in 1945, militarism in German culture was dramatically reduced as a backlash against the Nazi period.

The [[Federal Republic of Germany]] today maintains a [[Bundeswehr|large, modern military]] and has one of the [[list of countries by military expenditure#Stockholm International Peace Research Institute figures|highest defence budgets]] in the world, although the defence budget accounts for less than 1.5 percent of Germany's GDP and is lower than e.g. that of France or Great Britain. Contemporary opinions vary but Germans predominantly oppose unilateral military actions and are suspicious of all claims advocating them. {{Underdiscussion-inline}}

===Japan===
{{Main|Japanese militarism}}
In parallel with 20th-century German militarism, Japanese militarism began with a series of events by which the military gained prominence in dictating Japan's affairs. This was evident in 15th-century Japan's ''Sengoku'' period or ''Age of Warring States'', where powerful [[samurai]] warlords or [[shogun]] played a significant role in Japanese politics. Japan's militarism is deeply rooted in the ancient samurai tradition, centuries before Japan's modernization. Even though a militarist philosophy was intrinsic to the shogunates, a [[Japanese nationalism|nationalist]] style of militarism developed after the [[Meiji Restoration]], which restored the [[Emperor of Japan|Emperor]] to power and began the [[Empire of Japan]].  It is exemplified by the 1882 [[Imperial Rescript to Soldiers and Sailors]], which called for all members of the armed forces to have an absolute personal loyalty to the Emperor. 

In the 20th century (approximately in the 1920s), two factors contributed both to the power of the military and chaos within its ranks. One was the [[Cabinet of Japan|Cabinet]] Law, which required the [[Imperial Japanese Army]] (IJA) and [[Imperial Japanese Navy]] (IJN) to nominate servinet could be formed. This essentially gave the military veto power over the formation of any Cabinet in the ostensibly parliamentary country. Another factor was ''[[gekokujo]]'', or institutionalized [[insubordination|disobedience]] by junior officers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://content.cdlib.org/xtf/view?docId=ft0w1003k0&amp;doc.view=content&amp;chunk.id=d0e489&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;anchor.id=0&amp;brand=eschol &quot;Strengths and Weaknesses in the Decision-Making Process&quot;] Craig AM ''in'' Vogel, EM (ed.), Modern Japanese Organization and Decision-Making,  University of California Press,  1987.&lt;/ref&gt;  It was not uncommon for radical junior officers to press their goals, to the extent of assassinating their seniors. In 1936, this phenomenon resulted in the [[February 26 Incident]], in which junior officers attempted a [[coup d'état]] and killed leading members of the Japanese government. The rebellion enraged Emperor [[Hirohito]] and he ordered its suppression, which was successfully carried out by loyal members of the military.

In the 1930s, the [[Great Depression]] wrecked Japan's economy and gave radical elements within the Japanese military the chance to realize their ambitions of conquering all of [[Asia]]. In 1931, the [[Kwantung Army]] (a Japanese military force stationed in [[Manchuria]]) staged the [[Mukden Incident]], which sparked the [[Japanese invasion of Manchuria|Invasion of Manchuria]] and its transformation into the Japanese puppet state of [[Manchukuo]]. Six years later, the [[Marco Polo Bridge Incident]] outside [[Beijing|Peking]] sparked the [[Second Sino-Japanese War]] (1937-1945). Japanese troops streamed into [[Republic of China (1912-1949)|China]], conquering Peking, [[Battle of Shanghai|Shanghai]], and the national capital of [[Battle of Nanjing|Nanjing]]; the last conquest was followed by the [[Nanjing Massacre]]. In 1940, Japan entered into an [[Tripartite Pact|alliance]] with [[Nazi Germany]] and [[Kingdom of Italy (1861-1946)|Fascist Italy]], two similarly militaristic states in [[Europe]], and advanced out of China and into [[Southeast Asia]]. This brought about the intervention of the [[United States]], which embargoed all [[petroleum]] to Japan. The embargo eventually precipitated the [[Attack on Pearl Harbor]] and the entry of the U.S. into [[World War II]].

In 1945, Japan surrendered to the United States, beginning the [[Occupation of Japan]] and the purging of all militarist influences from Japanese society and politics. In 1947, the new [[Constitution of Japan]] supplanted the [[Meiji Constitution]] as the fundamental law of the country, replacing the rule of the Emperor with parliamentary government. With this event, the Empire of Japan officially came to an end and the modern [[State of Japan]] was founded.

===United States===
&lt;!--Should this be made into its own page as well?--&gt;
In the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries political and military leaders reformed the US federal government to establish a stronger central government than had ever previously existed for the purpose of enabling the nation to pursue an imperial policy in the Pacific and in the Caribbean and [[economic militarism]] to support the development of the new industrial economy. This reform was the result of a conflict between Neo-Hamiltonian Republicans and [[Jeffersonian political philosophy|Jeffersonian]]-[[Jacksonian democracy|Jacksonian]] Democrats over the proper administration of the state and direction of its foreign policy. The conflict pitted proponents of professionalism, based on business management principles, against proponents favoring more local control in the hands of laymen and political appointees.

After the end of the [[American Civil War]] the national army fell into disrepair. Reforms based on various European states including Imperial Britain, Imperial Germany, and Switzerland were made so that it would become responsive to control from the central government, prepared for future conflicts, and develop refined command and support structures; it led to the development of professional military thinkers and cadre.

During this time the intellectual ideas of [[Social Darwinism]] propelled the development of an [[Overseas expansion of the United States|American overseas expansion]] in the Pacific and Caribbean. This required modifications for a more efficient central government due to the added administration requirements.

The enlargement of the [[United States Army|U.S. Army]] for the [[Spanish-American War]] was considered essential to the occupation and control of the new territories acquired from Spain in its defeat ([[Guam]], the [[Philippines]], [[Puerto Rico]], and [[Cuba]]). The previous limit by legislation of 24,000 men was expanded to 60,000 regulars in the new army bill on 2 February 1901, with allowance at that time for expansion to 80,000 regulars by presidential discretion at times of national emergency.

Again, U.S. forces were enlarged immensely for [[World War I]]. Officers such as [[George S. Patton]] were permanent captains at the start of the war and received temporary promotions to colonel.

Between the first and second world wars, the [[US Marine Corps]] engaged in questionable activities in the [[Banana Wars]] in Latin America. Retired Major General [[Smedley Butler]], at the time of his death the most decorated Marine, spoke strongly against a trend to what he considered trends toward fascism and militarism.  The [[Latin America]]n expeditions ended with [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]]'s [[Good Neighbor Policy]] of 1934.

Butler briefed Congress on what he described as a [[business plot]] for a military coup, for which he had been suggested as leader; the matter was partially corroborated, but the real threat has been disputed. There is little evidence that any serious military coups were planned in the US. During the [[American Civil War]] those officers who were sympathetic to the [[Confederate States of America|Confederacy]] resigned their commissions rather than mutiny.

After [[World War II]], there were major cutbacks, such that units responding early in the Korean War, under [[United Nations]] authority (e.g., [[Task Force Smith]]) were unprepared, resulting in catastrophic performance.  It should be noted that when [[Harry S. Truman]] fired [[Douglas MacArthur]], the tradition of civilian control held and MacArthur left without any hint of military coup.

Serious permanent buildups were a result of the [[Cold War]]. [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]], a retired top military commander elected as a civilian President, warned of the development of a [[military-industrial complex]], more complex than many traditional ideas of militarism.  In the Cold War, there emerged many civilian academics and industrial researchers, such as [[Henry Kissinger]] and [[Herman Kahn]], who had significant input into the use of military force.

It has been argued that the United States has shifted to a state of neomilitarism since the end of the Vietnam War. This form of militarism is distinguished by the reliance on a relatively small number of volunteer fighters; heavy reliance on complex technologies; and the rationalization and expansion of government advertising and recruitment programs designed to promote military service.&lt;ref&gt;[[Alasdair Roberts (academic)|Roberts, Alasdair]].  [http://www.nyupress.org/books/The_Collapse_of_Fortress_Bush-products_id-5153.html ''The Collapse of Fortress Bush: The Crisis of Authority in American Government''].  New York: New York University Press, 2008, 14 and 108-117.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Military budget of the United States]] for 2008 was $740,800,000,000. [http://www.gao.gov/financial/fy2008/08stmt.pdf]

===India===
Rise of militarism in [[India]] dates back to the [[British Raj]] with the rise of several [[Indian independence movement]] organizations such as [[Indian National Army]]  led by [[Subhash Chandra Bose]]. The INA played a crucial role on pressuring the British Raj after it occupied [[Andaman and Nicobar Islands]] with the help of [[Imperial Japan]], but the movement lost momentum due to lack of support by [[Indian National Congress]], [[Battle of Imphal]] and Bose's sudden death.

After India gained independence in 1947, [[Indo-Pakistani relations|tensions with neighboring Pakistan]] over [[Kashmir dispute]] also led to rise militarism in India which also saw a boost during the various events that led to the [[political integration of India]]. After the [[Sino-Indian War]] in 1962, India dramatically expanded its military prowess which helped India emerge victorious during the [[Indo-Pakistani War of 1971]]. The rise of [[Kashmiri insurgency]] and recent events such as the [[Kargil War]] assured that the Indian government remained committed to military expansion.

===Israel===
Israel's many [[Arab-Israeli conflict|security difficulties]] since the [[Declaration of the Establishment of the State of Israel|establishment of the State]] have led to a prominence of security in politics and [[civil society]], resulting in many of Israel's top [[Politics of Israel|politician]]s being former high-ranking [[Israel Defense Forces|military officials]] (partial list: [[Yitzhak Rabin]], [[Ariel Sharon]], [[Ezer Weizman]], [[Ehud Barak]],  [[Shaul Mofaz]], [[Moshe Dayan]], [[Yitzhak Mordechai]], and [[Amram Mitzna]]).

==References==
{{reflist}}
* Bacevich, Andrew J. ''The New American Militarism''. Oxford: University Press, 2005.
* Barr, Ronald J. &quot;The Progressive Army: US Army Command and Administration 1870-1914.&quot; St. Martin's Press, Inc. 1998. ISBN 0-312-21467-7.
* Barzilai, Gad. ''Wars, Internal Conflicts and Political Order.'' Albany: State University of New York Press. 1996.
* Bond, Brian. ''War and Society in Europe, 1870-1970.'' McGill-Queen's University Press. 1985 ISBN 0-7735-1763-4
* Conversi, Daniele 2007 'Homogenisation, nationalism and war’, [http://www.blackwell-synergy.com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1469-8129.2007.00292.x Nations and Nationalism], Vol. 13, no 3, 2007, pp.&amp;nbsp;1–24
* Ensign, Tod. ''America's Military Today.'' The New Press. 2005. ISBN 1-56584-883-7.
* Fink, Christina. ''Living Silence: Burma Under Military Rule.'' White Lotus Press. 2001. ISBN 1-85649-925-1.
* Frevert, Ute. ''A Nation in Barracks: Modern Germany, Military Conscription and Civil Society.'' Berg, 2004. ISBN 1-85973-886-9
* Huntington, Samuel P.. ''Soldier and the State: The Theory and Politics of Civil-Military Relations.'' Cambridge: Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, 1981.
* [[Gerhard Ritter|Ritter, Gerhard]] ''The Sword and the Scepter; the Problem of Militarism in Germany'', translated from the German by Heinz Norden, Coral Gables, Fla., University of Miami Press 1969-73.
* Shaw, Martin.'' Post-Military Society: Militarism, Demilitarization and War at the End of the Twentieth Century''. Temple University Press, 1992.
* Tang, C. ''Comprehensive Notes on World History'' Hong Kong, 2004
* Vagts, Alfred. ''A History of Militarism.'' Meridian Books, 1959.
* Western, Jon. ''Selling Intervention and War.'' Johns Hopkins University . 2005. ISBN 0-8018-8108-0  &lt;div class=&quot;references-small&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

==External links==
* [http://www.nationmaster.com/graph-T/mil_exp_dol_fig Military Expenditure by Total, Per Capita, and Percentage of GDP] - [[Nationmaster.com]]
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2010}}

[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Military strategy]]
[[Category:Fascism]]

[[ar:سياسة عسكرية]]
[[az:Militarizm]]
[[be:Мілітарызм]]
[[be-x-old:Мілітарызм]]
[[ca:Militarisme]]
[[cs:Militarismus]]
[[cy:Militariaeth]]
[[da:Militarisme]]
[[de:Militarismus]]
[[et:Militarism]]
[[el:Μιλιταρισμός]]
[[es:Militarismo]]
[[eo:Militarismo]]
[[eu:Militarismo]]
[[fa:نظامی‌گری]]
[[fr:Militarisme]]
[[ko:군국주의]]
[[hy:Միլիտարիզմ]]
[[hi:सैन्यवाद]]
[[hr:Militarizam]]
[[io:Militarismo]]
[[id:Militerisme]]
[[it:Militarismo]]
[[he:מיליטריזם]]
[[ka:მილიტარიზმი]]
[[kk:Милитаризм]]
[[lv:Militārisms]]
[[mk:Милитаризам]]
[[nl:Militarisme]]
[[ja:軍国主義]]
[[no:Militarisme]]
[[pl:Militaryzm]]
[[pt:Militarismo]]
[[ro:Militarism]]
[[ru:Милитаризм]]
[[simple:Militarism]]
[[sk:Militarizmus]]
[[sr:Милитаризам]]
[[sh:Militarizam]]
[[fi:Militarismi]]
[[sv:Militarism]]
[[tr:Militarizm]]
[[uk:Мілітаризм]]
[[zh:军国主义]]</text>
      <sha1>pwrs5frciipcszvuxfybvkovz0aqfhq</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
