<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Miscegenation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>145031</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522440143</id>
      <parentid>522439551</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-11T06:08:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Malik Shabazz</username>
        <id>3020778</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* See also */  avoiding redirects, removing redirect to [[Sexual slavery]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="228949">{{Multiple issues
 | POV=May 2010
 | cleanup=May 2010
 | intro-tooshort=February 2009
}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2012}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Race}}
[[File:Admixture triangle plot.svg|thumb|Triangle plot shows average admixture of five North American ethnic groups. Individuals that self-identify with each group can be found at many locations on the map, but on groups tend to cluster differently.]]
'''Miscegenation''' ({{IPAc-en|m|ɪ|ˌ|s|ɛ|dʒ|ɨ|ˈ|n|eɪ|ʃ|ən}}; from the Latin ''miscere'' &quot;to mix&quot; + ''genus'' &quot;kind&quot;) is the mixing of different [[Race (classification of human beings)|racial groups]] through [[marriage]], [[cohabitation]], [[human sexuality|sexual relations]], and [[procreation]].&lt;ref name=dictionary.com&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/miscegenation |title=Miscegenation: Definition of Miscegenation at Dictionary.com |accessdate=31 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The term ''miscegenation'' has been used since the 19th century to refer to [[interracial marriage]] and interracial [[sexual intercourse|sex]],&lt;ref name=dictionary.com/&gt; and more generally to the process of [[#Genetic studies of racial admixture|racial admixture]], which has taken place since [[ancient history]]. The term entered historical records during European [[colonialism]] and the [[Age of Discovery]], but societies such as China and Japan also had restrictions on marrying with peoples they considered to be of a different race. Historically the term has been used in the context of laws banning interracial marriage and sex, so-called [[anti-miscegenation laws]]. Today, the use of the phrase is considered offensive.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last1=Downing |first1=Karen |last2=Nichols |first2=Darlene |last3=Webster |first3=Kelly |title=Multiracial America: A Resource Guide on the History and Literature of Interracial Issues |url=http://books.google.com/?id=g-fm97haJQEC&amp;pg=PA9 |year=2005 |publisher=Scarecrow Press |location=Lanham, Maryland |isbn=0-8108-5199-7 |page=9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Usage==
In the present day, the word miscegenation is avoided by many scholars, because the term suggests a concrete biological phenomenon, rather than a categorization imposed on certain relationships. The term's historical use in contexts that typically implied disapproval is also a reason why more unambiguously neutral terms such as &quot;interracial&quot;, &quot;interethnic&quot; or &quot;cross-cultural&quot; are more common in contemporary usage.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Newman |first=Richard |editor=[[Kwame Anthony Appiah|Kwame Appiah]] and [[Henry Louis Gates, Jr.]] |title=[[Encyclopedia Africana|Africana: The Encyclopedia of the African and African American Experience]] |edition=1st |year=1999 |publisher=Basic Civitas Books |location=New York |isbn=0-465-00071-1 |page=1320 |chapter=Miscegenation |quote=Miscegenation, a term for sexual relations across racial lines; no longer in use because of its racist implications}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term remains in use among scholars when referring to past practices concerning [[multiracial]]ity, such as anti-miscegenation laws that banned interracial marriages.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi|10.2307/2945474}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Spanish, Portuguese and French, the words used to describe the mixing of races are ''mestizaje'', ''mestiçagem'' and ''métissage''. These words, much older than the term miscegenation, are derived from the [[Late Latin]] ''mixticius'' for &quot;mixed&quot;, which is also the root of the Spanish word ''[[mestizo]]''. Portuguese also uses ''miscigenação'', derived from the same Latin root as the English word. These non-English terms for &quot;race-mixing&quot; are not considered as offensive as &quot;miscegenation&quot;, although they have historically been tied to the [[caste system]] ([[Casta]]) that was established during the colonial era in Spanish-speaking Latin America. Some groups in South America, however, consider the use of the word ''mestizo'' offensive because it was used during the times of the colony to refer specifically to the mixing between the conquistadores and the indigenous people.

Today, the mixes among races and ethnicities are diverse, so it is considered preferable to use the term &quot;mixed-race&quot; or simply &quot;mixed&quot; (''mezcla''). In Portuguese-speaking Latin America (i.e., [[Brazil]]), a milder form of caste system existed, although it also provided for legal and social discrimination among individuals belonging to different races, since [[slavery]] for blacks existed until the late 19th century. Miscegenation occurred significantly from the very first settlements, with their descendants achieving high rank in government and society. To this day, the Brazilian class system is drawn mostly around socio-economic lines, not racial ones (in a manner similar to other former [[Portugal|Portuguese]] colonies).

The concept of miscegenation is tied to concepts of racial difference. As the different connotations and etymologies of miscegenation and ''mestizaje'' suggest, definitions of [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]], &quot;race mixing&quot; and [[multiracial]]ity have diverged globally as well as [[Historical definitions of race|historically]], depending on changing social circumstances and cultural perceptions. Mestizo are people of mixed white and indigenous, usually [[Amerindian]] ancestry, who do not self-identify as indigenous peoples or [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Native Americans]]. In Canada, however, the [[Métis people (Canada)|Métis]], who also have partly Amerindian and partly white, often French-Canadian, ancestry, have identified as an ethnic group and are a constitutionally recognized [[Aboriginal peoples in Canada|aboriginal people]]. (In Canada these are referred to as [[Métis people (Canada)|Métis]]. A very famous one was [[Louis Riel]].)

The differences between related terms and words which encompass aspects of racial admixture show the impact of different historical and cultural factors leading to changing [[social interpretations of race]] and ethnicity. Thus the [[Comte de Montlosier]], in exile during the [[French Revolution]], equated class difference in 18th-century France with racial difference. Borrowing [[Boulainvilliers]]' discourse on the &quot;[[Nordic race]]&quot; as being the French aristocracy that invaded the plebeian &quot;Gauls&quot;, he showed his contempt for the lowest [[social class]], the [[Estates General (France)|Third Estate]], calling it &quot;this new people born of slaves ... mixture of all races and of all times&quot;{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}}.

==Etymological history==
''Miscegenation'' comes from the [[Latin]] ''[[:wikt:miscere|miscere]]'', &quot;to mix&quot; and ''[[:wikt:genus|genus]]'', &quot;kind&quot;. The word was coined in the U.S. in 1863, and the [[etymology]] of the word is tied up with political conflicts during the [[American Civil War]] over the [[abolitionism|abolition]] of [[slavery]] and over the [[racial segregation]] of [[African-Americans]]. The reference to ''genus'' was made to emphasize the supposedly distinct biological differences between whites and non-whites, though all humans belong to the same [[genus]], [[Genus Homo|''Homo'']], same [[species]], ''[[Homo sapiens]]'' and same subspecies, ''[[Homo sapiens sapiens]]''.

The word was coined in an anonymous [[propaganda]] [[pamphlet]] published in New York City in December 1863, during the [[American Civil War]]. The pamphlet was entitled ''Miscegenation: The Theory of the Blending of the Races, Applied to the American White Man and Negro''.&lt;ref name=&quot;hoaxes&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|title=The Miscegenation Hoax
|url=http://www.museumofhoaxes.com/hoax/archive/permalink/the_miscegenation_hoax/
|work=Museum of Hoaxes
|accessdate=2 April 2008
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
It purported to advocate the intermarriage of whites and blacks until they were indistinguishably mixed, as a desirable goal, and further asserted that this was the goal of the [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party]]. The pamphlet was a hoax, concocted by [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democrats]], to discredit the Republicans by imputing to them what were then radical views that offended against the attitudes of the vast majority of whites, including those who opposed slavery. There was already much opposition to the war effort.

The pamphlet and variations on it were reprinted widely in both the north and [[Confederate States of America|south]] by Democrats and Confederates. Only in November 1864 was the pamphlet exposed as a hoax. The hoax pamphlet was written by [[David Goodman Croly]], managing editor of the ''[[New York World]]'', a Democratic Party paper, and George Wakeman, a ''World'' reporter.

By then, the word ''miscegenation'' had entered the common language of the day as a popular [[buzzword]] in political and social discourse. The issue of miscegenation, raised by the opponents of [[Abraham Lincoln]], featured prominently in the election campaign of 1864.

In the United States, miscegenation has referred primarily to the intermarriage between whites and non-whites, especially blacks.

Before the publication of ''Miscegenation'', the word [[Amalgamation (history)|amalgamation]], borrowed from [[metallurgy]], had been in use as a general term for ethnic and racial intermixing. A contemporary usage of this metaphor was that of [[Ralph Waldo Emerson]]'s private vision in 1845 of America as an ethnic and racial smelting-pot, a variation on the concept of the [[melting pot]]. Opinions in the U.S on the desirability of such intermixing, including that between white [[Protestants]] and [[Irish Catholic]] immigrants, were divided. The term miscegenation was coined to refer specifically to the intermarriage of blacks and whites, with the intent of galvanising opposition to the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;hollinger&quot;&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1086/529971}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==The concept of miscegenation==

[[Franz Boas]] (considered to be the father of American cultural anthropology) as well as many of his students, such as [[Ashley Montagu]], considered race to be an invalid concept.{{citation needed|date=October 2012}} From this point of view, if the concept of race is invalid, then miscegenation as the crossing of races is equally invalid. These ideas are pursued in greater depth in Ashley Montagu's books on the subject.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Ashley Montagu|title=Man's most dangerous myth: the fallacy of race|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=tkHqP3vgYi4C&amp;pg=PA87|accessdate=11 December 2011|year=1997|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield|isbn=978-0-8039-4648-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Ashley Montagu|title=Race and IQ|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=NWFWm3GW90kC&amp;pg=PA82|accessdate=11 December 2011|year=1999|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-510221-5|pages=82–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Laws banning miscegenation==
{{Sex and the Law}}
{{Main|Anti-miscegenation laws}}
Laws banning &quot;race-mixing&quot; were enforced in certain U.S. states from 1691&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
|url=http://www.backintyme.com/essay050101.htm
|title=The Invention of the Color Line: 1691&amp;mdash;Essays on the Color Line and the One-Drop Rule
|author=Frank W Sweet
|publisher=Backentyme Essays
|date=1 January 2005
|accessdate=4 January 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; until 1967, in [[Nazi Germany]] (the [[Nuremberg Laws]]) from 1935 until 1945, and in South Africa during the early part of the [[Apartheid]] era (1949–1985). All these laws primarily banned marriage between spouses of different racially or ethnically defined groups, which was termed &quot;amalgamation&quot; or &quot;miscegenation&quot; in the U.S. The laws in Nazi Germany and many of the U.S. states, as well as South Africa, also banned sexual relations between such individuals.

In the United States, the various state laws prohibited the marriage of whites and blacks, and in many states also the intermarriage of whites with [[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]] or [[Asian American|Asians]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Karthikeyan|first=Hrishi |coauthors=Chin, Gabriel|year=2002|title=Preserving Racial Identity: Population Patterns and the Application of Anti-Miscegenation Statutes to Asian Americans, 1910–1950|journal=Asian Law Journal|volume=9|issue=1|ssrn=283998}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the U.S., such laws were known as [[anti-miscegenation laws]]. From 1913 until 1948, 30 out of the then 48 states enforced such laws.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://lovingday.org/map.htm|title=Where were Interracial Couples Illegal?|work=LovingDay|accessdate=13 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although an &quot;Anti-Miscegenation Amendment&quot; to the [[United States Constitution]] was proposed in 1871, in 1912–1913, and in 1928,&lt;ref&gt;[http://lovingday.org/courtroom.htm &quot;Courtroom History&quot;] Lovingday.org Retrieved 28 June 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Stein|first=Edward|year=2004|title=Past and present proposed amendments to the United States constitution regarding marriage|journal=Washington University Law Quarterly|volume=82|issue=3|ssrn=576181}}&lt;/ref&gt; no nation-wide law against racially mixed marriages was ever enacted. In 1967, the [[United States Supreme Court]] unanimously ruled in ''[[Loving v. Virginia]]'' that anti-miscegenation laws are [[unconstitutional]]. With this ruling, these laws were no longer in effect in the remaining 16 states that still had them.

The Nazi ban on interracial marriage and interracial sex was enacted in September 1935 as part of the [[Nuremberg Laws]], the ''Gesetz zum Schutze des deutschen Blutes und der deutschen Ehre'' (The Law for the Protection of German Blood and German Honour). The Nuremberg Laws classified [[Judaism|Jews]] as a race, and forbade marriage and extramarital sexual relations between persons of Jewish origin and persons of &quot;German or related blood&quot;. Such intercourse was condemned as ''[[Rassenschande]]'' (lit. &quot;race-disgrace&quot;) and could be punished by imprisonment (usually followed by deportation to a concentration camp) and even by death.

The [[Prohibition of Mixed Marriages Act]] in South Africa, enacted in 1949, banned intermarriage between different racial groups, including between [[Whites in South Africa|whites]] and non-whites. The [[Immorality Act]], enacted in 1950, also made it a criminal offense for a white person to have any sexual relations with a person of a different race. Both laws were repealed in 1985.

==History of ethnoracial admixture and attitudes towards miscegenation==

===Africa===
[[File:Jean Ping 080202-F-1644L-081 0YWDF.jpg|thumb|left|[[Jean Ping]] the Deputy Prime Minister of [[Gabon]] who has a [[Chinese people|Chinese]] father and a black Gabonese mother was elected as Chairperson of the Commission of the African Union on 1 February 2008.]]
[[File:Jerry Rawlings 2.jpg|thumb|left|Jerry John Rawlings, the ex-President of [[Ghana]] is the son of a [[Scottish people|Scottish]] father and a black Ghanaian mother.]]

Africa has a long history of interracial mixing with [[Arabs]] and later European men having sexual relations with black African women as well as taking them as [[wife|wive]]s. Arabs played a big role in the [[African slave trade]] and unlike the trans-atlantic trade most of the black African slaves in the [[Arab slave trade]] were women. Most of them were used as sexual slaves by the Arab men and some were even taken as wives.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Slavery and abolition in the Ottoman Middle East|author=Ehud R. Toledano|publisher=University of Washington Press|year=1998|isbn=0-295-97642-X|pages=13–4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sir [[Richard Francis Burton]] writes during his expedition to Africa about relationships between black women and white men. He writes, &quot;The women are well disposed toward strangers of fair complexion, apparently with the permission of their husbands.&quot; There are several mulatto populations throughout Africa mostly the results of interracial relationships between Arab and European men and black women. In South Africa there are big mulatto communities like the Coloureds and [[Griqua people|Griqua]] formed by White colonists taking native African wives. In Namibia there is a community called the [[Rehoboth Basters]] formed by the interracial marriage of [[Dutch people|Dutch]]/[[German people|German]] men and black African women.

In the former Portuguese Africa (now known as [[Angola]], [[Mozambique]] and [[Cape Verde]]) racial mixing between white [[Portuguese people|Portuguese]] and black Africans was fairly common, especially in Cape Verde where the majority of the population is of mixed descent.

There have been some recorded cases of [[Chinese people|Chinese]] merchants and labourers taking African wives throughout Africa as many [[Chinese people|Chinese]] workers were employed to build railways and other infrastructural projects in Africa. These labour groups were made up completely of men with very few Chinese women coming to Africa.

In West Africa, especially Nigeria there are many cases of Lebanese men taking African women. Many of their offsprings have gained prominent positions in Africa. Flight Lieutenant [[Jerry John Rawlings]], who has a [[Scottish people|Scottish]] father and a black Ghanaian mother became the President and Head of State of Ghana. [[Jean Ping]], the son of a [[Chinese people|Chinese]] trader and a black Gabonese mother, became the Deputy Prime Minister as well as the Foreign minister of Gabon and is currently the Chairperson of the Commission of the African Union in 2009. [[Ian Khama]] son of a Botswanian leader and a white mother is the President of Botswana and the paramount chief of the [[Bamangwato]] people.

[[Indian South Africans|Indian]] men, who have long been traders in [[East Africa]], at times married among local African women. The [[British Empire]] brought many Indian workers into East Africa to build the [[Uganda Railway]]. Indians eventually populated South Africa, [[Kenya]], [[Uganda]], [[Tanzania]], [[Malawi]], [[Rwanda]], [[Zambia]], [[Zimbabwe]] and [[Zaire]] in small numbers. These interracial unions were mostly unilateral marriages between Indian men and East African women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.colorq.org/MeltingPot/article.aspx?d=Africa&amp;x=Indians|title=Jotawa: Afro-Asians in East Africa|publisher=Color Q World|accessdate=15 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Réunion====
The majority of the population of [[Réunion]] is defined as mixed race. In the last 350 years, various ethnic groups (Africans, Chinese, English, French, Gujuratis, Tamil Indians) have arrived and settled on the island. There have been mixed race people on the island since its first permanent inhabitation in 1665.

====Madagascar====
Intermarriage between Chinese men and native [[Malagasy people|Malagasy]] women was not uncommon.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Pan|1994|p=157}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Several thousands [[Cantonese people|Cantonese]] men intermarried and cohabited with Malagasy women. 98% of the Chinese traced their origin from Guangdong more specifically Cantonese district of Shunde. For example the census alone in 1954 census found 1, 111 &quot;irregular&quot; Chinese-Malagasy unions, and 125 legitimate, i.e., legally married. Registered by their mothers under a Malagasy name. Intermarriage between French men and Native Malagasy women was not uncommon either.

===Americas===

====Canada====
The 2006 Census counted 289,400 mixed unions (marriages and common-law unions) involving a [[visible minority]] person with a non-visible minority person or a person from a different visible minority group. This was a 33.1% increase from 2001. Among all mixed unions in 2006, 247,600 couples were in unions involving a visible minority person and someone who was not a visible minority. The groups most likely to be involved in a mixed union were Japanese (74.4%), Latin Americans (47%) and blacks (40.6%).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title = Canada's 'mixed unions' grow with rising vis-min population| author= Fitzpatrick, Meagan|work=National Post |location=Canada | date=2 April 2008| url = http://www.nationalpost.com/news/story.html?id=417163|accessdate =6 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Jamaica and Haiti====
By some estimates, 80,000 North American and European women (most of them over the age of 40) visit [[Jamaica]] and [[Haiti]] every year for sex with young men (mostly in their 20s).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/travel/2006/jul/23/jamaica.theatre.theobserver How sex tourism became the basis of a Royal Court play |Travel |The Observer]. ''The Guardian''. 23 July 2006. Retrieved 11 December 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; They're called &quot;milk bottles&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.canada.com/ottawacitizen/news/arts/story.html?id=6f1d0124-af59-431a-b9eb-f75a5aa47882 Sex tourism: When women do it, it's called 'romance travelling']&quot;. Canada.com. 27 January 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[HIV/AIDS]] infection rates in the Caribbean are much higher than in Canada or the U.S. Even so, female sex tourists in the Caribbean are not preoccupied by the risk.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.smh.com.au/articles/2003/07/11/1057783358449.html Sex tourism as economic aid]&quot;. ''Sydney Morning Herald''. 12 July 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;

====United States====
{{See also|Race in the United States|Multiracial American}}

[[File:Official portrait of Barack Obama.jpg|thumb|right|US President [[Barack Obama]] is the son of a white American mother and a black Kenyan father.]]

Historically, &quot;race mixing&quot; between [[Black (people)|black]] and [[White (people)|white]] people was taboo in the United States. So-called [[anti-miscegenation laws]], barring blacks and whites from marrying or having sex, were established in [[colonial America]] as early as 1691.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal
|url=http://www.backintyme.com/essay050101.htm
|title=The Invention of the Color Line: 1691—Essays on the Color Line and the One-Drop Rule
|author=Frank W Sweet
|publisher=Backentyme Essays
|date=1 January 2005
|accessdate=4 January 2008
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 1691 Virginia law was amended in 1705 to remove Indian-white from the prohibition. [[Thomas Jefferson]]'s policy proposal for dealing with [[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]] was &quot;to let our settlements and theirs meet and blend together, to intermix, and become one people.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;David Nugent, Joan Vincent (2004). [http://books.google.com/books?id=sFibQhwxZW4C&amp;pg=PA407 A companion to the anthropology of politics]. Wiley-Blackwell. p. 407. ISBN 0-631-22972-8&lt;/ref&gt; He regretted in 1813 that white-Indian war had prevented this: “They would have mixed their blood with ours, and been amalgamated and identified with us within no distant period of time.“&lt;ref&gt;Michael Lind (1996). [http://books.google.com/books?id=znDscu7MVcEC&amp;pg=PT75 The next American nation: the new nationalism and the fourth American revolution]. Simon and Schuster. ISBN 0-684-82503-1&lt;/ref&gt;

The taboo among American whites surrounding white-black can be seen as a historical consequence of the oppression and [[racial segregation]] of African-Americans.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Yancey|first=George|date=22 March 2007|title=Experiencing Racism: Differences in the Experiences of Whites Married to Blacks and Non-Black Racial Minorities|journal=Journal of Comparative Family Studies|publisher=University of Calgary: Social Sciences|volume=38|issue=2|pages=197–213}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1111/j.0020-8701.2005.00534.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; In many U.S. states interracial marriage was already illegal when the term miscegenation was invented in 1863. The first laws banning interracial marriage were introduced in the late 17th century in the slave-holding colonies of Virginia (1691) and Maryland (1692). Later these laws also spread to colonies and states where slavery did not exist.

It has also been argued that the first laws banning interracial marriage were a response by the planter elite to the problems they were facing due to the socio-economic dynamics of the plantation system in the Southern colonies. The bans in Virginia and Maryland were established at a time when slavery was not yet fully institutionalized. At the time, most forced laborers on the plantations were [[Indentured servitude|indentured servants]], and they were mostly white. Some historians have suggested that the at-the-time unprecedented laws banning interracial marriage were originally invented by planters as a [[divide and rule]] tactic after the uprising of servants in [[Bacon's Rebellion]]. According to this theory, the ban on interracial marriage was issued to split up the racially mixed, increasingly mixed-race labour force into whites, who were given their freedom, and blacks, who were later treated as slaves rather than as indentured servants. By forbidding interracial marriage, it became possible to keep these two new groups separated and prevent a new rebellion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://backintyme.com/essays/?p=22|title=Why Did Virginia's Rulers Invent a Color Line?|last=Sweet|first=Frank. W.|date=1 November 2006|work=Essays on the Color Line and the One-Drop Rule|publisher=Backintyme Essays|accessdate=13 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:US miscegenation.svg|thumb|left|U.S States, by the date of repeal of anti-miscegenation laws: {{legend|#d3d3d3|No laws passed}}
{{legend|#5b9e39|Before 1887}}
{{legend|#f3ee66|1948 to 1967}}
{{legend|#cc2f2f|12 June 1967}}]]
In 1918, there was considerable controversy in [[Arizona]] when an Indian farmer B. K. Singh married the sixteen year-old daughter of one of his white tenants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Echoes of Freedom: South Asian Pioneers in California, 1899–1965 – Chapter 9: Home Life|publisher=University of California, Berkeley|url=http://www.lib.berkeley.edu/SSEAL/echoes/chapter9/chapter9.html|accessdate=8 January 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
During and after slavery, most American whites regarded interracial marriage between whites and blacks as taboo. However, during slavery many white American men and women did conceive children with black partners. These children automatically became slaves if the mother was a slave or were born free if the mother was free, as slavery was [[matrilineal]]. Some children were freed by their slave-holding fathers or bought to be emancipated if the father was not the owner. Many children of these unions formed enclaves under names such as [[Colored]] and [[Gens de couleur]], etc. Most mixed-raced descendants merged into the African-American ethnic group during [[Jim Crow laws|Jim Crow]], while over the centuries a minority of mixed-raced Americans passed and became white, and others exist to this day in small mixed enclaves of [[Mestee]]s such as the [[Melungeon]]s and [[Lumbee]].

Genetic research suggests that a considerable minority of white Americans (estimated at 1/3 of the population by some geneticists such as Mark Shriver) has some distant African-American ancestry, and that the majority of black Americans have some European ancestry. After the Civil War and the [[Abolition of slavery timeline|abolition]] of slavery in 1865, the marriage of white and black Americans continued to be taboo, especially but not only in the former slave states.

The Motion Picture [[Production Code]] of 1930, also known as [[Hays Code]], explicitly stated that the depiction of ''&quot;miscegenation... is forbidden.&quot;''
One important strategy intended to discourage the marriage of white Americans and Americans of partly African descent was the promulgation of the [[one-drop theory]], which held that any person with any known African ancestry, however remote, must be regarded as &quot;black.&quot; This definition of blackness was encoded in the anti-miscegenation laws of various U.S. states, such as Virginia's [[Racial Integrity Act of 1924]]. The plaintiffs in ''[[Loving v. Virginia]]'', [[Mildred Jeter]] and [[Richard Loving]] became the historically most prominent interracial couple in the US through their legal struggle against this act.
[[File:Robert De Niro and Grace Hightower in 2008.jpg|thumb|[[Robert De Niro]] and his wife [[Grace Hightower]]. Census data showed 117,000 black wife-white husband couples in 2006.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.usatoday.com/news/nation/2007-08-05-interracial-dating_N.htm?POE=click-refer More black women consider 'dating out']&quot;. ''USA Today''. 8/5/2007.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
In the mid 19th to 20th centuries, the Chinese that migrated were almost entirely of Cantonese origin. Hundreds of thousands of Chinese men in the U.S, mostly of Cantonese origin from Taishan migrated to the United States. [[Anti-miscegenation laws]] in many states prohibited Chinese men from marrying white women.&lt;ref&gt;[http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=283998 Chin, Gabriel and Hrishi Karthikeyan, (2002) Asian Law Journal vol. 9 &quot;Preserving Racial Identity: Population Patterns and the Application of Anti-Miscegenation Statutes to Asian Americans, 1910–1950&quot;]. Papers.ssrn.com. Retrieved 29 January 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; After the [[Emancipation Proclamation]], many intermarriages in some states were not recorded and historically, Chinese American men married African American women in high proportions to their total marriage numbers due to few Chinese American women being in the United States. After the Emancipation Proclamation, many Chinese Americans immigrated to the Southern states, particularly Arkansas, to work on plantations. For example, in 1880, the tenth [[US Census]] of [[Louisiana]] alone counted 57% of interracial marriages between these [[Chinese American]]s to be with [[African American]]s and 43% to be with [[European American]] women.&lt;ref name=&quot;The United States&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.colorq.org/MeltingPot/article.aspx?d=America&amp;x=ChineseBlacks|title=The United States|work=Chinese blacks in the Americas|publisher=Color Q World|accessdate=15 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Between 20 and 30 percent of the Chinese who lived in Mississippi married black women before 1940.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Susan Dente Ross|author2=Paul Martin Lester|title=Images That Injure: Pictorial Stereotypes in the Media|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=cpIHIKUS-e0C&amp;pg=PA144|accessdate=2 March 2012|date=19 April 2011|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=978-0-313-37892-8|pages=144–}}&lt;/ref&gt; In mids 1850s, 70 to 150 Chinese were living in New york city and 11 of them married Irish women. In 1906 the New York Times (6 August) reported that 300 white women(Irish American) were married to Chinese men in New York, with many more cohabited. In 1900, based on Liang research, of the 120,000 men in more than 20 Chinese communities in the United States, he estimated that one out of every twenty Chinese men (Cantonese) was married to white women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Benson Tong|title=Asian American children: a historical handbook and guide|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=uK6xhcu-4hAC&amp;pg=PA38|accessdate=2 March 2012|year=2004|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|isbn=978-0-313-33042-1|pages=38–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Accusations of support for miscegenation were commonly made by slavery defenders against Abolitionists before the Civil War. After the War, similar charges were used by white [[racial segregation|segregationists]] against advocates of equal rights for African Americans. They were said to be secretly plotting the destruction of the white race through miscegenation. In the 1950s, segregationists alleged a [[Communism|Communist]] plot funded by the Soviet Union with that goal. In 1957, segregationists cite the [[anti-semitism|anti-semitic]] hoax ''[[A Racial Program for the Twentieth Century]]'' as evidence for these claims.

In 1958, the [[Christian fundamentalist]] preacher [[Jerry Falwell]], at the time a defender of segregation, in a sermon railed against integration, warning that it would lead to miscegenation, which would &quot;destroy our [white] race eventually.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.thenation.com/doc/20070528/blumenthal|title=Agent of Intolerance|last=Blumenthal|first=Max|date=16 May 2007|work=The Nation|accessdate=13 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Asians were also specifically included in some state laws. California continued to ban Asian/white marriages until the [[Perez v. Sharp]] decision in 1948.
[[File:Tiger Woods.jpg|thumb|right|[[Tiger Woods]] refers to his ethnic make-up as ''&quot;Cablinasian&quot;'' (Caucasian, black, Indian and Asian) to describe the racial mixture he inherited from his African-American father and Thai mother.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.nydailynews.com/news/national/2009/12/06/2009-12-06_tiger_woods_alienates_black_community_with_white_lovers.html Tiger Woods alienates black community with white lovers]&quot;. ''Daily News'' (New York). 6 December 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
In the United States, segregationists and [[Christian identity]] groups have claimed that several passages in the [[Bible]],&lt;ref name=&quot;bibletools&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bibletools.org/index.cfm/fuseaction/Topical.show/RTD/Nave/ID/3419/Miscegenation.htm|title=Miscegenation|work=Nave's Topical Bible|publisher=Bible Tools|accessdate=13 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; for example the stories of [[Phinehas, son of Eleazar|Phinehas]] and of the so-called &quot;[[curse of Ham]],&quot; should be understood as referring to miscegenation and that certain verses expressly forbid it. Most theologians read these verses and references as forbidding inter-religious marriage, rather than inter-racial marriage.&lt;ref name=&quot;biblestudy&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.biblestudy.org/basicart/interace.html|title=Does the Bible Forbid Interracial Dating and Marriage?|last=Webster|first=Wesley|publisher=Bible Study|accessdate=13 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Miscegenation has become increasingly accepted in the United States since the Civil Rights movement and up to the present day.&lt;ref name=&quot;Swanbrow&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.umich.edu/news/index.html?Releases/2000/Mar00/r032300a |title=Intimate Relationships Between Races More Common Than Thought |last=Swanbrow |first=Diane |date=23 March 2000 |publisher=University of Michigan |accessdate=15 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Approval of mixed marriages in national opinion polls has risen from 4% in 1958, 20% in 1968 (at the time of the SCOTUS decision), 36% in 1978, to 48% in 1991, 65% in 2002, 77% in 2007 and 86% in 2011.&lt;ref&gt;Krugman, Paul, ''The Conscience of a Liberal'', W W Norton &amp; Company, 2007, p. 210.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gallup Poll, {{cite web |url=http://www.gallup.com/poll/149390/record-high-approve-black-white-marriages.aspx |title=Record-High 86% Approve of Black-White Marriages |deadurl=no |accessdate=13 September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The most notable American of mixed race is the current [[President of the United States]], [[Barack Obama]], who is the product of a mixed marriage between a black father and white mother. Nevertheless, as late as 2009, a [[Louisiana]] [[justice of the peace]] [[Refusal of interracial marriage in Louisiana|refused to issue a marriage license]] to an interracial couple, justifying the decision on grounds of concern for any children the couple might have.&lt;ref&gt;Foster, Mary. [http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/33349991/ns/us_news-race_and_ethnicity/ &quot;Interracial Couple Denied Marriage License in La&quot;]. [[Associated Press]]. 16 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

In recent years, interracial [[pornographic film]]s, which most commonly refers to black male/white female films,&lt;ref&gt;In a 2006 interview, performer and director [[Lexington Steele]] said that &quot;in porn, interracial ''always'' means black males with white females.&quot; {{Cite news|author=Justin Quirk |title=The New Porn Apartheid |newspaper=[[Arena (magazine)|Arena]] |date=February 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; have increased in popularity, becoming one of the fastest-growing and biggest-selling genres.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sextelevision.net/archives/episodeArchivesDisplay.asp?episodeID=179&amp;segmentID=472&amp;seasonID=8 |title=Black/White: Sex, Race &amp; Profit |accessdate=19 July 2007 |date=9 September 2006 |publisher=[[SexTV]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Hawaii====

The majority of Hawaiian Chinese were Cantonese migrants from Guangdong with minority from Hakka. If all people with Chinese ancestry in Hawaii (including the Chinese-Hawaiians) are included, they form about 1/3 of Hawaii's entire population. Many thousands of them married women of Hawaiian, Hawaiian/European and European origin. A large percentage of the Chinese men married Hawaiian and Hawaiian/European women. While an minority married white women in Hawaii were with [[Portuguese American|Portuguese]] women. The 12592 Asiatic-Hawaiians enumerated in 1930 were the result of Chinese men intermarrying with Hawaiian and part Hawaiian/European. Most Asiatic-Hawaiians men also married Hawaiians and European women (and vice versa). On the census some Chinese with little native blood would be classified as Chinese not an Asiatic-Hawaiians due to dilution of native blood. Intermarriage started to decline in the 1920s.&lt;ref name=adams&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=GrvXiBNOsO0C&amp;pg=PA396|title=Interracial Marriage in Hawaii|author=Romanzo Adams|year=2005|publisher=Kessinger Publishing|page=396|isbn=978-1-4179-9268-3|accessdate=14 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://www.informaworld.com/smpp/content~db=all~content=a904831799|title=Interethnic Marriage and Divorce in Hawaii A Panel Study of 1968 First Marriages|author=Margaret M. Schwertfeger|year=1982|publisher=Kessinger Publishing|accessdate=14 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Portuguese and other caucasian women married Chinese men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=_j2lXoxMIiAC&amp;pg=PA254&amp;dq=pattern+and+Portuguese+women+marrying+Chinese+males#v=onepage&amp;q=pattern%20and%20Portuguese%20women%20marrying%20Chinese%20males&amp;f=false|title=Divorce: crisis, challenge, or relief?|author=David Anthony Chiriboga, Linda S. Catron|year=1991|publisher=NYU Press|page=254|isbn=978-0-8147-1450-8|accessdate=14 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=AUL3iXlwKQgC&amp;pg=PA58|title=Intermarriage in the United States, Volume 5|author=Gary A. Cretser, Joseph J. Leon|year=1982|publisher=Psychology Press|page=58|isbn=978-0-917724-60-2|accessdate=14 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; These unions between Chinese men and Portuguese women resulted in children of mixed Chinese Portuguese parentage, called Chinese-Portuguese. For two years to 30 June 1933, 38 of these children were born, they were classified as pure Chinese because their fathers were Chinese.&lt;ref name=adams/&gt; A large amount of mingling took place between Chinese and Portuguese, Chinese men married Portuguese, Spanish, Hawaiian, Caucasian-Hawaiian, etc.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=hzoXAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=RA2-PA27|title=Bulletin, Issues 13–18|author=United States Bureau of Education|year=1921|publisher=U.S. G.P.O.|page=27|accessdate=14 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=0hSmD_8bhpwC&amp;pg=PA27|title=Bulletin, Issue 16|author=United States. Office of Education|year=1920|publisher=U.S. Dept. of Health, Education, and Welfare, Office of Education|page=27|accessdate=14 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=dewAAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA492|title=American journal of physical anthropology, Volume 3|author=American Association of Physical Anthropologists, Wistar Institute of Anatomy and Biology|year=1920|publisher=A. R. Liss|page=492|accessdate=14 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=AUL3iXlwKQgC&amp;pg=PA53|title=Intermarriage in the United States, Volume 5|author=Gary A. Cretser, Joseph J. Leon|year=1982|publisher=Routledge|page=111|isbn=978-0-917724-60-2|accessdate=14 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Only one Chinese man was recorded marrying an American woman.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=fsAUAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA42|title=The Journal of heredity, Volume 10|author=American Genetic Association|year=1919|publisher=American Genetic Association|page=42|accessdate=14 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Pf_zAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA42|title=J hered, Volume 10|author=American Genetic Association|year=1919|publisher=American Genetic Association|page=42|accessdate=14 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Chinese men in Hawaii also married Puerto Rican, Portuguese, Japanese, Greek, and half -white women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=_7a0sWazYH8C&amp;pg=PA988|title=New Outlook, Volume 81|author=Alfred Emanuel Smith|year=1905|publisher=Outlook Publishing Company, Inc.|page=988|accessdate=14 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=57_QAAAAMAAJ|title=The Outlook, Volume 81
|year=1905|publisher=Outlook Co.|page=988|accessdate=14 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Latin America====
[[File:German Venezuelan Family.jpg|thumb|right|Racial mix: [[German people|German]] mother (left), [[Venezuelan]] father -of German ancestry- (right) and their [[German Venezuelan]] daughter (center)]]
About 300,000 Cantonese coolies and migrants (almost all males) were shipped in 1849 to 1874 to Latin america, many of them intermarried and cohabited with the Black, Mestizo, and European population of Cuba, Peru, Guyana, and Trinidad.

About 100,000 Cantonese coolies (almost all males) in 1849 to 1874 migrated to Peru and intermarried with Peruvian women of mestizo, European, Ameridian, European/mestizo, African and mulatto origin. Many Peruvian Chinese today are of mixed Chinese, Spanish, African, Ameridian. Estimates for Chinese-Peruvian is about 1.3 – 1.6 millions. Asian Peruvians are estimated to be 3% of the population, but one source places the number of citizens with some Chinese ancestry at 4.2 million, which equates to 15% of the country's total population.&lt;ref&gt;[http://taste-of-peru.com/peruvian_culture/chinese.php Taste of Peru]. Taste of Peru. Retrieved 29 January 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

120,000 Cantonese coolies (all males) entered Cuba under contract for 80 years, most did not married, but Hung Hui (1975:80) cites there was an frequency of sexual activity between black women and Cantonese coolies. According to Osberg (1965:69) the free Chinese practice of buying slave women and freeing them expressly for marriage. In the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, Chinese men (Cantonese) engaged in sexual activity with white Cuban women and black Cuban women, and from such relations many children were born. (For a British Caribbean model of Chinese cultural retention through procreation with black women, see Patterson, 322-31).&lt;ref&gt;Identity, Rebellion, and Social Justice Among Chinese Contract Workers in Nineteenth-Century Cuba [http://www.upf.edu/mon/assig/xialmo/mat/dorsey_4.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1920s an additional 30000 Cantonese and small groups of Japanese also arrived; both immigrations were exclusively male, and there was rapid with white, black, and mulato populations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.history.com/topics/cuba Cuba — History.com Articles, Video, Pictures and Facts]. History.com. Retrieved 29 January 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=David Stanley|title=Cuba: a Lonely Planet travel survival kit|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=9HpqAAAAMAAJ|accessdate=29 January 2012|date=January 1997|publisher=Lonely Planet|isbn=978-0-86442-403-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the CIA World Factbook. Cuba. 2008. 15 May 2008 estimated 114,240 Chinese-Cuban coolies with only 300 pure Chinese.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/cu.html CIA – The World Factbook]. Cia.gov. Retrieved 29 January 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; In the study of Genetic origin, admixture, and asymmetry in maternal and paternal human lineages in Cuba. Thirty-five Y-chromosome SNPs were typed in the 132 male individuals of the Cuban sample. The study does not include any people with some Chinese ancestry. All the samples were White Cubans and Black Cubans. 2 out of 132 male sample belong to East Asian Haplogroup O2 which is found in significant frequencies among Cantonese people is found in 1.5% of Cuban population.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid|18644108}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Chinese in Costa Rica originated from the Cantonese male migrants. Pure Chinese make up only 1% of the Costa Rican population but according to Jacqueline M. Newman, as close to ten percent of the people in Costa Rica are Chinese, if we count the people who are Chinese, married to a Chinese, or of mixed Chinese descent. Than ten percent of three and a half million is a sizable number.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flavorandfortune.com/dataaccess/article.php?ID=221 Chinese Food in Costa Rica by Jacqueline M. Newman]. Flavorandfortune.com. Retrieved 2 March 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; Most Chinese immigrants since then have been Cantonese, but in the last decades of the 20th century, a number of immigrants have also come from Taiwan. Many men came alone to work and married Costa Rican women and speak Cantonese. However the majority of the descendants of the first Chinese immigrants no longer speak cantonese and feel themselves to be Costa Ricans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Margaret Tyler Mitchell|author2=Scott Pentzer|title=Costa Rica: a global studies handbook|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=0edCL8TY08gC&amp;pg=PA249|accessdate=2 March 2012|year=2008|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=978-1-85109-992-4|pages=249–}}&lt;/ref&gt; They married Tican women (Who an blend of Europeans, Caztizos, Mestizos, Indian, Black).&lt;ref&gt;[http://philip.greenspun.com/cr/moon/people Costa Rica, People]. Philip.greenspun.com. Retrieved 29 January 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; An Tican is also an White person with small portion of non-white blood like Caztizos. The census In 1989 shows about 98% of the of Costa Ricans were either White, Castizos, Mestizos, with 80% being White or Caztizos.

Around 20,000 Mostly Cantonese and some Hakka coolies migrated to Jamaica, Guyana, Trinidad. Many of them also intermarried with Black women and East Indian women due to Chinese women being an few. Unlike in Trinidad Tobago and Guyana who were predominantly Cantonese men who intermarried with Black women and East Indian women. The Chinese who migrated to Jamaica and intermarried Black women were mostly Hakka. According to the 1946 Census from Jamaica and Trinidad alone, 12,394 Chinese were located between [[Jamaica]] and [[Trinidad]]. 5,515 of those who lived in [[Jamaica]] were Chinese-Jamaicans and another 3,673 were Chinese-Trinidadians living in [[Trinidad]] 4,061 local born, 5,515 Chinese coloured (one Chinese parent). In Trinidad, there were 9,314: 2,366 China-born, 2,926 local born, 349 born abroad (from other colonies), 3,673 Chinese coloured.&lt;ref name=&quot;The United States&quot;/&gt; In Jamaica and other Caribbean nations as well many Chinese males over generations took up African wives, gradually assimilating or absorbing many Chinese descendants into the African Caribbean community or the overall mixed-race community.&lt;ref&gt;[http://motherearthtravel.com/guyana/population.htm Population of Guyana]. Motherearthtravel.com. Retrieved 29 January 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; In Guyana, the Chinese were mostly Cantonese men who intermarried with the local women. Because almost all of the Chinese indentured immigrants were men, they tended to intermarry with both East Indians and Africans, and thus the Chinese of Guyana did not remain as physically distinct as other groups.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.everyculture.com/Middle-America-Caribbean/Chinese-in-the-English-Speaking-Caribbean-Settlements.html: Chinese in the English-Speaking Caribbean – Settlements]. Everyculture.com. Retrieved 29 January 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; Their offspring also tended to intermarried with the local African and East Indian Guyanese rather than with the Chinese colored, as result some Guyanese who have little Chinese ancestry are not included in the Census, some may also don't know of there Chinese ancestry.

===Asia===
Inter-ethnic marriage in [[Southeast Asia]] dates back to the spread of [[Culture of India|Indian culture]], [[Hinduism]] and [[Buddhism]] to the region. From the 1st century onwards, mostly male traders and merchants from the [[Indian subcontinent]] frequently intermarried with the local female populations in [[Cambodia]], [[Burma]], [[Champa]], [[Central Thailand|central Siam]], the [[Malay Peninsula]], and [[Malay Archipelago]]. Many [[Indianized kingdom]]s arose in Southeast Asia during the [[Middle Ages]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |title=Streams of civilization|last=Albert Hyma|first=Mary Stanton|volume=1|publisher=Christian Liberty Press|page=215}}&lt;/ref&gt;

From the 9th century onwards, a large number of mostly male [[Arab]] traders from the Middle East settled down in the Malay Peninsula and Malay Archipelago, and they intermarried with the local [[Malay (ethnic group)|Malay]], [[Indonesia]]n and [[Filipino people|Filipina]] female populations. This contributed to the spread of [[Islam in Southeast Asia]].&lt;ref name=Arab-Malays&gt;{{cite web|title=Arab and native intermarriage in Austronesian Asia|work=ColorQ World|url=http://www.colorq.org/MeltingPot/article.aspx?d=Asia&amp;x=ArabMalays|accessdate=24 December 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; From the 14th to the 17th centuries, many [[China|Chinese]], [[History of India|Indian]] and Arab traders settled down within the maritime kingdoms of Southeast Asia and intermarried with the local female populations. This tradition continued among [[Portuguese people|Portuguese]] traders who also intermarried with the local populations.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |title=The Cambridge History of Southeast Asia|first=Nicholas|last=Tarling|year=1999|isbn=0-521-66370-9|page=149|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|location=Cambridge}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 16th and 17th centuries, thousands of [[Japanese people]] also travelled to Southeast Asia and intermarried with the local women there.&lt;ref name=Leupp/&gt;

From the tenth to twelfth century, [[Persian people|Persian]] women were to be found in [[Guangzhou]] (Canton), some of them in the tenth century like [[Mei Zhu]] in the harem of the Emperor [[Liu Chang]], and in the twelfth century large numbers of Persian women lived there, noted for wearing mulitiple earrings and &quot;quarrelsome dispositions&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Walter Joseph Fischel 1951 407&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Walter Joseph Fischel|title=Semitic and Oriental studies: a volume presented to William Popper, professor of Semitic languages, emeritus, on the occasion of his seventy-fifth birthday, October 29, 1949|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=v68NAAAAIAAJ|accessdate=2 March 2012|year=1951|publisher=University of California Press|page=407}}&lt;/ref&gt; Multiple women originating from the [[Persian Gulf]] lived in Guangzhou's foreign quarter, they were all called &quot;Persian women&quot; (波斯婦 Po-ssu-fu or Bosifu).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=http://books.google.com/books?ei=TUtTTZvCLcL6lwfv-rmNCg|title=Memoirs of the Research Department of the Toyo Bunko (the Oriental Library), Issue 2|author=Tōyō Bunko (Japan). Kenkyūbu|year=1928|publisher=The Toyo Bunko|location=the University of Michigan|page=34|accessdate=9 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Some scholars did not differentiate between Persian and Arab, and some say that the Chinese called all women coming from the Persian Gulf &quot;Persian Women&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=History of Science Society|author2=Académie internationale d'histoire des sciences|title=Isis|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=NlEbAAAAMAAJ|accessdate=2 March 2012|year=1939|publisher=Published by the University of Chicago Press for the History of Science Society|page=120}}&lt;/ref&gt; Genetic evidence shows Persian women intermarried with Cantonese men of Guangzhou. Yao Yonggang et al. reported that Kivisild detected one W mtDNA out of 69 Guangzhou Cantonese population, an common Middle Easterner and Iranian marker.&lt;ref name=&quot;ncbi.nlm.nih.gov&quot;&gt;{{cite pmid|11836649}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The white men who sailed to Asia in the 16th century left a generation of mixed-race offspring that, at the high point of empire building, was more than one-million strong.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,106427,00.html Eurasian Invasion]&quot;. Time. 16 April 2001.&lt;/ref&gt; Some 100,000 Amerasians stayed in [[Vietnam]] after the fall of Saigon.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,808572,00.html SOUTH VIET NAM: The Girls Left Behind]&quot;. Time. 10 September 1956.&lt;/ref&gt; During and after the Indonesian National Revolution (1945–1965) around 300,000 people, pre-dominantly [[Indo people|Eurasians]], left Indonesia to go to the Netherlands.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://press.princeton.edu/chapters/s8421.html When Ways of Life Collide: Multiculturalism and Its Discontents in the Netherlands]&quot;. Princeton University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 19th century and early 20th century, there was a network of small numbers of [[Han Chinese|Chinese]] [[Prostitution|prostitutes]] being [[Prostitution in Asia|trafficked across Asia]], in countries such as China, Japan, [[Korea]], [[Singapore]] and [[British India]], in what was then known as the ’Yellow Slave Traffic’. There was also a network of prostitutes from [[continental Europe]] being [[Prostitution in India|trafficked to India]], [[British Ceylon|Ceylon]], Singapore, China and Japan at around the same time, in what was then known as the ’White Slave Traffic’.&lt;ref name=&quot;doi10.1177/001946460304000202&quot;&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1177/001946460304000202}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Chinese girl from one of the Japanese Army's 'comfort battalions'.jpg|thumb|[[Rangoon]], [[Burma]]. 8 August 1945. A young [[Chinese diaspora|ethnic Chinese]] woman who was in one of the [[Imperial Japanese Army]]'s &quot;[[comfort women|comfort stations]]&quot; is interviewed by an [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] officer.]]

During World War II, [[Empire of Japan|Japanese]] soldiers engaged in [[war rape]] during their invasions across [[East Asia]] and Southeast Asia. The term &quot;[[comfort women]]&quot; is a [[euphemism]] for the estimated 200,000, mostly [[Korean people|Korean]] and Chinese, women who were employed as prostitutes in [[Imperial Japanese Army|Japanese military]] brothels during World War II. Some [[Dutch people|Dutch]] women, captured in Dutch colonies in Asia, were also forced into [[sexual slavery]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal
|ref=CITEREFchosun.com2007-03-19
|url=http://english.chosun.com/w21data/html/news/200703/200703190023.html
|title=Comfort Women Were 'Raped': U.S. Ambassador to Japan
|publisher=Digital Chosunibuto (English edition)
|date=19 March 2007
|accessdate=2 July 2008
| archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080605004220/http://english.chosun.com/w21data/html/news/200703/200703190023.html| archivedate = 5 June 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; More than 20,000 Indonesian women&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=qrxdE2sheOUC&amp;pg=PA82&amp;dq=20,000+indonesians+comfort+women&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=ru30T6XABouR0QXuvNSABw&amp;ved=0CDcQ6AEwAA#v=onepa]&lt;/ref&gt; and nearly 300 Dutch women.&lt;ref&gt;Korean American Women: From Tradition to Modern Feminism
edited by Young In Song, Ailee Moon [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=aQu7avHHTm4C&amp;pg=PA248&amp;dq=300+dutch+women+comfort+women&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=G-30T-q5A4Sr0QWviZyrBw&amp;ved=0CDsQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=300%20dutch%20women%20comfort%20women&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Sex tourism]] has emerged in the late 20th century as a controversial aspect of
Western tourism and globalization. Sex tourism is typically undertaken internationally by tourists from wealthier countries. Author [[Nils Johan Ringdal|Nils Ringdal]] alleged that three out of four men between the ages of 20 and 50 who have visited Asia or Africa have paid for sex.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment//reviews/love-for-sale-a-global-history-of-prostitution-by-nils-ringdal-trans-richard-daly-751462.html Love for Sale: a global history of prostitution by Nils Ringdal, trans Richard Daly]. By Sarah Burton. ''The Independent.'' November 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

====Central Asia====
Today Central Asians are a mixed race of various peoples such as Mongols, Turkics, Iranics. The Mongol invasion of Central Asia in 13th century resulted in the massacre of mostly white Iranic population and other [[Proto-Indo-Europeans|Indo-European people]] as well as large numbers of intermarriage and assimilation. Modern Genetic shows that Central Asian Turkic people and Hazara are an mixture of Northeast Asians and Indo-European people. Caucasian ancestry is prevalent in almost all central Asian Turkic people. Kazakhs, Hazara, Karakalpaks, Crimean Tatars have more European mtdna than European y-dna, Kyrgyz have mostly European y-dna with substantial European mtdna. Other Turkic people like Uyghurs, Uzbeks, have mostly European y-dna but also an significant high percentages of European mtdna. Turkmen have predominately European y-dna and mtdna.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1086/342096}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

====China====
There have been various periods in the [[history of China]] where a number of [[Arab]]s, [[Persian people|Persians]] and [[Turkic peoples|Turks]] from the [[Western Regions]] ([[Central Asia]] and [[West Asia]]) migrated to China, beginning with the arrival of [[Islam during the Tang Dynasty]] in the 7th century. Due to the majority of these immigrants being male, some have decided to intermarry with local [[Chinese people|Chinese]] females. Intermarriage was initially discouraged by the [[Tang Dynasty]]. In 836 Lu Chun was appointed as governor of Canton, he was disgusted to find Chinese living with foreigners and intermarriage between Chinese and foreigners. Lu enforced separation, banning interracial marriages, and made it illegal for foreigners to own property. Lu Chun believed his principles were just and upright.&lt;ref name=golden&gt;{{cite book|author=Edward H. Schafer|title=The golden peaches of Samarkand: a study of Tʻang exotics|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=jqAGIL02BWQC&amp;pg=PA22|accessdate=2 March 2012|year=1963|publisher=University of California Press|isbn=978-0-520-05462-2|pages=22–}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 836 law specifically banned Chinese from forming relationships with &quot;Dark peoples&quot; or &quot;People of colour&quot;, which was used to describe foreigners, such as &quot;Iranians, Sogdians, Arabs, Indians, Malays, Sumatrans&quot;, among others.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Mark Edward Lewis|title=China's cosmopolitan empire: the Tang dynasty|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=vpgVvAh2_EsC&amp;pg=PA170|accessdate=2 March 2012|date=30 June 2009|publisher=Harvard University Press|isbn=978-0-674-03306-1|pages=170–}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Jacques Gernet|title=A History of Chinese Civilization|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=jqb7L-pKCV8C|accessdate=2 March 2012|date=31 May 1996|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-0-521-49781-7|page=294}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Song Dynasty]] allowed [[Immigrant generations|third-generation immigrants]] with official titles to intermarry with Chinese imperial princesses.&lt;ref name=&quot;colorq&quot;/&gt;

Iranian, Arab, and Turkic women also migrated to China and mixed with Chinese.&lt;ref name=colorq&gt;{{cite web|title=Chinese of Arab and Persian descent|publisher=ColorQ World|url=http://www.colorq.org/MeltingPot/article.aspx?d=Asia&amp;x=ChineseWestAsians|accessdate=23 December 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; From the tenth to twelfth century, [[Persian people|Persian]] women were to be found in [[Guangzhou]] (Canton), some of them in the tenth century like [[Mei Zhu]] in the harem of the Emperor [[Liu Chang]], and in the twelfth century large numbers of Persian women lived there, noted for wearing mulitiple earrings and &quot;quarrelsome dispositions&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Walter Joseph Fischel 1951 407&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=v68NAAAAIAAJ|title=Semitic and Oriental studies: a volume presented to William Popper, professor of Semitic languages, emeritus, on the occasion of his seventy-fifth birthday, October 29, 1949|author=Walter Joseph Fischel|year=1951|publisher=University of California Press|page=407|accessdate=29 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=zucsAQAAIAAJ|title=University of California publications in Semitic philology, Volumes 11–12|author=University of California (1868–1952), University of California (System), University of California, Berkeley|year=1951|publisher=University of California Press|page=407|accessdate=29 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Multiple women originating from the [[Persian Gulf]] lived in Guangzhou's foreign quarter, they were all called &quot;Persian women&quot; (波斯婦 Po-ssu-fu or Bosifu).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=rBIUAQAAMAAJ|title=Memoirs of the Research Department of the Toyo Bunko (the Oriental Library), Issue 2|author=Tōyō Bunko (Japan). Kenkyūbu|year=1928|publisher=The Toyo Bunko|location=the University of Michigan|page=34|accessdate=9 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Genetic evidence shows Persian women intermarried with Cantonese men of Guangzhou. Yao Yonggang et al. reported that Kivisild detected one W mtDNA out of 69 Guangzhou Cantonese population, an common Middle Easterner and Iranian marker.&lt;ref name=&quot;ncbi.nlm.nih.gov&quot;/&gt; Iranian women as dancers were in demand in China during this period. During the Sui dynasty, ten young dancing girls were sent from Persia to China. During the [[Tang dynasty]] bars were often attended by Iranian or Sogdian waitresses who performed dances for clients.&lt;ref name=golden/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=SbgPAAAAYAAJ |title=Kukai the universal: scenes from his life|author=Ryōtarō Shiba|year=2003|publisher=ICG Muse|pages=127, 132, 135|isbn=4-925080-47-4|page=350|accessdate=29 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=UNa4-NkYYjAC&amp;pg=PA485|title=The Columbia Anthology of Traditional Chinese Literature|author=Victor H. Mair|year=1996|publisher=Columbia University Press|page=485|isbn=0-231-07429-8|accessdate=29 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=S6gwlvp61s4C&amp;pg=PA8|title=Music in the World of Islam|author=Amnon Shiloah|year=2003|publisher=Wayne State University Press|page=8|isbn=0-8143-2970-5|accessdate=29 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=QyyCAAAAIAAJ |title=The life and thoughts of Li Ho: the Tʾang poet|author=Naotaro Kudo|year=1969|publisher=Waseda University|page=62|accessdate=29 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=s6OR4V0M80AC&amp;pg=PA117|title=Oranges &amp; Peanuts for Sale|author=Eliot Weinberger|year=2009|publisher=New Directions Publishing|page=117|isbn=0-8112-1834-1|accessdate=29 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=YukVl8fUr48C&amp;pg=PA97 |title=Pre-modern East Asia: to 1800: a cultural, social, and political history|author=Patricia Buckley Ebrey, Anne Walthall, James Palais|year=2008|publisher=Cengage Learning|page=97|isbn=0-547-00539-3|accessdate=29 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=ixCyd2lByggC&amp;pg=PA423|title=History of humanity |author=Mohammad Adnan Bakhit|year=2000|publisher=UNESCO|page=423|isbn=92-3-102813-8|accessdate=29 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=7S_VAAAAMAAJ |title=The Westerners among the figurines of the T'ang dynasty of China|author=Jane Gaston Mahler|year=1959|publisher=Instituto italiano per il Medio ed Estremo Oriente|page=19|accessdate=29 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=jDUrAQAAIAAJ |title=ASSAPH.: Studies in the theatre, Issues 9–12|author=Universiṭat Tel-Aviv. Faḳulṭah le-omanuyot|year=1993|publisher=Faculty of Visual and Performing Arts, Tel Aviv University|page=89|accessdate=29 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=45ZZAAAAMAAJ |title=ASSAPH.: Studies in the theatre, Issues 9–12|author=Avraham Oz, Universiṭat Tel-Aviv. Faḳulṭah le-omanuyot|year=1993|publisher=Faculty of Visual and Performing Arts, Tel Aviv University|page=89|accessdate=29 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=eJfWAAAAMAAJ |title=Memoirs of the Research Department, Issue 20|author=Tōyō Bunko (Japan)|accessdate=29 June 2010|year=1961}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the Five Dynasties and Ten Kingdoms Period(Wudai) (907–960), there are examples of Persian women marrying Chinese emperors. Some Chinese officials from the Song Dynasty era also married women from Dashi (Arabia).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=jV9_YvgUmpsC&amp;pg=PA74|title=The history of women's mosques in Chinese Islam: a mosque of their own|author=Maria Jaschok, Jingjun Shui|year=2000|publisher=Routledge|page=74|isbn=0-7007-1302-6|accessdate=29 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Of the Han Chinese Li family in Quanzhou, [[Li Nu]], the son of Li Lu, visited [[Ormus|Hormuz]] in [[Persia]] in 1376, married a [[Persian people|Persian]] or an [[Arab]] girl, and brought her back to [[Quanzhou]]. He then converted to Islam, Li Nu was the ancestor of the Ming Dynasty reformer [[Li Zhi (philosopher)|Li Chih]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=067On0JgItAC&amp;pg=PA817 |title=A-L, Volumes 1–2|author=Association for Asian studies (Ann Arbor;Michigan)|year=1976|publisher=Columbia University Press|page=817|isbn=0-231-03801-1|accessdate=29 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Chen&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iranicaonline.org/articles/chinese-iranian-vii|title=Chinese-Iranian Relations vii. Persian Settlements in Southeastern China during the T'ang, Sung, and Yuan Dynasties|last=Chen|first=Da-Sheng|publisher=Encyclopædia Iranica|accessdate=28 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=l6TVhvYLaEwC&amp;pg=PA495|title=Science and civilisation in China, Volume 4|author=Joseph Needham|year=1971|publisher=Cambridge University Press|page=495|isbn=0-521-07060-0|accessdate=29 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By the 14th century, the total population of [[Islam in China|Muslims in China]] had grown to 4 million.&lt;ref name=&quot;Israeli&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|last = Israeli|first = Raphael|title = Islam in China|publisher = [[Rowman &amp; Littlefield|Lexington Books]]|year = 2002|location = United States of America|isbn = 0-7391-0375-X|page = 285}}&lt;/ref&gt; After Mongol rule had been overthrown by the [[Ming Dynasty]] in 1368, this led to a violent Chinese backlash against West and Central Asians. In order to contain the violence, the Ming administration instituted a policy where all West and Central Asian males were required to intermarry with native Chinese females, hence assimilating them into the local population. Their descendants are today known as the [[Hui people]].&lt;ref name=colorq/&gt; 6.7% Hui people's maternal genetics have an Caucasian origin, while slightly over 30% paternal genetics also have an Caucasian origin.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gnxp.com/blog/2005/08/western-barbarian-han-women-hui.php Gene Expression: Western barbarian + Han women = Hui]. Gnxp.com. Retrieved 29 January 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; In the 19th century, the Hui rebelled against the Chinese government trying to [[Panthay Rebellion|create]] an independent state.

Han women who married Hui men became Hui, and Han men who married Hui women also became Hui.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=BwuSpFiOFfYC&amp;pg=PA31|title=China's Muslim Hui community: migration, settlement and sects|author=Michael Dillon|year=1999|publisher=Curzon Press|location=Richmond|page=31|isbn=0-7007-1026-4|accessdate=17 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=_hJ9aht6nZQC&amp;pg=PA245 |title=Muslim Chinese: ethnic nationalism in the People's Republic|author=Dru C. Gladney|year=1996|publisher=Harvard Univ Asia Center|location=Cambridge Massachusetts|page=245|isbn=0-674-59497-5|accessdate=17 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=0UzrAAAAMAAJ |title=China archaeology and art digest, Volume 3, Issue 4|year=2000|publisher=Art Text (HK) Ltd.|page=30|accessdate=17 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the frontier districts of [[Sichuan]], numerous half Chinese-Tibetans were found. Tibetan women were glad to marry Chinese traders and soldiers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=I44XAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA355|title=The history of mankind, Volume 3|author=Friedrich Ratzel|year=1898|publisher=Macmillan and co., ltd|page=355|accessdate=30 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some Chinese traders married Tibetan girls.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=WyJBXpDyxXAC&amp;pg=PA19 |title=The A Tibetan Revolutionary: The Political Life and Times of Bapa Phüntso Wangye|author=Melvyn C. Goldstein, Dawei Sherap, William Siebenschuh, William R. Siebenschuh|year=2006|publisher=University of California Press|isbn=0-520-24992-5|page=19|accessdate=30 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Traders and officials in ancient times were often forbidden to bring Chinese women with them to Tibet, so they had to marry Tibetan women, the male offspring where considered Chinese and female offspring as Tibetan.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=STHWAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA606 |title=Littell's living age, Volume 191|author=Eliakim Littell, Robert S. Littell|year=1891|publisher=T.H. Carter &amp; Co.|page=606|accessdate=30 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=yCMtAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA81 |title=The National review, Volume 23|year=1894|publisher=W.H. Allen|page=81|accessdate=30 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=v4JKAAAAMAAJ |title=China at war, Volumes 1–2|author=China Information Committee|year=1938|publisher=The China Information Publishing Company|page=54|accessdate=30 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=Tymocjt1T2wC&amp;pg=PA8|title=Theosophical Review Magazine September 1903 – December 1903|author=Helena Petrovna Blavatsky, Annie Wood Besant|year=2003|publisher=Kessinger Publishing|isbn=0-7661-5327-4|page=8|accessdate=30 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=RZIkAQAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA8 |title=The Theosophical review, Volume 33|year=1904|page=8|accessdate=30 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Special names were used for these children of Chinese fathers and Tibetan mothers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=7qZ7Wk-5PHYC&amp;pg=PA100 |title=Lhasa|publisher=Concept Publishing Company|page=100|accessdate=30 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; They are often assimilated into the Tibetan population.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=RwUa3zUGhc8C&amp;pg=PA180 |title=Travels of a Consular Officer in Eastern Tibet|author=Teichman Eric|year=2009|publisher=BiblioBazaar, LLC|isbn=1-110-31267-9|page=180|accessdate=30 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Chinese and Nepalese in Tibet married Tibetan women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=RgOK7CgFp88C&amp;pg=PA243 |title=Tibet Past and Present|author=Charles Bell|year=1992|publisher=Motilal Banarsidass Publ.|isbn=81-208-1048-1|page=243|accessdate=30 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Qinghai]], premarital sex between Tibetan girls and Han Chinese was common, some Tibetan girls boasted of their sexual conquests of Han Chinese boys.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=1ReDfiQm5gQC&amp;pg=PA154 |title=Mao's People: Sixteen Portraits of Life in Revolutionary China|author=B. Michael Frolic|year=1981|publisher=Harvard University Press|page=154|accessdate=30 July 2010|isbn=978-0-674-54845-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Chinese men also married Turkic [[Uyghur people|Uyghur]] women in Xinjiang from 1880–1949. Sometimes poverty influenced Uyghur women to marry Chinese. These marriages were not recognized by local [[mullah]]s since Muslims women were not allowed to marry non-Muslim men under Islamic law. This did not stop the women because they enjoyed advantages, not being subject to Islamic law and they were not subjected to certain taxes. Uyghur women married to Chinese also did not have to wear a [[veil]] and they received their husband's property upon his death. These women were forbidden from having burial in Muslim graves. The children of Chinese men and Uyghur women were considered as Uyghur. Some Chinese soldiers had Uyghur women as temporary wives, and after the man's military service was up, the wife was left behind or sold, and if it was possible, sons were taken, and daughters were sold.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=cF4lMj8skvoC&amp;pg=PA85 |title=Community matters in Xinjiang, 1880–1949: towards a historical anthropology of the Uyghur|author=Ildikó Bellér-Hann|year=2008|publisher=BRILL|isbn=90-04-16675-0|pages=83–85|accessdate=30 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

European travellers noted that many Han Chinese in Xinjiang married Uyghur (who were called turki) women and had children with them. A Chinese was spotted with a &quot;young&quot; and &quot;good looking&quot; Uyghur wife and another Chinese left behind his Uyghur wife and child in Khotan.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=mCS1940T5MkC&amp;pg=PA77|title=Chinese Central Asia Volume II – A Ride to Little Tibet Volume|author=Henry Lansdell|year=2009|publisher=READ BOOKS|isbn=1-4446-2164-5|page=77|accessdate=30 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=dWlCAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA77|title=Chinese Central Asia; a ride to Little Tibet, Volume 2|author=Henry Lansdell|year=1894|page=77|accessdate=30 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=eEwTAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA893|title=Encyclopædia of religion and ethics, Volume 8|author=James Hastings, John Alexander Selbie, Louis Herbert Gray|year=1916|publisher=T. &amp; T. Clark|page=893|accessdate=30 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=p5U3AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA849|title=E.J. Brill's first encyclopaedia of Islam, 1913–1936, Volume 2|author=Martijn Theodoor Houtsma|year=1987|publisher=BRILL|isbn=90-04-08265-4|page=849|accessdate=30 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=AtwMAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA954|title=Through Asia, Volume 2|author=Sven Anders Hedin|year=1899|publisher=Harper and brothers|page=954|accessdate=30 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=8NKgFRMj7QAC&amp;pg=PA328 |title=The Pamirs Being a Narrative of a Year's Expedition on Horseback and on Foot through Kashmir, Western Tibet, Chinese Tartary and Russian Central Asia. Volume 1|publisher=Adegi Graphics LLC|isbn=1-4021-8434-4|page=328|accessdate=30 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=Qp82AAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA328 |title=The Pamirs: being a narrative of a year's expedition on horseback and on foot through Kashmir, western Tibet, Chinese Tartary, and Russian Central Asia, Volume 1|author=Charles Adolphus Murray Dunmore (Earl of)|year=1893|publisher=J. Murray|page=328|accessdate=30 July 2010|isbn=1-4021-8434-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After 1950, some intermarriage between Han and Uyghur continued. A Han married a Uyghur woman in 1966 and had three daughters with her, and other cases on intermarriage also continued.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=Jl_Zw9QzvxEC&amp;pg=PA120 |title=China's minorities on the move: selected case studies|author=Robyn R. Iredale, Naran Bilik, Fei Guo|year=2003|publisher=M.E. Sharpe|isbn=0-7656-1023-X|page=120|accessdate=30 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=r1lgwbnlWnoC&amp;pg=PA76|title=Imagined differences: hatred and the construction of identity, Volume 2001|author=Günther Schlee|year=2002|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|isbn=1-4039-6031-3|page=76|accessdate=30 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Hong Kong====

In the study of mitochondrial DNA control region variation in a population sample Irwin et al. found U2b mtDNA once, other U2 twice, H11 once and J1 once in 377 HKers which suggest 1.34% of West Eurasian female admixture in Hong Kong Cantonese population.&lt;ref&gt;
Mitochondrial DNA control region variation in a population sample from Hong Kong, China
Jodi A. Irwin a,*, Jessica L. Saunier a, Philip Beh b, Katharine M. Strouss a, Carla D. Paintner a, Thomas J. Parsons a,1 [http://w173496.s40.myverydz.com/viewthread.php?action=printable&amp;tid=4714]&lt;/ref&gt; In the sample of 112 found 2 (or 1.78%) mtDNA Indo-European markers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mendeley.com/research/mitochondrial-dna-control-region-variation-in-a-population-sample-from-hong-kong-china/#page-1]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|pmid=19647696 |title=Mitochondrial DNA control region variation in a population sample from Hong Kong, China|year=2009|last1=Irwin|first1=JA|last2=Saunier|first2=JL|last3=Beh|first3=P|last4=Strouss|first4=KM|last5=Paintner|first5=CD|last6=Parsons|first6=TJ|volume=3|issue=4|pages=e119–25|doi=10.1016/j.fsigen.2008.10.008|journal=Forensic science international. Genetics}}&lt;/ref&gt;
These results do not give any information as to the extent of male European admixture in the Hong Kong population. Many Tanka women conceived children with foreign men. Ernest John Eitel mentioned in 1889 how important change had taken place among Eurasian girls, the offspring of illicit connections: Instead of becoming concubines, they were commonly brought up respectably and married to Hong Kong Chinese husbands. Some believed many Hong Kong born Eurasian were assimilated into the Hong Kong society by Intermarriage with the [[Cantonese people|Cantonese]] population. A good example of a Cantonese Eurasian is [[Nancy Kwan]], a Hollywood sex symbol, she was of Eurasian origin born in 1939 in Hong Kong to a father who was a Cantonese architect and mother who is an model of British and Scottish descent. The world's most influential martial artist icon [[Bruce Lee]], was also born to parents of Hong Kong heritage to a Cantonese father and a Eurasian mother.

{{main|Tanka people}}
Ernest John Eitel controversially claimed that most &quot;half caste&quot; people in Hong Kong were descended exclusively from Europeans having relationship with [[Tanka people|Tanka women]]. The theory that most of the Eurasian mixed race Hong Kong people are descended only from Tanka women and European men, and not ordinary Cantonese women, has been backed up by other researchers who pointed out that Tanka women freely consorted with foreigners due to the fact that they were not bound by the same Confucian traditions as the Cantonese, and having a relationship with European men was advantageous for Tanka women, but Lethbridge criticized it as &quot;a 'myth' propagated by xenophobic Cantonese to account for the establishment of the Hong Kong Eurasian community&quot;. Carl Smith's study in late 1960s on the protected women seems, to some degree, support Ernest John Eitel theory. Smith says that the Tankas experienced certain restrictions within the traditional Chinese social structure. Being a group marginal to the traditional Chinese society of the Puntis (Cantonese), they did not have the same social pressure in dealing with Europeans. The ordinary Cantonese women did not sleep with European men, the Eurasian population was formed mostly from Tanka and European admixture.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Meiqi Lee |title=Being Eurasian: memories across racial divides |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=mVGd71y1Y-0C&amp;pg=PA262|year=2004 |publisher=Hong Kong University Press|isbn=962-209-671-9 |page=262 |quote=EJ Eitel, in the late 1890s, claims that the 'half-caste population in Hong Kong ' were from the earliest days of the settlement almost exclusively the offspring of liaisons between European men and women of outcaste ethnic groups such as Tanka (Europe in , 169). Lethbridge refutes the theory saying it was based on a 'myth' propagated by xenophobic Cantonese to account for the establishment of the Hong Kong Eurasian community. Carl Smith's study in late 1960s on the protected women seems, to some degree, support Eitel's theory. Smith says that the Tankas experienced certain restrictions within the traditional Chinese social structure. Custom precluded their intermarriage with the Cantonese and Hakka-speaking populations. The Tanka women did not have bound feet. Their opportunities for settlement on shore were limited. They were hence not as closely tied to Confucian ethics as other Chinese ethnic groups. Being a group marginal to the traditional Chinese society of the Puntis (Cantonese), they did not have the same social pressure in dealing with Europeans (CT Smith, Chung Chi Bulletin, 27). 'Living under the protection of a foreigner,' says Smith, 'could be a ladder to financial security, if not respectability, for some of the Tanka boat girls' (13 ).}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |coauthors=Maria Jaschok, Suzanne Miers |editor=Maria Jaschok, Suzanne Miers |title=Women and Chinese patriarchy: submission, servitude, and escape |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=f5o_t7VxHYAC&amp;pg=PA223 |accessdate=1 November 2011 |year=1994|publisher=Zed Books |isbn=1-85649-126-9 |page=223|quote=He states that they had a near- monopoly of the trade in girls and women, and that: The half-caste population in Hong Kong were, from the earliest days of the settlement of the Colony and down to the present day, almost exclusively the offspring of these Tan-ka people. But, like the Tan-ka people themselves, they are happily under the influence of a process of continuous re-absorption in the mass of Chinese residents of the Colony (1895 p. 169)}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Helen F. Siu |editor=Helen F. Siu |title=Merchants' Daughters: Women, Commerce, and Regional Culture in South |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=gM9cMIxjoVcC&amp;pg=PA305 |accessdate=2 November 2011 |year=2011 |publisher=Hong Kong University Press |isbn=988-8083-48-1 |page=305 |quote=The half-caste population of Hongkong were . . . almost exclusively the offspring of these Tan-ka women. EJ Eitel, Europe in , the History of Hongkong from the Beginning to the Year 1882 (Taipei: Chen-Wen Publishing Co., originally published in Hong Kong by Kelly and Walsh. 1895, 1968), 169.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Henry J. Lethbridge |title=Hong Kong, stability and change: a collection of essays |url=http://books.google.com/books?ei=VbqxTpHrAarg0QGggaGoAQ |accessdate=1 November 2011 |year=1978 |publisher=Oxford University Press|page=75 |quote=The half-caste population in Hong Kong were, from the earliest days of the settlement of the Colony and down to the present day [1895], almost exclusively the off-spring of these Tan-ka people}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
They invaded Hongkong the moment the settlement was started, living at first on boats in the harbour with their numerous families, and gradually settling on shore. They have maintained ever since almost a monopoly of the supply of pilots and ships' crews, of the fish trade and the cattle trade, but unfortunately also of the trade in girls and women. Strange to say, when the settlement was first started, it was estimated that some 2,000 of these Tan-ka lieople had flocked to Hongkong, but at the present time they are abont the same number, a tendency having set in among them to settle on shore rather than on the water and to disavow their Tan-ka extraction in order to mix on equal terms with the mass of the Chinese community. The half-caste population in Hongkong were, from the earliest days of the settlement of the Colony and down to the present day, almost exclusively the off-spring of these Tan-ka people. But, like the Tan-ka people themselves, they are happily under the influence of a process of continuous re-absorption in the mass of the Chinese residents of the Colony.&lt;ref&gt;Public Library{{cite book |author=Ernest John Eitel |title=Europe in China: the history of Hongkong from the beginning to the year 1882 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=20gQAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA169|accessdate=2 November 2011 |year=1895 |publisher=Luzac &amp; Co. |location=London |page=169}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Ernest John Eitel|title=Europe in China: the history of Hongkong from the beginning to the year 1882|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=20gQAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA169|year=1895|publisher=Luzac &amp; Co.|page=169}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[South Asians in Hong Kong|South Asians have been living in Hong Kong]] throughout the colonial period, before the [[partition of India]] into the nations of India and Pakistan. They migrated to [[Hong Kong]] and worked as police officers as well as army officers during colonial rule. 25,000 of the [[Islam in Hong Kong|Muslims in Hong Kong]] trace their roots back to what is now Pakistan. Around half of them belong to 'local boy' families, Muslims of mixed [[Chindian|Chinese and South Asian]] ancestry, descended from early Indian/Pakistani Muslim immigrants who took local Chinese wives and brought their children up as Muslims.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1017/S0026749X00013895}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Diaspora Entrepreneurial Networks: Four Centuries of History|last=Ina Baghdiantz McCabe|first=Gelina Harlaftis, Iōanna Pepelasē Minoglou|publisher=[[Berg Publishers]]|year=2005|isbn=1-85973-880-X|page=256}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Macau====
Due to a few Chinese living in Macau. The early Macanese ethnic group was formed from Portuguese men with Malay, Japanese, Indian women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Jonathan Porter |title=Macau, the imaginary city: culture and society, 1557 to the present |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=H2twAAAAMAAJ |accessdate=29 January 2012 |year=1996 |publisher=Westview Press |isbn=978-0-8133-2836-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Portuguese encouraged Chinese migration to Macau, and most Macanese in Macau were formed from intermarriages between Portuguese and Chinese. In 1810, the total population of Macau was about 4,033, of which 1,172 were white men, 1,830 were white women, 425 male slaves, and 606 female slaves. In 1830, the population increased to 4,480 and the breakdown was 1,202 white men, 2,149 white women, 350 male slaves and 779 female slaves. There is reason to speculate that large numbers of white women were involved in some forms of prostitution which would probably explain the abnormality in the ratio between men and women among the white population.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bjrhby.com/english/20617_5.html macau – The Las Vegas of the East &gt;&gt;Inscrutable Chinese&gt;&gt;English&gt;&gt;北京仁和博苑中医药研究院]. Bjrhby.com. Retrieved 29 January 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

Rarely did Chinese women marry Portuguese initially, mostly women from Goa, Siam, Indo China, or Malay, were brides of the Portuguese men in Macau.&lt;ref&gt;João de Pina-Cabral, p. 39: To be a Macanese is fundamentally to be from Macao with Portuguese ancestors, but not necessarily to be of Sino-Portuguese descent. The local community was born from Portugues emen. [...] but in the beginning the woman was Goanese, Siamese, Indo-Chinese, Malay – they came to Macao in our boats. Sporadically it was a Chinese woman.&lt;/ref&gt; Many Chinese became Macanese simply by converting to Catholicism, and had no ancestry from Portuguese, having assimilated into the Macanese people.&lt;ref&gt;João de Pina-Cabral, p. 39: When we established ourselves here, the Chinese ostracized us. The Portuguese had their wives, then, that came from abroad, but they could have no contact with the Chinese women, except the fishing folk, the tanka women and the female slaves. Only the lowest class of Chinese contacted with the Portuguese in the first centuries. But later the strength of Christianization, of the priests, started to convince the Chinese to become Catholic. [...] But, when they started to be Catholics, they adopted Portuguese baptismal names and were ostracized by the Chinese Buddhists. So they joined the Portuguese community and their sons started having Portuguese education without a single drop of Portuguese blood.&lt;/ref&gt; Majority of the early intermarriages of people from China with Portuguese were between Portuguese men and women of [[Tanka people|Tanka]] origin, who were considered the lowest class of people in China and had relations with Portuguese settlers and sailors, or low class Chinese women.&lt;ref&gt;João de Pina-Cabral, p. 164: I was personally told of people that, to this day, continue to hide the fact that their mothers had been lower-class Chinese women – often even tanka (fishing folk) women who had relations with Portguese sailors and soldiers.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;alibris.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.alibris.com/search/books/isbn/9781157453604 Society of Macau: Macanese People, Public Holidays in Macau, Tanka People]. Alibris. ISBN 978-1-157-45360-4 Retrieved 29 January 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;João de Pina-Cabral, p. 164&lt;/ref&gt; Western men were refused by high class Chinese women, who did not marry foreigners.&lt;ref&gt;João de Pina-Cabral, p. 165: In fact, in those days, the matrimonial context of production was usually constituted by Chinese women of low socio-economic status who were married to or concubies of Portuguese or Macanese men. Very rarely did Chinese women of higher status agree to marry a Westerner. As Deolinda argues in one of her short stories,&quot;8 should they have wanted to do so out of romantic infatuation, they would not be allowed to|&lt;/ref&gt; while an minority were Cantonese men and Portuguese women. Macanese men and women also married with the Portuguese and Chinese, as a result some Macanese became indistinguishable from the Chinese or Portuguese population. Because the Majority of the population who migrated to Macau was Cantonese, Macau became an culturely Cantonese speaking society, other ethnic groups became fluent in Cantonese. Most Macanese had paternal Portuguese heritage until 1974.&lt;ref name=&quot;alibris.com&quot;/&gt; It was in 1980s that Macanese and Portuguese women began to marry men who defined themselves ethnically as Chinese.&lt;ref&gt;João de Pina-Cabral, p. 165&lt;/ref&gt; Which resulted in many Macanese with Cantonese Paternal ancestry.

Literature in Macau was written about love affairs and marriage between the Tanka women and Portuguese men, like &quot;A-Chan, A Tancareira&quot;, by Henrique de Senna Fernandes.&lt;ref&gt;João de Pina-Cabral, p. 164: Henrique de Senna Fernandes, another Macanese author, wrote a short story about a tanka girl who has an affair with a Portuguese sailor. In the end, the man returns to his native country and takes their little girl with him, leaving the mother abandoned and broken-hearted. As her sailorman picks up the child, A-Chan's words are: 'Cuidadinho . . . cuidadinho' ('Careful . . . careful'). She resigns herself to ther fate, much as she may never have recovered from the blow (1978).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Christina Miu Bing Cheng, p. 173: Her slave-like submissiveness is her only attraction to him. A-Chan thus becomes his slave/mistress, an outlet for suppressed sexual urges. The story is an archetypical tragedy of miscegenation. Just as the Tanka community despises A-Chan's cohabitation with a foreign barbarian, Manuel's colleagues mock his 'bad taste' ('gosto degenerado') (Senna Fernandes, 1978: 15) in having a tryst with a boat girl ... As such, the Tanka girl is nonchalantly reified and dehumanized as a thing ( coisa). Manuel reduces human relations to mere consumption not even of her physical beauty (which has been denied in the description of A-Chan), but her 'Orientalness' of being slave-like and submissive.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Christina Miu Bing Cheng, p. 170: We can trace this fleeting and shallow relationship in Henrique de Senna Fernandes' short story, A-Chan, A Tancareira, (Ah Chan, the Tanka Girl) (1978). Senna Fernandes (1923–), a Macanese, had written a series of novels set against the context of Macau and some of which were made into films.&lt;/ref&gt;

After the handover of Macau to China in 1999 many Macaunese migrated to other countries. Of the Portuguese and Macanese women who stayed in Macau married with local Cantonese men, and many Macanese also now have Cantonese paternal heritage. There is between 25,000 – 46,000 Macanese, only 5000 – 8000 live in Macau, while most live in Latin america, America, Portugal. Unlike the Macanese of Macau who are strictly of Chinese and Portuguese heritage. Many Macanese living abroad are not entirely of Portuguese and Chinese ancestry, many Macanese men and women intermarried with the local population of America and Latin America etc. and have only partial Macanese heritage.

====Indian subcontinent====
{{Refimprove section|date=May 2010}}
[[File:Katrina-Kaif.jpg|thumb|right|The Indian actress [[Katrina Kaif]] is the daughter of an Indian father and a British (English) mother.]]
[[File:Lakmé.jpg|thumb|right|&quot;[[Lakmé]]&quot;, the Opera deals with the romantic relationship between a British Officer and an Indian Brahmin woman.]]
[[File:Khair-un-Nissa.jpg|thumb|right|An oil painting of Khair-un-Nissa by [[George Chinnery]]. c. 1805. Begum Khair-un-Nissa was a Muslim Indian [[Hyderabad State|Hyderabadi]] noblewoman who fell in love and married the British Lieutenant Colonel [[James Achilles Kirkpatrick]]. ]]

The [[Indian subcontinent]] has a long history of inter-ethnic marriage dating back to [[ancient history]]. Various groups of people have been intermarrying for millennia in [[South Asia]], including groups as diverse as the [[Dravidian peoples|Dravidian]], [[Indo-Aryan peoples|Indo-Aryan]], [[Austro-Asiatic languages|Austro-Asiatic]] and [[Tibeto-Burman languages|Tibeto-Burman]] peoples. Invading [[Classical Greece|Greeks]], [[Scythians]], [[Huns]], [[Persian people|Persians]], [[Mongols]] (known as [[Mughals]]), and Europeans took Indian wives.

3,000–8,000 years ago, [[Indo-European]]-speaking nomadic groups from Europe, the Near East, Anatolia, and the Caucasus migrated to India.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid|11381027}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to 19th-century British historians,{{Who|date=February 2011}} it was these &quot;Aryans&quot; who established the [[caste system]], an [[elitist]] form of social organization that separated the &quot;light-skinned&quot; Indo-Aryan conquerors from the &quot;conquered dark-skinned&quot; indigenous [[Dravidian people|Dravidian]] population through enforcement of &quot;racial [[endogamy]]&quot;. Much of this was simply [[conjecture]], fueled by [[British Empire|British]] [[imperialism]];&lt;ref name=&quot;NehruIndia&quot;&gt;From [[Discovery of India]] by [[Jawaharlal Nehru]], reproduced from &quot;History : Modern India&quot; (p 108) by S.N. Sen, New Age Publishers, ISBN 81-224-1774-4&lt;/ref&gt; British policies of [[divide and rule]] as well as enumeration of the population into rigid categories during the tenure of British rule in India contributed towards the hardening of these segregated caste identities.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Corbridge |first=Staurt |coauthors=Harriss, John |title= Reinventing India: Liberalization, Hindu Nationalism and Popular Democracy|year=2000 |publisher= Polity press |page=8|isbn=0-7456-2076-0}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Since the independence of India from British rule, the British [[fantasy]] of an &quot;Aryan Invasion and subjugation of the dark skinned Dravidians in India&quot; has become a staple polemic in [[South Asia]]n geopolitics, including the propaganda of [[Indophobia]] in Pakistan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1017/S0020743800061596}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is no decisive theory as to the origins of the caste system in India, and globally renowned historians and archaeologists like [[Jim Shaffer]], [[J.P. Mallory]], [[Edwin Bryant (author)|Edwin Bryant]], and others, have disputed the claim of &quot;Aryan Invasion&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;
*[[Jim Shaffer]] – &quot;Current archaeological data do not support the existence of an Indo-Aryan or European invasion into South Asia any time in the pre- or protohistoric periods. Instead, it is possible to document archaeologically a series of cultural changes reflecting indigenous cultural developments from prehistoric to historic periods&quot;{{Cite book|title = The Indo-Aryan Invasions : Cultural Myth and Archaeological Reality|author = Jim Shaffer}}
*[[J.P. Mallory]] – &quot;... the extraordinary difficulty of making a case for expansions from Andronovo to northern India, and that attempts to link the Indo-Aryans to such sites as the Beshkent and Vakhsh cultures only gets the Indo-Iranian to Central Asia, but not as far as the seats of the Medes, Persians or Indo-Aryans&quot;. As quoted in Bryant (see below)
*[[Edwin Bryant (author)|Edwin Bryant]] – &quot;India is not the only Indo-European-speaking area that has not revealed any archaeological traces of immigration.&quot;there is at least a series of archaeological cultures that can be traced approaching the Indian subcontinent, even if discontinuous, which does not seem to be the case for any hypothetical east-to-west emigration&quot;
{{Cite book| last =Bryant|first =Edwin|author-link =Edwin Bryant (author)|year =2001|title =[[The Quest for the Origins of Vedic Culture]]: The Indo-Aryan Migration Debate|publisher =Oxford University Press|isbn =0-19-513777-9}}.
{{Cite book|year=2005|editor-last=Bryant|editor-first=Edwin F.|editor-link=Edwin Bryant (author)|editor2-last=Patton|editor2-first=Laurie L.|title=The Indo-Aryan Controversy: Evidence and inference in Indian history|publication-place=London|publisher=Routledge|isbn=0-7007-1463-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some researchers claim that genetic similarities to Europeans were more common in members of the higher ranks.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|first=Bijal P|last=Trivedi|title=Genetic evidence suggests European migrants may have influenced the origins of India's caste system|url=http://www.genomenewsnetwork.org/articles/05_01/Indo-European.shtml|work=Genome News Network|publisher=J. Craig Venter Institute|date=14 May 2001|accessdate=27 January 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; Their findings, published in ''[[Genome Research]]'', supported the idea that members of higher castes are more closely related to Europeans than are the lower castes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=scientists-connect-indian Scientists Connect Indian Castes and European Heritage]. ''[[Scientific American]]''. 15 May 2001.&lt;/ref&gt; According to the research, invading European populations were predominantly male who intermarried with local females and formed the upper castes i.e. the local females had upward mobility in caste which was denied to local males. However, other researchers have criticized and contradicted this claim.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi| 10.1101/gr.1413403}}&lt;/ref&gt; A study by Joanna L. Mountain et al. of [[Stanford University]] concluded that there was &quot;no clear separation into three genetically distinct groups along caste lines&quot;, although &quot;an inferred tree revealed some clustering according to caste affiliation&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite pmid| 7717409}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2006 study by Ismail Thanseem et al. of [[Centre for Cellular and Molecular Biology]] (India) concluded that the &quot;lower caste groups might have originated with the hierarchical divisions that arose within the tribal groups with the spread of [[Neolithic]] agriculturalists, much earlier than the arrival of Aryan speakers&quot;, and &quot;the [[Indo-Aryans|Indo-Europeans]] established themselves as upper castes among this already developed caste-like class structure within the tribes.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi| 10.1186/1471-2156-7-42}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2006 genetic study by the National Institute of Biologicals in India, testing a sample of men from 32 tribal and 45 caste groups, concluded that the Indians have acquired very few genes from [[Indo-European languages|Indo-European]] speakers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|title=India Acquired Language, Not Genes, From West, Study Says
|author=Brian Handwerk
|url=http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2006/01/0110_060110_india_genes.html
|publisher=National Geographic News
|date=10 January 2006
|accessdate=8 December 2006
}}&lt;/ref&gt; More recent studies have also debunked the claims that so-called &quot;Aryans&quot; and &quot;Dravidians&quot; have a &quot;racial divide&quot;. A study conducted by the [[Centre for Cellular and Molecular Biology]] in 2009 (in collaboration with [[Harvard Medical School]], [[Harvard School of Public Health]] and the [[Broad Institute of Harvard]] and [[MIT]]) analyzed half a million genetic markers across the genomes of 132 individuals from 25 ethnic groups from 13 states in India across multiple caste groups.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dnaindia.com/scitech/report_indians-are-one-people-descended-from-two-tribes_1292864 Indians are one people descended from two tribes]. Dnaindia.com (25 September 2009). Retrieved 11 December 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The study establishes, based on the impossibility of identifying any genetic indicators across caste lines, that castes in South Asia grew out of traditional tribal organizations during the formation of Indian society, and were not the product of any Aryan invasion and subjugation of Dravidian people.

Rape and enslavement of [[Hindu]] women by invading Islamic armies was very common. For example, according to the [[Chachnama]] by Qazi Ismail, during the Arab invasion of Sindh (712 CE), [[Muhammad bin Qasim]] first attacked and conquered [[Debal]]. It was situated on the sea-coast (not far from modern [[Karachi]]). All males of the age of seventeen and upwards were put to the sword and their women and children were enslaved. 700 Hindu women, who were under the protection of Budh (that is, had taken shelter in the temple), were all captured with their valuable ornaments, and adorned with jewels. Muhammad despatched one-fifth of the legal spoil to Hajjaj which included seventy-five damsels, while the other four-fifths were distributed among the soldiers. Thereafter whichever places he attacked like [[Rawar]], Sehwan, Dhalila, Brahmanabad and [[Multan]], Hindu soldiers and men with arms were slain, many women of the higher classes immolated themselves in [[Jauhar]]. Most others became prize of the victors. These women were enslaved and converted, and batches of them were despatched to the Caliph in regular installments. For example, after Rawar was taken, many women and children were enslaved, of whom 30 were young ladies of royal blood. Muhammad Qasim sent all these to Hajjaj, who forwarded them to Walid the Khalifa. He sold some of these female slaves of royal birth, and some he presented to others. In Northern India, female slaves captured after every campaign of the marching army, were converted and married to Muslim soldiers who settled down in colonies established in places like Mansura, Kuzdar, Mahfuza and Multan. During the Islamic involvement in India, it was normal for kings to possess harems filled with native Hindu women won as booties of war. The most famous one was of Akbar's harem, which had over 5000 women.{{Citation needed|date=February 2010}} Most of these Muslim soldiers were [[Turkish people|Turks]], [[Afghanistan|Afghans]], [[Persian people|Persians]], [[Mongols]] (Mughals), other [[Central Asian]]s and [[Arabs]].

There are even cases of Indian princesses marrying kings abroad. For example, the [[Korean language|Korean]] text ''Samguk Yusa'' about the [[Geumgwan Gaya|Gaya]] kingdom (it was absorbed by the kingdom of [[Silla]] later), indicates that in 48 AD, [[Suro of Geumgwan Gaya|King Kim Suro of Gaya]] (the progenitor of the Gimhae Kim clan) took a princess ([[Heo Hwang-ok|Princess Heo]]) from the &quot;Ayuta nation&quot; (which is the Korean name for the city of [[Ayodhya]] in North India) as his bride and queen. Princess Heo belonged to the [[Mishra]] royal family of Ayodhya. According to the Samguk Yusa, the princess had a dream about a heavenly fair handsome king from a faraway land who was awaiting heaven's anointed ride. After Princess Heo had the dream, she asked her parents, the king and queen of [[Ayodhya]], for permission to set out and seek the foreign prince, which the king and queen urged with the belief that god orchestrated the whole fate. That king was no other than King Kim Suro of the Korean Gaya kingdom.

In [[Goa]], a [[Portuguese India|Portuguese colony in India]], during the late 16th century and 17th century, there was a community of over thousand [[Slavery in Japan|Japanese slaves]] and traders, who were either [[Christianity in Japan|Japanese Christians]] fleeing persecution in Japan,&lt;ref name=Leupp-52/&gt; or young [[Japanese people|Japanese]] women and girls brought or captured as [[Sexual slavery|sexual slaves]] by [[Portuguese Empire|Portuguese]] traders and their South Asian ''[[lascar]]'' crew members from Japan.&lt;ref name=Leupp-49/&gt; In both cases, they often intermarried with the local population in Goa.&lt;ref name=Leupp-52/&gt;

Interracial marriages between European men and Indian women were very common during colonial times. Most of these Indian women usually were Muslim belonging to aristocratic families and families with royal ancestry. According to the historian [[William Dalrymple (historian)|William Dalrymple]], about one in three European men had Indian wives in colonial India. This was primarily because the Europeans (mostly [[Dutch People|Dutch]], [[British people|British]], [[French People|French]] and [[Portuguese people|Portuguese]] and up to a lesser extent [[Swedish people|Swedes]] and [[Danish people|Danes]]) came to India when they were young and there were very few white women available in India. The most famous of such interracial liaisons was between the [[Hyderabad State|Hyderabadi]] noblewoman Khair-un-Nissa and the [[Scottish People|Scottish]] resident [[James Achilles Kirkpatrick]].

The 600,000-strong [[Anglo-Indian]] community was formed by British soldiers taking Indian women as wives. Such relationships have had a strong influence on the arts. ''[[Lakmé]]'', an opera by the Frenchman [[Léo Delibes]], deals with the romantic relationship between the British officer Gérald and the daughter of a Hindu high priest Lakmé (Laxmi in [[Sanskrit]]).

In Ceylon (present day [[Sri Lanka]]), interracial relationships between [[Dutch people|Dutch]], [[British people|British]] and [[Portuguese people|Portuguese]] men and local women were common. The 65,000-strong Burgher community was formed by the interracial marriages of [[Dutch people|Dutch]] and [[Portuguese people|Portuguese]] men with local [[Sinhalese people|Sinhalese]] and [[Tamil people|Tamil]] women. In addition to intermarriage, inter-ethnic [[prostitution in India]] was also fairly common at the time, when British officers would frequently visit Indian ''[[nautch]]'' dancers. In the mid-19th century, there were around 40,000 British soldiers but fewer than 2,000 British officials present in India.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1215/1089201x-2007-007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many British and other European officers had their own harems made up of Indian women similar to those the Nawabs and kings of India had. In the 19th century and early 20th century, thousands of women and girls from [[continental Europe]] were also [[Human trafficking|trafficked]] into [[British India]] (and [[British Ceylon|Ceylon]]), where they worked as prostitutes servicing both British soldiers and local Indian (and Ceylonese) men.&lt;ref name=&quot;doi10.1177/001946460304000202&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1177/0891243204272781}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Maneuvers: The International Politics of Militarizing Women's Lives|first=Cynthia H.|last=Enloe|publisher=University of California Press|year=2000|isbn=0-520-22071-4|page=58}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As British females began arriving in British India in large numbers from the early-to-mid-19th century, became increasingly uncommon in India as British women increasingly disapproved of relationships between local woman and their men. Interracial relationships were also despised after the events of [[India's First War of Independence (term)|India's First War of Independence]], where Indian [[sepoy]]s rebelled against the British East India Company.

The idea of protecting British female chastity from the &quot;lustful Indian male&quot; had a significant influence on the policies of the [[British Raj]] in order to prevent racial miscegenation between the British females and the native Indian male population. While some restrictive policies were imposed on British females in order to protect them from miscegenation, most of these policies were directed against native Indian males.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Converting Women|first=Eliza F.|last=Kent|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] US|year=2004|isbn=0-19-516507-1|pages=85–6}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1353/dia.1996.0005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For example, the 1883 [[Ilbert Bill]], which would have granted Indian judges the right to judge British offenders, was opposed by many British colonialists on the grounds that Indian judges cannot be trusted in dealing with cases involving British females.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|first=Sarah|last=Carter|title=Capturing Women: The Manipulation of Cultural Imagery in Canada's Prairie West|publisher=[[McGill-Queen's University Press]]|year=1997|isbn=0-7735-1656-5|page=17}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the aftermath of the 1919 [[Jallianwala Bagh massacre|Amritsar Massacre]], the long-held stereotype of Indian males as dark-skinned rapists lusting after white British females was challenged by several [[novel]]s such as ''[[A Passage to India]]'' (1924) and ''[[The Jewel in the Crown (novel)|The Jewel in the Crown]]'' (1966), both of which involve an Indian male being wrongly accused of raping a British female.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Colonialism-postcolonialism|first=Ania|last=Loomba|publisher=[[Routledge]]|year=1998|isbn=0-415-12809-9|pages=79–80}}&lt;/ref&gt;

When [[Burma]] was ruled under the administration of British India, millions of [[Burmese Indians|Indians]], mostly Muslim, migrated there. The small population mixed descendants of Indian males and local Burmese females are called &quot;Zerbadees&quot;, often in a pejorative sense implying mixed race.&lt;ref name=Myanmar/&gt;

====Japan====
{{See also|Comfort women|Eugenics in Japan}}

[[International marriage (Japan)|Inter-ethnic marriage in Japan]] dates back to the 7th century, when [[China|Chinese]] and [[Korea]]n immigrants began intermarrying with the local [[Japanese people|Japanese]] population. In the 1590s, over 50,000 [[Korean people|Koreans]] were forcibly brought to Japan during [[Hideyoshi's invasions of Korea]], where they intermarried with the local population. In the 16th and 17th centuries, around 58,000 Japanese travelled abroad, many of whom intermarried with the local women in [[Southeast Asia]].&lt;ref name=Leupp&gt;Leupp, pp. 52–3&lt;/ref&gt; During the anti-Christian persecutions in 1596, many [[Christianity in Japan|Japanese Christians]] fled to [[Macau]] and other [[Portuguese Empire|Portuguese colonies]] such as [[Goa]], where there was a community of Japanese slaves and traders by the early 17th century. Intermarriage with the local populations in these Portuguese colonies also took place.&lt;ref name=Leupp-52&gt;Leupp, p. 52&lt;/ref&gt; [[Portuguese people|Portuguese]] traders in Japan also intermarried with the local [[Christian]] women.&lt;ref&gt;Leupp, p. 53&lt;/ref&gt;

From the 15th century, [[Han Chinese|Chinese]], Korean and other [[Far East]]ern visitors frequented [[brothel]]s in Japan.&lt;ref&gt;Leupp, p. 48&lt;/ref&gt; This practice later continued among visitors from the &quot;[[Western Regions]]&quot;, mainly European traders.&lt;ref name=Leupp-49&gt;Leupp, p. 49&lt;/ref&gt; This began with the arrival of Portuguese ships to Japan in the 16th century. Portuguese visitors and their South Asian (and sometimes African) crewmembers often engaged in [[slavery in Japan]], where they brought Japanese slaves who were taken to Macau and other Portuguese colonies in [[Southeast Asia]], [[Portuguese colonization of the Americas|the Americas]],&lt;ref name=Leupp-49/&gt; and [[Portuguese India|India]].&lt;ref name=Leupp-52/&gt; Later European [[East India Company (disambiguation)|East India companies]], including those of the [[Dutch East India Company|Dutch]] and [[East India Company|British]], also engaged in [[prostitution in Japan]].&lt;ref&gt;Leupp, p. 50&lt;/ref&gt;

In the early part of the [[Shōwa era]], Japanese governments executed a eugenic policy to limit the birth of children with inferior traits, as well as aiming to protect the life and health of mothers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bioethics.jp/licht_genetics.html &quot;The National Eugenic Law&quot;] The 107th law that Japanese Government promulgated in 1940　(国民優生法) 第一条　本法ハ悪質ナル遺伝性疾患ノ素質ヲ有スル者ノ増加ヲ防遏スルト共ニ健全ナル素質ヲ有スル者ノ増加ヲ図リ以テ国民素質ノ向上ヲ期スルコトヲ目的トス, Kimura, Jurisprudence in Genetics&lt;/ref&gt; Family Center staff also attempted to discourage marriage between Japanese women and Korean men who had been recruited from the peninsula as laborers following its annexation by Japan in 1910. In 1942, a survey report argued that &quot;the Korean laborers brought to Japan, where they have established permanent residency, are of the lower classes and therefore of inferior constitution...By fathering children with Japanese women, these men could lower the caliber of the [[Yamato people|Yamato minzoku]].&quot;

In 1928, journalist Shigenori Ikeda promoted the 21 December as the blood-purity day (''junketsu de'') and sponsored free blood-test at the Tokyo Hygiene laboratory By the early 1930s, detailed &quot;eugenic marriage&quot; questionnaires were printed or inserted in popular magazines for public consumption. Promoters like Ikeda were convinced that these marriage surveys would not only insure the eugenic fitness of spouses but also help avoid class differences that could disrupt and even destroy marriage. The goal was to create a database of individuals and their entire households which would enable eugenicists to conduct in-depth surveys of any given family's genealogy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://sitemaker.umich.edu/jennifer.robertson/files/blood_talks__eugenic_modernity_anthro___hist_2002.pdf |author=Robertson, J. |pmid=19499628|pages= 191–216 (205–206)|year=2002|title=Blood talks: Eugenic modernity and the creation of new Japanese|volume=13|issue=3|journal=History and anthropology|doi=10.1080/0275720022000025547}}&lt;/ref&gt;

To prevent venereal diseases and rape by Japanese soldiers and to provide comfort to soldiers and head off espionage, the [[Imperial Japanese Army]] established &quot;comfort stations&quot; in the [[Greater East Asia Co-Prosperity Sphere]] where around 200,000 women, mostly from Korea and China, were recruited or kidnapped by the [[Kempeitai]] or the [[Tokeitai]] as [[comfort women]].&lt;ref&gt;Yuki Tanaka, ''Hidden Horrors, Japanese War Crimes in World War II'', 1996, pp. 94–98., [http://search.japantimes.co.jp/cgi-bin/nn20070418a5.html ''Evidence documenting sex-slaves coercion revealed''], &quot;An estimated 200,000 to 300,000 women across Asia, predominantly Korean and Chinese, are believed to have been forced to work as sex slaves in Japanese military brothels&quot;, {{Harvnb|BBC|8 December 2000|Ref=BBC2000-12-08}};&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;Historians say thousands of women&amp;nbsp;– as many as 200,000 by some accounts&amp;nbsp;– mostly from Korea, China and Japan worked in the Japanese military brothels&quot;, {{Harvnb|Irish Examiner|8 March 2007|Ref=IE2007-03-08}};&lt;br /&gt;
{{Harvnb|AP|7 March 2007|Ref=IHT2007-03-07}};&lt;br /&gt;
{{Harvnb|CNN|29 March 2001|Ref=CNN2001-03-29}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

One of the last eugenic measures of the Shōwa regime was taken by the [[Prince Higashikuni Naruhiko|Higashikuni]] government. On 19 August 1945, the Home Ministry ordered local government offices to establish a [[Recreation and Amusement Association|prostitution service for Allied soldiers]] to preserve the &quot;purity&quot; of the &quot;Japanese race&quot;. The official declaration stated that : &quot;Through the sacrifice of thousands of &quot;[[Okichi]]s&quot; of the [[Shōwa era]], we shall construct a [[wikt:dike|dike]] to hold back the mad frenzy of the occupation troops and cultivate and preserve the purity of our race long into the future....&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Herbert Bix, ''Hirohito and the making of modern Japan'', 2001, p. 538, citing Kinkabara Samon and Takemae Eiji, ''Showashi : kokumin no naka no haran to gekido no hanseiki-zohoban'', 1989, p. 244.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to [[Peter Schrijvers]] in &quot;''The GI War against Japan: American Soldiers in Asia and the Pacific during World War II''&quot;,&lt;ref name=het/&gt; rape &quot;reflects a burning need to establish total dominance of the other&quot; the enemy. According to Xavier Guillaume, [[United States Army|US soldiers]]' rape of Japanese women was &quot;general practice&quot;. Schrijvers states regarding rapes on Okinawa that &quot;The estimate of one [[Okinawa]]n historian for the entire three-month period of the campaign exceeds 10,000. A figure that does not seem unlikely when one realizes that during the first 10 days of the occupation of Japan there were 1,336 reported cases of rape of Japanese women by American soldiers in [[Kanagawa]] prefecture alone&quot;.&lt;ref name=het&gt;[http://www.h-net.org/reviews/showrev.cgi?path=114661059720058 A Heterology of American GIs during World War II] by Xavier Guillaume, Department of Political Science, University of Geneva July 2003, (H-NET review of Peter Schrijvers. &quot;The GI War against Japan: American Soldiers in Asia and the Pacific during World War II&quot;. New York: New York University Press, 2002) The citation is cited to page 212 of &quot;The GI War against Japan&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;

However, despite being told by the Japanese military that they would suffer rape, torture and murder at the hands of the Americans, Japanese civilians &quot;were often surprised at the comparatively humane treatment they received from the American enemy.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url = http://books.google.com/?id=RMDt86cokDUC&amp;pg=PA16|title = The American Occupation of Japan and Okinawa: Literature and Memory|first = Michael S.|last = Molasky|page = 16|year = 1999|isbn = 978-0-415-19194-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url = http://books.google.com/?id=6xMuWmEsAcMC&amp;pg=PA21|title = Southern Exposure: Modern Japanese Literature from Okinawa|first = Michael S.|last = Molasky|first2 = Steve|last2 = Rabson|page = 22|year = 2000|isbn = 978-0-8248-2300-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to ''Islands of Discontent: Okinawan Responses to Japanese and American Power'' by [[Mark Selden]], the Americans &quot;did not pursue a policy of torture, rape, and murder of civilians as Japanese military officials had warned.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Islands of Discontent: Okinawan Responses to Japanese and American Power|first = Susan D|last = Sheehan|first2 = Laura|last2 = Elizabeth|first3 = Hein Mark|last3 = Selden|page = 18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Ethnic issues in Japan|Japanese society]], with its ideology of homogeneity, has traditionally been intolerant of ethnic and other differences.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lclark.edu/~krauss/advwrf99/causeeffect/akikocause.html Ijime: A Social Illness of Japan by Akiko Dogakinai]. Lclark.edu (26 December 1994). Retrieved 11 December 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Men or women of [[multiracial|mixed ancestry]], [[Demography of Japan|foreigners]], and members of [[minority groups]] faced [[discrimination]] in a variety of forms. In 2005, a [[United Nations]] report expressed concerns about [[racism]] in Japan and that government recognition of the depth of the problem was not total.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unic.or.jp/new/pr05-057-E.htm |title=Press Conference by Mr Doudou Diène, Special Rapporteur of the Commission on Human Rights |accessdate=5 January 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/4671687.stm &quot;Japan racism 'deep and profound&quot;.] [[BBC News]] (11 July 2005). Retrieved 5 January 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2005, Japanese Minister [[Taro Aso]] called Japan a &quot;one race&quot; nation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://search.japantimes.co.jp/member/member.html?nn20051018a7.htm Aso says Japan is nation of 'one race'], The Japan Times, 18 October 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

The Japanese public was thus astounded by the sight of some 45,000 so-called &quot;pan pan girls&quot; ([[prostitution|prostitutes]]) fraternizing with American soldiers during the occupation.&lt;ref&gt;McLelland 2010, p. 518.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1946, the 200 wives of U.S. officers landing in Japan to visit their husbands also had a similar impact when many of these reunited couples were seen walking hand in hand and kissing in public.&lt;ref&gt;McLelland 2010, p. 529.&lt;/ref&gt; Both prostitution and marks of affection had been hidden from the public until then, and this &quot;democratization of eroticism&quot; was a source of surprise, curiosity, and even envy. The occupation set new relationships models for Japanese men and women: the practice of [[dating|modern &quot;dating&quot;]] spread, and activities such as dancing, movies and coffee were not limited to &quot;pan pan girls&quot; and American troops anymore, and became popular among young Japanese couples.&lt;ref&gt;McLelland 2010, pp. 519–520.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Korea====
Inter-ethnic marriage in [[Korea]] dates back to the arrival of [[Islam in Korea|Muslims in Korea]] during the [[Middle Ages]], when [[Persian people|Persian]] and [[Turkic peoples|Turkic]] navigators, traders and slaves settled in Korea and married local [[Korean people|Korean]] people. Some [[cultural assimilation|assimilation]] into [[Korean Buddhism|Buddhism]] and [[Korean Shamanism|Shamanism]] eventually took place, owing to Korea's geographical isolation from the [[Muslim world]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.pravda.ru/main/2002/11/06/39210_.html|title=Muslim society in Korea is developing and growing|work=[[Pravda]]|date=6 November 2002|accessdate=23 December 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are several Korean clans that are descended from such intermarriages. For example, the Deoksu Jang clan, claiming some 30,000 Korean members, view Jang Sunnyong, a [[Central Asia]]n who married a Korean female, as their ancestor.&lt;ref name=Grayson&gt;{{Cite book|title=Korea: A Religious History|first=James Huntley|last=Grayson|publisher=[[Routledge]]|year=2002|isbn=0-7007-1605-X|page=195}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another clan, Gyeongju Seol, claiming at least 2,000 members in Korea, view a Central Asian (probably an [[Uyghur people|Uyghur]]) named Seol Son as their ancestor.&lt;ref name=&quot;Baker&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Baker|first=Don|title=Islam Struggles for a Toehold in Korea |journal=Harvard Asia Quarterly|date=Winter 2006|url=http://www.asiaquarterly.com/content/view/167/|accessdate=23 April 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Goryeo2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rootsinfo.co.kr/name/n06/n060213.html|work=Rootsinfo.co.kr (Korean language)|title=덕수장씨|accessdate=20 March 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are even cases of Korean kings marrying princesses from abroad. For example, the Korean text Samguk Yusa about the Gaya kingdom (it was absorbed by the kingdom of Silla later), indicate that in 48 AD, King Kim Suro of Gaya (the progenitor of the Gimhae Kim clan) took a princess (Princess Heo) from the &quot;Ayuta nation&quot; (which is the Korean name for the city of Ayodhya in North India) as his bride and queen. Princess Heo belonged to the Mishra royal family of Ayodhya. According to the Samguk Yusa, the princess had a dream about a heavenly fair handsome king from a far away land who was awaiting heaven's anointed ride. After Princess Heo had the dream, she asked her parents, the king and queen of Ayodhya, for permission to set out and seek the foreign prince, which the king and queen urged with the belief that god orchestrated the whole fate. That king was no other than King Kim Suro of the Korean Gaya kingdom.

6,423 Korean women married US military personnel as [[war bride]]s during and immediately after the [[Korean War]]. The average number of Korean women marrying US military personnel each year was about 1,500 per year in the 1960s and 2,300 per year in the 1970s.&lt;ref&gt;Eui-Young Yu and Earl H. Phillips, ''Korean women in transition: at home and abroad'', Center for Korean-American and Korean Studies, California State University, Los Angeles, 1987, p. 185 ISBN 0-942831-00-4.&lt;/ref&gt; Since the beginning of the Korean War in 1950, nearly 100,000 Korean women have immigrated to the United States as the wives of American soldiers. Based on extensive oral interviews and archival research, Beyond the Shadow of the Camptowns tells the stories of these women, from their presumed association with U.S. military camptowns and prostitution to their struggles within the intercultural families they create in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.cntv.cn/program/newshour/20100505/102798.shtml Japan PM: Moving US base impossible CCTV News – CNTV English]. (5 May 2010) Retrieved 29 January 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

International marriages now make up 13% of all [[Marriage in South Korea|marriages in South Korea]]. Most of these marriages are unions between a [[Koreans|Korean]] male and a foreign female&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://yaleglobal.yale.edu/content/korea-greets-new-era-multiculturalism|title=Korea Greets New Era of Multiculturalism|last=Hae-in|first=Shin |date=3 August 2006|publisher=The Korea Herald|accessdate=15 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; usually from China, Japan, [[Vietnam]], the [[Philippines]], United States, [[Mongolia]], [[Thailand]], and Russia. On the other hand, Korean females have married foreign males from Japan, China, the United States, [[Bangladesh]], Pakistan, Philippines, and [[Nepal]]. Between 1990 and 2005, there have been 159,942 Korean males and 80,813 Korean females married to foreigners.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1080/13621020701794240}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Hye-Kyung Lee|title=International Marriage and the State in South Korea&amp;#124; |url=http://www.cct.go.kr/data/acf2006/multi/multi_0303_Hye%20Kyung%20Lee.pdf |accessdate=22 December 2008|doi=10.1080/13621020701794240 |year=2008 |journal=Citizenship Studies |volume=12 |page=107}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[South Korea]] is among the world's most ethnically homogeneous nations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://aparc.stanford.edu/news/koreas_ethnic_nationalism_is_a_source_of_both_pride_and_prejudice_according_to_giwook_shin_20060802/ Korea's ethnic nationalism is a source of both pride and prejudice, according to Gi-Wook Shin]. Aparc.stanford.edu. Retrieved 11 December 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Koreans have traditionally valued an unmixed blood as the most important feature of Korean identity. The term &quot;Kosian&quot;, referring to someone who has a Korean father and a non-Korean mother, is considered offensive by some who prefer to identify themselves or their children as Korean.&lt;ref&gt;Park Chung [http://www.dhseol.org/activity/ein2006_06.html Myth of Pure-Blood Nationalism Blocks Multi-Ethnic Society]. The Korean Times. 14 August 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.naver.com/news/read.php?mode=LSS2D&amp;office_id=079&amp;article_id=0000076691&amp;section_id=102&amp;section_id2=257&amp;menu_id=102 |title= '코시안'(Kosian) 쓰지 마라! (Do not use Kosian)|work=Naver news (in Korean) February 23, 2006|accessdate=4 March 2006}} See English-language reaction on [http://www.rjkoehler.com/2006/02/23/were-koreans-not-kosians-multicultural-families/ The Marmot's Hole]&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, the Korean office of [[Amnesty International]] has claimed that the word &quot;Kosian&quot; represents racial discrimination.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20080528001111/http://www.amnesty.or.kr/magazine/2006_07.pdf Do not use the new word Kosian], AMNESTY Internation South Korea Section, 2006, 07.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.upf.edu/enoticies/home_upf_en/1206.html|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20090521105207/http://www.upf.edu/enoticies/home_upf_en/1206.html|archivedate=21 May 2009|title=Ward's Win Brings 'Race' to the Fore|work=Korea Times |date=9 February 2006|accessdate=4 March 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kosian children, like those of other mixed-race backgrounds in Korea, often face [[discrimination]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.yna.co.kr/Engnews/20060212/480100000020060212100027E2.html|title=For mixed-race children in Korea, happiness is too far away|work=Yonhap News|accessdate=4 March 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are an estimated 35,000 mixed-raced South Koreans, most of them half Caucasian, according to the Pearl Buck Foundation. Discrimination is far worse against those who have [[African American]] fathers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.latimes.com/2006/feb/13/world/fg-ward13 S. Koreans Reclaim Biracial Football Champion as One of Them], Los Angeles Times, 13 February 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

====Malaysia and Singapore====
In West [[Malaysia]] and [[Singapore]], the majority of inter-ethnic marriages are between [[Overseas Chinese|Chinese]] and [[Non-resident Indian and Person of Indian Origin|Indians]]. The offspring of such marriages are informally known as &quot;[[Chindian]]&quot;, though the Malaysian government only classifies them by their father's ethnicity. As the majority of these intermarriages usually involve an Indian groom and Chinese bride, the majority of Chindians in Malaysia are usually classified as &quot;[[Malaysian Indian|Indian]]&quot; by the Malaysian government. As for the [[Malays (ethnic group)|Malays]], who are predominantly [[Muslim]], legal restrictions in Malaysia make it uncommon for them to intermarry with either the Indians, who are predominantly [[Hindu]], or the Chinese, who are predominantly [[Buddhism|Buddhist]] and [[Taoism|Taoist]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Daniels |first=Timothy P. |year=2005 |title=Building Cultural Nationalism in Malaysia |publisher=[[Routledge]] |isbn=0-415-94971-8 |page=189}}&lt;/ref&gt; Non-Muslims are required to convert to Islam in order to marry Muslims. However, this has not entirely stopped intermarriage between the Malays and the Chinese and Indians. There are more Indian-Malay marriages than there are Chinese-Malay ones; this has led to the emergence of a large Muslim Indian society that is most famously known for their 24-hour coffee shops and active involvement in the textile industry. The Muslim Chinese community, on the other hand, is small and has only a negligible impact on the socio-economy and demography of the region.

It is common for [[Arab Singaporean|Arabs in Singapore]] and Malaysia to take local Malay wives, due to a common [[Islam]]ic faith.&lt;ref name=Arab-Malays/&gt; The [[Chitty]] people, in Singapore and the [[Malacca]] state of Malaysia, are a [[Tamil people]] with considerable Malay descent, which was due to the first Tamil settlers taking local wives, since they did not bring along any of their own women with them. According to government statistics, the population of Singapore as of September 2007 was 4.68 million, of whom [[multiracial]] people, including [[Chindian]]s and [[Eurasian (mixed ancestry)|Eurasians]], formed 2.4%.

In the East Malaysian states of [[Sabah]] and [[Sarawak]], there have been many incidents of intermarriage between [[Overseas Chinese|Chinese]] and native tribes such as the [[Murut people|Murut]] and [[Dusun]] in Sabah, and the [[Iban people|Iban]] and [[Bisaya]] in Sarawak. This phenomenon has resulted in a potpourri of cultures in both states where many people claiming to be of native descent have some Chinese blood in them, and many Chinese have native blood in them. The offspring of these mixed marriages are called 'Sino-(name of tribe)', e.g. Sino-Dusun. Normally, if the father is Chinese, the offspring will adopt Chinese culture and if the father is native then native culture will be adopted, but this is not always the case. These Sino-natives are usually fluent in [[Malay language|Malay]] and [[English language|English]]. A smaller number are able to speak Chinese dialects and [[Mandarin Chinese|Mandarin]], especially those who have received education in vernacular Chinese schools.

====Burma====
[[Islam in Burma|Burmese Muslims]] are the descendants of [[Bengali people|Bengalis]], [[Islam in India|Indian Muslims]], [[Arabs]], [[Persian people|Persians]], [[Turkish people|Turks]], [[Pashtun people|Pathans]], [[Islam in China|Chinese Muslims]] and [[Malays (ethnic group)|Malays]] who settled and intermarried with the local [[Bamar|Burmese]] population and other [[List of ethnic groups in Burma|Burmese ethnic groups]] such as the [[Rakhine people|Rakhine]], [[Shan people|Shan]], [[Karen people|Karen]], and [[Mon people|Mon]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| publisher = Harrassowitz| isbn = 3-447-01357-5| last = Yegar| first = Moshe| title = The Muslims of Burma: a Study of a Minority Group| location = Wiesbaden| series = Schriftenreihe des Südasien-Instituts der Universität Heidelberg| year = 1972| oclc = 185556301| ref = CITEREFYegar1972| page = 6}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lay1973&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal| pages = 109–11| last = Lay| first = Pathi U Ko| title = Twentieth Anniversary Special Edition of Islam Damma Beikman| journal = Myanmar Pyi and Islamic religion| year = 1973}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The oldest Muslim group in [[Burma]] (Myanmar) are the [[Rohingya people]], who some believed are descended from Bengalis who intermarried with the native females in the [[Rakhine State]] after the 7th century, but this is just an theory. When Burma was ruled by the [[British India]] administration, millions of [[Burmese Indians|Indians]], mostly Muslim, migrated there. The small population of mixed descendants of Indian males and local Burmese females are called &quot;Zerbadees&quot;, often in a pejorative sense implying mixed race. The [[Panthays]], a group of [[Islam in China|Chinese Muslims]] descended from [[West Asia]]ns and [[Central Asia]]ns, migrated from China and also intermarried with local Burmese females.&lt;ref name=Myanmar&gt;[http://www.colorq.org/MeltingPot/article.aspx?d=Asia&amp;x=BurmeseMuslims Muslim Communities in Myanmar]. ColorQ World&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition, Burma has an estimated 52,000 [[Anglo-Burmese people]], descended from [[British people|British]] and Burmese people. Anglo-Burmese people frequently intermarried with [[Anglo-Indian]] immigrants, who eventually assimilated into the Anglo-Burmese community.

====Philippines====
[[File:Mixed-couple.jpg|right|thumb|160px|A Filipina bride and Nigerian groom walk down the aisle.]]
[[History of the Philippines (1898–1946)|Historically]], admixture has been an ever present and pervading phenomenon in the Philippines. The [[Philippines]] were originally settled by [[Australoid]] peoples called [[Negritos]] (different from other australoid groups) which now form the country's aboriginal community. Some Admixture may have occurred between this earlier group and the mainstream [[Malayo-Polynesian]] population.&lt;ref name=stanford&gt;{{cite doi|10.1016/S0960-9822(02)01336-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A considerable number of the population in the town of [[Cainta, Rizal]], are descended from [[Indian subcontinent|Indian]] soldiers who mutinied against the [[Indian Army (1858–1947)|British Indian Army]] when the British briefly occupied the Philippines in 1762 to 1763. These Indian soldiers called [[Sepoy]] settled in town and intermarried with native females. Cainta residents of Indian descent are very visible today, particularly in Barrio Dayap near Brgy. Sto Niño.

There has been a [[Chinese people|Chinese]] presence in the [[Philippines]] since the 9th century. However, large-scale migrations of Chinese to the Philippines only started during the Spanish colonial era, when the world market was opened to the Philippines. It is estimated that among [[Filipino people|Filipinos]], 10%–20% have some Chinese ancestry and 1.5% are &quot;full-blooded&quot; Chinese.&lt;ref name=ocac&gt;[http://www.ocac.gov.tw/english/public/public.asp?selno=1163&amp;no=1163&amp;level=B :: Overseas Compatriot Affairs Commission, R.O.C. ::]. Ocac.gov.tw (24 August 2004). Retrieved 14 August 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the American [[Anthropology|anthropologist]] Dr. H. Otley Beyer, the ancestry of [[Filipino people|Filipinos]] is 2% [[Arab]]. This dates back to when Arab traders intermarried with the local [[Malay race|Malay]] Filipina female populations during the [[History of the Philippines (Before 1521)|pre-Spanish history of the Philippines]].&lt;ref name=Arab-Malays/&gt; Major Arab migration to the Philippines coincided with the spread of [[Islam in the Philippines|Islam in the region]]. Filipino-Muslim royal families from the [[Sultanate of Sulu]] and the [[Sultanate of Maguindanao]] claim Arab descent even going as far as claiming direct lineage from the [[Prophets in Islam|Prophet]] [[Muhammad]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.seasite.niu.edu/Tagalog/Modules/Modules/MuslimMindanao/historical_timeline_of_the_royal.htm Historical Timeline Of The Royal Sultanate Of Sulu Including Related Events Of Neighboring Peoplesby Josiah C]. Seasite.niu.edu (30 August 2000). Retrieved 14 August 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Such intermarriage mostly took place around the [[Mindanao]] island area, but the arrival of [[Spanish people|Spanish]] [[Conquistadors]] to the [[Philippines]] abruptly halted the spread of [[Islam]] further north into the Philippines. Intermarriage with [[Spanish people]] later became more prevalent after the [[Philippines]] was colonized by the [[Spanish Empire]].

When the Spanish colonized the Philippines, a significant portion of the Filipino population mixed with the Spanish. When the United States took the Philippines from Spain during the [[Spanish-American War]], much intermixing of Americans, both [[White American|white]] and [[Black American|black]], took place on the island of [[Luzon]] where the USA had a Naval Base and Air Force Base even after the USA gave the Philippines independence after World War II. First children and descendants of male Filipino population with Spanish surnames who intermarried with white American female population may be considered Spanish mestizos. The descendants of Filipinos and Europeans are today known as [[mestizo]]s, following the term used in other former Spanish colonies.

Much mixing with the [[Japanese people|Japanese]] also took place due to the [[war rape]]s of Filipina women during World War II. Today there is an increasing number of Japanese men marrying Filipina woman and fathering children by them whose family remain behind in the Philippines and are financially supported by their Japanese fathers who make regular visits to the Philippines. Today mixed-race marriages have a mixed reaction in the Philippines, most urban centers like Manila and Cebu are more willing to accept interracial marriages than rural areas.

===Europe===

====Germany====
{{Main|Anti-miscegenation laws#Nazi Germany}}

During the tempestuous years following World War I, the [[French Army]] occupied the [[Rhineland]], utilising African soldiers amongst their forces. Their children were known as &quot;[[Rhineland Bastards]]&quot;.

Beginning in 1933, the mainstream Nazi [[anti-Semitism]] considered the [[Jew]]s as being a group of people bound by close, so-called genetic (blood) ties, to form a unit, which one could not join or secede from. The influence of Jews had been declared to have a detrimental impact on Germany, in order to justify the discriminations and persecutions of Jews. To be spared from those, one had to prove one's affiliation with the group of the ''[[Aryan]] race'', as conceived by the [[Nazism|Nazis]].

It was paradoxical that neither genetic tests nor allegedly racial outward features in one's physiognomy determined one's affiliation, although the Nazis talked a lot about physiognomy, but only the records of the religious affiliations of one's grandparents decided it. However, while earlier the grandparents had still been able to choose their religion, their grandchildren in the Nazi era were compulsorily categorised as Jews, thus ''non-Aryans'', if three or four grandparents had been enrolled as members of a Jewish congregation, regardless of whether the persecuted themselves were Jews according to the [[Halachah]] (roughly meaning: Jewish by birth from a Jewish mother or by conversion), [[apostate]]s, [[irreligionist]]s or Christians.

The [[Nuremberg Laws]] of 1935 forbade persons ''racially'' regarded as so-called ''Aryans'' and ''non-Aryans'' to marry; this included all marriages where at least one partner was a German citizen. ''Non-Aryans'' comprised mostly Jewish Germans and Gentile Germans of Jewish descent. However, Germans of extra-European and especially of African descent and Germans regarded as belonging to the minority group of [[Sinti]] and [[Roma (Romani subgroup)|Roma]] were also considered as ''non-Aryans''.

Eventually children – whenever born – within a mixed marriage, as well as children from extramarital mixed relationships born until 31 July 1936, were discriminated against as [[Mischling]]e. However, children later born to mixed parents, not yet married as at the passing of the Nuremberg Laws, were to be discriminated against as [[Geltungsjude]]n, regardless of whether the parents had meanwhile married abroad or remained unmarried. Eventually children who were enrolled in a Jewish congregation were also subject to discrimination as Geltungsjuden.

[[Geltungsjude]]n were subjected to varying degrees of forced labour in 1940, partly ordered for all Jewish-classified spouses, either only for Jewish-classified husbands or only exempting Jewish-classified wives taking care of minor children. No documents indicate the exemption of a mixed marriage and especially of its Jewish-classified spouse from some persecutions.&lt;ref&gt;''Meldungen aus dem Reich: Auswahl aus den geheimen Lageberichten des Sicherheitsdienstes der SS 1939–1944'' (&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;1965; Reports from the Reich: Selection from the secret reviews of the situation of the [[SS]] 1939–1944; 1984 extended to 14 vols.), Heinz Boberach (ed. and compilator), Munich: Deutscher Taschenbuch Verlag (dtv), &lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;1968, (dtv-dokumente; vol. 477) p. 208. ISBN B0000BSLXR&lt;/ref&gt;

Systematic [[Deportation#Deportation in the Holocaust|deportations of Jewish Germans and Gentile Germans of Jewish descent]] started on 18 October 1941.&lt;ref&gt;The earlier deportations of Jews and Gentiles of Jewish descent from Austria and [[Pomerania Province (1815-1945)|Pomerania]] (both to [[General Gouvernement|occupied Poland]]) as well as [[Baden]] and the [[Palatinate (region)|Palatinate]] (both to [[Military Administration in Belgium and North France|occupied France]]) had remained a spontaneous episode.&lt;/ref&gt; German Jews and German Gentiles of Jewish descent living in ''mixed marriages'' were in fact mostly spared from deportation.&lt;ref&gt;At the [[Wannsee Conference]] the participants decided to include persons classified as Jews, but married to persons classified as Aryans, however, only after a divorce. In October 1943 an act, facilitating compulsory divorce imposed by the state, was ready for appointment, however, [[Hitler]] never granted the competent referees an audience. Pressure by the [[NSDAP]] headquarters in early 1944 also failed. Cf. Uwe Dietrich Adam, ''Judenpolitik im Dritten Reich'', Düsseldorf: 2003, pp. 222–234. ISBN 3-7700-4063-5&lt;/ref&gt; In the event that a mixed marriage ended by the death of the so-called Aryan spouse or the divorce of the Jewish-classified spouse, the Jewish-classified spouse residing within Germany was usually deported soon after unless the couple still had minor children not counted as Geltungsjuden.&lt;ref name=&quot;Beate Meyer 2006, p. 83&quot;&gt;Beate Meyer, ''Die Verfolgung und Ermordung der Hamburger Juden 1933–1945'', Landeszentrale für politische Bildung (ed.), Hamburg: Landeszentrale für politische Bildung, 2006, p. 83. ISBN 3-929728-85-0&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 1943 an attempt to deport the Berlin-based Jews and Gentiles of Jewish descent, living in non-privileged mixed marriages, failed due to public protest by their in-laws of so-called ''Aryan'' kinship (see [[Rosenstraße protest]]). Also the Aryan-classified husbands and Mischling-classified children (starting at the age of 16) from mixed marriages were taken by the [[Organisation Todt]] for forced labour, starting in autumn 1944.

A last attempt, undertaken in February/March 1945, ended because the [[extermination camp]]s were already liberated. However, 2,600 from all over the Reich were deported to [[Theresienstadt]], of whom most survived the last months until their liberation.&lt;ref&gt;In summer 1945 all in all 8,000 Berliners whom the Nazis had classified as Jews because of 3 or 4 grandparents survived. Their personal faith – like Jewish, Protestant, Catholic or irreligionist – is mostly not recorded, since only the Nazi files which use the Nazi racial definitions report on them. 4,700 out of the 8,000 survived due to their living in a mixed marriage. 1,400 survived hiding, out of 5,000 who tried. 1,900 had returned from Theresienstadt. Cf. Hans-Rainer Sandvoß, ''Widerstand in Wedding und Gesundbrunnen'', Gedenkstätte Deutscher Widerstand (ed.), Berlin: Gedenkstätte Deutscher Widerstand, 2003, (Schriftenreihe über den Widerstand in Berlin von 1933 bis 1945; No. 14), p. 302. ISSN 0175-3592&lt;/ref&gt;

With the defeat of Nazi Germany in 1945 the laws banning so-called mixed marriages were lifted again. If couples who had already lived together during the Nazi era had remained unmarried due to the legal restrictions then got married after the war, their date of marriage was legally retroactively backdated if they wished it to the date they formed a couple.&lt;ref&gt;Cf. the ''Bundesgesetz über die Anerkennung freier Ehen'' (as of 23 June 1950, Federal law on recognition of free marriages).&lt;/ref&gt; Even if one spouse was already dead, the marriage could be retroactively recognised. In the [[West Germany|West German Federal Republic of Germany]] 1,823 couples applied for recognition, which was granted in 1,255 cases.

It is estimated that up to 7,000 postwar black German children with black GI fathers and white German mothers were adopted by Americans.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spiegel.de/international/germany/0,1518,651989,00.html Germany's 'Brown Babies']. Spiegel. 13 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Hungary====
The [[Eurasian Avars|Avars]], Asiatic nomads who during the late 6th and 7th centuries had formed an extensive empire largely inhabited by conquered [[Slavs]], made the agricultural Slavs pay taxes, and used their wives and daughters as concubines.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |author=Denis Sinor|title=The Cambridge of early Inner Asia|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ST6TRNuWmHsC&amp;pg=RA1-PA112|accessdate=11 December 2011|year=1990|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-0-521-24304-9|pages=112-}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Hungarians]] are thought to have originated in an ancient [[Finno-Ugric peoples|Finno-Ugric]] population that originally inhabited the forested area between the [[Volga River]] and the [[Ural Mountains]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://countrystudies.us/hungary/49.htm Origins and Language]. Source: ''U.S. Library of Congress.''&lt;/ref&gt; At the time of the [[Magyars|Magyar]] migration in the 10th century, the present-day Hungary was inhabited by [[Slavs]], numbering about 200,000,&lt;ref name=&quot;HungaryEarlyHistory&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=A Country Study: Hungary |publisher=Federal Research Division, [[Library of Congress]]|url=http://lcweb2.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/r?frd/cstdy:@field(DOCID+hu0013)|accessdate=6 March 2009|isbn=0-16-029202-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; who were either assimilated or enslaved by the Magyars.&lt;ref name=&quot;HungaryEarlyHistory&quot;/&gt;

During the [[Mongol invasion of Rus'|Russian campaign]] in the 13th century, the [[Mongol Empire|Mongols]] drove some 40,000 [[Cuman]] families, a nomadic tribe, west of the Carpathian Mountains.&lt;ref&gt;Józsa Hévizi [http://hungarianhistory.com/lib/hevizi/hevizi.pdf Autonomies in Europe and Hungary]. (PDF). Corvinus Society (2004)&lt;/ref&gt; The Iranian [[Jassic people]] came to Hungary together with the Cumans after they were defeated by the Mongols. Over the centuries they were fully assimilated into the Hungarian population.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nemzetijelkepek.hu/onkormanyzat-jaszbereny_en.shtml National and historical symbols of Hungary]. Nemzetijelkepek.hu. Retrieved 11 December 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Rogerius, a monk who survived the [[Mongol invasion of Hungary]], pointed out not only the genocidal element of the occupation, but also that the Mongols especially &quot;found pleasure&quot; in humiliating women.&lt;ref&gt;Richard Bessel, Dirk Schumann [http://books.google.com/books?id=NilW70Yol74C&amp;pg=PA143 Life after death: approaches to a cultural and social history of Europe during the 1940s and 1950s]. (2003). [[Cambridge University Press]]. p. 143. ISBN 0-521-00922-7&lt;/ref&gt;

====Iberian Peninsula====
[[File:Maler der Geschichte von Bayâd und Riyâd 002.jpg|thumb|''[[Hadith Bayad wa Riyad]]'' (12th century) was an [[Arabic literature|Arabic love story]] about an [[Al-Andalus|Andalusian]] female and a foreign [[Damascus|Damascene]] male.]]

In [[ancient history]], the [[Iberian Peninsula]] was frequently invaded by foreigners who intermarried with the native population. One of the earliest foreign groups to arrive in the region were the [[Indo-European languages|Indo-European]] [[Celts]] who intermarried with the [[Old European culture|pre-Indo-European]] [[Iberians]] in [[prehistoric Iberia]]. They were later followed by the [[Semitic]] [[Phoenicia]]ns and [[Carthage|Carthaginians]] and the Indo-European [[Roman conquest of Hispania|Romans]] who intermarried with the [[pre-Roman peoples of the Iberian Peninsula]] during [[Classical Antiquity]].

They were in turn followed by the [[Germanic peoples|Germanic]] [[Visigoths]], [[Suebi]] and [[Vandals]] and the [[Iranian peoples|Iranic]] [[Sarmatians]] and [[Alans]] who also intermarried with the local population in [[Hispania]] during [[late Antiquity]]. In the 6th century, the region was reconquered by the [[Byzantine Empire]] (Eastern [[Roman Empire]]), when [[Byzantine Greeks]] also settled there, before the region was lost again to the [[Visigothic Kingdom]] less than a century later.

The offspring of such marriages were known as ''[[Muladi]]'' or ''Muwallad'', an [[Arabic language|Arabic]] term still used in the modern [[Arab world]] to refer to people with Arab fathers and [[Ajam|non-Arab]] mothers.&lt;ref&gt;Kees Versteegh, et al. ''Encyclopedia of Arabic Language and Linguistics'', BRILL, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Some sources consider this term the origin for the Spanish word ''[[Mulatto|Mulato]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mgar.net/var/esclavos3.htm|title=La esclavitud en Huelva y Palos (1570–1587)|last=Izquierdo Labrado|first=Julio|language=Spanish|accessdate=14 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.syriatoday.ca/salloum-arab-lan.htm|title=The impact of the Arabic language and culture on English and other European languages|last=Salloum|first=Habeeb |publisher=The Honorary Consulate of Syria|accessdate=14 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the [[Real Academia|Real Academia Española]] does not endorse such etymology.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rae.es/rae-index.html|title=Real Academia Española|accessdate=9 December 2009}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, many ''Muladi'' were also descended from ''[[Saqaliba]]'' ([[Slavic peoples|Slavic]]) slaves taken from Eastern Europe via the [[Arab slave trade]].

After the [[Reconquista]], which was completed in 1492, most of the Moors were forced to either flee to [[Morocco]] or [[Conversion to Christianity|convert to Christianity]]. The ones who converted to Christianity were known as [[Morisco]]es, and they were often persecuted by the [[Spanish Inquisition]] as suspects of [[heresy]] on the basis of the ''[[Limpieza de sangre]]'' (&quot;Cleanliness of blood&quot;) doctrine, under which anti-miscegenation laws were implemented in the [[Iberian Peninsula]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Robert Lacey]] (1983), ''Aristocrats'', p. 67, [[Little, Brown and Company]]&lt;/ref&gt;

Anyone whose ancestors had miscegenated with the Moors or [[Jew]]s were suspected of secretly practicing [[Islam]] or [[Judaism]], so were often particularly monitored by the Inquisition. The claim to universal ''[[Hidalgo (Spanish nobility)|hidalguía]]'' (lowest nobility) of the [[Basque people|Basques]] was justified by erudites like Manuel de Larramendi (1690–1766)&lt;ref name=&quot;Larramendi&quot;&gt;[[Manuel de Larramendi]], ''Corografía de la muy noble y muy leal provincia de Guipúzcoa'', Bilbao, 1986, facsimile edition of that from Editorial [[Ekin]], Buenos Aires, 1950. (Also published by Tellechea Idígoras, San Sebastián, 1969.) Quoted in ''[http://www.uv.es/rseapv/Anales/97_98/A_117_139_La_idea_de_Espanya.pdf La idea de España entre los vascos de la Edad Moderna]'', by Jon Arrieta Alberdi, ''Anales 1997–1998'', Real Sociedad Económica Valenciana de Amigos del País&lt;/ref&gt; because the Arab invasion had not reached the Basque territories, so it was believed that Basques had maintained their original purity, while the rest of Spain was suspect of miscegenation. In fact, the Arab invasion also reached the Basque country and there had been a significant Jewish minority in Navarre, but the hidalguía helped many Basques to official positions in the administration.&lt;ref name=&quot;Auñamendi&quot;&gt;[http://www.euskomedia.org/aunamendi/100471 Limpieza de sangre] in the Spanish-language [[Auñamendi Encyclopedia]]&lt;/ref&gt; In December 2008, a genetic study of the current population of the Iberian Peninsula, published in the ''[[American Journal of Human Genetics]]'', estimated that about 10% have [[Moors|North African]] ancestors and 20% have [[Sephardi Jews]] as ancestors. Since there is no direct link between genetic makeup and religious affiliation, however, it is difficult to draw direct conclusions between their findings and forced or voluntary conversion.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cell.com/AJHG/abstract/S%2808% The Genetic Legacy of Religious Diversity and Intolerance: Paternal Lineages of Christians, Jews, and Muslims in the Iberian Peninsula], Adams et al. 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, the Sephardic result is in contradiction&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1038/sj.ejhg.5201225|title=Reduced genetic structure of the Iberian peninsula revealed by Y-chromosome analysis: Implications for population demography|year=2004|last1=Flores|first1=Carlos|last2=Maca-Meyer|first2=Nicole|last3=González|first3=Ana M|last4=Oefner|first4=Peter J|last5=Shen|first5=Peidong|last6=Pérez|first6=Jose A|last7=Rojas|first7=Antonio|last8=Larruga|first8=Jose M|last9=Underhill|first9=Peter A|journal=European Journal of Human Genetics|volume=12|issue=10|pages=855–63|pmid=15280900}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|pmid=12627534|year=2003|last1=González|first1=AM|last2=Brehm|first2=A|last3=Pérez|first3=JA|last4=Maca-Meyer|first4=N|last5=Flores|first5=C|last6=Cabrera|first6=VM|title=Mitochondrial DNA affinities at the Atlantic fringe of Europe|volume=120|issue=4|pages=391–404|doi=10.1002/ajpa.10168|journal=American Journal of Physical Anthropology}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1007/s00439-004-1168-9|title=Y chromosomal haplogroup J as a signature of the post-neolithic colonization of Europe|year=2004|last1=Giacomo|first1=F.|last2=Luca|first2=F.|last3=Popa|first3=L. O.|last4=Akar|first4=N.|last5=Anagnou|first5=N.|last6=Banyko|first6=J.|last7=Brdicka|first7=R.|last8=Barbujani|first8=G.|last9=Papola|first9=F.|journal=Human Genetics|volume=115|issue=5|pages=357–71|pmid=15322918}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|pmid=16500815|year=2006|last1=Sutton|first1=WK|last2=Knight|first2=A|last3=Underhill|first3=PA|last4=Neulander|first4=JS|last5=Disotell|first5=TR|last6=Mountain|first6=JL|title=Toward resolution of the debate regarding purported crypto-Jews ''in a'' spanish-American population: Evidence from the Y chromosome|volume=33|issue=1|pages=100–11|doi=10.1080/03014460500475870|journal=Annals of Human Biology}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1016/j.ajhg.2008.10.012|title=Identifying Genetic Traces of Historical Expansions: Phoenician Footprints in the Mediterranean|year=2008|last1=Zalloua|first1=Pierre A.|last2=Platt|first2=Daniel E.|last3=El Sibai|first3=Mirvat|last4=Khalife|first4=Jade|last5=Makhoul|first5=Nadine|last6=Haber|first6=Marc|last7=Xue|first7=Yali|last8=Izaabel|first8=Hassan|last9=Bosch|first9=Elena|journal=The American Journal of Human Genetics|volume=83|issue=5|pages=633–42|pmid=18976729|pmc=2668035}}&lt;/ref&gt; or not replicated in all the body of genetic studies done in Iberia and has been later questioned by the authors themselves&lt;ref&gt;&quot;'''''Despite alternative possible sources for lineages''' ascribed a Sephardic Jewish origin''&quot;, [http://www.cell.com/AJHG/abstract/S%2808%]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;La cifra de los sefardíes puede estar sobreestimada, ya que en estos genes hay mucha diversidad y quizá absorbieron otros genes de Oriente Medio&quot; ''('''&quot;The Sephardic result may be overestimated''', since there is much diversity in those genes and maybe absorbed other genes from the Middle East&quot;)''. ¿Pone en duda Calafell la validez de los tests de ancestros? &quot;Están bien para los americanos, nosotros ya sabemos de dónde venimos&quot; ''(Puts Calafell in doubt the validity of ancestry tests? &quot;They can be good for the Americans, we already know from where we come from)''.''''' ''&quot; [http://www.publico.es/ciencias//tres/culturas/adn]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;'''We think it might be an over estimate'''&quot; &quot;The genetic makeup of Sephardic Jews is probably common to other Middle Eastern populations, such as the Phoenicians, that also settled the Iberian Peninsula, Calafell says. &quot;'''In our study, that would have all fallen under the Jewish label.'''&quot;&quot; http://www.sciencenews.org/view/generic/id/39056/title/Spanish_Inquisition_couldn%E2%80%99t_quash_Moorish,_Jewish_genes&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;El doctor Calafell matiza que (...) los marcadores genéticos usados para distinguir a la población con ancestros sefardíes pueden producir distorsiones&quot;. &quot;ese 20% de españoles que el estudio señala como descendientes de sefardíes podrían haber heredado ese rasgo de movimiento más antiguos, como el de los fenicios o, incluso, primeros pobladores neolíticos hace miles de años.&quot; &quot;Dr. Calafell clarifies that (...) '''the genetic markers used to distinguish the population with Sephardim ancestry may produce distortions. The 20% of Spaniards that are identified as having Sephardim ancestry in the study could have inherited that same marker from older movements like the Phoenicians, or even the first Neolithic settlers thousands of years ago'''&quot; http://www.elmundo.es/elmundo/2008/12/04/ciencia/.html&lt;/ref&gt; and by [[Stephen Oppenheimer]] who estimates that much earlier migrations, 5000 to 10,000 years ago from the Eastern Mediterranean might also have accounted for the Sephardic estimates: &quot;They are really assuming that they are looking at his migration of Jewish immigrants, but the same lineages could have been introduced in the Neolithic&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newscientist.com/article/dn16200-spanish-inquisition-left-genetic-legacy-in-iberia.html Spanish Inquisition left genetic legacy in Iberia ], [[New Scientist]], 4 December 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; The rest of genetic studies done in Spain estimate the Moorish contribution ranging from 2.5/3.4%{{Citation needed|date=August 2012}}&lt;!-- Dead link&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal}}&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt; to 7.7%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1038/ejhg.2008.258|title=Moors and Saracens in Europe: Estimating the medieval North African male legacy in southern Europe|year=2009|last1=Capelli|first1=Cristian|last2=Onofri|first2=Valerio|last3=Brisighelli|first3=Francesca|last4=Boschi|first4=Ilaria|last5=Scarnicci|first5=Francesca|last6=Masullo|first6=Mara|last7=Ferri|first7=Gianmarco|last8=Tofanelli|first8=Sergio|last9=Tagliabracci|first9=Adriano|journal=European Journal of Human Genetics|volume=17|issue=6|pages=848–52|pmid=19156170|pmc=2947089}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Italian Peninsula====
[[File:Othello and Desdemona by Alexandre-Marie Colin.jpg|thumb|right|&quot;[[Othello (Othello)|Othello]] and [[Desdemona (Othello)|Desdemona]]&quot;, a painting by [[Alexandre-Marie Colin]] in 1829]]

As was the case in other regions [[Muslim conquests|conquered by Muslims]], it was acceptable in [[Islamic marital jurisprudence|Islamic marital law]] for a [[Muslim]] male to marry [[Christian]] and [[Jew]]ish females in [[History of Islam in southern Italy|southern Italy when under Islamic rule]] between the 8th and 11th centuries. In this case, most intermarriages were between [[Arab]] and [[Berber people|Berber]] males from North Africa and the local [[Greeks|Greek]], [[Ancient Rome|Roman]] and [[Ancient peoples of Italy|Italian]] females of [[Sicily]] and [[southern Italy]]. Such intermarriages were particularly common in the [[Emirate of Sicily]], where one writer visiting the place in the 970s expressed shock at how common it was in rural areas.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Emma Blake|contribution=The Familiar Honeycomb: Byzantine Era Reuse of Sicily's Prehistoric Rock-Cut Tombs|editor-last=Ruth M. Van Dyke|editor-first=Susan E. Alcock|title=Archaeologies of Memory|publisher=[[Blackwell Publishers]]|isbn=978-0-470-77430-4|doi=10.1002/9780470774304.ch10|year=2008|page=201|first1=Emma}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the [[Norman conquest of southern Italy]], all Muslim citizens (whether foreign, native or mixed) of the [[Kingdom of Sicily]] were known as &quot;[[Moors]]&quot;. After a brief period of [[Arab-Norman culture]] had flourished under the reign of [[Roger II of Sicily]], later rulers had forced the Moors to either [[Conversion to Christianity|convert to Christianity]] or be expelled from the kingdom.

In [[Malta]], Arabs and Italians from neighbouring Sicily and [[Calabria]] intermarried with the local inhabitants,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesofmalta.com/core/article.php?id=270452 Alex E. Felice, &quot;Genetic origin of contemporary Maltese,&quot; ''The Sunday Times (of Malta)'', 5 August 2007], last visited 5 August 2007&lt;/ref&gt; who were descended from [[Phoenicia]]ns, [[Greeks]], [[Ancient Rome|Romans]] and [[Vandals]]. The [[Maltese people]] are descended from such unions, and the [[Maltese language]] is descended from [[Siculo-Arabic]].

At times, the Italian city-states also played an active role in the [[Arab slave trade]], where Moorish and Italian traders occasionally exchanged slaves.

During World War II, France's [[Morocco|Moroccan]] troops known as [[Goumier]]s committed [[war rape]]s in Italy after the [[Battle of Monte Cassino]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://listserv.acsu.buffalo.edu/cgi-bin/wa?A2=ind9705&amp;L=twatch-l&amp;D=1&amp;O=D&amp;F=P&amp;P=1025 Italian women win cash for wartime rapes]. Listserv.acsu.buffalo.edu. Retrieved 11 December 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; and in Germany. In Italy, victims of the mass [[rape]] committed after the Battle of Monte Cassino by Goumiers are known as ''[[Marocchinate]]''. According to Italian sources, more than 7,000 Italian civilians, including women and children, were raped by Goumiers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=1952: Il caso delle &quot;marocchinate&quot; al Parlamento|url=http://www.cassino2000.com/cdsc/studi/archivio/n07/n07p09.html|accessdate=22 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Anton Hickel 001.JPG|thumb|An artistic depiction of [[Roxelana]] with [[Suleiman the Magnificent]], by German painter Anton Hickel (1780).]]

==== Russia  ====
{{See also|Afro-Russian}}
{{See also|Ethnic Chinese in Russia}}
The Metis Foundation estimates that there are about 40,000 mixed-race Russians.&lt;ref&gt;Gribanova, Lyubov [http://www.nashi-deti.ru/articles/15/ &quot;Дети-метисы в России: свои среди чужих&quot;] (in Russian). Nashi Deti Project. Retrieved 25 February 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

Many Chinese men, even those who had left wives and children behind in China, married local women in the 1920s as a result, especially those women who had been widowed during the wars and upheavals of the previous decade. Their [[mixed race]] children tended to be given [[Names in the Russian Empire, Soviet Union and CIS countries|Russian forenames]]; some retained their fathers' [[Chinese surnames]], while others took on Russian surnames, and a large proportion also invented new surnames using their father's entire family name and given name as the new surname.

====Southeastern and Eastern Europe====
[[Vikings]] explored and eventually settled in territories in [[Slavic peoples|Slavic]]-dominated areas of [[Eastern Europe]]. By 950 AD these settlements were largely Slavicized through intermarriage with the local population. Eastern Europe was also an important source for the [[Arab slave trade]] at the time, when ''[[Saqaliba]]'' (Slavic) slaves were taken to the [[Arab World]], where the women and girls often served in [[harem]]s, some of whom married their [[Arab]] masters. When the [[Mongol Empire]] annexed much of Eastern Europe in the 13th century, the [[Mongols]] also intermarried with the local population and often engaged in [[war rape]] during the [[Mongol invasion of Europe]].

In the 11th century, the [[Byzantine Empire|Byzantine]] territory of [[Anatolia]] was conquered by the [[Seljuq dynasty|Seljuq Turks]], who came from [[Turkestan]] in [[Central Asia]]. Their [[Ottoman Turks|Ottoman Turkish]] descendants went on to annex the [[Balkans]] and much of [[Eastern Europe]] in the 15th and 16th centuries. Due to [[Islamic marital jurisprudence|Islamic marital law]] allowing a [[Muslim]] male to marry [[Christian]] and [[Jew]]ish females, it was common in the [[Ottoman Empire]] for Turkish males to intermarry with European females. For example, various [[sultan]]s of the [[Ottoman Dynasty]] often had [[Greeks|Greek]] (''[[Rûm]]''), [[Slavic peoples|Slavic]] (''[[Saqaliba]]''), [[Republic of Venice|Venetian]], [[North Caucasus|Northcaucasian]] and French wives.

Some of these European wives exerted great influence upon the empire as ''[[Valide Sultan]]'' (&quot;Mother-Sultan&quot;), some famous examples including [[Roxelana]], a Slavic harem slave who later became [[Suleiman the Magnificent]]'s favourite wife, and [[Aimée du Buc de Rivéry]], wife of [[Abdul Hamid I]] and cousin of French Empress [[Joséphine de Beauharnais|Josephine]]. Due to the common occurrence of such intermarriages in the Ottoman Empire, they have had a significant impact on the ethnic makeup of the modern [[Turkish people|Turkish]] population in [[Turkey]], which now differs from that of the [[Turkic peoples|Turkic]] population in Central Asia.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Ottoman Empire, 1700–1922|last=[[Institute of Turkish Studies|Donald Quataert]]|year=2000|isbn=0-521-63328-1|page=2|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=New York}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to intermarriage, the large harems of Ottoman sultans often consisted almost entirely of female [[Concubinage|concubines]] who were of Christian European origin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The sultanate of women|publisher=Channel 4|url=http://www.channel4.com/history/microsites/H/history/e-h/harem.html|accessdate=30 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The degree of miscegenation is very high in the former Soviet Union. Interethnic marriages made up about 22% of all marriages in Moscow, according to the figures from 1995. The majority of such marriages consist among Russian, Ukrainians, Byelorussians and other Slavic.

Low levels of mixed ancestry are, in some areas (especially urban), almost universal, and generally go entirely ignored and unnoticed unless persons wish to identify themselves with ethnic minorities. Highly visible divergence from the local ethnic majority is also treated differently, depending on whether the individual identifies with the local culture or not. In modern times, attitudes towards miscegenation in the former Soviet Union vary greatly, depending on the race and gender of each partner. For example, unions between Slavic males and [[Mongoloid|Oriental (Asian)]] or Turkic, Northcaucasian, Southcaucasian and [[Finno-Ugric peoples|Finno-Ugric]] women are almost universally tolerated, and their children are generally identified and treated as members of the local ethnic majority.

However, unions between Slavic women and visibly non-Slavic men may meet varying degrees of discrimination, from light to none for Asian men (depending also on origin, whether they are immigrants or were born in the Soviet Union, and where in the Soviet Union they were born), to some hostility for [[Finno-Ugric peoples|Finno-Ugric]], [[Turkic peoples|Turkic]] and [[North Caucasus|Northcaucasian]] men (although much of this is due to the assumption of their faith as Muslim) and Jews, and quite high intolerance towards those who marry blacks or have children by them (young African-Russians in Moscow are often scornfully called 'Children of the Olympics', under the assumption that they were conceived by visiting tourists during the 1980 Moscow Olympic Games). The situation is also highly affected by self-identification, since many people of Asian or Turkic blood have assimilated to the point where they identify themselves as [[Russians|Russian]]/[[Ukrainians|Ukrainian]]/etc. and are socially accepted as such.

====United Kingdom====
{{See also|British Mixed-Race}}
[[File:Emmys-bennett-klum-seal.jpg|thumb| [[Seal (musician)|Seal]] with ex-wife [[Heidi Klum]].]]
Even though 80% of the genetic characteristics of most indigenous Britons today have been passed down from a few thousand Ice Age hunters and the genetic makeup of today's indigenous population is much the same as it was 12,000 years ago,&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2005/07/0719_050719_britishgene.html British Have Changed Little Since Ice Age, Gene Study Says]. News.nationalgeographic.com. Retrieved 14 August 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Britain has a fairly long history of inter-ethnic marriage among the various European populations that inhabited the island, including the [[Celts|Celtic]], [[Roman Britain|Roman]], [[Anglo-Saxons|Anglo-Saxon]] and [[Anglo-Norman]] peoples. Although it is debatable whether these can be described as ethnic groups with distinct cultural identities. The Celts cannot be described with a single ethnic identity and various tribal names were used and a 'Celtic' culture was shared in Europe despite the variety of languages. Norman and Vikings people rarely held onto an identity and allegiances were more to leaders and family rather than an ethnic group, there is no evidence the Vikings for example acted as an distinct ethnic group in Britain and so called Scandinavian markers may have been in Britain thousands of years in the Neolithic. Also there were Scandinavians and pre-Viking Scandinavian influence amongst the Anglo-Saxons as shown in Beowulf and Sutton Hoo. There is no evidence the Anglo-Saxons used that term or indeed forced their languages or culture on local Britons, indeed there is no evidence the majority of local Britons used the term Celt or even spoke a Celtic language, indeed a Germanic language which evolved into English may have been spoke in large parts of Britain as Oppenheimer suggests.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.proto-english.org How old is English?]. Proto-english.org (4 April 2011). Retrieved 11 December 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The numbers of Vikings, Anglo-Saxons, Romans may be widely exaggerated, Viking, Anglo-Saxons armies may have been small.&lt;ref&gt;Julian Richards, Viking Age England, ISBN 0-7524-1489-5, p. 20, 2000&lt;/ref&gt;

Intermarriage with non-European populations began in the late 15th century, with the arrival of the [[Romani people]], who have [[Indian subcontinent|Indian]] origins. The Romani in Britain intermarried with the local population and became known to the Romani as the [[Romanichal]]. In India, the British [[East India Company]] and other European soldiers intermarried with Indian women. The offspring of these mixed marriages between the British and Indians were known as [[Anglo-Indian]]s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.movinghere.org.uk/galleries/roots/asian/angloindians/angloindians.htm Anglo-Indians]. Movinghere.org.uk. Retrieved 11 December 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Indian wives sometimes accompanied their husbands back to Britain.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fathom.com/course/21701766/session4.html Asians in Britain: Their Social, Cultural and Political Lives]. Fathom.com. Retrieved 11 December 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[East India Company|British East India Company]] brought many South Asian [[lascar]]s to Britain, where many settled down with local [[white British]] wives, due to a lack of [[British Asian|Asian]] women in Britain at the time.&lt;ref name = &quot;Fisher&quot;&gt;{{citation| title= Counterflows to Colonialism|first= Michael Herbert|last= Fisher| year= 2006| publisher = Orient Blackswan | isbn = 81-7824-154-4}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Inter-ethnic relationships have become increasingly accepted over the last several decades. As of 2001, 2% of all marriages in Britain are inter-ethnic. Despite having a much lower non-white population (9%), mixed marriages in the United Kingdom are as common as in the United States, although America has many fewer specific definitions of race (four racial definitions as opposed to the United Kingdom's 86).&lt;ref name=&quot;Natstats&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.statistics.gov.uk/cci/nugget.asp?id=1090|title=Inter-Ethnic Marriage: 2% of all Marriages are Inter-Ethnic|date=21 March 2005|publisher=National Statistics|accessdate=15 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2005, it is estimated that nearly half of British-born [[British African-Caribbean community|African-Caribbean]] males, a third of British-born African-Caribbean females, and a fifth of [[British Indian|Indian]] and [[African migration to the United Kingdom|African]] males, have white partners.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1111/j.0953-5233.2005.00371.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2009, one in 10 children in the UK lives in a mixed-race or mixed-ethnicity family (families headed by one white-British parents and one white parent not of British origin are included in the figure) and two out of five [[British Chinese|Chinese]] women have partners of a different race.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk/2009/jan/18/race-identity-britain-study Major new study reveals the rise of mixed-race Britain. Some ethnic groups 'will disappear'], ''The Observer'', 18 January 2009&lt;/ref&gt; One out of five Chinese men have partners of a different race. According to the [[United Kingdom Census 2001|UK 2001 census]], [[black British]] males were around 50% more likely than black females to marry outside their race. [[British Chinese]] women (30%) were twice as likely as their male counterparts (15%) to marry someone from a different ethnic group.

===Middle East===
[[File:Geromeslavemarket.jpg|thumb|''The Slave Market'', painting by [[Jean-Léon Gérôme]], c. 1884]]

A Stanford team found the greatest diversity outside Africa among people living in the wide crescent of land stretching from the eastern shore of the Mediterranean to northern India. Not only was the region among the first colonized by the African migrants, they theorize, but the large number of European and East Asian genes among the population indicates that it has long been a human highway, with large numbers of migrants from both directions conquering, trading and generally reproducing along its entire length. The same team also found out that the [[Bedouins|Bedouin]] nomads of the Middle East actually have some European and South Asian blood.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}

In ancient times a [[Celts|Celtic]] people known as [[Galatians]] settled in what is present day Turkey and thus interbred with the people there. During the empire of [[Alexander the Great]], many [[Greeks|Greek]]/[[Ancient Macedonians|Macedonian]] soldiers had inter-ethnic relationships with women throughout the Middle East all the way to [[Pakistan|northwestern India]]. Later, coastal North Africa and parts of the Middle East were part of the [[Roman Empire]] and many Roman men were posted as soldiers there. Many of them had inter-ethnic relationships with local Middle-Eastern women. The [[Germanic peoples|Germanic]] people known as the [[Vandals]] also conquered parts of coastal North Africa during the great migration period which led to opportunities of inter-ethnic relationships between [[Germanic peoples|Germanic]] men and local North African women.{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}}

Inter-ethnic [[sexual slavery]] was common during the [[Arab slave trade]] throughout the [[Middle Ages]] and [[early modern period]], when women and girls captured from non-Arab lands often ended up as sexual slaves in the [[harem]]s of the [[Arab World]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/islam/history/slavery_7.shtml Islam and slavery: Sexual slavery], [[BBC]]&lt;/ref&gt; Most of these slaves came from places such as [[Sub-Saharan Africa]] (mainly ''[[Zanj]]''), South Asia ([[Hindus]]), the [[North Caucasus]] (mainly [[Circassians]]),&lt;ref&gt;[http://chnm.gmu.edu/lostmuseum/lm/311/ &quot;Horrible Traffic in Circassian Women—Infanticide in Turkey,&quot; New York Daily Times, 6 August 1856]. Chnm.gmu.edu. Retrieved 11 December 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Central Asia]] (mainly [[Tartary|Tartars]]), and [[Central Europe|Central]] and [[Eastern Europe]] (mainly ''[[Saqaliba]]'').&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.avalanchepress.com/Soldier_Khan.php Soldier Khan]. Avalanchepress.com. Retrieved 11 December 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Barbary pirate]]s also captured 1,250,000 slaves from [[Western Europe]] and North America between the 16th and 19th centuries.&lt;ref&gt;[http://researchnews.osu.edu/archive/whtslav.htm '&amp;#39;When europeans were slaves: Research suggests white slavery was much more common than previously believed'&amp;#39;]. Researchnews.osu.edu. Retrieved 11 December 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Davis, Robert. ''Christian Slaves, Muslim Masters: White Slavery in the Mediterranean, the Barbary Coast and Italy, 1500–1800''. Based on &quot;records for 27,233 voyages that set out to obtain slaves for the Americas&quot;. Stephen Behrendt, &quot;Transatlantic Slave Trade&quot;, ''Africana: The Encyclopedia of the African and African American Experience'' (New York: Basic Civitas Books, 1999), ISBN 0-465-00071-1.&lt;/ref&gt; It was also common for [[Muslim conquests|Arab conquerors]], [[Islamic economics in the world|traders]] and [[Geography in medieval Islam|explorers]] to marry local females in the lands they conquered or traded with, in various parts of Africa, Asia (see [[#Asia|Asia]] section) and Europe (see [[#Europe|Europe]] section).

Inter-ethnic relationships were generally accepted in Arabic society and formed a fairly common theme in medieval [[Arabic literature]] and [[Persian literature]]. For example, the [[Persian people|Persian]] poet [[Nizami Ganjavi|Nizami]], who had himself married his [[Kipchaks|Kipchak]] slave girl, wrote ''The Seven Beauties'' (1196). Its [[frame story]] involves a [[Persian Empire|Persian]] prince marrying seven foreign princesses, including [[Byzantine Empire|Byzantine]], Chinese, Indian, [[Khwarezm]]ian, [[Maghreb]]ian, [[Slavic peoples|Slavic]] and [[Tartar]] princesses. ''[[Hadith Bayad wa Riyad]]'', a 12th-century Arabic tale from [[Al-Andalus]], was a love story involving an [[Caucasian Iberia|Iberian]] girl and a [[Damascus|Damascene]] man. The ''[[One Thousand and One Nights]]'' tale of &quot;[[List of stories within One Thousand and One Nights#Volume 4|The Man of Al-Yaman and His Six Slave-Girls]]&quot; involves a [[Yemen]]i man's relationship with foreign slave girls, four of which are [[White people|white]], [[Black people|black]], [[Brown people|brown]] and [[Yellow people|yellow]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Arabian Nights Encyclopedia|last=Ulrich Marzolph, Richard van Leeuwen|first=Hassan Wassouf|publisher=[[ABC-CLIO]]|year=2004|isbn=1-57607-204-5|pages=289–90}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another ''One Thousand and One Nights'' tale, &quot;[[The Ebony Horse]]&quot;, involves the [[Prince of Persia (disambiguation)|Prince of Persia]], Qamar al-Aqmar, rescuing his lover, the Princess of [[Sana'a]], from the [[Byzantine Empire|Byzantine Emperor]] who also wishes to marry her.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Arabian Nights Encyclopedia|last=Ulrich Marzolph, Richard van Leeuwen|first=Hassan Wassouf|publisher=[[ABC-CLIO]]|year=2004|isbn=1-57607-204-5|pages=172–4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One study found that some Arabic-speaking populations—[[Palestinians]], [[Jordan]]ians, [[Syria]]ns, [[Iraq]]is, and [[Bedouin]]s—have what appears to be substantial mtDNA gene flow from [[sub-Saharan Africa]], amounting to 10–15% of lineages within the past three millennia.&lt;ref name = &quot;Richards&quot;&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1086/374384}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid|1180338}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the case of [[Yemenite Jews|Yemenites]], the average is higher at 35%.&lt;ref name = &quot;Richards&quot; /&gt; Of particular historic interest might be the finding that with almost no exceptions the sub-Saharan gene flow was exclusively female, at least in part as a result of the [[Arab slave trade]].&lt;ref name = &quot;Richards&quot; /&gt;

Between the 11th and 13th centuries, medieval [[Southwest Asia|Western Asia]] was repeatedly invaded by Europeans ([[Crusades]]) and [[Mongols]] ([[Mongol Empire]]) which led to opportunities for inter-ethnic relationships between European, [[Mongols|Mongol]] and [[Central Asia]]n soldiers with local Arab women. As well as many Europeans, there were North Africans, [[South Asia]]ns and [[Central Asia]]ns who worked as mercenaries and traders in the area, most of them converting to Islam and taking local women as wives. From 839 AD, [[Vikings|Viking]] [[Varangian]] mercenaries who were in the service of the [[Byzantine Empire]], notably [[Harald III of Norway|Harald Sigurdsson]], campaigned in North Africa, [[Jerusalem]] and other places in the Middle East during the [[Byzantine-Arab Wars]], and interbred with the local population as spoils of warfare or through eventual settling with many [[Norsemen|Scandinavian]] and [[Slavs|Slavic]] [[Viking]] men taking [[Arabs|Arab]] or [[Anatolians|Anatolian]] women as wives. There is archaeological evidence these Vikings had established contact with the city of [[Baghdad]], at the time the center of the [[Caliphate|Islamic Empire]], and connected with the populace there.{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}}

A genetic anthropological study known as The Genographic Project has found what is believed to be faint genetic traces left by medieval [[Crusaders]] in the Middle East. The team has uncovered a specific DNA signature in Lebanon that is probably linked to the Christian crusades of the 7th and 8th centuries. It is believed the Crusaders were welcomed by Christian Arabs long suffering under Islamic rule and many offered their daughters in marriage to the European Crusaders who originated from European kingdoms mostly France, England and the [[Holy Roman Empire]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/science/nature/7316281.stm Crusaders 'left genetic legacy']&quot;. BBC News. 27 March 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Ottoman Empire]], in addition to the Ottoman elites often taking large numbers of European wives and concubines (see [[#Southeastern and Eastern Europe|Southeastern and Eastern Europe]] section), there were also opportunities for the reverse, when the empire recruited young Christian boys (mostly Europeans in addition to Christian Arabs) to become the elite troop of the [[Turkish Empire]], the [[Janissaries]]. These Janissaries were stationed throughout the Turkish empire including the Middle-East and North Africa leading to inter-ethnic relationships between European men and women from the Middle East and North Africa. Further inter-ethnic marriages took place during the European colonial age when Great Britain, France and Italy ruled various parts of this region. The majority of these marriages were between European men and local [[Arabs|Arab]] and [[Berber people|Berber]] women.{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}}

The [[Imperial Harem|concubines of the Ottoman Sultan]] consisted chiefly of purchased slaves. Because Islamic law forbade Muslims to enslave fellow Muslims, the Sultan's concubines were generally of Christian origin. The mother of a Sultan, though technically a slave, received the extremely powerful title of ''Valide Sultan'', and at times became effective ruler of the Empire (see [[Sultanate of women]]). One notable example was [[Kösem Sultan]], daughter of a Greek Christian priest, who dominated the Ottoman Empire during the early decades of the 17th century.&lt;ref&gt;See generally Jay Winik (2007), ''The Great Upheaval''.&lt;/ref&gt; Another notable example was [[Roxelana]], the favourite wife of [[Suleiman the Magnificent]].

Inter-ethnic sexual slavery still continues today in a smaller form in the [[Arab states of the Persian Gulf]], where women and children are [[Human trafficking|trafficked]] from the [[post-Soviet states]], [[Eastern Europe]], [[Far East]], Africa, [[South Asia]] and other parts of the Middle East.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/hrrpt/2007/100608.htm United Arab Emirates], US Department of State&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.state.gov/g/tip/rls/tiprpt/2007/82807.htm Protection Act of 2000: Trafficking in Persons Report 2007], US Department of State&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.state.gov/g/tip/rls/tiprpt/2004/33195.htm Country Narratives: Near East], US Department of State&lt;/ref&gt;

====Israel====
The modern State of Israel was established as a nation-state for the Jewish people. The Jewish identity contains elements of religion (Judaism), ethnicity, and a sense of a common lineage.

In this sense, Jewish miscegenation could be viewed on two levels; one based on belonging to the Jewish ethnic group or Jewish people, and the other based on the race of a given Jew. Jewish miscegenation based on Jewishness (belonging to the Jewish ethnic group or Jewish people) would be defined on whether one parent is not Jewish, independent of whether either the Jewish or non-Jewish parent are of the same or different races. Racial miscegenation would be defined as the union between a Jew of a given race with a person of a different race, be the other person a Jew or not. Two Jewish people may still be considered &quot;interracial&quot; if those two Jews are of different races, although it would not be considered exogamous in the context of Jewish ethnicity, as both are still Jews.

In Israel, all marriages must be approved by religious celebrants, while civil marriages are legally recognized if performed abroad. Rules governing marriage are based on strict religious guidelines of each religion. By Israeli law, authority over all issues related to Judaism in Israel, including marriage, falls under the Orthodox Chief Rabbinate of Israel. Orthodox Judaism is the only form of Judaism recognized by the state, and marriages performed in Israel by non-Orthodox Rabbis are not recognized.

The Rabbinate prohibits marriage in Israel of halakhic Jews (i.e. people born to a Jewish mother or Jewish by conversion), whether they are Orthodox Jews or not, to partners who are non-Jewish or who are of Jewish descent that runs through the paternal line (i.e. not Jewish according to halakha). As a result, in the state of Israel, people of differing religious traditions cannot legally marry someone in another religion and multi-faith couples must leave the country to get married, most often to Central and Northern Greece{{Citation needed|date=May 2010|reason=please give a reliable source for this assertion.}}.

The only other option in Israel for the marriage of a halakhic Jew (Orthodox or not) to a non-Jew, or for that matter, a Christian to a non-Christian or Muslim to a non-Muslim, is for one partner to formally convert to the other's religion, be it to Judaism (Orthodox only), a Christian denomination (such as Eastern Orthodox or Maronite) or a denomination of Islam (such as Sunni or Shia). As for persons with patrilineal Jewish descent (i.e. not recognized as Jewish according to halakha) who wish to marry a halakhic Jew (i.e. born to a Jewish mother or is Jewish by Orthodox conversion) who is Orthodox or otherwise, is also required to formally convert to Judaism (Orthodox only) or they cannot legally marry.
According to a Haaretz article &quot;Justice Ministry drafts civil marriage law for ‘refuseniks’&quot; 300,000 people, or 150,000 couples, are affected by marriage restrictions based on the partners' disparate religious traditions or non-halakhic Jewish status.

Israeli law concerns itself with miscegenation based on Jewish ethnicity, not miscegenation based on race. Therefore, there are no restrictions on interracial marriages between Jews of different Jewish ethnic divisions, or between other co-religionists of different races, although social stigma may still exist.

Many Israeli Jews oppose mixed relationships between Jewish women and Arab men. A 2007 opinion survey found that more than half of Israeli Jews believed intermarriage is equivalent to &quot;national treason&quot;. A group of 35 Jewish men, known as &quot;Fire for Judaism&quot;, in [[Pisgat Ze'ev]] have started patrolling the town in an effort to stop Jewish women from dating Arab men. The municipality of [[Petah Tikva]] has also announced an initiative to prevent interracial relationships, providing a telephone hotline for friends and family to &quot;inform&quot; on Jewish girls who date Arab men as well as psychologists to provide counselling. The town of [[Kiryat Gat]] launched a school programme in schools to warn Jewish girls against dating local Bedouin men.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://fr.jpost.com/servlet/Satellite?cid=1253198149221&amp;pagename=JPost/JPArticle/ShowFull |title='Protecting' Jewish girls from Arabs |publist=[[Jerusalem Post]] |date=18 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.thenational.ae/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20090925/FOREIGN/709249932/0/rss |title=Israeli drive to prevent Jewish girls dating Arabs |publisher=[[The National (Abu Dhabi)|The National]] |first=Jonathan |last=Cook}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2010 [[Maariv]] has reported that the [[Tel Aviv]] municipality has instituted an official, government-sponsored &quot;counselling program&quot; to discourage Jewish girls from dating and marrying Arab boys. ''[[The Times]]'' has also reported on a vigilante parents’ group policing the Jerusalem neighborhood of [[Pisgat Ze'ev]] to intimidate and discourage local Arab-Jewish couples. The Jewish anti-missionary group [[Yad L'achim]] has also performed paramilitary &quot;rescue operations&quot; of Jewish women from non-Jewish husbands and celebrates the &quot;rescued women&quot; on their website.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://coteret.com/2010/02/24/tel-aviv-presents-municipal-program-to-prevent-arab-boys-from-dating-jewish-girls/ |title=Tel Aviv presents: Municipal program to prevent Arab boys from dating Jewish girls |publisher=[[Coteret]] |date=4 February 2010 |first=Dimi |last=Reider}}&lt;/ref&gt;
However, according to Halakha, descendants from a Jewish mother are always defined to be Jewish.

===Oceania===
[[File:Widemann1886Family1.jpg|thumb|German immigrant [[Hermann A. Widemann]] had a large family with his [[Hawaii]]an wife Mary Kaumana, 1886]]

====Australia====
Most of the early Chinese-Australia population consisted of Cantonese migrants from Guangzhou and Taishan, including some from Fujian, who came during the [[gold rush]] period of the 1850s. Marriage records show that between the 1850s and the start of the 20th century, there were about 2000 legal marriages between white women and Chinese men in Australia’s eastern colonies, probably with similar numbers involved in de facto relationships of various kinds (e.g., cohabitation, sexual intimacy, etc.).&lt;ref&gt;[http://epress.anu.edu.au/anu_lives/transnational/html/ch07s02.html Australian wives in China]. Chapter 7. A journey of love: Agnes Breuer’s sojourn in 1930s China. Epress.anu.edu.au. Retrieved 29 January 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; The number of such marriages declined, as stories of viciousness and the seduction of white women grew, mixed with opposition to intermarriage. Rallies against Chinese men marrying white women became widespread, with many Australian men reviewing Chinese men marrying and cohabiting with white women as an threat to the white race. In late 1878 there were 181 marriages between European women and Chinese men, and 171 couples cohabiting without matrimony, resulting in 586 Eurasian children.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=G. W. Trompf |author2=Carole M. Cusack |author3=Christopher Hartney |title=Religion and retributive logic: essays in honour of professor Garry W. Trompf |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=DqgezQo551kC&amp;pg=PA351 |accessdate=29 January 2012 |year=2010 |publisher=BRILL |isbn=978-90-04-17880-9 |pages=351–}}&lt;/ref&gt; Such numbers of intermarriage continued until the 1880s and the 1930s.

Analysis of the 2006 census reveals that 52% of Aboriginal men and 55% of Aboriginal women were married to non-Aboriginal Australians.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2009/apr/06/aborigines-australia-marriage Mixed marriage rates rise in Australia]&quot;. The Guardian. 6 April 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

====New Zealand====
Miscegenation is a politically charged topic in New Zealand, although mixed marriages are very common and almost universally accepted. People who identify as Māori typically have ancestors ('tīpuna'&lt;ref&gt;Tīpuna, ancestors, grandparents {{cite web|title=Māori Dictionary|url=http://www.maoridictionary.co.nz|accessdate=19 January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;) from at least two distinct ethnicities. Historically this has leant itself to the majority belief that &quot;real&quot; Māori were gradually disappearing from New Zealand and &quot;one people&quot; were forming.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Sharp|first=Andrew|title=Justice and the Māori|year=1991|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Auckland|pages=43–44}}&lt;/ref&gt; This view held sway in New Zealand until the late 1960s and 70s, when a revival and re-establishment of Māori culture and tradition coincided with a rejection of the majority opinion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Spoonley|first=Paul|title=Racism and Ethnicity|year=1993|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Auckland|pages=38–46}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The belief that Māori were disappearing was partially founded on the reality of high and ongoing rates of intermarriage between Europeans and Māori before and since colonisation. During the revival of Māori culture and tradition this belief began to be challenged by redefining &quot;Māori&quot; as an ethnic identity as opposed to a racial category.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Spoonley|first=Paul|title=Racism and Ethnicity|year=1993|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Auckland|pages=38–39}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result a person may have one European/Asian/Pacific parent and one Māori parent, but be considered no less &quot;authentically Māori&quot; than a descendent of two Māori.

Two-thirds of Māori births, half of Pacific births, and a third of white and Asian births belonged to more than one ethnic group.&lt;ref name=&quot;NZ_Herald_10663627&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nzherald.co.nz/nz/news/article.cfm?c_id=1&amp;objectid=10663627 |title=Harawira comments hurt race relations |date=4 August 2010 |agency=[[NZPA]] |work=[[The New Zealand Herald]] |accessdate=25 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Portuguese colonies===
{{see also|Orfas del Rei}}
According to [[Gilberto Freyre]], a Brazilian sociologist, miscegenation was commonplace in the [[Portuguese Empire|Portuguese colonies]], and was even supported by the court as a way to boost low populations and guarantee a successful and cohesive settlement. Thus, settlers often released [[African slave]]s to become their wives. The children were guaranteed full [[Portuguese citizenship]], provided the parents were married. Some former Portuguese colonies have large [[multiracial|mixed-race]] populations, for instance, [[Brazil]], [[Cape Verde]], [[Mozambique]], [[Timor Leste]], [[Macau]] and [[São Tomé and Príncipe]]. In the case of Brazil, the influential &quot;Indianist&quot; novels of [[José de Alencar]] ([[O Guarany]], [[Iracema]], and [[Ubirajara (novel)|Ubirajara]]) perhaps went farther than in the other colonies, advocating miscegenation in order to create a truly Brazilian race.&lt;ref&gt;Sá, Lúcia. Rain Forest Literatures: Amazonian Texts and Latin American Culture. Minneapolis, Minnesota: U of Minnesota Press, 2004. ISBN 978-0-8166-4325-7&lt;/ref&gt; Mixed marriages between [[Portuguese people|Portuguese]] and locals in former [[colonies]] were very common in all Portuguese colonies. Miscegenation was still common in Africa until the independence of the former Portuguese colonies in the mid-1970s.

==Demographics of ethnoracial admixture==

===U.S.===
According to the U.S. [[Census]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.census.gov/population/cen2000/phc-t19/tab01.pdf Hispanic Origin and Race of Coupled Households: 2000] U.S. Census. Retrieved 29 June 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; in 2000 there were 504,119 Asian-white marriages, 287,576 black-white marriages, and 31,271 Asian-black marriages. The black-white marriages increased from 65,000 in 1970 to 558,000 in 2010,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Table FG4. Married Couple Family Groups, by Presence of Own Children In Specific Age Groups, and Age, Earnings, Education, and Race and Hispanic Origin of Both Spouses: 2010 (thousands)|url=http://www.census.gov/population/www/socdemo/hh-fam/cps2010.html|publisher=U.S. Census Bureau}}&lt;/ref&gt; according to Census Bureau figures.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/18090277/ After 40 years, interracial marriage flourishing]. Msnbc.com. 15 April 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:The Gaze.jpg|thumb|New Jersey, 2008]]
In the United States, rates of interracial [[cohabitation]] are significantly higher than those of marriage. Although only 7% of married African American men have Caucasian American wives, 13% of cohabitating African American men have Caucasian American partners. 25% of married Asian American women have Caucasian spouses, but 45% of cohabitating Asian American women are with Caucasian American men. Of cohabiting Asian men, slightly over 37% of Asian men have white female partners over 10% married White American women.&lt;ref name=&quot;Swanbrow&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.modelminority.com/joomla/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=416:degrading-stereotypes-ruin-dating-experience-&amp;catid=37:dating&amp;Itemid=56 Degrading Stereotypes Ruin Dating Experience]. Modelminority.com (22 October 2002). Retrieved 11 December 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Asian American women and Asian American men who live with a white partner, 40 and 27 percent, respectively (Le, 2006b).In 2008, of new marriages including an Asian man, 80% were to an Asian spouse and 14% to a White spouse; of new marriages involving an Asian woman, 61% were to an Asian spouse and 31% to a White spouse.&lt;ref&gt;Jeffrey S. Passel, Wendy Wang and Paul Taylor [http://pewsocialtrends.org/files/2010/10/755-marrying-out.pdf Marrying Out: One-in-Seven New U.S. Marriages Is Interracial or Interethnic]. (PDF). Pew Research Center. 4 June 2010&lt;/ref&gt;
&gt; Almost 30% of Asians and Latinos outmarry, with 86.8 and 90% of these, respectively, being to a white person.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
|last = McClain DaCosta
|first = Kimberly
|title = Making multiracials: state, family, and market in the redrawing of the color line
|url = http://books.google.com/books?id=9WFAUYfFV2QC&amp;pg=PA9
|publisher = Stanford University Press
|year = 2007
|page = 9
|isbn = 0-8047-5546-9}}
&lt;/ref&gt; According to Karyn Langhorne Folan, &quot;...although the most recent census available reported that 70% of African American women are single, African American women have the greatest resistance to marrying 'out' of the race.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
|last = Langhorne Folan
|first = Karyn
|title = Don't Bring Home a White Boy: And Other Notions That Keep Black Women from Dating Out
|url = http://books.google.com/books?id=4xBRucoPhD0C&amp;pg=PA11
|publisher = Simon and Schuster
|year = 2010
|page = 11
|isbn = 1-4391-5475-9}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

One study on [[Higher education in the United States|college]] students noted that, while 90% of the 80 black men reported experiences in interracial dating, only 12% of the 140 white men reported such experiences.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=YNUDAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA162 Marriage and the Educated Black Woman]. ''Ebony''. August 1973.&lt;/ref&gt; The massive sexual survey revealed that 19% of black males had engaged in sexual activity with white women.&lt;ref name=&quot;smallpox&quot;&gt;{{Cite book
|last = Staples
|first = Robert
|title = Exploring black sexuality
|url = http://books.google.com/books?id=lm8mUih8Q2YC&amp;pg=PA124
|publisher = Rowman &amp; Littlefield
|year = 2006
|page = 124
|isbn = 0-7425-4659-4}}
&lt;/ref&gt; A [[Gallup poll]] on interracial dating in June 2006 found 75% of Americans approving of a white man dating a black woman, and 71% approving of a black man dating a white woman. Among people between the ages of 18 and 29, the poll found that 95% approved of blacks and whites dating, and about 60% said they had dated someone of a different race.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.usatoday.com/news/nation/2006-02-07-colorblind_x.htm New generation doesn't blink at interracial relationships]&quot;. USA Today (2 August 2006).&lt;/ref&gt; 69% of Hispanics, 52% of blacks, and 45% of whites said they have dated someone of another race or ethnic group.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.gallup.com/poll/19033/Most-Americans-Approve-Interracial-Dating.aspx Most Americans Approve of Interracial Dating]&quot;. Gallup.com. 7 October 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1980, just 17% of all respondents said they had dated someone from a different racial background.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://fll.stcloudstate.edu/classes/English191Spring2001/Heather_Huston_CrosCultural.htm Interracial and Cross Cultural Dating of Generation Y]&quot;. St. Cloud State University.&lt;/ref&gt;

However, according to a study from the University of California at Berkely, using data from over 1 million profiles of singles from online dating websites, whites were far more reluctant to date outside their race than non-whites. The study found that over 80% of whites, including whites who stated no racial preference, contacted other whites, whereas about 3% of whites contacted blacks, a result that held for younger and older participants. Only 5% of whites responded to inquiries from blacks. Black participants were ten times more likely to contact whites than whites were to contact blacks, however black participants sent inquiries to other blacks more often than otherwise.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://newscenter.berkeley.edu/2011/02/11/onlinedating/ In online dating, blacks more open to romancing whites than vice versa]&quot;. Berkely.edu February 11, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://healthland.time.com/2011/02/22/love-isnt-color-blind-white-online-daters-spurn-blacks/ Love Isn’t Color-Blind: White Online Daters Spurn Blacks]&quot;. healthland.time.com 22 February. 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

Interracial marriage is still relatively uncommon, especially among whites. In 2010, 15% of new marriages were interracial, and of those only 9% of Whites married outside of their race. Of the 275,000 new interracial marriages in 2010, 43% were white-Hispanic, 14.4% were white-Asian, 11.9% were white-black and the rest were other combinations. Black-white marriages are the least common interracial coupling.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052970204880404577226981780914906.html?mod=WSJ_hp_LEFTTopStories|title=More Marriages Cross Race, Ethnicity Lines|work=The Wall Street Journal|publisher=Theosophical University Press|accessdate=18 February 2012|first=Miriam|last=Jordan|date=17 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, interracial marriage has become more common over the past decades due to increasing racial diversity, and liberalizing attitudes toward the practice. According to the 2010 Census, the number of interracial marriages in the U.S. is up 20% since 2000, to around 4.5 million.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/37355330/ns/us_news-life/t/interracial-marriage-still-rising-us/ Interracial marriage still rising, but not as fast]&quot;. Msnbc.com. 26 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;A record 14.6% of all new marriages in the United States in 2008 were between spouses of a different race or ethnicity from one another. ... Rates more than doubled among whites and nearly tripled among blacks between 1980 and 2008. But for both Hispanics and Asians, rates were nearly identical in 2008 and 1980.&quot;, according to a [[Pew Research Center]] analysis of demographic data from the U.S. Census Bureau.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://pewresearch.org/pubs/1616/american-marriage-interracial-interethnic Marrying Out]&quot;. Jeffrey S. Passel, Wendy Wang and Paul Taylor, Pew Research Center. 4 June 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to studies by Jenifer L. Bratter and Rosalind B. King made publicly available on the [[Education Resources Information Center]], White female-Black male and White female-Asian male marriages are more prone to [[divorce]] than White-White pairings.&lt;ref name=&quot;ERIC&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://eric.ed.gov/ERICWebPortal/custom/portlets/recordDetails/detailmini.jsp?_nfpb=true&amp;_&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchValue_0=EJ789855&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchType_0=no&amp;accno=EJ789855|last=Bratter|first=Jenifer L.|title=&quot;But Will It Last?&quot;: Marital Instability among Interracial and Same-Race Couples|publisher=Blackwell Publishing|accessdate=13 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Conversely, unions between White males and non-White females (and between Hispanics and non-Hispanic persons) have similar or lower risks of divorce than White-White marriages, unions between white male-black female last longer than white-white pairings or white-Asian pairings.&lt;ref name=&quot;ERIC&quot; /&gt;

===Brazil===
{{See also|Race in Brazil}}

[[Multiracial]] Brazilians make up [[Mixed-race Brazilian|42.6% of Brazil's population]], 79.782 million people, and they live in all regions of [[Brazil]]. Multiracial Brazilians are mainly people of mixed European, African, East Asian (mostly Japanese) and [[Amerindian]] ancestry.

Interracial marriages comprised 22.6% of all marriages in 2000. 15.7% of blacks, 24.4% of whites and 27.6% of ''[[Pardo]]s'' (mixed-race/brown) married someone whose race was different from their own.&lt;ref&gt;Escóssia, F. “Casamento reflete discriminação racial.” ''[[Folha de São Paulo]].'' 23 October 2000. [http://scil.stanford.edu/research/learningcareers/capstones/brian/documents/brazil02.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Genetic studies of racial admixture==
Miscegenation between two populations reduces the genetic distance between the populations. During the [[Age of Discovery]] which began in the early 15th century, European explorers sailed all across the globe reaching all the major continents. In the process they came into contact with many populations that had been isolated for thousands of years. The [[Tasmanian aboriginal]]s were one of the most isolated groups on the planet.&lt;ref name=Chasteen&gt;{{Cite book|title=Problems in modern Latin American history, sources and interpretations|first1=John Charles |last1=Chasteen|first=2James A |last2=Wood |publisher=Sr Books| url=http://books.google.com/?id=FxRdCirZ-voC&amp;lpg=PA4|year=2003|pages=4–10|isbn=0-8420-5060-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; They were driven to extinction by European explorers, however a number of their descendants survive today as a result of [[admixture]] with Europeans. This is an example of how modern migrations have begun to reduce the genetic divergence of the human race.

The [[demographics|demographic]] composition of the [[old world]] has not changed significantly since the age of discovery. However, the [[new world]] demographics were radically changed within a short time following the voyage of [[Christopher Columbus|Columbus]].&lt;ref name=Chasteen/&gt; The colonization of Americas brought Native Americans into contact with the distant populations of Europe, Africa and Asia.&lt;ref name=Chasteen/&gt; As a result many countries in the Americas have significant and complex [[multiracial]] populations. Furthermore many who identify themselves by only one race still have multiracial ancestry.

===Admixture in the United States===
{{See also|Genetic history of indigenous peoples of the Americas|Multiracial American}}
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;float:right; margin-right:0; margin-left:1em&quot;
|+ Admixture in European-American population
! % European admixture || Frequency
|-
| 90–100 || 68%
|-
| 80–89.9 || 22%
|-
| 70–79.9 || 8%
|-
| 60–69.9 || &lt; 1%
|-
| 50–59.9 || &lt; 1%
|-
| 40–49.9 || &lt; 1%
|-
| 0–39.9 || 0
|}

Some claim the vast majority of African-Americans possess varying degrees of European admixture (the average Black American is 20% European) although studies suggest the Native American admixture in Black Americans is highly exaggerated; some estimates put average African-American possession of European admixture at 25% with figures as high as 50% in the Northeast and less than 10% in the south. A recent study by Mark D. Shriver of a European-American sample found that the average admixture in the white population is 0.7% African and 3.2% Native American. However, 70% of the sample had no African admixture. The other 30% had African admixture ranging from 2% to 20% with an average of 2.3%. By extrapolating these figures to the whole population some scholars suggest that up to 74 million European-Americans may have African admixture in the same range (2–20%).

Dr Mark Shriver, the team leader of the study, found that he had 11% West African ancestry though he identifies as white. Studies based on skin reflectance have shown the color line in the US applied selective pressure on genes that code for skin color but did not apply any selective pressure on other invisible African genes. Since there are an estimated 6 genetic loci involved in skin color determination it is possible for someone to have 15–20% African admixture and not possess any of alleles that code for dark skin.{{Dubious|date=January 2012}} This is the basis of the [[Passing (racial identity)|passing]] phenomenon. Thus African admixture amongst white Americans can increase without any significant change in skin tone. Conversely amongst African-Americans, an amount of African Admixture is directly correlated with darker skin since no selective pressure is applied; as a result, African-Americans may have a much wider range of African admixture (&gt;0–100%), whereas European-Americans have a lower range (2–20%). A small overlap exists so that it is possible that someone who identifies himself as [[white people|white]] may have more African admixture than a person who identifies himself as [[black people|black]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Sweet|first=Frank W. |title=Legal History of the Color Line: The Notion of Invisible Blackness|publisher=Backintyme Publishing|date=31 July 2005|page=542|isbn=0-939479-23-0 |url=http://backintyme.com/ad230.php}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://backintyme.com/essays/?p=5|title=Afro-European Genetic Admixture in the United States|last=Sweet|first=Frank W.|date=8 June 2004|work=Essays on the Color Line and the One-Drop Rule|publisher=Backintyme Essays|accessdate=13 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Alfred Jacob Miller - The Trapper's Bride - Walters 37194012.jpg|thumb|170px|''The Trapper's Bride'' shows a [[American Fur Company|trapper]], Francois, paying $600 in trade goods for an Indian woman to be his wife, ca. 1837]]
A statistical analysis done in 1958 using historical census data and historical data on immigration and birth rates, concluded that 21% of the white population had black ancestors. The growth in the white population could not be attributed to births in the white population and immigration from Europe alone, but had received significant contribution from the African American population as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Stuckert|first=Robert P.|month=May|year=1908|title=African Ancestry of the White American Population|journal=The Ohio Journal of Science|volume=58|issue=3|page=155|url=https://kb.osu.edu/dspace/bitstream/1811/4532/1/V58N03_155.pdf|format=PDF|accessdate=13 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The author states in 1958:

{{quote|The data presented in this study indicate that the popular belief in the non-African background of white persons is invalid. Over twenty-eight million white persons are descendants of persons of African origin. Furthermore, the majority of the persons with African ancestry are classified as white.}}

In the United States intermarriage among Filipinos with other races is common. They have the largest number of interracial marriages among Asian immigrant groups, as documented in California.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.asian-nation.org/interracial.shtml
|title=Interracial Dating &amp; Marriage
|publisher=asian-nation.org
|accessdate=30 August 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is also noted that 21.8% of Filipino Americans are of mixed blood, second among Asian Americans, and is the fastest growing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.asian-nation.org/multiracial.shtml
|title=Multiracial / Hapa Asian Americans
|publisher=asian-nation.org
|accessdate=30 August 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Admixture in Latin America===

====Background====
Prior to the European conquest of the [[Americas]] the demographics of Latin America was naturally 100% [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|American Indian]]. Today those who identify themselves as Native Americans are small minorities in many countries. For example the CIA lists [[Demographics of Argentina#Indigenous peoples|Argentina's native population]] at 0.9%, [[Indigenous peoples in Brazil|Brazil's]] at 0.4%, and [[Uruguay]]'s at 0%.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/index.html CIA Factbook]. Cia.gov. Retrieved 11 December 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; However, the range varies widely from country to country in [[Latin America]] with some countries having significantly larger [[Amerindian]] minorities. According to official statistics —as reported by the [[National Commission for the Development of Indigenous Peoples]] or CDI— Amerindians make up 10-14%&lt;ref&gt;http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/379167/Mexico,&lt;/ref&gt; of the population of [[Demographics of Mexico|Mexico]].
[[File:Casta painting all.jpg|thumb|180px|left|Depiction of casta system in [[New Spain|Mexico]], 18th century]]
The early conquest of Latin America was primarily carried out by male soldiers and sailors from Spain and Portugal. Since they carried very few European women on their journeys the new settlers married and fathered children with Amerindian women and also with women imported from Africa. This process of miscegenation was even encouraged by the [[Spanish monarchy]] and it led to the system of stratification known as the [[Casta]]. This system had Europeans ([[Spanish people|Spaniards]] and [[Portuguese people|Portuguese]]) at the top of the hierarchy followed by those of [[mixed race]]. Unmixed Blacks and Native Americans were at the bottom. A philosophy of [[Racial whitening|whitening]] emerged in which Amerindian and African culture was stigmatized in favor of European values. Many Amerindian languages were lost as mixed race offspring adopted Spanish and [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]] as their first languages. Only towards the end of the 19th century and beginning of the 20th century did large numbers of Europeans begin to migrate to South America and consequently altering its [[Latin america#Demographics|demographics]].

In addition many [[African people|Africans]] were shipped to regions all over the Americas and were present in many of the early voyages of the [[conquistador]]s. [[Brazil]] has the largest population of African descendants outside Africa. Other countries such as [[Jamaica]], [[Cuba]], [[Puerto Rico]], [[Dominican Republic]], [[Haiti]], [[Venezuela]], [[Colombia]], and [[Ecuador]] still have sizeable populations identified as [[Black people|Black]]. However countries such as [[Argentina]] and [[Chile]] do not have a visible African presence today. Census information from the early 19th century shows that people categorized as Black made up to 30% of the population, or around 400,000 people.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1002/ajpa.20083}}&lt;/ref&gt; Though almost completely absent today, their contribution to Argentine culture is significant include the [[Argentine tango|tango]], the [[milonga]] and the [[Zamba (artform)|zamba]], words of [[Bantu languages|Bantu]] origin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cwo.com/~lucumi/argentina.html|title=Blacks in Argentina: Disappearing Acts|last=Aidi|first=Hisham|date=2 April 2002|work=History Notes|publisher=The Global African Community|accessdate=13 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;float: right;&quot;
|-
! colspan=&quot;4&quot;|Demographics of Brazil in 1835, 1940, 2000 and 2008&lt;ref name=&quot;skidmore&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|first=Thomas E. |last=Skidmore |title=Fact and Myth: Discovering a Racial Problem in Brazil|journal=Working Paper|volume=173|url=http://www.nd.edu/~kellogg/publications/workingpapers/WPS/173.pdf|format=PDF|month=April|year=1992}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://noticias.uol.com.br/especiais/pnad/ultnot/2009/09/18/ult6843u18.jhtm Brasil perde brancos e pretos e ganha 3,2 milhões de pardos]. Noticias.uol.com.br (18 September 2009). Retrieved 11 December 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
! Year!! White !! Brown!! Black
|-
| 1835
| 24.4% || 18.2%||51.4%
|-
| 1940
| 64% ||21%||14%
|-
| 2000
| 53.7% ||38.5%||6.2%
|-
| 2008
| 48.8% ||43.8%||6.5%
|}
The ideology of whitening encouraged non-whites to seek white or lighter skinned partners. This dilution of non-white admixture would be beneficial to their offspring as they would face less stigmatization and find it easier to assimilate into mainstream society. After successive generations of European gene flow, non-white admixture levels would drop below levels at which skin color or physical appearance is not affected thus allowing individuals to identify as white. In many regions, the native and black populations were simply overwhelmed by a succession of waves of European immigration.

Historians and scientists are thus interested in tracing the fate of Native Americans and Africans from the past to the future. The questions remain about what proportion of these populations simply died out and what proportion still has descendants alive today including those who do not racially identify themselves as their ancestors would have. Admixture testing has thus become a useful objective tool in shedding light on the demographic history of Latin America.

====Recent studies====
[[File:Cabrera Pintura de Castas.jpg|thumb|170px|A Spaniard plays with his mixed-race daughter while his Mulatto wife looks on, 1763]]
Unlike in the United States, there were no anti-miscegenation policies in Latin America. Though still a racially stratified society there were no significant barriers to gene flow between the three populations. As a result admixture profiles are a reflection of the colonial populations of Africans, Europeans and Amerindians. The pattern is also sex biased in that the African and Amerindian maternal lines are found in significantly higher proportions than African or Amerindian Y chromosomal lines. This is an indication that the primary mating pattern was that of European males with Amerindian or African females. According to the study more than half the white populations of the Latin American countries studied have some degree of either native American or African admixture ([[MtDNA]] or [[Y Chromosome]]). In countries such as Chile and Colombia almost the entire white population was shown to have some non-white admixture&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Martínez Marignac|first=Verónica L.|coauthors=Bianchi Néstor O., Bertoni Bernardo, Parra Esteban J.|year=2004|title=Characterization of Admixture in an Urban Sample from Buenos Aires, Argentina, Using Uniparentally and Biparentally Inherited Genetic Markers|journal=Human Biology| volume=76|issue=4|pages=543–57|url=http://muse.jhu.edu/login?uri=/journals/human_biology/v076/76.4marignac.html| doi=10.1353/hub.2004.0058|pmid=15754971}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Gonçalves|first=V. F.|coauthors=Prosdocimi F., Santos L. S., Ortega J. M., Pena S. D. J.|date=9 May 2007|title=Sex-biased gene flow in African Americans but not in American Caucasians |journal=Genetics and Molecular Research|volume=6|issue=2|pages=256–61|issn=1676-5680|url=http://www.funpecrp.com.br/gmr/year2007/vol2-6/gmr0330_full_text.htm|accessdate=13 July 2008|pmid=17573655}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1086/303004}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Salzano|first=Francisco M. |coauthors=Cátira Bortolini, Maria |title=The Evolution and Genetics of Latin American Populations|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=Cambridge|year=2002|series=Cambridge Studies in Biological and Evolutionary Anthropology|volume=28|page=512|isbn=0-521-65275-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Frank Moya Pons, a [[Dominican Republic|Dominican]] historian documented that Spanish colonists intermarried with Taíno women, and, over time, these mestizo descendants intermarried with Africans, creating a tri-racial Creole culture. 1514 census records reveal that 40% of Spanish men in the colony of Santo Domingo had Taíno wives.&lt;ref&gt;Ferbel, Dr. P. J. [http://www.kacike.org/FerbelEnglish.html &quot;Not Everyone Who Speaks Spanish is from Spain: Taíno Survival in the 21st Century Dominican Republic.&quot;] ''Kacikie: Journal of Caribbean Amerindian History and Anthropology.'' . Retrieved 24 September 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; A recent study conducted in [[Puerto Rico]] suggests that over 61% of the population possess Amerindian mtDNA.&lt;ref&gt;Martínez Cruzado, Juan C. (2002). [http://www.kacike.org/MartinezEnglish.pdf The Use of Mitochondrial DNA to Discover Pre-Columbian Migrations to the Caribbean:Results for Puerto Rico and Expectations for the Dominican Republic.] ''Kacike: The Journal of Caribbean Amerindian History and Anthropology.'' Lynne Guitar, Ed. (Retrieved 25 September 2006)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Admixture in the Philippines===
[[History of the Philippines (1898–1946)|Historically]], admixture has been an ever present and pervading phenomenon in the Philippines. The Philippines was originally settled by [[Australoid]] peoples called [[Negritos]] which now form the country's aboriginal community. Admixture occurred between this earlier group and the mainstream [[Malayo-Polynesian]] population.&lt;ref name=stanford/&gt;

There has been [[Indian Filipino|Indian migration]] to and influence in the Philippines since the precolonial era. About 25% of the words in the Tagalog language are Sanskrit terms and about 5% of the country's population possess Indian ancestry from antiquity.&lt;ref name=precolonial&gt;[http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://www.geocities.com/CollegePark/Pool/1644/precolonial.html&amp;date=24 October 2009+21:35:10 Pre Colonial Period].&lt;/ref&gt; There has been a [[Chinese people|Chinese]] presence in the [[Philippines]] since the 9th century. However, large-scale migrations of Chinese to the Philippines only started during the Spanish colonial era, when the world market was opened to the Philippines. It is estimated that among [[Filipino people|Filipinos]], 10%–20% have some Chinese ancestry and 1.5% are &quot;full-blooded&quot; Chinese.&lt;ref name=ocac/&gt;

According to the American [[Anthropology|anthropologist]] Dr. H. Otley Beyer, the ancestry of [[Filipino people|Filipinos]] is 2% [[Arab]]. This dates back to when Arab traders intermarried with the local [[Malay race|Malay]] Filipina female populations during the [[History of the Philippines (Before 1521)|pre-Spanish history of the Philippines]].&lt;ref name=Arab-Malays/&gt; A recent genetic study by [[Stanford University]] indicates that at least 3.6% of the population are [[European ethnic groups|European]] or of part European descent from both [[Spanish Empire|Spanish]] and United States colonization.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1086/318205}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Admixture among the Romani people===
Genetic evidence has shown that the [[Romani people]] (&quot;[[Names of the Romani people|Gypsies]]&quot;) originated from the [[Indian subcontinent]] and mixed with the local populations in [[Central Asia]], the Middle East, and Europe. In the 1990s, it was discovered that Romani populations carried large frequencies of particular [[Y chromosome]]s (inherited paternally) that otherwise exist only in populations from [[South Asia]], in addition to fairly significant frequencies of particular [[mitochondrial DNA]] (inherited maternally) that is rare outside South Asia.

47.3% of Romani males carry Y chromosomes of [[Haplogroup H (Y-DNA)|haplogroup H-M82]] which is rare outside of the Indian subcontinent.&lt;ref name=&quot;kalaydjieva&quot;&gt;{{Cite pmid|16163730}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mitochondrial [[Haplogroup M (mtDNA)|haplogroup M]], most common in Indian subjects and rare outside Southern Asia, accounts for nearly 30% of Romani people.&lt;ref name=&quot;kalaydjieva&quot;/&gt; A more detailed study of Polish [[Roma (Romani subgroup)|Roma]] shows this to be of the M5 lineage, which is specific to India.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1111/j.1529-8817.2005.00222.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, a form of the inherited disorder [[Myasthenia gravis|congenital myasthenia]] is found in Romani subjects. This form of the disorder, caused by the 1267delG mutation, is otherwise only known in subjects of Indian ancestry. This is considered to be the best evidence of the Indian ancestry of the Romanies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bharti_Morar&quot;&gt;{{cite pmid|15322984}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Romanis have been described as &quot;a conglomerate of genetically isolated founder populations&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Luba_Kalaydjieva&quot;&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1186/1471-2350-2-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; while a number of common Mendelian disorders among Romanies from all over Europe indicates &quot;a common origin and founder effect&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Luba_Kalaydjieva&quot;/&gt; See also this table:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1186/1471-2350-2-5|year=2001|last1=Kalaydjieva|first1=Luba|last2=Gresham|first2=David|last3=Calafell|first3=Francesc|journal=BMC Medical Genetics|volume=2|page=5|pmid=11299048|title=Genetic studies of the Roma (Gypsies): A review|pmc=31389}} [http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2350/2/5/figure/F4 Figure 4].&lt;/ref&gt;

A study from 2001 by Gresham et al. suggests &quot;a limited number of related founders, compatible with a small group of migrants splitting from a distinct caste or tribal group&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;David Gresham&quot;&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1086/324681}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also the study pointed out that &quot;genetic drift and different levels and sources of admixture, appear to have played a role in the subsequent differentiation of populations&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;David_Gresham&quot;/&gt; The same study found that &quot;a single lineage ... found across Romani populations, accounts for almost one-third of Romani males. A similar preservation of a highly resolved male lineage has been reported elsewhere only for Jewish priests&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;David_Gresham&quot;/&gt; See also the [[Y-chromosomal Aaron|Cohen Modal Haplotype]].

A 2004 study by Morar et al. concluded that the Romani are &quot;a founder population of common origins that has subsequently split into multiple socially divergent and geographically dispersed Gypsy groups&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bharti_Morar&quot;/&gt; The same study revealed that this population &quot;was founded approximately 32–40 generations ago, with secondary and tertiary founder events occurring approximately 16–25 generations ago&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bharti_Morar&quot;/&gt;

==See also==
{{Col-begin}}
{{Col-2}}
* [[A Racial Program for the Twentieth Century]]
* [[Amalgamation (race)]]
* [[Anti-miscegenation laws]]
* [[Discrimination based on skin color]]
* [[Ethnic pornography]]
* [[Exogamy]]
* [[Interracial marriage]]
* [[List of interracial romance films|Interracial romance in film]]
* [[Melungeon]]
* [[Mestizo]]
{{Col-break}}
* [[Mixed Race Day]]
* [[Multiculturalism]]
* [[Multiracial]]
* [[Passing (racial identity)]]
* [[Plaçage]]
* [[Race and genetics]]
* [[Race and society]]
* [[Race of the future]]
* [[Racial Integrity Act of 1924]]
* [[Racism]]
{{Col-end}}

==Notes and references==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Bibliography==
*{{cite book |author=Christina Miu Bing Cheng|title=Macau: a cultural Janus|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=-Gr51C1eS1oC&amp;pg=PA173|year=1999 |publisher=Hong Kong University Press|isbn=962-209-486-4}}
*{{cite book |author=João de Pina-Cabral|title=Between China and Europe: person, culture and emotion in Macao|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=GglrUksvCUcC&amp;pg=PA164|volume=Volume 74 of London School of Economics monographs on social anthropology|year=2002|publisher=Berg|isbn=0-8264-5749-5}}
*{{Cite book|title=Interracial Intimacy in Japan|first=Gary P.|last=Leupp|publisher=[[Continuum International Publishing Group]]|year=2003|isbn=0-8264-6074-7}}

==Other sources==
* {{Cite book|author=Cavanaugh-O'Keefe, John. |title=The Roots of Racism and Abortion: An Exploration of Eugenics |publisher=Xlibris Corporation |date=23 October 2000 |url=http://www.eugenics-watch.com/roots/index.html|isbn=0-7388-3089-5|page=268}} See esp. [http://www.eugenics-watch.com/roots/chap07.html &quot;Chapter Seven: Laws Against Mixing Races&quot;]
* {{Cite book|author=Croly, David Goodman|title=Miscegenation, The Theory of the Blending of the Races, Applied to the American White Man and Negro|location=New York|isbn=0-7388-3089-5|publisher=H. Dexter, Hamilton &amp; Co|year=1864}}
* Deschamps, Bénédicte, ''Le racisme anti-italien aux États-Unis (1880–1940)'', in ''Exclure au nom de la race (États-Unis, Irlande, Grande-Bretagne)'', Michel Prum (Éd.). Paris: Syllepse, 2000. 59–81.
* {{Cite book|author=Hodes, Martha, ed. &quot;Miscegenation&quot;|title=Reader's Companion to U.S. Women's History|location=New York, Boston|publisher=Houghton Mifflin Company|year=1998|isbn=0-395-67173-6}}
* Jacobson, Matthew Frye, ''[http://www.columbia.edu/itc/hs/pubhealth/rosner/p8773/readings/jacobson1.pdf Whiteness of a different color. European Immigrants and the Alchemy of Race]'', Harvard University Press, 1998.
* {{Cite doi|10.2307/2715904|jstor=2715904}}
* {{Cite book|author=Lemire, Elise|title=&quot;Miscegenation&quot;: Making Race in America|location=Philadelphia|publisher=University of Pennsylvania Press|month=July|year=2002|isbn=0-8122-3664-5}}
* Novkov, Julie, ''Racial union: law, intimacy, and the White state in Alabama, 1865–1954'', University of Michigan Press, 2008, pp.&amp;nbsp;125–128.
* {{Cite doi|10.2307/744035}}
* {{Cite news|last=Pascoe |first=Peggy |title=Why the Ugly Rhetoric Against Gay Marriage Is Familiar to this Historian of Miscegenation |publisher=George Mason University's History News Network |date=19 April 2004 |url=http://hnn.us/articles/4708.html |accessdate=14 July 2008}}
* {{Cite book|last=Rosenthal|first=Debra J.|title=Race Mixture in Nineteenth-Century U.S and Spanish-American Fiction|publisher=University of North Carolina Press|year=2004|isbn=0-8078-5564-2|url=http://books.google.com/?id=i_8kSPDFVGEC}}
* {{Cite book|title=Interracialism: Black-White Intermarriage in American History, Literature, and Law|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Oxford|date=19 October 2000|edition=Sollors, Werner|isbn=0-19-512856-7|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_hb6524/is_200110/ai_n25878127|editor= Werner Sollors}}
* Tehranian, John, ''Whitewashed: America's invisible Middle Eastern minority'', New York University Press, 2009. ISBN 978-0-8147-8306-1
* Ubeysekara, Ruwan Nisantha, [http://opus.bath.ac.uk/17240/1/Questioning_the_Revival_-_White_Ethnicities_in_the_Racial_Pentagon.pdf Questioning the Revival: White Ethnicities in the Racial Pentagon], PhD Thesis, University of Bath, 2008.

==External links==
{{wiktionary}}
*[http://www.racerelations.about.com/ Explore Famous Interracial Couples and Other Race Relations] Issues on the About.com Website.
*[http://www.lovingday.org/cases/perez_v_sharp_1948.htm Perez v. Sharp]
*[http://academic.udayton.edu/race/04needs/sex04.htm Historical Background on Miscegenation]

{{Sexual ethics}}

[[Category:Antisemitism]]
[[Category:History of racial segregation in the United States]]
[[Category:Marriage]]
[[Category:Multiracial affairs]]
[[Category:Nazi Germany]]
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Racism]]

[[de:Interkulturelle Ehe]]
[[es:Mestizaje]]
[[eo:Rasmiksiĝo]]
[[fr:Métissage]]
[[it:Mescolanza razziale]]
[[pt:Miscigenação]]
[[ru:Метисация]]
[[sv:Rasblandning]]</text>
      <sha1>mgg94drpza5n8hk3as00ot0tumg4d8m</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
