<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Motion of no confidence</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>208101</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519315340</id>
      <parentid>517403178</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-23T02:26:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lucius Spinner</username>
        <id>17747349</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>I have added an introductory statement which is more simple, to introduce the subject, and have then turned it over to the legal definition as it was previously.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13703">{{Multiple issues|refimprove =August 2009|one source =August 2009|globalize =November 2010}}

A '''motion of no confidence''' is primarily a statement or vote which states that a person in a superior position - be it government, managerial, etc - is no longer deemed fit to hold that position. This may be based on said person falling short in some respect, failing to carry out obligations, or making choices that other members feel are detrimental. 

In law, a '''motion of no confidence''' (alternatively '''vote of no confidence''', '''censure motion''', '''no-confidence motion''', or (unsuccessful) '''confidence motion''') is a [[parliamentary motion]] which when passed would demonstrate to the [[head of state]] that the elected parliament no longer has confidence in (one or more members of) the appointed [[Executive (government)|government]].

==Overview==
Typically, when a parliament passes a vote of no confidence in an existing government, the head of state must respond in one of two ways:

*ask another individual, whom he or she believes will command the confidence of parliament, to try to form a government
*[[Dissolution of parliament|dissolve the elected parliament]] and call a [[general election]] to elect a new parliament

In determining whether another individual can command the confidence of parliament, the head of state examines whether that individual has the backing of a parliamentary party, a [[Coalition government|coalition]] of parties and MPs, or an agreement of support with enough parliamentary seats to withstand any confidence challenges. If this cannot be done, parliament is dissolved and a general election is called.

In some cases, the sitting government will request that the head of state [[Dissolution of parliament|dissolve the elected parliament]] and call a new election without seeking the forming of another Government, such that it would remain in power during the election period.  The head of state may agree to do this, depending on factors such as time until a mandated election, reasonable expectation of the forming of another government or in very rare circumstances, on royal prerogative alone. However, where the head of state believes the government no longer has the confidence of the ''responsible'' house (i.e., the directly elected [[lower house|lower chamber]] which can select and dismiss it; in some states both [[chambers of parliament|houses of parliament]] are responsible), a [[head of state]] may refuse a request for a parliamentary dissolution, so forcing an immediate resignation.

This procedure is either formalized through [[constitutional convention (political custom)|constitutional convention]], as is the case in Westminster style parliaments such as the [[United Kingdom]], [[Canada]] and [[Australia]],{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}} or explicitly stated in a written constitution, as is the case with [[Germany]] &lt;ref name=&quot;germanconst&quot;&gt;[https://www.btg-bestellservice.de/pdf/80201000.pdf German Constitution Official English Translation] Article 67 - Vote of No Confidence&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Spain]].&lt;ref name=&quot;spanishconst&quot;&gt;[http://www.tribunalconstitucional.es/es/constitucion/Paginas/ConstitucionIngles.aspx Spanish Constitution] Article 113&lt;/ref&gt;

Sometimes, the government will choose to declare that one of its bills is a motions of confidence. This may be used to prevent dissident members of parliament from voting against it. Sometimes (depending on the country) a government may lose a vote because the opposition ends debate prematurely when too many government members are away.

In the [[Westminster system]], the defeat of a [[supply bill]] (one that concerns the spending of money) automatically requires (by convention) the resignation of the government or dissolution of Parliament, much like a non-confidence vote, since a government that cannot spend money is hamstrung. This is called [[loss of supply]].

Where the upper house of a Westminster system country has the right to refuse supply, such as in Australia during [[1975 Australian constitutional crisis|the events of 1975]], the convention becomes a grey area as Westminster governments are not normally expected to maintain the confidence of the upper house.

==Variations==
There are a number of variations in this procedure.

For example, in [[Germany]], [[Spain]], and [[Israel]], a vote of no confidence requires that the opposition, on the same ballot, propose a candidate of their own whom they want to be appointed as successor by the respective [[head of state]].&lt;ref name=&quot;germanconst&quot; /&gt; Thus the motion of no confidence is required to be at the same time as a motion of confidence for a new candidate (this variation is called a [[constructive vote of no confidence]]). The idea was to prevent crises of the state such as those found near the end of the German [[Weimar Republic]] by ensuring that whoever is [[head of government]] has enough support to govern. Unlike the British system, the [[Chancellor of Germany (Federal Republic)|German Chancellor]] does not have to resign in response to the failure of a vote of confidence, provided it has been initiated by herself/himself and not by the parliamentary opposition, but rather may ask the [[President of Germany|Federal President]] to call general elections - a request the President may or may not fulfill.

A motion of no confidence in some countries can be proposed in the government collectively or by any individual member, including the [[Prime Minister]]. In [[Spain]] it is presented by the Prime Minister after consultation. Sometimes motions of no confidence are proposed, even though they have no likelihood of passage, simply to pressure a government or to embarrass its own critics who nevertheless for political reasons consider not to vote against it. In many parliamentary democracies, strict time limits exist as to the proposing of a no confidence motion, with a vote only allowed once every three, four or six months. Thus knowing when to use a motion of no confidence is a matter of political judgement; using a motion of no confidence on a relatively trivial matter may prove counterproductive to its proposer if a more important issue suddenly arises which warrants a motion of no confidence, because a motion cannot be proposed if one had been voted on recently and cannot be proposed again for a number of months.

In the [[consensus government]] system of the [[Northwest Territories]] and [[Nunavut]], [[Canada]], in which the premier is chosen among and by a vote of the members of the non-partisan legislature, a vote of no confidence removes the premier and cabinet from office and permits the members to elect a new premier.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbc.ca/canada/north/story/2009/02/04/nwt-leg.html (CBC)]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Parliament of the United Kingdom|British Parliament]], a no-confidence motion generally first appears as an [[early day motion]], although the vote on the [[Speech from the Throne|Queen's Speech]] also constitutes a confidence motion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.parliament.uk/documents/commons-information-office/m07.pdf |title=House of Commons Factsheet M7: Parliamentary Elections |publisher=House of Commons Information office |page=3 |accessdate=23 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Presidential systems===
In [[presidential system]]s, the legislature may occasionally pass motions of no confidence, as was done by the [[United States Congress]] to [[United States Secretary of State|Secretary of State]] [[Dean Acheson]] in the 1950s&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,890225,00.html|accessdate=29 March 2011|title=THE CONGRESS: Vote of No Confidence|date=Monday, Mar. 03, 1952|newspaper=Time}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was contemplated against [[United States Attorney General|Attorney General]] [[Alberto Gonzales]], but these motions are of symbolic effect only. Presidential systems also usually have the procedure of [[impeachment]] by which an executive or judicial officer can be removed.

In certain parts of the [[United States]] and [[Venezuela]], the [[recall election]] fills a similar role of removing an unpopular government, but, in contrast to a motion of no confidence, this vote involves the entire electorate.

===Russia===
In the [[Russia|Russian Federation]] the lower house of parliament (the [[State Duma]]) may by a [[majority|simple majority]] (i.e. at least 226 votes out of 450) pass a motion of no confidence against the [[Government of Russia]] as a whole. In this case the matter goes for consideration of the [[President of Russia|President]], who may choose to dismiss the cabinet (which the President can do at any moment of time at his own discretion anyway) or just to ignore the Duma's decision. Should the Duma pass a second motion of no confidence against the same composition of the cabinet within three months, the President will be forced to make a concrete decision - to dismiss the government or to dissolve the Duma itself and call for new general elections. The [[State Duma]] may not be dissolved on these grounds if it was elected less than a year ago, if it has already initiated impeachment proceedings against the [[President of Russia]] himself by bringing respective accusations, if less than six months is left until elections of the President or if there is a state of emergency or martial law throughout the whole territory of [[Russia]]. In the above mentioned cases the President would therefore be effectively forced to dismiss the Government.

==History==
{{See also|List of prime ministers defeated by votes of no confidence}}
The first motion of no confidence occurred in March 1782{{citation needed|date=September 2011}} when, following news of the [[Siege of Yorktown|British defeat at Yorktown]] in the [[American Revolutionary War]] the previous October, the [[Parliament of Great Britain]] voted that they &quot;can no longer repose confidence in the present ministers&quot;. [[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom|Prime Minister]] [[Frederick North, Lord North|Lord North]] responded by asking [[George III of the United Kingdom|King George III]] to accept his resignation. This did not immediately create a [[constitutional convention (political custom)|constitutional convention]]. During the early 19th century, however, attempts by prime ministers such as [[Robert Peel]] to govern in the absence of a parliamentary majority proved unsuccessful, and by the mid-19th century, the ability of a motion of no confidence to break a government was firmly established in the UK.

In the United Kingdom, there have been a total of 11 prime ministers defeated through a no-confidence motion. There has been only [[1979 vote of no confidence in the government of James Callaghan|one]] (against [[James Callaghan]]) since 1925.

In modern times, passage of a motion of no confidence is a relatively rare event in two-party democracies. In almost all cases, [[party discipline]] is sufficient to allow a majority party to defeat a motion of no confidence, and if faced with possible defections in the government party, the government is likely to change its policies rather than lose a vote of no confidence. The cases in which a motion of no confidence has passed are generally those in which the government party has a slim majority which is eliminated by either [[by-election]]s or defections, such as the [[1979 vote of no confidence in the government of James Callaghan|1979 vote of no confidence in the Callaghan government of the UK]] which was carried by one vote, forcing a UK General Election and the election of [[Margaret Thatcher]]'s government.

Motions of No Confidence are far more common in multi-party systems in which a minority party must form a [[coalition government]]. This can result in the situation in which there are many short-lived governments because the party structure allows small parties to break a government without means to create a government. This has widely been regarded as the cause of instability for the [[French Fourth Republic]] and the German [[Weimar Republic]]. More recent examples of this phenomenon have been in [[Italy]] between the 1950s and 1990s, [[Israel]], and [[Politics of Japan|Japan]].

To deal with this situation, the French placed large amount of executive power in the office of [[President of France]], which is immune from Motions of No Confidence.

In 2008, Canadian Prime Minister [[Stephen Harper]], of the re-elected minority government of Canada, requested that Governor General Michaëlle Jean [[Prorogation in Canada|prorogue Parliament]]. The request was granted, and it allowed the Prime Minister to delay a potential vote on the non-confidence motion presented by the opposition. (See [[2008–2009 Canadian parliamentary dispute]].)

==See also==
*[[Motions of no confidence in the United Kingdom]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Motion Of No Confidence}}
[[Category:Confidence motions| ]]

{{Link FA|de}}
[[be-x-old:Вотум недаверу]]
[[bg:Вот на недоверие]]
[[da:Mistillidsvotum]]
[[de:Misstrauensvotum]]
[[es:Moción de censura]]
[[eo:Mocio de demisio]]
[[fa:رای اعتماد]]
[[fr:Motion de censure]]
[[ko:불신임 결의]]
[[id:Mosi tidak percaya]]
[[it:Mozione di sfiducia]]
[[he:הצעת אי אמון]]
[[hu:Bizalmatlansági indítvány]]
[[nl:Motie van afkeuring]]
[[ja:内閣不信任決議]]
[[no:Mistillitsvotum]]
[[nn:Mistillitsframlegg]]
[[pl:Wotum nieufności]]
[[pt:Moção de censura]]
[[ro:Moțiune de cenzură]]
[[ru:Вотум]]
[[fi:Epäluottamuslause]]
[[sv:Misstroendeförklaring]]
[[th:การอภิปรายไม่ไว้วางใจ]]
[[uk:Вотум недовіри]]
[[zh:不信任动议]]</text>
      <sha1>02adne8kkmch4xhg9q7v9gh6eypi3i1</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
