<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Movement for a New Society</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>454066</id>
    <revision>
      <id>503082499</id>
      <parentid>497453137</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-07-19T07:27:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Vis-a-visconti</username>
        <id>5394025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Added categories</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="5443">The '''Movement for a New Society''' (MNS) was a [[United States|U.S.]]-based network of social activists, committed to the principles of [[nonviolence]], who played a key role in social movements of the 1970s and 80s.

The precursor to the MNS was [[A Quaker Action Group]](AQAG), founded by [[Lawrence Scott (Quaker)|Lawrence Scott]] in 1966. Dissatisfied with the response of the mainstream [[Quaker]] church to the United States involvement in the [[Vietnam War]], Scott founded AQAG with the intention of sparking a renewed commitment to the Quaker Peace Testimony.

Frustrated by their failure to achieve this end, AQAG members including Scott and “convinced” Quaker [[George Willoughby]], refashioned the group as the Movement for A New Society in 1971. Other founding members included [[William Moyer|Bill Moyer]] and [[George Lakey]].

The early members of MNS consciously sought to develop tools and strategies that could be employed to bring about revolutionary change through nonviolent means. Through the [[Life Center Association]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.vortexhouse.org/LCA/history.shtml&lt;/ref&gt; (Philadelphia, PA), an organization which survives to this day, MNS members also experimented with [[co-operative living arrangements]], in accordance with their [[radical feminist]] and nonviolent beliefs.

Unlike other radical organizations of the time, the MNS did not focus its energies exclusively on one issue or injustice. Its members were involved in working for social change on many fronts, most notably in the movement to end US involvement in the Vietnam war, and during the citizen-led opposition to the expansion of the US nuclear industry in the mid to late ‘70s.

According to a description from the MNS publication, ''Building Social Change Communities'' (1979),

:Movement for a New Society (MNS) is a nationwide network of groups working for fundamental social change through nonviolent action. Together we are developing an analysis of present-day society; a vision of a decentralized, democratic and caring social order; a nonviolent revolutionary strategy; and a program based on changed values and changed lives.

Through the co-operatively owned and managed [http://www.newsociety.com New Society Publishers], MNS members published numerous pamphlets and books providing practical advice on working for social change. The publications of NSP, most notably the co-operatively authored ''Resource Manual for a Living Revolution'' (known affectionately within movement circles as the “monster manual”) were a primary source of inspiration and guidance for citizens across the United States as opposition to nuclear expansion grew, and influenced movements as far afield as the Tasmanian Wilderness Society’s campaign to prevent the damming of the [[Franklin River]].

In 1988, MNS was dissolved by its members due to various factors, including its inability to achieve its objective of becoming multi-cultural, as well as difficulty adapting as an organization due to the self-imposed strictures of consensus decision-making. Other issues included conflicting ideas of the importance of leadership, as well as an excessive amount of time spent on internal anti-oppression work, leading to less time for world transformation work.&lt;ref&gt;Cf. Cornell&lt;/ref&gt; It could also be argued that it had achieved its primary goal of making Gandhian style non-violent action a primary method that American social change activists use to effect change.

New Society Publishers, now based in British Columbia, continues to publish social-change related titles, with an increased emphasis on the practical aspects of environmental sustainability. In 1995, members of the New Society Publishers Philadelphia office started a website, Nonviolence.org, which continues to publish resources, inspiration and analysis. Until his death in October, 2002, Bill Moyer continued to teach his influential eight-stage model for social change movements, the [[Movement Action Plan]], to activists around the US and around the world. [[George Lakey]], as director of the Philadelphia based Training for Change organisation, still works to promote [[nonviolence]] as a powerful technique for resisting injustice.

[[Douglas &amp; McIntyre]] bought New Society Publishers in 2008.

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
Cornell, Andrew (2011). ''Oppose and Propose: Lessons from Movement for a New Society'': [http://www.akpress.org AK Press]. ISBN 978-1-84935-066-2

Coover, Virginia ... [et al.] (1985). ''Resource Manual for a Living Revolution''. Philadelphia, PA : New Society Publishers. ISBN 0-86571-015-5

==External links==
*[http://www.newsociety.com New Society Publishers]
*[http://www.trainingforchange.org Training for Change]
*[http://www.indybay.org/uploads/movement_action_plan.pdf The Movement Action Plan] by Bill Moyer
*[http://historyisaweapon.com/defcon1/moyermap.html The Movement Action Plan] by Bill Moyer (text)
*[http://anarchiststudies.org/node/292 Anarchism and the Movement for a New Society: Direct Action and Prefigurative Community in the 1970s and 80s By Andrew Cornell]
*[http://www.upenn.edu/gazette/0706/feature3.html &quot;Heaven is a mixed neighbourhood&quot;]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Movement For A New Society}}
[[Category:Nonviolent resistance movements]]
[[Category:Activism]]
[[Category:Nonviolence]]
[[Category:Nonviolence organizations]]
[[Category:Pacifism in the United States]]
[[Category:Radical feminism]]</text>
      <sha1>frnh5iwoky6q2zsjnp0mbdg1nr75zeu</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
