<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Multi-party system</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>233475</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521992617</id>
      <parentid>521748978</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-08T12:50:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>88.70.63.212</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Examples */ The UK is not the best example for a Multi-party system</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7706">{{Refimprove|date=October 2012}}
{{Party politics}}
{{Cleanup|date=May 2012|reason=Poorly translated article, needs to be rewritten up to professional standards}}
A '''multi-party system''' is a system in which multiple political parties have the capacity to gain control of government offices, separately or in coalition. An example of such a coalition being the one in existence between the [[Christian-Democratic Union of Germany]] and [[Christian Social Union]] in Bavaria (CDU/CSU) and the [[Free Democratic Party]] (FDP) set up after the 2009 federal elections. The [[effective number of parties]] in a multi-party system is normally larger than two but lower than ten. In the vast majority of multi-party systems, numerous major and minor political parties hold a serious chance of receiving office, and because they all compete, a majority may not come to be, forcing the creation of a [[Coalition government|coalition]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://student.education2020.com/activities/vocab.aspx?keystr=12674&amp;order=02010205&amp;stbl=2196465] - Education 2020, definition of '''multiparty''': ''&quot;A system in which several major and many lesser parties exist, seriously compete for, and actually win public offices.&quot;''&lt;/ref&gt; In fact, in some countries, every government ever formed since its independence has been by means of a coalition. Multi-party systems tend to be more common in [[parliamentary systems]] than [[presidential systems]] and far more common in countries that utilize [[proportional representation]] compared to countries that utilize [[first past the post]] elections.

== Examples ==
[[Brazil]], [[Canada]], [[Denmark]], [[Finland]], [[Germany]], [[India]], [[Indonesia]],  [[Republic of Ireland|Ireland]], [[Israel]], [[Italy]], [[Japan]], [[Mexico]], the [[Netherlands]], [[New Zealand]], [[Norway]], [[Pakistan]], [[Portugal]], [[Serbia]], [[Spain]], [[Sweden]],[[Republic of China|Taiwan]] and [[Philippines]](source:[[Politics of the Philippines]]) are examples of nations that have used a multi-party system effectively in their democracies. In these countries, usually no single party has a parliamentary majority by itself. Instead, multiple political parties form [[coalition]]s for the purpose of developing power blocks for governing.

In some multi-party systems only two or three parties have a substantial chance of forming a government, with or without forming a coalition. An example of this being the [[United Kingdom]], where only the [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative Party]], the [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]], and the [[Liberal Democrats]] have a serious chance to win enough seats to be a part of the government. Though the [[Liberal Democrats]] since their formation have never had near enough amount to form a Government though have a substantial enough amount of seats to be able to be members of a government in a Coalition. To date the Liberal Democrats have only been in power once in a coalition, which is in the only coalition in recent history, which is the incumbent [[United Kingdom coalition government (2010-present)|Conservative-Liberal Democrat Coalition]].

== Comparisons with other party systems ==
=== Single-party system and Two-party system ===
{{see also|Single-party system|Two-party system}}

A system where only two parties have the possibility of winning an election is called two-party system. A system where only 3 parties have a ''realistic possibility'' of winning an election or forming a coalition is sometimes called a &quot;Third-party system&quot;, however in some cases the system is called a &quot;Stalled Third-Party System&quot; when there are 3 parties in the system, and all 3 parties win a large number of votes, however only 2 have a chance of winning a general election; this is usually because the electoral system penalises the third party e.g. UK politics, the Liberal Democrats gained 23% of the vote in 2010 elections but won less than 10% of the seats due to the First-Past-The-Post electoral system, however despite this they still have enough seats (and enough public support) for the other major 2 parties to form coalitions with them or make deals with the third party so to gain their support e.g. [[Conservative-Liberal Democrat coalition]] formed after the [[2010 general election]] and the [[Lib-Lab pact]] during Prime Minister James Callaghan's Minority [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour]] Government when Labour lost its 3 seat majority in 1977, the pact fell short of a full coalition.

Unlike a [[single-party system]] (or a two-party system), a multi-party system encourages the general [[constituency]] to form multiple distinct, officially recognized groups, generally called [[political party|political parties]]. Each party competes for votes from the [[suffrage|enfranchised]] constituents (those allowed to vote). A multi-party system prevents the leadership of a single party from controlling a single [[legislative]] chamber without challenge.

If the government includes an elected [[Congress]] or [[Parliament]] the parties may share power according to [[proportional representation]] or the [[first-past-the-post]] system.  In proportional representation, each party wins a number of seats proportional to the number of votes it receives. In first-past-the-post, the electorate is divided into a number of districts, each of which selects one person to fill one seat by a [[plurality voting|plurality of the vote]]. First-past-the-post is not conducive to a proliferation of parties, and naturally gravitates toward a [[two-party system]], in which only two parties have a real chance of electing their candidates to office. This gravitation is known as [[Duverger's law]]. Proportional representation, on the other hand, does not have this tendency, and allows multiple major parties to arise.

A two-party system requires voters to align themselves in large blocs, sometimes so large that they cannot agree on any overarching principles. Along this line of thought, some theories argue that this allows [[centrism|centrist]]s to gain control. On the other hand, if there are multiple major parties, each with less than a majority of the vote, the parties are strongly motivated to work together to form working governments. This also promotes centrism, as well as promoting coalition-building skills while discouraging polarization.

The two party system is caused by a political science theory called [[Duverger's law]]. As such, recent collation governments, such as that in the U.K. are two-party systems not multi-party systems. This is regardless of the number of parties in government.

==See also==
* [[Coalition]]
* [[Polarized pluralism]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Multi-Party System}}
[[Category:Forms of government]]
[[Category:Political systems]]
[[Category:Political party systems]]
[[Category:Elections]]

[[ar:نظام متعدد الأحزاب]]
[[ca:Sistema multipartidista]]
[[da:Flerpartisystem]]
[[de:Mehrparteiensystem]]
[[el:Πολυκομματισμός]]
[[es:Sistema multipartidista]]
[[eo:Multpartia sistemo]]
[[fr:Multipartisme]]
[[gl:Pluripartidismo]]
[[ko:다당제]]
[[hr:Višestranački sustav]]
[[it:Pluralismo dei partiti]]
[[he:מערכת רב-מפלגתית]]
[[kk:Көппартиялы жүйе]]
[[la:Systema polycommaticum]]
[[nl:Meerpartijenstelsel]]
[[ja:複数政党制]]
[[no:Flerpartisystem]]
[[pl:System wielopartyjny]]
[[pt:Pluripartidarismo]]
[[ru:Многопартийная система]]
[[sr:Вишепартијски систем]]
[[sh:Višepartijski sistem]]
[[fi:Monipuoluejärjestelmä]]
[[sv:Flerpartisystem]]
[[tr:Çok partili sistem]]
[[uk:Багатопартійна система]]
[[vi:Hệ thống đa đảng]]
[[zh:多黨制]]</text>
      <sha1>8c142ov1ec8sme1tkedahvgf6d6rruw</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
