<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Nasserism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3006762</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521557634</id>
      <parentid>520943200</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-05T20:05:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cattus</username>
        <id>543047</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>removed [[Category:History of Egypt]]; added [[Category:20th century in Egypt]] using [[WP:HC|HotCat]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11632">{{Infobox Political Party |
party_name = Nasserism |
colorcode = #000000 |
party_logo = [[File:Eagle of Saladin (green scroll).GIF|200px|The Eagle of Saladin, which Nasser adopted as a symbol of Arab Nationalism]] |
leader = [[Gamal Abdel Nasser]] |
foundation = |
ideology = [[Arab nationalism]],&lt;br&gt;[[Pan-Arabism]],&lt;br&gt;[[Arab socialism]] |
headquarters = |
international = |
website = |
}}
{{Life in the Arab League}}

'''Nasserism''' is a [[Left-wing politics|leftist]] [[Arab nationalism|Arab nationalist]] [[political ideology]] based on the thinking of [[Gamal Abdel Nasser]], one of the two principal leaders of the [[Egyptian Revolution of 1952]], and [[Egypt]]'s second [[President of Egypt|President]]. Spanning the domestic and international spheres, it combines elements of [[Arab socialism]], [[republicanism]], [[nationalism]], [[anti-imperialism]], and [[Non-Aligned Movement|international non-alignment]]. In the 1950s and 1960s, Nasserism was amongst the most potent political ideologies in the [[Arab World]]. This was especially true following the [[Suez Crisis]] of 1956 (known in Egypt as the ''Tripartite Aggression''), the political outcome of which was seen as a validation of Nasserism, and a tremendous defeat for Western imperial powers. During the [[Cold War]], its influence was also felt in other parts of [[Africa]], and the [[Developing country|Developing World]], particularly with regard to anti-imperialism, and non-alignment.

The scale of the Arab defeat in the [[Six Day War]] of 1967 severely damaged the standing of Nasser, and the ideology associated with him. Though it survived Nasser's death in 1970, certain important tenets of Nasserism were revised or abandoned totally by his successor as Egyptian President, [[Anwar El-Sadat]], during what he termed the '[[Corrective Revolution]]', and later his ''[[Infitah]]'' economic policies. Under the three decade rule of Sadat's successor, [[Hosni Mubarak]], most of the remaining socialist infrastructure of Egypt was replaced by [[neo-liberalism|neo-liberal]] policies strongly at odds with Nasserist principles. In the international arena, Mubarak departed almost entirely from traditional Egyptian policy, becoming a steadfast ally of both the [[United States|U.S. government]], and [[Israel]], the latter still viewed by most Egyptians with enmity and distrust, derived largely from the five wars that Egypt fought against Israel between 1948 and 1973.

During Nasser's lifetime, Nasserist groups were encouraged and often supported financially by Egypt, to the extent that many became seen as willing agents of the Egyptian government in its efforts to spread revolutionary nationalism in the Arab World. In the 1970s, as a younger generation of Arab revolutionaries came to the fore, Nasserism outside of Egypt metamorphosed into other Arab nationalist, and [[pan-Arabism|pan-Arabist]] movements, including component groups of the [[Lebanese National Movement]] during the [[Lebanese Civil War]].

Nasserism continues to have significant resonance throughout the Arab World to this day, and informs much of the public dialogue on politics in Egypt, and the wider region. Prominent Nasserist [[Hamdeen Sabahi]] competed in the first round of the [[Egyptian presidential election, 2012|2012 Egyptian Presidential election]], and only narrowly avoided securing a position in the run-off against eventual winner [[Mohammed Morsi]].

==Ideology==
Nasserism is an [[Arab nationalist]] and [[pan-Arab]] ideology, combined with a vaguely defined socialism, often distinguished from [[Eastern bloc]] or [[Western culture|Western]] socialist thought by the label '[[Arab socialism]]'. Though opposed ideologically to Western [[capitalism]], Arab socialism also developed as a rejection of [[communism]], which was seen as incompatible with Arab traditions, and the religious underpinnings of Arab society. As a consequence, Nasserists from the 1950s to the 1980s sought to prevent the rise of communism in the [[Arab World]], and advocated harsh penalties for individuals and organizations identified as attempting to spread communism within the region.

Though mindful of the [[Islamic]] and [[Christian]] heritage of the [[Arab World]], as with [[Ba'athism]], Nasserism is largely a [[secular]] ideology.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Sheikh|2003|p=34}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Shehadi|Mills|1988|p=265}}&lt;/ref&gt; Just as with other manifestations of Arab nationalism, this led to direct conflict with Islamic orientated Arab political movements from the 1950s onwards, particularly the [[Muslim Brotherhood]]. Nasserists espouse an end to Western interference in Arab affairs, [[Developing World]] solidarity, [[Non-Aligned Movement|international non-alignment]], [[modernisation]], and [[industrialisation]]. Nasser himself was opposed vehemently to Western [[imperialism]], sharing the commonly held Arab view that [[Zionism]] was an extension of European [[colonialism]] on Arab soil.

In world politics, Nasser's Egypt, along with [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]] under [[Josip Broz Tito]], and India under [[Jawaharlal Nehru]], was a major proponent of the [[Non-Aligned Movement]], which advocated developing countries remaining outside of the influence of the [[superpower]] blocs. However, notwithstanding this policy, and government suppression of [[communist]] organisations within Egypt, Egypt's deteriorating relations with Western powers, particularly following the [[Suez Crisis|Tripartite Aggression]] of 1956, made Egypt heavily dependent on military and civil assistance from the Soviet Union. The same was true for other revolutionary Arab governments which, although repressive of communism within Arab borders, entered into strong longstanding relationships with communist states outside of the Arab World. The Egyptian-Soviet alliance continued well into the presidency of Nasser's successor as [[President of Egypt|president]], [[Anwar El Sadat]], especially with regard to the [[Arab-Israeli Conflict]]. 
[[File:Gamal-002.jpg|thumb|Nasser and Soviet leader [[Nikita Khrushchev]] in May 1964]]

==Today==

Nasserism remains a political force throughout the [[Arab World]], but in a markedly different manner than in its heyday. Whereas in the 1950s and 60s Nasserism existed as a revolutionary and dynamic movement with definite political and social goals, by the 1980s it had become a much less pronounced and distinct ideology. Today, many more Arabs are informed by Nasserism in a general sense than actually espouse its specific ideals and objectives. In terms of political organisations within Egypt itself, during the presidency of former Egyptian President [[Hosni Mubarak]], Nasserism's scope was confined generally to writers, [[intellectual]]s, and minor opposition parties. Nasserist movements were largely overshadowed by Islamic political organisations, especially the [[Muslim Brotherhood]]. This was a part of an overall trend within Egypt and the Arab World of [[Arab nationalism]] being overshadowed, and even eclipsed, by [[political Islam]]. In Egypt, the [[Nasserist Party]] styles itself as the successor to Nasser and his [[Arab Socialist Union (Egypt)|Arab Socialist Union]], as does its offshoot,  the [[Dignity Party (Egypt)|Karama Party]] of [[Hamdeen Sabahi]]. However, as with all opposition parties in Egypt, their activities was severely limited by the Mubarak regime prior to the [[Egyptian Revolution of 2011]].

Whilst Nasser governed Egypt through a strictly [[authoritarian]] [[one-party system]], with extreme limits on any form of political dissent, present-day Nasserists stress their support for [[democracy]], explaining Nasser's autocratic excesses as necessary to implement his revolutionary policies.

==Influence outside of the Arab World==
[[File:Nasser's Three Circles Theory.jpg|thumb|According to Nasser's Three Circles Theory, the mission of the Egyptian Revolution had three spheres: the Arab World, Africa, and the Muslim world]]

Despite being a quintessentially Arab ideology, Nasserism influenced, to a degree, left-wing movements in other parts of the Developing World, particularly [[Sub-Saharan Africa]], and [[Latin America]]. Under Nasser, the Egyptian government gave support, both moral and material, to Sub-Saharan liberation movements fighting European imperialism. [[Nelson Mandela]], the former [[President of South Africa|South African President]], and Leader of the [[African National Congress]], remarked that this support was crucial in helping sustain the morale of such movements, including in South Africa. Similar sentiments have been expressed by [[Fidel Castro]], the former [[President of Cuba|Cuban President]], with regard to the [[Cuban Revolution]], and Cuba's later [[Bay of Pigs Invasion|adversities with the U.S. Government]]. Both men stated that Egypt's resistance under Nasser against the [[Suez Crisis|joint British, French, and Israeli invasion of Egypt in 1956]] proved to be inspirational for their own movements.

In the present day, [[Hugo Chavez]], President of [[Venezuela]], and leader of the self-styled '[[Bolivarian Revolution]]', has cited Nasserism as a direct influence on his own political thinking, stating: &quot;Someone talked to me about his pessimism regarding the future of Arab nationalism. I told him that I was optimistic, because the ideas of Nasser are still alive. Nasser was one of the greatest people of Arab history. To say the least, I am a Nasserist, ever since I was a young soldier.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.memritv.org/clip/en/1220.htm President of Venezuela Hugo Chavez] – MEMRI&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.memritv.org/clip_transcript/en/1220.htm MEMRI.tv]&lt;/ref&gt;

Left-wing British politician [[George Galloway]] has referred to Gamal Abdel Nasser as &quot;one of the greatest men of the 20th Century&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;George Galloway (2005). ''I'm Not the Only One''&lt;/ref&gt; and has called repeatedly for Arab governments to embrace the tenets of Nasserism in the 21st Century.

==See also==
*[[Gamal Abdel Nasser]]
*[[Arab nationalism]]
*[[Pan-Arabism]]
*[[Arab socialism]]
*[[Egyptian Revolution of 1952]]
*[[Ba'athism]]

==Footnotes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite book|title=Lebanon: a history of conflict and consensus|last1=Shehadi|first1=Nadim|last2=Mills|first2=Dana Haffar|year=1988|publisher=I.B.Tauris|isbn=978-1-85043-119-0|ref=CITEREFShehadiMills1988}}
*{{cite book|title=The new politics of Islam: pan-Islamic foreign policy in a world of states|first=Naveed S.|last=Sheikh|publisher=Routledge|year=2003|isbn=978-0-7007-1592-3|ref=CITEREFSheikh2003}}
*{{cite book|title=Arab nationalism: a history : nation and state in the Arab world|last=Choueiri|first=Youssef M.|publisher=Wiley-Blackwell|year=2000|isbn=978-0-631-21729-9|ref=CITEREFChoueiri2000}}
*{{cite journal|title=Nasser and Nasserism|last=Mansfield|first=Peter|journal=International Journal|volume=28|issue=4|year=1973|pages=pp. 670–688|publisher=Canadian International Council|ref=CITEREFMansfield1973}}
*{{cite journal|title=On Nasser and His Legacy|last=Ajami|first=Fouad|journal=Journal of Peace Research|volume=11|issue=1|year=1974|pages=pp. 41–49|publisher=Sage Publications, Ltd.|ref=CITEREFAjami1974}}

[[Category:Arab nationalism]]
[[Category:Arab socialism]]
[[Category:20th century in Egypt]]
[[Category:Political philosophy by politician]]
[[Category:Secularism in Egypt]]

[[ar:ناصرية (حركة)]]
[[da:Nasserisme]]
[[es:Nasserismo]]
[[fr:Nassérisme]]
[[hr:Naserizam]]
[[he:נאצריזם]]
[[nl:Nasserisme]]
[[no:Nasserisme]]
[[pl:Naseryzm]]
[[pt:Nasserismo]]
[[fi:Nasserismi]]
[[sv:Nasserism]]
[[tr:Nasırcılık]]</text>
      <sha1>3n8fddf6f6kt4ihre92j60fbwsl7wbs</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
