<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>National language</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1458526</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521093443</id>
      <parentid>520939040</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T19:03:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>A12n</username>
        <id>1863503</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Official versus national languages */  African usage</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23230">{{Multiple issues
 | date=March 2009
 | refimprove=May 2007
 | globalize=December 2006
 | expert=Languages
}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2012}}
A '''national language''' is a [[language]] (or [[variety (linguistics)|language variant]], i.e. [[dialect]]) which has some connection—''de facto'' or ''[[de jure]]''—with a people and perhaps by extension the territory they occupy. The term is used variously. A national language may for instance represent the [[national identity]] of a nation or country. National language may alternatively be a designation given to one or more languages spoken as first languages in the territory of a country.

C.M.B. bann, with particular reference to Africa, suggests that there are &quot;four quite distinctive meanings&quot; for national language in a polity:&lt;ref&gt;Brann, C.M.B. 1994. &quot;The National Language Question: Concepts and Terminology.&quot; ''Logos'' [University of Namibia, Windhoek] Vol 14: 125–134&lt;/ref&gt;
*&quot;Territorial language&quot; (''chthonolect'', sometimes known as ''chtonolect''&lt;ref&gt;Wolff, H. Ekkehard &quot;African Languages: An Introduction Ch./Art: Language and Society p. 321 pub. Cambride University Press 2000&lt;/ref&gt;) of a particular people
*&quot;[[Regional language]]&quot; (''choralect'')
*&quot;Language-in-common or community language&quot; (''demolect'') used throughout a country
*&quot;Central language&quot; (''politolect'') used by government and perhaps having a symbolic value.
The last seems often to be given the title &quot;[[official language]].&quot; 

[[Standard language]]s, such as [[Standard German]], [[Standard French]], and [[Standard Spanish]], may serve as national (language-in-common), regional, and international languages.

==Official versus national languages==
&quot;National language&quot; and &quot;[[official language]]&quot; are best understood as two concepts or legal categories with ranges of meaning that may coincide, or may be intentionally separate. Obviously a [[stateless nation]] is not in the position to legislate an [[official language]], but their language may be considered a national language.

Some languages may be recognized popularly as &quot;national languages,&quot; while others may enjoy a high degree of official recognition. Some examples of national languages that are not official languages include [[Cherokee language|Cherokee]], and [[Navajo language|Navajo]] (and other living [[Native American languages]]).{{cn|date=October 2012}}

In many African countries, some or all indigenous [[African languages]] are legally recognized as &quot;national languages&quot; with &quot;official language&quot; status being given to the former colonial language (English, French, Portuguese, or Spanish).

Certain languages may enjoy government recognition or even status as [[official languages]] in some countries while not in others.

==National and official languages==
===Algeria===
[[Berber_languages|Berber]] is a national language in [[Algeria]].

===Andorra===
[[Andorra]]'s national language is [[Catalan language|Catalan]], however the Catalan language is a [[regional language]] in Spain ([[Catalonia]], Valencian Community, [[Balearic Islands]], the Catalan-Aragonese borderlands known as [[La Franja]] and the Murcian municipality of [[El Carche]]), France ([[Pyrénées Orientales]]) and in Italy ([[Alghero]]).

===Bulgaria===
[[Bulgarian language]] is the national language in [[Bulgaria]].

===Canada===
{{main|Nationalisms in Canada|Bilingualism in Canada|Languages of Canada}}
[[Canada]]'s official languages since the [[Official Languages Act of 1969]] are [[English language|English]] ([[Canadian English]]) and [[French language|French]] ([[Canadian French]]).  Depending on one's views of what constitue a &quot;nation&quot; these two langaues may be consided two equal national langues of a nation called &quot;Canada&quot;, or the national langauges of two nations within one state, [[English Canada]] and [[French Canada]].

[[Quebec nationalists]] consider [[Quebec French]] the national language of the Quebec nation. 

Besides this there many [[Aboriginal peoples of Canada|Aboriginal languages of Canada]] which are the national langauges of one or more of Canada'a [[First Nations]] groups (formerly &quot;Indians&quot;), [[Inuit]] (formerly &quot;Eskimos&quot;), and [[Metis people (Canada)|Metis]] (mixed First Nations-European people).  Notably the [[Cree language]] is spoken (with variations) from Alberta to Labrador.

=== Greater China ===
:''See also: [[Standard Chinese]] and [[History of Mandarin]].''
In China, plenty of [[Chinese spoken languages|spoken variants]] exist in different parts of the country. In ancient times, several local dialects were chosen as the official spoken language, such as the dialects from [[Hangzhou]], [[Nanjing]], etc.

After the [[Xinhai Revolution]] in 1911, the [[Kuomintang]] (Chinese nationalists) founded the [[Republic of China]] (ROC). In order to promote a sense of national unity and enhance the efficiency of communications within the nation, the ROC decided to designate a national language. The [[Beijing dialect]] of [[Mandarin Chinese|Mandarin]] and [[Standard Cantonese|Guangzhou dialect]] of [[Cantonese language|Cantonese]] were the most popular options. Ultimately the Beijing dialect was chosen as the national language and given the name 國語 in Chinese ([[Pinyin]]: Guóyǔ, ''lit.'' national language, commonly known as &quot;Standard Chinese&quot; in English). In the beginning, there were attempts to introduce elements from other Chinese spoken variants into the national language, in addition to those existing in the Beijing dialect, but this was deemed too difficult and was abandoned in 1924. Since then, the Beijing dialect became the major source of standard national pronunciation, due to its prestigious status in the preceding [[Qing Dynasty]]. Elements from other dialects exist in the standard language.

After the [[Chinese Civil War]] in 1949, the [[Chinese Communist Party]] established the People's Republic of China (PRC) in [[mainland China]]. The [[Kuomintang]] regime of the [[Republic of China]] retreated to the island of [[Taiwan]] and maintained the same policy. Similarly, the People's Republic of China, which administers [[mainland China]], continued the effort and renamed the national language, largely based on the Beijing dialect, as 普通话 (Pinyin: pǔtōnghuà, ''lit.'' common speech).&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
|url=http://www.chinatoday.com/general/a.htm#LANGU
|title=General Information of the People's Republic of China (PRC): Languages
|publisher=chinatoday.com
|accessdate=2008-04-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Finland===
[[Finland]] has two national languages: namely the [[Finnish language]] and the [[Swedish language]] according to the [[Constitution of Finland]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
|url=http://www.servat.unibe.ch/icl/fi00000_.html
|title=Finland – Constitution
}}, Section 17. [http://www.servat.unibe.ch/icl/ International Constitutional Law] website.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=CIAFinland /&gt; The Language Act details the use of them by public authorities.&lt;ref&gt;Language Act : Unofficial Translation. Ministry of Justice. (PDF) Retrieved 2009-11-06.&lt;/ref&gt; However, there is an aboriginal nation Sami and another group Romani that have their languages mentioned as legal to be maintained and developed by such groups. The Sami have partial right to use [[Sami languages]] in official situations according to other laws.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.finlex.fi/fi/laki/kaannokset/1995/en19951727.pdf Decree on the Sami Parliament] FINLEX. Access date: 3 July.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Swedish language]] (6% of the people) is a valid language everywhere in Finland, whereas the [[Finnish language]] (92% of the people) is most widely used, but the latter is not legally valid everywhere.&lt;ref name=CIAFinland&gt;{{Citation
|url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/fi.html#People
|title=Sweden: People
|publisher=CIA World Factbook
|year=1994
|month=Nov
|author=Alfredson, Bb; Annerstedt, L
|volume=20
|issue=5
|pages=964–74
|issn=0309-2402
|pmid=7745191
|journal=Journal of advanced nursing
|format= – &lt;sup&gt;[http://scholar.google.co.uk/scholar?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;q=intitle%3ASweden%3A+People&amp;as_publication=Journal+of+advanced+nursing&amp;as_ylo=1994&amp;as_yhi=1994&amp;btnG=Search Scholar search]&lt;/sup&gt;}} {{Dead link|date=April 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the large difference in the numbers of users, Swedish is not officially classified as a minority language but equal to Finnish. Both national languages are compulsory subjects in school (except for children with a third language as mother tongue) and a language test is a prerequisite for governmental offices where a university degree is required.

===India===
{{Main|Languages of India}}
Article 343 of the [[Constitution of India]] specifies that the Official language of [[India]] is [[Standard Hindi|Hindi]] in [[Devanagari]] script, with [[English language|English]] as an additional language for official work. Article 345 states that a state of India may officially adopt one or more [[languages of India|languages]] in use in the state or Hindi/English as the language or languages to be used for all or any of the official purposes of that state.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|url=http://rajbhasha.nic.in/GOLPContent.aspx?t=enconst
|title=Official Language related—Part 17 of the Constitution of
|publisher=Government of India
|accessdate=2007-11-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, as neither the Constitution nor any Indian law defines any national language, India has no national language. This was affirmed by the [[Gujarat High Court]] in 2009; while observing that a majority of the nation accept Hindi as a national language, speak Hindi and write Hindi in [[Devanagari]] script, the court opined that India officially does not have a national language .&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|url=http://articles.timesofindia.indiatimes.com/2010-01-25/india/28148512_1_national-language-official-language-hindi
|title=There's no national language in India: Gujarat High Court
|publisher=The Times of India
|accessdate=2012-03-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Lebanon===
In [[Lebanon]], the [[Arabic language]] is the &quot;official national&quot; language.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.servat.unibe.ch/icl/le00000_.html Constitution of Lebanon {Adopted on: 21 September 1990}]. [http://www.servat.unibe.ch/icl/ Constitutional Documents]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Malta===
The [[Maltese language]] is the national language of Malta. It is also the official language of the island, together with English. Maltese only is recognised as &quot;national&quot; in Chapter 1 of the [[Laws of Malta]].

=== Namibia ===
{{Main|Languages of Namibia}}
Although English is the only nationwide official language in [[Namibia]], there are also 20 ''National languages'', which are each spoken by more or less sizeable portions of the population and are considered Namibia's cultural heritage. All national languages have the rights of a minority language and may even serve as a lingua franca in certain regions. Among Namibia's national languages are German, [[Afrikaans]], [[Oshiwambo]], [[Herero language|Otjiherero]], [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]], as well as the languages of the [[Himba]], [[Nama language|Nama]], [[San (people)|San]], [[Kavango]] and [[Damara (people)|Damara]].

=== Nigeria ===
Besides official English, Nigeria recognizes three 'majority', or national, languages. These are the big three, [[Hausa language|Hausa]], [[Igbo language|Igbo]], and [[Yoruba language|Yoruba]], each with some 20 million speakers or more.&lt;ref&gt;Article 55, [http://www.nigeria-law.org/ConstitutionOfTheFederalRepublicOfNigeria.htm Constitution of the Federal Republic of Nigeria : 1999].&lt;/ref&gt;

===Pakistan===
Article 251(1) of the [[Constitution of Pakistan#The Constitution of 1973 -- The Existing Constitution|1973 Constitution of Pakistan]], titled ''National language'', specifies: &quot;The National language of Pakistan is Urdu, and arrangements shall be made for its being used for official and other purposes within fifteen years from the commencing day.Although it has been declared as an official language , so far all the documentation, legislation,legal orders and every thing related on legal front is done in British English.Mostly the studies at the higher level i.e Masters , M.Phil and Phd. level is done in English.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
|url=http://www.pakistani.org/pakistan/constitution/
|title=The Constitution of the Islamic Republic of Pakistan
|chapter-url=http://www.pakistani.org/pakistan/constitution/part12.ch4.html
|chapter=PART XII (contd); Miscellaneous; Chapter 4. General
|date=14 August 1973
|accessdate=2008-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;[[National Language Authority]] is an organization established to make these arrangements since 1979.

===Philippines===
The 1973 [[Constitution of the Philippines|Philippine constitution]] designated Pilipino (a [[Tagalog language|Tagalog]]-based language) and English as official languages, &quot;until otherwise provided by law&quot; and mandated development and formal adoption of a common national language to be known as [[Filipino language|Filipino]].

The 1987 constitution designated the [[Filipino language]], which is based on Tagalog with the inclusion of terms from all recognized [[languages of the Philippines]], as the national language. It also designated both Filipino and English as the official languages for purposes of communication and instruction, and designated the regional languages as auxiliary official languages in the regions to serve as auxiliary media of instruction therein.

More than 170 [[Languages of the Philippines|languages]] are spoken in the [[Philippines]] and almost all of them belong to the [[Borneo–Philippines languages]] group of the [[Austronesian languages|Austronesian]] language family. In 2007, a six part series titled ''The Case of Ilokano as a National Language'' authored by Dr. Aurelio Solver Agcaoili of the University of Hawaii appeared in the  Culture, Essays, Lifestyle of Tawid News Magazine.&lt;ref&gt;Aurelio Solver Agcaoili, ''The Case of Ilokano as a National Language''; Part {{plainlink|http://www.aurelioagcaoili.com/2007/04/case-of-ilokano-as-national-language.html|1}}, {{plainlink|http://tawidnewsmag.com/2007/05/the-case-of-ilokano-as-a-national-language-part-2/|2}}, {{plainlink|http://tawidnewsmag.com/2007/05/the-case-of-ilokano-as-a-national-language-part-3|3}}, {{plainlink|http://tawidnewsmag.com/2007/05/the-case-of-ilokano-as-a-national-language-part-4|4}}, {{plainlink|http://tawidnewsmag.com/2007/05/the-case-of-ilokano-as-a-national-language-part-5|5}}, {{plainlink|http://tawidnewsmag.com/2007/05/the-case-of-ilokano-as-a-national-language-part-6|6}} (May 2007), [http://tawidnewsmag.com/ Tawid News Magasin]&lt;/ref&gt; {{as of|2008}}, leaders from the [[Ilocos|Ilocos region]] and other [[Ilocano people|Ilocano]]-dominated provinces were considering the possible declaration of [[Ilocano language]] as an official language in their provinces along with the national language to foster the continuity of their language and heritage.{{cn|date=October 2012}}

===Russia===
{{Main|Languages of Russia}}
The [[Russian language]] is the only official language of [[Russia]], but 27 other languages are considered official in different regions in Russia.

===Singapore===
[[Singapore]] has four official languages: [[English language|English]], [[Standard Chinese|Chinese]], [[Malay language|Malay]] and [[Tamil language|Tamil]]. Although English is the primary language of business and government and the main language used in education, Malay is designated as the national language. This is due to the geographical and historical ties to [[Malaysia]] as well as the recognition of ethnic [[Malays in Singapore|Malays]] (about 14% of the population) as the indigenous people of Singapore.

Traditionally, the [[lingua franca]] among the different ethnic groups in Singapore was [[Malay trade and creole languages|Bazaar Malay]], a Malay-based [[Malay-based creole languages|creole]]. Since independence, the government has been promoting English as the main language of Singapore. The bilingual education policy requires students to study only two languages: English and a &quot;mother tongue&quot; corresponding to the student's ethnicity. Malay is only offered to non-Malay students as an optional third language in secondary schools. As a result, English has displaced Bazaar Malay as the common language among Singaporeans. Therefore, despite the status of Malay as the national language, the majority of the population do not speak the language.

Notable official usage of Malay includes the national anthem [[Majulah Singapura]], and drill commands in the [[Singapore Armed Forces]].

=== South Africa ===
{{Main|Languages of South Africa}}
South Africa has 11 [[official language]]s. Namely: [[Afrikaans]], [[South African English|English]], [[Southern Ndebele language|Ndebele]], [[Northern Sotho]], [[Sotho language|Sotho]], [[Swazi language|Swazi]], [[Tswana language|Tswana]], [[Tsonga language|Tsonga]], [[Venda language|Venda]], [[Xhosa language|Xhosa]] and [[Zulu language|Zulu]]. [[South African Sign Language]] and [[Dutch Language|Dutch]] are distinct in South Africa though incompletely emerged national standard languages which also subsumes a cluster of semi-standardised dialects.

{{cquote|
[[Arabic]], [[German language|German]], [[Greek language|Greek]], [[Gujarati language|Gujarati]], [[Hebrew]], [[Hindi]], [[Khoi]], [[Nama language|Nama]], [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]], [[Khoisan languages|San]], [[Sanskrit]], [[Tamil language|Tamil]], [[Telugu language|Telugu]], [[Urdu]], [[South African Sign Language|Sign Language]] are all constitutionally recognised in South Africa.}}
::The above mentioned languages can be considered as ''minority [[Lingua franca]]s'' — none of these languages are of ''Official Language'' Status in the country.

=== Turkey ===
Ethnically, 10-18% of Turkey's population have got an Kurdish origin, and their language is [[Kurdish language|Kurdish]]. But the 95-98% of population can speak [[Turkish language|Turkish]] as native by their birth.{{cn|date=October 2012}} In that fact, Turkish is a national language of Turkey. Also there are many other ethnic origins like [[Circassians]], [[Arabians]] or [[Bosnians]], and they all can speak Turkish as native language.

=== United Kingdom ===
The [[English language|English]] is the ''de facto'' official language of the [[United Kingdom]] and is spoken monolingually by an estimated 95% of the [[United Kingdom|British]] population.{{citation needed|date=April 2012}} Interestingly, official regional languages exist without reference to a national language.&lt;ref&gt;In the United Kingdom, English is established by de facto usage. In [[Wales]], the [[Welsh Language Board|Bwrdd yr Iaith Gymraeg]] is legally tasked with ensuring that, &quot;in the conduct of public business and the administration of justice, the English and [[Welsh language]]s should be treated on a basis of equality&quot;. {{Citation|url=http://www.opsi.gov.uk/acts/acts1993/Ukpga_19930038_en_2.htm|title=Welsh Language Act 1993|publisher=Office of Public Sector Information|accessdate=3 September 2007}} [[Bòrd na Gàidhlig]] is tasked with &quot;securing the status of the [[Scottish Gaelic|Gaelic]] language as an [[official language]] of [[Scotland]] commanding equal respect to the English language&quot; {{Citation|url=http://www.opsi.gov.uk/legislation/scotland/acts2005/asp_20050007_en_1|title=Gaelic Language (Scotland) Act 2005|publisher=Office of Public Sector Information|accessdate=9 March 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== United States ===
{{main|Languages of the United States}}

In the United States, English is the national language only in an informal sense, by numbers and by historical and contemporary association. The [[United States Constitution]] does not explicitly declare any [[official language]], although the constitution is written in English, as is all federal legislation.

On 11 February 2009, [[United States House of Representatives|Representative]] [[Steve King]] (R-IA.) introduced House Bill H.R.997, to declare English as the official language of the United States. On 5 May 2009, [[United States Senate|Senator]] [[Jim Inhofe]] (R-OK) introduced Senate Bill S.991 as a companion bill.

On 26 February 2009, Representative Steve King (R-IA.) introduced House Bill H.R.1229, a bill to amend title 4, United States Code, to declare English as the official language of the Government of the United States, and for other purposes. On 6 May 2009, [[United States Senate|Senator]] [[Jim Inhofe]] (R-OK) introduced Bill S.992 as a companion bill.

On 10 March 2011, Representative Steve King (R-IA.) introduced House Bill H.R.997, a bill to amend title 4, United States Code, to declare English as the official language of the Government of the United States, and for other purposes. On 8 March 2011, [[United States Senate|Senator]] [[Jim Inhofe]] (R-OK) introduced Bill S.503 as a companion bill.

On 17 March 2011, Representative [[Peter T. King]] (R-NY.) introduced House Bill H.R.1164, a bill to amend title 4, United States Code, to declare English as the official language of the Government of the United States.

{{As of|2011|8}}, the last major actions on these bills were:&lt;ref&gt;[http://thomas.loc.gov/cgi-bin/thomas The library of Congress : Thomas].&lt;/ref&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! Bill || Last Major Action || Date
|-
| H.R.997 || Referred to the Subcommittee on the Constitution, Civil Rights, and Civil Liberties || 23 July 2009
|-
| S.991 || Referred to the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs || 6 May 2009
|-
| H.R.1229 || Referred to the Subcommittee on the Constitution, Civil Rights, and Civil Liberties || 19 August 2009
|-
| S.992 || Referred to the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs || 6 May 2009
|-
| H.R.997 || Referred to the Subcommittee on the Constitution. || 21 March 2011
|-
| H.R.1164 || Referred to the Subcommittee on the Constitution. || 1 June 2011
|}

Previous incarnations of these bills were co-written and supported by California millionaire [[Ron Unz]].{{citation needed|date=August 2011}}

=== Vietnam ===
In [[Vietnam]], the [[Vietnamese language]] is the national language.

== See also ==
* [[Ethnolect]]
* [[Indigenous language]]
* [[Language policy]]
* [[Regional language]]
* [[Standard language]]
* [[Official language]]
* [[Working language]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

{{Nationalism}}
{{Ethnicity}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:National Language}}
[[Category:Language varieties and styles]]
[[Category:Politics by issue]]
[[Category:Culture by region]]
[[Category:Linguistic rights]]
[[Category:Language policy]]

[[bg:Национален език]]
[[ca:Llengua nacional]]
[[ceb:Nasodnong pinulongan]]
[[cs:Národní jazyk]]
[[de:Nationalsprache]]
[[eo:Nacia lingvo]]
[[fr:Langue nationale]]
[[ko:국어]]
[[hi:राष्ट्रभाषा]]
[[id:Bahasa nasional]]
[[it:Lingua nazionale]]
[[kk:Ұлттық Тіл]]
[[sw:Lugha ya taifa]]
[[lt:Nacionalinė kalba]]
[[mk:Национален јазик]]
[[mr:राष्ट्रीय भाषा]]
[[ms:Bahasa kebangsaan]]
[[ja:国語]]
[[pt:Língua nacional]]
[[ro:Limbă națională]]
[[ru:Национальный язык]]
[[simple:National language]]
[[sk:Národný jazyk]]
[[fi:Kansalliskieli]]
[[tl:Wikang pambansa]]
[[uk:Національна мова]]
[[ur:قومی زبان]]
[[zh:國家語言]]</text>
      <sha1>implej0cvk9csqymwk5qpywajdfxrqz</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
