<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>National League of Cities</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2005288</id>
    <revision>
      <id>513242192</id>
      <parentid>511044022</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-17T20:12:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>75.150.69.161</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Changed founding date from 1976 to 1926.  It changed its name to the National League of Cities in 1964</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="5111">{{Advert|date=March 2009}}

The '''National League of Cities''' (NLC) is an [[United States|American]] [[advocacy organization]] representing 19,000 cities, towns, and villages, and encompassing 49 state municipal leagues.

NLC provides training to municipal officials, holds conferences, lobbies and provides assistance to cities in educational issues.

NLC is made up of six Centers: Research and Innovation; Federal Relations; Public Affairs and Member Relations; Enterprise Programs; Conferences, Education and Training; and the Institute for Youth, Education and Families.

==History==
The NLC was founded in 1926 when 10 state municipal leagues banded as the '''American Municipal Association'''. At this time, 37 state leagues existed, although only 21 were considered active.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nlc.org/state_municipal_leagues/ National League of Cities: State Municipal Leagues]&lt;/ref&gt; Over time, the organization's membership expanded to include individual cities of all sizes.&lt;ref&gt;Josh Fecht, [http://www.citymayors.com/orgs/natleague.html The National League of Cities speaks for more than 18,000 US communities], City Mayors website, accessed August 17, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

The current president of the NLC is [[Ted L. Ellis]], mayor of [[Bluffton, Indiana]].

Past presidents of the NLC have included:
* [[Detroit, MI|Detroit]] mayor [[Roman Gribbs]]
* [[Indianapolis, Indiana|Indianapolis]] Mayor [[Bart Peterson]]
* [[Anthony A. Williams]], mayor of [[Washington, DC]]
* [[Dick Lugar|Richard Lugar]], mayor of Indianapolis, Indiana
* [[Henry Cisneros]], mayor of [[San Antonio, Texas]]
* [[Dennis Archer]], mayor of [[Detroit, Michigan|Detroit]]
* [[William B. Hartsfield]], mayor of [[Atlanta]]
*James C. Hunt, former Mayor and City Councilman, Clarksburg, West Virginia

==Programs==
=== Federal lobbying ===
NLC lobbies Congress on multiple issues, including city [[infrastructure]], particularly [[transportation]]; supporting local energy efficiency and conservation efforts; strengthening and stabilizing the housing market; helping build stable families; supporting community safety; and reforming the country’s [[immigration]] system. NLC’s core lobbying principles include avoiding [[unfunded mandates]], preserving local authority and protecting the intergovernmental partnership.

=== Institute for Youth, Education and Families ===
The Institute for Youth, Education, and Families is an entity within NLC which assists municipal officials in providing services on behalf of the [[children]], [[youth]] and [[families]] in their communities. The YEF Institute offers resources in five core program areas, including [[early childhood]] success, [[education]] and afterschool, benefits for working families, youth participation in local government and child and youth safety.

=== Conferences ===

NLC hosts the annual Congress of Cities &amp; Exposition, at which municipal officials participate in workshops, general sessions, networking opportunities and leadership training seminars. NLC's other yearly conference is the Congressional City Conference, held each March in Washington, D.C. Thousands of municipal officials discuss NLC legislative priorities with [[Members of Congress]] and the Administration, share promising practices, discuss policy and participate in leadership training opportunities.

=== Leadership Training Institute ===

The Leadership Training Institute (LTI) is NLC’s primary learning and resource center for leadership development and training for our nation’s local municipal leaders, initiated in 1992. Programs provided by the Leadership Training Institute focus on strengthening leadership skills, along with exploring, sharing and recognizing innovative thinking and initiatives in community leadership.  LTI is led by the Leadership Training Council, made up of local elected officials and appointed annually by the NLC President.

== ''Nation's Cities Weekly'' ==

''Nation’s Cities Weekly'' is the official publication of the National League of Cities, highlighting Congressional activities, NLC research and NLC-sponsored conferences and workshops.

== NLC TV ==

[http://nlctv.org/ NLC TV] is NLC’s Internet-based TV web channel about and for cities. NLC TV features monthly newscasts showcasing the latest news about cities and the views of municipal officials. The channel also features web casts of events and seminars relevant to municipal officials.

==See also==
*[[Local government in the United States]]
*[[United States Conference of Mayors]]
*[[National Association of Counties]]
*[[International City/County Management Association]]
*[[National Governors Association]]
*[[National Conference of State Legislatures]]
*[[Council of State Governments]]
*[[Sister Cities International]]
*[[List of micro-regional organizations]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
*[http://www.nlc.org/ National League of Cities]
*[http://www.nlctv.org/ NLC TV]
*[http://www.nlc.org/iyef/ The Institute for Youth, Education, and Families]

[[Category:Civic and political organizations of the United States]]
[[Category:Councils of governments]]</text>
      <sha1>tm4subuvv1lkisbshqzk9yro2nwwwrl</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
