<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Non-partisan democracy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>384080</id>
    <revision>
      <id>518128823</id>
      <parentid>509967427</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-16T14:42:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>John of Reading</username>
        <id>11308236</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* National governments */Typo fixing, replaced: de-facto → de facto using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18548">{{refimprove|date=October 2011}}
{{POV|date=October 2011}}
{{Democracy}}
{{Party politics}}

'''Nonpartisan democracy''' (also '''no-party democracy''') is a system of [[Representative democracy|representative government]] or organization such that universal and periodic [[election]]s take place without reference to [[political party|political parties]].

==Overview==
Sometimes electioneering and even speaking about candidates may be discouraged, so as not to prejudice others' decisions or create a contentious atmosphere.  Nonpartisan democracies may possess indirect elections whereby an electorate are chosen who in turn vote for the representative(s). (This is sometimes known as a 2-tier election, such as an [[electoral college]].)  The system can work with a [[first past the post]] electoral system but is incompatible with (partisan) [[proportional representation]] systems other than [[Single Transferable Vote]].

A nonpartisan system differs from a [[single-party system]] in that the governing [[Political faction|faction]] in a single-party system identifies itself as a party, where membership might provide benefits not available to non-members. A single-party government often requires government officials to be members of the party, features a complex party [[hierarchy]] as a key institution of government, forces citizens to agree to a partisan ideology, and may enforce its control over the government by making all other parties illegal. Members of a nonpartisan government may not share any ideologies (though in voluntary organizations, they of course may). Various [[communist]] nations such as [[China]] or [[Cuba]] are single-party nations although the Members of Parliament are not elected as Party candidates. 

A direct democracy can be considered nonpartisan since citizens vote on laws themselves rather than electing representatives.  Direct democracy can be partisan, however, if factions are given rights or prerogatives that non-members do not have.

In many nations, the [[head of state]] is nonpartisan, even if the [[prime minister]] and [[parliament]] are chosen in partisan elections. The heads of state are expected to remain neutral with regards to partisan politics.

There are two basic types of nonpartisan governments - [[de facto]] and [[de jure]].  De facto nonpartisan governments are ones where no laws prevent the formation of political parties, but no parties exist.  Most of the de facto nonpartisan governments represent very small populations, such as in [[Niue]], [[Tuvalu]], and [[Palau]].   On the other hand, governments that outlaw political parties but do have elections are de jure nonpartisan systems.  Several de jure nonpartisan national governments are [[Persian Gulf]] states, such as [[Oman]] and [[Kuwait]].  The legislatures in these Gulf state nonpartisan governments typically have advisory capacity only (i.e. - They may comment on laws proposed by the executive branch, but are unable to create real laws themselves.), but are partially or entirely elected by citizens.

Unless there are legal [[restrictions on political parties]], factions within nonpartisan governments may evolve into political parties.  The United States of America initially did not have enfranchised political parties, but these evolved soon after independence.

==History==
The [[Athenian democracy|democracy of ancient Athens]] was a nonpartisan, direct democracy{{citation needed|being a representative democracy|date=December 2011}} where eligible citizens voted on laws themselves rather than electing representatives.

[[Historians]] have frequently interpreted [[Federalist No. 10]] to imply that the [[Founding Fathers]] of the [[United States]] intended the government to be nonpartisan. [[James Madison]] defined a faction as &quot;a number of citizens, whether amounting to a minority or majority of the whole, who are united and actuated by some common impulse of passion, or of interest, adverse to the rights of other citizens, or to the permanent and aggregate interests of the community.&quot; As political parties had interests which were adverse to the rights of citizens and to the general welfare of the nation, several Founding Fathers preferred a nonpartisan form of government.

The administration of [[George Washington]] and the first few sessions of the [[US Congress]] were nonpartisan. Factions within the early US government coalesced into the [[Federalist Party (United States)|Federalist]] and [[Democratic-Republican]] parties. The [[Era of Good Feeling]], when the Federalist party collapsed, leaving the Democratic-Republican party as the sole political faction, was the United States' only experience with a single-party system.

The [[Non-Partisan League]] was an influential [[socialist]] political movement in the [[United States]], especially in the Upper [[Midwest]], particularly during the 1910s and 1920s. It also contributed much to the ideology of the former [[Progressive Party of Canada]]. It went into decline and merged with the [[United States Democratic Party|Democratic Party]] of [[North Dakota]] in 1956. The [[Progressive Party of Canada]] and the [[United Farmers of Canada|United Farmers]] movement (which formed governments in the provinces of [[Alberta]], [[Manitoba]] and [[Ontario]]) also acted on a similar philosophy. In the case of the [[United Farmers of Ontario]] while in power (1919–1923) the administration of [[Ernest Drury]] suffered lots of infighting as the result of conflicting views.

Because of their nonpartisan ideology the Progressive Party of Canada refused to take the position of the [[official opposition]] after the [[Canadian general election, 1921|election of 1921]] when they came in second place. Four years later they lost that position and their rural supporters began to move to the Liberal Party and CCF.  Eventually the Progressive Party of Canada and the United Farmers movement faded into obscurity with most of their members joining the [[Liberal Party of Canada]] and the [[democratic socialist]], [[Co-operative Commonwealth Federation]] (CCF, or present day [[New Democratic Party]]).

==Structures==

===Elections===
In nonpartisan elections, each candidate for office is eligible based on her or his own merits rather than as a member of a political party. No political affiliation (if one exists) is shown on the ballot next to a candidate. Generally, the winner is chosen from a runoff election where the candidates are the top two vote-getters from a primary election.  In some elections, the candidates might be members of a national party, but do not run as party members for local office.

Louisiana uses a [[nonpartisan blanket primary]], also called a &quot;jungle primary&quot;, for state and local offices.  In this system, all candidates run against each other regardless of party affiliation during the primary, and then the two most popular candidates run against each other even if they are members of the same party.  This form of runoff election weakens political parties and transforms a partisan election into a partly nonpartisan election.  Once a candidate gets elected, the person maintains party affiliation and generally votes along party lines.  Louisiana is the only place that uses a nonpartisan blanket primary.

Nebraska uses a single nonpartisan primary for the [[Nebraska Legislature|State Legislature]] but not for other state and local races.

Nonpartisan elections are generally held for [[municipal]] and county offices, especially [[school board]], and are also common in the election of judges. In some nonpartisan elections, it is common knowledge which candidates are members of and backed by which parties; in others, parties are almost wholly uninvolved and voters make choices with little or no regard to partisan considerations.

While nonpartisan democracies can allow for a wide selection of candidates (especially within a no-nomination system whereby voters can choose any non-restricted person in their area), such systems are not incompatible with indirect elections (such as for large geographical areas), whereby delegates may be chosen who in turn elect the representatives.

===Appointments===
Even if a government's executive officer or legislature is partisan, appointments of cabinet members, judges, or directors of government agencies, may be nonpartisan.  The intent of appointing government officials in a nonpartisan manner is to insure the officers can perform their duties free from partisan politics, and are chosen in a fair manner that does not adversely affect a political party.  Twelve US states use the [[Missouri Plan]], and two use a variation of it, to choose judges in a nonpartisan manner.  Several countries with partisan parliaments use nonpartisan appointments to choose presidents.

===Legislatures===
In nonpartisan legislatures, there are no typically formal party alignments within the legislature; even if there are caucuses for specific issues. Alliances and causes with a nonpartisan body are often temporary and fluid since legislators who oppose each other on some issues may agree on other issues. Despite being nonpartisan, legislators typically have consistent and identifiable voting patterns. Decisions to investigate and enforce ethics violations by government officials are generally done on the basis of evidence instead of party affiliation. Committee chairs and other leaders within the legislature are often chosen for seniority and expertise, unlike the leaders in a partisan legislature who are often chosen because of loyalty to a party.

==Examples==

===National governments===
Very few national governments are completely nonpartisan, but nonpartisan political systems at the national level are not unheard of. Many national governments have nonpartisan offices even if their legislative branches are partisan.  [[Constitutional monarchies]] have nonpartisan monarchs as their head of state. [[Parliamentary republics]] generally have nonpartisan, figurehead presidents.

Nonpartisan governments are much more likely in countries with small populations. [[Nauru]], for example, has no political parties; its [[Parliament of Nauru|Parliament]] consists entirely in independent members of parliament or MPs, who form governing coalitions and opposition blocs through alliances of individuals.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dfat.gov.au/geo/nauru/nauru_brief.html &quot;Republic of Nauru country brief&quot;], Australian Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade&lt;/ref&gt; The same is true in [[Tuvalu]]. No political parties exist; &quot;MPs have very close links with their island constituencies and effort is directed towards balancing island representation in [[Cabinet of Tuvalu|Cabinet]]&quot;  Other nonpartisan island nations are [[Pitcairn]], [[Federated States of Micronesia|Micronesia]], [[Saint Helena]], and [[Palau]].  Some are de facto nonpartisan because no law forbids the formation of political parties, and the populations are small enough that factions are considered unnecessary.  Political allegiances depend mainly on family and island-related factors.

In [[Niue]], political parties have never played an important role. There is, at present, no political party, and candidates to elections therefore run as independents. The only party ever to have existed, the [[Niue People's Party]], disbanded in 2003.

The [[United Arab Emirates]] is a [[de jure]] nonpartisan semi-democratic state since all political parties were outlawed.  The [[Federal National Council]] (al-Majlis al-Watani al-Ittihadi) is the UAE’s parliamentary body and consists of 40 members, representing the Emirates, half appointed by the rulers of the constituent states and the other half elected to serve two-year terms, with only advisory tasks.

Political parties are illegal in the Gulf state of [[Kuwait]]. They have not been legalized since independence in 1961. Nonetheless, the constitution itself does not explicitly prohibit parties.  Candidates for election to the [[National Assembly of Kuwait]] stand in a personal capacity. In practice, however, several political groups act as de facto parties.

[[Oman]] does not allow political parties and only holds elections with expanding suffrage for a consultative assembly. Though Oman is developing into a constitutional monarchy, political parties are not yet allowed in Oman. The previously influential opposition movement, the [[Popular Front for the Liberation of Oman]], is dormant today.

A nonpartisan democracy might take root in other [[sovereign]] [[nations]], such as occurred in [[Uganda]] in 1986, whereby political parties were restricted by a constitutional referendum endorsed by the people of the country (this system did not have all of the features described above). During a subsequent [[Uganda multiparty referendum, 2005|referendum]] in 2005, over 92% of Ugandan citizens voted for the return of a multiple party system.

Until the mid-20th century, a Canadian politician's political affiliation was not shown on [[ballots]] at any level of government. The expectation was that citizens would vote according to the merit of the candidate, but in practice, party allegiance played an important role.  Beginning in 1974, the name of the candidate's political party was shown on the ballot.

=== Territorial governments ===
The territorial government of [[American Samoa]] is completely nonpartisan. It has 21 nonpartisan members elected by consensus to its [[American Samoa House of Representatives|Territorial House]] and 18 nonpartisan members elected to the [[American Samoa Senate|Territorial Senate]].  The [[List of governors of American Samoa|Governor]] and [[Lieutenant Governor of American Samoa|Lieutenant Governor]] are both nonpartisan offices.  However, its nonvoting member of the [[List of Delegates to the United States House of Representatives from American Samoa|U.S. House]] is a Democrat.

The British territory of [[Falkland Islands]] has a completely nonpartisan government in that no political parties operate on the islands.  All eight members of the [[Legislative Assembly of the Falkland Islands|Legislative Assembly]] are nonpartisan, as is the [[Chief Executive of the Falkland Islands|Chief Executive]] and the [[Governor of the Falkland Islands|Governor]].

[[Guernsey]] has a nonpartisan legislature.  The States of Guernsey, officially called the [[States of Guernsey|States of Deliberation]], consists of 45 People's Deputies, elected from multi- or single-member districts every four years.

Political parties played no official role in the [[Isle of Man]] before the 2006 elections and played a minor role in the 2006 elections.  At the 2001 election for the [[House of Keys]], the [[Manx Labour Party]] polled 17.3% of the vote and only 2 seats. The vast majority of seats at every election are won by independent candidates with no allegiance to any parties.

The head of the territory and head of government of Hong Kong, the Chief Executive, is required by law not to be member of any political party. There are political parties, but there is no legislation for political parties.

===State or provincial governments===
There are several examples of nonpartisan [[state (country subdivision)|state]] or [[province|provincial]] governments. The nonpartisan system is also used in many US states for the election of judges, district attorneys and other officials.

The [[Cantons of Switzerland|Swiss Cantons]] of [[Canton of Glarus|Glarus]] and [[Appenzell Innerrhoden]] are also nonpartisan, direct democracies; while they have a partisan parliament, all laws have to be passed by &quot;[[Landsgemeinde]]&quot;, an assembly of all citizens eligible to vote.

Twelve US states use the [[Missouri Plan]], and two use a variation of it, to choose judges in a nonpartisan manner.

The [[Canada|Canadian]] [[territory (country subdivision)|territories]] of the [[Northwest Territories]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.assembly.gov.nt.ca/_live/pages/wpPages/2009NewsReleases.aspx#april23
|title=MLAs Agree to Common Principles of Consensus Government
|date=23 April 2009
|accessdate=6 October 2009
}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Nunavut]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://open-site.org/Regional/North_America/Canada/Nunavut
|title=Premier of Nunavut - Hon. Paul Okalik
|accessdate=6 October 2009
}}&lt;/ref&gt; have nonpartisan democracies. The populace votes for individuals to represent it in the territorial assembly without reference to political parties. After the election, the assembly selects one of its number to form a government and act as [[premier (Canada)|premier]]. This system is in deference to the system of [[consensus government]] that predominates among the indigenous [[Inuit]] and other peoples of northern Canada.

The state of [[Nebraska]] in the [[United States]] has nonpartisan elections for its [[Nebraska Legislature|legislature]] because candidates are neither endorsed nor supported by political parties. However, its [[executive branch]] is elected on a partisan basis. It is the only state in the United States with a nonpartisan legislature.

Governors of Japanese prefectures are required by law not to be members of any political party.

===Municipal governments===
The municipal government of the City of [[Toronto]], [[Ontario]] ([[Canada]]) is the fifth largest government in the country, governing a population of more than 2.7 million. It consists of a nonpartisan, directly elected council.  The public may have a general idea of the candidates' political affiliations, but their parties have no official recognition or privilege in the functioning of City Council.  [[Councilors]] are free to vote on each motion individually, freeing them from [[party discipline]].

==See also==
*[[List of democracy and elections-related topics]]
*[[Consensus government]]
*[[Bahá'í administration]]
*[[Nonpartisan]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==References==
{{More footnotes|date=April 2009}}
* Abizadeh, Arash. &quot;[http://www.profs-polisci.mcgill.ca/abizadeh/Bahai-elections.htm Democratic Elections without Campaigns?] Normative Foundations of National Baha'i Elections.&quot; ''World Order'' (2005) 37.1: 7-49.
* Ware, Alan. ''Citizens, Parties and the State.'' Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1987.

==External links==
*[http://www.unicam.state.ne.us/learning/history.htm Nebraska Unicameral History]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Non-Partisan Democracy}}
[[Category:Elections]]
[[Category:Forms of government]]
[[Category:Democracy]]

[[es:Democracia sin partidos]]
[[fr:Démocratie non partisane]]
[[it:Democrazia apartitica]]
[[hu:Pártmentes demokrácia]]</text>
      <sha1>agbpjt71d0qitu124offvapj4jg350w</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
