<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Occidental College</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>22800</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521949117</id>
      <parentid>521827366</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-08T05:15:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>134.69.90.64</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Notable faculty */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="37097">{{Infobox university
 |name = Occidental College
 |native_name =
 |image_name = Seal-OccidentalCollege.png
 |image_size = 200px
 |caption =
 |latin_name =
 |motto = Occidens Proximus Orienti 
 |(&quot;The West is nearest the East&quot;)
 |established = April 20, 1887
 |closed =
 |type = [[Private university|Private]]
 |affiliation =
 |endowment = [[United States dollar|US$]] 342 million&lt;ref&gt;As of June 30, 2011. {{cite web | title = Occidental College| work = US News &amp; World Report | publisher = National Association of College and University Business Officers | url = http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/occidental-college-1249| format = URL | accessdate = February 12, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |chairman =
 |chancellor =
 |president = [[Jonathan Veitch]]
 |vice-president = Dennis Collins
 |dean = Jorge Gonzalez
 |director =
 |head_label = Chairman of the Board of Trustees
 |head = John Farmer
 |faculty = 183
 |staff =
 |students = 2,123
 |undergrad =
 |postgrad =
 |doctoral =
 |other =
 |city = [[Los Angeles, California|Los Angeles]]
 |state = [[California]]
 |province =
 |country = [[Higher education in the United States|United States]]
 |campus = [[urban area|Urban, Pastoral]]&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|120|acre|ha}}
 |former_names =
 |free_label =
 |free =
 |sports = 21 Varsity Teams
 |colors = [[Orange (color)|Orange]] &amp; [[Black (colour)|Black]] {{color box|#FFA500}}{{color box|black}}
 |colours =
 |nickname = [[Occidental Tigers|Tigers]]
 |mascot = [[Tiger|Oswald the Tiger]]
 |athletics = [[NCAA Division III]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Southern California Intercollegiate Athletic Conference]]
 |affiliations = [[Annapolis Group]]
 |website = [http://www.oxy.edu/ www.oxy.edu]
 |logo = [[File:OccidentalWordmark.png|210px]]
 |footnotes =
}}
[[File:Occidental College in the 1920's.jpg|right|thumb|250px|Occidental College in the 1920s]]

'''Occidental College''' is a [[Private university|private]], [[co-educational]] [[liberal arts]] college located in the historical [[Eagle Rock, Los Angeles|Eagle Rock]] neighborhood of [[Los Angeles, California]]. Founded in 1887 by clergy and members of the Presbyterian Church, Occidental College, or, &quot;Oxy&quot; as it is affectionately called by students and [[alumni]], is one of the oldest liberal arts colleges on the [[West Coast of the United States|West Coast.]] Although no longer formally affiliated with the Presbyterian Church, Occidental still retains the progressive and egalitarian values of its founders.

The [[Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching]] selected Occidental as a &quot;community engagement institution&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://classifications.carnegiefoundation.org/descriptions/community_engagement.php &quot;Community Engagement Elective Classification&quot;], ''http://classifications.carnegiefoundation.org'', retrieved 6-15-12&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://classifications.carnegiefoundation.org/lookup_listings/view_institution.php?unit_id=120254&amp;start_page=index.php&amp;clq=%7B &quot;Carnegie Foundation Classifications - Occidental College&quot;], ''http://classifications.carnegiefoundation.org'', retrieved 6-15-12&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
[[File:OccidentalColl-1904.jpg|left|thumb|250px|Highland Park campus, 1904.]]

===Origin===
Occidental College was founded on April 20, 1887, by a group of [[Presbyterian]] clergy, missionaries, and laymen, including [[James George Bell]]. The college’s first term began a year later with 27 men and 13 women students, and tuition of $50 a year. Initially located in [[Boyle Heights]], the college declined to move to an undeveloped area called &quot;Westwood&quot; and moved, instead, to a new campus in Los Angeles’ [[Highland Park, Los Angeles, California|Highland Park]] neighborhood in 1898. 

Despite a strong Presbyterian presence on its campus, Occidental began to diminish its ties to the church in 1910.  In 1912, the school began construction of a new campus located in Los Angeles’ Eagle Rock neighborhood. The Eagle Rock campus was to be designed by noted California Architect [[Myron Hunt]]. That same year, Occidental President [[John Willis Baer]] announced the trustees’ decision to convert Oxy into an all-men’s institution. However, students protested, and the idea was abandoned.

===Move to Eagle Rock===
Two weeks after [[Booker T. Washington]] came to visit Occidental, on March 27, 1914 — the school’s 25th anniversary — Swan, Fowler, and Johnson Halls were dedicated at its new Eagle Rock campus. The Eagle Rock campus covers over {{convert|120|acre|ha}}, much of which is undeveloped land on a hill known as “Mt. Fiji.” 

During World War I
in April 1917, the college formed an Army Corps to aid the war effort. The college opened its Hillside Theatre in 1925, and a student union in 1928. During [[World War II]], many students left Occidental to fight in the war. In July 1943, 53 students established a Navy [[V-12 Navy College Training Program|V-12]]&lt;ref name=&quot;occidentalv-12&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://alumni.oxy.edu/s/956/index.aspx?pgid=410&amp;gid=1 |title=Oxy Trivia |publisher=''http://alumni.oxy.edu'' |last= |first= |accessdate=September 28, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; unit on campus and left for active duty.

===1960-present===
In 1962, ''[[Time Magazine]]'' described Occidental as a little giant in a story about the college’s rise to national prominence.&lt;ref name=&quot;Little Giant&quot;&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,827489,00.html &quot;Little Giant&quot;] ''Time Magazine'', retrieved 6-13-2012&lt;/ref&gt; In 1969, the school opened its first two co-ed [[dormitories]], and two more followed a year later. On May 6, 1970, the faculty voted to suspend classes in the wake of the [[Kent State shootings]] and America’s invasion of Cambodia. Subsequently, Oxy students wrote 7,000 letters to Washington D.C., protesting U.S. involvement in the war in Southeast Asia.{{citation needed|date=June 2012}}

The era also inspired positive changes in administration in regards to ethnic minority rights. The college received grants designed to help equal the playing field for students traditionally neglected in higher education. This laid the foundation for a series of actions aiming to continue closing the access gap for minorities of virtually all categories in the decades to come, the most important of which was President [[John Brooks Slaughter]]'s institution of the college's &quot;mission statement,&quot; an organizational declaration around which the entire college would function and aspire to both academic excellence and equity.  The mission statement was written just 18 months after Slaughter was appointed President in 1988.&lt;ref name=&quot;Welcome to Multicultural U.&quot;&gt;[http://articles.latimes.com/1999/may/02/magazine/tm-33049/2 &quot;Welcome to Multicultural U.&quot;], pp.1-2, ''Los Angeles Times,'' Mithers, Caroline L. (1999), retrieved 6-11-2012&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Occidental College's Mission Statement&quot;&gt;[http://www.oxy.edu/x2990.xml &quot;Occidental College's Mission Statement&quot;], ''www.oxy.edu,'' retrieved 6-11-2012&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007, when ''[[U.S. News and World Report]]'' ranked Occidental College the 36th best liberal arts college in the country, tied with [[Bard College]] in New York and [[Whitman College]] in Washington, the magazine cited both ethnic and economic diversity as key achievements.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oxy Ranks High in Guides&quot;&gt;[http://www.oxy.edu/x2552.xml &quot;Oxy Ranks High in Guides&quot;], ''www.oxy.edu,'' retrieved 6-11-2012&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1979, Occidental installed ''Water Forms II'' (see [[#Notable faculty|image below]]), a kinetic fountain designed by professor George Baker. The fountain is a campus landmark and was featured prominently in the 1984 film ''[[Star Trek III: The Search for Spock]]''. During the [[1984 Summer Olympics|1984 Olympic Games]], some track events were held at Occidental’s Patterson Field. By 1986, for the first time since [[World War II]], women students outnumbered men. Today, the college is approximately 60 percent female and 40 percent male; roughly equivalent to the national average. On July 1, 2006, Susan Prager became Occidental's first female president. She then left her position in 2007 during the fall term.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 | title = A Brief History of Occidental College
 | url = http://www.oxy.edu/x3684.xml
 | work =
 | accessdate = 2007-08-02
}}&lt;/ref&gt; On July 1, 2009, [[Jonathan Veitch]], formerly dean of [[The New School]]'s [[Eugene Lang College]], became Occidental's 15th president, and the first to be a native [[Angeleno]].

==Campus==
[[File:Occidental Thorne Hall.jpg|left|thumb|250px|Thorne Hall]]
Architect [[Myron Hunt]], who also designed the [[Rose Bowl Stadium]], designed Oxy's original buildings in a Mediterranean style, with covered walkways and tile roofs. Currently, there are 12 on-campus residence halls. The three original buildings of the 1914 campus still stand today, although seismic concerns have limited them to classrooms and academic offices. Some buildings, such as the Hameetman Science Center (designed by [[Anshen &amp; Allen|Anshen + Allen]], 2003), deviates from the original architecture with its large glass windows and metal balconies (its lobby houses a large [[Foucault pendulum]]). Occidental's newest building, the 278 bed Rangeview Residence Hall, opened in January 2008 at a cost of a reported 38.8 million dollars and is the first residence hall built in 25 years.&lt;ref name=&quot;Upper Division Housing&quot;&gt;[http://prod.oxy.edu/residential-education-housing-services/residence-halls/upper-division-housing &quot;Upper Division Housing&quot;], ''www.oxy.edu,'' retrieved 6-15-2012&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:OxyThorne.jpg|thumb|Thorne Hall at Occidental College, used for assemblies/lectures]]
[[File:OxySamuelson.jpg|thumb|Samuelson, at Occidental College is more commonly known as &quot;the cooler&quot; where students and faculty may go enjoy a meal or a quick snack|left]]
[[File:OxyStudentCenter.jpg|thumbnail|This is the Occidental College balcony that leads to the Market Place dining hall and the on campus cafe called &quot;The Green Bean&quot;|left]]






































==Academics, resources==
There are 31 majors offered on campus and there is a 10:1 student-faculty ratio. The average class size is 19 students and most students take four class per semester. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Occidental College|title=By the Numbers|url=http://www.oxy.edu/our-story/numbers}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

{{col-begin}}
{{col-3}}
'''Student profile'''
* 2,123 students from 43 states, the District of Columbia and 25 foreign countries
* 56% women, 44% men
* 5% African American
* 12% Asian American
* 59% Caucasian
* 4% international
* 8% Latino/a
* .5% Native American or Alaska Native
* 0.1% Native Hawaiian or Pacific Islander
* 10% two or more races
* 3.7% race or ethnicity unknown

{{col-3}}
'''Faculty profile'''
* 183 full-time faculty
* 6.5% African American
* 11%  Asian American
* 10% Latino/a
* 48% women, 52% men&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oxy.edu/our-story/numbers &quot;By The Numbers&quot;], ''www.oxy.edu,'' retrieved 6-15-2012&lt;/ref&gt;

{{col-3}}
[[File:Occidental quad.jpg|right|thumb|325px|The academic quad at night]]
{{col-end}}

===Core program===
Divided in three parts, the Core Program was designed by the faculty of Occidental to unify and enhance the liberal arts education offered by the school. The Core Program requires students to achieve the following:
# complete two first-year writing seminars; one course in the fall, another in the spring (called [http://www.oxy.edu/core-program/courses CSPs]);
# complete a set number of courses in 3 of 6 available geographical areas worth at least 12 units: Africa and the Middle East, South, Central and East Asia, Europe, Latin America, the United States, Intercultural
# complete a 102-level language course or be exempt through 4 ways
# complete a course concerning the the Pre-1800s era and one focused on the fine arts
# complete three math and science courses; one has to be a lab-science
# pass a senior-year comprehensive examination within the student’s chosen major. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Occidental College|title=Core Program|url=http://www.oxy.edu/core-program/requirements|accessdate=2 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

First-year seminars (eight course hours in total) are the centerpiece of the Core Program. Students are given a variety of class choices to fulfill the seminar requirement, and to satisfy the first-year writing requirement. While the classes range in topic, each is based on a curriculum of cultural studies. The classes are designed to expose students to the rigor of college academics and to the four principles of the college mission—Excellence, Equity, Community, and Service.

The Core Program’s emphasis on global literacy requires students to take a minimum of three courses that touch on at least three of the following geographical areas: Africa and the Middle East; Asia and the Pacific; Europe; Latin America; the United States; and Intercultural. Students are also required to demonstrate proficiency in writing and in a foreign language and take courses in the fine arts and in the sciences, mathematics, or other courses that address formal methods of reasoning.

The final portion of the Core Program requires students to pass a senior comprehensive examination in their chosen field. Comprehensive examinations may include seminars, creative projects, fieldwork, oral exams, theses, or field research projects.

===Majors===
Students can choose from a wide range of majors, double major, or major and minor at Occidental.
Departments offered are:

*American Studies
*Art History &amp; Visual Arts
*Biochemistry
*Biology
*Chemistry
*Cognitive Science
*Critical Theory &amp; Social Justice
*Diplomacy &amp; World Affairs
*Economics
*English &amp; Comparative Literary Studies
*Geology
*German, Russian &amp; Classical Studies
*Group Language
*History
*Kinesiology
*Latino/a and Latin American Studies
*Mathematics
*Media Arts &amp; Culture
*Music
*Philosophy
*Physics
*Politics
*Psychology
*Religious Studies
*Sociology
*Spanish &amp; French Studies
*Theater
*Urban &amp; Environmental Policy &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Occidental College|title=Programs &amp; Majors|url=http://www.oxy.edu/academics/programs-majors|accessdate=2 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Exchange and Cooperative Joint Degree Programs==

===California Institute of Technology (Caltech) and Columbia University===
Students at Occidental can take courses at the [[California Institute of Technology]] in nearby [[Pasadena, California|Pasadena]] free of charge. In addition, a 3-2 engineering program allows qualified students the opportunity to study at Occidental for three years, completing their undergraduate experience with an additional two years either at [[Caltech]] or [[Columbia University]]. At the end of the five years, the student receives two degrees, a Bachelor of Arts in the Combined Plan from Occidental and a Bachelor of Science in the selected field of engineering from the engineering school.

===Art Center College of Design===
Art majors at Occidental College can take courses at the [[Art Center College of Design]] in Pasadena, one of the country’s top-ranked art schools. The program is not open to first-year students, but as with the Caltech exchange program, students receive full course credit. No additional tuition payments are required.

===Columbia University School of Law===
With a competitive GPA and LSAT scores, [[Columbia Law School]] admits students upon completion of their junior year at Occidental into its Accelerated Interdisciplinary Program in Legal Education. Admittance to the program enables students to earn a bachelor’s degree from Occidental and a law degree from Columbia in six years.

===Keck Graduate Institute===
Students who are interested in [[biotechnology]] and who become a [[biochemistry]] major maintaining a 3.2 GPA in the necessary courses, will be guaranteed admission to the Keck master’s in bioscience program. The [[Keck Graduate Institute]] is part of the [[Claremont Colleges]] consortium.

==Reputation and rankings==
In ''[[U.S. News and World Report]]'''s 2012 rankings of American liberal arts colleges, Occidental is tied with Connecticut College and Trinity College for 37th among liberal arts colleges.  Since 1908, Occidental has graduated 10 [[Rhodes Scholars]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oxy.edu/x2363.xml|archivedate=April 15, 2011|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5xyIrwewh|title=List of National Award Winners|publisher=oxy.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 2007 ''[[Princeton Review]]'' describes Occidental as having a “rising star quality” and notes that Occidental’s professors have been called “top quality.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | title = Reviews of Occidental College
 | url = http://www.oxy.edu/x2360.xml
 | work = [[The Princeton Review]]
 | accessdate = 2007-08-02
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 2006 edition of ''America's Best Value Colleges'' by the Princeton Review noted that the college “is committed to recruiting top students regardless of their financial background.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | title = Reviews of Occidental College
 | url = http://www.oxy.edu/x2360.xml
 | work = America's Best Value Colleges
 | accessdate = 2007-08-02
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''College Prowler'' says that people “look at Occidental degrees very highly,” but that Occidental often does not receive the attention it deserves.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | title = Reviews of Occidental College
 | url = http://www.oxy.edu/x2360.xml
 | work = The College Prowler
 | accessdate = 2007-08-02
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Athletics==
{{Main|Occidental Tigers}}
[[File:Johnson Student Center and Freeman College Union.jpg|right|thumb|250px|Johnson Student Center and Freeman College Union]]
Occidental is one of the five schools that founded the Southern California Intercollegiate Athletic Conference (SCIAC) in 1915 and is currently a member of the SCIAC and [[NCAA Division III]]. Occidental features 21 varsity sports teams and a program of club sports and intramural competition. Approximately 25 percent of the student body participates in a varsity sports program.&lt;ref name=&quot;Occidental College Athletics&quot;&gt;{{cite news
 | title = Occidental College Athletics
 | url = http://www.oxy.edu/Athletics.xml
 | work =
 | accessdate = 2007-08-02
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 2006–2007 athletic season, the Tiger’s [[Cross country running|cross country]], [[American football]] and [[basketball]] teams were [[Southern California Intercollegiate Athletic Conference]] champions. The school’s Blackshirts [[Rugby union]] team was also league champion for the first time in five years. In 2011, Jeremy Castro ('99) and Patrick Guthrie ('86) steered the squad to a NSCRO final falling to [[Longwood University]] 36-27 in Virginia Beach, VA. In addition the college boasts a competitive and growing elite dance team that also performs at every home football and basketball game.&lt;ref name=&quot;Occidental College Athletics&quot;/&gt;

In 1982, the Occidental College football team had the rare opportunity for national prominence when, due to the NFL football strike, their game with San Diego was broadcast on national television.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.oxy.edu/x2815.xml&lt;/ref&gt;

Famous Occidental College Tigers include NFL Coach Jim Mora Sr., Former NFL player Vance Mueller, and 2011 U.S. Sr. Open Champion Olin Browne.

==Notable faculty==
[[File:Herrick Memorial Chapel n fountain.jpg|thumb|250px|Herrick Interfaith Center, built 1964, with ''Water Forms II'' in the foreground.]]
Many Occidental faculty have received awards and honors over time, and some have held prominent positions in government and the private sector. 

Some faculty are notable in recent years:
* Larry Caldwell, Professor of Politics, has served in the Office of Soviet Analysis at the [[Central Intelligence Agency]], as Director of European Studies at the [[National War College]] in [[Washington, D.C.]], and as Research Associate at the [[International Institute for Strategic Studies]] in London
* [[Martha Ronk]], Price Professor of English Literature, is a 2005 [[PEN American Center]] Literary Award winner in poetry.
* Derek Shearer, Stuart Chevalier Professor of Diplomacy and World Affairs, was U.S. [[Ambassador]] to [[Finland]] from 1994 to 1997 and was formerly an aide to [[Bill Clinton]].
* James Sadd, Professor of Environmental Science, host of &quot;Earth Revealed&quot; Annenberg CPB Television series and college telecourse on geology.
* Robby Moore, Elbridge Amos Stuart Professor of Economics, was the originating editor of the Teaching Tools Section of ''[[Economic Inquiry]]''.
* Caroline Heldman is a Professor of Politics and is a political reviewer for the [[Associated Press]]. She frequently appears on national airwaves as a guest and contributor for [[CNN]] and [[Fox News]] [[talk shows]].
*Peter Dreier, Dr. E.P. Clapp Distinguished Professor of Politics, and director of the Urban and Environmental Policy Department. He was the Director of Housing at the Boston Redevelopment Authority and senior policy advisor to the Boston Mayor Ray Flynn for 9 years. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Occidental College|title=Peter Dreier|url=http://employees.oxy.edu/dreier/|accessdate=8 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

===Presidents===
*[[Samuel H. Weller]] (1887-1891)
*[[J. Melville McPherron]] (1892-1894)
*[[Elbert N. Condit]] (1894-1896)
*[[James W. Parkhill]] (1896-1897)
*[[Guy W. Wadsworth]] (1897-1905)
*[[William Stewart Young]] (1905-1906, acting)
*[[John Willis Baer]] (1906-1916)
*[[Thomas Gregory Burt]] (1916-1917
*[[Silas Evans]] (1917-1920)
*[[Thomas Gregory Burt]] (1920-1921, acting)
*[[Remsen Bird]] (1921-1927)
*[[Robert G. Cleland]] (1927-1928, acting)
*[[Remsen Bird]] (1928-1945)
*[[Arthur G. Coons]] (1945-1965)
*[[Richard C. Gilman]] (1965-1988)
*[[John Brooks Slaughter]] (1988-1999)
*[[Theodore R. Mitchell]] (1999-2005)
*[[Kenyon S. Chan]] (2005-2006, acting)
*[[Susan Westerberg Prager]] (2006-2007)
*[[Robert Skotheim]] (2008-2009)
*[[Jonathan Veitch]] (2009–present)

==Greek Life==
Occidental College's Greek Council consists of 8 members: sororities Alpha Lambda Phi Alpha, Delta Omicron Tau, [[Kappa Alpha Theta]] and [[Sigma Lambda Gamma]], and fraternities [[Kappa Alpha Psi]], [[Phi Kappa Psi]], [[Sigma Alpha Epsilon]], and Zeta Tau Zeta (co-ed). 

==Dorm Life==
For the first three years at Occidental, all students are required to live on campus; as a senior, it is an option. Freshmen do not get to choose where they live; res-ed life arranges housing by pairing students based on a short form students fill in the summer before they arrive on campus. The Occidental College dorm life consists of 13 co-ed residential housing. As a first year, students have the option of living in Newcomb Hall, Chilcott Hall, Braun Hall, and Stewart-Cleland Hall (commonly known as Stewie). After a student's first year, he or she can choose to live in a number of dorms that house sophomores, juniors, and seniors; one-third of all these halls are reserved for each grade. These dorms include Bell-Young Hall, Wylie Hall, Erdman Hall, Haines Hall, Rangeview Hall and Stearns Hall. All residence halls are smoke-free, have a computer lab for use, laundry facilities, meeting/gathering space (common room), and are equipped with DIREC TV in that lounge. There are also themed-living communities which consist of the Multicultural Hall known as Pauley (open to all years), the Women's Center (Berkus House), the E. Norris Hall, the Pet House (where currently students get to live with a dog), and the Food Justice house. The items supplied in each dorm room are a bed frame/mattress, a desk, a desk chair, a dresser, a microfridge, and a microwave.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Occidental College|title=Residence Halls|url=http://www.oxy.edu/residential-education-housing-services/residence-halls}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campus Dining==
Occidental's main dining facility is The Marketplace, which is located in the Johnson Student Center. The Tiger Cooler, an espresso bar and cafe is also popular among students. Faculty, students, staff, and visitors can also grab drinks and pastries at The Green Bean Coffee Lounge and Coffee Cart. Vending machines are also available. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Occidental College|title=Campus Dining|url=http://www.oxy.edu/campus-dining/locations-hours|accessdate=2 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

===The Marketplace===
Students can dine in the facility (in the cafeteria or outside in the patio) or grab food to go. Eco-friendly containers called Eco-Clamshells are offered to Occidental students, faculty and staff to reduce plastic waste. Furthermore, all food scraps and paper waste are recycled by a company. There are different food stations including the grill, homestyle, and the pasta station. Organic and local fruit is offered. On Mondays a &quot;Meatless Monday&quot; meal is offered. 

===The Tiger Cooler===
This espresso bar and cafe is located in Samuelson Pavilion. Many students work there, either at the counter or at the grill taking one or multiple shifts. Pizza, burgers, sandwiches, salads, sushi, assorted pastries, Fosselman's ice cream, frozen yogurt, smoothies, espresso coffee drinks and other beverages are offered. Packaged snacks are also available. It is open until 11: 45 P.M. Monday-Thursday and until 2 A.M. Fridays and Saturdays. Pizza delivery can be requested as well.

===The Coffee Cart===
It is located in Rangeview. Coffee, tea, and snacks are available along with organic options that are not sold elsewhere on campus. 

===The Green Bean Coffee Lounge===
Also located in the Johnson Student Center, this facility is student-run and was recently added by student request.

==Traditions==
At the beginning of every school year, freshmen participate in Convocation, a formal ceremony welcoming new students to the College in which the faculty wear their full academic regalia and students don robes. Students process from the Academic Quad to Thorne Hall as Faculty line their path, cheering for them. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oxy.edu/events/convocation-0 Convocation 2012]&lt;/ref&gt;

Students are often thrown into the Lucille Gilman Memorial Fountain on their birthday 

Founders day is celebrated April 20th, the day in 1887 when Occidental's incorporation papers were officially signed by the California Secretary of State &lt;ref&gt;http://www.oxy.edu/our-story/traditions/gallery/oxy-traditions&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable alumni==

===Business and industry===
* [[John Branca]] (entertainment industry lawyer)
* [[Norton Clapp]] (an original owner of [[Space Needle]])
* [[W. Don Cornwell]] (CEO of [[Granite Broadcasting]])
* [[Linda Bradford Raschke]] (hedge fund manager)

===Entertainment and the arts===
[[File:Terry Gilliam.jpg|thumb|100px|right|Terry Gilliam]]
[[File:Ben Affleck 2008.jpg|thumb|100px|right|Ben Affleck]]
* [[Ben Affleck]] (actor, director, screenwriter)
* [[Stephen Beal]] (visual artist)
* [[August Coppola]] (academic, author, film executive and advocate for the arts)
* [[Glenn Corbett]] (television actor)
* [[Mesh Flinders]] (filmmaker, creator of ''[[lonelygirl15]]'')
* [[Will Friedle]] (actor)
* [[Eddie Galan]] (songwriter and music producer)
* [[Emily Osment]] (actress; Class of 2015)
* [[Terry Gilliam]] (animator and actor in [[Monty Python]] comedy troupe; filmmaker: ''[[Brazil (film)|Brazil]]'', ''[[12 Monkeys]]'', others)
* [[Ra'uf Glasgow]] (screenwriter and producer in film and television, a producer of the series &quot;[[Lost (TV series)|Lost]]&quot;)
* [[Mike Hoover]] (cameraman,journalist,documentarian, rock climber, mountaineer, and adventurer, winner of Academy and Emmy awards)
* [[Joanna Gleason]] (actor)
* [[Scott Harris (agent)|Scott Harris]] (talent agent, co-founder and CEO of Innovative Artists Talent and Literary Agency)
* [[Terry Kitchen]] (musician)
* [[Loren Lester]] (actor)
* [[Marcel Ophüls]] (filmmaker)
* [[Peter Scolari]] (actor)
* [[Jake Shears]] (lead singer of Scissor Sisters)
* [[Anna Slotky]] (actress)
* [[Dan Slott]] (comic book writer)
* [[Roger Guenveur Smith]] (actor)
* [[Kirsten Smith (writer)|Kirsten Smith]] (screenwriter, ''[[Ten Things I Hate About You]]'', ''[[Legally Blonde]]'', ''[[The Ugly Truth (film)|The Ugly Truth]]'')
* [[Rider Strong]] (actor)
* [[Maurissa Tancharoen]] (actress, singer, dancer, television writer and lyricist)
* [[Tui St. George Tucker]] (composer)
* [[Luke Wilson]] (actor)
* [[Marshall Cook]] (Film Director, Actor)

===Government, diplomacy, and law===
* [[Kathy Augustine]] (U.S. politician from Nevada)
* [[Alphonzo E. Bell, Jr.]] (U.S. Congressman)
* [[David S. Cunningham, Jr.]] (Los Angeles City Council member, 1973–87)
* [[Dennis R. Patrick]] (Chairman of the Federal Communications Commission, 1987 - 1989)
* [[Gloria Duffy]] (President and CEO of [http://www.commonwealthclub.org/ The Commonwealth Club], former Asst Deputy Sec Def, Asst Sec Def, and Special Coordinator for Cooperative Threat Reduction)
* [[Richard Falkenrath]] (former deputy homeland security advisor)
* [[Robert Finch (American politician)|Robert Finch]] (Secretary of Health, Education and Welfare 1969—1970, Lieutenant Governor of California 1967—1969)
* [[U. Alexis Johnson]] (U.S. diplomat)
[[File:Jack Kemp-Congressional Portrait Collection.jpg|thumb|upright=.5|Jack Kemp]]
* [[Jack Kemp]] (AFL and NFL player from 1958–1970, [[U.S. Representative]] from New York 1971-1989, U.S. Secretary [[Department of Housing and Urban Development]] 1989-1993, Republican [[Vice President of the United States|Vice Presidential]] candidate for the 1996 Presidential election.)
* [[David M. Louie]] ([[attorney General of Hawaii]])
* [[Pete McCloskey]] (politician)
* [[Jacqueline Nguyen]] (federal judge, [[United States District Court for the Central District of California]])
* [[Chris Norby]] ([[California State Assembly]]man)
[[File:Official portrait of Barack Obama.jpg|thumb|upright=.5|Barack Obama]]
* [[Barack Obama]] (44th [[President of the United States]])&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 | first = Maurice
 | last = Possley
 | title = Obama's political activism started in college
 | url = http://www.chicagotribune.com/news/nationworld/chi-070329obama-college,1,2683821.story?track=rss/abr
 | work = [[Chicago Tribune]]
 | publisher = Chicago Tribune
 | date = 2007-03-29
 | accessdate = 2007-06-13
&lt;!-- | quote = Obama said had &quot;fond memories&quot; of Occidental. &quot;It's a wonderful, small, liberal arts college. The professors were diverse and inspiring. I ended up making some lifelong friendships there, and those first two years really helped me grow up.&quot;--&gt;
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Janette Sadik-Khan]] (commissioner, New York City Department of Transportation)
* [[Janis Lynn Sammartino]] (federal judge, [[United States District Court for the Southern District of California]])
* [[Mark S. Scarberry]] (professor of law at [[Pepperdine University School of Law]])

===Higher education and academia===
* [[Glenn S. Dumke]] (history professor and chancellor of the California State University)
* [[Lewis Sargentich]] (legal scholar at [[Harvard Law School]])
* [[Bernard K. Means]] (Anthropology Professor at [[Virginia Commonwealth University]])
* [[Coit D. Blacker]] (Political Science Professor at [[Stanford University]])

===Journalism===
[[File:Patt Morrison by David Shankbone.jpg|thumb|100px|right|Patt Morrison]]
* [[Steve Coll]] (former ''Washington Post'' Managing Editor, Pulitzer Prize winner)
* [[Andrea Elliott]] (reporter for ''[[The New York Times]]'', Pulitzer Prize winner)
* [[Chris Gulker]] (photographer)
* [[Patt Morrison]] (NPR radio personality and columnist for the ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'')
* [[Sam Rubin (Journalist)|Sam Rubin]] ([[KTLA]] entertainment anchor)
* [[Soren Bowie]] (Journalist at &quot;[[Cracked.com]]&quot;)

===Literature and writing===
* [[Mark Dery]] (author and cultural critic)
* [[Robinson Jeffers]] (poet)
* [[Linda A. Malcor]] (author)
* [[Scott O'Dell]] (author, Newbery Award winner)
* [[Carrie Vaughn]] (writer)
* [[Gladys Waddingham]] (teacher and local historian)
* [[Rosalind Wiseman]] (writer)

===Medicine===
* [[David G. Armstrong]] (physician/medical researcher)
* [[Howard Judd]] (medical researcher)

===Science===
* [[Brent Dalrymple]] (geologist and National Medal of Science winner)
* [[William Goddard (engineer)]]
* [[Edmund C. Jaeger]] (naturalist, author, teacher)
* [[J. P. Mallory]] (archaeologist)
* [[Fred Lawrence Whipple]] (astronomer)

===Social action, philanthropy, and community service===
* [[Howard Ahmanson, Jr]] (philanthropist for fundamentalist Christian causes)
* [[Cameron Townsend]] (founder, Wycliffe Bible Translators and Summer Institute of Linguistics)
* [[Rex Weyler]] (author, journalist, ecologist and co-founder of Greenpeace International; did not graduate)

===Sports and athletics===
* [[Jack Kemp]] (AFL and NFL star quarterback of the Buffalo Bills)
* [[Jim E. Mora|Jim Mora, Sr.]] (coach of the NFL's New Orleans Saints)
* [[Vance Mueller]] (NFL running back)
* [[Ron Botchan]] (five-time [[Super Bowl]] [[National Football League]] official from 1980 to 2002)
* [[Jim Tunney (American football official)|Jim Tunney]] (NFL official from 1960–1991)
* [[Olin Browne]] (PGA Tour winner)
* [[Sammy Lee (diver)|Dr. Sammy Lee]] (two-time Olympic gold medalist in diving)

==Film and television at Occidental==
[[File:Taft at Occidental.jpg|right|thumb|250px|President [[William Howard Taft]] at Occidental in October 1911]]
Occidental’s campus, architecture, and proximity to Hollywood have made it a desired location for a number of film and television productions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 | title = Occidental College as a Movie Location
 | url = http://www.oxy.edu/x1194.xml
 | work =
 | accessdate = 2007-08-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Film credits include:

* ''The Cup of Fury'' (1920)
* ''[[Horse Feathers]]'' (1932) with the [[Marx Brothers]]
* ''[[Pigskin Parade]]'' (1936) with [[Judy Garland]] and [[Betty Grable]]
* ''[[Second Chorus]]'' (1941) with [[Fred Astaire]]
* ''[[That Hagen Girl]]'' (1947) with [[Shirley Temple]] and [[Ronald Reagan]]
* ''[[Goodbye, My Fancy]]'' (1951) with [[Joan Crawford]] and [[Robert Young (actor)|Robert Young]]
* ''[[That's My Boy (1951 film)|That's My Boy]]'' (1951) with [[Dean Martin]]
* ''[[Pat and Mike]]'' (1952) with [[Katharine Hepburn]] and [[Spencer Tracy]]
* ''[[Tall Story]]'' (1960) with [[Jane Fonda]] and [[Anthony Perkins]]
* ''[[Take Her, She's Mine]]'' (1963) with [[James Stewart]]
* ''[[The Impossible Years]]'' (1968) with [[David Niven]]
* ''[[The One and Only (1978 film)|The One and Only]]'' (1978) with [[Henry Winkler]]
* ''[[Star Trek III: The Search for Spock]]'' (1984) featuring the Gilman Fountain as part of the Palace of Vulcan
* ''[[Real Genius]]'' (1985) with [[Val Kilmer]]
* ''[[Sneakers (1992 film)|Sneakers]]'' (1992) with [[Robert Redford]]
* ''[[Clueless (film)|Clueless]]'' (1995) with [[Alicia Silverstone]]
* ''[[Kicking and Screaming (1995 film)|Kicking and Screaming]]'' (1995) with [[Josh Hamilton (actor)|Josh Hamilton]]
* ''[[Don't Be a Menace to South Central While Drinking Your Juice in the Hood]]'' (1996) with the [[Wayans Brothers]]
* ''[[Boys and Girls (2000 film)|Boys and Girls]]'' (2000) with [[Freddie Prinze Jr.]]
* ''[[Jurassic Park III]]'' (2001) with [[Sam Neill]]
* ''[[Orange County (film)|Orange County]]'' (2002) with [[Colin Hanks]] and [[Jack Black]]
* ''[[The Holiday]]'' (2006) with [[Cameron Diaz]], [[Kate Winslet]], [[Jude Law]], and [[Jack Black]]
* ''[[Made of Honor]]'' (2008) with [[Patrick Dempsey]] and [[Michelle Monaghan]]
* ''[[Fired Up (film)|Fired Up]]'' (2009) with [[Nicholas D'Agosto]], [[Eric Christian Olsen]], and [[Sarah Roemer]]
* ''[[The Kids Are Alright (film)|The Kids Are All Right]] (2010) with [[Annette Bening]] and [[Julianne Moore]]

TV credits include: 

* ''[[Dragnet (series)|Dragnet]]'' 
* ''[[The West Wing]]''  
* ''[[Monk]]'' 
* ''[[Charmed]]'' 
* ''[[The L Word]]'' 
* ''[[Criminal Minds]]''
* ''[[Beverly Hills, 90210]]'' 
* ''[[Greek (TV series)|Greek]]''  
* ''[[Lou Grant]]''
* ''[[Remington Steele]]''
* ''[[NCIS (TV series)|NCIS]]''
* ''[[Cannon]]'' 
* ''[[Parenthood]]''
* ''[[Arrested Development (TV series)|Arrested Development]]''
* ''[[Switched at Birth (TV series)|Switched at Birth]]''

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Los Angeles|University}}
* [http://www.oxy.edu/ Occidental College official website]
* [http://www.oxyathletics.com/ Occidental College official athletics website]
* [http://koxyradio.com/ KOXY]—student-run radio station
* [http://www.oxyweekly.com Occidental Weekly Newspaper]

{{Southern California Intercollegiate Athletic Conference navbox}}
{{Oberlin Group}}
{{CLAC}}
{{Los Angeles}}
{{Colleges and universities in Los Angeles County}}
{{Los Angeles Eastside}}

[[Category:Occidental College|*]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Los Angeles County, California]]
[[Category:Independent Colleges of Southern California]]
[[Category:Liberal arts colleges]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1887]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:Schools accredited by the Western Association of Schools and Colleges]]
[[Category:Members of the Annapolis Group]]

[[da:Occidental College]]
[[es:Occidental College]]
[[fr:Occidental College]]
[[ko:옥시덴털 대학교]]
[[nl:Occidental College]]
[[ja:オクシデンタル大学]]
[[simple:Occidental College]]
[[sv:Occidental College]]</text>
      <sha1>qvpf4scg2m0iseigwnwg5ajliejvzfc</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
