<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Open government</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8297930</id>
    <revision>
      <id>517588837</id>
      <parentid>515345971</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-13T15:53:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lquilter</username>
        <id>6404</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Further reading */ addl citn</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11615">{{peacock|date=September 2011}}
{{refimprove|date=March 2012}}
{{About|the political doctrine|the ''Yes Minister'' episode|Open Government (Yes Minister)}}

'''Open government''' is the governing [[doctrine]] which holds that citizens have
the right to access the documents and proceedings of the government to allow for effective public [[Regulation|oversight]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ruma&quot;&gt;{{cite book |editor1-first=Daniel |editor1-last=Lathrop |editor2-first=Laurel |editor2-last=Ruma |title= Open Government: Transparency, Collaboration and Participation in Practice |publisher= O'Reilly Media |year= 2010 |month= February  |url = http://openlibrary.org/books/OL24435672M/Open_Government |isbn= 978-0-596-80435-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; In its broadest construction it opposes [[national interest|reason of state]] and other considerations, which have tended to legitimize extensive state [[secrecy]]. The origins of open government arguments can be dated to the time of the European [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]]: to debates about the proper construction of a then nascent [[democratic society]].

Among recent developments is the theory of [[open source governance]], which advocates the application of  the [[free software movement]] to [[democracy|democratic]] principles, enabling interested citizens to get more directly involved in the legislative process.

==History==
In the West, the idea that government should be open to public scrutiny and susceptible to [[public opinion]] dates back at least to the time of the [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]], when many ''[[philosophe]]s'' made an attack on [[Absolutism (European history)|absolutist]] doctrine of state secrecy, a core part of their intellectual project.&lt;ref&gt;Jurgen Habermas, ''The Structural Transformation of the Public Sphere'' (1962, trans., Cambridge Massachusetts, 1989)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Reinhart Koselleck, ''Critique and Crisis'' (1965, trans., Cambridge Massachusetts, 1988)&lt;/ref&gt;  The passage of formal legislative instruments to this end can also be traced to this time with [[Sweden]], for example, (which then included [[Finland]] as a Swedish-governed territory) enacting free press legislation as part of its constitution ([[Freedom of the Press]] Act, 1766).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=http://members.optusnet.com.au/~slamble/freedom_of_information.html |last=Lamble |first=Stephen  |year=2002 |month=February |title=Freedom of Information, a Finnish clergyman’s gift to democracy |publisher=Freedom of Information Review |volume=97 |pages=2–8}}&lt;/ref&gt; This approach, and that of the ''philosophes'' more broadly, is strongly related to recent historiography on the eighteenth-century public sphere.

Influenced by Enlightenment thought, the revolutions in America (1776) and France (1789), [[freedom of the press]] enshrined provisions and requirements for public budgetary accounting and freedom of the press in constitutional articles. In the nineteenth century, attempts by [[Metternich]]ean statesmen to row back on these measures were vigorously opposed by a number of eminent liberal politicians and writers, [[Jeremy Bentham|Bentham]], [[John Stuart Mill|Mill]] and [[John Dalberg-Acton, 1st Baron Acton|Acton]] prominent among the latter.

Open government is  widely seen to be a key hallmark of contemporary [[democratic]] practice and is often linked to the passing of [[freedom of information]] legislation. Scandinavian countries claim to have adopted the first freedom of information legislation, dating the origins of its modern provisions to the eighteenth century and Finland continuing the presumption of openness after gaining independence in 1917, passing its Act on Publicity of Official Documents in 1951 (superseded by new legislation in 1999).  

The [[United States]] passed its Freedom of Information Act ([[Freedom of Information Act (United States)|FOIA]]) in 1966, FOIAs, [[Access to Information Act]]s (AIAs) or equivalent laws were passed in [[Denmark]] and [[Norway]] in 1970, [[France]] and [[The Netherlands]] in 1978, [[Australia]], [[Canada]] and [[New Zealand]] in 1982, [[Hungary]] in 1992, [[Ireland]] and [[Thailand]] in 1997, [[South Korea]] in 1998, the [[United Kingdom]] in 2000, [[Japan]] and [[Mexico]] in 2002, [[India]] and [[Germany]] in 2005.&lt;ref&gt;[[Alasdair Roberts (academic)|Alasdair Roberts]], [http://www.cambridge.org/us/catalogue/catalogue.asp?isbn=9780521858700 ''Blacked Out: Government Secrecy in the Information Age''] (Cambridge, 2006)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Content==
Transparency in government is often credited with generating government [[accountability]].&lt;ref name=Schauer2011&gt;{{Citation | title = Transparency in Three Dimensions | url = http://illinoislawreview.org/wp-content/ilr-content/articles/2011/4/Schauer.pdf | year = 2011 | author = Schauer, Frederick | journal = University of Illinois Law Review | pages = 1339–1358 | volume = 2011 | issue = 4 | accessdate = 2011-10-16.}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|1346}}  Transparency often allows citizens of a democracy to control their government, reducing [[government corruption]], [[bribery]] and other [[Malfeasance in office|malfeasance]].&lt;ref name=Schauer2011/&gt;{{rp|1347–50}}  Some commentators contend that an open, transparent government allows for the dissemination of information, which in turn helps produce greater knowledge and societal progress.&lt;ref name=Schauer2011/&gt;{{rp|1350}}      

The contemporary doctrine of open government finds its strongest advocates in those [[non-governmental organisations]] keen to counter what they see as the inherent tendency of government to lapse, whenever possible, into secrecy. Prominent among these NGOs are bodies like ''[[Transparency International]]'' or the ''[[Open Society Institute]]''. They advocate the implementation of norms of openness and transparency across the globe and argue that such standards are vital to the ongoing prosperity and development of democratic societies.

Advocates of open government often argue that civil [[society]], rather than government [[legislation]], offers the best route to more transparent administration. They point to the role of [[whistleblowers]] reporting from inside the government bureaucracy (individuals like [[Daniel Ellsberg]] or [[Paul van Buitenen]]). They argue that an independent and inquiring press, printed or electronic, is often a stronger guarantor of transparency than legislative checks and balances.&lt;ref&gt;J. Michael, ''The Politics of Secrecy: Confidential Government and the Public's Right to Know'' (London, 1990)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;A.G. Theoharis, ed., ''A Culture of Secrecy: the Government Versus the People's Right to Know'' (Kansas, 1998)&lt;/ref&gt;

Along with an interest in providing more access to information goes a corresponding concern for protecting citizens' privacy so they are not exposed to &quot;adverse consequences, retribution or negative repercussions&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ruma&quot; /&gt; from information provided by governments.

A relatively new vision for the implementation of open government is coming from the municipal sector.  In a similar fashion to grassroot movements, open government technology expert Tobias SK Cichon postulates [http://codigigo.blogspot.com] that the swarming pressure of small local governments using technology to implement open government solutions will lead to similar adoptions by larger municipalities and eventually state, provincial and federal level changes.

Public and private sector platforms provide an avenue for citizens to engage while offering access to transparent information that citizens have come to expect. Numerous organizations have worked to consolidate resources for citizens to access government (local, state and federal) budget spending, stimulus spending, lobbyist spending, legislative tracking, and more.&lt;ref&gt;Giordano Koch &amp; Maximilian Rapp: Open Government Platforms in Municipality Areas: Identifying elemental design principles, In: Public Management im Paradigmenwechsel, Trauner Verlag, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the obvious and undeniable benefits that come from increased government transparency, a number of scholars have questioned the moral certitude behind much transparency advocacy, questioning the foundations upon which advocacy rests. They have also highlighted how transparency can support certain neoliberal imperatives.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation  | author-first = C. | author-last = Garsten | title = Transparency in a New Global Order:Unveiling Organizational Visions | publisher = Edward Elger| year = 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Clare Birchall in a special issue of the journal, [[Theory, Culture &amp; Society|Theory, Culture and Society]], examined the opposition between secrecy and transparency to question common understandings of this relationship.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation  | author-first = Clare | author-last = Birchall | title = 'Secrecy and Transparency: The Politics of Opacity and Openness', Theory, Culture and Society 28 (7-8)| publisher = Sage | year = 2011  | issn = 0263-2764}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Accountability]]
* [[Censorship]]
* [[e-democracy]]
* [[e-government]]
* [[Freedom of information legislation]]
* [[Public trust]]
* [[Open politics]]
* [[The Open Society and Its Enemies]], an essay written by [[Karl Popper]].
* [[Open source governance]]
* [[Open Society]]
* [[Political corruption]]
* [[Privacy]]
{{Open movements}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* {{Citation |publisher = Brookings Institution Press |publication-place = Washington, D.C |author = Jane E. Fountain |authorlink =Jane Fountain |url =  |title = Building the Virtual State: Information Technology and Institutional Change |publication-date = 2001 }}

* {{Citation |publisher = Brookings Institution Press |publication-place = Washington, D.C |author = Beth Simone Noveck |authorlink =Beth Simone Noveck |url = http://openlibrary.org/books/OL23153089M/Wiki_government |title = Wiki government: how technology can make government better, democracy stronger, and citizens more powerful |publication-date = 2009 }}

* {{cite journal |author=Jay Nath |year=2011 |title=Reimagining government in the digital age |journal=National Civic Review; Special Issue: Beyond the Digital Divide: How New Technologies Can Amplify Civic Engagement and Community Participation |volume=100 |issue=3 }}

* {{cite web |url=http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1899790 |title=Not with a Bang but a Whimper: The Politics of Accountability and Open Data in the UK |author=Tom McClean |date=2011 |work=American Political Science Association 2011 Annual Meeting Paper |publisher=Social Science Research Network}}

* {{cite book |title=Hear Us Now? A California Survey of Digital Technology's Role in Civic Engagement and Local Government |last= |first= |author= April Manatt |coauthors= |year=2011 |publisher=New America Foundation |url=http://newamerica.net/publications/policy/hear_us_now }}

*{{cite web |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/08/19/us/19iht-letter19.html?_r=1&amp;pagewanted=all |title=Remaking Government in a Wiki Age |author=C. Freeland |date=August 18, 2011 |work=New York Times }}

==External links== 
* [http://en.oreilly.com/gov2-international Gov 2.0 Conference]
* [http://eaves.ca/tag/gov20/ David Eaves's blog on open government in Canada]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Open Government}}
[[Category:Political science]]
[[Category:Political philosophy]]
[[Category:Open government| ]]
[[Category:Open data]]

[[ar:الحكومة المفتوحة]]
[[de:Open Government]]
[[es:Gobierno abierto]]
[[fr:Gouvernement ouvert]]
[[id:Pemerintahan terbuka]]
[[it:Open government]]
[[he:ממשל פתוח]]
[[pl:Open government]]
[[ru:Открытое государство]]
[[tr:Açık hükümet]]</text>
      <sha1>9pmkm5qrg3e337xeawcld8wr7bshmug</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
