<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Pacifism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>24956</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521727696</id>
      <parentid>521726286</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-06T21:09:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pass a Method</username>
        <id>14161360</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>fmt</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="73438">{{Redirect|Pacifist}}
{{Redirect|Dovish|the economic term|Dovish (inflation)}}
[[Image:PEACE.PNG|thumb|A [[peace sign]], which is widely associated with pacifism.]]
'''Pacifism''' is  opposition to [[war]] and [[violence]], even to the point of allowing self-harm rather than a resort to violent resistance. The term &quot;pacifism&quot; was coined by the French peace campaigner [[Émile Arnaud]] (1864–1921) and adopted by other peace activists at the tenth Universal Peace Congress in
[[Glasgow]] in 1901.&lt;ref&gt;''The Abolition of War: the Peace Movement in Britain, 1914-1919'' by [[Keith Robbins]].
University of Wales Press, 1976. ISBN 978-0-7083-0622-2 (p.10).&lt;/ref&gt; The concept is an ancient one that goes back to the teachings of [[Siddhartha Gautama]] (Buddha), and [[Jesus]]. In modern times, it was refined by [[Mohandas Gandhi]] (1869-1948) into the practice of steadfast [[nonviolent resistance|nonviolent opposition]] which he called &quot;[[satyagraha]]&quot;. Its effectiveness served as inspiration to [[Martin Luther King Jr.]] among many others. An iconic image of pacifism came out of the [[Tiananmen Square Protests]] of 1989 with the &quot;[[Tank Man]]&quot;, where one protester stood in nonviolent opposition to a column of tanks. Historians have identified that event as being a key motivation that led to the [[fall of the Berlin Wall]] which ultimately precipitated the nonviolent [[fall of Communism]].

== Definition ==
Pacifism covers a spectrum of views, including the belief that international disputes can and should be peacefully resolved, calls for the abolition of the institutions of the military and war, opposition to any organization of society through governmental force ([[anarcho-pacifism|anarchist or libertarian pacifism]]), rejection of the use of physical violence to obtain political, economic or social goals,  the obliteration of force except in cases where it is absolutely necessary to advance the cause of peace, and opposition to violence under any circumstance, even defense of self and others. Historians of pacifism [[Peter Brock (historian)|Peter Brock]] and [[Thomas Paul Socknat]] define pacifism &quot;in the sense generally accepted in English-speaking areas&quot; as &quot;an unconditional rejection of all forms of warfare&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''Challenge to Mars: Essays on Pacifism from 1918 to 1945''. Edited by Brock and Socknat University of Toronto Press, 1999 ISBN 0-8020-4371-2 (p. ix)&lt;/ref&gt; Philosopher [[Jenny Teichman]] defines the main form of pacifism as &quot;anti-warism&quot;, the rejection of all forms of warfare.&lt;ref&gt;''Pacifism and the Just War: A Study in Applied Philosophy'' by Jenny Teichman. Basil Blackwell, 1986
ISBN 0-631-15056-0&lt;/ref&gt; Teichman's beliefs have been summarized by [[Brian Orend]] as &quot;...A pacifist rejects war and believes there are no moral grounds which can justify resorting to war. War, for the pacifist, is always wrong.&quot; The whole theory is based on the idea that the end does NOT justify the means.&lt;ref&gt;''War and International Justice: a Kantian perspective'' by Brian Orend. Wilfrid Laurier Univ. Press, 2000. ISBN 0-88920-337-7 p. 145-6&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Moral considerations ===
Pacifism may be based on [[morality|moral]] principles (a [[deontological]] view) or [[pragmatism]] (a [[consequentialist]] view). Principled pacifism holds that at some point along the spectrum from war to interpersonal physical violence, such violence becomes morally wrong. Pragmatic pacifism holds that the costs of war and interpersonal violence are so substantial that better ways of resolving disputes must be found. Pacifists in general usually reject theories of [[Just War]]. Some, however, believe that if the foe is willing to hurt others, then it is justified to respond with force, even to the extent of the atomic bomb. Such people can be called semi-pacifists.

A counterargument to this is the belief that even if one side's resort to force can provide more peace in the long run, people on both sides will think they are on that side due to the worse side's [[propaganda]], so it would be safer for both sides to oppose war despite both believing they are on that side which should resort to force.

=== Nonviolence ===
Some pacifists follow principles of [[nonviolence]], believing that nonviolent action is morally superior and/or pragmatically most effective. Some pacifists, however, support physical violence for emergency defense of self or others. Others support [[property damage|destruction of property]] in such emergencies or for conducting symbolic acts of resistance like pouring red paint to represent blood on the outside of military recruiting offices or entering air force bases and hammering on military aircraft. 

By no means is all [[nonviolent resistance]] (sometimes also called [[civil resistance]]) based on a fundamental rejection of all violence in all circumstances. Many leaders and participants in such movements, while recognizing the importance of using non-violent methods in particular circumstances, have not been absolute pacifists. Sometimes, as with the US civil rights movement's march from Selma to Montgomery in 1965, they have called for armed protection. The interconnections between civil resistance and factors of force are numerous and complex.&lt;ref&gt;Adam Roberts and Timothy Garton Ash (eds.), ''Civil Resistance and Power Politics: The Experience of Non-violent Action from Gandhi to the Present'', Oxford University Press, 2009. See [http://books.google.com/books?id=BxOQKrCe7UUC&amp;dq=Civil+resistance+and+power+politics&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s]. Includes chapters by specialists on the various movements.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Non-aggression===
In contrast to the nonviolence principle stands the [[non-aggression principle]] which rejects the initiation of violence, but permits the use of violence for [[self-defense]] or [[delegated]] defense. People supporting the non-aggression principle claim that the moral prohibition of the use of violence follows from [[argumentation ethics]], which applies only when people are using [[argumentation]] to solve disputes. So it does not apply when someone is subject to initiated violence, and hence self-defense is not morally rejected. Another possible approach is a [[semantic]] one: the claim that defense and aggression are fundamentally different, a point that is obscured when using terms like &quot;defensive violence&quot; and &quot;initiated violence&quot;; that there is no moral prohibition on defense and no need to justify it or make an exception for it.{{Citation needed|date=May 2012}}

===Dove===
&quot;Dove&quot; or &quot;dovish&quot; are informal terms used, especially in politics, for people who prefer to avoid war or prefer war as a last resort. The terms refer to the story of [[Noah's Ark]] in which the dove came to symbolize the hope of salvation and peace.{{Citation needed|date=July 2009}} Similarly, in common parlance, the opposite of a dove is a hawk or [[war hawk]].

==Early history==
[[File:Apotheosis.jpg|thumb|250px|[[Vasily Vereshchagin|Vereschagin]]'s painting ''Apotheosis of War'' (1871) came to be admired as one of the earliest artistic expressions of pacifism.]]

Advocacy of pacifism can be found far back in history and literature.

===India===
Compassion for all life, human and nonhuman, is central to [[Buddhism]], which was founded by [[Siddhattha Gotama]]; and also [[Jainism]], which was founded by [[Mahavira]] 599–527 BC. Both the [[Buddha]] and Mahavira were by birth [[kshatriya]], the varna (social order) of soldiers and officials. An unusual example is that of Emperor [[Ashoka]] who became a pacifist after the bloody [[Kalinga war]].{{Citation needed|date=December 2011}}

===Greece===
In [[Ancient Greece]], however, pacifism seems not to have existed except as a broad moral guideline against violence between individuals. No philosophical program of rejecting violence between states, or rejecting all forms of violence, seems to have existed. Aristophanes, in his play [[Lysistrata]], creates the scenario of an [[Athens|Athenian]] woman's anti-war sex strike during the [[Peloponnesian War]] of 431–404 BC, and the play has gained an international reputation for its anti-war message. Nevertheless, it is both fictional and comical, and though it offers a pragmatic opposition to the destructiveness of war, its message seems to stem from frustration with the existing conflict (then in its twentieth year) rather than from a philosophical position against violence or war.
Equally fictional is the nonviolent protest of [[Hegetorides]] of [[Thasos]]. [[Euripides]] also expressed strong anti-war ideas in his work, especially ''[[The Trojan Women]]''. &lt;ref name=&quot;fsn&quot;&gt; &quot;Peace, War and Philosophy&quot; by F. S. Northedge,in
[[Paul Edwards (philosopher)|Paul Edwards]], ''The Encyclopedia of Philosophy'', Volume 6, Collier Macmillan, 1967 (pgs 63-67). &lt;/ref&gt;

===China===
During the [[Warring States Period]], the pacifist [[Mohist]] School opposed aggressive war between the feudal states. They took this belief into action by using their famed defensive strategies to defend smaller states from invasion from larger states, hoping to dissuade feudal lords from costly warfare.

The Taoist scripture &quot;''Classic of Great Peace'' (''[[Taiping Jing|Taiping jing]]'')&quot; foretells &quot;the coming Age of Great Peace (''taiping'').&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iep.utm.edu/d/daoism.htm#H10 ''Daoist Philosophy'' -- 10. &quot;Celestial Masters Daoism&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Taiping Jing'' advocates &quot;a world full of peace&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.kaogu.com.cn/upload/200811191348384181.doc&lt;/ref&gt;

===Africa===
The Lemba religion of southern French Congo, along with its symbolic herb, is named for pacifism : &quot; &quot;''lemba, lemba''&quot; (peace, peace), describes the action of the plant ''lemba-lemba'' (''Brillantaisia patula T. Anders'')&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| title = Lemba, 1650-1930 | first = John M. | last = Janzen | publisher = Garland Publishing, Inc. | location = New York | year = 1982 | isbn = 0-8240-9306-2 | pages = 173}}&lt;/ref&gt; Likewise in Cabinda, &quot;''Lemba'' is the spirit of peace, as its name indicates.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| title = Lemba, 1650-1930 | first = John M. | last = Janzen | publisher = Garland Publishing, Inc. | location = New York | year = 1982 | isbn = 0-8240-9306-2 | pages = 303 (8)}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Chatham Islands===
The [[Moriori]], of the [[Chatham Islands]], practiced pacifism by order of their ancestor [[Nunuku-whenua]]. This enabled the Moriori to preserve what limited resources they had in their harsh climate, avoiding waste through warfare. In turn, this led to their almost complete annihilation in 1835 by invading [[Ngāti Mutunga]] and [[Ngāti Tama]] [[Māori people|Māori]] from the [[Taranaki Region|Taranaki]] region of the [[North Island]] of [[New Zealand]]. The invading Māori killed, enslaved and [[cannibalism|cannibalised]] the Moriori.

===New Zealand===
Among the Māori, the major god ''[[Rongo]]'' is the &quot;god of peace&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://kupu.maori.nz/ShowKupu.aspx?kupu=459 &quot;Rongo : god of peace&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; The minor god Kahungunu is &quot;a pacifist in spirit&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| title = Takitimu | first = Tiaki Hikawera | last = Mitira | publisher = Reed Publishing, Ltd. | location = New Zealand | year = 1972 (1944) | isbn = 0-589-00717-3 | pages = 73}} http://www.nzetc.org/tm/scholarly/tei-MitTaki-t1-body-d2-d2.html&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hawaii===
In Hawaii at the time of Captain Cook's visit (1779 Chr.E.), Lono was worshipped as &quot;god of peace&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=8vupOp3E_5YC&amp;pg=PA3&amp;lpg=PA3&amp;dq=Lono+%22god+of+peace%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=7IANllWXM1&amp;sig=ie1Q_85ZqlVIO4sWXG5YTm1V_aA&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=2dFUS6CNL8GUtgep3IEf&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=10&amp;ved=0CCwQ6AEwCQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Lono%20%22god%20of%20peace%22&amp;f=false D. Z. Zhong : ''The Possibility of Anthropological Fideism''. BALLSACKUniversity Press of America, Lanham (MD), 2004. p. 3]&lt;/ref&gt;

===North America===
The [[Whilkut]] of northern California have a bird-god of peace-making, &quot;Merk&quot; ('Egret').&lt;ref&gt;Robert G. Lake : ''Chilula : People from the Ancient Redwoods''. University Press of America, Washington (DC), 1982. pp. 147-8&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Hopi]] people, whose name means 'Peaceful'&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.whatmagazine.org/bigmountain/bigmtn5.html &quot;Hopi Prophecies&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; (&quot;Hopi&quot; is a contraction of /hopitu/ 'peaceful'),&lt;ref&gt;[http://lucy.ukc.ac.uk/EthnoAtlas/Hmar/Cult_dir/Culture.7846 &quot;Society -- Hopi]&lt;/ref&gt; have followed religious doctrine that is generally &quot;anti-war&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://blog.beaming.com/2009/10/hopithe-anti-war-religion.html &quot;anti-war religion&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Among the [[Aztecs]], [[Quetzalcoatl]] was &quot;god of Peace ..., who required his people to live in peace&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.archive.org/stream/originlegacyofme00burcrich/originlegacyofme00burcrich_djvu.txt Katharine Tyler Burchwood : ''The Origin and Legacy of Mexican Art''. 1972.] p. 29&lt;/ref&gt;

===Judea under Roman control===
Throughout history, many have understood [[Jesus]] of Nazareth to have been a pacifist,&lt;ref name=&quot;weidhorn&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|  first =Manfred |last = Weidhorn | title = Pacifism Lost | journal = International Journal of Humanities and Peace | year = 2004 | volume = 20|issue = 1|pages = 13–18}}&lt;/ref&gt; drawing on his [[Sermon on the Mount]] (see [[Christian pacifism]]). In the sermon Jesus stated that one should &quot;not resist an evildoer&quot; and promoted his [[turn the other cheek]] philosophy. &quot;If anyone strikes you on the right cheek, turn the other also; and if anyone wants to sue you and take your coat, give your cloak as well... Love your enemies, do good to those who hate you, bless those who curse you, pray for those who abuse you.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://bible.oremus.org/?passage=Matthew+5 oremus Bible Browser : Matthew 5&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://bible.oremus.org/?passage=Luke+6 oremus Bible Browser : Luke 6&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;aqa&quot;&gt;{{Cite book| title = GCSE Religious Studies for AQA Christianity: Christianity: Behaviour, Attitudes &amp; Lifestyles | first = Joanne | last = Cleave | coauthors = Geddes, Gordon D.; Griffiths, Jane; | publisher = Heinemann Educational Publisher | location = Oxford | year = 2004 | isbn = 0-435-30714-2 | pages = 75}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The New Testament story is of Jesus, besides preaching these words, surrendering himself freely to an enemy intent on having him killed and proscribing his followers from defending him.

There are those, however, who deny that Jesus was a pacifist&lt;ref name=&quot;weidhorn&quot; /&gt; and state that Jesus never said that not to fight,&lt;ref name=&quot;aqa&quot; /&gt; citing examples from the New Testament. One such instance portrays an angry Jesus driving dishonest market [[Cleansing of the Temple|traders from the temple]].&lt;ref name=&quot;aqa&quot; /&gt;  A frequently quoted passage is Luke 22:36: &quot;He said to them, 'But now, the one who has a purse must take it, and likewise a bag. And the one who has no sword must [[Sell your cloak and buy a sword|sell his cloak and buy one]].'&quot; Others have interpreted the non-pacifist statements in the New Testament to be related to [[self-defense]] or to be metaphorical and state that on no occasion did Jesus shed blood or urge others to shed blood.&lt;ref name=&quot;weidhorn&quot; /&gt;

===Roman Empire===
Panda was a god of peace (according to a gloss by Philoxenos).&lt;ref&gt;Charlton T. Lewis &amp; Charles Short : ''A Latin Dictionary''. Oxford : Clarendon Press, 1879. s.v. &quot;Panda&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

Several Roman writers rejected the militarism of Roman society and gave voice to anti-war sentiments, &lt;ref name=&quot;fsn&quot;&gt; &lt;/ref&gt; 
including [[Propertius]], [[Tibullus]] and [[Ovid]]. &lt;ref&gt;''Restless Youth in Ancient Rome'', Emiel Eyben,
Routledge, 2004 ISBN 0203168488,  p. 194.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Stoicism|Stoic]] [[Seneca the Younger]] criticised warfare in his book ''[[Naturales quaestiones]]''
(circa 65 AD).&lt;ref&gt;''Panorama of the Classical World'' by Nigel Spivey and Michael Squire. Getty Publications, 2011,
ISBN 1-60606-056-2 (p.200).&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Maximilian (martyr)|Maximilian of Tebessa]] was a conscientious objector. He was killed for refusing to be conscripted.
&lt;ref&gt;''The Riddle of Saint Maximilian of Tebessa'' by Peter Brock. University of Toronto Press, 2000.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cathars===
Known in the Balkans as [[Bogomils]] and in northern Italy and southern France as [[Cathars]], they were pacifists totally dedicated to nonviolence. The Cathars were actually branded heretics, persecuted, and eventually annihilated by the Catholic Church through the [[Albigensian Crusade]] and the Inquisition that followed.&lt;ref&gt;Joseph Reese Strayer (1992). &quot;''[http://books.google.com/books?id=lskGFVtySXsC&amp;pg=PA143&amp;dq&amp;hl=en#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false The Albigensian Crusades]''&quot;. [[University of Michigan Press]]. p.143. ISBN 0-472-06476-2&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;These heretics are worse than the [[saracen]]s&quot; exclaimed Pope Innocent III, and on March 10, 1208, after the murder of the papal legate [[Pierre de Castelnau]], probably by [[Raymond VI, Count of Toulouse]], the pope took full advantage of it and proclaimed a crusade against a sect in southern France.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,897752-1,00.html Massacre of the Pure].&quot; ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]''. 28 April 1961.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Modern history==
[[File:Edward Hicks - Penn's Treaty.jpeg|thumb|right|[[Penn Treaty Park|Penn's Treaty]] with the Indians. This treaty was never violated.]]
Beginning in the 16th century, the [[Protestant Reformation]] gave rise to a variety of new Christian sects, including the [[Peace churches|historic peace churches]]. Foremost among them were the [[Religious Society of Friends]] (Quakers), [[Amish]], [[Mennonites]] and [[Church of the Brethren]]. After its founding by Quaker pacifist [[William Penn]], Quaker-controlled colonial Pennsylvania employed an anti-militarist public policy. Unlike residents of many of the colonies, Quakers chose to trade peacefully with the Indians, including for land. The colonial province was, for the 75 years from 1681 to 1756, essentially unarmed and experienced little or no warfare in that period.

The humanist writer [[Desiderius Erasmus]] was one of the most outspoken pacifists of the [[Renaissance]], arguing strongly against warfare in his essays ''[[The Praise of Folly]]'' (1509) and ''[[The Complaint of Peace]]'' (1517). &lt;ref name=&quot;fsn&quot;&gt; &lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;&quot;Erasmus, Desiderius&quot; by Garrett L. McAinsh, in ''The World Encyclopedia of Peace''.Edited by [[Linus Pauling]], [[Ervin László]], and [[Jong Youl Yoo]]. Oxford : Pergamon, 1986. ISBN 0-08-032685-4, (Volume 1, p.293).&lt;/ref&gt; 

From the 16th to the 18th centuries, a number of thinkers devised plans for an international organisation that would promote peace, and reduce or even eliminate the occurrence of war. These included the French politician [[Maximilien de Béthune, Duke of Sully|Duc de Sully]], the philosophers [[Émeric Crucé]] and the 
[[Charles-Irénée Castel de Saint-Pierre|Abbe de Saint-Pierre]], and the Quakers William Penn and [[John Bellers]].&lt;ref&gt;''Power and the Pursuit of Peace: Theory and Practice in the History of Relations between States'', by [[Francis Harry Hinsley]], Cambridge University Press, 1967, ISBN 0-521-09448-8, (pp. 13-45).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Thinking About Peace in History&quot; by [[Charles Chatfield]], in ''The Pacifist Impulse in Historical Perspective : Essays in Honour of Peter Brock'',  edited by [[Harvey L. Dyck]]. Toronto, University of Toronto Press, 1996, ISBN 0-8020-0777-5 (p.36-51).&lt;/ref&gt; These internationalist ideas influenced both [[Jean-Jacques Rousseau]], who promoted Saint-Pierre's plan, (while criticising many aspects of it), in ''Extrait du Projet de Paix Perpetuelle de Monsieur l'Abbe Saint-Pierre'' (1756),&lt;ref&gt;Hinsley, pp. 46-61.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Immanuel Kant]], in his ''Thoughts on Perpetual Peace''.&lt;ref&gt;Hinsley, 
pp.62-80.&lt;/ref&gt;   

Bohemian [[Bernard Bolzano]] (1781–1848) taught about the social waste of militarism and the needlessness of war. He urged a total reform of the educational, social, and economic systems that would direct the nation's interests toward peace rather than toward armed conflict between nations.

===Nineteenth century===

In the aftermath of the [[Napoleonic Wars]], a number of [[peace society|peace societies]] were set up to prevent future conflicts. The first such movements were the [[New York Peace Society]], founded in 1815 by the theologian [[David Low Dodge]], and the [[Massachusetts Peace Society]]. These groups merged with other US peace groups in 1828 to form the [[American Peace Society]].&lt;ref&gt;''Pacifism to 1914 : an overview'' by Peter Brock. Toronto, Thistle Printing, 1994. (pp. 38-9).&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Peace Society|London Peace Society]] (also known as the Society for the Promotion of Permanent and Universal Peace) was formed in 1816 with similar aims, and in
the 1840s, British women formed &quot;Olive Leaf Circles&quot;, groups of around 15 to 20 women, who discussed and promoted pacifist ideas.&lt;ref&gt;''The Long Road to Greenham : Feminism and Anti-Militarism in Britain since 1820'', by [[Jill Liddington]]. London, Virago, 1989 ISBN 0-86068-688-4 (pp. 14-5).&lt;/ref&gt;   

Russian writer [[Leo Tolstoy]] was a fervent advocate of pacifism. In one of his latter works, ''[[The Kingdom of God is Within You]]'', Tolstoy provides a detailed history, account and defense of pacifism. Tolstoy's work inspired a [[Tolstoyan movement|movement named after him]] advocating pacifism to arise in Russia and elsewhere.&lt;ref&gt;''Tolstoy's Pacifism'', by [[Colm McKeogh]], Cambria Press, 2009, ISBN 1-60497-634-9, (pp.105-107).&lt;/ref&gt; The book was a major early influence on [[Mohandas K. Gandhi]] (1869–1948), and the two engaged in regular correspondence while Gandhi was active in South Africa.&lt;ref&gt;''Pacifism in the Twentieth Century'', by [[Peter Brock]] and [[Nigel Young]]. Syracuse University Press, New York, 1999 ISBN 0-8156-8125-9 (p.73)&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Bertha von Suttner]], the first woman to be a [[Nobel Peace Prize]] laureate, became a leading figure in the peace movement with the publication of her novel, ''Die Waffen nieder!'' (&quot;Lay Down Your Arms!&quot;) in 1889 and founded an Austrian pacifist organization in 1891.

===Resistance to colonialism===
In [[New Zealand]], during the latter half of the 19th century British colonists used many tactics to confiscate land from the indigenous [[Māori people|Māori]], including warfare. In the 1870s and 1880s, [[Parihaka]], then reputed to be the largest Māori village in New Zealand, became the centre of a major campaign of non-violent resistance to European occupation of confiscated land in the area. One Māori leader, [[Te Whiti-o-Rongomai]], inspired warriors to stand up for their rights without using weapons, which had led to defeat in the past. In 1881 he convinced 2000 Maori to welcome battle-hardened British soldiers into their village and even offered food and drink. He allowed himself and his people to be arrested without resistance for opposing land confiscation. He is remembered as a great leader because the &quot;passive resistance&quot; he practiced prevented British massacres and even protected far more land than violent resistance.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pukeariki.com/en/stories/conflict/pacifistofparihaka.htm Winder, Virginia, “Conflict and Protest  - Pacifist of Parihaka - Te Whiti o Rongomai”]&lt;/ref&gt;
 [[Image:WeFightCartoon.jpg|thumb|300px|right|&quot;Leading Citizens want War and declare War; Citizens Who are Led fight the War&quot; 1910 cartoon]]

[[Mohandas K. Gandhi]] was a major political and spiritual leader of India, instrumental in the [[Indian independence movement]]. The Nobel prize winning great poet [[Rabindranath Tagore]], who was also an Indian, gave him the honorific  &quot;[[Mahatma]]&quot;, usually translated &quot;Great Soul.&quot; He was the pioneer of a brand of nonviolence (or ''[[ahimsa]]'') which he called ''[[satyagraha]]'' --translated literally as &quot;truth force&quot;. This was the resistance of tyranny through civil disobedience that was not only nonviolent but also sought to change the heart of the opponent. He contrasted this with ''duragraha'', &quot;resistant force,&quot; which sought only to change behaviour with stubborn protest.

During his 30 years of work (1917–1947) for the independence of his country from the [[British Raj]], Gandhi led dozens of nonviolent campaigns, spent over seven years in prison, and [[hunger strike|fasted nearly to the death]] on several occasions to obtain British compliance with a demand or to stop inter-communal violence.  His efforts helped lead India to independence in 1947, and inspired movements for civil rights and freedom worldwide.

===World War I===
There was strong antiwar sentiment in Western Europe during the 19th century and leading up to World War I.  In Britain prominent peace activist [[Stephen Henry Hobhouse]] went to prison for refusing military service, citing his convictions as an &quot;International Socialist and a Christian&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Hochschild, Adam, ''To end all wars : a story of loyalty and rebellion, 1914-1918'', p. 277, Boston: Houghton Mifflin Harcourt, 2011, ISBN 0618758283&lt;/ref&gt; Many [[socialism|socialist]] groups and movements were [[antimilitarist]], arguing that war by its nature was a type of governmental coercion of the [[working class]] for the benefit of [[capitalism|capitalist]] elites. The French socialist pacifist leader [[Jean Jaurès]] was assassinated by a nationalist fanatic on July 31, 1914.  The national parties in the [[Second International]] increasingly supported their respective nations in war and the International was dissolved in 1916.  Nevertheless many groups protested against the war, including the traditional peace churches, the [[Woman's Peace Party]] (which was organized in 1915 and led by noted reformer [[Jane Addams]]) and the [[International Committee of Women for Permanent Peace]] (ICWPP) (also organized in 1915).&lt;ref&gt;
[http://www.binghamton.edu/womhist/milit/intro.htm Pacifism vs. Patriotism in Women's Organizations in the 1920s].&lt;/ref&gt; Other groups included the [[American Union Against Militarism]], the [[Fellowship of Reconciliation]], and the [[American Friends Service Committee]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_gx5215/is_2002/ai_n19132457/pg_2 Chatfield, Charles, “Encyclopedia of American Foreign Policy” 2002].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jeanette Rankin]], the first woman elected to Congress, was another fierce advocate of pacifism, the only person to vote no to America's entrance into both World Wars.

===Between the two World Wars===
In the aftermath of [[World War I]], there was a great revulsion against war, leading to the formation of [[War Resisters' International]]&lt;ref&gt;''Radical Pacifism: The War Resisters League and Gandhian Nonviolence in America, 1915-1963'' by Scott H. Bennett. New York, Syracuse  University Press, 2003, ISBN 0-8156-3028-X, p.18.&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Women's International League for Peace and Freedom]], and in Britain the [[No More War Movement]] and the [[Peace Pledge Union]] (PPU). The [[League of Nations]] convened several disarmament conferences in the inter-war period.

The British [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]] had a strong pacifist wing in the early 1930s and between 1931 and 1935 was led by [[George Lansbury]], a Christian pacifist who later chaired the No More War Movement and was president of the PPU. The 1933 annual conference resolved unanimously to &quot;pledge itself to take no part in war&quot;. &quot;Labour's official position, however, although based on the aspiration towards a world socialist commonwealth and the outlawing of war, did not imply a renunciation of force under all circumstances, but rather support for the ill-defined concept of 'collective security' under the League of Nations. At the same time, on the party's left, [[Stafford Cripps]]'s small but vocal [[Socialist League (UK, 1932)|Socialist League]] opposed the official policy, on the non-pacifist ground that the League of Nations was 'nothing but the tool of the satiated imperialist powers'.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://eric.exeter.ac.uk/exeter/bitstream/10036/26952/3/Rearmament.pdf Richard Toye, ''The Labour Party and the Economics of Rearmament, 1935-1939'']&lt;/ref&gt; Lansbury was eventually persuaded to resign as Labour leader by the non-pacifist wing of the party and was replaced by [[Clement Attlee]].&lt;ref&gt;Rhiannon Vickers, ''Labour and the World'',  Manchester University Press, 2004 ISBN 0-7190-6745-6  ISBN 978-0-7190-6745-7&lt;/ref&gt;  As the threat from [[Nazi Germany]] increased in the 1930s, the Labour Party abandoned its pacifist position and supported re-armament, largely due to the efforts of [[Ernest Bevin]] and [[Hugh Dalton]] who by 1937 had also persuaded the party to oppose [[Neville Chamberlain]]'s policy of [[appeasement]].&lt;ref&gt;A.J.Davies, ''To Build A New Jerusalem: The British Labour Party from Keir Hardie to Tony Blair'', Abacus, 1996&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Berkeley, California. University of California Student Peace Strike. About half of the students assembled at the... - NARA - 532103.tif|thumb|200px|A peace strike rally at [[University of California]], Berkeley, April 1940]]
In the [[Soviet Union]], pacifism was initially tolerated. However with the advent of [[Joseph Stalin]]'s rule, while a pro-Soviet &quot;peace movement&quot; was allowed to operate abroad, &quot;home-grown pacifism was ruthlessly suppressed&quot;; all Soviet pacifist organisations were closed down by 1929. Stalin's regime also removed the law permitting [[conscientious objectors]] to serve in noncombatant roles in the [[Red Army]].&lt;ref&gt;Brock and Young, pp. 94-5.&lt;/ref&gt; A number of Tolstoyan pacifists were known to be among prisoners in the [[gulags]] in the 1940s and 1950s.
&lt;ref name=&quot;nsleu&quot;&gt;''Notes sur l'anarchisme en U.R.S.S : De 1921 à nos jours''.Les Cahiers du Vent du Chemin. Paris,1983.&lt;/ref&gt;

A noted [[Canadian pacifist]] was the politician [[J. S. Woodsworth]], who called for the strengthening of the [[League of Nations]] to ensure world peace. Woodsworth also called for the use of [[economic sanctions]] against states that committed aggression, such as Italy when it [[Second Italo-Abyssinian War|invaded Abyssinia]].&lt;ref&gt;''Fool for Christ:The Political Thought of J.S. Woodsworth'' by Allen Mills. Toronto, Ontario: University of Toronto Press, 1991. ISBN 0-8020-6842-1&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Agnes Macphail]], another noted Canadian pacifist, was the first woman to be elected to the [[Canadian House of Commons]]. Macphail objected to the [[Royal Military College of Canada]] in 1931 on pacific grounds.&lt;ref&gt;Preston `Canada`s RMC: A History of the Royal Military College` (University of Toronto Press, Toronto, 1969)&lt;/ref&gt; Macphail was also the first Canadian woman delegate to the League of Nations, where she worked with the World Disarmament Committee. Although a pacifist, she voted for Canada to enter [[World War II]].

The [[Spanish Civil War]] proved a major test for international pacifism, and the work of pacifist organisations (such as [[War Resisters' International]] and the [[Fellowship of Reconciliation]]) and individuals (such as [[José Brocca]] and [[Amparo Poch y Gascón|Amparo Poch]]) in that arena has until recently{{when|date=May 2011}} been ignored or forgotten by historians, overshadowed by the memory of the [[International Brigades]] and other militaristic interventions. Shortly after the war ended, [[Simone Weil]], despite having volunteered for service on the republican side, went on to publish ''[[The Iliad or the Poem of Force]]'', a work that has been described as a pacifist manifesto.&lt;ref name = &quot;NYB&quot;&gt;
{{Cite web
|url= http://www.nybooks.com/shop/product?usca_p=t&amp;product_id=4551
|title= War and the Iliad
|publisher=The New York Review of books
|accessdate=29 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In response to the threat of fascism, some pacifist thinkers, such as [[Richard B. Gregg]], devised plans for a campaign of [[nonviolent resistance]] in the event of a fascist invasion or takeover.&lt;ref&gt;Lynd, Staughton. ''Nonviolence in America: a documentary history'',Bobbs-Merrill, 1966, (pps. 271-296).&lt;/ref&gt;

===World War II===
With the start of [[World War II]], pacifist and anti-war sentiment declined in nations affected by war. Even the communist-controlled [[American Peace Mobilization]] reversed its anti-war activism once Germany invaded the Soviet Union in 1941. After the [[Japanese attack on Pearl Harbor]], mainstream [[isolationist]] groups like the [[America First Committee]], declined, but many smaller religious and socialist groups continued their opposition to war. [[Bertrand Russell]] argued that the necessity of defeating [[Adolf Hitler]] and the [[Nazis]] was a unique circumstance where war was not the worst of the possible evils; he called his position ''relative pacifism''. [[H. G. Wells]], who had joked after the armistice ending [[World War I]] that the British had suffered more from the war than they would have from submission to [[Germany]], urged in 1941 a large-scale British offensive on the continent of Europe to combat Hitler and [[Nazism]].{{citation needed|date=September 2010}} Similarly [[Albert Einstein]] wrote: &quot;I loathe all armies and any kind of violence; yet I'm firmly convinced that at present these hateful weapons offer the only effective protection.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Quoted on [http://www.ppu.org.uk/learn/infodocs/people/pp-einstein2.html Albert Einstein] at Peace Pledge Union, and but also discussed in detail in articles in Einstein, Albert (1954), ''Ideas and Opinions'', New York: Random House, ISBN 0-517-00393-7&lt;/ref&gt;

Pacifists in the [[Third Reich]] were dealt with harshly; German pacifist [[Carl von Ossietzky]],&lt;ref&gt;Brock and Young, p.99.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Olaf Kullmann]], a Norwegian pacifist active during the Nazi occupation,&lt;ref&gt;Brock and Socknat, pp. 402-3.&lt;/ref&gt; were both imprisoned in concentration camps and died as a result of their mistreatment there. Austrian farmer [[Franz Jägerstätter]] was executed in 1943 for refusing to serve in the [[Wehrmacht]].&lt;ref&gt;''[[In Solitary Witness: The Life and Death of Franz Jägerstätter]]'' by [[Gordon Zahn]].Springfield, Illinois: Templegate Publishers. ISBN 0-87243-141-X.&lt;/ref&gt; 

There were [[conscientious objectors]] and war [[tax resisters]] in both [[World War I]] and [[World War II]].  The United States government allowed sincere objectors to serve in noncombatant military roles. However, those [[draft dodgers|draft resisters]] who refused any cooperation with the war effort often spent much of each war in federal prisons. During World War II, pacifist leaders like [[Dorothy Day]] and [[Ammon Hennacy]] of the [[Catholic Worker Movement]] urged young Americans not to enlist in military service.

===Later twentieth century===
[[File:Vietnamdem.jpg|thumb|A demonstrator offers a flower to military police at an [[Opposition to Vietnam War|anti-Vietnam War protest]], 1967]]
[[Martin Luther King, Jr]] (1929–1968), a [[Baptist]] [[Minister of religion|minister]], led the [[American Civil Rights Movement (1955-1968)|American civil rights movement]] which successfully used Gandhian [[nonviolent resistance]] to repeal laws enforcing racial segregation and work for integration of schools, businesses and government. In 1957, his wife [[Coretta Scott King]], [[Albert Schweitzer]], [[Benjamin Spock]], and others formed the Committee for a Sane Nuclear Policy (now [[Peace Action]]) to resist the [[nuclear arms race]]. In 1958 British activists formed the [[Campaign for Nuclear Disarmament]] with Bertrand Russell as its president.

In 1960, [[Thich Nhat Hanh]] came to the US to study [[comparative religion]] at [[Princeton University]] and subsequently was appointed lecturer in Buddhism at [[Columbia University]]. Thich Nhat Hanh had written a letter to Martin Luther King in 1965 entitled &quot;Searching for the Enemy of Man&quot; and during his 1966 stay in the US met with King and urged him to publicly denounce the [[Vietnam War]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Searching for the Enemy of Man&quot;, in Nhat Nanh, Ho Huu Tuong, Tam Ich, Bui Giang, Pham Cong Thien. ''Dialogue''. Saigon: La Boi, 1965. P. 11-20., archived on the African-American Involvement in the Vietnam War website, [http://www.aavw.org/protest/king_journey_abstract09.html King's Journey: 1964 - April 4, 1967]&lt;/ref&gt; King gave his famous speech at the [[Riverside Church]] in [[New York City]] in 1967,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.aavw.org/special_features/speeches_speech_king01.html Beyond Vietnam]&quot;, 4 April 1967, speech made by Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. at the Riverside Church, NYC, archived on the African-American Involvement in the Vietnam War website&lt;/ref&gt; his first to publicly question the U.S. involvement in Vietnam.

Other examples from this period include the 1986 [[People Power Revolution]] in the [[Philippines]] led by [[Cory Aquino]], and the 1989 [[Tiananmen Square Protests]] which included the broadly publicized &quot;[[Tank Man]]&quot; incident.

===Costa Rica===
On December 1, 1948, President [[José Figueres Ferrer]] of [[Costa Rica]] abolished the [[military of Costa Rica|Costa Rica’s military]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/2019.htm Costa Rica]&quot;. U.S. Department of State.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1949, the abolition of the military was introduced in Article 12 of the Costa Rican Constitution. Unlike its neighbors, Costa Rica has not endured a [[civil war]] since 1948. Figueres later remarked with justifiable pride that such reforms gave Costa Rica a deeper and more human revolution than that of Cuba.&lt;ref&gt;''Costa Rica's Fierce Pacifist'', The [[New York Times]] June 17, 1990; Section 4; Page 20, Column 1&lt;/ref&gt; The budget previously dedicated to the military now is dedicated to providing health care services and education.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.nytimes.com/2010/01/07/opinion/07kristof.html?_r=1 The Happiest People]&quot;. The New York Times. January 6, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Religion==
===Ahmadiyya===
{{Further|Ahmadiyya view on Jihad}}
According to the [[Ahmadiyya]] understanding of Islam, pacifism is a strong current, and jihad is one's personal inner struggle and should not be used violently for political motives. Violence is the last option only to be used to protect religion and one's own life in extreme situations of persecution. [[Mirza Ghulam Ahmad]], the founder of the Ahmadiyya Muslim Community, said that in contrary to the current views, Islam ''does not allow the use of sword in religion, except in the case of defensive wars, wars waged to punish a tyrant, or those meant to uphold freedom''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.alislam.org/library/articles/Jihad-Brochure.pdf|title=Jihad the True Islamic Concept|accessdate=9 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ahmadiyya claims its objective to be the peaceful propagation of [[Islam]] with special emphasis on spreading the true message of Islam by the pen. Ahmadis point out that as per prophecy, who they believe was the promised messiah, Mirza Ghulam Ahmad, rendered the concept of violent jihad unnecessary in modern times. They believe that the answer of hate should be given by love.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.alislam.org/library/links/00000064.html|title=Jihad of the Pen|accessdate=9 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Bahá'í Faith===
[[Bahá'u'lláh]], the founder of the [[Bahá'í Faith]] abolished [[religious war|holy war]] and emphasized its abolition as a central teaching of his faith.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| url = http://bahai-library.com/wilmette_lawh_ridvan_notes | last = Troxel | first = Duane |coauthors = Cole, Juan; Lambden, Stephen | title = Tablet of Ridván: Wilmette Institute faculty notes | date =17 October 2003 | accessdate = 13 September 2006 | publisher = bahai-library.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the Bahá'í Faith does not have an absolute pacifistic position. For example Bahá'ís are advised to do social service instead of active army service, but when this is not possible because of obligations in certain countries, the [[Bahá'í laws|Bahá'í law]] of ''loyalty to one's government'' is preferred and the individual should perform the army service.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| url = http://bahai-library.com/mazal_comparison_christianity_bahai&amp;chapter=1 | title = Selected Topics of Comparison in Christianity and the Bahá'í Faith | accessdate = 13 September 2006 | first = Peter | last = Mazal | date = 21 October 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ud1&quot;&gt;{{Cite book| url=http://reference.bahai.org/en/t/se/UD/ud-136.html | first = Shoghi | last = Effendi | authorlink = Shoghi Effendi|title = Unfolding Destiny|pages = 134–135}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Shoghi Effendi]], the Guardian of the Bahá'í Faith, noted that in the Bahá'í view, absolute pacifists are anti-social and exalt the individual over society which could lead to anarchy; instead he noted that the Bahá'í conception of social life follows a moderate view where the individual is not suppressed or exalted.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| url = http://reference.bahai.org/en/t/se/DG/dg-144.html#gr1 | title = Directives from the Guardian | last = Effendi | first = Shoghi | authorlink = Shoghi Effendi | pages = 53–54 | publisher = Baha'i Publishing Trust | location = India}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the level of society, Bahá'u'lláh promotes the principle of [[collective security]], which does not abolish the use of force, but prescribes &quot;a system in which Force is made the servant of Justice.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|first=Shoghi
 |last=Effendi |authorlink= Shoghi Effendi |year= 1938 |title= The World Order of Bahá’u’lláh |publisher=Bahá'í Publishing Trust |location=Wilmette, Illinois, USA |isbn= 0-87743-231-7 |url= http://reference.bahai.org/en/t/se/WOB/wob-52.html#gr1 | pages = 191–203}}&lt;/ref&gt; The idea of collective security from the Bahá'í teachings states that if a government violates a fundamental norm of international law or provision of a future world constitution which Bahá'ís believe will be established by all nations, then the other governments should step in.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal| first = Danesh |last = Sarooshi | year = 1994 | title = Search for a Just Society, Review | journal = Baha'i Studies Review | volume = 4 | issue = 1 | url = http://bahai-library.com/saroosh_huddleston_just_society | accessdate = 13 September 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Buddhism===
{{Main|Buddhism and violence}} 
Buddhist [[Aung San Suu Kyi]] is a [[nonviolence|nonviolent]] pro-democracy activist and leader of the [[National League for Democracy]] in [[Myanmar]] (Burma). A devout [[Buddhism|Buddhist]], Suu Kyi won the [[Rafto Prize]] and the [[Sakharov Prize|Sakharov Prize for Freedom of Thought]] in 1990 and in 1991 was awarded the [[Nobel Peace Prize]] for her peaceful and non-violent struggle under a repressive [[military dictatorship]]. One of her best known speeches is the &quot;Freedom From Fear&quot; speech, which begins, &quot;It is not power that corrupts but fear. Fear of losing power corrupts those who wield it and fear of the scourge of power corrupts those who are subject to it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url= http://nobelprize.org/peace/laureates/1991/kyi-bio.html |title=Aung San Suu Kyi — Biography |publisher=Nobel Foundation |accessdate=4 May 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Christianity===
{{Main|Christian pacifism}}
[[File:Blessed are the Peacemakers.gif|alt=|thumb|right|''Blessed are the Peacemakers'' (1917) by [[George Bellows]]]]
[[File:The Deserter.jpg|alt=|thumb|''The Deserter'' (1916) by [[Boardman Robinson]].]]

====Peace churches====
[[Peace churches]] are Christian denominations explicitly advocating pacifism.  The term &quot;historic peace churches&quot; refers specifically to three church traditions: the [[Church of the Brethren]], the [[Mennonites]] (and some other [[Anabaptists]], such as [[Amish]] and [[Hutterites]]), and the [[Quakers]] (Religious Society of Friends). The historic peace churches have, from their origins as far back as the 16th century, always taken the position that [[Jesus]] was himself a pacifist who explicitly taught and practiced pacifism, and that his followers must do likewise. Pacifist churches vary on whether physical force can ever be justified in [[self-defense]] or protecting others, as many adhere strictly to [[nonresistance]] when confronted by violence.  But all agree that violence on behalf of a country or a government is prohibited for Christians.

====Pentecostal churches====
Jay Beaman's thesis&lt;ref name='beaman'&gt;Beaman, J: Pentecostal Pacifism: The Origin, Development, and Rejection of Pacific Belief among the Pentecostals, Center for Mennonite Brethren Studies, Hillsboro, Kansas, 1989&lt;/ref&gt; states that 13 of 21, or 62% of American Pentecostal groups formed by 1917 show evidence of being pacifist sometime in their history. Furthermore Jay Beaman has shown in his thesis&lt;ref name='beaman'/&gt; that there has been a shift away from pacifism in the American Pentecostal churches to more a style of military chaplaincy and support of war.  The major organisation for Pentecostal Christians who believe in pacifism is the PCPF, the [[Pentecostal Charismatic Peace Fellowship]].

The [[United Pentecostal Church]], an Apostolic/Oneness denomination, is the largest Pentecostal organization that takes an official stand of pacifism: its Articles of Faith read, &quot;We are constrained to declare against participating in combatant service in war, armed insurrection... aiding or abetting in or the actual destruction of human life.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.spiritualabuse.org/aof.html&lt;/ref&gt;

====Other Christian denominations====
The [[Peace Pledge Union]] was a pacifist organisation from which the Anglican Pacifist Fellowship (APF) later emerged within the Anglican Church. The APF succeeded in gaining ratification of the pacifist position at two successive [[Lambeth Conferences]], but many Anglicans would not regard themselves as pacifists. South African Bishop [[Desmond Tutu]] is the most prominent Anglican pacifist. [[Rowan Williams]] led an almost united Anglican Church in Britain in opposition to the 2003 [[Iraq War]].  In Australia [[Peter Carnley]] similarly led a front of bishops opposed to the [[Government of Australia]]'s involvement in the invasion of Iraq.

[[Image:Constantines-Sword.png|thumb|right|The shadow of the cross symbolizes the connection between religion and war in ''[[Constantine's Sword|Constantine's Sword (film)]]''.]]The [[Catholic Worker Movement]] is concerned with both social justice and pacifist issues, and voiced consistent opposition to the [[Spanish Civil War]] and World War II. Many of its early members were imprisoned for their opposition to [[conscription]].&lt;ref&gt;Catholic Worker Movement http://www.catholicworker.org&lt;/ref&gt; Within the Roman Catholic Church, the [[Pax Christi]] organisation is the premiere pacifist lobby group. It holds positions similar to APF, and the two organisations are known to work together on ecumenical projects. Within Roman Catholicism there has been a discernible move towards a more pacifist position through the twentieth and early twenty-first centuries. Popes [[Pope Benedict XV|Benedict XV]], [[Pope John XXIII|John XXIII]] and [[Pope John Paul II|John Paul II]] were all vocal in their opposition to specific wars. By taking the name [[Pope Benedict XVI|Benedict XVI]], some suspect that [[Pope Benedict XVI|Joseph Ratzinger]] will continue the strong emphasis upon nonviolent conflict resolution of his predecessor. However, the Roman Catholic Church officially maintains the legitimacy of Just War, which is rejected by some pacifists.

In the twentieth century there was a notable trend among prominent Roman Catholics towards pacifism.  Individuals such as [[Dorothy Day]] and [[Henri Nouwen]] stand out among them. The monk and mystic [[Thomas Merton]] was noted for his commitment to pacifism during the [[Vietnam War]] era.  Murdered [[El Salvador|Salvadoran]] Bishop [[Oscar Romero]] was notable for using non-violent resistance tactics and wrote meditative sermons focusing on the power of prayer and peace. [[School of the Americas Watch]] was founded by Maryknoll Fr. Roy Bourgeois in 1990 and uses strictly pacifist principles to protest the training of Latin American military officers by United States Army officers at the School of the Americas in the state of Georgia.

The [[Greek Orthodox Church]] also tends towards pacifism, though it has accepted defensive warfare through most of its history. However, more recently{{when|date=May 2011}} it took a strong stance towards the war in Lebanon and its large community there refused to take up arms during its civil wars. It also supports dialogue with Islam.  In 1998 the Third Pre-conciliar Pan-Orthodox Conference drew up a text on &quot;the contribution of the Orthodox Church to the achievement of peace&quot; emphasizing respect for the human person and the inseparability of peace from justice. The text states in part: &quot;Orthodoxy condemns war in general, for she regards it as a consequence of the evil and sin in the world.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.incommunion.org/articles/for-the-peace-from-above/the-orthodox-church-and-peace Clément, Olivier, &quot;The Orthodox Church and Peace Some Reflections&quot;] on the Orthodox Peace Fellowship website.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Southern Baptist Convention]] has stated in the [[Baptist Faith and Message]], &quot;It is the duty of Christians to seek peace with all men on principles of [[righteousness]]. In accordance with the spirit and teachings of Christ they should do all in their power to put an end to war.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sbc.net/bfm/bfm2000.asp#xvi SBC, “ Baptist Faith and Message 2000”]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[United Methodist Church]] explicitly supports conscientious objection by its members &quot;as an ethically valid position&quot; while simultaneously allowing for differences of opinion and belief for those who do not object to military service.&lt;ref&gt;Article V, section 2 of [http://archives.umc.org/interior.asp?ptid=4&amp;mid=989 The United Methodist Church and Peace]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Jainism===
[[Ahimsa in Jainism|Compassion for all life, human and non-human]], is central to [[Jainism]]. Human life is valued as a unique, rare opportunity to reach enlightenment; to kill any person, no matter what crime he may have committed, is considered unimaginably abhorrent. It is a religion that requires monks and laity, from all its sects and traditions, to be [[vegetarian]]. Some Indian regions, such as Gujarat, have been strongly influenced by Jains and often the majority of the local Hindus of every denomination have also become vegetarian.&lt;ref&gt;Titze, Kurt, Jainism: A Pictorial Guide to the Religion of Non-Violence, Mohtilal Banarsidass, 1998&lt;/ref&gt;

===Judaism===
Some pre-Holocaust [[Hasidism|Hasidic]] groups were pacifist.{{Citation needed|date=September 2010}}  The Jewish Peace Fellowship is a New-York based&lt;ref&gt;http://www.jewishdirectory.com/listing/jewish_peace_fellowship_497bb804c2044.html&lt;/ref&gt; [[nonprofit]], [[Jewish denominations|nondenominational]] organization set up to provide a [[Judaism|Jewish]] voice in the [[peace movement]]. The organization was founded in 1941 in order to support Jewish [[conscientious objectors]] who sought exemption from combatant military service.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.jewishpeacefellowship.org/index.php?p=about&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.beyondthepale.org/link/jewish-peace-fellowship&lt;/ref&gt;  It is affiliated to the [[International Fellowship of Reconciliation]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ifor.org/members.htm&lt;/ref&gt;  The small [[Neturei Karta]] group of anti-Zionist, ultra-orthodox Jews, supposedly take a pacifist line, saying that &quot;Jews are not allowed to dominate, kill, harm or demean another people and are not allowed to have anything to do with the Zionist enterprise, their political meddling and their wars.&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nkusa.org/aboutus/index.cfm What is the Neturei Karta?]&lt;/ref&gt; However, the Neturei Karta group do support violent, antisemitic terrorist groups such as [[Hezbollah]] and [[Hamas]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.haaretz.com/news/anti-zionist-ultra-orthodox-jews-celebrate-sabbath-in-gaza-1.265558]&lt;/ref&gt; Most religious Jews in Europe and North America agree with war when reasoning with the enemy does not work. Torah is full of examples when Jews were told to go and war against enemy lands. November 11 is a day a remembrance for many Jews as they honour those who fought to end the Hitler government which starved and burnt over six million Jews to death.

===Raelism===
Non-violence is an important doctrine within [[Raelism]]. The founder of this religion Rael has said &quot;''The one holding the weapon is as responsible as the one giving the orders''&quot;. Other Rael statements include &quot;''even if the Elohim asked them to kill someone they should refuse''&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Aliens adored: Raël's UFO religion - Page 62, Susan J. Palmer - 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

==Government and political movements==
While many governments have tolerated pacifist views and even accommodated pacifists' refusal to fight in wars, others at times have outlawed pacifist and anti-war activity. In 1918, The United States Congress passed the [[Sedition Act of 1918]]. During the periods between World Wars I and World War II, pacifist literature and public advocacy was banned in [[Italy]] under [[Benito Mussolini]], [[Germany]] after the rise of [[Adolf Hitler]],&lt;ref name=&quot;bz&quot;&gt;Benjamin Ziemann, &quot;Pacifism&quot; 
in ''World Fascism:An Encyclopedia'', edited by Cyprian P. Blamires. ABC-CLIO Ltd, 2006.  ISBN 1-57607-940-6 (p.495-6)&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Francoist Spain|Spain]] under [[Francisco Franco]], &lt;ref&gt;Brock and Young, pp. 96-7, 311. &lt;/ref&gt;
and the [[Soviet Union]] under [[Joseph Stalin]].&lt;ref name=&quot;nsleu&quot; /&gt; In these nations, pacifism was denounced as cowardice; indeed, Mussolini referred to pacifist writings as the &quot;propaganda of cowardice&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;bz&quot; /&gt;

Today, the United States requires that all young men register for selective service but does not allow them to be classified as conscientious objectors unless they are drafted in some future reinstatement of the draft. does permits enlisted personnel to become conscientious objectors, allowing them to be discharged or transferred to noncombatant status.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.objector.org/advice/conscientious_objector-6.html#pgfId-183 “Conscientious Objection Today, Central Committee for Conscientious Objectors”]&lt;/ref&gt;  Some European governments like [[Swiss Civilian Service|Switzerland]], [[Greece]], [[Norway]] and [[Germany]] offer [[civilian service]]. However, even during periods of peace, many pacifists still refuse to register for or report for military duty, risking criminal charges.

Anti-war and &quot;pacifist&quot; political parties seeking to win elections may moderate their demands, calling for [[de-escalation]] or major [[arms reduction]] rather than the outright [[disarmament]] which is advocated by many pacifists. [[Green parties]] list &quot;[[non-violence]]&quot; and &quot;[[decentralization]]&quot; towards anarchist co-operatives or minimalist village government as two of their ten key values. However, in power, Greens often compromise. The German Greens in the cabinet of Social Democrat [[Gerhard Schröder]] supported an intervention by German troops in [[Afghanistan]] in 2001 if that they hosted the peace conference in Berlin. However, during the 2002 election Greens forced Schröder to swear that no German troops would invade Iraq.

The controversial [[democratic peace theory]] holds that [[liberal democracies]] have never (or rarely) made war on one another and that lesser conflicts and internal violence are rare between and within democracies. It also argues that the growth in the number of democratic states will, in the not so distant future, end warfare.

Some pacifists and [[multilateralism|multilateralists]] are in favor of international criminal law as  means to prevent and control international aggression. The [[International Criminal Court]] has jurisdiction over war crimes, but the crime of aggression has yet to be clearly defined in international law.

The [[Constitution of Italy|Italian Constitution]] enforces a mild pacifist character on the Italian Republic, as Article 11 states that &quot;Italy repudiates war as an instrument offending the liberty of the peoples and as a means for settling international disputes....&quot; Similarly, Articles 24, 25 and 26 of the German Constitution (1949), Alinea 15 of the French Constitution (1946), Article 20 of the Danish Constitution (1953), Article 9 of the Japanese Constitution (1947) and several other mostly European constitutions correspond to the United Nations Charter by rejecting the institution of war in favour of collective security and peaceful cooperation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ne.jp/asahi/peace/unitednationsreform2007/liste24list_en.html “Constitutional clauses providing for limitations of national sovereignty to achieve cooperation, peace and disarmament”]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Pacifism and abstention from political activity===
However, some pacifists, such as the [[Christian anarchism|Christian anarchist]] [[Leo Tolstoy]] and [[autarchist]] [[Robert LeFevre]], consider the state a form of warfare. In addition, for doctrinal reason that a manmade government is inferior to divine governance and law, many pacifist-identified religious sects also refrain from political activity altogether, including the [[Anabaptists]], [[Jehovah's Witnesses]] and [[Mandaeans]]. This means that such groups refuse to participate in government office or serve under an oath to a government.

===Anarcho-pacifism===
{{Main|Anarcho-pacifism}}
[[File:Henry David Thoreau.jpg|left|thumb|150px|[[Henry David Thoreau]], early proponent of [[anarcho-pacifism]]]]Anarcho-pacifism (also pacifist anarchism or anarchist pacifism) is a form of [[anarchism]] which completely rejects the use of violence in any form for any purpose. The main precedent was [[Henry David Thoreau]] who through his work [[Civil Disobedience (Thoreau)|Civil Disobedience]] influenced the advocacy of both Leo Tolstoy and [[Mohandas Gandhi]] for [[nonviolent resistance]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ppu.org.uk&quot;&gt;[http://www.ppu.org.uk/e_publications/dd-trad8.html#anarch%20and%20violence The pacifist and anarchist tradition by Geoffrey Ostergaard]&lt;/ref&gt; As a global movement, Anarchist pacifism emerged shortly before [[World War II]] in the [[Netherlands]], [[Great Britain]] and the [[United States]] and was a strong presence in the subsequent campaigns for [[nuclear disarmament]].

Violence has always been controversial in anarchism. While many anarchists during the 19th century embraced [[propaganda of the deed]], [[Leo Tolstoy]] and other anarcho-pacifists directly opposed violence as a means for change. He argued that anarchism must by nature be nonviolent since it is, by definition, opposition to coercion and force and since the state is inherently violent, meaningful pacifism must likewise be anarchistic. His philosophy was cited as a major inspiration by [[Mohandas Gandhi]], an [[Indian independence movement|Indian independence]] leader and pacifist who self-identified as an anarchist. [[Ferdinand Domela Nieuwenhuis]] was also instrumental in establishing the pacifist trend within the anarchist movement.&lt;ref name=woodcock&gt;{{Cite book|last=Woodcock |first=George |title=Anarchism: a History of Libertarian Ideas and Movements |publisher=Broadview Press |location=Peterborough |year=2004 |isbn=1-55111-629-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; In France anti-militarism appeared strongly in individualist anarchist circles as [[Émile Armand]] founded &quot;Ligue Antimilitariste&quot; in 1902 with [[Albert Libertad]] and George Mathias Paraf-Javal.

===Opposition to military taxation===
Many pacifists who would be conscientious objectors to military service are also [[tax resistance|opposed to paying taxes]] to fund the military. In the United States, [[The National Campaign for a Peace Tax Fund]] works to pass a national law to allow conscientious objectors to redirect their tax money to be used only for non-military purposes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.peacetaxfund.org/aboutus/mission.htm Mission of National Campaign for a Peace Tax Fund]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticism==
{{Criticism section|date=June 2008}}
One common argument against pacifism is the possibility of using violence to prevent further acts of violence (and reduce the &quot;net-sum&quot; of violence). This argument hinges on [[consequentialism]]: an otherwise morally objectionable action can be justified if it results in a positive outcome. For example, either violent rebellion, or foreign nations sending in troops to end a dictator's violent oppression ''may'' save millions of lives, even if many thousands died in the war. Those pacifists who base their beliefs on [[deontology|deontological]] grounds would oppose such violent action, arguing that nonviolent resistance should be just as effective and with a much lesser loss of life. Others would oppose organized military responses but support individual and small group self-defense against specific attacks if initiated by the dictator's forces. Pacifists may argue that military action could be justified should it subsequently advance the general cause of peace.

Still more pacifists would argue that a nonviolent reaction may not save lives immediately but would in the long run. The acceptance of violence for any reason makes it easier to use in other situations. Learning and committing to pacifism helps to send a message that violence is, in fact, not the most effective way. It can also help people to think more creatively and find more effective ways to stop violence without more violence.

In light of the common criticism of pacifism as not offering a clear alternative policy, one approach to finding &quot;more effective ways&quot; has been the attempt to develop the idea of &quot;defence by [[civil resistance]]&quot;, also called &quot;[[social defence]]&quot;. This idea, which is not necessarily dependent on acceptance of pacifist beliefs, is based on relying on [[nonviolent resistance]] against possible threats, whether external (such as invasion) or internal (such as [[coup d'état]]).

There have been some works on this topic, including by [[Adam Roberts (scholar)|Adam Roberts]]&lt;ref&gt;Adam Roberts, ed. ''The Strategy of Civilian Defence: Non-violent Resistance to Aggression'', Faber, London, 1967. (Also published as ''Civilian Resistance as a National Defense'', Stackpole Books, Harrisburg, USA, 1968; and, with a new Introduction on &quot;Czechoslovakia and Civilian Defence&quot;, as ''Civilian Resistance as a National Defence'', Penguin Books, Harmondsworth, UK, and Baltimore, USA, 1969. ISBN 0-14-021080-6.)&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Gene Sharp]].&lt;ref&gt;Gene Sharp, ''Social Power and Political Freedom'', Porter Sargent, Boston, 1980, pp. 195-261. ISBN 0-87558-093-9 (paperback); and ''Civilian-based Defence: A Post-military Weapons System'', Princeton University Press, 1990. ISBN 0-691-07809-2.&lt;/ref&gt; However, no country has adopted this approach as the sole basis of its defence.&lt;ref&gt;[[Adam Roberts (scholar)|Adam Roberts]], in Roberts and Garton Ash (ed.), ''Civil Resistance and Power Politics'', Introduction, p.12.&lt;/ref&gt; (For further information and sources see [[social defence]].)

Japanese, Italian and Nazi aggression that precipitated World War II often is cited {{By whom|date=June 2010}}as an argument against pacifism. If these forces had not been challenged and defeated militarily, the argument goes, many more people would have died under their oppressive rule. [[Adolf Hitler]] told the British Foreign Secretary [[Lord Halifax]] in 1937 that the British should &quot;shoot Gandhi, and if this doesn't suffice to reduce them to submission, shoot a dozen leading members of the Congress, and if that doesn't suffice shoot 200, and so on, as you make it clear that you mean business.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Ghose, Sankar (1992). ''Jawaharlal Nehru, A Biography'', [http://books.google.com/books?id=MUeyUhVGIDMC&amp;pg=PA138&amp;dq&amp;hl=en#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false p.138]. Allied Publishers Limited.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Hermann Göring]] described, during an interview at the [[Nuremberg Trials]], how denouncing and outlawing pacifism was an important part of the Nazis' seizure of power: &quot;The people can always be brought to the bidding of the leaders. That is easy. All you have to do is tell them they are being attacked and denounce the pacifists for lack of patriotism and exposing the country to danger. It works the same way in any country.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[q:Hermann Göring#Nuremberg Diary (1947)]]&lt;/ref&gt;

Some commentators on the most nonviolent forms of pacifism, including [[Jan Narveson]], argue that such pacifism is a self-contradictory doctrine. Narveson claims that everyone has rights and corresponding responsibilities not to violate others' rights. Since pacifists give up their ability to protect themselves from violation of their right not to be harmed, then other people thus have no corresponding responsibility, thus creating a paradox of rights. Narveson said that &quot;the prevention of infractions of that right is precisely what one has a right to when one has a right at all&quot;. Narveson then discusses how rational persuasion is a good but often inadequate method of discouraging an aggressor. He considers that everyone has the right to use any means necessary to prevent deprivation of their civil liberties and force could be necessary.&lt;ref&gt;Narveson, January 1965. “Pacifism: A Philosophical Analysis.” ''Ethics'', LXXV: 4, pp 259-271.&lt;/ref&gt;

Many pacifists{{Who|date=June 2010}} would argue that not only are there other ways to protect oneself but that some of those ways are far more effective than violence, and that physical harm is not the only variety that can be done. Often pacifists would much rather take the physical harm inflicted by another rather than cause themselves emotional or psychological harm, not to mention harming the other.

The ideology and political practice of pacifism also have been criticized by the radical American activist [[Ward Churchill]], in his essay, ''[[Pacifism as Pathology: Notes on an American Pseudopraxis|Pacifism as Pathology]]''. Churchill argues that the social and political advancements pacifists claim resulted from non-violent action always have been made possible by concurrent violent struggles. In the late 1990s, Churchill's work convinced many anarchist and left-wing activists to adopt what they called &quot;diversity of tactics&quot; using &quot;[[black bloc]]&quot; formations that engage in property destruction and scuffles with police at larger mainstream protests.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| url = http://auto_sol.tao.ca/node/view/1334 | last = Hurl | first = Chris |coauthors = | title = Anti-Globalization and &quot;Diversity of Tactics&quot; | date =17 October 2003 | accessdate = 19 April 2007 | publisher = }} {{Dead link|date=November 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| url = http://www.ohlj.ca/archive/articles/41_23_conway.pdf |format=PDF| last = Conway | first = Janet |coauthors = | title = Civil Resistance and the &quot;Diversity of Tactics&quot; in the Anti-globalization Movement: Problems of Violence, Silence, and Solidarity in Activist Politics | year =2003 | accessdate = 19 April 2007 | publisher = Osgood Hall Law Journal, York University, Toronto, Canada}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One powerful pacifist reply to Churchill was from American activist George Lakey, a founder of [[Movement for a New Society]], in a detailed response to ''Pacifism as Pathology''. Lakey quotes Martin Luther King in entitling his 2001 article ''Nonviolent Action as the Sword that Heals''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| url = http://globalsolidarity.transcend.org/articles/nonviolent.pdf |format=PDF| last = Lakey | first = George |coauthors = | title = Nonviolent Action as the Sword that Heals | year =2001 | accessdate = 19 April 2007 | publisher = TrainingforChange.Org}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, he takes on Churchill's assumptions and reading of history from a pragmatic viewpoint, arguing the superiority of nonviolent action by describing &quot;some movements that learned, from their own pragmatic experience, that they could wage struggle more successfully through nonviolent direct action than through violence.&quot;

In his book ''[[The End of Faith]]'', [[Sam Harris (author)|Sam Harris]] argues that pacifism is a fallacy, combining hesitance with cowardice, in that the social context in which a pacifist can protest was created by the actions of direct activists. In the same philosophical chapter, he goes on to compare the collateral damage that could result from practicing torture with that resulting from errant bombing. He posits that if one is willing to accept the collateral damage that results from the incidental bombing of civilians on the one hand, one cannot denounce the collateral damage resulting from the accidental torture of the innocent on the other. He notes that the only difference between the two is that the revulsion one experiences when directly causing the suffering of another human being is more potent when done in person than when done from the safety of an aircraft or a command center. He brings to light these similarities not to so much to argue for the potential use of torture in combat but to demonstrate the hideousness of both. Ultimately, his book suggests just and humane action must be taken in order to reduce the total suffering of sentient beings.

==See also==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-break}}

* [[Ahimsa]]
* [[Antimilitarism]]
* [[Anti-war]]
* [[Anti-war movement]]
* [[Anarchism]]
* [[Aparigraha]]
* [[Appeasement]]
* [[Catholic peace traditions]]
* [[Christian anarchism]]
* [[Christian pacifism]]
* [[Christian Peacemaker Teams]]
* [[Civil resistance]]
* [[Criticisms of the War on Terrorism]]
* [[Conscientious objector]]
* [[Die-in]]
* [[Hélder Câmara]]
* [[Jainism]]
* [[Jewish Peace Fellowship]]
* [[Khudai Khidmatgar]]
* [[List of pacifist faiths]]
* Martialism
* [[Militarism]]
* [[Multilateralism]]
* [[Nuclear-free zone]]
* [[Non-aggression principle]]
* [[Nonkilling]]
{{col-break}}
* [[Nonresistance]]
* [[Nonviolence]]
* [[Nonviolent resistance]]
* [[Opposition to the Vietnam War]]
* [[Pacifist organisation]]
* [[Pacifist Socialist Party]]
* [[Peace]]
* [[Peace and conflict studies]]
* [[Peace camp]]
* [[Peace churches]]
* [[Peace Pledge Union]]
* [[Pentecostal Charismatic Peace Fellowship]]
* [[Popular opposition to the 2003 Iraq war]]
* [[Prison abolition]]
* [[Protests against the 2003 Iraq war]]
* [[Quakers]]
* [[Roerich Pact]]
* [[Rule of law]]
* [[Rule According to Higher Law]]
* [[Satyagraha]]
* [[Social defence]]
* [[Soka University of America]]
* [[Tax resistance]]
* [[Unitarian Universalist Association]]
* [[Weak theology]]
* [[World government]]
* [[Visigothic Code]]
{{col-end}}

==References==
&lt;!--See http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Footnotes for an explanation of how to generate footnotes using the &lt;ref(erences/)&gt; tags--&gt;
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
{{Refbegin}}
* [http://www.apu.edu/theology/faculty/palexander/ Paul Alexander], (2009), [http://www.cascadiapublishinghouse.com/ptw/ptw.htm ''Peace to War: Shifting Allegiances in the Assemblies of God]''.  Telford, PA: Cascadia Publishing/Herald Press.
*Bennett, Scott H.  ''Radical Pacifism: The War Resisters League and Gandhian Nonviolence in America, 1915-1963'' (New York: Syracuse Univ. Press, 2003).
*Bennett, Scott H., ed.  ''Army GI, Pacifist CO: The World War II Letters of Fank and Albert Dietrich'' (New York: Fordham Univ. Press, 2005).
*Brock, Peter and Young, Nigel. ''Pacifism in the Twentieth Century'' (New York, Syracuse University Press, 1999).
*Brock, Peter. ''Varieties of Pacifism: A Survey from Antiquity to the Outset of the Twentieth Century'' (New York, Syracuse University Press, 1999).
* Cortright, David. ''Peace :A History of Movements and Ideas'' (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2008).
*[http://www.assumption.edu/news/newshp/profiles/true.html True, Michael], &quot;Justice Seekers, Peace Makers: 32 Portraits in Courage&quot;, 1985. ISBN 0-89622-212-8
*{{Cite book|first=John Howard |last=Yoder |authorlink=John Howard Yoder |title=Nevertheless: the varieties and shortcomings of religious pacifism |publisher=Herald Press |location=[[Scottdale, Pennsylvania]] |year=1992 |pages= |isbn=0-8361-3586-5}}
{{Refend}}
Shalom: The Jewish Peace Letter. An online zine published by the Jewish Peace Fellowship.org/Shalom

==External links==
{{Sister project links
|wikt=no
|b=no
|q=Pacifism
|s=no
|commons=Category:Pacifism
|n=no
|v=no
|species=no}}
{{Refbegin}}
* [[s:Manifesto Against Conscription and the Military System|Manifesto Against Conscription and the Military System]]
* [http://www.stanford.edu/~rtracey/IHUM/index.html A Look at the Cultural Roots of German Pacifism]
* [http://www.bluffton.edu/~mastg/pacifism.htm Writings on Christian Nonresistance and Pacifism from Anabaptist-Mennonite Sources]
* [http://www.ppu.org.uk/pacifism PeacePledgeUnion]
{{Refend}}

{{anti-war}}
{{Gandhi}}

[[Category:Pacifism| ]]
[[Category:Peace]]
[[Category:Political theories]]

[[az:پاسيفيزيم]]
[[bg:Пацифизъм]]
[[bo:ཞི་བདེ་རིང་ལུགས།]]
[[ca:Pacifisme]]
[[cs:Pacifismus]]
[[cy:Heddychiaeth]]
[[da:Pacifisme]]
[[de:Pazifismus]]
[[et:Patsifism]]
[[el:Πασιφισμός]]
[[es:Pacifismo]]
[[eo:Pacismo]]
[[eu:Bakezaletasun]]
[[fa:صلح‌جویی]]
[[fr:Pacifisme]]
[[gl:Pacifismo]]
[[ko:평화주의]]
[[hy:Պացիֆիզմ]]
[[hr:Mirotvorstvo]]
[[io:Pacifismo]]
[[id:Pasifisme]]
[[is:Friðarsinni]]
[[it:Pacifismo]]
[[he:פציפיזם]]
[[ka:პაციფიზმი]]
[[kk:Пацифизм]]
[[lv:Pacifisms]]
[[lt:Pacifizmas]]
[[hu:Pacifizmus]]
[[mk:Пацифизам]]
[[ms:Pasifisme]]
[[mn:Пацифизм]]
[[nl:Pacifisme]]
[[ja:平和主義]]
[[no:Pasifisme]]
[[nn:Pasifisme]]
[[pl:Pacyfizm]]
[[pt:Pacifismo]]
[[ro:Pacifism]]
[[ru:Пацифизм]]
[[scn:Pacifismu]]
[[simple:Pacifism]]
[[sk:Pacifizmus]]
[[sl:Pacifizem]]
[[sr:Пацифизам]]
[[sh:Pacifizam]]
[[fi:Rauhanaate]]
[[sv:Pacifism]]
[[tl:Pasipismo]]
[[th:สันตินิยม]]
[[tr:Pasifizm]]
[[uk:Пацифізм]]
[[vi:Chủ nghĩa hòa bình]]
[[zh:和平主义]]</text>
      <sha1>0pcsla8avrnzbuxalpi224pbov5t32w</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
