<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Peace and conflict studies</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1546697</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522213886</id>
      <parentid>520203114</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T18:30:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2A01:E35:8AAF:B70:14F1:2418:1AD8:B26F</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* See also */ [[Peace education]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="52682">:''&quot;Peace Research&quot; redirects here
'''Peace and conflict studies''' is a [[social science]] field that identifies and analyses [[violence|violent]] and [[nonviolence|nonviolent]] behaviours as well as the structural mechanisms attending [[Conflict (process)|conflicts]] (including [[social conflict]]s) with a view towards understanding those processes which lead to a more desirable [[human condition]].&lt;ref&gt;Dugan, 1989: 74&lt;/ref&gt; A variation on this, '''peace studies''' (irenology), is an [[interdisciplinarity|interdisciplinary]] effort aiming at the prevention, de-escalation, and solution of conflicts by peaceful means, thereby seeking 'victory' for all parties involved in the conflict. This is in contrast to [[war studies]] (polemology) which has as its aim on the efficient attainment of victory in conflicts, big and large by violent means and to the satisfaction of one or more, but not all, parties involved. Disciplines involved may include [[political science]], [[geography]], [[economics]], [[psychology]], [[sociology]], [[international relations]], [[history]], [[anthropology]], [[religious studies]], and [[gender studies]], as well as a variety of others. [[Johan Galtung]] is widely considered &quot;the principal founder of the discipline of peace studies&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[John David Brewer|John D. Brewer]], ''Peace processes: a sociological approach'', p. 7, Polity Press, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

==Historical background==
Peace and conflict studies is both a pedagogical activity, in which teachers transmit knowledge to students; and a research activity, in which researchers create new knowledge about the sources of conflict. Peace and conflict studies entails understanding the concept of peace which is defined as political condition that ensures justice and social stability through formal and informal institutions, practices, and norms

===As pedagogical activity===
Academics and students in the world's oldest universities have long been motivated by an interest in [[peace]]. American student interest in what we today think of as peace studies first appeared in the form of campus clubs at U.S. colleges in the years immediately following the [[American Civil War]]. Similar movements appeared in Sweden in the last years of the 19th century, as elsewhere soon after. These were student-originated discussion groups, not formal courses included in college curricula.

The First World War was a turning point in Western attitudes to war. At the 1919 [[Paris Peace Conference, 1919|Peace of Paris]] where the leaders of France, Britain and the USA (led by [[Georges Clemenceau]], [[David Lloyd George]] and [[Woodrow Wilson]]) met to decide the future of Europe, Wilson proposed his famous Fourteen Points for peacemaking. These included breaking up European empires into nation states and the establishment of the [[League of Nations]]. These moves, intended to ensure a peaceful future, were the background to a number of developments in the emergence of Peace and Conflict Studies as an academic discipline (but they also, as [[Keynes]] presciently pointed out, laid the seeds for future conflict).&lt;ref&gt;Keynes 1920&lt;/ref&gt; The founding of the first chair in International Relations (at [[Aberystwyth University]], Wales), whose remit was partly to further the cause of peace, occurred in 1919.

After [[World War II]], the founding of the [[UN system]] provided a further stimulus for more rigorous approaches to peace and conflict studies to emerge. Many university courses in schools of higher learning around the world began to develop which touched upon questions of peace (often in relation to war) during this period.  The first undergraduate academic program in peace studies in the United States was not to develop until 1948, and then only at [[Manchester College (Indiana)|Manchester College]] in Indiana, a small liberal arts college.&lt;ref name=jg&gt;{{cite news|first=Holly |last=Abrams |title=Peace studies pioneer dies at 77
|url=http://www.journalgazette.net/article/20101104/LOCAL/311049973/1002/LOCAL|work=[[The Journal Gazette]] |publisher=|date=2010-11-04 |accessdate=2010-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was not until the late 1960s in the US that student concerns about the [[Vietnam War]] forced ever more universities to offer courses about peace, whether in a designated peace studies course or as a course within a traditional major. Work by academics such as [[Johan Galtung]] and John Burton, and debates in fora such as the Journal of Peace Research in the 1960s reflected the growing interest and academic stature of the field.&lt;ref&gt;Wallensteen 1988&lt;/ref&gt; Growth in the number of peace studies programmes around the world was to accelerate during the 1980s, as students became more concerned about the prospects of nuclear war. As the [[Cold War]] ended, peace and conflict studies courses shifted their focus from international conflict &lt;ref name=&quot;Harris, Fisk, and Rank 1998&quot;&gt;Harris, Fisk, and Rank 1998&lt;/ref&gt; and towards complex issues related to political violence, [[human security]], [[democratisation]], [[human rights]], [[social justice]], [[welfare]], [[Social development|development]], and producing sustainable forms of peace.  A proliferation of international organisations, agencies and international NGOs, from the UN, [[Organization for Security and Co-operation in Europe]], [[European Union]], and [[World Bank]] to [[International Crisis Group]], [[International Alert]], and others, began to draw on such research.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miall, Ramsbotham, &amp; Woodhouse 2005&quot;&gt;Miall, Ramsbotham, &amp; Woodhouse 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

Agendas relating to positive peace in European academic contexts were already widely debated in the 1960s.&lt;ref&gt;Galtung 1971&lt;/ref&gt; By the mid-1990s peace studies curricula in the US had shifted &quot;...from research and teaching about negative peace, the cessation of violence, to positive peace, the conditions that eliminate the causes of violence.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Harris, Fisk, and Rank 1998&quot;/&gt; As a result the topics had broadened enormously. By 1994, a review of course offerings in peace studies included topics such as: &quot;north-south relations&quot;; &quot;development, debt, and global poverty&quot;; &quot;the environment, population growth, and resource scarcity&quot;; and &quot;feminist perspectives on peace, militarism, and political violence.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Harris, Fisk, and Rank 1998&quot;/&gt; 

There is now a general consensus on the importance of peace and conflict studies amongst scholars from a range of disciplines in and around the social sciences, as well as from many influential policymakers around the world. Peace and conflict studies today is widely researched and taught in a large and growing number of institutions and locations. The number of universities offering peace and conflict studies courses is hard to estimate, mostly because courses may be taught out of different departments and have very different names. The [http://ipra.terracuranda.org/ International Peace Research Association website] gives one of the most authoritative listings available. A 2008 report in the ''International Herald Tribune'' mentions over 400 programmes of teaching and research in peace and conflict studies, noting in particular those at the [[United World Colleges]], Peace Research Institute(Oslo), the [[American University]], [[University of Bradford]], the UN mandated Peace University]] [[UPEACE]] in [[Ciudad Colón]]/[[Costa Rica]], [[George Mason]], [[Lund]], [[Michigan]], [[Notre Dame]], [[Queensland]], [[Uppsala]], [[Innsbruck]]/[[Austria]], [[Universitat Jaume I]] in [[Castellón de la Plana]] (Spain), [[Virginia]], and [[Wisconsin]]. The [[Rotary Foundation]] and the [[UN University]] (Tokyo) supports several international academic teaching and research programmes.

A 1995 survey found 136 U.S. colleges with peace studies programs: &quot;Forty-six percent of these are in church related schools, another 32% are in large public universities, 21% are in non-church related private colleges, and 1% are in community colleges. Fifty-five percent of the church related schools that have peace studies programs are [[Roman Catholic]]. Other denominations with more than one college or university with a peace studies program are the [[Quakers]], [[Mennonites]], [[Church of the Brethren]], and [[United Church of Christ]]. One hundred fifteen of these programs are at the undergraduate level and 21 at the graduate level. Fifteen of these colleges and universities had both undergraduate and graduate programs.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Harris, Fisk, and Rank 1998&quot;/&gt;  

Other notable programmes can be found at the University of Manitoba (Canada),University of Hiroshima (Japan), University of Innsbruck (Austria), Universitat Jaume I in Castellón de la Plana (Spain), University of Sydney, University of Queensland (Brisbane), King's College (London), Sault College (Sault Ste. Marie), London Metropolitan, Sabanci (Istanbul), Marburg (Germany), Sciences Po (Paris), University of Amsterdam (The Netherlands), Otago (New Zealand), St Andrews, and York (UK). Perhaps most importantly, such programmes and research agendas have now become common in institutions located in conflict, post-conflict, and developing countries and regions (e.g., National Peace Council (Sri Lanka), Centre for Human Rights, University of Sarajevo, Bosnia), Chulalongkorn University (Thailand), National University of Timor (Timor-Leste), University of Kabul (Afghanistan), Makerere University, Mbarara University (Uganda), Tel Aviv University (Israel), etc.

===As research activity===

Although individual thinkers such as [[Immanuel Kant]] had long recognised the centrality of peace (see [[Perpetual Peace]]), it was not until the 1950s and 1960s that peace studies began to emerge as an academic discipline with its own research tools, a specialized set of concepts, and forums for discussion such as journals and conferences. Beginning in 1959, with the founding of the [[Peace Research Institute Oslo]]- PRIO - (associated with [[Johan Galtung]]), a number of research institutes began to appear.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harris, Fisk, and Rank 1998&quot;/&gt; 

In 1963, [[Walter Isard]], the principal founder of [[Regional science]] assembled a group of scholars in [[Malmö]], Sweden, for the purpose of establishing the Peace Research Society.  The group of initial members included [[Kenneth Boulding]] and [[Anatol Rapoport]]. In 1973, this group became the [http://pss.la.psu.edu/ Peace Science Society]. Peace science was viewed as an interdisciplinary and international effort to develop a special set of concepts, techniques and data to better understand and mitigate conflict.&lt;ref&gt;[http://pss.la.psu.edu/2007-History.htm Home&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Peace science attempts to use the quantitative techniques developed in economics and political science, especially [[game theory]] and [[econometrics]], techniques otherwise seldom used by researchers in peace studies.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.einaudi.cornell.edu/PeaceProgram/student/minor.asp Peace Studies Program - Student Information- Graduate Minor Field&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The Peace Science Society website hosts the second edition of the [[Correlates of War]], one of the most well known collections of data on international conflict.&lt;ref&gt;[http://cow2.la.psu.edu/ Correlates of War 2]&lt;/ref&gt; The society holds an annual conference, attended by scholars from throughout the world, and publishes two scholarly journals: [[Journal of Conflict Resolution]] and [[Conflict Management and Peace Science]].

In 1964, the [[International Peace Research Association]] was formed at a conference organized by [[Quaker]]s in Clarens, Switzerland. Among the original executive committee was [[Johan Galtung]]. The IPRA holds a biennial conference. Research presented at its conferences and in its publications typically focuses on institutional and historical approaches, seldom employing quantitative techniques.&lt;ref&gt;[http://soc.kuleuven.be/pol/ipra/about/history.html History of the IPRA]&lt;/ref&gt; In 2001, the [[Peace and Justice Studies Association]] (PJSA) was formed as a result of a merger of two precursor organizations. The PJSA is the North American affiliate of IPRA, and includes members from around the world with a predominance from the United States and Canada. The PJSA publishes a regular newsletter (''The Peace Chronicle''), and holds annual conferences on themes related to the organization's mission &quot;to create a just and peaceful world&quot; through research, scholarship, pedagogy, and activism.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.peacejusticestudies.org/about.php Mission and Values of the PJSA]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Description==
Peace Studies can be classified as: 
*  Multidisciplinary, encompassing elements of [[Politics]] and [[International Relations]] (particularly [[critical international relations theory]]), [[Sociology]], [[Psychology]], [[Anthropology]] and [[Economics]]. [[Critical theory]] is also widely used in peace and conflict studies.
*  Multilevel.  Peace Studies examines intrapersonal peace, peace between individuals, neighbours, ethnic groups, marriages, states and civilisations.
*  Multicultural.  [[Gandhi]] is often cited as a paradigm of Peace Studies.  However, true multiculturalism remains an aspiration as most Peace Studies centres are located in the West.
*  Both [[Analytic induction|analytic]] and [[norm (sociology)|normative]].  As a normative discipline, Peace Studies involves value judgements, such as &quot;better&quot; and &quot;bad&quot;.
*  Both theoretical and applied.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miall, Ramsbotham, &amp; Woodhouse 2005&quot;/&gt;

There has been a long standing and vibrant debate on [[disarmament]] issues, as well as attempts to investigate, catalogue, and analyses issues relating to arms production, trade, and their political impacts.&lt;ref&gt;SIPRI 2007: Cooper, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; There have also been attempts to map the economic costs of war, or of relapses into violence, as opposed to those of peace.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.york.ac.uk/depts/econ/documents/research/war.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

Peace and conflict studies is now well established within the [[social sciences]]: it comprises many scholarly journals, college and university departments, peace research institutes, conferences, as well as outside recognition of the utility of peace and conflict studies as a method.

Peace Studies allows one to examine the causes and prevention of war, as well as the nature of violence, including social oppression, discrimination and marginalization.  Through peace studies one can also learn peace-making strategies to oversome persecution and transform society to attain a more just and equitable international community.

==Ideas==
===Conceptions of peace===

Galtung's negative and positive peace framework is the most widely used today. Negative peace refers to the absence of direct violence. Positive peace refers to the absence of indirect and structural violence, and is the concept that most peace and conflict researchers adopt.&lt;ref name=&quot;Galtung &amp; Jacobsen 2000&quot;&gt;Galtung &amp; Jacobsen 2000&lt;/ref&gt;

Several conceptions, models, or modes of peace have been suggested in which peace research might prosper.&lt;ref&gt;among  many, Richmond 2005&lt;/ref&gt;  

*The first is that '''peace is a natural social condition''', whereas war is not.  The premise is simple for peace researchers: to present enough information so that a rational group of decision makers will seek to avoid war and conflict.
*Second, the view that '''violence is sinful or unskillful''', and that '''non-violence is skillful or virtuous''' and should be cultivated. This view is held by a variety of religious traditions worldwide: Quakers, Mennonites and other [[Peace churches]] within Christianity; [[Jainism|Jains]], [[Satyagraha|the Satyagraha tradition in Hinduism]], [[Buddhism]], and other portions of [[Indian philosophy|Indian religion and philosophy]]; as well as certain schools of [[Islam]].
*Third is [[pacifism]]: the view that '''peace is a prime force''' in human behaviour.
* A further approach is that there are '''multiple modes of peace'''.&lt;ref&gt;[[Wolfgang Dietrich]], Daniela Ingruber, Josefina Echavarría, Gustavo Esteva and Norbert Koppensteiner (eds.): The Palgrave International Handbook of Peace Studies: A Cultural Perspective, London, Palgrave Macmillan, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

There have been many offerings on these various forms of peace. These range from the well known works  of [[Kant]], [[John Locke|Locke]], [[Rousseau]], [[Thomas Paine|Paine]], on various liberal international and constitutional and plans for peace. Variations and additions have been developed more recently by scholars such as Raymond Aron, Edward Azar, John Burton, Martin Ceadal, Wolfgang Dietrich, Kevin Dooley, Johan Galtung, Michael Howard, Vivienne Jabri, Jean-Paul Lederach, Roger Mac Ginty, Hugh Miall, David Mitrany, [http://www.bradford.ac.uk/acad/confres/html/oramsbotham.html Oliver Ramsbotham], [[Anatol Rapoport]], [http://polsci.ku.dk/english/staff/detaljer/?id=29769 Mikkel Vedby Rasmussen], [https://risweb.st-andrews.ac.uk/portal/da/persons/oliver-paul-richmond(837cc227-8f1b-4ab6-b368-48a78c1028af).html Oliver Richmond], [[S. P. Udayakumar|S.P. Udayakumar]], [http://www.brad.ac.uk/peace/academic/proftomwoodhouse/ Tom Woodhouse], others mentioned above and many more. [[Democratic peace]], liberal peace, sustainable peace, civil peace, trans-rational peace(s)and other concepts are regularly used in such work.

===Conflict triangle===
[[Johan Galtung]]'s conflict triangle works on the assumption that the best way to define peace is to define violence, its antithesis.  It reflects the normative aim of preventing, managing, limiting and overcoming violence.&lt;ref name=&quot;Galtung &amp; Jacobsen 2000&quot;/&gt;

* Direct (overt) violence, e.g., direct attack, massacre.
* Structural violence.  Death by avoidable reasons such as malnutrition.  Structural violence is indirect violence caused by an unjust structure and is not to be equated with an [[act of God]].
* Cultural violence.  Cultural violence occurs as a result of the cultural assumptions that blind one to direct or structural violence.  For example, one may be indifferent toward the homeless, or even consider their expulsion or extermination a good thing.
Each corner of Galtung's triangle can relate to the other two.  [[Ethnic cleansing]] can be an example of all three.

===Cost of conflict===

[[Cost of conflict]] is a tool which attempts to calculate the price of conflict to the human race. The idea is to examine this cost, not only in terms of the deaths and casualties and the economic costs borne by the people involved, but also the social, developmental, environmental and strategic costs of conflict. The approach considers direct costs of conflict, for instance human deaths, expenditure, destruction of land and physical infrastructure; as well as indirect costs that impact a society, for instance migration, humiliation, growth of extremism and lack of civil society. 

[[Strategic Foresight Group]], a think tank in [[India]], has developed a Cost of Conflict Series for countries and regions involved in protracted conflicts. This tool is aimed at assessing past, present and future costs looking at a wide range of parameters.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.strategicforesight.com/ Strategic Foresight Group]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Normative aims==
The normative aims of Peace Studies are [[conflict transformation]] and [[conflict resolution]] through mechanisms such as [[peacekeeping]], peacebuilding (e.g., tackling disparities in rights, institutions and the distribution of world wealth) and peacemaking (e.g., mediation and conflict resolution).  Peacekeeping falls under the aegis of negative peace, whereas efforts toward positive peace involve elements of peace building and peacemaking.&lt;ref&gt;Richmond 2002&lt;/ref&gt;

== Teaching peace and conflict studies to the military ==

One of the interesting developments within peace and conflict studies is the number of military personnel undertaking such studies.  This poses some challenges, as the military is an institution overtly committed to combat.  In the article &quot;Teaching Peace to the Military&quot;, published in the journal [[Peace Review]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://eprints.qut.edu.au/archive/00007876/ Page, James S. 2007. 'Teaching Peace to the Military'. [[Peace Review]], 19(4):571-577].&lt;/ref&gt;  [[James Smith Page|James Page]] argues for five principles that ought to undergird this undertaking, namely, respect but do not privilege military experience, teach the just war theory, encourage students to be aware of the tradition and techniques of nonviolence, encourage students to deconstruct and demythologize, and recognize the importance of military virtue.

==From conflict resolution via liberal peace- and statebuilding to trans-rational peace and elicitive conflict transformation==

Scholars working in the areas of peace and conflict studies have made significant contributions to the policies used by non-governmental organisations, development agencies, International Financial Institutions,  and the UN system, in the specific areas of conflict resolution and citizen diplomacy, development, political, social, and economic reform, peacekeeping, mediation, early warning, prevention, peacebuilding, and statebuilding.&lt;ref&gt;Wallensteen, 1988&lt;/ref&gt; This represented a shift in interest from conflict management approaches oriented towards a ‘negative peace’ to conflict resolution and peacebuilding approaches aimed at a 'positive peace'. This emerged rapidly at the end of the Cold War, and was encapsulated in the report of then-UN Secretary-General [[Boutros Boutros-Ghali]], ''[[An Agenda for Peace]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Boutros Ghali 1992&lt;/ref&gt; Indeed, it might be said that much of the machinery of what has been called ‘liberal peacebuilding’ by a number of scholars &lt;ref&gt;Duffield, 2001, Paris, 2004, Richmond, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; rests, or ‘statebuilding’ by another groups of scholars &lt;ref&gt;Caplan 2005, Chandler, 2006, Fukuyama, 2004&lt;/ref&gt; is based largely on the work that has been carried out in this area. Many scholars in the area have advocated a more ‘emancipatory’ form of peacebuilding, however, based upon a ‘Responsibility to Protect’ (R2P),&lt;ref&gt;www.responsibilitytoprotect.org&lt;/ref&gt; human security,&lt;ref&gt;Tadjbakhsh &amp; Chenoy 2006&lt;/ref&gt; local ownership and participation in such processes,&lt;ref&gt;Chopra &amp; Hohe 2004&lt;/ref&gt; especially after the limited success of liberal peacebuilding/ statebuilding in places as diverse as Cambodia, the Balkans, Timor Leste, Sierra Leone, Liberia, Nepal, Afghanistan and Iraq. This research agenda is in the process of establishing a more nuanced agenda for peacebuilding which also connects with the original, qualitatively and normatively  oriented work that emerged in the peace studies and conflict research schools of the 1960s (e.g. see the Oslo Peace Research Institute research project on &quot;Liberal Peace and the Ethics of Peacebuilding&quot; and the &quot;Liberal Peace Transitions&quot; project at the University of St Andrews &lt;ref&gt;http://www.prio.no/Research-and-Publications/Project/?oid=64922; http://www.st-andrews.ac.uk/intrel/cpcs/papers/liberalpeace/&lt;/ref&gt; and more critical ideas about peacebuilding that have recently developed in many European and non-western academic and policy circles.&lt;ref&gt;Jabri 2007: Richmond &amp; Franks 2009&lt;/ref&gt; 
The UNESCO Chair for Peace Studies at the University of Innsbruck/Austria proposed in 2008 a culture-based classification of peace interpretations: energetic, moral, modern, post-modern and trans-rational approaches.&lt;ref&gt;[[Wolfgang Dietrich]]: Variationen über die vielen Frieden; Wiesbaden [VS Verlag], 2008&lt;/ref&gt; The trans-rational approach unites existing spiritual interpretations of society and relation&lt;ref&gt;Samrat Schmiem Kumar: Bhakti - the yoga of love. Trans-rational approaches to Peace Studies; [LIT] Münster, Vienna, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; with the mechanistic methods of modern peace. Hence this school prefers the strictly relational and systemic method of elicitive conflict transformation (Lederach)&lt;ref&gt;Lederach, John Paul: Preparing for Peace; Syracuse [Syracuse University Press], 1996&lt;/ref&gt; to the prescriptive approaches of modern conflict resolution.&lt;ref&gt;Koppensteiner, Norbert: Tha Art of the Transpersonal Self. Transformation as Aesthetic and Energetic Practise; [ATROPOS] New York, Dresden, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

== Criticism and controversy ==
A number of criticisms have been aimed at peace and conflict studies, often but not necessarily from outside the realms of university system, including:  

*Peace studies do not produce practical prescriptions for managing or resolving global conflicts because &quot;[[ideology]] always trumps [[Objectivity (philosophy)|objectivity]] and [[pragmatism]]&quot;;
*are focused on putting a &quot;respectable face on Western [[self-loathing]]&quot;;
*are hypocritical because they &quot;tacitly or openly support [[terrorism]] as a permissible strategy for the 'disempowered' to redress real or perceived grievances against the powerful&quot; (i.e. ideological anti-Western concepts developed by social scientists such as [[Johan Galtung]] which arguably add a sense of unjustified acceptability which is used in support of radicalism)
*their curricula are (according to human rights activist [[Caroline Cox]] and philosopher [[Roger Scruton]]) &quot;intellectually incoherent, riddled with bias and unworthy of academic status...&quot;;&lt;ref name=barbarians&gt;&quot;[http://www.barbarakay.ca/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=20 Barbarians within the gate]&quot; by Barbara Kay, National Post, February 18, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;
*the faculty are not fully competent in the disciplines (such as [[economics]]) whose ideas were invoked as solutions to problems of conflict;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bawer 2007&quot;&gt;Bawer 2007&lt;/ref&gt;
*the policies proposed to &quot;eliminate the causes of violence&quot; are uniformly [[Left-wing politics|leftist]] policies, and not necessarily policies which would find broad agreement among social scientists.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bawer 2007&quot;/&gt;

[[Barbara Kay]], a columnist for the [[National Post]], specifically criticized the views of Norwegian professor [[Johan Galtung]], who is considered to be a leader in modern peace research. Kay wrote that Galtung has written on the &quot;structural fascism&quot; of &quot;rich, Western, Christian&quot; democracies, admires [[Fidel Castro]], opposed resistance to the [[Hungarian Revolution of 1956|Soviet Invasion of Hungary in 1956]], and has described [[Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn]] and [[Andrei Sakharov]] as &quot;persecuted elite personages.&quot; Galtung has also praised [[Mao Zedong]] for &quot;endlessly liberating&quot; China. Galtung has also stated that the United States is a “killer country” that is guilty of “neo-fascist state terrorism” and has reportedly stated that the destruction of Washington, D. C. could be justified by America's foreign policy. He has also compared the U.S. to Nazi Germany for bombing Kosovo during the [[1999 NATO bombing of Yugoslavia]].&lt;ref name=barbarians/&gt;  

In the Summer 2007 edition of [[City Journal (New York)|City Journal]], [[Bruce Bawer]] sharply criticized Peace Studies. He noted that many Peace Studies programs in American Universities are run by Marxist or far-left Professors. More broadly, he argued that Peace Studies are dominated by the belief that &quot;America that is the wellspring of the world’s problems&quot; and that while Professors of Peace Studies argue &quot;that terrorist positions deserve respect at the negotiating table,&quot; they &quot;seldom tolerate(s) alternative views&quot; and that &quot;Peace studies, as a rule, rejects questioning of its own guiding ideology.&quot;&lt;ref name=Bawer&gt;[http://www.city-journal.org/html/17_3_peace_racket.html The Peace Racket] by Bruce Bawer, City Journal, Summer 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;  

Regarding his claim that Peace Studies supports violence in the pursuit of leftist ideology, Bawer cited a quote from ''[http://search.barnesandnoble.com/Peace-and-Conflict-Studies/Charles-P-Webel/e/9780761925071/?itm=4 Peace and Conflict Studies]'',&lt;ref&gt;[http://search.barnesandnoble.com/Peace-and-Conflict-Studies/Charles-P-Webel/e/9780761925071/?itm=4 Peace and Conflict Studies] by Charles P. Webel and [[David P. Barash]], Textbook (Hardcover - Older Edition), SAGE Publications, March 2002, 592pp, ISBN 978-0-7619-2507-1.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.telegraphindia.com/1021115/asp/opinion/story_1382074.asp Take a Break from War] by Kaushik Roy, The Telegraph (Calcutta, India),  November 15, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; a widely used 2002 textbook written by Charles P. Webel and [[David P. Barash]] which praised [[Vladimir Lenin]] because he “maintained that only revolution—not reform—could undo capitalism’s tendency toward imperialism and thence to war.&quot;&lt;ref name=Bawer/&gt; 

[[David Horowitz]] has argued that Webel and Barash's book implicitly supports violence for socialist causes, noting that the book states &quot;the case of Cuba indicates that violent revolutions can sometimes result in generally improved living conditions for many people.&quot; Horowitz also argued that the book &quot;treats the Soviet Union as a sponsor of peace movements, and the United States as the militaristic, imperialist power that peace movements try to keep in check&quot; and that &quot;the authors justify Communist policies and actions while casting those of America and Western democracies in a negative light.&quot; Horowitz also claimed that the authors discuss the [[Cuban Missile Crisis]] without mentioning its cause (i.e. the placement of the Soviet missiles in Cuba) and blame [[John F. Kennedy]] while praising Soviet Premier [[Nikita Khrushchev]] for &quot;be[ing] willing to back down.&quot; Finally, Horowitz criticised the author's use of Marxist writers, such as [[Andre Gunder Frank]] and [[Frances Moore Lappe]], as the sole basis on which to study &quot;poverty and hunger as causes of human conflict&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.studentsforacademicfreedom.org/news/581/BSUonemansterroristDHarticle110804.htm &quot;One Man's Terrorist Is Another Man's Freedom Fighter&quot;] by David Horowitz, (website of Students for Academic Freedom), November 08, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

Kay and Bawer also specifically criticized Professor [http://www.brandeis.edu/departments/sociology/fellman.html Gordon Fellman], the Chairman of [[Brandeis University]]'s Peace, Conflict, and Coexistence Studies Program, whom they claimed has justified Palestinian suicide-bombings against Israelis as “ways of inflicting revenge on an enemy that seems unable or unwilling to respond to rational pleas for discussion and justice.” &lt;ref name=Bawer/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.peaceworkmagazine.org/pwork/0210/021020.htm September 11 and the Field of Peace Studies] by Gordon Fellman, Peacework, October 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;
  
[[Katherine Kersten]], who is a senior fellow at the Minneapolis-based conservative think tank [[Center of the American Experiment]], believes that Peace Studies programs are &quot;dominated by people of a certain ideological bent, and [are] thus hard to take seriously.&quot; [http://www.stthomas.edu/cathstudies/faculty/kennedy.htm Robert Kennedy], a professor of Catholic studies and management at the [[University of St. Thomas (Minnesota)|University of St. Thomas]], criticized his university's Peace Studies Program in an interview with Minneapolis Star Tribune in 2002, stating that the program employs several adjunct professors &quot;whose academic qualifications are not as strong as we would ordinarily look for&quot; and that &quot;The combination of the ideological bite and the maybe less-than-full academic credentials of the faculty would probably raise some questions about how scholarly the program is.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;For Young Activists, Peacemaking 101,&quot; by Tom Ford and Bob von Sternberg, Minneapolis Star Tribune, December 17, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Responses===

Such views have been strongly opposed by scholars who claim that these criticisms underestimate the development of detailed interdisciplinary, theoretical, methodological, and empirical research into the causes of violence and dynamics of peace that has occurred via academic and policy networks around the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miall, Ramsbotham, &amp; Woodhouse 2005&quot;/&gt;

In reply to [[Barbara Kay]]'s article, a group of Peace Studies experts in Canada responded that &quot;Kay's...argument that the field of peace studies endorses terrorism is nonsense&quot; and that &quot;Dedicated peace theorists and researchers are distinguished by their commitment to reduce the use of violence whether committed by enemy nations, friendly governments or warlords of any stripe.&quot; They also argued that: 

&lt;blockquote&gt;
...Ms. Kay attempts to portray advocates for peace as naive and idealistic, but the data shows that the large majority of armed conflicts in recent decades have been ended through negotiations, not military solutions. In the contemporary world, violence is less effective than diplomacy in ending armed conflict. Nothing is 100% effective to reduce tyranny and violence, but domestic and foreign strategy needs to be based on evidence, rather than assumptions and misconceptions from a bygone era.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationalpost.com/story.html?id=1325511 In defence of peace studies] by Catherine Morris, director, Peacemakers Trust, Victoria; Ben Hoffman, president and CEO, Canadian International Institute of Applied Negotiation, Ottawa; Dean E. Peachey, visiting professor in transitional justice, Global College, University of Winnipeg, National Post, February 25, 2009. ([http://peacemakers.ca.etherwork.net/bulletins/2009/02/in-defence-of-peace-studies-letter-to-the-national-post/ Full letter is available here])&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Most academics in the area argue that the accusations that peace studies approaches are not objective, and derived from mainly leftist or inexpert sources, are not practical, support violence rather than reject it, or have not led to policy developments, are clearly incorrect. They note that the development of UN and major donor policies (including the EU, US, and UK, as well as many others including those of Japan, Canada, Norway, etc.) towards and in conflict and post-conflict countries have been heavily influenced by such debates. A range of key policy documents and responses have been developed by these governments in the last decade and more, and in UN (or related) documentation such as 'Agenda for Peace', 'Agenda for Development', 'Agenda for Democratization', the [[Millennium Development Goals]], [[Responsibility to Protect]], and the 'High Level Panel Report'.&lt;ref&gt;Report of the Secretary- General’s High Level Panel on Threats, Challenges, and Change, United Nations, 2004: Boutros Boutros Ghali, An Agenda For Peace: preventative diplomacy, peacemaking and peacekeeping, New York: United Nations, 1992; An Agenda for Development: Report of the Secretary-General, A/48/935, 6 May 1994; “Supplement to An Agenda for Peace” A/50/60, S.1995/1, 3 January 1995; An Agenda for Democratization, A/50/332 AND A/51/512, 17 December 1996.&lt;/ref&gt; They have also been significant for the work of the World Bank, International Development Agencies, and  a wide range of Non Governmental Organisations.&lt;ref&gt;EG for the World Bank, see, &quot;Breaking the Conflict Trap: Civil War and Development Policy&quot; [http://econ.worldbank.org/WBSITE/EXTERNAL/EXTDEC/EXTRESEARCH/EXTPRRS/EXTBCTCWDP0,,menuPK:477815~pagePK:64168092~piPK:64168088~theSitePK:477803,00.html]: For DFID see [http://www.dfid.gov.uk/aboutdfid/performance/files/ev646s.pdf]; eg see also [[International Crisis Group]]&lt;/ref&gt; It has been influential in the work of, among others, the UN, UNDP, [[UN Peacebuilding Commission]], [[UNHCR]], [[World Bank]], [[European Union|EU]], [[Organization for Security and Co-operation in Europe]], for national donors uncluding USAID, DFID, SIDA, NORAD, DANIDA, Japan Aid, GTZ, and international NGOs such as [[International Alert]] or [[International Crisis Group]], as well as many local NGOs. Major databases have been generated by the work of scholars in these areas.&lt;ref&gt;eg Correlates of War at Harvard University [http://dvn.iq.harvard.edu/dvn/dv/cow]: PRIO/ Uppsala University Data on Armed Conflict [http://www.prio.no/CSCW/Datasets/Armed-Conflict/].&lt;/ref&gt; 

Finally, peace and conflict studies debates have generally confirmed, not undermined, a broad consensus (western and beyond) on the importance of [[human security]], human rights, development, democracy, and a rule of law (though there is a vibrant debate ongoing about the contextual variations and applications of these frameworks).&lt;ref&gt;Michael Doyle and Nicolas Sambanis, Making War and Building Peace, (Princeton University Press, 2006); Charles T. Call and Elizabeth M. Cousens, “Ending Wars and Building Peace: International Responses to War-Torn Societies,” International Studies Perspectives, 9 (2008): Stephen D. Krasner, “Sharing Sovereignty. New Institutions for Collapsed and Failing States,” International Security, 29, 2 (2004); Roland Paris, At War’s End, (Cambridge University Press, 2004).&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[War Against War]]
*''[[The Acorn (journal)|The Acorn: Journal of the Gandhi-King Society]]'' (journal)
*''[[Conflict Management and Peace Science]]'' (journal)
*[[Conflict resolution]]
*[[Conflict resolution research]]
*[[Democratic peace theory]]
*[[Georgetown University Master of Arts in Conflict Resolution]]
*[[Global Peace Index]]
*[[International Festival of Peace Poetry]]
*''[[Journal for Peace and Justice Studies]]'' (journal)
*[[Peace]]
*[[Peace education]]
*[[Peace and Justice Studies Association]]
*[[Peace Industry]]
*''[[Peace Review]]'' (journal)
*[[University for Peace]]
*[[Elise M. Boulding]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Sources==
*Aron, Raymond, Peace and War: A Theory of International Relations, London: Transaction, 2003 [1966].
*Avruch, Kevin, Peter W. Black, and Joseph A. Scimecca (eds.), Conflict Resolution: Cross-Cultural Perspectives, London: Greenwood Press, 1991.
*Azar, Edward E., The Management of Protracted Social Conflict, Hampshire, UK: Dartmouth Publishing, 1990.
*[[Francis Beer|Beer,Francis A.]], Meanings of War and Peace, College Station: Texas A&amp;M University Press 2001.
*[[Francis Beer|Beer, Francis A.]], Peace Against War, San Francisco: W.H. Freeman, 1981.
*Boutros Ghali, [[An Agenda for Peace|An Agenda For Peace: preventative diplomacy, peacemaking and peacekeeping]], New York: United Nations, 1992.
*Bawer, Bruce &quot;The Peace Racket&quot;, ''City Journal,'' Summer 2007 [http://city-journal.org/html/17_3_peace_racket.html link]
*Burton, J.,  &amp; EA Azar,  International  Conflict Resolution: Theory and Practice, Wheatsheaf Books, 1986.
*Caplan, Richard, International Governance of War-torn Territories: Rule and Reconstruction, Oxford: OUP, 2005.
*Ceadal, M, Thinking About Peace and War, Oxford: OUP, 1987.
*Chandler, D. Empire in Denial: The Politics of State-building. Pluto Press, 2006.
*Cooper, Neil, 'What's The Point of Arms Transfer Controls?', Contemporary Security Policy, Vol. 27, No. 1, April 2006 pp.&amp;nbsp;118–137.
*Jarat Chopra, Tanja Hohe, &quot;Participatory Intervention&quot;, Global Governance, Vol. 10, 2004.
*Darby, John, and Roger MacGinty, Contemporary Peacemaking, London: Palgrave, 2003.
*[[Wolfgang Dietrich]], Josefina Eachavarría Alvarez, Norbert Koppensteiner eds.: &quot;Key Texts of Peace Studies&quot;; LIT Münster, Vienna, 2006.
*[[Wolfgang Dietrich]], Daniela Ingruber, Josefina Echavarría, Gustavo Esteva and Norbert Koppensteiner (eds.): ''The Palgrave International Handbook of Peace Studies: A Cultural Perspective'', London, Palgrave Macmillan, 2011.
*Dooley, Kevin L, and S.P. Udayakumar, &quot;Reconceptualizing Global Conflicts: From Us Versus Them to Us Versus Then,&quot; Journal of Global Change and Governance, Volume 2, No. 1, Spring 2009.
*Duffield, Mark, Global Governance and the New Wars: The Merging of Development and Security, London: Zed Books, 2001.
*Dugan, M. 1989. &quot;Peace Studies at the Graduate Level.&quot; ''The Annals of the American    Academy of Political Science: Peace Studies: Past and Future'', 504, 72-79.
*Dunn, DJ, The First Fifty Years of Peace Research, Aldershot: Ashgate, 2005.
*[[Francis Fukuyama|Fukuyama, Francis]]: State Building. Governance and World Order in the Twenty-First Century, Ithaca, N.Y.: Cornell University Press, 2004.
*Galtung, J., “A Structural Theory of Imperialism”, Journal of Peace Research, Vol.13, No.2, 1971.
*Galtung, Johan and Carl G. Jacobsen, Searching for Peace: The Road to TRANSCEND, Pluto Press: London, 2000.
*Harris, Ian, Larry J. Fisk, and Carol Rank. (1998). &quot;A Portrait of University Peace Studies in North America and Western Europe at the End of the Millennium.&quot; ''International Journal of Peace Studies''. Volume 3, Number 1. ISSN 1085-7494 [http://www.gmu.edu/academic/ijps/vol3_1/Harris.htm link]
*Howard, M The Invention of Peace and the Re-Invention of War, London: Profile, 2002.
*Jabri, Vivienne, Discourses on Violence, Manchester UP, 1996.
*Jabri, Vivienne, War and the Transformation of Global Politics, London: Palgrave, 2007.
*Keynes, John Maynard, The Economic Consequences of the Peace, London: Macmillan, 1920.
*Koppensteiner, Norbert: The Art of the Transpersonal Self. Transformation as Aesthetic and Energetic Practice; [ATROPOS] New York, Dresden, 2009
*Kumar, Schmiem Samrat: Bhakti- the yoga of love. Trans-rational approaches to Peaec Studies; [LIT]Münster, Vienna, 2010.
*Lederach, J, Building Peace- Sustainable Reconciliation in Divided Societies, Tokyo: United Nations University Press, 1997.
*Lund, Michael S, “What Kind of Peace is Being Built: Taking Stock of Post- Conflict Peacebuilding and Charting Future Directions”, Paper presented on the 10th Anniversary of Agenda for Peace, International Development Research Centre, Ottawa, Canada, January 2003.
*López Martínez, Mario (dir) ''Enciclopedia de paz y conflictos.'' Granada, 2004. ISBN 84-338-3095-3, 2 tomos.
*Miall, Hugh, Oliver Ramsbotham, &amp; Tom Woodhouse, Contemporary Conflict Resolution, Polity Press, 2005.
*Mitrany, D.A.,  The Functional Theory of Politics, London: Martin Robertson, 1975.
*Richmond, OP, Maintaining Order, Making Peace, Macmillan, 2002.
*Richmond, OP, The Transformation of Peace, Palgrave Macmillan, 2005.
*Richmond OP &amp; Franks J, Liberal Peace Transitions: Between Statebuilding and Peacebuilding, Edinburgh University Press, 2009.

Routledge Contemporary Security Studies series: ‘Women, Peace and Security: Translating Policy into Practice’ First published 2010. Introduction by ‘Funmi Olonisakin, Director of Conflict, Security &amp; Development Group, King’s College London, and Karen Barnes. Chapter by Lesley Abdela ‘Nepal and the implementation of UNSCR1325’. ISBN 978-0-415-58797-6 (hbk)

*Rummel, RJ, The Just Peace, California, 1981.
*Tadjbakhsh, Shahrbanou &amp; Chenoy, Anuradha M. Human Security: Concepts and Implications, London: Routledge, 2006
*Taylor, Paul, and A.J.R. Groom (eds.), The UN at the Millennium, London: Continuum, 2000.
*Tidwell, Alan C., Conflict Resolved, London: Pinter, 1998.
*Vayrynen, R, New Directions in Conflict Theory: Conflict Resolution and Conflict Transformation, London: Sage, 1991.
*Vedby Rasmussen, Mikkel, The West, Civil Society, and the Construction of Peace, London: Palgrave, 2003.
*Wallensteen, Peter (ed.), Peace Research: Achievements and Challenges, Boulder, CO: Westview Press, 1988.
*Zartman, William, and Lewis Rasmussen (eds.), Peacemaking in International Conflict: Methods and Techniques, Washington, DC: United States Institute of Peace Press, 1997.

== External links ==
===Journals===
*[http://secure.pdcnet.org/pdc/bvdb.nsf/journal?openform&amp;journal=pdc_acorn The Acorn: Journal of the Gandhi-King Society]
*[http://www.bepress.com/peps/ Peace Economics, Peace Science and Public Policy]
*[http://pss.la.psu.edu/2007-CMPS.htm Conflict Management and Peace Science]
*[http://www.tandf.co.uk/journals/titles/10242694.html Defense and Peace Economics]
*[http://secure.pdcnet.org/pdc/bvdb.nsf/journal?openform&amp;journal=pdc_jpjs Journal for Peace and Justice Studies]
*[http://jcr.sagepub.com/ Journal of Conflict Resolution]
*[http://jpr.sagepub.com/ Journal of Peace Research]
*[http://www.tandf.co.uk/journals/titles/03050629.asp International Interactions]
*[http://www.trinstitute.org/ojpcr/ OJPCR: The Online Journal of Peace and Conflict Resolution] (open access)
*[http://www.gmu.edu/academic/pcs/ Peace and Conflict Studies]
*[http://www.goddard.edu/masterarts_individualized/ Goddard College Individualized MA with specialties in Peace and Conflict Studies]
*[http://www.gmu.edu/academic/ijps/index.htm The International Journal of Peace Studies]
*[http://www.jgcg.org/ Journal of Global Change and Governance]
*[http://www.peacestudiesjournal.org.uk/latest.asp Peace, Conflict &amp; Development] (open access)
*[http://www.usfca.edu/peacereview/PRHome.html Peace Review]
*[http://www.bepress.com/peps Peace Economics, Peace Science and Public Policy]
*[http://www.peacestudiesjournal.org/ Peace Studies Journal]
*[http://www.manchester.edu/Academics/departments/Peace_Studies/bulletin/index.htm Nonviolent Social Change - the Bulletin of the Manchester College Peace Studies Institute] a journal on nonviolent social change
*[http://www.religionconflictpeace.org Journal of Religion, Conflict, and Peace]
*[http://www.tandf.co.uk/journals/journal.asp?issn=1353-3312&amp;linktype=1 International Peacekeeping]
*[http://www.tandf.co.uk/journals/journal.asp?issn=1467-8802&amp;linktype=1 Conflict, Security &amp; Development]
*[http://www.sagepub.com/journalsProdDesc.nav?prodId=Journal200863 Conflict and Cooperation]
*[http://www.sagepub.com/journalsProdDesc.nav?prodId=Journal200769 Security Dialogue]
*[http://www.rienner.com/title/Alternatives_Global_Local_Political Alternatives: Global, Local, Political]
*[http://www.review.upeace.org/ Peace &amp; Conflict Review]
*[http://www.infactispax.org/ In Factis Pax: Journal of Peace Education and Social Justice]

===Other periodicals===
*[http://www.c-r.org/accord/ Accord: An International Review of Peace Initiatives]
*[http://www.usip.org/peacewatch/ Peace Watch]
*[http://commonknowledge.dukejournals.org/ Common Knowledge]

===Scholarly societies===
*[http://www.peacejusticestudies.org/ Peace &amp; Justice Studies Association]
*[http://pss.la.psu.edu/ Peace Science Society]
*[http://soc.kuleuven.be/pol/ipra/ International Peace Research Association]

=== Data ===
* [http://www.ucdp.uu.se/ Uppsala Conflict Data Program]
* [http://cow2.la.psu.edu/ Correlates of War 2]
* [http://www.visionofhumanity.org/ Global Peace Index]
* [http://www.prio.no/Data/ Data resources from PRIO]

=== Research Institutes ===
* [http://kroc.nd.edu/ Kroc Institute for International Peace Studies, University of Notre Dame]
* [http://www.angelo.edu/css Center for Security Studies, Angelo State University] San Angelo, Texas, United States
* [http://www.berghof-conflictresearch.org/en Berghof Conflict Research] Berlin, Germany
* [http://www.pcr.uu.se Department of Peace and Conflict Research, Uppsala University] Uppsala, Sweden
* [http://www.cpds-tu.edu.np Department of Conflict, Peace and Development Studies, Tribhuvan University] Kathmandu, Nepal
* [http://www.world-peace-academy.ch World Peace Academy - Swiss Centre for Peace Studies] Basel, Switzerland
* [http://www.otago.ac.nz/humanities/ncpacs National Centre for Peace and Conflict Studies at the University of Otago, NZ]
* [http://www.arts.usyd.edu.au/centres/cpacs/about/index.shtml The Centre for Peace and Conflict Studies, University of Sydney]
* [http://www.ncas.rutgers.edu/peace-and-conflict Rutgers MA in Peace and Conflict Studies]
* [http://www.ucalgary.ca/pdsp  Peacebuilding, Development and Security Program], Centre for Military and Security Studies, University of Calgary
* [http://www.rcsp.c.u-tokyo.ac.jp/ Research Centre for Sustainable Peace, Institute of Advanced Global Studies, The University of Tokyo], Tokyo, Japan
* [http://www.icu.ac.jp/index_e.html International Christian University], Tokyo, Japan
* [http://subsite.icu.ac.jp/pri/E/index.html Peace Research Institute], [http://www.icu.ac.jp/index_e.html International Christian University], Tokyo, Japan
* [http://www.tufs.ac.jp/common/pg/pcs/ Peace and Conflict Studies], Tokyo University of Foreign Studies, Japan
* [http://www.bradford.ac.uk/acad/peace/research/centres/ Department of Peace Studies, University of Bradford]
* [http://icar.gmu.edu/ Institute for Conflict Analysis and Resolution (ICAR) at [[George Mason University]] ]
* [http://www.HIIK.de Heidelberg Institute for International Conflict Research (HIIK)]
* [http://www.saybrook.edu/academics/concentrations.asp?strContent=Social%20Transformation Saybrook Graduate School and Research Center]
* [http://www.economicsandpeace.org/ Institute for Economics and Peace] Sydney, Australia
* [http://www.prio.no Peace Research Institute Oslo (PRIO)]
* [http://www.Futureworldscenter.org Future Worlds Center Nicosia, Cyprus]
* [http://uit.no/cps Centre for Peace Studies, University of Tromsø, Norway]
* [http://www.transcend.org/tpu TRANSCEND Peace University (TPU online), founded by Johan GALTUNG]
* [http://www.emu.edu/ctp/ Center for Justice and Peacebuilding of [[Eastern Mennonite University]] ]
* [http://www.trudeaucentre.ca University of Toronto, Trudeau Centre for Peace and Conflict Studies].
* [http://www.humanities.mcmaster.ca/~peace/ The Centre for Peace Studies at McMaster University in Hamilton, Ontario, Canada]
* [http://www.villanova.edu/artsci/peaceandjustice/ Center for Peace and Justice Education, Villanova University]
* [http://peace.fresno.edu/ Center for Peacemaking and Conflict Studies at [[Fresno Pacific University]]]
* [[Soka University of America]]'s Pacific Basin Research Center
* [http://www.stthomas.edu/justpeace Justice and Peace Studies at the University of St. Thomas, Minnesota]
* [http://www.bethelks.edu/kipcor/ Kansas Institute for Peace and Conflict Resolution at [[Bethel College (Kansas)|Bethel College]]]
* [http://www.iugm.es Instituto Universitario Gutierrez Mellado]
* [http://www.hope.ac.uk/research/warandpeace/ Archbishop Desmond Tutu Centre for War and Peace Studies at [[Liverpool Hope University]] ]
* [http://www.sipri.org/ Stockholm International Peace Research Institute]
* [http://www.coventry.ac.uk/peacestudy Centre for Peace and Reconciliation Studies at [[Coventry University]] ]
* [http://www.epu.ac.at/ EPU in Stadtschlaining [[Austria]].]
* [http://www.nd.edu/~krocinst/ Joan B. Kroc Institute for International Peace Studies, University of Notre Dame]
* [http://www.jmi.nic.in/cpcr/cpcr.htm Nelson Mandela Centre for Peace and Conflict Resolution, New Delhi].
* [http://www.uu.nl/conflictstudies/ Centre for Conflict Studies, University of Utrecht, The Netherlands]
* [http://www.hiroshima-u.ac.jp/category_view.php?category_child_id=48&amp;category_id=15&amp;template_id=15&amp;lang=en  Institute for Peace Science, [[Hiroshima University]] ]
* [http://serv.peace.hiroshima-cu.ac.jp/English/index.htm Hiroshima City University, Hiroshima Peace Institute]
* [http://www1.ocn.ne.jp/~hipe/indexE.html Hiroshima Institute for Peace Education]
* [http://www.nagasaki-heiwa.org/n4/npi.html NAGASAKI PEACE INSTITUTE]
* [http://www.nipc.nias.ac.jp/ Nagasaki Institute Of Applied Science, Nagasaki Institute for Peace Culture]
* [http://www.meijigakuin.ac.jp/~prime/ International Peace Research Institute, Meiji Gakuin University]
* [http://www.uibk.ac.at/peacestudies/ma-program/ MA Program in Peace, Development, Security and International Conflict Transformation, University of Innsbruck]
* [http://www.incore.ulst.ac.uk INCORE (International Conflict Research), University of Ulster]
* [http://www.upeace.org University for Peace, Costa Rica]
* [http://www.aupeace.org International Peace and Conflict Resolution, School of International Service, American University]
* [http://grebel.uwaterloo.ca/academic/undergrad/pacs/index.shtml Peace and Conflict Studies, Conrad Grebel University College, University of Waterloo, Canada]
* [http://peace.sandiego.edu Joan B. Kroc Institute for Peace and Justice, University of San Diego]
* [http://www.st-andrews.ac.uk/intrel/cpcs/ Centre for Peace and Conflict Studies, University of St Andrews, UK]
* [http://www.naropa.edu/academics/undergraduate/peacestudies/index.cfm Peace Studies at Naropa University]
* [http://pace.unipi.it/ Interdisciplinary Center 'Sciences for Peace' (CISP), University of Pisa, Italy]
* [http://www.peaceinstitute.hawaii.edu/ Spark M. Matsunaga Institute for Peace and Conflict Resolution, University of Hawai'i at Manoa]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Peace And Conflict Studies}}
[[Category:Aftermath of war]]
[[Category:Peace and conflict studies| ]]
[[Category:Subfields of political science]]

[[de:Friedensforschung]]
[[fr:Irénologie]]
[[it:Polemologia]]
[[nl:Polemologie]]
[[ja:平和学]]
[[no:Freds- og konfliktforskning]]
[[pl:Polemologia]]
[[pt:Polemologia]]
[[ro:Polemologie]]
[[sv:Freds- och konfliktkunskap]]</text>
      <sha1>9f62z2v8wq87v176bxy8kd0ark2lmza</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
