<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Peninsula Peace and Justice Center</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7643081</id>
    <revision>
      <id>511268444</id>
      <parentid>427825585</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-07T19:39:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Rjwilmsi</username>
        <id>203434</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[WP:AWB/T|typos fixed]]: mid-1960's → mid-1960s using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (8389)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3608">{{unreferenced|date=December 2006}}
{{Advert|date=July 2008}}

The '''Peninsula Peace and Justice Center''' is an activist organization in the [[San Francisco]] region.

==History==
The center was originally known as the '''Palo Alto Peace Center,''' and was founded in the mid-1960s by [[Barbara Jo Wenger]], [[Connie Yu]] and [[Helen Keating]]. The center was located on Hamilton Avenue and Cowper Street. It was the headquarters of [[The Grapevine (underground newsletter)|The Grapevine]], an underground newsletter that was critical of the [[Vietnam War]] and President [[Richard Nixon]].  Members of the Peace Union were actively involved with demonstrating against the war.  The Peace Union was raided by the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation]] twice in 1971. In 1982, the center was renamed the Mid-Peninsula Peace Center, and a final name change to '''Peninsula Peace and Justice Center''' in the early 1990s reflected the organization's commitment to a broad program that addresses the interconnectedness of the many issues and problems facing our world.

==Current Mission==
The Peninsula Peace and Justice Center (PPJC) is dedicated to building coalitions among progressive organizations to make all of its work more effective. The organization's efforts have led to the formation of broad-based coalitions fighting against U.S. military intervention, corporate globalization, the death penalty and many other issues.  PPJC is also committed to involving individuals in the struggle for a just and humane world, using the power of democracy and taking to heart the premise that in a democracy, the people should lead.

==Recent Activities==
When it comes to Iraq anti-war efforts, no organization has been more active than Peninsula Peace and Justice Center.  PPJC has held teach-ins and forums, met with Congress, organized vigils and protest rallies, and sent speakers to numerous organizations, churches and schools—beginning before the war and continuing through the disastrous occupation.  PPJC's work to change the tragic U.S. policy on Iraq goes back over 12 years.  We played a central role in the protests against [[Gulf War I]] and were early and consistent leaders in the national struggle to end the brutal sanctions.  As well as opposing the war in Iraq, we are continually working to end U.S. military support for oppressive regimes in Israel, Haiti, and all over the world.

PPJC has made repeal of the so-called [[PATRIOT Act]] a top priority, and helped pass a City Council resolution against this assault on our civil liberties.  We also helped pass a resolution by the county Board of Supervisors endorsing a moratorium on the [[death penalty]], as part of a statewide effort.

PPJC was part of a coalition whose demonstrations, community outreach and meetings with our local Representative helped convince her to vote against the potentially disastrous [[Central America Free Trade Agreement]].  PPJC has sponsored numerous speakers and films educating the local community about the true impacts of economic globalization.

==References==
Heyser, Holly A. &quot;Peace center runs out of gas because of financial and membership problems, the Palo Alto office will close December 15.&quot; [[San Jose Mercury News]], December 1, 1995.

==External links==
* [http://peaceandjustice.org/ Peninsula Peace and Justice Center site]
* [http://www.paloaltoonline.com/weekly/story.php?story_id=4976 Giving Peace a Chance: Peninsula Peace and Justice Center celebrates 25 years]

[[Category:International nongovernmental organizations]]
[[Category:Political advocacy groups in the United States]]</text>
      <sha1>s1bh4ymmg54pviqqxp3fcodsrylff4t</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
