<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Peronism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>242379</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522148932</id>
      <parentid>522044870</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T09:13:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bjenks</username>
        <id>1693504</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Updating ref link; consistent spelling Perón</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16216">[[File:Discurso de Perón.jpg|thumb|[[Juan Domingo Perón]] is the central symbol in the Peronist party.]]
[[File:Eva Perón Discurso.jpg|thumb|[[Eva Perón]] claims the female vote in 1947]]

'''Peronism''' ({{lang-es|Peronismo}}), or '''Justicialism''' (''Justicialismo''), is an [[Argentine]] political movement based on the thought of former President [[Juan Domingo Perón]] and his second wife, [[Eva Perón]]. Perón's party, the ''[[Partido Justicialista]]'', derived its name from the Spanish words for &quot;Social Justice&quot; (''Justicia Social'').

The pillars of the Peronist ideal, known as the &quot;three flags&quot;, are social justice, economic independence, and political sovereignty. Peronism can be described as a [[third position]] ideology, as it rejects the extremes of [[Capitalism]] and [[Communism]]. Peronism espouses [[Corporatism]] and thus aims to mediate tensions between the classes of society, with the state responsible for negotiating compromise in conflicts between managers and workers. 

It is, however, a generally ill-defined ideology; different, and sometimes contradictory sentiments are expressed in the name of Peronism. Today, the legacy and thought of Perón have transcended the confines of any single political party and bled into the broader political landscape of Argentina, therefore Peronists are usually described as a 'movement'. Traditionally the Peronist movement has drawn its strongest support from the working class and sympathetic unions, and has been characterized as proletarian in nature.

From the perspective of opponents, Peronism is an authoritarian ideology. Perón was often compared to [[fascist|fascist dictators]], accused of demagoguery, and his policies derided as [[populism|populist]]. Proclaiming himself the embodiment of nationality, Perón's regime often silenced dissent by accusing opponents of being unpatriotic. The corporatist character of Peronism drew attacks from Socialists who accused his administration of preserving capitalist exploitation and class division. Conservatives rejected its modernist ideology and felt their status threatened by the ascent of the Peronist apparat. Liberals condemned the Perón regime's arbitrariness and dictatorial tendencies.

Defenders of Peronism also describe the doctrine as [[populism|populist]], albeit in the sense that they believe it embodies the interests of the masses, and in particular the most vulnerable social strata. Admirers hold Perón in esteem for his administration's [[anti-imperialism]], and [[Non-Aligned Movement|non-alignment]], as well as its socially progressive initiatives.

Since its inception in 1946, Peronist candidates have won 8 of the 10 presidential elections that they have not been banned from participating in. Perón himself remains the only Argentine to have been elected President three times.

==Perón's policies==
{{History of Argentina}}
Perón's ideas were initially widely embraced by a variety of different groups in Argentina across the political spectrum. Perón's personal views would later become a burden on the ideology; for example, his [[anti-clericalism]] did not strike a sympathetic chord with upper-class Argentinians.

Peronism is widely regarded as a form of corporate socialism, or &quot;right-wing socialism&quot;. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/1990/01/13/world/buenos-aires-journal-carlos-carlos-how-does-your-economy-sink.html Buenos Aires Journal] ''[[The New York Times]]'' Jan 13, 1990&lt;/ref&gt; Perón's public speeches were consistently [[nationalism|nationalist]] and [[populism|populist]]. It would be difficult to separate Peronism from [[corporate nationalism]], for Perón nationalized Argentina's large corporations, blurring distinctions between corporations and government. At the same time, the [[labor union]]s became corporate, ceding the right to strike in agreements with Perón as Secretary of Welfare in the military government from 1943-45. In exchange, the state was to assume the role of negotiator between conflicting interests. 

A military and civilian coup, the ''[[Revolución Libertadora]]'', led by [[Pedro Eugenio Aramburu|General Aramburu]], overthrew the Perón regime in 1955.  Perón spent 18 years in exile, mostly in [[Francisco Franco]]'s [[Spain]]. Though his feelings for Franco were mixed, Perón never disguised his admiration for [[Benito Mussolini]]'s [[fascist]] domestic policies.

Perón and his administration resorted to organized violence and dictatorial rule.  Perón showed contempt for any opponents, and regularly characterized them as traitors and agents of foreign powers. Perón maintained the institutions of democratic rule, but subverted freedoms through such actions as nationalizing the broadcasting system, centralizing the unions under his control, and monopolizing the supply of newspaper print. At times, Perón also resorted to tactics such as  illegally imprisoning opposition politicians and journalists, including UCR leader [[Ricardo Balbin]], and shutting down opposition papers, such as ''[[La Prensa (Buenos Aires)|La Prensa]]''.

Peronism also lacked a strong interest in matters of [[foreign policy]] other than the belief that the political and economic influences of other nations should be kept out of Argentina; he was somewhat [[isolationism|isolationist]].  Early in his presidency, Perón envisioned Argentina's role as a model for other countries in Latin America and beyond.  Such ideas were ultimately abandoned.  Despite his oppositional rhetoric, Perón frequently sought cooperation with the U.S. government on various issues.

Perón's ideology was economic and political in character and did not have the [[racism]] of [[Nazi Germany]], though he was sympathetic to the Nazi government. He made arrangements for many Nazi war criminals and collaborators to reach Argentina under false passports after the Second World War. Among them were [[Joseph Mengele]], [[Adolf Eichmann]], and [[Erich Priebke]].

Before Perón came to power in Argentina, Argentina had the largest Jewish population in Latin America. After becoming president, he invited members of the Jewish community to participate in his government.  One of his advisors was [[José Ber Gelbard]], a Jewish man from Poland. Peronism did not have anti-Semitic or other racial bias.&lt;ref&gt;Crassweller, David. ''Perón and the Enigmas of Argentina''. W.W. Norton and Company. 1987: 221. ISBN 0-393-30543-0&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Jewish Virtual Library]] writes that while Juan Perón had sympathized with the Axis powers, &quot;Perón also expressed sympathy for Jewish rights and established diplomatic relations with Israel in 1949. Since then, more than 45,000 Jews have immigrated to Israel from Argentina.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Jewish Virtual Library. http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/vjw/Argentina.html#WW2&lt;/ref&gt; 

In the book ''Inside Argentina from Perón to Menem'' author Laurence Levine, former president of the US-Argentine Chamber of Commerce, writes: &quot;although anti-Semitism existed in Argentina, Perón's own views and his political associations were not anti-Semitic....&lt;ref&gt;''Inside Argentina from Perón to Menem: 1950–2000 From an American Point of View'' by Laurence Levine, page 23''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; While Perón allowed many Nazi criminals to take refuge in Argentina, he also attracted many Jewish immigrants. Argentina has a Jewish population of over 200,000  citizens, the largest in Latin America and one of the largest in the world.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Continuing Efforts to Conceal Anti-Semitic Past.&quot; Valente, Marcela. IPS-Inter Press Service. April 27, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

Perón's admiration for [[Benito Mussolini|Mussolini]] is well documented.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= Contemporary Political Ideologies |last= Eatwell |first=Roger |year=1999 |publisher=Continuum International Publishing Group |isbn= 978-0-8264-5173-6 |pages=196 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Many scholars categorize Peronism as a [[fascist]] ideology.&lt;ref name=&quot;peronism&quot;&gt;Peronism and Argentina By James P. Brennan&lt;/ref&gt; [[Carlos Fayt]] believes that Peronism was just &quot;an Argentine implementation of [[Italian fascism]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;peronism&quot;/&gt; Hayes reaches the conclusion that &quot;the Peronist movement produced a form of fascism that was distinctively Latin American&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;peronism&quot;/&gt;

One of the most vocal critics of Peronism was the Argentine writer [[Jorge Luis Borges]]. After Perón ascended to the presidency in 1946, Borges spoke before the Argentine Society of Writers (SADE), saying &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Dictatorships breed oppression, dictatorships breed servility, dictatorships breed cruelty; more loathsome still is the fact that they breed idiocy. Bellboys babbling orders, portraits of [[caudillo]]s, prearranged cheers or insults, walls covered with names, unanimous ceremonies, mere discipline usurping the place of clear thinking... Fighting these sad monotonies is one of the duties of a writer. Need I remind readers of ''[[Martín Fierro]]'' or ''[[Don Segundo Sombra|Don Segundo]]'' that individualism is an old Argentine virtue.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Borges: A Life'', page  295.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==From the 1960s to modern day==
The absence of Perón, who lived for 20 years in exile in [[Spain under Franco|Francoist Spain]], is an important key to understanding Peronism.  After he went into exile, he could be invoked by a variety of Argentine sectors opposed to the current state of affairs. The [[personality cult]] of [[Eva Perón]], in particular, was conserved by supporters, while despised by the &quot;national [[bourgeoisie]]&quot;. In the 1960s, [[John William Cooke]]'s writings became an important source of left-wing revolutionary Peronism. Left-wing Peronism was represented by many organizations, from the [[Montoneros]] and the ''[[Fuerzas Armadas Peronistas]]'' to the [[Peronist Youth]], the ''[[Frente Revolucionario Peronista]]'' and the [[Revolutionary Peronist Youth]], passing by ''[[Peronismo en Lucha]]'' or ''[[Peronismo de Base]]'', which supported a [[Marxist]] viewpoint.&lt;ref name=Navarrazo&gt;Alicia Servetto, [http://bibliotecavirtual.unl.edu.ar:8180/publicaciones/bitstream/1/681/1/ES_9_17_1999_pag_91_109.pdf El derrumbe temprano de la democracia en Córdoba: Obregón Cano y el golpe policial (1973-1974)], ''Estudios Sociales'' n°17, Segundo Semestre 1999, revised paper of a 1997 Conference at the [[National University of La Pampa]], 19 pages&lt;/ref&gt;

On the other hand, older Peronists formed the base of the orthodox bureaucracy, represented by the ''[[Unión Obrera Metalúrgica]]'' ([[Augusto Vandor]], famous for his 1965 slogan &quot;For a Peronism without Perón,&quot; and declaring as well: &quot;to save Perón, one has to be against Perón&quot;, or [[José Ignacio Rucci]]). Another current was formed by the ''[[62 Organizaciones &quot;De pie junto a Perón&quot;]]'', led by [[José Alonso (trade unionist)|José Alonso]] and opposed to the right-wing Peronist unionist movement. In the early 1970s, left-wing Peronism rejected liberal democracy and political pluralism as the mask of bourgeois domination.  The anti-communist right-wing Peronism also rejected it, in the name of corporatism, claiming to return to a &quot;Christian and humanist, popular, national socialism&quot;.&lt;ref name=Navarrazo&gt;Alicia Servetto, [http://bibliotecavirtual.unl.edu.ar:8180/publicaciones/bitstream/1/681/1/ES_9_17_1999_pag_91_109.pdf El derrumbe temprano de la democracia en Córdoba: Obregón Cano y el golpe policial (1973-1974)], ''Estudios Sociales'' n°17, Segundo Semestre 1999, revised paper of a 1997 Conference at the [[National University of La Pampa]], 19 pages&lt;/ref&gt;

By 1970, many groups from opposite sides of the political spectrum had come to support Perón, from the left-wing and Catholic [[Montoneros]] to the fascist-leaning and strongly anti-Semitic ''[[Movimiento Nacionalista Tacuara]]'', one of Argentina's first [[guerrilla]] movements. In March 1973, [[Héctor José Cámpora]], who had been named as Perón's personal delegate, was [[Argentine general election, March 1973|elected President of Argentina]]. A few months after Perón's return and the subsequent [[Ezeiza massacre]], during which the Peronist Left and Right violently clashed, [[Argentine general election, September 1973|new elections]] were held in September.&lt;ref name=Navarrazo/&gt;

José Cámpora, a left-wing Peronist, was replaced by interim President [[Raúl Alberto Lastiri]], while Perón chose to openly support the Peronist right. On October 1, 1973, senator [[Humberto Martiarena]], who was the national secretary of the Superior Council of the National Justicialist Movement, publicized a document giving directives to confront &quot;subversives, terrorist and Marxist groups&quot; which had allegedly initiated a &quot;war&quot; inside the Peronist organizations.&lt;ref name=Navarrazo/&gt; From then on, the Superior Council took a firm grip on the Peronist organizations to expel the Left from it.&lt;ref name=Navarrazo/&gt; 

On that same day, a meeting took place among President [[Raúl Lastiri]], Interior Minister [[Benito Llambí]], Social Welfare Minister [[José López Rega]], general secretary of the Presidency [[José Humberto Martiarena]] and various provincial governors, which has been alleged to have been the foundational act of the ''[[Alianza Anticomunista Argentina]]'' death-squad.&lt;ref&gt;Manuel Justo Gaggero, [http://www.pagina12.com.ar/diario/elpais/1-80601-2007-02-19.html “El general en su laberinto”], ''[[Pagina/12]]'', 19 February 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
[[File:Kirchner en Gualeguaychú 5-may-2006 3-presidencia-govar.jpg|thumb|250px|[[Néstor Kirchner]] addressing a multitude at Gualeguaychú.]]
The official Peronist party is the [[Justicialist Party]] (PJ), which was the only Peronist party for a long time. During the government of [[Carlos Menem]] a group of legislators led by [[Carlos Álvarez (politician)|Carlos Álvarez]], known as the &quot;Group of 8&quot;, left the party, claiming that the government was not following Peronist doctrines. They created a new party, the [[Broad Front|&quot;Frente Grande&quot; (Broad Front)]]. 

A short time later, [[José Octavio Bordón]] left the PJ as well, fearing that he might lose a [[primary election]] against Menem, so he created his own party to take part in the 1995 elections, and allied with Álvarez' Broad Front in the [[Frepaso]] coalition. Similar breakaway movements followed frequently after that, creating many small parties which were led by single politicians claiming to be the authentic inheritors of Peronism.

==== Kirchnerism ====
{{See|Kirchnerism}}
The PJ did not participate as such during the [[Argentine general election, 2003|2003 elections]].  The party allowed all three precandidates to run for the general elections, using small parties created for that purpose. [[Néstor Kirchner]] won the elections running on a [[Front for Victory]] ticket.  As he did not disband his party after the election, [[Kirchnerism]] relies on both the PJ and the Front for Victory.

==See also==
* [[Justicialist Party]]
* [[Juan Domingo Perón]]
* [[Eva Perón]]

'''General:'''
* [[Right-wing socialism]]
* [[Argentine nationalism]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==Bibliography==
*[[Tomas Eloy Martinez]], ''El Sueño Argentino' (The Argentine Dream, 1999) and ''Memorias del General'' (Memoirs of the General, 1996).
*[[Daniel James (historian)|Daniel James]], Resistance and Integration: Peronism and the Argentine Working Class, 1946-1979. NY: Cambridge University Press, 1988.
*[[Félix Luna]], Perón y Su Tiempo, Vol I-III.: Sudamericana, 1990.

{{Juan Domingo Perón}}
{{Argentina topics}}

[[Category:Justicialist Party]]
[[Category:Peronism]]
[[Category:Political philosophy by politician]]
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Third Position]]

{{Link GA|de}}

[[ar:بيرونية (الأرجنتين)]]
[[br:Peronouriezh]]
[[ca:Peronisme]]
[[cs:Perónismus]]
[[de:Peronismus]]
[[es:Peronismo]]
[[eu:Peronismo]]
[[fr:Péronisme]]
[[gl:Peronismo]]
[[ko:페론주의]]
[[it:Peronismo]]
[[he:פרוניזם]]
[[ka:პერონიზმი]]
[[ku:Peronîzm]]
[[nl:Peronisme]]
[[no:Peronisme]]
[[pl:Peronizm]]
[[pt:Peronismo]]
[[ru:Перонизм]]
[[sk:Peronizmus]]
[[fi:Peronismi]]
[[sv:Peronism]]
[[th:ลัทธิเปรอง]]
[[tr:Peronizm]]
[[uk:Перонізм]]
[[zh:庇隆主义]]</text>
      <sha1>a5bq7nqi0l9ftggm89inhbczsrw63on</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
