<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Peter F. Paul</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1529042</id>
    <revision>
      <id>508502269</id>
      <parentid>491830015</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-08-21T19:30:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>75.82.125.53</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23905">[[Image:Hillary Clinton and her largest donor Peter Paul.jpg|thumb|right|Peter Paul with [[Hillary Clinton]] in 2000.]]
'''Peter Franklin (F.) Paul''' (born September 2, 1948)&lt;ref name=&quot;USDOJ 2005-03-08&quot;&gt;United States Attorney's Office, [http://www.usdoj.gov/usao/nye/pr/2005mar8.htm &quot;Peter Paul, co-founder of Stan Lee Media, Inc., pleads guilty to securities fraud; Fraud scheme caused $25 million in losses to investors and financial institutions&quot;], press release, March ], 2005.&lt;!--checked--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; is a former [[lawyer]] and entrepreneur who was convicted for conspiracy and drug dealing, and later for securities fraud in connection with his business dealings with ''[[Spider-Man]]'' co-creator [[Stan Lee]]. He has repeatedly brought suit against [[Hillary Clinton]], accusing her of lying about donations he solicited on behalf of her 2000 senatorial campaign.&lt;ref name=&quot;Washington Post 2005-10-09&quot;&gt;April Witt, [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/10/04/AR2005100401150.html &quot;House Of Cards: What do Cher, a Hollywood con man, a political rising star and an audacious felon have in common? Together they gave Bill and Hillary Clinton a night they'll never forget &amp;ndash; no matter how hard they may try&quot;], ''The Washington Post'', October 9, 2005, p. W10.&lt;/ref&gt;

== The Cuban coffee caper==
In the 1970s, Peter Paul was a lawyer in [[Miami, Florida]], representing foreign governments and political leaders in [[South America]] and the [[Caribbean]].{{Citation needed|date=February 2008}} He also served as President of the [[Miami World Trade Center]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Lawyer Extradited Back to U.S. from Brazil for Fraud Charges&quot;, ''[[Miami Herald]]'', September 30, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; and was the original owner and operator of the largest{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}} [[Foreign Trade Zone]] in the U.S., Miami Free Zone Inc.&lt;ref name=&quot;Washington Post 2005-10-09&quot;/&gt; As a result of what Paul described as anti-Communist and anti-Castro political activities,&lt;ref name =&quot;cj200105&quot;&gt;&quot;Who Killed Stan Lee Media? Peter Paul Tells His Side of the Story&quot;, ''Comics Journal'', May 2001, p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt; he directed a fraud on the [[Cuba]]n government of $8.75 million dollars by selling agents of Cuban president [[Fidel Castro]] nonexistent coffee. The plan apparently also involved sinking the ship that was to deliver the nonexistent coffee to hide the fraud from Castro and, according to TIME Magazine, to defraud its insurer, but the conspirators neglected to bribe a port official in Santo Domingo, and the people who were supposed to scuttle the boat were not allowed on board.&lt;ref name=&quot;Washington Post 2005-10-09&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Cuban coffee caper&quot;, ''[[TIME Magazine]]'', February 12, 1979.&lt;/ref&gt;

Paul pleaded guilty to federal conspiracy charges. When his home was raided by the police in connection with this crime, they found cocaine in his garage, and Paul also pleaded guilty to possessing cocaine with intent to distribute.&lt;ref name=&quot;Washington Post 2005-10-09&quot;/&gt; He was sentenced to eight years in prison for the cocaine charge, and a concurrent three years for fraud; he was paroled after three years. His license to practice law was suspended as a result of the convictions,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Clinton benefit has a lesson: Double-check that donor list&quot;, ''[[The New York Times]]'', February 9, 2005, p. B1.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.awn.com/mag/issue5.11/5.11pages/rogersslee2.php3 &quot;Heroes wanted: Stan Lee Media struggles to stay afloat&quot;], ''Animation World Magazine'' 5.11, February 2001.&lt;/ref&gt; and he claims to have been sued by the Cuban government as well.&lt;ref name =&quot;cj200105&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;His supporters cite Dean Witter Reynolds v Fernandez v McDonald &amp; Paul, No 79-112 CIV-CA (S.D. Fla)&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1983, Paul was caught traveling to [[Canada]] using the identity of a dead man;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Clinton Link to Fund-Raiser Adds Spice to Mundane Trial,&quot; Leslie Eaton, ''New York Times,'' May 11, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; he pleaded guilty to federal charges of [[making false statements]] to customs inspectors. This was a violation of his parole terms from the 1979 felonies, and he went back to jail.&lt;ref name=&quot;Washington Post 2005-10-09&quot;/&gt;

== Involvement in politics and the entertainment industry ==

After being released from federal prison in California, Paul moved to [[Los Angeles, California|Los Angeles]]. In 1985, he was appointed President of the California Bicentennial Foundation for the Constitution and Bill of Rights&lt;!--NOTE I can find no contemporary sources referring to an entity of this name. All sources refer to the &quot;California Bicentennial Commission&quot; --&gt;, a foundation designated by the California state legislature and governor to direct California's role in the Bicentennial celebration of the Constitution and Bill of Rights.&lt;ref name=&quot;lat19870902&quot;&gt;&quot;Most Unconstitutional: Editorial&quot;, ''[[The Los Angeles Times Times]]'', September 2, 1987.&lt;/ref&gt; Paul's efforts on behalf of the Foundation were derided in the Los Angeles Times, in part because the commission was selling a book that described blacks as “pickaninnies”, and slaveowners as “the worst victims of slavery”,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;We The People: The Selling of the Bicentennial,&quot; ABA Journal, September 1, 1987.&lt;/ref&gt; and in part because Paul referred to the founding fathers of the United States as &quot;39 sweaty old men arguing in Philadelphia&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;lat19870902&quot;/&gt; and remarked that most Californians weren't able to understand the 18th century language in the constitution anyway.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Selling the Constitution,&quot; Los Angeles Times, September 1, 1987, Metro p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt; Prior to the Los Angeles Times article, Chief Justice [[Warren Burger]] had commended Paul for his efforts in a letter that read in part &quot;We commend you for the many contributions you have made during the national commemoration of the Constitution's 200th anniversary&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Letter published in the tribute journal for the 2nd Annual Spirit of America Awards and Governor's Ball, Los Angeles, California, October 17, 1988&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Hillary Returns Bucks to Ex-Felon&quot; [[Lloyd Grove]],''[[The Washington Post]]'', August 17, 2000.&lt;/ref&gt;

Paul became a business manager for, or otherwise involved with several celebrities, including becoming manager for a time of romance-novel icon [[Fabio Lanzoni|Fabio]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Wall Street: The dubious profits in patriotism&quot;, ''[[The New York Times]]'', July 22, 1990, p. A15.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Comics exec focuses on 'Spider-Man 2' as former partner prepares for trial&quot;, ''[[USA Today]]'', May 12, 2004, p. B01.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Hillary Clinton's senatorial campaign ===

Paul emerged in 2000 as the largest contributor to Senatorial candidate [[Hillary Clinton]]. Paul and his attorneys have at various times offered two explanations for this. First, that he was trying to attract her husband, then-President Bill Clinton, to serve on the board of [[Stan Lee Media]] after leaving office. Second, that he hoped to negotiate a [[pardon]] for his previous criminal convictions.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Golden Fleece; Aaron's Cash Cows&quot;, ''Vanity Fair'', August 2003, page 160.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;LAT 2003-07-20&quot;&gt;&quot;Money, Politics and the Undoing of Stan Lee Media; A fund-raiser for Hillary Clinton triggered events that contributed to the Web firm's collapse. In the fallout, several may face prison terms&quot;, ''Los Angeles Times'', July 20, 2003, p. C1.&lt;/ref&gt; Paul produced and underwrote what he described as the largest fund raising event ever held for a federal candidate,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newsmax.com/archives/ic/2006/1/5/114148.shtml Hillary Clinton Campaign Acknowledges Violation] by NewsMax.com Staff, NewsMax.com, Jan. 5, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; in [[Brentwood, Los Angeles, California|Los Angeles]], days before the 2000 Democratic Convention began. The [[Hollywood Farewell Gala Salute to President William Jefferson Clinton]] featured prominent entertainers singing for the President, while raising over $1 million for Hillary Clinton's Senate campaign.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hillcap.org/default.php?page_id=14 Clinton Campaign Magic: Making a Scandal Disappear&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The event cost $1.9 million to organize according to Paul and $500,000 according to the Federal Election Commission filing, much of it borrowed fraudulently by Paul from [[Merrill Lynch]]. Later indictments would state that Merrill Lynch lost about $5 million it had lent to Paul.&lt;ref name=&quot;LAT 2003-07-20&quot;/&gt;

Two days after the gala, the ''Washington Post'' publicized Paul's criminal record, and Hillary Clinton denied knowing Paul and &quot;vowed not to take any contributions from him&quot;. Through her spokesman, Howard Wolfson, Hillary stated on August 16, 2000, that she would return $2,000 she reported receiving from Paul in June 2000&lt;ref name=&quot;LAT 2003-07-20&quot;/&gt;.

Paul alleged that Clinton was deceitful in this,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hillcap.org/default.php?page_id=41 Clintons' Fall Guy May Turn the Tables] by Paul M. Rodriguez, Insight Magazine, October 16, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; and retained public interest law firm, and frequent Clinton opponent, [[Judicial Watch]] to represent him in a series of civil and criminal lawsuits against the Clintons, the Clinton campaign, and ultimately the Federal Election Commission (which he charged was negligent in failing to convict Mrs. Clinton).&lt;ref&gt;[http://video.google.com/videoplay?docid=1098759488588186036 Paul appeared on ABC's ''20/20'' with allegations against Hillary Clinton]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hillcap.org/pp_complaint_022504_njw.pdf Paul's civil fraud and coercion suit against the Clintons]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;U.S. fugitive tied to Clintons caught in Brazil&quot;, ''The Washington Post'', August 4, 2001, p. A12.&lt;!--TODO: check this--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;FEC Litigation Release, [http://www.fec.gov/law/litigation_CCA_J.shtml &quot;Judicial Watch Inc. and Peter F. Paul v. FEC (1:01CV02527)&quot;], August 30, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; These charges were delayed, as courts held that Paul could not bring charges against the Clintons as he fought extradition from Brazil (to which he had fled in 2001 to escape Stan-Lee-Media-related criminal charges, see below),&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hillcap.org &quot;Court upholds dismissal of fugitive's lawsuit against Clintons&quot;], ''Metropolitan News-Enterprise'', December 12, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; but proceeded once he was returned to the States.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Court allows suit against Clintons&quot;, San Francisco Chronicle, p. B2, October 21, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2005, Paul had a falling out with his advocates at Judicial Watch. He accused them of using his name to raise more than $15 million from people who disliked the Clintons, while doing little to advance his case. He announced his plan to replace them with a &quot;dream team&quot; of Republican lawyers,&lt;ref name=&quot;New York Times 2005-03-15&quot;&gt;“Battling the Clintons, and each other (Judicial Watch may tie up Peter F. Paul)”, ''[[The New York Times]]'', March 15, 2005, p. B3.&lt;/ref&gt; and in February 2007, he filed suit against them, saying that they had taken advantage of him and that he was “not a big fan of their behavior”.&lt;ref name=&quot;sun200702&quot;&gt;“Former Donor To Clinton Sues Judicial Watch”, Josh Gerstein, ''New York Sun'', February 8, 2007, p. 5.&lt;/ref&gt;

Regardless, Paul's claims have not found traction. An audit by the Federal Elections Commission found that neither Senator Clinton nor her Senate campaign had accepted any illegal funds in connection with the Hollywood fundraiser,&lt;ref name=&quot;ap200712&quot;&gt;“Court says Hillary Clinton shouldn't be defendant in lawsuit”, Greg Risling, Associated Press, October 16, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; though the campaign was asked to pay $35,000 in fines for having under-reported the cost of the party.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hillcap.org/default.php?page_id=53] MUR 5225 &quot;In the Matter of New York Senate 2000 and Andrew Grossman, in his official capacity as treasurer, Conciliation Agreement&quot;, December 19, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; Paul's suit against the FEC was thrown out; his attempt to bring ethics charges against Clinton were rejected,&lt;ref&gt;“Ethics Committee Won't Hear Clinton Fund-Raising Case”, ''The New York Sun'', June 14, 2006, p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt; and his fraud charges against Senator Clinton were tossed out in April 2006.&lt;ref&gt;“White House 2008 — The Democrats”, ''National Journal Group Hotline'', April 10, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;  Paul continued to press civil charges against Senator Clinton and former President Clinton for &quot;looting&quot;&lt;ref&gt;“Producer accuses Clintons of ‘looting’; Complaint will be heard today”, ''Washington Times'', September 25, 2006, page A01.&lt;/ref&gt; his business, but the courts refused to allow him to sue Senator Clinton, with the appellate court specifying that her behavior had been “perfectly legal”, and allowing her to recoup her legal fees from Paul.&lt;ref name=&quot;ap200712&quot;/&gt;

Finding no luck in the courts, in 2007 Paul promoted a thirteen and a half minute video titled “Hillary Exposed: The Case of Paul v. Clinton”, attacking Senator Clinton. Her office responded “Peter Paul is a professional liar who has four separate criminal convictions, two for fraud. His video repackages a series of seven-year-old false claims about Senator Clinton that have already been rejected by the California state courts, the Justice Department, the Federal Election Commission, and the Senate Ethics Committee.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;“Anti-Clinton Video Draws Web Audience”, Jim Kuhnhenn, Associated Press, October 30, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2008, he re-filed his complaint with the FEC.&lt;ref&gt;“Former Clinton Donor Files FEC Complaint Seeking Further Investigation Of 2000 Event”, ''National Campaign News'', January 8, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Paul's suit against former President Clinton remains, as of December 2007, outstanding. He is seeking $41.9 million in damages.&lt;ref&gt;“Clinton: Stand by Your (Wo)Man”, The Hotline, September 26, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Involvement with Stan Lee ==
=== Founding of Stan Lee Media, fraud, and flight ===

In 1998, Paul co-founded [[Stan Lee Media]] with comic book legend [[Stan Lee]]&lt;ref name=&quot;USDOJ 2005-03-08&quot;/&gt; and took the company public via a reverse-merger into a trading shell in August 1999.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Stan Lee Media debuts as public company, stock up 41 percent&quot;, ''[[Bloomberg News]]'', August 16, 1999.&lt;/ref&gt;

In February, 2000, in the midst of the Internet stock market boom, Stan Lee Media built a 165 person studio, and the company's market capitalization grew to over $370 million.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}} However, at the end of the year, Stan Lee Media ran out of money. Paul alleged in a later civil fraud and coercion suit against Bill and Hillary Clinton that the company failed because of the intervention of Bill Clinton, who he claims persuaded a large investor not to further support the company.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;All The Ex-President's Scandals&quot;, ''[[World Net Daily]]'', April 25, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the aftermath of the company's collapse, it was alleged that Paul and a corporate officer named Stephan Gordon had illegally tried to support the stock's price by using nominee accounts to buy 1.6 million shares of the company's stock, attempting to pay for the stock with bad checks.&lt;ref name=&quot;LR-18828 2004&quot;&gt;SEC Litigation Release No. LR-18828, August 11, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2001, Stan Lee Media filed for bankruptcy, and Peter Paul fled to São Paulo, Brazil.&lt;ref name=&quot;inside 2001-03-05&quot;&gt;&quot;Stan Lee Holder Peter Paul Flees to South America, According to Cohort's Affidavit&quot;, ''Inside.com'', March 5, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Washington Post 2005-05-13&quot;&gt;&quot;Witness: Fundraiser Knew Party's Cost&quot;,''The Washington Post'', May 13, 2005, p. A10.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Clintons ask court to dismiss fraud suit&quot;,''San Francisco Chronicle'', August 7, 2004, p. B3.&lt;/ref&gt; There he managed 112 Interactive do Brazil, a seller of English language acquisition software,&lt;ref name=&quot;inside 2001-03-05&quot;/&gt; and fought [[extradition]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Washington Post 2005-05-13&quot;/&gt;

=== Stan Lee-related litigation ===

Paul has promoted lawsuits against [[Marvel Entertainment]] claiming that Stan Lee Media owns the rights to all the Marvel characters created by Stan Lee.&lt;ref&gt;[http://amlawdaily.typepad.com/amlawdaily/2009/01/bam-whap-marty-garbus-joins-the-tortured-legal-history-of-stan-lee-marvel.html &quot;Bam! Whap! Marty Garbus Joins the Tortured Legal History of Stan Lee; Marvel&quot;] Brian Baxter, ''The American Lawyer,'' January 29, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; These would include [[Spider-Man]] and The [[X-Men]].&lt;ref name=&quot;barrons2008&quot;/&gt; Paul and his associates further claim that Stan Lee Media was never properly dissolved as a corporation, and that they control the company.&lt;ref name=&quot;ppfall2009&quot;&gt;[http://www.newsfeedunlimited.com/newsfeedunlimited_002.htm &quot;Peter Paul Takes The Fall&quot;], ''Newsfeed Unlimited'', August 9, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Though courts have found that some Stan Lee Media characters were improperly transferred to Stan Lee's later company, [[Pow Entertainment]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.law360.com/registrations/user_registration?article_id=84854&amp;concurrency_check=false Law360 summary, January 27, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; plaintiffs have not yet found traction with these broader claims,&lt;ref&gt;United States District Court, Central District of California, Case No. 07-CV-00225-SVW (SSx).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.powentertainment.com/Press_Releases/Entries/2009/3/17_STAN_LEE_SECURES_VICTORY_IN_COLORADO_LAWSUIT.html Pow Entertainment press release, March 17, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;thr201004&quot;&gt;[http://thresq.hollywoodreporter.com/2010/04/stan-lee-marvel-lawsuit-dismissed.html &quot;Federal Judge Dismisses Claims By Stan Lee Media Shareholders,&quot;] Eriq Gardner, ''THR, Esq,'' April 1, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; and Stan Lee himself has both publicly dismissed these claims and has engaged in a series of cross-suits with Stan Lee Media, Peter Paul, and his associates.&lt;ref name=&quot;ppfall2009&quot;/&gt;

On March 3, 2008, Paul posted a message to his blog,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.peterfpaul.com/2008/03/05/media-protects-hillarys-role-in-bill-clintons-civil-fraud-case-in-los-angeles/ &quot;Media Protects Hillary’s Role in Bill Clinton’s Civil Fraud Case in Los Angeles,&quot;] on Paul's personal website.&lt;/ref&gt; subsequently reposted by one or more unknown parties verbatim on other websites,&lt;ref&gt;[http://digg.com/2008_us_elections/The_Colbert_Report_Is_Hillary_Clinton_A_Muslim_Video] posting by &quot;pedromatos,&quot; on March 13, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://digitalartpress.wordpress.com/2008/03/15/obama-and-rezco-uncovered-ties/] posting by &quot;Pedro,&quot; on March 16, 2008, at 2:41 am.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://electioninspection.wordpress.com/2008/03/15/is-barack-obama-a-teflon-candidate/] posting by &quot;Pedro,&quot; on March 15, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.aol.com/political-machine/2008/03/07/if-there-was-a-michigan-redo/] posting by &quot;Lani,&quot; on March 8, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; in which he claimed that Stan Lee helped disguise the origin of Paul's unreported donations to Hillary Clinton, and that he (Paul) has a video tape of Lee admitting to this subterfuge. Lee responded with a lawsuit against Paul, claiming defamation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.peterfpaul.com/2008/08/26/stan-lee-sues-peter-paul-for-blogging-libel-in-100k-illegal-donation-to-hillary-clinton/ &quot;Stan Lee Sues Peter Paul For Blogging Libel in $100k Illegal Donation to Hillary Clinton,&quot;] on Paul's personal website.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Securities fraud conviction and jail terms ===

On June 12, 2001, Paul was indicted on one count of violating SEC Reg. 10(b)5, for manipulating the price of the stock in Stan Lee Media. On August 3, 2001, Paul was arrested in Brazil and jailed, pending the outcome of extradition proceedings.&lt;ref name=&quot;USDOJ 2005-03-08&quot;/&gt;  Paul failed in his efforts to avoid extradition and, in September 2003, he was delivered to the Metropolitan Detention Facility in [[Brooklyn, New York]], for arraignment and trial.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Lawyer extradited back to U.S. from Brazil for fraud charges&quot;, ''[[Miami Herald]]'', September 30, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;SEC joins probe of Stan Lee Media; Sources say investigators in Los Angeles are conducting interviews and reviewing records&quot;, ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'', October 2, 2003, p. C1.&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2004, the SEC formally filed its complaint against Paul for the manipulation of Stan Lee Media's stock in violation of the antifraud provisions of Section 17(a) of the Securities Act of 1933, Section 10(b) of the Securities Exchange Act, and SEC Rule 10b-5.&lt;ref name=&quot;LR-18828 2004&quot;/&gt; Paul pleaded guilty to the securities fraud charge. The government characterized his conduct as causing &quot;losses to the investing public and financial institutions of approximately $25 million&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;USDOJ 2005-03-08&quot;/&gt; In July 2005, he settled related civil charges, consenting to a permanent injunction against ever serving as an officer or director of any reporting company. He pleaded poverty and, as a result, was not asked to pay any fine.&lt;ref&gt;[http://thehollywoodreporter.com/thr/business/brief_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1000989551 &quot;Stan Lee Media co-founder settles SEC charges&quot;], ''The Hollywood Reporter'', July 22, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&lt;!-- agency or author missing --&gt;&quot;Final Judgment Against Stan Lee Media Co-Founder P. Paul&quot;, Litigation Release No. LR-19308, July 21, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; He then spent four years under house arrest,&lt;ref name=&quot;sun200702&quot;/&gt; wearing an &quot;ankle bracelet&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;barrons2008&quot;&gt;[http://online.barrons.com/article/SB121461369005812701.html?mod=article-outset-boxon &quot;The Rage Offstage at Marvel,&quot;] Bill Alpert, ''Barron's,'' June 30, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 2009, Paul accepted a plea bargain &lt;ref name=&quot;law360 2011&quot;&gt;[http://www.law360.com/articles/230265/2nd-circ-affirms-ex-stan-lee-exec-s-fraud-sentence &quot;2nd Circ. Affirms Ex-Stan Lee Exec's Fraud Sentence,&quot;] Melissa Lipman, law360.com&lt;/ref&gt; and was sentenced to ten years in prison,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.politico.com/blogs/joshgerstein/0709/After_4_years_Clintons_accuser_sentenced_to_10.html Politico.com] July 22, 2009, &quot;After 4 years, Clintons' accuser sentenced to 10&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; and ordered to pay over $11 million in restitution to Merrill Lynch and [[Spear, Leeds &amp; Kellogg]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ppfall2009&quot;/&gt; He self-surrendered on September 30, 2009, but subsequently tried to have the plea bargain annulled, claiming that the judge coerced him into agreeing to the deal.&lt;ref name=&quot;law360 2011&quot;/&gt; In March 2011, the courts rejected this attempt&lt;ref name=&quot;law360 2011&quot;/&gt;, and Paul is serving his 10-year imprisonment term as inmate number 78802-012.&lt;ref name=&quot;ppfall2009&quot;/&gt; As of February 2012, he was imprisoned in [[Anthony, Texas]] and eligible for parole in late 2014.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bop.gov/iloc2/InmateFinderServlet?Transaction=IDSearch&amp;needingMoreList=false&amp;IDType=IRN&amp;IDNumber=78802-012&amp;x=71&amp;y=16 Federal Prisoner Locator]&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
*[[Hollywood fundraiser controversy]]
*[[Paul v. Clinton]]

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

== External links ==
* [http://web.archive.org/web/20090221184446/http://peterfpaul.com/ Wayback archive of Peter Paul's personal website]
* [http://www.hillcap.org/ Hillary Clinton Accountability Project The public record on Paul v Clinton]
* [http://www.bop.gov/iloc2/InmateFinderServlet?Transaction=IDSearch&amp;needingMoreList=false&amp;IDType=IRN&amp;IDNumber=78802-012&amp;x=71&amp;y=16 Federal Bureau of Prisons] locator page for Peter F. Paul.

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Paul, Peter F.
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = September 2, 1948
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Paul, Peter F.}}
[[Category:1948 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:American businesspeople]]
[[Category:American drug traffickers]]
[[Category:American fraudsters]]
[[Category:American lawyers]]
[[Category:American people convicted of fraud]]
[[Category:American people imprisoned abroad]]
[[Category:American political fundraisers]]
[[Category:American white-collar criminals]]
[[Category:Disbarred lawyers]]
[[Category:Extradited people]]
[[Category:Hillary Rodham Clinton]]
[[Category:Prisoners and detainees of Brazil]]
[[Category:Prisoners and detainees of the United States federal government]]</text>
      <sha1>j9xx29wpfhspny3bm1iox3uj6yxohci</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
