<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Political spectrum</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>23490</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521712166</id>
      <parentid>521712142</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-06T19:21:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contributions/204.83.240.101|204.83.240.101]] to version by DexDor. False positive? [[User:ClueBot NG/FalsePositives|Report it]]. Thanks, [[User:ClueBot NG|ClueBot NG]]. (1318663) (Bot)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="48203">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
[[Image:Political chart.svg|thumb|250px|This chart proposed by the Political Compass Organization, which extends from -10 to +10 on each axis, is one of several competing models.]]
{{Party politics}}

A '''political spectrum''' is a way of modeling different [[politics|political]] positions by placing them upon one or more [[geometry|geometric]] [[coordinate axis|axes]] symbolizing independent political dimensions.

Most long-standing spectra include a [[right wing]] and [[left wing]], which originally referred to seating arrangements in the 18th century French parliament. According to the simplest [[left-right politics|left-right]] axis, [[communism]] and [[socialism]] are usually regarded internationally as being on the left, opposite [[fascism]] and [[conservatism]] on the right. [[Liberalism]] can mean different things in different contexts, sometimes on the left, sometimes on the right. There is politics that rejects the conventional left-right spectrum, this is known as [[syncretic politics]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Roger |last=Griffin |title=Fascism |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=3ssUAQAAIAAJ |year=1995 |publisher=Oxford University Press |isbn=978-0-19-289249-2 |pages=8,307}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |editor-first=Aristotle A. |editor-last=Kallis |title=The fascism reader |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=tP2wXl5nzboC |year=2003 |publisher=Routledge |isbn=978-0-415-24359-9 |page=71 |chapter=A 'Spectral-Syncretic' Approach to Fascism |chapterurl=http://books.google.com/books?id=tP2wXl5nzboC&amp;pg=PA71 |last=Eatwell |first=Roger }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

However, researchers have frequently noted that a single left-right axis is insufficient in describing the existing variation in political beliefs, and often include other axes. Though the descriptive words at polar opposites may vary, often in popular biaxial spectra the axes are split between cultural issues and economic issues, each scaling from some form of [[individualism]] (or government for the freedom of the individual) to some form of [[communitarianism]] (or government for the welfare of the community). In this context, the contemporary American left is often considered individualist (or [[Libertarianism|libertarian]]) on social/cultural issues and communitarian (or populist) on economic issues, while the contemporary American right is often considered communitarian (or populist) on social/cultural issues and individualist (or libertarian) on economic issues.

==Historical origin of the terms==
[[Image:Multi-axis political spectrum.svg|thumb|250px|right|An example of a biaxial political spectrum chart; it is a variant of the [[Nolan chart]].]]
&lt;imagemap&gt;Image:European-political-spectrum.png|thumb|right|372px|Hans Slomp projection of the [[Europe]]an political spectrum.&lt;ref name=&quot;slomp&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Slomp |first=Hans |title=European Politics Into the Twenty-First Century: Integration and Division |publisher=Praeger |isbn=0-275-96814-6 |year=2000 |location=Westport}}&lt;/ref&gt; Clickable.

rect 236 0 531 82 [[Libertarianism]]
rect 38 35 233 150 [[Anarchism]]
rect 272 112 453 199 [[Social liberalism]]
rect 456 143 637 232 [[Conservative liberalism]]
rect 138 169 327 263 [[Social democracy]]
rect 0 255 134 364 [[Left-wing politics]]
rect 624 255 764 364 [[Right-wing politics]]
rect 280 331 483 447 [[Christian democracy]]
rect 487 376 650 476 [[Conservatism]]
rect 543 526 696 617 [[Fascism]]
rect 83 512 246 613 [[Communism]]
rect 275 550 482 650 [[Authoritarianism]]
rect 280 266 482 328 [[Centrism]]

&lt;/imagemap&gt;

The terms ''[[Right-wing politics|Right]]'' and ''[[Left-wing politics|Left]]'' refer to political affiliations which originated early in the [[French Revolution]]ary era of 1789–1796, and referred originally to the seating arrangements in the [[Glossary of the French Revolution#Governmental structures|various legislative bodies]] of [[France]]. The [[aristocracy]] sat on the right of the [[Speaker (politics)|Speaker]] (traditionally the seat of honor) and the [[commoners]] sat on the Left, hence the terms [[Right-wing politics]] and [[Left-wing politics]].

Originally, the defining point on the ideological spectrum was the ''[[ancien régime]]'' (&quot;old order&quot;). &quot;The Right&quot; thus implied support for aristocratic or royal interests, and the church, while &quot;The Left&quot;  implied support for [[republicanism]], [[secularism]], and [[civil liberty|civil liberties]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Knapp&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first1=Andrew |last1=Knapp |first2=Vincent |last2=Wright |title=The Government and Politics of France|year=2006|publisher=Routledge |url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=67ttjXHhT3wC |isbn=0-415-35732-2 |edition=5th}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because the [[political franchise]] at the start of the [[revolution]] was relatively narrow, the original &quot;Left&quot; represented mainly the interests of the [[bourgeoisie]], the rising [[Bourgeoisie|capitalist class]] (with notable exceptions such as the proto-communist [[François-Noël Babeuf|Gracchus Babeuf]]). Support for [[laissez-faire capitalism]] and [[Free market]]s were expressed by politicians sitting on the left, because these represented policies favorable to capitalists rather than to the aristocracy; but outside of parliamentary politics, these views are often characterized as being on the Right.

The reason for this apparent contradiction lies in the fact that those 'to the left' of the parliamentary left, outside of official parliamentary structures (such as the ''[[sans-culottes]]'' of the French Revolution), typically represent much of the working class, poor peasantry, and the unemployed. Their political interests in the French Revolution lay with opposition to the aristocracy, and so they found themselves allied with the early capitalists. However, this did not mean that their economic interests lay with the 'laissez-faire' policies of those representing them politically.

As capitalist economies developed, the aristocracy became less relevant and were mostly replaced by capitalist representatives. The size of the working class increased as capitalism expanded, and began to find expression partly through trade unionist, socialist, anarchist, and communist politics, rather than being confined to the capitalist policies expressed by the original 'left'. This evolution has often pulled parliamentary politicians away from laissez-faire economic policies, although this has happened to different degrees in different countries.

Thus, the word 'left' in American political parlance may refer to 'liberalism' and be identified with the Democratic Party, whereas in a country such as France these positions would be regarded as relatively more right-wing, and 'left' is more likely to refer to 'socialist' positions rather than 'liberal' ones.

==Academic investigation==
For almost a century, social scientists have considered the problem of how best to describe political variation; a sample of their results is given below.

===Early research===
In 1950, [[Leonard W. Ferguson]] carried out an analysis of political values using ten scales measuring attitudes toward:
*[[Birth control]]
*[[Capital punishment]]
*[[Censorship]]
*[[Communism]]
*[[Evolution]]
*[[Law]]
*[[Patriotism]]
*[[Theism]]
*Treatment of [[criminals]]
*[[War]]

Submitting the results to [[factor analysis]], he was able to identify three factors, which he named ''[[Religionism]]'', ''[[Humanitarianism]]'', and ''[[Nationalism]]''.

Leonard Ferguson's ''Religionism'' was defined by [[belief in God]] and negative attitudes toward [[evolution]] and [[birth control]]; ''Humanitarianism'' was related to attitudes opposing the harsh [[Criminal justice|treatment of criminals]], [[capital punishment]], and [[war]]; and ''Nationalism'' described variation in opinions on [[censorship]], [[law]], [[patriotism]], and [[communism]].

This system was derived empirically; rather than devising a political model on purely theoretical grounds and testing it, Ferguson's research was exploratory. As a result of this method, care must be taken in the interpretation of Ferguson's three factors, as factor analysis will output an abstract 'factor' whether an objectively real factor exists or not.&lt;reF&gt;SAS(R) 3.11 Users Guide, [http://support.sas.com/documentation/cdl/en/stsug/62259/HTML/default/viewer.htm#ugmultfactor.htm Multivariate Analysis: Factor Analysis]&lt;/ref&gt; Although replication of the ''Nationalism'' factor was inconsistent, the finding of ''Religionism'' and ''Humanitarianism'' had a number of replications by Ferguson and others.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Ferguson, L.W. |title=The Stability of the Primary Social Attitudes: I. Religionism and Humanitarianism |journal=Journal of Psychology |volume=12 |issue=2 |pages=283–8 |year=1941 |doi=10.1080/00223980.1941.9917075 |url=http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/00223980.1941.9917075}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Kirkpatrick, C. |title=Religion and humanitarianism: a study of institutional implications |journal=Psychological Monograph |volume=63 |issue=9 |year=1949 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Eysenck's research===
Shortly afterward, [[Hans Eysenck]] began researching political attitudes in [[Great Britain]]. He believed that there was something existentially similar about the [[National Socialists]] or [[Nazis]] on the one hand, and the [[Communists]] on the other, despite their opposite positions on the [[left-right axis]].

As Hans Eysenck described in his 1956 book ''Sense and Nonsense in Psychology'',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ditext.com/eysenck/politics.html Digital Text International homepage]&lt;/ref&gt; Eysenck compiled a list of political statements found in newspapers and political tracts and asked subjects to rate their agreement or disagreement with each.

Submitting this value questionnaire to the same process of [[factor analysis]] used by Ferguson, Eysenck drew out two factors, which he named &quot;Radicalism&quot; (R-factor) and &quot;Tender-Mindedess&quot; (T-factor). 

Such analysis produces a factor whether or not it corresponds to a real-world phenomenon, and so caution must be exercised in its interpretation. While Eysenck's R-factor is easily identified as the classical &quot;left-right&quot; dimension, the T-factor (representing a factor drawn at right angles to the R-factor) is less intuitive; high-scorers favored [[pacifism]], [[racial equality]], [[religious education]], and restrictions on [[abortion]], while low-scorers had attitudes more friendly to [[militarism]], harsh [[punishment]], easier [[divorce]] [[laws]], and [[Triangular theory of love|companionate]] [[marriage]].

Despite the difference in [[methodology]], [[location (geography)|location]], and [[theory]], the results attained by Eysenck and Ferguson matched; simply rotating Eysenck's two factors 45 degrees renders the same factors of ''[[Religionism]]'' and ''[[Humanitarianism]]'' identified by Ferguson in America.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eysenck&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Eysenck, H.J. |title=Sense and nonsense in psychology |publisher=Penguin Books |location=London |year=1956 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Eysenck's dimensions of R and T were found by factor analyses of values in [[Germany]] and [[Sweden]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Eysenck, H.J. |title=Primary social attitudes: A comparison of attitude patterns in England, Germany, and Sweden |journal=Journal of Abnormal and Social Psychology |volume=48 |issue=4 |pages=563–8 |year=1953 |doi=10.1037/h0054347 |url=http://psycnet.apa.org/journals/abn/48/4/563/}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[France]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Eysenck&quot; /&gt; and [[Japan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Dator, J.A. |chapter=Measuring attitudes across cultures: A factor analysis of the replies of Japanese judges to Eysenck's inventory of conservative-progressive ideology |editor1-last=Schubert |editor2-first=David Joseph |editor2-last=Danelski |title=Comparative judicial behavior: cross-cultural studies of political decision-making in the East and West |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Yz5BAAAAIAAJ |year=1969 |publisher=Oxford University Press |editor1-first=Glendon A.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One interesting result Eysenck noted in his 1956 work was that in the [[United States]] and [[Great Britain]], most of the political variance was subsumed by the left/right axis, while in [[France]], the T-axis was larger, and in the [[Middle East]], the only dimension to be found was the T-axis: &quot;Among mid-Eastern Arabs it has been found that while the tough-minded/tender-minded dimension is still clearly expressed in the relationships observed between different attitudes, there is nothing that corresponds to the [[Political radicalism|radical]]-[[conservative]] continuum.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eysenck&quot; /&gt;

====Relationship between Eysenck's political views and political research====

Eysenck's political views related to his research: Eysenck was an outspoken opponent of what he perceived as the [[authoritarian]] abuses of the [[Left-wing politics|left]] and [[right]], and accordingly he believed that, with this T axis, he had found the link between [[nazism]] and [[communism]]. According to Eysenck, members of both [[ideologies]] were tough-minded. Central to Eysenck's thesis was the claim that tender-minded ideologies were [[democratic]] and friendly to [[liberty|human freedom]]s, while tough-minded ideologies were [[aggressive]] and [[authoritarian]], a claim that is open to political criticism. In this context, Eysenck carried out studies on [[nazism]] and [[communist]] groups, claiming to find members of both groups to be more &quot;dominant&quot; and more &quot;aggressive&quot; than control groups.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eysenck&quot; /&gt;

Eysenck left Nazi Germany to live in Britain, and was not shy in attacking [[Stalinism|Stalinist]] '[[communism]]' (which he regarded as representative of communist ideology), noting the [[Antisemitism|anti-Semitic]] prejudices of the Russian government, the luxurious lifestyles of the [[USSR]]'s leaders despite their talk about [[social equality|equality]] and the [[poverty]] of their people, and the [[George Orwell|Orwell]]ian &quot;[[doublethink]]&quot; of [[East Germany]]'s naming itself the ''[[German Democratic Republic]]'' despite being &quot;one of the most [[dictatorship|undemocratic]] [[regime]]s in the world today.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Eysenck, H.J. (1981). &quot;Left-Wing Authoritarianism: Myth or Reality?, by Hans J. Eysenck&quot; ''Political Psychology''&lt;/ref&gt; While Eysenck was an opponent of [[Nazism]], his relationship with fascist organizations was more complex. Eysenck himself lent theoretical support to the English [[National_Party_(UK,_1976)|National Party]] (which also opposed &quot;Hitlerite&quot; Nazism), and was interviewed in the first issue of their journal ''The Beacon'' in relation to his controversial views on relative intelligence between different races.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;An Interview with Prof. Hans Eysenck&quot;, ''Beacon'' February 1977&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stephen Rose, &quot;Racism&quot; ''Nature'' 14 September 1978, volume 275, page 86&lt;/ref&gt; At one point during the interview, Eysenck was asked whether or not he was of Jewish origin before the interviewer proceeded.&lt;ref&gt;Billig, Micheal. (1979) &quot;Psychology, Racism and Fascism&quot;, Chapter 6, footnote #70. Published by A.F. &amp; R. Publications.&lt;/ref&gt; His political allegiances were called into question by other researchers, notably [[Steven Rose]], who alleged that his scientific research was used for political purposes.&lt;ref&gt;Stephen Rose, &quot;Racism Refuted&quot;, ''Nature'' 24 August 1978, volume 274, page 738&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stephen Rose, &quot;Racism&quot;, ''Nature'' 14 September 1978, volume 275, page 86&lt;/ref&gt;

====Subsequent criticism of Eysenck's research====

Eysenck's conception of 'tough-mindedness' has been criticized for a number of reasons.

* Virtually no values were found to load only on the tough/tender dimension.
* The interpretation of tough-mindedness as a manifestation of &quot;[[authoritarian]]&quot; versus tender-minded &quot;[[democratic]]&quot; values was incompatible with the [[Frankfurt school]]'s [[single-axis model]], which conceptualized [[authoritarianism]] as being a fundamental manifestation of [[conservatism]], and many researchers took issue with the idea of &quot;left-wing authoritarianism.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Stone, W.F. |title=The myth of left-wing authoritarianism |journal=Political Psychology |volume=2 |issue=3/4 |pages=3–19 |year=1980 |jstor=3790998 |doi=10.2307/3790998}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The theory which Eysenck developed to explain individual variation in the observed dimensions, relating tough-mindedness to [[Extroversion]] and [[Psychoticism]], returned ambiguous research results.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Ray, J.J.; Bozek, R.S. |title=Authoritarianism and Eysenck's P-scale |journal=Journal of Social Psychology |volume=113 |issue=2 |pages=231–4 |year=1981 |doi=10.1080/00224545.1981.9924374 |url=http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/00224545.1981.9924374}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Eysenck's finding that [[nazis]] and [[communists]] were more tough-minded than members of mainstream political movements was criticised on technical grounds by [[Milton Rokeach]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Rokeach, Milton; Hanley, Charles |title=Eysenck's Tender-Mindedness Dimension: A critique |journal=Psychological Bulletin |volume=53 |issue=2 |pages=169–176 |date=March 1956 |doi=10.1037/h0045968 |url=http://psycnet.apa.org/journals/bul/53/2/169/ |pmid=13297921}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Eysencks method of analysis involves the finding of an abstract dimension (a 'factor') that explains the spread of a given set of data (in this case, scores on a political survey). This abstract dimension may or may not correspond to a real material phenomena, and obvious problems arise when it is applied to human psychology. The second factor in such an analysis (such as Eysenck's T-factor) is the second best explanation for the spread of the data, which is, by definition, drawn at right angles to the first factor. While the first factor, which describes the bulk of the variation in a set of data, is more likely to represent something objectively real, subsequent factors become more and more abstract. Thus, one would expect to find a factor that roughly corresponds to &quot;left&quot; and &quot;right&quot;, as this is the dominant framing for politics in our society, but the basis of Eysenck's &quot;tough/tender-minded&quot; thesis (the second, &quot;T&quot;-factor) may well represent nothing beyond an abstract mathematical construct. Such a construct would be expected to appear in factor analysis whether or not it corresponded to something real, thus rendering Eysenck's thesis [[Falsifiability|unfalsifiable]] through factor analysis.

===Rokeach's research===
Dissatisfied with Hans J. Eysenck's work, [[Milton Rokeach]] developed his own two-axis model of political values in 1973, basing this on the ideas of ''[[Freedom (political)|freedom]]'' and ''[[social equality|equality]]'', which he described in his book, ''The Nature of Human Values.''&lt;ref name=&quot;Rokeach&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first=Milton |last=Rokeach |title=The nature of human values |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=TfRGAAAAMAAJ |year=1973 |publisher=Free Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Milton Rokeach claimed that the defining difference between the [[Left-wing politics|left]] and [[right]] was that the left stressed the importance of equality more than the right. Despite his criticisms of Eysenck's tough-tender axis, Rokeach also postulated a basic similarity between [[communism]] and [[nazism]], claiming that these groups would not value freedom as greatly as more conventional [[social democrats]], [[democratic socialists]] and [[capitalists]] would, and he wrote that &quot;the two value model presented here most resembles Eysenck's hypothesis.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Rokeach&quot; /&gt;

To test this model, Milton Rokeach and his colleagues used [[content analysis]] on works exemplifying [[nazism]] (written by [[Adolf Hitler]]), [[communism]] (written by [[V.I. Lenin]]), [[capitalism]] (by [[Barry Goldwater]]) and [[socialism]] (written by various [[socialist]] authors). This method has been criticized for its reliance on the experimenter's familiarity with the content under analysis, and its dependence on the researcher's particular political outlooks.

Multiple raters made frequency counts of sentences containing [[synonyms]] for a number of values identified by Rokeach, including freedom and equality, and Rokeach analyzed these results by comparing the relative frequency rankings of all the values for each of the four texts:

''In excerpts from...''
*'''Socialists''' (socialism) — Freedom ranked 1st, Equality ranked 2nd
*'''Hitler''' (nazism) - Freedom ranked 16th, Equality ranked 17th
*'''Goldwater''' (capitalism) — Freedom ranked 1st, Equality ranked 16th
*'''Lenin''' (communism) — Freedom ranked 17th, Equality ranked 1st

Later studies using samples of [[United States|American]] [[ideologue]]s&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Rous, G.L.; Lee, D.E. |title=Freedom and Equality: Two values of political orientation |journal=Journal of Communication |volume=28 |pages=45–51 |date=Winter 1978 |doi=10.1111/j.1460-2466.1978.tb01561.x |url=http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1460-2466.1978.tb01561.x/abstract}}&lt;/ref&gt; and American [[US president|presidential]] [[United States presidential inauguration|inaugural address]]es&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Mahoney, J.; Coogle, C.L.; Banks, P.D. |title=Values in presidential inaugural addresses: A test of Rokeach's two-factor theory of political ideology |journal=Psychological Reports |volume=55 |pages=683–6 |year=1984 |url=http://ammonsscientific.com/link.php?N=7553 |doi=10.2466/pr0.1984.55.3.683 |issue=3}}&lt;/ref&gt; attempted to apply this model.

===Later research===
In further research,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Eysenck, Hans |title=The structure of social attitudes |journal=Psychological Reports |volume=39 |pages=463–6 |year=1976 |url=http://ammonsscientific.com/link.php?N=20755 |doi=10.2466/pr0.1976.39.2.463 |issue=2}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hans J. Eysenck refined his [[methodology]] to include more questions on [[economics|economic issues]]. Doing this, he revealed a split in the left–right axis between [[social policy]] and [[economic policy]], with a previously undiscovered dimension of ''socialism-capitalism'' (S-factor).

While factorially distinct from Eysenck's previous R factor, the S-factor did positively [[correlate]] with the R-factor, indicating that a basic left–right or right–left tendency underlies both [[social value]]s and [[value system|economic values]], although S tapped more into items discussing [[economic inequality]] and [[big business]], while R relates more to the treatment of [[criminal]]s, and to [[Human sexuality|sexual]] issues and [[military]] issues.

Most research and [[political theory]] since this time has [[replication (scientific method)|replicated]] the factors shown above, either with two axes or three.{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}}

A recent analysis of [[Statistical survey|survey]] [[data]] using [[principal component analysis]] was carried out in 2003 in the [[United Kingdom|UK]]; the results of this study yielded the same two dimensions as found by Eysenck's original research: the familiar &quot;left-right&quot; R-dimension that mixes [[economic]] issues and [[social issues]], and a second T-dimension that is described as &quot;[[pragmatism]] vs [[idealism]].&quot; See&lt;ref name=&quot;politics.beasts.org&quot;&gt;[http://politics.beasts.org Beasts.org]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Beasts.org&quot;&gt;[http://politics.beasts.org/scripts/survey Beasts.org]&lt;/ref&gt; for more information.

Another [[Replication (scientific method)|replication]] came from [[Ronald Inglehart]]'s research into national [[opinions]] based on the [[World Values Survey]], although Inglehart's research described the values of ''[[Country|countries]]'' rather than [[individuals]] or [[Group (sociology)|groups]] of individuals within [[nations]]. Inglehart's two-factor solution took the form of Ferguson's original [[Religionism]] and [[Humanitarianism]] dimensions; Inglehart labelled them &quot;secularism–traditionalism&quot;, which covered issues of tradition and religion, like [[patriotism]], [[abortion]], [[euthanasia]] and the importance of [[Obedience (human behavior)|obeying]] the [[law]] and [[authority figure]]s, and &quot;survivalism – self expression&quot;, which measured issues like everyday conduct and dress, acceptance of [[Diversity (politics)|diversity]] (including [[Alien (law)|foreigners]]) and [[innovation]], and [[Attitude (psychology)|attitudes]] towards people with specific controversial [[Lifestyle (sociology)|lifestyles]] such as [[homosexuality]] and [[vegetarianism]], as well as willingness to partake in political [[activism]]. See&lt;ref name=&quot;worldvaluessurvey.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web |author=Inglehart, Ronald; Welzel, Chris |title=The WVS Cultural Map of the World |publisher=World Values Survey |url=http://www.worldvaluessurvey.org/wvs/articles/folder_published/article_base_54}}&lt;/ref&gt; for Inglehart's national chart.

==Other proposed dimensions==
{{Annotated image | float=right | caption=Analysis of political positions by [[Duquesne University]] economics professor Antony Davies&lt;ref name=&quot;Analysis of political positions by Davies&quot;&gt;{{Cite paper| last = Davies| first = Antony| title = Who favors more freedom, liberals or conservatives? | LearnLiberty| location = Fairfax, VA, US| accessdate =23 June 2012| date = 15 July 2011| url = http://www.learnliberty.org/content/who-favors-more-freedom-liberals-or-conservatives}}&lt;/ref&gt;| image=2d political spectrum.svg | annotations =  {{Annotation|25|25|'''[[Economic freedom]]'''}}{{Annotation|95|120|[[Conservatism]]}}{{Annotation|205|90|[[Libertarianism]]}}{{Annotation|105|200|[[Progressivism_in_the_United_States|Progressivism]]}}{{Annotation|55|230|[[Authoritarianism]]}}{{Annotation|165|150|[[Modern liberalism in the United States|Modern Liberalism]]}}{{Annotation|170|270|'''[[Civil liberties|Personal freedom]]'''}}}}
Numerous alternatives exist, usually developed by those that feel their views are not fairly represented on the traditional right-left [[spectrum]].

One alternative spectrum offered by the [[Conservatism|conservative]] ''[[American Federalist Journal]]''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.federalistjournal.com/spectrum.php Federalistjournal.com]&lt;/ref&gt; accounts for only the &quot;Degree of [[political authority|Government Control]]&quot; without consideration for any other social or political variable, and thus places &quot;[[Fascism]]&quot; ([[totalitarianism]]) at one extreme and &quot;[[anarchism|Anarchy]]&quot; (no government at all) at the other extreme.

In 1998, political author [[Virginia Postrel]], in her book ''[[The Future and Its Enemies]]'', offered another single-axis spectrum that measures views of the future, contrasting ''stasists'', who allegedly fear the future and wish to control it, and ''dynamists'', who want the future to unfold naturally and without attempts to plan and control.  The distinction corresponds to the [[utopian]] versus [[dystopian]] spectrum used in some theoretical assessments of [[liberalism]], and the book's title is borrowed from the work of the anti-[[utopian]] [[classical liberalism|classic-liberal]] theorist [[Karl Popper]].

Other proposed axes include:
*'''Focus of political concern''': ''[[Communitarianism]]'' vs. ''[[Individualism]]''. These labels are preferred{{Who|date=January 2011}} to the loaded language of &quot;[[totalitarianism]]&quot; (anti-freedom) vs. &quot;[[libertarianism]]&quot; (pro-freedom), because one can have a political focus on the community without being totalitarian and undemocratic. [[Council communism]] is a [[political philosophy]] that would be counted as [[communitarian]] on this axis, but is not totalitarian or undemocratic.
*'''Responses to conflict''': according to the political philosopher [[Charles Blattberg]], those who would respond to conflict with conversation should be considered as on the left, with negotiation as in the centre, and with force as on the right. See his essay &quot;Political Philosophies and Political Ideologies.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Blattberg |first=Charles |authorlink=Charles Blattberg |chapter=Political Philosophies and Political Ideologies |chapterurl=http://ssrn.com/abstract=1755117 |title=Patriotic Elaborations: Essays in Practical Philosophy |publisher=McGill-Queen's University Press |year=2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''Role of the church''': ''[[Clericalism]]'' vs. ''[[Anti-clericalism]]''. This axis is less significant in the [[United States]] (where views of the role of [[religion]] tend to be subsumed into the general left-right axis) than in [[Europe]] (where clericalism versus anti-clericalism is much less correlated with the left-right spectrum).
*'''Urban vs. rural''': This axis may be the most useful and significant today in the politics of [[Politics of Europe|Europe]], [[Politics of Australia|Australia]], and [[Politics of Canada|Canada]]. The [[Urban area|urban]] vs. [[rural]] axis was equally prominent in the [[United States]]' political past, but its importance is debatable at present. In the late 18th century and early 19th century in the United States, it would have been described as the conflict between [[Alexander Hamilton|Hamiltonian]] [[Federalist Party (United States)|Federalists]] and [[Jeffersonian democracy|Jeffersonian Democrats]].
*'''Foreign policy''': ''[[interventionism (politics)|interventionism]]'' (the nation should exert power abroad to implement its policy) vs. ''[[non-interventionism]]'' (the nation should keep to its own affairs); similarly, ''[[multilateralism]]'' (coordination of policies with other countries) vs. ''[[isolationism]]'' and ''[[unilateralism]]''
:* Relations with individual states or groups of states may also be vital to [[party politics]]. During the [[Cold War]], parties often had to choose a position on a scale between [[pro-American]] and pro-[[Soviet Union]], although this could at times closely match a left-right spectrum. At other times in history relations with other powerful states has been important. In early [[Canadian history]] relations with [[Great Britain]] were a central theme, although this was not &quot;[[foreign policy]]&quot; but a debate over the proper place of [[Canada]] within the [[British Empire]].
*'''International action''': ''[[Multilateralism]]'' (states should cooperate and compromise) versus ''[[Unilateralism]]'' (states have a strong, even unconditional, right to make their own decisions).
*'''Political violence''': ''[[pacifism]]'' (political views should not be imposed by violent force) vs. ''militancy'' (violence is a legitimate or necessary means of political expression). In [[North America]], particularly in the [[United States]], holders of these views are often referred to as &quot;[[doves]]&quot; and &quot;[[War hawk|hawks]]&quot;, respectively.
*'''Foreign trade''': ''[[globalization]]'' (world economic markets should become integrated and interdependent) vs. ''[[autarky]]'' (the nation or polity should strive for economic independence). During the early history of the [[Commonwealth of Australia]], this was the major political continuum. At that time it was called ''[[Free trade]]'' vs. ''[[Protectionism]]''.
*'''Trade freedom vs. trade equity:''' ''[[Free trade]]'' (businesses should be able trade across borders without regulations) vs. ''[[Fair trade]]'' (international trade should be regulated on behalf of social justice).
*'''Diversity''': ''[[multiculturalism]]'' (the nation should represent a diversity of cultural ideas) vs. ''[[Assimilation (sociology)|assimilationism]]'' or ''[[nationalism]]'' (the nation should primarily represent, or forge, a majority culture).
*'''Participation''': ''[[Democracy]]'' (rule of the majority, or [[mob mentality|mob rule]]) vs. ''[[Aristocracy]]'' (rule by the enlightened) vs. ''[[Tyranny]]'' (total degradation of Aristocracy, ancient Greek philosophers such as [[Plato]] and [[Aristotle]] recognized tyranny as a state in which the tyrant is ruled by utter [[Stoic Passions|passion]], and not reason like the [[philosopher]], resulting in the tyrant pursuing his own desires rather than the common good.)
*'''Freedom''': ''[[Positive liberty]]'' (having ''rights'' which impose an obligation on others) vs. ''[[Negative liberty]]'' (having ''rights'' which prohibit interference by others).
*'''Social power''': ''[[Totalitarianism]]'' vs. ''[[Anarchism]]'' (Control vs. No Control) Analyzes the fundamental political interaction between people, and between individuals and their environment. Often posits the existence of a 'moderate' system as existing between the two extremes.
*'''Change''': ''[[Political radicalism|radicals]]'' (who believe in rapid change) and ''[[progressivism|progressives]]'' (who believe in measured, incremental change) vs. ''[[conservatism|conservatives]]'' (who believe in preserving the status quo) vs. ''[[Reactionary|reactionaries]]'' (who believe in changing things to a previous state).
*'''Origin of state authority''': ''[[popular sovereignty]]'' (the state as a creation of the people, with enumerated, delegated powers) vs. various forms of ''[[Autocracy|absolutism]]'' and ''[[organic state]]'' philosophy (the state as an original and essential authority) vs. the view held in ''[[anarcho-primitivism]]'' that &quot;Civilization originates in conquest abroad and repression at home.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Diamond, Stanley, ''In Search Of The Primitive: A Critique Of Civilization'', (New Brunswick: Transaction Books, 1981), p. 1.&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''Levels of sovereignty''': ''[[Unitary state|unionism]]'' vs. ''[[federalism]]'' vs. ''[[separatism]]''; or ''[[centralism]]'' vs. ''[[regionalism (politics)|regionalism]]''. Especially important in societies where strong regional or ethnic identities are political issues.
**'''[[European Integration]]''' ''(in Europe)'': ''[[Euroscepticism]]'' vs. ''[[European federalism]]''. ''[[nation state]]'' vs. ''[[multi-national state]]''

==Other multi-axis models==
===Nolan: economic freedom, personal freedom===
[[Image:Nolan-chart.svg|thumb|200px|right|[[Nolan chart]]]]

{{Main|Nolan chart}}
The [[Nolan chart]] was created by libertarian [[David Nolan (Libertarian Party)|David Nolan]]. This chart shows what he considers as &quot;[[economic freedom]]&quot; (issues like taxation, free trade and free enterprise) on the horizontal axis and what he considers as &quot;personal freedom&quot; (issues like [[drug legalization]], [[abortion]] and the [[Conscription|draft]]) on the vertical axis. This puts [[Left-wing politics|left-winger]]s in the left quadrant, [[libertarianism|libertarian]]s in the top, [[Right-wing politics|right-winger]]s in the right, and what Nolan originally named [[populism|populists]] in the bottom. It is possible to consider the Nolan chart to be an Eysenck model that has been rotated 45 degrees. The popular &quot;diamond&quot; presentation of the Nolan chart makes this particular comparison readily apparent.

The traditional left-right spectrum forms a diagonal across the Nolan chart, with communism and fascism both in the ultra-populist corner, an assignment hotly disputed by more liberal-minded communists who do not advocate state control over matters of personal freedom. There are some discrepancies between various forms of the model. In some,{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}} the bottom section is labeled with neutral, non-pejorative terms (such as '[[communitarian]]') whereas others use emotional, loaded terms such as 'statist', 'authoritarian', or 'totalitarian'.

The Nolan chart has been reoriented and visually represented in many forms since David Nolan first created it, and has been the inspiration for an endless array of political self-quizzes, perhaps the most famous of these being the [[World's Smallest Political Quiz]], which places one on the Diamond Chart with &quot;statist&quot; at the bottom. {{As of|2005}} this quiz is being used in 420 schools.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theadvocates.org/quiz-in-class.html The Quiz in Classrooms&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; It can be found in at least a dozen popular textbooks that feature the Quiz as part of their enhanced digital content.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theadvocates.org/quiz-in-textbooks.html The Quiz in Textbooks&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; In August 2000 Portrait of America did a telephone survey that was done using the same questions and scale.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theadvocates.org/library/poll-results.html Poll Results - Libertarian Litmus Test&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; More recently, The [[Institute for Humane Studies]] has created [http://www.politopia.com Politopia], a similar quiz. Interestingly, the Institute found that most applicants fell into the lower, [[Populism|populist]] section.{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}}

====Three axis variants of Nolan Chart====
There are two three-axis models based on the Nolan Chart. The Friesian Institute has suggested a model that combines the economic liberty and personal liberty axes with [[positive liberty]], creating a cube. The Vosem Chart (from [[Russian language|Russian]] восемь ''vosem'' 'eight') &lt;!--please don't link Vosem Chart; it was deleted as an article (too obscure), but we agreed to leave a mention of it here--&gt; splits the economic axis of the Nolan chart into two axes, corporate economics (z-axis) and individual economics (y-axis), which combine with the civil liberty axis (x-axis) to form a cube.

===Political compass===
{{Main|political compass}}
The [[political compass]] has two axes. One represents economic issues as right-vs-left. The other represents issues of freedom, or social issues, as authoritarian-vs-liberal. One can determine their position on the political compass through an [http://www.politicalcompass.org/test online quiz] by the same name. It is essentially the same as the Eysenck model and Nolan chart, with slightly different wording.

===Greenberg &amp; Jonas: left-right, ideological rigidity===
In a 2003 ''[[Psychological Bulletin]]'' paper,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Greenberg, J. |author2=Jonas, E. |author2-link=Eva Jonas |title=Psychological Motives and Political Orientation—The Left, the Right, and the Rigid: Comment on Jost et al. (2003) |journal=[[Psychological Bulletin]] |volume=129 |issue=3 |pages=376–382 |year=2003 |doi= 10.1037/0033-2909.129.3.376|url=http://psychoanalystsopposewar.org/resources_files/ConsevatismAsMotivatedSocialCognition_Critique.pdf |format=PDF |author1-link=Jeff Greenberg}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jeff Greenberg]] and [[Eva Jonas]] posit a model comprising the standard left-right axis and an axis representing ideological rigidity. For Greenberg and Jonas, ideological rigidity has &quot;much in common with the related concepts of dogmatism and authoritarianism&quot; and is characterized by &quot;believing in strong leaders and submission, preferring one’s own in-group, ethnocentrism and nationalism, aggression against dissidents, and control with the help of police and military.&quot; Greenberg and Jonas posit that high ideological rigidity can be motivated by &quot;particularly strong needs to reduce fear and uncertainty&quot; and is a primary shared characteristic of &quot;people who subscribe to any extreme government or ideology, whether it is right-wing or left-wing.&quot;

===UK inferred model: left-right, political pragmatism===
While multiple axes on the political spectrum had been postulated for a while, statistical analysis of survey data using [[principal component analysis]] to verify the theory and establish their existence, number and meaning was not done until recently. A 2003 study by [[Chris Lightfoot]] in the [[United Kingdom|UK]] consisted of a survey that yielded two significant [[eigenvectors]] (that is, groups of questions that tend to be answered consistently), one less well-constrained than the other. Upon examining the survey questions one could assign a meaning to the axes: one is like the familiar &quot;left-right&quot; axis that mixes economic and social issues, and the other indicates a degree of &quot;political pragmatism&quot;. The outcome of that study is that the UK political spectrum is most sensibly described with two axes.&lt;ref name=&quot;politics.beasts.org&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Beasts.org&quot;/&gt;{{clarify|date=July 2012|reason=This is too vague. What is the nature of this &quot;pragmatism&quot; axis? How is the left-right axis &quot;like&quot; the &quot;familiar&quot; left-right axis but unlike it?}}

===Pournelle: liberty-control, irrationalism-rationalism===

{{Main|Pournelle chart}}
This very distinct two-axis model was created by [[Jerry Pournelle]] in 1963 for his doctoral dissertation in political science. The [[Pournelle chart]] has [[liberty]] on one axis, with those on the left seeking freedom from control or protections for [[Deviance (sociology)|social deviance]] and those on the right emphasizing state authority or protections for [[Norm (sociology)|norm]] enforcement (farthest right being state worship, farthest left being the idea of a state as the &quot;ultimate evil&quot;).  The other axis is [[rationalism]], defined here as the belief in planned social progress, with those higher up believing that there are problems with society that can be rationally solved, and those lower down skeptical of such approaches.

===Inglehart: traditionalist–secular, and self expressionist – survivalist===
[[Image:Inglehart Values Map.svg|thumb|400px|A recreation of the Inglehart–Welzel Cultural Map of the World based on the [[World Values Survey]].]]
In its 4 January 2003 issue, ''[[The Economist]]'' discussed a chart,&lt;ref name=&quot;worldvaluessurvey.org&quot;/&gt; proposed by [[Ronald Inglehart|Dr. Ronald Inglehart]] and supported by the [[World Values Survey]] (associated with the [[University of Michigan]]), to plot cultural ideology onto two dimensions. On the y-axis it covered issues of tradition and religion, like [[patriotism]], [[abortion]], [[euthanasia]] and the importance of [[Obedience (human behavior)|obeying]] the law and authority figures. At the bottom of the chart is the ''traditionalist'' position on issues like these (with loyalty to country and family and respect for life considered important), while at the top is the ''secular'' position. The x-axis deals with self-expression, issues like everyday conduct and dress, acceptance of [[Diversity (politics)|diversity]] (including foreigners) and [[innovation]], and attitudes towards people with specific controversial lifestyles such as [[vegetarianism]], as well as willingness to partake in political [[activism]]. At the right of the chart is the open ''[[Self-expression Values|self-expressionist]]'' position, while at the left is its opposite position, which Dr. Inglehart calls ''survivalist''. This chart not only has the power to map the values of individuals, but also to compare the values of people in different countries. Placed on this chart, [[European Union|EU]] countries in continental Europe come out on the top right, Anglophone countries on the middle right, Latin American countries on the bottom right, African, Middle Eastern and South Asian countries on the bottom left, and ex-Communist countries on the top left.

===Mitchell: Eight Ways to Run the Country===
In his book ''[[Eight Ways to Run the Country: A New and Revealing Look at Left and Right]]'', [[Brian Patrick Mitchell]] identifies four main political traditions in Anglo-American history.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Brian Patrick |last=Mitchell |title=Eight ways to run the country: a new and revealing look at left and right |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Hg0epWuFdRcC |year=2007 |publisher=Greenwood Publishing |isbn=978-0-275-99358-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mitchell analyzed modern American political perspectives according to their regard for ''[[kratos]]'' (defined as the use of force) and ''[[archē]]'' or “archy” (defined as the recognition of rank), grounding this distinction of archy and kratos in the West's historical experience of church and state and crediting the collapse of the Christian consensus on church and state with the appearance of four main divergent traditions in Western political thought:

* [[republicanism|republican]] [[constitutionalism]] = pro archy, anti kratos
* [[Libertarianism|libertarian]] [[individualism]] = anti archy, anti kratos
* [[democratic]] [[progressivism]] = anti archy, pro kratos
* [[plutocratic]] [[nationalism]] = pro archy, pro kratos

Mitchell charts these traditions graphically using a vertical axis as a scale of [[kratos]]/[[akrateia]] and a horizontal axis as a scale of [[archy]]/[[anarchy]]. He places democratic progressivism in the lower left, plutocratic nationalism in the lower right, republican constitutionalism in the upper right, and libertarian individualism in the upper left. The political left is therefore distinguished by its rejection of archy, while the political right is distinguished by its acceptance of archy.

For Mitchell, anarchy is not the absence of government but the rejection of rank. Thus there can be both anti-government [[anarchists]] (Mitchell’s &quot;libertarian individualists&quot;) and pro-government anarchists (Mitchell's &quot;democratic progressives&quot;, who favor the use of government force against social hierarchies such as [[patriarchy]]). Mitchell also distinguishes between [[Left anarchism|left-wing anarchists]] and [[right-wing anarchism|right-wing anarchists]], whom Mitchell renames &quot;akratists&quot; for their opposition to the government’s use of force.

In addition to the four main traditions, Mitchell identifies eight distinct political perspectives represented in contemporary American politics:

* [[communitarian]] = ambivalent toward archy, pro kratos
* [[progressivism|progressive]] = anti archy, pro kratos (democratic progressivism)
* [[Political radicalism|radical]] = anti archy, ambivalent toward kratos
* [[individualist]] = anti archy, anti kratos (libertarian individualism)
* [[paleolibertarian]] = ambivalent toward archy, anti kratos
* [[paleoconservative]] = pro archy, anti kratos (republican constitutionalism)
* [[theoconservative]] = pro archy, ambivalent toward kratos
* [[neoconservative]] = pro archy, pro kratos (plutocratic nationalism)

A potential ninth perspective, in the midst of the eight, is [[populism]], which Mitchell says is vaguely defined and situation-dependent, having no fixed character other than opposition to the prevailing power.

==Political-spectrum-based forecasts==
As shown by Russian political scientist Stepan S. Sulakshin,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Sulakshin, S. |title=A Quantitative Political Spectrum and Forecasting of Social Evolution |journal=International Journal of Interdisciplinary Social Sciences |volume=5 |issue=4 |pages=55–66 |year=2010 |url=http://iji.cgpublisher.com/product/pub.88/prod.1091}}&lt;/ref&gt; political spectra can be used as a forecasting tool.  Sulakshin offered mathematical evidence that stable development (positive dynamics of the vast number of statistic indices) depends on the width of the political spectrum: if it is too narrow or too wide, stagnation or political disasters will result.  Sulakshin also showed that, in the short run, the political spectrum determines the statistic indices dynamic and not vice versa.

== Biological variables ==
A number of recent studies have investigated the relationship between [[biology and political orientation]]

==See also==
{{portal|conservatism}}
*[[Cleavage (politics)]]
*[[Differences between conservative and liberal brain]]
*[[Jennifer Government: NationStates]]
*[[Left-right politics]]
*[[List of politics-related topics]]
*[[Psephology]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.idealog.org Idealog (Education+Quiz)]
*[http://www.politopia.com/ Politopia (Quiz)]
*[http://politicalcompass.org/ The Political Compass]
*[http://rationalrevolution.net/articles/redefining_the_political_spectru.htm Redefining the Political Spectrum — The Rational Spectrum]
{{Political spectrum}}

[[Category:Elections]]
[[Category:Political science terms]]
[[Category:Political spectrum| ]]

[[ar:الطيف السياسي]]
[[ast:Espeutru políticu]]
[[ca:Espectre polític]]
[[de:Politisches Spektrum]]
[[et:Poliitiline spekter]]
[[el:Πολιτικό φάσμα]]
[[es:Espectro político]]
[[eo:Politika spektro]]
[[fr:Échiquier politique]]
[[it:Spettro politico]]
[[ku:Şebenga siyasî]]
[[mk:Политички спектар]]
[[nl:Politiek spectrum]]
[[ja:政治的スペクトル]]
[[pt:Espectro político]]
[[ru:Политический спектр]]
[[sl:Politični spekter]]
[[sr:Политички спектар]]
[[fi:Poliittinen kirjo]]
[[zh:政治光譜]]</text>
      <sha1>917q6e8nuddgq2h7qh3yf0yolmgyx1r</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
