<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Political science</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>24388</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521823617</id>
      <parentid>521241298</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-07T13:44:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Snotbot</username>
        <id>13752234</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Fixing section headings [[Wikipedia:Bots/Requests for approval/Snotbot 5|(task 5)]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="36010">{{Politics}}

{{Merge from|Political criticism|date=August 2012}}

'''Political Science''' is a [[social science]] discipline concerned with the study of the state, government, and politics. Aristotle defined it as the study of the state.&lt;ref&gt;Oxford Dictionary of Politics: political science&lt;/ref&gt; It deals extensively with the theory and practice of [[politics]], and the analysis of [[political system]]s and political behavior. Political scientists &quot;see themselves engaged in revealing the relationships underlying political events and conditions, and from these revelations they attempt to construct general principles about the way the world of politics works.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unc.edu/depts/wcweb/handouts/polisci.html Political Science]. The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill (1999-02-22). Retrieved on 2010-11-13.&lt;/ref&gt; Political science intersects with other fields; including [[economics]], [[law]], [[sociology]], [[history]], [[anthropology]], [[public administration]], [[public policy]], national politics, [[international relations]], [[comparative politics]], [[psychology]], [[political organization]], and [[political theory]]. Although it was codified in the [[19th century]], when all the social sciences were established, political science has ancient roots; indeed, it originated almost 2,500 years ago with the works of [[Plato]] and [[Aristotle]].&lt;ref&gt;Britannica Concise Encyclopedia: political science&lt;/ref&gt;

Political science is commonly divided into three distinct sub-disciplines which together constitute the field:&lt;br&gt;
* [[political philosophy]], 
* [[comparative politics]] and 
* [[international relations]].&lt;br&gt;
Political philosophy is the reasoning for an absolute normative government, laws and similar questions and their distinctive characteristics. Comparative politics is the science of comparison and teaching of different types of [[constitutions]], political actors, legislature and associated fields, all of them from an intrastate perspective. [[International relations]] deals with the interaction between [[nation-state]]s as well as intergovernmental and transnational organizations.

Political science is methodologically diverse and appropriates many methods originating in [[social research]]. Approaches include [[positivism]], [[Verstehen|interpretivism]], [[rational choice theory]], [[behavioralism]], [[structuralism]], [[post-structuralism]], [[Philosophical realism|realism]], [[institutionalism (disambiguation)|institutionalism]], and pluralism. Political science, as one of the [[social science]]s, uses methods and techniques that relate to the kinds of inquiries sought: primary sources such as historical documents and official records, secondary sources such as scholarly journal articles, [[sample survey|survey]] research, [[statistical analysis]], [[case studies]], experimental research and model building.

&quot;As a discipline&quot; political science, possibly like the social sciences as a whole, &quot;lives on the fault line between the 'two cultures' in the academy, the [[sciences]] and the [[humanities]].&quot;&lt;ref name=Stoner&gt;{{cite web|last=Stoner|first=J. R.|url=http://www.allacademic.com/meta/p_mla_apa_research_citation/2/4/5/5/8/p245585_index.html|title=Political Science and Political Education|publisher=Paper presented at the annual meeting of the APSA Teaching and Learning Conference ([[American Political Science Association|APSA]]), San José Marriott, [[San José, California]]|date=22 February 2008|accessdate=4 February 2009|quote=… although one might allege the same for social science as a whole, political scientists receive funding from and play an active role in both the [[National Science Foundation]] and the [[National Endowment for the Humanities]] [in the United States].|accessdate=2011-10-19}} &lt;nowiki&gt; &lt;http://www.allacademic.com/meta/p245585_index.html&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;.&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, in some American colleges where there is no separate [[College of Arts and Sciences|School or College of Arts and Sciences]] per se, political science may be a separate department housed as part of a division or school of Humanities or [[Liberal Arts]].&lt;ref name=Marist&gt;See, e.g., the department of [http://www.marist.edu/liberalarts/polsci/ Political Science] at [[Marist College]], part of a Division of Humanities before that division became the School of Liberal Arts (c. 2000).&lt;/ref&gt; Whereas classical [[political philosophy]] is primarily defined by a concern for [[Greece|Hellenic]] and [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]] thought, political scientists are also marked by a great concern for &quot;[[modernity]]&quot; and the contemporary [[nation state]], along with the study of classical thought, and as such share a greater deal of terminology with [[sociologists]] (e.g. [[structure and agency]]).

== Overview ==
Political scientists study matters concerning the allocation and transfer of power in [[decision making]], the roles and systems of governance including [[governments]] and [[international organizations]], [[political behavior]] and [[public policies]]. They measure the success of [[governance]] and specific policies by examining many factors, including [[Economic stability|stability]], [[justice]], [[material wealth]], and [[peace]]. Some political scientists seek to advance [[positive (social sciences)|positive]] (attempt to describe how things are, as opposed to how they should be) theses by analyzing politics. Others advance [[Norm (sociology)|normative]] theses, by making specific policy recommendations.

Political scientists provide the frameworks from which journalists, special interest groups, politicians, and the [[Constituency|electorate]] analyze issues. According to Chaturvedy, &quot;...Political scientists may serve as advisers to specific politicians, or even run for office as politicians themselves. Political scientists can be found working in governments, in political parties or as civil servants. They may be involved with [[non-governmental organizations]] (NGOs) or political movements. In a variety of capacities, people educated and trained in political science can add value and expertise to [[corporation]]s.{{Citation needed|date=October 2011}} Private enterprises such as [[think tank]]s, research institutes, polling and [[public relations]] firms often employ political scientists.&quot;{{Citation needed|date=October 2011}} In the United States, political scientists known as &quot;[[Americanist]]s{{Disambiguation needed|date=January 2012}}&quot; look at a variety of data including constitutional development, [[elections]], [[public opinion]] and public policy such as [[Social Security reform]],..... [[foreign policy]], [[US Congress]]ional committees, and the [[United States Supreme Court|US Supreme Court]] — to name only a few issues.

Most [[United States]] [[Higher education in the United States|colleges and universities]] offer B.A. programs in political science. M.A. or M.A.T. and Ph.D. or Ed.D. programs are common at larger universities. The term ''political science'' is more popular in [[North America]] than elsewhere; other institutions, especially those outside the United States, see political science as part of a broader discipline of ''political studies,'' ''politics,'' or ''government.'' While ''political science'' implies use of the [[scientific method]], ''political studies'' implies a broader approach, although the naming of degree courses does not necessarily reflect their content.&lt;ref&gt;''Politics'' is the term used to refer to this field by [[Brandeis University]]; [[Cornell College]]; [[University of California, Santa Cruz]]; [[Hendrix College]]; [[Lake Forest College]]; [[Monash University]]; [[Mount Holyoke College]]; [[New York University]]; [[Occidental College]]; [[Princeton University]]; [[Ursinus College]]; and [[Washington and Lee University]]. ''Government'' is the term used for this field by [[Bowdoin College]]; [[Colby College]]; [[Cornell University]]; [[Dartmouth College]]; [[Georgetown University]]; [[Harvard University]]; [[Smith College]]; [[Wesleyan University]]; the [[College of William and Mary]]; the [[University of Sydney]]; the [[University of Texas at Austin]]; the [[University of Ulster]]; the [[University of Essex]]; [[Victoria University of Wellington]], which has both a &quot;School of Government&quot; and a separate &quot;Political Science and International Relations Programme&quot;; and the [[London School of Economics|London School of Economics and Political Science]]. ''Politics and government'' is the term used by the [[University of Puget Sound]]. ''Government and politics'' is used by the [[University of Maryland, College Park]].&lt;/ref&gt; Separate degree granting programs in international relations and [[public policy]] are not uncommon at both the undergraduate and graduate levels. Master's level programs in political science are common when political scientists engage in [[public administration]].&lt;ref&gt;{{ok |last=Vernardakis |first=George |title=Graduate education in government |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Rd3DDiQm3M8C&amp;pg=PA77&amp;dq=political+science+international+relations+degree#v=onepage&amp;q=political%20science%20international%20relations%20degree&amp;f=false |page=77 |year=1998 |publisher=University Press of America |isbn=0-7618-1171-8 {{Please check ISBN|reason=Check digit (8) does not correspond to calculated figure.}} |quote=...existing practices at Harvard University, the University of California at Berkeley, and the University of Michigan.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The national honor society for college and university students of [[government and politics]] in the United States is [[Pi Sigma Alpha]].

== History ==
[[Image:Santi di Tito - Niccolo Machiavelli's portrait headcrop.jpg|thumb|right|[[Niccolò Machiavelli]], one of many influential political theorists]]

Political science as a separate field is a relatively late arrival in terms of [[social sciences]]. However, the term &quot;political science&quot; was not always distinguished from [[political philosophy]], and the modern discipline has a clear set of antecedents including also [[moral philosophy]], [[political economy]], [[political theology]], [[history]], and other fields concerned with [[Norm (sociology)|normative]] determinations of what ought to be and with [[Deductive reasoning|deducing]] the characteristics and functions of the ideal [[State (polity)|state]].

The antecedents of Western politics can be traced back to the [[Socrates|Socratic]] political philosophers, [[Plato]] (427–347 BC), [[Xenophon]] (c. 430–354 BC), and [[Aristotle]] (&quot;The Father of Political Science&quot;) (384–322 BC). These authors, in such works as ''[[The Republic (Plato)|The Republic]]'' and ''[[Laws (Plato)|Laws]]'' by Plato, and ''[[Politics (Aristotle)|The Politics]]'' and ''[[Nicomachean Ethics]]'' by Aristotle, analyzed political systems philosophically, going beyond earlier Greek poetic and historical reflections which can be found in the works of epic poets like [[Homer]] and [[Hesiod]], historians like [[Herodotus]] and [[Thucydides]], and dramatists such as [[Sophocles]], [[Aristophanes]], and [[Euripides]].

== The rise and fall of the Roman Empire ==

During the height of the [[Roman Empire]], famous historians such as [[Polybius]], [[Livy]] and [[Plutarch]] documented the rise of the [[Roman Republic]], and the organization and histories of other nations, while statesmen like [[Julius Caesar]], [[Cicero]] and others provided us with examples of the politics of the republic and Rome's empire and wars. The study of politics during this age was oriented toward understanding history, understanding methods of governing, and describing the operation of governments. Nearly a thousand years elapsed, from the foundation of the city of Rome in 753 BC to the [[fall of the Roman Empire]] or the beginning of the [[Middle Ages]]. In the interim, there is a manifest translation of [[Ancient Greece#Hellenistic Greece|Hellenic culture]] into the Roman sphere. The Greek gods become Romans and Greek philosophy in one way or another turns into Roman law e.g. [[Stoicism]]. The Stoic was committed to preserving proper hierarchical roles and duties in the state so that the state as a whole would remain stable. Among the best known Roman Stoics were philosopher [[Seneca the Younger|Seneca]] and the emperor [[Marcus Aurelius]]. Seneca, a wealthy Roman patrician, is often criticized by some modern commentators for failing to adequately live by his own precepts. [[The Meditations of Marcus Aurelius]], on the other hand, can be best thought of as the philosophical reflections of an emperor divided between his philosophical aspirations and the duty he felt to defend the Roman Empire from its external enemies through his various military campaigns. According to Polybius, Roman institutions were the backbone of the empire but [[Roman law]] is the [[wikt:medulla|medulla]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Aabriel Abraham |title=Ventures in political science |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=VMwpeKhifwcC&amp;pg=PA29&amp;dq=political+science+Roman+Stoics#v=onepage&amp;q=political%20science%20Roman%20Stoics&amp;f=false |page=29 |year=2002 |publisher=Lynne Rienner Publishers |isbn=1-58826-080-2 {{Please check ISBN|reason=Check digit (2) does not correspond to calculated figure.}} |quote=Polybius attributes the remarkable growth and power of Rome to its political institutions.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Middle Ages===


With the [[Decline of the Roman Empire|fall of the Western Roman Empire]], there arose a more diffuse arena for political studies. The rise of monotheism and, particularly for the Western tradition, [[Christianity]], brought to light a new space for politics and political action. Works such as [[Augustine of Hippo]]'s ''[[City of God (book)|The City of God]]'' synthesized current philosophies and political traditions with those of Christianity, redefining the borders between what was religious and what was political. During the [[Middle Ages]], the study of politics was widespread in the churches and courts. Most of the political questions surrounding the relationship between [[Separation of church and state|church and state]] were clarified and contested in this period. The Arabs lost sight of Aristotle's political science but continued to study Plato's ''[[Republic]]'' which became the basic text of Judeo-Islamic [[political philosophy]] as in the works of [[Alfarabi]] and [[Averroes]]; this did not happen in the Christian world, where Aristotle's ''[[Politics]]'' was translated in the 13th century and became the basic text as in the works of [[Saint Thomas Aquinas]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Muhsin |first=Mahdi |title=Alfarabi and the foundation of Islamic political philosophy |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=y6BF52Uw9BIC&amp;pg=PA35&amp;dq=Political+science+Plato%27s+republic#v=onepage&amp;q=Political%20science%20Plato's%20republic&amp;f=false |page=35 |year=2001 |isbn=0-226-50186-4 {{Please check ISBN|reason=Check digit (4) does not correspond to calculated figure.}} |quote=...a combination of Plato and Plotinum, could do much more to clarify political life as it then existed... }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Indian subcontinent===

In [[History of India|ancient India]], the antecedents of politics can be traced back to the ''[[Rig-Veda]]'', ''[[Vedas|Samhitas]]'', ''[[Brahmana]]s'', the [[Mahabharata]] and [[Buddhism|Buddhist]] ''[[Pali Canon]]''. [[Chanakya]] (c. 350–275 BC) was a political thinker in [[Takshashila]]. Chanakya wrote the ''[[Arthashastra]]'', a treatise on political thought, [[economics]] and social order. It discusses monetary and fiscal policies, welfare, international relations, and war strategies in detail, among other topics. The [[Manusmriti]], dated to about two centuries after the time of Chanakya is another important Indian political treatise.

===East Asia===

Ancient China was home to several competing schools of political thought, most of which arose in the [[Spring and Autumn Period]]. These included [[Mohism]] (a utilitarian philosophy), [[Taoism]], [[Legalism (Chinese philosophy)|Legalism]] (a school of thought based on the supremacy of the state), and [[Confucianism]]. Eventually, a modified form of Confucianism (heavily infused with elements of Legalism) became the dominant political philosophy in China during the Imperial Period. This form of Confucianism also deeply influenced and were expounded upon by scholars in [[Korea]] and [[Japan]].

===West Asia===

In Persia, works such as the [[Rubaiyat of Omar Khayyam]] and Epic of Kings by [[Ferdowsi]] provided evidence of political analysis, while the [[Middle Eastern]] [[Aristotelianism|Aristotelians]] such as [[Avicenna]] and later [[Maimonides]] and [[Averroes]], continued [[Aristotle]]'s tradition of analysis and [[empiricism]], writing commentaries on Aristotle's works. Averroe did not have at hand a text of Aristotle's ''Politics'', so he wrote a commentary on Plato's ''Republic'' instead.

== Renaissance ==

During the [[Italian Renaissance]], [[Niccolò Machiavelli]] established the emphasis of modern political science on direct [[empirical]] observation of political institutions and actors. Machiavelli was also a [[Realpolitik|realist]], arguing that even evil means should be considered if they help to create and preserve a glorious regime. Machiavelli therefore also argues against the use of idealistic models in politics, and has been described as the father of the &quot;politics model&quot; of political science.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Lane |first=Ruth |title=Political science in theory and practice: the 'politics' model |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=4nB0LuuYYCkC&amp;pg=PA89&amp;dq=Political+science+Plato+the+republic#v=onepage&amp;q=Political%20science%20Plato%20the%20republic&amp;f=false |page=89 |year=1996 |publisher=M. E. Sharpe |isbn=1-56324-940-2 {{Please check ISBN|reason=Check digit (2) does not correspond to calculated figure.}} |quote=Discussion then moves to Machiavelli, for whom the politics model was not an occasional pastime...}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later, the expansion of the scientific paradigm during the [[the Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]] further pushed the study of politics beyond normative determinations.

===Enlightenment===

The works of the French philosophers Voltaire, Rousseau, Diderot to name a few are paragon for political analysis, social science, social and political critic. Their influence leading to the French revolution has been enormous in the development of modern democracy throughout the world.

Like Machiavelli, [[Thomas Hobbes]], well known for his theory of the [[social contract]], believed that a strong central power, such as a monarchy, was necessary to rule the innate selfishness of the individual but neither of them believed in the [[divine right of kings]]. [[John Locke]], on the other hand, who gave us [[Two Treatises of Government]] and who did not believe in the divine right of kings either, sided with Aquinas and stood against both Machiavelli and Hobbes by accepting Aristotle's dictum that man seeks to be happy in a state of social harmony as a social animal. Unlike Aquinas' preponderant view on the salvation of the soul from original sin, Locke believed man comes into this world with a mind that is basically a [[tabula rasa]]. According to Locke, an absolute ruler as proposed by Hobbes is unnecessary, for [[natural law]] is based on reason and equality, seeking peace and survival for man.

Religion would no longer play a dominant role in politics. There would be separation of church and state. Principles similar to those that dominated the material sciences could be applied to society as a whole, originating the [[social sciences]]. Politics could be studied in a laboratory as it were, the social [[social environment|milieu]]. In 1787, [[Alexander Hamilton]] wrote: &quot;...The science of politics like most other sciences has received great improvement.&quot; (''[[The Federalist Papers]]'' Number 9 and 51). Both the marquis d'Argenson and the abbé de Saint-Pierre described politics as a science; d'Argenson was a philosopher and de Saint-Pierre an allied reformer of [[the enlightenment]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Gay |first=Peter |title=The enlightenment |page=448 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=gQPna6P69i0C&amp;pg=RA2-PA448&amp;dq=political+science+the+enlightenment#v=onepage&amp;q=political%20science%20the%20enlightenment&amp;f=false |volume=2 |year=1996 |publisher=W. W. Norton &amp; Co. |isbn=0-393-31366-6 {{Please check ISBN|reason=Check digit (6) does not correspond to calculated figure.}} |quote=The men of the Enlightenment sensed that they could realize their social ideals only by political means.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other important figures in American politics who participated in the Enlightenment were [[Benjamin Franklin]] and [[Thomas Jefferson]].

== Modern political science ==
Because political science is essentially a study of [[human behavior]], in all aspects of [[politics]], observations in controlled environments are often challenging to reproduce or duplicate, though [[experiment]]al methods are increasingly common (see [[experimental political science]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|editor1-last=Druckman|editor1-first=James|editor2-first=Donald|editor2-last=Green|editor3-first=James|editor3-last=Kuklinski|editor4-first=Arthur|editor4-last=Lupia|year=2011|title=Cambridge Handbook of Experimental Political Science|location=New York|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-0-521-17455-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; Citing this difficulty, former [[American Political Science Association]] President [[Lawrence Lowell]] once said &quot;We are limited by the impossibility of experiment. Politics is an observational, not an experimental science.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Lowell, A. Lawrence. 1910. &quot;The Physiology of Politics.&quot; ''American Political Science Review'' 4: 1-15.&lt;/ref&gt; Because of this, political scientists have historically observed political elites, institutions, and individual or group behavior in order to identify patterns, draw generalizations, and build theories of politics.

Like all social sciences, political science faces the difficulty of observing human actors that can only be partially observed and who have the capacity for making conscious choices unlike other subjects such as non-human organisms in [[biology]] or inanimate objects as in [[physics]]. Despite the complexities, contemporary political science has progressed by adopting a variety of methods and theoretical approaches to understanding politics and methodological pluralism is a defining feature of contemporary political science. Often in contrast with national media, political science scholars seek to compile long-term data and research on the impact of political issues, producing [http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/subject/code/000101/homepage/press_pass__2012_us_presidential_election_-_free_content.htm in-depth articles] breaking down the issues


The advent of political science as a university discipline was marked by the creation of university departments and chairs with the title of political science arising in the late 19th century. In fact, the designation &quot;political scientist&quot; is typically for those with a doctorate in the field. Integrating political studies of the past into a unified discipline is ongoing, and the history of political science has provided a rich field for the growth of both [[Norm (sociology)|normative]] and [[positive (social sciences)|positive]] political science, with each part of the discipline sharing some historical predecessors. The American Political Science Association was founded in 1903 and the [[American Political Science Review]] was founded in 1906 in an effort to distinguish the study of politics from economics and other social phenomena.

===Behavioral revolution and new institutionalism===

In the 1950s and the 1960s, a behavioral revolution stressing the systematic and rigorously scientific study of individual and group behavior swept the discipline. A focus on studying political behavior, rather than institutions or interpretation of legal texts, characterized early behavioral political science, including work by [[Robert Dahl]], [[Philip Converse]], and in the collaboration between sociologist [[Paul Lazarsfeld]] and public opinion scholar [[Bernard Berelson]].

The late 1960s and early 1970s witnessed a take off in the use of deductive, [[game theory|game theoretic]] formal modeling techniques aimed at generating a more analytical corpus of knowledge in the discipline. This period saw a surge of research that borrowed theory and methods from economics to study political institutions, such as the United States Congress, as well as political behavior, such as voting. [[William H. Riker]] and his colleagues and students at the [[University of Rochester]] were the main proponents of this shift.

===Recent developments===

In 2000, the [[Perestroika Movement]] in political science was introduced as a reaction against what supporters of the movement called the mathematicization of political science. Those who identified with the movement argued for a plurality of methodologies and approaches in political science and for more relevance of the discipline to those outside of it.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.btinternet.com/~pae_news/Perestroika/Miller.htm Chronicle of Higher Education 2001]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Evolutionary psychology]] theories argue that humans have evolved a highly developed set of psychological mechanisms for dealing with politics. However, these mechanisms evolved for dealing with the small group politics that characterized the ancestral environment and not the much larger political structures in today's world. This is argued to explain many important features and systematic [[cognitive bias]]es of current politics.&lt;ref name=AEP&gt;Michael Bang Petersen. &quot;The evolutionary psychology of mass politics&quot;. In {{cite doi|10.1093/acprof:oso/9780199586073.001.0001}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Around the world==

===Russia===
‘de facto political science’ existed in the '''[[Soviet Union]]''' as early as in 1960s before it became ‘de jure political science’ in 1989. In the USSR, political studies were carried out under the guise of some other disciplines like theory of state and [[law]], [[area studies]], [[international relations]], studies of labor movement, &quot;critique of bourgeois theories&quot; etc. Soviet scholars were represented at the [[International Political Science Association]] since 1955 (since 1960 by the Soviet Association of Political and State Studies). In 1979 11th World Congress of IPSA took place in [[Moscow]].

Until the late years of the Soviet Union, political science as a field was subjected to tight control of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union. The development of political science was marked by two major tendencies in the scientific community and in society in general. One was a general distrust of political scientists and institutions that were engaged in political science. Anti-communists accused political scientists of being &quot;false&quot; scientists and of having served the old regime. This atmosphere of animosity created heavy moral and professional strains on those who had worked for the introduction of political science under the old regime. They had to face a certain ignorance and ideological animosity from those pretending to be the &quot;true&quot; bearers of democratic ideals.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;Political Science in Russia: Institutionalization of the Discipline and Development of the Professional Community&lt;/ref&gt;

Two of the major institutions dealing with political science - the Institute of Contemporary Social Theories and the Institute of International Affairs - were disbanded, and most of their members were actually left without jobs and had to look for new professional careers. These institutes were victims of the first wave of [[Anti communism|anti-communist]] euphoria and of in many ways unfounded ideological attacks. Many of the people working in these institutes were competent scientists with a proficient knowledge of political science, and some of them, through their works, had played an important role in reforming the Communist Party and had helped to bring about the radical changes in 1989.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

Today the [[Russian Political Science Association]] unites professionals-political scientists from in Russia.

====Difficulties====
The main difficulties that haunted its development during the first two decades are still there: deficiency of means for research and development of university centers, need for funds for empirical research,a shortage of academic literature, disproportion in allocation of resources between center and periphery, deteriorating status of political science in university curriculums (at non-political-scientist departments) etc. At the beginning of 1990s, one of the major problems was absence of professionals with special education. Later in 2000s (decade) with the first graduations at political-science departments, the keenest problem turned out to be low inclusive capacities of the academic labor market. There are a lot of problems with connections between political science and political practice.

==Subfields==
Most political scientists work broadly in one or more of the following five areas:
* [[Comparative politics]], including [[area studies]]
* [[International relations]]
* [[Political philosophy]]
* [[Public administration]]
* [[Public law]]

Some political science departments also classify [[methodology]] as well as scholarship on the domestic politics of a particular country as distinct sub fields.

In contrast to this traditional classification, some academic departments organize scholarship into thematic categories, including political philosophy, [[Theories of political behavior|political behavior]] (including [[public opinion]], [[collective action]], and [[Identity (social science)|identity]]), and political institutions (including [[legislature]]s and [[international organization]]s). Political science conferences and journals often emphasize scholarship in more specific categories. The American Political Science Association, for example, has 42 organized sections that address various methods and topics of political inquiry.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.apsanet.org/content_4596.cfm APSA Organized Sections | APSA&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==

* [[Outline of political science]] - structured list of political topics, arranged by subject area
* [[Index of politics articles]] - alphabetical list of political subjects
* [[Political lists]] - lists of political topics
* [[Outline of law]]
* [[Index of law articles]]
* [[Process tracing]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== Further reading ==
*''[http://www.apsanet.org/section_714.cfm The Evolution of Political Science]'' (November 2006). APSR Centennial Volume of ''[[American Political Science Review]]''. ''Apsanet.org''. 4 February 2009.
*Goodin, R. E.; Klingemann, Hans-Dieter (1996). ''A New Handbook of Political Science''. Oxford and New York: [[Oxford University Press]]. ISBN 0-19-829471-9.
*Klingemann, Hans-Dieter, ed. (2007) ''The State of Political Science in Western Europe''. Opladen: Barbara Budrich Publishers. ISBN 978-3-86649-045-3 {{Please check ISBN|reason=Check digit (3) does not correspond to calculated figure.}}.
*Schramm, S. F.; Caterino, B., eds. (2006). ''Making Political Science Matter: Debating Knowledge, Research, and Method''. New York and London: [[New York University Press]]. [http://books.google.com/books?id=kyJ5GJ7DeMQC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=making+political+science+matter&amp;sig=s_bqA18zhy02NKJwsJHJj3vHzKc Making Political Science Matter]''. [[Google Books]]''. 4 February 2009.
*Roskin, M.; Cord, R. L.; Medeiros, J. A.; Jones, W. S. (2007). ''Political Science: An Introduction''. 10th ed. New York: [[Pearson Prentice Hall]]. ISBN 978-0-13-242575-9 (10). ISBN 978-0-13-242575-9 (13).
*Tausch, A.; Prager, F. (1993). ''Towards a Socio-Liberal Theory of World Development''. Basingstoke: Macmillan; New York: [[St. Martin's Press]].
*''[[Oxford Handbooks of Political Science]]''
*Noel, Hans (2010) [http://www.degruyter.com/view/j/for.2010.8.3_20120105083456/for.2010.8.3/for.2010.8.3.1393/for.2010.8.3.1393.xml?rskey=2OWKEq&amp;result=9&amp;q=noel &quot;Ten Things Political Scientists Know that You Don’t&quot;] ''The Forum'': Vol. 8: Iss. 3, Article 12.

== External links ==
{{Wikibooks|Political Science}}
{{Commons category|Political science}}
* [http://www.ipsa.org/ International Political Science Association]
* [http://www.isanet.org/ International Studies Association]
* [http://ipsaportal.unina.it/ IPSAPortal : Top 300 websites for Political Science]
* [http://www.iapss.org/ International Association for Political Science Students]
* [http://www.apsanet.org/ American Political Science Association]
* [http://www.mpsanet.org/ Midwest Political Science Association]
* [http://www.essex.ac.uk/ecpr/ European Consortium for Political Research]
* [[Graduate Institute of International and Development Studies]]. &quot;[http://www.graduateinstitute.ch/political-science Political Science Department which offers MA and PhD programmes]&quot;
* [http://www.psa.ac.uk/ Political Studies Association of the UK]
* [http://www.politicalscience.org/ PROL: Political Science Research Online (prepublished research)]
* [http://politicalscience.truman.edu/researchdesignhandbook.pdf Truman State University Political Science Research Design Handbook]
* [http://dca.tufts.edu/features/aas A New Nation Votes: American Elections Returns 1787–1825]
* [http://www.politicacomparada.com.ar/ Comparative Politics in Argentina &amp; Latin America]: Site dedicated to the development of comparative politics in Latin America. Paper Works, Articles and links to specialized web sites.

{{Social sciences-footer}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Political Science}}
[[Category:Political science|*]]
[[Category:Politology]]

[[am:የፖለቲካ ጥናት]]
[[ar:علوم سياسية]]
[[ast:Ciencies Polítiques]]
[[az:Siyasi elm]]
[[bn:রাষ্ট্রবিজ্ঞান]]
[[be:Паліталогія]]
[[be-x-old:Паліталёгія]]
[[bg:Политология]]
[[bs:Političke nauke]]
[[ca:Ciències polítiques]]
[[ceb:Siyensiya sa politika]]
[[cs:Politologie]]
[[cy:Gwyddor gwleidyddiaeth]]
[[da:Statskundskab]]
[[de:Politikwissenschaft]]
[[et:Politoloogia]]
[[el:Πολιτική επιστήμη]]
[[es:Ciencia política]]
[[eo:Politika scienco]]
[[eu:Politika zientzia]]
[[fa:علم سیاست]]
[[fo:Stjórnmálafrøði]]
[[fr:Science politique]]
[[fy:Politikology]]
[[fur:Siencis politichis]]
[[ga:Eolaíocht pholaitiúil]]
[[gv:Oaylleeaght pholitickagh]]
[[gl:Ciencia política]]
[[ko:정치학]]
[[hy:Քաղաքագիտություն]]
[[hi:राजनीति विज्ञान]]
[[hr:Političke znanosti]]
[[id:Ilmu politik]]
[[is:Stjórnmálafræði]]
[[it:Scienza politica]]
[[he:מדע המדינה]]
[[jv:Èlmu pulitik]]
[[ka:პოლიტოლოგია]]
[[csb:Pòlitologijô]]
[[kk:Саясаттану]]
[[ky:Саясий илимдер]]
[[lv:Politoloģija]]
[[lt:Politologija]]
[[lij:Sciensa politica]]
[[li:Politicologie]]
[[hu:Politikatudomány]]
[[mk:Политичка наука]]
[[arz:علوم سياسيه]]
[[ms:Sains politik]]
[[mwl:Ciéncia política]]
[[nl:Politicologie]]
[[ne:राजनीति विज्ञान]]
[[ja:政治学]]
[[no:Statsvitenskap]]
[[nn:Statsvitskap]]
[[nov:Politikal sientie]]
[[pl:Politologia]]
[[pt:Ciência política]]
[[ro:Politologie]]
[[ru:Политология]]
[[sc:Iscièntzia Polìtica]]
[[sq:Shkencat Politike]]
[[si:දේශපාලන විද්‍යාව]]
[[simple:Political science]]
[[sk:Politológia]]
[[sl:Politične znanosti]]
[[sr:Политичке науке]]
[[sh:Političke nauke]]
[[fi:Politiikan tutkimus]]
[[sv:Statsvetenskap]]
[[tl:Agham pampolitika]]
[[te:రాజనీతి శాస్త్రము]]
[[th:รัฐศาสตร์]]
[[tg:Сиёсатшиносӣ]]
[[tr:Siyaset bilimi]]
[[uk:Політологія]]
[[ur:سیاسیات]]
[[za:Cwngciyoz]]
[[vi:Chính trị học]]
[[war:Syensya panpolitika]]
[[zh:政治学]]</text>
      <sha1>p19lfxfhljxfvvbe03roaedkz9klbxu</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
