<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Politicization of science</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>345803</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521747778</id>
      <parentid>521747427</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-06T23:38:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>IjonTichyIjonTichy</username>
        <id>16635488</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>organized lists into columns</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="37426">The '''politicization of science''' is the manipulation of science for political gain. It occurs when [[government]], [[business]], or [[advocacy group]]s use legal or economic pressure to influence the findings of scientific research or the way it is disseminated, reported or interpreted.  The politicization of science may also negatively affect [[academic freedom|academic]] and [[scientific freedom]]. Historically, groups have conducted various campaigns to promote their interests in defiance of [[scientific consensus]], and in an effort to manipulate [[public policy]].&lt;ref name=discovery&gt;[http://www.discovery.org/scripts/viewDB/index.php?command=view&amp;program=CSC-News&amp;id=2445 Evolution or design debate heats up.]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=AAAS&gt;[http://www.aaas.org/news/releases/2006/pdf/0219boardstatement.pdf American Association for the Advancement of Science Statement on the Teaching of Evolution]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=nejm&gt;[http://content.nejm.org/cgi/content/full/354/21/2277 Intelligent Judging — Evolution in the Classroom and the Courtroom] George J. Annas, [[New England Journal of Medicine]], Volume 354:2277-2281  May 25, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

==Overview==

Researcher William R. Freudenburg and colleagues have noted that where decisions and action are required, science can offer valuable degrees of certainty, however, it can never offer a guarantee.&lt;ref name=SCAMs/&gt; [[John Horgan (American journalist)|John Horgan]] describes how this point is sometimes intentionally ignored as a part of what he calls an &quot;Orwellian tactic&quot;.&lt;ref name=HorganReview/&gt; Organizations sometimes seek to shift all discussion on some issues away from 'conclusions are most scientifically likely' to 'even the more probable conclusion is still uncertain.' 

[[Chris Mooney (journalist)|Chris Mooney]] has claimed these tactics are used to gain more attention for views that have been undermined by scientific evidence. In his view, the media ends up in a misguided pursuit of &quot;balance&quot; which results in undue weight in reporting. As examples, Mooney offers the [[Teach the Controversy]] campaign that seeks to cast doubt on some aspects of evolutionary explanations, and other campaigns that seek to cast doubt on certain aspects of [[anthropogenic climate change]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| author = [[Chris Mooney (journalist)|Mooney, Chris]]| title = The Republican War on Science| publisher = [[Basic Books]]| year = 2005| isbn = 0-465-04676-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

William R. Freudenburg and colleagues have written about this [[rhetoric]]al technique, and state that this is an attempt to shift the [[philosophic burden of proof|burden of proof]] in an argument.&lt;ref name=SCAMs&gt;[http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1475-682X.2008.00219.x/abstract William R. Freudenburg, Robert Gramling, Debra J. Davidson (2008)] &quot;Scientific Certainty Argumentation Methods (SCAMs): Science and the politics of doubt&quot;. ''Sociological Inquiry''. Vol. '''78''', No. 1. 2–38&lt;/ref&gt; Cigarette lobbyists combating laws that would control smoking via triavializing evidence as uncertain, is offered as an example of a SCAM (Scientific Certainty Argumentation Method). They maintain that what is needed is a balanced approach that carefully considers the risks of both [[Type 1 and Type 2 errors]] in a situation while noting that scientific conclusions are always tentative. The authors conclude that politicians and lobby groups are too often able to make &quot;successful efforts to argue for full 'scientific certainty' before a regulation can be said to be 'justified'&amp;nbsp;— and that, in short, is a SCAM.&quot;&lt;ref name=SCAMs/&gt;

==Historical examples==
===Soviet Union===

{{Main|Suppressed research in the Soviet Union}}

In the [[Soviet Union]], scientific research was under strict political control. A number of research areas were declared &quot;[[bourgeois pseudoscience]]&quot; and forbidden. This has led to significant setbacks for the Soviet science, notably in [[biology]] due to ban on [[genetics]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
 | first=Bentley | last=Glass | month=May | year=1962
 | title=Scientists in Politics | volume=18 | issue=5
 | page=3 | journal=Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists
 | url=http://books.google.com/books?id=PgkAAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA3 }}&lt;/ref&gt; (see &quot;[[Lysenkoism]]&quot;) and in [[computer science]], which drastically influenced the Soviet economy and technology.

===Tobacco and cancer===
[[File:Surgeon General's warning cigarettes.jpg|thumb|right|240px|A cigarette carton warns about the health risks of smoking. Public awareness was delayed by a SCAM (Scientific Certainty Argumentation Method)&lt;ref name=SCAMs/&gt;.]] 
By the mid-1950s there was a scientific consensus that smoking promotes lung cancer, but the [[tobacco industry]] fought the findings, both in the public eye and within the scientific community. Tobacco companies funded [[think tank]]s and lobbying groups, started health reassurance campaigns, ran advertisements in medical journals, and researched alternate explanations for lung cancer, such as pollution, asbestos and even pet birds. Denying the case against tobacco was &quot;closed,&quot; they called for more research as a tactic to delay regulation.&lt;ref name=physorg&gt;[http://www.physorg.com/news91078097.html Tobacco companies obstructed science, history professor says]&lt;/ref&gt; John Horgan, notes a rhetoric tactic that has been used by tobacco companies. It is summarized in a line that appeared in a confidential memo from a tobacco company, in 1969, when they sought to cast doubt on evidence that supports smoking causes cancer. It read, &quot;Doubt is our product since it is the best means of competing with the 'body of fact' that exists in the mind of the general public. It is also the means of establishing a controversy.&quot;&lt;ref name=HorganReview&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/18/books/review/18horgan.html?pagewanted=all &quot;'THE REPUBLICAN WAR ON SCIENCE,' BY CHRIS MOONEY&quot;, Political Science, Review by JOHN HORGAN, Published: December 18 2005]&lt;/ref&gt; 
&lt;ref name=DoubtIs&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://legacy.library.ucsf.edu/tid/wjh13f00|title=Original &quot;Doubt is our product...&quot; memo|date=21 August 1969|publisher=University of California, San Francisco|accessdate=3 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

===Eugenics===
{{Main|Eugenics}}

[[Nazi Germany]] under [[Adolf Hitler]] was well known for [[Eugenics]] programs which attempted to maintain a &quot;pure&quot; German race through a series of programs that ran under the banner of [[Racial Hygiene]]. The Nazis manipulated scientific research in Germany, by forcing some scholars to emigrate, and by allocating funding for research based on ideological rather than scientific merit. &lt;ref name=&quot;DeichmannDunlap1999&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=Ute Deichmann|author2=Thomas Dunlap|title=Biologists Under Hitler|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=gPrtE4K0WC8C|date=15 May 1999|publisher=Harvard University Press|isbn=978-0-674-07405-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Page needed|date=January 2012}}

In the early 20th century, Eugenics enjoyed substantial international support, from leading politicians and scientists. The First International Congress of [[Eugenics]] in 1912 was supported by many prominent persons, including: its president [[Leonard Darwin]], the son of [[Charles Darwin]]; honorary vice-president [[Winston Churchill]], then First Lord of the Admiralty and future Prime Minister of the United Kingdom; [[Auguste Forel]], famous Swiss pathologist; [[Alexander Graham Bell]], the inventor of the telephone; among other prominent people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Blom|first=Philipp|authorlink=Philipp Blom|title=The Vertigo Years: Change and Culture in the West, 1900-1914|year=2008|publisher=McClelland &amp; Stewart, Ltd.|location=Toronto|isbn=978-0-7710-1630-1|page=334}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The level of support for Eugenics research by the Nazis prompted an American Eugenics advocate to seek an expansion of the American program, with the complaint that &quot;the Germans are beating us at our own game&quot;. &lt;ref name=&quot;Lynn2001&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Lynn|first=Richard|authorlink=Richard Lynn|title=Eugenics: a reassessment|year=2001|publisher=Praeger|location=New York|isbn=0-275-95822-1|page=18|quote=By the middle decades of the twentieth century, eugenics had become widely accepted throughout the whole of the economically developed world, with the exception of the Soviet Union.}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

There was a strong connection between American and Nazi Eugenics research. Nazis based their [[Eugenics]] program on the United States' programs of forced [[Sterilisation (medicine)|sterilization]], especially on the eugenics laws that had been enacted in [[California]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/chronicle/archive/2003/11/09/ING9C2QSKB1.DTL ''San Francisco Chronicle'' Sunday, November 9, 2003--&quot;Eugenics and the Nazis – the California connection&quot; by Edwin Black:]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Recent examples==
=== George W. Bush administration ===
In 2004, The ''[[Denver Post]]'' reported that that [[George W. Bush administration]] &quot;has installed more than 100 top officials who were once lobbyists, attorneys or spokespeople for the industries they oversee.&quot; At least 20 of these former industry advocates helped their agencies write, shape or push for policy shifts that benefit their former industries. &quot;They knew which changes to make because they had pushed for them as industry advocates.&quot;&lt;ref name=denver_post&gt;[http://www.commondreams.org/headlines04/0523-02.htm When Advocates Become Regulators] Anne C. Mulkern. The Denver Post, May 23, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

Also in 2004, the scientific [[advocacy]] group [[Union of Concerned Scientists]] issued a report, ''Scientific Integrity in Policymaking: An Investigation into the Bush Administration's Misuse of Science''&lt;ref name=americanprogress&gt;[http://www.americanprogress.org/atf/cf/%7BE9245FE4-9A2B-43C7-A521-5D6FF2E06E03%7D/UCSINTEGRITY.PDF Scientific Integrity in Policymaking: An Investigation into the Bush Administration's Misuse of Science] Union of Concerned Scientists&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=ucsintegrity&gt;[http://www.ucsusa.org/scientific_integrity/interference/scientists-signon-statement.html Restoring Scientific Integrity in Policymaking] Union of Concerned Scientists&lt;/ref&gt; which charged the following: &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;A growing number of scientists, policy makers, and technical specialists both inside and outside the government allege that the current Bush administration has suppressed or distorted the scientific analyses of federal agencies to bring these results in line with administration policy. In addition, these experts contend that irregularities in the appointment of scientific advisors and advisory panels are threatening to upset the legally mandated balance of these bodies.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt; A petition, signed on February 18, 2004, by more than 9,000 scientists, including 49 [[Nobel laureates]] and 63 National Medal of Science recipients,&lt;ref&gt;[http://go.ucsusa.org/RSI_list/index.php Scientific Integrity Statement Signatories] Union of Concerned Scientists&lt;/ref&gt; followed the report. The petition stated: &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;When scientific knowledge has been found to be in conflict with its political goals, the administration has often manipulated the process through which science enters into its decisions. This has been done by placing people who are professionally unqualified or who have clear conflicts of interest in official posts and on scientific advisory committees; by disbanding existing advisory committees; by censoring and suppressing reports by the government’s own scientists; and by simply not seeking independent scientific advice. Other administrations have, on occasion, engaged in such practices, but not so systematically nor on so wide a front. Furthermore, in advocating policies that are not scientifically sound, the administration has sometimes misrepresented scientific knowledge and misled the public about the implications of its policies.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The same year, Francesca Grifo, executive director of the Union of Concerned Scientists' Scientific Integrity Program, stated &quot;We have reports that stay in draft form and don't get out to the public. We have reports that are changed. We have reports that are ignored and overwritten.&quot;&lt;ref name=npr&gt;[http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=5232410 Bush Science Push Fails to Transform Critics] Don Gonyea. National Public Radio, Weekend Edition Sunday, February 26, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

In response to criticisms, President Bush in 2006 unveiled a campaign in his [[State of the Union Address]] to promote scientific research and education to ensure American competitiveness in the world, vowing to &quot;double the federal commitment to the most critical basic research programs in the physical sciences over the next 10 years.&quot;

====Surgeon General====
Dr. [[Richard Carmona]], the first [[Surgeon General of the United States|surgeon general]] appointed by President George W. Bush, publicly accused the administration in July 2007 of political interference and muzzling him on key issues like [[embryonic stem cell research]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.nytimes.com/2007/07/11/washington/11surgeon.html?_r=1 | title=Surgeon General Sees 4-Year Term as Compromised | publisher=[[New York Times]] | date=July 11, 2007 | accessdate=2007-12-03 | first=Gardiner | last=Harris }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.reuters.com/article/politicsNews/idUSN1034212120070710 | title=Former Bush surgeon general says he was muzzled | date=July 10, 2007 | accessdate=2007-12-03 | first=Will | last=Dunham | publisher=[[Reuters]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;Anything that doesn't fit into the political appointees' ideological, theological or political agenda is often ignored, marginalized or simply buried,&quot; Carmona testified.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usatoday.com/tech/science/2007-08-05-science-politics_N.htm USA TODAY]&lt;/ref&gt;

Although he did not make personal accusations, the [[Washington Post]] reported on July 29 that the official who blocked at least one of Carmona's reports was [[William R. Steiger]].&lt;ref name=Post29&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/07/28/AR2007072801420.html?nav=hcmodule Bush Aide Blocked Report], Christopher Lee and Marc Kaufman, The Washington Post, July 29, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Food and Drug Administration====

In July 2006 the [[Union of Concerned Scientists]] (UCS) released survey results that demonstrate pervasive political influence of science at the [[Food and Drug Administration]] (FDA).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ucsusa.org/news/press_release/fda-scientists-pressured.html FDA Scientists Pressured to Exclude, Alter Findings&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Of the 997 FDA scientists who responded to the survey, nearly one fifth (18.4 percent) said that they &quot;have been asked, for non-scientific reasons, to inappropriately exclude or alter technical information or their conclusions in a FDA scientific document.&quot; This is the third survey Union of Concerned Scientists has conducted to examine inappropriate interference with science at federal agencies. 

The Department of Health and Human Services also conducted a survey addressing the same topic which generated similar findings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.usatoday.com/news/health/2004-12-16-fda-survey-usat_x.htm | work=USA Today | title=FDA scientists question safety | first1=Julie | last1=Schmit | date=December 17, 2004 | accessdate=May 22, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to ''[[USA Today]]'', a survey of [[Food and Drug Administration]] scientists by [[Public Employees for Environmental Responsibility]] and the Union of Concerned Scientists found that many scientists have been pressured to approve or reject new drugs despite their scientific findings concerns.&lt;ref name=usatoday&gt;[http://www.usatoday.com/news/health/2004-12-16-fda-survey-usat_x.htm Survey: FDA scientists question safety]&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2006, the Union of Concerned Scientists released survey results that they said &quot;demonstrate pervasive political influence of science&quot; at the [[Food and Drug Administration]].&lt;ref name=ucsfda&gt;[http://www.ucsusa.org/news/press_release/fda-scientists-pressured.html FDA Scientists Pressured to Exclude, Alter Findings; Scientists Fear Retaliation for Voicing Safety Concerns]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=ucsfda2&gt;[http://www.ucsusa.org/assets/documents/scientific_integrity/Scientific-Integrity-at-Risk-FDA.pdf  Examples of abuse, Scientific Integrity at Risk: The Food and Drug Administration]&lt;/ref&gt;

====United States Department of the Interior====

{{Main|Julie A. MacDonald}}

On May 1, 2007, deputy assistant secretary at the [[United States Department of the Interior]] [[Julie A. MacDonald|Julie MacDonald]] resigned after the Interior Department Inspector General, Honorable Earl E. Devaney, reported that MacDonald broke federal rules by giving non-public, internal government documents to oil industry and property rights groups, and manipulated scientific findings to favor Bush policy goals and assist land developers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.usatoday.com/news/washington/2007-03-29-interior_N.htm?csp=15 | title = Report: Interior official blasted for twisting environmental data | publisher = USA Today | date = March 30, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; On November 29, 2007, another report by the Devaney found that MacDonald could have also benefitted financially from a decision she was involved with to remove the [[Sacramento splittail]] fish from the federal endangered species list.&lt;ref name=ensnov29&gt;[http://www.ens-newswire.com/ens/nov2007/2007-11-29-10.asp U.S. Endangered Species Program Burdened by Political Meddling]&lt;/ref&gt;

MacDonald's conduct violated the [[Code of Federal Regulations]] (CFR) under 5 C.F.R. § 2635.703 '''Use of nonpublic information''' and 5 C.F.R. § 2635.101 '''Basic obligation of public service'''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.biologicaldiversity.org/swcbd/programs/esa/pdfs/DOI-IG-Report_JM.pdf | title = Report of Investigation: Julie MacDonald, Deputy Assistant Secretary, Fish, Wildlife and Parks | publisher = US Department of the Interior | date = March 23, 2007|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; MacDonald resigned a week before a House congressional oversight committee was to hold a hearing on accusations that she had &quot;violated the Endangered Species Act, censored science and mistreated staff of the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service.&quot;&lt;ref name=AP-20070501&gt;[http://www.boston.com/news/nation/washington/articles/2007/05/01/interior_official_quits_ahead_of_hearing Embattled Interior official resigns post&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Intelligent design===
{{Main|Intelligent design|Teach the controversy}}

The [[intelligent design movement]] associated with the [[Discovery Institute]], has been accused of seeking to &quot;defeat [the] [[Materialism|materialist]] [[world view]]&quot; represented by the theory of [[evolution]] in favor of &quot;a science consonant with [[Christian]] and [[Theism|theistic]] convictions&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;The '''[http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikisource/en/7/71/Wedge_Document.pdf Wedge Document]''' (PDF file), a 1999 Discovery Institute fundraising pamphlet. Cited in Handley P. [http://www.discovery.org/scripts/viewDB/index.php?command=view&amp;program=CSC-News&amp;id=2445 Evolution or design debate heats up.] ''The Times of Oman'', 7 March 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;  The Discovery Institute portrays [[evolution]] as a &quot;theory in crisis&quot; with scientists criticizing evolution and that &quot;fairness&quot; and &quot;equal time&quot; requires educating students about &quot;the controversy.&quot;

Some scientific community and science education organizations state that any controversial aspects of evolution are a matter of religion and politics, not science.&lt;ref name=AAAS&gt;&quot;Some bills seek to discredit evolution by emphasizing so-called &quot;flaws&quot; in the theory of evolution or &quot;disagreements&quot; within the scientific community. Others insist that teachers have absolute freedom within their classrooms and cannot be disciplined for teaching non-scientific &quot;alternatives&quot; to evolution. A number of bills require that students be taught to &quot;critically analyze&quot; evolution or to understand &quot;the controversy.&quot; But there is no significant controversy within the scientific community about the validity of the theory of evolution. The current controversy surrounding the teaching of evolution is not a scientific one.&quot;
[http://www.aaas.org/news/releases/2006/pdf/0219boardstatement.pdf AAAS Statement on the Teaching of Evolution] [[American Association for the Advancement of Science]]. February 16, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;That this controversy is one largely manufactured by the proponents of creationism and intelligent design may not matter, and as long as the controversy is taught in classes on current affairs, politics, or religion, and not in science classes, neither scientists nor citizens should be concerned.&quot; [http://content.nejm.org/cgi/content/full/354/21/2277 Intelligent Judging — Evolution in the Classroom and the Courtroom] George J. Annas, [[New England Journal of Medicine]], Volume 354:2277-2281  May 25, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; The 2005 ruling in the Dover trial, [[Kitzmiller v. Dover Area School District]], where the claims of intelligent design proponents were considered by a [[United States federal courts|United States federal court]] concluded that intelligent design is not science, that it &quot;cannot uncouple itself from its creationist, and thus religious, antecedents&quot;, and concluded that the school district's promotion of it therefore violated the [[Establishment Clause of the First Amendment|Establishment Clause]] of the [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First Amendment to the U.S. Constitution]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite court  |litigants=Kitzmiller v. Dover Area School District  |vol=04  |reporter= cv  |opinion= 2688  |pinpoint=  |court=  |date=December 20, 2005 }},  [[Wikisource:Kitzmiller v. Dover Area School District/6:Curriculum, Conclusion#Page 136 of 139|Conclusion of Ruling]].&lt;/ref&gt; 

A 2006 article in scientific journal ''[[Science (journal)|Science]]'', said the reason that among the thirty-four developed countries surveyed, the U.S. ranks second from last in the number of adults who accept the theory of evolution: &quot;The
acceptance of evolution is lower in the United States than in Japan or Europe, largely because of
widespread fundamentalism and the politicization of science in the United States.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Miller, Jon D.; Scott, Eugenie C.; and Okamoto, Shinji. 2006. [http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/summary/313/5788/765 Public Acceptance of Evolution] Science. 313: 765-766.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Global warming===
{{Main|Global warming controversy}}

Both mainstream climatologists and [[global warming controversy|global warming skeptics]] have accused each other of politicizing the science behind [[climate change]]. 

In 1991, a US corporate coalition including the [[National Coal Association]], the [[Western Fuels Association]] and [[Edison Electrical Institute]] created a [[public relations]] organization called the &quot;[[Information Council on the Environment]]&quot; (ICE). ICE launched a $500,000 advertising campaign to, in ICE's own words, &quot;reposition global warming as theory (not fact).&quot; Critics of industry groups have charged that the claims about a global warming controversy are part of a deliberate effort to reduce the impact any international treaty, such as the [[Kyoto Protocol]], might have on their business interests.&lt;ref name=earthisland&gt;[https://www.earthislandprojects.org/eijournal/spring98/sp98a_fe.htm The PR Plot to Overheat the Earth]&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2005, John Vidal, environment editor of ''[[The Guardian]]'', asserted the existence of [[US State Department]] papers showing that the Bush administration thanked [[Exxon]] executives for the company's &quot;active involvement&quot; in helping to determine climate change policy, including the US stance on Kyoto. Input from the industry advocacy group [[Global Climate Coalition]] was also a factor.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/climatechange/story/0,12374,1501646,00.html Revealed: how oil giant influenced Bush, White House sought advice from Exxon on Kyoto stance]  John Vidal. The Guardian, June 8, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 2006, ''Guardian'' columnist [[George Monbiot]] reported that according to data found in official Exxon documents, 124 organizations have taken money from ExxonMobil or worked closely with those that have, and that &quot;These organizations take a consistent line on climate change: that the science is contradictory, the scientists are split, environmentalists are charlatans, liars or lunatics, and if governments took action to prevent global warming, they would be endangering the global economy for no good reason. The findings these organisations dislike are labelled 'junk science'. The findings they welcome are labelled 'sound science'.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://environment.guardian.co.uk/climatechange/story/0,,1875762,00.html?gusrc=rss&amp;feed=1 The Denial Industry] The Guardian, September 19, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=pacinist&gt;[http://www.pacinst.org/topics/integrity_of_science/case_studies/selective_use_climate_update.pdf The Political and Selective Use of Data: Cherry-Picking Climate Information in the White House]&lt;/ref&gt; The &quot;selective use of data&quot;, [[Cherry picking (fallacy)|cherry picking]], is identified as a notable form of scientific abuse by the [[Pacific Institute]], an organization created to provide independent research and policy analysis on issues at the intersection of development, environment, and security.&lt;ref name=pacinst2&gt;[http://integrityofscience.org Integrity of Science initiative of the Pacific Institute]&lt;/ref&gt;

In December 2007, the ''[[Christian Science Monitor]]'' reported that at least since 2003, and especially after [[hurricane Katrina]], the George W. Bush administration has broadly attempted to control which [[List of climate scientists|climate scientists]] could speak with reporters, as well as edited scientists' congressional testimony on [[climate science]] and key legal opinions.&lt;ref name=csm&gt;[http://www.csmonitor.com/2007/1212/p03s03-uspo.html Study Finds White House Manipulation on Climate Science]&lt;/ref&gt; Those who have studied organizations set up to delay action and manufacture uncertainty about [[Scientific opinion on climate change|well established scientific consensus]] have divided their tactics into three basic categories: first deny there is a problem, second, make the case that it's not a problem and may actually be beneficial, and failing that to admit it's a problem but insist there's nothing anyone can do about it.&lt;ref name=goodforyou&gt;[http://www.houstonpress.com/2002-08-15/news/global-warming-is-good-for-you/ Global Warming is Good for You] Dylan Otto Krider, ''Houston Press, 2002''&lt;/ref&gt;
===Waxman report===

In August 2003, [[United States]], Democratic Congressman [[Henry A. Waxman]] and the staff of the [[United States House Committee on Government Reform|Government Reform Committee]] released a report concluding that the [[George W. Bush administration|administration of George W. Bush]] had politicized science and [[sex education]]. The report accuses the administration of modifying performance measures for abstinence-based programs to make them look more effective. The report also found that the Bush administration had appointed Dr. Joseph McIlhaney, a prominent advocate of abstinence-only program, to the Advisory Committee to the director of the [[Centers for Disease Control]]. According to the report, information about comprehensive sex education was removed from the CDC's website. 

Other issues considered for removal included [[Agriculture#Environmental impact|agricultural pollution]],  the [[Arctic National Wildlife Refuge]] and [[breast cancer]]; the report found that a [[National Cancer Institute]] website has been changed to reflect the administration view that there may be a risk of breast cancer associated with [[abortion]]s.&lt;ref name=waxmanreport&gt;[http://oversight.house.gov/features/politics_and_science/pdfs/pdf_politics_and_science_rep.pdf Politics and Science]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=waxmanpage&gt;[http://www.house.gov/reform/min/politicsandscience/ Politics &amp; Science: Investigating the Bush Administration's Promotion of Ideology Over Science]&lt;/ref&gt; The website was updated after protests and now holds that no such risk has been found in recent, well-designed studies.&lt;ref&gt;The full report in PDF format is available from http://oversight.house.gov/features/politics_and_science/pdfs/pdf_politics_and_science_rep.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

===Abortion–breast cancer hypothesis===
{{Main|Abortion–breast cancer hypothesis}}

The abortion-breast cancer hypothesis is the belief that induced abortions increase the risk of developing breast cancer.&lt;ref name=&quot;RUSSO_505&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Russo J, Russo I |title=Susceptibility of the mammary gland to carcinogenesis. II. Pregnancy interruption as a risk factor in tumor incidence |journal=Am J Pathol |volume=100 |issue=2 |pages=505–506 |year=1980 |pmid=6773421 |pmc=1903536}} &quot;In contrast, abortion is associated with increased risk of carcinomas of the breast. The explanation for these epidemiological findings is not known, but the parallelism between the DMBA-induced rat mammary carcinoma model and the human situation is striking. [...] Abortion would interrupt this process, leaving in the gland undifferentiated structures like those observed in the rat mammary gland, which could render the gland again susceptible to carcinogenesis.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; This belief is in contrast to the scientific consensus that there is no evidence suggesting that abortions can cause breast cancer.&lt;ref name=&quot;WHO&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs240/en/index.html |title=WHO - Induced abortion does not increase breast cancer risk |accessdate=2007-12-24 |work=who.int |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071214064635/http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs240/en/index.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-12-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;rcog_2000&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.rcog.org.uk/resources/Public/pdf/induced_abortionfull.pdf |title=The Care of Women Requesting Induced Abortion |page=43 |format=PDF |work=Royal College of Obstetricians and Gynaecologists |accessdate=2008-06-29 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080627022119/http://www.rcog.org.uk/resources/Public/pdf/induced_abortionfull.pdf &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2008-06-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;oversight&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://oversight.house.gov/features/politics_and_science/example_breast_cancer.htm |title=Politics &amp; Science - Investigating the State of Science Under the Bush Administration |accessdate=2008-04-14 |work=oversight.house.gov |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080327055020/http://oversight.house.gov/features/politics_and_science/example_breast_cancer.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2008-03-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the scientific community rejecting the hypothesis, many [[pro-life]] advocates continue to argue that a link between abortions and breast cancer exists, in an effort to influence public policy and opinion to further restrict abortions and discourage women from having abortions.&lt;ref name=&quot;JASEN&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|author= Jasen, P|title=Breast cancer and the politics of abortion in the United States|journal=Med Hist|volume=49|issue=2|pages=423–44|year=2005 |pmid=16562329|pmc= 1251638}}&lt;/ref&gt; While historically a controversial hypothesis, the debate now is almost entirely political rather than scientific.&lt;ref name=&quot;JASEN&quot; /&gt;

The most notable example of the politicization of this topic was the modification of the [[National Cancer Institute]] (NCI) fact sheet by the George W. Bush administration from concluding no link to a more ambiguous assessment regarding the abortion-breast cancer hypothesis,&lt;ref name=&quot;HOUSE&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://democrats.reform.house.gov/features/politics_and_science/example_breast_cancer.htm |title=Politics &amp; Science - Investigating the State of Science Under the Bush Administration |accessdate=2007-11-04 |work=oversight.house.gov}}&lt;/ref&gt; despite the NCI's scientifically-based assessment to the contrary.&lt;ref name=&quot;NCI&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cancer.gov/cancerinfo/ere-workshop-report |title=Summary Report: Early Reproductive Events Workshop - National Cancer Institute |accessdate=2007-11-04 |format= |work=cancer.gov}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==US House of Representatives Science Oversight and Investigation subcommittee==

In January 2007, the [[House Committee on Science and Technology]] announced the formation of a new subcommittee, the [[United States House Science Subcommittee on Investigations and Oversight|Science Subcommittee on Investigations and Oversight]], which handles investigative and oversight activities on matters covering the committee's entire jurisdiction.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Subcommittee handles investigative and oversight activities on matters covering the entire jurisdiction of the Committee on Science and Technology. This Subcommittee is new for the 110th Congress.&quot; [http://science.house.gov/subcommittee/default.htm Subcommittees, Committee on Science and Technology]&lt;/ref&gt; The subcommittee has authority to look into a whole range of important issues, particularly those concerning manipulation of scientific data at Federal agencies. 

In an interview, subcommitte chairman Rep. [[Brad Miller (congressman)|Brad Miller]] pledged to &quot;look into...scientific integrity issues under the Bush Administration. There have been lots of reports in the press of manipulating science to support policy, rigging advisory panels, and suppressing research by federal employees or with federal dollars. I've written about that here before, and you interviewed me a year ago about the manipulation of science. In addition to the published reports, the committee staff has been collecting accounts, some confidential, of interference by political appointees. I hope that more folks will come forward now that Democrats are in the majority and we show we're really going to pursue the issue.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dailykos.com/storyonly/2007/1/24/11426/3083 Democrats Form New Science Subcommittee] Brad Miller interview. [[Daily Kos]], January 24, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Scholarly studies of the politics of science==

The politicization of science is a subset of a broader topic, the politics of science, which has been studied by scholars in a variety of fields, including most notably [[Science and Technology Studies]]; [[history of science]]; political science; and the sociology of science, knowledge, and technology.  Increasingly in recent decades, these fields have examined the process through which science and technology are shaped.  Some of the scholarly work in this area is reviewed in ''The Handbook of Science &amp; Technology Studies'' (1995, 2008), a collection of literature reviews published by the [[Society for Social Studies of Science]].&lt;ref&gt;''Handbook of Science &amp; Technology Studies'', Second Edition, Sage Publications (1995)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Handbook of Science &amp; Technology Studies'', Third Edition, MIT Press (2008)&lt;/ref&gt;  There is an annual award for books relevant to the politics of science given by the Society for Social Studies of Science called the [[Rachel Carson Prize (academic book prize)|Rachel Carson Prize]].

== See also ==
{{refbegin|3}}
*[[Abortion and mental health]]
*[[Antiscience]]
*[[Cyril Burt]]
*[[David Nutt]]
*[[Denialism]]
*[[Discovery Institute intelligent design campaigns]]
*[[Framing (communication theory)]]
*[[Governmental impact on science during WWII]]
*[[Journal of Global Drug Policy and Practice]]
*[[Kansas evolution hearings]]
*[[List of books about the politics of science]]
*[[Politicized issue]]
*[[The Republican War on Science]]
*[[Scientific misconduct]]
*[[Scientists and Engineers for America]]
*[[Spin (public relations)]]
*[[Science by press release]]
*[[Trofim Lysenko]]
*[[William R. Steiger]]
{{refend}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
{{refbegin|2}}
* [http://www.house.gov/reform/min/politicsandscience/ Politics &amp; Science: Investigating the Bush Administration's Promotion of Ideology Over Science]. Website by US Congressman Henry Waxman and the Government Reform Committee.
*[http://www.ucsusa.org/scientific_integrity/interference/reports-scientific-integrity-in-policy-making.html ''Scientific Integrity in Policy Making: Investigation of the Bush administration's abuse of science''] [[Union of Concerned Scientists]] (2004).
*[http://integrityofscience.org Integrity of Science] initiative of the [[Pacific Institute]]
*[http://www.usatoday.com/tech/science/2007-08-05-science-politics_N.htm Science vs. politics gets down and dirty] - [[USA TODAY]]
*[http://www.skeptic.com/eskeptic/04-10-08.html Politicized Science: Science as Public Relations] [[Skeptic (U.S. magazine)]] (2004).
*{{cite book |title=Censoring Science: Inside the Political Attack on Dr. [[James Hansen]] and the Truth of Global Warming|last=Bowen |first=Mark |authorlink=Mark Bowen (writer)|year=2008 |publisher=Dutton |location=New York |isbn=978-0-525-95014-1}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
* [[Shawn Lawrence Otto]] ''Fool Me Twice: Fighting The Assault On Science In America'' Rodale Books (2011) ISBN 978-1-60529-217-5 

{{Lysenkoism}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Politicization Of Science}}
[[Category:Discovery Institute campaigns]]
[[Category:Politics by issue]]
[[Category:Types of scientific fallacy]]
[[Category:George W. Bush administration controversies]]
[[Category:Denialism]]
[[Category:Politics of science]]
[[Category:Scientific controversies]]
[[Category:Religion and science]]

[[es:Politización de la ciencia]]
[[zh:科學政治化]]</text>
      <sha1>k8r8b8bdr7vb8e0cxk57q9o7m9bs5br</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
