<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Political system</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>258724</id>
    <revision>
      <id>510686402</id>
      <parentid>510276637</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-04T00:58:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Riley Huntley</username>
        <id>16130333</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Please add to the top of the page in the proper format</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6482">{{Politics}}
{{Forms of government}}

A '''political system''' is a [[system]] of [[politics]] and [[government]]. It is usually compared to the [[legal system]], [[economic system]], [[cultural system]], and other [[social system]]s. However, this is a very simplified view of a much more complex system of categories involving the views: who should have authority, how religious questions should be handled, and what the government's influence on its people and economy should be.

== Overview ==
There are several definitions of &quot;political system&quot;:

* A political system is a complete set of [[institution]]s, [[interest group]]s (such as [[political party|political parties]], [[trade union]]s, [[lobby group]]s), the relationships between those institutions and the political norms and rules that govern their functions ([[constitution]], [[election]] [[law]]).
* A political system is composed of the members of a social organization (group) who are in power.
* A political system is a system that necessarily has two properties: a set of [[Interdependence|interdependent]] components and boundaries toward the [[Natural environment|environment]] with which it [[Interaction|interacts]].
*A political system is a concept in which theoretically regarded as a way of the government makes a policy and also to make them more organized in their administration.
*A political system is one that ensures the maintaining of order and sanity in the society and at the same time makes it possible for some other institutions to also have their grievances and complaints put across in the course of social existence.

Commonalities between political systems:

*Interdependent parts
**[[Citizenship|Citizen]]s Culture
**Government
*Boundaries
**Citizenship
**Territory
**Property

==Anthropological forms of political systems==

Anthropologists generally recognize four kinds of political systems, two of which are uncentralized and two of which are centralized.&lt;ref&gt;Haviland, W.A. (2003). ''Anthropology: Tenth Edition''. Wadsworth:Belmont, CA.&lt;/ref&gt;

*Uncentralized systems
** [[Band society|Band]]
*** Small kin group, no larger than an extended family or clan; it has been defined as consisting of no more than 30 to 50 individuals.
*** A band can cease to exist if only a small group walks out.
** [[Tribe]]
*** Generally larger, consisting of many families. Tribes have more social institutions, such as a chief or elders.
*** More permanent than bands; a band can cease to exist if only a small group walks out. Many tribes are sub-divided into bands.
*[[Centralized government|Centralized systems]]
** [[Chiefdom]]
*** More complex than a tribe or a band society, and less complex than a state or a civilization
*** Characterized by pervasive inequality and centralization of authority.
*** A single lineage/family of the elite class becomes the ruling elite of the chiefdom
*** Complex chiefdoms have two or even three tiers of political hierarchy.
*** &quot;An autonomous political unit comprising a number of villages or communities under the permanent control of a paramount chief&quot;
** [[Sovereign state|State]]
*** A sovereign state is a state with a permanent population, a defined territory, a government and the capacity to enter into relations with other sovereign states.

== Political Parties in Political Systems ==
 
Political systems do not inherently require the institution of political parties to advance the politics of the political system. Political parties are formed after political systems are put in place.
 
=== American Political Parties (Democracy/Republic) ===
 
In the case of American politics, [[Article Two of the United States Constitution]], specifically Section I, gives no mention to [[political parties]] when describing the [[presidential election]] process. It was only after the establishment of the government did the first political parties form.
 
[[George Washington]], the first U.S. president was against the establishment of political parties in most circumstances and therefore belonged to no party. In his Farewell Address Washington gives reason for his distrust in political parties, specifically in the newly formed United States. Washington does endorse political parties in some political systems however, specifically monarchies.
 
{{Further2|[[George Washington’s Farewell Address#Political parties|Political Parties]]}}
 
Washington is the only President not to be elected through a party oriented election process. Because of this, it is difficult to comment on an America without political party institutions. Washington’s case does point to the original path of the American political system however, one lacking political parties.  
 
Both the U.S. Constitution and Washington provide support for the American political system, a [[Democracy]] and [[Republic]], to be founded without political parties. The past has shown this type of system to work well with parties, but nonetheless, these two systems do not require political parties in their institutions.

== See also ==
*[[Government]]
*[[Voting system]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
*Almond, Gabriel A., et al. ''Comparative Politics Today: A World View'' (Seventh Edition). 2000. ISBN 0-316-03497-5
June 25, 2011.

== External links ==
{{Wiktionary|political system}}
{{Commons category|Political systems}}
* For further resources on political theory and the mechanics of political system design, see the Governance and Social Development Resource Centre's [http://www.gsdrc.org/go/topic-guides/political-systems topic guide on political systems]

{{Systems}}

[[Category:Political systems| ]]
[[Category:Political terms]]

[[ar:نظام سياسي]]
[[az:Siyasi sistem]]
[[be-x-old:Палітычная сыстэма]]
[[bg:Държавно устройство]]
[[bs:Politički sistemi]]
[[cs:Politický systém]]
[[de:Politisches System]]
[[es:Sistema político]]
[[fr:Système politique]]
[[ko:정치 체제]]
[[hy:Քաղաքական համակարգ]]
[[jv:Sistem pulitik]]
[[ky:Саясий система]]
[[lt:Politinė sistema]]
[[hu:Politikai rendszer]]
[[mk:Политички систем]]
[[ms:Sistem politik]]
[[ja:政治システム]]
[[pl:System polityczny]]
[[ro:Sistem politic]]
[[ru:Политическая система]]
[[sl:Politični sistem]]
[[fi:Poliittinen järjestelmä]]
[[sv:Politiskt system]]
[[ta:அரசாட்சி முறைமை]]
[[uk:Політична система]]
[[vi:Chế độ chính trị]]</text>
      <sha1>bg3eth0vm3umyf3e97i4ng5v6v7upw2</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
