<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Political economy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>46044</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521115998</id>
      <parentid>521115445</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T21:57:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>128.138.65.125</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Related disciplines */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25718">{{distinguish|Economic policy}}
{{Politics}}
{{Economics sidebar}}

'''Political economy''' was the original term used for studying [[Production (economics)|production]], buying, and selling, and their relations with law, [[custom (law)|custom]], and government, as well as with the [[distribution (economics)|distribution]] of [[national income]] and [[Economic wealth|wealth]]. ''Political economy'' originated in [[moral philosophy]]. It developed in the 18th century as the study of the economies of states, ''[[Polity|polities]]'', hence the term ''political'' economy.

In the late 19th century, the term ''[[economics]]'' came to replace ''political economy'', coinciding with publication of an influential textbook by [[Alfred Marshall]] in 1890.&lt;ref&gt;Marshall, Alfred. (1890) ''[[Principles of Economics (Marshall)|Principles of Economics]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; Earlier, [[William Stanley Jevons]], a proponent of mathematical methods applied to the subject, advocated ''economics'' for brevity and with the hope of the term becoming  &quot;the recognised name of a science.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Jevons, W. Stanley. ''The Theory of Political Economy'', 1879, 2nd ed. [http://books.google.com/books?id=aYcBAAAAQAAJ&amp;printsec=find&amp;pg=PR14=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false p. xiv.]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Groenwegen&quot;&gt;Groenwegen, Peter. (1987 [[The New Palgrave Dictionary of Economics|[2008]]]). &quot;'political economy' and 'economics'&quot;, ''[[The New Palgrave: A Dictionary of Economics]]'', v. 3, pp. 905-06. [Pp.&amp;nbsp;904–07.]&lt;/ref&gt;  

'''Today''', political economy, where it is not used as a synonym for economics, may refer to very different things, including [[Marxian]] analysis, applied [[public choice|public-choice]] approaches emanating from the [[Chicago school of economics|Chicago school]] and the [[Virginia school of political economy|Virginia school]], or simply the advice given by economists to the government or public on general [[economic policy]] or on specific proposals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Groenwegen&quot;/&gt;  A rapidly-growing mainstream literature from the 1970s has expanded beyond the  model of economic policy in which planners maximize utility of a representative individual toward examining how political forces affect the choice of policies, especially as to [[Distribution (economics)|distributional]] conflicts and political institutions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alesina&quot;&gt;[[Alberto Alesina|Alesina, Alberto F.]] (2007:3) &quot;Political Economy,&quot; ''NBER Reporter'', [http://www.nber.org/reporter/2007number3/2007number3.pdf pp. 1-5] (press +). Abstract-links [http://www.nber.org/reporter/2007number3/ version.]&lt;/ref&gt;  It is available as an area of study in certain colleges and universities.

== Etymology ==
Originally, ''political economy'' meant the study of the conditions under which production or consumption within limited parameters was organized in the nation-states. In that way, political economy expanded the emphasis of economics, which comes from the Greek ''oikos'' (meaning &quot;home&quot;) and ''nomos'' (meaning &quot;law&quot; or &quot;order&quot;); thus political economy was meant to express the laws of production of wealth at the state level, just as economics was the ordering of the home. The phrase ''économie politique'' (translated in English as ''political economy'') first appeared in France in 1615 with the well known book by [[Antoine de Montchrétien]]: ''Traité de l’economie politique''. French [[physiocrats]], [[Adam Smith]], [[David Ricardo]] and German philosopher and social theorist [[Karl Marx]] were some of the exponents of political economy. The world's first professorship in political economy was established in 1754 at the [[University of Naples Federico II]], Italy (then capital city of the Kingdom of Naples); the Neapolitan philosopher [[Antonio Genovesi]] was the first tenured professor; in 1763 [[Joseph von Sonnenfels]] was appointed a Political Economy chair at the [[University of Vienna]], Austria. In 1805, [[Thomas Malthus]] became England's first professor of political economy, at the [[East India Company College]], Haileybury, [[Hertfordshire]].

In the United States, political economy first was taught at the [[College of William and Mary]]; in 1784, [[Adam Smith]]'s ''[[The Wealth of Nations]]'' was a required textbook.&lt;ref&gt;Image of [[:Image:Priorities of the College (W&amp;M).jpg|&quot;Priorities of the College of William and Mary&quot;]]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[University of Glasgow]], where Smith was Professor of Logic and Moral Philosophy, changed the name of its Department of Political Economy to the Department of Economics (ostensibly to avoid confusing prospective undergraduates) in academic year 1997–98&lt;ref&gt;http://cheshire.cent.gla.ac.uk/ead/html/gb248gua-p6.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;, making the class of 1998 the last to be graduated with a Scottish Master of Arts degree in Political Economy.

==Current approaches==
In its contemporary meaning, ''political economy'' refers to different, but related, approaches to studying economic and related behaviours, ranging from the combination of economics with other fields to the use of different, fundamental assumptions that challenge orthodox economic assumptions:
* ''Political economy'' most commonly refers to interdisciplinary studies drawing upon [[economics]], [[law]], and [[political science]] in explaining how political institutions, the political environment, and the [[JEL classification codes#Economic systems JEL: P Subcategories|economic system]]—[[capitalism|capitalist]], [[socialist]], [[mixed economy|mixed]]—influence each other.  &quot;Traditional&quot; topics include the influence of elections on the choice of economic policy, determinants of electoral outcomes, the [[Business cycle#Politically-based business cycle|political business cycle]]s,&lt;ref&gt;Drazen, Allan. &quot;Political business cycles,&quot; ''[[The New Palgrave Dictionary of Economics]]'', 2nd Edition, 2008. [http://www.dictionaryofeconomics.com/article?id=pde2008_P000112&amp;edition=current&amp;q=Political%20business%20cycle&amp;topicid=&amp;result_number=4 Abstract.]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[William D. Nordhaus|Nordhaus, William D.]], &quot;Alternative Approaches to the Political Business Cycle,&quot; ''Brookings Papers on Economic Activity'', 1989, p [http://www.jstor.org/pss/2534461 p. 1]-68.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Central bank#Independence|central-bank independence]], redistributive conflicts in fiscal policy, and the politics of delayed reforms in developing countries and of excessive deficits.  From the late-1990s, the field has expanded to explore such wide-ranging topics as the origins and rate of change of political institutions, and the role of [[cultural economics|culture]] in explaining economic outcomes and developments.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alesina&quot;/&gt; When more narrowly construed, it analyzes such public policy as [[monopoly]], [[Protectionism|market protection]], institutional corruption,&lt;ref&gt;Bose, Niloy. &quot;corruption and economic growth,&quot; ''The New Palgrave Dictionary of Economics Online'', 2nd Edition, 2010. [http://www.dictionaryofeconomics.com/article?id=pde2010_C000616&amp;edition=current&amp;q=%20corruption&amp;topicid=&amp;result_number=1 Abstract.]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[rent-seeking]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Anne O. Krueger|Krueger, Anne O.]] &quot;The Political Economy of the Rent-Seeking Society,&quot; ''American Economic Review'', 64(3), 1974, [http://www.jstor.org/pss/1808883 p. 291]–303.&lt;/ref&gt; A more classical-liberal approach that dates from the 1970s that denotes 'public-choice' theory type approaches which question the benevolence of social planners to maximize the utility of a representative individual and instead stress how political forces affect the choice of policies that may not be so benevolent.
* Economists and political scientists often associate the term with approaches using [[rational choice theory|rational choice]] assumptions, especially [[game theory]] and [[social choice theory]], in explaining phenomena beyond economics' standard remit, such as corruption, government failure and complex decision-making in which context the term &quot;positive political economy&quot; is common.&lt;ref&gt;Alt, James E.; Shepsle, Kenneth (eds.) (1990), ''Perspectives on Positive Political Economy'' (Cambridge [UK]; New York: Cambridge University Press). [http://books.google.com/books?id=wKJu6g5ovhcC&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s Description] and [http://books.google.com/books?id=wKJu6g5ovhcC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_atb#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false preview.]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[New political economy]] students treat economic ideologies as the phenomenon to explain, per the traditions of Marxian political economy. Thus, Charles S. Maier suggests that a political economy approach: &quot;interrogates economic doctrines to disclose their sociological and political premises....in sum, [it] regards economic ideas and behavior not as frameworks for analysis, but as beliefs and actions that must themselves be explained.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Mayer, Charles S. (1987). &quot;In Search of Stability: Explorations in Historical Political Economy&quot;, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge,  pp.3–6.&lt;/ref&gt; This approach informs Andrew Gamble's ''The Free Economy and the Strong State'' (Palgrave Macmillan, 1988), and Colin Hay's ''The Political Economy of New Labour'' (Manchester University Press, 1999). It also informs much work published in ''New Political Economy'' an international journal founded by Sheffield University scholars in 1996.&lt;ref&gt;cf: Baker, David (2006). [http://davidlewisbaker.net/baker_political_economy_of_fascism &quot;The political economy of fascism: Myth or reality, or myth and reality?&quot;], ''New Political Economy'', 11(2), pp. 227–250.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[International Political Economy]] (IPE) is an interdisciplinary field comprising approaches to the actions of various actors. In the US, these approaches are associated with the journal ''[[International Organization]]'', which, in the 1970s, became the leading journal of international political economy under the editorship of [[Robert Keohane]], [[Peter J. Katzenstein]], and [[Stephen Krasner]]. They are also associated with the journal ''[[The Review of International Political Economy]]''. There also is a more critical school of IPE, inspired by [[Karl Polanyi]]'s work; two major figures are [[Matthew Watson (political economist)|Matthew Watson]] and Robert W. Cox.&lt;ref&gt;Cohen, Benjamin J. &quot;The transatlantic divide: Why are American and British IPE so different?&quot;, ''Review of International Political Economy'', Vol. 14, No. 2, May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Anthropologists, sociologists, and geographers use ''political economy'' in referring to the regimes of politics or economic values that emerge primarily at the level of states or regional governance, but also within smaller social groups and social networks.  Because these regimes influence and are influenced by the organization of both social and economic capital, the analysis of dimensions lacking a standard economic value (e.g., the political economy of language, of gender, of religion) often draw on the concepts used in Marxian critiques of [[Capitalist mode of production|capital]].  Such approaches expand on neo-Marxian scholarship related to [[economic development|development]] and [[underdevelopment]] postulated by [[André Gunder Frank]] and [[Immanuel Wallerstein]].
* [[Historian]]s have employed ''political economy'' to explore the ways in the past that persons and groups with common economic interests have used politics to effect changes beneficial to their interests.&lt;ref&gt;McCoy, Drew R. &quot;The Elusive Republic: Political Economy in Jeffersonian America&quot;, Chapel Hill, University of North Carolina.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Related disciplines==
Because political economy is not a unified discipline, there are studies using the term that overlap in subject matter, but have radically different perspectives:
* [[Sociology]] studies the effects of persons' involvement in society as members of groups, and how that changes their ability to function. Many sociologists start from a perspective of production-determining relation from [[Karl Marx]]. Marx's theories on the subject of political economy are contained in his book, [[Das Kapital]].
* [[Political Science]] focuses on the interaction between institutions and human behavior, the way in which the former shapes choices and how the latter change institutional frameworks. Along with economics, it has made the best works in the field by authors like Shepsle, [[Elinor Ostrom|Ostrom]], Ordeshook, among others.
* [[Anthropology]] studies political economy by investigating regimes of political and economic value that condition tacit aspects of sociocultural practices (for example, the pejorative use of [[Mock Spanish|pseudo-Spanish]] expressions in the US-American entertainment media) by means of broader historical, political, and sociological processes; analyses of structural features of transnational processes focus on the interactions between the world capitalist system and local cultures.
* [[Psychology]] is the fulcrum on which political economy exerts its force in studying decision-making (not only in prices), but as the field of study whose assumptions model political economy.
* [[History]] documents change, using it to argue political economy; historical works have political economy as the narrative's frame.
* [[Economics]] focuses on markets by leaving the political—governments, states, legal frameworks—as givens. Economics dropped the adjective ''political'' in the 19th century, but works backwards, by describing &quot;The Ideal Market&quot;, urging governments to formulate policy and law to approach said ideal.{{Citation needed|date=April 2012}}&lt;!-- this needs sources to stay; some tributaries of the wide river of economics may, indeed, posit what is claimed here.  However, the discipline is very wide.  Other schools, and other approaches within econ clearly emphasize other theoretical approaches that make the &quot;ideal market&quot; idea very narrow and limiting, and the idea of &quot;government&quot; as a non-self-interested neutral arbiter suspect.  So it is not correct, without source support, to caricature econ in so narrow a way. --&gt; Economists and political economists often disagree on what is preeminent in developing production, market, and political structure theories.
* [[Law]] concerns the creation of policy and its mediation via political actions that have specific results, it deals with political economy as political capital and as social infrastructure—and the sociological results of one society upon another.
* [[Human Geography]] is concerned with politico-economic processes, emphasizing space and environment.{{clarify|date=April 2012}}
* [[Ecology]] deals with political economy, because human activity has the greatest effect upon the environment, its central concern being the environment's suitability for human activity. The ecological effects of economic activity spur research upon changing market economy incentives.
* [[International Relations]] often uses political economy to study political and economic development.
* [[Cultural Studies]] studies social class, production, labor, race, gender, and sex.
* [[Communications]] examines the institutional aspects of media and telecommuncation systems. Communication, the area of study which focuses on aspects of human communication, pays particular attention to the relationships between owners, labor, consumers, advertisers, structures of production, the state, and power relationships embedded in these relationships.

==See also==
* [[Economic sociology]]
* [[Collective action|Economic study of collective action]]
* [[Constitutional economics]]
* [[Public choice theory]]
* [[EAEPE]]
* [[Economic system]]
* [[Economic ideology]]
* [[Institutional economics]]
* [[List of publications in economics#Political economy|Important publications in political economy]]
* [[Perspectives on Capitalism]]
* [[Social model]]
* [[Social capital]]
* [[land value tax]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|33em}}

==References==
* Acemoglu, Daron (2003). &quot;Why Not a Political Coase Theorem? Social Conflict, Commitment, and Politics,&quot; ''Journal of Comparative Economics'', 31(4), pp. [http://econ-www.mit.edu/files/4461 620–652] (close Bookmarks).
* Breyer, Friedrich (1994). &quot;The Political Economy of Intergenerational Redistribution,&quot;  ''European Journal of Political Economy'', 10(1), pp.&amp;nbsp;61–84. [http://www.sciencedirect.com/science?_ob=ArticleURL&amp;_udi=B6V97-46383PF-7&amp;_user=10&amp;_coverDate=05/31/1994&amp;_rdoc=1&amp;_fmt=high&amp;_orig=search&amp;_origin=search&amp;_sort=d&amp;_docanchor=&amp;view=c&amp;_rerunOrigin=scholar.google&amp;_acct=C000050221&amp;_version=1&amp;_urlVersion=0&amp;_userid=10&amp;md5=dfc37a3bb7197657fa1320111de1763a&amp;searchtype=a Abstract.]
* Alesina, Alberto,  and Roberto Perotti (1994). &quot;The Political Economy of Growth: A Critical Survey of the Recent Literature,&quot; ''World Bank Economic Review'', 8(3), pp. [http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/1999/09/11/000178830_98101911401317/Rendered/PDF/multi_page.pdf 351-371.]
* _____ (1995). &quot;The Political Economy of Budget Deficits&quot; IMF ''Staff Papers'', 42(1), pp. [http://www.jstor.org/pss/3867338 p. 1]-31.
* [[Paul A. Baran|Baran, Paul A.]] (1957). ''The Political Economy of Growth''.  Monthly Review Press, New York. Review [http://heinonline.org/HOL/LandingPage?collection=journals&amp;handle=hein.journals/guild19&amp;div=12&amp;id=&amp;page= extrract.]
* [[Gary S. Becker|Becker, Gary S.]] (1983). &quot;A Theory of Competition among Pressure Groups for Political Influence,&quot; ''Quarterly Journal of Economics'', 98(3), pp. [http://www2.bren.ucsb.edu/~glibecap/BeckerQJE1983.pdf 371-400.]
* Bolton, Patrick, and Gérard Roland (1997). &quot;The Breakup of Nations: A Political Economy Analysis,&quot; ''Quarterly Journal of Economics'',  112(4), p [http://www.jstor.org/pss/2951266 p. 1057]-1090.
* [[John R. Commons|Commons, John R.]]  (1934 [1986]). ''Institutional Economics: Its Place in Political Economy'', Macmillan. [http://www.transactionpub.com/title/Institutional-Economics-978-0-88738-797-5.html Description] and [http://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=1wFHlGU70ZAC&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PR11&amp;ots=5eJMq_gGXF&amp;sig=CJpmLDgk8uq32rloiJcBIMFPjQU#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false preview.]
* Drazen, Allan (2000). ''Political Economy in Macroeconomics''. Princeton.  Review [http://www.jstor.org/pss/2698665 extract,] [http://press.princeton.edu/titles/6819.html description] &amp; ch. 1-preview [http://press.princeton.edu/chapters/s6819.html link.]
* Leroux, Robert (2011), ''Political Economy and Liberalism in France :  The Contributions of Frédéric Bastiat'', London, Routledge.
* [[Per Krusell|Krusell, Per]], and José-Víctor Ríos-Rull (1999). &quot;On the Size of U.S. Government: Political Economy in the Neoclassical Growth Model,&quot; ''American Economic Review'', 89(5), p [http://www.jstor.org/pss/117052 p. 1156]-1181.
* Maggi, Giovanni, and Andrés Rodríguez-Clare (2007). &quot;A Political-Economy Theory of Trade Agreements,&quot; ''American Economic Review'', 97(4), p [http://www.jstor.org/pss/30034097 p. 1374]-1406.
* [[Torsten Persson|Persson, Torsten]], and [[Guido Tabellini]] (2000). ''Political Economics: Explaining Economic Policy'' MIT Press. Review [http://www.jstor.org/pss/2698665 extract,] [http://mitpress.mit.edu/catalog/item/default.asp?ttype=2&amp;tid=8754 description] and chapter-preview [http://books.google.com/books?id=q3h_M3QI7OYC&amp;printsec=find&amp;pg=PR7=gbs_atb#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false links.]
* Rose, N. L. (2001). &quot;Regulation, Political Economy of,&quot; ''[[International Encyclopedia of the Social &amp; Behavioral Sciences]]'', pp.&amp;nbsp;12967–12970. [http://www.sciencedirect.com/science?_ob=ArticleURL&amp;_udi=B7MRM-4MT09VJ-2YX&amp;_rdoc=11&amp;_hierId=151000135&amp;_refWorkId=21&amp;_explode=151000131,151000135&amp;_fmt=high&amp;_orig=na&amp;_docanchor=&amp;_idxType=SC&amp;view=c&amp;_ct=14&amp;_acct=C000050221&amp;_version=1&amp;_urlVersion=0&amp;_userid=10&amp;md5=275222d8e93eb1135b7ae20e38b67a8b Abstract.]
* [[Martin Shubik|Shubik, Martin]] (1981). &quot;Game Theory Models and  Methods in Political Economy,&quot; in [[Kenneth Arrow|K. Arrow]] and M. Intriligator, ed., ''Handbook of Mathematical Economics'', Elsevier, v. 1, pp.  [http://www.sciencedirect.com/science?_ob=ArticleURL&amp;_udi=B7P5Y-4FDF0FN-C&amp;_user=10&amp;_coverDate=01/01/1981&amp;_rdoc=11&amp;_fmt=high&amp;_orig=browse&amp;_origin=browse&amp;_zone=rslt_list_item&amp;_srch=doc-info(%23toc%2324615%231981%23999989999%23565707%23FLP%23display%23Volume)&amp;_cdi=24615&amp;_sort=d&amp;_docanchor=&amp;_ct=14&amp;_acct=C000050221&amp;_version=1&amp;_urlVersion=0&amp;_userid=10&amp;md5=cb34198ec88c9ab8fa59af6d5634e9cf&amp;searchtype=a 285]-330.
* _____ (1984). ''A Game-Theoretic Approach to Political Economy''.  MIT Press. [http://mitpress.mit.edu/catalog/item/default.asp?ttype=2&amp;tid=5086 Description] and review [http://www.jstor.org/pss/4225764 extract].
* _____ (1999). ''Political Economy, Oligopoly And Experimental Games: The Selected Essays of Martin Shubik'', v. 1, Edward Elgar.  [http://www.e-elgar.co.uk/bookentry_mainUS.lasso?id=834 Description] and contents of [http://books.google.com/books?id=DZ_97SqmzagC&amp;pg=PR5&amp;source=gbs_selected_pages&amp;cad=3#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Part I], Political Economy.
* Sturzenegger, Federico, and Mariano Tommasi (1998). ''The Polítical Economy of Reform'', MIT Press.  [http://mitpress.mit.edu/catalog/item/default.asp?ttype=2&amp;tid=7698 Description] and chapter-preview [http://books.google.com/books/mitpress?id=oxhsaTkxzRUC&amp;printsec=find&amp;pg=PP3=gbs_atb#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false links.]
* Weingast, Barry R., Kenneth A. Shepsle, and Christopher Johnsen, (1981). &quot;The Political Economy of Benefits and Costs: A Neoclassical Approach to Distributive Politics,&quot; '' Journal of Political Economy'', 89(4), p [http://www.jstor.org/pss/1833029 p. 642]-664.
*  O'Hara, Phillip Anthony, ed. (1999).  ''Encyclopedia of Political Economy'', 2 v. Routledge.  2003 review [http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa5437/is_4_37/ai_n29053295/ links.]
* [[Steven Pressman|Pressman, Steven]], ''Interactions in Political Economy: Malvern After Ten Years'' Routledge, 1996
*  Weingast, Barry R., and Donald Wittman, ed., 2008.  ''The Oxford Handbook of Political Economy''. Oxford UP. [http://books.google.com/books?id=WgHcf8Y0r9UC&amp;printsec=find&amp;pg=PR7=gbs_atb#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Preview.]
* Winch, Donald (1996). ''Riches and Poverty : An Intellectual History of Political Economy in Britain, 1750–1834'' Cambridge [etc.]: Cambridge U.P.
* Winch, Donald (1973). &quot;The Emergence of Economics as a Science, 1750–1870.&quot; In: ''The Fontana Economic History of Europe, Vol. 3''. London: Collins/Fontana.

==Journals==
{{MultiCol}}
* ''[[Constitutional Political Economy]]''
* [http://www.wiley.com/bw/journal.asp?ref=0954-1985 ''Economics &amp; Politics'']
* [http://www.elsevier.com/wps/find/journaldescription.cws_home/505544/description#description ''European Journal of Political Economy'']
{{ColBreak}}
* [http://www.springer.com/economics/public+finance/journal/11127 ''Public Choice'']
* [http://spe.library.utoronto.ca/index.php/spe ''Studies in Political Economy'']
{{EndMultiCol}}

==External links==
{{Wikibooks|Political Economy}}
{{NIE Poster|year=1905|Political Economy}}
* [http://furly.de/f3n81e Political Economy Academic Community]
* [[NBER]] (U.S.)  &quot;Political Economy&quot; [[working paper|working-paper]] abstract  [http://www.nber.org/papersbyprog/POL.html links.]
* [[Centre for Economic Policy Research#VoxEU.org|VoxEU.org]] (Europe) [http://www.voxeu.org/index.php?q=node/315 &quot;Politics and economics&quot;] article links.
*  [[Friedrich List|List, Friedrich]]. [http://socserv2.socsci.mcmaster.ca/~econ/ugcm/3ll3/list/national.html National System of Political Economy]
* Carey, Henry C. [http://www.hti.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?c=moa;cc=moa;q1=American%20System;rgn=full%20text;idno=AJB8869.0001.001;didno=AJB8869.0001.001;view=image;seq=00000019 Harmony of Interests] - compares American and British systems{{Clarify| date= January 2012}} of political economy
* [http://www.jacobs-university.de/ipe/ International Political Economy at Jacobs University Bremen]
*[http://www.city.ac.uk/study/courses/social/global-political-eco.html Global Political Economy] at City University London
*[http://www.sussex.ac.uk/cgpe Centre for Global Political Economy] at the University of Sussex, UK
*[http://www.cox.smu.edu/web/oneil-center/o-neil-center-for-global-markets-and-freedom O'Neil Center for Global Markets and Freedom at the SMU Cox School of Business Dallas, TX USA]
*[http://www.iuctorino.it/content/institute-study-political-economy-and-law-ipel Institute for the study of Political Economy and Law (IPEL) at the International University College of Turin (IUC), Italy]
* [http://www.ecipe.org/ European Centre for International Political Economy]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Political Economy}}
[[Category:Political economy| ]]

[[ar:اقتصاد سياسي]]
[[bg:Политическа икономия]]
[[ca:Economia política]]
[[cs:Politická ekonomie]]
[[da:Politisk økonomi]]
[[de:Politische Ökonomie]]
[[et:Poliitiline ökonoomia]]
[[el:Πολιτική οικονομία]]
[[es:Economía política]]
[[fa:اقتصاد سیاسی]]
[[fr:Économie politique]]
[[ko:정치경제학]]
[[id:Ilmu ekonomi politik]]
[[it:Economia politica]]
[[he:כלכלה פוליטית]]
[[ka:პოლიტიკური ეკონომია]]
[[la:Oeconomia politica]]
[[mk:Политичка економија]]
[[nl:Politieke economie]]
[[ja:政治経済学]]
[[no:Politisk økonomi]]
[[nn:Politisk økonomi]]
[[pl:Ekonomia polityczna]]
[[pt:Economia política]]
[[ro:Economie politică]]
[[ru:Политическая экономия]]
[[si:දේශපාලනික ආර්ථිකය]]
[[simple:Political economy]]
[[sk:Politická ekonómia]]
[[ckb:ئابووری سیاسی]]
[[sr:Економска политика]]
[[th:เศรษฐศาสตร์การเมือง]]
[[tr:Politik iktisat]]
[[uk:Політична економія]]
[[vi:Kinh tế chính trị]]
[[zh:政治经济学]]</text>
      <sha1>i83abhiwppm8bujfdsbk0spilgr7obx</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
