<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Political criticism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5386990</id>
    <revision>
      <id>506478425</id>
      <parentid>506476010</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-08-09T00:33:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Dating maintenance tags: {{Merge to}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="5973">{{Merge to|Political science|date=August 2012}}

'''Political criticism''' (also referred to as '''political commentary''' or '''political discussion''') is [[criticism]] that is specific of or relevant to [[politics]], including [[policies]], [[politicians]], [[political parties]], and types of [[government]].

==Controversy==
There is great controversy over the relevance and importance of political criticism in civilizations, particularly [[democratic]] [[societies]].

Those who contend that it is of vast importance assert that political discussion creates and promotes the variety of opinions necessary for a true democracy. The [[American constitution]] is often pointed to as support for the belief, ensuring for all peoples under its administration such maxims as [[free speech]].

Critics of this philosophy affirm instead that the general public (and, on a more individual  basis, the &quot;Average Joe&quot;) lacks the resources and capability to conceive opinions that are educated enough to be taken seriously. Thus, the abundance and fervent promotion of such opinions merely confuses and complicates political matters that, given an appropriate amount of factual education, are either easily understood or should be discussed only by those with sufficient [[intelligence]] to do the matter justice.

==Methods==
There are many methods used throughout [[written history|history]] of promoting political opinions, and with the development of new [[technologies]] new ways have materialized both in recent and ancient history. Some of the most common include the following:

===Books===
[[Image:Gutenberg Bible.jpg|thumbnail|250px|left|[[The Bible]], one of the most influential books of all time]]
Throughout history one of the most influential methods (arguably '''the''' most influential method) of promoting political opinions has been literary. This peculiar pattern of books influencing the thinking of the masses, reinstated with such books as [[the Bible]], [[Uncle Tom's Cabin]], the [[Qur'an]], ''[[The Diary of a Young Girl]]'', ''[[Nineteen Eighty-Four]]'' and many others, has been attributed to many of the characteristics of [[writing]]. While it has been proven that a well-written book can indeed appeal to one's intellect with reasoning and ideas sprung from [[common sense]], the drive of [[literature]] and writing is most commonly considered to be derivative of the [[emotions|emotional impact]] of the text, guiding people to think a certain way by making them feel a certain way. This often has great political consequences, most particularly when the subject of the emotional reaction is a plea for moral justice, as can be seen (to use America as an example once more) in the aftermath of the publication of [[Uncle Tom's Cabin]] concerning American views about [[slavery]]. It is from this correlation between books and politics that the phrase, &quot;[[the pen is mightier than the sword]]&quot;, derives.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}

===Television and films===
Since their development in this past century, both [[television]] and [[films]] have often had far-reaching political effects throughout the world. Influential films and television events include [[Countdown with Keith Olbermann]], [[Citizen Kane]], the works of [[Walt Disney]], and such political [[satire]] as that found in [[The Simpsons]]. Like literature (see above), a movie or television event has the capacity to have emotional impact on its viewers, making it an invaluable tool for politics. This attribute is noticed and used frequently by politicians and ordinary citizens alike; political [[propaganda]] on the screen now has an effect on everything from a nation's outlook on its economy to the smallest of elections and political decisions.

===Political cartoons===
{{Main|Political satire}}
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:conscripcartoon.jpg|thumb|150px|Editorial cartoon concerning [[William Lyon Mackenzie King]]'s freedom from his [[Conscription Crisis of 1944|Conscription promise]] by [[Johnny Canuck]].]] --&gt;
[[Political cartoons]] (also known as &quot;editorial cartoons&quot;) are infamous for their ability to promote political views through satirical means. With cartoons the fight for the minds of the public is not a [[:wikt:verbal|verbal]] but a [[visual]] one, and leaving strong impressions with the use of powerful [[symbols]] or [[metaphors]] in order to communicate the artist's messages.

===News Media===
Since many people know only a very little about their civilization and its present state except for what is told to them by [[news media|the media]], the potential for influence is extremely high with the publication of [[newspapers]], news broadcasts, etc. Any bias in these mediums alters people's impressions of current events into different understandings and opinions than those that may have been chosen with more accurate information.

===Internet===
With the recent invention of the [[Internet]], political criticism has been greatly extended to anyone with a connection to the [[World Wide Web]]. In a few decades already this has revolutionized politics to the extent that the public now has a virtually unlimited education quite literally at its fingertips, allowing people to choose with less work what aspects of current politics they wish to research.

The many means of exchanging ideas, including [[blogs]] and [[internet forum]]s, has extended the political debate to anyone that cares to contribute.  This ability and speed that which ideas can flow has literally changed the way that [[political parties]] stay connected to [[Electoral district|constituents]].

==See also==
*[[Art criticism]]
*[[Bad Subjects]]
*[[Literary criticism]]
*[[Official statistics]]

==External links==
*[http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-23837 The Effect of Propaganda] at the Encyclopædia Britannica

*[http://politicalhackjob.blogspot.com Free political discussion]

[[Category:Political communication|Criticism]]
[[Category:Criticism]]</text>
      <sha1>ehx6tm9czxhd1rdkzks2h3xf3c9zp7j</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
