<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Policy by press release</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8937262</id>
    <revision>
      <id>497580069</id>
      <parentid>497578907</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-06-14T17:22:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>192.249.47.177</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>&quot;climate change skeptics&quot; is also rampant OR; the articles do not make this claim at all; they also do not call out the &quot;entire body&quot;.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6080">'''Policy by press release''' refers to the act of attempting to influence [[public policy]] through [[press release]]s intended to alarm the public into demanding action from their [[elected official]]s. The practice is frowned upon, but remains effective and widely used. In modern times, the term is used to dismiss an opponent's claims, suggesting they are lacking in substance and created to generate media attention.

== Use during the [[Cold War]] ==

Perhaps the most common use of the term refers to an infamous period during the [[Dwight D. Eisenhower|Eisenhower administration]] when &quot;leaked&quot; documents were a common way for the various branches of the [[US Military]] to attempt to garner funding for their pet projects when traditional chains of command failed, or actively ended them. Practically any idea, no matter how outlandish, could gain some traction by simply claiming that the [[Soviet Union]] was working on a similar device.

The first, and most costly, example of this behavior was the mythical &quot;[[bomber gap]]&quot;. After seeing the latest Soviet designs in 1955, a clamor broke out in Washington about the Soviets developing a lead in deploying strategic bombers, with estimates that hundreds would be available shortly. The result was a massive expansion of the US's own building program, which led to the eventual introduction of about 2,500 jet bombers. Although it was not revealed at the time, US intelligence services had actually made real estimates of the size of the Soviet fleet as early as 1956, placing it around twenty aircraft. Nevertheless, the tactic of claiming the gap existed, and then brushing aside any criticism as being &quot;weak on defense&quot;, was so successful it led to a wave of similar claims.

Another famous case was a claim that suggested the Soviets were working on a global-range [[nuclear aircraft]]. An article, complete with &quot;leaked images&quot;, appeared in the December 1958 issue of ''[[Aviation Week]]''.&lt;ref&gt;''Soviets Flight Testing Nuclear Bomber'', Aviation Week, 1 December 1958, p. 27.&lt;/ref&gt; The article described a system that was suspiciously similar to some of the designs currently under consideration by large US aviation companies. Concerns were soon expressed in Washington that &quot;''the Russians were from three to five years ahead of the US in the field of atomic aircraft engines and that they would move even further ahead unless the US pressed forward with its own program''&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''Soviet Nuclear Plane Possibility Conceded'', Ford Eastman, Aviation Week, 19 January 1959, p. 29.&lt;/ref&gt; In fact, the entire article was a hoax: the aircraft appearing in the pictures was later revealed through 3rd parties to be the entirely conventional [[Myasishchev M-50]] ''Bounder'', which never entered production. The rumored aircraft was a nuclear-powered version of the [[Tupolev Tu-95]] bomber, called [[Tupolev Tu-119]]. The controversy managed to secure, for a time, continued funding of US efforts, culminating in the [[Convair B-36#Experiments|NB-36]] testbed aircraft.

Another apparent case of policy by press release during this period was the famous ''[[Look (American magazine)|Look]]'' article on [[flying saucer]]s.&lt;ref&gt;''Is this the real Flying Saucer?'', Look, Volume 19, 14 June 1955&lt;/ref&gt; At the time the [[US Air Force]] and (later) the [[US Army]] were funding the development of the [[Avrocar (aircraft)|Avrocar]] at [[Avro Canada]] in [[Toronto]]. The article, in the 14 June 1955 edition, suggested that the recent wave of saucer reports were possibly due to Soviet flying saucers, and went on to describe them and their capabilities. It included several images that appeared to be provided to them by [[Avro Canada]], or someone in contact with them, including a description of the control system which was identical to the one used on the Avrocar. In the end the concept proved unfeasible, and the Avrocar project was eventually cancelled in 1961. This article nevertheless remains famous to this day, as it is often presented as a US Government misinformation campaign to deflect attention away from &quot;real&quot; UFO's, although to exactly what end varies.

==Contemporary use==
The term is more commonly used today, especially in the U.S., in reference to [[environmental policy]], although it is still used in discussions of [[defense policy]]. Myriad claims asserting [[global warming]] or [[ozone depletion]] have been described by editorialists such as Mark Martin and the [[Chronicle Sacramento Bureau]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/c/a/2006/02/17/MNG56HAEPT1.DTL Governor to push global warming fight - Bold policy gambits expected in bid to lower greenhouse gases], San Francisco Chronicle, 17 February 2006&lt;/ref&gt;, and Dr. Hugh Ellsaesser as &quot;policy by press release&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationalcenter.org/npa159.html Why the U.S. Should Withdraw from the Montreal Protocol], The National Center for Public Policy Research, February 1997&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--BROKEN LINK:
&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sepp.org/key%20issues/ozone/ozonscare.html The Latest Ozone Scare: Policy by Press Release], Washington Times, 17 March 1992&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt; Likewise, the implication that Iraq was involved in the 9-11 attacks, or had [[Weapons of Mass Destruction]] based on evidence the CIA's own reports dismissed, was described as &quot;policy by press release&quot; by [[John Kerry]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/3916793/ January 11, 2004 - Meet the Press]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Lou Dobbs]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://transcripts.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/0701/26/ldt.01.html CNN.com Transcripts: Lou Dobbs Tonight]&lt;/ref&gt;

A related term, ''public health by press release,'' is occasionally  used ironically to imply official pronouncements or media campaigns belie inadequate effort or funding, though it appeared in an article warning against a pitfall from the opposite direction (potential mis-assessment of limited clinical studies by press and policymakers).&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The perils of public health by press release,&quot; Lancet, 2004 Sep 18;364:1037-1038&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Political terms]]
[[Category:Political communication]]</text>
      <sha1>3jpusaoi58hmwkh2js6ikxf5bmsnr6e</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
