<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Political history</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>221737</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521488694</id>
      <parentid>517654488</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-05T09:32:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Omnipaedista</username>
        <id>8524693</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>removing image (it does not add informative value)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11189">{{Politics}}
'''Political history''' is the narrative and analysis of political events, ideas, movements, and leaders.&lt;ref&gt;[http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/hi/DicHist/analytic/anaV.html Politics: The historical development of economic, legal, and political ideas and institutions, ideologies and movements.] In ''The Dictionary of the History of Ideas''.&lt;/ref&gt; It is distinct from, but related to, other fields of history such as [[Diplomatic history]], [[social history]], [[economic history]], and [[military history]], as well as constitutional history and public history.

Generally, political history focuses on decisions made by the leadership of [[nation-state]]s.  Political history studies the organization and operation of power in large societies. By focusing on the elites in power, on their impact on society, on popular response, and on the relationships with the elites in other countries.  The field often involves the deconstruction of myths and received wisdom. The political historian has the constant, and awesome, responsibility of doing justice to the leadership of the past.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Stephen J. Lee|title=Aspects of British Political History 1914-1995|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=EhMI9U3GIm8C&amp;pg=PA1|year=1996|publisher=Psychology Press|pages=1–2}}&lt;/ref&gt;  According to [[Hegel]], political History &quot;is an idea of the state with a moral and spiritual force beyond the material interests of its subjects: it followed that the state was the main agent of historical change&quot;&lt;ref&gt;John Tosh, ''The Pursuit of History'' (2nd ed. 1991), p. 74&lt;/ref&gt; This contrasts with [[social history]], which focuses predominantly on the actions and lifestyles of ordinary people,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.historycooperative.org/journals/jsh/39.3/parthasarathi.html/facts.about.me Parthasarathi, Prasannan, &quot;The State and Social History]&lt;/ref&gt; or [[people's history]], which is historical work from the perspective of common people.
 
In two decades from 1975 to 1995, the proportion of professors of history in American universities identifying with [[social history]] rose from 31% to 41%, while the proportion of political historians fell from 40% to 30%.&lt;ref&gt;Diplomatic dropped from 5% to 3%, economic history from 7% to 5%, and cultural history grew from 14% to 16%.  Based on full-time professors in U.S. history departments. Stephen H. Haber, David M. Kennedy, and Stephen D. Krasner, &quot;Brothers under the Skin: Diplomatic History and International Relations,&quot; ''International Security,'' Vol. 22, No. 1 (Summer, 1997), pp. 34-43 at p. 4 2; [http://www.jstor.org/stable/2539326 online at JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt;  In the history departments of British universities in 2007, of the 5723 faculty members, 1644 (29%)  identified themselves with [[social history]] while political history came next with 1425 (25%).&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.history.ac.uk/ihr/Resources/Teachers/a27.html &quot;Teachers of History in the Universities of the UK 2007 - listed by research interest&quot;] &lt;/ref&gt;  

==Political world history ==
{{main|history of political thinking}}

The [[political history of the world]] is the history of the various political entities created by the Human race throughout their existence on Earth and the way these states define their borders.  The [[history of political thinking]] goes back to antiquity. Political history, and thus the history of political thinking throughout human existence stretches though up to Medieval period and the Renaissance. In the Age of Enlightenment, political entities expanded from basic systems of self-governance and monarchy to the complex democratic and communist systems that exist of the Industrialied and the Modern Era, in parallel, political systems have expanded from vaguely defined frontier-type boundaries, to the definite boundaries existing today.

==Aspects of political history==
The first &quot;scientific&quot; political history was written by [[Leopold von Ranke]] in Germany in the 19th century.  His methodologies profoundly affected the way historians critically examine sources; see [[historiography]] for a more complete analysis of the methodology of various approaches to history. An important aspect of political history is the study of [[ideology]] as a force for historical change. One author asserts that &quot;political history as a whole cannot exist without the study of ideological differences and their implications.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.historycooperative.org/journals/cp/vol-02/no-02/author/ Freeman, Joanne B., &quot;Founding Bothers&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; Studies of political history typically centre around a single [[nation]] and its political change and development. Some historians identify the growing trend towards narrow specialization in political history during recent decades: &quot;while a college professor in the 1940s sought to identify himself as a &quot;historian&quot;, by the 1950s &quot;American historian&quot; was the designation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Richard J. Jensen, [http://members.aol.com/dann01/scribner.html Historiography of American Political History]. In Jack Greene, ed., ''Encyclopedia of American Political History'' (New York: Scribner's, 1984), vol 1. pp 1-25&lt;/ref&gt;

From the 1970s onwards, new movements sought to challenge traditional approaches to political history. The development of [[social history]] and [[women's history]] shifted the emphasis away from the study of leaders and national decisions, and towards the role of ordinary citizens; &quot;...by the 1970s &quot;the new social history&quot; began replacing the older style. Emphasis shifted to a broader spectrum of American life, including such topics as the history of urban life, public health, ethnicity, the media, and poverty.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.infoplease.com/spot/womensintro1.html Brunner, Borgna, &quot;The History of Women's History&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; As such, political history is sometimes seen as the more 'traditional' kind of history, in contrast with the more 'modern' approaches of other fields of history.

===Britain===
Readman (2009) discusses the historiography of British political history in the 20th century. It describes how British political scholarship mostly ignored 20th century history due to temporal proximity to the recent past, the unavailability of primary sources, and the potential for bias. The article explores how transitions in scholarship have allowed for greater interest in 20th century history among scholars, which include less reliance on archival sources, methodological changes in historiography, and the flourishing of new forms of history such as oral history.
===Germany===
In the course of the 1960s, however, some German historians (notably [[Hans-Ulrich Wehler]] and his cohort) began to rebel against this idea, instead suggesting a &quot;Primacy of Domestic Politics&quot; (''Primat der Innenpolitik''), in which the insecurities of (in this case German) domestic policy drove the creation of foreign policy.  This led to a considerable body of work interpreting the domestic policies of various states and the ways this influenced their conduct of foreign policy.
===France===
The French ''[[Annales School]]'' had already put an emphasis on the role of geography and economics on history, and of the importance of broad, slow cycles rather than the constant apparent movement of the &quot;history of events&quot; of high politics.  It downplayed politics and diplomacy. The most important work of the ''Annales'' school, [[Fernand Braudel]]'s ''The Mediterranean and the Mediterranean World in the Age of Philip II'', contains a traditional Rankean diplomatic history of Philip II's Mediterranean policy, but only as the third and shortest section of a work largely focusing on the broad cycles of history in the ''longue durée'' (&quot;long term&quot;).  The ''Annales'' were broadly influential, leading to a turning away from political history towards an emphasis on broader trends of economic and environmental change.

===Social history===
In the 1960s and 1970s, an increasing emphasis on giving a voice to the voiceless and writing the history of the underclasses, whether by using the quantitative statistical methods of [[social history]] or the more qualitative assessments of [[cultural history]], also undermined the centrality of diplomatic history to the historical discipline.

==See also==
*[[International history]]
*[[Historiography]]
* [[Diplomatic history]]
* [[Social history]]

== Further reading ==
* Swirski, Peter. (2011). ''American Utopia and Social Engineering in Literature, Social Thought, and Political History''. New York, Routledge.
* Elman, C., &amp; Elman, M. F. (2001). Bridges and boundaries: historians, political scientists, and the study of international relations. BCSIA studies in international security. Cambridge, Mass: MIT Press.
* Elton, G. R.  ''The practice of history'' (1968), British emphasis.
* French, John D.. &quot;Women in Postrevolutionary Mexico: The Emergence of a New Feminist Political  History,&quot; ''Latin American Politics and Society,'' Summer 2008, Vol. 50 Issue 2, pp 175-184
* Huret, Romain, “All in the Family Again? Political Historians and the Challenge of Social History,” ''Journal of Policy History,'' 21 (no. 3, 2009), 239–63.
* Pasquino, Gianfranco. &quot;Political History in Italy,&quot; ''Journal of Policy History'' July 2009, Vol. 21 Issue 3, pp 282-297; discusses  political historians such as Silvio Lanaro, Aurelio Lepre, and Nicola Tranfaglia, and studies of Fascism, the Italian Communist party, the role of the Christian Democrats in Italian society, and the development of the Italian parliamentary Republic.
* Readman, Paul. &quot;The State of Twentieth-Century British Political  History,&quot; ''Journal of Policy History,'' July 2009, Vol. 21 Issue 3, pp 219-238
* Sreedharan, E. (2007). A manual of historical research methodology. Trivandrum, Centre for South Indian Studies.
* Sreedharan, E. (2004). A textbook of historiography: 500 BC to AD 2000. New Delhi: Orient Longman.

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.mtholyoke.edu/acad/intrel/irhistry.htm Documents of Diplomatic History]
*[http://fletcher.tufts.edu/inter_resources/dhpgenresources.html Fletcher School at Tufts International Relations Resources]
* [http://dca.tufts.edu/features/aas A New Nation Votes: American Elections Returns 1787–1825]
* {{fr icon}} French Website of the '' [http://www.parlements.org/ Comité d'histoire parlementaire et politique]'' (Parliamentary and Political History Committee) and ''[http://www.parlements.org/revueparlements.html Parlement(s), Revue d'histoire politique]'', published three times a year. It contains a lot of information about French political history, including about 900 references of scholarly political history studies and a bibliography of parliamentary history.
{{commonscat|Political history}}

[[Category:Political science|History, political]]
[[Category:Fields of history]]
[[Category:Political history| ]]

[[ar:تاريخ سياسي]]
[[de:Politische Geschichte]]
[[es:Historia política]]
[[fr:Histoire politique]]
[[id:Sejarah politik]]
[[nl:Politieke geschiedenis]]
[[ja:政治史]]
[[no:Politisk historie]]
[[pl:Historia polityczna]]
[[pt:História da ciência política]]
[[fi:Poliittinen historia]]
[[tr:Siyasi tarih]]
[[uk:Політична історія]]</text>
      <sha1>677xsiplny89xi6hizsewjq9scf3mzp</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
