<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Post-war consensus</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1817074</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519790626</id>
      <parentid>519033033</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-25T17:06:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Everyking</username>
        <id>44020</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="5657">The '''post-war consensus''' is a name given by historians to an era in British political history which lasted from the end of [[World War II]] in 1945 to the election of [[Margaret Thatcher]] as [[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom]] in 1979.

The foundations of the post-war consensus (also sometimes referred to as ''[[Butskellism]]'') can be traced to the reports of [[William Beveridge]], who in 1942 formulated the concept of a more comprehensive [[welfare state]] in the [[United Kingdom]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan_6_a_8&quot;&gt;Kenneth O. Morgan, ''Britain Since 1945: The People's Peace'' (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2001), p. 4 and 6&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly after the surrender of [[Germany]] in May 1945, a general election was held in the UK.  The result was a landslide victory for the [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]], whose leader was [[Clement Attlee]].  The policies undertaken and implemented by this Labour government laid the base of the consensus. The [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative Party]] accepted many of these changes and promised not to reverse them in its 1947 ''[[Industrial Charter]]''. 

The post-war consensus can be characterised as a belief in [[Keynesian]] economics,&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan_6_a_8&quot;/&gt; a [[mixed economy]] with the nationalisation of major industries, the establishment of the [[National Health Service]] and the creation of the modern welfare state in Britain. The  policies were instituted by all governments (both Labour and Conservative) in the post-war period. 

Between 1947 and 1975, post-war consensus economic strategies created 28 consecutive years of [[Government budget|budget surpluses]], despite the massive reduction in the size of the British Empire during the period.&lt;ref name = &quot;GDP stats&quot;&gt;[http://www.ukpublicspending.co.uk/downchart_ukgs.php?chart=G0-total&amp;year=1692_2011&amp;units=p&amp;state=UK UK public net debt 1692-2011]&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 1970s global events such as the [[1973 oil crisis]] put pressure on the post-war consensus; this pressure was intensified by domestic problems such as high inflation, the [[three-day week]] and industrial unrest (particularly in the coal-mining industry). In early 1976, expectations that inflation and the [[Twin deficit hypothesis|double deficit]] would get worse precipitated a [[Pound sterling|Sterling]] crisis. By October, the pound had fallen by almost 25% against the [[United States dollar|U.S. dollar]]. At this point the [[Bank of England]] had exhausted its foreign reserves trying to prop up the currency, and as a result the [[James Callaghan|Callaghan]] government felt forced to ask the [[International Monetary Fund]] for a £2.3 billion loan, then the largest that the IMF had ever made. In  return the IMF demanded massive spending cuts and a tightening of the money supply, signalling a lull in [[Keynesian economics]] in Britain until 2008, when a Keynesian-style [[2008-2009 Keynesian resurgence|fiscal stimulus]] was applied to several of Britain's major high street banks as a result of the [[Financial crisis of 2007-2010|Credit Crunch]]. Callaghan reinforced this message in his speech to the [[Labour Party Conference]] at the height of the crisis, saying:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
We used to think that you could spend your way out of a recession and increase employment by cutting taxes and boosting government spending. I tell you in all candour that that option no longer exists, and in so far as it ever did exist, it only worked on each occasion since the war by injecting a bigger dose of inflation into the economy, followed by a higher level of unemployment as the next step.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Yet despite this, some elements of the post-war consensus continued.

However, in the 1970s the consensus was increasingly seen by those on the [[right wing]] as being the cause of the UK's relative economic decline.  Believers in [[New_Right#United_Kingdom|New Right]] political beliefs saw their ideology as the solution to Britain's economic dilemmas in the 1970s.  When the [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative Party]] won the 1979 general election in the wake of the 1978-79 [[Winter of discontent]], they implemented New Right ideas and brought the post-war consensus to an end. During the period 1947-1979 the post-war consensus economic model allowed successive Labour and Conservative governments to reduce government borrowing from an all time high of 237% of [[GDP]] in the aftermath of war down to 43.6%&lt;ref name = &quot;GDP stats&quot;/&gt; when the Conservatives abandoned the Keynesian style mixed economy and began shifting the balance of the national economy towards [[free-market capitalism]] through the [[privatisation]] of state-controlled infrastructure.

== New Zealand == 

The 'post-war consensus' is also regarded as an era of New Zealand political history, from the first [[New Zealand Labour Party]] government of the 1930s until the election of a fundamentally changed Labour party in 1984, following years of mostly [[New Zealand National Party]] rule. As in the UK, it was built around a 'historic compromise' between the different classes in society: the rights, health and security of employment for all workers would be guaranteed, in return for co-operation between unions and employers. The key ideological tenets of governments of the period were [[Keynesian]] economic policy, heavy [[economic interventionism|interventionism]], [[economic regulation]] and a very powerful [[welfare state]].

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==See also==
*[[Gaitskellism]]
*[[Butskellism]]

[[Category:Politics of the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:20th century in the United Kingdom]]

[[de:Post-war consensus]]
[[fr:Consensus d'après-guerre]]</text>
      <sha1>g07js773dh5qm4b4idej422uom7pa2e</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
