<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Princeton Project 55</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1707715</id>
    <revision>
      <id>493733215</id>
      <parentid>439015536</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-05-21T22:19:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Kaltenmeyer</username>
        <id>14703151</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>sp</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3472">'''Princeton Project 55''' is a [[nonprofit organization]] established by members of the Class of 1955 at [[Princeton University]] to mobilize alumni and students, and others who share their concerns, to provide civic leadership and to develop and implement solutions to systemic problems that affect the public interest. It was born of the realization that there is a vast untapped resource, available for the public good, among groups of college alumni.

Princeton Project 55 (PP55) is an independent nonprofit 501(c)(3) organization dedicated to providing opportunities for college alumni to improve our society. By bringing alumni together with students and recent graduates, Princeton Project 55 provides many opportunities for building the commitment, leadership, and mentoring needed to solve critical issues affecting the public interest.

They work through a variety of approaches including matching recent graduates with year-long fellowships in public-service organizations, providing mentors and professional development; supporting alumni from other universities engaged in similar initiatives; and collaborating with on-campus programs to raise the profile of civic engagement among current undergraduates.

Princeton Project 55 was founded in 1989 by the Princeton Class of 1955 and their spouses. So far, Princeton Project 55's Fellowship Programs have placed more than 1,100 students and recent Princeton graduates in paid fellowships and internship programs around the country. More than 20 other colleges and universities have developed similar programs based on the Princeton Project 55 model and are supported by The Alumni Network, our outreach initiative. 

Today, Princeton Project 55 is a multigenerational organization led by a Board of Directors consisting of Princeton alumni in classes ranging from 1955 to 2002. Opportunities exist for substantial involvement by both undergraduates and alumni from all classes.

== Public Interest Program ==

 
Project 55's flagship initiative, the Public Interest Program, engages recent Princeton graduates by placing them in yearlong fellowships across the country. Fellowships are primarily located in six locations: New York, Boston, Chicago, San Francisco, Connecticut, and Washington, DC. In each location, an all volunteer area committee exposes fellows to various issues in their community through regular seminars. The area committee also works to develop an ethos of civic leadership by providing opportunities for professional development and access to a network of mentors.

Princeton Project 55's Public Interest Program provides recent graduates with professional experience and exposure to a wide range of fields including: community development, education, employment/welfare, environmental issues, advocacy, health and medicine, housing, women's issues, and youth services through year-long paid fellowships. Through their work, Project 55 fellows contribute directly to the participating organization's mission.

Organizations that participate in the Public Interest Program gain access to a motivated and diverse pool of applicants with excellent writing, research, and analytical skills; strong work ethic; creativity; initiative; the ability to work in a team; and the ability to meet deadlines. 

 
http://www.project55.org/

{{Ralph Nader}}

[[Category:Civic and political organizations of the United States]]
[[Category:Princeton University]]
[[Category:Ralph Nader]]


{{org-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>r5m3pc3x1z8ksi6dbykfxovp3q8xfjl</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
