<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Private property</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>147767</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522278181</id>
      <parentid>522258380</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T03:37:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sarg Pepper</username>
        <id>16849829</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11824">[[File:Wolfsburg VW-Werk.jpg|thumb|250px|right|The Volkswagen factory, an example of private property. The factory is privately owned by shareholders who derive income from its operation in the form of profits.]]
{{About||the 2006 film|Private Property (film)}}
{{For|other forms of property|Property}}
{{confused|Property rights (economics)}}
{{Property law}}
[[File:Privately owned coastal property in connecticut under developement.JPG|thumb|300px|Privately owned coastal property in Connecticut under development.]]

'''Private property''' is the [[employment]], control, [[own]]ership, ability to dispose of, and bequeath [[Land (economics)|land]], [[Capital (economics)|capital]], and other forms of [[property]] by [[legal person]]s and privately owned [[Business|firms]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = McConnell | first = Campbell | coauthors =Stanley Brue and Sean Flynn | title = Economics | publisher = Twayne Publishers | location = Boston | page = G-22 | year = 2009 | isbn = 978-0-07-337569-4 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Private property is distinguishable from [[public property]] and [[Common ownership|collective property]], which refers to [[assets]] owned by a [[State (polity)|state]], [[community]] or [[government]] rather than by individuals or a business entity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.businessdictionary.com/definition/public-property.html |title=? |author= |date= |work= |publisher= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Private property emerged as the dominant form of property in the means of production and land during the [[Industrial Revolution]] in the early 18th century, displacing [[Manorialism|feudal property]], [[guild]]s, [[cottage industry]] and [[craft production]], which were based on ownership of the tools for production by individual laborers or guilds of craftspeople.&lt;ref&gt;''The Accumulation of Capital'', Economic Theories: http://www.economictheories.org/2009/05/accumulation-of-capital.html: &quot;The spoliation of the church's property, the fraudulent alienation of the state domains, the robbery of the common lands, the usurpation of feudal and clan property, and its transformation into modern private property under circumstances of reckless terrorism, were just so many idyllic methods of primitive accumulation.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Marxism|Marxian]] economics and [[socialist]] politics, there is distinction between &quot;private property&quot; and &quot;[[personal property]]&quot;. The former is defined as the [[means of production]] in reference to private ownership over an economic enterprise based on [[Socialization (economics)|socialized production]] and [[wage labor]]; the latter is defined as [[consumer goods]] or goods produced by an individual.&lt;ref&gt;Gewirth, Alan. (1996). The Community of Rights. [[University of Chicago Press]]. p 168&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Capital, Volume 1'', by Marx, Karl. From &quot;Chapter 32: Historical Tendency of Capitalist Accumulation&quot;: &quot;Self-earned private property, that is based, so to say, on the fusing together of the isolated, independent laboring-individual with the conditions of his labor, is supplanted by capitalistic private property, which rests on exploitation of the nominally free labor of others, i.e., on wage-labor. As soon as this process of transformation has sufficiently decomposed the old society from top to bottom, as soon as the laborers are turned into proletarians, their means of labor into capital, as soon as the [[capitalist mode of production]] stands on its own feet, then the further socialisation of labour and further transformation of the land and other means of production into socially exploited and, therefore, common means of production, as well as the further expropriation of private proprietors, takes a new form. That which is now to be expropriated is no longer the labourer working for himself, but the capitalist exploiting many laborers.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Prior to the 18th century, private property usually referred to [[Landed property|land ownership]].

The concept of property is not equivalent to that of [[possession]]. According to Phillip O'Hara, property and ownership refer to a socially constructed circumstance conferred upon individuals or collective entities by the state, whereas possession is a physical phenomenon.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= O'Hara|first= Phillip |title= Encyclopedia of Political Economy, Volume 2 |publisher= [[Routledge]]|year= 2003|month= September|isbn= 0-415-24187-1|page = 80|quote=One must never confuse possession with ownership; possession is a physical phenomenon, while ownership is a socially constructed circumstance. Only a state can confer the legal situation called ownership.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Roles of private property in society==
===Economic liberal perspective===
[[Economic liberals]] (defined as those who support a private sector-driven market economy) consider private property to be essential for the construction of a prosperous society. They believe private ownership of land ensures the land will be put to productive use and its [[Value (economics)|value]] protected by the [[landowner]].  If the owners must pay [[property taxes]], this forces the owners to maintain a productive output from the land to keep taxes current. Private property also attaches a monetary value to land, which can be used to [[trade]] or as [[Collateral (finance)|collateral]]. Private property thus is an important part of capitalization within the [[Economic system|economy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Connell|first=Shaun|title=Property Rights 101: The Foundation of Capitalism Explained|url=http://www.capitalisminstitute.org/property-rights/|publisher=Capitalism Institute|accessdate=25 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Private property gives its owners stability, as well as a vested interest in the [[enforcement]] of [[property law]].  Citizens that own private property have a vested interest in fighting [[Political corruption|corruption]] of government officials as in cases where corruption is a direct threat to private property and the laws that govern maintaining private property.{{citation needed|date=July 2012}}

===Socialist perspective===
In general, socialists view private property relations as limiting the potential of productive forces in the economy. They believe private property becomes obsolete when it concentrates into centralized, socialized institutions based on private appropriation of revenue until the role of the capitalist becomes redundant. With largely reduced [[capital accumulation]] from the original class of owners, private property in the means of production is to be replaced with a [[Free association (communism and anarchism)|free association]] based on public or common ownership of socialized assets.&lt;ref&gt;''The Political Economy of Socialism'', by Horvat, Branko. 1982. Chapter 1: Capitalism, The General Pattern of Capitalist Development (P.15-20)&lt;/ref&gt;

====Marxist perspective====
Marxists define private property as the right of an individual, or group of individuals, to exclude others from the use of an object. In its undeveloped form, private property is the simple relation of the individual to the natural world in which their individuality finds objective expression. Private property finds its ultimate expression only in the relation of wage-labor and capital.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.marxists.org/glossary/terms/p/r.htm |title=? |author= |date= |work= |publisher= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Norman Levine]], when Marx called for the abolition of private property, he was not referring to privately owned personal property such as clothing and furniture that was not used to produce the &quot;social wealth,&quot; but to [[means of production|productive property]].&lt;ref&gt;Norman Levine. (1991) Introduction to Györgi Lukács, ''The process of democratization''. [[SUNY Press]]. p 8&lt;/ref&gt;

===Austrian School perspective===
[[Austrian School]] economists [[Ludwig Von Mises]] and [[Friedrich August Hayek]] argued that private property rights are a requisite for what they called rational economic calculation and that the prices of goods and services cannot be determined accurately enough to make efficient economic calculation without clearly defined private-property rights.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.economictheories.org/2008/08/socialist-calculation-debate.html |title=? |author= |date= |work= |publisher= |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{{Expand section|date=November 2011}}

== Personal property versus the means of production ==
In general, personal property is almost an extension of one's person and does include property from which one has the right to exclude others. Personal property is different to private property, however, in that it refers to things that are personal: objects with which one has a personal connection, making them important to one person while potentially worthless to the next. These objects can range from CDs to houses, depending on one's perspective, but definitions tend to include personal items such as clothing, books, food, or records.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1848/communist-manifesto/ch02.htm |title=The Communist Manifesto |author=Karl Marx |date=1848 |work= |publisher= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.businessdictionary.com/definition/personal-property.html |title=? |author= |date= |work= |publisher= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

From the [[socialism|socialist]] perspective, private property refers to capital or means of production that is owned by a business or few individuals and operated for their profit. Personal property refers to tangible items and possessions individuals own, as mentioned above. Socialism does not advocate the abolition of personal property, believing that it is an acceptable form of ownership of an item, unlike private property.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1848/communist-manifesto/ch02.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

From the [[Marxism|Marxist]] perspective, which is very similar to the socialist perspective, private property is a social relationship, not (as with personal property) a relationship between person and thing. It also describes personal property, as above, as those objects which are personal, or an extension of one's self. The Marxist perspective also does not advocate the abolition of personal property: it believes that it is only private property that should be done away with.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1848/communist-manifesto/ch02.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[capitalism]] there is little distinction between personal and private property.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.wsm.ie/story/2664 |title=? |author= |date= |work= |publisher= |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;



== See also ==
{{div col |colwidth=20em}}
* [[Business]]
* [[Capitalism]]
* [[Constitutional economics]]
* [[Demutualization]]
* [[Economic liberalism]]
* [[Freedom to roam]]
* [[Means of production]]
* [[Nationalization]]
* [[Neoliberalism]]
* [[Personal property]]
* [[Property rights (economics)]]
* [[Private property sign]]
* [[Private sector]]
* [[Privately owned enterprise]]
* [[Privatization]]
* [[Public ownership]]
* [[Public property]]
* [[Right to property]]
* [[Rule of law]]
* [[Social ownership]]
{{div col end}}

== Notes ==
{{reflist|2}}

[[Category:Political economy]]
[[Category:Property]]
[[Category:Property law]]

[[az:Özəl]]
[[ca:Propietat privada]]
[[et:Eraomand]]
[[es:Propiedad privada]]
[[eo:Privata posedo]]
[[eu:Jabetza pribatu]]
[[fr:Propriété privée]]
[[ko:사유 재산]]
[[io:Privata proprieto]]
[[he:רכוש פרטי]]
[[kk:Жеке меншік]]
[[hu:Magántulajdon]]
[[ja:私的所有権]]
[[pt:Propriedade privada]]
[[ru:Частная собственность]]
[[simple:Private property]]
[[sk:Súkromné vlastníctvo]]
[[sr:Приватна својина]]
[[sh:Privatna svojina]]
[[fi:Yksityisomaisuus]]
[[tr:Özel mülkiyet]]
[[uk:Приватна власність]]
[[zh:私有制]]</text>
      <sha1>mwm9ezzs4rkdyccmp0ja2ie1rf1t0de</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
