<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Progressive Era</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>560252</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522134619</id>
      <parentid>521856126</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T06:19:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Hmains</username>
        <id>508734</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Economic policy */copyedit, refine cat, and AWB general fixes using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (8414)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="50723">{{Progressivism}}
The '''Progressive Era''' in the [[United States]] was a period of social activism and political reform that flourished from the 1890s to the 1920s.&lt;ref&gt;John D. Buenker, John C. Burnham, and Robert M. Crunden, ''Progressivism'' (1986) pp 3–21&lt;/ref&gt; One main goal of the [[Progressivism|Progressive movement]] was purification of government, as Progressives tried to eliminate corruption by exposing and undercutting [[political machine]]s and bosses. Many (but not all) Progressives supported [[Prohibition in the United States|prohibition]] in order to destroy the political power of local bosses based in [[bar (establishment)|saloon]]s.&lt;ref&gt;James H. Timberlake, ''Prohibition and the progressive movement, 1900–1920'' (1970) pp 1–7&lt;/ref&gt;  At the same time, [[Women's suffrage in the United States|women's suffrage]] was promoted to bring a &quot;purer&quot; female vote into the arena.&lt;ref&gt;On purification, see David W. Southern, ''The Malignant Heritage: Yankee Progressives and the Negro Question, 1901–1914,'' (1968); Southern, ''The Progressive Era And Race: Reaction And Reform 1900–1917'' (2005); Steven Mintz, &quot;Beaner Restriction&quot; in [http://www.digitalhistory.uh.edu/database/article_display.cfm?HHID=421 ''Digital History'']; Norman H. Clark, ''Deliver Us from Evil: An Interpretation of American Prohibition'' (1976) p 170; and Aileen Kraditor, ''The Ideas of the Woman Suffrage Movement: 1890–1920'' (1967). 134–36&lt;/ref&gt;  A second theme was achieving [[Efficiency movement|efficiency]] in every sector by identifying old ways that needed modernizing, and emphasizing scientific, medical and engineering solutions.

Many people led efforts to reform local government, public education, medicine, finance, insurance, industry, railroads, churches, and many other areas.  Progressives transformed, professionalized and made &quot;scientific&quot; the social sciences, especially history,&lt;ref name=&quot;Richard Hofstadter 1968&quot;&gt;Richard Hofstadter, ''The Progressive Historians: Turner, Beard, Parrington'' (1968)&lt;/ref&gt; economics,&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;&gt;Joseph Dorfman, ''The economic mind in American civilization, 1918–1933'' (vol 3, 1969&lt;/ref&gt; and political science.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barry Karl 1975&quot;&gt;Barry Karl, ''Charles E. Merriam and the Study of Politics'' (1975)&lt;/ref&gt; In academic fields the day of the amateur author gave way to the research professor who published in the new scholarly journals and presses. The national political leaders included [[Theodore Roosevelt]], [[Robert M. La Follette, Sr.]], [[Charles Evans Hughes]] and [[Herbert Hoover]] on the [[History of the Republican Party (United States)|Republican side]], and [[William Jennings Bryan]], [[Woodrow Wilson]] and [[Al Smith]] on the [[History of the Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic side]].

Initially the movement operated chiefly at local levels; later it expanded to state and national levels. Progressives drew support from the middle class, and supporters included many lawyers, teachers, physicians, ministers and business people.&lt;ref&gt;George Mowry, ''The California Progressives'' (1963) p 91.&lt;/ref&gt;  The Progressives strongly supported [[scientific method]]s as applied to economics,  government, industry, finance, medicine, schooling, theology, education, and even the family.  They closely followed advances underway at the time in Western Europe&lt;ref&gt;Daniel T. Rodgers, ''Atlantic Crossings: Social Politics in a Progressive Age'' (1998)&lt;/ref&gt; and adopted numerous policies, such as the banking laws which became the [[Federal Reserve System]] in 1913.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Yanak|first=Ted|title=The great American history fact-finder|year=1993|publisher=Houghton Mifflin|location=Boston (Mass.)|isbn=0395617154|coauthors=Mineta,, Pam Cornelison ; with a foreword by Norman Y.}}&lt;/ref&gt; They felt that old-fashioned ways meant waste and inefficiency, and eagerly sought out the &quot;one best system&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis L. Gould , ''America in the Progressive Era, 1890–1914'' (2000)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;David B. Tyack, ''The One Best System: A History of American Urban Education'' (Harvard UP, 1974), p. 39&lt;/ref&gt;

== Political reform ==
Disturbed by the waste, inefficiency,  corruption and injustices of the [[Gilded Age]], the progressives were committed to changing and reforming every aspect of the state, society and economy. Significant changes enacted at the national levels included the imposition of an [[income tax]] with the [[Sixteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Sixteenth Amendment]], [[direct election of Senators]] with the [[Seventeenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Seventeenth Amendment]], [[Prohibition]] with the [[Eighteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Eighteenth Amendment]], and [[women's suffrage]] through the [[Nineteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Nineteenth Amendment]] to the U.S. Constitution.&lt;ref&gt;David E. Kyvig, ''Explicit and authentic acts: amending the U.S. Constitution, 1776–1995'' (Kansas UP, 1996) pp 208–14&lt;/ref&gt;

===Exposing corruption===
[[Muckraker]]s were journalists who exposed waste, corruption, and scandal in the highly influential new medium of national magazines, such as [[McClure's]] Magazine.  [[Ray Stannard Baker]], [[George Creel]] and [[Brand Whitlock]] were active at the state and local level, while [[Lincoln Steffens]] exposed political corruption in many large cities; [[Ida Tarbell]] went after Rockefeller's Standard Oil Company.  [[Samuel Hopkins Adams]] in 1905 showed the fraud involved in many patent medicines, Upton Sinclair's ''[[The Jungle]]'' (1906) was a novel that gave a horrid portrayal of how meat was packed, and [[David Graham Phillips]] unleashed a blistering indictment of the U.S. Senate in 1906.   Roosevelt gave these journalists their nickname when he complained they were not being helpful by raking up all the muck.&lt;ref&gt;Robert Miraldi, ed. ''The Muckrakers: Evangelical Crusaders'' (Praeger, 2000)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Harry H. Stein, &quot;American Muckrakers and Muckraking: The 50-Year Schol  arship,&quot; ''Journalism Quarterly,'' Spring 1979 v56 n1 pp 9–17&lt;/ref&gt;

===Modernization===
The progressives were avid modernizers.  They believed in science, technology, expertise—and especially education—as the grand solution to society's weaknesses. Characteristics of progressivism included a favorable attitude toward urban-industrial society, belief in mankind's ability to improve the environment and conditions of life, belief in obligation to intervene in economic and social affairs, and a belief in the ability of experts and in efficiency of government intervention.&lt;ref&gt;John D. Buenker, and Robert M. Crunden. ''Progressivism'' (1986); Maureen Flanagan, ''America Reformed: Progressives and Progressivisms, 1890n s–1920s'' (2007)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Samuel Haber, ''Efficiency and Uplift Scientific Management in the Progressive Era 1890–1920'' (1964)656&lt;/ref&gt;

===Democracy===
Progressives sought to enable the citizenry to rule more directly and circumvent political bosses. Thanks to the efforts of Oregon [[Populist Party (United States)|Populist Party]] State Representative [[William Simon U'Ren|William S. U'Ren]] and his [[Direct Legislation League]], voters in Oregon overwhelmingly approved a ballot measure in 1902 that created the [[initiative]] and [[referendum]] processes for citizens to directly introduce or approve proposed laws or amendments to the state constitution, making Oregon the first state to adopt such a system. U'Ren also helped in the passage of an amendment in 1908 that gave voters power to [[Recall election|recall]] elected officials, and would go on to establish, at the state level, popular election of [[United States Senate|U.S. Senators]] and the first [[presidential primary]] in the United States.  In 1911, California governor [[Hiram Johnson]] established the Oregon System of &quot;Initiative, Referendum, and Recall&quot; in his state, viewing them as good influences for citizen participation against the historic influence of large corporations on state lawmakers.&lt;ref&gt;John M. Allswang, ''The initiative and referendum in California, 1898–1998,'' (2000) ch 1&lt;/ref&gt; These Progressive reforms were soon replicated in other states, including [[Idaho]], [[Washington (U.S. state)|Washington]], and [[Wisconsin]], and today roughly half of U.S. states have initiative, referendum and recall provisions in their state constitutions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.iandrinstitute.org/statewide_i&amp;r.htm | publisher = State Initiative &amp; Referendum Institute at USC | title = State Initiative and Referendum Summary | accessdate =27 November 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

About 16 states began using [[primary election]]s to reduce the power of bosses and machines.&lt;ref&gt;Alan Ware, ''The American direct primary: party institutionalization and transformation'' (2002)&lt;/ref&gt;  The Seventeenth Amendment was ratified in 1913, requiring that all senators be elected by the people (instead of state legislatures). The main motivation was to reduce the power of political bosses, who controlled the Senate seats by virtue of their control of state legislatures. The result, according to political scientist [[Henry Ford Jones]], was that the United States Senate had become a &quot;Diet of party lords, wielding their power without scruple or restraint, in behalf of those particular interests&quot; that put them in office.&lt;ref&gt;Christopher Hoebeke, ''The road to mass democracy: original intent and the Seventeenth Amendment'' (1995) p 18&lt;/ref&gt;

===Municipal reform===
Many cities set up municipal reference bureaus to study the budgets and administrative structures of local governments.  Progressive mayors were important in many cities,&lt;ref&gt;Kenneth Finegold, &quot;Traditional Reform, Municipal Populism, and Progressivism,&quot; ''Urban Affairs Review,'' Sept 1995, Vol. 31 Issue 1, p 20-42&lt;/ref&gt; such as Cleveland, Ohio (especially Mayor [[Tom L. Johnson|Tom Johnson]]); Toledo, Ohio;&lt;ref&gt;Arthur E. DeMatteo, &quot;The Progressive As Elitist: 'Golden Rule' Jones And The Toledo Charter Reform Campaign of 1901,&quot; ''Northwest Ohio Quarterly,'' 1997, Vol. 69 Issue 1, p 8-30&lt;/ref&gt; Jersey City, New Jersey;&lt;ref&gt;Eugene M. Tobin, &quot;The Progressive as Single Taxer: Mark Fagan and the Jersey City Experience, 1900–1917,&quot; ''American Journal of Economics &amp; Sociology,'' July 1974, Vol. 33 Issue 3, pp 287–298&lt;/ref&gt; Los Angeles;&lt;ref&gt;Martin J. Schiesl, &quot;Progressive Reform in Los Angeles under Mayor Alexander, 1909–1913,&quot; ''California Historical Quarterly,'' 1975, Vol. 54 Issue 1, p 37-56&lt;/ref&gt; Memphis, Tennessee;&lt;ref&gt;G. Wayne Dowdy, &quot;'A Business Government by a Business Man': E. H. Crump as a Progressive Mayor, 1910–1915,&quot; ''Tennessee Historical Quarterly,'' Sep 2001, Vol. 60 Issue 3, pp 162–175&lt;/ref&gt; Louisville, Kentucky;&lt;ref&gt;William E. Ellis, &quot;Robert Worth Bingham and Louisville Progressivism, 1905–1910,&quot; ''Filson Club History Quarterly,'' 1980, Vol. 54 Issue 2, pp 169–195&lt;/ref&gt; and many other cities, especially in the western states. In [[History of Illinois|Illinois]], Governor [[Frank Lowden]] undertook a major reorganization of state government.&lt;ref&gt;William Thomas Hutchinson, ''Lowden of Illinois: the life of Frank O. Lowden'' (1957) vol 2&lt;/ref&gt;  In Wisconsin, the stronghold of [[Robert M. La Follette, Sr.|Robert LaFollette]], the [[Wisconsin Idea]] used the state university as a major source of ideas and expertise.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Progressivism and the Wisconsin Idea|url=http://www.wisconsinhistory.org/turningpoints/tp-036/?action=more_essay|publisher=[[Wisconsin Historical Society]]|date=6 February 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Family and food===
[[File:Lindsey ben.jpg|thumb|Colorado judge [[Ben Lindsey (jurist)|Ben Lindsey]] was a pioneer in the establishment of juvenile court systems.]]
Progressives believed that the family was the foundation stone of American society, and the government, especially municipal government, must work to strengthen and enhance the family.&lt;ref&gt;Gwendoline Alphonso, &quot;Hearth and Soul: Economics and Culture in Partisan Conceptions of the Family in the Progressive Era, 1900–1920,&quot; ''Studies in American Political Development,'' Oct 2010, Vol. 24 Issue 2, pp 206–232&lt;/ref&gt;  Local public assistance programs were reformed to try and keep families together.  Inspired by crusading Judge [[Ben Lindsey (jurist)|Ben Lindsey]] of Denver, cities established juvenile courts to deal with disruptive teenagers without sending them to adult prisons.&lt;ref&gt;D'Ann Campbell, &quot;Judge Ben Lindsey and the Juvenile Court Movement, 1901–1904,&quot; ''Arizona and the West,'' 1976, Vol. 18 Issue 1, pp 5–20&lt;/ref&gt; Special emphasis was put on pure milk and water supplies.  At the state and national levels new food and drug laws strengthened local efforts to guarantee the safety of the food system. The 1906 federal [[Pure Food and Drug Act]], which was pushed by drug companies and providers of medical services, removed from the market patent medicines that had never been scientifically tested.&lt;ref&gt;Marc T. Law, &quot;The Origins of State Pure Food Regulation,&quot; ''Journal of Economic History,'' Dec 2003, Vol. 63 Issue 4, pp 1103–1131&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, with the increase in technology use and creation of standard working hours, families had more leisure time. Many spent this leisure time at movie theaters. Progressives advocated for censorship of motion pictures as it was believed that patrons (especially children) viewing movies in dark, unclean, potentially unsafe theaters, might be negatively influenced in witnessing actors portraying crimes, violence, and sexually suggestive situations. Progressives across the country influenced municipal governments of large urban cities, to build numerous parks where it was believed that leisure time for children and families could be spent in a healthy, wholesome environment, thereby fostering good morals and citizenship.&lt;ref&gt;Black, Gregory D. ''Hollywood Censored: Morality Codes, Catholics, and the Movies''. Cambridge University Press 1994&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Sheppard–Towner Act]] of 1921 provided federal funding for maternity and child care, especially federally-financed instruction in maternal and infant health care. It provided 50–50 matching funds to individual states to build women’s health care clinics.&lt;ref name=&quot;in JSTOR&quot;&gt;J. Stanley Lemons, &quot;The Sheppard-Towner Act: Progressivism in the 1920s,&quot; ''Journal of American History'' Vol. 55, No. 4 (Mar., 1969), pp. 776–786 [http://www.jstor.org/stable/1900152 in JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Eugenics====
Some progressives, especially among economists, sponsored [[eugenics]] as a collectivist solution to excessively large or underperforming families, hoping that birth control would enable parents to focus their resources on fewer, better children.&lt;ref name=&quot; Thomas C. Leonard &quot;&gt;Leonard, Thomas C. (2005) [http://www.princeton.edu/~tleonard/papers/retrospectives.pdf Retrospectives: Eugenics and Economics in the Progressive Era] Journal of Economic Perspectives, 19(4): 207–224&lt;/ref&gt;  However, there were no major national, state or local programs that practiced or endorsed eugenics. Progressive leaders like Herbert Croly and Walter Lippmann indicated their classically liberal concern over the danger posed to the individual by collectivism and statism.&lt;ref&gt;Nancy Cohen, ''The reconstruction of American liberalism, 1865–1914'' (2002) p 243&lt;/ref&gt;  The Catholics, although favoring collectivism, strongly opposed birth control proposals such as eugenics .&lt;ref&gt;Celeste Michelle Condit, ''The meanings of the gene: public debates about human heredity'' (1999) p. 51&lt;/ref&gt;

===Constitutional change===
The Progressives tried to permanently fix their reforms into law by constitutional amendments, included [[Prohibition]] with the 18th Amendment and [[women's suffrage]] by the 19th amendment, both in 1920 as well as the federal income tax with the 16th amendment and direct election of senators with the 17th amendment. After Progressivism collapsed, the 18th amendment was repealed (in 1933).&lt;ref&gt;David E. Kyvig, ''Explicit and authentic acts: amending the U.S. Constitution, 1776–1995'' (1996)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Prohibition===
Prohibition was the outlawing of the manufacture, sale and transport of alcohol. Drinking itself was never prohibited.  Throughout the Progressive Era, it remained one of the main causes at the local, state and national level. It achieved national success with the passage of the 18th Amendment by Congress in late 1917, and the ratification by three-fourths of the states in 1919. Prohibition was essentially a religious movement backed by the Methodists, Baptists, Congregationalists, Scandinavian Lutherans and other evangelical churches.  Activists were mobilized by the highly effective [[Anti-Saloon League]].&lt;ref&gt;K. Austin Kerr, ''Organized for Prohibition:  A New History of the Anti-Saloon League'' (1985).&lt;/ref&gt;  Timberlake (1963) argues the dries sought to break the liquor trust, weaken the saloon base of big-city machines, enhance industrial efficiency, and reduce the level of wife beating, child abuse, and poverty caused by alcoholism.&lt;ref&gt;James Timberlake, Prohibition and the Progressive Movement, 1900–1920'' (Harvard UP, 1963)&lt;/ref&gt;

Agitation for prohibition began during the [[Second Great Awakening]] in the 1840s when Crusades against drinking originated from evangelical Protestants.&lt;ref&gt;Jack S. Blocker, ''American Temperance Movements: Cycles of Reform'' (1989)&lt;/ref&gt; Evangelicals precipitated the second wave of prohibition legislation during the 1880s, which had as its aim local and state prohibition. During the 1880s, referendums were held at the state level to enact prohibition amendments. Two important groups were formed during this period. The [[Women’s Christian Temperance Union]] (WCTU) was formed in 1874.&lt;ref&gt;Jed Dannenbaum, ''Drink and Disorder: Temperance Reform in Cincinnati from the Washingtonian Revival to the WCTU'' (1984)&lt;/ref&gt;  The Anti-Saloon League was formed in 1893, uniting activists from different religious groups.&lt;ref&gt;Kerr, ''Organized for Prohibition:  A New History of the Anti-Saloon League'' (1985)&lt;/ref&gt;

The third wave of prohibition legislation, of which national prohibition was the grand climax, began in 1907, when Georgia passed a state-wide prohibition law. By 1917, two thirds of the states had some form of prohibition laws and roughly three quarters of the population lived in dry areas.  In 1913, the Anti-Saloon League first publicly appealed for a prohibition amendment. They preferred a constitutional amendment over a federal statute because although harder to achieve, they felt it would be harder to change. In 1913, Congress passed the Webb-Kenyon Act forbade the transport of liquor into dry states. As the United States entered World War I, the Conscription Act banned the sale of liquor near military bases.&lt;ref&gt;S.J. Mennell, &quot;Prohibition: A Sociological View,&quot; ''Journal of American Studies'' 3, no. 2 (1969): 159–175.&lt;/ref&gt; In August 1917, the Lever [[Food and Fuel Control Act]] banned production of distilled spirits for the duration of the war. The War Prohibition Act, November, 1918, forbade the manufacture and sale of intoxicating beverages (more than 2.75% alcohol content) until the end of demobilization.

The drys worked energetically to secure two-third majority of both houses of Congress and the support of three quarters of the states needed for an amendment to the federal constitution. Thirty-six states were needed, and organizations were set up at all 48 states to seek ratification. In late 1917, Congress passed the Eighteenth Amendment; it was ratified in 1919 and took effect in January 1920. It prohibited the manufacturing, sale or transport of intoxicating beverages within the United States, as well as import and export. The Volstead Act, 1919, defined intoxicating as having alcohol content greater than 0.5% and established the procedures for enforcement of the Act.&lt;ref&gt;David E. Kyvig,''Repealing National Prohibition'' (Kent State University Press. 2000)&lt;/ref&gt;

Consumer demand, however, led to a variety of illegal sources for alcohol, especially illegal distilleries and smuggling from Canada and other countries. It is difficult to determine the level of compliance, and although the media at the time portrayed the law as highly ineffective, even if it did not eradicate the use of alcohol, it certainly decreased alcohol consumption during the period.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;Kyvig, ''Repealing National Prohibition''&lt;/ref&gt;

The Eighteenth Amendment was repealed in 1930, with the passage of the Twenty-First Amendment, thanks to a well organized repeal campaign led by Catholics (who stressed personal liberty) and businessmen (who stressed the lost tax revenue).&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

===Education===
The Progressives worked hard to reform and modernize the schools at the local level.  The era was notable for a dramatic expansion in the number of schools and students served, especially in the fast-growing metropolitan cities. After 1910 that smaller cities began building high schools.  By 1940, 50% of young adults had earned a high school diploma.  The result was the rapid growth of the educated middle class, who typically were the grass roots supporters of progressive measures.&lt;ref&gt;David B. Tyack, ''The One Best System: A History of American Urban Education'' (Harvard University Press, 1974)&lt;/ref&gt; During the Progressive Era, many states began passing compulsory schooling laws.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.infoplease.com/ipa/A0112617.html |title=State Compulsory School Attendance Laws — |publisher=Infoplease.com |date=1999-10-01 |accessdate=2012-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; An emphasis on [[school hygiene|hygiene]] and health was made in education, with [[physical education|physical]] and [[school health education|health education]] becoming more important and widespread.&lt;ref name = &quot;ProgHealthA&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=The progressive era's health reform movement: a historical dictionary|first1=Ruth C.|last1=Engs|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=mNeGQRBgd_MC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|pages=20–22|publisher=Praeger Publishers|year=2003|location=Westport, CT|isbn=0-275-97932-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Medicine and law===
The &quot;Flexner Report&quot; of 1910, sponsored by the Carnegie Foundation, professionalized American medicine by discarding the scores of local small medical schools and focusing national funds, resources, and prestige on larger, professionalized medical schools associated with universities.&lt;ref&gt;Abraham Flexner, ''Flexner Report on Medical Education in the United States and Canada 1910'' (new edition 1960)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lawrence Friedman and Mark McGarvie, ''Charity, philanthropy, and civility in American history'' (2003) p. 231&lt;/ref&gt;  Prominent leaders included the [[William James Mayo|Mayo Brothers]] whose [[Mayo Clinic]] in Rochester, Minnesota, became world famous for innovative surgery.&lt;ref&gt;W. Bruce Fye, &quot;The Origins and Evolution of the Mayo Clinic from 1864 to 1939: A Minnesota Family Practice Becomes an International 'Medical Mecca'&quot;, ''Bulletin of the History of Medicine'' Volume 84, Number 3, Fall 2010 pp. 323–357 in [[Project MUSE]]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the legal profession, the American Bar Association set up in 1900 the Association of American Law Schools (AALS). It established national standards for law schools, which led to the replacement of the old system of young men studying law privately with established lawyers by the new system of accredited law schools associated with universities.&lt;ref&gt;Steven J. Diner, ''A Very Different Age: Americans of the Progressive Era'' (1998) p. 186&lt;/ref&gt;

===Social sciences===
Progressive scholars, based at the emerging research universities such as [[Harvard]], [[Columbia University|Columbia]], [[Johns Hopkins University|Johns Hopkins]], [[University of Chicago|Chicago]], [[University of Michigan|Michigan]], [[University of Wisconsin|Wisconsin]] and [[University of California|California]], worked to modernize their disciplines.  The heyday of the amateur expert gave way to the research professor who published in the new scholarly journals and presses.  Their explicit goal was to professionalize and make &quot;scientific&quot; the social sciences, especially as [[history]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Richard Hofstadter 1968&quot;/&gt; [[economics]],&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt; and [[political science]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Barry Karl 1975&quot;/&gt;  Professionalization meant creating new career tracks in the universities, with hiring and promotion dependent on meeting international models of scholarship.

==Economic policy==
[[File:Pump1913.jpg|thumb|[[Woodrow Wilson|President Wilson]] uses tariff, currency, and anti-trust laws to prime the pump and get the economy working.]]
The Progressive Era was one of general prosperity after the [[Panic of 1893]]—a severe depression—ended in 1897. The [[Panic of 1907]] was short and mostly affected financiers. However, Campbell (2005) stresses the weak points of the economy in 1907–1914, linking them to public demands for more Progressive interventions. The Panic of 1907 was followed by a small decline in real wages and increased unemployment, with both trends continuing until World War I. Campbell emphasizes the resulting stress on public finance and the impact on the Wilson administration's policies. The weakened economy and persistent federal deficits led to changes in fiscal policy, including the imposition of federal income taxes on businesses and individuals and the creation of the Federal Reserve System.&lt;ref&gt;Ballard Campbell, &quot;Economic Causes of Progressivism,&quot; ''Journal of the Gilded Age and Progressive Era,'' Jan 2005, Vol. 4 Issue 1, pp 7–22&lt;/ref&gt;  Government agencies were also transformed in an effort to improve administrative efficiency.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harold U. Faulkner 1951&quot;&gt;Harold U. Faulkner, ''The Decline of Laissez Faire, 1897–1917'' (1951)&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Gilded Age]] (late 19th century) the parties were reluctant to involve the federal government too heavily in the private sector, except in the area of railroads and tariffs. In general, they accepted the concept of [[laissez-faire]], a doctrine opposing government interference in the economy except to maintain law and order. This attitude started to change during the [[Panic of 1893|depression of the 1890s]] when small business, farm, and labor movements began asking the government to intercede on their behalf.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harold U. Faulkner 1951&quot;/&gt;

By the start of the 20th century, a middle class had developed that was leery of both the business elite and the radical political movements of farmers and laborers in the Midwest and West. The progressives argued the need for government regulation of business practices to ensure competition and free enterprise.  Congress enacted a law regulating railroads in 1887 (the [[Interstate Commerce Act]]), and one preventing large firms from controlling a single industry in 1890 (the [[Sherman Antitrust Act]]). These laws were not rigorously enforced, however, until the years between 1900 and 1920, when Republican President [[Theodore Roosevelt]] (1901–1909), Democratic President [[Woodrow Wilson]] (1913–1921), and others sympathetic to the views of the Progressives came to power. Many of today's U.S. regulatory agencies were created during these years, including the [[Interstate Commerce Commission]] and the [[Federal Trade Commission]]. [[Muckrakers]] were journalists who encouraged readers to demand more regulation of business.  [[Upton Sinclair]]'s ''[[The Jungle]]'' (1906) was influential and persuaded America about the supposed horrors of the Chicago [[Union Stock Yards]] (though Sinclair himself never visited the site), a giant complex of meat processing that developed in the 1870s.  The federal government responded to Sinclair's book and [[The Neill-Reynolds Report]] with the new regulatory [[Food and Drug Administration]]. [[Ida M. Tarbell]] wrote a series of articles against [[Standard Oil]], which was perceived to be a monopoly.  This affected both the government and the public reformers.  Attacks by Tarbell and others helped pave the way for public acceptance of the breakup of the company by the Supreme Court in 1911.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harold U. Faulkner 1951&quot;/&gt;

When Democrat [[Woodrow Wilson]] was elected President with a Democratic Congress in 1912 he implemented a series of progressive policies in economics.  In 1913, the [[Sixteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Sixteenth Amendment]] was ratified, and a small [[income tax]] was imposed on high incomes.  The Democrats lowered tariffs with the [[Revenue Act of 1913|Underwood Tariff]] in 1913, though its effects were overwhelmed by the changes in trade cause by the World War that broke out in 1914. Wilson proved especially effective in mobilizing public opinion behind tariff changes by denouncing corporate lobbyists, addressing Congress in person in highly dramatic fashion, and staging an elaborate ceremony when he signed the bill into law.&lt;ref&gt;Vincent W. Howard, &quot;Woodrow Wilson, The Press, and Presidential Leadership: Another Look at the Passage of the Underwood Tariff, 1913,&quot; ''CR: The Centennial Review,'' 1980, Vol. 24 Issue 2, pp 167–184&lt;/ref&gt; Wilson helped end the long battles over the trusts with the [[Clayton Antitrust Act]] of 1914. He managed to convince lawmakers on the issues of money and banking by the creation in 1913 of the [[Federal Reserve System]], a complex business-government partnership that to this day dominates the financial world.&lt;ref&gt;Arthur S. Link, ''Woodrow Wilson and the progressive Era, 1910-1917'' (1954) pp 25–80&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1913, [[Henry Ford]], adopted the moving assembly line, with each worker doing one simple task in the production of automobiles. Taking his cue from developments during the progressive era {{citation needed|date=September 2011}}, Ford offered a very generous wage—$5 a day—to his (male) workers, arguing that a [[mass production]] enterprise could not survive if average workers could not buy the goods.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.americanheritage.com/events/articles/web/20060105-henry-ford-five-dollar-day-model-t-ford-motor-company-assembly-line-james-couzens-highland-park-detroit-automobiles.shtml American Heritage website retrieved 27 October 2008.]{{dead link|date=September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Labor unions===
Labor unions, especially the [[American Federation of Labor]] (AFL) grew rapidly in the early 20th century, and had a progressive agenda as well.  After experimenting in the early 20th century with cooperation with business in the [[National Civic Federation]], it turned after 1906 to a working political alliance with the Democratic party.  The alliance was especially important in the larger industrial cities.  The unions wanted restrictions on judges who intervened in labor disputes, usually on the side of the employer.  They finally achieve that goal with the [[Norris-LaGuardia Act]] of 1932.&lt;ref&gt;Julie Greene, ''Pure and Simple Politics: The American Federation of Labor and Political Activism, 1881–1917'' (1998)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Immigration===
The level of immigration grew steadily after 1896, with most new arrivals unskilled workers from eastern and southern Europe, who found jobs working in the steel mills, slaughterhouses and construction crews in the mill towns and industrial cities.  The start of World War I in 1914 suddenly stopped most international movement, which only resumed after 1919. Starting in the 1880s, the labor unions aggressively promoted restrictions on immigration, especially restrictions on Chinese and other Asians.&lt;ref&gt;Robert D. Parmet, ''Labor and immigration in industrial America'' (1987) p. 146&lt;/ref&gt;  The basic fear was that large numbers of unskilled, low-paid workers would defeat the union's efforts to raise wages through collective bargaining.&lt;ref&gt;Gwendolyn Mink, ''Old Labor and New Immigrants in American Political Development: Union, Party and State, 1875–1920'' (1990)&lt;/ref&gt;  Other groups, such as the prohibitionists, opposed immigration because it was the base of strength of the saloon power, and the West generally.  Rural Protestants distrusted the urban Catholics and Jews who comprised most of the immigrants after 1890.&lt;ref&gt;Daniel J. Tichenor, ''Dividing lines: the politics of immigration control in America'' (2002) p. 71&lt;/ref&gt;  On the other hand, the rapid growth of the industry called for large numbers of new workers, so large corporations generally opposed immigration restriction.  By the early 1920s the consensus had been reached and that the total influx of immigration had to be restricted, and a series of laws in the 1920s accomplish that purpose.&lt;ref&gt;Claudia Golden, &quot;The Political Economy of Immigration Restriction in the United States, 1890 to 1921,&quot; in Goldin, ''The regulated economy'' (1994) ch 7&lt;/ref&gt;  A handful of eugenics advocates were also involved in immigration restriction.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas C. Leonard, [http://www.princeton.edu/~tleonard/papers/retrospectives.pdf &quot;Retrospectives: Eugenics and Economics in the Progressive Era&quot;] ''Journal of Economic Perspectives,'' (2005) 19(4): 207–224&lt;/ref&gt;  Immigration restriction continued to be a national policy until after World War II.

During World War I, the progressives strongly promoted [[Americanization (immigration)|Americanization]] programs, designed to modernize the recent immigrants and turn them into model American citizens, with diminishing loyalties to the old country.&lt;ref&gt;James R. Barrett, &quot;Americanization from the Bottom, Up: Immigration and the Remaking of the American Working Class, 1880–1930,&quot; ''Journal of American History'' 79 (December 1992): 996–1020. [http://www.jstor.org/pss/2080796 in JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt; These programs often operated through the public school system, which expanded dramatically.&lt;ref&gt;Christina A. Ziegler-McPherson, ''Americanization in the States: Immigrant Social Welfare Policy, Citizenship, and National Identity in the United States, 1908–1929'' (2009)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Decline==
In the 1940s typically historians saw the Progressive Era as a prelude to the [[New Deal]] and dated it from 1901 (when Roosevelt became president) to the start of World War I in 1914 or 1917.&lt;ref&gt;Eric Goldman, ''Rendezvous with Destiny: A History of Modern American Reform'' (1952)&lt;/ref&gt; Historians have moved back in time emphasizing the progressive reformers at the municipal&lt;ref&gt;Melvin G. Holli, ''Reform in Detroit: Hazen S. Pingree and Urban Politics'' (1969)&lt;/ref&gt;  and state&lt;ref&gt;David P. Thelen, ''The New Citizenship: Origins of Progressivism in Wisconsin, 1885–1900'' (1972)&lt;/ref&gt; levels in the 1890s.

===End of the era?===
Much less settled is the question of when the era ended. Historians on the left who emphasize civil liberties decry their suppression during World War I and do not consider the war progressive.&lt;ref&gt;Paul L. Murphy, ''World War I and the Origin of Civil Liberties in the United States'' (1979)&lt;/ref&gt; Most historians, however, see the &quot;war to end all wars&quot; as a globalized expression of the American movement, with Wilson's fight for the League of Nations as the climax.&lt;ref&gt;John Milton Cooper, ''Breaking the Heart of the World: Woodrow Wilson and the Fight for the League of Nations'' (2010)&lt;/ref&gt;

The politics of the 1920s was unfriendly toward the labor unions and liberal crusaders against business, so many if not most historians who emphasize those themes write off the decade. Urban cosmopolitan scholars recoiled at the moralism of prohibition and the intolerance of the nativists of the KKK, and denounced the era. [[Richard Hofstadter]], for example, in 1955 wrote that prohibition, &quot;was a pseudo-reform, a pinched, parochial substitute for reform&quot; that &quot;was carried about America by the rural-evangelical virus&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Richard Hofstadter, ''The Age of Reform'' (1955) p. 287&lt;/ref&gt;  However as [[Arthur S. Link]] emphasized, the progressives did not simply roll over and play dead.&lt;ref&gt;Arthur S. Link, “What Happened to the Progressive Movement in the 1920s?,&quot; ''American Historical Review'' Vol. 64, No. 4 (Jul., 1959), pp. 833–851 [http://www.jstor.org/stable/1905118 in JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt; Link's argument for continuity through the twenties stimulated a historiography that found Progressivism to be a potent force.  Palmer, pointing to leaders like [[George Norris]], says, &quot;It is worth noting that progressivism, whilst temporarily losing the political initiative, remained popular in many western states and made its presence felt in Washington during both the Harding and Coolidge presidencies.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Niall A. Palmer, ''The twenties in America: politics and history'' (2006) p 176&lt;/ref&gt; Gerster and Cords argue that, &quot;Since progressivism was a 'spirit' or an 'enthusiasm' rather than an easily definable force with common goals, it seems more accurate to argue that it produced a climate for reform which lasted well into the 1920s, if not beyond.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Patrick Gerster and Nicholas Cords, ''Myth in American history'' (1977) p 203&lt;/ref&gt;  Even the Klan has been seen in a new light, as numerous social historians reported that Klansmen were &quot;ordinary white Protestants&quot; primarily interested in purification of the system, which had long been a core progressive goal.&lt;ref&gt;Stanley Coben, &quot;Ordinary white Protestants: The KKK of the 1920s,&quot; ''Journal of Social History,'' Fall 1994, Vol. 28 Issue 1, pp 155–65&lt;/ref&gt;

While some progressive leaders became reactionaries, that usually happened in the 1930s, not in the 1920s, as shown by [[William Randolph Hearst]],&lt;ref&gt;Rodney P. Carlisle, ''Hearst and the New Deal: The Progressive as Reactionary'' (1979)&lt;/ref&gt; [[Herbert Hoover]], [[Al Smith]] and Henry Ford.

===Business Progressivism in 1920s===
What historians have identified as &quot;business progressivism&quot;, with its emphasis on efficiency and typified by Henry Ford and [[Herbert Hoover]]&lt;ref&gt;Joan Hoff Wilson, ''Herbert Hoover: Forgotten Progressive'' (1975)&lt;/ref&gt; reached an apogee in the 1920s. Wik, for example, argues that Ford's &quot;views on technology and the mechanization of rural America were generally enlightened, progressive, and often far ahead of his times.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Reynold M. Wik, &quot;Henry Ford's Science and Technology for Rural America,&quot; ''Technology &amp; Culture,'' July 1962, Vol. 3 Issue 3, pp 247–257&lt;/ref&gt;

Tindall stresses the continuing importance of the Progressive movement in the South in the 1920s involving increased democracy, efficient government, corporate regulation, social justice, and governmental public service.&lt;ref&gt;George B. Tindall, &quot;Business Progressivism: Southern Politics in the Twenties,&quot; ''South Atlantic Quarterly'' 62 (Winter 1963): 92–106.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;George B. Tindall, ''The Emergence of the New South, 1913–1945'' (1970)&lt;/ref&gt; William Link finds political progressivism dominant in most of the South in the 1920s.&lt;ref&gt;William A. Link, ''The Paradox of Southern Progressivism, 1880–1930'' (1997) p 294&lt;/ref&gt; Likewise it was influential in Midwest.&lt;ref&gt;Judith Sealander, ''Grand Plans: Business Progressivism and Social Change in Ohio's Miami Valley, 1890–1929'' (1991)&lt;/ref&gt;   

Historians of women and of youth emphasize the strength of the progressive impulse in the 1920s.&lt;ref&gt;Maureen A. Flanagan, ''America Reformed: Progressives and Progressivisms, 1890s–1920s'' (2006)&lt;/ref&gt; Women consolidated their gains after the success of the suffrage movement, and moved into causes such as world peace,&lt;ref&gt;Susan Zeiger, &quot;Finding a cure for war: Women's politics and the peace movement in the 1920s,&quot; ''Journal of Social History,'' Fall 1990, Vol. 24 Issue 1, pp 69–86 [http://www.jstor.org/pss/3787631 in JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt; good government, maternal care (the [[Sheppard–Towner Act]] of 1921),&lt;ref name=&quot;in JSTOR&quot;/&gt; and local support for education and public health.&lt;ref&gt;Jayne Morris-Crowther, &quot;Municipal Housekeeping: The Political Activities of the Detroit Federation of Women's Clubs in the 1920s,&quot; ''Michigan Historical Review,'' March 2004, Vol. 30 Issue 1, pp 31–57&lt;/ref&gt; The work was not nearly as dramatic as the suffrage crusade, but women voted&lt;ref&gt;Kristi Andersen, ''After suffrage: women in partisan and electoral politics before the New Deal'' (1996)&lt;/ref&gt; and  operated quietly and effectively.  Paul Fass, speaking of youth, says &quot;Progressivism as an angle of vision, as an optimistic approach to social problems, was very much alive.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Paula S. Fass, ''The damned and the beautiful: American youth in the 1920s'' (1977)  p 30&lt;/ref&gt; The international influences which had sparked a great many reform ideas likewise continued into the 1920s, as American ideas of modernity began to influence Europe.&lt;ref&gt;Daniel T. Rodgers, ''Atlantic Crossings: Social Politics in a Progressive Age'' (2000) ch 9&lt;/ref&gt; 

There is general agreement that that the era was over by 1932, especially since a majority of the remaining progressives opposed the New Deal.&lt;ref&gt;Otis L. Graham, ''An Encore for Reform: The Old Progressives and the New Deal'' (1968)&lt;/ref&gt;

== Notable leaders of the Progressive Era ==
&lt;div  style=&quot;-moz-column-count:4; column-count:4;&quot;&gt;
*[[Jane Addams]], social work
*[[Susan B. Anthony]], suffragist
*[[Robert P. Bass]], New Hampshire politician
*[[Charles A. Beard]], historian and political scientist
*[[Louis Brandeis]], Supreme Court justice
*[[William Jennings Bryan]], Democratic presidential nominee in 1896, 1900, 1908
*[[Lucy Burns]], suffragist
*[[Andrew Carnegie]], steel magnate, philanthropist
*[[Carrie Chapman Catt]], [[suffragist]]
*[[Winston Churchill (novelist)]], author (not the British politician)
*[[Herbert Croly]], journalist
*[[John Dewey]], philosopher
*[[W. E. B. Du Bois]], Black scholar
*[[Thomas Edison]], inventor
*[[Irving Fisher]], economist
*[[Abraham Flexner]], education
*[[Henry Ford]], automaker
*[[Charlotte Perkins Gilman]], feminist
*[[Susan Glaspell]], playwright, novelist
*[[Emma Goldman]], anarchist, philosopher, writer
*[[Lewis Hine]], photographer
*[[Charles Evans Hughes]], statesman
*[[William James]], philosopher
*[[Hiram Johnson]], California politician
*[[Samuel M. Jones]], politician, reformer
*[[Florence Kelley]], child advocate
*[[Robert M. La Follette, Sr.]], Wisconsin politician
*[[Fiorello LaGuardia]], New York City mayor and brother of [[Ravensbruck concentration camp]] survivor [[Gemma LaGuardia Gluck]]
*[[Walter Lippmann]], journalist
*[[William James Mayo|Mayo Brothers]], medicine
*[[John R. Mott]], YMCA leader
*[[George Mundelein]], Catholic leader
*[[Alice Paul]], [[suffragist]]
*[[Ulrich B. Phillips]], historian
*[[Gifford Pinchot]], conservationist
*[[Walter Rauschenbusch]], theologian of [[Social Gospel]]
*[[Jacob Riis]], reformer
*[[John D. Rockefeller, Jr.]], philanthropist
*[[Theodore Roosevelt]], President
*[[Elihu Root]], statesman
*[[Margaret Sanger]], birth control
*[[Anna Howard Shaw]], suffragist
*[[Upton Sinclair]], novelist
*[[Albion Small]], sociologist
*[[Ellen Gates Starr]], sociologist
*[[Lincoln Steffens]], reporter
*[[Henry Stimson]], statesman
*[[William Howard Taft]], President and Chief Justice
*[[Ida Tarbell]], muckraker
*[[Frederick Winslow Taylor]], efficiency expert
*[[Frederick Jackson Turner]], historian
*[[Thorstein Veblen]], economist
*[[Lester Frank Ward]], sociologist
*[[Booker T. Washington]], Black leader, educator
*[[Woodrow Wilson]], President
*[[Ida B. Wells]], Black leader
&lt;/div&gt;

==See also==
*[[Trust-busting]]
*[[Upton Sinclair]], ''[[The Jungle]]'' (1906)
*[[Wisconsin Idea]]

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Further reading==

===Overviews===
* Buenker, John D., John C. Burnham, and Robert M. Crunden. ''Progressivism'' (1986)
* Buenker, John D. and Joseph Buenker, Eds. ''Encyclopedia of the Gilded Age and Progressive Era.'' Sharpe Reference, 2005. xxxii + 1256 pp. in three volumes. ISBN 0-7656-8051-3. 900 articles by 200 scholars
* Buenker, John D., ed. ''Dictionary of the Progressive Era'' (1980)
* Cocks, Catherine, Peter C. Holloran and Alan Lessoff. ''Historical Dictionary of the Progressive Era'' (2009)
* Diner, Steven J. ''A Very Different Age: Americans of the Progressive Era'' (1998)
* Glad, Paul W. &quot;Progressives and the Business Culture of the 1920s,&quot; ''Journal of American History,'' Vol. 53, No. 1. (June 1966), pp.&amp;nbsp;75–89. [http://www.jstor.org/pss/1893931 in JSTOR]
* Gould, Lewis L. ''America in the Progressive Era, 1890–1914&quot; (2000)
* Gould Lewis L. ed., ''The Progressive Era'' (1974)
* Hays, Samuel D. ''The Response to Industrialization, 1885–1914'' (1957),
* [[Richard Hofstadter|Hofstadter, Richard]], ''[[The Age of Reform]]'' (1954), Pulitzer Prize
* Jensen, Richard. &quot;Democracy, Republicanism and Efficiency:  The Values of American Politics, 1885–1930,&quot; in Byron Shafer and Anthony Badger, eds, ''Contesting Democracy: Substance and Structure in American Political History, 1775–2000'' (U of Kansas Press, 2001) pp 149–180; [http://www.uic.edu/~rjensen/rj0025.htm online version]
* [[David M. Kennedy (historian)|Kennedy, David M]]. ed., ''Progressivism: The Critical Issues'' (1971), readings
* Lasch, Christopher. ''The True and Only Heaven: Progress and its Critics'' (1991)
* [[William Leuchtenburg|Leuchtenburg, William E.]] &quot;Progressivism and Imperialism: The Progressive Movement and American Foreign Policy, 1898–1916,&quot; ''[[The Mississippi Valley Historical Review]],'' Vol. 39, No. 3. (Dec., 1952), pp.&amp;nbsp;483–504. [http://www.jstor.org/pss/1895006 JSTOR]
* Mann, Arthur. ed., ''The Progressive Era'' (1975)
* McGerr, Michael. ''A Fierce Discontent: The Rise and Fall of the Progressive Movement in America, 1870–1920'' (2003)
*Mowry, George. ''The Era of Theodore Roosevelt and the Birth of Modern America, 1900–1912.'' (1954) general survey of era
* Burl Noggle, &quot;The Twenties: A New Historiographical Frontier,&quot; ''The Journal of American History,'' Vol. 53, No. 2. (Sep., 1966), pp.&amp;nbsp;299–314. [http://www.jstor.org/pss/1894201 in JSTOR]
* Pease, Otis, ed. ''The Progressive Years: The Spirit and Achievement of American Reform'' (1962), primary documents
* Rodgers, Daniel T.  ''Atlantic Crossings: Social Politics in a Progressive Age'' (2000). stresses links with Europe [http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/text-idx?c=acls;cc=acls;view=toc;idno=heb00064.0001.001 online edition]
* Thelen, David P. &quot;Social Tensions and the Origins of Progressivism,&quot; ''Journal of American History'' 56 (1969), 323–341 online at JSTOR
* [[Robert Wiebe|Wiebe, Robert]]. ''The Search For Order, 1877–1920'' (1967).

===Presidents and politics===
* [[Howard K. Beale|Beale Howard K.]] ''Theodore Roosevelt and the Rise of America to World Power.'' (1956).
*[[John Morton Blum|Blum, John Morton.]] ''The Republican Roosevelt.'' (1954). Series of essays that examine how TR did politics
* Brands, H.W. ''Theodore Roosevelt'' (2001).
* Clements, Kendrick A. ''The Presidency of Woodrow Wilson'' (1992).
* Coletta, Paolo. ''The Presidency of William Howard Taft'' (1990).
* [[Cooper, John Milton]] ''The Warrior and the Priest: Woodrow Wilson and Theodore Roosevelt.'' (1983).
* Cooper, John Milton ''Woodrow Wilson: A Biography'' (2009)
* Gould, Lewis L. ''The Presidency of Theodore Roosevelt'' (1991).
* Harbaugh, William Henry. ''The Life and Times of Theodore Roosevelt.'' (1963).
* Harrison, Robert. ''Congress, Progressive Reform, and the New American State'' (2004).
* [[Richard Hofstadter|Hofstadter, Richard]]. ''The American Political Tradition'' (1948), ch. 8–9–10.
* [[Gabriel Kolko|Kolko, Gabriel]]. &quot;The Triumph of Conservatism&quot; (1963).
* [[Arthur S. Link|Link, Arthur Stanley]]. ''Woodrow Wilson and the Progressive Era, 1910–1917'' (1954).
* [[Edmund Morris (writer)|Morris, Edmund]] ''Theodore Rex''. (2001), biography of T. Roosevelt covers 1901–1909
* Mowry, George E. ''Theodore Roosevelt and the Progressive Movement''. (2001).
* Pestritto, R.J. &quot;Woodrow Wilson and the Roots of Modern Liberalism.&quot; (2005).
* Sanders, Elizabeth. ''Roots of Reform: Farmers, Workers and the American State, 1877–1917''  (1999).
* Wilson, Joan Hoff. ''Herbert Hoover, Forgotten Progressive'' (1965).

===State, local, ethnic, gender, business, labor, religion===
* Abell, Aaron I. ''American Catholicism and Social Action: A Search for Social Justice, 1865–1950'' (1960).
* Bruce, Kyle and Chris Nyland. &quot;Scientific Management, Institutionalism, and Business Stabilization: 1903–1923&quot; ''Journal of Economic Issues'', Vol. 35, 2001. [http://www.jstor.org/pss/4227725 in JSTOR]
* Buenker,  John D. ''Urban Liberalism and Progressive Reform'' (1973).
* Buenker,  John D. ''The History of Wisconsin, Vol. 4: The Progressive Era, 1893–1914'' (1998).
* Feffer, Andrew. ''The Chicago Pragmatists and American Progressivism'' (1993).
* Frankel, Noralee  and Nancy S. Dye, eds. ''Gender, Class, Race, and Reform in the Progressive Era'' (1991).
* Hahn, Steven. ''A Nation under Our Feet: Black Political Struggles in the Rural South from Slavery to the Great Migration''  (2003).
* Huthmacher, J. Joseph. &quot;Urban Liberalism and the Age of Reform&quot; ''Mississippi Valley Historical Review'' 49 (1962): 231–241, [http://www.jstor.org/pss/1888628  in JSTOR]; emphasized urban, ethnic, working class support for reform
* Link, William A. ''The Paradox of Southern Progressivism, 1880–1930'' (1992).
* Montgomery, David. ''The Fall of the House of Labor: The workplace, the state, and American labor activism, 1865–1925'' (1987).
* Muncy, Robyn. ''Creating A Feminine Dominion in American Reform, 1890–1935'' (1991).
* Lubove, Roy. ''The Progressives and the Slums: Tenement House Reform in New York City, 1890–1917'' Greenwood Press: 1974.
* Recchiuti, John Louis.  ''Civic Engagement: Social Science and Progressive-Era Reform in New York City'' (2007).
* Stromquist, Shelton. ''Reinventing 'The People': The Progressive Movement, the Class Problem, and the Origins of Modern Liberalism,'' (U. of Illinois Press, 2006). ISBN 0-252-07269-3.
* Thelen, David. ''The New Citizenship, Origins of Progressivism in Wisconsin, 1885–1900'' (1972).
* Wesser, Robert F. ''Charles Evans Hughes: politics and reform in New York, 1905–1910'' (1967).
* Wiebe, Robert. &quot;Business Disunity and the Progressive Movement, 1901–1914,&quot; ''The Mississippi Valley Historical Review,'' Vol. 44, No. 4. (Mar., 1958), pp.&amp;nbsp;664–685. [http://www.jstor.org/pss/1886602 in JSTOR]

{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2011}}
{{US history}}
{{United States topics}}

[[Category:Eras of United States history]]
[[Category:Progressivism in the United States|*]]
[[Category:Political philosophy]]
[[Category:Social ethics]]
[[Category:Progressive Era in the United States|*]]

[[fr:Ère progressiste]]
[[ja:進歩主義時代 (アメリカ合衆国)]]
[[pl:Era postępowa]]
[[ru:Эра прогрессивизма]]
[[sv:Progressiva eran]]
[[zh:进步时代]]</text>
      <sha1>blol56fjlhssde9x1xcg3atgtunum2e</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
