<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Provisional ballot</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1128897</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521748043</id>
      <parentid>521739024</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-06T23:40:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Wing gundam</username>
        <id>4176030</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* History */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="5791">{{Expert-subject|Politics|date=February 2009}}
{{globalize|date=December 2010}}
{{voting}}
A '''provisional ballot''' is used to record a vote when there are questions in regards to a given [[Voter eligibility|voter's eligibility]].  A provisional ballot would be cast when:
*The voter refuses to show a photo ID (in regions that require one)
*The voter's name does not appear on the [[electoral roll]] for the given precinct.
*The voter's registration contains inaccurate or out-dated information such as the wrong address or a misspelled name.
*The voter's ballot has already been recorded
Whether a provisional ballot is counted is contingent upon the verification of that voter's eligibility. Many voters do not realize that the provisional ballot is not counted until 7–10 days after election so their vote does not affect the calling of the states to different candidates.

A guarantee that a voter could cast a provisional ballot if he or she believes that they are entitled to vote was one of the guarantees of the [[Help America Vote Act]] of 2002.

==History==
The right of [[political parties]] to have observers at [[polling place]]s is old.&lt;ref&gt;Title XIV, Chapter 5, Sec. 4922, [http://www.archive.org/details/electionlawsofst00ohiorich The Election Laws of the State of Ohio], Ohio Secretary of State, 1920.&lt;/ref&gt;  One of the established roles for such observers is to act as challengers, in the event that someone attempts to vote at the polling place who is not eligible to vote.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sos.state.mn.us/docs/challenger_faq_2008.pdf Election Day &quot;Challengers&quot;], [http://www.sos.state.mn.us/ Minnesota Secretary of State], June 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

When a voter's right to vote was challenged, state laws typically
allowed them to cast a ''challenged ballot''.  After the polls closed, the canvassing board was then charged with examining the challenged ballots and determining whether the challenge was to be upheld or not.&lt;ref&gt;Greg Brown, [www.earlcarl.org/publications/provisional%20ballots.pdf The Provisional Ballot vs. Challenged Ballot], Nov. 16, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

The right to a provisional ballot, as enacted by the Help America Vote Act, brings a degree of uniformity to the array of various challenged ballot rules enacted by various states.

==Potential problems==

At their best, provisional ballots provide voters who would otherwise be turned away from the polls to have their votes counted, but at their worst, the offer of a provisional ballot can be &quot;a way to brush off troublesome voters by letting them think they have voted.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Douglas W. Jones]], [http://www.cs.uiowa.edu/~jones/voting/cbc2004.shtml Reliability of US Voting Systems], Prepared Remarks for the [[Congressional Black Caucus]] Hearing on election preparedness
October 7, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; It is possible for parties to force certain voters to cast provisional ballots so they can suppress the vote total of an opponent being counted on election night.

In the [[2004 US Presidential Election]], controversy arose out of arguments regarding the interpretation of the criteria for determining the eligibility of voters using provisional ballots. Many allege that these discrepancies of interpretations, particularly in [[Ohio]], may have been a deciding factor in the outcome of the election. In the 2004 election, at least 1.9 million provisional ballots were cast, and 676,000 were never counted due to various states' rules on counting provisional ballots.&lt;ref&gt;[http://nationaljournal.com/about/njweekly/stories/2006/1103nj1.htm Let The Recounts Begin (National Journal)]&lt;/ref&gt;

Studies of the use of provisional ballots in the [[United States general elections, 2006|2006 general election in the United States]] show that around 21% of provisional ballots were rejected, where the majority of rejected ballots were cast by registered voters and the majority of rejections were for reasons that were preventable.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.advancementproject.org/pdfs/Provisional-Ballot-Report-Final-9-16-08.pdf Provisional Voting: Fail-Safe Voting or Trapdoor to Disenfranchisement], [http://www.advancementproject.org/ Advancement Project], Sept. 16, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

==Number of provisional ballots not counted in US elections==

According to the Election Assistance Commission thousands of provisional ballots are not counted each election.

'''''2004 US Election'''''

In the 2004 US Election 35.5 percent of all provisional ballots cast were discarded for various reasons. This meant a total of 675,676 votes were not counted. See 2004 EAC report [http://www.eac.gov/clearinghouse/2004-election-day-survey/ here.]

'''''2006 US Election'''''

In the 2006 US Election 20.5 percent of all provisional ballots cast were discarded for various reasons. This meant a total of 170,872 votes which were cast provisionally were not counted. See 2006 EAC report [http://www.eac.gov/News/press/clearinghouse/2006-election-administration-and-voting-survey here].

===Reasons for rejection===

The most common reason for rejection of provisional ballots is due to voters who have been purged off the voting rolls. 44 percent of those provisional ballots rejected in 2006 were due to this factor. {{Citation needed|date=November 2012}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.enquirer.com/midday/11/11032004_News_mday_ohprez04.html &quot;Provisional ballots could decide election&quot;] (''[[The Cincinnati Enquirer]]'')
*[http://www.gregpalast.com/kerry-won-ohio-rn-just-count-the-ballots-at-the-back-of-the-bus &quot;KERRY WON OHIO - JUST COUNT THE BALLOTS AT THE BACK OF THE BUS&quot;] (by [[Greg Palast]])
*[http://media.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A20565-2004Nov3.html &quot;20 Crucial Electoral Votes May Be Stuck in Limbo&quot;] (''[[Washington Post]]'')

{{DEFAULTSORT:Provisional Ballot}}
[[Category:Elections]]</text>
      <sha1>ck76ia3im6wadb63vk7u20qk243k1vt</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
