<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Public participation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5265708</id>
    <revision>
      <id>515559904</id>
      <parentid>506087028</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-02T02:08:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DASonnenfeld</username>
        <id>2922608</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Environment and Sustainable Development */ mce</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18738">'''Public participation''' is a political principle or practice, and may also be recognised as a right ('''right to public participation'''). The terms public participation may be used interchangeably with the concept or practice of [[stakeholder engagement]] and/or popular participation.

Generally public participation seeks and facilitates the involvement of those potentially affected by or interested in a decision. The principle of public participation holds that those who are affected by a decision have a right to be involved in the decision-making process. Public participation implies that the public's contribution will influence the decision.&lt;ref name=&quot;test&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iap2.org/displaycommon.cfm?an=4 |title=IAP2 Core Values for the Practice of Public Participation |publisher=Iap2.org |date= |accessdate=2012-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.co-intelligence.org/CIPol_publicparticipation.html |title=Principles of Public Participation |publisher=Co-intelligence.org |date=2008-05-23 |accessdate=2012-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Public participation may be regarded as a way of [[empowerment]] and as vital part of democratic governance.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;

In the context of [[knowledge management]] the establishment of ongoing '''participatory processes''' is seen by some in the facilitator of [[collective intelligence]] and inclusiveness, shaped by the desire for the participation of the whole community or society.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;

Public participation is part of “people centred” or &quot;human centric&quot; principles, which have emerged in [[Western world|Western]] culture over the last thirty
years, and has had some bearings of [[education]], [[business]], [[public policy]] and international relief and development programs. Public participation is advanced by the [[humanism|humanist]] movements. Public participation may be advanced as part of a “people first” paradigm shift. In this respect public participation may challenge the concept that &quot;big is better&quot; and the logic of centralized
hierarchies, advancing alternative concepts of “more heads are better than one” and arguing that public participation can sustain productive and durable change.&lt;ref name=autogenerated4&gt;[http://www.usaid.gov/our_work/cross-cutting_programs/transition_initiatives/pubs/ptdv1000.pdf ]{{dead link|date=August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The role of public participation in economic and human development was enshrined in the 1990 [[African Charter for Popular Participation in Development and Transformation]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.africaaction.org/african-initiatives/chartall.htm African Charter for Popular Participation in Development and Transformation]{{dead link|date=August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Public policy ==
In some countries public participation has become a central principle of [[public policy]] making. In the [[UK]] it has been observed that all levels of [[government]] have started to build [[citizen]] and [[stakeholder engagement]] into their policy-making processes. This may involve large-scale [[Public consultation|consultation]]s, [[focus group]] research, online discussion forums, or deliberative citizens' juries. There are many different public participation mechanisms, although these often share common features (for a list over 100, and a typology of mechanisms, see Rowe and Frewer, 2005).&lt;ref&gt;Rowe, G. and Frewer, L.J. (2005) A typology of public engagement mechanisms, Science, Technology, &amp; Human Values, 30 (2), 251-290.&lt;/ref&gt;

Public participation is viewed as a tool, intended to inform planning, organising or funding of activities. Public participation may also be used to measure attainable objectives, evaluate impact, and identify lessons for future practice.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.involve.org.uk/evaluation/ ]{{dead link|date=August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In the [[USA]] public participation in administrative rulemaking refers to the process by which proposed rules are subject to public comment for a specified period of time. Public participation is typically mandatory for rules promulgated by executive agencies of the US government.  Statutes or agency policies may mandate [[public hearing]]s during this period.

== Participatory budgeting ==
{{main|Participatory budgeting}}
Participatory budgeting is a process of democratic deliberation and decision-making, in which ordinary city residents decide how to allocate part of a municipal or public budget. Participatory budgeting is usually characterized by several basic design features: identification of spending priorities by community members, election of budget delegates to represent different communities, facilitation and technical assistance by public employees, local and higher level assemblies to deliberate and vote on spending priorities, and the implementation of local direct-impact community projects.
Participatory budgeting may be used by towns and cities around the world, and has been widely publicised in [[Porto Alegre]], [[Brazil]], were the first full participatory budgeting process was developed starting in 1989.

== Public trust ==
In recent years loss of public trust in authorities and politicians  has become a widespread concern in many democratic societies. Public participation is a regarded as one potential solution to the crisis in public trust and governance, particularly in the [[UK]], Europe, and other democracies. The idea is that public should be involved more fully in the policy process in that authorities seek public views and participation, instead of treating the public as simply passive recipients of policy decisions.  

The underlying assumption by political theorists, social commentators, and even politicians is that public participation increase public trust in authorities, improving citizen political efficacy, enhancing democratic ideals and even improving the quality of policy decisions. However, the assumed benefits of public participation in restoring public trust are yet to be confirmed.&lt;ref&gt;Rowe, G. and Frewer, L.J. (2000) Public participation methods: A framework for evaluation, Science, Technology, &amp; Human Values, 25 (1), 3-29.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rowe, G. and Gammack, J.G. (2004) Promise and perils of electronic public engagement, Science and Public Policy, 31 (1), 39-54.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ifr.ac.uk/Science/Partnership/RCS/public_perception.html |title=Public participation (science in society) |publisher=Ifr.ac.uk |date= |accessdate=2012-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Accountability and transparency==
{{main|Radical transparency}}
Public participation may also be viewed as accountability enhancing. The argument being that public participation can be a means for the participating communities to hold public authorities accountable for implementation.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt;Nazrul Islam, Nazrul Isable Martinez and Wang Xi, &quot;Environmental Law in Developing Countries: Selected Issues, IUCN, 2002, pg.7&lt;/ref&gt;

== Participatory development ==
In economic development theory the school of [[participatory development]]. The desire to increase public participation in humanitarian aid and development has led to the establishment of a numerous context-specific, formal methodologies, matrices,
pedagogies and ad hoc approaches. These include conscientization and praxis; [[Participatory action research]] (PPA), [[Participatory rural appraisal|rapid rural appraisal]] (RRA) and participatory rural appraisal (PRA); [[appreciation influence control analysis]] (AIC); “open space” approaches; [[Objectives Oriented Project Planning]] (ZOPP); [[vulnerability analysis]] and [[capacity analysis]].&lt;ref name=autogenerated4 /&gt;

== Environment and sustainable development ==
In recent years public participation has become to be seen as a vital part of addressing environmental problems and bringing about [[sustainable development]]. In this context the limits of solely relying on technocratic bureaucratic monopoly of decision making, and it is argued that public participation allows governments to adopt policies and enact laws that are relevant to communities and take into account their needs.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt;  

Public participation is recognised as an environmental principle, see [[Environmental Principles and Policies]], and has been enshrined in the [[Rio Declaration]].

=== Public participation in environmental governance ===
With growing complexities of the environmental issues, public participation has come to the fore in academic analysis concerning the contemporary debates about [[environmental governance]]. 

There have emerged a number of arguments in favour of a more participatory approach, which stress that public participation is a crucial element in environmental governance that contributes to better [[Decision-making|decision making]]. It is recognised that environmental problems cannot be solved by government alone.&lt;ref&gt;Pring, G. and Noé, S.Y. (2002) 'The Emerging International Law of Public Participation Affecting Global Mining, Energy, and Resource Development' in Zillman, D.M., Lucas, A. and Pring, G.(eds) ''Human Rights in Natural Resource Development: Public Participation in the Sustainable Development of Mining and Energy Resources'', Oxford University Press, Oxford, P 76.&lt;/ref&gt; Participation in environmental decision-making effectively links the public to environmental governance. By involving the public, who are at the root of both causes and solutions of environmental problems, in environmental discussions, transparency and accountability are more likely to be achieved, thus secures the democratic legitimacy of decision-making that good environmental governance depends on.&lt;ref name=&quot;two&quot;&gt;Bulkeley, H. and Mol, A.P.J. (2003), 'Participation and Environmental Governance: Consensus, Ambivalence and Debate', ''Environmental Values'' '''12''' (2): 143–54.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://globalnation.inquirer.net/cebudailynews/opinion/view/20080721-149784/Public-participation-in-Environmental-Governance |title=Ramos, G. Public participation in Environmental Governance |publisher=Globalnation.inquirer.net |date=2008-07-21 |accessdate=2012-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; Arguably, a strong public participation in environmental governance could increase the commitment among stockholders, which strengthens the compliance and enforcement of environmental laws. In addition, some opponents argue that the right to participate in environmental decision-making is a procedural right that “can be seen as part of the fundamental right to environmental protection”.&lt;ref name=&quot;four&quot;&gt;Du Plessis, A. (2008), ‘Public Participation, Good Environmental Governance and Fulfillment of Environmental Rights’, ''Potchefstroom Electronic Law Journal'', '''11'''(2): 170-201.(4)&lt;/ref&gt; From this ethical perspective, environmental governance is expected to operate within a framework coinciding the &quot;constitutional principle of fairness (inclusive of equality)&quot;, which inevitably requires the fulfillment of &quot;environmental rights&quot; and ultimately calls for the engagement of public.&lt;ref name=&quot;four&quot; /&gt; Further, in the context of considerable scientific uncertainties surrounding environmental issues, public participation helps to counter such uncertainties and bridges the gap between scientifically-defined environmental problems and the experiences and values of stakeholders.&lt;ref name=&quot;two&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fischer, F. (2000) ''Citizens, Experts and the Environment'', Durham, NC: Duke University Press, p.222.&lt;/ref&gt; Through joint effort of the government and scientists in collaboration with the public, better governance of environment is expected to be achieved by making the most appropriate decision possible.

Although broad agreements exist, the notion of public participation in environmental decision-making has been subject to a sustained critique concerning the real outcome of participatory environmental governance. Critics argue that public participation tends to focus on reaching a consensus between actors who share the same values and seek the same outcomes. However, the uncertain nature of many of the environmental issues would undermine the validity of public participation, given that in many cases the actors come to the table of discussion hold very different perceptions of the problem and solution which are unlikely to be welded into a consensus due to the incommensurability of different positions.&lt;ref&gt;Pellizzoni, L. (2003): ‘Uncertainty and Participatory Democracy’, ''Environmental Values'' '''12'''(2): 195-224.&lt;/ref&gt; This may run the risk of expert bias, which generates further exclusion as those who are antagonistic to the consensus would be marginalised in the environmental decision-making process, which violates the assumed advantage of participatory approach to produce democratic environmental decisions. This raises the further question of whether consensus should be the measure of a successful outcome of participation.&lt;ref&gt;Owens, S. (2000). ‘Engaging the public: information and deliberation in environmental policy’, ''Environment and Planning A'', 32: 1141–8.&lt;/ref&gt; As Davies suggests, participative democracy could not guarantee the substantive environmental benefits ‘if there are competing views of what the environment should be like and what it is valuable for’.&lt;ref&gt;Davies, A. (2001). ‘What silence knows – planning, public participation and environmental values’, ''Environmental Values'', 10: 77–102.&lt;/ref&gt; Consequently, who should be involved at what points in the process of environmental decision-making and what is the goal of this kind of participation become central to the debates on public participation as a key issue in environmental governance.&lt;ref name=&quot;two&quot; /&gt;

== Right to public participation ==
In some jurisdictions the right to public participation is enshrined by law. The right to public participation may also be conceived of as [[human right]], or as manifestation of the right to [[freedom of association]] and [[freedom of assembly]]. As such the [[Netherlands]], [[Germany]], [[Denmark]] and [[Sweden]], have public participation and [[freedom of information]] provisions in their legal systems since before the Middle Ages.&lt;ref name=autogenerated3&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.encora.eu/coastalwiki/Public_participation_legislation |title=Public participation legislation - Coastal Wiki |publisher=Encora.eu |date= |accessdate=2012-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Democracy]] and public participation are closely connected democratic societies have incorporated public participation rights into their laws for centuries. For example, in the US the right to petition has been part of the first Amendment of the [[US constitution]] since 1791.&lt;ref name=autogenerated3 /&gt; More recently, since the 1970s in New Zealand numerous laws (e.g.: health, local government, environmental management) require government officials to &quot;consult&quot; those affected by a matter and take their views into consideration when making decisions.  

Effective public participation depends on the public having accessing to accurate and comprehensive information. Hence laws regarding public participation often deal with the issue of the [[right to know]], access of information and [[freedom of information]].&lt;ref name=autogenerated3 /&gt;

The right to participation may also be advanced in the context of [[Equality of opportunity|equality]] and [[group rights]], meant to ensure equal and full participation of a designated group in society. For example in the context of disabled people.

=== Rio Declaration on Environment and Development ===
{{main|Rio Declaration on Environment and Development}}
The [[Rio Declaration]] of 1992 enshrines public participation in its 27 principles. Principle 10 states that &quot;environmental issues are best handled with participation of all concerned citizens, at the relevant level”. The [[Rio Declaration]] continues, drawing a close link between access to information and public participation: &lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;At the national level, each individual shall have appropriate access to information concerning the environment that is held by public authorities, including information on hazardous materials and activities in their communities, and the opportunity to participate in decision-making processes. States shall facilitate and encourage public awareness and participation by making information widely available. Effective access to judicial and administrative proceedings, including redress and remedy, shall be provided.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unep.org/Documents.Multilingual/Default.asp?DocumentID=78&amp;ArticleID=1163 |title=Rio Declaration - Rio Declaration on Environment and Development - United Nations Environment Programme |publisher=UNEP |date= |accessdate=2012-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

=== Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities ===
{{main|Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities}}
The 2006 [[Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities]] recognised that &quot;disability results from the interaction between persons with impairments and attitudinal and environmental barriers that hinders their full and effective participation in society on an equal basis with others&quot; and that &quot;persons with disabilities continue to face barriers in their participation as equal members of society.&quot; 

The Convention makes participation of disabled one of its principles, stating &quot;The principles of the present Convention shall be:...Full and effective participation and inclusion in society;&quot;, subsequently enshrining the right of disabled to participate fully and equally in the community, education, all aspect of life (in the context of habilitation and [[Physical medicine and rehabilitation|rehabilitation]]), political and public life, cultural life, leisure and sports.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/disabilities/convention/conventionfull.shtml |title=Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities |publisher=Un.org |date=2007-03-30 |accessdate=2012-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Counter-mapping]]
* [[Deliberative democracy]]
* [[Involve (think tank)]]
* [[Neighborhood planning]]
* [[Participatory economics]]
* [[Participatory GIS]]
* [[Participatory justice]]
* [[Progress in Community Health Partnerships|''Progress in Community Health Partnerships: Research, Education, and Action (PCHP)'']]
* [[Public participation in patent examination]]
* [[Strategic lawsuit against public participation]]
* [[Visual preference survey]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

{{Articles of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights}}
{{Substantive human rights}}

[[Category:Government]]

[[de:Bürgerbeteiligung]]
[[et:Üldsuse osalemine]]
[[es:Participación ciudadana]]
[[pt:Participação pública]]
[[zh:公眾參與]]</text>
      <sha1>lrcwdt2qjkt8y40s172p1kh311aaw4q</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
