<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Purple Rain Protest</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5868531</id>
    <revision>
      <id>509269462</id>
      <parentid>500166438</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-08-26T16:27:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dl2000</username>
        <id>917223</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>unify formatting per [[WP:MOSNUM|MoS]], script-assisted (ZAF subject)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7305">{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2012}}
{{Use South African English|date=August 2012}}
The '''Purple Rain Protest''', '''Purple Rain Revolt''' or '''Purple Rain Riot''' was an anti-[[apartheid]] protest held in [[Cape Town]] on 2 September 1989, four days before [[South Africa]]'s racially segregated parliament held its [[South African general election, 1989|elections]].  A police water cannon with purple dye was turned on thousands of [[Mass Democratic Movement]] supporters who poured into the city in an attempt to march on South Africa's Parliament. White office blocks adjacent to [[Greenmarket Square]] were sprayed purple four stories high as a protester leapt onto the roof of the [[water cannon]] vehicle, seized the nozzle and attempted to turn the jet away from the crowds.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1989&quot;&gt; Weekend Argus, &quot;Purple Rain halts city demo&quot;, front page, Saturday, 2 September 1989&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Purpcover.jpg|right|250px|thumb|Cover of &quot;Die Suid-Afrikaan&quot;, showing purple rain shower]]
One of the dyed buildings was the Cape Headquarters of the [[National Party (South Africa)|National Party]]. The historic Town House, a national monument, was sprayed purple and the force of the jet smashed windows in the Central Methodist Church.

[[Tear gas]] was fired and the crowd that had knelt defiantly in the purple jet fled. Adderley Street was closed to traffic as scores of shops and businesses closed their doors and hundreds of people were arrested, including Dr [[Allan Boesak]], [[University of Cape Town|UCT]] academic Dr Charles Villa-Vincencia, Western Cape Council of Churches official Rev. Pierre van den Heever and lawyer Essa Moosa.

==Climax==
The police were using a new water cannon with purple dye whose purpose was to stain protestors for later identification and [[arrest]].&lt;ref name=Leibenluft&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.slate.com/id/2193473/
|title=Purple Water Cannons: Why would the police spray protesters with colored water?
|first=Jacob
|last=Leibenluft
|publisher=Slate
|date=2008-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Protesters were warned to disperse, but instead knelt in the street.  When the cannon was turned on them, some protestors remained kneeling while others fled; some had their feet knocked out from under them by the force of the jet. In Adderley Street, shoppers ran for cover, their eyes streaming, and a young couple with a baby in a pram were hurriedly ushered into a shop which then locked its doors.

A lone protestor redirected the water cannon toward the local headquarters of the ruling [[National Party (South Africa)|National Party]].{{Dubious|date=March 2010}} The headquarters, along with the historic, white-painted [[Old Town House (Cape Town)|Old Town House]], overlooking [[Greenmarket Square]], were doused with purple dye.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=57gyw36xwk8C|title=Every Step of the Way: The Journey to Freedom in South Africa|author=Michael Morris, John Linnegar|location=South Africa|publisher=HSRC Press|year=2004|isbn=0-7969-2061-3|page=223}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A group of about 50 protesters streaming with purple dye, ran from Burg Street, down to the parade. They were followed by another group of clergymen and others who were stopped in Plein Street. Some were then arrested. On the Parade, a large contingent of policemen arrested everyone they could find who had purple dye on them. When they were booed by the crowd, police dispersed them. About 250 people marching under a banner stating &quot;The People Shall Govern&quot; dispersed at the intersection of Darling Street and Sir Lowry Road after being stopped by police. &lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1989&quot;/&gt;

==Graffiti==
After the riot, somebody sprayed graffiti that would make it into the history books. The [[Cape Times]] told it this way:{{Cite quote|date=March 2010}}

{{cquote|Graffiti artists at the weekend sprayed several Cape Town suburban railway stations with slogans reading: Release our leaders, Free our leaders, unban the ANC and Forward to purple people's power, -- a reference to the police use of purple dye in the water cannon directed against demonstrators....}}

Another piece of anti-apartheid graffiti, &quot;'''The purple shall govern'''&quot;, appeared on the old Townhouse in Greenmarket Square.  The statement is play on words of the [[Freedom Charter]]'s declaration that &quot;The people shall govern&quot;.

The slogan was used as the title of a book, &quot;The Purple shall govern: a South African A to Z of nonviolent action&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=hlQxAAAAIAAJ|author=Dene Smuts, Shauna Westcott, Margaret Nash|publisher=Oxford University Press, Centre for Intergroup Studies|year=1991|title=The Purple Shall Govern: a South African A to Z of Nonviolent Action}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Comments==
&quot;What about the purple people?&quot; a reader asked the Cape Times' Teleletters. &quot;Not only has the government messed up with the [[Tricameral Parliament|tricameral system]], now their police have created another problem. They, the government, have made 'provision' for the so-called coloureds and Indians -- how are they going to accommodate the 'purple people? Perhaps the next time they use their water cannon, they would like to consult with their voters as to which colour is fashionable.&quot; &lt;ref&gt; New House for purple people?, Cape Times, 5 September 1989&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;Who's going to pay for the city's day of purple spray?&quot; asked Don Holliday of the [[Cape Argus]]. &quot;As the controversy continues over who is to pay for the clean-up of buildings, streets, cars and clothing sprayed purple by police during Saturday's Mass Democratic Movement's attempted march to parliament, police announced that they would release details of the effects of the dye.&quot; &lt;ref&gt; The [[Cape Argus]], font page, Tuesday 5 September 1989&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;A spokesperson for the police directorate of public relations said they had approached their forensic science division to prepare a report on the effects of the dye -- including whether it would eventually wash off and possible solutions for washing.&quot;

A later statement reported that the dye was a &quot;harmless substance&quot; which was mixed with water and could be washed off clothing with soap and water. Walls sprayed with the dye could be cleaned using a mixture of one part hydrochloric acid to 100 parts water and then rinsed.

The Rev. Herbert Brand of the [[Dutch Reformed Church in South Africa|Dutch Reformed Church]]{{Disambiguation needed|date=June 2011}} was inspired by the &quot;purple drama&quot; as well as the 50th anniversary of the start of WW2 to deliver a passionate sermon on &quot;fascism in the city&quot;. &lt;ref&gt; Cape Times, Tuesday, 5 September 1989, pg9&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[1989 in South Africa]]
*[[Activism]]
*[[Civil disobedience]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

==External links==
*[http://heritage.thetimes.co.za/memorials/WC/ThePurpleShallGovern/ &quot;The Purple Shall Govern&quot;] - the [[Sunday Times]]' memorial page for the protest, including the [http://heritage.thetimes.co.za/Media.aspx?videoid=674&amp;width=720&amp;height=590 only existing video footage of the event].

[[Category:1989 in South Africa]]
[[Category:Activism]]
[[Category:History of Cape Town]]
[[Category:Civil disobedience]]
[[Category:Events associated with apartheid]]
[[Category:Protests in South Africa]]

{{Coord|33|55|20|S|18|25|14|E|display=title|region:ZA_type:event}}</text>
      <sha1>akikdjer02hkhnjonicr1r078uwgp50</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
