<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Realigning election</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>440517</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522022975</id>
      <parentid>521729886</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-08T16:35:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Robofish</username>
        <id>794371</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>removed recursive link</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="68882">'''Realigning election''' (often called a '''critical election'''  or '''political realignment''') are terms from [[political science]] and [[political history]] describing a dramatic change in the [[political system]]. Scholars frequently apply the term to American elections and occasionally to other countries. Usually it means the coming to power for several decades of a new coalition, replacing an old dominant coalition of the other party as in 1896 when the GOP (Republicans) became dominant, or 1932 when the Democrats became dominant. More specifically, it refers to American national elections in which there are sharp changes in issues, party leaders, the regional and demographic bases of power of the two parties, and structure or rules of the political system (such as voter eligibility or financing), resulting in a new political power structure that lasts for decades.

Realigning elections typically separate [[Party Systems]]--with 1828, for example, separating the [[First Party System]] and the [[Second Party System]] in the U.S. 

Political realignments can be sudden (1–4 years) or can take place more gradually (5–20 years). Most often, however, particularly in [[V._O._Key,_Jr.|Key]]'s (1955) original hypothesis, it is a single &quot;critical election&quot; that marks a realignment. By contrast a gradual process is called a &quot;secular realignment.&quot; An American example was the change in the voting patterns among white Southerners, who from the 1870s to 1962 had overwhelmingly voted at the national and state levels for Democratic (what was called the &quot;Solid South&quot;). A critical election came in 1964 with a shift at the presidential level to the Republican (GOP) presidential candidates. However there was a gradual shift toward the GOP at the state and local levels, as Aldrich (2000) and others have found. Democratic voting remained strong into the 1970s and only slowly shifted towards the GOP as state Republican organizations systematically broadened their base in the 1980s and 1990s.&lt;ref&gt;Jenkins et al. 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

Political scientists and historians often disagree about which elections are realignments and what defines a realignment, and even whether realignments occur. The terms themselves are somewhat arbitrary, however, and usage among political scientists and historians does vary. 

In the U.S. [[Walter Dean Burnham]] argued for a 30–36 year &quot;cycle&quot; of realignments. Many of the elections often included in the Burnham 36-year cycle are considered &quot;realigning&quot; for different reasons. Some political scientists, such as Mayhew (2004), are skeptical of the realignment theory altogether, saying there are no long-term patterns: &quot;Electoral politics,&quot; he writes, &quot;is to an important degree just one thing after another.... Elections and their underlying causes are not usefully sortable into generation-long spans.... It is a [[Rip Van Winkle]] view of democracy that voters come awake only once in a generation.... It is too slippery, too binary, too apocalyptic, and it has come to be too much of a dead end.&quot;

==Realignment theory==
The central holding of realignment theory, first developed in the political scientist [[V. O. Key, Jr.]]'s 1955 article, &quot;A Theory of Critical Elections,&quot; is that American elections, parties and policymaking routinely shift in swift, dramatic sweeps.

V.O. Key Jr., [[Elmer Eric Schattschneider|E.E. Schattschneider]], [[James L. Sundquist]], [[Walter Dean Burnham]] and [[Paul Kleppner]] are generally credited with developing and refining the theory of realignment.&lt;ref&gt;Schafer (1991); Rosenof (2003)&lt;/ref&gt;  Though they differed on some of the details, scholars have generally concluded that systematic patterns are identifiable in American national elections such that cycles occur on a regular schedule: once every 36-years or so. This period of roughly 30 years fits with the notion that these cycles are closely linked to generational change. For social scientists, this point is important, since it helps to provide an objective sociological basis for the theory. Some, such as Schafer and Reichley, argue that the patterns are longer, closer to 50 to 60 years in duration, noting the Democratic dominance from 1800 to 1860, and Republican rule from 1860 to 1932.

The alignment of 1860, with Republicans winning a series of close presidential elections, yielded abruptly in 1896 to an era of more decisive GOP control, in which most presidential elections were blowouts, and Democratic Congresses were infrequent and brief. Thirty-six years later, that system was displaced by a cycle of Democratic dominance, lasting throughout the [[Great Depression]] and beyond.&lt;ref&gt;Sundquist (1982); Rosenof (2003)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Voter realignment==
A central component of realignment is the change in behavior of voting groups. Realignment means the switching of voter preference from one party to another, in contrast to ''dealignment'' (where a voter group abandons a party to become independent or nonvoting). In the U.S. and Australia, as the ideologies of the parties define many of the aspects of voters' lives and the decisions that they make, a realignment by a voter tends to have a longer-lasting effect. In Britain and Canada, on the other hand, voters have a tendency to switch parties on a whim, perhaps only for one election, as there is far less loyalty towards a particular party.

==United States==
===Realigning elections in United States history===
Here is presented a list of elections most often cited as &quot;realigning,&quot; with disagreements noted:
*[[United States presidential election, 1800]] — [[Thomas Jefferson]]
** This election completed the turnover of power from the [[Federalist Party]], embodied in [[Alexander Hamilton]], to [[Thomas Jefferson]] and his [[Democratic-Republican Party]]. Power shifted from [[New England]] to the [[Southern United States|South]].
** Democratic-Republicans gained 19.7% of House seats in 1800, 9.4% in 1802 and 9.7% in 1804, for a total gain of 38.8% in 3 elections.
** As late as 1812, the Federalists came within one state of winning. A larger shift in electoral politics arguably came in the 1812–1816 period, as the Federalists became discredited after opposing the [[War of 1812]].

*[[United States presidential election, 1828]] — [[Andrew Jackson]]
** This election redefined the party system in the United States. The Democratic-Republicans split into two parties, later renamed as the [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic Party]] and the [[Whig Party (United States)|Whig Party]]. The Democrats were led by [[Andrew Jackson]] of Tennessee and [[Martin Van Buren]] of New York. By 1834 the Whigs emerged as the opposition to Andrew Jackson, led by [[Henry Clay]] of Kentucky.&lt;ref name=&quot;silbey&quot;&gt;Silbey (1991)&lt;/ref&gt;

*[[United States presidential election, 1860]] — [[Abraham Lincoln]]
** After the Whigs collapsed after 1852, party alignments were in turmoil, with several third parties, such as the [[Know Nothing]]s and the [[Opposition Party (United States)|Opposition Party]]. The system stabilized in 1858 and the presidential election marked the ascendence of the [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party]]. Abraham Lincoln beat out three other contenders — but even if they had somehow united he still had the majority of the electoral vote. The Republican party was pledged to the long-term ending of slavery, which was proximate cause of secession. Republicans rallied around nationalism in 1861 and fought the [[American Civil War]] to end secession. During the war the Republicans, under Lincoln's leadership, switched to a goal of short-term ending of slavery.&lt;ref name=&quot;silbey&quot;/&gt;  By 1864, the Republicans had a coalition built around followers of the &quot;free labor&quot; ideology, as well as soldiers and veterans of the [[Union Army]] (Since then, the military establishment has been solidly Republican).
**** The Republican Party went from 18.3% of the House in 1854, to 38.0% in 1856, 48.7% in 1858, and 59.0% in 1860, for a total gain of 59.0% in 4 elections.&lt;ref&gt;Michael F. Holt, ''The Political Crisis of the 1850s'' (1978)&lt;/ref&gt;

*[[United States presidential election, 1896]] — [[William McKinley]]
** The status of this election is hotly disputed; some political scientists, such as Jerome Clubb, do not consider it a realigning election. Other political scientists and historians, such as Kleppner and Burnham consider this the ultimate realignment and emphasize that the rules of the game had changed, the leaders were new, voting alignments had changed, and a whole new set of issues came to dominance as the old Civil-War-Era issues faded away. Funding from office holders was replaced by outside fund raising from business in 1896 — a major shift in political history. Furthermore McKinley's tactics in beating [[William Jennings Bryan]] (as developed by [[Mark Hanna]]) marked a sea change in the evolution of the modern campaigning. McKinley raised a huge amount of money from business interests, outspending Bryan by 10 to 1. Bryan meanwhile invented the modern technique of campaigning heavily in closely contested states, the first candidate to do so.&lt;ref&gt;Robert J. Dinkin, ''Campaigning in America: A History of Election Practices'' (1989)&lt;/ref&gt;  Bryan's message of [[populism]] and class conflict marked a new direction for the Democrats. McKinley's victory in 1896 and repeat in 1900 was a triumph for [[pluralism (political philosophy)|pluralism]], as all sectors and groups shared in the new prosperity brought about by his policy of rapid industrial growth.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis L. Gould, &quot;New Perspectives on the Republican Party, 1877–1913,&quot; ''American Historical Review'', Vol. 77, No. 4 (Oct., 1972), pp. 1074–1082&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Burnham (1986)&lt;/ref&gt;
** While Republicans lost House seats in 1896, this followed a massive two-election gain: from 25.9% in 1890 to 34.8% in 1892 and 71.1% in 1894, for a total 45.2% gain. Republicans lost 13.4% in 1896, but still held 57.7% of House seats.
** In terms of correlations among counties, the election of 1896 is a realignment flop, but this is only a problem if realignment is considered to occur in single elections. Rather, if realignment is thought of as a generational or long-term political movement, then change will occur over several elections, even if there is one &quot;critical&quot; election defining the new alignment. So, as pointed out above, the 1896 realignment really began around 1892, and the 130 seat GOP gain (after all, this is the ''all-time record'') in 1894 meant there were almost no seats left to pick up in 1896. However, the presidential election in 1896 is usually considered the start of the new alignment since the national election allowed the nation to make a more conscious decision about the future of industrial policy by selecting McKinley over Bryan, making this the defining election in the realignment.&lt;ref name=&quot;schafer1991&quot;/&gt; The [[United States presidential election, 1876|election of 1876]] passes the numbers test much better compared to 1896 alone, and Mayhew (2004) argues it resulted in far more drastic changes in United States politics: Reconstruction came to a sudden halt, African-Americans in the South would soon be completely disenfranchised, and politicians began to focus on new issues (such as [[tariff]]s and civil service reform).

* [[United States presidential election, 1932]] — [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]]
** Of all the realigning elections, this one musters the most agreement from political scientists and historians; it is the archetypal realigning election.&lt;ref name=&quot;schafer1991&quot;&gt;Schafer (1991)&lt;/ref&gt; FDR's admirers such as [[Arthur Schlesinger, Jr.]] have argued that [[New Deal]] policies, developed in response to the crash of 1929 and the miseries of the [[Great Depression]] under [[Herbert Hoover]], represented an entirely new phenomenon in American politics. More critical historians such as [[Carl Degler]] and [[David M. Kennedy (historian)|David Kennedy]] see a great deal of continuity with Hoover's energetic but unsuccessful economic policies. There is no doubt Democrats vehemently attacked Hoover for 50 years. In many ways, Roosevelt's legacy still defines the Democratic Party; he forged an enduring [[New Deal Coalition]] of big city machines, the White South, intellectuals, [[labor union]]s, Catholics, Jews, and Westerners.  In 1936, [[African-Americans]] were added to the coalition  (African-Americans had previously been denied the vote or voted Republican). For instance, [[Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania|Pittsburgh]], which was a Republican stronghold from the [[American Civil War|Civil War]] up to this point, suddenly became a Democratic stronghold, and has elected a Democratic mayor to office in every election since this time.
** The Democrats went from 37.7% of House seats in 1928 to 49.6% in 1930 and 71.9% in 1932, for a total gain of 34.2% in two elections.

===Possible modern realigning elections in the United States===
Some debate exists today as to what elections (if any) could be considered realigning elections after 1932.&lt;ref&gt;Mayhew (2004); Rosenof (2003); Shafer (1991)&lt;/ref&gt; Although several candidates have been proposed, there is no widespread agreement:

*[[United States presidential election, 1964|1964]] and [[United States presidential election, 1968|1968 presidential elections]] — [[Lyndon B. Johnson]] and [[Richard Nixon]]
** The 1968 election is often cited due to the innovative campaign strategy of Nixon.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Perlstein|first=Rick|authorlink=Rick Perlstein|title=[[Nixonland: The Rise of a President and the Fracturing of America]]|year=2008|publisher=Simon and Schuster|isbn=978-0-7432-4302-5}}; Rosenof (2003); Shafer (1991)&lt;/ref&gt;  In running against [[Hubert Humphrey]], he used what became known as the [[Southern strategy]]. He appealed to white voters in the South with a call for &quot;[[states' rights]],&quot; which they interpreted as meaning that the federal government would no longer demand the [[desegregation busing in the United States|forced busing]] of school children as ordered by federal courts. Democrats protested that Nixon exploited racial fears in winning the support of white southerners and northern white ethnics.&lt;ref&gt;Perlstein, ''Nixonland'' (2008);&lt;/ref&gt; Roosevelt's New Deal coalition had lasted over 30 years but after the urban riots and Vietnam crisis of the mid 1960s one by one the coalition partners peeled away until only a hollow core remained, setting the stage for a GOP revival. Nixon's downfall postponed the realignment which came about under Reagan, as even the term &quot;liberalism&quot; fell into disrepute.
**Including this as a realignment preserves the roughly 30-year cyclical pattern: 1896 to 1932, 1932 to 1964, and 1964 to 1994.&lt;!-- Except Reagan was elected in 1980 so that would be only 16 years. --&gt;
**For political scientists, 1964 was primarily an issue-based realignment. The classic study of the 1964 election, by Carmines and Stimson (1989), shows how the polarization of activists and elites on race-related issues sent clear signals to the general public about the historic change in each party's position on Civil Rights.{{Citation needed|date=June 2009}} Notably, while only 50% of African-Americans self-identified as Democrats in the 1960 National Election Study, 82% did in 1964, and the numbers are higher in the 21st century. The clearest indicator of the importance of this election, was that Deep Southern states, such as Mississippi, voted Republican in 1964. In contrast, much of the traditional Republican strongholds of the Northeast and Upper Midwest voted Democratic. Vermont and Maine, which stood alone voting against FDR in 1936, voted for LBJ in 1964.
**Many analysts do not consider 1968 a realigning election because control of [[United States Congress|Congress]] did not change; the Democrats would control the [[United States Senate|Senate]] until 1980 (and again from 1986 to 1994) and the [[United States House of Representatives|House]] until 1994.&lt;ref name=&quot;schafer1991&quot;/&gt;  Also missing was a marked change in the partisan orientation of the electorate. Importantly, these two elections are consistent with the theory in that the old New Deal issues were replaced by Civil Rights issues as the major factor explaining why citizens identified with each party. Other scholars&lt;ref&gt;Kleppner (1981)&lt;/ref&gt; contend that this is the beginning of a thirty year dealignment, in which citizens generally moved towards political independence, which ended with the 1994 election.

*[[United States presidential election, 1980|1980 presidential election]] — [[Ronald Reagan]]
**In this election, Ronald Reagan won a sweeping victory over Democrat [[Jimmy Carter]], who won only six states (plus the [[District of Columbia]]), which accounted for just 10% of the electoral vote. Republicans also took control of the Senate for the first time in over 25 years. (See [[Reagan's coattails]].) Many scholars viewed Reagan's policies as sufficiently new to consider this a realigning election.&lt;ref&gt;Rosenof (2003); Schafer (1991)&lt;/ref&gt;
** On the other hand, critics like Mayhew (2004) note that control of the House did not change, nor even come close to changing, at this time. Republicans actually held fewer House seats in 1983 than they held in 1973. In addition, the Republicans lost the Senate again only six years later, leading some to conclude that the Senators simply rode in on [[Reagan's coattails]], and did not represent a true shift in the ideological preferences of their constituents. Also absent was a shift in partisan alignment from [[public opinion poll]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Abramowitz and Saunders (1998)&lt;/ref&gt; Both [[liberals]], such as [[Nobel laureate]] [[Paul Krugman]], and [[conservatism|conservatives]], such as [[MSNBC]] [[political pundit]], [[Nixon administration]] [[political advisor]] and [[Reagan administration]] [[White House Communications Director|Communications Director]] [[Pat Buchanan]], would also argue that [[United States presidential election, 1968|Nixon’s victory in 1968]] set the stage for Reagan’s victory, and the fact that Reagan did so well in Southern states, [[Solid South|traditionally a Democratic stronghold]], as well as the fact that some of Reagan’s rhetoric involving [[law and order (politics)|law and order]] and [[states' rights (speech)|states’ rights]] seemed to mirror Nixon’s [[Southern Strategy]] seem to bear this fact out.&lt;ref&gt;[[Paul Krugman|Krugman, Paul]]. ''[[The Conscience of a Liberal]]''. New York City; W. W. Norton, 2007. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/3036789/vp/32626226#32626226 |title=Morning Joe |publisher=MSNBC |date= |accessdate=2012-03-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*[[United States presidential election, 1992|1992 presidential election]] — [[Bill Clinton]]
**The presence of independent candidate [[Ross Perot]], who received nearly 19% of the vote, made this a three-way contest. Perot, despite his strong showing for a third-party candidate, failed to win any electoral votes. Clinton won a plurality and carried several states that had previously been Republican or swing states in both the Northeast and on the West Coast. Most notably, the largest state [[California]] switched from being a reliably Republican state to being consistently Democratic: it has been carried by Democratic candidates ever since. Other states that switched and have remained with the Democrats since include [[Connecticut]], [[Delaware]], [[Illinois]], [[Maine]], [[Maryland]], [[Michigan]], [[New Jersey]], [[Pennsylvania]], and [[Vermont]]. In contrast, despite the fact Clinton came from the South, he only carried four of the former Confederate states: [[Arkansas]] (his home state), [[Louisiana]], [[Tennessee]] and [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]], confirming it as a Republican base of support.

*[[United States House of Representatives elections, 1994|1994 House of Representatives]] and [[United States Senate elections, 1994|Senate elections]]&lt;ref name=&quot;jenkins&quot;&gt;Jenkins et al. (2006)&lt;/ref&gt;
**This election is now generally seen as a realigning election by political scientists.&lt;ref name=&quot;jenkins&quot;/&gt; Republicans won majorities in both the House and the Senate, taking control of both chambers for the first time since 1954. In addition, control of the House continued until 2007. [[Newt Gingrich]], who promoted a &quot;[[Contract with America]]&quot;, successfully nationalized the campaign by coordinating races around the country. The overwhelming nature of the Republicans' victory points to a realignment; the party gained 54 seats (in a chamber of only 435), while neither party would gain more than a handful of seats in any election until 2006.
**The GOP gained seats in 43 of 46 state houses. These gains continued into the next decade, so that by 2002 the GOP held the majority of state legislative seats for the first time in fifty years.&lt;ref name=&quot;jenkins&quot;/&gt;
**Notably, the period of party decline and mass dealignment appears to have ended in the 1990s. Strength of partisanship, as measured by the National Election Study, increased in the 1990s, as does the percentage of the mass public who perceive important differences between each party.&lt;ref name=&quot;jenkins&quot;/&gt;
**This election also indicates the rise of religious issues as one of the most important [[Cleavage (politics)|cleavage]] in American politics.{{Citation needed|date=June 2009}} While Reagan's election hinted at the importance of the religious right, it was the formation of the Christian Coalition (the successor to the Moral Majority) in the early 1990s that gave Republicans organizational and financial muscle, particularly at the state level.&lt;ref&gt;Ruth Murray Brown, ''For a Christian America: A History of the Religious Right'' (2002)&lt;/ref&gt; By 2004 the media portrayed the political nation as divided into &quot;[[Red state vs. blue state divide|red]]&quot; (Republican) and &quot;[[Red state vs. blue state divide|blue]]&quot; (Democratic) states, with reputed differences in cultural attitudes and politics between the two blocs.

* [[United States presidential election, 2008|2008 Presidential election]] — [[Barack Obama]]
** In the 2008 elections, the [[Democratic party (United States)|Democrats]] expanded their majorities in [[United States Congress]], and won the Presidency decisively. This was due to the momentum carried over from the Democrats' 2006 successes, as well as the continued unpopularity of President [[George W. Bush]], whose administration was now faced with a financial crisis and economic recession. Some people believe that 2008 is possibly a realigning election with long-lasting impact, just as the election of [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]] was in [[united States presidential election, 1932|1932]] and the election of [[Ronald Reagan]] in [[United States presidential election, 1980|1980]] were.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theweek.com/article/index/90200/Obama_in_Reagans_shadow |title=Obama in Reagan's shadow |publisher=The Week |date= |accessdate=2012-03-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theweek.com/article/index/90147/End_Times_for_Reaganism |title=End Times for Reaganism |publisher=The Week |date= |accessdate=2012-03-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[United States House of Representatives elections, 2010]] and [[United States Senate elections, 2010]]
** The Republicans' 63-seat pickup in the House to take control of that chamber, as well as their six Senate seats gained, signified a dramatic rollback of recent Democratic gains. In the election, Republicans won their greatest number of House seats since 1946.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nationalaffairs.com/publications/detail/after-the-wave |title=After the Wave &gt; Publications &gt; |publisher=National Affairs |date=2010-11-02 |accessdate=2012-03-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; This has been attributed to the continued economic recession, as well as President Obama's controversial [[American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009|stimulus]] and [[Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act|health care reform]] bills. Republicans also took control of 29 of the 50 State governorships, and gained 690 seats in state legislatures to hold their greatest number since the 1928 elections.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Drake |first=Bruce |url=http://www.politicsdaily.com/2010/11/03/republicans-score-big-in-the-states-and-win-leg-up-on-redistrict/ |title=Republicans Score Big in the States and Win Leg Up on Redistricting |publisher=Politicsdaily.com |date= |accessdate=2012-03-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[North Carolina]], Republicans won control of both chambers of the state legislature for the first time in 140 years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.americanthinker.com/2010/11/voting_integrity_also_a_rural.html |title=Archived-Articles: Voting Integrity Also a Rural Issue |publisher=Americanthinker.com |date=2012-02-27 |accessdate=2012-03-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[Great Lakes]] region, which had recently favored the Democratic Party, went strongly Republican. In [[California]] and the [[Pacific Northwest]], however, the Democrats retained the upper hand.

==Canada==
The history of the critical realigning elections in Canada, both nationally and in the provinces, is covered by Argyle (2011).&lt;ref&gt;Ray Argyle, ''Turning Points: The Campaigns That Changed Canada - 2011 and Before'' (2011)  [http://www.amazon.com/gp/reader/B005233WJG/  excerpt and text search] 441pp &lt;/ref&gt;

Behiels (2010) suggests that experts in Canadian politics&lt;ref&gt;Behiels cites Tom Flanaganm ''Harpers Team: Behind the Scenes in the Conservative Rise to Power'' (2nd ed. McGill-Queens U.P. 2009); Chantal Hébert, ''French Kiss: Stephen Harpers Blind Date with Quebec'' (Knopf Canada, 2007); William Johnson, ''Stephen Harper and the Future of Canada'' (2nd ed. McClelland &amp; Stewart, 2006); Lloyd Mackay, ''Stephen Harper: The Case for Collaborative Governance'' (ECW Press, 2006); Bob Plamondon, ''Full Circle: Death and Resurrection in Canadian Conservative Politics'' (Key Porter Books, 2006); and Paul Wells, ''Right Side Up: The Fall of Paul Martin and the Rise of Stephen Harpers New Conservatism'' (Douglas Gibson Books, 2007)&lt;/ref&gt; are now reporting that a watershed political realignment is underway, the kind of shift that occurs but once a century. In light of the 2004, 2006, and 2008 minority government elections and the success of [[Stephen Harper]], many journalists, political advisors, and politicians argue that a new political paradigm is emerging, and it is based on Harper's drive for a right-wing political party capable of reconfiguring the role of the state – federal and provincial – in twenty-first-century.&lt;ref&gt;Michael D. Behiels, &quot;Stephen Harper’s Rise to Power: Will His 'New' Conservative Party Become Canada’s 'Natural Governing Party' of the Twenty-First Century?,&quot; ''American Review of Canadian Studies'' Vol. 40, No. 1, March 2010, 118–145&lt;/ref&gt;  Bloomfield and Nossal (2007) suggest that the new political alignment has reshaped Canadian foreign policy, especially in improving relations with the U.S., taking a harder line on the Middle East conflicts, and backing away from the [[Kyoto Protocol]] on global warming.&lt;ref&gt;Alan Bloomfield and Kim Richard Nossal, &quot;Towards an Explicative Understanding of Strategic Culture: The Cases of Australia and Canada&quot;, ''Contemporary Security Policy,'' (2007) 28:2, 286 - 307 [http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/13523260701489859 online]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Federal===
===Party systems model===
According to recent scholarship there have been four [[party systems]] in Canada at the federal level since Confederation, each with its own distinctive pattern of social support, [[patronage]] relationships, leadership styles, and electoral strategies.&lt;ref&gt;Alain-G. Gagnon, and A. Brain  Tanguay, ''Canadian Parties in Transition (3rd ed. 2007)&lt;/ref&gt;  Steve Patten identifies four party systems in Canada's political history&lt;ref&gt;Steve Patten,  &quot;The Evolution of the Canadian Party System&quot;. in Gagnon, and Tanguay, eds. ''Canadian Parties in Transition'' pp. 57-58&lt;/ref&gt;
* The first party system emerged from pre-Confederation colonial politics, had its &quot;heyday&quot; from 1896 to 1911 and lasted until the [[Conscription Crisis of 1917]], and was characterized by local patronage administered by the two largest parties, the [[Liberals (Canada)|Liberals]] and the [[Conservative Party of Canada (historical)|Conservatives]].
* The second system emerged following the First World War, and had its heyday from 1935 and 1957, was characterized by regionalism and saw the emergence of several protest parties, such as the [[Progressives (Canada)|Progressives]], the [[Social Credit Party (Canada)|Social Credit Party]], and the [[Co-operative Commonwealth Federation]].
* The third system emerged in 1963 and had its heyday from 1968 to 1983 and began to unravel thereafter.  The two largest parties were challenged by a strong third party, the [[New Democratic Party]]. Campaigns during this era became more national in scope due to [[electronic media]], and involved a greater focus on leadership. The dominant policy of the era was [[Keynesian]] economics.
* The fourth party system has involved the rise of the [[Reform Party of Canada|Reform Party]], the [[Bloc Québécois]], and the merger of the [[Canadian Alliance]] with the [[Progressive Conservative Party of Canada|Progressive Conservatives]]. It saw most parties move to one-member-one-vote leadership contests, and a major reform to campaign finance laws in 2004.  The fourth party system has been characterized by market-oriented policies that abandoned [[Keynesian]] policies, but maintained the welfare state.

Clarkson (2005) shows how the Liberal Party has dominated all the party systems, using different approaches. It began with a  &quot;clientelistic approach&quot; under [[Sir Wilfrid Laurier|Laurier]], which evolved into a &quot;brokerage&quot; system of the 1920s, 1930s and 1940s under [[William Lyon Mackenzie King|Mackenzie King]]. The 1950s saw the emergence of a &quot;pan-Canadian system&quot;, which lasted until the 1990s. The 1993 election — categorized by Clarkson as an electoral &quot;earthquake&quot; which &quot;fragmented&quot; the party system, saw the emergence of regional politics within a four party-system, whereby various groups championed regional issues and concerns. Clarkson concludes that the inherent bias built into the first-past-the-post system, has chiefly benefited the Liberals.&lt;ref&gt;Stephen Clarkson, ''The Big Red Machine: How the Liberal Party Dominates Canadian Politics'' (2005)&lt;/ref&gt;

====1896====
{{main|Canadian federal election, 1896}}
1896 saw as  [[Liberal Party of Canada|Liberal]] victory; Sir [[Wilfrid Laurier]] [[Prime Minister of Canada|Prime Minister]]. From the [[Canadian federal election, 1867|1867 election]] until 1896, the [[Conservative Party of Canada|Conservative Party]] of [[Sir John A. Macdonald]] had governed Canada, excepting a single term from 1873 to 1878. The Liberals had struggled to retake office, under Laurier and his predecessor, [[Edward Blake]]. 1896 was the first election held after the death of Macdonald in 1891, and the Conservatives had been in complete disarray in the ensuing years, with no less than four different leaders. The Liberals would remain in office until [[Canadian federal election, 1911|1911]]. Beyond that, political scientists often consider this election that made the Liberal Party the dominant force in Canadian politics, holding office for more than two thirds of the time between 1896 and 2006.&lt;ref&gt;Ray Argyle, ''Turning Points: The Campaigns That Changed Canada - 2011 and Before'' (2011)  [http://www.amazon.com/gp/reader/B005233WJG/  excerpt and text search] ch 4&lt;/ref&gt;

====1984====
{{main|Canadian federal election, 1984}}
1984 saw the victory of  [[Progressive Conservative Party of Canada|Progressive Conservative]] under  [[Brian Mulroney]]. The election of 1984 not only saw Brian Mulroney's Progressive Conservatives win the largest number of seats in Canadian History (211 of 282), and the second largest majority (behind [[John Diefenbaker|John Diefenbaker's]] 208 of 265 in [[Canadian federal election, 1958|1958]]), it ended over twenty years of [[Liberal Party of Canada|Liberal]] rule, not counting the brief [[Canadian federal election, 1979|1979]]–[[Canadian federal election, 1980|1980]] tenure of [[Joe Clark]]. The Liberal Party under prime minister [[John Turner]] saw their second worst result ever, winning a mere 40 seats. Turner had just succeeded [[Pierre Trudeau]] as prime minister when he decided to call the election, and the Liberals were losing popularity due to the downfall of the economy and Trudeau's last minute patronage appointments. 

The PCs' victory was aided in large part by a massive breakthrough in Quebec, winning 58 seats as compared to the one Quebec seat they won in 1980; Mulroney successfully campaigned in Quebec on a message that [[Pierre Trudeau|Pierre Trudeau's]] Liberals had &quot;sold out&quot; the province during the process of [[Patriation|patriating]] the [[Constitution of Canada|Canadian constitution]] in 1982, due to the fact that Quebec never formally signed on to the [[Constitution Act, 1982|new constitution]].  The Liberals were cut down to only 17 seats, all but four of them in Montreal.  Although Quebec had been a Liberal stronghold since 1896 (with the exception of 1958), from 1984 onwards the Liberals never managed to win the largest number of seats in that province (they came close in [[Canadian federal election, 2000|2000]] and took the majority by winning several by-elections), making this province the most long-lasting realignment in this election.

Although Mulroney is often grouped with contemporary [[conservatism|conservative]] leaders [[Margaret Thatcher]] and [[Ronald Reagan]], and the 1984 election is seen as Canada's version of the 1979 United Kingdom and 1980 United States elections, Mulroney proved in practice to be a relatively centrist leader.

====1993====
{{main|Canadian federal election, 1993}}
1993 saw not only the sweeping success of the Liberals under  [[Jean Chrétien]], but also the fracturing the [[Progressive Conservative Party of Canada|Progressive Conservatives]]' support base to regional parties in Quebec and the western provinces; resulting in a five party political system with the Liberals as the dominant party.&lt;ref name=&quot;fullcomment.nationalpost.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://fullcomment.nationalpost.com/2011/05/06/scott-stinson-liberals-begin-process-of-redefinition/ |title=Scott Stinson: Redefining the Liberals not a quick process &amp;#124; Full Comment &amp;#124; National Post |publisher=Fullcomment.nationalpost.com |date=2011-05-06 |accessdate=2012-03-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Throughout [[History of Canada|Canadian history]] two parties had taken turns in government and opposition: the Liberals and the [[Progressive Conservative Party of Canada|Progressive Conservatives]] (sometimes known as Liberal-Conservatives, Conservatives, Union and National Government). The Conservative majority election victories in [[Canadian federal election, 1984|1984]] and [[Canadian federal election, 1988|1988]] were based on a  &quot;Grand Coalition&quot; between socially conservative populists from the West, Quebec nationalists, and fiscal conservatives from Ontario and the Maritimes, making it difficult for the [[Brian Mulroney|Mulroney government]] to balance these diverse interests. During his second term, Mulroney's policies were unpopular, while the failure of the [[Meech Lake Accord|Meech Lake]] and [[Charlottetown Accord|Charlottetown]] Accords frustrated Quebec and stirred up Western alienation. New regional parties which formed in protest to Mulroney's government, the [[Bloc Québécois]] in Quebec and the [[Reform Party of Canada|Reform Party]] in [[Western Canada|the west]] won many seats formerly held by the PCs despite a lack of national support. The [[New Democratic Party]], the longtime third party in parliament, fell from 43 seats to nine. The unpopularity of the provincial NDP governments in Ontario and BC reflected badly on the federal NDP, also their endorsement of the Charlottetown Accord and Quebec nationalism cost them support among organized labour and rural voters in the West, which switched their support to Reform.  Meanwhile, the Progressive Conservatives were nearly wiped out, falling from 151 seats to only two--the worst defeat of a sitting government at the federal level.

The Liberals under Chrétien would win a further two consecutive majorities in 1997 and 2000, while never being seriously challenged as the largest party. The Progressive Conservatives never recovered, winning 20 (of 301) seats in [[Canadian general election, 1997|1997]]) and 12 in [[Canadian federal election, 2000|2000]] before merging with the Reform Party's successor, the [[Canadian Alliance]], to form the new [[Conservative Party of Canada]] in late 2003. Due to competition with the Liberals for left-leaning voters, the New Democrats had mixed successes in the next several elections, winning 21 in 1997 but dropping back to 13 in 2000, unable to approach their high water mark showing until 2006.

====2004====
{{main|Canadian federal election, 2004}}
While [[Paul Martin]]'s Liberals retains enough seats to continue as the government, it saw the re-emergence of the [[Conservative Party of Canada|Conservatives]] and the resurgence of [[Bloc Québécois]]; resulting in a four party system with the ruling party as a minority government. This was the first of three elections where no party managed a majority of seats. 

Martin succeeded a retiring [[Jean Chrétien]] in 2003 and initially polls predicted that the Liberals could expand their control of Parliament in the next election, as Martin sought inroads in Quebec and Western Canada, while the newly created Conservative Party was besought by controversy over its merger.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://fullcomment.nationalpost.com/2011/05/07/conrad-black-the-full-measure-of-harper%E2%80%99s-triumph/ |title=Conrad Black: The full measure of Harper’s triumph &amp;#124; Full Comment &amp;#124; National Post |publisher=Fullcomment.nationalpost.com |date= |accessdate=2012-03-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the revelation of the [[sponsorship scandal]], along with [[2004 Liberal Party of Canada infighting|party infighting between Chrétien and Martin]] weakened the Liberals, while the reunited Conservatives became a viable governing alternative, and the rejuvenated Bloc Québécois. At mid-campaign, polls predicted a Conservative lead, but the Liberals regained enough support to win a plurality of seats to remain the governing party.

Several trends would also begin in 2004 which signaled the Liberal party's decline; notably a high turnover of permanent party leaders (in contrast to their predecessors who usually served over two or more elections),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Wells |first=Paul |url=http://www2.macleans.ca/2011/05/04/politics-turned-over/ |title=The untold story of the 2011 election: Introduction and Chapter 1 - Paul Wells |publisher=Macleans.ca |date=2011-05-04 |accessdate=2012-03-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; and its inability to raise campaign funds competitively once Chrétien banned corporate donations,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/background/realitycheck/gray/20060613.html |title=CBC News In Depth: Reality Check - John Gray |publisher=Cbc.ca |date=2006-06-13 |accessdate=2012-03-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; and it would gradually lose support to the Conservatives, and later to the NDP. 

**[[Canadian federal election, 2006]] – [[Conservative Party of Canada|Conservative]] victory; [[Stephen Harper]] [[Prime Minister of Canada|Prime Minister]]
*** The 2004 election paved the way for the results in 2006, which is the first electoral victory of a Canadian [[Conservatism in Canada|conservative]] party since 1988 and the first conservative government in Canada since November 1993. This ended 13 years of [[Liberal Party of Canada|Liberal]] government, whose minority government from 2004–06 was propped up by the [[New Democratic Party]] until they withdrew their support after fallout from the Sponsorship Scandal. As early as 1989, Harper had theorized that a realignment would occur pitting middle class tax payers versus middle class tax recipients.&lt;ref&gt;William Johnson, ''Stephen Harper and the Future of Canada'' (2006) pp 117-19&lt;/ref&gt;

====2011====
{{main|Canadian federal election, 2011}}
The election resulted in a [[Conservative Party of Canada|Conservative]] majority victory under the leadership of Prime Minister [[Stephen Harper]], after forming two consecutive minority governments.&lt;ref&gt;Ray Argyle, ''Turning Points: The Campaigns That Changed Canada - 2011 and Before'' (2011)  [http://www.amazon.com/gp/reader/B005233WJG/  excerpt and text search] ch 1&lt;/ref&gt;  The Liberals dropped to third party status in Parliament for the first time, having previously always been either the governing party or the official opposition, and also no longer had a significant number of seats in Quebec (their bastion of support from 1892 to 1984) or Ontario (a stronghold since 1993, especially the Greater Toronto Area). Some suggested that [[Rob Ford]]'s mayoral victory in November 2010 had paved the way for the federal Conservatives' successes in Toronto, with right-of-centre politicians garnering significant support from immigrants that traditionally supported the Liberals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.nationalpost.com/2011/05/05/rob-fords-approval-rating-at-70-poll/ |title=Rob Ford’s approval rating at 70%: poll &amp;#124; Posted Toronto &amp;#124; National Post |publisher=News.nationalpost.com |date=2011-05-05 |accessdate=2012-03-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/politics/a-harper-government-would-benefit-taxpayers-rob-ford-tells-rally/article2005018/ |title=This page is available to GlobePlus subscribers |publisher=Theglobeandmail.com |date= |accessdate=2012-03-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[New Democratic Party]], led by [[Jack Layton]], won 103 seats to become the official opposition for the first time in party history, as a late-campaign surge of support in Quebec took them from one to 59 seats at the expense of the other parties, particularly the [[Bloc Québécois]] which saw their 47 seats in that province reduced to a rump of four seats. The Bloc had previously won the majority of Quebec's seats from 1993 to 2008. The party leaders of the Liberals and the Bloc, [[Michael Ignatieff]] and [[Gilles Duceppe]], respectively, were personally defeated in their own constituencies. This marked a return to the three party system in parliament which was last seen in the 1988 election.&lt;ref name=&quot;fullcomment.nationalpost.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

Commentators after the major shakeup in 2011 stressed the theme of a major realignment.  The ''Economist'' said, &quot;the election represents the biggest realignment of Canadian politics since 1993.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Economist'' May 3, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;  Lawrence Martin, commentator for the ''Globe and Mail'' said, &quot;Harper has completed a remarkable reconstruction of a Canadian political landscape that endured for more than a century. The realignment sees both old parties of the moderate middle, the Progressive Conservatives and the Liberals, either eliminated or marginalized.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Lawrence Martin, &quot;Harper’s triumph: a realignment of historic proportions, [http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/opinions/opinion/harpers-triumph-a-realignment-of-historic-proportions/article2008719/ ''Globe and Mail'' May 4, 2011]&lt;/ref&gt;  ''Maclean's'' said, the election marked &quot;an unprecedented realignment of Canadian politics&quot; as &quot;the Conservatives are now in a position to replace the Liberals as the natural governing party in Canada.&quot; [[Andrew Coyne]] proclaimed &quot;The West is in and Ontario has joined it&quot;, noting that the Conservatives accomplished the rare feat of putting together a majority by winning in ''both'' Ontario and the western provinces (difficult due to traditionally conflicting interests), while having little representation in Quebec.&lt;ref name=&quot;fullcomment.nationalpost.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Andrew Coyne, &quot;The West is in and Ontario has joined it: How the election led to an unprecedented realignment of Canadian politics.&quot; [http://www2.macleans.ca/2011/05/06/a-new-power-couple/ ''Maclean's'' May 6 2011]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Alberta===
*[[Alberta general election, 1971]] – End of the 36-year unbroken rule of the [[Social Credit Party of Alberta|Social Credit Party]], in favour of the [[Progressive Conservative Association of Alberta|Progressive Conservatives]]. [[Peter Lougheed]]'s Conservatives defeated the Socreds led by Premier [[Harry Strom|Harry E. Strom]]. Although the Socreds lost only a small share of its popular vote from 1967, their support in the province's two largest cities, [[Edmonton]] and [[Calgary]], almost disappeared.  They lost all of their seats in Edmonton, and all but five seats in Calgary.
**There were ominous signs of Socreds' decline in the 1967 election, in which they failed to win 50% of the popular vote since 1955.  Longtime Premier [[Ernest C. Manning]] retired a few months later. His successor Strom had been unable to revive a party that had grown tired and complacent, while the collapse of the other opposition parties made the PCs the only credible challenger to the Socreds. The Socreds sank into near-paralysis in opposition, being ill-prepared for that role after being the governing party for virtually all of its history prior to 1971. Their support collapsed in the 1975 election and they were all but wiped out in 1982, ceasing to be an effective force in Albertan politics.
**The Progressive Conservatives have won every election since 1968, despite losing some luster during [[Don Getty]]'s tenure from 1985–92, they have regained strength under [[Ralph Klein]].

===British Columbia===
*[[British Columbia general election, 1991]] – End of [[Social Credit Party of British Columbia|Social Credit]] as an effective political force in British Columbia politics. The Socreds under Premier [[Rita Johnston]] was reduced to third party status, while the [[New Democratic Party of British Columbia|New Democratic Party]] of [[Michael Harcourt|Mike Harcourt]] formed the government. [[British Columbia Liberal Party|Liberal Party]] leader [[Gordon Wilson (Canadian politician)|Gordon Wilson]] surprised observers by leading his party to winning one-third of the votes cast, and forming the [[official opposition]] in the legislature.
*Socred had been beset by scandals during [[William Vander Zalm|Bill Vander Zalm]]'s last term as premier. Party control shifted from urban fiscal conservatives to social conservatives, causing the coalition to unravel and pushing many moderates to eventually switch to the Liberals. After Premier Vander Zalm resigned, Socred members voted the lesser-known Johnston, a close ally of Vander Zalm, over [[Grace McCarthy]]. Many viewed this as a mistake, as Johnston was close to the Vander Zalm legacy; even NDP leader Harcourt admitted later that he preferred Johnston over McCarthy. Wilson's party gained gradually but surged after his strong performance in the televised leaders' debates' Wilson was initially not invited and took legal action to overturn his exclusion. However, once he became opposition leader, Wilson proved unable to consolidate the party's leadership; he was eventually deposed and later became a New Democrat.

===Quebec===
A considerable number of [[List of Quebec general elections|Quebec general elections]] have been known characterized by high seat turnovers, with certain ones being considered realigning elections, notably: 
* The 1936 election which ended 39 years of Liberal rule, 16 of them recently under [[Louis-Alexandre Taschereau]] and saw the rise of [[Maurice Duplessis]]'s [[Union Nationale (Quebec)|Union Nationale]].
* The 1960 election, after the deaths of Duplessis and his successor [[Paul Sauve]], which ended 15 continuous years of Union Nationale rule and precipitated its gradual decline. It also ushered in the [[Quiet Revolution]] under [[Jean Lesage]].
* The 1976 election, which saw [[René Lévesque]]'s ''[[Parti Québécois]]'' not only make a breakthrough in the National Assembly, it also drove [[Robert Bourassa]]'s Liberals from office. It also made [[Quebec sovereignty movement|sovereignty]] the dominant political issue.
* The 1985 election marked the successful political comeback of Bourassa and his Liberals, while also putting sovereignty as an issue to rest until a decade later.

The [[Quebec Liberal Party]] (unaffiliated with the federal Liberals since 1955) survived since Confederation but they have faced different opposition parties, several of which had formed the government, often alternating with the Liberals.

*[[Quebec general election, 2007]] – Ascent of the ''[[Action démocratique du Québec]]'' (ADQ) to [[Official Opposition]] status
**While the [[Quebec federalist ideology|federalist]] Liberals maintained a plurality in the [[National Assembly of Quebec]] and [[Jean Charest]] remained [[Premier of Quebec|Premier]], the conservative, Quebec nationalist ADQ successfully replaced the [[social democracy|social democratic]] and sovereigntist ''Parti Québécois'' as the Official Opposition; prior to this election, the ADQ never had more than five Members of the National Assembly.

*[[Quebec general election, 2008]] – Return of the ''[[Action démocratique du Québec]]'' (ADQ) to [[third party (Canada)|third party]] status
**The ADQ lost the great majority of the seats they had gained in the previous year. Soon after the election, leader [[Mario Dumont]] resigned and the party fell into a period of disarray.

==Realigning elections outside of North America==
===Asia===
*[[Israeli legislative election, 1977]] - [[Likud]] defeated the [[Alignment (political party)|Alignment]] and ended the 29-year reign of Mapai/Israeli Labor Party. The Israeli multiparty system shifted from a one-party dominant system to a two-party dominant system. Due to corruption in the Labor Party many former Labor voters defected to the new Democratic Movement for Change which won 15 seats coming in third behind the Likud with 46 seats and Alignment (Labor plus Mapam) with 32 seats. The DMC collapsed within three years and in the next election most Labor voters returned making the Alignment once more a viable competitor with the Likud. The two parties dominated Israeli politics until 2003 when Labor went into sudden decline due to a backlash against the failed Oslo peace process and the outbreak of the Al-Aksa Intifada.

*[[ROC presidential election, 2000]] ([[Republic of China|Taiwan]]) — [[Chen Shui-bian]]
**Though more popular and consistently ranked higher in the polls, [[James Soong]] failed to gain the ruling [[Kuomintang]]'s (KMT) nomination over incumbent Vice President [[Lien Chan]]. As a result, he announced his candidacy as an independent candidate, and was consequently expelled from the party. The split in the KMT vote resulted in a victory for [[Chen Shui-bian]] of the [[Democratic Progressive Party]], even though he won only 39% of the popular vote. After the election, Soong founded the [[People First Party (Republic of China)|People First Party]], which attracted members from the KMT and the pro-unification [[New Party (Republic of China)|New Party]], which was by that time beginning to fade. Angry from the defeat, the KMT expelled chairman [[Lee Teng-hui]], who was president until 2000 and was widely suspected of causing the KMT split so that Chen would win. Lee then founded the pro-independence [[Taiwan Solidarity Union]]. The impact of these events changed the political landscape of Taiwan. Not only did the KMT lose the presidency for the first time in half a century, but its policies swung away from Lee's influence and it began intra-party reform. The two newly-founded parties became far more viable than other minor parties in the past, and the multi-party nature of Taiwan's politics was confirmed by the [[ROC legislative election, 2001|legislative elections of 2001]]. The KMT would not return to power until 2008 under the leadership of [[Ma Ying-jeou]].

*[[Turkish general election, 2002]] ([[Justice and Development Party (Turkey)|Justice and Development Party]] victory)
**This election was notable in that every party in the previous [[Grand National Assembly of Turkey]] was ejected from Parliament, as none of them crossed the 10 percent threshold.  This not only included the governing coalition of the [[Democratic Left Party (Turkey)|Democratic Left Party]], [[Motherland Party (Turkey)|Motherland Party]] and [[Nationalist Movement Party]], but the largest opposition party, the [[True Path Party]].  The AK Party, which won government in this election, has dominated Turkish politics since then.

*[[Palestinian legislative election, 2006]] ([[Palestinian National Authority]]) – [[Hamas]] victory; [[Ismail Haniyeh]] [[Prime Minister of the Palestinian Authority|Prime Minister]]
**In January 2006 the militant [[Hamas]] organization, classified as a terrorist group by the United States government and other groups, won a landslide victory over the ruling [[Fatah]] party which had been in power under the leadership of former PLO chairman [[Yasser Arafat]]. The [[George W. Bush administration|Bush Administration]], the [[Quartet on the Middle East|Quartet]], and [[Israel]] all threatened to cut off aid to the Palestinian Authority if Hamas refused to abandon terrorist tactics and recognize the right of the State of Israel to exist. This concession, though discussed in Hamas circles, did not come about soon enough to prevent a serious breakdown in services under Hamas government, and Western (especially American) support of Fatah paramilitaries eventually led to the breakout of the [[Fatah–Hamas conflict]] (termed a &quot;Palestinian Civil War&quot; by some) in December 2006. The Hamas government was suspended by PA President [[Mahmoud Abbas]], a member of Fatah, after some weeks of fighting, and installed a caretaker government under the leadership of [[Salam Fayyad]].

===Europe===
*[[Irish general election, 1918]] — [[Sinn Féin]] victory
**For the previous four decades, Irish politics had been dominated by the moderate [[nationalist]] [[Irish Parliamentary Party]], which sought [[Home Rule]] within the United Kingdom. The 1918 election was a landslide victory for the [[Irish Republicanism|Republican]] [[Sinn Féin]] party, which won nearly 70% of the seats. The new Sinn Féin MPs refused to take their seats in the [[Parliament of the United Kingdom|Westminster Parliament]], and instead set up their own republican assembly called the [[First Dáil|Dáil Éireann]]. This assembly issued a [[unilateral declaration of independence|unilateral]] [[Irish Declaration of Independence|Declaration of Independence]], which led to the start of the [[Irish War of Independence|War of Independence]] and eventually to Irish independence from the United Kingdom in 1922. The Irish Parliamentary Party never recovered from this defeat. The two largest parties in Ireland, [[Fianna Fáil]] and [[Fine Gael]], originated from splits in the Sinn Féin party which won the election of 1918.

*[[United Kingdom general election, 1922|UK general election, 1922]] - [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative]] victory; [[Andrew Bonar Law]] [[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom]]
** This election marked the Conservatives' first election victory since 1900.  More importantly, the [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]] passed the two wings of the [[Liberal Party (UK)|Liberals]] to become the Loyal Opposition for the first time ever.  For over 200 years, the Liberals and Conservatives (and their antecedents) had been the UK's major parties.  However, the 1922 election saw Labour pass the Liberals in the British landscape.  Labour and the Conservatives have been the UK's major parties since then.  The Liberals would not be a major force in UK politics again until 2010, when as the [[Liberal Democrats]] they formed a coalition government with the Conservatives.

*[[United Kingdom general election, 1979|UK general election, 1979]] — [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative]] victory; [[Margaret Thatcher]] [[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom|Prime Minister]]
** This election brought the Conservatives into government where they remained for 18 years. Thatcher's policies of [[monetarism]] and [[privatization]] represented a very different strand of Conservatism to that of previous governments and a bold shift from the [[post war consensus]] that had existed since 1945. The shockwaves led to a new party (the [[Social Democratic Party (UK)|Social Democratic Party]]) and a long period of opposition for [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour]] during which time they were reformed and transformed into [[New Labour]] before they returned to government. At a more base level it led to a shift in voting patterns as the traditional class based voting started to break down and many of the working classes (in particular skilled workers, home owners and those in southern England) voted Conservative, whilst at the same time many public sector professionals turned away from them.

*[[Italian general election, 1994]] - [[Forza Italia]]/[[Pole of Freedoms]] victory
**This election resulted in the near-destruction of the [[Italian People's Party (1994)|Italian People's Party]] (the renamed [[Christian Democracy (Italy)|Christian Democrats]]), which had been the largest party in the country since 1946.  The [[Italian Socialist Party]], a major coalition partner for the last 30 years, was decimated as well. 

*[[Polish parliamentary election, 2005]] – resulted in a widely-expected heavy defeat for the post-Communist [[Democratic Left Alliance]] government, with conservative parties such as [[Law and Justice]] and [[Civic Platform]] emerging as the dominant parties in Poland.

*[[Irish general election, 2011]] — [[Fianna Fáil]] (FF), who had governed Ireland for most of the post-independence era, were heavily defeated in the election following anger over Ireland's financial crisis. For the first time, [[Fine Gael]] overtook FF to win the most votes and seats, while FF fell from first place to third place, in terms of votes and seats. Fine Gael and the second largest party in the Dail, the [[Labour Party (Ireland)|Labour Party]] formed a coalition government.

*[[Greek legislative election, May 2012]] - Greece's two main political parties since the restoration of democracy in 1974, [[New Democracy (Greece)|New Democracy]] and the [[Panhellenic Socialist Movement]] (PASOK), saw a combined fall in support from nearly 80% in 2009 to just one third of support for their role in supporting austerity measures to alleviate the [[Greek government-debt crisis]]. In this election, PASOK fell dramatically from first place to third place. This election also saw the shift of left-leaning support to [[Coalition of the Radical Left]] (SYRIZA) which has at been the forefront of opposition to the austerity measures.

===Oceania===
*[[Australian federal election, 1972]] – [[Australian Labor Party|Labor]] victory; [[Gough Whitlam]] [[Prime Minister of Australia|Prime Minister]]
**After twenty-three years of [[Liberal Party of Australia|Liberal]] rule, the Labor Party took power in 1972, with the slogan, 'It's Time'. The significance of this election was broader than merely a change of partisan rule; new issues, such as the environment, Aboriginal affairs, abortion, multiculturalism, and a broader acceptance of state spending, resulted from the [[Gough Whitlam|Whitlam]] government, which in many respects created a bipartisan consensus on major issues of social policy. Although the Whitlam government was relatively brief, its policy legacy—in creating new government policies for society and culture—lasted in many respects to the [[Australian federal election, 1996|1996 election]], and even to the present day.

*[[Australian federal election, 1996]] – [[Liberal Party of Australia|Liberal]] victory; [[John Howard]] [[Prime Minister of Australia|Prime Minister]]
**The recent Australian political spectrum has consisted of two major parties, the conservative [[Liberal Party of Australia]] and the democratic socialist [[Australian Labor Party]] (ALP) although as of late Labor has been more aligned with the [[Third Way (centrism)|third way]]. This election followed Labor's re-election in the [[Australian federal election, 1993|1993 election]] which was termed the &quot;unwinnable election&quot; for the Labor Prime Minister [[Paul Keating]]. It marked the end of the [[Bob Hawke|Hawke]]/[[Paul Keating|Keating]] Labor government which had been in power for 13 years. During this time the conservative Liberal party had undergone several failed leadership changes including [[Andrew Peacock]] in [[Australian federal election, 1984|1984]] and [[Australian federal election, 1990|1990]], John Howard in [[Australian federal election, 1987|1987]] and [[John Hewson]] in [[Australian federal election, 1993|1993]]. The 1996 election saw the ALP lose 31 seats in the [[Australian House of Representatives|House of Representatives]] with a [[two-party-preferred vote|two-party-preferred]] result of 46.37%, the lowest for Labor since [[Australian federal election, 1934|1934]]. The 1996 election was significantly influenced by the demographic coined as the [[Aussie battler|Howard's battlers]]. These were traditionally lower middle class Labor party voters who felt that the ALP was no longer giving them the recognition they deserve. Notorious demographics which fell in 1996 were outer suburb [[mortgage belt]] areas. Howard's battlers played a part in the [[Australian federal election, 2007|2007 election]] where the ALP under [[Kevin Rudd]] was returned to power. Large gains made by Labor took place in many of former Liberal strongholds in the mortgage belt due to various issues common with the 1996 election in terms of general dissatisfaction as well as high [[interest rates]].

==See also==
*[[American election campaigns in the 19th century]]
* [[Second Party System]]
* [[Third Party System]]
* [[Fifth Party System]]

==Notes and references==
{{reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* Abramowitz, Alan I. and Kyle L. Saunders. 1998. “Ideological Realignment in the US Electorate.” Journal of Politics 60(3):634–652.
* Aldrich, John H. 1995. Why Parties? The Origin and Transformation of Party Politics in America. Chicago: The University of Chicago Press.
* Aldrich, John H. 2000. “Southern Politics in State and Nation.” ''Journal of Politics'' 62: 643–670.
*Buchanan, Scott E. &quot;The Realignment of 1964?&quot; ''Politics and Policy'' 30:140-158.
*Buchanan, Scott E. &quot;The Dixiecrat Rebellion: Long-Term Partisan Implications in the Deep South.&quot; ''Politics and Policy'' 33:754-769.
*Bullock, Charles S. III, Donna R. Hoffman and Ronald Keith Gaddie, &quot;Regional Variations in the Realignment of American Politics, 1944–2004,&quot; ''Social Science Quarterly'' v 87#3 (Sept 2006) pp 494+; Abstract: Using the concepts of critical and secular realignments as a framework, models change in the end product of realignment, election outcomes. Tests for secular and critical changes in partisan strength across six geographic regions in US, focusing on office-holding data at both the federal and state legislative level. There are elements of both critical and secular realignments at work with different patterns in each region, and that different regions have been affected by a variety of elections associated with critical events since 1944. The collapse of Republican hegemony in the Northeast and Pacific West has gone largely unnoticed, buried in the intense examination of the growth of the Republican Party in the American South. The 1994 election is the most prominent in terms of its impact on seat holding by the parties at both the state and national level, and constitutes a realigning election.
*Burnham, Walter Dean. ''Critical elections and the mainsprings of American politics'' (1970) (ISBN 0-393-09962-8)
*Burnham, Walter Dean. &quot;Periodization Schemes and 'Party Systems': The 'System of 1896' as a Case in Point,&quot; ''Social Science History,'' Vol. 10, No. 3, (Autumn, 1986), pp.&amp;nbsp;263–314. [http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0145-5532%28198623%2910%3A3%3C263%3APSA%22ST%3E2.0.CO%3B2-L in JSTOR]
*William Nisbet Chambers and Walter Dean Burnham, eds. ''American Party Systems: Stages of Political Development'' (1968) (ISBN 0-19-631662-6)
*Carmines, Edward G., and James A. Stimson. 1989. ''Issue Evolution: Race and the Transformation of American Politics''. (ISBN 0-69-107802-5)
*[http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=98202267 Clubb, Jerome M., William H. Flanigan, Nancy H. Zingale. ''Partisan Realignment: Voters, Parties, and Government in American History '' (1990)]
* Cunningham, Sean P. ''Cowboy Conservatism: Texas and the Rise of the Modern Right'' (2010)
*Gerring, John. ''Party Ideologies in America, 1828–1996'' 1998. (ISBN 0-52-178590-1)
*Gienap, William E. ''The Origins of the Republican Party, 1852–1856'' 1987. (ISBN 0-19-505501-2)
* Holt, Michael F. &quot;The New Political History and the Civil War Era,&quot; ''Reviews in American History,'' Vol. 13, No. 1 (Mar., 1985), pp.&amp;nbsp;60–69 [http://www.jstor.org/stable/2702012 in JSTOR]&lt;/
*Jensen, Richard J. ''Grass Roots Politics: Parties, Issues, and Voters, 1854-1983.'' Westport: Greenwood, 1983. (ISBN 0-83-716382-X)
*Jensen, Richard. ''The Winning of the Midwest: Social and Political Conflict, 1888-1896'' 1971. (ISBN 0-22-639825-0)
*Jenkins, Shannon, Douglas D. Roscoe, John P. Frendreis, and Alan R. Gitelson. 2006. &quot;Ten Years After the Revolution: 1994 and Partisan Control of Government&quot; in Green and Coffey, ''The State of the Parties'', 5th ed. (ISBN 0-74-255322-1)
*Key, V.O. &quot;A Theory of Critical Elections.&quot; ''The Journal of Politics'', 1955. 17: 3–18.
*Kleppner, Paul ed. ''Evolution of American Electoral Systems'' (1981) (ISBN 0-31-321379-8)
*Ladd Jr., Everett Carll with Charles D. Hadley. ''Transformations of the American Party System: Political Coalitions from the New Deal to the 1970s'' 2d ed. (1978). (ISBN 0-39-309065-5)
*Lichtman, Allan J. &quot;Critical elections theory and the reality of American presidential politics, 1916–40.&quot; ''American Historical Review'' (1976) 81: 317–348. in JSTOR
*Lichtman, Allan J. &quot;Political Realignment and 'Ethnocultural' Voting in Late Nineteenth Century America,&quot; ''Journal of Social History'', Vol. 16, No. 3 (Spring, 1983), pp.&amp;nbsp;55–82 [http://www.jstor.org/stable/3786930 in JSTOR]
*Manza, Jeff and Clem Brooks; ''Social Cleavages and Political Change: Voter Alignments and U.S. Party Coalitions,'' Oxford University Press, 1999 (ISBN 0-19-829492-1)
* McCormick, Richard P. ''The Second American Party System: Party Formation in the Jacksonian Era'' 1966. (ISBN 0-39-300680-8)
* Maisel, L. Sandy, ed. ''Political Parties and Elections in the United States: An Encyclopedia''. 1991. (ISBN 0-82-407975-2)
* Mayhew, David R. ''Electoral Realignments: A Critique of an American Genre''. 2004. (ISBN 0-30-009336-5)
* Paulson, Arthur. ''Electoral Realignment and the Outlook for American Democracy'' (2006) (ISBN 1-55-553667-0)
* Rosenof, Theodore. ''Realignment: The Theory That Changed the Way We Think about American Politics'' (2003) (ISBN 0-74-253105-8)
* Rapoport, Ronald and Walter Stone. 2005. ''Three's a Crowd: The Dynamic of Third Parties, Ross Perot, and Republican Resurgence''. (ISBN 0-47-211453-0)
* Saunders, Kyle L. and Alan I. Abramowitz. 2004. “Ideological Realignment and Active Partisans in the American Electorate.” American Politics Research 32(3):285–309.
* Schafer, Byron (ed.). 1991. &quot;Critical realignment: Dead or alive?&quot;  in ''The End of Realignment'' Madison: University of Wisconsin Press
* Schlesinger, Arthur M. Jr., ed. ''History of American Presidential Elections''. 4 vols. 1971 and later editions (ISBN 0-79-105713-5)
* Shafer, Byron E. and Anthony J. Badger, eds. ''Contesting Democracy: Substance and Structure in American Political History, 1775–2000'' (2001) (ISBN 0-70-061139-8)
* Sternsher, Bernard. &quot;The New Deal Party System: A Reappraisal,&quot; ''Journal of Interdisciplinary History'' v.15#1 (Summer, 1984), pp.&amp;nbsp;53–81 [http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0022-1953%28198422%2915%3A1%3C53%3ATNDPSA%3E2.0.CO%3B2-I JSTOR]
* Silbey, Joel. ''The American Political Nation, 1838–1893''. Stanford: Stanford University Press, 1991. (ISBN 0-80-472338-9)
* [http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=29223022  * Sundquist, James L. ''Dynamics of the Party System: Alignment and Realignment of Political Parties in the United States'' (1983)] (ISBN 0-81-578225-X)

==External links==
*[http://dca.tufts.edu/features/aas/index.html A New Nation Votes: American Election Returns, 1787–1825]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Realigning Election}}
[[Category:Elections terminology]]

[[ar:انتخابات حاسمة]]
[[simple:Party realignment]]</text>
      <sha1>mm0u2bbpkzr7zpykjvzyeji0rldfcds</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
