<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Recall election</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>129203</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521867377</id>
      <parentid>521488010</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-07T19:07:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>69.155.81.253</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Successful recalls */  Added Janice Daniels</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25468">{{Elections}}
A '''recall election''' (also called a '''recall referendum''' or '''representative recall''') is a procedure by which voters can remove an elected official from office through a direct vote  before his or her term has ended. Recalls, which are initiated when sufficient voters sign a petition, have a history dating back to the ancient Athenian democracy&lt;ref&gt;Aristotle, ''Constitution of Athens'' 43.4&lt;/ref&gt; and are a feature of several contemporary constitutions.

==Canada==
The [[British Columbia|Province of British Columbia]] enacted representative recall in 1995. In that province, voters in a provincial [[electoral district (Canada)|riding]] can petition to have a sitting representative removed from office, even a Premier presently leading a government. If enough registered voters sign the [[petition]], the Speaker of the legislature announces before the House that the member has been recalled and a [[by-election]] follows as soon as possible, giving voters the opportunity to replace the politician in question.  By January 2003, 22 recall efforts had been launched.  No one has been recalled so far, but one representative, [[Paul Reitsma]], resigned in 1998 when it looked as if the petition to recall him would have enough signatures to spur a recall election.  Reitsma resigned during the secondary verification stage, and the recall count ended. {{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}

==Switzerland==
While recalls are not provided for at the federal level in Switzerland, six [[Cantons of Switzerland|cantons]] allow them:&lt;ref name=NZZ&gt;{{cite news|last=Jankovsky|first=Peter|title=Der Versuch, eine Exekutive zu stoppen|accessdate=22 March 2011|newspaper=[[Neue Zürcher Zeitung]]|date=22 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Canton of Bern|Bern]]: Recall of the executive and legislative is possible since 1846. 30,000 signatures (4% of all adult citizens) are required to trigger a recall referendum. There has been one unsuccessful attempt to recall the executive in 1852.
*[[Schaffhausen]]: Recall of the executive and legislative is possible since 1876. 1,000 signatures (2% of all adult citizens) are required to trigger a recall referendum. There has been one unsuccessful attempt to recall the executive in 2000.
*[[Canton of Solothurn|Solothurn]]: Recall of the executive and legislative is possible since 1869. 6,000 signatures (3% of all adult citizens) are required to trigger a recall referendum. There has been one unsuccessful attempt to recall the executive and legislative in 1995.
*[[Ticino]]: Recall of the executive is possible since 1892. 15,000 signatures (7% of all adult citizens) are required to trigger a recall referendum. There has been one unsuccessful recall attempt in 1942. In addition, recall of municipal executives is possible since 2011. Signatures of 30% of all adult citizens are required to trigger a recall referendum.
*[[Thurgau]]: Recall of the executive and legislative is possible since 1869. 20,000 signatures (13% of all adult citizens) are required to trigger a recall referendum. There have been no recall attempts.
*[[Canton of Uri|Uri]]: Recall of the executive and legislative is possible since 1988. 600 signatures (3% of all adult citizens) are required to trigger a recall referendum. In addition, recall of municipal executives and legislatives is possible since 2011. Signatures of 10% of registered voters are required to trigger a recall referendum. There have been no recall attempts either at the cantonal or municipal levels.

The possibility of recall referenda (together with the popular election of executives, the [[initiative]] and the legislative referendum) was introduced into several cantonal constitutions after the 1860s in the course of a broad movement for democratic reform. The instrument has never been of any practical importance – the few attempts at recall so far have failed, usually because the required number of signatures was not collected – and it was abolished in the course of constitutional revisions in [[Aargau]] (1980), [[Baselland]] (1984) and [[Canton of Lucerne|Lucerne]] (2007). But the possibility of recalling municipal executives was newly introduced in Ticino in 2011, with 59% of voters in favor, as a reaction to the perceived problem of squabbling and dysfunctional municipal governments.&lt;ref name=NZZ /&gt;

==United States==
[[File:Presenting Seattle recall petitions 1910.jpg|thumb|400 px|Submitting petitions for the recall of [[Seattle, Washington]] mayor [[Hiram Gill]] in December 1910; Gill was removed by a recall election the following February, but voters returned him to the office in 1914.]]
Recall first appeared in Colonial America in the laws of the General Court of the Massachusetts Bay Colony in 1631.&lt;ref&gt;Joshua Spivak, History News Network, http://hnn.us/articles/1660.html&lt;/ref&gt; This version of the recall involved one elected body removing another official. During the American Revolution the Articles of Confederation stipulated that state legislatures might recall delegates from the continental congress.&lt;ref&gt;Article V of the Articles of Confederation provided, &quot;a power reserved to each state, to recall its delegates, or any of them, at any time within the year, and to send others in their stead, for the remainder of the Year.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;  According to New York Delegate John Lansing, the power was never exercised by any state. The [[Virginia Plan]], issued at the outset of the [[Philadelphia Convention]] of 1787, proposed to pair recall with rotation in office and to apply these dual principles to the lower house of the national legislature. The recall was rejected by the Constitutional Convention. However, the anti-Federalists used the lack of recall provision as a weapon in the ratification debates.

Several states proposed adopting a recall for US senators in the years immediately following the adoption of the Constitution. However, it did not pass.

Only two governors have ever been successfully recalled. In 1921, [[Lynn Frazier]], Governor of [[North Dakota]], was recalled during a dispute about state-owned industries. In 2003, Governor [[Gray Davis]] of [[California]] was recalled over the state budget. In 2012, [[Wisconsin|Wisconsin's]] governor, [[Scott Walker (politician)|Scott Walker]] became the first US governor to survive a recall election.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Carrol|first=Rory|title=Wisconsin governor Scott Walker survives bitterly fought recall election|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2012/jun/06/wisconsin-governor-scott-walker-survives-recall|accessdate=6 June 2012|newspaper=The Guardian|date=6 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, in 1988, a recall was approved against [[Arizona]] Governor [[Evan Mecham]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Watkins |first=Ronald J.|title=High Crimes and Misdemeanors : The Term and Trials of Former Governor Evan Mecham|publisher=William Morrow &amp; Co |location=New York |year=1990 |isbn=0-688-09051-6|pages=194–195, 274}}&lt;/ref&gt; but he was impeached and convicted before it got on the ballot.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nytimes.com/1988/04/13/us/arizona-s-supreme-court-blocks-a-special-gubernatorial-election.html |title=Arizona's Supreme Court Blocks A Special Gubernatorial Election |pages=A20:1 |work=The New York Times |date=April 13, 1988}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Alaska]], [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]], [[Kansas]], [[Minnesota]], [[Montana]], [[Rhode Island]], and [[Washington (U.S. state)|Washington]], specific grounds are required for a recall. Some form of malfeasance or misconduct while in office must be identified by the petitioners. The target may choose to dispute the validity of the grounds in court, and a court then judges whether the allegations in the petition rise to a level where a recall is necessary. In the November 2010 general election, [[Illinois]] passed a [[referendum]] to amend the state constitution to allow a recall in light of ex-Governor [[Rod Blagojevich corruption charges|Rod Blagojevich's corruption scandal]]. In the other eleven states that permit state-wide recall, no grounds are required and recall petitions may be circulated for any reason.  However, the target is permitted to submit responses to the stated reasons for recall.

The minimum number of signatures and the time limit to qualify a recall vary among the states. In addition, the handling of recalls once they qualify differs. In some states, a recall triggers a simultaneous special election, where the vote on the recall, as well as the vote on the replacement if the recall succeeds, are on the same ballot. In the [[California recall election, 2003|2003 California recall election]], over 100 candidates appeared on the replacement portion of the ballot. In other states, a separate special election is held after the target is recalled, or a replacement is appointed by the Governor or some other state authority.

===2011 recalls===
In 2011, there were at least 150 recall elections in the United States. Of these, 75 officials were recalled, and nine officials resigned under threat of recall. Recalls were held in 17 states in 73 different jurisdictions. [[Michigan]] had the most recalls (at least 30). The year set a record for number of state legislator recall elections (11 elections) beating with previous one-year high (three elections). Three jurisdictions adopted the recall in 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;blogspot1&quot;&gt;http://recallelections.blogspot.com/2011/12/year-in-recalls-150-recalls-in-2011.html&lt;/ref&gt;

Of recall elections, 52 were for [[city council]], 30 were for [[mayor]], 17 were for [[school board]], 11 were for [[state legislators]], one was for [[prosecuting attorney]] ([[York County, Nebraska]]). The largest municipality to hold a recall was [[Miami-Dade County, Florida]], for mayor.&lt;ref name=&quot;blogspot1&quot;/&gt;

The busiest day was November 8 ([[Election Day (United States)|Election Day]]) with 26 recalls. In 34 jurisdictions, recalls were held over multiple days.&lt;ref name=&quot;blogspot1&quot;/&gt;

===Successful recalls===
*1911 recall of [[Hiram Gill]], mayor of [[Seattle, Washington]]&lt;ref&gt;Burton J. Hendrick, &quot;The 'Recall' in Seattle', ''[[McClure's]]'', October 1911, p. 647–663.&lt;/ref&gt;
*1916 recall of [[J. W. Robinson (Boise mayor)|J. W. Robinson]], mayor of [[Boise, Idaho]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.idahohistory.net/Reference%20Series/0047.pdf |title=Idaho State Historical Society Reference Series, Corrected List of Mayors, 1867-1996|format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2010-05-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[North Dakota recall election, 1921|1921 recall]] of [[Lynn Frazier]], [[governor of North Dakota]]
*1928 [[Lester R. Rice-Wray]], [[Los Angeles, California]], City Council member
*1983 recall of Michigan state senators Phil Mastin and David Serotkin due to their support for a state income tax hike. Loss of these two Democratic lawmakers, along with two special elections won by Republicans, flipped the state senate to GOP control, where it has remained ever since (as of September 2011.)
*1987 recall of [[Mike Boyle]], mayor of [[Omaha, Nebraska]].
*1987 recall of [[James W. Holley, III|James Holley]], mayor of [[Portsmouth, Virginia]]
*1994 recall of officials in [[River Vale, New Jersey]]: Mayor Walter Jones, Councilwoman Patricia Geier, and Councilman Bernard Salmon&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=River Vale Recall Vote Offers Two Slates Split by 911 Issue|last=James|first=Michael S.|date=July 22, 1994|work=The Bergen Record|accessdate=2008-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*1995 recall of [[California State Assembly]]man [[Paul Horcher]]
*1995 recall of [[California State Assembly]] Speaker [[Doris Allen (politician)|Doris Allen]]
*1996 recall of Carrollton Texas mayor Gary Blanscet and council members Stan Sewell, Linda Caldwell, Bernis Francis, Stan Hampton, Bob Novinsky and Bert Colter.
*1996 recall of [[Wisconsin Senate|Wisconsin State Senator]] [[George Petak]]&lt;ref name=&quot;state1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.legis.state.wi.us/LRB/gw/gw_13.pdf |title=State.wi.us |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2010-05-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*2002 recall of [[Woodrow Stanley]], mayor of [[Flint, Michigan]].
*2002 recall of multiple [[Milwaukee County, Wisconsin]], elected county officials including Executive [[Tom Ament|F. Thomas Ament]] (resigned before election); Board Chair Karen Ordinans; and Board Supervisors Penny Podell, LeAnn Launstein, David Jasenski, Kathy Arciszewski, James McGuigan, and Linda Ryan.  All were recalled due to a retirement pension controversy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.legis.state.wi.us/LRB/gw/gw_13.pdf State.wi.us], Wisconsin Constitution Article XIII, section 12&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[California gubernatorial recall election, 2003|2003 recall]] of [[Gray Davis]], [[governor of California]]
*2003 recall of Wisconsin State Senator [[Gary George (Wisconsin politician)|Gary George]]&lt;ref name=&quot;state1&quot;/&gt;
*2005 recall of [[James E. West (politician)|James E. West]], mayor of [[Spokane, Washington]].
*2006 recall of Neil Marko, mayor of [[Roosevelt, New Jersey]].
*2008 recall of Carmen Kontur-Gronquist, mayor of [[Arlington, Oregon]].
*2010 recall of [[James W. Holley, III|James Holley]], mayor of [[Portsmouth, Virginia]].
*2011 recall of [[Carlos Alvarez (mayor)|Carlos Alvarez]], mayor of [[Miami-Dade County, Florida]].
*2011 recall of Wisconsin State Senator [[Randy Hopper]]
*2011 recall of Wisconsin State Senator [[Dan Kapanke]]
*2011 recall of Neal Knight, mayor of [[Cornelius, Oregon]], and city councilors Mari Gottwald and Jamie Minshall, less than a year after their election, due to unhappiness over their votes to fire the city manager.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cornelius, OR, recall&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Fuller|first=Kathy|title=Cornelius voters oust 'Team 3' from office|url=http://www.oregonlive.com/argus/index.ssf/2011/09/cornelius_voters_oust_team_3_f.html|newspaper=Hillsboro Argus|location=[[Hillsboro, Oregon|Hillsboro, OR]]|date=September 30, 2011|accessdate=October 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*2011 recall of multiple [[Killeen, Texas]] elected city officials including Mayor Pro Tem Scott Cosper and four city council members.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.kdhnews.com/news/story.aspx?s=62160&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2011 recall of [[Arizona Senate|Arizona state senator]] [[Russell Pearce]].
* 2011 recall of Michigan Representative [[Paul H. Scott|Paul Scott]]
* 2012 recall of [[Bob Ryan (mayor)|Bob Ryan]], Mayor of Sheboygan, WI&lt;ref name=&quot;Sheboygan, WI, recall&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Sheboygan mayoral recall: Mayor Bob Ryan ousted from office by challenger Terry Van Akkeren|url=http://www.sheboyganpress.com/article/20120222/SHE0104/120221205/Van-Akkeren-wins-ousts-incumbent-Ryan-historic-mayoral-recall-election|newspaper=Sheboygan Press|location=[[Sheboygan, Wisconsin|Sheboygan, WI]]|date=February 21, 2012|accessdate=February 22, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2012 recall of Wisconsin State Senator [[Van H. Wanggaard]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Wisconsin Recall Results&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Wisconsin June 5 recall election results|url=http://www.jsonline.com/news/statepolitics/june-5-recall-election-results-155977565.html|newspaper=Milwakee Wisconsin Journal-Sentinel|date=June 6, 2012|accessdate=June 10, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2012 recall of Janice Daniels, Mayor of [[Troy, Michigan]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Troy MI Recall Results&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=RECALLED: Troy Mayor Janice Daniels Voted Out of Office|url=http://troy.patch.com/articles/troy-mayor-janice-daniels-recall-election|newspaper=Troy Patch|date=November 7, 2012|accessdate=November 7, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Unsuccessful recalls===
*1932 recall election of Wisconsin State Senator [[Otto Mueller (Wisconsin politician)|Otto Mueller]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ncsl.org/default.aspx?tabid=16581 Recall Election]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Cleveland recall election, 1978|1978 Cleveland Recall Election]] of Mayor [[Dennis Kucinich]]
*1983 recall of [[San Francisco Mayor]] [[Dianne Feinstein]]
*2008 recall of [[California State Senate|California State Senator]] [[Jeff Denham]]
*2008 recall of [[Michigan House of Representatives]] Speaker [[Andy Dillon]]
*In 2009, a petition for the recall of [[San Jose City Council|San Jose, California city Council]] member [[Madison Nguyen]] obtained enough signatures to qualify the recall for the ballot; but the subsequent recall election failed.
*2009 recall of [[Akron, Ohio|Akron]] Mayor [[Don Plusquellic]]
*2010 recall of Mayor [[Anthony R. Suarez]] in [[Ridgefield, New Jersey]]
*2011 recall of [[Omaha| Omaha Nebraska]] Mayor [[Jim Suttle]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.omaha.com/article/20110125/NEWS01/110129780&lt;/ref&gt;
*2011 recall of Wisconsin State Senator [[Dave Hansen]]
*2011 recall of Wisconsin State Senator [[Robert Cowles]]
*2011 recall of Wisconsin State Senator [[Sheila Harsdorf]]
*2011 recall of Wisconsin State Senator [[Luther Olsen]]
*2011 recall of Wisconsin State Senator [[Alberta Darling]]
*2011 recall of Wisconsin State Senator [[Robert Wirch]]
*2011 recall of Wisconsin State Senator [[Jim Holperin]]
*[[Wisconsin gubernatorial recall election|2012 recall]] of Wisconsin Governor [[Scott Walker (politician)|Scott Walker]]
*2012 recall of Wisconsin Lieutenant Governor [[Rebecca Kleefisch]]
*2012 recall of [[Wisconsin]] State Senator [[Scott L. Fitzgerald]]
*2012 recall of Wisconsin State Senator [[Terry Moulton]]

===Unsuccessful attempts to qualify recall elections===
* 1967 [[United States Senator]] [[Frank Church]] of [[Idaho]] was the subject of an unsuccessful recall effort.&lt;ref&gt;[http://library.boisestate.edu/special/church/CHURCH1.HTM Frank Church Chronology]{{dead link|date=May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Courts ruled that a federal official is not subject to state recall laws.
* 1988 [[Evan Mecham]], Governor of [[Arizona]], was scheduled for a recall election on May 17 of that year, after a successful petition drive (301,000 signatures).  However, the Supreme Court of Arizona canceled the election, since Mecham had already been impeached and removed from office by the Senate on April 4.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Arizona's Supreme Court Blocks A Special Gubernatorial Election |pages=A20:1 |publisher=The [[New York Times]] |date=April 13, 1988}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*1992-93 California Governor [[Pete Wilson]] was targeted for recall by the ''[[Bite 'Em Back]]'' campaign, which was a [[grassroots]] effort that came about as a result of a piece by ''[[San Jose Mercury News]]'' [[columnist]] [[San Jose Mercury News West Magazine|Pat Dillon]], in response to the then-ongoing California budgetary crisis.&lt;ref&gt;[http://titanyearbook.com/archives/1992/1992-11-18.pdf Daily Titan], &quot;''Group asks for Wilson's recall'',&quot; by Matt Cliff (November 18th, 1992 - retrieved on June 18th, 2011).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.latimes.com/1992-10-04/local/me-780_1_valley-college Los Anegles Times], &quot;''VALLEY COLLEGE:  Wilson Recall Campaign Started'',&quot; by Jennifer Case (October 4th, 1992 - retrieved on June 19th, 2011).&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Bite 'Em Back'' campaign also intended to recall then-[[List of Speakers of the California State Assembly|Speaker]] of the [[California State Assembly|Assembly]] [[Willie L. Brown]], and then-[[President pro tempore of the California State Senate|President Pro Tem]] of the [[California State Senate|state Senate]], [[David Roberti]].{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}
*2009 [[Joseph Cao]] [[U.S. representative]] for [[Louisiana's 2nd congressional district]], was determined to inelligble for recall as per his status as a [[Federal government of the United States|Federal]] office holder.
*2009 a petition failed to garner sufficient signatures to oblige an election for [[Eddie Price III#Failure of recall petition|recall of Eddie Price III]], mayor of [[Mandeville, Louisiana]].
*2009 a petition for [[Malcolm Suber|recall of Stacy Head]], [[New Orleans]] city councilwoman, likewise failed to gain the requisite number of signatures.
*2010 there were two unsuccessful recall petitions for [[Sam Adams (Oregon politician)|Sam Adams]] mayor of [[Portland, OR]].
*2010 there was one unsuccessful recall petition for [[Lisa Poppaw]] city council member of [[Fort Collins, CO]].
*2010 there was one unsuccessful recall petition for [[Antonio Villaraigosa]] mayor of [[Los Angeles, CA]].
*2010, a recall proposal aimed at mayor [[Ron Littlefield]] of [[Chattanooga, Tennessee]] failed after a judge of the [[Hamilton County, Tennessee]] [[circuit court]] ruled that too many of the petition signatures were invalid and that the petitioners had failed to properly adhere to the state's recall law, leaving &quot;pages without dates.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://chattanoogan.com/articles/article_183480.asp]&lt;/ref&gt;
*2011, the [[Tennessee Court of Appeals]] ruled in November that the Hamilton County Circuit Court Judge [[Jeff Hollingsworth]] did not have the jurisdiction in entering an injunction against the Hamilton County Election Commission. In its judgment summary the Appeals Court said, &quot;The trial court acted without jurisdiction in entering an injunction against the Election Commission. The judgment of the trial court is vacated and the complaint dismissed.&quot; Mayor Littlefield is continuing legal action to stop the recall.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chattanoogan.com/articles/article_212673.asp]&lt;/ref&gt;
*2011, as part of the [[Wisconsin Senate recall elections, 2011]], there were a number of failed recall petitions.  Petitions against senators [[Lena Taylor]] (D), [[Spencer Coggs]] (D), [[Mark F. Miller|Mark Miller]] (D), [[Glenn Grothman]] (R), [[Julie Lassa]] (D), [[Fred Risser]] (D), and [[Mary Lazich]] (R), were unsuccessful.  Many senators had multiple recall petitions filed against them, and in the case of both Wirch and Hansen, one succeeded while others failed.
*2011, an effort to recall [[Michigan]] [[Governor of Michigan|Governor]] [[Rick Snyder]] was ended after organizers did not obtain enough petition signatures to appear on the ballot.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mlive.com/lansing-news/index.ssf/2011/09/report_effort_to_recall_michig.html?utm_medium=twitter&amp;utm_source=twitterfeed&lt;/ref&gt;
*2011, an attempt to prompt recall election of [[Trenton, New Jersey]] mayor [[Tony F. Mack]] failed to obtain enough support.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nj.com/mercer/index.ssf/2011/11/committee_to_recall_mayor_mack.html&lt;/ref&gt;
*2011 recall of Alaska State Representative [[Kyle Johansen]], sponsored by an opposing faction within the local Republican Party. Rejected by Alaska Division of Elections on Oct 10, 2011 &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.krbd.org/2011/10/11/recall-application-rejected/ ''KRBD,'' &quot;Recall application rejected,&quot; October 11, 2011]&lt;/ref&gt;
*2012 recall of [[Wisconsin]] State Senator [[Pam Galloway]]. On March 16, 2012, Galloway announced her resignation from office due to health issues in her family&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.jsonline.com/news/statepolitics/state-sen-galloway-to-resign-4c4jk6e-142927885.html|title = State Sen. Galloway to resign, leaving Senate split|date = March 16, 2012|author = Patrick Marley|publisher = [[Milwaukee Journal Sentinel]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Current===

==Venezuela==
Article 72 of the [[Constitution of Venezuela]] enables the recall of any elected representative, including the President. This provision was used in the [[Venezuelan recall referendum, 2004]], which attempted to remove President [[Hugo Chavez]]:

:&lt;small&gt;&lt;u&gt;Article 72&lt;/u&gt;: All &lt;nowiki&gt;[...]&lt;/nowiki&gt; offices filled by popular vote are subject to revocation.&lt;/small&gt;
:&lt;small&gt;Once one-half of the term of office to which an official has been elected has elapsed, a number of voters representing at least 20% of the registered voters in the affected constituency may petition for the calling of a referendum to revoke that official's mandate.&lt;/small&gt;
:&lt;small&gt;When a number of voters equal to or greater than the number of those who elected the official vote in favour of the recall, provided that a number of voters equal to or greater than 25% of the total number of registered voters vote in the recall referendum, the official's mandate shall be deemed revoked and immediate action shall be taken to fill the permanent vacancy as provided for by this Constitution and by law.&lt;/small&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Politics}}
'''General'''

*[[Motion of no confidence]]
*[[Ostracism]], the process by which Athenians could ban a possible tyrant from the city
*[[Popular referendum]]
*[[Imperative mandate]]

==Bibliography==
*[http://books.google.com/books?id=23tBFmXLxAMC&amp;pg=PP1&amp;dq=inauthor:alexander+inauthor:santana&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=1&amp;as_pt=ALLTYPES&amp;ei=OPlwScWeN4TkygShjsSgBA SANTANA, Alexander. ''O direito de revogação do mandato político representativo.'' Curitiba, 2004. 146 f. Monografia (Graduação em Direito) - Setor de Ciências Jurídicas, Universidade Federal do Paraná.] (wrote in [[Brazilian Portuguese]]) English Title: ''The right of recall elected officials.''
*Paolo Ronchi, Una Forma di Democrazia Diretta: L'Esperienza del Recall Negli Stati Uniti d'America, in &quot;Quaderni dell'Osservatorio elettorale&quot;, num. 61, 2009, pp.&amp;nbsp;99–130, also published in [http://www.forumcostituzionale.it/site/images/stories/pdf/documenti_forum/paper/0143_ronchi.pdf Forumcostituzionale.it] {{it icon}} En. Title: “A form of direct democracy: the experience of the recall in the United States of America”.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Recall Election}}
[[Category:Recall elections| ]]
[[Category:Right to petition]]
[[Category:Ballot measures]]

[[de:Recall (Politik)]]
[[ko:소환투표제]]
[[hi:वापस बुलाने का अधिकार]]
[[he:Recall Election]]
[[ja:リコール (地方公共団体)]]
[[no:Tilbakekallingsvalg]]
[[pl:Recall]]
[[pt:Recall político]]
[[sv:Recall]]
[[th:การถอดถอนผู้ได้รับเลือกตั้ง]]
[[zh:罢免选举]]</text>
      <sha1>pmwn6jpmoxt4xbbekxe5m1vg5jq7dz8</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
