<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Redistribution of wealth</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>21554936</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522305929</id>
      <parentid>522304193</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T09:15:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Saddhiyama</username>
        <id>5160420</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 521751720 by [[Special:Contributions/108.100.19.25|108.100.19.25]] ([[User talk:108.100.19.25|talk]])-rv spammer</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23712">[[File:Distribution of Wealth in the United States.jpg|thumb|U.S. mean family net worth by percentile of net worth (1989–2010).]]
'''Redistribution of wealth''' is the transfer of [[income]], [[wealth]] or [[property]] from some [[individual]]s to others caused by a social mechanism such as [[tax]]ation, [[Monetary policy|monetary policies]], [[welfare]], [[charitable organization|charity]], [[divorce]] or [[tort]] law.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/redistribution/ |title=Redistribution |date=2 July 2004 |work=Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy  |publisher=Stanford University |quote=&quot;The ''social mechanism'', such as a change in tax laws, monetary policies, or tort law, that engenders the redistribution of goods among these subjects&quot;|accessdate=13 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The desirability and effects of redistribution are actively debated on ethical and economic grounds.

== Types of redistribution ==
Today, income redistribution occurs in some form in most [[Democracy|democratic]] countries. In a [[Progressive tax|progressive income tax]] system, a high income earner will pay a higher tax rate than a low income earner. The difference between the [[Gini index]] for an income distribution before taxation and the Gini index after taxation is an indicator for the effects of such taxation.
{{rquote|right|Money is like [[manure|muck]], not good except it be spread.|[[Francis Bacon]], 'Of seditions and Troubles', ''Essays,'' 15.}}
''Property redistribution'' is a term applied to various policies involving taxation or [[nationalization]] of [[property]], or of [[regulation]]s ordering [[Ownership|owners]] to make their property available to others. Public programs and policy measures involving redistribution of property include [[eminent domain]], [[land reform]], [[inheritance tax]] and certain provisions found in [[family law]].

Two common types of governmental redistribution of wealth are subsidies and vouchers (such as [[Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program|food stamps]]).  These &quot;[[transfer payment]]&quot; programs are funded through general taxation, but disproportionately benefit the poor, who pay fewer or no taxes.  While the persons receiving redistributions from such programs may prefer to be directly given cash, these programs may be more palatable to society, as it gives society some measure of control over how the funds are spent.&lt;ref&gt;Harvey S. Rosen &amp; Ted Gayer, Public Finance p. 271-72 (2010).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Current policy illustration===

Currently in the [[United States]], any [[means-tested]] [[entitlement program]] can be considered a redistributive effort. This is because the US Government practices a progressive income tax that disproportionately yields public [[revenue]]s from various earnings brackets. As the wealthy pay more into the system and the poor receive more [[marginal utility]] through programs such as [[TANF]], [[Medicaid]], [[FHA insured loans]], and the [[earned income tax credit]] (all of which are means-tested), it could be argued that the United States has democratically opted for the redistribution of wealth.  Each of these programs provide services or financial aid to the poor.

==Supporting arguments==
{{Refimprove-section|date=January 2011}}
[[File:Global Distribution of Wealth v3.jpg|thumb|The distribution of total liquid net worth in the world per person in 2012.  The chart is divided into the top .001% (91 thousand people), the next .01% (800 thousand people), the next .1% (8 million people), and the bottom 99.9% (6 billion people).&lt;ref&gt;http://www.taxjustice.net/cms/upload/pdf/The_Price_of_Offshore_Revisited_Presser_120722.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The objectives of income redistribution are varied and almost always include the funding of [[public services]]. Supporters of redistributive policies argue that less [[Social stratification|stratified]] [[Economics|economies]] are more [[Social justice#General understanding of social justice|socially just]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/redistribution/ Redistribution (Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

One basis for redistribution is the concept of [[distributive justice#Distributive justice and wealth|distributive justice and wealth]]. One premise of redistribution is that money should be distributed to benefit the poorer members of society, and that the rich have an obligation to assist the poor, thus creating a more financially [[Egalitarianism|egalitarian]] society.{{Citation needed|date=July 2007}} This argument rests on the [[social welfare function]], or the concept that society’s [[utility]] is made up in some way through the utilities of its individuals. Particularly the Max-Min or Maximin Criterion for social welfare explains this concept:
:&lt;math&gt;W = \min(Y_1, Y_2, \cdots, Y_n)&lt;/math&gt;
This states that the utility of society (W) is dependent on that of the least (min) individual (Y&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;), or in terms of income, the poorest individual. In this case, society would want to distribute income to the poorest individuals until all incomes were equal. 

Another argument is that the rich [[Exploitation|exploit]] the poor or otherwise gain unfair benefits{{Citation needed|date=December 2011}}, and thus should return some of those benefits. Another argument is that a larger [[middle class]] benefits an economy by enabling more people to be consumers, while providing equal opportunities for individuals to reach a better standard of living.{{Citation needed|date=May 2009}} 

Some proponents of redistribution argue that [[capitalism]] results in an [[externality]] that creates unequal wealth distribution.&lt;ref&gt;Marx, K. A Contribution to the Critique of Political Economy. Progress Publishers, Moscow, 1977&lt;/ref&gt; They also argue that [[economic inequality]] contributes to crime{{Citation needed|date=December 2011}}. There is also the issue of [[equal opportunity]] to access services such as education and health care. Studies show that a lower rate of redistribution in a given society increases the inequality found among future incomes, due to restraints on wealth investments in both human and physical capital.&lt;ref name=&quot;Econ Review&quot;&gt;http://www.jstor.org/stable/117283 Unequal Societies: Income Distribution and the Social Contract. Roland Benabou. ''The American Economic Review'', Vol. 90, No. 1 (March 2000), pp.96-129.&lt;/ref&gt;  Roland Benabou states that greater inequality and a lower redistribution rate decreases the likelihood that the lower class will register to vote.&lt;ref name=&quot;Econ Review&quot;/&gt; Benabou does not find a relationship between levels of inequality and government welfare transfers to the needy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Econ Review&quot;/&gt;

Some{{who|date=December 2011}} argue that wealth and income inequality are a cause of [[economic crises]], and that reducing these inequalities is one way to prevent or ameliorate economic crises, with redistribution thus benefiting the economy overall{{Citation needed|date=December 2011}}, there being synergies{{Citation needed|date=December 2011}}. This view was associated with the [[underconsumptionism]] school in the 19th century, now considered an aspect of some schools of [[Keynesian economics]]{{Citation needed|date=December 2011}}; it has also been advanced, for different reasons, by [[Marxian economics]]. It was particularly advanced in the US in the 1920s by [[Waddill Catchings]] and [[William Trufant Foster]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harv|Dorfman|1959}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Allgoewer&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Allgoewer|first=Elisabeth|date=May 2002|title= Underconsumption theories and Keynesian economics. Interpretations of the Great Depression|journal=Discussion paper no. 2002-14|url=http://www.vwa.unisg.ch/RePEc/usg/dp2002/dp0214allgoewer_ganz.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A system with no redistribution of wealth which adds some measure of redistribution may actually experience a [[Pareto efficiency|Pareto]] Improvement, meaning that no persons within the system are worse off and at least one person is better off.  Such an outcome is most likely if all high-income people in the system are [[altruist]]ic in nature, in that they derive some economic utility in giving to the poor.  For example, a rich person may experience more utility from giving $100 to the poor than they would have gained had they spent $100 on something for themselves.  The poor person receiving the $100 will also be better off.  In addition to altruistic reasons, rich persons may support governmental redistribution of wealth: 1) as a form of [[insurance]] policy (should they ever become poor, the policy pays off and they are able to collect benefits from the government); or 2) because it improves social stability (lowers crime and rioting among poor people){{Citation needed|date=December 2011}}, allowing rich persons to more easily enjoy the benefits of their wealth.&lt;ref&gt;Harvey S. Rosen &amp; Ted Gayer, Public Finance p. 265-66 (2010).&lt;/ref&gt;

According to one study, &quot;All demographic groups—even those not usually associated with wealth redistribution such as Republicans and the wealthy—desired a more equal distribution of wealth than the status quo.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Norton, M. I., &amp; [[Ariely]], D., [http://www.people.hbs.edu/mnorton/norton%20ariely%20in%20press.pdf &quot;Building a Better America – One Wealth Quintile at a Time&quot;], [[Perspectives on Psychological Science]], January 2011 6: 9-12&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;nowiki&gt;[in the USA]&lt;/nowiki&gt;

===Economic effects===
{{Seealso|Economic inequality#Inequality and economic growth}}
[[File:Number of High Net Worth Individuals, 2011 v4.jpg|thumb|Number of high net worth individuals in the world, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.taxjustice.net/cms/upload/pdf/Price_of_Offshore_Revisited_120722.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;]]
[[File:Employment_growth_by_top_tax_rate.jpg|thumb|right|Average annual growth in U.S. employment, by top income tax bracket rate, 1940-2011]]

Using statistics from 23 developed countries and the 50 states of the US, British researchers [[Richard G. Wilkinson]] and [[Kate Pickett]] show a correlation between income inequality on the one hand and  higher rates of health and social problems ([[obesity]], [[mental illness]], [[homicide]]s, [[teenage birth]]s, [[List of countries by incarceration rate|incarceration]], child conflict, drug use), and lower rates of social goods ([[List of countries by life expectancy|life expectancy]], educational performance, [[Trust (social sciences)|trust among strangers]], [[Women's_rights#2011_study_of_status_by_country|women's status]], [[social mobility]], even numbers of [[patent]]s issued per capita), on the other.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.equalitytrust.org.uk/resources/slides Statistics and graphs from Wilkinson and Pickett research.]&lt;/ref&gt;  The authors argue inequality leads to the social ills through the psychosocial [[Stress (psychological)|stress]], [[Social status|status]] anxiety it creates.&lt;ref name=thinktanks&gt;http://www.guardian.co.uk/books/2010/aug/14/the-spirit-level-equality-thinktanks The Spirit Level: how 'ideas wreckers' turned book into political punchbag]| Robert Booth| The Guardian| 13 August 2010 &lt;/ref&gt;

A 2011 report by the [[International Monetary Fund]] by Andrew G. Berg and Jonathan D. Ostry found a strong association between lower levels of inequality and sustained periods of economic growth. Developing countries (such as Brazil, Cameroon, Jordan) with high inequality have &quot;succeeded in initiating growth at high rates for a few years&quot; but &quot;longer growth spells are robustly associated with more equality in the income distribution.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/sdn/2011/sdn1108.pdf Inequality and Unsustainable Growth: Two Sides of the Same Coin?] Andrew G. Berg and Jonathan D. Ostry| IMF STAFF DISCUSSION NOTE | April 8, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=BergOstryEE&gt;{{Cite journal |last= Berg |first= Andrew G. |last2= Ostry |first2= Jonathan D. |date= 2011 |title= Equality and Efficiency |journal= Finance and Development |volume= 48 |issue= 3 |publisher= International Monetary Fund |url= http://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/fandd/2011/09/berg.htm |accessdate= September 10, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Supply-side economics]] is a school of [[macroeconomic]] thought that argues that [[economic growth]] can be most effectively created by lowering barriers for people to produce (supply) goods and services, such as lowering [[income tax]] and [[capital gains tax]] rates, and by allowing greater flexibility by reducing regulation. According to supply-side economics, consumers will then benefit from a greater supply of goods and services at lower prices.  Typical policy recommendations of supply-side economists are lower [[marginal tax rates]] and less regulation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Way the World Works: How Economies Fail—and Succeed |last=Wanniski |first=Jude |authorlink= |year=1978 |publisher=Basic Books |location=New York |isbn=0-465-09095-8 |pages= |url= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Most economists view supply-side as an ill-conceived economic theory{{Citation needed|date=October 2012}}. Critics of supply-side economics point to the lack of academic economics credentials by movement leaders such as Jude Wanniski  and [[Robert Bartley]] to imply that the theories behind it are bankrupt.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chait&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=The Big Con: How Washington Got Hoodwinked and Hijacked by Crackpot Economics |last=Chait |first=J. |authorlink= |year=2007 |publisher=Houghton Mifflin |location=Boston |isbn=0-618-68540-5 |pages= |url= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Harper&quot;&gt;{{cite web |first = David |last = Harper |url=http://www.investopedia.com/articles/05/011805.asp|title=Understanding Supply-Side Economics}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nobel prize winning economist [[Paul Krugman]] published a book dedicated to attacking the theory, and Reaganomics, under the title &quot;[[Peddling Prosperity]]&quot;. Mundell in his [[Nobel Memorial Prize in Economic Sciences|The Sveriges Riksbank Prize in Economic Sciences in Memory of Alfred Nobel]] acceptance lecture (awarded for unrelated work in [[optimum currency area]]) countered that the success of price stability was proof that the supply-side revolution had worked. The continuing debate over supply-side policies tends to focus on the massive federal and current account deficits, increased income inequality and its failure to promote growth.&lt;ref name=&quot;Orzsag&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.brookings.edu/views/op-ed/gale/20030509.htm |author=Gale, W. G. &amp; Orszag, P. R. |title=Bush's Tax Plan Slashes Growth |date=2003-05-09 |publisher=The Brookings Institution |accessdate=2007-10-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:US high-income effective tax rates.png|thumb| Average tax rate percentages for the highest-income U.S. taxpayers, 1945-2009]]
The [[Pigou–Dalton principle]] is that redistribution of wealth from a rich person to a poor person reduces inequality, so long as the order is not switched (the initially richer person is not made poorer than the initially poorer person: they are brought together and not switched). [[Hugh Dalton]] suggested further that, assuming no effects other than transfer, such transfers increase collective welfare, because the marginal utility of income or wealth to a rich person is less than that to a poor person. Maximal welfare is achieved if all have equal wealth or income. Dalton's analysis sets aside questions of economic efficiency: redistribution may increase or decrease overall output – it may grow or shrink the pie, not simply change how it is divided. 

The [[Congressional Budget Office]] (CBO) has estimated that extending the [[Bush tax cuts]] of 2001-2003 beyond their 2010 expiration would increase deficits by $1.8 trillion dollars over the following decade.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbo.gov/ftpdocs/78xx/doc7878/03-21-PresidentsBudget.pdf Analysis of President's Budget Table 1-3 Page 6]&lt;/ref&gt; The CBO also completed a study in 2005 analyzing a hypothetical 10% income tax cut and concluded that under various scenarios there would be minimal offsets to the loss of revenue. In other words, deficits would increase by nearly the same amount as the tax cut in the first five years, with limited feedback revenue thereafter. Through increased budget deficits, the tax cuts primarily benefiting the wealthy will be paid for &amp;mdash; plus interest &amp;mdash; by [[Taxation in the United States|taxes borne relatively evenly by all taxpayers]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbo.gov/ftpdocs/69xx/doc6908/12-01-10PercentTaxCut.pdf CBO Study Grey Box Page 1]&lt;/ref&gt; The paper points out that these projected shortfalls in revenue would have to be made up by federal borrowing: the paper estimates that the federal government would pay an extra $200 billion in interest over the decade covered by the paper's analysis.&lt;ref name=&quot;CBO&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.cbo.gov/ftpdocs/69xx/doc6908/12-01-10PercentTaxCut.pdf|title=CBO. (December 1, 2005). ''Analyzing the Economic and Budgetary Effects of a 10 Percent Cut in Income Tax Rates''|accessdate=2007-12-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the absence of negative [[Externality|externalities]], the introduction of taxes into a market reduces [[economic efficiency]] by causing [[deadweight loss]]. In a competitive market the [[price]] of a particular [[economic good]] adjusts to ensure that all trades which benefit both the buyer and the seller of a good occur. The introduction of a tax causes the price received by the seller to be less than the cost to the buyer by the amount of the tax. This causes fewer transactions to occur, which reduces [[welfare economics|economic welfare]]; the individuals or businesses involved are less well off than before the tax. The [[tax burden]] and the amount of deadweight cost is dependent on the [[elasticity (economics)|elasticity]] of supply and demand for the good taxed. Most taxes—including [[income tax]] and [[sales tax]]—can have significant deadweight costs.

==Prospect of Upward Mobility hypothesis==
[[File:U.S. Distribution of Wealth, 2007.jpg|thumb|The distribution of net wealth in the United States, 2007. The chart is divided into the top 20% (blue), upper middle 20% (orange), middle 20% (red), and bottom 40% (green). (The net wealth of many people in the lowest 20% is negative because of debt.)&lt;ref name=&quot;levyinstitute.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.levyinstitute.org/pubs/wp_589.pdf Recent Trends in Household Wealth in the United States: Rising Debt and the Middle-Class Squeeze—an Update to 2007] by Edward N. Wolff, Levy Economics Institute of Bard College, March 2010&lt;/ref&gt;]]

The Prospect of Upward Mobility (POUM) hypothesis is an argument that explains why some poor and working class voters do not support efforts by governments to redistribute wealth. It states that many people with below average income do not support higher tax rates because of a belief in their prospect for upward mobility.&lt;ref name=&quot;Poum&quot;&gt;[http://www.jstor.org/stable/2696470] Social Mobility and the Demand for Redistribution: The Poum Hypothesis. Roland Benabou, Efe A. Ok. The Quarterly Journal of Economics, Vol. 116, No. 2 (May, 2001), pp. 447-487&lt;/ref&gt;  These workers strongly believe that there is opportunity for either themselves, their children, or their grandchildren to move upward on the economic ladder.

There are three key assumptions that form the foundation for the POUM hypothesis.  First, one must assume that policies that are enacted in the present will endure into the future and carry enough weight to impact the future.&lt;ref name=&quot;Poum&quot;/&gt; Second, one must assume that poorer workers are &quot;not too risk averse&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Poum&quot;/&gt; This assumption rests on the fact that the people in question must realize that their income may also go down instead of up.  Finally, poor workers must have an optimistic view of their future, as they expect to go from poorer than the average to richer than average.&lt;ref name=&quot;Poum&quot;/&gt; 

After much analysis of the POUM hypothesis, Benabou and Ok recognize two key limitations. One limitation is that other potential problems that create more concavity in the POUM system, such as risk aversion, must not increase too much.&lt;ref name=&quot;Poum&quot;/&gt; Concavity must be kept at a minimum to ensure that the POUM hypothesis generates the expected results. The other limitation is that there must be adequate commitment to the choice of fiscal policy including the government and institutions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Poum&quot;/&gt;

==Criticism==
[[Conservativism|Conservative]], [[Libertarianism|libertarian]] and [[neoliberalism|neoliberal]] arguments against property redistribution consider the term a [[euphemism]] for theft or forced labor, and argue that redistribution of legitimately obtained property cannot ever be just.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.anthonyflood.com/redist4.htm &quot;Redistribution&quot; as Euphemism or, Who Owns What?]'' [[Philosophy Pathways]],'' Number 65, 24 August 2003, by Anthony Flood&lt;/ref&gt;{{self-published inline|date=September 2011}} [[Public choice]] theory states that redistribution tends to benefit those with political clout to set spending priorities more than those in need, who lack real influence on government.&lt;ref&gt;Plotnick, Robert (1986) &quot;An Interest Group Model of Direct Income Redistribution&quot;, ''The Review of Economics and Statistics, vol. 68'', #4, pp. 594-602.&lt;/ref&gt; 

In the [[United States]], some of the founding fathers and several subsequent leaders expressed opposition to redistribution of wealth. [[Samuel Adams]] stated: &quot;The utopian schemes of leveling [redistribution of wealth], and a community of goods, are as visionary and impracticable as those that vest all property in the Crown. [These ideas] are arbitrary, despotic, and, in our government, unconstitutional.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://my.opera.com/BAMAToNE/blog/2008/10/29/the-real-sam-adams&lt;/ref&gt; [[James Madison]], author of the [[United States Constitution|Constitution]], wrote, &quot;I cannot undertake to lay my finger on that article of the Constitution which granted a right to Congress of expending, on objects of benevolence, the money of their constituents.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://econfaculty.gmu.edu/wew/articles/fee/constitution.html &quot;Constitution Day - George Mason University&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{columns-list|3|
* [[Basic income]]
* [[Causes_of_the_Great_Depression#Disparities_in_wealth_and_income|Causes of the Great Depression—disparities in wealth and income]]
* [[Class conflict]]
* [[Distribution of wealth]]
* [[Federal taxation and spending by state]]
* [[Gini coefficient]]
* [[Living wage]]
* [[Nationalization]]
* [[Nordic model]]
* [[Ownership]]
* [[Progressive taxation]]
* [[Redistributive change]]
* [[Regressive taxation]]
* [[Robin Hood effect]]
* [[Sabbath economics]]
* [[Social equality]]
* [[Social inequality]]
* [[Wealth concentration]]
* [[Welfare state]]

'''Ideologies:'''
* [[Capitalism]]
* [[Communism]]
* [[Egalitarianism]]
* [[Islamic economic jurisprudence]]
* [[Social liberalism]]
* [[Socialism]]

'''Lists:'''
* [[List of countries by income equality]]
* [[List of countries by inequality-adjusted HDI]]

'''US specific:'''
* [[Hawaii Housing Authority v. Midkiff]]
* [[Wealth inequality in the United States]]
}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
*[http://www.poorcity.richcity.org Small calculus of inequality measures]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Redistribution (Economics)}}
[[Category:Politics by issue]]
[[Category:Taxation and redistribution]]
[[Category:Public economics]]
[[Category:Political philosophy]]
[[Category:Socioeconomics]]
[[Category:Egalitarianism]]
[[Category:Income distribution]]
[[Category:Welfare state]]

[[cs:Přerozdělování]]
[[cy:Ailddosbarthu cyfoeth]]
[[de:Umverteilung]]
[[fr:Redistribution des richesses]]
[[ko:소득 재분배]]
[[la:Redistributio divitiarum]]
[[lt:Perskirstymas]]
[[ja:富の再分配]]
[[pl:Redystrybucja]]
[[ru:Распределение (экономика)]]
[[sv:Fördelningspolitik]]
[[uk:Розподіл (економіка)]]</text>
      <sha1>7xra8f7p5hmxapjr0uo6acgvkzzto90</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
