<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Reflections on the Revolution in France</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1449087</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519789076</id>
      <parentid>517443284</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-25T16:54:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>148.85.251.131</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13256">{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2011}}
{{Italic title}}
'''''Reflections on the Revolution in France''''' is a 1790 book by [[Edmund Burke]] and one of the best-known intellectual attacks against the [[French Revolution]]. The central claim of the book was that not only must revolutionary France be defeated militarily but, in a break with other British politicians who did not support the revolution, that the [[ancien regime]] must be reinstated as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Hampsher-Monk|2005|p=65}}&lt;/ref&gt; The tract has been used as a defining piece of modern [[conservatism]] as well as an important contribution to international theory. Above all else, it has been one of the defining efforts of Edmund Burke's transformation of &quot;traditionalism into a self-conscious and fully conceived political philosophy of conservatism.&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Mazlish|1958|p=21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The pamphlet has not been easy to classify. Academics have had trouble identifying whether Burke, or his tract, can best be understood as &quot;a realist or an idealist, Rationalist or a Revolutionist.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Armitage|2000|p=619}}&lt;/ref&gt; The current academic consensus is that the tract is a &quot;classic text in political theory&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Bruyn|2001|p=577}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thanks to thoroughness, rhetorical skill and literary power, it has become one of the most widely known of Burke's writings. For this reason many writers have attempted to recruit Burke for their own political viewpoints. 

In the twentieth century, it greatly influenced [[conservatism|conservative]] and [[classical liberalism|classical liberal]] intellectuals, who recast Burke's Whig arguments as a critique of Communism and Socialist revolutionary programmes.

[[Image:BurkeReflections.jpg|thumb|right|''Reflections on the Revolution in France, And on the Proceedings in Certain Societies in London Relative to that Event. In a Letter Intended to Have Been Sent to a Gentleman in Paris.'' By the Right Honourable [[Edmund Burke]].]]

== Background ==

{{See also|Edmund Burke#French Revolution: 1688 versus 1789}}

Eugene Lee served in the [[British House of Commons]], representing the [[British Whig Party|Whig]] party, in close alliance with liberal politician [[Charles Watson-Wentworth, 2nd Marquess of Rockingham|Lord Rockingham]]. In Burke's political career, he vigorously defended constitutional limitation of the Crown's authority, denounced the religious persecution of Catholics in his native Ireland, voiced the grievances of Britain's American colonies, supported [[American Revolution|American Independence]], and vigorously pursued [[impeachment of Warren Hastings]], the [[Governor-General of India|Governor-General]] of [[British India]], for corruption and abuse of power. For these actions, Burke was widely respected by liberals in Great Britain, the United States, and the European continent.

In 1789, soon after the [[fall of the Bastille]], the French aristocrat Charles-Jean-François Depont asked his impressions of the Revolution; Burke replied with two letters. The longer, second letter became ''Reflections on the Revolution in France'', published in 1790.

==Arguments==

In the ''Reflections'', Burke argued that the French Revolution would end disastrously because its abstract foundations, purportedly rational, ignored the complexities of human nature and society. Further, he focused on the practicality of solutions instead of the metaphysics, writing 'What is the use of discussing a man's abstract right to food or to medicine? The question is upon the method of procuring and administering them. In this deliberation I shall always advise to call in the aid of the farmer and the physician, rather than the professor.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Edmund Burke, ''Reflections on the Revolution in France'' [1790] (Pearson Longman, 2006), p. 144.&lt;/ref&gt; Following [[St. Augustine]] and [[Cicero]], he believed in &quot;human heart&quot;-based government. Nevertheless, he was contemptuous and afraid of the [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]], led by intellectuals such as [[Jean-Jacques Rousseau|Rousseau]], [[Voltaire]], and [[Anne-Robert-Jacques Turgot, Baron de Laune|Turgot]], who disbelieved in divine moral order and [[original sin]], saying that society should be handled like a living organism, that people and society are limitlessly complicated, thus, leading him to conflict with [[Thomas Hobbes]]'s assertion that politics might be reducible to a [[deductive system]] akin to [[mathematics]]. 

A dominant theme in Reflections is that the French were not only upholding the rights accorded to all men, like the American revolutionaries that he supported or the English in the Glorious Revolution. C. B. Macpherson, goes as far as saying any contradiction can &quot;be dismissed very quickly.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Macpherson|1980|p=7}}&lt;/ref&gt; Others, such as Jeff Spinner, argue that opposition to the United States revolution was more pragmatic. Burke believed only war and the spread of uniquely American ideals, which were illsuited for Europe, could result from opposition to the American self-determination.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Spinner|1991|pp=400–402}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

As a Protestant and Whig, he expressly repudiated the belief in divinely appointed monarchic authority ''and'' the idea that a people have no right to depose an oppressive government; however, he advocated central roles for private property, tradition, and 'prejudice' (adherence to values regardless of their rational basis) to give citizens a stake in their nation's social order. He argued for gradual, constitutional reform, not revolution (in every case except the most qualified case), emphasizing that a political doctrine founded upon abstractions such as ''liberty'' and the ''rights of man'' could be easily abused to justify tyranny. He saw inherited rights, restated in England from the [[Magna Carta]] to the [[Bill of Rights 1689|Declaration of Right]], as firm and concrete providing continuity (like tradition, 'prejudice,' inheritable private property,) by contrast enforcement of 'speculative' abstract rights might waver and be subject to change based on currents of politics. Instead, he called for the constitutional enactment of specific, concrete rights and liberties as protection against governmental oppression.

In the phrase, &quot;[prejudice] renders a man's virtue his habit,&quot; he defends people's cherished, but untaught, irrational prejudices (the greater it behooved them, the more they cherished it). Because a person's moral estimation is limited, people are better off drawing from the &quot;general bank and capital of nations and of ages&quot; than from their own intellects.&lt;ref&gt;Edmund Burke, ''Reflections on the Revolution in France'' [1790] (Penguin Classics, 1986), p. 183.&lt;/ref&gt;

He predicted that the Revolution's concomitant disorder would make the army &quot;mutinous and full of faction,&quot; and then a &quot;popular general,&quot; commanding the soldiery's allegiance, would become &quot;master of your assembly, the master of your whole republic.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Edmund Burke, ''Reflections on the Revolution in France'' [1790] (Penguin Classics, 1986), p. 342.&lt;/ref&gt; Though he may have been thinking of Lafayette, Napoleon fulfilled this prophecy on the [[18 Brumaire|18th Brumaire]], two years after Burke's death.

Most of the [[House of Commons of the United Kingdom|House of Commons]] disagreed with Burke and his popularity declined. As the French Revolution broke into factions, the Whig Party broke in two: the New Whig party and the Old Whig party. As founder of the Old Whigs, Burke always took the opportunity to engage in debate with the New Whigs about French [[Jacobinism]].

After trying to loosen the Protestant minority's control of Irish government, he was voted out of the House of Commons with a great pension. He later adopted French and Irish children, believing himself correct in rescuing them from government oppression. Before dying, he ordered his family to bury him secretly, believing his cadaver would be a political target for desecration should the Jacobins prevail in England.

==Intellectual influence==
{{refimprove|date=September 2011}}
''Reflections on the Revolution in France'' was read widely on publication, though not every Briton approved of Burke's kind treatment of their historic enemy or its royal family. His English enemies speculated he either had become mentally unbalanced or was a secret Catholic, outraged by the democratic French government's anti-clerical policies and expropriation of Church land. The publication of this work drew a swift response, first with  ''[[Rights of Man]]'' (1791-2) by [[Thomas Paine]], and then with ''[[A Vindication of the Rights of Man]]'' (1792) by [[Mary Wollstonecraft]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Wollstonecraft|first=Mary|title=The Wrongs of Woman; or Maria|year=2004|publisher=College Publishing|location=Glen Allen|isbn=0-9679121-6-4|pages=&quot;Introduction,&quot; pp. 3}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Nonetheless, Burke's work became popular with [[reactionaries]] such as King [[George III of the United Kingdom|George III]] and the [[Savoy]]ard philosopher [[Joseph de Maistre]].

Historically, ''Reflections on the Revolution in France'' became the founding philosophic opus of Conservatism when some predictions occurred: the [[Reign of Terror]] succeeded the execution of King Louis XVI and his wife, to purge anti-revolutionary enemies of the people. That, in turn, led to the political reaction of Gen. [[Napoleon Bonaparte]]'s government, which appeared to some to be a [[military dictator]]ship. Burke had predicted the rise of a military dictatorship and that the revolutionary government instead of protecting the rights of the people would be corrupt and violent.

In the nineteenth century, [[positivism|positivist]] French historian [[Hippolyte Taine]] repeated the Englishman's arguments in ''Origins of Contemporary France'' (1876–1885): that centralisation of power is the essential fault of the Revolutionary French government system; that it does not promote democratic control; and that the Revolution transferred power from the divinely chosen [[aristocracy]] to an &quot;[[Age of Enlightenment|enlightened]]&quot; heartless elite more incompetent and tyrannical than the aristocrats. 

In the twentieth century, Western conservatives applied Burke's anti-revolutionary ''Reflections'' to popular socialist revolutions, thus establishing Burke's iconic political value to conservatives and classical liberals. For example, an important classical economic liberal, [[Friedrich Hayek]], acknowledged an intellectual debt to Burke.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Bibliography==
*{{cite journal
|last1=Armitage
|first1=Dave
|year=2000
|title=Edmund Burke and Reason of State
|journal=Journal of the History of Ideas
|volume=61
|issue=4
|pages=617–634
|publisher=University of Philadelphia Press
|ref=harv}}
*{{cite journal
|last1=Bruyn
|first1=Frans De
|year=2001
|title=Anti-Semitism, Millenarianism, and Radical Dissent in Edmund Burke's Reflections on the Revolution in France
|journal=Eighteenth-Century Studies
|volume=34
|issue=4
|pages=577–600
|publisher=John Hopkins University Press
|ref=harv}}
*{{cite journal 
|last1=Hampsher-Monk
|first1=Ian
|year=2005
|title=Edmund Burke's Changing Definition for Intervention
|journal=The Historical Journal
|volume=48
|issue=1
|pages=65–100
|publisher=Cambridge University Press
|ref=harv}}
*{{cite journal
|last1=Mazlish
|first1=Bruce
|year=1958
|title=The Conservative Revolution of Edmund Burke
|journal=The Review of Politics
|volume=20
|issue=1
|pages=21–23
|publisher=Cambridge University Press
|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book 
|title=Burke
|last=Macpherson
|first=C. R.
|year=1980
|publisher=Hilland Wang
|location=New York
|accessdate=August 2, 2012 
|ref=harv}}
*{{cite journal 
|last1=Spinner
|first1=Jeff
|year=1991
|title=Constructing Communities: Edmund Burke on Revolution
|journal=Polity
|volume=23
|issue=3
|pages=395–421 
|publisher=Palgrave Macmillian Journals
|ref=harv}}

==External links==
{{Wikisource|Reflections on the Revolution in France}}
* [http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/mod/1791burke.html An online version of the text (scanned excerpt + OCR)]
* [http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/15679 Another online version of the text]
* [http://www.theatlantic.com/past/docs/issues/2004/04/hitchens.htm &quot;Reactionary Prophet: Edmund Burke understood before anyone else that revolutions devour their young—and turn into their opposites&quot;] by Christopher Hitchens, ''The Atlantic Monthly'', April 2004.

{{Edmund Burke}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Reflections On The Revolution In France}}
[[Category:1790 events of the French Revolution]]
[[Category:Works by Edmund Burke]]
[[Category:Philosophy books]]
[[Category:Conservatism]]
[[Category:1790 works]]
[[Category:Books about the French Revolution]]

{{Link GA|it}}
[[bg:Размисли за революцията във Франция]]
[[ca:Reflexions sobre la Revolució Francesa]]
[[es:Reflexiones sobre la Revolución francesa]]
[[eo:Pensoj pri la Revolucio en Francio]]
[[fr:Réflexions sur la Révolution de France]]
[[it:Riflessioni sulla Rivoluzione in Francia]]
[[he:הרהורים על המהפכה בצרפת]]
[[ja:フランス革命の省察]]
[[pl:Rozważania o rewolucji we Francji]]
[[ru:Размышления о Французской революции]]</text>
      <sha1>75h35m9p1mo5xsrzc0rielbmj9b2v8h</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
