<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Religious Coalition for Reproductive Choice</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2747481</id>
    <revision>
      <id>499984126</id>
      <parentid>493467248</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-06-30T00:21:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dante8</username>
        <id>12713376</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7579">{{Multiple issues|POV = April 2012|weasel = August 2010|refimprove = April 2012}}
The '''Religious Coalition for Reproductive Choice''' (RCRC) was founded in 1973 by clergy and lay leaders from mainline denominations and faith traditions to provide interfaith support for the new constitutional right to privacy in decisions about abortion. In 1993, the original name - the Religious Coalition for Abortion Rights (RCAR) - was changed to the Religious Coalition for Reproductive Choice to reflect the expansion of the coalition's work.

== Leadership ==
*President and CEO: The Reverend [[Carlton W. Veazey]]
*Chair of the Board: Dean Alton Pollard, Howard University School of Divinity
*Chair of the Council of Governors, Linda Bales Todd, General Board of Church and Society, United Methodist Church

==State affiliates==
The state affiliates and state networks of the Religious Coalition are involved in advocacy, education, community service, and implementing RCRC programs such as Clergy for Choice, All Options Clergy Counseling, and Spiritual Youth for Reproductive Freedom at the community and state level.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rcrc.org/getinvolved/affiliate.cfm RCRC affiliates]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Member organizations ==
*[[Rabbinical Assembly]]
*[[United Synagogue of Conservative Judaism]]
*[[Women's League for Conservative Judaism]]
*[[The Episcopal Church]]
*[[American Ethical Union National Service Conference]]
*[[Society for Humanistic Judaism]]
*Presbyterian Church (USA) and Presbyterians Affirming Reproductive Options (PARO) of the [[Presbyterian Church (USA)]]
*[[Jewish Reconstructionist Federation]]
*[[Reconstructionist Rabbinical Association]]
*[[Central Conference of American Rabbis]]
*[[North American Federation of Temple Youth]]
*[[Women of Reform Judaism, The Federation of Temple Sisterhoods]]
*[[Women's Rabbinic Network]] of Central Conference of American Rabbis
*The [[United Church of Christ]]
*The General Board of Church and Society of The [[United Methodist Church]]
*The General Board of Global Ministries, Women's Division of the United Methodist Church
*[[Unitarian Universalist Association]]
*[[Unitarian Universalist Women's Federation]]
*[[Young Religious Unitarian Universalists]]
*[[Continental Unitarian Universalist Young Adult Network]]
*[[American Jewish Committee]]
*[[American Jewish Congress]]
*[[Anti-Defamation League]]
*[[Catholics for Choice]]
*[[Christian Lesbians Out]] (CLOUT)
*[[Church of the Brethren Women's Caucus]]
*[[Disciples for Choice]]
*[[Episcopal Urban Caucus]]
*[[Episcopal Women's Caucus]]
*[[Hadassah]], WZOA
*[[Jewish Women International]]
*[[Lutheran Women's Caucus]]
*[[Methodist Federation for Social Action]]
*NA'AMAT USA
*[[National Council of Jewish Women]]
*[[Women's American ORT]]
*[[YWCA of the USA]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Member Orgs&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.rcrc.org/about/members.cfm | title = Member Organizations |= publisher = The Religious Coalition for Reproductive Choice |accessdate = 2007-08-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
In the 1960s, clergy who counseled women concerned about an unintended pregnancy were increasingly horrified by the injury and death being suffered by women undergoing illegal abortions. They became convinced of their moral responsibility to help women with unwelcome pregnancies locate safe abortion providers. In 1967, Reverend Howard Moody and Arlene Carmen organized the first Clergy Consultation Service on Abortion, at Judson Memorial Church in New York City. The service was a network of clergy who counseled women and identified safe abortion providers. Similar services developed throughout the country.

Simultaneously, Protestant denominations and other religious organizations were working to pass their own policies supporting decriminalization of abortion and collectively lobbying for decriminalization legislation. They were convinced that religious freedom required reproductive freedom. They consistently pointed out that where religions disagree, no one religious view should be legislated.

Even when the U.S. Supreme Court recognized that the right to privacy encompassed a woman’s decision about abortion in its 1973 ''Roe v. Wade'' decision, denominations and faith groups that had worked so hard for legalization knew the struggle had not ended. They founded the Religious Coalition for Abortion Rights (RCAR) that year to provide interfaith support for women's right to choose abortion. The original intent was to focus primarily on abortion and the issue of separation of church and state.

Local affiliates were established in key states to block an anticipated constitutional amendment to counter the guarantees of the ''Roe v. Wade'' decision. However, the need for interfaith support for reproductive rights has continued and even intensified and RCRC has accordingly expanded.

===1985—Women of Color Partnership Established===

The Women of Color Partnership (WOCP) was formed to provide a vehicle through which women of color could become actively involved as decision-makers in the reproductive choice movement. The WOCP sought to identify and address reproductive health care concerns from the perspectives of women of color, thereby building a multicultural and anti-racist alliance.

===1993—Mission Expanded===

Largely at the urging of women of color and others who wanted a more inclusive agenda, the Coalition expanded its mission to reflect its commitment to all reproductive options, including sexuality education, access to affordable family planning, adequate health care, and other reproductive health concerns. To reflect the expanded mission, the name was changed to the Religious Coalition for Reproductive Choice. Today, the Coalition pursues a reproductive justice agenda, supporting policies to ensure the medical, economic, and educational resources that make reproductive choice possible.

===1996 – Coalition Programs Expanded===

Growth has been rapid since 1996, when the National Black Church Initiative was launched. In 1998, two new departments were established—-Field Services (now Interfaith Outreach) and MultiCultural Programs. The same year, the Board of Directors established the Council of Governors, a body that extends the Coalition’s reach by expanding partnerships and collaborative opportunities. In 2000, the Coalition responded to the call for more religious involvement in HIV/AIDS prevention by beginning to work with South African churches. The Coalition’s program for youth and young adults, Spiritual Youth for Reproductive Freedom, began in 2000 to reach out to the growing number of youth whose commitment to social justice is based on deeply held faith principles. An educational program with Latino churches, La Iniciativa Latina, was started in 2001. In 2002, Seminarians for Choice was launched nationally. The Coalition’s Public Policy Department began in 2007 to provide a dedicated focus on legislation and policy issues; its early projects included increasing interfaith support for comprehensive, medically accurate sexuality education.

==See also==
*[[Evangelical and Ecumenical Women's Caucus]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.rcrc.org/ Religious Coalition of Reproductive Choice] (official website)

{{DEFAULTSORT:Religious Coalition For Reproductive Choice}}
[[Category:Religious organizations based in the United States]]
[[Category:Civic and political organizations of the United States]]
[[Category:Pro-choice organizations in the United States]]
[[Category:Pro-choice religious organizations]]
[[Category:Organizations established in 1973]]</text>
      <sha1>kl6q7s5tbar2gqivj32mhczaqh1ryug</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
