<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Representative democracy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>52318</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522133605</id>
      <parentid>522106858</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T06:06:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mediatech492</username>
        <id>9904943</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 522106858 by [[Special:Contributions/74.139.75.26|74.139.75.26]] ([[User talk:74.139.75.26|talk]])unconstructive</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11784">{{Refimprove|date=November 2010}}
{{Democracy}}
{{Forms of government}}

'''Representative democracy''' is a [[varieties of democracy|variety of democracy]] founded on the principle of elected people representing a group of people, as opposed to [[direct democracy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=28 July 2005|accessdate=14 December 2007|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20071213045132/http://www.parliament.vic.gov.au/SARC/E-Democracy/Final_Report/Glossary.htm&lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt;|archivedate=13 December 2007|title=Victorian Electronic Democracy, Final Report - Glossary}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, three countries which use representative democracy are the [[United States Of America]] (a representative democracy), the [[United Kingdom]] (a [[constitutional monarchy]]) and [[Poland]] (a [[parliamentary republic]]).

It is an element of both the [[parliamentary system]] and [[presidential system]] of [[form of government|government]] and is typically used in a '''[[lower chamber]]''' such as the [[House of Commons]] (UK) or [[Bundestag]] (Germany), and is generally curtailed by constitutional constraints such as an upper chamber. It has been described by some political theorists as [[Polyarchy]].{{citation needed|date=December 2011}}

==Powers of representatives==
Representatives sometimes hold the power to select other representatives, presidents, or other officers of government (indirect representation).{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}}

The power of representatives is never usually curtailed by a [[constitution]] (as in a [[constitutional democracy]] or a [[constitutional monarchy]]) or other measures to balance representative power:{{Citation needed|date=August 2010}}
*An [[independent judiciary]], which may have the power to declare legislative acts unconstitutional (e.g. [[constitutional court]], [[supreme court]])
*It{{clarify|what?|date=December 2011}} may also provide for some [[deliberative democracy]] (e.g., [[Royal Commission]]s) or direct popular measures (e.g., [[initiative]], [[referendum]], [[recall election]]s).  However, these are not always binding and usually require some legislative action&amp;mdash;legal power usually remains firmly with representatives{{Where|date=July 2011}}.
*In some cases, a [[Bicameralism|bicameral legislature]] may have an &quot;[[upper house]]&quot; that is not directly elected, such as the [[Canadian Senate]], which was in turn modeled on the [[British House of Lords]].

Theorists such as [[Edmund_Burke#Democracy|Edmund Burke]] believe that part of the duty of a representative was not simply to communicate the wishes of the electorate but also to use their own judgement in the exercise of their powers, even if their views are not reflective of those of a majority of voters:

&lt;blockquote&gt;...it ought to be the happiness and glory of a representative to live in the strictest union, the closest correspondence, and the most unreserved communication with his constituents. Their wishes ought to have great weight with him; their opinion, high respect; their business, unremitted attention. It is his duty to sacrifice his repose, his pleasures, his satisfactions, to theirs; and above all, ever, and in all cases, to prefer their interest to his own. But his unbiassed opinion, his mature judgment, his enlightened conscience, he ought not to sacrifice to you, to any man, or to any set of men living. These he does not derive from your pleasure; no, nor from the law and the constitution. They are a trust from Providence, for the abuse of which he is deeply answerable. Your representative owes you, not his industry only, but his judgment; and he betrays, instead of serving you, if he sacrifices it to your opinion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Works of the Right Honourable Edmund Burke. Volume I|location=London|publisher=Henry G. Bohn| year=1854|pages=446–8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Representative democracy and republicanism==
The related term [[republic]] may have many different meanings. It normally means a state with an elected or otherwise non-[[monarchy|monarchical]] [[head of state]], such as the [[Islamic Republic of Iran]] or [[Republic of Korea]].

Sometimes in the US it is used similarly to liberal (representative) democracy.{{citation needed|date=December 2011}} For example:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=An Introduction to the American Legal System |last=Scheb |first=John M. |year=2006 |publisher=Thomson Delmar Learning |page=6 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|The United States relies on representative democracy, but its system of government is much more complex than that. It is not a simple representative democracy, but a [[constitutional republic]] in which majority rule is tempered.}}

==History==
The Roman Republic was the first government in the western world to have a representative government, although it didn't have much of a democracy. The Romans invented the concept of classics and many works from Ancient Greece were preserved.&lt;ref&gt;Watson, 2005, p. 285&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, the Roman model of governance inspired many political thinkers over the centuries,&lt;ref&gt;Livy, 2002, p. 34&lt;/ref&gt; and today's modern representative democracies imitate more the Roman than the Greek models because it was a state in which supreme power was held by the people and their elected representatives, and which had an elected or nominated a leader.&lt;ref&gt;Watson, 2005, p. 271&lt;/ref&gt; Representative democracy is a form of democracy in which people vote for representatives who then vote on policy initiatives as opposed to a direct democracy, a form of democracy in which people vote on policy initiatives directly.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Budge, Ian|chapter=Direct democracy|editors=Clarke, Paul A.B. &amp; Foweraker, Joe|title=Encyclopedia of Political Thought|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|year=2001|isbn=978-0-415-19396-2|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=srzDCqnZkfUC&amp;pg=PA224}}&lt;/ref&gt; A European medieval traditions of selecting representatives from the various [[estates of the realm|estates]] ([[social class|classes]], but not as we know them today) to advise/control monarchs led to relatively wide familiarity with representative systems inspired by Roman systems.{{citation needed|date=December 2011}}

Representative democracy came into particular general favour in post-[[industrial revolution]] [[nation state]]s where large numbers of subjects or (latterly) citizens evinced interest in [[politics]], but where technology and population figures remained unsuited to direct democracy. As noted above, Edmund Burke in his speech to the electors of Bristol classically analysed their operation in Britain and the rights and duties of an elected representative.

Globally, a majority of the world's people live in representative democracies including constitutional monarchy with strong representative branch– the first time in history that this has been true{{citation needed|first time|date=December 2011}}.

==Criticisms==
In his book ''Political Parties'', written in 1911, [[Robert Michels]] demonstrates that most representative systems deteriorate towards an oligarchy. This is known as the &quot;[[Iron Law of Oligarchy]]&quot; and also as the First Law of Politicology.  In line with this law, all representative democracies are known to become after time a [[particracy]].&lt;ref&gt;Zur Soziologie des Parteiwesens in der modernen Demokratie. Untersuchungen über die oligarchischen Tendenzen des Gruppenlebens (1911, 1925; 1970). Translated as ''Sociologia del partito politico nella democrazia moderna : studi sulle tendenze oligarchiche degli aggregati politici'', from the German original by Dr. Alfredo Polledro, revised and expanded (1912). Translated, from the Italian, by Eden and Cedar Paul as Political Parties: A Sociological Study of the Oligarchical Tendencies of Modern Democracy (Hearst's International Library Co., 1915; Free Press, 1949; Dover Publications, 1959); republished with an introduction by Seymour Martin Lipset (Crowell-Collier, 1962; Transaction Publishers, 1999, ISBN 0-7658-0469-7); translated in French by S. Jankélévitch, Les partis politiques. Essai sur les tendances oligarchiques des démocraties, Brussels, Editions de l'Université de Bruxelles, 2009 (ISBN 978-2-8004-1443-0).&lt;/ref&gt;
Representative democracies which are stable have been analysed by Adolf Gasser and compared to the unstable representative democracies.&lt;ref&gt;http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adolf_Gasser&lt;/ref&gt; in his book &quot;Gemeindefreiheit als Rettung Europas&quot; which was published in 1943 (first edition in German) and a second edition in 1947 (in German).&lt;ref&gt;Gemeindefreiheit als Rettung Europas. Grundlinien einer ethischen Geschichtsauffassung. Verlag Bücherfreunde, Basel 1947. In 1983 republished under: &quot;Gemeindefreiheit - kommunale Selbstverwaltung&quot; (Adolf Gasser/Franz-Ludwig Knemeyer), in de reeks &quot;Studien zur Soziologie&quot;, Nymphenburger, München, 1983.&lt;/ref&gt; Adolf Gasser noted the following requirements for a representative democracy in order to remain stable, unaffected by the &quot;Iron Law of Oligarchy&quot;: 
* Society has to be built up from bottom to top. As a consequence, society is built up by people, which are free and have the power to defend themselves with weapons.
* These free people join or form local communities. These local communities are independent, which includes financial independence, and they are free to determine their own rules.
* Local communities join together into a higher unit e.g. a canton.
There is no hierarchical bureaucracy.
* There is competition between these local communities e.g. on services delivered or on taxes.

The system of [[stochocracy]] has been proposed as an improved system compared to the system of representative democracy, where representatives are elected.  Stochocracy aims to be at least reduce this degradation by having all representatives appointed by lottery instead of by voting. Therefore this system is also called lottocracy. The system was proposed by the writer Roger de Sizif in 1998 in his book ''La Stochocratie''.

==See also==
*[[Citizenship]]
*[[History of citizenship]]
*[[Non-partisan democracy]]
*[[Stochocracy]] or (&quot;Lottocracy&quot;)
*[[Totalitarian democracy]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2010}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Representative Democracy}}
[[Category:Democracy]]
[[Category:Elections]]

[[als:Repräsentative Demokratie]]
[[ar:ديمقراطية تمثيلية]]
[[bg:Представителна демокрация]]
[[ca:Democràcia representativa]]
[[cs:Zastupitelská demokracie]]
[[da:Repræsentativt demokrati]]
[[de:Repräsentative Demokratie]]
[[et:Esindusdemokraatia]]
[[el:Αντιπροσωπευτική δημοκρατία]]
[[es:Democracia representativa]]
[[eu:Demokrazia ordezkatzaile]]
[[fr:Démocratie représentative]]
[[ko:대의제]]
[[id:Demokrasi perwakilan]]
[[is:Fulltrúalýðræði]]
[[it:Democrazia rappresentativa]]
[[he:דמוקרטיה ייצוגית]]
[[krc:Келечилик демократия]]
[[lt:Atstovaujamoji demokratija]]
[[mk:Посредна демократија]]
[[nl:Representatieve democratie]]
[[ja:間接民主制]]
[[no:Representativt demokrati]]
[[nn:Representativt demokrati]]
[[pl:Demokracja pośrednia]]
[[pt:Democracia representativa]]
[[ro:Democrație reprezentativă]]
[[ru:Представительная демократия]]
[[simple:Indirect democracy]]
[[sk:Reprezentatívna demokracia]]
[[ckb:دیموکراسییەتی نوێنەرایەتی]]
[[fi:Edustuksellinen demokratia]]
[[sv:Representativ demokrati]]
[[ta:சார்பாண்மை மக்களாட்சி]]
[[th:ประชาธิปไตยแบบมีผู้แทน]]
[[tr:Temsilî demokrasi]]
[[uk:Представницька демократія]]
[[vi:Dân chủ đại nghị]]
[[yo:Òṣèlú aṣojú]]
[[zh:代議民主制]]</text>
      <sha1>ek2naw7q3uo8ag6tm1b4khyajgfq4m6</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
