<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Revolutionary socialism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5660929</id>
    <revision>
      <id>513320577</id>
      <parentid>511993665</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-18T05:40:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>50.131.66.55</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Origins */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12574">{{Socialism sidebar |expanded=Strategies}}

The term '''revolutionary socialism''' refers to [[Socialism|socialist]] tendencies that subscribe to the doctrine that a social [[revolution]] is necessary in order to effect structural changes to society, and specifically, that revolution is necessary to achieve socialism. Revolution is not necessarily defined as a violent insurrection, rather, it is defined as the seizure of political power by mass movements of the [[working class]] so that the [[State (polity)|state]] is directly controlled by the working class as opposed to the capitalist class.&lt;ref name=sdvrds&gt;[http://www.marxists.org/history/usa/parties/spusa/1903/1000-thompson-whatrevsoc.pdf What Revolutionary Socialism Means] by Carl D. Thompson.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Revolutionary socialism includes a diverse range of social movements that might define &quot;revolution&quot; differently from each other. It includes [[Leninism]] and [[Marxism-Leninism]], which are based on [[Vanguardism]]; revolutionary [[Syndicalism]]; revolutionary [[democratic socialism]] and [[anarchism]].

It is used in contrast to the reformism of [[social democracy]], which is not anti-capitalist, and the advocacy of gradually ameliorating the economic and social problems of capitalism. 

Revolutionary socialism also exists in contrast to the concept of small revolutionary groups seizing power without first achieving mass support, termed [[Blanquism]].

== Origins ==
[[File:Karl Marx.jpg|thumb|right|[[Karl Marx]], 1875.]]
In the [[Communist Manifesto]], [[Karl Marx]] and [[Friedrich Engels]] wrote:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1848/communist-manifesto/ch01.htm#007]&lt;/ref&gt; 

{{quote|All previous historical movements were movements of minorities, or in the interest of minorities. The proletarian movement is the self-conscious, independent movement of the immense majority, in the interest of the immense majority. The proletariat, the lowest stratum of our present society, cannot stir, cannot raise itself up, without the whole superincumbent strata of official society being sprung into the air. 
Though not in substance, yet in form, the struggle of the proletariat with the bourgeoisie is at first a national struggle. The proletariat of each country must, of course, first of all settle matters with its own bourgeoisie. 
In depicting the most general phases of the development of the proletariat, we traced the more or less veiled civil war, raging within existing society, up to the point where that war breaks out into open revolution, and where the violent overthrow of the bourgeoisie lays the foundation for the sway of the proletariat.| Karl Marx and Friedrich Engels}}

Scholars have pointed out that the term &quot;revolution&quot; as used by Marx, Engels and their followers tends to refer to complete change of a social and economic nature by a mass movement of the &quot;immense majority&quot; (as shown by the quote above). In addition, if this revolutionary change was not opposed by the existing ruling elite, Marx and Engels contended, it could be carried out peacefully.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;... we do not deny that there are countries like England and America... where labour may attain its goal by peaceful means.&quot; Marx, 18 September 1872, at the Hague Congress of the International, http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1872/09/08.htm, K. Marx and F. Engels, On Britain, Foreign Languages Press, Moscow, 1962&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Both Marx and Engels and, later, Lenin on many occasions referred to a ''peaceful'' revolution, that is, one attained by a class struggle, but not by violence.&quot; Schaff, Adam, 'Marxist Theory on Revolution and Violence', p. 263. in Journal of the history of ideas, Vol 34, no.2 (Apr-Jun 1973)&lt;/ref&gt; By contrast, the [[Blanquist]] view emphasised the overthrow by force of the ruling elite in government by an active minority of revolutionaries, who then proceed to implement socialist change, disregarding the state of readiness of society as a whole and the mass of the population in particular for revolutionary change. 

The reformist viewpoint was introduced into Marxist thought by [[Eduard Bernstein]], one of the leaders of the [[Social Democratic Party of Germany]] (SPD). From 1896 to 1898, Bernstein published a series of articles entitled &quot;Probleme des Sozialismus&quot; (&quot;Problems of Socialism&quot;). These articles led to a debate on [[Marxist revisionism|revisionism]] in the SPD, and can be seen as the origins of a reformist trend within Marxism.

In 1900, [[Rosa Luxemburg]] wrote ''[[Social Reform or Revolution]]'', a [[polemic]] against Bernstein's position. The work of reforms, Luxemburg argued, could only be carried on, &quot;in the framework of the social form created by the last revolution&quot;. In order to advance society to socialism from the capitalist 'social form', a social revolution will be necessary:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marxists.org/archive/luxemburg/1900/reform-revolution/ch08.htm Luxemburg, Rosa, ''Social Reform or Revolution'', Chapter 8, ''Conquest of Political Power''], accessed 1 July 2007. ''Rosa Luxemburg Speaks'', p107-8, Pathfinder, (1970)&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|Bernstein, thundering against the conquest of political power as a theory of Blanquist violence, has the misfortune of labeling as a Blanquist error that which has always been the pivot and the motive force of human history. From the first appearance of class societies, having class struggle as the essential content of their history, the conquest of political power has been the aim of all rising classes. Here is the starting point and end of every historic period…In modern times, we see it in the struggle of the bourgeoisie against feudalism.|Rosa Luxemburg, ''Social Reform or Revolution''}}

[[Vladimir Lenin]] attacked Bernstein’s position in his ''What is to be Done''. When Bernstein first put forward his ideas the majority of the SPD rejected them. The 1899 Congress of the SPD reaffirmed the Erfurt programme, as did the 1901 congress. The 1903 congress denounced &quot;revisionist efforts&quot;.

== The First World War and Zimmerwald==

However on 4 August 1914 the SPD members of the Reichstag voted for the government’s war budget, while the French and Belgium socialists publicly supported their governments. [[Vladimir Lenin]], [[Leon Trotsky]], [[Karl Liebknecht]] and [[Rosa Luxemburg]], together with a small number of other Marxists opposed to the war, came together in the [[Zimmerwald Conference]] in September 1915. This conference saw the beginning of the end of the uneasy coexistence of revolutionary socialists and [[Reformism|reformist]] socialists in the [[Second International]]. The conference adopted a proposal by Trotsky to avoid an immediate split with the Second International. At first opposed to it, in the end Lenin voted&lt;ref&gt;See Christian Rakovsky's [http://www.marxists.org/archive/rakovsky/biog/biog2.htm biography] by Gus Fagan for details&lt;/ref&gt; for Trotsky's resolution to avoid a split among anti-war socialists.

In December, 1915 and March, 1916, eighteen Social Democratic representatives, the Haase-Ledebour Group, voted against war credits, and were expelled from the Social Democratic Party. Liebknecht wrote ''Revolutionary Socialism in Germany'' in 1916, arguing that this group was not a revolutionary socialist group, despite their refusal to vote for war credits, further defining, in his view, what was meant by a revolutionary socialist.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marxists.org/archive/liebknecht-k/works/1916/misc/revolutionary-socialism-germany.htm Liebknecht, Karl, ''Revolutionary Socialism in Germany'', 1916], accessed 1 July 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

==The Russian revolution of 1917 and after==
{{Marxism–Leninism sidebar}}

Many revolutionary socialists argue that the Russian revolution of October 1917 led by Lenin and Leon Trotsky follows the revolutionary socialist model of a revolutionary movement of the immense majority. By contrast, the October revolution is {{cn-span|text=popularly|date=August 2012}} portrayed as a putsch or coup d'état along the lines of Blanquism. 

Revolutionary socialists, particularly [[Trotskyist]]s, argue that the [[Bolshevik]]s only seized power as the expression of the mass of workers and peasants, whose desires are brought into being by an organised force - the revolutionary party. Marxists such as Trotskyists argue that Lenin did not advocate seizing of power until he felt that the majority of the population, represented in the [[Soviet (council)|soviet]]s, demanded revolutionary change and no longer supported the reformist government of [[Alexander Kerensky]] established in the earlier revolution of February 1917:

{{quote|&quot;Lenin, after the experience of the reconnoiter, withdrew the slogan of the immediate overthrow of the Provisional Government. But he did not withdraw it for any set period of time, for so many weeks or months, but strictly in dependence upon how quickly the revolt of the masses against the conciliationists would grow.&quot;|Leon Trotsky, Lessons of October, Chapter Four, The April Conference}}

For these Marxists, the fact that the Bolsheviks won a majority (in alliance with the [[Left Socialist-Revolutionaries]]) in the second all-Russian congress of Soviets - democratically elected bodies - which convened at the time of the October revolution, shows that they had popular support of the masses of workers, peasants and soldiers, the vast majority of Russian society.

In his pamphlet, The Lessons of October, published in 1923,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.marxist.net/trotsky/russia/lessons.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Trotsky argued that military power lay in the hands of the Bolsheviks before the October revolution was carried out but this power was not used against the government until the Bolsheviks gained mass support. 

The mass of the soldiers began to be led by the Bolshevik party after the 'July days' of 1917, and followed only the orders of the [[Military Revolutionary Committee]] under the leadership of Trotsky in October (also termed the 'Revolutionary Military Committee' in Lenin's collected works).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marxist.net/trotsky/russia/lessons.htm#6 Trotsky, Leon, ''Lessons of October'']: &quot;On October 16th the Military Revolutionary Committee was created, the legal Soviet organ of insurrection.&quot; Accessed 27/8/07&lt;/ref&gt;
Yet Trotsky only mobilised the Military Revolutionary Committee to seize power on the advent of the Second All-Russian Congress of Soviets of Workers' and Soldiers' Deputies, which began on 25 October 1917.

Following the [[October Revolution|Russian Revolution of 1917]] the [[Third International]] was founded. This International became widely identified with [[Communism]], but also defined itself in terms of revolutionary socialism.  However, in 1938, Trotskyists formed the [[Fourth International]] because they thought that the Third International was lost to [[Stalinism]]; this latter International became identified with revolutionary socialism.

Emerging from the [[Communist International]], but critical of the post-1924 Soviet Union, the Trotskyist tradition in Western Europe and elsewhere uses the term 'revolutionary socialism'. For instance, in 1932, the first issue of the first Canadian Trotskyist newspaper, ''The Vanguard'', published an editorial, &quot;Revolutionary Socialism vs Reformism&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.socialisthistory.ca/Docs/TrotOrigin/VanguardEdits32.htm ''Socialist History Project''], accessed 1 July 2007&lt;/ref&gt;  Today, many Trotskyist groups advocate &quot;revolutionary socialism&quot; as opposed to reformism, and are considered, and consider themselves, &quot;revolutionary socialists&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;For instance, the Committee for a Workers International states, &quot;We campaign for new workers’ parties and for them to adopt a socialist programme. At the same time, the CWI builds support for the ideas of revolutionary socialism&quot; [http://www.socialistworld.net/z/bin/kw.cgi/show?id=2771] and the UK Socialist Workers Party’s Alex Callinicos argues ''The Case for Revolutionary Socialism'', [http://www.swp.org.uk/swp_archive.php?article_id=5039].&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Luxemburgism]] is another revolutionary socialist tradition.

==See also==
*[[Impossibilism]]
*[[Political revolution]]
*[[Social revolution]]
*[[Socialism from below]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Economic ideologies]]
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:History of socialism]]
[[Category:Socialism]]

[[ar:اشتراكية ثورية]]
[[es:Socialismo revolucionario]]
[[it:Socialismo rivoluzionario]]
[[nl:Revolutionair socialisme]]
[[pl:Socjalizm rewolucyjny]]
[[ru:Революционный социализм]]
[[zh:革命社會主義]]</text>
      <sha1>dqog278dseufeitc6nexnathz69ga52</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
