<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Revolutions of 1848</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>10156432</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520957520</id>
      <parentid>520953457</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-01T21:24:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Rmhermen</username>
        <id>835</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>copyedit</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="35126">{{Infobox historical event
  |Event_Name     = Revolutions of 1848
  |Image_Name     = Horace Vernet-Barricade rue Soufflot.jpg
  |Image_Caption  = ''[[Barricade]] on the rue Soufflot'',&lt;ref&gt;{{event|date=1848-06-24|showname=Battle at Soufflot barricades-1848|street-address1=Rue Soufflot|city=Paris|lat=48.846792 |lon=2.343473}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=mRBYlHSKpjsC&amp;pg=PA201&amp;lpg=PA201|page=201|title=1848: Year of Revolution|author=Mike Rapport|isbn=978-0-465-01436-1|publisher=Basic Books|year=2009|quote=The first deaths can at noon on 23 June.}}&lt;/ref&gt; an 1848 painting by [[Horace Vernet]]. The [[Panthéon, Paris|Panthéon]] is shown in the background.
  |AKA            = Spring of Nations, Springtime of the Peoples, Year of Revolution
  |Participants   = People of [[France]], the [[German Confederation|German states]], the [[Austrian Empire]], the [[Italy|Italian states]], [[Denmark]], [[Wallachia]], [[Poland]], and others
  |Location       = [[Western Europe|Western]] and [[Central Europe]]
  |Date           = 23 February 1848-early 1849
  |Result         = Little overall structural change &lt;br&gt; Significant overall social and cultural change
}}
[[File:Image Germania (painting).jpg|thumb|right|200px|1848 painting titled ''[[Germania (painting)|Germania]]'', by [[Philipp Veit]]]]
The '''European Revolutions of 1848''', known in some countries as the '''Spring of Nations''', '''Springtime of the Peoples'''&lt;ref&gt;Merriman, John, A History of Modern Europe: From the French Revolution to the Present, 1996, p 715&lt;/ref&gt; or the '''Year of Revolution''', were a series of [[political upheaval]]s throughout Europe in 1848. It was the only Europe-wide collapse of traditional authority to date, but within a year, [[reactionary]] forces had won out, and the revolutions collapsed. 

This [[revolutionary wave]] began in [[French Revolution of 1848|France in February]], and immediately spread to most of Europe and parts of Latin America.  Over 50 countries were affected, but with no coordination or cooperation among the revolutionaries in different countries.  Five factors were involved: the widespread dissatisfaction with the political leadership; the demand for more participation and democracy; the demands of the working classes; the upsurge of nationalism; and finally, the regrouping of the reactionary forces based in the royalty, the aristocracy, the army, and the peasants.&lt;ref&gt;R.J.W. Evans and Hartmut Pogge von Strandmann, eds., ''The Revolutions in Europe 1848–1849'' (2000) pp v, 4&lt;/ref&gt; 

The uprisings were led by shaky ''ad hoc'' coalitions of reformers, the middle classes and workers, but it could not hold together for long. Tens of thousands of people were killed, and many more forced into exile. The only significant lasting reforms were the abolition of [[serfdom]] in Austria and Hungary, the end of [[absolute monarchy]] in Denmark, and the definitive end of the [[Capetian dynasty|Capetian monarchy]] in France. The revolutions were most important in France, Germany, Poland, Italy, and the Austrian Empire, and did not reach Russia, Great Britain, &lt;!-- stet. Do not change to the ambiguous 'Britain' or the wrong 'United Kingdom [of Great Britain and Ireland] because there was an 'upheaval' in Ireland --&gt;Spain, Sweden, Portugal, or the Ottoman Empire.&lt;ref&gt;Nor did it reach Spain, Belgium, Sweden, Portugal, or the Ottoman Empire. Evans and Strandmann (2000) p 2&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origins==
These revolutions arose from such a wide variety of causes that it is difficult to view them as resulting from a coherent movement or social phenomenon. Numerous changes had been taking place in European society throughout the first half of the 19th century. Both [[Classical liberal|liberal]] reformers and [[Radicalism (historical)|radical politician]]s were reshaping national governments. 

Technological change was revolutionizing the life of the working classes. A popular press extended political awareness, and new values and ideas such as [[liberalism|popular liberalism]], [[nationalism]] and [[socialism]] began to emerge.  Some historians emphasize the serious crop failures, particularly those of 1846, that produced hardship among peasants and the working urban poor.

[[File:Galician slaughter in 1846.PNG|thumb|250px|''[[Galician slaughter]]'' (Polish: ''Rzeź galicyjska'') by [[Jan Lewicki]] (1795–1871), depicting the massacre of Polish nobles by Polish peasants in [[Galicia (Eastern Europe)|Galicia]] in 1846]]
Large swathes of the [[nobility]] were discontented with [[absolute monarchy|royal absolutism]] or near-absolutism. In 1846, there had been an [[Kraków Uprising|uprising]] of [[Poland|Polish]] nobility in Austrian [[Kingdom of Galicia and Lodomeria|Galicia]], which was only countered when peasants, in turn, rose up against the nobles.&lt;ref&gt;Robert Bideleux and Ian Jeffries, ''A History of Eastern Europe: Crisis and Change'', Routledge, 1998. ISBN 0-415-1611-8. p. 295 – 296.&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, an [[Greater Poland Uprising (1846)|uprising]] by democratic forces against [[Prussia]] occurred in [[Greater Poland]].

Next, the [[middle class]]es began to agitate. Working-class objectives tended to fall in line with those of the middle class. Although [[Karl Marx]] and [[Friedrich Engels]] had written at the request of the [[Communist League]] in London (an organization consisting principally of German workers) ''[[The Communist Manifesto]]'' (published in German in London on February 21, 1848), once they began agitating in Germany following the March insurrection in Berlin, their demands were considerably reduced. They issued their &quot;Demands of the Communist Party in Germany&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1848/03/24.htm Demands of the Communist Party in Germany], Marx-Engels Collected Works, vol 7, pp. 3ff (Progress Publishers: 1975–2005)&lt;/ref&gt; from Paris in March; the pamphlet only urged unification of Germany, universal suffrage, abolition of feudal duties, and similar middle-class goals.

The middle and working classes thus shared a desire for reform, and agreed on many of the specific aims. Their participations in the revolutions, however, differed. While much of the impetus came from the middle classes, much of the cannon fodder came from the lower.{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}} The revolts first erupted in the cities.

===Urban workers===
The population in French rural areas had [[Population explosion|rapidly risen]], causing many peasants to seek a living in the cities. Many in the [[bourgeoisie]] feared and distanced themselves from the [[working poor]].  Many unskilled laborers toiled from 12 to 15 hours per day when they had work, living in squalid, disease-ridden slums. Traditional artisans felt the pressure of industrialization, having lost their [[guild]]s. Revolutionaries such as Marx built up a following.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=A History of Modern Europe: From the Renaissance to the Present|author=Merriman, John|year=1996|page=718|publisher=New York: W.W. Norton}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The situation in the German states was similar. Parts of [[Prussia]] were beginning to industrialize. During the decade of the 1840s, mechanized production in the textile industry brought about inexpensive clothing that undercut the handmade products of German tailors.&lt;ref&gt;Merriman, 1996, p. 724&lt;/ref&gt;  Reforms ameliorated the most unpopular features of rural [[feudalism]], while industrial workers remained dissatisfied with these and pressed for greater change.
[[File:Revolutions of 1848 in Europe (pasopt eng).svg|thumb|Map of Europe, showing the major events of 1848 and 1849]]
Urban workers had no choice but to spend half of their income on food, which consisted of bread and potatoes. As a result of harvest failures, food prices soared{{quantify|date=September 2012}} and the demand for manufactured goods decreased,{{quantify|date=September 2012}} causing an increase in unemployment.{{quantify|date=September 2012}} During the revolution, to address the problem of unemployment, workshops were organized for men interested in construction work. Officials also set up workshops for women when they felt they were excluded. Artisans and unemployed workers destroyed industrial machines when their social demands were neglected.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Revolutions and the Revolutionary Tradition|author=Breuilly, John ed. Parker, David|year=2000|page=114|publisher=New York: Routledge}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Rural areas===
Rural population growth had led to food shortages, [[Land (economics)|land]] pressure, and migration, both within Europe and out from Europe, especially to North America. In the years 1845 and 1846, a [[potato blight]] caused a [[European Potato Famine|subsistence crisis in Northern Europe]].  The effects of the blight were most severely manifested in the [[Great Irish Famine]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Helen Litton&quot;&gt;Helen Litton, ''The Irish Famine: An Illustrated History'', Wolfhound Press, 1995, ISBN 0-86327-912-0&lt;/ref&gt; but also caused famine-like conditions in the [[Scottish Highlands]] and throughout [[continental Europe]].

[[Aristocracy|Aristocratic]] wealth (and corresponding power) was synonymous with the ownership of farm lands and effective control over the [[peasant]]s. Peasant grievances exploded during the revolutionary year of 1848.

===Role of ideas===
Despite forceful and often violent efforts of established and reactionary powers to keep them down, disruptive ideas gained popularity: [[democracy]], [[liberalism]], [[nationalism]], and [[socialism]].&lt;ref&gt;Charles Breunig, ''The Age of Revolution and Reaction, 1789 – 1850'' (1977)&lt;/ref&gt;

In the language of the 1840s, 'democracy' meant universal male [[suffrage]]. 'Liberalism' fundamentally meant consent of the governed and the restriction of church and [[Sovereign state|state]] power, [[Republicanism|republican government]], [[freedom of the press]] and the individual. 'Nationalism' believed in uniting people bound by (some mix of) common [[language]]s, [[culture]], [[religion]], shared [[history]], and of course immediate [[geography]]; there were also [[Irredentism|irredentist]] movements. At this time, what are now [[Germany]] and [[Italy]] were collections of small states. 'Socialism' in the 1840s was a term without a consensus definition, meaning different things to different people, but was typically used within a context of more power for workers in a system based on [[Worker cooperative|worker ownership]] of the [[means of production]].

==Events==
[[File:Horace Vernet-Barricade rue Soufflot.jpg|thumb|250px|la ''[[Barricade de la rue Soufflot]]'', Paris, Feb 1848, by [[Horace Vernet]]]]

===Italian states===
{{main|Sicilian revolution of independence of 1848|Revolutions of 1848 in the Italian states}}

Although little noticed at the time, the first major outbreak came in Sicily, starting in January 1848. There had been several previous revolts against Bourbon rule; this one produced an independent state that lasted only 16 months before the Bourbons came back. During those months, the constitution was quite advanced for its time in liberal democratic terms, as was the proposal of an Italian confederation of states. The failed revolt was reversed a dozen years later as the Bourbon kingdom of the Two Sicilies collapsed in 1860–61 with the [[Risorgimento]].

===France===
{{main|French Revolution of 1848}}

The &quot;February Revolution&quot; in France was sparked by the suppression of the ''[[campagne des banquets]]''. This revolution was driven by nationalist and republican ideals among the French general public, who believed the people should rule themselves. It ended the [[constitutional monarchy]] of [[Louis-Philippe of France|Louis-Philippe]], and led to the creation of the [[French Second Republic]]. This government was headed by Louis-Napoleon, who, after only four years, returned France to a monarchy with the establishment of the Second French Empire in 1852.

[[Alexis de Tocqueville]] remarked in his ''Recollections'' of the period, &quot;society was cut in two: those who had nothing united in common envy, and those who had anything united in common terror.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Tocqueville, Alexis de. &quot;Recollections,&quot; 1893&lt;/ref&gt;

===German states===
{{main|Revolutions of 1848 in the German states}}

[[File:Maerz1848 berlin.jpg|thumb|256px|Cheering revolutionaries after fighting in March 1848]]
The &quot;March Revolution&quot; in the German states took place in the south and the west of Germany, with large popular assemblies and mass demonstrations. Led by well-educated students and intellectuals,&lt;ref&gt;Louis Namier, ''1848: The Revolution of
the Intellectuals'' (1964)&lt;/ref&gt; they demanded [[German national unity]], [[freedom of the press]], and [[freedom of assembly]].  The uprisings were not well coordinated, but had in common a rejection of traditional, autocratic political structures in the 39 independent states of the [[German Confederation]]. The middle-class and working-class components of the Revolution split, and in the end, the conservative aristocracy defeated it, forcing many liberals into exile.&lt;ref&gt;Theodote S. Hamerow, ''Restoration, Revolution, Reaction: Economics and Politics in Germany, 1825–1870'' (1958) focuses mainly on artisans and peasants&lt;/ref&gt;

===Denmark===
{{main|History of Denmark#Nationalism and liberalism}}
Denmark had been governed by a system of absolute monarchy since the 17th century.  King [[Christian VIII of Denmark|Christian VIII]], a moderate reformer but still an absolutist, died in January 1848 during a period of rising opposition from farmers and liberals.  The demands for constitutional monarchy, led by the [[National Liberal Party (Denmark)|National Liberals]], ended with a popular march to [[Christiansborg]] on March 21.  The new king, [[Frederick VII of Denmark|Frederick VII]], met the liberals' demands and installed a new Cabinet that included prominent leaders of the [[National Liberal Party (Denmark)|National Liberal Party]]. The national-liberal movement wanted to abolish absolutism, but retain a strongly centralized state.  The king accepted [[Constitution of Denmark|a new constitution]] agreeing to share power with a bicameral parliament called the [[Rigsdag]]. Although army officers were dissatisfied, they accepted the new arrangement which, in contrast to the rest of Europe, was not overturned by reactionaries.&lt;ref&gt;Weibull, Jörgen. &quot;Scandinavia, History of.&quot; ''[[Encyclopædia Britannica]]'' 15th ed., Vol. 16, 324.&lt;/ref&gt; The liberal constitution did not extend to Schleswig, leaving the [[Schleswig-Holstein Question]] unanswered.
[[File:Tropper 1849.jpg|250px|thumb|Danish soldiers return victorious]]

====Schleswig====
{{main|First Schleswig War}}
[[Schleswig]], a region containing both Danes and Germans, was a part of the Danish monarchy, but remained a duchy separate from the Kingdom of Denmark.  Spurred by [[Pan-Germanism|pan-German]] sentiment, Germans of Schleswig took up arms to protest a new policy announced by Denmark's [[National Liberal Party (Denmark)|National Liberal]] government, which would have fully integrated the duchy into Denmark. The German population in Schleswig and Holstein revolted, inspired by the Protestant clergy. The German states sent in an army, but Danish victories in 1849 led to the Treaty of Berlin (1850) and the London Protocols (1852). They reaffirmed the sovereignty of the King of Denmark, while prohibiting union with Denmark. The violation of the latter provision led to renewed warfare in 1863 and the Prussian victory in 1864.

===Habsburg Empire===
{{main|Revolutions of 1848 in the Habsburg areas}}

[[File:Proglasenje srpske vojvodine.jpg|thumb|250px|Proclamation of [[Serbian Vojvodina]] in [[Sremski Karlovci]].]]
From March 1848 through July 1849, the Habsburg Austrian Empire was threatened by revolutionary movements, which often had a nationalist character.  The empire, ruled from Vienna, included Austrian Germans, Hungarians, Slovenes, Poles, Czechs, Croats, Slovaks, Ukrainians/[[Ruthenians]], Romanians, [[Serbs]] and Italians, all of whom attempted in the course of the revolution to either achieve autonomy, independence, or even hegemony over other nationalities. The nationalist picture was further complicated by the simultaneous events in the German states, which moved toward greater German national unity.

====Hungary====
{{main|Hungarian Revolution of 1848}}

[[File:Jakobey Buda ostroma 2.jpg|thumb|250px|[[Battle of Buda (1849)|Battle of Buda]], May 1849, by [[Mór Than]]]]
[[File:Komáromi csata II Than 2.jpg|thumb|250px|Hungarian [[hussar]]s in battle during the Hungarian Revolution]]
The Hungarian revolution of 1848 started on 15 March 1848, when [[Hungarian people|Hungarian]] patriots organized mass demonstrations in [[Pest, Hungary|Pest]] and [[Buda]] (today Budapest) which forced the Imperial governor to accept their [[12 points of the Hungarian Revolutionaries of 1848|12 points of demands]]. This resulted in [[Klemens von Metternich]], the Austrian prince and foreign minister, resigning. In turn, Emperor Ferdinand promised Hungary a constitution, an elected parliament, and the end of censorship. The revolution grew into a war for independence from the Austrian Empire when [[Josip Jelačić]], Ban of Croatia, crossed the border to restore Habsburg control. The new government, led by [[Lajos Kossuth]], was initially successful against the Habsburg forces, but eventually, after one and a half years of fighting, the revolution was crushed when Russian Tsar [[Nicholas I of Russia|Nicholas I]] marched into Hungary with over 300,000 troops. Hungary was thus placed under brutal martial law, with the Austrian government restored.&lt;ref&gt;The Making of the West: Volume C, Lynn Hunt, Pages 683–684&lt;/ref&gt; In the long run, the passive resistance following the revolution led to the [[Austro-Hungarian Compromise of 1867|Austro-Hungarian Compromise]] (1867), which marked the birth of the [[Austria-Hungary|Austro-Hungarian Empire]].

===Switzerland===
{{main|Sonderbund war}}
Switzerland, already an alliance of republics, also saw major internal struggle. The creation of the [[Sonderbund]] led to a short [[Swiss civil war]] in November 1847. In 1848, a new constitution ended the almost-complete independence of the cantons, and transformed Switzerland into a federal state.

===Western Ukraine===
The center of the Ukrainian national movement was in [[Galicia (Eastern Europe)|Eastern Galicia]]. On April 19, 1848, a group of representatives led by the Greek Catholic clergy launched a petition to the Austrian Emperor. It expressed wishes that in those regions of Galicia where the Ruthenian (Ukrainian) population represented majority, the [[Ukrainian language]] should be taught at schools and used to announce official decrees for the peasantry; local officials were expected to understand it and the Ruthenian clergy was to be equalized in their rights with the clergy of all other denominations.&lt;ref&gt;Kost' Levytskyi, The History of the Political Thought of the Galician Ukrainians, 1848-1914, (Lviv, 1926), 17.&lt;/ref&gt;

On May 2, 1848, the [[Supreme Ruthenian Council|Supreme Ruthenian (Ukrainian) Council]] was established. The Council (1848-1851) was headed by the Greek-Catholic Bishop Gregory Yakhimovich and consisted of 30 permanent members. Its main goal was the administrative division of Galicia into Western (Polish) and Eastern (Ruthenian/Ukrainian) parts within the borders of the Habsburg Empire, and formation of a separate region with a political self-governance.&lt;ref&gt;Ibid., 26.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Greater Poland===
{{main|Greater Poland Uprising (1848)}}
Polish people mounted a military insurrection in the [[Grand Duchy of Poznań]] (or the [[Greater Poland]] region) against the occupying [[Prussia]]n forces.

===Danubian Principalities===
{{main|Wallachian Revolution of 1848}}

[[File:1848-revolutia-Romania.jpg|thumb|190px|People in [[Bucharest]] during the 1848 events, carrying the [[Flag of Romania|Romanian tricolor]]]]
A [[Romanians|Romanian]] [[Liberalism|liberal]] and [[Romantic nationalism|Romantic nationalist]] uprising began in June in the principality of [[Wallachia]]. Closely connected with the 1848 unsuccessful [[Moldavian Revolution of 1848|revolt in Moldavia]], it sought to overturn the administration imposed by [[Russian Empire|Imperial Russian]] authorities under the ''[[Regulamentul Organic]]'' regime, and, through many of its leaders, demanded the abolition of [[boyar]] privilege. Led by a group of young intellectuals and officers in the Wallachian military forces, the movement succeeded in toppling the ruling [[List of rulers of Wallachia|Prince]] [[Gheorghe Bibescu]], whom it replaced with a provisional government and a [[Regent|regency]], and in passing a series of major liberal reforms, first announced in the [[Proclamation of Islaz]].

===Belgium===
In [[History of Belgium|Belgium]], the uprisings were local and concentrated in the industrial basins of the Provinces of Liège and Hainaut. A more or less greater threat was coming from France, where among the seasonal workers, Communism was spread by the small Communist clique of Belgium, basically the people were brought into a Belgian Legion, with the promise of a free ride home and money. The Belgian Legion would 'invade' Belgium by train and travel to Brussels, where the government and monarchy had to be overthrown. Several smaller groups managed to infiltrate Belgium, but the reinforced Belgian border troops were successful in splitting up the larger groups of the Legion, and the invasion eventually came to nothing.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ohio.edu/chastain/ac/belgium.htm Belgium in 1848 – ''Encyclopedia of 1848 Revolutions'']&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ireland===
The [[Young Irelander Rebellion of 1848]] was a small, failed rebellion which broke out in [[Ballingarry, South Tipperary|Ballingarry]], [[Co. Tipperary]]. It was led by the [[Young Ireland]] movement, inspired by [[Great Famine (Ireland)|famine conditions in Ireland]] and the 1848 rebellions throughout Europe.

===Other English-speaking lands===
[[File:Chartist meeting, Kennington Common.jpg|thumb|250px|[[Chartism|Chartist]] meeting on [[Kennington Common]] 10 April 1848]]
Elsewhere in [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|Britain]], the middle classes had been pacified by general enfranchisement in the [[Reform Act 1832]]; the consequent agitations, violence, and petitions of the [[Chartism|Chartist movement]] came to a head with [[Chartism#The 1848 petition|their peaceful petition to Parliament]] of 1848. The repeal in 1846 of the protectionist agricultural tariffs{{spaced ndash}}called the &quot;[[Corn Laws]]&quot;{{spaced ndash}}had defused some proletarian fervour.&lt;ref&gt;Henry Weisser, &quot;Chartism in 1848: Reflections on a Non-Revolution,&quot; ''Albion: A Quarterly Journal Concerned with British Studies'' Vol. 13, No. 1 (Spring, 1981), pp. 12–26 [http://www.jstor.org/stable/4049111 in JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt;

The revolutions had little impact in British colonies, aside from a modest influx of immigration from German-speaking lands.  In the United States, the main impact of the revolutions and their failure was [[Forty-Eighters|substantially increased immigration]], especially from Germany.  This, in turn, fuelled the [[Nativism (politics)|nativist]] &quot;[[Know Nothing]]&quot; movement in the years preceding the [[American Civil War]].  The &quot;Know Nothings&quot; were opposed to immigration, especially immigration of German and Irish Catholics and held the [[Pope]], [[Pius IX]], responsible for the revolutions' failure.

===New Grenada===
In Spanish Latin America, the Revolution of 1848 appeared in [[Republic of New Granada|New Grenada]], where Colombian students, liberals, and intellectuals demanded the election of General [[José Hilario López]]. He took power in 1849 and launched major reforms, abolishing slavery and the death penalty, and providing freedom of the press and of religion. The resulting turmoil in [[History of Colombia|Colombia]] lasted four decades; from 1851 to 1885, the country was ravaged by four general civil wars and 50 local revolutions.&lt;ref&gt;J. Fred Rippy, '' Latin America: A Modern History'' (1958) pp 253–4&lt;/ref&gt;

===Brazil===
{{main|Praieira revolt}}
In [[Brazil]], the &quot;Praieira revolt&quot;, a movement in [[Pernambuco]], lasted from November 1848 to 1852.  Unresolved conflicts left over from the period of the regency and local resistance to the consolidation of the [[Empire of Brazil|Brazilian Empire]] that had been proclaimed in 1822 helped to plant the seeds of the revolution.

==Legacy and memory==
{{quote|''. . . We have been beaten and humiliated . . . scattered, imprisoned, disarmed and gagged. The fate of European democracy has slipped from our hands.''|[[Pierre-Joseph Proudhon]]|&lt;ref&gt;Breunig, Charles (1977), The Age of Revolution and Reaction, 1789 – 1850 (ISBN 0-393-09143-0)&lt;/ref&gt;}}

[[File:Rundgemälde Europa 1849.jpg|thumb|250px|Caricature by Ferdinand Schröder on the defeat of the revolutions of 1848/49 in Europe (published in ''Düsseldorfer Monatshefte'', August 1849)]]
There were multiple memories of the Revolutions. Democrats looked to 1848 as a democratic revolution, which in the long run insured liberty, equality, and fraternity. Marxists denounced 1848 as a betrayal of working-class ideals by a bourgeoisie indifferent to the legitimate demands of the proletariat. For nationalists, 1848 was the springtime of hope, when newly emerging nationalities rejected the old multinational empires. They were all bitterly disappointed in the short run. The year 1848, at best, was a glimmer of future hope, and at worst, it was a deadweight that strengthened the reactionaries and delayed further progress.&lt;ref&gt;Robert Gildea, &quot;1848 in European Collective Memory,&quot; in Evans and Strandmann, eds. ''The Revolutions in Europe, 1848–1849'' pp 207–235&lt;/ref&gt;

In the post-revolutionary decade after 1848, little had visibly changed, and most historians considered the revolutions a failure, given the seeming lack of permanent structural changes. 

Nevertheless, there were a few immediate successes for some revolutionary movements, notably in the Habsburg lands. [[Austrian Empire|Austria]] and [[Prussia]] eliminated feudalism by 1850, improving the lot of the peasants. European middle classes made political and economic gains over the next 20 years; France retained universal male suffrage. Russia would later [[Emancipation reform of 1861|free the serfs on February 19, 1861]]. The Habsburgs finally had to give the Hungarians more [[self-determination]] in the ''[[Ausgleich]]'' of 1867.  The revolutions inspired lasting reform in [[Denmark]], as well as the [[Netherlands]].

==Exceptions==
[[Great Britain]],&lt;!-- NOT the UK of GB&amp;I because there was a revolution in Ireland --&gt; the Netherlands, the [[Russian Empire]] (including [[Congress Poland]]), and the [[Ottoman Empire]] were the only major European states to go without a national revolution over this period. [[Sweden]] and [[Norway]] were little affected. [[Principality of Serbia|Serbia]], though formally unaffected by the revolt as it was a part of the Ottoman state, actively supported the [[Revolutions of 1848 in the Habsburg areas|Serbian revolution in the Habsburg Empire]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ohiou.edu/~Chastain/rz/serbvio.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

Russia's relative stability was attributed to the revolutionary groups' inability to communicate with each other.{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}} In the [[Congress Poland|Kingdom of Poland]] and the [[Grand Duchy of Lithuania]], uprisings took place in 1830–31 (the [[November Uprising]]) and 1846 (the [[Kraków Uprising]]). A final revolt took place in 1863–65 (the [[January Uprising]]), but none occurred in 1848. 

[[Switzerland]] and [[Portugal]] were also spared in 1848, though both had gone through civil wars in the preceding years (the [[Sonderbund War]] in Switzerland and the [[Liberal Wars]] in Portugal). The introduction of the [[Swiss Federal Constitution]] in 1848 was a revolution of sorts, laying the foundation of Swiss society as it is today. In the Netherlands, no major unrests appeared because the king, [[William II of the Netherlands|Willem II]], decided to alter the constitution to reform elections and effectively reduce the power of the monarchy. While no major political upheavals occurred in the Ottoman Empire as such, political unrest did occur in some of its [[Vassal States (Ottoman Empire)|vassal states]]. In Serbia, [[feudalism]] was finally abolished in 1838, and power of the Serbian prince was reduced with the [[Turkish constitution (Serbia)|Turkish constitution]].

==References==
{{Ibid|date=May 2012}}
{{Reflist}}

==Bibliography==

===Surveys===
* Breunig, Charles (1977), ''The Age of Revolution and Reaction, 1789 – 1850'' (ISBN 0-393-09143-0)
* Chastain, James, ed. (2005) ''Encyclopedia of Revolutions of 1848''  [http://www.ohio.edu/chastain/contents.htm online from Ohio State U.]
* Dowe, Dieter, ed. ''Europe in 1848: Revolution and Reform'' (Berghahn Books, 2000)
* Evans, R.J.W., and Hartmut Pogge von Strandmann, eds. ''The Revolutions in Europe, 1848–1849: From Reform to Reaction'' (2000), 10 essays by scholars [http://www.amazon.com/Revolutions-Europe-1848-1849-Reform-Reaction/dp/0198208405/ excerpt and text search]
*Pouthas, Charles. &quot;The Revolutions of 1848&quot; in J. P. T. Bury, ed. ''New Cambridge Modern History: The zenith of European power 1830–70'' (1960) pp 389–415 [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=jRQ9AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PR5&amp;source=gbs_selected_pages&amp;cad=3#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false online excerpts]
* Langer, William. ''The Revolutions of 1848'' (Harper, 1971), standard overview
* Rapport, Mike (2009), ''1848: Year of Revolution'' ISBN 978-0-465-01436-1 [http://www.h-net.org/reviews/showrev.php?id=25808 online review], a standard survey
* Robertson, Priscilla (1952), ''Revolutions of 1848: A Social History'' (ISBN 0-691-00756-X), despite the subtitle this is a traditional political narrative
* Sperber, Jonathan. ''The European revolutions, 1848–1851'' (1994) [http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/text-idx?c=acls;cc=acls;view=toc;idno=heb01876.0001.001 online edition]
* Stearns, Peter N. ''The Revolutions of 1848'' (1974). [http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=30508731 online edition]
* Weyland, Kurt. &quot;The Diffusion of Revolution: '1848' in Europe and Latin America,&quot; ''International Organization'' Vol. 63, No. 3 (Summer, 2009) pp.&amp;nbsp;391–423 [http://www.jstor.org/stable/40345942 in JSTOR]

===France===
* Duveau, Georges. ''1848: The Making of a Revolution'' (1966)
* Fasel, George. &quot;The Wrong Revolution: French Republicanism in 1848,&quot; ''French Historical Studies'' Vol. 8, No. 4 (Autumn, 1974), pp.&amp;nbsp;654–677 [http://www.jstor.org/stable/285857 in JSTOR]
* Loubère, Leo. &quot;The Emergence of the Extreme Left in Lower Languedoc, 1848–1851: Social and Economic Factors in Politics,&quot; ''American Historical Review'' (1968), v. 73#4 1019–1051 [http://www.jstor.org/stable/1847387 in JSTOR]

===Germany and Austria===
* Deak, Istvan. ''The Lawful Revolution: Louis Kossuth and the Hungarians, 1848–1849'' (1979)
* Hahs, Hans J. ''The 1848 Revolutions in German-speaking Europe'' (2001)
* Hewitson, Mark. &quot;'The Old Forms are Breaking Up, … Our New Germany is Rebuilding Itself': Constitutionalism, Nationalism and the Creation of a German Polity during the Revolutions of 1848–49,&quot; ''English Historical Review,'' Oct 2010, Vol. 125 Issue 516, pp 1173–1214 [http://ehr.oxfordjournals.org/content/CXXV/516/1173.extract online]
* Macartney, C. A. &quot;1848 in the Habsburg Monarchy,&quot; ''European Studies Review,'' 1977, Vol. 7 Issue 3, pp 285–309 [http://ehq.sagepub.com/content/7/3/285.extract online]
* O'Boyle Lenore. &quot;The Democratic Left in Germany, 1848,&quot; ''Journal of Modern History'' Vol. 33, No. 4 (Dec., 1961), pp.&amp;nbsp;374–383 [http://www.jstor.org/stable/1877214 in JSTOR]
* Robertson, Priscilla. ''Revolutions of 1848: A Social History'' (1952),  pp 105–85 on Germany, pp 187–307 on Austria
* Sked, Alan. ''The Survival of the Habsburg Empire: Radetzky, the Imperial Army and the Class War, 1848'' (1979)
* Vick, Brian. ''Defining Germany The 1848 Frankfurt Parliamentarians and National Identity''  (Harvard University Press, 2002) ISBN 978-0-674-00911-0).

===Italy===
* Ginsborg, Paul. &quot;Peasants and Revolutionaries in Venice and the Veneto, 1848,&quot; ''Historical Journal,'' Sep 1974, Vol. 17 Issue 3, pp 503–550 [http://www.jstor.org/stable/2638387 in JSTOR]
* Ginsborg, Paul. ''Daniele Manin and the Venetian Revolution of 1848–49'' (1979)
* Robertson, Priscilla (1952). ''Revolutions of 1848: A Social History'' (1952) pp 309–401

===Other===
* Feyzioğlu, Hamiyet Sezer et al. &quot;Revolutions of 1848 and the Ottoman Empire,&quot; ''Bulgarian Historical Review,'' 2009, Vol. 37 Issue 3/4, pp 196–205

===Historiography===
* Dénes, Iván Zoltán. &quot;Reinterpreting a 'Founding Father': Kossuth Images and Their Contexts, 1848–2009,&quot; ''East Central Europe,'' April 2010, Vol. 37 Issue 1, pp 90–117
* Hamerow, Theodore S. &quot;History and the German Revolution of 1848,&quot; ''American Historical Review'' Vol. 60, No. 1 (Oct., 1954), pp.&amp;nbsp;27–44 [http://www.jstor.org/stable/1842744 in JSTOR]
* Jones, Peter (1981), ''The 1848 Revolutions (Seminar Studies in History)'' (ISBN 0-582-06106-7)
* Mattheisen, Donald J. &quot;History as Current Events: Recent Works on the German Revolution of 1848,&quot; ''American Historical Review,'' Dec 1983, Vol. 88 Issue 5, pp 1219–37 [http://www.jstor.org/pss/1904890 in JSTOR]
* Rothfels, Hans. &quot;1848 – One Hundred Years After,&quot; ''Journal of Modern History,'' Dec 1948, Vol. 20 Issue 4, pp 291–319 [http://www.jstor.org/pss/1871060 in JSTOR]

==External links==
{{commons category|Revolutions of 1848}}
*[http://www.age-of-the-sage.org/history/1848/revolution_of_1848.html The Revolutions of 1848 begin]

{{Revolutions of 1848}}

[[Category:Revolutions of 1848| ]]

[[als:1848er-Revolution]]
[[ar:ثورات 1848]]
[[be:Рэвалюцыі 1848—1849 гадоў]]
[[ca:Revolució de 1848]]
[[cs:Revoluce v roce 1848]]
[[da:Revolutionerne i 1848]]
[[de:Revolution von 1848/1849]]
[[el:Άνοιξη των λαών]]
[[es:Revoluciones de 1848]]
[[eo:Revolucio de 1848]]
[[eu:1848ko iraultzak]]
[[fa:جنبش‌های ۱۸۴۸]]
[[fr:Printemps des peuples]]
[[fy:Revolúsjejier 1848]]
[[ga:Bliain na Réabhlóidí]]
[[gl:Revolucións de 1848]]
[[ko:1848년 혁명]]
[[id:Revolusi 1848]]
[[ia:Revolutiones de 1848]]
[[it:Primavera dei popoli]]
[[he:אביב העמים]]
[[lb:Fréijoer vun de Vëlker]]
[[lt:Tautų pavasaris]]
[[nl:Revolutiejaar 1848]]
[[ja:1848年革命]]
[[no:Revolusjonene i 1848]]
[[pl:Wiosna Ludów]]
[[pt:Revoluções de 1848]]
[[ro:Revoluția de la 1848]]
[[ru:Революции 1848—1849 годов]]
[[simple:European Revolutions of 1848]]
[[sk:Revolúcia v rokoch 1848 – 1849]]
[[sl:Revolucije leta 1848]]
[[fi:Euroopan hullu vuosi]]
[[sv:Revolutionerna 1848]]
[[ta:1848 ஆம் ஆண்டுப் புரட்சிகள்]]
[[tr:1848 Devrimleri]]
[[uk:Революції 1848—1849 років]]
[[zh:1848年革命]]</text>
      <sha1>plvh0v3dakv7ao0ovf0h5eu2v9q5k3p</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
