<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Right-wing politics</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>56522</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522229931</id>
      <parentid>522188267</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T20:27:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Rick Norwood</username>
        <id>301854</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Standard dictionaries capitalize Right and Left in &quot;the Right&quot; and &quot;the Left&quot;, but not in right-wing and left-wing.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="39498">{{Redirect|Right wing|conservative political thought|conservatism}}
{{Party politics}}
In [[politics]], '''right-wing''' describes an outlook or specific position that accepts or supports [[Social stratification|social hierarchy]] or [[social inequality]].&lt;ref&gt;Bobbio, Norberto and Allan Cameron,''Left and Right: The Significance of a Political Distinction''. [[University of Chicago Press]], 1997, p. 51, 62. ISBN 978-0-226-06246-4&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;J. E. Goldthorpe. ''An Introduction to Sociology''. Cambridge, England, UK; Oakleigh, Melbourne, Australia; New York, New York, USA Pp. 156. ISBN 0-521-24545-1.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rodney P. Carlisle. ''Encyclopedia of politics: the left and the right, Volume 2''. University of Michigan; Sage Reference, 2005. Pp.693, 721. ISBN 1-4129-0409-9&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;T. Alexander Smith 2003. Pp 30&quot;&gt;T. Alexander Smith, Raymond Tatalovich. ''Cultures at war: moral conflicts in western democracies''. Toronto, Canada: Broadview Press, Ltd, 2003. Pp 30. &quot;That viewpoint is held by contemporary sociologists, for whom 'right-wing movements' are conceptualized as 'social movements whose stated goals are to maintain structures of order, status, honor, or traditional social differences or values' as compared to left-wing movements which seek 'greater equality or political participation.' In other words, the sociological perspective sees preservationist politics as a right-wing attempt to defend privilege within the ''social hierarchy''.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Social hierarchy and social inequality is viewed by those affiliated with the Right as either inevitable, natural, normal, or  desirable,&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt; whether it arises through traditional social differences&lt;ref&gt;Smith, T. Alexander and Raymond Tatalovich. ''Cultures at War: Moral Conflicts in Western Democracies'' (Toronto, Canada: Broadview Press, Ltd., 2003) pp. 30. &quot;That viewpoint is held by contemporary sociologists, for whom 'right-wing movements' are conceptualized as 'social movements whose stated goals are to maintain structures of order, status, honor, or traditional social differences or values' as compared to left-wing movements which seek 'greater equality or political participation.' '&lt;/ref&gt; or from competition in market economies.&lt;ref&gt;Scruton, Roger “A Dictionary of Political Thought” &quot;Defined by contrast to (or perhaps more accurately conflict with) the left the term right does not even have the respectability of a history. As now used it denotes several connected and also conflicting ideas (including) 1)conservative, and perhaps authoritarian, doctrines concerning the nature of civil society, with emphasis on custom, tradition, and allegiance as social bonds ... 8) belief in free enterprise free markets and a capitalist economy as the only mode of production compatible with human freedom and suited to the temporary nature of human aspirations ...&quot; pp. 281-2, Macmillian, 1996&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;J. E. Goldthorpe. ''An Introduction to Sociology''. &quot;There are ... those who accept inequality as natural, normal, and even desirable. Two main lines of thought converge on the Right or conservative side...the truly Conservative view is that there is a natural hierarchy of skills and talents in which some people are born leaders, whether by heredity or family tradition. ... now ... the more usual right-wing view, which may be called 'liberal-conservative', is that unequal rewards are right and desirable so long as the competition for wealth and power is a fair one.&quot; p. 156. Cambridge, England, UK; Oakleigh, Melbourne, Australia; New York, New York, USA Pp. 156. ISBN 0-521-24545-1.&lt;/ref&gt; It typically accepts or justifies this position on the basis of [[natural law]] or [[tradition]].&lt;ref name=&quot;T. Alexander Smith 2003. Pp 30&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Allan Cameron pg. 37&quot;&gt;''Left and right: the significance of a political distinction'', Norberto Bobbio and Allan Cameron, pg. 37, [[University of Chicago Press]], 1997.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fuchs, D. 1990. Pp.203&quot;&gt;[[Seymour Martin Lipset]], cited in Fuchs, D., and Klingemann, H. 1990. The left-right schema. Pp.203–34 in Continuities in Political Action: A Longitudinal Study of Political Orientations in Three Western Democracies, ed.M.Jennings et al. Berlin:de Gruyter&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Lukes&gt;Lukes, Steven. 'Epilogue: The Grand Dichotomy of the Twentieth Century': concluding chapter to T. Ball and R. Bellamy (eds.), The Cambridge History of Twentieth-Century Political Thought. Pp.610–612&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Clark, William 2003&quot;&gt;Clark, William. Capitalism, not Globalism. University of Michigan Press, 2003. ISBN 0-472-11293-7, ISBN 978-0-472-11293-7&lt;/ref&gt;

The political terms ''Right'' and ''[[Left-wing politics|Left]]'' were coined during the [[French Revolution]] (1789–99), and referred to where politicians sat in the French parliament; those who sat to the right of the chair of the parliamentary president were broadly supportive of the institutions of the monarchist ''[[Ancien Régime]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Parliaments 1988 pp. 287–302&quot;&gt;Goodsell, Charles T., &quot;The Architecture of Parliaments: Legislative Houses and Political Culture&quot;, British Journal of Political Science, Vol. 18, No. 3 (July , 1988) pp. 287–302&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Linski, Gerhard, ''Current Issues and Research In Macrosociology'' (Brill Archive, 1984) p. 59&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Clark, Barry ''Political Economy: A Comparative Approach'' (Praeger Paperback, 1998) pp. 33–34&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Knapp&quot;/&gt;  The original Right in France was formed as a [[Reactionary|reaction]] against the Left, it comprised those politicians supporting hierarchy, tradition, and [[clericalism]].&lt;ref&gt;Rodney P. Carlisle. ''Encyclopedia of politics: the left and the right, Volume 2''. University of Michigan; Sage Reference, 2005, p. 693. ISBN 1-4129-0409-9&lt;/ref&gt; The use of the expression ''la droite'' (''the right'') became prominent in France after the restoration of the monarchy in 1815, when ''le droit'' was applied to describe the [[Ultra-royalist]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Gauchet, Marcel, &quot;Right and Left&quot; in Nora, Pierre, ed., ''Realms of Memory: Conflicts and Divisions'' (1996) pp. 247-8&lt;/ref&gt; In English-speaking countries it was not until the 20th century that people applied the terms &quot;right&quot; and &quot;left&quot; to their own politics.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The English Ideology: Studies in the Language of Victorian Politics&quot; George Watson Allen Lane: London 1973 p.94&lt;/ref&gt; 

Although the term originally designated [[Traditionalist conservatism|traditional conservatives]] and [[reactionary|reactionaries]], the usage of “right-wing” has been extended to describe [[Liberal conservatism|liberal conservatives]], [[classical liberalism|classical liberals]], [[Libertarian conservatism|libertarian conservatives]], [[Christian democrats]], and [[nationalism|nationalists]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Knapp&quot;/&gt;  The left, right, and center are often associated with [[socialism]], [[conservatism]], and [[liberalism]] respectively, in varying degrees.&lt;ref name=&quot;Political Man 1960 p. 131&quot;&gt;''Political Man'' (1960) by Seymour Martin Lipset, pp. 131–133&lt;/ref&gt; Some historians and social scientists seek to reduce political beliefs to class, with left, right, and center politicians representing the working, upper or middle classes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Political Man 1960 p. 131&quot;/&gt;  Others draw attention to the role which religious, ethnic, and regional differences play in democratic politics.&lt;ref&gt;Phillips, Kevin, &quot;The Cousins' Wars: Religion, Politics, &amp; The Triumph of Anglo-America&quot; (1999) pp.513-607&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{{See also|Left–right politics}}
[[File:Estatesgeneral.jpg|thumb|5 May 1789: Opening of the Estates-General in Versailles]]

The political term ''right-wing'' originates from the [[French Revolution]], when [[Liberalism|liberal]] deputies from the [[Estates-General of 1789|Third Estate]] generally sat to the left of the president's chair, a habit which began in the [[French States-General|Estates General]] of 1789. The nobility, members of the [[Second Estate]], generally sat to the right. In the successive [[Legislative Assembly (France)|legislative assemblies]], [[Monarchism|monarchists]] who supported the [[Ancien Régime]] were commonly referred to as rightists, because they sat on the right side. A major figure on the right was [[Joseph de Maistre]], who argued for an [[authoritarianism|authoritarian]] form of [[conservatism]]. Throughout the [[France in the 19th century|19th century]], the main line dividing [[Politics of France|Left and Right in France]] was between supporters of the [[Republic]] and supporters of the [[Monarchy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Knapp&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Andrew Knapp and Vincent Wright|url=http://books.google.com/?id=67ttjXHhT3wC&amp;dq=the+government+and+politics+of+france&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;q=|title=The Government and Politics of France|year=2006|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-0-415-35732-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the right, the [[Legitimists]] and [[Ultra-royalist]]s held [[counter-revolutionary]] views, while the [[Orléanist]]s hoped to create a [[constitutional monarchy]] under their preferred branch of the royal family, a brief reality after the 1830 [[July Revolution]].  The centre-right Gaullists in post-World War II France advocated considerable social spending on education and infrastructure development, as well as extensive economic regulation, but limited the wealth redistribution measures characteristic of social democracy. 

According to ''The Cambridge History of Twentieth-Century Political Thought'', the Right has gone through five distinct historical stages: (i) the reactionary right, which sought a return to aristocracy and established religion; (ii) the moderate right, who sought limited government and distrusted intellectuals; (iii) the radical right, who favored a romantic and aggressive nationalism; (iv) the extreme right, who proposed anti-immigration policies and implicit racism; and (v) the [[Neoliberalism|neo-liberal]] right, who sought to combine a belief in a market economy and economic deregulation with the traditional Right-wing beliefs in [[patriotism]], [[élitism]], and law and order.&lt;ref&gt;Ball, T. and R. Bellamy, eds., ''The Cambridge History of Twentieth-Century Political Thought'' pp. 610–612&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Clark, William. ''Capitalism, not Globalism'' (University of Michigan Press, 2003) ISBN 0-472-11293-7, ISBN 978-0-472-11293-7&lt;/ref&gt;

==Positions==
The meaning of right-wing &quot;varies across societies, historical epochs, and political systems and ideologies.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''The meaning of 'right-wing' and 'left-wing' varies across societies, historical epochs and political systems and ideologies.'' [http://books.google.com/books?id=CYjEwFRPEQgC&amp;pg=PA230 Social cognition: an integrated introduction] Martha Augoustinos, Iain Walker, Ngaire Donaghue; SAGE, June 15, 2006 - 364 pages, page 30&lt;/ref&gt;  According to ''The Concise Oxford Dictionary of Politics'', in liberal democracies the political Right opposes socialism and social democracy.  Right-wing parties include  conservatives, Christian democrats, classical liberals, nationalists and, on the far Right, racists and fascists.&lt;ref&gt;''Concise Oxford Dictionary of Politics'', Iain McLean, Alistair McMillan, eds., Oxford University Press, 2009, ISBN 9780199205165&lt;/ref&gt;   

There has been considerable criticism of the reduction of politics to a simple left-right axis.  [[Friedrich Hayek]] suggests that it is incorrect to view the political spectrum as a line, with socialists on the left, conservatives on the right, and liberals in the middle. He places each group at the corner of a triangle.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Hayek, Friedrich, Why I Am Not a Conservative&quot;, in ''The Constitution of Liberty'' (1960) [http://www.fahayek.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=46]&lt;/ref&gt;

Eatwell and O'Sullivan divide the Right into five types:  'reactionary', 'moderate', 'radical', 'extreme', and 'new'.&lt;ref&gt;Davies, p. 13&lt;/ref&gt;  Each of these &quot;styles of thought&quot; are seen as &quot;responses to the left&quot;, including both liberalism and socialism, that have arisen since the French Revolution of 1789.&lt;ref name=&quot;Berlet, p. 117&quot;&gt;Berlet, p. 117&lt;/ref&gt;

The 'reactionary right' looks toward the past and is &quot;aristocratic, religious and authoritarian&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Berlet, p. 117&quot;/&gt;

The 'moderate right' is typified by the writings of [[Edmund Burke]].  It is tolerant of change, provided it is gradual, and accepts some aspects of liberalism, including the rule of law and capitalism, although it sees radical laissez-faire and individualism as harmful to society.  Often it promotes nationalism and social welfare policies.&lt;ref&gt;Eatwell: 1999, p. 284&lt;/ref&gt;

The 'radical right' is a term developed after the Second World War to describe groups as different as [[McCarthyism]], the [[John Birch Society]], [[Thatcherism]], the [[Republikaner Party]] in West Germany, and so on. Eatwell stresses that this use has &quot;major typological problems&quot; and that the term &quot;has also been applied to clearly democratic developments.&quot;&lt; &lt;ref&gt;Eatwell: 2004, pp. 7-8&lt;/ref&gt;  It includes [[right-wing populism]] and various other subtypes.&lt;ref&gt;Berlet, p.117&lt;/ref&gt;

The 'extreme right' has four traits according to Roger Eatwell: &quot;1)anti-democracy; 2) nationalism; 3) racism; 4) the strong state&quot;. He adds that violence is now dropped as a characteristic.&lt;ref&gt;Eatwell: 2004, &quot;Today four other traits feature most prominently in definitions: 1) anti-democracy; 2) nationalism; 3) racism; 4) the strong state...&quot;; pp.8&lt;/ref&gt;

The 'New Right' consists of the liberal conservatives, who stress small government, free markets, and individual initiative.&lt;ref&gt;Andrew Vincent, ''Modern Political Ideologies'', 2nd Edition, &quot;Who to include under the rubric of the New Right remains puzzling.  It is usually seen as an amalgam of traditional liberal conservatism, Austrian liberal economic theory, ... extreme libertarianism (anarch-capitalism) and crude populism.&quot; p. 66, Wiley-Blackwell, 2008, ISBN 978-0-631-19507-8.&lt;/ref&gt;

Other authors make a distinction between the centre-right and the far right.&lt;ref&gt;Betz &amp; Immerfall 1998; Betz 1994; Durham 2000; Durham 2002; Hainsworth 2000; Mudde 2000; Berlet &amp; Lyons, 2000.&lt;/ref&gt;  Parties of the centre-right generally support liberal democracy, capitalism, the market economy (though they may accept government regulation to control monopolies), private property rights, and a limited welfare state (for example government provision of education and medical care).  They support conservatism and economic liberalism, oppose socialism and communism.  The phrase far right, by contrast, is used to describe those who favor an absolutist government, which uses the power of the state to support the dominant ethnic group or religion and often to criminalize other ethnic groups or religions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=YYdTvMmSYpEC&amp;dq=%22far+right%22&amp;printsec=frontcover |title=The Routledge companion to fascism ... - Google Books |publisher=Books.google.ca |date= |accessdate=2010-05-13|isbn=978-0-415-21495-7|year=2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=Ual1NR2WPasC&amp;dq=%22far+right%22&amp;printsec=frontcover#PPR7,M1 |title=The Christian right: the far right ... - Google Books |publisher=Books.google.ca |date= |accessdate=2010-05-13|isbn=978-0-7190-5486-0|year=2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=sVZ8EUvJjJ4C&amp;dq=%22far+right%22&amp;printsec=frontcover#PPR5,M1 |title=Right-wing extremism in the twenty ... - Google Books |publisher=Books.google.ca |date=2000-06-30 |accessdate=2010-05-13|isbn=978-0-7146-5182-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=JcJ5nr2MZfUC&amp;dq=%22far+right%22&amp;printsec=frontcover |title=Western democracies and the new ... - Google Books |publisher=Books.google.ca |date= |accessdate=2010-05-13|isbn=978-0-415-36971-8|year=2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/1857918.stm |title=Pim Fortuyn: The far-right Dutch maverick |publisher=BBC News |date=2002-03-07 |accessdate=2012-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Typical examples of leaders to whom the ''far right'' lable is often applied are [[Francisco Franco]] in [[Spain]] and [[Augusto Pinochet]] in [[Chile]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=6069233|title=A Dictator's Legacy of Economic Growth|date=2006-09-14|accessdate=2007-10-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Greenwald |first=Glenn |url=http://www.salon.com/opinion/greenwald/2007/05/04/politico_funding/ |title=Glenn Greenwald |publisher=Salon.com |date=31 May 2012  |accessdate=2012-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;canovan&quot;&gt;Canovan, Margaret. 1981. ''Populism.''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Betz |first=Hans-Georg |title=Radical Right-Wing Populism in Western Europe |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |year= 1994|isbn=978-0-312-08390-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Michael E. Brown, Owen R. Cote Jr., ''Nationalism and Ethnic Conflict'', &quot;Anti-immigrant and anti-refugee feeling is being exploited by extreme right-wing parties throughout Europe...&quot;, p. 442, MIT Press, 2001, ISBN 978-0-262-52315-8&lt;/ref&gt; The US [[Department of Homeland Security]] defines right-wing extremism as [[hate groups]] who target racial, ethnic or religious minorities and may be dedicated to a single issue.&lt;ref&gt;http://wnd.com/images/dhs-rightwing-extremism.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; The phrase is also used to describe support for [[ethnic nationalism]].

===Anti-communism===
{{Main|Anti-communism}}
The original use of &quot;right-wing&quot; in reference to communism had the conservatives on the Right, the liberals in the center, and the communists on the Left.  Both the conservatives and the liberals were strongly anti-communist.  As time went on, however, conservatives accused liberals of being &quot;soft on communism&quot;, and using freedom of speech and freedom of religion as a cover for their hidden communist sympathies.  The history of the use of the term &quot;right-wing&quot; to mean anti-communist is a complicated one.

Early Marxist movements were at odds with the traditional monarchies that ruled over much of the [[Europe]]an continent at the time. Many European monarchies outlawed the public expression of communist views, and the [[Communist Manifesto]], which began &quot;A spectre is haunting Europe,&quot; stated that monarchs feared for their thrones. Advocacy of communism was illegal in the [[Russian Empire]], the [[German Empire]] and [[Austria-Hungary]], the three most powerful monarchies in continental Europe prior to [[World War I]]. Many Monarchists (except [[Constitutional Monarchy|Constitutional Monarchists]]) viewed inequality in wealth and political power as resulting from a divine natural order.  The struggle between monarchists and communists was often described as a struggle between the Right and the Left.

By [[World War I]] however, in most European monarchies, the Divine Right of Kings had become discredited and replaced by [[liberalism|liberal]] and [[Nationalism|nationalist]] movements. Most European monarchs became figureheads; elected governments held the real power. The most conservative European monarchy, the Russian Empire, was replaced by the communist Soviet Union. The Russian Revolution inspired a series of other communist revolutions across Europe in the years 1917–1922. Many of these, such as the [[German Revolution]], were defeated by nationalist and monarchist military units.  In this period, nationalism began to be considered right-wing, especially when it opposed the internationalism of the communists.

The 1920s and 1930s saw the fading of traditional right-wing politics. The mantle of conservative anti-communism was taken up by the rising [[Fascism|fascist]] movements on the one hand, and by [[United States|American]]-inspired [[Liberal conservatism|liberal conservatives]] on the other. When communist groups and political parties began appearing around the world, as in the [[Republic of China]] in the 1920s, their opponents were usually [[colonialism|colonial authorities]], and the term right-wing came to be applied to [[colonialism]].

After [[World War II]], communism became a global phenomenon, and anti-communism became an integral part of the domestic and foreign policies of the [[United States]] and its [[NATO]] allies. Conservatism in the post-war era abandoned its monarchist and aristocratic roots, focusing instead on patriotism, religion, and nationalism.  Throughout the [[Cold War]], colonial governments in [[Asia]], [[Africa]], and [[Latin America]] turned to the United States for political and economic support.  Communists were also enemies of capitalism, portraying [[Wall Street]] as the oppressor of the masses. The United States made anti-communism the top priority of its foreign policy, and many American conservatives sought to combat what they saw as communist influence at home. This led to the adoption of a number of domestic policies that are collectively known under the term &quot;[[McCarthyism]]&quot;.  While both liberals and conservatives were anti-communist, the followers of Senator McCarthy were called right-wing, and those on the Right called liberals who favored free speech, even for communists, leftist.

===Economics===
In France after the French Revolution, the Right fought against the rising power of those who had grown rich through commerce, and sought to preserve the rights of the hereditary nobility.  They were uncomfortable with capitalism, with the Enlightenment, with individualism, and with industrialism and fought to retain traditional social hierarchies and institutions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Parliaments 1988 pp. 287–302&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Martin E. Marty, R. Scott Appleby, American Academy of Arts and Sciences. ''Fundamentalisms observed'', &quot;Reactionary right-wing themes emphasizing authority, social hierarchy, and obedience, as well as condemnations of liberalism, the democratic ethos, the &quot;rights of man&quot; associated with the legacy of the Enlightenment and the French Revolution, and the political and cultural ethos of modern liberal democracy are especially prominent in the writings and public statements of Archbishop Lefebere&quot;, p. 91, University of Chicago Press, 1994. P. 91. ISBN 0-226-50878-1, ISBN 978-0-226-50878-8.&lt;/ref&gt; 

By the 19th century, the Right had shifted to support the newly rich, and instead of favoring the nobility over industrialists, favored capitalists over the working class.  There are, however, still a few right-wing movements today, notably American [[paleoconservatives]], that are often in opposition to capitalist ethics and the effects they have on society as a whole, which they see as infringing upon or causing the decay of social traditions or hierarchies that they see as essential for social order.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fascism pg 19&quot;&gt;''Fascism, Comparison and Definition'', Stanley Payne, University of Wisconsin Press, ISBN 0-299-08064-1, ISBN 978-0-299-08064-8, pg 19: &quot;Right radicals and conservative authoritarians almost without exception became corporatists in formal doctrines of political economy, but the fascists were less explicit and in general less schematic.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

In modern times, &quot;right-wing&quot; is sometimes used to describe laissez-faire capitalism.  In Europe, capitalists formed alliances with the Right during their conflicts with workers after 1848. In France, the Right's support of capitalism can be traced to the late 19th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;Knapp&quot;/&gt; The so-called [[neoliberal]] Right, popularized by [[Ronald Reagan]] and [[Margaret Thatcher]], combines  support for [[free markets]], [[privatisation]], and [[deregulation]] with traditional right-wing support for social conformity.&lt;ref name=Lukes/&gt; [[Right-libertarianism|Right-wing libertarianism]] (sometimes known as [[libertarian conservatism]] or [[conservative libertarianism]]) supports a decentralized economy based on [[economic freedom]], and holds [[property rights]], [[free markets]] and [[free trade]] to be the most important kinds of freedom. Russell Kirk believed that freedom and property rights were interlinked.&lt;ref name=&quot;heritage.org&quot;/&gt; Anthony Gregory has written that right-wing libertarianism, &quot;can refer to any number of varying and at times mutually exclusive political orientations.&quot; He listed some as: being &quot;interested mainly in 'economic freedoms'&quot;; following the &quot;conservative lifestyle of right-libertarians&quot;; seeking &quot;others to embrace their own conservative lifestyle&quot;; considering big business &quot;as a great victim of the state&quot;; favoring a &quot;strong national defense&quot;; having &quot;an Old Right opposition to empire.&quot; He holds that the issue is not right or left but &quot;whether a person sees the state as a major hazard or just another institution to be reformed and directed toward a political goal.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Anthony Gregory, [http://www.lewrockwell.com/gregory/gregory127.html Left, Right, Moderate and Radical], [[LewRockwell.com]], December 21, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

Conservative authoritarians and those on the [[far right]] have supported [[fascism]] and [[corporatism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Fascism pg 19&quot;/&gt;

===Nationalism===
In France, [[nationalism]] was originally a left-wing and Republican ideology.&lt;ref&gt;William Doyle, ''The Oxford History of the French Revolution'', Oxford University Press, 2003, ISBN 978-0-19-925298-5, &quot;An exuberant, uncompromising nationalism lay behind France's revolutionary expansion in the 1790s...&quot;, &quot;The message of the French Revolution was that the people are sovereign; and in the two centuries since it was first proclaimed it has conquered the world.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; After [[Georges Ernest Boulanger|the period of ''boulangisme'']] and the [[Dreyfus Affair]] nationalism became a trait of the right-wing .&lt;ref&gt;[[Michel Winock|Winock, Michel]] (dir.), ''Histoire de l'extrême droite en France'' (1993)&lt;/ref&gt; Right-wing nationalists sought to define and defend a &quot;true&quot; national identity from elements deemed to be corrupting that identity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Knapp&quot;/&gt; Some were [[ethnic nationalists]] who, in accordance with [[Social Darwinism]], applied the concept of &quot;[[survival of the fittest]]&quot; to nations and races.&lt;ref&gt;Adams, Ian ''Political Ideology Today'' (2nd edition), Manchester University Press, 2002, pg. 68&lt;/ref&gt; Right-wing nationalism was influenced by [[romantic nationalism]], in which the state derives its political legitimacy from the organic unity of those it governs. This generally includes, the language, race, culture, religion and customs of the &quot;nation&quot;, all of which were &quot;born&quot; within its culture. Linked with right-wing nationalism is [[cultural conservatism]], which supports the preservation of the heritage of a nation or culture, and often sees deviations from cultural norms as an existential threat.&lt;ref&gt;Sabrina P. Ramet, ''The Radical Right in Central and Eastern Europe since 1989'', Pennsylvania State University Press, 1999, ISBN 978-0271018119&lt;/ref&gt;

===Natural law and traditionalism===
Right-wing politics typically justifies a hierarchical society on the basis of [[natural law]] or [[tradition]].&lt;ref name=&quot;T. Alexander Smith 2003. Pp 30&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Allan Cameron pg. 37&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fuchs, D. 1990. Pp.203&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lukes&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Clark, William 2003&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated68&quot;/&gt;

Traditionalism was advocated by a group of U.S. university professors (labeled the &quot;New Conservatives&quot; by the popular press) who rejected the notions of [[individualism]], [[liberalism]], [[modernity]], and [[social progress]], and sought instead to promote cultural and educational renewal,&lt;ref&gt;Frohnen, Bruce, Jeremy Beer, and Jeffrey O. Nelson, ed. (2006) ''American Conservatism: An Encyclopedia'' Wilmington, DE: ISI Books, p. 870.&lt;/ref&gt; and a revived interest in what [[T. S. Eliot]] referred to as &quot;the permanent things&quot; (those perennial truths which endure from age to age and those basic institutions that ground society such as the church, the family, the state, and community life.)

The term &quot;[[family values]]&quot; has been used as a buzzword by right-wing parties such as the [[Republican Party (U.S.)|Republican Party]] in the United States, the [[Family First Party]] in Australia, the [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative party]] in the United Kingdom and the [[Bharatiya Janata Party]] in India to describe support for traditional families, and opposition to the changes the modern world has made in how families live. Right-wing supporters of &quot;family values&quot; may oppose [[abortion]], [[euthanasia]], [[homosexuality]], and [[adultery]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=2004 Republican Party Platform: A Safer World and a More Hopeful America|url=http://msnbcmedia.msn.com/i/msnbc/Sections/News/Politics/Conventions/RNC-2004platform.pdf|publisher=MSNBC|accessdate=23 July 2012|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Populism===
{{Main|Right-wing populism}}
[[Right-wing populism]] is a combination of [[ethno-nationalism]] with [[anti-elitism]], using populist rhetoric to provide a radical critique of existing political institutions. According to Margaret Canovan, a right-wing populist is &quot;...a charismatic leader, using the tactics of politicians’ populism to go past the politicians and intellectual elite and appeal to the reactionary sentiments of the populace, often buttressing his claim to speak for the people by the use of referendums.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Margaret Canovan, ''Populism'', Houghton Mifflin Harcourt, 1981, ISBN 978-0151730780&lt;/ref&gt; 

In Europe, right-wing populism often takes the form of distrust of the European Union, and of politicians in general, combined with anti-immagrant rhetoric, and a call for a return to traditional, national values.&lt;ref&gt;Jack Hayward, editor, ''Elitism, Populism, and European Politics'', Oxford University Press, 1996, ISBN 978-0198280354&lt;/ref&gt;

===Religion===
Government support for an established religion was associated with the original French &quot;right wing.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Martin E. Marty 1994. P. 91&quot;&gt;Martin E. Marty, R. Scott Appleby, American Academy of Arts and Sciences. ''Fundamentalisms observed''. University of Chicago Press, 1994. P. 91. ISBNISBN 0-226-50878-1, ISBN 978-0-226-50878-8.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Joseph de Maistre]] argued for the indirect authority of the [[Pope]] over temporal matters. According to Maistre, only governments founded upon a Christian constitution, implicit in the customs and institutions of all European societies but especially in [[Roman Catholic Church|Catholic]] [[Europe]]an monarchies, could avoid the disorder and bloodshed that followed the implementation of [[Rationalism|rationalist]] political programs, as in the [[French Revolution]]. The [[Church of England]] was established by [[Henry VIII]]. Some churchmen are given seats in the [[House of Lords]] but are considered politically neutral, rather than right or left wing. 

The [[Christian right]] is a major force in the West. They generally support laws upholding religious values, and also laws limiting immigration.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.voanews.com/english/2009-06-08-voa4.cfm |title=Conservative Parties Cheer Victory in EU Parliamentary Elections |publisher=Voanews.com |date=2009-11-02 |accessdate=2012-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In India, [[Hindu nationalism]] is considered a part of the right-wing. The Hindu nationalist movement has attracted privileged groups fearing encroachment on their dominant positions, and also &quot;plebeian&quot; and impoverished groups seeking recognition around a majoritarian rhetoric of cultural pride, order, and national strength.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas Blom Hansen, ''The Saffron Wave: Democracy and Hindu Nationalism in Modern India'', Princeton University Press, 2001, ISBN 1-4008-0342-X, 9781400803422&lt;/ref&gt; Many [[Islamist]] groups have been called &quot;right wing&quot; including the [[Great Union Party]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.turkishweekly.net/news/68827/rescue-teams-could-not-reach-turkish-party-leader-muhsin-yazicioglu-after-helicopter-crash.html|author=Demirtas, Burcu|title=Rescue Teams Could Not Reach Turkish Party Leader, Muhsin Yazicioglu after Helicopter Crash|publisher=Turkishweekly.net |date=27 March 2009 |accessdate=2012-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Combatant Clergy Association]]/Association of Militant Clergy&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uvm.edu/~fgause/168read.htm |title=Readings |publisher=uvm.edu |date=Fall 2007 |accessdate=2012-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/623899.stm |title=Poll test for Iran reformists |publisher=BBC News |date=2000-02-10 |accessdate=2012-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Islamic Society of Engineers]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.merip.org/mero/mero020101.html |title=Middle East Report Online: Iran's Conservatives Face the Electorate, by Arang Keshavarzian |publisher=Merip.org |date=1997-05-23 |accessdate=2010-05-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Anoushiravan Ehteshami and Mahjoob Zweiri, ''Iran and the rise of its neoconservatives: the politics of Tehran's silent revolution'', I.B.Tauris, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; of Iran.

Religious fundamentalists frequently feel that governments should enact laws supporting their religious tenets.&lt;ref&gt;Martin E. Marty, R. Scott Appleby, American Academy of Arts and Sciences. Fundamentalisms observed. University of Chicago Press, 1994. P. 91. ISBN 0-226-50878-1, ISBN 978-0-226-50878-8.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kerry Noble, ''Tabernacle of Hate: Seduction Into Right-Wing Extremism'', Syracuse University Press, 2010, ISBN 978-0815632481&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;John R. Bradley, ''After the Arab Spring'', &quot;... the right-wing Arab-Iranian exile Amir Teheri ...&quot; p. 143, Palgrave Macmillan, 2012, ISBN 978-0230338197&lt;/ref&gt;  

The religious Right may be in conflict with scientific positions on [[evolution]] and other matters where science disagrees with dogma.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.irr.org.uk/cgi-bin/news/open.pl?id=4447, &quot;Christian school teaches right-wing creationist theories, by Liz Fekete, 1 August 2002, 'The government policy of funding for faith schools has been criticised after it was revealed that the Emmanuel City Technology College in Gateshead is teaching creationism - that human origins are (relatively) recent and divine - as opposed to scientific evolution, to explain our origins.'&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://nationalacademies.org/evolution/Intro.html, &quot;Biological evolution is one of the most important ideas of modern science. Evolution is supported by abundant evidence from many different fields of scientific investigation. It underlies the modern biological sciences, including the biomedical sciences, and has applications in many other scientific and engineering disciplines.&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/15857761/, ''Muslim creationism makes inroads in Turkey'', by Tom Heneghan, Reuters, Nov. 22, 2006, &quot;Creationism is so widely accepted here that Turkey placed last in a recent survey of public acceptance of evolution in 34 countries — just behind the United States.&quot; &quot;Darwinism did become an issue during the left-vs.-right political turmoil before a 1980 military coup because Communist bookshops touted Darwin’s works as a complement to Karl Marx. 'It looked like Marx and Darwin were together, two long-bearded guys spreading ideas that make people lose their faith,' said Istanbul journalist Mustafa Akyol.]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Diana DeGette, ''Sex, Science, and Stem Cells: Inside the Right Wing Assault on Reason'', The Lyons Press, 2008, ISBN 978-1-59921-431-3.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Chris Mooney, ''The Republican War on Science: Revised and Updated'', ASIN: B001OQOIPM&lt;/ref&gt;

===Social stratification===
Right-wing politics involves in varying degrees the rejection of [[Egalitarianism|egalitarian]] objectives of [[left-wing politics]], claiming either that inequality is natural and inevitable or that it is beneficial to society.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated68&quot;&gt;''Left and right: the significance of a political distinction'', Norberto Bobbio and Allan Cameron, pg. 68, [[University of Chicago Press]], 1997.&lt;/ref&gt;
Right-wing ideologies and movements support [[social order]]. The original French right-wing was called &quot;the party of order&quot; and held that France needed a strong political leader to keep order.&lt;ref name=&quot;Knapp&quot;/&gt;

British conservative scholar R. J. White, who rejects egalitarianism, wrote: &quot;Men are equal before God and the laws, but unequal in all else; hierarchy is the order of nature, and privilege is the reward of honourable service&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2003&quot;&gt;Moyra Grant. ''Key Ideas in Politics''. Cheltenham, England, UK: Nelson Thornes, Ltd., 2003. Pp. 52.&lt;/ref&gt; American conservative [[Russell Kirk]] also rejects egalitarianism as imposing sameness, stating: &quot;Men are created different; and a government that ignores this law becomes an unjust government for it sacrifices nobility to mediocrity&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2003&quot;/&gt;  He took as one of the &quot;canons&quot; of conservatism the principle that &quot;civilized society requires orders and classes&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;heritage.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=John |first=David C. |url=http://www.heritage.org/Research/PoliticalPhilosophy/HL811.cfm |title=The Origins of the Modern American Conservative Movement|publisher=heritage.org |date=21 November 2003  |accessdate=2010-05-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
Right libertarians reject collective or state-imposed equality as undermining reward for personal merit, initiative, and enterprise.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2003&quot;/&gt; In their view, it is unjust, limits personal freedom, and leads to social uniformity and mediocrity.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2003&quot;/&gt;

==See also==
* [[Ideology]]
* [[Status quo ante]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

== References ==
* Berlet, Chip. &quot;When Alienation turns Right&quot;. In Langman, Lauren and Kalekin-Fishman (Eds.) ''The Evolution of Alienation: Trauma, Promise, and the Millennium''.  Lanham, MD: Rowman &amp; Littlefield, 2006 ISBN 0-7425-1835-3, ISBN 978-0-7425-1835-3
* Davies, Peter. ''The Extreme Right in France, 1789 to the Present: From De Maistre to Le Pen''. New York, NY: Routledge, 2002 ISBN 0-415-23982-6, ISBN 978-0-415-23982-0
* Eatwell, Roger. &quot;Introduction: the new extreme right challenge&quot;. In Eatwell, Roger and Muddle, Cas (Eds.) ''Western Democracies and the new Extreme Right Challenge.'' London, UK: Routledge, 2004 ISBN 0-415-36971-1, ISBN 978-0-415-36971-8
* Eatwell, Roger.  &quot;Conclusion: The 'End of Ideology'&quot;. In Eatwell, Roger and Wright, Anthony (Eds.) ''Contemporary Political Ideologies''. Continuum International Publishing Group, 1999 ISBN 0-8264-5173-X, 9780826451736

{{Political spectrum}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Right-Wing Politics}}
[[Category:Right-wing politics| ]]
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Political terms]]

{{Link GA|zh}}
[[ar:يمينية]]
[[ast:Derecha política]]
[[zh-min-nan:Iū-phài]]
[[ca:Dreta (política)]]
[[cs:Pravice]]
[[da:Højreorienteret]]
[[de:Politische Rechte (Politik)]]
[[el:Δεξιά (πολιτική)]]
[[es:Derecha política]]
[[eo:Politika dekstro]]
[[fa:راست (گرایش سیاسی)]]
[[fr:Droite (politique)]]
[[gl:Dereita política]]
[[ko:우익]]
[[hi:दाएँ की राजनीति]]
[[hr:Politička desnica]]
[[id:Sayap kanan]]
[[is:Hægristefna]]
[[it:Destra (politica)]]
[[kn:ಬಲಪಂಥೀಯ ರಾಜಕೀಯ]]
[[ku:Milê rastê]]
[[lv:Labēja politika]]
[[lt:Dešinė (politikoje)]]
[[hu:Jobboldal]]
[[mk:Политичка десница]]
[[ms:Politik haluan kanan]]
[[mwl:Dreita política]]
[[nl:Rechts (politiek)]]
[[ja:右翼]]
[[no:Høyresiden]]
[[nn:Høgresida]]
[[pms:Drita (polìtica)]]
[[pl:Prawica]]
[[pt:Direita política]]
[[ru:Правые (политика)]]
[[scn:Dritta]]
[[simple:Right-wing]]
[[sl:Politična desnica]]
[[sr:Десница]]
[[fi:Oikeisto]]
[[sv:Politisk höger]]
[[ta:வலது சாரி அரசியல்]]
[[th:ฝ่ายขวา (การเมือง)]]
[[tr:Sağcılık]]
[[uk:Правиця]]
[[ug:ئوڭچى]]
[[vi:Cánh hữu]]
[[zh:右派]]</text>
      <sha1>qvhtz0sf7cl16mcsm2ch1hklvk0tkd8</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
