<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Robert Filmer</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>706877</id>
    <revision>
      <id>515742213</id>
      <parentid>510942085</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-03T04:47:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Crusoe8181</username>
        <id>10172481</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>wlink after page move</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9629">{{other persons}}
{{Citations missing|date=December 2007}}
[[image:Robert Filmer.jpg|thumbnail|150px|right|Robert Filmer (1588-1653)]]

'''Sir Robert Filmer''' (1588 – 26 May 1653) was an [[England|English]] [[political theorist]] who defended the [[divine right of kings]]. His best known work, ''[[Patriarcha]]'', published posthumously in 1680, was the target of numerous [[Whig (British political party)|Whig]] rebuttals, including [[Algernon Sidney]]'s ''Discourses Concerning Government'', [[James Tyrrell (writer)|James Tyrrell]]'s ''Patriarcha Non Monarcha'', and [[John Locke]]'s ''[[Two Treatises of Government]]''. Filmer also wrote critiques of [[Thomas Hobbes]], [[John Milton]], [[Hugo Grotius]], and [[Aristotle]].

==Life==
The son of Sir [[Edward Filmer]] of [[East Sutton]] in [[Kent]], he studied at [[Trinity College, Cambridge]], where he matriculated in 1604.&lt;ref&gt;{{Venn|FLMR604R}}&lt;/ref&gt; Knighted by [[Charles I of England|Charles I]] at the beginning of his reign, he was an ardent supporter of the king's cause, and his house is said to have been plundered by the [[Parliament of England|parliamentarians]] ten times. He was imprisoned in [[Leeds Castle]] in 1643.

He and his father died in the same city, and he is buried in the church there, surrounded by his descendants to the tenth generation. His son, also Robert, was created the first of the [[Filmer baronets]] in 1674.

==''Patriarcha'' and other works==
[[Image:Patriarcha-Book of-Robert Filmer Originally from 1680.png|thumbnail|200px|right|''Patriarcha'', London, 1680]]

Filmer was already a middle-aged man when the controversy between the king and the [[House of Commons of England|House of Commons]] roused him into literary activity. His writings afford examples of the doctrines held by the extreme section of the [[Divine Right of Kings|Divine Right]] party. 

The most complete expression of Filmer's thought is given in ''Patriarcha, or the Natural Power of Kings'', which was published posthumously in 1680, but was probably begun in the 1620s, and almost certainly was completed before the Civil War began in 1642.&lt;ref&gt;''Patriarcha and Other Writings'', ed. by Johann P. Sommerville (1991), viii, xiii, xxxii-xxxiv (&quot;The Date of Filmer's ''Patriarcha''&quot;); John M. Wallace, ''The Date of Sir Robert Filmer's Patriarcha'', The Historical Journal, Vol. 23, No. 1 (Mar., 1980), pp. 155-165.&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Christopher Hill (historian)|Christopher Hill]], &quot;The whole argument of ... ''Patriarcha'', and of his works published earlier in the 1640s and 1650s, is based on Old Testament history from ''Genesis'' onwards&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[Christopher Hill (historian)|Christopher Hill]], ''The English Bible and the Seventeenth-Century Revolution'' (1993), p. 20.&lt;/ref&gt; 

His position was enunciated by the works which he published during his lifetime. ''Of the Blasphemie against the Holy Ghost'' from 1646 or 1647 was against [[Calvinists]], starting from [[John Calvin]]'s doctrine on [[blasphemy]].&lt;ref&gt;Ian Bostridge, ''Witchcraft and Its Transformations, C.1650-c.1750'' (1997), p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt; ''The Freeholders Grand Inquest'' (1648) concerned English constitutional history; Filmer's early published works did not receive much attention, while ''[[Patriarcha]]'' circulated only in manuscript.&lt;ref&gt;Kim Ian Parker, ''The Biblical Politics of John Locke'' (2004), pp. 80-1.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Anarchy of a Limited and Mixed Monarchy'' (1648) was an attack on a treatise about [[monarchy]] by [[Philip Hunton]]. Hunton had maintained that the king's prerogative is not superior to the authority of the Houses of Parliament. 

His ''Observations concerning the Original of Government upon Mr Hobbes's Leviathan, Mr Milton against Salmasius, and H. Grotius' De jure belli ac pacis'' appeared in 1652. As its title suggests, it attacks several political classics, the ''[[De jure belli ac pacis]]'' of [[Grotius]], the ''[[Leviathan (book)|Leviathan]]'' of [[Thomas Hobbes]], and the ''[[Defensio pro Populo Anglicano]]'' of [[John Milton]]. The pamphlet entitled ''The Power of Kings, and in particular, of the King of England'' (written 1648) was first published in 1680.

==Views==

Filmer's theory is founded upon the statement that the [[Family as a model for the state|government of a family by the father]] is the true origin and model of all government. In the beginning God gave authority to [[Adam]], who had complete control over his descendants, even over life and death itself. From Adam this authority was inherited by [[Noah]]; here, Filmer most likely quotes the legend of Noah, who sailed up the [[Mediterranean]] and allocated the three continents of the [[Old World]] to the rule of his three sons. From [[Shem]], [[Ham, son of Noah|Ham]] and [[Japheth]] the patriarchs inherited the absolute power which they exercised over their families and servants; and it is from these patriarchs that all kings and governors (whether a single monarch or a governing assembly) derive their authority, which is therefore absolute, and founded upon divine right. 

The difficulty inherent in judging the validity of claims to power by men who claim to be acting upon the 'secret' will of God was disregarded by Filmer, who held it in no way altered the nature of such power, based on the [[natural rights|natural right]] of a supreme father to hold sway. The king is perfectly free from all human control. He cannot be bound by the acts of his predecessors, for which he is not responsible; nor by his own, for it is impossible that a man should give a law to himself -  a law must be imposed by another upon the person bound by it. 

With regard to the [[Constitution of the United Kingdom|English constitution]], he asserted, in his ''Freeholders Grand Inquest touching our Sovereign Lord the King and his Parliament'' (1648), that the Lords give counsel only to the king, that the Commons are to perform and consent only to the ordinances of parliament, and that the king alone is the maker of laws which derive their power purely from his will. Filmer considered it monstrous that the people should judge or depose their king, for they would then become judges in their own cause.

Filmer was a severe critic of democracy. In his opinion, democracy of ancient Athens was in fact a &quot;justice-trading system&quot;. Athenians never knew real justice, only the will of the mob. Ancient Rome was, according to Filmer, ruled fairly only after the Empire was established.

==Reception==
Filmer's theory, owing to a timely posthumous publication, obtained a wide recognition. Nine years after the publication of ''[[Patriarcha]]'', at the time of the [[Glorious Revolution|Revolution]] which banished the [[House of Stuart|Stuarts]] from the throne, [[John Locke]] singled out Filmer among the advocates of Divine Right and attacked him expressly in the first part of the ''[[Two Treatises of Government]]''. The first ''Treatise'' goes into all his arguments [[seriatim]], and especially pointing out that even if the first principles of his argument are to be taken for granted, the rights of the eldest born have been so often cast aside that modern kings can claim no such inheritance of authority, as Filmer asserts.

Filmer's patriarchal monarchism was also the target of [[Algernon Sydney]] in his ''Discourses Concerning Government'' and of [[James Tyrrell (writer)|James Tyrrell]] in his ''Patriarcha non monarcha''.

==Family==
His first son Sir Edward Filmer was [[Gentleman of the Privy Chamber]]. He died in 1668 and the East Sutton estate passed to his brother Robert who was created a baronet in 1674 in honour of their father's loyalty to the Crown. See [[Filmer baronets]].

==List of works==
* ''Of the Blasphemie against the Holy Ghost'' (1647)
* ''The Free-holders Grand Inquest'' (1648)
* ''The Anarchy of a Limited or Mixed Monarchy'' (1648)
* ''The Necessity of the Absolute Power of All Kings'' (1648)
* ''Observations Concerning the Originall of Government, upon Mr Hobs Leviathan, Mr Milton against Salmasius, H. Grotius De Jure Belli'' (1652)
* ''Observations Upon Aristotles Politiques concerning Forms of Government, Together with Directions for Obedience to Gouvernors in dangerous and doubtfull times'' (1652)
* ''[[Patriarcha]]'' (1680)

There are two modern editions of the complete works of Filmer:
* ''Filmer: Patriarcha and Other Writing'', edited by Johann P. Sommerville (Cambridge University Press, 1991).
* ''Patriarcha and other political works of Sir Robert Filmer'', edited by Peter Laslett (B. Blackwell, 1949).

==References==
*{{1911|article=Sir Robert Filmer|url=http://www.1911encyclopedia.org/Sir_Robert_Filmer}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.constitution.org/eng/patriarcha.htm R. Filmer ''Patriarcha'']

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Filmer, Robert
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1588
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     = 26 May 1653
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Filmer, Robert}}
[[Category:1588 births]]
[[Category:1653 deaths]]
[[Category:English non-fiction writers]]
[[Category:Political theorists]]
[[Category:English knights]]
[[Category:Alumni of Trinity College, Cambridge]]
[[Category:People of the Tudor period]]
[[Category:16th-century writers]]
[[Category:16th-century English people]]
[[Category:People from Kent]]

[[bg:Робърт Филмър]]
[[ca:Robert Filmer]]
[[de:Robert Filmer]]
[[et:Robert Filmer]]
[[es:Robert Filmer]]
[[fr:Robert Filmer]]
[[ko:로버트 필머]]
[[id:Robert Filmer]]
[[it:Robert Filmer]]
[[pl:Robert Filmer]]
[[sv:Robert Filmer]]</text>
      <sha1>kjaiingipzrzn8bjs9zkv400583maye</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
