<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Sabotage</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>29462</id>
    <revision>
      <id>513884672</id>
      <parentid>508105211</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-21T15:27:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>78.149.38.32</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Value of Simple Sabotage in Wartime */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26844">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
{{about}}
{{redirect|Saboteur}}
{{distinguish2|[[cabotage]], the transport of goods or passengers between two points in the same country}}

'''Sabotage''' is a deliberate action aimed at weakening another entity through subversion, obstruction, disruption, or destruction. In a workplace setting, sabotage is the conscious withdrawal of efficiency generally directed at causing some change in workplace conditions. One who engages in sabotage is a saboteur. As a rule, saboteurs try to conceal their identities because of the consequences of their actions. For example, whereas an environmental pressure group might be happy to be identified with an act of sabotage, it would not want the individual identities of the perpetrators known.

==Etymology==
Claimed explanations include:
*That it derives from the [[Netherlands]] in the 15th century when workers would throw their sabots (wooden shoes) into the wooden gears of the textile looms to break the cogs, fearing the automated machines would render the human workers obsolete.&lt;ref&gt;Hodson, Randy and Teresa A. Sullivan, The Social Organization of Work, Chap. 3 pg. 69&lt;/ref&gt;
* That it derives from the French ''[[Clog (shoe)|sabot]]'' (a wooden shoe or clog) via its derivative ''saboter'' (to knock with the foot, or work carelessly).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Partridge | first = Eric | authorlink = | coauthors = | title = Origins: A Short Etymological Dictionary of Modern English | publisher = Routledge | year = 1977 | location = | page = 2843 | url = | doi =  | isbn = 0-203-42114-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* That it derives from the late 19th-century French slang use of the word ''sabot'' to describe an unskilled worker, so called due to their wooden clogs or sabots; ''sabotage'' was used to describe the poor quality work which such workers turned out.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Donald | first = Graeme | authorlink = | coauthors = | title = Sticklers, Sideburns &amp; Bikinis: The Military Origins of Everyday Words and Phrases | publisher = Osprey Publishing | year = 2008 | location = | page = 230 | url = | doi =  | isbn = 1-84603-300-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Luddite]]s and radical [[trade unions|labor unions]] such as the [[Industrial Workers of the World]] (IWW) have [[Industrial Workers of the World philosophy and tactics#Sabotage|advocated sabotage]] as a means of self-defense and [[direct action]] against unfair working conditions. 

The IWW was shaped in part by the [[industrial unionism]] philosophy of [[Bill Haywood|Big Bill Haywood]], and in 1910 Haywood was exposed to sabotage while touring [[Europe]]:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The experience that had the most lasting impact on Haywood was witnessing a general strike on the French railroads. Tired of waiting for parliament to act on their demands, railroad workers walked off their jobs all across the country. The French government responded by drafting the strikers into the army and then ordering them back to work. Undaunted, the workers carried their strike to the job. Suddenly, they could not seem to do anything right. Perishables sat for weeks, sidetracked and forgotten. Freight bound for [[Paris]] was misdirected to [[Lyon]] or Marseille instead. This tactic &amp;mdash; the French called it &quot;sabotage&quot; &amp;mdash; won the strikers their demands and impressed Bill Haywood.&lt;ref&gt;Roughneck, The Life and Times of Big Bill Haywood, Peter Carlson, 1983, page 152.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jimthor, Stablewars, May 2008&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
For the IWW, sabotage came to mean [[Industrial Workers of the World philosophy and tactics#Sabotage|any withdrawal of efficiency]] &amp;mdash; including the [[slowdown]], the [[strike action|strike]], [[working to rule]] or creative bungling of job assignments.&lt;ref&gt;Roughneck, The Life and Times of Big Bill Haywood, Peter Carlson, 1983, pages 196-197.&lt;/ref&gt;

One of the most severe examples was at the construction site of the [[Robert-Bourassa generating station|Robert-Bourassa Generating Station]] in 1974, when workers used bulldozers to topple electric generators, damaged fuel tanks, and set buildings on fire.  The project was delayed a year, and the direct cost of the damage estimated at $2 million CAD. The causes were not clear, however three factors have been cited: inter-union rivalry, poor working conditions, and the perceived arrogance of American executives of the contractor, [[Bechtel|Bechtel Corporation]].&lt;ref&gt;Rinehart, J.W. ''The Tyranny of Work'', Canadian Social Problems Series. Academic Press Canada (1975), pp. 78-79. ISBN 0-7747-3029-3.&lt;/ref&gt;

== As environmental action ==
{{Main|Ecotage}}
Certain groups turn to destruction of property in order to immediately stop environmental destruction or to make visible arguments against forms of modern technology they consider detrimental to the earth and its inhabitants. The [[FBI]] and other law enforcement agencies use the term [[eco-terrorist]] when applied to damage of property. Proponents argue that since property can not feel terror, damage to property is more accurately described as sabotage. Opponents, by contrast, point out that property owners and operators can indeed feel terror. The image of the [[monkey wrench]] thrown into the moving parts of a machine to stop it from working was popularized by [[Edward Abbey]] in the novel [[The Monkeywrench Gang]] and has been adopted by eco-activists to describe destruction of earth damaging machinery.

== As war tactic ==
In war, the word is used to describe the activity of an individual or group not associated with the [[military]] of the parties at war (such as a foreign [[Espionage|agent]] or an indigenous supporter), in particular when actions result in the destruction or damaging of a productive or vital facility, such as equipment, [[factory|factories]], [[dam]]s, [[public services]], storage plants or [[logistics|logistic]] routes. Prime examples of such sabotage are the events of [[Black Tom explosion|Black Tom]] and the [[Kingsland Explosion]].  Unlike acts of [[terrorism]], acts of sabotage do not always have a primary objective of inflicting casualties. Saboteurs are usually classified as enemies, and like [[spy|spies]] may be liable to [[prosecution]] and criminal penalties instead of [[Detention (Imprisonment)|detention]] as a [[prisoner of war]].
It is common for a government in power during war or supporters of the war policy to use the term loosely against opponents of the war. Similarly, German [[nationalist]]s spoke of a [[stab in the back legend|stab in the back]] having cost them the loss of World War I.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dokumentarfilm.com/en/030303.htm Dokumentarfilm.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

A modern form of sabotage is the distribution of software intended to damage specific industrial systems. For example, the CIA is alleged to have [[Siberian pipeline sabotage|sabotaged a Siberian pipeline]] during the Cold War, using information from the [[Farewell Dossier]]. A more recent case may be the [[Stuxnet]] [[computer worm]], which was designed to subtly infect and damage specific types of industrial equipment. Based on the equipment targeted and the location of infected machines, security experts believe it to be an attack on the [[Iran]]ian [[Nuclear program of Iran|nuclear program]] by the [[United States]], [[Israel]] or, according to the latest news, even [[Russia]].&lt;ref&gt;Markoff, John, &quot;[http://www.nytimes.com/2011/02/13/science/13stuxnet.html?scp=1&amp;sq=Malware%20Aimed%20At%20Iran%20Hit%20Five%20Sites,%20Report%20Says&amp;st=cse Malware Aimed at Iran Hit Five Sites, Report Says]&quot;, ''[[New York Times]]'', 13 February 2011, p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt;

Sabotage, done well, is inherently difficult to detect and difficult to trace to its origin.  During WWII, the [[FBI]] investigated 19,649 cases of sabotage and concluded the enemy had not caused any of them. &lt;ref name=SA&gt;{{cite book|last=Marrin|first=Albert|title=The Secret Armies : Spies, Counterspies, and Saboteurs in World War II|year=1985|publisher=Atheneum|location=New York|isbn=0-689-31165-6|page=37}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Sabotage in warfare, according to the OSS manual, varies from highly technical ''coup de main'' acts that require detailed planning and the use of specially trained operatives, to innumerable simple acts which the ordinary individual citizen-saboteur can perform.  Simple sabotage is carried out in such a way as to involve a minimum danger of injury, detection, and reprisal. There are two main methods of sabotage; physical destruction and the &quot;human element.&quot;  While physical destruction as a method is self-explanatory, its targets are nuanced, reflecting objects to which the saboteur has normal and inconspicuous access in everyday life.  The &quot;human element&quot; is based on universal opportunities to make faulty decisions, to adopt a non-cooperative attitude, and to induce others to follow suit. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Office of Strategic Services Simple Sabotage Manuel|url=http://www.gutenberg.org/files/26184/page-images/26184-images.pdf|accessdate=24 March 2012|page=1–2|date=17 January 1944}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are many examples of physical sabotage in wartime.  However, one of the most effective uses of sabotage is against organizations.  The OSS manual provides  numerous techniques under the title “General Interference with Organizations and Production”:

* When possible, refer all matters to committees for “further study and consideration.”  Attempt to make the committees as large as possible- never less than five
* Bring up irrelevant issues as frequently as possible
* Haggle over precise wordings of communications, minutes, resolutions
* In making work assignments, always sign out the unimportant jobs first.  See that the important jobs are assigned to inefficient workers of poor machines
* Insist on perfect work in relatively unimportant products; send back for refinishing those which have the least flaw.  Approve other defective parts whose flaws are not visible to the naked eye
* To lower morale and with it, production, be pleasant to inefficient workers; give them undeserved promotions.  Discriminate against efficient workers; complain unjustly about their work
* Hold conferences when there is more critical work to be done
* Multiply the procedures and clearances involved in issuing instructions, pay checks, and so on.  See that three people have to approve everything where one would do.
* Spread disturbing rumors that sound like inside dope.

From the section entitled, “General Devices for Lowering Morale and Creating Confusion” comes the following quintessential simple sabotage advice: Act stupid. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Office of Strategic Services Simple Sabotage Manuel|url=http://www.gutenberg.org/files/26184/page-images/26184-images.pdf|accessdate=24 March 2012|page=28-31|date=17 January 1944}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Value of Simple Sabotage in Wartime===
The United States [[Office of Strategic Services]], later renamed the [[CIA]], noted specific value in committing simple sabotage against the enemy during wartime: &quot;slashing tires, draining fuel tanks, starting fires, starting arguments, acting stupidly, short-circuiting electric systems, abrading machine parts will waste materials, manpower, and time.&quot;  To underline the importance of simple sabotage on a widespread scale, they wrote, &quot;widespread practice of simple sabotage will harass and demoralize enemy administrators and police.&quot;  The OSS was also focused on the battle for hearts and minds during wartime;  &quot;the very practice of simple sabotage by natives in enemy or occupied territory may make these individuals identify themselves actively with the [[United Nations]] War effort, and encourage them to assist openly in periods of Allied invasion and occupation.&quot;  &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Office of Strategic Services|url=http://www.gutenberg.org/files/26184/page-images/26184-images.pdf|accessdate=24 March 2012|page=2|date=17 January 1944}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Sabotage in World War I ===
On 11 January 1917, Fiodore Wozniak, using a rag saturated with phosphorus or an incendiary pencil supplied by German sabotage agents, set fire to his workbench at an ammunition assembly plant near Kingsland, NY, causing a four-hour fire that destroyed half a million 3-inch explosive shells and destroyed the plant for an estimated at 17 million in damages.  Wozniak's involvement was not discovered until 1927.&lt;ref name=GF&gt;{{cite journal|last=McGeorge II|first=Harvey J.|coauthors=Christine C. Ketchem|title=Sabotage: A Strategic Tool for Guerilla Forces|journal=World Affairs|volume=146|issue=3|pages=249–256|year=1983–1984|page=250|publisher=World Affairs Institute|jstor=20671989}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
&lt;br /&gt;

12 February 1917, Beduins loyal to the British destroyed a Turkish railroad near the port of [[Wajh]], derailing a Turkish locomotive.  The Beduins traveled by camel and used explosives which demolished a portion of the track.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Conduit, D.M., et al.|title=Challenge and Response in Internal Conflict, Volume II: The Experience in Europe and the Middle East|year=1968|publisher=The American University|location=Washington}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

30 July 1916 [[Black Tom explosion]]

=== Post World War I ===
In Ireland, The [[Irish Republican Army]] used sabotage against the British following the Easter 1916 uprising.  The IRA compromised communication lines and lines of transportation and fuel supplies.  The IRA also employed passive sabotage, refusing dock and train workers to work on ships and rail cars used by the government.  In 1920, agents of the IRA committed arson against at least fifteen British warehouses in Liverpool.  The following year, the IRA set fire to numerous British targets again, including the Dublin Customs House, this time sabotaging most of Liverpool's firetrucks in the firehouses before lighting the matches.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Howard L. Douthit III, Captain, USAF|title=The Use and Effectiveness of Sabotage as a Means of Unconventional Warfare- An Historical Perspective from World War I Through Vietnam|year=1988|publisher=Air Force Institute of Technology|location=Wright-Patterson Air Force Base, Ohio}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Sabotage in World War II ===
Sabotage training for the [[Allies of World War II]] consisted of teaching would-be saboteurs the key components to working machinery on which to focus their destruction.
&quot;Saboteurs learned hundreds of small tricks to cause the Germans big trouble.  The cables in a telephone junction box... could be jumbled to make the wrong connections when numbers were dialed.  A few ounces of plastique, properly placed, could bring down a bridge, cave in a mine shaft, or collapse the roof of a railroad tunnel.&quot; &lt;ref name=SA&gt;{{cite book|last=Marrin|first=Albert|title=The Secret Armies : Spies, Counterspies, and Saboteurs in World War II|year=1985|publisher=Atheneum|location=New York|isbn=0-689-31165-6|page=77}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The [[French Resistance]] ran an extremely effective sabotage campaign against the Germans during WWII.  Receiving their sabotage orders through messages over the [[BBC radio]] or by aircraft, the French used both passive and active forms of sabotage.  Passive forms included losing German shipments and allowing poor quality material to pass factory inspections.  Many active sabotage attempts were against critical rail lines of transportation.  German records count 1,429 instances of sabotage from French Resistance forces between January 1942 and February 1943.  From January through March 1944, sabotage accounted for three times the number of locomotives damaged by Allied airpower.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Howard L. Douthit III, Captain, USAF|title=The Use and Effectiveness of Sabotage as a Means of Unconventional Warfare- An Historical Perspective from World War I Through Vietnam|year=1988|publisher=Air Force Institute of Technology|location=Wright-Patterson Air Force Base, Ohio}}&lt;/ref&gt; See also [[Normandy Landings]] for more information about sabotage on [[D-Day]].
&lt;br /&gt;

During [[WWII]], the Allies committed sabotage against the Peugeot truck factory.  After repeated failures in Allied bombing attempts to hit the factory, a team of French Resistance fighters and SOE agents distracted the German guards with a game of soccer while part of their team entered the plant and destroyed machinery.&lt;ref name=SA&gt;{{cite book|last=Marrin|first=Albert|title=The Secret Armies : Spies, Counterspies, and Saboteurs in World War II|year=1985|publisher=Atheneum|location=New York|isbn=0-689-31165-6|page=83}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

In 1944 the Germans ran a false flag sabotage infiltration, [[Operation Grief]].

=== Sabotage Post WWII ===
From 1948-1960 the Malayan Communists committed numerous effective acts of sabotage against the [[Malaysian Government]], first targeting railway bridges, then hitting larger targets such as military camps.  Most of their efforts were centered around crippling [[Malaysia]]'s economy and involved sabotage against trains, rubber trees, water pipes, and electric lines.  The Communist's sabotage efforts were so successful that they caused backlash amongst the Malaysian population, who gradually withdrew support for the Communist movement as their livelihoods became threatened.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Report prepared by the Historical Evaluation and Research Organization under contract for the Army Research Office|title=Isolating the Guerrilla: Classic and Basic Case Studies (Volume II)|year=1966|publisher=Historical Evaluation and Research Organization|location=Washington}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In newly formed [[Israel]] from 1945-1948, Jewish groups opposed British control over Israel.  Though that control was to end according to the [[Balfour Declaration]] in 1948, the groups used sabotage as an opposition tactic.  The [[Haganah]] focused their efforts on camps used by the British to hold refugees and radar installations that could be used to detect illegal immigrant ships.  The [[Stern Gang]] and the [[Irgun]] used terrorism and sabotage against the British government and against lines of communications.  In November 1946, the Irgun and Stern Gang attacked a railroad twenty-one times in a three week period, eventually causing shell-shocked Arab railway workers to strike.  The [[6th Airborne Division]] was called in to provide security as a means of ending the strike.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Conduit, D.M., et al|title=Challenge and Response In Internal Conflict, Volume II: The Experience in Europe and the Middle East.|year=1967|publisher=The American University|location=Washington}}&lt;/ref&gt;
=== Sabotage in Vietnam ===
The [[Viet Cong]] used swimmer saboteurs often and effectively during the [[Vietnam War]].  Between 1969 and 1970, swimmers saboteurs sunk, destroyed, or damaged 77 friendly assets.  Viet Cong swimmers were poorly equipped but well trained and resourceful.  The swimmers provided a low cost/ low risk option with high payoff; possible loss to the country for failure compared to the possible gains from a successful mission led to the obvious conclusion the swimmer saboteurs were a good idea.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Babyak, E.E., Jr., LtJG, USN|title=Swimmer Sabotage or The Most Dangerous Mine|year=1971|publisher=Naval Mine Warfare School|location=Charleston}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sabotage during the [[Cold War]]===
On 1 January 1984, the Cuscatlan bridge over Lempa river in [[El Salvador]], critical to flow of commercial and military traffic, was destroyed by guerilla forces using explosives after using mortar fire to &quot;scatter&quot; the bridge's guards, causing an estimated 3.7 million dollars in required repairs, and considerably impacted El Salvadoran business and security.&lt;ref name=GF&gt;{{cite journal|last=McGeorge II|first=Harvey J.|coauthors=Christine C. Ketchem|title=Sabotage: A Strategic Tool for Guerilla Forces|journal=World Affairs|volume=146|issue=3|pages=249–256|year=1983–1984|page=249|publisher=World Affairs Institute|jstor=20671989}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
&lt;br /&gt;

In 1982 in [[Honduras]], a group of nine Salvadorans and Nicaraguans destroyed a main electrical power station, leaving [[Tegucigalpa]], the capital city, for three days without power. &lt;ref name=GF&gt;{{cite journal|last=McGeorge II|first=Harvey J.|coauthors=Christine C. Ketchem|title=Sabotage: A Strategic Tool for Guerilla Forces|journal=World Affairs|volume=146|issue=3|pages=249–256|year=1983–1984|page=253|publisher=World Affairs Institute|jstor=20671989}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== As crime ==
Some criminals have engaged in acts of sabotage for reasons of [[extortion]]. For example, [[Klaus-Peter Sabotta]] sabotaged German railway lines in the late 1990s in an attempt to extort [[Deutsche Mark|DM]]10 million from the German railway operator [[Deutsche Bahn]]. He is now serving a sentence of [[life imprisonment]].

== As political action ==

The term [[political]] sabotage is sometimes used to define the acts of one political camp to disrupt, harass or damage the reputation of a political opponent, usually during an electoral campaign. See [[Watergate]].

=== Sabotage in a Coup d'Etat ===
Sabotage is a crucial tool of the successful [[coup d’etat]], which requires control of [[communications]] before, during, and after the coup is staged.  Simple sabotage against physical communications platforms using semi-skilled technicians, or even those trained only for this task, could effectively silence the target government of the coup, leaving the [[War of ideas|information battle space]] open to the dominance of the coup’s leaders.  To underscore the effectiveness of sabotage, “a single cooperative technician will be able temporarily to put out of action a [[radio station]] which would otherwise require a full-scale [[assault]].” &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Luttwak|first=Edward|title=Coup d'Etat, a Practical Handbook|year=1968|publisher=The Penguin Press|location=London|isbn=0-674-17547-6|page=119}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Railroads]], where strategically important to the regime the coup is against, are prime targets for sabotage- if a section of the track is damaged entire portions of the transportation network can be stopped until it is fixed. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Luttwak|first=Edward|title=Coup d'Etat, a Practical Handbook|year=1968|publisher=The Penguin Press|location=London|isbn=0-674-17547-6|page=128}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Derivative usages ==
=== Sabotage Radio ===
A '''sabotage radio''' was a small [[two-way radio]] designed for use by [[resistance movement]]s in World War II, and after the war often used by [[exploration|expedition]]s and similar parties.
=== Cybotage ===
Arquilla and Rondfeldt, in their work entitled ''Networks and Netwars'', differentiate their definition of “[[netwar]]” from a list of “trendy synonyms,” including “cybotage,” an agglutination of the words “sabotage” and “[[cyber]].”  They dub the practitioners of cybotage “cyboteurs” and note while all cybotage is not netwar, some netwar is cybotage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Networks and Netwars|year=2001|publisher=RAND|isbn=0-8330-3030-2|editor=John Arquilla and David Ronfeldt|page=5-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
=== Counter-sabotage ===
Counter-sabotage, defined by [[Webster's dictionary]], is &quot;counterintelligence designed to detect and counteract sabotage.&quot;  The United States [[United States Department of Defense|Department of Defense]] definition, found in the Dictionary of Military and Associated Terms, is &quot;Action designed to detect and counteract sabotage. See also [[counterintelligence]]&quot;
==== Counter Sabotage in WWII ====
During WWII, British subject Eddie Chapman, trained by the Germans in sabotage, became a double agent for the British.  The German [[Abwehr]] entrusted Chapman to destroy the British de Haviland Company's main plant for the manufacture of heavy bombers, but required photographic proof from their agent to verify the mission’s completion.  A special unit of the Royal Engineers known as the Magic Gang covered the de Haviland plant with canvas panels and scattered paper mache furniture and chunks of masonry around three broken and burnt giant generators.  Photos of the plant taken from the air reflected devastation for the factory and a successful sabotage mission, and Chapman, as a British sabotage double-agent, fooled the Germans for the duration of the war.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Marrin|first=Albert|title=The Secret Armies|year=1985|publisher=Atheneum|location=New York|isbn=0-689-31165-6|page=24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{columns-list|2|
* [[Birth control sabotage]]
* [[Edmund Charaszkiewicz]]
* [[CIA]]
* [[Cichociemni]]
* [[Colin Gubbins]]
* [[Direct action]]
* [[Espionage]]
* [[Fifth column]]
* [[Guerrilla warfare]]
* [[Industrial espionage]]
* [[Kedyw]]
* [[The Mole (TV series)]]
* [[Norwegian heavy water sabotage]]
* [[Partisan (military)|Partisan]]
* [[Political Warfare]]
* [[Setting up to fail]]
* [[Social undermining]]
* [[Special Activities Division]]
* [[Special Operations Executive]]
* [[Tampering (crime)|Tampering]]
* [[Terrorism]]
}}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}
* [[Émile Pouget]], ''Le sabotage; notes et postface de Grégoire Chamayou et Mathieu Triclot'', 1913; Mille et une nuit, 2004; English translation, ''Sabotage'', paperback, 112 pp., University Press of the Pacific, 2001, ISBN 0-89875-459-3.
* Pasquinelli, Matteo. [http://matteopasquinelli.com/docs/ideology-of-free-culture.pdf &quot;The Ideology of Free Culture and the Grammar of Sabotage&quot;]; now in ''Animal Spirits: A Bestiary of the Commons'', Rotterdam: NAi Publishers, 2008.

== External links ==
* [http://www.gutenberg.org/files/26184/page-images/26184-images.pdf Office of Strategic Services Simple Sabotage Manual]
* [http://libcom.org/tags/sabotage News, accounts and articles on workplace sabotage and organising] - Sabotage, employee theft, strikes, etc.
* [http://www.reachoutpub.com/osh/ Ozymandias Sabotage Handbook]
*[http://theanarchistlibrary.org/HTML/Various_Authors__Ecodefense__A_Field_Guide_to_Monkeywrenching.html Ecodefense: A Field Guide to Monkeywrenching]
* [http://www.du.edu/~jcalvert/railway/malice.htm Article on malicious railroad sabotage]
* [[Elizabeth Gurley Flinn]], [http://www.iww.org/culture/library/sabotage/ Sabotage, the conscious withdrawal of the workers' industrial efficiency]

{{Workplace}}

[[Category:Activism]]
[[Category:Crimes]]
[[Category:Economic warfare tactics]]
[[Category:Industrial Workers of the World]]
[[Category:Revolutionary tactics]]
[[Category:Sabotage| ]]
[[Category:Property crimes]]

[[af:Sabotasie]]
[[ast:Sabotax]]
[[bg:Саботаж]]
[[br:Sabotaj]]
[[ca:Sabotatge]]
[[cs:Sabotáž]]
[[da:Sabotage]]
[[de:Sabotage]]
[[es:Sabotaje]]
[[eo:Sabotado]]
[[eu:Sabotaje]]
[[fr:Sabotage]]
[[fur:Sabotaç]]
[[hr:Sabotaža]]
[[id:Sabotase]]
[[it:Sabotaggio]]
[[he:סבוטאז']]
[[kk:Саботаж]]
[[nl:Sabotage]]
[[ja:破壊活動]]
[[no:Sabotasje]]
[[pl:Sabotaż]]
[[pt:Sabotagem]]
[[ru:Саботаж]]
[[sk:Sabotáž]]
[[sh:Sabotaža]]
[[fi:Sabotaasi]]
[[sv:Sabotage]]
[[uk:Саботаж]]
[[diq:Sabotac]]</text>
      <sha1>2pgchtcc6zn03hzqivz0asj08hfn8s0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
