<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>School of the Americas Watch</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3060376</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519877773</id>
      <parentid>519877589</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-26T03:48:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pol098</username>
        <id>169132</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* ¡Presente! newspaper */ anchor for coming redirect</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12676">'''School of the Americas Watch''' is an [[advocacy]] organization founded by [[Maryknoll]] Father [[Roy Bourgeois]] and a small group of supporters in 1990 to protest the training of mainly [[Latin America]]n military officers, by the [[United States Department of Defense]], at the [[Western Hemisphere Institute for Security Cooperation|School of the Americas]] (SOA). Most notably, SOA Watch conducts a [[vigil]] each November at the site of the academy, located on the grounds of [[Fort Benning]], a U.S. Army military base near [[Columbus, Georgia]], in protest over human rights abuses committed by some graduates of the academy or under their leadership, including [[murder]]s, [[rape]]s and [[torture]] and contraventions of the [[Geneva Conventions]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.soaw.org/about-the-soawhinsec/soa-manuals |title=SOA Manuals |publisher=SOA Watch |accessdate=November 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Military officials state that even if graduates commit [[war crime]]s after they return to their home country, the school itself should not be held accountable for their actions. Responding to &quot;mounting protests&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=SOA Protests to Focus on Torture |author=Patrick Mulvaney |url=http://www.thenation.com/article/soa-protests-focus-torture |newspaper=The Nation |date=November 28, 2005 |accessdate=November 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=SOA Protest Draws Scant Support From Candidates |author=Patrick Mulvaney |url=http://www.thenation.com/article/soa-protest-draws-scant-support-candidates |newspaper=The Nation |date=November 12, 2007 |accessdate=November 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; spearheaded by SOA Watch, in 2000 the [[United States Congress]] renamed the School of the Americas the [[Western Hemisphere Institute for Security Cooperation]] (WHINSEC), rather than closing the academy. In addition, all students must undergo a minimum of eight hours of class on human rights and the principle of civilian control of the military.

==Origins==
Inspired by the case of slain Archbishop [[Óscar Romero]], who said &quot;we who have a voice must speak for the voiceless,&quot; Father Bourgeois and two companions posed as military officers and crossed into Ft. Benning in 1983. The two men and a woman climbed a tree near the barracks housing Salvadoran troops and read the final homily of Archbishop Oscar Romero through megaphones. Bourgeois and his companions were arrested and Bourgeois was then sentenced to 18 months in prison for trespassing onto Federal property.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.soaw.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=339 |title=Chronology of SOA Prisoners of Conscience |publisher=SOA Watch |accessdate=November 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bourgeois and his followers began to research the [[School of the Americas]], conduct public education campaigns, lobby [[United States Congress|Congress]], and practice [[nonviolent resistance]] at the School of the Americas facilities.

Following the November 1989 murders of six [[Jesuit]] priests, their housekeeper and her daughter at the [[Central American University]] in [[El Salvador]] in which graduates of the School of the Americas were involved,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cja.org/article.php?list=type&amp;type=84 |title=The Jesuits Massacre Case: El Salvador: Justice for the Murders of November 16, 1989 |publisher=The Center for Justice and Accountability |accessdate=November 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.haguejusticeportal.net/eCache/DEF/12/002.html The Jesuit massacre - The Hague Justice Portal]. Retrieved November 20, 2010.{{dead link|date=August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; SOA Watch organized an annual protest to be held on the anniversary of the massacre beginning the next year. The event has been held every year since then.

==Objectives==
'''Mission Statement'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.soaw.org/about-us |title=About SOA Watch |publisher=SOA Watch |accessdate=August 12, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;SOA Watch is a nonviolent grassroots movement that works to stand in solidarity with the people of Latin America and the Caribbean, to close the SOA/WHINSEC and to change oppressive U.S. foreign policy that the SOA represents. We are grateful to our sisters and brothers throughout Latin America and the Caribbean for their inspiration and the invitation to join them in their struggle for economic and social justice.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Non-violent demonstrations==
Protest demonstrations are staged by SOA Watch at the main gate of Ft. Benning in November each year, in commemoration of the anniversary of the [[Murdered scholars of UCA]]. The growing annual protest has remained a major focus for SOA Watch and the [[grassroots]] movement to close the SOA/WHINSEC, which likewise has grown throughout the Americas since the first protest in 1990. The original band of ten resisters who marched onto Ft. Benning and [[Plowshares_Movement#Pouring_of_blood|splashed blood]] upon the School of Americas to commemorate the first anniversary of the UCA massacre has grown in recent years to a community of 10,000. People come from across the country and around the globe to honor victims of the School of the Americas, as well as their survivors, with music, words, puppets and theatre.

Traditionally the legal vigil and memorial service concludes with a mock funeral procession, using the ''Presente! litany'', onto Ft. Benning, with all who choose to march onto the post [[trespass]]ing on federal property and subject to arrest. Subsequent to [[September 11 attacks|9/11]] and the erection of a security fence at the main gate of Ft. Benning in 2001, protesters who wish to take their mourning onto the post need to go over, under, or around that fence, as opposed to the simple marching of the past.

At the 2002 protest, the city of Columbus began requiring all attending the event to submit to a metal detector search at the designated entrance. After a lengthy legal battle, however, in October 2004 the [[Eleventh Circuit Court of Appeals]] ruled unanimously that the forced search was unconstitutional.

In 2004, the Army added a second fence topped by razor wire, and erected a third fence in 2005.

On November 20, 2005, roughly 20,000 protesters attended the Ft. Benning vigil, &quot;remembering those who have been silenced by SOA violence&quot;. Forty protesters climbed over or under the fence and were arrested by [[military police]]. Columbus police also arrested bystanders, including some who lifted the fence. Since protests against the school began, 183 people have cumulatively served over 81 years in prison for their [[civil disobedience]].

On November 19, 2006, over 22,000 protesters attended the vigil, a record high attendance number. On December 3, 2006, Georgia Public Radio broadcasted &quot;The Sounds of Protest at the School of the Americas&quot;, an hour-long documentary with audio collected at the 2006 protest. [http://www.prx.org/pieces/15428 &quot;Sounds of Protest&quot; Audio Documentary]

On November 20, 2010, at least 20 people attending the vigil were arrested, including Kaelyn Forde, a journalist from [[Russia Today]], and her cameraman, Jon Conway. They were charged with unlawful assembly, demonstrating without a permit and failing to obey a police order to disperse. Forde and Conway were jailed for 29 hours before they were released the following day on $1,300 bond each. Both workers maintain they were &quot;wrongfully arrested&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |agency=Associated Press |url=http://www.boston.com/news/nation/articles/2010/11/22/russian_tv_news_crew_arrested_filming_ga_protest/ |title=Russian TV news crew arrested filming Ga. protest |newspaper=The Boston Globe |date=November 22, 2010 |accessdate=November 30, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Presente litany===
The ''Presente! litany'' is a memorial [[litany]] in which the names of people killed in political repression (usually in [[Central America|Central]] and [[South America]]) are recited. This litany is used at the annual memorial service held at the gates of the [[School of the Americas]] in [[Columbus, Georgia]], for those killed by graduates of the school.&lt;ref name=PresenteAboutUs&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.soaw.org/presente/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=section&amp;id=5&amp;Itemid=69 |title=About Us |work=¡Presente! |publisher=SOA Watch |accessdate=November 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Presente&quot; means &quot;here&quot; or &quot;present&quot; in Spanish.

==''¡Presente!'' newspaper{{Anchor|Presente newspaper}}==
The movement to close the School of the Americas (formerly known as the SOA Watch Update) publishes a newspaper, ''[[¡Presente!]]'', three times a year which is sent to approximately 50,000 subscribers.&lt;ref name=PresenteAboutUs /&gt; The purpose of the newspaper is to give updates about the state of the campaign and of events and developments of the movement.

==See also==
*[[Army Foreign Intelligence Assistance Program]]
*[[Dorothy Hennessey]]
*[[Gwen Hennessey]]

==Further reading==
*{{cite book
| last = Hodge
| first = James
| authorlink =
| coauthors = Linda Cooper
| year = 2004
| title = Disturbing the Peace: The Story of Father Roy Bourgeois and the Movement to Close the School of Americas
| publisher = Orbis Books
| location = Maryknoll, NY
| isbn = 1-57075-434-9
}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.soaw.org/ SOAW.org] SOA Watch homepage 'Shut Down the School of the Americas'(retrieved November 20, 2010)
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=V8sHNKvGm7g&amp;feature=related] Oscar Romero Speech (retrieved November 20, 2010)
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ILCZh1SIypA&amp;feature=related ] &quot;Romero&quot; - a 1989 film about Salvadoran Archbishop Oscar Romero directed by John Duigan - Trailer (retrieved November 20, 2010)
* [http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/21879985/ns/politics-decision_08 Kucinich protests U.S. army training school - MSNBC - November 19, 2007 - Associated Press] (retrieved November 20, 2010)
* [http://www.haguejusticeportal.net/Docs/NLP/Spain/Jesuits_UN_Truth_Commission_Report.pdf Truth Commissions: Reports: El Salvador - The Hague Justice Portal] (retrieved November 20, 2010)
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G5L1VdlktOw&amp;feature=related War on democracy- documentary by [[John Pilger]]- School of Americas] (retrieved November 20, 2010)
* [http://chicagofreespeechzone.blogspot.com/2007/09/by-sergio-barreto-narrative-comprising.html Crossing the Line] The story of two activists arrested at the 2005 SOA Watch vigil
* [https://salsa.democracyinaction.org/o/727/t/10867/shop/shop.jsp?storefront_KEY=777] Resources (documentary film, books) concerning School of Americas and SOA Watch] (retrieved November 20, 2010)
* [http://www.hartford-hwp.com/archives/40/index-a.html Hartford-HWP.com] - 'History of the School of the Americas (SOA)', [[World History Archives]]
*[[School of the Americas Assassins]], a [[1994 in film|1994]] [[short subject|short]] [[documentary film]] produced by [[Robert Richter (American film producer)|Robert Richter]]. It was nominated for an [[Academy Award]] for [[Academy Award for Documentary Short Subject|Best Documentary Short]].
* [http://carlisle-www.army.mil/usamhi/usarsa/main.htm Carlisle-www.army.mil] - 'The US Army School of the Americas Officially Closed its Doors at 1200 Noon on December 15, 2000 After a long Tradition of Service to the United States of America. This Site is Available Only for Historical Purposes.', School of the Americas (official site, last updated December 20, 2000)
*[http://video.google.com/videoplay?docid=2903309148620605209# Hidden in Plain Site: La Escuela de Las Americas - Documentary by [[Andrés Thomas Conteris]] ] (Spanish and English) documentary (retrieved November 20, 2010)
*[http://www.hiddeninplainsight.org/ HiddenInPlainSight.org] - ''[[Hidden in Plain Sight]]'', 'Feature-length documentary that looks at the nature of U.S. policy in Latin America through the prism of the School of the Americas, the controversial military school that trains Latin American soldiers in the USA'
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UGrAeG3QgtE The War on Democracy - Documentary By John Pilger] (accessed November 20, 2010)
*[http://video.google.com/videoplay?docid=6721555445314285342&amp;hl=en VIDEO: Father Roy Bourgeois - Shut Down the School of the Americas!], talk and discussion in Portland, Oregon, on September 15, 2008.
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mGDv-c5LvGA&amp;feature=related Vigil at School of the Americas - Presente! - Recorded on November 22, 2009 by the participants] (retrieved November 20, 2010)

[[Category:Political advocacy groups in the United States]]
[[Category:Non-governmental organizations based in the United States]]
[[Category:Human rights abuses]]
[[Category:Operation Condor]]
[[Category:Human rights in Latin America]]

[[de:Presente Litany]]</text>
      <sha1>npfjon3gp4evla3ar10i70pv1wi7ihs</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
