<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Science policy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>317282</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521934667</id>
      <parentid>519248538</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-08T02:44:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cydebot</username>
        <id>1215485</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Robot - Moving category Economics of innovation to [[:Category:Innovation economics]] per [[WP:CFD|CFD]] at [[Wikipedia:Categories for discussion/Log/2012 November 1]].</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20434">{{incomplete|date=December 2010}}
{{science}}

'''Science policy''' is an area of [[public policy]] concerned with the policies that affect the conduct of the science and research enterprise, including the [[funding of science]], often in pursuance of other national policy goals such as technological innovation to promote commercial product development, weapons development, health care and environmental monitoring.  Science policy also refers to the act of applying scientific knowledge and consensus to the development of public policies.

Science policy thus deals with the entire domain of issues that involve the [[natural science]]s.  In accordance with public policy being concerned about the well-being of its citizens, science policy's goal is to consider how science and technology can best serve the public.

==History==
{{main|History of science policy}}

[[State (polity)|State]] [[policy]] has influenced the funding of [[public works]] and science for thousands of years, dating at least from the time of the [[Mohists]], who inspired the study of logic  during the period of the [[Hundred Schools of Thought]], and the study of defensive fortifications during the [[Warring States Period]] in China. General levies of labor and grain were collected to fund great public works in China, including the accumulation of grain for distribution in times of famine,&lt;ref&gt;Francesca Bray (1984), ''[[Science and Civilisation in China]]'' '''VI.2''' '''''Agriculture'''''&lt;/ref&gt; for the building of levees to control flooding by the great rivers of China, for the building of canals and locks to connect rivers of China, some of which flowed in opposite directions to each other,&lt;ref&gt;[[Joseph Needham]], ''[[Science and Civilisation in China]]''&lt;/ref&gt; and for  the building of bridges across these rivers. These projects required a [[civil service]], the [[Scholar-bureaucrats|scholars]], some of whom demonstrated great mastery of [[hydraulics]].

In Italy, Galileo noted that individual taxation of minute amounts could fund large sums to the State, which could then fund his research on the trajectory of cannonballs, noting that &quot;each individual soldier was being paid from coin collected by a general tax of pennies and farthings, while even a million of gold would not suffice to pay the entire army.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Galileo]] (1638) [http://oll.libertyfund.org/?option=com_staticxt&amp;staticfile=show.php%3Ftitle=753&amp;chapter=109891&amp;layout=html&amp;Itemid=27 Two New Sciences], Salviati, first day of the dialogs&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Great Britain]], [[Lord Chancellor]] [[Sir Francis Bacon]] had a formative effect on science policy with his identification of &quot;experiments of .. light, more penetrating into nature [than what others know]&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[[Sir Francis Bacon]] (1624). ''[[New Atlantis]]''&lt;/ref&gt; which today we call the [[crucial experiment]].  Governmental approval of [[the Royal Society]] recognized a [[scientific community]] which exists to this day. British prizes for research spurred the development of an accurate, portable [[chronometer]], which directly enabled reliable navigation and sailing on the high seas, and also funded Babbage's computer.

The professionalization of science, begun in the nineteenth century, was partly enabled by the creation of scientific organizations such as the [[United States National Academy of Sciences|National Academy of Sciences]], the [[Kaiser Wilhelm Institute]], and State funding of universities of their respective nations. In the United States, a member of the National Academy of Sciences can sponsor a Direct Submission for publication in the ''[[Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pnas.org/site/misc/iforc.shtml#submission PNAS Submission Guidelines]&lt;/ref&gt; ''PNAS'' serves as a channel to recognize research of importance to at least one member of the National Academy of Sciences.

Public policy can directly affect the funding of [[capital equipment]], intellectual infrastructure for industrial research, by providing tax incentives to those organizations who fund research. [[Vannevar Bush]], director of the office of scientific research and development for the U.S. government in July 1945, wrote &quot;Science is a proper concern of government&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nsf.gov/od/lpa/nsf50/vbush1945.htm Vannevar Bush (July 1945), &quot;Science, the Endless Frontier&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;  Vannevar Bush directed the forerunner of the [[National Science Foundation]], and his writings directly inspired researchers to invent the [[hyperlink]] and the [[computer mouse]].  The [[DARPA]] initiative to support computing was the impetus for the [[Internet Protocol]] stack. In the same way that scientific consortiums like [[CERN]] for [[high-energy physics]] have a commitment to public knowledge, access to this public knowledge in physics led directly to CERN's sponsorship of development of the [[World Wide Web]] and standard Internet access for all.

==Philosophies of science policy==
{{Ref improve section|date=November 2010}}

===Basic versus applied research===

The programs that are funded are often divided into four basic categories: [[basic research]], [[applied research]], [[Research and development|development]], and facilities and equipment.&lt;ref name=&quot;AAASpresentation&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Clemins|first=Patrick|title=R&amp;D in the President's FY 2011 Budget|url=http://www.aaas.org/spp/rd/presentations/|accessdate=20 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Translational research]] is a newer concept that seeks to bridge the gap between basic science and practical applications.

Basic science attempts to stimulate breakthroughs. Breakthroughs often lead to an explosion of new technologies and approaches.  Once the basic result is developed, it is widely published; however conversion into a practical product is left for the free market.  However, many governments have developed risk-taking research and development organizations to take basic theoretical research over the edge into practical [[engineering]].  In the [[United States|U.S.]], this function is performed by [[DARPA]].

On the other hand, technology development is a policy in which engineering, the application of science, is supported rather than basic science.  The emphasis is usually given to projects that increase important strategic or commercial engineering knowledge.  The most extreme success story is doubtless the [[Manhattan Project]] that developed [[nuclear weapon]]s.  Another remarkable success story was the &quot;X-vehicle&quot; studies that gave the US a lasting lead in aerospace technologies.

These exemplify two disparate approaches: The Manhattan Project was huge, and spent unblinkingly on the most risky alternative approaches.  The project members believed that failure would result in their enslavement or destruction by [[Nazi Germany]].  Each X-project built an aircraft whose only purpose was to develop a particular technology.  The plan was to build a few cheap aircraft of each type, fly a test series, often to the destruction of an aircraft, and never design an aircraft for a practical mission.  The only mission was technology development.

A number of high-profile technology developments have failed.  The US Space Shuttle failed to meet its cost or flight schedule goals.  Most observers explain the project as over constrained: the cost goals too aggressive, the technology and mission too underpowered and undefined.  

The Japanese [[fifth generation computer systems project]] met every technological goal, but failed to produce commercially-important [[artificial intelligence]].  Many observers believe that the Japanese tried to force engineering beyond available science by brute investment.  Half the amount spent on basic research rather might have produced ten times the result.

=== Utilitarian versus monumental science policy ===
[[Utilitarianism|Utilitarian]] policies prioritize scientific projects that significantly reduce [[suffering]] for larger numbers of people.  This approach would mainly consider the numbers of people that can be helped by a research policy.  Research is more likely to be supported when it costs less and has greater benefits.  Utilitarian research often pursues incremental improvements rather than dramatic advancements in knowledge, or break-through solutions, which are more commercially viable.

In contrast, monumental science is a policy in which science is supported for the sake of a greater understanding of the universe, rather than for specific short-term practical goals.  This designation covers both large projects, often with large facilities, and smaller research that does not have obvious practical applications and are often overlooked.  While these projects may not always have obvious practical outcomes, they provide education of future scientists, and advancement of scientific knowledge of lasting worth about the basic building blocks of science.

Practical outcomes do result from many of these &quot;monumental&quot; science programs.  Sometimes these practical outcomes are foreseeable and sometimes they are not.  A classic example of a monumental science program focused towards a practical outcome is the [[Manhattan project]].  An example of a monumental science program that produces unexpected practical outcome is the [[laser]].  Coherent light, the principle behind lasing, was first predicted by Einstein in 1916, but not created until 1954 by Charles H. Townes with the [[maser]].  The breakthrough with the maser led to the creation of the laser in 1960 by Theodore Maiman.  The delay between the theory of coherent light and the production of the laser was partially due to the assumption that it would be of no practical use.&lt;ref&gt;Suplee, Curt (1999) ''Physics In The 20th Century'' Harry N. Abrams Inc, 58-63.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Big Science versus small science===
{{main|Big Science|Small Science}}

{{Empty section|date=December 2010|section=5}}

===Government versus academic control of research direction===
{{main|Haldane principle}}

{{Empty section|date=December 2010|section=6}}

===Scholastic conservation===
This policy approach prioritizes efficiently teaching all available science to those who can use it, rather than investing in new science.  In particular, the goal is not to ''lose'' any existing knowledge, and to find new practical ways to apply the available knowledge.  The classic success stories of this method occurred in the 19th century U.S. land-grant universities, which established a strong tradition of research in practical agricultural and engineering methods.  More recently, the [[Green Revolution]] prevented mass famine over the last thirty years.  The focus, unsurprisingly, is usually on developing a robust curriculum and inexpensive practical methods to meet local needs.

==Intellectual property policy==
{{main|Patent}}
{{empty section|date=November 2010|section=8}}

==Science and the public==
{{main|Public awareness of science|Science outreach}}
{{empty section|date=November 2010|section=9}}

==Science and politics==
{{main|Evidence-based policy|Politicization of science}}
{{empty section|date=November 2010|section=10}}

== Science policy by country ==

Most developed countries usually have a specific national body overseeing national science (including technology and innovation) policy. In the case developing countries many follow the same fashion.  Many governments of [[developed country|developed countries]] provide considerable funds (primarily to universities) for scientific research (in fields such as [[physics]] and [[geology]]) as well as social science research (in fields such as [[economics]] and [[history]]). Much of this is not intended to provide concrete results that may be commercialisable, although research in scientific fields may lead to results that have such potential. Most university research is aimed at gaining publication in [[peer review]]ed [[academic journal]]s.

A funding body is an organisation that provides [[research funding]] in the form of [[research grant]]s or [[scholarship]]s.  Research councils are funding bodies that are government-funded agencies engaged in the support of research in different disciplines and postgraduate funding.  Funding from research councils is typically competitive. As a general rule, more funding is available in science and engineering disciplines than in the arts and social sciences.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.prospects.ac.uk/cms/ShowPage/Home_page/Funding_my_further_study/Public_funding_bodies/p!ejclk | title = Public funding bodies | work = [[Graduate Prospects]] | accessdate = 2007-02-19 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Australia===
In [[Australia]], the two main research councils are the [[Australian Research Council]] and the [[National Health and Medical Research Council]].

===Canada===
{{see also|Science and technology in Canada}}

In [[Canada]], the three main research councils are the [[Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council]], the [[Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council]], and the [[Canadian Institutes of Health Research]].  Additional research funding agencies include the [[Canada Foundation for Innovation]], [[Genome Canada]], the [[Networks of Centres of Excellence]] [http://www.nce.gc.ca/] partnerships between university, government and industry, the [[Minister of Research and Innovation (Ontario)]], and the Michael Smith Foundation for Health Research (MSFHR) [http://www.msfhr.org].

===European Union===
{{see also|Science and technology in Europe}}

The science policy of the [[European Union]] is carried out through the [[European Research Area]], a system which integrates the scientific resources of member nations and acts as a &quot;common market&quot; for research and innovation.  The European Union's executive body, the [[European Commission]], has a [[Directorate-General for Research (European Commission)|Directorate-General for Research]], which is responsible for the Union's science policy.  In addition, the [[Joint Research Centre]] provides independent scientific and technical advice to the European Commission and Member States of the [[European Union]] (EU) in support of EU policies.&lt;ref name=&quot;a1370&quot;&gt;http://ec.europa.eu/dgs/jrc/index.cfm?id=1370&lt;/ref&gt;  There is also the recently-established [[European Research Council]], the first European Union [[Funding of science|funding body]] set up to support investigator-driven research.

There are also European science agencies that operate independently of the European Union, such as the [[European Science Foundation]], [[European Space Agency]], and the [[European Higher Education Area]] created by the [[Bologna process]].

=== Germany ===
{{see also|Science and technology in Germany}}

German research funding agencies include the [[Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft]], which covers both [[science]] and [[humanities]].

=== India ===
{{see also|Science and technology in the Republic of India}}

Research funding by the Government of India comes from a number of sources.  For basic science and technology research, these include the Council for Scientific and Industrial Research (CSIR), Department of Science and Technology (DST), and University Grants Commission (UGC).  For medical research, these include the Indian Council for Medical Research (ICMR), CSIR, DST and Department of Biotechnology (DBT).  For applied research, these include the CSIR, DBT and Science and Engineering Research Council (SERC).

Other funding authorities are the Defence Research Development Organisation (DRDO), the Indian Council of Agricultural Research (ICAR), the Indian Space Research Organisation (ISRO), the Department of Ocean Development (DOD), the Indian Council for Social Science Research (ICSSR), and the Ministry of Environment and Forests (MEF) etc.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.unom.ac.in/gcl-opac/Research%20funding.htm#Indian%20Research%20Funding%20Agencies&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Ireland ===
Irish funding councils include the [[IRCSET|Irish Research Council for Science, Engineering and Technology]] (IRCSET), the Irish Research Council for the Humanities and Social Sciences (IRCHSS), and the [[Science Foundation Ireland]].

=== The Netherlands ===
Dutch research funding agencies include [[Nederlandse Organisatie voor Wetenschappelijk Onderzoek]] (NWO) [http://nwo.nl/] and [[Agentschap NL]] [http://www.agentschapnl.nl/].

=== Pakistan ===
{{see also|Science and technology in Pakistan}}

The Government of Pakistan has mandated that a certain percentage of gross revenue generated by all telecom service providers be allocated to development and research of information and communication technologies. The [[National ICT R&amp;D Fund (Pakistan)|National ICT R&amp;D Fund]] was established in January 2007 by Ministry of IT, Government of Pakistan with the vision to transform Pakistan's economy into a knowledge based economy by promoting efficient, sustainable and effective ICT initiatives through synergic development of industrial and academic resources.

=== Switzerland ===
{{see also|Science and technology in Switzerland}}

Swiss research funding agencies include the [[Swiss National Science Foundation]] (SNSF) [http://www.snf.ch/E/Pages/default.aspx], the innovation promotion agency CTI (CTI/KTI) [http://www.bbt.admin.ch/kti/index.html?lang=en], Ressortforschung des Bundes [http://www.ressortforschung.admin.ch/], and Eidgenössische Stiftungsaufsicht [http://www.edi.admin.ch/esv/].

===United Kingdom===
{{main|UK Research Councils}}
* See also:[http://www.sciencecouncil.org Science Council]

In the [[United Kingdom]], there are seven grant-awarding Research Councils:
* [[Arts and Humanities Research Council]] (AHRC)
* [[Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council]] (BBSRC)
* [[Economic and Social Research Council]] (ESRC)
* [[Engineering and Physical Sciences Research Council]] (EPSRC)
* [[Medical Research Council (UK)|Medical Research Council]] (MRC)
* [[Natural Environment Research Council]] (NERC)
* [[Particle Physics and Astronomy Research Council]] (PPARC)
* [[Science and Technology Facilities Council]] (STFC)

===United States===
{{main|Science policy of the United States}}

The [[United States]] has a long history of government support for science and technology.  Science policy in the United States is the responsibility of many organizations throughout the [[Federal government of the United States|federal government]].  Much of the large-scale policy is made through the legislative [[United States budget process|budget process]] of enacting the yearly [[United States federal budget|federal budget]].  Further decisions are made by the various federal agencies which spend the funds allocated by Congress, either on in-house research or by granting funds to outside organizations and researchers.

Research funding agencies in the United States are spread among many different departments, which include:
* Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency ([[DARPA]])
* [[United States Department of Energy]] Office of Science
* [[National Institutes of Health]]: biomedical research
* [[National Science Foundation]]: fundamental research and education in all the non-medical fields of science and engineering.
* [[Office of Naval Research]]

==See also==
* [[History of science policy]]
* [[History of military science]]
* [[Politicization of science]]
* [[Office of Science and Technology Policy]]
* [[Big Science]]
* [[Haldane principle]]
* [[List of books about the politics of science]]
* [[Operations Research]]
* [[Suppressed research in the Soviet Union]]
* [[Science and Technology Policy Research]] (SPRU)
* [[Science of science policy]] (SoSP)
* [[List of funding opportunity databases]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.sciencepolicyjournal.org The Journal of Science Policy &amp; Governance]
* [http://www.researchamerica.org Research!America]
* [http://www.scipol.co.uk/spphome.html Journal of Science and Public Policy]
* [http://www.battellecenter.org The Battelle Center for Science and Technology Policy, OSU]
* [http://www.newsciencepolicy.org NEWScience Policy a weekly review of Science Policy News]

{{Public policy}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Science Policy}}
[[Category:Innovation economics|policy]]
[[Category:Public policy]]
[[Category:Politics by issue]]
[[Category:Research]]
[[Category:Policy]]
[[Category:Politics of science]]
[[Category:Public finance]]
[[Category:Research management]]

[[de:Wissenschaftspolitik]]
[[ko:과학기술정책]]
[[lt:Mokslo politika]]
[[pl:Polityka naukowa]]</text>
      <sha1>s13q1hsex9h884ybdn3t1y5aq3ta3kq</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
