<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Secret ballot</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>479210</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521900995</id>
      <parentid>521880715</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-07T22:48:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>24.225.115.206</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* United States */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18814">{{For|2001 Iranian film|Secret Ballot (film)}}
{{Redirect|Australian ballot|voting in Australia|Electoral system of Australia}}
{{Elections}}

The '''secret ballot''' is a voting method in which a [[voter]]'s choices in an [[election]] or a [[referendum]] are anonymous. The key aim is to ensure the voter records a sincere choice by forestalling attempts to influence the voter by [[intimidation]] or [[bribery]]. The system is one means of achieving the goal of [[political privacy]]. However, the secret ballot may increase the amount of vote buying where it is still legal by paying lukewarm supporters to turn out and paying lukewarm opponents to stay home, and therefore may reduce the costs of buying an election.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite report |last= Morgan |first= John |last2= Várdy |first= Felix |title= ''Negative Vote Buying and the Secret Ballot'' |date= November 9, 2010 |publisher= International Monetary Fund |type= IMF working papers series |location= University of California, Berkeley |url= http://ssrn.com/abstract=1706490 |doi= 10.2139/ssrn.1706490 |accessdate= September 22, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Secret ballots are suitable for many different [[voting system]]s. The most basic form may be blank pieces of paper, upon which each voter writes only his or her choice. Without revealing their votes to anyone, the electors place the [[ballot]]s into a sealed box, which is emptied later for counting.

In the modern world one of the most common forms of the secret ballot involves pre-printed ballot papers with the name of the candidates or questions and respective checkboxes. Provisions are made at the [[polling place]] for the voters to record their preferences in secret. The ballots are specifically designed to eliminate bias and to prevent anyone from linking voter to ballot. This system is also known as the '''Australian ballot''', because it originated in [[Australia]] during the 1850s.  In the [[United States]], it is also known as the '''Massachusetts ballot''' since [[Massachusetts]] was the first [[U.S. state]] to use the secret ballot. In the U.S., voting by secret ballot was universal by 1892, but criminal prohibitions against paying people to vote for a particular candidate or not were instituted in 1925.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/18/597 18 U.S.C. § 597 - Expenditures to influence voting]&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
In [[ancient Greece]], secret ballots were used in several occasions,&lt;ref&gt;Saalfeld, Thomas. 1995. On Dogs and Whips: Recorded Votes. In: Herbert Döring. Parliaments and Majority Rule in Western Europe. New York : St. Martin's Press, 1995. Page 531&lt;/ref&gt; like [[ostracism]] and also to remain hidden from people seeking favors.
In [[ancient Rome]], the laws regulating elections were collectively known as ''[[Tabellariae Leges]]'', the first of which was introduced in 139 BC (''[[Lex Gabinia]]'').&lt;ref&gt;[http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/secondary/SMIGRA*/Tabellariae_Leges.html Tabellariae Leges]. [[William Smith (lexicographer)|William Smith]], D.C.L., LL.D.: [[A Dictionary of Greek and Roman Antiquities]], John Murray, London, 1875.&lt;/ref&gt; Today the practice of casting secret ballots is so commonplace that most voters would not consider that any other method might be used.

=== France ===
Article 31 of the [[French Constitution of 1795]]&lt;ref&gt;[[Image:wikisource-logo.svg|15px]] [[s:fr:Constitution du 22 août 1795|Full text]] of the [[French Constitution of 1795]] on [[Wikisource]] {{fr icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; states that &quot;All elections are to be held by secret ballot&quot;. The same goes with the [[French Constitution of 1848|constitution of 1848]]&lt;ref&gt;''Article 24. — Le suffrage est direct et universel. Le scrutin est secret''. [[:s:fr:Constitution du 4 novembre 1848]]&lt;/ref&gt; : voters could hand-write the name of their preferred candidate on their ballot at home (the only condition was to write on a white paper&lt;ref&gt;''Pour être recevable, chaque vote doit être inscrit sur un papier blanc'' : [[:fr:Élection présidentielle française de 1848]]&lt;/ref&gt;) or receive one in a distribution in the street.&lt;ref&gt;See the picture captioned '' Distribution des bulletins d'élections dans les rues. L'Illustration du 23 septembre 1848 on [http://www.assemblee-nationale.fr/histoire/suffrage_universel/suffrage-1848.asp Assemblée Nationale website]&lt;/ref&gt; The ballot is folded in order to prevent other people from reading its content.&lt;ref&gt;[[:fr:Isoloir]]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Napoleon III|Louis-Napoléon Bonaparte]] attempted to abolish the secret ballot for the 1851 [[plebiscite]] with an electoral [[decree]] requesting electors to write down &quot;yes&quot; or &quot;no&quot; (in French: &quot;oui&quot; or &quot;non&quot;) under the eyes of everyone. But he faced a strong opposition and finally changed his mind, allowing secret ballot to take place.&lt;ref&gt;[[Karl Marx]] [[The Eighteenth Brumaire of Louis Napoleon]] : ''For the bourgeois and the shopkeeper had learned that in one of his decrees of December 2 Bonaparte had abolished the secret ballot and had ordered them to put a “yes” or “no” after their names on the official registers. The resistance of December 4 intimidated Bonaparte. During the night he had placards posted on all the street corners of Paris announcing the restoration of the secret ballot. '' [http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1852/18th-brumaire/ch07.htm Full text (chapter VII)]&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the official web site of the ''Assemblee nationale'' (the lower house of the French parliament), the [[voting booth]] was permanently adopted only in 1913.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.assemblee-nationale.fr/histoire/suffrage_universel/suffrage-1870.asp#gauche]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== United Kingdom ===
[[Image:William Hogarth 031.jpg|thumb|320px|''[[Humours of an Election|The Polling]]'' by [[William Hogarth]] (1755). Before the secret ballot was introduced, voter intimidation was commonplace.]]
The demand for a secret ballot was one of the six points of [[Chartism]].&lt;ref&gt;In the words of the [[petition]] that was published in 1838:
:''&quot;The [[suffrage]], to be exempt from the corruption of the wealthy and the violence of the powerful, must be secret.&quot;'' [http://www.chartists.net/The-six-points.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;
The [[Parliament of the United Kingdom|British parliament]] of the time refused to even consider the Chartist demands but it is notable that [[Thomas Babington Macaulay, 1st Baron Macaulay|Lord Macaulay]], in his speech of 1842, while rejecting Chartism's six points as a whole, admitted that the secret ballot was one of the two points he could support.

The secret ballot was eventually introduced in the [[Ballot Act 1872]], substantially reducing the cost of campaigning, and was first used on 15 August 1872 to re-elect [[Hugh Childers]] as MP for [[Pontefract (UK Parliament constituency)|Pontefract]] in a [[ministerial by-election]] following his appointment as [[Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster]].  The original [[ballot box]], sealed in wax with a liquorice stamp, is held at Pontefract museum.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/ahistoryoftheworld/objects/WryVwsknTr-aa4IQ-ID9iQ Pontefract's secret ballot box, 1872].&lt;/ref&gt; The [[#Secrecy vs. reliability|use of numbered ballots]] makes it possible, given access to the relevant documents, to identify who has voted for whom, although this is only rarely done.

=== Australia ===
[[Chartism|Chartist]] ideas influenced the miners of [[Eureka Stockade]] in 1854 in [[Victoria (Australia)|Victoria]] where they adopted all of Chartism's six points including the secret ballot. Secret balloting appears to have been first implemented in the former [[Australia]]n [[colony]] (now a [[States and territories of Australia|state]]) of [[Tasmania]] on February 7, 1856. Until the original Tasmanian Electoral Act of 1856 was 're-discovered' recently, credit for the first implementation of the secret ballot often went to the colonies of Victoria and [[South Australia]].&lt;ref&gt;Terry Newman, {{PDFlink|[http://www.enrollingthepeople.com/tasmania/newman_tasmania_and_secret_ballot.pdf Tasmania and the Secret Ballot]|144&amp;nbsp;[[Kibibyte|KiB]]&lt;!-- application/pdf, 147664 bytes --&gt;}} (2003), 49(1) ''Aust J Pol &amp; Hist 93'', accessed February 27, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;  Victoria enacted [[Electoral Act 1856|legislation]] for secret ballots on March 19, 1856, and South Australian Electoral Commissioner [[William Boothby]] generally gets credit for creating the system finally enacted into law in South Australia on April 2 of that same year (a fortnight later).

===United States===
[[Image:1900 New York polling place.jpg|thumb|[[New York]] polling place circa 1900, showing [[voting booth]]s on the left.]]
In the [[United States]] the practice became known as the &quot;Australian ballot&quot;, defined as having four parts:&lt;ref&gt;See page 59 of: {{cite book
  | title = Webster's Seventh New Colligiate Dictionary
  | publisher = G&amp;C Merriam Company
  | year = 1967
  | location = [[Springfield, Massachusetts]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# an official ballot being printed at public expense,
# on which the names of the nominated candidates of all parties and all proposals appear,
# being distributed only at the polling place and
# being marked in secret.

In the United States, most states had moved to secret ballots soon after the [[United States presidential election, 1884|presidential election of 1884]].  However, [[Kentucky]] was the last state to do so in 1891, when it quit using an [[oral ballot]]. Therefore, the first [[President of the United States]] elected completely under the Australian ballot was president [[Grover Cleveland]] in [[United States presidential election, 1892|1892]]. 

The first city to start using Australian ballot in the United States was  [[Louisville, Kentucky]]. However, the first state to adopt Australian ballot was [[Massachusetts]].

Elections in the United States are mostly held by secret ballot,&lt;ref&gt;The [[Political party|party]] nominating [[caucus]]es in some [[U.S. state]]s (most significantly the leadoff Presidential nominating state of [[Iowa]]) still require an open casting of ballots.&lt;/ref&gt; although some states use mail ballots instead, which violate two of the four requirements of the &quot;Australian ballot&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Postal_voting#United_States&lt;/ref&gt;  The Constitution for the State of [[West Virginia]] still allows voters to cast &quot;open ballots&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''See'' W. Va. Const. Art. IV, §2, &quot;In all elections by the people, the mode of voting shall be by ballot; but the voter shall be left free to vote by either open, sealed or secret ballot, as he may elect.&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Disabled people==
[[Image:topvoter2.jpg|thumb|ISG TopVoter, a voting machine which assures secret ballot for voters with disabilities.]]
Ballot design and polling place architecture often denies the disabled the possibility to cast a vote in secret. In many democracies{{Citation needed|date=August 2012}} disabled persons vote by appointing another person who fills the ballot in their name. This does not assure secrecy of the ballot.

The [[United Nations]] [[Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities]] which entered into force in 2008 assures secret ballot for [[disabled]] voters. Article 29 of the Convention requires that all Contracting States protect &quot;the right of persons with [[disabilities]] to vote by secret ballot in [[elections]] and public [[referendums]]&quot;. According to this provision, each Contracting State should provide for voting equipment which would enable disabled voters to vote independently and secretly. Some democracies, e.g. the [[United States]], the [[Netherlands]], [[Slovenia]], [[Albania]] or [[India]] allow disabled voters to use electronic [[voting machines]]. In others, among them [[Azerbaijan]],  [[Canada]], [[Ghana]], the [[United Kingdom]], and most [[African]] and [[Asia]]n countries, visually impaired voters can use ballots in [[Braille]] or paper ballot templates. Article 29 also requires that Contracting States ensure &quot;that voting procedures, facilities and materials are appropriate, accessible and easy to understand and use.&quot; In some democracies, e.g. [[The United Kingdom]], [[Sweden]] and the [[United States]], all the polling places already are fully accessible for disabled voters.

==Secrecy vs. reliability==
{{Refimprovesect|date=April 2010}}
The [[United Kingdom]] secret ballot arrangements are sometimes criticised because it is possible to link a ballot paper to the voter who cast it. Each ballot paper is individually numbered and each elector also has a number. When an elector is given a ballot paper, their number is noted down on the counterfoil of the ballot paper (which also carries the ballot paper number). This means, of course, that the secrecy of the ballot is not guaranteed, if anyone can gain access to the counterfoils, which are locked away securely before the ballot boxes are opened at the count. Polling station officials colluding with election scrutineers may therefore determine how individual electors have voted.

This measure is thought to be justified as a security arrangement so that if there was an allegation of fraud, false ballot papers could be identified. The process of matching ballot papers to voters is permissible only if an [[Election Court]] requires it, and this is an extremely unlikely occurrence. In fact the Election Court has never made such an order since the secret ballot was introduced in 1872. The legal authority for this system is set out in the Parliamentary Elections Rules in Schedule 1 of the [[Representation of the People Act 1983]].&lt;ref&gt;{{PDFlink|[http://www.electoralcommission.org.uk/__data/assets/electoral_commission_pdf_file/0020/13259/Ballot-Secrecy-2006-12_23827-6127__E__N__S__W__.pdf Factsheet: Ballot secrecy]|48 [[KiB]]}} (2006), [[Electoral Commission (United Kingdom)|Electoral Commission of the United Kingdom]]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[United States]], sometimes the number on the ballot is printed on a perforated stub which is torn off and placed on a ring (like a [[shower curtain]] ring) before the ballot is cast into the ballot box.  The stubs prove that an elector has voted and ensure he can only vote once, but the ballots themselves are anonymous.  At the end of voting day, the number of ballots inside the box should match the number of stubs on the ring, certifying that every ballot was cast by a registered elector, and that none of them were lost or fabricated. Sometimes the ballots themselves are numbered, making the vote trackable. This was ruled legal by Federal District Judge [[Christine Arguello]], who denied the existence of a constitutional right to a secret ballot.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.denverpost.com/breakingnews/ci_21601455/federal-judge-says-no-constitutional-right-secret-ballot&lt;/ref&gt;

==Chronology of introduction==
{{Unreferenced section|date=September 2008}}
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
! Date
! Country
! Notes
|-
|1795 (August 22)
|[[France]]
|
|-
|1849
|[[Netherlands]]
|
|-
|1853
|[[Colombia]]
|
|-
|1856 (February 7)
|[[Australia]] ([[Tasmania (Australia)|Tasmania]])
|The other Australian states of [[Victoria (Australia)|Victoria]] (March 19, 1856), [[South Australia]] (April 2, 1856), [[New South Wales]] (1858), [[Queensland]] (1859), and [[Western Australia]] (1877) followed.
|-
|1861
|[[Italy]]
|
|-
|1861
|[[Ecuador]]
|
|-
|1866
|[[Sweden]]
|Voter chooses party-specific ballot in the open, limiting the secrecy. There is, however, the possibility to choose a blank ballot on which you can choose any  party in complete secrecy.
|-
|1870
|[[New Zealand]]
|
|-
|1872
|[[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|United Kingdom]]
|In the UK this was passed by the [[Ballot Act 1872]], but is no longer the case by virtue of Schedule 1 of the Representation of the People Act 1983, as mentioned above.
|-
|1872
|[[Switzerland]]
|
|-
|1874
|[[Canada]]
|
|-
|1877
|[[Belgium]]
|
|-
|1885
|[[Norway]]
|
|-
|1891
|[[United States of America]]
|[[Massachusetts]] was the first state to hold a secret ballot, in 1888, and [[Kentucky]] was the last to do so, in 1891.
|-
|1901
|[[Denmark]]
|In connection with [[Cabinet of Deuntzer#Shift_of_government|The Shift of Government]] (Danish: ''Systemskiftet'')&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Elklit | first = Jørgen | authorlink = Jørgen Elklit | coauthors = | title = Fra åben til hemmelig afstemning | publisher = Politica | year = 1988 | location = Århus, Denmark | pages = 299 ff | url = | doi = | id = | isbn = }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|1906
|[[Russia]]
|
|-
|1907
|[[Austria]]
|
|-
|1907
|[[Finland]]
|
|-
|1912
|[[Argentina]]
|
|-
|1918
|[[Poland]]
|
|-
|1918
|[[Uruguay]]
|
|-
|1919
|[[Romania]]
|
|-
|1925
|[[Costa Rica]]
|
|-
|1931
|[[Peru]]
|
|-
|1932
|[[Brazil]]
|
|-
|1946
|[[Venezuela]]
|
|-
|1947
|[[Hungary]]
|
|-
|1950
|[[Turkey]]
|
|-
|1950
|[[El Salvador]]
|
|}

== Chronology of Repeal ==

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
! Date
! Country
! Notes
|-
|1983
|[[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland|United Kingdom]]
|
|}

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==See also==
*[[Ballot]]
*[[Election fraud]]
*[[Voter suppression]]
*[[List of democracy and elections-related topics]]

==External links==
{{wikisource|A History of the Australian Ballot System in the United States}}
*[http://www.enrollingthepeople.com/tasmania/tassie_secret_ballot.htm A little bit of revision: Tasmania adopts the ballot in 1856]
*[http://www.guardian.co.uk/Columnists/Column/0%2C5673%2C945518%2C00.html Death of the secret ballot]
*[http://www.meridianmagazine.com/historybits/041028ballot.html The Secret Ballot Comes To Utah (1878)]
*[http://www.enrollingthepeople.com/published/CTDec18_2005.htm Celebrating the 150th anniversary of the Australian ballot]
*[http://www.aceproject.org/ace-en/topics/ei/eif/eif09/eif09a Secrecy of the Vote], article from the [http://www.aceproject.org ACE Project]
*[http://www.idea.int/publications/esd/index.cfm A handbook of electoral system Design] from [http://www.idea.int International IDEA]
*[http://www.decing.com Decing] - Simple Web 2.0 online service for quick decision making via Secret Ballot for small teams.
*[http://www.princeton.edu/~ppettit/papers/Unveiling_BJPS_1990.pdf Philip Pettit &amp; Geoffrey Brennan, &quot;Unveiling the Vote&quot; British Journal of Political Science, Vol. 20, pp. 311-33]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Secret Ballot}}
[[Category:Elections]]
[[Category:Secrecy]]

[[da:Hemmelig afstemning]]
[[de:Wahlgeheimnis]]
[[es:Sufragio secreto]]
[[fr:Vote à bulletin secret]]
[[ko:비밀 선거]]
[[he:הצבעה חשאית]]
[[mr:गुप्त मतदान]]
[[nl:Geheime stemming]]
[[ja:秘密投票]]
[[pl:Tajność wyborów]]
[[pt:Voto secreto]]
[[ru:Тайное голосование]]
[[sh:Tajno glasanje]]
[[fi:Vaalisalaisuus]]
[[sv:Sluten omröstning]]
[[tr:Gizli oy]]
[[uk:Таємне голосування]]
[[ur:خفیہ ووٹ]]
[[zh-yue:不記名投票]]
[[zh:不記名投票]]</text>
      <sha1>etae02iu2p5b0nu2kk7ql53blmx12wl</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
