<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Separation of powers</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>28561</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522407055</id>
      <parentid>522406470</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-11T00:32:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Demiurge1000</username>
        <id>12547828</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted [[WP:AGF|good faith]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/Slurpy121|Slurpy121]] ([[User talk:Slurpy121|talk]]): That's the exact opposite of what is in the cited source. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="42676">{{Redirect|Balance of powers|other uses|Balance of power (disambiguation){{!}}Balance of power}}
{{Other uses}}
{{Multiple issues
 | refimprove=March 2011l
 | cleanup=March 2010
}} 
The '''separation of powers''', often imprecisely used interchangeably with the '''''trias politica''''' principle,&lt;ref&gt;This latter refers specifically to the separation of powers into three branches of government: legislative, executive and judicial.&lt;/ref&gt; is a model for the [[governance]] of a state (or who controls the state). The model was first developed in the [[Roman Republic]] as part of the unmodified [[Constitution of the Roman Republic]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bible-history.com/rome/Romerome00000099.htm|Checks and Balances.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.newworldencyclopedia.org/entry/Checks_and_balances|Checks and Balances.&lt;/ref&gt;. Under this model, the [[State (polity)|state]] is divided into branches, each with separate and independent powers and areas of responsibility so that no branch has more power than the other branches. The normal division of branches is into a [[legislature]], an [[Executive (government)|executive]], and a [[judiciary]].

==Montesquieu's tripartite system==
{{cleanup|section|date=October 2008}}
The term is ascribed to [[France|French]] [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]] [[political philosopher]] [[Charles de Secondat, baron de Montesquieu|Baron de Montesquieu]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/montesquieu/#4 |title=Baron de Montesquieu, Charles-Louis de Secondat (Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy) |publisher=Plato.stanford.edu |date= |accessdate=2008-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lawiki.org/lawwiki/Separation_of_powers |title=lawiki.org law&amp;nbsp;— Separation of Powers: the reality |publisher=lawiki.org|date= |accessdate=2010-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Montesquieu]] described division of [[political power]] among a [[legislature]], an [[executive (government)|executive]], and a [[judiciary]]. He based this model on the British constitutional system, in which he perceived a separation of powers among the monarch, Parliament, and the courts of law. Subsequent writers have noted that this was misleading,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.crf-usa.org/bill-of-rights-in-action/bria-20-2-c-hobbes-locke-montesquieu-and-rousseau-on-government.html |title=Hobbes, Locke, Montesquieu, and Rousseau on Government |publisher=Constitutional Rights Foundation |date= |accessdate=2012-07-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; because the United Kingdom had a very closely connected legislature and executive, with further links to the judiciary (though combined with [[judicial independence]]).

Montesquieu did specify that &quot;the independence of the judiciary has to be real, and not apparent merely&quot;. &quot;The judiciary was generally seen as the most important of powers, independent and unchecked&quot;, and also considered it dangerous.{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}}

==Comparison between Presidential and Parliamentary systems==
{{Unreferenced section|date=December 2008}}
In democratic systems of [[governance]] based on the trias politica, a fundamental parallel and a fundamental difference exists between ''presidential systems'' and constitutional monarchic ''[[parliamentary system]]'' of government.  

The parallel is that the three branches of government (legislative, executive, judicial) exist largely independent of each other, with their own prerogatives, domains of activity, and exercises of control over each other.  
*The legislative body has control of the executive finances, and has judiciary powers, it also has control of the way the judiciary works.
*The judiciary often has control of laws not being contradictory to the constitution or other laws and it has the power to correct and control the way the executive body exercises its powers (to execute the law)

The difference between the two systems is:
*In presidential systems, the chief executive is elected to office and, after transfer of power, appoints his or her administration (like in the United States, with a [[unitary executive]]). However, a government headed by a prime minister is formed within the parliament, based on the elected majority (as in [[France]], for example). The latter might lead to &quot;cohabitation&quot; where a president and his government belong to different parties or coalitions.

*In constitutional monarchic parliamentary systems, only the legislative body is elected and a government formed on the basis of majority or a coalitions of parties. Elected members of parliament have to resign from their mandate in order to accept an executive office. This is true in regional and local councils are elected and the executive nominated.
*In a parliamentary system, when the term of the legislature ends, so to may the tenure of the executive selected by that legislature. However, in a presidential system, the executive's term may or may not coincide with the legislature's, as their selection is technically independent of the legislature.

Two-branch power systems may have systems in which certain branches have more than one power. Often a legislative body is elected, while the executive is nominated. The nominated executive branch also has power of presenting legislation, while the legislative body only has a controlling function. In those systems, the judiciary is subservient to the executive and has no power to control either the executive or the legality of new legislative texts.    

The separation of powers is a doctrine which provides a separate authority that makes it possible for the authorities to check each other's checks and balances (see United States Executive Authority Act 1936).

==Various models==
[[Constitution]]s with a high degree of separation of powers are found worldwide. The [[Westminster system|UK system]] is distinguished by a particular entwining of powers. In [[Italy]] the powers are completely separated, even if Council of Ministers need the [[vote of confidence]] from both chambers of Parliament, that's however formed by a wide number of members (almost 1,000). A number of [[Latin America]]n countries have [[electoral branch]]es of government.

Countries with little separation of power include [[Politics of New Zealand|New Zealand]] and [[Politics of Canada|Canada]]. Canada makes limited use of separation of powers in practice, although in theory it distinguishes between branches of government. New Zealand also subscribes to the principle of 'Separation of Powers' through a series of constitutional safeguards. The Executive requires regular approval from the Legislature to carry out decisions. The Mixed Members Proportionate framework also caters for a coalition of parties to form government where a majority from a single party does not exist. The Judiciary is also free of government interference. If a series of judicial decisions result in an interpretation of the law which the Executive considers does not reflect the intention of the policy, the Executive can change the legislation. However, they can not direct or request a judicial officer to revise or reconsider a decision. These decisions are final. Should there be a dispute between the Executive and Judiciary, the Executive has no authority to direct the Judiciary, or its individual members. 

Complete separation-of-powers systems are almost always [[presidential]], although theoretically this need not be the case. There are a few historical exceptions, such as the [[French Directory|Directoire]] system of revolutionary France. [[Swiss politics|Switzerland]] offers an example of non-Presidential separation of powers today: It is run by a seven-member executive branch, the [[Swiss Federal Council|Federal Council]]. However, some might argue that Switzerland does not have a strong separation of powers system, as the Federal Council is appointed by parliament (but not dependent on parliament), and the judiciary has no power of review.

===Three branches===

====Australia====
{{Main|Separation of powers in Australia}}
[[Australia]] does not maintain a strict separation between the legislative and executive branches of government—indeed, government ministers are required to be a member of parliament—but the federal judiciary strictly guards its independence from the other two branches. However, under influence from the American constitution, the Australian constitution does define the three branches of government separately, and this has been interpreted by the judiciary to induce an implicit separation of powers. State governments have a similar level of separation of power, but this is generally on the basis of convention, rather than constitution.

====France====
{{Main|Government of France}}
{{Expand section|date=April 2009}}
The government of France is divided up into three branches:
* Executive. This includes the popularly elected [[President of France|president]] as well as the [[Prime minister of france|prime minister]] and cabinet.
* [[Parliament of France|Legislature]]. A bicameral legislature that includes the [[French Senate|Senate]] (upper house) and the [[National Assembly of France|National Assembly]] (lower house).
* [[Judiciary of France|Judiciary]]. This includes the judicial and administrative orders. It also includes a [[Constitutional Council of France|constitutional court]].

====Hong Kong====
[[Hong Kong]] is a [[Special administrative region|self-governing Chinese territory]] pursuant to the [[Sino-British Joint Declaration]], an international treaty registered with the [[United Nations]]. Currently, Hong Kong has three branches of government as codified in the [[Hong Kong Basic Law|Basic Law]], which preserves the political setup of the [[British Hong Kong|British colonial era]] under the doctrine of [[one country, two systems]]:
* [[Government of Hong Kong|Government]] - '''executive'''
* [[Legislative Council of Hong Kong|Legislative Council]] - '''legislature'''
* [[Judiciary of Hong Kong |Judiciary]] (Court of Final Appeal and other courts and tribunals) - '''judiciary'''

The [[Chief Executive of Hong Kong|Chief Executive]], elected by a 1200-member [[Election Committee]], is both head of the region and head of government, and chairs the [[Executive Council of Hong Kong|Executive Council]] which is composed of unofficial members and government secretaries. The law courts exercise the power of [[judicial review in Hong Kong|judicial review]] of [[constitutionality|constitutionality of legislation]] and [[Judicial review#Judicial review of administrative acts|administrative actions]], and emphasize the separation of powers in their rulings. The [[Chief Justice of the Court of Final Appeal|Chief Justice]] also stated this position in the ceremonial opening of the 2010 legal year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.info.gov.hk/gia/general/201001/11/P201001110174.htm|title=Chief Justice's Speech at Ceremonial Opening of the Legal Year 2010|publisher=Hong Kong Judiciary|date= |accessdate=2011-03-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, politically separation of powers is usually argued against, with the leaders of the People's Republic of China and supportive politicians publicly requesting for the three branches to cooperate and emphasizing an &quot;executive-led&quot; system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://globalasia.org/pdf/issue3/v2n2sing.pdf|title=Mature Enough for Democracy, And Sensible Too|publisher=Global Asia|date= |accessdate=2011-03-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====India====
{{Main|Constitution of India|Government of India}}
* [[Parliament]] - '''[[Legislative]]'''
* [[Prime Minister of India|Prime Minister]], [[Cabinet (government)|Cabinet]], Government Departments &amp; Civil Service - '''[[Executive (government)|Executive]]'''
* [[Supreme Court]] - '''[[Judicial]]'''
{{Expand section|date=December 2010}}
[[India]] follows a parliamentary system of government, which offers a clear separation of powers. The judiciary branch is fairly independent of the other two branches. Executive powers are vested with the President and Prime Minister, who are assisted by the [[Cabinet Secretary]] and other [[Secretary (government)|Secretaries]]. All three branches have &quot;'''checks and balances'''&quot; over each other to maintain the balance of POWER.

====United Kingdom====
{{main|Separation of powers in the United Kingdom}}
* Parliament - '''legislature'''
* Prime Minister, Cabinet, Government Departments &amp; Civil Service - '''executive'''
* Courts - '''judiciary'''

The development of the British constitution, which is not a [[codified]] document, is based on this fusion in the person of the Monarch, who has a formal role to play in the legislature (Parliament, which is where legal and political sovereignty lies, is the Crown-in-Parliament, and is summoned and dissolved by the Sovereign who must give his or her Royal Assent to all Bills so that they become Acts), the executive (the Sovereign appoints all ministers of His/Her Majesty's Government, who govern in the name of the Crown) and the judiciary (the Sovereign, as the fount of justice, appoints all senior judges, and all public prosecutions are brought in his or her name).

Although the [[doctrine]] of separation of power plays a role in the United Kingdom's constitutional doctrine, the UK constitution is often described as having &quot;a weak separation of powers&quot; [[A. V. Dicey]], despite its constitution being the one to which Montesquieu originally referred. For example, in the United Kingdom, the executive forms a subset of the legislature, as did—to a lesser extent—the judiciary until the establishment of the [[Supreme Court of the United Kingdom]]. The Prime Minister, the Chief Executive, sits as a member of the [[Parliament of the United Kingdom]], either as a peer in the [[House of Lords]] or as an elected member of the [[British House of Commons|House of Commons]] (by convention, and as a result of the supremacy of the Lower House, the Prime Minister now sits in the [[British House of Commons|House of Commons]]) and can effectively be removed from office by a simple majority vote. Furthermore, while the courts in the United Kingdom are undoubtedly amongst the most independent in the world, the [[Law Lords]], who were the final arbiters of judicial disputes in the UK sat simultaneously in the [[House of Lords]], the upper house of the legislature, although this arrangement ceased in 2009 when the [[Supreme Court of the United Kingdom]] came into existence. Furthermore, because of the existence of Parliamentary sovereignty, while the theory of separation of powers may be studied there, a system such as that of the UK is more accurately described as a &quot;[[fusion of powers]]&quot;.{{Citation needed|date=January 2009}}

Until 2005, the [[Lord Chancellor]] fused the Legislature, Executive and Judiciary, as he was the ex officio [[Lord Speaker|Speaker of the House of Lords]], a Government Minister who sat in [[Cabinet of the United Kingdom|Cabinet]] and was head of the [[Lord Chancellor's Department]] which administered the courts, the justice system and appointed judges, and was the head of the Judiciary in England and Wales and sat as a judge on the [[Judicial Committee of the House of Lords]], the highest domestic court in the entire United Kingdom, and the [[Judicial Committee of the Privy Council]], the senior tribunal court for parts of the Commonwealth. The [[Lord Chancellor]] also had certain other judicial positions, including being a judge in the Court of Appeal and President of the Chancery Division. The [[Lord Chancellor]] combines other aspects of the constitution, including having certain ecclesiastical functions of the [[Church of England|established state church]], making certain church appointments, nominations and sitting as one of the thirty-three Church Commissioners. These functions remain intact and unaffected by the [[Constitutional Reform Act 2005|Constitutional Reform Act]].  In 2005, the [[Constitutional Reform Act 2005|Constitutional Reform Act]] separated the powers with Legislative functions going to an elected [[Lord Speaker]] and the Judicial functions going to the [[Lord Chief Justice of England and Wales|Lord Chief Justice]]. The [[Lord Chancellor's Department]] was replaced with a [[Ministry of Justice]] and the [[Lord Chancellor]] currently serves in the position of [[Secretary of State for Justice]]. 

The judiciary has no power to strike down primary legislation, and can only rule on secondary legislation that it is invalid with regard to the primary legislation if necessary. Under [[parliamentary sovereignty]], [[Lords Spiritual and Temporal and Commons|Parliament]] can do whatever it wants and can overrule the judiciary and amend, repeal and introduce laws. A recent example, is when a court ruled that it was illegal for local authority councils to hold prayers before undertaking the council business (though part of the session) and the [[Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government]] signed a Parliamentary Order approved by Parliament, to overrule the court and legally allow all local authorities to hold prayers at sessions.

The British legal systems are based on [[common law]] traditions, which require:
* [[Police]] or [[Regulatory agency|regulators]] cannot initiate complaints under [[criminal law]] but can only investigate (prosecution is mostly reserved for the [[Crown Prosecution Service]]), which prevents [[selective enforcement]], e.g. the 'fishing expedition' which is often specifically forbidden.
* [[Prosecutor]]s cannot withhold evidence from [[Lawyer|counsel]] for the [[defendant]]; to do so results in [[trial#Mistrials|mistrial]] or dismissal. Accordingly, their relation to police is no advantage.
* [[Defendant]]s convicted can [[appeal (law)|appeal]], but only fresh and compelling evidence not available at trial can be introduced, restricting the power of the [[court of appeal]] to the process of law applied.

====United States====
{{Main|Separation of powers under the United States Constitution}}
In the United States Constitution, Article 1 Section I gives Congress only those &quot;legislative powers herein granted&quot; and proceeds to list those permissible actions in Article I Section 8, while Section 9 lists actions that are prohibited for Congress. The vesting clause in Article II places no limits on the Executive branch, simply stating that, &quot;The Executive Power shall be vested in a President of the United States of America.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.archives.gov/exhibits/charters/constitution.html Constitution of the United States]&lt;/ref&gt; The Supreme Court holds &quot;The judicial Power&quot; according to Article III, and it established the implication of [[Judicial review]] in Marbury vs Madison.&lt;ref&gt;Madison, James. (8 February 1788) [http://www.foundingfathers.info/federalistpapers/fed51.htm &quot;The Structure of the Government Must Furnish the Proper Checks and Balances Between the Different Departments&quot;] ''The Federalist Papers No. 51''&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Federal government of the United States|federal government]] refers to the branches as &quot;branches of government&quot;, while some systems use &quot;government&quot; to describe the executive. The Executive branch has attempted to claim power arguing for separation of powers to include being the Commander in Chief of a standing army since the [[American Civil War]], executive orders, emergency powers and security classifications since [[World War II]], national security, signing statements, and the scope of the [[Unitary executive theory|unitary executive]].

=====Checks and balances=====
To prevent one branch from becoming supreme, protect the &quot;opulent minority&quot; from the majority, and to induce the branches to cooperate, government systems that employ a separation of powers need a way to balance each of the branches. Typically this was accomplished through a system of &quot;'''checks and balances'''&quot;, the origin of which, like separation of powers itself, is specifically credited to [[Charles de Secondat, Baron de Montesquieu|Montesquieu]]. Checks and balances allow for a system based regulation that allows one branch to limit another, such as the power of Congress to alter the composition and jurisdiction of the federal courts. 

{|
! width=&quot;33%&quot; | [[Legislature|Legislative]] (Congress)
! width=&quot;33%&quot; | [[Executive (government)|Executive]] (President)
! width=&quot;33%&quot; | [[Judiciary|Judicial]] (Supreme Court)
|-
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
* Passes bills; has broad [[Taxing and Spending Clause|taxing and spending power]]; controls the [[United States federal budget|federal budget]]; has power to borrow money on the credit of the United States (may be vetoed by President, but [[Veto override|vetoes may be overridden]] with a two-thirds vote of both houses)
* Has sole power to [[Declaration of war by the United States|declare war]], as well as to raise, support, and regulate the [[U.S._Military|military]].
* Oversees, investigates, and makes the rules for the government and its officers.
* Defines by law the jurisdiction of the federal judiciary in cases not specified by the Constitution
* Ratification of treaties signed by the President and gives [[advice and consent]] to presidential appointments to the [[United States federal courts|federal judiciary]], [[United States federal executive departments|federal executive departments]], and other posts (Senate only)
* Has sole power of [[Impeachment in the United States|impeachment]] (House of Representatives) and trial of impeachments (Senate); can remove federal executive and judicial officers from office for [[high crimes and misdemeanors]]
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
* Is the [[commander-in-chief]] of the [[United States armed forces|armed forces]]
* Executes the instructions of Congress.
* May veto bills passed by Congress (but the veto may be overridden by a two-thirds majority of both houses)
* Executes the spending authorized by Congress.
* Declares states of emergency and publishes regulations and [[Executive order (United States)|executive orders]].
* Makes executive agreements (does not require ratification) and signs treaties (ratification requiring by two-thirds of the Senate)
* Makes appointments to the federal judiciary, [[United States federal executive departments|federal executive departments]], and other posts with the advice and consent of the Senate. Has power to make [[Recess appointment|temporary appointment during the recess of the Senate]]
* Has the power to grant &quot;reprieves and pardons for offenses against the United States, except in cases of impeachment.&quot;
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
* Determines which laws Congress intended to apply to any given case
* Exercises [[Judicial review in the United States|judicial review]], reviewing the constitutionality of laws
* Determines how Congress meant the law to apply to disputes
* Determines how a law acts to determine the disposition of prisoners
* Determines how a law acts to compel testimony and the production of evidence
* Determines how laws should be interpreted to assure uniform policies in a top-down fashion via the appeals process, but gives discretion in individual cases to low-level judges. The amount of discretion depends upon the [[standard of review]], determined by the type of case in question.
* Federal judges [[Life tenure|serve for life]]
|}

===Other systems===

====Belgium====
[[Belgium]] is currently a federated state that has imposed the trias politica on different governmental levels. The constitution of 1831, considered one of the most liberal of its time for limiting the powers of its monarch and imposing a rigorous system of separation of powers, is based on three principles:

'''Trias Politica (horizontal separation of powers):'''
*The legislative power is attributed to an elected parliamentary body elected with a representative general election system (one person one vote).
*The executive power is attributed to the Council of Ministers. Ministers are appointed by the King, usually from the elected members of parliament (non-elected people can also be nominated). However, they must first resign from their elected seat.
*The judicial power is in the hands of the courts. Magistrates are nominated by the minister (on proposal from a Council of the Magistrates).
**Magistrates can be nominated to become a judge (sitting magistrates) or instructing judge (investigating judge) of Procureur (public prosecutor) (the standing magistrates).
**The executive branch of the government is responsible to provide the physical means to execute its role (infrastructure, staff, financial means).
**Judges and some other people cannot run for elected office while they are nominated to certain positions (military, police-officers, clergy, notaries, bailiffs).

'''Subsidiarity (vertical separation of powers):'''
*Supranational directives (EU legislation) and international treaties are subjected to approval of the federal level (the federal level being Belgium the nation state)
*The federal level is composed of the following:
**A bicameral parliament (House of Representative and Senate) (in 2014 this will be a directly elected house and an indirectly appointed Senate of the regions)
**A federal government (lead by the Prime Minister and the ministers and secretaries of state)
****Tasked with overseeing justice, defense, foreign affairs, and social security, public health
**High Court, constitutional Court, Cassation Court
*The regional level is composed of the following:
**A monocameral parliament
**A regional government led by the minister-president (ministers and secretaries of state) is tasked with regional matters.
*Provinces also have similar structures:
**A monocameral provincial council
**A provincial governor assisted by deputies and arrondissements commissars is tasked with provincial matters.
**Appellate Court, Assisses Court
*City and communal entities:
**A city or communal council composed of a mayor, assisted by aldermen, is tasked with local matters.
**Magistrates Court, Correctional Court (three judges).
**Justice of the peace and Police Court judges (single judge courts)

'''Secularism (separation of state and religion):'''
*The king, the head of state, holds no political authority and requires executive approval by a minister for every action and statement; he nominates the ministers but he does not choose them (his executive powers); he signs and decrees the laws voted in parliament (his legislative powers);
*The head of state is commander in chief of the military (in title only), politically the military depends of the Minister of Defense and the chiefs of staff are responsible towards parliament and take their orders from the Minister of Defense and the government;
*Certain functions are deemed incompatible and people must to resign from their function if they want to assume responsibilities in another function (military commanders have never been government ministers, even during a war)

====Costa Rica====
In the aftermath of the [[Costa Rican Civil War|44-day civil war]] in 1948 (after former President and incumbent candidate Rafael Álgel Calderón Guardia tried to take power through fraud, by not recognising the results of the presidential election that he had lost), the question of which transformational model the Costa Rican State would follow was the main issue that confronted the victors. A Constituent Assembly was elected by popular vote to draw up a new constitution, enacted in 1949, and remains in force. This document was an edit of the constitution of 1871, as the constituent assembly rejected more radical corporatist ideas proposed by the ruling Junta Fundadora de la Segunda República (which, although having come to power by military force, abolished the armed forces). Nonetheless, the new constitution increased centralization of power at the expense of municipalities and eliminated provincial government altogether, at the time it increased the powers of congress and the judiciary.

It established the three supreme powers as the '''legislature''', '''executive''', and '''judicial''' branches, but also created two other autonomous state organs that have equivalent power, but not equivalent rank. The first is the [[Supreme Elections Tribunal]] ('''electoral''' branch) which controls elections and makes unique, unappealable decisions on their outcomes.

The second is the office of the [[Comptroller General]] ('''audit''' branch), an autonomous and independent organ nominally subordinate to the unicameral legislative assembly. All budgets of ministries and municipalities must pass through this agency, including the execution of budget items such as contracting for routine operations. The Comptroller also provides financial vigilance over government offices and office holders, and routinely brings actions to remove mayors for malfeasance, firmly establishing this organization as the fifth branch of the Republic

====European Union====
First, note that the [[European Union]] is a supranational polity, and is neither a country nor a federation; but as the EU wields political power and is fully aware of its &quot;democratic deficit&quot;, it attempts to comply with the principle of separation of powers. There are seven [[institutions of the European Union]]. In intergovernmental matters, most power is concentrated in the [[Council of the European Union]] – giving it the characteristics of a normal [[international organization]]. Here, all power at the EU level is in one branch. In the latter there are four main actors. The [[European Commission]] acts as an independent executive which is appointed by the Council in conjunction with the European Parliament; but the Commission also has a legislative role as the sole initiator of EU legislation. An early maxim was: &quot;The Commission proposes and the Council disposes&quot;; and although the EU's lawmaking procedure is now much more complicated, this simple maxim still holds some truth. As well as both executive and legislative functions, the Commission arguably exercises a third, quasi-judicial, function under Articles 101 &amp; 102 TFEU (competition law ); although the ECJ remains the final arbiter. The [[European Parliament]] is one half of the legislative branch and is directly elected. The Council itself acts both as the second half of the legislative branch and also holds some executive functions (some of which are exercised by the related [[European Council]] in practice). The [[European Court of Justice]] acts as the independent judicial branch, interpreting EU law and treaties. The remaining institution, the [[European Court of Auditors]], is an independent audit authority (due to the sensitive nature of fraud in the EU).
* [[Council of the European Union]] – '''legislative and executive'''
* [[European Commission]] – '''executive, legislative and quasi-judicial'''
* [[European Council]] – '''executive'''
* [[European Court of Auditors]] – '''audit'''
* [[European Court of Justice]] – '''judicial'''
* [[European Parliament]] – '''legislative'''

====Germany====
The three branches in German government are further divided into six main bodies enshrined in the [[Basic Law for the Federal Republic of Germany]]:
* Federal '''President''' (''[[President of Germany|Bundespräsident]]'') - '''executive'''
* Federal Cabinet (''[[Bundesregierung]]'') - '''executive'''
* Federal Diet (''[[Bundestag]]'') &amp; Federal Council (''[[Bundesrat of Germany|Bundesrat]]'') - '''legislative'''
* Federal Assembly (''[[Bundesversammlung (Germany)|Bundesversammlung]]'') - '''presidential electoral college''' (consisting of the members of the Bundestag and electors from the [[States of Germany|constituent states]])
* Federal '''Constitutional Court''' (''[[Bundesverfassungsgericht]]'') - '''judiciary'''

Besides the constitutional court the '''judicial''' branch at the federal level is made up of five supreme courts&amp;nbsp;— one for civil and criminal cases (''Bundesgerichtshof''), and one each for administrative, tax, labour, and social security issues. There are also state (''[[States of Germany|Länder / Bundesländer]]'') based courts beneath them, and a rarely used senate of the supreme courts.

====Hungary====
The four independent branches of power in Hungary (the parliament, the government, the court system, and the office of the public accuser) are divided into six bodies:
* Parliament ([[Magyar Országgyűlés]]): elected every 4 years by the people in a highly complex, two-round voting system
* Government (Magyar Kormány): installed and removed by 50%+1 basic majority vote of the parliament, 4 year terms
* Supreme Court (Legfelsőbb Bíróság): Chief justice elected by qualified (2/3) majority of the parliament, no government oversight
* Constitutional court (Alkotmánybíróság): members elected by qualified majority of the parliament for 8 years, this body nullifies laws and has no government oversight.
* Chief public accuser (Legfőbb ügyész): elected by qualified majority of the parliament, 6 year terms, office budget fixed, no government oversight.
* The President of the Republic (Köztársasági Elnök) is elected by qualified majority of the Hungarian parliament for 5 year terms (cannot be reelected more than once). He/she has ceremonial powers only, signs laws into power and commands the military in time of peace.

The independent pillar status of the Hungarian public accuser's office is a unique construction, loosely modeled on the system Portugal introduced after the 1974 victory of the [[Carnation Revolution]]. The public accuser (attorney general) body has became the fourth column of Hungarian democracy only in recent times: after communism fell in 1989, the office was made independent by a new clausule XI. of the Constitution. The change was meant to prevent abuse of state power, especially with regards to the use of false accusations against opposition politicians, who may be excluded from elections if locked in protracted or excessively severe court cases.

To prevent the Hungarian accuser's office from neglecting its duties, natural human private persons can submit investigation requests, called &quot;pótmagánvád&quot; directly to the courts, if the accusers' office refuses to do its job. Courts will decide if the allegations have merit and order police to act in lieu of the accuser's office if warranted. In its decision No.42/2005 the Hungarian constitutional court declared that the government does not enjoy such privilege and the state is powerless to further pursue cases if the public accuser refuses to do so.

====Republic of China (Taiwan)====
{{main|Government of the Republic of China}}
According to [[Sun Yat-sen]]'s idea of &quot;[[Five-Power Constitution|separation of the five powers]]&quot;, the government of the Republic of China has five branches:
*[[Executive Yuan]] - led by the [[Premier of the Republic of China|premier]] but in actuality it is the [[President of the Republic of China|president]] who sets policy - '''executive'''
*[[Legislative Yuan]] - [[unicameral]] - '''legislature'''
*[[Judicial Yuan]] - its Constitutional Court (highest) and [[Supreme Court of the Republic of China|Supreme Court]] have different jurisdictions - '''judiciary'''
*[[Control Yuan]] - '''audit''' branch
*[[Examination Yuan]] - '''civil service personnel management''' and human resources

The president and [[Vice President of the Republic of China|vice president]] as well as the defunct [[National Assembly of the Republic of China|National Assembly]] are constitutionally not part of the above five branches. Before being abolished in 2005, the National Assembly was a [[Constitutional convention (political meeting)|constitutional convention]] and [[electoral college]] for the president and vice president. Its constitutional amending powers were passed to the legislative yuan and its electoral powers were passed to the electorate.

The relationship between the executive and legislative branches are poorly defined. An example of the problems this causes is the near complete political paralysis that results when the president, who has neither the power to veto nor the ability to dissolve the legislature and call new elections, cannot negotiate with the legislature when his party is in the minority.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fpri.org/enotes/asia.20020418.rigger.taiwanpoliticalparalysis.html |title=E-Notes: Why Taiwan's Political Paralysis Persists&amp;nbsp;— FPRI |publisher=Fpri.org |date= |accessdate=2008-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; The examination and control yuans are marginal branches; their leaders as well as the leaders of the executive and judicial yuans are appointed by the president and confirmed by the legislative yuan. The legislature is the only branch that chooses its own leadership. The vice president has practically no responsibilities.

==See also==
* [[Autocracy|Absolute power]]
* [[Balance of power (federalism)]]
* [[Consociationalism|Power sharing]]
* [[Constitution of the Roman Republic]]
* [[Constitutionalism]]
* [[Constitutional economics]]
* [[Corruption Perceptions Index]] - Parliamentary systems are, in general, perceived as less corrupt than other systems
* [[Fourth Estate]], the press
* [[Fifth power]]
* [[Fusion of powers]]
* [[Independence of the judiciary]]
* [[Judicial activism]]
* [[Legal reform]]
* [[Mixed government]]
* [[Philosophy of law]]
* [[Portal:Politics|List of democracy and elections-related topics]]
* [[Pith and substance]]
* [[Reserve power]] - powers exercisable by the head of state without the approval of another branch of the government
* [[Rule of Law]]
* [[Rule According to Higher Law]]
* [[Separation of duties]]
* [[Signing statement]]
* [[Unitary executive theory]]

==References==
{{More footnotes|date=July 2009}}
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Further reading==
* Peter Barenboim, ''[http://www.florentine-society.ru/pdf/Biblical_Roots_of_Separation_of_Powers.pdf Biblical Roots of Separation of Powers]'', Moscow, Letny Sad, 2005. ISBN 5-94381-123-0, Permalink: http://lccn.loc.gov/2006400578
* Biancamaria Fontana (ed.), ''[http://www.cambridge.org/us/catalogue/catalogue.asp?isbn=0521033764 The Invention of the Modern Republic]'' (2007) ISBN 978-0-521-03376-3
* W. B. Gwyn, ''The Meaning of the Separation of Powers'' (1965) (no ISBN)
* Bernard Manin, ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=GhAJ2x2coEoC Principles of Representative Government]'' (1995; English version 1997) ISBN 0-521-45258-9 (hbk), ISBN 0-521-45891-9 (pbk)
* José María Maravall and [[Adam Przeworski]] (eds), ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=EMB-F6Forx8C Democracy and the Rule of Law]'' (2003) ISBN 0-521-82559-8 (hbk), ISBN 0-521-53266-3 (pbk)
* Paul A. Rahe, [http://www.hillsdalesites.org/personal/prahe/logicofliberty.html ''Montesquieu and the Logic of Liberty''] (2009) ISBN 978-0-300-14125-2 (hbk), ISBN 978-0-300-16808-2 (pbk)
* Iain Stewart, [http://www.law.mq.edu.au/html/MqLJ/volume4/vol4_stewarti.pdf &quot;Men of Class: Aristotle, Montesquieu and Dicey on 'Separation of Powers' and 'The Rule of Law'&quot;] (2004)
* Iain Stewart, [http://ouclf.iuscomp.org/articles/montesquieu.shtml &quot;Montesquieu in England: his 'Notes on England', with Commentary and Translation&quot;] (2002).
* [[Alec Stone Sweet]], ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=61AzsGk7EW0C Governing with Judges: Constitutional Politics in Europe]'' (2000) ISBN 978-0-19-829730-7
* M. J. C. Vile, ''[http://oll.libertyfund.org/Home3/Book.php?recordID=0024 Constitutionalism and the Separation of Powers]'' (1967, Indianapolis: Liberty Fund, 1998) Second edition. ISBN 0-86597-174-9 (hbk), ISBN 0-86597-175-7 (pbk)
* [http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1294671 Steven G. Calabresi, Debate, ''The Great Divorce: The Current Understanding of Separation of Powers and the Original Meaning of the Incompatibility Clause'', 157 '''U. Pa. L. Rev. PENNumbra''' 134 (2008).]
* [http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1099355 ''Why Our Next President May Keep His or Her Senate Seat: A Conjecture on the Constitution's Incompatibility Clause'', 4 '''Duke J. Const. L. &amp; Pub. Pol'y''' 107 (2009).]
* [http://scholarship.law.duke.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1038&amp;context=djclpp Saikrishna Bangalore Prakash, ''Why the Incompatibility Clause Applies to the Office of President'', 4 '''Duke J. Const. L. &amp; Pub. Pol'y''' 143 (2009).]

==External links==
*[http://www.mlloyd.org/mdl-indx/polybius/intro.htm Polybius and the Founding Fathers: the separation of powers]
*[http://www.bartleby.com/43/9.html Arbitrary Government Described and the Government of the Massachusetts Vindicated from that Aspersion (1644)]
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2011}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Separation Of Powers}}
[[Category:Constitutional law]]
[[Category:Philosophy of law]]
[[Category:Separation of powers|*]]
[[Category:Political science terms]]

[[ace:Trias politica]]
[[af:Trias politica]]
[[ar:فصل السلطات]]
[[an:División de Poders]]
[[ast:Separtación de poderes]]
[[zh-min-nan:Hun-koân]]
[[be:Падзяленне ўлады]]
[[be-x-old:Падзяленьне ўлады]]
[[bg:Разделение на властите]]
[[ca:Separació de poders]]
[[cs:Dělba moci]]
[[da:Magtadskillelse]]
[[de:Gewaltenteilung]]
[[et:Võimude lahusus]]
[[el:Διάκριση των εξουσιών]]
[[es:Separación de poderes]]
[[eo:Disigo de povoj]]
[[fa:اصل تفکیک قوا]]
[[fr:Séparation des pouvoirs]]
[[ko:권력 분립]]
[[hi:शक्तियों का पृथक्करण]]
[[hr:Dioba vlasti]]
[[id:Pemisahan kekuasaan]]
[[is:Skipting ríkisvaldsins]]
[[it:Separazione dei poteri]]
[[he:הפרדת הרשויות]]
[[jv:Pamisahan kakuwasan]]
[[sw:Mgawanyo wa madaraka]]
[[la:Trias politica]]
[[lv:Valsts varas dalīšana]]
[[lt:Valdžių padalijimo principas]]
[[hu:Hatalmi ágak szétválasztása]]
[[mk:Поделба на власта]]
[[ml:അധികാര പൃഥക്കരണം]]
[[ms:Pembahagian kuasa]]
[[nl:Trias politica]]
[[ja:権力分立]]
[[no:Maktfordelingsprinsippet]]
[[nn:Maktfordelingsprinsippet]]
[[oc:Separacion dels poders]]
[[nds:Scheden vun de Mächt]]
[[pl:Podział władz]]
[[pt:Teoria da separação dos poderes]]
[[ro:Separarea puterilor]]
[[qu:Kimsantin atiy]]
[[ru:Разделение властей]]
[[simple:Separation of powers]]
[[sk:Deľba moci]]
[[sl:Ločitev oblasti]]
[[sr:Подјела власти]]
[[sh:Podjela vlasti]]
[[fi:Vallan kolmijako-oppi]]
[[sv:Maktdelningsprincipen]]
[[tl:Paghihiwalay ng mga kapangyarihan]]
[[ta:அதிகாரங்களைப் பிரித்துவைத்தல்]]
[[th:การแบ่งแยกอำนาจ]]
[[tr:Kuvvetler ayrılığı]]
[[uk:Розділення влади]]
[[vi:Tam quyền phân lập]]
[[war:Pagbulagbulag han gahom]]
[[yi:רעגירונגס מאכט אבטייל]]
[[zh:權力分立]]</text>
      <sha1>57n1l8h6rhwd4vcu6tsg1rv0svpz75a</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
