<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Settler colonialism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>10144455</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521969813</id>
      <parentid>521967816</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-08T09:09:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Dating maintenance tags: {{Merge}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12424">{{merge|Settler|date=November 2012}}
{{Expand German|Grenzkolonisation|date=June 2011}}
{{Multiple issues|refimprove = May 2008|POV = April 2009|original research = September 2010}}

'''Settler [[colonialism]]''' is a specific colonial formation whereby foreign family units move into a region and reproduce. Land is thus the key resource in settler colonies, whereas natural (e.g. gold, cotton, oil) and human (e.g. labour, existing trade networks, convertible souls) resources are the main motivation behind other forms of colonialism. Normal colonialism typically ends, whereas settler colonialism lasts forever, except in the rare event of complete evacuation (''e.g.'', the [[Lost Colony of Roanoke]]) or settler [[decolonization]]. The historian of race and settler colonialism Patrick Wolfe writes that &quot;settler colonialism destroys to replace&quot; and insists that &quot;invasion&quot;, in settler colonial contexts, is &quot;a structure, not an event&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Patrick Wolfe, &quot;Settler Colonialism and the Elimination of the Native&quot;, Journal of Genocide Research, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

This definition, by contrast, comes from the Settler Colonial Studies website:&lt;ref&gt;http://settlercolonialstudies.org/about-this-blog/ Settler Colonial Studies&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|Settler colonialism is a global and transnational phenomenon, and as much a thing of the past as a thing of the present. There is no such thing as neo-settler colonialism or post-settler colonialism because settler colonialism is a resilient formation that rarely ends. Not all migrants are settlers: settlers come to stay, and are founders of political orders who carry with them a distinct sovereign capacity. And settler colonialism is not colonialism: settlers want Indigenous people to vanish (but can make use of their labour before they are made to disappear). Sometimes settler colonial forms operate within colonial ones, sometimes they subvert them, sometimes they replace them. But even if colonialism and settler colonialism interpenetrate and overlap, they remain separate as they co-define each other.}}

==In the ancient world==
Settler colonialism has occurred extensively throughout human history, including in the ancient world.

===Hellenes===
{{Expand section|date=December 2009}}
Greek settlers cloned their city-states through much of the coastlines of the Mediterranean. Under the [[Macedonian Empire]], the Hellenistic pattern of settler colonies extended deep into Asia.  However, many of the people living in these cities were non-ethnic Greeks who had adopted the dominant [[Ancient Greek language]] and its concomitant [[Hellenistic civilization]].

===Rome===
The [[Roman Republic]] and later the [[Roman Empire]] commonly established settler colonies in newly conquered regions.  The colonists in these colonies were often veterans of the Roman army, who received agricultural land to develop.  These agricultural communities provided bastions of loyal citizens in often hostile areas of the Empire, and often accelerated the process of Romanisation among the nearby conquered peoples.  For examples of such  colonies: near the city of [[Damascus]] in present-day [[Syria]], the contemporary settlements of Mezze and Deraya can trace their origins back to villages opened for settlement by the Romans during the third century CE.  [[Philip the Arab]], the Roman Emperor from 244 to 249 designated this area around Damascus a ''colonia'', and encouraged settlement by veterans of the VI Ferrata legion, as commemorated by coins minted in the city around this time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Burns|first=Ross|title=Damascus: a history|publisher=Routledge|pages=76, 85|isbn=978-0-415-27105-9}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

==In early modern and modern times==
During the [[early modern period]], some European [[nation-states]] and their agents adopted policies of [[colonialism]], competing with each other to establish colonies outside of Europe, at first in the Americas, and later in Asia, Africa, and Oceania.


{{further information|[[Indian removal]]}}
[[File:Colonization of America (Continent) 1750.PNG|right|300px|thumb|Territories in the Americas colonized by a European [[great power]] in 1750]]
{{Expand section|date=December 2010}}

===Settler colonialism in Oceania===
Europeans came and settled in Australia, in many cases displacing [[Indigenous Australians]]. The Indigenous Australian population, estimated at about 350,000 at the time of European settlement,&lt;ref&gt;Smith, L. (1980), The Aboriginal Population of Australia, [[Australian National University]] Press, Canberra&lt;/ref&gt; declined steeply for 150 years following settlement from 1788, mainly because of [[infectious disease]] combined with forced re-settlement and cultural disintegration. The [[Stolen Generations|removal of children]], that historians and Indigenous Australians have portrayed as [[Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide|genocide]],&lt;ref&gt;Tatz, C. (1999). ''[http://www.aiatsis.gov.au/rsrch/rsrch_dp/genocide.htm Genocide in Australia]'', [[Australian Institute of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Studies|AIATSIS]] Research Discussion Papers No 8, Australian Institute of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Studies, Canberra&lt;/ref&gt;
may have made a contribution to the decline in the indigenous population. Such interpretations of Aboriginal history are disputed by some, such as Keith Windshuttle, as being exaggerated or fabricated for political or ideological reasons.&lt;ref&gt;Windschuttle, K. (2001). ''[http://www.newcriterion.com/archive/20/sept01/keith.htm# The Fabrication of Aboriginal History]'', ''[[The New Criterion]]'' Vol. 20, No. 1, September 20&lt;/ref&gt; This debate is known within Australia as the [[History wars|History Wars]]. Following the [[Australian referendum, 1967 (Aboriginals)|1967 referendum]], the Federal government gained the power to implement policies and make laws with respect to Aborigines. Traditional ownership of land — [[native title]] — in Australia first gained legal recognition in 1992, when the [[High Court of Australia|High Court]] case ''[[Mabo v Queensland|Mabo v Queensland (No 2)]]'' overturned the notion of Australia as ''[[terra nullius]]'' at the time of European occupation.

=== Settler colonialism in Africa ===
{{see|Pied noir}} and {{see|Afrikaners}}

=== Settler colonialism in Asia ===
Jews have lived in Palestine continuously since ancient times, particularly in the Four Holy Cities: [[Jerusalem]], [[Safed]], [[Tiberias]] and [[Hebron]].&lt;ref&gt;The Jerusalem Cathedra &quot;Building the Land: Stages in First Aliya Colonization (1882-1904)&quot; Yad Izhak Ben Zvi &amp; Wayne State University Press, No. 3, 1983.&lt;/ref&gt;
Nevertheless, founders of [[Zionism]] such as [[Theodore Herzl]] and [[Ahad Ha'am]] envisaged colonising from the outset. In 1967 the French historian [[Maxime Rodinson]] wrote an article later translated and published in English as ''Israel: A Colonial Settler-State?''&lt;ref&gt;Rodinson, Maxime. &quot;Israel, fait colonial?&quot; ''Les Temps Moderne'', 1967. Republished in English as ''Israel: A Colonial Settler-State?'', New York, Monad Press, 1973.
&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Lorenzo Veracini]] treats Israel's colonial nature as a given and writes that Jewish settlers could expel the British in 1948 only because they had their own colonial relationships inside and outside Israel's new borders.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Israel could celebrate its anticolonial/anti-British struggle exactly [http://www.borderlands.net.au/vol6no2_2007/veracini_settler.htm because it was able to establish a number of colonial relationships within and without the borders of 1948.&quot;] Lorenzo Veracini, Borderlands, vol 6 No 2, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
Veracini believes the possibility of an Israeli disengagement is always latent and this relationship could be severed, through an &quot;[[One state solution|accommodation of a Palestinian Israeli autonomy within the institutions of the Israeli state]]&quot; (Veracini 2006)&lt;ref&gt;Veracini, Lorenzo, &quot;Israel and Settler Society&quot;, London: Pluto Press. 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
Other scholars, such as [[Daiva Stasiulis]] and [[Nira Yuval-Davis]],&lt;ref&gt;
[http://search.barnesandnoble.com/Unsettling-Settler-Societies/Daiva-K-Stasiulis/e/9780803986947 Unsettling Settler Societies: Articulations of Gender, Race, Ethnicity and Class, Vol. 11], Nira Yuval-Davis (Editor), Daiva K Stasiulis (Editor), Paperback 352pp, ISBN 978-0-8039-8694-7, August 1995 SAGE Publications.&lt;/ref&gt;
and [[Joseph Massad]] in the &quot;Post Colonial Colony: time, space and bodies in Palestine/ Israel in the persistence of the Palestinian Question&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Post Colonial Colony: time, space and bodies in Palestine/ Israel in the persistence of the Palestinian Question&quot;, Routledge, NY, (2006) and &quot;The Pre-Occupation of Post-Colonial Studies&quot; ed. Fawzia Afzal-Khan and Kalpana Rahita Seshadri. (Durham: Duke University Press)
&lt;/ref&gt;
have included Israel in their global analysis of settler societies.

Some [[Palestinian people|Palestinian]]s express similar opinions - writer and [[sociologist]] [[Jamil Hilal]], member of the [[Palestinian National Council]] lives in what he describes as &quot;the heavily-colonised [[West Bank]]&quot;, and drew parallels in 1976 between South African and Israeli settler colonialism, noting that &quot;as in [[Southern Africa]], stretches of land were acquired by the Zionist settlers [...] and their [[Arab]] tenants thrown out&quot;. Hilal also argues that the defence industries of the two nations collaborated against the sanctions on South Africa, especially on their respective nuclear programs in the 1980s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://archive.lib.msu.edu/DMC/African%20Journals/pdfs/Utafiti/vol1no1/aejp001001004.pdf &quot;IMPERIALISM AND SETTLER-COLONIALISM IN WEST ASIA: ISRAEL AND THE ARAB PALESTINIAN STRUGGLE.&quot;] Jamil Hilal, UTAFITI journal of the arts and social sciences, University of Dar Es Salaam. 1976.&lt;/ref&gt; Former Palestinian Foreign Minister Dr. Nasser al-Qidwa opposes the policy of Israeli settlements and has described those efforts as colonialism.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jmcc.org/debate/06/nov/nasserqidwa.htm &quot;a classical colonialist phenomenon&quot;] Speech: Dr. Nasser al-Qidwa, former Palestinian Foreign Minister, Jerusalem Media &amp; Communication Centre, November 2006.
&lt;/ref&gt;

Ambassador [[Rastam Mohd Isa]], former permanent representative of [[Malaysia]] to the [[United Nations]], speaking on behalf of the [[non-aligned movement]] (NAM) in 2003 expressed grave concern about &quot;the continuing and escalating [[Israeli military]] campaign ... excessive and indiscriminate use of force, and ''continuing settler colonial activities''&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;... Israeli military campaign ... excessive and indiscriminate use of force, [http://www.un.int/malaysia/NAM/SC14Octo3NAM.html and ''continuing settler colonial activities''&quot;] STATEMENT TO THE UNITED NATIONS, Situation in the Middle East - Palestine, Malaysian Permanent Representative [[Rastam Mohd Isa]] speaking to the UN on behalf of the non-aligned movement 2003.
&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Expansionism]]
* [[Lebensraum]]
* [[Human migration]]
* [[Overpopulation]]
* [[Imperialism]]
* [[Indian removal]]
* [[List of diasporas]]

==Further reading==
* {{cite book|last= Belich|first= James|authorlink= James Belich (historian)|title=Replenishing the earth : the settler revolution and the rise of the Anglo-world, 1783-1939|url= http://books.google.com/books?id=Rh76bzOX7XAC|accessdate=2009-12-18|year= 2009
|publisher= Oxford University Press|location= Oxford|isbn= 978-0-19-929727-6|pages= 573}}
*''Settler Colonialism in the Twentieth Century'' (edited by [[Susan Pedersen (historian)|Susan Pedersen]] and [[Caroline Elkins]], Routledge, 2005)
* [http://www.jcpa.org/JCPA/Templates/ShowPage.asp?DRIT=2&amp;DBID=1&amp;LNGID=1&amp;TMID=111&amp;FID=378&amp;PID=0&amp;IID=3472&amp;TTL=Is_Israel_a_Colonial_State?_The_Political_Psychology_of_Palestinian_Nomenclature Irwin J. Mansdorf: Is Israel a Colonial State?] [http://www.jcpa.org Jerusalem Center for Public Affairs]
* {{cite book|last=Veracini|first= Lorenzo|title=Settler Colonialism: A Theoretical Overview|year= 2010|publisher= Palgrave MacMillan|location= Hampshire, UK|isbn= 978023022097 {{Please check ISBN|reason=Invalid length.}} |{{Please check ISBN|reason=Invalid length.}}|pages= 182}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Colonialism}}
{{Colonization}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Settler Colonialism}}
[[Category:Colonialism]]
[[Category:Cultural geography]]

[[de:Grenzkolonisation]]
[[fr:Colonie de peuplement]]
[[ru:Переселенческий колониализм]]
[[fi:Siirtokunta]]</text>
      <sha1>swik6yeqgxytj5urwywlfh2fxysumnk</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
