<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Single-issue politics</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>822310</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519242658</id>
      <parentid>518707315</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-22T18:07:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Wbm1058</username>
        <id>14383484</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>[[Green parties]]—don't pipe it, [[cannabis political parties]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="5194">{{Unreferenced|date=August 2008}}

'''Single-issue politics''' involves political [[Political campaign|campaign]]ing or political support based on one essential [[policy]] area or idea.

==Political expression==

One weakness of such an approach is that effective [[political party|political parties]] are usually [[coalition]]s of [[Political factions|faction]]s or [[advocacy group]]s. Bringing together political forces based on a single intellectual or cultural common denominator can be unrealistic; though there may be considerable [[public opinion]] on one side of an argument, it does not necessarily follow that mobilizing under that one banner will bring results. A '''defining issue''' may indeed come to dominate one particular electoral campaign, sufficiently to swing the result. Imposing such an issue may well be what single-issue politics concern; but for the most part success is rather limited, and electorates choose governments for reasons with a broader base.

Single-issue politics may express itself through the formation of a single-issue party, an approach that tends to be more successful in [[parliamentary system]]s based on [[proportional representation]] than in rigid [[two-party system]]s (like that of the [[United States]]). Alternatively, it may proceed through political [[advocacy group]]s of various kinds, including Lobby groups, pressure groups and other forms of political expression external to normal [[representative government]]. Within a broad-based party it may be the concern of a '''single-issue [[caucus]]'''.

Very visible as it was in [[Western world|Western]] democracies in the second half of the twentieth century, single-issue politics is hardly a new phenomenon. In the 1880s, the third government of [[William Ewart Gladstone]] made [[British politics]] in practical terms single-issue, around the [[Home Rule Bill]], leading to a split of the [[Liberal Party (UK)|Liberal Party]].

==Groups and voters==

Single-issue politics are a form of [[litmus test (politics)|litmus test]]; common examples are [[abortion]], [[taxation]], [[animal rights]], [[environment (biophysical)|environment]], and [[gun politics]]. The [[National Rifle Association]] in the United States, which has only one specific interest, is an example of a single-issue group. What differentiates single-issue groups from other interest groups is their intense style of lobbying. 

The term ''single-issue voter'' has been used to describe people who may make voting decisions based on the candidates' stance on a single issue (e.g. &quot;pro-life&quot; or &quot;pro-choice&quot;, support for gun rights or gun-control). The existence of single-issue voters can give a distorted impression: a candidate's overall views may not enjoy the same support. For example, a person who votes for a socially conservative Republican candidate, based solely on his or her support of gun rights, may not necessarily share the candidate's other views on social issues, such as abortion or [[family values]].

==Single-issue parties==

A '''single-issue party''' is a [[political party]] that campaigns on only one issue. Such a party is rarely successful in gaining elected office. 

It is generally believed that single-issue parties are favoured by [[voluntary voting system]]s, as they tend to attract very committed supporters who will always vote. Through systems like [[instant runoff voting]] and [[proportional representation]] they can have substantial influence on the results of elections. [[First past the post]] voting systems tend to nullify their influence. 

In instant-runoff electoral systems which allow unsuccessful parties to designate where their votes are redistributed, single-issue parties may be formed as a way to funnel more votes to another candidate with quite different policies. For instance, in the [[New South Wales state election, 1999]], one candidate who received just 0.2% of the primary vote achieved the quota of 4.5% required to win a Legislative Council seat after receiving preferences from a wide range of minor parties (including both the 'Gun Owners and Sporting Hunters Rights Party' and the 'Animal Liberation Party'); MLC [[Lee Rhiannon]] accused many of these parties of being nothing more than fronts..[http://www.parliament.nsw.gov.au/prod/parlment/hanstrans.nsf/V3ByKey/LC19991110]

Some examples of single-issue parties are the former Greedy 40% Extra party formed to protest against the increase in politician wages, the [[Bloc Québécois]] party in [[Canada]], formed to call for the separation of [[Quebec]], and the [[Party for the Animals]], which gained two seats in the [[Netherlands|Dutch]] parliament in 2006.  

[[Green parties]] and [[cannabis political parties]], which exist in a number of countries, are explicitly based around single issues.  These parties often evolve to adopt a full platform, however, and most Green parties and today's  Bloc Québécois have full platforms.  In the case of the Bloc Québécois, separatism is today a secondary issue.

==See also==
*[[Issue voting]]
*[[Voting bloc]]
*[[Identity politics]]

[[Category:Politics by issue]]

[[de:Interessenpartei]]
[[nl:One-issuepartij]]
[[sv:Enfrågeparti]]</text>
      <sha1>qdpvz7gi4e5g9v1sz57cswx0p2its39</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
