<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Smith College</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>247957</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521264161</id>
      <parentid>521263233</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-03T21:55:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Vacation9</username>
        <id>13634631</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted to revision 519108632 by CircleAdrian: Test edits were restored. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="39490">{{Infobox university
| image_name      = Smithcollege-logo.png
| motto           = {{lang|grc|Ἐν τῇ ἀρετῇ τὴν γνῶσιν}}
| mottoeng        = In Virtue [One Gains] Knowledge
| established     = Chartered in 1871; opened its doors in 1875
| type            = [[Women's colleges in the United States|Women's college]] ([[Private school|Private]])
| endowment       = [[United States dollar|$]]1.43 billion (2011)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2011_NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values_Final_January_17_2012.pdf |title=Part One |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2010-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| cost            = [[United States dollar|$]]47.660 thousand&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Student Financial Services&quot;&gt;[http://www.smith.edu/finaid/guides/feesandpayments], Smith College website.&lt;/ref&gt;
| president       = [[Carol T. Christ]]
| faculty         = 285&lt;ref name=&quot;justthefacts&quot;&gt;[http://www.smith.edu/about_justthefacts.php Just the Facts], Smith College website.&lt;/ref&gt;
| undergrad       = 2,600&lt;ref name=&quot;justthefacts&quot; /&gt;
| postgrad = 102&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Smith College:Faculty Facts|url=http://www.smith.edu/registrar/faculty_facts.php|publisher=Smith College|accessdate=21 October 2012|year=2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| academic departments = 37&lt;ref name=&quot;justthefacts&quot; /&gt;
| city            = [[Northampton, Massachusetts|Northampton]]
| state           = [[Massachusetts]]
| country         = US
| coor            = {{Coord|42.318119|-72.638139|region:US_type:edu|display=inline, title}}
| campus setting  = [[Urban]]
| colors          = Blue with gold trim {{colorbox|#002D62}} {{colorbox|#F1AB00}}&lt;ref name=Colors&gt;{{cite web|title=Smith College:Visual Identity Program|url=http://www.smith.edu/vid/using.php|publisher=Smith College|accessdate=20 August 2012|year=2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
| nickname        = Pioneers
| anthem          =
| facebook        = &lt;ref&gt;http://www.facebook.com/smithcollege&lt;/ref&gt;
| twitter         = &lt;ref&gt;http://twitter.com/smithcollge&lt;/ref&gt;
| website         = [http://www.smith.edu/ smith.edu]
|}}

'''Smith College''' is a [[Private university|private]], [[Independent school|independent]] [[Women's colleges in the United States|women's]] [[Liberal arts colleges in the United States|liberal arts college]] located in [[Northampton, Massachusetts]], [[United States]]. It is the largest member of the [[Seven Sisters (colleges)|Seven Sisters]]. Smith is also a member of the [[Five Colleges (Massachusetts)|Five Colleges]] consortium,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fivecolleges.edu |title=Five Colleges, Incorporated: Home |publisher=Fivecolleges.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; which allows its students to attend classes at four other [[Pioneer Valley]] institutions: [[Mount Holyoke College]], [[Amherst College]], [[Hampshire College]], and the [[University of Massachusetts Amherst]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fivecolleges.edu] Five College Consortium website. &quot;Accessed July 9, 2009&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, [[U.S. News &amp; World Report]] ranked it 14th among Best Liberal Arts Colleges.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/northampton-ma/smith-college-2209 |title=Smith College - Best College - Education - US News |publisher=Colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com |date=2010-08-17 |accessdate=2010-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Smith College#Notable alumnae|Notable alumnae]] include [[Catharine MacKinnon]], [[Nancy Reagan]], [[Barbara Bush (First Lady)|Barbara Bush]], [[Betty Friedan]], [[Gloria Steinem]], [[Julia Child]], [[Madeleine L'Engle]], [[Sylvia Plath]], [[Sherry Rehman]], [[Sharmeen Obaid-Chinoy]], [[Rochelle Lazarus]], [[Laura D'Andrea Tyson]] and [[Yolanda King]].

==History==
[[File:The Botanic Garden of Smith College.jpg|thumb|200px|upright|The Botanic Gardens at Smith College]]The college was chartered in 1871 by a bequest of [[Sophia Smith]] and opened its doors in 1875 with 14 students and six faculty.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.smith.edu/collegerelations/sophia.php &quot;Sophia Smith: Smith College's Founder&quot;], Smith College website.&lt;/ref&gt; When she inherited, at age 65, a fortune from her father, Smith decided that leaving her inheritance to found a women's college was the best way for her to fulfill the moral obligation she expressed in her will: &quot;I hereby make the following provisions for the establishment and maintenance of an Institution for the higher education of young women, with the design to furnish for my own sex means and facilities for education equal to those which are afforded now in our colleges to young men.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.smith.edu/about_smithtradition.php] Smith College Web site&lt;/ref&gt; By 1915–16 the student enrollment was 1,724 and the faculty numbered 163.

Today, with some 2,600 undergraduates on campus, and 250 students studying elsewhere,&lt;ref name=&quot;smith1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.smith.edu/about_justthefacts.php |title=Smith College: Just the Facts |publisher=Smith.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Smith is the largest privately endowed college for women in the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| title = Peterson's Four-year Colleges 2008  | publisher = Peterson  | year = 2007 | page = 2226  | isbn = 978-0-7689-2400-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The campus was planned and planted in the 1890s as a [[botanical garden]] and [[arboretum]], designed by [[Frederick Law Olmsted]]. The campus landscape now encompasses {{convert|147|acre|km2|1}} and includes more than 1,200 varieties of trees and shrubs.

Smith has been led by 10 presidents and two acting presidents.  For the 1975 centennial, the college inaugurated its first woman president, [[Jill Ker Conway]] ([[Elizabeth Cutter Morrow]] was the first acting president of Smith College and the first female head of the college, but she did not use the title of president), who came to Smith from [[Australia]] by way of [[Harvard University|Harvard]] and the [[University of Toronto]].  Since President Conway's term, all Smith presidents have been women, with the exception of John M. Connolly's one-year term as acting president in the interim after President Simmons left to lead [[Brown University]].

* [[Laurenus Clark Seelye]] 1875–1910
* [[Marion LeRoy Burton]] 1910–1917
* [[William Allan Neilson]] 1917–1939
* [[Elizabeth Cutter Morrow]] 1939–1940 (acting president)
* [[Herbert Davis]] 1940–1949
* Benjamin Fletcher Wright 1949–1959
* [[Thomas C. Mendenhall (historian)|Thomas Corwin Mendenhall]] 1959–1975
* [[Jill Ker Conway]] 1975–1985
* [[Mary Maples Dunn]] 1985–1995
* [[Ruth Simmons]] 1995–2001
* John M. Connolly 2001–2002 (acting president)
* [[Carol T. Christ]] 2002–present

==Academics and educational programs==
&lt;!-- Image with unknown copyright status removed: [[Image:Smithcollege-classroom.jpg|thumb|right|240px|upright|Smith offers more than 1,000 courses in more than 50 areas of study.]] --&gt;Smith College has 285 professors in 41 academic departments and programs, for a faculty:student ratio of 1:9.&lt;ref name=&quot;smith1&quot;/&gt;  It is the first and only women's college in the United States to grant its own undergraduate degrees in [[engineering]].  The Picker Engineering Program offers a single [[ABET]] accredited [[Bachelor of Science]] in engineering science, combining the fundamentals of multiple engineering disciplines.

Smith recently joined the [[Liberal arts colleges in the United States#SAT optional movement|SAT optional movement]] for undergraduate admission.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Monday, May 26, 2008 By FRED CONTRADA fcontrada@repub.com |url=http://www.masslive.com/metrowest/republican/index.ssf?/base/news-14/1211786427249410.xml&amp;coll=1 |title=Smith drops SATs |publisher=MassLive.com |date=2008-05-26 |accessdate=2010-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Smith runs its own junior year abroad (JYA) programs in four European cities: [[Paris]], [[Hamburg]], [[Florence]] and [[Geneva]]. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.smith.edu/studyabroad/jya.php&lt;/ref&gt; These programs are notable for requiring all studies to be conducted in the language of the host country (with both Paris and Geneva programs conducted in French).  In some cases students live in homestays with local families.  Nearly half of Smith's juniors study overseas, either through Smith JYA programs or at more than 40 other locations around the world.

Junior math majors from other undergraduate institutions are invited to study at Smith College for one year through the [[Center for Women in Mathematics]].  Established in the fall of 2007 by Professors Ruth Haas and Jim Henle, the program aims to allow young women to improve their mathematical abilities through classwork, research and involvement in a department centered on women.   The [[Center for Women in Mathematics|Center]] also offers a post-baccalaureate year of math study to women who either did not major in mathematics as undergraduates or whose mathematics major was not strong.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.math.buffalo.edu/mad/NAM/newsletter/NAM38.1.pdf &quot;Smith College Women in Mathematics Program&quot;  National Association of Mathematicians, Spring 2007]. Retrieved 3 September 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Louise W. and Edmund J. Kahn Liberal Arts Institute supports collaborative research without regard to the traditional boundaries of academic departments and programs. Each year the Institute supports long-term and short-term projects proposed, planned and organized by members of the Smith College faculty. By becoming Kahn Fellows, students get involved in interdisciplinary research projects and work alongside faculty and visiting scholars for a year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.smith.edu/kahninstitute/ |title=Smith College: Kahn Liberal Arts Institute |publisher=Smith.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Students can develop leadership skills through Smith's two-year Phoebe Reese Lewis Leadership Program. Participants train in public speaking, analytical thinking, teamwork strategies and the philosophical aspects of leadership.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.smith.edu/acad_specialleadership.php |title=Smith College: Academic Programs |publisher=Smith.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Through Smith's internship program, &quot;Praxis: The Liberal Arts at Work,&quot; every undergraduate is guaranteed access to one college funded internship during her years at the college. This program enables students to access interesting self-generated internship positions in social welfare and human services, the arts, media, health, education, and other fields.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.smith.edu/acad_specialpraxis.php |title=Smith College: Academic Programs |publisher=Smith.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Ada Comstock]] Scholars Program is a [[bachelor's degree]] program for [[non-traditional students]].

===Graduate degrees and study options===
Smith offers men and women graduate work leading to the degrees of master of arts in teaching (elementary, middle or high school), master of fine arts, master of education of the deaf, master of science in biological sciences, master of science in exercise and sport studies and master and Ph.D. in social work. In special one-year programs, international students may qualify for a certificate of graduate studies or a diploma in American studies. Each year approximately 100 men and women pursue advanced graduate work at Smith.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.smith.edu/gradstudy/degrees.php |title=Smith College: Graduate Study |publisher=Smith.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Also offered in a non-degree studies program is the Diploma in American Studies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.smith.edu/gradstudy/nondegree.php |title=Smith College: Graduate Study |publisher=Smith.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is a highly competitive one-year program open only to international students of advanced undergraduate or graduate standing. It is designed primarily, although not exclusively, for those who are teaching or who plan to teach some aspect of American culture and institutions.

The Smith College master of social work (M.S.W.) degree is nationally recognized for its specialization in clinical social work and puts a heavy emphasis on direct field work practice. The program is accredited by the [[Council on Social Work Education]]. The school also offers a Ph.D. program designed to prepare MSWs for leadership positions in clinical research education and practice.

The college has a limited number of other programs leading to Ph.D.s, and is part of a cooperative doctoral program co-administered by [[Amherst College]], [[Hampshire College]], [[Mount Holyoke College]] and the [[University of Massachusetts Amherst]].

==Houses==
Smith College has many different houses serving as dormitories. Each house is self-governing and collects its own dues. While many students remain in the same house for the entirety of their four years at Smith, they are not obligated to do so, and may move to different houses on campus as space allows.

Houses are found in three main regions of campus: Upper and Lower Elm Street, Green Street/Center Campus, and the Quadrangle. Each region can, in turn, be divided into smaller areas to more precisely provide the location of the house in question.

===Green Street houses===
* Chapin House
* Hubbard House
* Lawrence House
* Morris House
* Tyler House
* Washburn House

===Center Campus houses===
* Cutter/Ziskind Houses
* Friedman Apartments
* Haven/Wesley Houses
* Hopkins House
* Park Complex
* Sessions Complex
* Tenney House

===Upper Elm Street houses===
* Capen House
* Dawes House
* Lamont House
* Northrop House
* Parsons Complex
* Talbot House

===Lower Elm Street houses===
* Albright House
* Baldwin House
* Chase House
* Conway House
* Duckett House
* Gillett House
* 150 Elm Street
* 12 Bedford Terrace
* 26 Bedford Terrace

===East Quadrangle houses===
* Cushing House
* Emerson House
* Jordan House
* King House
* Scales House

===West Quadrangle houses===
* Comstock House
* Gardiner House
* Morrow House
* Wilder House
* Wilson House

==Traditions==
===Athletics===
[[Image:Smithcollege-spiritmark.png|thumb|left|200px|upright|Smith College's spirit mark, introduced in December 2008.]]Smith's athletic teams have been known as the Pioneers since 1986. The name expresses the spirit of Smith's students and the college's leadership role in women's athletics (the first women's basketball game was played at Smith in 1893).

A new spirit mark was unveiled to the Smith community in December 2008.  The new visual identity for Smith's sports teams marks the culmination of a yearlong project to promote visibility and enthusiasm for Smith's intercollegiate and club teams—and to generate school spirit broadly. It will be used for athletics uniforms, casual apparel and promotional items for clubs and organizations. As Smith was the first women’s college to join the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]], the new mark is seen as linking the college’s pioneering alumnae athletes to their equally determined and competitive counterparts today.[http://www.smith.edu/spirit/]

Smith College does not have college colors in the usual sense. Its official color is white, trimmed with gold, but the official college logo is currently blue and yellow (a previous logo was burgundy and white). NCAA athletic teams have competed in blue and white (or blue and yellow, in the case of the soccer, crew, swimming, and squash teams) uniforms since the 1970s, and selected Pioneers as the official name and mascot in 1986. Popular club sports are free to choose their own colors and mascot; both Rugby and Fencing have chosen red and black.

Smith has a rotating system of class colors dating back to the 1880s, when intramural athletics and other campus competitions were usually held by class. Today, class colors are yellow, red, blue and green, with incoming first-year classes assigned the color of the previous year's graduating class; their color then &quot;follows&quot; them through to graduation.  Alumnae classes, particularly at reunion, continue to identify with and use their class color thereafter.

===Residential culture and student life===
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Smithcollege-wesley.jpg|thumb|right|240px|upright|Wesley House, one of Smith's residential houses.]] --&gt;Smith requires all first-year undergraduate students, as well as most other undergraduates, to live in on-campus houses unless they reside locally with their family. This policy is intended to add to the camaraderie and social cohesion of its students. Unlike most institutions of its type, Smith College does not have dorms, but rather 36 separate houses, ranging in architectural style from 18th-century to contemporary. (A popular rumor perpetuated by students is that Sophia Smith stated in her will that each house be constructed in the style of the period; this is, however, only an urban legend). {{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

Two recent additions to the campus, both of which enhance its sense of community, are the architecturally dramatic Campus Center &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.smith.edu/campuscenter/ |title=Smith College: Office of Student Engagement |publisher=Smith.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the state-of-the-art Olin Fitness Center.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.smith.edu/news/2003-04/OlinOpening.html |title=Smith College: News |publisher=Smith.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009, construction was also completed on Ford Hall, a new science and engineering facility.  According to the Smith College website, Ford Hall is a &quot;...facility that will intentionally blur the boundaries between traditional disciplines, creating an optimum environment for students and faculty to address key scientific and technological developments of our time.&quot;  The building was officially dedicated on October 16, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;Ford Hall: http://www.smith.edu/fordhall/&lt;/ref&gt;

The campus also boasts a botanic garden that includes a Japanese tea house, a variety of specialty gardens including a rock garden, and historic glass greenhouses dating back to 1895. It is rumored that the architecture of Chapin House was the inspiration for the one in Tara in ''[[Gone with the Wind]]''. ([[Margaret Mitchell]] went to Smith for one year.)

A novelty of Smith's homelike atmosphere is the continuing popularity of Sophia Smith's recipe&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.smith.edu/libraries/ca/sophia/fun/fun.htm |title=Sophia Through the Years |publisher=Smith.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; for molasses cookies. These are often served at the traditional Friday afternoon tea held in each house, where students, faculty and staff members and alumnae socialize.&lt;ref name=&quot;justthefacts&quot; /&gt;

Smith offers &quot;panel discussions and seminars for lesbian, bisexual, and transgender students on subjects such as coming out as transgender at work.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;April 8, 2007 article, Boston Globe, http://www.boston.com/news/globe/magazine/articles/2007/04/08/when_she_graduates_as_he/&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2003, Smith students voted to remove pronouns from the language of the Student Government Association constitution, in order to make that document inclusive of transgendered students who don't identify with the female pronouns &quot;she&quot; and &quot;her.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.smith.edu/oid/gender_faq.php |title=Smith College: Office of Institutional Diversity |publisher=Smith.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Academic year events===
'''[[Convocation]]''' signals the start of the fall semester. For new students it is the first chance to experience Smith College's tradition and spirit. Likewise, for some returning students, the annual event is like a big, welcome-home party as well as an occasion for celebration and an opportunity for creative attire. House communities develop imaginative themes for group fashion, and Smith seniors put special touches on favorite hats to create their own unique &quot;senior hats,&quot; to be worn for the first time at Convocation.

'''[[Mountain Day]]''' is observed early in the fall semester. The President of the College selects a crisp, sunny, beautiful autumn day when the leaves are in full color, and announces the cancellation of classes by having bells rung on campus at 7:15 AM on the chosen day. The eager anticipation of Mountain Day leads to intense speculation meteorology by students in the weeks leading up to the surprise announcement. Traditional observance of Mountain Day by students might involve [[New England]] road trips or outdoor pursuits, and college dining services provides box lunches to be taken off-campus.

'''[[Otelia Cromwell]] Day''', named for Smith's first African-American student, began in 1989 to provide students with an in-depth program specifically addressing issues of racism and diversity.  Afternoon classes are cancelled, and students are invited to participate in lectures, workshops, symposia and cultural events focused on a different theme each year.

'''Rally Day''' In February 1876, the College began an annual observance of [[George Washington]]'s birthday.  In 1894, a rally became part of the day's events, and the focus of the celebration became primarily patriotic rather than exclusively social—though always with a women's college twist. Students that year staged a mock debate on the subject, &quot;Does Higher Education Unfit a Man for Domestic Life?&quot; In 1906 the celebration was first referred to as '''Rally Day''' (although the name was not used officially by the College until 1992). In 1944, seniors made Rally Day the first public wearing of their graduation caps and gowns; since then, mortarboards have been replaced by wacky, often homemade hats. Today, the Rally Day Convocation is centered around a historical theme, and features a distinguished keynote speaker and the awarding of Smith College Medals to accomplished alumnae.

===Reunions and Commencement events===
The Alumnae Association of Smith College hosts official class reunions every five years, plus a special two-year reunion. All alumnae from all classes are welcome to return in any year; &quot;off-year&quot; alumnae attend campus-wide events as the &quot;Class of 1776.&quot;

Traditional reunion and Commencement events are linked, and celebrate the close ties between Smith's alumnae and its graduating seniors and their families. At the conclusion of final exams, most underclasswomen leave the campus, while seniors remain in their houses for a week to celebrate and prepare for Commencement. Alumnae arrive for reunions later in the week, and many alumnae arrange for official accommodations in the campus houses, right alongside senior residents.

[[File:Smith College - Ivy Day Seniors.jpg|thumb|220px|Ivy Day]]

'''[[Ivy Day]]''', the day before Commencement, is the high point of reunion and a significant event for seniors as well. Junior ushers lead a parade through campus, carrying vines of ivy to be planted by the departing seniors as a symbol of their lifelong connection to the college.  Alumnae (and, often, their children), dressed in white and wearing sashes in their class color, line up in reverse order by class along both sides of the route.  Seniors line up nearest the end of the parade route, wearing traditional white outfits and each carrying a single red rose.  All cheer each alumnae class as it marches past, then fall in to join the end of the parade. Many alumnae classes carry signs with humorous poems or slogans, or hold balloons or wear hats in their class color. Ivy Day festivities conclude in the Quad, where the seniors plant their ivy and speakers address alumnae on the progress of fundraising and the state of the college.

&lt;!-- Image with unknown copyright status removed: [[Image:Smithcollege-illumination.jpg|thumb|left|220px|upright|On Illumination Night, the Smith campus is lit by paper lanterns.]] --&gt;'''Illumination Night''', beginning at dusk on the Saturday evening before Commencement, is a celebration of the campus and a send-off of sorts for graduating seniors. Throughout central campus, electric street lights are replaced for one night by multicolored Japanese-style paper lanterns, lit with real candles. These hang on both sides of every walking path and cast a soft glow over the buildings and lawns. Student a cappella singing groups and improv comedy troupes roam the campus, stopping occasionally to entertain the crowds. A jazz band, hired by the college, turns the science buildings' courtyard into a dance floor. Seniors, alumnae, faculty and their families spend the evening on walking tours of the illuminated campus and [[The Botanic Garden of Smith College|Botanic Gardens]].  The major official event of the night is the '''Senior Step Sing''': seniors gather on the steps of Neilson Library, where they are serenaded by members of the '''Sophomore Push''' committee, then are physically pushed off the stairs and &quot;into the real world.&quot;

Until the early 1990s, all alumnae reunions were held during Commencement weekend. However, as the number of returning alumnae grew beyond the capacity of the campus, reunions were split into Reunion I/Commencement Weekend and Reunion II, held the following weekend. &quot;Significant&quot; reunions (50-, 25- and 10- year, but also 2-year) and the earliest reunion classes (65-year and prior) are assigned to Reunion I; other reunions (5-, 15-, 20-, 30-year, and so on) are assigned to Reunion II.

===Campus folklore===
Smith has numerous folk tales and ghost stories that emerge from the histories of some of its historic buildings. One such tale holds that Sessions House is inhabited by the ghost of Lucy Hunt, who died of a broken heart after being separated from her lover, General Burgoyne.  Reports of a ghost in Sessions House predate its history as a campus house. Built in 1751 by the Hunt family, the house has a secret staircase where, according to legend, the Hunt's eldest daughter Lucy would rendezvous with her lover, General Burgoyne. The two were ultimately driven apart, and in the 1880s it was believed that the ghost of a heartbroken Burgoyne haunted the staircase. Since Sessions House became part of college housing in the 20th century, the specter has taken on a decidedly feminine identity, and some former residents of Sessions claim to have seen Lucy's ghost in the stairwell.

==Environmental sustainability==

Smith has taken numerous steps toward environmental sustainability, including a 30% reduction in energy use. Also, through a contract with Zipcar, the college has reduced the need for individually owned cars on campus. Complimenting this effort, the college has also promoted sustainability through academics and through the arts.&lt;ref name=&quot;smith.edu&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.smith.edu/green/news.php |title=Smith College: Green Smith |publisher=Smith.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In keeping with its sustainability efforts, all Smith dining locations have discontinued the use of &quot;to-go&quot; supplies which included paper cups and plates, as well as plastic utensils. They now encourage students to bring their own, reusable containers and utensils if they wish to bring food back to their rooms. Smith College provides all students with a reusable drink container at the beginning of each academic year. In past years, these containers have been variations on travel mugs, Sigg bottles, and nalgenes. Those dining halls that still offer &quot;To-Go&quot; options no longer provide paper bags, and instead use wax paper bags, biodegradable plastic, and recyclable utensils made of vegetable cellulose.

For Smith's efforts regarding sustainability, the institution earned a grade of &quot;A-&quot; on the &quot;College Sustainability Report Card 2010&quot; administered by the Sustainable Endowments Institute. Smith was lauded for many of the indicator categories, including student involvement, green building, and transportation, but was marked down for endowment transparency.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.greenreportcard.org/report-card-2010/schools/smith-college |title=Smith College - Green Report Card 2010 |publisher=Greenreportcard.org |date=2008-06-30 |accessdate=2010-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable alumnae==

{{Main|List of Smith College people}}
A number of Smith alumnae have gone on to become notable in their respective fields and endeavors.  Some examples include:

*[[Barbara Adams (General Counsel of Pennsylvania)|Barbara Adams]], [[General Counsel]] of [[Pennsylvania]]
*[[Tammy Baldwin]], [[Member of Congress|Congresswoman]], D-Wisconsin
*[[Barbara Bush (First Lady)|Barbara Bush]], former First Lady of the [[United States]]
*[[Ernestine Gilbreth Carey]], author
*[[Penny Chenery]], recipient of the Smith College Medal, owner/breeder of [[Secretariat (horse)|Secretariat]]
*[[Julia Child]], chef and author
*[[Barbara Cooney]], author and award-winning illustrator
*[[Margaret Edson]], award-winning playwright
*[[Julie Nixon Eisenhower]], former First daughter
*[[Margaret Farrar]], crossword puzzle editor
*[[Janet Fish]], artist
*[[Bonnie Franklin]], actress
*[[Betty Friedan]], feminist, activist, author
*[[Sara Haines]], Online Correspondent, NBC News TODAY Show
*[[Jane Lakes Harman]], head of the Woodrow Wilson Center, former Congresswoman, D-California
*[[Molly Ivins]], columnist and author
*[[Yolanda King]], actress, activist daughter of [[Martin Luther King, Jr.]] and [[Coretta Scott King]]
*[[Karen Klinger]], rower and Smith crew head coach
*[[Carol Herselle Krinsky]], architectural historian
*[[Tosca Lee]], author
*[[Madeleine L'Engle]], award-winning author
*[[Anne Morrow Lindbergh]], author and aviator
*[[Catharine MacKinnon]], feminist, activist, lawyer
*[[Sarah MacLean]], bestselling author
*[[Tori Murden McClure]], first woman to row solo across the Atlantic Ocean
*[[Kathleen Marshall]], choreographer
*[[Ann M. Martin]], author
*[[Joan Mitchell]], painter
*[[Margaret Mitchell]], award-winning author of 'Gone With the Wind'
* [[Elizabeth Cutter Morrow]], acting Smith College president 1939-40
*[[Sharmeen Obaid-Chinoy]], Emmy and Oscar awards-winning film documentarian
*[[Sylvia Plath]], poet and author
*[[Halina Poświatowska]], poet
*[[Nancy Reagan]], former First Lady of the United States
*[[Sherry Rehman]], Pakistan's Ambassador to U.S.
*[[Eleanor Sanger]], first women's sports producer
*[[Gloria Steinem]], feminist, activist, journalist (Class of 1956)
*[[Niki Tsongas]], Congresswoman, D-Massachusetts
*[[Laura Tyson]],Chairperson, National Economic Council under President Clinton
*[[Cynthia Voigt]], award-winning author
*[[J.R. Ward]], bestselling author
*[[Virginia Euwer Wolff]], award-winning author
*[[Jane Yolen]], award-winning author
*[[Frances Mossiker]], author
*[[Rose Jang]], pop opera singer and PR ambassador for [[South Korea]], [[UNESCO]] and [[New7Wonders of Nature]].
*[[Olga Gorelli]], composer and pianist.
*[[Caterina Fake]], entrepreneur, founder of [[Flickr]] and [[Hunch (website)|Hunch]]
*[[Susan George (political scientist)|Susan George]], is a well-known Franco-American political and social scientist, activist and writer

The Alumnae Association of Smith College considers all former students to be members, whether they graduated or not, and does not generally differentiate between graduates and non-graduates when identifying Smith alumnae.

==Smith College in popular culture==

References to Smith abound in literature. In [[Sylvia Plath]]'s novel ''[[The Bell Jar]]'', the protagonist Esther Greenwood attends Smith College. In ''[[Running with Scissors (memoir)|Running With Scissors]],'' a memoir by [[Augusten Burroughs]], the author details how he and his foster-sister, Natalie, took walks together on the campus. The fictional Catamount College in the novella ''[[Beasts (novella)|Beasts]]'' by [[Joyce Carol Oates]] is based on Smith College. The character Chenault in ''[[The Rum Diary (novel)|The Rum Diary]]'' by [[Hunter S. Thompson]] went to Smith College. ''Commencement'', a novel by J. Courtney Sullivan was published in 2009 and recounts the friendship of four Smith College classmates.

Smith has its place in films as well. The 1954 film ''[[White Christmas (film)|White Christmas]]'' referenced Smith. Jean Simmons plays a recent Smith grad in 1957's &quot;[[This Could Be the Night (film)|This Could Be the Night]]&quot;. The 1966 movie ''[[Who's Afraid of Virginia Woolf?]]'' and the 1993 movie ''[[Malice (film)|Malice]]'' were both filmed on the Smith campus. In the 1971 film ''[[Carnal Knowledge]]'', [[Candice Bergen]]'s character, Susan, is a Smith student, and portions of the film take place on the Smith campus. The character Joanna Kramer, played by [[Meryl Streep]] in the 1979 film ''[[Kramer vs. Kramer]]'', is a Smith College graduate. In the movie ''[[The Nanny Diaries]]'' Mrs. X is a Smith alumna. [[Spike Lee]] also has a reference to a Smithie as a lesbian paying an ex-biotech exec to inseminate her and many other homosexual women in the movie ''[[She Hate Me]]''. Sadie (Nicole Vicius) from 2007 lesbian-comedy [[Itty Bitty Titty Committee]] dropped out of the college after meeting her partner, a guest lecturer at Smith.

Well-known television shows integrate references to Smith into character plot lines. An episode in the second season of the series ''[[Felicity (TV series)]]'' has a Smith College graduate who refuses to serve as an egg donor for Javier because he is gay. Charlotte York in the show ''[[Sex and the City]]'' is a Smith College graduate. In an episode of ''[[The Simpsons]]''—&quot;[[I'm Spelling as Fast as I Can]]&quot;—[[Lisa Simpson]] is tempted by the Siren-like representatives of the [[Seven Sisters (colleges)|Seven Sisters]] (and [[George Plimpton]]), who offer a scholarship to the Sister school of her choice (and a George Plimpton hot plate) if she will throw a
Spelling Bee. [[Dr. Cristina Yang]], a surgical resident played by [[Sandra Oh]] on ''[[Grey's Anatomy]]'', graduated from Smith College with degrees in French Literature and Chemistry, and lived in Chapin House. [[Ainsley Hayes]] (played by [[Emily Procter]]), the conservative lawyer hired to work in the White House Counsel's Office on ''[[The West Wing]]'', graduated from Smith. In an episode of ''[[Mad About You]]'' Paul's sister and her girlfriend are referred to as &quot;The Fighting Lesbians.&quot; Paul ([[Paul Reiser]]) replies, &quot;No, that would be the name of the Smith College Ice Hockey Team.&quot; Emily Gilmore in the show ''[[Gilmore Girls]]'' went to Smith and majored in history. In season two of &quot;Nip Tuck&quot;- episode &quot;Julia McNamara&quot;, Julia gets anesthesia before her facial surgery. One of the dreams she has is that Dr. Liz Cruz's made-up daughter will be attending Smith that coming fall.  In the third season of [[ER (TV series)|ER]], Dr. Doug Ross (played by [[George Clooney]]) mentions he is dating a Smith graduate.  Nurse Carol Hathaway makes a joke about Dr. Ross's normal dates being unable to spell Smith.  A very similar joke was made in the movie [[White Christmas (film)|White Christmas]], which starred George Clooney's aunt, [[Rosemary Clooney]].

In the 2009 ''[[Heroes (TV series)|Heroes]]'' episode &quot;[[A Clear and Present Danger]]&quot;, the Smith College viewbook is displayed prominently at the top of a stack of college materials [[Claire Bennet]] is apparently reviewing. [[Angela Petrelli]] asks Claire if she's found a favorite, to which Claire replies, &quot;Hamilton, Smith, Georgetown, they're all the best schools in the country.&quot;

The webcomic [[Questionable Content]] mentions Smith College (usually referred to as &quot;Smif&quot; in the comic) as the place where one of the main characters, Marten, is employed as library staff, and several of the minor characters attend. Ellen, studies marine biology. Tai, Natasha and Cosette are also students. Jeph Jacques, the author, went to [[Hampshire College]], one of the neighboring schools.
Some characters from the webcomic Minimalist Stick Figure Theatre, set primarily in Northampton, are students at Smith College.

In a recent [[Hallmark Channel]] original movie titled &quot;Mrs. Washington Goes to Smith,&quot; [[Cybill Shepherd]] stars in a story about a woman in her 40s who returns to Smith College to finish her bachelor's degree. Smith alumna Susan Rice '63 wrote the script for the film, which aired August 1, 2009.

In [[Grace Metalious]]'s 1956 novel [[Peyton Place (novel)|Peyton Place]], the school teacher, Miss Elsie Thornton, is a Smith alum.&lt;ref&gt;Metalious, Grace. Peyton Place. New York: Dell Publishing, Inc., 1956.&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Grace Metalious]]'s 1960 novel &quot;The Tight White Collar&quot; the character Margery Cooper attends Smith College.&lt;ref&gt;Metalious, Grace. The Tight White Collar. New York: Dell Books, 1962.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable staff==

*In 1960, three Smith professors, one who had been there for 38 years, were fired or &quot;allowed to retire&quot; for being gay.  This was chronicled in a book (&quot;The Scarlet Professor — Newton Arvin: A Literary Life Shattered by Scandal&quot; (Doubleday, 2001), by Barry Werth), and the PBS Independent Lens film, &quot;The Great Pink Scare.&quot;  &lt;http://www.pbs.org/independentlens/greatpinkscare/film.html&gt; In 2002, Smith, the nation's largest liberal arts college for women, acknowledged a wrong from four decades earlier by creating a lecture series and a small scholarship — the $100,000 Dorius/Spofford Fund for the Study of Civil Liberties and Freedom of Expression, and the Newton Arvin Prize in American Studies, a $500 annual stipend. But despite faculty appeals, there was no apology. &lt;http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/20/obituaries/20dorius.html&gt;
*[[Leonard Baskin]] taught at Smith from 1953 to 1974.

==Notes==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
{{Refbegin}}
* [[Helen Lefkowitz Horowitz|Horowitz, Helen Lefkowitz]]. [http://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN0870238698&amp;id=Z3qWLyDZ8PsC&amp;pg=PP1&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;ots=xMmu_yuuHV&amp;dq=alma+mater&amp;sig=N7RcPpZKbQvPM1m5ohSuIcu_KxU#PPP1,M1 ''Alma Mater: Design and Experience in the Women's Colleges from Their Nineteenth-Century Beginnings to the 1930s''], Amherst: [[University of Massachusetts Press]], 1993 (2nd edition).
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons}}
{{Wikisource1911Enc}}

* {{Official website|http://www.smith.edu/}}
* [http://www.smithpioneers.com Official athletics website]
* [http://www.smithsophian.com/ The ''Sophian''], Smith's student newspaper
* [http://www.facebook.com/smithcollege Smith on Facebook]
* {{Cite Americana|Smith College}}

{{Smith College}}
{{Annapolis Group}}
{{Oberlin Group}}
{{CLAC}}
{{Five Colleges}}
{{Seven Sisters}}
{{New England Women's and Men's Athletic Conference navbox}}
{{Current women's universities and colleges in the United States}}

[[Category:Smith College|*]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Massachusetts]]
[[Category:New England Association of Schools and Colleges]]
[[Category:Liberal arts colleges]]
[[Category:Women's universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1871]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Northampton, Massachusetts]]
[[Category:Seven Sister Colleges]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Hampshire County, Massachusetts]]
[[Category:Members of the Annapolis Group]]
[[Category:Association of Independent Colleges and Universities in Massachusetts members]]

[[bg:Колеж Смит]]
[[de:Smith College]]
[[es:Smith College]]
[[fr:Smith College]]
[[ko:스미스 대학교]]
[[id:Universitas Smith]]
[[nl:Smith College]]
[[ja:スミス大学]]
[[pnb:سمتھ کالج]]
[[pt:Smith College]]
[[ro:Colegiul Smith]]
[[ru:Колледж Смит]]
[[sv:Smith College]]
[[zh:史密斯學院]]</text>
      <sha1>2hlpp7tm110qwpjga42c6d8o6zcvkmc</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
