<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Social democracy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18247265</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521747357</id>
      <parentid>520966941</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-06T23:34:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>R-41</username>
        <id>1266754</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Neoliberalism and social democratic response, contemporary period, 1979 to present */ Schroeder is another Third Way proponent - the photo of Giddens represents a major Third Way proponent, the paragraph here is on Lafontaine's challenging of Third Way</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="94567">{{Social democracy sidebar}}
'''Social democracy''' is a political ideology that considers itself to be a form of [[Reformism|reformist]] [[democratic socialism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Busky8&quot;&gt;{{Citation |first=Donald F. |last=Busky |title=Democratic Socialism: A Global Survey |place=Westport, Connecticut, USA |publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group, Inc., |year=2000 |page=8 |quote=The Frankfurt Declaration of the Socialist International, which almost all social democratic parties are members of, declares the goal of the development of democratic socialism}}&lt;/ref&gt; Common social democratic policies include advocacy of universal social rights to attain universally-accessible [[public service]]s such as: [[universal education|education]], [[universal health care|health care]], [[workers' compensation]], and other services including [[child care]] and care for the elderly.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas Meyer, Lewis P. Hinchman. ''The theory of social democracy''. Cambridge, England, UK; Malden, Massachusetts, USA: Polity Press, 2007. Pp. 137.&lt;/ref&gt; Social democracy is connected with the [[trade union]] [[labour movement]] and supports [[Collective bargaining|collective bargaining rights]] for workers.&lt;ref&gt;Martin Upchurch, Graham John Taylor, Andy Mathers. ''The crisis of social democratic trade unionism in Western Europe: the search for alternatives''. Surrey, England, UK; Burlington, Vermont, USA: Ashgate Publishing, 2009. Pp. 51.&lt;/ref&gt; Most social democratic parties are affiliated with the [[Socialist International]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Busky8&quot;/&gt;

Social democracy was developed by [[Revisionism (Marxism)|revisionist]] [[Marxism|Marxist]] [[Eduard Bernstein]] who opposed [[orthodox Marxism]]'s support of [[Revolutionary socialism|revolution]] and [[class conflict]], claiming that socialism could be achieved through evolutionary means via [[representative democracy]] and cooperation between people regardless of class.&lt;ref name=&quot;Steger, Manfred B. 1997. pg. 146&quot;&gt;Steger, Manfred B. ''The Quest for Evolutionary Socialism: Eduard Bernstein And Social Democracy''. Cambridge, England, UK; New York, New York, USA: Cambridge University Press, 1997. pg. 146.&lt;/ref&gt; Bernstein claimed that a [[mixed economy]] of [[Public enterprise|public]], [[cooperative]] and [[private enterprise]] would be necessary for a long period of time before private enterprises would evolve of their own accord into cooperative enterprise.&lt;ref name=&quot;Steger, Manfred B. 1997. pg. 146&quot;&gt;Steger, Manfred B.  ''The Quest for Evolutionary Socialism: Eduard Bernstein And Social Democracy''. Cambridge, England, UK; New York, New York, USA: Cambridge University Press, 1997. pg. 146.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Christopher Pierson 2001. Pp. 25&quot;&gt;Christopher Pierson. ''Hard choices: social democracy in the twenty-first century''. Cambridge, England, UK; Oxford, England, UK; Malden, Massachusetts, USA: Polity Press, 2001. Pp. 25.&lt;/ref&gt; Non-Marxist adherents to social democracy arose, including the [[Fabian Society|Fabians]] in Britain.&lt;ref&gt;Ian Britain. Fabianism and Culture: A Study in British Socialism and the Arts c1884-1918. 2005 Paperback edition. Cambridge University Press, 2005. Pp. 258.&lt;/ref&gt;  The development of [[liberal socialism]] that began in the 1920s by figures such as [[G. D. H. Cole]], [[R. H. Tawney]], and [[Carlo Rosselli]] that fused [[Liberalism|liberal]] and socialist ideals while rejecting both Marxism and [[state socialism]], influenced social democracy, including influencing contemporary social democrats in favour of the [[Third Way (centrism)|Third Way]].&lt;ref&gt;Steve Bastow, James Martin. ''Third way discourse: European ideologies in the twentieth century''. Edinburgh, Scotland, UK: Edinburgh University Press, 2003. 72-79.&lt;/ref&gt; By the post-[[World War II]] period, most social democrats in Europe had abandoned their ideological connection to Marxism.&lt;ref&gt;Ian Adams. ''Political ideology today''. Greater Manchester, England, UK; New York, New York: Manchester University Press, 1993. Pp. 146.&lt;/ref&gt;

Critics of contemporary social democracy such as Jonas Hinnfors argue that when social democracy abandoned Marxism it also abandoned socialism and has become in effect a liberal capitalist movement.&lt;ref&gt;Jonas Hinnfors. Reinterpreting social democracy: a history of stability in the British Labour Party and Swedish Social Democratic Party. Greater Manchester, England, UK: Manchester University Press, 2006 Pp. 137-139, 117.&lt;/ref&gt; Those who believe that social democracy abandoned socialism contend that it did so in the 1930s by endorsing [[Keynesianism|Keynesian]] [[welfare capitalism]].&lt;ref&gt;Tony Fitzpatrick. ''After the new social democracy: social welfare for the twenty-first century''. Greater Manchester, England, UK: Manchester University Press, 2003. Pp. 2-3.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Roger Eatwell, Anthony Wright. ''Contemporary political ideologies''. Continuum International Publishing Group, 1999. Pp. 91.&lt;/ref&gt; Socialist political theorist [[Michael Harrington]] argues that social democracy historically supported Keynesianism as part of a &quot;social democratic compromise&quot; between capitalism and socialism. This compromise created [[welfare state]]s which Harrington contends that, although it did not allow for the immediate creation of socialism, it &quot;recognized noncapitalist, and even anticapitalist, principles of human need over and above the imperatives of profit&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Harrington. ''Socialism: Past and Future''. Reprint edition of original published in 1989. New York, New York, USA: Arcade Publishing, 2011. Pp. 93.&lt;/ref&gt; More recently, social democrats in favour of the Third Way have been accused of having endorsed capitalism, including by anti-Third Way social democrats who have accused Third Way proponents such as [[Anthony Giddens]] of being anti-social democratic and anti-socialist in practice.&lt;ref&gt;Sarah Hale, Will Leggett, Luke Martell. The Third Way and Beyond: Criticisms, Futures and Alternatives. Manchester University Press, 2004. Pp. 155.&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==

===Pre-reformist usage of the term &quot;social democracy&quot;, 1848-1889===
In the 19th Century, the term &quot;Social Democrat&quot; was used as a broad catch-all for international socialists owing their basic ideological allegiance to [[Karl Marx]] or [[Ferdinand Lassalle]], in contrast to those advocating various forms of [[utopian socialism]]. In one of the first scholarly works on European socialism written for an American audience, [[Richard T. Ely|Richard T. Ely's]] 1883 book, ''French and German Socialism in Modern Times,'' Social Democrats were characterized as &quot;the extreme wing of the socialists&quot; who were &quot;inclined to lay so much stress on equality of enjoyment, regardless of the value of one's labor, that they might, perhaps, more properly be called [[communists]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Richard T. Ely, ''French and German Socialism in Modern Times.'' New York: Harper and Brothers, 1883; pg. 204.&lt;/ref&gt; Ely continued:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;They have two distinguishing characteristics. The vast majority of them are laborers, and, as a rule, they expect the violent overthrow of existing institutions by revolution to precede the introduction of the socialistic state. I would not, by any means, say that they are all revolutionists, but the most of them undoubtedly are. *  *  * &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;The most general demands of the social democrats are the following: The state should exist exclusively for the laborers; land and capital must become collective property, and production be carried on unitedly. Private competition, in the ordinary sense of the term, is to cease.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Ely, ''French and German Socialism in Modern Times,'' pp. 204-205.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Many parties in this era described themselves as &quot;social democratic,&quot; including the [[General German Workers' Association]] and the [[Social Democratic Workers' Party of Germany]] (which merged to form the [[Social Democratic Party of Germany]]), the British [[Social Democratic Federation]], and the [[Russian Social Democratic Labour Party]]. The term &quot;social democracy&quot; continued to be used in this context up to the time of the [[Bolshevik Revolution]] of November 1917, at which time the term &quot;communist&quot; came into vogue for individuals and organizations espousing a revolutionary road to socialism.

===Second International era, 1889-1914===
[[File:Bernstein Eduard 1895.jpg|thumb|150px|right|[[Eduard Bernstein]]]]
The modern social democratic movement came into being through a division within the socialist movement, this division can be described as a parting of ways between those who insisted upon political revolution as a precondition for the achievement of socialist goals and those who maintained that a gradual or evolutionary path to socialism was both possible and desirable.&lt;ref name=Berman&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www8.georgetown.edu/centers/cdacs//bermanpaper.pdf|title=Understanding Social Democracy|author=Berman, Sheri|accessdate=2007-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

One of the key founders of contemporary social democracy was [[Eduard Bernstein]], a proponent of [[Reformism|reformist]] socialism and an adherent of Marxism. The term &quot;[[Revisionism|revisionist]]&quot; was applied to Bernstein by his critics who referred to themselves as [[Orthodox Marxism|&quot;orthodox&quot; Marxists]], even though Bernstein claimed that his principles were consistent with [[Karl Marx]]'s and [[Friedrich Engels]]' stances, especially in their later years when Marx and Engels advocated that socialism should be achieved through parliamentary democratic means where-ever possible.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Harrington. ''Socialism: Past and Future''. Reprint edition of original published in 1989. New York, New York, USA: Arcade Publishing, 2011. Pp. 42.&lt;/ref&gt; Revisionists have criticized orthodox Marxism and particularly its founder [[Karl Kautsky]], for having disregarded Marx's view of the necessity of evolution of capitalism to achieve socialism by replacing it with an &quot;either/or&quot; polarization between capitalism and socialism; for disregarding Marx's emphasis on the role of parliamentary democracy in achieving socialism; as well as criticizing Kautsky for his idealism of [[state socialism]].&lt;ref&gt;Michael Harrington. ''Socialism: Past and Future''. Reprint edition of original published in 1989. New York, New York, USA: Arcade Publishing, 2011. Pp. 43-59.&lt;/ref&gt;

Bernstein had held close association to Marx and Engels, but he saw flaws in Marxian thinking and began such criticism when he investigated and challenged the Marxian [[Materialism|materialist]] theory of history.&lt;ref&gt;Berman, Sheri. ''Social Democracy and the Making of Europe's Twentieth Century''. Cambridge University Press, 2006. Pp. 38-39.&lt;/ref&gt; He rejected significant parts of Marxian theory that were based upon [[Hegelian]] [[metaphysics]], he rejected the Hegelian dialectical perspective.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Harrington. ''Socialism: Past and Future''. Reprint edition of original published in 1989. New York, New York, USA: Arcade Publishing, 2011. P. 251.&lt;/ref&gt;  Bernstein declared that the massive and [[homogeneous]] working-class claimed in the ''[[Communist Manifesto]]'' did not exist, and that contrary to claims of a proletarian majority emerging, the middle-class was growing under capitalism and not disappearing as Marx had claimed. Bernstein noted that the working-class was not homogeneous but heterogeneous, with divisions and factions within it, including socialist and non-socialist trade unions. Marx himself later in his life acknowledged that the middle-class was not disappearing, in his work ''[[Theories of Surplus Value]]''. However due to the popularity of the ''Communist Manifesto'' and the obscurity of ''Theories of Surplus Value'', Marx's acknowledgement of this error is not well known.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Harrington. ''Socialism: Past and Future''. Reprint edition of original published in 1989. New York, New York, USA: Arcade Publishing, 2011. Pp. 249-250.&lt;/ref&gt;

Bernstein criticized Marxism's concept of &quot;irreconciliable [[class conflict]]s&quot; and Marxism's hostility to [[liberalism]].&lt;ref name=Steger133&gt;Manfred B. Steger,  ''The Quest for Evolutionary Socialism: Eduard Bernstein and Social Democracy.'' Cambridge, England: Cambridge University Press, 1997; pg. 133.&lt;/ref&gt; He challenged Marx's position on liberalism by claiming that [[Liberal democracy|liberal democrats]] and social democrats held common grounds that he claimed could be utilized to create a &quot;socialist republic&quot;.&lt;ref name=Steger133 /&gt; He believed that economic class disparities between the [[bourgeoisie]] and the [[proletariat]] would gradually be eliminated through legal reforms and economic redistribution programs.&lt;ref name=Steger133 /&gt; Bernstein rejected the [[Marxism|Marxian]] principle of [[dictatorship of the proletariat]], claiming that gradualist democratic reforms will improve the rights of the [[working class]].&lt;ref name=Steger141&gt;Steger,  ''The Quest for Evolutionary Socialism,'' pg. 141.&lt;/ref&gt; According to Bernstein, unlike orthodox Marxism, social democracy did not seek to create a socialism separate from bourgeois society but instead sought to create a common development based on Western humanism.&lt;ref&gt;Roger Eatwell, Anthony Wright. ''Contemporary political ideologies''. 2nd edition. Continuum International Publishing Group, 2000. Pp. 86.&lt;/ref&gt; The development of socialism under social democracy does not seek to rupture existing society and its cultural traditions but to act as an enterprise of extension and growth.&lt;ref&gt;Roger Eatwell, Anthony Wright. ''Contemporary political ideologies''. 2nd edition. Continuum International Publishing Group, 2000. Pp. 88.&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, he believed that class cooperation was a preferable course to achieve socialism, rather than class conflict.&lt;ref&gt;Berman, Sheri. ''Social Democracy and the Making of Europe's Twentieth Century''. Cambridge University Press, 2006. Pp. 2.&lt;/ref&gt; On the issue of class conflict and responding to the Marxian principle of dictatorship of the proletariat, Bernstein said:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
''&quot;No one thinks of destroying civil society as a community ordered in a civilized war. Quite to the contrary, Social Democracy does not want to break up civil society and make all its members proletarians together; rather, it ceaselessly labors to raise the worker from the social position of a proletarian to that of a citizen and thus make citizenship universal. It does not want to replace civil society with a proletarian society but a capitalist order of society with a socialist one.&quot;'' Eduard Bernstein&lt;ref&gt;Steger,  ''The Quest for Evolutionary Socialism,'' pg. 137.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Bernstein urged social democrats to be committed to a long-term agenda of transforming the capitalist economy to a socialist economy rather than a sudden upheaval of capitalism, saying:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
''&quot;Social democracy should neither expect nor desire the imminent collapse of the existing economic system … What social democracy should be doing, and doing for a long time to come, is organize the working class politically, train it for democracy, and fight for any and all reforms in the state which are designed to raise the working class and make the state more democratic.&quot;'' Eduard Bernstein&lt;ref&gt;Steger,  ''The Quest for Evolutionary Socialism,'' pg. 80.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Bernstein accepted a [[mixed economy]] for an unspecified amount of time:&lt;ref name=&quot;Steger, pg. 146&quot;&gt;Steger,  ''The Quest for Evolutionary Socialism,'' pg. 146.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
''&quot;It [socialism] would be completely mad to burden itself with the additional tasks of so complex a nature as the setting up and controlling of comprehensive state production centers on a mass scale – quite apart from the fact that only certain specific branches of production can be run on a national basis…Competition would have to be reckoned with, at least in the transitional period.&quot;'' Eduard Bernstein.&lt;ref name=&quot;Steger, pg. 146&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;''[...] in addition to public enterprises and cooperative enterprises, there are enterprises run by private individuals for their own gain. In time, they will of their own accord acquire a cooperative character.''&quot; Eduard Bernstein.&lt;ref&gt;Christopher Pierson. Hard choices: social democracy in the twenty-first century. Cambridge, England, UK; Oxford, England, UK; Malden, Massachusetts, USA: Polity Press, 2001. Pp. 25.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[File:Jean-Jaurès01.jpg|thumb|left|[[Jean Jaurès]]]]
[[File:Frank Podmore.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Frank Podmore]], founder of Britain's [[Fabian Society]].]]
Another prominent figure who influenced social democracy, was French revisionist Marxist and reformist socialist [[Jean Jaurès]]. During the 1904 Congress of the [[Second International]], Jaurès challenged orthodox Marxist [[August Bebel]], the mentor of Kautsky, over his promotion of monolithic socialist tactics. Jaurès claimed that no coherent socialist platform could be equally applicable to different countries and regions due to different political systems in them; noting that Bebel's homeland of Germany at the time was very authoritarian and had limited parliamentary democracy. He compared the limited political influence of socialism in government in Germany to the substantial influence that socialism had gained in France due to its stronger parliamentary democracy. He claimed that the example of the political differences between Germany and France demonstrated that monolithic socialist tactics were impossible, given the political differences of various countries.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Harrington. ''Socialism: Past and Future''. Reprint edition of original published in 1989. New York, New York, USA: Arcade Publishing, 2011. Pp. 47.&lt;/ref&gt;

===World War I, revolutions and counterrevolutions, 1914-1920===
As tensions between Europe's [[Great Powers]] escalated in the late 19th and early 20th centuries, Bernstein feared that Germany's [[arms race]] with other powers was threatening the possibility of a major war.&lt;ref name=&quot;Steger, Manfred B. 1997. pg. 217-218&quot;&gt;Steger, Manfred B. ''The Quest for Evolutionary Socialism: Eduard Bernstein And Social Democracy''. Cambridge, England, UK; New York, New York, USA: Cambridge University Press, 1997. pg. 217-218.&lt;/ref&gt; Bernstein's fears were realized with the outbreak of [[World War I]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Steger, Manfred B. 1997. pg. 217-218&quot;/&gt; 

Immediately after the outbreak of World War I, Bernstein traveled from Germany to Britain to meet with British Labour Party leader [[Ramsay MacDonald]]. Bernstein regarded the outbreak of the war with great dismay, but even though the two countries were at war with one another, MacDonald honoured Bernstein at the meeting.&lt;ref name=&quot;Steger, Manfred B. 1997. pg. 167&quot;&gt;Steger, Manfred B. ''The Quest for Evolutionary Socialism: Eduard Bernstein And Social Democracy''. Cambridge, England, UK; New York, New York, USA: Cambridge University Press, 1997. pg. 167.&lt;/ref&gt; In spite of Bernstein's and other social democrats' attempts to secure the unity of the Second International, with national tensions increasing between the countries at war, the Second International collapsed in 1914.&lt;ref name=&quot;Steger, Manfred B. 1997. pg. 217-218&quot;/&gt; Anti-war members of the [[Social Democratic Party of Germany]] (SPD) refused to support finances being given to the German government to support the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;Steger, Manfred B. 1997. pg. 217-218&quot;/&gt; However a nationalist-revisionist faction of SPD members led by [[Friedrich Ebert]], [[Gustav Noske]], and [[Philipp Scheidemann]], supported the war, arguing that Germany had the &quot;right to its territorial defense&quot; from the &quot;destruction of Tsarist despotism&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Steger, Manfred B. 1997. pg. 218-219&quot;&gt;Steger, Manfred B. ''The Quest for Evolutionary Socialism: Eduard Bernstein And Social Democracy''. Cambridge, England, UK; New York, New York, USA: Cambridge University Press, 1997. pg. 218-219.&lt;/ref&gt; The SPD's decision to support the war, including Bernstein's decision to support it, was heavily influenced by the fact that the German government lied to the German people, as it claimed that the only reason Germany had declared war on Russia was because Russia was preparing to invade [[East Prussia]], when in fact this was not the case.&lt;ref name=&quot;Steger, Manfred B. 1997. pg. 218-219&quot;&gt;Steger, Manfred B. ''The Quest for Evolutionary Socialism: Eduard Bernstein And Social Democracy''. Cambridge, England, UK; New York, New York, USA: Cambridge University Press, 1997. pg. 219.&lt;/ref&gt; Jaurès opposed France's intervention in the war and took a [[Pacifism|pacifist]] stance, but was soon assassinated in 1914.&lt;ref name=&quot;Steger, Manfred B. 1997. pg. 218-219&quot;/&gt; 

Bernstein soon resented the war and by October 1914 was convinced of the German government's war guilt; and contacted the orthodox Marxists of the SPD, to unite to push the SPD to take an anti-war stance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Steger, Manfred B. 1997. pg. 218-219&quot;/&gt; Kautsky attempted to put aside his differences with Bernstein and join forces in opposing the war, and Kautsky praised him for becoming a firm anti-war proponent, saying that although Bernstein had previously supported &quot;civic&quot; and &quot;liberal&quot; forms of nationalism, his committed anti-war position made him the &quot;standard-bearer of the internationalist idea of social democracy&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Steger, Manfred B. 1997. pg. 218-219&quot;/&gt; The nationalist position by the SPD leadership under Ebert refused to rescind.&lt;ref name=&quot;Steger, Manfred B. 1997. pg. 218-219&quot;/&gt; 

[[File:Arthurhenderson.jpg|thumb|150px|left|Arthur Henderson]]
[[File:Alexander Kerensky LOC 24416.jpg|thumb|150px|right|Alexander Kerensky]]
In Britain, the British Labour Party became divided on the war. Labour Party leader Ramsay MacDonald was one of a handful of British MPs who had denounced Britain's declaration of war on Germany. MacDonald was denounced by the pro-war press on accusations that he was &quot;pro-German&quot; and a pacifist, both charges that he denied.&lt;ref&gt;Spencer C. Tucker, Priscilla Mary Roberts. World War I: A Student Encyclopedia. Pp. 1158.&lt;/ref&gt; In response to pro-war sentiments in the Labour Party, MacDonald resigned from being its leader and associated himself with the [[Independent Labour Party]]. [[Arthur Henderson]] became the new leader of the Labour Party, and served as a cabinet minister in Prime Minister Asquith's war government. After the [[February Revolution]] of 1917 in Russia (not to be confused with the [[October Revolution]]) in which the Tsarist regime in Russia was overthrown by the [[Socialist-Revolutionary Party]], a democratic socialist movement led by [[Alexander Kerensky]], MacDonald visited the [[Russian Provisional Government]] in June 1917, seeking to persuade Russia to oppose the war and seek peace. His efforts to unite the Russian Provisional Government against the war failed after Russia fell back into political violence resulting in the October Revolution in which the Bolsheviks led [[Vladimir Lenin]]'s rise to power.&lt;ref&gt;Austen Morgan. J. Ramsay MacDonald. Manchester, England, UK: Manchester University Press, 1987. Pp. 69-70.&lt;/ref&gt; Though MacDonald critically responded to the Bolsheviks' political violence and rise to power by warning of &quot;the danger of anarchy in Russia&quot;, he gave political support to the Bolshevik regime until the end of the war because he then thought that a democratic internationalism could be revived.&lt;ref&gt;Austen Morgan. J. Ramsay MacDonald. Manchester, England, UK: Manchester University Press, 1987. Pp. 71.&lt;/ref&gt; The British Labour Party's trade union affiliated membership soared during World War I. Henderson with the assistance of [[Sidney Webb]] designed a new constitution for the British Labour Party, in which it adopted a strongly left-wing platform in 1918 to ensure that it would not lose support to the new Communist Party, exemplified by [[Clause IV]] of the new constitution of the Labour Party.&lt;ref&gt;David Rubinstein. The Labour Party and British Society: 1880-2005. Pp. 46-47.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 102-00015, Friedrich Ebert.jpg|thumb|150px|left|Friedrich Ebert, President of Germany, 1919-1925.]]
The overthrow of the Tsarist regime in Russia by Kerensky's Socialist-Revolutionaries in February 1917 impacted politics in Germany, as it ended the legitimation used by Ebert and other pro-war SPD members that Germany was in the war against a reactionary Russian government. With the overthrow of the Tsar and revolutionary socialist agitation increased in Russia, such events influenced socialists in Germany. With rising bread shortages in Germany amid war rationing, mass strikes occurred beginning in April 1917 with 300,000 strikers taking part in a strike in Berlin. The strikers demanded bread, freedom, peace, and the formation of workers' councils as was being done in Russia. Amidst the German public's uproar, the SPD alongside the Progressives and the Catholic labour movement in the [[Reichstag]] put forward the &quot;Peace Resolution&quot; on 19 July 1917 that called for a compromise peace to end the war, that was passed by a majority of members of the Reichstag. The German High Command opposed the Peace Resolution, however it did seek to end the war with Russia, and presented the [[Treaty of Brest-Litovsk]] to the Bolshevik regime in 1918 that agreed to the terms and the Reichstag passed the treaty, that included the support of the SPD, the Progressives, and the Catholic political movement.&lt;ref&gt;Roger Chickering. Imperial Germany and the Great War, 1914-1918. Pp. 155.&lt;/ref&gt; 

By late 1918 the war situation for Germany had become hopeless, and Kaiser Wilhelm II was pressured to make peace. Wilhelm II appointed a new cabinet that included SPD members in it. At the same time the Imperial Naval Command was determined to make a heroic last stand against the British Royal Navy, and on 24 October 1918 it issued orders for the German Navy to depart to confront while the sailors refused, resulting in the [[Kiel Mutiny]]. The Kiel Mutiny resulted in the [[German Revolution of 1918–1919]]. Faced with military failure and revolution, Chancellor Max [[Prince Maximillian of Baden]] resigned, giving SPD leader Ebert the position of Chancellor, Wihelm II abdicated the German throne immediately afterwards, and the German High Command officials [[Paul von Hindenburg]] and [[Erich Ludendorff]] resigned whilst refusing to end the war to save face, leaving the Ebert government and the SPD-majority Reichstag to be forced to make the inevitable peace with the Allies and take the blame for having lost the war. With the abdication of Wilhelm II, Ebert declared Germany to be a republic and signed the armistice that ended World War I on 11 November 1918.

The new social democratic government in Germany faced political violence in Berlin by a movement of communist revolutionaries known as the [[Spartacist League]] who sought to repeat the feat of Lenin and the Bolsheviks in Russia, by overthrowing the German government.&lt;ref name=&quot;TwoRed2&quot;&gt;The Two Red Flags: European Social Democracy and Soviet Communism Since 1945, p. 2&lt;/ref&gt; Tensions between the governing &quot;Majority&quot; Social Democrats (led by Ebert) versus the strongly left-wing elements of the Independent Social Democratic Party (USPD) and communists over Ebert's refusal to immediately reform the German Army, resulted in the &quot;January rising&quot; by the newly formed [[Communist Party of Germany]] (KPD) and the USPD, resulting in communists mobilizing a large workers' demonstration. The SPD responded by holding a counterdemonstration that was effective in demonstrating support for the government, and the USPD soon withdrew its support for the rising.&lt;ref name=&quot;Berman145&quot;&gt;Sheri Berman. ''The Social Democratic Moment:
Ideas and Politics in the Making of Interwar Europe''. Harvard University Press, 1998, p. 145.&lt;/ref&gt; However the communists continued to revolt, and between 12 to 28 January 1919, communist forces had seized control of several government buildings in Berlin. Ebert responded by requesting that Defense Minister [[Gustav Noske]] take charge of loyal soldiers to fight the communists and secure the government.&lt;ref name=&quot;TwoRed2&quot;/&gt; Ebert was furious with the communists' intransigence and said that he wished &quot;to teach the radicals a lesson they would never forget&quot;. Noske was able to rally groups of mostly reactionary ex-soldiers, known as the ''[[Freikorps]]'' who were eager to fight the communists. The situation soon went completely out of control when the recruited ''Freikorps'' went on a violent rampage against workers and murdered the communist leaders [[Karl Liebenknecht]] and [[Rosa Luxembourg]]. The atrocities by the government-recruited ''Freikorps'' against the communist revolutionaries badly tarnished the reputation of the SPD and strengthened the confidence of reactionary forces. In spite of this, the SPD was able to win the largest number of seats in the parliamentary election held on 19 January 1919 and Ebert was elected [[President of Germany]], but the USPD in response to the atrocities committed by the government-recruited ''Freikorps'', refused to support the SPD government.&lt;ref name=&quot;Berman145&quot;/&gt;

Due to the unrest in Berlin, the construction of the constitution of the new German republic was created in the city of [[Weimar]], and is referred to as the [[Weimar Republic]]. Upon founding the new government, President Ebert cooperated with liberal members of his coalition government to create the constitution, Ebert sought to begin a program of [[nationalization]]s of some parts of the economy. Political unrest and violence continued and the government's continued reliance on the help of the ''Freikorps'' counterrevolutionaries to fight the communist revolutionaries continued to alienate potential left-wing support for the SPD. The SPD coalition government's acceptance of the harsh peace conditions of the [[Treaty of Versailles]] in June 1919, infuriated the right, including the ''Freikorps'' that had previously been willing to cooperate with the government to fight the communists. In the German parliamentary election of June 1919, the SPD share of the vote declined significantly. In March 1920, a group of right-wing [[Militarism|militarists]] led by [[Wolfgang Kapp]] and former German military chief-of-staff Erich Ludendorff initiated a briefly successful [[putsch]] against the German government, in what became known as the [[Kapp Putsch]], however the putsch failed and the government was restored.&lt;ref&gt;Sheri Berman. ''The Social Democratic Moment:
Ideas and Politics in the Making of Interwar Europe''. Harvard University Press, 1998. Pp. 146.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Interwar period and the Great Depression, 1920-1939===
[[File:Noe Zhordania meets 2nd International delegation. 1920.jpg|thumb|300px|right|[[Noe Zhordania]] (man with white beard and wearing a white hat on the left side of the car), the President of newly independent Georgia, attending a meeting of the refounded Second International in Georgia 1920. The invasion of Georgia in 1921 and overthrow of Zhordania's elected social democratic government by Bolshevik Russia provoked outcry by social democrats as well as revolutionary Mensheviks.]]
[[File:Hjalmar branting stor bild.jpg|thumb|150px|right|Hjalmar Branting, Prime Minister of Sweden, 1920, 1921-1923, 1924-1925.]]

At a global level, after World War I several attempts were made to re-found the Second International that collapsed amidst national divisions in the war. The Vienna International formed in 1921 attempted to end the rift between reformist socialists - including social democrats; and revolutionary socialists - including communists, and particularly [[Mensheviks]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Naarden509&quot;&gt;Bruno Naarden. ''Socialist Europe and Revolutionary Russia: Perception and Prejudice 1848-1923''. First paperback edition. Cambridge, England, UK: Cambridge University Press, 2002, p. 509.&lt;/ref&gt; However a crisis soon erupted that involved the new country of Georgia led by a social democratic government led by President [[Noe Zhordania]], that had declared itself independent from Russia in 1918 whose government had been endorsed by multiple social democratic parties. At founding meeting of the Vienna International, the discussions were interrupted by the arrival of a telegram from President Zhordania who said that Georgia was under invasion by Bolshevik Russia. Delegates attending the International's founding meeting were stunned, particularly the Bolshevik representative from Russia, [[Mecheslav Bronsky]], who refused to believe this and left the meeting to seek confirmation of this, but upon confirmation Bronsky did not return to the meeting.&lt;ref name=&quot;Naarden425&quot;&gt;Bruno Naarden. ''Socialist Europe and Revolutionary Russia: Perception and Prejudice 1848-1923''. First paperback edition. Cambridge, England, UK: Cambridge University Press, 2002, p. 425.&lt;/ref&gt; The overall response from the Vienna International was divided, the Mensheviks demanded that the International immediately condemn Russia's aggression against Georgia, but the majority as represented by German delegate Alfred Henke sought to exercise caution and said that the delegates should wait for confirmation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Naarden509&quot;/&gt; Russia's invasion of Georgia completely violated the non-aggression treaty signed between Lenin and Zhordania, as well as violating Georgia's sovereignty by annexing Georgia directly into the [[Russian Soviet Federated Socialist Republic]]. Tensions between Bolsheviks and social democrats worsened with the [[Kronstadt rebellion]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Naarden425&quot;/&gt; Unrest by leftists against the Bolshevik government in Russia resulted in the Kronstadt rebellion, Russian social democrats distributed leaflets calling for a general strike against the Bolshevik regime, the Bolsheviks responded by forcefully repressing the rebels.&lt;ref&gt;Bruno Naarden. ''Socialist Europe and Revolutionary Russia: Perception and Prejudice 1848-1923''. First paperback edition. Cambridge, England, UK: Cambridge University Press, 2002. Pp. 434.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Relations between the social democratic movement and Bolshevik Russia descended into complete antagonism in response to the [[Russian famine of 1921]] and the Bolsheviks' violent repression of opposition to their government. Multiple social democratic parties were disgusted with Russia's Bolshevik regime, particularly Germany's SPD and the Netherlands' Social Democratic Workers' Party (SDAP) that denounced the Bolsheviks for defiling socialism and declared that the Bolsheviks had &quot;driven out the best of our comrades, thrown them into prison and put them to death&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Bruno Naarden. ''Socialist Europe and Revolutionary Russia: Perception and Prejudice 1848-1923''. First paperback edition. Cambridge, England, UK: Cambridge University Press, 2002. Pp. 441.&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 1923, social democrats united to found their own international, the [[Labour and Socialist International]] (LSI), founded in [[Hamburg]], Germany. The LSI declared that all its affiliated political parties would retain autonomy to make their own decisions regarding internal affairs of their countries; but that international affairs would be addressed by the LSI.&lt;ref name=&quot;Naarden509&quot;/&gt;  The LSI addressed the issue of the rise of [[fascism]], by declaring the LSI to be [[Anti-fascism|anti-fascist]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Larry Ceplair 1939. Pp. 78&quot;&gt;Larry Ceplair. Under the Shadow of War: Fascism, Anti-Fascism, and Marxists, 1918-1939. Pp. 78.&lt;/ref&gt; In response to the outbreak of the [[Spanish Civil War]] in 1936 between the democratically-elected Republican government versus the authoritarian right-wing Nationalists led by [[Francisco Franco]] with the support of [[Kingdom of Italy|Fascist Italy]] and [[Nazi Germany]], the Executive Committee of the LSI declared not only its support for the [[Second Spanish Republic|Spanish Republic]] but also that it supported the Spanish government having the right to purchase arms to fight Franco's Nationalist forces. LSI-affiliated parties, including the British Labour Party declared their support for the Spanish Republic.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Alpert. A New International History of the Spanish Civil War. Pp. 67.&lt;/ref&gt; However the LSI was criticized on the left for failing to put action into its anti-fascist rhetoric.&lt;ref name=&quot;Larry Ceplair 1939. Pp. 78&quot;/&gt; 

The stock market crash of 1929 that began an economic crisis in the United States that globally spread and became the [[Great Depression]] profoundly affected economic policymaking.&lt;ref name=&quot;Notermans102&quot;&gt;Ton Notermans. Money, Markets, and the State: Social Democratic Economic Policies since 1918. Pp. 102.&lt;/ref&gt; The collapse of the gold standard and the emergence of mass unemployment resulted in multiple governments recognizing the need for state macroeconomic intervention to reduce unemployment as well as economic intervention to stabilize prices, a proto-Keynesianism that [[John Maynard Keynes]] himself would soon publicly endorse.&lt;ref&gt;Ton Notermans. Money, Markets, and the State: Social Democratic Economic Policies since 1918. Pp. 102, 110.&lt;/ref&gt; Multiple social democratic parties declared the need for substantial investment in economic infrastructure projects to respond to unemployment, and creating social control over money flow. Furthermore, social democratic parties declared that the Great Depression demonstrated the need for substantial macroeconomic planning while their pro-property rights opponents staunchly opposed this.&lt;ref&gt;Ton Notermans. Money, Markets, and the State: Social Democratic Economic Policies since 1918. Pp. 111.&lt;/ref&gt; However attempts by social democratic governments to achieve this were unsuccessful due to the ensuing political instability in their countries from the depression, the British Labour Party became internally split over the policies while Germany's SPD government did not have the time to implement such policies as Germany's politics turned to violent civil unrest in which the Nazis rose to power in 1933 and dismantled parliamentary democracy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Notermans102&quot;/&gt;

A major development for social democracy was the victories of several social democratic parties in [[Scandinavia]], particularly the [[Social Democratic Party of Sweden]] (SAP) in the 1920 Swedish election.&lt;ref&gt;Francis Sejersted. The Age of Social Democracy: Norway and Sweden in the Twentieth Century. Princeton, New Jersey, USA: Princeton University Press, 2011. Pp. 180.&lt;/ref&gt; The SAP was elected to a [[minority government]]. It created a Socialization Committee that declared support for a [[mixed economy]] that combined the best of private initiative with social ownership or control, it supported substantial socialization &quot;of all necessary natural resources, industrial enterprises, credit institutions, transportation and communication routes&quot; that would be gradually transferred to the state.&lt;ref name=&quot;Preston T. King 1996. Pp. 44&quot;&gt;Preston T. King. ''Socialism and the Common Good: New Fabian Essays''. London, England, UK; Portland, Oregon, USA: Frank Cass, 1996. Pp. 44.&lt;/ref&gt; It permitted private ownership outside of these areas.&lt;ref name=&quot;Preston T. King 1996. Pp. 44&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Ramsay MacDonald ggbain 35734.jpg|thumb|150px|left|Ramsay MacDonald, Prime Minister of the United Kingdom, 1924, 1929-1935.]]
[[File:Gandhi at Darwen with women.jpg|thumb|right|[[Mohandas Gandhi]] meeting with women textile workers in Britain. Gandhi was a leadership figure of India's anti-colonial and social democratic [[Indian National Congress]].]]
In 1922 Ramsay MacDonald returned to the leadership of the Labour Party from the Independent Labour Party.  in the 1924 British election the Labour Party won a plurality of seats and was elected as a minority government but required assistance from the Liberal Party to have a majority of the parliament. Opponents of the Labour Party accused the party of communist sympathies. Prime Minister MacDonald responded to these allegations by stressing the party's commitment to reformist gradualism and openly opposing the radical wing in the party.&lt;ref&gt;Kevin Morgan. Ramsay MacDonald. London, England, UK: Haus Publishing Ltd, 2006. Pp. 43-44.&lt;/ref&gt; MacDonald emphasized that the Labour minority government's first and foremost commitment was to uphold democratic responsible government over all other policies. MacDonald emphasized this because he knew that any attempt to pass major socialist legislation in a minority government status would endanger the new government because it would be opposed and blocked by the Conservatives and the Liberals who together held a majority of seats. The Labour Party had risen to power in the aftermath of Britain's severe recession of 1921-1922, with the economy beginning to recover, British trade unions demanded that their wages be restored from the cuts they took in the recession. The trade unions soon became deeply dissatisfied with the MacDonald government and labour unrest and threat of strikes arose in transportation sector, including docks and railways. MacDonald viewed the situation as a crisis, consulting the unions in advance to warn them that his government would have to use strikebreakers if the situation continued. The anticipated clash between the government and the unions was averted, however the situation alienated the unions from the MacDonald government. MacDonald's most controversial action was having Britain recognize the government of the Soviet Union in February 1924. The British Conservative press, including the ''[[Daily Mail]]'' used this to promote a [[red scare]], claiming that the Labour government's recognition of the Soviet Union proved that Labour held pro-Bolshevik sympathies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jeffreys29&quot;&gt;{{Citation |first=Kevin |last=Jeffreys |title=Leading Labour: From Keir Hardie to Tony Blair |page=29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The British Labour Party lost the 1924 election and a Conservative government was elected. Though MacDonald faced multiple challenges to his leadership of the party, the party stabilized by 1927 as a capable opposition party to the Conservative government. MacDonald released a new political programme for the party titled ''[[Labour and the Nation]]'' (1928). The Labour Party returned to government in 1929, but soon faced the economic catastrophe of the stock market crash of 1929.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jeffreys29&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 102-06069, Rudolf Hilferding mit Gattin.jpg|thumb|left|SPD policymaker [[Rudolf Hilferding]] along with his wife, psychologist [[Margarete Hilferding]]. Mr. Hilferding became a major figure for the [[Sopade]], the name for the SPD in exile after Germany's Nazi regime banned all opposition parties. He and his wife were both Jewish and were killed by the Nazis during the [[Holocaust]].]]
In the 1920s, SPD policymaker and Marxist [[Rudolf Hilferding]] proposed substantial policy changes in the SPD as well as influencing social democratic and socialist theory. Hilferding was an influential Marxian socialist both in social democracy and outside it, such as his pamphlet titled ''Imperialism'' influencing Lenin's own conception of imperialism in the 1910s. Prior to the 1920s Hilferding declared that capitalism had evolved beyond what had been laissez-faire capitalism into what he called &quot;organized capitalism&quot;. Organized capitalism was based upon [[Trust (monopoly)|trusts]] and [[cartel]]s controlled by financial institutions that could no longer make money within their countries' national boundaries and thus needed to export to survive, resulting in support for imperialism.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Harrington. ''Socialism: Past and Future''. Reprint edition of original published in 1989. New York, New York, USA: Arcade Publishing, 2011. Pp. 56.&lt;/ref&gt; Hilferding described that while early capitalism promoted itself as peaceful and based on free trade, the era of organized capitalism was aggressive and said that &quot;in the place of humanity there came the idea of the strength and power of the state&quot;. He said that this had the consequence of creating effective collectivization within capitalism and had prepared the way for socialism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harrington57&quot;&gt;Michael Harrington. ''Socialism: Past and Future''. Reprint edition of original published in 1989. New York, New York, USA: Arcade Publishing, 2011. Pp. 57.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Originally Hilferding's vision of a socialism replacing organized capitalism was highly Kautskyan in assuming an either/or perspective, expecting a catastrophic clash between organized capitalism versus socialism. However by the 1920s, Hilferding became an adherent to promoting a gradualist evolution of capitalism into socialism. He then praised organized capitalism for being a step towards socialism, saying at the SPD congress in 1927 that &quot;''organized capitalism''&quot; is nothing less than &quot;''the replacement of the capitalist principle of free competition by the socialist principle of planned production''&quot;. He went on to say that &quot;''the problem is posed to our generation: with the help of the state, with the help of conscious social direction, to transform the economy organized and led by capitalists into an economy directed by the democratic state.''&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harrington57&quot;/&gt;

In the 1930s, the SPD began to transition away from revisionist Marxism towards [[liberal socialism]] beginning in the 1930s. After the party was banned by the Nazis in 1933, the SPD acted in exile through the [[Sopade]].&lt;ref&gt;Lewis Joachim Edinger. ''German exile politics: the Social Democratic Exexctive Committee in the Nazi era''. University of California Press, 1956. Pp. 215.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1934 the Sopade began to publish material that indicated that the SPD was turning towards liberal socialism. Sopade member [[Curt Geyer]] was a prominent proponent of liberal socialism within the Sopade, and declared that Sopade represented the tradition of Weimar Republic social democracy - liberal democratic socialism, and declared that Sopade's held true to its mandate of traditional liberal principles combined with the political realism of socialism.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis Joachim Edinger. ''German exile politics: the Social Democratic Exexctive Committee in the Nazi era''. University of California Press, 1956. Pp. 219-220.&lt;/ref&gt; After the restoration of democracy in West Germany, The SPD's [[Godesberg Program]] in 1959 eliminated the party's remaining Marxist-aligned policies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dietrich Orlow 2000. Pp. 108&quot;&gt;Dietrich Orlow. ''Common destiny:a comparative history of the Dutch, French, and German social democratic parties, 1945-1969''. Berghahn Books, 2000. Pp. 108.&lt;/ref&gt; The SPD then became officially based upon ''freiheitlicher Sozialismus'' (liberal socialism).&lt;ref name=&quot;Dietrich Orlow 2000. Pp. 108&quot;/&gt; West German Chancellor Willy Brandt has been identified as a liberal socialist.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephen Eric Bronner 1999. Pp. 104&quot;&gt;Stephen Eric Bronner. Ideas in action: political tradition in the twentieth century. Lanham Maryland, USA; Oxford, England, UK: Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers, Inc., 1999. Pp. 104.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Myrdal 1934.jpg|thumb|150px|right|[[Alva Myrdal]], an early prominent female figure in the Sweden's SAP in the 1930s, and a pioneer in the development of the social welfare state in Sweden.]]
The only social democratic governments in Europe that remained by the early 1930s were in Scandinavia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Notermans102&quot;/&gt; In the 1930s several Swedish social democratic leadership figures, including former Swedish Prime Minister [[Rickard Sandler]] - the secretary and chairman of the Socialization Committee, and [[Nils Karleby]], rejected earlier SAP socialization policies pursued in the 1920s for being to extreme.&lt;ref name=&quot;Preston T. King 1996. Pp. 44&quot;/&gt; Karlby and Sanders developed a new conception of social democratic socialism: the [[Nordic model|social market economy]] that called for gradual socialization and redistribution of purchasing power, provision of educational opportunity, support of property rights, permitting private enterprise on the condition that it adheres to the principle that the resources of which it disposes are in reality public means, and the creation of a broad category of social welfare rights.&lt;ref&gt;Preston T. King. ''Socialism and the Common Good: New Fabian Essays''. London, England, UK; Portland, Oregon, USA: Frank Cass, 1996. Pp. 44-45.&lt;/ref&gt; The new SAP government of 1932, replaced the previous government's universal commitment to a  [[balanced budget]] to a Keynesian-like commitment to a balanced budget within a [[business cycle]]. Unlike the 1921-1923 SAP governments that had run large deficits, after a strong increase in state expenditure in 1933, the SAP government reduced Sweden's budget deficit, the government had scheduled Sweden to have its budget deficit eliminated in seven years, however it took only three years to eliminate the deficit and Sweden held a budget surplus from 1936 to 1938. However this policy was criticized because although the budget deficit had been eliminated, major unemployment still remained in Sweden.&lt;ref&gt;Ton Notermans. Money, Markets, and the State: Social Democratic Economic Policies since 1918. Pp. 121.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:General Lázaro Cárdenas del Río.jpg|thumb|left|Lázaro Cárdenas, President of Mexico, 1934-1940.]]
[[File:JamesSc.JPG|thumb|150px|right|[[James Scullin]], Prime Minister of Australia, 1929-1932.]]
In the [[Americas]] from the 1920s to 1930s, social democracy was rising as a major political force. In [[Mexico]], several social democratic governments and presidents were elected from the 1920s to the 1930s. The most important Mexican social democratic government of this time was that led by President [[Lázaro Cárdenas]] and the [[Institutional Revolutionary Party|Party of the Mexican Revolution]] whose government initiated agrarian reform that broke up vast aristocratic estates and redistributing property to peasants. Cárdenas was deeply committed to social democracy, but was criticized by his left-wing opponents for being pro-capitalist due to his personal association with a wealthy family and for being corrupt due to his government's exemption from agrarian reform of the estate held by former Mexican President [[Alvaro Obregón]]. Political violence in Mexico had become serious in the 1920s with the [[Cristero War]] in which right-wing reactionary clericals fought against the left-wing government that was attempting to institute secularization of Mexico. Furthermore, Cardenas' government openly supported Spain's Republican government while opposing [[Francisco Franco]]'s Nationalists during the [[Spanish Civil War]]. During the Spanish Civil War, Cárdenas staunchly asserted that Mexico was progressive and socialist - working with socialists of various types including communists, and accepted refugees from Spain as well as accepting communist renegade [[Leon Trotsky]] as a refugee after [[Joseph Stalin]] removed Trotsky and sought to have him killed. Cárdenas strengthened the rights of Mexico's labour movement, nationalized foreign oil companies, and controversially supported peasants in their struggle against landlords by allowing them to form militias to fight the private armies of landlords in the country. Cárdenas' actions deeply aggravated right-wing reactionaries and there was fear that Mexico would succumb to civil war. Cardenas stepped down as Mexican President and supported a compromise presidential candidate who held support from business interests, in order to avoid further antagonizing the right-wing that could have caused a civil war.&lt;ref&gt;W. Dirk Raat (ed.), William H. Beezley (ed.). ''Twentieth-Century Mexico''. Pp. 13.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cold War period (1945-1979)===
{{See also|History of socialism}}
[[File:Awolowo-Obafemi.JPG|thumb|150px|right|[[Obafemi Awolowo]], Premier of the Nigerian province of Western Nigeria, 1954-1960. Founder of the [[Unity Party of Nigeria]], and a prominent Nigerian social democratic figure.]]
After World War II, a new international organization to represent social democracy and democratic socialism, the [[Socialist International]] in 1951. In the founding [[Frankfurt Declaration]], the Socialist International denounced both capitalism and [[Bolshevik]] communism. As for Bolshevik communism, the Declaration denounced it in articles 7, 8, 9, and 10, saying:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
*7. Meanwhile, as Socialism advances throughout the world, new forces have arisen to threaten the movement towards freedom and social justice. Since the Bolshevik Revolution in Russia, Communism has split the International Labour Movement and has set back the realisation of Socialism in many countries for decades.&lt;ref name=&quot;socialistinternational.org&quot;/&gt;

*8. Communism falsely claims a share in the Socialist tradition. In fact it has distorted that tradition beyond recognition. It has built up a rigid theology which is incompatible with the critical spirit of Marxism.&lt;ref name=&quot;socialistinternational.org&quot;/&gt;

*9. Where Socialists aim to achieve freedom and justice by removing the exploitation which divides men under capitalism, Communists seek to sharpen those class divisions only in order to establish the dictatorship of a single party.&lt;ref name=&quot;socialistinternational.org&quot;/&gt;

*10. International Communism is the instrument of a new imperialism. Wherever it has achieved power it has destroyed freedom or the chance of gaining freedom. It is based on a militarist bureaucracy and a terrorist police. By producing glaring contrasts of wealth and privilege it has created a new class society. Forced labour plays an important part in its economic organisation.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;socialistinternational.org&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv B 145 Bild-F033246-0022, Bonn, Bundestag, Rede Bundeskanzler Brandt.jpg|thumb|250px|left|[[Willy Brandt]], Chancellor of West Germany, 1969-1974.]]
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-61849-0001, Indien, Otto Grotewohl bei Ministerpräsident Nehru cropped.jpg|thumb|right|150px|[[Jawaharlal Nehru]], Prime Minister of India, 1947-1964.]]
India upon becoming a sovereign state in 1947, elected the social democratic [[Indian National Congress]] to government with its leader [[Jawaharlal Nehru]] becoming Indian Prime Minister. Nehru declared &quot;In Europe, we see many countries have advanced very far on the road to socialism. I am not referring to the communist countries but to those which may be called parliamentary, social democratic countries.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;S. P. Agrawal, J. C. Aggarwal. Nehru On Social Issues. Concept Publishing Company, 1989. Pp. 85.&lt;/ref&gt; In power, Nehru's government emphasized state-guided national development of India, he took inspiration from social democracy, though India's newly formed Planning Commission also took inspiration from post-1949 China's agricultural policies.&lt;ref&gt;Mark T. Berger. ''The Battle for Asia: From decolonization to globalization''. Oxon, England, UK; New York, New York, USA: RoutledgeCurzon, 2004. Pp. 73.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Neoliberalism and social democratic response, contemporary period, 1979 to present===
[[File:Olof Palme statsminister, tidigt 70-tal.jpg|thumb|150px|right|[[Olof Palme]], Prime Minister of Sweden, 1969-1976, 1982-1986.]]
[[File:Indira2.jpg|thumb|left|150px|[[Indira Gandhi]], Prime Minister of India, 1966-1977, 1980-1984.]]

The economic crisis in the Western world during the mid to late 1970s resulted in the rise of [[neoliberalism]] and politicians elected on neoliberal platforms such as British Prime Minister [[Margaret Thatcher]] and US President [[Ronald Reagan]]. The rise in support for neoliberalism raised questions over the political viability of social democracy, such as sociologist [[Ralf Dahrendorf]] predicting the &quot;end of the social democratic century&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;After the Third Way: The Future of Social Democracy in Europe. I.B. Taurus, 2012. Pp. 4.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1985, an agreement was made between several social democratic parties in the Western bloc countries of Belgium, Denmark, and the Netherlands; with the communist parties of the Eastern Bloc countries of Bulgaria, East Germany, and Hungary; to have multilateral discussions on trade, nuclear disarmament and other issues.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oudenaren144&quot;&gt;John Van Oudenaren. Detente in Europe: The Soviet Union &amp; The West Since 1953. Duke University Press, 1991, p. 144.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1989, the Socialist International adopted its present Declaration of Principles. The Declaration of Principles addressed issues concerning the &quot;internationalization of the economy&quot;. The Declaration of Principles defined its interpretation of the nature of socialism. It stated that socialist values and vision include &quot;a peaceful and democratic world society combining freedom, justice and solidarity&quot;. It defined the rights and freedoms it supported, stating: &quot;Socialists protect the inalienable right to life and to physical safety, to freedom of belief and free expression of opinion, to freedom of association and to protection from torture and degradation. Socialists are committed to achieve freedom from hunger and want, genuine social security, and the right to work.&quot; However it also clarified that it did not promote any fixed and permanent definition for socialism, stating: &quot;Socialists do not claim to possess the blueprint for some final and fixed society which cannot be changed, reformed or further developed. In a movement committed to democratic self-determination there will always be room for creativity since each people and every generation must set its own goals.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Declaration of Principles''. Socialist International, 1989. http://www.socialistinternational.org/viewArticle.cfm?ArticleID=31&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Nelson Mandela-2008 (edit).jpg|thumb|150px|left|[[Nelson Mandela]], President of South Africa, 1994-1999. Mandela became the first non-white to be elected South African President after the dismantlement of [[apartheid]].]]
The 1989 Socialist International congress was politically significant in that members of [[Communist Party of the Soviet Union]] during the reformist leadership of [[Mikhail Gorbachev]], attended the congress. The SI's new Declaration of Principles abandoned previous statements made in the Frankfurt Declaration of 1951 against Soviet-style communism. After the congress, the Soviet state newspaper ''[[Pravda]]'' noted that thanks to dialogue between the Soviet Communist Party and the SI since 1979 that &quot;the positions of the CPSU and the Socialist International on nuclear disarmament issues today virtually coincide&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oudenaren144&quot;/&gt;

The collapse of the Marxist-Leninist regimes in Eastern Europe after the end of the Cold War, and the creation of multiparty democracy in many many of those countries, resulted in the creation of multiple social democratic parties. Though many of these parties did not achieve initial electoral success, they became a significant part of the political landscape of Eastern Europe. In Western Europe, the prominent [[Italian Communist Party]] transformed itself into the post-communist [[Democratic Party of the Left]] in 1991.&lt;ref&gt;Peter Lamb, J. C. Docherty. Historical Dictionary of Socialism. Oxford, England, UK: Scarecrow Press, 2006, p. 82.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Anthony Giddens at the Progressive Governance Converence, Budapest, Hungary, 2004 October.jpg|thumb|150px|right|[[Anthony Giddens]], a prominent proponent of Third Way politics.]]
A highly controversial development in social democracy occurred in the 1990s, with the development of [[Third Way]] politics and social democratic adherents of it. The social democratic variant of the Third Way has been advocated by its proponents as an alternative to both capitalism and what it regards as the traditional forms of socialism, including [[Socialism (Marxism)|Marxist socialism]] and [[state socialism]], that Third Way social democrats reject. It officially advocates [[ethical socialism]], [[reformism]], [[gradualism]] - that includes advocating the humanized capitalism, a [[mixed economy]], political pluralism, and [[liberal democracy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Arora922&quot;&gt;N.D. Arora. ''Political Science for Civil Services Main Examination''. Tata McGraw-Hill Education, 2010. 9.22.&lt;/ref&gt; Left-wing opponents of Third Way social democracy claim that it is not a form of socialism, and claim that it represents social democrats who responded to the [[New Right]] by accepting [[capitalism]].&lt;ref&gt;Flavio Romano. Clinton and Blair: the political economy of the third way. Oxon, England, UK; New York, New York, USA: Routledge, 2006. Pp. 5.&lt;/ref&gt;  The Third Way has been strongly criticized within the social democratic movement.&lt;ref&gt;Sarah Hale, Will Leggett, Luke Martell. ''The Third Way and Beyond: Criticisms, Futures and Alternatives''. Manchester University Press, 2004, p. 155.&lt;/ref&gt;

Third Way supporter and former British Prime Minister [[Tony Blair]] when he was a British Labour Party MP wrote in a Fabian pamphlet in 1994 of the existence of two prominent variants of socialism: one is based on a [[Marxism|Marxist]] economic determinist and collectivist tradition that he rejected, and the other is an &quot;ethical socialism&quot; that he supported, that was based on values of &quot;social justice, the equal worth of each citizen, equality of opportunity, community&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Stephen D. Tansey, Nigel A. Jackson. ''Politics: the basics''. Fourth Edition. Oxon, England, UK; New York, New York, USA: Routledge, 2008. Pp. 97.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Prominent Third Way  proponent [[Anthony Giddens]] views conventional socialism as essentially having become obsolete. However Giddens claims that a viable form of socialism was advocated by [[Anthony Crosland]] in his major work ''[[The Future of Socialism]]'' (1956).&lt;ref name=&quot;Giddens67&quot;&gt;Anthony Giddens. ''Beyond Left and Right: The Future of Radical Politics''. 1998 edition. Cambridge, England, UK: Polity Press, 1994, 1998, p. 67.&lt;/ref&gt; Giddens has complimented Crosland as well as [[Thomas Humphrey Marshall]] for promoting a viable socialism.&lt;ref&gt;Anthony Giddens. ''Beyond Left and Right: The Future of Radical Politics''. 1998 edition. Cambridge, England, UK: Polity Press, 1994, 1998. Pp. 73.&lt;/ref&gt; Giddens views what he considers the conventional form of socialism - state socialism - that defines socialism as a theory of economic management, as nor longer viable.&lt;ref&gt;Sarah Hale, Will Leggett, Luke Martell. The Third Way and Beyond: Criticisms, Futures and Alternatives. Manchester University Press, 2004. Pp. 152.&lt;/ref&gt; Giddens rejects what he considers top-down socialism as well as rejecting neoliberalism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Arora922&quot;/&gt; Giddens criticizes conventional socialism for its common advocacy that socialization of production, as achieved by [[central planning]], can overcome the irrationalities of capitalism. Giddens claims that this claim &quot;can no longer be defended&quot;. He says that with the collapse of legitimacy of centrally-planned socialization of production, &quot;With its dissolution, the radical hopes for by socialism are as dead as the Old Conservatism that opposed them&quot;. Giddens says that although there have been proponents of [[market socialism]] who have rejected such central planned socialism as well as being resistant to capitalism, that &quot;There are good reasons, in my view, to argue that market socialism isn't a realistic possibility&quot;. Giddens makes clear that Third Way as he envisions it, is not market socialist and says &quot;There is no Third Way of this sort, and with this realization the history of socialism as the avant-garde of political theory comes to a close.&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Giddens67&quot;/&gt;

However Giddens commends Crosland's ''A Future of Socialism'' for recognizing that socialism cannot be defined merely in terms of a rejection of capitalism, because if capitalism did end and was replaced with socialism, then socialism would have no purpose with the absence of capitalism.&lt;ref&gt;Anthony Giddens. ''Beyond Left and Right: The Future of Radical Politics''. 1998 edition. Cambridge, England, UK: Polity Press, 1994, 1998.  Pp. 71.&lt;/ref&gt; From Crosland's analysis, Giddens proposes a description of socialism:
{{quote|''The only common characteristic of socialist doctrines is their ethical content. Socialism is the pursuit of ideas of social cooperation, universal welfare, and equality - ideas brought together by a condemnation of the evils and injustices of capitalism. It is based on the critique of individualism and depends on a 'belief in group action and &quot;participation&quot;, and collective responsibility for social welfare'.''|Anthony Giddens, ''Beyond Left and Right: The Future of Radical Politics''.&lt;ref&gt;Anthony Giddens. ''Beyond Left and Right: The Future of Radical Politics''. 1998 edition. Cambridge, England, UK: Polity Press, 1994, 1998. Pp. 71.&lt;/ref&gt;}} 

Paul Cammack has condemned the Third Way as conceived by Anthony Giddens as being a complete attack upon the foundations of social democracy and socialism in which Giddens has sought to replace them with capitalism. Cammack claims that Giddens devotes more energy into criticizing conventional social democracy and conventional socialism, including Giddens' claim that conventional socialism has &quot;died&quot; because Marx's vision of a new economy with wealth spread in an equitable way is not possible, while at the same time making no criticism of capitalism. As such, Cammack condemns Giddens and his Third Way for being anti-social-democratic, anti-socialist, and pro-capitalist that Giddens disguises in rhetoric to make appealing within social democracy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hale155&quot;&gt;Sarah Hale, Will Leggett, Luke Martell. The Third Way and Beyond: Criticisms, Futures and Alternatives. Manchester University Press, 2004, p. 155.&lt;/ref&gt;

British political theorist [[Robert Corfe]] who was in the past a social democratic proponent of a new socialism free of class-based prejudices, criticized both Marxist classists and Third Way proponents within the Labour Party.&lt;ref&gt;Robert Corfe, The Future of Politics. Pp. 178.&lt;/ref&gt; Corfe has denounced the Third Way as developed by Giddens for &quot;intellectual emptiness and ideological poverty&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Robert Corfe, The Future of Politics. Pp. 33.&lt;/ref&gt; Corfe has despondently noted and agreed with former long-term British Labour Party MP [[Alice Mahon]]'s statement in which she said &quot;Labour is the party of bankers, not workers. The party has lost its soul, and what has replace it is harsh, American style politics...&quot; Corfe claims that the failure to develop a new socialism has resulted in what he considers the &quot;death of socialism&quot; that left social capitalism as only feasible alternative.&lt;ref&gt;Robert Corfe, The Future of Politics. Pp. 33, 178.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Oskar Lafontaine, 2011-03-21.jpg|thumb|left|[[Oskar Lafontaine]], co-founder of Germany's political party [[The Left (Germany)|The Left]]. Lafontaine had been chairman of the SPD, but resigned and left the party out of opposition to the SPD's adoption of Third Way positions.]]
Former SPD chairman [[Oskar Lafontaine]] condemned then-SPD leader and German Chancellor [[Gerhard Schröder]] for his Third Way policies, saying that the SPD under Schröder had adopted &quot;a radical change of direction towards a policy of neoliberalism&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Sarah Hale, Will Leggett, Luke Martell. The Third Way and Beyond: Criticisms, Futures and Alternatives. Manchester University Press, 2004. Pp. 18.&lt;/ref&gt; After resigning from the SPD, Lafontaine co-founded [[The Left (Germany)|The Left]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Oskar Lafontaine 2009. Pp. 7&quot;&gt;Oskar Lafontaine. Left Parties Everywhere? Spokesman Books, 2009. Pp. 7.&lt;/ref&gt; The Left was founded out of a merger of the [[Party of Democratic Socialism (Germany)|Party of Democratic Socialism]] (PDS) and [[Labour and Social Justice – The Electoral Alternative]] (WASG) - a breakaway faction from the SPD. The Left has been controversial because as a direct successor to the PDS, it is also a direct successor of former [[East Germany]]'s ruling Marxist-Leninist [[Socialist Unity Party]] (SED) that transformed into the PDS after the end of the Cold War. However the PDS did not continue the SED's policies, as the PDS adopted policies to appeal to democratic socialists, greens, feminists, and pacifists.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hudson1_2&quot;&gt;Kate Hudson. The New European Left: A Socialism for the Twenty-First Century? Hampshire, England, UK; New York, New York, USA: Palgrave Macmillan, 2012. Pp. 1-2.&lt;/ref&gt; Lafontaine said in an interview that he supports the type of social democracy pursued by [[Willy Brandt]] but claims that the creation of The Left was necessary because &quot;formerly socialist and social democratic parties&quot; had effectively accepted [[neoliberalism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Oskar Lafontaine 2009. Pp. 7&quot;/&gt; The Left grew in strength and in the 2009 German parliamentary election gained 11 percent of the vote while the SPD gained 23 percent of the vote.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hudson1_2&quot;/&gt;

Lafontaine has noted that the founding of The Left in Germany has resulted in emulation in other countries, with several Left parties being founded in Greece, Portugal, Netherlands, and Syria.&lt;ref&gt;Oskar Lafontaine. Left Parties Everywhere? Spokesman Books, 2009. Pp. 3.&lt;/ref&gt; Lafontaine claims that a ''[[de facto]]'' British Left movement exists, identifying British Green Party MEP [[Caroline Lucas]] as holding similar values.&lt;ref&gt;Oskar Lafontaine. Left Parties Everywhere? Spokesman Books, 2009. Pp. 4.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Jack Layton - 2011.jpg|thumb|150px|right|[[Jack Layton]], leader of the [[New Democratic Party]] of Canada, 2003-2011. Layton led the party to become the second largest Canadian political party, for the first time in its history.]]
Others have claimed that social democracy needs to move past the Third Way, such as Olaf Cramme and Patrick Diamond in their book ''After the Third Way: The Future of Social Democracy in Europe'' (2012).&lt;ref&gt;After the Third Way: The Future of Social Democracy in Europe. I.B. Taurus, 2012. Pp. 47.&lt;/ref&gt; Cramme and Diamond recognize that the Third Way arose as an attempt to break down the traditional dichotomy within social democracy between state intervention and markets in the economy, however they contend that the [[2007–2012 global economic crisis|global financial crisis of the late 2000s]] requires that social democracy must rethink its political economy. Cramme and Diamond note that optimism in economic planning amongst socialists was strong in the early to mid-twentieth century, but declined with the rise of the neoliberal right that both attacked economic planning and associated the left with economic planning. They claim that this formed the foundation of the &quot;Right's moral trap&quot; in which the neoliberal right attacks on economic planning policies by the left, that provokes a defense of such planning by the left as being morally necessary, and ends with the right then rebuking such policies as being inherently economically incompetent while presenting itself as the champion of economic competence.&lt;ref&gt;After the Third Way: The Future of Social Democracy in Europe. I.B. Taurus, 2012. Pp. 50.&lt;/ref&gt; Cramme and Diamond state that social democracy has four different strategies both to address the economic crisis in global markets at present that it could adopt in response: market conforming, market complimenting, market resisting, market substituting, and market transforming.&lt;ref&gt;After the Third Way: The Future of Social Democracy in Europe. I.B. Taurus, 2012. Pp. 54.&lt;/ref&gt;

Cramme and Diamond identify market conforming as being equivalent to historic social democratic policymaker [[Philip Snowden]]'s desire for a very moderate socialist agenda based above all upon fiscal prudence, as Snowden insisted that socialism had to build upon fiscal prudence or else it would not be achieved.&lt;ref&gt;After the Third Way: The Future of Social Democracy in Europe. I.B. Taurus, 2012. Pp. 54-55.&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[File:Dilma Lula Temer Convenção PT.jpg|thumb|left|[[Dilma Rousseff]], President of Brazil, 2011-present; with [[Luiz Inácio Lula da Silva]], President of Brazil, 2003-2010; during the 2010 Brazilian presidential campaign in which Rouseff was elected President.]]

In the 2000s (decade) and 2010s, several major European social democratic parties lost support, such as the defeat of the Social Democratic Party of Germany in the 2005 German election, and the defeat of the British Labour Party in the 2010 British election, and the [[Spanish Socialist Workers' Party]] in the 2011 Spanish election. However there have been major increases in support for social democratic parties elsewhere. In North America there was a massive surge in support for Canada's [[New Democratic Party]] in the 2011 Canadian election, allowing the party for its first time to become the second largest political party in the Canadian Parliament. The New Democratic Party is the second strongest social democratic party of a sovereign state in North America. The [[Institutional Revolutionary Party]] is one of two parties in [[Mexico]] affiliated with the Socialist International (the [[Party of the Democratic Revolution]] is the other), and has formed a government at the federal level in Mexico, unlike the New Democratic Party, which has only formed a government in Canada at the provincial level.

[[File:Mizuho Fukushima.jpg|thumb|150px|right|[[Mizuho Fukushima]], leader of the [[Social Democratic Party of Japan]].]]
Social democracy advocates the creation of legal reforms and [[Redistribution of wealth|economic redistribution]] programs to eliminate economic class disparities between the [[bourgeoisie]] and the [[proletariat]].&lt;ref name=Steger133 /&gt; It advocates the development of an [[economic democracy]] and the development of [[cooperative]] [[business]] organizations as an alternative to [[private enterprise]].&lt;ref&gt;Steger, ''The Quest for Evolutionary Socialism,'' pg. 36.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;congress&quot;&gt;Socialist International. &quot;Aims and Tasks of Democratic Socialism: Declaration of the Socialist International&quot;. ''Socialist International, First Congress''. Frankfurt-am-Main, Federal Republic of Germany: Socialist International, 1951. http://www.socialistinternational.org/viewArticle.cfm?ArticleID=39.&lt;/ref&gt; One example of a modern social democratic economic plan was the Meidner Plan in Sweden which was enacted in 1982 and promoted a gradualist [[Market socialism|market socialist]] achievement of [[social ownership]] through taxation on private enterprise and transferring of the money gained to socially-owned investment funds that gradually will result in wage-earners gaining a controlling share in their enterprises;&lt;ref name=&quot;Christopher Pierson 1995. Pp. 204&quot;&gt;Christopher Pierson. Socialism after communism: the new market socialism. Pennsylvania State Press, 1995. Pp. 204.&lt;/ref&gt; although by the early 1990s the Social Democrats had lost their enthusiasm for it.&lt;ref&gt;Dorrien, Gary. 2009. A Case for Economic Democracy. Tikkun 24(3): 34.&lt;/ref&gt; Practical modern social democratic policies include the promotion of a [[welfare state]], and the creation of [[economic democracy]] as a means to secure workers' rights.&lt;ref&gt;Steger, ''The Quest for Evolutionary Socialism,'' pg. 140.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Frankfurt Declaration]] of the [[Socialist International]] in 1951, attended by many social democratic parties from across the world, committed adherents to oppose [[Bolshevik]] [[communism]]—especially [[Stalinism]], and to promote a gradual transformation of capitalism into socialism.&lt;ref name=&quot;socialistinternational.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.socialistinternational.org/viewArticle.cfm?ArticleID=39 Socialist International. &quot;Aims and Tasks of Democratic Socialism: Declaration of the Socialist International&quot;], ''Socialist International, First Congress'', Frankfurt-am-Main, Federal Republic of Germany, 1951.&lt;/ref&gt;

Many of the policies espoused by social democrats in the first half of the 20th century have since been put into practice by social democratic governments throughout the industrialized world. Industries have been nationalized, public spending has seen a large long-term rise, and the role of the state in providing free-to-user or subsidized health care and education has increased greatly. Many of the reforms made by social democrats in Europe, such as the establishment of national health care services, have been embraced by liberals and conservatives, and there is no support outside of a radical fringe for a return to 19th-century levels of public spending and economic regulation. Even in the United States, where no major social democratic party exists, there are regulatory programmes (such as public health and environmental protection) and welfare programmes (such as [[Medicare (United States)|Medicare]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.medicarerights.org/maincontenthistory.html History of Medicare (United States)]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Medicaid]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cms.hhs.gov/history/01_overview.asp? Brief History of Medicare and Medicaid (United States)]&lt;/ref&gt;) which enjoy bipartisan support.

In recent years, several{{citation needed|date=December 2011}} social democratic parties (in particular, the British [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]]) have embraced more centrist, [[Third Way (centrism)|Third Way]] policy positions, and thus supported both the [[privatization]] of certain state-controlled industries and services and the reduction of certain forms of regulation of the market. Since the 1980s, there has been a perception that social democracy has been on the retreat in the Western world, particularly in English-speaking countries, where social democratic values are arguably not as firmly rooted in local law and culture as elsewhere. Traditional social democrats argue that Third Way ideology has caused the movement to become too [[centrism|centrist]], and even that the movement may be becoming [[centre-right]].  In general, apparent reversals in policy have encountered significant opposition among party members and core voters; many of the latter have claimed that their leaders have betrayed the principles of social democracy.&lt;ref name=sacrifices&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/in_depth/uk_politics/2000/labour_centenary/651231.stm BBC News: Sacrifices in the scramble for power]&lt;/ref&gt; The development of Third Way social democracy has resulted in the rise of [[democratic socialism]] as a distinct break away ideology from social democracy. In many countries, social democrats continue to exist alongside [[democratic socialism|democratic socialist]]s, who stand to the left of them on the [[political spectrum]]. The two movements sometimes operate within the same political party, such as the [[Workers' Party (Brazil)|Brazilian Workers' Party]]&lt;ref name=Lula&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/4311957.stm BBC News: South America's leftward sweep, 2005]&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Socialist Party (France)|Socialist Party]] of [[France]]. 

Supporters of Third Way ideals argue that they merely represent a necessary or pragmatic adaptation of social democracy to the realities of the modern world: traditional social democracy thrived during the prevailing international climate of the post-war [[Bretton Woods system|Bretton Woods consensus]], which collapsed in the 1970s. In Britain, where the electorate rejected the Labour Party four times consecutively between 1979 and 1997, Third Way politician [[Tony Blair]] and his colleagues in the [[Labour Party (UK)|New Labour]] movement took the strategic decision to disassociate themselves publicly from the previous, explicitly democratic socialist incarnations of their party.  The Labour Government that came to power in 1997 continued the tradition that [[Margaret Thatcher]] started in the 1980s of selling out nationalized industries, and the income gap between the rich and the poor grew.  This challenge to traditional social democratic ideals alienated many [[backbenchers]], including some who advocated a less militant ideology of social democracy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://politics.guardian.co.uk/thinktanks/story/0,,1274517,00.html The Guardian: Rich-poor gap 'has widened under Blair' Monday August 2, 2004]&lt;/ref&gt;

The development of new social democratic policies in this environment is the subject of wide-ranging debate within the left and centre-left. A number of political think-tanks, such as [[Policy Network]] and [[Wiardi Beckman Stichting]], have been active in facilitating and promoting this debate.

Since the rise in popularity of the [[New Right]] and [[neoliberalism]], a number of prominent modern social democratic parties have abandoned the goal of the gradual evolution of [[capitalism]] to socialism and instead support [[welfare state]] capitalism.&lt;ref&gt;O'Hara, Phillip Anthony (ed.). ''Encyclopedia of political economy, Volume 2''. London, England, UK: Routledge, 1999 Pp. 539.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Political parties==
{{see also|List of social democratic parties}}
Social democratic [[political party|political parties]], which sometimes also include a democratic socialist element, operate in many developed and developing countries, including France, Germany, the United Kingdom, Spain, Australia, Israel and Brazil. Most European social democratic parties are members of the [[Party of European Socialists]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pes.org/content/view/11/48/lang,en/ PES Member Parties]&lt;/ref&gt; which is one of the main political parties at the European level,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.civitas.org.uk/eufacts/FSCIT/CIT3.htm EU facts: Party Politics in the EU]&lt;/ref&gt; and its parliamentary group the [[Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats]]. Globally, most social democratic parties worldwide are members of the [[Socialist International]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.socialistinternational.org/2Members/who.html#full Members of the Socialist International].&lt;/ref&gt;

In many cases, social democratic parties are the dominant (India, Portugal, Australia) or second-placed (Canada, Italy, Sweden, Germany, United Kingdom)&lt;ref&gt;In Canada, the CCF/NDP have been or are the government at the provincial level of governance, and as of [[Canadian federal election, 2011|2011]] form the [[Official Opposition (Canada)|Official Opposition]].&lt;/ref&gt; players within their respective political systems, though in some cases they are minor parties in federal politics (Ireland, Russia).

Since the 1960s, many social democrats have broadened their objectives beyond the field of economic policy to include aspects of [[environmentalism]], [[feminism]], [[racial equality]] and [[multiculturalism]]. Another notable development is the tendency since the 1980s for social democratic parties to distance themselves from distinctively left-wing economic policies such as public ownership and [[dirigisme]], adopting instead policies that support a relatively lightly regulated economy and emphasize [[equality of opportunity]].

This trend, known as the [[Third Way (centrism)|Third Way]], is controversial among some of the left, many of whom argue that Third Way politicians (such as [[Tony Blair]] and [[Bill Clinton]])&lt;ref name=sacrifices/&gt; have moved too far to the centre, or even the centre-right. Others, such as the leadership of the UK Labour Party, reject this critique.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.labour.org.uk/labour_policies Labour policies]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticism==
{{expand section|date=October 2012}}
{{refimprove section|date=October 2012}}
Socialist critics of contemporary social democracy include [[Democratic socialists]], [[Marxist socialism|Marxian socialists]], [[market socialists]], [[Syndicalists]]{{who|date=October 2012}} and [[anarchist]]s{{who|date=October 2012}}. Socialist criticisms of social democratic policies range from critiques of the welfare state and social corporatism to critiques of the political strategy of reformism.{{citation needed|date=October 2012}} 

Marxian socialists of the [[Classical Marxism|classical]], [[Orthodox Marxism|orthodox]] and [[Analytical Marxism|analytical]] variations argue that because social democratic programs retain the capitalist mode of production, they also retain the fundamental issues of capitalism, including [[Business cycle|cyclical fluctuations]], exploitation and alienation. Social democratic programs intended to ameliorate capitalism, such as unemployment benefits, taxation on profits and the wealthy, create contradictions of their own by limiting the efficiency of the capitalist system by reducing incentives for capitalists to invest in production.&lt;ref name=&quot;Market Socialism 1998. P.60-61&quot;&gt;''Market Socialism: The Debate Among Socialists'', by Schweickart, David; Lawler, James; Ticktin, Hillel; Ollman, Bertell. 1998. (P.60-61): &quot;The Marxist answers that market socialism cannot exist because it involves limiting the incentive system of the market through providing minimum wages, high levels of unemployment insurance, reducing the size of the reserve army of labour, taxing profits, and taxing the wealthy. As a result, capitalists will have little incentive to invest and the workers will have little incentive to work. Capitalism works because, as Marx remarked, it is a system of economic force (coercion).&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; 

Democratic socialists, such as David Schweickart, contrast social democracy with democratic socialism by defining the former as an attempt to strengthen the welfare state, and the latter as an alternative socialist economic system to capitalism. According to Schweickart, the democratic socialist critique of social democracy states that capitalism could never be sufficiently &quot;humanized&quot;, and any attempt to suppress the economic contradictions of capitalism would only cause them to emerge elsewhere. For example, attempts to reduce unemployment too much would result in inflation, and too much job security would erode labor discipline.&lt;ref&gt;Schweickart, David. ''Democratic Socialism''. Encyclopedia of Activism and Social Justice (2006): http://orion.it.luc.edu/~dschwei/demsoc.htm: &quot;Social democrats supported and tried to strengthen the basic institutions of the welfare state--pensions for all, public health care, public education, unemployment insurance.  They supported and tried to strengthen the labor movement.  The latter, as socialists, argued that capitalism could never be sufficiently humanized, and that trying to suppress the economic contradictions in one area would only see them emerge in a different guise elsewhere. (E.g., if you push unemployment too low, you'll get inflation; if job security is too strong, labor discipline breaks down; etc.)&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast to social democracy, democratic socialists advocate a post-capitalist economic system based either on market socialism combined with workers self-management, or on some form of [[Decentralized planning (economics)|participatory-economic planning]].&lt;ref&gt;Schweickart, David. ''Democratic Socialism''. Encyclopedia of Activism and Social Justice (2006): http://orion.it.luc.edu/~dschwei/demsoc.htm: &quot;Virtually all (democratic) socialists have distanced themselves from the economic model long synonymous with 'socialism,' i.e. the Soviet model of a non-market, centrally-planned economy...Some have endorsed the concept of 'market socialism,' a post-capitalist economy that retains market competition, but socializes the means of production, and, in some versions, extends democracy to the workplace.  Some hold out for a non-market, participatory economy.  All democratic socialists agree on the need for a democratic alternative to capitalism.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; 

Market socialists contrast social democracy with market socialism. While a common goal of both systems is to achieve greater social and economic equality, market socialism does so by changes in enterprise ownership and management, whereas social democracy attempts to do so by government-imposed taxes and subsidies on privately-owned enterprises. Frank Roosevelt and David Belkin criticize social democracy for maintaining a property-owning capitalist class, which has an active interest in reversing social democratic policies and a disproportionate amount of power over society to influence governmental policy as a class.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Roosevelt|first= Frank |coauthors= David Belkin |title= [[Why Market Socialism?]] |publisher= [[M.E. Sharpe, Inc.]] |year= 1994|month= |isbn= 1-56324-465-9|pages = 314–315|quote=Social democracy achieves greater egalitarianism via ex post government taxes and subsidies, where market socialism does so via ex ante changes in patterns of enterprise ownership...the maintenance of property-owning capitalists under social democracy assures the presence of a disproportionately powerful class  with a continuing interest in challenging social democratic government policies.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another criticism of social democracy has to do with its relationship to [[neoliberalism]] and labour unions. It is argued in ''Social Democracy: After the Cold War'', that
&lt;blockquote&gt; 
&quot;social democratic parties shifted to the right in the 1980’s, abandoning their traditional policy stance and embracing neoliberalism – either explicitly or in the guise of a ‘Third Way.’ Ultimately, they distanced themselves from their core union base to regain electoral viability.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Evans, Bryan &amp; Schmidt, Ingo. 2012. ''Social Democracy: After the Cold War.'' AU Press, Athabasca University. pp. 184.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[Communism|Communists]] accuse social democracy of accepting the values of capitalist society and therefore not being a genuine form of socialism.&lt;ref name=&quot;David Robertson 2004. Pp. 212&quot;&gt;David Robertson. ''A dictionary of modern politics''. 3rd edition. London, England, UK: Europa Publications, 2004. Pp. 212.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable social democrats==
{{refimprove section|date=September 2012}}
:''This is an abbreviated list of well-known social democrats. For a comprehensive list, see [[List of social democrats]]
''
&lt;div style=&quot;-moz-column-count:3; column-count:3;&quot;&gt;
*[[Clement Attlee]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cre.gov.uk/Default.aspx.LocID-0hgnew06b.RefLocID-0hg00900c002.Lang-EN.htm Commission for Racial Equality: Clement Attlee Lecture: Trevor Phillips's speech, 21 April 2005]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Obafemi Awolowo]]
*[[José Batlle y Ordóñez]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.larepublica.com.uy/editorial/286765-nuevo-impulso-conservador Nuevo impulso conservador] - La República&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Otto Bauer]]
*[[David Ben-Gurion]]
*[[Eduard Bernstein]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/bernstein/index.htm Eduard Bernstein Reference Archive]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Zulfikar Ali Bhutto]]
*[[Léon Blum]]
*[[Willy Brandt]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-9016223/Willy-Brandt Encyclopædia Britannica: Willy Brandt]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Hjalmar Branting]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/peace/laureates/1921/branting-bio.html Hjalmar Branting: The Nobel Peace Prize 1921]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Gro Harlem Brundtland]]
*[[Vince Cable]]
*[[Job Cohen]]
*[[Brendan Corish]]
*[[Tommy Douglas]]
*[[Willem Drees]]
*[[Friedrich Ebert]]
*[[Einar Gerhardsen]]
*[[Bob Hawke]]
*[[Roy Jenkins]]
*[[Wim Kok]]
*[[Jack Layton]]
*[[David Lewis (politician)|David Lewis]]
*[[Wilhelm Liebknecht]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-9048179/Wilhelm-Liebknecht Encyclopædia Britannica: Wilhelm Liebknecht]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Luiz Inácio Lula da Silva]]&lt;ref&gt;{{pt}} [http://diariodonordeste.globo.com/materia.asp?codigo=550729 &quot;Em 28 anos, Lula troca Marx pela social democracia&quot; (&quot;In 28 years, Lula trades Marx for social democracy&quot;)]. ''Diário do Nordeste''. June 30, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Vasos Lyssaridis]]
*[[Dom Mintoff]]
*[[David Owen]]
*[[Olof Palme]]
*[[Wim Schermerhorn]]
*[[Shirley Williams]]
*[[Joop den Uyl]]
*[[José Luis Rodríguez Zapatero]]
*[[Vera Zasulich]]
*[[Frank P. Zeidler]]
&lt;/div&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Socialism|Social movements}}
*[[History of socialism]]
*[[List of social democratic parties]]
*[[List of social democrats]]
*[[Democratic socialism]]

===Political theory===
*[[Dirigisme]]
*[[Constitutional economics]]
*[[Political economy]]
*[[Rule according to higher law]]
*[[Left-wing politics]]
*[[Progressivism]]
*[[Liberalism]]
*[[Reformism]]
*[[Mixed Economy]]
*[[Third Way (centrism)|The Third Way]]

===Social democracy in practice===
*[[Flexicurity]]
*[[Scandinavian welfare model]]
*[[Social corporatism]]
*[[Social welfare in Sweden]]
*[[Social market economy]]
*[[Rhine Capitalism]] {{dubious|date=July 2012}}
*[[Welfare state]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth = 30em}}

==External links==
{{Wiktionary}}
*[http://www.misc-iecm.mcgill.ca/socdem/epaper.htm Papers on the Future of Social Democracy in Canada]
*[http://sciam.com/article.cfm?chanID=sa006&amp;colID=31&amp;articleID=000AF3D5-6DC9-152E-A9F183414B7F0000 Beyond Ideology, The Social Welfare State] by Jeffrey D. Sachs
*[http://www.sussex.ac.uk/Users/hafa3/socdem.htm Social Democracy in the unfinished global revolution] by Martin Shaw
*[http://www.policy-network.net/articles/4089/Conflicts-in-cosmopolitanism-and-the-global-left Global Social Democracy]

{{Navboxes
|list =
{{Social democracy}}
{{Political ideologies}}
{{Socialism}}
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Social Democracy}}
[[Category:Economic ideologies]]
[[Category:Political ideologies]]
[[Category:Social democracy| ]]
[[Category:Social philosophy]]

[[ar:ديمقراطية اشتراكية]]
[[ast:Socialdemocracia]]
[[bg:Социалдемокрация]]
[[bs:Socijaldemokratija]]
[[ca:Socialdemocràcia]]
[[cs:Sociální demokracie]]
[[da:Socialdemokratisme]]
[[de:Sozialdemokratie]]
[[et:Sotsiaaldemokraatia]]
[[el:Σοσιαλδημοκρατία]]
[[es:Socialdemocracia]]
[[eo:Socialdemokratio]]
[[eu:Sozialdemokrazia]]
[[fa:سوسیال دموکراسی]]
[[fr:Social-démocratie]]
[[fy:Sosjaaldemokrasy]]
[[gl:Socialdemocracia]]
[[ko:사회민주주의]]
[[hr:Socijaldemokracija]]
[[id:Demokrasi Sosial]]
[[it:Socialdemocrazia]]
[[he:סוציאל-דמוקרטיה]]
[[ka:სოციალ-დემოკრატია]]
[[kk:Социал-Демократия]]
[[ky:Социал Демократия]]
[[la:Democratia socialis]]
[[lv:Sociāldemokrātija]]
[[lt:Socialdemokratija]]
[[hu:Szociáldemokrácia]]
[[mk:Социјалдемократија]]
[[arz:اشتراكيه ديموقراطيه]]
[[ms:Demokrasi sosial]]
[[nl:Sociaaldemocratie]]
[[ja:社会民主主義]]
[[no:Sosialdemokrati]]
[[nn:Sosialdemokrati]]
[[ps:ټولنیزه ولسواکي]]
[[pl:Socjaldemokracja]]
[[pt:Social-democracia]]
[[ro:Social-democrație]]
[[ru:Социал-демократия]]
[[se:Sosiálademokratiija]]
[[scn:Sucialdimucrazzìa]]
[[simple:Social democracy]]
[[sk:Sociálna demokracia]]
[[sl:Socialna demokracija]]
[[ckb:سۆسیالدیموکراسی]]
[[sr:Социјалдемократија]]
[[sh:Socijaldemokratija]]
[[fi:Sosiaalidemokratia]]
[[sv:Socialdemokrati]]
[[tr:Sosyal demokrasi]]
[[uk:Соціал-демократія]]
[[vi:Chủ nghĩa xã hội-dân chủ]]
[[yi:סאציאל דעמאקראטיע]]
[[yo:Òṣèlú aláwùjọ]]
[[zh-yue:社會民主主義]]
[[zh:社會民主主義]]</text>
      <sha1>rajq8ulc1mdhdh8bxbv4h59atxl6n9r</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
