<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Social class</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>29174</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522206033</id>
      <parentid>521065688</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T17:40:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Gareth Griffith-Jones</username>
        <id>13358461</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting revision(s) by [[Special:Contributions/196.201.35.52|196.201.35.52]] which were identified as [[Wikipedia:Vandalism|vandalism]], whilst using [[WP:STiki|STiki]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="35829">{{Redirect|Class system|the role-playing game concept|Character class}}
{{Sociology}}
'''Social class''' (or simply &quot;class&quot;) is a set of concepts in the [[social sciences]] and [[political theory]] centered on models of [[social stratification]] in which people are grouped into a set of [[hierarchical]] social categories.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Grant, J. Andrew|chapter=class, definition of|editor=Jones, R.J. Barry|title=Routledge Encyclopedia of International Political Economy: Entries A-F|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|year=2001|isbn=978-0-415-24350-6|page=161|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=a29qBofx8Y8C&amp;pg=PA161}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Class is an essential object of analysis for [[sociologists]], [[political scientist]]s, [[anthropologists]] and [[social history|social historians]]. However, there is not a consensus on the best definition of the term &quot;class&quot;, and the term has different contextual meanings. In common parlance, the term &quot;social class,&quot; is usually synonymous with &quot;[[Socioeconomic status|socio-economic]] class,&quot; defined as: &quot;people having the same social, economic, or educational status,&quot; e.g., &quot;the working class&quot;; &quot;an emerging professional class.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Princeton University. [http://wordnetweb.princeton.edu/perl/webwn?s=social+class&amp;sub=Search+WordNet&amp;o2=&amp;o0=1&amp;o8=1&amp;o1=1&amp;o7=&amp;o5=&amp;o9=&amp;o6=&amp;o3=&amp;o4=&amp;h=0 &quot;Social class.&quot;] WordNet Search 3.1. Retrieved on: 2012-01-25.&lt;/ref&gt;

The term &quot;class&quot; is etymologically derived from the Latin ''classis'', which was used by [[census]] takers to categorize citizens by wealth, in order to determine military service obligations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Brown, D.F.|chapter=Social class and Status|editor=Mey, Jacob|title=Concise Encyclopedia of Pragmatics|publisher=Elsevier|year=2009|isbn=978-0-08-096297-9|page=952|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=GcmXgeBE7k0C&amp;pg=PA952}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the late 18th century, the term &quot;class&quot; began to replace classifications such as estates, rank, and orders as the primary means of organizing society into hierarchical divisions. This corresponded to a general decrease in significance ascribed to hereditary characteristics, and increase in the significance of wealth and income as indicators of position in the social hierarchy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|chapter=Class, Social|editor=Kuper, Adam|title=The social science encyclopedia|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|year=2004|isbn=978-0-415-32096-2|page=111|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=2oES3pJufP4C&amp;pg=PA111}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Penney, Robert|chapter=Class, social|editors=Christensen, Karen &amp; Levinson, David|title=Encyclopedia of community: from the village to the virtual world, Volume 1|publisher=SAGE|year=2003|isbn=978-0-7619-2598-9|page=189|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=t1geOjQ6R0MC&amp;pg=PA189}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Theoretical models==
Definitions of social classes reflect a number of [[social theory|sociological perspectives]], informed by [[anthropology]], [[economics]], [[psychology]], and [[sociology]]. The major perspectives historically have been [[Marxism]] and [[Structural functionalism]]. The common ''stratum model of class'' divides society into a simple hierarchy of [[working class]], [[middle class]] and [[upper class]]. Within academia, two broad schools of definitions emerge: those aligned with 20th-century sociological stratum models of class society, and those aligned with the 19th-century [[historical materialist]] economic models of the [[Marxist]]s and [[anarchist]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Serravallo, Vincent|chapter=Class|editor=Parrillo, Vincent N.|title=Encyclopedia of social problems, Volume 1|publisher=SAGE|year=2008|isbn=978-1-4129-4165-5|page=131|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=mRGr_B4Y1CEC&amp;pg=PA131}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The American Class Structure&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Gilbert | first = Dennis | authorlink = | coauthors = | year = 1998 | title = The American Class Structure | publisher = Wadsworth Publishing | location = New York | id = 0-534-50520-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Marriages, Families &amp; Intimate Relationships&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Williams | first = Brian | authorlink = | coauthors = Stacey C. Sawyer, Carl M. Wahlstrom | year = 2005 | title = Marriages, Families &amp; Intimate Relationships | publisher = Pearson | location = Boston, MA | id = 0-205-36674-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another distinction can be drawn between ''analytical'' concepts of social class, such as the ''Marxist'' and ''Weberian'' traditions, and the more ''empirical'' traditions such as socio-economic status approach, which notes the correlation of income, education and wealth with social outcomes without necessarily implying a particular theory of social structure.&lt;ref&gt;John Scott, ''Class: critical concepts'' (1996) Volume 2 P. 310&lt;/ref&gt;

===Marxist===
{{Main|Class in Marxist theory}}
{{quote box|quote=&quot;&lt;nowiki&gt;[Classes are]&lt;/nowiki&gt; large groups of people differing from each other by the place they occupy in a historically determined system of social production, by their relation (in most cases fixed and formulated in law) to the means of production, by their role in the social organization of labor, and, consequently, by the dimensions of the share of social wealth of which they dispose and the mode of acquiring it.&quot;|width=25%|source=[[Vladimir Lenin]], [http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1919/jun/19.htm ''A Great Beginning''] - June, 1919|align=right}}

For Marx, class is a combination of objective and subjective factors.  Objectively, a class shares a common [[relations of production|relationship]] to the [[means of production]].
Subjectively, the members will necessarily have some perception (&quot;[[class consciousness]]&quot;) of their similarity and common interest. Class consciousness is not simply an awareness of one's own class interest but is also a set of shared views regarding how society should be organized legally, culturally, socially and politically.  These class relations are reproduced through time.

In [[Marxist theory]], the [[class structure]] of the [[capitalist]] [[mode of production]] is characterized by the conflict between two main classes: the [[bourgeoisie]], the capitalists who own the means of production, and the much larger [[proletariat]] (or 'working class') who must sell their own labour power (See also: [[wage labour]]). This is the fundamental economic structure of work and property, a state of inequality that is normalized and [[Base and superstructure|reproduced through cultural ideology]].

Marxists explain the history of &quot;civilized&quot; societies in terms of a [[class conflict|war of classes]] between those who control production and those who produce the goods or services in society. In the Marxist view of [[capitalism]], this is a conflict between capitalists ([[bourgeoisie]]) and wage-workers (the proletariat). For Marxists, class antagonism is rooted in the situation that control over social production necessarily entails control over the class which produces goods—in capitalism this is the [[exploitation]] of workers by the bourgeoisie.&lt;ref&gt;Karl Marx &amp; Friedrich Engels. &quot;Manifesto of the Communist Party&quot;, ''Selected Works'', Volume 1; London,' 1943; p. 231.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Furthermore, &quot;in countries where modern civilisation has become fully developed, a new class of petty bourgeois has been formed&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Karl Marx &amp; Friedrich Engels. &quot;Manifesto of the Communist Party&quot;, ''Selected Works'', Volume 1; London,' 1943; p. 231&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;An industrial army of workmen, under the command of a capitalist, requires, like a real army, officers (managers) and sergeants (foremen, over-lookers) who, while the work is being done, command in the name of the capitalist&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Karl Marx. ''Capital: An Analysis of Capitalist Production'', Volume 1; Moscow; 1959; p. 332.&lt;/ref&gt;

Marx himself argued that it was the goal of the proletariat itself to displace the capitalist system with [[socialism]], changing the social relationships underpinning the class system and then developing into a future [[communist]] society in which: &quot;..the free development of each is the condition for the free development of all.&quot; ([[Communist Manifesto]]) This would mark the beginning of a classless society in which human needs rather than profit would be motive for production. In a society with democratic control and production for use, there would be no class, no state and no need for money.&lt;ref&gt;Karl Marx &amp; Friedrich Engels. &quot;Manifesto of the Communist Party&quot;, ''Selected Works'', Volume 1; London,' 1943; p. 232-234.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Weberian===
{{main|Three-component theory of stratification}}
[[Max Weber]] formulated a [[three-component theory of stratification]], that saw [[political power]] as an interplay between &quot;class&quot;, &quot;status&quot; and &quot;group power&quot;. Weber believed that class position was determined by a person's skills and [[education]], rather than by their relationship to the means of production. Both Marx and Weber agreed that social stratification was undesirable, however where Marx believed that stratification would only disappear along with capitalism and [[private property]], Weber believed that the solution lay in providing &quot;equal opportunity&quot; within a competitive, capitalist system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Jones, Helen|title=Towards a classless society?|publisher=Psychology Press|year=1997|isbn=978-0-415-15331-7|page=4|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=P6T5j2ywnqQC&amp;pg=4}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Leander, Anna|chapter=class, Weberian approaches to|editor=Jones, R.J. Barry|title=Routledge Encyclopedia of International Political Economy: Entries A-F|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|year=2001|isbn=978-0-415-24350-6|page=227|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=LT7r94epBz0C&amp;pg=PA227}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Weber derived many of his key concepts on social stratification by examining the social structure of [[Germany]]. He noted that contrary to Marx's theories, stratification was based on more than simply ownership of [[Capital (economics)|capital]]. Weber examined how many members of the aristocracy lacked economic wealth yet had strong political power. Many wealthy families lacked prestige and power, for example, because they were [[Jewish]]. Weber introduced three independent factors that form his theory of stratification hierarchy; class, status, and power&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Stark, Rodney|year=2007|title=Sociology|edition=Tenth edition | publisher=Thompson Wadsworth}}&lt;/ref&gt;:
* '''Class''': A person's economic position in a society. Weber differs from Marx in that he does not see this as the supreme factor in stratification. Weber noted how managers of corporations or industries control firms they do not own.
* '''Status''': A person's prestige, social honor, or popularity in a society. Weber noted that political power was not rooted in capital value solely, but also in one's individual status. Poets or saints, for example, can possess immense influence on society with often little economic worth.
* '''Power''': A person's ability to get their way despite the resistance of others. For example, individuals in state jobs, such as an employee of the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation]], or a member of the [[United States Congress]], may hold little property or status but they still hold immense power.

===The common three-stratum model===

Today, concepts of social class often assume three general categories: a very wealthy and powerful ''upper class'' that owns and controls the means of production; a ''middle class'' of professional workers, [[small business]] owners, and low-level [[managers]]; and a ''lower class'', who rely on low-paying [[wage]] jobs for their livelihood and often experience [[poverty]].

====Upper class====
[[File:Wolfensohn-bush.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Members of the upper class generally wield much greater political power than members of the lower or middle class. Pictured here are U.S. President [[George W. Bush]] and [[World Bank]] President [[James Wolfensohn]].]]
{{Main|Upper class}}
{{See also|Elite|Aristocracy|Oligarchy}}

The upper class&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown-2009-953&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Brown, D.F.|chapter=Social class and Status|editor=Mey, Jacob|title=Concise Encyclopedia of Pragmatics|publisher=Elsevier|year=2009|isbn=978-0-08-096297-9|page=953|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=GcmXgeBE7k0C&amp;pg=PA953}}&lt;/ref&gt; is the social class composed of those who are [[economic inequality|wealthy]], well-born, or both.  They usually  wield the greatest political power.  In some countries, wealth alone is sufficient to allow entry into the upper class.  In others, only people born into certain aristocratic bloodlines are considered members of the upper class, and those who gain great wealth through commercial activity are looked down upon as ''[[nouveau riche]]''.  In the United Kingdom, for example, the Upper Classes are the aristocracy and royalty, with wealth playing a less important role in class status.  Many Aristocratic Peerages Titles have 'seats' attached to them, with the holder of the title (e.g. Earl of Bristol) and his family being the custodians of the house, but not the owners. Many of these require high expenditures, so wealth is typically needed. Many Aristocratic Peerages and their homes are parts of estates, owned and run by the title holder with moneys generated by the land, rents, or other sources wealth.  In America, however, where there is no aristocracy or royalty, the Upper Class status belongs to the extremely wealthy, the so-called 'super-rich', though there is some tendency even in America for those with old family wealth to look down on those who have earned their money in business.  

The upper class is generally contained within the wealthiest 1 or 2 percent of the population. Members of the upper class are often born into it, and are distinguished by immense wealth which is passed from generation to generation in the form of estates.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Akhbar-Williams, Tahira|chapter=Class Structure|editor=Smith, Jessie C.|title=Encyclopedia of African American Popular Culture, Volume 1|publisher=ABC-CLIO|year=2010|isbn=978-0-313-35796-1|page=322|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=10rEGSIItjgC&amp;pg=PA322}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Sometimes members of the upper class are called &quot;the one percent&quot;.

====Middle class====
{{Main|Middle class |Bourgeoisie}}
The middle class is the most contested of the three categorizations, the broad group of people in contemporary society whom fall socio-economically between the lower class and upper class.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|chapter=Middle class|editor=Stearns, Peter N.|title=Encyclopedia of social history|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|year=1994|isbn=978-0-8153-0342-8|page=621|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=kkIeyCEedrsC&amp;pg=PA621}}&lt;/ref&gt; One example of the contestation of this term is that in the United States &quot;middle class&quot; is applied very broadly and includes people who would elsewhere be considered [[lower class]].  Middle class workers are sometimes called &quot;[[white-collar worker]]s&quot;.

Theorists such as [[Ralf Dahrendorf]] have noted the tendency toward an enlarged middle class in modern Western societies, particularly in relation to the necessity of an educated work force in technological economies.&lt;ref&gt;Dahrendorf, Ralf. (1959) Class and Class Conflict in Industrial Society. Stanford: Stanford University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; Perspectives concerning [[globalization]] and [[neocolonialism]], such as [[dependency theory]], suggest this is due to the shift of low-level labour to [[developing nation]]s and the [[Third World]].&lt;ref&gt;Bornschier V. (1996), 'Western society in transition' New Brunswick, N.J.: Transaction Publishers.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Lower class====
[[File:Camden NJ poverty.jpg|thumb|right|250px|In the United States the lowest stratum of the working class, the [[underclass]], often lives in urban areas with low-quality [[civil services]].]]
{{Main|Working class |Proletariat}}

Lower class (occasionally described as working class) are those employed in low-paying wage jobs with very little economic security. 

The working class is sometimes separated into those who are [[working poor|employed but lacking financial security]], and an underclass—those who are long-term [[unemployment|unemployed]] and/or [[homeless]], especially those receiving [[welfare]] from the [[state (polity)|state]]. The latter is analogous to the Marxist term ''&quot;[[lumpenproletariat]]&quot;''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown-2009-953&quot; /&gt; Members of the working class are sometimes called [[blue-collar worker]]s.

In the United States, the terms working class and blue-collar may refer to employed and hard-working members of the middle-middle and lower-middle class, while the upper-middle class in the United States often refers to employment positions that require a college or graduate degree.

==Consequences of class position==
A person's socioeconomic class has wide-ranging effects.  It may determine the schools they are able to attend, the jobs open to them, who they may marry, and their treatment by police and the courts.{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}

===Education===
A person's social class has a significant impact on their educational opportunities.  Not only are upper-class parents able to send their children to exclusive schools that are perceived to be better, but in many places state-supported schools for children of the upper class are of a much higher quality than those the state provides for children of the lower classes.&lt;ref&gt;Jonathan Kozol, ''Savage Inequalities'', Crown, 1991&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=McDonough, Patricia M.|title=Choosing colleges: how social class and schools structure opportunity|publisher=SUNY Press|year=1997|isbn=978-0-7914-3477-2|pages=1–2|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=PHdy8ql2mM4C&amp;pg=PA1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|authors=Shin, Kwang-Yeong &amp; Lee, Byoung-Hoon|chapter=Social class and educational opportunity in South Korea|editors=Attewell, Paul &amp; Newman, Katherine S.|title=Growing gaps: educational inequality around the world|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=2010|isbn=978-0-19-973218-0|page=105|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=tqf8ShfYk_YC&amp;pg=PA105}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|authors=McNamee, Stephen J. &amp; Miller, Robert K.|title=The meritocracy myth|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield|year=2009|isbn=978-0-7425-6168-7|page=199|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=6szZEsV-dDEC&amp;pg=PA199}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|authors=Thomas, Scott L. &amp; Bell, Angela|chapter=Social class and higher education: a reorganization of opportunities|editor=Weis, Lois|title=The Way Class Works: Readings on School, Family, and the Economy|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|year=2007|isbn=978-0-415-95707-6|page=273|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=sj1HCJaRkHMC&amp;pg=PA273}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|authors=Sacks, Peter|title=Tearing down the gates: confronting the class divide in American education|publisher=University of California Press|year=2007|isbn=978-0-520-24588-4|pages=112–114|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=EE-m0ZwjuqsC&amp;pg=PA112}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This lack of good schools is one factor that perpetuates the class divide across generations.

In 1977, British [[cultural theorist]] [[Paul Willis (cultural theorist)|Paul Willis]] published a study titled &quot;Learning to Labor&quot;, in which he investigated the connection between social class and education.  In his study, he found that a group of working class schoolchildren had developed an antipathy towards the acquisition of knowledge as being outside their class, and therefore undesirable, perpetuating their presence in the working class.&lt;ref&gt;Paul Willis, ''Learning to Labor'', Columbia University Press, 1981&lt;/ref&gt;

===Health and nutrition===
[[File:Starved girl.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Members of the working class, and particularly peasantries, [[starvation|starve to death]] at a much higher rate than petits-bourgeois professionals or capitalists.]]
A person's social class has a significant impact on their physical health, their ability to receive adequate [[medical care]] and [[nutrition]], and their [[life expectancy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Barr, Donald A.|title=Health disparities in the United States: social class, race, ethnicity, and health|publisher=JHU Press|year=2008|isbn=978-0-8018-8821-2|pages=1–2|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=US21MlGw3-IC&amp;pg=PA1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Gulliford, Martin|chapter=Equity and access to health care|editors=Gulliford, Martin &amp; Morgan, Myfanwy|title=Access to health care|publisher=Psychology Press|year=2003|isbn=978-0-415-27546-0|page=39|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=mOXP05u5alAC&amp;pg=PA39}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Budrys, Grace|title=Unequal Health: How Inequality Contributes to Health Or Illness|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield|year=2009|isbn=978-0-7425-6507-4|pages=183–184|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=kUSM_kCNsSAC&amp;pg=PA183}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lower-class people experience a wide array of health problems as a result of their economic status. They are unable to use health care as often, and when they do it is of lower quality, even though they generally tend to experience a much higher rate of health issues. Lower-class families have higher rates of [[infant mortality]], [[cancer]], [[cardiovascular disease]], and disabling physical injuries. Additionally, poor people tend to work in much more hazardous conditions, yet generally have much less (if any) health insurance provided for them, as compared to middle and upper class workers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Liu, William Ming|title=Social Class and Classism in the Helping Professions: Research, Theory, and Practice|publisher=SAGE|year=2010|isbn=978-1-4129-7251-2|page=29|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=4IbVbxXisUgC&amp;pg=PA29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Employment===
The conditions at a person's job vary greatly depending on class.  Those in the upper-middle class and middle class enjoy greater freedoms in their occupations.  They are usually more respected, enjoy more diversity, and are able to exhibit some authority.  Those in lower classes tend to feel more alienated and have lower work satisfaction overall. The physical conditions of the workplace differ greatly between classes.  While middle-class workers may &quot;suffer alienating conditions&quot; or &quot;lack of job satisfaction&quot;, blue-collar workers are more apt to suffer alienating, often routine, work with obvious physical health hazards, injury, and even death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Kerbo  | first = Herald | title = Social Stratification and Inequality  | publisher = The McGraw-Hill Companies Inc. | year = 1996 | location = New York | pages = 231–233 | isbn =0-07-034258-X }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Class conflict==
{{expand section|date=January 2012}}
{{Main|Class conflict}}

For Marx, the history of class society was a history of class conflict.  He pointed to the successful rise of the bourgeoisie, and the necessity of revolutionary violence—a heightened form of class conflict—in securing the bourgeoisie rights that supported the capitalist economy.

Marx believed that the exploitation and poverty inherent in capitalism were a pre-existing form of class conflict.  Marx believed that wage labourers would need to [[revolt]] to bring about a [[Wealth redistribution|more equitable distribution of wealth]] and political power.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Streeter, Calvin L.|chapter=Community|editor=Mizrahi, Terry|title=Encyclopedia of social work, Volume 1|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=2008|isbn=978-0-19-530661-3|page=352|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=aF-Mpm9JDogC&amp;pg=PA352}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Hunt, Stephen|chapter=class conflict|editors=Ritzer, George &amp; Ryan, J. Michael|title=The Concise Encyclopedia of Sociology|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons|year=2011|isbn=978-1-4051-8353-6|page=66|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Dz4wU64f_JYC&amp;pg=PA66}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Classless societies==
{{Main|Classless society}}
{{expand section|date=January 2012}}

==Relationship between race and class==
[[File:Elizaveta with Black Servant (Hermitage).jpg|thumb|right|275px|Equestrian portrait of Empress Elisabeth of Russia with a black servant]]
{{Main|Racial inequality}}
[[Race (classification of human beings)|Race]] and other large-scale groupings can also influence class standing. The association of particular ethnic groups with class statuses is common in many societies.  As a result of conquest or internal ethnic differentiation, a ruling class is often ethnically homogenous and particular races or ethnic groups in some societies  are legally or customarily restricted to occupying particular class positions.  Which ethnicities are considered as belonging to high or low classes varies from society to society. In modern societies strict legal links between ethnicity and class have been drawn, such as in [[apartheid]], the [[caste system in Africa]], and in the position of the [[Burakumin]] in Japanese society.{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}

== See also ==
{{Columns-start|num=3}}
*[[Caste]]
*[[Character class]]
*[[Chattering classes]]
*[[Classless society]]
*[[Drift Hypothesis]]
*[[Elite theory]]
*[[Elitism]]
*[[Gilbert Model]]
{{Column}}
*[[Health and Social Class]]
*[[Mass society]]
*[[National Statistics Socio-economic Classification]] (NS-SEC)
*[[Passing (social class)|Passing]]
*[[Ranked society]]
*[[Raznochinets]]
*[[Second-class citizen]]
{{Column}}
*[[Social exclusion]]
*[[Social mobility]]
*[[Social position]]
*[[Social status]]

{{Columns-end}}

===Class by region or historical period===
*[[Class in Aztec society]]
*[[Class in the contemporary United States]]
*[[Four divisions of society]]
*[[Inca society]]
*[[Indian caste system]]
*[[Korean ruling class]]
*[[Social class in Cambodia]]
*[[Social class in ancient Rome]]
*[[Social structure of Britain]]
*[[Social class in Italy]]
*[[Social structure of China]]
*[[Social class in New Zealand]]
*[[Poverty in the United States]]
*[[Social class in American history]]
*[[Social structure of the United States]]

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2011}}

==Further reading==
{{Refbegin|60em}}
* Archer, Louise et al. ''Higher Education and Social Class: Issues of Exclusion and Inclusion'' (RoutledgeFalmer, 2003) (ISBN 0-4152-7644-6)
* [[Stanley Aronowitz|Aronowitz, Stanley]], [http://books.google.com/books?id=5EuYM4nW04AC&amp;printsec=frontcover ''How Class Works: Power and Social Movement''], Yale University Press, 2003. ISBN 0-300-10504-5
*{{cite book | first = Richard | last = Barbrook  | year = 2006 | title = The Class of the New | edition = paperback | publisher = OpenMute | location = London | isbn = 0-9550664-7-6 | url = http://www.theclassofthenew.net}}
* Beckert, Sven, and Julia B. Rosenbaum, eds. ''The American Bourgeoisie: Distinction and Identity in the Nineteenth Century'' (Palgrave Macmillan; 2011) 284 pages; Scholarly studies on the habits, manners, networks, institutions, and public roles of the American middle class with a focus on cities in the North.
* Benschop, Albert. [http://www.sociosite.net/class/summary.php ''Classes -  Transformational Class Analysis''] (Amsterdam: Spinhuis; 1993/2012).
* Bertaux, Daniel &amp; Thomson, Paul; ''Pathways to Social Class: A Qualitative Approach to Social Mobility'' (Clarendon Press, 1997)
* Bisson, Thomas N.; ''Cultures of Power: Lordship, Status, and Process in Twelfth-Century Europe'' (University of Pennsylvania Press, 1995)
* {{Cite news|title= Why workers can change the world |url=http://www.socialistreview.org.uk/article.php?articlenumber=11839|last= {{Smallcaps|Blackledge, Paul}} |year= 2011 |journal= Socialist Review ''364'' |location= London - A useful analysis of class generally and nature of working class more specifically|}}
* Blau, Peter &amp; Duncan Otis D.; ''The American Occupational Structure'' (1967) classic study of structure and mobility
* Brady, David &quot;Rethinking the Sociological Measurement of Poverty&quot; ''[[Social Forces]]'' Vol. 81 No.3, (March 2003), pp.&amp;nbsp;715–751 (abstract [http://muse.jhu.edu/login?uri=/journals/social_forces/v081/81.3brady.html online] in Project Muse).
* Broom, Leonard &amp; Jones, F. Lancaster; ''Opportunity and Attainment in Australia'' (1977)
* Cohen, Lizabeth; ''Consumer's Republic'', (Knopf, 2003) (ISBN 0-375-40750-2). (Historical analysis of the working out of class in the United States).
* Croix, Geoffrey de Ste.; [http://www.newleftreview.org/?page=article&amp;view=1359 &quot;Class in Marx's Conception of History, Ancient and Modern&quot;], [[New Left Review]], No. 146, (1984), pp.&amp;nbsp;94–111 (good study of Marx's concept).
* Dargin, Justin [http://www.atimes.com/atimes/Central_Asia/IL06Ag01.html ''The Birth of Russia's Energy Class''], [[Asia Times]] (2007) (good study of contemporary class formation in Russia, post communism)
* Day, Gary; ''Class'', (Routledge, 2001) (ISBN 0-415-18222-0)
* [[G. William Domhoff|Domhoff, G. William]], ''Who Rules America? Power, Politics, and Social Change'', Englewood Cliffs, N.J. : Prentice-Hall, 1967. ([http://sociology.ucsc.edu/whorulesamerica/ Prof. Domhoff's companion site to the book] at the [[University of California, Santa Cruz]])
* Eichar, Douglas M.; ''Occupation and Class Consciousness in America'' (Greenwood Press, 1989)
* Fantasia, Rick; Levine, Rhonda F.; McNall, Scott G., eds.; ''Bringing Class Back in Contemporary and Historical Perspectives'' (Westview Press, 1991)
* Featherman, David L. &amp; Hauser Robert M.; ''Opportunity and Change'' (1978).
* [[Takis Fotopoulos|Fotopoulos, Takis]], [http://www.inclusivedemocracy.org/dn/vol6/takis_class.htm Class Divisions Today: The Inclusive Democracy approach], ''[[Democracy &amp; Nature]]'', Vol. 6, No. 2, (July 2000)
* [[Paul Fussell|Fussell, Paul]]; ''Class (a painfully accurate guide through the American status system)'', (1983) (ISBN 0-345-31816-1)
* [[Anthony Giddens|Giddens, Anthony]]; ''The Class Structure of the Advanced Societies'', (London: Hutchinson, 1981).
* [[Anthony Giddens|Giddens, Anthony]] &amp; Mackenzie, Gavin (Eds.), ''Social Class and the Division of Labour. Essays in Honour of Ilya Neustadt'' (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1982).
* Goldthorpe, John H. &amp; Erikson Robert; ''The Constant Flux: A Study of Class Mobility in Industrial Society'' (1992)
* Grusky, David B. ed.; ''Social Stratification: Class, Race, and Gender in Sociological Perspective'' (2001) scholarly articles
* Hazelrigg, Lawrence E. &amp; Lopreato, Joseph; ''Class, Conflict, and Mobility: Theories and Studies of Class Structure'' (1972).
* Hymowitz, Kay; ''Marriage and Caste in America: Separate and Unequal Families in a Post-Marital Age'' (2006) ISBN 1-56663-709-0
* Kaeble, Helmut; ''Social Mobility in the Nineteenth and Twentieth Centuries: Europe and America in Comparative Perspective'' (1985)
* Jens Hoff, &quot;The Concept of Class and Public Employees&quot;. ''Acta Sociologica'', vol. 28, no. 3, July 1985, pp.&amp;nbsp;207–226.
* Mahalingam, Ramaswami; &quot;Essentialism, Culture, and Power: Representations of Social Class&quot; ''Journal of Social Issues'', Vol. 59, (2003), pp.&amp;nbsp;733+  on India
* Mahony, Pat &amp; Zmroczek, Christine; ''Class Matters: 'Working-Class' Women's Perspectives on Social Class'' (Taylor &amp; Francis, 1997)
* Manza, Jeff &amp; Brooks, Clem; ''Social Cleavages and Political Change: Voter Alignments and U.S. Party Coalitions'' (Oxford University Press, 1999).
* Manza, Jeff; &quot;Political Sociological Models of the U.S. New Deal&quot; ''Annual Review of Sociology'', (2000)  pp.&amp;nbsp;297+
* Manza, Jeff; Hout, Michael &amp; Brooks Clem; &quot;Class Voting in Capitalist Democracies since World War II: Dealignment, Realignment, or Trendless Fluctuation?&quot; ''Annual Review of Sociology'', Vol. 21, (1995)
* Marmot, Michael; ''The Status Syndrome: How Social Standing Affects Our Health and Longevity''  (2004)
* Marx, Karl &amp; Engels, Frederick; ''The Communist Manifesto'', (1848). (The key statement of class conflict as the driver of historical change).
* Merriman, John M.; ''Consciousness and Class Experience in Nineteenth-Century Europe'' (Holmes &amp; Meier Publishers, 1979)
* Ostrander, Susan A.; ''Women of the Upper Class'' (Temple University Press, 1984).
* Owensby, Brian P.; ''Intimate Ironies: Modernity and the Making of Middle-Class Lives in Brazil'' (Stanford University, 1999).
* Pakulski, Jan &amp; Waters, Malcolm; ''The Death of Class'' (Sage, 1996). (rejection of the relevance of class for modern societies)
* Payne, Geoff; ''The Social Mobility of Women: Beyond Male Mobility Models'' (1990)
* Savage, Mike; ''Class Analysis and Social Transformation'' (London: Open University Press, 2000).
* Sennett, Richard &amp; Cobb, Jonathan;  ''The Hidden Injuries of Class'', (Vintage, 1972) (classic study of the subjective experience of class).
* Siegelbaum, Lewis H. &amp; Suny, Ronald; eds.; ''Making Workers Soviet: Power, Class, and Identity.'' (Cornell University Press, 1994). Russia 1870-1940
* Wlkowitz, Daniel J.; ''Working with Class: Social Workers and the Politics of Middle-Class Identity'' (University of North Carolina Press, 1999).
* Weber, Max. &quot;Class, Status and Party&quot;, in e.g. Gerth, Hans and C. Wright Mills, ''From Max Weber: Essays in Sociology'', (Oxford University Press, 1958). (Weber's key statement of the multiple nature of stratification).
*Weinburg, Mark; [http://www.mises.org/journals/jls/2_1/2_1_4.pdf &quot;The Social Analysis of Three Early 19th century French liberals: Say, Comte, and Dunoyer&quot;], ''[[Journal of Libertarian Studies]]'', Vol. 2, No. 1, pp.&amp;nbsp;45–63, (1978).
* [[Ellen Meiksins Wood|Wood, Ellen Meiksins]]; ''The Retreat from Class: A New 'True' Socialism'', (Schocken Books, 1986) (ISBN 0-8052-7280-1) and (Verso Classics, January 1999) reprint with new introduction (ISBN 1-8598-4270-4).
* [[Ellen Meiksins Wood|Wood, Ellen Meiksins]]; [http://www.monthlyreview.org/797wood.htm &quot;Labor, the State, and Class Struggle&quot;], ''[[Monthly Review]]'', Vol. 49, No. 3, (1997).
* Wouters, Cas.;  &quot;The Integration of Social Classes.&quot; ''Journal of Social History''. Volume 29, Issue 1, (1995). pp 107+. (on social manners)
* Wright, Erik Olin; ''The Debate on Classes'' (Verso, 1990). (neo-Marxist)
* Wright, Erik Olin; ''Class Counts: Comparative Studies in Class Analysis'' (Cambridge University Press, 1997)
* Wright, Erik Olin ed. ''Approaches to Class Analysis'' (2005). (scholarly articles)
* Zmroczek, Christine &amp; Mahony, Pat (Eds.), ''Women and Social Class: International Feminist Perspectives.'' (London: UCL Press 1999)
{{Refend}}

==External links==
* [http://www.truelithuania.com/society-of-lithuania-1008 Class divisions of Lithuania, typical to a Post-Soviet society] - True Lithuania website
* Domhoff, G. William, ''&quot;[http://www2.ucsc.edu/whorulesamerica/power/class_domination.html The Class Domination Theory of Power]&quot;'', University of California, Santa Cruz

{{Social class}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Social Class}}
[[Category:Social classes| ]]
[[Category:Anthropology]]
[[Category:Social divisions]]
[[Category:Socialism]]
[[Category:Sociology index]]

[[ar:طبقة اجتماعية]]
[[bg:Социална класа]]
[[ca:Societat de classes]]
[[cs:Sociální třída]]
[[de:Klasse (Soziologie)]]
[[et:Sotsiaalne klass]]
[[es:Clase social]]
[[eo:Socia klaso]]
[[eu:Gizarte klase]]
[[fa:طبقه اجتماعی]]
[[fr:Classe sociale]]
[[gl:Clase social]]
[[ko:사회 계급]]
[[hi:सामाजिक वर्ग]]
[[id:Kelas sosial]]
[[is:Stétt]]
[[it:Classe sociale]]
[[he:מעמד חברתי]]
[[ky:Коомдук таптар]]
[[la:Classis]]
[[lt:Visuomenės sluoksnis]]
[[mk:Општествена класа]]
[[nl:Sociale klasse]]
[[ja:社会階級]]
[[no:Klasse (sosiologi)]]
[[pl:Klasa społeczna]]
[[pt:Classe social]]
[[ro:Clasă socială]]
[[ru:Социальный класс]]
[[simple:Social class]]
[[sk:Spoločenská trieda]]
[[sl:Družbeni razred]]
[[sr:Друштвена класа]]
[[fi:Yhteiskuntaluokka]]
[[sv:Samhällsklass]]
[[tl:Uring panlipunan]]
[[tr:Toplumsal sınıf]]
[[uk:Соціальний клас]]
[[vi:Giai cấp]]
[[zh:社会阶级]]</text>
      <sha1>qdaa5i9351b2kwj4ula1xg0xzsfxf5p</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
