<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Socialist feminism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1178286</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520294860</id>
      <parentid>503068307</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-28T17:56:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Idioma-bot</username>
        <id>2964546</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>r2.7.3) (Robot: Adding [[lt:Socialistinis feminizmas]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8578">{{Feminism sidebar}}
'''Socialist feminism''' is a branch of [[feminism]] that focuses upon both the public and private spheres of a woman's life and argues that [[Women's liberation|liberation]] can only be achieved by working to end both the [[economy|economic]] and [[culture|cultural]] sources of women's [[oppression]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.feministezine.com/feminist/modern/Socialist-Feminism.html What is Socialist Feminism?], retrieved on May 28th 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;  Socialist feminism is a two-pronged theory that broadens [[Marxist feminism]]'s argument for the role of [[capitalism]] in the oppression of women and [[radical feminism]]'s theory of the role of [[gender]] and the [[patriarchy]]. Socialist feminists reject radical feminism’s main claim that patriarchy the only or primary source of oppression of women.&lt;ref&gt;Buchanan, Ian. &quot;Socialist Feminism.&quot;  ''A Dictionary of Critical Theory.'' Oxford Reference Online.  Oxford University Press.  Web. 20 October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Rather, socialist feminists assert that women are unable to be free due to their financial dependence on males in society. Women are subjects to the male rulers in capitalism due to an uneven balance in wealth.  They see economic dependence as the driving force of women’s subjugation to men.   Further, socialist feminists see women’s liberation as a necessary part of larger quest for social, economic and political justice. 

[[File:Socialist-cover-72.jpeg|thumb|left|CWLU's &quot;Social Feminism: A Strategy for the Women's Movement,&quot; 1972]]
Socialist feminism draws upon many concepts found in Marxism; such as a [[historical materialism|historical materialist]] point of view, which means that they relate their ideas to the material and historical conditions of people’s lives.Socialist feminists thus consider how the sexism and gendered division of labor of each historical era is determined by the economic system of the time.  Those conditions are largely expressed through capitalist and patriarchal relations.Socialist feminists,thus reject the Marxist notion that class and class struggle are the only defining aspects of history and economic development. 
Marx asserted that when class oppression was overcome, gender oppression would vanish as well. According to socialist feminists, this view of gender oppression as a sub-class of class oppression is naive and much of the work of socialist feminists has gone towards specifying how gender and class work together to create distinct forms of oppression and privilege for women and men of each class.   For example, they observe that women’s class status is generally derivative of her husband’s class or occupational status,.e.g., a secretary that marries her boss assumes his class status. 

In 1972 the [[Chicago Women's Liberation Union]] published &quot;Socialist Feminism: A Strategy for the Women's Movement,&quot; which is believed to be the first to use the term &quot;socialist feminism,&quot; in publication.&lt;ref name=&quot;CWLUOver&quot;&gt;{{cite web | author1=Margeret &quot;Peg&quot; Strobel |author2=Sue Davenport | year=1999 | title=The Chicago Women's Liberation Union: An Introduction | work=The CWLU Herstory Website | publisher=University of Illinois | url=http://www.uic.edu/orgs/cwluherstory/CWLUAbout/abdoc1.html | accessdate=25 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other socialist feminists, notably two long-lived [[United States|American]] organizations [[Radical Women]] and the [[Freedom Socialist Party]], point to the classic Marxist writings of [[Frederick Engels]] (''[[The Origin of the Family, Private Property and the State]]'') and [[August Bebel]] (''Woman and Socialism'') as a powerful explanation of the link between gender oppression and class exploitation.

On the other hand, the [[Socialist Party USA]] is an example of a socialist feminist party which is not explicitly Marxist (although some members identify as Marxists). The party's [http://sp-usa.org/principles.html statement of principles] says, &quot;Socialist feminism confronts the common root of sexism, racism and classism: the determination of a life of oppression or privilege based on accidents of birth or circumstances. Socialist feminism is an inclusive way of creating social change. We value synthesis and cooperation rather than conflict and competition.&quot;

==Socialist Feminist Praxis==

Holds the belief that to achieve women’s liberation, women's liberation must be sought in conjunction with the social and economic justice of all people.  Socialist feminists see the fight to end male supremacy as key to social justice, but not the only issue, rather one of many forms of oppression that are mutually reinforcing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Kennedy|first=Elizabeth Lapovsky|title=Socialist Feminism: What Difference Did It Make To The History Of Women's Studies?|journal=Feminist Studies|year=2008|accessdate=2011-11-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Socialist Feminism, Motherhood,and the Private Sphere==

Socialist feminists highlight how motherhood and the gendered division of labor many assert grows “naturally” from women’s role as mothers is the source of women’s exclusion from the public sphere and creates women’s economic dependence on men.They assert that there is nothing natural about the gendered division of labor and show that the expectation that women perform all or most reproductive labor, i.e., labor associated with birthing and raising children but also the cleaning, cooking, and other tasks necessary to support human life, deny women the capacity to participate fully in economic activity outside the home.  
In order to free themselves from the conditions of work as a mother and housekeeper, socialist feminists such as [[Charlotte Perkins Gilman]] saw the professionalization of housework as key. This would be done by hiring professional nannies and housekeepers to take the load of domestic work away from the woman in the house&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Perkins Gilman|first=Charlotte|title=Women and Economics|year=1898|publisher=Small, Maynard &amp; Company}}&lt;/ref&gt;
.Perkins Gilman also recommended the redesign of homes in ways that would maximize their potential for creativity and leisure for women as well as men, i.e., emphasizing the need for rooms like studios and studies and eliminating kitchens and dining rooms.  These changes would necessitate the communalization of meal preparation and consumption outside the home and free women from their burden of providing meals on a house-by-house scale.

==Theorists==

*[[Johanna Brenner]]
*[[Barbara Ehrenreich]]
*[[Clara Fraser]]
*[[Charlotte Perkins Gilman]]
*[[Emma Goldman]]
*[[Donna Haraway]]
*[[Heidi I. Hartmann]]
*[[Selma James]]
*[[Sheila Rowbotham]]
*[[Sylvia Walby]]
*[[Nellie Wong]]

==Socialist Feminism Groups==

*[[Chicago Women's Liberation Union]]
*[[Bread and Roses of Boston]]

==See also==
*[[Oppressors-oppressed distinction]]
*[[History of Feminism]]
*[[Capitalist Patriarchy and the Case for Socialist Feminism]]
*[[Material feminism]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.redletterpress.org/rwmanifesto.html The Radical Women Manifesto: Socialist Feminist Theory, Program and Organizational Structure]
*[http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1132/is_10_54/ai_99146088 The socialist feminist project] by Nancy Holmstrom
* [http://www.redletterpress.org/firstdecade.html Socialist Feminism: The First Decade, 1966-76] by Gloria Martin
*[http://silviafederici.littlerednotebook.com/ Silvia Federici, recorded live at Fusion Arts, NYC. 11.30.04]
*[http://www.cwluherstory.com/CWLUArchive/socialfem.html What is Socialist Feminism?] by Barbara Ehrenreich at the CWLU Herstory Archive
*[http://college.hmco.com/history/readerscomp/women/html/wm_013118_socialistfem.htm Entry for Socialist Feminism] in the Reader's Companion to U.S. Women's History
*[http://www.historyisaweapon.org/defcon1/chisocfem.html Socialist Feminism: A Strategy for the Women's Movement By Hyde Park Chapter, Chicago Women's Liberation Union]
* [http://radicalblogs.org/lpps London Project for a Participatory Society] A Canadian &quot;anti-racist, pro-feminist, anti-capitalist organization&quot;

{{DEFAULTSORT:Socialist Feminism}}
[[Category:Socialism|Feminism, socialist]]
[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Feminism and social class]]
[[Category:Socialist feminism| ]]

[[el:Σοσιαλιστικός φεμινισμός]]
[[fa:فمینیسم سوسیالیستی]]
[[fr:Féminisme socialiste]]
[[lt:Socialistinis feminizmas]]
[[ru:Социалистический феминизм]]
[[sh:Socijalistički feminizam]]
[[sv:Socialistisk feminism]]
[[tr:Sosyalist feminizm]]</text>
      <sha1>dd3glaq80lyv9ue79ix8zjizyht9irs</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
