<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Socialist realism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>66491</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521615796</id>
      <parentid>521342114</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-06T03:37:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>EmausBot</username>
        <id>11292982</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>r2.7.2+) (Robot: Modifying [[zh:社會主義寫實主義]] to [[zh:社会主义的现实主义]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="39210">{{Distinguish|Social realism|Real socialism}}

'''Socialist realism''' is a style of [[realism (arts)|realistic art]] which was developed in the [[Soviet Union]] and became a dominant style in other socialist countries. Socialist realism is a [[Teleology|teleologically]]-oriented style having its purpose the furtherance of the goals of socialism and communism.  Although related, it should not be confused with [[social realism]], a broader type of art that realistically depicts subjects of social concern.  Unlike social realism, socialist realism often glorifies the roles of the meek and [[working class]] and the [[Revolutionary socialism|struggle for its emancipation]].

==Soviet Union==
[[File:Russia-Moscow-VDNH-3.jpg|thumb|left|[[All-Russia Exhibition Centre]] in Moscow]]

In conjunction with the [[Stalinist architecture|Socialist Classical]] style of architecture, Socialist realism was the officially approved type of art in the [[Soviet Union]] for nearly sixty years. All material goods and means of production belonged to the community as a whole; this included means of producing art, which were also seen as powerful propaganda tools. During the [[October Revolution]] of 1917, the [[Bolshevik]]s established an institution called [[Proletkult]] (the Proletarian Cultural and Enlightenment Organizations) which sought to put all arts into the service of the [[dictatorship of the proletariat]].

In the early years of the Soviet Union, Russian and Soviet artists embraced a wide variety of art forms under the auspices of Proletkult. Revolutionary politics and radical non-traditional art forms were seen as complementary. In art, [[Constructivism (art)|Constructivism]] flourished. In poetry, the nontraditional and the [[avant-garde]] were often praised.

This, however, was rejected by some members of the Communist party, who did not appreciate modern styles such as [[Impressionism]] and [[Cubism]], since these movements existed before the revolution and were thus associated with &quot;decadent bourgeois art.&quot; Socialist realism was, to some extent, a reaction against the adoption of these &quot;decadent&quot; styles. It was thought that the non-representative forms of art were not understood by the proletariat and could therefore not be used by the state for propaganda. [[Alexander Bogdanov]] argued that the radical reformation of society to Communist principles meant little if any bouregeois art would prove useful; some of his more radical followers advocated the destruction of libraries and museums.&lt;ref&gt;[[Richard Pipes]], ''Russia Under the Bolshevik Regime'', p. 288, ISBN 978-0-394-50242-7&lt;/ref&gt; Lenin rejected this philosophy,&lt;ref&gt;Richard Pipes, ''Russia Under the Bolshevik Regime'', p. 289, ISBN 978-0-394-50242-7&lt;/ref&gt; deplored the rejection of the beautiful because it was old, and explicitly described art as needing to call on its heritage: &quot;Proletarian culture must be the logical development of the store of knowledge mankind has accumulated under the yoke of capitalist, landowner, and bureaucratic society.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Oleg Sopontsinsky, ''Art in the Soviet Union: Painting, Sculpture, Graphic Arts'', p 6 Aurora Art Publishers, Leningrad, 1978&lt;/ref&gt; Modern art styles appeared to refuse to draw upon this heritage, thus clashing with the long realist tradition in Russia and rendering the art scene complex.&lt;ref&gt;Oleg Sopontsinsky, ''Art in the Soviet Union:  Painting, Sculpture, Graphic Arts'', p. 21 Aurora Art Publishers, Leningrad, 1978&lt;/ref&gt; Even in Lenin's time, a cultural bureaucracy began to restrain art to fit [[Propaganda in the Soviet Union|propaganda purposes]].&lt;ref&gt;Richard Pipes, ''Russia Under the Bolshevik Regime'', p283, ISBN 978-0-394-50242-7&lt;/ref&gt;

Socialist realism became state policy in 1932 when [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] leader [[Joseph Stalin]] promulgated the decree &quot;On the Reconstruction of Literary and Art Organizations&quot;.  Accordingly, the Moscow and Leningrad Union of Artists was established in 1932, which brought the history of post-revolutionary art to a close. The epoch of Soviet art began.&lt;ref&gt;''Sergei V. Ivanov'' Unknown Socialist Realism. The Leningrad School, p. 28 – 29. ISBN 5-901724-21-6, ISBN 978-5-901724-21-7.&lt;/ref&gt; In Leningrad well-known artist and art teacher [[Kuzma Petrov-Vodkin]] was elected the first president of the Union of Artists. This choice laid down the foundation of the lasting development of the Leningrad Union of Artists and Academy of Arts as a unified creative body.    In 1931-2, the early emphasis on the &quot;little man&quot; and the anonymous laboring masses gave way to the &quot;hero of labor&quot;, derived from the people but set apart by the scale of his deeds.&lt;ref name=&quot;overy259&quot;&gt;[[Richard Overy]], ''The Dictators: Hitler's Germany, Stalin's Russia'', p259 ISBN 0-393-02030-4&lt;/ref&gt;  Writers were explicitly enjoined to develop &quot;heroization.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;overy259&quot;/&gt;  This reflected a call for romantic art, which reflected the ideal rather than the realistic.&lt;ref name=&quot;Richard Overy p355-6&quot;&gt;Richard Overy, ''The Dictators: Hitler's Germany, Stalin's Russia'', p 355-6 ISBN 0-393-02030-4&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, it should show one clear and unambiguous meaning.&lt;ref&gt;Richard Overy, ''The Dictators: Hitler's Germany, Stalin's Russia'', p368 ISBN 0-393-02030-4&lt;/ref&gt;

The first exhibition organized by the Leningrad Union of Artists took place in 1935. Its participants – [[Piotr Buchkin]], [[Rudolf Frentz]], [[Alexander Nikolayevich Samokhvalov|Alexander Samokhvalov]], [[Isaak Brodsky]], [[Kuzma Petrov-Vodkin]], [[Kazimir Malevich]], Nikolai Dormidontov, Mikhail Avilov among them – became the founding fathers of the Leningrad school while their works formed one of its richest layers and the basis of the largest museum collections of Soviet painting of the 1930-1950s.

In 1932, the Leningrad Institute of Proletarian Visual Arts was transformed into the Institute of Painting, Sculpture and Architecture (since 1944 named [[Ilya Repin]]). The 15-year period of constant reformation of the country’s largest art institute came to an end. Thus, basic elements of the [[Leningrad School of Painting|Leningrad school]] – namely, a higher art education establishment of a new type and a unified professional union of Leningrad artists, were created by the end of 1932. In 1934 [[Isaak Brodsky]], a disciple of [[Ilya Repin]] was appointed director of the National Academy of Arts and the Leningrad Institute of Painting, Sculpture and Architecture. Brodsky invited distinguished painters and pedagogues to teach at the Academy, namely [[Konstantin Yuon]], Pavel Naumov, [[Boris Ioganson]], Semion Abugov, Pavel Shillingovsky, [[Dmitry Kardovsky]], [[Alexander Osmerkin]], [[Nikolai Radlov]], Yevgeny Lansere, Alexander Lubimov, [[Rudolf Frentz]], Nikolai Petrov, Victor Sinaisky, Vasily Shukhaev, Dmitry Kiplik, Nikolai Punin, Vasily Meshkov, Mikhail Bernshtein, Efim Cheptsov, [[Ivan Bilibin]], [[Matvey Manizer]], [[Piotr Buchkin]], [[Anna Ostroumova-Lebedeva]], Alexander Karev, Leonid Ovsyannikov, Sergei Priselkov, Ivan Stepashkin, [[Konstantin Rudakov]] and others.

[[File:Pozdneev-Sday-per20bw.jpg|thumb|220px|left|[[Spring Day (painting)|&quot;Spring day&quot;]] &lt;br&gt;by [[Nikolai Pozdneev]]]]
Art exhibitions of 1935–1940 disprove the claims that artistic life of the period was suppressed by the ideology and artists submitted entirely to what was then called ‘social order’. A great number of [[landscape painting|landscapes]], [[portrait painting|portraits]], [[genre painting]]s exhibited at the time pursued purely technical purposes and were thus ostensibly free from any ideology. Genre painting was also approached in a similar way.&lt;ref&gt;''Sergei V. Ivanov'' Unknown Socialist Realism. The Leningrad School, p. 29, 32 – 340. ISBN 5-901724-21-6, ISBN 978-5-901724-21-7.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the post-war period between the mid-fifties and sixties, the Leningrad school of painting was approaching its vertex. New generations of artists who had graduated from the Academy ([[Repin Institute of Arts]]) in the 1930s–50s were in their prime. They were quick to present their art, they strived for experiments and were eager to appropriate a lot and to learn even more. Their time and contemporaries, with all its images, ideas and dispositions found it full expression in portraits by [[Lev Russov]], [[Victor Oreshnikov]], [[Boris Korneev]], [[Leonid Steele]], [[Oleg Lomakin]], Semion Rotnitsky, [[Vladimir Gorb]], [[Samuil Nevelshtein]], [[Engels Kozlov]], in landscapes by [[Nikolai Timkov]], [[Vladimir Ovchinnikov (painter)|Vladimir Ovchinnikov]], [[Sergei Ivanovich Osipov|Sergei Osipov]], [[Alexander Mikhailovich Semionov|Alexander Semionov]], [[Arseny Semionov]], [[Vasily Golubev]], [[Nikolai Galakhov]], [[Dmitry Maevsky]], in genre paintings by [[Nikolai Pozdneev]], [[Yuri Neprintsev]], Yevsey Moiseenko, Andrey Milnikov, [[Nina Veselova]], [[Mikhail Trufanov]], [[Yuri Tulin]], [[Mikhail Natarevich]], and others.

In 1957, the first all-Russian Congress of Soviet artists took place in Moscow. In 1960, the all-Russian Union of Artists was organized. Accordingly, these events influenced the art life in Moscow, Leningrad and the provinces. The scope of experimentation was broadened; in particular, this concerned the form and painterly and plastic language. Images of youths and students, rapidly changing villages and cities, virgin lands brought under cultivation, grandiose construction plans being realized in Siberia and the Volga region, great achievements of Soviet science and technology became the chief topics of the new painting. Heroes of the time – young scientists, workers, civil engineers, physicians – were made the most popular heroes of paintings.

[[File:Semionov-Alexase35bw.jpg|thumb|right|220px|&quot;[[Malaya Sadovaya street (painting)|Malaya Sadovaya Street]]&quot; &lt;br&gt;by [[Alexander Semionov]]]]
In this period, life provided artists with plenty of thrilling topics, positive figures and images. Legacy of many great artists and [[art movements]] became available for study and public discussion again. This greatly broadened artists’ understanding of the [[realist art|realist method]] and widened its possibilities. It was the repeated renewal of the very conception of [[Realism (visual arts)|realism]] that made this style dominate [[Russian art]] throughout its history. Realist tradition gave rise to many trends of [[Contemporary art|contemporary painting]], including painting from nature, &quot;severe style&quot; painting and decorative art. However, during this period [[impressionism]], [[postimpressionism]], [[cubism]] and [[expressionism]] also had their fervent adherents and interpreters.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.leningradschool.com/outline.htm ''Sergei V. Ivanov.'' The Leningrad School of painting 1930 – 1990s. Historical outline.]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Union of Soviet Writers]] was founded to control the output of authors, and the new policy was rubber-stamped at the Congress of Socialist Writers in 1934. It was enforced ruthlessly in all spheres of artistic endeavour. Artists who strayed from the official line were severely punished&lt;!-- should be referenced --&gt;. Form and content were often limited, with erotic, religious, abstract, surrealist and expressionist art being forbidden. Formal experiments, including internal dialogue, stream of consciousness, nonsense, free-form association and cut-up were also disallowed. This was either because they were &quot;decadent&quot;, unintelligible to the proletariat or [[counter-revolutionary]].
In response to the 1934 Congress in Russia, the most important American writers of the left gathered in the First American Writers Congress of 26, 27 April 1935 in Chicago, at the meetings which were supported by Stalin. [[Waldo David Frank]] was its first president See the [[League of American Writers]] which was backed by the Communist Party USA. A number of the novelists balked at the control, and the League broke up at the invasion of the Soviet Union by German forces.

The restrictions were relaxed somewhat after Stalin's death in 1953, but the state still kept a tight rein on personal artistic expression. This caused many artists to choose to go into exile, for example the [[Odessa Group]] from the city of that name. Independent-minded artists that remained continued to feel the hostility of the state. In 1974, for instance, a show of unofficial art in a field near Moscow was broken up, and the artworks destroyed with a water cannon and bulldozers (see [[Bulldozer Exhibition]]). [[Mikhail Gorbachev]]'s policy of [[glasnost]] and [[perestroika]] facilitated an explosion of interest in alternative art styles in the late 1980s, but socialist realism remained in limited force as the official state art style until as late as 1991. It was not until after the [[fall of the Soviet Union]] that artists were finally freed from state censorship{{Citation needed|date=August 2008}}.

==Other socialist states==
[[File:Wuhan-Flood-Memorial-0226.jpg|thumb|The people of [[Wuhan]] fighting [[1954 Yangtze River Floods|the flood of 1954]], as depicted on a monument erected in 1969]]

After the Russian Revolution, socialist realism became an international literary movement. Socialist trends in literature were established in the 1920s in Germany, France, Czechoslovakia, and Poland. Writers who helped develop socialist realism in the West included [[Louis Aragon]], [[Johannes Becher]], and [[Pablo Neruda]].&lt;ref name=&quot;cultinfo.ru&quot;&gt;[http://www.cultinfo.ru/fulltext/1/001/008/104/892.htm D.F. Markov and L.I. Timofeev, &quot;Socialist Realism&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The doctrine of socialist realism in other [[People's Republic]]s, was legally enforced from 1949 to 1956. It involved all domains of visual and literary arts, though its most spectacular achievements were made in the field of architecture, considered a key weapon in the creation of a new [[social order]], intended to help spread the communist doctrine by influencing citizens' consciousness as well as their outlook on life. During this massive undertaking, a crucial role fell to architects perceived not as merely engineers creating streets and edifices, but rather as &quot;[[engineers of the human soul]]&quot; who, in addition to extending simple aesthetics into urban design, were to express grandiose ideas and arouse feelings of stability, persistence and political power.

Today, arguably the only countries still focused on these aesthetic principles are [[North Korea]], [[Laos]], and to some extent [[Vietnam]]. The People's Republic of China occasionally reverts to socialist realism for specific purposes, such as idealised propaganda posters to promote the [[Chinese space program]]. Socialist realism had little mainstream impact in the non-Communist world, where it was widely seen as a totalitarian means of imposing state control on artists.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sinoss.net/qikan/uploadfile/2011/0708/20110708020439197.pdf Lin Jung-hua. Post-Soviet Aestheticians Rethinking Russianization and Chinization of Marxizm//Russian Language and Literature Studies. Serial № 33. Beijing, Capital Normal University, 2011, №3. Р.46-53.]&lt;/ref&gt;

The former [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia]] was an important exception among the communist countries, because after the [[Tito-Stalin split]] in 1948, it abandoned socialist realism along with other elements previously imported from the Soviet system and allowed greater artistic freedom.&lt;ref&gt;[[Library of Congress Country Studies]] – [http://lcweb2.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/r?frd/cstdy:@field(DOCID+yu0035) Yugoslavia: ''Introduction of Socialist Self-Management'']&lt;/ref&gt; [[Miroslav Krleža]], one of the leading Yugoslav intellectuals, held a speech at the Third Congress of the Writers Alliance of Yugoslavia in [[Ljubljana]] in 1952, which is considered a turning point in the Yugoslav denouncement of [[dogmatic]] socialist realism.

==Roots==

The initial tendencies toward socialist realism date from the mid-19th century. They include revolutionary literature in Great Britain (the poetry of the Chartist movement), Germany (Herwegh, Freiligrath, and G. Weerth), and France (the literature of the Paris Commune and Pottier's &quot;Internationale.&quot;) Socialist realism emerged as a literary method in the early 20th century in Russia, especially in the works of Gorky. It was also apparent in the works of writers like Kotsiubinsky, Rainis, Akopian, and Edvoshvili. Following Gorky, writers in several countries combined the realistic depiction of life with the expression of a socialist world view. They included Barbusse, Andersen Nexø, and John Reed.&lt;ref name=&quot;cultinfo.ru&quot;/&gt;

The political aspect of socialist realism was, in some respects, a continuation of pre-Soviet state policy. [[Censorship]] and attempts to control the content of art did not begin with the Soviets, but were a long-running feature of Russian life. The [[Tsar]]ist government also appreciated the potentially disruptive effect of art and required all books to be cleared by the censor. Writers and artists in 19th century [[Imperial Russia]] became quite skilled at evading censorship by making their points without spelling it out in so many words. However, Soviet censors were not easily evaded.

Socialist realism had its roots in [[neoclassicism]] and the traditions of realism in [[Russian literature]] of the 19th century that described the life of simple people. It was exemplified by the aesthetic philosophy of [[Maxim Gorky]]. The work of the [[Peredvizhniki]] (The Itinerants (or Wanderers), a Russian [[realism (arts)|realist]] movement of the late 19th / early 20th centuries), [[Jacques-Louis David]] and [[Ilya Yefimovich Repin]] were notable influences.

Socialist Realism was a product of the Soviet system. Whereas in market societies professional artists earned their living selling to, or being commissioned by rich individuals or the Church, in Soviet society not only was the market suppressed, there were few if any individuals able to patronise the arts and only one institution – the State itself. Hence artists became state employees. As such the State set the parameters for what it employed them to do.
What was expected of the artist was that he/she be formally qualified and to reach a standard of competence. However, whilst this rewarded basic competency, it did not provide an incentive to excel, resulting in a stultification similar to that in other spheres of Soviet society.
[[File:Avrora Krasnodar.jpg|thumb|13 May 1967 Cinemacenter Avrora. Architect E.A. Serdjukov. 1300 Seats.]]
The State, after the Congress of 1934, laid down four rules for what became known as &quot;Socialist Realism&quot;:
{{quote|
That the work be:
# Proletarian: art relevant to the workers and understandable to them.
# Typical: scenes of every day life of the people.
# Realistic: in the representational sense.
# Partisan: supportive of the aims of the State and the Party.}}

Even so, many of the art works glorifying [[Joseph Stalin]] and other leaders are hardly in keeping with these ideals and the charge that art be understandable to the whole people negated the notion of the [[avant garde]] and discouraged experimental approaches. The realism achieved was often technically very good and similar to many Western works intended as magazine illustration or bookjackets, rather than High Art. The partisan quality tends to attract the most criticism, in that it often predominated to the exclusion of the other tenets, so that paintings of peasants feasting after bumper harvests was neither real nor typical of the lot of many of those depicted, especially in the [[Ukrainian Famine]].{{Citation needed|date=April 2009}}

==Characteristics==

[[File:Socrealizm.jpeg|thumb|right|150px|Socialist-Realist allegories surrounding the [[Palace of Culture and Science]] in [[Warsaw]]]]
Socialist realism held that successful art depicts and glorifies the proletariat's struggle toward socialist progress. The Statute of the Union of Soviet Writers in 1934 stated that socialist realism

{{quote|is the basic method of Soviet literature and literary criticism. It demands of the artist the truthful, historically concrete representation of reality in its revolutionary development. Moreover, the truthfulness and historical concreteness of the artistic representation of reality must be linked with the task of ideological transformation and education of workers in the spirit of socialism.|Page 148, ''On Socialist Realism&quot; by [[Andrei Sinyavsky]] writing as Abram Tertz|ISBN 0-520-04677-3}}

Its purpose was to elevate the common worker, whether factory or agricultural, by presenting his life, work, and recreation as admirable. In other words, its goal was to educate the people in the goals and meaning of Communism. The ultimate aim was to create what Lenin called &quot;an entirely new type of human being&quot;: ''[[New Soviet man|New Soviet Man]]''. Stalin described the practitioners of socialist realism as &quot;engineers of souls&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Richard Overy, ''The Dictators: Hitler's Germany, Stalin's Russia'', p. 354 ISBN 0-393-02030-4&lt;/ref&gt;

The &quot;realism&quot; part is important. Soviet art at this time aimed to depict the worker as he truly was, carrying his tools.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}} In a sense, the movement mirrors the course of American and Western art, where the everyday human being became the subject of the novel, the play, poetry, and art. The proletariat was at the center of communist ideals; hence, his life was a worthy subject for study. This was an important shift away from the aristocratic art produced under the Russian [[tsar]]s of previous centuries, but had much in common with the late-19th century fashion for depicting the social life of the common people.  In practice, this entailed realistic depictions of objects, so that ordinary people could understand; a theater could not use a box to represent a chair.&lt;ref&gt;Tobia Frankel, ''The Russian Artist'', p 124, MacMillian Company, New York, NY, 1972&lt;/ref&gt;  The artist could not, however, portray life just as he saw it; because everything that reflected poorly on Communism had to be omitted, and indeed, people who were not simply good or evil could not be used as characters.&lt;ref&gt;Tobia Frankel, ''The Russian Artist'', p 125, MacMillian Company, New York, NY, 1972&lt;/ref&gt; All characters were poured into a heroic mold, sometimes termed [[heroic realism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;design&quot;&gt;eye magazine, &quot;[http://www.eyemagazine.com/feature.php?id=62&amp;fid=270 Designing heroes]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;  This reflected a call for heroic and romantic art, which reflected the ideal rather than the realistic.&lt;ref name=&quot;Richard Overy p355-6&quot;/&gt;  Art was filled with health and happiness; paintings teemed with busy industrial and agricultural scenes, and sculptures depicted workers, sentries, and schoolchildren.&lt;ref name=&quot;Way1&quot;&gt;Lewis Stegelbaum and Andrei Sokolov, ''Stalinism As A Way Of Life'', p. 1 ISBN 0-300-08480-3&lt;/ref&gt;

Compared to the eclectic variety of 20th century Western art, socialist realism often resulted in a fairly bland and predictable range of artistic products (indeed, Western critics wryly described the principles of socialist realism as &quot;girl meets tractor&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;Sheila Fitzpatrick, [http://books.google.ca/books?id=p2Hxcbxl0OoC&amp;pg=PA209&amp;lpg=PA209&amp;dq=%22girl+meets+tractor%22&amp;source=web&amp;ots=EQyhU0Jbkh&amp;sig=cGMG2SYpULzAY3QGReVzoiTMgrY&amp;hl=en The Cultural Front: Power and Culture in Revolutionary Russia], Published 1992
by Cornell University Press, ISBN 0-8014-9516-4.&lt;/ref&gt; Painters would depict happy, muscular peasants and workers in factories and collective farms;&lt;ref name=&quot;Way1&quot;/&gt; during the Stalin period, they also produced numerous heroic portraits of the dictator to serve his [[cult of personality]].&lt;ref name=&quot;design&quot;/&gt; Industrial and agricultural landscapes were popular subjects, glorifying the achievements of the Soviet economy. Novelists were expected to produce uplifting stories in a manner consistent with the Marxist doctrine of [[dialectical materialism]]. Composers were to produce rousing, vivid music that reflected the life and struggles of the proletariat. It was argued that mere photographic replication of facts was merely &quot;[[Naturalism (arts)|naturalism]]&quot;, while socialist realism was distinguished by a will and purpose on part of the artist, and his recognition of these facts as part of a vision of the whole.&lt;ref&gt;Jochen Hellbeck, ''Revolution on My Mind'', p 98-99, ISBN 0-674-02174-6&lt;/ref&gt;  Even diarists would attempt to fit their accounts of their daily lives into suitable purpose-driven, future-oriented accounts.&lt;ref&gt;Jochen Hellbeck, ''Revolution on My Mind'', p 99, ISBN 0-674-02174-6&lt;/ref&gt;

Socialist realism thus demanded close adherence to party doctrine, and has often been criticized as detrimental to the creation of true, unfettered art{{spaced ndash}} or as being little more than a means to censor artistic expression. [[Vsevolod Kochetov]] is one of the typical representatives who rigorously applied those doctrines even in 1960s and early 1970s. [[Czesław Miłosz]], writing in the introduction to Sinyavsky's ''On Socialist Realism'',&lt;!--page 134--&gt; describes the products of socialist realism as &quot;inferior&quot;, ascribing this as necessarily proceeding from the limited view of reality permitted to creative artists.

Not all Marxists accepted the necessity of socialist realism ([[Marx]]'s, [[Engels]]' and [[Trotsky]]'s views on art and culture were very liberal and may have balked at the propagandism of Socialist realism themselves). Its establishment as state doctrine in the 1930s had rather more to do with internal Communist Party politics than classic Marxist imperatives. The [[Hungary|Hungarian]] Marxist essayist [[Georg Lukács]] criticized the rigidity of socialist realism, proposing his own &quot;critical realism&quot; as an alternative. However, such critical voices were a rarity until the 1980s.

==Notable works and artists==
[[File:Womacka Gemeinschaftsarbeit.jpg|thumb|250px|Mosaic by [[Walter Womacka]] in [[Eisenhüttenstadt]]]]
[[Maxim Gorky]]'s novel ''[[Mother (novel)|Mother]]'' is usually considered to have been the first socialist realist novel. Gorky was also a major factor in the school's rapid rise, and his pamphlet, ''On Socialist Realism'', essentially lays out the needs of Soviet art. Other important works of literature include [[Fyodor Gladkov]]'s ''[[Cement (novel)|Cement]]'' (1925), [[Nikolai Ostrovsky]]'s ''[[How the Steel Was Tempered]]'' and [[Mikhail Sholokhov]]'s two volume epic, ''[[Quiet Flows the Don]]'' (1934) and ''[[The Don Flows Home to the Sea]]'' (1940). [[Yury Krymov]]'s novel ''[[Tanker &quot;Derbent&quot;]]'' (1938) portrays Soviet merchant seafarers being transformed by the [[Stakhanovite movement]].

[[Martin Andersen Nexø]] developed socialist realism in his own way. His creative method was characterized by a combination of publicistic passion, a critical view of capitalist society, and a steadfast striving to bring reality into accord with socialist ideals. The novel ''Pelle, the Conqueror'' is considered to be a classic of socialist realism. The novel ''Ditte, Daughter of Man'' had a working-class woman as its heroine. He battled against the enemies of socialism in the books ''Two Worlds'', and ''Hands Off!''.

The novels of [[Louis Aragon]] such as ''The Real World'' depicts the working class as a rising force of the nation. He published two books of documentary prose, ''The Communist Man''. In the collection of poems ''A Knife in the Heart Again'', Aragon criticizes the penetration of American imperialism into Europe. The novel ''The Holy Week'' depicts the artist's path toward the people against a broad social and historical background.

[[Hanns Eisler]] composed many workers' songs, marches, and ballads on current political topics such as ''Song of Solidarity'', ''Song of the United Front'', and ''Song of the Comintern''. He was a founder of a new style of revolutionary song for the masses. He also composed works in larger forms such as ''Requiem for Lenin''. Eisler's most important works include the cantatas ''German Symphony'', ''Serenade of the Age'' and ''Song of Peace''. Eisler combines features of revolutionary songs with varied expression. His symphonic music is known for its complex and subtle orchestration.

Closely associated with the rise of the labor movement was the development of the revolutionary song, which was performed at demonstrations and meetings. Among the most famous of the revolutionary songs are ''[[The Internationale]]'' and ''[[Warszawianka (1905)|Warszawianka]]''. Notable songs from Russia include ''Boldly, Comrades, in Step'', ''Workers' Marseillaise'', and ''Rage, Tyrants''. Folk and revolutionary songs influenced the Soviet mass songs. The mass song was a leading genre in Soviet music, especially during the 1930s and the war. The mass song influenced other genres, including the art song, opera, and film music. The most popular mass songs include [[Isaak Dunayevsky|Dunaevsky's]] ''Song of the Homeland'', [[Matvey Blanter|Blanter's]] ''[[Katyusha (song)|Katiusha]]'', Novikov's ''Hymn of Democratic Youth of the World'', and [[Alexander Vasilyevich Alexandrov|Aleksandrov's]] ''[[Svyaschennaya Voyna|Sacred War]]''.

In the early 1930s, [[Soviet cinema|Soviet filmmakers]] applied socialist realism in their work. Notable films include ''Chapaev'', which shows the role of the people in the history-making process. The theme of revolutionary history was developed in films such as ''[[The Youth of Maxim]]'', by [[Grigori Kozintsev]] and [[Leonid Trauberg]], ''[[Shchors (film)|Shchors]]'' by Dovzhenko, and ''We are from Kronstadt'' by E. Dzigan. The shaping of the new man under socialism was a theme of films such as ''A Start Life'' by N. Ekk, ''Ivan'' by Dovzhenko, ''Valerii Chkalov'' by M. Kalatozov and the film version of ''Tanker &quot;Derbent&quot;'' (1941). Some films depicted the part of peoples of the Soviet Union against foreign invaders: ''Alexander Nevsky'' by Eisenstein, ''Minin and Pozharsky'' by Pudvokin, and ''Bogdan Khmelnitsky'' by Savchenko. Soviet politicians were the subjects in films such as [[Sergei Yutkevich|Yutkevich]]'s trilogy of movies about Lenin. 

Socialist realism was also applied to [[Bollywood|Hindi films]] of the 1940s and 1950s.{{fact|date=October 2012}} These include [[Chetan Anand (producer &amp; director)|Chetan Anand]]'s ''[[Neecha Nagar]]'' (1946), which won the [[Palme d'Or|Grand Prize]] at the [[1946 Cannes Film Festival|1st Cannes Film Festival]], and [[Bimal Roy]]'s ''[[Two Acres of Land]]'' (1953), which won the International Prize at the [[1954 Cannes Film Festival|7th Cannes Film Festival]].

The painter [[Aleksandr Deineka]] provides a notable example for his expressionist and patriotic scenes of the Second World War, collective farms, and sports. [[Yuri Pimenov]], [[Boris Ioganson]] and [[Geli Korzev]] have also been described as &quot;unappreciated masters of twentieth-century realism&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=Marek |last=Bartelik, |url= http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0425/is_4_58/ai_59552693 |title=Concerning Socialist Realism: Recent Publications on Russian Art (book review) |journal=Art Journal |year=1999}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another well-known practitioner was [[Fyodor Pavlovich Reshetnikov]].

==Consequences==
[[File:Waw-soviet-military-cemetery-relief.jpg|thumb|250px|A relief from the [[Soviet military cemetery in Warsaw]] showing workers greeting victorious soldiers.]]

Socialist realism had a significant impact on art in Russia and elsewhere. In Russia, the works of authors such as Gorky, Mayakovsky, Sholokhov, Tvardovsky, Fadeyev, Leonov, and many other writers became established classics, achieved worldwide renown, and have become a firm part of the world's cultural heritage. Socialist realism was credited for helping talent to develop and art to flourish in many forms and for making it more accessible to the masses.&lt;ref&gt;http://bse.sci-lib.com/article104892.html&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Mikhail Bulgakov]] wrote his work, ''[[The Master and Margarita]]'', in secret, despite earlier successes such as ''White Guard''. In 1936 [[Dmitri Shostakovich]] was criticized for his opera [[Lady Macbeth of Mtsensk]] in a [[Pravda]] article entitled &quot;Muddle instead of Music&quot;,.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Muddle instead of Music |url=http://www.arnoldschalks.nl/tlte1sub1.html|accessdate=20 September 2010|newspaper=[[Pravda]]|date=28 January 1936|language=English Translation}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sergei Prokofiev]] too found his musical language increasingly restricted in the years after his permanent return to the Soviet Union in 1935 (especially in the wake of the 1948 [[Zhdanov Doctrine|Zhdanov Decree]]), although he continued to compose until the end of his life five years later.

The political doctrine behind socialist realism also underlay the pervasive censorship of Communist societies. Apart from obvious political considerations that saw works such as those of [[George Orwell]] being banned, access to foreign art and literature was also restricted on aesthetic grounds. [[Bourgeoisie|Bourgeois]] art and all forms of experimentalism and [[Formalism (art)|formalism]] were denounced as decadent, degenerate and pessimistic, and therefore anti-Communist in principle. The works of [[James Joyce]] were particularly harshly condemned. The net effect was that it was not until the 1980s that the general public in the Communist countries were able to freely access many works of Western art and literature.

== Painting ==
&lt;gallery&gt;
file:Rylov Blue Expanse.jpg|A. Rylov. In the Blue Expanse (1918)
file:Furmanov by malutin.jpg| S. Malyutin. Portrait of writer Furmanov
File:Sergey Malyutin 07.jpg|S. Malyutin. Partisan
file:Brodski lenin.jpg|I. Brodsky. Lenin in Smolny (1930)
File:Isaak Brodsky stalin02.jpg|I. Brodsky. Stalin
File:Mitrophan Grekov 01.jpg|M. Grekov. Trumpeter and standard-bearer
file:Slushajut moskvu.jpg|&quot;They are hearing Moscow&quot; (poster).

file:Pionerka kasatkin.jpg|N. Kasatkin. Pioneer-girl with book (1926)
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Sculpture==
&lt;gallery&gt;
file:Shadr-stone-proletariat.jpeg|Ivan Shadr. Stone as a weapon of proletariat
File:Socrealizm.jpeg|Socialist-Realist allegories surrounding the [[Palace of Culture and Science in Warsaw|Palace of Culture and Science]]
File:Waw-soviet-military-cemetery-relief.jpg|A relief from the [[Soviet military cemetery in Warsaw]] showing workers greeting victorious soldiers.
File:Letna stalin sousosi.jpg|[[Stalin's Monument (Prague)|Monument]] in [[Prague]]-Letná (1955–1962)

File:Zaliasis Tiltas Statues.JPG|The construction and industry statue on the Green Bridge, [[Vilnius]]; it is one of the few remaining in its original place in Lithuania.
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== See also ==
*[[Capitalist realism]]
*[[Socialist realism in Romania]]
*[[Socialist realism in Poland]] 

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* Bek, Mikuláš, Geoffrey Chew, and Petr Macek (eds.). ''Socialist Realism and Music''. Musicological Colloquium at the Brno International Music Festival 36. Prague: KLP; Brno: Institute of Musicology, Masaryk University, 2004. ISBN 80-86791-18-1
* Golomstock, Igor.  ''Totalitarian Art in the Soviet Union, the Third Reich, Fascist Italy and the People's Republic of China'', Harper Collins, 1990.
* James, C. Vaughan. ''Soviet Socialist Realism: Origins and Theory''. New York: St. Martin's Press, 1973.
* Ivanov, Sergei. ''&quot;Unknown Socialist Realism. The Leningrad School&quot;''. Saint Petersburg, NP-Print, 2007 ISBN 978-5-901724-21-7
* Prokhorov, Gleb. ''Art under Socialist Realism: Soviet Painting, 1930–1950''. East Roseville, NSW, Australia: Craftsman House; G + B Arts International, 1995. ISBN 976-8097-83-3
* Rideout, Walter B. ''The Radical Novel in the United States: 1900–1954. Some Interrelations of Literature and Society''. New York: Hill and Wang, 1966.
* Christian Saehrendt, Kunst als Botschafter einer künstlichen Nation (Art from an artificial nation – about modern art as a tool of the GDRs propaganda), Stuttgart 2009 (
* [[Andrei Sinyavsky|Sinyavsky, Andrei]] [writing as Abram Tertz]. ''&quot;The Trial Begins&quot;, and &quot;On Socialist Realism&quot;'', translated by Max Hayward and George Dennis, with an introduction by [[Czesław Miłosz]]. Berkeley: University of California Press, 1960–1982. ISBN 0-520-04677-3
* Lin Jung-hua. Post-Soviet Aestheticians Rethinking Russianization and Chinization of Marxizm//Russian Language and Literature Studies. Serial № 33. Beijing, Capital Normal University, 2011, №3. Р.46-53.

==External links==
{{Commons category|Socialist realism}}

*[http://www.modernamuseet.se/en/Stockholm/Programme/Conference-Socialist-Realist-Art// Moderna Museet in Stockholm, Sweden: Socialist Realist Art Conference]
*[http://www.marxists.org/subject/art/visual_arts/painting/exhibits/socialist-realism.htm Marxists.org Socialist Realism page]
*[http://www.korpanyuk-art.com/ Socialist Realism art gallery]
*[http://horvath.members.1012.at/soc.htm Virtual Museum of Political Art – Socialist Realism]
*[http://www.leningradschool.com/outline.htm ''Sergei V. Ivanov.'' The Leningrad School of painting. Historical outline.]
*[http://www.library.illinois.edu/spx/webct/SubjectResources/SubSourRus/artsruart2.htm Research Guide to Russian Art]

{{Avant-garde}}
{{Russian art movements}}
{{Joseph Stalin}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Socialist Realism}}
[[Category:Communism]]
[[Category:Film styles]]
[[Category:Socialism]]
[[Category:Socialist realism| Socialist realism]]
[[Category:Soviet art]]
[[Category:Realism (art movement)]]
[[Category:Art movements]]
[[Category:Propaganda art]]
[[Category:Socialist realism artists]]
[[Category:Soviet painters]]
[[Category:Censorship in the Soviet Union]]

{{Link FA|af}}

[[af:Sosialistiese realisme]]
[[ar:واقعية اشتراكية]]
[[az:Sosialist realizmi]]
[[be:Сацыялістычны рэалізм]]
[[be-x-old:Сацыялістычны рэалізм]]
[[bg:Социалистически реализъм]]
[[ca:Realisme socialista]]
[[cs:Socialistický realismus]]
[[de:Sozialistischer Realismus]]
[[et:Sotsialistlik realism]]
[[es:Realismo socialista]]
[[eu:Errealismo sozialista]]
[[fa:واقع‌گرایی سوسیالیستی]]
[[fr:Réalisme socialiste soviétique]]
[[gl:Realismo socialista]]
[[hr:Socrealizam]]
[[it:Realismo socialista]]
[[he:ריאליזם סוציאליסטי]]
[[ka:სოციალისტური რეალიზმი]]
[[ky:Социалисттик Реализм]]
[[lv:Sociālistiskais reālisms]]
[[lt:Socialistinis realizmas]]
[[hu:Szocialista realizmus]]
[[mk:Социјалистички реализам]]
[[ml:സോഷ്യലിസ്റ്റ് റിയലിസം]]
[[mn:Социалист реализм]]
[[nl:Socialistisch realisme]]
[[ja:社会主義リアリズム]]
[[no:Sosialistisk realisme]]
[[nn:Sosialistisk realisme]]
[[pl:Socrealizm]]
[[pt:Realismo socialista]]
[[ro:Realism socialist]]
[[ru:Социалистический реализм]]
[[sq:Realizmi socialist]]
[[sk:Socialistický realizmus]]
[[sl:Socialistični realizem]]
[[sr:Социјалистички реализам]]
[[fi:Sosialistinen realismi]]
[[sv:Socialistisk realism]]
[[tr:Sosyalist gerçekçilik]]
[[uk:Соціалістичний реалізм]]
[[zh:社会主义的现实主义]]</text>
      <sha1>jqonl7grdgjoo3t49nscopks5k2pg72</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
