<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Somaly Mam Foundation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>12834046</id>
    <revision>
      <id>484648343</id>
      <parentid>479035190</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-03-30T04:41:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cntras</username>
        <id>13805718</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14665">{{Multiple issues|POV = April 2010|COI = September 2011}}

The '''Somaly Mam Foundation''' is a registered 501(c)(3) [[nonprofit organization]] focused on combating the global [[human trafficking|sex slave trade]] through supporting the rescue, rehabilitation, and reintegration of the victims and through raising global awareness on the issue. The foundation funds more than 10 organizations in various parts of the world that are combating [[sexual slavery]] and [[human trafficking]] in the field. These include groups that are rescuing girls from [[brothels]], offering them shelter and safety, providing them with basic [[education]], and helping them reintegrate into new communities when their healing processes are complete.

==Somaly Mam==
{{Main|Somaly Mam}}
Somaly Mam was born in the [[Mondulkiri]] province of [[Cambodia]]. Orphaned at a young age, Somaly does not know who her real parents are, nor does she know her real name or exact birth date. Although she did not receive formal schooling, she was later trained to be a midwife after the genocidal regime. However, Somaly was sold many times by a man she called &quot;grandfather&quot; as a slave and coerced into prostitution. She was forced to work in a brothel with many other young girls that were treated horrifically through torture, manipulation, and scare tactics. One night she watched a close friend murdered by a pimp. Her past is a major contributing factor regarding her passion and effort to help young children and women involved with human trafficking. Mam later returned to Cambodia to bring back some of her experience and ideas to her homeland. She began establishing a [[non-governmental organization]] in French called “Agir Pour les Femmes en Situation Précaire (AFESIP),” translated in English “Acting for Women in Distressing Circumstances.” She became co-founder of [[AFESIP]] and President of AFESIP Cambodia in [[Phnom Penh]]. This organization’s main cause is the rescue, rehabilitation, and reintegration of girls forced into [[prostitution]].

==Programs==
The Somaly Mam Foundation is dedicated to ending [[sex slavery]] around the world with a results-oriented, three-step approach to critical program areas: victim services, survivor empowerment, and the eradication of slavery. The common thread woven through all of the Foundation's programs is the collective voice of survivors. The vision is modeled after Somaly’s inspiring life, ensuring that survivors take charge in reclaiming their lives, fight back against their former oppressors, and refuse to turn their backs on those who remain behind.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Programs: Overview|url=http://www.somaly.org/programs|publisher=Somaly Mam Foundation|accessdate=16 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Victim services===
The Somaly Mam Foundation supports the entire process of healing a survivor from rescue and recovery to rehabilitation and reintegration. The Foundation supports over ten shelters in four countries, providing resources and funding to victim services providers. These organizations provide survivors of human trafficking with food, shelter, and medical and psychological care.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Programs: Rescue and Recovery|url=http://www.somaly.org/programs/rescue_recovery|publisher=Somaly Mam Foundation|accessdate=16 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; These partners include [http://www.afesip.org/ AFESIP Cambodia], [http://www.afesiplaos.org/ AFESIP Laos], [http://www.allianceantitrafic.org/ Alliance Anti-Trafic] in [[Vietnam]], and [http://www.mysistersplaceny.org/ My Sister's Place].

===Survivor empowerment===
Once basic needs have been met, SMF supports education and vocational training programs to prepare survivors for reintegration to mainstream society. Survivors are given access to primary and secondary education, and beyond if they wish to do so. These skills are invaluable for survivors to flourish and sustain lives of dignity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Programs: Education|url=http://www.somaly.org/programs/education|publisher=Somaly Mam Foundation|accessdate=16 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Helping survivors of sex slavery become self-sufficient emotionally and financially translates to sustainable employment and alternative long-term solutions to reduce the risk of being re-trafficked or returning to the sex industry.

While survivors have experienced significant [[psychological trauma|trauma]], they are often able to thrive with the proper support. Young women have opened businesses, hold steady employment, and have even gotten married.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=From Slavery to Empowerment: The Wedding of a Survivor with Shay Mitchell and Somaly Mam|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MaB0DLLMjZk|publisher=Somaly Mam Foundation}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Cambodia, teams visit reintegrated survivors to check in and make sure that all is well with them in their new empowered lives.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=AFESIP CAMBODIA Reintegration|url=http://www.afesip.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=53&amp;Itemid=62|publisher=AFESIP Cambodia|accessdate=16 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Eradication of slavery===
The Somaly Mam Foundation is dedicated to eradicating slavery and the root causes that allow this evil to persist. [[Rule of law]] is crucial to the fight against human trafficking. The Foundation is dedicated to supporting and promoting rule of law in regions where the concept is threatened or non-existent. SMF has developed a powerful network of domestic and international partners, such as [[Lexis Nexis]] and [[The Body Shop]], to apply pressure to the Cambodian government and justice system to combat corruption and complicity on the part of public officials. SMF works with local groups to demand legislation that effectively addresses the issue and to allocate more resources toward enforcement of these laws.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Combatting Human Traffickin|url=http://www.lexisnexis.com/about-us/rule-of-law/human-trafficking.aspx|publisher=[[Lexis Nexis]]|accessdate=16 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Stop Sex Trafficking of Children and Young People|url=http://www.thebodyshop.com/_en/_ww/values-campaigns/stop-trafficking-select-country.aspx|publisher=The Body Shop}}&lt;/ref&gt; The goal is to make engaging in this crime more difficult and costly, as the likelihood of being apprehended and prosecuted will increase. While initial efforts are focused in [[Cambodia]], advocacy campaigns will gradually expand to other countries as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Programs: Advocacy|url=http://www.somaly.org/programs/advocacy|publisher=Somaly Mam Foundation|accessdate=16 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Awareness and advocacy are crucial across the globe as well. By increasing knowledge of trafficking, by understanding its root causes, and by creating an environment where the world says &quot;no more,&quot; the end of trafficking can come about in the foreseeable future.

==Voices for Change==
Survivors of trafficking are not weak and helpless. They are strong, resilient, and have demonstrated incredible courage in overcoming their tortured past and building a promising future for themselves. The Somaly Mam Foundation is there to lend a hand and provide them with a platform from which their voices can be heard around the world. Voices for Change is that platform.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Programs: Voices for Change|url=http://www.somaly.org/programs/voices-for-change|publisher=Somaly Mam Foundation|accessdate=16 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Co-directed by Sina Vann, a survivor of sex slavery in Cambodia, and modeled after Mam’s life example, VFC is designed to give survivors an opportunity to help themselves by helping others, to have their voices heard in the courts of law and public perception, and to have influence and impact on effectuating change. From those who have struggled through the pain of slavery, a new generation of leaders who stand for [[justice]] and [[free will]] will arise. Those who have undergone rescue, recovery, education, and reintegration are survivors who can choose to join the Voices for Change initiative and help in the survivor services program area by speaking to new victims brought to the centers, completing intake forms, teaching classes, and sharing life skills training.

Program participants join legal training seminars and courageously share their stories with magistrates, judges, and other members of the legal community brought together to better understand sex slavery. The survivors’ first-hand accounts of the horrors of life as a slave in the sex trade serve as dramatic wake-up calls to those in the legal profession who have pledged themselves to the cause of justice. Participating survivors host public service announcements in [[Cambodia]] and [[Southeast Asia]]. They also accompany Mam to certain fundraising and awareness events to share their experiences, educate the public, and show that this is happening to real people — not just nameless, faceless masses. Each one of these women has lived through horrific conditions and has emerged as a young leader.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Fight Slavery with [[Shay Mitchell]] and Voices for Change|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PaUXrZqW0Sw|publisher=Somaly Mam Foundation}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==PROJECT FUTURES global==
PROJECT FUTURES global is the volunteer and activist platform of the Somaly Mam Foundation. This program empowers volunteers to take action and join the fight against slavery by using their skills and interests, their communities, and their social networks to speak out, increase awareness, and raise funds for the Somaly Mam Foundation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=About PROJECT FUTURES global|url=http://projectfutures.somaly.org/about|accessdate=16 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

PROJECT FUTURES global supports and assists volunteers with activities such as online campaigns&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Action: Campaign Online|url=http://projectfutures.somaly.org/action/campaign_online|publisher=PROJECT FUTURES global}}&lt;/ref&gt; and media stunts, grassroots events,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Action: Awareness Events|url=http://projectfutures.somaly.org/action/host_awareness|publisher=PROJECT FUTURES global}}&lt;/ref&gt; film nights, runs and walks,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Action: Run/Ride/Walk for a Survivor|url=http://projectfutures.somaly.org/action/run_ride|publisher=PROJECT FUTURES global}}&lt;/ref&gt; campus outreach, workplace presentations, and more. PROJECT FUTURES global mobilizes volunteers and activists all over the world, empowering a generation to shape their world into one where women and children are safe from slavery.

==Origins of the Somaly Mam Foundation==
The following excerpt was take directly from the Somaly Mam Foundation website (http://www.somaly.org/whoweare/history):

In 2007, [[Jared Greenberg]] and [[Nicholas Lumpp]], two graduates of the [[United States Air Force Academy]], learned of a growing international crisis — [[human trafficking]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Foundation History|url=http://www.somaly.org/whoweare/history|publisher=Somaly Mam Foundation|accessdate=16 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[sex slave trade]] had developed into the third most profitable criminal industry, behind only narcotics and weapons.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Arlacchi|first=Pino|title=Opening Statement of Pino Arlacchi Under-Secretary-General Director-General to the International Seminar on Trafficking in Human Beings|url=http://www.unodc.org/unodc/en/about-unodc/speeches/speech_2000-11-28_1.html|publisher=United Nations Office on Drugs and Crime|accessdate=19 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Governments had yet to effectively handle the problem, and funding for organizations fighting the illegal trade was minimal. Disturbed by the public's lack of awareness of these ongoing atrocities, Greenberg and Lumpp decided it was time to take action and help put an end to sexual slavery, once and for all. But with an industry that generates $12 billion a year,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=A profitable enterprise|url=http://thecnnfreedomproject.blogs.cnn.com/2011/07/29/a-profitable-enterprise/|publisher=The CNN Freedom Project|accessdate=16 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; enslaves millions of young women and children, and is protected by corrupt government and law enforcement officials, they had their work cut out for them.

A few months later Greenberg and Lumpp viewed an online video clip of [[Anderson Cooper 360]] and saw a show spotlighting a woman by the name of [[Somaly Mam]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Fighting for Justice: Somaly Mam|url=http://dai.ly/r5TyFd|publisher=CNN Heroes}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sold into slavery at the age of 12, she later escaped and made it her mission to rescue, rehabilitate, and reintegrate survivors of this heinous crime. The result was [[AFESIP]], an organization that has transformed the lives of thousands of victims of the illegal trade since its inception in 1996. Mam is now regarded as one of the most prolific activists fighting sexual slavery. Greenberg and Lumpp traveled to [[Cambodia]] into the center of the sex slave industry. They met with Somaly Mam, toured shelters, and met some of the young women who had been rescued. The experience changed their lives. They realized that too many people around the world do not know that [[slavery]] still exists. Increasing awareness and funding organizations like AFESIP seemed paramount to combating the illegal trade. During a car ride from [[Phnom Penh]] to [[Siem Reap]], Mam explained her vision for a U.S. based organization that would take her life's passion to the next level. Thus, the Somaly Mam Foundation was born.

==Press Coverage==
* [http://www.cnn.com/SPECIALS/2007/cnn.heroes/flash_gallery/content.19.html/ CNN Heroes Somaly Mam]
* [http://thestory.org/archive/the_story_020811_full_show.mp3/view Saved From Captivity] Interview with Somaly Mam on American Public Media
* [http://www.successmagazine.com/stolen-innocence/PARAMS/article/1517/channel/22/ Stolen Innocence: One Woman's Fight Against Child Sex Slavery], ''SUCCESS'' magazine
* [http://www.pbs.org/wnet/religionandethics/episodes/february-12-2010/rescuing-child-sex-workers/5684/ Rescuing Child Sex Workers], [[PBS]]
* [http://www.marieclaire.com/world-reports/news/diary-escaped-sex-slave/ Diary of an Escaped Sex Slave], ''[[Marie Claire]]''
* [http://www.marieclaire.com/world-reports/inspirational-women/daryl-hannah-charity?click=rel Daryl Hannah: Saving Sex Slaves], [[Daryl Hannah]] in ''[[Marie Claire]]''

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.somaly.org/ Somaly Mam Foundation]

{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2011}}

[[Category:International human rights organizations]]
[[Category:International non-profit organizations]]
[[Category:Organizations opposed to human trafficking]]</text>
      <sha1>npiplfa7htdphm0juhgo7vvraziw31k</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
