<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Sovereign state</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>23604120</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521828230</id>
      <parentid>521827432</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-07T14:23:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Vrenator</username>
        <id>10509096</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/212.219.243.109|212.219.243.109]] ([[User talk:212.219.243.109|talk]]) identified as unconstructive ([[WP:HG|HG]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27043">{{Confuse|Federated state}} {{Seealso|List of sovereign states}} 
[[File:Europe countries map 2.png|thumb|right|Sovereign states in [[Europe]]]]	
A '''sovereign state''' is a political organization with a [[centralized government]] that has supreme independent authority over a geographic area.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The powers of external sovereignty on the part of the State do not depend on the affirmative grant of this in the Constitution. ... The State would not be completely sovereign if it did not have in common with other members of the family of nations the right and power in the field of international relations equal to the right and power of other states. These powers of the State include the power to declare war or to participate in a war, to conclude peace, to make treaties, and maintain diplomatic relations with other states.&quot; — {{Cite BAILII |country=ie |litigants=Crotty v An Taoiseach |court=IESC |year=1987  |num=4 |date=1987-04-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has a permanent [[population]], a [[government]], and the capacity to enter into [[International relations|relations]] with other sovereign states.&lt;ref&gt;See the following:
*{{Cite book|title=International law|first1=Malcolm Nathan|last1=Shaw|year=2003|publisher=Cambridge University Press|page=178|quote=Article 1 of the [[Montevideo Convention]] on Rights and Duties of States, 1933 lays down the most widely accepted formulation of the criteria of statehood in international law. It note that the state as an international person should possess the following qualifications: '(a) a permanent population; (b) a defined territory; (c) government; and (d) capacity to enter into relations with other states'}}
*{{Cite book|title=Perspectives on international law|editor1-first=Nandasiri|editor1-last=Jasentuliyana|publisher=Kluwer Law International|year=1995|page=20|quote=So far as States are concerned, the traditional definitions provided for in the Montevideo Convention remain generally accepted.}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is also normally understood to be a state which is neither dependent on nor subject to any other power or state.&lt;ref&gt;See the following:
*{{Cite book|title=Elements of international law: with a sketch of the history of the science|first1=Henry |last1=Wheaton|publisher=Carey, Lea &amp; Blanchard |year=1836|page=51|quote=A sovereign state is generally defined to be any nation or people, whatever may be the form of its internal constitution, which governs itself independently of foreign powers.}}
*{{Citation|title=sovereign|work=The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language|edition=4th|publisher=Houghton Mifflin Company|year=2004|accessdate=21 February 2010|url=http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/sovereign|quote=adj. 1. Self-governing; independent: a sovereign state.}}
*{{Citation|title=sovereign|work=The [[New Oxford American Dictionary]]|edition=2nd|yeat=2005|publisher=Oxford University Press|place=Oxford|isbn=0-19-517077-6|quote=adjective ... [ attrib. ] (of a nation or state) fully independent and determining its own affairs.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The existence or disappearance of a state is a question of fact.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lalonde2002&quot;&gt;{{cite book |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=x7qEqVpq9poC |title=Determining boundaries in a conflicted world: the role of uti possidetis |first=Suzanne |last=Lalonde |chapter=Notes to pages |publisher=McGill-Queen's Press - MQUP |year=2002 |isbn=978-0-7735-2424-8 |page=181}}&lt;/ref&gt; While according to the declaratory theory of state recognition a sovereign state can exist without being [[Diplomatic recognition|recognised]] by other sovereign states, unrecognised states will often find it hard to exercise full treaty-making powers and engage in [[Diplomacy|diplomatic]] relations with other sovereign states.

The word &quot;[[country]]&quot; is often [[colloquialism|colloquially]] used to refer to sovereign states, although it means, originally, only a [[geographic region]], and subsequently its meaning became extended to the sovereign [[polity]] which controls the geographic region.

== Westphalian sovereignty ==
{{Main|Westphalian sovereignty}}
Westphalian sovereignty is the concept of [[nation-state]] sovereignty based on territoriality and the absence of a role for external agents in domestic structures. It is an international system of states, [[multinational corporations]], and organizations that began with the [[Peace of Westphalia]] in 1648.

Sovereignty is a term that is frequently misused.&lt;ref&gt;See &quot;Sovereignty: organized hypocrisy, Stephen D. Krasner, Princeton University Press, 1999, ISBN 0-691-00711-X&lt;/ref&gt; Up until the 19th century, the radicalised concept of a &quot;standard of civilisation&quot; was routinely deployed to determine that certain peoples in the world were &quot;uncivilised&quot;, and lacking organised societies. That position was reflected and constituted in the notion that their &quot;sovereignty&quot; was either completely lacking, or at least of an inferior character when compared to that of &quot;civilised&quot; people.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Ralph Wilde, 'From trusteeship to self-determination and back again: the role of the Hague Regulations in the evolution of international trusteeship, and the framework of rights and duties of occupying powers,' Fall, 2009, 31 Loy. L.A. Int'l &amp; Comp. L. Rev. 85, page 94, [http://ilr.lls.edu/documents/WILDEFINAL3-29.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Lassa Oppenheim]] said &quot;There exists perhaps no conception the meaning of which is more controversial than that of sovereignty. It is an indisputable fact that this conception, from the moment when it was introduced into political science until the present day, has never had a meaning which was universally agreed upon.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;1 Lassa Oppenheim, International Law 66 (Sir Arnold D. McNair ed., 4th ed. 1928)&lt;/ref&gt; In the opinion of [[H. V. Evatt]] of the [[High Court of Australia]] &quot;sovereignty is neither a question of fact, nor a question of law, but a question that does not arise at all.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;See Sovereignty in cases of Mandated Territories, in &quot;International law and the protection of Namibia's territorial integrity&quot;, By S. Akweenda, Martinus Nijhoff Publishers, 1997, ISBN 90-411-0412-7, page 40&lt;/ref&gt;

Sovereignty has taken on a different meaning with the development of the principle of [[self-determination]] and the prohibition against the threat or use of force as ''[[jus cogens]]'' norms of modern [[international law]]. The [[United Nations Charter]], the [[Declaration on Rights and Duties of States]], and the charters of regional international organisations express the view that all states are juridically equal and enjoy the same rights and duties based upon the mere fact of their existence as persons under international law.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Chapter IV Fundamental Rights and Duties of States|url=http://www.oas.org/dil/treaties_A-41_Charter_of_the_Organization_of_American_States.htm#ch4|work=Charter of the Organization of American States|publisher=Secretariat of The Organization of American States|accessdate=21 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Draft Declaration on Rights and Duties of States|url=http://untreaty.un.org/ilc/texts/instruments/english/draft%20articles/2_1_1949.pdf|publisher=UN Treaty Organization|accessdate=21 November 2010|year=1949}}&lt;/ref&gt; The right of nations to determine their own political status and exercise permanent sovereignty within the limits of their territorial jurisdictions is widely recognised.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=General Assembly resolution 1803 (XVII) of 14 December 1962, &quot;Permanent sovereignty over natural resources&quot; |url=http://www2.ohchr.org/english/law/resources.htm|publisher=United Nations|accessdate=21 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Schwebel, Stephen M., The Story of the U.N.'s Declaration on Permanent Sovereignty over Natural Resources, 49 A.B.A. J. 463 (1963)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights|url=http://www2.ohchr.org/english/law/ccpr.htm|publisher=United Nations|accessdate=21 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In political science, sovereignty is usually defined as the most essential attribute of the state in the form of its complete self-sufficiency in the frames of a certain territory, that is its supremacy in the domestic policy and independence in the foreign one.&lt;ref&gt;Grinin L. E. Globalization and Sovereignty: Why do States Abandon their Sovereign Prerogatives? Age of Globalization. Number 1 / 2008 [http://www.socionauki.ru/journal/articles/127716/]&lt;/ref&gt;

In casual usage, the terms &quot;[[country]]&quot;, &quot;nation&quot;, and &quot;state&quot; are often used as if they were [[synonym]]ous; but in a more strict usage they can be distinguished:{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}

* '''''[[Nation]]''''' denotes a people who are believed to or deemed to share common customs,  religion, language, origins, ancestry or history. However, the adjectives ''national'' and ''international'' are frequently used to refer to matters pertaining to what are strictly ''sovereign states'', as in ''national capital'', ''international law''.

* '''''[[State (polity)|State]]''''' refers to the set of governing and supportive institutions that have [[sovereignty]] over a definite territory and [[population]]. Sovereign states are [[Legal personality|legal persons]].

==Recognition==

State recognition signifies the decision of a sovereign state to treat another entity as also being a sovereign state.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.answers.com/topic/recognition &quot;Recognition&quot;], ''Encyclopedia of American Foreign Policy''.&lt;/ref&gt; Recognition can be either express or implied and is usually retroactive in its effects. It doesn't necessarily signify a desire to establish or maintain diplomatic relations.

There is no definition that is binding on all the members of the community of nations on the criteria for statehood. In actual practice, the criteria are mainly political, not legal.&lt;ref&gt;See B. Broms, &quot;IV Recognition of States&quot;, pp 47-48 in ''International law: achievements and prospects'', UNESCO Series, Mohammed Bedjaoui(ed), Martinus Nijhoff Publishers, 1991, ISBN 92-3-102716-6 [http://books.google.com/books?id=jrTsNTzcY7EC&amp;lpg=PA47&amp;client&amp;pg=PA47#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt;  L.C. Green cited the recognition of the unborn [[Poland|Polish]] and [[Czechoslovakia|Czech]] states in World War I and explained that &quot;since recognition of statehood is a matter of discretion, it is open to any existing State to accept as a state any entity it wishes, regardless of the existence of territory or of an established government.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;See Israel Yearbook on Human Rights, 1989, [[Yoram Dinstein]], Mala Tabory eds., Martinus Nijhoff Publishers, 1990, ISBN 0-7923-0450-0, page 135-136 [http://books.google.com/books?id=5okNqth8I9wC&amp;lpg=PA136&amp;ots=ARGGNDm7G-&amp;dq=t&amp;pg=PA136#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[international law]], however, there are several theories of when a state should be recognized as sovereign.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas D. Grant, ''The recognition of states: law and practice in debate and evolution'' (Westport, Connecticut: Praeger, 1999), chapter 1.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Constitutive theory===
The constitutive theory of statehood defines a state as a person of international law if, and only if, it is recognized as sovereign by other states. This theory of recognition was developed in the 19th century. Under it, a state was sovereign if another sovereign state recognized it as such. Because of this, new states could not immediately become part of the international community or be bound by international law, and recognized nations did not have to respect international law in their dealings with them.&lt;ref name=&quot;ctos&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Sourcebook on Public International Law |last=Hillier |first=Tim |year=1998 |publisher=Routledge |isbn=1-85941-050-2 |pages=201–2 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Kr0sOuIx8q8C }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1815 at the [[Congress of Vienna]] the [[Final Act of the Congress of Vienna|Final Act]] recognised only 39 sovereign states in the European diplomatic system, and as a result it was firmly established that in future new states would have to be recognized by other states, and that meant in practice recognition by one or more of the [[great powers]].&lt;ref&gt;Kalevi Jaakko Holsti ''Taming the Sovereigns'' [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=Jh6gjr-2ho8C&amp;pg=PA128&amp;dq=Final+Act+of+the+Congress+of+Vienna&amp;lr=&amp;sig=ACfU3U1FTkJPODAK8KkyGV5Nz6O-ke9_Ig p. 128].&lt;/ref&gt;

One of the major criticisms of this law is the confusion caused when some states recognize a new entity, but other states do not. Hersch Lauterpacht, one of the theory's main proponents, suggested that it is a state's duty to grant recognition as a possible solution. However, a state may use any criteria when judging if they should give recognition and they have no obligation to use such criteria. Many states may only recognize another state if it is to their advantage.&lt;ref name=&quot;ctos&quot; /&gt;

In 1912, [[L. F. L. Oppenheim]] had the following to say on constitutive theory:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
...International Law does not say that a State is not in existence as long as it is not recognised, but it takes no notice of it before its recognition. Through recognition only and exclusively a State becomes an International Person and a subject of International Law.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = Lassa Oppenheim, Ronald Roxburgh | title = International Law: A Treatise | publisher = The Lawbook Exchange, Ltd. | year = 2005 | isbn = 1-58477-609-9, 9781584776093 | pages = 135 | url = http://books.google.com/books?id=vxJ1Jwmyw0EC&amp;pg=PA135}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Declarative theory===
By contrast, the &quot;declarative&quot; theory defines a state as a [[subject of international law|person in international law]] if it meets the following criteria:  1) a defined territory; 2) a permanent population; 3) a government and 4) a capacity to enter into relations with other states. According to declarative theory, an entity's statehood is independent of its recognition by other states. The declarative model was most famously expressed in the 1933 [[Montevideo Convention]].

Article 3 of the Montevideo Convention declares that statehood is independent of recognition by other states. In contrast, recognition is considered a requirement for statehood by the constitutive theory of statehood.

A similar opinion about &quot;the conditions on which an entity constitutes a state&quot; is expressed by the [[European Economic Community]] ''Opinions of the [[Badinter Arbitration Committee]]'', which found that a state was defined by having a territory, a population, and a political authority.

===State practice===
State practice relating the recognition states typically falls somewhere between the declaratory and constitutive approaches.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=International law |first1=Malcolm Nathan |last1=Shaw |year=2003 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |page=369}}&lt;/ref&gt; International law does not require a state to recognise other states.&lt;ref&gt;Opinion No. 10. of the [[Arbitration Commission of the Conference on Yugoslavia]].&lt;/ref&gt;

Recognition is often withheld when a new state is seen as illegitimate or has come about in breach of international law. Almost universal non-recognition by the international community of [[Rhodesia]] and [[Northern Cyprus]] are good examples of this. In the former case, recognition was widely withheld when the white minority seized power and attempted to form a state along the lines of [[South Africa under apartheid|Apartheid South Africa]], a move that the [[United Nations Security Council]] described as the creation of an &quot;illegal racist minority régime&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[s:United Nations Security Council Resolution 216]]&lt;/ref&gt; In the latter case, recognition was widely withheld from a state created in Northern Cyprus on land illegally invaded by Turkey in 1974.&lt;ref&gt;[[s:United Nations Security Council Resolution 541]]&lt;/ref&gt;

===De facto and de jure states===
Most sovereign states are states [[de jure]] and [[de facto]] (i.e. they exist both in law and in reality). However, sometimes states exist only as de jure states in that an organisation is recognised as having sovereignty over and being the legitimate government of a territory over which they have no actual control. Many continental European states maintained [[government in exile|governments-in-exile]] during the [[Second World War]] which continued to enjoy diplomatic relations with the [[Allies of World War II|Allies]], notwithstanding that their countries were under Nazi occupation. A present day example is the [[State of Palestine]], which is [[Foreign relations of the Palestine Liberation Organization#Chronological table of recognition and relations|recognized by multiple states]], but doesn't have control over any of its claimed territory in [[Palestine (region)|Palestine]]&lt;ref name=&quot;saeb&quot;/&gt;{{#tag:ref|Israel allows the [[Palestinian National Authority|PNA]] to execute some functions in the [[Palestinian territories]], depending on [[Administrative divisions of the Oslo Accords|special area classification]]. Israel maintains [[Israel's unilateral disengagement plan|minimal interference]] (retaining control of borders: [[National airspace|air]],&lt;ref name=&quot;GazaSeaAir&quot;&gt;[[B'Tselem]] - The Israeli Information Center for Human Rights in the Occupied Territories: [http://www.btselem.org/english/Gaza_Strip/Control_on_Air_space_and_territorial_waters.asp Israel's control of the airspace and the territorial waters of the Gaza Strip], Retrieved 2012-03-24.&lt;/ref&gt; sea [[United Nations Convention on the Law of the Sea#UNCLOS III|beyond internal waters]],&lt;ref name=&quot;GazaSeaAir&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://dissidentvoice.org/wp-content/uploads/2009/12/Gaza-map-08s-fishing-limits-20090119.jpg Map of Gaza fishing limits, &quot;security zones&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; [[European Union Border Assistance Mission Rafah|land]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mfa.gov.il/MFA/Peace+Process/Guide+to+the+Peace+Process/Israels+Disengagement+Plan-+Renewing+the+Peace+Process+Apr+2005.htm Israel's Disengagement Plan: Renewing the Peace Process]: &quot;Israel will guard the perimeter of the Gaza Strip, continue to control Gaza air space, and continue to patrol the sea off the Gaza coast. ... Israel will continue to maintain its essential military presence to prevent arms smuggling along the border between the Gaza Strip and Egypt ([[Philadelphi Route]]), until the security situation and cooperation with Egypt permit an alternative security arrangement.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;) in the [[Gaza strip]] and maximum in &quot;[[Administrative divisions of the Oslo Accords|Area C]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web  | last = Gold  | first = Dore  | coauthors = Institute for Contemporary Affairs  | title = Legal Acrobatics: The Palestinian Claim that Gaza is Still &quot;Occupied&quot; Even After Israel Withdraws  | work = Jerusalem Issue Brief, Vol. 5, No. 3  | publisher = Jerusalem Center for Public Affairs
  | date = 26 August 2005  | url = http://www.jcpa.org/brief/brief005-3.htm  | accessdate = 2010-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
  | last = Bell  | first = Abraham  | title = International Law and Gaza: The Assault on Israel's Right to Self-Defense
  | work = Jerusalem Issue Brief, Vol. 7, No. 29  | publisher = Jerusalem Center for Public Affairs  | date = 28 January 2008
  | url = http://www.jcpa.org/brief/brief005-3.htm  | accessdate = 2010-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite press release  | title = Address by Foreign Minister Livni to the 8th Herzliya Conference  | publisher = Ministry of Foreign Affairs of Israel  | date = 22 January 2008  | url = http://www.mfa.gov.il/MFA/Government/Speeches+by+Israeli+leaders/2008/Address+by+FM+Livni+to+the+8th+Herzliya+Conference+22-Jan-2008.htm?DisplayMode=print  | accessdate = 2010-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web  | last = Salih
  | first = Zak M.  | title = Panelists Disagree Over Gaza’s Occupation Status  | publisher = University of Virginia School of Law  | date = 17 November 2005  | url = http://www.law.virginia.edu/html/news/2005_fall/gaza.htm  | accessdate = 2010-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web  | title = Israel: 'Disengagement' Will Not End Gaza Occupation  | publisher = Human Rights Watch
  | date = 29 October 2004  | url = http://www.hrw.org/english/docs/2004/10/29/isrlpa9577.htm  | accessdate = 2010-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; See also [[Israeli-occupied territories]].&lt;br&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;saeb&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|author=Staff writers|title=Palestinians 'may declare state'|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/7254434.stm|newspaper=BBC News|publisher=British Broadcasting Corporation|date=20 February 2008|accessdate=2011-01-22}}:&quot;Saeb Erekat, disagreed arguing that the Palestine Liberation Organisation had already declared independence in 1988. &quot;Now we need real independence, not a declaration. We need real independence by ending the occupation. We are not Kosovo. We are under Israeli occupation and for independence we need to acquire independence&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
  | last = Gold  | first = Dore  | coauthors = Institute for Contemporary Affairs  | title = Legal Acrobatics: The Palestinian Claim that Gaza is Still &quot;Occupied&quot; Even After Israel Withdraws  | work = Jerusalem Issue Brief, Vol. 5, No. 3  | publisher = Jerusalem Center for Public Affairs  | date = 26 August 2005  | url = http://www.jcpa.org/brief/brief005-3.htm  | accessdate = 2010-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web  | last = Bell  | first = Abraham  | title = International Law and Gaza: The Assault on Israel's Right to Self-Defense  | work = Jerusalem Issue Brief, Vol. 7, No. 29  | publisher = Jerusalem Center for Public Affairs  | date = 28 January 2008  | url = http://www.jcpa.org/brief/brief005-3.htm  | accessdate = 2010-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite press release  | title = Address by Foreign Minister Livni to the 8th Herzliya Conference  | publisher = Ministry of Foreign Affairs of Israel  | date = 22 January 2008  | url = http://www.mfa.gov.il/MFA/Government/Speeches+by+Israeli+leaders/2008/Address+by+FM+Livni+to+the+8th+Herzliya+Conference+22-Jan-2008.htm?DisplayMode=print
  | accessdate = 2010-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web  | last = Salih  | first = Zak M.  | title = Panelists Disagree Over Gaza’s Occupation Status  | publisher = University of Virginia School of Law  | date = 17 November 2005  | url = http://www.law.virginia.edu/html/news/2005_fall/gaza.htm  | accessdate = 2010-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web  | title = Israel: 'Disengagement' Will Not End Gaza Occupation  | publisher = Human Rights Watch  | date = 29 October 2004  | url = http://www.hrw.org/english/docs/2004/10/29/isrlpa9577.htm  | accessdate = 2010-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; |name=&quot;israel&quot;}} and possess only [[extraterritoriality|extraterritorial]] areas (i.e. [[embassies]] and [[consulates]]). Other states may have sovereignty over a territory but lack international recognition; these are considered by the [[international community]] to be only de facto states (they are considered de jure states only according to their own Law and by states that recognize them). [[Somaliland]] is commonly considered to be such a state.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://yalejournal.org/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/083206arieff.pdf |title=De facto Statehood? The Strange Case of Somaliland |accessdate=2010-01-04 |date=November 2008 |author=Arieff, Alexis |publisher=Yale Journal of International Affairs}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.foreignpolicy.com/story/cms.php?story_id=3903 |title=The List: Six Reasons You May Need A New Atlas Soon |accessdate=2010-01-04 |date=July 2007 |publisher=Foreign Policy Magazine}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.unpo.org/content/view/8418/244/ |title=Overview of De-facto States |accessdate=2010-01-04 |date=July 2008 |publisher=[[Unrepresented Nations and Peoples Organization]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.lesnouvelles.org/P10_magazine/15_grandentretien/15055_mahamudsalahnur_eng.html |title=France recognizes de facto Somaliland |accessdate=2010-01-04 |date=April 2008 |author=Wiren, Robert |publisher=Les Nouvelles d'Addis Magazine}}&lt;/ref&gt; For a list of entities that wish to be universally recognized as sovereign states, but do not have complete worldwide [[diplomatic recognition]], see the [[list of states with limited recognition]].

==See also==
{|
|
* [[List of sovereign states and dependent territories by continent]]
* [[Country]]
* [[Exclusive mandate]]
* [[Failed state]]
* [[Federal state]]
* [[List of sovereign states]] ([[List of sovereign states by date of formation|by formation date]])
* [[Montevideo Convention]]
|
* [[Nation]]
* [[Nation-building]]
* [[Nation state]]
* [[Rule according to higher law]]
* [[Stateless society]]
* [[Unitary state]]

|}

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}
&lt;references/&gt;

==Further reading==
*Chen, Ti-chiang. ''The International Law of Recognition, with Special Reference to Practice in Great Britain and the United States''. London, 1951.
*Crawford, James. ''The Creation of States in International Law''. Oxford University Press, 2005. ISBN 0-19-825402-4,  pp.&amp;nbsp;15–24.
*[[Hersch Lauterpacht|Lauterpacht, Sir Hersch]]. ''Recognition in International Law''. Cambridge, U.K., 1947.
*Raič, D. ''Statehood and the Law of Self-determination''. Martinus Nijhoff Publishers, 2002. ISBN 978-90-411-1890-5.  p 29 (with reference to Oppenheim in International Law Vol. 1 1905 p110)

== External links ==
*[http://ejil.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/reprint/3/1/178 Opinions of the Badinter Arbitration Committee] at the ''European Journal of International Law''
*[http://www.burneylawfirm.com/international_law_primer.htm A Brief Primer on International Law] With cases and commentary.  Nathaniel Burney, 2007.
*[http://journals.cambridge.org/action/displayFulltext?type=1&amp;fid=6305536&amp;jid=RIS&amp;volumeId=22&amp;issueId=04&amp;aid=6305528&amp;bodyId=&amp;membershipNumber=&amp;societyETOCSession= What constitutes the sovereign state?] by Michael Ross Fowler and Julie Marie Bunck 
*[http://www.ipoliticalrisk.com Links to the best political risk websites, ipoliticalrisk.com] information on tracking, evaluating and managing sovereign risk for trade and permanent investment

{{DEFAULTSORT:Sovereign State}}
[[Category:International law]]
[[Category:Political geography]]
[[Category:Sovereignty|State]]

[[ar:دولة ذات سيادة]]
[[an:Estato sobirán]]
[[be:Суверэнная дзяржава]]
[[be-x-old:Сувэрэнная дзяржава]]
[[bg:Суверенна държава]]
[[br:Stad emveliek]]
[[ca:Estat]]
[[de:Souveräner Staat]]
[[et:Suveräänne riik]]
[[es:Estado]]
[[eo:Suverena ŝtato]]
[[fa:کشور مستقل]]
[[fr:État souverain]]
[[gl:Estado soberano]]
[[ko:주권국]]
[[hr:Suverena država]]
[[is:Fullvalda ríki]]
[[it:Stato sovrano]]
[[he:מדינה ריבונית]]
[[la:Civitas sui iuris]]
[[mn:Бүрэн эрхт улс]]
[[nl:Soevereine staat]]
[[ja:主権国家体制]]
[[nn:Suverenitet#Suveren stat]]
[[pt:Teoria constitutiva do Estado]]
[[ro:Stat suveran]]
[[ru:Суверенное государство]]
[[simple:Sovereign state]]
[[ckb:دەوڵەتی سەروەر]]
[[sr:Суверена држава]]
[[sh:Suverena država]]
[[sv:Suverän stat]]
[[ta:இறைமையுள்ள நாடு]]
[[tr:Egemen devlet]]
[[uk:Суверенна держава]]
[[vi:Quốc gia có chủ quyền]]
[[war:Estado soberanya]]
[[zh:主权国家]]</text>
      <sha1>qylmasei5y4fy5avigzk231gz8dk0zo</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
