<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Stalinism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>28621</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519918242</id>
      <parentid>518992902</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-26T10:19:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>77.200.242.35</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bourgeoisie</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="39081">{{For|architecture|Stalinist architecture}}
{{POV|date=April 2011}}

{{Stalinism sidebar}}
{{Communism sidebar}}
{{Marxism–Leninism sidebar}}
'''Stalinism''' is the ideology that [[Joseph Stalin]] conceived and implemented in the [[Soviet Union]], and is generally considered a branch of [[Marxism–Leninism|Marxist–Leninist]] ideology but considered by some historians to be a significant deviation from this philosophy.&lt;ref name=&quot;B. Bottomore. 1991. Pp. 54&quot;&gt;T. B. Bottomore. ''A Dictionary of Marxist thought''. Malden, Massaschussetts, USA; Oxford, England, UK; Melbourne, Victoria, Australia; Berlin, Germany: Wiley-Blackwell, 1991. Pp. 54.&lt;/ref&gt; Stalinist policies in the [[Soviet Union]] included: rapid [[industrialization]], [[socialism in one country]], a centralized state, [[collectivization]] of agriculture, and subordination of interests of other communist parties to those of the [[Communist Party of the Soviet Union|Soviet party]] - deemed to be the most forefront [[vanguard party]] of communist revolution at the time.&lt;ref name=&quot;B. Bottomore. 1991. Pp. 54&quot;/&gt; 

Stalinist rapid industrialization in the Soviet Union was officially designed to accelerate the [[Marxism|Marxian]] development towards [[communism]], stressing that such rapid industrialization was needed because the country was previously economically backward in comparison with other countries; and that it was needed in order to challenge internal and external enemies of communism.&lt;ref&gt;Stephen Kotkin. ''Magnetic Mountain: Stalinism As a Civilization''. First Paperback Edition. Berkeley and Los Angeles, California, USA: University of California Press, 1997. ISBN 9780520208230. Pp. 70-71.&lt;/ref&gt; Rapid industrialization was accompanied with mass [[Collective farming|collectivization]] of agriculture and rapid [[urbanization]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephen Kotkin 1997. Pp. 70-79&quot;&gt;Stephen Kotkin. ''Magnetic Mountain: Stalinism As a Civilization''. First Paperback Edition. Berkeley and Los Angeles, California, USA: University of California Press, 1997. ISBN 9780520208230. Pp. 70-79.&lt;/ref&gt; Rapid urbanization converted many small villages into industrial cities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephen Kotkin 1997. Pp. 70-79&quot;/&gt; To accelerate the development of industrialization, Stalin pragmatically created [[joint venture]] contracts with major [[United States|American]] [[private enterprise]]s, such as [[Ford Motor Company]], that under state supervision assisted in developing the basis of industry of the Soviet economy from the late 1920s to 1930s.&lt;ref name=&quot;LTC Roy E Peterson 2011. Pp. 94&quot;&gt;LTC Roy E Peterson. Russian Romance: Danger and Daring. AuthorHouse, 2011. Pp. 94.&lt;/ref&gt; After the American private enterprises completed their tasks, Soviet state enterprises took over.&lt;ref name=&quot;LTC Roy E Peterson 2011. Pp. 94&quot;/&gt;
[[File:Marcha PC(AP).jpg|300px|thumbnail|The [[Chilean Communist Party (Proletarian Action)]] during [[International Workers' Day|May Day]] manifestations in [[Santiago, Chile]], carring a banner with the portraits of Marx, Engels, Lenin and Stalin.]]
Stalinism took an aggressive stance on [[class conflict]], utilizing [[state violence]] to forcibly purge society of the [[bourgeoisie]] such as the affluent middle-class peasant [[Kulaks]] and other &quot;class enemies&quot;, as well as claiming that class conflict existed within communist parties.&lt;ref&gt;Stephen Kotkin. ''Magnetic Mountain: Stalinism As a Civilization''. First Paperback Edition. Berkeley and Los Angeles, California, USA: University of California Press, 1997. ISBN 9780520208230. Pp. 71, 307, 81.&lt;/ref&gt; Stalin committed [[classicide]] against the Kulaks for being such class enemies.&lt;ref&gt;Jacques Semelin, Stanley (INT) Hoffman. Purify and Destroy: The Political Uses of Massacre and Genocide. New York, New York, USA: Columbia University Press, 2007. Pp. 37.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Stalinism is commonly used in a negative or pejorative manner due to the known extremely repressive political actions undertaken by Stalin. The reasons for Stalin's repressive actions have been debated.&lt;ref name=&quot;Edvard Radzinsky 1997. Pp. 319&quot;&gt;Edvard Radzinsky. Stalin: The First In-Depth Biography Based on Explosive New Documents from Russia's Secret Archives. Random House Digital, Inc., 1997. ISBN 9780385479547. Pp. 319.&lt;/ref&gt; One perspective claims that Stalin's repressive actions were calculated and that he was mentally sane in his execution of repressive measures.&lt;ref name=&quot;Edvard Radzinsky 1997. Pp. 319&quot;/&gt; Another perspective claims that Stalin's repressive political actions were the result of him having [[mental illness]].&lt;ref&gt;Edvard Radzinsky. Stalin: The First In-Depth Biography Based on Explosive New Documents from Russia's Secret Archives. Random House Digital, Inc., 1997. ISBN 9780385479547. Taylor &amp; Francis, 2003. Pp. 319.&lt;/ref&gt; This claim states that Stalin likely had the mental disorder of [[psychopathy]] and that its traits such as [[paranoia]] and manipulative behaviour influenced his political decisions.&lt;ref&gt;Roman Brackman. The Secret File of Joseph Stalin: A Hidden Life. Pp. 349.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Christopher J. Patrick. Handbook of Psychopathy. Guilford Press, 2007. ISBN 9781593855918. Pp. 483.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Chris S. Adams, Jr. ''Ideologies in Conflict: A Cold War Docu-Story''. iUniverse, 2001. ISBN 9780595189632. Pp. 245.&lt;/ref&gt; A third perspective claims that Stalinism's repressive actions were an extension of the prevailing authoritarian and repressive political culture that originated in [[Russian Empire|Tsarist Russia]].&lt;ref&gt;Stephen Kotkin. ''Magnetic Mountain: Stalinism As a Civilization''. First Paperback Edition. Berkeley and Los Angeles, California, USA: University of California Press, 1997. ISBN 9780520208230. Pp. 9-11&lt;/ref&gt;

==Etymology==

The term came into prominence during the mid-1930s, when [[Lazar Kaganovich]], a Soviet politician and associate of Stalin, reportedly declared, &quot;Let's replace Long Live Leninism with Long Live Stalinism!&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Montefiore 2004 164&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last= Montefiore |first= Simon Sebag|title= Stalin: The Court of the Red Tsar |publisher= Knopf |year= 2004 |month= |isbn= 1-4000-4230-5 |page=164 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Stalin initially met this usage with hesitancy, dismissing it as excessively praiseful and contributing to a [[cult of personality]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Montefiore 2004 164&quot;/&gt;

==Stalinist policies==
{{Soviet Union sidebar}}
[[File:Lenin and stalin crop.jpg|thumb|left|[[Vladimir Lenin]] with Stalin in the early 1920s.]]
[[File:Stalin birthday2.jpg|thumb|left|Members of the [[Communist Party of China]] celebrating Stalin's birthday, in 1949.]]
[[File:Stalin in London.jpg|thumb|left|Communists in a parade in [[London]] carrying a poster of Stalin.]]
Stalinism usually denotes a style of a government, and an ideology. While he claimed to be a perfect adherent to the ideas of [[Vladimir Lenin]] and [[Karl Marx]], and hence claimed that it was merely a style of government, many of his policies and beliefs were different or in direct opposition to those of Lenin and Marx&lt;ref&gt;http://www.politicalaffairs.net/how-stalin-distorted-marxism-2/&lt;/ref&gt;. Stalin's ideas of [[Socialism in one country]], his adoption of many aspects of [[capitalism]]&lt;ref&gt;http://socialistworker.org/2003-2/462/462_08_Stalin.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;, and his turn to complete, permanent dictatorship were all in stark contradiction to the ideologies put forth by Lenin or Marx.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.politicalaffairs.net/how-stalin-distorted-marxism-2/&lt;/ref&gt;

Stalinism is a certain political regime claiming to apply the ideas of Marx or Lenin in ways fitting the changing needs of society, as with the transition from &quot;socialism at a snail's pace&quot; in the mid-1920s to the rapid industrialization of the [[Five-Year Plans for the National Economy of the Soviet Union|Five-Year Plan]]s. Sometimes, although rarely, the compound terms &quot;Marxism–Leninism–Stalinism&quot; (used by the [[Brazil]]ian [[Revolutionary Movement 8th October|MR-8]]), or ''teachings of Marx/[[Friedrich Engels|Engels]]/Lenin/Stalin'', are used to show the alleged heritage and succession. 

[[File:Poster14.jpg||thumb|left|250px|Poster &quot;Study the great path of the Lenin-Stalin Party&quot;]]Simultaneously, however, many people who profess [[Marxism]] or [[Leninism]] view Stalinism as a perversion of their ideas; [[Trotskyists]], in particular, are virulently anti-Stalinist, considering Stalinism a counter-revolutionary style of governance that used vaguely Marxist-sounding rhetoric to achieve power. 

From 1917 to 1924, Lenin, Trotsky, and Stalin often appeared united, but their ideological differences never disappeared. In his dispute with [[Leon Trotsky]], Stalin de-emphasized the role of workers in advanced [[capitalism|capitalist]] countries (for example, he considered the U.S. working class as bourgeoisified [[labour aristocracy]]). Also, Stalin polemicized against Trotsky on the role of peasants, as in [[China]], whereas Trotsky's position was in favor of urban insurrection over peasant-based [[guerrilla warfare]].

The main contributions of Stalin to communist theory were:
* The groundwork for the Soviet policy concerning nationalities, laid in Stalin's 1913 work ''[[Marxism and the National Question]]'',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/stalin/works/1913/03.htm &quot;Marxism and the National Question&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; praised by Lenin.
* '[[Socialism in One Country]]'
* The theory of [[Aggravation of class struggle under socialism|aggravation of the class struggle along with the development of socialism]], a theoretical base supporting the repression of political opponents as necessary.

Stalin argued that the state must become stronger before it can &quot;wither away&quot; in favor of creating a classless Communist society.  In Stalin's view, the state must be powerful enough to defeat counterrevolutionary elements.  For this reason, Communist regimes influenced by Stalin have been widely described as [[totalitarianism|totalitarian]].

Soviet puppet [[Sheng Shicai]] extended Stalinist rule in [[Xinjiang]] province in the 1930s. Stalin opposed the Chinese Communist Party, and Sheng conducted a purge similar to Stalin's [[Great Purge]] in 1937.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=IAs9AAAAIAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=warlords+and+muslims&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=KzhMe1dpqU&amp;sig=YUq2zwbyUFNCsO5Jnt2RTAKL0rc&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=SdobTNyIEYO8lQfuvYm1Cg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CBgQ6AEwAQ#v=snippet&amp;q=fascist%20trotskyite%20plotters&amp;f=false|title=Warlords and Muslims in Chinese Central Asia: a political history of Republican Sinkiang 1911-1949|author=Andrew D. W. Forbes|year=1986|publisher=CUP Archive|location=Cambridge, England|isbn=0-521-25514-7|pages=151|pages=376|accessdate=2010-12-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Stalinist economic policy==
At the start of the 1930s Stalin launched a wave of radical economic policies, which completely overhauled the industrial and agricultural face of the Soviet Union. This came to be known as the '[[Great Turn]]' as Russia turned away from the near-capitalist [[New Economic Policy]]. The NEP had been implemented by Lenin in order to ensure the survival of the Communist state following seven years of war (1914–1921, [[World War I]] from 1914 to 1917, and the subsequent Civil War) and had rebuilt Soviet production to its 1913 levels. However, Russia still lagged far behind the West, and the NEP was felt by Stalin and the majority of the Communist party, not only to be compromising Communist ideals, but also not delivering sufficient economic performance, as well as not creating the envisaged Socialist society. It was therefore felt necessary to increase the pace of [[industrialisation]] in order to catch up with the West.

[[Fredric Jameson]] has said that &quot;Stalinism was [...] a success and fulfilled its historic mission, socially as well as economically&quot; given that it &quot;modernised the Soviet Union, transforming a peasant society into an industrial state with a literate population and a remarkable scientific superstructure.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Fredric Jameson]], collected in ''Marxism Beyond Marxism'' (1996) ISBN 0-415-91442-6, page 43&lt;/ref&gt; [[Robert Conquest]] disputed such a conclusion and noted that &quot;Russia had already been fourth to fifth among industrial economies before World War I&quot; and that Russian industrial advances could have been achieved without [[collectivisation]], famine or terror. The industrial successes were, according to Conquest, far less than claimed, and the Soviet-style industrialisation was &quot;an anti-innovative dead-end&quot;, according to him.&lt;ref name=&quot;reflections&quot;&gt;[[Robert Conquest]] ''Reflections on a Ravaged Century'' (2000) ISBN 0-393-04818-7, page 101&lt;/ref&gt;

According to several Western historians{{citation needed|date=December 2010}}, Stalinist agricultural policies were a key factor in causing the [[Soviet famine of 1932–1933]], which the Ukrainian government now calls ''the [[Holodomor]]'', recognizing it as an act of [[genocide]]. However, there is still [[Holodomor genocide question|considerable debate]] in other countries as to whether or not the famine can be recognized as genocide.

==Legacy==

After Stalin's death in 1953, his successor [[Nikita Khrushchev]] repudiated his policies, condemned Stalin's [[cult of personality]] in his [[Khrushchev Secret Speech|Secret Speech]] to the [[Twentieth Party Congress]] in 1956, and instituted [[destalinisation]] and relative liberalisation (within the same political framework). Consequently, most of the world's Communist parties, who previously adhered to Stalinism, abandoned it and, to a greater or lesser degree, adopted the positions of Khrushchev.

A few of the notable exceptions were [[North Korea]] under [[Kim Il-sung]], the [[People's Republic of China]], under [[Mao Zedong]], the [[Albanian Party of Labour]] under [[Enver Hoxha]], the [[Communist Party of Indonesia]], certain sections of the [[Communist Party of Vietnam]], and the [[Communist Party of New Zealand]]. In countries where the local Communist Party sided with the [[Communist Party of the Soviet Union]] (CPSU) under the leadership of Khrushchev, various groupings of dissident party members left to begin pre-party formations based on their specific interpretations of Marxism-Leninism.  This process accelerated as the 1960s progressed into the 1970s, eventually leading to what was called the [[New Communist Movement]] in various countries. 

For example, in the United States the New Communist Movement led to a plethora of formations, among them the [[Progressive Labor Party (United States)|Progressive Labour Party]], the [[Revolutionary Communist Party, USA]], the [[Freedom Road Socialist Organization]], and the [[October League]], amongst others.  Kim simply purged the North Korean Communist party of de-Stalinisation advocates, either executing them or forcing them into exile or labour camps.&lt;ref&gt;Lankov, Andrei N., ''Crisis in North Korea: The Failure of De-Stalinisation, 1956'' Honolulu:Hawaii University Press (2004)&lt;/ref&gt; Under Mao, the People's Republic grew antagonistic towards what they saw as the new Soviet leadership's &quot;[[Marxist revisionism|revisionism]]&quot;, resulting in the [[Sino-Soviet Split]] in 1960. Subsequently, China independently pursued the ideology of [[Maoism]], which still largely supported the legacy of Stalin and his policies. 

The [[Socialist People's Republic of Albania]] took the [[Communist Party of China|Chinese party's]] side in the Sino-Soviet Split and remained committed, at least theoretically, to [[Hoxhaism]], its brand of Stalinism, for decades thereafter, under the leadership of [[Enver Hoxha]]. Despite their initial cooperation against &quot;revisionism,&quot; [[Sino-Albanian split|Hoxha denounced Mao]] as a revisionist, along with almost every other self-identified Communist organization in the world. This had the effect of isolating Albania from the rest of the world, as Hoxha was hostile to both the pro-USA and pro-Soviet spheres of influence, as well as the [[Non-Aligned Movement]] under the leadership of [[Josip Broz Tito]], whom Hoxha had also denounced.

The ousting of Khrushchev in 1964 by his former party-state allies has been described as a Stalinist restoration by some, epitomised by the [[Brezhnev Doctrine]] and the [[apparatchik]]/[[nomenklatura]] &quot;stability of cadres,&quot; lasting until the period of [[glasnost]] and [[perestroika]] in the late 1980s and the [[History of the Soviet Union (1985-1991)|fall of the Soviet Union]].

Some historians and writers (like German [[Dietrich Schwanitz]]&lt;ref&gt;Dietrich Schwanitz, Bildung. Alles, was man wissen muss. &quot;At the same time, Stalin was a kind of monstrous reincarnation of Peter the Great. Under his tyranny, Russia transformed into a country of [[industrial slave]]s, and the gigantic empire was gifted with a network of working camps, the [[Gulag Archipelago]].&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;) draw parallels between Stalinism and the economic policy of [[Tsar]] [[Peter I of Russia|Peter the Great]], although Schwanitz in particular views Stalin as &quot;a monstrous reincarnation&quot; of him. Both men wanted [[Russia]] to leave the western [[Europe]]an states far behind in terms of development. Both largely succeeded, turning Russia into Europe's leading power. Others compare Stalin with [[Ivan the Terrible]] because of his policies of [[oprichnina]] and restriction of the liberties of common people.

Some analysts like [[Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn]] in ''The Mortal Danger: Misconceptions about Soviet Russia and the Threat to America'' consider the use of the term &quot;Stalinism&quot; is an excuse to hide the inevitable effects of communism as a whole on human liberties. He writes that the concept of Stalinism was developed after 1956 by western intellectuals so as to be able to keep alive the communist ideal. The term &quot;Stalinism&quot; however was in use as early as 1937 when Leon Trotsky wrote his pamphlet &quot;Stalinism and Bolshevism&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.marxists.org/archive/trotsky/1937/08/stalinism.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

===Trotskyism===

[[Trotskyism|Trotskyists]] argue that the &quot;Stalinist USSR&quot; was not [[socialism|socialist]] (and not communist), but a [[bureaucracy|bureaucratised]] [[degenerated workers state|degenerated workers' state]] &amp;mdash; that is, a non-capitalist state in which exploitation is controlled by a ruling caste which, although not owning the means of production and not constituting a [[social class]] in its own right, accrued benefits and privileges at the expense of the working class. Some in the [[Third Camp]] use [[bureaucratic collectivism]] as a theory to critique Stalinist forms of government. In foreign affairs the distinction between Trotskyism and Stalinism was even sharper. Trotsky believed that the Russian revolution needed to be spread all over the globe's working class, the proletarians for world revolution; Stalin insisted on consolidating Bolshevism in Russia and industrialization, &quot;socialism in one country.&quot; The dispute did not end until Trotsky's assassination in his Mexican villa by the communist assassin, Ramon Mercader in 1940.&lt;ref name=RefFariaStatistics&gt;{{cite web|last=Faria|first=MA|title=Stalin, Communists, and Fatal Statistics|url=http://www.haciendapublishing.com/articles/stalin-communists-and-fatal-statistics|accessdate=5 September 2012|date=January 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Council Communism===

Although worker's councils were politically significant in the earliest stages of the Soviet Union, they soon lost their power and significance as political power was concentrated in the hands of the [[Communist Party of the Soviet Union]] (CPSU). The operation of the Soviet Union under Stalinism was almost entirely undemocratic, vesting absolute power into unelected bureaucrats. This was abhorent to [[council communists]], who believe that [[workers' council]]s, or [[commune (Socialism)|communes]], embody the fundamental principles of socialism, such as workers' control over production and distribution. Indeed, some have described council communism as &quot;socialism from below,&quot; which they counterpose against what they see as the &quot;socialism from above&quot; that was endorsed by Stalinism.  According to this view, socialism from above is carried out by a centralized state run by an elite bureaucratic apparatus, whereas socialism from below represents the self-administration and self-rule of the working class.

Council communists described the Soviet Union as a [[capitalism|capitalist]] state, believing that the [[Bolshevik]] revolution in Russia became a &quot;[[bourgeois]] revolution&quot; when a party bureaucracy replaced the old feudal aristocracy. Although most council communists felt the Russian Revolution was [[working class]] in character, they believed that the Soviet Union was a [[state capitalist]] country, with the state replacing the individual capitalists (an additional argument in favour of that was the continued existence of capitalist relations, as manifested e.g. in the [[New Economic Policy]]).

The core principle of council communism is that the government and the [[Economic system|economy]] should be managed by [[workers' councils]] composed of delegates elected at workplaces and [[recall election|recallable]] at any moment. As such, council communists oppose the idea of an [[authoritarian]] &quot;[[State socialist]]&quot;/&quot;[[State capitalist]]&quot;  [[planned economy]] such as in the Soviet Union. They also oppose the idea of a &quot;revolutionary party&quot;, since council communists believe that a revolution led by a party will necessarily produce a party dictatorship. Council communists support a [[Workplace democracy|worker's democracy]], which they want to produce through a federation of workers' councils.
[[File:PMLI banners at rally.jpg|thumb|right|Supporters of the Marxist-Leninist Party of Italy, one carrying a flag portraying Marx, Engels, Lenin, Stalin, and Mao.]]
[[Image:Ekh-faust-foto.png|thumbnail|right|Raised fist, stenciled protest symbol of [[Autonomism|''Autonome'']], a left-wing anti-Stalinist movement influenced by [[social anarchism|anarchism]], [[left communism]], and the [[Situationist International]].]]
[[Left communist]]s like [[C. L. R. James]] and the Italian [[autonomist]]s, as well as unorthodox Trotskyists like [[Tony Cliff]], described Stalinism as &quot;[[state capitalism]]&quot;{{spaced ndash}}i.e., a form of capitalism where the state takes over the role of capital. [[Milovan Đilas]] argues that a [[New Class]] arose under Stalinism, a theory also put forward by various liberal theorists.

===''Socialisme ou Barbarie''===

[[Socialisme ou Barbarie]], led by philosopher [[Cornelius Castoriadis]], was a radical Marxist and [[libertarian socialist]] group based in France that significantly developed the [[council communist]] tradition as well as laying the foundation for [[autonomism]]. Socialisme ou Barbarie harshly criticised the communist regime in the [[USSR]], which it considered a form of &quot;[[bureaucratic collectivism|bureaucratic capitalism]]&quot; and not at all the [[state socialism|socialism]] it claimed to be. Philosopher [[Jean-François Lyotard]] was also part of this movement.

===Situationist International===

The [[Situationist International]] was a group of strongly anti-authoritarian Marxist theorists, influenced by the early 20th century [[avant-garde]] art movements in Europe, chiefly led by [[Guy Debord]] and [[Raoul Vaneigem]]. The Situationists were ruthlessly critical of Stalin and the Soviet Union, which they regarded as an oppressive undemocratic bureaucracy that was just as freedom-deprived as [[capitalism|capitalist society]], if not more so. The Situationists believed that Stalinist practices amounted to a complete rejection of Marxism, and that the hierarchy of power was identical in practice to capitalist society, arguing that a class of high-ranking bureaucrats and party officials had replaced the [[bourgeoisie]]. In contrast to Stalin's sprawling authoritarian and totalitarian state, the Situationists favored democratic [[workers' councils]] and [[worker self-management|workers' self-management]] intended to empower every individual equally and prevent anyone from centralizing power.

===Anarchism===

[[Anarchism|Anarchists]] like [[Emma Goldman]] were initially enthusiastic about the Bolsheviks, particularly after dissemination of Lenin's pamphlet ''[[State and Revolution]]'', which painted Bolshevism in a very [[Libertarianism|libertarian]] light. However, the relations between the anarchists and the Bolsheviks soured in Soviet Russia (e.g., in the suppression of the [[Kronstadt rebellion]] and the [[Makhnovist]] movement). Anarchists and Stalinist Communists were also in armed conflict during the [[Spanish civil war]]. Anarchists are critical of the statist, [[totalitarian]] nature of Stalinism, as well as its [[cult of personality]] around Stalin (and subsequent leaders seen by anarchists as Stalinists, such as Mao).

[[Social anarchism]] sees &quot;individual freedom as conceptually connected with social equality and emphasize community and [[mutual aid (organization)|mutual aid]].&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Suissa, Judith(2001) &quot;Anarchism, Utopias and Philosophy of Education&quot; ''Journal of Philosophy of Education'' 35 (4), 627–646. {{doi|10.1111/1467-9752.00249}}&lt;/ref&gt; Social anarchists argue that this goal can be achieved through the decentralization of political and economic power, distributing power equally among all individuals, and finally abolishing [[authoritarian]] institutions which control certain means of production.&lt;ref&gt;Mendes, Silva. ''Socialismo Libertário ou Anarchismo'' Vol. 1 (1896): &quot;Society should be free through mankind's spontaneous federative affiliation to life, based on the community of land and tools of the trade; meaning: Anarchy will be equality by abolition of private property and liberty by abolition of authority&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Social anarchism rejects private property, seeing it as a source of social inequality.&lt;ref&gt;[[Geoffrey Ostergaard|Ostergaard, Geoffrey]]. &quot;Anarchism&quot;. A Dictionary of Marxist Thought. Blackwell Publishing, 1991. p. 21.&lt;/ref&gt; Social Anarchism political philosophies almost always share strong characteristics of anti-authoritarianism, [[anti-capitalism]] and [[anti-statism]]. As the Soviet Union under Stalin manifested itself as a strong centralized authoritarian state, Stalinism and libertarian socialism are almost directly opposed.

===Democratic socialism===

[[Peter Hain]] defines democratic socialism as a form of anti-authoritarian &quot;socialism from below&quot;, in contrast to Stalinism and [[Social democracy]], which are variants of authoritarian [[state socialism]]. A significant current of the [[Democratic socialism|democratic socialist]] movement has defined itself in opposition to Stalinism. This includes [[George Orwell]] and the [[Independent Labour Party]] in Britain (particularly after [[World War II]]), the group around [[Marceau Pivert]] in France and, in America, [[the New York Intellectuals]] around the ''[[Partisan Review]]''. These democratic socialists saw Stalinism as a form of [[totalitarianism]] in some ways mirroring [[fascism]].

===Hillel Ticktin / ''Critique''===

In the journal ''[[Critique (Journal of Socialist Theory)]]'', [[Hillel H. Ticktin]] argues that the new Soviet rulers found themselves unable to use the market to control and exploit the peasantry and workers. So, instead, they used vast coercion, in the form of forced collectivisation, enabling them to both control the peasantry and to create an influx of new labour for rapid industrial expansion.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scribd.com/doc/54949537/Class-Structure-of-the-USSR-and-the-Elite-by-Hillel-Ticktin, Hillel Ticktin, 'The Class Structure of the USSR and the Elite'], ''Critique'' No.9, p56-9.&lt;/ref&gt;  Unprecedented levels of repression prevented any collective resistance. But, with little fear of unemployment and little monetary incentive to work harder, individual workers were still able to resist management interference. Workers also indulged in less-productive working, absenteeism and alcoholism.&lt;ref&gt;Hillel Ticktin, ''Origins of the Crisis in the USSR: Essays on the Political Economy of a Disintegrating System'', 1992, p12-13, 85-6, 117, 144; [http://www.scribd.com/search?query=ticktin+ussr Hillel Ticktin, 'Theories of Disintegration of the USSR'], in Paul G. Hare (ed.), ''Systemic Change in Post-Communist Economies'', p158.&lt;/ref&gt;  

This Stalinist system was neither socialist nor capitalist. Neither workers nor managers really controlled the work process and this created enormous inefficiencies and waste.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scribd.com/search?query=ticktin+ussr Hillel Ticktin, 'Towards a Political Economy of the USSR'], ''Critique'' No.1, p27; [http://www.scribd.com/doc/54944305/The-Political-Economy-of-Class-in-the-Transitional-Epoch-by-Hillel-Ticktin Hillel Ticktin, 'The Political Economy of Class in the Transitional Epoch'], ''Critique'' No.20-21, p16-18; Hillel Ticktin, 'Soviet Society and Professor Bettleheim', ''Critique'' No.6, p35, 43.&lt;/ref&gt;  As long as industry kept expanding by using new labour from the countryside, these inefficiencies could be covered up. But - Ticktin says - once this labour source &quot;dried up, as it did in the mid-1970s, the regime was doomed&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scribd.com/doc/54949537/Class-Structure-of-the-USSR-and-the-Elite-by-Hillel-Ticktin 'The Class Structure of the USSR and the Elite'], ''Critique'' No.9, p61; [http://www.scribd.com/search?query=ticktin+ussr 'Theories of Disintegration of the USSR' ], p158-161.&lt;/ref&gt; Ticktin also argues that the problems of post-Soviet Russia - which are exacerbated by the continuing decline of [[capitalism]] - show that Russia is still, essentially, a &quot;disintegrating Stalinism&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://libcom.org/history/political-economy-disintegrating-stalinism-hillel-ticktin Hillel Ticktin, 'Political Economy of a Disintegrating Stalinism&quot;], ''Critique'' Vol. 36, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Relationship to Leninism==

The [[historiography]] of Stalin is diverse, with many different aspects of continuity and discontinuity between the regimes of Stalin and Lenin proposed. Totalitarian historians such as [[Richard Pipes]] tend to see Stalinism as the natural consequence of Leninism, that Stalin &quot;faithfully implemented Lenin's domestic and foreign policy programmes&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Richard|last=Pipes|title=Three Whys of the Russian Revolution|pages=83–4}}&lt;/ref&gt; More nuanced versions of this general view are to be found in the works of other Western historians, such as [[Robert Service (historian)|Robert Service]], who notes that &quot;institutionally and ideologically, Lenin laid the foundations for a Stalin... but the passage from Leninism to the worse terrors of Stalinism was not smooth and inevitable.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Lenin: Individual and Politics in the October Revolution|journal=Modern History Review|volume=2|year=1990|number=1|pages=16–19}}&lt;/ref&gt; Likewise, historian [[Edvard Radzinsky]] believes that Stalin was a real follower of Lenin, exactly as he claimed himself.&lt;ref name=&quot;Radzinsky&quot;&gt;[[Edvard Radzinsky]] ''Stalin: The First In-depth Biography Based on Explosive New Documents from Russia's Secret Archives'', Anchor, (1997) ISBN 0-385-47954-9&lt;/ref&gt;

Proponents of continuity cite a variety of contributory factors: it is argued that it was Lenin, rather than Stalin, whose civil war measures introduced the [[Red Terror]] with its hostage taking and [[internment camps]], that it was Lenin who developed the infamous [[Article 58 (RSFSR Penal Code)|Article 58]], and who established the autocratic system within the Communist Party.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pipes&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|first=Richard|last=Pipes|title=Communism: A History|year=2001|isbn=0-8129-6864-6|pages=73–74}}&lt;/ref&gt; They also note that Lenin put a [[ban on factions within the Russian Communist Party]] and introduced the one-party state in 1921 - a move that enabled Stalin to get rid of his rivals easily after Lenin's death, and cite [[Felix Dzerzhinsky]], who, during the Bolshevik struggle against opponents in the [[Russian Civil War]], exclaimed  &quot;We stand for organised terror – this should be frankly stated&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;George Leggett, &quot;The Cheka: Lenin's Political Police&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

Opponents of this view include [[Historical revisionism|revisionist]] historians and a number of post–Cold War and otherwise dissident Soviet historians including [[Roy Medvedev]], who argues that although &quot;one could list the various measures carried out by Stalin that were actually a continuation of anti-democratic trends and measures implemented under Lenin... in so many ways, Stalin acted, not in line with Lenin's clear instructions, but in defiance of them&quot;.{{citation needed|date=October 2010}} In doing so, some historians have tried to distance Stalinism from Leninism in order to undermine the Totalitarian view that the negative facets of Stalin (terror, etc.) were inherent in Communism from the start.{{citation needed|date=October 2010}} Critics of this kind include anti-Stalinist communists such as [[Leon Trotsky]], who pointed out that Lenin attempted to persuade the CPSU to remove Stalin from his post as its [[General Secretary of the CPSU|General Secretary]]. [[Lenin's Testament]], the document which contained this order, was suppressed after Lenin's death. British historian [[Isaac Deutscher]], in his biography of Trotsky, says that on being faced with the evidence &quot;only the blind and the deaf could be unaware of the contrast between Stalinism and Leninism&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Isaac|last=Deutscher|title=Trotsky: The Prophet Unarmed|year=1959|pages=464–5}}&lt;/ref&gt; A similar analysis is present in more recent works, such as those of [[Graeme Gill]], who argues that &quot;[Stalinism was] not a natural flow-on of earlier developments; [it formed a] sharp break resulting from conscious decisions by leading political actors.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Gill|first=Graeme J.|title=Stalinism|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=3Pt35DCU580C|accessdate=1 October 2010|year=1998|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|isbn=978-0-312-17764-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Claims of Stalinism being &quot;Red fascism&quot;==
{{See also|Comparison of Nazism and Stalinism}}
Stalinism has been considered by some reviewers as a &quot;[[Red fascism]]&quot;. The ''[[New York Times]]'' dubbed Stalinism &quot;red [[fascism]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Fried |first= Richard M.|title= Nightmare in Red: The McCarthy Era in Perspective |publisher= Oxford University Press |year= 1991 |month= |isbn= 0-19-504361-8|page=50 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Though fascist regimes were ideologically opposed to the Soviet Union, some of them positively regarded Stalinism as evolving Bolshevism into a form of fascism. [[Benito Mussolini]] positively reviewed Stalinism as having transformed Soviet Bolshevism into a Slavic fascism.&lt;ref&gt;MacGregor Knox. Mussolini Unleashed, 1939-1941: Politics and Strategy in Italy's Last War. Pp. 63-64.&lt;/ref&gt; Despite ideological differences and holding territorial claims on the Soviet Union, [[Adolf Hitler]] admired Stalin and his politics and believed that Stalin was in effect transforming Soviet Bolshevism into a form of Nazism.&lt;ref&gt;François Furet. ''Passing of an Illusion: The Idea of Communism in the Twentieth Century''. Chicago, Illinois, USA; London, England, UK: University of Chicago Press, 1999. ISBN 0226273407. Pp. 191-192.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Anti-Revisionism]]
* [[Anti-Stalinist left]]
* [[Comparison of Nazism and Stalinism]]
* [[Cult of personality]]
* [[Joseph Stalin]]
* [[Maoism]]
* [[Neo-Stalinism]]
* [[Putinism]]
* [[Stalin Society]]
* [[Stalinist architecture]]
* [[Totalitarianism]]

==Further reading==
* ''[http://marxists.org/reference/archive/stalin/works/1951/economic-problems/index.htm Economic Problems of Socialism in the USSR]'', written in 1951
* Vincent Barnett, &quot;Understanding Stalinism: The 'Orwellian Discrepancy' and the 'Rational Choice Dictator',&quot; [[Europe-Asia Studies]], vol. 58, no. 3, May 2006 ([http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/routledg/ceas/2006/00000058/00000003/art00007;jsessionid=a8qf1bz1bwax.henrietta online abstract]).
* Alan Bullock, ''[[Hitler]] and Stalin: Parallel Lives'', Goldmann
* [[Isaac Deutscher]], ''Stalin: A Political Biography'', Dietz, 1990
* Philip Ingram, ''Russia and the USSR 1905–1991'', [[Cambridge University Press]], Cambridge, 1997
* Lankov, Andrei N., ''Crisis in North Korea: The Failure of De-Stalinization, 1956''. Honolulu: Hawaii University Press (2004)
* [[Boris Souvarine]], ''[http://www.marxists.org/history/etol/writers/souvar/works/stalin/index.htm Stalin: A Critical Survey of Bolshevism]'', Alliance Book, 1939
* [[Robert Service (historian)|Robert Service]], ''Lenin: A Biography'', [[Harvard University Press|Belknap Press]], 2002 ISBN 0-330-49139-3
* [[Robert Service (historian)|Robert Service]]. ''Stalin: A Biography'', Belknap Press, 2005 ISBN 0-674-01697-1
* {{cite book |author=[[Vladimir Tismăneanu]] |title=Stalinism for all seasons: a political history of Romanian Communism |publisher=[[University of California Press]] |location=Berkeley |year=2003 |pages= |isbn=0-520-23747-1 |oclc= |doi=}}
* Allan Todd, ''The European Dictatorships: Hitler, Stalin, Mussolini'', Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, 2003
* John Traynor, ''Challenging History: Europe 1890–1990'', Nelson Thornes Ltd, Cheltenham, 2002
* [[C.L.R. James]]. ''State Capitalism and World Revolution''. Chicago: Charles H. Kerr Publishing Co., 1950.

==References==
{{More footnotes|date=December 2008}}
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
* Stalin, Joseph V. [http://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/stalin/index.htm Stalin Reference Archive] at [http://www.marxists.org/ Marxists Internet Archive]. Retrieved May 11, 2005.
* [http://www.spartacus.schoolnet.co.uk/RUSstalin.htm ''Joseph Stalin''] on Spartacus Schoolnet
* [http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/historic_figures/stalin_joseph.shtml Joseph Stalin] by the [[BBC]]
*[http://www.havanatimes.org/?p=25327 Basic Economic Precepts of Stalinist Socialism] by Pedro Campos, ''Havana Times'', June 21, 2010

{{Joseph Stalin}}
{{authoritarian}}
{{Secret police of Communist Europe}}

[[Category:Stalinism| ]]
[[Category:Economy of the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:Politics of the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:Political philosophy by politician]]

[[ar:ستالينية]]
[[ast:Estalinismu]]
[[bg:Сталинизъм]]
[[br:Stalinouriezh]]
[[ca:Estalinisme]]
[[cs:Stalinismus]]
[[da:Stalinisme]]
[[de:Stalinismus]]
[[et:Stalinism]]
[[el:Σταλινισμός]]
[[es:Estalinismo]]
[[eo:Stalinismo]]
[[eu:Stalinismo]]
[[fa:استالینیسم]]
[[fr:Stalinisme]]
[[ko:스탈린주의]]
[[hr:Staljinizam]]
[[id:Stalinisme]]
[[is:Stalínismi]]
[[it:Stalinismo]]
[[he:סטליניזם]]
[[ka:სტალინიზმი]]
[[kk:Сталинизм]]
[[lt:Stalinizmas]]
[[hu:Sztálinizmus]]
[[nl:Stalinisme]]
[[ja:スターリニズム]]
[[no:Stalinisme]]
[[nn:Stalinisme]]
[[pl:Stalinizm]]
[[pt:Stalinismo]]
[[ro:Stalinism]]
[[ru:Сталинизм]]
[[simple:Stalinism]]
[[sk:Stalinizmus]]
[[fi:Stalinismi]]
[[sv:Stalinism]]
[[ta:இசுராலினிசம்]]
[[th:ลัทธิสตาลิน]]
[[tr:Stalinizm]]
[[uk:Сталінізм]]
[[zh:斯大林主义]]</text>
      <sha1>jpdfuwb8nllcrjyq2dcb5sluxk984bx</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
