<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Steven Lukes</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3711163</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521506899</id>
      <parentid>507423658</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-05T13:13:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>62.7.70.238</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added category</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8308">'''Steven Michael Lukes''' (born 1941) is a political and social theorist. Currently he is a professor of politics and sociology at [[New York University]]. He was formerly a professor at the [[University of Siena]], the [[European University Institute]] (Florence) and the [[London School of Economics]].

==Life and career==
Lukes attended the [[Newcastle Royal Grammar School|Royal Grammar School in Newcastle upon Tyne]],&lt;ref&gt;http://sociology.fas.nyu.edu/object/stevenlukes&lt;/ref&gt; completing his studies there in 1958. Lukes completed his [[Bachelor of Arts|B.A.]] in 1962 at [[Balliol College, Oxford|Balliol College]], [[University of Oxford|Oxford]]. He worked as a research fellow at [[Nuffield College, Oxford|Nuffield College]] and as a lecturer in politics at [[Worcester College, Oxford|Worcester College]] and completed his [[Master of Arts (postgraduate)|M.A.]] in 1967. In 1968, he completed his Ph.D. on the work of [[Émile Durkheim]]. From 1966 to 1987 he was fellow and tutor in politics at Balliol College. He is a Fellow of the [[British Academy]] (FBA) and a visiting professor at the [[University of Paris]],  New York University, [[University of California, San Diego]], and [[Hebrew University]]. 

From 1974 to 1983 he was President of the Committee for the History of Sociology of the [[International Sociological Association]].

He was the co-director of the European Forum on Citizenship at the European University Institute from 1995 to 1996.

In April 2006, Lukes married the political commentator and author [[Katha Pollitt]]; this being his third marriage.  Lukes was previously a widower.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/30/fashion/weddings/30poll.html The New York Times: Katha Pollitt and Steven Lukes]&lt;/ref&gt;  He has three children from his previous marriage to the English barrister [[Nina Stanger]]: freelance journalist Daniel (born 1977), musician Michael (born 1979) and NYU professor Alexandra (born 1981).

==Academic interests==
His main interests are political and social theory, the sociology of [[Durkheim]] and his followers, [[individualism]], rationality, the category of the person, [[Marxism]] and ethics, sociology of morality and new forms of liberalism, varieties of conceptions of [[Power (sociology)|power]], the notion of the &quot;good society&quot;, rationality and relativism, moral conflict and politics.

Lukes's most famous academic theory is that of the &quot;three faces of power&quot;.  This theory claims that governments control people in three ways: through decision-making power, non decision-making power and ideological power. Decision-making power is the most public of the three faces, and is the manner in which governments want to be seen: the power of governments to make [[policy]] decisions after widespread consultation with opposition parties and the wider public.  Non decision-making power is the power that governments have to control the [[Political agenda|agenda]] in debates and make certain issues (such as the possible merits of Communism in the United States) unacceptable for discussion in moderate public forums.  The third and most important face of power is [[ideological]] power, which is the power to influence people's wishes and thoughts, even making them want things opposed to their own self-interest (such as women supporting a patriarchal society).

He is a member of the editorial board of the ''European Journal of Sociology'' and directs a research project on what is left of the [[socialism|socialist]] idea in Western and Eastern Europe.

==The Three Dimensions of Power==
The three views of Power previously mentioned are discussed by Lukes in his book, ''Power: A Radical View''.  The idea is that the effectiveness and level of power for a given group or individual can be measured by considering certain criteria. The focuses of these views are discussed at length in Lukes' work, and he offers the Third Dimension as his own view of the shortcomings of the other views previously postulated by others, as well as being a more appropriate way to assess power.

The One Dimensional View of Power focuses only on behavior in decision making, specifically on key issues and essentially only in blatantly observable situations.  These often take the form of subjective interests: policy preferences demonstrated through political action.&lt;ref&gt;Lukes, Steven.  ''Power: A Radical View''.  London: Macmillan Press, 1974. p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Two Dimensional View of Power qualifies the First Dimension's critique of behavior and focuses on decision-making and nondecision-making.  It also looks at current ''and'' potential issues and expands the focus on observable conflict to those types that might be observed overtly or covertly.  But the Two Dimensional View still focuses on subjective interests, though those seen as policy preferences or even grievances.&lt;ref&gt;Lukes, Steven.  ''Power: A Radical View''.  London: Macmillan Press, 1974. p. 20.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Three Dimensional View of Power, offered by Lukes in his work, is a &quot;thoroughgoing critique&quot; of the behavioral focus.&lt;ref&gt;Lukes, Steven.  ''Power: A Radical View''.  London: Macmillan Press, 1974. p. 24.&lt;/ref&gt;  It concentrates on the decision-making in a political agenda and the control over that agenda.  As in the Two Dimensional View, both current issues and potential issues are considered.  But Lukes expands the critique to include both overt and covert observable conflicts, and those that might be latent.  Also, Lukes illustrates that a full critique of power should include both subjective interests and those &quot;real&quot; interests that might be held by those excluded by the political process.&lt;ref&gt;Lukes, Steven.  ''Power: A Radical View''.  London: Macmillan Press, 1974. p. 25.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Selected works==
*''Emile Durkheim: His Life and Work. A Historical and Critical Study'' (orig. pub. 1972); [[Penguin Books]], 1973.
*''Individualism,'' New York: [[HarperCollins|Harper &amp; Row]], 1973. ISBN 0-631-14750-0
*''Power: a Radical View,'' [[Macmillan Publishers|Macmillan]], 1974; [[Wiley-Blackwell|Blackwell]], 1986.
*''Essays in Social Theory,'' [[Columbia University Press]], 1977.
*''Rationality and Relativism,'' edited with [[Martin Hollis (philosopher)|Martin Hollis]], Blackwell, 1982.
*''Durkheim and the Law,'' edited with Andrew Scull, Martin Robertson, 1983.
*''Marxism and Morality''. [[Clarendon Press]], 1985.
*''The Category of the Person: Anthropology, Philosophy, History,'' co-edited with M. Carrithers and S. Collins. [[Cambridge University Press]], 1985.
*''Moral Conflict and Politics,'' Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1991.
*The essay &quot;Five Fables about Human Rights&quot;, in On Human Rights, Susan Hurley and Stephen Shute (eds.), [[Basic Books]], 1993.
*''Isaiah Berlin: Tra la filosofia e la storia delle idee. Una conversazione con Steven Lukes'' (Italian), Florence: Ponte alle Grazie, 1994.
*''[[The Curious Enlightenment of Professor Caritat]],'' [[Verso]], 1995.
*''Multicultural Questions'' (ed. jointly), 1999.
*''Liberals and Cannibals'' Verso 2003.
*''Power: A Radical View,'' Macmillan, 2nd Edition, 2005.
*''Moral Relativism,'' Picador/[[Macmillan Publishers|Macmillan]], 2008. ISBN 978-0-312-42719-1

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://sociology.fas.nyu.edu/object/stevenlukes Biography on New York University website]
*[http://stevenlukes.net Official website]

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Lukes, Steven
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1941
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Lukes, Steven}}
[[Category:1941 births]]
[[Category:Academics of the London School of Economics]]
[[Category:European University Institute faculty]]
[[Category:Alumni of Balliol College, Oxford]]
[[Category:British political theorists]]
[[Category:British sociologists]]
[[Category:Fellows of Balliol College, Oxford]]
[[Category:Fellows of the British Academy]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:New York University faculty]]
[[Category:Social sciences writers]]
[[Category:University of Siena faculty]]
[[Category:Political philosophers]]

[[de:Steven Lukes]]
[[fr:Steven Lukes]]
[[gl:Steven Lukes]]
[[ja:スティーヴン・ルークス]]
[[pl:Steven Michael Lukes]]
[[sv:Steven Lukes]]</text>
      <sha1>1w9fp86cd3c5xlojcz46722xo0ijtmr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
