<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Street-level bureaucracy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7518360</id>
    <revision>
      <id>479307185</id>
      <parentid>479263465</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-02-28T15:12:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ilikenwf</username>
        <id>413879</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>enforce is a better word here</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="4377">{{Politics}}
'''Street-level bureaucracy''' is the subset of a public agency or government institution containing the individuals who carry out and enforce the actions required by laws and public policies. Street-level bureaucracy is accompanied by the idea that these individuals vary the extents to which they enforce the rules and laws assigned to them.

==Street-level bureaucrats==
The concept of street-level bureaucracy was first coined by [[Michael Lipsky]] in 1980, who argued that &quot;policy implementation in the end comes down to the people who actually implement it&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lipsky&quot;&gt;Lipsky, M., ''Street-level Bureaucracy; Dilemmas of the Individual in Public Services'', 1980, [http://www.odi.org.uk/Rapid/Projects/R0163/Communications/Comms_Abs_47.html view summary]&lt;/ref&gt; He argued that state employees such as [[police]] and [[social workers]] should be seen as part of the &quot;policy-making community&quot; and as exercisers of [[political power]]. 

===Examples of street-level bureaucrats===
Street-level bureaucrats include [[police|police officers]], [[firefighters]], and other individuals, who on a daily basis interact with regular citizens and provide the force behind the given rules and laws in their areas of expertise.

==Problems with street-level bureaucracy==
Lipsky identified several problems with street-level bureaucracy, including &quot;the problem of limited resources, the continuous negotiation that is necessary in order to make it seem like one is meeting targets, and the relations with (nonvoluntary) clients&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lipsky&quot;/&gt; However, some commentators have challenged Lipsky's model. Tony Evans and John Harris.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Evans&quot;&gt;Evans, T and Harris, J, ''Street-Level Bureaucracy, Social Work and the (Exaggerated) Death of Discretion'', British Journal of Social Work, vol.34, no.6, September 2004, [http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/oup/social/2004/00000034/00000006/art00871 view abstract]&lt;/ref&gt; argue that &quot;the proliferation of rules and regulations should not automatically be equated with greater control over professional discretion; paradoxically, more rules may create more discretion.&quot; They also argue that the exercise of professional discretion by street-level bureaucrats is not inherently &quot;bad&quot;, but can be seen as an important professional attribute.&lt;ref name=&quot;Evans&quot;/&gt;

A 2003 [[United States|American]] study, conducted by Steven Maynard Moody of the [[University of Kansas]], reiterated the significance of street-level bureaucrats in the political process, asserting that street-level workers &quot;actually make policy choices rather than simply implement the decisions of elected officials.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;polrev&quot;&gt;Maynard-Moody, S and Musheno, M, ''Cops, Teachers, Counselors: Stories from the Front Lines of Public Service'', University of Michigan Press, 2003, [http://www.politicalreviewnet.com/polrev/reviews/PUAR/R_0033_3352_214_1005289.asp view summary]&lt;/ref&gt; They also claim, based on a study of 48 street-level state employees in two states, that &quot;workers' beliefs about the people they interact with continually rub against policies and rules&quot; and that the [[prejudice]]s of the street-level bureaucrats influence their treatment of citizens.&lt;ref name=&quot;polrev&quot;/&gt;  &lt;ref name=&quot;Riccucci&quot;&gt;Also see [[Norma M. Riccucci]], How Management Matters: Street-Level Bureaucrats and Welfare Reform. Washington, DC: Georgetown University Press, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, Emil Mackey confirmed that even the Resident Assistants in campus housing exercise their discretion to change policy at the implementation level. Furthermore, these policy implementation changes reflected the individual values of each street-level bureaucrat rather than the will of policymakers. Therefore, this research not only confirmed previous street-level bureaucrat research and literature, but also expanded it to include the Higher Education policy environment. &lt;ref&gt;Mackey, Emil Robert (2008). “Street-level bureaucrats and the shaping of university housing policy.” Fayetteville, Arkansas: University of Arkansas Press.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://library.uark.edu/search~S0?/aMackey/amackey/1%2C53%2C81%2CB/frameset&amp;FF=amackey+emil+robert+1970&amp;1%2C1%2C/indexsort=-&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Public administration]]
[[Category:Organizational culture]]

[[ms:Birokrasi tahap jalanan]]
[[nl:Street-level bureaucracy]]
[[zh:基层官僚]]</text>
      <sha1>fmc2y2zrlqgh9bavftdy5p4sd7149au</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
