<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Tax increment financing</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1280596</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520168704</id>
      <parentid>520168538</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-27T21:22:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Nikosgreencookie</username>
        <id>3568620</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* External links */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16591">

{{about|financing method|other uses of the abbreviation TIF|TIF (disambiguation)}}
{{Inappropriate tone|date=May 2008}}
{{POV-section|date=May 2011}}

'''Tax Increment Financing''', or '''TIF''', is a public financing method that is used for subsidizing [[redevelopment]], infrastructure, and other community-improvement projects in many countries, including the [[United States]]. Similar or related [[value capture]] strategies are used around the world. 

[[File:TIF_graph.pdf|thumb|300px|If the cost of basic services increases, with TIF in place, the result is a revenue shortfall that has to be paid from sources other than tax revenues of the TIF district.]] 
TIF is a method to use future gains in taxes to subsidize current improvements, which are projected to create the conditions for said gains. The completion of a public project often results in an increase in the value of surrounding [[real estate]], which generates additional tax revenue.  Sales-tax revenue may also increase, and jobs may be added, although these factors and their multipliers usually do not influence the structure of TIF.

When an increase in site value and private investment generates an increase in tax revenues, it is the &quot;tax increment.&quot; Tax Increment Financing dedicates tax increments within a certain defined district to finance the debt that is issued to pay for the project. TIF is often designed to channel funding toward improvements in distressed, underdeveloped, or underutilized parts of a jurisdiction where development might otherwise not occur. TIF creates funding for public or private projects by borrowing against the future increase in these property-tax revenues. &lt;ref&gt;Various, (2001). ''Tax Increment Financing and Economic Development, Uses, Structures and Impact.'' Edited by Craig L. Johnson and Joyce Y. Man. State University of New York Press.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Currently, thousands of TIF districts operate nationwide in the US, from small and mid-sized cities, to the State of California. As of 2008, California had over four hundred TIF districts with an aggregate of over $10 billion per year in revenues, over $28 billion of long-term debt, and over $674 billion of assessed land valuation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sco.ca.gov/Files-ARD-Local/LocRep/redevelop_fy0708redev_reports.pdf California State Controller's Annual Report on Redevelopment Agencies, 2007-2008]&lt;/ref&gt; California, where TIF began in the United States in 1952, has currently discontinued the use of them.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ti.org/antiplanner/?p=6059 &quot;Urban Renewal Dead in California,&quot;] ''The Antiplanner'', Thoreau Institute (2 January 2012).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;See California Redevelopment Association v. Ana Matosantos.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Every state including the [[District of Columbia]], except [[Arizona]] and Wyoming, have enabled legislation for tax increment financing. While some states, such as [[Illinois]], have used TIF for decades, many others did not pass or amend state laws to allow them to use this tool until the first decade of the 21st century.&lt;ref&gt;Arkansas (2000), Washington (2001), New Jersey (2002), Delaware (2003), Louisiana (2003), North Carolina (2005), and New Mexico (2006).&lt;/ref&gt;

Since the 1970s, a reduction in federal funding for redevelopment-related activities including spending increases, restrictions on [[municipal bonds]] which are [[tax-exempt]] [[Bond (finance)|bonds]], and an administrative transference of urban policy to local, lower-level governments, has led many cities to consider tax increment financing.  State-imposed caps on municipal [[property tax]] collections and limits on the amounts and types of city expenditures have also led many local governments to consider this funding strategy as a way to strengthen tax bases, to attract private investment, and to increase economic activity.

== Criticism ==
TIF districts are not without criticism. Although tax increment financing is one mechanism for local governments that does not directly rely on federal funds, some question whether TIF districts actually serve their resident populations. As investment in an area increases, it is not uncommon for real estate values to rise and for [[gentrification]] to occur. An organization called Municipal Officials for Redevelopment Reform (MORR) holds regular conferences on redevelopment abuse.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.redevelopment.com/|title=Redevelopment.com website|accessdate=2009-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Here are further claims made by TIF opponents:

* Although generally sold to legislatures as a tool to redevelop [[Blight (urban)|blighted]] areas, some districts are drawn up where development would happen anyway such as prime areas at the edges of cities. [[California]] has had to pass legislation designed to curb this abuse.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.coalitionforredevelopmentreform.org/references/morrreport.php|title=Redevelopment: The unknown government|publisher=Coalition for Redevelopment Reform|accessdate=2009-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ppic.org/content/pubs/report/R_298MDR.pdf|title=Subsidizing Redevelopment in California| publisher=Public Policy Institute of California|accessdate=2009-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* The designation as blighted, essential to most TIF implementation, can allow governmental condemnation of property through eminent domain laws. The famous [[Kelo v. City of New London]] United States Supreme Court case, where homes were condemned for a private development, was about actions within a TIF district.

*The process arguably leads to favoritism for politically connected developers, implementing lawyers, economic development officials and others involved in the process

* In some set-ups school districts within areas that are big TIF users are experiencing larger increases in state aid than those within areas that are not relying heavily on this mechanism. This may be creating an incentive for governments to over-TIF and to take on more risk. Governments are under no obligation to recognize when TIF would seriously harm a school district’s financial condition. 

* Normal inflationary increases in property values can be captured with districts in poorly-written TIFs, representing money that would have gone to the public coffers even without the financed improvements.

* Districts can sometimes be drawn too large and capture value that would have been increased anyway for unrelated reasons.

* Approval of districts can sometimes capture one entity's future taxes without its ''official'' input, i.e. a school districts taxes will be frozen on action of a city.

* Capturing the full tax increment and directing it to repay the development bonds ignores the fact that the incremental increase in property value likely requires an increase in the provision of public services, which will now have to be funded from elsewhere (often from subsidies from less economically thriving areas). For example, the use of tax increment financing to create a large residential development means that public services from schools to public safety will need to be expanded, yet if the full tax increment is captured to repay the development bonds, other money will have to be used.&lt;ref&gt;See Richard Dye and David Merriman, &quot;The Effects of Tax-Increment Financing on Economic Development,&quot; 47 ''Journal of Urban Economics'', no. 2 (2000) pp. 306-328&lt;/ref&gt;

===Examples===
====Chicago====
The city of [[Chicago]], in [[Cook County, Illinois]], has a significant number of TIF districts and has become a prime location for examining the benefits and disadvantages of TIF districts. The city runs 131 districts with tax receipts totaling upwards of $500 million for 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cookctyclerk.com/pdf/Chicago_TIF_revenue.pdf|title=City of Chicago TIF Revenue Totals by Year 1986-2006|publisher=Cook County Clerk's Office|accessdate=2008-05-29|format=PDF}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Lori Healey]], appointed commissioner of the city's Planning and Development department in 2005 was instrumental in the process of approving TIF districts as first deputy commissioner.

The [[Chicago Reader]], a [[Chicago]] [[alternative newspaper]] published weekly, has published articles regarding tax increment financing districts in and around Chicago. Written by staff writer Ben Joravsky, the articles are critical of tax increment financing districts as implemented in Chicago.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chicagoreader.com/tifarchive/|title=articles by Reader staff writer Ben Joravsky on Chicago's TIF (tax increment financing) districts|publisher=Chicago Reader|accessdate=2008-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cook County Clerk [[David Orr]], in order to bring transparency to Chicago and Cook County tax increment financing districts, began to feature information regarding Chicago area districts on his office's website.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cookcountyclerk.com/tsd/tifs/Pages/TIFs101.aspx|title=TIFs 101: A taxpayer's primer for understanding TIFs|accessdate=2008-05-29|publisher=Cook County Clerk's Office}}&lt;/ref&gt; The information featured includes City of Chicago TIF revenue by year, maps of Chicago and Cook County suburban municipalities' TIF districts.

The Neighborhood Capital Budget Group of Chicago, Illinois, a non-profit organization, advocated for area resident participation in capital programs. The group also researched and analyzed the expansion of Chicago's TIF districts. Though the organization closed on February 1, 2007, their research will be available on their website for six months.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncbg.org/research.htm|title=Research|publisher=Neighborhood Capital Budget Group of Chicago, Illinois|accessdate=2008-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Albuquerque====
Currently, the largest TIF project in America is located in [[Albuquerque, New Mexico]]: the $500 million [[Mesa del Sol]] development. Mesa del Sol is controversial in that the proposed development would be built upon a &quot;green field&quot; that presently generates little tax revenue and any increase in tax revenue would be diverted into a tax increment financing fund. This &quot;increment&quot; thus would leave governmental bodies without funding from the developed area that is necessary for the governmental bodies' operation.

====Alameda, California====
In 2009, SunCal Companies, an Irvine, California based developer, introduced a ballot initiative that embodied a redevelopment plan for the former [[Naval Air Station Alameda]] and a financial plan based in part on roughly $200 million worth of tax increment financing to pay for public amenities. SunCal structured the initiative so that the provision of public amenities was contingent on receiving tax increment financing, and on the creation of a community facilities (Mello-Roos) district, which would levy a special (extra) tax on property owners within the development.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ci.alameda.ca.us/news/pdf/0905_latest_report.pdf|title=Alameda Point Development Initiative Election Report Executive Summary Part I|format=[[PDF]]|publisher=City of Alameda|accessdate=2009-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since Alameda City Council did not extend the Exclusive Negotiation Agreement with Suncal, this project will not move forward. In California, Community Redevelopment Law governs the use of tax increment financing by public agencies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hcd.ca.gov/hpd/rda/rdalaw.html|title=California Community Redevelopment Law|accessdate=2009-12-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Applications and administration==

Cities use TIF to finance [[public infrastructure]], land acquisition, [[demolition]], [[utilities]] and planning costs, and other improvements including [[sanitary sewer|sewer]] expansion and repair, [[Curb (road)|curb]] and [[sidewalk]] work, storm drainage, [[traffic control]], street construction and expansion, [[street lighting]], water supply, [[landscaping]], park improvements, environmental remediation, [[bridge]] construction and repair, and [[Parking garage|parking structures]].

State enabling legislation gives local governments the authority to designate tax increment financing districts. The district usually lasts 20 years, or enough time to pay back the bonds issued to fund the improvements. While arrangements vary, it is common to have a city government assuming the administrative role, making decisions about how and where the tool is applied.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.opr.ca.gov/planning/docs/79515.pdf|title=Growth Within Bounds: Report of the Commission on Local Governance for the 21st Century|publisher=State of California|format=[[PDF]]|accessdate=2009-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

Most jurisdictions only allow bonds to be floated based upon a portion (usually capped at 50%) of the assumed increase in tax revenues. For example, if a $5,000,000 annual tax increment is expected in a development, which would cover the financing costs of a $50,000,000 bond, only a $25,000,000 bond would be typically allowed. If the project is moderately successful, this would mean that a good portion of the expected annual tax revenues (in this case over $2,000,000) would be dedicated to other public purposes other than paying off the bond.

== See also ==
* [[Public finance]]
* [[Value capture]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
&lt;!-- ==============================({{NoMoreLinks}})============================== --&gt;
&lt;!-- DO NOT ADD MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. WIKIPEDIA IS NOT A COLLECTION OF LINKS --&gt;
&lt;!-- If you think that your link might be useful,  instead of placing it here, put --&gt;
&lt;!-- it on this article's discussion page first. Links that have not been verified --&gt;
&lt;!--                                WILL BE DELETED                                --&gt;
&lt;!-- ============================================================================= --&gt;
* [http://research.northumbria.ac.uk/urbanfutures/research-projects/urban-development/tif Tax Increment Financing: Imagining Urban Futures] - Research on the circulation of the Tax Increment Financing model across North America and the UK by Professor Kevin Ward (University of Manchester)
* Michael Dardia [http://www.ppic.org/main/publication.asp?i=70  &quot;Subsidizing Redevelopment in California&quot;] (1998). Written for the Public Policy Institute of California.
* Nathan A. Benefield's academic paper titled [http://publishing.yudu.com/Freedom/Acvui/TaxIncrementFinancin/ &quot;The Effects of Tax Increment Financing on Home Values in the City of Chicago&quot;] (2003). Benefield's paper was prepared for presentation at the annual meeting of the Midwest Political Science Association.
* Swenson &amp; Eathington's [http://www.econ.iastate.edu/research/webpapers/paper_4094_N0138.pdf &quot;Do Tax Increment Finance Districts in Iowa Spur Regional Economic and Demographic Growth?&quot;] (2002).
* Weber's paper titled [http://www.uic.edu/cuppa/gci/pdf/TIF.pdf &quot;Making Tax Increment Financing (TIF) Work for Workforce Development: The Case of Chicago&quot;] (1999).{{Dead link|date=October 2012}}
* An abstract of Weber's [http://uar.sagepub.com/cgi/content/abstract/38/5/619 ''Equity and Entrepreneurialism: The Impact of Tax Increment Financing on School Finance''] (2003).
* An abstract of Weber, et al.'s [http://taylorandfrancis.metapress.com/(4omkl055n0gkpu55zvrirvvu)/app/home/contribution.asp?referrer=parent&amp;backto=issue,6,12;journal,38,265;linkingpublicationresults,1:100403,1 &quot;Does Tax Increment Financing Raise Urban Industrial Property Values?&quot;] (2003).{{Dead link|date=October 2012}}
* An abstract of Robinson's [http://uar.sagepub.com/cgi/content/abstract/40/2/246 &quot;Hunger Discipline and Social Parasites: The Political Economy of the Living Wage&quot;] (2004).
* An abstract of Man's [http://taylorandfrancis.metapress.com/link.asp?id=pt1puwu8jtbc37uk &quot;Fiscal Pressure, Tax Competition and the Adoption of Tax Increment Financing&quot;] (1999).{{Dead link|date=October 2012}}
* Hubbell &amp; Eaton's [http://cei.haag.umkc.edu/cei/EconRep/June97/ &quot;Tax Increment Financing in the State of Missouri&quot;] (University of Missouri-Kansas City, 1997).{{Dead link|date=October 2012}}
* Wood &amp; Hughes' report for Center on Wisconsin Strategy (at University of Wisconsin–Madison) titled [http://www.cows.org/pdf/rp-stumps.pdf &quot;From Stumps to Dumps: Wisconsin's Anti-Environmental Subsidies&quot;] (2001).
* Matthew Mayrl's report for Center on Wisconsin Strategy (at University of Wisconsin–Madison) titled [http://www.cows.org/pdf/econdev/tif/rp-tif_2005.pdf &quot;Refocusing Wisconsin’s TIF System On Urban Redevelopment: Three Reforms&quot;] (2005) and the [http://www.cows.org/pdf/ex-tif_2005.pdf Executive Summary].

[[Category:Public finance]]
[[Category:Taxation]]
[[Category:Government]]</text>
      <sha1>7fzln9vreslldf7kyy1q66i21tkp9s1</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
