<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>The Social Contract</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1922779</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522244714</id>
      <parentid>522204849</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T22:21:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jojalozzo</username>
        <id>4328601</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[Help:Reverting|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/160.36.55.55|160.36.55.55]] ([[User talk:160.36.55.55|talk]]) to last version by EmausBot</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8068">{{about|Jean-Jacques Rousseau's 1762 treatise|&quot;social contract&quot; as a political and philosophical concept|Social contract|other meanings|Social Contract (disambiguation)}}
{{Infobox book
| name             = Of The Social Contract, Or Principles of Political Right 
| title_orig       = Du contrat social ou Principes du droit politique
| translator       = 
| image            = [[File:Social contract rousseau page.jpg|200px]]
| image_caption    = Title page of the first octavo edition
| author           = [[Jean-Jacques Rousseau]] 
| illustrator      = 
| cover_artist     = 
| country          = [[Kingdom of France]]
| language         = [[French language|French]]
| series           = 
| subject          = 
| genre            = 
| publisher        = 
| pub_date         = 1762
| english_pub_date = 
| media_type       = 
| pages            = 
| isbn             = 
| oclc             = 
| dewey            = 
| congress         = 
| preceded_by      = 
| followed_by      = 
}}
'''''Of The Social Contract, Or Principles of Political Right''''' (''Du contrat social ou Principes du droit politique'') (1762) by [[Jean-Jacques Rousseau]], is the book in which Rousseau theorized about the best way in which to set up a political [[community]] in the face of the problems of commercial society which he had already identified in his ''[[Discourse on Inequality]]'' (1754).

&lt;blockquote cite=&quot;The Social Contract, Book I, Chapter 1:Subject of the First Book&quot;&gt;Man is born free, and everywhere he is in chains.&lt;ref&gt;''The Social Contract'', Book I, Chapter 1:''Subject of the First Book''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote cite=&quot;The Social Contract, Book III, Chapter 12:How the Sovereign Authority Maintains Itself&quot;&gt;The Sovereign, having no force other than the legislative power, acts only by means of the laws; and the laws being solely the authentic acts of the general will, the Sovereign cannot act save when the people is assembled.&lt;ref&gt;''The Social Contract'', Book III, Chapter 12:''How the Sovereign Authority Maintains Itself''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote cite=&quot;The Social Contract, Book III, Chapter 15:Deputies or Representatives&quot;&gt;Every law the people have not ratified in person is null and void — is, in fact, not a law.&lt;ref name=SC_3_15&gt;''The Social Contract'', Book III, Chapter 15:''Deputies or Representatives''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote cite=&quot;The Social Contact, Book III, Chapter 1:Government in General&quot;&gt;The legislative power belongs to the people, and can belong to it alone.&lt;ref name=SC_3_1&gt;''The Social Contract'', Book III, Chapter 1:''Government in General''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The ''Social Contract'' was a progressive work that helped inspire political reforms or revolutions in [[Europe]], especially in [[France]]. ''The Social Contract'' argued against the idea that monarchs were divinely empowered to legislate; as Rousseau asserts, only the people, in the form of the sovereign, have that all-powerful ''right''.

:''The heart of the idea of the social contract may be stated simply: Each of us places his person and authority under the supreme direction of the [[general will]], and the group receives each individual as an indivisible part of the whole...''

==Overview==
[[File:Rousseau pirated edition.jpg|right|150px|thumb|Title page of a pirated edition of the ''Social Contract'', probably printed in Germany.&lt;ref&gt;R.A. Leigh, Unsolved Problems in the Bibliography of J.-J. Rousseau, Cambridge, 1990, plate 22.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The stated aim of the ''Social Contract'' is to determine whether there can be a legitimate political authority. In order to accomplish more and remove himself from the [[state of nature]], man must enter into a Social Contract with others. In this social contract, everyone will be free because all forfeit the same amount of rights and impose the same duties on all. Rousseau also argues that it is illogical for a man to surrender his freedom for [[slavery]]; and so, the participants must be free. Furthermore, although the contract imposes new laws, especially those safeguarding and regulating [[property]], a person can exit it at any time (except in a time of need, for this is desertion), and is again as free as when he was born.

Rousseau posits that any administration, whatever form it takes, should be divided into two parts. First, there must be the [[sovereign]] (which Rousseau states must consist of the whole population, women included) who represents the [[general will]] and is the legislative power within the state. The second division is that of the [[government]], being distinct from the sovereign. This division must be since the sovereign cannot deal with particular matters (it is then acting as particular wills and not the general will — the sovereign is no longer whole and therefore ruined), like applications of the law. Therefore a government must be separate from that of the sovereign body. 

Rousseau claims that the size of the territory to be governed often decides the nature of the government. Since a government is only as strong as the people, and this strength is absolute, the larger the territory the more strength the government must be able to exert over the populace. In his view, a monarchical government is able to wield the most power over the people since it has to devote less power to itself, while a democracy the least. In general, the larger the [[bureaucracy]], the more power required for government discipline. Normally, this relationship requires the state to be an [[aristocracy]] or [[monarchy]]. It is important to note here that when Rousseau talks of aristocracy and monarchy he does not necessarily mean they are not a democracy in the sense we see it now - the aristocracy or monarch could be elected, being like Cabinet Governments or Presidents are today - when Rousseau uses the word democracy he refers to a [[direct democracy]] rather than a [[representative democracy]] like most democratic states have today. In light of all this, Rousseau argues that, like his native [[Geneva]], small [[city-states]] are the form of nation in which freedom can best flourish. For any state large enough to require intermediaries between the people and the government, an elected aristocracy may be preferable, and in very large states a benevolent monarch; but even monarchical rule, to be legitimate, must be subordinate to the sovereign rule of law.

==See also==
* [[Social contract]]; the more general concept

== Notes ==
{{reflist|2}}

== References ==
*Wraight, Christopher D. (2008), ''Rousseau's The Social Contract: A Reader's Guide''. London: Continuum Books.

==External links==
{{commons category|Du contrat social}}
* ''[http://metalibri.wikidot.com/title:du-contrat-social Du contrat social]'' (MetaLibri)
*[http://www.constitution.org/jjr/socon.htm The Social Contract at constitution.org]
*[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/04335a.htm Catholic Encyclopedia] Based on an article critical of ''The Social Contract'', written in 1908.
*[http://www.sparknotes.com/philosophy/socialcontract SparkNotes entry on ''The Social Contract'']
*[http://kaltric.de/mat/matphil/gv Rousseaus Gesellschaftsvertrag in Kurzform]
*[http://www.earlymoderntexts.com A site containing The Social Contract, slightly modified for easier reading]

{{Jean-Jacques Rousseau}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Social Contract}}
[[Category:1762 books]]
[[Category:Philosophy books]]
[[Category:Works by Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]
[[Category:Social philosophy literature]]

[[bg:За обществения договор]]
[[ca:El contracte social]]
[[de:Vom Gesellschaftsvertrag oder Prinzipien des Staatsrechtes]]
[[es:El contrato social]]
[[fr:Du contrat social]]
[[ko:사회 계약론]]
[[id:Du contrat social]]
[[is:Samfélagssáttmálinn]]
[[it:Contratto sociale (libro)]]
[[he:האמנה החברתית (ספר)]]
[[nl:Het maatschappelijk verdrag]]
[[ja:社会契約論]]
[[pt:Do Contrato Social]]
[[fi:Yhteiskuntasopimuksesta]]
[[uk:Про суспільну угоду, або принципи політичного права]]
[[zh:社会契约论]]</text>
      <sha1>9accjs9dkvjrgh4ade4b38ii6z2po8u</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
