<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>The Communist Manifesto</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>30312</id>
    <revision>
      <id>516125639</id>
      <parentid>514468019</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-05T10:12:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Gadrauhts</username>
        <id>109356</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25307">{{pp-protected|expiry=2012-12-23T22:12:44Z|small=yes}}{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
{{Use British English|date=October 2011}}
{{Infobox book| &lt;!-- WikiProject_Novels or Wikipedia:WikiProject_Books --&gt;
| name = The Communist Manifesto
| image = [[File:communist-manifesto.png|201px|]]
| image_caption = The first edition of the book, in German.
| author=[[Karl Marx]] and [[Friedrich Engels]]
| cover_artist =
| country = United Kingdom
| language = Originally German, subsequently into many others.
| genre = History, [[sociology]], philosophy
| release_date = 21 February 1848
| isbn =
}}
{{Marxism|expanded=Works}}
{{Communism sidebar}}

'''''The Communist Manifesto''''' (''Das Kommunistische Manifest''), originally titled '''''Manifesto of the Communist Party''''' ({{langWithName|de|German|''Manifest der Kommunistischen Partei''}}) is a short 1848 publication written by the political theorists [[Karl Marx]] and [[Friedrich Engels]]. It has since been recognized as one of the world's most influential political manuscripts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Seymour-Smith|first=Maerin|title=The 100 Most Influential Books Ever Written: The History of Thought from Ancient Times to Today|publisher=Citadel Press|location=Secaucus, NJ|year=1998}}&lt;/ref&gt; Commissioned by the [[Communist League]], it laid out the League's purposes and program. It presents an analytical approach to the [[class struggle]] (historical and present) and the problems of capitalism, rather than a prediction of communism's potential future forms.&lt;ref&gt;The Great Philosophers, by Jeremy Stangroom and James Garvey, Arcturus 2005/ 2008 ISBN 978-1-84837-018-0, pp160 UKP9.99&lt;/ref&gt;

The book contains Marx and Engels' theories about the nature of society and politics, that in their own words, &quot;The history of all hitherto existing society is the history of class struggles&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Manifesto_ch1&quot; /&gt; It also briefly features their ideas for how the capitalist society of the time would eventually be replaced by [[socialism (Marxism)|socialism]], and then eventually [[communism]].

==Authorship==
Friedrich Engels has often been credited in composing the first drafts, which led to ''The Communist Manifesto''. In July 1847, Engels was elected into the Communist League, where he was assigned to draw up a catechism. This became the ''Draft of a Communist Confession of Faith.'' The draft contained almost two dozen questions that helped express the ideas of both Engels and Karl Marx at the time. In October 1847, Engels composed his second draft for the Communist League entitled ''The Principles of Communism.'' The text remained unpublished until 1914, despite its basis for ''The Manifesto.'' From Engels's drafts Marx was able to write, once commissioned by the Communist League, ''The Communist Manifesto,'' where he combined more of his ideas along with Engels's drafts and work, ''The Condition of the Working Class in England.''&lt;ref&gt;Marx's General: The Revolutionary Life of Friedrich Engels, by Tristram Hunt, Metropolitan Books 2009 ISBN 978-0-8050-8025-4,pg. 142-44&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the names of both Engels and Karl Marx appear on the title page alongside the &quot;persistent assumption of joint-authorship&quot;, Engels, in the preface introduction to the 1883 German edition of the Manifesto, said that the ''Manifesto'' was &quot;essentially Marx's work&quot; and that &quot;the basic thought... belongs solely and exclusively to Marx.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Marx and Engels, ''The Communist Manifesto'', introduction by Martin Malia (New York: Penguin group, 1998), pg. 35 ISBN 0-451-52710-0&lt;/ref&gt;

Engels wrote after Marx's death, {{quote|&quot;I cannot deny that both before and during my forty years' collaboration with Marx I had a certain independent share in laying the foundations of the theory, but the greater part of its leading basic principles belongs to Marx....Marx was a genius; we others were at best talented. Without him the theory would not be by far what it is today. It therefore rightly bears his name.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Marx's General: The Revolutionary Life of Friedrich Engels, by Tristram Hunt, Metropolitan Books 2009 ISBN 978-0-8050-8025-4,pg. 117&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Despite Engels's modesty in these two quotations, in fact he made major contributions to the Manifesto, starting with the suggestion to abandon &quot;the form of a catechism and entitle it the Communist ''Manifesto''.&quot; Moreover, Engels joined Marx in [[Brussels]] for the writing of the Manifesto. There is no evidence of what his contributions to the final writing were, but the Manifesto bears the stamp of Marx's more rhetorical writing style. Nevertheless, it seems clear that Engels's contributions justify his name's appearance on the title page after Marx's.&lt;ref&gt;''The Life and Thought of Friedrich Engels: A Reinterpretation'', by J.D. Hunley, Yale University Press 1991 ISBN 0-300-04923-4,pg. 65–79 (quotation pg. 66) for an extended discussion of the two men's contributions&lt;/ref&gt;

== Textual history ==
''The Communist Manifesto'' was first published (in German) in London by a group of German political refugees in 1848. It was also serialised at around the same time in a German-language London newspaper, the ''Deutsche Londoner Zeitung''.&lt;ref&gt;Kuczynski, Thomas, ''Das kommunistische Manifest (Manifest der Kommunistischen Partei) von Karl Marx und Friedrich Engels: von der Erstausgabe zur Leseausgabe, mit einer Editionsbericht'' (Trier, 1995).&lt;/ref&gt; The first English translation was produced by [[Helen Macfarlane]] in 1850, and the book was first published in the United States by [[Stephen Pearl Andrews]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Jeff Riggenbach|Riggenbach, Jeff]] (1 April 2011) [http://mises.org/daily/5161/Stephen-Pearl-Andrewss-Fleeting-Contribution-to-Anarchist-Thought Stephen Pearl Andrews's Fleeting Contribution to Anarchist Thought], [[Mises Institute]]&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Manifesto'' went through a number of editions from 1872 to 1890; notable new prefaces were written by Marx and Engels for the 1872 German edition, the 1882 Russian edition, the 1883 French edition, and the 1888 English edition. The [[s:Manifesto of the Communist Party|1910 edition]], translated by Samuel Moore with the assistance of Engels, has been the most commonly used English text since.{{Citation needed|date=October 2011}}

However, some recent English editions, such as Phil Gasper's annotated &quot;road map&quot; ([[Haymarket Books]], 2006), have used a slightly modified text in response to criticisms of the Moore translation made by [[Hal Draper]] in his 1994 history of the ''Manifesto'', ''The Adventures of the &quot;Communist Manifesto&quot;'' (Center for Socialist History, 1994).

In late 2010, [http://www.redquillbooks.com/ Red Quill Books] announced the release of a modern, illustrated [http://www.redquillbooks.com/Communist_Manifesto.html &quot;comic book&quot;] version of the Communist Manifesto in four parts.&lt;ref&gt;Susan Polo. 20 December 2010. &quot;The Communist Manifesto: The Comic Book&quot; http://www.geekosystem.com/the-communist-manifesto-the-comic-book/ Accessed 20 February 2012&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jamie Long. 29 December 2010. &quot;Communist Manifesto to get Comic Books Treatment&quot; Toronto Sun. http://www.torontosun.com/news/weird/2010/12/29/16703416.html&lt;/ref&gt;

== Contents ==
The ''Manifesto'' is divided into an introduction, three substantive sections, and a conclusion.

=== Introduction ===
The preamble to the main text of the Manifesto states that the continent of Europe fears the &quot;spectre of communism&quot;, and the powers of old Europe are uniting in &quot;a holy alliance [intended to] exorcise this spectre&quot;. Marx refers here to not only the houses of power and landed gentry of old Europe—the bourgeoisie—but diverse factions such as the papacy and the emerging corporate world as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;Manifesto_intro&quot;&gt;[[#Mar48|Marx and Engels 1848]]. Introduction.&lt;/ref&gt; Marx declares that &quot;It is high time that Communists should openly, in the face of the whole world, publish their views, their aims, their tendencies, and meet this nursery tale of the spectre of communism with a manifesto of the party itself&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Manifesto_intro&quot; /&gt;

=== I. Bourgeois and Proletarians ===
The first chapter of the ''Manifesto'', &quot;Bourgeois and Proletarians&quot;, examines the Marxist conception of history, with the initial idea asserting that &quot;The history of all hitherto existing society is the history of class struggles&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Manifesto_ch1&quot;&gt;[[#Mar48|Marx and Engels 1848]]. Chapter One.&lt;/ref&gt; It goes on to say that in capitalism, the working class, [[proletariat]], are fighting in the class struggle against the owners of the means of production, the [[bourgeois]], and that past class struggle ended either with revolution that restructured society, or &quot;common ruin of the contending classes&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Manifesto_ch1&quot; /&gt;

It continues by adding that the bourgeois exploits the proletariat through the &quot;constant revolutionising of production [and] uninterrupted disturbance of all social conditions&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Manifesto_ch1&quot; /&gt;

The Manifesto explains that the reason the bourgeois exist and exploit the proletariat with low wages is [[private property]], &quot;the accumulation of wealth in private hands, the formation and increase of capital&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Manifesto_ch1&quot; /&gt; and that competition amongst the proletariat creates wage-labour, which rests entirely on the competition among the workers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Manifesto_ch1&quot; /&gt;

This section further explains that the proletarians will eventually rise to power through class struggle: the [[bourgeoisie]] constantly exploits the proletariat for its manual labour and cheap wages, ultimately to create profit for the bourgeois; the proletariat rise to power through revolution against the bourgeoisie such as riots or creation of unions. The Communist Manifesto states that while there is still class struggle amongst society, capitalism will be overthrown by the proletariat only to start again in the near future; ultimately communism is the key to class equality amongst the citizens of Europe.

=== II. Proletarians and Communists ===
The second section, &quot;Proletarians and Communists&quot;, starts by stating the relationship of conscious communists to the rest of the working class, declaring that they will not form a separate party that opposes other working-class parties, will express the interests and general will of the proletariat as a whole, and will distinguish themselves from other working-class parties by always expressing the common interest of the entire proletariat independently of all [[nationality|nationalities]] and representing the interests of the movement as a whole.&lt;ref name=&quot;Manifesto_ch2&quot;&gt;[[#Mar48|Marx and Engels 1848]]. Chapter Two.&lt;/ref&gt;

The section goes on to defend communism from various objections, such as the claim that communists advocate &quot;[[free love]]&quot;, and the claim that people will not perform labor in a communist society because they have no incentive to work.&lt;ref name=&quot;Manifesto_ch2&quot; /&gt; The section ends by outlining a set of short-term demands:

{{colbegin|2}}
# Abolition of [[land tenure|property in land]] and application of all [[renting|rents]] of land to public purposes.
# A heavy [[progressive tax|progressive]] or graduated income tax.
# Abolition of all right of [[inheritance]].
# [[Confiscation]] of the property of all [[Emigration|emigrants]] and [[Rebellion|rebels]].
# Centralisation of [[Credit (finance)|credit]] in the hands of the [[Sovereign state|State]], by means of a [[national bank]] with State [[Capital (economics)|capital]] and an exclusive monopoly.
# Centralisation of the means of communication and transport in the hands of the State.
# Extension of factories and [[means of production|instruments of production]] owned by the State; the bringing into [[Tillage|cultivation]] of [[wasteland|waste-lands]], and the improvement of the [[soil]] generally in accordance with a [[Agricultural science|common plan]].
# Equal [[Legal liability|liability]] of all to labour. Establishment of industrial [[army|armies]], especially for agriculture.
# Combination of agriculture with manufacturing [[Industry|industries]]; gradual abolition of the distinction between town and country, by a more equitable [[population density|distribution of the population]] over the country.
# [[Free education]] for all children in [[Public school (government funded)|public schools]]. Abolition of [[Child labor|children's factory labour]] in its present form and combination of education with industrial production.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/61|title=The Communist Manifesto at Project Gutenberg |accessdate=24 January 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{colend}}

The implementation of these policies would, as believed by Marx and Engels, be a precursor to the stateless and [[classless society]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Manifesto_ch2&quot; /&gt; In a controversial passage they suggested that the &quot;proletariat&quot; might in competition with the bourgeoisie be compelled to organise as a class, form a revolution, make itself a ruling class, sweep away the old conditions of production, and in that step have abolished its own supremacy as a class.&lt;ref name=&quot;Manifesto_ch2&quot; /&gt; This account of the transition from socialism to communism was criticised particularly during and after the Soviet era.

=== III. Socialist and Communist Literature ===
The third section, &quot;Socialist and Communist Literature,&quot; distinguishes communism from other socialist doctrines prevalent at the time the ''Manifesto'' was written.&lt;ref name=&quot;Manifesto_ch3&quot;&gt;[[#Mar48|Marx and Engels 1848]]. Chapter Three.&lt;/ref&gt; While the degree of reproach of Marx and Engels toward rival perspectives varies, all are dismissed for advocating [[reformism]] and failing to recognise the preeminent role of the working class.

=== IV. Position of the Communists in Relation to the Various Opposition Parties ===
The concluding section, &quot;Position of the Communists in Relation to the Various Opposition Parties&quot;, briefly discusses the communist position on struggles in specific countries in the mid-nineteenth century such as France, Switzerland, Poland, and Germany, and declares that Germany &quot;is on the eve of a bourgeois revolution&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Manifesto_ch4&quot; /&gt; and predicts that a world revolution will soon follow.&lt;ref name=&quot;Manifesto_ch4&quot; /&gt; It then ends by declaring an alliance with the [[social democrat]]s, boldly supporting other communist revolutions, and calling the proletarians to action, ending with the rallying cry of communism, &quot;[[Workers of the world, unite!]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Manifesto_ch4&quot;&gt;[[#Mar48|Marx and Engels 1848]]. Chapter Four.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reception==
The [[revolutionary wave]] [[European Revolutions of 1848|throughout Europe in 1848]], which began in [[French Revolution of 1848|France in February]] and immediately spread to most of Europe and parts of Latin America,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Merriman |first=John M. |authorlink=John M. Merriman |title=A History of Modern Europe. Volume 2: From the French Revolution to the Present |location=New York |publisher=[[W. W. Norton &amp; Company|Norton]] |year=1996 |page=715 |isbn=0-393-96928-2 |oclc=152762820 }}&lt;/ref&gt; owed nothing to ''The Communist Manifesto'', but within a year the revolutions collapsed.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last1=Eyck |first1=Frank |last2=Evans |first2=Robert John Weston |authorlink2=Robert John Weston Evans |last3=von Strandmann |first3=Hartmut Pogge |title=The Revolutions in Europe  1848–1849: From Reform to Reaction |location=Oxford |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |year=2000 |volume=4 |isbn=0-19-820840-5 |oclc=4669489521 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Subsequently, traditional authorities found in ''The Communist Manifesto'' and its contents a good excuse for action against its authors.  As a consequence, Marx and his wife were arrested and expelled from [[Belgium]], the German daily newspaper published by Marx in [[Cologne]] between 1 June 1848 and 19 May 1849, ''[[Neue Rheinische Zeitung|Neue Rheinische Zeitung: Organ der Demokratie]]'', was suppressed,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Marx |first=Karl |authorlink=Karl Marx |title=The Summary Suppression of the Neue Rheinische Zeitung |journal=Neue Rheinische Zeitung |issue=301 |date=19 May 1849 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last1=Marx |first1=Karl |authorlink1=Karl Marx |last2=Engels |first2=Friedrich |authorlink2=Friedrich Engels |title=Marx-Engels Collected Works |volume=Volume 9 |chapter=The Summary Suppression of the ''Neue Rheinische Zeitung'' |location=New York |publisher=[[International Publishers]] |year=1977 |pages=451–453 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and Marx himself was expelled from Germany and France, and, in August 1849 he sought refuge in London.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Wheen |first=Francis |authorlink=Francis Wheen |title=Karl Marx: A Life |location=New York |publisher=[[W. W. Norton &amp; Company|Norton]] |year =2001 |origyear=1999 |edition=1st American ed. |pages=147–148 |isbn=978-0-393-32157-9 |oclc=48001599 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Watson |first=Peter |authorlink=Peter Watson (intellectual historian) |title=The German Genius: Europe's Third Renaissance, the Second Scientific Revolution, and the Twentieth Century |date=22 June 2010 |location=&quot;New York |publisher=[[HarperCollins]] |isbn=0-06-076022-2 |oclc=456179681 |pages=250–... }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last1=Carter |first1=John |authorlink1=John Carter (author) |last2=Muir |first2=Percy H. |title=[[Printing and the Mind of Man|Printing and the Mind of Man: A Descriptive Catalogue Illustrating the Impact of Print on the Evolution of Western Civilization During Five Centuries]] |publisher=London: [[Cassell (publisher)|Cassell]]; New York: [[Holt McDougal|Holt, Rinehart &amp; Winston]] |year=1967 |page=236 |oclc=576854 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A number of 21st century writers have commented on ''The Communist Manifesto'''s continuing relevance. Academic John Raines, writing in 2002, noted that &quot;In our day this Capitalist Revolution has reached the farthest corners of the earth. The tool of money has produced the miracle of the new global market and the ubiquitous shopping mall. Read ''The Communist Manifesto'', written more than one hundred and fifty years ago, and you will discover that Marx foresaw it all.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Raines, John. 2002. &quot;Introduction&quot;. ''Marx on Religion'' (Marx, Karl). Philadelphia: Temple University Press. Page 05.&lt;/ref&gt; Writing in 2003, the English Marxist [[Chris Harman]] described the work, stating that:

{{quote|There is still a compulsive quality to its prose as it provides insight after insight into the society in which we live, where it comes from and where its going to. It is still able to explain, as mainstream economists and sociologists cannot, today's world of recurrent wars and repeated economic crisis, of hunger for hundreds of millions on the one hand and &quot;overproduction&quot; on the other. There are passages that could have come from the most recent writings on globalisation.&lt;ref&gt;Harman, Chris. 2010. &quot;The Manifesto and the World of 1848&quot;. ''The Communist Manifesto'' (Marx, Karl and Engels, Friedrich). Bloomsbury, London: Bookmarks. Page 03.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The continued relevance of the Marxist theories found within the text has also been supported by the Marxist academic [[Alex Callinicos]], editor of ''[[International Socialism (journal)|International Socialism]]'', who stated that &quot;This is indeed a manifesto for the 21st century.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Callinicos, Alex. 2010. &quot;The Manifesto and the Crisis Today&quot;. ''The Communist Manifesto'' (Marx, Karl and Engels, Friedrich). Bloomsbury, London: Bookmarks. Page 08.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Writing in ''[[The London Evening Standard]]'' on 23 April, Andrew Neather cited [[Verso Books]]' 2012 re-edition of ''The Communist Manifesto'', with an introduction by [[Eric Hobsbawm]], as part of a resurgence of left-wing-themed ideas which includes the publication of [[Owen Jones (writer)|Owen Jones]]' best-selling ''Chavs: The Demonization of the Working Class'', and [[Jason Barker]]'s documentary ''[[Marx Reloaded]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;The London Evening Standard&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.thisislondon.co.uk/lifestyle/london-life/the-marx-effect-7669766.html | title=The Marx effect | work=[[The London Evening Standard]] | date=23 April | accessdate=8 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Communism}}
* [[Anti-capitalism]]
* [[Erwin Schulhoff]] (created a music version of ''The Communist Manifesto'')
* [[List of current communist states]]
* [[Wage slavery]]
{{clear}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
{{columns-list|2|&lt;!-- column start --&gt;
* {{cite book |title= The Communist Manifesto |last= Marx |first= Karl and Engels, Friedrich |year= 1848 |isbn= |nopp=|ref=Mar48}}
}}&lt;!-- split column end --&gt;
{{refend}}

== External links ==
{{Wikisource}}
* Full text of [http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1848/communist-manifesto/index.htm '''''The Communist Manifesto'''''] English edition of 1888 from the Marxists Internet Archive in all formats: PDF, Audio, HTML, Word, Text, etc.
* {{gutenberg|no=61|name=The Communist Manifesto}}&amp;nbsp;— [[English language|English edition]] of 1888, edited by Friedrich Engels
* [http://librivox.org/the-communist-manifesto-by-karl-marx-and-friendrich-engels Free audiobook] from [http://librivox.org LibriVox]
* [http://www.anu.edu.au/polsci/marx/marx.html A Marxism resource page]
* Only remaining page of the [http://www.iisg.nl/collections/manifest/manifest.php first draft of the Manifesto] in Marx's handwriting from the Marx papers at the International Institute of Social History.
* [http://www.rationalrevolution.net/special/library/communist_manifesto.htm Images of English versions]
* [http://books.google.com/books?id=mURxuWGr79IC&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s The Communist Manifesto] (Full Version in [[Google Books]])
* [http://www.internationalviewpoint.org/spip.php?article1557 The Communist Manifesto 160 Years Later] by [[Michael Löwy]]

{{Marx/Engels}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Communist Manifesto, The}}
[[Category:1848 books]]
[[Category:Books by Karl Marx and Friedrich Engels]]
[[Category:Communism]]
[[Category:Communist books]]
[[Category:Futurology books]]
[[Category:Marxism]]
[[Category:Political books]]
[[Category:Political manifestos]]
[[Category:Socialism]]
[[Category:Theories of history]]
[[Category:German books]]
[[Category:Pamphlets]]
[[Category:1848 in politics]]
[[Category:Philosophical literature]]
[[Category:Party programs]]

[[ar:بيان الحزب الشيوعي]]
[[an:Manifiesto comunista]]
[[ast:Manifiestu comunista]]
[[bn:কমিউনিস্ট ইস্তেহার]]
[[zh-min-nan:Kiōng-sán-tóng Soan-giân]]
[[be:Маніфест камуністычнай партыі]]
[[be-x-old:Маніфэст камуністычнай партыі]]
[[bg:Комунистически манифест]]
[[bs:Manifest komunističke partije]]
[[ca:Manifest Comunista]]
[[ceb:Pagsangyaw sa mga Komunista]]
[[cs:Komunistický manifest]]
[[da:Det Kommunistiske Manifest]]
[[de:Manifest der Kommunistischen Partei]]
[[et:Kommunistliku partei manifest]]
[[el:Το Κομμουνιστικό Μανιφέστο]]
[[es:Manifiesto del Partido Comunista]]
[[eo:Manifesto de la Komunista Partio]]
[[eu:Agiri Komunista]]
[[fa:مانیفست حزب کمونیست]]
[[fr:Manifeste du Parti communiste]]
[[fy:Kommunistysk Manifest]]
[[gl:Manifesto do Partido Comunista]]
[[got:𐍃𐌰 𐌲𐌰𐌼𐌰𐌹𐌽𐌳𐌿𐌸𐌴𐌹𐌽𐌹𐍃𐌺𐌰 𐍃𐍅𐌹𐌺𐌿𐌽𐌸𐌹]]
[[ko:공산당 선언]]
[[hi:कम्युनिस्ट पार्टी का घोषणापत्र]]
[[hr:Komunistički manifest]]
[[id:Manifesto Komunis]]
[[is:Kommúnistaávarpið]]
[[it:Manifesto del Partito Comunista]]
[[he:המניפסט הקומוניסטי]]
[[kk:Коммунистік партияның манифесі]]
[[ku:Manîfestoya Komunîstî]]
[[lad:Manifiesto komunista]]
[[la:Praeconium Communisticum]]
[[lv:Komunistiskās partijas manifests]]
[[hu:Kommunista kiáltvány]]
[[mk:Комунистички манифест]]
[[ml:കമ്മ്യൂണിസ്റ്റ് മാനിഫെസ്റ്റോ]]
[[mr:साम्यवादी जाहीरनामा]]
[[arz:المانيفيستو الشيوعى]]
[[ms:Manifesto Komunis]]
[[nl:Manifest van de Communistische Partij]]
[[new:द कम्युनिस्ट म्यानिफेस्टो]]
[[ja:共産党宣言]]
[[no:Det kommunistiske manifest]]
[[nn:Det kommunistiske manifestet]]
[[uz:Kommunistik partiya manifesti]]
[[pa:ਕਮਿਉਨਿਸਟ ਪਾਰਟੀ ਦਾ ਮੈਨੀਫੈਸਟੋ]]
[[pl:Manifest komunistyczny]]
[[pt:Manifesto Comunista]]
[[ro:Manifestul comunist]]
[[ru:Манифест коммунистической партии]]
[[sco:Communist Manifesto]]
[[sq:Manifesti Komunist]]
[[scn:Manifestu dû Partitu Cumunista]]
[[simple:The Communist Manifesto]]
[[sk:Manifest komunistickej strany]]
[[sl:Komunistični manifest]]
[[sr:Комунистички манифест]]
[[sh:Manifest Komunističke partije]]
[[fi:Kommunistinen manifesti]]
[[sv:Kommunistiska manifestet]]
[[tl:Manipestong Komunista]]
[[ta:பொதுவுடமை அறிக்கை]]
[[th:แถลงการณ์พรรคคอมมิวนิสต์]]
[[tr:Komünist Manifesto]]
[[uk:Маніфест комуністичної партії]]
[[vi:Tuyên ngôn của Đảng Cộng sản]]
[[yo:Manifẹ́stò Kómúnístì]]
[[zh-yue:共產黨宣言]]
[[zh:共产党宣言]]</text>
      <sha1>ra141pwzd96ifxv8t2367rhqfec4s48</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
