<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Three Principles of the People</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>123510</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521959799</id>
      <parentid>521903732</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-08T07:24:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Benlisquare</username>
        <id>262194</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[Help:Reverting|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/67.174.152.96|67.174.152.96]] ([[User talk:67.174.152.96|talk]]) to last version by Mendsetting</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="19119">{{Chinese
|t=三民主義
|s=三民主义
|j=saam&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; man&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt; zyu&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; ji&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;
|p=Sān Mín Zhǔyì
|w=San-min Chu-i
|bpmf=ㄙㄢ ㄇㄧㄣˊ ㄓㄨˇ ㄧˋ
|xej=صً مٍ ﺟُﻮْ ىِ
|poj=Sam-bîn Chú-gī
|wuu=sae&lt;sup&gt;平&lt;/sup&gt; min&lt;sup&gt;平&lt;/sup&gt; tsy&lt;sup&gt;上&lt;/sup&gt; nyi&lt;sup&gt;去&lt;/sup&gt;
|h=sam&lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt; min&lt;sup&gt;11&lt;/sup&gt; zu&lt;sup&gt;31&lt;/sup&gt; ngi&lt;sup&gt;55&lt;/sup&gt;
|pic=Sunyatsen1.jpg
|piccap=[[Sun Yat-sen]], who developed the Three Principles of the People
}}
{{contains Chinese text}}
The '''Three Principles of the People''', also translated as '''Three People's Principles''', or collectively '''San-min Doctrine''', is a [[political philosophy]] developed by [[Sun Yat-sen]] as part of a philosophy to make [[China]] a free, prosperous, and powerful nation. Its legacy of implementation is most apparent in the governmental organization of the [[Republic of China]] (ROC), which currently administers [[Taiwan]], [[Penghu]], [[Quemoy]], and [[Matsu Islands]]. This philosophy has been claimed as the cornerstone of the Republic of China's policy as carried by the [[Kuomintang]] (KMT). The principles also appear in the first line of the [[National Anthem of the Republic of China]]. The three principles are often translated and summarized as nationalism, democracy, and the livelihood of the people.

==Origins==
[[File:The organ of Tongmen Hui.png|thumb|right|300px|The concept first appearing in the Min Bao newspaper in 1905 appearing as &quot;Three Big Principles&quot; (三大主義) instead of &quot;Three Principles of the People&quot; (三民主義)]]
In 1894 when the [[Revive China Society]] was formed, Sun only had two principles: nationalism and democracy.  He did not pick up the third idea, welfare, until his three years trip to [[Europe]] (1896-1898).&lt;ref name=&quot;Li&quot;&gt;Li Chien-Nung. Li Jiannong. Teng, Ssu-yu. Ingalls, Jeremy. [1956] (1956). The political history of China, 1840-1928. Stanford University Press. ISBN 0-8047-0602-6, ISBN 978-0-8047-0602-5. pg 203-206.&lt;/ref&gt;  He did not announce these ideas until spring of 1905 when he was in Europe again.  Sun was in [[Brussels]], and made the first speech of his life on the &quot;Three Principles of the People&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharman&quot;&gt;{{Cite book  | last1 = Sharman| first1 = Lyon| title = Sun Yat-sen: His life and its meaning, a critical biography | year = 1968 | publisher = Stanford University Press | location = Stanford| page = 94, 271 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  In many cities he was able to organize the Revive China Society.  There were about 30 members in the branch at the time in Brussels, and 20 in [[Berlin]], 10 in [[Paris]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharman&quot; /&gt;  After the [[Tongmenghui]] was formed, Sun published an editorial in Min Bao (民報).&lt;ref name=&quot;Li&quot; /&gt;  This was the first time the ideas were expressed.  Later on, in the anniversary issue of Min Bao, his long speech of the Three Principles were printed, and the editors of the newspaper discussed the problem of people's livelihood.&lt;ref name=&quot;Li&quot; /&gt;

The ideology is said to be heavily influenced by Sun's experiences in the [[United States]] and contains elements of the American progressive movement and the thought championed by [[Abraham Lincoln]].  Sun credited a line from Lincoln's [[Gettysburg Address]], &quot;government of the people, by the people, for the people,&quot; as an inspiration for the Three Principles. &lt;ref name=&quot;Sharman&quot; /&gt;

==Enumeration==
===Mínzú===
The Principle of Mínzú (民族主義, Mínzú Zhǔyì) is commonly rendered as &quot;[[nationalism]]&quot;, literally &quot;Populism&quot; or &quot;the People's rule/government&quot;, &quot;Mínzú/People&quot; clearly describing a nation rather than a group of persons united by a purpose, hence the commonly used and rather accurate translation &quot;nationalism&quot;. By this, Sun meant freedom from imperialist domination. To achieve this he believed that China must develop a &quot;China-nationalism,&quot; ''[[Zhonghua Minzu]]'', as opposed to an &quot;ethnic-nationalism,&quot; so as to unite all of the different ethnicities of China, mainly composed by the [[Five Races Under One Union|five major groups]] of [[Han Chinese|Han]], [[Mongols]], [[Tibetans]], [[Manchus]], and the [[Muslims]] (such as the [[Uyghurs]]), which together are symbolized by the [[Five Color Flag]] of the First Republic (1911–1928). This sense of nationalism is different from the idea of &quot;ethnocentrism,&quot; which equates to the same meaning of nationalism in Chinese language. To achieve this he believed that China must develop a &quot;national consciousness&quot; so as to unite the Han in the face of imperialist aggression. He argued that &quot;minzu&quot;, which can be translated as &quot;people&quot;, &quot;nationality&quot; or &quot;race&quot;, were defined by sharing common blood, livelihood, religion, language and customs.

===Mínquán===
The Principle of Mínquán (民權主義, Mínquán Zhǔyì) is usually translated as &quot;[[democracy]]&quot;; literally &quot;the People's power&quot; or &quot;government by the People.&quot; To Sun, it represented a Western constitutional government. He divided political life of his ideal for China into two sets of 'powers': the power of politics and the power of governance.

The power of politics (政權, zhèngquán) are the powers of the people to express their political wishes, similar to those vested in the citizenry or the parliaments in other countries, and is represented by the [[National Assembly of the Republic of China|National Assembly]]. There are four of these powers: election (選舉), [[recall election|recall]] (罷免), [[initiative]] (創制), and [[referendum]] (複決). These may be equated to &quot;[[civil rights]]&quot;.

The power of governance (治權, zhìquán) are the powers of administration. Here he expanded the European-American constitutional theory of a [[Three powers of the State|three-branch government]] and a system of [[checks and balances]] by incorporating traditional Chinese administrative tradition to create a government of five branches (each of which is called a Yuan (院, yuàn, literally &quot;court&quot;). The [[Legislative Yuan]], the [[Executive Yuan]], and the [[Judicial Yuan]] came from [[Charles de Secondat, Baron de Montesquieu|Montesquieu]]an thought; the [[Control Yuan]] and the [[Examination Yuan]] came from Chinese tradition. (Note that the Legislative Yuan was first intended as a branch of governance, not strictly equivalent to a national parliament.)

===Mínshēng===
{{main|Chinese socialism}}The Principle of Mínshēng (民生主義, Mínshēng Zhǔyì) is sometimes translated as &quot;the People's welfare/livelihood,&quot; &quot;Government for the People&quot;. The concept may be understood as [[social welfare]] and as a direct criticism of the inadequacies of both socialism and capitalism. Here he was influenced by the American thinker [[Henry George]] (see [[Georgism]]); the [[land value tax]] in Taiwan is a legacy thereof. He divided livelihood into four areas: food, clothing, housing, and transportation; and planned out how an ideal (Chinese) government can take care of these for its people. Sun died before he was able to fully explain his vision of this Principle and it has been the subject of much debate within both the Chinese Nationalist and Communist Parties, with the latter suggesting that Sun supported socialism.

==Canon==
The most definite (canonical) exposition of these principles was a book compiled from notes of speeches Sun gave near [[Guangzhou]] (taken by a colleague, [[Huang Changgu]], in consultation with Sun), and therefore is open to interpretation by various parties and interest groups (see below) and may not have been as fully explicated as Sun might have wished. Indeed, [[Chiang Kai-shek]] supplied an annex to the Principle of Mínshēng, covering two additional areas of livelihood: education and leisure, and explicitly arguing that Mínshēng was not to be seen as either supporting [[communism]] or [[socialism]].
The French historian of Chinese history, Marie-Claire Bergère's view is that the book is a work of propaganda.  Its purpose is to appeal to action rather than to thought.  As Sun Yat-sen declared, a principle is not simply an idea; it is &quot;a faith, a power.&quot;  &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book  | last1 = Bergère | first1 = Marie-Claire (translated by Janet Lloyd) | title = Sun Yat-sen | year = 1994 | publisher = Stanford University Press | location = Stanford | isbn = 0-8047-3170-5 | page = 353 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
[[Image:Dscf0207.jpg|thumb|Right|250px|A propaganda sign on [[Quemoy]] facing [[Mainland China]] proclaiming &quot;Three Principles of the People Unites China&quot;]]
The Three Principles of the People were claimed as the basis for the ideologies of the Kuomintang under [[Chiang Kai-shek]], of the [[Communist Party of China]] under [[Mao Zedong]], and of the [[Wang Jingwei Government]]. The Kuomintang and the Communist Party of China largely agreed on the meaning of [[nationalism]] but differed sharply on the meaning of democracy and people's welfare, which the former saw in Western social democratic terms and the latter interpreted in Marxist and communist terms. The Japanese collaborationist governments interpreted nationalism less in terms of anti-imperialism and more in terms of cooperating with Japan to advance pan-Asian interests.

There were several [[higher education|higher-education]] institutes (university departments/faculties and [[graduate school|graduate institute]]s) in Taiwan that used to devote themselves to the 'research and development' of the Three Principles in this aspect. Since the late 1990s, these institutes have re-oriented themselves so that other political theories are also admitted as worthy of consideration, and have changed their names to be more ideologically neutral (such as Democratic Studies Institute).

In addition to this institutional phenomenon, many streets and businesses in Taiwan are named &quot;Sān-mín&quot; or for one of the three principles. In contrast to other controversial street names, there has been no major renaming of these streets or institutions in the 1990s.

Although the term &quot;Sanmin Zhuyi&quot; (三民主義) has been less explicitly invoked since the mid-1980s, no major political party has explicitly attacked its principles. The Three Principles of the People remains explicitly part of the platform of the Kuomintang and in the [[Constitution of the Republic of China]].

As for [[Taiwan independence]] supporters, some have objections regarding the formal constitutional commitment to a particular set of political principles. Also, they have been against the mandatory indoctrination in schools and universities, which have now been abolished in a piecemeal fashion beginning in the late 1990s. However, there is little fundamental hostility to the substantive principles themselves. In these circles, attitudes toward the Three Principles of the People span the spectrum from indifference to reinterpreting the Three Principles of the People [[Taiwanese localization movement|in a local Taiwanese context]] rather than in a pan-Chinese one.

The Vietnam Revolutionary League was a union of various Vietnamese nationalist groups, run by the pro-Chinese [[Viet Nam Quoc Dan Dang]]. The Viet Nam Quoc Dan Dang translates directly into Vietnamese Kuomintang, and it was based on the Chinese Kuomintang party. Its stated goal was for unity with China under the Three Principles of the People, and opposition to Japanese and French Imperialists.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=SSxyTlkmv2cC&amp;pg=PA81&amp;dq=Chang+Fa-Kuei+vnqdd#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|title=The endless war: Vietnam's struggle for independence|author=James P. Harrison|year=1989|publisher=Columbia University Press|location=|page=81|isbn=0-231-06909-X|pages=|accessdate=2010-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=uEDfAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=Chang+Fa-Kuei+vnqdd&amp;dq=Chang+Fa-Kuei+vnqdd|title=The History of the Joint Chiefs of Staff: History of the Indochina incident, 1940-1954|author=United States. Joint Chiefs of Staff. Historical Division|year=1982|publisher=Michael Glazier|location=|page=56|isbn=|pages=|accessdate=2010-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Revolutionary League was controlled by [[Nguyen Hai Than]], who was born in China and could not speak Vietnamese. General Zhang shrewdly blocked the Communists of Vietnam, and [[Ho Chi Minh]] from entering the league, as his main goal was Chinese influence in Indo China.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=9RorGHF0fGIC&amp;pg=PA106&amp;dq=Chang+Fa-Kuei+vnqdd#v=onepage&amp;q=Chang%20Fa-Kuei%20vnqdd&amp;f=false|title=The last emperors of Vietnam: from Tu Duc to Bao Dai|author=Oscar Chapuis|year=2000|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|location=|page=106|isbn=0-313-31170-6|pages=|accessdate=2010-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; The KMT utilized these Vietnamese nationalists during World War II against Japanese forces.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=HKRuAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=Chang+Fa-Kuei+vnqdd&amp;dq=Chang+Fa-Kuei+vnqdd|title=The rise of nationalism in Vietnam, 1900-1941|author=William J. Duiker|year=1976|publisher=Cornell University Press|location=|page=272|isbn=0-8014-0951-9|pages=|accessdate=2010-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The pro-Kuomintang and pro-ROC [[Khamba]] revolutionary leader [[Pandatsang Rapga]], who established the [[Tibet Improvement Party]], adopted Dr. Sun's ideology including the Three Principles, incorporating them into his party and using Sun's doctrine as a model for his vision of Tibet after achieving his goal of overthrowing the Tibetan government.

[[Pandatsang Rapga]] hailed the Three Principles of Dr. Sun for helping Asian peoples against foreign imperialism and called for the feudal system to be overthrown. Rapga stated that &quot;The Sanmin Zhuyi was intended for all peoples under the domination of foreigners, for all those who had been deprived of the rights of man. But it was conceived especially for the Asians. It is for this reason that I translated it. At that time, a lot of new ideas were spreading in Tibet&quot;, during an interview in 1975 by Dr. Heather Stoddard.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|accessdate=12-27-2011|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=KlOEi9C4T3QC&amp;pg=PA152&amp;dq=The+attempt+to+apply+SunYat-sen's+ideology+in+a+Tibetan+context+failed+precisely+because+those+who+supported+this+activity+were+not+at+the+center+of+elite+Tibetan+religious+culture.+Revolutionary+Tibetans+realized+and+were+often+frustrated+by+this+problem.100+In+a+sense+they+were+trying+to+change+Tibet+from+the+outside,+through+secular+means+.+Despite+this+failure,+from+Stoddard's+interviews,+we+learn+that+even+in+1975+Rapga+still+held+to+his+beliefs+that+Sun's+theories+were+valuable:+The+San+min+zhuyi+was+intended+for+all+peoples+under+the+domination+of+foreigners,+for+all+those+who+had+been+deprived+of+the+rights+of+man.+But+it+was+conceived+especially+for+the+Asians.+It+is+for+this+reason+that+I+translated+it.+At+that+time,+a+lot+of+new+ideas+were+spreading+in+Tibet.%22%22+If+the+Panchen+Lama+had+been+willing+to+personally+and+publicly+support+these+early+efforts+at+seeking+local+Tibetan+autonomy+(in+particular+among+Chinese+Buddhists+and+the+media+that+followed+his+ritual+activities),+might+the+movement&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=NLn7Tu38JefV0QHe_PjAAg&amp;ved=0CDEQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=The%20attempt%20to%20apply%20SunYat-sen's%20ideology%20in%20a%20Tibetan%20context%20failed%20precisely%20because%20those%20who%20supported%20this%20activity%20were%20not%20at%20the%20center%20of%20elite%20Tibetan%20religious%20culture.%20Revolutionary%20Tibetans%20realized%20and%20were%20often%20frustrated%20by%20this%20problem.100%20In%20a%20sense%20they%20were%20trying%20to%20change%20Tibet%20from%20the%20outside%2C%20through%20secular%20means%20.%20Despite%20this%20failure%2C%20from%20Stoddard's%20interviews%2C%20we%20learn%20that%20even%20in%201975%20Rapga%20still%20held%20to%20his%20beliefs%20that%20Sun's%20theories%20were%20valuable%3A%20The%20San%20min%20zhuyi%20was%20intended%20for%20all%20peoples%20under%20the%20domination%20of%20foreigners%2C%20for%20all%20those%20who%20had%20been%20deprived%20of%20the%20rights%20of%20man.%20But%20it%20was%20conceived%20especially%20for%20the%20Asians.%20It%20is%20for%20this%20rea|title=Tibetan Buddhists in the Making of Modern China|author=Gray Tuttle|editor=|year=2007|publisher=Columbia University Press|edition=illustrated|location=|volume=|page=152|isbn=0-231-13447-9|pages=|}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dr. Sun's ideology was put into a Tibetan translation by Rapga.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|accessdate=12-27-2011|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Upwq0I-wm7YC&amp;pg=PA450&amp;dq=rapga+chinese&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=WI_FTdqrJoiugQeJxvnKBA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ved=0CD4Q6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q=rapga%20chinese&amp;f=false|title=A history of modern Tibet, 1913-1951: the demise of the Lamaist state|author=Melvyn C. Goldstein|editor=|year=1991|publisher=University of California Press|edition=reprint, illustrated|location=|volume=Volume 1 of A History of Modern Tibet|page=450|isbn=0-520-07590-0|pages=|}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;!--{{zh|t=西藏自治共和國|p=Xīzàng zìzhì gònghéguó}}) --&gt;

He believed that change in Tibet would only be possible in a manner similar to when the [[Qing Dynasty]] was overthrown in China. He borrowed the theories and ideas of the Kuomintang as the basis for his model for Tibet. The party was funded by the Kuomintang&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|accessdate=12-27-2011|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=rsLQdBUgyMUC&amp;pg=PA95&amp;dq=shen+in+Chongqing+to+render+clandestine+support+to+pro-Nationalist+underground+forces+led+by+a+Khampa+Tibetan&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=D8XFTbbFLofq0gHc1KzwBw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCoQ6AEwAA#v=snippet&amp;q=rapga%20appealed%20khampa%20militia%20against%20tibetan%20troops&amp;f=false|title=Modern China's ethnic frontiers: a journey to the west|author=Hsiao-ting Lin|editor=|year=2010|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|edition=illustrated|location=|volume=Volume 67 of Routledge studies in the modern history of Asia|page=95||isbn=0-415-58264-4|pages=|}}&lt;/ref&gt; and by the Pandatsang family.

==See also==
* [[Chiang Kai-shek]]
* [[National Revolutionary Army]]
* [[Whampoa Military Academy]]
* [[History of the Republic of China]]
* [[Politics of the Republic of China]]
* [[Republic of China]]
* [[Kuomintang]]
* [[Pancasila (politics)]]

==Bibliography==
* [[Sun Yat-sen]], translated by Pasquale d'Elia.''The Triple Demism of Sun Yat-Sen''.  New York: AMS Press, Inc., 1974.

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}
{{Sun Yat-sen}}
{{Politics of the Republic of China}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Three Principles Of The People}}
[[Category:Chinese numbered policies]]
[[Category:Government of the Republic of China]]
[[Category:Books in political philosophy]]
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Social philosophy]]
[[Category:Politics of the Republic of China]]
[[Category:Xinhai Revolution]]

[[de:Drei Prinzipien des Volkes]]
[[es:Tres Principios del Pueblo]]
[[fr:Trois principes du peuple]]
[[ko:삼민주의]]
[[id:Tiga Prinsip Rakyat]]
[[he:שלושת העקרונות של העם]]
[[nl:Drie principes van het volk]]
[[ja:三民主義]]
[[no:Folkets tre prinsipper]]
[[ru:Три народных принципа]]
[[fi:Kansan kolme periaatetta]]
[[th:หลัก 3 ประการแห่งประชาชน]]
[[vi:Chủ nghĩa Tam dân]]
[[zh:三民主義]]</text>
      <sha1>gywhy9rs9ax0thrq3q7m8b91n0xhh1y</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
