<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Thucydides</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>30864</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520461954</id>
      <parentid>520461939</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-29T18:10:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contributions/64.127.64.178|64.127.64.178]] to version by O.Koslowski. False positive? [[User:ClueBot NG/FalsePositives|Report it]]. Thanks, [[User:ClueBot NG|ClueBot NG]]. (1302255) (Bot)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="42521">{{Other uses}}
[[File:Thucydides-bust-cutout ROM.jpg|thumb|200px|Bust of Thucydides residing in the [[Royal Ontario Museum]], [[Toronto]]]]

'''Thucydides''' ({{IPAc-en|θj|u:|ˈ|s|ɪ|d|ɪ-|d|i:|z}}; [[Ancient Greek|Greek]]: Θουκυδίδης, ''Thoukydídēs''; [[Circa|c.]] 460 – c. 395 BC) was a [[Greeks|Greek]] [[history|historian]] and author from [[Alimos]]. His ''[[History of the Peloponnesian War]]'' recounts [[Peloponnesian war|the 5th century BC war]] between [[Sparta]] and [[Athens]] to the year 411 BC. Thucydides has been dubbed the father of &quot;scientific history&quot;, because of his strict standards of evidence-gathering and analysis in terms of cause and effect without reference to intervention by the gods, as outlined in his introduction to his work.&lt;ref&gt;Cochrane, p. 179; Meyer, p. 67; de Sainte Croix.&lt;/ref&gt;

He has also been called the father of the school of [[political realism]], which views the relations between nations as based on might rather than right.&lt;ref&gt;Strauss, p. 139.&lt;/ref&gt;  His  text is still studied at advanced military colleges worldwide, and the [[Melian dialogue]] remains a seminal work of [[international relations theory]].

More generally, Thucydides showed an interest in developing an understanding of human nature to explain behaviour in such crises as [[Plague (disease)|plague]], [[List of events named massacres|massacres]], as in that of the [[Melian dialogue|Melians]], and [[civil war]].

==Life==
In spite of his stature as a historian, modern historians know relatively little about Thucydides' life. The most reliable information comes from his own ''[[History of the Peloponnesian War]]'', which expounds his nationality, paternity and native locality. Thucydides informs us that he fought in the war, contracted the plague and was exiled by the [[Athenian democracy|democracy]]. He may have also been involved in quelling the [[Samian Revolt]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Thucydides|en|1|117|ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Evidence from the Classical Period===
Thucydides identifies himself as an [[Athenian]], telling us that his father's name was [[Olorus]] and that he was from the Athenian [[deme]] of [[Alimos|Halimous]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Thucydides|en|4|104|shortref}}&lt;/ref&gt; He survived the [[Plague of Athens]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Thucydides|en|2|48|1|3|shortref}}&lt;/ref&gt; that killed [[Pericles]] and many other Athenians. He also records that he owned [[gold mine]]s at [[Scapte Hyle]] (literally: &quot;Dug Woodland&quot;), a coastal area in [[Thrace]], opposite the island of [[Thasos]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Thucydides|en|4|105|1|shortref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Amphipolis Cousinery.jpg|left|thumb|The ruins of Amphipolis as envisaged by E. Cousinéry in 1831: the bridge over the Strymon, the city fortifications, and the acropolis]]
Because of his influence in the Thracian region, Thucydides wrote, he was sent as a [[strategos]] (general) to [[Thasos]] in 424 BC. During the winter of 424-423 BC, the Spartan general [[Brasidas]] attacked [[Amphipolis]], a half-day's sail west from Thasos on the Thracian coast, instigating the [[Battle of Amphipolis]]. Eucles, the Athenian commander at Amphipolis, sent to Thucydides for help.&lt;ref&gt;{{Thucydides|en|4|104|1|shortref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Brasidas, aware of Thucydides' presence on Thasos and his influence with the people of Amphipolis, and afraid of help arriving by sea, acted quickly to offer moderate terms to the Amphipolitans for their surrender, which they accepted. Thus, when Thucydides arrived, Amphipolis was already under Spartan control.&lt;ref&gt;{{Thucydides|en|4|105|shortref}}&amp;ndash;106.3&lt;/ref&gt;

Amphipolis was of considerable strategic importance, and news of its fall caused great consternation in Athens.&lt;ref&gt;{{Thucydides|en|4|108|1|7|shortref}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was blamed on Thucydides, although he claimed that it was not his fault and that he had simply been unable to reach it in time. Because of his failure to save Amphipolis, he was sent into [[exile]]:&lt;ref&gt;{{Thucydides|en|5|26|5|shortref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{cquote|I lived through the whole of it, being of an age to comprehend events, and giving my attention to them in order to know the exact truth about them. It was also my fate to be an exile from my country for twenty years after my command at [[Amphipolis]]; and being present with both parties, and more especially with the Peloponnesians by reason of my exile, I had leisure to observe affairs somewhat particularly.}}

Using his status as an exile from Athens to travel freely among the Peloponnesian allies, he was able to view the war from the perspective of both sides. During this time, he conducted important research for his history, having claimed that he pursued the project as he thought it would be one of the greatest wars waged among the Greeks in terms of scale.[[File:AGMA Hérodote.jpg|thumb|Purported bust of [[Herodotus]]]]
This is all that Thucydides wrote about his own life, but a few other facts are available from reliable contemporary sources. [[Herodotus]] wrote that Thucydides' father's name, [[Olorus|''Όloros'']], was connected with [[Thrace]] and Thracian royalty.&lt;ref&gt;{{Herodotus|en|6|39|1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thucydides was probably connected through family to the Athenian statesman and general [[Miltiades the Younger|Miltiades]], and his son [[Cimon]], leaders of the old [[aristocracy]] supplanted by the Radical [[democracy|Democrats]]. [[Cimon]]'s maternal grandfather's name was also [[Olorus]], making the connection exceedingly likely. Another [[Thucydides (politician)|Thucydides]] lived before the historian and was also linked with Thrace, making a family connection between them very likely as well. Finally, [[Herodotus]] confirms the connection of Thucydides' family with the mines at Scapté Hýlē.&lt;ref&gt;{{Herodotus|en|6|46|1|ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Combining all the fragmentary evidence available, it seems that his family had owned a large estate in [[Thrace]], one that even contained gold mines, and which allowed the family considerable and lasting affluence. The security and continued prosperity of the wealthy estate must have necessitated formal ties with local kings or chieftains, which explains the adoption of the distinctly Thracian royal name &quot;''Όloros''&quot; into the family. Once exiled, Thucydides took permanent residence in the estate and, given his ample income from the gold mines, he was able to dedicate himself to full-time history writing and research, including many fact-finding trips. In essence, he was a retired and well-connected gentleman of considerable resources who, by then retired from the political and military spheres, decided to fund his own historical project.

===Later sources===
The remaining evidence for Thucydides' life comes from rather less reliable later ancient sources. According to [[Pausanias (geographer)|Pausanias]], someone named Oenobius was able to get a law passed allowing Thucydides to return to Athens, presumably sometime shortly after the city's surrender and the end of the war in 404 BC.&lt;ref&gt;Pausanias, [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?lookup=Paus.+1.23.9 1.23.9].&lt;/ref&gt; Pausanias goes on to say that Thucydides was murdered on his way back to Athens. Many doubt this account, seeing evidence to suggest he lived as late as 397 BC. [[Plutarch]] claims that his remains were returned to Athens and placed in [[Cimon]]'s family vault.&lt;ref&gt;Plutarch, [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?lookup=Plut.+Cim.+4.1 Cimon 4.1].&lt;/ref&gt;

The abrupt end to Thucydides' narrative, which breaks off in the middle of the year 411 BC, has traditionally been interpreted as indicating that he died while writing the book, although other explanations have been put forward.

[[File:112307-BritishMuseum-Perikles.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Pericles]]
Inferences about Thucydides' character can only be drawn (with due caution) from his book.  His sardonic sense of humour is evident throughout, as when, during his description of the [[Athenian plague]], he remarks that old Athenians seemed to remember a rhyme which said that with the Dorian War would come a &quot;great death&quot;.  Some claimed that the rhyme was actually about a &quot;great dearth&quot; (''limos''), and was only remembered as &quot;death&quot; (''loimos'') due to the current plague.  Thucydides then remarks that should another Dorian War come, this time attended with a great dearth, the rhyme will be remembered as &quot;dearth,&quot; and any mention of &quot;death&quot; forgotten.&lt;ref&gt;{{Thucydides|en|2|54|3|shortref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Thucydides admired [[Pericles]], approving of his power over the people and showing a marked distaste for the [[demagogue]]s who followed him. He did not approve of the democratic mob nor the radical democracy that Pericles ushered in but considered democracy acceptable when guided by a good leader.&lt;ref&gt;{{Thucydides|en|2|65|1|shortref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thucydides' presentation of events is generally even-handed; for example, he does not minimize the negative effect of his own failure at [[Battle of Amphipolis|Amphipolis]]. Occasionally, however, strong passions break through, as in his scathing appraisals of the demagogues [[Cleon]];&lt;ref&gt;{{Thucydides|en|3|36|6|shortref}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Thucydides|en|4|27|shortref}}, {{Thucydides|en|5|16|1}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Hyperbolus]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Thucydides|en|8|73|3|shortref}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cleon]] has sometimes been connected with Thucydides' exile.&lt;ref&gt;Marcellinus, ''Life of Thucydides'' 46&lt;/ref&gt;

That Thucydides was clearly moved by the suffering inherent in war and concerned about the excesses to which human nature is prone in such circumstances is evident in his analysis of the atrocities committed during civil conflict on [[Corcyra]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Thucydides|en|3|82|shortref}}&amp;ndash;83&lt;/ref&gt; which includes the phrase &quot;War is a violent teacher&quot;.

===The History of the Peloponnesian War===
{{Main|History of the Peloponnesian War}}
[[File:Acropolis from south-west.jpg|thumb|The Acropolis in Athens]]
[[File:Sparta ruins.PNG|thumb|Ruins at Sparta]]
After his death, Thucydides' history was subdivided into eight books: its modern title is the ''[[History of the Peloponnesian War]]''. His great contribution to history and [[historiography]] is contained in this one dense history of the [[Peloponnesian War|27-year war]] between [[Athens]] and [[Sparta]], each with their respective allies. The history breaks off near the end of the 21st year; the last sketchy book suggests that his death was unexpected. Thucydides believed that the Peloponnesian War represented an event of unmatched magnitude.&lt;ref&gt;{{Thucydides|en|1|1|1|shortref}}&lt;/ref&gt; His intention was to write an account of the events of the late fifth century which would serve as &quot;a possession for all time&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Thucydides|en|1|22|4|shortref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Thucydides is generally regarded as one of the first true historians. Like his predecessor [[Herodotus]], known as &quot;the father of history&quot;, Thucydides places a high value on [[eyewitness testimony]] and writes about events in which he himself probably took part. He also assiduously consulted written documents and interviewed participants about the events that he recorded. Unlike Herodotus, whose stories often teach that a foolish arrogance—[[hubris]]—invites the wrath of the gods, Thucydides does not acknowledge divine intervention in human affairs.

A noteworthy difference between Thucydides' method of writing history and that of modern historians is Thucydides' inclusion of lengthy formal speeches that, as he himself states, were literary reconstructions rather than actual quotations of what was said &amp;mdash; or, perhaps, what he believed ''ought'' to have been said. Arguably, had he not done this, the gist of what was said would not otherwise be known at all &amp;mdash; whereas today there is a plethora of documentation &amp;mdash; written records, archives and recording technology for historians to consult. Therefore Thucydides' method served to ''rescue'' his mostly oral sources from oblivion. We do not know how these historical figures actually spoke. Thucydides' recreation uses a heroic stylistic register. A celebrated example is [[Pericles' funeral oration]], which heaps honour on the dead and includes a defence of democracy:
{{cquote|The whole earth is the sepulchre of famous men; they are honoured not only by columns and inscriptions in their own land, but in foreign nations on memorials graven not on stone but in the hearts and minds of men.}}

Stylistically, the placement of this passage also serves to heighten the contrast with the description of the plague in [[Athens]] immediately following it, which graphically emphasizes the horror of human mortality, thereby conveying a powerful sense of verisimilitude:
{{cquote|Though many lay unburied, birds and beasts would not touch them, or died after tasting them [...]. The bodies of dying men lay one upon another, and half-dead creatures reeled about the streets and gathered round all the fountains in their longing for water.  The sacred places also in which they had quartered themselves were full of corpses of persons who had died there, just as they were; for, as the disaster passed all bounds, men, not knowing what was to become of them, became equally contemptuous of the gods' property and the gods' dues.  All the burial rites before in use were entirely upset, and they buried the bodies as best they could.  Many from want of the proper appliances, through so many of their friends having died already, had recourse to the most shameless sepultures: sometimes getting the start of those who had raised a pile, they threw their own dead body upon the stranger's pyre and ignited it; sometimes they tossed the corpse which they were carrying on the top of another that was burning, and so went off.}}

Thucydides omits discussion of the arts, literature or the social milieu in which the events in his book take place and in which he himself grew up. He saw himself as recording an event, not a period, and went to considerable lengths to exclude what he deemed frivolous or extraneous. 
[[Image:Thucydides pushkin01.jpg|thumb|left|upright|alt=A bust of Thucydides.|Thucydides; cast of a renowned bust at [[Holkham Hall]] ([[Pushkin Museum]])]]

==Critical interpretation==

Scholars traditionally view Thucydides as recognizing and teaching the lesson that democracies need leadership, but that leadership can be dangerous to democracy. [[Leo Strauss]]  (in ''The City and Man'') locates the problem in the nature of Athenian democracy itself, about which, he argued, Thucydides had a deeply ambivalent view: on one hand, Thucydides' own &quot;wisdom was made possible&quot; by the Periclean democracy, which had the effect of liberating individual daring, enterprise and questioning spirit, but this same liberation, by permitting the growth of limitless political ambition, led to imperialism and, eventually, civic strife.&lt;ref&gt;Russett, p. 45.&lt;/ref&gt;

For Canadian historian [[Charles Norris Cochrane]] (1889&amp;ndash;1945), Thucydides' fastidious devotion to observable phenomena, focus on cause and effect, and strict exclusion of other factors anticipates twentieth century scientific positivism. Cochrane, the son of a physician, speculated that Thucydides generally (and especially in describing the plague in Athens) was influenced by the methods and thinking of early medical writers such as [[Hippocrates]] of [[Kos]].&lt;ref&gt;Charles Norris Cochrane, ''Thucydides and the Science of Medicine'' (1929).&lt;/ref&gt;

After World War II, [[Classical literature|Classical]] scholar [[Jacqueline de Romilly]] pointed out that the problem of Athenian [[imperialism]] was one of Thucydides' central preoccupations and situated his history in the context of Greek thinking about international politics. Since the appearance of her study, other scholars further examined Thucydides' treatment of ''[[realpolitik]]''.

More recently, scholars have questioned the perception of Thucydides as simply &quot;the father of realpolitik&quot;. Instead they have brought to the fore the literary qualities of the ''History'', which they see as belonging to narrative tradition of Homer and Hesiod and as concerned with the concepts of justice and suffering found in Plato and Aristotle and problematized in Aeschylus and Sophocles.&lt;ref&gt;Clifford Orwin, ''The Humanity of Thucydides'', Princeton, 1994.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Richard Ned Lebow]] terms Thucydides &quot;the last of the tragedians&quot;, stating that &quot;Thucydides drew heavily on epic poetry and tragedy to construct his history, which not surprisingly is also constructed as a narrative.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Richard Ned Lebow, ''The Tragic vision of Politics'' (Cambridge University Press, 2003), p. 20.&lt;/ref&gt; In this view, the blind and immoderate behaviour of the Athenians (and indeed of all the other actors), though perhaps intrinsic to human nature, ultimately leads to their downfall. Thus his ''History'' could serve as a warning to future leaders to be more prudent, by putting them on notice that someone would be scrutinizing their actions with a historian's objectivity rather than a chronicler's flattery.&lt;ref&gt;See also Walter Robert Connor, ''Thucydides'' (Princeton University Press, 1987).&lt;/ref&gt;

Finally, the question has recently been raised as to whether Thucydides was not greatly, if not fundamentally, concerned with the matter of religion. Contrary to Herodotus, who portrays the gods as active agents in human affairs, Thucydides attributes the existence of the divine entirely to the needs of political life. The gods are seen as existing only in the minds of men. Religion as such reveals itself in the ''History'' to be not simply one type of social behaviour among others, but what permeates the whole of social existence, permitting the emergence of justice.&lt;ref&gt;Benjamin Patrick Newton, &quot;Thucydidean Answers to Nietzschean Questions: What is Religious?&quot;, ''Polis: The Journal of the Society for Greek Political Thought'' (2010) 27/1: 111-133.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Thucydides versus Herodotus==
[[File:Herodot und Thukydides.jpg|thumb|left|Herodotus and Thucydides]]
Thucydides and his immediate predecessor [[Herodotus]] both exerted a significant influence on Western historiography. Thucydides does not mention his counterpart by name, but his famous introductory statement is thought to refer to him:&lt;ref&gt;Lucian, How to write history, p. 42&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Thucydides I,22&lt;/ref&gt;
{{cquote|To hear this history rehearsed, for that there be inserted in it no fables, shall be perhaps not delightful. But he that desires to look into the truth of things done, and which (according to the condition of humanity) may be done again, or at least their like, shall find enough herein to make him think it profitable. And it is compiled rather for an everlasting possession than to be rehearsed for a prize.}}

Herodotus records in his ''[[Histories (Herodotus)|Histories]]'' not only the events of the [[Persian Wars]] but also geographical and ethnographical information, as well as the fables related to him during his extensive travels. Typically, he passes no definitive judgment on what he has heard. In the case of conflicting or unlikely accounts, he presents both sides, says what he believes and then invites readers to decide for themselves.&lt;ref&gt;Momigliano, pp. 39, 40.&lt;/ref&gt; The work of Herodotus is reported to have been recited at festivals, where prizes were awarded, as for example, during the games at [[Olympia, Greece|Olympia]].&lt;ref&gt;Lucian: ''Herodotus'', pp. 1-2.&lt;/ref&gt;

Herodotus views history as a source of moral lessons, with conflicts and wars as misfortunes flowing from initial acts of injustice perpetuated through cycles of revenge.&lt;ref&gt;Ryszard Kapuscinski: ''Travels with Herodotus'', p. 78.&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast, Thucydides claims to confine himself to factual reports of contemporary political and military events, based on unambiguous, first-hand, eye-witness accounts,&lt;ref&gt;Thucydides I, 23&lt;/ref&gt; although, unlike Herodotus, he does not reveal his sources. Thucydides views life exclusively as ''political'' life, and history in terms of ''political'' history. Conventional moral considerations play no role in his analysis of political events while geographic and [[ethnography|ethnographic]] aspects are omitted or, at best, of secondary importance. Subsequent Greek historians &amp;mdash; such as [[Ctesias]], [[Diodorus]], [[Strabo]], [[Polybius]] and [[Plutarch]] &amp;mdash; held up Thucydides' writings as a model of truthful history. [[Lucian]]&lt;ref&gt;Lucian, p. 25, 41.&lt;/ref&gt; refers to Thucydides as having given Greek historians their ''law'', requiring them to say ''what had been done'' ({{lang|grc|ὡς ἐπράχθη}}). Greek historians of the fourth century BC accepted that history was political and that contemporary history was the proper domain of a historian.&lt;ref&gt;Momigliano, Ch. 2, IV.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cicero]] calls Herodotus the &quot;father of history;&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Cicero, ''Laws'' 1.5.&lt;/ref&gt; yet the Greek writer Plutarch, in his [[Moralia]] (Ethics) denigrated Herodotus, as the &quot;father of lies&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Plutarch, ''On the Malignity of Herodotus'', ''[[Moralia]]'' XI (''Loeb Classical Library 426'').&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike Thucydides, however, these historians all continued to view history as a source of moral lessons.
[[File:Thomas Hobbes (portrait).jpg|thumb|[[Thomas Hobbes]]]]

Due to the loss of the ability to read Greek, Thucydides and Herodotus were largely forgotten during the [[Middle Ages]] in Western Europe, although their influence continued in the Byzantine world. In Europe, Herodotus become known and highly respected only in the late-sixteenth and early-seventeenth century as an ethnographer, in part due to the discovery of [[United States|America]], where customs and animals were encountered even more surprising than what he had related. During the [[Protestant Reformation|Reformation]], moreover, information about Middle Eastern countries in the ''Histories'' provided a basis for establishing [[Bible|Biblical]] chronology as advocated by [[Isaac Newton]].

The first European translation of Thucydides (into Latin) was made by the humanist [[Lorenzo Valla]] between 1448 and 1452, and the first Greek edition was published by Aldo Manunzio in 1502. During the [[Renaissance]], however, Thucydides attracted less interest among Western European historians as a political philosopher than his successor, [[Polybius]],&lt;ref&gt;Momigliano Chapter 2, V.&lt;/ref&gt; although [[Poggio Bracciolini]] claimed to have been influenced by him. There is not much trace of Thucydides' influence in [[Niccolò Machiavelli]]'s  ''[[Il Principe|The Prince]]'' (1513), which held that the chief aim of a new prince must be to &quot;maintain his state&quot; [i.e., his power] and that in so doing he is often compelled to act against faith, humanity and religion. Later historians, such as [[J. B. Bury]], however, have noted parallels between them:&lt;blockquote&gt;If, instead of a history, Thucydides had written an analytical treatise on politics, with particular reference to the Athenian empire, it is probable that  . . . he could have forestalled Machiavelli. . . .[since] the whole innuendo of the Thucydidean treatment of history agrees with the fundamental postulate of Machiavelli, the supremacy of [[national interest|reason of state]]. To maintain a state said the Florentine thinker, &quot;a statesman is often compelled to act against faith, humanity and religion.&quot;  . . . But . . . the true Machiavelli, not the Machiavelli of fable. . . entertained an ideal: Italy for the Italians, Italy freed from the stranger: and in the service of this ideal he desired to see his speculative science of politics applied. Thucydides has no political aim in view: he was purely a historian. But it was part of the method of both alike to eliminate conventional sentiment and morality.&lt;ref&gt;[[J. B. Bury]], ''The Ancient Greek Historians'' (London, MacMillan, 1909), pp. 140-143.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;In the seventeenth century, the [[England|English]] political philosopher [[Thomas Hobbes]], whose ''[[Leviathan (book)|Leviathan]]'' advocated absolute monarchy, admired Thucydides and in 1628 was the first to translate his writings into English directly from Greek. Thucydides, Hobbes and Machiavelli are together considered the founding fathers of [[political realism]], according to which state policy must primarily or solely focus on the need to maintain military and economic [[Power in international relations|power]] rather than on ideals or ethics.

Nineteenth-century [[positivist]] historians stressed what they saw as Thucydides' seriousness, his scientific objectivity and his advanced handling of evidence. A virtual [[cult following]] developed among such [[Germany|German]] philosophers as [[Friedrich Schelling]], [[Karl Wilhelm Friedrich Schlegel|Friedrich Schlegel]] and [[Friedrich Nietzsche]], who claimed that, &quot;[in Thucydides], the portrayer of man, that culture of the most impartial knowledge of the world finds its last glorious flower.&quot; For [[Eduard Meyer]], [[Thomas Babington Macaulay, 1st Baron Macaulay|Macaulay]] and [[Leopold von Ranke]], who initiated  modern source-based history writing,&lt;ref&gt;See Anthony Grafton, ''The Footnote, a Curious History'' (Cambridge Mass: Harvard University Press, 1999)&lt;/ref&gt; Thucydides was again the model historian.&lt;ref&gt;Momigliano, p. 50.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;For his part, Peter Green notes of these historians, the fact &quot;That [Thucydides] was exiled for military incompetence, did a hatchet job on the man responsible and praised as virtually unbeatable the Spartan general to whom he had lost the key city of Amphipolis bothered them not at all.&quot; Peter Green (2008) cit.&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt;Generals and statesmen loved him: the world he drew was theirs, an exclusive power-brokers' club. It is no accident that even today Thucydides turns up as a guiding spirit in military academies, neocon think tanks and the writings of men like Henry Kissinger; whereas Herodotus has been the choice of imaginative novelists (Michael Ondaatje's novel ''The English Patient'' and the film based on it boosted the sale of the Histories to a wholly unforeseen degree) and — as food for a starved soul — of an equally imaginative foreign correspondent from Iron Curtain Poland, Ryszard Kapuscinski.&lt;ref&gt;(Green 2008, op cit)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

These historians also admired Herodotus, however, as social and ethnographic history increasingly came to be recognized as complementary to political history.&lt;ref&gt;Momigliano, pg.52.&lt;/ref&gt; In the twentieth century, this trend gave rise to the works of [[Johan Huizinga]], [[Marc Bloch]] and [[Braudel]], who pioneered the study of long-term cultural and economic developments and the patterns of everyday life. The [[Annales School]], which exemplifies this direction, has been viewed as extending the tradition of Herodotus.&lt;ref&gt;Stuart Clark (ed.): ''The Annales school: critical assessments'', Vol. II, 1999.&lt;/ref&gt;

At the same time, Thucydides' influence was increasingly important in the area of [[international relations]] during the Cold War, through the work of [[Hans Morgenthau]], [[Leo Strauss]]&lt;ref&gt;See essay on Thucydides in ''The Rebirth of Classical Political Rationalism: An Introduction to the Thought of Leo Strauss – Essays and Lectures by Leo Strauss'', edited by Thomas L. Pangle ([[Chicago]]: [[University of Chicago Press]], 1989).&lt;/ref&gt; and [[E. H. Carr|Edward Carr]].&lt;ref&gt;See, for example, E.H. Carr's [[The Twenty Years' Crisis]].&lt;/ref&gt;

The tension between the Thucydidean and Herodotean traditions extends beyond historical research. According to [[Irving Kristol]], self-described founder of American [[Neoconservatism]], Thucydides wrote &quot;the favorite neoconservative text on foreign affairs&quot;;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.weeklystandard.com/Content/Public/Articles/000/000/003/000tzmlw.asp &quot;The Neoconservative Persuasion&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; and Thucydides is a required text at the [[Naval War College]], an American institution located in Rhode Island. On the other hand, Daniel Mendelsohn, in a review of a recent edition of Herodotus, suggests that, at least in his graduate school days during the Cold War, professing admiration of Thucydides served as a form of self-presentation:
&lt;blockquote&gt;To be an admirer of Thucydides' History, with its deep cynicism about political, rhetorical and ideological hypocrisy, with its all too recognizable protagonists &amp;mdash; a liberal yet imperialistic democracy and an authoritarian oligarchy, engaged in a war of attrition fought by proxy at the remote fringes of empire &amp;mdash; was to advertise yourself as a hardheaded connoisseur of global Realpolitik.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Arms and the Man: What was Herodotus trying to tell us?&quot; (''[[The New Yorker]]'', April 28, 2008)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Another author, [[Thomas Geoghegan]], whose speciality is labour rights, comes down on the side of Herodotus when it comes to drawing lessons relevant to Americans, who, he notes, tend to be rather isolationist in their habits (if not in their political theorizing): &quot;We should also spend more funds to get our young people out of the library where they're reading Thucydides and get them to start living like Herodotus &amp;mdash; going out and seeing the world.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.prospect.org/cs/articles?articleId=12547  The American Prospect]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Thucydides in popular culture==
In 1991, the [[BBC]] broadcast a new version of [[John Barton (director)|John Barton's]] 'The War that Never Ends', which had first been performed on stage in the 1960s. This adapts Thucydides' text, together with short sections from [[Plato]]'s dialogues.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0103235/ Listing at Internet Movie Database]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Quotes==
* &quot;But, the bravest are surely those who have the clearest vision of what is before them, glory and danger alike, and yet notwithstanding, go out to meet it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Thucydides|en|2|40|3|shortref}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* &quot;Right, as the world goes, is only in question between equals in power, while the strong do what they can and the weak suffer what they must.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Thucydides|en|5|89|shortref}}&lt;/ref&gt; — This quote is part of the [[Melian dialogue]] (Strassler 352/5.89).
* &quot;It is a general rule of human nature that people despise those who treat them well, and look up to those who make no concessions.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Thucydides|en|3|39|5|shortref}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* &quot;In peace and prosperity states and individuals have better sentiments, because they do not find themselves suddenly confronted with imperious necessities; but war takes away the easy supply of daily wants and so proves a rough master that brings most men's characters to a level with their fortunes&quot; (Strassler 199/3.82.2).
* &quot;War takes away the easy supply of daily wants, and so proves a rough master, that brings most men's characters to a level with their fortunes.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Thucydides|en|3|82|2|shortref}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* &quot;The cause of all these evils was the lust for power arising from greed and ambition; and from these passions proceeded the violence of parties once engaged in contention.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Thucydides|en|3|82|8|shortref}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* &quot;So that, though overcome by three of the greatest things, honour, fear and profit, we have both accepted the dominion delivered us and refuse again to surrender it, we have therein done nothing to be wondered at nor beside the manner of men.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Thucydides|en|1|76|shortref}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* &quot;Indeed men too often take upon themselves in the prosecution of their revenge to set the example of doing away with those general laws to which all can look for salvation in adversity, instead of allowing them to subsist against the day of danger when their aid may be required&quot; (Strassler 201/3.84.3).
* &quot;It is the habit of mankind to entrust to careless hope what they long for, and to use sovereign reason to thrust aside what they do not desire&quot; (Strassler 282/4.108.4).

A quotation frequently attributed to Thucydides on the Internet, but which is in fact spurious (ref needed), is:
* &quot;The State that separates its scholars from its warriors will have its thinking done by cowards and its fighting by fools.&quot;

==Quotations about Thucydides==
&lt;blockquote&gt;

And after [the time of Herodotus], Thucydides, in my opinion, easily vanquished all in the artfulness of his style: he so concentrates his copious material that he almost matches the number of his words with the number of his thoughts. In his words, further, he is so apposite and compressed that you do not know whether his matter is being illuminated by his diction or his words by his thoughts. ([[Cicero]],[http://web.gc.cuny.edu/Classics/gk701/8crit.htm ''De Oratore'' 2.56 (55 B.C.)])

&lt;/blockquote&gt;In the preface to his 1628 translation of Thucydides, entitled, ''Eight Bookes of the Peloponesian Warres'', political philosopher [[Thomas Hobbes]] calls Thucydides &lt;blockquote&gt; &quot;the most politic historiographer that ever writ.&quot;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

A hundred years later, philosopher [[David Hume]], wrote that:
 &lt;blockquote&gt;[T]he first page of Thucydides is, in my opinion, the commencement of real history. All preceding narrations are so intermixed with fable, that philosophers ought to abandon them to the embellishments of poets and orators. (&quot;Of the Populousness of Ancient Nations&quot;, 1742)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[Friedrich Nietzsche]] wrote that the best antidotes for Platonism were to be found in Thucydides:
 &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;My recreation, my predilection, my cure, after all Platonism, has always been Thucydides. Thucydides and perhaps Machiavelli's ''principe'' are most closely related to me owing to the absolute determination which they show of refusing to deceive themselves and of seeing reason in ''reality''-- not in &quot;rationality,&quot; and still less in &quot;morality.&quot; There is no more radical cure than Thucydides for the lamentably rose-coloured idealisation of the Greeks... His writings must be carefully studied line by line, and his unuttered thoughts must be read as distinctly as what he actually says. There are few thinkers so rich in unuttered thoughts... Thucydides is the great summing up, the final manifestation of that strong, severe positivism which lay in the instincts of the ancient Hellene. After all, it is courage in the face of reality that distinguishes such natures as Thucydides from Plato: Plato is a coward in the face of reality-- consequently he takes refuge in the ideal: Thucydides is a master of himself-- consequently he is able to master life.&quot; (A Nietzsche Compendium, [[Twilight of the Idols]], trans. Anthony M. Ludovici)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[W. H. Auden]]'s poem, [http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=7519773 &quot;September 1, 1939&quot;], written at the start of [[World War II]], contains these lines:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;poem&gt;
''Exiled Thucydides knew
''All that a speech can say
''About Democracy,
''And what dictators do,
''The elderly rubbish they talk
''To an apathetic grave;
''Analysed all in his book,
''The enlightenment driven away,
''The habit-forming pain,
''Mismanagement and grief:
''We must suffer them all again.''&lt;/poem&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==See also==
* [[Melian dialogue]]
* [[Pericles' Funeral Oration]]
* [[Speech of Hermocrates at Gela]]
; Manuscripts
* [[Papyrus Oxyrhynchus 16]]
* [[Papyrus Oxyrhynchus 17]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|3}}

==References and further reading==
{{Wikisourcelang|el|Θουκυδίδης|Thucydides in Greek}}

===Primary sources===
*[[Herodotus]], [[The Histories of Herodotus|''Histories'']], [[A. D. Godley]] (translator), Cambridge: Harvard University Press (1920). ISBN 0-674-99133-8 [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?lookup=Hdt.+toc &amp;nbsp;].
*[[Pausanias (geographer)|Pausanias]], ''Description of Greece'', Books I-II, ([[Loeb Classical Library]]) translated by W. H. S. Jones; Cambridge, Massachusetts: Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann Ltd. (1918). ISBN 0-674-99104-4.[http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?lookup=Paus.+1.1.1 &amp;nbsp;].
* [[Plutarch]], [[Parallel Lives|''Lives'']], Bernadotte Perrin (translator), Cambridge, MA. Harvard University Press. London. William Heinemann Ltd. (1914). ISBN 0-674-99053-6 [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0182;query=toc;layout=;loc=Cim.%201.1 &amp;nbsp;].
*''The Landmark Thucydides'', Edited by Robert B. Strassler, [[Richard Crawley]] translation, Annotated, Indexed and Illustrated, A Touchstone Book, New York, NY, 1996 ISBN 0-684-82815-4
* Thucydides, ''The Peloponnesian War''. London, J. M. Dent; New York, E. P. Dutton (1910).[http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?lookup=Thuc.+toc &amp;nbsp;].  The classic translation by Richard Crawley.
* Thucydides, ''The Peloponnesian War.'' Indianapolis, Hackett (1998);  translation by Steven Lattimore.  ISBN 9870872203945 {{Please check ISBN|reason=Check digit (5) does not correspond to calculated figure.}} {{Please check ISBN|reason=13 digit ISBN should start with  978 or 979.}}.

===Secondary sources===
*[[Charles Norris Cochrane|Cochrane, Charles Norris]], Thucydides and the Science of History, Oxford University Press (1929).
*Connor, W. Robert, ''Thucydides''. Princeton: Princeton University Press (1984). ISBN 0-691-03569-5
* Dewald, Carolyn. ''Thucydides' War Narrative: A Structural Study''. Berkeley, CA: University of California Press, 2006 (hardcover, ISBN 0-520-24127-4).
* Finley, John Huston, Jr., ''Thucydides'', Cambridge, Massachusetts : Harvard University Press, 1947.
* Forde, Steven, ''The ambition to rule : Alcibiades and the politics of imperialism in Thucydides''. Ithaca : Cornell University Press (1989). ISBN 0-8014-2138-1.
* Hanson, Victor Davis, ''A War Like No Other: How the Athenians and Spartans Fought the Peloponnesian War''. New York: Random House (2005). ISBN 1-4000-6095-8.
* Hornblower, Simon, ''A Commentary on Thucydides''. 2 vols. Oxford: Clarendon (1991–1996). ISBN 0-19-815099-7 (vol. 1), ISBN 0-19-927625-0 (vol. 2).
* Hornblower, Simon, ''Thucydides''. London: Duckworth (1987). ISBN 0-7156-2156-4.
* [[Donald Kagan|Kagan, Donald]]. (2003). ''The Peloponnesian War''. New York: Viking Press. ISBN 0-670-03211-5.
* Luce, T.J., ''The Greek Historians''. London: Routledge (1997). ISBN 0-415-10593-5.
* Luginbill, R.D., ''Thucydides on War and National Character''. Boulder: Westview (1999). ISBN 0-8133-3644-9.
* [[Arnaldo Momigliano|Momigliano, Arnaldo]], ''The Classical Foundations of Modern Historiography''. Sather Classical Lectures, 54 Berkeley: University of California Press (1990).
* Meyer, Eduard, [[Kleine Schriften]] (1910), (Zur Theorie und Methodik der Geschichte).
* [[Clifford Orwin|Orwin, Clifford]], ''The Humanity of Thucydides''. Princeton: Princeton University Press (1994). ISBN 0-691-03449-4.
* Podoksik, Efraim. &quot;Justice, Power, and Athenian Imperialism: An Ideological Moment in Thucydides’ History&quot;, ''[[History of Political Thought (journal)|History of Political Thought]]''. 26(1): 21-42, 2005.
* Romilly, Jacqueline de, ''Thucydides and Athenian Imperialism''. Oxford: Basil Blackwell (1963). ISBN 0-88143-072-2.
* Rood, Tim, ''Thucydides: Narrative and Explanation''. Oxford: Oxford University Press (1998). ISBN 0-19-927585-8.
* {{cite book | author=Russett, Bruce | title=Grasping the Democratic Peace | publisher=Princeton University Press | year=1993 | isbn=0-691-03346-3 }}
* de Sainte Croix. ''The origins of the Peloponesian War'' (1972). London: Duckworth. 1972. Pp. xii, 444.
* Strassler, Robert B, ed. ''The Landmark Thucydides: A Comprehensive Guide to the Peloponnesian War''. New York: Free Press (1996). ISBN 0-684-82815-4.
* [[Strauss, Leo]], ''The City and Man'' Chicago: Rand McNally, 1964.

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
{{Sister project links|s=Author:Thucydides}}
*{{gutenberg author| id=Thucydides | name=Thucydides}}
*[http://www-rci.rutgers.edu/~edmunds/thuc.html Short Bibliography on Thucydides] Lowell Edmunds, [[Rutgers University]]
*[http://archive.org/details/LeoStraussSeminarOnThucydides1962 Leo Strauss' 1962 Seminar] course transcript on Thucydides.
*[[Perseus Project]] [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0200;layout=;query=toc;loc=1.1.1 Thucydides, Table of Contents]
*[http://oll.libertyfund.org/Intros/Thucydides.php Thomas Hobbes' Translation of Thucydides]
*[http://lycurgus.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=category&amp;id=3&amp;Itemid=7 Thucydides on Lycurgus.org]

{{Ancient Greece topics}}

{{Authority control|LCCN=n/79/021175}}

&lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
{{Persondata
|NAME=Thucydides
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=Θουκυδίδης; Thoukudídēs
|SHORT DESCRIPTION=Greek historian
|DATE OF BIRTH=between 460 and 455 BC
|PLACE OF BIRTH=Alimos, Greece
|DATE OF DEATH=ca. 400 BC or 395 BC
|PLACE OF DEATH=
}}
[[Category:460 BC births]]
[[Category:395 BC deaths]]
[[Category:Ancient Athenian generals]]
[[Category:Ancient Athenian historians]]
[[Category:Classical-era Greek historians]]
[[Category:Ancient Thracian Greeks]]
[[Category:Ancient Greek merchants]]
[[Category:People of the Peloponnesian War]]
[[Category:5th-century BC Greek people]]
[[Category:4th-century BC Greek people]]
[[Category:5th-century BC historians]]
[[Category:Philosophers of science]]
[[Category:Ancient Greek agnostics]]
[[Category:Ostracized Athenians]]
[[Category:Attic Greek writers]]
[[Category:Political realists]]

{{Link GA|de}}

[[af:Thukydides]]
[[am:ቶኪዳይደስ]]
[[ar:ثوسيديديس]]
[[an:Tucidides]]
[[ast:Tucídides]]
[[be:Фукідыд]]
[[bg:Тукидид]]
[[br:Thoukydides]]
[[ca:Tucídides]]
[[cs:Thúkýdidés]]
[[cy:Thucydides]]
[[da:Thukydid]]
[[de:Thukydides]]
[[et:Thukydides]]
[[el:Θουκυδίδης]]
[[es:Tucídides]]
[[eo:Tucidido]]
[[eu:Tuzidides]]
[[fa:توکودیدس]]
[[fr:Thucydide]]
[[ga:Thucydides]]
[[gl:Tucídides]]
[[ko:투키디데스]]
[[hy:Փուկիտիդես]]
[[hr:Tukidid]]
[[io:Thukydides]]
[[id:Thukidides]]
[[ia:Thucydides]]
[[is:Þúkýdídes]]
[[it:Tucidide]]
[[he:תוקידידס]]
[[ka:თუკიდიდე]]
[[kk:Фукидид]]
[[la:Thucydides]]
[[lv:Tukidīds]]
[[lb:Thukydides (Historiker)]]
[[lt:Tukididas]]
[[hu:Thuküdidész]]
[[mk:Тукидид]]
[[ml:തുസ്സിഡിഡീസ്]]
[[xmf:თუკიდიდე]]
[[nl:Thucydides (historicus)]]
[[ja:トゥキディデス]]
[[no:Thukydid]]
[[nn:Thukydides]]
[[oc:Tucidides]]
[[pnb:تھیوسائیڈیسس]]
[[pms:Tucìdide]]
[[pl:Tukidydes]]
[[pt:Tucídides]]
[[ro:Tucidide]]
[[ru:Фукидид]]
[[sq:Thukididi]]
[[scn:Tucìdidi]]
[[simple:Thucydides]]
[[sk:Thoukydides]]
[[sl:Tukidid]]
[[sr:Тукидид]]
[[sh:Tukidid]]
[[fi:Thukydides]]
[[sv:Thukydides]]
[[tl:Thoukydidis]]
[[th:ธูซิดดิดีส]]
[[tr:Tukididis]]
[[uk:Фукідід]]
[[ur:تھوسی ڈائڈز]]
[[vi:Thucydides]]
[[yo:Thucydides]]
[[diq:Tukidid]]
[[zh:修昔底德]]</text>
      <sha1>s9os9vl7vedmlzhs9aqckc1p8f5obq2</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
