<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Tree sitting</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>315811</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520772980</id>
      <parentid>514967371</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-31T17:21:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Geni</username>
        <id>55582</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* List of tree sits */ rm POV update</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26243">{{Refimprove|date=March 2011}}
[[Image:Protester climbing to treeSit in upper florentine valley.jpg|thumb|right|Protester climbing to a tree sit 35m high in [[Upper Florentine Valley]], in Tasmania, Australia.]]

'''Tree sitting''' is a form of [[environmentalism|environmentalist]] [[civil disobedience]] in which a [[protest]]er sits in a [[tree]], usually on a small platform built for the purpose, to protect it from being cut down (speculating that [[logging|loggers]] will not endanger human lives by cutting an occupied tree). Supporters usually provide the tree sitters with food and other supplies.

Tree sitters have successfully prevented [[logging]] of ancient [[old-growth forest]]s for months at a time, and in some instances have convinced logging companies not to cut trees in some areas.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}} Sometimes, tree sitting is used as a long-term resistance strategy, with activists occupying trees for months or years at a time. On the other hand, tree sitting is often used as a stalling tactic, to prevent the cutting of trees while [[lawyer]]s fight in the courts to secure the long-term victories.

When tree sitting occurs on private land, it is considered by some to be an act of [[trespassing]]. Some activists stand up to this charge in court, claiming a [[necessity]] defense – that the harm done by trespassing is negligible compared to the potential harm to the environment caused by the proposed logging. Sometimes logging companies will hire tree climbers to remove trespassers sitting in trees.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}} Although it's argued that it is the companies' legal right to do so, some tree sitters {{Who|date=September 2008}} are suing Pacific Lumber to challenge this practice. Most tree sitting in [[California]] occurs on private land{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}. In [[Oregon]], where there are more logging projects on [[public land]] ([[United States National Forest|National Forests]] and [[United States Bureau of Land Management|BLM]] lands), tree sitting is usually not trespassing but tree sitters can be fined for violating [[closure order]]s or camping limits, or for erecting illegal structures.

==Extractions==
Tree-sitters in trees claimed by Pacific Lumber in Humboldt County have been subject to forced removal by hired [[tree-sit extractors]].  The practice started with a single extractor in the late 90’s but in 2003 Pacific Lumber hired teams of climbers to remove dozens of tree-sitters, particularly in the Freshwater area East of Eureka, California.

The extractors are not actually deputized but police often show up to assist extractors and arrest tree-sitters.  On March 17, 2003, more than 30 police arrived{{Where|date=July 2011}} and enforced the closure of a public road to assist in the removal of two long-time tree-sitters from old-growth redwoods.{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}}

Most of the extractions in Northern California are done under the leadership of Eric Schatz of Schatz Tree Service, a well known professional [[arborist]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Walters|first=Heidi|title=Eric Schatz: Tree-trimmer? Monster? Gentleman? Fall guy?|url=http://www.northcoastjournal.com/042006/cover0420.html|accessdate=13 December 2011|newspaper=North Coast Journal|date=20 April 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Schatz testified in court that he has removed 42 tree sitters from trees.{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}}

==List of tree sits==

[[Image:Berkeley Oak Grove Tree-sitter Camp.jpg|thumb|right|The tree-sitters' camp in Berkeley, California protesting the planned removal of coastal live oaks as of 2008-07-08. The protesters were in the trees from 2006-12-02 to 2008-09-09, making it the longest running urban tree-sit in history.&lt;ref name=&quot;DC Supplies Removed Again&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;grandmothers&quot;/&gt;]]
Some of the more notable tree sittings include:
*Tree sitting in 1978 (the first tree sitting action) led to the protection of what is now the [[Pureora Forest Park]] in New Zealand.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Copyright NZ Native Forests Restoration Trust |url=http://www.nznfrt.org.nz/index.php?page_id=111 |title=NZ Native Forests Restoration Trust :: Our history |publisher=Nznfrt.org.nz |date= |accessdate=2009-11-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*Mikal Jakubal was the first American tree sitter.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}} On May 20, 1985 he ascended a [[Douglas Fir]] in an area of the Middle Santiam region of [[Willamette National Forest]] that was in the process of being clearcut. While short-lived, his tree sitting action inspired a group tree sitting event by [[Earth First!]] activists that lasted from June 23 to July 20, 1985, when two [[Linn County, Oregon]] sheriff's deputies wrestled Marylander Ron Huber from his tree after a day-long stand-off.

*[[Native Forest Action]] used tree sitting during its campaign to save the [[West Coast, New Zealand]] native forests.  In April 1997, the logging company, [[Timberlands West Coast Limited]] destroyed one of the sites by deliberately swinging a tree from a helicopter into it without ensuring that it was fully clear of protesters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.prwatch.org/prwissues/2000Q1/helicopt.html |title=When Helicopters Attack: A Near Accident Leads To Coverup &amp;#124; Center for Media and Democracy |publisher=Prwatch.org |date= |accessdate=2009-11-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The CAA cleared the helicopter pilot of wrongdoing in a controversial judgment that was appeared to have been interfered with, according to [[Secrets and Lies (Hager)|leaked internal documents]].

*[[Julia Butterfly Hill]], an activist in [[Humboldt County, California]] became known for her 738 day sit (from December 10, 1997 until December 18, 1999) in a {{convert|180|ft|m|sing=on}}, 600-year-old [[Coast Redwood]] tree she named ''Luna''. Eventually, Hill and other activists raised $50,000 to spare her tree and a {{convert|200|ft|m|sing=on}} buffer around it.

*In 2002, two US environmental activists involved in tree-sitting protests died in separate accidents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.portlandtribune.com/archview.cgi?id=18908 |title=A new fight for old growth |publisher=Portlandtribune.com |date= |accessdate=2009-11-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.santacruzsentinel.com/archive/2002/October/11/local/stories/01local.htm ]{{dead link|date=November 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*In 2004, activists from [[Greenpeace]] and the [[Australia]]n environmental organization [[The Wilderness Society (Australia)|The Wilderness Society]] hold the record for the world's highest tree-sit at 65m, in the [[Styx Valley]], [[Tasmania]]. Peter (Peck) Firth spent 51 days up a giant Eucalyptus tree nicknamed [[Gandalf's Staff]].&lt;ref&gt;Still Wild Still Threatened - Styx Valley (2011) http://www.stillwildstillthreatened.org/styx/styx-valley&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Greenpeace - Styx Valley Global Rescue Station (2011) http://weblog.greenpeace.org/tasmania/&lt;/ref&gt;

*In 2004, at least six tree sits were erected in Tuart trees at Ludlow Tuart Forest near Busselton in South Western, Western Australia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://perth.indymedia.org/?action=default&amp;featureview=89 |title=Perth Independent Media Centre |publisher=Perth.indymedia.org |date=2009-09-10 |accessdate=2009-11-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*In 2006, two sits were built in Jarrah (Eucalyptus) trees at &quot;Arcadia&quot; Jarrah Forest near Collie in South Western, Western Australia.  Two activists were removed and arrested but one had his charges dropped and the other went to court and was acquitted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://perth.indymedia.org/?action=default&amp;featureview=423 |title=Perth Independent Media Centre |publisher=Perth.indymedia.org |date= |accessdate=2009-11-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*In 2006, following a successful protest lasting over one year, tree sitters in [[Cathedral Grove]] (also known as [[MacMillan Provincial Park]]), British Columbia, halted the removal of a number of old growth [[Douglas Fir]] trees which were scheduled to be to taken down in an attempt to calm traffic and improve the parking facilities.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}

*In May 2006, protesters at [[Titnore Wood]] began a tree-sitting campaign against a major urban extension to the town of [[Worthing]] in West Sussex.  Around 25 protesters created tree-houses and a network of tunnels.  In March 2010, after nearly four years of tree-sitting, the local council voted unanimously to turn down the application for development.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC-plans rejected&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/sussex/8570425.stm|title=Plans for homes next to Worthing's Titnore Woods voted down|date=16 March 2010|publisher=BBC News|accessdate=17 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;


*In 2006, 2007, and 2008, protesters in [[Berkeley, California]] [[Berkeley oak grove controversy#Tree-sit|sat in coast live oak trees]] to prevent the construction of a new sports facility by the [[University of California, Berkeley]].  On September 5, 2008, the University began logging the grove, after winning court agreement.  Four days later, after a little more than 21 months, the final four tree sitters surrendered to authorities, ending the longest running urban tree-sit in history.&lt;ref name=&quot;DC Supplies Removed Again&quot;&gt;{{Cite news | last =Trott | first =Ashley | publication-date =19 June 2008 | title =Tree-Sitters' Supplies Removed From Oaks by University-Hired Arborists | periodical =[[The Daily Californian]]| publication-place =[[Berkeley, California]] | place =[[Berkeley, California]] | publisher =Independent Berkeley Students Publishing Company, Inc. | url =http://archive.dailycal.org/article/101931/tree-sitters_supplies_removed_from_oaks_by_univers | accessdate =13 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;grandmothers&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Taylor |first=Matthew |url=http://www.berkeleydailyplanet.com/issue/2007-11-27/article/28556?status=3 |title=Reader Report: Grandmothers Break Oak Grove Siege |publisher=The Berkeley Daily Planet |date=27 November 2007 |accessdate=13 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Bulwa|first=Demian|title=Tree-sitters act to save oaks at stadium site|url=http://articles.sfgate.com/2006-12-04/bay-area/17324020_1_third-tree-berkeley-law-balancing-act|accessdate=13 December 2011|newspaper=San Francisco Chronicle|date=4 December 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 2007, protesters of the [[University of California Santa Cruz]]'s Long Range Development Plan set up a tree sit, in red wood trees, on the proposed site of a biomedical research facility.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}

* In 2008, a tree-sitter climbed an oak tree on the [[University of California Berkeley]] campus to begin advocating the democratization of the UC Regents.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}

*  In 2000 after two years living in Mariah, a thousand-year-old tree, Nate Madsen descended. Both Pacific Lumber (PL) and the California Department of Forestry (CDF) signed off on the timber harvest plan, which means protection for Mariah for the moment. PL can still file another plan, but for now, Mariah seems safe. http://www.treesfoundation.org/publications/article-49

*In 2008, a tree sit was constructed in College Grove (remnant bushland), Bunbury, Western Australia and was removed after being occupied for three months.  Another was promptly constructed nearby in the next stage that was threatened by housing development; it included a functional trampoline.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=by Jerome |url=http://perth.indymedia.org/?action=newswire&amp;parentview=122628 |title=Perth Independent Media Centre |publisher=Perth.indymedia.org |date= |accessdate=2009-11-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*In 2009, there are ongoing tree-sits in Humboldt County, Ca. to prevent logging of 100+ year old redwoods by Green Diamond (formerly known as Simpson). One of the tree-villages is defending the territory of an active Spotted Owl mating pair.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://efhumboldt.org |title=Earth First! Humboldt |publisher=Efhumboldt.org |date= |accessdate=2009-11-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*In 2009, on August 25 two protesters with [[Climate Ground Zero]] halted blasting above Pettry Bottom in Raleigh County, West Virginia. Laura Steepleton and Nick Stocks climbed 80 feet in two trees in direct protest of [[Massey Energy]]'s [[mountaintop removal mine]]. The trees were located within 30 feet of the Edwight mine, and within the 300 feet of blasting. Kim Ellis and Zoe Beavers were arrested for providing direct support, only to return later that afternoon at the behest of state police to serve as liaisons for the sitters. Kim Ellis and Zoe Beavers were then asked to leave the site at 5:30pm by mine security only to refuse and get arrested again by state police at 7:30pm. The tree sit halted blasting for six days while facing harassment from miners including threats of rape, trees being felled in close proximity, and chainsaws partially cutting the trees the sitters occupied.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=West Virginia Tree Sitters Halt Mountaintop Removal Blasting|url=http://www.ens-newswire.com/ens/aug2009/2009-08-28-091.html|accessdate=30 January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Treesit stopping blasts in West Virginia|url=http://www.demotix.com/news/treesit-stopping-blasts-west-virginia|publisher=Demotix|accessdate=30 January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Suggs|first=Charles|title=Treesitters descend, threatened with chainsaw, $50,000 bail|url=http://climategroundzero.net/2009/08/pettry-chainsaw/|publisher=Climate Ground Zero|accessdate=30 January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*In 2009, environmental activists from the [http://www.stillwildstillthreatened.org/ Still Wild Still Threatened] group in [[Tasmania]], [[Australia]] were forced down from tree sits in the [[Upper Florentine Valley]] by police acting in conjunction with [[Forestry Tasmania]] in two separate busts in January and May.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stillwildstillthreatened.org/camp-florentine/about-camp |title=Camp Florentine: About Camp |publisher=Still Wild Still Threatened |accessdate=13 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*In 2010, on January 20 three protesters associated with [[Climate Ground Zero]] and [[Mountain Justice]] halted blasting on a portion of [[Massey Energy]]'s Bee Tree [[mountaintop removal mine]] on Coal River Mountain, West Virginia by ascending three trees, two [[tulip poplars]] and an oak tree. David Aaron Smith, 23 Amber Nitchman, 19 and Eric Blevins, 28 were on platforms approximately 60 feet up in direct protest of mountaintop removal mining and blasting near the Brushy Fork Impoundment. Joshua Graupera, Isabelle Rozendaal, Bernard Fiorillo and David Baghdadi were also arrested for providing ground support. The tree sit halted blasting for nine days. A federal judge granted a permanent injunction to Marfork Coal Co. Inc., a subsidiary of Massey Energy, ordering the defendants to keep off all company property.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Guttata|first=Clem|title=Tree Sit Halts the Blasting on Coal River Mountain (YES, AGAIN)|url=http://www.wvablue.com/diary/5490/tree-sit-halts-the-blasting-on-coal-river-mountain-yes-again|publisher=West Virginia Blue|accessdate=30 January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Lannom|first=Andrea|title=Marfork Coal Co. Granted Permanent Injunction|url=http://66.118.80.206/story.cfm?func=viewstory&amp;storyid=101446|publisher=WBOY Channel 12|accessdate=30 January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=MARFORK COAL COMPANY, Plaintiff, v. CIVIL ACTION NO.  5:10-cv-00069 DAVID AARON SMITH, et al., Defendant|url=http://docs.justia.com/cases/federal/district-courts/west-virginia/wvsdce/5:2010cv00069/64422/44/0.pdf|publisher=IN THE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT FOR THE SOUTHERN DISTRICT OF WEST VIRGINIA BECKLEY DIVISION|accessdate=30 January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*In 2010, One of the tree-villages in Humboldt County,Ca. remains and has grown to include over 30 trees that are tied together with tyrolean traverses. Though Earth First! Humboldt will not say exactly how many people or sits are up there, they do say there is a crew of tree-dwellers. The Earth First!ers withdrew from the village bordering the suburbs in order to strengthen their defense of the older and more secluded of the two groves where many more wildlife species find habitat and refuge.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}

* In 2011, on July 20 two protesters associated with the RAMPS Campaign halted blasting on a portion of [[Alpha Natural Resources]] Bee Tree mountaintop removal mine on Coal River Mountain, West Virginia by ascending two trees, a [[tulip poplar]] and an northern red oak tree.  Catherine-Ann MacDougal, 24, and Becks Kolins, 21, were on platforms approximately 80 feet off the ground within 300 feet of active blasting on the mine in direct protest of [[mountaintop removal]] mining. Becks Kolins stayed on their platform for 14 days while Catherine-Ann MacDougal remained for a total of 30 days making this the longest tree sit east of the Mississippi River. Elias Schewel and Junior Walk were arrested immediately for providing direct support on the ground. Criminal cases are still pending for the two sitters, while a civil suit seeking compensatory and punitive damages is pending for all four activists.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Moore|first=Catherine|title=‘Tree-sitters’ take up residence to fight strip mining|url=http://www.register-herald.com/local/x1452096081/-Tree-sitters-take-up-residence-to-fight-strip-mining|publisher=The Register Herald|accessdate=30 January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Press|first=Associated|title=Marfork Coal sues tree-sitters over state protest|url=http://www.wvgazette.com/News/201109152136|publisher=The Charleston Gazette|accessdate=30 January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*In 2011, on December 14, [http://observertree.org/ Miranda Gibson] climbed up a 60m old-growth Eucalyptus delegatensis tree, in the heart of Tasmania’s southern virgin rainforest. Gibson has vowed to stay until the forest is protected. The area is imminently due to logged, despite being part of the area supposed to be protected under the fraught [http://australia.gov.au/AGOSP/global_site/library/documents/Tasmanian_Forests_Intergovernmental_Agreement.pdf Forests Intergovernmental Agreement] (IGA).

==Tree villages==
[[Image:Fallfish1.jpg|thumb|left|A view of the Fall Creek village showing aerial walkway]]
A '''tree village''' is an extension of the tree sit/tree house protest, involving several more tree houses.

The ''Fall Creek/Red Cloud Thunder Tree-Village'' was a long running example. It was a 6-year occupation of a small timber sale in the [[Willamette National Forest]] at Fall Creek [[Oregon]] US which ran from February 1998 to November 2003. It comprised seven houses of up to 5 occupants each tied together with rope 'traverses' {{convert|200|ft|m}} high and up to {{convert|125|ft|m}} between 'platforms'. This tree village was designed to be totally self-sufficient with composting toilets, solar/wind power, communications, cargo lines between ground and other sits, individual rappel lines and hydroponic sprout farms. An estimated 1000 activists occupied the trees at various times. The forest occupied during the Fall Creek campaign remains uncut to this day.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}

''Winberry Tree Village'' in the Willamette National Forest was another long-term occupation undertaken by Cascadian tree-sitters. The village consisted of two treehouses (160 feet high and {{convert|175|ft|m}} high) and one suspension structure hung between trees. The Winberry village was occupied for 5 years. One tree house was two story, situated in a huge [[Thuja plicata|Western Red-Cedar]] tree. It featured a bottom story built from branches in the manner of a bird's nest as well as a running water system.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}

The Nanning Creek treesit (&quot;Bonanza&quot;) is centered around Spooner, a {{convert|290|ft|m|sing=on}} [[Sequoia sempervirens|Redwood]] with a near {{convert|40|ft|m|sing=on}} circumference, one of the oldest unprotected trees remaining in the area. This is also a village setup. Nanning Creek is located in the hills overlooking the town of Scotia, America's last company-owned town and the site of Pacific Lumber's headquarters. The area was long protected as a [[Marbled Murrelet]] nesting habitat, but recent changes in environmental law keep loggers out only for the nesting season.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}

&quot;Fern Gully&quot; is located south of Arcata, California, and north of the Nanning Creek sit. It is one of the few remaining tracts of old-growth in the Freshwater area. Fern Gully was started as a &quot;Pirate&quot; sit, unconnected at first from any organizations such as [[Earth First!]].  By 2005, it had 22 trees tied together for transarboreal travel. The village was equipped with a raincatch system that transported water {{convert|40|ft|m}} down to a running tap at the platform, as well as a solar panel at {{convert|207|ft|m}} in a tree named Watsi.  Around that time it was raided by Pacific Lumber contracted climbers. They did not extract a single person, instead cutting out unoccupied traverses, platforms and dreamcatchers. This was a major blow to the village, but the sit continues, and the area remains uncut.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}

&quot;Upper Village&quot; was a set of 3 redwoods, Jerry, Everstine/Diversity (a double trunk tree) and Anastasia. Jerry was one of Humboldt County's most famous redwoods.  A woman named Jeny Card (aka &quot;Remedy&quot;) stayed without touching ground for 361 days, and later a young man named Willow did the same for over 18 months.  Amy Gershman (aka &quot;Wren&quot;) stayed in Everstine for almost ten months, and was later extracted, arrested, and jailed.  After she was released, she went to court, and her case ended in a [[hung jury]].  Upper Village appeared on Da Ali G Show, and Willow was interviewed from the platform of Jerry by Tom Greene, who was doing a segment for The Tonight Show with Jay Leno. No other tree has the extraction history of Jerry. Activists were forcibly removed from the tree on three separate occasions between March 17, 2003 and June 17, 2003. Each time, the tree-sit platforms were destroyed by climbers, but immediately replaced by activists. The Timber Harvest Plan for Upper Village expired in 2005, and the trespassers removed their platforms and traverses. These trees are located directly alongside Greenwood Heights road in Freshwater, California.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}

The &quot;Ludlow&quot; tree village consisted of three basic sits, one large traditional Western Australian sit and two new sits that were two levels and three levels consecutively; each allowed the sitter a separate area for sleeping and relaxing and one for storage, cooking and other activities; one featured a &quot;sun-deck&quot; for outdoor living.  The Ludlow Tuart Forest was targeted, by the Cable Sands mineral sands mining company, for Titanium Dioxide, for products such as white paint and toothpaste to fortify the coating of depleted Uranium weapons.  One person remained in one of the sits for 29 days, without leaving the tree once.  The sits were removed but the concept has been used several times since.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}

Current EF! Tree-village in California (Spring 2011): A tree village is ongoing in the Ryan Creek watershed next to Eureka, California. Over 45 trees are now tied together, the tree-sits scattered amongst them. This is to interfere with clear-cutting and development plans by the Green Diamond Resource Company. The Earth First! Humboldt collective is organizing a campaign to disrupt logging of this Redwood forest. The company owns around {{convert|400000|acre|km2}} of Redwoods in Humboldt and Del Norte counties making them the largest single landowner of Redwood forest. In December 2010, Green Diamond announced they now have plans with non-profit groups to try to turn approx. {{convert|2000|acre|km2}} of the area, including the tree-village zone, into a community forest. The details on this plan are still mostly unclear as of May, 2011. [http://efhumboldt.org EF! Humboldt website]

==Tree houses==
In the [[United Kingdom]] permanent [[tree houses]] are common. One treehouse, ''BattleStar Galactica'' at the [[Manchester Airport|Manchester International Airport]], held 12 people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eco-action.org/dod/no6/battle_star.htm |title=Life on the Battle Star (Do or Die) |publisher=Eco-action.org |date= |accessdate=2009-11-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Permanent tree-houses can be occupied for a year or more. They often have ''lock-on'' points for protesters to chain themselves to during [[eviction]]s. Tree houses have also been used at [[Newbury bypass]], [http://wiedel.photoshelter.com/gallery-image/Eco-Warriors/G0000ubmY9aKe.NM/I0000g.jzcqhQDjk/P0000sEQ5h1p56G0 Crystal Palace] and [http://www.independent.co.uk/news/judge-allows-ecowarrior-11-to-carry-on-living-in-protesters-tree-house-1174290.html Epsom].

==See also==
* [[Green anarchism]]
* [[Tree spiking]]
* [[Eco-terrorism]]
* [[Direct action]]
* [[David Chain]], activist who was killed during a non-violent tree sitting in the [[Redwood Forest]] of Northern California.

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://maineindymedia.org/media/all/display/984 Audio recording of first EF! tree sitter making first climb 5/20/85]
* [http://www.users.qwest.net/~cmcenter1/ewok/ Movies of tree-sitters living in 'Tree Village' at Fall Creek Oregon]
* [http://www.penbay.org/ef/milleniumlog85b.html July 23, 1985 group treesit coverage in Oregon newspaper]
*[http://www.penbay.org/ef/eforegon85.html Review of 1985 Earth First!] - treesitting actions in Oregon.
* [http://weblog.greenpeace.org/tasmania/ Greenpeace] - Styx Valley: Global Rescue Station
* [http://www.cnn.com/2003/US/West/03/18/tree.sitter.ap/index.html Timber firm begins bringing down tree sitter] - Article from when Wren and Remedy were extracted.
* [http://www.sacredredwood.org/news/2003july02sit.php Hung Jury in Tree Sit Case] - Information Wren's trial after her extraction
*[http://www.petition.co.uk/home.html Free Petition website]
*[http://www.berkeleydailyplanet.com/issue/2008-06-26/article/30396?headline=Tree-Sitting-Since-1930 Tree-sitting history]
*[http://efhumboldt.org Earth First! Humboldt - Current Tree-sits 2009]

[[Category:Activism by method]]
[[Category:Environmental protests]]
[[Category:Radical environmentalism]]

[[de:Baumbesetzung]]</text>
      <sha1>s2ug4r59qzb3zl1p9nzp36c721lybdi</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
