<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Tricameralism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>363810</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521108131</id>
      <parentid>492098075</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T20:52:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Zorrobot</username>
        <id>7218328</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>r2.7.3) (Robot: Adding [[sv:Trekammarsystem]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11285">{{Refimprove|date=April 2008}}

'''Tricameralism'''  is the practice of having three [[legislature|legislative]] or [[parliamentary]] chambers. It is contrasted to [[unicameralism]] and [[bicameralism]], both of which are far more common.

The term was used in [[South Africa]] to describe the [[Parliament of South Africa|Parliament]] established under the [[apartheid]] regime's new [[South African Constitution of 1983]]. Other instances of tricameral legislatures in history include [[Simón Bolívar]]'s model state. The word could also describe{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}} the [[French Estates-General]], which had three 'estates'.

==South African tricameralism==
{{Main|Tricameral Parliament}}
In 1983, [[South Africa]]'s [[apartheid]] government put forward a constitution providing for a tricameral legislature. On 2 November, around seventy percent of the country's white population voted in favour of the changes &amp;mdash; black South Africans were not consulted, and under the proposal they continued to be denied representation since in theory they were citizens of independent or autonomous [[bantustan]]s. 

The South African tricameral parliament consisted of three [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]]-based chambers:
*'''House of Assembly''' &amp;mdash; 178 members, reserved for whites 
*'''House of Representatives''' &amp;mdash; 85 members, reserved for [[Coloured]], or mixed-race, people
*'''House of Delegates''' &amp;mdash; 45 members, reserved for [[Indian South Africans|Indians]]

The creation of the tricameral parliament was controversial on two fronts. On the one hand, many white conservatives disliked the idea of non-whites participating in Parliament at all. The dispute was a factor in the creation of the [[Conservative Party (South Africa)|Conservative Party]], a breakaway from the dominant [[National Party (South Africa)|National Party]]. On the other hand, many coloureds and Asians rejected the system as a sham, saying that the chambers reserved for them were powerless. 

The tricameral parliament was not particularly strong. The 1983 constitution significantly weakened the powers of parliament, and abolished the position of Prime Minister. Most authority was transferred to the [[State President of South Africa|State President]], including the ability to appoint the Cabinet. This was seen by many as an attempt to limit the power of coloureds and Indians&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; not only were the 'non-white' Houses of Parliament less powerful than the 'white' one, but parliament itself was subordinate to a white President.

==Bolívar's tricameralism==
[[Simón Bolívar]], the [[South America]]n revolutionary leader, included a tricameral legislature as part of his proposals for a model government. Bolívar described the three houses as follows:
*'''Chamber of Tribunes''', holding powers relating to government finance, foreign affairs, and war. The tribunes would, unlike the other two houses, be popularly elected.
*'''Senate''', an apolitical body holding powers to enact law, supervise the judiciary, and appoint regional officials. Bolívar believed that the senate should be [[hereditary]], saying that this was the only way to ensure its neutrality. There are parallels between Bolívar's Senate and other houses such as the [[United Kingdom|British]] [[House of Lords]].
*'''Censors''', a group who would act as a check against the powers of the other two. Bolívar described them as &quot;prosecuting attorneys against the government in defense of the Constitution and popular rights&quot;. He also said that they should ensure that the executive was functioning satisfactorily, perhaps having powers of [[impeachment]].

Bolívar intended his model government to have a [[presidential system]], and so the tricameral parliament was not expected to govern. Bolívar was explicit that the legislature should not have an active role in administration &amp;mdash; it merely made law and supervised other branches of government.

Despite Bolívar's huge influence in South America, no country employs his tricameral parliament. Early attempts to implement the model, such as in [[Bolivia]], were not successful, although the chaos of the period was likely a factor in this outcome.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}

==French tricameralism==
===Ancien Régime===
Some historians view the [[France|French]] [[French States-General|States-General]] as an example of a tricameral legislature. The States-General evolved gradually over time, and provided advice on various matters (including legislative issues) to the [[King of France|King]]. The three Estates were the simply labeled [[First Estate|First]] (consisting of [[clergy]]), [[Second Estate|Second]] (consisting of [[nobility]]), and [[Third Estate|Third]] (consisting of [[commoner]]s). (The term &quot;[[fourth estate]]&quot;, referring to the press, derives from this system, but was coined long after the revolution that abolished it.)

There are problems with regarding the States-General as a tricameral legislature, however. Firstly, the States-General never had any formal powers to legislate, although at times, it played a major role in the King's legislative activity. Secondly, the division between the three estates was not always maintained &amp;mdash; the estates sometime deliberated separately, but at other times, they deliberated as a single body, undermining the idea of tricameralism.

===Consulate===
The [[French Consulate]] (and later [[First French Empire]], although the lower two chambers were by then entirely without power) had a tricameral legislature, consisting of:
* the ''[[Sénat conservateur]]'' (''Conservative Senate''), the highest chamber, whose duty was to guard the constitution, and which upon the consul's proposal could enact special laws known as ''sénatus-consultes'',
* the ''[[Corps législatif]]'' (''Legislative body''), successor to the [[French Directory|Directoire]]'s [[Council of Ancients|Conseil des Anciens]] (upper house), which was to vote on laws without discussing them (or, after 1804, with only a strictly curtailed discussion),
* the ''[[Tribune#French revolutionary tribunat|Tribunat]]'', successor of the [[French Directory|Directoire]]'s [[Council of Five Hundred|Conseil des Cinq Cents]] (lower house), which was to discuss laws and only vote on whether to &quot;recommend&quot; them for the Corps législatif.

Whether the Sénat was part of legislature, however, is open to doubt, because [[Emmanuel-Joseph Sieyès|Sieyès]] (the main instigator of the Consulate's Constitution and later president of this Senate) described it as belonging to an altogether different power beyond the executive, legislative and judiciary: the ''conservative'' power.  In effect, [[Napoleon I of France|Napoléon]] made the Sénat into a political élite to back his power as Consul and later as Emperor, whereas the other two chambers were subdued into submission.  In 1807, the Tribunat was definitely abolished.

==Republic of China tricameralism==
According to the original [[Constitution of the Republic of China|Constitution]] of the [[Republic of China]] (which is drafted according to the idea of Dr. [[Sun Yat-sen]]), under the [[National Assembly of the Republic of China|National Assembly]], there are five branches of government, named Yuan(院), which are: the [[Executive Yuan]], [[Legislative Yuan]], [[Judicial Yuan]], [[Examination Yuan]], and [[Control Yuan]].

The National Assembly represent the [[sovereignty]] and all citizens, the Legislative Yuan is responsible to do the technical job of [[legislation]] and the Control Yuan is the watchdog which monitors the government.

However, the constitution did not mention which is the [[parliament]] of the country. Finally the Judicial Yuan decided that the National Assembly, Legislative Yuan, and Control Yuan resembled the parliament.

{{Wikisource|zh:釋字第76號}}

Originally, the Control Yuan was elected, but later become nominated by the President. After the suspension of the National Assembly, the Legislative Yuan became the current [[Unicameralism|unicameral parliament]].

==Other examples==

===Former Yugoslavia===
The [[Socialist Republic of Croatia]] had three houses in Parlament (Sabor Socijalističke republike Hrvatske, now [[Parliament of Croatia|Hrvatski Sabor]]): Socio-Political Council (Društveno-političko vijeće), Council of Municipalities (Vijeće općina) and Council of United Labor (Vijeće udruženog rada). This was abolished with new constitution in 1990.

===Isle of Man===
The parliament of the [[Isle of Man]], [[Tynwald]], is sometimes called tricameral, but this description is not universally accepted. The two commonly accepted houses of Tynwald are the [[House of Keys]] and the [[Legislative Council (Isle of Man)|Legislative Council]], but according to some, the [[Tynwald Court]] (consisting of the members of both houses meeting together) counts as a third house. Others disagree, saying that as there are no members of the Court who are not also members of the other houses, the Court should not be considered separately (by comparison, in Australia, Switzerland and India deadlocks between the two Houses can sometimes be resolved by a joint sitting, but experts would not classify either of those countries as &quot;tricameral&quot;).

===Church of England===
The [[General Synod]] of the [[Church of England]] is sometimes described as tricameral. It is divided into a House of [[Bishop]]s, the House of [[Clergy]] and the House of [[Laity]]. As the Church of England is the state church of [[England]], the [[Parliament of the United Kingdom]] has given the General Synod the power (subject to veto) to make law relating to the Church.

However, a Diocesan Synod is not a tricameral institution. It is a [[bicameral]] institution, as it consists of the House of [[Laity]], who are directly elected by the parishes, and the House of [[Clergy]]. The Bishop is not a member of either House, even though he is constitutionally a member of Synod.

===Labor unions===

Tricameral meeting arrangements are a growing trend in [[labor unions]] where some members will always be working on one of three shifts. Under such arrangements, each shift will have its own meeting, but the action of one meeting will have to be adopted by the other two.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.parliamentaryprocedure.org/pdf/ShiftMeetings.pdf Meetings of Members Working in Shifts&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Unicameralism]]
* [[Bicameralism]]
* [[Tetracameralism]]
* [[Multicameralism]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.sahistory.org.za/pages/library-resources/official%20docs/1983-constitution.htm An overview of South Africa's 1983 constitution]
*[http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://www.geocities.com/Athens/Acropolis/7609/repbol.html&amp;date=2009-10-25+05:45:24  An overview of Bolivar's model government]

[[Category:Government]]
[[Category:Liberalism]]
[[Category:Legislatures]]
[[Category:Tricameral legislatures|*]]

[[de:Dreikammersystem]]
[[es:Tricameralidad]]
[[fr:Parlement tricaméral]]
[[ko:삼원제]]
[[it:Tricameralismo]]
[[nl:Driekamerstelsel]]
[[pl:Trikameralizm]]
[[ru:Трёхпалатный парламент]]
[[sv:Trekammarsystem]]
[[th:ระบบสามสภา]]
[[zh:三院制]]</text>
      <sha1>48v5wm9m6e7aot4ltix5xx6v54wgxzu</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
