<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Tripartite classification of authority</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>856265</id>
    <revision>
      <id>508567470</id>
      <parentid>497331308</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-08-22T04:58:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yworo</username>
        <id>9813438</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* See also */ rm link to deleted article</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8179">{{sociology}}
[[Max Weber]] distinguished three [[ideal type]]s of legitimate political leadership, domination and authority: 
# '''[[charismatic authority]]''' (''[[family|familial]] and [[religion|religious]]''),
# '''[[traditional authority]]''' (''patriarchs, patrimonalism, feudalism'') and
# '''[[legal authority]]''' (''modern law and state, bureaucracy'').

These three types are ideal pure types and rarely appear in their pure form. 

According to Weber, authority is power accepted as legitimate by those subjected to it. These three forms of authority are said to appear in an &quot;hierarchical development order&quot;. [[Sovereign state|States]] progress from ''charismatic authority'', to ''traditional authority'', and finally reach the ''state of rational-legal authority'' which is characteristic of a modern [[liberal democracy]].

==Charismatic domination==
{{main|Charismatic domination}}
Charismatic authority grows out of the personal charm or the strength of an individual personality.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.12manage.com/methods_weber_charismatic_leadership.html Charismatic Leadership (Weber)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; It was described by Weber in a lecture as &quot;the authority of the extraordinary and personal gift of grace (charisma)&quot;; he distinguished it from the other forms of authority by stating &quot;Men do not obey him [the charismatic ruler] by virtue of tradition or statute, but because they believe in him.&quot;&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;[http://www.ne.jp/asahi/moriyuki/abukuma/weber/lecture/politics_vocation.html Politics as a Vocation&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Thus the actual power or capabilities of the leader are irrelevant, as long as the followers believe that such power exists. Thus, according to Weber, it is particularly difficult for charismatic leaders to maintain their authority because the followers must continue to legitimize the authority of the leader. 

Charismatic domination is insofar different from legal-rational and tradition power as it does not develop from established tradition but rather from the belief the followers have in the leader.

According to Weber, once the leader loses his charisma or dies, systems based on charismatic authority tend to transform into traditional or legal-rational systems.

==Traditional domination==
{{main|Traditional domination}}
In traditional authority, the legitimacy of the [[authority]] comes from [[tradition]] or custom; Weber described it as &quot;the authority of the eternal yesterday&quot; and identified it as the source of authority for [[monarchy|monarchies]].&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; In this type of domination, the traditional rights of a powerful individual or group are accepted by the subordinate, or at least not challenged. The dominant individual could be a clan leader, eldest, the head of a family, a patriarchal figure or dominant elite. Historically this has been the most common type of government. 

According to Weber inequalities are created and preserved by traditional authority. Should this authority not be challenged, the dominant leader or group will stay in power. For Weber, traditional power blocked the development of rational-legal authority.

==Legal Rational domination==
{{main|Legal domination}}
Legal authority, also known as legal-rational authority, is where an individual or institution exerts power by virtue of the legal office that they hold. It is the authority that demands obedience to the office rather than the office holder; once they leave office, their rational-legal authority is lost. Weber identified ''&quot;rationally-created rules&quot;''&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; as the central feature of this form of authority. Modern [[democracy|democracies]] contain many examples of legal-rational regimes. There are different ways in which legal authority can develop. Many societies have developed a system of laws and regulations and there exist many different principles of legality. With the development of a legal-rational system, the political system is likely to be rationalized similarly. Constitutions, written documents, established offices and regular elections are often associated with modern legal-rational political systems. These in the past have tended to develop in opposition to earlier traditional systems such as monarchies, where the set of rules are not well developed. As these systems develop in a rational manner, authority takes on a legal-rational form. Those who govern have the legitimate legal right to do so and those subordinated accept the legality of the rulers.

Albeit rational-legal authority may be challenged by those subordinated, it is unlikely to result in a quick change in the nature of the system. Such power-struggles, according to Weber, may be based on nationalism, ethnicity and are mostly political struggles.

==The classification of authority in the context of history==
Weber also notes that legal domination is the most advanced, and that societies evolve from having mostly traditional and charismatic authorities to mostly rational and legal ones, because the instability of charismatic authority inevitably forces it to &quot;routinize&quot; into a more structured form of authority. Likewise he notes that in a pure type of traditional rule, sufficient resistance to a master can lead to a &quot;traditional revolution&quot;. Thus he alludes to an inevitable move towards a rational-legal structure of authority, utilizing a bureaucratic structure. This ties to his broader concept of [[Rationalization (sociology)|rationalization]] by suggesting the inevitability of a move in this direction. Thus this theory can be sometimes viewed as part of the [[social evolutionism]] theory.

In traditional authority, the legitimacy of the [[authority]] comes from [[tradition]], in charismatic authority from the personality and leadership qualities of the individual ([[charisma]]), and in legal (or rational-legal) authority from powers that are [[bureaucracy|bureaucratically]] and legally attached to certain positions. A classic example of these three types may be found in religion: [[priests]] (traditional), [[Jesus]] (charismatic), and the [[Roman Catholic Church]] (legal-rational). Weber also conceived of these three types within his three primary modes of conflict: traditional authority within status groups, charismatic authority within [[social class|class]], and legal-rational authority within party organizations.

In his view every historical relation between rulers and ruled contained elements that can be analyzed on the basis of the above distinction.

==Comparison table==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Characteristic !! Charismatic !! Traditional !! Legal-Rational
|-
| Type of ruler
| Charismatic leader
| Dominant personality
| Functional superiors or bureaucratic officials
|-
| Position determined by
| Having a dynamic personality
| Established&amp;nbsp;tradition or routine
| Legally established authority
|-
| Ruled using
| Extraordinary qualities and exceptional powers
| Acquired or inherited (hereditary) qualities
| Virtue of rationally established norms, decrees, and other rules and regulations
|-
| Legitimized
| Victories and success to community
| Established tradition or routine
| General belief in the formal correctness of these rules and those who enact them are considered a legitimized authority
|-
| Loyalty
| Interpersonal &amp; personal allegiance and devotion
| Based on traditional allegiances
| To authority / rules
|-
| Cohesion
| Emotionally unstable and volatile
| Feeling of common purpose
| Abiding by rules (see [[Robert K. Merton#Merton's theory of deviance|Merton's theory of deviance]])
|-
| Leadership
| Rulers and followers (disciples)
| Established forms of social conduct
| Rules, not rulers
|}

== See also ==
* [[Form of government]]
* [[The Three Types of Legitimate Rule]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

{{DEFAULTSORT:Tripartite Classification Of Authority}}
[[Category:Max Weber]]
[[Category:Sociology index]]
[[Category:Sociological terms]]
[[Category:Authority]]

[[bg:Трипартитна класификация на властта]]
[[el:Οι τρεις μορφές κυριαρχίας]]
[[scn:Classificazzioni tripartita di l'autorità]]</text>
      <sha1>r7wsgq22ppomigxuiqu7aa2yfbcp9fs</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
