<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Triumphalism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1654376</id>
    <revision>
      <id>518903445</id>
      <parentid>518896370</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-20T18:10:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Anglicanus</username>
        <id>4280508</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Quotations */ mos</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7853">{{Refimprove|date=July 2011}}

'''Triumphalism''' is the attitude or belief that a particular doctrine, religion, culture, or social system is superior to and should triumph over all others. Triumphalism is not an articulated [[doctrine]] but rather a term that is used to characterize certain attitudes or belief systems by parties such as political commentators and [[historian]]s.

==Definition==
The term triumphalism is what anthropologists call an [[Emic and etic|&quot;observer's category&quot;]]; it is generally taken as having a [[pejorative]] sense (see the ''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]'') and few members of groups would identify themselves as being triumphalist.

The term is sometimes used to refer to relatively inconsequential behavior, such as excessively demonstrative glee at the defeat or failure of a sports rival. People experience triumphalism in this [[recreation]]al form as collective pride (e.g., school spirit) or sports fanaticism (''“We’re Number One!”'').

Triumphalism also takes more consequential forms, including extreme forms of [[patriotism]], [[nationalism]], [[ideological]], or [[religious]] extremism.

A triumphalist may derive a sense of pride, security, or virtue from their sense of superiority and expectation of ultimate triumph. However, those who believe in their own group’s superiority or inevitable ascendancy do not typically claim the label ‘triumphalist’.  Instead, the term usually has a negative connotation and is used by those who do not accept the superiority of the belief or group in question, or by those who are warning against the effects of over-confidence and hubris within their own group.

==Analysis==
Triumphalism may both benefit and prove detrimental to the survival of a doctrine, culture, or social system. Dangers&lt;ref&gt;Kimball, C: &quot;When Religion Becomes Evil: Five Warning Signs&quot;, HarperCollinsSanFrancisco, 2002&lt;/ref&gt; include:&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Impaired ability to judge the value or morality of the group's actions;
&lt;li&gt;Cessation of creativity and innovation within the group;
&lt;li&gt;Blindness to other groups’ strengths and innovations;
&lt;li&gt;A tendency to over-reach against the group’s competitors, based on an inflated sense of the likelihood of triumph in conflict.&lt;/ul&gt;

At the same time, triumphalism also provides impetus to proselytization, conquest and the general expansion of a group or doctrine. Many successful historical movements have worked from a triumphalist base. Examples include the [[Islamic conquests]] of the 7th century, European [[colonialism]], and the concept of [[manifest destiny]] which helped the [[United States]] to [[Hegemony|dominance]] in [[North America]], in the process transforming itself into what some call the [[American empire]].

Movements need not be triumphalist to be dynamic and successful. The Western drive for the [[emancipation of women]] and the [[civil rights movement]], for instance, succeeded on the basis of [[egalitarianism]] rather than triumphalism.{{OR|date=October 2012}}

==Quotations==
'''2008, [[Capitalism]]'''
*''However, soon after this euphoric capitalist triumphalism, capitalism seems to be heading to another cross-road, which is capable of undermining the aforesaid euphoria. As capital is now set to continue its accumulation, expansion and profitability, unemployment is on the rise, as government ability to create lasting employment has become ineffective due to the privatisation of the public sectors, retrenchment by private business, etc. The state of affairs is exacerbating the crime rate (both within nations and globally), ethnic and global tension, poverty and ill-feeling. Hence, there could be other better global alternatives to the current single capitalist triumphant orthodoxy.'' Wilfred I. Ukper, Andre D. Slabbert&lt;ref&gt;''Triumphant capitalism and the future of human, social and economic progress in the post-Cold War era'' [[International Journal of Social Economics]] [http://ideas.repec.org/a/eme/ijsepp/v35y2008i6p417-422.html Volume 35 No. 6 pp: 417-422].&lt;/ref&gt;

'''2005, [[Muslim]]'''
*''The upshot of the matter is that to reduce Islam—with its transcendental moral essence which is based on commitment to 'enjoining the right and forbidding the wrong’—is universal. (Qu'ran 3:103) Those who reduce Islam to an ideological agenda, under the socio-political reality...and all the Muslim triumphalism that this brings, simply have not understood the message of Islam comprehensively.'' Tarek A Ghanem, in Islam Online &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.islamonline.net/english/In_Depth/DisasterVictims/Articles/2005/01/02.shtml Helping Disaster Victims]{{dead link|url=http://www.islamonline.net/english/In_Depth/DisasterVictims/Articles/2005/01/02.shtml|date=March 2011}}, [[IslamOnline]]&lt;/ref&gt;

'''2004, [[Jewish]]'''
*''Yet in addition to being self-defeating, sectarian triumphalism undermines core Jewish values of common peoplehood and mutual bonds between Jews worldwide.'' [[Steven Bayme]], in ''[[The Jewish Week]]''.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}

'''2004, [[United States|American]]'''
*''The abasement rituals at [[Abu Ghraib torture and prisoner abuse|Abu Ghraib]] were most generally conditioned by the climate of impunity created by triumphalist strategy, ideology and rhetoric, which led, at least, to dismissive negligence and then cover-ups by authorities.'' [[Michael A. Weinstein]], in the [[Power and Interest News Report]]{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}

'''2001, [[scientific]]'''
*''A better understanding of science should lead not to triumphalism but to the kind of humility recently expressed by Nobel Prize-winning geneticist Francois Jacob in ''Of Flies, Mice and Men'': &quot;Science cannot answer all questions. . . . It can, however, give some indications, exclude certain hypotheses. Engaging in the pursuit of science may help us make fewer mistakes.” ''[[Jon Beckwith]], in [[American Scientist Online]]

'''2001, [[Christian]]'''
*''Christian triumphalism has been the energy that has marred our missionary efforts around the globe and in all ages. Consider what we have done to the Native Americans in this country - from the time of Columbus to the time of the great Western Migration. .... Just read Barbara Kingsolver's [[The Poisonwood Bible|Poisonwood Bible]] to get a sense of the effects of Christian triumphalism.” ''The Rev. Canon Elizabeth Kaeton, in a sermon preached at Christ [[Episcopal Church in the United States of America|Episcopal]] Church, New Jersey on September 23, 2001 &lt;ref&gt;Rev'd Canon Elizabeth Kaeton. [http://www.rci.rutgers.edu/~lcrew/joyanyway/joy171.html Stella's Song: A Celebration of Women in the Midst of the War on Terrorism]&lt;/ref&gt;

'''2012, [[Politics]]'''
*''But Obama’s ego, spurred by Democratic triumphalism and the boundless credulity of the establishment press, led Obama to not take Romney seriously and to fail to adopt his preferred persona of a reasonable man working in an unreasonable system.” ''Chris Stirewalt, Power Play, Published October 04, 2012&lt;ref&gt;Chris Stirewalt. [http://www.foxnews.com/politics/2012/10/04/obama-goes-from-cool-to-cold/#ixzz28N2ZDFS5]&lt;/ref&gt;

'''1994, [[Soviet]]'''
*''But not only did Soviet triumphalism eventually provoke the Reaganite reaction in the United States, but, Kissinger suggests, it produced the over-extension of Soviet resources that led directly to economic and ultimately political collapse. ''[[Michael Howard]], in [[Foreign Affairs]].

==See also==
*[[Chauvinism]]
*[[Jingoism]]
*[[Supremacism]]
*[[Victory Jig]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

==External links==
{{wiktionary}}
* [http://www.patheos.com/Resources/Additional-Resources/Beyond-Jewish-Triumphalism-Reb-Zalman &quot;Beyond Jewish Triumphalism&quot;], on ''[[Patheos]]''

&lt;!--Categories--&gt;
[[Category:Political theories]]

&lt;!--Other languages--&gt;
[[lt:Triumfalizmas]]
[[uk:Тріумфалізм]]</text>
      <sha1>hj6lnqyubau8owiyla0ktwth8w57mgr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
