<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Tyrant</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>198512</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521928046</id>
      <parentid>521928036</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-08T02:01:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contributions/72.199.102.149|72.199.102.149]] to version by Reahad. False positive? [[User:ClueBot NG/FalsePositives|Report it]]. Thanks, [[User:ClueBot NG|ClueBot NG]]. (1322147) (Bot)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13969">{{Redirect|Tyranny}}
{{About|a political ruler}}
{{Forms of government}}

A '''tyrant''' ([[Greek language|Greek]] {{lang|grc|τύραννος}}, ''tyrannos'') was originally one who illegally seized and controlled a governmental power in a [[polis]]. Tyrants were a group of individuals who took over many Greek poleis during the uprising of the middle classes in the sixth and seventh centuries BC, ousting the aristocratic governments. [[Plato]] and [[Aristotle]] define a tyrant as, &quot;one who rules without law, looks to his own advantage rather than that of his subjects, and uses extreme and cruel tactics&amp;mdash;against his own people as well as others&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Glad, B. (2002, March).  Why Tyrants Go Too Far: Malignant Narcissism and Absolute Power. Political Psychology, 33. Retrieved May 15, 2010, from JSTOR database.&lt;/ref&gt;

In common usage, the word &quot;tyrant&quot; carries connotations of a harsh and cruel ruler who places his or her own interests or the interests of an [[oligarchy]] over the best interests of the general population, which the tyrant governs or controls. The Greek term carried no [[pejorative]] connotation during the [[Archaic Greece|Archaic]] and early [[Classical Greece|Classical]] periods but was clearly a bad word to Plato, and on account of the decisive influence of political philosophy its negative connotations only increased down into the [[Hellenistic period]], becoming synonymous with &quot;Authenteo&quot; - another term which carried authoritarian connotations around the turn of the first century A.D.{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}} During the seventh and sixth centuries BC, tyranny was often looked upon as an intermediate stage between narrow oligarchy and more democratic forms of [[polity]]. However, in the late fifth and fourth centuries, a new kind of tyrant, the military dictator, arose, specifically in Sicily.

==Etymology==
The English noun ''[[:wikt:tyrant|tyrant]]'' appears in [[Middle English]] use, via [[Old French]], from the 1290s.
The word derives from [[Latin]] ''tyrannus'', meaning &quot;illegitimate ruler&quot;, and this in turn from the [[Ancient Greek|Greek]] {{lang|grc|τύραννος}} &quot;monarch, ruler of a [[polis]]&quot;.
The final ''-t'' arises in Old French by association with the present participles in ''-ant''.&lt;ref&gt;''tyrant'', ''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]'', 2nd edition&lt;/ref&gt;

Greek {{lang|grc|τύραννος}} is itself a loanword from a [[Pre-Greek substrate|pre-Greek]] source, like [[basileus|βασιλεύς]], and perhaps also  [[anax|ἄναξ]], a loan from a [[superstrate]] semantic sphere.
Speculations on  [[Tyrrhenian languages|Tyrrhenian]] origin connect the Etruscan theonym ''[[Turan (mythology)|Turan]]'' for [[Venus (mythology)|Venus]] (perhaps from an epitheton &quot;*Lady&quot;, paired with [[Adonis|Atunis]] &quot;*Lord&quot;) and the ethnonym of the [[Tyrrhenians]] itself.&lt;ref&gt;Heubeck. ''Praegraeca'' 68 ff.; Windekens [[Kuhns Zeitschrift|KZ]] 74, 123ff.; see [[Hjalmar Frisk]], ''Greek Etymological Dictionary'' (1960). Further speculation is also found in [[Eric Partridge]], ''Origins'' (1958).&lt;/ref&gt;

== Historical forms ==
In [[ancient Greece]], tyrants were influential opportunists that came to power by securing the support of different factions of a [[deme]]. The word &quot;tyrannos&quot;, possibly pre-Greek, [[Pelasgian]] or eastern in origin,&lt;ref&gt;Forrest, George &quot;Greece, the history of the Archaic period&quot; in Boardman, John et al (1986), &quot;The Oxford History of the Classical World&quot; (OUP)&lt;/ref&gt; then carried no ethical censure; it simply referred to anyone, good or bad, who obtained executive power in a [[polis]] by unconventional means. Support for the tyrants came from the growing middle class and from the peasants who had no land or were in debt to the wealthy land owners. It is true that they had no legal right to rule, but the people preferred them over kings or the [[aristocracy]]. The Greek tyrants stayed in power by using mercenary soldiers from outside of their respective city-state. To mock tyranny, [[Thales]] wrote that the strangest thing to see is ''&quot;an aged tyrant&quot;'' meaning that tyrants do not have the public support to survive for long.

=== Corinth ===

In '''[[Corinth]]''', growing wealth from colonial enterprises, and the wider horizons brought about by the export of wine and oil, together with the new experiences of the Eastern Mediterranean brought back by returning [[mercenaries|mercenary]] [[hoplites]] employed overseas allowed [[Cypselus]], the first tyrant of [[Corinth]] in the 7th century BC, to overthrow the [[aristocracy|aristocratic]] power of the dominant but unpopular [[Bacchiadae]], who were killed, executed, driven out and exiled in 657 BC.  Corinth prospered economically under his rule and Cypselus manages to rule without a [[bodyguard]] but when he managed to bequeath his position to his son, [[Periander]], whose position was less secure, his son required a bodyguard of mercenary soldiers personally loyal to himself.

Nevertheless, under Cypselus and Periander, Corinth extended and tightened her control over her colonial enterprises, and exports of Corinthian pottery flourished.  However, tyrants seldom succeeded in establishing an untroubled line of succession. Periander's successor was less fortunate and was expelled. Afterward, Corinth was ruled by a lackluster oligarchy, and was eventually eclipsed by the rising powers of Athens and Sparta.

=== Athens ===

In '''[[Athens]]''', the inhabitants first gave the title of tyrant to [[Peisistratos (Athens)|Peisistratus]], a relative of [[Solon]], the Athenian lawgiver, who succeeded in 546 BC, after 2 failed attempts, to install himself as tyrant.  Supported by prosperity of the peasantry and landowning interests of the plain (prospering from the rise of olive exports), and his clients from [[Marathon]], he managed to achieve supreme power.  Through an ambitious program of public works, by fostering the state cult of [[Athena]], by encouraging the creation of festivals and supporting the Panathenaean games, in which prizes were jars of olive oil, and in his support of the Dionosia (leading to the development of Athenian drama) Peisistratus managed to maintain his personal popularity.

He was followed by his sons, and with the subsequent growth of Athenian [[democracy]], the title &quot;tyrant&quot; took on its familiar negative connotations. The murder of his son, the tyrant [[Hipparchus (tyrant)|Hipparchus]] by [[Harmodius and Aristogeiton|Aristogeiton and Harmodios]] in Athens in 514 BC marked the beginning of the so-called &quot;cult of the [[tyrannicide]]s&quot; (i.e., of killers of tyrants). Contempt for tyranny characterised this [[cult movement]]. Despite financial help from Persia, in 510 the Peisistratids were expelled by a combination of intrigue, exile and Spartan arms.  The anti-tyrannical attitude became especially prevalent in Athens after 508 BC, when [[Cleisthenes]] reformed the political system so that it resembled ''[[demokratia]]'' (ancient participant democracy as opposed to the modern representative democracy).

The [[Thirty Tyrants]] whom the Spartans imposed on a defeated Attica in 404 BC would not be classified as tyrants in the usual sense and were in effect an [[oligarchy]].

===Aesymnetes===
An [[aesymnetes]] (pl. aesymnetai) had similar scope of power to the tyrant, such as [[Pittacus|Pittacus of Mytilene]] (c. 640-568 BC), and was elected for life or for a specified period by a city-state in a time of crisis—the only difference being that the aesymnetes was a constitutional office and was comparable to the [[Roman dictator]]. Magistrates in some city-states were also called aesymnetai.

===Archaic tyrants===
The heyday of the [[Archaic Greece|Archaic period]] tyrants came in the early 6th century BC, when [[Cleisthenes of Sicyon|Cleisthenes]] ruled [[Sicyon]] in the [[Peloponnesus]] and [[Polycrates]] ruled [[Samos Island|Samos]]. During this time, revolts overthrew many governments in the [[Aegean Sea|Aegean]] world. [[Chilon]], the ambitious and capable [[ephor]] of [[Sparta]], built a strong alliance amongst neighbouring states by making common cause with these groups seeking to oppose unpopular tyrannical rule.  By intervening against the tyrants of Sicyon, Corinth and Athens, Sparta thus came to assume Hellenic leadership prior to the Persian invasions.  Simultaneously [[Persian Empire|Persia]] first started making inroads into Greece, and many tyrants sought Persian help against forces seeking to remove them.

===Populism===
Greek tyranny in the main grew out of the struggle of the popular classes against the [[aristocracy]] or against priest-kings where archaic traditions and mythology sanctioned hereditary and/or traditional rights to rule. Popular [[coup]]s generally installed tyrants, who often became or remained popular rulers, at least in the early part of their reigns. For instance, the popular imagination remembered [[Peisistratos (Athens)|Peisistratus]] for an episode - related by (pseudonymous) [[Aristotle]], but possibly fictional - in which he exempted a farmer from taxation because of the particular barrenness of his plot.

Peisistratus' sons [[Hippias (son of Peisistratus)|Hippias]] and [[Hipparchus (son of Pisistratus)|Hipparchus]], on the other hand, were not such able rulers, and when the disaffected aristocrats [[Harmodius and Aristogeiton|Harmodios and Aristogeiton]] slew Hipparchus, Hippias' rule quickly became oppressive, resulting in the expulsion of the Peisistratids in 510 BC, who resided henceforth in Persepolis as clients of the Persian Shahanshah (King of kings).

===Sicilian tyrants===
The tyrannies of Sicily came about due to similar causes, but here the threat of [[Carthaginian]] attack prolonged tyranny, facilitating the rise of military leaders with the people united behind them. Such Sicilian tyrants as [[Gelo]], [[Hiero I]], [[Hiero II]], [[Dionysius the Elder]], [[Dionysius the Younger]], and [[Agathocles]] maintained lavish courts and became patrons of culture.

===Roman tyrants===
Roman historians like [[Suetonius]], [[Tacitus]], [[Plutarch]], and [[Josephus]] often spoke of &quot;tyranny&quot; in opposition to &quot;liberty&quot;.  Tyranny was associated with imperial rule and those rulers who usurped too much authority from the Roman Senate.  Those who were advocates of &quot;liberty&quot; tended to be pro-Republic and pro-Senate.  For instance, regarding [[Julius Caesar]] and his assassins, Suetonius wrote:
:Therefore the plots which had previously been formed separately, often by groups of two or three, were united in a general conspiracy, since even the populace no longer were pleased with present conditions, but both secretly and openly rebelled at his tyranny and cried out for defenders of their liberty.&lt;ref&gt;Suetonius, ''The Lives of Twelve Caesars'', Life of Julius Caesar 80&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Niccolò Machiavelli]], building on this opposition, conflates all rule by a single person (whom he generally refers to as a &quot;prince&quot;) with &quot;tyranny,&quot; regardless of the legitimacy of that rule, in his ''[[Discourses on Livy]]''. He also identifies liberty with [[republic]]an regimes; whether he would include so-called &quot;[[crowned republic]]s&quot; (such as modern [[constitutional monarchy|constitutional monarchies]]) is somewhat unclear from the text.

== In the arts ==
[[Ancient Greece|Ancient Greeks]], as well as the [[Roman Republic]]ans, became generally quite wary of anyone seeking to implement a popular coup. [[Shakespeare]] portrays the struggle of one such anti-tyrannical Roman, [[Marcus Junius Brutus]], in his play ''[[Julius Caesar (play)|Julius Caesar]]''.

== Enlightenment ==
In the [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]], thinkers applied the word tyranny to the system of governance that had developed around [[aristocracy]] and [[monarchy]]. Specifically, [[John Locke]] as part of his argument against the &quot;[[Divine Right of Kings]]&quot; in his book ''[[Two Treatises of Government]]'' defines it this way: “Tyranny is the exercise of power beyond right, which nobody can have a right to; and this is making use of the power any one has in his hands, not for the good of those who are under it, but for his own private, separate advantage.”&lt;ref&gt;[[Two Treatises of Government]](199)&lt;/ref&gt; Locke's concept of tyranny influenced the writers of subsequent generations who developed the concept of tyranny as counterpoint to ideas of [[human rights]] and [[democracy]].  [[Thomas Jefferson]] referred to the tyranny of [[King George III of Great Britain]] in the [[Declaration of Independence]], and the concept was refined in turn to refer to the [[Kings of France]], the tyrants of [[the Terror]], and to [[Napoleon I]] in turn during the [[French Revolution]] and subsequent regimes.

==See also==
* [[Tyranny of the majority]]
* [[Tyrannicide]]
* [[Dictator]]
* [[Dictatorship]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
{{wikiquote|Tyranny}}
*[http://www.livius.org/tt-tz/tyrant/tyrant.html Tyrant] by [[Jona Lendering]] at livius.org.
*[http://bmcr.brynmawr.edu/1997/97.07.18.html Bryn Mawr Classical Review]

{{Authoritarian types of rule}}

[[Category:Ancient Greek tyrants| ]]
[[Category:Ancient Greek titles]]
[[Category:Ancient Roman government]]
[[Category:Ancient Greek government]]
[[Category:Positions of authority]]

[[af:Tiran]]
[[ar:طاغية]]
[[bg:Тиран]]
[[bs:Tiranija]]
[[ca:Tirania]]
[[cs:Tyrannis]]
[[de:Tyrann]]
[[et:Türann]]
[[el:Τύραννος]]
[[es:Tiranía]]
[[eo:Tirano (reganto)]]
[[eu:Tirano]]
[[fa:جباریت]]
[[fr:Tyran]]
[[gl:Tiranía]]
[[ko:참주]]
[[hr:Tiranin]]
[[io:Tirano]]
[[id:Tiran]]
[[it:Tiranno]]
[[he:טיראניה]]
[[ka:ტირანია]]
[[kk:Тирания]]
[[la:Tyrannis]]
[[lv:Tirāns]]
[[hu:Türannisz]]
[[arz:طاغيه]]
[[nl:Tiran]]
[[ja:僭主]]
[[no:Tyrann]]
[[nn:Tyrann]]
[[pl:Tyran]]
[[pt:Tirania]]
[[ro:Tiranie]]
[[ru:Тирания]]
[[scn:Tirannu]]
[[sr:Тиранин]]
[[fi:Tyranni]]
[[sv:Tyrann]]
[[uk:Тиранія]]
[[zh:僭主]]</text>
      <sha1>gk50my59zfumw7siq96macqw2h9rkt8</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
