<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>U.S. Committee for Human Rights in North Korea</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6623804</id>
    <revision>
      <id>517583461</id>
      <parentid>508323836</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-13T15:10:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Magioladitis</username>
        <id>1862829</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>clean up using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (8459)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11603">{{Infobox NPO
|organization_name  = Committee for Human Rights in North Korea
|organization_logo  = [[File:Committee for Human Rights in North Korea Logo.jpg|201px]]
|organization_type  = Non-profit&lt;br /&gt;[[Non-governmental organization|NGO]]
|founded            = October 2001
|location           = [[Washington, D.C.]]
|key_people         = Roberta Cohen (Co-Chair, Board of Directors)&lt;br&gt; [[Andrew Natsios]] (Co-Chair, Board of Directors)&lt;br&gt; Greg Scarlatoiu (Executive Director)
|homepage           = {{URL|www.hrnk.org}}
}}

The '''Committee for Human Rights in North Korea''' (HRNK), formerly known as the U.S. Committee for Human Rights in North Korea, is a Washington D.C.-based non-governmental research organization that “seeks to raise awareness about conditions in North Korea and to publish research that focuses the world’s attention on human rights abuses in that country.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=U.S. Committee for Human Rights in North Korea|url=http://hrnk.org/|publisher=The Committee for Human Rights in North Korea|accessdate=24 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

Founded in 2001 by a group of foreign policy and human rights specialists, HRNK has published twelve reports on issues relevant to North Korean human rights today.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=HRNK Publications|url=http://hrnk.org/publications-2/|publisher=Committee for Human Rights in North Korea|accessdate=24 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;   The Committee’s leadership has testified to Congress about North Korean human rights and China’s forced repatriation of North Korean refugees.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Testimony of Greg Scarlatoiu, Executive Director of the Committee for Human Rights in North Korea|url=http://foreignaffairs.house.gov/112/sca092011.pdf|publisher=U.S. House Committee on Foreign Affairs|accessdate=24 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Greg Scarlatoiu - Congressional-Executive Commission on China|url=http://cecc.gov/pages/hearings/general/hearing5/CECC%20Hearing%20-%20China's%20Repatriation%20of%20North%20Korean%20Refugees%20Hearing%20-%20Greg%20Scarlatoiu%20Witness%20Statement.pdf|publisher=Congressional-Executive Commission on China|accessdate=24 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;    In April 2012, HRNK held its first major conference on North Korean human rights to launch its publication, ''The Hidden Gulag, Second Edition'' on North Korean political prison camps.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Hidden Gulag April 10|url=http://mansfieldfdn.org/blog/hidden-gulag-april-10/|publisher=The Maureen and Mike Mansfield Foundation|accessdate=24 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==

===Establishment===
Founded in 2001 by a group of foreign policy and human rights specialists, HRNK filled a major gap in non-governmental expertise on North Korea.  Well-established organizations such as Amnesty International and Human Rights Watch initially found it difficult to incorporate North Korea, where information is notoriously challenging to obtain, into traditional models of research and advocacy.  HRNK, an explicitly non-partisan research organization, began to break new ground in 2003 with the first edition of The Hidden Gulag by David Hawk.  This was the first comprehensive study of North Korea’s prison camp system.

===Non-Partisan Credibility===
From the beginning, HRNK cultivated its image as a non-partisan holder of expertise on North Korea in the United States.  Early members of the Board of Directors included individuals with varying political affiliations and policy prescriptions—including Chuck Downs, Nicholas Eberstadt, Carl Gershman, Morton Abramowitz, and Samantha Powers. 
Co-chairs of the Board of Directors included US Representative Stephen J. Solarz and Ambassador James R. Lilley, for whom the North Korean Human Rights Act of 2001 is named.  Solarz, a former New York Democratic congressman, was known as the “Marco Polo of Congress” for his long record of international travel and involvement in foreign affairs.  Most notably, he was the first American politician to visit Kim Il-sung.  Lilley was personally close to former President George HW Bush and served as Ambassador to the Republic of Korea and the People’s Republic of China.  Both Solarz and Lilley garnered respect from both sides of the aisle and emphasized a spirit of bipartisan comity.

===&quot;Hidden Gulag&quot; Conference===
HRNK hosted its first major conference on the &quot;Hidden Gulag,&quot; addressing North Korea’s network of political prison camps, in Washington D.C. on April 10, 2012.  HRNK launched its publication, the second edition of ''The Hidden Gulag'' by former Amnesty International Executive Director and human rights specialist David Hawk, at the conference.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Hidden Gulag April 10|url=http://mansfieldfdn.org/blog/hidden-gulag-april-10/|publisher=The Maureen and Mike Mansfield Foundation|accessdate=24 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;   

The conference attracted significant media attention, including an editorial in The Washington Post that touted the conference as “unprecedented.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Turning A Blind Eye To North Korea's &quot;Hidden Gulag&quot;|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/north-koreas-hidden-gulag/2012/04/12/gIQASJP3CT_story.html|publisher=The Washington Post|accessdate=24 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Robert King, the U.S. Special Envoy for North Korean Human Rights Issues, addressed the conference.  Glyn Davies, the U.S. Special Representative for North Korean Policy, was also in attendance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=JBI Co-Sponsors Conference on Human Rights in North Korea|url=http://www.jbi-humanrights.org/jacob-blaustein-institute/2012/04/jbi-co-sponsors-conference-on-human-rights-in-north-korea.html|publisher=The Jacob Blaustein Institute for the Advancement of Human Rights|accessdate=24 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Publications==
HRNK has released 12 publications on North Korean human rights, based on independent research and the testimony of [[North Korean defectors]].  The most recent publications have addressed the North Korean security apparatus, North Korea’s “songbun” social classification system, and the Kim regime’s network of “hidden gulag” political prison camps.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=HRNK Publications|url=http://hrnk.org/publications-2/|publisher=Committee for Human Rights in North Korea|accessdate=24 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

# ''Marked For Life: Songbun, North Korea's Social Classification System'' by Robert Collins (2012)
# ''The Hidden Gulag, Second Edition'' by David Hawk (2012)
# ''Taken! North Korea's Criminal Abduction of Citizens in Other Countries'' by Yoshi Yamamoto (2011)
# ''North Korea After Kim Jong-il: Can We Hope for Better Human Rights Protection?'' by Kim Kwang-jin (2011)
# ''Lives for Sale: Personal Accounts of Women Fleeing North Korea to China'' by Lee Hae-young (2009)
# ''After Kim Jong-il: Can We Hope for Better Human Rights Protection?'' by Kim Kwang-jin (2009)
# ''Failure to Protect: The Ongoing Challenge of North Korea'' by DLA Piper LLC (2008)
# ''Legal Strategies for Protecting Human Rights in North Korea'' by Skadden, Arps, Meagher &amp; Flom LLP (2007)
# ''Failure to Protect: A Call for the UN Security Council to Act in North Korea'' by DLA Piper LLC (2006)
# ''The North Korean Refugee Crisis: Human Rights and International Response'' by Stephen Haggard and Marcus Noland (2006)
# ''Hunger and Human Rights: The Politics of Famine in North Korea'' by Stephen Haggard and Marcus Noland  (2005)
# ''The Hidden Gulag, First Edition'' by David Hawk (2003)

==HRNK and Congress==
In September 2011, HRNK Executive Director Greg Scarlatoiu testified at a hearing of the House Foreign Affairs Subcommittee on Africa, Global Health, and Human Rights entitled “Human Rights in North Korea: Challenges and Opportunities.”  Scarlatoiu particularly emphasized the flow of information into North Korea, recommending on behalf of HRNK that “the United States should continue to expand radio broadcasting into North Korea and encourage other efforts that provide information directly to the North Korean people in accordance with the North Korean Human Rights Act.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Testimony of Greg Scarlatoiu, Executive Director of the Committee for Human Rights in North Korea|url=http://foreignaffairs.house.gov/112/sca092011.pdf|publisher=U.S. House Committee on Foreign Affairs|accessdate=24 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Congressional-Executive Commission on China received testimony from HRNK Chair Roberta Cohen and Executive Director Greg Scarlatoiu on March 5, 2012 at a hearing on “China’s Repatriation of North Korean Refugees.” HRNK presented six recommendations to the Commission and encouraged China to fulfill international obligations to protect North Korean refugees.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Greg Scarlatoiu - Congressional-Executive Commission on China|url=http://cecc.gov/pages/hearings/general/hearing5/CECC%20Hearing%20-%20China's%20Repatriation%20of%20North%20Korean%20Refugees%20Hearing%20-%20Greg%20Scarlatoiu%20Witness%20Statement.pdf|publisher=Congressional-Executive Commission on China|accessdate=24 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Board of Directors==
HRNK's Board of Directors includes prominent individuals from the North Korea and human rights policy communities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Board of Directors|url=http://hrnk.org/sample-page/the-board-of-directors/|publisher=Committee for Human Rights in North Korea|accessdate=24 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Roberta Cohen&lt;br&gt;
'''Co-Chair'''&lt;br&gt;
Non-Resident Senior Fellow, Brookings Institution



Andrew Natsios&lt;br&gt;
'''Co-Chair'''&lt;br&gt;
Former Director, U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID)



Suzanne Scholte&lt;br&gt;
'''Vice Co-Chair'''&lt;br&gt;
President, Defense Forum Foundation&lt;br&gt;
Seoul Peace Prize Laureate



Gordon Flake&lt;br&gt;
'''Vice Co-Chair'''&lt;br&gt;
Executive Director, The Maureen and Mike Mansfield Foundation



Helen Louise-Hunter&lt;br&gt;
'''Secretary'''&lt;br&gt;
Attorney&lt;br&gt;
Author, ''Kim Il Song's North Korea''



John Despres&lt;br&gt;
'''Treasurer'''&lt;br&gt;
Consultant on International Financial and Strategic Affairs



Morton Abramowitz&lt;br&gt;
Senior Fellow, The Century Foundation



Jerome Cohen&lt;br&gt;
Of Counsel (Retired Partner), Paul, Weiss, Rifkind, Wharton &amp; Garrison LLP



Lisa Colacurcio&lt;br&gt;
Advisor, Impact Investments



Rabbi Abraham Cooper&lt;br&gt;
Associate Dean of The Simon Wiesenthal Center, LA



Jack David&lt;br&gt;
Senior Fellow, Hudson Institute



Paula Dobriansky&lt;br&gt;
Senior Vice President and Head of Government Affairs, Thomson Reuters



Nicholas Eberstadt
Henry Wendt Chair in Political Economy at the American Enterprise Institute

==See also==
* [[Human rights in North Korea]]

==References==
{{reflist}}
{{refbegin}}
*[http://www.hrnk.org U.S. Committee for Human Rights in North Korea]
**[http://www.hrnk.org/download/The%20Hidden%20Gulag.pdf The Hidden Gulag: Exposing North Korea's Prison Camps Prisoners' Testimonies and Satellite Photograph (2003)]
**[http://www.hrnk.org/hunger/hungerReport05.pdf Hunger and Human Rights: The Politics of Famine in North Korea (2005)]
**[http://www.hrnk.org/failureToProtect-Report.pdf  Failure to Protect: A Call to the UN Security Council to Act in North Korea (2006)]
**[http://www.hrnk.org/refugeesReport06.pdf  The North Korean Refugee Crisis: Human Rights and International Response (2006)]
**[http://www.hrnk.org/legalStrategies-1107.pdf  Legal Strategies for Protecting Human Rights in North Korea (2007)]
{{refend}}

[[Category:Political organizations in the United States]]
[[Category:Human rights in North Korea]]

[[ru:Комитет США по правам человека в Северной Корее]]
[[uk:Комітет США з прав людини в Північній Кореї]]</text>
      <sha1>8vjscbr5agf7z26nprljll0uz347w2c</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
