<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>United We Stand America</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1047294</id>
    <revision>
      <id>501239701</id>
      <parentid>500340770</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-07-08T13:10:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>RussBot</username>
        <id>279219</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Robot: Editing intentional link to disambiguation page in hatnote per [[WP:INTDABLINK]] [[User:RussBot#About the hatnote task|(explanation)]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3486">{{Other uses|United We Stand (disambiguation){{!}}United We Stand}}
{{Unreferenced|date=August 2009}}
'''United We Stand America''' was the name selected by [[Texas]] businessman [[Ross Perot|H. Ross Perot]] for his citizen action organization after his 1992 independent political campaign for [[President of the United States]].  Perot's 19% showing in the [[U.S. presidential election, 1992|1992 election]] was sufficient to entitle him to federal matching funds for the 1996 campaign. After the campaign, Perot announced, on January 11, 1993, the formation of a non-profit watchdog organization named United We Stand America.

==History==
In the early 1990s, many people were talking about forming a new political party.  These discussions centered around [[populism|populist]] themes.  The eventual result of the movement that followed was ''United We Stand America'', followed by the Reform Party.

The early history of UWSA revolved around establishment of chapters in all 50 states and citizen activism against the [[North American Free Trade Agreement]] (NAFTA).  The first state granted a charter by the national leadership of UWSA, [[Virginia]], was chartered in June 1993. In November 1993 Ross Perot and vice-president [[Al Gore]] conducted a nationally televised debate about NAFTA on [[CNN]] which is still the most widely viewed political program in US history. {{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}

UWSA remained active under Perot's leadership until late 1995 when the paid staff was moved to a new organization dubbed &quot;Citizens for the Reform Party&quot; which actively campaigned to petition the [[Reform Party of the United States of America|Reform Party]] on to the ballot in all 50 states for the 1996 presidential election.  The name of Perot's organization conflicted with that of a [[United Way of America|United Way]]-type [[LGBT]] group, which had [[copyright]]ed the name 'United We Stand'.

==Founding of the Reform Party==
{{main|Reform Party of the United States of America}}

The Reform Party, founded in 1995 with ballot access in all 50 states, nominated Ross Perot for President after a convention battle between Perot and [[Richard Lamm]], former [[governor of Colorado]].
Perot's running mate in 1996 was [[Pat Choate]], a well-known author, economist and professor.  The future of the Reform Party was somewhat clouded by the 1996 election results when the Perot/Choate ticket received only 9% of the overall vote.  Since many states require a minimum of 10% to retain ballot access, the ability of the party to field candidates without the time and expense of petition drives was limited.  However, based on the 1996 results, the party retained the ability to earn federal [[matching funds]] in the 2000 Presidential election - a fact that was not lost on [[Pat Buchanan]].  The battle for control of the Reform Party between many of the founding members and Buchanan's weakened the Reform Party to the extent that it has diminished as a factor in U.S. politics in the years since the 2000 election.

United We Stand America exists today as a [[website]] which appears to be re-purposed as a debt-consolidation web site.
Archives of material from the original organization can be found at http://www.uwsa.com/books/Uwsabook.html, but the original group founded by Ross Perot ceased to be active after the Reform Party was founded in 1995.

[[Category:Civic and political organizations of the United States]]
[[Category:Ross Perot]]


{{US-poli-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>slbmoaot28f909wzuqqq1hm5g1qqvkl</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
