<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Universal health care</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>570661</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521843420</id>
      <parentid>521841523</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-07T16:24:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Saddhiyama</username>
        <id>5160420</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/204.113.117.32|204.113.117.32]] ([[User talk:204.113.117.32|talk]]): Rv nonsense editorialising. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="19147">{{Use mdy dates|date=November 2011}}
[[File:Universal health care.svg|thumb|300px|Universal health care around the world (November 2010).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.pacifichealthsummit.org/downloads/UHC/the%20political%20economy%20of%20uhc.PDF|title=The political economy of universal health coverage|authors=David Stuckler, Andrea B Feigl, Sanjay Basu, Martin McKee|date=November 2010|journal=Global symposium on health systems research, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
{{space}}
{{legend|#3CE67B|Nations with universal health care (determined by proxy of ≥90% skilled birth attendance and ≥90% social insurance coverage)}}
{{legend|#FFD0D0|Nations with legislated mandate for Universal health coverage, but which have not yet reached thresholds above}}]]
{{see also|Universal health coverage by country}}

'''Universal health care''' — sometimes referred to as '''universal health coverage''', '''universal coverage''', '''universal care''' or '''social health protection''' — usually refers to a [[health care]] system which provides health care and financial protection to all its citizens. It is organized around providing a specified package of benefits to all members of a society with the end goal of providing financial risk protection, improved access to health services, and improved health outcomes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=2010 World Health Report|url=http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universal_health_care#cite_note-whqlibdoc.who.int-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Universal health care is not a one-size-fits-all concept; nor does it imply coverage for all people for everything. Universal health care can be determined by three critical dimensions: who is covered, what services are covered, and how much of the cost is covered.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=2010 World Health Report|url=http://www.who.int/healthsystems/topics/financing/healthreport/en/index.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
Germany has the world's oldest universal health care system, with origins dating back to [[Otto von Bismarck]]'s [[Otto von Bismarck#Bismarck's social legislation|social legislation]], which included the [[Health Insurance Bill of 1883]], [[Accident Insurance Bill of 1884]], and [[Old Age and Disability Insurance Bill of 1889]]. In the United Kingdom, the [[National Insurance Act 1911]] marked the first steps there towards universal health care, covering most employed persons and their financial dependents and all persons who had been continuous contributors to the scheme for at least five years whether they were working or not. This system of health insurance continued in force until the creation of the [[National Health Service]] in 1948 which extended health care security to all legal residents. Most current universal health care systems were implemented in the [[Aftermath of World War II|period following the Second World War]] as a process of [[health care reform]], intended to make health care available to all, in the spirit of Article 25 of the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]] of 1948, signed by every country doing so. The US did not ratify the [[International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights|social and economic rights]] sections, including Article 25's [[right to health]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web|url=http://www.amnestyusa.org/escr/files/escr_qa.pdf |format=PDF|title=Economic, Social and Cultural Rights: Questions and Answers |accessdate=2008-06-02 |publisher=Amnesty International |page=6 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Funding models==
{{see also|Health care economics}}
Universal health care in most countries has been achieved by a mixed model of funding. General taxation revenue is the primary source of funding, but in many countries it is supplemented by specific levies (which may be charged to the individual and/or an employer) or with the option of private payments (either direct or via optional insurance) for services beyond those covered by the public system.

Almost all European systems are financed through a mix of public and private contributions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bentes&quot;&gt;Bentes M, Dias CM, Sakellarides C, Bankauskaite V. [http://www.euro.who.int/document/e82937.pdf#search=%22Portugal%2C%20health%20care%22 ''Health Care Systems in Transition: Portuagal.''] WHO are Regional Offices for Europe on behalf of the European Observatory on Health Systems and Policies, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; The majority of universal health care systems are funded primarily by [[tax revenue]] (e.g. Portugal&lt;ref name=&quot;Bentes&quot;/&gt; Spain, Denmark and Sweden). Some nations, such as Germany, France&lt;ref name=&quot;Physicians 1&quot;&gt;Physicians for a National Health Program [http://www.pnhp.org/facts/international_health_systems.php?page=all &quot;International Health Systems&quot;.]&lt;/ref&gt; and Japan&lt;ref name=&quot;Chua&quot;&gt;Chua, Kao-Ping. [http://www.amsa.org/uhc/SinglePayer101.pdf &quot;Single Payer 101&quot;.] February 10, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; employ a multi-payer system in which health care is funded by private and public contributions. However, much of the non-government funding is by contributions by employers and employees to regulated [[non-profit]] sickness funds. These contributions are compulsory and defined according to law. 

A distinction is also made between municipal and national healthcare funding. For example, one model is that the bulk of the healthcare is funded by the municipality, speciality healthcare is provided and possibly funded by a larger entity, such as a municipal co-operation board or the state, and the medications are paid by a state agency.

Universal health care systems are modestly redistributive. Progressivity of health care financing has limited implications for overall income inequality.&lt;ref&gt;Sherry A. Glied, [http://www.nber.org/papers/w13881.pdf &quot;Health Care Financing, Efficiency, and Equity,&quot;] [[National Bureau of Economic Research]] Working Paper No. 13881, March 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

===Compulsory insurance===
{{main|National health insurance}}
[[File:Social health protection.svg|thumb|300px|'''Social health protection:'''&lt;ref&gt;Per ILO, &quot;Social health protection is defined by the ILO as a series of public or publicly organized and mandated private measures against social distress and economic loss caused by the reduction of productivity, stoppage or reduction of earnings, or the cost of necessary treatment that can result from ill health.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Proportion of the population covered by law, latest available year (percentages)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=International Labour Organization|authorlink=:en:International Labour Organization|url=http://www.ilo.org/gimi/gess/RessShowRessource.do?ressourceId=15263|title=World Social Security Report 2010/11: Providing coverage in times of crisis and beyond|year=2010|isbn=978-92-2-123269-8|format=PDF|publisher=International Labour Office|location=Geneva}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
{{space}}
{{legend|#FFFF66|Less than 10%}}
{{legend|#A1DAB4|10-40%}}
{{legend|#41B6C4|40-70%}}
{{legend|#2C7FB8|70-95%}}
{{legend|#253494|More than 95%}}
{{legend|#e0e0e0|No data}}
]]

This is usually enforced via legislation requiring residents to purchase insurance, though sometimes, in effect, the government provides the insurance. Sometimes there may be a choice of multiple public and private funds providing a standard service (as in Germany) or sometimes just a single public fund (as in Canada). The U.S. [[Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act]] is a law based on compulsory insurance.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2010/mar/22/health-care-vote-us-obama |location=London |work=The Guardian  | title=Healthcare vote: Barack Obama passes US health reform by narrow margin | date=March 22, 2010 | first=Michael | last=Tomasky}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In some European countries where there is private insurance and universal health care, such as Germany, Belgium, and The Netherlands, the problem of adverse selection (see Private insurance below) is overcome using a risk compensation pool to equalize, as far as possible, the risks between funds. Thus a fund with a predominantly healthy, younger population has to pay into a compensation pool and a fund with an older and predominantly less healthy population would receive funds from the pool. In this way, sickness funds compete on price and there is no advantage to eliminate people with higher risks because they are compensated for by means of risk-adjusted capitation payments. Funds are not allowed to pick and choose their policyholders or deny coverage, but then mainly compete on price and service. In some countries the basic coverage level is set by the government and cannot be modified.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://goliath.ecnext.com/coms2/browse_R_R016 |title=Goliath – Research in Healthcare Financial Management – Industry &amp; Business News Articles – Article, News, Research, Information |publisher=Goliath.ecnext.com |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ireland at one time had a &quot;community rating&quot; system through [[VHI]], effectively a single-payer or common risk pool. The government later opened VHI to competition but without a compensation pool. This resulted in foreign insurance companies entering the Irish market and offering cheap health insurance to relatively healthy segments of the market which then made higher profits at VHI's expense. The government later re-introduced community rating through a pooling arrangement and at least one main major insurance company, [[BUPA]], then withdrew from the Irish market.

Among the potential solutions posited by economists are single payer systems as well as other methods of ensuring that health insurance is universal, such as by requiring all citizens to purchase insurance and limiting the ability of insurance companies to deny insurance to individuals or vary price between individuals.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Rothschild and Joseph Stiglitz, &quot;Equilibrium in Competitive Insurance Markets: An Essay on the Economics of Imperfect Information,&quot; Quarterly Journal of Economics, November 1976 (90:629–649) (known as the Rothschild-Stiglitz Model)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Paulo Belli, [http://www-wds.worldbank.org/servlet/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2001/04/13/000094946_01040505331570/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf ''How Adverse Selection Affects the Health Insurance Market'']&lt;/ref&gt;

===Tax-based financing===
In tax-based financing, individuals contribute to the provision of health services through various taxes. These are typically pooled across the whole population, unless local governments raise and retain tax revenues. Some countries (notably the United Kingdom, Ireland, Italy, Spain, Portugal, Greece and the Nordic countries) choose to fund health care directly from taxation alone. Other countries with insurance-based systems effectively meet the cost of insuring those unable to insure themselves via [[social security]] arrangements funded from taxation, either by directly paying their medical bills or by paying for insurance premiums for those affected.

===Social Health Insurance===
In social health insurance, contributions from workers, the self-employed, enterprises and government are pooled into a single or multiple funds on a compulsory basis. These funds typically contract with a mix of public and private providers for the provision of a specified benefit package. Preventive and public health care may be provided by these funds or responsibility kept solely by the Ministry of Health. Within social health insurance, a number of functions may be executed by parastatal or non-governmental sickness funds or in a few cases by private health insurance companies. 

===Private insurance===
In private health insurance, premiums are paid directly from employers, associations, individuals and families to insurance companies, which pool risks across their membership base. Private insurance includes policies sold by commercial for profit firms, non-profit companies, and community health insurers. Generally private insurance is voluntary in contrast to social insurance programs that tend to be compulsory.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=World Health Organization Health Financing Unit|url=http://www.who.int/health_financing/mechanisms/en/index3.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

In some countries with universal coverage, private insurance often excludes many health conditions which are expensive and which the state health care system can provide. For example, in the UK, one of the largest private health care providers is [[BUPA]], which has a long list of general exclusions even in its highest coverage policy,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bupa.co.uk/individuals/health-insurance/treatment-care/treatment-care-exclusions|title=BUPA top coverage product and exclusion list |publisher=Bupa.co.uk |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; most of which are routinely provided by the [[National Health Service|NHS]]. In the USA dialysis treatment for end stage renal failure is generally paid for by government and not by the insurance industry. Persons with privatized Medicare (Medicare Advantage) are the exception and must get their dialysis paid through their insurance company, but persons with end stage renal failure generally cannot buy Medicare Advantage plans.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.medicare.gov/Publications/Pubs/pdf/10128.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

The Planning Commission of India has also suggested that the country should embrace insurance to achieve universal health &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.downtoearth.org.in/content/universal-health-scare Down To Earth: Universal health scare]&lt;/ref&gt;coverage. As of now general tax is used to meet the essential health requirements of all people.

===Single payer===
{{Main|Single-payer health care}}
The term single-payer health care is used in the United States to describe a funding mechanism meeting the costs of medical care from a single fund. Although the fund holder is usually the government, some forms of single-payer employ a public-private system.

===Community-based Health Insurance===
A particular form of private health insurance that has often emerged in environments where financial risk protection mechanisms only have a limited impact is community-based health insurance. Contributions are not risk-related, and there is generally a high level of community involvement in the running of such schemes.

==Implementation and comparisons==
{{main|Universal health coverage by country}}
{{See also|Health care system|Health systems by country}}
[[File:Total health expenditure per capita, US Dollars PPP.png|thumb|250px|Health spending per capita, in US$ [[Purchasing power parity|PPP-adjusted]], amongst various first world nations.]]
Universal health care systems vary according to the extent of government involvement in providing care and/or health insurance. In some countries, such as the UK, Spain, Italy and the Nordic countries, the government has a high degree of involvement in the commissioning or delivery of health care services and access is based on residence rights not on the purchase of insurance. Others have a much more pluralistic delivery system based on obligatory health with contributory insurance rates related to salaries or income, and usually funded by employers and beneficiaries jointly. Sometimes the health funds are derived from a mixture of insurance premiums, salary related mandatory contributions by employees and/or employers to regulated sickness funds, and by government taxes. These insurance based systems tend to reimburse private or public medical providers, often at heavily regulated rates, through mutual or publicly owned medical insurers. A few countries such as the Netherlands and Switzerland operate via privately owned but heavily regulated private insurers that are not allowed to make a profit from the mandatory element of insurance but can profit by selling supplemental insurance.

Universal health care is a broad concept that has been implemented in several ways. The common denominator for all such programs is some form of government action aimed at extending access to health care as widely as possible and setting minimum standards. Most implement universal health care through legislation, regulation and taxation. Legislation and regulation direct what care must be provided, to whom, and on what basis. Usually some costs are borne by the patient at the time of consumption but the bulk of costs come from a combination of compulsory insurance and tax revenues. Some programs are paid for entirely out of tax revenues. In others tax revenues are used either to fund insurance for the very poor or for those needing long term chronic care. The UK government's [[National Audit Office (United Kingdom)|National Audit Office]] in 2003 published an international comparison of ten different health care systems in ten developed countries, nine universal systems against one non-universal system (the U.S.), and their relative costs and key health outcomes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nao.org.uk/idoc.ashx?docId=e902d344-ab56-4808-ab63-399241d33484&amp;version=-1 |title=International Health Comparisons: A Compendium of published information on healthcare systems, the provision of health care and health achievement in 10 countries |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; A wider international comparison of 16 countries, each with universal health care, was published by the [[World Health Organization]] in 2004&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.euro.who.int/document/e85400.pdf Snapshots of Health Systems: The state of affairs in 16 countries in summer 2004 WHO]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In some cases, government involvement also includes directly managing the [[health care system]], but many countries use mixed public-private systems to deliver universal health care.

==See also==
&lt;!-- Please maintain in alphabetical order --&gt;
*[[Health care reform debate in the United States]]
*[[Health insurance cooperative]]
*[[Health system]]
*[[National health insurance]]
*[[Public health]]
*[[Publicly-funded health care]]
*[[Socialized medicine]]
*[[Single-payer health care]]
*[[Two-tier health care]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
&lt;!-- Please maintain in alphabetical order --&gt;
*[http://www.medicc.org/mediccreview/index.php?issue=17 ''MEDICC Review'' theme issue on Achieving Universal Health Care] Authors from 19 countries on dimensions of the challenges of providing universal access to health care.
*[http://www.pnhp.org/ Physicians for a National Health Program] A group of physicians and health professionals who support single-payer reform.
*[http://www.rockefellerfoundation.org/news/publications/catalyzing-change-system-reform-costs The System Reform Costs of Universal Health Coverage] Rockefeller Foundation report on the feasibility of establishing the systems and institutions needed to pursue UHC
*[http://www.universalhealthcareprosandcons.com/ The Pros and Cons of Universal Health Care] A group of journalists who support universal health care.
*[http://uhcforward.org/ UHC Forward] Portal on Universal Health Coverage

{{DEFAULTSORT:Universal Health Care}}
[[Category:Universal healthcare| ]]
[[Category:Health economics]]
[[Category:Health insurance]]

[[es:Asistencia sanitaria universal]]
[[eu:Osasun arreta unibertsal]]
[[ne:युनिभर्सल हेल्थ केयर]]
[[ja:健康保険]]
[[uk:Обов'язкове медичне страхування]]</text>
      <sha1>nlwse3juzwfimehv5v1jio4j5a442ct</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
