<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Urban75</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5208235</id>
    <revision>
      <id>517366289</id>
      <parentid>476853349</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-12T10:28:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yobot</username>
        <id>7328338</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[WP:CHECKWIKI]] error 61 fix, References after punctuation per [[WP:REFPUNC]] and [[WP:PAIC]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (8459)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8221">[[Image:Urban75 homepage.PNG|thumb|The Urban75 homepage]]'''Urban75''' (also sometimes referred to as '''u75''' or '''urban''') is a website and messageboard based in [[Brixton]], [[England]]. It was founded in 1995 and includes various e-zine content, as well as [[bulletin boards]]. The site was founded and is currently run by Mike Slocombe.

==History==
Urban75 initially originated from a [[football (soccer)|football]] [[comic]] that started in 1991.  Its editor claims that &quot;the first issue sold out in three hours and at one point became the fastest-selling small press [[comic]] in the [[United Kingdom|UK]].&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.urban75.org/comics/bjonesintr.html Bluebird Jones]&lt;/ref&gt;{{Failed verification|date=May 2010}}

From here, a ''Football Fans Against The Criminal Justice Act'' [[Advertising campaign|campaign]] started in 1994. The campaign received large amounts of exposure in the media, and in May 1995 a helper on the campaign from [[Brighton]] put together the first version of the Urban75 site, using a [[modem]] donated by [[The Levellers (band)|The Levellers]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mcspotlight.org/media/press/wired_17jun97.html Wired world: Eighties survivor cracks the zine scene], ''[[Wired magazine|Wired]]''&lt;/ref&gt;

As the site expanded into areas other than football and protest, it grew in popularity and was moved to a different, bigger server (becoming part of The Head-Space Project until it moved to its own domain in 1998).  Early publicity was generated by [[Adobe Shockwave|Shockwave]] games in which celebrities could be virtually &quot;slapped&quot; or &quot;punched&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ojr.org/ojr/workplace/1017968134.php The Urban Web Warrior:Urban75's Mike Slocombe] [[Online Journalism Review]]&lt;/ref&gt;

Urban75 entered the national news when Brixton's police chief [[Brian Paddick]] posted on the bulletin boards in order to discuss issues with Brixton's internet users while he was conducting a [[cannabis]] tolerance experiment. However, when the [[tabloid journalism|tabloid]] press discovered Paddick's posting on the site, a scandal was born.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/gayrights/story/0,12592,1095048,00.html The Guardian profile: Brian Paddick], [[Guardian Unlimited]]&lt;/ref&gt; In particular, the press highlighted one post on the boards, where Paddick supposedly said &quot;The concept of anarchy has always appealed to me&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbcmar02&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/1866274.stm Police chief rebuked over 'anarchy' remark], [[BBC]] 2002-03-11. Retrieved 2010-12-31.&lt;/ref&gt; Paddick subsequently met with the Metropolitan Police Commissioner, Sir John Stevens, and accepted criticism of his remarks.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbcmar02&quot; /&gt; No disciplinary action was taken&lt;ref name=&quot;bbcmar02&quot; /&gt; and Paddick remained in his post until his retirement in 2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbcapr07&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/6599007.stm Met's Paddick set to retire early], BBC, 2007-04-27. Retrieved 2010-12-31.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Site content==
The 'Action' section of the site contains an events diary, information, articles, reports and photos from various protests and marches.

Urban75 features around 3,500 original photographs, mostly taken by the site's owner. There are galleries of Brixton, [[London]], [[New York]], [[Chicago]], [[Brighton]], and [[Wales]], as well as various 360° [[panorama]]s and photography tutorials.

There is a drugs information section of the site. There is information on most well-known drugs available. The site has stated its aim is to give honest information about drug effects, so people can make their own informed decision.

There is a series of links to the bulletin board on drugs, although this requires registration.

The site features dozens of 'useless' games, made by various web designers.
The games section revels in the fact that many games are pointless and have no meaning (such as 'The DOT-CLICKING game' and 'The Curious Thingy!'). The most popular games are:
* ''Mr Insult'' - a series of games based on a character who swears frequently
* ''The Cossack'' - games with a mysterious Soviet character
* ''Punch a Celeb'' - a section where images of nominated [[celebrities]] are clicked on and are, supposedly, punched.
* ''Slap a Spice Girl'' - a hugely popular game that was available at the height of the [[Spice Girls]] fame.

Despite being the website's popular feature, the ''Slap a Spice Girl'' game has since been removed for unknown reasons.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.urban75.com/Punch/spicebelt.html urban75 information page&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Football (soccer)|Football]] remains a solid part of the site, with articles and features on recent cup competitions as well information as on the [[Criminal Justice Act]] and original strips from the ''Bluebird Jones'' comic.

==The boards==
The [[internet forums|bulletin boards]] have grown into a popular community, with over 40,000 registered members. At present, there are around a quarter of a million page impressions each day,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.alexa.com/data/details/traffic_details?url=urban75.net Alexa Traffic rankings for Urban75]&lt;/ref&gt; with around 5-6,000 new posts daily. There are currently 26 sub forums covering a range of topics.

The forums are divided into &quot;General discussion&quot;, &quot;Community forums&quot;, &quot;Politics, protest and current affairs&quot;, &quot;Travel &amp; places&quot; and &quot;Art, tech &amp; science&quot;, in addition to an archive section.

==Offline Club==

The first Offline club night was held on 19 February 2004, at the Brixton Ritzy cinema, and featured DJs only. The line-up included Dubversion of [[People's Republic Of Disco]], DJ Hoax of Urbanites and Hedge Party infamy, Ian of [[How Does It Feel To Be Loved?]], and Blagsta.

Organised by the site's editor, Offline showcases a wide range of [[DJ]]s, bands, poets, videos and artists. On 30 September 2004, the club expanded to the Dogstar club in Brixton, and has been hosted at other venues in Brixton, Crystal Palace, central London and occasionally New York.

Its growing popularity forced a move to the larger Brixton Jamm club in 2006 before transferring back to the Dogstar on April 9, 2009, with the club now occupying three rooms and two floors in the central Brixton  venue.

In line with the club's eclectic tastes, [http://www.urban75.org/offline/offline58_dogstar.html the Dogstar relaunch party] featured a large bill including samba drummers, go-go girls, punk rock bands, poets and a hip hop vocal performance.

A second, regular live music night takes place in the Prince Albert bar on Coldharbour Lane, London SW9.

Offline has put on well known acts such as Mercury Prize nominees The Portico Quartet, author [[Howard Marks]], comedians [[Robert Newman (comedian)|Rob Newman]], [[Stewart Lee]], [[Josie Long]], [[Robin Ince]], [[Richard Herring]] and new wave legend [[Tom Robinson]], with all acts being paid two pints of beer.

Described as being &quot;Like someone's friendly house party, opened up for the general public....Entertaining, friendly, and free&quot; [http://londonist.com/2008/05/review_offline.php The Londonist], the Offline club nights are always free.

==Radio==
On May 1, 2005 a group of posters made a [[television pilot|pilot]] radio show for the website, available to download as an [[mp3]]. The three pilots that followed including an interview with the manager of the site, some originally recorded music contributed by members, documentaries, and live recordings from the Offline club night. There is now a mainly music based radio channel which is updated as and when new shows are recorded.

==Press==
Posters can find themselves quoted in national papers or other websites. An example is when Rachel North, a survivor of the London tube bombings, posted an account on the boards of her experience, which became a [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/4670099.stm blog on the BBC website].&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/4670099.stm#saturday Tube Survivor Blog]&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.urban75.com/ Urban75]
* [http://www.urban75.net/vbulletin/ Urban75 bulletin boards]
* [http://www.urban75.org/offline/ Offline Club Night]

[[Category:Internet forums]]
[[Category:DIY culture]]
[[Category:British websites]]

[[cy:Urban75]]
[[pt:Urban75]]
[[simple:Urban75]]</text>
      <sha1>2417cx06stam1x3es5h8hi7i9jo5bsd</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
