<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Ursinus College</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>885071</id>
    <revision>
      <id>515526631</id>
      <parentid>514883518</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-01T21:19:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>71.246.24.13</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Notable Alumni and Former Students */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27764">{{Infobox University 
|name            = Ursinus College
|image           = [[File:Ursinus College seal.png|200px]]
|established     = 1869 
|type            = [[Private university|Private]] 
|affiliation     = Secular (historically related to the [[United Church of Christ]])
|president       = [[Dr. Bobby Fong]]
|city            = [[Collegeville, Pennsylvania|Collegeville]] 
|state           = [[Pennsylvania|PA]] 
|country         = [[United States|USA]] 
|campus          = {{convert|170|acre|km2}}&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ursinus.edu/content.asp?page=WhatMakesUCSpecial/ursinus_at_a_glance.html&amp;tab=What_Makes_UC_Special ]{{dead link|date=February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|undergrad       = 1,750&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ursinus.edu/netcommunity/page.aspx?pid=203 |title= About Ursinus College |accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/ursinus-3385 |title=Ursinus &amp;#124; Ursinus College &amp;#124; Best College &amp;#124; US News |publisher=Colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com |date=2012-02-06 |accessdate=2012-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|mascot          = Grizzly Bear
|colors=Red, Old Gold, &amp; Black {{color box|Red}}{{color box|Gold}}{{color box|Black}}
|free_label = Athletics
|free = [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] Division III [[Centennial Conference]]
|endowment       = $120 million&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ursinus.edu/netcommunity/document.doc?id=1173&lt;/ref&gt;
|website         = [http://www.ursinus.edu ursinus.edu] 
|logo            = [[File:Ursinus College circle.png|200px]]
|}}
[[Image:Ursinus College Temple Sculpture.jpg|thumb|300px|The Temple is an iconic piece in the outdoor sculpture garden on the Ursinus campus]]
[[Image:Ursinus College Berman Museum.jpg|thumb|250px|Berman Museum of Art]]

'''Ursinus College''' is a [[Private school|private]], [[Independent school|independent]], [[coeducation]]al, [[Liberal arts colleges in the United States|liberal arts college]] located in [[Collegeville, Pennsylvania|Collegeville]], [[Pennsylvania]]. 

Founded in 1869, Ursinus sits on a 170-acre wooded campus approximately 25 miles from Center City [[Philadelphia]]. Ursinus is one of the eleven [[Centennial Conference]] schools, a [[Phi Beta Kappa]] college, and is a member of the [[Thomas J. Watson Fellowship]] list, [[Project Pericles]], Project DEEP, the Bonner Leader Program, and the [[Annapolis Group]]. The college is also home to the Philip and Muriel Berman Museum of Art, regarded{{by whom?|date=September 2012}} as one of the nation's finest small-college art museums.  

==History==
'''1867'''
Members of the [[Reformed Church in the United States|German Reformed Church]] begin plans to establish a college where &quot;young men could be liberally educated under the benign influence of Christianity.&quot; These founders were hoping to establish an alternative to the seminary at [[Mercersburg, Pennsylvania]], a school they believed was increasingly heretical to traditional Reformed faith.

'''1869'''
The college is granted a charter by the Legislature of Pennsylvania to begin operations in its current location on the grounds of Todd’s School (founded 1832) and the adjacent Freeland Seminary (founded 1848). Dr. John Henry Augustus Bomberger, for whom the campus' signature Romanesque building is named (see ''Gallery'', below), served as the college’s first president until his death in 1890. Bomberger had proposed naming the college after [[Zacharias Ursinus]], a 16th-century German theologian and an important figure in the [[Protestant Reformation]], in order to declare the Reformed orthodoxy of the College.

'''1870'''
Instruction begins at the college in September; on October 4, the Zwinglian Literary Society was founded. For many years the annual opening meetings of &quot;Zwing&quot; and its rival society, Schaff, were the major events of the student year.

'''1881'''
Women first admitted, as a direct consequence of the closing of the Pennsylvania Female College in 1880, and a separate literary society for women, The Olevian, is formed.

'''1893'''
The first meeting of the college's alumni association is held at the Colonnade Hotel in [[Philadelphia, Pennsylvania]].

'''1897'''
''The Ruby'', Ursinus' yearbook is first published by the Class of 1897 as a tribute to Professor Samuel Vernon Ruby, who collapsed as he was entering Bomberger Hall in 1896 and died in its chapel, surrounded by students and teachers who had gathered there for morning prayers.

'''1921'''
The first aerial photograph of Ursinus is taken, by future college president D.L. Helfferich, and is published in the 1921 ''Ruby''.

'''1995'''
The college appoints Dr. [[John Strassburger]] as its 12th president, the first president from outside the Ursinus alumni group.  Dr. Strassburger was an American Historian, a graduate of Bates College, Oxford University, and Princeton University.

'''2006'''
Ursinus College is profiled among only 40 colleges in former ''[[New York Times]]'' education editor Loren Pope's popular guidebook, ''[[Colleges That Change Lives]].''

'''2010'''
Aakash Shah '10 of Harvard Medical School is named Ursinus' first Rhodes Scholar.

'''2011'''
Dr. Bobby Fong, a graduate of Harvard and UCLA and former president of Butler University, began his tenure as the 13th president of Ursinus on July 1, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.butler.edu/absolutenm/templates/?a=2207&amp;z=22
|title=Bobby Fong To Become 13th President of Ursinus College
|date=October 29, 2010
|accessdate=February 13, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://articles.philly.com/2012-02-03/news/31021586_1_college-presidents-asian-american-higher-education
|title=Ursinus' Fong a rare Asian American college president
|newspaper=Philadelphia Inquirer
|date=February 3, 2012
|author=Jeff Gammage
|accessdate=February 13, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  For the third year in a row Ursinus is designated as a Top Ten ''Up and Coming College'' by U.S. News &amp; World Report. 

Ursinus College is now independent in character with historical but no longer any operational ties to its church past, and currently operates on a growing $118,000,000 endowment.

==Academics==
[[Image:Pfahler Hall of Science Ursinus College.jpg|thumb|left|300px|Pfahler Hall of Science]]

Ursinus established its chapter of [[Phi Beta Kappa]] in 1992. At the time, only 242 of the nation's 3,500 colleges and universities had gained acceptance into the elite group. The school is a member of the Watson Foundation List, [[Project Pericles]], Project DEEP, and the [[Annapolis Group]].

While students choose from 60 courses of study, &quot;biology, business and economics, and English are the three majors with the largest numbers of students.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.princetonreview.com/college/research/profiles/schoolsaysmore.asp?listing=1023818&amp;LTID=1&amp;intbucketid=%20&amp;category=5]&lt;/ref&gt; Many graduates go on to attend law and medical schools, with over 90 percent of Ursinus applicants accepted.{{needs citation|date=June 2012}}

==Current students==
While the first students enrolled at Ursinus were almost exclusively Pennsylvanians, today the school's 1,750 students come from 35 states and 12 countries. Twenty percent are students of color and two percent are international students. The school has a 12:1 student/faculty ratio.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.princetonreview.com/college/research/profiles/schoolsays.asp?category=1&amp;listing=1023818&amp;LTID=1&amp;intbucketid=&lt;/ref&gt;{{dead link|date=January 2012}}

==Campus and facilities==
[[Image:Ursinus kaleidoscope.jpg|thumb|300px|Kaleidoscope Performing Arts Center]]

The {{convert|170|acre|km2|sing=on}} campus is {{convert|25|mi|km}} northwest of [[Philadelphia, Pennsylvania]], and is also within three hours’ driving distance of [[New York City]], [[Baltimore, Maryland]] and [[Washington, DC]].

Notable facilities at Ursinus include:&lt;ref name=&quot;UCCampus&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ursinus.edu/netcommunity/page.aspx?pid=448 |title=The Campus Setting |publisher=Ursinus College |accessdate=February 13, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Bomberger Memorial Hall, opened in 1892 and renovated in 2006.  Bomberger Hall is named for John Henry Augustus Bomberger, the 1st President of Ursinus College.  Bomberger Auditorium is home to the Heefner Memorial Organ, a three-manual 62-rank organ dedicated in 1986, the gift of the late Mrs. Lydia V. Heefner in memory of her husband, Russell E. Heefner.
*The Phillip and Muriel Berman Museum of Art, dedicated in 1989, located in the original Alumni Memorial Library, built in 1921, expanded in 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;UCCampus&quot;/&gt;  The museum program is fully accredited by the American Association of Museums and houses over 4,000 paintings, prints, drawings, sculpture, decorative, and cultural objects representing a broad array of art historical genres.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.ursinus.edu/netcommunity/page.aspx?pid=1024
|publisher=Berman Museum
|title=About the Museum
|accessdate=February 13, 2012
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://collegenews.org/campus-news/2008/ground-broken-for-new-pfeiffer-wing-at-ursinus-berman-museum.html
|title=Ground Broken for New ‘Pfeiffer’ Wing at Ursinus’ Berman Museum
|publisher=CollegeNews.org
|date=November 5, 2008
|accessdate=February 13, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://museumpublicity.com/2010/09/25/berman-museum-of-art-opens-new-wing-and-celebrates-20-year-anniversary/
|title=Berman Museum of Art Opens New Wing and Celebrates 20-year Anniversary
|date=September 25, 2010
|publisher=MuseumPublicity.com
|accessdate=February 13, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The Eger Gate, erected in 1925.
*Brodbeck-Wilkinson-Curtis Hall, Brodbeck and Curtis opened in 1927, Wilkinson Hall, named for Joseph C. Wilkinson, opened in 1966 connecting Brodbeck and Curtis.
*Pfahler Hall &amp; the Walter W. Marstellar Memorial Observatory.  Pfahler Hall opened in 1932, renovated and expanded in 1998.  Named in honorof Dr. George E. Pfahler, famed radiologist, Pfahler Hall is where Professor John Mauchly built key components of ENIAC, considered the world’s first computer, and Nobel LaureateGerald Edelman (Ursinus Class of 1950) attended classes. Pfahler’s well-equipped laboratoriescontain a 300-MHz nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectrometer, three Fourier-transform(FTIR) spectrometers, an isothermal calorimeter, two gas chromatography/ mass spectrometers(GC/MS), a voltammetric analyzer, four U-V visible absorbance spectrometers, seven highperformance liquid chromatographs (HPLC), an atomic absorption (AA) spectrometer, a capillary electrophoresis (CE) apparatus, a Mössbauer spectrometer, and a fluorescence spectrometer.&lt;ref name=&quot;UCCampus&quot;/&gt;
*Beardwood-Paisley-Stauffer  Hall, opened in 1957, named in honor of Hannah Beardwood and her husband Matthew, a chemistry professor at Ursinus from 1903 until 1940, Dr. Harry Paisley, president of the Ursinus board of directors from 1910 till 1961, and Rev. George A. Stauffer, class of 1894.
[[Image:Curtis Hall Ursinus College.jpg|thumb|left|275px|Curtis Hall, where [[J.D. Salinger]] lived on the third floor during his time at Ursinus]]
*Wismer Center, opened in 1964, named for Ralph Fry Wismer, class of 1905.
*Reimert Hall, opened in 1966, named for William D. Reimert, class of 1924.
*Corson Hall, dedicated in 1970.
*Thomas Hall, opened in 1970 and renovated in 1991, it is the home of the Biology and Psychology departments and the following endowed laboratories: Levi Jay Hammond Laboratory of Comparative Anatomy, the W. Wayne Babcock Laboratory of GeneralBiology, the Anna Heinly Schellhammer Laboratory, and the Parlee Laboratory.&lt;ref name=&quot;UCCampus&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://articles.philly.com/1992-06-07/news/26030531_1_president-richard-p-richter-berman-museum-ursinus-college
|title=Ursinus College Sets Fund-raising Goal Of $39 Million By 1994 It Will Be The College's Largest Effort. The Endowment, Library, Renovation Projects And Student Life Would Gain.
|newspaper= Philadelphia Inquirer
|date= June 7, 1992
|accessdate=February 13, 2012
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Myrin Library, opened in 1971, renovated in 1988, and again in 2004-05.  Myrin houses more than 420,000 volumes, 202,000 microforms, 32,000 audiovisual materials,3,800 e-books, and offers on-site and remote access to approximately 25,900 print, microformand electronic periodical titles.The library is also one of only three U.S. Government depositories in Montgomery County,Pa. and, as such, receives print and electronic federal documents for the collection.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://articles.mcall.com/1986-07-17/news/2542185_1_ursinus-college-grant-renovations
|title=Ursinus College Gets Largest Grant Ever
|newspaper=Allentown Morning Call
|date=July 17, 1986
|accessdate=February 13, 2012
}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Myrin Library is home to an extensive [[Pennsylvania German]] archive and is one of three government repositories in Montgomery County.
[[Image:Hobson Hall Ursinus College.jpg|thumb|left|250px|Hobson Hall, a typical Victorian house in the Residential Village on Main Street]]
*Ritter Center, opened in 1980.&lt;ref name=&quot;UCCampus&quot;/&gt;
*Olin Hall, opened in 1990, named for the F.W. Olin Foundation.  Olin Hall contains a 320-seat lecture hall, a 63-seat tieredclassroom, a 42-seat tiered classroom, a Writing Center, eight traditional classrooms and four seminar rooms.&lt;ref name=&quot;UCCampus&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
|url=http://articles.mcall.com/1989-06-04/news/2687297_1_ursinus-college-liberal-arts-olin-foundation
|title=Ursinus College Ceremony Starts $5.7 Million Project
|newspaper=Allentown Morning Call
|date=June 4, 1989
|author=Jill Wendling
|accessdate=February 13, 2012
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The Floy Lewis Bakes Field House, dedicated in 2001 upon the expansion and renovation of Helferich Hall, 1972. The Field House encompasses the D.L. Helfferich Hall of Health and Physical Education and the William Elliott Pool. The field house pavilion opened in 2001, while the other buildings were dedicated in 1972 in honor, respectively, of the ninth president of Ursinus College and Dr. William Elliott. Helfferich Hall now includes completely renovated locker and training rooms, and a two-story, glass-enclosed area for fitness and recreation. The physical education complex serves both men and women with three full-size basketball courts; locker rooms and team rooms; wrestling room; weight room; dance studio; classrooms; a regulation collegiate-sized swimming pool; squash and handball courts, and a gymnastics space. (Helfferich
[[Image:Thomas Hall Ursinus College.jpg|thumb|250px|Thomas Hall]]
*Richter-North Residence Hall, opened in 2002, named for former college President Richard P. Richter.
*[[Kaleidoscope Performing Arts Center]], opened in April 2005 with a performance by jazz legend [[Wynton Marsalis]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://collegenews.org/campus-news/2005/ursinus-college-opens-new-performing-arts-center.html
|title=Ursinus College Opens New Performing Arts Center
|publisher=CollegeNews.org
|accessdate=February 13, 2012
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The performing arts center features The Lenfest Theater (a 380 seat state-of-the-art Proscenium Arch Theater), a flexible seated black box “experimental” studio theater, a box office and concession booth, a rehearsal studio, a scenic workshop, as well as teaching support space and a gallery and work space for art students.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.ursinus.edu/NetCommunity/Page.aspx?pid=767
|title=The Kaleidoscope Performing Arts Center
|accessdate=February 13, 2012
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*New Residence Hall, opened in 2007.

==Athletics==
{{see also|List of college athletic programs in Pennsylvania #Division III}}
Ursinus is a member of the [[Centennial Conference]], founded in 1992, and which now contains eleven highly-selective private colleges in the mid-Atlantic region, including [[Bryn Mawr College|Bryn Mawr]], [[McDaniel College|McDaniel]], [[Johns Hopkins]], [[Dickinson College|Dickinson]], [[Haverford College|Haverford]], [[Franklin and Marshall]], [[Swarthmore College|Swarthmore]], [[Gettysburg College|Gettysburg]], [[Muhlenberg College|Muhlenberg]], and [[Washington College|Washington]]. Ursinus' athletic teams regularly place regionally and nationally. Its [[field hockey]] team was the [[NCAA Women's Field Hockey Championship#Division III|2006 National Champion]] for [[Division III (NCAA)|NCAA Division III]]. The team earned spots in the national championship game three times before, between 1975–77, as a [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] program, and the [[USA Field Hockey Hall of Fame|United States Field Hockey Hall of Fame]]'s permanent home is at the college.

In the immediate years following its founding, there were no organized [[college athletics|athletics]] at Ursinus College. Baseball matches held against neighboring towns, hiking along the [[Perkiomen Creek]] and in nearby [[Valley Forge]], and skating, bathing and boating in the Perkiomen were popular pastimes for students. Students first organized a tennis club in 1888, and [[college baseball|intercollegiate baseball]] began with play against [[Swarthmore College]], [[Haverford College]], and [[Muhlenberg College]] in 1890. The college's first [[college football|football]] team was also fielded in 1890.

[[Image:Ursinus Track &amp; Field.jpg|thumb|250px|Ursinus Track]]
A field house with shower and locker facilities was first built in 1909, and a &quot;field cage&quot; with facilities for indoor [[college basketball|basketball]] practice was built behind the field house in 1910. 

The college was well known for many years for its Patterson Field endzone, in which a large sycamore tree grew undisturbed. [[Ripley's Believe it or Not]] featured the famous tree for being the only one on an active field of athletic play,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://myrin.ursinus.edu/archives/aba-4041.htm |title=May Day Pageant, c.1950 |publisher=Myrin.ursinus.edu |date=1919-05-08 |accessdate=2012-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the seclusion &quot;of the tree at night for generations afforded lovers a trysting place. Greek organizations initiated pledges into their mysteries under its branches.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ursinus1&quot;&gt;[http://webpages.ursinus.edu/rrichter/bodgermirage7.htm ]{{dead link|date=February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; A new sycamore, growing since 1984 from a seedling taken from the old tree, stood nearby until a recent turf field project required its removal.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ursinus.edu/netcommunity/page.aspx?pid=3412]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1974, the [[NCAA Award of Valor]] was presented to the 1973 basketball team. Every member of the team had entered a burning building, with their combined efforts leading to the rescue of 14 persons.

==Gallery==
&lt;center&gt;&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Olin Plaza Ursinus College.jpg| Olin Plaza 
Image:Bomberger Hall Ursinus College.jpg| Bomberger Hall
Image:Ursinus Bomberger Hall.JPG|Bomberger Hall during Winter
Image:Chadwick Sculptures Ursinus College.jpg| Chadwick sculptures at Ursinus
Image:Reimert Hall.JPG|Reimert Hall (exterior)
&lt;/gallery&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

==Ursinus and the world beyond==
===Outside recognition===
{{Advert|section|date=March 2011}}
;1989
*During the dedication of the school's Berman Museum of Art, novelist [[James Michener]] credits Ursinus as &quot;a college with managers who are bright enough to see that this ought to be done, an industrialist who had the courage to buy the material, and a group of professors and students and citizens of the community who will enjoy this that we are doing today for the next 100 years.&quot;
;1992
*[[Polio vaccine]] developer [[Jonas Salk]] declares that uniting Ursinus' psychology and biology departments under one roof &quot;represents a union of nature and human nature&quot; and calls the school &quot;one of the few colleges integrating these concepts which will serve as a role model for other institutions.&quot;
;1999
*''[[Yahoo!]] Internet Life'' lists Ursinus as one of the 100 Most Wired Colleges in the United States.
;2000
*''[[New York Times]]'' education editor [[Loren Pope]] includes Ursinus in his book ''[[Colleges That Change Lives]]''.
;2001
*''The Fiske Guide to Colleges'' assigns Ursinus three bells for academics, three bells for social life and three bells for quality of life.
*''[[The Princeton Review]]'' lists Ursinus among the country's 331 best colleges, assigning it three out of four bells for academics and indicating a high degree of professor accessibility and professor interest in students.
;2004
*The ''[[Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools]]'' accrediting team writes in 1998 that “developments at Ursinus in the last five years are nothing short of astonishing.”
*One of the 50 top colleges in the nation for undergraduate research, according to ''U.S. News &amp; World Report's America's Best Colleges 2004''.
*Forbes.com: Most Connected Campuses. Top 25&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.forbes.com/lists/results.jhtml?passListId=8&amp;passYear=2004&amp;passListType=Misc&amp;resultsSortProperties=%2Bnumberfield5&amp;resultsSortCategoryName=Rank&amp;searchParameter1=unset&amp;searchParameter2=unset&amp;resultsStart=1&amp;resultsHowMany=25&amp;category1=category&amp;category2=category&amp;passKeyword= ]{{dead link|date=February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
;2005
*The ''[[National Survey of Student Engagement]]'' report identifies Ursinus as one of 20 (out of 700) campuses nationally that &quot;do an especially good job of educating students&quot; and have a “clear educational purpose and coherent educational philosophy&quot; and an “unshakable focus” on student learning.
;2006
*''Newsweek Kaplan College Guide'' names Ursinus one of 25 &quot;Hottest Freshman Year&quot; schools and &quot;one of America's 367 most interesting schools.&quot;
;2007
*''U.S. News America's Best Colleges'' gives Ursinus an &quot;A+ rating for B students&quot;, commending its &quot;first-rate programs&quot; and calling it one of the country's “Best Liberal Arts Colleges&quot; (53rd among its 215 peers in terms of graduation and retention).
*''[[The Princeton Review]]'' identifies Ursinus as one of the nation's &quot;Best 361 Colleges.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.princetonreview.com/college/research/profiles/schoolsays.asp?category=1&amp;listing=1023818&amp;LTID=1&amp;intbucketid=]&lt;/ref&gt;
*''[[The Chronicle of Higher Education]]'' reports that Ursinus' Kaleidoscope Performing Arts Center &quot;comes alive at night, and the building's showpiece space, a three-floor atrium with a glass-lined south face-dazzles from within.&quot;
*[[Jeffrey Sachs]] calls the college &quot;very proudly and very successfully committed to the power of ideas.&quot;

===Notable faculty===
* '''[[Raymond Dodge]]''', experimental psychologist: Appointed Professor of Philosophy in 1896
* '''[[John Mauchly]]''', computer pioneer and creator of the [[ENIAC]]: While Professor of Physics at Ursinus from 1933 to 1941, developed and tested digital electronic calculating devices at Ursinus's science labs in Pfahler Hall, a building which still stands on campus (see ''Gallery'', below)
* '''[[Royal Meeker]]''', statistician: Taught at Ursinus from 1906 until his appointment by President Wilson to be Commissioner of Labor Statistics in 1913. He later served (1923–24) as Pennsylvania Secretary of Labor and Industry
* '''[[Joseph Melrose]]''', former U.S. Ambassador to [[Sierra Leone]]: Ambassador-in-Residence of the school's International Relations Program
* '''[[Deborah Poritz]]''', former Chief Justice of the New Jersey Supreme Court: Taught at Ursinus in the late 1960s
* '''[[Richard Powell]]''', noted investor: served as adjunct professor of finance from 2010 to 2012

==Notable Alumni and Former Students==
{{Refimprove section|date=January 2008}}
* '''[[Barrie Ciliberti]]''' (Class of 1957): [[Maryland House of Delegates]] legislator and [[Reagan administration]] appointee
* '''[[Larry Crabb]]''' (Class of 1965): Author and psychologist; founder and director of ''New Way Ministries''
* '''[[J. William Ditter Jr.]]''' is a judge on the United States District Court
* '''[[Steve Donahue]]''' (Class of 1984): Head men's basketball coach at [[Boston College]]
* '''[[Gerald Edelman]]''' (Class of 1950): Winner of the 1972 [[Nobel Prize]] in medicine
* '''[[Hermann Eilts]]''' (Class of 1943): Former U.S. ambassador to [[Saudi Arabia]] and [[Egypt]] who assisted [[Henry Kissinger]]'s Mideast shuttle diplomacy effort, worked with Egyptian President [[Anwar el-Sadat]] throughout the [[Camp David Accords]], and dodged a Libyan hit team
* '''[[Jacob G. Francis]]''' (Class of 1891): Author, historian, [[Church of the Brethren]] pastor, and founder of [[Elizabethtown College]]
* '''[[Norman E. Gibbs]]''' (Class of 1964): was an American software engineer, scholar and educational leader.
* '''[[Kim Guadagno]]''' (Class of 1980), [[Lieutenant Governor of New Jersey]]&lt;ref&gt;Stile, Charles. [http://www.northjersey.com/news/politics/nj_politics/chrischristieltgov072009.html &quot;Christie announces lieutenant governor pick&quot;], ''[[The Record (Bergen County)]]'', July 20, 2009. Accessed July 21, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''[[Russell Conwell Johnson]]''' (Class of 1916): [[Major League Baseball]] pitcher ([[Philadelphia Athletics]], 1916–1928)
* '''[[Sam Keen]]''' (Class of 1953): Author, professor of philosophy and religion, and former contributing editor of [[Psychology Today]]
* '''[[Joseph Melrose]]''' (Class of 1966): Former U.S. Ambassador to [[Sierra Leone]]
* '''[[Dan Mullen]]''' (Class of 1994): Head Coach of the [[Mississippi State Bulldogs football]] team
* '''[[J.D. Salinger]]''' (attended 1937-38): Author of ''[[The Catcher in the Rye]]''; he left the school after one semester and continued his studies at other institutions. Attended prep school at nearby [[Valley Forge Military Academy]]. A letter from Salinger hangs in Ursinus' Corson Hall
* '''[[Ismar Schorsch]]''' (Class of 1957): Former Chancellor of the [[Jewish Theological Seminary of America]]
*'''[[Michael Marcon]]''' (Class of 1986): Founder and CEO of Equity Risk Partners [http://www.equityrisk.com/principals.htm]
* '''[[Linda M. Springer]]''' (Class of 1979): Director of the United States [[Office of Personnel Management]]
* '''[[Jeff Trinkle]]''' (Class of 1979): Professor and Chair of Computer Science at [[Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute]]; known for his work in robotic manipulation, multibody dynamics, and automated manufacturing
* '''[[Robert Yerkes]]''' (Class of 1897): Psychologist, ethologist and primatologist best known for his work in intelligence testing and in the field of comparative psychology; co-developer of the [[Yerkes-Dodson law]] relating arousal to performance
* '''[[Joseph DeSimone]]''' (Class of 1986): American chemical engineer, 2008 recipient of the [[Lemelson–MIT Prize]]
* '''[[Kristen Bone]]''' (Class of 2010 or 12): Television actor, BFA in communication arts[http://greenerpartners.org/about/team.php]

==References==
{{Reflist}}
* ''Ursinus College Catalog''. Ursinus College: January 1991.
* Yost, Calvin Daniel. ''Ursinus College: A History of Its First Hundred Years''. Ursinus College: 1985.

==External links==
{{Portal|Philadelphia|Pennsylvania|University}}
* {{official website|http://www.ursinus.edu/}}
* [http://www.ursinusathletics.com/ Official athletics website]
* {{twitter|UrsinusCollege}}
* [http://wiki.ursinus.edu/index.php/ Ursinus Wiki]
{{-}}

{{Colleges and Universities in Pennsylvania}}
{{Education in Montgomery County, Pennsylvania}}
{{Centennial Conference navbox}}
{{Colleges and universities in metropolitan Philadelphia}}
{{Annapolis Group}}

{{coord|40.1934|-75.4559|region:US-PA_type:edu|display=title}}

[[Category:Ursinus College| ]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Eastern Pennsylvania Rugby Union]]
[[Category:Council of Independent Colleges]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Montgomery County, Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1869]]
[[Category:Members of the Annapolis Group]]</text>
      <sha1>21gg8hyakum7rqvdux5xhxg44yaq7tv</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
