<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Utopia</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>31718</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522275511</id>
      <parentid>522275496</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T03:11:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contributions/72.220.50.14|72.220.50.14]] to version by 78.26. False positive? [[User:ClueBot NG/FalsePositives|Report it]]. Thanks, [[User:ClueBot NG|ClueBot NG]]. (1326786) (Bot)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="41069">{{Other uses}}

'''Utopia''' ({{IPAc-en|juː|ˈ|t|oʊ|p|i|ə}}) is an ideal [[community]] or [[society]] possessing highly desirable or perfect qualities. The word was coined in Greek by [[Sir Thomas More]] for his 1516 book ''[[Utopia (book)|Utopia]]'', describing a fictional [[island]] society in the Atlantic Ocean. The term has been used to describe both [[intentional community|intentional communities]] that attempt to create an ideal society, and fictional societies portrayed in [[utopian and dystopian fiction|literature]]. It has spawned other concepts, most prominently [[dystopia]].

==Varieties==
{{refimprove section|date=January 2012}}
[[File:Hieronymus Bosch - The Garden of Earthly Delights - The Earthly Paradise (Garden of Eden).jpg|thumbnail|right|200px|Left panel (The Earthly Paradise – [[Garden of Eden]]) from [[Hieronymus Bosch]]'s ''[[The Garden of Earthly Delights]]''.]]
Chronologically, the first recorded utopian proposal is [[Plato]]'s ''[[Republic (Plato)|Republic]]''.&lt;ref&gt;More, Travis; Rohith Vinod
(1989)&lt;/ref&gt; Part conversation, part fictional depiction, and part policy proposal, it proposes a categorization of citizens into a rigid class structure of &quot;golden,&quot; &quot;silver,&quot; &quot;bronze&quot; and &quot;iron&quot; socioeconomic classes. The golden citizens are trained in a rigorous 50-year long educational program to be benign oligarchs, the &quot;philosopher-kings.&quot; The wisdom of these rulers will supposedly eliminate poverty and deprivation through fairly distributed resources, though the details on how to do this are unclear. The educational program for the rulers is the central notion of the proposal. There is a general [[pacifism]] or pacifist attitude. However, the people of the Republic are all ready to defend themselves or to compete militarily for resources (such as land) if necessary. It has few laws, no [[lawyer]]s and rarely sends its citizens to war, but hires [[mercenary|mercenaries]] from among its war-prone neighbors (these mercenaries were deliberately sent into dangerous situations in the hope that the more warlike populations of all surrounding countries will be weeded out, leaving peaceful peoples).

In the sixteenth century, Thomas More's book ''Utopia'' proposed an ideal society of the same name. Some {{Who|date=August 2012}} readers, including utopian socialists, have chosen to accept this imaginary society as the realistic blueprint for a working nation, while others have postulated that More intended nothing of the sort. Some{{Who|date=April 2010}} maintain the position that More's ''Utopia'' functions only on the level of a satire, a work intended to reveal more about the England of his time than about an idealistic society.  This interpretation is bolstered by the title of the book and nation, and its apparent confusion between the Greek for &quot;no place&quot; and &quot;good place&quot;: &quot;utopia&quot; is a compound of the syllable ou-, meaning &quot;no&quot;, and topos, meaning place. But the [[Homophone|homophonic]] prefix eu-, meaning &quot;good,&quot; also resonates in the word, with the implication that the perfectly &quot;good place&quot; is really &quot;no place.&quot;'''''

===Ecology===
Ecological utopian society describes new ways in which society should relate to nature. They react to a [[ecotopia|perceived]] widening gap between the modern Western way of living that destroys nature{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}} and the traditional way of living{{Clarify|date=June 2011}} that is thought{{Who|date=June 2011}} to be more in harmony with nature. According to the Dutch philosopher Marius de Geus, ecological utopias could be sources of inspiration for green political movements.&lt;ref&gt;Geus, Marius de (1996). Ecologische utopieën- Ecotopia's en het milieudebat. Uitgeverij Jan van Arkel.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the novelette ''Rumfuddle'' (1973), [[Jack Vance]] presents a novel twist on the ecological utopia. His hero invents paratime travel and becomes effectively the ruler of earth by giving everyone their own alternate-earth wilderness worlds as vacation retreats/suburbs without neighbors. However, he requires them to work during the week cleaning up the original Earth and restoring its pristineness. A typical job is driving a bulldozer that shoves the detritus of industrial civilization through a portal into the oceans of a paratime garbage world.

===Economics===
Economic utopias are based on economics. Most [[intentional community|intentional communities]] attempting to create an economic utopia were formed in response to the harsh economic conditions of the 19th century.{{dubious|date=November 2010}}

Particularly in the early 19th century, several utopian ideas arose, often in response to their belief that social disruption was created and caused by the development of [[commercialism]] and [[capitalism]]. These are often grouped in a greater &quot;[[utopian socialism|utopian socialist]]&quot; movement, due to their shared characteristics: an [[egalitarian]] distribution of goods, frequently with the total abolition of [[money]], and citizens only doing [[labour (economics)|work]] which they enjoy and which is for the [[common good]], leaving them with ample time for the cultivation of the arts and sciences. One classic example of such a utopia was [[Edward Bellamy]]'s ''[[Looking Backward]]''. Another socialist utopia is [[William Morris]]' ''[[News from Nowhere]]'', written partially in response to the top-down ([[bureaucratic]]) nature of Bellamy's utopia, which Morris criticized.  However, as the socialist movement developed it moved away from utopianism; [[Marx]] in particular became a harsh critic of earlier socialism he described as utopian. (For more information see the [[History of Socialism]] article.) Also consider [[Eric Frank Russell]]'s book ''[[The Great Explosion]]'' (1963) whose last section details an economic and social utopia. This forms the first mention of the idea of [[Local Exchange Trading Systems]] (LETS). {{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

Utopias have also been imagined by the opposite side of the political spectrum. For example, [[Robert A. Heinlein]]'s ''[[The Moon Is a Harsh Mistress]]'' portrays an [[individualism|individualistic]] and [[libertarian utopia]], as does [[Ayn Rand]]'s main novel, ''[[Atlas Shrugged]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Cf. only ''Atlas Shrugged'', pt. III, ch. 2: &quot;The Utopia of Greed.&quot; See also Clardy (2012).&lt;/ref&gt; [[Capitalism|Capitalist]] utopias of this sort are generally based on [[free market]] economies, in which the presupposition is that private enterprise and personal initiative without an institution of coercion, [[government]], provides the greatest opportunity for achievement and progress of both the individual and society as a whole.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last = Folbre
  | first = Nancy
  | authorlink = http://www.nytimes.com/2009/03/11/business/economy/Folbre.ready.html?_r=1
  | coauthors =
  | title = Utopian Capitalism
  | work = Business Daily
  | publisher = New York Times
  | date = December 26, 2011
  | url = http://economix.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/12/26/utopian-capitalism/
  | format =
  | doi =
  | accessdate = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another view that capitalist utopias do not address is the issue of [[market failure]], any more than socialist utopias address the issue of planning failure. Thus a blend of [[socialism]] and [[capitalism]] is seen by some as the type of economy in a utopia. For example, one such idea is to have small, community-owned enterprises working under a market-based model of economy. Such a model of market-based [[Communism]] itself was in theory supposed to create a &quot;classless utopia&quot;, but no nation has ever reached that point. {{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

===Politics and history===
A global utopia of [[world peace]] is often seen as one of the possible [[end of history (disambiguation)|endings of history]]. Within the localized political structures or spheres it presents, &quot;[[polyculturalism]]&quot; is the model-based adaptation of possible interactions with different cultures and identities in accordance with the principles of participatory society.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last = Spannos
  | first = Chris
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = What is Real Utopia?
  | work = Z Magazine
  | publisher = [[Z Communications]]
  | date = 2008-07-05
  | url = http://www.zmag.org/znet/viewArticle/18100
  | format =
  | doi =
  | accessdate = 2008-09-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Soviet writer [[Ivan Efremov]] produced during the &quot;Thaw&quot; period the science-fiction utopia ''[[Andromeda (novel)|Andromeda]]'' (1957) in which a united humanity communicates with a galaxy-wide Great Circle and develops its technology and culture within a social framework characterized by vigorous competition between alternative philosophies.

The communes of the 1960s in the United States were often an attempt to greatly improve the way humans live together in communities. The back to the land movements and hippies inspired many to try to live in peace and harmony on farms, remote areas, and to set up new types of governance. 

[[Intentional communities]] were organized and built all over the world with the hope of making a more perfect way of living together.  However, many of these new small communities failed, but some are growing like the Twelve Tribes Communities that started in the United States and have grown to many tribes around the world.

===Religious utopia===
[[File:New Harmony by F. Bate (View of a Community, as proposed by Robert Owen) printed 1838.jpg|300px|right|thumb|[[New Harmony, Indiana|New Harmony]], a utopian attempt; depicted as proposed by [[Robert Owen]]]]

Religious utopias can be intra-religious or inter-religious.
The inter-religious utopia borders on a concept like [[Polyculturalism]] and is not deemed possible in the near future or the near-far future. Fledgling theories are generally canceled as impossible, but the ideology of God and Religion used in inter-religious utopia is commonly stated by many people as their view of God.  In more extended theories it goes up to the level of different religious leaders setting aside their differences and accepting harmony, peace and understanding to unite all religions within one another, thereby forming a utopian religion or a religion of Humans with God any type of force that reigned before the birth of the [[universe]]. Religion and God being used as a self-motivating factor for people to believe in and raise themselves out of difficult situations.

Intra-Religious utopias are based on [[religion|religious]] ideals, and are to date those most commonly found in human society. Their members are usually required to follow and believe in the particular religious tradition that established the utopia. Some permit non-believers or non-adherents to take up residence within them; others (such as the Community at [[Qumran]]) do not.

The [[Islam]]ic, [[Judaism|Jewish]], and [[Christianity|Christian]] ideas of the [[Garden of Eden]] and [[Heaven]] may be interpreted as forms of [[utopianism]], especially in their [[folk religion|folk-religious]] forms. Such religious utopias are often described as &quot;gardens of delight&quot;, implying an existence free from worry in a state of bliss or enlightenment. They postulate freedom from sin, pain, poverty, and death, and often assume communion with beings such as [[angel]]s or the [[houri]]. In a similar sense the [[Hinduism|Hindu]] concept of [[Moksha]] and the [[Buddhism|Buddhist]] concept of [[Nirvana (concept)|Nirvana]] may be thought of as a kind of utopia. In Hinduism or Buddhism, however, Utopia is not a place but a state of mind. A belief that if we are able to practice meditation without continuous stream of thoughts, we are able to reach enlightenment. This enlightenment promises exit from the cycle of life and death, relating back to the concept of utopia.

In the United States and Europe during the [[Second Great Awakening]] of the 19th century and thereafter, many radical religious groups formed utopian societies in which all aspects of people's lives could be governed by their faith. Among the best-known of these utopian societies were the [[Shakers]], which originated in England in the 18th century but moved to America shortly afterward. A number of religious utopian societies from Europe came to the United States from the 18th century throughout the 19th century, including the Society of the Woman in the Wilderness (led by [[Johannes Kelpius]]), the [[Ephrata Cloister]], and the [[Harmony Society]], among others.  The [[Harmony Society]] was a [[Christian theosophy]] and [[Pietism|pietist]] group founded in [[Iptingen]], [[Germany]], in 1785. Due to religious persecution by the [[Lutheranism|Lutheran Church]] and the government in [[Württemberg]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Sutton1&quot;&gt;Robert Paul Sutton, ''Communal Utopias and the American Experience: Religious Communities'' (2003) p. 38&lt;/ref&gt; the society moved to the United States on October 7, 1803, settled in [[Pennsylvania]], and on February 15, 1805, they, together with about 400 followers, formally organized the Harmony Society, placing all their goods in [[Commune (intentional community)|common]]. The group lasted until 1905, making it one of the longest-running financially successful communes in American history. The [[Oneida Community]], founded by [[John Humphrey Noyes]] in [[Oneida, New York]], was a utopian religious commune that lasted from 1848 to 1881. Although this utopian experiment is better known today for its manufacture of Oneida silverware, it was one of the longest-running communes in American history. The [[Amana Colonies]] were communal settlements in [[Iowa]], started by radical German [[pietists]], which lasted from 1855 to 1932. The [[Amana Corporation]], manufacturer of refrigerators and household appliances, was originally started by the group. Other examples are [[Fountain Grove]], Riker's Holy City and other Californian utopian colonies between 1855 and 1955 (Hine), as well as Sointula&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Finnish Utopian Settlements in North America | author = Teuvo Peltoniemi | url = http://www.sosiomedia.fi/utopia/na_settlements.pdf | publisher = sosiomedia.fi | year = 1984 | accessdate = 2008-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; in [[British Columbia]], Canada.  The Amish and Hutterites can also be considered an attempt towards a better world to live in.  A wide variety of intentional communities with some type of faith based ideas have started across the world.

The book of Revelation in the Christian bible depicts a better time, in the future, after Satan and evil are defeated.  One interpretation is that there will eventually be heaven on Earth, or a new Earth without sin.  The details of this new Earth where God and Jesus rules is not made clear.  It can be assumed that it will be something like the Garden of Eden before the fall. Another possibility is that heaven will not be a physical realm, but instead an incorporeal place for souls.

===Science and technology===
[[File:Early flight 02561u (2).jpg|thumb|Utopian flying machines, France, 1890-1900 (chromolithograph [[trading card]]).]]

Scientific and technological utopias are set in the future, when it is believed that advanced [[science]] and [[technology]] will allow utopian [[living standards]]; for example, the absence of [[death]] and [[suffering]]; changes in [[human nature]] and the [[human condition]]. Technology has affected the way humans have lived to such an extent that normal functions, like sleep, eating or even reproduction, have been replaced by artificial means. Other examples include a society where humans have struck a balance with technology and it is merely used to enhance the human living condition (e.g. ''[[Star Trek]]''). In place of the static perfection of a utopia, [[libertarian transhumanist]]s envision an &quot;[[extropianism|extropia]]&quot;, an open, evolving society allowing individuals and voluntary groupings to form the institutions and social forms they prefer.

[[Buckminster Fuller]] presented a theoretical basis for [[technological utopianism]] and set out to develop a variety of technologies ranging from maps to designs for cars and houses which might lead to the development of such a utopia.

One notable example of a technological and [[libertarian socialist]] utopia is Scottish author [[Iain Banks]]' [[The Culture|Culture]].

Opposing this [[optimism]] is the prediction that advanced science and technology will, through deliberate misuse or accident, cause environmental damage or even humanity's [[extinction]]. Critics, such as [[Jacques Ellul]] and [[Timothy Mitchell]] advocate [[precautionary principle|precautions]] against the premature embrace of new technologies, raising questions on responsibility and freedom brought by [[division of labour]]. Authors such as [[John Zerzan]] and [[Derrick Jensen]] consider that modern technology is progressively depriving humans of their autonomy, and advocate the collapse of the industrial civilization, in favor of small-scale organization, as a necessary path to avoid the threat of technology on human freedom and [[sustainability]].

There are many examples of techno-dystopias portrayed in mainstream culture, such as the classics ''[[Brave New World]]'' and ''[[Nineteen Eighty-Four]]'', which have explored some of these topics.

===Feminism===

Utopias have been used to explore the ramification of gender being either a societal construct, or a biologically &quot;hard-wired&quot; imperative.&lt;ref name=WSEncyc1442&gt;{{cite book |title= Women's Studies Encyclopedia|last=Tierney |first=Helen |authorlink= |coauthors= |year= 1999|publisher= Greenwood Publishing Group|page=1442 |isbn=978-0-313-31073-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; The fictional aliens in [[Mary Gentle]]'s ''[[Golden Witchbreed]]'' start out as gender-neutral children and do not develop into men and women until puberty, and gender has no bearing on social roles. In contrast, [[Doris Lessing]]'s ''[[The Marriages Between Zones Three, Four and Five]]'' (1980) suggests that men's and women's values are inherent to the sexes and cannot be changed, making a compromise between them essential. In ''My Own Utopia'' (1961) by [[Elizabeth Mann Borghese]], gender exists but is dependent upon age rather than sex&amp;nbsp;— genderless children mature into women, some of whom eventually become men.&lt;ref name=WSEncyc1442/&gt;

Utopic [[single-gender worlds]] or single-sex societies have long been one of the primary ways to explore implications of gender and gender-differences.&lt;ref name=DGinSF13/&gt; In speculative fiction, female-only worlds have been imagined to come about by the action of disease that wipes out men, along with the development of technological or mystical method that allow female [[parthenogenic]] [[reproduction]]. The resulting society is often shown to be utopian by feminist writers. Many influential feminist utopias of this sort were written in the 1970s;&lt;ref name=DGinSF13&gt;Attebery, p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=erotic1189&gt;[[Gaétan Brulotte]] &amp; John Phillips,''Encyclopedia of Erotic Literature'', &quot;Science Fiction and Fantasy&quot;, CRC Press, 2006, p. 1189, ISBN 1-57958-441-1&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name =Utop101/&gt; the most often studied examples include [[Joanna Russ]]'s ''[[The Female Man]]'' and [[Suzy McKee Charnas]]'s ''[[Walk to the End of the World]]'' and ''[[Motherlines]]''.&lt;ref name =Utop101&gt;Martha A. Bartter, ''The Utopian Fantastic'', &quot;Momutes&quot;, Robin Anne Reid, p.101 ISBN 0-313-31635-X&lt;/ref&gt; Utopias imagined by male authors have generally included equality between sexes, rather than separation.&lt;ref name =Utop102&gt;Martha A. Bartter, ''The Utopian Fantastic'', &quot;Momutes&quot;, Robin Anne Reid, p. 102 ISBN&lt;/ref&gt;  Such worlds have been portrayed most often by lesbian or feminist authors; their use of female-only worlds allows the exploration of female independence and freedom from [[patriarchy]]. The societies may not necessarily be lesbian, or sexual at all&amp;nbsp;— a famous early sexless example being ''[[Herland (novel)|Herland]]'' (1915) by [[Charlotte Perkins Gilman]].&lt;ref name=erotic1189/&gt; Charlene Ball writes in ''Women's Studies Encyclopedia'' that use of speculative fiction to explore gender roles in future societies has been more common in the United States compared to Europe and elsewhere.&lt;ref name=WSEncyc1442/&gt;

===Utopianism===
[[File:Goldenes-Zeitalter-1530-2.jpg|thumbnail|right|200px|''The Golden Age'' by Lucas Cranach the Elder.]]
In many cultures, societies, and religions, there is some myth or memory of a distant past when humankind lived in a primitive and simple state, but at the same time one of perfect happiness and fulfillment. In those days, the various [[mythology|myth]]s tell us, there was an instinctive harmony between humanity and nature. People's needs were few and their desires limited. Both were easily satisfied by the abundance provided by nature. Accordingly, there were no motives whatsoever for war or oppression. Nor was there any need for hard and painful work. Humans were simple and [[piety|pious]], and felt themselves close to the gods. According to one anthropological theory, hunter-gatherers were the [[original affluent society]].

These mythical or religious archetypes are inscribed in all the cultures and resurge with special vitality when people are in difficult and critical times. However, the projection of the myth does not take place towards the remote past, but either towards the future or towards distant and fictional places, imagining that at some time of the future, at some point of the space or beyond the death must exist the possibility of living happily.

These myths of the earliest stage of humankind have been referred to by various cultures, societies, and religions:

'''Golden Age'''
The [[Ancient Greek|Greek]] poet [[Hesiod]], around the 8th century BC, in his compilation of the mythological tradition (the poem ''[[Works and Days]]''), explained that, prior to [[Ages of Man|the present era]], there were other four progressively more perfect ones, the oldest of which was the [[Golden Age]].

[[Plutarch]], the Greek historian and biographer of the 1st century, dealt with the blissful and mythic past of the humanity.

'''[[Arcadia (utopia)|Arcadia]]''', e.g. in [[Sir Philip Sidney]]'s prose romance ''[[Countess of Pembroke's Arcadia|The Old Arcadia]]'' (1580). Originally a region in the [[Peloponnesus]], Arcadia became a [[synonym]] for any rural area that serves as a [[pastoral]] setting, as a ''locus amoenus'' (&quot;delightful place&quot;):

'''The Biblical Garden of Eden'''
The [[Hebrew Bible|Biblical]] [[Garden of Eden]] as depicted in [[Book of Genesis|Genesis]] 2 ([[King James Version of the Bible|Authorized Version of 1611]]):

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;And the Lord God planted a garden eastward in Eden; and there he put the man whom he had formed. And out of the ground made the Lord God to grow every tree that is pleasant to the sight, and good for food; the tree of life also in the midst of the garden, and the tree of knowledge of good and evil. [...]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
And the Lord God took the man, and put him into the garden of Eden to dress it and to keep it. And the Lord God commanded the man, saying, Of every tree of the garden thou mayest freely eat: but of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil, thou shalt not eat of it: for in the day that thou eatest thereof thou shalt surely die. [...]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
And the Lord God said, It is not good that the man should be alone; [...] And the Lord God caused a deep sleep to fall upon Adam, and he slept: and he took one of his ribs, and closed up the flesh instead thereof; and the rib, which the Lord God had taken from man, made he a woman, and brought her unto the man.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

'''The Land of Cockaigne'''
The  Land of [[Cockaigne]] (also Cockaygne, Cokaygne), was &lt;blockquote&gt;an imaginary land of idleness and luxury, famous in medieval story, and the subject of more than one poem, one of which, an early translation of a 13th-century French work, is given in Ellis's ''Specimens of Early English Poets''. In this, &quot;the houses were made of barley sugar and cakes, the streets were paved with pastry, and the shops supplied goods for nothing.&quot;  London has been so called (see [[Cockney#Cockaigne|Cockney]]), but Boileau applies the same to Paris.&lt;ref&gt;Cobham Brewer E. ''Brewer's Dictionary of Phrase and Fable'', Odhams, London, 1932&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; 

'''[[The Peach Blossom Spring]]''', a prose written by [[Tao Yuanming]], describes a utopian place.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last=Tian| first=Xiaofei| title=The Cambridge History of Chinese Literature| year=2010| publisher=Cambridge University Press| location=Cambridge| isbn=978-0-521-85558-7| page=221| chapter=From the Eastern Jin through the Early Tang (317–649)}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last=Berkowitz| first=Alan J.| title=Patterns of Disengagement: the Practice and Portrayal of Reclusion in Early Medieval China| year=2000| publisher=Stanford University Press| location=Stanford| isbn=978-0-8047-3603-9| page=225}}&lt;/ref&gt; The narrative goes that a fisherman from Wuling sailed upstream a river and came across a beautiful blossoming peach grove and lush green fields covered with blossom petals.&lt;ref name=zh182&gt;{{cite book| last=Longxi| first=Zhang| title=Allegoresis: Reading Canonical Literature East and West| year=2005| publisher=Cornell University Press| location=Ithaca| isbn=978-0-8014-4369-5| page=182}}&lt;/ref&gt; Entranced by the beauty, he continued upstream.&lt;ref name=zh182/&gt; When he reached the end of the river, he stumbled onto a small grotto.&lt;ref name=zh182/&gt; Though narrow at first, he was able to squeeze through the passage and discovered an ethereal utopia, where the people led an ideal existence in harmony with nature.&lt;ref name=zh182-3&gt;{{cite book| last=Longxi| first=Zhang| title=Allegoresis: Reading Canonical Literature East and West| year=2005| publisher=Cornell University Press| location=Ithaca| isbn=978-0-8014-4369-5| pages=182–183}}&lt;/ref&gt; He saw a vast expanse of fertile lands, clear ponds, mulberry trees, bamboo groves, and the like with a community of people of all ages and houses in neat rows.&lt;ref name=zh182-3/&gt; The people explained that their ancestors escaped to this place during the civil unrest of the [[Qin Dynasty]] and they themselves had not left since or had contact with anyone from the outside.&lt;ref name=zh183&gt;{{cite book| last=Longxi| first=Zhang| title=Allegoresis: Reading Canonical Literature East and West| year=2005| publisher=Cornell University Press| location=Ithaca| isbn=978-0-8014-4369-5| pages=183}}&lt;/ref&gt; They had not even heard of the later dynasties of bygone times or the then-current [[Jin Dynasty (265–420)|Jin Dynasty]]. In the story, the community was secluded and unaffected by the troubles of the outside world.&lt;ref name=zh183/&gt; The sense of timelessness was also predominant in the story as a perfect utopian community remains unchanged, that is, it had no decline nor the need to improve.&lt;ref name=zh183/&gt; Eventually, the Chinese term ''Peach Blossom Spring'' (桃花源) came to be synonymous for the concept of utopia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last=Gu| first=Ming Dong| title=Chinese Theories of Fiction: A Non-Western Narrative System| year=2006| publisher=State University of New York Press| location=Albany| isbn=978-0-7914-6815-9| page=59}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

'''Schlaraffenland''' is an analogous German tradition. ([[:de:Schlaraffenland|See in German Wikipedia]].)

These myths also express some hope that the [[idyll]]ic state of affairs they describe is not irretrievably and irrevocably lost to mankind, that it can be regained in some way or other.

One way might be a quest for an &quot;earthly paradise&quot;—a place like [[Shangri-La]], hidden in the [[Tibet]]an mountains and described by [[James Hilton]] in his utopian novel ''[[Lost Horizon (novel)|Lost Horizon]]'' (1933). [[Christopher Columbus]] followed directly in this tradition in his belief that he had found the Garden of Eden when, towards the end of the 15th century, he first encountered the [[New World]] and its indigenous inhabitants.

==Etymology==
The word comes from the ''{{lang-el|οὐ}}'' (&quot;not&quot;) and ''τόπος'' (&quot;place&quot;) and means &quot;no place&quot;. The [[English language|English]] [[homophone]] ''eutopia'', derived from the Greek ''εὖ'' (&quot;good&quot; or &quot;well&quot;) and ''τόπος'' (&quot;place&quot;), means &quot;good place&quot;. This, due to the identical pronunciation of &quot;utopia&quot; and &quot;eutopia&quot;, gives rise to a [[double meaning]].

==List of utopian literature==

===Pre-20th century===
*''[[The Republic (Plato)|The Republic]]'' (written around 380 BC) by [[Plato]] is one of the earliest conceptions of a utopia.
*''[[Panchaea]]'', (In 'Sacred History' (&quot;Hiera Anagraphê&quot;) of [[Euhemerus]], around 3rd c BC), described as a rational island paradise located just after the Red sea and around the Arabian Peninsula.
*''[[Book of Revelation]]'', (1st century AD), a new Earth with God ruling, no more death, and a new Jerusalem.
*''[[City of God (book)|The City of God]]'' (written 413–426 AD) by [[Augustine of Hippo]], describes an ideal city, the &quot;eternal&quot; Jerusalem, the archetype of all Christian utopias.
*''[[Tao Hua Yuan]]'', (421 AD) is a utopia for Chinese intellects.
*''[[Al-Madina al-Fadila]]'', written by [[Al-Farabi]] (874-950), where he theorized an ideal state as in Plato's The Republic. Al-Farabi represented religion as a symbolic rendering of truth, and, like Plato, saw it as the duty of the philosopher to provide guidance to the state.
*''[[Utopia (book)|Utopia]]'' (1516) by [[Thomas More]].
*''[[Gargantua]]'', written by [[François Rabelais]] (1532). In a passing way presents the community of Thélème, which while serving to poke fun at monastic institutions, can also be seen as an ideal society dedicated to the cultivation of love.
*''[[La Città felice]]'' (1553) by [[Frane Petrić]].
*''Christianopolis'' (1619) by [[Johann Valentin Andrea|Johann Valentin Andreæ]], describes a Christian utopia inhabited by a community of scholar-artisans and run as a democracy.
*''[[The City of the Sun]]'' (1623) by [[Tommaso Campanella]] depicts a theocratic and egalitarian society.
*''[[New Atlantis]]'' (1627) by [[Francis Bacon (philosopher)|Francis Bacon]].
*''[[The Law of Freedom in a Platform]] (1652), by [[Gerrard Winstanley]].
*''[[Gulliver's Travels]]'' (1726), Book IV, satire.
*''[[Erewhon]]'' (1872) by [[Samuel Butler (novelist)|Samuel Butler]], constitute a satiric romp through a hidden utopia (with dystopian elements) in the Southern Alps, New Zealand.
*''[[News from Nowhere]]'' by [[William Morris]] (1892), Shows &quot;Nowhere&quot;, a place without politics, a future society based on common ownership and democratic control of the means of production.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last=Morris | first=William | authorlink=William Morris | title=The Earthly Paradise | publisher=Obscure Press | origyear=1903 | year=2006 | isbn=1-84664-523-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*''[[Looking Backward]]'' (1888) by [[Edward Bellamy]].
*''Gloriana, or the Revolution of 1900'' (1890) by [[Lady Florence Dixie]]. The female protagonist poses as a man, Hector l'Estrange, is elected to the [[British House of Commons|House of Commons]], and [[suffragette|wins women the vote]]. The book ends in the year 1999, with a description of a prosperous and peaceful Britain governed by women.&lt;ref name=gates&gt;Gates, Barbara T. (ed.), ''In Nature's Name: An Anthology of Women's Writing and Illustration, 1780-1930'' [[University of Chicago Press]], 2002&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:A Crystal Age (1906 Edition Cover).jpg|thumb|[[A Crystal Age]], by [[W.H. Hudson]] (1906 Edition Cover).]]

===20th century &amp; after===
*''[[A Modern Utopia]]'' (1905) by [[H. G. Wells]].
*''[[A Crystal Age]]'' (1906), by [[W.H. Hudson]]. First published anonymously, in 1887. An amateur [[Ornithologists|ornithologist]] and [[botanist]] falls down a crevice, and wakes up centuries later, in a world where humans live in families, in harmony with each other and animals; but, where [[Human reproduction|reproduction]], emotions, and [[Secondary sex characteristic|secondary sexual]] characteristics are repressed, except for the [[Alpha (ethology)|Alpha males and females]]; and, the [[Human evolution|human species]] is gradually dying out.
*''[[Men Like Gods]]'' (1923) by H. G. Wells, men and women in an alternative universe live without [[world government]] in a perfected state of [[anarchy]]; &quot;Our education is our government,&quot; a Utopian named Lion says;&lt;ref&gt;H. G. Wells, ''Men Like Gods'', Book I, Ch. 5, Sect. 6.&lt;/ref&gt; sectarian religion, like politics, has died away, and advanced scientific research flourishes; life is governed by &quot;the Five Principles of Liberty,&quot; which are privacy, free movement, unlimited knowledge, truthfulness, and free discussion and criticism.
*''[[For us, the living|For Us, The Living]]'' (1938, published in 2003) by [[Robert A. Heinlein]], a futuristic utopian novel explaining practical views on love, freedom, drive, government and economics.
*''[[Islandia (novel)|Islandia]]'' (1942), by [[Austin Tappan Wright]], an imaginary island in the Southern Hemisphere, a utopia containing many [[Arcadia (utopia)|Arcadian]] elements, including a policy of isolation from the outside world and a rejection of industrialism. (In three sequels by [[Mark Saxton]], including ''[[The Islar]]'' (1969), below.)
*In the film ''[[Road to Utopia]]'' (1943), it was suggested (comically) that a personal Utopia could be obtained from the wealth of gold mines in Alaska, USA.
*''[[Walden Two]]'' (1948) by [[B. F. Skinner]], a community in which every aspect of living is put to rigorous scientific testing. A professor and his colleagues question the effectiveness of the community started by an eccentric man named T.E. Frazier.
*''[[Childhood's End]]'' (1954) by Arthur C. Clarke, alien beings guide humanity towards a more economically productive and technologically advanced society, allowing humans to broaden their mental capacities.
*''[[Big Planet]]'' (1957), by [[Jack Vance]], depicts a world in which attempts by utopian misfits to set up new societies have gone haywire after many revert to savagery and violence. But one city, Kirstendale, sets up a successful order in which citizens constantly shift their status, titles and duties (from servant to aristocrat and back again) according to an elaborate schedule.
*''[[Island (novel)|Island]]'' (1962) by [[Aldous Huxley]] follows the story of Will Farnaby, a cynical journalist, who shipwrecks on the fictional island of Pala and experiences their unique culture and traditions which create a utopian society.
*''[[The Islar]]'' (1969), the Islandians develop a modern air force to fend off hostile communist-allied neighbors, and debate whether to join the UN.
*''[[The Lathe of Heaven]]'' (1971), by [[Ursula K. Le Guin]], a man is able to &quot;effectively&quot; dream, changing waking reality. A psychologist to whom he goes for treatment tries to use the man's talent to improve society but finds that each of his &quot;solutions&quot; has disastrous unintended consequences.
*''[[The Dispossessed]]'' (1974), by [[Ursula K. Le Guin]], the story of two planets, one very much like the capitalist, materialistic, profligate United States and the other a &quot;nonpropertarian&quot; society in which private ownership is unknown and people merely use as much  natural resources or finished goods as they need. The two worlds are walled off (as were the capitalist and Communist world at the time of its writing). A physicist named Shevek travels between the two worlds and compares them in a literary structure much like that of Tolstoy's War and Peace.
*''[[Ecotopia]]: The Notebooks and Reports of William Weston'' (1975) by [[Ernest Callenbach]], ecological utopia in which the Pacific Northwest has seceded from the union to set up a new society.
*''[[Woman on the Edge of Time]]'' (1976) by [[Marge Piercy]], the story of a middle-aged Hispanic woman who has visions of two alternative futures, one utopian and the other dystopian.
*''[[The Probability Broach]]'' (1980), by [[L. Neil Smith]], presents both utopian and dystopian views of present day North America, through alternative outcomes of the American War for Independence.
*''[[Always Coming Home]]'' (1985), by [[Ursula K. Le Guin]], a combination of fiction and fictional [[anthropology]] about a society in California in the distant future.
*''[[The Fifth Sacred Thing]]'' (1993), by [[Starhawk]], a [[Apocalyptic and post-apocalyptic science fiction|post-apocalyptic novel]] depicting two societies, one a [[sustainable economy]] based on social justice, and its neighbor, a militaristic and intolerant [[theocracy]].
*''[[Aria (manga)|Aria]]'' (2001-2008), by [[Kozue Amano]], is a [[manga]] and [[anime]] series set on terraformed version of the planet [[Mars]] in the 24th century. The main character, Akari, is a trainee gondolier working in the city of Neo-Venezia, based on modern day [[Venice]].
*''The [[Star Trek]] Franchise'' (1966 to present day), consisting of many TV series, books and feature films, depicts a golden age for Mankind, in which earthlinks have achieved unprecedented social progress, mainly through technology, and uphold tolerance as a core virtue in their relations to neighbouring alien cultures. This golden age culminates in the late 24th century&lt;ref&gt;See for example [[Star Trek: The Next Generation]].&lt;/ref&gt; (the whole franchise's timeline spanning from the 22nd to the 24th century - or from the 20th to the 29th century if you take [[flashback (narrative)|flashbacks]]&lt;ref&gt;See for example [[Star Trek First Contact]] or [[Carbon Creek (Star Trek: Enterprise)|Carbon Creek]].&lt;/ref&gt; and [[time travel]] stories&lt;ref&gt;See for example [[Future's End]].&lt;/ref&gt; into account). The franchise also explores alternate timelines, some [[dystopia]]n.&lt;ref&gt;See for example [[In a Mirror, Darkly]].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
* [[Patricia Vieira &amp; Michael Marder, editors]] (2011) ''[http://www.amazon.com/Existential-Utopia-Perspectives-Utopian-Thought/dp/1441169210 Existential Utopia: New Perspectives on Utopian Thought]'' (London &amp; New York: Continuum) ISBN 1-4411-6921-0
* Clardy, Alan (2012) &quot;Galt's Gulch: Ayn Rand's Utopian Delusion&quot; ''Utopian Studies'' 23, 238-262 ISSN 1045-991X
* [[Krishan Kumar|Kumar, Krishan]] (1991) ''Utopianism'' (Milton Keynes: Open University Press) ISBN 0-335-15361-5
* [[Frank Manuel|Manuel, Frank]] &amp; [[Fritzie Manuel|Manuel, Fritzie]] (1979) ''Utopian Thought in the Western World'' (Oxford: Blackwell) ISBN 0-674-93185-8
* Hine, Robert V. (1983) ''California's Utopian Colonies'' (University of California Press)  ISBN 0-520-04885-7
* Kumar, K (1987) ''Utopia and Anti-utopia in Modern Times'' (Oxford: Blackwell) ISBN 0-631-16714-5
* Shadurski, Maxim I. (2007) ''Literary Utopias from More to Huxley: The Issues of Genre Poetics and Semiosphere. Finding an Island'' (Moscow: URSS) ISBN 978-5-382-00362-7

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
{{1913CE|Utopia}}
* [http://www.bartleby.com/65/ut/Utopia.html Utopia - The Columbia Encyclopedia, Sixth Edition, 2001]
* [http://www.ic.org Intentional Communities Directory]
* [http://www.utopias.info History of 15 Finnish] utopian settlements in Africa, the Americas, Asia, Australia and Europe.
* [http://www.stadtbaukunst.com/uploads//2_1_Towards_Another_Utopia_of_The_City.pdf Towards Another Utopia of The City] Institute of Urban Design, Bremen, Germany
* [http://www.bl.uk/learning/histcitizen/21cc/utopia/utopia.html Utopias] - a learning resource from the [[British Library]]
* [http://caius-ebook.com/Utopias.htm Utopia of the GOOD] An essay on Utopias and their nature.
* [http://www.scatolini.net/G.2009.art.01_SCATOLINI_EhudBenZVI_Utopia-and-Dystopia-in-Prophetic-Literature.pdf Review of Ehud Ben ZVI, Ed. (2006). Utopia and Dystopia in Prophetic Literature. Helsinki: The Finnish Exegetical Society.] A collection of articles on the issue of utopia and dystopia.
* [http://archive.org/details/storyutopias00mumfgoog The story of Utopias]  Mumford, Lewis

{{Narrative|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Idealism]]
[[Category:Utopias| ]]
[[Category:Words originating in fiction]]
[[Category:Greek loanwords]]

[[ar:أدب المدينة الفاضلة]]
[[az:Utopiya]]
[[be:Утопія]]
[[bg:Утопия]]
[[bo:ཡུལ་ཏོ་པི་ཡ།]]
[[ca:Utopia]]
[[cs:Utopie]]
[[da:Utopi]]
[[de:Utopie]]
[[et:Utoopia]]
[[el:Ουτοπία]]
[[es:Utopía]]
[[eo:Utopio]]
[[eu:Utopia]]
[[fa:آرمان‌شهر]]
[[fr:Utopie]]
[[ko:유토피아]]
[[hi:यूटोपिया]]
[[io:Utopio]]
[[id:Utopia]]
[[is:Útópía]]
[[it:Utopia]]
[[he:אוטופיה]]
[[kn:ಯುಟೊಪಿಯ]]
[[kk:Утопия]]
[[la:Utopia]]
[[lb:Utopie]]
[[lt:Utopija]]
[[hu:Utópia]]
[[ml:ഉട്ടോപ്യ]]
[[arz:يوتوبيا]]
[[ms:Utopia]]
[[nl:Utopie]]
[[ja:ユートピア]]
[[no:Utopi]]
[[nn:Utopi]]
[[oc:Utopia]]
[[pl:Utopia]]
[[pt:Utopia]]
[[ro:Utopie]]
[[ru:Утопия]]
[[sq:Utopia]]
[[simple:Utopia]]
[[sk:Utópia]]
[[sr:Утопија]]
[[sh:Utopija]]
[[fi:Utopia]]
[[sv:Utopi]]
[[ta:யுட்டோபியா]]
[[te:ఆదర్శధామం]]
[[tr:Ütopya]]
[[uk:Утопія]]
[[vi:Utopia]]
[[bat-smg:Utuopėjė]]
[[zh:乌托邦]]</text>
      <sha1>gsuk2tf5v2pyx7mnp8o9g640kp2jzt6</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
