<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Utopian socialism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>443081</id>
    <revision>
      <id>518427494</id>
      <parentid>518427362</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-18T01:30:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>75.157.55.34</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 518427362 by [[Special:Contributions/75.157.55.34|75.157.55.34]] ([[User talk:75.157.55.34|talk]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18608">{{Refimprove|date=November 2010}}
{{Unbalanced|date=November 2010}}
{{Socialism sidebar |expanded=Currents}}

'''Utopian Socialism''' is  a term used to define the first currents of modern [[Socialism|socialist]] thought as exemplified by the work of [[Claude Henri de Rouvroy, comte de Saint-Simon|Henri de Saint-Simon]], [[Charles Fourier]], and [[Robert Owen]], which inspired [[Karl Marx]] and other early socialists.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.pbs.org/heavenonearth/synopsis.html| title=Heaven on Earth: The Rise and Fall of Socialism| publisher=Public Broadcasting System| accessdate=December 15, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, visions of imaginary ideal societies, which competed with revolutionary social-democratic movements, were viewed as not being grounded in the material conditions of society and as reactionary.&lt;ref name=Draper&gt;{{cite book|last=Draper|first=Hal|title=Karl Marx's Theory of Revolution, Volume IV: Critique of Other Socialisms|year=1990|publisher=Monthly Review Press|location=New York|isbn=08534507980 {{Please check ISBN|reason=Invalid length.}}|pages=1–21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although it is technically possible for any set of ideas or any person living at any time in history to be a utopian socialist, the term is most often applied to those socialists who lived in the first quarter of the 19th century who were ascribed the label &quot;utopian&quot; by later socialists as a negative term, in order to imply naivete and dismiss their ideas as fanciful or unrealistic.&lt;ref name=&quot;SocialismAVeryShortIntroduction&quot;&gt;''Newman, Michael''. (2005) ''Socialism: A Very Short Introduction'', Oxford University Press, ISBN 0-19-280431-6&lt;/ref&gt; 

Religious sects whose members live communally, such as the [[Hutterites]], for example, are not usually called &quot;utopian socialists&quot;, although their way of living is a prime example. They have been categorized as [[religious socialism|religious socialists]] by some. Likewise, modern [[intentional communities]] based on socialist ideas could also be categorized as &quot;utopian socialist&quot;.

==Definition==
The utopian socialist thinkers did not use the term ''utopian'' to refer to their ideas. [[Karl Marx]] and [[Friedrich Engels]] referred to all socialist ideas that were simply a vision and distant goal for society as utopian. Utopian socialists were likened to scientists who drew up elaborate designs and concepts for creating what socialists considered a more equal society. They were contrasted by scientific socialists, likened to engineers, who were defined as an integrated conception of the goal, the means to producing it, and the way that those means will inevitably be produced through examining social and economic phenomena.

This distinction was made clear in Engels' work ''[[Socialism: Utopian and Scientific]]'' (1892, part of an earlier publication, the ''[[Anti-Dühring]]'' from 1878). Utopian socialists were seen as wanting to expand the principles of the French revolution in order to create a more &quot;rational&quot; society and economic system, and despite being labeled as utopian by later socialists, their aims were not always utopian with their values often included rigid support for the scientific method and creating a society based upon such.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1880/soc-utop/ch01.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

A key difference between &quot;utopian socialists&quot; and other socialists (including most [[anarchists]]) is that utopian socialists generally don't feel class struggle or political revolutions are necessary to implement their ideas; that people of all classes might voluntarily adopt their plan for society if it were presented convincingly.&lt;ref name=Draper&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; They often feel their form of cooperative socialism can be established among like-minded people within the existing society and establish small enterprises designed to demonstrate their plan for society.&lt;ref name=Draper&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Development==
[[Utopia]]n socialists never actually used this name to describe themselves; the term &quot;Utopian socialism&quot; was introduced by Karl Marx and Friedrich Engels in ''[[The Communist Manifesto]]'' in 1848, although Marx shortly before the publication of this pamphlet already attacked the ideas of [[Pierre-Joseph Proudhon]] in ''[[The poverty of philosophy|Das Elend der Philosophie]]'' (originally written in French, 1847) and used by later socialist thinkers to describe early socialist or quasi-socialist intellectuals who created hypothetical visions of [[egalitarian]], [[communalist]], [[meritocratic]], or other notions of &quot;perfect&quot; societies without actually concerning themselves with the manner in which these societies could be created or sustained.

In ''Das Elend der Philosophie'', English title ''The Poverty of Philosophy'', Marx criticized the [[Economics|economic]] and [[philosophy|philosophical]] arguments of Proudhon set forth in ''[[The System of Economic Contradictions, or The Philosophy of Poverty]]''. Marx accused Proudhon of wanting to rise above the [[bourgeoisie]]. In the history of Marx' thought and [[marxism]], this work is pivotal in the distinction between the concepts of utopian socialism and what Marx and the marxists claimed as ''scientific socialism''.

Although the utopian socialists did not share many common political, social, or economic perspectives, Marx and Engels argued that certain intellectual characteristics of the Utopian socialists unified the disparate thinkers. In ''The Communist Manifesto'',&lt;ref&gt;Engels, Friedrich and Marx, Karl Heinrich. »Manifest der Kommunistischen Partei«. Edited by Sálvio M. Soares. MetaLibri, October 31, 2008, v1.0s.&lt;/ref&gt; Marx and Engels wrote, &quot;The undeveloped state of the class struggle, as well as their own surroundings, causes Socialists of this kind to consider themselves far superior to all class antagonisms. They want to improve the condition of every member of society, even that of the most favored. Hence, they habitually appeal to society at large, without distinction of class; nay, by preference, to the ruling class. For how can people, when once they understand their system, fail to see it in the best possible plan of the best possible state of society? Hence, they reject all political, and especially all revolutionary, action; they wish to attain their ends by peaceful means, and endeavor, by small experiments, necessarily doomed to failure, and by the force of example, to pave the way for the new social Gospel.&quot;

Marx and Engels used the term &quot;[[scientific socialism]]&quot; to describe the type of socialism they saw themselves developing. According to Engels, socialism was not &quot;an accidental discovery of this or that ingenious brain, but the necessary outcome of the struggle between two historically developed classes{{spaced ndash}}the proletariat and the bourgeoisie. Its task was no longer to manufacture a system of society as perfect as possible, but to examine the historical-economic succession of events from which these classes and their antagonism had of necessity sprung, and to discover in the economic conditions thus created the means of ending the conflict.&quot;

Critics have argued that Utopian socialists who established experimental communities were in fact trying to apply the [[scientific method]] to human social organization, and were therefore not Utopian. For instance, [[Joshua Muravchik]], on the basis of [[Karl Popper]]'s definition of science as &quot;the practice of experimentation, of hypothesis and test,&quot; argued that &quot;Owen and Fourier and their followers were the real ‘scientific socialists.’ They hit upon the idea of socialism, and they tested it by attempting to form socialist communities.&quot; Muravchik further argued that, in contrast, Marx made untestable predictions about the future, and that Marx's view that socialism would be created by impersonal historical forces may lead one to conclude that it is unnecessary to strive for socialism, because it will happen anyway.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aei.org/speech/10009 The Rise and Fall of Socialism] Joshua Muravchik SPEECHES AEI Bradley Lecture Series Publication Date: February 8, 1999&lt;/ref&gt;

From the mid-19th century onwards, [[Marxism]] and [[Marxism-Leninism]] overtook utopian socialism in terms of intellectual development and number of adherents. At one time, almost half of the world's population was governed by self-proclaimed Marxists.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.historyguide.org/intellect/marx.html| author=Steven Kreis| title=Karl Marx, 1818-1883| publisher=The History Guide| date=January 30, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Utopian socialism in literature and in practice==
Perhaps the first utopian socialist was [[Thomas More]] (1478-1535), who wrote about an imaginary socialist society in his satire ''[[Utopia (book)|Utopia]]'', which was published in 1516. The contemporary definition of the English word &quot;utopia&quot; derives from this work.

[[File:Portrait of Robert Owen.png|thumb|Robert Owen was one of the founders of Utopian socialism.]]

[[Saint-Simonianism]] was a [[France|French]] political and social movement of the first half of the 19th century, inspired by the ideas of [[Claude Henri de Rouvroy, comte de Saint-Simon]] (1760–1825). His ideas influenced [[Auguste Comte]] (who was, for a time, Saint-Simon's secretary), [[Karl Marx]], [[John Stuart Mill]], and many other thinkers and social theorists.

[[Robert Owen]] (1771–1858) was a successful Welsh businessman who devoted much of his profits to improving the lives of his employees. His reputation grew when he set up a textile factory in [[New Lanark]], [[Scotland]], co-funded by his teacher, the [[Utilitarianism|utilitarian]] [[Jeremy Bentham]], and introduced shorter working hours, schools for children and renovated housing. He wrote about his ideas in his book ''A New View of Society'', which was published in 1813, and ''An Explanation of the Cause of Distress which pervades the civilized parts of the world'' in 1823. He also set up an [[Owenite]] commune called [[New Harmony, Indiana|New Harmony]] in [[Indiana]], USA. This collapsed when one of his business partners ran off with all the profits. Owen's main contribution to socialist thought was the view that human social behavior is not fixed or absolute, and that human beings have the free will to organize themselves into any kind of society they wished.

[[Charles Fourier]] (1772–1837) was by far the most utopian of the socialists{{Dubious|date=November 2010}}. Rejecting the [[industrial revolution]] altogether and thus the problems that arose with it, he made various fanciful claims about the ideal world he envisioned. Despite some clearly non-socialist inclinations{{Clarify|date=November 2010}}, he contributed significantly - if indirectly - to the socialist movement. His writings about turning work into play influenced the young [[Karl Marx]] and helped him devise his [[Marx's theory of alienation|theory of alienation]]. Also a contributor to [[feminism]], Fourier invented the concept of ''[[phalanstère]]'', units of people based on a theory of passions and of their combination. Several colonies based on Fourier's ideas were founded in the United States by [[Albert Brisbane]] and [[Horace Greeley]].

[[Étienne Cabet]] (1788–1856) who was influenced by Robert Owen, published a book in 1840 entitled ''Travel and adventures of Lord William Carisdall in Icaria'' in which he described an ideal [[communalist]] society. His attempts to form real socialist communities based on his ideas, through the [[Icarians|Icarian movement]] however, did not survive, but one such community was the precursor of [[Corning, Iowa]]. Possibly inspired by [[Christianity]], he coined the word &quot;communism&quot; and influenced other thinkers, including [[Karl Marx]] and [[Friedrich Engels]].

[[Edward Bellamy]] (1850–1898),  published ''[[Looking Backward]]'' in 1888, a utopian romance novel about a future socialist society. In Bellamy's utopia, property was held in common and money replaced with a system of equal credit for all. Valid for a year and non-transferable between individual persons, expenditure of this credit was to be tracked via 'credit-cards' (which bear no resemblance to modern credit cards which are tools of debt-finance). Labour between the ages of 21-40 was to be compulsory, and organised via various departments of an 'Industrial Army' to which most citizens belonged. However working hours were to be cut drastically due to technological advances (including organisational). People were expected to be motivated by a Religion of Solidarity, and e.g. criminal behavior was treated as a form of mental illness or 'atavism'. It was the second or third ranking best seller of its time (after Uncle Tom's Cabin and Ben Hur). Bellamy published a sequel ''Equality'' in 1897 as a reply to his critics, and from which the Industrial Army and other authoritarian aspects were absent.

[[William Morris]] (1834–1896) published ''[[News from Nowhere]]'' in 1890, partly as a response to Bellamy's ''Looking Backwards'' which he equated with the socialism of Fabians such as Sydney Webb. Morris' vision of the future socialist society was centred around his concept of useful work as opposed to useless toil, and the redemption of human labour. Morris believed that all work should be artistic, in the sense that the worker should find it both pleasurable and an outlet for creativity. Morris' conception of labour thus bears strong resemblance to Fourier's, whilst Bellamy's (i.e. the reduction of labour to a minimum) is more akin to that of Saint-Simon or indeed Marx.

The [[Brotherhood Church]] in Britain and the [[Life and Labor Commune]] in Russia were based on the [[Christian anarchist]] ideas of [[Leo Tolstoy]] (1828–1910).

[[Pierre-Joseph Proudhon]] (1809–1865) and [[Peter Kropotkin]] (1842–1921) wrote about anarchist forms of socialism in their books. Proudhon wrote ''[[What is Property?]]'' (1840) and ''[[The System of Economic Contradictions, or The Philosophy of Poverty]]'' (1847). Kropotkin wrote ''[[The Conquest of Bread]]'' (1892) and ''[[Fields, Factories and Workshops]]'' (1912). Many of the anarchist collectives formed in [[Spain]], especially in [[Aragon]] and [[Catalonia]], during the [[Spanish Civil War]] were based on their ideas.

Many participants in the historical [[kibbutz]] movement in [[Israel]] were motivated by utopian socialist ideas, but few examples of this type of kibbutz remain.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.askisrael.org/facts/qpt.asp?fid=21| title=The Kibbutz—Utopian Socialist Community| publisher=AskIsrael.org| accessdate=January 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Augustin Souchy]] (1892–1984) spent most of his life investigating and participating in many kinds of socialist communities. He wrote about his experiences in his autobiography ''Beware! Anarchist!''.

The [[philosopher]] and [[pornographer]] [[Marquis de Sade]] (1740-1814) anticipated Charles Fourier in his project of a harmonious utopia based on the free play of sexual passion in the pamphlet ''Yet Another Effort, Frenchmen, If You Would Become Republicans'', found in [[Philosophy in the Bedroom]].&lt;ref&gt;Marshall, Peter. ''Demanding the Impossible: A History of Anarchism.'' p.149.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Behavioral psychologist]] [[B.F. Skinner]] (1904–1990) published ''[[Walden Two]]'' in 1948. The [[Twin Oaks Community]] was originally based on his ideas.

[[Ursula K. Le Guin]] (born 1929) wrote about an impoverished anarchist planet in her book ''[[The Dispossessed]]'', which was published in 1974. The anarchists agree to leave their home planet and colonize the barren planet in order to avoid a bloody revolution.

==Related concepts==
A related concept is that of a '''socialist utopia''', usually depicted in works of fiction as possible ways society can turn out to be in the future, and often combined with notions of a technologically-revolutionized economy.

Some communities of the modern [[intentional community]] movement could be categorized as utopian socialist.

==Notable utopian socialists==
{{col-begin}}{{col-break}}
*[[Edward Bellamy]]
*[[Tommaso Campanella]]
*[[David Dale]]
*[[Etienne Cabet]]
**[[Icarians|Icarian movement]]
*[[Charles Fourier]]
**[[North American Phalanx]]
**''[[The Phalanx]]'' - journal {{nb10}}
{{col-break}}
*[[Jean-Baptiste Godin]]
*[[Thomas More]]
*[[John Humphrey Noyes]]
*[[Robert Owen]]
*[[Claude Henri de Rouvroy, comte de Saint-Simon|Claude Henri de Saint-Simon]]
*[[Wilhelm Weitling]]
{{col-end}}

==Notable utopian communities==
'''Owenian communities'''
*[[New Lanark]], [[New Harmony, Indiana|New Harmony]]

'''Fourierist communities'''
*[[La Reunion (Dallas)]] (founded in 1855) by [[Victor Considérant]]
*[[Brook Farm]]
*[[North American Phalanx]]

'''Icarian communities'''
*[[Corning, Iowa]]

'''Anarchist communities'''
*[[Whiteway Colony]]
*[[Life and Labor Commune]]

'''Others'''
*[[Kaweah Colony]]
*[[Oneida Community]]
*[[Ruskin Colony]]

==See also==
{{col-begin}}{{col-break}}
*[[List of anarchist communities]]
*[[Communist utopia]]
*[[Intentional communities]]
*[[Kibbutz]]
*[[Marxism]]
*[[Nanosocialism]]
{{col-break}}
*[[Post-capitalism]]
*[[Post-scarcity]]
*[[Scientific socialism]]
*[[Socialism]]
*[[Socialist economics]]
*[[Christian socialism]]
{{col-end}}

==References==
;Notes
{{Reflist}}

{{Refimprove|date=December 2007}}

==External links==
* [http://www.thenation.com/doc/20090323/pollin Be Utopian: Demand the Realistic] by Robert Pollin, ''The Nation'', March 9, 2009

{{DEFAULTSORT:Utopian Socialism}}
[[Category:Utopian socialism| ]]
[[Category:Socialism]]
[[Category:Utopias|Socialist]]
[[Category:History of social movements]]
[[Category:Social theories]]

[[ar:اشتراكية خيالية]]
[[ca:Socialisme utòpic]]
[[cs:Utopický socialismus]]
[[de:Frühsozialismus]]
[[et:Utopistlik sotsialism]]
[[es:Socialismo utópico]]
[[eu:Sozialismo utopiko]]
[[fa:سوسیالیسم تخیلی]]
[[fr:Socialisme utopique]]
[[gl:Socialismo utópico]]
[[ko:공상적 사회주의]]
[[id:Sosialisme Utopis]]
[[it:Socialismo utopistico]]
[[he:סוציאליזם אוטופי]]
[[kk:Утопиялық социализм]]
[[ky:Утопиялык социализм]]
[[lt:Utopinis socializmas]]
[[hu:Utópista szocializmus]]
[[nl:Vroege socialisme]]
[[ja:空想的社会主義]]
[[oc:Socialisme utopic]]
[[pl:Socjalizm utopijny]]
[[pt:Socialismo utópico]]
[[ru:Утопический социализм]]
[[sk:Utopický socializmus]]
[[sl:Utopični socializem]]
[[fi:Utopistinen sosialismi]]
[[sv:Utopisk socialism]]
[[uk:Утопічний соціалізм]]
[[vi:Chủ nghĩa xã hội không tưởng]]
[[zh:空想社会主义]]</text>
      <sha1>gnoy83o5tp1orlybj0yrgct51u6s34y</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
