<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Vladimir Lenin</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>11015252</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522144387</id>
      <parentid>522105041</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T08:20:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>RolandR</username>
        <id>689041</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted to revision 521249761 by Soul Train: Already agreed in talk discussions thet atheism is not a religion. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="140022">{{Redirect|Lenin}}
{{pp-move-indef}}{{pp-semi|small=yes}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2012}}
{{Infobox officeholder
|name = Vladimir Ilyich Lenin
&lt;small&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Владимир Ильич Ленин&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
|image =Lenin CL.jpg
|image_size = 210px
|caption = Lenin in 1920
|nationality =[[Soviet Union|Soviet]]&lt;br&gt;[[Russia]]n
|religion = None ([[atheist]])
|office= Chairman of the [[Council of People's Commissars|Council of People's Commissars of the Soviet Union]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;([[Premier of the Soviet Union]])
|term_start = 30 December 1922
|term_end = 21 January 1924
|predecessor = Position created
|successor = [[Alexey Rykov]]
|office2 = [[List of leaders of the Russian SFSR|Chairman]] of the [[Government of the Russian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic|Council of People's Commissars of the Russian SFSR]]
|term_start2 = 8 November 1917
|term_end2 = 21 January 1924
|predecessor2 = Position created
|successor2 = Alexey Rykov
| office3      =  Full member of the [[Politburo of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union|Politburo]]
| term_start3  = 25 March 1919
| term_end3    = 21 January 1924
|birth_date = {{birth date|df=yes|1870|4|22|df=y}}
|birthname = Vladimir Ilyich Ulyanov ({{lang|ru|Владимир Ильич Ульянов}})
|birth_place = [[Simbirsk]], [[Russian Empire]]
|death_date = {{death date and age|1924|1|21|1870|4|22|df=y}} (stroke)
|death_place = [[Gorki Leninskiye|Gorki]], [[Russian SFSR]], [[Soviet Union]]
|resting_place = [[Lenin's Mausoleum]], Moscow, [[Russian Federation]]
|profession = Lawyer, [[revolutionary]], politician
|spouse = [[Nadezhda Krupskaya]] (1898–1924)
|party = [[Russian Social Democratic Labour Party]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Communist Party of the Soviet Union|Russian Communist Party (bolsheviks)]]
|a.k.a. = Nikolai Lenin, N. Lenin, V. I. Lenin
|signature = Unterschrift_Lenins.svg
}}
'''Vladimir Ilyich Lenin''' ({{lang-rus|Владимир Ильич Ленин|a=Ru-Lenin.ogg|p=vlɐˈdʲimʲɪr ɪlʲˈjitɕ ˈlʲenʲɪn}}; born '''Vladimir Ilyich Ulyanov''', {{lang-rus|link=no|Владимир Ильич Ульянов|}}; {{OldStyleDate|22 April|1870|10 April}}&amp;nbsp;– 21 January 1924) was a [[Russian people|Russian]] [[Communism|communist]] revolutionary, politician and political theorist who served as the leader of the [[Russian SFSR]] from 1917, and then concurrently as [[Premier of the Soviet Union|Premier]] of the [[Soviet Union]] from 1922, until 1924. 

Born into a wealthy middle-class family in [[Simbirsk]], Lenin gained an interest in revolutionary leftist politics following the execution of his brother in 1887. Briefly attending the [[University of Kazan]], where he was ejected for his involvement in anti-Tsarist protests, he devoted the next few years to gaining a degree in law and to radical politics, becoming a Marxist. In 1893 he moved to Russia's capital at [[St. Petersburg]], where he continued with his political agitation, becoming a senior figure within the [[League of Struggle for the Emancipation of the Working Class]]. Arrested and exiled to Siberia for three years, he subsequently fled to Western Europe, living in Germany, England and then Switzerland. Following the [[February Revolution]] of 1917, in which the Tsar was overthrown and a provisional government took power, he decided to return home.

As the leader of the [[Bolshevik]] faction of the [[Russian Social Democratic Labour Party]], he took a senior role in orchestrating the [[October Revolution]] in 1917, which led to the overthrow of the [[Russian Provisional Government]] and the establishment of the [[Russian Socialist Federative Soviet Republic]], the world's first constitutionally [[socialist state]]. Immediately afterwards, Lenin proceeded to implement socialist reforms, including the transfer of estates and crown lands to workers' [[soviet (council)|soviets]]. Faced with the threat of German invasion, he argued that Russia should immediately [[Treaty of Brest-Litovsk|sign a peace treaty]]—which led to Russia's exit from the [[First World War]]. In 1921 Lenin proposed the [[New Economic Policy]], a system of [[state capitalism]] which started the process of industrialisation and recovery from the [[Russian Civil War]]. In 1922, the Russian SFSR [[Treaty on the Creation of the USSR|joined]] former territories of the Russian Empire in becoming the [[Soviet Union]]. The Bolshevik faction later became the [[Communist Party of the Soviet Union]], which acted as a [[vanguard party]] presiding over a [[Single-party state|single-party]] [[dictatorship of the proletariat]]. 

As a politician, Lenin was a persuasive and charismatic [[orator]]. As an intellectual his extensive theoretic and philosophical developments of [[Marxism]] produced [[Leninism|Marxism–Leninism]], a pragmatic [[Soviet Union|Russian]] application of Marxism that emphasized the critical role played by a committed and disciplined political vanguard in the revolutionary process, while defending the possibility of a socialist revolution in less advanced capitalist countries through an alliance of the proletarians with the rural peasantry. Lenin remains a controversial and highly divisive world figure. Critics labeled him a [[dictatorship|dictator]] whose administration oversaw multiple human rights abuses, but supporters countered this criticism citing the limitations on his power and promoted him heroically as a champion of the working class. He has had a significant influence on the Marxist–Leninist movement, which since his death had developed into a variety of schools of thought, namely [[Stalinism]], [[Trotskyism]] and [[Maoism]].

== Early life ==

=== Childhood: 1870&amp;ndash;1887 ===
Lenin's father, [[Ilya Nikolayevich Ulyanov]] (1831&amp;ndash;1886), had been born the fourth and final child of a couple living in [[Astrakhan]]. Ilya's father, a poor tailor named Nikolai Vassilievich Ulyanov, had been born a [[serfdom|serf]] of either [[Kalmyk people|Kalmyk]] or [[Tatars|Tatar]] descent, before marrying a far younger illiterate Kalmyk girl named Anna Alexeevna Smirnova when in his fifties. Ilya had escaped the poverty of his family by gaining admittance to the [[Kazan (Volga region) Federal University|University of Kazan]], where he studied mathematics and physics, before gaining employment teaching those subjects at the [[Institute for Nobles|Penza Institute for the Nobility]] in 1854.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Fis64|Fischer 1964]]. pp. 1&amp;ndash;2.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. pp. 12&amp;ndash;13.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. pp. 21&amp;ndash;23.&lt;/ref&gt; Introduced through a mutual friend to a woman named [[Maria Alexandrovna Ulyanova|Maria Alexandrovna Blank]] (1835&amp;ndash;1916), they fell in love, and were married in the summer of 1863.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Fis64|Fischer 1964]]. p. 5.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. p. 23.&lt;/ref&gt; Having been born into a relatively prosperous background, Mariya was the daughter of a Russian Jewish physician named Alexander Dmitrievich Blank, and his German-Swedish wife, Anna Ivanovna Grosschopf. An eccentric, Dr Blank had insisted on providing his children with a good education, ensuring that Mariya learned English and French alongside Russian and German and that she was well versed in Russian literature.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Fis64|Fischer 1964]]. pp. 2&amp;ndash;3, 7.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. p. 12.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. pp. 16&amp;ndash;19, 23.&lt;/ref&gt; Soon after their wedding, Ilya obtained a job teaching in [[Nizhni Novgorod]], before being appointed to the position of director of primary schools in the [[Simbirsk]] district six years later. Five years after that, he was promoted to Director of Public Schools for the province, overseeing the foundation of over 450 schools as a part of the government's plans for modernisation. As a result, he was awarded the [[Order of St. Vladimir]] and given the position of an [[Russian nobility|hereditary nobleman]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer 1964. p. 6&quot;&gt;[[#Fis64|Fischer 1964]]. p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. pp. 13&amp;ndash;14, 18.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. pp. 25, 27.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Lenin Age 4.jpg|right|thumb|upright|&quot;Volodya&quot;, aged four. Following the foundation of the Soviet Union, this image would be widely published.]]

The middle-class couple had two children, Anna (born 1864) and Alexander (born 1868) before the birth of their third child, Vladimir &quot;Volodya&quot; Ilyich ({{lang-rus|Владимир Ильич Ульянов}}), on 10 April 1870, who would be baptised in the nearby St Nicholas Cathedral several days later. They would be followed by three more children, Olga (born 1871), Dmitry (born 1874) and Mariya (born 1878). Another brother, Nikolai, had been born in 1873, but had died several days after birth.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer 1964. p. 6&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. p. 12, 14.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. pp. 13, 25.&lt;/ref&gt; Ilya was a devout member of the [[Russian Orthodox Church]] and had his children baptised into it, although Mariya, who had been raised a [[Lutheranism|Lutheran]], was largely indifferent to [[Christianity]], a view that influenced the beliefs of her children.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Fis64|Fischer 1964]]. pp. 3, 8.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. pp. 14&amp;ndash;15.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. p. 29.&lt;/ref&gt; Politically, both parents were [[monarchism|monarchists]] and [[liberal conservatism|liberal conservatives]], being committed to the [[Emancipation reform of 1861]] introduced by the reformist [[Alexander II of Russia|Tsar Alexander II]] and hoping that Russia would progress in much the same way as Western Europe had; they avoided associating with political radicals and there is no evidence that the Tsarist police ever put them under surveillance for subversive thought.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Fis64|Fischer 1964]]. p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. p. 27.&lt;/ref&gt; Every summer they would leave their home in Moscow Street, Simbirsk and spend a holiday at a rural manor house in [[Lenino-Kokushkino|Kokushkino]] that was shared with the family's Veretennikov cousins, relatives of Mariya.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. p. 26.&lt;/ref&gt; Among his siblings, the young Vladimir was closest to his sister Olya, whom he often bossed around, having an extremely competitive nature; he could be destructive, but would usually admit to his misbehaviour.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer 1964. p. 7&quot;&gt;[[#Fis64|Fischer 1964]]. p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. pp. 32&amp;ndash;36.&lt;/ref&gt; A keen sportsman, he spent much of his free time outdoors or playing [[chess]], but his father insisted that he devote his life to study, leading him to excel at school, the Simbirsk Classical Gimnazia, a strictly disciplinarian and conservative institution. By his teenage years, Vladimir was coaching his elder sister in his favourite subject, [[Latin]], and gave private tuition to a student from the ethnic [[Chuvash people|Chuvash]] minority.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer 1964. p. 7&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. pp. 36&amp;ndash;41, 43&amp;ndash;46.&lt;/ref&gt;

Ilya Ulyanov died of a [[brain haemorrhage]] on 12 January 1886, when Vladimir was 16 years old.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Fis64|Fischer 1964]]. pp. 6, 9.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. pp. 48&amp;ndash;49.&lt;/ref&gt; His behaviour becoming increasingly erratic and confrontational, shortly thereafter Vladimir renounced his belief in [[God]], becoming an [[atheism|atheist]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Fis64|Fischer 1964]]. p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. pp. 50&amp;ndash;51, 64.&lt;/ref&gt; At the time, Vladimir's elder brother [[Aleksandr Ulyanov]], whom he affectionately knew as Sacha, was studying biology at [[Saint Petersburg State University|St. Petersburg University]], in 1885 having been awarded a gold medal for his dissertation, after which he was elected onto the university's Scientific-Literary Society. He had become involved in political agitation against the [[absolute monarchy]] of reactionary [[Tsar]] [[Alexander III of Russia|Alexander III]] which governed the Russian Empire, reading the writings of a number of banned leftist authors, including [[Dmitry Pisarev]], [[Nikolay Dobrolyubov]], [[Nikolay Chernyshevsky]] and [[Karl Marx]]. Helping to organise protests against the Tsarist government, he joined a small cell of socialist revolutionaries who were bent on assassinating the Tsar and with his scientific background was selected to construct a bomb for use in the plot. Before they had the chance to carry out the attack, the conspirators were arrested by police and put on trial. On 25 April 1887, Sacha was sentenced to death by hanging, and executed on 8 May.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Fis64|Fischer 1964]]. pp. 10&amp;ndash;17.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. pp. 20, 22&amp;ndash;24.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. pp. 52&amp;ndash;58.&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the emotional trauma brought on by the recent deaths of his father and brother, Vladimir continued with his studies, leaving school with a gold medal for his exceptional performance, and decided that he wanted to study law at Kazan University.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer 18&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. p. 25.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. p. 61.&lt;/ref&gt;

===University and political radicalism: 1887&amp;ndash;1893===

Entering the Judicial Faculty of [[Kazan (Volga region) Federal University|Kazan University]] in August 1887, Vladimir moved into a flat in the city, being joined in November by his mother, who began renting out their Simbirsk family home.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer 18&quot;&gt;[[#Fis64|Fischer 1964]]. p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. p. 26.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. pp. 61&amp;ndash;63.&lt;/ref&gt; He had begun to take an interest in his late brother's radical ideas, having been particularly interested by Nikolai Chernyshevsky's novel ''[[What Is to Be Done? (novel)|What is to be Done?]]'' (1863). He began meeting with a secretive revolutionary cell run by the militant [[agrarian socialism|agrarian socialist]] Lazar Bogoraz. Joining the now-illegal Samara-Simbirsk ''[[zemlyachestvo]]'' at the university, he was elected to be its representative in the university's secret ''zemlyachestvo'' council, and began to associate with leftists intent on reviving the [[Narodnaya Volya|People's Freedom Party]] (''Narodnaya Volya''), a leftist militant group responsible for assassinating Tsar [[Alexander II of Russia|Alexander II]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. pp. 26&amp;ndash;27.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. pp. 64&amp;ndash;68, 70.&lt;/ref&gt; On 4 December he took part in a demonstration demanding the abolition of the 1884 statute and the re-legalisation of student societies, but along with 100 other protesters was arrested by police. Accused of being a ringleader in the protests, the university expelled him and the [[Ministry of Internal Affairs (Russia)|Ministry of Internal Affairs]] ordered him to be put under police surveillance and exiled to his family's Kokushkino estate.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer 18&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. p. 27.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. pp. 68&amp;ndash;69.&lt;/ref&gt; From here, he set about voraciously reading radical texts, becoming particularly enamoured with the work of Chernyshevsky.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer 18&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. p. 28.&lt;/ref&gt; His mother disliked his radicalism, in September 1888 persuading him to write to the Ministry of the Interior asking them to allow him to study at a foreign university, and although they refused his request, they did allow him to move back to [[Kazan]], where he settled on the Pervaya Gora with his mother and brother Dmitry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer 18&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. p. 71.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Lenin-circa-1887.jpg|thumb|150px|left|Lenin, {{circa|1887}}, as he was beginning to develop revolutionary socialist beliefs.]]

In Kazan, he made contact with the revolutionary M.P. Chetvergova, joining her secret political circle, who spent much of their time discussing political strategies. Here he was introduced to [[Marxism|Marxist]] theory through Karl Marx's study of capitalist economy, ''[[Das Kapital|Capital]]'' (1867), a book which exerted a strong influence on him.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer 19&quot;&gt;[[#Fis64|Fischer 1964]]. p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. pp. 32&amp;ndash;33.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. p. 72.&lt;/ref&gt; His mother was increasing wary of his political views, and purchased an estate in the village of Alakaevka, [[Samara Oblast]] &amp;ndash; made famous in the work of poet [[Gleb Uspensky]], of whom Lenin was a great fan &amp;ndash; in the hope that Vladimir would turn his attention to agriculture rather than politics. Here, he began studying the life of the peasants and the poverty that many of them faced, something that would later exert a strong influence over his views. Nevertheless, he remained locally unpopular, with peasants stealing his farm equipment and livestock, and so his mother subsequently decided to sell the farm.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer 19&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. p. 33.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. pp. 74&amp;ndash;76.&lt;/ref&gt; In September 1889, the Ulyanovs moved to [[Samara, Russia|Samara]] for the winter, where Vladimir made contact with a number of dissidents who had been exiled there for their political views, joining a discussion circle run by Alexei P. Sklyarenko. At the time both Vladimir and Sklyarenko adopted Marxism, with Vladimir translating Marx and [[Friedrich Engels]]' political pamphlet, ''[[The Communist Manifesto]]'' (1848), into Russian for the benefit of his circle. He began to read the works of the Russian Marxist [[Georgi Plekhanov]] (1856&amp;ndash;1918), a founder of the [[Black Repartition]] movement, concurring with Plekhanov's argument that Russia was undoubtedly moving from [[feudalism]] to [[capitalism]], and that a Marxist analysis of Russian society was therefore apt. Becoming increasingly sceptical of the usefulness of militant attacks and assassinations, he argued against such tactics in a December 1889 debate with M.V. Sabunaev, who was in the area trying to recruit members for the People's Freedom Party. Nevertheless, despite disagreeing on tactics, he made friends among the People's Freedom Party, in particular an older man named Apollon Shukht, who would later ask Vladimir to be the [[Legal guardian|godfather]] of his daughter in 1893.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. p. 34.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. pp. 77&amp;ndash;80.&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 1890, Mariya managed to convince the authorities to allow Vladimir to undertake his exams externally at a university of choice. He picked the [[Saint Petersburg State University|University of Saint Petersburg]], where he obtained the equivalent of a first-class degree honours. However, celebrations were marred when his sister Olga was struck down with [[typhoid]] and died.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. pp. 34&amp;ndash;36.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. pp. 82&amp;ndash;86.&lt;/ref&gt; Vladimir remained in Samara for several years, in January 1892 being employed as a legal assistant for a regional court, and soon after gaining a job working for local lawyer Andrei N. Khardin. Embroiled primarily in disputes between peasants and artisans, he continued to devote much of his time to radical politics, remaining active in Skylarenko's group and formulating his own ideas about Marxism's applicability to Russia. Inspired by Plekhanov's work, Vladimir began collecting data on Russian society and its various social classes, using it to support a Marxist interpretation of societal development.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer 21&quot;&gt;[[#Fis64|Fischer 1964]]. p. 21.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. pp. 36&amp;ndash;37.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. pp. 86&amp;ndash;90.&lt;/ref&gt; Hoping to be taken seriously as an intellectual, in 1893 he submitted a paper, &quot;New Economic Developments in Peasant Life&quot;, to the liberal journal ''Russian Thought'', but it was rejected; it would eventually see publication in 1927.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer 21&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. p. 38.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. pp. 93&amp;ndash;94.&lt;/ref&gt; In the autumn of 1893, Lenin wrote ''On the So-Called Market Question'' which was his first attempt to reveal the true capitalist nature of the peasant economy of Russia.&lt;ref&gt;V. I. Lenin, &quot;On the So-Called Market Question,&quot; contained in ''Lenin: Collected Works, Volume 1'', pp. 75–125.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Revolutionary activities==

===St. Petersburg and foreign visits: 1893&amp;ndash;1895===

In the autumn of 1893, Vladimir moved to [[St. Petersburg]], capital city of the Russian Empire, which was then undergoing a process of massive [[industrialisation]]. He first took up residence in an apartment block on Sergievsky Street in the Liteiny district, before moving to 7 Kazachy Alley, near the Haymarket.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. pp. 38&amp;ndash;39.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. pp. 90&amp;ndash;92.&lt;/ref&gt; Taking up a job as assistant to the lawyer M.F. Volkenstein, he joined a clandestine revolutionary cell run by S.I. Radchenko, whose members were primarily students from the city's [[Saint Petersburg State Institute of Technology|Technological Institute]]. Like Vladimir, they were Marxists, and called themselves the &quot;Social Democrats&quot; after the [[Social Democratic Party of Germany]], which at the time was also Marxist. Impressed by his extensive knowledge, they welcomed him in and he soon became a senior member of the group.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. pp. 39&amp;ndash;40.&lt;/ref&gt; Championing Marxist thought among the revolutionary socialist movement, in January 1894 he openly debated with the well known theorist V.P. Vorontsov, author of ''The Fate of Capitalism in Russia'' (1882) at a clandestine meeting, where his outspoken behaviour was noted by a police spy who was present.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt; Intent on building the Marxist movement in Russia, Vladimir contacted Petr Bernardovich Struve, a wealthy sympathizer whom he hoped could aid in the publication of further Marxist literature, and encouraged the foundation of further revolutionary cells in Russia's major industrial centres.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. p. 43.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. p. 96.&lt;/ref&gt; He also became friends with a young Russian Jewish Marxist named [[Julius Martov]] (1873&amp;ndash;1923), who encouraged his comrades in the group to spend less time intellectually theorising and more time engaged in revolutionary activity.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. pp. 104&amp;ndash;105.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{double image|right|Lenin-1895-mugshot.jpg|170|KrupskayaPhoto.png|160|Lenin, then Ulyanov, (left) in a [[mug shot|police photograph]] from December 1895, and his lover Nadya (right), who would later become his wife.}}

Vladimir entered into a relationship with a fellow Marxist, the schoolteacher [[Nadezhda Krupskaya|Nadezhda &quot;Nadya&quot; Krupskaya]] (1869&amp;ndash;1939), who introduced him to a number of socialist workers.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Fis64|Fischer 1964]]. p. 22.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. p. 41.&lt;/ref&gt; By autumn 1894, Vladimir was the leader of a workers' circle who met for two hours on a Sunday to discuss revolutionary socialist ideas; to them he was known by a pseudonym, Nikolai Petrovich, although they affectionately referred to him as ''starik'' (old man) because of his appearance. He was meticulous in covering his tracks, knowing that the police had many spies trying to infiltrate the revolutionary movement.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. pp. 41&amp;ndash;42.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. p. 105.&lt;/ref&gt; He also wrote his first political tract, ''What the &quot;Friends of the People&quot; Are and How They Fight the Social-Democrats''; based largely on his experiences in Samara, around 200 copies were printed illegally and then distributed.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. pp. 42&amp;ndash;43.&lt;/ref&gt; Although they borrowed ideas from one another, Lenin and the Social-Democrats clashed with the ideas of the [[Socialist–Revolutionary Party]] (SR), who were inspired by the example of the now-defunct People's Freedom Party. Advocating an agrarian-socialist platform, the SR emphasised the role of the peasant as revolutionary, highlighting the fact that in 1881, the Russian peasantry numbered 75 million, while the urban proletariat numbered only 1 million. In contrast, the Marxists believed that the peasant class' primary motivation was to own their own land, and that they were therefore capitalists, not socialists; instead, they saw the proletariat as the revolutionary force who would bring about socialism.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Fis64|Fischer 1964]]. pp. 23&amp;ndash;25.&lt;/ref&gt; Lenin nevertheless retained an influence from the thought of militant agrarian-socialist [[Pyotr Tkachev|Pëtr Tkachëvi]] (1844&amp;ndash;1886).&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. p. 98.&lt;/ref&gt;

He hoped that connections could be cemented between his Social-Democratic movement and the [[Emancipation of Labour]] group; an organisation founded in [[Geneva]], [[Switzerland]] by Pleckhanov and other Russian Marxist emigres in 1883. Vladimir and E.I. Sponti were selected to travel to Switzerland to meet with Pleckhanov, who was generally supportive but criticised the Social-Democrats for ignoring the role that the [[bourgeoisie]] could play in the anti-Tsarist revolution.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer 30&quot;&gt;[[#Fis64|Fischer 1964]]. p. 30.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. pp. 44&amp;ndash;45.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Service 103&quot;&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. p. 103.&lt;/ref&gt; Traveling on to [[Zurich]], Vladimir met and befriended [[Pavel Axelrod]], another member of Emancipation of Labour.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. pp. 45&amp;ndash;46.&lt;/ref&gt; Proceeding to [[Paris]], [[France]], Vladimir met with [[Paul Lafargue]] and undertook research into the [[Paris Commune|Paris Commune of 1871]], which he saw as an early prototype for a proletarian government.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rice 1990. p. 46&quot;&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. p. 46.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Service 103&quot;/&gt; Financed by his mother, he returned to Switzerland to stay in a health spa before traveling to [[Berlin]], [[Germany]], where he studied for six weeks at the [[Staatsbibliothek]] and met with [[Wilhelm Liebknecht]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer 30&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Rice 1990. p. 46&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Service 103&quot;/&gt; Returning to Russia with a stash of illegal revolutionary literature, he traveled to various cities, becoming aware that he was being monitored by the police. Coinciding with a series of strikes in St. Petersburg, centered on the Thornton textile mill in 1895, he distributed Marxist literature to the workers,&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. pp. 47&amp;ndash;48.&lt;/ref&gt; and was also involved in the production of a news sheet, ''The Workers' Cause''. However, both he and 40 other activists were arrested on the night before the first issue's publication and charged with committing seditious activities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer 31&quot;&gt;[[#Fis64|Fischer 1964]]. p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. p. 48.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Siberian exile: 1895&amp;ndash;1900===
Imprisoned at the House of Preliminary Detention in Shpalernaya Street, during initial interrogation Vladimir was refused legal representation, and so denied all of the charges that the police brought against him. His family rallied round to help him, but he was refused bail, meaning that he had to remain imprisoned for a year before sentencing. His fellow revolutionaries were able to smuggle messages into him, while he devised a code for playing chess with the inmate in his neighbouring cell. He spent much of his time writing, focusing on the role of the working class in what he thought was the coming revolution; believing that the rise of industrial capitalism had led large numbers of peasants to move to the cities, where they became proletariat, he argued that [[class consciousness]] would eventually develop, leading the proletariat to rise up in violent revolution against the aristocracy and bourgeoisie who oppressed them. By July 1896 he had finished ''Draft and Explanation of A Programme for the Social Democratic Party'' and had commenced work on his book ''The Development of Capitalism in Russia''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer 31&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. pp. 48&amp;ndash;51.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. pp. 107&amp;ndash;108.&lt;/ref&gt;

Along with most of his comrades, Vladimir Ulyanov was sentenced without trial to 3 years exile in eastern Siberia. Given a few days in St. Petersburg in February 1897 to put his affairs in order before being sent east, he used this as an opportunity to meet up with fellow revolutionaries. While imprisoned, the Social-Democratic movement had been renamed the [[League of Struggle for the Emancipation of the Working Class]], and with many of its leading intelligentsia imprisoned, workers had taken over a number of senior positions, a move that caused rifts in the organisation but which gained Vladimir's cautious support. In 1896&amp;ndash;97, strikes had hit St. Petersburg in an attempt to decrease the working day from 12 or 13 hours to 10 and a half, but while the Marxists were not responsible for its organisation, they had proved influential in helping to organise the strikers themselves. Believing his predictions regarding class consciousness to be coming true, Vladimir was unhappy at having to abandon the movement at this crucial period.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer 31&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. pp. 52&amp;ndash;55.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. pp. 109&amp;ndash;110.&lt;/ref&gt; The Tsarist government made use of a large network of prison camps and areas of exile on the verges of its empire to deal with dissidents and criminals; by 1897 there were 300,000 Russian citizens in this system, and Vladimir was now one of them.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. p. 53.&lt;/ref&gt; Permitted to make his own way there without escort, the journey to eastern Siberia took him 11 weeks, for much of which he was accompanied by his mother and sisters. Considered a minor threat, Vladimir was exiled to the village of [[Shushenskoye]] in the [[Minusinsky District]], a settlement that Vladimir would describe as &quot;not a bad place&quot;. Renting a room in a peasant's hut, he was kept under constant police surveillance, but maintained a large number of correspondences with other subversives, many of whom actually came to visit him, and also went on trips to hunt duck and snipe and to swim in the [[Yenisei River]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer 31-32&quot;&gt;[[#Fis64|Fischer 1964]]. pp. 31&amp;ndash;32.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. pp. 53, 55&amp;ndash;56.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. pp. 110&amp;ndash;113.&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 1898, Vladimir's partner Nadya joined him in exile, having been arrested in August 1896 for organizing a strike. Although she was initially posted to [[Ufa]], she successfully convinced the authorities to allow her to move to Shushenskoye, claiming that she and Vladimir were engaged; they subsequently married in a church service on 10 July 1898.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer 33&quot;&gt;[[#Fis64|Fischer 1964]]. p. 33.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. pp. 114, 140.&lt;/ref&gt; Settling into a family life with Nadya's widowed mother Elizaveta Vasilyevna, the couple began translating [[Sidney Webb|Sidney]] and [[Beatrice Webb]]'s ''The History of Trade Unionism'' (1894) into Russian, a job obtained for them by Struve.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer 33-32&quot;&gt;[[#Fis64|Fischer 1964]]. pp. 33&amp;ndash;34.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. pp. 53, 55&amp;ndash;56, 58.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. p. 117.&lt;/ref&gt; The couple were keen to keep abreast of the developments within the German Marxist movement, which had received significant electoral support through the [[Social Democratic Party of Germany|Social Democratic Party]] (SDP). However, in Germany there had been an ideological split, with [[Revisionism (Marxism)|revisionists]] like [[Eduard Bernstein]] advocating a peaceful and electoral path to socialism, something that conflicted with the orthodox Marxist idea advocating violent proletariat revolution; he remained devoted to the latter, composing ''A Protest by Russian Social-Democrats'' attacking revisionist arguments.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. pp. 61&amp;ndash;63.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. p. 124.&lt;/ref&gt; Vladimir, by this time using various pseudonyms, also finished writing ''[[The Development of Capitalism in Russia]]'' (1899), then his longest book to date, which offered a well-researched and polemical attack on the Social-Revolutionaries and their beliefs, arguing that capitalism was already establishing itself in the Russian countryside, thereby supporting a Marxist analysis of Russian economic development. Published under the pseudonym of &quot;Vladimir Ilin&quot;, it would later be described by Lenin biographer [[Robert Service (historian)|Robert Service]] as  &quot;a ''tour de force''&quot;, but received predominantly poor reviews upon publication.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. pp. 57&amp;ndash;58.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. pp. 121&amp;ndash;124, 137.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Munich, London and Geneva: 1900&amp;ndash;1905===
His three year exile over, Vladimir was banned from returning to St. Petersburg, instead settling in [[Pskov]], a small town two hours' train ride from the capital, in February 1900. However, his wife, who had not served the entirety of her sentence, remained in exile in [[Ufa]], where she fell ill.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer 34-35&quot;&gt;[[#Fis64|Fischer 1964]]. pp. 34&amp;ndash;35.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. p. 64.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. pp. 124&amp;ndash;125.&lt;/ref&gt; Intent on founding a newspaper through which he could advocate his positions against the Marxist revisionists, the Social-Revolutionary Party and the government, Vladimir and Struve began raising money for the publication of ''[[Iskra]]'' (''The Spark''), a new organ of the Russian Marxist movement, by now calling itself the [[Russian Social Democratic Labour Party]] (RSDLP). After visiting his wife in Ufa, on 29 July 1900, he then left Russia for Western Europe. In Switzerland and Germany, he held talks with senior Marxists such as Axelrod, Plekhanov and Potresov and gave lectures on the situation in Russia. On 24 August 1900, a conference of Russian Marxists was held in the Swiss town of [[Corsier]] to discuss the development of ''Iskra'', but both Vladimir and Potresov were shocked at the controlling nature of Plekhanov, particularly when he gave an [[anti-semitic]] outburst; both of them lost a lot of respect for &quot;the father of Russian Marxism&quot;, a man whom they had always looked up to. Ultimately, it was agreed that the paper would be produced in Munich, where it would be harder for the Swiss-based Plekhanov to control it, and Vladimir moved to the city in September 1900. The first issue was printed on Christmas Eve, and contained an article written by Vladimir decrying European intervention in the [[Boxer Rebellion]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer 35&quot;&gt;[[#Fis64|Fischer 1964]]. p. 35.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. pp. 64&amp;ndash;69.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. pp. 129&amp;ndash;135.&lt;/ref&gt; A second RSDLP publication, entitled ''[[Zarya (publication)|Zarya]]'', appeared in March 1901, and would run for four issues, but ''Iskra'' was far more successful, being smuggled into Russia illegally, where it was then distributed, becoming the most successful Russian underground publication for 50 years. It contained contributions from such figures as the Polish [[Rosa Luxemburg]], the Czech-German [[Karl Kautsky]], and a young Ukrainian Marxist, [[Leon Trotsky]], who became a regular contributor from the autumn of 1902.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. pp. 69&amp;ndash;70.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Iskra.jpg|thumb|300px|left|The first issue of ''Iskra'', official organ of the Russian Social Democratic Labour Party. Edited by Lenin from his base in Geneva, Switzerland, copies would be smuggled into Russia, where it would prove successful in winning support for the Marxist revolutionary cause.]]

Vladimir Ulyanov adopted the ''[[nom de guerre]]'' of &quot;Lenin&quot; in December 1901, possibly taking the [[River Lena]] as a basis, thereby imitating the manner in which Plekhanov had adopted the pseudonym on &quot;Volgin&quot; after the [[River Volga]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Fis64|Fischer 1964]]. pp. 4&amp;ndash;5.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. p. 137.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1902, he published a political pamphlet entitled ''[[What Is to Be Done?]]'' &amp;ndash; named after the influential Chernychevsky novel &amp;ndash; under this new pseudonym. His most influential publication to date, it dealt with Lenin's thoughts on the need to form a [[vanguard party]] who would lead the working classes to revolution.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. pp. 137&amp;ndash;142.&lt;/ref&gt; When his wife finished her sentence in exile, she too left Russia for [[Munich]], where the couple were reunited; she became his personal secretary, aiding him in the production of ''Iskra''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer 37&quot;&gt;[[#Fis64|Fischer 1964]]. p. 37.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. p.70.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. p. 136.&lt;/ref&gt; Together, they continued their political agitation, with Lenin writing further articles for ''Iskra'' and drafting the program for the RSDLP, attacking both ideological dissenters and external critics.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer 37&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. pp. 143&amp;ndash;144.&lt;/ref&gt; Despite remaining an orthodox Marxist, he had begun to accept the Social Revolutionary Party's views on the revolutionary power of the Russian peasantry, penning a pamphlet while in Geneva in 1903 entitled ''To the Village Poor'', in which he tried to convert them to the Marxist cause.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer 38&quot;&gt;[[#Fis64|Fischer 1964]]. p. 38.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1903, Lenin attended the [[2nd Congress of the Russian Social Democratic Labour Party]] which initially convened at [[Brussels]] before moving to London. Here a longstanding ideological split developed within the party between the [[Bolshevik]] faction, led by Lenin, and the [[Menshevik]] faction, led by Martov. These terms &quot;Bolshevik&quot; (from the Russian ''bol'shinstvo'' meaning &quot;majority&quot;) and &quot;Menshevik&quot; (from the Russian ''menshinstvo'' meaning &quot;minority&quot;) derive from the narrow Bolshevik electoral defeat of the Mensheviks to the party's newspaper editorial board, and to central committee leadership.&lt;ref name=&quot;christopher_read_lenin&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title=Lenin: A Revolutionary Life | publisher=Psychology Press | author=Read, Christopher | year=2005 | isbn=978-0-415-20649-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|pages=60–1}} The break partly originated from Lenin's book ''[[What Is to Be Done?]]'' (1902), which proposed a smaller party organisation of ''professional'' [[revolutionary|revolutionaries]], with ''Iskra'' in a primary [[Ideology|ideologic]] role. Another issue which divided the two factions was Lenin's support of a worker-peasant alliance to overthrow the Tsarist regime as opposed to the Menshevik's support of an alliance between the working classes and the liberal bourgeoisie to achieve the same aim (whilst a small third faction led by [[Trotsky]] espoused the view that the working class alone was the instrument of revolutionary change—needing no help from either the peasants or the middle classes).&lt;ref&gt;Rupert Woodfin (2004) ''Introducing Marxism''. Royston: Icon Books, p. 91&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:House of Lenin in Zurich.jpg|thumb|right|Lenin's residence during his exile in [[Zürich]], Switzerland, taken in 1920]]

===The 1905 Revolution: 1905&amp;ndash;1907===

In November 1905, Lenin returned to Russia to support the [[Russian Revolution (1905)|1905 Russian Revolution]].&lt;ref name=&quot;christopher_read_lenin&quot;/&gt;{{rp|page=81}} In 1906, he was elected to the Presidium of the RSDLP; and shuttled between [[Finland]] and Russia, but resumed his exile in December 1907, after the Tsarist defeat of the revolution and after the scandal of the [[1907 Tiflis bank robbery]].&lt;ref name=&quot;christopher_read_lenin&quot;/&gt;{{rp|page=81}} Until the February and October revolutions of 1917, he lived in Western Europe, where, despite relative poverty, he developed [[Leninism]]—urban [[Marxism]] adapted to agrarian Russia reversing Karl Marx's economics–politics prescription to allow for a dynamic revolution led by a [[vanguard party]] of professional revolutionaries.&lt;ref name=&quot;christopher_read_lenin&quot;/&gt;{{rp|page=86}}&lt;ref name=&quot;international_political_economy&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title=Introduction to International Political Economy | publisher=Prentice-Hall | author=Balaam, David N. and Veseth, Michael | year=2001 | edition=2 | pages=76–78 | isbn=978-0-13-018349-1 | quote=Lenin developed a perspective on IPE that took Marx's class struggle, based on the mode of production, and used it to explain capitalism's international effects as transmitted through the production and finance structures of rich industrial countries to the poorer developing regions of the world. Lenin's famous summary of his views is Imperialism: The Highest Stage of Capitalism (1917). | url=http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/commandingheights/shared/minitextlo/ess_leninscritique.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Return to exile: 1907&amp;ndash;1917===

In 1909, to disambiguate philosophic doubts about the proper practical course of a [[Communist revolution|socialist revolution]], Lenin published ''[[Materialism and Empirio-criticism]]'' (1909), which became a [[philosophy|philosophic]] foundation of [[Marxism-Leninism]]. Throughout exile, Lenin travelled Europe, participated in socialist activities, (the 1912 [[Prague Party Conference]]). When [[Inessa Armand]] left Russia for Paris, she met Lenin and other exiled Bolsheviks. Rumour has it she was Lenin's lover; yet historian Neil Harding notes that there is a &quot;slender stock of evidence . . . we still have no evidence that they were sexually intimate&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Harding, Neil, ''Lenin's Political Thought'' (1986), p. 250.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1914, when the [[First World War]] (1914–18) began, most of the mass Social Democratic parties of Europe supported their homelands' war effort. At first, Lenin disbelieved such political fickleness, especially that the Germans had voted for war credits; the Social Democrats' war-authorising votes broke Lenin's mainstream connection with the [[Second International (political)|Second International]] (1889–1916). He opposed the Great War, because the peasants and workers would be fighting the bourgeoisie's &quot;imperialist war&quot;—one that ought be transformed to an international civil war, between the classes. Lenin's view of the war can be summed up in a letter he wrote to the Romanian poet [[Valeriu Marcu]] in 1917: &quot;One slaveowner, Germany is fighting another slaveowner, England, for a fairer distribution of the slaves&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;test&quot;&gt;Seumas Milne. Learn the real lessons of a savage imperial bloodbath. Comment and Debate. Page 31. The Guardian newspaper. 17 October 2012. &lt;/ref&gt; At the beginning of the war, the Austrians briefly detained him in [[Poronin]], his town of residence; on 5 September 1914 Lenin moved to neutral [[Switzerland]], residing first at [[Bern]], then at [[Zürich]].&lt;ref&gt;Clar, Ronald W. ''Lenin: the Man Behind the Mask'' (1988) p. 154.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1915, in Switzerland, at the anti-war [[Zimmerwald Conference]], he led the [[Zimmerwald Left]] minority, who failed, against the majority [[pacifist]]s, to achieve the conference's adopting Lenin's proposition of transforming the imperialist war into a [[Class struggle|class war]]. In the next conference (24–30 April 1916), at [[Kienthal]], Lenin and the Zimmerwald Left presented a like resolution; but the conference concorded only a compromise manifesto.&lt;ref name=&quot;christopher_read_lenin&quot;/&gt;{{rp|pages=132–4}}

In the spring of 1916, in [[Zürich]], Lenin wrote ''[[Imperialism, the Highest Stage of Capitalism]]'' (1916). In this work Lenin synthesised previous works on the subject by [[Karl Kautsky]], [[John A. Hobson]] ([[Imperialism (Hobson)|''Imperialism: A Study'']], 1902), and [[Rudolf Hilferding]] (''Das Finanzkapital'', 1910), and applied them to the new circumstances of the [[First World War]] (1914–18) fought between the German and the British empires—which exemplified the imperial capitalist competition, which was the thesis of his book. This thesis posited that the merging of [[banking|banks]] and industrial [[cartel]]s gave rise to [[Finance Capital|finance capital]]—the basis of imperialism, the zenith of capitalism. To wit, in pursuing greater profits than the home market can offer, business exports capital, which, in turn, leads to the division of the world, among international, monopolist firms, and to European states colonising large parts of the world, in support of their businesses. [[Imperialism]], thus, is an advanced stage of capitalism based upon the establishment of [[monopoly|monopolies]], and upon the exportation of capital (rather than goods), managed with a [[global financial system]], of which [[colonialism]] is one feature.&lt;ref name=&quot;christopher_read_lenin&quot;/&gt;{{rp|pages=116–26}}&lt;ref&gt;Paul Bowles (2007) ''Capitalism''. Pearson: Harlow: 93&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lenin, V. I., ''Imperialism, the Highest Stage of Capitalism'' (2000) New Delhi: LeftWord Books p. 34&lt;/ref&gt;

In accordance with this thesis, Lenin believed that Russia was being used as a tool of French and British capitalist imperialism in World War I and that its participation in the conflict was at the behest of those interests.&lt;ref name=&quot;christopher_read_lenin&quot;/&gt;{{rp|page=144}}

[[File:Lenin 05d.jpg|upright|left|thumb|''Vilén'', Lenin bewigged and clean shaven, [[Finland]], 11 August 1917]]

==The February Revolution==
{{Main|February Revolution}}
[[File:Locomotive 293.jpg|thumb|upright|The locomotive that brought Lenin to Petrograd in April 1917]]
In February 1917 popular demonstrations in Russia provoked by the hardship of war forced Tsar [[Nicholas II of Russia|Nicholas II]] to abdicate. The monarchy was replaced by an uneasy political relationship between, on the one hand, a [[Russian Provisional Government|Provisional Government]] of parliamentary figures and, on the other, an array of &quot;[[Soviet (council)|Soviets]]&quot; (most prominently the [[Petrograd Soviet]]): revolutionary councils directly elected by workers, soldiers and peasants. Lenin was still in exile in Zurich.

Lenin was preparing to go to the [[Altstadt (Zurich)|Altstadt]] library after lunch on 15 March when a fellow exile, the Pole [[:de:Mieczysław Broński|Mieczyslav Bronski]], burst in to exclaim: &quot;Haven't you heard the news? There's a revolution in Russia!&quot; The next day Lenin wrote to [[Alexandra Kollontai]] in Stockholm, insisting on &quot;revolutionary propaganda, agitation and struggle with the aim of an ''international'' proletarian revolution and for the conquest of power by the Soviets of Workers' Deputies&quot;. The next day: &quot;Spread out! Rouse new sections! Awaken fresh initiative, form new organisations in every stratum and prove to them that peace can come only with the armed Soviet of Workers' Deputies in power.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Reminiscences of Lenin&quot;&gt;N. K. Krupskaya, ''[http://www.marxists.org/archive/krupskaya/works/rol/rol21.htm Reminiscences of Lenin]'' (1933), [http://www.marxists.org/archive/krupskaya/index.htm Krupskaya Internet Archive].&lt;/ref&gt;

Lenin was determined to return to Russia at once. But that was not an easy task in the middle of the First World War. Switzerland was surrounded by the warring countries of [[French Third Republic|France]], [[German Empire|Germany]], [[Austria-Hungary]] and [[Italian Campaign (World War I)|Italy]], and the seas were dominated by Russia's ally Britain. Lenin considered crossing Germany with a Swedish passport, but Krupskaya joked that he would give himself away by swearing at Mensheviks in Russian in his sleep.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reminiscences of Lenin&quot;/&gt;

Negotiations with the Provisional Government to obtain passage through Germany for the Russian exiles in return for German and Austro-Hungarian prisoners of war dragged on. Eventually, bypassing the Provisional Government, on 31 March the Swiss Communist [[Fritz Platten]] obtained permission from the German Foreign Minister through his ambassador in Switzerland, Baron Gisbert von Romberg, for Lenin and other Russian exiles to travel through Germany to Russia in a sealed one-carriage train. At Lenin's request the carriage would be protected from interference by a special grant of [[extraterritorial]] status.

On 9 April Lenin and Krupskaya met their fellow exiles in [[Bern]], a group eventually numbering thirty boarded a train which took them to Zurich. From there they travelled to the specially arranged train which was waiting at Gottmadingen, just short of the official German crossing station at Singen. Accompanied by two German Army officers, who sat at the rear of the single carriage behind a chalked line, the exiles travelled through Frankfurt and Berlin to Sassnitz (arriving 12 April), where a ferry took them to Trelleborg. Krupskaya noted how, looking out of the carriage window as they passed through wartime Germany, the exiles were &quot;struck by the total absence of grown-up men. Only women, teenagers and children could be seen at the wayside stations, on the fields, and in the streets of the towns.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Reminiscences of Lenin&quot;/&gt; Once in Sweden the group travelled by train to Stockholm and thence back to Russia.

Just before midnight on {{OldStyleDate|16 April|1917|3 April|1917}}, Lenin's train arrived at the [[Finlyandsky Rail Terminal|Finland Station]] in [[Petrograd]]. He was greeted, to the sound of the [[Marseillaise]], by a crowd of workers, sailors and soldiers bearing red flags: by now a ritual in revolutionary Russia for welcoming home political exiles.&lt;ref&gt;Orlando Figes, ''A People's Tragedy: The Russian Revolution 1891–1924'', London: Pimlico (1996), p. 384.&lt;/ref&gt; Lenin was formally welcomed by [[Nikolay Chkheidze|Chkheidze]], the Menshevik Chairman of the Petrograd Soviet. But Lenin pointedly turned to the crowd instead to address it on the international importance of the Russian Revolution:
&lt;blockquote&gt;The piratical imperialist war is the beginning of civil war throughout Europe ... The world-wide Socialist revolution has already dawned ... Germany is seething ... Any day now the whole of European capitalism may crash ... Sailors, comrades, we have to fight for a socialist revolution, to fight until the proletariat wins full victory! Long live the worldwide socialist revolution!&lt;ref&gt;Ronald W. Clark, ''Lenin: The Man Behind the Mask'', London: Faber and Faber (1989), pp. 210–1.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==The April Theses==
{{Main|April Theses}}
{{Marxism–Leninism sidebar}}
On the train from Switzerland, Lenin had composed his famous ''[[Lenin's April Theses|April Theses]]'': his programme for the Bolshevik Party. In the Theses, Lenin argued that the Bolsheviks should not rest content, like almost all other Russian socialists, with the &quot;bourgeois&quot; February Revolution. Instead the Bolsheviks should press ahead to a socialist revolution of the workers and poorest peasants:

{{bquote|2) The specific feature of the present situation in Russia is that the country is ''passing'' from the first stage of the revolution—which, owing to the insufficient class-consciousness and organisation of the proletariat, placed power in the hands of the bourgeoisie—to its ''second stage'', which must place power in the hands of the proletariat and the poorest sections of the peasants.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lenin Internet Archive&quot;/&gt;}}

Lenin argued that this socialist revolution would be achieved by the Soviets taking power from the parliamentary Provisional Government: &quot;No support for the Provisional Government ... Not a parliamentary republic – to return to a parliamentary republic from the Soviets of Workers' Deputies would be a retrograde step – but a republic of Soviets of Workers', Agricultural Labourers' and Peasants' Deputies throughout the country, from top to bottom.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lenin Internet Archive&quot;&gt;Vladimir Ilyich Lenin, ''[http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1917/apr/04.htm The Tasks of the Proletariat in the Present Revolution (a.k.a. The April Theses)]'' (1917), [http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/index.htm Lenin Internet Archive].&lt;/ref&gt;

To achieve this, Lenin argued, the Bolsheviks' immediate task was to campaign diligently among the Russian people to persuade them of the need for Soviet power:

{{bquote|4) Recognition of the fact that in most of the Soviets of Workers' Deputies our Party is in a minority, so far a small minority, ... and that therefore our task is, as long as ''this'' government yields to the influence of the bourgeoisie, to present a patient, systematic, and persistent explanation of the errors of their tactics, an ''explanation'' especially adapted to the practical needs of the masses.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lenin Internet Archive&quot;/&gt;}}

The April Theses were more radical than virtually anything Lenin's fellow revolutionaries had heard. Previous Bolshevik policy had been like that of the Mensheviks in this respect: that Russia was ready only for bourgeois, not socialist, revolution. [[Joseph Stalin]] and [[Lev Kamenev]], who had returned from exile in Siberia in mid-March and taken control of the Bolshevik newspaper ''[[Pravda]]'', had been campaigning for support for the Provisional Government. When Lenin presented his Theses to a joint [[Russian Social Democratic Labour Party]] (RSDLP) meeting, he was booed by the Mensheviks. Boris Bogdanov called them &quot;the ravings of a madman&quot;. Of the Bolsheviks, only [[Kollontai]] at first supported the Theses.&lt;ref&gt;Orlando Figes, ''A People's Tragedy: The Russian Revolution 1891–1924'', London: Pimlico (1996), p. 388.&lt;/ref&gt;

Lenin arrived at the revolutionary April Theses thanks to his work in exile on the [[Imperialism, the Highest Stage of Capitalism|theory of imperialism]]. Through his study of worldwide politics and economics, Lenin came to view Russian politics in international perspective. In the conditions of the First World War, Lenin believed that, although Russian capitalism was underdeveloped, a socialist revolution in Russia could spark revolution in the more advanced nations of Europe, which could then help Russia achieve economic and social development. [[A. J. P. Taylor]] argued: &quot;Lenin made his revolution for the sake of Europe, not for the sake of Russia, and he expected Russia's preliminary revolution to be eclipsed when the international revolution took place. Lenin did not invent the iron curtain. On the contrary it was invented against him by the anti-revolutionary Powers of Europe. Then it was called the ''[[cordon sanitaire]].''&quot;&lt;ref&gt;A. J. P. Taylor, 'Introduction', in John Reed, ''Ten Days That Shook the World'', London: Penguin (1977), xviii.&lt;/ref&gt;

In this way, Lenin moved away from the previous Bolshevik policy of pursuing only bourgeois revolution in Russia, and towards the position of his fellow Russian revolutionary [[Leon Trotsky]] and his theory of [[permanent revolution]], which may have influenced Lenin at this time.&lt;ref&gt;Orlando Figes, ''A People's Tragedy: The Russian Revolution 1891–1924'', London: Pimlico (1996), p. 387 n.&lt;/ref&gt;

Controversial as it was in April 1917, the programme of the April Theses made the Bolshevik party a political refuge for Russians disillusioned with the Provisional Government and the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;christopher_read_lenin&quot;/&gt;{{rp|pages=157–60}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Read |first=Christopher |year=1996 |title=From Czar to Soviets: The Russian People and Their Revolution, 1917–21 |publisher=Oxford University Press |pages=151–153 |isbn=0-19-521241-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==The October Revolution==
{{Main|October Revolution}}
[[File:Brodskiy's Lenin.jpg|thumb|Painting of Lenin in front of the [[Smolny Institute]] by [[Isaak Brodsky]]]]

In Petrograd dissatisfaction with the regime culminated in the spontaneous [[July Days]] riots, by industrial workers and soldiers.&lt;ref name=&quot;christopher_read_lenin&quot;/&gt;{{rp|page=158–61}} After being suppressed, these riots were blamed by the government on Lenin and the Bolsheviks.&lt;ref name=&quot;christopher_read_lenin&quot;/&gt;{{rp|pages=160–1}} [[Aleksandr Kerensky]], [[Grigory Aleksinsky]], and other opponents, also accused the Bolsheviks, especially Lenin—of being Imperial German ''[[agent provocateur|agents provocateurs]]''; on 17 July, [[Leon Trotsky]] defended them:&lt;ref&gt;{{ru icon}} [http://www.hrono.ru/biograf/alexinski.html Biography of Grigory Aleksinsky, XPOHOC, www.hrono.ru]&lt;/ref&gt;

{{bquote|An intolerable atmosphere has been created, in which you, as well as we, are choking. They are throwing dirty accusations at Lenin and Zinoviev. Lenin has fought thirty years for the revolution. I have fought [for] twenty years against the oppression of the people. And we cannot but cherish a hatred for German militarism . . . I have been sentenced by a German court to eight months' imprisonment for my struggle against German militarism. This everybody knows. Let nobody in this hall say that we are hirelings of Germany.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Trotsky |first=Leon |title=The Month of The Great Slander |work=The History of the Russian Revolution; Volume 2,Chapter 27 |url=http://www.marxists.org/archive/trotsky/works/1930-hrr/ch27.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In the event, the Provisional Government arrested the Bolsheviks and outlawed their Party, prompting Lenin to go into hiding and flee to Finland. In exile again, reflecting on the July Days and its aftermath, Lenin determined that, to prevent the triumph of counter-revolutionary forces, the Provisional Government must be overthrown by an armed uprising.&lt;ref name=&quot;christopher_read_lenin&quot;/&gt;{{rp|pages=162–3}} Meanwhile, he published ''[[State and Revolution]]'' (1917) proposing government by the [[soviet (council)|soviets]] (worker-, soldier- and peasant-elected councils) rather than by a parliamentary body.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Lenin |first=Vladimir |title=The State and Revolution |year=1917 |url=http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1917/staterev/index.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In late August 1917, while Lenin was in hiding in Finland, the Commander-in-Chief of the Russian Army [[Lavr Kornilov|General Lavr Kornilov]] sent troops from the front to Petrograd in what appeared to be a [[Kornilov Affair|military coup attempt]] against the Provisional Government. Kerensky panicked and turned to the Petrograd Soviet for help, allowing the revolutionaries to organise workers as [[Red Guards (Russia)|Red Guards]] to defend Petrograd. The coup petered out before it reached Petrograd thanks to the industrial action of the Petrograd workers and the soldiers' increasing unwillingness to obey their officers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sheila Fitzpatrick 2008 p. 60&quot;&gt;Sheila Fitzpatrick, ''The Russian Revolution'', Oxford: Oxford University Press (2008), p. 60.&lt;/ref&gt;

However, faith in the Provisional Government had been severely shaken. Lenin's slogan since the [[April Theses]]&amp;nbsp;– &quot;All power to the soviets!&quot;&amp;nbsp;– became more plausible the more the Provisional Government was discredited in public eyes. The Bolsheviks won a majority in the Petrograd Soviet on 31 August and in the Moscow Soviet on 5 September.&lt;ref&gt;Sheila Fitzpatrick, ''The Russian Revolution'', Oxford: Oxford University Press (2008), pp. 60–1.&lt;/ref&gt;

In October Lenin returned from Finland. From the [[Smolny Institute]] for girls, Lenin directed the Provisional Government's [[deposition (politics)|deposition]] (6–8 November 1917), and the storming (7–8 November) of the [[Winter Palace]] to realise the Kerensky [[capitulation (surrender)|capitulation]] that established Bolshevik government in Russia.

==Forming a government==
[[File:Lenin-office-1918.jpg|right|thumb|Lenin working in the Kremlin, 1918]]

Lenin had argued in a newspaper article in September 1917:&lt;blockquote&gt;The peaceful development of any revolution is, generally speaking, extremely rare and difficult ... but ... a peaceful development of the revolution is possible and probable if all power is transferred to the Soviets. The struggle of parties for power within the Soviets may proceed peacefully, if the Soviets are made fully democratic&lt;ref&gt;V. I. Lenin, [http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1917/sep/29.htm 'The Russian Revolution And Civil War: They Are Trying To Frighten Us With Civil War'], ''Rabochy Put'' ('The Workers' Path') No. 12 (29 September 1917), [http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/ Lenin Internet Archive].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;The October Revolution had been relatively peaceful. The revolutionary forces already had ''de facto'' control of the capital thanks to the defection of the city garrison. Few troops had stayed to defend the Provisional Government in the [[Winter Palace]].&lt;ref&gt;Orlando Figes, ''A People's Tragedy: The Russian Revolution 1891–1924'', London: Pimlico (1996), pp. 481, 491.&lt;/ref&gt; Most citizens had simply continued about their daily business while the Provisional Government was actually overthrown.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sheila Fitzpatrick 2008 p. 60&quot;/&gt;
It thus appeared that all power had been transferred to the Soviets relatively peacefully. On the evening of the October Revolution, the [[All-Russian Congress of Soviets|Second All-Russian Congress of Soviets]] met, with a Bolshevik-[[Left SR]] majority, in the [[Smolny Institute]] in Petrograd. When the left-wing Menshevik [[Julius Martov|Martov]] proposed an all-party Soviet government, the Bolshevik [[Anatoly Lunacharsky|Lunacharsky]] stated that his party did not oppose the idea. The Bolshevik delegates voted unanimously in favour of the proposal.&lt;ref&gt;Orlando Figes, ''A People's Tragedy: The Russian Revolution 1891–1924'', London: Pimlico (1996), pp. 489–90.&lt;/ref&gt;

However, not all Russian socialists supported transferring all power to the Soviets. The [[Socialist–Revolutionary Party|Right SRs]] and [[Mensheviks]] walked out of this very first session of the Congress of Soviets in protest at the overthrow of the Provisional Government, of which their parties had been members.&lt;ref&gt;Orlando Figes, ''A People's Tragedy: The Russian Revolution 1891–1924'', London: Pimlico (1996), p. 490.&lt;/ref&gt;

The next day, on the evening of 26 October [[Old Style|O.S.]], Lenin attended the Congress of Soviets: undisguised in public for the first time since the July Days, although not yet having regrown his trademark beard. The American journalist [[John Reed (journalist)|John Reed]] described the man who appeared at about 8:40&amp;nbsp;pm to &quot;a thundering wave of cheers&quot;:
&lt;blockquote&gt;A short, stocky figure, with a big head set down in his shoulders, bald and bulging. Little eyes, a snubbish nose, wide, generous mouth, and heavy chin; clean-shaven now, but already beginning to bristle with the well-known beard of his past and future. Dressed in shabby clothes, his trousers much too long for him. Unimpressive, to be the idol of a mob, loved and revered as perhaps few leaders in history have been. A strange popular leader—a leader purely by virtue of intellect; colourless, humourless, uncompromising and detached, without picturesque idiosyncrasies—but with the power of explaining profound ideas in simple terms, of analysing a concrete situation. And combined with shrewdness, the greatest intellectual audacity.&lt;ref&gt;John Reed, ''Ten Days That Shook the World'', London: Penguin (1977), p. 128. (Available [http://www.marxists.org/archive/reed/1919/10days/10days/ch5.htm online], courtesy of the [http://www.marxists.org Marxists Internet Archive].)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
According to Reed, Lenin waited for the applause to subside before declaring simply: &quot;We shall now proceed to construct the Socialist order!&quot; Lenin proceeded to propose to the Congress a [[Decree on Peace]], calling on &quot;all the belligerent peoples and to their Governments to begin immediately negotiations for a just and democratic peace&quot;, and a [[Decree on Land]], transferring ownership of all &quot;land-owners' estates, and all lands belonging to the Crown, [and] to monasteries&quot; to the Peasants' Soviets. The Congress passed the Decree on Peace unanimously, and the Decree on Land faced only one vote in opposition.&lt;ref&gt;John Reed, ''Ten Days That Shook the World'', London: Penguin (1977), pp. 129–137. (Available [http://www.marxists.org/archive/reed/1919/10days/10days/ch5.htm online], courtesy of the [http://www.marxists.org Marxists Internet Archive].)&lt;/ref&gt;

Having approved these key Bolshevik policies, the Congress of Soviets proceeded to elect the Bolsheviks into power as the [[Council of People's Commissars (Russia)|Council of People's Commissars]] by &quot;an enormous majority&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;online&quot;&gt;John Reed, ''Ten Days That Shook the World'', London: Penguin (1977), p. 143. (Available [http://www.marxists.org/archive/reed/1919/10days/10days/ch5.htm online], courtesy of the [http://www.marxists.org Marxists Internet Archive].)&lt;/ref&gt; The Bolsheviks offered posts in the Council to the [[Left SRs]]: an offer which the Left SRs at first refused,&lt;ref name=&quot;Ronald W. Clark 1988 p. 279&quot;&gt;Ronald W. Clark, ''Lenin: The Man Behind the Mask'', London: Faber and Faber (1988), p. 279.&lt;/ref&gt; but later accepted, joining the Bolsheviks in coalition on 12 December [[Old Style|O.S]].&lt;ref&gt;Orlando Figes, ''A People's Tragedy: The Russian Revolution 1891–1924'', London: Pimlico (1996), p. 512.&lt;/ref&gt; Lenin had suggested that Trotsky take the position of Chairman of the Council—the head of the Soviet government—but Trotsky refused on the grounds that his Jewishness would be controversial, and he took the post of Commissar for Foreign Affairs instead.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ronald W. Clark 1988 p. 279&quot;/&gt; Thus Lenin became the head of government in Russia.

Trotsky announced the composition of the new Soviet Central Executive Committee: with a Bolshevik majority, but with places reserved for the representatives of the other parties, including the seceded Right SRs and Mensheviks. Trotsky concluded the Congress: &quot;We welcome into the Government all parties and groups which will adopt our programme.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;online&quot;/&gt;

Lenin declared in 1920 that &quot;Communism is Soviet power plus the electrification of the entire country&quot; in modernising Russia into a 20th-century country:&lt;ref&gt;Lenin &quot;Collected Works&quot;, vol. 31, p. 516.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Lenin buhar.jpg|thumb|''Vladimir Ulyanov (Lenin)'', drawing by [[Nikolai Bukharin]], 31 March 1927]]
{{bquote|We must show the peasants that the organisation of industry on the basis of modern, advanced technology, on electrification, which will provide a link between town and country, will put an end to the division between town and country, will make it possible to raise the level of culture in the countryside and to overcome, even in the most remote corners of land, backwardness, ignorance, poverty, disease, and barbarism.&lt;ref&gt;Lenin &quot;Collected Works&quot;, vol. 30, p. 335.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Yet the Bolshevik Government had to first withdraw Russia from the [[First World War]] (1914–18). Facing continuing [[German Army (German Empire)|Imperial German]] eastward advance, Lenin proposed immediate Russian withdrawal from the West European war; yet, other, doctrinaire{{Clarify|date=June 2011}} [[Bolshevik]] leaders (e.g. [[Nikolai Bukharin]]) advocated continuing in the war to foment revolution in Germany. Lead peace treaty negotiator Leon Trotsky proposed ''No War, No Peace'', an intermediate-stance Russo–German treaty conditional upon neither belligerent annexing conquered lands; the negotiations collapsed, and the Germans renewed their attack, conquering much of the (agricultural) territory of west Russia. Resultantly, Lenin's withdrawal proposal then gained majority support, and, on 3 March 1918, Russia withdrew from the First World War via the [[Treaty of Brest-Litovsk]], losing much of its European territory. Because of the German threat Lenin moved the Soviet Government from Petrograd to Moscow on 10–11 March 1918.&lt;ref name=&quot;christopher_read_lenin&quot;/&gt;{{rp|page=212}}
&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/mem/archive-free/pdf?_r=1&amp;res=9A02E0DF103BEE3ABC4E52DFB5668383609EDE LENINE'S MIGRATION A QUEER SCENE], ''[[The New York Times]]'', 16 March 1918&lt;/ref&gt;

On 19 January 1918, relying upon the [[Soviet (council)|soviets]], the Bolsheviks, allied with anarchists and the [[Socialist Revolutionary Party|Socialist Revolutionaries]], dissolved the [[Russian Constituent Assembly]] thereby consolidating the Bolshevik Government's political power. Yet, that [[Left wing politics|left-wing]] coalition collapsed consequent to the Social Revolutionaries opposing the territorially expensive [[Brest-Litovsk treaty]] the Bolsheviks had concorded with [[German Empire|Imperial Germany]]. The anarchists and the Socialist Revolutionaries then joined other political parties in attempting to depose the Bolshevik Government, who defended themselves with persecution and jail for the anti-Bolsheviks.

To initiate the Russian economic recovery, on 21 February 1920, he launched the [[GOELRO plan]], the ''State Commission for Electrification of Russia'' (Государственная комиссия по электрификации России), and also established free [[universal health care]] and [[free education]] systems, and promulgated the politico-civil [[feminism|rights of women]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/subject/women/index.htm |title=Women and Marxism – Lenin |publisher=Marxists.org |date=14 November 2003 |accessdate=2012-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, since 1918, in re-establishing the economy, for the productive [[business administration]] of each industrial enterprise in Russia, Lenin proposed a government-accountable leader for each enterprise. Workers could request measures resolving problems, but had to abide the leader's ultimate decision. Although contrary to [[workers' self-management]], such pragmatic industrial administration was essential for efficient production and employment of worker expertise. Yet Lenin's doctrinaire{{Clarify|date=June 2011}} Bolshevik opponents argued that such industrial business management was meant to strengthen State control of labour, and that worker self-management failures were owed to lack of resources, not incompetence. Lenin resolved that problem by licencing (for a month) all workers of most factories; thus historian S. A. Smith's observation: &quot;By the end of the [[Russian Civil War|civil war]], not much was left of the democratic forms of industrial administration promoted by the [[factory committees]] in 1917, but the government argued that this did not matter since industry had passed into the ownership of a workers' state.&quot;
[[File:У здания Харьковской ЧК.jpg|thumb|Excavation of [[Red Terror]] victims outside the headquarters of the Kharkov Cheka, Summer 1919.]]
Internationally, Lenin's admiration of the Irish socialist revolutionary [[James Connolly]], led to the USSR's being the first country to grant [[diplomacy|diplomatic recognition]] to the [[Irish Republic]] that fought the [[Irish War of Independence]] from Britain. In the event, Lenin developed a friendship with Connolly's revolutionary son, [[Roddy Connolly]].

===Establishing the Cheka===
{{Main|Cheka}}
On 20 December 1917, &quot;The Whole-Russian Extraordinary Commission for Combating Counter-Revolution and Sabotage&quot;, the [[Cheka]] (''Chrezvychaynaya Komissiya''&amp;nbsp;– Extraordinary Commission) was created by a decree issued by Lenin to defend the [[Russian Revolution (1917)|Russian Revolution]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Impact of Stalin's Leadership in the USSR, 1924–1941 |authorlink=John Laver |year=2008 |publisher=Nelson Thornes |isbn=978-0-7487-8267-3 |page=3}}&lt;/ref&gt; The establishment of the Cheka, [[secret police|secret service]], headed by [[Felix Dzerzhinsky]], formally consolidated the censorship established earlier, when on &quot;17 November, the Central Executive Committee passed a decree giving the Bolsheviks control over all newsprint and wide powers of closing down newspapers critical of the régime. . . .&quot;;&lt;ref&gt;Leonard Shapiro, ''The Communist Party of the Soviet Union''&lt;/ref&gt; non-Bolshevik soviets were disbanded; anti-soviet newspapers were closed until ''[[Pravda]]'' (''Truth'') and ''[[Izvestia]]'' (''The News'') established their communications monopoly. According to [[Leonard Schapiro]] the Bolshevik &quot;refusal to come to terms with the [Revolutionary] socialists, and the dispersal of the [[Russian Constituent Assembly|Constituent]] assembly, led to the logical result that [[revolutionary terror]] would now be directed, not only against traditional enemies, such as the [[bourgeoisie]] or [[Right-wing politics|right-wing]] opponents, but against anyone, be he socialist, worker, or peasant, who opposed Bolshevik rule&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Leonard Bertram Schapiro. ''The Communist Party of the Soviet Union''. Eyre &amp; Spottiswoode, 1970. ISBN 0-413-27900-6 p. 183. See also: [http://econfaculty.gmu.edu/bcaplan/museum/his1e.htm Lenin and the First Communist Revolutions, V]&lt;/ref&gt; On 19 December 1918, a year after its creation, a resolution was adopted at Lenin's behest that forbade the Bolshevik's own press from publishing &quot;defamatory articles&quot; about the Cheka.&lt;ref name=&quot;Black Book 79&quot;&gt;[[Black Book of Communism]], p. 79&lt;/ref&gt; As Lenin put it: &quot;A Good Communist is also a good [[Chekism|Chekist]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Black Book 79&quot;/&gt;

===Lenin on anti-Semitism===
[[File:Ekaterinoslav1905.jpg|thumb|right|Jewish children killed in [[Anti-Jewish pogroms in the Russian Empire#1903-1906|1905 pogroms of the Russian Empire]] in Yekaterinoslav (now [[Dnipropetrovsk]]); institutionalized persecution of Jews convinced Lenin that they were victims of tsarist oppression.]]

Lenin was enthusiastic about new mass communication technology like the radio and the [[phonograph|gramophone]] and its capacity for educating Russia's mostly illiterate peasant population. In 1919 Lenin recorded eight speeches on to [[gramophone records]]. During the [[Nikita Khrushchev]] era (1953–64), seven were published. The eighth speech, which was not published, outlined Lenin's thoughts on [[anti-Semitism]]:&lt;ref&gt;Ronald W. Clark, ''Lenin: The Man Behind the Mask'', London: Faber and Faber (1988), ISBN 978-0-06-015802-6, p. 456.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;The tsarist police, in alliance with the landowners and the capitalists, organised [[pogroms]] against the Jews. The landowners and capitalists tried to divert the hatred of the workers and peasants who were tortured by want against the Jews. ... It is not the Jews who are the enemies of the working people. The enemies of the workers are the capitalists of all countries. Among the Jews there are working people, and they form the majority. They are our brothers, who, like us, are oppressed by capital; they are our comrades in the struggle for socialism. ... The capitalists strive to sow and foment hatred between workers of different faiths, different nations and different races. ... Rich Jews, like rich Russians, and the rich in all countries, are in alliance to oppress, crush, rob, and disunite the workers. ... Shame on those who foment hatred towards the Jews, who foment hatred towards other nations.&lt;ref&gt;V. I. Lenin, [http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1919/mar/x10.htm 'Anti-Jewish Pogroms'] (1919), [http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/ Lenin Internet Archive].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Failed assassinations===
[[File:Lenin.platten (2).jpg|thumb|right|Comrades under fire—Lenin and [[Fritz Platten]], 1919]]

Lenin survived two serious assassination attempts.  The first occasion was on 14 January 1918 in [[Petrograd]], when  assassins ambushed Lenin in his automobile after a speech. He and [[Fritz Platten]] were in the back seat when assassins began shooting, and &quot;Platten grabbed Lenin by the head and pushed him down... Platten's hand was covered in blood, having been grazed by a bullet as he was shielding Lenin&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Volkogonov |first=Dimitri |title=Lenin{{spaced ndash}}A New Biography |publisher= Free Press|page=229 |isbn=0-02-933435-7 |location=New York}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The second event was on 30 August 1918, when the [[Socialist Revolutionary Party|Socialist Revolutionary]] [[Fanya Kaplan]] approached Lenin at his automobile after a speech; he was resting a foot on the running board as he spoke with a woman. Kaplan called to Lenin, and when he turned to face her she shot at him three times. The first bullet struck his arm, the second bullet his jaw and neck, and the third missed him, wounding the woman with whom he was speaking; the wounds felled him and he became unconscious.&lt;ref&gt;Pipes, Richard, ''The Russian Revolution'' (Vintage Books, 1990) p. 807&lt;/ref&gt; Fearing in-hospital assassins, Lenin was brought to his [[Kremlin]] apartment; physicians decided against removing the bullets lest the surgery endanger his recovery, which proved to be slow.

''[[Pravda]]'' publicly ridiculed Fanya Kaplan as a failed assassin, a latter-day [[Charlotte Corday]] (the murderess of [[Jean-Paul Marat]]) who could not derail the Russian Revolution, reassuring readers that, immediately after surviving the assassination: &quot;Lenin, shot through twice, with pierced lungs spilling blood, refuses help and goes on his own. The next morning, still threatened with death, he reads papers, listens, learns, and observes to see that the engine of the locomotive that carries us towards global revolution has not stopped working...&quot;; despite unharmed lungs, the neck wound did spill blood into a lung.&lt;ref&gt;Dr. V.&amp;nbsp;Bonch-Bruevich, Lenin's attending physician, ''Tri Pokusheniia na V. Lenina'', 1924.&lt;/ref&gt;

Historian [[Richard Pipes]] reports that &quot;the impression one gains ... is that the Bolsheviks deliberately underplayed the event to convince the public that, whatever happened to Lenin, they were firmly in control&quot;. Moreover, in a letter to his wife (7 September 1918), [[Leonid Krasin|Leonid Borisovich Krasin]], a Tsarist and Soviet régime diplomat, describes the public atmosphere and social response to the failed assassination attempt on 30 August and to Lenin's survival:

{{bquote|As it happens, the attempt to kill Lenin has made him much more popular than he was. One hears a great many people, who are far from having any sympathy with the Bolsheviks, saying that it would be an absolute disaster if Lenin had succumbed to his wounds, as it was first thought he would. And they are quite right, for, in the midst of all this chaos and confusion, he is the backbone of the new body politic, the main support on which everything rests.&lt;ref&gt;Krassin, Lubov, ''Leonid Krassin: His Life and Work, by his wife'' (1929) Skeffington: London&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Red Terror===
 {{Main|Red Terror}}

[[File:Tov lenin ochishchaet.jpg|thumb|upright|A picture saying, &quot;Comrade Lenin Cleanses the Earth of Filth&quot;]]

In response to Fanya Kaplan's failed assassination of Lenin on 30 August 1918, and the successful assassination of the Petrograd [[Cheka]] chief [[Moisei Uritsky]], Stalin proposed to Lenin &quot;open and systematic mass terror . . . [against] . . . those responsible&quot;; the Bolsheviks instructed [[Felix Dzerzhinsky]] to commence a [[Red Terror]], announced in the 1 September 1918 issue of the ''Krasnaya Gazeta'' (''Red Gazette'').&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.spartacus.schoolnet.co.uk/RUSterror.htm |title=Red Terror |publisher=Spartacus.schoolnet.co.uk |accessdate=2012-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; To that effect, among other acts, at Moscow, [[execution warrant|execution lists]] signed by Lenin authorised the shooting of 25 Tsarist ministers, civil servants, and 765 [[White Movement|White Guards]] in September 1918.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
 |last = Gellately
 |first = Robert
 |title = Lenin, Stalin, and Hitler: The Age of Social Catastrophe
 |publisher = [[Knopf]]
 |year = 2007
 |page = 57
 |isbn = 1-4000-4005-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; In his ''Diaries in Exile, 1935'', [[Leon Trotsky]] recollected that Lenin authorised the [[Shooting of the Romanov family|execution of the Russian Royal Family]].&lt;ref&gt;Trotskii, ''Dnevniki i pis'ma'', 100-1, cited in {{cite book |last=Figes |first=Orlando |title=A People's Tragedy: The Russian Revolution 1891–1924 |publisher=[[Penguin Books]] |year=1997 |page=638 |isbn=0-19-822862-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, according to [[Greg King (author)|Greg King]] and Penny Wilson's investigation into the fate of the Romanovs, Trotsky's recollections on this matter, seventeen years after the events described, are unsubstantiated, inaccurate, and contradicted by what Trotsky himself said on other occasions.&lt;ref&gt;Greg King and Penny Wilson (2003) ''The Fate of the Romanovs''. Hoboken, Wiley: 294&lt;/ref&gt; Most historians say there is enough evidence to prove Lenin ordered the killings.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blomfield&quot;&gt;Adrian Blomfield. [http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/russia/3115053/Russia-exonerates-Tsar-Nicholas-II.html Russia exonerates Tsar Nicholas II] [[The Daily Telegraph|The Telegraph]], 1 October 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; According to the late Soviet historian [[Dmitri Volkogonov]]:&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Volkogonov|first=Dmitri|authorlink=Dmitri Volkogonov|title=Lenin: A New Biography|publisher=[[Free Press (publisher)|Free Press]]|year=2006|isbn=0-02-933435-7|page=212}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Indirect evidence shows that the order to execute the royal family was given verbally by Lenin and [[Yakov Sverdlov|Sverdlov]]. The object of 'exterminating the entire Romanov kin' is confirmed by the almost simultaneous murders of Grand Duchess [[Princess Elisabeth of Hesse and by Rhine (1864–1918)|Yelizaveta Feodorovna]], Grand Duke [[Grand Duke Sergei Mikhailovich of Russia|Sergei Mikhailovich]], Prince [[Prince John Constantinovich of Russia|Ivan Konstantinovich]], Prince [[Prince Constantine Constantinovich of Russia|Konstantin Konstantinovich]], Prince [[Prince Igor Constantinovich of Russia|Igor Konstantinovich]] and Count [[Vladimir Pavlovich Paley|Vladimir Paley]] (son of Grand Duke [[Grand Duke Paul Alexandrovich of Russia|Paul Alexandrovich]]), all of them in [[Alapaevsk]], a hundred miles from [[Yekaterinburg]].&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Earlier, in October, [[Lev Kamenev]] and cohort, had warned the Party that terrorist rule was inevitable, given Lenin's assumption of sole command.&lt;ref&gt;[[Orlando Figes]]. ''A People's Tragedy: The Russian Revolution 1891–1924.'' [[Penguin Books]], 1997 ISBN 0-19-822862-7 p. 630&lt;/ref&gt; In late 1918, when he and [[Nikolai Bukharin]] tried curbing Chekist excesses, Lenin overruled them; in 1921, via the [[Politburo]], he expanded the Cheka's discretionary death-penalty powers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 |last = Figes
 |first = Orlando
 |title = [[A People's Tragedy]]: The Russian Revolution: 1891–1924
 |publisher = Penguin
 |year = 1998
 |page = 649
 |isbn = 0-14-024364-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Volkogonov |first=Dimitri |title=Lenin{{spaced ndash}}A New Biography |publisher= Free Press|page=238 |isbn=0-02-933435-7 |location=New York}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The foreign-aided [[White Movement|White Russian]] counter-revolution failed for want of popular Russian support, because the Bolshevik [[Proletariat|proletarian state]], protected with &quot;mass terror against enemies of the revolution&quot;, was socially organised against the previous capitalist establishment, thus [[Class conflict|class warfare]] terrorism in post–Tsarist Russia originated in working class (peasant and worker) anger against the privileged [[Aristocracy|aristocrat]] classes of the [[deposition (politics)|deposed]] [[absolute monarchy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Figes |first=Orlando |title=A People's Tragedy: The Russian Revolution: 1891–1924 |publisher=Penguin |year=1998 |pages=524–25 |isbn=0-14-024364-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the Russian Civil War, anti-Bolsheviks faced [[torture]] and [[summary execution]], and by May 1919, there were some 16,000 [[enemy of the people|enemies of the people]] imprisoned in the Tsarist [[katorga]] [[labor camp|labour camps]]; by September 1921 the prisoner populace exceeded 70,000.&lt;ref&gt;[[Robert Gellately]]. ''Lenin, Stalin, and Hitler: The Age of Social Catastrophe.'' [[Knopf]], 2007 ISBN 1-4000-4005-1 [http://books.google.com/books?id=Q8bTWCJMqAQC&amp;pg=PT81 p. 65]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Sergei Melgunov|Melgunov, Sergei]], ''Red Terror in Russia'' (1975) Hyperion Pr, ISBN 0-88355-187-X. See: [http://www.paulbogdanor.com/left/soviet/redterror.pdf The Record of the Red Terror]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[W. Bruce Lincoln|Lincoln, W. Bruce]], ''Red Victory: A History of the Russian Civil War'' (1999) [[Da Capo Press]].[http://books.google.com/books?id=R6HAJIJhNp4C&amp;pg=PA383 pp. 383–385] ISBN 0-306-80909-5&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Leggett |first=George |title=The Cheka: Lenin's Political Police |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |year=1987 |pages=197–198 |isbn=0-19-822862-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Orlando Figes]]. ''A People's Tragedy: The Russian Revolution 1891–1924.'' [[Penguin Books]], 1997 ISBN 0-19-822862-7 p. 647&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Black Book of Communism]], p. 80&lt;/ref&gt;

In pursuing their revolution and [[counter-revolution]] the White and the Red Russians committed atrocities, against each other and their supporting populaces, yet contemporary historians disagree about equating the terrorisms—because the [[Red Terror]] was Bolshevik Government policy (e.g. [[Decossackization]]) against given social classes, whilst the class-based [[White Terror]] was [[antisemitism|racial]] and political, against Jews, anti-monarchists, and Communists, (cf. [[White Movement]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;users.erols.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://users.erols.com/mwhite28/warstat1.htm#Russian |title=Twentieth Century Atlas{{spaced ndash}}Death Tolls}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Black Book of Communism'', p. 82&lt;/ref&gt; Such numbers are recorded in cities occupied by the Bolsheviks:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
In [[Kharkov]] there were between 2,000 and 3,000 executions in February–June 1919, and another 1,000–2,000 when the town was taken again in December of that year; in [[Rostov-on-Don]], approximately 1,000 in January 1920; in [[Odessa]], 2,200 in May–August 1919, then 1,500–3,000 between February 1920 and February 1921; in [[Kiev]], at least 3,000 in February–August 1919; in [[Ekaterinodar]], at least 3,000 between August 1920 and February 1921; In [[Armavir, Russia|Armavir]], a small town in [[Kuban]], between 2,000 and 3,000 in August–October 1920. The list could go on and on.&lt;ref&gt;Nicolas Werth, Karel Bartosek, Jean-Louis Panne, Jean-Louis Margolin, Andrzej Paczkowski, Stephane Courtois, ''Black Book of Communism: Crimes, Terror, Repression'', [[Harvard University Press]], 1999, hardcover, page 106, ISBN 0-674-07608-7. Chapter 4: ''The Red Terror'' ''Black Book''&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Professor Christopher Read states that though terror was employed at the height of the Civil War fighting, &quot;from 1920 onwards the resort to terror was much reduced and disappeared from Lenin's mainstream discourses and practices&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;christopher_read_lenin&quot;/&gt;{{rp|page=251}} However, after a [[clergy|clerical]] insurrection in the town of Shuia, in a 19 March 1922 letter to [[Vyacheslav Molotov]] and the [[Politburo]], Lenin delineated action against defiers of the decreed Bolshevik removal of Orthodox Church valuables: &quot;We must... put down all resistance with such brutality that they will not forget it for several decades... The greater the number of representatives of the [[reactionary]] clergy and reactionary [[bourgeoisie]] we succeed in executing... the better.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 |last = Pipes
 |first = Richard
 |title = The Unknown Lenin: From the Secret Archive
 |publisher = Yale University Press
 |year = 1996
 |pages = 152–154
 |isbn = 0-300-06919-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of this letter, historian [[Orlando Figes]] estimates that perhaps 8,000 priests and laymen were executed.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
 |last=Figes
 |first=Orlando
 |title=Censored by His Own Regime
 |journal=The New York Times
 |date=27 October 1996
 |url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E1DB1230F934A15753C1A960958260&amp;sec=&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=2}}&lt;/ref&gt; And the crushing of the revolts in [[Kronstadt rebellion|Kronstadt]] and [[Tambov Rebellion|Tambov]] in 1921 resulted in tens of thousands of executions.&lt;ref&gt;[[Donald Rayfield]]. ''[[Stalin and His Hangmen]]: The Tyrant and Those Who Killed for Him.'' [[Random House]], 2004. ISBN 0-375-50632-2 [http://books.google.com/books?id=Yi3ow3TU8-4C&amp;pg=RA2-PA1915 p. 85]&lt;/ref&gt; Estimates for the total number of people killed in the Red Terror ranger from 50,000&lt;ref&gt;Mastering Twentieth Century Russian History, Norman Lowe&lt;/ref&gt; to over a million&lt;ref&gt;Stewart-Smith,, D. G. THE DEFEAT OF COMMUNISM. London: Ludgate Press Limited, 1964.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Rummel&quot;&gt;Rummel, Rudolph, [http://www.hawaii.edu/powerkills/USSR.TAB2A.GIF Lethal Politics: Soviet Genocide and Mass Murder Since 1917] (1990).&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[File:1919-Trotsky Lenin Kamenev-Party-Congress.jpg|thumb|left|[[Leon Trotsky|Trotsky]], Lenin and [[Lev Kamenev|Kamenev]] at the II Party Congress in 1919]]

===Civil War===
{{Main|Russian Civil War}}

In 1917, as an [[imperialism|anti-imperialist]], Lenin said that oppressed peoples had the unconditional right to secede from the Russian Empire; however, at end of the Civil War, the USSR annexed [[Armenia]], Georgia, and [[Azerbaijan]], because the White Movement used them as attack bases.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Pipes, Richard |year=1994 |title=Russia Under the Bolshevik Regime |publisher=Vintage |isbn=0-679-76184-5 |pages=141–166}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lenin defended the annexations as [[Geopolitics|geopolitical]] protection against capitalist imperial depredations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Lenin |first=Vladimir |title=The Revolutionary Proletariat and the Right of Nations to Self-Determination |year=1915 |url=http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1915/oct/16.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

To maintain the war-isolated cities, keep the armies fed, and to avoid [[economic collapse]], the Bolshevik government established [[war communism]], via ''[[prodrazvyorstka]]'', food requisitioning from the peasantry, for little payment, which peasants resisted with reduced harvests. The Bolsheviks blamed the ''[[kulak]]''s' withholding grain to increase profits; but statistics indicate most such business occurred in the [[black market]] economy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://wsws.org/correspo/1998/mar1998/leni-m06.shtml |title=An exchange of letters on the BBC documentary Lenin's Secret Files |publisher=[[World Socialist Web Site]] |date=6 March 1998 |accessdate=16 March 2007 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070213155724/http://www.wsws.org/correspo/1998/mar1998/leni-m06.shtml &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 13 February 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Carr, E.H. |year=1966 |title=The Bolshevik Revolution 1917–1923, Part 2 |page=233}} {{cite book |author=Chase, W.J. |year=1987 |title=Workers, Society and the Soviet State: Labour and Life in Moscow 1918–1929 |pages=26–27}} {{cite book |author=Nove, A. |year=1982 |title=An Economic History of the USSR |page=62}} {{cite web |url=http://www.whatnextjournal.co.uk/Pages/Back/Wnext5/Warcomm.html |title=Flewers, Paul, War Communism in Retrospect}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nonetheless, the ''prodrazvyorstka'' resulted in armed confrontations which the [[Cheka]] and Red Army suppressed with shooting hostages, [[poison gas]], and labour-camp deportation; yet Lenin increased the requisitioning.&lt;ref name=&quot;users.erols.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Black Book of Communism]] pp. 92–97, 116–121.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gmu.edu/departments/economics/bcaplan/museum/his1g.htm |title=Lenin and the First Communist Revolutions, VII |publisher=Gmu.edu |accessdate=2012-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The six-year long White–Red civil war, the war communism, the [[Russian famine of 1921|famine of 1921]], which killed an estimated five million, and foreign military intervention reduced much of Russia to ruin, and provoked rebellion against the Bolsheviks, the greatest being the [[Tambov rebellion]] (1919–21). After the March 1921 left-wing [[Kronstadt Rebellion]] mutiny, Lenin replaced war communism with the [[New Economic Policy]] (NEP), and successfully rebuilt industry and agriculture. The NEP was his pragmatic recognition of the political and economic realities, despite being a tactical, [[ideology|ideological]] retreat from the socialist ideal; later, the doctrinaire [[Joseph Stalin]] reversed the NEP in consolidating his control of the Communist Party and the USSR.

== Retirement and death ==
[[File:Lenin and stalin crop.jpg|thumb|upright|During Lenin's sickness (1922–23), Stalin used this altered photograph as his ''bona fides'' claim to leading the CPSU.&lt;ref&gt;Gilbert, Felix and Large, David Clay, ''The End of the European Era: 1890 to the Present'', 6th edition, p. 213.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Persistant stories mark [[syphilis]] as the cause of Lenin's death. A &quot;retrospective diagnosis&quot; published in The European Journal of Neurology in 2004 stengthens these suspicions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/22/science/a-retrospective-diagnosis-says-lenin-had-syphilis.html?pagewanted=all&amp;src=pm A Retrospective Diagnosis Says Lenin Had Syphilis], C.J. Chivers,  [[New York times]], June 22, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

The mental strains of leading a revolution, governing, and fighting a civil war aggravated the physical debilitation consequent to the wounds from the attempted assassinations; Lenin retained a bullet in his neck, until a German surgeon removed it on 24 April 1922.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://query.nytimes.com/mem/archive-free/pdf?res=9400E6D91739EF3ABC4E51DFB2668389639EDE |title=LENIN UNDER THE KNIFE. - Surgeon Extracts a Bullet Which Troubled Him for Three Years. - View Article |work=New York Times |date=26 April 1922 |accessdate=2012-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Among his comrades, Lenin was notable for working almost ceaselessly, fourteen to sixteen hours daily, occupied with minor, major, and routine matters. About the man at his life's end, [[Dmitri Volkogonov|Volkogonov]] said:

{{bquote|Lenin was involved in the challenges of delivering fuel into [[Ivanovo|Ivanovo-Vosnesensk]]... the provision of clothing for miners, he was solving the question of [[dynamo]] construction, drafted dozens of routine documents, orders, trade agreements, was engaged in the allocation of rations, edited books and pamphlets at the request of his comrades, held hearings on the applications of [[peat]], assisted in improving the workings at the &quot;Novii Lessner&quot; factory, clarified in correspondence with the engineer P. A. Kozmin the feasibility of using [[wind turbines]] for the electrification of villages... all the while serving as an adviser to party functionaries almost continuously.&lt;ref&gt;Триумф и Трагедия – И. В. Сталин: политический портрет. (Triumph and Tragedy&amp;nbsp;– I. V. Stalin : A Political Portrait) Дмитрий Волкогонов (Dmitriy Volkogonov). Book 1, Part 1, pp. 114. Новости Publications. Moscow. 1989.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

When already sick, Lenin remembered that, since 1917, he had only rested twice: once, whilst hiding from the Kerensky Provisional Government (when he wrote [[State and Revolution|''The State and Revolution'']]), and whilst recovering from Fanya Kaplan's failed assassination.&lt;ref&gt;Триумф и Трагедия – И. В. Сталин: политический портрет. (Triumph and Tragedy&amp;nbsp;– I. V. Stalin : A Political Portrait) Дмитрий Волкогонов (Dmitriy Volkogonov). Book 1, Part 1, pp. 111. Новости Publications. Moscow. 1989.&lt;/ref&gt; In March 1922, when physicians examined him, they found evidence of neither nervous nor organic [[pathology]], but, given his [[fatigue (medical)|fatigue]] and the headaches he suffered, they prescribed rest. Upon returning to St. Petersburg in May 1922, Lenin suffered the first of three strokes, which left him unable to speak for weeks, and severely hampered motion in his right side; by June, he had substantially recovered. By August he resumed limited duties, delivering three long speeches in November. In December 1922, he suffered the second stroke that partly [[paralysis|paralyzed]] his right side, he then withdrew from active politics. In March 1923, he suffered the third stroke that rendered him [[muteness|mute]] and bed-ridden until his death.

[[File:Lenin-last-photo.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Lenin in 1923]]
After the first stroke, Lenin dictated government papers to Nadezhda; among them was ''[[Lenin's Testament]]'' (changing the structure of the soviets), a document partly inspired by the 1922 [[Georgian Affair]], which was a conflict about the way in which social and political transformation within a [[Republics of the Soviet Union|constituent republic]] was to be achieved. It criticized high-rank Communists, including [[Joseph Stalin]], [[Grigory Zinoviev]], [[Lev Kamenev]], [[Nikolai Bukharin]], and [[Leon Trotsky]]. About the Communist Party's General Secretary (since 1922), Joseph Stalin, Lenin reported that the &quot;unlimited authority&quot; concentrated in him was unacceptable, and suggested that &quot;comrades think about a way of removing Stalin from that post.&quot; His phrasing, ''&quot;Сталин слишком груб&quot;'', implies &quot;personal rudeness, unnecessary roughness, lack of finesse&quot;, flaws &quot;intolerable in a Secretary-General&quot;.

At Lenin's death, Nadezhda mailed his testament to the central committee, to be read aloud to the 13th Party Congress in May 1924. However, to remain in power, the ruling ''[[Troika (triumvirate)|troika]]''—Stalin, Kamenev, Zinoviev—suppressed ''Lenin's Testament''; it was not published until 1925, in the United States, by the American [[intellectual]] [[Max Eastman]]. In that year, Trotsky published an article minimising the importance of ''Lenin's Testament'', saying that Lenin's notes should not be perceived as a will, that it had been neither concealed, nor violated;&lt;ref&gt;Trotsky, L. D., &quot;Concerning Eastman's Book Since Lenin Died&quot;, ''Bolshevik'' 16; 1 September 1925; p. 68. Concerning Eastman's Book ''Since Lenin Died'' minimising its significance. &quot;In several parts of his book, Eastman says that the Central Committee concealed from the Party a number of exceptionally important documents written by Lenin in the last period of his life (it is a matter of letters on the national question, the so-called 'will', and others); there can be no other name for this, than slander against the Central Committee of our Party. . . . Vladimir Ilyich did not leave any 'will', and the very character of his attitude towards the Party, as well as the character of the Party, itself, precluded any possibility of such a 'will'. What is usually referred to as a 'will' in the ''émigré'' and foreign bourgeois and Menshevik press (in a manner garbled beyond recognition) is one of Vladimir Ilyich's letters containing advice on organisational matters. The 13th Congress of the Party paid the closest attention to that letter, as to all of the others, and drew from it the conclusions appropriate to the conditions and circumstances of the time. All talk about concealing or violating a 'will' is a malicious invention.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; yet he did invoke it in later anti-Stalin polemics.&lt;ref&gt;Trotsky, Leon. ''My Life'' (1930) The Marxists Internet Archive&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=On the Suppressed Testament of Lenin|url=http://www.marxists.org/archive/trotsky/1932/12/lenin.htm|author=Trotsky, Leon|year=1932|publisher=The Marxists Internet Archive|accessdate=16 March 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lenin died at 18.50 hrs, Moscow time, on 21 January 1924, aged 53, at his estate at Gorki settlement (later renamed [[Gorki Leninskiye]]). In the four days that the Bolshevik Leader Vladimir Ilyich Lenin [[Lying in state|lay in state]], more than 900,000&amp;nbsp;mourners viewed his body in the Hall of Columns; among the statesmen who expressed condolences to the Soviet Union was Chinese premier [[Sun Yat-sen]], who said:

{{bquote|Through the ages of world history, thousands of leaders and scholars appeared who spoke eloquent words, but these remained words. You, Lenin, were an exception. You not only spoke and taught us, but translated your words into deeds. You created a new country. You showed us the road of joint struggle... You, great man that you are, will live on in the memories of the oppressed people through the centuries.&lt;ref&gt;Gorin, Vadim, ''Lenin: A Biography'' (1983) Progress Publishers, pp. 469–70&lt;/ref&gt;|15px|15px}}

[[Winston Churchill]], who encouraged British intervention against the [[Russian Revolution (1917)|Russian Revolution]], in league with the [[White Movement]], to destroy the Bolsheviks and Bolshevism, said:

{{bquote|He alone could have found the way back to the causeway... The Russian people were left floundering in the bog. Their worst misfortune was his birth... their next worst his death.&lt;ref&gt;Mauchline Roberts, Elizabeth, ''Lenin and the Downfall of Tsarist Russia'' (1966) p. 92.&lt;/ref&gt;|15px|15px}}

===Funeral===
[[File:Pogrzeb Lenina1924.jpg|thumb|right|Pallbearers carrying Lenin's coffin during his funeral, from [[Paveletsky Rail Terminal]] to the Labor Temple. [[Felix Dzerzhinsky]] at the front with [[Timofei Sapronov]] behind him and [[Lev Kamenev]] on the left.]]
The Soviet government publicly announced Lenin's death the following day, with head of State [[Mikhail Kalinin]] tearfully reading an official statement to delegates of the All-Russian Congress of Soviets at 11am, the same time that a team of physicians began a postmortem of the body.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt; On 23 January, mourners from the Communist Party Central Committee, the Moscow party organisation, the trade unions and the soviets began to assemble at his house, with the body being removed from his home at about 10am the following day, being carried aloft in a red coffin by Kamenev, Zinoviev, Stalin, Bukharin, Bubhov and Krasin. Transported by train to Moscow, mourners gathered at every station along the way, and upon arriving in the city, a funerary procession carried the coffin for five miles to the [[House of Trade Unions]], where the body lay in state.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. pp. 7&amp;ndash;8.&lt;/ref&gt;

Over the next three days, around a million mourners from across the Soviet Union came to see the body,  many queuing for hours in the freezing conditions, with the events being filmed by the government.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rice 9&quot;&gt;[[#Ric90|Rice 1990]]. p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt; On Saturday 26 January, the eleventh All-Union Congress of Soviets met to pay respects to the deceased leader, with speeches being made by Kalinin, Zinoviev and Stalin, but notably not Trotsky, who had been convalescing in the Caucasus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rice 9&quot;/&gt; Lenin's funeral took place the following day, when his body was carried to Red Square, accompanied by martial music, where assembled crowds listened to a series of speeches before the corpse was carried into a vault, followed by the singing of the revolutionary hymn, &quot;You fell in sacrifice.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Rice 9&quot;/&gt;

Three days after his death, Petrograd was renamed [[Saint Petersburg|Leningrad]] in his honour, so remaining until 1991, when the USSR dissolved, yet the administrative area remains &quot;Leningrad Oblast&quot;. In the early 1920s, the Russian [[Cosmism (Russian)|cosmism]] movement proved so popular that [[Leonid Krasin]] and [[Alexander Bogdanov]] proposed to [[Cryonics|cryonically preserve]] Lenin for future resurrection, yet, despite buying the requisite equipment, that was not done.&lt;ref&gt;See the article: А.М. и А.А. Панченко «Осьмое чудо света», in the book Панченко А.М. О русской истории и культуре. St. Petersburg: Azbuka, 2003. p. 433.&lt;/ref&gt; Instead, the body of V. I. Lenin was [[Embalming|embalmed]] and permanently exhibited in [[Lenin's Mausoleum]], in Moscow, on 27 January 1924.

Despite the official diagnosis of death from stroke consequences, the Russian scientist Ivan Pavlov reported that Lenin died of [[neurosyphilis]], according to a publication by V. Lerner and colleagues in the ''European Journal of Neurology'' in 2004. The authors also note that &quot;It is possible that future DNA technology applied to Lenin's preserved brain material could ultimately establish or disprove neurosyphilis as the primary cause of Lenin's death.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;V. Lerner, Y. Finkelstein and E. Witztum, &quot;The enigma of Lenin's (1870–1924) malady&quot;. ''European Journal of Neurology'', 2004, 11: 371–376&lt;/ref&gt;

In a poll conducted by a Russian website, 48 per cent of the people that responded voted that the body of the former leader should be buried.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Russians want Bolshevik leader Lenin to be buried|url=http://www.business-standard.com/generalnews/news/russians-want-bolshevik-leader-lenin-to-be-buried/20479/|publisher=Business Standard|accessdate=13 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Bennetts|first=Marc|title=Russians mull burying Soviet leader Lenin|url=http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2012/jul/10/russians-mull-burying-soviet-leader-lenin/|accessdate=13 July 2012|newspaper=The Washington Times|date=July 10, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Politics and world revolution==
Lenin was a Marxist and principally a revolutionary. His revolutionary theory—the belief in the necessity of a violent overthrow of capitalism through communist revolution, to be followed by a [[dictatorship of the proletariat]] as the first stage of moving towards communism, and the need for a vanguard party to lead the proletariat in this effort—developed into [[Marxism–Leninism]], a highly influential ideology. Lenin biographer [[Robert Service (historian)|Robert Service]] noted that Lenin considered &quot;moral questions&quot; to be &quot;an irrelevance&quot;, rejecting the concept of [[moral absolutism]]; instead he judged whether an action was justifiable based upon its chances of success for the revolutionary cause.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. p. 80.&lt;/ref&gt;

As stated in his ''[[Imperialism, the Highest Stage of Capitalism]]'', Lenin's revolutionary project embraced not just Russia but the world. To implement world revolution the Third or [[Communist International]] was convened in Russia in 1919, to replace the discredited Second International.&lt;ref&gt;E. H. Carr (1979) ''The Russian Revolution From Lenin to Stalin 1917–1929''. London, Macmillan: 14&lt;/ref&gt; Lenin dominated the first, second (1920) and third (1921) Congresses of the International and hoped to use the organisation as an agency of international socialist revolution.&lt;ref&gt;E.H. Carr (1979) ''The Russian Revolution From Lenin to Stalin 1917–1929''. London, Macmillan: 14, 16–17, 46–8&lt;/ref&gt; After the failure of revolutionary ambitions in Poland, in the [[Polish–Soviet War]] of 1919–21, and after [[Revolutions of 1917–23|various revolutions in Germany and Eastern Europe in 1919]] had been crushed, Lenin, increasingly, saw that anti-colonial struggles in the Third World would be the foci of the revolutionary struggle. He believed that revolution in the Third World would come about through an alliance of the proletarians with the rural peasantry.&lt;ref&gt;Триумф и Трагедия – И. В. Сталин: политический портрет.  (''Triumph and Tragedy – I. V. Stalin : A Political Portrait'') Дмитрий Волкогонов (Dmitriy Volkogonov). Book 1, Part 1, PP. 95 – 114. Новости Publications.  Moscow. 1989.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1923 Lenin said:
:The outcome of the struggle will be determined by the fact that Russia, India, China, etc,. account for the overwhelming majority of the population of the globe. And during the last few years it is this majority that has been drawn into the struggle for emancipation with extraordinary rapidity, so that in this respect there cannot be the slightest doubt what the final outcome of the world struggle will be. In this sense the complete victory of socialism is fully and absolutely assured.&lt;ref&gt;Lenin, quoted in Prabhat Patnaik &quot;Introduction&quot; to ''Imperialism, the Highest Stage of Revolution''.  New Delhi, Leftward Books, p. 8&lt;/ref&gt;

Lenin praised [[Chinese socialism|Chinese socialist]] revolutionary leader [[Sun Yatsen]] and his [[Kuomintang]] party for their ideology and principles. Lenin praised Sun, his attempts on social reformation and congratulated him for fighting foreign Imperialism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=[[Mao Tse-tung: Ruler of Red China]]|author=Robert Payne|year=2008|publisher=Brownell Press|edition=reprint|page=22|page=324|isbn=1-4437-2521-8|accessdate=2010-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=vnOFYI3g-N4C|title=Great Soviet Encyclopedia|page=237|accessdate=2010-06-28|year=1980}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=mF0NAQAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA237|title=Great Soviet encyclopedia, Volume 25|editor=Aleksandr Mikhaĭlovich Prokhorov|year=1982|publisher=Macmillan|accessdate=2010-06-28}}(Original from the University of Michigan)&lt;/ref&gt; Sun also returned the praise, calling him a &quot;great man&quot;, and sent his congratulations on the revolution in Russia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=lSVK8qxOsG8C&amp;pg=PA170|title=Aunt Mae's China|author=Bernice A Verbyla|year=2010|publisher=Xulon Press|page=170|page=358|isbn=1-60957-456-7|accessdate=2010-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Organised on [[Leninism]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=GTgEPrlfvG4C&amp;pg=PA337|title=Chiang Kai Shek: China's Generalissimo and the Nation He Lost|author=Jonathan Fenby|year=2005|publisher=Carroll &amp; Graf Publishers|edition=illustrated|page=504|page=562|isbn=0-7867-1484-0|accessdate=2010-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Kuomintang was a nationalist revolutionary party, which had been supported by the Soviet Union.

===Writings===
[[File:Mcita murutsxi.jpg|thumb|Lenin the icon: A 1929 [[Laz language]] newspaper featuring Lenin's writing]]

Lenin was a prolific political theoretician and philosopher who wrote about the practical aspects of carrying out a proletarian revolution; he wrote pamphlets, articles, and books, without a [[shorthand|stenographer]] or secretary, until prevented by illness.&lt;ref&gt;Триумф и Трагедия – И. В. Сталин: политический портрет. (Triumph and Tragedy&amp;nbsp;– I. V. Stalin : A Political Portrait) Дмитрий Волкогонов ([[Dmitri Volkogonov]]). Book 1, Part 1, pp. 110. Новости Publications. Moscow. 1989.&lt;/ref&gt; He simultaneously corresponded with comrades, allies, and friends, in Russia and world-wide. His ''Collected Works'' comprise 54 volumes, each of about 650 pages, translated into English in 45 volumes by Progress Publishers, Moscow 1960–70.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/cw/index.htm |title=Lenin Collected Works |publisher=Marxists.org |accessdate=2012-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; The most influential include:

* ''[[What is to be Done?]]'' (1902) states that a revolution requires a professional [[vanguard party]].
* ''[[Imperialism, the Highest Stage of Capitalism]]'' (1916) explains why capitalism had not collapsed, as Marx had posited, presenting the [[First World War]] as a capitalist war for land, resources, and cheap labour.
* ''[[State and Revolution|The State and the Revolution]]'' (1917) interprets the ideas of Marx and Engels, the October Revolution's theoretic basis, and opposes the social-democratic tendency as indecisive in effecting revolution.
* ''[[April Theses]]'' (1917) propose the socio-economic need for a socialist revolution.
* ''[[&quot;Left-Wing&quot; Communism: An Infantile Disorder]]'' (1920) sharply criticizes the &quot;ultra-left&quot;

After Lenin's death, the [[Censorship in the Soviet Union|USSR selectively censored]] his writings, to establish the [[dogma]] of the [[infallibility]] of Lenin, Stalin (his successor), and the Central Committee;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book |last=Trotsky |first=Leon |authorlink=Leon Trotsky|title=Volume Three: The Triumph of the Soviets; Appendix No. 1 |work=The History of the Russian Revolution |year=1930}}&lt;/ref&gt; thus, the Soviet fifth edition (55 vols., 1958–65) of Lenin's ''œuvre'' deleted the Lenin–Stalin contradictions, and all that was unfavourable to the founder of the USSR.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Figes|first=Orlando|title=Censored by His Own Regime|journal=The New York Times|date=27 October 1996|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E1DB1230F934A15753C1A960958260}}&lt;/ref&gt; The historian [[Richard Pipes]] published a documentary collection of letters and telegrams excluded from the Soviet fifth edition, proposing that edition as incomplete.&lt;ref name=&quot;unknownlenin_201204&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title=The Unknown Lenin: From the Secret Archive | publisher=Yale University Press | author=Pipes, Richard | year=1999 | pages=2–3 | isbn=978-0-300-07662-2 | quote=It has long been known to scholars that the fifth, the &quot;complete&quot; edition was in fact far from complete. The two-volume ''Trotsky Papers'', based on the Trotsky Archive at the Harvard Houghton Library, brought to light a number of previously unpublished documents by Lenin. It was also apparent to Western scholars that in addition to omitting entire documents, the editors of the fifth edition had occasionally tampered with Lenin's texts, censoring passages which for one reason or another they judged unfit of republic consumption. But just how incomplete the fifth edition was did not become known until the breakup of the Soviet Union in late 1991, when President Boris Yeltsin ordered Russian archives to be removed from the control of the Communist Party and placed under the authority of state organs. It then transpired that the Central Party Archive, now renamed the Russian Center for the Preservation and Study of Documents of Recent History, or RTsKhIDNI, held no fewer than 6,7724 unpublished Lenin manuscripts—that is, twice the number included in the so-called complete collection!}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal life and characteristics==
{{Quote box|width=25em|align=right|bgcolor=#ACE1AF|quote=&quot;[Lenin's collected writings] reveal in detail a man with iron will, self-enslaving self-discipline, scorn for opponents and obstacles, the cold determination of a zealot, the drive of a fanatic, and the ability to convince or browbeat weaker persons by his singleness of purpose, imposing intensity, impersonal approach, personal sacrifice, political astuteness, and complete conviction of the possession of  the absolute truth. His life became the history of the Bolshevik movement.&quot;
|source=—Biographer Louis Fischer, 1964.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Fis64|Fischer 1964]]. pp. 21&amp;ndash;22.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

One of Lenin's biographers, the historian [[Robert Service (historian)|Robert Service]], asserted that the Russian had been &quot;a young man of intense emotions&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. p. 73.&lt;/ref&gt; who also exhibited a &quot;visceral hatred&quot; of the &quot;slightest sign of illegality or corruption&quot; which he saw exhibited throughout Tsarist Russia.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. p. 81.&lt;/ref&gt; He furthermore argued that Lenin was a man who could be &quot;moody and volatile&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. p. 116.&lt;/ref&gt; Service noted that Lenin developed an &quot;emotional attachment&quot; to his ideological heroes, such as Marx, Engels and Chernyshevsky, owning portraits of them.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. p. 118.&lt;/ref&gt;

Lenin despised untidiness, always keeping his work desk tidy and his pencils sharpened.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ser00|Service 2000]]. pp. 99&amp;ndash;100.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to [[Leon Trotsky]], who knew him well:
:Lenin's outward appearance was distinguished by simplicity and strength. He was below the middle height, with the plebeian features of the Slavonic type of face, brightened by piercing eyes; and his powerful forehead and still more powerful head gave him a marked distinction.&lt;ref&gt;Leon Trotsky (1939) &quot;Lenin&quot; in ''The Encyclopædia Britannica'' (Fourteenth Edition): 911–914&lt;/ref&gt;
According to [[Bertrand Russell]], who had an hours conversation with him:
:He is very friendly, and apparently simple, entirely without a trace of hauteur. If one met him without knowing who he was, one would not guess that he is possessed of great power or even that he is in any way eminent. I have never met a personage so destitute of self-importance. He looks at his visitors very closely, and screws up one eye, which seems to increase alarmingly the penetrating power of the other. He laughs a great deal; at first his laugh seems merely friendly and jolly, but gradually I came to feel it rather grim. He is dictatorial, calm, incapable of fear, extraordinarily devoid of self-seeking, an embodied theory. The materialist conception of history, one feels, is his life-blood. He resembles a professor in his desire to have the theory understood and in his fury with those who misunderstand or disagree, as also in his love of expounding, I got the impression that he despises a great many people and is an intellectual aristocrat.&lt;ref&gt;
http://www.revleft.com/vb/philosopher-bertrand-russell-t127222/index.html?s=794f2e8c04b3d8ad0a9541d7e978a128&amp;amp;t=127222&quot;Philosopher Bertrand Russell about the personality of Lenin and Trotsky&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
According to most reports, in his personal life Lenin was a modest and unassuming man. He liked children and cats and his enthusiasms included bicycling, amateur photography, chess, skating, swimming, hunting, music and hiking.&lt;ref&gt;Paul Le Blanc (2008) ''Revolution, Democracy, Socialism&amp;nbsp;– Selected Writings of Lenin''. London, Pluto Press: 24–5&lt;/ref&gt; When in exile in Switzerland, Lenin, accompanied by his wife Krupskaya, developed a considerable passion for mountain walking in the Swiss peaks.&lt;ref name=&quot;christopher_read_lenin&quot;/&gt;{{rp|pages=20, 64, 132–37}} Lenin's personal life is documented in detail in his wife's book ''Memories of Lenin''.&lt;ref name=&quot;christopher_read_lenin&quot;/&gt;{{rp|pages=2, 301}}

==Legacy==

{{Cquote2|As influential as he was in life, Lenin may have been more so in death. Over 100 million have lined up to view [[Lenin's Mausoleum|his mummified body]]. His memory has been used to support every change in Soviet policy and every new regime since his death. His theories inspired the successful revolutions of [[Fidel Castro]], [[Mao Zedong]], and [[Ho Chi Minh]]; as well as countless other revolutionaries in countries full of oppressed and powerless people.| ''Vladimir Lenin: Voice of Revolution'', [[A&amp;E Network|A&amp;E]] [[Biography (TV series)|Biography]], 2005&lt;ref name = &quot;LeninDoc&quot; /&gt;}}

[[File:URSS 1 rublo centenario nascita Lenin.JPG|Commemorative [[Soviet rouble|one rouble]] coin minted in 1970, in honor of Lenin's 100th birthday.|thumb|right]]

When Lenin died on 21 January 1924, near Moscow, he was acclaimed as &quot;the greatest genius of mankind&quot; and &quot;the leader and teacher of the peoples of the whole world&quot;.&lt;ref name = &quot;1968Encyclopedia&quot;&gt;[http://www.encyclopedia.com/topic/Vladimir_Ilyich_Lenin.aspx Lenin] entry from the ''[[International Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences]]'', 1968&lt;/ref&gt; Historian [[J. Arch Getty]] has remarked that &quot;Lenin deserves a lot of credit for the notion that the meek can inherit the earth, that there can be a political movement based on social justice and equality&quot;.&lt;ref name = &quot;LeninDoc&quot;&gt;[[Biography (TV series)]] – [http://www.newvideo.com/ae/vladimir-lenin-voice-of-revolution/ ''Vladimir Lenin, Voice of Revolution''], [[A&amp;E Network]], 2005, ASIN B000AABKX6&lt;/ref&gt; ''Time Magazine'' also named Lenin one of the [[Time 100: The Most Important People of the Century|100 most important people of the 20th century]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://205.188.238.181/time/time100/leaders/profile/lenin.html TIME 100: Vladimir Lenin] by David Remnick, 13 April 1998.&lt;/ref&gt; and one of their top 25 political icons of all time; remarking that &quot;for decades, Marxist–Leninist rebellions shook the world while Lenin's embalmed corpse lay in repose in the [[Red Square]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/specials/packages/article/0,28804,2046285_2045996_2046096,00.html Top 25 Political Icons: Lenin] by Feifei Sun, ''[[Time Magazine|Time]]'', 4 February 2011&lt;/ref&gt; Following the dissolution of the USSR in 1991, reverence for Lenin declined among the post-Soviet generations, yet he remains an important historical figure for the Soviet-era generations.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
 |last=Pipes
 |first=Richard
 |title=Flight From Freedom: What Russians Think and Want
 |journal=Foreign Affairs
 |date=May/June 2004
 |url=http://www.foreignaffairs.org/20040501facomment83302-p20/richard-pipes/flight-from-freedom-what-russians-think-and-want.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the article in [[Encyclopædia Britannica]] written by Professor of [[Northern Illinois University]] [[Albert Resis]]:&lt;ref name=&quot;EB&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia | title=Vladimir lenin | encyclopedia=Encyclopædia Britannica | accessdate=11 August 2011 | author=Resis, Albert | url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/335881/Vladimir-Ilich-Lenin}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{cquote|If the Bolshevik Revolution is-as some people have called it-the most significant political event of the 20th century, then Lenin must for good or ill be considered the century's most significant political leader. Not only in the scholarly circles of the former Soviet Union, but even among many non-Communist scholars, he has been regarded as both the greatest revolutionary leader and revolutionary statesman in history, as well as the greatest revolutionary thinker since Marx}}

===Statues and city names===
{{Main|List of places named after Vladimir Lenin|List of statues of Vladimir Lenin}}
During the Soviet period, many statues of Lenin were erected across Eastern Europe. Although many of the statues have subsequently been removed, some remain standing, and a few new ones have been erected.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unian.net/eng/news/news-312409.html Two Lenin monuments opened in Luhansk Oblast], [[UNIAN]] (April 22, 2008)&lt;/ref&gt; 

Many places and entities were named in honor of Lenin. The city of [[Saint Petersburg]], the site where both February and October revolutions started, was renamed ''Leningrad'' in 1924, four days after Lenin's death. In 1991, after a contested vote between Communists and liberals, the Leningrad government reverted the city's name to [[Saint Petersburg]] whilst the surrounding [[Leningrad Oblast]] remained so named;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sos.state.md.us/International/MDSS/RussiaHistory.htm Maryland Government], St Petersburg/Leningrad Oblast&lt;/ref&gt; like-wise the city of [[Ulyanovsk]] (so-named after Lenin's [[birth name]]) and the [[Ulyanovsk Oblast]] remain so named. [[Gyumri]] in Armenia was named ''Leninakan'' from 1924 to 1990, [[Khujand]] in Tajikistan ''Leninabad'' from 1936 to 1991.

In space, the [[852 Wladilena]] [[asteroid]] was named in his honor.

==In popular culture==

===Film===
[[File:October film Lenin.jpg|thumb|right|Lenin as represented in [[Sergei Eisenstein]]'s 1927 film ''[[October: Ten Days That Shook the World|October]]''.]]

* [[Sergei Eisenstein]]'s ''[[October: Ten Days That Shook the World]]'' (1927) became an influential celebratory dramatization of the 1917 [[October Revolution]].
* ''[[Three Songs About Lenin]]'' (1934) is a documentary silent film by Russian filmmaker [[Dziga Vertov]].
* Lenin appeared as a character in the Soviet films ''[[Lenin in October]]'' (1937) and ''[[Lenin in 1918]]'' (1939), both directed by [[Mikhail Romm]].
* [[Sergei Yutkevich]] directed a series of films about Lenin, featuring [[Maxim Straukh]]. These include ''[[The Man With the Gun]]'' (1938), ''[[Yakov Sverdlov]]'' (1940), ''[[Stories of Lenin]]'' (1957), ''[[Lenin in Poland]]'' (1966) and ''[[Lenin in Paris]]'' (1981).&lt;ref&gt;David Robinson (1981) ''World Cinema 1895–1980''. London, Methuen: 223&lt;/ref&gt;
* Lenin was portrayed by [[Michael Bryant (actor)|Michael Bryant]] in the 1971 film ''[[Nicholas and Alexandra]]''.
* ''[[All My Lenins]]'' (1997) is a historical comedy by [[Hardi Volmer]].

===Television===
*Lenin was portrayed by [[Patrick Stewart]] in the 1974 BBC miniseries ''[[Fall of Eagles]]''.
*Lenin was portrayed by [[Kenneth Cranham]] in the 1983 BBC miniseries ''[[Reilly: Ace of Spies]]''.
*Lenin was portrayed by [[Ben Kingsley]] in the 1988 television film ''[[Lenin: The Train]]''.
*Lenin was portrayed by [[Maximilian Schell]] in the 1992 HBO television film ''[[Stalin (1992 film)|Stalin]]''

{{clear}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Communism|Politics|Soviet Union}}
{{Multicol}}
*[[Anti-Leninism]]
*[[National delimitation in the Soviet Union]]
*[[Marxist‒Leninist atheism ]]
{{Multicol-break}}
*[[Lenin Prize]]
*[[Lenin Peace Prize]]
*[[Order of Lenin]]
{{Multicol-end}}
{{clear}}

==References==

===Footnotes===
{{reflist|3}}

===Bibliography===
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book |title=The Life of Lenin |last=Fischer |first=Louis |authorlink=Louis Fischer |year=1964 |publisher=Weidenfeld and Nicolson |location=London |isbn=978-1842122303 |ref=Fis64}}
* {{cite book |title=Lenin: Portrait of a Professional Revolutionary |last=Rice |first=Christopher |year=1990 |publisher=Cassell |location=London |isbn=978-0304318148 |ref=Ric90}}
* {{cite book |title=Lenin: A Biography |last=Service |first=Robert |year=2000 |publisher=Macmillan |location=London |isbn=978-0333726251 |ref=Ser00}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin|30em}}
*{{Cite journal
|author =Blackledge, Paul
|date = 3 July 2006
|title = What was done
|journal = [[International Socialism (magazine)|International Socialism]]
|issue = 111
|publisher = [[Socialist Workers Party (Britain)]]
|location = London
|issn = 1754-4653
|url = http://www.isj.org.uk/index.php4?id=218&amp;issue=111
|accessdate = 2010-06-25
 }} A review of Lars T Lih, Lenin Rediscovered: What is to be Done? in Context
*{{Cite book
 |last=Cliff
 |first=Tony
 |authorlink=Tony Cliff
 |title=Building the Party: Lenin, 1893–1914
 |publisher=[[Haymarket Books]]
 |year=1986
 |isbn=1-931859-01-9}}
*{{Cite book
 |last=Felshtinsky
 |first=Yuri
 |authorlink=Yuri Felshtinsky
 |title=Lenin and His Comrades: The Bolsheviks Take Over Russia 1917–1924
 |publisher=Enigma Books
 |year=2010
 |isbn=1-929631-95-2}}
*{{Cite book
 |last=Fischer
 |first=Louis
 |authorlink=Louis Fischer
 |title=The Life of Lenin
 |publisher=[[Orion Publishing Group|Orion Publishing Co.]]
 |year=2001
 |isbn=1-84212-230-4 }}
*{{Cite book
 |last=Gellately
 |first=Robert
 |authorlink=Robert Gellately
 |title=Lenin, Stalin, and Hitler: The Age of Social Catastrophe
 |publisher=[[Knopf]]
 |year=2007
 |isbn=1-4000-4005-1}}
*{{Cite book
 |last=Gooding
 |first=John
 |title=Socialism In Russia: Lenin and His Legacy, 1890–1991
 |publisher=[[Palgrave Macmillan]]
 |year=2002
 |isbn=0-333-97235-X}}
*{{Cite book
 |last=Hill
 |first=Christopher
 |authorlink=Christopher Hill (historian)
 |title=Lenin and the Russia Revolution
 |publisher=[[Pelican Books|Pelican Books Ltd.]]
 |year=1971
 |isbn=978-0-14-021297-6}}
*{{Cite book
 |author=[[Leszek Kołakowski|Kolakowski, Leszek]] and Falla, P. S.
 |title=Main Currents of Marxism
 |publisher=[[W. W. Norton &amp; Company]]
 |year=2005
 |isbn=0-393-06054-3}}
*{{Cite book
 |last=Leggett
 |first=George
 |title=The Cheka: Lenin's Political Police
 |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]
 |year=1987
 |isbn=0-19-822862-7}}
*{{Cite book |last1=Lih |first1=Lars T. |title=Lenin Rediscovered: What is to be Done? in Context |year=2008 |origyear=2006 |publisher=[[Haymarket Books]] |location= Chicago |isbn=978-1-931859-58-5 |lastauthoramp=&amp;}}
*{{Cite book
 |last=Lenin
 |first=Vladimir
 |title=Revolution at the Gates: A Selection of Writings from February to October 1917 by V. I. Lenin
 |publisher=[[Pelican Books|Verso Books]]
 |year=2002
 |isbn=1-85984-661-0}}
*{{Cite book
 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=L89oAAAAMAAJ |last1=Pannekoek |first1=Anton |last2=Richey |first2=Lance Byron
 |title=Lenin as Philosopher
 |authorlink=Antonie Pannekoek
 |publisher=[[Marquette University Press]]
 |year=2003
 |isbn=0-87462-654-4}}
*{{Cite book
 |last=Payne
 |first=Robert
 |authorlink=Pierre Stephen Robert Payne
 |title=The Life And Death Of Lenin
 |publisher=[[Simon &amp; Schuster]]
 |year=1967
 |isbn=0-671-41640-5}}
*{{Cite book
 |last=Pipes
 |first=Richard
 |authorlink=Richard Pipes
 |title=The Unknown Lenin: From the Secret Archive
 |publisher=[[Yale University Press]]
 |year=1999
 |isbn=0-300-07662-2}}
*{{Cite book
 |last=Rappaport
 |first=Helen
 |authorlink=Helen Rappaport
 |title=Conspirator: Lenin in Exile
 |publisher=[[Basic Books]]
 |year=2010
 |isbn=978-0-465-01395-1}}
*{{Cite book
 |last=Service
 |first=Robert
 |authorlink=Robert Service (historian)
 |title=Lenin: A Biography
 |publisher=[[Belknap Press]]
 |year=2002
 |isbn=0-674-00828-6}}
*{{Cite book
 |last=Shub
 |first=David
 |title=Lenin: A Biography
 |publisher=[[Penguin Books]]
 |year=1965
 |isbn=0-14-020809-7}}
*{{Cite journal
 |last=Toynbee
 |first=Arnold
 |authorlink=Arnold J. Toynbee
 |title=A Centenary View of Lenin
 |journal=[[International Affairs (journal)|International Affairs]]
 |volume=46
 |issue=3
 |pages=490–500
 |month=July |year=1970
 |doi=10.2307/2613225|jstor=2613225
 |publisher=[[Blackwell Publishing]]}}
*{{Cite book
 |last=Trotsky
 |first=Leon
 |authorlink=Leon Trotsky
 |title=On Lenin: Notes Towards a Biography
 |publisher=[[Harrap]]
 |year=1971
 |isbn=0-245-50302-1}}
*{{Cite book
 |last=Tucker
 |first=Robert C.
 |authorlink=Robert C. Tucker
 |title=The Lenin Anthology
 |publisher=[[W. W. Norton &amp; Company]]
 |year=1975
 |isbn=0-393-09236-4}}
*{{Cite book
 |last=Volkogonov
 |first=Dmitri
 |authorlink=Dmitri Volkogonov
 |title=Lenin: A New Biography
 |publisher=[[Free Press (publisher)|Free Press]]
 |year=2006
 |isbn=0-02-933435-7}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Sister project links|s=Author:Vladimir Lenin|b=no|v=no|n=no|wikt=no}}
* {{worldcat id|id=lccn-n80-67085}}
*[http://www.marx2mao.com/Lenin/Index.html Marx2Mao.org]{{spaced ndash}}Lenin Internet Library
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-l53FPENoAU Lenin's speech (video)]{{spaced ndash}}Lenin's speech with subtitles
*[http://www.marxists.org/archive/trotsky/1939/xx/lenin02.html Article on Lenin written by Trotsky for the Encyclopædia Britannica]
*[http://www2.cddc.vt.edu/marxists/archive/krupskaya/works/rol/index.htm Reminiscences of Lenin by N. K. Krupskaya]
*[http://www.lenin.fi/uusi/uk/index.htm The Lenin Museum] in [[Tampere]], Finland
*[http://www.gmu.edu/departments/economics/bcaplan/museum/hisfram1.htm Lenin and the First Communist Revolutions]
*[http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/bio/index.htm Lenin Internet Archive Biography] includes interviews with Lenin and essays on the leader
*[http://www.marxists.org/archive/bryant/works/1923-mom/lenin.htm Mirrors of Moscow: Nikolai Lenin] by [[Louise Bryant]]
*[http://debs.indstate.edu/z77n5_1918.pdf Nicolai Lenin] His Life and Work by G. Zinovieff, [[Indiana State University]]
*[http://net.lib.byu.edu/~rdh7/wwi/memoir/Robins/Robins4.htm The Personality and Power of Nikolai Lenin] From Raymond Robins' Own Story by William Hard (1920)
*[http://205.188.238.181/time/time100/leaders/profile/lenin.html TIME 100: V.I. Lenin] by [[David Remnick]], 13 April 1998
*{{YouTube|6ybDtm93e4c|Re: Lenin in color – high quality edition}}
*[http://mnweekly.ru/local/20090115/55364151.html The Ghosts of Lenin Abound] by ''The Moscow News Weekly'', 15 January 2009
*[http://www.themilitant.com/2010/7416/741650.html Lenin's Fight to Defend Working-class Power and Revolutionary Internationalism] by ''[[The Militant]]''
*[http://www.internationalsteam.co.uk/trains/russia06.htm Lenin's Funeral Train] in its own museum next to [[Paveletsky Rail Terminal]]
* {{gutenberg author|id=Vladimir_Ilyich_Lenin_(1870–1924)|name=Vladimir Ilyich Lenin}}
* [http://econfaculty.gmu.edu/bcaplan/museum/musframe.htm Museum of Communists]
** [http://econfaculty.gmu.edu/bcaplan/museum/his1e.htm Vladmir Lenin]
*[http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/index.htm Marxists.org Lenin Internet Archive]{{spaced ndash}}Extensive compendium of writings, a biography, and many photographs

===Selected works===
: Main website [http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/cw/index.htm Lenin's Works]
* [http://www.marxists.org/romana/audio/index.htm Lenin's Speeches on Gramophone Records]
*[http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1899/devel/index.htm The Development of Capitalism in Russia]
*''[[What is to be Done? (pamphlet)|What is to be Done?]]'' [http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1901/witbd/index.htm]
*[http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1904/onestep/index.htm One Step Forward, Two Steps Back]
*[http://marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1904/sep/15a.htm Reply by N. Lenin] to [[Rosa Luxemburg]]
*[http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1905/tactics/index.htm Two Tactics of Social-Democracy in the Democratic Revolution]
*[http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1908/mec/index.htm Materialism and Empirio-Criticism]
*[http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1915/oct/16.htm The Right of Nations to Self-Determination]
*[http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1916/imp-hsc/index.htm Imperialism, the Highest Stage of Capitalism]
*''[[The State and Revolution]]'' [http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1917/staterev/index.htm]
*[http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1917/dec/25.htm How to Organise Competition?]
*''The [[April Theses]]'' [http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1917/apr/04.htm]
*[http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1918/oct/10.htm The Proletarian Revolution and the Renegade Kautsky]
*''[[Left-Wing Communism: An Infantile Disorder]]'' [http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1920/lwc/index.htm]
*[http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1922/dec/testamnt/index.htm Lenin's ''Testament'']
*[http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1923/mar/05.htm Lenin's last letter to Stalin]
*[http://politazbuka.ru/biblioteka/marksizm/562-lenin-vladimir-polnoe-sobranie-sochineniy-5-izdanie.html Lenin's ''Complete Collected Works''], in 55 volumes. (Russian)

{{S-start}}
{{S-off}}
{{S-bef|before=None}}
{{S-ttl|title=[[List of leaders of the Russian SFSR|Chairman]] of the [[Council of People's Commissars (Russia)|Council of People's Commissars]] of the [[Russian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic|Russian Socialist Federative Soviet Republic]]|years=1917–1924}}
{{S-aft|rows=2|after=[[Alexey Rykov]]}}
|-
{{S-bef|before=None}}
{{S-ttl|title=[[Premier of the Soviet Union|Chairman]] of the [[Council of People's Commissars]] of the [[Union of Soviet Socialist Republics]]|years=1922–1924}}
|-
{{S-mil}}
|-
{{S-bef|before=None}}
{{S-ttl|title=Chairman of the [[Council of Labour and Defence]]|years=1918–1920}}
{{S-aft|after=Himself&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;as Chair of the [[Sovnarkom]]&lt;/small&gt;}}
|-
{{S-end}}

{{Leaders of CPSU}}
{{USSRpremier}}
{{Prime Ministers of Russia}}
{{Works of Lenin}}
{{Russian Revolution 1917}}
{{Authority control|PND=118640402|LCCN=n/80/67085|VIAF=7393146|TSURL=viaf/7393146}}

{{Persondata
|NAME=Lenin, Vladimir Ilyich
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES= Vladimir Illyich Ulyanov, Владимир Ильич Ульянов (Ленин) (Russian)
|SHORT DESCRIPTION=[[Russia]]n politician, led [[October Revolution]]
|DATE OF BIRTH={{birth date|df=yes|1870|4|22}}
|PLACE OF BIRTH=[[Simbirsk]], Russia
|DATE OF DEATH={{death date|df=yes|1924|1|21}}
|PLACE OF DEATH=Moscow, Russia
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Lenin, Vladimir Ilyich}}
[[Category:Atheist philosophers]]
[[Category:Atheism activists]]
[[Category:Comintern people]]
[[Category:Russian-German people]]
[[Category:Heads of government of the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:Marxist theorists]]
[[Category:Old Bolsheviks]]
[[Category:Russian journalists]]
[[Category:World system scholars]]
[[Category:Russian people of Swedish descent]]
[[Category:Russian people of German descent]]
[[Category:Russian people of Jewish descent]]
[[Category:Tatar people of Russia]]
[[Category:Russian Social Democratic Labour Party members]]
[[Category:Leaders who took power by coup]]
[[Category:Heads of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:People buried in the Kremlin Wall Necropolis]]
[[Category:People from Ulyanovsk]]
[[Category:People of the Russian Civil War]]
[[Category:Political philosophers]]
[[Category:Attempted assassination survivors]]
[[Category:Russian atheists]]
[[Category:Russian economists]]
[[Category:Russian communists]]
[[Category:Russian Marxists]]
[[Category:Russian lawyers]]
[[Category:Russian philosophers]]
[[Category:Russian revolutionaries]]
[[Category:Saint Petersburg State University alumni]]
[[Category:Soviet politicians]]
[[Category:Vladimir Lenin| ]]
[[Category:1870 births]]
[[Category:1924 deaths]]
[[Category:Politburo of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union members]]
[[Category:Former Eastern Orthodox Christians]]
[[Category:Pseudonymous writers]]

{{Link GA|tr}}
{{Link FA|hr}}
&lt;!-- interwiki --&gt;
[[af:Wladimir Lenin]]
[[ang:Fladimir Lenin]]
[[ar:فلاديمير لينين]]
[[an:Lenin]]
[[ast:Lenin]]
[[az:Vladimir İliç Lenin]]
[[bn:ভ্লাদিমির লেনিন]]
[[zh-min-nan:Lenin]]
[[ba:Ленин, Владимир Илья улы]]
[[be:Уладзімір Ільіч Ленін]]
[[be-x-old:Уладзімер Ленін]]
[[bcl:Vladimir Lenin]]
[[bg:Владимир Ленин]]
[[bar:Lenin]]
[[bo:ལེ་ཉིན།]]
[[bs:Vladimir Iljič Lenjin]]
[[br:Vladimir Lenin]]
[[ca:Lenin]]
[[cv:Ленин Владимир Ильич]]
[[cs:Vladimir Iljič Lenin]]
[[co:Lenin]]
[[cy:Vladimir Lenin]]
[[da:Vladimir Lenin]]
[[de:Lenin]]
[[et:Vladimir Lenin]]
[[el:Βλαντιμίρ Λένιν]]
[[eml:Vladimir Il'ič Lenin]]
[[es:Lenin]]
[[eo:Lenin]]
[[ext:Vladimir Lenin]]
[[eu:Vladimir Lenin]]
[[fa:ولادیمیر لنین]]
[[hif:Vladimir Lenin]]
[[fr:Lénine]]
[[fy:Vladimir Lenin]]
[[ga:Vlaidímír Leinín]]
[[gd:Vladimir Lenin]]
[[gl:Lenin]]
[[gan:列寧]]
[[gu:લેનિન]]
[[got:𐌻𐌴𐌽𐌴𐌹𐌽𐍃]]
[[ko:블라디미르 레닌]]
[[hy:Վլադիմիր Իլյիչ Լենին]]
[[hi:व्लादिमीर लेनिन]]
[[hsb:Lenin]]
[[hr:Vladimir Lenjin]]
[[io:Vladimir Lenin]]
[[ilo:Vladimir Lenin]]
[[bpy:লেনিন]]
[[id:Vladimir Lenin]]
[[ia:Vladimir Lenin]]
[[os:Ленин]]
[[is:Vladímír Lenín]]
[[it:Lenin]]
[[he:ולדימיר איליץ' לנין]]
[[jv:Lenin]]
[[kn:ವ್ಲಾಡಿಮಿರ್ ಲೆನಿನ್]]
[[ka:ვლადიმერ ლენინი]]
[[kk:Владимир Ильич Ленин]]
[[sw:Vladimir Lenin]]
[[ku:Lenîn]]
[[ky:Ленин (Ульянов), Владимир Ильич]]
[[lad:Lenin]]
[[la:Vladimirus Lenin]]
[[lez:Владимир Ильич Ленин]]
[[lv:Vladimirs Ļeņins]]
[[lt:Leninas]]
[[jbo:lenin]]
[[hu:Vlagyimir Iljics Lenin]]
[[mk:Владимир Илич Ленин]]
[[mg:Vladimir Ilich Ulianov Lenin]]
[[ml:ലെനിൻ]]
[[mr:व्लादिमिर इलिच लेनिन]]
[[xmf:ვლადიმერ ლენინი]]
[[arz:لينين]]
[[mzn:لنین]]
[[ms:Vladimir I. Lenin]]
[[mwl:Lenin]]
[[mn:Владимир Ильич Ленин]]
[[my:လီနင်]]
[[nl:Vladimir Lenin]]
[[ne:व्लादिमीर लेनिन]]
[[ja:ウラジーミル・レーニン]]
[[no:Vladimir Lenin]]
[[nn:Vladimir Lenin]]
[[nrm:Léninne]]
[[oc:Lenin]]
[[mhr:Ленин, Владимир Ильич]]
[[pnb:ولادیمیر لینن]]
[[ps:ولادمير ايليچ لېنين]]
[[km:វ្លាឌីមៀរ អ៊ីលីច លេនីន]]
[[nds:Vladimir Il'ič Ul'janov]]
[[pl:Włodzimierz Lenin]]
[[pt:Lenin]]
[[kaa:Vladimir Lenin]]
[[ro:Vladimir Ilici Lenin]]
[[qu:Lenin]]
[[rue:Володимир Ленін]]
[[ru:Ленин, Владимир Ильич]]
[[sah:Ленин Владимир Ильич]]
[[sa:व्लाडिमिर लेनिन]]
[[sco:Vladimir Lenin]]
[[st:Vladimir Lenin]]
[[sq:Lenini]]
[[scn:Vladimir Lenin]]
[[simple:Vladimir Lenin]]
[[sk:Vladimir Iľjič Lenin]]
[[sl:Vladimir Iljič Uljanov]]
[[szl:Władimir Leńin]]
[[so:Faladimir Lenin]]
[[ckb:ڤلادیمیر لێنین]]
[[sr:Владимир Лењин]]
[[sh:Vladimir Iljič Lenjin]]
[[fi:Vladimir Lenin]]
[[sv:Vladimir Lenin]]
[[tl:Vladimir Lenin]]
[[ta:விளாடிமிர் லெனின்]]
[[tt:Vladimir Lenin]]
[[te:లెనిన్]]
[[th:วลาดีมีร์ เลนิน]]
[[tg:Владимир Ленин]]
[[tr:Vladimir Lenin]]
[[udm:Ленин, Владимир Ильич]]
[[uk:Ленін Володимир Ілліч]]
[[ur:ولادیمیر لینن]]
[[vi:Vladimir Ilyich Lenin]]
[[fiu-vro:Lenini Vladimir]]
[[war:Vladimir Lenin]]
[[yi:וולאדימיר לענין]]
[[yo:Vladimir Lenin]]
[[zh-yue:列寧]]
[[diq:Lenin]]
[[bat-smg:Lenėns]]
[[zh:列宁]]</text>
      <sha1>78k4t08betd1vw05r12s9ynx6ri6ci4</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
