<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Wage labour</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1650227</id>
    <revision>
      <id>516932465</id>
      <parentid>516932413</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-10T02:15:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Omnipaedista</username>
        <id>8524693</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8945">{{Sociology}}
'''Wage labour''' (or '''wage labor''') is the [[socioeconomics|socioeconomic]] relationship between a [[Workforce|worker]] and an [[Employment|employer]], where the worker sells their [[Labour economics|labour]] under a formal or informal employment [[contract]]. These transactions usually occur in a [[labour market]] where [[wage]]s are market determined.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Deakin|Wilkinson|2005}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Marx|1847|loc=[http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1847/wage-labour/ch02.htm Chapter&amp;nbsp;2.]}}&lt;/ref&gt; In exchange for the wages paid, the work product generally becomes the [[work for hire|undifferentiated property]] of the employer, except  for special cases such as the vesting of [[intellectual property]] patents in the United States where [[patent#Ownership|patent rights]] are [[freelancer|usually]] vested in the original personal inventor. A '''wage labourer''' is a person whose primary means of income is from the selling of his or her labour in this way.

In modern mixed economies such as those of the [[OECD]] countries, it is currently the dominant form of work arrangement. Although most work occurs following this structure, the wage work arrangements of  [[CEO]]s, professional employees, and professional contract workers are sometimes conflated with [[working class|class assignments]], so that &quot;wage labour&quot; is considered to apply only to unskilled, semi-skilled or [[manual labour]].

== Types ==
The most common form of wage labour currently is ordinary direct, or &quot;full-time&quot;, employment in which a free worker sells his or her labour for an indeterminate time (from a few years to the entire career of the worker), in return for a money-wage or salary and a continuing relationship with the employer which it does not in general offer contractors or other irregular staff. However, wage labour takes many other forms, and explicit as opposed to implicit (i.e. conditioned by local labour and tax law) contracts are not uncommon. Economic history shows a great variety of ways in which labour is traded and exchanged. The differences show up in the form of:

*''employment status'': a worker could be employed full-time, part-time, or on a casual basis. He could be employed for example temporarily for a specific project only, or on a permanent basis. Part-time wage labour could combine with part-time [[self-employment]]. The worker could be employed also as an [[apprenticeship|apprentice]].
*''civil (legal) status'': the worker could for example be a free citizen, an [[indentured labour]]er, the subject of [[forced labour]] (including some prison or army labour); a worker could be assigned by the political authorities to a task, he could be a [[slavery|semi-slave]] or a [[serfdom|serf]] bound to the land who is hired out part of the time. So the labour might be performed on a more or less voluntary basis, or on a more or less involuntary basis, in which there are many gradations.
*''method of payment (remuneration or [[Compensation of employees|compensation]])''. The work done could be paid &quot;in cash&quot; (a money-wage) or &quot;in kind&quot; (through receiving goods and/or services), or in the form of &quot;[[piecework|piece rates]]&quot; where the wage is directly dependent on how much the worker produces. In some cases, the worker might be paid in the form of credit used to buy goods and services, or in the form of [[stock options]] or [[shares]] in an enterprise.
*''method of hiring'': the worker might engage in a labour-contract on his own initiative, or he might hire out his labour as part of a group. But he may also hire out his labour via an intermediary (such as an employment agency) to a third party. In this case, he is paid by the intermediary, but works for a third party which pays the intermediary. In some cases, labour is [[subcontracting|subcontracted]] several times, with several intermediaries. Another possibility is that the worker is assigned or posted to a job by a political authority, or that an agency hires out a worker to an enterprise ''together'' with [[means of production]].

==Criticisms==
The first point of criticism is on the freedom of the worker. Wage-labour societies emerged from removing the alternative means of self-sustainment used previously by peasants. Historically, whenever people had their own land to cultivate—as was the case for most of the population in pre-industrial England, colonial Kenya,&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Elkins|2005|loc=Chapter 1.}}&lt;/ref&gt; colonial Australia, or colonial Namibia&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Olusoga|Erichsen|2011|pp=100–1.}}&lt;/ref&gt;—they did not commit to work for an employer. In such cases, laws were promulgated to expel peasants from their lands, and to make the price of the land artificially high so that a common person would have to work an entire lifetime to buy it.

The second point of criticism is that after people have been compelled by economic necessity to no feasible alternative than that of wage labour, [[exploitation]] occurs; thus the claim that wage labor is &quot;voluntary&quot; on the part of the labourer is considered a [[red herring]] as the relationship is only entered into due to systemic coercion brought about by the [[inequality of bargaining power]] between labor and capital as classes.

Wage labour is often criticized as &quot;[[wage slavery]]&quot; by [[socialism|socialists]] and most [[anarchism|anarchists]]. They see wage labour as a major, if not defining, aspect of hierarchical industrial systems. In [[Marxist theory|Marxist terminology]], wage labour is defined as &quot;the '''[[mode of production]]''' where the worker sells their '''[[labour power]]''' as a [[commodity]]&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[[Karl Marx|Marx, Karl]]. ''Wage Labour and Capital''&lt;/ref&gt; and a wage labourer is one who sells their labour power.

Some opponents of capitalism compare wage labour to slavery (see [[wage slavery]]). For example, [[Karl Marx]] said ''&quot;The slave, together with his labour-power, was sold to his owner once for all... The [wage] labourer, on the other hand, sells his very self, and that by fractions... He [belongs] to the capitalist class; and it is for him... to find a buyer in this capitalist class.&quot;''

While most opponents of wage labor blame the capitalist owners of the means of production for its existence, most [[anarchists]] and [[libertarian socialists]] also hold the state as equally responsible as it exists as a tool utilized by capitalists to subsidize themselves and protect the institution of [[privatism|private ownership of the means of production]]—which guarantees the concentration of capital among a wealthy elite leaving the majority of the population without access. As some opponents of wage labor take influence from Marxist propositions, many are opposed to [[private property]], but maintain respect for [[personal property]].

Most opponents of the institution support [[worker self-management]] and [[economic democracy]] as alternatives to both wage-labor and to capitalism.

==See also==
*[[Anarcho-Syndicalism]]
*[[Capitalist mode of production]]
*[[Child labour]]
*[[Eight-hour day]]
*[[Full Employment]]
*[[Immiseration thesis]]
*[[Labour (economics)]]
*[[Labour theory of value]]
*[[Marx's theory of alienation]]
*[[Marxian economics]]
*[[Reserve army of labour]]
*[[Rate of exploitation]]
*[[Surplus value]]
*[[Unfree labour]]
*[[Working poor]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==Bibliography==
*{{citation
 |last1=Deakin |first1=Simon |last2=Wilkinson |first2=Frank
 |year=2005
 |title=The Law of the Labour Market: Industrialization, Employment, and Legal Evolution
 |location=Oxford |publisher=University Press |isbn=978-0-19-815281-1
 |url=http://ukcatalogue.oup.com/product/9780198152811.do }}
*{{citation
 |last=Elkins |first=Caroline
 |year=2005
 |title=Britain's Gulag: The Brutal End of Empire in Kenya
 |location=London |publisher=Pimlico |isbn= }}
*{{citation
 |last1=Olusoga |first1=David |last2=Erichsen |first2=Casper W
 |year=2011 |origyear=2010
 |title=The Kaiser's Holocaust: Germany's Forgotten Genocide
 |location=London |publisher=Faber and Faber |isbn=978-0-571-23142-3 }}
*{{citation
 |last=Marx |first=Karl
 |year=1847
 |title=Wage Labour and Capital
 |url=http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1847/wage-labour/ }}

==External links==
*{{cite book | first = Richard | last = Barbrook  | year = 2006 | title = The Class of the New | edition = paperback | publisher = OpenMute | location = London | isbn = 0-9550664-7-6 | url = http://www.theclassofthenew.net}}
* [http://laborfair.com/resources.php LaborFair Resources] - Link to Fair Labor Practices

{{Employment}}

[[Category:Capitalism]]
[[Category:Labor economics]]
[[Category:Marxist theory]]
[[Category:Socialism]]
[[Category:Sociology index]]

[[de:Lohnarbeit]]
[[es:Mano de obra asalariada]]
[[fr:Salariat]]
[[it:Lavoro subordinato]]
[[la:Laborator]]
[[nl:Loonarbeid]]
[[ja:賃労働]]
[[no:Lønnsarbeid]]
[[pt:Trabalho assalariado]]
[[sv:Förvärvsarbete]]
[[vi:Tiền công lao động]]</text>
      <sha1>8xfqtrqp7t0si24h7t33ujojueatrbk</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
