<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>War</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>33158</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522412743</id>
      <parentid>522360561</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-11T01:23:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Srich32977</username>
        <id>8372814</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/Radamanf|Radamanf]] ([[User talk:Radamanf|talk]]): Unhelpful, unencyclopedic, promotion of POV. Please do not add again. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="101396">{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2012}}
{{About|war in general||War (disambiguation)|and|The War (disambiguation)}}
{{War}}'''War''' is an organized, armed, and, often, a prolonged conflict that is carried on between [[State (polity)|states]], [[nation]]s, or other parties typified by extreme [[aggression]], [[Society|social]] disruption, and usually high mortality.&lt;ref name=AHD&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thefreedictionary.com/War |title=American Heritage Dictionary: War |publisher=Thefreedictionary.com |accessdate=2011-01-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=MWD&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/war |title=Merriam Webster's Dictionary: War |publisher=Merriam-Webster |date=13 August 2010 |accessdate=2011-01-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; War should be understood as an actual, intentional and widespread armed conflict between political communities, and therefore is defined as a form of [[political violence]].&lt;ref name=AHD /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/war/ |title=Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy}}&lt;/ref&gt; The set of techniques used by a group to carry out war is known as '''warfare'''. An absence of war (and other violence) is usually called [[peace]].

In 2003, Nobel Laureate [[Richard E. Smalley]] identified war as the sixth (of ten) biggest problem facing the society of mankind for the next fifty years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Smalley Institute Grand Challenges |first=Richard E. |last=Smalley |publisher=[[Rice University]] |year=2008 |accessdate=24 April 2011 |url=http://cnst.rice.edu/content.aspx?id=246}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1832 [[treatise]] ''[[On War]]'', Prussian military general and theoretician [[Carl von Clausewitz]] defined war as follows: &quot;War is thus an act of force to compel our enemy to do our will.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1= Clausewitz|first1= Carl von|authorlink1= Carl Von Clausewitz|editor1-first= Michael|editor1-last= Howard|editor1-link=Peter Paret|editor2-first= Peter|editor2-last= Paret |title= On War|trans_title= Vom Krieg |edition= Indexed |year= 1984 |origyear= 1832|publisher= Princeton University Press|location= New Jersey |isbn= 978-0-691-01854-6|page= 75}} Italics in original.&lt;/ref&gt;

While some scholars see warfare as an inescapable and integral aspect of human culture, others argue that it is only inevitable under certain socio-cultural or ecological circumstances. Some scholars argue that the practice of war is not linked to any single type of political organization or society. Rather, as discussed by [[John Keegan]] in his ''History of Warfare'', war is a universal phenomenon whose form and scope is defined by the society that wages it.&lt;ref&gt;Keegan, John, (1901) ''A History of Warfare'', (Pimlico)&lt;/ref&gt; Another argument suggests that since there are human societies in which warfare does not exist, humans may not be naturally disposed for warfare, which emerges under particular circumstances.&lt;ref&gt;Societies at Peace (Howell and Willis 1989)&lt;/ref&gt; The ever changing technologies and potentials of war extend along a historical continuum. At the one end lies the [[endemic warfare]] of the [[Paleolithic]]{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}} with its stones and clubs, and the naturally limited loss of life associated with the use of such weapons. Found at the other end of this continuum is [[nuclear warfare]], along with the recently developed possible outcome of its use, namely the potential risk of the complete [[human extinction|extinction of the human species]].

==Etymology==
[[File:Gari-Melchers-War-Highsmith.jpeg|thumb|right|350px|Mural of War (1896), by [[Gari Melchers]].]]
The English word ''war'' derives from the late [[Old English]] (c.1050) words ''wyrre'' and ''werre''; the [[Old French|Old North French]] ''werre''; the [[Franks|Frankish]] ''werra''; and the [[Proto-Germanic language|Proto-Germanic]] ''werso''. The denotation of ''war'' derives from the [[Old Saxon]] ''werran'', [[Old High German]] ''werran'', and the German ''verwirren'': “to confuse”, “to perplex”, and “to bring into confusion”.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=war |publisher=Online Etymology Dictionary |url=http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=war |year=2010 |accessdate=24 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another posited derivation is from the [[Ancient Greek]] ''barbaros'', the [[Old Persian]] ''varhara'', and the Sanskrit ''varvar'' and ''barbara''. In German, the equivalent is ''Krieg''; the equivalent Spanish, [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]], and Italian words for &quot;war&quot; is ''guerra'', derived from the Germanic ''werra'' (“fight”, “tumult”).&lt;ref&gt;''Diccionario de la Lengua Española'', 21&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt; edición (1992) p. 1071&lt;/ref&gt; Etymologic legend has it that the Romanic peoples adopted a foreign, Germanic word for &quot;war&quot;, to avoid using the [[Latin]] ''bellum'', because, when sounded, it tended to merge with the sound of the word ''bello'' (&quot;beautiful&quot;)

==History of warfare==
{{Main|History of war}}
Before the dawn of civilization, war likely consisted of small-scale raiding. One half of the people found in a [[Nubia]]n cemetery dating to as early as 12,000 years ago had died of violence.&lt;ref name=&quot;Keeley&quot;&gt;Keeley: ''War before civilization: The myth of the peaceful savage''&lt;/ref&gt; Since the rise of the [[State (polity)|state]] some 5,000 years ago,&lt;ref&gt;Diamond, Jared, Guns, Germs and Steel&lt;/ref&gt; military activity has occurred over much of the globe. The advent of [[gunpowder]] and the acceleration of technological advances led to modern warfare. According to Conway W. Henderson, &quot;One source claims 14,500 wars have taken place between 3500 BC and the late 20th century, costing 3.5 billion lives, leaving only 300 years of peace (Beer 1981: 20).&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Conway W. Henderson|title=Understanding International Law|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=AwMovLqKw2oC&amp;pg=PA212|accessdate=31 May 2012|date=9 February 2010|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons|isbn=978-1-4051-9764-9|pages=212–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''[[War Before Civilization]]'', Lawrence H. Keeley, a professor at the [[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign|University of Illinois]], says that approximately 90–95% of known societies throughout history engaged in at least occasional warfare,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://brneurosci.org/reviews/war.html |title=Review: War Before Civilization |publisher=Brneurosci.org |date=4 September 2006 |accessdate=2011-01-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; and many fought constantly.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.atimes.com/atimes/Front_Page/HG04Aa02.html|title=The fraud of primitive authenticity|last=Spengler|date=4 July 2006|work=Asia Times Online|accessdate=2009-06-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:War deaths caused by warfare.svg|thumb|right|300px|The percentages of men killed in war in eight tribal societies, and Europe and the U.S. in the 20th century. (Lawrence H. Keeley, Archeologist)]]
Keeley explained several styles of primitive combat such as, small raids, large raids, and massacres. All of these forms of warfare were perpetrated by primitive societies. The use of the massacre by pre-state societies can be exhibited by the [[Dogrib people|Dogrib]] tribes of the subarctic in North America. The Dogrib tribe eventually destroyed the Yellowknife tribe by killing 4 men, 13 women, and 17 children which accounted for 20 percent of the population.&lt;ref name=&quot;Keeley&quot;/&gt; This was a devastating blow from which the Yellowknife tribe never recovered. Keeley further explains how small raids are not organized due to the lack of leadership and any formal training. This causes raids to be short and quick with relatively low numerical casualties but may significantly damage a percentage of a population. The deficit of resources also can account for a lack of fortifications and defensive structures in primitive prestate societies. The protection provided by a defensive could not justify the valuable resources used and labor implemented to build it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Keeley&quot;/&gt;

[[William Rubinstein]] wrote that &quot;Pre-literate societies, even those organised in a relatively advanced way, were renowned for their studied cruelty ... 'archaeology yields evidence of prehistoric massacres more severe than any recounted in ethnography [ie, after the coming of the Europeans]'. At [[Crow Creek massacre|Crow Creek]], South Dakota, as noted, archaeologists found a [[mass grave]] of 'more than 500 men, women, and children who had been slaughtered, scalped, and mutilated during an attack on their village a century and a half before Columbus's arrival (ca. AD 1325)' &quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=W. D. Rubinstein|title=Genocide: A History|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=nMMAk4VwLLwC&amp;pg=PA22|accessdate=31 May 2012|year=2004|publisher=Pearson Longman|isbn=978-0-582-50601-5|pages=22–50}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Western Europe, since the late 18th century, more than 150 conflicts and about 600 battles have taken place.&lt;ref name=War&gt;[http://www.ralphmag.org/CG/world-war-one2.html World War One – A New Kind of War | Part II], From ''14 – 18 Understanding the Great War'', by Stéphane Audoin-Rouzeau, Annette Becker&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:MokoShuraiE-Kotoba IV.jpg|thumb|250px|Japanese [[samurai]] attacking a [[Mongol Empire|Mongol]] ship, 13th century]]
The [[Human Security Report 2005]] documented a significant decline in the number and severity of armed conflicts since the end of the [[Cold War]] in the early 1990s. However, the evidence examined in the 2008 edition of the Center for International Development and Conflict Management's &quot;Peace and Conflict&quot; study indicated that the overall decline in conflicts had stalled.&lt;ref&gt;Hewitt, Joseph, J. Wilkenfield and T. nevertheless the concept war is more than just a word but a signification to the meaning Death. Gurr ''[http://www.cidcm.umd.edu/pc/ Peace and Conflict 2008]'', Paradigm Publishers, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

Recent rapid increases in the technologies of war, and therefore in its destructiveness (see [[Mutual assured destruction]]), have caused widespread public concern, and have in all probability forestalled, and may hopefully altogether prevent the outbreak of a nuclear World War III. At the end of each of the last two World Wars, concerted and popular efforts were made to come to a greater understanding of the underlying dynamics of war and to thereby hopefully reduce or even eliminate it all together. These efforts materialized in the forms of the [[League of Nations]], and its successor, the United Nations.

Shortly after [[World War II]], as a token of support for this concept, most nations joined the United Nations. During this same post-war period, with the aim of further delegitimizing war as an acceptable and logical extension of foreign policy{{Citation needed|date=April 2011}}, most national governments also renamed their Ministries or Departments of War as their Ministries or Departments of Defense, for example, the former US Department of War was renamed as the [[US Department of Defense]].

In 1947, in view of the rapidly increasingly destructive consequences of modern warfare, and with a particular concern for the consequences and costs of the newly developed [[atom bomb]], [[Albert Einstein]] famously stated, &quot;I know not with what weapons World War III will be fought, but World War IV will be fought with sticks and stones.&quot;&lt;ref name = &quot;EinsteinWWIV&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| year = 1947
| url = http://www.wagingpeace.org/menu/action/urgent-actions/einstein/
| title= Albert Einstein: Man of Imagination
| accessdate = 2010-02-03}} Nuclear Age Peace Foundation paper
&lt;/ref&gt;
Fortunately, the anticipated costs of a possible third world war are currently no longer deemed as acceptable by most, thus little motivation currently seems to exist on an international level for such a war.

Still since the close of World War II, limited non-nuclear conflicts continue, and surprisingly enough, some outspoken celebrities and politicians have even advocated for the proclamation of another world war.&lt;ref name = &quot;NewsCommentators&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| year = 2006
| url = http://mediamatters.org/research/200607140017
| title= Right-wing media divided: Is U.S. now in World War III, IV, or V?
| accessdate = 2010-02-04}} Discussion of attempts to proclaim World Wars III, IV and V
&lt;/ref&gt; [[Mao Zedong]] urged the socialist camp not to fear nuclear war with the United States since, even if &quot;half of mankind died, the other half would remain while imperialism would be razed to the ground and the whole world would become socialist.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,946612-2,00.html Instant Wisdom: Beyond the Little Red Book]&quot;. ''Time''. 20 September 1976.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;gallery perrow=&quot;7&quot;&gt;
File:Greek-Persian duel.jpg|Greek [[hoplite]] and Persian warrior depicted fighting, on an ancient kylix, 5th century BC
File:MS Ghent - Battle of Tewkesbury.jpg|The ''[[Battle of Tewkesbury]]'' (1471) during the [[Wars of the Roses]] in England
File:Schwäbischer Bund Luzerner Schilling.jpg|A cattle raid during the [[Swabian War]] ([[Luzerner Schilling]])
File:Battle of Ravenna (1512).JPG|The ''[[Battle of Ravenna (1512)|Battle of Ravenna]]'', in which France defeated the Spaniards on Easter Sunday in 1512
File:Bad-war.jpg|[[Swiss mercenaries|Swiss]] and [[Landsknecht]] pikemen fight at &quot;[[push of pike]]&quot; during the [[Italian Wars]]
File:Battle of Orsha (1514-09-08).jpg|Russo-Polish war, ''[[Battle of Orsha]]'' in 1514
File:Battle of Lepanto 1571.jpg|The Spanish naval victory of the ''[[Battle of Lepanto (1571)|Battle of Lepanto]]'', 1571, the last battle to be fought primarily between [[galley]]s
File:Schlacht am Weißen Berg C-K 063.jpg|''[[Battle of White Mountain]]'', 1620, an early battle in the [[Thirty Years' War]]
File:Van Soest, Four Days Battle.jpg|''The [[Four Days' Battle]], 1–4 June 1666'', during the [[Second Anglo–Dutch War]]
File:Marten's Poltava.jpg|The ''[[Battle of Poltava]]'' (1709), a decisive battle between Russian and Swedish troops
File:Charge of the French Cuirassiers at Waterloo.jpg|Depicting French Cuirassiers charging onto the British squares during the ''[[Battle of Waterloo]]''
File:Inkermann.jpg|The [[Lancashire Fusiliers|20th Foot]] at the ''[[Battle of Inkerman]]'', Crimean War, 1854
File:Battle of Fort Fisher.jpg|American Civil War, [[Union (American Civil War)|Union]] captures [[Fort Fisher]], 1865
File:Crossingtherhine.jpg|US Army's [[89th Infantry Division (United States)|89th Infantry Division]] [[Operation Plunder|cross the Rhine River]] in assault boats, 1945
&lt;/gallery&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

==Ten largest wars (by death toll)==
{{Main|List of wars by death toll}}
Three of the ten most costly wars, in terms of loss of life, have been waged in the last century. These are of course the two World Wars, then followed by the [[Second Sino-Japanese War]] (which is sometimes considered part of [[World War II]], or overlapping with that war). Most of the others involved China or neighboring peoples. The death toll of World War II, being 60 million plus, surpasses all other war-death-tolls by a factor of two. This may be due to significant recent advances in weapons technologies, as well as recent increases in the overall human population.

{| class=wikitable
! Deaths&lt;br&gt;(millions)
! Date
! War
|-
| 60–72 || 1939–1945 || [[World War II]] (see [[World War II casualties]])&lt;ref&gt;Wallinsky, David: ''David Wallechinsky's Twentieth Century: History With the Boring Parts Left Out'', Little Brown &amp; Co., 1996, ISBN 0-316-92056-8, ISBN 978-0-316-92056-8 – cited by [http://users.erols.com/mwhite28/warstat1.htm#Second White]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Brzezinski, Zbigniew: ''Out of Control: Global Turmoil on the Eve of the Twenty-first Century'', Prentice Hall &amp; IBD, 1994, ASIN B000O8PVJI – cited by [http://users.erols.com/mwhite28/warstat1.htm#Second White]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 36 || 755–763 || [[An Shi Rebellion]]  (number exaggerated based on census system,but not considering the territorial shrink and inefficient census system afterwar）&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://users.erols.com/mwhite28/warstat0.htm#AnLushan |title=Selected Death Tolls for Wars, Massacres and Atrocities Before the 20th Century |publisher=Users.erols.com |accessdate=2011-01-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 30–60 || 13th century || [[Mongol Empire|Mongol Conquests]] (see [[Mongol Conquests|Mongol invasions]] and [[Tatar invasions]])&lt;ref&gt;Ping-ti Ho, &quot;An Estimate of the Total Population of Sung-Chin China&quot;, in ''Études Song'', Series 1, No 1, (1970) pp. 33–53.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://users.erols.com/mwhite28/warstat0.htm#Mongol |title=Mongol Conquests |publisher=Users.erols.com |accessdate=2011-01-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1510/is_1987_Fall/ai_5151514/pg_2 |title=The world's worst massacres Whole Earth Review |publisher=Findarticles.com |accessdate=2011-01-24 |year=1987}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- 25 || 1616–1662 || [[Qing dynasty]] conquest of [[Ming Dynasty|Ming dynasty]]&lt;ref&gt;McFarlane, Alan: ''The Savage Wars of Peace: England, Japan and the Malthusian Trap'', Blackwell 2003, ISBN 0-631-18117-2,
ISBN 978-0-631-18117-0 – cited by [http://users.erols.com/mwhite28/warstat0.htm#Manchu17c White]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 20 || 1914–1918 ||[[World War I]]  (see [[World War I casualties]])&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= Michael Duffy |url=http://www.firstworldwar.com/features/casualties.htm |title=Military Casualties of World War One |publisher=Firstworldwar.com |date=22 August 2009 |accessdate=2011-01-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 20 || 1850–1864 || [[Taiping Rebellion]] (see [[Dungan revolt (1862–1877)|Dungan revolt]])&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://concise.britannica.com/ebc/article-9380148/Taiping |title=Taiping Rebellion – Britannica Concise |publisher=Britannica |accessdate=2011-01-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 20 || 1937–1945 || [[Second Sino-Japanese War]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/worldwars/wwtwo/nuclear_01.shtml |title=Nuclear Power: The End of the War Against Japan |publisher=BBC News |accessdate=2011-01-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 8–12 || 1862–1877 || [[Dungan revolt (1862–1877)|Dungan revolt]]
|-
| 7–20 || 1370–1405 || Conquests of [[Tamerlane]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://users.erols.com/mwhite28/warstat0.htm#Timur |title=Timur Lenk (1369–1405) |publisher=Users.erols.com |accessdate=2011-01-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Matthew's White's website (a compilation of scholarly estimates) -[http://users.erols.com/mwhite28/warstat0.htm#Asian Miscellaneous Oriental Atrocities]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 5–9 || 1917–1922 || [[Russian Civil War|Russian Civil War and Foreign Intervention]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.spartacus.schoolnet.co.uk/RUScivilwar.htm |title=Russian Civil War |publisher=Spartacus.schoolnet.co.uk |accessdate=2011-01-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

==Types of warfare==
{{Original research|section|date=January 2010}}
War, to become known as one, must entail some degree of confrontation using weapons and other [[military technology and equipment]] by armed forces employing [[military tactics]] and [[operational art]] within the broad [[military strategy]] subject to [[military logistics]]. [[War Studies]] by military theorists throughout [[military history]] have sought to identify the [[philosophy of war]], and to reduce it to a [[military science]].
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-H25224, Guernica, Ruinen.jpg|thumb|Ruins of [[Guernica]] (1937). The [[Spanish civil war]] was one of Europe's bloodiest and most brutal civil wars.]]
In general, modern military science considers several factors before a [[Defence policy|National defence policy]] is created to allow a war to commence: the environment in the area(s) of combat operations, the posture national forces will adopt on the commencement of a war, and the type of warfare troops will be engaged in.

[[Conventional warfare]] is an attempt to reduce an opponent's military capability through open battle. It is a declared war between existing states in which nuclear, biological, or chemical weapons are not used or only see limited deployment in support of conventional military goals and maneuvers.

The opposite of conventional warfare, [[unconventional warfare]], is an attempt to achieve military victory through acquiescence, capitulation, or clandestine support for one side of an existing conflict.

[[Nuclear warfare]] is warfare in which [[nuclear weapon]]s are the primary, or a major, method of coercing the capitulation of the other side, as opposed to a supporting tactical or strategic role in a conventional conflict.

Civil war is a war where the forces in conflict belong to the same nation or political entity and are vying for control of or independence from that nation or political entity.

[[Asymmetric warfare]] is a conflict between two populations of drastically different levels of military capability or size. Asymmetric conflicts often result in [[Guerrilla warfare|guerrilla]] tactics being used to overcome the sometimes vast gaps in technology and force size.

Intentional air pollution in combat is one of a collection of techniques collectively called [[chemical warfare]]. Poison gas as a [[Chemical warfare|chemical weapon]] was principally used during [[World War I]], and resulted in an estimated 91,198 deaths and 1,205,655 injuries.{{Citation needed|date=June 2008}} Various treaties have sought to ban its further use. Non-lethal chemical weapons, such as [[tear gas]] and [[pepper spray]], are widely used, sometimes with deadly effect.

===Warfare environment===
The environment in which a war is fought has a significant impact on the type of combat which takes place, and can include within its area different types of terrain. This, in turn, means that soldiers have to be trained to fight in a specific types of environments and terrains that generally reflects troops' mobility and limitations.
===Types of warfare===
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
[[File:British Paratroops inside one of the C-47 transport aircraft.jpg|thumb|200px|British [[paratroopers]] inside one of the C-47 transport aircraft, September 1944]]
'''Warfare by objective''':
* [[Strategic defence|Defensive warfare]]
* [[Strategic offensive|Offensive warfare]]

'''Warfare by doctrine''':
* [[Attrition warfare]]/[[Fabian strategy|Fabian warfare]]
* [[Maneuver warfare]]
* [[Guerrilla warfare|Guerilla warfare]]
* [[Static warfare]]/[[Positional warfare]]
* [[Insurgency]] warfare
* [[Counterinsurgency]] warfare
[[File:Marine-raiders.jpg|thumb|200px|U.S. [[Marine Raiders]] gathered in front of a Japanese dugout, January 1944]]
'''Warfare by terrain''':
* [[Jungle warfare]]
* [[Desert warfare]]
* [[Mountain warfare]]
* [[Arctic warfare]]
* [[Naval warfare]]
* [[Littoral warfare]]
* [[Urban warfare]]
* [[Amphibious Warfare]]
{{col-end}}

===Behaviour and conduct in war===
{{rquote|right|The nature of warfare ''never'' changes, only its superficial manifestations. [[Joshua]] and [[David]], [[Hector]] and [[Achilles]] would recognize the combat that our soldiers and Marines have waged in the alleys of Somalia and Iraq. The uniforms evolve, bronze gives way to titanium, arrows may be replaced by laser-guided bombs, but the heart of the matter is still killing your enemies until any survivors surrender and do your will.|[[Ralph Peters]]&lt;ref&gt;Peters, Ralph. ''New Glory: Expanding America's Global Supremacy'', 2005. p. 30&lt;/ref&gt;}}
The behaviour of troops in warfare varies considerably, both individually and as units or armies. In some circumstances, troops may engage in [[genocide]], [[war rape]] and [[ethnic cleansing]]. Commonly, however, the conduct of troops may be limited to posturing and sham attacks, leading to highly rule-bound and often largely symbolic combat in which casualties are much reduced from that which would be expected if soldiers were genuinely violent towards the enemy.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1996&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Lt. Col. Dave Grossman|title=On Killing – The Psychological Cost of Learning to Kill in War &amp; Society|publisher= Little, Brown &amp; Co., |year=1996}}&lt;/ref&gt; Situations of deliberate dampening of hostilities occurred in [[World War I]] by some accounts, e.g., a volley of gunfire being exchanged after a misplaced mortar hit the British line, after which a German soldier shouted an apology to British forces, effectively stopping a hostile exchange of gunfire.&lt;ref&gt;Axelrod, Robert. 1984. ''The Evolution of Cooperation.'' New York: Basic Books.&lt;/ref&gt; Other examples of non-aggression, also from [[World War I]], are detailed in &quot;[[Good-Bye to All That]].&quot; These include spontaneous ceasefires to rebuild defences and retrieve casualties, alongside behaviour such as refusing to shoot at enemy during ablutions and the taking of great risks (described as 1 in 20) to retrieve enemy wounded from the battlefield. The most notable spontaneous ceasefire of [[World War I]] was the [[Christmas truce]].

The psychological separation between combatants, and the destructive power of modern weaponry, may act to override this effect and facilitate participation by combatants in the mass slaughter of combatants or civilians, such as in the bombing of [[Bombing of Dresden in World War II|Dresden in World War II]].{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}} The unusual circumstances of warfare can incite apparently normal individuals to commit atrocities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Waller|first=James|title=Becoming Evil: How Ordinary People Commit Genocide and Mass Killing}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Effects of war==
{{Quote|Nations customarily measure the ‘costs of war’ in dollars, lost production, or the number of soldiers killed or wounded. Rarely do military establishments attempt to measure the costs of war in terms of individual human suffering. Psychiatric breakdown remains one of the most costly items of war when expressed in human terms.|''No More Heroes'', Richard Gabriel&lt;ref name=War/&gt;}}

[[File:War world map - DALY - WHO2004.svg|thumb|200px|[[Disability-adjusted life year]] for war per 100,000&amp;nbsp;inhabitants in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.who.int/entity/healthinfo/global_burden_disease/gbddeathdalycountryestimates2004.xls |title=Mortality and Burden of Disease Estimates for WHO Member States in 2004 |work=World Health Organization }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;references-small&quot; style=&quot;-moz-column-count:3; column-count:3;&quot;&gt;
{{legend|#b3b3b3|no data}}
{{legend|#ffff65|less than 100}}
{{legend|#fff200|100–200}}
{{legend|#ffdc00|200–600}}
{{legend|#ffc600|600–1000}}
{{legend|#ffb000|1000–1400}}
{{legend|#ff9a00|1400–1800}}
{{legend|#ff8400|1800–2200}}
{{legend|#ff6e00|2200–2600}}
{{legend|#ff5800|2600–3000}}
{{legend|#ff4200|3000–8000}}
{{legend|#ff2c00|8000–8800}}
{{legend|#cb0000|more than 8800}}
&lt;/div&gt;]]

[[File:800px-Apotheosis.jpg|thumb|300px|''The Apotheosis of War'' (1871) by [[Vasily Vereshchagin]]]]

===On soldiers===
Soldiers subject to combat in war often suffer psychological and physical casualties, including depression, [[Post Traumatic Stress Disorder]], disease, injury, and death.

{{Quote|In every war in which American soldiers have fought in, the chances of becoming a psychiatric casualty – of being debilitated for some period of time as a consequence of the stresses of military life – were greater than the chances of being killed by enemy fire.|''No More Heroes'', Richard Gabriel&lt;ref name=War/&gt;}}

During World War II, research conducted by US Army Brigadier General S.L.A. Marshall found that, on average, only 15% to 20% of American riflemen in WWII combat fired at the enemy.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1996&quot;/&gt; In Civil War Collector’s Encyclopedia, F.A. Lord notes that of the 27,574 discarded muskets found on the Gettysburg battlefield, nearly 90% were loaded, with 12,000 loaded more than once and 6,000 loaded 3 to 10 times. These studies suggest that most soldiers resist firing their weapons in combat, that – as some theorists argue – human beings have an inherent resistance to killing their fellow human beings.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1996&quot;/&gt; Swank and Marchand’s WWII study found that after sixty days of continuous combat, 98% of all surviving soldiers will become psychiatric casualties. Psychiatric casualties manifest themselves in fatigue cases, confusional states, conversion hysteria, anxiety, obsessional and compulsive states, and character disorders.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1996&quot;/&gt;

{{Quote|One-tenth of mobilised American men were hospitalised for mental disturbances between 1942 and 1945, and after thirty-five days of uninterrupted combat, 98% of them manifested psychiatric disturbances in varying degrees.|''14–18: Understanding the Great War'', Stéphane Audoin-Rouzeau, Annette Becker&lt;ref name=War/&gt;}}

Additionally, it has been estimated that anywhere from 18% to 54% of Vietnam war veterans suffered from [[Post Traumatic Stress Disorder]].&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1996&quot;/&gt;

Based on 1860 census figures, 8% of all white American males aged 13 to 43 died in the [[American Civil War]], including about 6% in the North and approximately 18% in the South.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Maris Vinovskis|title=Toward a Social History of the American Civil War: Exploratory Essays|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=9D4TAwc93VoC|accessdate=31 May 2012|date=28 September 1990|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-0-521-39559-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; The war remains the deadliest conflict in American history, resulting in the deaths of 620,000 soldiers. [[United States military casualties of war]] since 1775 have totaled over two million. Of the 60 million European soldiers who were mobilized in [[World War I]], 8 million were killed, 7 million were permanently disabled, and 15 million were seriously injured.&lt;ref&gt;Kitchen, Martin (2000), ''[http://www.jimmyatkinson.com/papers/versaillestreaty.html#endnotes The Treaty of Versailles and its Consequences]'', New York: Longman&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Goya-Guerra (32).jpg|thumb|200px|'' Why?'', from ''[[The Disasters of War]]'' (''Los desastres de la guerra''), by [[Francisco Goya]], 1812–15. A collection of depictions of the brutalities of the [[Peninsular War|Napoleonic-Peninsular War]].]]

During [[Napoleon I of France|Napoleon]]'s retreat from Moscow, more French soldiers died of [[typhus]] than were killed by the Russians.&lt;ref&gt;[http://entomology.montana.edu/historybug/TYPHUS-Conlon.pdf The Historical Impact of Epidemic Typhus]. Joseph M. Conlon.&lt;/ref&gt; Felix Markham thinks that 450,000 crossed the [[Neman River|Neman]] on 25 June 1812, of whom less than 40,000 recrossed in anything like a recognizable military formation.&lt;ref&gt;See a large copy of the chart here: http://www.adept-plm.com/Newsletter/NapoleonsMarch.htm, but discussed at length in Edward Tufte, ''The Visual Display of Quantitative Information'' (London: Graphics Press, 1992)&lt;/ref&gt; More soldiers were killed from 1500–1914 by typhus than from all military action during that time combined.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,794989,00.html War and Pestilence]. ''TIME''.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, if it were not for the modern medical advances there would be thousands of more dead from disease and infection. For instance, during the [[Seven Years' War]], the [[Royal Navy]] reported that it conscripted 184,899 sailors, of whom 133,708 died of disease or were 'missing'.&lt;ref&gt;A. S. Turberville (2006). ''Johnson's England: An Account of the Life &amp; Manners of His Age''. ISBN READ BOOKS. p.53. ISBN 1-4067-2726-1&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:The Hanging by Jacques Callot.jpg|right|thumb|200px|''[[Les Grandes Misères de la guerre]]'' depict the destruction unleashed on civilians during the [[Thirty Years' War]].]]

It is estimated that 378,000 people died due to war each year between 1985 and 1994.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Obermeyer Z, Murray CJ, Gakidou E |title=Fifty years of violent war deaths from Vietnam to Bosnia: analysis of data from the world health survey programme |journal=BMJ |volume=336 |issue=7659 |pages=1482–6 |year=2008 |month=June |pmid=18566045 |pmc=2440905 |doi=10.1136/bmj.a137 |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===On civilians===
{{see also|Civilian casualties}}

Many wars have been accompanied by significant depopulations, along with destruction of infrastructure and resources (which may lead to [[famine]], disease, and death in the civilian population). Civilians in war zones may also be subject to war atrocities such as [[genocide]], while survivors may suffer the psychological aftereffects of witnessing the destruction of war. During the [[Thirty Years' War]] in Europe, for example, the population of the [[Holy Roman Empire|German]] states was reduced by about 30%.&lt;ref&gt;[http://users.erols.com/mwhite28/warstat0.htm#30YrW The Thirty Years War (1618–48)], Alan McFarlane, The Savage Wars of Peace: England, Japan and the Malthusian Trap (2003)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/195896/history-of-Europe/58335/Demographics#ref=ref310375 History of Europe – Demographics]. Encyclopædia Britannica.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Swedish Empire|Swedish]] armies alone may have destroyed up to 2,000 castles, 18,000 villages and 1,500 towns in Germany, one-third of all German towns.&lt;ref name=&quot;Population-HLS&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.historylearningsite.co.uk/population_thirty_years_war.htm|title=Population|publisher=History Learningsite|accessdate=2008-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Estimates for the total [[World War II casualties|casualties of World War II]] vary, but most suggest that some 60 million people died in the war, comprising around 20 million soldiers and 40 million civilians.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=World War II Fatalities|url=http://www.secondworldwar.co.uk/casualty.html|accessdate=2007-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Soviet Union]] lost around [[World War II casualties of the Soviet Union|27 million people]] during the war, about half of all World War II casualties.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4530565.stm|title=Leaders mourn Soviet wartime dead | date=9 May 2005 | accessdate=6 January 2010|work=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since a high proportion of those killed were young men, the postwar Soviet population was 45 to 50 million fewer than post–1939 projections would have led one to expect.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Geoffrey A. Hosking|title=Rulers And Victims: The Russians in the Soviet Union|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=CDMVMqDvp4QC&amp;pg=PA242|accessdate=31 May 2012|year=2006|publisher=Harvard University Press|isbn=978-0-674-02178-5|pages=242–}}&lt;/ref&gt; The largest number of civilian deaths in a single city was 1.2 million citizens dead during the 872-day [[Siege of Leningrad]].

===On the economy===
{{see also|Military keynesianism}}

Once a war has ended, losing nations are sometimes required to pay [[war reparations]] to the victorious nations. In certain cases, land is ceded to the victorious nations. For example, the territory of [[Alsace-Lorraine]] has been traded between France and Germany on three different occasions.

Typically speaking, war becomes very intertwined with the economy and many wars are partially or entirely based on economic reasons such as the [[American Civil War]]. In some cases war has stimulated a country's economy (World War II is often credited with bringing America out of the [[Great Depression]]) but in many cases, such as the wars of Louis XIV, the [[Franco-Prussian War]], and [[World War I]], warfare serves only to damage the economy of the countries involved. For example, Russia's involvement in World War I took such a toll on the Russian economy that it almost collapsed and greatly contributed to the start of the [[Russian Revolution of 1917]].

====World War II====
One of the starkest illustrations of the effect of war upon economies is the [[Second World War]]. The [[Great Depression]] of the 1930s ended as nations increased their production of war materials to serve the [[war effort]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://memory.loc.gov/learn/features/timeline/depwwii/depwar.html Great Depression and World War II]. ''The Library of Congress''.&lt;/ref&gt; The financial cost of World War II is estimated at about a trillion U.S. dollars worldwide,&lt;ref&gt;Mayer, E. (2000) [http://emayzine.com/lectures/WWII.html &quot;World War II&quot;] course lecture notes on ''Emayzine.com'' (Victorville, California: Victor Valley College)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Coleman, P. (1999) [http://replay.web.archive.org/20080302153205/http://members.aol.com/forcountry/ww2/wc1.htm &quot;Cost of the War,&quot;] ''World War II Resource Guide'' (Gardena, California: The American War Library)&lt;/ref&gt; making it the most costly war in capital as well as lives.

By the end of the war, the European economy had collapsed with 70% of the industrial infrastructure destroyed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Marc Pilisuk|author2=Jennifer Achord Rountree|title=Who Benefits from Global Violence and War: Uncovering a Destructive System|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=r9kNZrmG0E8C&amp;pg=PA136|accessdate=31 May 2012|year=2008|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|isbn=978-0-275-99435-8|pages=136–}}&lt;/ref&gt; Property damage in the Soviet Union inflicted by the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Axis invasion]] was estimated to a value of 679 billion rubles. The combined damage consisted of complete or partial destruction of 1,710 cities and towns, 70,000 villages/hamlets, 2,508 church buildings, 31,850 industrial establishments, 40,000 miles of railroad, 4100 railroad stations, 40,000 hospitals, 84,000 schools, and 43,000 public libraries.&lt;ref&gt;''[[The New York Times]]'', 9 February 1946, Volume 95, Number 32158.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Factors ending a war==
{{Unreferenced section|date=June 2008}}

{{Original research|section|date=January 2010}}
[[File:Aftermath Battle of Triboltingen.jpg|thumb|Women and priests retrieve the dead bodies of Swabian soldiers just outside the city gates of Constance after the [[battle of Schwaderloh]]. ''([[Luzerner Schilling]])'']]
The political and economic circumstances, in the peace that follows war, usually depend on the [[facts on the ground]]. Where evenly matched adversaries decide that the conflict has resulted in a [[stalemate]], they may cease hostilities to avoid further loss of life and property. They may decide to restore the [[antebellum period|antebellum]] territorial boundaries, redraw boundaries at the line of military control, or negotiate to keep or exchange captured territory. Negotiations between parties involved at the end of a war often result in a [[treaty]], such as the [[Treaty of Versailles]] of 1919, which ended the [[First World War]].

A warring party that [[surrender (military)|surrenders]] or [[capitulation (surrender)|capitulates]] may have little negotiating power, with the victorious side either imposing a settlement or dictating most of the terms of any treaty. A common result is that conquered territory is brought under the dominion of the stronger military power. An [[unconditional surrender]] is made in the face of overwhelming military force as an attempt to prevent further harm to life and property. For example, the [[Empire of Japan]] gave an unconditional surrender to the [[Allies of World War II]] after the [[atomic bombings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki]] (see [[Surrender of Japan]]), the preceding massive strategic bombardment of Japan and declaration of war and the immediate invasion of Manchuria by the Soviet Union. A settlement or surrender may also be obtained through [[deception]] or bluffing.

Many other wars, however, have ended in complete destruction of the opposing territory, such as the [[Battle of Carthage (c. 149 BCE)|Battle of Carthage]] of the [[Third Punic War]] between the [[Phoenicia]]n city of [[Carthage]] and Ancient Rome in 149 BC. In 146 BC the Romans burned the city, enslaved its citizens, and razed the buildings.

Some wars or aggressive actions end when the military objective of the victorious side has been achieved. Others do not, especially in cases where the state structures do not exist, or have collapsed prior to the victory of the conqueror. In such cases, disorganised [[Guerrilla warfare|guerilla warfare]] may continue for a considerable period. In cases of complete surrender conquered territories may be brought under the permanent dominion of the victorious side. A raid for the purposes of [[looting]] may be completed with the successful capture of goods. In other cases an aggressor may decide to end hostilities to avoid continued losses and cease hostilities without obtaining the original objective, such as happened in the [[Iran–Iraq War]].

Some hostilities, such as [[insurgency]] or civil war, may persist for long periods of time with only a low level of military activity. In some cases there is no negotiation of any official treaty, but fighting may trail off and eventually stop after the political demands of the belligerent groups have been reconciled, a political settlement has been negotiated, the combatants are gradually killed or decide the conflict is futile, or the belligerents cease active military engagement but still threaten each other. An example is the [[Chinese Civil War]] which essentially ceased by 1950 but the People's Republic of China fought diplomatically to isolate Taiwan, but it still threatens [[Republic of China]] (commonly known as [[Taiwan]]) with an invasion. For this reason, some historians consider the war not ended but continuing.

==List of ongoing wars==
{{Main|List of ongoing conflicts}}

{{Incomplete|date=May 2011}}
Conflicts in the following list are currently causing at least 1,000 violent deaths per year, a categorization used by the [[Uppsala Conflict Data Program]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pcr.uu.se/research/ucdp/definitions/|title=Definitions Uppsala Conflict Data Program |accessdate=2009-05-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; and recognised by the United Nations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/world/war/index.html |publisher=[[GlobalSecurity.org]] |title=The World at War |accessdate=2008-05-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://ochaonline.un.org/humanitariannegotiations/Chapter1-2.htm#FNfour |title=Humanitarian Negotiations with Armed Groups, A Manual &amp; Guidelines for Practitioners |accessdate=2009-05-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; The UN also use the term &quot;[[low intensity conflict]],&quot; which can overlap with the 1,000 violent deaths per year categorisation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.startribune.com/nation/43815017.html?elr=KArks:DCiUMEaPc:UiacyKUUr |title=UN peacekeeping chief says Darfur 'a low-intensity conflict' with 150 deaths a month |accessdate=2009-05-07}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
! Start of conflict
! War/conflict
! Location
! Cumulative fatalities
! Fatalities in 2010/11
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1964
| [[Colombian armed conflict (1964–present)|Colombian Armed Conflict]]
| {{flag|Colombia}}
| {{ntsh|150000}} 150,000–200,000&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2011/nov/08/alfonso-cano-colombia-farc | location=London |work=The Guardian | first=Kristian | last=Herbolzheimer | title=After Alfonso Cano's death, Colombia must rethink its path to peace – Kristian Herbolzheimer | date=8 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| 1,000+&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.colombiareports.com/colombia-news/news/17441-military-claims-to-have-killed-3500-criminals-in-2011.html |title=Colombian military claims to have killed 3,500 criminals in 2011 – Colombia news |publisher=Colombia Reports |date=6 July 2011 |accessdate=2011-10-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| align=center | 1967
| [[Naxalite-Maoist insurgency]]
| {{flag|India}}
| ~11,200
| 1,174+&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/8529124.stm |work=BBC News | title=India's Maoists offer ceasefire | date=22 February 2010 | accessdate=2010-05-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| align=center | 1978
| [[Afghan Civil war]]
| {{flag|Afghanistan}}
| 600,000–2,000,000 {{Citation needed|date=November 2011}}
| 10,461+&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/breaking/2011/0116/breaking1.html] 2,412+ civilians, 711 foreign troops, 1,292 Afghan police, 821 Afghan soldiers and 5,225 insurgents kileld in 2010&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| align=center | 1991
| [[Somali Civil War]]
| {{flag|Somalia}}
| 300,000&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://users.erols.com/mwhite28/warstat3.htm |title=Twentieth Century Atlas – Death Tolls and Casualty Statistics for Wars, Dictatorships and Genocides |publisher=Users.erols.com |accessdate=2011-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;–400,000&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=John Pike |url=http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/library/news/2004/11/mil-041105-irin03.htm |title=Hundreds of thousands killed in years of war, says new president |publisher=Globalsecurity.org |date=5 November 2004 |accessdate=2011-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| 2,318+&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.irinnews.org/Report.aspx?ReportID=91267 |title=IRIN Africa &amp;#124; SOMALIA: Accusations traded over rising casualties at Mogadishu market &amp;#124; Human Rights |publisher=Irinnews.org |date=2 December 2010 |accessdate=2011-10-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| align=center | 2004
| [[War in North-West Pakistan]]
| {{flag|Pakistan}}
| 30,452&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vamban.com/global-war-on-terror-claims-30000-pakistani-casualties|title=Global War on Terror Claims 30,000 Pakistani Casualties}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| 7,435&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ploughshares.ca/content/pakistan-1992-first-combat-deaths |title=Pakistan (1992 – first combat deaths) &amp;#124; Project Ploughshares |publisher=Ploughshares.ca |date=30 April 2011 |accessdate=2011-10-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| align=center | 2004
| [[Shia Insurgency in Yemen]]
| {{flag|Yemen}} and {{flag|Saudi Arabia}}
| 25,000&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Barak A. Salmoni|author2=Bryce Loidolt|author3=Madeleine Wells|title=Regime and Periphery in Northern Yemen: The Huthi Phenomenon|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Sj81Eaxz-2kC|accessdate=31 May 2012|date=16 June 2010|publisher=Rand Corporation|isbn=978-0-8330-4933-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| 8,000
|-
| align=center | 2006
| [[Mexican Drug War]]
| {{flag|Mexico}}
| 39,392+&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-latin-america-10860614|title=Mexico says 28,000 killed in drugs war since 2006 |work=BBC News | date=4 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| 24,374&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.jornada.unam.mx/ultimas/2011/07/28/201721657-en-2010-hubo-24-mil-374-homicidios-en-mexico-inegi/ | work=INEGI | title=Durante 2010 hubo 24 mil 374 homicidios en México: La Jornada | date=28 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| align=center | 2009
| [[Sudanese nomadic conflicts]]
| {{flag|Sudan}}
| 2,000–2,500&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aljazeera.com/news/africa/2010/01/20101712175653198.html|title=Scores killed in Sudan tribal clash}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| 708
|-
| align=center | 2011
| [[Sudan–SPLM-N conflict (2011)|Sudan–SPLM-N conflict]]
| {{flag|Sudan}}
| 1,500+
| 1,500+ {{Citation needed|date=November 2011}}
|-
| align=center | 2011
| [[Syrian civil war]]
| {{flag|Syria}}
| 3,000+&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-15304741 |title=Syria uprising: UN says protest death toll hits 3,000 |publisher=BBC News|date=14 October 2011 |accessdate=2011-10-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| 3,000+
|}

==Efforts to stop wars==
[[File:1917 - Execution à Verdun lors des mutineries.jpg|thumb|Execution at Verdun at the time of the [[French Army Mutinies (1917)|mutinies]] of 1917, when parts of the French Army refused to conduct further offensive operations.]]
Anti-war movements have existed for every major war in the 20th century, including, most prominently, [[World War I]], [[World War II]], and the [[Vietnam War]]. In the 21st century, worldwide anti-war movements occurred ever since the United States declared wars in Afghanistan and Iraq. In 2001, the US government decided to invade Afghanistan to fight against international terrorism that caused the [[September 11 attacks]]. Protests [[Opposition to the War in Afghanistan (2001–present)|opposing the War in Afghanistan]] occurred in cities in Europe, Asia, and all over the United States. Organizations like [[Stop the War Coalition]], based in the United Kingdom, work on campaigning against the War. They raise awareness of the war, organize demonstrations, and lobby the governments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Stop the War Coalition: Timeline of Events 2001–2011 |unused_data=ur}}&lt;/ref&gt; There also exist significant worldwide [[opposition to the Iraq War]]. Critics oppose the war based on the argument of violation of sovereignty, absence of the UN approval, and perceived illegitimacy. 

The [[Mexican Drug War]], with estimated casualties of 40,000 since December 2006, has been recently facing a fundamental opposition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=How many have died in Mexico's drug war? |unused_data=ur}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2011, the movement for peace and justice has started a popular middle-class movement against the war. It has won the recognition of President Calderon, who started the war, but has not ended it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Calderon apologises to drug war victims |unused_data=ur}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Governments also use the method of [[disarmament]] to stop and prevent the cost of war.

==Theories for motivation==
There is no scholarly agreement on which are the most common motivations for war.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Levy|first=Jack S.|year=1989|title=The Causes of War: A Review of Theories and Evidence|journal=Behavior, Society and Nuclear War|volume=I|page=295|location=New York|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|editor1-first=Philip E.|editor1-last=Tetlock|editor2-first=Jo L.|editor2-last=Husbands|editor3-first=Robert|editor3-last=Jervis|editor4-first=Paul C.|editor4-last=Stern|editor5-first=Charles|editor5-last=Tilly|accessdate=4 May 2012|url=http://fas-polisci.rutgers.edu/levy/1989%20Causes%20of%20War.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; Motivations may be different for those ordering the war than for those undertaking the war. For example, in the [[Third Punic War]], Rome's leaders may have wished to make war with [[Carthage]] for the purpose of eliminating a resurgent rival, while the individual soldiers may have been motivated by a wish to make money. Since many people are involved, a war may acquire a life of its own from the confluence of many different motivations.

An interpretation of the ancient Jewish commentary (BeReshit Rabbah) on the fight between [[Cain and Abel]] in Genesis 4 (Parashot BeReshit XXII:7) states that there are three universal reasons for wars: A) Economics, B) Power, and C) Religion.&lt;ref name = &quot;MidrashQuote&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| year = 2008
| url = http://www.yutorah.org/lectures/lecture.cfm/728352/Rabbi_David_Horwitz/Parashat_Bereshit:_The_Conflict_between_Cain_and_Abel
| title= The Conflict between Cain and Abel
| accessdate = 2010-02-07}} Analysis of Midrash re: Cain &amp; Abel
&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Szigetvar 1566.jpg|thumb|200px|The [[List of campaigns of Suleiman the Magnificent|Ottoman campaign]] for territorial [[Ottoman wars in Europe|expansion in Europe]] in 1566, Crimean Tatars as vanguard. The Tatars essentially sought booty, especially [[Slavery in the Ottoman Empire|slaves]].]]
In ''Why Nations Go to War'', by [[John G. Stoessinger]], the author points out that both sides will claim that morality justifies their fight. He also states that the rationale for beginning a war depends on an overly optimistic assessment of the outcome of hostilities (casualties and costs), and on [[Fundamental attribution error|misperceptions of the enemy's intentions]].

As the strategic and tactical aspects of warfare are always changing, theories and doctrines relating to warfare are often reformulated before, during, and after every major war. [[Carl Von Clausewitz]] said, 'Every age had its own kind of war, its own limiting conditions, and its own peculiar preconceptions.'&lt;ref&gt;Clausewitz, Carl Von (1976), On War (Princeton University Press) p.593&lt;/ref&gt; The one constant factor is war’s employment of organized violence and the resultant destruction of property and/ or lives that necessarily follows.

===Psychoanalytic psychology===
Dutch psychoanalyst [[Joost Meerloo]] held that, &quot;War is often...a mass discharge of accumulated internal rage (where)...the inner fears of mankind are discharged in mass destruction.&quot;&lt;ref name = &quot;meerloo&quot;&gt;
| A. M. Meerloo, M.D. ''The Rape of the Mind'' (2009) p.134, Progressive Press, ISBN 978-1-61577-376-3
&lt;/ref&gt; Thus war can sometimes be a means by which man's own frustration at his inability to master his own self is expressed and temporarily relieved via his unleashing of destructive behavior upon ''others.'' In this destructive scenario, these ''others'' are made to serve as the scapegoat of man's own unspoken and subconscious frustrations and fears.

Other psychoanalysts such as E.F.M. Durban and [[John Bowlby]] have argued that human beings are [[Inheritance|inherently]] violent.&lt;ref&gt;Durbin, E.F.L. and John Bowlby. ''Personal Aggressiveness and War'' 1939.&lt;/ref&gt; This aggressiveness is fueled by [[displacement (psychology)|displacement]] and [[Psychological projection|projection]] where a person transfers his or her grievances into bias and hatred against other [[Race (classification of human beings)|races]], religions, nations or [[Ideology|ideologies]]. By this theory, the nation state preserves order in the local society while creating an outlet for aggression through warfare. If war is innate to human nature, as is presupposed and predetermined by many psychological theories, then there is little hope of ever escaping it.

The Italian psychoanalyst Franco Fornari, a follower of [[Melanie Klein]], thought that war was the paranoid or projective “elaboration” of mourning.&lt;ref&gt;(Fornari 1975)&lt;/ref&gt; Fornari thought that war and violence develop out of our “love need”: our wish to preserve and defend the sacred object to which we are attached, namely our early mother and our fusion with her. For the adult, nations are the sacred objects that generate warfare. Fornari focused upon sacrifice as the essence of war: the astonishing willingness of human beings to die for their country, to give over their bodies to their nation.

Despite Fornari's theory that man's altruistic desire for self-sacrifice for a noble cause is a contributing factor towards war, in history only a tiny fraction of wars have originated from a desire for war from the general populace.&lt;ref&gt;Blanning, T.C.W. &quot;The Origin of Great Wars.&quot; ''The Origins of the French Revolutionary Wars.'' pg. 5&lt;/ref&gt; Far more often the general population has been reluctantly drawn into war by its rulers. One psychological theory that looks at the leaders is advanced by Maurice Walsh.&lt;ref&gt;Walsh, Maurice N. ''War and the Human Race.'' 1971.&lt;/ref&gt; He argues that the general populace is more neutral towards war and that wars only occur when leaders with a psychologically abnormal disregard for human life are placed into power. War is caused by leaders that seek war such as [[Napoleon I of France|Napoleon]] and [[Adolf Hitler|Hitler]]. Such leaders most often come to power in times of crisis when the populace opts for a decisive leader, who then leads the nation to war.

{{Quotation|Naturally, the common people don't want war; neither in Russia nor in England nor in America, nor for that matter in Germany. That is understood. But, after all, it is the leaders of the country who determine the policy and it is always a simple matter to drag the people along, whether it is a democracy or a fascist dictatorship or a Parliament or a Communist dictatorship. ... the people can always be brought to the bidding of the leaders. That is easy. All you have to do is tell them they are being attacked and denounce the pacifists for lack of patriotism and exposing the country to danger. It works the same way in any country.|
[[Hermann Göring]] at the Nuremberg trials, April 18, 1946&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.snopes.com/quotes/goering.htm In an interview with Gilbert in Göring's jail cell during the Nuremberg War Crimes Trials (18 April 1946)]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Evolutionary ===
{{POV-section|date=October 2011}}
{{Disputed-section|date=October 2011}}
Several theories concern the evolutionary origins of warfare. There are two main schools: One sees organized warfare as emerging only in the mesolithic, as a result of the emergence of complex social organization, higher population density and political organization and competition over resources. The other school tends to see human warfare simply as an extension of animal behavior, such as territoriality and sexual competition.&lt;ref&gt;Peter Meyer. Social Evolution in Franz M. Wuketits and Christoph Antweiler (eds.) Handbook of Evolution The Evolution of Human Societies and Cultures Wiley-VCH Verlag&lt;/ref&gt;

This school argues that since organized warlike behavior patterns are also found in many other primate species such as [[chimpanzee]]s,&lt;ref name = &quot;ApesWar&quot;&gt;{{cite news
| url = http://www.telegraph.co.uk/science/science-news/3317461/Apes-of-war...-is-it-in-our-genes.html
| title= Apes of war...is it in our genes?
| accessdate = 2010-02-06
| location=London
| work=The Daily Telegraph
| first=Sanjida
| last=O'Connell
| date=7 January 2004}} Analysis of chimpanzee war behavior
&lt;/ref&gt;
as well as in many [[ant]] species,&lt;ref name = &quot;AntsLandmines&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
| year = 1996
| ssrn = 935783
| title= Warrior Ants: The Enduring Threat of the Small War and the Land-mine
}} Scholarly comparisons between human and ant wars
&lt;/ref&gt; this suggests that between group conflict is a general feature of animal social behavior. Biologists studying primate behavior have added to the debate, documenting warlike activities among several primate species and seeing similarities to humans.&lt;ref&gt;Crofoot, Margaret C. and Richard W. Wrangham, 2010 &quot;Intergroup Aggression in Primates and Humans: The Case for a Unified Theory&quot; in Kappeler, Thomas M &amp; Joan B Silk (eds) ''Mind the Gap – tracing the origins of human universals''. Springer.&lt;/ref&gt; Others argue that while war may be a natural phenomenon, the development of technology and complex social organization has accelerated the scale of warfare to exceptional levels among modern humans, starting at some point in the mesolithic, and escalating with the development of weaponry and large-scale state formations.&lt;ref&gt;Johan M.G. van der Dennen. 1995. The Origin of War: Evolution of a Male-Coalitional Reproductive Strategy. Origin Press, Groningen, 1995 chapters 1 &amp; 2&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:COLLECTIE TROPENMUSEUM Een Ibu Dajak krijger uit Long Nawan Z. en O. afdeling Borneo. TMnr 60034031.jpg|thumb|[[Dayak people|Dayak]] headhunters in Borneo, ca. 1927]]
One line of evidence for violent conflict among the ancestors of humans is [[sexual dimorphism]]. In species that have high levels of male competition over females, males tend to be larger and stronger than females. Humans have considerable sexual dimorphism, although lower than our nearest primate relatives.&lt;ref&gt;Roger Lewin and Robert Foley. 2004 Principles of human evolution, 2nd ed.p. 182-3&lt;/ref&gt; The strength difference is greater for upper-body strength than for lower-body strength. Men are in general terms also larger, faster, and more aggressive. Their skeleton, especially in the vulnerable face, is more robust. This suggests that male competition has been an important factor in human evolution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1016/j.evolhumbehav.2010.02.005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Steven Pinker]] in his book ''[[The Blank Slate]]'' argues that raiding or warfare between groups of humans in the ancestral environment was often beneficial for the victors. This includes gaining control over scarce resources as well as the women of the defeated or raided group. Various features of modern warfare such as alliances between groups and [[preemptive war]]s were likely part of these conflicts. In order to have a credible [[deterrence theory|deterrence]] against other groups (as well as on an individual level), it was important to have a reputation for retaliation, causing humans to develop instincts for [[revenge]] as well as for protecting a group's (or an individual's) reputation (&quot;[[honor]]&quot;). Pinker argues that the development of the state and the police have dramatically reduced the level of warfare and violence compared to the ancestral environment. Whenever the state breaks down, which can be very locally such as in poor areas of a city, humans again organize in groups for protection and aggression and concepts such as violent revenge and protecting honor again become extremely important.

[[Ashley Montagu]] strongly denied universalistic instinctual arguments, arguing that social factors and childhood socialization are important in determining the nature and presence of warfare. Thus, he argues, while human aggression may be a universal occurrence, warfare is not, and would appear to have been a historical invention, associated with certain types of human societies.&lt;ref&gt;Montagu, Ashley (1976), ''The Nature of Human Aggression'' (Oxford University Press)&lt;/ref&gt; This argument has been supported by ethnographic research conducted in societies where the concept of aggression seems to be entirely absent, e.g., the [[Chewong language|Chewong]] of the Malay peninsula.&lt;ref&gt;Howell, Signe and Roy Willis, eds. (1989) Societies at Peace: Anthropological Perspectives. London: Routledge&lt;/ref&gt; Crofoot and Wrangham have instead argued that warfare, if defined as group interactions in which &quot;coalitions attempt to aggressively dominate or kill members of other groups&quot;, is a characteristic of most human societies. Those in which it has been lacking &quot;tend to be societies that were politically dominated by their neighbors&quot;.&lt;ref name=HumanPrimateAggression&gt;&quot;Mind the Gap: Tracing the Origins of Human Universals&quot; By Peter M. Kappeler, Joan B. Silk, 2009, Chapter 8, &quot;Intergroup Aggression in Primates and Humans; The Case for a Unified Theory&quot;, Margaret C. Crofoot and Richard W. Wrangham&lt;/ref&gt;

===Economic ===
[[File:Disabled Iraqi T-54A, T-55, Type 59 or Type 69 tank and burning Kuwaiti oil field.jpg|thumb|Kuwaiti [[oil well]]s on fire, during the [[Gulf War]], 1 March 1991]]
War can be seen as a growth of economic competition in a competitive international system. In this view wars begin as a pursuit of markets for [[natural resource]]s and for wealth. While this theory has been applied to many conflicts, such counter arguments become less valid as the increasing mobility of capital and information level the distributions of wealth worldwide, or when considering that it is relative, not absolute, wealth differences that may fuel wars. There are those on the extreme [[right (politics)|right]] of the political spectrum who provide support, fascists in particular, by asserting a natural right of a strong nation to whatever the weak cannot hold by force.&lt;ref&gt;[[Roger Griffin]] and Matthew Feldman, eds., ''Fascism: Fascism and Culture'', New York: [[Routledge]], 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hawkins, Mike. ''[[Social Darwinism]] in European and American Thought, 1860–1945: Nature as Model and Nature as Threat'', [[Cambridge University Press]], 1997.&lt;/ref&gt; Some centrist, capitalist, world leaders, including [[Presidents of the United States]] and US [[General officer|Generals]], expressed support for an economic view of war.

{{quote|Is there any man, is there any woman, let me say any child here that does not know that the seed of war in the modern world is industrial and commercial rivalry?
– [[Woodrow Wilson]], September 11, 1919, St. Louis.&lt;ref&gt;''The Papers of [[Woodrow Wilson]]'', Arthur S. Link, ed. (Princeton, N.J.: [[Princeton University]] Press, 1990), vol. 63, pp. 45–46.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

{{quote|I spent 33 years and four months in active military service and during that period I spent most of my time as a high class muscle man for [[Big Business]], for [[Wall Street]] and the bankers. In short, I was a [[racketeer]], a [[gangster]] for capitalism.
– [[Major General]] [[Smedley Butler]] (simultaneously the highest ranking and most decorated [[United States Marine Corps|United States Marine]] (including two [[Medal of Honor|Medals of Honor]]) and [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party]] primary candidate for the [[United States Senate]]) 1935.&lt;ref&gt;1935 issue of left of the magazine, ''[[Common Sense]].''&lt;/ref&gt;}}

{{quote|For the corporation executives, the military metaphysic often coincides with their interest in a stable and planned flow of profit; it enables them to have their risk underwritten by public money; it enables them reasonably to expect that they can exploit for private profit now and later, the risky research developments paid for by public money. It is, in brief, a mask of the subsidized capitalism from which they extract profit and upon which their power is based.
– [[C. Wright Mills]], ''Causes of World War 3'', 1960.}}

{{quote|In the councils of government, we must guard against the acquisition of unwarranted influence, whether sought or unsought, by the [[military-industrial complex]]. The potential for disastrous rise of misplaced power exists and will persist.
– [[Dwight D. Eisenhower|Dwight Eisenhower]], Farewell Address, January 17, 1961.}}

===Marxist ===
The [[Marxism|Marxist]] theory of war is quasi-economic in that it states that all modern wars are caused by competition for resources and markets between great ([[Imperialism|imperialist]]) powers, claiming these wars are a natural result of the [[free market]] and [[Social class|class system]]. Part of the theory is that war will only disappear once a [[world revolution]], over-throwing free markets and class systems, has occurred. Marxist philosopher [[Rosa Luxembourg]] theorized that [[imperialism]] was the result of capitalist countries needing new [[economic market|markets]]. Expansion of the [[means of production]] is only possible if there is a corresponding growth in [[consumer demand]]. Since the workers in a [[capitalist economy]] would be unable to fill the demand, producers must expand into non-capitalist markets to find consumers for their goods, hence driving imperialism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.marxists.org/archive/mandel/1955/08/imp-crit.html |title=The Marxist Theory of Imperialism and its Critics |first=Einde |last=O'Callaghan |publisher=[[Marxist Internet Archive]] |date=25 October 2007 |accessdate=24 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Demographic===&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[The Clash of Civilizations|Clash of Civilizations]] --&gt;

Demographic theories can be grouped into two classes, Malthusian theories and [[youth bulge]] theories.

====Malthusian ====
[[File:US soldiers in Kismayo, 1993.JPEG|thumb|US Army soldiers in [[Somalia]], 1993]]
Malthusian theories see expanding population and scarce resources as a source of violent conflict.

[[Pope Urban II]] in 1095, on the eve of the [[First Crusade]], spoke:
{{quote|For this land which you now inhabit, shut in on all sides by the sea and the mountain peaks, is too narrow for your large population; it scarcely furnishes food enough for its cultivators. Hence it is that you murder and devour one another, that you wage wars, and that many among you perish in civil strife. Let hatred, therefore, depart from among you; let your quarrels end. Enter upon the road to the Holy Sepulchre; wrest that land from a wicked race, and subject it to yourselves.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Lend me your ears: great speeches in history |first=William |last=Safire |publisher=[[W. W. Norton &amp; Company]] |year=200] |isbn=978-0-393-05931-1 |page=94}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

This is one of the earliest expressions of what has come to be called the Malthusian theory of war, in which wars are caused by expanding populations and limited resources. [[Thomas Malthus]] (1766–1834) wrote that populations always increase until they are limited by war, disease, or [[famine]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Geography: an integrated approach |first=David |last=Waugh |publisher=[[Nelson Thornes]] |year=2000 |isbn=978-0-17-444706-1 |page=378}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This theory is thought by Malthusians to account for the relative decrease in wars during the past fifty years, especially in the [[Developed country|developed world]], where advances in agriculture have made it possible to support a much larger population than was formerly the case, and where [[birth control]] has dramatically slowed the increase in population.

====Youth bulge====
[[File:Median age.png|thumb|300px|[[Population pyramid|Median age]] by country. A youth bulge is evident for [[Demographics of Africa|Africa]], and to a lesser extent for South and Southeast Asia and Central America.]]
[[Youth bulge]] theory differs significantly from Malthusian theories. Its adherents see a combination of large male youth cohorts – as graphically represented as a &quot;youth bulge&quot; in a [[population pyramid]] – with a lack of regular, peaceful employment opportunities as a risk pool for violence.

While Malthusian theories focus on a disparity between a growing population and available natural resources, youth bulge theory focuses on a disparity between non-inheriting, 'excess' young males and available social positions within the existing social system of [[division of labour]].

Contributors to the development of [[youth bulge]] theory include French sociologist Gaston Bouthoul,&lt;ref&gt;Bouthoul, Gaston: &quot;L`infanticide différé&quot; (deferred infanticide), Paris 1970&lt;/ref&gt; U.S. sociologist [[Jack Goldstone|Jack A. Goldstone]],&lt;ref&gt;Goldstone, Jack A.: &quot;Revolution and Rebellion in the Early Modern World&quot;, Berkeley 1991; Goldstone, Jack A.: &quot;Population and Security: How Demographic Change can Lead to Violent Conflict&quot;, [http://www.mafhoum.com/press6/179S21.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt; U.S. political scientist Gary Fuller,&lt;ref&gt;Fuller, Gary: &quot;The Demographic Backdrop to Ethnic Conflict: A Geographic Overwiew&quot;, in: CIA (Ed.): &quot;The Challenge of Ethnic Conflict to National and International Order in the 1990s&quot;, Washington 1995, 151–154&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.strategicinspirations.com/ispu/go/images/F000180/Graham+Fuller+paper.pdf |title=Fuller, Gary (2004): &quot;The Youth Crisis in Middle Eastern Society&quot; |format=PDF |accessdate=2011-01-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fuller, Gary (2003): &quot;The Youth Factor: The New Demographics of the Middle East and the Implications for U.S. Policy&quot;[http://www.brook.edu/fp/projects/islam/fuller2003.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt; and German sociologist [[Gunnar Heinsohn]].&lt;ref&gt;Gunnar Heinsohn (2003): &quot;Söhne und Weltmacht: Terror im Aufstieg und Fall der Nationen&quot; (&quot;Sons and Imperial Power: Terror and the Rise and Fall of Nations&quot;), Zurich 2003), available online as free download (in German) [http://www.pdf4ebook-verlag.de/ShneundWeltmacht.html#Zweig4]; see also the review of this book by Göran Therborn: &quot;Nato´s Demographer&quot;, New Left Review 56, March/April 2009, 136–144 [http://www.newleftreview.org/?page=article&amp;view=2775]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Samuel P. Huntington|Samuel Huntington]] has modified his [[The Clash of Civilizations|Clash of Civilizations]] theory by using youth bulge theory as its foundation:

{{quote|I don't think Islam is any more violent than any other religions, and I suspect if you added it all up, more people have been slaughtered by Christians over the centuries than by Muslims. But the key factor is the demographic factor. Generally speaking, the people who go out and kill other people are males between the ages of 16 and 30.

During the 1960s, 70s and 80s there were high birth rates in the Muslim world, and this has given rise to a huge youth bulge. But the bulge will fade. Muslim birth rates are going down; in fact, they have dropped dramatically in some countries. Islam did spread by the sword originally, but I don't think there is anything inherently violent in Muslim theology.&lt;ref&gt;‘So, are civilizations at war?’, Interview with Samuel P. Huntington by Michael Steinberger, The Observer, Sunday October 21, 2001 [http://observer.guardian.co.uk/islam/story/0,,577982,00.html]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Youth Bulge theories represent a relatively recent development but seem to have become more influential in guiding U.S. foreign policy and military strategy as both Goldstone and Fuller have acted as consultants to the U.S. Government. CIA Inspector General [[John L. Helgerson]] referred to youth bulge theory in his 2002 report &quot;The National Security Implications of Global Demographic Change&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Helgerson, John L. (2002): &quot;The National Security Implications of Global Demographic Trends&quot;[http://www.au.af.mil/au/awc/awcgate/cia/helgerson2.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Palestinian militant with rifle.png|thumb|Palestinian militant with rifle, 2009]]
According to Heinsohn, who has proposed youth bulge theory in its most generalized form, a youth bulge occurs when 30 to 40 percent of the males of a nation belong to the &quot;fighting age&quot; cohorts from 15 to 29 years of age. It will follow periods with [[total fertility rate]]s as high as 4–8 children per woman with a 15–29-year delay.

A total fertility rate of 2.1 children born by a woman during her lifetime represents a situation of in which the son will replace the father, and the daughter will replace the mother accounting for a small proportion of deaths to factors such as illness and accidents. Thus, a total fertility rate of 2.1 represents replacement level, while anything below represents a [[sub-replacement fertility]] rate leading to [[population decline]].

Total fertility rates above 2.1 will lead to population growth and to a youth bulge. A total fertility rate of 4–8 children per mother implies 2–4 sons per mother. Consequently, one father has to leave not 1, but 2 to 4 social positions (jobs) to give all his sons a perspective for life, which is usually hard to achieve. Since respectable positions cannot be increased at the same speed as food, textbooks and vaccines, many &quot;angry young men&quot; find themselves in a situation that tends to escalate their adolescent anger into violence: they are

# Demographically superfluous,
# Might be out of work or stuck in a menial job, and
# Often have no access to a legal sex life before a career can earn them enough to provide for a family. ''See: [[Hypergamy]], [[Waithood]]''.

The combination of these [[stress (biological)|stress]] factors according to Heinsohn&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://www.geocities.com/funnyguy_35/DefenceTraining.PDF&amp;date=2009-10-25+22:25:12 |title=Heinsohn, G.(2006): &quot;Demography and War.&quot; |publisher=Webcitation.org |accessdate=2011-01-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; usually heads for one of six different exits:
[[File:Detenciones Michoacán.jpg|thumb|right|Mexican soldiers detain [[Mexican Drug War|cartel]] suspects in Michoacán, 2007]]
# Emigration (&quot;non-violent [[colonization]]&quot;)
# Violent Crime
# Rebellion or [[putsch]]
# Civil war and/or revolution
# [[Genocide]] (to take over the positions of the slaughtered)
# [[Conquest (military)|Conquest]] (violent colonization, frequently including genocide abroad).

Religions and ideologies are seen as secondary factors that are being used to legitimate violence, but will not lead to violence by themselves if no youth bulge is present. Consequently, youth bulge theorists see both past &quot;Christianist&quot; European colonialism and imperialism and today's &quot;Islamist&quot; civil unrest and terrorism as results of high birth rates producing youth bulges.&lt;ref&gt;Heinsohn, G.(2005): &quot;Population, Conquest and Terror in the 21st Century.&quot; [http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://www.geocities.com/funnyguy_35/HeinsohnPopulation.PDF&amp;date=2009-10-25+22:25:15]&lt;/ref&gt; With the [[Gaza Strip]] now being seen as another example of youth-bulge-driven violence, especially if compared to [[Lebanon]] which is geographically close, yet remarkably more peaceful.&lt;ref&gt;G. Heinsohn: &quot;Why Gaza is Fertile Ground for Angry Young Men.&quot; Financial Times Online, 14 June 2007 [http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/0db3a2b8-1a14-11dc-99c5-000b5df10621.html?nclick_check=1], retrieved on December 23, 2007; compare demographic data for Gaza Strip ([http://www.census.gov/cgi-bin/ipc/idbpyrs.pl?cty=GZ&amp;out=s&amp;ymax=250&amp;Submit.x=15&amp;Submit.y=7],[http://www.census.gov/ipc/www/idb/country/gzportal.html])and Lebanon ([http://www.census.gov/cgi-bin/ipc/idbpyrs.pl?cty=LE&amp;out=s&amp;ymax=250&amp;submit=Anfrage+abschicken], [http://www.census.gov/ipc/www/idb/country/leportal.html]) provided by the U.S. Census Bureau; see also David Bau: &quot;History is Demographics&quot;[http://davidbau.com/archives/2007/02/03/history_is_demographics.html], retrieved on December 23, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

Among prominent historical events that have been linked to the existence of youth bulges is the role played by the historically large youth cohorts in the rebellion and revolution waves of early modern Europe, including [[French Revolution]] of 1789,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Jack A. Goldstone|title=Revolution and Rebellion in the Early Modern World|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=M-T9dR7nWDUC|accessdate=31 May 2012|date=4 March 1993|publisher=University of California Press|isbn=978-0-520-08267-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the importance of economic depression hitting the largest German youth cohorts ever in explaining the rise of [[Nazism]] in Germany in the 1930s.&lt;ref&gt;Moller, Herbert (1968): ‘Youth as a Force in the Modern World’, Comparative Studies in Society and
History 10: 238–260; 240–244&lt;/ref&gt; The 1994 [[Rwandan Genocide]] has also been analyzed as following a massive youth bulge.&lt;ref&gt;Diessenbacher, Hartmut (1994): Kriege der Zukunft. Die Bevölkerungsexplosion gefährdet den Frieden. Muenchen: Hanser 1998; see also (criticizing youth bulge theory) Marc Sommers (2006): &quot;Fearing Africa´s Young Men: The Case of Rwanda.&quot; The World Bank: Social Development Papers – Conflict Prevention and Reconstruction, Paper No. 32, January 2006 [http://www.eldis.org/vfile/upload/1/document/0708/DOC21389.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt;

While the implications of population growth have been known since the completion of the [[National Security Study Memorandum 200]] in 1974,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.population-security.org/28-APP2.html |title=National Security Study Memorandum 200 (NSSM 200) – April 1974 |publisher=Population-security.org |accessdate=2011-01-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; neither the U.S. nor the WHO have implemented the recommended measures to control population growth to avert the terrorist threat. Prominent demographer [[Stephen D. Mumford]] attributes this to the influence of the Catholic Church.&lt;ref&gt;Stephen D. Mumford: [http://www.population-security.org/index.html ''The Life and Death of NSSM 200: How the Destruction of Political Will Doomed a U.S. Population Policy'']&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Youth Bulge]] theory has been subjected to statistical analysis by the World Bank,&lt;ref&gt;[[Henrik Urdal|Urdal, Henrik]] (2004): &quot;The Devil in the Demographics: The Effect of Youth Bulges on Domestic Armed Conflict,&quot; [http://www-wds.worldbank.org/servlet/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2004/07/28/000012009_20040728162225/Rendered/PDF/29740.pdf],&lt;/ref&gt; [[Population Action International]],&lt;ref&gt;Population Action International: &quot;The Security Demographic: Population and Civil Conflict after the Cold War&quot;[http://www.populationaction.org/Publications/Report/The_Security_Demographic/Summary.php]&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Berlin Institute for Population and Development]].&lt;ref&gt;Kröhnert, Steffen (2004): &quot;Warum entstehen Kriege? Welchen Einfluss haben demografische Veränderungen auf die Entstehung von Konflikten?&quot; [http://www.berlin-institut.org/fileadmin/user_upload/Jugend_und_Kriegsgefahr/Warum_entstehen_Kriege.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt; Detailed demographic data for most countries is available at the international database of the [[United States Census Bureau]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.census.gov/ipc/www/idb/informationGateway.php |title=United States Census Bureau: International Database |publisher=Census.gov |accessdate=2011-01-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Statistic data about historical development of demographic and economic parameters over the last 200 years for each country can be visualized at [[Gapminder]].&lt;ref&gt;Gapminder World: Development of total fertility rates and income per person, 1800–2009 [http://www.gapminder.org/world/#$majorMode=chart$is;shi=t;ly=2003;lb=f;il=t;fs=11;al=30;stl=t;st=t;nsl=t;se=t$wst;tts=C$ts;sp=5.59290322580644;ti=2009$zpv;v=0$inc_x;mmid=XCOORDS;iid=phAwcNAVuyj1jiMAkmq1iMg;by=ind$inc_y;mmid=YCOORDS;iid=phAwcNAVuyj0TAlJeCEzcGQ;by=ind$inc_s;uniValue=8.21;iid=phAwcNAVuyj0XOoBL_n5tAQ;by=ind$inc_c;uniValue=255;gid=CATID0;by=grp$map_x;scale=log;dataMin=282;dataMax=119849$map_y;scale=lin;dataMin=0.855;dataMax=8.7$map_s;sma=49;smi=2.65$cd;bd=0$inds=]&lt;/ref&gt;

Youth bulge theories have been criticized as leading to racial, gender and age &quot;discrimination&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Hendrixson, Anne: &quot;Angry Young Men, Veiled Young Women: Constructing a New Population Threat&quot; [http://www.thecornerhouse.org.uk/item.shtml?x=85999]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Rationalist===
Rationalist theories of war assume that both sides to a potential war are rational, which is to say that each side wants to get the best possible outcome for itself for the least possible loss of life and property to its own side. Given this assumption, if both countries knew in advance how the war would turn out, it would be better for both of them to just accept the post-war outcome without having to actually pay the costs of fighting the war. This is based on the notion, generally agreed to by almost all scholars of war since [[Carl von Clausewitz]], that wars are reciprocal, that all wars require both a decision to attack and also a decision to resist attack.
Rationalist theory offers three reasons why some countries cannot find a bargain and instead resort to war: issue indivisibility, [[information asymmetry]] with incentive to deceive, and the inability to make credible commitments.&lt;ref&gt;Fearon, James D. 1995. &quot;Rationalist Explanations for War.&quot; International Organization 49, 3: 379–414. [http://www.polisci.ucsd.edu/~bslantch/courses/pdf/fearon-io1995v49n3.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:U.S. Marines in Operation Allen Brook (Vietnam War) 001.jpg|thumb|U.S. Marines direct a concentration of fire at the enemy, Vietnam, 8 May 1968]]
Issue indivisibility occurs when the two parties cannot avoid war by bargaining because the thing over which they are fighting cannot be shared between them, only owned entirely by one side or the other. Religious issues, such as control over the [[Temple Mount]] in Jerusalem, are more likely to be indivisible than economic issues.

A bigger branch of the theory, advanced by scholars of international relations such as [[Geoffrey Blainey]], is that both sides decide to go to war and one side may have miscalculated.

Some go further and say that there is a problem of information asymmetry with incentives to misrepresent. The two countries may not agree on who would win a war between them, or whether victory would be overwhelming or merely eked out, because each side has military secrets about its own capabilities. They will not avoid the bargaining [[failure]] by sharing their secrets, since they cannot trust each other not to lie and exaggerate their strength to extract more concessions. For example, Sweden made efforts to deceive Nazi Germany that it would resist an attack fiercely, partly by playing on the myth of Aryan superiority and by making sure that [[Hermann Göring]] only saw elite troops in action, often dressed up as regular soldiers, when he came to visit.

The American decision to enter the [[Vietnam War]] was made with the full knowledge that the communist forces would resist them, but did not believe that the guerrillas had the capability to long oppose [[United States armed forces|American forces]].

Thirdly, bargaining may fail due to the states' inability to make credible commitments.&lt;ref&gt;Powell, Robert. 2002. &quot;Bargaining Theory and International Conflict.&quot; ''Annual Review of Political Science'' 5: 1–30.&lt;/ref&gt; In this scenario, the two countries might be able to come to a bargain that would avert war if they could stick to it, but the benefits of the bargain will make one side more powerful and lead it to demand even more in the future, so that the weaker side has an incentive to make a stand now.

Rationalist explanations of war can be critiqued on a number of grounds. The assumptions of cost-benefit calculations become dubious in the most extreme genocidal cases of World War II, where the only bargain offered in some cases was infinitely bad. Rationalist theories typically assume that the state acts as a unitary individual, doing what is best for the state as a whole; this is problematic when, for example, the country's leader is beholden to a very small number of people, as in a personalistic dictatorship. Rationalist theory also assumes that the actors are rational, able to accurately assess their likelihood of success or failure, but the proponents of the psychological theories above would disagree.

Rationalist theories are usually explicated with [[game theory]], for example, the [[Peace war game|Peace War Game]], not a [[Military simulation|wargame]] as such, rather a simulation of economic decisions underlying war.

===Political science===
{{Refimprove section|date=June 2008}}
The statistical analysis of war was pioneered by [[Lewis Fry Richardson]] following [[World War I]]. More recent databases of wars and armed conflict have been assembled by the Correlates of War Project, Peter Brecke and the [[Uppsala Conflict Data Program]].

There are several different [[international relations theory]] schools. Supporters of [[realism in international relations]] argue that the motivation of states is the quest for security.
Which sometimes is argued to contradict the realist view, that there is much empirical evidence to support the claim that states that are [[Democracy|democracies]] do not go to war with each other, an idea that has come to be known as the [[democratic peace theory]]. Other factors included are difference in moral and religious beliefs, economical and trade disagreements, declaring independence, and others.

Another major theory relating to [[power in international relations]] and ''[[Power politics|machtpolitik]]'' is the [[Power Transition theory]], which distributes the world into a hierarchy and explains major wars as part of a cycle of [[hegemony|hegemons]] being destabilized by a [[great power]] which does not support the hegemons' control.

Military adventurism can sometimes be used by political leaders as a means of boosting their domestic popularity, as has been recorded in US war-time presidential popularity surveys taken during the presidencies of several recent US leaders.&lt;ref name = &quot;MilitaryAdventurism&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| year = 2001
| url = http://www.bepress.com/peps/vol7/iss3/3/
| title= Peace Economics, Peace Science and Public Policy (pg. 19)
| accessdate = 2010-02-07}} Leaders may use war as instant popularity boost
&lt;/ref&gt;

==War ethics==
[[File:Morgen nach der Schlacht967b.jpg|thumb|200px|''Morning after the [[Battle of Waterloo]]'', by [[John Heaviside Clark]], 1816]]

{{Unreferenced section|date=June 2008}}
{{Original research|section|date=January 2010}}

The seeming contradiction between warfare and morality has led to serious [[morality|moral]] questions, which have been the subject of debate for thousands of years.&lt;ref name=&quot;DeForrest&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=DeForrest|first=Mark Edward|title=Conclusion|url=http://www.gonzagajil.org/content/view/72/26/|work=JUST WAR THEORY AND THE RECENT U.S. AIR STRIKES AGAINST IRAQ|publisher=Gonzaga Journal of International Law|accessdate=8/1/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The debate, generally speaking, has two main viewpoints: [[Pacifists]], who believe that war is inherently immoral and therefore is never justified regardless of circumstances, and those who believe that war is sometimes necessary and can be moral.

There are two different aspects to ethics in war, according to the most prominent and influential thought on justice and war: The [[Just War Theory]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=DeForrest|first=Mark Edward|title=GENERALLY RECOGNIZED PRINCIPLES OF JUST WAR THEORY|url=http://www.gonzagajil.org/content/view/72/26/|work=JUST WAR THEORY AND THE RECENT U.S. AIR STRIKES AGAINST IRAQ|publisher=Gonzaga Journal of International Law|accessdate=8/1/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Codevilla, Seabury 1989 304&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Codevilla, Seabury|first=Angelo, Paul|title=War: Ends and Means|year=1989|publisher=Basic Books|location=New York, NY|isbn=0-465-09067-2|page=304|url=http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/157488610X/ref=pd_lpo_k2_dp_sr_1?pf_rd_p=486539851&amp;pf_rd_s=lpo-top-stripe-1&amp;pf_rd_t=201&amp;pf_rd_i=0465090672&amp;pf_rd_m=ATVPDKIKX0DER&amp;pf_rd_r=0144DHEVCX1XCVMJXAZQ}}&lt;/ref&gt; First is [[Jus ad bellum]] (literally translated as &quot;right to war&quot;), which dictates which unfriendly acts and circumstances justify a proper authority in declaring war on another nation. There are six main criteria for the declaration of a just war: first, any just war must be declared by a lawful authority; second, it must be a just and righteous cause, with sufficient gravity to merit large-scale violence; third, the just belligerent must have rightful intentions – namely, that they seek to advance good and curtail evil; fourth, a just belligerent must have a reasonable chance of success; fifth, the war must be a last resort; and sixth, the ends being sought must be proportional to means being used.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Aquinas|first=Thomas|title=Part II, Question 40|url=http://ethics.sandiego.edu/Books/Texts/Aquinas/JustWar.html|work=The Summa Theologica|publisher=Benziger Bros. edition, 1947|accessdate=8/1/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Mosley|first=Alexander|title=The Jus Ad Bellum Convention|url=http://www.iep.utm.edu/justwar/|work=Just War Theory|publisher=Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy|accessdate=8/1/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Once a just war has been declared, the second standard, or aspect, is put into effect. [[Jus in bello]], which literally translates to &quot;right in war&quot;, are the ethical rules of conduct when conducting war. The two main principles in ''jus in bello'' are proportionality and discrimination. Proportionality regards how much force is necessary and morally appropriate to the ends being sought and the injustice suffered.&lt;ref name=&quot;Moseley&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Moseley|first=Alexander|title=The Principles Of Jus In Bello|url=http://www.iep.utm.edu/justwar/|work=Just War Theory|publisher=Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy|accessdate=8/1/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The principle of Discrimination determines who are the legitimate targets in a war, and specifically makes a separation between combatants, who it is permissible to kill, and non-combatants, who it is not.&lt;ref name=&quot;Moseley&quot;/&gt; Failure to follow these rules can result in the loss of legitimacy for the just war belligerent, and so thereby forfeit the moral right and justice of their cause.&lt;ref name=&quot;Codevilla, Seabury 1989 304&quot;/&gt;
[[File:RIAN archive 324 In besieged Leningrad.jpg|thumb|210px|In besieged [[Leningrad]]. &quot;Hitler ordered that Moscow and Leningrad were to be razed to the ground; their inhabitants were to be annihilated or driven out by starvation. These intentions were part of the '[[General Plan East]]'.&quot;  – ''The Oxford Companion to World War II.''&lt;ref&gt;[[I.C.B. Dear|Ian Dear]], [[M.R.D. Foot|Michael Richard Daniell Foot]] (2001). ''The Oxford Companion to World War II.'' Oxford University Press. p.88. ISBN 0-19-860446-7&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The Just War standard is as old as Western Civilization itself, and still has significant impact on thinking about the morality of wars and violence today.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Moseley|first=Alexander|title=Introduction|url=http://www.iep.utm.edu/justwar/|work=Just War Theory|publisher=Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy|accessdate=8/1/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Just War Theory was foundational in the creation of the United Nations and in [[International Law]]'s regulations on legitimate war.&lt;ref name=&quot;DeForrest&quot;/&gt;

These two positions generally cover the broad philosophical and ethical bents mainstream society. However, there are several theories on and about War which are in the minority in culture, but which, because of the influence they have had in recent history, demand mention here. These strains of thought on human society and war can be broken up into two main camps: [[Marxist]] and Fascist, both of which view war as purely practical.

Marxism, and other such [[historicist]] ideals, hold that history advances through a set of [[dialectics]] (as stated by [[Heinrich Moritz Chalybäus]]: thesis, antithesis, synthesis). Marx, and his followers, in particular held that history advances through violence. [[Marxism-Leninism]], in fact, held the belief that outright incitement to violence and war was necessary to topple Capitalism and free the [[proletariat]]. In these theories, the question of ethics has no place, as the value of the war is entirely dependent on whether it advances the revolution or synthesis.

Fascism, and the ideals it encompasses, such as [[Pragmatism]], Racism, and [[Social Darwinism]], hold that violence is good.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Griffin and Feldman, eds|first=Roger and Matthew|title=Fascism: Fascism and Culture|year=2004|publisher=Routledge|page=185}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Woodley|first=Daniel|title=Fascism and political theory critical perspectives on fascist ideology|year=2010|publisher=Routledge|location=London|isbn=0-203-87157-X|page=276|url=http://wxy.seu.edu.cn/humanities/sociology/htmledit/uploadfile/system/20100724/20100724163537707.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pragmatism holds that war and violence can be good if it serves the ends of the people, without regard for universal morality. Racism holds that violence is good so that a master race can be established, or to purge an inferior race from the earth, or both. Social Darwinism thinks that violence is sometimes necessary to weed the unfit from society so that civilization can flourish. These are broad [[archetypes]] for the general position that [[the ends justify the means]].

==See also==
{{portal|War}}
{{Wikipedia books|War}}

;General reference
{{Div col|cols=2}}
* [[Undeclared war]]
* [[Colonial war]]
* [[Religious war]]
* [[List of active autonomist and secessionist movements|Breakaway states]]
* [[Casus belli]]
* [[Fault line war]]
* [[Islam and war]]
* [[Horses in warfare]]
* [[War cycles]]
* [[Nuclear warfare|Nuclear war]]
* [[War as metaphor]]
{{Div col end}}

;War-related lists
{{Div col|cols=2}}
* [[List of battles]]
* [[List of battles and other violent events by death toll]]
* [[List of battles by casualties|List of battles by death toll]]
* [[List of invasions]]
* [[Lists of wars]]
* [[List of military commanders]]
* [[List of ongoing conflicts]]
* [[List of orders of battle]]
* [[List of terrorist incidents]]
* [[List of war crimes]]
* [[List of wars by death toll]]
{{Div col end}}

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

===Bibliography===
&lt;div class=&quot;references-small&quot;&gt;
* Angelo Codevilla and Paul Seabury, [http://www.toreadnext.com/9781574886108 ''War: Ends and Means''] (Potomac Books, Revised second edition by Angelo Codevilla, 2006) ISBN-X
* Angelo M. Codevilla, ''No Victory, No Peace'' (Rowman and Littlefield, 2005) ISBN
* Barzilai Gad, ''Wars, Internal Conflicts and Political Order: A Jewish Democracy in the Middle East'' (Albany: State University of New York Press, 1996).
* Clausewitz, Carl Von (1976), ''On War'' (Princeton and New Jersey: Princeton University Press)
* Fry, Douglas P., 2005, ''The Human Potential for Peace: An Anthropological Challenge to Assumptions about War and Violence'', Oxford University Press.
* Gat, Azar 2006 ''War in Human Civilization'', Oxford University Press.
* Gunnar Heinsohn, ''Söhne und Weltmacht: Terror im Aufstieg und Fall der Nationen'' (&quot;Sons and Imperial Power: Terror and the Rise and Fall of Nations&quot;), Orell Füssli (September 2003), ISBN, available online as [http://www.pdf4ebook-verlag.de/ShneundWeltmacht.html#Zweig4 free download] (in German)
* {{cite book|author=Fabio Maniscalco|title=World heritage and war: linee guida per interventi a salvaguardia dei beni culturali nelle aree a rischio bellico|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=lelEGQAACAAJ|accessdate=31 May 2012|year=2007|publisher=Massa|isbn=978-88-87835-89-2}}
* Keegan, John, (1994) &quot;A History Of Warfare&quot;, (Pimlico)
* Kelly, Raymond C., 2000, ''Warless Societies and the Origin of War,'' University of Michigan Press.
* {{cite book|author=David Livingstone Smith|title=The Most Dangerous Animal: Human Nature and the Origins of War|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=FwBUuzr6QFAC|accessdate=31 May 2012|date=17 February 2009|publisher=Macmillan|isbn=978-0-312-53744-9}}
* {{cite book|author1=Melvin Small|author2=Joel David Singer|title=Resort to arms: international and civil wars, 1816–1980|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=rvASAQAAMAAJ|accessdate=31 May 2012|date=1 April 1982|publisher=Sage Publications|isbn=978-0-8039-1776-7}}
* Otterbein, Keith, 2004, ''How War Began''.
* Turchin, P. 2005. ''War and [[Peace]] and War: Life Cycles of Imperial Nations''. New York, NY: Pi Press. ISBN
* Van Creveld, Martin ''The Art of War: War and Military Thought'' London: Cassell, Wellington House
* Fornari, Franco (1974). ''The Psychoanalysis of War.'' Tr. Alenka Pfeifer. Garden City, New York: Doubleday Anchor Press. ISBN . Reprinted (1975) Bloomington: Indiana University Press. ISBN
* Walzer, Michael (1977) ''[[Just and Unjust Wars]]'' (Basic Books)
* Keeley, Lawrence. ''War Before Civilization'', Oxford University Press, 1996.
* Zimmerman, L. ''The Crow Creek Site Massacre: A Preliminary Report'', US Army Corps of Engineers, Omaha District, 1981.
* Chagnon, N. ''The Yanomamo'', Holt, Rinehart &amp; Winston,1983.
* Pauketat, Timothy. ''North American Archaeology'' 2005. Blackwell Publishing.
* Wade, Nicholas. ''Before the Dawn'', Penguin: New York 2006.
* Rafael Karsten, ''Blood revenge, war, and victory feasts among the Jibaro Indians of eastern Ecuador'' (1923).
* S. A. LeBlanc, ''Prehistoric Warfare in the American Southwest'', University of Utah Press (1999).
* Duane M. Capulla, ''War Wolf'', University of Pili (2008)
&lt;/div&gt;

==External links==
&lt;!--Any links that have not been cited in the article, but related to the article subject area--&gt;
&lt;!--======================== {{No more links}} ============================
 | PLEASE BE CAUTIOUS IN ADDING MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. Wikipedia |
 | is not a collection of links nor should it be used for advertising. |
 | |
 | Excessive or inappropriate links WILL BE DELETED. |
 | See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details. |
 | |
 | If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or |
 | replacements on this article's discussion page, or submit your link |
 | to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org) |
 | and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template. |
 ======================= {{No more links}} =============================--&gt;
{{Commons category|War}}
{{Commons category|Warfare}}
{{wikiquote}}
* [http://www.umich.edu/~cowproj/ Correlates of War Project]
* [http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/war/ Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy entry]
* [http://www.cedat.org Complex Emergency Database (CE-DAT)] – A database on the human impact of conflicts and other complex emergencies.
* [http://libluna.colorado.edu/wwi/index.asp World War I primary source collection]
* [http://www.icrc.org/eng/ihl International humanitarian law] – International Committee of the Red Cross website
* [http://www.icrc.org/web/eng/siteeng0.nsf/htmlall/section_ihl_customary_humanitarian_law Customary international humanitarian law] International Committee of the Red Cross
* [http://www.icrc.org/ihl International humanitarian law database] – Treaties and States Parties
* [http://www.icrc.org/customary-ihl/eng/docs/home Customary IHL Database]

[[Category:War| ]]
[[Category:Violence]]
[[Category:Ethics]]

{{Link FA|sh}}

[[af:Oorlog]]
[[ar:حرب]]
[[an:Guerra]]
[[arc:ܩܪܒܐ]]
[[az:Müharibə]]
[[bn:যুদ্ধ]]
[[zh-min-nan:Chiàn-cheng]]
[[map-bms:Perang]]
[[be:Вайна]]
[[be-x-old:Вайна]]
[[bg:Война]]
[[bo:དམག་འཁྲུག]]
[[bs:Rat]]
[[br:Brezel]]
[[ca:Guerra]]
[[cv:Вăрçă]]
[[ceb:Gubat]]
[[cs:Válka]]
[[ch:Gera]]
[[sn:Hondo]]
[[cy:Rhyfel]]
[[da:Krig]]
[[pdc:Grieg]]
[[de:Krieg]]
[[et:Sõda]]
[[el:Πόλεμος]]
[[es:Guerra]]
[[eo:Milito]]
[[ext:Guerra]]
[[eu:Gerra]]
[[fa:جنگ]]
[[hif:Yudh]]
[[fr:Guerre]]
[[fy:Oarloch]]
[[fur:Vuere]]
[[ga:Cogadh]]
[[gd:Cogadh]]
[[gl:Guerra]]
[[gan:打仗]]
[[ko:전쟁]]
[[hy:Պատերազմ]]
[[hi:संग्राम]]
[[hr:Rat]]
[[id:Perang]]
[[ia:Guerra]]
[[iu:ᐊᑭᕋᖅᑑᑎᔪᑦ]]
[[is:Stríð]]
[[it:Guerra]]
[[he:מלחמה]]
[[jv:Perang]]
[[kn:ಯುದ್ಧ]]
[[krc:Къазауат]]
[[ka:ომი]]
[[kk:Соғыс]]
[[sw:Vita]]
[[kv:Тыш]]
[[kg:Vita]]
[[ht:Lagè]]
[[ku:Şer]]
[[ky:Согуш]]
[[la:Bellum]]
[[lv:Karš]]
[[lb:Krich]]
[[lt:Karas]]
[[hu:Háború]]
[[mk:Војна]]
[[ml:യുദ്ധം]]
[[mr:युद्ध]]
[[arz:حرب]]
[[ms:Peperangan]]
[[mwl:Guerra]]
[[mn:Дайн]]
[[nl:Oorlog]]
[[nds-nl:Kraig]]
[[new:हताः]]
[[ja:戦争]]
[[no:Krig]]
[[nn:Krig]]
[[nrm:Dgèrre]]
[[oc:Guèrra]]
[[mhr:Сар]]
[[pnb:لڑائی]]
[[ps:جګړه]]
[[nds:Krieg]]
[[pl:Wojna]]
[[pt:Guerra]]
[[ksh:Kreech]]
[[ro:Război]]
[[qu:Maqanakuy]]
[[rue:Война]]
[[ru:Война]]
[[sa:युद्धम्]]
[[sq:Lufta]]
[[scn:Guerra]]
[[si:යුද්ධය]]
[[simple:War]]
[[sk:Vojna]]
[[sl:Vojna]]
[[so:Dagaalada]]
[[sr:Рат]]
[[sh:Rat]]
[[fi:Sota]]
[[sv:Krig]]
[[tl:Digmaan]]
[[ta:போர்]]
[[te:యుద్ధం]]
[[th:สงคราม]]
[[tr:Savaş]]
[[uk:Війна]]
[[ur:جنگ]]
[[vec:Guera]]
[[vi:Chiến tranh]]
[[fiu-vro:Sõda]]
[[wa:Guere]]
[[war:Gerá]]
[[xh:Imfazwe]]
[[yi:מלחמה]]
[[yo:Ogun]]
[[zh-yue:打仗]]
[[bat-smg:Vaina]]
[[zh:战争]]</text>
      <sha1>q0lcya052eiund2iq46h3yov7t6q16r</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
