<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Working class</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18247421</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520940990</id>
      <parentid>520890495</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-01T19:31:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Rwood128</username>
        <id>11180150</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Further reading */Addition</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16936">{{For|the TV series|Working Class (TV series)}}
{{sociology}}
'''Working class''' (or '''lower class''', '''labouring class,''' sometimes '''[[proletariat]]''') is a term used in the [[social science]]s and in ordinary conversation to describe those employed in lower tier jobs (as measured by skill, education and lower incomes), often extending to those in [[unemployment]] or otherwise possessing below-average incomes. Working classes are mainly found in [[industrialized]] [[economy|economies]] and in [[urban area]]s of non-industrialized economies.

As with many terms describing [[social class]], ''working class'' is defined and used in many different ways. When used non-academically, it typically refers to a section of society dependent on physical [[labor (economics)|labor]], especially when compensated with an hourly [[wage]]. Its use in academic discourse is contentious, especially following the decline of manual labor in [[postindustrial]] societies.  It is often used synonymously for proletariat, particularly amongst Marxist authors.  Some academics question the usefulness of the concept of a working class{{Cn|date=June 2012}}. 

The term is usually contrasted with the ''[[upper class]]'' and ''[[middle class]]'', in general terms of access to economic resources, [[education]], cultural interests, and other goods and services. The cut-off between ''working class'' and ''middle class'' is more specifically where a population spends money primarily as a lifestyle rather than for sustenance (for example, on [[fashion]] versus merely [[nutrition]] and shelter). Problematically, relying on this method of distinction would rule out many of the people who are often identified as working class. 

Its usage can alternately be derogatory, or can express a sense of pride in those who self-identify as ''working class''.

==Definitions==
For purposes of [[political science]], and less scientific or journalistic political analysis, defining the working class as less well-educated workers is useful. One can then meaningfully analyze the political opinions and political behavior of, say, the white [[working class in the United States]]. In the case of the United States, for example, the white working class is often defined as white, non-Hispanic workers who have not completed college.&lt;ref name=NYTCanary&gt;{{cite news|title=Canaries in the CoaMine|url=http://campaignstops.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/06/17/canaries-in-the-coal-mine/|accessdate=June 18, 2012|newspaper=The New York Times|date=June 17, 2012|author=Thomas B. Edsall|authorlink=Thomas B. Edsall|format=Blog by expert}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

===Marxist definition===
{{main|proletariat}}
[[Image:battle strike 1934.jpg|thumb|300px|[[Class conflict|Class War]]: Workers in battle with the police during the [[Minneapolis Teamsters Strike of 1934]].]]
[[Karl Marx]] defined the working class or [[proletariat]] as individuals who [[wage labor|sell their labor power]] for [[wage]]s and who do not own the [[means of production]]. He argued that they were responsible for creating the [[wealth]] of a society.  He asserted that the working class physically build bridges, craft furniture, grow food, and nurse children, but do not own land, or [[factories]]. A sub-section of the proletariat, the [[lumpenproletariat]] (''rag-proletariat''), are the extremely poor and unemployed, such as [[day laborer]]s and [[homeless]] people.

In ''[[The Communist Manifesto]]'', Marx argued that it was the destiny of the working class to displace the [[capitalism|capitalist]] system, with the [[dictatorship of the proletariat]], abolishing the social relationships underpinning the class system and then developing into a future [[communist]] society in which &quot;the free development of each is the condition for the free development of all.&quot; In ''[[Das Kapital|Capital]]'', Marx dissected the ways in which capital can forestall such a revolutionary extension of the Enlightenment. Some issues in Marxist arguments about working class membership have included:
*The class status of people in a temporary or permanent position of [[unemployment]].
*The class status of [[domestic labor]], particularly the children (see [[child labor]]), and also traditionally the wives of male workers, as some spouses do not themselves work in paying jobs outside the home.
*Whether workers can be considered working class if they own [[personal property]] or small amounts of stock ownership.
*The relationships among peasants, rural smallholders, and the working class.
*The extent to which non-class group identities and politics (race, gender, et al.) can obviate or substitute for working class membership in Enlightenment projects, where working class membership is prohibitively contradictory or obfuscated.

Some answers to some of these issues, as argued, analyzed, and formulated over the centuries, are:
*Unemployed workers are proletariat.
*Class for dependents is determined by the primary income earner.
*Personal property is clearly different from private property. For example, the proletariat can own houses; this is personal property.
*The self-employed worker may be a member of the ''[[petite bourgeoisie]]'' (for example a highly paid professional, athlete, etc.), or a member of the proletariat (for example, a contract worker whose income may be relatively high but is precarious).
*Students' class status depends on that of their family, and also on whether they remain financially dependent on them.
*Race, gender and class are overlapping social stratification categories. It is possible for capitalists to strategically substitute the members of race, class, and gender groups to attain capitalist objectives; but once these stratification categories are formed and deployed, membership balkanizes experiences and interests.

In general, in Marxist terms, [[wage slavery|wage laborers]] and those dependent on the [[welfare state]] are working class, and those who live on accumulated capital and/or exploit the labor of others are not. This broad dichotomy defines the [[class struggle]]. Different groups and individuals may at any given time be on one side or the other. For example, retired factory workers are working class in the popular sense; but to the extent that they live off [[fixed income]]s, financed by stock in corporations whose earnings are [[surplus value|profit]] extracted from current workers, retired factory workers' interests, and possibly their identities and politics, are not working class. Such contradictions of interests and identity within individuals' lives and within communities can effectively undermine the ability of the working class to act in solidarity to reduce exploitation, inequality, and the role of ownership in determining people's life chances, work conditions, and political power.

The position of core capitalists is not nearly as contradictory within a capitalist system. Capitalists get their income, wealth, status, and power from owning the means of production, and they will have it managed for their own aggrandizement. From the capitalist perspective, it would be silly to manage production (or build political resources that could influence economic relationships) for the benefit of workers. To the extent that workers sometimes benefit in some ways from capitalism, it is not a central goal, but a byproduct. Thus, operating with less class interest contradiction and less identity contradiction, and more resources for political coordination, capitalist class members can often coordinate and prosecute their interests with a great deal of efficacy, over and against workers.

==History==
[[Image:Victorian Bishopgate.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Working class life in [[Victorian era|Victorian]] [[Wetherby]], [[West Yorkshire]], [[UK]].]]
The history of the working class has been defined by two contradictory processes, the immiseration of traditional communities in order to produce workers, and the vast surplus of production available from industrialization creating better living standards.  Throughout this process workers have taken cultural and political action to create their own cultures and positions within industrial society. Many of these responses have emphasized that working class individuals are defined by processes other than work. Working class history is generally accepted to begin with the enclosure of English commons, and the generation of paid industrial labor in manufactories in Holland and England.

In [[feudalism|feudal]] Europe, the working class as such did not exist in large numbers. Instead, most people were part of the laboring class, a group made up of different professions, trades and occupations. A lawyer, craftsman and peasant were all considered to be part of the same [[social unit]], a [[third estate]] of people who were neither [[aristocracy|aristocrats]] nor church officials. Similar hierarchies existed outside Europe in other [[pre-capitalist societies]]. The social position of these laboring classes was viewed as ordained by [[natural law]] and common religious belief. This social position was contested, particularly by peasants, for example during the [[German Peasants' War]].

[[Image:Coal Miner-27527.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Statue of a [[coal miner]] in [[Charleston, West Virginia]].]]
In the late 18th century, under the influence of the [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]], European society was in a state of change, and this change could not be reconciled with the idea of a changeless god-created social order. Wealthy members of these societies created ideologies which blamed many of the problems of working-class people on their morals and ethics (i.e. excessive consumption of alcohol, perceived laziness and inability to save money). In ''[[The Making of the English Working Class]]'', [[E.P. Thompson]] argues that the English working class was present at its own creation, and seeks to describe the transformation of pre-modern laboring classes into a modern, politically self-conscious, working class.

[[Vladimir Lenin]] saw the potential for [[imperialism]] to ameliorate the drudgery of working class life in the advanced countries, and argued this had already begun in the United Kingdom in the early 20th century. Access to cheap sports such as boxing and bicycling, expanded food cultures including coffee, chocolate and later junk food, and particularly access to motor vehicles and home ownership, transformed the complexion of first world working classes during the 20th century. A similar process occurred in the Soviet-style societies, but at a far slower pace.

Starting around 1917, a number of countries became ruled ostensibly in the interests of the working class. (see [[Soviet working class]]) While arguments over standards of living and potential growth rates have occurred in academic history and sociology, the development indexes of these countries are often higher than other countries of equivalent gross domestic product. However, additional criticisms have been leveled at these countries from authors who criticize the presence of massive human rights abuses which impacted primarily on workers, and for the lack of democracy within and amongst the working class. Some historians have noted that a key change in these Soviet-style societies has been a massive a new type of proletarianisation, often effected by the administratively achieved forced displacement of peasants and rural workers. Since then, three major industrial states have turned towards semi-market-based governance ([[China]], [[Laos]], [[Vietnam]], [[Cuba]]), and one state has turned inwards into an increasing cycle of poverty and brutalisation ([[North Korea]]). Other states of this sort have either collapsed (such as the [[Soviet Union]]), or never achieved significant levels of industrialization or large working classes.

Since 1960, large-scale proletarianisation and [[enclosure]] of commons has occurred in the [[third world]], generating new working classes at the margins of living. Additionally, countries such as [[India]] have been slowly undergoing social change, expanding the size of the urban working class.

==See also==
*[[Apprentice]]
*[[Embourgeoisement thesis|Embourgeoisement]]
*[[Globalization]]
*[[Household income in the United States]]
*[[Industrial novel]]
*[[Knowledge worker]]
*[[Labour movement]]
*[[Living wage]] and [[Minimum wage]]
*[[Proletarian literature]]
*[[Proletarian novel]]
*[[Social class]]
**[[Blue-collar worker]] and [[White-collar worker]]
**[[Bourgeoisie]]
**[[False Consciousness]]
**[[Lower middle class]]
**[[Middle class]]
**[[Proletarianization]]
**[[Proletariat]]
**[[Ruling class]]
**[[Reserve army of labor]]
**[[Underclass]] or [[Lumpenproletariat]]
**[[Upper middle class]]
**[[Upper class]]
**[[Working poor]]
*[[Social mobility]]
*[[Trade union]]
*[[Unfree labor]]
*[[US working class]]
*[[Vocational education]]
*[[Wage slavery]]
*[[Working class culture]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite article|title= Why workers can change the world |url=http://www.socialistreview.org.uk/article.php?articlenumber=11839|last= {{aut|Blackledge, Paul}} |year= 2011 |journal= Socialist Review ''364'' |location= London |}}
*Engels, Friedrich, ''Condition of the Working Class in England [in 1844]'', Stanford University Press (1968), trade paperback, ISBN 0-8047-0634-4 Numerous other editions exist; first published in German in 1845. Better editions include a preface written by Engels in 1892.
*Ernest Mandel, Workers under Neo-capitalism [http://www.marxists.org/archive/mandel/19xx/xx/neocap.htm]
*Moran, W. (2002). &lt;cite&gt;Belles of New England: The women of the textile mills and the families whose wealth they wove&lt;/cite&gt;. New York: St Martin's Press, ISBN 0-312-30183-9.
*Rose, Jonathan, ''The Intellectual Life of the British Working Classes''. New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 2001.
*Rubin, Lillian Breslow, ''Worlds of Pain: Life in the Working Class Family, Basic Books (1976), hardcover ISBN 0-465-09245-4; trade paperback, 268 pages, ISBN 0-465-09724-3
*Shipler, David K., ''The Working Poor: Invisible in America'', Knopf (2004), hardcover, 322 pages, ISBN 0-375-40890-8
*Skeggs, Beverley. ''Class, Self, Culture'', Routledge, (2004),
*Thompson, E.P, ''[[The Making of the English Working Class]]'' - paperback Penguin, ISBN 0-14-013603-7
*Zweig, Michael, ''Working Class Majority: America's Best Kept Secret'', Cornell University Press (2001), trade paperback, 198 pages, ISBN 0-8014-8727-7

==External links==
{{Wiktionary}}
*[http://cwcs.ysu.edu/ The Center for Working-Class Studies at Youngstown State University]
*[http://www.ilwch.rutgers.edu/ International Labor and Working-Class History Journal]
*[http://www.mccord-museum.qc.ca/en/collections/theme/17 Images of the working class between 1840 and 1945] from the McCord Museum's online collection
*[http://www.libcom.org/history libcom.org Working Class History page]
*[http://www.gerald-massey.org.uk/massey/bpm_poetry.htm The Working-Class poetry of Gerald Massey]
*[http://dictionary.reference.com/search?q=working+class Definition of &quot;Working Class&quot;], Dictionary.com
*[http://www.prole.info An introduction to the working class, Prole.info]
*[http://socserv.mcmaster.ca/labourstudies/graduate/gradPDF/ResourcesWS700.pdf Bibliography - WORK, WORKERS AND THEIR WORKPLACES]
*[http://www.mommaworks.com/report/how-to-balance-work-and-family-life-%E2%80%93-the-reality-of-working-moms.php Working Moms]
*[http://www.rebelgraphics.org/workingclassliterature.html List of Working Class Literature]
*[http://www.rebelgraphics.org/workingclassmovies.html List of Working Class Videos &amp;mdash; Movies, and Documentaries]
*[http://paulofreirefinland.org Paulo Freire Research Center–Finland]
*[http://www.bbc.co.uk/archive/working/ BBC Archive collection of TV &amp; Radio programmes about Working Class Britain]


{{Social class}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Working Class}}
[[Category:Socialism]]
[[Category:Social classes]]
[[Category:Labor]]
[[Category:Marxism]]
[[Category:Marxist theory]]
[[Category:Sociology index]]

[[ast:Clase obrera]]
[[cs:Dělnická třída]]
[[cy:Dosbarth gweithiol]]
[[da:Arbejderklasse]]
[[de:Arbeiterklasse]]
[[es:Clase obrera]]
[[eo:Laborista klaso]]
[[fa:طبقه کارگر]]
[[fr:Classe ouvrière]]
[[ga:Lucht oibre]]
[[hi:कामगार वर्ग]]
[[hr:Radnička klasa]]
[[id:Buruh]]
[[it:Classe lavoratrice]]
[[jv:Buruh]]
[[kk:Жұмысшылар]]
[[mk:Работничка класа]]
[[ja:労働者階級]]
[[no:Arbeiderklasse]]
[[nn:Arbeidarklassen]]
[[pt:Classe trabalhadora]]
[[qu:Llamk'aq]]
[[ru:Рабочий класс]]
[[simple:Working class]]
[[sk:Robotnícka trieda]]
[[sr:Радничка класа]]
[[sh:Radnička klasa]]
[[sv:Arbetarklass]]
[[tt:Эшче сыйныф]]
[[te:శ్రామిక వర్గం]]
[[tr:İşçi sınıfı]]
[[uk:Робітництво]]
[[vi:Giai cấp công nhân]]
[[zh:工人阶级]]</text>
      <sha1>ssg4qhndhyzr17z5rzqrg4y42xwvbyn</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
