<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Workers' self-management</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1864690</id>
    <revision>
      <id>505860246</id>
      <parentid>497750911</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-08-05T06:23:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>151.28.104.82</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Wording mistakenly suggested that Tito-Stalin split was because of self-management - in fact took place earlier, in c. 1947-8</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17533">[[File:Autogestion.jpg|thumb|right|Poster for the Movimiento Nacional de Empresas Recuperadas (MNER), at a worker-recovered print shop, Chilavert Artes Gráficas in [[Buenos Aires]]]]
'''Worker self-management''' (sometimes called '''workers' control''' or '''autogestion''') is a form of workplace decision-making in which the workers themselves agree on choices (for issues such as customer care, general production methods, scheduling, division of labour) instead of an owner or traditional supervisor telling workers what to do, how to do it and where to do it. Examples of such self-management allegedly include the [[Paris Commune]], the [[Russian Revolution (1917)|Russian Revolution]], the [[German Revolution of 1918–19|German Revolution]], the [[Spanish Revolution]], [[Titoist]] [[Yugoslavia]], [[Algeria]] under [[Ahmed Ben Bella]], the ''fábricas recuperadas'' movement in [[Argentina]], the [[LIP factory]] in [[France]] in the 1970s, the [[Mondragón Cooperative Corporation]] which is the [[Basque Country (autonomous community)|Basque Country]]'s largest corporation, [[AK Press]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.akpress.org AKPress.org]&lt;/ref&gt; in the [[United States]], etc.

Argentina's ''fábricas recuperadas'' movement, which emerged in response to Argentine's [[Argentine economic crisis|2001 economic crisis]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Galafassi2004p222&quot;/&gt; is the current most significant workers' self-management phenomenon in the world.

English-language discussions of this phenomenon may employ several different translations of the original Spanish expression other than ''recovered factory''. For example, ''recuperated factory/business'', ''reclaimed factory'', and ''worker-run factory'' have been noted. The phenomenon is also known as &quot;autogestion,&quot; which comes from the French word for self-management (applied to factories, [[popular education]] systems, and other uses). Worker self-management may coincide with [[employee ownership]].

Workers' self-management is often the decision-making model used in co-operative economic arrangements such as [[worker cooperative]]s, [[workers' council]]s, [[participatory economics]], and similar arrangements where the workplace operates without a boss.  This model of decision making does not involve consulting all employees for every tiny issue in a time-consuming, inefficient and ineffective manner.  Real-world examples show that only large-scale decisions are made by all employees during council meetings and small decisions are made by those implementing them while coordinating with the rest and following more general agreements.

== Theory ==
{{Unreferenced section|date=August 2010}}
Autogestion was first theorized by [[Pierre-Joseph Proudhon]] during  the first part of the 19th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Proudhon|first=Pierre-Joseph|title='Oeuvres Complètes', volume 17|year=1866-1876|publisher=Lacroix|location=Paris|pages=188–9}}&lt;/ref&gt; It then became a primary component of some [[trade unions|trade union]] organizations, in particular [[anarcho-syndicalism|revolutionary syndicalism]] which was introduced in late 19th century France and [[guild socialism]] in early 20th century Britain, although both movements collapsed in the early 1920s. French trade-union [[Confédération Française Démocratique du Travail|CFDT]] (''&quot;Confédération Française Démocratique du Travail&quot;'') included worker self-management in its 1970 program, before later abandoning it. The philosophy of workers' self-management has been promoted by the [[Industrial Workers of the World]] (IWW) since its founding in the United States in 1905.

Critics of workers' self-management from the left, such as [[Gilles Dauvé]] and [[Jacques Camatte]], do not admonish the model as [[reactionary]] but simply as not [[progressivism|progressive]] in the context of developed [[capitalism]]. Such critics suggest that capitalism is more than a relationship of management. Rather, they suggest capitalism should be considered as a social totality which workers' self-management in and of itself only perpetuates and does not challenge - despite its seemingly radical content and activity. This theory is used to explain why self-management in Yugoslavia never advanced beyond the confines of the larger state monopoly economy, or why many modern worker-owned facilities tend to return to hiring managers and accountants after only a few years of operation.

== History ==
&lt;!-- Image with inadequate rationale removed: [[File:LIP movie.jpg|thumb|Movie poster: &quot;[[LIP (clockwork company)|LIP]], Imagination to Power&quot;, 2007.]] --&gt;
One significant experiment with workers' self-management took place during the [[Spanish Revolution]] (1936–1939).&lt;ref name=Dolgoff1974&gt;{{Citation
 | title = The Anarchist Collectives: Workers' Self-Management in the Spanish Revolution
 | year = 1974
 | author = Dolgoff, S.
 | isbn = 978-0-914156-03-1
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1950s, at the height of the [[Cold War]], [[Titoism|Titoist]] [[Yugoslavia]] advocated a [[socialist]] version of autogestion, in distinction from the [[Eastern Bloc]] countries, all of which practiced central planning and state ownership of industry. The [[economy of SFRY|economy of Yugoslavia]] was organized according to the theories of [[Josip Broz|Tito]] and &amp;ndash; more directly &amp;ndash; [[Edvard Kardelj]]. [[Croatia]]n scientist [[Branko Horvat]] also made a significant contribution to the theory of socialism (''radničko samoupravljanje'') as practiced in Yugoslavia. With the exception of a recession in the mid-1960s, the country's economy prospered under Titoist Socialism. Unemployment was low, the education level of the work force steadily increased. The life expectancy (which was about 72 years) and living standards of Yugoslav citizens was nearly equal to the life expectancy and living standards of  citizens of “western” capitalist countries such as [[Portugal]]. Due to Yugoslavia's neutrality and its leading role in the [[Non-Aligned Movement]], Yugoslav companies exported to both Western and Eastern markets. Yugoslav companies carried out construction of numerous major infrastructural and industrial projects in Africa, Europe and Asia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Liotta|first=P.H.|title=Paradigm Lost :Yugoslav Self-Management and the Economics of Disaster|url=http://balkanologie.revues.org/index681.html|accessdate=18 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Yugoslavia: Introduction of Socialist Self-Management|url=http://www.country-data.com/cgi-bin/query/r-14787.html|publisher=Country Data|accessdate=18 August 2010|date=December 1990}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After [[May 1968 in France|May 68]] in [[France]], [[LIP factory]], a clockwork factory based in [[Besançon]], became self-managed starting in 1973, after the management's decision to liquidate it. The LIP experience was an emblematic social conflict of post-68 in France. [[Confédération Française Démocratique du Travail|CFDT]] (the CCT as it was referred to in Northern Spain), trade-unionist Charles Piaget led the strike in which workers claimed the [[means of production]]. The [[Unified Socialist Party (France)|Unified Socialist Party]] (PSU), which included former [[Radical and Socialist Party (France)|Radical]] [[Pierre Mendès-France]], was in favour of ''autogestion'' or self-management.&lt;ref name=Halimi&gt;[http://www.monde-diplomatique.fr/carnet/2007-03-20-LIP LIP, l'imagination au pouvoir], article by [[Serge Halimi]] in ''[[Le Monde diplomatique]]'', 20 March 2007 {{Fr icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== South America ==
In October 2005 the first ''Encuentro Latinoamericano de Empresas Recuperadas'' (&quot;Latin American  Encounter of Recovered Companies&quot;) took place in [[Caracas]], [[Venezuela]], with representatives of 263 such companies from different countries living through similar economical and social situations. The meeting had, as its main outcome, the ''Compromiso de Caracas'' (Caracas' Commitment); a vindicating text of the movement.
[[File:Hotel bauen.jpg|thumb|right|The [[Hotel Bauen]] in Buenos Aires, occupied and self-managed since 2003.]]

===The ''fábricas recuperadas'' movement (Argentina)===
Argentina's ''fábricas recuperadas'' movement, which emerged in response to Argentine's [[Argentine economic crisis|2001 economic crisis]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Galafassi2004p222&quot;/&gt; is the current most significant workers' self-management phenomenon in the world. Workers took over control of the factories in which they had worked, commonly after [[bankruptcy]], or after a [[Occupation of factories|factory occupation]] to circumvent a [[lockout (industry)|lockout]]. 

''Fábricas recuperadas'' means &quot;reclaimed/recovered factories.&quot; The Spanish verb ''recuperar'' means not only &quot;to get back&quot;, &quot;to take back&quot; or &quot;to reclaim&quot; but also &quot;to put back into good condition&quot;. Although initially referring to industrial facilities, the term may also apply to businesses other than factories (e.g. [[Hotel Bauen]] in [[Buenos Aires]]).

Throughout the 1990s in [[History of Argentina|Argentina]]'s southern province of [[Neuquén Province|Neuquén]], drastic economic and political events occurred where the citizens ultimately rose up.  Although the first shift occurred in a single factory, bosses were progressively fired throughout the province so that by 2005 the workers of the province controlled most of the factories.

The movement emerged as a response to Argentine's [[Argentine economic crisis|2001 economic crisis]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Galafassi2004p222&quot;&gt;Guido Galafassi, Paula Lenguita, Robinson Salazar Perez (2004) [http://books.google.com/books?id=XLTEMYfB4bEC&amp;pg=PA239 ''Nuevas Practicas Politicas Insumisas En Argentina''] pp.222, 238&lt;/ref&gt; and about 200 Argentine companies were &quot;recovered&quot; by their workers and turned into co-operatives. Prominent examples include the [[Brukman factory]], the [[Hotel Bauen]] and [[FaSinPat]] (formerly known as Zanon). As of 2005, about 15,000 Argentine workers run recovered factories.

The phenomenon of ''fabricas recuperadas'' (&quot;recovered factories&quot;) is not new in Argentina. Rather, such [[social movement]]s were completely dismantled during the so-called &quot;[[Dirty War]]&quot; in the 1970s. Thus, during [[Héctor Cámpora]]'s first months of government (May–July 1973), a rather moderate and left-wing [[Peronist]], approximately 600 social conflicts, strikes and factory occupations had taken place.&lt;ref&gt;Hugo Moreno, ''Le désastre argentin. Péronisme, politique et violence sociale (1930-2001)'', [[Editions Syllepses]], Paris, 2005, p.109 {{fr icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many recovered factories are run co-operatively and all workers receive the same [[wage]]. Important management decisions are taken [[direct democracy|democratically]] by an assembly of all workers, rather than by professional managers.

The proliferation of these &quot;recoveries&quot; has led to the formation of a '''recovered factory movement''', which has ties to a diverse political network including [[socialists]], [[Peronists]], [[anarchists]] and [[communists]]. Organizationally, this includes two major federations of recovered factories, the larger [http://www.mnerweb.com.ar/ Movimiento Nacional de Empresas Recuperadas] (or National Movement of Recuperated Businesses, or MNER) on the left and the smaller National Movement of Recuperated Factories (MNFR)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fabricasrecuperadas.org.ar/ Movimiento Nacional de Fabricas Recuperadas]&lt;/ref&gt; on the right.&lt;ref&gt;Marie Trigona, [http://www.zmag.org/content/showarticle.cfm?ItemID=995 Recuperated Enterprises in Argentina - Reversing the Logic of Capitalism], Znet, March 27, 2006 {{en icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some [[labor union]]s, unemployed protestors (known as [[piquetero]]s), traditional [[worker cooperative]]s and a range of political groups have also provided support for these take-overs. In March 2003, with the help of the MNER, former employees of the luxury [[Hotel Bauen]] occupied the building and took control of it.

One of the highest difficulties such a movement faces is its relation towards the classic [[economic]] system, as most classically managed firms refused,{{Verify source|date=June 2010}} for various reasons (among which ideological hostility to the very principle of autogestion) to work and deal with recovered factories. Thus, isolated recovered factories find it easier to work together in building an alternative, more [[economic democracy|democratic economic system]] and thus manage to reach a critical size and power which enables it to negotiate with the ordinary capitalistic firms.

The movement led in 2011 to a new [[bankruptcy]] law that facilitates take over by the workers.&lt;ref&gt;Pagina12: [http://www.pagina12.com.ar/diario/suplementos/cash/35-5106-2011-04-17.html ''Nueva Ley de Quiebras''] (April 2011), [http://www.pagina12.com.ar/diario/economia/2-169306-2011-06-02.html ''Fábricas recuperadas y también legales''] (June 2nd 2011)&lt;/ref&gt; The legislation was signed into law by President [[Cristina Kirchner]] on June 29, 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pagina1220110629&quot;&gt;[http://www.pagina12.com.ar/diario/ultimas/20-171094-2011-06-29.html ''CFK promulgó la reforma de la Ley de Quiebras''] in ''[[Página/12]]'', June 29th 2011&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- 
To expand: legal problems and appeals, threats of eviction and resistance, new conception of ownership --&gt;

==See also==
{|
|
* [[Anarcho-syndicalism]]
* [[Austromarxism]]
* [[Ceylon Transport Board]]
* [[Collectivism]]
* [[Consensus decision-making]]
* [[Co-operatives]]
* [[Council communism]]
* [[Direct democracy]]
* [[Distributism]]
* [[Edvard Kardelj]], a Yugoslavian Communist Party leader
* [[Employee ownership]]
* [[Inclusive Democracy]]
* [[Industrial democracy]]
* [[Mutualism (economic theory)]]
* [[Mondragón Corporation]], probably the world's largest self-managed enterprise
|
* [[Orpheus Chamber Orchestra]]
* [[Paris Commune|Paris Commune of 1871]]
* [[Participatory economics]]
* [[Popular Education]]
* [[The Take (2004 film)|''The Take'' (2004 film)]], documentary about reclaimed factories and worker co-operatives in Argentina
* [[Unified Socialist Party (France)]]
* [[United States Federation of Worker Cooperatives]]
* [[Worker cooperative]]
* [[Workers' control]]
* [[Workers' council]]
* [[Workplace democracy]]
* [[1971 Harco work-in]] (a four-week &quot;work-in&quot; by Australian steelworkers)
|}

== Notes ==
{{Reflist}}

== References ==
* {{cite book |last=Bolloten |first=Burnett |authorlink=Burnett Bolloten |title=The Spanish Civil War: Revolution and Counterrevolution |year=1991 |publisher=University of North Carolina |location=Chapel Hill |isbn=0-8078-1906-9}}

==Further reading==
*''For All The People: Uncovering the Hidden History of Cooperation, Cooperative Movements, and Communalism in America'', PM Press, by John Curl, 2009, ISBN 978-1-60486-072-6

==External links==
* [[n:Argentinian workers preparing to defend control of factory|Argentinian workers preparing to defend control of factory]], April 26, 2005
* [http://www.ww4report.com/node/756 THE NEW RESISTANCE IN ARGENTINA], by Yeidy Rosa
* [http://www.nodo50.org/cubasigloXXI/congreso/flaherty_15abr03.pdf Self-management and Requirements for Social Property: Lessons from Yugoslavia by Diane Flaherty]
* [http://libcom.org/library/worker-self-management-in-historical-perspective Worker self-management in historical perspective by James Petras and Henry Veltmeyer]
* [http://www.zmag.org/znet/viewArticle/21721 Sources Of The Democratic Deficit In The Yugoslav System Of &quot;Self-Government&quot; by Dan Jakopovich ]
* [http://www.fabricasrecuperadas.org.ar/ Movimiento Nacional de Fabricas Recuperadas] (National Movement of Recovered Factories, Spanish only)
* [http://www.globaljusticecenter.org/papers2006/ruggeriENG.htm  The Worker-Recovered Enterprises in Argentina: The Political and Socioeconomic Challenges of Self-Management] Andrés Ruggeri, University of Buenos Aires, Argentina
* [http://www.elcambiosilencioso.com.ar Official site for El Cambio Silencioso, book on recovered factories] by Esteban Magnani (Spanish and English mostly)
* [http://lsj.sagepub.com/content/35/3/295.abstract The Social Innovations of Autogestión in Argentina’s Worker-Recuperated Enterprises: Cooperatively Reorganizing Productive Life in Hard Times (Labor Studies Journal, 2010)] by Marcelo Vieta
* [http://www.tectum-verlag.de/9912_Kristina_Hille_Die_%93empresas_recuperadas%93_in_Argentinien._Selbsthilfe_von_Erwerbslosen_in_Krisenzeiten_%93Reaktivierte_Unternehmen%93_Arbeiterselbstverwaltung_%93Soziale_Bewegungen_%93Cono_Sur%93_Peronismus_Gewerkschaften_Wirtschaftskrise_Insolvenz_Enteignung. Selbsthilfe von Erwerbslosen in Krisenzeiten. Die empresas recuperadas in Argentinien, by Kristina Hille]

{{Co-operatives}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Workers' Self-Management}}
[[Category:Political philosophy]]
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Socialism]]
[[Category:Anarchist theory]]
[[Category:Social philosophy]]
[[Category:Cooperatives]]
[[Category:Recovered factories]]
[[Category:Labor]]
[[Category:Labour relations]]

[[ar:إدارة العمال الذاتية]]
[[br:Emveradur]]
[[ca:Autogestió]]
[[cs:Samospráva pracujících]]
[[de:Kollektive Selbstverwaltung]]
[[es:Empresa de trabajo asociado]]
[[eo:Memzorgismo]]
[[eu:Autogestio]]
[[fr:Autogestion]]
[[gl:Autoxestión]]
[[he:ניהול עצמי (עבודה)]]
[[ja:自主管理]]
[[nl:Arbeiderszelfbestuur]]
[[no:Arbeiderselvstyre]]
[[nn:Arbeidarsjølvstyre]]
[[pl:Samorządność pracownicza]]
[[pt:Autogestão]]
[[ru:Рабочее самоуправление]]
[[sr:Samoupravljanje]]
[[sv:Självförvaltning]]
[[tr:Özyönetim]]
[[zh:工人自治]]</text>
      <sha1>24yfvc1eetkojq2qflw6anzcj3rrhq8</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
