<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Worker center</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6317344</id>
    <revision>
      <id>491527255</id>
      <parentid>437624275</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-05-09T04:45:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Helpful Pixie Bot</username>
        <id>14216826</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>ISBNs (Build KE)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3966">'''Worker centers''' (alternatively workers' centers or workers centers) are [[non-profit]] organizations that organize workers who are not already members of a collective bargaining organization (such as a [[trade union]]). Many worker centers in the United States focus on immigrant workers, and most focus on low-wage workers in sectors such as restaurant, construction, [[day labor]] or agriculture. In the United States, over 130 such worker centers exist, as defined by [[Janice Fine]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Fine&quot;&gt;Fine, &quot;Worker Centers,&quot; ''EPI Briefing Paper #159,'' December 14, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Definition==
Fine defines worker centers as: &quot;community-based and community-led organizations that engage in a combination of service, advocacy, and organizing to provide support to low-wage workers. The vast majority of them have grown up to serve predominantly or exclusively immigrant populations. However, there are a few centers that serve a primarily African American population or bring immigrants together with African Americans.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fine&quot; /&gt;

José Oliva, director of the [[Interfaith Worker Justice]] network of worker centers, emphasizes that worker centers perform three main functions: service, organizing and advocacy. While many other organizations provide services, or advocate on behalf of low-wage workers, only worker centers perform all three functions for workers outside of traditional [[trade union]]s.

==Networks==
Nationally, there exist at least two networks that link worker centers together:

:1. The [[National Day Laborer Organizing Network]] (NDLON) that works with approximately 30 day labor centers.
:2. [[Interfaith Worker Justice]] (IWJ), which connects 14 worker centers that have strong ties to religious communities.

In August 2006, NDLON announced a new partnership with the [[AFL-CIO]]:
&quot;The AFL-CIO and NDLON will work together for state and local enforcement of rights as well as the development of new protections in areas including wage and hour laws, health and safety regulations, immigrants’ rights and employee misclassification.  They will also work together for comprehensive immigration reform that supports workplace rights and includes a path to citizenship and political equality for immigrant workers – and against punitive, anti-immigrant, anti-worker legislation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;AFL-CIO &amp; NDLON Enter Watershed Agreement to Improve Conditions for Working Families,&quot; press release, National Day Laborer Organizing Network, August 9, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

This partnership stems from the AFL-CIO's decision to embrace immigrant workers, a change from the federation's policies in the 1980s and 1990s.

==Notes==
&lt;references /&gt;

==References==
*[http://ndlon.org/press/pressrafl8-06.htm &quot;AFL-CIO &amp; NDLON Enter Watershed Agreement to Improve Conditions for Working Families.&quot; Press release. National Day Laborer Organizing Network. August 9, 2006.]
*Fine, Janice. ''Worker Centers: Organizing Communities at the Edge of the Dream.'' Ithaca, N.Y.: Cornell University Press, 2006. ISBN 0-8014-4423-3
*[http://www.epinet.org/content.cfm?id=2221 Fine, Janice. &quot;Worker Centers: Organizing Communities at the Edge of the Dream.&quot; ''EPI Briefing Paper #159.'' December 14, 2005.]
*Gordon, Jennifer. &quot;Immigrants Fight the Power: Workers Centers Are One Path to Labor Organizing and Political Participation.&quot; ''The Nation.'' January 3, 2000.
*Hollens, Mary. &quot;Workers Center: Organizing in Both the Workplace and Community.&quot; ''Labor Notes.'' September 1994.
*Levine, David. &quot;New York Workers' Centers: Creative Response to Growth of Modern Day Sweatshops.&quot; ''Independent Politics.'' July/August 1995.
*Ten Eyck, Tiffany. &quot;Workers Centers Increasingly Are Forging Alliances with Unions.&quot; ''Labor Notes.'' January 2007.

==External links==
*[http://www.iwj.org InterFaith Worker Justice]
*[http://www.ndlon.org/ National Day Labor Organizing Network]

[[Category:Non-profit organizations]]
[[Category:Labour relations]]
[[Category:Activism]]</text>
      <sha1>qleju4gv85xcu7u0g0gmnwrjwdvb5fo</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
