<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>World Network of Users and Survivors of Psychiatry</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3781123</id>
    <revision>
      <id>482602235</id>
      <parentid>458191674</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-03-18T20:46:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Johnfos</username>
        <id>3046455</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>template</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9059">The '''World Network of Users and Survivors of Psychiatry''' ('''WNUSP''') is an international organisation representing, and led by &quot;[[Psychiatric survivors movement|survivors]] of [[psychiatry]]&quot;. As of 2003, over 70 national organizations were members of WNUSP, based in 30 countries.[http://www.un.org/esa/socdev/enable/rights/contrib-wnusp.htm] The network seeks to protect and develop the [[human rights]], [[disability rights]], [[dignity]] and self-determination of those [[labeling theory|labeled]] as '[[Mental disorder|mentally ill]]'.

==Activities==
WNUSP has special consultative status with the [[United Nations]]. It contributed to the development of the UN's [[Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities]].[http://www.un.org/esa/socdev/enable/rights/wgcontrib-wnusp.htm][http://www.un.org/esa/socdev/enable/rights/contrib-wnusp.htm] WNUSP has produced a manual to help people use it called &quot;Implementation Manual for the United Nations Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities.&quot; [http://wnusp.rafus.dk/documents/WNUSP_CRPD_Manual.doc]

WNUSP joined with other organizations to create the International Disability Caucus, which jointly represented organizations of people with disabilities and allies during the CRPD negotiations.  WNUSP was part of the steering committee of the IDC, which maintained a principle of respecting the leadership of diverse constituencies on issues affecting them, and also maintained that the convention should be of equal value to all persons with disabilities irrespective of the type of disability or geographical location.  Tina Minkowitz, WNUSP's representative on the IDC steering committee, coordinated the IDC's work on key articles of the CRPD, including those on legal capacity, liberty, torture and ill-treatment and integrity of the person. Since the adoption and entry into force of the CRPD, WNUSP has worked with other organizations in the International Disability Alliance and its CRPD Forum to guide the interpretation and application of the CRPD on these issues.[http://wnusp.rafus.dk/crpd.html] 

In 2007 at a Conference held in Dresden on &quot;Coercive Treatment in Psychiatry: A Comprehensive Review&quot;, the president and other leaders of the [[World Psychiatric Association]] met, following a formal request from the World Health Organization, with four representatives from the user/survivor movement, including Judi Chamberlin, co-chair of WNUSP, who participated in her personal capacity.&lt;ref&gt;Mezzichi, J.E. (2007) [http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=2174591 The dialogal basis of our profession: Psychiatry with the Person World Psychiatry.] 2007 October; 6(3): 129–130.&lt;/ref&gt;

Moosa Salie is the current Chair of WNUSP.

Current International Representative and former co-chair of WNUSP is Tina Minkowitz, an international advocate and lawyer.[http://www.un.org/disabilities/default.asp?id=163] She represented WNUSP in the Working Group convened by the UN to produce a draft text of the Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities [http://www.un.org/esa/socdev/enable/rights/ahcwg.htm#membership] and contributed to a UN seminar on torture and persons with disabilities [http://www.ohchr.org/english/issues/disability/seminartorturereportfinal.doc][http://www.ohchr.org/english/issues/disability/docs/torture/AnnexIII.ppt] that resulted in an important report on the issue by Special Rapporteur on Torture Manfred Nowak in 2008.[http://www.ohchr.org/english/issues/disability/docs/A.63.175_en.doc]

==Core values==
The core values of WNUSP, in representating a diversity of perspectives within the user/survivor movement or psychiatric survivors movement, guide its activities and assists in determining the focus of the network.  These values stress [[empowerment]], equality, self-determination, [[respect]], dignity, independence, hearing voices, mutual support, self-help, advocacy, education, and the right to pursue individual spiritual beliefs.

WNUSP values exposure to information and knowledge as means to enabling empowerment and individual self-direction, understanding that knowledge results in better-informed choices and opportunities to enhance [[quality of life]].  The network ascribes to person-centred values where the individual is more important than any diagnostic label or experience in dealing with the mental health system.  WNUSP believes the experiences of living with madness or mental health problems can be valuable in exploring human experience, both to individuals and society, and that those suffering distress may offer invaluable insights to necessary changes in mental health diagnosis, treatment and laws.

==History==

Since the 1970s, the  psychiatric survivors movement has grown from a few scattered self-help groups to a world-wide network engaged in protecting [[civil rights]] and facilitation of efforts to provide [[House|housing]], [[employment]], public [[education]], [[research]], socialisation and [[advocacy]] programmes.  The term 'psychiatric survivor' is used by individuals who identify themselves as having experienced human rights violations in the mental health system.  WNUSP was established to further promote this movement and to respond on an international level to the oppression survivors continue to experience.

After initially meeting, in 1991, as the World Federation of Psychiatric Users at the biennial [[World Federation for Mental Health]] conference in [[Mexico]], the network's name was changed to WNUSP in 1997.  In 2000, the WNUSP Secretariat was established in [[Odense]], [[Denmark]].  In 2001, the network held its First General Assembly in [[Vancouver, British Columbia]], with 34 groups from twelve countries represented, and adopted its governing statutes.

In 2004, the network held its Second General Assembly in [[Vejle, Denmark]] with 150 participants from 50 countries attending.  

In 2007 WNUSP received ECOSOC special consultative status at the United Nations.

In 2009, WNUSP held its third General Assembly in Kampala, Uganda.  It adopted the Kampala Declaration stating its positions on the CRPD, which was later expanded into a longer version adopted by consensus of the board and the participants in the Kampala GA.[http://wnusp.rafus.dk/general-assemblies/]

==ENUSP==
The European Network of (Ex)Users and Survivors of Psychiatry is the most important European [[NGO]] of (ex-)users and survivors. Forty-two representatives from 16 European countries met at a conference to found it in the Netherlands in October 1991. Every 2 years, delegates from the ENUSP members in more than 40 European countries meet at a conference where the policies for the coming period are set out. All delegates are (ex-)users and survivors of psychiatry. ENUSP is officially involved in consultations on mental health plans and policies of the [[European Union]], [[World Health Organization]] and other important bodies. Initial funding came from the Dutch government and from the European Commission but has since proved more difficult to secure. ENUSP is involved in commenting and debating declarations, position papers, policy guidelines of the EU, UN, WHO and other important bodies.&lt;ref&gt;Hollis, I. (2002) [http://www3.interscience.wiley.com/journal/119016304/abstract About the impossibility of a single (ex-)user and survivor of psychiatry position] Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavica Volume 104 Issue s410, Pages 102 - 106&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Anti-psychiatry]]
*[[Icarus Project]]
*[[Involuntary commitment]]
*[[MindFreedom International]]
*[[Community Alliance for the Ethical Treatment of Youth]]
*[[EUFAMI]]
*[[Judi Chamberlin]]

==External links==
*[http://www.wnusp.net WNUSP] - World Network of Users and Survivors of Psychiatry (WNUSP main web site)
*[http://www.enusp.org/index.htm ENUSP] - [[European Network of (ex-)Users and Survivors of Psychiatry]] (ENUSP)
**[http://www.enusp.org/congresses/vejle/press-release.htm ENUSP.org] - 'ENUSP Press Release' (July 20, 2004)
*[http://www.inclusion-international.org/en/ii_initiatives/13.html Inclusion-International.org] - [[International Disability Alliance]]
*[http://moosa-salie.oism.info/ Moosa-Salie.oism.info] - 'Launching Conference of the [[Pan African Network of Users and Survivors of Psychiatry]] (PANUSP)', Moosa Salie (WNUSP board co-chair)
*[http://www.chrusp.org CHRUSP] - Center for the Human Rights of Users and Survivors of Psychiatry
*[http://www.un.org/esa/socdev/enable/rights/wgcontrib-wnusp.htm UN.org] - 'Contribution by World Network of Users and Survivors of Psychiatry', United Nations Ad Hoc Committee on a Comprehensive and Integral International Convention on the Protection and Promotion of the Rights and Dignity of Persons with Disabilities (January, 2004)

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Anti-psychiatry}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:World Network Of Users And Survivors Of Psychiatry}}
[[Category:1991 establishments]]
[[Category:Anti-psychiatry]]
[[Category:Civil disobedience]]
[[Category:Disability rights organizations]]
[[Category:Psychiatric survivor activists]]</text>
      <sha1>s5jvbjt7m4674akox6bo62m80bhb0eg</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
