<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Write-in candidate</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>480905</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522226450</id>
      <parentid>522225575</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T20:00:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Victor Victoria</username>
        <id>10265385</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* As a protest vote */ Add Charles Darwin</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="30523">{{Use mdy dates|date=October 2012}}
{{Globalize/US|date=June 2011}}
{{Elections}}
A '''write-in candidate''' is a candidate in an election whose name does not appear on the [[ballot]], but for whom voters may [[vote]] nonetheless by writing in the person's name.  Some states and local jurisdictions allow a voter to affix a sticker with a write-in candidate's name on it to the ballot in lieu of actually writing in the candidate's name. Write-in candidacies are sometimes a result of a candidate being legally or procedurally ineligible to run under his or her own name or party. In some cases, write-in campaigns have been organized to support a candidate who is not personally involved in running; this may be a form of [[Draft (politics)|draft]] campaign.

Write-in candidates rarely win, and votes are often cast for ineligible people or fictional characters.  Some jurisdictions require write-in candidates be registered as official candidates before the election.&lt;ref&gt;See, for example, Section 1-4-1101, Colorado Revised Statutes (2008)&lt;/ref&gt;  This is standard in elections with a large pool of potential candidates, as there may be multiple candidates with the same name that could be written in.

Many [[U.S. state]]s and municipalities allow for write-in votes in a partisan [[primary election]] where no candidate is listed on the ballot to have the same functional effect as nominating petitions: for example, if there are no [[Reform Party of the United States of America|Reform Party]] members on the ballot for state general assembly and a candidate receives more than 200 write-in votes when the primary election is held (or the other number of signatures that were required for ballot access), the candidate will be placed on the ballot on that ballot line for the general election.  In most places, this provision is in place for non-partisan elections as well.

==United States==
Typically, write-in candidates have a very small chance of winning, but there have been some notable write-in candidates in the past.

===Presidential primaries===
*In 1928, [[Herbert Hoover]] won the Republican Massachusetts presidential primary on write-ins, polling 100,279.

*In 1940, [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]] won the Democratic New Jersey presidential primary with 34,278 write-ins.

*In 1944, [[Thomas Dewey]] won the Republican Pennsylvania presidential primary with 146,706 write-ins.  He also won the Oregon Republican presidential primary with 50,001 write-ins.

*In 1948, [[Harold Stassen]] won the Republican Pennsylvania presidential primary with 81,242 write-ins.

*In 1952, [[Robert Taft]] won the Republican Nebraska presidential primary with 79,357 write-ins.

*Also in 1952, [[Estes Kefauver]] won the Democratic Pennsylvania presidential primary with 93,160 write-ins.

*Also in 1952, [[Dwight Eisenhower]] won the Republican Massachusetts presidential primary with 254,898 write-ins.

*In 1956, Dwight Eisenhower won the Republican Massachusetts presidential primary with 51,951 write-ins.

*In 1960, [[Richard Nixon]] won the Republican Massachusetts presidential primary with 53,164 write-ins.

*Also in 1960, [[John F. Kennedy]] won the Democratic Pennsylvania presidential primary with 183,073 write-ins, and he won the Democratic Massachusetts presidential primary with 91,607 write-ins.

* In 1964, a write-in campaign organized by supporters of former U.S. Senator and vice presidential nominee [[Henry Cabot Lodge, Jr.]] won Republican primaries for President in [[New Hampshire]], [[New Jersey]], and [[Massachusetts]], defeating declared candidates [[Barry Goldwater]], [[Nelson Rockefeller]], and [[Margaret Chase Smith]].

* In 1968 in the Democratic presidential primary in New Hampshire, incumbent President [[Lyndon Johnson]] did not file, but received write-ins totaling 50% of all Democratic votes cast. Senator [[Eugene McCarthy]], who campaigned actively against Johnson’s Vietnam war policies, was on the ballot. He received an impressive 41% of the vote and gained more delegates than the President. Johnson was so stunned that he did not run for reelection.&lt;ref name=&quot;New Hampshire’s First-In-The-Nation Presidential Primary&quot;&gt;[http://www.nh.gov/nhinfo/highlights.html New Hampshire Almanac &gt;First-in-the-Nation]&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[consumer protection|Consumer advocate]] [[Ralph Nader]] ran a write-in campaign in 1992 during the [[New Hampshire primary]] for the [[presidential nomination]] of both the Democratic and Republican parties. Declaring himself the &quot;[[none of the above]] candidate&quot; and using the [[Concord Principles]] as his platform, Nader received 3,054 votes from [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democrats]] and 3,258 votes from [[Republican Party (United States)|Republicans]].

===Senate===
* Republican [[William Knowland]] was elected in 1946 to the U.S. Senate from California, for a two-month term. The special election for the two-month term featured a November ballot with no names printed on it, and all candidates in that special election were write-in candidates.&lt;ref name=WashPost-2010-11-03-Wilgoren-Murkowski&gt;Washington Post, [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/11/03/AR2010110302555.html &quot;Murkowski appears to make history in Alaska&quot;], Debbi Wilgoren, November 3, 2010 (accessed November 3, 2010)&lt;/ref&gt;
* Democrat [[Strom Thurmond]] was [[South Carolina United States Senate election, 1954|elected in 1954]] to the [[United States Senate]] in [[South Carolina]] as a write-in candidate, after state Democratic leaders had blocked him from receiving the party's nomination.&lt;ref name=WashPost-2010-11-03-Wilgoren-Murkowski/&gt;
*In [[United States Senate election in Alaska, 2010|2010]] incumbent [[List of United States Senators from Alaska|Alaska Senator]] [[Lisa Murkowski]] lost the Republican primary to [[Joe Miller (Alaska politician)|Joe Miller]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.elections.alaska.gov/results/10PRIM/data/results.htm Official election results for the 2010 primaries]. Alaska Division of Elections.&lt;/ref&gt; Following her defeat she ran in the general election as a write in candidate. Murkowski had filed, and won, a lawsuit requiring election officials to have the list of names of write in candidates distributed at the polls&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2010/10/28/lisa-murkowski-can-appear_n_775221.html|work=Huffington Post|title=Lisa Murkowski Can Appear On List Of Write-In Candidates, State Supreme Court Rules|first=Dan|last=Joling|date=October 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and subsequently won the election with a wide enough margin over both Miller, and [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic Party]] candidate [[Scott T. McAdams]], to make moot the write-in ballots that had been challenged by Miller.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.boston.com/news/politics/articles/2010/11/18/murkowski_becomes_1st_write_in_senator_since_54/|title=Murkowski becomes 1st write-in senator since '54|date=November 18, 2010|first=Becky|last=Bohrer|agency=[[Associated Press]]|work=Boston Globe}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===House of Representatives===
* In 1918, [[Peter F. Tague]] was elected to the U.S. House as a write-in independent Democrat, defeating the Democratic nominee, [[John F. Fitzgerald]].
* In 1930 Republican [[Charles F. Curry, Jr.]] was elected to the House as a write-in from Sacramento, California. His father, [[Congress of the United States|Congressman]] [[Charles F. Curry]] Sr., was to appear on the ballot, but due to his untimely death his name was removed and no candidate's name appeared on the ballot.
* Democrat [[Dale Alford]] was elected as a write-in candidate to the [[United States House of Representatives]] in Arkansas in 1958. As member of the [[Little Rock School District|Little Rock school board]], Alford launched his write-in campaign a week before the election because the incumbent, [[Brooks Hays]], was involved in the incident in which [[Dwight D. Eisenhower|president Eisenhower]] sent federal troops to enforce [[racial integration]] at [[Central High School (Little Rock)|Little Rock Central High School]]. Racial integration was unpopular at the time, and Alford won by approximately 1,200 votes, a 2% margin.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rudin&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=5698889|title=What Happens If Lieberman Wins|publisher=[[National Public Radio]]|author=Ken Rudin|date=August 23, 2006|accessdate=2006-09-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Republican [[Joe Skeen]] was elected as a write-in candidate to Congress in New Mexico in November 1980 after the incumbent Democrat, [[Harold Runnels]], died in August of that year. No Republican filed to run against Runnels before the close of filing, and after the death, the New Mexico Secretary of State ruled that the Democrats could have a special primary to pick a replacement candidate, but the Republicans could not have a special election, since they had nobody to replace. Runnels' widow lost the special primary, and launched her own write-in candidacy, which split the Democratic vote and allowed Skeen to win with a 38% [[Plurality (voting)|plurality]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Rudin&quot;/&gt;
* [[Ron Packard]] of California finished in second place in the 18 candidate Republican primary to replace the retiring [[Clair Burgener]]. Packard lost the primary by 92 votes in 1982, and then mounted a write-in campaign as an independent. He won the election with a 37% [[Plurality (voting)|plurality]] against both a Republican and a Democratic candidate. Following the elections, he re-aligned himself as a Republican.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rudin&quot;/&gt;
* Democrat [[Charlie Wilson (Ohio politician)|Charlie Wilson]] was the endorsed candidate of the Democratic Party for [[Ohio's 6th congressional district]] in Ohio to replace [[Ted Strickland]] in 2006.  Strickland was running for Governor and had to give up his congressional seat. Wilson, though, did not qualify for the ballot because only 46 of the 96 signatures on his candidacy petition were deemed valid, while 50 valid signatures were required for ballot placement. The Democratic Party continued to support Wilson, and an expensive primary campaign ensued – over $1 million was spent by both parties. Wilson overwhelmingly won the Democratic primary as a write-in candidate on May 2, 2006 against two Democratic candidates whose names were on the ballot, with Wilson collecting 44,367 votes, 67% of the Democratic votes cast.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.columbusdispatch.com/news-story.php?story=183395|title=Wilson wins primary as write-in candidate|publisher=The Columbus Dispatch|first=Alan|last=Johnson|date=May 3, 2006|accessdate=2006-06-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; Wilson faced [[United States Republican Party|Republican]] Chuck Blasdel in the general election on November 7, 2006, and won, receiving 61% of the votes.
* Democrat [[Dave Loebsack]] entered the 2006 Democratic primary in Iowa's second congressional district as a write-in candidate after failing to get the required number of signatures. He won the primary and in the general election he defeated 15 term incumbent [[Jim Leach]] by a 51% to 49% margin.
* [[Jerry McNerney]] ran as a write-in candidate in the March 2004 Democratic Primary in [[California's 11th congressional district]]. He received 1,667 votes (3% of the votes cast), and, having no opposition (no candidates were listed on the Democratic primary ballot), won the primary.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sos.ca.gov/elections/sov/2004_primary/congress.pdf|format=PDF|title=Election Results for the March 2004 Primary|publisher=[[Secretary of State of California|California Secretary of State]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although he lost the November 2004 general election to Republican [[Richard Pombo]], McNerney ran again in 2006 (as a candidate listed on the ballot) and won the Democratic Primary in June, and then the rematch against Pombo in November.
*[[Shelley Sekula-Gibbs]] failed as a write-in candidate in the November 7, 2006 election to represent the 22nd Texas congressional district in the [[110th United States Congress|110th Congress]] (for the full term commencing January 3, 2007). The seat had been vacant since June 9, 2006, due to the resignation of the then representative [[Tom DeLay]]. Therefore, on the same ballot, there were two races: one for the 110th Congress, as well as a race for the unexpired portion of the term during the [[109th United States Congress|109th Congress]] (until January 3, 2007). Sekula-Gibbs won the race for the unexpired portion of the term during the 109th Congress as a candidate listed on the ballot. She could not be listed on the ballot for the full term because Texas law did not allow a replacement candidate to be listed on the ballot after the winner of the primary (Tom DeLay) has resigned.
*[[Peter Welch]], a Democrat representing [[Vermont]]'s sole congressional district, became both the Democratic and Republican nominee for the House when he ran for re-election in 2008. Because the Republicans did not field any candidate on the primary ballot, Welch won enough write-in votes to win the Republican nomination.&lt;ref name=&quot;VT Times Agnus&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Write-ins give Welch GOP nomination|date=September 18, 2008|url=http://www.timesargus.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20080918/NEWS02/809180364|publisher=The Barre Montpelier Times Agnus}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===State legislatures===
* [[Charlotte Burks]] won as a Democratic write-in candidate for the Tennessee State Senate seat left vacant when the incumbent, her husband [[Tommy Burks|Tommy]], was assassinated by his opponent, [[Byron Looper]], two weeks before the elections of November 2, 1998. The assassin was the only name on the ballot, so Charlotte ran as a write in candidate.
* [[Carl Hawkinson]] of [[Galesburg, Illinois|Galesburg]], Illinois won the Republican primary for State Senator from Illinois's 47th District in 1986 as a write-in candidate. He went on to be elected in the general election and served until 2003. Hawkinson defeated another write-in, David Leitch, in the primary. Incumbent State Senator Prescott Bloom died in a home fire after the filing date for the primary had passed.
* Several members of the [[Alaska House of Representatives]] were elected as write-in candidates during the 1960s and 1970s, particularly from [[The Bush (Alaska)|rural districts]] in the [[Far North Alaska|northern and western portions of the state]].  Factors in play at the time include the newness of Alaska as a state and the previous absence of electoral politics in many of the rural communities, creating an environment which made it hard to attract candidates to file for office during the official filing period.  Most of the areas in question were largely populated by [[Alaska natives]], who held little political power in Alaska at the time.  This only began to change following the formation of the [[Alaska Federation of Natives]] and the passage of the [[Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act]].  Known examples of successful write-in candidates include Kenneth A. Garrison and [[Society of Jesus|Father]] [[Segundo Llorente]] (1960), Frank R. Ferguson (1972), James H. &quot;Jimmy&quot; Huntington (1974) and Nels A. Anderson, Jr. (1976).  The incumbent in Llorente's election, Axel C. Johnson, ran for re-election as a write-in candidate after failing to formally file his candidacy paperwork.  Johnson and Llorente, as write-in candidates, both outpolled the one candidate who did appear on the ballot. Ferguson and Anderson were both incumbents who launched their write-in campaigns after being defeated in the [[primary election]].  Anderson's main opponent, Joseph McGill, had himself won election to the House in 1970 against a write-in candidate by only 5 votes.
*After failing to receive the Republican Party's 1990 [[Wilson Pakula]] nomination, incumbent and registered [[Conservative Party of New York State|Conservative]] New York State Senator [[Serphin Maltese]] won the party's nomination as a write-in candidate.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.queensnewyork.com/elections/senateny/maltese.html Serphin R. Maltese R-C]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Local government===
* Julia Allen of [[Readington Township, New Jersey|Readington]], New Jersey won a write-in campaign in the November 2005 elections for the Township Committee,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.co.hunterdon.nj.us/election/2005general/readington.htm#committee|title=2005 General Election results for Hunterdon County}}&lt;/ref&gt; after a candidate accused of corruption had won the primary.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.braac.org/HCN-readington_campaign_violations.pdf Reprint from The Huntington County News]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Tom Ammiano]], President of the [[San Francisco Board of Supervisors]], entered the race for Mayor of San Francisco as a write-in candidate two weeks before the 1999 general election. He received 25% of the vote, coming in second place and forcing incumbent Mayor [[Willie Lewis Brown, Jr.|Willie Brown]] into a [[Two-round system|runoff election]], which Brown won by margin of 59% to 40%. In 2001, the campaign was immortalized in the award-winning documentary film ''See How They Run''.
*[[John R. Brinkley]] ran as a write-in candidate for governor of Kansas in 1930. He was motivated at least in part by the state's revocation of his medical license and attempts to shut down his clinic, where he performed alternative medical procedures including transplantation of goat glands into humans. He won 29.5% of the vote in a three-way race. Brinkley's medical and political career are documented in Pope Brock's book ''Charlatan''.
* [[Donna Frye]] ran as a write-in candidate for Mayor of San Diego in 2004. A controversy erupted when several thousand votes for her were not counted because the voters had failed to fill in the bubble next to the write-in line. Had those votes been counted, she would have won the election.{{citation needed|date=November 2010}}
* [[Michael Jarjura]] was re-elected Mayor of [[Waterbury, Connecticut|Waterbury]], Connecticut in 2005 as a write-in candidate after losing the Democratic party primary to Karen Mulcahy, who used to serve as Waterbury's tax collector before Jarjura fired her in 2004 &quot;for what he claimed was her rude and abusive conduct toward citizens&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.wtnh.com/Global/story.asp?S=3947552&amp;nav=3YeX|title=Waterbury mayor to wage write-in campaign}}&lt;/ref&gt; After spending $100,000 on a general elections write-in campaign,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.waterburyobserver.com/worxcms_published/recent_stories_94.shtml The Waterbury Observer – The Write Stuff&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Jarjura received 7,907 votes, enough for a plurality of 39%.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.wtnh.com/2005vote/race192.html News Channel 8 / 2005 Vote Election Results&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* James Maher won the mayorship of [[Baxter Estates, New York|Baxter Estates]], New York on March 15, 2005 as a write-in candidate with 29 votes. Being the only one on the ballot, the incumbent mayor, James Neville, did not campaign, as he did not realize that there was a write-in campaign going on. Neville received only 13 votes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.antonnews.com/portwashingtonnews/2005/04/01/news/elections.html|title=Baxter Estates Mayor James Neville &quot;Stunned&quot; by Write-in Defeat|first=Dolores|last=Kazanjian O'Brien|publisher=Port Washington News|date=April 1, 2005|accessdate=2006-06-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Beverly O'Neil won a third term as Mayor of [[Long Beach, California|Long Beach]], California as a write-in candidate in 2002. The Long Beach City City Charter has a [[term limit]] amendment that says a candidate cannot be on the ballot after two full terms, but does not prevent the person from running as a write-in candidate.&lt;ref&gt;[http://longbeach.legistar.com/LegislationDetail.aspx?ID=186782&amp;GUID=E700C5E7-4A2C-46FB-9E0B-EAE13A1063B2&amp;Options=&amp;Search= Recommendation to review proposed amendments to the Long Beach City Charter]&lt;/ref&gt; She finished first in a seven-candidate primary, but did not receive more than 50% of the vote, forcing a runoff contest. In the runoff, still restricted from the ballot, she got roughly 47% of the vote in a three-way election that included a second write-in candidate.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.presstelegram.com/news/ci_3942287 Legacy of a Legend]. ''Long Beach Press-Telegram''.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Michael Sessions]], an 18-year-old high school senior, won as a write-in candidate for Mayor of [[Hillsdale, Michigan|Hillsdale]], Michigan in 2005. He was too young to qualify for the ballot.
* [[Anthony A. Williams]], then incumbent Mayor of Washington, D.C. was forced to run as a write-in candidate in the 2002 Democratic primary, because he had too many invalid signatures for his petition. He won the Democratic primary, and went on to win re-election.
* In the November 8, 2011, election for [[Commonwealth's Attorney]] of [[Richmond County, Virginia|Richmond County]], Virginia, 16-year incumbent Wayne Emery has been certified the winner as a write-in candidate over challenger James Monroe by a margin of 53 votes (2.4%) out of 2,230 votes cast, after his petitions were challenged and his name was removed from the ballot.&lt;ref&gt;http://www2.timesdispatch.com/news/2011/nov/10/tdmet03-richmond-county-write-in-campaign-workedma-ar-1448412&lt;/ref&gt;
* In the 1997 election for Mayor of [[Talkeetna, Alaska|Talkeetna]], Alaska, [[Stubbs (cat)|Stubbs the Cat]] won over the two human candidates.  He has been re-elected every mayoral election since, and as of July 18, 2012, celebrates 15 years in office.&lt;ref&gt;http://newsfeed.time.com/2012/07/17/cat-marks-15-years-as-mayor-of-alaska-town/&lt;/ref&gt;

===Others===
* [[Aaron Schock]] was elected to the District 150 School Board in [[Peoria, Illinois|Peoria]], Illinois in 2001 by a write-in vote, after his petitions were challenged and his name was removed from the ballot.  He defeated the incumbent by over 2,000 votes, approximately 6,400 to 4,300 votes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://aaronschock.com/about.htm School Board Write-in Campaign]&lt;/ref&gt;  He went on to serve in the [[Illinois House of Representatives]], and was elected to the [[United States House of Representatives]] in 2008.
* John Adams became an [[Orange County, California|Orange County]], California judge in November 2002 after running along with 10 other write-in candidates in the primaries on March 5, 2002 against incumbent Judge Ronald Kline.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://archives.cnn.com/2002/ALLPOLITICS/03/06/california.primary/index.html|title='Fight' seen in California's governor's race|publisher=CNN|date=March 6, 2002|accessdate=2006-03-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the filing deadline in which no candidate filed to run against Kline, a computer hacker discovered that Judge Kline had child pornography on his home computer. Kline got less than 50% of the vote in the primaries, requiring a runoff between him and write-in candidate John Adams (who actually received more votes than Kline).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oc.ca.gov/election/Live/e2/result2.htm#c2721 Orange County Registrar of Voters Election Results for March 5, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt; After some legal maneuvers, Kline's name was removed from the general elections, leaving the general election a runoff between Adams and Gay Sandoval, who was the second highest write-in vote getter.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oc.ca.gov/election/Live/e5/result5.htm#c2721 Orange County Registrar of Voters Election Results for November 5, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt; Charges against Kline were eventually thrown out.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.irvineworldnews.com/Astories/oct30/kline.htm|title=Case against ex-judge Kline gutted|publisher=Irvine World News|date=October 30, 2003|accessdate=2006-06-30|first=Rachanee|last=Srisavasdi}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*On September 15, 2009, four write-in candidates in the [[United States Independence Party|Independence Party]] primaries for various offices in [[Putnam County, New York|Putnam County]], New York defeated their on-ballot opponents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.putnamcountycourier.com/news/2009-10-01/Front_Page/A_Reversal_of_Fortune_for_Interim_Independence_Par.html|title=A Reversal of Fortune for Interim Independence Party|date=October 1, 2009|publisher=The Putnam County Courier|first=Michael Brendan|last=Dougherty|accessdate=November 27, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*In a May 2011 school board election for the [[Bentley Community Schools|Bentley School]] Board in Michigan, Lisa Osborn ran as a write-in candidate and needed just one vote to win a seat. However, she did not receive any votes, even from herself. She explained herself by saying that she was at her son's baseball game and did not have time to go to the polls.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Acosta|first=Roberto|title=School board candidate loses election because she didn't vote for herself; calls not voting a 'dumb move'|url=http://www.mlive.com/news/flint/index.ssf/2011/05/bentley_school_board_candidate.html|publisher=Mlive.com|accessdate=November 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Other countries==
With a few exceptions, the practice of recognizing write-in candidates is typically viewed internationally as an [[Politics of the United States|American]] tradition.&lt;ref&gt;[http://abcnews.go.com/Entertainment/WolfFiles/story?id=91051&amp;page=1 ABC News: Donald Duck's a Big Bird in Politics&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk_politics/212163.stm |work=BBC News | title=Livingstone threatens write-in campaign | date=November 11, 1998}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* One of the most famous examples was the 1826 County Clare By-Elections in Ireland. Daniel O'Connell had won by way of a write-in due to the illegality of an Irish Catholic running as a political candidate at that time.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}

* Several cases of elected write-in candidates took place in the 2006 Swedish municipal elections. Due to Swedish electoral law, free ballots are provided for any party that received more than 1 percent of the votes in one of the two latest parliamentary elections, irrespective of whether the party actually stood any candidates in the municipality. In some municipalities, voters cast a sufficient number of ballots for the nationalist [[Sweden Democrats]] to allow them to get a seat on the municipal council. (Municipal councils in Sweden are relatively large, with even the smallest municipalities, numbering just a few thousand inhabitants, required to have a council of at least 31 members.) In case the party did not field any eligible candidates, people whose names were written in were elected, though many subsequently resigned their seats. In places where no candidates were written in, the seats were left empty.&lt;ref&gt;[http://expressen.se/1.428456 Skämtet gjorde Jonas till sd-politiker – GT.se – Expressen.se – Sveriges bästa nyhetssajt!&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

* A bizarre incident involving a fictitious write-in candidacy occurred in the small town of [[Picoazá]], Ecuador in 1967. A company ran a series of campaign-themed advertisements for a foot powder called Pulvapies. Some of the slogans used included &quot;Vote for any candidate, but if you want well-being and hygiene, vote for Pulvapies&quot;, and &quot;For Mayor: Honorable Pulvapies.&quot; The foot powder Pulvapies ended up receiving the most votes in the election.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F50815F83A5E137A93CAA8178CD85F438685F9 Foot Powder Produces Headaches in Ecuador].&quot; ''[[The New York Times]]''. July 18, 1967. Page 39. Retrieved December 19, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.snopes.com/politics/ballot/footpowder.asp Snopes report on the election result]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Foot Powder Wins Election Hands Down.&quot; ''[[The Washington Post]]''.  July 18, 1967  (p. A13).&lt;/ref&gt;

* In Brazil, until the introduction of [[electronic voting]] in 1994, the ballot had no names written for [[legislative]] candidates, so many voters would protest by voting on fictional characters or religious figures. In a famous case, the São Paulo city zoo [[rhinoceros]] ''Cacareco'' got around 100,000 votes in the 1959 elections for the municipal council, more than any candidate. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Ferreira|first=Neil|title=Cacareco agora é Excelência|url=http://www.memoriaviva.com.br/ocruzeiro/24101959/241059_8.htm|work=O Cruzeiro|accessdate=20 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, those votes were not considered because Brazilian law stipulates that a candidate must be affiliated to a political party to take office.{{citation needed|date=November 2010}}

==As a protest vote==
* ''[[Mad Magazine]]'' has satirically called to vote for [[Alfred E. Neuman]] as a write-in candidate for every U.S. presidential election from 1960 to 1980 with slogans like &quot;You could do worse-and you already have&quot; and &quot;There are Bigger Idiots running for office!&quot;.

*In the [[United States presidential election, 1980|1980 U.S. Presidential election]], rock star [[Joe Walsh]] ran a mock write-in campaign, promising to make his song &quot;[[Life's Been Good]]&quot; the new national anthem if he won, and running on a platform of &quot;Free Gas for Everyone.&quot; Though Walsh (then aged 33) was not old enough to actually assume the office, he wanted to raise public awareness of the election. (In 1992, Walsh purportedly ran for ''vice''-president, in his song &quot;Vote For Me&quot;, a track on his album ''[[Songs for a Dying Planet]]'', which was released that year.)

*During the 2000 [[United States Congress#Elections|United States Congress Elections]], film-maker [[Michael Moore]] led a campaign for voters to submit a [[ficus]] tree as a write-in candidate.  This campaign was replicated across the country and was recounted in an episode of ''[[The Awful Truth (TV show)|The Awful Truth]]''.

*In the [[Ultimate Marvel]] universe, as of issue #15 of ''[[Ultimate Comics: The Ultimates]]'', [[Captain America]] has become president of America as a write-in candidate.

*In 2012, a campaign was waged to write in [[Charles Darwin]]'s name against [[Paul Broun]] after Broun &quot;called evolution and other areas of science 'lies straight from the pit of hell.'” Darwin received approximately 4,000 votes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://onlineathens.com/election/2012-11-08/charles-darwin-gets-nearly-4000-write-votes-athens-against-rep-broun|title=Charles Darwin gets 4,000 write-in votes in Athens against Paul Broun|date=November 9, 2012|first=Jim|last=Thompson|publisher=[[Athens Banner-Herald]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- Should be updated after December 2012 after official results are tabulated --&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Write-In Candidate}}
[[Category:Elections]]
[[Category:Political parties in the United States]]

[[it:Candidato write-in]]
[[nl:Write-in]]
[[pl:Kandydat dopisany do listy]]
[[sv:Write-in kandidat]]</text>
      <sha1>b5z8w5q9d9o2ojzbzm1667wwqk228pb</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
