<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Age of consent</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1653</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519899194</id>
      <parentid>519304865</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-26T07:30:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>197.254.125.249</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="28026">{{other uses}}
{{pp-move-indef|small=yes}}&lt;!-- This page has been automatically assigned the correct protection templates by [[User:Lowercase sigmabot]]. If the protection templates are wrong, please fix them. Thanks. --&gt;
{{Sex and the Law}}
While the phrase '''age of consent''' rarely appears in legal [[statute]]s,&lt;ref name=&quot;waites&quot;&gt;{{cite book| last=Waites| first=Matthew| title=The Age of Consent: Young People, Sexuality and Citizenship| publisher=Palgrave Macmillan| year=2005| isbn=1-4039-2173-3| oclc=238887395 58604878}}&lt;/ref&gt; when used in relation to [[Human sexual activity|sexual activity]], the age of consent is the minimum age at which a person is considered to be legally competent to consent to sexual acts. It should not be confused with the [[age of majority]], [[defense of infancy|age of criminal responsibility]], the [[marriageable age]], the voting age, the drinking age, driving age, or other purposes. Laws vary widely, and while most jurisdictions set the age of consent in the range 14 to 18, ages of consent as low as 12 and as high as 21 exist.

The age of consent varies from jurisdiction to jurisdiction.&lt;ref name=&quot;waites&quot; /&gt; The relevant age may also vary by the type of sexual act, the gender of the actors, or other restrictions such as abuse of a [[position of trust]]. Some jurisdictions may also make allowances for minors engaged in sexual acts with each other, rather than a single age. Charges resulting from a breach of these laws may range from a [[misdemeanor]] such as ''corruption of a minor'', to what is popularly called ''[[statutory rape]]'' (which is considered equivalent to rape, both in severity and sentencing).

There are many &quot;gray areas&quot; in this area of law, some regarding unspecific and untried legislation, others brought about by debates regarding changing societal attitudes, and others due to conflicts between federal and state laws. These factors all make age of consent an often confusing subject, and a topic of highly charged debates.&lt;ref name=&quot;waites&quot; /&gt;

==History and social attitudes==
Traditionally, across the globe, the age of consent for a sexual union was a matter for the family to decide, or a tribal custom. In most cases, this coincided with signs of puberty, [[menstruation]] for a woman and pubic hair for a man.&lt;ref name=&quot;Encyclopedia of Children and Childhood in History and Society, A-Ar, Age of Consent&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.faqs.org/childhood/A-Ar/Age-of-Consent.html | title=Encyclopedia of Children and Childhood in History and Society }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Hesiod in &quot;Works and Days&quot; (circa 700BC) suggests that a man should marry around the age of thirty, and that he should take a wife who is five years past puberty. In Ancient Rome, it was very common for girls to marry and have children shortly after the onset of puberty.{{Citation needed|date=July 2012}}

The first recorded age-of-consent law dates back 800 years: In 1275, in England, as part of the rape law, a statute, Westminster 1, made it a misdemeanor to &quot;ravish&quot; a &quot;maiden within age,&quot; whether with or without her consent. The phrase &quot;within age&quot; was interpreted by jurist Sir Edward Coke as meaning the age of marriage, which at the time was 12 years of age.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephen Robertson, University of Sydney, Australia&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Stephen Robertson, University of Sydney, Australia |url=http://chnm.gmu.edu/cyh/teaching-modules/230 |title=Children and Youth in History &amp;#124; Age of Consent Laws |publisher=Chnm.gmu.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-06-30| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20100627095601/http://chnm.gmu.edu/cyh/teaching-modules/230?| archivedate= 27 June 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 12th century [[Gratian (jurist)|Gratian]], the influential founder of [[Canon law]] in [[medieval]] Europe, accepted age of puberty for marriage to be between 12 and 14 but acknowledged consent to be meaningful if the children were older than&amp;nbsp;7. There were authorities that said that consent could take place earlier. Marriage would then be valid as long as neither of the two parties annulled the marital agreement before reaching puberty, or if they had already consummated the marriage. It should be noted that Judges honored marriages based on mutual consent at ages younger than&amp;nbsp;7, in spite of what Gratian had said; there are recorded marriages of 2 and 3 year olds.&lt;ref name=&quot;Encyclopedia of Children and Childhood in History and Society, A-Ar, Age of Consent&quot;/&gt;

The American colonies followed the English tradition, and the law was more of a guide. For example, Mary Hathaway (Virginia, 1689) was only 9 when she was married to William Williams. Sir Edward Coke (England, 17th century) &quot;made it clear that the marriage of girls under 12 was normal, and the age at which a girl who was a wife was eligible for a [[dower]] from her husband's estate was 9 even though her husband be only four years old.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Encyclopedia of Children and Childhood in History and Society, A-Ar, Age of Consent&quot;/&gt;

Reliable data for when people would actually marry is very difficult to find. In England for example, the only reliable data on age at marriage in the early modern period comes from records involving only those who left property after their death. Not only were the records relatively rare, but not all bothered to record the participants' ages, and it seemed that the more complete the records are, the more likely they are to reveal young marriages. Additionally, 20th and 21st centuries' historians have sometimes shown reluctance to accept data regarding young ages of marriage, and would instead explain the data away as a misreading by a later copier of the records.&lt;ref name=&quot;Encyclopedia of Children and Childhood in History and Society, A-Ar, Age of Consent&quot;/&gt;

A small number of Italian and German states introduced an age of consent in the 16th century, setting it at 12 years. Towards the end of the 18th century, other European countries also began to enact age of consent laws. The first French Constitution established an age of consent of 11 years in 1791, which was raised to 13 in 1863. Portugal, Spain, Denmark and the Swiss cantons, initially set the age of consent at 10–12 years and then raised it to between 13 and 16 years in the second half of the 19th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephen Robertson, University of Sydney, Australia&quot;/&gt; Historically, the English common law set the age of consent to range from 10 to 12.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.slate.com/articles/health_and_science/human_nature/2007/09/the_mindbooty_problem.html|title=The Mind-Booty Problem : Rethinking the age of sexual consent|author=William Saletan||date=Sept. 27, 2007|work=Slate.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the United States, by the 1880s, most states set the age of consent at 10–12, and in one state, Delaware, the age of consent was only&amp;nbsp;7. A New York Times article states that it was still aged 7 in Delaware in 1895.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=The New York Times|date=October 15, 1895|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9B01EEDC113AE533A25756C1A9669D94649ED7CF&amp;scp=1&amp;sq=%22age+of+consent%22+delaware&amp;st=p|title=PURITY CONGRESS MEETS; A Great Gathering for Moral Work in the City of Baltimore. AIMS AND OBJECTS OF THE MOVEMENT Determined to Prevent State Regulation of Vice and to Rescue Fallen Men and Fallen Women.|location=BALTIMORE, Oct. 14.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Female reformers and advocates of social purity initiated a campaign in 1885 to petition legislators to raise the legal age of consent to at least&amp;nbsp;16, with the ultimate goal to raise the age to 18. The campaign was successful, with almost all states raising the age of consent to 16–18 by 1920.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Stephen Robertson, University of Sydney, Australia |url=http://chnm.gmu.edu/cyh/teaching-modules/230?section=primarysources&amp;source=24 |title=Children and Youth in History &amp;#124; Age of Consent Laws |publisher=Chnm.gmu.edu |date=2007-11-29 |accessdate=2010-06-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://womhist.alexanderstreet.com/teacher/aoc.htm |title=Campaign to Raise the Legal Age of Consent, 1885–1914, Lesson Plan |publisher=Womhist.alexanderstreet.com |date= |accessdate=2010-06-30| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20100617063339/http://womhist.alexanderstreet.com/teacher/aoc.htm| archivedate= 17 June 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Social (and the resulting legal) attitudes toward the appropriate age of consent have drifted upwards in modern times. For example, while ages from 10 to 13 were typically acceptable in [[western world|Western countries]] during the mid-19th century,&lt;ref name=&quot;waites&quot; /&gt; the end of the 19th century and the beginning of the 20th century were marked by changing attitudes towards sexuality and childhood resulting in raising the ages of consent to around 16.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephen Robertson, University of Sydney, Australia&quot;/&gt;

==Law==
[[File:Age of Consent - Global.svg|thumb|300 px|Age of consent for heterosexual sex by country&lt;br /&gt;
{{Color box|#FFA07A}} – puberty&lt;br /&gt;
{{Color box|#DC143C}} – less than 12&lt;br /&gt;
{{Color box|#E0FFFF}} – 12&lt;br /&gt;
{{Color box|#7FFFD4}} – 13&lt;br /&gt;
{{Color box|#00CED1}} – 14&lt;br /&gt;
{{Color box|#1E90FF}} – 15&lt;br /&gt;
{{Color box|#0000CD}} – 16&lt;br /&gt;
{{Color box|#808000}} – 17&lt;br /&gt;
{{Color box|#32CD32}} – 18&lt;br /&gt;
{{Color box|#006400}} – 19&lt;br /&gt;
{{Color box|#EE82EE}} – 20&lt;br /&gt;
{{Color box|#9400D3}} – 21+&lt;br /&gt;
{{Color box|#DAA520}} – varies by state/province/region/territory&lt;br /&gt;
{{Color box|#FF1493}} – must be married&lt;br /&gt;
{{Color box|#808080}} – no law&lt;br /&gt;
{{Color box|#D3D3D3}} – no data available]]
Sexual relations with a person under the age of consent is a [[criminal offense]] in most countries. Many different terms exist for the charges laid and can include ''[[child sexual abuse]]'', ''[[statutory rape]]'', ''illegal [[carnal knowledge]]'', and ''corruption of a minor''.&lt;ref name=&quot;waites&quot; /&gt;

The enforcement practices of age-of-consent laws vary depending on the social sensibilities of the particular culture (see above). Often, enforcement is not exercised to the letter of the law, with legal action being taken only when a sufficiently socially-unacceptable age gap exists between the two individuals, or if the perpetrator is in a position of power over the minor (e.g., a teacher, minister, or doctor). The [[Gender#Sex|sex]] of each participant can also influence perceptions of an individual's guilt and therefore enforcement.&lt;ref name=&quot;waites&quot; /&gt;

===&quot;Age&quot;===
The concept of what actually makes up an age of consent differs between jurisdictions. Common examples include:
; Fixed age of consent: In most jurisdictions, the age of consent is actually a specified fixed age, such as in all of the [[United Kingdom]], where it is 16.&lt;ref name=SOA2003/&gt;
; Onset of [[puberty]] as the age of consent: In some jurisdictions, there is no fixed age of consent. Instead, sex is allowed with people who are pubescent or post pubescent. Such jurisdictions include [[Ages of consent in Asia#Yemen|Yemen]], but only in marriage, and the states of [[Nayarit]] and [[Querétaro]] (in [[Ages of consent in North America#Mexico|Mexico]]) and [[Ages of consent in South America#Bolivia|Bolivia]]. This was also the case of the Russian Soviet Federal Socialist Republic (RSFSR) and other Soviet republics during the Soviet era.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cyberussr.com/rus/uk136-e.html&lt;/ref&gt;
; Marriageable age: Not all countries have an age of consent, but a number of those jurisdictions (including [[Kuwait]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Kuwait&quot;/&gt;) make all [[sexual intercourse]] outside of marriage illegal.

===Defenses and exceptions===
The age of consent is a legal barrier to the minor ability to consent and therefore obtaining consent is not in general a defense to having sexual relations with a person under the prescribed age. Common examples:
; Reasonably believing that the victim is over the age of consent: In some jurisdictions, (such as [[England and Wales]]&lt;ref name=SOA2003&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.opsi.gov.uk/acts/acts2003/pdf/ukpga_20030042_en.pdf |format=PDF|title=Sexual Offences Act 2003 (See Sections 9 to 12) |publisher=Published by the Government of the United Kingdom, (Office of Public Sector Information)}}&lt;/ref&gt;), it is a defense if the accused can show that he or she reasonably believed the victim was over the age of consent. However, where such a defense is provided, it normally applies only when the victim is close to the age of consent or the accused can show [[due diligence]] in determining the age of the victim (e.g., a 15-year-old who used a fake identification document claiming she was 18 or older).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Larry W. Myers | title=Reasonable Mistake of Age: A Needed defense to Statutory Rape| journal= Michigan Law Review| volume= 64| issue=1|year=1965|pages=105–136. – [http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0026–2234(196511)64:1&lt;105:RMOAAN&gt;2.0.CO;2–D] | doi=10.2307/1287118|publisher=The Michigan Law Review Association|jstor=1287118}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; Marriage: In some jurisdictions, including [[Brunei]]&lt;ref name=Brunei_01 &gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.interpol.int/Public/Children/SexualAbuse/NationalLaws/CsaBrunei.pdf |title=Legislation of Interpol member states on sexual offences against children – Brunei |publisher=Interpol |year=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; it is an exception to age of consent laws if the accused can show that he or she is legally married to the other person.
; {{visible anchor|Close-in-age exemptions}}: Some jurisdictions have laws explicitly allowing minors under the age of consent to engage in sexual acts with partners who are close to their age by enacting legal ''close in age exemptions'': for instance in [[Canada]] the age of consent is 16, but there are two close-in-age exemptions: minors 14–15 may have sex with a partner who is less than five years older, and minors aged 12–13 may have sex with a partner who is less than two years older.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cbc.ca/canada/story/2008/05/01/crime-bill.html|title=Canada's age of consent raised by 2 years|publisher=CBC News|date=2008-05-01|accessdate=2009-03-22| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20090320002644/http://www.cbc.ca/canada/story/2008/05/01/crime-bill.html| archivedate= 20 March 2009 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; These different defenses can change dramatically from jurisdiction to jurisdiction, even between neighboring states of the same union with the same age of consent. Other countries state that the sexual conduct with the minor is not to be punished if the partners are of a similar age and development: for instance the age of consent in [[Finland]] is 16, but the law states that the act will not be punished if &quot;there is no great difference in the ages or the mental and physical maturity of the persons involved&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.finlex.fi/en/laki/kaannokset/1889/en18890039&lt;/ref&gt;

; Homosexual and heterosexual age discrepancies: Some jurisdictions, such as [[The Bahamas]], [[Bermuda]], [[Chile]], [[Greece]], [[Paraguay]] and [[Suriname]]&amp;nbsp;–have a higher age of consent for [[Homosexuality|homosexual]] intercourse. In the United Kingdom for example the age of consent was originally 21 for homosexual behavior, while it was 16 for heterosexual behavior.&lt;ref&gt;''The Causes and Cures of Criminality'' Eysenck, Hans 1989 Plenum Press New York page 229&lt;/ref&gt; However, such discrepancies are increasingly being challenged. In both [[Canada]] and the [[Australia]]n state of [[Queensland]], the age of consent for [[anal sex]] is officially higher at 18 years, compared with 16 years for vaginal and oral sex.&lt;ref name=&quot;can&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.efc.ca/pages/law/cc/cc.159.html |title=159. ANAL INTERCOURSE |publisher=Efc.ca |date= |accessdate=2010-03-22| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20100323224444/http://www.efc.ca/pages/law/cc/cc.159.html| archivedate= 23 March 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;aust&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/legis/qld/consol_act/cc189994/s208.html |title=CRIMINAL CODE 1899 – SECT 208 208 Unlawful sodomy |publisher=Austlii.edu.au |date= |accessdate=2010-03-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the Canadian provinces of [[Alberta]], [[Ontario]] and [[Quebec]], this discrepancy has been declared unconstitutional by courts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ctv.ca/servlet/ArticleNews/story/CTVNews/20060622/age_consent_060622/20060623/ |title=Mixed reviews to Tories' sexual consent bill – CTV News |publisher=Ctv.ca |date= |accessdate=2010-03-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.egale.ca/index.asp?item=468 |title=The State of the Play |publisher=Egale.ca |date= |accessdate=2010-03-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; Gender-age differentials: In some jurisdictions (such as [[Indonesia]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Indonesia&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.interpol.int/Public/Children/SexualAbuse/NationalLaws/csaIndonesia.asp |title=Sexual Offences Laws – Indonesia |publisher=Interpol |accessdate=2009-09-05 }}&lt;/ref&gt;), there are different ages of consent for heterosexual sexual activity that are based on the gender of each person. In countries where there are gender-age differentials, the age of consent may be higher for girls—for example in [[Papua New Guinea]], where the age of consent for heterosexual sex is 16 for girls and 14 for boys,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.paclii.org/pg/LRC/WP_1.htm&lt;/ref&gt; or they may be higher for males, such as in Indonesia, where males must be 19 years old and females must be 16 years old.&lt;ref name=&quot;Indonesia&quot; /&gt; There are also numerous jurisdictions—such as Kuwait&lt;ref name=&quot;Kuwait&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.unhchr.ch/tbs/doc.nsf/0/2f5665ae20b956cb8025675a0033cafb?Opendocument |title=Summary record of the 488th meeting : Kuwait |publisher=Committee on the Rights of the Child |accessdate=2009-09-05 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Palestinian National Authority|Palestine]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Palestine&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.law.emory.edu/ifl/legal/palestine.htm |title=Palestinian Territories of West Bank and Gaza Strip – Marriage Age |publisher=Emory Law |accessdate=2009-09-05 }}&lt;/ref&gt;—in which marriage laws govern the gender-age differential. In these jurisdictions, it is illegal to have [[sexual intercourse]] outside of marriage so the ''de facto'' age of consent is the marriageable age. In Kuwait, this means that boys must be at least 17 and girls at least 15 years old.
;Maximum age of adult: A less frequent criterion is that sexual intercourse between an minor and an adult is legal under the condition that the latter does not exceed a certain age. Thus the age of consent in Delaware is 18, but it is allowed for teenagers aged 16 and 17 to engage in sexual intercourse as long as the older partner is younger than 30.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | work = Delaware Code | title = TITLE 11, Crimes and Criminal Procedure, Delaware Criminal Code, CHAPTER 5. SPECIFIC OFFENSES, Subchapter II. Offenses Against the Person, Subpart A. Assaults and Related Offenses (see § 768 and § 770) | url = http://delcode.delaware.gov/title11/c005/sc02/index.shtml#768}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; Position of authority/trust: In most jurisdictions where the age of consent is below 18 (such as England and Wales&lt;ref name=SOA2003_a&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.opsi.gov.uk/acts/acts2003/pdf/ukpga_20030042_en.pdf |format=PDF|title=Sexual Offences Act 2003 (See Sections 16 to&amp;nbsp;24) |publisher=Published by the Government of the United Kingdom, (Office of Public Sector Information)}}&lt;/ref&gt;), in cases where a person aged 18 or older is in a position of trust over a person under 18 the age of consent usually rises to 18, or higher. Examples of such positions of trust include relationships between teachers and students. For example, in England and Wales the age of consent is 16, but if the person is a student of the older person it becomes&amp;nbsp;18.

===Extraterritoriality===
{{see also| PROTECT Act of 2003}}
Increasingly the age of consent laws of a state are applied not only to acts committed in the state's own territory, but also to those committed by the state's citizens or inhabitants while they are on foreign soil.&lt;ref name=&quot;waites&quot; /&gt; An example is the United States, which has passed a Federal age of consent law banning sexual activity by US citizens with foreigners or with other US citizens who are from another one of the States, if any of the partners is under 18. This applies in cases where any of the partners travels into or out of the United States, or from one State into another one, for the purpose of a sexual encounter.&lt;ref name=&quot;SOLR&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.solresearch.org/~SOLR/rprt/USnatlAoC.asp |title=Research on sex offender laws and their effects on people and society |year=2009 |publisher=SOL Research.org |accessdate=2011-10-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; The United States also applies this law in cases where the age of consent is lower than the age of both partners in both the states or countries involved.

==Other concerns==
===Marriage===
{{Main|Marriageable age}}&lt;!-- Please note that this section is a summary of another article and should reflect that article's current state. Do not add any extra information here, rather edit the alternate article and then summarize that article here. --&gt;
The age at which a person can be legally married can also differ from the age of consent. In jurisdictions where the marriageable age is lower than the age of consent, those laws usually override the age of consent laws in the case of a married couple where one or both partners are below the age of consent. Further still, some jurisdictions prohibit any sex outside of marriage, which can take place at any age, as in the case of [[Yemen]].

===Pornography===
{{Main|Child pornography}}&lt;!-- Please note that this section is a summary of another article and should reflect that article's current state. Do not add any extra information here, rather edit the alternate article and then summarize that article here. --&gt;
Variations also exist in some countries between the age of consent and the age at which an individual can appear in [[pornography|pornographic]] images and films. In many jurisdictions, the minimum age for legal participation and even viewing of such productions is&amp;nbsp;18. Films and images showing individuals under the age of 18 in applicable jurisdictions can be classified as child pornography, even though the legal age of consent in those same jurisdictions is lower than&amp;nbsp;18. For example in the United States under federal law it is a crime to film minors below 18 in sexual acts, even in states where the age of sexual consent is below 18.&lt;ref name=&quot;SOLR&quot; /&gt; In those states of the USA where the age of consent is below 18, charges such as child porn are used as alternatives. For example Ross Frame, an Indiana police officer, had sex with a girl over 16 but under 18 in Indiana, where the age of consent is 16, but was prosecuted because he produced porn videos containing her. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Brilliant|first=Jeremy|title=New Castle detective resigns over child porn charges|url=http://www.wthr.com/Global/story.asp?S=10854092&amp;nav=9Tai|accessdate=25 May 2012|newspaper=wthr.com Eyewitness News|date=August 5, 2009|location=Henry County}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Prostitution===
{{Main|Prostitution of children}}&lt;!-- Please note that this section is a summary of another article and should reflect that article's current state. Do not add any extra information here, rather edit the alternate article and then summarize that article here. --&gt;
In many countries there are specific laws against child prostitution.

==Initiatives to change the age of consent==
{{Main|Age of consent reform}}
Age-of-consent reform refers to the efforts of some individuals or groups, for different reasons, to alter or abolish age-of-consent laws. These efforts advocate five main positions:
* Introductions of close-in-age exceptions.
* A change in the way that age-of-consent laws are examined in court.
* Either increases in the ages of consent or more severe penalties or both.
* Either decreases in the ages of consent or less severe penalties or both.
* Abolition of the age-of-consent laws either permanently or as a temporary, practical expedient.

==By country or region==
Specific jurisdictions' laws relating to age of consent can be found, organized by region, on the following pages:

*[[Ages of consent in Africa]]
*[[Ages of consent in Asia]]
*[[Ages of consent in Oceania]]
*[[Ages of consent in Europe]]
*[[Ages of consent in North America]]
*[[Ages of consent in South America]]

There are no specific age of consent laws in the [[Antarctica|Antarctic]]. In the unlikely event of an adult engaging in sexual activity with a minor, under the [[Antarctic Treaty]], scientists and support staff stationed there may be subject to the laws of the country of which they are nationals. Other visitors to the continent may need to follow the laws of the country in which their expedition is organized, or the country from which it departs.&lt;ref name=&quot;AusAnt&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aad.gov.au/default.asp?casid=78 |title=What is the treaty? |accessdate=2006-07-18 |date=2006-03-23 |publisher=Australian Antarctic Division| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20060820032245/http://www.aad.gov.au/default.asp?casid=78| archivedate= 20 August 2006 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Sexuality|Law}}
&lt;div style=&quot;-moz-column-count:2; column-count:2;&quot;&gt;
* [[1891 Age of Consent Act]] (British India)
* [[Adult film industry regulations]]
* [[Age disparity in sexual relationships]]
* [[Age of accountability]]
* [[Age of reason (canon law)]]
* [[Age of consent manifestations (UK)]]
* [[Child sexual abuse]]
* [[Convention on the Rights of the Child]]
* [[Emancipation of minors]]
* [[French petitions against age of consent laws]]
* [[Minors and abortion]]
* [[Mature minor doctrine]]
* [[Sexual Morality and the Law]]
* [[Sodomy law]]
* [[The Maiden Tribute of Modern Babylon]], a Victorian expose of child prostitution
&lt;/div&gt;

==References==
;Notes
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

;Further reading
* Brewer, Holly. [http://uncpress.unc.edu/browse/book_detail?title_id=833 ''By Birth or Consent: Children, Law, &amp; the Anglo-American Revolution in Authority'']; Univ. of North Carolina Press (Chapel Hill, 2005) ISBN 978-0-8078-5832-5
* Waites, Matthew (2005) ''The Age of Consent: Young People, Sexuality and Citizenship'', (New York [United States] and Houndmills, Basingstoke [United Kingdom]: Palgrave Macmillan) ISBN 1-4039-2173-3

==External links==
* [http://www.interpol.int/Public/Children/SexualAbuse/NationalLaws/Default.asp Legislation of Interpol member states on sexual offenses against children]{{dead link|date=August 2012}} (Some information may be out of date)
*[http://moraloutrage.net/state-laws/ Links to the relevant state laws for all 50 States and Washington DC]{{dead link|date=August 2012}}
*[http://www.avert.org/age-of-consent.htm Avert.org list]

&lt;!--spacing--&gt;

{{Sex}}
{{Sexual ethics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Age Of Consent}}
[[Category:Age and society]]
[[Category:Ageism]]
[[Category:Legal fictions]]
[[Category:Sex laws]]
[[Category:Sexuality and age]]
[[Category:Statutory law]]

[[ca:Edat de consentiment sexual]]
[[cs:Legální věk způsobilosti k pohlavnímu styku]]
[[cy:Oed cydsyniad]]
[[da:Seksuel lavalder]]
[[de:Schutzalter]]
[[es:Edad de consentimiento sexual]]
[[eo:Aĝo de konsento por seksumado]]
[[fr:Majorité sexuelle]]
[[id:Usia dewasa]]
[[it:Età del consenso]]
[[he:גיל ההסכמה]]
[[hu:Beleegyezési korhatár]]
[[ms:Cukup umur]]
[[ja:性的同意年齢]]
[[no:Seksuell lavalder]]
[[pl:Wiek przyzwolenia]]
[[pt:Idade de consentimento]]
[[ru:Возраст сексуального согласия]]
[[simple:Age of consent]]
[[sh:Uzrast seksualne saglasnosti]]
[[fi:Suojaikäraja]]
[[sv:Sexuell myndighetsålder]]
[[ta:பாலுறவுச் சம்மத வயது]]
[[th:อายุที่ยอมให้ร่วมประเวณีได้]]
[[tr:Cinsel rüşt yaşı]]
[[uk:Вік сексуальної згоди]]
[[zh-yue:衰十一]]
[[zh:最低合法性交年齡]]</text>
      <sha1>pcfsm2l3yqtrxcr7c320sd9olekqebs</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
