<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Child sexuality</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>250193</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520309052</id>
      <parentid>520308112</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-28T19:34:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lova Falk</username>
        <id>3665380</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Freud and Kinsey: theories and research on child sexuality */ shortening the title by removing redundant parts</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23076">{{Multiple issues|expert=Psychology|refimprove=December 2008|date=March 2009|lead too short=June 2011}}

'''Child [[human sexuality|sexuality]]''' is the sexual feelings, behaviors, and development of [[child]]ren.

==Freud==
Until [[Sigmund Freud]] published his ''[[Three Essays on the Theory of Sexuality]]'' in 1905, children were often regarded as [[asexual]], having no sexuality until later development. Freud was one of the first researchers to seriously study child sexuality. While his ideas, such as [[psycho-sexual development]] and the [[Oedipus complex]], have been rejected, acknowledging the existence of child sexuality was a significant change.&lt;ref name=&quot;Santrock&quot;/&gt;{{Page needed|date=November 2011}} Children are naturally curious about their bodies and sexual functions&amp;nbsp;— they wonder where babies come from, they notice anatomical differences between males and females, and many engage in [[genital play]] or [[masturbation]]. Child sex play includes exhibiting or inspecting the genitals. Many children take part in some sex play, typically with siblings or friends.&lt;ref name=&quot;Santrock&quot;&gt;Santrock, J.W. (2008). ''A Topical Approach to Life-Span Development (4''th''ed.).'' New York: McGraw-Hill.&lt;/ref&gt; Sex play with others usually decreases as children go through their elementary school years, yet they still may possess romantic interest in their peers. Curiosity levels remain high during these years, escalating in puberty (roughly the teenage years) when the main surge in sexual interest occurs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Santrock&quot;/&gt;

==Child sexualization==
Some [[cultural critic]]s have postulated that over recent decades children have been subject to a premature [[sexualization]], as indicated by a level of sexual knowledge or sexual behaviour inappropriate for their age group.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://aboutourkids.med.nyu.edu/aboutour/articles/sexual.html#effects
|title=The effects of increasing sexualization on children
|accessdate=February 22, 2007
|author=Fred Kaeser, Ed.D., Director of Health Services for Community School District Two, NYC
|last=Kaeser
|first=Fred
|date=2001-10-30
|work=Towards a Better Understanding of Children's Sexual Behavior
|publisher=NYU Child Study Center
|quote=We know that exposure to sexualized messages, particularly those that are incomprehensible, can have several effects on children.
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The causes of this premature sexualization that have been cited include portrayals in the [[mass media|media]] of sex and related issues, especially in media aimed at children; the [[marketing]] of products with sexual connotations to children, including clothing;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/pages/live/articles/news/news.html?in_article_id=109621&amp;in_page_id=1770)
|title=Outrage as Argos sells G-strings for children
|accessdate=February 22, 2007
|last=Chambers
|first=Suzanna
|authorlink=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/pages/dmsearch/overture.html?in_page_id=711&amp;in_overture_ua=cat&amp;in_start_number=0&amp;in_restriction=byline&amp;in_query=suzanna%20chambers&amp;in_name=on&amp;in_order_by=relevance+date
|date=2002-04-14
|publisher=the Daily Mail
|quote=High Street chain Argos has been branded irresponsible for promoting a range of sexually provocative lingerie designed for primary schoolgirls.
}}&lt;/ref&gt; the lack of parental oversight and [[discipline]]; access to adult culture via the [[internet]]; and the lack of comprehensive school [[sex education]] programs.&lt;ref&gt;APA, 2007; Lamb, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
For girls and young women in particular, studies have found that sexualization has a negative impact on their &quot;[[self-image]] and healthy development&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.apa.org/pi/wpo/sexualization.html
|title=Report of the APA Task Force on the Sexualization of Girls
|accessdate=February 22, 2007
|author=APA Task Force on the Sexualization of Girls
|coauthors=
|date=2007-02-19
|publisher=American Psychological Association
|quote=The proliferation of sexualized images of girls and young women in advertising, merchandising, and media is harming girls’ self-image and healthy development. This report explores the cognitive and emotional consequences, consequences for mental and physical health, and impact on development of a healthy sexual self-image.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

When an adult or older adolescent has a sexual relationship with a child, it is considered to be a form of [[child abuse]] known as [[child sexual abuse]].&lt;ref name=medline2008&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/childsexualabuse.html |title=Child Sexual Abuse |work=Medline Plus|date = 2008-04-02 |publisher=U.S. National Library of Medicine,}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;APA Guidelines&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author= |title=Guidelines for psychological evaluations in child protection matters. Committee on Professional Practice and Standards, APA Board of Professional Affairs |journal=The American Psychologist |volume=54 |issue=8 |pages=586–93 |year=1999 |month=August |pmid=10453704 |doi=10.1037/0003-066X.54.8.586 |quote='''Abuse, sexual (child)''': generally defined as contacts between a child and an adult or other person significantly older or in a position of power or control over the child, where the child is being used for sexual stimulation of the adult or other person.}}&lt;/ref&gt; This can also bring on the premature sexualization of the child.{{CN|date=July 2012}}  Other effects of child sexual abuse include [[clinical depression|depression]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Roosa&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Roosa MW, Reinholtz C, Angelini PJ |title=The relation of child sexual abuse and depression in young women: comparisons across four ethnic groups |journal=Journal of Abnormal Child Psychology |volume=27 |issue=1 |pages=65–76 |year=1999 |month=February |pmid=10197407}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[post-traumatic stress disorder]],&lt;ref name=Widom2007&gt;{{cite journal |author=Widom CS, DuMont K, Czaja SJ |title=A prospective investigation of major depressive disorder and comorbidity in abused and neglected children grown up |journal=Archives of General Psychiatry |volume=64 |issue=1 |pages=49–56 |year=2007 |month=January |pmid=17199054 |doi=10.1001/archpsyc.64.1.49  |laysummary=http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2007/01/070102092229.htm |laysource=[[ScienceDaily]] |laydate=January 3, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[anxiety]],&lt;ref name=&quot;levitan&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Levitan RD, Rector NA, Sheldon T, Goering P |title=Childhood adversities associated with major depression and/or anxiety disorders in a community sample of Ontario: issues of co-morbidity and specificity |journal=Depression and Anxiety |volume=17 |issue=1 |pages=34–42 |year=2003 |pmid=12577276 |doi=10.1002/da.10077}}&lt;/ref&gt; propensity to further victimization in adulthood,&lt;ref name=&quot;Messman-Moore&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1177/088626000015005003 |title=Child Sexual Abuse and Revictimization in the Form of Adult Sexual Abuse, Adult Physical Abuse, and Adult Psychological Maltreatment |year=2000 |last1=Messman-Moore |first1=T. L. |last2=Long |first2=P. J. |journal=Journal of Interpersonal Violence |volume=15 |issue=5 |pages=489}}&lt;/ref&gt; and physical injury to the child, among other problems.&lt;ref name=&quot;dinw&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Dinwiddie S, Heath AC, Dunne MP, ''et al.'' |title=Early sexual abuse and lifetime psychopathology: a co-twin-control study |journal=Psychological Medicine |volume=30 |issue=1 |pages=41–52 |year=2000 |month=January |pmid=10722174 |doi=10.1017/S0033291799001373}}&lt;/ref&gt; Child sexual abuse by a family member is a form of [[incest]], and can result in more serious and long-term [[psychological trauma]], especially in the case of parental [[incest]].&lt;ref name=Courtois&gt;{{cite book |last=Courtois |first=Christine A. |title=Healing the incest wound: adult survivors in therapy |publisher=Norton |location=New York |year=1988 |page=208 |isbn=0-393-31356-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;American Psychological Association. (2007). ''[http://www.apa.org/pi/wpo/sexualizationrep.pdf APA Task Force on the Sexualization of Girls].''&lt;/ref&gt;

==Theories and Research==
===Freud and Kinsey===
[[Sigmund Freud]] in his 1905 work ''[[Three Essays on the Theory of Sexuality]]'' outlined a theory of [[psycho-sexual development]] with five distinct phases: the ''oral stage'' (0&amp;ndash;1.5 years), the ''anal stage'' (1.5&amp;ndash;3.5 years), the ''phallic stage'' (3.5&amp;ndash;6 years) which culminates in the resolution of the [[Oedipus conflict]], [[Latency stage|The Latency Phase]] (6–12 years of age), and the ''genital'' (or adult) stage.

[[Alfred Kinsey]] in the [[Kinsey Reports]] (1948 and 1953) included research on the physical sexual response of children, including pre-pubescent children (though the main focus of the reports was adults). It has been stated that some of the data in his reports could not have been obtained without observation or participation in [[child sexual abuse]], or through collaborations with child molesters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Treating Child Sex Offenders and Victims: A Practical Guide|last=Salter, Ph.D.|first=Anna C.|year=1988|pages=22–24 |publisher=Sage Publications Inc |isbn= 0-8039-3182-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2000, Swedish researcher Ing-Beth Larsson noted, &quot;It is quite common for references still to cite Alfred Kinsey&quot;, due to the paucity of subsequent large-scale studies of child sexual behavior.&lt;ref name=&quot;larsson&quot;&gt;Larsson, IngBeth. ''[http://www.jeanyveshayez.net/tele-pdf/larsson.pdf Child sexuality and sexual behavior]'' (2000, Swedish National Board of Health and Welfare (report), Article number 2000-36-001. English translation (Lambert &amp; Tudball) Article number 2001-123-20.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Current methodology of study===
Empirical knowledge about child sexual behavior is not usually gathered by direct interviews of children, partly due to ethical consideration.&lt;ref name=&quot;larsson&quot; /&gt; Information about child sexual behavior is gathered by the following methods:

*Observing children being treated for problematic behavior, such as use of force in sex play,&lt;ref name=&quot;larsson_cite_gil&quot;&gt;Gil &amp; Cavanagh Johnson, 1993, op. cit.; Cavanagh Johnson, T., Feldmeth, J. R. (1993). &quot;Sexual behaviors – a continuum&quot;. In I. E. Gil &amp; T. Cavanagh Johnson. ''Sexualized Children'' (pp. 39 – 52); Friedrich, W. N., Grambsch, P., Damon, L., Hewitt, S., Koverola, C., Lang, R., Wolfe, V., Broughton, D. (1992). &quot;Child sexual behavior inventory: Normative and clinical comparisons&quot;. ''Psychological Assessment'', vol. 4, no.3:303 – 311. Cited in Larsson, 2000, op. cit.&lt;/ref&gt; often using [[Anatomically correct doll|dolls having genitals]]&lt;ref name=&quot;larsson_cite_cohn&quot;&gt;Cohn, D. S. (1991). &quot;Anatomic doll play of preschoolers referred for sexual abuse and those not referred&quot;. ''Child Abuse &amp; Neglect'' 15:455 – 466.; Everson &amp; Boat, 1991; Jampole, L. &amp; Weber, M. K. (1987). &quot;An assessment of the behavior of sexually abused and nonabused children with anatomically correct dolls&quot;. ''Child Abuse &amp; Neglect'': 11 187 – 192.; Sivan, A., Schor, D., Koeppl, G., Noble, L. (1988). &quot;Interaction of normal children with anatomic dolls&quot;. ''Child Abuse &amp; Neglect'', 12:295 – 304. Cited in Larsson, 2000, op. cit.&lt;/ref&gt;
*Recollections by adults&lt;ref name=&quot;larsson_cite_haugaard&quot;&gt;Haugaard, J. J. &amp; Tilly, C (1988). &quot;Characteristics predicting children’s responses to sexual encounters with other children&quot;. ''Child Abuse &amp; Neglect'' 12:209 – 218.; Haugaard, J. J. (1996). &quot;Sexual behaviors between children: Professionals’ opinions and undergraduates’ recollections&quot;. ''Families in Society: The Journal of Contemporary Human Services'', 2:81 – 89.; Lamb &amp; Coakley, 1993; Larsson, Lindell &amp; Svedin, publication datat not available; cited in Larsson, 2000, op. cit.&lt;/ref&gt;
*Observation by caregivers&lt;ref name=&quot;larsson_cite_friedrich&quot;&gt;Friedrich, W. N., Grambsch, P., Broughton, D., Kuiper, J., Beilke, R. L. (1991). &quot;Normative sexual behavior in children&quot;. ''Pediatrics'' 88: 456 – 464; Phipps-Yonas, S., Yonas, A., Turner, M., Kauper, M, (1993). &quot;Sexuality in early childhood&quot;. ''University of Minnesota Center for Urban and Regional Affairs Reports'', 23:1 – 5. ; Lindblad, F., Gustafsson, P., Larsson, I., Lundin, B. (1995). &quot;Preschooler’s sexual behaviour at daycare centers: an epidemiological study&quot;. ''Child Abuse &amp; Neglect'' vol. 19, no. 5:569 – 577.; Fitzpatrick &amp; Deehan, 1995; Larsson, I., Svedin, C-G. (1999). ''Sexual behaviour in Swedish preschool children as observed by their parents''. Manuscript.; Larsson, I., Svedin C-G., Friedrich, W. &quot;Differences and similarities in sexual behaviour among preschoolers in Sweden and USA&quot;. ''Nordic Journal of Psychiatry''. Printing information unavailable.; Smith &amp; Grocke, 1995; cited in Larsson, 2000, op. cit.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Behavior==
===Normative and non-normative behaviors===
Although there are variations between individual children, children are generally curious about their bodies and those of others, and explore their bodies through [[Genital play|explorative sex play]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://parentkidsright.com/pt-sexplay.html SEX PLAY: parenting strategies by Dr. Marilyn Heins&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ces.purdue.edu/providerparent/Health-Safety/WhenChildren'sPlay.htm PPP: Health and Safety || When Children's Play Involves Sexuality || Sex play is normal&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Playing doctor]] is one example of such childhood exploration.   Such games are generally considered to be normal in young children.  Child sexuality is considered fundamentally different from adult sexual behavior, which is more goal-driven.  Among children, genital penetration and oral-genital contact are very uncommon,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Friedrich WN, Fisher J, Broughton D, Houston M, Shafran CR |title=Normative sexual behavior in children: a contemporary sample |journal=Pediatrics |volume=101 |issue=4 |pages=E9 |year=1998 |pmid=9521975|doi=10.1542/peds.101.4.e9}}&lt;/ref&gt; and may be perceived as imitations of adult behaviors.&lt;ref name=&quot;larsson_cite_larsson&amp;svedin&quot;&gt;Larsson &amp; Svedin, 1999, op. cit.; Larsson &amp; Svedin, publication data unavailable; cited in Larsson, 2000, op. cit.&lt;/ref&gt; Such behaviors are more common among children who have been [[sexual abuse|sexually abused]].&lt;ref name=&quot;larsson&quot; /&gt;

A 1997 study based on limited variables found no correlation between early childhood (age 6 and under)  peer sexual play and later adjustment.&lt;ref name=Okami&gt;{{cite journal | doi = 10.1080/00224499709551902 | last1 = Okami | first1 = Paul | last2 = Olmstead | first2 = Richard | last3 = Abramson | first3 = Paul R. | year = 1997 | title = Sexual experiences in early childhood: 18-year longitudinal data from the UCLA family lifestyles project - University of California, Los Angeles | url = http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m2372/is_n4_v34/ai_20536042/pg_1 | journal = Journal of Sex Research | volume = 34 | issue = 4| pages = 339–347 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The study notes that its results do not demonstrate conclusively that no such correlates exist.&lt;ref name=&quot;Okami&quot;/&gt;  The study also does not address the question of consequences of intense sexual experiences or aggressive or unwanted experiences.&lt;ref name=Okami&gt;(Okami, p. 9)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Symptomatic behaviors===
Children who have been the victim of [[child sexual abuse]] sometimes display overly [[sexualization|sexualized behavior]],&lt;ref name=&quot;larsson_cite_kendall&quot;&gt;(Friedrich et al., 1992, 1993, op. cit.; Kendall-Tackett, K. E., Williams, L., Finkelhor, D. (1993). &quot;The impact of sexual abuse on children: A review and synthesis of recent empirical studies&quot;. ''Psychological Bulletin'', 113:164 – 180.; Cosentino, C. E, Meyer-Mahlenburg, H., Alpert, J., Weinberg, S., Gaines, R. (1995). &quot;Sexual behavior problems and psychopathology symptoms in sexually abused girls&quot;. ''Journal of American Academy Child &amp; Adolescent Psychiatry'', 34, 8:1033–1042.; cited in Larsson, 2000, op. cit.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;larsson_cite_friedrich2&quot;&gt;Friedrich et al. (1992), op. cit.; cited in Larsson, 2000, op. cit.&lt;/ref&gt; which may be defined as expressed behavior that is non-normative for the culture.

Typical symptomatic behaviors may include excessive or public [[masturbation]] and coercing, manipulating or tricking other children into non-consensual or unwanted [[sexual activities]], also referred to as &quot;[[child-on-child sexual abuse]]&quot;. Sexualized behavior is thought to constitute the best indication that a child has been sexually abused.&lt;ref name=&quot;larsson_cite_kendall&quot; /&gt;

Children who exhibit sexualized behavior may also have other behavioral problems.&lt;ref name=&quot;larsson_cite_friedrich2&quot; /&gt; Other symptoms of child sexual abuse may include manifestations of [[post-traumatic stress]] in younger children; fear, aggression, and nightmares in young school-age children; and depression in older children.&lt;ref name=&quot;larsson_cite_kendall&quot; /&gt;

==Normative behavior==
{{Globalize/US|date=December 2010}}&lt;!-- too american --&gt;
The following sections describe typical culturally-normed behavior among developed Western societies.

===Early childhood===
From the ages of three to seven, the following behaviors are normal among children:
*Children are curious about where babies come from.&lt;ref name=&quot;pike&quot;&gt;[http://muextension.missouri.edu/xplor/hesguide/humanrel/gh6002.htm GH6002 Sexuality and Your Child: For Children Ages 3 to 7, MU Extension&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Children may explore other children's and adults' bodies out of curiosity.&lt;ref name=&quot;pike&quot; /&gt;
*By age four, children may show significant attachment to the opposite-sex parent.&lt;ref name=&quot;pike&quot; /&gt;
*Children begin to have a sense of learned modesty and of the differences between private and public behaviors.&lt;ref name=&quot;pike&quot; /&gt;
*For some children, genital touching increases, especially when they are tired or upset.&lt;ref name=&quot;pike&quot; /&gt;

===Early school age===
Early school age covers approximately ages five to seven.

Children become more aware of gender differences, and tend to choose same-sex friends and playmates, even disparaging the opposite sex.&lt;ref name=&quot;mayoclinic&quot;&gt;[http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/sex-education/HQ00547 Sex education: Talking to toddlers and preschoolers about sex - MayoClinic.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Children may drop their close attachment to their opposite-sex parent and become more attached to their same-sex parent.&lt;ref name=&quot;pike&quot; /&gt;

During this time, children, especially girls, show increased awareness of social norms regarding sex, nudity, and privacy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Richardson-Schuster&quot;&gt;Richardson, Justin, M.D., and Schuster, Mark, M.D., Ph.D. ''[http://www.enotalone.com/article/2479.html Everything You Never Wanted Your Kids to Know About Sex (But Were Afraid They'd Ask)]'', 2003, Three Rivers Press&lt;/ref&gt; Children may use sexual terms to test adult reaction.&lt;ref name=&quot;pike&quot; /&gt; &quot;Bathroom humor&quot; (jokes and conversation relating to excretory functions), present in earlier stages, continues.&lt;ref name=&quot;planned_parenthood_ohio&quot;&gt;[http://www.plannedparenthood.org/central-ohio/sexuality-development.htm Planned Parenthood - Sexuality Development&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Masturbation continues to be common.&lt;ref name=&quot;pike&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;planned_parenthood_ohio&quot; /&gt;

===Middle childhood===&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[List of psychology topics]] --&gt;
&quot;Middle childhood&quot; covers the ages from about six to eleven, depending on the methodology and the behavior being studied, individual development varies considerably.

As this stage progresses, the choices of children picking same-sex friends becomes more marked and extending to disparagement of the opposite sex.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.secasa.com.au/index.php/workers/50/131 Adolescent and child sexuality&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sex play among siblings===
In 1980, a survey of 796 undergraduates, 15 percent of females and 10 percent of males reported some form of sexual experience involving a sibling; most of these fell short of actual intercourse. Approximately one quarter of these experiences were described as abusive or exploitative.&lt;ref&gt;Finkelhor, David. Ph.D. ''[http://www.springerlink.com/content/qg7tu631r7503228 Sex Among Siblings: A Survey on Prevalence, Variety and Effects.]'' Archives of Sexual Behavior. Volume 9, Number 3 / June, 1980. p. 171-194.&lt;/ref&gt; A 1989 paper reported the results of a questionnaire with responses from 526 undergraduate college students in which 17 percent of the respondents stated that they had preadolescent sexual experiences with a sibling.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.springerlink.com/content/t188h6334n81313g/ SpringerLink - Journal Article&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==In other cultures==

The following section describes behaviors observed outside of Western societies.

===Papua New Guinea===
At seven or eight years of age, children of the [[Trobriand Islands]] begin to play erotic games with each other and imitate adult seductive attitudes. About four or five years later, they begin to pursue sexual partners in earnest. They change partners often. Women are just as assertive and dominant as men in pursuing or refusing a lover.&lt;ref name=Weiner&gt;Weiner, Annette B. The Trobrianders of Papua New Guinea. United States of America: Wadsworth, Cengage Learning, 1988.&lt;/ref&gt; This is not only allowed but encouraged.

==See also==
*[[Age of consent]]
*[[Covert incest]]
*[[Developmental psychology]]
*[[Developmental stage theories]]
*[[Genital play]]
*[[Playing doctor]]
*[[Psychosexual development]]
*[[Puberty]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
*Diana Gittins, Children's Sexuality: Why Do Adults Panic?. In The Child in Question. Macmillan, 1997. ISBN 0-333-51109-3.
*Ronald Goldman and Juliette Goldman, Children's Sexual Thinking: A Comparative Study of Children Aged Five to Fifteen Years in Australia, North America, Britain and Sweden. London: Routledge and Kegan Paul, 1982. ISBN 0-7100-0883-X..
*Stevi Jackson, Childhood and Sexuality. Blackwell Publishing, 1982. ISBN 0-631-12871-9.
*Susan M. Moore, Doreen A. Rosenthal, Sexuality in Adolescence. Routledge, 1993. ISBN 0-415-07528-9.
*Sharon Lamb (2002). ''The Secret Lives of Girls: What Good Girls Really Do—Sex Play, Aggression, and Their Guilt'', Free Press. ISBN 0-7432-0107-8.
*Sharon Lamb (2006). ''Sex, Therapy, and Kids: Addressing their Concerns through Talk and Play.'' W.W. Norton.
*Sharon Lamb &amp; Lyn Mikel Brown (2006). ''Packaging Girlhood: Rescuing our Daughters from Marketers' Schemes.'' St. Martin's Press.
*Gil, E. &amp; Cavanagh Johnson, T. (1993). ''Sexualized children – Assessment and treatment of sexualized children and children who molest.'' Launch Press. Cited in Larsson, 2000, op. cit.

{{Sexual ethics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Child Sexuality}}
[[Category:Childhood]]
[[Category:Sexuality and age]]

[[ca:Sexualitat infantil]]
[[de:Infantile Sexualität]]
[[eu:Haurren sexualitatea]]
[[fr:Sexualité infantile (psychanalyse)]]
[[ko:아동의 성]]
[[id:Seksualitas anak]]
[[it:Sessualità infantile]]
[[ja:子供の性]]
[[no:Barneseksualitet]]
[[pt:Sexualidade infantil]]
[[ru:Детская сексуальность]]
[[fi:Lasten seksuaalisuus]]
[[uk:Дитяча сексуальність]]
[[zh:兒童性行為]]</text>
      <sha1>1fi54omn72pd32wioajgdlsgb4xc3z4</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
