<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Genetic sexual attraction</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>550948</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520491805</id>
      <parentid>518570082</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-29T21:33:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>204.102.218.122</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* In fiction */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12430">'''Genetic sexual attraction''' ('''GSA''') is a term that describes the phenomenon of [[sexual attraction]] between close relatives, such as siblings, first and second cousins or a parent and offspring, who first meet as adults.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbcamerica.com/content/334/index.jsp BBC America: Brothers and Sisters in Love]&lt;/ref&gt; 

== History and definition ==
The term was popularized in the US in the late 1980s by [[Barbara Gonyo]], the founder of [[Truth Seekers In Adoption]], a Chicago-based support group for adoptees and their new-found relatives.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Genetic sexual attraction |first=Alix |last= Kirsta |newspaper=[[The Guardian]] |date=17 May 2003 |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/theguardian/2003/may/17/weekend7.weekend2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Genetic sexual attraction is presumed to occur as a consequence of genetic relatives meeting as adults, typically as a consequence of [[adoption]].  Although this is a rare consequence of adoptive reunions, the large number of adoptive reunions in recent years means that a larger number of people are affected.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|work=[[The Current (radio program)|The Current]] |title=Part 2: Genetic Sexual Attraction - Part One |url=http://www.cbc.ca/thecurrent/2009/200905/20090507.html |author=[[Bob McKeown]] |coauthors=Aziza Sindhu |publisher=[[CBC Radio]] |date=May 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; If a sexual relationship is entered, it is known as [[incest]]. 

GSA is rare between people raised together in early childhood due to a ''reverse'' sexual [[Imprinting (psychology)|imprinting]] known as the [[Westermarck effect]], which desensitizes them to later close [[sexual attraction]]; it is hypothesized that this effect [[Evolution|evolved]] to prevent inbreeding.

== Contributing factors ==
Several factors may contribute to GSA. People commonly rank faces similar to their own as more attractive, trustworthy, etc. than average. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Penton-Voak|first=I.S.|coauthors=et al.|title=Computer graphic studies of the role of facial similarity in judgements of attractiveness|journal=Current Psychology: Developmental, Learning, Personality, Social|date=Spring 1999|year=1999|volume=18|issue=1|pages=104-117 |url=http://www.psyc.nott.ac.uk/research/vision/jwp/papers/pentonvoak1999.pdf |doi=10.1007/s12144-999-1020-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Heredity]] produces substantial physical similarity between close relatives. However, Bereczkei (2004) attributes this in part to childhood [[imprinting (psychology)|imprinting]] on the opposite-sex parent. Shared interests and personality traits are commonly considered desirable in a mate. The [[heritability]] of these qualities is a matter of [[Nature versus nurture|great debate]]; to whatever extent they are heritable, they will tend to cluster in close relatives. In cases of parent-child attraction, the parent may recognize traits of their own in the child and ultimately end up mating with them. Such reunions typically produce complex emotions in all involved.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://abcnews.go.com/Primetime/Story?id=2886819&amp;page=1|title=Brother and Sister, and Lovers|work=[[ABC News]]|first=Maggie|last=Burbank|date=February 19, 2007|accessdate=October 5, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Instances ==
A brother and sister couple in Germany, the [[Patrick Stübing|Stübings]], fought their country's anti-incest laws. They grew up separately, met as adults, and have had four children. Their appeal was rejected in 2008, upholding Germany's anti-incest laws.&lt;ref&gt;Kate Connolly, [http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2007/feb/27/germany.kateconnolly &quot;Brother and sister fight Germany's incest laws&quot;], ''[[The Guardian]]'', 27 February 2007. Accessed 20 May 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dietmar Hipp: [http://www.spiegel.de/international/germany/0,1518,540831,00.html &quot;Dangerous Love: German High Court Takes a Look at Incest&quot;]. ''[[Der Spiegel]],'' 11 March 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Kathryn Harrison]] published a memoir in the 1990s regarding her four-year incestuous relationship with her biological father, whom she had not seen for almost 20 years prior to beginning the relationship, titled ''The Kiss''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Harrison|first=Kathryn|title=The Kiss|year=1997|publisher=Avon Books, Inc.|isbn=0-380-73147-9|url=http://books.google.com/?id=bGZIfEqPX4cC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=The+kiss+harrison#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A couple in South Africa who had been together for five years and are expecting a child discovered that they are brother and sister just before their wedding. They were raised up separately and met as adults in college.&lt;ref&gt;STEWART MACLEAN, [http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2057081/Engaged-couple-discover-brother-sister-parents-meet-days-wedding.html &quot;Engaged couple discover they are brother and sister when their parents meet just before wedding&quot;], ''[[Daily Mail]]'', 3rd November 2011. Accessed 9th November 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

Garry Ryan at 18 left his pregnant girlfriend and he moved to America. The daughter, Penny Lawrence, grew up and later set out to find her missing father. When they  met, they &quot;both felt an immediate sexual attraction&quot;. They then lived together as a couple and as of April 2012 were expecting their first child together. &lt;ref&gt; [http://enigerianews.blogspot.co.uk/2012/04/i-am-pregnant-with-my-dads-baby-and-we.html &quot;I am pregnant with my dad's baby and We are Madly In love with Each Other&quot;], ''[[Latest Trending News]]'', 30th April 2012. Accessed 13th May 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2012, a 32-year-old father and his 18-year-old daughter were convicted of incest after they admitted to having an incestuous relationship which began in August 2010 when the girl was 16. The incest continued until May 2012 and resulted in the couple having a daughter, who was born in 2011. The teen, who was conceived in an incestuous relationship between the male offender and his 30-year-old foster mother, told the court she was in love with her father and that they had been living as 'husband and wife' after meeting each other in 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;BNONews2012&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=New Zealand father-daughter couple told to end incest |publisher=[[BNO News]] |date=29 August 2012 |url=http://www.bnonews.com/inbox/?id=1069 |accessdate=29 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== In fiction ==

* The theme is present in ''[[Oedipus the King|Oedipus Rex]]'', the [[Classical Athens|Athenian]] tragedy by Sophocles, that was first performed c. 429 BC.
* It is also present in ''[[Le Morte d'Arthur]]'', where King Arthur has an affair with [[Morgause]], who he didn't know at the time was his sister.  His (second) illegitimate son [[Mordred]] is born of that affair.  In the last part of the Morte, Arthur and Mordred kill each other in battle.
* It is also present in ''[[Die Walküre]]'' the second of four operas in the ''[[Der Ring des Nibelungen]]'' cycle by [[Richard Wagner]], in which separated twins Siegmunde and Sieglinde meet in adulthood and fall passionately in love. The fate of their offspring [[Siegfried]] forms the subject matter of the third opera in the cycle.
* [[Vladimir Nabokov]]'s novel ''[[Ada or Ardor: A Family Chronicle|Ada]]'' tells the story of an affair between siblings who believe they are merely cousins (relations between first cousins being acceptable and even common in many eras), including a love triangle with the eponymous character's believed full, actually half sister.
* The eponymous heroine of ''[[Moll Flanders]]'', as an adult, unknowingly marries her half-brother.
* The novels ''[[Flowers in the Attic]]'' and ''[[Garden of Shadows]]'' also deal with an incestuous relationship between brother and sister, Cathy and Christopher, and their subsequent marriage.
* The [[Sam Shepard]] play ''[[Fool for Love (play)|Fool for Love]]'' involves a half brother and half sister who met as teenagers and are still in love ten years on.
* In ''[[Star Wars]]'', Luke Skywalker and Leia Organa are separated twins who meet as adults. In ''[[Star Wars Episode V: The Empire Strikes Back|The Empire Strikes Back]]'', Leia kisses Luke in front of Han Solo to make him jealous. After Leia starts an actual relationship with Han, Luke informs Leia they are siblings, having learned this himself from his Jedi Mentor, Obi-Wan Kenobi.
* In [[J.R.R. Tolkien]]'s ''[[Silmarillion]]'', [[Túrin Turambar|Turin]], the hero of the ''[[Tale of the Children of Hurin]]'', meets his sister [[Nienor]] after having been separated from her in childhood.  The two, failing to recognize each other as siblings, are attracted and marry.
*[[Jax Teller]], the main character of ''[[Sons of Anarchy]]'', almost ends up having sex with his half-sister Trinity when they first meet as adults, not knowing they are related.
* In the Korean film [[Old Boy]] an incestuous relationship occurs between a father and his daughter after a long period of separation.
* In George RR Martin's A Song of Fire and Ice series, Cersei Lannister and her twin brother Jaime, although raised together, carry on an incestuous relationship beginning in childhood. 
* In episode &quot;[[Father Dearest (Law &amp; Order: Special Victims Unit)|Father Dearest]]&quot; of ''[[Law &amp; Order: Special Victims Unit]]'', a man posing as a sperm donor seduces young teenage girls, pretending to be their biological father. Psychiatrist [[George Huang (Law &amp; Order: Special Victims Unit)|Dr George Huang]] identifies the girls' sexual attraction to their father as Genetic Sexual Attraction.
* In [[William F. Buckley, Jr.]]'s novel ''The Redhunter'', the main characters, deeply involved in the [[anti-Communism]] campaign of Sen. [[Joseph McCarthy]], who thought that they were merely the offspring of two men who were best friends, later learn that they are in fact half-siblings and immediately break off their relationship, leaving unresolved feelings of guilt and longing.
* In [[Banana Yoshimoto]]'s Novel [[NP (novel)|NP]], character Sui (at different times) maintains a relationship with her father and her half brother without knowing in the beginning they were related. After finding it out, she still goes on with both relationships.
* In Nip/Tuck Matt met his half sister and they both had an instant attraction without knowing their relationship. 
* In the film [[Joe Dirt]], the title character has sexual intercourse with a woman he believes to be his long-lost sister.
* In the anime/manga series [[Koi Kaze]], the two main characters, Koshiro and Nanoka, develop an attraction for one another before realizing that they are siblings raised separately from one another. The series centers on their struggle with their developing feelings after learning of their relation.

== See also ==
* [[Incest]]
* [[Inbreeding]]
* [[Accidental incest]]
* [[Kin recognition]]
* [[Laws regarding incest]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist}}

== References ==
* {{cite journal | author=Bereczkei, Tamas, et al. | title=Sexual imprinting in human mate choice | journal= Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences | year=2004 | volume=271 | issue=1544 | pages=1129–1134 | url=http://www.journals.royalsoc.ac.uk/(d3345445hr2uftqbb1lyav55)/app/home/contribution.asp?referrer=parent&amp;backto=issue,5,14;journal,49,221;linkingpublicationresults,1:102024,1  | doi=10.1098/rspb.2003.2672 | pmid=15306362 | pmc=1691703}}

== Further reading ==
* Greenberg, M., and Littlewood, R. (1995). [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids=7779767&amp;dopt=Abstract &quot;Post Adoption Incest and Phenotypic Matching: Experience, Personal Meanings and Biosocial Implications&quot;]. ''British Journal of Medical Psychology'' '''68''': 29–44.
* {{cite news |title=Genetic sexual attraction |first=Alix |last= Kirsta |newspaper=[[The Guardian]] |date=17 May 2003 |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/theguardian/2003/may/17/weekend7.weekend2}}
* {{cite news |title=Genetic sexual attraction: Forbidden love | newspaper=[[CBC News]] | date= 7 May 2009 | url= http://www.cbc.ca/canada/story/2009/05/06/f-gsa.html }}
* &quot;Genetic Sexual Attraction&quot;-web page: http://www.geneticsexualattraction.com 

[[Category:Adoption reunion]]
[[Category:Incest]]
[[Category:Sexual attraction]]

[[cs:Genetická sexuální přitažlivost]]
[[da:Genetisk seksuel tiltrækning]]
[[es:Atracción sexual genética]]
[[ko:유전적 성적 이끌림]]
[[it:Attrazione sessuale genetica]]
[[lt:Genetinis lytinis potraukis]]
[[ja:ジェネティック・セクシュアル・アトラクション]]
[[fi:Geneettinen seksuaalinen viehätys]]
[[zh:遗传性性吸引]]</text>
      <sha1>1ww41dyjfdrkrx3kmhyl9c933tz3bko</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
