<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Hentai</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>14183</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519867473</id>
      <parentid>519321993</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-26T02:11:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Preslethe</username>
        <id>249117</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>minor linguistic edits</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20422">{{pp-semi-indef|small=yes|expiry=April 01, 2009}}
[[File:Hentai - yuuree-redraw.jpg|thumb|Hentai illustration typical for [[eroge]]s]]
{{nihongo|'''Hentai'''|変態 or へんたい|}} ''{{Audio|Hentai.ogg|listen}}'' is a [[Japanese language|Japanese]] word that, in the [[Western world|West]], describes sexually explicit or [[Pornography|pornographic]] [[comic]]s and [[animation]]—especially those of Japanese origin, such as [[anime]], [[manga]], and [[eroge]]. The word ''hentai'' is a [[kanji]] compound of 変 (''hen''; &quot;change&quot;, &quot;weird&quot;, or &quot;strange&quot;) and 態 (''tai''; &quot;attitude&quot; or &quot;appearance&quot;). The term is used as a shortened form of the phrase 変態性欲 (''hentai seiyoku'') meaning &quot;sexual [[perversion]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Short History&quot;/&gt; In Japanese slang, ''hentai'' is used as an insult meaning roughly &quot;pervert&quot; or &quot;weirdo&quot;.

The English use of ''hentai'' is more similar to the way the Japanese use the slang term エッチ (''H'' or ''[[ecchi]]''), which refers to any sexually explicit content or behaviour. The Japanese seldom use the term ''hentai'' to refer to [[pornography in Japan]]. Instead, terms such as {{Nihongo3||18禁|18-kin|extra=&quot;18-prohibited&quot;}}, meaning &quot;prohibited to those not yet 18 years old&quot;, and {{Nihongo3||成人漫画|'''seijin manga'''|extra=&quot;adult manga&quot;}} are used.&lt;ref name=&quot;Short History&quot;/&gt; Less official terms also in use include {{nihongo|'''[[erotic|ero]] anime'''|エロアニメ}}, {{nihongo|'''ero manga'''|エロ漫画}}, and the English acronym '''AV''' (for &quot;adult video&quot;).

==History==
The earliest association between anime and adult animation occurred prior to the 1972 release of ''[[Fritz the Cat (film)|Fritz the Cat]]'' when American distributors attempted to cash in on the publicity garnered from the rating by rushing out dubbed versions of two other adult animations from Japan, both of which featured an X rating in their advertising material: ''Senya ichiya monogatari'' and ''Kureopatora'', retitled ''[[One Thousand and One Arabian Nights (film)|One Thousand and One Arabian Nights]]'' and ''[[Cleopatra: Queen of Sex]]'', respectively.  However, neither film was actually submitted to the [[MPAA]], and it is not likely that either feature would have received an X rating.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.michaelbarrier.com/Funnyworld/FritzPartOne/FritzOne.htm |title=Funnyworld Revisited: I. Bucking the Tide |publisher=MichaelBarrier.com |date= |accessdate=2011-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''One Thousand and One Nights'' was the first erotic animated feature film, and at 130 minutes, it remains one of the longest animated films.

The ''[[Lolita Anime]]'' series was the first hentai [[original video animation]] (OVA), released in 1984 by Wonder Kids, which mainly focused on underage sex, rape, and [[Bondage (sexual)|bondage]].  ''[[Cream Lemon]]'', which contained many themes found in hentai today, was released later that year by Fairy Dust and contained some in-depth storylines and classic (late 1970s to early 1980s style) artwork.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.animenation.net/blog/2003/07/22/ask-john-how-much-cream-lemon-is-there/  |title=Ask John: How Much Cream Lemon is There?| publisher=animenation.net }}&lt;/ref&gt;  ''The Brothers Grime'' was a three-video cartoon-pornography series produced by Excalibur Films in 1986, 1987, and 1988, using titles primarily from the ''Cream Lemon'' series, the most popular of Japan's erotic anime before ''[[Urotsukidoji]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Anime Porn Market&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.awn.com/mag/issue3.4/3.4pages/3.4patten.html |title=The Anime &quot;Porn&quot; Market |publisher=awn.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the tentacle scene in [[Guyver: Out of Control]] in December 1986, the ''[[Urotsukidoji]]'' [[anime]] series by [[Toshio Maeda]] was released on OVA beginning in 1987 and released in America in 1992 by [[Central Park Media|Anime 18]].  It is most famous for being viewed as the first in the [[tentacle rape]] genre, though only one scene in the first OVA actually contains any tentacle rape.  Tentacle rape was not present in the ''Urotsukidoji'' [[manga]], but was featured in a series that he would publish years later called ''[[Demon Beast Invasion]]''.  ''Demon Beast Invasion'' created what might be called the modern paradigm of tentacle porn, in which the elements of sexual assault are emphasized. Maeda explained that he invented the practice to get around strict [[Japanese censorship regulations]], which prohibit the depiction of the [[penis]] but apparently do not prohibit showing sexual penetration by a tentacle or similar (often robotic) appendage.  Maeda went on to create ''[[La Blue Girl]]'', which departs somewhat from its predecessors by lightening the atmosphere with humor, lightly parodying the tentacle rape genre.

In November 1994, [[A.D. Vision]] released their first title, ''[[The Legend of Lyon]]'', under its hentai label, Soft Cel Pictures. A.D. Vision put out 19 Soft Cel Pictures releases during 1995 and 12 through the first half of 1996, some of which were rereleases of previous A.D. Vision Films titles in their unedited form.&lt;ref name=&quot;Anime Porn Market&quot; /&gt;  Soft Cel Pictures shut down in 2005 and most of its titles were acquired by [[The Right Stuf International|Critical Mass]].

[[The Right Stuf International|Critical Mass]] was created in 1996 when The Right Stuf made a deal with [[Manga Entertainment]] to release an unedited edition of ''[[Violence Jack]]'', which they deemed too intense for their normal line.&lt;ref name=&quot;Anime Porn Market&quot; /&gt;  Critical Mass has since released a large number of hentai titles.  Most of their titles are associated with ''The [[Vanilla Series]]'', a series of hentai titles produced in Japan by Digital Works which are tied-in with [[eroge]] games of the same title.  When [[Central Park Media]] went bankrupt in the year of 2009, the licenses for all Anime 18-related products and movies were transferred to Critical Mass.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2009-06-08/central-park-media-licenses-offered-by-liquidator |title=Central Park Media's Licenses Offered by Liquidator |publisher=Animenewsnetwork.com |date=2009-06-08 |accessdate=2011-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Censorship is practiced differently in Japan and in the USA, due to their different laws.  Japanese law discourages showing of genitals in hentai, while the United States is more concerned about forbidding the display of sex acts involving people under 18, so the characters in hentai have to look 18 or older.  Hence, there are censoring mosaics in Japan, and scene removals and different ages of characters in America.&lt;ref name=&quot;Anime Porn Market&quot; /&gt;  While not featuring the censoring mosaics of the original Japanese version, the US release of ''[[La Blue Girl]]'' was [[edited]] during the initial VHS release and all scenes featuring Miko's companion Nin-Nin engaged in a sexual act were removed, probably to avoid the charge of [[pedophilia]], in spite of the fact that the character is not a minor but a [[dwarfism|dwarf]] ninja.  For similar reasons, the age of the heroine was also altered: initially stated to be a 16 year old high-schooler in the original Japanese version, she is an 18 year old [[college]] student in the US version. The DVD release contains this edited version.&lt;ref name=&quot;editingreport&quot;&gt;''[http://www.animeprime.com/index.shtml Anime Prime]'' (April 14, 2004). &quot;[http://www.animeprime.com/reports/lbg.shtml La Blue Girl Editing Report]&quot;. Retrieved November 27, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;animexcpm2000&quot;&gt;''[http://www.mania.com/ Mania]'' (July 03, 2000). &quot;[http://www.mania.com/anime-expo-central-park-media-panel_article_86089.html Anime Expo - Central Park Media Panel]&quot; by Chris Beveridge. Retrieved November 27, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;  In the UK, the [[British Board of Film Classification]] refused to classify it, thus prohibiting its distribution.&lt;ref name=&quot;LBGrejectedBBFC&quot;&gt;''[http://www.bbfc.co.uk/general/index.php bbfc]'' (December 30, 1996). &quot;[http://www.bbfc.co.uk/website/Classified.nsf/ClassifiedWorks/06F862821A46D9C8802566C00033C26C?OpenDocument LA BLUE GIRL Rejected by the BBFC]&quot;. Retrieved November 27, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BBFCCatherineTaylorTalks&quot;&gt;''UK Anime''. &quot;[http://www.ukanime.com/template2.php?page=bbfcint.php The BBFC Talks Hentai]&quot;. [http://web.archive.org/web/*/http://www.ukanime.com/template2.php?page=bbfcint.php Archived copies] from the [[Wayback Machine]]. Retrieved from the Internet Archive Wayback Machine November 27, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Demographics==
As with other forms of Japanese pop-culture media, publishers of erotic media target material to specific demographic groups. For manga, the most typical divisions are:

===Types which are pornographic by definition===
*'''ero-manga''' or {{Nihongo|''seijin''|成人||literally &quot;adult&quot;}}, aimed at (presumptively heterosexual) men
*'''ladies' comics''' (''redīsu komikku'' or ''redicomi''), originally meaning any manga for adult women&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Gravett|first=Paul|authorlink=Paul Gravett|title=[[Manga: Sixty Years of Japanese Comics]]|publisher=Laurence King Publishing|year=2004|page=116|isbn=1-85669-391-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; (see [[josei]]) but now often applied specifically to pornographic manga for women&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Shamoon|first=Deborah|title=Porn Studies|editor=[[Linda Williams (United States film critic)|Linda Williams]]|publisher=[[Duke University Press]]|year=2004|pages=77–103|chapter=Office Sluts and Rebel Flowers: The Pleasures of Japanese Pornographic Comics for Women|isbn=0-8223-3312-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Types which often (but do not necessarily) contain pornographic content===
*'''[[Bara (genre)|gei comi]]''' or ''menslove'' (ML), often called ''bara'' in the West, for gay men
*'''[[Yaoi|boys' love]]''' (''boizu rabu'' or BL), predominately aimed at the [[Shōjo manga|shōjo]] and [[Josei manga|josei]] markets (also see below)
*'''teen's love''' (TL), a more explicit type of [[Shōjo manga|shōjo]] [[Romance novel|romances]], likewise aimed predominantly at the [[Shōjo manga|shōjo]] and [[Josei manga|josei]] markets
*'''[[Yuri (genre)|yuri]]''' or ''girls' love'' (GL), which has long been a component of both men's ''ero-manga'' and [[Shōjo manga|shōjo]] gender-exploration but has more recently arisen as a genre in its own right, in both ''seijin'' and [[Josei manga|josei]] flavors (also see below)

==Classification==
[[File:Lolicon Sample.png|thumb|[[Lolicon]] art often blends childlike characteristics with erotic undertones]]
Hentai that features mainly heterosexual interactions occur in both male-targeted (''ero'') and female-targeted (&quot;ladies' comics&quot;) form. Those that feature mainly [[homosexuality|homosexual]] interactions are known as [[yaoi]] (male-male) and [[Yuri (genre)|yuri]] (female-female). Both yaoi and, to a lesser extent, yuri are generally aimed at members of the opposite sex from the persons depicted.

Yaoi commonly features males of ambiguous [[gender]]—in both physical appearance and, frequently, mannerism—called ''[[bishōnen]]'',  literally &quot;beautiful boy&quot;. Some feature ''biseinen'' (&quot;beautiful man&quot;), males of more adult or masculine appearance than ''bishōnen''. Less common are ''bara''—larger, often heavily muscled and sometimes hairy males, the yaoi counterpart of the &quot;[[Bear community|bear]]&quot; in [[gay pornography]]—as well as ''[[oyaji]]'' (meaning &quot;daddy&quot; or &quot;uncle&quot;), featuring middle-aged and elderly men; these types are mainly found in material aimed at gay men, which may be called ''[[Bara (genre)|bara]]'' or 'men's love' (ML), and is considered to be distinct from yaoi.&lt;ref name=&quot;pedagogy&quot;&gt;Wilson, Brent; Toku, Masami. [http://www.csuchico.edu/~mtoku/vc/Articles/toku/Wil_Toku_BoysLove.html &quot;Boys' Love,&quot; Yaoi, and Art Education: Issues of Power and Pedagogy] 2003&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Korean Fandom&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://moongsil.com/study/yaoi_eng.pdf|format=PDF|title=Reading YAOI Comics: An Analysis of Korean Girls’ Fandom|last=Noh|first=Sueen|year=2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; Yaoi also extends beyond the hentai genre, since it applies to any anime/manga material that includes male homosexuality, except for that actually aimed at a gay male audience. In Western usage, yaoi is distinguished from [[shōnen-ai]] (literally, &quot;boy-love&quot;), in which two males merely express romantic feelings for each other without actually having sexual relations; however in current Japanese usage this term most commonly refers to pornographic [[shotacon]] for men. Women interested in Yaoi are called &quot;[[Fujoshi]]&quot; (腐女子), a [[pun]] which translate loosely as &quot;rotten girl&quot;  or &quot;rotten woman&quot;.

Yuri is very similar to yaoi, except that the focus is on female homosexual interactions. The characters in yuri are typically &quot;[[bishōjo]]&quot;, meaning &quot;beautiful girl&quot; (this term is not specific to yuri but is applied generally to depictions of attractive women for a male audience; for example, in the term &quot;[[bishōjo game]]&quot;). Shōjo-ai (&quot;girl love&quot;) is a western term for the female equivalent of shōnen-ai; in Japan these works are also called yuri. Yuri may be aimed at (presumptively heterosexual) male, [[heterosexual]] female, or [[lesbian]] female audiences.

Hentai is perceived as &quot;dwelling&quot; on [[sexual fetishism|sexual fetishes]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Peek-a-boo&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.springerlink.com/content/r1267467784j8710/ |title=Peek-a-boo, I See You: Watching Japanese Hard-core Animation |doi=10.1007/s12119-008-9039-5 |publisher=Springerlink.com |date= |accessdate=2011-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; including:
*[[Bakunyū]], the depiction of women with large breasts. Literally translated to &quot;bursting breasts&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[Jason Thompson (writer)|Thompson, Jason]]. (2007) [[Manga: The Complete Guide]]; p. 451.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Futanari]], depictions of [[hermaphrodites]] or [[transsexualism|transsexuals]] that have both phallic genitalia (penis with scrotum, only a penile shaft, or an enlarged clitoris) and vaginal genitalia, or, alternatively, a feminine hourglass shape including breasts combined with a penis and scrotum.
*[[Incest]], sexual activity with legal family members; noticeably seen in ''[[The Sagara Family]]'', a hentai computer game.
*[[Lolicon]], depicts [[prepubescent]] or [[preadolescent]] girls.
*{{nihongo|[[Omorashi]]|オモラシ / おもらし / お漏らし}} in which individuals struggle with a full bladder before finally wetting themselves (also known as [[Urolagnia|watersports]]).
*[[Shotacon]], the depiction of young boys, either with other young boys or older men, or depicting young boys with older women (known as &quot;straight shota&quot; in western jargon).
*[[Tentacle erotica]], the depiction of tentacled creatures and sometimes monsters (fictional imaginative or otherwise, also includes alien-like creatures) engaging in sex or [[sexual assault|rape]] with girls and, less often, men.

==Hentai media==
[[File:Hentai manga in Japan 002.jpg|right|thumb|Hentai manga on display at a Japanese bookstore.]]
*Adult anime, or [[List of hentai anime|hentai anime]], is anime that relies primarily on sex.
*Adult manga, or hentai manga, is manga designed for purely pornographic purposes. Plot is still used to develop character and setting, but most of the time, the ultimate goal is to show scenes of sexuality with few exceptions. Adult manga is often sold in convenience stores, book stores, and magazine stores in Japan, and also other public places such as airports, and is far more prolific and accessible than the U.S. adult [[comic book]] market. It is usually distributed in [[digest size|digest format]], containing several stories by different artists (e.g. an [[anthology]]).
*Adult [[CG artwork]] includes individual drawings by artists. Art can be available on websites, [[CD-ROM]]s, or in printed art books. CG artwork is used frequently in adult video games.
*Adult video games, or [[eroge]], are games with a pornographic element. They can include [[bishōjo game]]s that involve character driven plots, and can exist as sex [[simulation]]s.
*Adult dōjinshi, or H dōjinshi, refers to a type of work that uses copyrighted characters presented in sexual situations. It usually refers to printed manga, but can also refer to any type of visual work depicting copyrighted characters, including video games, animation, and CG artwork. Familiarity with a particular character or setting can add a sense of relating to the character over a generic character used in mainstream hentai, making dōjinshi more appealing to fans of a particular work. Despite not representing characters and licensed properties as intended, companies often view these works as a free form of license recognition and advertising through dedicated fandom. Some manga artists create hentai dōjinshi with characters from their own manga, such as [[Maki Murakami]] creating dōjinshi of ''[[Gravitation (manga)|Gravitation]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.publishersweekly.com/article/CA6474900.html |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20100209115249/http://www.publishersweekly.com/article/CA6474900.html |archivedate=2010-02-09 |title=Sex &amp; Silliness: Maki Murakami’s Gravitation |publisher=publishersweekly.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://intersections.anu.edu.au/issue20/pagliassotti.htm |title=GloBLisation and Hybridisation: Publishers' Strategies for Bringing Boys' Love to the United States |author=Dru Pagliassotti  |date = April 2009|publisher=intersections.anu.edu.au }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Lemon===
In Western [[fanfiction]] circles, hentai-based works are popularly referred to as &quot;lemon&quot;, based on a more popular hentai anime anthology series called ''[[Cream Lemon]]''. Fictions referred to as &quot;lime&quot; are ones in which the characters do everything short of having sexual intercourse with each other.&lt;ref name=&quot;Short History&quot;&gt;[http://wwwsshe.murdoch.edu.au/intersections/issue12/mclelland.html &quot;A Short History of &lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;''Hentai''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;&quot;], by Mark McLelland, ''Intersections: Gender, History and Culture in the Asian Context'', Issue 12, January 2006.  Footnoted HTML version.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Pornography|Anime and Manga}}
*[[Cartoon pornography]]
*[[Ero guro]]
*[[List of hentai authors]] (groups, studios, production companies, circles)
*[[List of pornographic sub-genres]]
*[[Panchira]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* Aquila, Meredith (2007). &quot;[http://www.upress.umn.edu/Books/L/lunning_mechademia2.html Ranma 1/2 Fan Fiction Writers: New Narrative Themes or the Same Old Story?]&quot; ''[[Mechademia]] 2''.
* Buckley, Sandra (1991). &quot;'Penguin in Bondage': A Graphic Tale of Japanese Comic Books&quot;, pp.&amp;nbsp;163–196, In ''Technoculture''. C. Penley and A. Ross, eds. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota. ISBN 0-8166-1932-8.
* McCarthy, Helen, and [[Jonathan Clements]] (1998). ''The Erotic Anime Movie Guide''. London: Titan. ISBN 1-85286-946-1.
* {{Cite book | last = Napier | first = Susan J. |authorlink=Susan J. Napier | year = 2000 | title = [[Anime from Akira to Princess Mononoke: Experiencing Contemporary Japanese Animation|Anime: From ''Akira'' to ''Princess Mononoke'']] | location = New York | publisher = Palgrave | isbn = 0-312-23863-0}}
* Perper, Timothy and Cornog, Martha (March 2002). [http://www.springerlink.com/content/30p8x1878nbjlrax/ Eroticism for the masses: Japanese manga comics and their assimilation into the U.S.] ''Sexuality &amp; Culture'', '''6''' (1) pp.&amp;nbsp;3–126.

==External links==
{{commons category|Hentai}}
*[http://www.seekjapan.jp/article-1/744/The+(Almost)+Complete+Japanzine+Dictionary+of+Japan+Sex Dictionary of Japan Sex]

{{Japanese Erotic Cinema}}
[[Category:Hentai| ]]
[[Category:Anime and manga terminology]]
[[Category:Japanese sex terms]]
[[Category:Pornographic animation]]

{{Link GA|uk}}
{{Link FA|ru}}
{{Link GA|zh}}
{{Link FA|zh}}

[[ar:هنتاي]]
[[ast:Hentai]]
[[bg:Хентай]]
[[bo:ཧེན་ཐའེ།]]
[[ca:Hentai]]
[[cs:Hentai]]
[[da:Hentai]]
[[de:Hentai]]
[[et:Hentai]]
[[el:Χεντάι]]
[[es:Hentai]]
[[eo:Hentajo]]
[[fa:هنتای]]
[[fr:Hentai]]
[[gl:Hentai]]
[[ko:헨타이]]
[[id:Hentai]]
[[is:Hentai]]
[[it:Hentai]]
[[he:הנטאי]]
[[hu:Hentai]]
[[ms:Hentai]]
[[nl:Hentai]]
[[ja:ヘンタイ]]
[[no:Hentai]]
[[pl:Hentai]]
[[pt:Hentai]]
[[ro:Hentai]]
[[ru:Хентай]]
[[sq:Hentai]]
[[simple:Hentai]]
[[sk:Hentai]]
[[sr:Хентај]]
[[fi:Hentai]]
[[sv:Hentai]]
[[tl:Hentai]]
[[th:เฮ็นไต]]
[[tr:Hentai]]
[[uk:Хентай]]
[[vi:Hentai]]
[[zh:變態 (日語)]]</text>
      <sha1>mg4l87orsffq6map6etutpc9o76n3n0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
