<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Orgasm</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>22546</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519596557</id>
      <parentid>515670887</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-24T16:41:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>1exec1</username>
        <id>7661756</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>date formats per [[WP:MOSNUM]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="114588">{{Other uses}}
{{pp-semi-indef}}{{pp-move-indef}}
[[File:Podkowiński-Szał uniesień-MNK.jpg|thumb|225px|''[[Frenzy of Exultations]]'' (1894), by [[Władysław Podkowiński]]]]

'''Orgasm''' (from Greek οργασμός ''orgasmos'', from ''organ'' to mature, swell, also '''sexual climax''') is the sudden discharge of accumulated sexual tension during the [[Human sexual response cycle|sexual response cycle]], resulting in rhythmic [[Muscle contraction|muscular contractions]] in the [[human pelvis|pelvic]] region characterized by an intense sensation of pleasure.&lt;ref name=&quot;M&amp;J&quot;&gt;{{Cite book| publisher = Little, Brown | isbn = 0-316-54987-8, 9780316549875 | page = 366 | last = Masters | first = William H. | coauthors = Virginia E. Johnson, Reproductive Biology Research Foundation (U.S.) | title = Human Sexual Response | year = 1966}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;health.discovery.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Orgasm| publisher=Health.discovery.com|accessdate=21 April 2010|url=http://health.discovery.com/centers/sex/sexpedia/orgasm.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; Experienced by males and females, orgasms are controlled by the involuntary or [[autonomic nervous system]]. They are often associated with other involuntary actions, including muscular [[spasm]]s in multiple areas of the body, a general [[Euphoria (emotion)|euphoric]] sensation and, frequently, body movements and [[Manner of articulation|vocalization]]s are expressed. The period after orgasm (known as a [[refractory period (sex)|refractory period]]) is often a relaxing experience, attributed to the release of the [[neurohormone]]s [[oxytocin]] and [[prolactin]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Exton MS, Krüger TH, Koch M, ''et al.'' |title=Coitus-induced orgasm stimulates prolactin secretion in healthy subjects |journal=Psychoneuroendocrinology |volume=26 |issue=3 |pages=287–94 |year=2001 |month=April |pmid=11166491 |doi=10.1016/S0306-4530(00)00053-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Human orgasms usually result from the stimulation of the [[human penis|penis]] in males, typically accompanying [[ejaculation]], and the [[clitoris]] in females.&lt;ref name=health.discovery.com/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Weiten&quot;&gt;{{cite book|authors=Wayne Weiten, Dana S. Dunn, Elizabeth Yost Hammer|title=Psychology Applied to Modern Life: Adjustment in the 21st Century|isbn =1-111-18663-4, 9781111186630|publisher=Cengage Learning|year=2011|pages=688 pages|accessdate=5 January 2012|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=CGu96TeAZo0C&amp;pg=PT423&amp;dq=&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=MwIGT-jxEojU2AWzv5ylCg&amp;ved=0CDwQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Connell&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|author=O'Connell HE, Sanjeevan KV, Hutson JM |title=Anatomy of the clitoris |journal=The Journal of Urology |volume=174 |issue=4 Pt 1 |pages=1189–95 |year=2005 |month=October |pmid=16145367 |laysummary=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/health/5013866.stm Time for rethink on the clitoris -|laysource=[[BBC News]] |laydate=11 June 2006 |doi=10.1097/01.ju.0000173639.38898.cd}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stimulation can be by self-practice ([[masturbation]]) or by a partner (penetrative [[sexual intercourse]], [[non-penetrative sex]], and other erotic sexual activities). In addition, partners simultaneously stimulating each other's sex organs by mutual masturbation, penetrative intercourse, or other rhythmic inter-genital contact may experience simultaneous orgasms.

==Definitions==
In a clinical context, orgasm is usually defined strictly by the muscular contractions involved during sexual activity, along with the characteristic patterns of change in heart rate, blood pressure, and often respiration rate and depth.&lt;ref name=&quot;M&amp;J&quot;/&gt; This is categorized as the sudden discharge of accumulated sexual tension during the [[Human sexual response cycle|sexual response cycle]], resulting in rhythmic muscular contractions in the pelvic region.&lt;ref name=&quot;M&amp;J&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;health.discovery.com&quot;/&gt; However, definitions of 'orgasm' vary and there is sentiment that consensus on how to consistently classify it is absent.&lt;ref name=levine_orgasm&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Levine, R.J.|year=2004|title=An orgasm is... who defines what an orgasm is?|journal=[[Sexual and Relationship Therapy]]|volume=19|pages=101–107 |doi=10.1080/14681990410001641663}}&lt;/ref&gt; At least twenty-six definitions of orgasm were listed in the journal ''Clinical Psychology Review''.&lt;ref name=mah_&amp;_binik&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Mah K, Binik YM |title=The nature of human orgasm: a critical review of major trends |journal=Clinical Psychology Review |volume=21 |issue=6 |pages=823–56 |year=2001 |month=August |pmid=11497209 |doi=10.1016/S0272-7358(00)00069-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There is some debate whether certain types of sexual sensations should be accurately classified as orgasms, including female orgasms caused by [[G-Spot]] stimulation alone, and the demonstration of extended or continuous orgasms lasting several minutes or even an hour.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| author =  Schwartz, Bob | title = The One Hour Orgasm: A New Approach to Achieving Maximum Sexual Pleasure | publisher = Breakthru Publishing | month = May | year = 1992 | isbn = 0-942540-07-7}}{{Page needed|date=August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The question centers around the clinical definition of orgasm, but this way of viewing orgasm is merely physiological, while there are also psychological, endocrinological, and neurological definitions of 'orgasm'.&lt;ref name=levine_orgasm/&gt;&lt;ref name=mah_&amp;_binik/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mah&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Kenneth Mah, Yitzchak M. Binik|title=Do all orgasms feel alike? Evaluating a two-dimensional model of the orgasm experience across gender and sexual context|work=[[The Journal of Sex Research]]|date=May 2002|accessdate=27 August 2012|url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-91475118.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; In these and similar cases, the sensations experienced are subjective and do not necessarily involve the involuntary contractions characteristic of orgasm. However, the sensations in both sexes are extremely pleasurable and are often felt throughout the body, causing a mental state that is often described as transcendental, and with [[vasocongestion]] and associated pleasure comparable to that of a full-contractionary orgasm. For example, modern findings support distinction between ejaculation and male orgasm.&lt;ref name=mah_&amp;_binik/&gt; For this reason, there are views on both sides as to whether these can be accurately defined as orgasms.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mah&quot;/&gt;

==Achieving orgasm==
===In general===
Orgasms may be achieved by a variety of activities. In men, sufficient stimulation can be achieved during [[vagina]]l or [[anal sex|anal]] sexual intercourse, [[oral sex]] ([[fellatio]]) or masturbation/[[non-penetrative sex]]. In women, orgasm can be achieved during vaginal sexual intercourse, oral sex ([[cunnilingus]]) or masturbation/non-penetrative sex. It may also be by the use of a [[Vibrator (sex toy)|sensual vibrator]] or an [[erotic electrostimulation]], and can additionally be achieved by stimulation of the [[nipples]], [[uterus]], or other [[erogenous zone]]s, though this is rarer.&lt;ref name=&quot;Otto&quot;&gt;Otto, Herbert A. (1988) New Orgasm Options: Expanding Sexual Pleasure.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Answer&quot;&gt;{{cite book|authors =Barry R. Komisaruk, [[Beverly Whipple]], Sara Nasserzadeh, Carlos Beyer-Flores|title=The Orgasm Answer Guide|isbn = 0-8018-9396-8, 9780801893964|publisher=JHU Press|year=2009|pages=151 pages|accessdate=6 November 2011|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Kkts3AX9QVAC&amp;pg=PA108&amp;dq=anal+orgasm&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=Fii3TuC2NfCpsALW8fHsAw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=6&amp;ved=0CEcQ6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q=anal%20orgasm&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to physical stimulation, orgasm can be achieved from psychological arousal alone, such as during [[dream]]ing (nocturnal emission for males or females)&lt;ref name=mah_&amp;_binik/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mah&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Komisaruk&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |authors=Komisaruk, B., &amp; [[Whipple, B.]]|title=Functional MRI of the brain during orgasm in women|journal=Annual review of sex research|volume= 16 |pages= 62–86|year=2005 |pmid= |accessdate=3 January 2012|url=http://www.scribd.com/doc/302148/Functional-MRI-of-the-Brain-During-Orgasm-In-Women}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cornforth&quot;&gt;{{cite web|first=Tracee|last=Cornforth|title=The Clitoral Truth. Interview with author and sex educator Rebecca Chalker.|publisher=[[About.com]]|date=17 July 2009|accessdate=21 April 2010|url=http://womenshealth.about.com/cs/sexuality/a/clitoraltruthin.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; or by [[orgasm control]]. Orgasm by psychological stimulation alone was first reported among people who had [[spinal cord injury]] (SCI).&lt;ref name=&quot;Komisaruk&quot;/&gt; Although SCI very often leads to loss of certain sensations and altered self-perception, a person with this disturbance is not deprived of sexual feelings such as [[sexual arousal]] and erotic desires.&lt;ref name=&quot;Komisaruk&quot;/&gt;

Orgasms can be multiple or spontaneous,&lt;ref name=&quot;Dunn&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Dunn ME, Trost JE |title=Male multiple orgasms: a descriptive study |journal=Archives of Sexual Behavior |volume=18 |issue=5 |pages=377–87 |year=1989 |month=October |pmid=2818169 |doi=10.1007/BF01541970}}&lt;/ref&gt; and some non-sexual activity may result in a spontaneous orgasm. Orgasms can also be involuntary, as the result of forced sexual contact as during rape or [[sexual assault]], and are often associated with feelings of [[shame]] caused by internalization of victim-blaming attitudes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.anugrahaa.com/downloads/Fr.%20D.J.Antony%20-%20Trauma%20Counselling.pdf] D. John Anthony, &quot;Trauma Counseling&quot;, Anugraha Publications, Tamil Nadu, India, Sep. 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Non-consensual&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Levin RJ, van Berlo W |title=Sexual arousal and orgasm in subjects who experience forced or non-consensual sexual stimulation – a review |journal=Journal of Clinical Forensic Medicine |volume=11 |issue=2 |pages=82–8 |year=2004 |month=April |pmid=15261004 |doi=10.1016/j.jcfm.2003.10.008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The incidence of those who experience unsolicited sexual contact and experience orgasm is very low, though possibly under-reported due to shame or embarrassment. Involuntary orgasms additionally happen regardless of gender.&lt;ref name=&quot;Non-consensual&quot;/&gt;

Scientific literature focuses on the female orgasm significantly more than it does on the male orgasm, which &quot;appears to reflect the assumption that female orgasm is psychologically more complex than male orgasm,&quot; but &quot;the limited empirical evidence available suggests that male and female orgasm may bear more similarities than differences. In one controlled study by Vance and Wagner (1976), independent raters could not differentiate written descriptions of male versus female orgasm experiences&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mah&quot;/&gt;

===In males===
====Two-stage model====
In men, the most common way of achieving orgasm is by the [[sexual stimulation|stimulation]] of the [[human penis|penis]].&lt;ref name=health.discovery.com/&gt; This is usually accompanied by [[ejaculation]]. It is possible for a man to have an orgasm without ejaculation (known as a &quot;dry orgasm&quot;) or to ejaculate without reaching orgasm (which may be a case of [[delayed ejaculation]], a [[nocturnal emission]] or a case of [[anorgasmic ejaculation]]).&lt;ref name=mah_&amp;_binik/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dunn&quot;/&gt; Men may also achieve orgasm by stimulation of the [[prostate]] ([[#Anal and nipple stimulation in males and females|see below]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Male hot spot&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title= The male hot spot – Massaging the prostate|publisher=[[Go Ask Alice!]]|date=27 September 2002|accessdate=21 April 2010|url=http://goaskalice.columbia.edu/male-hot-spot-massaging-prostate}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

&quot;The traditional view assumes there are two stages of orgasm in males: emission following orgasm, almost instantly followed by a [[refractory period (sex)|refractory period]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dunn&quot;/&gt; In 1966, [[Masters and Johnson]] published pivotal research about the phases of sexual stimulation.&lt;ref name=M&amp;J/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title=Masters and Johnson | url=http://health.discovery.com/centers/sex/sexpedia/mandj.html | publisher=The Discovery Channel | accessdate=28 May 2006 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20060518002107/http://health.discovery.com/centers/sex/sexpedia/mandj.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 18 May 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Their work included women and men, and, unlike [[Alfred Kinsey]] in 1948 and 1953,&lt;ref name=&quot;Andersen&quot;&gt;{{cite book|authors=Margaret L. Andersen, Howard Francis Taylor|title=Sociology: understanding a diverse society|isbn = 0-495-00742-0, 9780495007425|publisher=Cengage Learning|year=2007|pages=151 pages|accessdate=3 January 2012|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=UILcQZS6Bi4C&amp;pg=PA338&amp;dq=Kinsey+criticized+Freud&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=jFADT5u0KKWo2wXY9pSeAg&amp;ved=0CDcQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Kinsey%20criticized%20Freud&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; tried to determine the [[physiology|physiological]] stages before and after orgasm. Masters and Johnson argued that, in the first stage, &quot;accessory organs contract and the male can feel the ejaculation coming; two to three seconds later the ejaculation occurs, which the man cannot constrain, delay, or in any way control&quot; and that, in the second stage, &quot;the male feels pleasurable contractions during ejaculation, reporting greater pleasure tied to a greater volume of ejaculate&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dunn&quot;/&gt; They reported that, unlike females, &quot;for the man the resolution phase includes a superimposed refractory period&quot; and added that &quot;many males below the age of 30, but relatively few thereafter, have the ability to ejaculate frequently and are subject to only very short refractory periods during the resolution phase&quot;. Masters and Johnson equated male orgasm and ejaculation and maintained the necessity for a refractory period between orgasms.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dunn&quot;/&gt; 
====Subsequent and multiple orgasms====
In contrast to the two-stage model, Kahn (1939) equalized orgasm and ejaculation and stated that several orgasms can occur and that &quot;indeed, some men are capable of following it up with a third and a fourth&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dunn&quot;/&gt; Though rare, Kahn's assertion that &quot;some men are capable of following [an orgasm] up with a third and a fourth&quot; is supported by men who have reported having multiple, consecutive orgasms, particularly without ejaculation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dunn&quot;/&gt; Males who experience dry orgasms can often produce multiple orgasms, as the refractory period is reduced.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dunn&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Janssen&quot;&gt;{{Cite book| author=Janssen, D.F. | title=Growing Up Sexually – The Sexual Curriculum |month=October | year=2002 | chapter=Volume II: The Sexual Curriculum: The Manufacture and Performance of Pre-Adult Sexualities. | chapterurl=http://www2.rz.hu-berlin.de/sexology/GESUND/ARCHIV/GUS/CHILDORG.HTM}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some men are able to masturbate for hours at a time, achieving orgasm many times.&lt;ref name=&quot;Janssen&quot;/&gt; Many men who began masturbation or other sexual activity prior to puberty report having been able to achieve multiple non-ejaculatory orgasms. Some evidence indicates that orgasms of men before puberty are qualitatively similar to the &quot;normal&quot; female experience of orgasm, suggesting that hormonal changes during puberty have a strong influence on the character of male orgasm.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.themarriagebed.com/pages/sexuality/splay/betterforhim.shtml | title=How to make sex better for him | accessdate=2 November 2006 | last=Byerly | first=Paul &amp; Lori  | quote=Boys who discover masturbation before puberty can't ejaculate, but they can have orgasms. They can also have multiple orgasms like women can, but then lose this ability when puberty adds ejaculation to their orgasms.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some men have been multiorgasmic since they can recall, while others have learned to achieve multiple orgasms.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dunn&quot;/&gt; 

A number of studies have pointed to the hormone [[prolactin]] as the likely cause of the male refractory period. Because of this, there is currently an experimental interest in drugs which inhibit prolactin, such as [[cabergoline]] (also known as Cabeser, or Dostinex). Anecdotal reports on cabergoline suggest it may be able to eliminate the refractory period altogether, allowing men to experience multiple ejaculatory orgasms in rapid succession. At least one scientific study supports these claims,&lt;ref name=&quot;Prolactin&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Krüger TH, Haake P, Haverkamp J, ''et al.'' |title=Effects of acute prolactin manipulation on sexual drive and function in males |journal=The Journal of Endocrinology |volume=179 |issue=3 |pages=357–65 |year=2003 |month=December |pmid=14656205 |doi=10.1677/joe.0.1790357}}&lt;/ref&gt; although cabergoline is a hormone-altering drug and has many potential side effects. It has not been approved for treating sexual dysfunction.&lt;ref name=&quot;Prolactin&quot;/&gt; Another possible reason for the lack or absence of a refractory period in men may be an increased infusion of the hormone [[oxytocin]]. It is believed that the amount by which oxytocin is increased may affect the length of each refractory period. A scientific study to successfully document natural, fully ejaculatory, multiple orgasms in an adult man was conducted at [[Rutgers University]] in 1995. During the study, six fully ejaculatory orgasms were experienced in 36 minutes, with no apparent refractory period.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal| first=B. | last=Whipple | coauthors=B. Myers and B. Komisaruk | year=1998 | title=Male Multiple Ejaculatory Orgasms: A Case Study | journal=[[Journal of Sex Education and Therapy]] | volume=23 | issue=2 | pages=157–62}}&lt;/ref&gt; It can also be said that in some cases, the refractory period can be reduced or even eliminated through the course of puberty and on into adulthood. Later, P. Haake ''et al.'' observed a single male individual producing multiple orgasms without elevated prolactin response.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Haake P, Exton MS, Haverkamp J, ''et al.'' |title=Absence of orgasm-induced prolactin secretion in a healthy multi-orgasmic male subject |journal=International Journal of Impotence Research |volume=14 |issue=2 |pages=133–5 |year=2002 |month=April |pmid=11979330 |doi=10.1038/sj.ijir.3900823}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In recent years, a number of books have described various techniques to achieve multiple orgasms. Most multi-orgasmic men (and their partners) report that refraining from ejaculation results in a far more energetic post-orgasm state.&lt;ref&gt;Havelock Ellis ''Studies in the Psychology of Sex, vol. vi, p. 552, F. A. Davis Co., 1910, [[Amazon Kindle|Kindle Edition]] 2008 ISBN B0016PEMOS''&lt;/ref&gt; One technique for refraining from ejaculation is to put pressure on the [[perineum]], about halfway between the [[scrotum]] and the anus, just before ejaculating to prevent ejaculation. This can, however, lead to [[retrograde ejaculation]], i.e., redirecting semen into the [[urinary bladder]] rather than through the [[urethra]] to the outside. It may also cause long term damage due to the pressure put on the nerves and blood vessels in the perineum, akin to that reported by some males who ride bicycles with narrow seats for extended periods.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cdc.gov/niosh/updates/upd-06-30-04-2.html | title=NIOSH Update:Bicycle Saddles Without Protruding Noses Reduce Pressure Associated With Erectile Dysfunction Measure | accessdate=2 April 2011 |date=30 June 2004 | last=Blosser | first=Fred  | quote=In a 2002 NIOSH report, perineal pressure was associated with genital numbness in a group of bicycle-patrol police officers, and with a decrease in the amount of time that the officers had erections during sleep..}}&lt;/ref&gt; Men who have had prostate or bladder surgery, for whatever reason, may also experience dry orgasms because of retrograde ejaculation.

Other techniques are analogous to reports by multi-orgasmic women indicating that they must relax and &quot;let go&quot; to experience multiple orgasms. These techniques involve mental and physical controls over pre-ejaculatory vasocongestion and emissions, rather than ejaculatory contractions or forced retention as above. Anecdotally, successful implementation of these techniques can result in continuous or multiple &quot;full-body&quot; orgasms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sexuality.org/l/sex/cmo.html | title=Continuous Male Orgasms|quote=Learn to enhance and maintain indefinitely the physiological events and associated pleasure of an absolutely imminent ejaculatory orgasm.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===In females===
====Clitoral and vaginal variabilities==== 
Discussions of the female orgasm are complicated by orgasms in women typically being divided into two categories: [[Clitoris|clitoral]] orgasm and [[vagina]]l (or [[G-Spot]]) orgasm.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mah&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Sex and Society&quot;&gt;{{cite book|authors=[[Marshall Cavendish|Marshall Cavendish Corporation]]|title=Sex and Society, Volume 2|isbn =0761479074, 9780761479079|publisher=Marshall Cavendish Corporation|year=2009|page=590|accessdate=17 August 2012|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=YtsxeWE7VD0C&amp;pg=PA590&amp;lpg=PA590&amp;dq=&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=YYqnMyUDID&amp;sig=_rwzCljz5MBKMvG_0MsJILX7-HA&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=sn0uUO-JOZDy2gWw6IHwAw&amp;ved=0CF0Q6AEwCDgy#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ladas, [[Beverly Whipple|Whipple]] and Perry proposed three categories: the tenting type (derived from clitoral stimulation), the A-frame type (derived G-Spot stimulation), and the blended type (derived from clitoral and G-Spot stimulation); Whipple and Komisaruk later proposed [[cervix]] stimulation as inducing a fourth type,&lt;ref name=&quot;Bolin &amp; Whelehan&quot;&gt;{{cite book|authors=Anne Bolin, Patricia Whelehan|title=Human Sexuality: Biological, Psychological, and Cultural Perspectives|isbn = 0-7890-2672-4, 9780789026729|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|year=2009|pages=624 pages|accessdate=11 February 2012|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=lDQoIhOwwdYC&amp;pg=PA276&amp;dq=Ladas,+Whipple,+and+Perry+three+types+of+orgasm&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=7QY3T5GBLcTC2wWVlI2YDg&amp;ved=0CDsQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Ladas%2C%20Whipple%2C%20and%20Perry%20three%20types%20of%20orgasm&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; though orgasms by means other than clitoral or vaginal/G-Spot stimulation are less prevalent in scientific literature&lt;ref name=&quot;Mah&quot;/&gt; and most scientists contend that no distinction should be made between &quot;types&quot; of female orgasm.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sex and Society&quot;/&gt; This distinction began with [[Sigmund Freud]], who postulated the concept of &quot;vaginal orgasm&quot; as separate from clitoral orgasm.&lt;!--Rules are &quot;promulgated&quot;; theories are &quot;postulated&quot;--&gt; In 1905, Freud stated that clitoral orgasms are purely an adolescent phenomenon and that upon reaching puberty, the proper response of mature women is a change-over to vaginal orgasms, meaning orgasms without any clitoral stimulation. While Freud provided no evidence for this basic assumption, the consequences of this theory were considerable. Many women felt inadequate when they could not achieve orgasm via vaginal intercourse alone, involving little or no clitoral stimulation, as Freud's theory made penile-vaginal intercourse the central component to women's sexual satisfaction.&lt;ref name=&quot;Irvine&quot;&gt;{{cite book|authors=Janice M. Irvine|title=Disorders of desire: sexuality and gender in modern American sexology|isbn =1-59213-151-4, 9781592131518|publisher=Temple University Press|year=2005|pages=304 pages|accessdate=3 January 2012|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=uIJXT7ZCTCsC&amp;pg=PA37&amp;dq=Kinsey+criticized+Freud&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=jFADT5u0KKWo2wXY9pSeAg&amp;ved=0CD4Q6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=Kinsey%20criticized%20Freud&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Difference&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Difference between clitoral and vaginal orgasm|publisher=[[Go Ask Alice!]]|date=23 December 1994 (Last Updated/Reviewed on 28 March 2008)|accessdate=21 April 2010|url=http://goaskalice.columbia.edu/difference-between-clitoral-and-vaginal-orgasm}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Koedt&quot;&gt;{{cite news|first=Anne|last=Koedt|title=The Myth of the Vaginal Orgasm|publisher=[[Chicago Women's Liberation Union]] (CWLU)|year=1970|accessdate=12 December 2011|url=http://www.uic.edu/orgs/cwluherstory/CWLUArchive/vaginalmyth.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Gould&quot;&gt;{{cite book | author= [[Stephen Jay Gould]]| title = The Structure of Evolutionary Theory | publisher =[[Harvard University Press]]|year = 2002|pages=1262-1263|accessdate =27 August 2012| isbn = 0674006135, 9780674006133 |url = http://books.google.com/books?id=nhIl7e61WOUC&amp;pg=PA767&amp;lpg=PA767&amp;dq=The+female+counterpart,+however,+has+evoked+much+argument,+and+imposed+substantial+grief+upon+millions+of+women+during+the+20th+century:+why+do+most+female+orgasms+emanate+from+a+clitoral,+rather+than+vaginal+%28or+some+other%29,+site.&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=ZCoB-8KWvC&amp;sig=YILNTkcbgiG2v5kpJ-Lzb1FAK0k&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=dKo7UJqOOPGA2QXOi4HIBA&amp;ved=0CC0Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=The%20female%20counterpart%2C%20however%2C%20has%20evoked%20much%20argument%2C%20and%20imposed%20substantial%20grief%20upon%20millions%20of%20women%20during%20the%2020th%20century%3A%20why%20do%20most%20female%20orgasms%20emanate%20from%20a%20clitoral%2C%20rather%20than%20vaginal%20%28or%20some%20other%29%2C%20site.%20The%20male%20biologists%20who%20fretted%20over%20this%20question%20simply%20assumed%20that%20a%20deeply%20vaginal%20site.&amp;f=false}}
&lt;/ref&gt; 

The first major national surveys of sexual behavior were the [[Kinsey Reports]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Andersen&quot;/&gt; [[Alfred Kinsey]] was the first researcher to harshly criticize Freud's ideas about female sexuality and orgasm when, through his interviews with thousands of women,&lt;ref name=&quot;Andersen&quot;/&gt; Kinsey found that most women could not have vaginal orgasms.&lt;ref name=&quot;Irvine&quot;/&gt; He &quot;criticized Freud and other theorists for projecting male constructs of sexuality onto women&quot; and &quot;viewed the clitoris as the main center of sexual response&quot; and the vagina as &quot;relatively unimportant&quot; for sexual satisfaction, relaying that &quot;few women inserted fingers or objects into their vaginas when they masturbated&quot;. He &quot;concluded that satisfaction from penile penetration [is] mainly psychological or perhaps the result of referred sensation&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Irvine&quot;/&gt; [[Masters and Johnson]]'s research into the female [[sexual response cycle]] generally supported Kinsey's findings about the female orgasm,&lt;ref name=&quot;Irvine&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Archer, Lloyd&quot;&gt;{{cite book | authors= John Archer, Barbara Lloyd | title = Sex and Gender | publisher =[[Cambridge University Press]]|year = 2002|pages=85-88| accessdate =25 August 2012| isbn = 0521635330, 9780521635332 |url = http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=BJ1V9r_J0sUC&amp;pg=PA85&amp;lpg=PA85&amp;dq=Masters+and+Johnson+presented+a+four-stage+description+of+the+sexual+response+that+emphasised+similarities+rather+than+differences+between+men+and+women.&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=O-DoMmyk5R&amp;sig=OJ9OFeOvIIqVd_d8ODSlKNK8-gU&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=sGc5UNToJeiM2gWCzIHwCQ&amp;ved=0CDEQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=Masters%20and%20Johnson%20presented%20a%20four-stage%20description%20of%20the%20sexual%20response%20that%20emphasised%20similarities%20rather%20than%20differences%20between%20men%20and%20women.&amp;f=false}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Masters and Johnson&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Federation of Feminist Women’s Health Centers |year=1991 |title=A New View of a Woman’s Body |publisher= Feminist Heath Press |pages=46 |isbn=0-929945-0-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; which inspired feminists such as [[Anne Koedt]] to speak about the &quot;false distinction&quot; made between clitoral and vaginal orgasms and women's biology not being properly analyzed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Koedt&quot;/&gt;

Research, including research by [[Shere Hite]], has consistently demonstrated that 70–80% of women achieve orgasm only through direct clitoral stimulation,&lt;ref name=&quot;Hite&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Hite|first=Shere|author=[[Shere Hite]]|title=The Hite Report: A Nationwide Study of Female Sexuality |publisher=[[Seven Stories Press]]|year=2003|location=New York, NY|pages=512 pages|isbn=1-58322-569-2, 9781583225691|accessdate=2 March 2012|url=http://books.google.com/?id=s3OZaVn2wfkC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;dq=The%20Hite%20Report%3A%20a%20Nationwide%20Study%20of%20Female%20Sexuality&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Flaherty&quot;&gt;&quot;The amount of time of sexual arousal needed to reach orgasm is variable – and usually much longer – in women than in men; thus, only 20–30% of women attain a coital climax. b. Many women (70–80%) require manual clitoral stimulation...&quot; {{cite book|authors=Joseph A. Flaherty, John Marcell Davis, Philip G. Janicak|title=Psychiatry: Diagnosis &amp; therapy. A Lange clinical manual|isbn = 0-8385-1267-4, 9780838512678|publisher=Appleton &amp; Lange (Original from Northwestern University)|year=1993, Digitized 29 October 2010|pages=544 pages|accessdate=5 January 2012|url=https://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;noj=1&amp;biw=1024&amp;bih=629&amp;tbm=bks&amp;q=The+amount+of+time+of+sexual+arousal+needed+to+reach+orgasm+is+variable+%E2%80%94+and+usually+much+longer+%E2%80%94+in+women+than+in+men%3B+thus%2C+only+20-30%25+of+women+attain+a+coital+climax.+b.+Many+women+%2870-80%25%29+require+manual+clitoral+stimulation.&amp;btnG=Search&amp;oq=The+amount+of+time+of+sexual+arousal+needed+to+reach+orgasm+is+variable+%E2%80%94+and+usually+much+longer+%E2%80%94+in+women+than+in+men%3B+thus%2C+only+20-30%25+of+women+attain+a+coital+climax.+b.+Many+women+%2870-80%25%29+require+manual+clitoral+stimulation.&amp;aq=f&amp;aqi=&amp;aql=&amp;gs_sm=s&amp;gs_upl=2326483l2326991l0l2328690l1l1l0l0l0l0l0l0ll0l0}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kenneth Mah&quot;&gt;
{{cite journal | first = Kenneth | last = Mah | first2 = Yitzchak M | last2 = Binik | title = The nature of human orgasm: a critical review of major trends | journal = [[Clinical Psychology Review]] | volume = 21 | issue = 6 | pages = 823–856 | month = 7 January | year = 2001, available online on 17 July 2001 | pmid = | doi = 10.1016/S0272-7358(00)00069-6 | url = http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0272735800000696 | quote=Women rated clitoral stimulation as at least somewhat more important than vaginal stimulation in achieving orgasm; only about 20% indicated that they did not require additional clitoral stimulation during intercourse.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lloyd&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=[[Elisabeth Lloyd|Elisabeth Anne Lloyd]]|title=The Case of the Female Orgasm: Bias In the Science of Evolution|isbn = 0-674-01706-4, 9780674017061|publisher=Harvard University Press|year=2005|pages=311 pages|accessdate=5 January 2012|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=6GFNvA6TvlwC&amp;pg=PA53&amp;dq=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=Jg0GT_3QNoqQ2QWL-KSBCg&amp;ved=0CEMQ6AEwADgo#v=onepage&amp;q=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kammerer-Doak&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | first = Dorothy | last = Kammerer-Doak | first2 = Rebecca G. | last2 = Rogers | title = Female Sexual Function and Dysfunction | journal = Obstetrics and Gynecology Clinics of North America | volume = 35 | issue = 2 | pages = 169–183 | month = June | year = 2008, available online on 16 May 2008 | pmid = 18486835 | doi = 10.1016/j.ogc.2008.03.006 | url = http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0889854508000235 | quote=Most women report the inability to achieve orgasm with vaginal intercourse and require direct clitoral stimulation ... About 20% have coital climaxes...}}
&lt;/ref&gt; though indirect clitoral stimulation may also be sufficient.&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Connell&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Buisson and Foldès 2008&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |display-authors=2 |last=Buisson|first=Odile|last2=Foldès  |first2=Pierre|title=Sonography of the Clitoris|journal=[[The Journal of Sexual Medicine]]|volume=5 |issue=2 |pages=413–417|year=2008 |pmid= |doi=10.1111/j.1743-6109.2007.00699.x}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Buisson and Foldès 2009&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |display-authors=2 |last=Buisson|first=Odile|last2=Foldès  |first2=Pierre|title=The clitoral complex: a dynamic sonographic study.|journal=[[The Journal of Sexual Medicine]]|volume= 6|issue= 5|pages= 1223–31|year=2009 |pmid=19453931|doi |doi=10.1111/j.1743-6109.2009.01231.x}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[Mayo Clinic]] stated, &quot;Orgasms vary in intensity, and women vary in the frequency of their orgasms and the amount of stimulation necessary to trigger an orgasm.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Anorgasmia&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/anorgasmia/DS01051 |title=Mayo Clinic; Womans Health|publisher=[[Mayo Clinic]]|accessdate=23 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Clitoral orgasms are easier to achieve because the [[clitoral glans|glans of the clitoris]], or clitoris as a whole, has more than 8,000 sensory [[nerve ending]]s, as much as or more than the human penis, as well as more than any other part of the human body.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cornforth&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Harvey | first = Elizabeth D. | date = Winter, 2002 | title = Anatomies of Rapture: Clitoral Politics/Medical Blazons | journal = [[Signs (journal)|Signs]] | volume = 27 | issue = 2 | pages = 315–346 | pmid = | doi = 10.1086/495689 | ref = {{sfnRef|Harvey|2002}}| jstor = 3175784 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Carroll&quot;&gt;
{{cite book | title =Sexuality Now: Embracing Diversity | publisher = [[Cengage Learning]] | year = 2009 | page = 629 | accessdate =23 June 2012 | url = http://books.google.com/?id=5f8mQx7ULs4C&amp;pg=PA118&amp;lpg=PA118&amp;dq=The+glans+clitoris#v=onepage&amp;q=The%20glans%20clitoris|isbn =978-0-495-60274-3 | first = Janell L. | last = Carroll}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Can't feel&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=I'm a woman who cannot feel pleasurable sensations during intercourse|publisher=[[Go Ask Alice!]]|date=8 October 2004 (Last Updated/Reviewed on 17 October 2008)|accessdate=19 November 2011|url=http://goaskalice.columbia.edu/im-woman-who-cannot-feel-pleasurable-sensations-during-intercourse}}&lt;/ref&gt; As the clitoris is [[Homology (biology)|homologous]] to the penis, it is the equivalent in its capacity to receive sexual stimulation,&lt;ref name=&quot;Merz&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first=Eberhard |last=Merz |first2=F. |last2=Bahlmann |title=Ultrasound in Obstetrics and Gynecology, Volume 1 |publisher=[[Thieme Medical Publishers]] |year=2004 |isbn=978-1-58890-147-7 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=eeLAOyt71w4C&amp;pg=PA129&amp;dq=Embryonic+development+of+the+clitoris#v=onepage&amp;q=Embryonic%20development%20of%20the%20clitoris&amp;f=false | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Schünke&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first=Michael |last=Schünke |first2=Erik |last2=Schulte |first3=Lawrence M. |last3=Ross |first4=Edward D. |last4=Lamperti |first5=Udo |last5=Schumacher |title=Thieme Atlas of Anatomy: General Anatomy and Musculoskeletal System, Volume 1 |publisher=[[Thieme Medical Publishers]] |year=2006 |isbn=978-3-13-142081-7 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=NK9TgTaGt6UC&amp;pg=PA192&amp;dq=Embryonic+development+of+the+clitoris#v=onepage&amp;q=Embryonic%20development%20of%20the%20clitoris&amp;f=false | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Clitoris&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title='I Want a Better Orgasm!'|work=[[WebMD]]|accessdate=18 August 2011|url=http://web.archive.org/web/20090113132443/http://www.webmd.com/sex/want-better-orgasms}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Francoeur&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Francoeur |first=Robert T. |year=2000 |title=The Complete Dictionary of Sexology |publisher=The Continuum Publishing Company |page=180 |isbn=0-8264-0672-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; It surrounds the vagina somewhat like a [[horseshoe]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Cornforth&quot;/&gt; with &quot;legs&quot; that extend along the vaginal lips back to the anus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Doin' the butt&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Doin' the butt – objects in anus?|publisher=[[Go Ask Alice!]]|date=7 October 1994 (Last Updated/Reviewed on 26 March 2010)|accessdate=22 April 2010|url=http://goaskalice.columbia.edu/doin-butt-objects-anus}}&lt;/ref&gt; While the G-Spot can produce an orgasm,&lt;ref name=&quot;Cornforth&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;G-Spot&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=The G-spot|publisher=health.discovery.com|accessdate=21 December 2011|url=http://health.discovery.com/centers/sex/sexpedia/gspot.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CNNreal&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.cnn.com/2010/HEALTH/01/05/g.spot.sex.women/index.html |title=Finding the G-spot: Is it real?|publisher=[[CNN]].com|date=January, 05, 2010|accessdate=7 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Aquila&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Gravina GL, Brandetti F, Martini P, ''et al.'' |title=Measurement of the Thickness of the Urethrovaginal Space in Women with or without Vaginal Orgasm |journal=J Sex Med |volume= 5|issue=  3|pages=610–8|year=2008 |pmid=18221286 |doi=10.1111/j.1743-6109.2007.00739.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[urethral sponge]], an area in which the G-Spot may be found, runs along the &quot;roof&quot; of the vagina and can create pleasurable sensations when stimulated, the vagina has insufficient capability of producing pleasure and orgasm in women.&lt;ref name=&quot;Weiten&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cornforth&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Irvine&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Can't feel&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kilchevsky&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |authors=Kilchevsky A, Vardi Y, Lowenstein L, Gruenwald I.|title=Is the Female G-Spot Truly a Distinct Anatomic Entity?|journal=[[The Journal of Sexual Medicine]]|volume= 2011|year=2012 |month= January |pmid=22240236|doi=10.1111/j.1743-6109.2011.02623.x|laysummary=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/01/19/g-spot-does-not-exist_n_1215822.html G-Spot Does Not Exist, 'Without A Doubt,' Say Researchers -|laysource=''[[Huffington Post]]''|laydate=19 January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Go Ask Alice!]] reports that although vaginal intercourse may promote a satisfying feeling of fullness or closeness with a sexual partner,&lt;ref name=&quot;No stimulation &quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=No stimulation from intercourse|publisher=[[Go Ask Alice!]]|date=30 September 1994 (Last Updated / Reviewed on: 13 May 2011)|accessdate=27 November 2011|url=http://goaskalice.columbia.edu/no-stimulation-intercourse}}&lt;/ref&gt; the vaginal walls &quot;contain relatively few nerve endings, making intense sexual stimulation, pleasure, and orgasm from vaginal-only penetration unlikely&quot; and that &quot;it's generally only the lower third of the vagina that has enough nerve endings to feel any stimulation at all from a penis, finger, toy, or other penetrative object&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Can't feel&quot;/&gt; Sex educator Rebecca Chalker states that only one part of the clitoris, the urethral sponge, is in contact with the penis, fingers, or a [[dildo]] in the vagina.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cornforth&quot;/&gt; Hite and Chalker note that the tip of the clitoris and the inner lips, which are also very sensitive, are not receiving direct stimulation during intercourse.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cornforth&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hite&quot;/&gt; Because of this, some couples may engage in the [[coital alignment technique]] to maximize clitoral stimulation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eichel&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |authors=Eichel EW, Eichel JD, Kule S.|title=The technique of coital alignment and its relation to female orgasmic response and simultaneous orgasm|journal=[[Journal of Sex &amp; Marital Therapy]] |volume= '''14'''(2)|pages=129–141|year=1988 |pmid=3204637|laysummary= |laysource= |laydate= |doi=10.1080/00926238808403913}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hurlbert&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |authors= Hurlbert DF, Apt C|title=The coital alignment technique and directed masturbation: a comparative study on female orgasm|journal=[[Journal of Sex &amp; Marital Therapy]] |volume= '''21'''(1)|pages=21–29|year=1995 |pmid=7608994|laysummary= |laysource= |laydate= |doi=10.1080/00926239508405968}}&lt;/ref&gt; For some women, the clitoris is very sensitive after climax, making additional stimulation initially painful.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rathus&quot;&gt;{{Citation | last1 = Rathus | first1 = Spencer A. | last2 = Nevid | first2 = Jeffrey S. | last3 = Fichner-Rathus | first3 = Lois | last4 = Herold | first4 = Edward S. | last5 = McKenzie | first5 = Sue Wicks | title = Human sexuality in a world of diversity | edition = Second | year = 2005 | publication-place = New Jersey, USA | publisher = Pearson Education | isbn = 1-205-46013-5{{Please check ISBN|reason=Check digit (5) does not correspond to calculated 6.}}|accessdate =20 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Accounts that the vagina is capable of producing orgasms continue to be subject to debate because in addition to the vagina's low concentration of nerve endings, the G-Spot's location is inconsistent and appears to be nonexistent in some women, and may be an extension of another structure (such as the [[Skene's gland]] or the clitoris, which is a part of the Skene's gland).&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Connell&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;G-Spot&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CNNreal&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kilchevsky&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hines&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Hines T |year=2001 |month=August |title=The G-Spot: A modern gynecologic myth |journal=Am J Obstet Gynecol |volume=185 |issue=2 |pages=359–62 | doi=10.1067/mob.2001.115995|pmid=11518892}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Reports in the public media would lead one to believe the G-Spot is a well-characterized entity capable of providing extreme sexual stimulation, yet this is far from the truth,&quot; stated scholars Kilchevsky, Vardi, Lowenstein and Gruenwald in a 2012 ''[[Journal of Sexual Medicine]]'' article.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kilchevsky&quot;/&gt; Masters and Johnson were the first to determine that the clitoral structures surround and extend along and within the labia. In addition to observing that the majority of their female subjects could only have clitoral orgasms, they found that both clitoral and vaginal orgasms had the same stages of physical response. On this basis, they argued that clitoral stimulation is the source of both kinds of orgasms.&lt;ref name=&quot;Archer, Lloyd&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Masters and Johnson&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cairney&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Cairney|first=Richard|title=Exploring female sexuality|publisher=ExpressNews|date=21 October 2002|accessdate=21 December 2011|url=http://www.expressnews.ualberta.ca/article.cfm?id=3201|archivedate=29 June 2011|archiveurl=http://liveweb.archive.org/http://www.archives.expressnews.ualberta.ca/article/2002/10/3201.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; Likewise, Australian [[Urology|urologist]] Helen O'Connell's discoveries about the size of the clitoris, published in 2005, suggest that clitoral tissue extends into the anterior wall of the vagina, which may invalidate the hypothesis that clitoral and vaginal orgasms are of two different origins.&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Connell&quot;/&gt; While some studies, using [[ultrasound]], have found physiological evidence of the G-Spot in women who report having orgasms during intercourse,&lt;ref name=&quot;CNNreal&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Aquila&quot;/&gt; O'Connell asserts that the clitoris's interconnected relationship with the vagina is the physiological explanation for the conjectured G-Spot and experience of vaginal orgasms, taking into account the stimulation of the internal parts of the clitoris during vaginal penetration.&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Connell&quot;/&gt; Having used [[Magnetic resonance imaging|MRI]] technology which enabled her to note a direct relationship between the legs or roots of the clitoris and the erectile tissue of the &quot;clitoral bulbs&quot; and corpora, and the distal urethra and vagina, O'Connell stated, &quot;The vaginal wall is, in fact, the clitoris. If you lift the skin off the vagina on the side walls, you get the bulbs of the clitoris—triangular, crescental masses of erectile tissue.&quot; O'Connell, who had made the claims in 1998, and her team were already aware that the clitoris is more than just its glans – the &quot;little hill&quot;. They reasoned that it is possible that some women have more extensive clitoral tissues and nerves than others, and therefore whereas many women can only achieve orgasm by direct stimulation of the external parts of the clitoris, for others the stimulation of the more generalized tissues of the clitoris via intercourse may be sufficient.&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Connell&quot;/&gt; 

French researchers Odile Buisson and Pierre Foldès reported similar findings to that of O'Connell's. In 2008, they published the first complete 3D [[Medical ultrasonography|sonography]] of the stimulated clitoris, and republished it in 2009 with new research, demonstrating that the erectile tissue of the clitoris engorges and surrounds the vagina, arguing that women may be able to achieve vaginal orgasm via stimulation of the G-Spot because the highly innervated clitoris is pulled closely to the anterior wall of the vagina when the woman is sexually aroused and during vaginal penetration. They assert that since the front wall of the vagina is inextricably linked with the internal parts of the clitoris, stimulating the vagina without activating the clitoris may be next to impossible.&lt;ref name=&quot;Buisson and Foldès 2008&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Buisson and Foldès 2009&quot;/&gt; In their 2009 published study, the &quot;coronal planes during perineal contraction and finger penetration demonstrated a close relationship between the root of the clitoris and the anterior vaginal wall&quot;. Buisson and Foldès suggested &quot;that the special sensitivity of the lower anterior vaginal wall could be explained by pressure and movement of clitoris's root during a vaginal penetration and subsequent perineal contraction&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Buisson and Foldès 2009&quot;/&gt;

O'Connell's findings were criticized by Vincenzo Puppo, who states that O'Connell and other researchers use imprecise terminological and anatomical descriptions of the clitoris. &quot;Clitoral bulbs is an incorrect term from an embryological and anatomical viewpoint, in fact the bulbs do not develop from the phallus, and they do not belong to the clitoris: 'clitoral bulbs' is not a term used in human anatomy, the correct term is the vestibular bulbs,&quot; stated Puppo, arguing that the &quot;anterior vaginal wall is separated from the posterior urethral wall by the urethrovaginal septum (its thickness is 10–12 mm)&quot; and that the &quot;inner clitoris&quot; does not exist. &quot;The female perineal urethra, which is located in front of the anterior vaginal wall, is about one centimeter in length and the G-Spot is located in the pelvic wall of the urethra, 2–3 cm into the vagina,&quot; Puppo stated. &quot;The male penis cannot come in contact with the venous plexus of [[Georg Ludwig Kobelt|Kobelt]] (situated until the angle of the clitoris) or with the roots of the clitoris (which do not have sensory receptors or erogenous sensitivity) during vaginal intercourse.&quot; Puppo did, however, dismiss the orgasmic definition of the G-Spot that emerged after [[Ernst Gräfenberg]], stating that &quot;there is no anatomical evidence of the vaginal orgasm which was invented by Freud in 1905, without any scientific basis&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Puppo&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Vincenzo Puppo |title=Anatomy of the Clitoris: Revision and Clarifications about the Anatomical Terms for the Clitoris Proposed (without Scientific Bases) by Helen O'Connell, Emmanuele Jannini, and Odile Buisson.|journal=ISRN Obstetrics and Gynecology |volume= 2011|issue=ID 261464 |pages=5 |year=2011 |month= September|pmid=21941661|laysummary=  |laysource= |laydate= |doi=10.5402/2011/261464 |pmc=3175415}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In contrast to Puppo's belief that there is no anatomical relationship between the vagina and clitoris, the majority of researchers maintain that vaginal orgasms are the result of clitoral stimulation, reaffirming that clitoral tissue extends even in the area most commonly reported to be the G-Spot.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sex and Society&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kilchevsky&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Can't find it&quot;&gt;{{cite news|first=Brian|last=Alexander|url=http://todayhealth.today.msnbc.msn.com/_news/2012/01/18/10177335-does-the-g-spot-really-exist-scientist-cant-find-it|title=Does the G-spot really exist? Scientists can't find it|publisher=[[MSNBC]].com|date=18 January 2012|accessdate=2 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;My view is that the G-Spot is really just the extension of the clitoris on the inside of the vagina, analogous to the base of the male penis,&quot; said Kilchevsky. Because humans all start out as female in the womb and therefore the penis is essentially an enlarged clitoris, changed by male hormones, Kilchevsky believes that there is no evolutionary reason why females would have two separate structures capable of producing orgasms and blames the porn industry and &quot;G-Spot promoters&quot; for &quot;encouraging the myth&quot; of a distinct G-Spot.&lt;ref name=&quot;Can't find it&quot;/&gt; Arguments that vaginal orgasms help encourage sexual intercourse in order to facilitate reproduction are challenged by the fact that vaginal orgasms are significantly difficult to achieve,&lt;ref name=&quot;Lloyd&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kilchevsky&quot;/&gt; a predicament that is believed to be the result of nature easing the process of child bearing by drastically reducing the number of vaginal nerve endings.&lt;ref name=&quot;Weiten&quot;/&gt; However, one study, published 2011, which was the first to map the female genitals onto the sensory portion of the brain,&lt;ref name=&quot;Komisaruk 2&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Komisaruk, B. R., Wise, N., Frangos, E., Liu, W.-C., Allen, K. and Brody, S. |title=Women's Clitoris, Vagina, and Cervix Mapped on the Sensory Cortex: fMRI Evidence |journal=[[The Journal of Sexual Medicine]] |year=2011|doi=10.1111/j.1743-6109.2011.02388.x|laysummary= http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2011/08/05/scitech/main20088836.shtml Surprise finding in response to nipple stimulation |laysource=[[CBS|CBSnews.com]]|laydate=5 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; keeps &quot;the possibility of a discrete G-Spot viable&quot;. When a [[Rutgers University]] research team asked several women to stimulate themselves in a [[Functional magnetic resonance imaging|functional magnetic resonance]] (fMRI) machine, brain scans showed stimulating the clitoris, vagina and cervix lit up distinct areas of the women's sensory cortex,&lt;ref name=&quot;Komisaruk 2&quot;/&gt; which means the brain registered distinct feelings between stimulating the clitoris, the cervix and the vaginal wall – where the G-Spot is reported to be. &quot;I think that the bulk of the evidence shows that the G-Spot is not a particular thing,&quot; stated Komisaruk, head of the research findings. &quot;It's not like saying, 'What is the thyroid gland?' The G-Spot is more of a thing like New York City is a thing. It's a region, it's a convergence of many different structures.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kilchevsky&quot;/&gt;

====Other factors and views====

In many cases, women, or less often men,&lt;ref name=&quot;Dunn&quot;/&gt; either do not have a [[refractory period (sex)|refractory period]] or have a significantly short one and thus can experience an additional orgasm, or multiple orgasms, soon after the first.&lt;ref name=soc&gt;{{Citation| title = The Sexual Response Cycle| publisher = [[University of California, Santa Barbara]]  | url = http://www.soc.ucsb.edu/sexinfo/article/the-sexual-response-cycle|accessdate =6 August 2012|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20110725051823/http://www.soc.ucsb.edu/sexinfo/article/the-sexual-response-cycle|archivedate=25 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the first orgasm, subsequent climaxes may be stronger or more pleasurable as the stimulation accumulates.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rathus&quot;/&gt;

Regular difficulty reaching orgasm after ample sexual stimulation, known as [[anorgasmia]], is significantly more common in women than in men ([[#Dysfunction and satisfaction|see below]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Anorgasmia&quot;/&gt; In addition to sexual dysfunction being a cause for women's inability to reach orgasm, or the amount of time for sexual arousal needed to reach orgasm being variable and longer in women than in men, other factors include a lack of communication between sexual partners about what is needed for the woman to reach orgasm, feelings of sexual inadequacy in either partners, a focus on only penetration (vaginal or otherwise), and men generalizing women's trigger for orgasm based on their own sexual experiences with other women.&lt;ref name=&quot;Weiten&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Flaherty&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wallen K, Lloyd EA&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |authors=Wallen K, Lloyd EA.|title=Female sexual arousal: genital anatomy and orgasm in intercourse.|journal=Hormones and Behavior|year=2011 |month= May |pmid=21195073|laysummary=  |laysource= |laydate= |doi=10.1016/j.yhbeh.2010.12.004 |volume=59 |issue=5 |pages=780–92}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Big O&quot;&gt;Dr. [[Gail Saltz]] and Dr. [[Drew Pinsky]] interview. {{cite web|title=Dissatisfied, ladies? Tips to reach the Big O.|publisher=[[MSNBC]]|date=November, 02, 2007|accessdate=10 April 2011|url=http://today.msnbc.msn.com/id/21597671}}&lt;/ref&gt; Masters and Johnson found that men took about 4 minutes to reach orgasm with their partners. Women took about 10–20 minutes to reach orgasm with their partners, but 4 minutes to reach orgasm when they masturbated.&lt;ref name=&quot;Weiten&quot;/&gt; Scholars Weiten, Dunn and Hammer reasoned, &quot;Unfortunately, many couples are locked into the idea that orgasms should be achieved only through intercourse [penetrative vaginal sex]. Even the word ''[[foreplay]]'' suggests that any other form of sexual stimulation is merely preparation for the 'main event.'... ...Because women reach orgasm through intercourse less consistently than men, they are more likely than men to have faked an orgasm.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Weiten&quot;/&gt; In the first large-scale empirical study worldwide to link specific practices with orgasm, reported in ''[[The Journal of Sex Research]]'' in 2006, demographic and sexual history variables were comparatively weakly associated with orgasm. Data was analyzed from the Australian Study of Health and Relationships, a national telephone survey of sexual behavior and attitudes and sexual health knowledge carried out in 2001–2002, with a representative sample of 19,307 Australians aged 16 to 59. Practices included &quot;vaginal intercourse alone (12%), vaginal + manual stimulation of the man's and/or woman's genitals (49%), and vaginal intercourse + manual + oral (32%). Encounters may also have included other practices. Men had an orgasm in 95% of encounters and women in 69%. Generally, the more practices engaged in, the higher a woman's chance of having an orgasm. Women were more likely to reach orgasm in encounters including [[cunnilingus]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Richters J&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |authors=Richters J, Visser R, Rissel C, Smith A.|title=Sexual practices at last heterosexual encounter and occurrence of orgasm in a national survey.|journal=[[The Journal of Sex Research]]|year=2006 |month=August|pmid=17599244|laysummary=  |laysource= |laydate= |doi=10.1080/00224490609552320 |volume=43 |issue=3 |pages=217–26}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

There is some research suggesting that women's vaginal orgasm consistency is associated with being told in childhood or adolescence that the vagina is the important zone for inducing female orgasm. Other factors include how well women focus mentally on vaginal sensations during penile-vaginal intercourse, the greater duration of intercourse, and preference for above-average penis length.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brody, Weiss&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |authors=Brody S, Weiss P.|title=Vaginal orgasm is associated with vaginal (not clitoral) sex education, focusing mental attention on vaginal sensations, intercourse duration, and a preference for a longer penis.|journal=[[The Journal of Sexual Medicine]]|pages=2774–81 |year=2010 |month= August |pmid=19732304|laysummary=  |laysource= |laydate= |doi=10.1111/j.1743-6109.2009.01469.x |volume=7 |issue=8}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other studies suggest that women exposed to lower levels of prenatal [[androgen]]s are more likely to experience orgasm during sexual intercourse,&lt;ref name=&quot;Wallen K, Lloyd EA&quot;/&gt; or that vaginal orgasm is more prevalent among women with a prominent [[tubercle of the upper lip]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Brody, Costa&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |authors=Brody S, Costa RM.|title=Vaginal orgasm is more prevalent among women with a prominent tubercle of the upper lip.|journal=[[The Journal of Sexual Medicine]]|year=2011 |month= June |pmid=21676178|laysummary=  |laysource= |laydate= |doi=10.1111/j.1743-6109.2011.02331.x |volume=8 |issue=10 |pages=2793–9}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;A prominent and sharply raised lip tubercle has been associated with greater odds (odds ratio = 12.3) of ever having a vaginal orgasm, and also with greater past month vaginal orgasm consistency (an effect driven by the women who never had a vaginal orgasm), than less prominent lip tubercle categories.&quot; However, lip tubercle was not associated with social desirability responding, or with orgasm triggered by masturbation during penile-vaginal sex, solitary or partner clitoral or vaginal masturbation, vibrator, or cunnilingus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brody, Costa&quot;/&gt; An empirical study carried out in 2008 provides evidence for Freud's implied link between inability to have a vaginal orgasm and psychosexual [[Defence mechanism|immaturity]]. In the study, women reported their past month frequency of different sexual behaviors and corresponding orgasm rates and completed the Defense Style Questionnaire (DSQ-40), which is associated with various [[Psychopathology|psychopathologies]]. The study concluded that a &quot;vaginal orgasm was associated with less somatization, dissociation, displacement, autistic fantasy, devaluation, and isolation of affect.&quot; Moreover, &quot;vaginally anorgasmic women had immature defenses scores comparable to those of established (depression, social anxiety disorder, panic disorder, and obsessive–compulsive disorder) outpatient psychiatric groups.&quot; In the study, a vaginal orgasm (as opposed to a clitoral orgasm) was defined as being triggered solely by penile–vaginal intercourse.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |authors=Brody S, Costa R.M.|title=Vaginal orgasm is associated with less use of immature psychological defense mechanisms|journal=[[The Journal of Sexual Medicine]]|pages=1167–1176 |year=2008 |month= May |pmid=|laysummary= |laysource= |laydate= |doi=10.1111/j.1743-6109.2008.00786.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Wilhelm Reich]], the lack of women's capacity to have a vaginal orgasm is due to a lack of [[orgastic potency]] as caused by our culture's suppression of genital sexuality.&lt;ref&gt;Reich, Wilhelm (1984) Children of the Future: On the Prevention of Sexual Pathology. New York: Farrar Straus and Giroux, footnote on p. 142: &quot;1949: The statement that the girl's clitoral masturbation is normal is also due to the then prevalent psychoanalytic concept that the little girl had no vaginal genatility. The lack of vaginal genatility was later shown by sex-economy to be an artifact of our culture, which suppresses genitality completely and instills castration anxiety not only in the boy but also in the girl. This creates a true secondary drive in the form of penis envy and predominance of clitoral genitality. Psychoanalytic theory mistook these artificial secondary drives for primary, natural functions.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

===Anal and nipple stimulation in males and females===
In both sexes, pleasure can be derived from the nerve endings around the anus and the anus itself, such as during [[anal sex]]. It is possible for men to achieve an orgasm through [[prostate]] stimulation alone.&lt;ref name=&quot;Male hot spot&quot;/&gt; The prostate is located next to the rectum and is the larger, more developed&lt;ref&gt;The G Spot: And Other Discoveries About Human Sexuality by Alice Kahn Ladas, [[Beverly Whipple]], and John D. Perry, pg 57.&lt;/ref&gt; male [[homology (biology)|homologue]] to the [[Skene's glands]] (which are believed to be connected to the female G-Spot).&lt;ref name=&quot;www.newscientist.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|first=Nicola|last=Jones|title=Bigger is better when it comes to the G spot|publisher=[[New Scientist]]|date=July 2002|accessdate=21 April 2010|url=http://www.newscientist.com/article/dn2495-bigger-is-better-when-it-comes-to-the-g-spot.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

&quot;For some men, prostate stimulation produces an orgasm that they describe as 'deeper,' more global and intense, longer-lasting, and associated with greater feelings of ecstasy than orgasm elicited by penile stimulation only.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Answer&quot;/&gt; For women, other than nerve endings found within the anus and rectum, anal pleasure may be achieved through clitoral &quot;legs&quot; — extensions of the clitoris stretching along the vaginal lips back to the anus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Doin' the butt&quot;/&gt; The G-Spot, considered to be interconnected with the clitoris,&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Connell&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Answer&quot;/&gt; may also be accessible through anal penetration; orgasms other than those derived by clitoral legs are made possible because only a thin membrane separates the vaginal cavity from the rectal cavity, allowing for indirect stimulation of the clitoris or G-Spot.&lt;ref name=&quot;Answer&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Newman&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Felice Newman|title=The Whole Lesbian Sex Book: A Passionate Guide For All Of Us|isbn = 1-57344-199-6, 9781573441995|publisher=Cleis Press|year=2004|pages=376 pages|accessdate=6 November 2011|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=OquFdu3Qt9sC&amp;pg=PA205&amp;dq=anal+penetration+is+very+intimate+sex+play&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=1iG3Tvj1MoGJsgK3kPHlAw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CDEQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=anal%20penetration%20is%20very%20intimate%20sex%20play&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Taormino&quot;&gt;See [http://books.google.com/books?id=bG8XqRO6rRQC&amp;pg=PA3&amp;dq=Tristan+Taormino+prefer+anal+to+vaginal&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=qu62Ts-YJZPJsQL42pzzAw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CDQQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false page 3] for women preferring anal to vaginal, and [http://books.google.com/books?id=bG8XqRO6rRQC&amp;pg=PA15&amp;dq=a+thin+membrane+is+all+that+seperates+the+vaginal+cavity+from+the+rectal+cavity&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=hO22TqG0LsGHsgKd3Lz7Aw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CDIQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false page 15] for reaching orgasm through indirect stimulation of the G-Spot. {{cite book|author=Tristan Taormino|title=The Ultimate Guide to Anal Sex for Women|isbn =
1573442216, 9781573442213|publisher=Cleis Press|year=1997|pages=282 pages|accessdate=6 November 2011|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=hLv1ohTIiicC&amp;dq=The+Ultimate+Guide+to+Anal+Sex+for+Women&amp;hl=iw&amp;ei=cdlETbaaKJHG4Absw50Q&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCsQ6AEwAA}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Valdez&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author =Natasha Janina Valdez|title=Vitamin O: Why Orgasms Are Vital to a Woman's Health and Happiness, and How to Have Them Every Time!|isbn = 1-61608-311-5, 9781616083113|publisher=Skyhorse Publishing Inc.|year=2011|pages=282 pages|accessdate=6 November 2011|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=5PsNKTB87isC&amp;pg=PT79&amp;dq=en&amp;ei=VRSxTpXcLsWa2AW67bW2Aw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=8&amp;ved=0CE0Q6AEwBzgK#v=onepage&amp;q=anal%20orgasm&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; Only a small percentage of women are able to orgasm from this type of stimulation alone.&lt;ref name=&quot;Valdez&quot;/&gt; Direct stimulation of the clitoris, G-Spot, or both, during anal sex can help some women to enjoy the experience and reach orgasm.&lt;ref name=&quot;Taormino&quot;/&gt;

The aforementioned orgasms are sometimes referred to as &quot;anal orgasms,&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Valdez&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wasserman&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author =Marlene Wasserman|title=Pillowbook: creating a sensual lifestyle|isbn = 1-77020-009-6, 9781770200098|publisher=Oshun|year=2007|pages=303 pages|accessdate=6 November 2011|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=BC74fx9DrqoC&amp;pg=PA95&amp;dq=anal+orgasm&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=xt62TpCABIWEsgLA7J3VAw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=8&amp;ved=0CFYQ6AEwBw#v=onepage&amp;q=anal%20orgasm&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; but experts generally believe that orgasms derived from anal penetration are the result of the anus's proximity to the clitoris or G-Spot in women, and the prostate in men, rather than orgasms originating from the anus itself.&lt;ref name=&quot;Answer&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Taormino&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Valdez&quot;/&gt; Jack Morin, however, has postulated that &quot;anal orgasm&quot; has nothing to do with the prostate orgasm, although the two are often confused.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| author = Morin, Jack | title = Anal Pleasure and Health | edition = 3d | publisher = Down There Press | year = 1998 | isbn = 0-940208-20-2}}{{Page needed|date=August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In some women, stimulation of the [[breast]] area during sexual intercourse and [[foreplay]], or just the simple act of having their breasts fondled, creates mild to intense orgasms, sometimes referred to as a &quot;breast&quot; or &quot;nipple orgasm&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Otto2&quot;&gt;&quot;Dr. Herbert Otto describes the breast orgasm as happening at the peak of stimulation when the sensation seems to radiate from the breasts.&quot; {{cite web|title=The Nipple Orgasm|publisher=Menshealth.com|date=14 December 2009|accessdate=12 September 2011|url=http://www.menshealth.com/sex-women/nipple-orgasm}}&lt;/ref&gt; Research, however, has suggested that the sensations are genital orgasms caused by nipple stimulation, and may also be directly linked to &quot;the genital area of the brain,&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Komisaruk 2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Levay|first=Simon|coauthors=Sharon McBride Valente|title=Human Sexuality, Second Edition|publisher = Sinauer Associates, Inc.|date=15 November 2005|isbn =978-0-87893-465-2}}{{Page needed|date=August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; though at least one account has suggested that the orgasms radiate from the breasts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Otto2&quot;/&gt; An orgasm is believed to occur in part because of the hormone [[oxytocin]], which is produced in the body during [[Sexual arousal|sexual excitement and arousal]]. It has also been shown that oxytocin is produced when a man or woman's nipples are stimulated and become erect.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Levin R, Meston C |title=Nipple/Breast stimulation and sexual arousal in young men and women |journal=The Journal of Sexual Medicine |volume=3 |issue=3 |pages=450–4 |year=2006 |month=May |pmid=16681470 |doi=10.1111/j.1743-6109.2006.00230.x}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A study published in the July 2011 ''[[Journal of Sexual Medicine]]'' was the first to map the female genitals onto the sensory portion of the brain, and concluded that sensation from the nipples travels to the same part of the brain as sensations from the vagina, clitoris and cervix. &quot;Four major nerves bring signals from women's genitals to their brains,&quot; said researcher Barry Komisaruk of [[Rutgers University]]. &quot;The pudendal nerve connects the clitoris, the pelvic nerve carries signals from the vagina, the hypogastric nerve connects with the cervix and uterus, and the vagus nerve travels from the cervix and uterus without passing through the spinal cord (making it possible for some women to achieve orgasm even though they have had complete spinal cord injuries).&quot; Komisaruk cited one reason for this possibility to be oxytocin, which is also released during labor and triggers uterus contractions. Nipple stimulation triggers uterine contractions, which then produce a sensation in the genital area of the brain. Komisaruk also relayed, however, that preliminary data suggests that nipple nerves may directly link up with the brain, skipping the uterine middleman, acknowledging the men in his study who showed the same pattern of nipple stimulation activating genital brain regions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Komisaruk 2&quot;/&gt;

Most women do not experience this effect when the breasts are stimulated. According to one study, by Herbert Otto, which questioned 213 women, 29% of them had experienced an orgasm of this kind at one time or another.&lt;ref name=&quot;Otto&quot;/&gt;

==Medical aspects==
===Physiological responses===
Masters and Johnson were some of the first to study the sexual response cycle in the early 1960s, based on the observation of 382 women and 312 men. They described a cycle that begins with excitement as blood rushes into the genitals, then reaches a plateau during which they are fully aroused, which leads to orgasm, and finally resolution, in which the blood leaves the genitals.&lt;ref name=&quot;M&amp;J&quot;/&gt;

In the 1970s, [[Helen Singer Kaplan]] added desire to the cycle, which she claimed preceded sexual excitation. She noted that the emotions of anxiety, defensiveness and the failure of communication could interfere with desire and hence orgasm.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Kaplan HS |title=Hypoactive sexual desire |journal=[[Journal of Sex &amp; Marital Therapy]] |volume=3 |issue=1 |pages=3–9 |year=1977 |pmid=864734|doi=10.1080/00926237708405343}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the late 1980s and after, Rosemary Basson proposed a more cyclical alternative to what had largely been viewed as linear progression.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| first=Martin | last=Portner | title=The Orgasmic Mind: The Neurological Roots of Sexual Pleasure | date=15 May 2008 |  url =http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=the-orgasmic-mind | work =Scientific American | accessdate =16 July 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In her model desire feeds arousal and orgasm, and is in turn fueled by the rest of the orgasmic cycle. Rather than orgasm being the peak of the sexual experience, she noted that is just one point in the circle and that people could feel sexually satisfied at any stage, reducing the focus on climax as an end-goal of all sexual activity.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Basson R |title=The female sexual response: a different model |journal=[[Journal of Sex &amp; Marital Therapy]] |volume=26 |issue=1 |pages=51–65 |year=2000 |pmid=10693116 |doi=10.1080/009262300278641}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Males====
As a man nears orgasm during stimulation of the penis, he feels an intense and highly pleasurable pulsating sensation of [[neuromuscular]] [[Euphoria (emotion)|euphoria]]. These pulses begin with a throb of the anal sphincter and travel to the [[glans penis|tip of the penis]]. They eventually increase in speed and intensity as the orgasm approaches, until a final &quot;plateau&quot; (the orgasmic) pleasure sustained for several seconds.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dunn&quot;/&gt; 

During orgasm, a human male experiences rapid, rhythmic contractions of the [[anal sphincter]], the prostate, and the muscles of the penis. The [[sperm]] are transmitted up the [[vas deferens]] from the [[testicles]], into the prostate gland as well as through the [[seminal vesicle]]s to produce what is known as [[semen]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Dunn&quot;/&gt; The prostate produces a secretion that forms one of the components of ejaculate. Except for in cases of a dry orgasm, contraction of the sphincter and prostate force stored semen to be expelled through the penis's urethral opening. The process takes from three to ten seconds, and produces a pleasurable feeling.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mah&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dunn&quot;/&gt; Ejaculation may continue for a few seconds after the euphoric sensation gradually tapers off. It is believed that the exact feeling of &quot;orgasm&quot; varies from one man to another.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mah&quot;/&gt; Normally, as a man ages, the amount of semen he ejaculates diminishes, and so does the duration of orgasms. This does not normally affect the intensity of pleasure, but merely shortens the duration.

After ejaculation, a [[refractory period (sex)|refractory period]] usually occurs, during which a man cannot achieve another orgasm. This can last anywhere from less than a minute to several hours, depending on age and other individual factors.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dunn&quot;/&gt;

====Females====
A woman's orgasm may last slightly longer or much longer than a man's.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rathus&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=soc/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Levin&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Levin|first=Roy J.|coauthors=Gorm Wagner|title=Orgasm in women in the laboratory—quantitative studies on duration, intensity, latency, and vaginal blood flow|journal=Archives of Sexual Behavior|year=1985|page=439|volume=14|issue=5|doi=10.1007/BF01542004|url=http://www.springerlink.com/content/x7x308040h745x78/|accessdate=10 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| title = Women fall into 'trance' during orgasm | work = Mark Henderson |work=The Times  | date = 20 June 2005| url = http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/life_and_style/health/article535521.ece|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20110715222511/http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/life_and_style/health/article535521.ece|archivedate=15 July 2011|accessdate =6 August 2012| location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; Women's orgasms have been estimated to last, on average, approximately 20 seconds, and to consist of a series of muscular contractions in the pelvic area that includes the vagina, the uterus and the anus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Levin&quot;/&gt; For some women, on some occasions, these contractions begin soon after the woman reports that the orgasm has started and continue at intervals of about one second with initially increasing, and then reducing, intensity. In some instances, the series of regular contractions is followed by a few additional contractions or shudders at irregular intervals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Levin&quot;/&gt; In other cases, the woman reports having an orgasm, but no pelvic contractions are measured at all.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Bohlen|first=Joseph G.|coauthors=James P. Held, Margaret Olwen Sanderson and Andrew Ahlgren|title=The female orgasm: Pelvic contractions|journal=Archives of Sexual Behavior|year=1982|page=367|volume=11|issue=5|doi=10.1007/BF01541570|url=http://www.springerlink.com/content/u2146228wwp46614/|accessdate=10 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Women's orgasms are preceded by erection of the clitoris and moistening of the opening of the vagina. Some women exhibit a [[Flushing (physiology)|sex flush]], a reddening of the skin over much of the body due to increased blood flow to the skin. As a woman nears orgasm, the [[clitoral glans]] moves inward under the [[clitoral hood]], and the [[labia minora]] (inner lips) become darker. As orgasm becomes imminent, the outer third of the vagina tightens and narrows, while overall the vagina lengthens and dilates and also becomes congested from engorged soft tissue.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title = Anatomic and physiologic changes during female sexual response | work = Clinical Proceedings | publisher = Association of Reproductive Health Professionals | url = http://www.arhp.org/healthcareproviders/cme/onlinecme/NYNCP/changes.cfm | accessdate =1 February 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Elsewhere in the body, myofibroblasts of the nipple-[[Areolar connective tissue|areolar]] complex contract, causing erection of the nipples and contraction of the areolar diameter, reaching their maximum at the start of orgasm.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|journal= [[Sexual and Relationship Therapy]] |volume= 21 |issue= 1 |pages=  237–249| url=http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/routledg/csmt/2006/00000021/00000002/art00011 | title=The Breast/Nipple/Areola Complex and Human Sexuality | accessdate=2 April 2011 |date=2 May 2006 | publisher = Routledge | last=Levin | first=Roy  | quote=Areola corrugation immediately after orgasm physically signals that orgasm has occurred | doi=10.1080/14681990600674674}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[uterus]] then experiences a series of between 3 and 15 muscular contractions{{Citation needed|date=November 2009}}. A woman experiences full orgasm when her uterus, vagina, anus, and [[human pelvis|pelvic]] muscles undergo a series of rhythmic contractions. Most women find these contractions very pleasurable.

Researchers from the University Medical Center of Groningen, the Netherlands, correlated the sensation of orgasm with muscular contractions occurring at a frequency of 8–13&amp;nbsp;Hz centered in the pelvis and measured in the anus. They argue that the presence of this particular frequency of contractions can distinguish between voluntary contraction of these muscles and spontaneous involuntary contractions, and appears to more accurately correlate with orgasm as opposed to other metrics like heart rate that only measure excitation. They assert that they have identified &quot;[t]he first objective and quantitative measure that has a strong correspondence with the subjective experience that orgasm ultimately is&quot; and state that the measure of contractions that occur at a frequency of 8–13&amp;nbsp;Hz is specific to orgasm. They found that using this metric they could distinguish from rest, voluntary muscular contractions, and even unsuccessful orgasm attempts.&lt;ref name = &quot;Kortekaas 2008&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|author=van Netten JJ, Georgiadis JR, Nieuwenburg A, Kortekaas R |title=8–13 Hz fluctuations in rectal pressure are an objective marker of clitorally-induced orgasm in women |journal=Archives of Sexual Behavior |volume=37 |issue=2 |pages=279–85 |year=2008 |month=April |pmid=17186125 |doi=10.1007/s10508-006-9112-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since ancient times in Western Europe, women could be [[Medical diagnosis|medically diagnosed]] with a disorder called [[female hysteria]], the [[symptoms]] of which included faintness, nervousness, insomnia, fluid retention, heaviness in abdomen, muscle spasm, shortness of breath, irritability, loss of appetite for food or sex, and &quot;a tendency to cause trouble&quot;.&lt;ref name=Maines&gt;{{cite book |author=Maines, Rachel P. |title=The Technology of Orgasm: &quot;Hysteria&quot;, the Vibrator, and Women's Sexual Satisfaction |publisher=The Johns Hopkins University Press |location=Baltimore |year=1998 |isbn=0-8018-6646-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Women considered suffering from the condition would sometimes undergo &quot;pelvic massage&quot; — manual [[masturbation|stimulation of the genitals]] by the doctor until the woman experienced &quot;hysterical paroxysm&quot; (i.e., orgasm). Paroxysm was regarded as a medical treatment, and not a sexual release.&lt;ref name=Maines/&gt; The disorder has ceased to be recognized as a medical condition since the 1920s.

===Brain===
There have been very few studies correlating orgasm and brain activity in real time, owing to cultural barriers and technical difficulties. However a series of studies conducted by [[Gert Holstege]] and his colleagues at the University of Groningen in the Netherlands have established physiological characteristics which are unique to orgasm, including brain activity, as well as variation in the responses between men and women.

One study examined 12 healthy women using a positron emission tomography (PET) scanner while they were being stimulated by their partners. Brain changes were observed and compared between states of rest, sexual stimulation, faked orgasm, and actual orgasm. &quot;Differences were reported on the brain changes associated with men and women during stimulation. However, the same changes in brain activity were observed in both sexes in which the brain regions associated with behavioral control, fear and anxiety shut down. Regarding these changes, Holstege said in an interview with ''[[The Times]]'', &quot;What this means is that deactivation, letting go of all fear and anxiety, might be the most important thing, even necessary, to have an orgasm.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| first=Mark | last=Henderson | title=Women fall into 'trance' during orgasm | date=20 June 2005 |  url=http://www.thetimes.co.uk/tto/health/article1964119.ece |work=The Times  | accessdate =8 December 2011 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During stroking of the clitoris, the parts of the female brain responsible for processing fear, anxiety and behavioral control start to relax and reduce in activity. This reaches a peak at orgasm when the female brain’s emotion centers are effectively closed down to produce an almost trance-like state. Holstege is quoted as saying, at the 2005 meeting of the European Society for Human Reproduction and Development: &quot;At the moment of orgasm, women do not have any emotional feelings.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| first= Martin | last=Portner | title=The Orgasmic Mind: The Neurological Roots of Sexual Pleasure | date=15 May 2008 |  url = http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=the-orgasmic-mind | work =Scientific American | accessdate =7 July 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Initial reports indicated it was difficult to observe the effects of orgasm on men using PET scan, because the duration of male orgasm was much shorter. However, a subsequent report by Rudie Kortekaas, et al. stated, &quot;Gender commonalities were most evident during orgasm... From these results, we conclude that during the sexual act, differential brain responses across genders are principally related to the stimulatory (plateau) phase and not to the orgasmic phase itself.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Georgiadis&quot;/&gt;

Human [[Electroencephalography|brain wave]] patterns have shown distinct changes during orgasm, which indicate the importance of the limbic system in the orgasmic response.&lt;ref name=health.discovery.com/&gt; Male and female brains demonstrate similar changes during orgasm, with brain activity scans showing a temporary decrease in the [[metabolism|metabolic]] activity of large parts of the [[cerebral cortex]] with normal or increased metabolic activity in the limbic areas of the brain.&lt;ref name=&quot;Georgiadis&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Georgiadis JR, Reinders AA, Paans AM, Renken R, Kortekaas R |title=Men versus women on sexual brain function: prominent differences during tactile genital stimulation, but not during orgasm |journal=Human Brain Mapping |volume=30 |issue=10 |pages=3089–101 |year=2009 |month=October |pmid=19219848 |doi=10.1002/hbm.20733}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Health===
====General====
Orgasm, and sex as a whole, are physical activities that can require exertion of many major bodily systems. A 1997 study in the ''[[British Medical Journal]]'' based upon 918 men age 45–59 found that after a ten year follow-up, men who had fewer orgasms were twice as likely to die of any cause as those having two or more orgasms a week.&lt;ref&gt;''Sex and Death, Are They Related''?{{Verify source|need some more bibliographic info|date=November 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; A follow-up in 2001 which focused more specifically on [[cardiovascular]] health found that having sex three or more times a week was associated with a 50% reduction in the risk of heart attack or stroke. (Note that as a rule, [[correlation does not imply causation]].)

There is some research suggesting that greater resting heart rate variability is associated with orgasms through penile-vaginal intercourse without additional simultaneous clitoral stimulation. As a differential hypothesis, resting heart rate variability measures were unrelated to orgasmic frequency from non-coital sexual activities. The authors concluded that greater resting heart rate variability is associated with orgasms through penile-vaginal intercourse, but not with orgasms from other sources:&lt;blockquote&gt;Coitally experienced men and women (N=143) had their heart rate measured for 5 minutes and reported the frequency of various sexual behaviors and corresponding orgasms in a recent representative month. Partial correlations and analyses of covariance controlling for social desirability responding were used to examine the associations of sexual activities with time and frequency domains of resting heart rate variability. For men, greater resting SD of HR was associated with greater [penile-vaginal] orgasm frequency. For women, greater resting SD of HR was associated with any vaginal orgasm. These findings remained after controlling for cohabitation. Sexual activities were unrelated to HF. Lifetime number of [penile-vaginal sex] partners was unrelated to SD of HR and HF. Findings are discussed in the context of orgasms through [penile-vaginal sex] enhancing HRV, and greater parasympathetic tone favoring the capacity to engage in [penile-vaginal sex], and in the case of women, to reach vaginal orgasm. The possibility of healthier people having greater resting HRV and more frequent orgasms through specifically [penile-vaginal sex] is also considered.&lt;ref name=&quot;Costa RM, Brody S.&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |authors=Costa RM, Brody S.|title=Greater resting heart rate variability is associated with orgasms through penile-vaginal intercourse, but not with orgasms from other sources.|journal=[[Journal of Sexual Medicine]]|year=2011 |month= November |pmid=22082262|laysummary=  |laysource= |laydate=|doi=10.1111/j.1743-6109.2011.02541.x |volume=9 |issue=1 |pages=188–97}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

====Dysfunction and satisfaction====
The inability to have orgasm is called [[anorgasmia]], ejaculatory [[anhedonia]], or inorgasmia. If a male experiences [[erection]] and ejaculation but no orgasm, he is said to have [[Ejaculatory anhedonia|sexual anhedonia]]. Difficulty reaching orgasm after ample sexual stimulation is significantly more common in women than in men,&lt;ref name=&quot;Anorgasmia&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Frank JE&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | pmid = 18350761 | volume=77 | issue=5 | title=Diagnosis and treatment of female sexual dysfunction | year=2008 | month=March | pages=635–42 | author=Frank JE, Mistretta P, Will J | journal = American family physician|url=http://www.aafp.org/afp/2008/0301/p635.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; though sexual dysfunction is common for both women (43%) and men (31%), and is associated with age and educational attainment. 

About 15% of women report difficulties with orgasm, 10% have never climaxed, and 40–50% have either complained about sexual dissatisfaction or experienced difficulty becoming sexually aroused at some point in their lives.&lt;ref name=&quot;Big O&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Frank JE&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Birch&quot;&gt;{{cite web|first=Robert|last=Birch |title=Did you orgasm?|publisher=Sexualhealth.com|date=16 November 2007|accessdate=21 April 2010|url=http://www.sexualhealth.com/article/read/women-sexual-health/orgasm/486/|archivedate=16 July 2011|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20110716044630/http://www.sexualhealth.com/article/read/women-sexual-health/orgasm/486/}}&lt;/ref&gt; 75% of men and 29% of women always have orgasms with their partner.&lt;ref name=&quot;Laumann&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |authors=Laumann, E., Gagnon, J.H., Michael, R.T., and Michaels |title=The Social Organization of Sexuality: Sexual Practices in the United States |journal=University of Chicago Press (Also reported in the companion volume, Michael et al, Sex in America: A Definitive Survey.) |year=1994 |pmid= |accessdate=3 January 2012|url=http://www.iub.edu/~kinsey/resources/FAQ.html#orgasm }}&lt;/ref&gt; Women are much more likely to be nearly always or always orgasmic when alone than with a partner.&lt;ref name=&quot;Davis&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |authors=Davis, C.M., Blank, J., Hung-Yu, L., &amp; Bonillas, Consuelo|title=Characteristics of vibrator use among women|journal=Journal of Sex Research|volume=  33(4) |pages= 313–320.|year=1994 |pmid= |accessdate=3 January 2012|url=http://www.iub.edu/~kinsey/resources/FAQ.html#orgasm}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, in a 1996 study reported in the ''[[Journal of Sex Research]]'', 62% of women in a partnered relationship said they were satisfied with the frequency/consistency of their orgasms.&lt;ref name=&quot;Davis&quot;/&gt; Additionally, many women express that their most satisfying sexual experiences entail being connected to someone, rather than solely basing satisfaction on orgasm.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bridges&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |title=Predicting sexual satisfaction in women: Implications for counselor education and training |journal=Journal of Counseling &amp; Development|volume= 82(2) |pages=158–166 |year=2004 |pmid= |accessdate=4 March 2011|url=http://www.iub.edu/~kinsey/resources/FAQ.html#orgasm}}&lt;/ref&gt; Robert Birch of Sexualhealth.com stated, &quot;As statistics based on surveys tend to do, the numbers assigned to female orgasms vary, depending on who was surveyed and who is reporting.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Birch&quot;/&gt; 

Kinsey's ''[[Kinsey Reports|Sexual Behavior in the Human Female]]'' showed that, over the previous five years of sexual activity, 78% of women had orgasms in 60% to 100% of [[human sexual behavior|sexual encounters]] with other women, compared with 55% for heterosexual sex.&lt;ref&gt;[[Alfred Kinsey|Kinsey, A.]]; [[Wardell Pomeroy|Pomeroy, W.]]; [[Clyde Martin|Martin, C.]], &amp; [[Paul Gebhard|Gebhard, P.]] ''Sexual Behavior in the Human Female'', Philadelphia: Saunders (1953), ISBN 978-0-253-33411-4.&lt;/ref&gt; Kinsey attributed this difference to female partners knowing more about women's sexuality and how to optimize women's sexual satisfaction than male partners do.&lt;ref name=&quot;Weiten&quot;/&gt; Like Kinsey, scholars such as Peplau, Fingerhut and Beals (2004) and Diamond (2006) found that lesbians have orgasms more often and more easily in sexual interactions than heterosexual women do,&lt;ref name=&quot;Weiten&quot;/&gt; and that female partners are more likely to emphasize the emotional aspects of lovemaking.&lt;ref name=&quot;Weiten&quot;/&gt;

Specifically in relation to simultaneous orgasm and similar practices, many sexologists claim that the problem of [[premature ejaculation]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www2.hu-berlin.de/sexology/IES/italy.html |title=The International Encyclopedia of Sexuality: Italy |publisher=.hu-berlin.de |date=1 January 1999 |accessdate=15 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; is closely related to the idea encouraged by a scientific approach in early 20th century when mutual orgasm was overly emphasized as an objective and a sign of true sexual satisfaction in intimate relationships.

If orgasm is desired, anorgasmia may be attributed to an inability to relax, or &quot;let go.&quot; It seems to be closely associated with performance pressure and an unwillingness to pursue pleasure, as separate from the other person's satisfaction. Often, women worry so much about the pleasure of their partner that they become anxious, which manifests as impatience with the delay of orgasm for them. This delay can lead to frustration of not reaching orgasmic sexual satisfaction.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frank JE&quot;/&gt; Psychoanalyst [[Wilhelm Reich]], in his 1927 book ''[[Die Funktion des Orgasmus]]'' (published in English in 1980 as ''Genitality in the Theory and Therapy of Neurosis'') was the first to make orgasm central to the concept of mental health, and defined [[neurosis]] in terms of blocks to having [[orgastic potency]]. Although orgasm dysfunction can have psychological components, physiological factors often play a role. For instance, delayed orgasm or the inability to achieve orgasm is a common side effect of many medications.

[[Menopause]] may involve loss of hormones supporting sexuality and genital functionality. Vaginal and clitoral atrophy and dryness affects up to 50%–60% of postmenopausal women.&lt;ref&gt;Michael L. Krychman, MD, &quot;Vaginal Atrophy: The 21st Century Health Issue Affecting Quality of Life &quot;,Medscape Ob/Gyn Expert Columns, 1999 Feb 10;281(6):537-44, [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10022110?dopt=Abstract]. Retrieved 24 May 2011&lt;/ref&gt;  Testosterone levels in men fall as they age.  Sexual dysfunction overall becomes more likely with poor physical and emotional health.  &quot;Negative experiences in sexual relationships and overall well-being&quot; are associated with sexual dysfunction.&lt;ref&gt;Laumann EO, Paik A, Rosen RC, &quot;Sexual dysfunction in the United States: prevalence and predictors&quot;, JAMA, 2007 August, [http://www.medscape.org/viewarticle/561934]. Retrieved 24 May 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Yee LA, Sundquist KJ, &quot;Older women's sexuality&quot;, The Medical Journal of Australia, 2003, 178 (12): 640–643, [http://www.mja.com.au/public/issues/178_12_160603/yee10847_fm-2.html#i1082816]. Retrieved 24 May 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

==Theoretical biological and evolutionary functions==
Because male orgasms that expel [[sperm]] from the body into the vagina during intercourse may result in conception, researchers have several hypotheses about the role, if any, of the female orgasm in the reproductive and therefore evolutionary process.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lloyd&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Gould&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wallen K, Lloyd EA&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Geoffrey Miller&quot;&gt;{{cite book| author= [[Geoffrey Miller (psychologist)|Geoffrey Miller]]| title = The Mating Mind: How Sexual Choice Shaped the Evolution of Human Nature | publisher = [[Random House|Random House Digital]] |year = 2011|pages=238-239| accessdate =27 August 2012| isbn = 0307813746, 9780307813749|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=QG-8PbZb4csC&amp;pg=PA238&amp;lpg=PA238&amp;dq=The+human+clitoris+shows+no+apparent+signs+of+having+evolved+directly+through+male+mate+choice.&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=W6SFlfwfXf&amp;sig=B6auGtZ2ieK0EQ48rHsG4C37Fpc&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=6qI7UNXQO8S-2AX90IGADg&amp;ved=0CC8Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=The%20human%20clitoris%20shows%20no%20apparent%20signs%20of%20having%20evolved%20directly%20through%20male%20mate%20choice.&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; Wallen K and Lloyd EA stated, &quot;In men, orgasms are under strong selective pressure as orgasms are coupled with ejaculation and thus contribute to male reproductive success. By contrast, women's orgasms in intercourse are highly variable and are under little selective pressure as they are not a reproductive necessity.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wallen K, Lloyd EA&quot;/&gt; In 1967, [[Desmond Morris]] first suggested in his popular-science book ''[[The Naked Ape]]'' that the female orgasm evolved to encourage physical intimacy with a male partner and help reinforce the pair bond. Morris suggested that the relative difficulty in achieving female orgasm, in comparison to the male's, might be favorable in [[Darwinism|Darwinian]] evolution by leading the female to select mates who bear qualities like patience, care, imagination, intelligence, as opposed to qualities like size and aggression, which pertain to mate selection in other primates. Such advantageous qualities thereby become accentuated within the species, driven by the differences between male and female orgasm. If males were motivated by, and taken to the point of, orgasm in the same way as females, those advantageous qualities would not be needed, since self-interest would be enough. Morris also proposed that orgasm might facilitate conception by exhausting the female and keeping her horizontal, thus preventing the sperm from leaking out. This possibility, sometimes called the &quot;Poleax Hypothesis&quot; or the &quot;Knockout Hypothesis,&quot; is now considered highly doubtful.

A 1994 [[TLC (TV channel)|Learning Channel]] documentary on sex had fiber optic cameras inside the vagina of a woman while she had sexual intercourse. During her orgasm, her [[Pelvic floor|pelvic muscles]] contracted and her [[Vaginal portion of cervix|cervix]] repeatedly dipped into a pool of semen in the [[vaginal fornix]], as if to ensure that sperm would proceed by the [[external orifice of the uterus]], making conception more likely.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video | people=[[Desmond Morris]] (host) |year=1994 | title=[[The Human Animal (TV series)|The Human Animal]] | medium=TV | publisher=The Learning Channel}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Elisabeth Lloyd]] has criticized the accompanying narration of this film clip which describes it as an example of &quot;Sperm Upsuck.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lloyd2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mypage.iu.edu/%7Eealloyd/Reviews.html#IsntItObviousThat |title=Reviews |publisher=Mypage.iu.edu |accessdate=15 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The clitoris is [[homology (biology)|homologous]] to the penis; that is, they both develop from the same embryonic structure.&lt;ref name=&quot;Merz&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Schünke&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Francoeur&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Clitoris&quot;/&gt; While researchers such as [[Geoffrey Miller (psychologist)|Geoffrey Miller]], [[Helen Fisher (anthropologist)|Helen Fisher]], [[Meredith Small]] and [[Sarah Blaffer Hrdy]] &quot;have viewed the clitoral orgasm as a legitimate [[Adaptationism|adaptation]] in its own right, with major implications for female sexual behavior and sexual evolution,&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Geoffrey Miller&quot;/&gt; others, such as [[Stephen Jay Gould]] and [[Donald Symons]], have asserted that the clitoris is [[vestigiality|vestigial]] or nonadaptive, and that the female orgasm serves no particular evolutionary function.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gould&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Geoffrey Miller&quot;/&gt; However, Gould acknowledged that &quot;most female orgasms emanate from a clitoral, rather than vaginal (or some other), site&quot; and stated that his nonadaptive belief &quot;has been widely misunderstood as a denial of either the adaptive value of female orgasm in general, or even as a claim that female orgasms lack significance in some broader sense&quot;. He explained that although he accepts that &quot;clitoral orgasm plays a pleasurable and central role in female sexuality and its joys,&quot; &quot;[a]ll these favorable attributes, however, emerge just as clearly and just as easily, whether the clitoral site of orgasm arose as a [[Spandrel (biology)|spandrel]] or an adaptation&quot;. He said that the &quot;male biologists who fretted over [the adaptionist questions] simply assumed that a deeply vaginal site, nearer the region of fertilization, would offer greater selective benefit&quot; due to their Darwinian, ''[[summum bonum]]'' beliefs about enhanced reproductive success.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gould&quot;/&gt;

Proponents of the nonadaptive hypothesis, such as Elisabeth Lloyd, refer to the relative difficulty of achieving female orgasm through vaginal sex, the limited evidence for increased fertility after orgasm and the lack of statistical correlation between the capacity of a woman to orgasm and the likelihood that she will engage in intercourse.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lloyd&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Chivers&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | first = Meredith L. | last = Chivers | first2 = Michael W. | last2 = Wiedermana | title = A Narrow (But Thorough) Examination of the Evolutionary Significance of Female Orgasm | journal = [[Journal of Sex Research]] | volume = 44 | issue = 1 | pages = 104–105 | year = 2007 | pmid = | doi =    10.1080/00224490709336797 | url = http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-162790350.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Lloyd is by no means against evolutionary psychology. Quite the opposite; in her methods and in her writing, she advocates and demonstrates a commitment to the careful application of evolutionary theory to the study of human behavior,&quot; stated Meredith L. Chivers. She added that Lloyd &quot;meticulously considers the theoretical and empirical bases for each account and ultimately concludes that there is little evidence to support an adaptionist account of female orgasm&quot; that Lloyd instead &quot;views female orgasm as an ontogenetic leftover; women have orgasms because the urogenital neurophysiology for orgasm is so strongly selected for in males that this developmental blueprint gets expressed in females without affecting fitness, just as males have nipples that serve no fitness-related function&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chivers&quot;/&gt;

Miller, Hrdy, Helen O'Connell and [[Natalie Angier]] have criticized the &quot;female orgasm is vestigial&quot; hypothesis as understating and devaluing the psychosocial value of the female orgasm.&lt;ref name=&quot;Geoffrey Miller&quot;/&gt; Hrdy stated that the hypothesis smacks of [[sexism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| author=Christopher Shea| title=Orgasmic science|work=The Boston Globe| date=24 April 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;  O'Connell said, &quot;It boils down to rivalry between the sexes: the idea that one sex is sexual and the other reproductive. The truth is that both are sexual and both are reproductive.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Connell&quot;/&gt; O'Connell used [[Magnetic resonance imaging|MRI]] technology to define the true size and shape of the clitoris, suggesting that it extends into the anterior wall of the vagina ([[#In females|see above]]). She describes typical textbook descriptions of the clitoris as lacking detail and including inaccuracies, saying that the work of [[Georg Ludwig Kobelt]] in the early 19th century provides a most comprehensive and accurate description of clitoral anatomy. O'Connell asserts that the bulbs appear to be part of the clitoris and that the distal urethra and vagina are intimately related structures, although they are not erectile in character, forming a tissue cluster with the clitoris that appears to be the locus of female sexual function and orgasm.&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Connell&quot;/&gt; In contrast, Nancy Tuana, at the 2002 conference for ''Canadian Society of Women in Philosophy'', asserted that the clitoris is unnecessary in reproduction, but that this is why it has been &quot;historically ignored,&quot; mainly because of &quot;a fear of pleasure. It is pleasure separated from reproduction. That's the fear&quot;. She reasoned that this fear is the cause of the ignorance that veils female sexuality.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cairney&quot;/&gt;

Evolutionary psychologists Christopher Ryan and Cacilda Jethá note in their discussion of the female orgasm how long it takes for females to achieve orgasm compared to males and their ability to have multiple orgasms, hypothesizing how especially well suited to multiple partners and insemination this is. They quote primate sexuality specialist Alan Dixson in saying that the monogamy-maintenance explanation for female orgasm &quot;seems far-fetched&quot; because &quot;females of other primate species, and particularly those with multimale-multifemale [promiscuous] mating systems such as macaques and chimpanzees, exhibit orgasmic responses in the absence of such bonding or the formation of stable family units.&quot; On the other hand, Dixson notes that &quot;Gibbons, which are primarily monogamous, do not exhibit obvious signs of female orgasm.&quot; Although Dixson classifies humans as mildly polygynous in his survey of primate sexuality, he appears to have doubts, when he writes, &quot;One might argue that... the female's orgasm is rewarding, increases her willingness to copulate with a variety of males rather than one partner, and thus promotes [[sperm competition]].&quot; Ryan and Jethá use this as evidence for their theory that [[partible paternity]] and promiscuity were common for early modern humans.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ryan&quot;&gt;{{cite book|authors=Christopher Ryan Ph.D and Cacilda Jethá Ph.D;|title=Sex at Dawn|isbn =0062207946, 9780062207944|publisher=HarperCollins|year=2012|page=263|accessdate=25 May 2012|url=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The female promiscuity explanation of female sexuality was echoed at least 12 years earlier by other evolutionary biologists, and also mentioning the increasing scientific awareness of female [[proceptive phase]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk/2000/sep/03/anthonybrowne.theobserver&lt;/ref&gt;

There are theories that the female orgasm might increase fertility.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lloyd&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Gould&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Geoffrey Miller&quot;/&gt; For example, the 30% reduction in size of the vagina could help clench onto the penis (much like, or perhaps caused by, the [[pubococcygeus muscle]]s), which would make it more stimulating for the male (thus ensuring faster or more voluminous ejaculation). The British biologists Baker and Bellis have suggested that the female orgasm may have an &quot;upsuck&quot; action (similar to the [[esophagus]]' ability to swallow when upside down), resulting in the retaining of favorable sperm and making conception more likely.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|doi=10.1006/anbe.1993.1272 |author=Baker, R. R., and Bellis, M. A. |year=1993 |title=Human sperm competition: Ejaculate manipulation by females and a function for the female orgasm |journal=Animal Behavior |volume=46 |issue=5 |pages=887–909}}&lt;/ref&gt; They posited a role of female orgasm in [[sperm competition]]. The observation that women tend to reach orgasm more easily when they are ovulating also suggests that it is tied to increasing fertility.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| first=David | last=Adam | url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/life/science/story/0,12996,1501314,00.html | date=8 June 2005 | title=Female orgasm all in the genes |work=The Guardian  | accessdate=28 May 2006 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; Evolutionary biologist Robin Baker argues in ''[[Sperm Wars]]'' that occurrence and timing of orgasms are all a part of the female body's unconscious strategy to collect and retain sperm from more evolutionarily fit men{{citation needed|date=November 2011}}. An orgasm during intercourse functions as a bypass button to a woman's natural cervical filter against sperm and pathogens. An orgasm before functions to strengthen the filter. 

A 2005 [[twin study]] found that one in three women reported never or seldom achieving orgasm during intercourse, and only one in ten always orgasmed. This variation in ability to orgasm, generally thought to be psychosocial, was found to be 34% to 45% genetic. The study, examining 4000 women, was published in ''[[Biology letters]]'', a [[Royal Society]] journal.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/health/4616899.stm | title=Female orgasm is 'down to genes' |publisher=BBC | date=7 June 2005 | accessdate=28 May 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release | publisher=Primary Care Sciences Research Centre, Keele University | date=7 June 2005 | url=http://www.eurekalert.org/pub_releases/2005-06/rs-sir060605.php | title=Genetic influences on variation in female orgasmic function: a twin study by Dr KM Dunn, Dr LF Cherkas and Prof TD Spector | accessdate=28 May 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Elisabeth Lloyd has cited this as evidence for the notion that female orgasm is not adaptive.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lloyd&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lloyd2&quot;/&gt;

==In tantric sex==
[[Tantric sex]], which is not the same thing as [[Vajrayana|Buddhist tantra (Vajrayana)]], is the ancient Indian spiritual tradition of sexual practices. It attributes a different value to orgasm than traditional cultural approaches to sexuality. Some practitioners of [[Tantra|tantric]] sex aim to eliminate orgasm from sexual intercourse by remaining for a long time in the pre-orgasmic and non-emission state. Advocates of this, such as [[Rajneesh]], claim that it eventually causes orgasmic feelings to spread out to all of one's conscious experience.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| author = Rajneesh, Bhagwan Shree | title = Tantra, Spirituality, and Sex | year = 1983 | isbn = 0-88050-696-2 | publisher = Rajneesh Foundation Internat. | location = Rajneeshpuram, Or.}}{{Page needed|date=August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| author = Chia, Mantak &amp; Abrams, Douglas | title = The Multi-Orgasmic Man | publisher = Harper San Francisco | year = 1996 | isbn = 0-06-251336-2}}{{Page needed|date=August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Advocates of tantric and neotantric sex who claim that Western culture focuses too much on the goal of climactic orgasm, which reduces the ability to have intense pleasure during other moments of the sexual experience, suggest that eliminating this enables a richer, fuller and more intense connection.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| author = Douglas, N &amp; Slinger, P | title = Sexual Secrets: The Alchemy of Ecstasy | publisher = Destiny Books | year = 1979 | isbn = 0-89281-266-4}}{{Page needed|date=August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In literature==
[[File:Carracci - Jupiter et Junon.jpeg|thumb|''[[Jupiter (mythology)|Jupiter]] and [[Juno (mythology)|Juno]]'', by [[Annibale Carracci]].]]
Orgasm has been widely described in literature over the centuries. In antiquity, [[Latin literature]] addressed the subject as much as [[Greek literature]]: Book III of [[Ovid]]'s ''[[Metamorphoses]]'' retells a discussion between [[Jove]] and [[Juno (mythology)|Juno]], in which the former states: &quot;The sense of pleasure in the male is far / More dull and dead, than what you females share.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Ovid]], ''[[Metamorphoses|Met]].'' III, 320-21 (translated by Sir Samuel Garth, [[John Dryden]], et al, 1717). In the original in [[Latin]], Ovid writes: ''maior vestra profecto est, / quam quae contingit maribus.''&lt;/ref&gt; Juno rejects this thought; they agree to ask the opinion of [[Tiresias]] (&quot;who had known [[Venus (mythology)|Venus]]/Love in both ways,&quot; having lived seven years as a female).&lt;ref&gt;''Met''. III, 323 (translated by [[A. S. Kline]], 2000).&lt;/ref&gt; Tiresias offends Juno by agreeing with Jove, and she strikes him blind on the spot (Jove lessens the blow by giving Tiresias the gift of foresight, and a long life).&lt;ref&gt;''Met.'' III, 335.&lt;/ref&gt; Earlier, in the ''[[Ars Amatoria]]'', Ovid states that he abhors sexual intercourse that fails to complete both partners.&lt;ref&gt;{{pt}} ''Jornal de Letras, Artes e Ideias'', Ano XXV/Number 930. 24 May to 6 June 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

The theme of orgasm survived during [[Romanticism]] and [[Homoeroticism]]. [[Percy Bysshe Shelley]] (1792–1822), &quot;a translator of extraordinary range and versatility&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Webb, 1976, p. 2.&lt;/ref&gt; in ''FRAGMENT: Supposed to be an Epithalamium of Francis Ravaillac and Charlotte Cordé'', wrote phrase &quot;No life can equal such a death.&quot;, that has been seen as a [[metaphor]] for orgasm,&lt;ref name=&quot;Lauritsen&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://paganpressbooks.com/jpl/HHREV3.HTM Hellenism and Homoeroticism in Shelley and his Circle]&quot;, by John Lauritsen (2008). Consulted on 10 December 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; and that was preceded by a rhythmic urgency of the previous lines &quot;Suck on, suck on, I glow, I glow!&quot;, alluding explicitly to ''[[fellatio]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lauritsen&quot; /&gt; For Shelley, orgasm was &quot;the almost involuntary consequences of a state of abandonment in the society of a person of surpassing attractions.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Plato, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Edward Ellerker Williams]], the last love of Shelley's life, was remembered by the poet in &quot;The Boat on the Serchio&quot;, which is seen as probably &quot;the grandest portrayal of orgasm in literature&quot;:&lt;ref name=&quot;Lauritsen&quot; /&gt;

&lt;poem style=&quot;margin-left: 2em&quot;&gt;
  The Serchio, twisting forth
Between the marble barriers which it clove
  At Ripafratta, leads through the dread chasm
The wave that died the death which lovers love,
  Living in what it sought; as if this spasm
Had not yet passed, the toppling mountains cling,
  But the clear stream in full enthusiasm
Pours itself on the plain....
&lt;/poem&gt;

Again, Shelley, in this poem, associates orgasm with death when he writes &quot;death which lovers love&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lauritsen&quot; /&gt; Curiously, in [[French literature]], the term ''[[la petite mort]]'' (the little death) is a famous [[euphemism]] for orgasm;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Georgiadis J, Kortekaas R, Kuipers R, Nieuwenburg A, Pruim J, Reinders A, Holstege G |title=Regional cerebral blood flow changes associated with clitorally induced orgasm in healthy women |journal=Eur J Neurosci |volume=24 |issue=11 |pages=3305–16 |year=2006 |pmid=17156391 |doi=10.1111/j.1460-9568.2006.05206.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; it is the representation of man who forgets himself and the world during orgasm. [[Jorge Luis Borges]], in the same vision, wrote in one of the several [[footnote]]s of &quot;[[Tlön, Uqbar, Orbis Tertius]]&quot; that one of the churches of [[Tlön]] claims [[Platonism|Platonic]]ally that &quot;All men, in the vertiginous moment of coitus, are the same man. All men who repeat a line from [[Shakespeare]] ''are'' William Shakespeare.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Borges, ''Ficciones'', p.28&lt;/ref&gt; Shakespeare himself was a knowledgeable of this idea: lines &quot;I will live in thy heart, die in thy lap, and be buried in thy eyes&quot; and &quot;I will die bravely, like a smug bridegroom&quot;, said respectively by [[Benedick]] in ''[[Much Ado About Nothing]]'' and by King Lear in [[King Lear|the homonymous play]],&lt;ref&gt;''MUCH ADO'', v ii 99–101. &amp; ''Lear'', iv vi 201.&lt;/ref&gt; are interpreted as an option to die in a woman's lap to experience a sexual orgasm.&lt;ref&gt;Partridge, 2001, p.118.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sigmund Freud]] with his [[psychoanalytic]] projects, in &quot;[[The Ego and the Id]]&quot; (1923), speculates that sexual satisfaction by orgasm make [[Eros]] (&quot;life instinct&quot;) exhausted and leaves the field open to [[Thanatos]] (&quot;death instinct&quot;), in other words, with orgasm Eros fulfills its mission and gives way to Thanatos.&lt;ref&gt;See [[Sigmund Freud|Freud, Sigmund]]. &quot;The Ego and the Id&quot;. The Hogarth Press Ltd. London, 1949. Quoted by ''Vida Íntima: Enciclopédia do Amor e do Sexo'', Abril Cultural, Vol. 1, 1981, [[São Paulo]], Brazil, p. 66-67.&lt;/ref&gt; Other modern authors have chosen to represent the orgasm without metaphors. In novel ''[[Lady Chatterley's Lover]]'' (1928), by [[D.H.Lawrence]], we can find an explicit narrative of a sexual act between a [[couple]]: &quot;As he began to move, in the sudden helpless orgasm there awoke in her strange thrills rippling inside her...&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[D. H. Lawrence]], New York: Grove Press, 1969, cited by BANKER-RISHKIN; GRANDINETTI, 1997, p.141&lt;/ref&gt;

==In other animals==
{{See also|Animal sexual behaviour}}
The mechanics of male orgasm are similar in most mammals. Females of some mammal and some non-mammal species such as alligators&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.crocodilian.com/crocfaq/faq-8.html |title=Crocodilian Captive Care FAQ (Caiman, Alligator, Crocodile) |publisher=Crocodilian.com |date=5 March 1996 |accessdate=15 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; have clitorises. There has been ongoing research about the sexuality and orgasms of dolphins, a species which apparently engages in sexual intercourse for reasons other than procreation.&lt;ref&gt;National Geographic's ''Dolphins: The wild side'' documentary (1999), [http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0386415/ IMDb]. &quot;Sex is as frequent as it is casual, a social tool used to strengthen and maintain bonds. But beneath the harmony lies a darker side of dolphins. Gangs of strong males pick on younger or smaller dolphins.&quot;, quote from [http://www.nationalgeographic.com/tv/press/990202.html National Geographic website]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{multicol}}
* [[Child sexuality]]
* [[Coitus reservatus]]
* [[Eroto-comatose lucidity]]
* [[Female ejaculation]] (''squirt'')
* [[Female sexual arousal disorder]]
* [[Forced orgasm]] (a [[BDSM]] term)
* [[Erogenous zone]]
* [[Human sexual behavior]]
* [[Orgastic potency]]
{{multicol-break}}
* [[Persistent sexual arousal syndrome]]
* [[Sexual function]]
* ''[[La petite mort]] ''— &quot;the little death&quot; in French (a euphemism for orgasm)
* [[Venus Butterfly]]
* [[List of sex positions]]
* [[Kama Sutra]] — an ancient text on human sexual behaviour
{{multicol-break}}
{{Portal|Sexuality}}
{{multicol-end}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== Further reading ==
*BANKER-RISKIN, Anita; GRANDINETTI, Deborah (1997). ''Simultaneous Orgasm: And Other Joys of Sexual Intimacy''. Hunter House. ISBN 0-89793-221-8, ISBN 978-0-89793-221-9.
*PARTRIDGE, Eric (2001). ''Shakespeare's bawdy: Classics Series Routledge classics''. 2nd ed., Routledge. ISBN 0-415-25400-0, ISBN 978-0-415-25400-7.
*[[Plato]] (2001). ''The Banquet''. (P.B. Shelley, Trans., J. Lauritsen, Ed., Foreword). Provincetown, MA: Pagan Press.
*WEBB, Timothy (1976). ''The violet in the crucible: Shelley and translation'', 1976. Oxford: Clarendon Press.
* Gabriele Froböse, Rolf Froböse, Michael Gross (Translator): ''Lust and Love: Is it more than Chemistry?'' Publisher: Royal Society of Chemistry, ISBN 0-85404-867-7, (2006).
* Komisaruk, Barry R.; Beyer-Flores, Carlos; Whipple, Beverly. ''The Science of Orgasm''. Baltimore, MD; London: The Johns Hopkins University Press, 2006 (hardcover, ISBN 0-8018-8490-X).

==External links==
*[http://menshealth.about.com/od/sexualhealth/a/male_orgasm.htm Men's Health: Male Orgasm]
*[http://www.christianitytoday.com/mp/2001/004/3.36.html What Every Woman Needs to Know About Sexual Satisfaction]
*[http://www.netdoctor.co.uk/menshealth/feature/helpwithorgasms.htm Net Doctor: Female Orgasm]
*[http://books.google.com/books?id=7rfLcoQ2koQC&amp;dq=&amp;pg=PP1&amp;ots=wVP5clVxss&amp;sig=cRJ8rsavVqgSAoVHcOvwCmANfq4&amp;prev=http://www.google.com/search%3Fhl%3Den%26q%3D%2522The%2BScience%2Bof%2BOrgasm%2522%2BWhipple%26btnG%3DSearch&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=print&amp;ct=title The Science of Orgasm, by Barry R. Komisarak, Carlos Beyer-Flores, &amp; Beverly Whipple]
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7jx0dTYUO5E Ted Talk by [[Mary Roach]] on 10 things you didn't know about orgasm]
&lt;!--spacing--&gt;

{{Reproductive physiology}}
{{sex}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2012}}

[[Category:Orgasm| ]]
[[Category:Greek loanwords]]
[[Category:Human sexuality]]
[[Category:Sexual acts]]

{{Link GA|de}}
{{Link FA|hr}}

[[af:Orgasme]]
[[ar:هزة الجماع]]
[[az:Orqazm]]
[[be:Аргазм]]
[[be-x-old:Аргазм]]
[[bg:Оргазъм]]
[[ca:Orgasme]]
[[cs:Orgasmus]]
[[cy:Orgasm]]
[[da:Orgasme]]
[[de:Orgasmus]]
[[et:Orgasm]]
[[el:Οργασμός]]
[[es:Orgasmo]]
[[eo:Orgasmo]]
[[eu:Orgasmo]]
[[fa:اوج لذت جنسی]]
[[fr:Orgasme]]
[[gl:Orgasmo]]
[[ko:오르가슴]]
[[hsb:Orgazm]]
[[hr:Orgazam]]
[[id:Orgasme]]
[[ia:Orgasmo]]
[[it:Orgasmo]]
[[he:אורגזמה]]
[[jv:Orgasme]]
[[ka:ორგაზმი]]
[[ku:Orgazm]]
[[la:Orgasmus]]
[[lv:Orgasms]]
[[lt:Orgazmas]]
[[hu:Orgazmus]]
[[mk:Оргазам]]
[[ml:രതിമൂര്‍ച്ഛ]]
[[mzn:اوج لذت جنسی]]
[[ms:Puncak syahwat]]
[[nl:Orgasme]]
[[ja:オーガズム]]
[[no:Orgasme]]
[[nn:Orgasme]]
[[nds:Orgasmus]]
[[pl:Orgazm]]
[[pt:Orgasmo]]
[[ro:Orgasm]]
[[ru:Оргазм]]
[[scn:Urgàsimu]]
[[simple:Orgasm]]
[[sk:Orgazmus]]
[[sr:Оргазам]]
[[sh:Orgazam]]
[[su:Orgasme]]
[[fi:Orgasmi]]
[[sv:Orgasm]]
[[tl:Sukdulan]]
[[ta:புணர்ச்சிப் பரவசநிலை]]
[[te:భావప్రాప్తి]]
[[th:จุดสุดยอดทางเพศ]]
[[tr:Orgazm]]
[[uk:Оргазм]]
[[vi:Cực khoái]]
[[yi:ארגאזם]]
[[bat-smg:Uorgazmos]]
[[zh:性高潮]]</text>
      <sha1>ncqt0a5xarb7lobmn4xqfl50zqr6bhb</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
